
   
      
         
            A True chronologi of all the kings of England from Brute, the first king vnto our most sacred King Charles mo[n]arke of ye whole yies.
         
         
            
               1635
            
         
         Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00028
            STC 10023.5
            ESTC S2071
            23006728
            ocm 23006728
            26061
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00028)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26061)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1795:18)
         
         
            
               
                  A True chronologi of all the kings of England from Brute, the first king vnto our most sacred King Charles mo[n]arke of ye whole yies.
               
               1 broadside : ports., coats of arms.  
               
                  s.n.,
                  [London :
                  1635?]
               
               
                  Contains 147 numbered portraits (as well as unnumbered portraits of Henrietta Maria and Prince Charles).
                  Place and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).
                  Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.
               Great Britain --  History.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-09
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-09
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A TRVE CHRONOLOGI OF ALL THE KINGS OF ENGLAND FROM BRVE THE FIRST KING VNTO OUR MOST SACRED KING CHARLES MŌARKE OF YE WHOLE YIES▪
               ▪
            
            
               
                  
                     Brutes armes
                     blazon of Brutus
                  
               
               1 
                     Brute
                     portrait of Brutus
                  
               
               2 
                     Locrine
                     portrait of Locrine
                  
               
               3 
                     Madan
                     portrait of Madan
                  
               
               4 
                     Mempricius
                     portrait of Mempricius
                  
               
               5 
                     Ebrank
                     portrait of Ebrank
                  
               
               6 
                     Brutegrēſhielde
                     portrait of  Brutegrenshield
                  
               
               7 
                     Leill
                     portrait of Leill
                  
               
               8 
                     Ludrudibras
                     portrait of Ludrudibras
                  
               
               9 
                     Bladud
                     portrait of Bladud
                  
               
               10 
                     Leire
                     portrait of King Lear
                  
               
               11 
                     Cordyla
                     portrait of Cordelia
                  
               
               12 
                     Morgan and Conedagus
                     portrait of Morgan and Conedagus
                  
               
               13 
                     Riuallo
                     portrait of Riuallo
                  
               
               14 
                     Gurguſtus
                     portrait of Gurgustus
                  
               
               15 
                     Scicilius
                     portrait of Scicilius
                  
               
               16 
                     Iago
                     portrait of Iago
                  
               
               17 
                     Kinimacus
                     portrait of Kinimacus
                  
               
               18 
                     Gorbodug
                     portrait of Gorboduc
                  
               
               19 
                     Forrex and Porrex
                     portrait of Forrex and Porrex
                  
               
               
                  
                     Mulmutius armes
                     blazon of Mulmutius
                  
               
               20 
                     Mulmutius
                     portrait of Mulmutius
                  
               
               21 
                     Belius &amp; Brennus
                     portrait of Belius &amp; Brennus
                  
               
               22 
                     Gurgūſtus
                     portrait of Gurgunſtus
                  
               
               23 
                     Guinthelinus
                     portrait of Guinthelinus
                  
               
               24 
                     Cecilius
                     portrait of Cecilius
                  
               
               25 
                     Kimarus
                     portrait of Kimarus
                  
               
               26 
                     Elanius
                     portrait of Elanius
                  
               
               27 
                     Morindus
                     portrait of Morindus
                  
               
               28 
                     Gorbomānus
                     portrait of Gorbomannus
                  
               
               29 
                     Archigallo
                     portrait of Archigallo
                  
               
               30 
                     
                        Ʋigenius and Peredurus
                     portrait of Vigenius and Peredurus
                  
               
               31 
                     Elidurus
                     portrait of Elidurus
                  
               
               32 
                     Gorbonian
                     portrait of Gorbonian
                  
               
               33 
                     Morgan
                     portrait of Morgan
                  
               
               34 
                     Emerianus
                     portrait of Emerianus
                  
               
               35 
                     Iuall
                     portrait of Iuall
                  
               
               36 
                     Rymo
                     portrait of Rymo
                  
               
               37 
                     Gerūcius
                     portrait of Geruncius
                  
               
               38 
                     Catillus
                     portrait of Catillus
                  
               
               39 
                     Coilus
                     portrait of Coilus
                  
               
               40 
                     Porer
                     portrait of Porer
                  
               
               41 
                     Chirinnus
                     portrait of Chirinnus
                  
               
               42 
                     Fulgen
                     portrait of Fulgen
                  
               
               43 
                     Eldred
                     portrait of Eldred
                  
               
               44 
                     Adrogius
                     portrait of Adrogius
                  
               
               45 
                     
                        Ʋarianus
                     portrait of Ʋarianus
                  
               
               46 
                     Eliud
                     portrait of Eliud
                  
               
               47 
                     Dedantius
                     portrait of Dedantius
                  
               
               48 
                     Detonus
                     portrait of Detonus
                  
               
               49 
                     Gurgineus
                     portrait of Gurgineus
                  
               
               50 
                     Merianus
                     portrait of Merianus
                  
               
               51 
                     Bladunus
                     portrait of Bladunus
                  
               
               52 
                     Capenus
                     portrait of Capenus
                  
               
               53 
                     Ouinus
                     portrait of Ouinus
                  
               
               54 
                     Silius
                     portrait of Silius
                  
               
               55 
                     Bledgabredꝰ
                     portrait of Bledgabredus
                  
               
               56 
                     Archemalus
                     portrait of Archemalus
                  
               
               57 
                     Eldelus
                     portrait of Eldelus
                  
               
               58 
                     Rodianus
                     portrait of Rodianus
                  
               
               59 
                     Redargius
                     portrait of Redargius
                  
               
               60 
                     Samulius
                     portrait of Samulius
                  
               
               61 
                     Peniſellus
                     portrait of Penisellus
                  
               
               62 
                     Pirrhus
                     portrait of Pyrrhus
                  
               
               63 
                     Caporus
                     portrait of Caporus
                  
               
               64 
                     Dinellus
                     portrait of Dinellus
                  
               
               65 
                     Helius
                     portrait of Helius
                  
               
               66 
                     Lud
                     portrait of Lud
                  
               
               67 
                     Caſsiuelane
                     portrait of Cassiuelanus
                  
               
               68 
                     Theomantius
                     portrait of Theomantius
                  
               
               69 
                     Cymbalinus
                     portrait of Cymbaline
                  
               
               70 
                     Guiderius
                     portrait of Guiderius
                  
               
               71 
                     Aruiragus
                     portrait of Aruiragus
                  
               
               72
                     Marius
                     portrait of Marius
                  
               
               73 
                     Coilus
                     portrait of Coilus
                  
               
               74 
                     Lucie
                     portrait of Lucie
                  
               
               75 
                     Seuerus
                     portrait of Seuerus
                  
               
               76 
                     Baſſianus
                     portrait of Bassianus
                  
               
               77 
                     Caraſsus
                     portrait of Carassus
                  
               
               78 
                     Aſclepiodatus
                     portrait of Asclepiodatus
                  
               
               79 
                     Coill
                     portrait of Coill
                  
               
               80 
                     Conſtantius
                     portrait of Constantius
                  
               
               81 
                     Conſtantine ma▪
                     
                     portrait of Constantine the Great
                  
               
               82 
                     Octauius
                     portrait of Octauius
                  
               
               83 
                     Traherus
                     portrait of Traherus
                  
               
               84 
                     Maximus
                     portrait of Maximus
                  
               
               85 
                     Gratian
                     portrait of Gratian
                  
               
               86 
                     Conſtantne
                     portrait of Constantine
                  
               
               87 
                     Conſtantius
                     portrait of Constantius
                  
               
               88 
                     
                        Ʋortiger
                     portrait of Vortiger
                  
               
               89 
                     
                        Ʋortimer
                     portrait of Vortimer
                  
               
               90 
                     Aurelius
                     portrait of Aurelius
                  
               
               91 
                     
                        Ʋther pendragon
                     portrait of Vther Pendragon
                  
               
               
                  
                     Arthurs armes
                     blazon of King Arthur
                  
               
               92 
                     Arthur
                     portrait of King Arthur
                  
               
               93 
                     Conſtantine
                     portrait of Constantine
                  
               
               94 
                     Aurelius conanus
                     portrait of Aurelius conanus
                  
               
               95 
                     
                        Ʋortiporus
                     portrait of Vortiporus
                  
               
               96 
                     Malgo
                     portrait of Malgo
                  
               
               97 
                     Careticus
                     portrait of Careticus
                  
               
               98 
                     Cadwan
                     portrait of Cadwan
                  
               
               99 
                     Cadwallin
                     portrait of Cadwallin
                  
               
               100 
                     Cadwallader
                     portrait of Cadwallader
                  
               
               
                  
                     Cadwalladers
Armes
                     blazon of Cadwallader
                  
               
               
                  
                     ye Weſt Saxons Armes
                     blazon of the West Saxon kings
                  
               
               101 
                     Brithricus
                     portrait of Brithricus
                  
               
               102 
                     Egbert
                     portrait of Egbert
                  
               
               103 
                     Ethelwolphus
                     portrait of Ethelwulf
                  
               
               104 
                     Ethelwaldus
                     portrait of Ethelwald
                  
               
               105 
                     Ethelbert
                     portrait of Ethelbert
                  
               
               106 
                     Etheldred
                     portrait of Etheldred
                  
               
               107 
                     Alured
                     portrait of King Alfred
                  
               
               108 
                     Edward
                     portrait of Edward the Confessor
                  
               
               109 
                     Adelſtane
                     portrait of Athelstan
                  
               
               110 
                     Edmunde
                     portrait of Edmund
                  
               
               111 
                     Eldred
                     portrait of Eldred
                  
               
               112 
                     Edwine
                     portrait of Edwine
                  
               
               113 
                     Edgar
                     portrait of Edgar
                  
               
               114 
                     Edward
                     portrait of Edward
                  
               
               115 
                     Egelrede
                     portrait of Egelrede
                  
               
               116 
                     Swen Forkbeard
                     portrait of Swain
                  
               
               117 
                     Edmunde ironſydes
                     portrait of Edmund Ironsides
                  
               
               118 
                     Canutus
                     portrait of Canute
                  
               
               119 
                     Haroldharefoote
                     portrait of Harold Harefoot
                  
               
               120 
                     Hardikenitus
                     portrait of Hardecanute
                  
               
               121 
                     Edwarde
                     portrait of Edward
                  
               
               122 
                     Harolde
                     portrait of Harold
                  
               
               
                  
                     William Conquers Armes
                     blazon of William the Conqueror
                  
               
               123 
                     William Cōqueror
                     portrait of William the Conqueror
                  
               
               124 
                     William Rufus
                     portrait of William Rufus
                  
               
               125 
                     Henri the .i.
                     portrait of Henry I
                  
               
               
                  
                     K. Stephēs armes
                     blazon of King Stephen's armes
                  
               
               126 
                     K. Stephen.
                     portrait of King Stephen
                  
               
               
                  
                     Henri ye 2 arme.
                     blazon of Henry II
                  
               
               127 
                     Henri the .2.
                     portrait of Henry II
                  
               
               128 
                     Richard the .1.
                     portrait of Richard I
                  
               
               129 
                     K. Iohn.
                     portrait of King John
                  
               
               130 
                     Henry the .3.
                     portrait of Henry III
                  
               
               131 
                     Edward the .1.
                     portrait of Edward I
                  
               
               132 
                     Edward the .2.
                     portrait of Edward II
                  
               
               
                  
                     E. the 
                           •
                         armes
                     blazon of Edward II
                  
               
               133 
                     Edward the .3.
                     portrait of Edward III
                  
               
               134 
                     Richard the .2.
                     portrait of Richard II
                  
               
               135 
                     Henri the .4.
                     portrait of Henry IV
                  
               
               
                  
                     H. the .5. Armes.
                     blazon of Henry V
                  
               
               136 
                     Henri the. 5.
                     portrait of Henry V
                  
               
               137 
                     Henri the 6
                     portrait of Henry VI
                  
               
               138 
                     Edward the .4.
                     portrait of Edward IV
                  
               
               139 
                     Edward the .5.
                     portrait of Edward V
                  
               
               140 
                     Richard the .3.
                     portrait of Richard III
                  
               
               141 
                     Henri the .7.
                     portrait of Henry VII
                  
               
               142 
                     Henri the .8.
                     portrait of Henry VIII
                  
               
               143 
                     Edward the 6
                     portrait of Edward VI
                  
               
               144 
                     Queene. Marye .i.
                     portrait of Queen Mary
                  
               
               145 
                     Qu. Elizabeth.
                     portrait of  Elizabeth I
                  
               
               
                  
                     the Kīges armes
                     royal blazon or coat of arms
                  
               
               146 
                     King Iames
                     portrait of James I
                  
               
               147 
                     King Charles
                     portrait of Charles I
                  
               
               
                  
                     Queene Marye
                     portrait of Queen Henrietta Maria
                  
               
               
                  
                     Prince Charles
                     portrait of Prince Charles (the future Charles II)
                  
               
            
         
      
   

