
   
      
         
            A declaration of certaine principall articles of religion set out by the order of both archbishops metropolitans, and the rest of the byshops, for the vnitie of doctrine to be taught and holden by all parsons, vicars, and curates aswell in testification of their common consent in the sayde doctrin, to the stopping of the mouthes of them that go about to slaunder the ministers of the church for diuersitie of iudgement, as necessarie for the instruction of their people, to be read by the syd parsons, vicars and curates, at their possession taking or first entrie into their cures, and also after that yeerely at two several times, that is to say, the Sundayes next following Easter day and Saint Michael tharchangell, or on some other Sunday within one moneth after those feastes, immediatly after the gospell.
            Church of England.
         
         
            
               1579
            
         
         Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00044
            STC 10034.7
            ESTC S3157
            33143080
            ocm 33143080
            28216
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00044)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28216)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1877:65)
         
         
            
               
                  A declaration of certaine principall articles of religion set out by the order of both archbishops metropolitans, and the rest of the byshops, for the vnitie of doctrine to be taught and holden by all parsons, vicars, and curates aswell in testification of their common consent in the sayde doctrin, to the stopping of the mouthes of them that go about to slaunder the ministers of the church for diuersitie of iudgement, as necessarie for the instruction of their people, to be read by the syd parsons, vicars and curates, at their possession taking or first entrie into their cures, and also after that yeerely at two several times, that is to say, the Sundayes next following Easter day and Saint Michael tharchangell, or on some other Sunday within one moneth after those feastes, immediatly after the gospell.
                  Church of England.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.).   
               
                  By Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes Maiestie,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1579?]
               
               
                  Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England. --  Thirty-nine Articles.
               Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               ❧A declaration of certaine principall Articles of Religion,
ſet out by the order of both Archbiſhops Metropolitans, and the reſt of the Byſhops,
for the vnitie of doctrine to be taught and holden of all Parſons, Vicars, and Curates, aſwell in teſtification of their
common conſent in the ſayde doctrine, to the ſtopping of the mouthes of them that go about to ſlaunder the miniſters of the Church
for diuerſitie of iudgement: as neceſſarie for the inſtruction of their people, to be read by the ſayd Parſons, Vicars, and Curates,
at their poſſeſſion taking o
                  •
                firſt entrie into their Cures: And alſo after that yeerely at two ſeuerall times. That is to ſay,
the Sundayes next following Eaſter day and Saint Michael tharchan
                  •
               ell, or on ſome other
Sunday within one moneth after thoſe feaſtes, immediatly after the Goſpell.
            
               FOraſmuch as it appertaineth to all Chriſtian men, but eſpecially to the miniſters and the
paſtours of the Church, being teachers &amp; inſtructers of others, to be ready to giue a reaſon
of their faith when they ſhalbe thereunto required: I for my part nowe appointed
your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, hauing before mine eyes the feare of God, &amp; the teſtimonie
of my conſcience, do acknowledge for my ſelfe, and require you to aſſent to the ſame.
i Fyrſt that there is but one liuing and true God, of infinite power, wiſedome, &amp; goodneſſe,
the maker and preſeruer of all things, and that in vnitie of this Godhead, there be three perſons of
one ſubſtance, of equall power and eternitie, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.
            ii I beleeue alſo whatſoeuer is conteined in the holy Canonicall Scriptures, in the which Scriptures
are conteined all things neceſſarie to ſaluation, by the which alſo al errours &amp; hereſies may ſufficiently be
reproued and conuicted, and all doctrine and Articles neceſſarie to ſaluation eſtablyſhed. I do alſo moſt
firmely beleeue and confeſſe all the Articles conteined in the three Creedes: the Nicene Creede, Athanaſius
Creede, and our common Creede, called the Apoſtles Creede: for theſe do briefly conteine the principall
Articles of our faith, which are ar large ſet forth in the holy Scriptures.
            iii I acknowledge alſo that Church to be the ſpouſe of Chriſt, wherein the word of God is truly taught,
the Sacraments orderly miniſtred according to Chriſtes inſtitution, and the authoritie of the keys duely
vſed. And that euery ſuch particular Church hath authoritie to inſtitute, to change, &amp; cleane to put away
Ceremonies and other Eccleſiaſticall rites, as they be ſuperfluous, or be abuſed, and to conſtitute other,
making more to ſeemelyneſſe, to order, or edification.
            iiii Moreouer I confeſſe that it is not lawfull for any man to take vpon him any office or miniſtery, eyther
Eccleſiaſtical or ſecular, but ſuch onely as are lawfully thereunto called by their high authorities, according
to the ordinances of this Realme.
            v Furthermore I do acknowledge the Queenes Maieſties prerogatiue, and ſuperioritie of gouernement
of all eſtates &amp; in all cauſes, aſwel Eccleſiaſticall as Temporal, within this Realme, &amp; other her dominions
&amp; countreys, to be agreeable to Gods word, &amp; of right to appertaine to her highneſſe, in ſuch ſort
as is in ye late Act of Parliament expreſſed, &amp; ſithens by her Maieſties Iniūctions declared &amp; expounded.
            vi Moreouer, touching the Byſhop of Rome, I do acknowledge and confeſſe, that by the Scriptures
and word of God, he hath no more authoritie then other Byſhops haue in their prouinces and dioceſſes:
And therefore ye power which he now challengeth, that is, to be ye ſupreme head of the vniuerſall Church
of Chriſt, and ſo to be aboue all Emperours, Kinges, and Princes, is an vſurped power, contrary to the
Scriptures and worde of God, and contrary to the example of the primitiue Church. And therefore is
for moſt iuſt cauſes taken away, and abolyſhed within this Realme.
            vii Furthermore I do graunt and confeſſe, that the booke of common prayer &amp; adminiſtration of the
holy Sacraments, ſet forth by authoritie of parliament, is agreeable to the Scriptures, &amp; that it is Catholike,
Apoſtolike, &amp; moſt for the aduauncing of Gods glory, and the edifying of Gods people, both for
that it is in a tongue that may be vnderſtanded of the people, and alſo for the doctrine and fourme of miniſtration
contained in the ſame.
            viii And although in the adminiſtration of Baptiſme, there is neyther exorciſme, oyle, ſalt, ſpittle, or halowing
of the water nowe vſed. And for that they were of late yeeres abuſed, and eſteemed neceſſarie,
where they perteine not to the ſubſtance and neceſſitie of the Sacrament, they be reaſonably abolyſhed:
and yet the Sacrament ful and perfectly miniſtred to all intents and purpoſes agreeable to the inſtitution
of our Sauiour Chriſt.
            ix Moreouer I do not onely acknowledge, that priuate maſſes were neuer vſed amongſt the fathers of
the primitiue Church, I meane publike miniſtration &amp; receiuing of the Sacrament by the prieſt alone,
without a iuſt number of communicants, according to Chriſtes ſaying, Take ye, and eate ye, &amp;c. but alſo
that the doctrine, which maintaineth the maſſe to be a propitiatorie ſacrifice for the quicke and the dead,
and a meane to deliuer ſoules out of purgatorie, is neyther agreeable to Chriſts ordinance, nor grounded
vpon doctrine Apoſtolike, but contrarywiſe moſt vngodly &amp; moſt iniurious to the precious redemption of
our Sauiour Chriſt, and his onely ſufficient ſacrifice offered once for euer vpon the altar of the croſſe.
            x I am of that minde alſo, that the holy Communion or Sacrament of the body and bloud of Chriſt, for
the due obedience to Chriſtes inſtitution, and to expreſſe the vertue of the ſame, ought to be miniſtred vnto
the people vnder both kindes, &amp; that it is auouched by certaine fathers of the Church, to be a plaine ſacriledge
to robbe them of the myſticall cup, for whom Chriſt hath ſhed his moſt precious bloud: Seing he
him ſelfe hath ſaid, Drinke ye all of this. Conſidering alſo that in the time of the auncient doctours of the
Church, as Ciprian, Ierome, Auguſtine, Gelaſius &amp; others, vi.C. yeeres after Chriſt and more, both the
partes of the Sacrament were miniſtred to the people.
            Laſt of all, as I do vtterly diſalowe the extolling of Images, Relickes, and fayned myracles, and alſo
all kindes of expreſſing God inuiſible, in the fourme of an olde man, or the holy Ghoſt, in fourme of a
Doue, and all other vaine worſhipping of God, deuiſed by mans fantaſie, beſides or contrary to ye Scriptures:
(as wandring on pilgrimages, ſetting vp of candles, praying vpon beades, &amp; ſuch like ſuperſtition,)
which kinde of workes haue no promiſe of reward in ſcripture, but contrarywiſe threatnings and maledictions:
So I do exhort all men to the obedience of Gods lawe, and to the woorkes of faith, as charitie,
mercie, pitie, almes, deuout and feruent prayer with thaffection of the heart, &amp; notwith the mouth onely,
godly abſtinence &amp; faſting, chaſtitie, obedience to the rulers &amp; ſuperiour powers, with ſuch like works
and godlynes of life, commaunded by God in his word: which as Saint Paul ſaith, hath promiſes both
of this life, and of the life to come, and are workes onely acceptable in Gods ſight.
            Theſe thinges aboue rehearſed, though they be appointed by common order, yet do I without all
compulſion, with freedome of minde &amp; conſcience, from the bottome of my heart, and vpon moſt ſure perſwaſion,
acknowledge to be true and agreeable to Gods word. And therefore I exhort you al, of whom
I haue cure, heartily &amp; obediently to embrace and receiue the ſame, that we al ioyning together in vnitie
of ſpirit, faith, &amp; charitie, may alſo at length be ioyned together in ye kingdome of God, &amp; that through the

                  •••…
               ts and death of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be all

                  •••
               ry and empire, nowe and for euer. Amen.
         
      
      
         
            ¶Imprinted at London by Chriſtopher Barker, printer
to the Queenes Maieſtie.
         
      
   

