
   
      
         
            A letter vvritten out of England to an English gentleman remaining at Padua containing a true report of a strange conspiracie, contriued betweene Edward Squire, lately executed for the same treason as actor, and Richard Walpoole a Iesuite, as deuiser and suborner against the person of the Queenes Maiestie.
            Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.
         
         
            
               1599
            
         
         Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00021
            STC 10017
            ESTC S101177
            99836999
            99836999
            1303
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00021)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1303)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 341:14)
         
         
            
               
                  A letter vvritten out of England to an English gentleman remaining at Padua containing a true report of a strange conspiracie, contriued betweene Edward Squire, lately executed for the same treason as actor, and Richard Walpoole a Iesuite, as deuiser and suborner against the person of the Queenes Maiestie.
                  Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.
               
               [2], 13, [1] p.   
               
                  By the deputies of Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1599.
               
               
                  Attributed to Francis Bacon.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Squire, Edward, d. 1598.
               Walpole, Richard, 1564-1607.
               Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2000-00
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2001-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-01
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-01
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Text and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A Letter written out of England
to an English Gentleman remaining
at Padua, containing a true Report of a
strange Conspiracie, contriued betweene
Edward Squire, lately exec
                  ••
               ed for the same treason as Actor, and Richard

                     •
                  allpoole a Iesuite, as Deuiser
and Suborner against the
person of the Queenes
Maiestie.
            Imprinted at London by the Deputies
of CHRISTOPHER BARKER,
Printer to the Queenes most
excellent Maiestie.
1599.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            SIR, I thanke you for
your Relation of Ferrara;
and to make you paiment
in the like commodities,
I returne to you a
true report of a fresh accident
of State, happened
here with vs; memorable
for the strangenesse
of the matter, and the
great signification it carieth
with it of Gods extraordinarie
and most visible prouidence; but otherwise
woorthy to be damned to perpetuall obliuion, as
well for the detestable nature of the fact, as yet more
(if more were possible) for the impietie of the perswasion;
such as I assure you, a man ought to make scruple
to infame the times, or infect mens cogitations with
the repetition of it, were it not that these workes of
darknesse are framed and forged in such a deepe vawte
of hypocrisie, as there is more danger, that they should
be vnreuealed or vnbeleeued, then that being brought
to cleare light, they should prouoke an imitation in any,
of that which is so odious and foule.
            And this Sir you may beleeue, that as I haue had
good meanes, to informe my selfe to the full, of that

which passed in this matter, and the trueth of all the
particulars, aswell those which were opened at the arreignment
of Edward Squire, one of the offenders, as
those which were reserued, so I haue set downe this
Narration, rather abridged of some circumstances,
then any wayes amplified or inlarged.
            This Squire dwelt in Greenwich diuers yeeres, and
tooke vpon him the practise of a Scriuener, yet rather
as a helpe to maintaine himselfe for a time, then that
he bare a minde to settle in that trade. He obtained
also before his going to Sea, for some two yeres space,
an imployment about the Queenes Stable, by way of
deputation to one Kaies, a Purueiour of those prouisions.
But being of a wit aboue his vocation, disliked
with that condition of life, and put himselfe into action
by Sea, in the last voyage Sir Francis Drake made
into the Indies; in which voyage, it was his hap, that
the Frances
                     •
                  
                (a small barke wherein he went) was scattered
from the Fleet about Guadalupe, and taken by

                  •
               iue Spanish frigots. And so was Squire brought prisoner
into Spaine, where soone after he was set at libertie.
            Not long after his inlargement, he became known
to Richard Walpoole an English fugitiue, and by order
a Iesuite, a man of principall credit there, and a kinde
of Vicar generall to Parsons in his absence. This Walpoole,
carrying a waking &amp; waiting eye, vpon those of
our Nation, to discouer and single out sit instruments
for the greatest treasons, obserued this Squire, found
him a man of more then ordinarie sence and capacitie,
for his qualitie and education; found him a man,
that had passed his middle age, well aduised, and yet

resolued enough, and not apprehensiue at all of danger;
(for I doe affirme this vnto you, that neuer man
answered vpon his triall for life and death, with lesse
perturbation, nay scarsely with any alteration, as if he
vnderstood not his perill and calamitie, and yet as
sensible for speech, as insensible for passion.) But besides
the disposition and temper of the man, Walpoole
discerned in him two conditions of speciall aduantage;
The one, that comming into Spaine a prisoner,
and not a fugitiue, his returne into England would be
subiect to lesse suspition: The other, that he vnderstood,
Squire had formerly had some attendance about
the Queenes Stable, which he streight caught
holde of, as an opportunity.
            Yet neuerthelesse, the better to prepare him, and
worke him to his purpose; and the better also to giue
couler,(when Squire should returne into England) that
he was a man that had suffered in Spaine for his conscience,
subtilly he compassed, that vpon a quarrell
picked, Squire was put into the Inquisition. By this
meanes, when he had got his heart into his handes,
mollified by distresse, and became secure of him, that
he was a fixed and resolued Papist.
            After probation and preparation sufficient, hee began
to open himselfe vnto him; and first for introduction,
fell into the ordinary burden or song, of that
kinde of people, touching the tyrannies and persecutions
exercised here in England against Catholiques;
though Sir, you know very well, the distinction and
moderation of the proceedings here in Ecclesiasticall
causes, with what lenitie, and gentlenesse, it hath
bene caried, except where it was mixed with matter

of State; for els I would gladly learne, what should
make the difference, betweene the temper of the
Lawes in the first yeere of the Queene, and in 23. or
27. but that at the one time, they were Papists in conscience,
and at the other they were growne Papists in
faction; or what should make the difference at this
day in Lawe, betweene a Queene Mary Priest, and a
Seminarie Priest, saue that the one is a Priest of supers
                  •
               ition,
and the other is a Priest of sedition. But to
the purpose; After the Iesuite had at sundry conferences,
discoursed his pleasure of the miseries of Catholiques
here in England, and of the slanders of the
gouernment, and vpon how fewe persons liues, the
State here did stand; and Squire on the other side,
(who wanted no witte to perceiue which way hee was
ledde) had first made some signification, and after
some more serious and vehement protestation of his
minde and deuotion, to doe seruice to the cause, when
the wicked Frier fawe hee was gotten into the true
circle, hee began to charme; and yet not hauing the
power to fall vpon the highest point first, without a
gradation or bridge, It were no doubt (saith hee) an
acte 
                     •
                  ery meritorious to kill the Earle of Essex, but Vnum
necessarium, One thing is necessary. And hauing kept
him in suspence a while, brake with him plainely,
and tolde him, that hee would put a seruice into his
hands, that he might execute and accomplish, without
any euident perill of his life, because it was to be
done, what time the Queene her selfe should not bee
in presence; (which I thinke he spake as hauing heard
that which is very true, of some Conspirators, that
hauing vndertaken and vowed her Maiesties destruction,

haue neuerthelesse at the very instant of the accesse
and opportunitie, bene stricken with astonishment,
and had no power to execute their malice.)
Nay further he said, that he should not need to feare,
in the doing thereof, to be seene or obserued, by any
persons of care or iudgement, but such as might be
easily conuersed withall, without suspition: And it
was the impoysonment of the pommell of the
Queenes Sadell, at such time as shee should ride abroad;
her Maiestie being like to rest her hand thereupon,
for a good time together, and not vnlike for her
hand to come often about her face, mouth, and nosethrils;
and this by reason of his former acquaintance
and seruice about the Stable, he thought hee might
easily performe, and safely; And yet he said, If imminent
death should insue thereupon hee might not accompt
of it, as beeing assured that hee should exchange
his present state, with the state of a glorious Saint in heauen.
Vnto which accursed proposition after that
Squire had assented, then did the Frier vse all diligence
to confirme and binde him to resolution and performance.
And to that ende, at sundry confessions
tooke his vow and promise to be constant; caused him
to receiue the Sacrament vpon it; renued his diuelish
perswasions, varying them in all fourmes to besiege
his minde and cogitations, that he might finde no
way to get out of this wicked purpose; Telling him
that he stood now in the state of damnation, if he did not
his vttermost endeuour to perfourme his vowe. And bid
him remember how that sinne did seldome obtaine pardon;
and if he did but once make doubt of the lawfulnesse
or merit of the acte, it was enough to cast him headlong

downe into hell; And if he did cast any difficulties or
terrors, he wished him to consider What it did auaile
a man to winne the whole world, and to leese his owne soule.
So as now Squire must not descend into himselfe, he
must make no obiections, cast no doubts; but the eyes
of his vnderstanding blinded and sealed vp, he must
onely contemplate vpon these vowes and adiurations.
And for a conclusion and finall benediction of this
most execrable plot, Squire kneeling before Wallpoole
at confession, he lifted him vp, hugde him about the
necke with his left arme (such were Squires owne
wordes) and crossing him with the other hand after
some wordes mumbled in Latine, sayd distinctly to
him in English, God blesse thee and giue thee strength my
sonne; be of good courage, I pawne my soule for thine, and
thou shalt haue my prayers dead and aliue. And vpon this
imbracement and inchantment, this desperate wretch
and this blasphemous Exorcist parted for that time.
            Then doeth he giue him ful instructions for the disposing
of this poison; shewing him that he should receiue
it in a double bladder, and when it should bee
vsed, hee was to pricke the bladderfull of holes vpon
the vpper part, and so to carie it within the palme of his
hand with a thicke gloue for the safegard of his hand:
and in the instant when it was to be applied, he should
turne it in his hand 
                  •
               he vpside downe, and so presse
it hard vpon the pommell of the saddell: telling him
further of the nature of it, That it would lie and tarrie
long where it was laide; and that it would not be checked
by the aire. And lastly vpon his comming away,
deliuered him the confection it selfe in such a bladder
as was before described.
            
               This was the true maner of the subornation of Edward
Squire by Richard Wallpoole as it was confessed by
the same Squire almost in the same wordes, as well for
the perswasions as for the instructions. Which confession
I doe affirme vnto you vpon knowledge was deliuered
without torture or shewe of torture: and was
roundly and sensibly vttered with all circumstances of
a credible narration for that part which concerneth
the maner of the impoisonment: and for that part
which concerneth the manner of the perswasion was
set downe by an aduised declaration vnder his owne
hand, and the same as farre as hitherto we haue gone,
was mainteined and confirmed, and in no point retracted
or disauowed, either at his trial or at his death.
            It seemes also that Wallpoole in some of his conferences
did insist vpon the impoisonment of the Earle
of Essex, the rather to defeate the voyage by Sea, then
exspected (for these things past about May 1597.) So
as Squire conceiued it, there could bee no one thing
more acceptable in the second degree.
            Nowe after that Squire had receiued both poisons,
as well the spirituall poison of wicked resolution, as
the materiall within the bladders; and that Wallpoole
had interlaced some promise to him of rewardes and
comforts, besides those of the other world, and had
schooled him for secrecie, which he made to be parcel
of his vow, there rested onely his dispatch for England.
Whereunto to giue an apt colour, it was deuised that
there should be a permutation treated, by the meanes
of a Chanon in Ciuill of two Spanish prisoners here, taken
at Cales, friends of the saide Chanon, for Squire
and Rowles nowe Prisoner in the Towre, who came ouer

with him
                  •
                wherby it might be caried, farre off from
suspition, that Squire did not returne as a man imploied,
but vpon that priuate occasion. According to
which proiect he was sent away conueniently moneyed,
that he might be the better in heart, and yet not so
abundantly as might make him loue his life too well,
and to goe away with his fare quietly, though indeed
there were more money stirring, but not in that hand.
            And being arriued here in England about a fortnight
before the Earles setting foorth towardes the
Ilandes, hee did addresse himselfe to a Counseller of
Estate here, both to shew himselfe to the end to auoid
suspition, and with pretence also of some aduertisements,
to the ende to winne the better opinion and
trust; and finding his comming well conceiued of according
to his desire, hee did craftily and subtilely deuise
with himselfe, that if he could finde any opportunitie
to execute his purpose before the Earle went,
(supposing that the poyson could not worke but in
some space of time) it would be more securitie for him
to be absent, and in the voyage, left percase some suspitious
tokens of poison
                  •
                appearing, somewhat might
fall out (vpon such diligent inquisition as in such a case
were like to bee made) to bee discouered against
him; and therefore made his meanes to goe with the
Earle in his Shippe
                  •
                and obtained his sute. So as nowe
making his reckoning to haue the peril vpon his back,
he did but watch his time.
            And it pleased God for the manifestation of his glory,
that the Mundaie seuennight next after Squires
comming home out of Spaine, he vnderstood that the
horses were making readie for her Maiesties riding abroad.

Whereupon, full of those euill spirites wherewith
so many exorcismes had possessed him, hee came
into the Stable yard where her Maiesties horse stood
ready sadled, and in a familiar and cheerefull maner in
the hearing of diuers that stood thereby, hauing all
things ready according to his instructions, he laied his
hand vpon the pommell of the Saddle, and sayd, God
saue the Queene, (wherein it pleased God to take his
words and not his meaning) and bruized the poison as
he was directed.
            Thus was her Maiesties sacred and precious life by
the All-haile of a second Iudas betrayed, the attempt
put in act, and all the Conspirators part plaied to the
vttermost line and title; there rested onely Gods part:
For so it was, that her Maiesties going abroad held; &amp;
as the Viper was vpon S. Pauls hand, and shaked off
without hurt; so this done, was in Iuly in the heate of
the yeere, when the poores and veines were openest to
receiue any maligne vapor or tincture, if her Maiestie
by any accident had layd her hand vpon the place. And
as the Heathenish people at that time did argue and
conclud
                  •
                thereupon, that S. Paul was a God, so wee
may christianly inferre that it was Gods doing and
power who hath defended his Handmaid and seruant
by his secret and more then naturall influence and preseruatiue
from so actuall &amp; mortall a danger, speaking
by these signes to all her disloyall Subiects and ambitious
enemies, That as he hath done great things by her,
past ordinarie discourse of reason, so he hath done, and
will doe as great things for her, beyond the course of
his ordinarie prouidence.
            For surely, if a man consider how many times her

life hath bene sought and assailed, since the beginning
of her raigne, by violence, by poisoning, by supersticious
Votaries, by ambicious Vndertakers, by singular
Conspirators, by Conspirators combined, (speaking
of those that haue bene reuealed, besides a number (no
doubt) of the like which haue groueled in darkenesse,
and neuer came to light) hee will not find the like reflexion
of Gods fauour in any Soueraigne Prince that
hath reigned.
            But in the meane time you see the strange mysteries
of the Iesuites doctrine that haue mingled heauen and
hel, and lift vp the hands of Subiects against the anointed
of God; arming them with the inuisible armour of
Scriptures, Sacraments, Vowes, Prayers and Blessings
against their naturall Soueraigns. Wherein there is
great difference betweene the spirite that wrought in
Dauid, and this that worketh in them. For Dauid when
relation was made to him (by one that thought he had
done Saul the last good office) how Saul had fallen vpon
his owne sword in battell, and being in the anguish
of death, and carefull not to fall aliue in the handes of
the Philistims a people vncircumcised desired this soldiour
to make an ende of him, who did so, and was
therefore by Dauid adiudged to die, because hee dared
to lay his hands vpon the anointed of the Lord: and
yet was Saul a king forsaken and abandoned of God;
he had taken his mortall wound before, so as this soldiour
tooke from him his paine, and not his life; and it
was to a good ende, least a heathenish people should
reproch the name of God by insulting vpon the person
of Saul.
            
            And surely for my part I doe wonder that Princes

doe not concurre in loosing these bands, and suppressing
this Sect, which maketh a traffique of their sacred
liues, concluding and contracting for them with these
blinded Votaries in the secrecie of confessions and
shrifts. For I doe not see that Pirates (whom the Ciuilians
account to be Publici hostes societatis humanae, and
therefore Princes bound as they affirme, though they
be otherwise in no league one with an other, yea and
though they be enemies, to ioyne in the suppressing &amp;
extirpation of them) are any such disturbers of humane
societie as these are. Neither doe I thinke, that
the order of the Templers (that was put down throughout
Christendome in a fewe weekes) were euer offenders
in so high a degree. And I find somewhat strange
that the bishop of Rome (if it were but to auoyd the
aspersion of so great a slander and imputation to that
Religion) should not purge out this leauen so strange
and odious.
            But to returne: within fiue or sixe dayes after this
fact committed, Squire went to Sea in the Erles owne
ship, and belike as Tacitus sayth, Ferox scelerum quia
prima prouenerant, taking the remaine of the same poison
with him in a little pot in his portmantue, when
the Earle was at Sea betweene Faial and S
                     •
                   Michael, he
bestowed it vpon the pommels of a chaire of wood,
where the Earle vsed to dine and sup: but thankes be
to God nothing came of it neither.
            Now let me acquaint you a little with the maner of
detecting of this matter, which God did likewise
strangely bring about. Squire slept now in securitie:
for although he failed of successe, yet he tooke himselfe
to be out of danger: thinking because it was carried

betweene his Confessour and him, it could neuer
be reuealed. But his Confessour whom it imported
not so much to keepe it secret as it did Squire, tickled
belike with the ioy, that he had such an iron in the
fire, imparted it (for his owne glory) to some principall
of the fugitiues there; This raised a great expectation
in them of some effect to insue. When time passed,
and nothing came of it, they made construction
of it, that Squire had beene false to them. One of the
more passionate of them inueyeth bitterly against
Squire, telles how he was trusted, and how he had vndone
the cause; and the better to be reuenged on him,
is content that one (that they let slip hither as if he had
fled from them) should giue information of this matter,
not with the circumstances, but generally against
Squire, partly to win himselfe credit, partly to wrecke
themselues on Squire. And this fellow, because hee
would be thought to do the better seruice, would not
bring this in his mouth, but in a letter, which he pretended
to haue stolne out of one of their Studies. This
letter compared with another letter that the same
man brought as written from a seuerall person, both
which letters had one and the same busie knot to both
names, is suspected to be counterfeited; it is so found.
Heereupon it is collected that this was but an engine
against Squire, and that he was an honest man. Yet because
it was a tender matter, Squire was sent for and examined.
For a time he denieth; after, he commeth to
some circumstances, which concurring with the others
tale, it gaue it to be vnderstood that there was
somewhat true, and that all was not an inuention against
him: Holde was taken of that; and thereupon

               Squire, not knowing how farre his Confessor had broken
trust with him, by good perswasion, and Gods
good working, disclosed all without any rigour in the
world.
            
               
                  •
               ut vpon a second aduise being a man of a very
good reach, finding that it had bene his wisest way to
haue confessed the whole plot and subornation which
was knowen to Wallpoole, and there to haue stopt, and
not to haue tolde of the putting of i
                  •
                in execution,
which was onely knowne to himselfe, and which indeede
was wonne from him by good following, hee
endeuoured at his arraignment to haue distinguished,
and auowching the first part, to haue retracted the second;
pretending that although he vndertooke it, yet
he had not any purpose to performe it.
            Whereupon one of the Commissioners being wel
acquainted with all the particular circumstances, did
set before him the absurditie of his deniall against his
former confession which was voluntarie, particular,
and needlesse (otherwise then in conscience of trueth)
vpon which speech hee being stricken with remorse,
and conuicted in himselfe, acknowledged and iustified
the trueth of his former confession in the hearing of all
the standers by.
            Thus Sir, I haue interteined you with a discourse,
which I thinke in reading will affect you diuersly, as it
did me in writing; But in the ende I thinke wee shall
ioyne in congratulating for our good deliuerance,
and desiring of God the continuance of her
Maiestie, in whom our good
dayes do consist.
         
      
   

