
   
      
         
            Merie tales of the made men of Gotam gathered to gether by A.B. of phisike doctour.
            Merry tales of the mad men of Gotham.
         
         
            
               1565
            
         
         Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00179
            STC 1020.5
            ESTC S1525
            20191373
            ocm 20191373
            23790
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00179)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23790)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1700:21)
         
         
            
               
                  Merie tales of the made men of Gotam gathered to gether by A.B. of phisike doctour.
                  Merry tales of the mad men of Gotham.
                  Boorde, Andrew, 1490?-1549.
               
               [39] p.   
               
                  Imprinted at London in Fletstret, beneath the Conduit, at the signe of S. John euangelist, by Thomas Colwell,
                  [London] :
                  [1565]
               
               
                  T.p. contains woodcut illustration.
                  Sometimes attributed to Andrew Boorde--NUC pre-1956 imprints.
                  Imprint taken from colophon; date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).
                  Signatures: A-B⁸ C⁴.
                  Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-07
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-08
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-08
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Merie Tales of the mad men of Gotam.
            Gathered to gether by A. B. of Phiſike Doctour.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ¶ Here beginneth certain merie tales of the mad men of Gotam.
            
               ¶ The firſt tale.
               
                  THeare was two men of Gotam, &amp; the one was goyng to the market to Nottyngham to buye ſheepe and the other dyd come from the Market, and bothe met together vppon Nottingham brydge. Well met ſaid the one to the other. Whether be you going (ſayde hee that came from Nottyngeham, to hym that wente to Nottingeham.) Marye ſayde be that wente to Nottyngham, I goe to the market to buye ſheepe.

Buye ſheepe ſaide the other? and whyche waye wylte thou brynge them. Marye ſayde the other. I wyll brynge them ouer thys bridge. By Robyn hoode ſayd he that cam from Nottingham, but thou ſhalte not. By Mayde Maryon ſayde he that wente to the market but I wyll. Thou ſhalte not ſayde the other. I wyll ſayde the other. Let bere, ſayd the one. Shows theare, ſayde the other. They beat theyr ſtaues agaynſte the grounde, one agaynſte the other, as theare had bene a hundred ſeepe betwixt them. Holde in theare layde the one. Beware of 
                     〈…〉
                  yng ouer the brydge of my ſheepe ſayd the other, I care not ſa
                     •
                  d the other, they ſhal not come thys waye by the maſſe. By the maſſe ſayde the other, but they

ſhall. Then ſayde the other, and thou make muche to doe, I wyll put my fynger in thy mouthe. A turde thou wilte, ſaide the other. And as they weare at thys contencyon, another man of Gotam dyd come from the market wyth a ſacke of meale vppon an horſe. And ſeyng &amp; hearing his neyghboures at ſtryfe, for ſheepe, and none betwixt them ſaid a fooles will you neuer learne wyt. Helpe we ſaide bee that had the meale, and laye my ſacke vppon my ſhulder, they dyd ſo. And he went to the one ſide of the bridge, and vn loſed the mouth of the ſacke, and did ſhake oute all hys meale in to the ryuer, now neyghbour ſayde this man, howe much meale is theare in my ſacke nowe, marye theare is noue at all ſayde they,

Now by my faythe ſayd he euen as muche witte is in youre twoo headdes, to ſtryue for that thyng which ye haue not.
               Which was the wiſeſt of al theſe three perſons? Judge you.
            
            
               ¶ The ii. tale.
               THeare was a man of Gotam dyd ryde to thee market wyth twoo buſſheles of wheate, and bycauſe hys horſe ſhoulde not beare heauye, hee caryed hys corne vppon hys owne necke, and dyd ryde vppon hys horſe, becauſe hys horſe ſhoulde not cary no heauy burthen.
            
            
               ¶ The iii. tale.
               On a time the mē of Gotam,

wold haue py
                     •
                  ned the Cockow, that ſhe ſhould ſing all the yeare and in the myddeſt of the towne they dyd make a hedge (round in compas,) and they had got a Cocow, and put her in it and ſayde, ſinge here all the yeare, and thou ſhalte lacke neyther meate nor drincke. The Cocow as ſoone as ſhee was ſet wyth in the hedge, flew her waye. A vengeaunce on her ſayde they, we made not our hedge high ynough.
            
            
               ¶ The iiii. tale.
               THere was a man of Gotam the which went to the market to Nottingham to ſell cheeſe. And as hee was goynge downe the hyll to Nottingham b
                     〈…〉
                  e, one of hys cheeſes dyd fall out of

hys poake, and did runne downe the hyl. A horſons ſaid the felow, can you rūne to the market alone I will ſende the one after the other of you. He layde downe hys poake, and tooke the cheeſes, and dyd trundle them downe the hyll one after another: and ſome ran into one buſſhe, and ſome into another. And at the laſte he ſayde I charge you all meete me in the market place. When the fellowe dyd come into the market place to meete hys cheeses, hee dyd tarie tyll the market was almoſte done. Then he went about, and dyd inquyre of hys neighboures, and other men if they did ſee his cheeſes come to the market? Who ſhoulde bringe them? ſayd one of the market men. Marye them ſelues ſayd the fellow, they knew

the way well ynoughe. He taryed ſtill tyll it was nyght. At nyghte he ſaid a vengeaunce on them al. I dyd feare to ſee that my cheeſes dyd runne ſo faſte, that they runne beyonde the market: I am ſure that they be almoſte now at Yorke. He hyred a horſe to ryde after to Yorke to ſeeke hys cheeſes wheare they weare not. But to thys daye, no man coulde tell hym of hys cheeſes.
            
            
               ¶ The v. tale.
               THeare was a man of Gotam and he did buy at Nottynge ham a Trefete (or a Brandyron.) And as he was going home, his ſhoulder dyd ake:

And hee dyd ſet downe hys Trefete, and ſee that it had thre feete ſayde, a horſen, haſte thou three feete, and I but two, thou ſhalte beare me home if thou wilte, and dyd ſyt downe on the trefete and ſayd, beare me as long as I haue borne the, for if thou do not, thou ſhalt ſtand ſtill for mee. The man of Gotam dyd ſee that hys Trefete wolde not goe further, ſtand ſtyll ſayd he in the Mares name, and folowe mee if thou wylte, I wyll tell thee the ryghte waye to my houſe. Whā he did com home to his houſe his wife ſayd, where is my Brandiron or trefete. The man ſayde he hath three legges, and I haue but two legges, and I dyd teach hym the way to my houſe, let hym come home if hee wyll. Wheare lefte ye the Trefete

ſayde the wyfe, at Gotam hyll, ſayde the man. The wife did run and fetch home hir trefete, or elſe ſhe had loſt it.
            
            
               ¶ The vi tale.
               THeare dwelt a ſmith in Gotam the whych had a Waſpes neſt in the ſtraw in the ende of his Forge. Theare dyd come one of hys neyghboures to haue hys horſe ſhooed, and the waſpes weare ſo buſye that the fellow was ſtong, with a waſpe. He beyng angrye ſayde, art thou worthy to keepe a Forge, to haue men ſt
                     •
                  nge here wythe Waſpes? O neyghboure ſayde the ſmythe, be content. I wyll put them from theyr neſte bye and bye. He tooke a Coulter and heated it in hys

Forge glowyng hote, and thruſte it into the ſtrawe in the ende of hys Forge. And ſo he dyd ſet hys Forge a fyre, and dyd burne it vppe. Than ſayde the Smythe. I tolde thee that I woulde fyre them forth of theyr neſtes.
            
            
               The vii. tale.
               WHen that good Frydaye was come, the men of Gotam dyd caſte theyr heads together what they ſhuld doe with theyr whyte hearyng, and theyr red hearyng, and their ſprottes, and ſalt fyſhe, One conſulted with the other, and agreed that all ſuch fyſh ſhould be caſt into their pōd or poole (the whiche was in the myddle of theyr towne,) that it myghte increaſe

againſte the nexte yeare. Euerye man that had any fiſhe lefte, dyd caſt it into the poole, the one ſayd I haue thus manye whyte hearinges, the other ſayde, I haue thus many ſprots, another ſayde I haue thus many red hearings, the other ſaid I haue thus much ſalte fyſhe. Let all go together in to the poole or pond, and we ſhall fare like Lordes next lent. At the beginninge of the next lent, folowinge, the men dyd drawe theyr ponde to haue theyr ſyſhe: &amp; there was nothing but a great Ele.
               (A ſayde they all) a mychiefe on this Ele, for he hathe eate vp all our fyſhe. What ſhal we do wyth hym ſayde the one to the other. Kill hym ſaid another. Chop him al to peces ſaid another. Nay not ſo ſaid other, let vs drowne him: be it ſayd all.
               
                  
They wente to another poole or pond by, and dyd caſt in the Eele into the water. Lye theare ſayde they and ſhift for thy ſelfe, for no helpe thou ſhalte haue of vs. And theare they lefte the Eele to bee drowned.
            
            
               The viii. tale.
               ON a time the men of Gotam had forgotten to paye theyr rent to their Lord. The one ſayd to the other, to morow is our pay day, and what reamedy ſhall we fynde to ſende our money to oure Lorde? The one ſayde thys daye I haue taken a quicke Hare, and he ſhall carye it, for he is lyght of foote. Be it ſayde all, he ſhal haue a letter, and a purſe to put in our money and wee wyll tell hym the

waye. When the Letters weare wryt, and the money put into a purſſe, they dyd tye them aboute the Hares necke ſayinge, fyrſte thou muſt go to Lowghburrow, and thē to Leyceter, and at newwarke theare is our Lorde, and commende vs to him, and theare is hys dutye. The hare as ſoone as hee was out of theyr handes, he did run a clene contrary way▪ Some cryed out to hym ſayinge thou muſt goe to Lowghburrow fyrſte. Some ſayde lett the Hare alone, he can tel a nearer way thē the beſt of vs all: let him go.
            
            
               The ix. tale.
               ON a tyme theare was one of Gotam mowynge in the meades, and found a great graſhopper.

He dyd caſte downe hys ſythe and dyd runne home to his neighbours and ſayde that there was a Deuill in the fyelde that hopped in the graſſe. Then there was euerye man readye wythe clubbes and ſtaues, wythe, Halbardes, and other weapons, to go to kill the Graſhopper. Whan they did come to the place where that the Graſhopper ſhoulde bee. Sayde the one to the other, lette euerye man croſſe hym ſelfe from this deuill, for we wyll not meddle wyth hym. And ſo they returned home againe and ſayde, wee weare well bleſte thys daye that we went no further. A cowardes ſayd he that had the ſythe in the mead, helpe me to fetch my ſithe. No ſaide they, it is good to ſleape in a whole ſkynne: better it is to

leeſe thy ſithe, then to mar vs all.
            
            
               The x. tale.
               IN a certaine tyme theare weare twelue of Gotam did goe a fyſſhyng, &amp; ſome did wade in the water, and ſome ſtoode a drye lande. And when that they went homewarde, the one ſayde to the other, wee haue ventured farre to day in wadyng I pray god that none of vs (that dyd come from home) bee drowned. Marye ſayde the one to the other, let vs ſee that, for theare dyd twelue of vs come oute. And they tolde themſelues, and euerye man dyd tell a leuen, and the twelfe man dyd neuer tell hym ſelfe. Alas ſayde the one to the other there is one of vs drowned.

They went backe to the brooke whear that they had ben fiſhing and ſought vp and down for him that was drowned, &amp; dyd make great lamentacion. A Courtyer dyd come ridyng by and dyd aſke what that they dyd ſeeke. And whye they weare ſo ſorye. O ſayd they this daye we wente to fyſſhe this brooke and there dyd come out twelue of vs, and one is drowned. Why ſaid the Courtier tell how many be of you. And the one tolde. xi. and hee dyd not tell himſelfe. Well ſayd the Courtier what will you geue mee &amp; I wyll fynd out twelue 
                     〈◊〉
                   Syr ſayde they, al the money that we haue. Geue mee the money: ſayde the courtier. And he began with the fyrſte, and did geue him a te
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  
                  bētibus ouer the ſhoulders that

he groned, and ſayd there is one: ſo be ſerued all that they groned on the matter when he dyd come to the laſte he payde him a good ſayinge, here is the twelfe man. Gods bleſſing on your hart ſayd nil the companie, that you haue found out our neighbour.
            
            
               ¶ The xi. tale.
               THere was a man of Gotam did ride by ye way &amp; did find a cheeſe in the bye way, &amp; he puld, out his ſword, &amp; poryd &amp; prieked with the poynte of his ſwerd to take by the cheeſe. Theare did come another mā by &amp; did a lyght &amp; toke vp the cheſe &amp; rid his way. The man of gotam did ride back to Nottingham to buye a longer ſwerd to take vp the cheeſe. And whē he had bought his ſwerd he 
                     •
                  turned back.
               
                  
And when he did come to ye place wheare the cheeſe dyd lye he pulled out his ſwerde and prycked at the grounde ſayinge, a murryon take it, if I had had thys ſwerde I had had the cheeſe.
            
            
               ¶ The. xii. tale.
               THere was a man of Gotam &amp; hee dyd not loue his wyfe: &amp; ſhe hauinge a fayre heare, hir huſbande ſaid diuers times yt he would cut it of, &amp; he durſte not doe it when ſhe was waking, but when ſhe was a ſleape. So on a night he toke vp a paire of ſheres and layde them vnder hys beads head, the whyche the wyfe perceyued. And then ſhee dyd call to her one of her maydes and ſayde, go to bead to my huſband, for hee

is mynded to cut of my heare to nyght, let hym cut of thy heare, &amp; I wyll giue thee as good a kyrtle as euer thou dydſt weare. The mayde dyd ſo, &amp; faynded her ſelfe a ſleepe the whiche the man perceyuyng cut of the maydes heare and dyd wrap it about the ſhetes and layde it vnder hys beaddes head, and fell a ſleape. The wyfe made her mayde to aryſe, &amp; tooke the heare and the ſheres, &amp; went into the hall &amp; burnte the heare. This man had a horſe the which hee dyd loue aboue all thynges. The wyfe went into the ſtable, &amp; cut of the horſe tayle. &amp; dyd wrap the ſheres in the horſe tayle, and layd it vnder hir huſbāds heade. In the mornynge ſhee dyd ryſe be time, &amp; did ſit by the fire keyming hir head. At laſt the mā did come

to the fire, &amp; ſeynge his wife keyming hir hed maruelled on it the maide ſeing her maſter ſtandyng in a browne ſtudie ſaide, what a deuil aileth the horſe in the ſtable for he bledeth ſare, the good man ran into the ſtable, &amp; fou
                     •
                  de that h
                     •
                  s horſe taile was cut of hee wēt to his beads head &amp; did finde the ſheres wrapt in hys horſe taile, &amp; did com to his wife ſaying, I cry the merit for I had thought that I had cut of thy heare to night, &amp; I haue cut of my horſe tayle. Ye ſayd ſhe ſelfe do ſelfe haue, manye a man thinketh to do another mā a ſhrewdde turne, and turnethe oft tymes to his owne ſelfe.
            
            
               ¶ The. xiii. tale.
               THere was a man in Gotam that layde a wager wythe hys wyfe that ſhee ſhoulde

not make him cokold. No ſaid ſhe but I can. Spare not ſaid he, do what thou canſte, On a tyme ſhe hyd al the ſypggots &amp; faſſets in ye houſe, and ſhee went into her but terie and ſet a barrell a broche, &amp; cryed to her huſband and ſayde, I preye you brynge me heather a ſpyggot and a faſſet, or elſe al the ale wyll runne out. The good mā ſought vp and downe and coulde fynde none. Come hether ſayde ſhe than, and holde your fynger in the tap hole. She pulled out her finger, and the good man put in hys. She then called to her a Tayler the whyche did dwell at the nexte doore, with whom ſhee made a blinde bargyne. And wythin a whyle ſhee did come to  her huſbande and dyd brynge a ſpiggot &amp; a faſſet with hir saying

pul out your finger out of the tap hole gentle Cockold for you haue loſt your bargayn. I be ſhrew thy hair for thy fauour ſaid the good man. Make no ſuche bargaynes then ſayde ſhe with me.
            
            
               ¶ The xiiii. tale.
               THeare was a man of Gotam that had take a Buſtard, &amp; to the eating of it bee did did. iiii. or. v. gentlemens ſeruaunts. The wyfe had kylled an olde broone gooſe: and ſhe and two of hir goſſeps had eaten vpp the Buſtarde. The olde gooſe was layde to the fyre for the gentlemens ſeruants. Whan that they were come, and the old gooſe ſet before thē, what is this ſayd one of the men? The goodmā ſaid, a good fat buſtard.

A buſtard ſaid they? it is an olde gooſe, and thou arte a knaue to mocke vs. And in a great anger they departed out of the houſe &amp; went home. The fellow was ſory that the gentlemans ſeruanntes weare angry, and dyd take a bag and dyd put in the Buſtardes fethers, and thought to go to them and ſhew them the fethers of the Buſtarde, and ſo to pleaſe them. The wife prayed hir huſband (or he wente) to fetche in a blocke to the fyre: and in the meane ſpace ſhe dyd put out all the Buſtardes fethers, and dyd put in the gooſe fethers. The man takynge hys purse or bag, went to the gentlemens ſeruauntes and ſayde. I pray you be not angrye wyth mee for you ſhall ſee here that I had a buſtard, for here be the fethers▪ &amp;

he opened his bag, and did ſhake out the gooſe fethers, The gentlemens ſeruants ſeing the gooſe fethers ſayde, why knaue couldeſt thou not be cōtented to mocke vs at home at thine owne houſe, but art come to mock vs here, the one tooke a waſter, &amp; dyd geue hym a doſen ſtripes ſayng, take this for a reward, &amp; mock vs no more.
            
            
               ¶ The xv. tale.
               THeare was a yonge man of Gotam the which ſhould go a woing to a faire maid: his mother did warne hym ſayinge, whē than doſt loke vpon her, caſt a ſheepes eye and ſaye, bow daye ſweete pygges aye? The felowe went to ye butchers &amp; bought vii. or. viii. ſheepeseyes, &amp; when thys luſty woer did ſit, at di
                     •
                  t he wold

loke vpon his faire wench &amp; wold caſte in hir face a ſheepes eye ſayinge, how do you my pigges nye. how do I (ſaid the wēch ſwines face, why doeſt yu caſt the ſheepes eye vpon me. O ſweete piggs eye ſayd he, haue at thee another. I defye thee ſwynes face ſayde the wenche. The fellow beinge abaſſhed ſayd, what ſweete pygge be content for and if thou do liue vntill the next yeare, thou wilt be a foule ſow▪ Walk knaue walk ſayd ſhe, for if thou duſt liue til ye next yeare, thou wil be a ſtarke kneue a lubber, and a foole. Here a man may ſee, for a mans good will he ſhall haue euil will &amp; dipleaſure.
            
            
               ¶ The xvi. tale.
               A Mans wife of Gotam was brought a bed of a mā childe

The father dyd vyd the goſſops, the whiche were chyldren of viii. or nyne yeares of age. The eldeſt childes name that ſhould be godfather was named Gylbert. The ſecond chyld was named Hūfry. And the godmothers name was Chriſtabell. The friends of them dyd monyſhe them ſayinge, that dyuers tymes they muſt ſay after the prieſte. Whan all weare come to the church dore, the prieſt ſaid, be you agreed of the name? be you ſaid Gylbert agreed of the name? Be you ſayde Hūfry agreed of the name. Be you ſaid Chryſtabell agreed of the name, the prieſt ſayd whearfore bee you come hether? Gylbert ſayde, wherefore be you come hether. Humfry ſaid wherefore hee you come hether Chriſtabell ſayde whearfore, be you come

hether. The prieſt being amaſed coulde not tell what to ſaye, but whiſteled &amp; ſaide whew, Gylbert whiſteled and ſaid whew, Hūfry whiſtled and ſaid whew, &amp; ſo did Chriſtabell. The prieſt being angry ſaid, go home fooles go home Go home fooles go home ſaid gilbert, go home fooles go hom ſaid Humfry, go home fooles go home ſaid Chriſtabell. The prieſt then prouided for God fathers &amp; Godmothers. Here a man maye ſee that chyldren can do nothing wt out good inſtructions. And they be not wiſe yt wil regard childrēs wordes.
            
            
               ¶ The xvii. tale.
               THere was a man of Gotam the whych ſhuld be maried, &amp; when the day of maryage was

appoynted, &amp; the time came that they ſhoulde be maried together, the prieſt ſayd ſay after me. The man ſaid ſay after me. The prieſt ſaid, ſay not after me ſuch words but ſay after me as I wil tel thee. The fellow ſaid, ſay not after me ſuch wordes, but ſaye after me as I will tell thee. The prieſt ſayde, thou doſt playe the foole and the knaue, to mock with this holy ſacrament of matrymony. The fellow ſaid, thou doſt play the foole and the knaue to mock with this holie ſacrament of matrymonye. The prieſt could not tell what to ſay, but ſaid what ſhal I do with this foole? The felow ſaid, what ſhal I doe with this foole. Farewell ſayde the prieſte, I wyll not marrie thee. Farewell ſayde the fellow, I wyll not marrye thee.

The prieſte departed: how bee it the fellow (by other men) was inſtructed how to doe: &amp; after that hee was maryed. And I hard ſay ſuch a foliſh pranke was played at Kingſton of late dayes.
            
            
               The xviii. tale.
               Theare was a Scottiſh man the whiche dyd dwell at gotam, and hee had taken an houſe a lytle from London, and of it he would make an Inne, and to his Signe hee woulde haue a Bores head. And he wente to London to haue a Bores head made. He dyd come to a Caruer (or a Joyner) ſaying in his mother-tonge, I ſaye ſpek, kens thou make me a Bare heade?; ye ſaid the Caruer.

Than ſayd the ſkotyſhman, mek me a bare head anenſt yowle, an thowſe bus haue xx pence for thy hyre. I wyll doe it ſayde the Caruer. On S. Andrewes daye before Chryſtmas (the which is named yowle in Scotland, &amp; in England in the north.) the ſkottiſh mā did com to Londē for his Bores heade to ſet at a dore for a ſigne. I ſay ſpeke ſaid the ſkotiſh man, haſte thou made me a Bare head? Yea ſaid the Caruer. Then thowſe a gewd fellow. The Caruer went and did bryng a mans head of wod that was bare and ſayd, ſyr here is youre bare head. I ſay ſayde the ſkotyſhman, the mokyl deuill, is this a bare head? Ye ſaid the caruer. I ſay ſayd the Shotiſhman, I will haue a bare head, ſyk an head as doth follow

a Sew that hath Gryces. Syr ſaid the caruer, I cā not tel what is a Sew, nor what is a Gryce. whet herſō, kenſt thou not a ſew that wil greet &amp; grone, &amp; her gryces wil run after her &amp; cry a weke a weke. O ſaid the Caruer, it is a pigge. Yea ſaid the ſkotiſh mā, let me haue his fathers head made in timber, &amp; mek me a bird &amp; ſet it on his ſkalps, and cauſe her to ſing whip whir, whip whir. The caruer ſayde, I can not cauſe her to ſinge whip whir. Whe horſon ſayde the ſkotiſh man gar her as ſhe woulde ſinge whip whir.
               Here a man maye ſee that euerye man doth delight in his owne ſē
                  ces, or doth reioice in his fantaſie
            
            
               ¶ The xix. tale.
               IN old time whē as theſe afore ſaid Jeſtes was (as mē of that

cuntrey reporteth) that ſuch fantaſticall matters weare done at gotam (the which I can not tell halfe.) The wyues weare gathered together in an ale houſe and the one ſayde to the other yt they weare all profitable to their huſbandes. Whyche waye good goſſips ſayd the Ale wife. The fyrſte ſayd, I ſhall tell you all good goſſips: I can neither bake nor brew nor I can doe no worke, whearefore I do make euery day holiday &amp; I go to the ale houſe, bicauſe at all times I cānot go to ye church, &amp; in the ale houſe I praye to God to ſpeede well my huſband. And I do think my praier ſhal do him much more good then my labour if I could worke. Then ſayde the ſecond, I am profitable to my huſbād in ſauing of cādels in winter

for I do cauſe my huſband and al my houſe ſolkes to go to bead by daylighte, &amp; to rile by daylight. The thyrd wife ſayd, &amp; I am profytable to my huſbande in ſpending of bread, for I will eate but litle, for to the drinckyng of a galon or two of good ale, I care for no meate. The fourth wife ſaide, I am loth to ſpend meat &amp; drinke at home in my owne houſe, wher fore I do go to the wine tauerne at Nottingham, &amp; do take wine, and ſuch things as god ſhal ſend me theare. The fifte wyfe ſayd a man ſhall euer haue more companye in another mans houſe then his owne (&amp; moſt cōmonlye in an Ale houſe is the beſt cheare in a towne.) And for ſparing of meate &amp; drynke and other neceſſaryes, I do go to the ale houſe. The ſixt

wife ſaid, my huſband hath woll, and flax and tow: and to ſpare it, I go to other mens houſes to do other mens worke. The ſeuenth wife ſaid, I do ſpare my huſbāds wood &amp; cole, and do ſit talking al the day by other mens fires. The eight ſaid, beefe, mutton, &amp; porcke is dere, wherfore I doe ſpare it, &amp; do take pigge, gooſe, hen, chicken conye and capon, the which be of lower pryce. The ninth ſaid, &amp; I do ſpare my huſbands ſope &amp; lye, for when hee ſhoulde be waſſhed once in a weeke, I doe waſh once in a quarter of a yeer. Then ſayd the ale wife, and I doe keepe my huſbandes ale (that I do brew,) from ſowryng. For wheare as I was wont to drynke vp all, nowe I do haue neuer a drop.
            
            
               
               The. xx. tale.
               ON Aſh wedneſday the prieſt of gotam wold make a colacion to his pariſhoners and ſaid, freyndes the tyme is come that you muſt vſe praier and faſting, &amp; almes dedes, and this weke cum you to ſhryfte, and I wyll tel you more of my mynd, for as for prayers, I thinke theare bit not two perſons in the pariſh can ſay halfe their Pater noſter. As for faſting you faſt ſtyll: for you haue not a good meales meat through the whole yeare. As for almes dedes, what ſhuld you do to giue any thyng, that hath nothing to take to. But when that you doe come to ſhrift, I will tel you more of my mynd. After maſſe, ye good man that did keepe the ale houſe, did come to ſhrift, &amp; aboue al thinges bee confeſſed hymſelfe to bee

drunck diuers times in the yeere, ſpecially in Lent. The prieſt ſayd in Lent thou ſhouldeſt moſte refraine from drūkenes, &amp; abſtaine frō drinke. Not ſo ſaid the fellow, for it is an old prouerbe, that fiſhe muſt ſwim, Ye ſayd the prieſte, it muſt ſwim in water. I crye God mercy  ſayd the fellow. I thought it ſhuld haue ſwom in good ale.
            
            
               ¶ The xxi tale.
               SO one after another the men of Gotam did come to ſhrift, &amp; whan they were ſhryuē the prieſt ſaid I cannot tell what penaūce to geue you. If I ſhould enioyne you to prayer, there is non of you that can ſay your Pater noſter, &amp; you be now to old to learne. And i
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  nioye you to faſt, it weare but folyſhnes, for you doe not eate a good meales meate in a yeare.

Wherefore I do inioyne the to labour wel the weeke, yt thou maiſt farewel to diner on the ſondaies: and I wil come to dnner and ſee that it be ſo, and take part. Another man hee dyd enioyne to fare well the monday. And another the tueſday. And ſo one after another, that one or other ſhoulde fare well once a weeke, that hee myght haue parte of the meate. And as for almes deedes ye prieſt ſayd, you be but beggers all, excepte it be one or two, therfore beſtowe the almes on youre owne ſelues.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            Imprinted at London in Fletſtret, beneath thf Conduit, at the ſigne of S. John Euangeliſt, by Thomas Colwe
                  •
               .
         
      
   

