
   
      
         
            Articles to be enquired of, in the ordinarie visitation of the most reuerend father in God, George by Gods providence, Lord Arch-bishop of Canterbury ... holden in the yeere of our Lord God, 1632, and in the two and twenty yeere of His Graces translation.
            Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1611-1633 : Abbot)
         
         
            
               1632
            
         
         Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00190
            STC 10227.3
            ESTC S422
            22372238
            ocm 22372238
            25483
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00190)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25483)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1752:58)
         
         
            
               
                  Articles to be enquired of, in the ordinarie visitation of the most reuerend father in God, George by Gods providence, Lord Arch-bishop of Canterbury ... holden in the yeere of our Lord God, 1632, and in the two and twenty yeere of His Graces translation.
                  Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1611-1633 : Abbot)
                  Abbot, George, 1562-1633.
               
               [16] p.   
               
                  For Robert Milbourne,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1632.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-B⁴.
                  Formerly STC 10191.
                  Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.
               Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ARTICLES TO BE ENQVIRED OF, IN THE ORDINARIE Visitation of the most Reuerend Father in God, GEORGE by Gods Providence, Lord Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, Primate of all England, and Metropolitan: in, and for the Cities and Diocesse of COVENTRY and LICHFIELD, the See there being voyd.
            Holden in the yeere of our Lord God, 1632. and in the two and twenty yeere of his Graces Translation.
            Imprinted at London for Robert Milbourne 1632.
         
         
            
            The Tenor of the Oath, to bee ministred to the Church-wardens and Side-men.
            YOu shall sweare, That you and every of you, shall duely consider, and diligently enquire of all and every of these Articles given you in charge; and that all affection, favour, hatred, hope, of reward and gaine, or feare of displeasure, or malice set aside, you shall present all and euery such person, of, or within your Parish, as hath committed any offence, or made any default mentioned in these, or any of these Articles▪ or which are vehemently suspected or defamed of any such offence or default: wherein you shall deale vprightly and full; neither presenting, nor sparing to present any, contrary to trueth: hauing in this action God before your eyes, with an earnest zeale to maintaine trueth, and to suppresse vice. So helpe you God, and the holy Contents of this booke.
         
      
      
         
            
            I. Concerning the Ministers.
            
               
                  INprimis, Whether doeth your Minister distinctly and reuerendly say diuine Seruice vpon Sundayes and Holy-dayes, and other dayes appoynted to be obserued by the Booke of Common Prayer: Wednesdayes and Frydayes, and the Eues of euery Sunday and Holyday, at fit and vsuall times? And doth your Minister duly obserue the Orders, Rites, and Ceremonies prescribed in the said Book of Common Prayer, as well in reading pulibke Prayers and the Letany, as also in administring the Sacraments, solemnization of Matrimony, Uisiting the sick, Burying the dead, Churching of women, and all other like Rites and offices of the Church, in such maner and forme, as in the Book of Common prayer is enioyned? And doth he reade the booke of the last Canons once yéerely, and weare a Surplice according to the sayd Canons?
            2 Item whether doth your Minister bid Holydayes &amp; Fasting dayes, as by the Booke of Common Prayer is appointed? And doth hee giue warning beforehand to the parishoners, for the receiuing of the holy Cō
               munion as the 22. canon requireth? And whether doth he administer the holy Cōmunion so often, &amp; at such times, as that euery parishioner may receiue the same at the least thrice in euery yere: wherof once at Easter as by the Booke of Common Prayer is appointed? And doeth your Minister receiue the same himselfe on euery day that hee administreth it to others, and vse the words of Institution according to the Booke, at euery time that the Bread and Wine is renewed, accordingly as by the Prouiso of the 21 Canon is directed? And doeth háe deliuer the Bread and Wine to euery Cōmunicant seuerally? Whether hath he admitted to the holy Communion any offender or Schismaticke, contrary to the 26. and 27. constitutions, or receiued any to the Communion being not of his owne Cure or put any from the Communion, not being publikely infamous for some notorious crime? Doeth he vse the signe of the Crosse in Baptisme, or Baptize in any Bason, or other Uessell and not in the vsuall Font: or admit any Father to be Godfather to his own child, or such who haue not receiued the holy Cōmunion, or Baptize any children that were not borne in the parish, or wilfully refuse to Baptize

any Infant in his Parish being in danger, hauing bene enformed of the weakenesse of the sayd child: and whether hath the child dyed through his default without Baptisme?
            3 Item, whether hath your Minister married any without a Ring or without Banes published thrée seueral Sundayes or Holydayes in time of diuine Seruice, in the seueral Churches or Chappels of their seuerall abode, according to the book of Common Prayer, or in times prohibited albeit the Banes were thrice published, without a License or dispensation from the Archbishop, the Bishop of the Diocesse, or his Chancellor, first obtained in that behalfe? or not betwixt the houres of eight and twelue in the forenoone, or married in any priuate house: or if the parties be vnder the age of 21. yeres, before their parents or gouernors haue signified their consent vnto him?
            4 Item, whether doth he refuse to bury any, which ought to be interred in Christian buriall, or deferre the same longer then he should, or bury any in Christian burial, which by the Constitutions of the Church of England ought not to be so interred?
            5 Item, whether the body of any excommunicate person dying within your parish hath bin buried by any of your parishioners disorderly (your Minister iustly refusing to bury it) within your Church or Churchyard, or haue the body or bodies of any such excommunicate person or persons bin carried out of your Parish to be buried in another Parish, without consent of your Minister, or Ordinary first had and obtained; and what are their seuerall names and sirnames?
            6 Item, whether is your Minister a Preacher allowed? If so, then by whom? If not, whether doth he procure some who are lawfully licensed, to preach amongst you monethly at the least?
            7 Item, whether doth your Minister (being licensed) preach vsually according to the Canons, either in his owne Cure, or in some other Church or Chappell, neere adioyning, where no Preacher is and how often hath he bin negligent in that behalfe? and doth he preach standing and with his hat off? Or whether doth he or his Curate vpon euery Sunday, when there is no Sermon, reade an Homily, or some part thereof, according as he ought to doe: or in case hee bee not licensed to Preach doth he take vpon him to preach or expound the Scriptures in his owne Cure, or elsewhere? If so then you are to present the same, the time and place, when, and where he did it.
            8 Item, whether doth your Minister in his Sermons, Lectures and other exercises, vse to pray for the Kings Maiesty, King Charles and for our gracious Quéene Mary, and all the Royal Progeny, with addition of

such Stile and Titles as are due to his Highnes, and exhort the people to obedience to his Maiestie, and all Magistrates in authority vnder him: not omitting particular mencion of the Bishop of the Diocesse, according to his Maiesties late direction in that behalfe?
            9 Item, whether is your Minister continually resident vpon his Benifice, and how long time hath he bin absent, &amp; in case he be licensed to be absent whether doth he cause his Cure to be sufficiently supplyed, according to the Canons: or in case hee hath another Benefice, whether doth he supply his absence by a Curate sufficiently licensed to preach in that Cure, where he himselfe is not resident? Or otherwise, in case the smallnesse of the liuing cannot finde a preaching Minister, doeth hee preach at both his Benefices vsually?
            10 Item, whether doeth your Minister or Curate serue any more Cures then one: If so, then what other Cure doth he serue, and how farre are they distant?
            11 Item, whether doth your Minister euery Sunday and Holyday, before Euening Prayer, for halfe an houre, or more, examine and instruct the Youth and ignorant persons of his Parish, in the Ten Commandements, Articles of the Beliefe and in the Lords prayer and the Sacraments according as it is prescribed in the Catechisme, and set foorth in the Book of Common Prayer; and also strictly enioyned by our late Soueraigne King Iames of blessed memory, in his directions to the Bishops of each Diocesse?
            12 Item, whether doth your Minister in the Rogation dayes goe in perambulation of the circuit of the parish saying and vsing the prayers and thanksgiuing to God, appointed by law, according to his duty, thanking God for his blessings, if there be plenty on the earth: Or otherwise▪ to pray for his grace and fauour, if there be a feare of scarcity?
            13 Item, whether hath your Minister admitted any woman, begotten with child in adultery or fornication, to be churched without license of the Ordinary?
            14 Item, whether hath your Minister, or any other Preacher, Baptized children, churched any woman or ministred the holy Communion in any priuate house, otherwise then by Law is allowed?
            15 Item, whether doth your Minister, being a Preacher, endeauour &amp; labor diligently to reclaime the Popish Recusants in his parish from their errors (if there be any such abiding in your Parish) Or whether is your Parson Uicar, or Curate, ouerconuersant with or a fauourer of Recusants, whereby he is suspected not to be sincere in Religion?
            16 Item, whether hath your Minister taken vpon him, to appoint any

Publike or priuate Fasts, Prophecies or exercises, not approued by Law, or publike authority, or hath vsed to méete in any priuate house or place, with any person or persons, there to consult how to impeach or depraue the book of Common prayer, or the Doctrine or Discipline of the Church of England? If so, then you shall present them all.
            67 Item, whether hath your Minister stayed the publication of any excommunications, or suspensions? or doth he euery halfe yere denounce in his parish Church all such of his parish, as are excommunicated, &amp; perseuere therin without séeking to be absolued, or doth he wittingly &amp; willingly keep company with such as are excommunicate: And hath he admitted into your Church any person excommunicate, without a Certificate of his absolution from the Ordinary, or other competent Iudge?
            18 Item, whether doth your Minister carefully looke to the reliefe of the poore, and from time to time call vpon his Parishioners to giue somewhat as they can spare, to godly and charitable vses, especially when they make their Testaments?
            19 Item, whether doth your Minister, or any hauing taken the holy Orders, being now silenced or suspended, or any other person of your knowledge, or as you haue heard, hold any conuenticles, or preach in any place, or vse any other forme of Diuine Seruice then is appointed in the Booke of Common Prayer? If so, then you are to present their names, and with whom.
            20 Item, whether is your Curate licensed to serue, by the Bishop of this Diocesse or by any other, and by whom?
            21 Item, whether doth your Minister vse such decencie and comelinesse in his apparell, as by the 47. Canon is enioyned: and is he of sober behauiour and one that doth not vse such bodily labor, as is not séemely for his function and calling?
            22 Item, whether is your Minister noted or defamed to haue obtained his Benefice or his Orders by Simony, or any other way defamed, to be a Symoniacall person, or any way noted to be a Schismaticke, or Schismatically affected, or reputed to be an incontinent person, or to table or lodge any such in his house: or is he a frequenter of Tauernes, Innes, Alehouses, or any place suspected for ill rule: or is he a common Drunkard a common Gamester or a player at Dice, a Swearer, or one that applieth not his Studie, or is otherwise offensiue and scandalous to his function or Ministery?
            23 Item, whether are there any Lectures, or exercises vsed within your parish Church? If so, then whether do the sayd Lecturer or Lecturers, refuse to conforme themselues to the Lawes and Ordinances of the

Church of England, and especially to the late instructions for Lectures published by his Sacred Maiesty King Charles, and directed to the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury his Grace, and accordingly by his Grace, sent to euery Diocesse of his Graces Prouince. Anno Dom. 1629. And so by the Lord Bishop of this Diocesse, commanded to bee published thorow this Diocesse, by his Lordships Arch-deacous, at their seuerall visitations after Easter, Anno Dom. 1630. And doth your Lecturer or Lecturers, and euery of them obserue that Article, and instruction of his Maiestie, wherein it is prouided precisely, that euery Lecturer shall before his Lecture, or Sermon, reade Diuine Seruice in his Surplice, and Hood according to his Degrée: If you know of any default or neglect hereof, in not obseruing this instruction of his Maiesties, or other the Lawes Ecclesiasticall of this Kingdome, you are to present it, otherwise you are likely to answere for this your contempt.
            24 Item, whether do any Knight, or Gentlemen within your Parish maintaine or keepe any Chaplaine, contrary to the Lawes of the Land, not being thereunto Licensed by the Bishop of this Diocesse?
            25 Item, whether doth your Preacher or Lecturer reade Diuine Seruice, and Minister the Sacraments twice a yeere at least in his owne person, according to the Canons?
         
         
            II. Concerning the Church, the Ornaments thereof, and the Churches possessions.
            26 WHether haue you in your seuerall Churches and Chappels, the whole Bible of the largest volume, and the book of Common Prayer, as also the book of Homilies set forth by his Maiesties authority, all fairely and substantially bound: a Font of stone, set vp in the ancient vsuall place: a conuenient &amp; decent Communion Table, with a Carpet of silke▪ or some other decent Stuffe, continually layd vpon the Table at the time of Diuine Seruice, and a faire linnen cloth vpon the same, at the time of the receiuing of the holy Communion? And whether is the same Table placed in such conuenient sort within the Chancel or Church, as that the Minister may be best heard in his prayer &amp; administration, and that the greatest number may communicate? And whether is it so vsed out of time of diuine Seruice, as is not agréeable to the holy vse of it: and as by sitting on it throwing hats on it writing on it or is it abused to other prophane vses? And are the Ten Commandements set vpon the East end of your Church or Chappell, where the people may best see and reade them and other Sentences of holy Scripture, written on the walles likewise for that purpose?
            
               27 Item, whether haue you in your said Church or Chappell, a conuenient seate for your Minister to read Seruice in, together with a comely Pulpit, set vpon a conuenient place, with a decent cloth or Cushion for the same, a comely large Surplice, a faire Communion Cup, with a couer, of Siluer, &amp; a Flagon of Siluer Tinne, or Peuter, to put the Wine in wherby it may be set vpon the Communion Table, at the time of the blessing thereof, with all other things and Ornaments necessary for the celebration of diuine Seruice &amp; administration of the Sacraments? And whether haue you a strong chest for almes of the Poore with thrée lockes and keyes, and another Chest for the keeping the Bookes, and Ornaments of the Church▪ and the Register Booke? And whether haue you a Register Booke in Parchment, for Christenings, Weddings, and Burialls, and whether the same be kept in all points, according to the Canons in that behalfe prouided? And whether haue you in your said Church or Chancell a Table set, of the degrées, wherein by Law men are prohibited to marry?
            28 Item, whether are your Church and Chappells, with the Chancels thereof and your Parsonage, or Uicarage house, your Parish almes-house and Church-house, in good reparations, and are they imployed to godly, &amp; their right holy vses? Is your Church, Chancell &amp; Chappell, decently and comely kept, as well within as without and the seats well maintained, according to the 85 Canon in that behalfe prouided? Whether your Church-yard be well fenced &amp; kept without abuse: and if not, in whose default the same is, and what the defect or fault is? And whether any person haue encroched vpon the ground of the Churchyard, or whether any person or persons haue vsed any thing or place consecrated to holy vse prophanely or wickedly?
            29 Item, whether haue you the Terrier of all the Gleabe Lands, Meddowes Gardens, Orchards, Houses, Stockes, Implements, Tenements and portions of Tithes (whether within your Parish or without) belonging vnto your Parsonage or Uicarage, taken by the view of honest men in your sayd Parish? And whether the sayd Terrier bée layd vp in the Bishops Registry, and in whose hands any of them are now? And if you haue no Terrier already made in Parchment, you the Church-wardens and Side-men, together with your Parson or Uicar, or in his absence, with your Minister, are to make diligent enquirie and presentment of the premisses, and make, subscribe, and signe the sayd Terrier as aforesayd.
         
         
            
            III. Schoole-Masters.
            30 WHether doeth any in your Parish take vpon him to teach Schoole, without license of the Ordinary, and is he conformable to the Religion now established? And doth he bring his Schollers to the Church to heare Diuine Seruice and Sermons? And doeth he instruct his Schollers in the grounds of Religion now established in this Church of England? and is hee carefull and diligent to benefit his Schollers in learning?
         
         
            IIII. Parish-Clerkes, and Sextons.
            31 WHether haue you a fit Parish-Clerke, aged twenty yéeres at least, of honest conuersation, able to reade and write? Whether are his &amp; the Sextons wages payed without fraud, according to the ancient custome of your parish: if not, then by whom are they so defrauded or denied? By whom are they chosen? and whether the said Clerke be approued by the Ordinary: and hath he taken an Oath as in such cases is fit and required: and is he diligent in his Office, &amp; seruiceable to the Minister, &amp; doth he take vpon him to meddle with any thing aboue his Office; as Churching of women, burying the dead, and such like?
            32 Item, whether doeth your Clerke or Sexton kéepe the Church cleane, the doores locked? Is any thing lost or spoyled in the Church through his default? doeth hee suffer any vnreasonable ringing, or any propane exercise in your Church: or doth he (when any is passing out of this life) neglect to tole a Bell, hauing notice thereof?
         
         
            V. Physicians, Surgeons, and Mid-vviues.
            34 HOw many Physicians, Chirurgions, or Mid-wiues haue you in your Parish? How long haue they vsed their seuerall Sciences or Offices, and by what authority? And how haue they demeaned themselues therein, and of what skill are they accounted to bee in their profession?
         
         
            VI. Touching the Church-wardens and Sidemen.
            34 WHether you the Churchwardens, Quest-men, or Sidemen from time to time do &amp; haue done their diligences, in not suffering any idle person to abide either in the Church-yard, or Church-porch in Seruice or Sermon time, but causing them either to come into the Church to heare diuine Seruice, or to depart, &amp; not disturbe such as hée hearers there? And whether haue they, and do you diligently sée the

Parishioners duly resort to the Church euery Sunday and Holy, day, and there to remaine during diuine Seruice &amp; Sermon? And whether you or your predecessors Church-wardens there, suffer any Playes, Feasts, Drinkings, or any other prophane vsages, to bee kept in your Church, Chappel or Church yards, or haue suffered to your and their vttermost power and endeauour, any person or persons, to be tippling or drinking in any Inne or Uictualling house in your Parish, during the time of diuine Seruice or Sermon, on Sundayes or Holydayes?
            35 Item, whether, and how often haue you admitted any to preach within your Church or Chappell which was not sufficiently Licensed? And whether you together with your Minister, haue not taken diligent héed and care, that euery of your Parishioners being of sixeteene yeeres of age or vpwards, haue receiued thrice euery yéere, as aforesaid: and also that no stranger haue vsually come to your Church, from their owne Parish Church?
            36 Item, whether haue there bin prouided against euery Communion, a sufficient quantitie of fine white bread, and of good and wholesome wine for the communicants that shall receiue? And whether that wine be brought in a cleane and swéete standing pot of pewter, or of other purer mettall?
            37 Item, whether were you chosen by the consent of the Minister and the parishioners? And haue the late Church-wardens giuen vp a iust account for their time, and deliuered to their Successors the money, and other things belonging to the Church, which was in their hands? And are the Almes of the Church faithfully distributed to the vse of the poore?
         
         
            VII. Concerning the Parishoners.
            38 Whether is there any of your Parishioners, beeing sixteene yeeres of age, or vpwards, or others lodging or commonly resorting to any house within your parish, that do wilfully absent them selues from your Parish-church vpon Sundayes or Holydayes, at Morning and Euening Prayers: or who come late to Church, &amp; depart from Church before Seruice be done vpon the said daies? Or who do not reuerently behaue themselues during the time of Diuine Seruice deuoutly knéeling when the generall confession of sins, the Letany, the ten Commandements, and all prayers and Collects are read &amp; vsing all due and lowly reuerence, whē the blessed Name of the Lord Iesus Christ is mentioned, &amp; standing vp when the Articles of the Beliefe are read, or who do couer their heads in the Church during the time of Diuine Seruice, vnlesse it be in case of necessity, in which case they may weare a Night

cap or Coyse? Or who doe giue themselues to babling▪ talking, or walking, and are not attentiue to the word preached, or read: or reading, or praying, during the time aforesaid? Whether any of your Parish being of sixteene yeares of age and vpwards, do not receiue the holy Communion in your Church thrice euery yéere: wherof once at Easter and whether they doe not deuoutly kneele at the receiuing thereof?
            39 Item, whether any of your Parishioners, being admonished, therof, doe not send their children, seruants, and apprentises to the Minister, to be catechised vpon such Sundayes and Holidayes as are appointed? or whether any of them do refuse to come: or if they come, refuse to learne the Catechisme set foorth in the booke of Common Prayer?
            40 Item how many of the sayd Catechismes haue bin dispersed in your Parish or Chappell, according to the number of such children and seruants as can reade and are to learne the same, according to the late Iniunction of your Ordinary, and who they bee that haue refused to obey that order so enioyned? and what are their seuerall names?
            41 Item, whether any of your Parish doe entertaine within their house any soiournier, common guests, or other persons, who refuse to frequent diuine Seruice, or receiue the holy Communion, as aforesayd? Present their names, their qualities or conditions.
            42 Item, what recusāt Papists are there in your parish? or haue dwelt or made vsuall abode there within the space of two or thrée yéeres last past, and whether they still dwell or remaine there, or where doe they dwell, or make their abode? Present their names, qualities, or conditions. And whether keepe they any Schoole-master in their house, which commeth not to Church to heare Diuine Seruice and receiue the Communion? What is his name, and how long hath he taught there, or else where?
            43 Item, whether doe any of the sayd Popish Recusants labor to seduce and withdraw others from the Religion now established? or instruct their Families or children in Popish Religion? or refuse to entertaine any, especially in place of greatest seruice or trust, but such as concurre with them in their Papistry?
            44 Item, whether the tuition of the children of any of your Parishioners, dying within your Parish, be committed to any Popish Recusants conuict, contrary to the Stat. 3 I
                     ••
                  . Cap. 5. and if so, to present and certifie the names both of such children, and of the Tutors, or Guardians, to whose tuition and education they are committed.
            45 Item, how long haue the sayd Popish Recusants abstained from Diuine Seruice or from the Communion as aforesayd?
            46 Item, whether is there any in your parish that retaine vndefaced,

or sell, vtter or disperse any Popish Bookes or Writings or other Bookes, Libels, or writings of any Seetaries, touching the Religion, State, or Gouernment Ecclesiasticall of this Kingdome of England, or kéepe any Ornaments of superstition vncancelled or vndefaced?
            48 Item, whether haue you any in your parish, which hertofore being Popish Recusants, or Sectaries, haue since reformed themselues, and come to Church to heare Diuine Seruice, and receiue the Sacraments? If yea▪ then who they are: &amp; how long since haue they so reformed themselues? And whether they still remaine and abide in that conformitie?
            49 Item, whether is there any in your parish, that refuse to haue their children baptized, or themselues to receiue the Cōmunion at the hands of your Minister, taking exception against him, and what causes or exceptious doe they alledge? Or haue any married wiues refused to come to Church according to the book of Common prayer to giue God thanks after their Child-birth, for their safe deliuerance? And whether doe any of, or in your Parish, refuse to haue their children Baptized in your parish Church, according to the forme prescribed in the booke of cōmon prayer?
            50 Item, whether any in your parish hauing a Preacher to your Parson Uicar, or Curate doe absent themselues from his Sermons, and resort to other places to heare other Preachers: or whether any of your parish doe Communicate or Baptize their children in any other parish?
            51 Item, what persons within your parish, for any offence, contumacy or crime of Ecclesiasticall conusance, doe stand Excommunicate? Present their names, and for what cause they are Excommunicated, and how long they haue so stood, and what person and persons doe wittingly and vsually kéepe them company.
            52 Item, whether doe any, not being in Orders, execute any Priestly or Ministeriall office in your Church, Chappell or Churchyard, and what be their names?
            53 Item, whether is there any in your parish, that hauing hertofore taken vpon him the Order of Priesthood, or Deacon, hath since relinquished the same and liues a Lay-man neglecting his vocation?
            54 Item, whether hath any person or persens in your parish quarrelled or stricken or vsed any violence to your Minister, or hath strucken or quarreld with any other persō within your Church or Churchyard, or demeaned himselfe disorderly in the Church, by filthy or prophane talke, or any other lewd or immodest behauior? Or haue disturbed the Minister in time of diuine Seruice or Sermon, or haue libelled or spoken slanderous words against your Minister to the scandall of his vocation▪ or defamed any of his neighbours touching any crime of Ecclesiasticall conusance?
            
               55 Item, whether haue any of, or in your parish, without consent of the Ordinary, or other lawfull authoritie, caused any to doe penance, or to be censured or punished for any matter of Ecclesiastical conusance, by any Uestry-meetings, or otherwise by their own authority? or haue takē any money or cōmutatiō for the same present their names that haue don it? and who haue béen so punished: in what manner▪ and vpon what cause.
            56. Item whether any person in your parish do exercise any trade or labour▪ buy or sell, or keepe open shops or ware-houses vpon any Sunday or Holiday by thēselues, their seruants or apprentices, or haue otherwise profaned the said daies, contrary to the orders of the Church of Englād? And whether there be any Inne keepers, Ale-house-kéepers, Uictualers, or other persons that permit any persons in their houses to eate, drinke, or play during the time of Diuine Seruice, or Sermon, or reading the Homilies in the forenoone or after-noone, vpon these dayes?
            57 Item, whether hath the fift day of Nouember bin kept holy, and thanksgiuing made to God▪ for his Maiesties &amp; this States happy deliuerance, according to the Ordinance in that behalfe? And whether haue you in your Parish Church or Chappell the bookes in this behalfe set foorth and commanded by publike authority.
            58 Item, whether doth any of your parish hold or frequent any conuē
               ticles or priuate congregations, or make or maintain any constitutions, agreed vpon in any such assemblies? Or are there any that do write, or publikely or priuately speake against the booke of Common prayer, or any thing therein contained, or against any of the Articles of Religion, agréed vpon in Anno 1562. or against the Kings Supremacy in causes Ecclesiasticall, or against the Oath of Supremacy, or of Allegiance, as pretending the same to be vnlawful, &amp; not warrantable by the Word of God? Or against any of the Rites or Ceremonies of the Church of England now established? Or against the gouernment of the Church of England, vnder the Kings most excellent Maiestie, by Archbishops Bishops, Deanes Archdeacons and other Officers of the same: affirming, that the same is repugnant to the Word of God, &amp; that the sayd Ecclesiastical Officers are not lawfully ordained? Or whether be there any Authors, maintainers, or fauourers of Heresie or Schisme, or that be suspected to be Anabaptists, Libertines Brownists of the Familie of Loue, or of any other Heresie or Schisme: present their names.
            59 Item whether haue any in your Parish married within the degrées by law prohibited; or any couple in your Parish being lawfully married, liue apart one from the other, without due separation of the Law: or any that haue bin diuorced, which keepe company with

any other at Bed or at Bord, and when and where they married?
            58 Item, whether doe any persons administer the goods of the dead without lawfull authoritie, or suppresse the last will of the dead? Or are there in your Parish any wils not yet proued, or goods of the dead dying intestate left vnadministred? By authority in that behalfe you shall not faile to present the Executors, and all others faulty therein: and also how many persons being possessed of any goods and chattels, haue dyed within your Parish since the yéere 1617.
            59 Item, whether doth any with-hold the stocke of the Church, or any goods or other things, giuen to good and charitable vses?
            60 Item, whether are your Hospitalls and Almes-houses and other such houses and Corporations, founded to good and charitable vses: and the lands, possessions, and goods of the same, ordered and disposed of as they should bee? And doe the Masters, Gouernours, Fellowes, and others of the said Houses and Corporations, behaue and demeane themselues, according to the godly Ordinances, and Statutes of their seuerall Foundations?
            61 Item, whether haue you any in your parish to your knowledge, or by common fame &amp; report, which haue committed Adultery, Fornication, or Incest, or any which haue impudētly bragged or boasted that he or she haue liued incontinently with any person or persons whatsoeuer: or any that hath attempted the chastity of any woman, or solicited any woman to haue the carnall knowledge of her body, or which are commonly reputed to bee common Drunkards, Blasphemers of Gods holy Name, common Swearers, common Slanderers of their Neighbours, &amp; sowers of discord, filthy and laciuious talkers, Usurers, Symonaicall persons, Bawds, or harbourers of women with child which be vnmarried, or conueying or suffering them to goe away before they haue made satisfaction to the congregation, or any that hauing heretofore bene presented, or suspected of any the aforesaid crimes, haue for that cause departed your parish, and are now returned again? Or any which haue vsed any inchantments, sorceries, incantations or witchcrafts, which are not made fellony by the statutes of this Realme, or any which haue cōmitted any periury in any Ecclesiasticall Court, in an Ecclesiasticall cause, or which haue committed any forgery, punishable by the Ecclesiasticall lawes, and the procurers and abettors of the sayd offences? You shall truely present the names of all and singular the sayd offendors, and with whom they haue committed the said offences, in case they haue not bin publikely punished to your knowledge for the same crimes.
            62 Item, whether was the publike prayers and fast lately enioyned by

authority for the pacifying of Gods wrath, and for asswaging the late fearefull Plague, béen duely and solemnely performed both by your Minister and Parishioners on the dayes and times appointed, as also, The day of thankesgiuing for Gods mercy in asswaging that fearefull sicknesse, being Religiously obserued, according to those publike formes set foorth by authority, and whether haue you the sayd Bookes so published, as by the same authority you were commanded.
         
         
            VIII. Concerning Ecclesiasticall Magistrates and Officers.
            63 WHether doe you know or haue heard of any payment, composition, or agreement, to, or with any Ecclesiasticall Magistrate, Iudge, or Officer, for winking at, or sparing to punish any person for any offence of Ecclesiastical conusance, or for suppressing, or concealing of any Recusant, or any other offendour in the cases afore-sayd? What sum of money, or other consideration hath bin receiued or promised, by, or to any of them in that respect, by whom and with whom?
            64 Item, whether hath any person within your parish, payd, or promised any sum of mony or other reward, for communication of penance for any crime of Ecclesiastical conusance? If so, then with whom, when, and for what and how hath the same bene imployed?
            65 Item whether are your Ecclesiasticall Iudges and their Substitutes Masters of Arts or Bachelours of the Law at the least, learned and practised in the Ciuill and Ecclesiasticall Lawes: Men of good life and fame, zealously affected in Religion, and iust vpright in executing their offices? Haue they heard any matter of Office priuately in their chambers, without their sworne Registers, or their Deputies presence?
            66 Item, whether doe you know, or haue you heard, that any Ecclesiasticall Iudge, Offcer, or Minister hath receiued or taken any extraordinary fees, or other rewards or promises, by any wayes or meanes directly, or indirectly, of any person or persons whatsoeuer, either for the granting of the administration of the goods and chattells of those that haue died intestate, to one before another, or for allotting of larger portions of the goods and chattells of those that haue dyed intestate to one more then to another: or for allowing large and vnreasonable accounts, made by Executors or administrators: or for giuing them Quietus est, or discharges, without Inuentory or account, to defraud Creditors, &amp; Legataries, or those who are to haue portions? And what summes of money do you know, or haue you heard that any Ecclesiastical Iudge or Officer hath taken out of the state of any dying intestate, vpon pretence

                  〈1… pages missing〉
               
            
         
      
   

