
   
      
         
            To my faythfull bretheren now affycted ...
         
         
            
               1566
            
         
         Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00275
            STC 10389
            ESTC S111870
            99847131
            99847131
            12149
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00275)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12149)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:31)
         
         
            
               
                  To my faythfull bretheren now affycted ...
                  Whittingham, William, d. 1579, attrib. name.
               
               [8] p.   
               
                  E. van der Erve,
                  [Emden :
                  1566]
               
               
                  Sometimes attributed to William Whittingham.
                  Caption title (A1 recto).
                  Imprint from STC.
                  The copy catalogued is bound with STC 10390 and STC 10391.
                  Signatures: A⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church vestments --  England --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-03
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-03
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            To my louynge brethren that is troublyd abowt the popiſhe aparrell, two ſhort and comfortable Epiſtels.
by Anthony Gilby.
            
            Be ye conſtant: for the Lorde ſhall fyght for yow, yowrs in Chriſt.
[1566.]
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               ¶ To all my faithful brethren in Chriſt Jeſu and to all other that labour to weade out the wedes of popery, Peace in the Lorde Jeſu be with you, and make you perfite in all good workes to doe his will, working in you that which is pleaſant in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.
            
            DEare Brethren, becauſe we are creatid for gods glory the edification one of another in Chriſt, and are bounde to ſerue thervnto by wealthe or woo, lyfe or death, and cheifly, they to whom God haue geuen the greter gyftes, and whom he hath callyd to higher romes, are moſte bounde to be zelous for gods glory with godly zelouſie to profyt the churche and ſponſe of Chriſte vnder their charge, and that by no ſubteltye as the Apoſtel warnithe, they ſhulde be corrupted from the ſymplicitie of Chriſt: therfore there is no doubt of your good zealle and diligence. My good fathers &amp; deare brethren, who ar firſt callid to the battel, to ſtriue for gods glory and the edification of his people, againſt the Romiſh reliques and rages of Antichriſt, I doubt not but that you wyl coragiouſlye and conſtantlye in Chriſt, rape at theſe rages of Gods enemyes, and that you will by this occaſion race vp many as grete enormites that we all know, &amp; labore to race out all the dregges &amp; remnants of

tranſformid popery, that are crept into England, by to much lenite of them that wylbe namid the Lordes of the cleargie: what is he that hath the zeale of gods glory before his face, that wyl not ioyne both in prayer, and in ſufferinge with you, in ſo good a cauſe, that is ſo much for gods glory, and the edificacion of gods church, in the pure ſimplicite of Chriſtes word &amp; ſacramentes, wherin our enemies and perſecutours are ſtrangely bewitchid. I wote not by what Circes cupe, that they do make ſuche a diuerſite betwixt Chriſtes worde &amp; his ſacramentes, that they can not thinke the worde of God ſafelye ynoughe preachid, &amp; honorably inough handlyd, without cap, cope, ſurplis. But that the ſacraments the maryinge, the buryinge, the churching of wemen, &amp; other church ſeruice, as they call it, muſte nedes be decored with croſſinge, with capping, wt ſurpleſſing, with knelinge, with preti wafer cakes, and other knackes of poperi. O Paule that thou were a lyue, thou durſt tell thoſe politike gentelmen, that ther hath bin to much laboure beſtoued vpon them in vaine, thou durſte ſay vnto them, as thou dideſt to y• Corinthians, that they eat not the Lordes ſupper, but pley a pagent of their owne to blynde the people, and kepe them ſtill in ſuperſticion, fare from the ſymplicite of Chriſtes ſupper: but howe

many ſely ſowles is ther that dothe beleue veryly, that they haue an Engliſh maſſe, and ſo put no difference betwene truth &amp; falſhod, betwene Chriſt and antichriſt, betwene God and the deuell, they are ſtrangely bewitched. I ſay that thus wyll bynde theyr Englyſhe preſthode &amp; ſacraments, but muche more enchauntid that can fynd no garments to pleaſe them. But ſuch as haue ben polutid openly with popiſhe ſuperſticion &amp; Idolatry, but moſt of all in this point ſhall theyr madnes apere to all poſterites, that they make theſe Antichriſtian rages Cauſam ſine qua non, that is, a cauſe without which ther is no holy miniſtery in Chriſt, ſo that this ſhall make an Englyſhe preſte, be he neuer ſuche a dolt or vnlearnid in the knouledge of the ſcripture as we haue very manye, and without theſe romiſſhe reliques not Paule hym ſelfe ſhalbe admittid (as one of them dyd blaſpheme &amp; the reſt of them in effecte do affirme) well agaynſte ſuche popiſhe chaffer and popery, hathe byne longe agone foughten witheall, when the gret captaines of that religion lyuyd, and yet God gaue the victory. Therfor let vs not fear now, although it doth begine to ſture agayn, for ther is no craft, conninge, counſell, wyſdom, or policy againſt the Lord. We haue Chriſt &amp; hys Apoſtells &amp; the Prophetes euer ſtryuing agaynſt the Ipocrites

of their time on our ſyde. a ſtran for popiſhe polici we haue the worde of God to warant vs, to rote out al monuments of ſuperſticion and Idolatry, &amp; are charged to abhor them, to accompt them, accurſed, and to defy them, and to deteſt them as menſtreous clowtes, they haue not the worde of God for them. And what wyſdom is in them, ſayth god by his Prophet Jeremi, they talke of obedience &amp; concorde, but ther is no obedience againſt the Lorde, no nor concorde to be deſired, but wher gods glory and verite is preſerued, Els better to haue al the worlde in hurly burleis, and heauen &amp; earth to ſhake, then one ioyte of gods glory ſhulde decaie. So far forth as in vs leithe, we haue theyr owne lawes and proclamacions, to rote out all monuments of ſuperſticion and Idolatrye, &amp; theyr oune wordes are contrarye to theyr doinges. Yt ſhulde apere that they repent their reformation proclamid, as did y• Iſralites, they buylde agayn that which ons they haue diſtroied and this is doue openlye that all the worlde may wonder, and behold: but what is done ſecretlye, god wyll one daye haue it declarid openly, ye they make the name of god &amp; this doctrine that we profeſſe to be euell ſpoken of alredy. By many of theyr doinges, theyr iudgement haſteth that for ſuch cauſes perſecute Gods true preachers. Wherfor let vs

not feare theyr threteninges, ther can none perſecute the godly for this cauſe &amp; traſſhe. but ether ſuch as are nether hote nor colde, and then they ſhalbe vomyted out vnleſſe their zeale encreaſe, or ſuch as haue no God before their eies, whoſe god is their bellie, or 
                  •
               is open papiſts, whom god hathe geuen vp 
                  •
               o a reprobate ſenſe, wherfore we muſt thus 
                  •
               ake it, that they ar gods rodds for oure ſinnes, becauſe we haue not ben more zelous in Gods cauſe, nether carefull to ſeke his glorye, that wolfe Wyncheſter &amp; blodie bucher Bonar fought once againſt many godli men for the grounde of this gere, and thei had all the power of the Realme ſeruinge theyr luſtes, but beholde how the Lorde in ſhort time ouerthrew them al, to giue vs coradge to go forwarde, the Lord forgeue vs, we ar to ſlacke and neglygent in heauenly thynges, this monſter Bonar remainithe and is fed as papiſts ſay, for their ſakes, &amp; it muſt be grauntyd, it is for ſome purpos, althoughe he be a traytor and an enemi to the crowne and realme, and bothe to God and man, whiche brunnid godes holy teſtament, murderid his ſaintes and his ſervātes. But what the Lord requyrith to be done wythe falſe Prophetes it is manyfeſt: we haue bothe the lawe of god &amp; man for vs, But we ar anſwerid nay, you your ſealues ſhalbe compellid to turne

your coates and cappes, and get you into his leueris, and to be lyke him in your garments. O Elyas that thou lyuedſte, or that thy ſpyrit weare amongſt vs, thou wolde
                  ••
                ſay with the Prophet Sophoni, that God will vyſit the werears of this Idolatours garmentes or ſtrange aparell, thou woldeſt ſay, that thinges dedicatid once to idolatry, is not indifferent, thou woldeſt ſay reuerence to the ſacramēt is wrought by doctrine and diſcipline, and not by popiſſhe &amp; Idolatours garments, thou woldeſt ſaye, what decency can ther be gaynyd to the ſacramēts, by that which hath byn deuiſyd &amp; vſyd to deface it, if the golde ordeinyd by god for the reuerence and decenci of the Jewes temple, is not to be admittyd to beutify the churche of Chriſte, much leſſe copes brought in by papiſtes the enemyes of god, and alwayes continwyd in their ſeruice as ornamētes of their religion in no wyſe ought of vs Chriſtians to be retaynid. But the papiſtes triumphe and glori in their aſſembles, that the hote goſpelars ſhalbe driuen to their doltiſhe attires, for the Lords ſake let vs neuer giue them any cauſe of Joye, thoughe we ſhoulde dye for yt: Moyſes wold not yelde on hoofe of a beſte in gods buſines, he wolde not leue the loupe vnmade, nor make a button or a claſpe more or leſſe. Eleaſar will not decemble by

eatynge of vnlawfull meates, the faythfull Iſralites wolde not receyue ſo muche as an y
                  •
               i buſhe. Contrariwyſe Orygen caryinge a braunche and profeſſynge, that he bare it for Chriſt at the firſt. But was afterwarde compellid to open Idolatry, ſo curſid a thing it is to geue any place to the wicked: all the papiſtes that ſaye, they worſhip Chriſt in the croſſe, and God in the ſacrament, do ſtill vnder theſe wordes continew ſtill in their Idolatri, beware of deceitfull wordes, that couer wickid purpoſes, to drawe vs from Chriſtiā ſymplicite. Let vs ſtand conſtantly agaynſte all abuſes, and repent for our former coldnes in religion, and our ſynnes, and call for healpe from aboue, for the hand of the Lorde is not ſhortenid: we ar aſſured that we ſeke Gods glory, and our aduerſaries may ſee, yf they can ſe any thinge, that this thinge that they ſeke is not for gods glory, ſeing the papiſtes the enemyes of God, doe ſo deſyre yt and glory in yt. And reioyſe, that we, whom they moſt hate, cannot beſafe but vnder their garments: we ar aſſurid that we ſeke godes glory in folowinge Chriſt his Apoſteles and Prophets. who euer diſpiſed theſe phariſaicall outward faces and viſures, Chriſte fyndethe fault withe the garmentes of the phariſeis. Paule counteth all his phariſaicall,

ſhew to be donge. Zachari ſaithe, that the falſe Prophet ſhalbe aſhamed of his prophecye, and forſake his garments wherin he deceyuid. &amp; ſhal the true Prophetes be fayne to crepe into their coules? for by the ſame autorite may be comaundid any peace of popery, ſo that it be namyd policie. Ezechias and Joſias knew no ſuche au
                  •
               thoritie, but they ſay: It is for policie, For it plainly apearithe that ther is leſſe care for religion, then for policie. But beware that the example of Jeroboham be not folowed, that made ſuch like preſtes for policie as wolde do as he commaundid them. Achaz of policie brought the faſhion of an alter into Jeruſalem, as he ſawe at Damaſcus, where he had ouercome the Idolatours and their Idolls, but curſed was his policie, and ſo at all they that wil retaine any thinge of their Idolatrie. Nabuchodonoſors Idoll was for vnitye and policie, but without the warraunt of gods worde, ther is neyther good vnitye nor police. The godlie father Buc
                  •
               r callithe the tenthes and the firſt fruites ſacriledge and roberie, they be kept ſtil for policie. Croſſe and candelſtickes at ſuperſticious, though they be kepte. I wot not for what policie the adoration of the Sacrament in the countres, where they knocke and knele to a wafer cake is a popiſhe

policie. That wemen baptiſe, that pluralites, tot quot
                  •
                impropriacions, non reſidence, deſpenſacions, ſuſpenſions, excomunications, &amp; abſolucions, for money at grauntyd, yt is evell, like as are many other inormites berowed from Rome, which remayne in the name of policie. All theſe thinges were abhorryd as popiſhe ſuperſticious, and Idolatries, amonge our goſpellers both biſhops &amp; others, when they were vnder gods roddes in pouerte. But how thei now haue learnid courtely deuinite, to grounde all apon policie? Humble them agayne o Lorde, that they do not forget the, and thy great kindnes and mercie ſhewid apon them, and ſture vp their hartes and myndes, that they may be carefull ouer thy pore flocke. O Chriſte, whom thou haſt dearly bought, by this theyr policy ar blindid, &amp; carithe for no more, but that thei may haue this ſuperſticious ſhew which is ſo ſtifely maintained. Let him mumble as he liſte, yf he be thus apparelid, al his ſeruice is well ynough, otherwyſe yt is nothing worthe, Thus cauſe you them to periſhe by your polices, for whome Chriſt hathe dyed. further more, yf poperi be ſuperſtitious and idolatrous, euel and wicked, as yet ther was neuer a worſe thinge in the worlde, then ar we commaunded to abſteine from all participatio

the
                  •
                o
                  •
               , and from all the ſhewe therof ab omni ſpecie mali, that is, from all ſhewe of wickidnes. Theſe garments were the ſhewe of their blaſphemous preaſthod, herein they dyd ſinge and ſaye their ſuperſticious idolatrous ſeruice, they dyd ſence their Idolls and healpe forwarde theyr Idolatrous maſſes, what policie can it be then to weare this gere. But a ſuperſticious wickid and popiſhe policie, they doe it for policie, they ſaye, that their prieſtes may be knowen and magnified of men. Dyd not the Phariſies vſe the ſame policie, to doe all their workes and make all their garmentes bothe Philacteris vpon their headdes, and their wide and ſyde robes and borders, that they might be more expectable, and notorious to the people: but their woo is throtenid aboue al other ſinners. To ſuche ypocrites, as beinge voyde of all true holynes, delite in all outward ſhewes, theyr curſe is moſt inculcate, their polyci is that y• preiſtes ſhall weare white in the churches to ſignify their vertue▪ their purenes, and holines. and when they go fourth of the church they muſt weare blacke gownes and blacke hornes, for cōtrary polycies, and for dyuers ſignificacions, Our maſter Chriſtes polycie was expreſſyd in one worde, fede, fede, fede. and the Prophetes before, and the Apoſtelles

afterwarde, yf Chriſte be the wyſdome of the father, the true miniſters ſhalbe well inough knowen, by that one marke which he geueth: and yf that he haue not that marke better vnknowen then knowen, both for him ſelfe and others, therfore lett them not ſaye for ſhame, that they ſeeke gods glorie, Chriſtes wil, or the edification of his church, by their polycie. Why les they thretē &amp; ſtope the ſpredinge of gods worde and fedinge of Chriſtes flocke, cōmandyd by writing to excōmunicate the moſt faithful laborers in the planting of the goſpell, becauſe thei will not weare the rages of popery, to expulſe y• moſt valiant ſoldiars agaynſt the Romiſhe Antichriſt, the moſt earneſt ouerthrowars of the kyngdom of ſatan, which ſtandith in ſin and blindnes. O beware you, that wilbe Lordes ouer the flockes, that you be not ſore punyſhed for your pryde, towardes your brethren, and your cowardlines in gods cauſe, that for Princes pleaſures and pompoſe liuinges, do turne poperi into policie, and to become our perſecutors vnder the cloke of policie: it were better to loſe your liuings, then to diſpleaſe god in perſecutinge of youre brethren, &amp; hinder the courſe of the worde. But as oure deutie is, we wyll praye for you, and for all our brethren in the miniſteri, that god of his

grace would graunte vs more zeale for his glorie, than any of vs hathe had heretofore, more deſire to edifie, Chriſtes people in pure ſimplicite, to preſent them a chaſt virgin vnto Chriſt, then hitherto hathe apeared, that when the hedeſhepherde ſhall cal to accounte, we be not aſhamyd▪ But beinge founde perfecte in all good workes, may receiue the crowne prepared, as for you deare brethren whome God hath callyd into the brunte of the batell, The Lorde kepe ye conſtant, that ye yelde nether to tolleracion, nether to anye other ſubtelte perſuaſious of diſpenſacions, or lycences which were to fortifie their Romiſhe practiſes. but as you fyght the Lords fyght, be valiant. God will not leue you, nether forſake you, as you ſeke gods glorye, god wyll glorifye you, and as by you Chriſtes church is edifyed, comfortid and confirmid in Chriſtian ſimplycite, ſo ſhall you receyue comfort by Chriſte your heede captaine, when you ſhalbe callyd to geue acomptes of your ſtewardſhippes, and to be rewardyd for your fidelite, the matter is not ſo ſmalle as the worlde do take yt, yt wyll appeare before all be endyd, what an harde thinge it is, to cut of the rages of the Hidra of Rome, it is beutifull, but poyſonful, ther is no daling with ſuch a mounſter, beware of lokyng backe

to Sodome or delyght anye witte in the garments of Babilone, neyther once touche the poyſonid cupe, though yt be of golde or gliteringe. Let vs repent of our former ſynnes vnfaynidlye, and then ſhall we abhor and ſtamp vnder our fette theſe rages, that were apoyntid to ſuperſticion and idolatry, Let vs hate the blaſphemous preaſthode, ſo iniurious to Chriſtes preiſthode, that euery pache and token of it be in execration, deteſtation, and accurſed, and take no parte of yt vpon our heddes nor backes, leaſt we be accurſed as it is. Let vs not make the heritage of god as a byrde of many colours, holdinge of diuers religions, Let vs not mix
                  •
               e the Jewes with the gentills, let vs not in no wiſe mixt this our religion with any thinge of Antichriſt, let vs not confyrme the blinde in their blindnes, neyther the weacke in their ſuperſticion. But rather let vs take awaye, if we can, the names, memories, and all monumēts of poperye and that Antichriſtes prieſthod. Let vs open our wyndous with Daniel, and profeſſe what we ar: their cruelte ſhalbe our glorie. Let vs followe paull, that knew that the truthe goſpel cold not be retainyd, if any Jewiſhe cerimonies were mayntainyd. Lett vs rather neuer weare anye garment, then we ſhould weare thoſe, wherby our brethren

ſhulde be weakened, offendyd or boldenyd to take parte with the idolatours, &amp; ſo through our hautines in knouledge, oure weake brethren periſhe, for whom Chriſt died. Behold and marke well, how they falle backwarde that yelde in anye iote, and ſe how they are edifyed, and increaſe in godlines, which holde that ryght waye that you goe in, the which the Lorde increaſe you, &amp; vs all, and ſtrenthen vs with his holy ſpyrit, that we may continewe to oure lyues ende, al wayes both by our thoughtes, wordes, and workes, to auaunce his glorye and honor dayly more and more, now and for euer.
            Amen.
         
         
            
            
               ¶ Grace and peace with all maner ſpiritual feling and liuing worthi of the kindnes of Chriſt, be with all that thriſt the will of God.
            
            TO my faythfull and deare brethren in Chriſt Jeſu, as in comen daungers of fier, or ſuche lyke, welbelouyd, they that be fare of, com to ſocoure thoſe that haue nede, ſo I beinge out of iepordie and fartru Chriſtian loue of, can not but of deuty wyſhe well to thoſe that be touchyd about the popiſhe apparell in thys libertye of Gods truthe, whyche is tought plainely without offencis, in y• greatyſt miſterys of our religion and ſaluacion, yt is much to be maruayled, that this ſmall controuerſye of aparell ſhould be ſo heuelythe pract
                     ••
                   of the wickid. taken. But this is the mallis of ſatan, that wher he can not ouerthrow the greatiſt matters, he will cauſe great troubels in trifels. Peter and Paule agreyde in the greatyſte articles of our ſaluacion, and yet they differyd ſo about meattes, that Paule withſtodeThe infirmites of the godl
                     •
                  
                and rebuckid hym openly. Paule and Batnabas fell at ſuche bytter contention, whether Marke ſhuld go with them or no, that they partyd companyes, and eyther of them went ſondry waies. God defend vs from thethe conſtance of the god▪
                lyke. Paule circumciſyd Timothe when ther

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
was hope to wine the Jewes: but when they wold haue it of neceſſite, he would not circumciſe Titus, therfore compellinge would not be vſyd in thinges of liberte, yt is a lamētable caſe, that among them that are civil &amp; full of knouledge, that yt ſhuld come thus to paſſe. Conſyder dearly belouyd, I beſech you; how that all countres, whiche haue reformid religion, haue caſt away the popiſhe aparell with the pope: and yet we that wyll be taken for the beſt goſpelars, are contentid to kepe it as an holie religion. Marke well alſo how many godly and learnid miniſters ther be here in all countres, that be ſo zelous not onlie to forſake the wickyd doctrine of poperie, ready to leue the minyſtry, &amp; to loſe lyuinges, rather then to be lyke the popiſhe teachers of ſuperſticious order in aparell or behaviour. This realme hath ſuch ſkacite of teachers, that yf ſo many worthye men and learnid ſhuld be caſt out of the miniſtrie for ſuche ſmall matters, many placis ſhulde be deſtitude of preachers, &amp; yt wold geue an incurable offence to all the fauourars of gods truthe here, and in other countres, alſo ſhall we make ſo much and ſo precious of the popes rages that other reformyd places, exteme as uyle &amp; filthye. God forbid. S. Paule byddich wemen vſe ſuche aparell as becomith

them that profes true godlines, which rule is muche more to be obſeruid of men, &amp; eſpeciallye of preachers. But yf we forſake popery as wickid, ſhall we ſay that their aparell becommith ſaintes, and profeſſars of tru holines. Saint Paule bydith vs refraine from al outward ſhew of evell, but ſurely in kepinge of this popiſhe aparell, we forbear not an outwarde ſhew of much euell, yf popery be iudgid evell, as greter wickidnes can not be, as we wolde haue a diuers ſhewe of aparel to be knowē from the comon people, ſo is yt neceſſary in aparell, to haue a ſhew, howe a proteſtante is to be knowen from a papiſte. Yt hathe pleaſyd God to call vs to preache his heuenly worde to that hye office, God geue you grace and vs all to ſeke hys honor &amp; glorie: yf we ſo do with a pure hart and mynde, he hath promyſed, He that honorith me, I will glorify him, and he that contemnith me, I wyll contemne him. Let ther be no curtiſye made to healpe gods people now they be in danger. Call to your remembraunce Quene Eaſter, ſhe begaue to make curtiſy to ſpeke in yt cauſe, but Mardocheus ſayd vnto her: Yf thou now hold thy peace, God ſhall delyuer by an other meane, &amp; yet thou &amp; thy fathers houſe ſhall peryſhe. You that can and may do good, do it whyle tyme

is offerid, the tyme will come when it wylbe to late: yet god wyll comfort his by ſome other meane: It ys a perilous thinge, not to healpe in the tyme of neade, &amp; not to ſuffer religion to goe forward in all ſyncerite, and to further gods cauſe when ye maye, when Terenti a good Chriſtian captaine returnid with great triumphe &amp; victory, the Emperor Valerius bade him are what he wold, and he ſhuld haue it for his good ſeruice: he hauing God before his cyes, deſyryd nether ryches, nether honor, but thoſe which had aduentered their liues for true religion, might haue a church alowid them, to ſerue their god purely in, &amp; ſeueral from the Arrians. The Emperour beyng angrie with his requeſt, pullyd his ſupplicacion in pecis, and bade him axe ſom other thing. but he gathered vp the pecis of his, paper and ſayd: I haue receuid my rewarde, I wyll axe nothinge els, God encrece about Princes the ſmall nomber of ſuche zelous ſuters &amp; promoters of religion, and then no doubt gods glorye ſhall floriſhe when we ſeke his dewe honor, and not oure owne profyte. But to avoide contencion &amp; ſciſme Auſten gevith good counſel to godly and quiet men, that they mercifully correcte that whiche they can, &amp; that which they can not, paciently beare, grone and morne, with

loue, vntil▪ god ether correct or amend them. But how this Chriſtian loue ſhuld be kept in this church, when ſo manye godlie for ſo ſmall thinges ſhalbe thruſte out, &amp; alſo how many already is from the miniſtery &amp; theyr lyuinges, yt paſſyth manye good and godlie wittes to conceyue. S. Pauls rule in ſuche thinges, ſayth: All thinges to me is lawfull, but all thinges is not erpedient: all thinges to me is lawfull, but all thinges edefye not. Therfor in this caſe we muſt not ſo ſuttelly diſpute, what Chriſtian liberte will ſuffer vs to do, but what is metiſt and moſt edefying for Chriſtian charite, &amp; promoting Chriſtian and pure religion. But ſurely how popiſhe aparell ſhuld edefie, or ſet forwarde the goſpell of Chriſt Jeſus, it can not be ſeen of the multitude, nay, it is to much fealt how gredly it reioyſith the aduerſaries of the truth, when they ſee what we borowe of them; &amp; contend for the ſame as thinges neceſſarie▪ marke well the byſſhopes wearing of their whyte rochets, what grounde they fyrſte had, and from whence they receyuid it. Ther was a certayne man, namid Siſinius an heriticke biſhop of the No
                  •
               acions, and he firſt begane yt. all thoſe other popiſh traſhe hath the lyke foundacions, but they haue to long contineuyd &amp; pleaſyd poperie, which is beggerly

pacchid vp of al ſortes of cerimones, &amp; that they coulde neuer be routyd out ſence, no not from manie profeſſors of the goſpel. Wherfore you that ſe others that is come to a better perfection, grudge not at yt, but be thankfull to God, though thynges may be borne wythe for a tyme for Chriſtian lybertes ſake, in hope to winne the weake. yet when lyberte is turnyd into neceſſite, yt ys evell, &amp; no lenger lyberte: and that, that was for wynning the weake ſufferid for a tyme, is become the confyrminge of the frowarde in their obſtinacie. Paul vſyd circūciſion for a tyme as of lyberte, but when it was vrgyd of neceſſite, he wold not bende vnto it. That famous father Maſter Bucer, when he was aryd why he wolde not weare a ſquare cape, made aunſwere, becauſe hys heade was not foure ſquare. wherin ſurelye he notyd well the comlynes of aparell to be, when yt was faſſionyd lyke the body, &amp; a gret folly when a ſquare cape was ſet on a rounde heade.
            God be mercyfull vnto vs, and graunte vs vprightly to ſeke hys honore wyth all carneſtnes &amp; ſimplicite. The Lorde comfort his afflictid church, &amp; graunte that in this oulde age of the worlde, we may ſerue the Lord of hoſtes in ſynglenes of hart, and laboure to rote out all ſtomblinge blockes in religion,

that Chriſtes glorie maye nakydly ſhyne of yt ſealue, without all tradicions or inuencions of men, as in the begynninge when yt was pureſt, and all ſuch deuyſes vnknowen, but inuentid of late to bleare the eyes of the ignorant, with outwarde ſhewe of holines. God graunt that we may geue all honor to whom al honore is deue, both inwardly and outwardly, to ſerve hym vnfaynedlye al the dayes of oure lyfe. Fare well deare brethren in the Lorde Jeſu, who euer kepe vs in hys fayth, feare, and loue, for euer.
            Amen.
         
         
            
            
            
               ¶ To my faythfull Brethren now afflycted, &amp; to all thoſe that vnfaynedly loue the Lorde Jeſus, the Lorde guyde vs with his holy ſpret, that we maye always ſerue hym bothe in body and mynde in all ſynceryte to oure lyues ende.
            
            WHen I do remember, dearly belouyd, the great charge inioynyd vnto vs of almyghtie God, &amp; the ſtrayghte accounte that we ſhall haue to make, for the ryghte vſe and diſpenſacion of his myſteries, I fynde no compariſon myght iuſtly moue any Chriſtyan to doubt of the better of thoſe two choyſes, only that whych makythe a ſhewe for the mayntenaunce of popiſhe apparel is the opynion of indifferency,marke wel good Chriſtyan. whych thynge he yt wyll perſwade, muſt fyrſt proue that it tendythe to Godes glory. Concurrythe wythe his worde, edefyeth his churche, mayntaynyth Chriſtyan lyberte: whych condycions &amp; circunſtances if they wante, The thynge whych otherwyſe by nature is indifferent, dothe degenerat and become hurtfull. but howe can Godes glory be auaunced by thoſe popiſhe garmētes whych ſuperſticyous men &amp; Antychriſt haue inuentyd for the maynteyninge &amp; beuty fyinge of Idolatry, what

agrement can mans ſuperſticious inuencyons haue wythe the eternall worde of God, what edifycacion can there be wher the ſpirit of god is greuyd, Chriſtes lytillous diſcoragyd, y• weake brethren broughtthe bōdage of ceremonies what it bringith into doubt of relygyon, the wyckyd papiſts confyrmyd in their errour, And adore new ſet open to all Popiſh tradycions and Antychriſtian impietie: nether can any man call this Chriſtian lybertie, where a yoke is layd vpon the dyſciples neckes, where the conſciens is cloggyd, true preachers thretenyd, the curſe of Godes worde ſtayed, the congregacyons ſpoylyd of godlye and learnyd paſtors, the Sacramentes brought vnder ſubieccyon of Idolators &amp; ſuperſticious veſtiments, therefore where either the formar condycion wante or this latter be annexſyd, yt can not be callyd a thynge mere indifferent. Auguſtine vpon indifferent thyngs ſay the, Thoſe thynges that are not contrarye to faythe, nether yet contrarye to good manners, and haue ſomwhat to exhorte to the amendemēt of lyfe, wherſoeuer we ſe ſuch thynges commaundyd, or do know to be inſtitutid, we do not only alowe, but alſo we will folow them in prayſynge and imytatinge them: yf the infyrmyte of ſome do not let that yt

ſhuld be a further detrimente or damage, here Auguſtine requiryth two poynts in thyngs indifferent. Firſt that they induce to a better lyfe, &amp; do ſerue to edyfycacion, next that we beware leſt any offence come therbye, or any weake conſciens be hynderydmarke wel the nature of indifferēt thinges in y• curſe of religion, Chriſt hym ſelfe geuyth a good warning ſaynge, wo be to offences, there myght be brought dyuers examples and teſtymonies to proue, that thynges whych of them ſelues haue byne or are indifferēt, by circunſtāce &amp; abuſinge becom euel, what thynge is more requirid for ſondry cauſis in this lyfe, then faſtinge, and for the dayes &amp; tymes, what thynges can be more indifferent. yet yf by y• obſeruacion of dayes and appoyntinge of tymethe godly wil haue nothinge to do in cerimonies of the wicked. we ſhuld confirme the opinion of the wyckyd, &amp; ſo gyue conſente to them we were worthely to be blamyd &amp; reprouyd, as Auguſtine wytneſſith wryting after this ſort, To faſte on the Sonday is a great offence, cheflye after y• deteſtable hereſye of the Manichees, whych is planlye contrary to the Catholyke fayth of manye, &amp; the ſcriptures of God dyd ſhew it ſelfe, whych cō
               ſtitutyd to their hearers, to faſt on ye Sonday, was a moſt mete daye. Tertulian in his boke De corona militis, defendyth the

cauſe of a ſoudyar that was zelous for the glory of god, &amp; wold not weare a garlonde on his heade as y• reſt of his felowes dyd, leſt he ſhuld ſeame to conſent with ye Idolators,God ſend vs manye ſuche zelours chriſtyanes. &amp; ſo bringe true relygion into doubt, &amp; wheras many of the Chriſtiās myſlyhid of this ſoudyars facte, which for ſo ſmal a try fill wolde haſarde the Emperors fauor and ſo auenture his lyfe, ſeinge to weare the garlonde was not agaynſte y• ſcriptures. Tertullian who iuſtifyed this zelous acte anſwerethe on this ſoudiars behalfe ſayinge: Yf for this cauſe it may be ſayd y• he myght lawfully be crownyd, becauſe the ſcriptures do not forbyd it, by this ſame reaſon it ſhalbe anſwered, that therfor he ought not to be crounyd, becauſe ye ſcriptures doth not commande it. The Counſel of Toletane ordenyd that in Baptymſe ſhulde be vſyd but one dyppynge, leſt they ſhuld ſeame to conſente with the heretiks whiche vſed to dypp the child thryſe, &amp; ſendynge to Gregory for his counſell herein, they receuyd this anſwere, for the eſchewinge of the ſclaunder of ſciſme and tradycion of the heritikes, let vs hold the ſymple vſe of Baptiſme, leſ
                  •
                they whiche amō
               geſt vs do vſe to dypp thry ſe to allowe the aſſercyon of the heretykes, whyle y• folow their

not onlye to holde the Idoll as accurſyd, but alſo that we vtterlye abhorre and accounte moſte abhominable thynges that apperteyne ther vnto, and haue nothynge to do with it, leaſt we be ſnaryd with it, rede we not in the Machabees, howe the Lorde diſtroyd all thoſe that had any ſtuff2. mach. 12 Joſua. 7. of the Idolls, and howe was Achan plagyd for reſeruynge thoſe thynges, whych the Lorde wold haue dyſtroyd and accutſyd,a ſuttle practys. we reade that Juliamis the apoſtata cauſyd the heathen to accomodat them ſelues to the maners of the Chriſtyans, and theyr vſages thynkyng by this meanes to entice them to Paganiſme, and yf we compell the godlye to conforme themſelues to the Papiſtes, I greatlye feare, leaſt we fall into Papiſme: alas, that ſuch compulſyon ſhuld be vſyd toward vs, and ſo great lenite towards the Papiſtes, how many Papiſtes inioye lyberte &amp; lyuyngs, whyche neyther haue ſworne obedyene to the Quenes maieſtie, nether do yet anye parte of deutye towardes theyr miſerable ſtlockes, thoſe myſers laughe, and triumphe to ſe vs thus delt wythe, not aſhamyd here vpon to bragg, that they truſte that the reſt of theyr thynges wyll folow. But he that ſittyth in the heauens, ſhal laughe

them to thorne, and at leangthe ſhal geue an end to oure depe ſyghinges, and delyuer vs from all heuynes ſorowes and myſeris, wherfore let vs neuer yealde to this tryumphe of the Pope agaynſt Chriſte, Lorde Jeſus be mercyfull vnto vs, and let thy wrathe be pouryd vpon them that call not on the name of the Lorde, yf true reformacyon can not be had. Yet lett Chriſtyan lybertie preuayle agaynſt compulſion to euell, lett not the Papiſtes abuſe vs as the Jewys dyd the Chriſtyans, when they had the temporall ſworde on theyr ſyde, pytey ye dyſſolate churches heare the cryes and gronyns of ſo manye thouſandes of godes pore children that hunger and thyrſt for ſprituall fode, we neade not to apealle to godes worde, to the prymatiue church to the iuſt plages whyche hath byne pouryd and is pouryd contynuallye, vpon the wordle for lacke of true reformacyon of relygyon, but let your owne conſcience iudge betwene oure cauſe and oure enemyes, and yf we ſeke nothynge but godes glorye craue equitie and ryght deſyre Chriſtyan lybertie, labor to ouerthrowe Idolatry and to wyne ſoulys vnto Chriſte, why ſhulde we not be harde, why are we ſo vncharitably dealt with all

the Lorde moue youre hartes and open your eies, that we may all prayſe gloryfy his holy name, that when the end of oure pylgrymage ſhalbe endyd moſt ioyfullye we maye reſt with hym in his euerlaſtinge glory through Chriſt oure ſauyour, to whome wyth the Father and the Holygoſt be all prayſe glorye and honor, for euer.
         
         
            
            
            ¶ To the Reader.
            TO my faythfull Brethren, we geue thankes to God for your conſtancie and vpryght delynge in this gret controuerſie now rayſyd by packynge of enemys about the wearinge of popiſh apparell, and as ye haue well begonne, ther is no doubt, but the Lorde in mercy ſhall kepe ye pure and blameles to the ende. It hathe byne no ſmall ioye and comfort to many godlye and good Churches, which dayly and howerly prayeth for your perſeuerāce, and that it wolde pleaſe God to eaſe it, whē his good will and pleaſure is. So on the other ſyde muche lamentynge the blyndnes of thoſe that goeth about to defende it: but eſpeciallye thoſe that are become perſecutors of their godly &amp; faithfull brethren: but as charite requireth, we deſyre God neuer laye it to theyr charge, but geue them grace to ryſe agayne vnto whom we leue them wether they ſtande or falle. Let Lottes wyfe be a warnynge in tyme to take hede. Moſes that bleſſyd ſeruant of God wolde not alter the valew of a curten, or a lytill pyne in the Arche, ſo zelous was he in the Lordes worke: nor neuer brought any thynge out of his owne heade to the people: But had always the

warrant of the worde for hym, to cōclude, what ſo euer may be obiected agaynſt the refuſars of thoſe ydolators garmētes, for what ſo euer they brynge, may be reduſed into this poyntes, that Godly men ether nede not or ought not to be ſcrupulous in ſo ſmall a matter, which anſwer ye ſhall vnderſtand as folowith with an anſwere to a queſtion at the end hereof. The Lord for his Chriſt ſake make Ephrahim and Manaſſis agre, that we maye all with on hart and mynde vnfaynydly ſeke Godes glorye, the edificacion of his people, that we may lyue in all godly peace, vnyte, and concord. This grant, o Lorde, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, to whom, with the, and the Holy goſte, be all prayſe, glory, and honor for euer and euer.
            Fare ye well deare Brethren.
         
         
            
            DEarly belouyd, you that haue wytte, vnderſtanding, and wyll to be inſtructyd in this controuerſi▪ now rayſyd in the Churche about apparell, at thys tyme thys ſhall ſuffyce. Yt is true that the teachers of handye craftes affyrme, that no man can attayne to ſuche excellente perfeccyon in worke, as maye be diſputed of by reaſone, muche leſſe when the rule of religion muſte be framyd accordynge to the rule of Godes wyll, which is y• rule of all perfeccyon, may we loke that any thyng can ſo perfectly be performyd of vnperfect mā, that in all poynts yt may anſwere to the perfeccion that God requirith: neuertheles God requirith his ſeruice to be ſuche as hym ſealfe is, deuyne, pure, ſyncere, vnmingled, and in no parte corruptyd, and as lacke of ſtrenthe ſhal not excuſe vs, in that we can not, ſo neclygence makythe vs more wickyd, yf that we may performe, and we will not. Fyrſte we are requiryd to loue God with all our hartes, all our myndes, and all our ſtrength, that preciſenes is comendable, which withholdith not a lytill, whē all is requiryd. ThouDeut. 18. ſhalt be perfect with thy Lorde thy god. Thou ſhalt not bende ether to thy ryghthande, or to the leafte. Thou ſhalt nether

               
                  〈…〉
                mau
                  •
               dyd. Thou ſhalt not inquier for the gods of the Gentyls, ſayinge: Howe dyd thoſe Gentyles ſerue theyr godes. Thou ſhalt not do ſo to the Lorde thy god. For whatſoeuer the Lorde abhorreth, that dyd they to theyr godes. God wyll haue his children ſo to abhorre theſe ſuperſticion, y• they ſhuld fle euen from that infecciō thatThe zeall that God requirith. comythe by hearynge. Furthermore, ſo many thinges as ar cōmandyd of leprous, mēſtreous, dead bodys, were many, which myght not be touchyd without defyling, what other thinges were they in that rude people, but exerciſes of precyſe purenesGod kepe vs frō all outwarde ſhew of Popery. and cleanes, the obſeruance of ſuche ſhadowes, althoughe it hath byn longe ſynce abolyſhyd, yet the euerlaſtinge truthe remaynyth: muche more in preſence of the bodye, that no prophane or defylyd thinge may be minglyd with gods ſeruice. Moreouer god forbydyth all ſtrange corruptious mixtures, whē he forbyddyth them to ſowe land with diuers ſeedes, to plowghe with an oxe and an aſſe, to weare lynyne and wollen to gether. For lyberte &amp; coſtome euen in ye leaſte matters bredythe boldnes, &amp; in hys cōmandement god hath alſo reſpecte to the hynde of apparell. Fynallie

when this c
                  •
               ea
                  •
               es is ſtreachyd euenmarke well. to brute beaſtes, who wold not beleue that God requirith an vtter deteſtacion of all vncleanes, eſpecially in religion. Seing all theſe lawes perteyne to the fyrſt cōmandement, accordinge to the ſame preciſe rule dyd the holy fathers exerciſe them ſelues vnto puryte, therfore it is neuer rede that the godly Patriarches dyd ſacrifyce vpon the Idolators alters, but whyther ſoeuer they remouid, always they buyldid neweExample of holy men. alters. Furthermore Abraham wolde not take a thryde of the Kynge of Sodoma. Jacob buryed the earinges that weare ornamentes of ſuperſticion, with the Idoles them ſelues. Moyſes to blemiſhe the ſeruice of God wolde accepte no condicions at all, there ſhall not remayne on hou
                  •
               e, ſaythe he very preciſlye. Dauith wold not take the names of the Idoles in his lypes. Ezechias brake the braſen ſerpēt, not only chāgyd the vſe of it. The Holyghoſt prayſitheWhat greter herytykes cā ther be, then the Papiſtes? thoſe godly Kinges, which deſtroyed the highe places, as Ezechias and Joſias, in whiche places ſomtyme the people dyd worſhip god. Elyazer wold not fayne that he dyd cate ſwynes fleſhe. S. Pawle byddythe, Refrayne from all ſhew of euyll. S. John forbyddyth vs to ſalute an herytyke

               
                  〈…〉
                
               
                  •
               eneus wytneſſith, when he mett an herityke, wolde not gyue hym other anſwere, but that he knewe hym to be the Deuells eldeſte ſonne. for ſuche feare had the Apoſtels &amp; theyr diſciples, that they wolde not comunicate withe on worde with any that had corruptyd the faith. Fynallie S. Pawle in playne wordes cōmandyth preciſnes,Ephe. 5. ſayinge, Take hede that ye walke preciſlye or exactlye, for ſo the greke worde ſignifieth. Laſt of all, let vs not forget what our Sauiour Chriſt ſaythe: He that is faythfull in the leaſte, wyl be faythfull in the moſte. Who alſo teachith vs, howe faythfully and preciſlye we ſhulde walke, what colde be more preciſly ſpoken of, the law ſhall paſſe vntyll all be fullfyllyd, and he that breakyth one of the leaſte cōmandements, and teachith other ſo to do, ether by worde, or by example, ſhalbe leaſt in the Kyngdome of heauen. Yt is euident by theſe reaſons and examples, that no preciſenes or ſcrupuloſite in godes religion, can be to muche or blame worthie. Towchinge y• ſubſtance, ther is no controuerſy, but yt is lawfull as the good creature of god, and to this purpoſe pertayne thoſe ſayinges: The kyngdome of heauen is nether

meate nor drynke. Meate cōmendith vs not to god. Whatſoeuer enterithe in to the mouth, defylyth not the man. All thinges ar cleane to them that ar cleane▪ &amp; other lyke places of ſcripture, all which they pertayne to the matter or creature &amp; ſubſtance only, not to euery vſe, faſſion, or maner of vſynge. It is to muche doltyſhenes, not to vnderſtand all thynge a ryght, excepte we wyll alſo conclude of the ſame places, that by glotony, dronkenes, whordome, diſquiſyd aparell, and ſuche lyke, the lawe of god is not brokē. garments therfore that ar vrgyd in reſpecte of the forme and vſe, they are not indifferent, and fyrſt of the ende, which they labor ſo muche to proue that it is chaungyd, that thoſe thinges which before were vſyd to ſuperſticiō, now are cōmandyd for order &amp; comlynes. No godly man doubtyth, but the Quenes Maieſte intendinge an other end in commanding of thoſe thinges, then the Papiſtes vſyd them for. But who ſo well conſiderith y• nature of thoſe thinges, ſhall playnely ſe, that the end which the commander propoundyth, dothe not folowe, but accordinge to the diuerſite of them y• vſe them, and them that iudge of them, a cleane cō
               trary end enſuythe, for many popiſhe preſtes

vſe them to the ſame ſuperſticious end that they dyd in Popery, and greateſt of all is y• multitude of ignorant people, that iudgith none otherwyſe of them. All menCor. 8. haue not knowledge, for ſome with conſcience of the Idole, euen yet do eate meate offred to Idoles. So Gedcon made an Ephode, not that y• people ſhulde go a whoryngeJud. 8. after it, yet was it the deſtruction of hym and his howſe for euer. Secondly it can not ſerue for order and comlynes,Cor. 14. which hath in it no neceſſary cauſe of edifying. Let all thinges be donne for edifying. Nether can it be conuertyd to y• comlynes of the Chriſtian Churche, which is the chaſte ſpowſe of Chriſt, which is takē from Antichriſt, and the fylthye whore of Babylon. What cōſent hath Chriſt with Belyall: what porcion hath the faythfull with the infydell: or what agrement hath the temple of God with Images? Yf the reaſon of S. Paule be examynyd, by the2. Cor. 6. which he diſſuadith the Corynthians frō eating of meate offeryd to Idoles, the ſame may be alſo extendyd to garmēts conſecratyd to Idolatry. The nature of cerymonies and rytes is to make the vſer to haue felowſhip with the principall of that religion, as the Jewes of the alter, Chriſtians

with Chriſt, and Gentils with Deuells. As manye as are partakers of the breade which we breake, are partakers of the bodye of Chriſte. They therfore that eate meate offeryd to Idoles, are partakers of deuells. And as many as are baptized haue put on Chriſt: it is not to be fearyd, leaſte as many as weare antychriſtes robes, wil take more yf auctorite comand it, neyther dothe the auctoryte of the Chriſtian Magiſtrat excuſe vs, except we thinke, that Sergius Paulus myght permyteAct. 15. Deut. 12. that S. Paule had forbydden the ſentence of Jamys, which is, that the gentyls ſhulde abſtayne from the polucion of Idoles, God will borowe nothynge of Idoles to garnyſh or become his religion. thou ſhalt not do ſo to the Lorde thy god, but rather he commandyth vtterly to deſtroye theyr alters, woddes, pyllers, and theyr very names. He forbyddyth them alſo to brynge any thinge in to theyr howſes that belongythe to Idoles. Eſaye chap. 30. byddyth thoſe that are earneſtly turnyd to the worſhippe of god, to caſt awaye the reliques of Idolatrie, You ſhall, ſayth he, put outthat is all thing belonging to Idolatry. the couerynge of the Imagis of ſyluer, &amp; the precious veſtymēts of the goldē Imagis, and thou ſhalt caſte them awaye lyke

a menſtrous clowte, and ſaye vnto yt: Auawnte, or get the hence. Fynallye when all godly men abhorre the monstrous apparell of Fryers, Monkes, Chanons, I can not ſe, by what order they ſhulde exteme the ornaments of Popiſhe Preaſtes, whoſe order is as wyckyd as Freyers, Monkes, or any other, which thyng may be ſayd of the reſte of the Popiſhe ceremonies, which may all with lyke precepte and coloure, &amp; by as good reaſon be receuid in the Churches as thoſe. But admyttinge that theſe thynges were neuer ſo indifferent, yet it can not be that we ſhulde thynke them lawfull, for vs to vſe them: for euē thoſe thinges, which by them ſealues are lawfull, whē an other circumſtance is ioynyd to them, then become they vnlawfull for a Chriſtian to vſe them, as in theſe caſes. Firſt we can not caſt of all doubtfulnes, hauing ſo many reaſons on our ſyde, and ſo manye examples bothe of learnyd men, and beſt reformyd Churches, but in all thinges moſt indifferent. Saint Paule chargith euery mā to be certanly perſuadyd in his owne mynde, which ſome men vntruly tranſlate, Let euery man abownde in his owne ſence, for he that with doubt of conſcience eatyth, which of it ſealfe is

lawfull, is condemnyd, becauſe he doth it not of fayth. Now the aſſurance of fayth muſte be ſought no where, but in Gods worde. Secondlye, thowghe we ſhulde ſatiſfye our conſciences, yet this man is defylid, which is not perſuadid by Gods worde, but encreaſed by our examples, that he dare do that, whereof before he doubted, and this is to giue an offence, as they cō
               monly call it to anger them, for they that are beſt pleaſyd with theſe matters, are moſt offendyd that they ſtomble and falle, we muſt not do what ſo euer is lawfull, but what ſo euer alſo is profytable to edifying: nether muſt we only regarde what lyberte permyttyth, but rather what our brothers proffyt requiryth. Thyrdlye, we maye not altogether neclecte what infydells iudge of vs in the vſynge of thinges lawfull by them ſealfes, and therefore S. Paule byddeth them that are callyd to the feaſtes of the gentyls, ſo ſone as mencyon is made of meate offeryd to Idoles, to abſtayne from eatinge of it, becauſe of hym that tolde of it, and his conſcience, not of hym ſealfe, but of an other. What the Papiſtes iudge of vs, maye caſely be ſeene by this, yt Harding for the retayning of thoſe Popiſhe cerymonies, cōteynith hope that

popery ſhalbe reſtoryd: what the ignorant people iudge of the reamnants of papiſtri retaynyd, wyſe men may well conſyder. Herunto might haue byne ioynid the ſentences of olde Doctors, Juſtinus, Jreneus, Tertullianus, Aguſtyne, Ambros, Chryſoſtums, Celeſtinus, &amp; almoſt all the reſt, for abhorrynge the cuſtomes and ryghtes of the Jewes and gentyles and heritykes, but Gods truthe nedyth not mans auctoryte, except they that be againſt vs, in this cauſe wyll appeale to the fathers, thē ſhall they perceyue, that in nomber both of Doctors, and ſentences, we ſhall be nothinge inferior to them. In the meane tyme this maye ſuffyce, to ſhew fyrſt that the precyſians is blameles, ſecondly the garmētes ar not indifferent, &amp; thyrdly that thowghe they were indifferent yet ther is ſufficient reaſon at this tyme, why we ſhoulde not weare them. Come Lord Jeſus, and make an ende of thys wyckyd wordle, that thy ſainctes may come to gether, that we may ſynge with the in thy holy hyll for euer. He that ouercomith ſhalbe crownyd. Pray, pray, as the Apoſtell Peter ſayth: the end of all thinges is at hand.
         
         
            
            ¶ An Anſwere to a queſtion, that was mouyd, whi the godly men wold not weare a ſurples.
            ALthoughe we muſte nedes confeſſe,Anſwere. that we haue to much conſentyd heretofore with the Papiſte in robbing and bereuinge God of his glory &amp; honor, yet may we not now in the lyght of Gods truthe contynew a partaker with you in the adulteracion of Chriſtes ſacramentes, cōtrary to our conſciences &amp; knowledge, wherein we iudge our ſealues onlye, not preiudiſynge other mens doinge, whō we leaue to God, before whō they ether ſtand or falle. For oure partes we muſt render accompte, not obſtinatly bent againſt any thing y• ſhalbe approuyd by Gods worde.
            We are perſuadyd, that we may not vſeMaios. any thinge repugnant to Chriſtian lyberte, nor mayntayne an opinion of holynes wher none is, whiche were Ipocriſy, nor conſent to Idolatri, which were denyall of the truthe, or diſcorage the godly, incoragynge the wyckyd, nor diſtroying y• Churche of Chriſt, which are bownde to edifye, nor conſent vnto confuſion, wher God requiryth order, nor ſhew diſobedience, wher God requiryth to obeye.
            
               But in vſynge of a ſurples, we ſhuldeMinor. do that which is repngnaunt to Chriſtian lybertie, maintaine an opinion of holines, where none is, ſhew conſent to Idolatry, deny the truthe, dyſcorage the godly, and incorage the wyckyd or vngodly, conſent to confuſion and ſhew diſobedience, wher God commandithe to obeye.
            
               CōcluſionWe may not with good conſcience, as we are perſuadyd weare a ſurples.
            The Maior is prouyd by Saynt Paule Gal. 5. who commandyth to Chriſtian libertie, by the example of Chriſt Matt. 15. who wold not haue his diſciples to maintaynenote the example of good men. an opinion of holynes, whiche the Jewes had in waſſhyng of handes: by the doctryne of Pawle. 2. Cor. 6. who wyll haue no agremēt with the temple of God and the Idoles: by the example of Danyel. 6. who openid his wyndowe towardes Jeruſalem, leſt he myght ſeame to denye his profeſſion or conſent with ye wychyd: by the example of Paule Gal. 2. who reprouyd Peter for the diſcoragyng of the godly gentiles, and incoraging of the froward Jewes: by the doctryne of the ſame Apoſtell. 2. Cor. 13. where he teachith that Mynyſters haue power to edifye, not to deſtroye: by the example of Patriarkes,

and Prophetes, which in the worſhipping of God, wear by no meanes confowndyd withe the Idolators: by the doctryne of Peter and John actes, which affyrmithe to be more ryght to obey God, then men. But for more euident profe herof, we may let you ſe ſome practiſes of auncient Fathers. Tertulian in his boke De coronamilitis, lykythe them vnto dom̄e Idolls, ſuche as do vſe any thinge accordynge to the ornament of Idolles: and further, yf to leane apon an Idoll, is ſtrange from the fayth, what ſhall ſeame apon the habytefaſtyng is good, yet the godly wold not vſe it that day as the h
                     ••
                   ytyk dyd. of an Idoll. Auguſtyne ad Caſulanum, warnythe not to faſte on the Sondaye, leaſt therby conſente might be ſhewyd to the wyckyd Maniches. They that weare any thinge after the maner of Idoles, and yf it be ſtrange from fayth to leane apon an Idoll, what is it to weare the habyt of an Idoll. The fourth Counſell of Toletane Canon. 5. for auoydynge of conſent with Herytyckes, decreed that once dyppynge ſhulde be vſyd in Baptyſme. A Papiſt of our tyme affyrmith that the Apoſtels to auoyde conſent to Judaiſme, abolyſſhed the Sabothe daye, and ſanctyfyed the daye of the Lorde. The great Clarke Orygen, as Epiphanius wrytith in his. 2.

boke. 1. Tome, caryed palme withe thouBeware of decemblyng. that offeryd to the Image Serapis, allthoughe he proteſtyd openly, that he dyd offer vnto Chriſt, and not vnto Serapis, yet was he excomunycatyd, and caſt out of the Church by the Marters and Confeſſors whiche then were at Athens. The Chriſtian ſowdiars which by Julian ſultelteBeware of deceytfull practyſes. were browght to offer incens, as it is wryten Hiſtoria Tripartita lib. 6. chap. 30. when they perceuyd theyr faute, whiche vnwares they had commytted in conſentyng to Idolatri, they rane forthe into the ſtreats profeſſede theyr relygion, teſtifyed them ſealues to be Chriſtians, affyrmyng that theyr handes only had cōſentyd vnto Paganiſme, and that theyr hartes dyd nothyngthe nature of true Chriſtian. agre thervnto, and whereas theyr handes had offendyd vnaduyſydlye, they wyſhyd to beſtowe theyr whole bodyes to be tormentyd for Chriſt, althoughe wyth tormentes and paynes moſte creuell and horyble. I truſt we nede not to laboure any further for the profe. By the vſe of the ſurples men are iniciat in to ye Popes clergye, as it aperith by ye Pontifycall, De clerico faciendo. Yf y• Galathians by circumciſion rather loſte theyr lyberte in Chriſt, then profytyd any thynge, by iniciatinge

them ſealues in to Judaiſme. How maye you retayne the lyberte in Chriſt, and profyt in his religion by wearinge the Popes lyuerye, we can not perceaue? But by the vſe of the ſurples, is mayntaynyd an Ipocritycall opinion of holynes, ye Pontificall termithe it Habitum ſancte religionis, the habyt of an holy religion. Durand lib. 3. de rationale diuinorum, ſaythe, That it is Deſtis linea, the lynyne garment, in which they that ſerue about the ſeruices of the alter and holy thinges, ought to vſe apon theyr clothes, a ſurples, it is for the whitnes of it, or it ſignifieth the puryte or chaſtete, accordinge to that ſayinge: Let your garments, that is, your workes, be whiteMarke What lying ſignes is in the ſurples inuentyd by Papiſtes. at all tymes, that is cleane: but for his name, it figurith the mortificacion of the fleſhe. It is callyd a Surples, becauſe that in the olde tyme they dyd weare it apon ſhynny coates, made of the ſkynnes of the deade, whiche is vſyd to this daye in certayne Churches, repreſentynge that Adame, after he had ſynnyd, was clothedWith what good conſcience can the godly Weare yt, iudge good Brother. with ſuche garments. Thyrdly, it notith Innocenci, and therfore it is put on before all other holye veſtures, becauſe that they that are deputyd to worſhippynge, ought to excell in lyfe and in all vertues, accordyng

to the ſayinge of the pſalme: Innocencies do ryghtly 
                  •
               l
                  •
               ue vnto me. Fourthely, for the bredthe of it, it betokenythe Charite, wherefore they are worne apon prophane and cōmon veſtures, it is to be markyd that charite coueryth the multitude of ſynnes. Fyftlye, for the faſſyon of it, in that is it made lyke a Croſſe, or Jewes gallows, it fygurythe the paſſion of the Lord, and they y• weare, that ought to be creweyfyed with the vices and concupiſcences. In mayntayninge this opinion of holynes, with all other muēcions, which by lyinge ſeignes, which they haue had to it, we knowe not howe to auoyde conſent vnto that Idolatri, which Durant and the Papiſte mayntayne and profeſſe, &amp; to deny the Popes cerimonies, the doctryne whiche we teache, howe ſhuld it not dyſcorage the godly, and incorage the ſuperſticious in theyr errors: we can not edefye the Church of Chriſt apparentlye, ſhewinge our ſealues to be on of the Popes clergye. Seing S. Paull Theſſ. 3. willythe to auoyde all apparens of euyll, and to be ſhufflyd in a ſurples, whiche the Popes clergye wear, were rather a confuſion then an order, whiche they them ſealues wolde be lothe to ſuffer, if they might get

agayne the keys into theyr handes, they wolde crye withe open mowthe, as theyr pontificall teache them, &amp; plucke the ſurplesThe ſurples is an holy garmēt of the Papiſtes. of our backes by the autoryte of almyghtie God the Father, the Sonne, and the Holyghoſte. ſaying, and we take from the all our clerkly habyt, and we put on ye apparell of religion, and depoſe, degrade, and ſpoyle the of all orders clerkely benefice,Marke the follye of Papiſtes. and clerkelye lyuinge, and we reſtore the to the ſeruitude and ignominie of the ſecular habyte. Is it not a diſorder, that Chriſtians ſhoulde ſhewe them ſelues ſlaues to the Popes order? were it not better to ſerue God in commun attyre, then to pleaſe the Pope by diſquiſinge our ſelues in ſuperſticious ſurpleſſis: were it not better to obey God, who wyllyth vs to ſerue hym in ſpret, and in truthe, then to obey men, followyng the deuyſe of Pope Sylueſter, the faſſyon of the Jewes, and practyſe of the Papiſtes: where it not better, by leauynge of a Surples to folow Chriſt in breakynge mens tradicions, thē by the vſe therof to be a companion of Popes &amp; Phariſes? Yf this do not ſeame ſufficient to proue the Minor at this tyme, it ſhalbe more at large dyſcourſyd hereafter. Concernyng ye Quenes Maieſtes commandement,

herein we acknowledge our ſealues bownde to obey in all thynges lawfullye commaundyd, ſo can not we be perſuadyd to vſe that in the minyſteri, which our conſciences teacheth vs to be repleniſhed with Idolatrous Ipocriſye, &amp; alſo the example of other men which dothe were it, ought nothing at all to moue vs to were a ſurples in the minyſterie, no more then to conſent with them in perſecutyng thoſe men whom they terme ſedicious ſciſmatyckes for leauyng them of. Thus as ye ſe, ſhortlye dere Brethren, we leue the ſurples, as the Popes badge to the ſhauen Clergye, and you as Gods choſen to the protection of the almyghtie whyſſhynge, that God may geue vs grace aswell inwardelye as outwardlye, to ſeke for ſyncerite, and to wayght with all pacience the good wyll &amp; pleaſure of the almyghtye, who wyll &amp; can healpe when pleaſith hym. Fare ye well in the Lorde Jeſus.
         
         
            
            ¶ A Godly Prayer.
            OH Lord God and heauenly Father, which art a iuſt Judge to puniſhe all them, that do contynewe to offende the, as thou art a Father moſt pytyfull to receaue to mercy all thoſe, whiche geue ouer themſelues to pleaſe the, ſhewe me thy grace and fauour, ſo that I may be truly touchid withe inward diſpleaſure of my ſynnes; and that in the place of flattering my ſelf to ſlepe in ſynne, I may be ſo caſt downe in hart, that the rather I may truly with mouthe confeſſe moſt humbly to geue the, the honour, glory, and prayſe, dew vnto thy holy name, and that as thou of thy greate mercy doſte inſtruct vs therevnto by thy holy word, ſo (for thy names ſake) make that ye ſame may ſo lighten and cleare our conſcience, that in dew examination of all our hole lyſte, we may truly learne to be angry &amp; diſpleaſid with all our former, and corrupte lyning. Oh that it may pleaſe the to drawe nere vnto vs, in addreſſyng and guydyng our footſteppes in the true and perfect may of obedyence to thy holy lawes and cōmaundementes. Send thy holye Angel to pitche his tentes round about us, that Sathan &amp;

               
                  •
               is internall army, neuer preuayſe againſt vs, but allways with ſtrong faith we may thorough Jeſus Chriſt withſtand all his crafty engins and ſnares, knowynge vndoubtedly that thou neuer forſakeſt them that put their truſt in the. Oh let vs not be led by the infirmytie of our vntowarde fleſhe, but ſtrenghten vs by the vertue of the holy ſpiryte. Suffer vs not to lye vnder thy heuy wrathe &amp; vengeaunce throughe I pocryſye, but rather touche vs ſo inwardly, that we may without ceaſyng, ſyghe, and grone vnto the, by true and vnfayned repentaunce. And althoughe we be not allwayes ſo wel diſpoſyd to aſke &amp; praye, as we ought to do, yet (good Lord) for thy names ſake, ſtretche out thy mightie hande, that by the gratious workyng of thy holy Spirite, our myndes and hartes may be drawen from all erthly and corruptible thinges, ſo that our prayers may procede of an erneſt and inward affection, ſo that we neuer preſume to cōme before y• with a dobell hart, knowing that whoſoeuer aſkethe and prayeth for anye thing of the, not aſking in faith, can not obteyne. Increace our faithe therfore (oh mercyfull Father) that we preſently may lyuely feele the benefit of remiſſion and pardon

of all our ſynnes, thoroughe the merytes and death of Chriſt Jeſus our Sauiour, and ſo work in vs foreuer hereafter to lyue in thy feare, and to ſtand in awe of thy diſpleaſure, that thou mayſt contynew our mercyfull Father world without end. God graunt yt.
         
      
   

