
   
      
         
            To my louynge brethren that is troublyd abowt the popishe aparrell, two short and comfortable epistels. Be ye constant: for the Lorde shall fyght for yow, yowrs in Christ
         
         
            
               1566
            
         
         Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00277
            STC 10390
            ESTC S111875
            99847135
            99847135
            12155
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00277)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12155)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:32)
         
         
            
               
                  To my louynge brethren that is troublyd abowt the popishe aparrell, two short and comfortable epistels. Be ye constant: for the Lorde shall fyght for yow, yowrs in Christ
                  Gilby, Anthony, ca. 1510-1585.
                  Pilkington, James, 1520?-1576.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  E. van der Erve,
                  [Emden :
                  1566]
               
               
                  The first epistle is by Anthony Gilby and the second epistle is by James Pilkington. Register is continuous.
                  Imprint from STC.
                  First epistle (Gilby's) begins on leaf A2 recto; salutation reads: To all my faithful brethren in Christ Ieusu and to all other that labour to weade out the wedes of popery ..
                  Second epistle (Pilkington's) begins on leaf C1 recto: salutation reads: Grace and peace with all maner spiritual feling and liuing worthi of the kindnes of Christ, be with all that thrist the will of God ..
                  Another version of Gilby's epistle catalogued as STC 11888.
                  The copy catlaogued is bound with STC 10389 and STC 10391.
                  Signatures: A-C⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church vestments --  England --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            To my louynge brethren
that is troublyd abowt the popishe
aparrell, two short and
comfortable Epistels.
            Be ye constant: for the Lorde
shall fyght for yow,
yowrs in Christ.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ¶To all my faithful brethren in Christ Jesu
and to all other that labour to weade out
the wedes of popery, Peace in the Lorde
Jesu be with you, and make you perfite in
all good workes to doe his will, working
in you that which is pleasant in his sight,
through Jesus Christ our Lord.
            DEare Brethren, because we are creatid
for gods glory the edification one
of another in Christ, and are bounde
to serue thervnto by wealthe or woo, lyfe or
death, and cheifly, they to whom God haue
geuen the greter gyftes, and whom he hath
callyd to higher romes, are moste bounde to
be zelous for gods glory with godly zelousie
to profyt the churche and sponse of Christe
vnder their charge, and that by no subteltye
as the Apostel warnithe, they shulde be corrupted
from the symplicitie of Christ: therfore
there is no doubt of your good zealle
and diligence. My good fathers &amp; deare brethren,
who ar first callid to the battel, to striue
for gods glory and the edification of his
people, against the Romish reliques and rages
of Antichrist, I doubt not but that you
wyl coragiouslye and constantlye in Christ,
rape at these rages of Gods enemyes, and
that you will by this occasion race vp many
as grete enormites that we all know, &amp; labore
to race out all the dregges &amp; remnants of

transformid popery, that are crept into England,
by to much lenite of them that wylbe
namid the Lordes of the cleargie: what is he
that hath the zeale of gods glory before his
face, that wyl not ioyne both in prayer, and
in sufferinge with you, in so good a cause,
that is so much for gods glory, and the edification
of gods church, in the pure simplicite
of Christes word &amp; sacramentes, wherin
our enemies and persecutours are strangely
bewitchid. I wote not by what Circes cupe,
that they do make suche a diuersite betwixt
Christes worde &amp; his sacramentes, that they
can not thinke the worde of God safelye ynoughe
preachid, &amp; honorably inough handlyd,
without cap, cope, surplis. But that the
sacraments the maryinge, the buryinge, the
churching of wemen, &amp; other church seruice,
as they call it, muste nedes be decored with
crossinge, with capping, wt surplessing, with
knelinge, with preti wafer cakes, and other
knackes of poperi. O Paule that thou were
a lyue, thou durst tell those politike gentelmen,
that ther hath bin to much laboure bestoued
vpon them in vaine, thou durste say
vnto them, as thou didest to ye Corinthians,
that they eat not the Lordes supper, but pley
a pagent of their owne to blynde the people,
and kepe them still in supersticion, fare from
the symplicite of Christes supper: but howe

many sely sowles is ther that dothe beleue
veryly, that they haue an English masse, and
so put no difference betwene truth &amp; falshod,
betwene Christ and antichrist, betwene God
and the deuell, they are strangely bewitched.
I say that thus wyll bynde theyr Englyshe
presthode &amp; sacraments, but muche more enchauntid
that can fynd no garments to please
them. But such as haue ben polutid openly
with popishe supersticion &amp; Idolatry, but
most of all in this point shall theyr madnes
apere to all posterites, that they make these
Antichristian rages Causam sine qua non, that
is, a cause without which ther is no holy ministery
in Christ, so that this shall make an
Englyshe preste, be he neuer suche a dolt or
vnlearnid in the knouledge of the scripture
as we haue very manye, and without these
romisshe reliques not Paule hym selfe shalbe
admittid (as one of them dyd blaspheme
&amp; the rest of them in effecte do affirme) well
agaynste suche popishe chaffer and popery,
hathe byne longe agone foughten witheall,
when the gret captaines of that religion lyuyd,
and yet God gaue the victory. Therfor
let vs not fear now, although it doth begine
to sture agayn, for ther is no craft, conninge,
counsell, wysdom, or policy against the Lord.
We haue Christ &amp; hys Apostells &amp; the Prophetes
euer stryuing agaynst the Ipocrites

of their time o
                  •
                our 
                  •
               yde. a strau for popishe
polici we haue the worde of God to warant
vs, to rote out al monuments of supersticion
and Idolatry, &amp; are charged to abhor them,
to accompt them, accursed, and to defy them,
and to detest them as menstreous clowtes,
they haue not the worde of God for them.
And what wysdom is in them, sayth god by
his Prophet Jeremi, they talke of obedience
&amp; concorde, but ther is no obedience against
the Lorde, no nor concorde to be desired, but
wher gods glory and verite is preserued, Els
better to haue al the worlde in hurly burleis,
and heauen &amp; earth to shake, then one ioyte
of gods glory shulde decaie. So far forth as
in vs leithe, we haue theyr owne lawes and
proclamacions, to rote out all monuments
of supersticion and Idolatrye, &amp; theyr oune
wordes are contrarye to theyr doinges. Yt
shulde apere that they repent their reformacion
proclamid, as did ye Isralites, they buylde
agayn that which ons they haue distroied
and this is doue openlye that all the worlde
may wonder, and behold: but what is done
secretlye, god wyll one daye haue it declarid
openly, ye they make the name of god &amp; this
doctrine that we professe to be euell spoken
of alredy. By many of theyr doinges, theyr
iudgement hasteth that for such causes persecute
Gods true preachers. Wherfore let vs

               
                  •
               ot feare theyr threteninges, ther can none

                  •
               ersecute the godly for this cause &amp; trasshe.

                  •
               ut ether such as are nether hote nor colde,

                  •
               nd then they shalbe vomyted out vnlesse

                  •
               heir zeale encrease, or such as haue no God
before their eies, whose god is their bellie, or

                  •
               ls open papists, whom god hathe geuen vp

                  •
               o a reprobate sense, wherfore we must thus
take it, that they ar gods rodds for oure sinnes,
because we haue not ben more zelous in
Gods cause, nether carefull to seke his glorye,
that wolfe Wynchester &amp; blodie bucher
Bonar fought once against many godli men
for the grounde of this gere, and thei had all
the power of the Realme seruinge theyr lustes,
but beholde how the Lorde in short time
ouerthrew them al, to giue vs coradge to go
forwarde, the Lord forgeue vs, we ar to slacke
and neglygent in heauenly thynges, this
monster Bonar remainithe and is fed as papists
say, for their sakes, &amp; it must be grauntyd,
it is for some purpos, althoughe he be a
traytor and an enemi to the crowne and realme,
and bothe to God and man, whiche
brunnid godes holy testament, murderid his
saintes and his servātes. But what the Lord
requyrith to be done wythe false Prophetes
it is manyfest: we haue bothe the lawe of
god &amp; man for vs, But we ar answerid nay,
you your sealues shalbe compellid to turne

your coates and cappes, and get you into
his leueris, and to be lyke him in your garments.
O Elyas that thou lyuedste, or tha
                  •
               
thy spyrit weare amongst vs, thou woldes
                  •
               
say with the Prophet Sophoni, that God
will vysit the werears of this Idolatours
garmentes or strange aparell, thou woldest
say, that thinges dedicatid once to idolatry,
is not indifferent, thou woldest say reuerence
to the sacramēt is wrought by doctrine and
discipline, and not by popisshe &amp; Idolatours
garments, thou woldest saye, what decency
can ther be gaynyd to the sacramēts, by that
which hath byn deuisyd &amp; vsyd to deface it, if
the golde ordeinyd by god for the reuerence
and decenci of the Jewes temple, is not to be
admittyd to beutify the churche of Christe,
much lesse copes brought in by papistes the
enemyes of god, and alwayes continwyd in
their seruice as ornamētes of their religion
in no wyse ought of vs Christians to be retaynid.
But the papistes triumphe and glori
in their assembles, that the hote gospelars
shalbe driuen to their doltishe attires, for the
Lords sake let vs neuer giue them any cause
of Joye, thoughe we shoulde dye for yt:
Moyses wold not yelde on hoofe of a beste
in gods busines, he wolde not leue the loupe
vnmade, nor make a button or a claspe
more or lesse. Eleasar will not decemble by

eatynge of vnlawfull meates, the faythfull
Isralites wolde not receyue so muche as an
yuibushe. Contrariwyse Orygen caryinge
a braunche and professynge, that he bare it
for Christ at the first. But was afterwarde
compellid to open Idolatry, so cursid a thing
it is to geue any place to the wicked: all the
papistes that saye, they worship Christ in the
crosse, and God in the sacrament, do still vnder
these wordes continew still in their Idolatri,
beware of deceitfull wordes, that couer
wickid purposes, to drawe vs from Christiā
symplicite. Let vs stand constantly agaynste
all abuses, and repent for our former coldnes
in religion, and our synnes, and call for
healpe from aboue, for the hand of the Lorde
is not shortenid: we ar assured that we seke
Gods glory, and our aduersaries may see, yf
they can se any thinge, that this thinge that
they seke is not for gods glory, seing the papistes
the enemyes of God, doe so desyre yt
and glory in yt. And reioyse, that we, whom
they most hate, cannot be safe but vnder their
garments: we ar assurid that we seke godes
glory in folowinge Christ his Aposteles and
Prophets. who euer dispised these pharisaicall
outward faces and visures, Christe fyndethe
fault withe the garmentes of the phariseis.
Paule counteth all his pharisaicall,

shew to be donge. Zachari saithe, that the
false Prophet shalbe ashamed of his prophecye,
and forsake his garments wherin he dereyuid.
&amp; shal the true Prophetes be fayne to
crepe into their coules? for by the same autorite
may be comaundid any peace of popery,
so that it be namyd policie. Ezechias and
Josias knew no suche aucthoritie, but they
say: It is for policie, For it plainly apearithe
that ther is lesse care for religion, then for
policie. But beware that the example of Jeroboham
be not folowed, that made such like
prestes for policie as wolde do as he commaundid
them. Achaz of policie brought the
fashion of an alter into Jerusalem, as he sawe
at Damascus, where he had ouercome the
Idolatours and their Idolls, but cursed was
his policie, and so ar all they that wil retaine
any thinge of their Idolatrie. Nabuchodonosors
Idoll was for vnitye and policie,
but without the warraunt of gods worde,
ther is neyther good vnitye nor police. The
godlie father Bucer callithe the tenthes and
the first fruites sacriledge and roberie, they
be kept stil for policie. Crosse and candelstickes
ar supersticious, though they be kepte.
I wot not for what policie the adoration of
the Sacrament in the countres, where they
knocke and knele to a wafer take is a popishe

policie. That wemen baptise, that pluralites,
tot quots impropriacions, non residence,
despensacions, suspensions, excomunications,
&amp; absolucions, for money at grauntyd,
yt is evell, like as are many other inormites
borowed from Rome, which remayne in the
name of policie. All these thinges were abhorryd
as popishe supersticious, and Idolatries,
amonge our gospellers both bishops &amp;
others, when they were vnder gods roddes
in pouerte. But how thei now haue learnid
courtely deuinite, to grounde all apon policie?
Humble them agayne o Lorde, that they
do not forget the, and thy great kindnes and
mercie shewid apon them, and sture vp their
hartes and myndes, that they may be carefull
ouer thy pore flocke. O Christe, whom
thou hast dearly bought, by this theyr policy
at blindid, &amp; carithe for no more, but that
thei may haue this supersticious shew which
is so stifely maintained. Let him mumble as
he liste, yf he be thus apparelid, al his seruice
is well ynough, otherwyse yt is nothing
worthe, Thus cause you them to perishe by
your polices, for whome Christ hathe dyed.
further more, yf poperi be superstitious and
idolatrous, evel and wicked, as yet ther was
neuer a worse thinge in the worlde, then ar
we commaunded to absteine from all participatio
                  •
               
               
thero
                  •
               , and from all the shewe therof
ab omni specie mali, that is, from all shewe of
wickidnes. These garments were the shewe
of their blasphemous preisthod, herein they
dyd singe and saye their supersticious idolatrous
seruice, they dyd sence their Idolls and
healpe forwarde theyr Idolatrous masses,
what policie can it be then to weare this gere.
But a supersticious wickid and popishe
policie, they doe it for policie, they saye, that
their priestes may be knowen and magnified
of men. Dyd not the Pharisies vse the same
policie, to doe all their workes and make
all their garmentes bothe Philacteris vpon
their headdes, and their wide and syde robes
and borders, that they might be more expectable,
and notorious to the people: but their
woo is thretenid aboue al other sinners. To
suche ypocrites, as beinge voyde of all true
holynes, delite in all outward shewes, theyr
curse is most inculcate, their polyci is that
ye preistes shall weare white in the churches
to signify their vertue▪ their purenes, and holines.
and when they go fourth of the church
they must weare blacke gownes and blacke
hornes, for cōtrary polycies, and for dyuers
significations, Our master Christes polycie
was expressyd in one worde, fede, fede, fede.
and the Prophetes before, and the Apostelles

afterwarde, yf Christe be the wysdome
of the father, the true ministers shalbe well
inough knowen, by that one marke which
he geueth: and yf that he haue not that marke
better vnknowen then knowen, both for
him selfe and others, therfore lett them not
saye for shame, that they seeke gods glorie,
Christes wil, or the edification of his church,
by their polycie. Whyles they thretē &amp; stope
the spredinge of gods worde and fedinge of
Christes flocke, cōmandyd by writing to excōmunicate
the most faithful laborers in the
planting of the gospell, because thei will not
weare the rages of popery, to expulse ye most
valiant soldiars agaynst the Romishe Antichrist,
the most earnest ouerthrowars of the
kyngdom of satan, which standith in sin and
blindnes. O beware you, that wilbe Lordes
ouer the flockes, that you be not sore punyshed
for your pryde, towardes your brethren,
and your cowardlines in gods cause, that for
Princes pleasures and pompose liuinges, do
turne poperi into policie, and to become our
persecutors vnder the cloke of policie: it were
better to lose your liuings, then to displease
god in persecutinge of youre brethren, &amp;
hinder the course of the worde. But as oure
deutie is, we wyll praye for you, and for all
our brethren in the ministeri, that god of his

grace would graunte vs more zeale for his
glorie, than any of vs hathe had heretofore,
more desire to edifie, Christes people in pure
simplicite, to present them a chast virgin vnto
Christ, then hitherto hathe apeared, that
when the hedeshepherde shall cal to accounte,
we be not ashamyd. But beinge founde
perfecte in all good workes, may receiue the
crowne prepared, as for you deare brethren
whome God hath callyd into the brunte of
the batell, The Lorde kepe ye constant, that
ye yelde nether to tolleracion, nether to anye
other subtelte persuasions of dispensacions,
or lycences which were to fortifie their Romishe
practises. but as you fyght the Lords
fyght, be valiant. God will not leue you, nether
forsake you, as you seke gods glorye,
god wyll glorifye you, and as by you Christes
church is edifyed, comfortid and confirmid
in Christian simplycite, so shall you receyue
comfort by Christe your heede captaine,
when you shalbe callyd to geue acomptes
of your stewardshippes, and to be rewardyd
for your fidelite, the matter is not so smalle
as the worlde do take yt, yt wyll appeare before
all be endyd, what an harde thinge it is,
to cut of the rages of the Hidra of Rome, it
is beutifull, but poysonful, ther is no daling
with such a mounster, beware of lokyng backe

to Sodome or delyght anye witte in the
garments of Babilone, neyther once touche
the poysonid cupe, though yt be of golde or
gliteringe. Let vs repent of our former synnes
vnfaynidlye, and then shall we abhor and
stamp vnder our fette these rages, that were
apoyntid to supersticion and idolatry, Let vs
hate the blasphemous preasthode, so iniurious
to Christes preisthode, that euery pache
and token of it be in execration, detestation,
and accursed, and take no parte of yt vpon
our heddes nor backes, least we be accursed
as it is. Let vs not make the heritage of god
as a byrde of many colours, holdinge of diners
religions, Let vs not mixte the Jewes
with the gentills, let vs not in no wise mixt
this our religion with any thinge of Antichrist,
let vs not confyrme the blinde in their
blindnes, neyther the weacke in their supersticion.
But rather let vs take awaye, if we
can, the names, memories, and all monumēts
of poperye and that Antichristes priesthod.
Let vs open our wyndous with Daniel, and
professe what we at: their cruelte shalbe our
glorie. Let vs followe Paull, that knew that
the truthe gospel cold not be retainyd, if any
Jewishe cerimonies were mayntainyd. Lett
vs rather neuer weare anye garment, then
we should weare those, wherby our brethren

shulde be weakened, offendyd or boldenyd to
take parte with the idolatours, &amp; so through
our hautines in knouledge, oure weake brethren
perishe, for whom Christ died. Behold
and marke well, how they falle backwarde
that yelde in anye iote, and se how they are
edifyed, and increase in godlines, which holde
that ryght waye that you goe in, the which
the Lorde increase you, &amp; vs all, and strenthen
vs with his holy spyrit, that we may continewe
to oure lyues ende, al wayes
both by our thoughtes, wordes,
and workes, to avaunce his
glorye and honor dayly
more and more, now
and for euer.
            Amen.
         
         
            
            ¶Grace and peace with all maner spiritual
feling and liuing worthi of
the kindnes of Christ, be with
all that thrist the will
of God.
            TO my faythfull and deare brethren in
Christ Jesu, as in comen daungers of
fier, or suche lyke, welbelouyd, they
that be fare of, com to socoure those that haue
nede, so I beinge out of iepordie and far
of,tru Christian loue▪
                can not but of deuty wyshe well to those
that be touchyd about the popishe apparell
in thys libertye of Gods truthe, whyche is
tought plainely without offencis, in ye greatyst
misterys of our religion and saluacion,
yt is much to be marvayled, that this small
controuersye of aparell should be so heuely
taken.the practi
                     ••
                   of the wickid. But this is the mallis of satan, that
wher he can not ouerthrow the greatist matters,
he will cause great troubels in trifels.
Peter and Paule agreyde in the greatyste
articles of our saluacion, and yet they differyd
so about meattes, that Paule withstode
and rebuckid hym openly.the infirmites of the godly▪
                Paule and Barnabas
fell at suche bytter contention, whether
Marke shuld go with them or no, that
they partyd companyes, and eyther of them
went sondry waies. God defend vs from the
lyke.the constance of the godl
                     •
                  
                Paule circumcisyd Timothe when ther

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
was hope to wine the Jewes: but when they
wold haue it of necessite, he would not circumcise
Titus, therfore compellinge would
not be vsyd in thinges of liberte, yt is a lamētable
case, that among them that are civil
&amp; full of knouledge, that yt shuld come thus
to passe. Consyder dearly belouyd, I besech
you; how that all countres, whiche haue reformid
religion, haue cast away the popishe
aparell with the pope: and yet we that wyll
be taken for the best gospelars, are contentid
to kepe it as an holie religion. Marke well
also how many godly and learnid ministers
ther be here in all countres, that be so zelous
not onlie to forsake the wickyd doctrine of
poperie, ready to leue the minystry, &amp; to lose
lyuinges, rather then to be lyke the popishe
teachers of supersticious order in aparell or
behaviour. This realme hath such skacite of
teachers, that yf so many worthye men and
learnid shuld be cast out of the ministrie for
suche small matters, many placis shulde be
destitude of preachers, &amp; yt wold geue an incurable
offence to all the fauourars of gods
truthe here, and in other countres, also shall
we make so much and so precious of the popes
rages that other reformyd places, exteme
as vyle &amp; filthye, God forbid. S. Paule
byddith wemen vse suche aparell as becomith

them that profes true godlines, which
rule is muche more to be obseruid of men, &amp;
especiallye of preachers. But yf we forsake
popery as wickid, shall we say that their aparell
becommith saintes, and professars of
tru holines. Saint Paule bydith vs refraine
from al outward shew of evell, but surely in
kepinge of this popishe aparell, we forbear
not an outwarde shew of much euell, yf popery
be iudgid evell, as greter wickidnes can
not be, as we wolde haue a diuers shewe of
aparel to be knowē from the comon people,
so is yt necessary in aparell, to haue a shew,
howe a protestate is to be knowen from a
papiste. Yt hathe pleasyd God to call vs to
preache his heuenly worde to that hye office,
God geue you grace and vs all to seke hys
honor &amp; glorie: yf we so do with a pure hart
and mynde, he hath promysed, He that honorith
me, I will glorify him, and he that contemnith
me, I wyll contemne him. Let ther
be no curtisye made to healpe gods people
now they be in danger. Call to your remembraunce
Quene Easter, she begane to make
curtisy to speke in yt cause, but Mardocheus
sayd vnto her: Yf thou now hold thy peace,
God shall delyuer by an other meane, &amp; yet
thou &amp; thy fathers house shall peryshe. You
that can and may do good, do it whyle tyme

is offerid, the tyme will come when it wylbe
to late: yet god wyll comfort his by some other
meane: It ys a perilous thinge, not to
healpe in the tyme of neade, &amp; not to suffer
religion to goe forward in all syncerite, and
to further gods cause when ye maye, when
Terenti a good Christian captaine returnid
with great triumphe &amp; victory, the Emperor
Valerius bade him axe what he wold. and he
shuld haue it for his good seruice: he hauing
God before his eyes, desyryd nether ryches,
nether honor, but those which had aduentered
their liues for true religion, might haue
a church alowid them, to serue their god purely
in, &amp; seueral from the Arrians. The Emperour
beyng angrie with his request, pullyd
his supplicacion in pecis, and bade him
axe som other thing. but he gathered vp the
pecis of his, paper and sayd: I haue receuid
my rewarde, I wyll axe nothinge els, God
encrece about Princes the small nomber of
suche zelous futers &amp; promoters of religion,
and then no doubt gods glorye shall florishe
when we seke his dewe honor, and not oure
owne profyte. But to avoide contencion &amp;
scisme Austen gevith good counsel to godly
and quiet men, that they mercifully correcte
that whiche they can, &amp; that which they can
not, paciently beare, grone and morne, with

loue, vntil god ether correct or amend them.
But how this Christian loue shuld be kept
in this church, when so manye godlie for so
small thinges shalbe thruste out, &amp; also how
many already is from the ministery &amp; theyr
lyuinges, yt passyth manye good and godlie
wittes to conceyue. S. Pauls rule in suche
thinges, sayth: All thinges to me is lawfull,
but all thinges is not expedient: all thinges
to me is lawfull, but all thinges edefye not.
Therfor in this case we must not so suttelly
dispute, what Christian liberte will suffer vs
to do, but what is metist and most edefying
for Christian charite, &amp; promoting Christian
and pure religion. But surely how popishe
aparell shuld edefie, or set forwarde the gospell
of Christ Jesus, it can not be seen of the
multitude, nay, it is to much fealt how gredly
it reioysith the aduersaries of the truth,
when they see what we borowe of them; &amp;
contend for the same as thinges necessarie.
marke well the bysshopes wearing of their
whyte rochets, what grounde they fyrste
had, and from whence they receyuid it. Ther
was a certayne man, namid Sisinius an heriticke
bishop of the Nova
                  •
               ions, and he first
begane yt. all those other popish trashe hath
the lyke founda
                  •
               ions, but they haue to long
contineuyd &amp; pleasyd poperie, which is beggerly

pacchid vp of al sortes of cerimones, &amp;
that they coulde neuer be routyd out sence,
no not from manie professors of the gospel.
Wherfore you that se others that is come
to a better perfection, grudge not at yt, but
be thankfull to God, though thynges may
be borne wythe for a tyme for Christian lybertes
sake, in hope to winne the weake. yet
when lyberte is turnyd into necessite, yt ys
evell, &amp; no lenger lyberte: and that, that was
for wynning the weake sufferid for a tyme,
is become the confyrminge of the frowarde
in their obstinacie. Paul vsyd circūcision for
a tyme as of lyberte, but when it was vrgyd
of necessite, he wold not bende vnto it. That
famous father Master Bucer, when he was
axyd why he wolde not weare a square cape,
made aunswere, because hys heade was not
foure square. wherin surelye he notyd well
the comlynes of aparell to be, when yt was
fassionyd lyke the body, &amp; a gret folly when
a square cape was set on a rounde heade.
God be mercyfull vnto vs, and graunte vs
vprightly to seke hys honore wyth all earnestnes
&amp; simplicite. The Lorde comfort his
afflictid church, &amp; graunte that in this oulde
age of the worlde, we may serue the Lord of
hostes in synglenes of hart, and laboure to
rote out all stomblinge blockes in religion,

that Christes glorie maye nakydly shyne of
yt sealue, without all tradicions or inuencions
of men, as in the begynninge when yt
was purest, and all such deuyses vnknowen,
but inuentid of late to bleare the eyes of the
ignorant, with outwarde shewe of holines.
God graunt that we may geue all honor to
whom al honore is deue, both inwardly and
outwardly, to serve hym vnfaynedlye al the
dayes of oure lyfe. Fare well deare
brethren in the Lorde Jesu,
who euer kepe vs in
hys fayth, feare,
and loue, for
euer.
            Amen.
         
         
            
            
            ¶To my faythfull Brethren
now afflycted, &amp; to all those that vnfaynedly
loue the Lorde Jesus, the Lorde guyde vs
with his holy spret, that we maye always
serue hym bothe in body and mynde in
all synceryte to oure lyues ende.
            WHen I do remember, dearly belouyd,
the great charge inioynyd vnto vs of
almyghtie God, &amp; the strayghte accounte
that we shall haue to make, for the
ryghte vse and dispensacion of his mysteries,
I fynde no comparison myght iustly
moue any Christyan to doubt of the better
of those two choyses, only that whych
makythe a shewe for the mayntenaunce of
popishe apparel is the opynion of indifferency,marke wel good Christyan.
whych thynge he yt wyll perswade,
must fyrst proue that it tendythe to Godes
glory. Concurrythe wythe his worde,
edefyeth his churche, mayntaynyth Christyan
lyberte: whych condycions &amp; circumstances
if they wante, The thynge whych
otherwyse by nature is indifferent, dothe
degenerat and become hurtfull. but howe
can Godes glory be auaunced by those popishe
garmētes whych supersticyous men
&amp; Antychrist haue inuentyd for the maynteyninge
&amp; beutyfyinge of Idolatry, what

agrement can mans supersticious inuencyons
haue wythe the eternall worde of
God, what edifycacion can there be wher
the spirit of god is greuyd, Christes lytillous
discoragyd,the bōdage of ceremonies what it bringith ye weake brethren brought
into doubt of relygyon, the wyckyd papists
confyrmyd in their errour, And adore
new set open to all Popish tradycions
and Antychristian impietie: nether can any
man call this Christian lybertie, where a
yoke is layd vpon the dysciples neckes,
where the consciens is cloggyd, true preachers
thretenyd, the curse of Godes worde
stayed, the congregacyons spoylyd of godlye
and learnyd pastors, the Sacramentes
brought vnder subieccyon of Idolators &amp;
supersticious vestiments, therefore where
either the formar condycion wante or this
latter be annexsyd, yt can not be callyd a
thynge mere indifferent. Augustine vpon
indifferent thyngs saythe, Those thynges
that are not contrarye to faythe, nether
yet contrarye to good manners, and haue
somwhat to exhorte to the amendemēt of
lyfe, whersoeuer we se such thynges commaundyd,
or do know to be institutid, we
do not only alowe, but also we will folow
them in praysynge and imytatinge them:
yf the infyrmyte of some do not let that yt

shuld be a further detrimente or damage,
here Augustine requiryth two poynts in
thyngs indifferent. First that they induce
to a better lyfe, &amp; do serue to edyfycacion,
next that we beware lest any offence come
therbye,marke wel the nature of indifferēt thinges or any weake consciens be hynderyd
in ye curse of religion, Christ hym selfe
geuyth a good warning saynge, wo be to
offences, there myght be brought dyuers
examples and testymonies to proue, that
thynges whych of them selues haue byne
or are indifferēt, by circunstāce &amp; abusinge
becom euel, what thynge is more requirid
for sondry causis in this lyfe, then fastinge,
and for the dayes &amp; tymes, what thynges
can be more indifferent. yet yf by ye obseruacion
of dayes and appoyntinge of tyme
we shuld confirme the opinion of the wyckyd,the godly wil haue nothinge to do in cerimonies of the wicked.
&amp; so gyue consente to them we were
worthely to be blamyd &amp; reprouyd, as Augustine
wytnessith wryting after this sort,
To faste on the Sonday is a great offence,
cheflye after yt detestable heresye of the
Manichees, whych is planlye contrary to
the Catholyke fayth of manye, &amp; the scriptures
of God dyd shew it selfe, whych cō
               stitutyd
to their hearers, to fast on ye Sonday,
was a most mete daye. Tertulian in
his boke De corona militis, defendyth the

cause of a soudyar that was zelous for the
glory of god, &amp; wold not weare a garlonde
on his heade as ye rest of his felowes dyd,
lest he shuld seame to consent with ye Idolators,God send vs manye suche zelours christyanes.
&amp; so bringe true relygion into doubt,
&amp; wheras many of the Christiās myslykid
of this soudyars facte, which for so smal a
tryfill wolde hasarde the Emperors fauor
and so auenture his lyfe, seinge to weare
the garlonde was not agaynste ye scriptures.
Tertullian who iustifyed this zelous
acte answerethe on this soudiars behalfe
sayinge: Yf for this cause it may be sayd
yt he myght lawfully be crownyd, because
the scriptures do not forbyd it, by this same
reason it shalbe answered, that therfor
he ought not to be crounyd, because ye scriptures
doth not commande it. The Counsel
of Toletane ordenyd that in Baptymse
shulde be vsyd but one dyppynge, lest they
shuld seame to consente with the heretiks
whiche vsed to dypp the child thryse, &amp; sendynge
to Gregory for his counsell herein,
they receuyd this answere, for the eschewinge
of the sclaunder of scisme and tradycion
of the heritikes, let vs hold the symple
vse of Baptisme, lest they whiche amō
               gest
vs do vse to dypp thryse to allowe the
assercyon of the heretykes, whyle y• folow

                  〈2… pages missing〉
               
               
not onlye to holde the Idoll as accursyd,
but also that we vtterlye abhorre and accounte
moste abhominable thynges that
apperteyne ther unto, and haue nothynge
to do with it, least we be snaryd with it,
rede we not in the Machabees. howe the
Lorde distroyd all those that had any stuff
of the Idolls,2. mach. 12. Josua. 7. and howe was Achan plagyd
for reseruynge those thynges, whych
the Lorde wold haue dystroyd and accursyd,a suttle practys.
we reade that Julianus the apostata
causyd the heathen to accomodat them
selues to the maners of the Christyans,
and theyr vsages thynkyng by this meanes
to entice them to Paganisme, and yf
we compell the godlye to conforme them
selues to the Papistes, I greatlye feare,
least we fall into Papisme: alas, that such
compulsyon shuld be vsyd toward vs, and
so great lenite towards the Papistes, how
many Papistes inioye lyberte &amp; lyuyngs,
whyche neyther haue sworne obedyenc to
the Quenes maiestie, nether do yet anye
parte of deutye towardes theyr miserable
flockes, those mysers laughe, and triumphe
to se vs thus delt wythe, not ashamyd
here vpon to bragg, that they truste that
the rest of theyr thynges wyll folow. But
he that sittyth in the heauens, shal laughe

them to skorne, and at leangthe shal geue an
end to oure depe syghinges, and delyuer
vs from all heuynes sorowes and myseris,
wherfore let vs neuer yealde to this
tryumphe of the Pope agaynst Christe,
Lorde Jesus be mercyfull vnto vs, and let
thy wrathe be pouryd vpon them that call
not on the name of the Lorde, yf true reformacyon
can not be had. Yet lett Christyan
lybertie preuayle agaynst compulsion
to euell, lett not the Papistes abuse
vs as the Jewys dyd the Christyans, when
they had the temporall sworde on theyr
syde, pytey ye dyssolate churches heare the
cryes and gronyns of so manye thousandes
of godes pore children that hunger
and thyrst for sprituall fode, we neade not
to apealle to godes worde, to the prymatiue
church to the iust plages whyche hath
byne pouryd and is pouryd contynuallye,
vpon the wordle for lacke of true reformacyon
of relygyon, but let your owne
conscience iudge betwene oure cause and
oure enemyes, and yf we seke nothynge
but godes glorye craue equitie and ryght
desyre Christyan lybertie, labor to ouerthrowe
Idolatry and to wyne soulys vnto
Christe, why shulde we not be harde,
why are we so vncharitably dealt with all

the Lorde moue youre hartes and open
your eies, that we may all prayse gloryfy
his holy name, that when the end of oure
pylgrymage shalbe endyd most ioyfullye
we maye test with hym in his euerlastinge
glory through Christ oure sauyour, to
whome wyth the Father and
the Holygost be all prayse
glorye and honor,
for euer.
         
         
            
            
            ¶To the Reader.
            TO my faythfull Brethren, we geue
thankes to God for your constancie
and vpryght delynge in this gret
controuersie now raysyd by packynge of
enemys about the wearinge of popish apparell,
and as ye haue well begonne, ther
is no doubt, but the Lorde in mercy shall
kepe ye pure and blameles to the ende. It
hathe byne no small ioye and comfort to
many godlye and good Churches, which
dayly and howerly prayeth for your perseuerāce,
and that it wolde please God to
ease it, whē his good will and pleasure is.
So on the other syde muche lamentynge
the blyndnes of those that goeth about to
defende it: but especiallye those that are
become persecutors of their godly &amp; faithfull
brethren: but as charite requireth, we
desyre God neuer laye it to theyr charge,
but geue them grace to ryse agayne vnto
whom we le
                  •
               e them wether they stande or
falle. Let Lottes wyfe be a warnynge in
tyme to take hede. Moses that blessyd seruant
of God wolde not alter the valew of
a curten, or a lytill pyne in the Arcke, so zelous
was he in the Lordes worke: nor neuer
brought any thynge out of his owne
heade to the people: But had always the

warrant of the worde for hym, to cōclude,
what so euer may be obiected agaynst the
refusars of those ydolators garmētes, for
what so euer they brynge, may be redused
into this poyntes, that Godly men ether
nede not or ought not to be scrupulous in
so small a matter, which answer ye shall
vnderstand as folowith with an answere
to a question at the end hereof. The Lord
for his Christ sake make Ephrahim and
Manassis agre, that we maye all with on
hart and mynde vnfaynydly seke Godes
glorye, the edificacion of his people, that
we may lyue in all godly peace, vnyte, and
concord. This grant, o Lorde, for Christ
Jesus sake, to whom, with the, and the
Holy goste, be all prayse, glory, and
honor for euer and euer.
Fare ye well deare
Brethren.
            
               
Dearly 
                  •
               elouy
                  •
               , you that haue wytte,
vnderstanding, and wyll to be instructyd
in this controuersi. now
raysyd in the Churche about apparell, at
thys tyme thys shall suffyce. Yt is true
that the teachers of handye craftes affyrme,
that no man can attayne to suche excellente
perfeccyon in worke, as maye be
disputed of by reasone, muche lesse when
the rule of religion muste be framyd accordynge
to the rule of Godes wyll, which is
ye rule of all perfeccyon, may we loke that
any thyng can so perfectly be performyd
of vnperfect mā, that in all poynts yt may
answere to the perfeccion that God requirith:
neuertheles God requirith his seruice
to be suche as hym sealfe is, deuyne, pure,
syncere, vnmingled, and in no parte corruptyd,
and as lacke of strenthe shal not excuse
vs, in that we can not, so ne
                  •
               lygence
makythe vs more wickyd, yf that we may
performe, and we will not. Fyrste we are
requiryd to loue God with all our hartes,
all our myndes, and all our strength, that
precisenes is comendable, which withholdith
not a lytill,Deut. 18. whē all is requiryd. Thou
shalt be perfect with thy Lorde thy god.
Thou shalt not bende ether to thy ryght-hande,
or to the leafte. Thou shalt nether

               
                  〈1 line〉
               
ma
                  ••
               dyd. Thou shalt not inquier for th
                  •
               
gods of the Gentyls, sayinge: Howe dyd
those Gentyles serue theyr godes. Thou
shalt not do so to the Lorde thy god. For
whatsoeuer the Lorde abhorreth, that dyd
they to theyr godes. God wyll haue his
children so to abhorre these supersticion, yt
they shuld fle euen from that infecciō that
comythe by hearynge.The zeall that God requirith. Furthermore, so
many thinges as ar cōmandyd of leprous,
mēstreous, dead bodys, were many, which
myght not be touchyd without defyling,
what other thinges were they in that rude
people,God kepe vs frō all outwarde shew of Popery. but exercises of precyse purenes
and cleanes, the obseruance of suche shadowes,
althoughe it hath byn longe synce
abolyshyd, yet the euerlastinge truthe remaynyth:
muche more in presence of the
bodye, that no prophane or defylyd thinge
may be minglyd with gods seruice. Moreouer
god forbydyth all strange corruptions
mixtures, whē he forbyddyth them
to sowe land with diuers seedes, to plowghe
with an oxe and an asse, to weare lynyne
and wollen to gether. For lyberte &amp;
costome euen in ye leaste matters bredythe
boldnes, &amp; in hys cōmandement god hath
also respecte to the hynde of apparell. Fynallie

when this cleanes is 
                  〈◊〉
                euen
to brute beastes,marke well. who wold not beleue that
God requirith an vtter detestacion of all
vncleanes, especially in religion. Seing all
these lawes perteyne to the fyrst cōmandement,
accordinge to the same precise rule
dyd the holy fathers exercise them selues
vnto puryte, therfore it is neuer rede that
the godly Patriarches dyd sacrifyce vpon
the Idolators alters, but whythersoeuer
they remouid, always they buyldid newe
alters.Example of holy men. Furthermore Abraham wolde not
take a thryde of the Kynge of Sodoma.
Jacob buryed the eatinges that weare ornamentes
of supersticion, with the Idoles
them selues. Moyses to blemishe the seruice
of God wolde accepte no condicions
at all, there shall not remayne on house,
saythe he very precislye. Dauith wold not
take the names of the Idoles in his lypes.
Ezechias brake the brasen serpēt, not only
chāgyd the vse of it.what greter herytykes cā ther be, then the Papistes? The Holyghost praysithe
those godly Kinges, which destroyed
the highe places, as Ezechias and Josias,
in whiche places somtyme the people dyd
worship god. Elyazer wold not fayne that
he dyd eate swynes fleshe. S. Pawle byddythe,
Refrayne from all shew of euyll.
S. John forbyddyth vs to salute an herytyke

               
                  〈1 line〉
               
wytnessith, when he mett an herityke,
wolde not gyue hym other answere,
but that he knewe hym to be the Deuells
eldeste sonne. for suche feare had the Apostels
&amp; theyr disciples, that they wolde
not comunicate withe on worde with any
that had corruptyd the faith. Fynallie S.
Pawle in playne wordes cōmandyth precisnes,Ephe. 5.
sayinge, Take hede that ye walke
precislye or exactlye, for so the greke worde
signifieth. Last of all, let vs not forget
what our Sauiour Christ saythe: He that
is faythfull in the leaste, wyl be faythfull
in the moste. Who also teachith vs, howe
faythfully and precislye we shulde walke,
what colde be more precisly spoken of, the
law shall passe vntyll all be fullfyllyd, and
he that breakyth one of the leaste cōmandements,
and teachith other so to do, ether
by worde, or by example, shalbe least in the
Kyngdome of heauen. Yt is euident by
these reasons and examples, that no precisenes
or scrupulosite in godes religion,
can be to muche or blame worthie. Towchinge
ye substance, ther is no controuersy,
but yt is lawfull as the good creature of
god, and to this purpose pertayne those
sayinges: The kyngdome of heauen is nether

meate nor drynke. Meate cōmendith
vs not to god. Whatsoeuer enterithe in
to the mouth, defylyth not the man. All
thinges ar cleane to them that ar cleane.
&amp; other lyke places of scripture, all which
they pertayne to the matter or creature &amp;
substance only, not to euery vse, fassion, or
maner of vsynge. It is to muche doltyshenes,
not to vnderstand all thynge a ryght,
excepte we wyll also conclude of the same
places, that by glotony, dronkenes, whordome,
disquisyd aparell, and suche lyke, the
lawe of god is not brokē. garments therfore
that ar vrgyd in respecte of the forme
and vse, they are not indifferent, and fyrst
of the ende, which they labor so muche to
proue that it is chaungyd, that those thinges
which before were vsyd to supersticiō,
now are cōmandyd for order &amp; comlynes.
No godly man doubtyth, but the Quenes
Maieste intendinge an other end in commanding
of those thinges, then the Papistes
vsyd them for. But who so well considerith
ye nature of those thinges, shall playnely
se, that the end which the commander
propoundyth, dothe not folowe, but accordinge
to the diuersite of them yt vse them,
and them that iudge of them, a cleane cō
               trary
end ensuythe, for many popishe prestes

vse them to the same supersticious end
that they dyd in Popery, and greatest of
all is ye multitude of ignorant people, that
iudgith none otherwyse of them.Cor. 8. All men
haue not knowledge, for some with conscience
of the Idole, euen yet do eate meate
offred to Idoles. So Gedeon made an Ephode,
not that ye people shulde go a whorynge
after it,Jud. 8. yet was it the destruction
of hym and his howse for euer. Secondly
it can not serue for order and comlynes,Cor. 14.
which hath in it no necessary cause of edifying.
Let all thinges be donne for edifying.
Nether can it be conuertyd to ye comlynes
of the Christian Churche, which is
the chaste spowse of Christ, which is takē
from Antichrist, and the fylthye whore of
Babylon. What cōsent hath Christ with
Belyall: what porcion hath the faythfull
with the infydell: or what agrement hath
the temple of God with Images? Yf the
reason of S. Paule be examynyd,2. Cor. 6. by the
which he dissuadith the Corynthians frō
eating of meate offeryd to Idoles, the same
may be also extendyd to garmēts consecratyd
to Idolatry. The nature of cerymonies
and rytes is to make the vser to
haue felowship with the principall of that
religion, as the Jewes of the alter, Christians

with Christ, and Gentils with Deuells.
As manye as are partakers of the
breade which we breake, are partakers of
the bodye of Christe. They therfore that
eate meate offeryd to Idoles, are partakers
of deuells. And as many as are baptized
haue put on Christ: it is not to be fearyd,
leaste as many as weare antychristes
robes, wil take more yf auctorite comand
it, neyther dothe the auctoryte of the Christian
Magistrat excuse vs, except we thinke,
that Sergius Paulus myght permyte
that S. Paule had forbydden the sentence
of Jamys,Act. 15. Deut. 12. which is, that the gentyls shulde
abstayne from the polucion of Idoles,
God will borowe nothynge of Idoles to
garnysh or become his religion. thou shalt
not do so to the Lorde thy god, but rather
he commandyth vtterly to destroye theyr
alters, woddes, pyllers, and theyr very names.
He forbyddyth them also to brynge
any thinge in to theyr howses that belongythe
to Idoles. Esaye chap. 30. byddyth
those that are earnestly turnyd to the worshippe
of god, to cast awaye the reliques
of Idolatrie, You shall, sayth he, put out
the couerynge of the Imagis of syluer,that is all thing belonging to Idolatry. &amp;
the precious vestymēts of the goldē Imagis,
and thou shalt caste them awaye lyke

a menstrous clowte, and saye vnto yt: Auawnte,
or get the hence. Fynallye when
all godly men abhorre the monstrous apparell
of Fryers, Monkes, Chanons, I
can not se, by what order they shulde exteme
the ornaments of Popishe Preastes,
whose order is as wyckyd as Freyers,
Monkes, or any other, which thyng may
be sayd of the reste of the Popishe ceremonies,
which may all with lyke precepte and
coloure, &amp; by as good reason be receuid in
the Churches as those. But admyttinge
that these thynges were neuer so indifferent,
yet it can not be that we shulde thynke
them lawfull, for vs to vse them: For euē
those thinges, which by them sealues are
lawfull, whē an other circumstance is ioynyd
to them, then become they vnlawfull
for a Christian to vse them, as in these cases.
First we can not cast of all doubtfulnes,
hauing so many reasons on our syde,
and so manye examples bothe of learnyd
men, and best reformyd Churches, but in
all thinges most indifferent. Saint Paule
chargith euery mā to be certanly persuadyd
in his owne mynde, which some men
vntruly translate, Let euery man abownde
in his owne sence, for he that with doubt
of conscience eatyth, which of it sealfe is

lawfull, is condemnyd, because he doth it
not of fayth. Now the assurance of fayth
muste be sought no where, but in Gods
worde. Secondlye, thowghe we shulde satisfye
our consciences, yet this man is defylid,
which is not persuadid by Gods worde,
but encreased by our examples, that he
dare do that, whereof before he doubted,
and this is to geue an offence, as they cō
               monly
call it to anger them, for they that
are best pleasyd with these matters, are
most offendyd that they stomble and falle,
we must not do what so euer is lawfull,
but what so euer also is profytable to edifying:
nether must we only regarde what
lyberte permyttyth, but rather what our
brothers proffyt requiryth. Thyrdlye, we
maye not altogether neclecte what infydells
iudge of vs in the vsynge of thinges
lawfull by them sealfes, and therefore S.
Paule byddeth them that are callyd to the
feastes of the gentyls, so sone as mencyon
is made of meate offeryd to Idoles, to abstayne
from eatinge of it, because of hym
that tolde of it, and his conscience, not of
hym sealfe, but of an other. What the Papistes
iudge of vs, maye casely be seene by
this, ye Harding for the retayning of those
Popishe cerymonies, cōteynith hope that

popery shalbe restoryd: what the ignorant
people iudge of the reamnants of papistri
retaynyd, wyse men may well consyder.
Herunto might haue byne ioynid the sentences
of olde Doctors, Justinus, Ireneus,
Tertullianus, Agustyne, Ambros, Chrysostums,
Celestinus, &amp; almost all the rest,
for abhorrynge the customes and ryghtes
of the Jewes and gentyles and heritykes,
but Gods truthe nedyth not mans auctoryte,
except they that be against vs, in this
cause wyll appeale to the fathers, thē shall
they perceyue, that in nomber both of Doctors,
and sentences, we shall be nothinge
inferior to them. In the meane tyme this
maye suffyce, to shew fyrst that the precysians
is blameles, secondly the garmētes
ar not indifferent, &amp; thyrdly that thowghe
they were indifferent yet ther is sufficient
reason at this tyme, why we shoulde not
weare them. Come Lord Jesus, and make
an ende of thys wyckyd wordle, that thy
sainctes may come to gether, that we may
synge with the in thy holy hyll for euer.
He that ouercomith, shalbe crownyd.
Pray, pray, as the Apostell Peter
sayth: the end of all thinges
is at hand.
         
         
            
            ¶An Answere to a question, that was
mouyd, whi the godly men wold
not weare a surples.
            ALthoughe we muste nedes confesse,Answere.
that we haue to much consentyd heretofore
with the Papiste in robbing
and bereuinge God of his glory &amp; honor,
yet may we not now in the lyght of Gods
truthe contynew a partaker with you in
the adulteracion of Christes sacramentes,
cōtrary to our consciences &amp; knowledge,
wherein we iudge our sealues onlye, not
preiudisynge other mens doinge, whō we
leaue to God, before whō they ether stand
or falle. For oure partes we must render
accompte, not obstinatly bent against any
thing yt shalbe approuyd by Gods worde.
            We are persuadyd,Maior. that we may not vse
any thinge repugnant to Christian lyberte,
nor mayntayne an opinion of holynes
wher none is, whiche were Ipocrisy, nor
consent to Idolatri, which were denyall of
the truthe, or discorage the godly, incoragynge
the wyckyd, nor distroying ye Churche
of Christ, which are bownde to edifye,
nor consent vnto confusion, wher God requiryth
order, nor shew disobedience, wher
God requiryth to obeye.
            
               
But in vsynge of a surples,Minor. we shulde
do that which is repugnaunt to Christian
lybertie, maintaine an opinion of holines,
where none is, shew consent to Idolatry,
deny the truthe, dyscorage the godly, and
incorage the wyckyd or vngodly, consent
to confusion and shew disobedience, wher
God commandithe to obeye.
            We may not with good conscience,Cōclusion as
we are persuadyd weare a surples.
            The Maior is prouyd by Saynt Paule
Gal. 5. who commandyth to Christian libertie,
by the example of Christ Matt. 15.
who wold not haue his disciples to maintayne
an opinion of holynes,note the example of good men. whiche the
Jewes had in wasshyng of handes: by the
doctryne of Pawle. 2. Cor. 6. who wyll
haue no agremēt with the temple of God
and the Idoles: by the example of Danyel.
6. who openid his wyndowe towardes
Jerusalem, lest he myght seame to denye
his profession or consent with ye wyckyd:
by the example of Paule Gal. 2. who reprouyd
Peter for the discoragyng of the
godly gentiles, and incoraging of the froward
Jewes: by the doctryne of the same
Apostell. 2. Cor. 13. where he teachith that
Mynysters haue power to edifye, not to
destroye: by the example of Patriarkes,

and Prophetes, which in the worshipping
of God, wear by no meanes confowndyd
withe the Idolators: by the doctryne of
Peter and John actes, which affyrmithe
to be more ryght to obey God, then men.
But for more euident profe herof, we may
let you se some practises of auncient Fathers.
Tertulian in his boke De corona
militis, lykythe them vnto dom̄e Idolls,
suche as do vse any thinge accordynge to
the ornament of Idolles: and further, yf
to leane apon an Idoll, is strange from the
fayth,fastyng is good, yet the godly wold not vse it that day, as the herytyk dyd. what shall seame apon the habyte
of an Idoll. Augustyne ad Casulanum,
warnythe not to faste on the Sondaye,
least therby consente might be shewyd to
the wyckyd Maniches. They that weare
any thinge after the maner of Idoles, and
yf it be strange from fayth to leane apon
an Idoll, what is it to weare the habyt of
an Idoll. The fourth Counsell of Toletane
Canon. 5. for auoydynge of consent
with Herytyckes, decreed that once dyppynge
shulde be vsyd in Baptysme. A Papist
of our tyme affyrmith that the Apostels
to auoyde consent to Judaisme, abolysshed
the Sabothe daye, and sanctyfyed
the daye of the Lorde. The great Clarke
Orygen, as Epiphanius wrytith in his. 2.

boke. 1.Beware of decemblyng. Tome, caryed palme withe thos
that offeryd to the Image Serapis, allthoughe
he protestyd openly, that he dyd
offer vnto Christ, and not vnto Serapis,
yet was he excomunycatyd, and cast out of
the Church by the Marters and Confessors
whiche then were at Athens. The
Christian sowdiars which by Julian sultelte
were browght to offer incens,Beware of deceytfull practyses. as it is
wryten Historia Tripartita lib. 6. chap. 30.
when they perceuyd theyr faute, whiche
vnwares they had commytted in consentyng
to Idolatri, they rane forthe into the
streats professede theyr relygion, testifyed
them sealues to be Christians, affyrmyng
that theyr handes only had cōsentyd vnto
Paganisme,the nature of true Christian. and that theyr hartes dyd nothyng
agre thervnto, and whereas theyr
handes had offendyd vnadvysydlye, they
wyshyd to bestowe theyr whole bodyes to
be tormentyd for Christ, althoughe wyth
tormentes and paynes moste creuell and
horyble. I trust we nede not to laboure any
further for the profe. By the vse of the
surples men are iniciat in to ye Popes clergye,
as it aperith by ye Pontifycall, De clerico
faciendo. Yf ye Galathians by circumcision
rather loste theyr lyberte in Christ,
then profytyd any thynge, by iniciatinge

them sealues in to Judaisme. How maye
you retayne the lyberte in Christ, and profyt
in his religion by wearinge the Popes
lyuerye, we can not perceaue? But by the
vse of the surples, is mayntaynyd an Ipocritycall
opinion of holynes, ye Pontificall
termithe it Habitum sancte religionis, the
habyt of an holy religion. Durand lib. 3.
de rationale diuinorum, saythe, That it is
Destis linea, the lynyne garment, in which
they that serue about the seruices of the
alter and holy thinges, ought to vse apon
theyr clothes, a surples, it is for the whitnes
of it, or it signifieth the puryte or chastete,
accordinge to that sayinge: Let your
garments, that is, your workes, be white
at all tymes,Marke what lying signes is in the surples inuentyd by Papistes. that is cleane: but for his name,
it figurith the mortification of the fleshe.
It is callyd a Surples, because that
in the olde tyme they dyd weare it apon
skynny coates, made of the skynnes of the
deade, whiche is vsyd to this daye in certayne
Churches, representynge that Adame,
after he had synnyd,with what good conscience can the godly weare yt, iudge good Brother. was clothed
with suche garments. Thyrdly, it notith
Innocenci, and therfore it is put on before
all other holye vestures, because that they
that are deputyd to worshippynge, ought
to excell in lyfe and in all vertues, accordyng

to the sayinge of the psalme: Innocencies
do ryghtly cleue vnto me. Fourthely,
for the bredthe of it, it betokenythe
Charite, wherefore they are worne apon
prophane and cōmon vestures, it is to be
markyd that charite coueryth the multitude
of synnes. Fyftlye, for the fassyon
of it, in that is it made lyke a Crosse, or
Jewes gallows, it fygurythe the passion
of the Lord, and they yt weare, that ought
to be creweyfyed with the vices and concupiscences.
In mayntayninge this opinion
of holynes, with all other inuēcions,
which by lyinge seignes, which they haue
had to it, we knowe not howe to auoyde
consent vnto that Idolatri, which Durant
and the Papiste mayntayne and professe,
&amp; to deny the Popes cerimonies, the doctryne
whiche we teache, howe shuld it not
dyscorage the godly, and incorage the supersticious
in theyr errors? we can not edefye
the Church of Christ apparentlye,
shewinge our sealues to be on of the Popes
clergye. Seing S. Paull Thess. 3. willythe
to auoyde all apparens of euyll, and
to be shufflyd in a surples, whiche the Popes
clergye wear, were rather a confusion
then an order, whiche they them sealues
wolde be lothe to suffer, if they might get

agayne the keys into theyr handes, they
wolde crye withe open mowthe, as theyr
pontificall teache them, &amp; plucke the surples
of our backes by the autoryte of almyghtie
God the Father,The surples is an holy garmēt of the Papistes. the Sonne, and
the Holyghoste. saying, and we take from
the all our clerkly habyt, and we put on ye
apparell of religion, and depose, degrade,
and spoyle the of all orders clerkely benefice,
and clerkelye lyuinge,Marke the follye of Papistes. and we restore
the to the seruitude and ignominie of the
secular habyte. Is it not a disorder, that
Christians shoulde shewe them selues slaues
to the Popes order? were it not better
to serue God in commun attyre, then to
please the Pope by disquisinge our selues
in supersticious surplessis: were it not better
to obey God, who wyllyth vs to serue
hym in spret, and in truthe, then to obey
men, followyng the deuyse of Pope Syluester,
the fassyon of the Jewes, and practyse
of the Papistes▪ where it not better,
by leauynge of a Surples to folow Christ
in breakynge mens tradicions, thē by the
vse therof to be a companion of Popes &amp;
Pharises? Yf this do not seame sufficient
to proue the Minor at this tyme, it shalbe
more at large dyscoursyd hereafter. Concernyng
ye Quenes Maiestes commandement,

herein we acknowledge our sealues
bownde to obey in all thynges lawfullye
commaundyd, so can not we be persuadyd
to vse that in the minysteri, which our consciences
teacheth vs to be replenished with
Idolatrous Ipocrisye, &amp; also the example
of other men which dothe were it, ought
nothing at all to moue vs to were a surples
in the minysterie, no more then to consent
with them in persecutyng those men
whom they terme sedicious scismatyckes
for leauyng them of. Thus as ye se, shortlye
dere Brethren, we leue the surples, as
the Popes badge to the shauen Clergye,
and you as Gods chosen to the protection
of the almyghtie whysshynge, that God
may geue vs grace aswell inwardelye as
outwardlye, to seke for syncerite, and to
wayght with all pacience the good
wyll &amp; pleasure of the almyghtye,
who wyll &amp; can healpe
when pleasith hym.
Fare ye well in
the Lorde
Jesus.
         
         
            
            ¶A Godly Prayer.
            OH Lord God and heauenly Father,
which art a iust Judge to punishe
all them, that do contynewe to offende
the, as thou art a Father most pytyfull
to receaue to mercy all those, whiche
geue ouer themselues to please the, shewe
me thy grace and fauour, so that I may be
truly touchid withe inward displeasure of
my synnes, and that in the place of flattering
my self to slepe in synne, I may be so
cast downe in hart, that the rather I may
truly with mouthe confesse most humbly
to geue the, the honour, glory, and prayse,
dew vnto thy holy name, and that as thou
of thy greate mercy doste instruct vs therevnto
by thy holy word, so (for thy names
sake) make that ye same may so lighten
and cleare our conscience, that in dew
examination of all our hole lyffe, we may
truly learne to be angry &amp; displeasid with
all our former, and corrupte lyuing. Oh
that it may please the to drawe nere vnto
vs, in addressyng and guydyng our footsteppes
in the true and perfect way of obedyence
to thy holy lawes and cōmaundementes.
Send thy holye Angel to pitche
his tentes round about vs, that Sathan &amp;

               
                  •
               is internall army, neuer preuayle again
                  ••
               
vs, but allways with strong faith we may
thorough Jesus Christ withstand all his
crafty engins and snares, knowynge vndoubtedly
that thou neuer forsakest them
that put their trust in the. Oh let vs not
be led by the infirmytie of our vntowarde
fleshe, but strenghten vs by the vertue of
the holy spiryte. Suffer vs not to lye vnder
thy heuy wrathe &amp; vengeaunce throughe
Ipocrysye, but rather touche vs so inwardly,
that we may without ceasyng, syghe,
and grone vnto the, by true and vnfayned
repentaunce. And althoughe we
be not allwayes so wel disposyd to aske &amp;
praye, as we ought to do, yet (good Lord)
for thy names sake, stretche out thy mightie
hande, that by the gratious workyng
of thy holy Spirite, our myndes and hartes
may be drawen from all erthly and corruptible
thinges, so that our prayers may
procede of an ernest and inward affection,
so that we neuer presume to cōme before
yu with a dobell hart, knowing that whosoeuer
askethe and prayeth for anye thing
of the, not asking in faith, can not obteyne.
Increace our faithe therfore (oh mercyfull
Father) that we presently may lyuely
feele the benefit of remission and pardon

of all our synnes, thoroughe the merytes
and death of Christ Jesus our Sauiour,
and so work in vs foreuer hereafter
to lyue in thy feare, and to stand in awe
of thy displeasure, that thou mayst
contynew our mercyfull Father
world without end.
            God graunt yt.
         
      
   

