
   
      
         
            The true discripcion of a childe with ruffes borne in the parish of Micheham in the cou[n]tie of Surrey in the yeere of our Lord. M.D.LXvi
            H. B., fl. 1566.
         
         
            
               1566
            
         
         Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00257
            STC 1033
            ESTC S117265
            99852480
            99852480
            17804
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00257)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17804)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1226:15)
         
         
            
               
                  The true discripcion of a childe with ruffes borne in the parish of Micheham in the cou[n]tie of Surrey in the yeere of our Lord. M.D.LXvi
                  H. B., fl. 1566.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  
               
                  By Iohn Allde and Richarde Iohnes and are to be solde at the long shop adioining vnto S. Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie and at the litle shop adioining to the northwest doore of Paules Churche,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  Anno domini. M.D.Lxvi. the .xx. of August [1566]
               
               
                  Signed: H.B.
                  Woodcut illustration with letterpress prose description and with verses.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Skin --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.
               Monsters --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-04
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2004-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
            
            ¶ The true discripcion of a Childe with Ruffes borne in the parish of Micheham in the Coūtie of Surrey in the yeere of our Lord. M. D. LXvi.
            
               The for part and the back part
            
            
               THis presēt yeere of our Lord M. D. Lxvi the .vii. day of Iune one Helene Iermin the wife of Iohn Iermin Husbandman Dwelling in the parishe of Micheham was deliuered of a Woman Childe named Christiā beeing aftur this maner &amp; fourme following. That is to say, the Face comly &amp; of a cheerful countenaūce. The Armes and hands, Leggs and Feet of right shape, and the Body wt all other members therunto apperteinīg, wel proporciōed in due fourme &amp; order, sauing yt it is as it were wunderfully clothed with suche a Flesshy skin as the like at no time hath ben seene. For it hath the said flesshy skin behinde like vnto a Neckerchef growing from the reines of the Back vp vnto the neck as it were with many Ruffes set one after another and beeing as it were somthing gathered, euery Ruf about an inche brode hauīg here growing on the edges of the same, &amp; so wt Ruffes cōming ouer ye Shoulders and couering some part of ye Armes proceding vp vnto the nape of the neck behinde and almoste round about the neck, like as many womens Gownes be, not cloce to gither before: but that the throte beeing (with a faire white skin) bare betweene bothe the sides of the ruffes, the said ruffes about the neck beeing double and as it were thick gathered, muche like vnto the Ruffes that many do vse to weare about their necks.
            ¶ This Childe beforsaid (the day of the date vnder written)was to be seene in Glene Alley in Suthwark beeing aliue and x weeks olde and iiii. dayes not vnlikly to liue long.
         
         
            ¶ An Admonition vnto the Reader,
            
               THis picture prest in paper white, our natures dooth declare:
               Whose fourme so straunge by natures spite may lerne vs to beware.
            
            
               ¶ By natures spite, what doo I saye? dooth nature rule the roste?
               Nay god it is say wel I may: by whom nature is cost.
            
            
               ¶ The face ful faire, the members all, in order stand and place:
               But yet too muche: by natures thrall, dooth woork a great disgrace.
            
            
               ¶ This ruffeling world in ruffes al rolde, dooth God detest and hate:
               As we may lerne the tale wel tolde, of Children borne of late.
            
            
               What meanes this childe by natures woork: thus Ruffed for to be?
               But by these Ruffes our natures spurk, we might be holde and sée.
            
            
               ¶ Her squares our squaring dooth set out, this here our heres dooth checke:
               This monstrouse monster out of dout, agréeth in eche respect.
            
            
               ¶ Our filthy liues in Piggꝭ are shewd, our Pride this Childe dooth bere:
               Our raggꝭ and Ruffes that are so lewd, beholde her fleshe and here.
            
            
               ¶ Our Beastꝭ and Cattel plagued are, all monstrouse in their shape:
               And eke this Childe dooth wel declare, the pride we vse of late.
            
            
               ¶ Our curled here her here dooth preche, our ruffes and gises gaie:
               Our straunge attire wherto we reche, our flesshe that plese we may.
            
            
               ¶ The poet telleth how Daphenes was, transformd into a trée:
               And Io to a Cow did passe, a straunge thing for to sée.
            
            
               ¶ But poets tales may passe and go, as trifels and vntrueth:
               When ruffes of flesshe as I doo trowe, shall moue vs vnto ruthe.
            
            
               ¶ Deformed are the things we were, deformed is our hart:
               The Lord is wroth with all this géere, repent for fere of smarte.
            
            
               ¶ Pray we the Lord our hartꝭ to turn, whilest we haue time and space:
               Lest that our soules in hel doo burn, for voiding of his grace.
            
            
               ¶ And ye O England whose womākinde, in ruffes doo walke to oft:
               Parswade them stil to bere in minde, this Childe with ruffes so soft.
            
            
               ¶ In fourme as they in nature so, a maid she is in déed:
               God graunt vs grace how euer we go, for to repent with spéed.
            
            FINIS. THE.
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London by Iohn Allde and Richarde Iohnes and are to be solde at the Long Shop adioining 
                  •
               nto S. Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie and at the litle shop adioining to the Northwest doore of Paules Churche. Anno domini. M. D. Lxvi. the .xx. of August
         
      
   

