
   
      
         
            Newes out of France for the gentlemen of England a stratagem most ventrously attempted, and valiantly atchiued by the French King, the 27. day of Iuly. anno Domini 1591 : wherein is desciphered, what trust His Royall Maiestie reposeth on the valour of the English, and their duetifull seruice vnto him at all assayes : newes also touching 16. shippes taken nigh the hauen of deepe, and the discomfiture of the Popes forces transported into France towards the ayde of the leaguers, both concurring on the 28. of Iuly last past : vvith a report of the princely meeting, and honorable conioyning of the whole power of the French King the sixt day of this present moneth of August, consisting of English, Germane, and his owne people.
            G. B.
         
         
            
               1591
            
         
         Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00234
            STC 1030.7
            ESTC S1049
            19999272
            ocm 19999272
            23599
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00234)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23599)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1719:27)
         
         
            
               
                  Newes out of France for the gentlemen of England a stratagem most ventrously attempted, and valiantly atchiued by the French King, the 27. day of Iuly. anno Domini 1591 : wherein is desciphered, what trust His Royall Maiestie reposeth on the valour of the English, and their duetifull seruice vnto him at all assayes : newes also touching 16. shippes taken nigh the hauen of deepe, and the discomfiture of the Popes forces transported into France towards the ayde of the leaguers, both concurring on the 28. of Iuly last past : vvith a report of the princely meeting, and honorable conioyning of the whole power of the French King the sixt day of this present moneth of August, consisting of English, Germane, and his owne people.
                  G. B.
               
               [20] p.   
               
                  For Iohn Kid ...,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1591?]
               
               
                  Dedication signed: G.B.
                  Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).
                  Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-C⁴ (last leaf blank).
                  Imperfect: t.p. cropped at bottom with slight loss of print.
                  Reproduction of original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-08
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-08
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            NEWES
Out of France for the Gentlemen
of England.
A Stratagem moſt ventrouſly attempted, and valiantly
atchiued by the French King, the 27. day of Iuly.
Anno Domini 1591. Wherein is deſciphered, what truſt
his royall Maieſtie repoſeth on the valour of the
Engliſh, and their duetifull ſeruice vnto
him at all aſſayes.
            Newes alſo touching 16. Shippes taken nigh
the Hauen of Deepe, and the diſcomfiture of
the Popes Forces tranſported into France towards
the ayde of the Leaguers, both concurring
on the 28. of Iuly laſt paſt.
            VVith a report of the princely meeting, and honorable
conioyning of the whole power of the French King the
ſixt day of this preſent Moneth of Auguſt, conſiſting
of Engliſh, Germane, and his owne
people.
            Deuteronomie. 1. 30.
            The Lord your God, who goeth before you he ſhall fight for you, according to
all that he did vnto you in Egypt before your eyes.
            Imprinted at London for Iohn Kid and are to be

                  〈…〉
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            In laudem Angliae chariſsimae ſuae
Patriae decaſticon.
            
               ANglia cincta mari' eſt, Anglis mare commoda mille,
               Vt
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   alter globus eſt Anglia cincta mari:
               Anglia cincta mari' eſt, ſacris quià virgo gubernat
               Regibus, hinc foelix Anglia cincta mari:
               Anglia cincta mari' eſt, homines quià moenia tanquam,
               Quos amor vnit, abhinc Anglia cincta mari:
               Anglia cincta mari' eſt, quòd fert Satrapáſque, Ducóſque
               Inuictos Marti', hinc Anglia cincta mari:
               Anglia pſalle Deo, quòd Terra, fretum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   beârunt
               Te ante' alias gentes, Anglia pſalle Deo.
            
            
               Cato.
               Pugna pro patria.
            
         
         
            
            To his friends, the Gentlemen
Readers of England,
health.
            
               GEntlemen, whereas the
old world admired Hanibal
for but ſcaling the
Alpes, Caeſar for building
a bridg ouer Rheyne,
Pompey for ſubduing a
few barbarous Territories,
leaue now to maruaile
at the ſtrategems, the world affordes you
greater maruailes. Looke on the experienced
proweſſe of your owne Countreymen,
farre exceeding the puiſſance of baſe Pagans,
who as they bee preſidents moſt honorable:
ſo are they by your ſteps, and plaudities
to be honoured. Imitate the vertues of
your Anceſtours, that all the world may ring
of your noble acts, of your Anceſtours ſaid I,
nay of our Caualiers yet liuing, who as they
be equall in valour to the beſt of any time; ſo
are they before al other to be followed of your
perſons at this time. Remember the fortitude

of Norris neuer quailed, conſider the magnanimitie
of Williams neuer daunted, and worthie
Yorkes forwardnes neuer impeached: But
what ſhould I compile a catalogue of them,
whoſe valours and vertues are beſt knowne
vnto you: onely this our Soueraigne, and the
whole commonwealth intreates you, that as
whilom your politique Predeceſſours, &amp; now
theſe your martiall Progenitours by their exploytes
haue attayned the heigth of renowne
in the world; ſo yee like renowned Children
of ſo renowned Parents, would by your
couragious enterpriſes brandiſh your
names and fames throughout
the world: facite, &amp;
valete.
            
            
               Yours to commande in all
curteſie.
G. B.

M.of Arte.
            
         
         
            
            A Poem touching the credit of
this Newes, with an item to them,
that takes felicitie in publiſhing
Lies.
            
               NOthing (ſaith Quintilian)
ſo much commēdeth the perſon
of the writer, as the truth
of the ſubiect, he propoſeth to
write: And certes nothing
aduaunced ſo highly Iulius
Caeſars historie, as truth poliſhed
with Eloquence diſcreetely:
for as in the iudgement
of the wiſe the one without the other had argued
great imperfection: ſo both intermingled ſauour of wonderfull
diſcretion, and ſo much the rather, becauſe the
Author ſeemeth estranged from Philautie, &amp; Ambition.
I cannot but praiſe them of ancient time, &amp; touch
ſome in theſe dayes, who either for that they know not, or
care not for truth, or wil not inquire after the truth, wil
be ſure to publiſh nothing but vntruth, miſpending their
time, miſdemeaning their braine, and miſuſing their
pen, no leſſe foes to themſelues, then back friends to the
welminded. I ſpeake this (Gentlemen) for that this
Pamphlet had many dayes ſithence come to your view,
had not theſe apiſh Pamphleters neither left waie for
themſelues, nor other, any further to thruſt out their
heads: But whereas this obortiue Pygmey dare peepe
out, and ſhew his face to the world, vnderſtand that it
is but vnder ſureties, on conditiō, that he neither mutter,

ſpeake, nor write any thing but truth, or at the leaſt
that whereof he can alleadge ſufficient authoritie: who
although hee hath been ſtaied, but not brought to a
blancke, therein taketh ſo much the more heartie grace,
becauſe he knoweth ſome of theſe counterfeites will bee
driuen to a Nonplus: And thus much I will ſaye, and
and in ſaying truly auouch (being priuie to all his proceedings)
that at this time he will not, (nay if he would
he may not) neither would hee if hee might ſpeake any
more than truth, or that hath been credibly informed,
or that commonly among the beſt paſſeth for truth,
wherein if peraduenture hee ſpeake not ſo much, as
ſome of you knowe; or write ſo much, as others heare,
thinke, that neither his eares, nor his eyes are ſo large, as
to heare and ſee all things done in his owne countrey,
much leſſe ouer Sea in a forrayne climate: but accept
his Newes fauourably, as he giues it friendly, and if in
any iot hee ſhall offend you, hee most humbly
craues your pardon, euer remayning
courteouſly at your commande.
            
               G. B.
Magna' eſt veritas, ét preualet.
         
         
            
            A Stratagem moſt venterouſly
attempted, and valiantly atchieued
by the French King, the 27. day of
Iuly Anno Domini,
1591.
            
               THe French King (who for
his ſingular wiſedome deſerueth
to be reckoned a ſecon
Solomon, and inuincible
fortitude an other
Sampſon) hauing drawen
his forces downe into Picardie,
preſented his armes
before the town of Noyan,
&amp; begirt the ſame, where hauing continued the ſiege
ſome few dayes, no daye frée from ſome hard ſkirmiſh,
hot incounter, or daungerous aſſault, the loſſe
for the moſt part falling on the enemies, whereby the
ſaid towne was in ieopardie to haue reuolted (which
was practiſed by ſome) to the King his part, in ſo
much they ſtoode on tearmes of yeelding, but that
they had ſome ſmall hope of ſuccour, and ſupply of
victualles to be ſent them from Roan for the conuoying
whereof (as they vnderſtoode) ſhould bée ſent
Mounſier Tauanas late commaunder of Roan, whoſe
forſes conſiſted of 400. Horſe, and 5000. footemen euery
way well fitted for ſuch a ſeruice, carrying
mindes reſolutely determined (as appeared by the
inſuing conflict) by ſome ſudden ſurpriſe to haue raiſed

the ſiege, yea and indaungered the Kinges owne
perſon, if God (who hath promiſed to defend his ſeruant
Ioſua, that is his faithfull magiſtrates, &amp; bring
the counſailes of the wicked to naught) had not by
ſtraunge meanes miraculouſly diſcouered their malicious
treacherie, making his verie enimies his
willing friendes at ſuch an exigent. For Monſier
Iean de Primadian, Regiſterer to the Biſhoppe of
Roan priuie to their intentions, although (as they
tearme him) a Catholique, yet mooued in conſcience
to croſſe by what meanes poſſible hée could any wicked
action, or attempt that might touch the ſafetie of
the King his ſoueraigne perſon, manifeſted by letters
the day before, the whole plot of treaſon intended
toward his Maieſtie. Whereupon the King no
leſſe deſirous to take the opportunitie, then carefull
to preuent the euil, immediatly that night commaunded
a Cornet of horſe, conducted by a braue French
Captaine to diſcouer the Enimie, who by the breake
of day approched the walles of Roan, where eſtſoones
they had ſpied iſſuing forth, the foreſaid companies
in martch toward Noyan, whereupon they preſently
retired, till by ſome meanes, and in ſome conueniēt
place for the purpoſe happily they might charge
them, or at the leaſt diſcry their determinations: therof
to certify his Maieſty, which (as God would) they
performed luckely: for hauing ambuſhe themſelues
in the ſkirt of a wood, on the ſudden charged the enimies
vauncurriers, ledde by a hardie gentleman (as
it ſeemed.) For notwithſtanding our ſudden charging
them (which was done to the proofe,) whereby
they were well nigh diſcomfited, and that the ſaid
leader hardly eſcaped himſelfe, with ſome few in his
companie by his retreate, yet loth to receiue ſo great
a wound to his reputation, as to be mated, or rather
vanquiſhed by ſo ſmall a troupe, as was ours, ſeconded

ye reſt of his followers, yet fighting: but though
he performed reſolutely his part therein, yet was it
his fortune to be taken hardly with life, by one Mayſter
Thomas Robartes an Engliſh gentleman, the
reſt were all chaſed and taken priſoners, euen at the
front of the enimies battalious, with little loſſe on
our ſide, to the number of ſome 23. men, hurt, taken,
and ſlaine: But the foreſaid Priſoner being with expedition
conuaied to the King, confirmed all that before
by letters his maieſtie had intelligence of, and
diſcloſed alſo, what wayes, and meanes they had
layd downe to ſurpriſe his Maieſties forces. The K.
ſuppoſing it not neceſſarie to ſuffer them make their
approach in ſight of Noyan, forthwith conſulted to
incounter them further of, ſending foorth ſcouces to
barre the newes of their comming from the towne,
determining himſelfe to follow (as he might) with
part of his armie (for hée thought it altogether troubleſome,
and vnméete to diſlodge the whole.) And in
regarde of the reſolute Engliſh (for ſo hée tearmeth
them) whom he ment moſt to imploy in this ſeruice,
of whom alſo he had good experience, for ſuch like ſeruices
heretofore by them performed, his Maieſtie decrees
to vſe the fewer of his owne Nation, and therefore
ſending ſecretly for his approued champion Sir
Roger Williams, imparted vnto him both what had
bin performed, as alſo his intention: of which the redoubted
Cheualier was verie ioyful, &amp; as forward as
valiant, greedily thirſted for the incounter, &amp; thought
euery minute an hower, til they were marching. All
things being put in readines for the iourney, ſuddenly
the eſpialles returned with newes of the enemies
approach, and their order: which Sir Roger Williams
vnderſtanding, euer like himſelfe, and hauing
now (as he thought) found a danger equall to his
heart) which heart through his good fortune hath gotten

a courage to deſpiſe al dangers) earneſtly deſired
his Maieſtie doo him the honour of the firſt incounter,
in regarde of the ſafetie of his Maieſties owne
perſon; which the King through intreatie graunted.
            This requeſt obtayned, and our Vauncurriers in
view of the Enemie, worde was brought the King
thereof, and being (as God would) in a place ſituate
by nature for the purpoſe, his Maieſtie cauſed a ſquadr
on of pikes to march forward ſtrongly armed, and
in the Reregard of them vndiſcouered certaine companies
of Muſquetters on the left ſide, in manner of
an ambuſh (yet as a wing to the mayne Squadron)
was Sir Roger Williams, and with him certaine
Cornets of horſe, and ſome companies of Muſquetters,
to ſecond thoſe of ours, that the Enemie had
ſight of, and were now readie to incounter: on the
right wing was the King with moſt of the horſe in
the fielde, as well ſhot as other, ſomewhat behinde
Sir Roger lying alſo in ambuſcado, to anſwere the
hope of the other, if néede required: But in ſuch ſort▪
as when occaſion was offered, ye ſayd Horſmen with
thoſe of Sir Roger Williams, anſwered his Maieſties
expectation, and ſuddenly purſuing the opportunitie
(while 300. of their horſe were charging our
mayne Battaile, (which ſtrongly indured the ſhock)
incloſed the Enemie, and happily at the firſt incounter,
being hotly maintained, diſcomfited them, and
very vigorouſly purſued the victorie, which (by the
omnipotent power of GOD eſpecially, and triumphant
valour of the Engliſh) being gotten, as hauing
chaſed, and ſlaughtered them almoſt the ſpace
of two leagues, the retreict ſounded, the dead were
ouerlooked, and priſoners numbred: The dead were
many, and captiues ſome fewe, all for the moſt part
men of name, worth raunſoming, amongſt whome

was the Generall himſelfe, Monſieur Tauanas Leiutenant
of Roan, ſore hurt, and likewiſe his Nephew
Commaunder of the Fort of S. Katharins taken
priſoner: which glorie was renownedly atchieued
on all parts the 27. day of Iuly, Anno Domini
1591. The Lord the giuer of victorie bee prayſed
therefore.
            This one thing remayneth yet in this report vntouched,
which I cannot any way omit, and all true
hearted Engliſhmen may bée ioyfull to record. For
the French King both in this pettie battaile, and at
all times els, perceiuing the hearts of the Engliſh
readie preſt to doo him ſeruice, and their haughtie
mindes prompt to attempt any graund enterpriſe,
(whereby either glorie, or gaine may he purchaſed)
as alſo the ſwift forwardnes, and forward ſwiftnes
of his Eagle Sir Roger Williams, to ſoare ouer and
detallant the Martiall foes of ſo Martiall a field, his
Maieſtie well noting it, and in noting it ſcanning
what was beſt to bee done, called them before him,
where yéelding firſt his royall Siſter, and them all
immortall and moſt heartie thankes for their paynefull,
and no leſſe powerfull ſeruice, vttered many
gracious words to the euerlaſting commendation
of all England. Thus farre concerning this heroicall
Stratagem, and wonderfull, and no leſſe worthie
exployte, effected by the flower of Chiualrie, and
mirrour of Curteſie the French King now raigning.
            Newes is alſo brought to the French Ledger of
the taking of 16. Ships of the Leaguers without
any perill, all well laden with commodious Marchandize,
and prouiſion for warre, right againſt and
nigh the Hauen of Deepe the 28. day of Iuly laſt
paſt, which were fraught for Roan, (ſome ſay for

               Newhauen) but by diuine prouidence brought thether.
The mightie GOD of Iſrael neuer ſend vs
worſe newes.
            Newes alſo from the Dukedome of Sauoy, how
Monſieur de Eguidiers Gouernour of his Maieſties
Forces in thoſe parts, incountred the troupes
of horſe, that were ſent into France by the Pope towards
the ſtrengthning of the Leaguers, and ouerthrewe
foure hundred of them a little belowe the
Alpes; the reſt miſerably eſcaping by flight, the 28.
day of Iuly alſo: Some ſay the remnaut is returned
into Italie: others that they yet houer and liuger
in the Countrey. But howſoeuer it be, it is to be
hoped they ſhall haue as infortunate ſucceſſe, as they
haue had hetherto: no other reaſon I can aſſigne
thereof, but this, that God now in theſe letter times
vouchſafeth to bring things to ſpeedie euen▪ there
by to haſten the comming of his Sonne to iudgement,
for that hee hath promiſed to ſhorten thoſe
dayes; and we knowe by all accompts that they are
both likely to bee ſhortened, and drawe to an ende.
For who doubteth but as that butcherly Citie,
(Rome I meane) and bloudie Nation was firſt
founded in bloud, (the one Brother bathing his
hands in the bloud of the other) ſo ſhee ſhall ende in
bloud and abominable deſolation, as her ſtiffenecked
Siſter Ieruſalem did before her. And to beleeue this
I am ſo much ye rather incited, becauſe I both heare
and ſee daily by the omnipotent power, and outſtretched
arme of GOD, that both that Citie, that
Kingdome, and all the friends and adherents of the
ſame, doo come to perpetuall ruine, and vtter deſtruction,
as is now exemplifled by the noble Rebels, and
rebellious Nobles of France: for who eſtéemeth
that euer the Duke de Mayne, or thoſe noble perſonages,

that irreligiouſly reſiſt their God, and proudly
rebell againſt their Soueraigne, could haue béen
brought to ſo extreame miſerie, and grieuous calamitie,
as to flye from Citie to Citie, from Coaſt to
Coaſt, from Countrey to Countrey, and finde no ſafetie,
eyther in inward Conſcience, or outward conuerſation,
if they were not euen thoſe, on whom God
predeſtinated to powre his dreadfull and execrable
vengeance, permitting them like caſtaway Cayne,
no place of ſafegard, but to become runnagates ouer
all the fare of the earth.
            A ſecond reaſon alſo forcible enough I haue to
perſwade me, that euen now the kingdome of Antichriſt
is falling, and ſhortly (the Lorde of hoſtes
knowes how ſoone) will fall, for that another piller
of his chayre, or rather a mayne proppe of his pauili
                  ••…
               
begins to ſhrink, his golden Metropolis (Spaine
I meane) who hauing now many hundred yeares
maintained his Religion, foſtred his ſucklings, panipred
his ſhauelings, defended his Inquiſition, and
furthered his proceedings, in part 
                  •••••
               ereth and is
wearie of hir burden, a burden in deede no leſſe burden
ſome, then comberſome both to bodie and ſoule.
For within theſe fewe dayes, not a moneth ſithence,
variance hapning betweene the chiefe Maſters of
the Inquiſition, and the Kings Arch-ſecretarie, Sarogoſa,
a citie of Aragon (wherin the ſaide Secretarie
was borne (began to take armes againſt the Inquiſition,
and approoue unexpected, and vntrue poſitions
(as they tearmed them) contrarie to their Decretalls,
their Doctours, their Diuines, and diuells.
A Kingdome (ſaith our Sauiour) deuided in itſelfe,
cannot ſtand: certes then the kingdome of Sathan
deuided, muſt needes be ruinated: for as by concord
ſmall things come to perfection: ſo by diſcorde the

greateſt powers, puiſſantes, and principalities, that
euer haue béen in the Worlde, bend to deſtruction.
Weigh the ſtate of the 4. Monarchies both flouriſhing
and declining, the cauſe of their eſtabliſhment,
and originall of their decaye, and yee ſhall finde concord
a meane to the one, and diſcord a mother of the
other: bath bringing foorth ſtrange effects. But to
come nigher, what was the firſt cauſe of planting
the Goſpell (for which ſo many haue, and yet ſpend
their deareſt bloud in France) but their firſt ſupplanting
of common quiet, their vnſpeakeable butcheries,
horrible martyrdonies, and execrable maſſakers,
all doubtles begon, and practiſed by the ſufferance
of God to none other end, but to raiſe vp freſh
feedes, and nouriſh the increaſe of the Goſpell, calling
home thouſands of ſoules elected to his kingdome.
This did France, and wee are daily to hope,
and howerly to pray for the like of Spayne: The
Lord open their eyes to diſcerne white from black,
light from darkenes, truth from errour in due time
according to his good will and pleaſure.
            But leauing Spayne, let vs returne agayne to
France, from wherlie euery day (the Lord for his
merries ſake increaſe it) are heard bliſſefull and moſt
happie notes, his Maieſties affayres ſucceſſiuely
proſpering an all ſides. For ſithence the departine
of our Souldiers from London, which was on the
23. 24. 25. and 26. dayes of Iuly laſt, vnto this 12.
of Auguſt, beſides the Newes already ſet downe,
many matters of great importance haue chaunced,
the veritie whereof (for that I cannot attayne, and
learne the circumſtances directly) I paſſe them ouer
in ſilence, onely of this paſſell inſuing, I haue receiued
credible information, that on the ſixt day of this
moneth, being the 16. after their computation at

               Bloys, his Maieſties Forces all met, and royally counited
themſelues together, at what time the braue
worthies and warlike Gallants of Germany appearing
on horſebacke in Martiall order, euery one
throughly furniſhed with all habiliments neceſſarie,
were firſt welcomed by his Maieſtie, and entertayned
of the Campe with a peale of ordinance ioyfully.
But whereas in the letter (from whence I coppied
out this Newes) all his Forces be named, and
yet no mention made of the Engliſh, I ſuppoſe hée
meant it by the forces of the Almaygnes onely, and
thoſe his own ſubiects that were ſent out of Brytain
to ioyne with his Maieſties hoaſt there, and none otherwiſe.
For there is newes come lately, that the
Earle with his companies remaine yet about
Deipe, there ſtaying a while on weightie conſiderations,
till they heare further. But how euer it bee,
this is moſt certaine, that his Maieſtie hath a goodlie
armie, beſides thoſe warlike troupes the right
Honorable Earle of Eſſex is to come with, who
how they were appointed, is knowne to al England,
and I neede not now diſcourſe.
            Thus farre concerning the proſperous ſucceſſe,
and fortunate progreſſe of this mighty Prince, whom
the Lorde hath preſerued from time to time, from
yeare to yeare, day to day, hower to hower, ſo many
times, yeares, dayes, and howers moſt miraculoufly
from all the furious inuaſions, and cancared conſpiracies
of all his enemies, and made him to triumphe
ouer them, outliuing the moſt part, reclayming by
his vertues the better ſort, and taming by policie the
peruerſe and obſtinate, being ſnatched from the
chawes of the Lyons, deliuered from the gates of
Death, and reſerued from infinite perills (as the
wide world confeſſeth) by diuine prouidence, to none

other end, but to declare the wonderous workes of
the Lorde, and ſhew forth his mightie acts vnto the
Princes of the earth, and eſpecially that Man of ſin,
and ſtrumpet of Babylon, foſter-father of brauls and
battayles among Chriſtian Princes, and generally
the Bloudſucker, Butcher, and tormentour of all
Europe, whome God in due time at his good pleaſure
will by the hand of this his annoynted (as hee
did by Dauid fighting againſt the vncircumciſed,
Philiſtin,) terrifie, torment, ſcourge, and confound,
which he hath begon by his Engliſh Debora firſt, and
wil finiſh in this his Champion, (making them both
mirrours for all Potentates) that all the world, and
eſpecially the kingdome of Antichriſt may acknowledge,
that there is a God that ruleth in Iſrael, and
protecteth the houſe of Iaacob, making his enemies
his footeſtooles. The Lord in mercy graunt it, to the
comfort of his little flock, the aboliſhment of ſinne,
confuſion of his enemies, and eſtabliſhment of his
owne glorie in Sion, and let all faithfull Soldiers,
and loyall ſubiects ſay, Amen, and crie in feruent
zeale of ſpirit, Lord Ieſus come quickely, euen ſo.
Amen.
         
      
      
         
            
            Epilogus.
            
               GEntlemen Readers,
thus though rudelie,
and vntimelie,
yet truly and ſufficientlie,
yee haue
heard the tenour of
this newes, or at the leaſt ſo much, as I
could well fiſh out, for it is a thing altogether
impoſsible, and may paſſe
for a paradox, to reach vnto euerie
particular accidēt. For the newes being
not inacted in our own Countrey,
comming from farre, as alſo wee our
ſelues not preſent, or oculati testes, but
relying on letters, bare reportes, and
hereſay, like testes auriti, wee muſt
needes miſſe of much of the matter, &amp;
ſometimes happily, (or rather vnhappily)
either in too much, or too little
cōmit an abſurditie; But (as I ſaid before)
aſſure your ſelues, wee ſwarue
not wittingly one tittle from truth,
but haue inquired diligently thereafter,
&amp; offred vnto your view nothing

but that we haue ſeen in the letters of
credible perſons, or been inſtructed
of at the hands of men of account, or
that commonly paſſeth for trueth at
the Exchange, or hath been preached
to the French congregation, or is toſſed
vp &amp; down at the Ambaſſadours
houſe in the mouthes of the beſt;
which al in my opinion may ſerue for
a certificate autentique. But leauing
theſe ambages, and cleauing to your
curteſie, I beſeech you in courteſie be
not too curious, but more willing to
lep ouer a block, than wilfull to ſtumble
at a ſtrawe, conſidering the fineſt
Veluet hath his brack, and nothing is
fo currantly writtē, but admitts ſome
crabbed imperfection, &amp; may
captiouſly bee miſconſtred.
Macte vertute
ſitis.
            
         
         
            
            Precatio ad coeleſtem noſtrum
Patrem miſeris hiſce
temporibus.
            
               
                  O Tater patrum rutilas Olimpi
               Qui ſedes ſedes ſuper, ét potenti
               Diriges verbo, tua quae creauit
               Cuncta potestas:
               Da tuis ſeruis placidam quietem,
               Dirimas tristeis (precibus precamur
               Feruidis) lites, refluáſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   caedes
               Sanguine ſedes;
               Arma flacceſcant, timor esto nullus
               Martis, armorum ſonus asperorum
               Dirus abſcedat, valeat
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   pugnae
               Saeua cupido:
               Quid iuuat bellum, (ratio moduſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
               
               Si procul cedant)? amor iste campi
               Peſſimus vadat, propere
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   coeli
               Quaerite regnum:
               
               Charitas creſcat, probit áſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   morum
               Regnet occultis hominum medullis,
               Faxit, vt dignos fidei feramus
               
                  Ʋndique fructus:
               Túnc tuum nomen (Deus ô ſupreme)
               Sempèr extollet precibus, triumphis,
               Laudibus, pſalmis, modulis, choraeis
               Anglia parua.
            
            
               Angli quaſi angeli.
            
            
            
            
         
      
   

