
   
      
         
            Articles to be inquired of, by the churchwardens and sworne men within the Archdea[c]onrie of Worcester in the visitation of the R. Worshipful M. Iohn Iohnson Doctor of Divinitie, Archdeacon of the Archdeaconry of Worcester aforesaide, in this present yeare of our Lorde God, 1609.
            Church of England. Archdeaconry of Worcester.
         
         
            
               1609
            
         
         Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00265
            STC 10372.2
            ESTC S2107
            23030930
            ocm 23030930
            26115
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00265)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26115)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1795:54)
         
         
            
               
                  Articles to be inquired of, by the churchwardens and sworne men within the Archdea[c]onrie of Worcester in the visitation of the R. Worshipful M. Iohn Iohnson Doctor of Divinitie, Archdeacon of the Archdeaconry of Worcester aforesaide, in this present yeare of our Lorde God, 1609.
                  Church of England. Archdeaconry of Worcester.
                  Johnson, John, Archdeacon of Worcester.
               
               9 p.   
               
                  Printed by Ralph Blower,
                  At London :
                  1609.
               
               
                  Signatures: A⁶ (last leaf blank).
                  Reproduction of original in the National Library of Wales.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.
               Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-10
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-10
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Articles to be inquired
of, by the Churchwardens and Sworne
men, within the Archdeaōnrie of Worceſter,
in the Viſitation of the R. Worſhipful, M. Iohn Iohnſon
Doctor of Divinitie, Archdeacon of the Archdeaconry
of Worceſter aforeſaide, in this preſent yeare
of our Lorde God. 1609.
            At London printed by Ralph Blower,
ANNO DOMINI. 1609.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               ❧Mattters enquirable, concerning
the Clergie,
            1 VVHether any do ſerue as Miniſter, or Curat, in your
Church or Chappel, not being lawfully Ordered according
to the Lawes of this Realme of Englande:
And Whether your Miniſter hath obteyned his Benefice,
by any Simonicall Compact, eyther directly, or indirectly.
            2 Whether your Parſon or Vicar be not reſident vpon his Benefice
(and being alowed to preach) and doth he not preach in his owne
perſon, one Sermon euery Sunday: And if hee bee not him-ſealfe a
Preacher allowed: Doth he not procure one Sermon euery Moneth
at the leaſt, to be preached in your Church, and thoſe alſo, by Preachers
lawfully lycenced. And if your Parſon or Vicar reſide not continually
with you, is the cure ſupplyed by a ſufficient Curat yt is learned
and a licenſed Preacher? And how many Sermons haue you had
in your Church or Chappell within thieſe twelue moneths laſt paſt,
and by whom preached?
            3 Whether your Miniſter be negligent in the ſtudy of holy Scriptures,
or workes of his calling, or vſeth he to play at any vn-lawfull
games? I
                  •
                he an Ale-houſe hunter, or a ſower of diſcord, and not a
peace-maker, or is hee Noted. Famed or Suſpected, of any notorious
Crime? Doth he not vſe the Surplice in time of diuine prayers, and
in adminiſtring of the holy Sacraments, and alſo, ſuch comly attire,
as well in the Church, as elſe where, agreeable to his Calling, as is
preſcribed by the Canons of the Cōuocation lately ſet foorth by ye 
               Kings
Aucthority: Or hath he admitted any vnlawfully begotten wt Childe
to her publique Thankes-giuing in the Church after her Deliuery:

otherwiſe, then in a white ſhéets, in forme of a penitent perſon: Or
hath he receiued to ye holy Communion, any excommunicat perſon, or
Sciſmatike, or any knowne to be notorious Offenders, without apparant
ſignes of Repentance: Or hath hee reiected or put backe any
from ye Communion, without good &amp; iuſt cauſe therein.
            4 Whether doth not your miniſter euery Sunday, when there is
no Sermon, reade ſome part of an Homilie? Doth he not in ye church
before Evening prayer, teach▪ inſtruct &amp; exammin the Youth of Conuenient
age, in ye Cathechiſme &amp; principles of Religion. And whether
vppon Wednſdayes &amp; Fridayes, the Letante, and other prayers
be not read in the Church as to inioyned. And doth not your miniſter
vſe the dayes of per-ambulation accuſtomed, and in ſuch manner alſo,
as is allowable▪ and no otherwiſe.
            5 Whether doth your miniſter ſerue two cures, or doth any ſerue
as Curat in your pariſh, or preach, or any teach ſchoole publiquely, or
in any priuat houſe not licenſed vnder yt Ordinaries Seale.
            6 Whether hath your miniſter made any waſt or ſpoyle of his benefice,
or ſuffreth be his Chauncell, or houſes, or any part thereof, 
                  •
               
be vn-repayred, or to fall into ruin or decay.
            7 Whether hath your Miniſter neglected the publique reading 
                  ••
               
the late Canons and Conſtitutions in the Church, as is required 
                  ••
               
the Intimating of holidaies and faſting daies appointed to be kept
or the ſetting downe in the Church Regiſtrie, and publiſhing openli
in the Church vppon the Saboth daies: the names of all ſuch as we
                  ••
               
Baptized Maried and Buried the whole weeke before. And hath &amp;
not one Key of the Coffer where the Regiſter booke concerning to
premiſſes is kept.
            8 Whether your Miniſter, hath admitted any of another pariſh 
                  •
               
receiue the hofte Communion in dispariſh Church, or hath adminiſtred
the holy Communion to any which doe 
                  〈◊〉
                kneele at the re
               
                  •
               y
                  •
               ing

                  〈◊〉
               
               ▪ 
               
                  〈…〉
                
               
excomunicate perſons publiquelie in the Church, till he receiue a warrant
to the Contrarie, or a Certificate of their Abſolutions from the
office where they were excommunicate. Hath he maried any within
the Degrees of Conſanguinitie, or affinitie forbidden, or in time prohibited
or without banes of Matrimony thrice ſolemlie, aſked in the
Church three ſeuerall ſundaies or holidaies vnles it be by licence of the
ordinarie vnder ſeale: or at any other time of the daie
                  •
                then betwixt
the howers of eight and Twelue of the Clocke in the forenone, or
that your miniſter admitted any to be God fathers or God mothers to
any Child in your pariſh before he or ſhe ſuch god father or godmother
hath bin partaker of the holie Communion.
            
               
                  
                     •
                   Matters enquirable concerning the laytie.
               9 WHether haue you not in your Chucrh or Chappell, The booke
of common prayer lately ſet foorth by the Kings Authoritie,
the great Engliſh Bible, of the trāſlations Authoriſed, ye two volumes,
and all other bookes commaunded, a table of the Ten Commaundements,
and a Table of the degrées forbidding mariag, a conueneint
Pulpit, a Comelis Communion table on a frame, A recent Linnen
Cloath to couer the ſaid Table, with ſome other Couering or Carpet
of ſilke or ſuch like, A Communion Cuppe and Couer of ſiluer. A faire
ſtanding pot of Pewter or purer me
                     •••
                  l for the Communion wine, A
decent Surpleſſe wt ſléeues, A Font of ſtone for Baptiſing of Children
A Cheſt for the almes Box and another for the Regiſter booke with
three locks and Keyes a péecs, And to there a tranſcript yearely giuen
vp to the ordinarie of all Chriſtnings weddings and burialls as the
Lawes requier.
               10 Whether is your Church and Chauncell in the roofe walles,

windowes ſeates and pauement, and in euery other part thereof well
and ſufficientlie repaired. And the Churchyard well and ſufficientlie
with good ra
                     •
                  les and ſufficient p
                     •
                  les, or ſtone wall, fenced and kept
ſwéet and cleane, if not, in whoſe default, and are your bells and bellropes
&amp; all other apurtenantes thereto belonging in good order or not.
               11 Whether haue not your Churchw, from time, to time, truelie
leuied xij d for euerie ſunday, of thoſe which abſent themſelues from
their pariſh Church to the vſe of the poore or deteyne they any of the
common 
                     ••
                  ocke or 
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  e they not made and deliuered vp a iuſt accompt
to the pariſhioners of all their receipts and burſements, Whether is
the poore-mans Box orderlie kept, and ſuch Somes of Money as are
giuen diſtributed too the poore accordingly, or haue your Churchwardens
continued in that office aboue one yeare without a new election.
And were your churchwardens elected in the Eaſter weeke as by the
late canons Authoriſed by his Maieſtie, is required.
               12 Whether is there any in your pariſh that doe refuſe to come to
their pariſh church or chappell to diuine prayers and Sermones vpon
the Lords days commonly called Sundaies or vppon al other feſtiual
or holidaies, appointed by his Maieſties authoritie, or any that doe
not orderlie frequent the ſame, and doe not reſort to their ſaid church,
or chappell vpon ſuch daies to diuine praiers and Sermons: and there
behaue not themſelues ſoblery and diſcreetlie in hearing attentiuely
the Scriptures reade and in ioyning with the Miniſter and people,
in prayers as becometh, or doe not reuerently remaine with their
heads vncouered at ſuch times and places aforeſaid. And whether the
ſaid pariſhioners eſpeciallie one of euery houſe at leaſt doe not frequent
their ſaid church or chappell to diuine prayers vppon wedneſdaies
and Fridaies.
               13 Whether any in your pariſh being of the Age of xvj yeares or
aboue, haue not receiued the holy communion in your pariſh church
or chappel, and that humbly kneeling, three ſeverall times in this laſt
yeare at the leaſt, of which Eaſter to be one, or any that haue not
brought or ſeat their children Seruants and youth to the church vpon

Sundaies aud holidaies in the afternoone to be catechiſed according to
the order latelie appointed by the canons. And whether any doe not
humblie kneele at the generall confeſſions and praiers and at their receiuing
the holy communion or any that vſe any talking walking or
other vnſeemly behauiour in the church or churchyard in time of deuine
Seruice and Sacrament or doe any way diſturbs common praiers
Preaching or other exerciſes of religion.
               14 Whether▪ any Dauncers players of Enterludes or ſuch like, or
any other doe Daunce play or vſe any vnſeemly parts or games, or
ſell any victualls or other Marchandiſe in the church or churchyard
or doe vſe to ſit in the ſtreet, tauernes, Alehowſes or at home during
ſeruice time and exerciſes of gods Worſhip▪ and is there any that
ſuffer any ſuch in their Houſes at ſeruice time, and who be they: or be
there any feaſtes drinckings, Churchales, temporall Courtes, laye
Iuries muſters, or other prophane vſage in the Church or churchyard
or any ſuperſtitious ringing of belles: vppon holidaies or Eues
abrogated by authoritye.
               15 Whether any in your pariſh vppon the Saboth daies or holidaies
doe vſe their Trade, or doe any other woorke or labour as brewing
baking, waſhing, or ſuch like, or doe open their ſhoppes for ſale of
wares vppon thoſe daies.
               16 Whether is there any in your pariſh knowen or ſuſpected to reſort
or to go to any Maſſe▪ or to any other ſuch ſecret meetings any
maynteyners of ſuperſtition, or falſe Opinions, contrarie to the booke
of common praier or Articles of religion or any that ſpeake againſt
the Eſtabliſhed gouerment of the church in this Realme.
               17 Whether is there in your Pariſh, any Childe or Children which
haue bin Baptized by any midwife, or other laye perſon, whoe they be
that haue ſee donne, and what and who bee the parents of ſuch childe
or children and whether any childe hath not bin brought to the church
to be Baptized, or doth any perſon take vpon him or her to be godfather
or godmother to any child before he or ſhe hath receiued the holie communion.
               
                  
18 Whether haue you a Parriſh clarke in your church or chappell,
was he choſen by the Miniſter, is he dutifull and dilligent to the Miniſter,
and learned, and ſufficient to diſcharge his place. And doth he
orderly Demeane himſelfe and diſcharge his ſaid office accordingly
as he ought, and is there any that with-hold his accuſtomed duties
from him.
               19 Whether are ther any in your pariſh who are known ſuſpected or
famed, to be of euil life, to be inceſtuous perſons Adulterers, fornicators,

                     •
                  au
                     •
                  s, or barhorers of incontinent perſōs in their houſes, or who
haue conueyed them away before they haue made ſatiſfaction to the
congregation offended. Any drunkards, Ribands, Kailers, common
ſlaunderers makers of libels, ſcoulds or ſowers of diſcord, any ſwearors,
Blaſphemers of Gods name, or prophaners of his Saboth, or any
that haue fought, or ſtricken, or brawled in the Church, or churchyarde.
               20 Whether is ther any in your pariſh which hath, or hath had, at one
time two wiues, or any woeman two Huſbandes any maryed with
in the Degrees of Conſanguinitie or affinitie forbidden. Any diuerced
keeping companie ſtil together. Any maried which without order of
lawe liue a ſunder and not together as man and wife, Any married
which haue made precontracts to others or any maried without banes
thrice ſolemly aſked in the Church three ſeueral ſundaies or holidaies
in the ſeuerall places of their aboade, otherwiſe then by licence of the
ordinarie, or anie that marry foorth of the pariſh Church where they
dwell, or that marry without Conſent of their parents or gardians
or at anie other time of the daie then betwixt the howers of eight
and twelue in the forenoone.
               21. Whether is there any in your pariſh that haue or doe take any
Vſurie or intereſt aboue Ten in the hundred for a yeare for Lending
their Money Corne &amp;c. or by any indirect meanes and Colourable
practiſes in bargaining, doe vſe that Deteſtable Crime, to the pinching

and eating by of the Poore: by their Exceſſiue gaine.
               22 Whether is there any in your Pariſh that doe preſume to entermeddle
or Deale with the goods of any Deceaſed before the will (if
he made any) be Lawfuly proued, or before Adminſtration (if he died
inteſtate) be duly committed vnto him vnder ſeale, or is there any
hinderers of the Performans of ſuch will or Adminiſtration. Any
forgets or Changers of teſtaments or any Executors that haue not
fullfilled the Teſtators will, Eſpeciallie in not paieing Legacies giuen
to the Church, to the poore, to amend High waies or to ſuch like good
and Godly vſes.
               23 Whether haue your Churchwardens and ſidemen trulie Noted
and ſet downe in writing in a paper booke for that purpoſe, the names
of all Preachers which come to them from any other place, and hath
euery ſuch Preacher Subſcribed his name therto with the day when
he preached, and the name of the Buſhop of whom he had Licence to
preach according to the 52 Canon.
               24 Generallie Whether doe you know any other Eccleſiaſticall
matter, worthy of preſenting or no. And if you do, by the oathes you
haue Taken you ſhall trulie preſent the ſame, aſwell now as heereafter,
when it ſhall come to your knowledg.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
   

