
   
      
         
            Articles to be enquired of by the church-wardens and sworne-men, within the diocesse of Winchester in the visitation of the Reuerend Father in God, Thomas Bishop of Winton, in his triennall visitation, holden 1603 in the first yeere of the raigne of Our Most Gracious Soueraigne Lord, Iames by the grace of God King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c.
            Church of England. Diocese of Winchester. Bishop (1597-1616 : Bilson)
         
         
            
               1603
            
         
         Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00263
            STC 10356.5
            ESTC S874
            22916244
            ocm 22916244
            25883
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00263)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25883)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1777:19)
         
         
            
               
                  Articles to be enquired of by the church-wardens and sworne-men, within the diocesse of Winchester in the visitation of the Reuerend Father in God, Thomas Bishop of Winton, in his triennall visitation, holden 1603 in the first yeere of the raigne of Our Most Gracious Soueraigne Lord, Iames by the grace of God King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c.
                  Church of England. Diocese of Winchester. Bishop (1597-1616 : Bilson)
                  Bilson, Thomas, 1546 or 7-1616.
               
               [16] p.   
               
                  By Thomas Purfoot,
                  Printed at London :
                  1603.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-B⁴.
                  Reproduction of original in the Magdalene College (University of Cambridge). Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.
               Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.
            
         
      
      
         
            2000-00
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2001-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-02
            TCP Staff (Oxford)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-02
            TCP Staff (Oxford)Text and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-03
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               ARTICLES
To be enquired of by
the Church-wardens and Swornemen,
within the Diocesse of Winchester
in the Visitation of the reuerend Father
in God, Thomas Bishop of Winton, in
his Triennall Visitation, holden
1603.
            In the first yeere of the raigne of our most gracious
Soueraigne Lord, Iames by the grace of God
King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland,
defender of the Faith, &amp;c.
            
            Printed at London by Thomas
Purfoot. 1603.
         
         
            
            THe Church-wardens and their
assistants are straightly required
to read or heare all these
Articles read ouer vnto them,
and diligently to consider and enquire
thereof, betweene the time of the deliuery
hereof vnto them, and the making of their
presentments.
         
      
      
         
            
            Articles to bee enquired of, by the Church-wardens and
Sworne-men, within the Diocesse of Winchester, and the trueth
thereof to be by them, vpon their oathes, certainely presented
to the Bishop or his Deputie, with perticular answere to euerie
Article.
            
               Articles concerning the Cleargie.
               
                  WHether your common prayer be read by your
Minister in your Churches or Chappels
plainly and reuerently vpon all Sundayes
and Holydaies, and other daies prescribed,
in such order as is set foorth in the Booke of
common praier, authorized by the Lawes of
this Realme, without any innouation, or change of any
part thereof at due and conuenient houres? And whether the
holy Sacraments be likewise ministred reuerently in such
manner, as by the Booke of common praier is appointed.
                  2 Item, whether any person, not being ordered, at the
least a Deacon, hath attempted to say common praier openly
in your Church or Chappell, or to solemnize matrimonie,
or administer the Sacrament of Baptisme.
                  3 Item, whether the Church-wardens haue permitted or
do suffer any Curator Minister to serue your Church before
he be admitted and examined by the Ordinarie in writing,
and doe shew his licence vnder seale vnto the Church-wardens:
and whether any Curate doe serue two Cures in one
day.
                  
                     
4 Item, whether your Minister not being a Preacher, do
euerie Sunday when there is no Sermon, read distinctly
and plainely, some part of the Homilies prescribed and set
forth by the Queens authoritie to be read: and whether any
Minister, not admitted by the Ordinarie, or by other lawfull
authoritie, doe expound any scripture or manner of
doctrine, and thereby omit and leaue off the reading of Homilies:
or whether any in your Parish doe depraue or speake
against the Homilies, and the vse of them in the Church?
                  5 Item, whether your Minister doe at the administration
of the Lords Supper, reuerently kneele when himselfe receiueth
it, according to the Booke of common praier: and
whether the communicants themselues in like sort doe reuerently
kneele vppon their knees at the time of the receiuing
thereof: or whether he doe administer it confusedly, to some
kneeling, to some sitting, and to some standing.
                  6 Item, whether your preacher, in his praier made in his
Sermon, whether it be at the beginning, middle, or end therof,
doe vse or omit at any time the praier for his Maiestie,
with his whole title giuen him as King of England, Scotland,
Fraunce, and Ireland, desender of the faith, &amp;c. of all
causes, and ouer all persons within his Maiesties Dominion,
as well ecclesiasticall as temporall, next and immediatly
vnder God supreame Gouernour? and for our most gracious
Queene, the Prince of Wales their eldest Sonne, and
all their royall Progenie.
                  7 Item, whether any Lectures. Cenuenticles, or priuate
meetings, be read or vsed within your Parishes, either publique
in the Church, or priuately in any house, by any not
licenced thereto by the Ordinary? Or whether any such Reader
do teach any doctrine of innouation, to withdraw ye people
from due obedience to the ordinances of the Church, set
foorth by publique authoritie, or to cause them to forbeare
participating in prayer and sacraments with our Church?
                  
                     
8 Item, how many sermons hath your Parson or Uicar
preached in his owne Church within this yeere past. And if
your Parson or Uicar be not a preacher, how many sermons
hath he procured to be preached there in this yeere past: and
who hath preached them, and whether were they that did
preach them, licensed or no? and by whom?
                  9 Item, whether your Minister hath receiued to the holy
communion, any persons which be not of his owne Parish,
without testimony from the minister of the place where they
dwell what they be, that it may appeare they be not persons
excommunicate, or otherwise notorious offenders?
                  10 Item, whether your Minister doe euerie Sunday or
holiday, openly in the Church, call for, heare, and instruct all
the children, apprentices and seruants that be of conuenient
age within your Parish, or at the least, so many of them
(by course) as the time will serue, and as he may well heare
and instruct for one halfe houre, (at the least) before or after
Euening praier; in the ten commandements, the articles of
the beleefe, the Lords praier, and the sacraments, and diligently
examine and teach them the Catechisme, as it is now
allowed, and set forth in the Booke of common prayer: and
whether (to that purpose) he hath taken the names of them
all, and by course call certaine of them (by name) euery Sunday
and Holiday to come to the teaching of this Catechisme:
and if the Parents &amp; Master be slacke in sending them, whether
he hath called vpon the churchwardens to present them?
                  11 Item, whether your Parson, Uicar, or Curate, or other
Minister in your Church or Chappell, hath admitted to
the holy communion any publicke excommunicate person, or
any open or notorious fornicator, adulterer, or euill liuer,
by whom publicke offence is giuen, without due pennance
first done, to the satisfaction of the congregation, enioyned
him by his Ordinarie.
                  12 Item, whether your Preachers or Ministers be peacemakers,

and exhort their Parishioners to obedience towards
their Prince, and all other that be in authoritie, and to the
gouernement ecclesiasticall now established, and to charitie
and mutuall loue among themselues: whether they be diligent
in visiting the sicke, and comforting them?
                  13 Item, whether any person hath preached, declared, or
spoken any thing in derogation of the Book of cōmon praier,
which is set forth by the Lawes of this Realme, dispraising
or deprauing the same, or any thing therein contained; or
against the Preachers or Ministers of the word and sacraments?
                  14 Item, whether there be prouided in your Parish one
conuenient parchment Book? And whether therin are written
the names of all persons, which haue beene christened,
married, or buried in that Parish since the beginning of the
raigne of our late most gracious Soueraigne Ladie Queene
Elizabeth? And whether euerie page of that Booke being filled
with the inscription of those names be subscribed by the
Minister and Church-wardens? And whether euerie Sunday
after morning or euening praier, the Minister in the
presence of the Churchwardens, doe write into that parchment
booke, the names of all persons that haue been christeneed,
married, or buried in the Parish the weeke before?
And immediatly after the wr
                        •
                     ting of all the saide names,
whether the Minister hath openly and distinctly read in the
Church all the said names of that precedent weeke, and the
day and moneth of the christening, marriage, or buriall of euerie
such person. And whether there bee prouided in the
Church a conuenient coffer with three locks and keyes, for
the sure keeping of that Register parchment booke? And whether
the Minister and both the Church-wardens, hauing euerie
of them one of the sayd keyes in their custodie, doe safely
keepe the said Register Booke in the sayd coffer, according
as hath been by the Canons of this Church of England prouided.
                  
                     
15 Item, whether your Ministers doe keepe any man or
woman in their houses, suspected to be incontinent persons,
or bee themselues giuen to drunkennesse, haunters of Tauernes,
ale-houses, or suspected places, or otherwise suspected
of any notorious crime, or light disordered behauiour,
or haue giuen any euill example of life, or vse vnseemely apparell
in colours, guards, or light fashions.
                  16 Item, whether for the retaining of the perambulation
of the circuit of your Parish, the Minister, Churchwardens,
and certain substantiall men of the Parish, in the dates
of the Rogations (commonly called Gang-daies) walke the
accustomed bounds of your parish? whether in the same they
vse any superstitious or popish ceremonie, but onely meditate
of Gods mercie, giue him thankes for blessing of the
earth, as is by the law of the Church set downe.
                  17 Item, whether there be any in your Parish that readeth
any priuate lectures, or vseth expositions of the Scriptures
in any priuate mans house whatsoeuer, contrarie to
law? and whether any preach, and doe not at certaine times
in the yeere minister the Sacraments in their owne persons,
and in such Church where he readeth his Lecture.
                  18 Item, whether any Parson, Uicar, or Minister hath
procured himselfe to bee admitted into sacred orders by any
corrupt meanes of money, reward, guift, or promise of reward,
or by any symonicall compact hath procured his benefice,
directly or indirectly, or be thereof by common same suspected
or defamed.
                  19 Item, whether your Minister doe reiect those women
(being married) which do come to the Church to giue thanks
after child birth, according to the order set down in the booke
of common prayer.
                  20 Item, whether your Minister haue married any person,
not being three seuer all sundaies lawfully asked in their

Parish churches, according to the book of common prayer, or
not being sufficiently licensed thereunto, by license from the
L. Bishop of Winchester his officers.
                  21 Item, whether your Parsons and Uicars doe maintaine
and keep in due reparations, their mansion houses and
other edifices belonging to their ecclesiasticall liuings, and
not suffer them to fall into ruine and decay: and whether
your almeshouses, hospitals, and spittles, be well and godly
vsed, according to the foundation and auncient ordinances
of the same: and whether there be any other placed in them
than poore, impotent, and needie persons, that haue not
wherewith, or whereby to liue?
               
            
            
               Articles concerning the Churchwardens and
their assistants.
               
                  ITem, whether you haue in your Parish Churches and
Chappels, all things necessarie and requisite for common
praier and administration of the Sacraments: specially the
booke of common praier with the new Kalender, two Psalters,
the English Bible in the largest volume, the Table of
the ten commaundements, a conuenient Pulpit well placed,
a comely and decent Table standing on a frame, for the holy
communion, with a faire linnen cloath to lay vppon the
same, and some couering of silke, buckeram, or other such like,
for the cleane keeping thereof, a faire and comely communion
cup of siluer, and a couer of siluer for the same, which may
serue also for the ministration of the communion bread, and
a decent large surplesse with sleeues.
                  2 Item, whether your Churches, and Chappels, with the
chancell, be well and sufficiently repaired and kept, without
abuse of any thing: and whether your churchyards be well
fenced and cleanly kept: and if any part thereof be in decay,
through whose default it is so, and whether any strife hath
growne amongst your neighbours, about pewes or seats in
the Church?
                  
                     3 Item, whether those decayes of your Chauncels and
Churches which were lately vppon speciall inquisition presented:
haue been and are sufficiently repaired sithence that
time according to former commandement giuen to that purpose,
or how much thereof doe yet remaine vndecent, ruinous,
or in any decay, and to what value, &amp; by whose fault?
                  4 Item, whether your Font or Baptisteries be remooued
from the place where they were woont to stand: or whether
any persons (leauing the vse of them) doe christen or baptize
in basons, or other prophane vessels, not accustomably used
in the Church before time.
                  5 Item, whether the Schoolemasters within your Parish,
openly or priuately in any mans house, be of good and sincere
religion, life and conuersation, and be diligent in teaching
and bringing vp of youth, and whether with their Schollers
they do resort orderly on Sundaies and Holidaies to church:
and whether your Schoolemasters doe receiue the holy communion
so oft as they ought to do, and so many of their schollers
as be of sufficient age and capacitie to receiue: and whether
they haue ben examined, allowed, and licensed for schoolmaisters
by the Ordinarie or his officers in that behalfe?
                  6 Item, whether all Houshoulders in your Parish haue
caused their children, seruants, and apprentices, both mankind
and womankind, (being aboue seauen yeeres of age)
which haue not learned the Catechisme, to come to the church
on Sundaies and Holydaies at the times appointed for catechizing,
and there diligently and obediently to heare: and
what be the names of those that haue not caused their children,
seruants, and apprentices, so to come to the Church to
be instructed and examined?
                  7 Item, whether doe any worke or keepe any shop, or any
part of their shop open vpon the Saboath daies, or vpon any
Holydaies, (appointed by the lawes of the Realme to be kept

holyday, or doe vse any worke or labour vpon those daies.
                  8 Item, whether you your selues, or the Churchwardens
in the yeeres before, haue suffered any vnmarried woman
(being begotten with child) to go out of the Parish before she
hath done penance: or any man defamed of whoredom, to depart
vnpunished: and forth of whose houses they haue gone
away with vnpunished.
                  9 Item, whether there be any in your Parish, which for
any cause whatsoeuer, wilfully forbeare to come to Church,
to publique praier, or to heare Gods word preached, pretending
it vnlawfull to come to our assemblies, as the church of
England now standeth: and how many moneths they and
euerie of them haue so absented themselues by the space of
one yeere last past.
                  10 Item, whether any doe refuse to receiue the holy communion
at their owne Ministers hand, either because he is
not a preacher, or because he duely obserueth y• order of ministration,
appointed by the booke, and who they be that doe go
from their owne Parish to receiue at any other Ministers
hands: and whether any of your Parishioners (hauing a
preacher to their Minister) doe absent themselues from his
sermons, and resort to other places to heare other Preachers?
                  11 Item, whether the people of your Parish (especially
housholders, hauing not lawfull excuse to be absent) doe diligently
themselues resort with their children and seruants,
to the Parish Church or Chappell on holydaies, and cheefely
on the sundaies, to Morning and Euening prayer, or vppon
reasonable let thereof, to some vsuall place where common
praier is vsed, and then and there abide orderly and soberly
during the time of common praier, Homilies, Sermons, and
other seruice of God there vsed, reuerently and deuoutly giuing
themselues to the hearing therof, and who they be that
negligently absent themselues, or come verie late to the
Church, or vse any gaming or pastime abroad, or in any

house, or sit in the street, Churchyard, or in any tauerne or
alehouse vpon the Saboth or holiday, in the time of common
prayer, Sermon, or reading of ye Homilies, either before or
after noone?
                  12 Item, whether there be within your Parish any Inkeepers,
ale-wiues, victuallers or tiplers, that suffer or doe admit
any person or persons in their houses to eate, drinke, or
play at cards, tables, or such like games in the time of common
praier or Sermon on the Sundaies or Holydaies: and
whether any Butchers or others that commonly vse to sell
meat or other things, doe make sale in the time of common
praier, preaching or reading of Homilies: and whether in
any Faires or common Markets (falling vpon the Sunday)
there be any shewing of any wares before Morning prayer
be done: and whether any Markets and selling of wares be
vsed or suffered in any churchyards, by common packemen
or pedlers going about, or any such people either of your parish,
or not?
                  13 Item, whether the Church-wardens of the last yeere
haue giuen to the Parish a iust account of the Church goods
and rents that were committed to their charge, according to
the custome that hath been afore time vsed: and what Church
goods they or any other haue sould, and to whom: and whether
to the profit of your Church, or no? and what hath been
done with the monney thereof comming?
                  14 Item, whether any of your parish (being of conuenient
age) haue not receiued the holy communion thrice in euarie
yeere at the least, and namely at Easter, or thereabouts
for once: and what their names are, or which (at their receiuing)
haue not signified the same before to your Parson, Uicar,
or Curate, that he might conueniently examine them:
and who haue refused to come to him to be examined?
                  15 Item, Whether there be any in your Parish, that administer
the goods of those that be dead without lawfull authoritie,

or any that suppresse the last will of the dead, or any
Executors that haue not fulfilled their Testators Will, especially
in paying of Legacies giuen to the Church, or to other
good and godly vses, as to the rel
                        •
                     ef
                        •
                      of pouertie, to helplesse
Orphanes, poore Schollers, poore Maidens mariages, high
waies, and such like: and by whom they are so detained?
                  16 Item, whether there be any in your parish that hath
or doth offend contrarie to the Statute made in the 37. yeere
of the Raigne of King Henrie the eight for the reformation
of Usurie, and reuiued by an Act made the thirteenth yeere
of the raigne of the late Queene Elizabeth, taking aboue the
rate of ten pounds for the lending of an hundred pounds by
the yeere: and what be the names of such offendours?
                  17 Item, whether your Minister, or any of the Parish,
without the consent of the Ordinarie, haue caused any to do
penance or bee punished, either openly or otherwise, for any
crime punishable by the Ecclesiasticall lawes onely, and
what be the names of the parties that haue been so punished,
and in what manner?
                  18 Item, whether there bee amongst you any that vse
sorcery or witchcraft, punishable by the Ecclesiasticall laws,
or that bee suspected of the same, and whether any vse any
charmes, or vnlawfull praiers: and whether any doe resort
to any such for helpe and counsaile, and what bee the names
both of such as vse it, and of such as resort vnto them for help?
                  19 Item, whether there bee among you, any blasphemer
of the name of God great or often swearers, adulterers, fornicators,
incestuous persons, bawdes or receiuers of incontinent
persons, or harbourers of women with child which be
vnmarried, conueving or suffering them to goe away before
they doe any penance, or make satisfaction to the congregation,
or any that be vehemently suspected of any such fault: any
drunkards, or ribawdes, or any that be malitious, contentious,
or vncharitable persons, common slaunderers of their

neighbours, raylers, scolders, or sowers of discord between
neighbours, and especially raylers against Ministers, and against
their mariage.
                  20 Item, whether there bee any in these parts that haue
married within the degrees of affinitie or consanguinitie, by
the lawes of God forbidden, or any, that being diuorsed or
separated for the same, do yet notwithstanding cohabite and
keepe company still together, or any that being maried without
those degrees, haue vnlawfully forsaken their wiues or
husbands and maried others, any man that hath two wiues,
or woman that hath two husbands, any that being diuorced
or separated asunder haue maried againe, any that haue maried
and contracted themselues without the consent of their
parents, tutors, and gouernours, any that haue maried without
banes thrice solemnly asked, any couples married that
liue not together, but slaunderously liue apart.
                  21 Item, whether your Minister and Church-wardens
haue suffered any lord of misrule or summer Lords or ladies,
or any disguised persons, or May-games, or morice dancers,
at any time to come vnreuerently into the church or churchyard,
and there to daunce or pl
                        •
                     y, in the time of common
Praier, Seruice, or Sermon vppon the Saboath day?
                  22 Item, whether any within your Parishes doe resort
vnto barnes, fields, woo
                        ••
                     , or priuate houses for any extraordinary
expositions of scriptures, or conferences together, and
so doe (as it were 
                        •
                     make a seuerall Church or sect vnto themselves,
or be drawers, or perswaders of others to any such
schismaticall sect, and in whose houses, or in what places
haue you heard of any such meetings.
                  23 Item, whethe
                        •
                      there be any of your parish known or
suspected to conc
                        ••
                     le o
                        •
                      keep hiddē in their house, any Masse
books or other books of Popery &amp; superstision, or any chalices,
copes, vestiments, or other like superstitious ornamentes in
their forme and fashion vndefacet, for some exercise of their

superstition, as may be suspected, if they may haue time or
opportunitie theretoo: or whether any be known or suspected
to receiue any such bookes or like trumperie from beyond the
seas, and so disperse and carrie them abroad to others.
                  24 Itē, whether any in your parish, maried in any priuat
houses since the last visitation, haue bin knowne or suspected
to haue bin maried by any popish priest, or in any other order
then is appointed by the church of England.
                  25 Item, whether any children borne within your parish
do remaine vnbaptized, or be suspected to be baptized by any
popish priest, Seminarie, or Iesuite: or whether any Recusants
liue together as man and wife, who are not knowen
to be maried according to the lawes of this Realme.
                  26 Item, whether you know any notorious Recusant,
who obstinately refuseth to be partaker, with the church of
England in publique praier &amp; hearing the word of God preached,
being for his disobedience and contempt excommunicated,
and so dying excommunicate, to be buried in christian
buriall, not hauing before his death sought to be absolued.
                  27 Item, whether any of the stocks appertaining to the
church, be substracted by any person, and to what value, and
by whom.
               
               Generally, what faults soeuer you know to be within
your parishes not specified or mentioned in these Articles, &amp;
punishable by the Ecclesiastical laws, you shall by vertue of
your oath aforesaide duely and truely present them to your
Ordinarie, that reformation may be had accordingly.
            
            
               
               These subscribed Articles, are specially enioyned and commanded
by the said Reuerend father, to be from time to time obserued
by the Minister and Churchwardens of euery church.
               
                  1 THat henceforth the Church-wardens shall not permit
any Minister to serue the cure of their church
vntill the minister doe first shew forth vnto the said churchwardens
his licence thereto, vnder the hand and seale of the
said Bishop of Winchester, or of his Chancellor, vpon paine
of contempt.
                  2 Item, that from henceforth they doe not admit any minister
to preach in their cures, but only such as already be,
or henceforth first shall be allowed thereto, vnder the hand
or seale of the L. Archbishop of Canterburie his Grace, or of
the said Bishop of Winchester.
                  3 Item, that a true copy of the names, daies, and month
of the christning, marying, and burial of all persons in euery
parish yeerely subscribed vnder the hands of the minister and
church-wardens, testifying their collation and agreement of
the said copie with the said parchment booke, shall be yeerely
exhibited into the Registry of the Bishoprick of Winchester,
in the yeerely visitations of the Bishop or his Chancellor.
                  4 Item, that in this triennall visitatiō, the names of all
lay men presuming, or which by any fauour are tollerated to
read diuine seruice in any church, be diligently enquired &amp;
presented: &amp; that henceforth ye churchwardens vpon paine of
law, do not permit any lay man to read diuine seruice in the
church, without y• speciall licence of the bishop of Winchester
or of his chancellor vnder their hand &amp; seale, of which licenses
there shall remaine record in the registry of the said Bishop.
                  5 Item, that the churchwardens do vpon the saboth daies
diligently obserue the careles &amp; negligent commers to diuine
seruice, &amp; after admonition giuen by the minister and church
wardens, do at y• least at euery visitation, present the names

of such negligent persons, &amp; the seueral days of their absence.
                  6 Item, that euery beneficed man, not being a preacher
allowed by publique authoritie, and the farmers of beneficed
men not being resident, shall euery Uisitation deliuer to the
Register a note in writing of all Sermons preached in their
Cures from one Uisitation to another, subscribed with the
preachers hand, which notes the Register shall (after the visitation
ended) certifie vnto the said reuerend father.
                  7 Item, if the Church-wardens &amp; side-men at this visitation,
or any other henceforth, shall wilfully or negligently
omit to present any crime or offence worthy of presentment
and reformation, whereof the Minister, then or after, may
haue knowledge, that then the Minister shall giue aduertizement
thereof to the said reuerend
father or his Chancellor.
               
            
            FINIS.
            God saue the King.
         
      
   

