
   
      
         
            A consolatory letter to all the afflicted Catholikes in England
            H. B., fl. 1588.
         
         
            
               1588
            
         
         Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00249
            STC 1032
            ESTC S116626
            99851842
            99851842
            17134
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00249)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17134)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 307:02)
         
         
            
               
                  A consolatory letter to all the afflicted Catholikes in England
                  H. B., fl. 1588.
               
               111, [1] p.   
               
                  Arundel House by John Charlewood?,
                  Imprinted at Roan in Normandy [i.e. London :
                  1588?]
               
               
                  Actual imprint from STC.
                  Signed at end: H. B.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholics --  England.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-02
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-02
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A CONSOLATORY LETTER TO ALL THE AFFLICTED CATHOLIKES in England.
            
               Philip. 4.
               Sic ſtate in domino Chariſsimi:
            
            So ſtand in our Lorde, my Deareſt.
            Imprinted at Roan in Normandy.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            TO HIS MOST DEARE COVNTREYMEN ALL THE AFFLICTED CAtholickes in England H.B. wiſheth all comfort and ſtrength and ꝑſeueraunce in Chriſt Ieſus.
            
               RIght Noble Lordes, and worſhippfull Gentlemē with other worthy Confeſſors of Chriſt his Church, and religion, &amp; generally all ye that vnder the name of wilfull and obſtinate Recuſants, but in verye deed becauſe you be true and conſtant Catholickes, eyther alredy haue ben, or by likelihood may be herafter, endomaged in your worldly goods and poſſeſſions, empeached of liberty, or other wyſe perſecuted and afflicted. If the light of fayth did as clearely ſhine, &amp; the fire of godly zeale and charity were now as feruent in mens harts, as it was in the golden dayes of thoſe firſt Chriſtians among whome the precious blood of our Sauior was yet warme, the memory of the bleſſed Apoſtles moſt freſh, &amp; the example of invincible Martirs in euery ſex age and condition ſo frequent as that nothing could be more cōmon then dayly to ſee men and women, olde and young, rich &amp; poore Prieſtes and ſecular for Chriſts ſake to offer

them ſelues with willing and glad mindes to all kinde of exquiſite and greuous torments. If it might pleaſe God (I ſay) but in ſome parte to renue &amp; kindle againe the deuotion of thoſe times, in this our dull age &amp; dead ſeaſon: neyther ſhould this preſent perſecutiō ſeeme ſo terrible, as now I feare it ſeemeth, to many: neyther ſhould it be needfull at all to vſe ſo much comfort, encouragement, and exhortation as now perhapps to a great number ſhal be very neceſſary to be applyed. For ſo farr were the moſt Chriſtians in that flouriſhing prime tyde and cleare. Noone dayes of the Church from being afrayde of any kind of death (although moſt cruell and painfull) that euery one deemed him ſelfe the more happy, by how much more he might endure for the loue of our Sauiour: and as for temporall goods they were then ſo litle eſteemed as that many preuented the perſecutors hands, by ſelling all that they had, and diſtributing their money for the reliefe of their poore Chriſtian brethren. But now (alas) that ſaying of the Prophet Ieremie is to playnly verified of this our miſerable time:
               Hier: 6 Vae nobis quia declinauirdies quia longiores factae ſunt vmbrae veſperi: woe to vs becauſe the day is farr ſpent, becauſe the

ſhadowes are growen longer in the eauening. The light of true knowledge being diminiſhed charity waxing colde, &amp; iniquity encreaſing, the ſhadowes of tranſitory things ar become ſo greate, that now a mole hill appeareth more then a mountayne did in times paſt, the loſſe of a litle money, is now accompted greater, thē here-tofore of a whole world of wealth, yea more at this day perhapps ar diſmayed at the pinching of their purſe, then would in former age haue ben appalled at the tearing of their fleſhe &amp; breaking in ſunder of all their bones.
               Heb: 6 
               I meane not in this ſpeach to include many of you moſt conſtant and approued Confeſſors of whom I confidently truſt better things and nearer to ſaluation: who haue well d
                     •
                  ſeru
                     •
                  d that honorable teſtimony, which Saint Paule giueth to the Hebrues h
                     •
                  uing ſuſteyned already a great fight of paſſions:
               Heb: 10 
               on the one part by reproches and tribulations made a ſpectacle: and on thother part made companions of them that cōuerſed in ſuch ſort. You haue taken compaſſion on them that were in bondes: the ſpoyl of your owne goods you haue taken with ioy, knowing that you haue a better and a more permanent ſubſtance Ther remayneth for you no more but that you doe not loſe

your cōfidēce which hath a great renumeratiō. How long this perſecutiō ſhall continue, &amp; to what extremitie it may grow hereafter, God knoweth: And although we may hope the beſt yet in reſpect of our ſinns, we haue cauſe alſo to feare the worſt. Therfore patience is neceſarie for you: that doing the will of god, you may receiue the promiſe for yet a litle &amp; a verie litle while, he that is to come, will come, &amp; will not ſlacke. Liue you in the meane while by the aſſured fayth &amp; hope of Chriſt his cō
                  ming, and withdraw not your ſelues from the Catholike Church, being redy to reſiſt vſque ad ſaguinem.Heb: 12 
               Even to the patient ſhedding of your blood, if the glory of Chriſt his name ſhall ſo require. But I ſpeake of the baſe minded multitude who hardlye be perſwaded in hope of felicitie in the life to come to liue here with patience in penury or willingly to endure a paynfull death: who ar ether with holdē by feare of penall lawes agaynſt their cōſciēces, frō the harbour of ſaluation: or if they be yet in the Church, they ſtagger and ar ready to fall at the terror &amp; blaſt of euery new ſtatute that commeth forth, behauing them ſelues in the meane time ſo coldly in their profeſſion, that ſcarcely ſhall you perceiue them by any outward

acte to be Catholickes. For theſe eſpeacially I haue taken in hand this labour of exhortation, although I truſt it ſhal-be acceptable to you alſo, who by likelihod haue leſſe need to be comforted:
               
                  Tertu: ad Martires. 
               for even thoſe that fight or runne beſt are encouraged not onlye by their maiſters and gouernours, but alſo by the vulgar multitude that ſtandeth a farr of: &amp; that which to others is a neceſſary perſwaſion, to you is a great and excellent commendation: for ſo much as you do that of your ſelues with out externall admonition, wher vnto others haue neede to be often and vehementlye exhorted. And if I profite not otherwiſe by this endevour, yet I hope I ſhall reape profite by calling to remembraunce that which maye bring comfort to my ſelfe, wherof I confeſſe I ſtand in neede, in reſpect of the ſorowe which I ſuffer for your affliction my deare beloued contrymen, and for the lamētable ſtate of our natiue Land, being abſent in body, yet alwayes preſent with you in minde and ſpirit, &amp; likewiſe doe I need the prayers of good folke which I beſech all Catholikes that ſhall read this ſimple treatiſe of their charitable goodnes to beſtow vpon me.
            
            
               ANd now to come to my intended matter. The weyght of this preſēt perſecution ſeemeth chiefly to conſiſt in two penall ſtatutes: thone enforcing you to make ſhew by outward ſignes of yelding to a contrary religiō: the other debarring you from practiſe of your owne: the one propoſing vnto you detriment of temporall goods: the other thretning bodily deth: I meāe thone in flicting penalty, of .xx. pownd by the month to be exacted of all thoſe that refuſe to be preſent at the ſchiſmaticall prayers now called in England by the name of diuine ſeruice, the other forbidding you to receyue catholicke Prieſts, and conſequently excluding you from the benefite of god his ſeruice &amp; Sacramēts, vnder no leſſe payne thē for the ſame to ſuffer death as in caſe of felony. Agaynſt the terror of both theſe, lawes, I intend to geue ſuch comfort, as it ſhall pleaſe god by my poore pen to aforde. And firſt I will aſſay to geue a cordiall agaynſt the thirten monthes mulct, as that which may extend it ſelfe more generally, and is more like to be

put in execution, then that other lawe which draweth blood at the firſt encoū
               ter: the world being more earneſtly ſet in theſe dayes to thirſt after money, thē to deſire the ſhedding of mens blood. And like as peſecution beginneth commonlye with leſſer penalties before it proceed to greater: ſo ſhall it not be a miſſe to keepe the ſame order in applying remedye to theſe afflictions: The loue of worldly goods being not ſo naturall as the care of keeping of a mans life, &amp; therfore ordinarily the loſe more eaſlly digeſted. Although many will ſay that they would rather dye, ſpeedely, then liue a long time in miſerie: The reſon of this their iudgement may be geuen for that they haue already ſome feeling of want in this life, but of deathe they haue not yet taſted, neyther doe they feele it ſo much, being in their opinion farther from them: but if death were iminēt, I thinke ther are very few that would not ſaue their liues if they could although with very hard conditions for their maner of liuing: ſo that comonly that is found true, although

it were vttered by the Father &amp; Author of lyes: pellem pro pelle, et cuncta que habet homo dabit pro anima ſua:Iob: 2. Skyne for ſkyne and all that a man hath he will geue for his ſoule, that is to ſay for the redemption of his naturall lyfe. Yet neuertheleſſe ther is good hope that if we maye perſwade men to endure patiently the with-drawing of goods &amp; liuings, they will more boldly aduenture if it ſhal-be needfull, the loſſe of liues: the departing from theſe temporall poſſeſſions, being one eſpeciall payne, that mē hauing ſubſtance doe find at the time of their death being alſo a greate cauſe why they feare to dye, and therfore many times a great impedimēt to the happy atchiuing of glorious martirdom.
            ACording to this order therfore let vs firſt conſider this penalty of twē
               ty pownd by the month, for what cauſe it is layde vpon you, what incōueniences it bringeth, and what recompence you maye expect in time to come for this vrgent detriment. So that waying the goodnes of your cauſe, and ioyning

therto hope of future reward, you may rather reioyce in the gayne that is to come, then ſorow for the preſent loſſe, or feare the diſtreſſe or incommoditye that may enſue. And firſt touching the cauſe wherfore your purſes be thus puniſhed. You ſuffer becauſe you ar Catholickes, or as the world termeth you recuſants: Let vs ſee therfore what you refuſe to doe, and vpon what ground: &amp; although you haue the ſame declared more at large in ſundry learned treatyſes, it ſhall not be amiſſe perhaps to call ſome few poynts amongſt the reſt to remembraunce.
            YOu refuſe to doe directly agaynſt your conſcience,1 Doing agaynſt conſcience in Pſal: 54
                to deſcend quick vnto hell, and to be ſwallowed vp a liue by your enemies, for Saint Auguſtine ſayeth, when thou knoweſt it to be euill which thou doeſt, and yet doeſt the ſame, thou doeſt downe quicke vnto hell. And in a nother place,
                  in Pſal: 123 thoſe are they ſayeth he that are ſwallowed vp alyue, who know a thing to be euill, and doe geue conſent with their tongues. And great reaſon haue you to ſhun this

manifeſt and wilfull perdition of your owne ſoules, knowinge that as Saint Paule ſayeth,Ro: 14 he that diſcerneth, that is to ſaye, he that iudgeth a thing to be euill although it were otherwiſe indifferent, if he doe it, is damned: becauſe, not of fayth, but becauſe he doeth not according to his conſcience and knowledg, for all that is not of fayth, all that is done agynſt a man his conſcience, is ſinne albeit the thinge were of it ſelfe lawfull: much rather if it be vtterly vnlawfull, as the going to church with heretikes is holdē in euery diſcreete mans conſcience and iudgement: And Saint Iames ſayeth,
                  
                     •
                  io: 4 to one knowinge to doe good, &amp; not doing it: to him it is ſinne, much rather if a man know a thinge to be euill &amp; do it, his offence muſt needs be great.
                  
                     •
                  ot 14 Bleſſed ar you therfore in refuſing to condemne your ſelues by doing contrary to that which you beſt alow.
            
               D
                     •
                  ſhmo
                  
                     ••
                  g of 2 god.ALſo you refuſe to diſhonor god by fleeing from his banner and furniſhing his enimies campe with your viſible preſence: Where as it is written in

the Prouerbs:Prouerbes: 14 
               That in the multitude of his people is the kings dignity, &amp; in the ſmale nū
                  ber of his folke, the ignominy of a Prince.
               Pſal: 31 And ther-fore of ſuch as ſhrinke awaye in time of aduerſity our Sauiour complayneth in one of the pſalmes in behalfe of him ſelfe and of his ſpouſe the Catholike Church in lamentable manner ſayinge: Aboue all myne enimies I haue byn made a reproch to my neighbours and a feare to mine acquaintance excedingly: they that did ſee me haue fled forth from me, vpon which place Saint Auguſtine ſayth,
                  in Pſal. 31 that the departure of thoſe that had ſeene &amp; known the Church is more greeuous &amp; altogether intollerable, thē the obſtinate reſiſtinge of thoſe that haue byn nouſeled &amp; brought vp in error from their infancy.
            And therfore it followeth after a few words in the aforeſayde pſalme, I haue heard the diſprayſe of manye dwelling round about me. As vndoubtedly, yf you ſhould forſake god, for feare of tē
               porall loſſe, you ſhould geue occaſion to many to blaſphem god as if he were not able to deliuer you, or as if you had

no truſt in his power and goodnes ſaying. Non eſt ſalus ipſis in deo eorum: They haue no ſaluatiō in their god,Pſal: 3. they haue no hope or aſſurance in their religion which they haue hyther to profeſſed.
            You ſhall alſo geue them occaſion to thinke very euill of the Catholike religion by ſeeming to make leſſe accompt of the defence &amp; profeſſiō of the ſame, then of a litle money, yea then of all your worldlye goods and poſſeſſions. They that trouble you ſhall reioyſe yf you be moued,Pſal: 12. but doe you hope ſtill in our Lord his mercy.
            
               3 Scandall.YOu refuſe likewiſe not only to geue this cauſe of reioyſing to your aduerſaries, but alſo to make a ſhew of euill, that by doing that which is euill of it ſelfe to induce many weakelings depending on your example, as your children, your ſeruaunts, friends, neyghbours, &amp; others, partly hauing iudgement and knowledge to follow you to church agaynſt their conſciences, and partly being ignorāt, to allow the ſchiſmaticall ſeruice now vſed, and finally to like of hereſy wherby (ſo much as lieth

in you) you ſhould be homicides and deſtroyers of their ſoules: for as Saint Paule ſayeth,1 Cor: 8 If a man ſe him that hath knowledge, ſitt at a table in the Idols temple: ſhall not his conſcience being weake be edified to eate things ſacrificed to Idols? vpon which place of Saint Paule, the famous doctor ſaint Auguſtine inferreth, that we ar forbidden to vſe or to doe that wher-by we maye be thought to doe any thinge in the honour of ſtraūge gods,
                  Aug: epſt: 154: ad Publicolam. receiuing it in ſuch ſort, that although in harte we deſpiſe ſuch things yet we edifie or induce thoſe that know not our harts in deed to honour the ſame. In lke mā
               ner to compare the caſe of goinge to church in theſe our dayes vnto meates offered to Idols. If men ſhall ſee you in churches in time of ſacriligious ſeruice ſhould not their conſciences be edified eyther to thinke yt the ſeruice of God, or at the leſt with out feare to frequēt the ſame: and ſo in tract of time to like and allow of hereſy, and ſo ſinning agaynſt your brethren &amp; ſtryking their weake conſciences: you ſhall ſinne agaynſt

Chriſt. Therfore ſayeth the Apoſtle if meate ſcandalize my brother: I will neuer eate fleſh. Of the ſame mynd was that notable Eleazaurus who choſe rather to dye,2 Mach: 6. then to make ſo much as a ſhew of eating meates forbidden by the lawe: ſaying that he would firſt be ſent vnto hell: for ſayeth he it is not ſeemly for our age to fayne: that many young men thinking Eleazaurus now of ninty yeares age to haue paſſed to the lyfe of the gentills, may alſo them ſelues thorough my diſſimulation, and for a litle time of this corruptible lyfe be deceyued, &amp; therby I may procure a blemiſh &amp; malediction to myne olde age for although I be deliuered at this preſēt time from the tormēts of men, yet ſhall I not eſcape the hand of the almighty, neyther aliue nor dead. And ſhoulde not men haue greate cauſe to thinke that you were paſſed to the lyfe &amp; conuerſation of heretikes ſeeing you to differ nothing from them in principall ſignes &amp; tokens of religion ſhould you not cauſe many to ſaye: ther is no differēce, men contēding among them

ſelues haue made theſe controuerſies, god is to be honoured euery wher: yf the very ſilence of a man in matter of fayth by Saint Auguſtins Iudgement ſhould cauſe many to thinke all religiō indifferent?
                  Aug. De paſtoribus cap. 7.
                And therfore thryſe well aduiſed ar you in refuſing to doe ſuch an acte wherby your catholike brethrē might be offēded, ſcandalized,Rom. 14 or weakened.
            MOreouer you refuſe,
                  4 Deniall of the fayth. by conforming your ſelues (as men terme it) to the proceedings of a nother religion, to denye that fayth, which you vndoubtedly knowe to be moſt true, ſincere, vniuerſall, &amp; auncient as that wherin you haue byn borne and baptiſed, wherin al your worthy auncetors haue liued and dyed, which alwayes &amp; onlye hath floryſhed in this Realme of Englande till within theſe late yeares: yeelding in euerye age moſt plentiful fruite of deuotion towards God, of obedience towardes Princes and other ſuperiors, of mercy towards the poore, of charity, of trueth, fidelity, and plaine dealing of all ſortes of men towards

their neighbours. And that you ſhold ſo denye your faith by going to church with the proteſtantes, yet is it moſte playn by the nature of the thing it ſelfe being an acte properlye belonging to Religion, by the intente of the lawe, being made to no other ende but to exacte of you ſome ſigne of yeelding in matters of conſcience, by your longe refuſal and ſuffering for the ſame cauſe heretofore, by the iudgment of the aduerſaries holding them-ſelues ſatiſfied if you relent but in this one poynte of or externall behauior, and finally by the confeſſion of all men of any meane vnderſtanding, if they wil vtter plainly what they thinke▪ &amp; if it were thought heretofore in times of perſecutiō that the onlye wearing of a garland in certayne feaſtes of Idoles were to be holden as a ſigne that a man had denyed his fayth: In ſo muche that Tertulian ſaythe,Liber. De corona militis. although a Chriſtian man hold his peace whiles others doe ſacrifice to falſe goddes, yet by wearing that garlande vppon his head he maketh aunſwere in fauour of Idolatrye: whereas

this was a thing by nature indifferent being onlye made a ſigne of religion by vſe and opinion of men: what ſhall wee iudge then of ioyning with proteſtants in their publike prayers and ſeruice which is peculier to them, as the bleſſed Sacrifice of the Maſſe is common to all Catholikes. And therfore as wee are knowen by the one, ſo they are knowen and diſcerned by the other.
                  Tert. De Idola. If it were not permitted hereto fore that Chriſtians ſhold in anye ſorte conforme them-ſelues to the Gentils, not euen ſo-much as to hang a lantern or a branche of Laurell at their dores, when greate feaſtes were celybrated in honour of Idoles? How can it be lawfull to keepe feaſtes with hereticks and to enter into their churches when they are buſied in ſuche actes whereby they are diſtinguiſhed not onlye from Catholiques, but alſo one ſecte and ſorte of them from a nother? If it were thought a great offence, to be preſent at the publike ſpectackles &amp; playes,Tertu. et Cip. De ſpectaculis
                becauſe the beginning and fynall ende of them was the honour of Idoles:

Is it poſſible that a catholike mā ſhold ſafly exhibit his preſence at ſuch kinde of ſeruice as had beginning by deuiſiō from the Church, and was inuēted for the ſetting forth of hereſie? Let vs here what Tertulian ſaith of the aforeſayde plaies in a peculier treatis of that argument, he requireth herein the iudgmēt of the very Gentils, whether Chriſtians might be there preſent or no. For ſaith he They moſt of all vnderſtād a man to be made a Chriſtian by the refuſing of ſuch ſpectakles. Therfore he denieth manifeſtlye who taketh away the thing wherby he is knowen. In like maner may we ſaye at this preſent: the proteſtants eſpecially vnderſtande that one is become a Catholike by the refuſing of their churches. Therfore he denyeth himſelfe to be a Catholike, whoſoeuer fayleth in this poynt pf his profeſſion. Nether let anye man thinke to eſcape this daūger of deniall by ſubtile euations: For as S.Cyp. Epiſ. 31. Ciprian ſaieth whoſoeuer ſeeketh deceytfull ſleightes to excuſe him-ſelfe hath denied, and he that will ſeeme to haue ſatiſfied the Edicts or lawes propoſed

a gainſt the Goſpel hath obeyed euen in this, that he wolde ſeeme to haue obeyed. Now who-ſoeuer ſhall thus by his outwarde acte denye himſelfe to be a Catholike, ſhall therby denyethe whole Catholike religion: euen as he that denyeth him-ſelfe to be a Chriſtian, denyeth Chriſte. And conſequently a Chriſtian and Catholique being all one, to goe to Churche with heretickes is plainely to denye Chriſt: As contrarie-wiſe to refuſe their conuenticles is a cleere cōfeſſion of Chriſt. And this is a moſt important reaſon of your refuſall where-vpon I haue ſtayed the longer, becauſe it concerneth you as muche, as to be acknowleged or denyed before God the Father and all his Angels when Chriſte ſhall come in his maieſtie to iudge the worlde.Mat. 10.
            
            HEreof it foloweth alſo that you refuſe by damnable ſchiſme to ſeuer your ſelues from the Church your mother,5 Schiſme. where-by you ſhoulde ceaſe to haue God to your father:
                  CiP. De vnitate Eccleſiae. yea you ſhold ceaſe altogether to be Chriſtians: for by the iudgement of S. Cyprian &amp;

S. Augustine he is no Chriſtian, who is not in the church of Chriſt. Wherby you ſholde departe out of Noes arke, &amp; commit your ſelues to preſent drowning. Wherby you ſholde be debarred frō eating the lambe in God his houſe, &amp; ſo be exterminated from the people of God. Wherby you ſholde be found out of the houſe of Raab:Exo. 12. Ioſ. 6. to periſhe moſt vndoubtedlye by the ſworde of Gods iudgment. Wherby you ſhold be diuided from the bodye of Chriſt, hauing him no longer to be your heade, receyuing no influence of his grace,
                  Aug. De vnitate eccleſica. 16
                no liuely motion of his ſpirite, no parte of his merits, no fruite of his bleſſed paſſion. Wherby you ſholde be cut of frō the true vine and ſo wither, &amp; become fuel for hel fier.Io. 15. Wherby you ſhold loſe the felowſhip &amp; cōmunion of holy Angels &amp; ſancts in heauen, being alſo excluded from the ſuffrages of the millitant church here in earth. You ſhould be ſeuered from the promiſes of Chriſt by forſaking his ſpouſe,
                  Cip. De vnitate. and ioyning your ſelues to the aduouterous cōgrecation. You ſhould be excluded from

the rewardes of the heauenly kingdōe, by forſaking her,
                  Aug: de Bap: con: Dona: li: i. ca: 2. that is apointed there to raygne. You ſholde loſe the benefit of your baptiſme, and withal the right that you haue to receaue other Sacraments, which cannot be fruitfully receiued, but in the Catholike church.de verb: Domu. 1. ſer. 11. You ſhould depriue your ſelues of the meanes to haue remiſſiō, ſo much as of one veniall ſinne, although you ſholde puniſhe your ſelues with neuer ſo hard &amp; auſtere penance. You ſhould loſe the fruite of all your good woorkes heretofore done,EP: 152: de fide ad Petrum: ca 39. making all your actions from thence-forthe altogether vnprofitable, in reſpecte of euerlaſting lyfe: although you ſholde liue neuer ſo lawdablye, although you ſholde geue neuer ſo great almes, although you ſhold ſhed your blood for the name of chriſt, yet continuing ſo out of the churche, you could by no meanes be ſaued. To be ſhorte you ſholde breake that vnity for whiche our Sauiour ſo earneſtlye prayed vnto his Father. For the eſtabliſhing wherof,Io. 17. 11. he ſuffered his Paſſiō and ſhedd his moſt pretious bloode.

In defence of which vnitye Dioniſius Alexandrinus holdeth it no leſſe glorious to dye,
                  Euſ. Eccleſi hiſto. Liber. 7. Cap. 37.
                then to ſuffer for refuſing to ſacrifice to Idols. For ſaithe he, in that euerie one ſuffereth martirdome for one ſoule, but in this caſe for the whole Churche. Now that all theſe inconueniences here mentioned, &amp; what ſoeuer elſe may be comprehended vnder the deteſtable name of ſciſme, ſhold enſue of your going to the proteſtants churches, I thinke it maye be manifeſt by theſe reaſons folowing.Pſal. 121 Firſt of all  the Church is a city or cōmon wealth, hauing a participation or felowſhip of ſpirituall benefits with-in itſelfe: and therfore whoſoeuer doth communicat in ſpirituall things with any other cō
               gregation, muſt needs be diuided frō the fellowſhipe of the Church &amp; from thoſe benefits which cannot be receiued but in the ſame ſociety, euen as he that ſhould ioyne with the enimye of his countrey ſhould worthily be depriued of all ſuch priuileges as he enioyed at home. Neyther is it poſſible for one to participate at once with two

diſtinct churches no more thē for one member to be in two ſeuerall bodyes you cannot drincke the chalice of our Lorde ſayeth Saint Paule,1. Cor. 10 and the chalice of deuills, you cānot be partakers of the table of our Lorde, and of the table of deuills. So likewiſe you cānot be of Chriſt his Church and repayre to Sathans Sinnagogue. But ſome perhaps will anſwer that by going to church they doe not in deed participate, but only ſeme to participat with thoſe of a nother religion. To this I ſaye: Secondlye  that as the Churche is viſible, ſo muſt all her members be knowne &amp; manifeſt. So that no man can rightly ſaye him-ſelfe to be in the Church, although in bodily apparance he ioyne with heretickes. For wher-as he viſibly exhibiteth his preſence, there is he a viſible member, and not other where. For a Cathecumen might ſaye muche better that he is mentally in the Church, and yet is he not properly &amp; actually accounted of the Church, nor is admitted to any Sacrament before he be baptiſed. Saint Cornelius in a certayne

epiſtle to Saint Ciprian,Cyp. Ep. 46. maketh mentiō of ſome that were reduced frō the ſchiſme of Nouatus who proteſted openly that although they ſeemed to cōmunicate in ſome ſorte with a ſchiſmaticall and hereticall man, yet neuertheleſſe their ſincere mindes were alwayes within the church. And thinke you the moſte parte of Sciſmatickes at this daye wolde not ſaye as muche, if this excuſe were ſufficient. But this is not enough, neither did it then ſuffice thoſe men vntil they were openlye reconciled to the church, and admitted in preſence of the whole conciſtorie of prieſtes at Rome. And furthermore their reconciliation was notified to the whole people, to the end that al might ſee them preſent in the church whome before they had ſeene with ſorowe, to err &amp; wander as ſheepe diſperſed from the Catholike flocke.Conf. 8. ca. 2. Alſo S. Auguſtin reportethe of one Victorinus, a man greatly honored in Rome for his excellent learning and eloquence, that being conuerted from Idolatrie to the Chriſtian religion, he deferred a longe

while, or feare to diſpleaſe his worldly friendes, to make open ſhew of that he beleeued in ſecrete. And yet ſaying often to ſome of his faithful acqaintāce, that he was alreadie a chriſtian, he was alwayes tolde that they wolde not ſo repute him, vntil they ſaw him in the church of Chriſt, wher-vnto he wolde replye in ſcornful manner, aſking whether the walles made men to be Chriſtians? as manye at this daye wil aſke, whether their reſorte to the material churche of heretikes, can make them ceaſe to be of the Catholike churche? But in the ende, by God his grace, he turned ouer the leafe, and going gladlye to the church, he was inſtructed in the faythe, baptiſed and made a true Chriſtian. And when the time came, that he ſhould make profeſſion of his faythe before the faythful people, for that was then the manner for ſuche as were newly conuerted: It was offered him that he ſhould do it more ſecretly, leſte ſo great an aſſemblye at the firſte ſhould abaſh him. But he made choyſe

to confeſſe his fayth before the whole multitude. And ſo he did moſt confidentlye, the whole people cryeing for ioye: Victorinus Victorinus. A notable example, to be folowed by many a Victorinus in our age; I meane manye an honorable man, &amp; famous ſcholer being in harte and conſcience Catholikes: &amp; withal it is an euident proofe, that it ſufficeth not to be a Catholike in ſecret, vnleſſe by outwarde ſignes a man doe alſo ſhew and profeſſe his religion, according to the ſaying of our Sauiour,Math. 5. that Men doe not light a candle and put it vnder a buſhel, but on a candleſtick that it may ſhine to all that are in the houſe. Therfore ſayth he, Let your lyght ſo ſhyne before men: Let the confeſſion of your fayth, and your good conuerſation be ſo manifeſte, that they maye ſee your good woorkes, and gloryfie your father which is in  heauen. Thirdly therfore it is to be conſiddered that the Church for maintayning of her viſible vnitye hath certaine outwarde ſignes, wherin her children do participat one with a nother, wherby ſhe is knowen and diſtinguiſhed frō
               
other companies. For as S.To 7 Cō
                     tra Fauſtum. Li. 19. Ep. 11. Auguſtine ſayth, Into no name of religion, either true or falſe, can men be firmely compacted excepte they be tyed together by ſome fellowſhip of viſible ſignes or ſacraments. And theſe outward ſignes are eſſpeciallye the bleſſed Scacrifice, the holy ſacramentes of the ſame, publike prayers and ſeruice of God, which are not in the proteſtants churches. And therfore whoſoeuer reſorteth thither, doth manifeſtly fayle in theſe tokens of his profeſſion, and ſo diuideth himſelfe frō the viſible vnity. Fourthly  this vnitye requireth not onlye that a man participate in ſacramentes and prayers, but alſo that he be obediente to his lawfull paſtours. And now it is euident that the whole churche in the Councel of Trent by condemning the hereſies of this time, hath alſo forbidden vs to haue felowſhip with the folowers of thoſe hereſies in diuine thinges. Neither was it needful by expreſſe wordes to prohibit the comming to their churches: ſeing that it was forbidden expreſly to pray with heretikes

euen by the Cannons of the Apoſtles, and in diuers ages by ſundry Councels whiche wee ſhal haue occaſion to cite herafter. And who knoweth not that the meaning, will and commaūdement of all Catholike paſtors at this daye, is that we ſhold abſtaine from the a foreſayd churches vnder no leſſe payne, thē to be caſt out of the true church. Fiftly  the practice of our country is moſt manifeſt, wherby thoſe that only haue bin preſēt at the ſciſmatical ſeruice, are holden for very ſciſmatikes, &amp; accordingly are dealt withal in their riſing vp from their ruine, and they in the mean time in their owne conſciences do acknowledge them-ſelues to be debarred from  the vſe of al holye Sacraments. Sixtly al this is grounded vpon great reaſon: for like as the proteſtants are heretikes in reſpect of their falſe doctrine, ſo are the ſciſmatikes in their different manner of ſeruing God. And therfore who ſoeuer doth but ſeeme to concurr with them in that outward acte of ſeruice, the Churche being not able to ſearche his harte and minde, but iudging him

acording to that which he ſheweth outwardly,
                  Aug. cont aduerſar. Legis et Proph. ca. 17.
                muſt needs cēſure him as a ſciſmatike. Which cenſure is more greeuous &amp; terrible, then if a man were adiudged to be ſtriken with a ſworde, to be conſumed with fire, or to be deuoured with wilde beaſtes: And more bitterly and vnhappily is a man bound by the keyes of the church after ſuch iudgment, then by any other moſt greuous and harde bondes, albeit they were of yron or Adamant ſtone. Neither let anye man thinke to be acquite from the crime of ſciſme, or from this heauy cē
               ſure, becauſe his acte of going to the proteſtants churche is conſtrayned by feare of worldlye loſſe and not altogether voluntarie. For although he wold not doe this acte, if the feare were remoued, yet according to the condition of this preſente time, he choſeth it as moſt expedient for him. And therfore al circumſtances conſiddered, and as thinges goe now it is more voluntary, then againſt his wil, and ſimpliciter as it is termed &amp; as the caſe now ſtandeth it is voluntarie. For if feare might haue

excuſed, the Churche had done greate wrong, not onlye to thoſe who had denyed their fayth by doing ſacrifice, or caſting of incence into the fyre before Idoles, through conſtraint of torment, but euen to thoſe who had geuen vp their names among thē that ſacrificed: al which ſortes of offenders were long time with-holden from the Sacramēts and cauſed to doe harde penance: yea manye of them were not admitted to the company of the faithful, vntil that eyther the perſecution ceaſed, or that the extreme poynt of death ouertoke them, or if ſuch faynt hartes might be holden blameleſſe, where ſhould become the glorye of martirs, or the inuincible perſeuerance of conſtant Confeſſors. And therfore great cauſe haue you rather to ſuffer your ſelues to be condemned to the payment of twenty poūdes by the moneth, then to be ſubiecte to this ſo iuſt and withal ſo heuye damnation.
            
               6 Diſsimulation.LIkewiſe you refuſe to diſſemble in matters belonging to God &amp; your conſcience, which kind of diſſimulatiō
               
S. Auguſtine reckeneth for the firſt and worſt kind of deteſtable lying:De Ciuita te Dei. Li. 6. Ca. 10.
                Therfore in one place ſpeaking or Seneca, who in his harte knew the Idols of the gentils to be moſt falſe and vayne and yet by his outward behauiour, ſeemed to honour them, the ſame doctor pronounceth this ſentence in this ſorte: that he dyd more damnablye worſhip thoſe falſe gods, for-ſomuch as thoſe thinges which he did faynedly, he did them in ſuche ſorte, that the people thought him to doe them truely and in deede from his harte: and in a treatis of purpoſe writtē againſt the Priſcillianiſts,Liber. De mendacio. who defended it as a thing lawful, for a man to counterfayt a contrarye religion for aduantage, and alſo againſt certain Catholikes (who forſoth as they ſayd) to eſpye and finde out heretiks, would put on a viſard of hereſy:Cōtramē
                  dacium. He determineth that diſsimulation in no wiſe to be vſed: ſhewing that if they ſhold cōuert any of thoſe heretikes, by going among thē in that ſort, yet ſhold they as muche confirme their diſciples in that errour of thinking it lawful to

lye &amp; diſsēble,Cap. 3. et. 4. as they ſhold edify them in other poynts of doctrine. So that neither the catholiks ſhold know whether an heretike were in other things cōuerted or no, ſo long as he remained in that doctrine of lying: Nether ſhold the new conuert knowe when or wherin to beleue his maiſter whom he had found in many thinges here to fore haue bin a diſsembler &amp; a lyar. In the ſame treatis he reciteth the example of Iehu, who fained to cōmit Idolatrye, therby to entrape the prieſtes of Baal, as wicked and ſacriligious and by no meanes to be folowed. For neuer did the Apoſtles who were in deed right holye and true martyrs, any ſuch thing for the ſauing of their owne lyues, as this King did vppon indiſcreete zeale to take away the liues of others.Rom. 14 And wherfore? becauſe that with the harte we beleue to Iuſtice: but with the mouth confeſſion is made to ſaluation. Which confeſsion is of dutye and neceſsity when ſoeuer a man by his ſilence, ſhould be thought to haue forſaken his faythe, or that the religiō ſhould be the worſe

lyked of, or that others ſhould be induced to wauer, in their fayth, thorough diſsimulation. All whiche conditions may &amp; doe concurr in this caſe of yelding to heretikes to reſorte to theyr churches and ſeruice. And here it is to be noted that the Priſcillianiſts were not the firſt, that would warrant men to denye their fayth in time of perſecution. It was certayne hundred yeares before the doctrine of the Helaeſaites: and ſome time before them it was taught by the Gnoſtikes or Valentinians againſt whome Tertulian purpoſlye did write a booke called Scorpiacum,
               Eus. Ecc. Hiſt. Li. 6 cap. 31. as it were a remedye againſt the biting of Scorpians. A neceſſarye medicine for theſe diſsembling dayes, wherin as it ſayde, the obſcure familie of Loue haue ſett vpp a gaine this ſchole of lying. And as for the proteſtants although they doe not openly holde and maintayne this doctrine of diſsimulation: yet as it appereth by the behauiour of their eſpials in ſūdrie places it is much practiſed a mong thē &amp; therfore not greatly diſalowed. But this playing on both handes is odious

a mong men euen in humane matters. For as Tully ſayth. Odio digna eſt diſsimulatio.
               De officijs Diſsimulation is worthy of hatred. And contrarywiſe he ſaythe, that which is true ſimple &amp; ſincere, is moſt agreable to mans nature. So we ſee by experience there is nothing more repugnant to a noble courage, then for feare or fauour to pleaſe a nother mans humor, contrarye to his owne lyking. Therfore Ariſtotle deſcribing the conditions of one that is Magnanimus, of loftye and noble minde aſſigneth this for one that he is no diſsembler. Alſo a mong the moral vertues he reckneth Trueth for one, wherby a man ſheweth himſelfe in his lyfe, to be ſuche as he is in deede inwardly. Furthermore in all cōmon weales wiſely gouerned, thoſe that haue remayned neuters in ciuile diſſention, haue bin ſuſpected as frindes to none and common enemyes to all. And ſurely me thinketh there ſhold be good hope that your mercyefull Prince with her honourable counſell ſhould in tyme conſidder, and lyke wel of your playne dealing and ſinceritye:

wherby it appereth manifeſtly that you doe not temporiſe, nor expecte anye daye to come: other then the general daye wherin Chriſt ſhal geue to euerye one according to his woorkes good or euil. But for this as it ſhal pleaſe God. Now to our purpoſe, it is certayne that diſsimulation dothe highlye diſpleaſe him, eſpecially in matters belonging to his ſeruice:Leu. 11. In figure wherof ſome fowles that partly liue vppon the lande, &amp; Partlye in the water were holden vncleane in the olde lawe. It was likewiſe forbidden in deteſtation of doublenes for anye man to ſowe his ground with two kindes of ſeede,Deut. 22 to plowe with an oxe and an aſſe, to weare a garment of lincywolſie. And to the ſame purpoſe belonged ſo many ceremonies, ordayned for the diſtinguiſhing of God his people from ſtraungers to the end that they might in no wiſe be like in aparel, in dyate, in al kinde of outward behauiour. And more plainly wiſdome her ſelfe in the prouerbes declareth that ſhe doth hate &amp; deteſt a double tōgue.Pro. 8. Likewiſe the wiſe-man forbiddeth to

come to God with a double harte. woe be to the mā of double hart (ſaith he) to him that goeth two wayes vppon the earth at once.
               Eccleſiaſti. 2. 
               The harte that goeth two wayes ſhal not haue ſucceſſe, and a wicked harte ſhal be ſcandaliſed by his proceedings. Therfore he admoniſheth. 
               Non ſumere faciem contrafaciem, not to make a ſhewe againſt a mans inward  conſcience, as it is playnly expounded by that which foloweth. Neyther do thou receaue a lye againſt thy ſoule. That is to ſay doe not make falſe ſemblance to thine owne damnation. The Prophet Helias cryeth vnto the people in God his behalfe of the ten tribes.4. Re. 18 
               How long doe you halte on both partes? If our Lord be God folow him, or yf Baal be God folow him. And in the ſame booke of the Kinges they ar cōmended by God his owne mouth,19 who had not bowed their knees before Baal neyther had they kiſſed the Idols hand. Our Sauiour him-ſelfe affirmeth that no man can ſerue two maſters,Mat. 6. 
               God and Māmon, but either he ſhall hate the one and loue the other:
               Luc. 11. 
               or ſuſteyn the one, and cō
                  tēne the other. He that is not with me (ſaith our Lord) is againſt me, and he that gathereth

not with me, ſcattereth.
               Apo. 3. And in ſaynt Iohns Reuelation he complaynetn of one that is neyther colde nor hott. I would (ſayth he) thou were colde or hott. A true Catholike or a flat heretike. But becauſe thou art luke warme &amp; neyther colde nor hott, I will begin to caſte the out of my mouth. For dread therfore to be caſt of by almighty God, you doe iuſtly refuſe to pleaſe the world by double dealing: Keeping as you doe that faythful and vpright courſe which is moſt honourable for the ſetting forthe of your religion, moſt ſeemly for your magnanimitye, moſt honeſt before men, and moſte free from ſuſpition of treacherye, and therfore moſt dutiful towards your Prince, whom you ſhould rather delude then obey by fained conformitye, wheras now you performe the true obediēce of good ſubiects by ſuffering patiently whatſoeuer the lawe of your countrye ſhal laye vppon you.
            BEſides al this you refuſe to come to the Proteſtantes congregation,7 Participation. for feare to be partakers of the ſinnes ther in committed, &amp; ſo to be ioyned with

them in puniſhment. This auoyding of ſuche as are authors or folowerers of new ſectes and ſchiſmes is commanded by God him-ſelfe, and therfore by no meanes can be diſpenced withal. An example of this commaundement and of tranſgreſsion againſt the ſame, &amp; withal of puniſhment due for ſuch offence, we haue in the firſt patern of al ſchſme I meane the ſedition of Corē,Num. 14 Dathan and Abiron. From whoſe tabernacles the people were cōmanded to depart, &amp; not to touch thoſe thinges whih did belong vnto them, leaſt they ſhould be inwrapped in their ſinnes. And imediatly the earthe opening ſwalowed vpp the captayns, and two hundred &amp; fifty of their complyces were ſlayn with fire from heauen. Yea fortye thouſand and ſeauen hundred of the people for murmuring in their behalfe, the next daye were deſtroyed by fire.3 Reg. 13 The man of god who was ſent to Ieroboam the author of diuiſion in the people of Iſrael, was commaunded not to eate nor drinke a mong the ſchiſmatikes: And for doing the contrary he was ſlayne by a Lyon in

the waye. The godly King Ioſaphat is greuouſlye reprehended for ioyning with an Infidel euen in temporal matters.Par. 19. Thou geueſt ayd vnto the vngodlye (ſaythe one Prophet vnto him) and thou art ioyned in friendſhip to thoſe that hate our Lorde: And therfore in deede thou dydeſt deſerue our Lordes wrath. Therfore the Prophet Dauid,Pſal. 1. deſcribing a happy and wiſe man ſaith, Bleſſed is the man that hath not gone a waye in the counſell of the vngodly, and hathe not ſtoode in the waye of ſinners, and hath not ſitt in the chayer of peſtilence. In whiche verſe may be noted three degres of cō
               ſenting to ſchiſme: The firſt are of thoſe that goe a waye through frayltye, the ſecond are thoſe that ſtandeth therin by continuance, the thirde are thoſe that defend and teache it to others as a thing lawful, who may verely be ſayd to ſitt in the chayer of peſtelence, teaching the doctrine of Balaam to geue ſcā
               dal. Ouer many ſuch haue bene in our dayes, and I praye God there be not yet ſome remayning.Apo. 2. But let them take heede, for Chriſt wil come quicklye &amp;

wil fight againſt them with the ſworde of his mouthe: that is to ſaye with the trueth of his worde.Lib. De ſpectaculis The a foreſayde verſe Tertuliā thinketh ſufficiēt, to forbid al reſort to al vnlawful aſſemblies, whether they be gathered with entent of Idolatrye, of iniquitye, or for vanities ſake, as wanton playes and diſhoneſt ſpectacles, although they be not expreſlye forbidden in ſcripture. And therfore vndoubtedly it may wel be applied vnto the cōuenticles of heretiks, wherin ſo many vngodly folke concurt together in the verye acte of diſhonouring God, by impugning his true religion: of contempt of the churche, by vſurpatiō of their new deuiſed ſeruice, &amp; of deriſion of Chriſts Sacraments by profane rites of their owne friuolous inuention.Pſal. 25. Yet furthermore the ſame royal Prophet in an other pſalme declaring his owne innocency ſayth, I haue not ſitten, that is to ſay I haue not ſtayed any while with the councel of vanitye, and with them that doe wickedlye I wil not goe in by once ſeeming to alowe that which they doe, I haue hated

the church of the malignant, and with the vngodly I wil not ſitt. I wil waſh my handes among innocents, and I wil cō
               paſſe thine altar round a bout by cleauing faſt to Chriſte and his Catholike Church. And within a few wordes. I haue loued the cōelynes of thy houſe, and the dwelling place of thy glory. As a Catholike might ſaye, the cauſe wherfore I refrayne in this ſort from wicked company of heretiks in their churches, is the loue and zeale whiche I beare to the beauty of Gods Church, the merueylous diſpoſition of her ſeruice, the reuerend maieſty of her Sacraments, &amp; decent order of her Ceremonies, wher of I find no reſemblance in the newe deformed congregation. In an other Pſalme he ſaythe after, he hath ſpoken of vngodly men.Pſal. 141 
               I wil not cōmunicat with their elect or choſen men. Which S. Auguſtine in his time applyed to the cheefe maſters of the Manachies who were called Electi. And we may applye it wel ro all thoſe of Caluins crew who moſt vndoubtedly preſume, that they are elected by God and predeſtinat to euerlaſting

ſaluation.Pſal. 49. Contrariwiſe in an other Pſalme, an euil man is reprehended by God, with theſe wordes. Thou dideſt ſee a theefe and dideſt runne with him, and with aduouterers thou dideſt lay thy portion. Heretikes are the theeues by ſtealing and abuſing the Scripture. They are alſo aduouterers by corrupting the ſincerity of ſimple mens faith with falſe doctrine. And whereof did proceede ſuch boldnes, to ioyne and take parte with iniquity? Thou haſt thought wickedly, that I wil be like vnto thee, as commonly men wil ſaye God is mercyful as gentle to beare with ſchiſme as thou to fauour hereſye. I wil reproue thee, and ſaye it to thy face, by charging thee with it at the dreadful day of iudgment. But theſe places may ſeme a like for the auoyding of al euil companye. Now more particularly for the ſhunning of ſuch as wilfully diuide thē ſelues from Gods church: we reade in the Goſpel of S. Iohn, that the Iewes did not communicate with the Samarytans, who were ſchiſmatikes in reſpect of the olde law and therfore were moſt

abhorred by the faithful folke of Gods people: And although they did alſo abſtayne from hauing conuerſation with other Infidels.Mat. 18. Wher-vppon our Sauiour geueth vs a rule, to ſhunn an heretike, or anye one that diſobayeth the Churche euen as the Iewes did deteſte the Heathen and the Publicane. And the like cōmandement hath ben geuen continualye by the bleſſed Apoſtles in their writings. Firſt by S. Paule.Rom. 16 
               I deſire you brethern (ſayth he) to marke, them that make diſsentions &amp; ſcandals contrary to doctrine which you haue learned and auoyd thē. The reaſone he yeldeth within a few words, for that this cōpany is perilous: Becauſe by ſweete ſpeeches &amp; benedictiōs they ſeduce the hartes of innocents. By often naming of the Lord, and his woorde, by frequēt cyting of Scripture, by reading the Goſpel, the Pſalmes, &amp; other partes of the olde and new Teſtament, they ſteale to them by title and litle the mindes of ignorant people.2. Cor. 6. And to the Corinthians he vrgeth the matter more vehemenlye after that he hathe geuen commandement not to beare the yoke

with Inſidels (that is to ſay) not to communicate with them in anye ſorte in their woorkes of infidelitye: ſhewing by diuers poynts of diſagreement, that there could be no felowſhipe or conueniencie betwene them. Firſt in reſpect of the diuers diſpoſition of their wils, what participation hath Iuſtice with iniquitye. Iuſtice requireth that a man exhibet his ſeruice to God in the Catholike Church, &amp; it is great iniquitie to withdraw him-ſelfe and others from the ſame ſeruice as heritikes do by rayſing perticuler factions. Then becauſe of their different doctrine: What ſocietie is there betwene light &amp; darknes? So you haue bene brought vpp in the lignt of Gods trueth, and the proteſtantes wander in darknes of ſunderye foule and abſurde errors. Thirdlye becauſe of the diuers Authors and founders of their congregations: what agreemēt betwene Chriſt &amp; Belial? Now Chriſt hath builded his Church vppon the ſucceſsion of S. Peeter, and Belial the ſpirite of diſobedience is the verye beginner of all heretical and ſchiſmattical

conuentickles. Fourthlye becauſe their whole ſtate differeth: what parte hath the faithful with the heretikes or Infidels, yea and the worſe ſorte of Infidels, becauſe of their departure from the faythe once receyued: by reaſone wherof their error is leſſe excuſeable, their malice commonly greater, their company more perilous for infection, and leſſe hope of their recouerye, then of ſuch as neuer knew Chriſts religion. Laſtly for the diuerſitie of their external ſeruice: What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? for you ar the Temple of the liuing God ſayth the Apoſtle, which he proueth by that ſaying in the lawe that God wil dwel and walke in them and wil be their God &amp; they ſhal be his people. So the whole Catholike church is the Tēple of God: but the doctrine of heretikes, their cō
               munion &amp; al their other external rites of religion are ſpiritual Idoles of their owne inuention, and haue ſucceded in place of groſſe and carnal Idolatry and therfore no leſſe to be ſhunned and deteſted. For which cauſe ſayth the Apoſtle

aledging the Prophet Iſay and Ieremye,Iſay. 52. 
               Goe out of the midſt of them, by geuing no credit to their falſe teaching, and ſeaperat your ſelues by auoyding of occaſions of contagion and touche not the vncleane by ſeeming in anye ſorte to conſent vnto their wickednes: and I will receyue you, and I will be a father to you: and you ſhalbe my ſonnes and daughters, ſayth our Lorde omnipotent. Likewiſe to the Theſſalonians he denounceth in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt that they ſhould withdraw them-ſelues frō euerye brother walking in ordinatly &amp; not according to the tradition which they had receyued:2. Theſs. 3. 
               Alſo yf any were diſobediente they ſhould note him by an epiſtle and not companye with him, that he might be confounded: Wihche is one principal cauſe why the Churche layeth vppon heretikes this payne to be excluded frō the ſocietye of her children, intending therby their correctiō, as hauing more power ouer them then other Infidels. A nother cauſe which is the peril, leſte the ſincere parte ſhould be corrupted by their companye, is expreſſed in one of the Epiſtles to Timothye where it is

ſayde:2. Timo. 2. 
               That their ſpeache ſpredeth as a canker, pernitiouſly creeping from one member to a nother. Alſo the ſame Apoſtle commandeth Titus by expreſſe worde to auoyd an heretike,Timo. 3. knowing that ſuch a one is ſubuerted, that is to ſaye, he is commonly paſt hope of amendment, and condemned by his owne iudgmēt, by his wilful running out of the Catholike churche. And agreably vnto this S. Iohn in one of his epiſtles, ſayth. Yf anye man come vnto you, and bring not thys doctrine [meaning that which had bene taught by the Apoſtles &amp; other lawful paſtors] receyue him not into thy houſe, nor ſaye, God ſaue you, vnto him, for he that ſayeth vnto him, God ſaue you, communicateth with his wicked wordes. And in his Reuelation he maketh reporte of Chriſt his owne wordes denouncing terrible puniſhment vnto all that ſhal participate with hereſie,Apo. 2. vnder figure of thoſe that cōmited aduoutry with a certein famos woman. And in the ſame booke of Pro. phecye he reherſeth the voyce of an Aungel who geueth warning vnto the ſeruants of God to auoyd &amp; flye al vngodly

godly cōpany,Apo. 18. ſignified by the name &amp; figure of wicked Babylon: Leſt they ſhold be partakers of her ſinnes and therby ſhould receyue of her plagues, and puniſhmētes. This poynte was diligently obſerued by S. Iohn himſelf who refuſed to tary in the ſame bathe with Cerinthus the enemye of truth, leſt the bath ſhould fal downe and oppreſſe them bothe: Alſo by Policarpus S. Iohn his ſcholer, who would not take acquaintance of Marcian that famous heretike, otherwiſe then by calling him the deuils eldeſt ſonne: And by S. Anthonie, of whom it is written that he could not indure to ſpeake one peaceable worde to an heretike. And although it be permitted in places where heretikes are in great multitude, for neceſsities ſake to cōuerſe and haue deling with them in worldly affayres, ſo long as they be not by name excomunicated and denounced: yet to haue felowſhip with them in actes of religiō, it neuer was nor could be allowed or ſuffered: But hath bene alwayes forbid den, as I ſayde before by the Cannons of the Church reyued from the bleſſed

Apoſtles.Can. 12. 45.46. 63. The authority of which Cannons moued Origen to refuſe by anye meanes to be preſent at prayers with a certain heretike called Paule.Eus. L. 6. Ca. 2. The ſame alſo moued Heraclas to caſt out of the Churche certayne Chriſtians becauſe they had vſed the cōpanye of heretiks, and not to be admitted againe before they had publikly declared whatſoeuer they had harde of thoſe enemies of the trueth,
                  L. 7. C. 6 notwithſtanding that he knewe them from their verye harte to be turned from all error and falſe doctryne. The like is decreed by the bleſſed Pope and martyr Fabian,Ep. 1. Ant. ca. 1 Laod. ca. 9.33. Car. 4. ca 71.72.73. De vnit. Ecc. verſus finem.
                and by the Counſels of Antioche and Laodicea, by the fourthe Counſel of Carthage, and dyuers others. The ſame hath ben taught by holy Doctors, as by S. Cyprian, who ſpeaking of heretiks and ſchiſmatikes, ſayth. we muſt depart frō ſuch offēders, or rather we muſt flye frō them in haſte, leſt that ioyning our ſelues with ſuch as walke peruerſly going with them in the waye of their error &amp; cryme, and wandering a ſtraye from the right and courſe of our iorney, we be holden guilty of lyke offence. And by S. Auguſtine who

entring into conference with one of the Manachies ſecte,Cont. Ep. Fund. cap 3. maketh exception of three thinges, whiche in no wiſe he wolde conſente to doe. Firſt that he wolde not praye with them: Secondly that he wolde not keepe ſolemne conuenticles with them: Thirdlye that he wolde not take vpon him the name of a Manichie. More-ouer it hathe bene practiſed by the whole church of al ages as may appeere by the exāple of thoſe godly people of Allexādria, Samoſata, Edeſſus,Theodo. Li. 2.17. Li. 4.19. 14.16. with diuers other Cityes wher whole multitudes wolde rather chooſe to ſuffer deathe then once to enter the churches while the Arian prelats were preſent: Whoſe godly zeale maye wel confound the colde deuotion of this vnhappy time wherin ſo few are found in compariſon of a great number who in hart doe beleeue the Catholike religion, ſo few there be I ſaye that wil be content to ſuſtayne the loſſe of a fewe goods for the open profeſsion of their fayth. Yea many there be that wil not take knowledge of this caſe wherof in times paſt no man was ignorant, no not

the verye heretikes, as Arians Donatiſts and ſuche like, all hauing their ſeueral churches by them ſelues, and refuſing to communicate either with Catholiks or with any other ſect diſagreing from their opinion.
            AND this maye be a nother important reaſon of your moſt iuſt,8 The iudgment of Infidels. and aduiſed refuſal: I meane the very iudgment and example of al Infidels touching participation with thoſe of a nother religion, the Iewes doe not enter into the churches of Chriſtians. The Turkes hold it for a ſigne of Mahomets religiō for one to come into their moſkeyes, the Lutherans and Caluiniſtes haue their ſeueral congregations one diſtincte from thother, and al the proteſtantes in other countryes refuſe to be preſent at the Catholike ſeruice. So did as manye of them as had zeale or care of their cōſcience in the late dayes of Quene Mary. In which time a famos preacher of their faction, inroled for a martire in Fox his booke, making anſwere to a certayn woman who demanded of him whether ſhe might goe to

mattens and euenſong [for to goe to maſſe her conſcience would not ſuffer her] pronounced and gaue his ſentēce in this or in muche like ſorte: that to goe to anye parte of the ſeruice then vſed, ſholde be a thing greatly againſt the honour of God, and contrarye to the charitye due vnto her neyghbour. It ſholde be againſt God his honour, becauſe (ſayth he) God is not to be honored but in ſuch ſort as he hath commaūded and taught by his worde meaning by God his worde expreſſe Scripture, where-as we include alſo ſuche trueth, as God hath reuealed vnto his Churche. Alſo he ſayde that by going vnto ſuch ſeruice ſhe ſhould denye and diſalowe of the whole doctrine of the Goſpel. And concerning breach of charity towardes her neyghbour, ſhe ſhold therby ſeuer her ſelfe from the congregation of the faithful. She ſhould great lye confirme the obſtinate Papiſts in their error, ſhe ſhould cauſe the weake Proteſtants to wauer in their religion, and ſhe ſhould greatly offend the more firme ſort of Goſpellers. Beholde here

the cauſe wherfore Catholiks be afflicted, determined by the iudgment of a Proteſtant preacher and recorded in the a fore-ſayd booke of Fox his monſterous monuments. Which thing being wel coſiddered wolde make one to woūder, that we ſhould be ſo vrged by the Proteſtants at this daye to doe the ſame thing whiche in their owne caſe, they haue thought &amp; muſt thinke very damnable ſeing that this common conſent of all ſectes and religions muſt nedes ſhew it to be a thing forbidden not only by man his ordinance, but by the verye lawe of God and nature and conſequently to be repugnant to the iudgment of euerye one that hathe in his breſte, but anye lytle ſparke of vprightnes and ſinceritye.9 Miſlike of the ſeruice
            
            AND now laſtlye to make vpp this matter of defence for your not going to the church, you refuſe to reſort to ſuch a ſeruice as beſides that it hath bene deuiſed by the Engliſh Proteſtāts a mong them ſelues, beſides that it is condemned of other ſectes, beſides that yt hathe no lyke paterne or platforme

a mongſte their Euangelicall brethren in other countries, beſides falſe tranſlation of Scripture, the defect of a lawful miniſter, the want of ſacrifice, ſacraments, reuerent ceremonies, and other things belonging to the honour of God which are conteyned in the Catholike ſeruice, beſides falſe doctrine and blaſphemye which muſt needes be offenſiue to all religious eares, is miſlyked of moſt euen at home and hath bene impugned by ſundery printed pamphelets which hath geuen occaſion of writing great bookes of controuerſie: Yea by all liklyhoode it had bene chaūged long before this day had not the grauer ſorte made ſtaye of the matter, for feare to incurr the note of inconſtancie, yea in the laſt parlament holden in your Realme anno. 29. wher in this monthly exaction was more aggrauated vpon you with peril of a greater forfayture, a booke was exhibited for the reformation of the forme of cō
               mon prayer now vſed, neyther was the matter determined otherwiſe then by contrarye commaundement of the ſuperiors:

although one wold thinke by reaſone it ſhould haue bene agreed amongſte them-ſelues, what ſeruyce they ſhould thinke beſte to vſe before you ſhould haue bene compelled vnder ſo greuous a payne to reſorte vnto their churches. Lo now you ſee here the cauſes of your refuſal. A moſt happye refuſal vndoubtedly yf you continue therin being grounded vppon ſo good reaſons of conſcience, of duetye towards God, of charity towards your Catholike bretheren, of reſpect to religion, of reuērece towards the Church of common honeſtie and playne dealing amongſt men, of care to auoyde the felowſhip of other mens ſinnes, being alſo iuſt, as that euen thoſe that do moſte perſecute you, yf the caſe were their owne: muſt needes plead for thē ſelues with the like alegations, and fynally being moued with miſlyke of the ſeruice where-vnto you are now commaūded to reſort, in which poynt your aduerſaryes cannot iuſtly reproue you, them-ſelues being not yet agreed whether it be the ſeruice of God or no, &amp;

manye of them earneſtly mainteyning the contrarye.
            
               The Second Parte what Recuſants ſhall loſe.
               NOW Let vs conſidder what loſſe you ſhal ſuſtayne for this refuſall. You ſhal loſe, ſo manye of you as ſhal not be able to diſcharge and aunſwere this heauye ſummes, your whole ſubſtance of moue-able goods, and ſuche as haue landes, ſhal loſe moreouer two partes of their reuenewes, and thoſe that are of more abilitye to ſupporte this greeuous burthen ſhal be greatlye impoueriſhed &amp; forced to abridge thē
                  ſelues of that which otherwiſe ſhould be verye conueniēt for their eſtate and calling. A verye hard caſe vndoubtdely, but yet not ſo harde but that by Gods grace it maye be eaſilye digeſted. And firſte of all thoſe that haue greater lyuinges doe leſſe ſtand in neede of comforte and with more quiete minds may ſuſtayn the loſſe that ſhal fall vpon thē:Comfort for them of more abillity. bothe for that they maye holde themſelues the better cōtented in reſpect of

thākfulnes towards God to loſe a litle for his ſake, hauing receiued much: &amp; farthermore becauſe the inconueniēce which they ſhal ſuffer is but the abaſing of their out-warde countenance in the world, which I hope there is no Catholike but wil patiētly and gladly indure if it wer for no other cauſe yet for chriſtian humilitye and modeſtye. To ſuch of you therfore as are of greater calling and haue more wher-with to mayntain your ſelues, I ſaye that I truſt there is none of you that ſo looketh towardes preferment but that you wil rather be content likewiſe to be aflicted with the people of God, then by offending God to haue temporal pleaſure for a while,Exo. 2 Heb. 11 eſteeming the reproche which you ſhal ſuffer for Chriſt greater riches then the treaſure of the Egiptians that is to ſaye of the whole worlde. There is none of you that ſo atendeth to purchaſe lands for the encreaſing of your patrimonye but that you haue greater care by good deedes to buy the kingdome of heauē. For if you purchaſe here on earth [you are as it were] not poſſeſsing:Cor. 7. And yf

you reioyce in the worlde you are as yf you reioyced not: And yf you vſe the world as thogh you vſed it not. Becauſe the figure of this world paſſeth awaye I truſt you account your ſelues here as ſtraungers and Pilgrims,1. Pet. 2. and therfore you ſeeke to haue houſes to dwel in for a while and not as though you ſhould remayne in them for euer. You ſhal be hindred by this perſecution from prouiding for your children ſo plentifully as otherwiſe you would, but you ſhal leaue vnto them Gods bleſſing whiche is more then al earthly riches. You ſhal not marrye your daughters ſo richlye nor with ſo great portiōs, but you ſhal matche them with Cotholikes who in this tyme of common neceſſitye ſhal more eſteeme of religion thē of riches, and ſhal more regard vertuous behauiour then vayne brauerye. You ſhal perhapes not haue ſo great attendance of ſeruants, but you ſhal be attended with Angels wherſoeuer you goe. And if you keepe not ſo greate familyes yet you maye keepe ſuch as be deuout towards God and faithful towards your ſelues:

As vndoubtedlye you ſhal make them much the better by this your example of ſuffering for Gods cauſe. Alſo you ſhal haue the leſſe to aunſwere for manye idle perſons and in a ſmaller number you ſhal haue the fewer euyl. You ſhal keepe leſſe hoſpitality among your neyghbours, but you ſhal be the leſſe enuyed by your aduerſaryes, and withal you ſhal haue leſſe occaſion to entertayne vnthankful heretikes anb ſchiſmatikes, who preying vpon your monye, can the leſſe expecte to be fedd at your tables. Yea perhaps you ſhal be able to beſtow more largelye vpon the domeſtical of fayth or if your almes be leſſe for lack of ability your good-wils ſhal be rather the more. For as you know the widdowes two mites is more then any riche mans treaſure and good folke wil conſidder, that you are afflicted Catholiks and therfore wil require the leſſe at your handes. I truſt you wil always folow the rule of good Tobias,Tob. 4. to be merciful in ſuch ſorte as you ſhal be able, and if you haue much, to geue aboundantly: If you haue litle, to beſtowe

yet a lytle willynglye: yea this whiche ſhal-be the greateſt almes that could be geuen. For as that bleſſed martyr Sir Thomas more ſayth, whē a man loſeth anye thing for Gods cauſe, although the deuils eſcheator ſeaſe vpon it, yet it is rendred to God. And as for delicate and ſumptuous fare, gaye apparrel &amp; other external worldly pompe I hope you are ſo farr frō being in loue with anye of thoſe thinges that rather you wil thanke God for geuing you occaſion to cut of ſuch ſuperfluous expences. But now for ſuche of you as haue lytle &amp; therfore not being able to ſatiſfie the penaltye ſhal loſe two partes of that which you haue, and for ſuche whoſe ſubſtance conſiſteth wholye or for the moſt parte in moueable goods, and therfore are lyke to loſe all and ſo to fal into great pouerty: there is great cauſe why they ſhould be releeued by ſuch whom god hath bleſſed more larglye with temporal benefits, and wherfore they ſhould be comforted agaynſt the extremity of this imminent ſtorme of worldlye affliction. And yet peraduenture

it ſhal be eaſier for ſome of thē to deſcend from their meane ſtate vnto the loweſt then for ſome other that haue borne a great port to come down but to a certayn mediocrity of liuing. For where there be leſt poſſeſsiōs, ther is manye times leſſe loue of the world: Although in deede there be no greate differēce between leeſing much or litle for Gods ſake, ſo that a man beare like loue towards God. But to ſuch of you now whoſe loſſe may be more greuous or that maye fall in to greater wante I directe my ſpeach, deſiring you to conſydder a while the condition of theſe earthlye goods and the burthen of pouertye whiche maye light vpon you in the hardeſt caſe that may be foreſeene by mans reaſone.Comfort for the poore. So ſhall you ſee neyther the loſſe to be ſo great nor the inconuenience that maye follow therof ſo intollerable, as at the firſt ſighte it might be eſteemed.
               AND Firſt touching wordly goods I myghte tell you accordyng to ſome phyloſophers,Conſideration of riches. yea by the iudgemente of manye Chriſtyan Doctors,

that they are not worthye the name of goods, becauſe they make not their poſſeſſors any thing the better. But rather they make them for the moſt parte farr the worſe: for ſo much as they are the occaſion of pryde whiche is the verye worme and diſeaſe that foloweth ryches. They kindle couetouſnes &amp; ther fore they be lyke to colde water being drounke by a man that is in ſome hott diſeaſe: the more that he drinketh the more it increaſeth his thirſt. They are matter of intemperance and ouer delicate lining. They geue impunity to vices and conſequently are occaſion of manye ſinnes. I might ſaye that they are common to good and to euil men, but more commonlye they ar beſtowed vpon the euil then vppon the good. Beholde ſinners haue obteyned riches, ſayth Dauid in one Pſalme:Pſal. 72. And this is ſo diſpoſed for ſundrye good reaſons. Firſt becauſe we ſhoulde vnderſtande theſe earthlye poſſeſsions not to be the true goods nor the rewarde whiche we expect to receyue, alſo becauſe thoſe wicked men are manye tymes rewarded

with earthlye ryches for ſome morall good which they haue done being not worthye at all of better recompence. And for the moſt part this aboundance of wealth, is an occaſion wherfore they become more vitious &amp; ſo is permitted vnto them as matter of more greeuous damnation. I might ſaye vnto you that none of theſe externall thinges whiche a man poſſeſſeth are to be called hys owne, becauſe they are not within him ſelf, &amp; therfore it is not in a mās power to keepe or not to leeſe them. This moued certayne Phyloſophers as Bias and Stilpo of Megara being ſpoylled of all that whiche they had, to boaſte that they caryed with them all their goods, meaning that they had not loſte theyr inward vertues. This bragg they made perhaps more confidently then truely, but how much better may a Chriſtian ſaye that although he be depryued of his earthlye goods, yet he hopeth that he ſhal not loſe his fayth, his truſt, and his loue towards God, and conſequent lye he ſhal not loſe God himſelfe the geuer of all goodnes and the onlye ryches

that maye ſuffice and cauſe him to line content and happye. I might ſhew to you out of profane hiſtoryes that manye Philoſophers either for loue of knowledge or deſire of vayne glorye as Anacharſis, Crates, Antiſthenes, and almoſt all thoſe of like ſtudye and profeſsion, and manye worthye Captayns and honourable men in their common wealthes, as Ariſtides and Phocion among the Athenians, and among the Romanes, Fabritius and M. Curius, haue eyther choſen to become poore, or haue refuſed to be made rich, when occaſion was offered. I might proue further by good reaſon, that this external wealth, is no otherways profitable, but when it is wel beſtowed. And how can it be beſtowed with more aduaū
                  tage, then being forſaken for gods loue and for the redemption of your owne ſoules. Otherwiſe what benefite hath the rich man by his great aboūdance? Or what doe his large poſſeſsiōs auayle him? Are they profitable in reſpect of his health? we ſee that moſte wealthy men can hardlye repayre their bodies

by contynuall applying of medicyne, where-as the poore man contynueth ſound without healpe of phyſike. Hath he more libertye to goe where he wil, or more freedome to do what him beſt pleaſeth? vndoubtedlye no. For ſetting a ſide the couetous mā whoſe hart is alwayes tyed and chayned vnto his money, and take what riche man you wil, he is more reſtrayned from beſtowing his tyme at his pleaſure by the manifolde inſtance of his tēporal affayres then the poore cottier, by the neceſsitye of getting his dayly liuing by daylye labour. But dothe he enioye more pleaſures? No ſurely. For although he haue perhapps greater ſtore of delights yet pleaſure cōſiſteth rather in rarenes then in continual vſe, &amp; rather in mens deſires, then in the nature of thinges themſelues. The rich man can ſcarcely finde any dayntyes that maye content his appetite, where as the poore hath hūger for his ſauce to al kind of meats. As it is written in the Prouerbs.
                  Pro. 7. 
                  That the ſoule which is already fully ſatiſfied wil tread the hony combe vnder foote: but the hungry

wil take men bitter for ſwete. The rich man toſſeth vp and doune in his ſofte bedd after a ful ſtomake, where as the poore man, ſleepeth ſoundly vpon his ſimple couche, after meane dyet, by reaſone of his long dayes labour. Sleepe is ſweete, (ſayth wiſe Salomon) to him that worketh whether he eate lytle or muche:
                  Eccle. 5, 
                  but the fulnes of a rich man doth not ſuffer him to ſleep. The rich hath moe fauning friends peraduenture, but he hathe leſſe aſſurance of their fidelitye becauſe they maye be friendes in reſpect of his riches, rather then for the loue of his perſone. He is ſerued of many, but withal he hath the charge to prouid for many.Eccle. 5. 
                  Wher ther is much wealth, ther be alſo many that eate to cō
                     ſume the ſāe, &amp; than what doth it profit the poſſeſſor, but that he ſeeth his riches with his eyes. He hath the name of Lord &amp; maiſter, but in dede he hath but the ſtewardſhip &amp; diſpoſition of theſe earthly goods to the benefit of others, who liue at his coſt more quietly or merely then him-ſelfe: hauing no more for his owne parte thē wil feede one belly &amp; cloth one backe, fare he neuer ſo wel, or be he clothed

neuer ſo trimly. But perhapps the rich are leſſe ſubiect to iniuries and oppreſſions? It is altogether contrarye. For the poore man lyueth without moleſtation of any if you conſider him as he is poore: and if he be any wayes troubled it is in reſpect of ſome litle goods that he hath or procureth to haue. But the rich man is more often a pray to thoſe that are more mightye and riche, then the poore people are to him-ſelfe. He is had in geloſie by his ſuperiors, he is impugned by his equalls, he is enuyed and vndermined by his inferiors, he is betrayed many times for his money by his ſeruants, yea by his owne children. Therfore I might ſaye farther, that by cōmon experiēce the hauing of worldlye pelfe is matter of care, how it maye be kepte, how it may be imployed, and how it may be increaſed. It is occaſion of feare: for the rich man feareth thoſe that be richer then him-ſelfe, and ſuch as be poorer: he feareth theeues, he feareh chaūge of weather. He feareth ſtrā
                  gers in time of war, he feareth his neighbours when there is peace: he feareth

his owne familye, he ſcarcely dare truſt his owne handes. Furthermore it breedeth ſutes and contentions: it prouoketh enemyties, it procureth a thouſād perils, ſo that we ſee mo to haue peryſhed for their riches, then to haue died for famine. And if we ſhal geue credite to the holye Scriptures, this baſe and earthly baggage, is often times a great impediment to mens ſaluation. Therfore ſayth out Sauiour:Mat. 19. 
                  That a rich man ſhall hardly enter into the kingdome of heauē: Yea that it is more eaſye for a Camell to paſſe through the ſtreicte eye of a needle. The reaſons herof be many, firſt the multitude of cares, which theſe worldlye goodes commonly bring with them, in reſpect whereof they are called thornes that ſuffocate and choke vp the ſeede of god his word.Mat. 13. eSecondly the delycate manner of lyfe which the moſt part of wealthye folke leade, and therfore ſaith our Sauiour:Luc. 6. 
                  wo to you that be rich, becauſe you haue your conſolation. Alſo becauſe it is harde to haue manye poſſeſsions, and not to loue them beyond meaſure.Luc. 14. And you know wel that whoſoeuer ſo much

loueth theſe earthly goods that he be not ready to renounce and forſake thē all for the loue of God when the cauſe ſo requireth, cannot be the diſciple of Chriſt, neither can he haue part in god his kingdome. Hereof it came that he which had bought a farme, &amp; he which had bought fiue yoke of oxen refuſed to come to the ſupper, wher-vnto they were inuited. Moreouer it is very harde to haue much, and not to couet more▪ wherby worldly mē deſiring to be rich doe fall as S. Paule ſaith into temptatiō,1. Tim. 6 and into the ſnare of the deuil, and manye deſyres vnprofitable and hurteful which drown men into diſtruction and perdition: The proufe herof is very euident by the manyfolde intricate caſes wher-with euen they that thinke them ſelues to haue vpright conſciences be ofte intangled and doe offend by pretence of Tytles, by ordinary buying ſelling and bargayning, and other temporal dealings and affayres. For theſe and many other conſiderations I ſay to you as vnto Chriſtians, and vnto men that haue care of their ſoules health. That

what-ſoeuer it is poſsible for you to haue in this worlde, were it neuer ſo properly called by the name of goods, were it neuer ſo rightlye termed your owne, were it neuer ſo profitable, ſo pleaſant and ſo apt to good vſes yea although you ment to imploye it to the beſt vſe that might be deuiſed, cannot yet be ſo much worth as that you ſhold for the retayning of the ſame diſpleaſe God by one mortal ſinne and muche leſſe ſeperate your ſelfe frō the Church by heynous and damnable ſchiſme and participation with hereſye.Mat. 16. 
                  For what ſhould it profit you to gaine the whole worlde and ſustayne the damage of your ſoules. And ſpecially ſince al that you poſſeſſe hath come vnto you freely by God his gifte and then thinke with your ſelues what a greuous poynt of ingratitude it ſhold be to forſake the geuer for any parte of that which he hath geuen. This conſidderation moued bleſſed Iob to beare paciently the loſſe of al his wealth and not to offend God, ſo much as with anye impacient or fooliſh woorde.Iob. 1. 
                  Naked I came out of my motheres wombe (ſaith

he) and naked I ſhall retourne thyther, our Lorde hath geuen, our Lorde hath taken awaye: as it hathe pleaſed our Lorde, ſo it is done the name of our Lorde be bleſſed. It is greatly to be noted that although the Sabeans had taken away his oxen and aſſes, although the Chaldies had ſpoled him of his Cammels, although the deuil had cōſumed his ſhepe with fire, and had rayſed a winde to ouerthrowe his houſe, and to oppreſſe his children, yet he ſaith our Lord hath taken away, knowing wel that none of theſe things coulde haue hapned without God his permyſsion and ſpecial prouydence: which may teache you in all loſſes that may fal out, to conſidder God his ordinance, and ſo to reſte contented accepting his holy wil and diſpoſition. Conformably to thoſe wordes of Iob S. Paule ſaythe.1. Tim. 6 
                  we brought nothing into thys worlde: doubtleſſe neither can we take awaye anye thing. Conſidder I praye you how bare, how needy and deſtitute of all helpe, you were firſte borne, and how you differd nothing from the pooreſt childe that is brought to light, ſetting

a ſide the care and prouiſion of others that were nere about you. And thē ſhal you wel perceyue that whatſoeuer you now enioye, or haue enioyed hath bene beſtowed vpon you thorough God his infinite bountye and liberalytye, and what a poynte of clowniſhe inciuylitye would you thinke it were for a beggers brat, being taken by ſome great Prince into his courte, who ſhould cauſe him to be dayntilye nouriſhed and richlye appareled, intending after-wardes to make him heyre of his kyngdome, to ſett at naught the great fauour of that Prince, &amp; wilfully to forſake his courte yf he would dot in al things make him ſo large allowance as he had done before. And euen lyke vncourteſy, naye infinite tymes more ſhould it be for anye man after ſo great number of benefites receiued at God his hands, beſides the expectation of heauen in time to come, to ſett naught by his grace, to neglect his fauour, to commit hye treaſon againſt him for the ſauing of a litle worldlye traſhe whiche he alone hath geuen, and when it pleaſeth hym can

take it a way againe. This point I beſech you to waye aduiſedlye, and with-al to conſider the ſecond parte of S. Paules ſentence that moſt certaynlye you ſhal carye nothyng wyth you out of thys world. Thinke what vnſpeakable grefe it ſhal-be for one that hath diſpleaſed God for the ſauyng of hys worldlye goodes when at the time of his death he muſt depart and leaue his fayre houſes, his goodlye mānors and lordſhips and al that he helde moſt deere in this lyfe: neyther that nor al the ſubſtance of the worlde if he had it to geue can procure him one houres reſpite for penance, and much leſſe can obtayne his ſaluation.Pſal. 49. 
                  He ſhall not geue the price of redemption of his owne ſoule. Saith Dauid of the rich man truſting in his riches: whē he dyeth he ſhall not take with him all that he hath, neyther ſhall his glorye goe downe with him. But perhapps he truſteth to leaue hys poſſeſsyons to his chyldren, the Pſalme ſeemeth to affirme the cōtrary: They ſhall leaue their ryches to ſtraungers, which is to be vnderſtood as S. Auguſtine ſaith vpō that place, that although

their children ſucceed them in the poſſeſsion of their patrymonyes yet can they nothing relieue the miſeryes of their friends being damned to hel fire, and what profit then doe they reape to them-ſelues. Their ſepulchers are their houſes for euer, they haue prepared to them-ſelues coſtlye monumentes as if they ſhould dwell in thē perpetually not prouiding for the manſions wherin they ſhould liue in deede euerlaſtingly. But what becommeth of the poore ſoules who reape no benefite of their ſolemne funerals, &amp; ſtately tombes, but rather haue their paynes agrauated, it foloweth within a while that the wicked rich man ſhal enter euen into the generation of his fathers, that is to ſay of vngodly men that here to fore hath bene lyke to him-ſelfe and he ſhal not ſee light for euer, becauſe when he was here he delighted in darknes, and reioyced in falſe goodes, not louing the true goodes he ſhal therfore goe hence to hel: after the darkenes of his dreames wherin he imagined to himſelfe a deceitful kinde of felicity he ſhalbe geuen ouer to the darkenes of eternall

tormentes. Looke into thoſe houſes, I meane thoſe Sepulchers, and conſidder the lengthe,
                  Pſal. 75. 
                  breadeth, and height of thoſe manſions, and compare the ſame, with thoſe ſtatelye roomes wherin they dwelled here-tofore. Looke vpon their decayed nature, their rotten bones and conſumed members. See whether you can diſcerne the maiſter from the ſeruant, the riche man frō the begger, the Prince from his pooreſt ſubiect. Cōſidder what is become of their gallant traynes of ſeruitors, their gorgeous apparell, their goodly plate, and coſtly furniture. See whether they haue now anye vſe of theſe thinges. All is earth, all is duſt, all is wormes all is putrefaction. And what ſhalbe the ſtate of ſuch fooles at the day of Iudgement? The Prophet telleth vs in a nother pſalme that the louers of thys worlde whome he calleth the men of riches: Haue ſlepte their ſleepe, and waking they haue foūd nothing in their hands. whiles they were here in this lyfe they thought thē ſelues to be happye, they ſlept in their deſires, they were delighted in vayne pompes, but at the daye of reſurrection, they haue found their handes empty for lacke of good woorkes being deſtitute of al that wherin they gloried before.
                  
Tel me what comforte had the riche man burning in the flames of hel, who before neglected to geue his crommes to poore Lazarus, by remembrance of his former wealth, his dainty foode, &amp; ſumptuous clothing. Or what reaped that other curmogion of all his aboundance. To whom thinking to enlarge his barnes, and to make mery with his ſtore for a long time together: It was ſayde, Thou foole this night they ſhal require thy ſoule of thee.
                  Luc. 12. 
                  And theſe thinges whiche thou haſt prouided, whoſe ſhal they be? Note wel thoſe wordes. Whoſe ſhall they be? A man heapeth vp treaſures ſaythe the Pſalme,Pſal. 38. 
                  and knoweth not for whom he gathereth them. Whether for an vnthankful, or a prodigal childe. Whether they ſhal be euicted by his aduerſaries thorough coloure of lawe, or ſhal to the Prince by attaynder, or ſhall come to the marchants hands by way of vſury. O deare Catholikes, lifte vp your eyes, and looke vpon this general day of waking from the ſleepe of death,Sap. 5. ſee with what conſtancie you ſhal ſtande in that dreadful day, if you be now conſtant,

againſt thoſe which haue opreſſed you and haue taken awaye from you the fruites of your labours. Behold againe how your perſecutors ſhalbe troubled with horrible feare, and ſhal woūder at your ſodayne and vnexpected ſaluation: how they ſhal ſaye within themſelues with much anguiſh of ſpirit and groning: what hath our pride profited vs? or what the boaſting of our riches auayled vs? al thoſe thinges haue paſſed awaye like a ſhadowe with a greate deale more, whiche is expreſſed in the booke of wiſdome. And as you would not in that daye chaūge with them, yf you might enioye a thouſand worldes: So now thinke your ſelues more happy what-ſoeuer you ſhal leeſe for Chriſte his ſake, then yf for a temporal cōmodity you ſhould be ioyned to that cōmpany of the damned to ſuffer extreame cōfuſion and torments that neuer ſhal haue end. Conſider beſides al this the vncertayntye of riches euen in this life to what daungers and chaunces they are ſubiect, and how they ebb &amp; flowe from one to a nother. Therfore if riches

flow aboūdantly, ſett not your harts vpon thē, in ſuche wiſe that you flow with-al and rūne frō God in this time of perſecution.Pſal. 61. Truſte not ſo much in the incertayntye of worldly goodes ſo that you loſe for them the hope of your heauen lye heritage. Be not deceitful in your waytes to deceyue your ſelues with to much accompt of vanity, but eſteeme al temporal thinges as they are, according vnto the conditions which I haue layde downe before you.
               
                  Conſideration of pouertye.NOW If riches be no more to be eſteemed then as it may apeare by theſe reaſons here recited, let vs waye likewiſe the burden and incōuenience of pouertye whether by any meanes it may be endured with quiet and indifferent mind. A light burthē vndoubtedly ſuppoſing ſufficiencie as we ſhal proue herafter, with the preſēce of gods grace yea in this caſe when it is ſuſtayned for Gods ſake a ſweete and delightful burthen. And firſt in thoſe riches which ar common to al men by nature. As the inflūece of the heauens, the commoditye of the bryght and warme ſunne the

goodlye moone, the cleere ſterres, the pure and freſhe ayre: And many other benefits of Gods creatures, there is no doubt but that pouertye enioyeth her parte more freely, more often and with more delight, then doth the rich man, who for the moſt parte leadeth his lyfe in a cloſe houſe and when he goeth abroad he attēdeth not to take pleaſure in ſuch thinges hauing his minde occupied about his manifolde temporal buſines. And for the vſe of al neceſſaryes we haue partlye heretofore compared the rich and poore together, and now we maye ſaye agayne that the poore haue their ſubſtance with leſſe coſte &amp; care &amp; their reſt with leſſe diſturbance. They are alſo ſerued more ſurely &amp; dulye By their owne indeuour then thoſe wealthy folke for whom the prouiſion. of Sea and Lande wil not ſuffice who cannot cōtriue how they may lay their heades at conuenient eaſe and for whō all the ſeruice of men in liuerye coates is to litle. O happy pouerty that is not forced to make friendes in court, to retayn counſailers for the barr, to wayte

vpon atturneyes, to folow ſiſe and ſeſsions, to make her part ſtrong by banding of men againſt her aduerſaryes. She is not vexed with exactions ſhe is either more ſafe in common calamityes to abide without daunger, or more readye to flye and eſcape: ſhe aduentureth not her ſelfe by ſea for lucres ſake and therfore is not in perill of pirates: ſhe maye better goe without weapon by lande, for as the common prouerbe is ſhe may ſinge before a theefe. And to the exerciſe of vertue ſhe is no impedimēt but rather many times a great furtherance. She is companion with humilitye ſhe is mother of modeſtye and temperance maintayner of ſobryetye ſchoole-miſtres and teacher of patiēce nurſe of deuotion &amp; contēplation. Only in geuing of corporal almes, ſhe ſeemeth to be inferyor and yet ſhe is not excluded from geuing a cupp of colde water which may be meritorious of life euerlaſting ſhe maye feede a prophet with alitle oyle and flower ſhe may entertayne Chriſt in a poore fiſhers houſe ſhe may waſhe the weried feete of gods

pilgrims. She may healpe and ſerue the ſicke ſhe may viſite and comfort priſoners if ſhee cannot otherwiſe releeue them. She may further the cauſe of religion, if not by money, yet by induſtry of minde and bodilye trauaile.Rom. 6. Aquila and Priſcilla were poore folkes and liued by the labour of their handes by making of tentes and yet S. Paule calleth them his helpers in Chriſt Ieſus to whom not only he geueth thankes but alſo al the churches of the Gentiles: &amp; morouer they had a domeſtical church of their owne. But one obiectiō is here needful to be anſwered, wherfore Salomon ſhould earneſtly deſire God not to geue him beggerye leſte perhaps he ſhould be compelled to ſteale, and to forſweare the name of his God. The anſwere is eaſelye geuen that Salomon ſpake according to the ſtate of the olde Teſtament,Pro. 30. and in the perſon of the imperfect, who maye fall into ſuch inconueniences when they become poore againſt their wils by worldly miſchāce. But ſuch peril is in no wiſe to be feared when a man leaueth or loſeth his gooddes

and willinglye be commeth poore for the loue of God.Mat. 19. Otherwiſe if pouerty were an impediment to ſaluation our Sauiour would not haue propoſed it as a poynt of perfection to a certayn rich yoūg man that aſked him coūſaile what he ſhould doe ouer and beſides the keping of Gods commandements. Yea which is more he would not haue conſecrated the ſame in his owne perſon as it was fore-tolde of him in one of the Pſames.Pſal. 39. 
                  I am a begger and a poore man, ſaith Dauid in the figure of chriſt. This is a ſinguler prerogatiue of pouertye and a principal motiue to al Chriſtians to ſuſtayne gladly anye want for his ſake who was made poore where as he was riche that by his pouertye we might be rich. What ſubiect would diſdayn to folowe the faſhion of his ſoueraygne?2. Cor. 8 what ſoldier wold thinke ſcorn to be attyred like his Captayne? what ſcholler would be aſhamed to reſemble his maiſter in his profeſsion? Now our Lorde and King our Captayne our M. Ieſus Chriſte dyd chooſe to be borne poore to be ſwadled in ſimple clothes

and to be layd in a maūger. His bleſſed mother was poore and ſo was holy Ioſepth the guardian of his infancie.Mat. 3. His birth was firſt reueiled to poore ſheepherds.Mat. 5. His fore runner S. Iohn baptiſt was poore being clothed with a camels ſkinn and fed with locuſt and wyld honye.Luc. 9. He began his preaching with commendation of pouerty: he led a poore life hauing not where to reſt his head.Mat. 19. He choſe for his Apoſtles poore men, or yf they had anye thing before, they lefte al whē they folowed him. He gaue it for a principal token that he was the true Meſſias that he preached the glad tidings of the Goſpel to the poore.Mat. 11. He dyed poore hauing no houſe nor roofe to couer him, not lying vpon a ſofte bedd but hanging vpon his hard croſſe hauing a crown of thorne in ſtead of a pillowe for his head: being ſpoyled of his clothes to the bare ſkinn whiles the wicked ſoldiers that crucified him deuided his garments among them and caſt lotts for his coate: being withal ſo deſtitute of friendes yea in his burning thirſt he could get nothing to drinke

but ſower vineger. But what ſpeake I of his pouertye? He ſhead his pretious blood for your redemption: And can you thinke much for his loue to depart from a litle worldly pelfe and vile trumpery?1. Cor. 2 S. Paule deſcribing generally the calling of Chryſtians ſaythe, That God hath not choſen many wyſe according to the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble: And like-wiſe S. Iames ſayth,Iac. 2. 
                  That god hath choſen the poore in this worlde, rich in fayth, and heyres of the kingdome which God hath promiſed to them that loue him. And one would thinke that the heauenly wiſdōe preferring the poore in this ſorte were better to be truſted then the iudgment of worldly folke who cōmonly eſteme of a man according to his money.
               
                  3 Rewarde for Recuſantes.AND Thus hauing pondered the ſeueral conditions of riches and pouertye, it remayneth to be conſidered what further aduantage you may haue, if for conſcience ſake you ſhal be driuē to exchange the one for the other: to the ende that ſeeing before your eyes aſſurance of moſt vndoubted gayne, you maye boldlye aduenture vpon a

bargain ſo beneficial, wherin almighty God him-ſelfe becommeth your debtor. For he that is faythful and true, hath promiſed with his owne mouthe,Mat. 19. 
                  That who ſoeuer forgoeth anye thing for his loue ſhall receyue a hundreth fold, and ſhall poſseſſe lyfe euerlaſting. You ſhal receyue an hundred fold as an earned pennye in this lyfe, and lyfe euerlaſting ſhal be your reward in time to come. This hū
                  dred fold as it maye diuers wayes be vnderſtode, ſo principally,A hundred folde I thinke yt may be taken to conſiſte in three thinges, in ſufficiencye, of neceſſaryes for the preſent tyme,Sufficiēcy. in quietnes and contentment of minde, and in manye other ſpiritual guiftes and graces. Firſt concerning ſufficiency of tēporal thinges. It conſiſteth in Gods prouidence, in his almightye power and fatherlye goodnes we haue many promiſes therof, and manye examples, bothe in the old and newe Teſtament, as where it is ſayde,Pſal. 32. 
                  That the eyes of our Lorde are vpon thē that feare him and vpon thoſe that truſt in his mercy to deliuer their ſoules from death and to nouriſhe them in famyne: that there

is no pouerty or want to thoſe that feare him. That the rich haue lacked,
                  Pſal. 33. 
                  and haue ben hungery by reaſon of their couetous and inſatiable mindes,
                  Pſal. 36. 
                  but they that ſeeke our Lord ſhall not fayle to haue all good. That the iuſt ſhall not be confounded, in the euill and hard time, &amp; in the dayes of famine they ſhalbe ſatiſfied. Like-wiſe in the Prouerbs it is ſaid that God will not afflicte with famine the ſoule of the iuſt. And as for examples we might bringe greate ſtore for proofe of this poynt wherby it may appeare that not only God doth not ſuffer his ſeruants to be deſtitute of things belonging to the ſuſtentation of their tēporal life, but furthermore when it pleaſeth him he rewardeth them aboundantly euen in this worlde.Gen. ca. 12. Abraham forſooke hys countrye and kinſe-folke and wente at God his cōmandement into a ſtraūge lande where he had no foote of poſſeſſion, and God bleſſed him with worldlye ſubſtance during his lyfe, and three hūdred yeares &amp; more after his death, he gaue that whole land to be poſſeſſed by his poſteritye.Gen. ca. 32. Iacob paſſed Iordein with his ſtaffe fleeing from his brother

Eſau into Meſopotamia,Gen. ca. 41. but he returned agayne with two troupes hauing wyues and children, and great aboundance of cattell. Ioſeph was ſolde into Egipt as a bondſlaue &amp; there for righteouſnes ſake was thruſt downe into a dungeon, but after a while it pleaſed God to deliuer him and to make him ruler of the whole countrye.Exo. ca. 3 Moyſes forſoke the wealth of Egipt and kepte ſheepe in the deſert: and it pleaſed god ther to apeare vnto him &amp; to make him gouernour ouer his people. Holy Iob was abaſed euen to ſitt vpon the dunghil ful of ſores,Iob. ca. 42. but in the ende God beſtowed vpon him double welth to that which he had before.Reg. Li. 3. ca. 17. 19. Elias was poore and fled from the perſecution of Ieſabel but he was ſufficiently fed, once by the rauens that daylye broughte him meate, and a nother tyme by bread which God miraculouſly prouided for him. Elizeus was poore,Re. Li. 4. cap. 4. but he was ſued vnto by great Princes: yea he was able to feede others by bread miraculouſlye multiplyed.Tob. c. 1. Bleſſed Toby was ſpoyled of al his ſubſtance by the wicked

King Senu-Acherib for his charitye towardes the dead: but after fortye fyue dayes he was reſtored to hys houſe and to al his poſſeſsions agayne.Daniell. Cap. 14. Daniel for his religion towards God, was caſt into the Lions den, but he was fedd by a Prophet being wonderfullye brought out of the lande of Iurye for that purpoſe.Machabi orum. Li. 4. Cap. 2. And ſo as Mathias ſayde to his ſonnes, conſider through-out euery generation, and you ſhal ſee, that al which truſt in him are not weakned nor ouerthrowne. But what doe I rehearſe the example of godlye men, our Sauiour ſendeth vs,Mat. 6. euen vnto the foules of the ayre to ſee how they are fed, &amp; to the lillies of the fielde to beholde how they are clothed to thende that we ſhould not doubte of God his prouidence, for meate drinke clothing &amp; other thinges neceſſary for the mayntenance of this lyfe. And vndoubtedly this is a conſideration of great importance. For if God of his goodnes extēd to feed the pore wormes of the earth:Pſal. 31. As it is written in the Pſalme, That he openeth his hand and filleth euery lining creture with bleſsing,
                  Pſa. 144. 
                  if he beſtow foode euen vpō
                     pon

 the yong Rauens,
                  Pſal. 146 
                  being not ſuccoured by their dames that brought them forth. If neyther the feather of anye foule, nor the leafe of any tree, be deſtitute of his prouidence, yf the verye Infidels be viſited daylye with God hys benefyttes whiche they receyue of the Sunne,Iob. ca. 39. the Ayre, and the Earth yeelding her fruites in due time, how muche rather wil he prouide for his ſeruantes that ſuffer affliction for the glorye of his name. How much rather will he prouide for you O ye of verye ſmale faith ſayth our Sauiour. Is not the lyfe more then the meate:
                  Mat. 6. 
                  and the bodye more then the rayment? Therfore he that hath geuen the greater benefites, wil not fayle to prouide for the leſſe. Your father knoweth that you neede al theſe thinges, and who wil miſtruſt the prouyſion of ſo mightye, ſo wyſe, ſo good and ſo louing a father. Seeke therfore firſt the kingdome of God and the iuſtice of him: Take care how you maye ſaue your owne ſoules, &amp; pleaſe God: And all theſe thinges ſhalbe geuen you beſides, ſo that you ſhal not nede to feare anye incōuenience by loſſe of temporal goods

for god his cauſe. For declaratiō of this prouidence:Luc. 10. Our Sauiour when he ſent his Apoſtles firſt to preache, he forbad them to carye Purſe, or ſcrip or ſhoes, and a litle before his Paſsion he aſked them When I ſent you Without purſe and ſcrip and ſhoes,
                  Luc. 22. 
                  did you lacke anye thing? But they ſayde nothing. And after Chriſte his aſcenſion when they went into farther countryes and therfore ſtode in more neede, and had leſſe prouiſion for neceſſaries, heare what S. Paule ſaythe of him-ſelfe and other his fellowes.S. Pa. ad Cor. cap. 4. Epi. ſecūd 
                  In all thinges we ſuffer tribulation, and are not in diſtreſſe, we want, but are not deſtitute: we ſuffer perſecution, but are not forſaken: we are caſt downe,
                  Cap. 6. 
                  but we periſhe not. And within two chapters of the ſame epiſtle after a great number of thinges recyted that might ſeme contrary at the firſt apparance, he maketh vpp the ſentence with theſe wordes, As needye, but inriching manye, as hauing nothing, and poſſeſſing all thinges. Meaning that they had the whole world and all God his creatures at cōmandement. And leaſt you ſhould thinke this priuiledge proper

to the Apoſtles and to none other, beholde the poore Hebrues,Act. 4. the very firſt flowers of Gods Church, who ſold al that they had &amp; gaue the price to be diſtributed in godly vſes: and you ſhal perceiue that they receiued their hundreth folde by Gods prouiſion, when the Gentils of ſunderye nations were careful to contribute to their reliefe,Rom. 16 &amp; S. Paule him-ſelfe was collector and bearer of the almes beſtowed vpon thē. And among holye Martyrs as we reade of manye that haue bene fed by the ſeruice of Angels, ſo we find very few that eyther in priſon or out of priſon haue periſhed for lacke of ſuſtenance. And in the number of Hermites that willinglye became poore for Chriſte hys ſake, we reade of S. Paule fed by a Rauen, and S. Gyles nouriſhed by the milke of an Hinde. And among thouſands that be extremelye poore in diuers religious familes, doe we not ſee that the moſt of them lyue and finde no great defect of neceſſaries? And can anye man doubt of ſufficiencie, hauing ſo manye examples of Gods goodnes

in this behalfe? Or is not this ſufficiencie as muche as al the wealthe of the world can afforde, and therfore an hundreth folde in cōpariſon of that which anye one man poſſeſſeth. Eſpecialye if a contented minde be ioyned therwith al.2. Tim. 6 According to that ſaying of S. Paule. Piety with ſufficiency is a great gayne. Therfore ſaythe he, Hauing foode, and where-with to be couered, with theſe we are content.
               
               
                  2 Contentmente of mynde.THIS Quietnes &amp; contentment of mynde proceedeth eſpeciallye of Gods grace whiche tempereth the appetite of man, being before inſatiable and crying ſtil after, bring, bring, although he haue neuer ſo muche alreadye. And as the deſire of hauing more, is a great tormente to couetous riche men, enwrapping them with many cares, and ſetting them about much vnhappye buſines: ſo this limiting of a mans deſire, to be contente with that which God ſendeth, be it more or litle is a ſinguler benefite, more worth then anye golde, yea ſuch a one as no world lye treaſure can procure. For tell me I

pray you is it not much better to cure a man of his feuer, which cauſeth him ſtil to deſire drinke and neuer to be ſatiſfied, then to geue him drinke at his deſyre and not to quench but rather to kindle this thirſt. Here-of it commeth to be true which is ſayde in one of the Pſalmes. A litle is better to the iuſte man,
                  Pſal: 36. 
                  then the aboundante riches of ſinners. And that whiche S. Hierome ſaythe.Epi. ad. Pauiinū. The beleeuing man hath a world of riches: to the couetous mā nothing is enough. And the verye heathen Philoſophers, acknowledged that for a man to be cō
                  tente with his owne was the greateſt &amp; the moſt certayne riches: And it was a cōmon ſaying among them. The mind of a man is riche, and not his cofer. Of this contented minde, we haue an example of S. Paule, who ſayth ſpeaking of himſelfe. I know both to be brought low,
                  Phil. 4. 
                  I know alſo to abound: (euerye wher and in all thinges I am inſtructed) both to be full, &amp; to be hungerye, both to abounde and to ſuffer penurye. And if anye man ſhould ſaye: I am not S. Paule, I am not an Apoſtle: let him at leaſte, not be found inferiour

to Socrates a heythen man, who notwithſtanding that he was pore, paſsing one tyme thorough the market place, and ſeing great ſtore of diuers wares, ſayd with him-ſelfe. How many things be here, that I doe not deſire. And can not the grace of God worke as muche in the harte of a faythful man falling in to pouertye for his loue by meanes of perſecution? I thinke there is none of you that haue bene conuerted to God from the way of ſinne, and loue of this wretched worlde, eſpeciallye hauing loſt anye thing for Gods cauſe, that he hath not withal felt by experience the proofe of this poynte, and therfore I ſhal not neede to-ſtande longer in confirming the ſame.
               
                  3 Spirytuall graces.AND As for ſpiritual giftes and graces whiche God beſtoweth vpon thoſe that willinglye forgoe their temporal goods for his loue: S. Peter was a poore fiſher and for his boate whiche he lefte at Chriſts commandement he receiued the gouerment of Chriſte his Church,Luc. 5. in place of his nett. The worde of God was committed vnto him and

for his trade of taking fiſhes to their diſtruction,Act. 3. he was made a fiſher of mens ſoules to ſaluatiō.Cap: 5. He had neither gold nor ſiluer but with hys worde in the name of Chriſt he could cure the lame,Cap: 9. with his onlye ſhadow he could heale the ſicke, and by his prayers he could rayſe the dead againe to life.Phil. 3. S. Paule eſteemed the things that were gaynes to him before to be detriments for the exceeding loue of Chriſt:Act, 9. And he was made a veſſel of election to cary Gods name before the Gentils, to teache &amp; cōuert the greateſt parte of the world. He was rapte into the thirde heauen,2. Co. 14 &amp; ſawe the ioyes of Paradiſe. His name was terrible to wicked ſpirites,Act. 19. his very napkins and handkerchifs had efficacy to cure all kind of malladies. The reſte of Chriſts Apoſtles for that litle which they froſooke at his bidding, receyued authoritye to preach the Goſpel,Pſal. 44. vertue to cure diſeaſes, and power to caſt out deuils.Mat. 19. They were made Princes ouer the whole earth, and appoynted iudges of the worlde in time to come. S. Anthony. S. Hilarion and others be

came willinglye poore, where-by they might more freelye ſerue God: and they became as it were Angels here in earth, they were made euen in this life fellowes with heauenly ſpirits,2. Pet. 1 conquerors of deuils, phiſitions for infirmities, fathers of many ſpiritual children, teachers of manye Relygious familyes, and Lordes ouer all Gods creatures. Who could liue more poorelye then S. Francis or S. Dominike choſe to lyue for Chriſtes ſake and yet theyr lyues were miraculous their memory at this daye continueth honourable and the fruites of their doctrine and examples haue bene found thorough out al chriſtendome almoſte innumerable. And though ſuch excellent prerogatiues ar not beſtowed vpon euery one yet there be certain giftes which God beſtoweth vpon al that truly ſerue him and much more vpon thoſe that ſuffer anye thing for the profeſsion of his true catholike fayth. I meane his grace wherby they are made in a ſorte pertakers of the deuine nature, wherby their ſoules are bewtified and made amyable in Gods

ſight, wherby they are inabled to performe the offices of all vertues, and wher-with they are armed againſt al aſſaultes and temptations. The lighte of vnderſtanding wherby they perceyue Gods goodnes and withal they knowe the vanitye and vncertainty of al thinges that be in this worlde. The comfortes of the holye Ghoſt which neuer fayle to them that willingly weane thē ſelues from worldly ſolaces. The quietnes of a pure conſcience, which as the wiſe-man ſayth Is lyke a continuall feaſte.
                  Pro. 15. The increaſe of Gods loue which maketh al afflictions light and eaſye. The hope and confidence of Gods merciful fauour and protection whiche cauſeth them euen to reioyce in their greateſt tribulations. The libertye of ſpyrite wherby they finde them ſelues free frō the baſe ſeruitude of earthlye deſires. The gift of patience, wherby they endure quietly and gladly whatſoeuer affliction is layde vpon them for Chriſte his name. The marueylous comforte, which all good folke receyue at theyr departing out of this vale of miſerye.

Theſe and many other be the rewards wher-with al temporal domage is recompenſed not only a hundreth, but euen an hundreth thouſande folde yf one might vſe any compariſon as ſuerlye there is non to be made in this caſe.
               
                  Life euerlaſting.NOW If Gods payments be ſo plentiful in this lyfe what thinke you is contained in thes words Vita aeterna, life euerlaſting. Among al the tēporal bene fits that god hath beſtowed vpō vs, ther is none more dearly eſtemed, non more carefully defended then is our lyfe: although it be ſhort &amp; vnſure to continue ſubiect to many chaūges annoyed with ſundry wantes &amp; diſtreſſes, in wrapped on euerye ſide with infinite miſeryes, and rather to be called a death then a lyfe. If then we make ſuch accompt of this lyfe wherin we are daylye dying, the ſtate wherof, is ſo vncertayne, ſo mutable, ſo ful of neceſsities, labours, paynes, woes, and al kinde of wretchednes: How greatly ſhould we deſyre to enioye a perpetual lyfe, a lyfe voyd of al peril, free from al mutation, wherin is no defecte, no trauayle, no

ſorow: A quiet lyfe, a lyfe abounding with all kinde of good, and in euerye reſpect a moſt happye and bleſſed lyfe. There is ſcarſlye any man that deſireth not to lyue although he be ſure by lyuing longer to ſuffer manye afflictions both of minde and bodye: and for the purchaſing of a litle falſe felicitye, conſiſting in tranſitorye goods, honours, and ſoueraygntye, although it ſhal indure but a verye ſmale while, we ſee that men ſpare for no expence, they ſhunn no trauayle, and finallye they refuſe not to doe or ſuffer anye thing, wherby they maye attayne vnto theyr deſired ende. Now when true felicitye and ſecure eternitye ſhal be ſo happily ioyned together, that neyther there ſhal be anye feeling of preſent wante nor anye doubt of defect to fall herafter, is not this a lyfe to be procured and to be purchaſed with any bodylye payne, or temporal loſſe whatſoeuer maye be imagined greateſt. Dearly beloued Catholikes it is not poſsible to conceyue with thought, muche leſſe to expreſſe with wordes the dignytye

of thys rewarde which is reſerued for you, yf you perſeuer faythfull to the ende.Mat. 24. 
                  Eye hath not ſeene, nor eare hath not hearde, neyther hathe it aſcended into the harte of man,
                  1. Cor. 2. 
                  what thinges god hath prepared for them that loue hym. Therfore it maye rather be cōmended with ſilence then ſufficientlye ſett forthe by anye ſpeach. Yet neuertheleſſe ſomewhat I meane to ſaye touching this moſt happye inheritance when I ſhal haue paſſed ouer the vttermoſt poynte of perſecution which is the ſheading of blood. In the meane time to comforte you againſt the loſſe of your worldly goods, I maye be bolde to ſaye hauing almightye God for my warrant that for the loſſe of worldlye offices which you might beare in the common wealth, and nowe doe forbeare them for conſcience ſake, you ſhal be all crowned Kinges in that heauenlye,Mat. 5. bleſſed, and euerlaſting kingdome. For your lands whiche maye be taken from you, you ſhal enioye euery one of you the lande of the liuing without diſturbance,Pſal. 141 enuye, or contradiction. For ſupplye of

the wants which yon maye fall into by the ſpoile of your moueable goods youIſaie. 49. ſhal be ſure neyther to ſuffer hunger nor thirſt nor other neceſsitye.Apo. 7. In lieu of your howſes of timber and ſtone, which happylye you ſhal forgoe, and moſt ſure you are not long to continue in them, beſides that they may alſo fall to ruine by ſome miſchance:2 Cor. 5. you ſhal haue manſyon places in heauen not built with hand which cannot decaye, and you ſhal dwel in them for euer. For the diſgrace wherin you lyue being in a manner debarred from the court &amp; from the ſight of your PrinceIſa. 33. you ſhal ſee the King of Kinges in his maieſty being preſēt before his throne and ſeruing him daye and night in his Temple. You ſhal ſee God,Apo. 7. you ſhal loue God, you ſhal prayſe God foreuer. You ſhal haue Pallaces for priſons, you ſhal haue gratulations of Angels,Ioan. 12. for the reproche which you ſuffer among men. In ſtead of earthly honour &amp; ſeruice,Luc. 12. you ſhal haue honour from God the father, yea you ſhal haue chriſt him-ſelfe to ſerue and minyſter vnto

you the greateſt prefermente that by anye harte could be deſired.
               
                  Concluſiō of this firſt parte.AND Thus ſeeing your refuſal and abſtayning from the proteſtantes churches to be moſt iuſt &amp;: reaſonable: The loſſe which you ſhal ſuſtayne for ſo good a cauſe to indifferent mindes tollerable: The recompence whiche you ſhal receaue with-out all proportion [both here and in the lyfe to come] incomparable:Iac. 5. I exhorte you all (deare country-men and beloued brethren in Chriſte) to follow the example of huſband men who committ their ſeede to the ground nothing miſtruſting to receyue in time the precious fruite of the earth albeit their ſeede be for a tyme buried and trodden vnder foote, and ſowſed with ſhowers and bittten with many a cruel winter ſtorme: It is now winter with you, the ſeede which you muſt caſte into the ground are theſe worldlye goodes which you ſhal either leeſe or geue for Gods-ſake. Feare not the pinching colde of this hard ſeaſon nor the ſharpe ſtormes of perſecution. For ſhortlye the ſpring tyme of the reſurrection

ſhal come, and then your plentiful fruites ſhal appeare, and you ſhal haue a glad ſommer of heauenlye ioye, and a perpetual harueſt of perfect bleſſednes. Immytate here-in thoſe merchaūtes who are contente to haue their money tranſported by waye of exchange into ſuche places where they maye receyue it more commodiouſly. Your countrye is heauen, be contented that your goodes be tranſported thether, although by the handes of ſuche as thinke to ſpoyle you. God him-ſelfe wil be your aſſurance for receipt of the whole. And wher-as men are glad to geue ſome-what for the exchaūge, you ſhal haue manyfolde gayne both in reſpecte of quantitye and quallitye. You ſhal haue muche for a little, golde for ſiluer, thinges ſpiritual and euerlaſting for bodylye and corruptible thinges. At the leaſt-wiſe prouide for your ſafetye as paſſengers doe on the ſea in outragious tempeſt, they caſt awaye theyr goods and ar contented ſo that themſelues maye come ſafe to lande. The violence of this preſent ſtorme may perhaps

be ſuche by Gods ſufferance as that you ſhal hardly keepe your wealth and ſaue your ſoules withal, be content to be depriued of the one, wherby you maye preſerue the other, arriuing ſafe at the heauenlye porte, where al your friendes and kinſe-folke expecte you: I mean the nine orders of Angels with al, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Virgins, Confeſſors,Pſal. 141 &amp; other glorious Sayntes, among whom you ſhal haue no lack, and with whom you ſhal liue and reioyce euerlaſtinglye. Set before your eyes the notable conſtancie and firme reſolution of thoſe three worthy yong Hebrues, who being captiues in a ſtrange lande,Dan. 3. deſtitute of frindes, and depriued of al humane ayde and comforte, would chooſe rather to be caſte a lyue into a burning fornace, then to worſhipp the ſtatue of Nabuchodonoſor, or to doe anye honour to his Gods. Deare Catholikes your caſe is ſome-what like, albeit the extremitye be not euery way ſo great, they being in peril of death, and you onlye at this preſent in danger to leeſe your goods &amp; liuelyhoods.

The fornace of pouertye is threatned to al thoſe that ſhal refute to honour Caluins bread, and Cranmers communion booke by the aſsiſtance of their bodylye preſence. But feare not the terryble flames of extreeme neceſsitye. Geue no eare to the vayne ſounde and pernicious Muſike of worldly &amp; carnal mens perſwaſions who geue you counſel to reſerue your ſelues for a better daye and in the meane tyme to dallye and diſſemble with the world and not to lett your enemies take the ſpoyle of your goodes where-by they maye tryumphe ouer you. But aſſure your ſelues, howſoeuer the conditions of times ſhal change this is your tyme of tryal wherin you muſt eyther ſaue your ſoules and wynn gloryous crownes for your faythful confeſsyon or elſe you ſhal damne your ſelues by cowardlye yealding to doe aginſt your cōſcience. And to ſaye the verye trueth, the deuil is your onlye enemye: theſe men that afflicte you temporallye are more your friends, then they are aware of: They are but fyles to polyſhe and make you

bright, they are but hammers to bring you to good faſhion, they are but roddes of correction to keepe you in due awe and obedience to your heauenlye Father. The only triumphe and victory whiche the fiende your mortal aduerſarye ſeeketh is, to make you caſte awaye your ſoules by greuous ſinne and damnable deuiſyon from God hys Churche: and contrary-wiſe, your conſtant perſeuerance ſhalbe to his confuſion and to your great honour and renowme. Be not moued with the multitude of thoſe whiche fale thorough faynte harte and lacke of patience, but looke to the cōmendable example of theiſe three young men whom I nowe ſpeake of, and make aunſwere as they did that your God whom you worſhip can deliuer you from this burning furnace, and from the handes of al thoſe that perſecute and oppreſſe you. And if he wil not, yet make it knowen vnto al men that you wil neyther by worde deede nor anye kinde of outwarde ſemblance, alowe or acknowledge anye other religion then that which, by the

conſent of al Chriſtendome hath bene and is accounted Catholike. Dreade not the flames of penurye in this lyfe, knowing that if you be caſte into thys furnace, Chriſt him-ſelfe wil come and ioyne in companye with you, cauſing this feruent flame of worldlye wante, to become lyke a freſhe ayre or comfortable dew, by ſpiritual comfort thorough his grace. The fire ſhal not hurte or greeue you, it ſhal only burne your bondes and ſett you at lybertye from ſundrye noyſome cares of this worlde. Your perſecutors are thoſe who euen now are ſcorched with this flame being al-wayes needye, and deſirous to haue more, poſſeſſe they neuer ſo much. And the daye wil once come (I would for their partes it might be otherwiſe) whē you ſhal eate, &amp; they ſhal be hungerye: you ſhall drincke and they ſhal-be thirſtye, you ſhal-be glad, and they ſhal be confounded: you ſhal prayſe God thorough exultation of hart: and they ſhal crye for inwarde ſorowe,Eſaie. 65 and ſhal howle thorough contrition of ſpirite, I meane al this in the next life: in hope

wherof I deſire you to continew ſteadfaſte and firme in the way of our Lord, and that you may the better perſeuer, I exhorte you to cōmend your ſelues to God by your owne prayers and by the deuotion of others which you may purchaſe by your almes, now whiles you are able, releeuing thoſe that be al-readye in neceſsitye. And eſpecially you maye appeaſe God his wrathe by hauing the bleſſed Sacryfice daylye offered in your houſes, for your owne ſtates and for our whole countrye, alſo your chiefeſt armour againſt all aſſaultes ſhal-be the holye Sacramentes for the admyniſtring where-of, and for your ſpiritual comforte otherwiſe, yt ſhal-be neceſſary for you to retaine and to make muche of thoſe godlye Prieſtes with you, who be emongeſt you in daylye perril of theyr lyues for your ſoules health. Whiche is the ſecond thing where-vnto I meane to exhorte you: In the meane tyme I deſire you to take this in good worthe vntil God ſhal make me able to performe the reſte.
               
                  And with-all I humblye and earneſtly beſeeche the God of all grace, who hathe called vs vnto his eternal glorye in Chriſte Ieſus, to perfyt you, hauing ſuffered a lyttle, to confyrme, and ſtabliſhe you. To him be all honour and glorye for euer and euer. Amen.
               
                  Your Honours and Worſhipps humble ſeruant in Chryste. H. B.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

