
   
      
         
            Moriemini. A verie profitable sermon preached before her Maiestie at the court, about xiij. yeares since: by H.B.
            H. B., fl. 1593.
         
         
            
               1593
            
         
         Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00259
            STC 1034
            ESTC S118909
            99854116
            99854116
            19523
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00259)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19523)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 450:13)
         
         
            
               
                  Moriemini. A verie profitable sermon preached before her Maiestie at the court, about xiij. yeares since: by H.B.
                  H. B., fl. 1593.
                  Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612, attributed name.
               
               [2], 24 p.   
               
                  Printed [R. Field for] by Iohn VVolfe,
                  London :
                  1593.
               
               
                  The New College (University of Oxford) Library copy is ascribed to Hugh Broughton in an early 17th-century hand--STC.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2005-11
            Apex CoVantageRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            MORIEMINI.
            A VERIE PROFITABLE SERMON PREACHED before her Maieſtie at the Court, about xiij. yeares ſince: By H. B.
            
            
            LONDON, Printed by Iohn VVolfe.
            1593.
         
         
            
            
               
                  〈1 page missing〉
                euen great enuie tovvards ſuch as are godly and vvell affected; he vvill in that reſpect beare the more vvith me, neither take it indignantly at my hands, that his godly labours are rather thus preſerued for the vſe of men, then reſerued (as afore) to be conſumed of mothes. The argument of this ſermon may appeare vnto thee by this one vvord in the forehead of it (Moriemini.) And thus not doubting, but that after thou shalt once aduiſedly haue peruſed it, thou vvilt allovv both of him that firſt did pen it, and of my poore ſelfe alſo, vvho thus did print it for thy behoofe and benefit. I bid thee farevvell.
         
      
      
         
            
            A VERIE PROFITABLE SERMON PREACHED BEFORE her Maieſtie at the Court, about xiij. years ſince, by H. B.
            
               Pſal. 82. 6. 7.
               6 I haue ſayd, ye are Gods, and ye are all the children of the higheſt:
               7 But ye shall die like men, &amp; fall like one of the princes.
            
            
               I haue ſayd, ye are Gods: But ye shall die like men.
               
                  THe princely Prophet Dauid, being himſelf aduaunced by the goodneſſe of God, to be king ouer Iſraell, by dayly experience plainly ſaw, how common a thing it is, that the great and mightie, the rich and wealthie men of this world, doe many times forget both them ſelues, what they be, and their God, from whom they be. And glorying in nobilitie, and ſwelling in authoritie, and ſwimming in worldly wealth, do truſt in their treaſures, and ſeeke their owne pleaſures, &amp; thinke them ſelues Gods.
               Therefore, that the great perſonages of this world ſhould not be deceiued with their great eſtates in this

world, and thinke them ſelues Gods to worke their own willes, and neglect the will and wayes of the euerliuing God. The Prophet here doth plainely tell them, that though they be Gods, that is, Gods in maieſtie, Gods in authoritie, Gods in wealth and glorie, &amp; in all the things of this world liue like Gods among men: yet are they but Gods on earth, and Gods of earth, that is, earthy and mortal Gods, and muſt die like other men, and part from all their pompe, &amp; render accompt to the God of heauen for their earthy Godhead. And this (me thinke) is the purpoſe of the Prophet in theſe words, I haue ſaid, ye are Gods: But ye shall die like men.
               
               Wherein the Prophet ſetteth downe two ſpecial pointes of Princes and great perſonages
               
                  1. The Maieſtie and
                  2. The mortality
               
               1. Their Maieſtie, in theſe words, I haue ſaid, ye are Gods, therein giuing to note
               
                  1. The dutie done vnto them. and
                  2. The dutie required of them, for that they be Gods.
               
               2. Their mortality, in theſe wordes, But ye shall die like men: therein alſo noting death. For that they ſhall die, like men.
               
                  1. The certainty of their death and
                  2. Their riſing againe from
               
            
            
               I haue ſayd, yee are Gods.
               As the Prophet Dauid by the ſpirit of God in this place, euen ſo the ſame ſpirit in ſundry places of the holy Scriptures doth call the Princes and great perſonages of this world, Gods.
               
                  1 So the Lord God himſelfe ſaid vnto Moſes, I willExod. 12. 12. be auenged of all the Gods in Egypt: meaning Pharao, &amp; all the men of might in Egypt.
               2 And Moſes the man of God amongſt other, gaue this law to the people of God; Thou ſhalt not ſpeakeExod. 22. 28. euill of the Gods: meaning the heads and rulers of the people.
               3 And our ſauiour Chriſt in the goſpell ſaith; Is itIoh. 10. 34. not written in the law, I haue ſaid, ye are gods? Ratifying and confirming, that the men of this world are well called Gods in the word of God.
               And the reaſon why they be called Gods, the queene of Saba rendreth, when ſhe ſaith to king Salomon; Bleſſed2. Para. 9. 8. be the Lord thy God, which had a loue to thee, to ſet thee king on his ſeat, that thou maiſt be king, for the Lord thy God. Plainly teſtifying that the Princes and great perſonages in this world, do ſit on Gods ſeat, by Gods appointment, in ſtead of God, therefore called gods.
               
                  I haue ſaid, ye are Gods, that is, Ye ſit on Gods ſeat by Gods appointmēt, in ſtead of God, ye repreſent Gods maieſtie, and beare Gods authoritie, therefore ye are Gods.
               And for that ye are gods, that is, ſet on Gods ſeate, by Gods appointment, in ſtead of God, therefore this dutie is due vnto you by all, that are vnder you, to honour and obey you euen for the Lord.
               1 For ſo the Lord God himſelfe in the firſt commandement of the ſecond table commandeth, To honour FatherExod. 20. 12. and mother, that is, to honor and obey all ſuperiors, rulers, and gouernors, and promiſeth long life for fulfilling the ſame.
               2 And our ſauiour Chriſt comming not to breake the law, but to fulfill the law, in token of his obedience,

according to the law paid tribute to Caeſar, commanding Peter to take a hooke, and caſt into the ſea, and in theMat. 17. 27. mouth of the firſt fiſh he gat, he ſhould find a peece of twentie pence, that take (ſaith he) and giue them for tribute for thee and me.
               3 And when the Iewes came vnto him, and asked him, whether they ſhould pay tribute to Caeſar, or not, heMat. 22. 21. ſayd vnto them, Giue vnto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars: teaching all ſubiects obedience to their Caeſars, that is, their Princes, heads, and gouernours.
               4 S. Paul in the 13. to the Romanes, ſetteth downeRom. 13. 1. ſundrie reaſons to proue, that euery ſoule ought to be ſubiect to the higher powers, as to the ordinance of God.
               5 And S. Peter is plaine: Submit your ſelues to euery1. Pet. 2. 13. ordinance of man, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   that is, euen for the Lord: whether it be to the king, as hauing the preheminence: or to the rulers appointed by him, for the puniſhment of euill doers, but for the praiſe of them, that do wel.
               Thus the Spirit of God doth teach the people of God in the word of God, that the Princes and great perſonages of this world are gods, that is, ſet on Gods ſeate, by Gods appointment, in ſtead of God: they repreſent Gods maieſtie, and beare Gods authoritie: and therefore this dutie is due vnto them by all, that are ſubiect to them, to honor and obey them euen for the Lord.
               Whence then is that ſpirite, and whence is that doctrine, that ſetteth on ſubiects to conſpiracies, rebellions, and treaſons? and teacheth them by gunſhot, by witchcraft, by coniuring, by ſorcerie, by dealings with the deuill him ſelfe, to worke miſchiefe againſt their naturall Prince, and their natiue countrey? and yet telleth them, that therein they do God ſeruice, and promiſe them pardons,

and hight them heauen for their diſobedience?
               Surely, ſurely, ſpiritus mendax in ore Prophetarum, that3. Reg. 22. 2
                        •
                     
                   is, a lying ſpirit, the ſpirit of the deuill and Antichriſt is in the mouths of ſuch teachers, and the harts of ſuch dealers.
               For the Spirit of God by the wiſeman ſaith: Wiſh noEccleſ. 10. 20 euill to the king in thy thought, &amp; ſpeake no euill againſt great men in thy ſecret chamber: for the foules of the aire will bewray thee. The foules of the aire, that is, the deuill (for ſo our Sauiour Chriſt in the parable of the ſowerMatt. 13. 15. expoundeth the foules of the aire to ſignifie the deuill.) The deuill, that ſetteth traitours on worke, he will paye them their hire, that is, he wil bewray their wicked practiſes againſt their Princes, to their ſhame and confuſion.
               
                  For ye are Gods, that is, ſet on Gods ſeate, by Gods appointment, in ſtead of God, ye repreſent Gods maieſtie, and beare Gods authoritie: therefore this dutie is due vnto you by all that are vnder you, to honor and obey you, euen for the Lord.
               Yet ſome thinke them ſelues ſet free from this dutie of obedience to their naturall Prince, by betaking thē ſelues to the protection of the holy father, and by reconciling them ſelues to his ſubiection. As for their natural Prince, the preſent ſtate, and Religion, they are in doubt of the goodneſſe of them, that they be not of God, nor agreeable to the word and will of God.
               Yet haue they ſeene, and full wel do know, how wonderfully God hath bleſſed, proſpered, and preſerued vs by this Prince, in this ſtate, and for this Religion by the ſpace of theſe two and twentie yeares and vpwardes. And in all this time, neither Balac his treacherie, nor Balam
                  Num. 23. his curſe for money hath preuayled againſt vs. For howe could they curſe whom God doth bleſſe? how

could they hurt whom God doth defend? And yet too well they know, that Balac hath bragged, and Balam hath banned, that is, the Pope hath curſed, and the popiſh haue cōſpired: Papiſts haue deuiſed, &amp; Atheiſts haue practiſed cunning conſpiracies, trecherous treaſons, peſtilent practiſes, and diueliſh deuiſes againſt the Prince, againſt the ſtate, and againſt the religion; onely God his holy hand hath ſtill from time to time preſerued and maintained the Prince, the ſtate, and the Religion: whereby they might ſee (were they not too too blind, &amp; will not ſee) that God doth loue and like, proſper &amp; bleſſe, the Prince, the ſtate, and the Religion.
               But theſe buſie rebellious Frogs, that cannot yet like the bleſſed blocke of ſo peaceable a prince, muſt needs at length haue a deuouring Storke.
               God for his mercies ſake turn their harts, or ouerturne all that take their parts.
               Amen.
            
            
               I haue ſayd, yee are Gods.
               And for that ye are Gods, ſet on Gods ſeat by Gods appointment, in ſtead of God, therefore this dutie is alſo due vnto you by them that are vnder you, to pray continually to the liuing God for you.
               So S. Paul teacheth ſaying; I exhort you, 1 That1. Tim. 2. 1. praiers, ſupplications, interceſſions, and giuing of thanks, be made for all men, eſpecially for kings, and all that are in authoritie.
               2 And the reaſon why, the wiſe man rendreth, where

he ſaith, The hart of the king is in the hand of the Lord:Pro. 21. 1. Therefore the people are to pray to the Lord to diſpoſe the hart of the king and all that are in authoritie, to his good will and pleaſure.
               3 So Dauid praied for the king &amp; ſaid; Giue the kingPſal. 72. 1. thy iudgements, O Lord, and thy righteouſneſſe to the kings ſonne: then ſhall hee iudge the people according vnto right, and defend the poore.
               4 And when our ſauiour Chriſt came to Hieruſalem riding like a king, the people that went before him,Matt. 21. 9. and they that came after him, cried vnto him Hoſanna, i. Hoſchianna, i. Lord ſaue the king, Lord ſaue the king. Which action allowed by our ſauiour Chriſt, teacheth the Chriſtians to cry Hoſanna, that is, to pray continually for the peace, wealth and ſafetie of the Prince, and all that are in authoritie.
               Ye are Gods to be praid for to the ſuperior God, yet not to be prated of by inferior men: by the wiſe to be aduiſed, yet not to be chatted of by euery vnaduiſed.
               The law of God by Moſes, Thou ſhalt not ſpeake euillExod. 22. 28. of the Gods, was giuen to bridle the licentious libertie of mens tongues, in pratling of Princes and other great perſonages.
               For, that euerie prentiſe ſhould prate of Princes, and euerie Cobler ſeeme a Counſellor, and euerie Iack Straw deuiſe a new law, and euerie medling mate miſlike the whole ſtate, is neither commendable by the word of God, not tollerable in a Chriſtian common-wealth: yee are Gods to be praied for, not to be prated of.
               And thus much breefly of the dutie due vnto you, for that ye are Gods.
               The God of heauen grant, that all dutie due vnto you,

may of all parts be faithfully performed vnto you, to honor and obey you, and pray to God for you.
               Amen.
            
            
               I haue ſayd, yee are Gods.
               And for that ye are Gods, that is, ſet on Gods ſeate, by Gods appointment, in ſtead of God: therefore there is a dutie alſo required of you towards that God, that hath made you gods.
               For you are gods, not the gods of the heathen, ſiluer &amp; gold, the workes of mens handes, which haue eyes andPſal. 115. 3. ſee not, eares and heare not, mouthes and ſpeake not, hands and handle not, feet and walke not, neither is there any breath in their noſthrils: but ye are gods, liuely gods, and haue eyes to ſee, and eares to heare, mouths to ſpeake, and hands to worke the things, that are good and pleaſing to the euerliuing God.
               Therefore the Prophet Dauid ſaith vnto you: BringPſal. 29. 1. vnto the Lord, ô ye mightie, bring yong rammes vnto the Lord, aſcribe vnto the Lord your worſhip, and your ſtrength: giue the Lord the honor due vnto his name, &amp; worſhippe the Lord with an holy worſhippe. By which words the prophet teacheth plainly, that there is a dutie required of you that are mightie, towards that God, that hath made you gods.
               But it becomes not me, perhaps, to tell you gods your dutie, yet thus much without offence, I hope, I may ſay, ſaying it truly: that the God of heauen is angrie with the gods on earth for want of dutie.
               
               Reuelatur enim ira Dei, &amp;c.
               
                  Rom. 1. 28.
For the wrath of God in heauen is reuealed, &amp; made manifeſt againſt the gods on earth by ſundrie ſignes and tokens of Gods wrath, both in the heauens aboue, and in the earth beneath. For euen of late dayes amongſt vs the often eclypſes of the Sunne and the Moone, the diuerſe Cometes and blazing ſtarres, the ſundrie ſights and lights in the aire, the riſe reſemblances of fire and bloud in the clouds, the maine monſtruous &amp; ſtrange birthes (though ſome ſeeme to render ſome naturall reaſons for them) yet are they vnnaturall, and the wrath of God is reuealed by them. As for the late earthquake amongſt vs, that was ſoone forgotten of vs, becauſe it paſſed away ſo ſoone, and did ſo litle hurt amongſt vs. Yet the prophet Dauid ſaith,Pſal. 18. 7. The earth trembled and quaked, the verie foundations of the hilles ſhooke, and were moued, becauſe God is wroth. The prophet telleth plainly, that the trembling and quaking of the earth, is a ſure ſigne and token of the wrath of God in heauen. And that the late earthquake amongſt vs, did paſſe ſo ſoone away from vs, and with ſo litle hurt among vs, is an argument, that the wrath of God againſt vs, is yet mixed with much mercie towards vs, threatning vs ſo terribly, and yet ſparing vs ſo mercifully.
               Thus then by ſundrie ſignes &amp; tokens it is euident and plaine, that the God of heauen is angry with the gods on earth for want of dutie.
               For ſome being aduanced by God to be gods, do liue without God, that is, without the knowledge and feare of God, and become Dauids fooles, and ſaye in theirPſal. 14. 1. hearts, There is no God. But ſet vp their hornes on high,Pſalm. 75. 6. and ſay with a ſtiffe necke, That promotion commeth

from the Eaſt and from the Weſt, that is, They ſay, their honour and authoritie, their lands and great liuings, their credit and their countenaunce comes to them by heritage, by birth and parentage, or by the worthineſſe of their wit and policie, or by the deſerts of their labours and induſtrie.
               Therefore they offer ſacrifice to their nets (ſayth theHabac. 1. 16. Lord by the Prophet) and burne incenſe to their yarne, becauſe by thē their portion is made fat, that is, they boaſt of their birth, they vaunt of their value, their wiſedome, and their worth, becauſe by them they thinke they haue whatſoeuer they haue. And ſo ſet their whole delightLuc. 16. 19. with the rich glutton to be finely fed and trimly clad, and hauing wealth inough in ſtore for many yeares, they ſayLuc. 12. 19. to their ſoules, Soule take thine eaſe, eat, drinke and bee merrie; and grow to be like to that wicked iudge, Nec
                  Luc. 18. 4. 
                  Deum timere, nec hominem reuereri, that is, neither to feare God nor care for man.
               For theſe godleſſe Gods haue commonly, if not continually about them, bewitching Elimaſſes, that is, beſottingAct. 13. 8. epicures, Machiuiliſts, and Atheiſts, which feed thē with the follies of their owne fanſies, and peruert them from all care and feare of God, from reading, hearing, or beleeuing the word of God.
               But when God had giuen his people reſt in the daies of Aſa king of Iuda, the king and all the people made a2. Pat. 15. 12. couenaunt with the Lord to ſeeke and ſerue the Lord their God with all their harts, and with all their ſoules: And they made a law, that whoſoeuer would not ſerue the Lord God, ſhould die for it, were he ſmall or great.
               Oh if we would well conſider the peace and reſt, the proſperitie and plentie, where with the Lord hath bleſſed

vs in the daies of our Aſa, that is, our gratious queene Elizabeth, we haue great cauſe to make a couenant with the Lord, to ſeeke and ſerue the Lord our God with all our hearts, and with all our ſoules. But if Aſa his law were in England, That whoſoeuer would not ſerue the Lord God ſhould die for it, were he ſmall or great, then ſurely God ſhould be a great deale better ſerued both of ſmall and great. For our peace and reſt, our proſperitie and plentie, hath bred a godleſſe ſecuritie both in ſmall and great: and the God of heauen is angrie with the gods on earth for want of dutie.
               For ſome being aduanced by God to be gods, do yet with Achab miſlike good Elias, and maintaine Baals
                  3. Reg. 16. 32. prieſts, that is, they cannot like of the preaching &amp; preachers of the word of God, but maintaine bald prieſts to nuſle them in Idolatrie and ſuperſtition ſtill: ſuch muſt be their chaplens, their ſchoolemaiſters, ſtewards of their houſes, clearks of their kitchins, and beare all the ſway. By ſufferance whereof it is come to paſſe, that not onely themſelues are hardned in their ſuperſtition, paſt hope to be wonne, but alſo their children, a great number that haue bene borne ſince your Maieſties raigne, are ſo taught in their trade, that they are become more obſtinate enemies to the ſtate and religion, then their fathers are. And this is one great cauſe, why after ſo long preaching of Gods truth, the enemies of truth are ſo ſmallie decreaſed, nay ſo mightily increaſed amongſt vs.
               O what a happie thing had it bene for this land, if the children of ſuch as are knowne to be ſuperſtitious, had bene taken from their parents at the yeares of diſcretion, and committed to the education of ſuch, as are knowne to loue the ſtate and religion. But better late then neuer,

they ſay, Nunquam ſera eſt ad bonos mores via.
               
               Chriſt and his Goſpell hath a long time, two &amp; twentie yeares bene on foot in England, and faine would ride, as he did ſomtime in Hieruſalem, with ſome glorie. And
                     
                        •
                     . 1. 2. for this purpoſe he hath ſent foorth his two Diſciples to bring both the old Aſſe and the yoong Colt vnto him. The two diſciples are Doctrine and Diſcipline, the word and the ſword, miniſters and magiſtrats: both which are ſent out, that is, appointed and commaunded by Chriſt, to bring both the old ſtubborne aſſes, and the yoong wild colts to Chriſt, that is, to the preaching &amp; teaching of the goſpell of Chriſt. Theſe two diſciples haue a long time bene in bringing, and haue not yet brought neither the old aſles nor the yoong colts to Chriſt, becauſe they do not go togither to bring them; diſciple Doctrine faine would bring them, but diſciple Diſcipline is verie ſlacke to go with him: the one ſeekes means by counſell to bring them to Chriſt, the other makes means manie times by countenaunce to ſtaie them from Chriſt. And the one without the other cannot bring them to Chriſt.
               Surely, Dominus his opus habet, that is, The Lord hathMatt. 21. 3. need of them.
               Now therfore I moſt humblie beſeech your Maieſtie euen for Chriſt his ſake, and on Chriſts behalfe, to giue a new and a ſtraight charge to theſe two diſciples, to go togither ſpeedilie, and to ioine togither effectuallie, to bring both the old ſtubborne aſſes, and the yoong wild colts to Chriſt, that is, to the preaching and teaching of the goſpell of Chriſt, to the ſaluation of their ſoules through faith in Chriſt. Let Chriſt now no longer ſtaie on foot amongſt vs, leaſt at laſt he be troden vnder foot of vs: for whileſt we be ſtill careleſſe of their conuerſion,

they ſeeke and worke our vtter ſubuerſion. And the God of heauen is alreadie angrie with the gods on earth, for want of this dutie.
               For ſome being aduaunced of God to be gods, do countenaunce ſuch as ſeeke to diſcountenaunce the preaching and preachers of the word of God: both the carpers at their liues, and the catchers at their liuings. Euerie accuſer hath too too manie hearers, and too many bearers againſt Gods miniſters, to abate their credit &amp; their countenaunce: and euerie ſhifter now becomes a ſuter, to pill and pull away their liuings and their maintainance. But when theſe dallying Dalilaes, haue curtold Sampſons
                  Iudic. 16. 21. locks, and robbed him of his ſtrength, that is, when they haue curtold the clergies countenance, and robbed them of their maintenance, Sampſon ſhall become a blind Sampſon, that is, the Clergie ſhall become a blind Clergie, and pull downe the houſe of Gods wrath and vengeance both vpon themſelues, and vpon thoſe pilling Philiſtines that ſought their decay.
               To be ſhort and plaine, Gods word and religion is contemned by Atheiſts, condemned by Papiſts, ſlaundered by ſchiſmatikes, hindered by too many, not faithfully furthered by anie. And becauſe the loue of Gods word and religion thus in England is decreaſed, therefore the wrath of God againſt England is increaſed.
               For as the Oracle told the men of Athens, that the ſtrongeſt ſtate and beſt defenſe of their citie, was 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  i. Their rotten wood; meaning their good laws that were graued in wood, and by antiquitie were waxen rotten. Euen ſo the heauenly oracles of the liuing God tel vs, that the ſtrongeſt ſtaie, and beſt defenſe of a chriſtian common wealth, is the preaching and teaching of the

word of God, the true religion and ſeruice of God.
               So ſayth the Prophet Dauid; There is no king thatPſal. 33. 16. can be ſaued by the multitude of an hoaſt, neither is anie mightie man deliuered by his much ſtrength: a horſe isPſal. 118. 16. accounted but a vaine thing to ſaue a man, but the hand of the Lord hath the preheminence: the hand of the Lord is mightie in operation, the hand of the Lord bringeth mightie things to paſſe.
               1 Nymrod and his confederates thought themſeluesGen. 11. 1. ſafe, when they builded their Babell vp to the heauens: but all their high Babell was but a bable, that is, a verie vaine deuiſe, and came ſoone to confuſion.
               2 Arphaxad truſted in his ſtrong and well fenced citieIudith 1. 1. Ecbatanis, but Ecbatanis could not hold him when the hand of the Lord was againſt him.
               
                  Pharao truſted in the multitude of his chariots andExod. 14. 28. horſemen, and how ſoone were they all ouerwhelmed in the red ſea.
               So, not Nymrods high Babels, that is, not high caſtels and towers: not Arphaxads Ecbatanis, that is, not ſtrong townes and well fenced cities: not Pharaos chariots and horſemen, that is, not the multitude of men and munition, but the holie hand of the Lord, for his word, and by his word is the ſtrength and ſtay of the people of God.
               Not the wals of Bethulia, but the hand of the LordIudith 13. 4. held out Holophernes, and ſtrengthened weake Iudith to hacke off his head.
               Therefore that we in England haue bene ſo long, ſo mightily, and ſo miraculouſly ſaued and deliuered from the hands of them that hate vs, (which are ſo many, ſo mightie, and ſo maliciouſly bent againſt vs) that their trecheries and conſpiracies, their counſels &amp; confederacies,

haue bene ſo many times reuealed, and ſo many waies preuented, that they haue not taken from vs our moſt gratious Queene Elizabeth by their gunſhot, their witchcraft, their coniuring, their ſorcerie, and their dealings with the Diuell himſelfe, to the vtter ouerthrowe of the preſent ſtate and Religion. All this, and all elſe hath not bene ſo much by the wiſedome of man, by the counſell or carefull circumſpection of man, but by the mercifull goodneſſe of the Lord our God towardes vs, and by the holie hand of the Lord our God ouer vs, onely for his word and religion amongſt vs.
               For ſo the prophet Elyzeus, when he ſaw Elias taken4. Reg. 2. 12. vp from him, he cried after him: O my father, ô my father, the chariots and the horſemen, the chariots and the horſemen of Iſraell. Plainely teſtifying, that Elias the Prophet of the Lord, who had plentifully preached the word of the Lord in Iſraell, he was the chariots and the horſemen, that is, the ſtrength and ſtaie of Iſraell. And euen ſo doubtleſſe Elias, that is, the preaching and teaching of the word of God, the true religion and ſeruice of God in England, is the chariots and horſemen, that is, the ſtrength and the ſtay of England.
               Make much then of Elias, O make much of Elias.
                  3. Reg. 17. 3. Let not Achab his accuſations make you beleeue, that Elias troubleth all England: not Elias, but Achab, that is, not the religion, but the enemies of the religion, their trecheries and conſpiracies, their counſels and confederacies, their crackings, and their priuie packings, trouble all England.
               Make much of Elias, O make much of Elias. Let not3. Reg. 18. 10 the godleſſe Iezabels driue Elias out of houſe and home,

and make him to liue in the wilderneſſe and be fed of the rauens, or elſe to liue vpon the poore pittance of the widdow at Sareptha, that is, Let not the godleſſe greedie ſort take away the preachers lands and liuings, and put them to liue vpon ſmall penſions, or little deuotions.
               Make much of Elias, O make much of Elias, yet make not a cloake of Elias to caſt about you in foule weather, and caſt from you in faire weather. Thinke it not inough3. Reg. 18. 10. to ſeeke for Elias in the time of drought and dearth, and care not for him in the time of plentie and reſt, that is, Thinke it not enough when any trouble or aduerſitie comes, then to crie Religion, Religion, the Goſpell, the Goſpell, and when all is quiet and well, then to haue no care of Religion and the Goſpell. O make much of religion both in weale and woe, Religion is your ſtrength and ſtay both in weale and woe. And the more the loue of Gods word and religion in you decreaſeth, the more the wrath of God againſt you increaſeth. For the Lord is2. Par. 15. 2. with you whileſt you are with the Lord, and when you ſeeke him, he will be found of you, and when you forſake him, he will alſo forſake you.
               The God of all mercies graunt, that you gods on earth may carefully performe your dutie to the God of heauen, that al want of dutie being ſpeedily amēded, Gods wrath for the ſame may in time be preuēted, that God may continue a good God towards England ſtill,
               Amen.
            
            
               But yee shall dye.
               1 When God made man firſt, he made him after theGen. 1. 27.
                  
image and likeneſſe of God, but his bodily ſubſtance heGen. 2. 7. made of the duſt and ſlime of the earth, that man ſhould not boaſt himſelfe of the image of God, whereunto he was made, conſidering the earthly ſubſtaunce wherof he was made.
               2 And when God had giuen him the Lordſhip ouerGen. 3. 19. all the things of the earth, that man ſhould not ſwell with his great authoritie, God put man in mind of his mortalitie, ſaying; Thou ſhalt turne againe to the earth, from whence thou cameſt.
               3 And when good father Abraham found fauor withGen. 18. 27. God to talke with God, leaſt in talking with God he ſhould forget himſelfe towards his God, he ſtill abated himſelfe with the conſideration of his mortalitie, ſaying; Puluis &amp; cinis, quid loquar ad Dominum? that is, O duſt and aſhes that I am, why ſhould I preſume to ſpeake vnto the Lord?
               Euen ſo the ſpirit of God in this place to abate the glorie, to bridle the vanitie, and daunt the delights of men that are mightie, doth put them in mind of their mortalitie: telling princes and all great perſonages, that though they be gods, that is, gods in maieſtie, gods in authoritie, gods in wealth and glorie, and in all things of this world liue like gods among men: yet all your godhead, that is, all your honour and authoritie, all your pleaſures &amp; your treaſures, all your beautie and your brauerie, all is but earthie, fickle, and tranſitorie, and all ſhall leaue you, or you ſhall leaue all, for you ſhall die.
               1 For ſo the voice of the Lord commanded the Prophet to crie, That all fleſh is graſſe, and all the godlineſſeEſa. 40. 6. thereof is but a flower of the field: man is but graſſe, to day freſh and greene, to morrow cut downe and withered

away: man is but a flower of the field, to day ſweet and goodly, to morrow faded and fallen away.
               2 And S. Iames ſayth, What is our life but a vapourIac. 4. 14. or a ſmoake, which for a while appeareth, and ſuddenly vaniſheth away?
               3 And the Poet ſayth; Puluis &amp; vmbra ſumus, i. We be but duſt, we be but a ſhadow. The wind bloweth, the duſt is ſoone puffed away: the ſunne ſhineth, and the ſhadow is ſuddenly carried away: Man is but duſt ſoon puffed away, man is but a ſhadow ſuddenly carried away.
               And it is a common prouerbe: Homo bulla, i. Man is but a bubble of the water, ſoone vp, ſoone downe. Man is but graſſe, ſoone withered away: but a flower ſoone faded away: but a ſmoke ſoone vaniſhing away: but duſt ſoone puffed away: but a ſhadow ſuddenly carried away: but a bubble of the water ſoone ſunk away: And though ye be gods then, yet muſt ye die.
               And as the Prophet ſayth; Your pompe and yourEſa. 14. 11. pride ſhall be layd into the graue: wormes ſhall lie vnder you, and wormes ſhall be your couering.
               For all your goodly eſtate in this world, is but like the great glorious image that Nabuchodonoſor ſaw in aDan. 2. 3
                        •
                     . dreame, whoſe head was of gold, the ſhoulders of ſiluer, the bellie of braſſe, the legges of yron, but the feet of clay: &amp; a little ſtone was caſt againſt the great glorious image, and hit him vpon the earthie feet, and downe it fell, and brake all in peeces.
               Euch ſo all your golden heads, that is, al your honours and great glorie: all your ſiluer ſhoulders, that is, all your beautie and your brauerie: all your braſſie bellies, that is, all your pleaſures and worldly treaſures: all your yron legges, that is, all your ſtrength, youth, and health, all

ſtands vpon earthie, clayie fickle feet, and a little ſtroke of death ſhall hit vpon their earth and clay, and footing fails, and downe fals all.
               For all is but like vnto Ionas his guord, which for a day,Ion. 4. 7. for a time, for a while, makes a goodly ſhadow (and yet but a ſhadow) ouer Ionas his head, and ſuddenly, euen in one night, the worme of Gods wrath pierceth the root, and all your goodly guords wither cleane away. And then your pompe and your pride is laid into the graue: wormes lie vnder you, and wormes be your couering.
               Though Ezechias for a while boaſt of his treaſures,Eſa. 39. 2. his gold, his ſiluer, and all his goodly iewels, yet he heareth this meſſage from the Lord: Man ſet thine houſe inEſa. 38. 1. an order for thou ſhalt die.
               Though Balthaſar for a while ſeemes to bath in bliſſe,Dan. 5. 25. feaſting and banquetting with his nobles and his concubines, yet ſuddenly he ſeeth the fingers write vpō his wal; Mene, mene, Thecell, Vpharſin, that is, Thy daies are numbred and come to an end.
               Though man for a while ſeeme neuer ſo honourable and mightie, neuer ſo rich and welthie, neuer ſo yoong, and luſtie, neuer ſo beautifull and comely, neuer ſo fortunate and happie, yet muſt he in time ſet his things in an order, for he ſhall die, and the finger of God ſhall ſuddenly write vpon his painted wall, Mene, mene, that is, Thy daies are numbred and come to an end: and thy pompe and thy pride ſhall be layd into the graue, wormes ſhal lie vnder thee, and wormes ſhall be thy couering.
               
                  1 Abraham was rich,
                  2 Salomon was wiſe,
                  3 Sampſon was ſtrong:
               
               Yet are they all dead.
               
                  
                  1 Ioſua was fortunate,
                  2 Ionathas was amiable,
                  3 Abſolon was beautifull:
               
               Yet are they all dead.
               
                  1 Moſes Gods ſeruaunt,
                  2 Aaron Gods Prieſt,
                  3 Dauid Gods darling:
               
               Are all dead.
               
                  1 The proud Herode,
                  
                  2 The rich Glutton,
                  3 And the poore Lazar:
               
               Are all dead.
               And you that be gods, muſt alſo die. Veniet enim hora, &amp;c. (ſayth S. Chryſostom) Doubtleſſe the houre will come, when thou muſt needs part from all thy worldly wealth, and ſhalt carrie nought away therof: (for nought thou broughteſt into this world, nought ſhalt thou carrie out.) Then what ſhall become of thy beautifull face, thy gliſtering eyes, thy pampered body, ſo finely fed, ſo trimly clad? Nónne omnia puluis? omnia cinis? omnia putredo &amp; foetor? that is, Shall not then all be duſt? all aſhes? all rottenneſſe and filthineſſe? Haec eſt via vniuerſa carnis, that is, This is the way that all fleſh muſt go.
               
                  I haue ſayd: Ye are gods, But ye shall dye.
               
            
            
               Lyke men.
               And as it is certaine that ye ſhall die, ſo is it, that ye ſhall die like men: and if you ſhall die like men, then ſhall you riſe againe from death.
               So ſayth S. Paul, As by a man death came to men: euen1. Cor. 15. 21.
                  
ſo by a man came the riſing againe from death to men. For as by Adam all men ſhall die, euen ſo by Chriſt, all men ſhall riſe againe from death.
               Chriſt is the reſurrection and the life, whoſoeuer beleeuethIoh. 11. 26. in him ſhall neuer die.
               Therefore the Prophet Dauid ſayd of himſelfe: I ſhallPſal. 117. 17. Pſal. 26. 13. not die but liue: and ſhall ſee the goodneſſe of God in the land of the liuing.
               And good Iob ſayd of himſelfe: I know that my RedeemerIob. 19. 25. liueth, and that I ſhall riſe againe in the laſt day, and ſhall be couered againe with my skin, and ſhall ſee God in my fleſh, and I my ſelfe ſhall behold him, not with other, but with theſe ſame eies.
               And our ſauiour Chriſt ſayth of the dead Damoſell:Matt. 9. 24. She is not dead, but ſleepeth.
               And the ſcriptures of God do often teſtifie of the dead, that they ſleepe: for that euen as they that ſleepe, do wakeIohn 11. 11. 1. Cor. 15. 18. 1. Theſ. 4. 3. and riſe againe, euen ſo the dead ſhall riſe againe. As many as die in Chriſt, ſhall be partakers of the reſurrection vnto ſaluation: and as many as die without Chriſt, ſhall riſe againe to condemnation.
               But what need I ſtand to prooue the reſurrection of the dead?
               The ſect of the Sadduces, that beleeue no reſurrectionAct. 23. 23. of the dead, neither angell, nor ſpirit, is ſufficiently confuted by our ſauiour Chriſt in the goſpell.
               And that godleſſe ſort that ſay: Our life is but a breathSap. 2. 2. in our noſthrils, and our bodies ſhall returne to duſt and aſhes, and our ſoules ſhall vaniſh into the ſoftaire, are alreadie condemned by the wiſe man.
               To ſpend ſpeech then in that point, it needs not, or it boots not.
               
                  Therefore to conclude, I haue ſayd, Ye are gods, but ye ſhall die like men, and your bodies ſhall returne to the earth from whence they came, and your ſoules ſhall returne to God that gaue them, there to render an account to the God of heauen for your earthy godhead, and to receiue the iudgement, either to the ioy that neuer ſhall haue end, or els to the paine that neuer ſhall haue end.
               So ſayth S. Paul, All muſt appeare before the iudgementRom. 14. 10. ſeat of Chriſt, that euerie one may yeeld vnto God an account of himſelfe.
               For all in this life are but the Lord his ſtewards, andLuc. 16. 1. when Death the Lord his bailiffe, ſhall arreſt you with his writ, Non amplius villicabere, then muſt you appeare before the great iudge, and render an account euerie one of his ſtewardſhip.
               Then, then (O man, whatſoeuer thou art) then ſhalt thou ſee vpon thy right hand, thine owne ſinnes accuſing thee: vpon thy left hand infinit leagions of diuels pleading againſt thee: aboue thee, the terrible countinance of the iuſt iudge againſt thee: vnderneath thee, the gaping gulfe of hell fire to deuoure thee: within thee, thine owne conſcience condemning thee. Miſer homo, quid tum facies? i. O miſerable man, what wilt thou then do? Latere impoſsibile, apparere intollerabile, i. To hide thee then it is not poſſible, to ſhew thy ſelfe then is a thing intollerable.
               For then the Lord ſhall trie out thy workes, &amp; ſearchSap. 6. 3. out thine imaginations, and all thy ſecret thoughts, ſhall be layd open before thee, And the heauens ſhall bewraieIob. 20. 27. thine iniquities, and the earth ſhall riſe vp againſt thee, and all thy ſinnes ſhall lie at thy doore, and all thy miſdeedsGen. 4. 3. ſhall be rife in thy remembrance.
               
                  Then they, that now account it but a ſport to ſinne, and take great pleaſure in the workes of wickedneſſe, ſhall then houle and crie in the anguiſh of their owne ſoules, and ſay: O we haue ſinned, we haue dealt wickedly, we haue forſaken the wayes of the Lord, and haue followed the paths of perdition in ſinne. Woe therefore vnto vs: for the Lord ſhall heape ſorrowe vpon ſorrow vnto our ſoules, and we ſhall neuer find reſt.
               Then ſhall they crie to the hilles, fall vpon vs, and toApoc. 6. 16. the mountaines, Couer vs from the face of the Lambe. Nay, they ſhall creepe into the holes and caues of theEſa. 2. 19. earth, to hide themſelues from the feare of the Lord, and from the glorie of his Maieſtie: yet ſhall they not eſcape the iudgements of the Lord, and they that beare rule, ſhalSap. 6. 6, 7. haue the ſorer triall: and the mightie ſhall be mightilie tormented.
               Heare therefore, heare euerie one the good counſell of that good father to euerie one: Cogita, vndè ſis, &amp; erubeſce:
                  
                     
                        •
                     ern. in ſerm. quodam. 
                  vbiſis, &amp; ingemiſce: quò ſis iturus, &amp; contremiſce, that is, Thinke ſtill, O man, whence thou art, vz. of the duſt and ſlime of the earth, be not high minded, but humble thy ſelfe.
               Thinke ſtill, O man, where thou art: vz. In a world of woe and wickedneſſe: delight not in it, but mourne and lament it.
               Thinke ſtill, O man, whither thou ſhalt, vz. to the iudgement ſeat of God: forget it not, but tremble at it.
               So that whither thou cateſt or drinkeſt, or whatſoeuerHierom. ſuper Matth. thou doeſt, thou ſtill thinke, thou heareſt the trumpet ſound, Ariſe ye dead, and come to iudgement.
               And this continuall cogitation of death, wil be a greatAug. lib. exhortat.
                  
moderation to the actions of this life, to make preparation in time for death.
               Knowing, that though ye be gods, that is, ſet on Gods ſeat, by Gods appointment, in ſtead of God: though ye repreſent Gods maieſtie, and beare Gods authoritie, and in all the things of this world, liue like gods among men, yet are you but gods on earth, and gods of earth, that is, earthie and mortall gods, and muſt die like other men, and part from all your pompe, and render account to the God of heauen for your earthie godhead.
               And thus I haue ſayd, Ye are gods, but ye ſhall die like men.
               God be mercifull therefore vnto vs, and bleſſe vs, and graunt vs his heauenly ſpirit and grace, that we that be vnder you; may honour and obey you, and pray to God for you, as our dutie is to you, for that ye are gods: and that you gods on earth may carefully performe your dutie to the God of heauen, that when you ſhal die like men, and part from your earthie godhead, you may returne to the God of heauen, and haue the fruition of the eternall godhead, by the death and merits of Chriſt Ieſus the ſonne of God, To whom, with the Father, and the Holy-ghoſt, be all honour, praiſe, and glorie▪ for euer and euer,
               Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

