
   
      
         
            A briefe and plaine declaration, concerning the desires of all those faithfull ministers, that haue and do seeke for the discipline and reformation of the Church of Englande which may serue for a iust apologie, against the false accusations and slaunders of their aduersaries.
         
         
            
               1584
            
         
         Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00283
            STC 10395
            ESTC S111889
            99847149
            99847149
            12169
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00283)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12169)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:36)
         
         
            
               
                  A briefe and plaine declaration, concerning the desires of all those faithfull ministers, that haue and do seeke for the discipline and reformation of the Church of Englande which may serue for a iust apologie, against the false accusations and slaunders of their aduersaries.
                  Fenner, Dudley, 1558?-1587, attributed name.
                  Fulke, William, 1538-1589, attributed name.
                  Travers, Walter, 1547 or 8-1635, attributed name.
               
               [8], 148 p.   
               
                  Printed by Robert Walde-graue,
                  At London :
                  1584.
               
               
                  Variously attributed to William Fulke, Dudley Fenner, or Walter Travers.
                  Caption title reads: A learned discourse of ecclesiasticall gouernment.
                  Surrounding title page ornament reads: God is my defender.
                  Reprinted and answered in Bridges, John.  A defence of the gouernment established in the church of Englande for ecclesiasticall matters (STC 3734); defended by Travers, Walter. A defence of the ecclesiastical discipline ordayned of God to be vsed in his church (STC 24183).
                  Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.
               Reformation --  England --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-04
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2004-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ A BRIEFE
and plaine declaration, concerning
the desires of all those faithfull
Ministers, that haue and do seeke for the
Discipline and reformation of the Church
of Englande:
            Which may serue for a iust Apologie, against
the false accusations and slaunders
of their aduersaries.
            GOD IS MY
DEFENDER.
            AT LONDON;
Printed by Robert Walde-graue.
1584.
         
         
            
            
            A praeface to
the Christian
Reader.
            
               THE holy Prophets hauing
oftentymes,1. Pet. 9. 10. * but searched
vvhen and at vvhat time the
foreseeing spirit of God declared
vnto them the manifold
afflictions and troubles
of the church to come; haue
therevpon entered into great lamentations for
the same: And haue not onely vvept and fasted
them selues,Lamen. 1. 2 3. 4. * but haue compiled for the church
vvhole bookes of lamentations; therein instructing
them what vvay to take,Ioel. 2. for appeasing the
fierce wrath of God breaking out against them.
VVhich dutie in semblable maner should novv
long agoe haue beene done of vs, did not the
hope vvee conceiue in the middest of manye
tempestes, confirme vs in such expectation of
her maiestie and her most honourable counsell,
as that according to their clemencie tovvardes
the poore ministers and their families, but most
especially according to their holye and zealous
care, vvhich ought to abound for the cleane driuing
out of the Cananites, and planting, hedging,
pruning, and continuall preseruing of the
Lord his vineyard, from Foxes, yea little Foxes,

this ciuill vvar, as a man may say, of the church
vvherein so much of that bloudAct. 20. 26. * (vvherof Paule
speaketh) is powred to the grounde, shoulde by
their holie and iuste authoritie, fully bee ended.
Now, vvhen as vve at this time, are subiect almoste
vnto all the afflictions vvhich can come
vnto a church, blessed of God vvith such a christian
and happie regiment; as to the prophane
scoffing of the *Neh. 4. 2. 3. 4 Hammonits at the buylding of
the church,Neh. 4. 7. as at a vval vvhich a Fox should destroy;
to the conspiracies of the Arrabies and
those of Ashod; to the falseNeh. 6. 5. 6. * charges of sedition,
contempt of all good lavves and proceedinges,
like to that of Sanballat; yea to theNeh. 10. 11. 12 * prophetes
them selues, vndermining, nay reuiling,
displacing, and grieuouslye afflicting the Godly
and learned ministerie, &amp; so consequently plaging
the Church vvith that plague vvherbyIoel. 1. 9. * the
priestes may mourne,Amos. 8. 11. 12. 13. because there is no offering,
and the people perishe, euen the yong men
vvith the famine of hearing the vvorde of God
preached: when I say, we are subiect to al these,
vvee can thinke of no vvaye for reconciling the
brethren at variance, &amp; after a most sure &amp; holy
vnion of both their forces, for a couragious setting
vpon the common aduersary, then the certaine,
peaceable and reasonable vvay following.
VVhich is, that vvhereas both by bookes alreadie
written, and by treatizes latelye and novv
published, it may appeare vve seeke that vvhich
at the least in the iudgement of all true Christians
hath no small probabilitie (as vve iudge necessitie)
of trueth out of the scriptures: it maye
please her most excellent maiestie and their honours

to appoynt on both sides the best learned,
most Godly &amp; moderate men to debate all differences
of vvaight betweene them and vs. So
that first vpon sufficient consideration, the questions
to be debated be vvithout all ambiguitie
set downe, the reasons of both sides vvithout all
out-goynges shortly and plainely deliuered in
vvriting each to other, that after vpon sufficient
examination the reasons of both be continuallye
confirmed and resolued, till eyther by the euidence
of truth one part yeeld vnto the other;
or the folly and madnes of those vvhich gaynesay it, do in equall iudgement become manifest,
in regarde of the contradictions and absurdities
vvhereto they shall bee dryuen by the force of
Gods vvorde. VVhich vvay though it shoulde
come naked vnto vs can not well be refused, but
beeing richly attyred vvith all robes and ornaments
vvhich the scripture giueth vnto the Synodicall
assemblyes for such conferences: as
namely that there beeAct. 15. 7. * much searching of the
trueth by sufficient reasoning vvithout all by
matters, quarrels, euasions and colours vvhatsoeuer,
that there be much1. Cor. 14. 13. 32. * order, vvhen the spirite
of euerye prophet shall be subiect vnto the
spirits of the other prophets, &amp; the iudgement of
al shalbe sufficiently heard, vvithout stopping of
free &amp; sufficient answere, without Lordly carrying
away of the matter with no substāce of reason,
vvhere no authoritie, pregnancie of vvit,
plausible perswasion of mans vvisedome, shall
turn the truth aside, but al shal stand in the1. Cor. 2. 4. * euident
demonstration of Gods spirite: lastly that
there be1. Cor. 14. 33 * peace without all bitternes, reuilinges,

suspicions, chargings of men dead &amp; aliue, wherby
affections are mooued, iudgement blinded,
and men driuen as vvith a mighty streame from
the loue of the truth: vvhen it commeth thus adorned
vve thinke, that vvhich we labor to procure
to be so honorableAct. 14. 16. * not only before God,
but also before men, that none can iudge othervvise
of it then vve doe. For if any shall obiect,
that the graue authoritie of Archbishops &amp; Bishoppes
shall receiue a checke, whilest they are
brought to deale with those, whome they iudge
fewe, young, vnlearned, and not comparable to
them selues: or that it is a challenge not much
vnlike the Papistes: or lastly, that it shall be preiudiciall
to the estate of gouerment established:
It maye please their wisedomes vvho are to bee
iudges, to consider what vvee haue to aunsvvere
vnto these things: which, if they haue the truth
of God his word, containe the safest &amp; best way
in such cases, tend to the full quieting of all, and
the remoouing of the plagues vvhich are vppon
vs, and are like dayly further to come, euen from
the cōmon aduersary: VVe may boldly yet most
humbly vppon our knees requyre them before
God and all his elect Angels no
                  •
                to cast it away.
VVherfore for the first, let vs grant the great
difference vvhich they make of yeares and learning,
yet the speech of Elihu giueth them sufficient
answere,Iob. 32. 7. 8. that this vnderstanding is not tyed
to such outvvard respectes but to theIob. 32. 21. 22. * reuelation
of Gods spirit, and to accept in such cases
the persons of men, or to giue titles, is but to
prouoke God to destroy vs. Yea let the memorable
examples of2. Chro. 30. 1 5. 23. ver. * Ezechias and the priestes: of

               Actes. 15. 23. the Apostles in their counsels, of *Gal. 1. 1. Paule in his
Epistles, and euen of *Act. 11. 1. 2. 3 4. &amp;c. Peter in yeelding to the
challenge of some not so well instructed mooue
them, vvho not onely not refused the Leuites &amp;
Elders; but accepted the people in some maner
to be heard to speake, and to authorize their determinations
and writings: at least let their own
opinion, that, in interpreting the scriptures and
deliuerye of doctrine,D. VVhitgifts booke. page. 389. we are equall vvith them,
persvvade them, not to refuse those, vvho if they
coulde straine their consciences to subscribe to
the Archbish. articles, they would gladly receiue
them to be the Ambassadors of Iesus Christ. As
for the fevvnes it may bee, if the ignorant ministers,
the varietie of other which subscribe, some
doing it vvith this limitation &amp; some vvith that,
some holding their former iudgement as not
gaine sayd by their subscription, some lamenting
their slip in that behalfe vvere deducted, the nū
               ber
of the one vvoulde not so greatly surmount
the other. As for the challenge of the Papistes
knit vp vvith the consideration of the estate, the
difference may be considered in the matter and
maner. Concerning the matter, they make it in
the substaunce of religion vvhich hath in diuers
assemblies abroad and at home beene disputed,
resolued, and novv publikly maintayned for our
true &amp; holy faith. VVe in maters concerning the
gouernment of Christ of great moment indeed,
yet neuer thus handled, nor vrging the alteration,
but perfection of the estate of the Church, &amp;
further good of the common wealth, vvhilst by
this means amongst many other things of great
importance, the ignorant ministery, &amp; by it poperie,

&amp; by popery rebellion should be auoyded,
vvhich by the other are most manifestly bred &amp;
nourished. Concerning the maner, they call it to
a sudden and tumultuous reasoning, vvhere the
readiest vvit, the best memorye, the moste filed
speech, shall carry avvaye the truth, at least maruailously
moue the vngrounded harers. VVe require
that where both sides may vpon mature &amp;
sufficient deliberation be beard vvithout any of
these shewes, and the matter deliuered vnto her
maiestie, their Hh: and vvhomsoeuer they shall
chuse, to receiue and examine the allegations of
both sides: So that it neede not be communicated
vnto the people, vntill the manifest light of
truth appeare first vnto them. And if this so safe
and reasonable an offer, cannot be liked in the
respect of the last obiected consideration, vve
thinke it impossible, but the persons vvhich desire
a vvay so sound, peaceable and dutifull, shall
recouer this fauor that vvith safety of their consciences,
they shall exercise their ministery vvith
that libertie, vvhich is meet for those, vvho shall
be tyed in all thinges to haue especiall regard to
the peace of the Church and publique orders.
VVherefore most christian Reader, vvhen thou
shalt by these sevve, take knovvledge of these
things, pray vnto God for vs, and as thy place is,
solicite and further so iust a cause, to this ende
onely, that Christes kingdome may be perfectly
established, the consciences of al the godly quieted,
and the happy regiment of her maiestie
honored, vvith much peace ioye and quietnesse
at home.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ A LEARNED DISCOVRSE,
OF ECCLESIASTIcall
Gouernement, prooued by the
worde of God.
            
               THE Churche
of God is the
house of God,Tim. 3. 15.
and therefore
ought to bee
directed in all
thinges,The definition of the Church. according
to the order
prescribed by the Housholder
himselfe: Which order is not to bee
learned else-where, but in his Holy
worde. The first of these principles
or propositions, is the very worde of
the holy Ghost vttered by Paul: The
seconde followeth necessarily of the
first. The thirde is a manifest trueth
beleeued of all them, that acknowledge
the scripture of God, to bee a

perfect rule of all our life, and able
to make the man of God perfect,2. Tim. 3. 17.
prepared to all good workes.
            This foundation being surely layde,VVhat ministers are appointed in the church.
against which the gates of hell cannot
preuayle: wee ought diligently
and reuerently to searche the holie
scriptures, that wee may finde what
order our sauiour Christe our onely
housholder hath set foorth in them,
by which he woulde haue his house
or church to be directed in al things,
appertaining to the eternall saluation
of vs men, his vnprofitable seruants.
Nowe we finde in the scriptures,
that our sauiour Christe ascending
into Heauen, was not vnmindfull
of his Church on earth,Ephes. 4. 11. but ordayned
an holy ministerye of men,1. Cor. 12. 28. to
the building vp of the body of Christ
in vnity of faith and knowledge. We
finde also, that as the offices are
diuerse of this ministery: so they are
not generall vnto all the Church, but
as order and necessitye require, for
executing of their office, distributed
and limitted vnto certaine places or

particuler Churches, according to
the diuision of Regions, Cities, and
Townes. For we reade that Paule and
Barnabas ordeyned at Derbe, Lystra,
Iconium, Antiochia, &amp;c: Elders by election
in euery Churche,Act. 14. 23. with Prayer
and fasting, and so commended them
to the Lorde, in whome they beleeued.Titus. 1. 5.
Also Paule left Titus in the Ile of
Creta, that he shoulde ordaine Elders
in euery City, as hee had appointed.
Concerning the diuers offices of the
Ministery, wee are taught by Saynte
Paule. Rom. 12. 6. Also 1. Cor.
12. 28. and Ephes. 4. 11.Rom. 12. 6. 1. Cor. 12. 28 Ephes. 4. 11. Where
we reade, that God hath ordained in
the ministery of his Church, these seuerall
offices: Namely, Apostles, Euangelistes,
Prophetes, Pastors, Doctours, Gouernoures
and Deacons: Also men indewed
with the giftes of healing, of
powers or myracles, and of diuerse
tongues.
            Of these offices, some were temporall,
seruing onelye for the firste
planting &amp; foundation of the church
amonge the Heathen: some are

perpetuall, pertaining to the nourishing
and building vp the Church for
euer. Of the former sort were Apostles,
Prophets, Euangelists, men endued
with the graces of powers, of
healings, and of diuerse tongues. Of
the latter kinde are doctors, Pastors,
Gouernours and Deacons. The Apostles
were ordained by God, and sent
foorth immediatly by Christ, hauing
a generall Commission to spread the
Gospell ouer all the worlde: Which
worke when they had accomplished,
that office ceased.Math. 28. 19. Such were the 12.
Apostles,Mark. 16. 25. 
               Paule and Barnabas, &amp;c.
            And for this cause the Apostles appointed
Mathias in the place of Iudas,
               Act. 1. 15.
according to the Scriptures, permitting
neuerthelesse, the election
vnto God, by casting of Lots, that the
number might bee full, for the first
planting of the Churche. But when
Herod had slaine Iames the brother of
Iohn with the sworde,Act. 12. 2. they chose no
man to succeede in his place, because
they had no warrant of Gods worde,
but the holy ghost, as he sawe it was

expedient for the Church, afterward
separated Paul and Barnabas which liued
at Antioche,
               Act. 13. 2. as Prophetes and
Teachers, to the worke whereto hee
had called them.
            The Prophets were suche as were
indued with a singular gifte of Reuelation
in the interpretation of the
Scriptures,1. Cor. 12. and applying them to the
present vse of the Church:Ephes. 4. 11. of whome
some also did foreshewe of thinges to
come,Acts. 11. 28▪ &amp; 21. 10. as Agabus. Also there were
in euery City that Prophecied to S.
Paul, as he passed by them, that bonds
and afflictions were prepared for him
at Hierusalem.
               Acts. 20. 23 This office being in the
number of them that were ordeyned
for beautifying the Gospell, in the
first publishing thereof, it ceassed with
that singuler and extraordinary gift,
to bee an ordinarye function of the
Church.
            The Euangelists were such as were
stirred vp of God, to assist the Apostles
in their ministerye of generall
charge: in planting the Gospell, and
confirming the same by their preaching,

but inferiour in dignity to the
Apostles.Acts. 8. 5. Such was Philip that firste
preached the gospel in Samaria: Whither
Peter and Iohn were sent by the
Apostles,Act. 8. 14. to conferre vnto them by
prayer and imposition of hands, the
visible Graces of the holye Ghoste,
which Philip did not. The same Philip
in Act. 21.Acts. 21. 8. verse 8. is called an
Euangelist. So is Timothy, 2. Timoth.
4. 5.2. Tim. 2. 5. 5 Such was Titus, Silus, and many
other. This office also with the order
of the Apostles is expired, and hath
no place. Likewise, as wee doe plainly
see, that the gifts of healing, of povvers
or myracles, and of diuerse
tonges, haue long since ceassed to be
in the Church: So the offices of them
which were groūded vpon these gifts,
must also cease and bee determined.
Therfore the Papists do vainly retain
the name &amp; office of Exorcists, when
they cānot cast out diuels: &amp; extream
vnction, when they cannot cure disseases:
and to speak with straunge
tonges, which they haue not by inspiration,
&amp; that without any interpretation,

which Saint Paule expresly forbiddeth.1. Corin. 14.
There remayneth therefore
of these before rehearsed, onely in the
Church, these Ecclesiasticall offices
instituted of God:VVhat offices remaine in the Church. namely, Pastors,
Doctors, Gouernours, and Deacons: By
which the church of God may, according
to his worde, be directed in all
matters, which are commonly called
Ecclesiasticall. And therefore as it is
vnlawful, so it is vnneedeful for men,
following the deuises of their owne
brayne, without the warrant of Gods
worde, to institute and ordayne anye
other offices or kindes of ministerye
beside these, appointed &amp; approued
by God himself, exercised in the Primitiue
&amp; pure church, vntil the mistery
of iniquity working a way for Antichristes
pride &amp; presumption, changed
Gods ordinance, and brought in
al kind of false doctrine &amp; confusion:
and now againe, restored in al rightly
reformed Churches, with such daylie
increase, and glory of the kingdom of
Christ, and suppression of the tyrannie
of Sathan, that the onelye experience

hereof, might bee a sufficient
perswasion to vs to leaue this disordered
state of ours, wherein we haue
so long laboured with so little profit:
and to imbrace that most beautifull
order of Ecclesiastical regimēt, which
God so manifestlye doth blesse and
prosper in our neighboures handes.
But while we speake of Ecclesiasticall
gouernment, it maye bee thought of
some, that we shoulde intreat first of
the supreame authority of Christian
Princes: Whereuppon it seemeth that
al the regiment of the church dependeth,
which is such a myst to dazle the
eyes of ignoraunt persons, that they
thinke all thinges in the Ecclesiastical
state, ought to be disposed by that
onelye high authoritye and absolute
power of the Ciuil magistrate. Others
there be, with more colour of reason,
that referre onely indifferent matters
to the disposition of Princes: but in
determining indifferēt matters, they
shewe themselues not to bee indifferent
Iudges. For, whatsoeuer it shall
please the Ciuill Magistrate, or themselues,

to call or count indifferent, it
must be so holden of all men, without
anye further enquiry. But of the supreame
authority of christian princes
in Ecclesiasticall causes, howe farre it
extēdeth by the word of God: we shal
haue better occasiō to intreat hereafter,
when we haue described the Ecclesiastical
state. And that it is neither
needefull nor agreeable to good order
of teaching, to begin first therewith,
it may be plaine to euerye man
by this reason. The Church of God
was perfect in all her regiment, before
there was any Christian Prince:
yea, the Churche of God may stande,
and doth stande at this day in moste
blessed estate, where the Ciuill Magistrates,
are not the greatest fauorers.
By which, it is manifest, that the regiment
and gouernement thereof, dependeth
not vppon the authority of
Princes, but vpon the ordinaunce of
God, who hath most mercifully and
wisely so established the same, that as
with the comfortable ayde of Christian
Magistrates, it may singulerlie

flourish &amp; prosper, so without it, it may
continue, and against the aduersaries
therof preuail. For the church craueth
help &amp; defence of christian Princes, to
continue &amp; go forward more peaceably
&amp; profitably, to the setting vp of
the kingdō of Christ: but al hir authority
she receiueth immediatly of God.
Let vs therfore return to those offices
of Ecclesiasticall regiment, which now
remain to be exercised in the Church
of God, being instituted &amp; ordained
by Christe himselfe, which before we
haue proued out of the scriptures to
be only these, Doctors, Pastors, Gouernors
&amp; Deacons, wherof some appertain to
doctrin,Doctors. some to gouernment and discipline.
The duty of doctors &amp; Pastors,
is chiefly to teach and instruct the people
of god, in al things that God hath
appointed thē to learne. The office of
Elders &amp; Deacons, is to prouide that
good order and discipline bee obserued
in the church. These offices being
rightly established &amp; exercised in the
Church, are able to make vs meet together
in the vnity of faith, and knowledge

of the sonne of God, vnto a perfect
man acording to doctrine.Ephes. 4. 13. And
both for doctrine and order of gouernement,
to make vs one body of
Christe,1. Cor. 12. 27. and members one of another.
Nowe what shoulde be desired
more then this in the church of God?
or what wisdom of man can espy better
then the spirite of God, by what
means this shold be brought to effect
which we do desire? what mans wit cā
deuise better, then the wisdom of god
hath expressed? Or whē God hath established
an order, for the administratiō
of his own house: what presūptiō
of man dare change it? But what dare
not dust &amp; ashes presūe to do against
his maker, &amp; that with greatest incō
               uenience,
when with best pretences of
correcting and reforming that, which
they do thinke to be vnperfect in his
doings? Exāple thereof we haue most
euident. That which is alleaged as the
chief defence of this disordered state,
which now remaineth in our church:
namely, that our fathers of old time
were not content with the simple order

instituted by Christe, and established
by his Apostles: but for better
gouerning of the Church, thought
good some offices to ad therto, some
to take away: some to alter &amp; change:
and in effect to peruerte and ouerthrow
all Christian and Ecclesiastical
pollicie, which was builded vpon the
foundation of the Prophetes and Apostles,Ephes. 2. 20.
Iesus Christ being the cheeft
corner stone. But how vnhappy a successe
this good intent, (as they call
it) of theirs deserued to haue of God,
who alwayes abhorreth all good intentes
of men, that are contrarye to
the good pleasure of his will, expressed
in his holy worde, the age before
vs (alasse) hath felt, the present time
doth plainly see, and wee praye God
the posterity, warned by examples of
their auncesters, maye take heede of
it. For where there are specially two
thinges propounded in the Churche
of God: Doctrine and Discipline, as
if a man woulde say, knowledge and
practise, by which the glory of God
is sought and shineth therin: In steed

of true Doctrine, followed all manner
of corruptions of the same, both
in the whole and in euery part thereof,
as ignorance, heresies, idolatry, superstition,
&amp;c. The Discipline degenerated
vnto intollerable tyrannye
and external domination, clean contrarye
to the commaundemente of
Christ, whereof insued all vnbrideled
license of vngodly liuing. To be short,
the exchaunge of the ordinaunce of
God and Christ,2. Thes. 2. 1
                     •
                  
                brought in nothing
else, but the Diuell and Antichriste.
Wherefore if we minde such a reformation,
as shall bee acceptable to
God, &amp; profitable vnto his church:
We must thoroughly bee resolued to
set vp no new kinde of ministerye, of
our owne inuention, neyther for teaching,
nor for discipline in the Ecclesiastical
state, but bring all thinges to
that most perfect and absolute order,
which God himselfe hath established
by his worde. And because all offices
of the Churche are so lincked togeather,
as the members of one bodye,
whereof Christe is the heade: we will

so describe one part, as the descriptiō
of thē al may be sufficiently cōprehended
therin. As if a man wold set forth
the manifold office &amp; vses of the hād,
he shold declare what it doth alone, &amp;
what it doth with the helpe of the other
hand, or with the arme, with the
brest, with the knee, or with the foot,
&amp;c: what it cā do with diuers kinds of
tooles, &amp; what without al maner of instrumēts. This order we thought good
to obserue, in describing the ministery
of the Church, as by which, both the
distinction &amp; cōmunicatiō of al offices
&amp; seruices in the Church, might most
plainli appear. Otherwise we force not
by what method, so the same truth be
plainly set forth by any mā. And as we
controle not other mens methods by
ours, so we wold not, that other mens
maner of teaching shold be preiudicial
to ours. This we say because of thē,
which either for lack of wit, or thorow
too much wilfulnes, if they see any difference
in the form &amp; order of teaching
of diuers men, though in matter &amp;
substaunce they all agree, they exclaim

there is no vnitie, &amp; therfore no truth
among thē. Let vs then proceed in our
purpose. The office of teaching is the
chiefe &amp; principall office that is in the
church. By that we be taught to know
God, &amp; how to serue him, &amp; what benefits
to look for at his hand, without
which knowlege, ther cā be no felicity
but only destruction loked for, according
to the saying of the wise man:
Wher propheciyng fayleth,
               Prou. 29. 18. 
               ther the people perish.
The ministery is diuided into two
functiōs: they that exercise the first are
called Pastors:
               The office of a Doctor. the other are called Doctors
or Teachers. The office of a Doctor
is to teach, as the very name doth declare,
but yet euery teacher is not mēt
thereby, for it appertaineth to Pastors
also to teach: yet this latter is distinct
frō the former. Almighty God, being
carefull that true doctrin should continue
in his church, from time to time
most wisely prouided, that certain mē
shold be appointed in euery cōgregation,
(whō he hath endued with gifts
meete for the same purpose) which
shoulde employe themselues, either
wholly or principally to the studie of

holy scriptures, therebye to learne to
auouche the principles of true religion,
and to represse and beate downe
al false and strange opinions, of which
sathan neuer ceaseth to sow the seeds,
but cheefly where this office is not set
vp &amp; mayntained according to Gods
ordinance. These men must not content
themselues with contemplatiue
knowledge: but, as by the grace of
God they excell other men in vnderstanding:
so they must diligentlye instruct
other mē in the same learning,
and openly confute al false Doctrine
and herisie: and especially they ought
to take payne in the instruction of
such men, as maye bee made meete
to serue in the Churche: as Pastoures,
and to succeede in their place as Doctours.
Their institution is set foorth,
1. Corin. 12. 28. Also Ephes. 4. 11.
In the former place the Apostle teacheth,
that they are the ordinaunce
of God: Sayth he, God hath ordayned in
the Church: First Apostles, Secondly Prophets,
Thirdly Doctors, or Teachers. In
the latter place hee testifieth,Ephes. 4. 11. that our

Sauior Christ ascended on high, ledde cap
                  
                     •
                  iuitie
captiue, and hath giuen giftes vnto

                     •
                  en, amongst which gifts, he accoun
               
                  •
               eth
the function of Teachers. Who

                  ••
               oulde then refuse to imbrace the

                  •
               rdinaunce of God? Who should de
               
                  •
               riue
vs of the free gyft of Christ?
The office of Doctours, is briefly ex
               
                  •
               ressed
in Rom. 12. 7.Rom. 12. 7. 
               Let him that is
Teacher, attend vppon teaching, where

                  •
               lso it is distinguished from other of
               
                  •
               ces,
and namely from the office of

                  •
               astors. For it followeth immediat
               
                  •
               e,Rom. 12. 8.
               Let him that exhorteth, (which is a

                  •
               rincipall part of a Pastors office, not

                  •
               ecessarily requyred in a Teacher) Be

                     •
                  ligent in his exhortation. For the office
of Doctours, is onely to teach true
doctrine, and to confute all heresies.
and false opinions by the worde of
God, concerning all Articles &amp; prin
               
                  ••
               ples
of Christian religion, without
applying their teaching to anye particular
state of time, of persons or
places. The example or practize of
this office, is set foorth Acts. 13. 1.
Where it is recorded by S. Luke, that

               Paule and Barnabas, (before the holy
Ghost commanded them to be separated
for the worke wherevnto he
called them) were in the number of
prophetes and Doctors, with Symeon
Niger, Lucius of Syrene, and Manahen
                     •
                  
               
in the Church of Antiochia, where
they continued in that office a whol
                  •
               
yeare, in which Citie the Disciples
were first called by the name of christians.
Act. 11. 26.Acts. 11. 26. Likewise, Apollo
                     •
                  
               
which was an eloquent man &amp; mightie
in the scriptures, firste at Ephesus
but afterward beeing more perfectly
instructed in the waye of God, by
Aquila and Priscilla in the church of
Acha
                     •
                  a, exercised the office of a Teacher,
with great profite of thē which
had beleeued, and to the great confusion
of the stiffnecked Iewes, while
hee proued plainly by the scriptures,
that Iesus was the Christ. Act. 18. 28.Acts. 18. 28.
Therefore if we purpose to haue the
church to flourish in true knowlege,
we must prouide that this office be
restored, both in the vniuersities, and
in as manie other places as maye be,

as well for the better instruction of
al men, which are desirous to learne,
as especiallye for the information of
those, which shoulde occupye the

                  •
               oomes of Pastours, of which sort

                  •
               here ought to be a great number alwayes
in good towardnesse to take
charge of so many seuerall flockes, as
must of necessitie be, in so great a
Church as this is.
            Besides Doctors,Pastors and their Titles. there must be Pa
               
                  •
               tours
ordained in euery congregation,
which haue diuers appellations

                  •
               n the scripture, as Eph. 4. They are

                  •
               alled by the name of Pastours, be
               
                  •
               ause
they ought to feede the seueral

                  •
               ocks of Gods sheepe committed to

                  •
               heir charge. As it appeareth Act. 20

                  •
               8. 1. Peter. 5. 2.Acts. 20. 28. 1. Pet. 5. 2. They are called also
Elders, not alwaies in respect of their

                  •
               ge, but of their office and grauitie.

                  •
               or Timothie was but a young man,
and yet had the office of an Elder.
This name was receiued of an an
               
                  •
               ient
custome of the people of Is
               
                  •
               aell,
who vsed so to call those that
were Rulers and Officers amonge

them, as it appeareth by many places
both of the old and new Testament,Num. 11. 16.
but chiefly in Numb. 11. 16. Where
God ordayned seuenty ancientes, to
assist Moses in his gouernment, who
were also endued at the same time,
with the spirite of prophecie, from
which time it became an ordinarie
office, and name of Gouernours in
Israell. Wherein we haue to note against
the papistes, that the ministers
of the Church, are neuer called in
the new Testament, by the name of
sacrificing Priestes, which were vnder
the lawe, but often are called Elders,
of the similitude of those ancientes
                  •
               
that gouerned the people of God
Whereas, if they had beene appoynted
of God to be sacrificers, the similitude
&amp; name of sacrificing priestes,
would a great deale better haue
agreed vnto them. But, whereas both
these names were vsuall amongst the
Iewes, Iereus and Presbyteroi, the one
signifiyng sacrificers, and the other
Elders: The spirit of God doth often
call the ministers Elders, but euermore

preciselye auoydeth to name
them sacrificers or priestes (as we vse
the terme): yea, though they succeed
them in one principall part of their
office, that is to saye in teaching, as it

                  •
               s written.Mala. 2. 7. 
               The lippes of the priest shoulde
preserue knowledge, and men shal seeke the
law at his mouth. The cause whereof is
euident to bee this, that the sacrificing
priesthoode of Aaron,Heb. 7. 12. 24 is wholly
translated vnto Christ, in whom onely
it resteth, and passeth from him to
none other. But by the name of Elders,
the Pastors are called Act. 14. 23Act. 14 23.
Where Paule and Barnabas ordained
Elders by election in euerye congregation.
And Act. 20. 17.Act. 20. 17. Paule sent for
the Elders of Ephesus to Miletū. Also

                  •
               he affirmeth those Elders especially,1. Tim. 5. 17.
which labour in preaching and doctrine,
to be worthy of double honor.
Which place also testifieth of an other
kind of Elders, of whom we shal

                  •
               haue occasion to speake more hereafter,Tit. 1. 5.
whose office consisteth only in
gouernement, and not in publique
teaching. Moreouer, he sheweth that

he appoynted Titus to ordaine Eldersin
euery Citie, and afterwarde
describeth what maner of men hee
woulde haue to bee chosen into the
office.Iam. 5. 14. Also Saint Iames in Cap. 5. 14.
willeth that if anye bee sicke, they
shoulde call for the Elders of the
Churche, who being indewed with
the gifte of healinge at that time,
should pray for the diseased, and annoint
him with oyl, and he should be
restored to his health. Finally, Saint
Peter,
               Pet. 5. 2. as a fellowe Elder exhorteth
the Elders to employe all their diligence
to the feeding of the flocke
of God.
            An other name they haue in the
scripture, which is Superintendents,
or Ouerseers, because they ought to
be vigilant and watchfull, to ouersee
the flocke, and euery member thereof.
Which name is neuer vsed in the
scripture for such Bishops, as clayme
and exercise dominion, and authoritie
ouer whole regions, &amp; all the Pastours
of the same, but only for those
that bee Pastours of euery seuerall

congregation, hauing no superiority

                  •
               uer their fellow Pastors, but be al of
equall dignity and authoritie. So are

                  •
               hey named Act. 20.Act. 20. 17. where S. Luke in

                  •
               he 17. vers. calleth them Elders of the
Church of Ephesus. S. Paule in the 28.

                  •
               erse, calleth the same ouerseers: say
               
                  •
               ng,
Take heede to your selues and to the

                     •
                  hole flocke, ouer which the holy Ghoste

                     •
                  ath made you ouerseers, to feede or go
                  
                     •
                  erne
the Church of God, which he hath

                     ••
                  rchased with his owne bloud. In this

                  •
               lace all the three appellations con
               
                  •
               urre:
namely, of ouerseers plaine
               
                  •
               e,
and Pastoures inclusiuely in the

                  •
               orde flocke, and in the worde Pot
                  
                     •
                  ainan,
which signifieth to feede or
gouern, as a Pastor doeth his sheepe.
Where is to bee noted, that Byshoppes
or ouerseers of one Citye
were manye, which plainelye argu
               
                  •
               th
that they were none such as now
a days are commonly called bishops,
which can be but one in one whole
Diocesse, much lesse many in one citie.
The same thing is to be obserued,
in the name of Bishoppes, vsed

by S. Paule. Phillip. 1. 1, where he &amp;
Timothie sende salutations vnto the
Bishops and Deacons of the church,Phillip. 1. 1.
which was in the Citie of Philippi:
which bishops, were the Elders or pastors,
else would he not haue saluted
in special words, the Deacons which
were in inferiour office, and omitted
the Elders, which were of more excellent
calling. In the same maner of
speaking,1. Tim. 3. 2. 8. he describeth the qualities
of those, which were to be chosen into
the office of the bishops and Deacons.
Likewise vnto Titus. 1. 5. He
calleth them Elders, and immediatly
after, discribing the qualities of such,
as were meet to be ordained Elders,
he calleth them bishops: saying, For
this cause did I leaue thee in Creta,
               Tit. 1. 5. 6. 7. 
               that
thou shouldest continue, to redresse the
thinges that remaine: and that thou shouldest
ordayne Elders in euery Citie, if anie
be vnreproueable: the husband of one wife,
hauing faithfull Children which are not
accused of riot, nor are disobedient. For a
Bishop or ouer seer must be vnreprooueable,
as the Steward of God, not froward, &amp;c. Finally,

S. Peter, chapter. 5. 1. the place
before alleadged, comprehendeth al
the three names of Elders, Pastours,
&amp; Bishops.1. Pet. 5. 1. 
               The Elders (saith he) which
are among you, I beseech. The name of
Pastor, is vnderstanded by relation of
the names of feeding, and the flocke
which he vseth, also by the name of
Archipoymē, which signifieth the chief
of Pastours, which is our Sauiour
Christ. The name of bishops or ouerseers
is included in the worde Episcopountes,
which signifieth them which
do carefully exercise the office of bishops
or ouerseers. His exhortation
is this. The Elders which are amongst
you I beseech,
               1. Pet. 5. 1. 2. 3 4. 
               which am also a fellow Elder
and a witnesse of the sufferinges of Christ,
and also a partaker of the glory that shalbe
reuealed: Feede the flocke of God which
is committed vnto you, so much as in you
lieth, carefully ouerseeing, not by constraint
but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a
readie minde, not as exercising Lordshippe
ouer the heritage, but that you may be examples
to the flocke, and when the chiefe
Pastor shall appeare, you shal receiue an incorruptible

Crowne of glory. S. Peter in
this place reprooueth three notable
vices, which doe great hurt among
the ministers of the Church, if they
bee not taken heede of: slouthfulnes
in teaching: couetousnes of lucre, &amp;
ambitious desire of exercising Lordship:
exhorting them to painfull diligence,
because they were Byshops or
Ouerseers: to a ready care, because
they were Pastoures, and therefore
should labour for loue of the flock,
and not for lucre like hirelinges: to
modest humility, because their cheef
dignity in that they were Elders, was
to excell in Godlinesse, that they
might be an ensample to the flock,
which cannot bee, except they submit
themselues and their liues, to the
common rule of other men: which
most excellente vertues if they imbrace,
they shoulde bee sure to bee
plentifullye rewarded by him, who
onelye deserueth to bee called the
cheefe of all Elders, Pastors, and Byshops:
to whome onely these honorable
names of Archipresbyter, Archiepiscopus,

Archiepoimen, and suche
like, do properly agree. For as the Apostle
calleth our Sauiour Christe in
this place, the chiefe Pastor: So in the
second Chapiter the 25. vers. he calleth
him both the Pastor and Byshop
of our soules. Wherefore as he onelye
is oure chiefe Pastour or Archiepoimen,
               Pet. 2. 25.
so is hee also our onelye
Archbyshoppe: And that the name
of Archipresbyter or chiefe of Elders,
pertayneth tono mortall man,
may bee seene by this place, where
Saint Peter that excellent and high
Apostle, who if anye man coulde,
might as well as anye, haue challenged
that name, durste not call
him selfe other then Sunpresbyteros,
a fellowe Elder, no not when hee
sought authoritie to him selfe, by
that name to be bold, to exhort the
Elders of the Church. But least any
man shoulde thinke wee staye onely
in names and tearmes, which are
not so greatlye materiall: let him
consider, that Sainte Peter expresly
forbiddeth the Elders, to exercise

Lordship ouer their seuerall congregations,
how much more ouer their
fellowe Elders. Which thing also
our Sauiour Christ precisely forbiddeth,
when there was a contention
among his Apostles, about the
prymacie.Luk. 22. 25. 
               The kings of the nations haue
dominion ouer them, and they that beare
rule ouer them are called gratious Lordes
or beneficiall, but you shall not be so. Also
Math. 20. 25.Mat. 20: 25. and Mark. 10. 41. vpon
the ambitious request of the sonnes
of Zebedy,Mark. 10. 41. and the disdaine of the other
against them. The Princes of the
Gentiles, exercise Lordship ouer them, and
they that be great, exercise authoritie ouer
them, but it shall not be so amongst you, but
who so will be great amongst you, let him be
your Minister, and he that will be first among
you, let him be your seruaunt. The
same thing he taught by his example,
when hee washed his Apostles
feet,Iohn. 13. 13. and commanded them to shew
the like humilitie one towarde an other,
which were all brethren, which
he their Lord and maister shewed towards
them. Also Math. 23. 8.Mat. 23. 8. &amp;c. he

forbiddeth all ambitious Titles of
Rabbi, Maister, Father, &amp;c. the reason
hee addeth, for you are all Brethren.
For these names agree properly
to God &amp; Christ. For the greatest
dignitie of an Ecclesiasticall person
is a ministery, and not a lordship.
S. Ioh.3. Iohn. 9. also in his third epistle sharply
reprooueth Diotrephes, because he
was Philoproteuon, one that desired
the primacie in the Church. Howbeit
in this case we must take heede,
that we spoyle not the ministers of
the church, of al their lawfull authoritie.
For, although these testimonies
of scripture, directly condemne the
authoritie of one Pastour aboue an
other: yet neither do they set euery
pastour at libertie by him selfe, to do
what they list without controlment:
nor yet doe take away the lawful authoritie
he hath ouer his flocke: but
that imperious and pompeous dominion,
which is meet for ciuill magistrates,
and great Potentates to exercise
in worldly affayres: otherwise
in respect of their lawfull authoritie,

they are called by the Apostle in his
Epistle to the Hebrewes,Heb. 13. 7. Guides,
such as are appoynted to ouersee
the flocke with authority, and vnto
them submission and obedience is
commaunded in the same Chapiter,
verse 17. Other names are
applied to them in the Scripture,
but they bee for the moste parte
more generall, pertaining to all
kinde of Teachers in the Church of
GOD, both in the time of the Lawe
and of the Gospell, as Seers, Prophets,
VVatchmen, Angelles, Labourers,
Builders, Stewardes, and such like: all
which with many other, serue to expresse
some parte of their office, as
their knowledge, their diligence, their
authority, their faithfullnesse, their
discretion: also the necessity of them,
the commoditie that commeth by
them &amp;c. But concerning the names
of Pastours, as they are a speciall office
in the Church, this maye suffise.
But for as muche as we haue vndertaken,
so to describe a Pastour and
and his office, as all other offices of

the Church, may be described therewith:
wee must not staye onelye in
the name, but set foorth also the
whole substaunce of the person. For
which intent, it shall bee necessarye
for vs to consider a Pastour or Bishop,
these two wayes: in the proper
function of his Ministerye, and in
gouernement with his Elders: By
which we shall vnderstande how this
Ministerye ought to bee refourmed
and restored amongest vs. As touching
his office, something hath
beene sayde before generallye, vnder
the description of his seuerall
names. But now more particularlye,
wee must examine, what belongeth
to his charge. The Pastor must
be limitted to one onelye congregation
of such competent number, as
he, (if hee be but one,) or if they be
two, may be sufficient, to the instruction
of all and euerye member of the
same Church. And first, he may no
more lawfully haue charge of two or
three churches, then he can be possibly
in diuerse places. No more then a

sheephearde of whome he taketh his
name, may haue the leading of sundrie
flockes in diuers places: neither
maye he be absent from his charge,
with better reason, then a shepheard
from his flocke. As for substitutes or
                  •
               
hyrelinges, will not bee allowed in
this case: for Pastors are substitutes
of God, and haue an office of credite
committed vnto them, therefore by
no good reason may they make any
substitutes in their place, or commit
their charge vnto an other. The law
of a man grounded vppon good reason,
alloweth not substitutes of substitutes:
nor committing ouer of an
office of credite in temporall matters.
How shall God almighty then
take it in good part, when the flocke
of Christe, which he hath purchased
with his own bloud, shal be so greatly
neglected, to the endaungering
of their euerlasting saluation? Therfore
the ordinaunce of God is, that
the Pastor should attend vnto his peculiar
flocke.1. Pet. 5. That Elders should be
ordayned in euery Citie,Tit. 1. 5. Towne and

other places. Tit. 1. 5.Tit. 1. 5. and Act: 14.
23. The Apostles ordeined Elders in

                  •
               uery Church of Derbe,
               Actes. 14. 23 
               Lystra, Iconi
                  
                     •
                  m
and Tichia, and all the Congrega
               
                  ••
               ons
about.
            Secondly, the office of Pastors is,

                  •
               ot onely to teach the same truth in

                  •
               heir seuerall flockes, but also to ap
               
                  •
               ye
it to the time and persons, of

                  •
               home they haue charge, with ex
               
                  •
               ortation
and reprehension: with

                  •
               onsolation of the afflicted, &amp; threat

                  •
               ing of the obstinate &amp;c. This in

                  •
               we wordes is set foorth by S. Paule

                  ••
               eaking of the diuerse Gifts of God

                  〈◊〉
                his Church,Rom. 12. 7. 8. hee saith: Whether it

                     ••
                  e hee that teacheth, in his Doctrine,

                     〈◊〉
                   hee that exhorteth, in his exhortati
                  
                     ••
                  .
The Doctour therefore teacheth

                  •
               ithout exhortation. The Pastor tea
               
                  •
               heth
and exhorteth withall. More

                  〈◊〉
                larg he setteth forth the same offi
               
                  ••
               
in his exhortation vnto the Past
               
                  •
               rs
of Ephesus, willing them to folow

                  ••
               s example,Acts. 20. whoe supplied that of
               
                  ••
               ce,
vntill they were able to succeed

                  〈◊〉
                his Place. Also very breifly and yet

fully, hee describeth the same vnto
Timothy,
               2. Tim. 3. 16. 17. shewing first that al his foundation
must be out of the scriptures,
which were sufficient for all parts o
                  •
               
his charge, and then moste earnestly
commaundeth him to practise the
same with all diligence: his wordes
are these,2. Tim. 4. 1. 2▪
                
               All Scripture is inspired of
GOD, and profitable for Doctrine, for
exhortation, for reformation and for instruction,
which is in righteousnesse, tha
                     •
                  
the man of God maye bee prepared to a
                     •
                  
good workes: Therefore I charge thee before
God, &amp; before the Lord Iesus Christ,
which shall iudge the quicke and the
deade at his appearing, and in his kingdome,
preache the worde, bee instan
                     •
                  
in season and out of season: improoue, rebuke,
exhort, with all long suffering and doctrine.
            
            The firste part therefore, and the
cheefest of a Pastours office or duety
is, to feede with wholsome doctrine,
the flocke that is committed to his
charge, and therefore Sainte Paul
                     •
                  
               
describing what manner of men are
meete for that charge vnto Timothy,
               
requireth that a Byshop or Pastour
bee apt or able to teache:1. Tim. 3. 2. for if a
man haue neuer so much knoweledge,
and bee not apt or able to
teach, he ought by no meanes to be
admitted vnto this vocation. And
vnto Titus writing Chap. 1. verse 9.
he requireth that he be such a one as
holdeth fast the faythfull worde,
               Tit. 2. 9. 
               according
to Doctrine, that he also may be able to
exhort with wholesome Doctrine, and improoue
them that say against it. Wherevppon
it followeth necessarily, that
whosoeuer is himselfe ignoraunt in
the knowledge of Gods worde, and
therefore vnable eyther to exhorte
with wholsome doctrine, or to confute
them that gainsay it, is altogether
vnmeete for the office of a Pastor
or bishop. Wherefore if euer we
minde suche a reformation, as God
shall thereby bee glorifyed, and his
Churche edifyed, wee must vtterlye
remooue al the vnlearned pastors, as
men by no means to be tollerated to
haue any charge ouer the lords flok:
&amp; also prouide that herafter none be

receiued into that office, but such as
are sufficient for their knowledge &amp;
abilitie, in teaching to take so waightie
a charge in hand. What man hauing
but one hundreth sheep, would
make such a man shepheard or ouerseer
ouer them, as were a naturall Idiott,
or otherwise altogeather vnskilfull
or vnable to performe those
thinges that belong to a shepheard?
If no man haue so little care of
brute beastes: What brutishe negligence
is it to commit the people of
God, redeemed with the precious
bloud of Iesus Christ, to such vnskilfull
and vnsufficient Pastours, as neither
them selues know the waye of
saluation, neither are able to lead other
vnto it, whereof they are ignoraunt
them selues? If there bee no
waye of saluation but by faith,Rom. 10. 14. and
none can beleeue but such as heare
the worde of God preached: O
Lorde how miserable is the state of
many flockes in this lande, who either
seldome or neuer heare the
worde of God truely preached, and

               
                  •
               herefore know not how to beleeue
that they might be saued.
            But here it will be aunswered, that,
as it is a thing greatly to be desired:
To it is altogether vnpossible to prouide
the Church of so many learned
Pastours, as shoulde take charge of euery
seueral congregation. But hereto
we replie, that it is a thing necessarily
required at our hands by God
almighty, and therefore we must obiect
no impossibilitie, especially whē
our owne negligence, is the cause of
all the difficultie, or if you will so
call it, impossibilitie. We confesse it
will be harde at the first, but we must
doe our endeuour, and commit the
successe vnto God, and there is no
doubt but in time it will grow to an
happy ende. But when we shall be
altogether carelesse, as we haue been
of long time, and that is worse, not
acknowledging anye default in this
behalfe, (as there be that doe not):
and that is most of all, mayntaining
suche lets and hinderaunces as bee
continuall nurseies of ignoraunce

and ignorant pastors: We may bee ashamed
to alledge that difficulty, for
which none are to be blamed but we
our selues. We may be ashamed, now
that our church hath had rest and
peace, with free preaching of the gospel
this 25. or 26. years, vnder the protection
of our most gratious Queen,
to bee so vnfurnished of learned Pastors
as we are: whereas, if that diligence
had bene vsed of all partes, as
might and shoulde haue beene emploied
of all them, that vnfaignedly
seeke the kingdome of God and his
righteousnesse, almoste in halfe the
time, this necessitie might haue bene
well supplied. If we seeke experience,
what diligent &amp; carefull prouision is
able to do with the blessing of God:
looke to our neighbours &amp; brethren
in Christ, of Fraunce, whoe although
they neuer enioyed one day of such
peace, as we haue don so many years:
Yet how plentifullie they are furnished
withall kinds of Ecclesiasticall ministers,
and namely with Godly and
learned pastors, it would reioyce any

Christian heart to beholde in them,

                  •
               nd lament to see the lack in vs. But

                  •
               s for those that acknowledge no de
               
                  •
               ect
in our Church, thorow the great
multitude of ignoraunt Pastors, We
had rather at this time praie to God

                  •
               o lighten their blindenes, then by

                  •
               ny long discourse, to discouer their
palpable darkenes. Would to God
there were not more difficultie in reforming
them that maintaine suche
inconueniences, as except they bee
taken away, we shall neuer be disburdened
of the cankers of the church,
those vnlearned ministers. For while
Nonresidents and Pluralities be reteined,
we shal neuer want vnlearned
Curates, that for small stipendes will
supplie the absence of Pluralities and
Nonresidentes: Which grosse corruptions
of pastorall office, as they
maye haue some honest pretence,
so canne they haue no better pretence,
neyther are they reteyned
with a better conscience, then the
Priestes in our Sauiour Christs time,
suffered the exchaungers of mony,

Grasyers and Pulterers to make a
Burse or shambles, and a Pultrie, yea,
a denne of theeues of the Temple of
God, which was appoynted to be a
house of prayer to all nations.Math. 21. 22. Math.
21. 12. Mark. 11. 15. Iohn. 2. 14. But
especially,Mark. 11. 15. while the whole office of
a Pastour,John. 2. 14. shall be thought to consist
in reading onely a prescript number
of Psalmes and chapters of the scriptures,
with other appointed formes
of prayer: and that he maye bee allowed
as a sufficient Pastour which
doth the thinges, which a Childe of
ten yeares olde maye doe as well as
he, so long shall we neuer lacke vnlearned
Pastours, ignoraunt and vngodly
people: Symonicall and sacrilegious
patrones: So long the building
of Gods Church, shall goe but
slowly forwarde, beside other superstitious
fantasies, mayntained in the
peoples heartes, which for shortnesse
wee omitte to speake off. What
though some saye formall reading
might be borne withall for a time,
vntill the Church might bee prouided

of sufficient Pastours, which yet
is not graunted: shall it therefore
continue alwayes to the perpetuall
decay of knowledge, and hurt of the
Church of God? What greater discouragement
is there vnto Students
then to see the rewardes of learning,
bestowed as commonly vppon the
ignorant as vpon the learned? What
encouragement is it to idlenesse and
slouthfulnesse, in them that bee alreadye
in that vocation, to beholde
them that take no paine, to liue in
wealth and ease, without punishement
of their negligence?
            But here againe it will be obiected,
because there are not liuinges able
to maintaine all learned Pastors,
we must be inforced to admitte manie
ignoraunt ministers. But againe
we aunswere, it is our part, not onely
to prouide learned Pastours: but also
liuinges sufficient to maintayne
them, vppon the necessitie of Gods
commaundement.Gal. 6. 6. 
               Let him that is instructed
in the worde (sayth Saint Paul)
minister to him,
               1. Cor. 9. 7. 
               that doth instruct him in

all good thinges. Be not deceaued for God
is not mocked.
               Gal. 6. 6. 7. By which saying the Apostle
confuteth all vaine excuses,
which manie are wonte to alleadge,
why they would contribute nothing
to the maintenance of their Pastors:
al which he affirmeth to be vain, because
they haue to do with God, and
not with men onely: For here is not
regarded the liuing of a man, but
howe much they esteeme Christ and
the Gospell of God. Therefore except
we will mocke God to his face,
Let vs obiect nothing to testifie such
shamefull ingratitude, that we would
doubt, how they should be prouided
of bodely foode, of whom we receiue
the foode of our souls, as though we
coulde not afford them an earthely
recompence, of whome wee receiue
heaunely benefits. If nothing had
bene before time allotted, towards
the liuing of the Pastors; Yet were
vvee bounde in payne of damnation,
to prouide sufficient for them;
and nowe there is somewhat towardes
a liuing where there is least,

and in all places sufficient, if it
were well disposed: Why should we
obiect necessity through lacke of

                  •
               iuinges to reteine idols in steede
of true Pastors? Looke once againe
into Fraunce (for examples
moue muche) and beholde the
Churches there impouerished, and
spoiled with long warres, persecution
&amp; vnquietnes. They haue neither
Byshoppricks, Deaneries, Prebends
nor benefices to bestow on their
Pastors, and yet minister vnto them
all things necessarie for an honest
sober life: And shall wee that haue
all this while liued in peace, and
prosperitie, vnder a godly and religious
Princesse, hauing all these
helpes, thincke it is impossible, by
disposition of godly and wise gouernours,
to appoint a sufficient portion
for so manie learned Pastors as are
necessarie for our Churches? There
is none excuse therefore to be admitted,
but that wee must endeuour
to the vttermost of our power
that euery seuerall congregation,

Church or parrishe be prouided of a
learned Pastour. For vnskilful sheepheardes
haue beene to long thrust
vppon vs, to the great dishonour of
God and defacing of the Gospell of
Christe. We haue hitherto taken
vpon vs without warraunt of Gods
worde, to allow such for Pastours of
mens soules, whom no carefull owner
of Cattell, woulde make ouerseer
of his sheepes bodyes. Which
thing almightye God hath alwayes
detested, and signified his mislyking
by diuers testimonies, both of the
olde and newe Testament. Therefore
he sayeth by the Prophet Esaye,
complayning of the vnlearned Pastours
of Israell, which was the onelye
cause of their affliction and miseries.
Their watchmen are all blinde,
they haue no knowledge,
               Esai. 56. 10. 11. 12. 
               they cannot barke,
they lye and sleepe and delight in sleeping,
and these greedie dogges can neuer haue
ynough, and these sheepheardes cannot vnderstande,
for they all looke to their owne
way, euery one for his aduantage and for
his owne purpose. Come I will bring wine,

and we wil fill our selues with strong drink,
and to morrowe shall bee as, this day, and
much more aboundant. If the Prophet
had liued in these our days, might
he not haue spoken the same more
truely of many Shiers in Englande?
We see therefore that blinde watchmen,
and ignoraunt dumbe Dogges,
and idle greedie Curres and vnlearned
sheepheardes that serue for nothing,
but to fill their owne purses,
or their paunches, by the testimonie
of God his spirite, are denied to be
meet Pastours of the people of God.
The prophet Ezechiell also inueigheth
at large, against the vnfeeding
sheepheardes of Israell:Eze. 34. 2. 3. 4 saying (Woe)
be vnto the sheepheardes of Israell which
feede them selues: shoulde not the sheepeheardes
feede the flockes? Yee eate the fat
and you cloth you with the wooll: yee kill
them that are fedde, but yee feede not the
sheepe. The weake haue yee not strengthened,
the sicke haue yee not healed, neither
haue yee bound vp the broken, nor brought
againe that which was driuen awaye, neither
haue yee sought that which was lost,

&amp;c. throughout the whole Chapter.
When feeding of Gods sheepe is a
matter of so great importaunce, and
consisteth of so many partes, which
the Prophet hath heere described,
how shoulde we admit them whome
God reiecteth? which being ignoraunt
and vnlearned, knowe nothing
at all, and therefore nothing can do
that appertaineth to this charge, or
any part thereof. Vndoubtedly the
retaining of such, is a manifest token
of the vengeance of God against vs,
for so he threatneth by the Prophet
Zachary:
               Zac. 15. 16. 16 his wordes are these. And
the Lorde sayde vnto me: Take to thee yet
the Instrumentes of a foolish Sheepheard,
for loe, I will rayse vp a Sheapheard in the
Lande, which shall not looke for the thinge
that is lost, nor seeke the tender Lambes,
nor heale that is hurt: nor feed that which
standeth vp, but he shall eat the flesh of the
fat, &amp; tear their hooues in peeces. O Idole
sheaphearde that leaueth the flocke, the
Sworde shall bee vppon his arme, and vpon
his right eye: his arme shall be cleane
dried vp, and his right eye shall bee vtterly

darkened.
            
            Now, seeing we are taught by these
wordes of the Lord God, that it is a
greate and horrible plague, to haue
the church of God encumbred with
such foolish and Idole Sheapheards:
Let vs study to remoue such plagues
from the flocke of Christe, vvhose
armes are cleane dried vp that they
haue no force, and their eyes vtterly
darkned, that they haue no skill, so
that they are not able to perfourme
those duties, which pertaine to a
vvise and faythfull Sheaphearde, excepte
wee will betraye the Sheepe
of Christe, into the mouthes of rauenous
Wolues, and speciallye into
the teethe of that greate ramping
Lyon the deuill,1. Pet. 1. 8. who neuer ceaseth
going aboute to seeke whome
hee may deuoure for his pray. For
what doe these readinge Ministers
differ from those Idole Sheapheards,
which God in his vengeance threatneth
to sende for the ingratitude of
the people?
            
               
It wil be answered (no doubt) that
to supplie their ignorance, there are
added to their appointed seruice, manie
Godly &amp; learned homilies, which
if they read with their seruice, there
is not so great neede of Preaching, &amp;
interpretation of the scriptures. We
will derogate nothing here from the
dignitie of those homilies: we will
not accuse here the vnsensible reading
of vnlearned ministers, neither
yet the vnreuerent contempt of the
ignoraunt hearers; but, which all
godly and wise men must needs confesse,
those exhortations that are not
applied, to the proper circumstances
of times, places, persons and occasions,
are of small power to perswade
any man, and least of all the
ignoraunt people, Let long experience
the Mystresse of fooles teach vs,
if knowledge the instructer of wise
men cannot mooue vs. Howe many
papists conuerted? How many ignoraunt
instructed? How many wicked
reformed, are ye able to shew by this
ignoraunt and vnlearned ministery,

with all the helpes of reading of for
               
                  •
               all
prayers and homilies, without

                  •
               eaching and applying the Scrip
               
                  ••
               res
to the proper circumstaunces

                  •
               efore rehearsed? Againe, who seeth

                  •
               ot but he that is so blinde, that he

                  •
               ill see nothing, that these partes of

                  •
               true Pastors duetie, which both the

                  •
               rophetes, Ezechiel and Zachary re
               
                  •
               earse,
namely, to strengthen the

                  •
               eake, to heale the sicke, to bind the

                  •
               roken, to seeke the lost, to bring

                  •
               ome that is carried away, to cherish

                  •
               e yong Lambs, to feede the strong

                  •
               eepe. &amp;c. cannot be performed of

                  •
               y man by such means as these, but

                  •
               nely by such one, as is a Godly and

                  •
               arned shepheard. Wherefore, these

                  •
               oore helpes of prescript forme of

                  •
               ading of praiers, of Homilies, and

                  •
               ch like, when they are alleadged to
maintaine the ignorance of vnskilful

                  •
               astors, are called no better, by the

                  •
               dgement of God, but the instru
               
                  •
               entes
of foolish and idole sheap
               
                  •
               eardes,
which haue a certaine pre
               
                  ••
               nce
of pastorall office, but in effect

are altogether vnmeet for the same.
Euen as Idiots and Idolles are good
for nothing, but able to doe much
hurt, concerning whom our sauiour
Christ pronounceth this feareful sentence.Math. 15. 14.
               If the blind lead the blind, they shal
both fall into the pit. How long therefore
shal wee suffer the blinde to lead the
blind, to the destruction of both? Let
vs therfore now at the lēgth, remoue
these blind guides, and place in their
steeds faithfull ouerseers, that may
lead the flock of Christ into the way
of saluation. The ministers of the
church are the salt of the earth.Math. 5. 13. 
               If the
salt be vnsauory, wherwith shall it be seasoned,
It is good for nothing but to bee cast
out, and troden downe of mens feete. Let
vs not therfore seek politike shifts to
maintain the vnsauory salt, which our
Sauiour Christe pronounceth to bee
good for nothing but to be cast out.
            By these and many other testimonies
of the scripture, it is as cleere as
the Sunne at Noone dayes, that it
is the office and duetie of a Pastor,
both to be able and willing to teach

his flocke, and that no ignorant and
vnlearned person is to bee admitted
to that charge, or reteined, if hee bee

                  •
               rept in, no more then a blind mā is
to be suffred in an office, which must
be executed only with the sight: or a
Humbe Dog to giue warning which
cannot barke: or an Idol to haue the
place of a man, or a fool of a wise mā
or a Wolfe of a Sheapheard, or darknesse
in steede of light, or Salt that is
vnsauory, to season withal. But while
we intreat of teaching, to be the duty
of a pastor, we do not only meane
publike preaching, when the cōgregation
is assembled, but also priuate
exhortation, reprehēsion, consolatiō,
of euery particular person within his
charge, so often as need shall require.
And that this also is the duetye of a
faithful Bishop, S. Paule testifieth, setting
before the elders of the church,
of Ephesus the example of his diligēce
which he wold haue thē to folow.Acts. 20. 18. 19. 20. 
               You
know (saith hee) from the first day that I
came into Asia, after what manner I haue
bin with you at al seasons, seruing the Lord

withall modesty, &amp;c. And how I kept back
nothing that was profitable, but haue shewed
you, and taught you, both openly, and
throughout euery house. By vvhich it
is manifest, that the Pastor must not
onely teache al his flocke openly:
but also he must instruct euery familie
priuatelie, vvhersoeuer hee shal see
it to be needfull or expedient, which
duty cannot bee accomplished by a
reading Minister. Also in the 26. vers.
of the same Chapiter, hee commendeth
vnto the Elders, a general care
of the vvhole flocke.Acts. 20. 26. 
               Take heede to
your selues (sayth hee) and to the whole
flocke. Which care can not be wel, or
at al vndertaken, except they be diligent
to teach, both al and euerie one
of their flocke, as neede shal require.
Which thing also hee willeth them
once againe to obserue in his example,
verse. 31. saying: Therefore watch
yee,
               Acts. 20. 31. 
               remembring that by the space of three
yeeres, I ceassed not night and day, exhorting
euery one of you. By these testimonies
it is euident to see, what diligence
the holy Ghoste requireth of

Pastors in teaching, both publikely
and priuately: as well generallye all
their flocke, as particularlye euerye
one of them. Hee therefore that is
vnapt to execute this parte of a Pastors
duety, is altogether vnmeete, to
whome gouernance of the flocke of
God, shoule be committed. In temporal
affayres, no man vvil commit
the least charge that can bee, to such
persons as he knoweth to be altogether
vnmeete, or vnable to aunswere
vnto the charge: And shall we continue
as we haue done hitherto, to put
thē in trust with the greatest charge
that can be, the saluation of so many
thousande soules redeemed with the
bloud of Christe, whome wee knowe
certainely to be able to doe, no parte
of a Pastours duety sufficiently? God
forbid that we should still continue,
so lightly to esteeme so waightye a
matter, as though we accounted the
bloud of Christ, by which we are sanctified,
to be prophane, and woulde
contumeliously withstande the spirit
of God.
            
               
But necessitie (you wil answere) hath
no lawe. This necesity we haue aunswered
before, to consist in 2. points:
in lack of liuings, and lack of learned
men. The first we haue shewed ought
to be no lette, no not of an howre, if
the other wante, coulde so soone bee
supplied. And both must of necessity
bee prouided for in time, or else wee
testify before God and his holy Angels,
that they which neglect or with
stand this prouision, shal be guilty of
the bloude of all them, that peris
                  •
               e
through the desaulte of teaching, in
the whole realm. The lack of liuings
may be supplied, either by restoring
the sacriledges of Abbies, as Impropriations
of benefices. &amp;c. or by deuiding
the supersluities of some places
that haue to muche, vnto them
that haue too little, or by any other
godly meanes, that may bee thought
meet to these godly and wise gouernors,
that by duty ought, and by authority
may do it. The lacke of learned
preachers, must be so farre forth
supplied, as it maye presentlye, by encouraging

and exhorting so many as
are able, to take that charge in hand,
by ouerseeing the Readers &amp; schollers
in diuinity in the Vniuersities, to
doe their duties, the one in teaching
purely, the other in learning diligētly:
by thrusting out these vnprofitable
heades of Colledges, and other
drone Bees, which either are vnable
or vnwilling to set forward the study
of diuinity in their seuerall huoses, &amp;
placing diligent and learned gouernors
&amp; students in their places, &amp; by
other good means reforming vniuer
sities, by erecting of doctors &amp; teachers,
in as many places as may be: by
cōpelling the vnlearned ministers, in
whome is any towardnes to become
schollers in diuinity, with some allow
aunce of liuing if they bee willing to
study, or else to sende thē frō whence
they came, to get their liuinges with
sweate of their brows: and especially
cōsidering the gretnes of the haruest
&amp; fewnes of the laborers, by praying
earnestly the Lord of the haruest in
this great necessity of ours,Math. 9. 38. to thrust

foorth labourers into his Haruest.
And in the meane time till God shal
blesse vs with a sufficient number of
learned pastors, to take some extraordinarie
and temporall order for
ouerseeing the Churches, that although
they can not bee all sufficientlie
instructed and gouerned: yet
so many shall not be altogether destitute,
of al knowledge and spiritual
gouernment, as ther are now in this
most corrupt state of the Church, in
which we haue hitherto continued.
If any man thinke this is ouer harde
to be brought to passe, let him consider
that there was neuer worke of
more difficulty, then to build vp the
Church of God: so that the necessity
and commodity of the work, should
cause vs to stay nothing at the difficultie
thereof. For with our faithfull
endeuor, we shall not want the mighty
assistance of God, who will blesse
our Godly labours, with greater successe,
then we can looke for. If God
therefore will graunt that these and
such like meanes may take place, by

the high authority of our dread soueraigne
the Queenes Maiesty, and
continue this comfortable peace,
which we enioy, vnder her most gratious
gouernment, wee dare ieopard
oure liues, that in lesse then halfe
the time, that is already prosperously
passed, of her Maiesties moste honourable
and glorious reigne, the
necessity of learned pastors shall bee
so well supplied, as wee shall haue no
great cause to complaine for lacke
of them, if we may vse like diligence
to continue them: if not, we wil spēd
the rest of oure life in mourning, &amp;
expectation of the heauy vengeance
of God, which must needes fall vpon
vs, for this manifest contempt of his
expresse commaundement, aud neglect
of increasing the glorious kingdome
of our Sauiour Christe. In the
meane time, we may boldly say with
the Apostle. Act. 20.Actes. 20. 26. 27. 
               We testify vnto you
this day, that we are cleane from the bloud
of you all, for we haue not failed to shew you
the whole Counsell of God, concerning the
regiment of his Church.
            
            
               
Hitherto wee haue somewhat at
large set foorth, the principall parte
of a Pastors office, which is to preach
the word of God, and to instruct the
people committed to his charge in
the same. Here followeth now in the
second part of his duety, which consisteth
in right administration of the
Sacramentes of God. For seeing it
hath pleased God to adde such outwarde
signes to be helpes of our infirmitie,
as seales for confirmation of
his promises, vttered by his worde
Rom. 4. 11. He hath appoynted ministers
of the same,Rom. 4. 11. to deliuer them
vnto his people. Math. 28. 19.Math. 28. 19. Luke.
22. 19. For no man may take vppon
him any office in the Church,Luke. 22. 19. but he
that is called of God, as was Aaron.
Heb. 3. 4.Heb. 3. 4. Seeing therefore that God
hath giuen some to bee Pastours in
his Church. Ephes. 4. 11.Ephes. 4. 11. And it is
the duetie of Pastours to feede the
flocke of God committed to their
charge, with all maner of spirituall
pasture of their soules, appoynted by
God. 1. Cor. 4. 1.1. Cor. 4. 1. And that the Sacramentes

are a part of this spiritual
food, it is manifest that it belongeth
to the dutie of Pastors, to administer
the holy Sacramentes: and that the
Sacramentes appertaine to the doctrine
and worde of God, it is euident,
that whome God hath instituted
to be minister of the worde, him
also hath he made to be minister of
the Sacramentes: and as the Sacramentes
are compared by the holye
Ghost vnto seales: and the worde or
promise of God vnto writinges: so
it appertaineth to him to deliuer the
seale, which deliuereth the writings.
For, as the seale hath alwayes relation
vnto the writinges: so haue the
Sacramentes vnto the word of God.
By this it appeareth, that as it is the
duetie of euerye Pastour to administer
the Sacramentes of Christe: so
this office appertayneth to none, but
to those which are ministers of the
worde. Our Sauiour Christ authorizing
his Apostles to Baptize all
Nations, sayeth: Goe yee foorth and
teache all Nations,
               Math. 28. 19. 
               baptizing them

in the name of the father, the sonne and
the Ghoste, teaching them to obserue all
thinges, that I haue commaunded you.
Likewise to the same effect, Goe yee
foorth into the whole worlde,
               Mark. 16. 15. 
               and preache
the Gospell to euery creature, he that shall
beleeue and is baptized shall be saued. &amp;c.
Also instituting his holy supper, hee
sayde:Luke. 2
                     •
                  
                  ▪ 19. 
               Doe this in remembraunce of me.
Which remembrance Saint Paul declareth,
that it ought to bee celebrated,
by preaching of the Lords death.
So often (saith he) as you shall eate of tbis
Bread,
               1. Cor. 24. 
               and drinke of this Cup, you shal shew
foorth the Lords death vntill he come. By
these testimonies it is euidēt, that the
administratiō of the sacramēts ought
to bee committed to none, but vnto
such as are Preachers of the worde,
that are able to teach them that they
baptise, that are able to preache the
mystery of Christs death to them, to
whom they doe deliuer the outward
signe thereof. Howe intollerable an
abuse then is it, of the sacraments of
the Lord, to commit the administration
of them to those men, that are

not able to expounde the mystery of
them. And seeing the elementes of
the worlde, of which the outwarde

                  •
               art of the sacramentes is taken, bee
leade and beggerly of themselues,
except they bee animated and enti
               
                  •
               hed
with the promise and worde of
God, which is the life of the Sacramentes:
what can it bee better then

                  •
               acriledge to seperate the ministratition
of preaching of the worde from
the sacramentes? And forasmuch as
the spirite of God, compareth the
Sacraments to seales that are added,
for confirmation of writinges; wee
knowe well that a worde or writing,
may be auailable without a seale, but

                  •
               euer a seale without a writing.
            Therefore in this behalfe we haue

                  •
               ad greate defaulte, so long time to

                  •
               ommit the administration of the
Sacramentes to those men, who not
onely haue beene knowne to be vnable,
but also haue beene forbidden
to preach the word. And that which
is more strange, to be suffered in this
cleare light of the Gospel, to permit

the ministration of baptisme, not only
to ignorante men, but also to women
which haue no voyce to speake
in the congregation. 1. Cor. 14. 34.1. Cor. 14. 34. &amp;
1. Tim. 2. 11.Tim. 2. 11. and that in priuate places,
but in case (they say) of necessity,
as though there were such necessity
of the outward signe, when it cannot
bee ministred according to the institution
of Christ, which is nothing els
but to affirme with the Papistes, that
Sacraments confer grace of the work
wrought: and that the sacrament of
baptisme, is a sacrament of such necessity,
that whosoeuer is not dipped
in water, must be eternally condemned.
Which hereticall opinion, as we
haue hissed out in our profession and
preaching, so is it a great shame for
vs to maintain by such corrupt vsage
of Christes holy sacramentes. Let vs
therefore reteine this principle, that
the administration of the sacraments
is a part of the pastors duety: for although
the office of preaching bee
more excellent, then of ministration
of the sacraments, as S. Paul speaketh

comparatiuely. Christ sent me not to
baptize but to preach. 1. Cor. 1. 17.1. Cor. 1. 17. Yet
they are of such affinitie, that the accessory
cannot be seperated from the
principall thereof. For where is no
preacher of the worde, ther ought to
be no minister of the Sacramentes.
Furthermore, it pertaineth to the dutie
of the pastor, to make prayers: as
Act. 16. 16.Act. 16. 16. not onely priuate, as all
men are bound to doe, but also publike
prayers in the name of the whol
Church. Act. 6. 4. 1. Timot. 2. 1. being
the mouth thereof.Acts. 6. 4. For whereas the
spirit of God,Tim. 2. 1. commandeth al things
to be done in decent and comely order,1. Cor. 14. 16.
and forbiddeth all confusion and
disorder. As it were great confusiō &amp;
vncomelines, for euery man to make
his seuerall praiers in the publike assemblies:
so is it orderly for one to
pronounce the praier in the name of
the rest, and the rest to pray with him
in silence, &amp; to answer Amē. It is also
decēt that he which is the shepherd,1. Cor. 14 40.
should go before the sheep in praier,
&amp; the sheepe to follow him in lifting

vp of their harts in mutuall consent.
Moreouer for asmuch as preaching
and administration of the sacramēts,
ought not to bee vsed without publique
prayers: as it is the Pastors office
to preache, and minister the Sacraments:
so is it his duety also to go
before his flocke in publique prayers.
            But heere we haue to obserue two
things: the first, that as it perteineth
to the Pastor to conceiue publique
praiers: so it is the duty of the whole
Church, in the name of the whole
Church, to ioyne in hart with the pastor
in the same praiers, that they
knowing and vnderstanding what he
hath praied, may at the end giue ther
consent by answering Amen.1. Cor. 14. 16 Wherin
their is great abuse in our Churches.
For, as though it weare notinough,
to keepe out preaching by
longe prescribed formes of praier:
these praiers are so pronounced by
the minister, that a great number, &amp;
some not of the worst disposed people,
thinck, it perteineth not to them,

to giue eare or consent of mind vnto
them. We speake not here of such
insensible Readers, whose voyce eyther
cannot be heard, or else cannot
be vnderstood, wherof there be great
numbers: nor of the vnfit place prescribed
for the ministers, standing at
prayer in the east ende of the house,
whē the simple people shal stand oftētimes
40. or 50. yards of in the west
ende: or of the confusion of voyces
whilest all speake at once: besides
scrines of roode-lofts, Organe lofts,
Idoll cages, otherwise called Chauntrie
Chappelles, and high pewes betweene
them: which although they
do manifestly hinder edifycation, yet
may they not be remooued in many
places, for defacing the beauty of the
materiall houses, whereas S. Paule so
much estemeth the building of gods
spirituall house, that he commaundeth
the glorious giftes of the holye
Ghost to cease in the congregation,1. Cor. 14. 28.
when they do not helpe to edification.
But we speake of this that a great
multitude thinke they haue wel serued

God: if they haue been present
at common prayers, or anye part of
them, as they were wont to thinke in
popery, although they bee neuer so
vainly occupyed in the Church, some
in walking, some in talking, in gathering
of money, not onely for the
poore, but for other contributions,
&amp;c. And they that thinke they doe
best, are occupyed in their priuate
praiers, or in reading of books, while
their minister pronounceth publique
praiers.
            Thus as preaching is neglected, vppon
colour of publique prayers: So
publique prayers by priuate exercises,
are made altogether vnprofitable
to a great number. For who knoweth
the right vse of publique prayer,
but they that are taught by the word
of God. Let vs therfore establish publique
preaching, and publique prayers
will follow of necessitie. But if
we continue to vpholde formal praiers,
that preaching bee neglected, it
will come to passe, that neither shall
be regarded. For what did thrust

out preaching from the Romishe
Church, but long prescript formes of
reading, of singing, of praying: so that
their ordinarye was ynough, and to
much to occupye the whole daye,
though there were no sermon, wheras
contrariwise there woulde be no
ordinarie publique prayer without
preaching. Which terrible example
of the practize of Sathan in the man
of sinne, shoulde make vs afrayde to
giue any like occasion of such inconuenience
hereafter to come. For is
not this opinion already growen into
a great manye mens heades, that
the seruice maye not giue place to a
sermon, no though the time be not
sufficient for both? And are ther not
many that had much rather heare a
chaunted Mattens and Euensong,
then a godly &amp; learned sermon? Yea
they frequent the one, and refuse the
other. Let Cathedral Churches, &amp;c.
be an example, where you shall see a
great number, that tarrye while the
seruice is songe, but depart so soone
as the Sermon beginneth.
            
               
While the Organes pipe, some are
drawen with the sweetnes of musike
to come vp, but while the preacher
cryeth out, continue beneath and in
laughter or brawling, be lowder then
he oftentimes. So, that which was
wont to be sayd of the Masse, Missa
non mordet, the masse was a gentle
beast, and did bite no man, and therfore
was so well beloued of manye,
may rightly be verified of our ordinary
seruice. For therefore a great
number can so well away with it, because
it doth not sharpely reprooue
them of theire sinnes, nor disclose
the secreates of their heartes, but
that they maye continue still in all
kinde of voluptuousnes, and al other
kind of wickednes. Wheras by preaching,
their conscience is gauled, ther
wickednes and hipocrisy discouered,
their damnation threatned, they are
called to repentaunce and forsaking
of their pleasant sinnes, and to holynesse
and innocencie of life. So that
if there be any sparke of the feare of
God in them, hearing preaching, so

often as they vse to heare seruice,
they will fall downe on their faces &amp;
worship God, acknowledging the
great power of God in his ministers.
1. Cor. 14. 15.1. Cor. 14. 15 But that they cannot
away with all, beeing like vnto Felix
the liefetenaunt of the Romanes in
Iewrie: Who when he heard Paule a
poore prysoner that stoode before
him bound in chaines, preaching of
righteousnes, of temperaunce, and of
the iudgement to come, he was wearie
of him because he was a great oppressour,
and an intemperate person,
and therfore feared the iudgment of
God for his sinne, which he purposed
not to forsake. Such is the maiestie
of Gods word, when it is preached,
that either it boweth or breaketh
the wicked in pieces. God grant
therefore that in steede of ordinarie
formes of praiers, we may haue preaching
in all places.
            The seconde thing that we haue to
obserue is this, that although we
make it the dutie of the Pastour, to
pray in the name of the whole congregation,

yet we doe not so meane,
but that the whole congregatiō with
one heart,1 Cor. 14. 15 &amp; 26. and with one voyce maye
praise God, with singing of Psalmes,
all at once. For this custome hath
continued in the church from the beginning,
that the congregation haue
praised God with Psalmes singing altogeather.
And these three partes of
a pastors dutie, to preach, to minister
the sacramentes, and to praye, are so
necessarilye requyred of him in the
word of God, as no man may rightly
execute the office of a Pastor, but he
that performeth al these, each one in
their due time. And to this part of
prayer, maye be referred the blessing
of marriages, not of necessitie, but of
an auncient vse of the Church. Furthermore,
in those thinges that are
necessarie partes of the Pastours office,
the Church hath authoritie to
dispose them. as touching the circumstaunces,
for order and comelynesse
sake: but cheefely for edification.
As the dayes and times of preaching
and administring the Sacramentes,

the places meet for the same,
&amp; for publique praiers: also the form
and maner of vsing those thinges, so
that all things be don comely and agreeably
to order, but especially that
in all things, principall regarde be had
to edification, which S. Paule so often
and so precisely vrgeth in the 14. chapiter
of the 1. Cor. For therfore ought
our assemblies and comminges together
to serue, that therefore we maye
be better, that we may be taught, that
we may be edified. 1. Cor. 11. 17. 1.
Cor. 14. 23. 24. 25. 26. 31.1. Cor. 11. 17. 1. Cor. 14. 23. 24. 25. 26. 31. And therefore
we haue great maruell that some
are so precise in vrging ceremonies, as
many thinke much hindering edification,
but as moste men confesse, nothing
profiting to edifycation, hauing
alwayes in their mouth, that
sentence of Saint Paule. 1. Corinth.
14. 40.1. Cor. 14. 40 
               Let all thinges bee done decently,
and according to an order, And doe so
little remember that the Apostle in
that long Chapiter, laboureth altogether
to driue al things to edificatiō,
or els to driue thē out of the church.

As he saith of him that hath the gift
of tongues, being of it selfe an excellente
and comely gifte of the holye
ghost, and being vsed orderly of one
or two by course, with an interpreter,
mighte doe muche good in the
Church.
            But if there be none interpreter
(saith he) Let him holde his peace in
the congregation. 1. Cor. 14. 28.1. Cor. 14. 28. The
vncomlinesse that Saint Paule reproueth,
was, that women shold preach
in the Church, as ver. 30. 35. The disorder,
that those giftes which serued
leaste for edifying, were preferred
before them that serued moste for
edifying, as tongs before prophecie.
By which it is euident that S. Paules
words are wrested of some, clean contrary
to his meaning, to make him a
Patron of idle, if not hurtful ceremonies,
maintained more vpon wil then
reason, or graunted of Gods worde,
vnder the colour of order and decency,
not onely with neglect, but also
with great hinderance of Gods building,
by spoyling the Churche of so

many learned pastoures. There are
besides these thinges, certaine other
matters: as confirmation, Churching
of women, buriall of the deade,
thoughte to belonge to the office
of a Byshoppe or Pastour. Whereof
the firste two are meere deuises of
men, and ought to haue no place
in the Churche of Christe. The
other, albeit it bee to bee retayned
with a certayne honestye, yet it is
not to bee tied to the proper office
of a Pastour. And as for Confirmation,
it oughte therefore to be shut
oute, and haue no place in the
church of God, as wel because it displaced
Catechising, and broughte
in steede thereof vayne toyes, and
Childishe ceremonies to the greate
hurte of the Churche; as for that
also it derogateth muche from the
dignitye of Baptisme, the sacrament
of the Lorde, and is extolled aboue
it, being a deuise of man, and is pretended
to bee a signe to certify the
Children of the fauoure and gratious
goodnesse of GOD, towardes

them, falsely grounded vpon the example
of the Apostles: Whereas the
ministration of baptisme, is permitted
to euery hedge-priest, minister
and Deacon.
            And as for Churching of Women,
because it sauoureth of the Iewish
purification, and of Popish institution,
it ought altogether to bee
omitted, for it breedeth and nourisheth
many superstitious opinions
in the simple peoples hearts: as, that
the woman which hath born a child,
is vncleane or vnholy: whereas the
Apostle pronounceth, that Godlye
women are sanctified and saued by
bearing of Children. 1. Timoth. 2.
15.1. Tim. 2. 15. that it is vnlawfull for her, for any
necessity, to go out of her doores,
before she bee Churched: that this
churching is a necessarye part of the
Pastors office, that shee must weare a
white raile ouer her head, when she
goeth to Churche by the Midwife,
waighted Home with the Parishe
Clearke, with diuers suche like Bables,
vvhiche in a vvell refourmed

Churche, are not to bee suffered.
As for the buriall of the deade, because
Sathan tooke occasion vppon
Ceremonies appointed therunto, to
sowe the seede of manye Herisies in
the Church, as prayers for the dead,
oblations for the deade, Purgatory,
&amp;c. Also many superstitions, as hallowing
of Churcbyardes, distinction
of Burialls, as some in the Chauncel,
some in the Churche, and some in
the Church-yardes: some with more
pompe, as singing, ringing, &amp;c. some
with lesse, burying towards the East,
lightes and holy water bestowed vpon
the dead, &amp;c. It is thought good,
to the best and right reformed churches,
to burye their deade reuerently,
without any ceremonies of praying
or preaching at them, because
experience hath taught them, what
inconuenience may grow therof▪ by
exāple of that which hath bin before
And as they are not to be excused, if
any for small tri
                  ••
               es only, raise vp h
                  •
               t
contentions: so they haue much to
aunswere before God, that suffer the

people of God to lacke the onelye
foode of their souls for such humain
constitutions. But to conclude, it is
the duty of euery true Pastor, to obserue
those thinges that are concluded
by the lawfull authoritye of the
church, concerning ceremonial matters,
for order and comlinesse sake,
and for edification, and not to controll
publique order,Acts. 28. 29. by his priuate
iudgement, but vpon great &amp; waighty
causes. Wee haue hitherto intreated
of the proper dutye of a Pastour
himselfe: nowe it followeth, that we
likewise set foorth his authoritye
in common gouernment with the
Elders. But least any man shoulde
mistake that, which wee purpose to
say of his authority, wee haue neede
to expresse what wee meane by this
worde authoritye. For euen those
thinges that wee haue shewed before
to bee the duetye of a Pastor,
may also bee called his authority, as
to preach and teach, wherein is included
his authoritye to forgiue
and retaine sinnes: also his authoritye

to minister the Sacramentes,
and to doe other thinges in the
Churche, which none may doe but
hee. But in this place, wee vnderstande
authority, for power of gouernment
in the Church. Whereof
the Apostle speaketh,1. Cor. 12. 28. that it is one
of the graces and giftes of GOD
necessarye for the building of his
Church. This authority of regiment,
we haue declared that it ought not
to be a Lordly ruling,1. Pet. 5. 3. neither ouer
their flocke:Luke. 23. 26. nor yet ouer their fellowe
seruauntes and brethren: and
leaste of all, that they ought to haue
dominion or Lordship ouer the faith
of the Church.2. Cor. 1. 14. In all these the man
of sinne hath exalted him selfe, contrary
to the worde of God: So that
he would be head of all the Church,Hierarchia.
Byshop of all Byshops, and haue authoritye
to make nevve Articles of
Faythe. Whose vntollerable presumption,
as we haue long since banished
out of this Lande: so we wish
that no steppes of such pride and arrogancy,
might be left behind him:

namely, that no elder or minister of
the Church, shoulde challendge vnto
himselfe, or accept it, if it were offred
vnto him, any other authority, then
that is allowed by the spirit of God:
but cheefly to beware that hee vsurp
no authority which is forbidden by
the word of God. For wherefore do
wee de
                  •
               est the Pope and his vsurped
supremacy, but bicau•se he arrogateth
the same vnto himself, not only with
out the warrant of Gods worde, but
also cleane contrarye to the same?
Now, if the same reasons &amp; authorities
that haue banished the Pope, do
serue to condemn all other vsurped
authoritye, that is practised in the
Church: Why shoulde not all such vsurped
authority be banished as well
as the Pope? We can alledge against
the Pope and rightly, that which S.
Ioh. Baptist did answere to his disciples.
No man can take vnto himself any
thing, except it be giuen him from Heauen.
Ioh. 3. 27.Iohn. 3. 27. And that saying of the
Apostle to the Hebrewes:Heb. 5. 4. 
               No man
may take vpō him any honor (in the church

of God) but he that is called of God, as
was Aaron. Insomuch that Christe
himselfe, did not giue himselfe to be
an high Priest, but he that saide vnto
him. Thou art my Sonne, this day I haue
begotten thee. Hee sayth in another
place,Philip. 2. 6. 
               Thou art a priest for euer after the
order of Melchisedec. Now seeing these
rules are so generall, that the Sonne
of God him selfe, was not exempted
from them, but shewed foorth
the decree, wherein he was authorized:
By what rule cā any man reteine
that authority in the church of god,
which is not called thereto by the
worde of God? Likewise we can alledge
again, against the supremacie
of the Pope, to proue that Peter was
not superiour to the other Apostles,
that which our sauiour Christ sayeth
to his Apostles,Luke. 22. 26. Luk. 22. 26. and Mat.
20. 25. Mark. 10. 42. It shall not be so
among you,
               Math. 20. 25 
               but he that is greatest amongst
you,
               Mark. 10. 42. 
               shall be as the yongest, and he that ruleth,
as he that serueth. And Mat. 23. 8.Math. 23. 8.
               You haue but one master, which is Christ,

and all you are brethren. If these places
prooue, that the Pope ought not to
bee aboue other ministers of the
church: Why doe they not likewise
proue, that the Ministers are equal
among themselues? And for the most
part, all those arguments and authorities
of Scripture, that are vsed
to confute the vsurped authoritie of
the pope, are of as great force aganst
all other vsurped authorities of one
pastor ouer an other. Therfore while
we intreate of the authoritie of the
pastors, we must take heede that we
open not a window to popish tyrannie,
in steede of pastorall authoritye,
&amp; that we enlarge not the bounds of
authoritye, without the boundes of
the Scripture. Wherefore while wee
search the Scripture, the onelye rule
whereby the Church of God oughte
to be gouerned, we finde that in regiment
&amp; gouernāce of the church,
the pastor, bishop or elder, hath none
authority by himself, seperated from
other. For in the Church, ther ought
to be no monarchy or sole absolute

gouernment, but that is referred peculiarly
to our sauiour Christe only,
2. Tim. 6. 7. Iude. 4.2. Tim. 6. 15. And that regimente,
which hee hath left vnto his
Church, is a consent of his houshold
seruaunts, to do all things according
to his prescription, as he witnesseth,
Math. 18. 19.Math. 18. 19. 
               If two of you consent vpon
earth vppon any matter, what soeuer ye
shall aske, it shall bee graunted to you of my
Father, which is in Heauen: For wheresoeuer
two or three bee gathered together in
my name, there am I in the middest of
them. Seeing therefore that our Sauiour
Christe, hath neither authorized
nor promised to blesse anye other
forme of regiment, then that which
consisteth of the consent, and gathering
together of his Seruauntes in
his name: wee holde vs content with
this simplicity, and therefore we are
bolde to say, that the authoritye of
a Pastour in publique Regiment or
Discipline, seperate from others, is
nothing at all.
            Let vs then see, what is his authority
ioined with others, and first, who

are so ioyned in Commission with
him, that without their consent hee
can do nothing. We say therefore,
that the authority of Christ, is left
vnto his whole Church, and so to euery
church, that none may challēge
Episcopall or Metropoliticall authority,
as it is with vs at this day ouer
other, without greate tyrannye and
manifest iniury. For, seeing our Sauiour
Christe, promised his presence
and authority to euery Churche indifferentlye,
Math. 18. 19. 20:Math. 18. 19. 20. None
may challenge any such prerogatiue
a
                  •
               ore other: but as the Churches
are limitted out for order &amp; conueniency,
so is euery one of them of
like authority in it self: but because
they make al but one church, &amp; one
body of Christ, therefore there is but
one authority in them, to determine
of matters concerning them all. By
which ther appeareth to be a double
authority of the Pastor: one with the
seuerall congregation, in which he is
Pastour, the other with the whole
Synode or assembly, whereof hee is a

member, and both these authorities,
wee finde sufficientlye authorized
in the Scripture, as shall playn
                  •
               
               lye
appeare in the seuerall Discourses
of them. First therefore, wee
will speake of his authoritye in his
seuerall Churche, in which hee maye
doe nothing without the consente
of the Churche. And first, let vs
examine, whether this authority bee
so diffused ouer the whole Churche,
that the hearing, trying and determyning
of all matters, pertayneth
to the vvhole multitude, or to some
speciall chosen persons amongest
them, meete for that purpose.
            The authoritye is the power of our
Lorde Iesus Christe, graunted vnto
the Church: But because the iudgement
of the multitude is confuse,
whereas God is not the authoure
of Confusion, but of order: and
that we finde in the worde of God,
certayn Officers appoynted for gouernmente:
vvee are bolde to affirme,
that that charge belongeth
vnto those that are such.
            
               
And that doth S. Paule playnely declare,
where hee putteth a difference
of the seuerall offices of the Church,
whereof hee nameth Gouernors for
one. 1. Cor. 28. 29.1. Cor. 28. 29▪
                and Rom. 12. 8.Rom. 
                     •
                  2. 8.
               Let him that ruleth doe it with diligence.
Therefore there ought to be in euery
Church a Consistory or segnorye
of Elders or gouernors, which ought
to haue the hearinge, examination
and determining of all matters, pertaining
to Discipline and Gouernement
of that Congregation: which
authoritye of theirs neuerthelesse
ought to be moderated, that their
iudgment may be rightly accounted
the iudgement of the holy Church.
Which thing consisteth in these two
pointes. First, that the Elders bee elected
and chosen by consent of the
whole Congregation, men of Godlinesse
and Wisedome, in whome the
whole Churche reposeth such confidence,
that they commit vnto them
their authoritye, in hearing &amp; determining
such matters, as without horrible
confusion they cānot perform

themselues. And hereto also may be
referred that, which is sayde of Election
of Pastours, that the Apostles
Paul and Barnabas did ordain, by Election
of the congregation, Elders vnto
many Churches, Actes. 14. 23.Acts. 14. 23. because,
the name of Elders is common
to both: to Pastors and Gouernors,
and is vsed in the Scripture to comprehend
both at once, as it appeareth
manifestly by S. Paul. 1. Tim. 5. 7.1. Tim. 5. 7.
               Those Elders that gouern well, are worthy
of double honor, especially those that labour
in the word and doctrine. Of which testimonie,
we learne these three things:
First, that there bee Elders in the
Church, which meddle not with teaching,
but are occupied altogether
in gouerning. Secondly, that the Elders,
which labor in teaching, otherwise
called Pastors, are ioined also in
gouernment with them, which teach
not. And thirdlye, that the name
of Elder, comprehendeth both sorts
of Elders. And especially in the place
before alleadged for election, ther is
great reason to lead vs to think, that

the elders for gouernment, are as wel
vnderstood, as the other for doctrin,
because it is writtē in the same place,
that after they had ordeined them
Elders in euery congregation by election,Acts. 14. 23.
as hauing set the Churches in
perfect order (which could not be, except
thei had established discipline as
wel as doctrine) they cōmitted thē to
the Lorde, in whome they beleeued.
            The second point for moderation
of the elders authority, in such sorte
that their sentēce may be the sentēce
of the Church is this, that when the
cōsistory hath traueled in examining
of causes pertaining to Ecclesiasticall
Discipline, and agreed what iudgement
ought to passe vpon the matters,
they propound it to the whole
multitude, that it may be confirmed
by their consent. Wherof S. Paul speaketh,
touching the execution of Excōmunication
(because the fact was
manifest) Whē you are gathered together
with my spirit,
               
                  
                     •
                  . Cor. 5. 4. 
               in the name of our Lord Iesus
Christ, and with the power of our Lord
Iesus Christ, to deliuer such a one vnto Sathan,
               
Nowe therfore, to
                  •
                prooue that
there ought to be a Consistory of elders
in euery Church, for gouerning
of the same: It is manifest by the cōmandemēt
of our Sauior Christ, touching
him that despiseth pryuate admonitiō:Math. 18. 17.
               If he hear not them, tel the congregation,
if hee hear not the congregation,
let him be vnto thee as an heathē &amp; publicane.
Verily I say vnto you, whatsoeuer you
shall bind vpon earth shall be bound in heauen.
In which saying of our Sauiour
Christ, this worde Congregation, is not
so largely taken, as in other places
for the whole multitude, but for the
chosen assembly of elders. For our sauiour
Christ, in that worde alludeth
vnto the assembly of elders that was
amōg the Iews, which they called but
corruptlie of a greeke worde Synedrion,
which signifieth a Counsell or
Consistory, Sanedrin, which had the
hearing and determining of all difficult
and waightie matters among
the Iews, the like wherof hee willed
to be established in his Churche, for
administration of gouernment. For,

seeing it was first instituted by God
for gouernement of his Church in
the olde lawe, as hath beene shewed
before out of Num. 11. 6.Num. 11. 6. although it
was shamefully abused by the wicked
Iewes, our sauiour Christ trāslateth
it into his Church also in the
new Testament: and the name of Elders,
doth moste aptlye agree vnto
them that bee gouernours in the
Church now, euen as it did to the
ancients of Israel: so that the Pastors
seme to haue borrowed the name of
Elders, speciallye in respect of their
gouernment. The name of this consistory
also in the new Testament, we
finde to be agreable with that of the
Iewes, whereof our sauiour Christe
speaketh when he sayth:Mat. 18. 
               Tell the congregation
or assembly. S, Paule. 1. Tim.
4. 14.1. Tim. 4. 14. 
               Dispise not the gift which was giuen
thee, thorough prophecie, with imposition
of handes of the Eldership, where the
greeke word is Presbyterion the assemblie
or Consistorye of the Elders.
Which worde is vsed also by Saint
Luke in his Gospell, speaking of the

consistory of the Iewish Elders. Luke
22. 66.Luke. 22. 66. 
               As soone as it was daye, the whole
Eldership or assemblie of Elders came togeather,
both chiefe Priestes and Scribes,
and brought him into their counsell. In
which saying, their counsel Synedrion
is called Presbyterion. Also Saint Paule
Act. 20. 5.Acts. 20. 5. that he had beene a persecutor
of christians, taketh witnesse of
the high priest and of the whol consistory
of Elders, vsing the same word
Presbyterion. By which it is euident,
that our sauiour Christ by this word
Ecclesia in that place, meaneth a consistory
or assemblye of Elders, whose
authoritie he doth ratifie with such
power, that whatsoeuer is bounde or
loosed by them on earth, in the feare
of God, and with heartie prayer, the
Lord will bring it to passe, yea he him
selfe will be in the middest of them,
as President of their counsell, to direct
their consultations, to the glory
of God, and the profite of his owne
Church. Therefore in euery Church,
there ought to be a consistory of Elders
or Gouernours, which with the

Pastor may take charge of Ecclesiasticall
discipline, and good order to bee
obserued in the church, to the punishment
of vice, and the aduauncement
of true vertue. These, if they gouerne
well, as Saint Paule doth testifie, are
worthy of double honour, both that
honour which is due to Godly men,
and that which is due to good gouernours.
            How necessarye it is,The ende of Discipline. that Discipline
shoulde be in the Church, to keepe
men in awe from offending, and to
bring offenders to repentaunce, to auoyde
the infection of sinne, within
the Church, and the reproche that
groweth by neglecting the punnishment
of sinne, among them that are
without the Church: We thinke it
needlesse to stande long in proouing,
the matter of it selfe is so apparaunt,
and hath such plentifull testimonies
in the scripture. And especially let the
reasons of Saint Paule.1. Cor. 5. 1. Cor. 5. and 2.
Cor. 2.2. Cor. 2. where he purposely intreateth
of ecclesiasticall Discipline, be weighed.
A little leauen sowreth a whole lumpe

of dowe. For infection; yee are puffed vp
where yee should be sad and ashamed. For
ignominie: We deliuer him to Sathan, to
the destruction of his fleshe, that his spirite
may be saued in the day of the Lorde: For
repentance, publique reprehension of
manye, which beeing Godly refuse to
eat with such one, is profitable both
to driue him selfe to repentaunce, and
to keepe other in order for feare of
like punishment. Where this Discipline
is not, no maruell if all wickednesse
ouerflowe, to the dishonour of
God, and of his Gospel, to the destruction
of many &amp; corrupting of more,
to the griefe of the Godly, offence of
the weake, incouragement of the
wicked, and reioycing of the aduersary.
            Let vs therefore proceede, in setting
foorth the authoritie of the Pastour
with the Elders, which is; first to punishe
offendours, and bring them to
repentance: or else to cut them cleane
frō the church, as rotten and infected
members. But heere we haue to enquire,
for what offences the Church

may proceede to so sharpe a punishment.
For God forbidde that the
swoorde of excommunication, shold
be drawne out to cut off the members
of our bodie, for euery small disease
that is in them, but onely when
the disease is deadlye, and the member
rotted thereby. For, we ought as
hardly to be brought to excommunicate
anye of our brethren: as we
woulde haue a legge or an arme, cut
off from our body. Therfore the popish
tyrannie is detestable, which
thundereth out their pretended excommunication
for euery trifle: yea
suche as are no sinnes; as non payment
of a little mony, where it is not
deteyned of fraude: non apparance,
where men otherwyse haue necessary
impediments, as though it were
but a smal matter, to put men out of
the protection of Christ, and to deliuer
them vnto the tyrannie of Sathan:
to depriue them of eternall saluation,
and to cast them into euerlasting
damnation. Least therefore we
should vse such vnreasonable rigour,

the spirite of God teacheth vs, what
maner of sinnes deserue excommunication.
1. Cor. 5. 11.1. Cor. 5. 11. 
               If any that is
called a brother, be an whooremonger, or a
couetous person, or an idolater, or a slaunderer,
or a drunckard, or an extorcioner, with
such a one see that yee eat not. These offences
therefore and such like, are to
be punnished by excommunication.
Also an obstinate Heretique, that wil
not repent by admonition, is worthy
of this punishment. Tit. 3. 10.Tit. 3. 10. 2. Tim.
2. 16. 1. Tim. 1. 20. 2. Ioh. 10. &amp; 11.2. Tim. 2. 16.
And not onely these great and notorious
sinnes,1. Tim 1. 20. deserue this correction,2. Ioh. 10. &amp; 11.
but also lesser crimes, increased with
contumacie and contempt of the
Churches admonition, become worthie
of the same castigation. Therefore
sayth our sauiour Christ of priuate
offences, Math. 18. 15. 16. &amp;c.Math. 18. 15. 16. &amp;c. 
               If
thy brother sinne against thee, goe and reprooue
him betweene him and thee alone:
if he heare thee thou hast won thy brother:
but if he heare thee not, take with thee one
or two, that in the mouth of two or three
witnesses, euerye worde may stande: if he

disobey them, then tell the Church, if he
disobey the Church, then let him be to thee
as an heathen or Publicane. The Apostle
Saint Paule likewise. 2. Thes. 3. 6.
                  
                     •
                   Thes. 3. 6. &amp;c.
concerning those that were idle, and
walked disorderlye, will haue all-gentle
meanes vsed to bring them to labour
and good order, but if they
woulde not be refourmed for anye
admonition, he commaundeth them
to be seperated by excommunication.
But it may be obiected that hitherto
appeareth not so great vse of
this Consistorye, why it shoulde bee
thought necessarye for excommunication:
Neyther doth Saint Paule
make mention of it in all places,
where he speaketh of excommunication.
We aunswere, that although the
simple institution of Christ, and approbation
of the holy Ghost, shoulde
suffice vs to thinke it necessarye: yet
there are many necessary vses thereof
to be alleadged. For wheras our Sauiour
Christ commandeth in priuate
offences, the matter to be brought
before the congregation, except you

vnderstande thereby, the congregation
or assemblye of Elders: there shall
follow horrible confusion and disorder
thereby. For, admit a man might
accuse his brother vnto the whole
multitude, yet how should the whole
multitude admonish him, and exhort
him to repentance? Againe, of these
notorious offences that are worthye
of excommunication, some are openly
knowen, so that they neede no
tryall, as the adultery of that Corinthian.
1. Cor. 5.1. Cor. 
                     •
                  . some are in controuersie
and are to be examined, concerning
which, Saint Paule warneth
Timothie, that he admit not any accusation
against an Elder, but vnder
two or three witnesses: and chargeth
him before GOD, and before
the Lorde Iesus Christe, and his elect
Aungelles, that he doe nothing
thorow rashe, or ouer hastie iudgement:
and that hee doe all thinges
without partialitie or affection vnto
parties. 1. Timothie 5. cap. 19.1. Tim. 5. 19 &amp; 21.
and twentie one verse. We see heere
manyfestly a necessarye vse of the

Eldership. For howe is it possible for
the whole Churche, to examine and
discusse such difficult controuersies?
Therefore it behooueth the Church,
to haue such ordinary Delegates, as
may and ought to applye their diligence,
vuto such matters. Moreouer,
to ouersee the Church for matters
pertaining to order and Discipline:
How can the multitude ouersee thē
               selues,
or the Pastours onelye, which
haue a principall care of Doctrine, to
attēd vpon? And to the secōd part of
the obiection, that S. Paul doth make
mention of the Eldership or Consistory
of Elders in all places, where he
speaketh of Excommunication: wee
aunswere, that it is not necessary hee
should so do. For, wheras our sauiour
Christ hath prescribed a form thereof,
that hee which obeyeth not the
Congregation should be excommunicated:
and that in other places, hee
maketh sufficient mention, both of
the Elders and of the assemblie, wee
oughte to vnderstande, that his purpose
is, to obserue that forme to the

vttermost. And although he doe not
always make expresse mētion therof,
yet must we not imagine, that he mēt
to alter or chaunge the same. In the
first to the Corinthians the fift verse,
It is manifest, that albeit he
                  •
                desired
nothing more, then that the incestuous
Adulterer should bee excommunicated,
and therefore determined
of him for his owne part,
as absent in body, but present in spirite:
yet hee acknowledgeth that hee
could not be excommunicated, without
the consent of the Congregation,
being gathered together in the
name of our Lorde Iesus Christe. 1.
Cor. 5. 4.1. Cor. 5. 4. Likewise when he shoulde
be receiued againe, he was to be pardoned,
not onelie by him, but by
them also. 2. Cor. 1. 10.2. Cor. 1. 10. And therefore,
if so high an Apostle, could not
by his priuate authority excommunicate
that Corinthian: we must not
thinke, that by his priuate authority
but by consent of the Churche of Ephesus,
he excommunicated Himmineus
&amp; Alexander,
               1. Tim. 2. 20. although he do not

make expresse mentiō of the consent
of the church in that place. 1. Tim. 2.
20.1. Tim. 2. 20. So likewise where he speaketh to
Timothie in the singular nūber, concerning
the hearing &amp; determining
of matters pertaining to Discipline,
we ought to acknowlege, that he teacheth
in Timothie his person, the duty
of elders, &amp; neuer ment to giue Timothy
an absolute or singular authority,
to be iudge in these matters, without
consent of the Eldership, whereof he
maketh mention but a little before.
To conclude therfore, the Pastor with
aduise &amp; consent of the Elders, hath
authoritie to heare &amp; examine matters,
pertaining to Ecclesiasticall Discipline,
and as the cause requireth to
excommunicate offenders, and vpon
their repentance and amendment, to
receiue them againe into the bosom
of the church, approued by the word
of God. Insteede of which, Antichrist
hath set vp a tyrannicall iurisdiction
of one Bishop to be iudge of excommunication,
which is practized neyther
for causes sufficient, nor by sufficient

authoritie, in so much as it
hath beene alreadye testified by the
scripture, that the power of excommunication,
is in no one man, no not
in an Apostle, but is common to the
whole church, &amp; ought to be executed
by lawful delegats of the church
also. But so much that vsurped authoritie
presumeth, that the bishop as an
absolute owner therof, commiteth it
ouer to his chancelor or Archdeacō,
the Archdeacon to his Official, &amp; he
to his register, &amp; he again to his substitute,
and his substitute to his seruants,
man or boy as it happeneth: in
so much that a learned preacher, may
be excommunicated by a folish boy.
If this matter seeme not to requyre
speedy reformatiō, god hath blinded
our eies that we can not see the clere
light of the sun shining in our faces.
For if we loke to banish the tyrannye
of the Pope out of all mens harts, we
must vtterly remoue al his detestable
enormities out of the Realme, as it
was wont to be sayd in the common
prayers of the Church in the time of

K. Henry and Edward, whereas now
by reteining stil, all the detestable enormities
of his prerogatiue and faculties,
&amp; whole course of his Canon
law, the papacie is not so much banished
in name, as translated in deede
from the Sea of Rome, to the Sea of
Caunterbury, vnder the shadowe of
the Princes supremacie, with as heynous
iniurie and contumely, of the
lawful authoritie &amp; godly supremacie
of the Prince, as ioyned with the
great dishonour of God, and the miserable
disorder of the Church. But
we meane not in this place to prosecute
our iust complaintes, nor to inueigh
againste the abuse of these
thinges, with such vehemencie of
wordes as the worthines of the matters
deserueth: but onelye in setting
foorth the plaine trueth, to giue a
glimpst by the waye of the contrarye
falshoode.
            We must therefore returne to the
authoritie of the Pastour, which he
hath ioyned with the Elders of the
Church, whereof he is pastour. The

Church hath alwayes had great care
for prouision of the poore, by which
compassion they shewed, that they
were liuely members of the body of
Christ, and auoyded great reproch of
them that were without. For what
shame is it, for them that professe to
be all sonnes of one father, and therfore
all brethren: yea that be members
all of one body, to suffer their
brethren &amp; fellow members, to lacke
necessaries to sustayne their temporal
life: as though they that communicate
in all spiritual graces and blessinges,
were not worthye to take part
of these worldlye benefites, at leastwyse
so farre forth as to supply their
necessities? Therefore our Sauiour
Christe, alwayes commendeth brotherly
loue among his Disciples, to
teach vs how ready we ought to be,
to distribute vnto the necessities of
our brethren, which is a true testimonie
of our loue declared by his
owne example. For, although hee
were so poore, that he liued of the
almesse and liberalitie of other men:

yet of that which was more then
serued his owne necessitie, he vsed to
bestowe vppon the poore: as Iohn.
13. 29.Ioh. 13. 29. to teache them whome hee
hath blessed with Temporall riches,
which hee refused, to enrich vs with
heauenlye treasures, that they of
their superfluitie, woulde be content
to giue to the reliefe of their
poore bretheren, which he did not
neglect in his extreame pouerty: To
teach also them that haue but mean
substaunce, that they ought not to
bee excused, but somewhat to contribute
vnto the necessitie of their
poore bretheren, when he that had
nothing at all but that which was giuen,
euen of that bestowed part.
Therefore the Apostles in the primitiue
Church, thought it to be expedient,
for the better prouiding for
the poore, that certaine men shoulde
be appoynted of approoued Godlinesse
and diligence, which shoulde
take the speciall charge of the distribution
vnto the poore. Act. 6.Actes 6. These
men were called Deacons or ministers,

because they did minister and
serue the poore in their necessities,
and because the occasion of the ordinaunce
continueth alwayes (as our
Sauiour Christ hath sayde) we should
alwayes haue the poore amongest
vs, Iohn. 12. 8.Ioh. 12. 8. vvhereby GOD
woulde exercise our charitie. The office
of Deacons also is perpetuall.
Therefore the Apostle Saint Paule,
prescribeth what kinde of men are
meete for that office. 1. Timothie.
3. 8.1. Tim. 3. 8. And in euery well constituted
Church, they were ordayned accordingly:
as Phillip. 1. 1.Phil. 
                     •
                  . 1. Also after
the ordeyning of the seuen Deacons,
this office was deuided into
diuers partes, as necessitie shewed
diuers occasions. For some were
appoynted for the collection and
distribution of al
                  •
               esse: as Romans
12. 8. and some for attending vppon
the sicke and impotent among the
poore,Rom. 12. 8. as in the same place. Let him
that distributeth, doe it with simplicitie,
and let him that sheweth mercie, doe it
with cheerefulnesse.
            
            
               
Which kinde of Deacons. 1. Cor. 12.
28.1. Cor. 12. 28. are called helpers: and for the
seruice of this office, were appointed
diuers olde poore widowes, who as
they were mainteined by the church:
so they serued the church, attending
vppon the other poore, who beeing
sicke and impotent, had neede not
onely of things necessary, but also of
seruice and attending. 1. Timoth. 5. 5.1. Tim. 5. 5.
These offices being instituted by the
spirit of God, for the necessary vse of
the Church, which vse still continueth,
ought also to be reteined among
vs. For we see, for want of these offices,
what great inconueniences are among
vs, concerning the poore. For,
although ther be very good politike
laws made for prouision of the pore:
yet smal reliefe commeth thereby to
the poore indeed: at least wise manie
abuse the reliefe which they receiue,
which commeth of this, that there be
not in euery church or congregatiō,
such Deacons as the holy ghost hath
appointed, which should take a speciall
care, &amp; employ a great diligence,

for the prouision of the poore: not
only some, to gather and distribute,
but also to see it well imployed on
the poore, and to imploy the poore,
that liue of the almes of the church,
to the releefe of their fellow poore,
which are more impotēt thē they, as
it was vsed in the Primatiue Church.
And aboue all thinges, to beware
of them that walke disorderlye,
and labour not if they be able. Of
which kinde of people, when there
is so greate multitudes in this land,
that they doe euen ouerflowe the
Countryes, and haue beene knowne
to bee practizers of greate matters
agaynste the state: It is maruayle,
that neither by politique, nor by ecclesiasticall
Lawe, they are broughte
into order, and sette to laboure, or
else (as Saynt Paule prescribeth,) so
that they shoulde not eate, vntill
they bee willing to labour. 2. Thes.
3. 10.
            But now, to return to the Election
of Deacons. Concerning the form
of chusing of Deacons, we may reade

at large. Actes. 6. that they were
chosen, by consente of the vvhole
Churche, and hadde the approbation
of the Apostles. And because
wee maye not thinke, there was anye
confusion in that blessed companye,
wee muste needes confesse,
that vvhich hath beene before declared,
that there were euen in that
assemblie and firste Churche at Hierusalem,
certayne elders appoynted,
which in the name and by the
consente of the rest, had the disposition
of suche matters, as appeareth
by manie places of the Actes of
the Apostles, where the Elders are
named with the Apostles: As Actes
15. 4. 12. &amp;c. but especiallye
concerning this matter of the distribution
vnto the poore, we reade,
that when the Church of Antiochia,
was so wel disposed as to make a collection
to bee sente vnto the poore
Brethren that dwelt in Iury, they
sent vnto the Elders, by the handes
of Barnabas and Saule. Actes. 11.Act. 11. 30.
               
30. By vvhich it appearethe, that
the Elders had the disposition and
appoynting of suche as shoulde destribute
it vnto the Congregation,
which were the Deacons. For it
is agreeable to reason, that hee that
should doe any seruice in the name
of all, should be chosen and approued
by the consent of all. For the
Regiment of the church, as it ought
to bee furthest of from all Tirannye:
so ought it to be as farre from
Confusion and disorder. Tyranny is
auoyded when no one man, (contrarie
to the ordinaunce of Christe)
shall presume to doe anye thing in
the Church, without the aduise and
consent of others that bee Godlye
and vvise, and authorized by the
consent of the Church. Confusion is
preuented by the graue counsayle,
and orderlye assemblye of Elders,
vnto vvhome the Churche hathe
committed her authority.
            By this it maye easily appeare,
vvhat great defaulte there is in our
Church, where those that are sayde

to be ordeined Deacons, neuer purpose
in their life to execute any part
of a Deacons office, neither are chosen
for that end: but only that within
a short time after, they may bee
made Priestes or ministers, nothing
in the worlde differing from the superstition
of Popery: where the office
of Deacon was conferred onely,
as a step vnto priesthood. As though
it were necessarye, that euerye one
which is ordayned an Elder, shoulde
first be a Deacon, and yet when he is
made a Deacon, hee is but an Idoll,
yea scarse an Idoll of a Deacon, hauing
no resemblaunce at all vnto a
Deacon indeed, but that he is a man.
This prophaning of Gods institution,
God will not alwayes suffer vnpunished,
especially when it is not
maintained of ignoraunce or infirmity,
but defended against knowledge,
and vpon wilfulnesse. Therefore,
the Collectors are more like to
deacons a great deal, then those that
the Byshops make Deacons. For, first
they haue after a sort election of the

Church, whereas the other haue, but
the approbation of one man. And
secondly, they gather and distribute
the common almes vnto the poore,
which the other neuer think of. But
yet we may not allow them for lawfull
Deacons indeede, because they
are not alwayes endued with suche
qualities, as the Apostle requireth.
1. Tim. 2.1. Tim. 
                     •
                  . For they ought to bee men
of good estimation in the Churche,
full of the holy Ghost, and of wisedome,
that should be chosen, Acts. 6.
For, as it is an office of good credit,
so ought the person to bee of good
reputation. Therefore saith S. Paule,
that Those Deacons that Minister well,
doe get them selues a good degree,
               1. Tim. 3. 13. 
               and
great liberty in the faith, which is in Christ
Iesus. Insomuch that S. Paule him self
doth salute in speciall wordes the
Deacons, next to the Byshops or ouerseers
in the Churche of Philipi.Phillip. 1. 1.
Wee reade also, what worthye men
were chosen to be the first Deacons;
as Stephen the first Martyr, and Philip,
which afterwarde was an Euangelist,

when the Churche was dispersed
thoroughe the persecution
raysed aboute Stephen. So that euery
ignoraunte contemptible personne,
is not to bee allowed vnto
this office: but as Godly, wise, and
vvorshipfull, as maye conuenientlye
bee founde in the Congregation,
maye not thinke them selues
too good to minister vnto Christe,
in his members, and in the name
of the Churche. The Election also
of oure Collectours, is too Prophane
for so holye an Office. Wee
maye reade in the Historye of the
Actes: Actes. 6.Act. 6. with vvhat grauitye,
reuerence, and religiousnesse,
the Apostles ordayned Deacons,
vvith Prayer and Imposition of
handes. For these and suche like
causes, althoughe the ordinarye
Collectors haue some resemblance,
with the Deaconship of the church:
yet wee cannot in all poyntes allowe
them for Deacons: whose office
truely consisteth onelye in ministration
vnto the poore, as wee

haue shewed, in that they bee Deacons.
Wee haue declared before,
that there is a double authority of
the Pastour, the one ioyned vvith
the Elders of the Churche, vvhereof
hee is Pastour: the other vvith
the Synode or holy assembly, whereof
he is a member.
            Of the former wee haue intreated
hitherto. Nowe it followeth,
that wee speake of the latter. There
aryseth oftentimes in the Church,
diuerse Controuersyes, which cannot
bee othervvise expressed, pertayning
to the state of the vvhole
Churche, then by a generall assemblye
of all the Pastoures of that
Churche, vvhich is called a Synode
or generall Counsayle. Also there
bee diuerse cases, vvherein the seuerall
Churches, are driuen to pray
the ayde of the Synode, vvhere
matters can not bee determined among
them selues. For this cause,
the Holye Ghoste hathe ordayned
these Holy assembles, with promise,
that they being gathered together

in the name of Christe, he him selfe
will bee among them. With the Synode,
the Pastour hath authority to
determine, concerning regiment of
the Church. Wherefore we haue to
enquire, of what persons a Synode
doth consist: For which intent wee
finde in the history of Act. 15. 6. that
when a cont
                  •
               ouersie arose concerning
the Ceremonies of the Lawe,
whether they were to bee vsed, by
those Christians that were conuerted
of the Gentiles: The Apostles &amp;
Elders came together to consider of
this matter, and that the people was
not excluded, appeareth by the 12.
verse, the whol multitude, being perswaded
by the argumentes alleaged
by Peter, helde their peace, and quietly
hearde Paule and Barnabas, declare
what signes &amp; wonders, God
had wrought by them amongest the
Gentiles. And least ye should vnderstand
the multitude in that place, for
the multitude of the Apostles, It followeth
in the 22. verse. Then it pleased
the Apostles and Elders, with the

whole Church, to chuse certaine men. &amp;c.
By which scripture we learn, that the
Synode consisteth principally of Pastours,
Elders, Teachers, and men of
wisdome, iudgement and grauitie, as
it were of necessary regents. For, although
the whole multitude came
togeather, yet the Apostles and Elders
came togeather to enquire, and
consider of the matter in controuersie,
the multitude heard, and for their
better instruction and modestye, submitted
their consent, vnto the determination
of the Apostles and Elders.
All mens reasons were hearde. For
there was great disputation, but the
authoritie of Gods worde preuailed,
good order was obserued. So, after
the matter was throughly discussed,
by the godly arguments, alledged by
Peter and Barnabas, &amp; Paul, the controuersie
was concluded by the sentence
of Iames, to whom that prerogatiue
was graunted, not of singular
authoritie, but for orders sake. And
this place doth admonishe vs, to intreate
some what of the preeminence

of one Elder or pastor aboue the rest
We confesse that in euery assemblye
or company, some one of necessitie
must haue this prerogatiue, to order
and dispose the same with reason, or
els great confusion is like to follow.
But this preeminence is onely of order
and not of authoritie, as to propound
matters to be decided, to gather
the reasons and consent of the
rest, and so to conclude, &amp;c. As we see
in this place Iames did: of whom also
we reade, that he had this preeminence.
Act. 21. 18,Act. 21. 18. &amp;c. And we maye
gather the same. Gal. 2. 9. 12.
                  
                     •
                  al. 2. 9. 12. Not
that Iames had greater authority in
his Apostleship, then Peter or Paule,
or Iohn, or anye other of the Apostles:
But because he was chosen of
the rest to haue prerogatiue of order,
which some one must haue in euerye
assembly, and such was the prerogatiue
at the first, which was graunted
sometime to the bishop of Rome, &amp;
sometime to some other bishops, to
be president or prolocutor in the generall
counsels, being chosen therto

for the time by consent of the rest, as
the prolocutor is chosen in our conuocatiōs,
that are called with parliaments.
Therfore, as it were an absurd
thing for our prolocutor in our conuocation,
to take vppon him to be a
controller of the whole synode, &amp; to
challenge that office to him and to
his heires for euer: so vnreasonable is
the authority that the Pope claimeth
ouer generall counsels. One therfore
is to be chosen by consent, to be as it
were the prolocutor or moderator of
order, but not of authoritie in euery
assembly, whose prerogatiue must so
be tempered, that in al thinges tirannie
be auoyded. Which we see by experience
easely crepeth in vpō proud
natures, to whome if you graunt an
inch, they wil be ready to take an ell,
according to the Prouerbe. But let vs
return to the authority of the sinode
which cōsisteth in deciding &amp; determining
such maters as cānot otherwise
in perticular churches be cōcluded,
either because they cōcerne the
cōmō state of al churches, or because

they lacke sufficient authoritie in
some one church. First therefore the
lawfull Synode hath to consider, if anie
controuersie of doctrine do arise,
that it be determined by the word of
God: for in the controuersie of binding
the Gentiles, to the obseruations
of the ceremoniall lawe, was a
matter of faith and doctrine.
            Secondly, it hath to determine of
the vse of the ceremonies, not of will
without reason or grounde of scripture,
but vpon necessary causes of auoiding
offence and similitude of superstition,
of bearing with the weak,
of order and comelinesse and edification.
So did the Synode of the Apostles
and Elders, command for a time
abstinencie from meate offered to Idols,
otherwise lawfull in it selfe, for
offences sake, and for auoyding of all
pollution of Idolatrie. Act. 6. 20. 29.Act. 6. 20. 29
and forbearing the weaknesse of the
Iewes in abstinencie, from eating of
bloud &amp; of strangled, which was forbidden
by God before Moses time,
to teach that Childishe age of Gods

people to abstaine from cruelty, as in
Gen. 9. 4.Genes. 9. 4. Such ceremoniall constitutions
are but temporall, and so long
are to be reteined, as the cause continueth,
for which they were made. So
that if weaknes cease, or be turned to
obstinacie, they are no longer to be
reteined. Also for order and comelinesse,
and best edification, the Synode
hath to determine, what shall be obserued
in particular charges: as of the
time, place, and forme of preaching
and praying, and administring of the
sacraments. For, who shoulde be able
to know what order, comelines and
edification requireth according to
Gods worde, but they that be Teachers
and preachers of the same vnto
al others? For it is absurde, that they
shoulde bee taught by such in these
small thinges, as ought to learne the
truth of them in all matters. This authoritie
therefore cannot be graunted
vnto any Ciuill Christian Magistrate,
that without consent of the
learned Pastours and Elders: yea against
their consent (of whom, as in

some respect hee is a feeling member)
he maye lawfully make ceremoniall
Constitutions, whereby the
Church muste be gouerned, in meere
Ecclesiasticall matters.
            It is ou
                  •
               e of all controuersye,
that before there vvere anye Christian
Magistrates (for wee will, not
speake of SERGIVS PAVLVS
proconsull of Cyprus, because hee
was but a Lieuetenaunt of the Romane
Emperour) this authoritie was
proper vnto the Synode.
            Which authoritye vvee knovve
to bee graunted to the Church by
oure Sauioure CHRISTE: practized
by his Apostles: continued
by their successours three hundred
yeares, before there was anye
Christian Emperours, (for wee receiue
not Phillip for a Christian
Emperour) and long time after there
were Christian Emperours, euen as
long as anye puritie continued in
religion, vntill both Emperours and
Synodes were thrust out of all lawfull
authoritie, which they ought to

haue in the Church, by the tyrannie
of Antichrist.
            But wee finde not in the Scripture,
this authoritye graunted by
Christe to Ciuill Magistrates, which
in his, and his Apostles tyme were
not, nor anye promise that when
they were, the Synode shoulde resigne
it vnto them. Therefore it
remayneth, that it bee shewed by
them, that defende that this absolute
authoritie is in the Ciuill Magistrate,
by what spirite or reuelation,
or Scripture (if there be anye
that wee know not): For, we woulde
bee gladde to learne howe this authoritie
was translated from the
Church, (in which it was once lawfullye
vested) vnto the Ciuill Christian
Magistrate.
            Therefore, vntill this maye bee
shewed, by sufficient warraunt of
GODS holye worde, vve holde
that the Synode of euerye Prouince,
hath authority to decree concerning
ceremoniall orders of the Church:

Whereof some may be generall to al
congregations, some particular to
certaine Churches. For, as it were to
be wished that all places might bee
brought to one perfection: So it is
not alwayes necessarye, that they be
like in all thinges. The wisedome of
the Synode therefore ought to haue
such regard of all churches, that they
haue speciall respect to euerye one.
Wherin we of long time in England
haue beene caried away, with an vntrue
principle, that vniformitie must
be in all places, and thinges a like, as
though we would feede old men and
sucking infants all with one kind of
meat: or as though we would cloath
all ages in a robe of one assize: and
that which is more absurde, compell
men of ripe age to sucke the dugge,
to weare their biggins, and to carrye
Rattles and other Childish bables.
Our lande is not yet wholly conuerted
to Christe (so great hath beene
our negligence hitherto) therefore
there can not bee suche an vniformitye
of orders in all places, as

shall be profitable for all. Therefore
it were meete, that the Ouerseers
and Elders of the Churche,
shoulde come together to consider
of this matter, what orders were
moste meete for diuerse places, to
bring thē to the obediēce of Christ:
what for the furtheraunce of them
that are newly come, and what for
the continuance and increase, of thē
that are very well come on.
            The same doctrine, although not
the same parts of Doctrine, is to bee
euery where: but ceremonies, euen
as they be ceremonies, do admit variety:
as time, persons, and occasions
serue to be diuerse. Yea Christian liberty,
in them somtimes, is necessary
to be testified, because there are many
so simple, that they know not the
difference betweene those thinges,
that are necessarye in the Churche,
and those that are not of necessitye.
There be that thinke a Crosse
or Font (as they call it) is as necessary
in baptisme, as water: and that kneeling
at the Communion is more necessary

then preaching of the Lordes
death: that a Surplusse in common
prayer, is more necessary, then a deuoute
minde: and greate occasions
offered to the ignoraunt so to
thinke, vvhen they see them that
preache moste diligently, pray most
feruentlye, and minister the Sacramentes
moste reuerently, according
to Christes institution, to be displaced
of all ministery, for a Crosse or
a Fonte, or a Surplusse, or some such
other trifle. The Synode therefore,
oughte to bee carefull in ordayning
of Ceremonyes, not onelye
that they bee pure and agreeable to
the worde of God: but also that
they bee expediente for the time
and personnes, for whose vse they
are ordayned: And as wilfull contemners
of good orders established
by publique authoritye, are worthy
to bee corrected, so intangling
of mens consciences, or tyrannicall
coaction in these indifferente matters,
must alwayes bee auoyded.
The Synode hathe further authoritye

concerninge Discipline, to refourme
and redresse by Ecclesiasticall
Censure, all suche defaultes and
controuersies, as cannot bee determined
in the particuler Churches:
as for example: If the Pastour himselfe,
haue neede to bee seuerelye
punished, vvhere there is but one
Pastour in a Churche: or if Elders,
vvhiche shoulde bee refourmers of
others, haue notoriouslye misgouerned
them selues: or if they haue
beene ledde by affection, to condemne
an Innocente, or to iustifye
the vngodlye: in these and suche
like cases, all Contention is to bee
concluded, by the authority of the
Synode. Some example vvee haue
thereof. Acts. 15.Act. 15. where those contentious
Schismatiques, that withstoode
Paule and Barnabas at Antiochia,
were constrained to yeelde
by authoritye of the Councell, and
Paul and Barnabas restored to their
credite.
            For which causes, Synodes ought oftentimes

to bee assembled, though
not general of the whole realme, but
particular of euery prouince or shire,
as it may be most conueniently, that
such thinges as are to be refourmed,
may bee redressed with speede.
            Last of all, forasmuch as the election
of Pastors, is a great &amp; waighty matter,
which ought not to bee permitted
to the iudgement of anye one
man, but pertaineth to the Church,
whereunto they shoulde be chosen,
both for better aduise in chusing of
a meete man, and for authority in
causing him to accept their election:
it is conuenient that it bee done by
iudgement of the particular Sinode.
That no one man hath authority to
ordaine Pastors, and to impose them
ouer churches, hath bene before declared,
by example of the Apostles
Paule and Barnabas, who although
they were Apostles, yet would they
not challenge that prerogatiue vnto
themselues, but by common election,
they ordained Elders in euery
Church. Acts. 14. 23.Actes. 14. 23. Timothy also

receiued his charge, although it were
through prophecy, by imposition of
handes of the Eldership. 1. Timoth.
4. 14.1. Tim. 4. 14. Therefore as it hath bene euidently
declared before, the assembly
of Elders, consisting of graue, wise,
and Godly men, ought to enquire,
when the Pastors place is voyd, wher
they may finde a man meete to supplie
his roome, and therein to desire
aide of the Synode. The man by such
Godly aduise so chosen, ought to be
presented to the Congregation, and
of them to be allowed and receiued,
if no man can shew anye reasonable
cause to the contrarie. This is the
right election and ordaining of Pastors,
grounded vppon the worde of
God, and practised by the primatiue
Church, two hundred yeeres after
Christ, vntil the mistery of iniquity,
grew to work more openly to the
setting vp of the tyrannicall kingdome
of Antichrist. By this we may
plainly see, that our presentation of
patrons, is both prophane and preiudicial:
our giuing of orders by Byshoppes

is presumptuous, and full
of absurdities. Firste, because they
take vppon them to do that, which
none of the Apostles durst doe: that
is, without election of Churches, to
ordayne Elders. Secondly, that they
giue an Office vvithout a charge,
to make a Pastour, and sende him
to seeke a Flocke, where hee canne
finde it: which is as vnreasonable a
thing, as if one were chosen to bee
a Church-warden, and had neuer a
Churche to keepe: or made a Constable,
that had neuer a Towne or
place appoynted, whereof he should
bee Constable. For the name of a
Pastour, Elder, or Ouerseer, is the
name of an office in Act and esse, because
it is a proper Relatiue, and not
a Potentiall abilitye in the Cloudes.
            If Byshoppes as they bee nowe,
were consecrated after the same maner
to seeke theire Byshoprickes,
vvhere they coulde finde them, it

                  〈◊〉
                no greater absurdity, then it is
to ordayne Pastoures, and let them
proll where they can for their benefices.

Thirdlye, by this wandring
(we may also say vagabounde) ministery,
shifting from place to place, and
in all places to bee counted a Minister
where he hath no charge, it wold
grieue a man to thinke, what inconueniences
doth follow, but principally,
how filthily it stinketh of the olde
Popish indelible character, frō whēce
it hath his ground, and neither of any
reason, or of the worde of God.
And yet forsooth it is so perfect, that
it may abide no reformatiō. Fourthly,
if you will see how well the authority
which they claime and practize,
is vsed of them, that onelye haue the
choyse and admission of Ministers:
Looke ouer the vvhole Realme of
Englande, What a multitude of vnfitte
Pastours shall you finde in euery
place? So that Ieroboam neuer
made worse Priestes of the refuse
of the people, to serue his Golden
Calues, then they haue ordayned
Ministers to feede the Flocke of
Christe, which hee hathe purchased
with his owne bloude.
            
               
This complaint we confesse is greeuous,
but the indignity of the matter
inforceth it. We know that vaine
excuses shall not be wanting, of necessity,
&amp;c. But if necessity compelled
thē to take such at the first; what
necessity compelleth them, to suffer
them to bee such still? For, if they
woulde needes admit ignoraunt persons
to that charge: yet should they
haue enforced them to study, as wel
as to other thinges, they haue inforced
them vnto, that in time they
might haue growne to be meete for
their calling. Which if they had done
in 10. 12. or 13. yeeres space, a great
many might haue proued excellētly
well learned, and able to serue in the
Church with great fruit and profit:
and the rest according to proportion
of their time, might haue come to
some mediocrity in knowledg, wheras
nowe as ignoraunt and as vnfit as
they were the first day, so are they
still for the moste parte, and will so
continue to theire liues ende, if
they may be suffered in idlenesse, as

they haue beene hitherto. Then it is
a torment to thinke what ambitious
suing, what enuious labouring, what
vnseemelie flattering, what prodigall
bribing, is vsed to attayne to greate
dignities in the Church, to farre vnmeete
for the modesty and grauitye
that shoulde be in Christian preachers.
And as for the inferior benefices,
from the fattest Parsonadge, to the
poorest Vicaradge almoste, if it bee
worth 40. pounds by the year, what
Symonicall bargains of leases, Annuities,
Reseruations, exhibitions: yea,
notwithstanding the Act of Parliament,
Anno. 13. by Antedates and
other subtil conueyances, what christian
heart can think of them, without
detestation of such horrible abuses?
Shall we speak here any thing
of the popish priesthood, the greatest
blasphemy that euer was: how long
was it allowed for a lawfull ministery,
vntill by the Godlye meaning of
the sayde Parliament, some brandmarke
of shame, was set vppon it?
But howe pitifullye that authority

was abused, which was by the same
statute committed to the bishops, in
allowing of priests that came to doe
their penance, by negligence of the
bishops, &amp; bribery of their Officers:
the country crieth out of it, and the
state of the church, is little amended
by it. Old Sir Iohn Lacklatin, that had
not seen some of his benefices, a dosē
yeare before, was carried aboute on
his Mare, and sometimes on a Cart:
First to the bishop whom he chose, if
he might for his purpose, such one as
had bene a priest of his owne order,
and cared leaste what ministers serue
in his Diocesse, and then from Shire
to Shire, one distant an hundred mile
from another, mumbling vp his Articles
in his morowmasse voice, in euery
Church where hee had liuing,
and returned as very a beaste as hee
came.
            But this and all other inconueniences
before rehearsed, shoulde
vtterlye bee auoyded, if wee mighte
once establish the lawfull election
of Pastours, according to the word

of God. It were also greatly to bee
wished, that it might bee broughte
to passe, that in euery Congregation,
there shoulde be two pastors at
the least, both because the charge is
great, and also for supplying the lack
of the one, if the other were sicke or
absent vppon necessity, or any such
like case. Which thing were both
agreeable to the example of the Apostolike
Churche, and also verye
profitable for the Congregation.
Wee doe not meane this in euerye
Parish, as they bee nowe distinguished,
but in euery Congregation as
they may be disposed, both for best
edifying and also for sufficient liuing
for the Pastors.
            It will bee obiected, when we haue
all thinges at our pleasure, concerning
the Election of Pastors, yet will
there creepe in many abuses. Wee
answere, they shall not so soone, nor
so easily, nor so many abuses creepe
in, as nowe at wide Windowes, yea,
great port-gates doe throng in.
            But if as many or more abuses (if

more coulde bee) were crept in, yet
were the case better then it is now:
for we shoulde be sure, that God approoueth
our order, though he condemn
the abuses, because it is grounded
vpon Gods worde, whereas now
he abhorreth both.
            But of the authority that Pastors
haue as members of the Synode, we
haue spoken hitherto sufficiently.
By which it is euidēt, how all things
haue beene corrupted in Poperye,
which had at the first any good institution,
which corruptions we also retaine
at this day, without desiring of
any refourmation. For, to begin first
with our particuler Synodes, good
lord what a mockery they are of law
ful synodes, beeing holden for no other
ende almoste, but to gather vp
fees, both ordinary &amp; extraordinary,
with dayly newe deuises to poll the
poore Priestes of their mony, which
they extort for seeing the Letters of
orders, for Dynners and suche like
matters. And yet a newe inuented
pyllage, vvhereby they compell men

to buy Bookes of them for 4. pence
or 6. pence, which are to deare of a
peny or two pence: and not onelye
suche small Ware, but also greate
bookes, beeing such as euerie parish
is appointed to buy, must be bought
of them for two or three Shyllinges
in a Booke dearer, then it may bee
bought in Paules Church-yarde: yea
otherwhiles, though the Parish bee
furnished of them alreadye, they
are not authenticall, except they be
boughte at Master Chauncellers and
Officiall, at Master Regesters hands.
As for refourmation of any thing
in the Churche, there are indeede
many presentments, and men sworn
to presente matters, but little or
none amendmente at all doth followe.
So that it is a common saying
in the Countrie, when the presentment
is once receyued, they shal
neuer heare more of it. Soone after
the Visitation or Synode, the petitbribing
Sumner, rideth foorth laden
with Excommunications, which hee
scattereth abroad in the Country, as

thicke as Haileshot, against this parson,
and that Vicar: this Church warden,
and that Side-man, whome hee
himselfe when he came to summon
him to the Synode, for a Cheeze
or a Gammon of Bacon, had vndertaken
to excuse for none apparaunce.
But when he is once Excommunicated,
there is no remedy,
but hee must trudge to the Chauncelour
or Officiall for absolution,
who after hee hath once absolued
his Purse of a fewe Groates, giueth
him his blessing and sendeth him away.
And this is the image of our litle
or particuler Synode.
            Our generall Conuocations haue
a more shevve of good order,Chusing of Clearkes of the Conuocatiō house. but
in effect little better. For firste, they
are stuffed full of Popish and prophane
Chauncelloures, and other
Lawyers, which beeing meere laye
men, and vnlearned in Diuinitie, by
their owne Lawe, ought to be no
members of the Synode: And yet
these will beare the greatest sway in
all thinges. The Byshops, as though

they were greater then the Apostles,
must haue their seuerall couuenticle,
wheras the Apostles and elders came
together with the whole multitude,
Actes 15.Actes 15. And as they are seuered in
place, so will they bee higher in authoritie.
So that whatsoeuer is decreed
amongest them, that must bee
called the determynation of the
whole Synode. So that no manne
muste bee suffered to speake anye
thinge agaynste it, bee it neuer so
reasonable, or agreeable to the
vvorde of GOD: yea, vvhosoeuer
vvill not subscribe to all suche
thinges, as they decree, muste bee
excluded out of the Conuocation,
as vvas practized and threatened in
the Conuocation at the foresayde
Parliamente, vnto diuerse Godlye
and learned Preachers, that offered
to speake agaynste dyuerse grosse
and palpable erroures, that had escaped
the Byshoppes decrees. As
for the distinction of Canonicall
and Apocriphall bookes, for explication
of the clause in the article of

Predestination: where it is sayde,
that the elect may fall from Grace,
and such like matters. If this bee
not to practise Lordshippe ouer our
faith: to set downe decrees of Religion,
which must bee accepted of
all men, without eyther reason or testimony
of the Scripture to prooue
them, and no man permitted to shew
anye reason or Scripture, that inforceth
his Conscience to the contrarye,
but onely to hang vppon the
authority of bishops: Let some other
declare what Paul meaneth, 2. Cor. 1.
4.2. Cor. 1. 14. where he denieth, that he woulde
excercise any Lordship, ouer the faith
of the Corinthians.
            For, although their decrees were
neuer so perfect, yet it were an example
of tyrannicall Dominion, neither
to giue reasons to satisfie the ignoraunt
them selues, nor to hear or
cōfute that which might be alleaged
against them by others, but for a few
lordbishops in comparison of all the
conuocation, to sit by them selues &amp;
order all thinges at their pleasures,

as though the Gospell sprang firste
from them, or had come vnto them
only, it sauoreth of nothing so much
as of popish tyranny: Whereas otherwise
it is well knowne they are not al
of the best learned, nor all of longest
study, nor all of soundest iudgement,
nor all of greatest zeale, nor all of
best example, and therfore not meetest
to be the onely determiners in
Ecclesiasticall matters, to the preiudice
of the whole synode. Wherefore
it is greatly to be desired, that our
synodes also, which are so farre out
of order, maye be refourmed according
to the scripture, and the example
of the primitiue Church, that all
thinges may be done with such modesty,
grauitie &amp; iudgement, as they
were by the Apostles and Elders.Actes. 15. Act.
15. And now that we haue set forth
the whole Ecclesiasticall ministerye,
according to the word of God, with
all the duties &amp; authoritie that pertayneth
vnto it: the place requyreth,
that we should also intreat of the authority
of the ciuil Magistrate in matters

ecclesiastical. Of the title of the
princes supremacie, if it be truly vnderstood,
we moue no contronersie:
but that it doth properly apperteine
to the ciuil magistrat, to be the highest
gouernor of al persons within his
dominion, so that the soueraign Empyre
of God be kept whol. But herein
resteth all the doubt, howe this is
truely to be vnderstoode, &amp; that shal
we best vnderstand by the contrarie:
namely by the vsurped tiranny of antichrist.
For antichrist did challenge
vnto himselfe al authority, both that
which is proper to god, &amp; that which
is cōmon to men. Therefore that the
pope claimed to be that only head of
the church, frō which the whol body
receiued direction, &amp; was kept in vnity
of faith: This was blasphemous
against Christ, &amp; therfore may not be
vsurped by any Ciuill magistrate, no
more thē by the pope. Likewise, wher
hee challengeth authoritye to alter,
change &amp; dispence with the cōmandement
of god, to make new articles
of faith, to ordain new sacramēts, &amp;c.

this is also blasphemous and ought
not to be vsurped of any ciuil prince,
On the other side, where he challengeth
authority ouer all princes, &amp; so
ouer al the clergy, that he did exempt
them from the ciuil iurisdiction, this
is contumelious, &amp; iniurious against
al christian kings. And therfore euery
prince in his own dominiō, ought
to cast off the yoke of his subiection,
and to bring al ecclesiastical persons
vnto his obedience and iurisdiction.
Here haue we the first part of the title
of supreame gouernment ouer al
persons. In matter or causes ecclesiastical:
likewise, the pope doth not only
presume against god, as we said before:
but also against the lawfull authority,
giuen by God vnto men. For
he forbiddeth princes to medle with
reformation of Ecclesiasticall matters,
or to make anye lawes pertayning
to causes of religion, answering
them, that those things do appertain
onlye to him &amp; the general counsel.
But when he cōmeth to debate anye
thing with his clergy, then al laws &amp;

knowledge, are enclosed in the closet
of his brest. When any generall
counsel must be holden, all that they
doe receiueth authoritie from him.
For except he doe allowe, it is nothing.
And he is so wyse, that neyther
with the councell, nor without
the counsell he can erre or thinke amisse
in matters Ecclesiasticall: wheras
it is not onely lawful, but also necessary
for Princesse, if they will doe
their dutie, to looke to the reformation
of religion, and to make lawes
of matters Ecclesiasticall, but so that
we confounde not the offices of the
Prince and the Pastour. Eor, as it is
not lawfull for the Prince to preach,
nor administer the Sacramentes: no
more is it lawfull for him to make
lawes in Ecclesiastical causes, contrarie
to the knowledge of his learned
Pastors. For, as these three partes of
a pastors dutie, are graunted to him
by God, preaching, ministring of sacraments,
and Ecclesiasticall gouernment:
he maye no more take from a
Pastor the third, then he may the two

first. By this it appeareth, how farre
it is lawful for Princes to intermedle
with causes Ecclesiasticall: namelye
that it is the chiefest poynt of their
dutie, to haue especiall regarde that
God may be glorified in their dominion,
and therefore they ought to
make ciuill lawes to binde the people
vnto the confession of true faith,
and the right administring and receiuing
of the sacramentes, and to all
ecclesiastical orders, that they beeing
instructed by the worde of God, thorow
the ministerie of the preaching
of the same, shall vnderstande to bee
profitable for edifying of the church
of Christe, and the aduauncement of
the glory of God. If any shall offende
against the laws, whether he be preacher
or hearer, beside the ecclesiasticall
censure, which he shoulde not escape,
he is also to be punished in bodye
by the ciuill magistrate. This we
see that all christian Emperours obserued,
that when anye controuersie
arose, either of doctrine, or of order
and ceremonies, they commaunded

the Cleargie to consult &amp; determine
thereof, according to the scripture,
who assembling togeather incounsel
obeyed their commandement. Their
conclusion then by authoritie of the
Emperour, was commaunded euerye
where to be obserued, and those that
impugned it, to be punished: the same
order we reade also to bee obserued,
by the christian kinges of Fraunce &amp;
Spaine, yea and of this our Brittany
also, in gouerning their Ecclesiastical
state, by the aduise of the Cleargie of
their dominion. But it will perhaps
be sayd, that for Princes to subscribe
to the determination of priestes (as
they call them) is no supremacie, but
a subiection. We answer, it is no subiection
vnto men, but to God &amp; his
worde, to doe nothing in these matters,
but by the faithfull aduise of
thē, that know his will, &amp; are bounde
to teach it vnto all men: No more
then it is to be counted a subiection
for a Prince in ciuill affayres, to follow
the aduise of wise and faithfull
Counsellers. Whereby we see that if

Gods ordinaunce were not plaine in
the scriptures, yet reason it self wold
conclude, that if in Temporal matters,
a wise prince wil doe nothing of
weight, without the counsell of wise
men: how much more in Gods busines
which are of greatest importāce,
shold they not decree any thing with
out the aduise of them, that be learned
in those matters. And if all princes
by heathen wise mens iudgments
are so rulers, that they are seruaunts
of the laws, &amp; of the cōmon wealth:
why should it be accounted for anye
dishonour vnto princes, to be obedient
to the lawes of God their father,
and to serue to the commoditie of
the church their mother? It is a greater
honor to be the son of God, and
the child of the church, then to be a
monarch of al the earth. Of this honourable
subiection to GOD and
his church. Esay prophesieth Chapiter.
49. 23. Kinges shall be thy nursing
Fathers,
               Esay. 49. 23. 
               and Queenes shall bee thy
Nurses. They shall worship thee with their
faces towardes the earth, and licke the dust

of thy feete, and thou shalt know that I am
the Lord. The prophet meaneth, that
Kinges and Queenes shal be so careful,
for the preseruatiō of the church,
that they shall thinke no seruice too
base for them, so they maye profite
the Church of Christ withal. Vnto
this honourable subiection, the
holy Ghost exhorteth princes in the
second psalme: after that they haue
tryed that they preuayle nothing in
stryuing againste the kingdome of
Christ: Be now therefore wise (O yee
Kinges):
               Psal. 2. 10. 11 
               be learned that iudge the earth,
serue the Lord with feare, and reioyce vnto
him with trembling, Declaring that it
is a ioyfull seruice to bee obedient
to Christ: yea to serue GOD is indeede
to reigne. And especiallye
it is to be noted, where Saint Paule
commaundeth prayers and supplications,
to bee made for the conuersion
of Kinges vnto the knowledge
of the truth, and their own saluation,
that he alleadgeeth this reason,1. Tim. 2. 2.
               That we may lead a quiet and peaceable
life, in all Godlinesse and honestie vnder

their protection. A godly and honest
life, wee may liue, vnder enemies of
the Churche and persecutors: but a
peaceable and quiet life in all godlinesse
and honesty, only vnder a christian
Prince. This thing therefore the
Church most humbly desireth of the
prince: for this end the Church continually
prayeth to GOD for the
Prince: in this respect the Churche
most obediently submitteth her self
vnto the Prince, as a Childe to his
nurce, that both prince and people
may honour God in this life, and after
this life, reigne with Christe euerlastingly.
            Thus haue we breefely set foorth a
form of reformation, touching matters
ecclesiastical (as we are throughly
perswaded) agreeable to the word
of God, and as we are able to proue,
consenting with the example of the
primitiue Church, building only vppon
the most sure foundation of the
canonicall scriptures: but intending
more at large, if occasion shall serue,
hereafter to set foorth, the practize

and consent of the Godly fathers in
their Actes, Counsels and writinges,
following the same rule &amp; interpretation
of the scripture that we haue
done. Therfore we protest before the
liuing God and his holy Angels, and
before the Lord Iesus Christ, that shal
come to iudge the quicke and the
dead, and before the Queenes maiestie
our most gratious Soueraigne, &amp;
the whole assemblie of all estates of
this Realme: that as the whol world
may plainly see, we seeke hereby not
our owne profite, ease nor aduancement,
but onely the glorye of God,
and the profite of his Church: so by
this present writing, wee discharge
our conscience, according to our dutie
which is to shew vnto all men the
true waye of reformation: and to
mooue them that haue authoritie to
put it in practize, and to seeke by all
lawfull and ordinarye meanes, that it
may take place, that if it may please
God to giue it good successe, at this
time to be imbraced, we maye fulfill
the rest of our course with ioy. But if

our sinnes be the let, that this or the
like groūded vpon Gods worde, may
not now be receiued: yet the present
age may see &amp; iudge, what is the vttermost
of our desire, concerning reformation,
which hitherto for lacke
of such a publike testimoniall, hath
been subiect to infinite slaunders, deuised
by the aduersaries of Gods
truth &amp; hinderance of Godly procedings
vnto reformatiō. And that the
posterity may know that the truth in
this time, was not generallye vnknowen
nor vntestified, concerning the
right regiment of the church of god:
nor this disordered forme of ecclesiasticall
gouernement, which we haue
receiued for the most part of popery,
deliuered to our Children without
contradictiō, that our example shold
not be preiudicial vnto them: as the
exāple of our Godly fathers (which
in this poynt neglected their duetie)
hath beene preiudiciall vnto vs. The
Lorde graunt for Christes sake, that
we beeing so farre from perfection,
God may open al our eyes to see the

same, and bend our heartes earnestly
to labour to attaine therevnto: and
in the mean time, so farre as we haue
attained, that we may proceede al by
one rule, that we may be like affectioned
to seeke the glory of God, and
to build vp the ruynes of his temple,
that with one hearte and with one
voyce, we maye praise the Father of
our Lorde Iesus Christ in his holye
Temple, which is the congregation
of saints in the holy ghost,
to whom be al honor &amp;
Dominion for euermore.
Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

