
   
      
         
            Articles to be enquired of vvithin the diocesse of London In the third trienniall visitation of the Right Honourable, and Right Reverend Father in God, William, Lord Bishop of London, Lord High Treasurer of England. Holden in the yeare of our Lord God, 1640
            Visitation articles. 1640
            Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1633-1660 : Juxon)
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00214
            STC 10267
            ESTC S101627
            99837436
            99837436
            1757
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00214)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1757)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1485:7)
         
         
            
               
                  Articles to be enquired of vvithin the diocesse of London In the third trienniall visitation of the Right Honourable, and Right Reverend Father in God, William, Lord Bishop of London, Lord High Treasurer of England. Holden in the yeare of our Lord God, 1640
                  Visitation articles. 1640
                  Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1633-1660 : Juxon)
                  Juxon, William, 1582-1663.
                  Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662.
               
               [28] p.   
               
                  Printed by Richard Badger,
                  London :
                  M.DC.XL [1640]
               
               
                  Drawn up by Peter Heylyn.
                  Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges --  Early works to 1800.
               Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-10
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-11
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-02
            AptaraRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2003-04
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ARTICLES
TO BE
ENQUIRED OF
Within the Diocesse of
LONDON.
            
            In the third Trienniall Visitation
Of the Right Honourable, and
Right Reverend Father in GOD,
WILLIAM,
Lord Bishop of LONDON,
Lord High Treasurer of ENGLAND.
Holden in the Yeare of our LORD GOD, 1640
            LONDON,
Printed by RICHARD BADGER.
M.DC.XL
         
         
            
            The Oath to be administred to the
Church-wardens and Sworn-men.
            YOu shall sweare that you and every of you shall diligently enquire of
the Articles given you in charge; and without any affection, favour,

                  〈◊〉
               , hope of reward and gaine, or feare of displeasure, or malice of
any person, you shall present all and every such person and persons that now
is, or 
                  •
               f late was within your Parish, as hath committed any incest, adultery,
fornication, or simony, and any misdemeanour or disturbances committed or
made in any Church or Ch
                  •
               ppell, in time of Common Prayer, Preaching, or
Divine Service there used, to the disturbance thereof: and also that have committed
or done any other offence, fault or default, presentable in the E
                  •
               clesiasticall
Court, according to the Articles now delivered to you. Wherein you
shall deale uprightly and according to truth, neither of malice presenting any
contrary to truth, nor of corrupt affection sparing to present any, and 
                  •
               o conceale
the truth: having in this action God before your eyes, with an earnest
zeale to maintaine the truth, and suppresse vice. So helpe you God, and the
Contents of this Booke.
         
      
      
         
            
            Articles to be enquired of within the Diocesse
of LONDON, in the Visitation to be holden
in the Yeare of our LORD, 1640.
            
               Concerning Religion, and the true worship of God▪
In This Realme established.
               
                  IS there any who doth affirme &amp; teach that
the 39▪ Articles agréed upon by th
                     •
                   Archbishops
and Bishops in b
                     •
                  th Provinces,Can. 5. and the whole
Clergie, in the Convocation h
                     •
                  lden at London,
Anno▪
                   1562. are in any part superstitio
                     •
                  s or

                     〈◊〉
                  , or such as hée may not with a good
conscience subscribe unto? Who is that so
teacheth or affirmeth, and what is his name?
               2 Is there any who doth affirme and 
                     •
                  ea
                     •
                  h▪
that the forme of Gods worship in the Church of

                     ••
                  gland,Can. 4. established by the Law, and contai
                     ••
                  d in the booke of Common

                     •
                  rayer and administration of Sacraments, is a corrupt, superstitio
                     •
                  s,

                     〈◊〉
                   unlawfull worship of God, or containeth any thing in it that is rep
                     •
                  g
                  
                     ••
                  nt,
to the Scriptures, Who is it that so teacheth, &amp;c.?
               
               3 Is there any who doth affirme or teach,Can. 6. that the Rites and Ceremo
                  
                     •
                  ies
of the Church of England by Law established, are wicked, antichristian,
or superstitious, or such as being commanded by lawfull Authoritie,

                     •
                  ay not with good cons
                     •
                  ience 
                     •
                  ee approved, used, or subscribed unto, by
men who are zealously and godly affected, who is it, &amp;c?
               
               4 Is there any that separateth himselfe from the Communion of
Saints,Can. 9. as it is approved by the Apostles Rules in the Church of England,
and c
                     •
                  mbine themselves together in a new brother-hood, accounting the
Christians who are conformable to the Doctrine, Governement, 
                     •
                  ites,
and Ceremonies of the Church of England, to be prophane or unmeet for
him to ioyne within Christian profession, who are they that so separa
                     •
                  e

                     ••
                  mselves, and what are their names?
            
            
               
               Concerning the Church, the Governement, Authoritie,
and Discipline thereof.
               1 IS there any who doth affirme or teach,Can. 3. that the Church of
England by Law established under the Kings Maiestie, is not a true
and Apostolicall Church, teaching and maintaining the Doctrine of the
Apostles. Who is it that doth so affirme and teach, &amp;c?
               
               2 Is there any who doth affirme and teach,Can. 7. that the Governement of

                     •
                  he Church of England under his Maiestie by Archbishops, Bishops,
Deanes, Archdeacons, and the rest that beare office in the same, is antichristian
and repugnant to the Word of God. Who is it that doth, &amp;c.
               
               3 Is there any who doth affirme or teach,Can. 8. that the formes or manner
of making and Consecrating Bishops, Priests, and Deacons, containeth
any thing in it, that is repugnant to the Word of God: or that they who
are made Bishops, Priests, and Deacons in that forme, are not lawfully
made, nor ought to be accounted either by themselves or others, to be truly
either Bishops, Priests, or Deacons, untill they have some other calling
unto those Divine Offices. Who is it, &amp;c.
               
               4 Is there any who doth affirme or teach,Art. 20. 34. that the Church hath no
power to decree Rites or Ceremonies, nor any authoritie in Controversies
of Faith, or in the changing &amp; abolishing of Ceremonies and R
                     •
                  tes of the
Church, ordained only by mans authority, contrary to the 20. and 34.
Articles of the Church of England. Who is it, &amp;c.
               
               5 Is there any who doth affirme or teach,Can. 2. &amp; 1. that the Kings Maiestie
hath not the same Authoritie in causes Ecclesiasticall, that the godly Kings
had among the Iewes, and Christian Emperours in the Primitive
Church. Or that the Kings Maiestie within his Realmes of England,
Scotland, and Ireland, and all other his Dominions and Countries, is not
the highest Power under God, to whom all men, as well Inhabitants as
bor
                     •
                  e within the same, doe by Gods law owe most loyaltie and obedience.
Or that impeach any part his Royall Supremacie in the said causes restored
to the Crowne, and by the Lawes of the Realme therein established.
Who is it, &amp;c?
               
               6 Is there any who doth affirme or teach,
                     
                        •
                     an. 
                        •
                      4 that no manner of person
eith
                     •
                  r of the Clergie or Laitie, are to be subiect to the Decrees and Constitutions
of the Church in causes Ecclesiasticall, made and ratified by the
Kings Maiesties Supreme authoritie, other then such as are particularly
assembled in the sacred Synods of the Church for the making of the said
Decrees, and Constitutions, and have given their voices, to the same.
Who is it, &amp;c?
               
               
                  
7 Is there any that doth affirme or teach,Can. 12. that it is lawfull for any
sort of Ministers and lay persons, or either of them to ioyne together,
and make rules, orders, and Constitutions in Causes Ecclesiasticall
without the Kings Authority, or any that submit themselves to be ruled
and Governed by the same. Who is it, &amp;c?
               
               8 Is there any who doth affirme,Can. 10. teach▪ maintaine or publish, that
such Ministers who refuse to subscribe to the forme and manner of Gods
worship in the Church of England,
                  Can. 11. and their adherents may truly take unto
them the name of another Church: or that there are within this Realme,
other meetings, assemblies, or congregations of the Kings borne Subiects,
then such as by the lawes of this Land are held and allowed, which may
rightly chalenge to themselves the name of true and lawfull Churches.
Who is it that doth so affirme, &amp;c?
               
               9 Doth any Minister or Ministers,Can. 72. without the Licence and direction
of the Bishop of the Diocesse first obtained, appoint or keep any solemne
Fasts publikely, or in any private houses, other then such as are or shall
be appointed by lawfull authoritie, or not being Licensed as afore is said,
presumes to appoint or hold any meeting for Sermons, Sermon Lectures,
Prophecies, or exercises in Market Townes or other places, or doth attempt
without such Licence upon any pretence whatsoever, either of possession
or obsession, to cast out any Divell or Divels. Who is it that offendeth
in the premises, &amp;c.
               
               10 Doe any Priests or Ministers of the Word of God,Can. 73. or any other
persons meet together in any private hou
                     •
                  e or el
                     •
                  ewhere, to consult upon any
matter or course to be taken by them or by any other, upon their motion
and direction, which may any way tend to the impeaching or depraving of
the Church of E
                        •
                     gland, or of the booke of Common Prayer, or of any part
of the Government or Discipline in the Church of England now established,
and who are they?
            
            
               Concerning Churches, the Ornaments, Vtensils, and other
necessaries to the same belonging.
               1 IS your Parish Church or Chappell well and sufficiently
repaired,Can. 85. and so from time to time maintained and kept? Are the windowes
well glazed, the floare kept paved plaine and even, and all things
there in such 
                     •
                  n orderly 
                     •
                  nd decent sort, without dust, or any thing that
may bee either noysome or un
                     •
                  eemely, as best becommeth the house
of God?
               2 Are the ten Commandements set upon the East end of your Church
or Chappell,Can. 82. where the people may best see and reade the same, and other

chosen sen
                     •
                  ences written upo
                     •
                   the walls of your said Church or Chappell, in
convenient places?
               3 Doe the Cha
                     •
                  cels remaine as they have d
                     •
                  ne in times past,Rubr. before Morning Prayer. that i
                     •
                  
to say, in the convenient situation of the Seates, and in the ascent or 
                     〈◊〉
                  
unto the place appointed anciently for the standing of the holy Tab
                     ••
                  ? Is
the Chancell of your Church or Chappell cleane kept,Orders of Queene Elizabe
                        ••
                     , An. 1561. Ib. Order 
                        •
                     . and repaire
                     •
                   within
and without, in the windowes and otherwhere as appertaineth▪ And is
there a comely partition betwixt your Chancell and the body of the Church
or Chappell, as is required by the Law?
               4 Is the Church-yard of your Church or Chappell well and sufficiently
sensed,Can, 85. maintained and kept with walls, 
                     •
                  ailes or poles, as hath beene
heretofore accustomed: And if not, then by whose neglige
                     ••
                  e or default is
it, that the fenses of the same are grown into decay▪
               
               5 Are there any Playes,Can. 88. Foasts, Banquets, Suppers, Church-Ales,
Drinkings, Temporall Courts or Le
                     •
                  tes, Lay-iuries or Musters: or
is there any other prophane usage, kept in your Church, Chappell, o
                     •
                  
Churchyards, of what sort soever▪ By whom 
                     •
                  re your said Church or
Chappell, or Churchyard so prophaned as afore is said, and by whose
permission.
               6 Have you in the Chancell of your Church or Chappell a decent and
convenient Table for the celebration of the Holy Comm
                     ••
                  ion? Is i
                     •
                  
so set as is directed in the Queenes Iniunctions,Injunct. of Q▪ Eliz. Orders of Q▪ Eli
                        •
                     . and appointed by the Canon
made in the Synod held at London,
                  Can. 82. 
                  Anno 1640. Have you a Carpet
of silke or other decent stuffe, appointed by the Ordinary, to lay upon the
Table in the time of Divine Service, and a faire linnen cloth to lay upon
the same in time of the Communion? And is the said Carpet and linnen
cloth laid constantly upon the Table, at the times aforesaid?
               7 Have you a faire Communion Cup,Com. Book. or Chalice of silver, with a cover
of the same,Can. 20. and a decent standing pot or Flagon of pewter, if not of purer
metall, in which the wine for the Communion is to be brought unto
the holy Table? Is the said Table, Carpet, Linnen cloth▪ Cup, or Flagon,
or either of them any wayes prophaned, or otherwise imployed, then to
their owne proper and right holy uses?
               8 Have you in your Church or Chappell a Font of stone,Can. 81. where Baptisme
is to be administred, decently made, and kept as it ought to be? Is
the same set in the Ancient usuall place appointed for it, and doth your Minister
publikely baptize, in the same Font only?
               9 Have you in your Church or Chappell,Can. 82. 83. a convenient Seat made 
                     〈◊〉
                  
the Minister to reade Service in, as also a comely and decent Pulpit set
in a convenient place within the same for the preaching of Gods Word,
and there seemely kept?
               
                  
10 Have you in your Church or Chappell a strong Chest with an hole
in the upper part thereof,Can. 84 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   the Almes of the poore? Hath the same chest
three severall keyes, and is the one of them in the castodie of the Parson,
Uicar, or Curat? Is the same so set and fastened in the most convenient

                     〈◊〉
                  , to the intent the parishioners may put into it their Almes, for their
poore neighbours?
               11 Have you a true note and Terrar,Can. 
                        •
                     7 of all the Glebes, Lands, Meadowes,
Gardens, Orchards, Houses, stockes, implements, Tenements
and portions of tythes lying out of your Parish, which belong unto your
Parsonage, or Uicarage? And is the same, or a true Coppie of the same
layed up in the Bishops Registry for a perpetuall Memory thereof?
               12 Have you a comely decent Surplisse with sleeves for the use of your
Minister in saying the publike prayers,Can. 58. or ministring the Sacraments,
and other rites of the Church: together with an Universitie hood, according
to the degree of your said Minister? And doth the Parson, Uicar, or
Cu
                     ••
                  te use the same, as oft as he officiates Gods publike Service, administreth
the Sacraments, or dischargeth any publike duty in the Congregation?
               13 Have you a Bible of the largest volume,Can. 80. allowed by Authoritie,
the booke of Common Prayer, and the booke of Homilies, all very well,
and fairely bound? As also a booke of the Canons And Constitutions,
made in the Synod held at London, Anno 1603. and ratified by the Kings
Authority? A booke of prayers for the 5. of November, and for the 27. of
March being the day of his Maiesties most happy Inauguration?
               Have you a parchment Register booke wherein to keep upon record,Can. 70▪
                  
the severall Christenings, Weddings, and Burials, which happen weekly,
quarterly,Can. 52 or yearly, in your Parish? Have you also a Register booke
wherein to write the names of all Preachers, which come and Preach in
your Church from other places?Can. 70 And have you one sure Co
                     •
                  er with thrée
lockes and keyes, for keeping of the bookes aforesaid. And doth one of your
keyes remaine alwayes in the hands of your Minister?
               Whether is your Parsonage-house or Vicarage-house, Barnes, Stables,
and other out-houses thereto belonging, in good and sufficient repaire.
               Whether hath any person in
                     •
                  roached upon the ground of your Churchyard,
or other consecrated ground, if any hath, then you shall present him,
and set out what quantitie of ground is so incroached upon, and whether any
new doore or window hath be
                     •
                  ne lately made into your Church or Churchyard▪
and by what authority?
            
            
               
               Concerning the Celebration of Divine Service, the
Administration of the Sacraments. &amp;c.
               DOth your Minister or Curate that ministreth in your Parish
Church or Chappell,Rubrick after the Pre
                        •
                     ace. say daily the Morning and Evening Prayer,
in the same Parish Church or Chappell where he ministreth, unlesse he
be lawfully hindered? And d
                     •
                  th he cause a Bell to be tolled thereunto, a
convenient time before he begin, that such as be disposed may come to heare
Gods Word, and to pray with him? Especially,
               Is the Common Prayer said or sung distinctly and rev
                     •
                  rently
upon such dayes as are appointed to be kept holy,Can. 14▪
                   and upon their E
                     •
                  es?
Is the same said or sung at convenient and usu
                     •
                  ll times of those dayes, and
in such pl
                     •
                  ce of every Church, as the people may be most edified thereby?
And doth the Pars
                     •
                  n U
                     •
                  car or Curate▪ observe the Orders Rites and Ceremonies
prescribed in the booke of Common Prayer, as well in reading the
holy Scripture, and saying of prayers, a
                     •
                   in administration of the Sacraments:
without either diminishing in regard of Preaching, or in any other
respect, or adding any thing, in the matter and forme thereof?
               2 Doth the Minister reade the Psalmes,Rub
                        •
                     i
                        •
                     k of the Common P
                        •
                     ayer booke▪
                   and Lessons appointed in the
Kalendar for Morning and Evening Prayer? And at the end of every
Psalme throughout the yeare, and likewise at the end of the Benedictus,
Benedicite, Magnificat, and Nunc dimittis, doth he repeate, Glory be to the
Father, &amp;c. And at the reading of the Lessons, doth he stand and turne
him so, as he may best be heard of all such as be present? And is the Creed
called Athanasius Creed, beginning with (Whosoever will be saved) said
by your Minister constantly at the times appointed in the Common Prayer
booke, and doth your Minister sing or say any other Psalmes or Hymns
other then aforesaid in the place of those, contrary to Law?
               3 Doth your Parson,Can. 15. Uicar, or Curate, say the Letanie on every Sunday
duely throughout the yeare▪ as also upon all Wednesdayes and Fridaies
weekely, though they be not holy-dayes? In what convenient place
of your Church or Chappell doth hee say the same, and by whom was that
place appointed? Doth hee say the same at the accustomed houres of Service,
and is there warning giuen to the people by the tolling of a Bell?
And doth euery house-holder dwelling within halfe a mile of the Church,
come, or send one at the least of his houshold to ioyne with the Minister?
               4 Doth your Minister read the Communion Service,Rubr. f
                        ••
                     r the Communion. or the second
Service on every Sunday and Holyday throughout the yeare, though
                     •
                   there
bee no Communion, according as it is appointed in the Booke of Common
Prayer?
               
                  
5 Doth your Parson re
                     •
                  ide upon his Bene
                     ••
                  ce or not,Can. 4
                        •
                     
                   If yea, then, being
a licensed Preacher, doth he preach one Sermon every Sunday in the
yeare in his owne Cure,Can. 4
                        •
                      46▪
                   or in some Church or Chappell neare adioyning,
having no lawfull impediment? And being not a licensed Preacher, doth
he offer at any time to preach or expound the Scriptures, or rather doth he
procure Sermons to bee Preache
                     •
                   in his Cure once every moneth at the
least by Preachers which bee lawfully licensed?Can. 47 If he be licensed by the
Lawes of this Realme not to reside upon his Benef
                     •
                  ce, then in that Case
doth he supply his cure by one that is a sufficient and Licensed Preacher?
And is your Curate allowed to serve there by the Bishop of the Diocesse,Can. 48
or by the Ordinary of the place having Episcopall iurisdiction, and by
no other?
               6 Doth your Parson,Rubr▪
                   Uicar, or Curate upon every Sunday and holyday
throughout the yeare when there is no Sermon, reade one of the Homilies
set forth by publike Authority? Doth he use to read the same in the
Pulpit only, according as he is required in the Canons of the yeare 1571.Cap. 4.
And doth your Minister as well before the Homilie as before his Sermon
move and exhort the people 
                     •
                  o ioyne with him in Prayer according to the
forme laid downe in the book of Canons,Can. 55 and doth hee use any other forme
then is there prescribed?
               7 Have you in your Parish,Can. 55▪
                   besides your Parson, Uicar, and Curate,
any Lecturer or Lecturers not having cure of soules therein?Can. 56 Doth your
Lecturer use before his Lectures, the forme of prayer before remembred,
and no other forme? And doth he twice at the least every yeare read the
Divine Service on two severall Sundaies both in the fore-noone and afternoone,
publikely and at the usuall times, and doth he as oft in every yeare
administer the Sacraments of Baptisme and the Lords Supper, in such
manner and form, and with the observation of such Rites and Ceremonies
as are prescribed in the book of Common Prayer?
               8 Doe your Lecturer or Lecturers preach in their Gownes and not in
their Cloaks, according to his Maiesties Instructions, An. 1629. Doth he
professe his willingnesse to take upon him a Living with cure of soules, in
that place or Parish, in the which he Lectures or elsewhere. And doth he
actually take such Cure or Benef
                     •
                  ce if any hath beene offered to him?
               9 Is your Lecturer licensed by the Bishop of the Diocesse?Can. 5
                        •
                     
                   And doth
your Lecturer or any other Preacher that Lectureth or preacheth in your
Church or Chappell, impugne or confute any Doctrine formerly delivered
in the same, or in any Church neare adioyning, before hee hath acquainted
the Bishop of the Diocesse therewith, and received order from him what
to doe in that case for the avoiding of dissention?
               10 Doth your Lecturer conforme himselfe to the Lawes,can. 5
                        •
                     
                   Ordinances,

a
                     •
                  d Rites Ecclesiasticall established in the Church of England? If not, you
are to certifie the same unto the Bishop of the Diocesse, or other Ordinary
of the place, to the end that if the said Lecturer doe not conforme himselfe
after admonition, his Licence may be voided, and himselfe removed?
               11 Doth your Parson,Can. 21▪
                   Uicar, or Curate, administer the Communion
in your Church or Chappell so often, and at such times, as every parishioner
may communicate at least thrice in the yeare, whereof the Feast of Easter
to be one?Can. 2
                        •
                     
                     ▪
                   And doth he give warning to his parishioners publikely in the
Church at Morning prayer the Sunday before, for the better preparation of
themselves? And doe such as purpose to communicat
                     •
                   signifie their minds
unto the 
                     •
                  urate over night or the morning early?
               12 Doth your Minister admit to the receiving of the holy Communion,Can. 26▪
                  
such of his Cure which be openly knowne to live in sinne notorious
without repentance, or any who have openly or maliciously contended with
their neighbours, and will not be induced by him to a reconcilement? Or
any Church-wardens or Sidemen, who having taken oath to present to
their Ordinaries every such publike offence, as they are particularly
charged to enquire of in their severall parishes, shall wittingly incurre the
horrible crime of periurie?
               13 Doth he wittingly administer the same to any but to such as kneel,Can. 27.
or to any that refuse to bee present at the publike prayers, or to any that bee
common and notorious depravers of the booke of Common-prayer, or of any
thing contained in the Booke of Articles agreed upon in the Convocation,
Anno 1562. Or in the booke of Ordering Priests and Bishops, or to
any that hath spoken against, and depraved his Maiesties Soveraigne Authority
in causes Ecclesiasticall, except such persons doe first acknowledge
to the Minister before you the Church-wardens that hee is sorry for the
same, and promise either by word of mouth, or under his hand to doe so
no more?
               14 Is the bread provided for the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper,
                     
                        •
                     ubr.
of the best and purest white-bread that may conveniently be gotten?
Doth the Minister take the same into his hands to blesse and consecrate it
to that holy use as oft as he administreth the Communion? Doth he
so likewise with the wine provided? And if any bread or wine bee newly
brought, doth he first use the words of the Institution before it be distributed
to the Communicants?
                     
                        •
                     an. 
                        •
                     1.
               
               15 Doth your Minister as oft as he celebrateth the Communion,
                     
                        •
                     ubr.
receive the Sacrament first in both kindes himselfe,
                     
                        •
                     an. 21. and having so received
the same, doth he severally deliver the bread and wine to every Communicant
in their ha
                     •
                  ds knéeling? And at his delivery of the same, doth hee
reherse the whole forme mentioned in the Communion Booke saying (The

body of our Lord Iesus Christ, &amp;c.) or doth he only use some part thereof, as
he list himselfe?
               16 Doth your Parson Uicar or Curate administer the Communion
at any time publikely in the congregation except there be foure or three (at
the least) to communicate with him?Rubr. &amp; Doth he administer the same to any
strangers, which come often and commonly from their owne Parish Churches?
And doe you the Church-wardens give notice to your Minister of
such strangers,Can. 28. 57. that so hee may remit them home to their owne Parish
Churches, there to Communicate with th
                     •
                  ir owne Minister and
neighbours?
               17 Doth your Minister,Can. 71▪
                   except it be in times and cases of necessity,
Preach or administer the holy Communion in any private house in which
there is no Chappell dedicated and allowed by the Ecclesiasticall lawes of
this Kingdome? Doth any Chaplaine living within your parish, preach
or administer the Communion in any other place then in the Chappell of
the said houses? Doth the Lords and Masters of such Chaplaines, or houses,
at other times resort to their owne Parish Churches,Instructions. and there receive
the holy Communion, at least once in the yeare? And doe any under Noble
men, and men qualified by law keepe any private Chaplaine in their
house or houses?
               18 Doth your Minister refuse or delay to Christen any child that is
brought to him to the Church on Sundayes or Holy-dayes,Can. 6
                        •
                     
                     ▪
                   knowledge thereof
being given to him over night or in the morning before Morning prayer?Rubr▪ o
                        •
                      Bap.
Doth hee proceed therein in all things according to the forme of publike
Baptisme in the Common prayer Booke,Can. 30. doth he neglect, refuse, or pretermit
at any time to signe the child baptized with the signe of the crosse,
or doth hee admit the parent of a childe to answer as a Godfather to his own
childe,Can. 29. or any other person to be a Godfather or Godmother, before the said
pers
                     •
                  n so undertaking hath received the holy Communion?
               19 Doth your Minister being duly informed of the weaknesse and danger
of death of any infant unbaptized in his Parish, and being thereupon
desired to goe unto the place and baptize the same, either wilfully refuse to
d
                     •
                  e it,Can▪ 69 or negligently delay the time, so that the child departeth without
Baptisme 
                     •
                  hrough his def
                     •
                  ult: if the childe so baptized doe recover afterwards,
is it brought into the Church by the Godfathers and Godmothers,
to the intent the congregation may bee certified of the Baptizing thereof,
according to the 
                     •
                  orme prescribed in the Common prayer Book?
               20 Doth your Minister having Cure and charge of 
                     •
                  oules,Can. 61 doe his best
endeavour to prepare children,Can▪ 59. and make them ready for confirmation?
And to that end,Rubr. of Con
                        •
                     ir. doth hee on every Sunday and Holyday before Evening
prayer for the space of halfe an houre or more instruct the youth and ignorant▪
                  
persons of the parish, according 
                     〈◊〉
                   the Catechisme set forth in the Common
prayer booke? And are the afternoone Sermons in your
                     •
                   parish (if you
had any formerly) turned into Catechising by way of questions and answers
according to the Kings Instructions?Inst
                        •
                     ucti
                     
                        •
                     ns▪
                  
               
               21 Doth your Minister either bring,Rub. of Confirm. or send in writing to the Bishop
of the Diocesse the names of all those Children of his parish which can
answer to the questions contained in the Catechisme, that by the imposition
of hands and prayer, they may receive strength and defence against temptation?
And doth he admit any person or persons to y• holy Comm
                     •
                  nion, untill
such time as he or they can orderly say the catechisme and be confirmed?
               22 Doth your Parson,Can. 62. Uicar, or Curate celebrate Matrimony betwixt
any persons, without a facultie or Licence granted by authority Lawfull,
or without the Banes of Matrimony first published, on three severall
Sundayes or Holydayes, in the parish Church or Chappell where the said
parties dwell, or at the times by Law prohibited without speciall Licence:
Or doth he celebrate the same in any other place than in the Church, or in
the Church at any other time than betweene the hours of eight and twelve
in the forenoone, and at that time betwixt such persons as are under the age
of twenty one yeares, without the consent of their parents signifie
                     •
                   unto
him▪ or a Licence granted to him so to doe?
               23 Doth your Minister in the solemnizing of holy Matrimony keepe
himselfe to the forme and Ceremonies prescribed in the Common Prayer
booke,Rubr▪ of Matrimo
                     
                        •
                     ie. doth he at any time marry any without a King, or without going to
the Lords Table, as it is appointed: Doth he in case there bee no Sermon
read those Texts of Scripture, wherein the offices of man and wife, are declared,
according as it is prescribed? And doe the new married persons the
same day of their marriage receive the holy Communion, as by Law they
ought?
               24 Doth your Minister or Curate resort to such of your parish as are
dangerously sick (if the disease be n
                     •
                  t probably suspected to be infectious) to
instruct and comfort them in that distresse,Can. 87. doth hee exhort the sick party to
be in charity with all the world,Rubr. of 
                        •
                     isitation. and to dispose of his goods, and declare his
debts, and doth he move him and that most earnestly to liberalitie towards
the poore, and to unburden his conscience?
               25 If any sick person finde his conscience troubled with anyweighty
matter,Rubr. of Visitation. and doth unburden the same to his Priest or Minister, doth the
said Priest or Minister give him absolution according to the forme prescribed:Can. 130
And have you ever heard that the said Priest or Minister hath revealed
and made knowne at any time to any person whatsoever, any crime
or 
                     •
                  ffence committed to his trust and secrecy, either in case of such extremity,
or any other case whatsoever (except they be such crimes as by the lawes of

this Realme, the life of the sai
                     •
                   Priest or Minister ma
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  e called in questi
                     •
                  n
for concealing of it) declare the name of the offender, when and by
whome you heare the 
                     •
                  ame?
               26 Doth the Curate that ministreth in your parish,Rubrick of Com. upon convenient
notice giuen him, administer the Communion unto such as be dangerously
sicke, and not able to come unto the Church, and yet are desirous to receive
the same in their houses, and are unquiet for he lack thereof: Or doth hee
obstinately and wilfully refuse so to doe being thereunto required, and finding
all things necessary for the doing of it?
               27 Doth your minister refuse or delay to bury any corps that is
brought into the Church or Church-yard,Can. 68. convenient warning being given
him before, except the partie deceased were denounced excommunicate for
some grievous crime, Majori Excommunicatione, and no man able to testifie
of his repentance: And doth he do it decently and gravely, not swerving
from the forme prescribed by the Church in the Common prayer booke?
               28 Doth any woman in your parish after her delivery from the paines
and perill of Childbirth refuse to come into the Church to render thanks to
God for so great a mercy: Doth she goe thither covered with a decent veil
according to the laudable and ancient custome: And being come doth she
goe▪ n
                     •
                  ere unto the place where the Table standeth,Rubr. and offereth her accustomed
offerings: And doth your Minister doe his dutie in churching the
said women according to the forme prescribed: And doth the woman that
commeth to give her tha
                     •
                  kes▪ receive the holy Communion if there by any?
               29 Doth your Minister at and upon seasonable times, especially on the
first day of Lent, cause the people, to bee called together and assembled in
the Church by the ringing of a Bell: And being drawne together doth hee
read unto them the commination against sinners, with the other prayers
appointed?
            
            
               Concerning the Clergie, their Duty, Carriage▪ &amp;c.
               DOth your Parson,Can. 1. Uicar, Curate, or Lecturer, (if you
have any) purely and syncerely teach, manifest and declare foure times
every yeare at the least in his Sermons and other Collations and Lectures
that all usurped and forraigne power is for most iust cau
                     •
                  es taken away
and abolished, and that therefore no obedience or subiection within his
Maiesties Realmes and Dominions, is due unto any such forraigne power.
And doth he preach the Doctrine of obedience, and the Kings authority according
to the Canons published, and set out by the late holy Synod,Can. 64.
                  Anno 1640.Rub. of Com.
               
               2 Doth your Minister declare to the parishioners, every Sunday at

the time appointed in the Communion booke whether there be any Holydayes
or fasting-dayes in the following weeke: And doth hee call upon
them to observe the same, according to the Lawes of the Land, and of holy
Church?
               3 Doth your Minister or Curate in the Rogation dayes goe in perambulation
about your parish saying and using the Psalmes and suffrages by
Law appointed,Injunctions and Adver
                        •
                     isements of Q Eliz
                        •
                     b. as viz. Psalme 103. &amp; 104. the Letany and suffrages, together
with the Homily set out for that end and purpose: Doth hee admonish
the people to give thankes to God, if they see any likely hopes of plenty, and
to call upon him for his mercy, if there be any feare of scarcitie: And doe
you the Churchwardens assist him in it?
               4 Doth your Curate serve more then one Church or Chappell upon one
day,Can. 48. except the said Chappell be a member of the parish Church or united
thereto:Can An. 1571. Cap. ult. How farre distant are the said Churches or Chappels which he
serveth from one another? What wages hath he for his paines?
               5 Doth your Minister if he be commanded by the Ordinary,Can. 65. openly
on some Sunday denounce and declare for excommunicate, all those, who
either for refusing to frequent the divine service of the Church, or for notorious
contumacie, or other notable crimes stand lawfully excommunicated
by the lawes of the Church, that others thereby may bee admonished to refraine
their Companies: And doth your Minister himselfe refraine th
                     •
                  
company of persons excommunicated and so denounced?
               6 Doth your Parson,Can. 74. Uicar, or Curate usually weare such apparell as
is prescribed by the Canon, that is to say, a gowne with standing colla
                     •
                  
and wide sleeves straite at the hands, and a square cap: Or doth hee go
                     •
                  
at any time abroade in his dublet and ho
                     •
                  e without coat or cassock, or doth
he use to weare any light coloured stockings, d
                     •
                  th he weare any 
                     •
                  oi
                     •
                  e, and
wrought nightcaps, or only plaine night-caps of silke, sattin, or velvet:
And in his iourneying, doth he usually weare a cloake with sleeves, commonly
called the Priests cloak, without guards, we
                     •
                  ts, long buttons
or cuts?
               7 Doth your Parson,Can. 75. Uicar, or Curate resort at any time, other then
for his honest necessities to any Tavernes, or Ale
                     •
                  ouses, or doth your Curate
lodge or board, in any such places: Doe they or either of them give
themselves to any base or servile labour, or to drinking or Riot, or to playing
at di
                     •
                  e, cards or tables, or to an
                     •
                   other unlawfull game, or games: or
doe they otherwise spend their time idly by day or by night?
               8 Is there any in your Parish,Can. 76. who having beene a Deacon or Minister
hath voluntaryly relinquished his calling, and doth u
                     •
                  e himselfe in the
course of his li
                     •
                  e as a lay man, what are their names that have forsaken
their said callinge?
               
                  
9 Doth your Minister (if he be a Preacher,Can. 66▪
                   and thought fit by your
Bishop) having any popish Recusant, or Recusants in his parish, labour
diligently with them from time to time,Can. 66. thereby to reclaime them from
their errours: And if he be n
                     •
                   Preacher, or not such a Preacher, doth hee
procure some that are Preachers so qualified, to take paines with them to
that purpose?
               10 Doth your Parson,Can. 114 Uicar, or Curate, carefully informe himselfe
every yeare, how many popish Recusants, men, woemen, and children above
the age of thirteene yeares, or being otherwise popishly given, are inhabitants
within their parish or parishes, or make their abode there, either
as soiourners or common guests?
               11 Doth your Minister every Sunday weekly (if there be occasion) in
the presence of you the Churchwardens,Can. 70. write and record in the▪ Register-booke
the names of all persons christened, together with the names and surnames
of their parents, as also, the names and surnames of all persons
married and buried in that parish the weeke before, and the day and 
                     •
                  eare
of every such Christening, Marriage, and Burial, and unto every page therof
when it is fild, do you and your said Minister subscribe your names: And
is a true coppie of the said Christnings, Marriages, and Burials, subscribed
with the names of your Minister and you the Churchwardens, transmit
                     •
                  ed
yearely within one moneth after the 25 of March, unto the Bishop
of the Dio
                     •
                  esse to be preserved in his Registry?
               12 Doth your Minister in the parish Church or Chappell, where

                     •
                  ee hath charge, reade the Canons, Orders, and Constitutions,
(agreed on in the Synod held at London, Anno 1603.) once every yeare
upon some Sundayes or Holydayes in the afternoone before Divine Service:
and doth he so divide the same, as the one halfe may be read one day▪
and the other halfe the other day?
               Whether hath your Minister, Churchwardens, and Sidemen, presented
unto the Lord Bishop of London, or his Chancellour, within fortie dayes after

                     •
                  aster, the names of all the Parishioners, as well men as woemen, which being

                     •
                  bove 16. yeares of age, received not the Communion, at or about Easter be
                  
                     •
                  ore
according to the 112. Canon; If not, you shall present, whether that

                     •
                  resentment should have beene brought in by your selves or your predecessors,

                     •
                  nd specifie the names of every one that should have made such presentment at

                     •
                  aster last past?
            
            
               
               Concerning Schoolemasters, Parish Clarkes, and Sextens.
               DOth any man in your Parish 
                     •
                  each either in publike Schoo
                     •
                  
or 
                     ••
                  iva
                     •
                  e house,Can. 77. but such as 
                     •
                  e allowed by the Bishop of the Diocesse
or other Ordinary of the place under his hand and Seale:Can. 78. And if there 
                     〈◊〉
                  
no publike Grammer-schoole founded in y
                     •
                  ur parish, doth any other teac
                     •
                  
Schoole in your parish, than your Cura
                     •
                  e only, if he be willing so to doe?
               2 Doth your Schoolemaster teach in English or Latine,Can. 79. as the chil
                     •
                  dren
are able to beare, the shorter or longer Catechisme set forth by Autho
                     •
                  rity
and no other: doth he on Sundayes and Holydayes when there is
                     •
                  
Sermon cause his S
                     •
                  hollers to 
                     •
                  ome unto the Church, and there see the
                     •
                  
quietly and orderly behave themselves▪ And doth he traine them up at 
                     〈…〉
                  
in sentences of holy Scripture▪ And doth he teach them any o
                     •
                  ther
Grammar than that which was set forth by King. Henry VIII. an
                     •
                  
hath since conti
                     •
                  ued▪
               
               3 Have you belonging to your Church or Chappell a Parish Clark
                     •
                  
aged:Can. 91. 21. yeares at the least? As he of 
                     〈◊〉
                   convers
                     •
                  tion, sufficient 
                     〈◊〉
                  
his reading, writing: and also for his 
                     〈…〉
                  
said Clarke chosen by any your Parson, Uicar, o
                     •
                   other Minister. An
                     •
                  
doth your Clarke so chosen as before is said, receiv
                     •
                   his 
                     〈…〉
                  ,
without any fraud or diminution, as h
                     •
                  th beene a
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
who is it that denyeth to pay that wages?
               4 D
                     •
                  th your Se
                     •
                  ten or your Parish Clarke (if there be no Se
                     •
                  ton)
wh
                     •
                  n,Can. 67. and as often as any person in passing out of this life, cause 
                     〈◊〉
                   Bell 
                     〈◊〉
                  
be tolled, that so his neighbours may be warned to recommend his soule 
                     〈◊〉
                  
the grace of God? And after the said parties death (if it so 
                     •
                  all out) doth 
                     〈◊〉
                  
ring or cause one short peale to be 
                     •
                  orthwith run
                     •
                  , that so his neighbour
may have notice that he is departed:
               Whether do you the Churchwardens of every Parish within the Ci
                     •
                  ie an
                     •
                  
Suburbs of London (according to the Kings Majesties Letters Patents, unde
                     •
                  
the great Seale of England in that behalfe granted) suffer your Parish Clar
                     ••
                  
to gather his wages himselfe, in as full and ample manner, as the fame ha
                     ••
                  
formerly beene gathered, in or by colour of his name, without dimin
                     •
                  tio
                     •
                  
upon pre
                     •
                  ence of pewage, or the like, and without any manner of disturban
                     ••
                  
or interruption or forbidding any one so to pay the same unto him, and wh
                     ••
                  ther
doe you assist your Clarke in collecting his wages (if need be) accordin
                     •
                  
to his Majesties said Letters Patent: and whether doe you duely present a
                     •
                  
such persons of your Parish as refuse to pay the said Clarkes accustomed wage
                     •
                  
as by his Majesties said grant, you are required and commanded?
            
            
               
               Concerning Parishioners.
               IS there any in your Parish either Mas
                     •
                  er or servant,Can 109 Soiour
                     •
                  er
or Inhabiter, that hath offended either by Adultery, Whoredome, Incest,
or drun
                     •
                  ennesse, or by swearing, ribaldry, (or filthy speaking) usury, or
any other uncleannesse, or wickednesse of life? you shall faithfully present
all and every the said offenders.
               2 Doe you know of any in your Parish,Can. 110 or elsewhere, that is an hinderer
of the word of God to be read, or syncerely preached, or of the execution of any Ecclesiasticall Canons, now by law in force? or a fa
                     ••
                  our
of any usurped or forraigne power, by the lawes of this Realme 
                     •
                  ustly
rejected and taken away, or a defendour of any popish and erronious doctrine?
you shall de
                     •
                  ect, and faithfully present. &amp;c.
               3 Have you in your parish any popish Recusants,Can. 114. men, women▪ or
children, above the age of 13. yeares, whether inhabitants, or sojourners,
and common guests, that refuse to come to Church, or comming to
the Church, refuse to receive the Communion? you shall set downe their
names in writing, if you know their names, or otherwise▪ those names
by which they are called, and who they are that entertaine such guests or
sojourners.
               4 Have you any that disswade any of his Majes
                     •
                  ies subjects,Q Eliz. 
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     
                   from comming
to the Divine Service in this Church established, or that haue or
doe practise with any of them to disswade them from taking the oath of
Allegiance▪ or that have any wayes offended against the Canon lately
made, for the suppressing of popish superstition:
               5 Doe all and every person or persons inhabiting or so
                     •
                  ourning within
your Parish,1 E
                        •
                     z. c. 
                        •
                     
                   diligen
                     •
                  ly and faithfully resort unto your parish Church,
or Chappell accustomed, upon euery Sunday, and other dayes appointed
to be u
                     •
                  ed and kept as Holydayes, doe they then and there abide orderly
and soberly, 
                     〈◊〉
                   the time of common prayer, preaching, or other
service of God there to be used, or m
                     •
                  nistred? Or, (which is contrary
thereunto) have you any that come unto the preachings only,Can. Ann
                        •
                      157 1. c
                        •
                     . 5 and not unto
the common prayer, or comming to the common prayer, neither use
to come at the beginning,Can. 111 nor 
                     •
                  arry out unto the end? Or that being
there doe rudely and disorderly behave themselves, or which by walking,
talking, or any other noise doe hinder the Minister or Preacher?
               6 Have you any that upon the Sundayes or Holydaies, imploy themselves
in their bodily and ordinary labour, or that permit their servants
so to doe? Or that keepe open Shops in time of divine Service? Or any
Uintners,Can: An
                        •
                      1571. Inn-keepers, or other Uictuallers, that permit any to lie tipling

in their houses, or that doe tipple, dice▪ or play at cards, or any other
game in time of divine Service on the aforesaid dayes? Or that use
any plowing, carting, or workes of husbandry, on any of those Sundayes
or holydayes, throughout the yeare, unlesse according to Law, or otherwise
dispose themselves then according 
                     •
                  o Gods holy will and pleasure,
and the orders of the Church of England pres
                     •
                  ribed in that behal
                     •
                  e, and
by Law in force?
               7 Doth any manner of person cover his head in your Church or Chappell
in time of divine Service or Sermon,Can. 18. or any part thereof, except he
have some infirmitie, and in case of such infirmitie, doth he weare a co
                     ••
                  
or nightcap only, and not his hat? doe all and every person of your parish
reverently kneele upon their knees, when the generall Confession, the
Letany, the ten Commandements and other prayers are read, and also
at the receiving the blessed Sacrament of the Lords Supper, doe they
all say the Creed, and Lords prayer, next immediately following in a
loud voice together with the Minister?Can. 18. doe they stand up at the saying of
the Beliefe, and such other parts of divine Service as former
                     •
                  y they have
beene used to stand up at, according to the Rules and ancient custome of
this Church? And when and as often as in the time of divine Seruice
the Lord Iesus shall be mentioned, is due and lowly reverence done by all
persons present? have you any that offend in the neglect of these particulars▪
and what are there names?
               8 Have you any parishioner that being 16.Can. 114 yeares of age doth not receive
the Communion,Rubr. at the least thrice in the yeare, of which Easter to
be one, or that doth not receive the Sacraments, and other rites according
to the order of the common prayer booke?Can. 122 Or that doth not reckon
with his Parson Uicar or Curate, or his or their deputies at Easter,
yearely paying such Ecclesiasticall du
                     •
                  ies as are accustomably due then,
and at that time to be paid?
               9 The Minister standing as he is appointed at the North side,Rubr. or end of
the Table, when hee prepares to celebrate the holy Communion, and
calling on those who doe intend to communicate, to draw neare and take
that holy Sacrament to their comfort,
                     
                        •
                     nvi
                        •
                     ation as it is in the words of the common
prayer booke, have you any in your parish that keepe their seats, and sit
still in their places, not drawing neare as is commanded by the Church,
but looking that the Minister should forsake the place of his station, by the
Church appointed, to bring it to them?
               10 Is there any of your parish,
                     
                        •
                     an. 58. who doth forsake his owne Church or
Chappell to receive the Communion at the hands of any other than their
owne Minister, or any strangers that usually repaire to your Church or
Ch
                     •••
                  ell to the same intent, or any that refuse to receive the holy Communion

at 
                     ••
                  e hands of their owne Minister, because hee is no Preacher
or to have their children baptized by him in the same respect, or that in the
same respects communicate, or cause their children to be baptized in other
Parishes abroad? Or doth your Minister baptize any children presented
unto him out of other Parishes? you shall present the names of all offenders
in these particulars.
               11 Have you any that procure their children to be baptized at home in
their houses without great cause and necessity,Rubr of B
                        ••
                     
                   or by any other than their
own lawfull Minister if he may be had? Or after any other form and manner
than is pr
                     •
                  scribed by the Liturgie of the Church of England, or any
that procure themselves to be married privately, or 
                     •
                  fter any other manner than the Church prescribes?
               12 Do all and every housholder of your Parish,Can. 59 Fathers, Mothers, Masters
&amp; Mistresses, cause their children, seruants, and apprentises, which have
not learned their catechisme, come unto the Church on Sundayes and
Holydayes in the afternoone, obediently to heare and to be ordered by the
Minister till they have learnt the same.
               13 Have you any in your Parish that refuse to contribute,Can. 91 and pay the
rate ass
                     •
                  ssed 
                     •
                  pon him,Can. 8 for the repaire of your Church or Chapp
                     •
                  ll, or the
providing of any bookes, utensils or necessary ornaments to the same belonging?
present the names of those which doe so refuse.
               14 Have you any that keepe company and hold society with suc
                     •
                   as
are denounced and declared Excommunicate?Can. 6
                        •
                     
                  
               
               15 Have you any living in your Parish,Can. 10 which have beene legally separated
and divorced, have afterwards beene married unto others, either
men or women, during the life of each other, or that being so divorced as
afore is said, keepe company with each other at bed and at board? Or any
that being lawfully married, doe yet live asunder, without a separation
in due course of law?
               16 Have you any persons in your Parish▪
                  Can. 9 which are and have been married
within the d
                     •
                  grees prohibited by the Lawes of God, and expressed in
a Table set forth by authority? And is the said Table publikely set up
and fix
                     •
                  d in your Church or Chappell at the Charge of the Parish?
               17 Are there in your Parish any Wills unproved,Can. 
                        •
                     
                   or any goods unadministred
by lawfull Authority? Did any dying in your Parish give
any legacy unto your Church or Chappell, or to the use of the▪ poore and
needy? 
                     〈◊〉
                   how have the said legacies so given beene disposed of by whom
and by whose Authority? And have they otherwise beene disposed of,
then to the said pious and charitable uses?
               
                  
Whether is there in your parish, a common fame and report of any
which have committed Adulterie, Fornication, or Incest, or any Baudes,
harbourers, or receivers of such persons, or vehemently suspected thereof, if
yea, then specifie their names; Whether have you any in your Parish, which
are by common fame and report and vehement suspition, reputed and taken to
be common Drunkards, blasphemers of Gods holy Name, common and usuall
swearers, filthy speakers, railers, sowers of discord among their neighbours,
or speakers against Ministers Marriages; or Vsurers, contrary to the Sta
                     •
                  ute
made in the 37. yeare of King Henry the eighth? you shall not faile to present
their names.
               Whether have any in your Parish, received or harboured any women
with child, suspected to be of a
                     •
                   incontinent life, or have had any such woman
delivered of child in his or her house, or have suffered such women to depart
without penance first inflicted upon them by the Ordinary, if yea, you shall
present as well the partie harbouring, as harboured, and all that help to conveigh them away, and the parties suspected to have committed adultery or
fornication with them.
               Whether doe you know, or have heard of any Patron, or any having an
Advowson in your Parish, that have made gaine by any colour, deceit, or Symoniacall
pact in bestowing his Be
                     •
                  efice and presenting to the same for gaine,
for or receiving money, or promise of the Lease of the whole or part▪ or by reserving
his owne tithes, or any pension to himselfe, or any other?
               What Almes-houses, Hospitals, Free-schooles have you in your Parish,
that are not of t
                     •
                  e Foundation or Patronage of the King, and who was the
Patron or Founder thereof, and whether the said Almes-houses, Hospitals, or
Free-schooles in your Parish, being under the Rule and Government of the
Lord Bishop of London, be well and godly used, according to the ancient
Foundations and Ordinances of the same.
               Whether any Persons within your Parish, either for the offences aforesaid,
or for any other contumacy or crime, doe remaine excommunicated, what be
their names, and for what cause, and how long have they stood excommunicated?
            
            
               Concerning Church-Wardens and Sidemen.
               ARe you the Churchwardens chosen by the ioynt consent of
your Minister and Parishioners,
                     
                        ••
                     n. 89 or one of you by the Minister, and
the other by the Parishioners: Have the last Churchwardens given
up their accounts, delivering up to the Parishioners the money remaining
in their hands, and other things of right belonging to your Church or
Chappell, and is the same delivered to you by bill indented?
               
                  
2 Do you the Churchwardens and Sidemen diligently see that all
your parishioners resort duly to your Church or Chappell,Can. 90▪
                   upon Sundayes
and Holydayes, and there continue the whole time of Divine Service?
doe you suf
                     •
                  er any to walke or stand idle or talk in the Church or in the
Church-yard,Can. 19. 90 or Church
                     •
                  porch, during that time, to the disturbance of the
Minister and scandall of the congregation? You must present the names
of such as offend herein?
               3 Do you against the time of every Communion,Can. 20. at the charge of the
Parish provide a sufficient quantitie of fine white bread, and of good and
wholesome wine, for the number of the Communicants? And doe you
doe the same with the advice and direction of your Minister? And the wine
so provided, do you bring to the Communion Table in a cleane and sweet
standing pot or flaggon?
               4 Doe you the Churchwardens and Sidemen see,Can. 52. that the names of
all Preachers which come to your Church from other places, be noted in a
booke prouided for that purpose? And doth every such Preacher subscribe
his name in the said booke, the day when he preached, and the name of the
Bishop of whom he had licence to preach?
               5 If there be any publike dissension and contradicting in your Pulpit,Can. 53.
betweene the Minister of your Church or Chappell, and any other
Preacher or Preachers, whereby disq
                     •
                  ietnesse and offence may grow among
the people, doe you forthwith signifie the same unto the Bishop, and
not suffer the partie to enjoy the place so by him abused, untill the Bishop
hath taken further order in it?
               6 Doe any person or persons,Can. 115
                        •
                     
                   trouble or molest you the Churchwardens,
for presenting all or any of those persons, which do off
                     •
                  nd in any of
the premisses, who are they that doe so molest or trouble you, and before
whom, and in what Court doe they so molest you?
               7 Doe you the Churchwardens leuie by way of distresse,1. Eliz. 
                        •
                     .
                        ••
                     
                   on the goods
Lands and Te
                     •
                  ements of every person in your Parish, that doth not re
                  
                     •
                  ort
unto your Parish Church or Chappell on every Sunday and Holyday
throughout the yeare,Ca
                        •
                     . 1571▪
                   (having no reasonable excuse to bee absent) the

                     •
                  umme of xii. pence, for every Sunday or Holydaie that he is so absent?
And doe you dist
                     •
                  ibute the severall summes so levied as before is said, among
the poore of the parish, according to the Law in that case provided?
               8 Have you had time sufficient for drawing up of your presentments?Can. 119
                  
                     •
                  ow long is it since this booke of Articles was sent unto you? have you

                     •
                  erused and considered as well the Oath you are to take, as the Articles

                     •
                  hereon to ground your presentments, and 
                     •
                  very branch and clause thereof,
and have you framed your presentments punctually, according to the

                     •
                  everall branches and clauses of those Articles? For know assuredly that

as well the discharging of your Office,Can. 
                        •
                     6. is the chie
                     •
                  e me
                     ••
                  es whereby publike
sinnes and offences may be reformed and punished, so if you wil
                     ••
                  lly
omit to present such crimes as either you know to be commi
                     ••
                  ed, or otherwise
have heard by publike fame,C
                        •
                     n. 117 that in such cases your Ord
                     •
                  naries are to
proceed against you, as in causes of wilfull perjurie, in their Ecclesiasticall
Courts?
            
            
               Concerning Chancellors, Registers, Proctors, Apparators,
and other Ecclesiasticall Officers.
               IS the Chancellor,Can. Art. 1571. p. 11. Commissarie, or Officiall, that exerciseth
Ecclesiasticall Iurisdiction according as you know or have heard in holy
Orders of the Ministerie,Can. An. 1603. c. 127. or if he be not, is he well affected and zealously
bent towards Religion, and such a man touching whose life no evill example
is had?
               2 Doe they or any of them substitute any in their absence to keepe
Court for them,Can. 178 that is not either a grave Minister, and a Graduate, o
                     •
                  
a licensed publike Preacher, and a Benificed man neare the place where
the Courts are kept, or a Batchellour of Law, or a Master of Ar
                     •
                  s at
the least, who hath some skill in the Civill and Ecclesiasticall Lawes? Is
he or they so substituted, a favourer of true Religion, and a man of modest
and honest conversation? Declare the truth according to your knowledge
or best information in these particulars.
               3 Do they or any of them (not being themselves in holy Orders) pronounce
the sentence of Excommunication,Can An. 1571. or leave it only to the Bishop,
and is the same pronounced only by the Bishop, or by some grave man o
                     •
                  
his appointment, which is in the Ministery? Or doe they or any of them
absolve any that are Excommunicated at his or their owne house or houses,
or otherwise in private houses, or only openly and in the Consistorie
                     •
                  
declare your knowledge in this point.
               4 Doth your Chancellor,Can. An. 1571. &amp; 1597. Archdeacon, Commi
                     •
                  sarie or Officiall
take upon him, or them to a
                     •
                  ter any penanc
                     •
                   enjoyned without leave o
                     •
                  
the Bishop? Have they or either or any of them, comm
                     •
                  ted any penan
                     ••
                  
with any dwelling in your Parish? What summe of monie hath beene taken
for the said commutation? Is the said summe made knowne unt
                     •
                  
you in the congregation either by the penitent himselfe, or by the Ministe
                     •
                  
of your Parish, As by the Canons of the yeare 1597. it ought to be 
                     •
                   An
                     •
                  
being so made knowne, hath the same summe or summes of monie, bee
                     •
                  
distributed on the poore of your Parish▪ or otherwise bestowed upon pio
                     ••
                   uses?
And on what pious uses, as you have beene credibly informed, wa
                     •
                  
the samebestowed?
               
                  
5 Doth your Chancellor,Can. 120▪
                   Archdeacon, Of
                     •
                  iciall, or other Ecclesiasticall
Iudge, suffer any generall Processe of Quo
                        •
                     um Nomina▪
                   to be sent
out of the Court, except the names of all such as be cited▪ are first expres
                     ••
                  e
entered by the hand of the Register or his Deputie, and the said proc
                     •
                  sses
and names be subscribed by the Iudge or his Deputie, and his seale of Office
thereto affixed?
               6 Doth the Chancellor,Can. 12
                        •
                     . or any Commissarie within your Diocesse,
cite any of your Parish for any crime into his court, that hath beene
formerly detected or presented to the Archdeacon? Or doth your Archdeacon
cite any dwelling in your Parish, to appeare before him for any

                     •
                  rime presented to the Chancellor in his Uisitation? by which of the two
aforesaid Iuris
                     •
                  ictions was the partie offending cited last?
               7 Doth your Chancellor,Can. 123▪
                   Commissarie▪ Archdeacon, Officiall, or any
other using Ecclesiasticall Iuris
                     •
                  iction, speede any Iudiciall▪ Act except
he have the Ordinary▪ Register of the court, or his lawfull Deputy,
or else such persons to write and speed the same, as are by 
                     •
                  aw allowed in
that behalfe? Or have they, or either, or any of them, without
the Bishops consent any moe seales then one, for the sealing of all matters
incident to his or their Office? And doth the said Seale remaine in
the custodie of the Iudge himselfe, or of the lawfull substitute by him appointed?
And is the same kept in the Citie or principall Towne in the

                     •
                  ountie, as the Law requireth?
               8 Doth your Chancellor,Can. 125. Commissarie, Archdeacon, Officiall or
others exercising any Ecclesiasticall Iurisdiction, or eith
                     •
                  r or any of them,
appoint such place or places for the keeping of their Courts, as are convenient
for the entertainment of those that are to make their appearance
there, and most indifferent for travell? And doe they end in their Courts
in such convenient time or times, as every man may returne homewards
in as due season as may be?
               9 Hath any Register unto your knowledge,Ca
                        •
                     . 134 or as you have credibly
beene informed, receiued wittingly any certificate without the knowledge
of the Iudge? Or willingly omitted to call any persons cited to appeare
upon any Court day? Or that hath unduely put off, and deferred
the Examination of witnesses to be examined by a day, set and assigned
by the Iudge? Or that hath set downe or enacted any thing false, or
conceited by himselfe, as decreed by the Iudge, or not as so ordered or decreed
by the Iudge? Or that hath received any reward in any Causes
whatsoever in favour of any partie, or that is of counsell directly or indirectly
with either of the parties in suit? declare your knowledge in these
particulars.
               10 Do
                     •
                  h any Register or any other Minister of Ecclesiastical Courts
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  
or any of the Iudges of the said Courts take or receive any other or greater
fees, then such as were ratified and approved by the Archbishop of
Canterbury, Anno 1597. and contained in the Tables of fees, for that
purpose made: And are two Tables, containing the severall rates and
summes of the said fees,Can. 136 set up according to the Law in that case provided?
That is to say, one of them in the usuall place or Consistorie where the
Court is kept, and the other of them in the Registry, or Registers Office?
And are they set up in such sort that every man whom it concerneth
may without difficultie come to the view thereof and take a copie of them
if they so desire?Can. 137 And doth any Register or other Ecclesiasticall Officer
take more for shewing Letters of Orders▪ then is appointed in the 137.
Canon?
               11 Doth any Proctor take upon him to appeare in any Cause or
pretend to be entertained in the same,Can. 1
                        •
                     9 unlesse hee be constituted and appointed
by the party himselfe either before the Iudge and in open Court,
or by sufficient Proxie con
                     ••
                  rmed by some authenticall Seale, the parties
ratification therewithall concurring? If you know any such present him,
that so he may be punished as the law provides? Or doth any Proctor

                     •
                  ake the oath in Animam Domini, in any cause what ever, contrary to the
ordinance of holy Church?
               12 How many Apparatours have you in your Dioc
                     •
                  sse or Archdeaconrie,Can. 138
as you either know or doe conjecture? Doe they or any of them
execute their Office by themselves or by their Deputies? And if by their
Deputies, then is the cause of such their deputation and employment made
knowne and approved of by the Ordinary of the place? Doe they take
upon them the Offfce of Promot
                     •
                  rs or Informers for the Court, or exact
more or greater fees then are prescribed in the Tables before remembred?
What other abuses and aggrievances can you complaine of justly in the
said Apparators?
               Whether any Archdeacon or Officiall within the Diocesse of London
hath or doth commute or change any p
                     •
                  nance or corporall punishment, in
whole or in part, and what money such Archdeacon or Officiall hath
received, what 
                     〈◊〉
                   offence was for which any summe of money was
received, or appointed to be paid? set downe the particulars of
the premisses.
               Whether any Archd
                     •
                  acon or Officiall, or his Surrogate, have within thes
                     •
                  
three yeares last past, granted any Licences for the Marriage of any parties
in your parish Church, or elsewhere, whether hath your Minister by vertue o
                     •
                  
the said Licences, so married them, and by whom the said Licences were so granted,
and you are likewise required by vertue of your corporall oath to make diligent

search in the Register booke of marriages kept within your parish, what
parties have beene married by the said authoritie, and if you know any such,
present their names, and places where they dwell.
               Whether have you in your Parish any Curats, Schoolemasters, Physitians,
Ch
                     ••
                  urgions, Parish Clarkes, or Midwives, licensed by any other authority
than of the Lord-bishop of this Diocesse, or his Chancellor, and whether any
fees have beene demanded or received by any other besides the Lord Bishop of
this Diocesse, or his Chancellor, in the Lord Bishops Visitation, for exhibiting
the said licences?
               Whether any Commissarie, Archdeacon, or Officiall, have at any time,
especially within these three yeares last past, intermedled in the placing or displacing
of any persons in pewes, in your Parish Churches, or have granted
any confirmation of seates, under his seale of office, or by his authority hath
caused to be removed the Pulpit, or Font, or reading Deske f
                     •
                  om their ancient
and accustomed place, or given way to making of doores or windowes
in Churches or Chappels, or erecting of Galleries?
               Whether any Commissarie, Archdeacon or Officiall have proved the Wils,
or granted Administration of the goods of any beneficed man or Curat dying
within his Iurisdiction, or of any other person being in holy Orders?
            
         
         
            
            The Charge of the Church-wardens and
Sworn men set downe for the better performance
of their duties, and discharge of their Oaths.
            THey are not to bring in any Bills into the Archdeacons Court upon
the Articles to be enquired of in their Visitation, by reason of my
Lords Visitation, but only now during the said Visitation, to make their
presentments upon these Articles. They are therefore charged, that after their
Oath taken, and their returne home, they doe require their Minister to reade
over both the Book of Canons or Constitutions, set forth by his Majestie, in the
Convocation holden in the year of our God, 1604. and also these Articles unto
them, and to consider of every particular Article, and of the offences by them
to be presented, as also of such persons in their Parish as shall bee noted to
offend in the same: and so the Church-wardens and Side-men assembling
themselves together within some convenient time, are to make their Bill, answering
every Article by it selfe, before the time hereafter appointed them,
which Bill shall be signed with the hands of all the Church-wardens and Side
                  •
               men,
with conference had with their Minister upon the said Bill of presentment,
who, according to the 26. Canon▪ is to see that the said Church-wardens
doe their duties in presenting, upon the penaltie in the 26. Canon prescribed.
These Bills shall be brought by both the Church-wardens
            
               
AT the delivery of your Bill of presentment, at the time and place before
set downe, you the Church-wardens are likewise in the said Bill,
to set downe the names of all such as have died within your parish at any,
time since the day of Iuly last past being Men, Maides
or Widowes: and what person or persons have beene married since the
said time, and by what Licence or authority: and likewise you the Minister,
Church-wardens and Side-men of every Parish, must in the end of
the said Bill of presentment, set downe, the number of all Recusants,
and non-Communicants as followeth


                  Recusants men—
                  Recusants women.—
                  Non-Communicants of both sex.—
                  Communicants of both sex in the whole Parish
               

So setting down the number of every one, you the Minister,
Church-wardens and Side-men must put your hands to the said
Note.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

