
   
      
         
            A declaration and catholick exhortation to all Christian princes to succour the Church of God and realme of France. Written by Peter Erondelle, natife of Normandie. Faithfully translated out of the French
            Erondelle, Pierre, fl. 1586-1609.
         
         
            
               1586
            
         
         Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00397
            STC 10512
            ESTC S112258
            99847516
            99847516
            12553
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00397)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12553)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 223:03)
         
         
            
               
                  A declaration and catholick exhortation to all Christian princes to succour the Church of God and realme of France. Written by Peter Erondelle, natife of Normandie. Faithfully translated out of the French
                  Erondelle, Pierre, fl. 1586-1609.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  Imprinted [by G. Robinson] for Edward Aggas,
                  At London :
                  1586.
               
               
                  In English and French--STC.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Sub title page on C1r reads: Remonstrance &amp; exhortation catholick. Londres chez E. Aggas 1586--STC.
                  Signatures: A B⁴.
                  Imperfect; lacks all after leaf B4.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               France --  History --  HenryIII, 1574-1589 --  Early works to 1800.
               France --  Church History --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
Declaration and Catholick
exhortation to all Chriſtian
Princes to ſuccour the
Church of God and Realme
of France.
            Written by Peter Erondelle, natife
of Normandie.
            Faithfully tranſlated out of the French.
            
               
AT LONDON,
Imprinted for Edward Aggas. 1586.
         
         
            
            
            ¶To all true louers of the
pure Goſpell and holy doctrine of
Ieſus Chriſt, and to all thoſe that
deſire the preſeruation of the Realme
of France, Peter Erondelle wiſheth
health in the Lord.
            
               
                  I
                Doubt not but doe ſtedfaſtly
perceiue, that whoſoeuer
ſhall conſider of my
calling wil diſdain to looke
vpon this briefe Treatiſe,
as proceeding frō a perſon
vnworthie ſuch a worke,
yea and will maruaile from whence J ſhould
gather ſuch boldneſſe, ſith I am not adorned or
furniſhed with any humaine wiſedome wherewith
to beautifie or rather paint out the ſame.
But what aunſwer ſhall J make them? For it
is not I that haue wrought this woorke, but
euen GOD himſelfe through the vertue and
power of the holy Ghoſt working in mee, who
word by word hath ſhewed and enſtructed me
in all that is herein ſet downe, as vſing mee a
poore and miſerable ſinner to indure and perſwade
or rather commaund all thoſe that haue
the feare of God and doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt
before their eyes, to ſuccour his afflicted people
who are on euery ſide oppreſſed, but principally

in our France by ſome tyrants, vnto whō
J preſent not this briefe diſcourſe, for I am ſufficiently
perſwaded that this kinde of people do
but ſeeke occaſion to ſubuert &amp; ſet at va
                  •••…
               nce
ſuch a Commonwealth as before remayned in
peace and vnitie: But vnto you my brethren,
doe J direct the ſame, deſiring you not to diſdaine
the ſight therof, but in equitie and without
al paſſion (other thē reaſon) to reade it, notwithstanding
therein you finde ſome fault:
Neither would I herein ſeeke to flatter or conceale
the aucthors of theſe preſent troubles:
namely the houſe of Guyze, who are the chiefe
Captaines and conductors thereof, as alſo I
ſhould get nothing by concealing them, as being
a matter which euery man knoweth better
then J can tell them how it ſtandeth. Beſides I
will not delay the time in beautifying this diſcourſe
with any painted ſpeech to adorne it
withall, as ſome doe when they ſeeke and goe about
to perſwade lyes in ſtead of trueth vnder
the colour of a pleaſant phraſe and painted
ſpeech which is ſufficient to leade the Readers
thereunto, and lulling them on ſleepe procureth
them, as afore is ſayde, to admit lyes in liew of
truth, euen as the Mermaide who by her pleaſant
ſong ouercommeth the Saylers, and when
they be at reſt deuoureth them all. J would not

therefore imitate them, but onely ſpeake plainly
according to all the wordes that haue fallen into
my mouth whereby God hath holpen me to
bring the ſame to paſſe. To him therfore are we
to yeeld thankes, and withal to pray him to direct
al our workes to the glory of his name and
excellencie of his iustice, as also that through
the blood of his welbeloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt,
he will vouchſafe vs remiſſion of all our ſinnes.
Amen.
            
            
               A Prayer.
               
                  O Lord God almightie who
knoweſt the hearts and thoughtes
of al men, ſo as we doe not ſo ſon
                     •
                  
imagine what to ſay but thou knoweſt
better then our ſelues what
our tongue ſhould pronounce, &amp;
that there is nothing vpon the earth or vnder the ſame
how ſecrete ſoeuer, but is manifeſt vnto thee. Wee beſeech
thee O Lorde in the name of thy welbeloued
ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, that it may pleaſe thee to open and
reueale whatſoeuer the wicked purpoſes of the peruerſe,
whereby they may haue no meanes left to perſecute
thy faithful. Neuertheleſſe if it pleaſe thee O Lord
yet to continue the afflictions of thy Church, like as
we know thee to be a iuſt and true Iudge, we do notwithſtanding
beſeech thee not to puniſh vs in thy
wrath or according to our deſerts, who deſerue onely
euerlaſting damnation, but thy will be done, for ſo it is

moſt expedient. We confeſſe that we haue grieuouſly
prouoked thee againſt vs and are greatly endaungered
to thy moſt iuſt iudgement, howbeit we beſeech thee
O Lorde, enter not thereinto with vs, for our ſinnes in
thy ſight are innumerable euen as the ſand of the Sea
or droppes of water of the ſame, it may pleaſe thee
therefore O Lord, not to call thē to thy remembrance,
but through the death and paſſion of thy welbeloued
ſonne Ieſus Chriſt to wipe thē away. We beſeech thee
alſo that it may pleaſe thee to preſerue thoſe Kings &amp;
Princes that are endued with the knowledge of thy
Goſpell, and doe dayly fight for the ſame, thereby vnder
the ſhadow of their wings preſeruing many faithfull
poore perſons: vouchſafe them the encreaſe of thy
grace. Touch alſo the mindes of ſuch Kings and Princes
as doe vexe thy poore ſeruants, and ſuffer not their
hearts to be hardened like as was the heart of Pharao
King of Egipt againſt thy people of Iſraell, and eſpecially
O Lord vouchſafe to bring them into the boſome
of thy Church, ſo to enioye the cleare light thereof,
which is, to ſee and knowe the trueth. And this do we
moſt humbly beſeech thee in the name and fauour of
thy dearely beloued ſonne our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt as
himſelfe hath taught vs ſaying. Our Father which art
in heauen, &amp;c.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶A Declaration and exhortation
to Princes, &amp;c.
            
               LOng time haue we ſeene
our France thus tormented
&amp; afflicted with wars,
miſeries and calamities,
vnder colour of religion,
and yet euen to this day,
do we behold how it doth
daily waſte and decay more and more, which
cauſeth mee to thincke, that vnleſſe God doe
ſpeedely ſet to his hand, we ſhall in ſhort time
behold the deſtruction and diſſipation of the
moſt floriſhing Realme in Chriſtendome, at
the appetite of certaine perticuler parſons,
who vppon a deſire and vnſatiable thirſt to
raigne, doe ſeeke no other but the loſſe, or rather
vſurpation thereof, as ſeeming to them
that God is blind, and ſeeth not the torments
which they inflict vppon his people, in baniſhing
ſome, and defrauding them of their
goods, and in putting other ſome moſt cruelly
to death. They might ſurely thincke, that
if the Religion which they tearme new, were
not good, it would ſoone waſte, and be in a
moment ſwalowed vp, but that contrariwiſe,
if it be according to God and Chriſt Ieſus, al

the weapons and power of the world are not
able to deſtroy it, no not ſo much as any whit
to diminiſh the ſame, and therefore they ought
rather to followe the counſayle of the Phariſaicall
Doctor of the Iewiſh law Gamaliel,
who being in the Counſaile houſe when they
ſought to put the Apoſtles to death, ſaid, that
if their Religion were of Man, the remembrance
thereof would ſoone periſh, but if it
were of God, they ſhould neuer be able to deſtroy
it. How many bloody battailes haue we
ſeen? Howe much Innocent blood ſhed, not
onely in our France, but euen throughout all
Chriſtian-dome for this onely point, and yet
doe we ſee this holy doctrine floriſh and augment
all ouer the worlde. Beſides it was neuer
ſeene, neither in the time of the holy Patriarkes
or Primitiue Church that Religion
was decided, confirmed or diſputed vpon by
force of Armes, but onely by the Sworde of
godlineſſe, &amp; the pure word of God conteined
in the Bible. Howe many errors did ſpring
vp in the Primitiue Church, and yet there
needed no other weapon then the holy ſcripture,
neither did we euer know falſe doctrine
but the ſame immediatly vaniſhed through
the power of Chriſt Ieſus. Wee may therefore
eaſely preſume, that the aucthors of theſe

ciuill warres, couering themſelues vnder the
vizerd of religion, doe ſeeke no other but the
vtter ruine of this Realme, wherof they were
to make their profite and commoditie. Wee
know, that before the deceaſe of the late Lord
Duke of Anieow and Alencon the Kinges
onely brother there was nothing ſpoken of,
But they will now ſay that the Crowne belongeth
to them, then ſhould they greatly deceiue
themſelues, for in liewe of benefiting
the Realme, they conſume all the ſubſtaunce
thereof in the charges of the Warre. If any
man aſke who bee theſe goodly aucthors of
theſe preſent ciuill Warres, I will anſwere
that it is the houſe of Guize, which ſaith that
in cace it ſhoulde ſo come to paſſe, that the
King ſhould dye without iſſue, the Crowne
can not belong to the King of Nauarre, becauſe
he is a Hereticke: But truely any man
endued with the feare of GOD, which will
iudge vprightly, may well know that Popiſh
Religion is meere error, beſides that in the
Primitiue Church the ſheepeheards and Biſhops
liued not in ſo greate pride and ſuperfluitie
as doe the Popes: for ſince that Chriſtian
Emperors, Kings and Princes permitted
them libertie to rule, they haue not onely
abandoned the true Church of Chriſt Ieſus,
but alſo haue embraſed falſhoode in ſtead of

trueth, and liued ouer loſely and diſſolutely.
Neither is it the office of a Biſhop to ſeeke
the dominion of a whole climate of the earth,
but rather onely to inſtruct his flocke according
to the holy ſcriptures, and the true doctrine
of Ieſus Chriſt. Let vs conſider whether
Saint Peter (whoſe ſucceſſer the Pope
chalengeth himſelfe to be) or the other Apoſtles
ſought to rule Monarkes. No, no, but
contrariwiſe Chriſt himſelf ſaid, that no man
could ſerue God and Mammon. But let vs
returne to our purpoſe, for I am not to meddle
in matters which ſo many learned Parſons
haue debated vpon, in preſenting to the
view and palpably feeling of the Popiſh errors,
neither is it the marke that I leuell at,
who doe pretend only to ſhew vnto you what
iuſt occaſions we haue to take armes for our
neceſſary defence. For it is extreeme crueltie
and meere tyranny to baniſh the poore, and vſurpe
their goods, as in theſe doyes they doe
in our France. I doe therefore moſt humbly
beſeeche all true louers of the Goſpell, and
ſuch as deſire the preſeruatiō of this crowne,
not to ſuffer, for want of taking armes, and
ſuccouring of vs, ſo floriſhing a Realme, as
ours to be loſt: for all men may ſee, and it is
moſt euident, that the aucthors of this warre

doe ſeeke the onely decay thereof. Haue wee
not ſeene all Germany, England, Scotland,
and the moſt part of Europe troubled for this
onely cauſe of Religion? and yet nowe wee
find, that at this day they doe enioy moſt bleſſed
peace through ſuch agreements and order
as on either part haue beene taken. Theſe
men cannot excuſe themſelues of ſeeking the
vtter deſtruction of this countrie: for we haue
had ſo many Peaces and Agreementes in
time paſt, that now it is a moſt manifeſt matter,
that the onely point of Religion is no
cauſe of preſent troubles, but rather an enuious
deſire to vſurpe. They miniſter cauſe neuer
to repoſe confidence in whatſoeuer promeſſe
or peace, which properly be tearmed a
Childrens paſtime, who may ſay and vnſay,
and all with one breath, what ſoeuer they 
                  •…
               ſt.
How many holy and iuſt edicts haue we had,
and eſpecially the Edict of Ianuary made in
the yere of grace. 1561. vnder King Charles
the ninth, which was both good and lawfully
made, to the benefite as well of the one as other
religion. Was not the ſame ſufficient,
whereby wee might enioy an aſſured peace,
as doe other the bordring realmes our neighbours?
But what? It was of ouer great importance
to the enemies of peace. What ſhal

I ſay more? haue we not ſince that had many
other edicts? &amp; by ye laſt, was not the French
Nation aſſured to enioye a bleſſed peace,
though to the great preiudice of our reformed
religion, and very beneficiall to the contrary,
as wanting more then halfe the libertie of
that of Ianuary, which notwithſtanding, the
wicked could not continue in that Peace.
This ſufficiently ſheweth their peruerſe and
miſchieuous mindes, as alſo that they haue
no other deſire, but to deſtroy or vſurpe this
Crowne of the Flowerdeluce: But what
neede I ſo largely deſcribe a matter which
all the world knoweth better then my ſelfe?
Wot wee not that this houſe of Guize and
their aſſociates, are the chiefe Captaines and
Conductors of all this alteration? See wee
not that they ſeeke to deliuer and abandon,
as it were in praye, this poore kingdome, to
the Spaniſh nation? Moreouer, haue we not
already found howe they haue endeuoured,
and ſtill doe goe about to bring all Chriſtiandome
into confuſion. And howe? In Scotlande
haue they not ſought to drowne the
Realme in troubles and Ciuill warres, ſo as
we haue ſeene the Nobilitie and Commons
ſo ſore bent one againſt another, that no peace
could bee obtained without moſt grieuous

and horrible bloodſhed? Yea, had it not bene
by meanes of the moſt ſacred of GOD, the
Queenes Maieſtie of England, the troubles
had yet cōtinued, and al through the Guizes.
Vndoubtedly we can not thincke but that after
ſo many miſchiefes God will powre out
his iuſt iudgement vpon that Family, notwithſtanding
many tymes we ſee the perturbers
of publicke peace and ennemies to the
trueth proſper more then the good, neither
are we to meruaile, when we ſee the wicked
exalted before our faces, for God will ſometimes
vſe ſuch inſtruments to trie the pacience
of his elect. Nowe haue I ſufficiently
ſhewed you the iuſt cauſes that wee haue to
defend our ſelues, there reſteth no more but
to open vnto you the end whereto I doe pretend,
which is, to deſire all true louers of the
Goſpell not to ſuffer the tyrannizing of the
faithfull flock of Ieſus Chriſt, who ſaith that
his ſhalbe knowen by the brotherly loue that
they ſhall beare one to another: but what amitie
is it to ſee his brother or neighbour dye
truelly before his eyes? vndoubtedly if wee
would conſider what charitie and brotherly
loue to our neighbour is, we ſhould feele our
conſciences wonderfully oppreſſed. I we ſee
a thiefe or robber take a pooremans purse in

the wood, and doe not our endeuours to deliuor
him from the ſaid oppreſſion, ſhall not we
be guiltie of the treſpaſſe? If I demaund of
you who is the better or who is moſt worthy
puniſhment, the thiefe or the receiuer▪ you wil
anſwere they are alike guiltie the one one as
the other: who then is the better, he that committeth
the tyranny, or he that being by goeth
not about to let it: In this caſe you will
ſay, he is not guiltie of the deede becauſe hee
furdereth it not, neither helpeth to doe it,
whereto, I may well reply, that no more doth
the receiuer ſteale, and yet is he not free from
puniſhment, for if there were no receiuer,
there would be no thiefe: euen ſo if euery one
would endeuour to withſtand the perturbers
of common peace, we ſhould not haue ſo many
cruell warres and tyrannyes, as at this
day are in force: Wee may therefore well
thinke, that thoſe that looke vpon the executing
of ſuch tyrannies, and doe not oppoſe
them ſelues againſt them, are in as great or
rather greater fault then thoſe that commit
them: A man diſpoſed to doe euill, if he finde
any l
                  •
               t, will not goe forward therein, and ſo
ſhal not his offence be ſo heynous in the ſight
of men, as if he had done it, notwithſtanding
I will not quite excuſe him, or ſay that hee

ought to be exempt of puniſhment, ſith God
ſaith that will is reputed for the deede: but he
that ſeeth the wickedneſſe committed, and to
his power letteth it not, is worthy double puniſhment,
for both him ſelfe offendeth, and his
winking is cauſe that the other proceedeth in
his bad purpoſe, which hee would not haue
done if hee had bene letted: Hee therefore is
guiltie both of his owne fault &amp; yt others alſo,
and ſo ſuch perſons can not eſchue the iuſt
vengeance of God either in this worlde, or in
the worlde to come, vnleſſe his great mercie
deliuer them. For God ſaith, loue God aboue
all things, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe: if
then we loue our neighbour as our ſelfe, wee
can not before our faces ſee hym oppreſſed
with tyranny, but we muſt needes afford him
ſome helpe and comfort, and therefore we are
herein guiltie both to God and our neighbor:
But was there euer greater tyranny practized
then the ſame that the Guizards do now
vſe in France? They be theeues, murderers
and perturbers of publicke peace. For can
there be any greater thieuery, then to baniſh
an infinite number of poore peoplee, and to vſurpe
their goods, Landes, Lordſhips and enheritances?
But nowe we ſee ſome that are
willing to withſtand them, but doe feare to

be ouer weake: Let vs not feare my frends,
but conſider for what we fight. Wee fight for
our peace, our country, our liues, and the reſtitution
of our goods: for the deliuery of our
brethren, for the obteining of peace and quietneſſe,
and to be briefe, for al moſt iuſt and lawfull
cauſes: Contrariwiſe our ennemies fight
onely for the maintenance of their tyrannies
and ranſoming of the poore people, yea onely
of a gready deſire to raigne aud vſurpe. If
we would conſider al theſe things, we ſhould
conceine a greater courage to defend our
ſelues, then the others haue to aſſaile, beſides
that we ſee our great capteine Ieſus Chriſt,
who taketh our cauſe in hand, as being moſt
iuſt and righteous. Let vs not quaile though
we ſee our ennemies to bee three times moe
then our ſelues: For if they fortefie themſelues
it is onely for feare of vs, as alſo the
force of man is nothing in reſpect of the power
of God, who nameth him ſelfe the God
of Armes and battailes: who graunteth victorie
to whom he pleaſe, who alſo wil reueale
his might in vs in breaking the greateſt Army
that may be leuied through euē one ſmale
handfull of men: Let vs couragionſly goe to
the Combat, and ſtedfaſtly beleene that our
good God and Lord Ieſus Chriſt will graſſe

vs the victorie, ſo as we craue it at his-hands
in faith: for of him we obteine whatſoeuer we
faithfully doe craue: But firſt let vs alſo ſee
that our army conſiſt not of wicked parſons,
but let euery one enter into his owne conſcience,
for God neither is called, neither wilbe
leader of peruerſe and wicked people, ſo no
doubt we ſhall obteine a perfect and full victory:
Let vs ſo march as the boulder may be
an example of vertue to the reſt. Again I beſeech
all Kinges, Princes and Lordes, both
ſtrangers and others, that haue any meanes
to ſuccour vs, or that doe beare any goodwill
or fauour to France, not to ſuffer ſo floriſhing
a realme to be loſt for want thereof, at the appetite
of a famely which ſeeketh no other but
the vſurping of the ſame vnder ſhadow of religion,
ſo ſhall yee accompliſh the workes of
charitie, and fulfill the Commaundement of
GOD, which is, loue thy neighbour as thy
ſelfe. And in as much as we all are brethren
and neighbours, let vs one helpe another in
our neceſſitie, for ſo ſhal the noble hearts and
vertuous parſons be knowen. I knowe ſome
may reply and ſay, that forreine Kings and
Princes are not to enterprize vpon the Dominions
of other Princes their neighbours,
for ſometimes vnder ſuch a cloke of Godlineſſe

they do extend their owne limites with
the loſſe of their neighbours, and therefore it
is not their parts to ſet foote into other mens
Lordſhips: For anſwere I would faine aſke
them whether we doe not all agree that there
is one onely vniuerſall Church whereof Ieſus
Chriſt is the head and the members are
ſo vnited and confoyned that the leaſt of them
can not bee greeued but the reſt muſt feele
ſome ſmart, according as we ſee that the holy
Scripture doth teſtifie. See wee not many
times the whole body periſh through ſome
wound, not onely in the Arme or Thigh, but
alſo ſome times through ſome ſmale inconuenience
happened to the litle finger? Marke
the Serpent or any other venemous beaſt,
when it ſtingeth any body, it ſeeketh not the
head or any other principall member of the
body, but onely or for the moſt part, the foot,
and yet ye ſee the parſon ſo hurt dye of ſuch a
ſtinging. And what? would you make any
accompt of ſuch a Phiſition as hath reſpect
onely to ſome one part of his patient? no, no,
he muſt looke vpon &amp; viſite al the whole body,
euen from the foot to the head, to ſee whether
any other me
                  ••••…
                bee infected. Euen ſo doe
wee compare the Church to this body which
hath diuers mēbers, ſome in one place, ſome

in another▪ Now as this Church is only and
vniuerſall, ſo is it not cōmitted to the chardge
of one onely King, but generally to all chriſtian
Princes, and perticulerly to euery one,
becauſe it were danngerous to leaue the cuſtodie
to one onely, and yet the vnitie thereof
is ſuch, as can by no meanes bee ſeperated,
notwitſtanding it be vniuerſally diſperſed ouer
the whole fate of the earth. The Church
of England and the Church of Fraunce are
not two Churches, but all are mēbers of one.
God hath committed it wholy to euery one
perticulerly, and all the partes thereof to all
in generall, to the end not onely to preſerue it
whole and ſound, but alſo more and more to
encreaſe it, ſo that if one prince careth but for
part of the Church, as of that of Germany or
Scotland, and the whiles contemneth and abandoneth
an other part that is oppreſſed, and
it lieth in him to ſuccour, he hath abandoned
the Church, for Chriſt Ieſus hath bnt one only
Spouſe diſperſed throughout the whole
world, whom euery prince ought ſo to defend
and keepe, that ſhe may not be any where defiled,
if poſſibly hee may, neither is it to any
purpoſe to excuſe himſelfe by ſuch vſurpation
as a Prince might take hould of in an others
country: for who ſo is led by a wil procéeding

from the ſpirit of Ieſus Chriſt, can not vnder
ſuch a falſe title expell his neighbour out of
his patrimony: as being a matter farre repugnant
to Gods commaundement, which is,
that hee ſhall not couet any thing that is his
neighbours. Such ſuperfluous allegations
are not therefore to be feared, for whatſoeuer
is guided by the holy ghoſt, can yeld nothing
but what proceedeth from the ſame: and ſith
the holy ghoſt proceedeth from the wholy
perfect goodneſſe, namely God, who is conteined
in the three parſons, the Father, the
ſonne, and the holy ghoſt, who proceedeth frō
the two, we muſt needes beleeue, that who ſo
is guided by God, can doe nothing contrarie
to his will. I ſay therefore, and it is moſt certaine,
that God willeth Chriſtian Princes to
take armes in defence of his afflicted people
which are of the Church, examples whereof
we find in ſundry places of the holy ſcripture.
We ſee that in the time of Ezechias King of
Iuda, the kingdome of Iſrael had long continued
in ſubiection to the Aſſirians, therfore
if onely the Church of Iuda, and not the vniuerſall
Church had bene committed to the
charge of Ezechias, alſo, that if in the preſeruation
of the Church, he ought to haue kept
like meaſure as in the deuiſion of the lande,

no doubt Ezechias would haue cōteined him
ſelfe within his owne bonds, when the Aſſirians
ruled ouer the reſt, but hee ſent Poſtes
throughout all Iſrael to ſummon them to the
obſeruation of the Paſſeouer. Doe wee not
reade alſo of good K. Ioſias, that he put out
Idolatrie, not onely forth of his realme, but
alſo out of the kingdom of Iſrael, &amp; that iuſtly?
for when the kingdom of Chriſt is in queſtion,
there is neither bounds nor limites that
ſhoulde ſtaye the zeale of Chriſtian Princes.
Theſe examples of ſuch and ſo good princes
might ſtand for a Lawe, but let vs alſo looke
what God himſelf pronoūceth by ye mouthes
of his holy Prophets againſt thoſe that make
no accompt of his Church: beſides wee doe
roade, that the Gadites, Rubenites, and the
halfe tribe of Manaſſes, required Moyſes to
alot thē their portion on this ſide of Iordan,
which Moyſes did graunt to condicionally,
that they ſhould not onely helpe their other
brethren the Iſraelites to conquere the Land
of Canaan, but alſo ſhould marche formoſt &amp;
make the auantgarde. Haue we not teſtimonies
enowe to proue the duetie of Princes to
ſuccour the Church? ſurely if we would alledge
all other the examples that might bee
found in the word of God, wee might haue enough

to make a very large volume, but becauſe
I meane to write onely a ſhort declaration,
I would make no further mention therof,
as alſo this is enough, and therefore wee
want onely goodwill. Alas, I feare God wil
one day reprooue vs of vnprofitableneſſe in
this world. And what? you Kings and Princes
doe you not feare that God will aſke accompt
of you for your gouernments? &amp; wherfore
it is that he hath made you his miniſters
and preſeruers of his Spouſe? Is this the
oath that you make at your admiſſions, when
you take the ſword into your hand, and looke
both Eaſt, Weſt, South and North, as if you
would inferre, that there ſhall be no corner in
the world, but you will indeuour therein to
mainteine and encreaſe this Spouſe? This
Church of Chriſt is it comprehended within
your dominions, and is it not vniuerſall ouer
the whole face of the earth? No, no, wee can
haue no lawfull excuſe, &amp; truely I doubt the
reproche of the Propheteſſe Debora againſt
the Rubenites, will fall vpon vs as alſo the
iudgement: for we profeſſe our ſelues to bee
Chriſtians, and yet charitie dwelleth not in
vs, when we ſuffer our brethren, who alſo are
members of Chriſtes Church, to be thus tyrannized.
I beſeech you let vs eſchue the iuſt

iudgement of God that is readie to fall vpon
our heades: let vs giue ouer all excuſes, for
we haue none ſufficient. Let vs leaue all amities
for the Church of Chriſt Ieſus, for it
is he onely that can ſaue vs: let vs immitate
the good Princes Ioſias and Ezechias, alſo
that vertuous Prince Conſtantine, who with
open Warre aſſailed Licinius euen in his
own countrie, becauſe he proſecuted the Chriſtians:
But as ſaith the comon prouerbe, It
booteth not to preach to him that careth not
for wel doing, neither is it to any purpoſe for
me to alledge examples, ſith they will not be
followed: We tearme our ſelues Chriſtians,
and knowe the duetie of Chriſtians, and yet
doe not the workes of Chriſtians. Chriſt Ieſus
teacheth vs that he is more worthy of puniſhment
that knoweth his maſters will and
doth it not, then he that not knowing it doth
it not. Hauing therefore attained to my principall
purpoſe, which is, to deſire all Chriſtian.
Kings and Princes, that doe profeſſe the
pure doctrine to Chriſt Ieſus to graunt ſuccour
to his people in France afflicted by tyrants
and meere bloudſuckers, who drawe
forth mans bloud to glut therewith a forrain
famely: and hauing ſhewed as well by Gods
word, as by good &amp; holy teſtimonies takē out

of the ſame, how by all law, as wel of God as
man they be bound to doe the ſame, I haue no
more to doe, but to require the Readers to
reade and conſider of this diſcourſe with reaſon,
and throwly to way the matters therein
contained without any paſſion, and to iudge
according to equitie: ſo ſhall they perceiue
that it proceedeth not of my ſelfe, but of God,
and therefore not to haue any reſpect to my
age or calling: for any man knowing me, may
well iudge, that of my ſelfe I am vtterly vncapable
of ſuch a deede. Take it therefore as
proceeding frō God, who for the moſt p
                  •
               rt reuealeth
him ſelfe to the ignorant and doultes,
and hydeth himſelfe from the wiſe of the
worlde. Conſider Saint Peter, who was a
ſimple Fiſherman, alſo the reſt of the Apoſtles,
who were but of meane calling. For likewiſe
God hath vſed me in this worke, whome
I doe beſeech to open the heartes of Kinges
and Princes, and to deliuer them from
blindneſſe which ſtoppeth their
ſights, and to make them
partakers of his
cleare light
which
is the knowledge of
his will.
So be it.
            
            
         
      
   

