
   
      
         
            The great mystery of godliness Jesus Christ our Lord God and man, and man with God; one in Jesus Christ our Lord. By Mr. Erbury minister of the word.
            Erbery, William, 1604-1654.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00395
            STC 10511.5
            ESTC S120456
            99855653
            99855653
            21155
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00395)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21155)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 738:10)
         
         
            
               
                  The great mystery of godliness Jesus Christ our Lord God and man, and man with God; one in Jesus Christ our Lord. By Mr. Erbury minister of the word.
                  Erbery, William, 1604-1654.
               
               [4], 43, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by M. F[lesher] for Rob. Milbourne, in little Britain, at the signe of the Holy Lambe,
                  London :
                  1640.
               
               
                  An edition of: The great mystery of godlinesse.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Helps to devotion, partly in outline form.
                  Identified as STC 10511a on UMI microfilm, reel 738.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Jesus Christ --  Mystical body --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
GREAT MYSTERY
OF
GODLINESS:
JESUS CHRIST our Lord
GOD and MAN, and
MAN with GOD;
One in
JESUS CHRIST our LORD.
            By Mr. ERBURY Miniſter of the Word.
            1 COR. 2. 6, 7, 14.
            
               We ſpeak wiſdome among them that are perfect; yet not
the wiſdome of this world, nor of the Princes of this world
that come to nought; But we ſpeak the wiſdome of God in
a Myſtery.
               But the naturall man receiveth not the things of the Spirit
of God; for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him: neither can
he know them becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.
            
            Gal. 3. 28.
            Ye are All, One, in Jeſus Chriſt.
            LONDON,
Printed by M. F. for ROB. MILBOURNE,
in little Britain, at the ſigne of the Holy
Lamb. 1640.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE
MYSTICALL
Union of CHRIST and
his CHURCH;
Grace, Mercy and Peace with all
ſpirituall and ſpeciall bleſſings of
Heaven be multiplied upon you and in
you, by the bleſſed Spirit from God
the Father through CHRIST
JESUS our Lord.
Amen.
            
               Q.
               WHat muſt you do to be
holy here, and happy
hereafter?
            
               A. Two things; Firſt,
Know CHRIST,
John, 17. 3.
            Secondly, Be knit unto him, John
               
                  •
               7. 21, 22, 23, 24.
            
               Q. By what meanes may we come

                  •
               o this?
            
               
               A. Firſt, Outwardly.
            1. In the Word I am taught to know
him Joh. 17. 8.
            2. In the Sacraments I am tied and
knit to him, 1 Cor. 10. 61.
            Secondly, inwardly
            1. By Faith on my part, Ephe. 3. 17.
Gal. 3. 27, 28, 29.

                  1. Grounded on the Word wherein
I receive him.
                  2. Growing in the Sacrament
wherein I am received into him.
               
            
            2. By the Spirit on Gods part, 1 Cor.
6. 17. and 12. 13.

                  1. Aſſuring Chriſt unto me in the
Word, Eph. 1. 13.
                  2. Sealing Chriſt unto me in the
Sacrament, Rom. 4. 11.
               
            
            This is my Body, ſo the Word ſaies
without, when the bread is given in
the Sacrament, and ſo the Spirit ſpeaks
within, aſſuring, yea,
            
               
               making
               1. The Body of Chriſt as verily
preſent to the faithfull,
as the bread is to the receiver,
1 Cor. 11. 24, 26.
               2. The faithfull partaker of
Chriſts Body as verily as
of the bread which he eates,
1 Cor. 10. 16.
               3. The faithfull one with
Chriſts Body as verily as
the bread received &amp; eaten
is one with his body that
feeds upon it, 1 Cor. 12. 12.
            
            
               PART .I.
               
                  Quest. WHat is it to know
Chriſt?
               
                  A. To find
                  1. The want of Chriſt,
Phil. 3. 7.
                  2. The worth of Chriſt,
Phil. 3. 8.
                  3. A willingneſſe in me to
receive Chriſt, Phil. 3. 9,
10, 12, 14.
               
               
                  
Firſt, when I feele the want of Chriſt
in reſpect of the guilt and filth of ſin
in me. Secondly, find the worth of
Chriſt to pardon and purge my ſin.
Thirdly, feele and find a willingneſſe
in me to receive, Chriſt, that is, to accept
of him on his own conditions.
               1 Not only to be my Prieſt and Jeſus
to ſave me by his blood, Heb. 2. 17
               2 Nor only to be my Prophet and
Chriſt, to teach me by his Word, Act.
3. 22.
               3 But alſo to be my Prince &amp; Lord
to rule mee by his Spirit, leaving my
old luſt, and living by his laws, denying
my ſelfe, and delighting to do
whatever he commands, Act. 5. 31.
               Then I know Chriſt, and this is to
beleeve in him. Read 1 Joh. 1. 6, 7. and
cha. 2. 1, 2, 3, 4. So Mat. 28. 20. Mar. 9.
from v. 43. to the end. Luke 6. 46. Joh.
15. 14.
               
                  §. 1.
                  
                     Q. HOw do you know the want
of Chriſt?
                  
                     
                     A. 1 I am far and for ever in my
ſelfe ſeparated from God by my ſin
naturall and actuall, Iſa. 59. 2. Pſal. 58
3. Ephe. 2. 13, 14.
                  2 I am foully ſtained and ſtinking
with all ſin in my whole nature, ſoule
and body, Pſal. 14. 3. and 51. 5. Rom. 3
from ver. 10. to 20.
                  3 There is no power in me to think
a good thought, or to keep any one of
Gods commandements once in all my
life, 2 Cor. 3. 5. Rom. 3. 9, 10. James 3. 2.
                  4 There is no plague but is upon me,
and for the ſinfulneſſe of my nature &amp;
ſins of my life, every curſe of God is on
my ſoule and body in this life, and that
which is to come, Deut. 27. 26. &amp; 28. 16
Mat. 25. 41.
                  5 There is no good dwelling in my
fleſh, nay not onely an emptineſſe of all
good, but an enmity againſt it, Gen. 6.
5. Rom. 7. 18. &amp; 8. 7.
                  6 I have no power to pleaſe God in
any good I doe, Rom. 8. 8. Prov. 15. 8.
Heb. 11. 6.
                  7 I have no hope to goe to heaven
when I die, 1 Cor. 15. 50. Rev. 21. 27.
                  
                     
O how miſerable and wretched is
that man or woman that lives and
dies (as many doe, Mat. 7. 13.) in this
corrupt and curſed condition without
Chriſt!
               
               
                  §. 2.
                  
                     Q. VVHat worth do you find
in Chriſt?
                  
                     A. 1. The excellency of his perſon,
being the onely begotten, beloved Son
of God, the heire of all things, the head
of his Church, Angels, Principalities
and Powers, being ſubject unto him,
Eph. 1. 21, 22. Col. 1. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.
Heb. 1, 2, 3, 4. 1 Pet. 3. 22.
                  2 The exceeding riches of his grace
freely offered, and fully given unto me
in the Goſpel, Eph. 2. 7. &amp; 3. 8. Iſay 61.
1, &amp;c.
                  3 The bleſſings that he brings, Acts
3. 26. Eph. 1. 3.
                  4 The graces that he gives, John 1.
14. 16.
                  O how happy is that man or woman
that is made one with the Son of God!

(how few are they Chriſt knowes,
Mat. 7. 14.) yet thrice happy is hee or
ſhee that have him for their head and
husband, who hath all power in his
hands, all heavenly bleſſings to beſtow
upon them, all ſpirituall graces to give
unto them, and an unſearchable riches
of grace to endow them to eternall
glory.
                  
                     Q. What is the grace of Chriſt?
                  
                     A. It is an honourable, holy and
happy condition that Chriſt hath called
me unto by the Goſpel; who being
the ſecond Adam, received my
nature unto himſelfe, reſtored it with
himſelfe into favour with God againe
from whom I fell, and raiſed my faln
nature into a higher favour and grace
with God the Father then it was in
the firſt Adam before his fall, Eph. 2.
5, 6.
                  1 He hath taken my nature ſeparated
from God, and hath now united it
to the Godhead for ever, Joh. 1. 14.
Heb. 2. 11, 14.
                  2 He hath ſanctified my nature ſinfull
in me, but perfectly holy in him,

                     Luke 1. 35. Joh. 17. 19. Heb. 7. 26.
                  3 He hath in my nature fulfilled the
whole Law for me, which I could never
doe, Rom. 10. 5. &amp; 8. 4.
                  4 Hee hath for my ſin in my ſtead
ſuffered the whole wrath of the Lord,
the curſe of the Law which I could never
ſuffer, Iſa. 53. 4, 5. 2 Cor. 5. 21. Gal.
3. 13. 1 Pet. 2. 24.
                  5 He filled my nature in himſelfe
with all grace, God gave him not the
Spirit by meaſure, but being made
fleſh, we beheld his glory, the glory as
of the only begotten of the Father, full
of grace and truth, John 1. 14. and 3.
34, 35.
                  6 He fulfilled all righteouſneſſe that
was to be done or ſuffered in life or
death by me, in my nature, in whom
God was well pleaſed, Mat. 3. 15, 17.
Mat. 12. 18.
                  7 He raignes in my nature glorified
above all in heaven, Epheſ.
1. 20.
               
               
                  
                  §. 3.
                  
                     Q. VVHy are you ſo willing
to receive Chriſt?
                  
                     A. That I may be knit unto him,
Gal, 3. 26. 28.
               
            
            
               PART .II.
               
                  Q. VVHat is it to bee knit
unto Chriſt.
               
                  A. To become one with him by
his Spirit, and my faith looking up
and laying hold on my nature in
him, that as hee tooke my fleſh and
made it his, ſo I take his fleſh and
make it mine, that thus I might bee
one with him and he with me. I dwell
in him and he in me; hee dwelleth in
me by faith, and I dwell in him in my
fleſh; that as my nature is become
his, ſo all his might be mine, Joh. 17.

21. and 6. 56. Epheſ. 3. 17. Cant. 6. 7.
               
                  Q. How are you one with Chriſt
Jeſus?
               
                  A. 1. Not one in conceit and
imagination.
               2 Nor one in conſent and affection.
               3 Nor one in ſubſtance and tranſfuſion,
as if the Godhead or manhood
of Chriſt were mixt with any ſubſtance.
               4 But one in ſpirit, or rather one
ſpirit, that is more, the ſelf-ſame ſpirit
dwelling in him, dwels in me: ſo uniting
me unto him, that through his
manhood from his Godhead, it conveyes,
and I receive all ſpirituall life
in ſoule and body for ever, 1 Cor. 6. 17
Rom. 8. 11. 1 Joh. 3. 23. John 6. 60.
               
                  Q. What union then is this that is
betweene Chriſt and you?
               
                  A. The neareſt that may be imagined:
for there is an union, firſt, of
linage or fleſh; thus many kinſmen
are one.
               2 Of love or friendſhip; thus many
men are one, Acts 4. 32. the ſoule

of Jonathan was knit to David, and this
union of Spirits is nearer then the firſt
of bodies.
               3 Matrimoniall; thus man and
wife are one, and this union is nearer
then both the former, ſeeing married
perſons are not onely one in fleſh, but
in higheſt love and friendſhip; beſides
a man muſt forſake father, neareſt fleſh
and friends to follow and cleave to
his wife.
               4 Myſticall, thus Chriſt and his
Church are one by a nearer union
then all the three; for Chriſt is not
onely, firſt, partaker of fleſh and blood
with us, Heb. 2. 14. Secondly, We are
his friends, John 15. 14. Thirdly, he is
our husband alſo, Iſay 54. 5. Fourthly,
But alſo he is our head, and we are
members of his body, of his fleſh, and
of his bone; and this union is called
Myſticall, becauſe it is more then any,
unconceivable in thought, and unutterable
by tongue; kinſmen, friends,
and married ones muſt die, and then
their union ends. But Chriſt hath ſo
taken my fleſh as never to be divided

from it; ſuch a friend as not life nor
death can divide me from him, whoſe
love paſſeth all knowledge and time,
loving me unto the end, and after all;
and not onely beloved, but I am betrothed
and married to him for ever,
and not onely betrothed, but I am of
his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones,
nay, by faith I eate his fleſh and drink
his blood, what nearer union can be?
               
                  Q. What is it to eat his fleſh?
               
                  A. 1. To apprehend, apply, and
partake of his fleſh as my owne, as the
meat I eat is mine.
               2 To beleeve that I am truely and
really (though ſpiritually) united unto
him, and one with him, of his bone,
and of his fleſh, as the meat I eat becomes
one with my ſubſtance.
               3 To expect in faith for all grace
and growth in good ſtrength in his
ſervices, quickning and comfort, and
eternall life from the fleſh of Chriſt:
as the meat I eat maintaines life, gives
nouriſhment and enables mee for all
naturall actions, ſo doth Chriſt, for
ſpirituall bread ſtrengthens mans

heart, and wine cheares it, ſo, and
more in mee doth Chriſts fleſh and
blood.
               
                  Q. How ſhall I make this knowledge
of Chriſt effectuall, and the knot
faſt for ever?
               
                  A. 1. By a faithfull humble meditating
on the grace of Chriſt, Joh. 6. 43,
44, 45, 55, 56.
               2 By an affectionate hearty thankſgiving
to God the Father who hath
bleſſed me with all ſpirituall bleſſings
in Chriſt, Eph. 1. 3.
               3 By a fruitfull diligent growing in
all the graces of the Spirit, Joh. 15. 3.
               4 By fervent daily prayer to God
the Father through Chriſt Jeſus by the
Spirit to enlighten and lead me to the
love of God unto eternall life, Eph. 1.
17. and 3. 19. 2 Theſſ. 3. 5.
               
                  §. 4.
                  
                     Q. HOw doe you meditate on
Chriſt?
                  
                     
                     A. I deſire to know Chriſt, not as
one farre from mee, but as one with
me, and I in him, and from him, or
rather through my fleſh in him, receiving
all things from God the Father
for my ſalvation. This is the meaning
of that, Joh. 6. 56. ſpoken of before, to
eate the fleſh of Chriſt (i. e.) by faith
to apply and truly to partake of Chriſts
fleſh as mine owne, and being out of
my ſelf, in it to have life, and through
it to have all things that concerne
grace and glory.
                  This is that S. Paul determined to
know, onely Jeſus Chriſt, and him
crucified, 1 Cor. 2. 2. Gal. 2. 20. for this
excellent knowledge S. Paul counted
all things but dung, that he might
win Chriſt; what is that? That I
might bee found in him not having
mine owne righteouſneſſe but his, not
my ſelfe, but him, Phil. 3. 8, 9, 10.
                  
                     Q. What doe you meditate of in
Chriſt?
                  
                     A. 1. I finde my nature, ſoule and
body united to God in him, and
therefore feele my ſelf reconciled, and

at one with God the Father; his Father,
my Father, his God my God,
Joh. 14. 20. 21, 23. &amp; 20. 17.
                  2 I ſee my nature ſanctified perfectly
in his perſon, from which I ſeek a
power to ſanctifie mine more and
more in my perſon, Heb. 2. 11. John
17. 10.
                  3 As hee hath fulfilled the law for
me, ſo
                  1 In him God accounts me righteous,
Rom. 3. 22. 2 Cor. 5. 21.
                  2 In me God accepts of my upright
purpoſe to pleaſe him in all things
for perfect righteouſneſſe, Pſal.
119. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
                  3 From him I receive a power to
perform the whole law in every point,
though not perfectly in the higheſt
pitch and purity that the Law requires,
yet (ſeeking and ſtriving to
perfection) pleaſingly as God accepts
in Chriſt Jeſus; who fulfilling the
Law for me in my fleſh, which he took,
writes the Law in me by his Spirit,
which he gives, making me to delight

                        •
                     n the Law of God in the inward man,

to be ready to doe his will, to have reſpect
to all his Commandements, to
refrain my feet from every evill way,
to purge my ſelf from all filthineſſe of
fleſh and Spirit, perfecting holineſſe in
his fear, Jer. 31. 33. &amp; 32. 40. Heb. 8. 10.
Rom. 7. 22. Pſal. 40. 8. &amp; 119. 6. 101. 2.
2 Cor. 7. 1 Phil. 3. 12, 13, 14, 15.
                  4 He hath ſatisfied Gods juſtice in
ſuffering in my ſtead, being made a
curſe for me, and in his own ſelf bearing
my ſins in his own body upon the
tree; ſo I look for
                  1 Peace in my ſelf from above, being
crucified with Chriſt, Gal. 2. 20
                  2 Power over ſin within, being crucified
with Chriſt in my corrupt
nature, Rom. 6. 6.
                  Chriſt ſtood on the Croſſe as my
ſurety in my ſtead.
                  1 As a ſinner; for he was made ſin
for me, 2 Cor. 5. 2.
                  2 As accurſed, for hee was made a
curſe for me, Gal. 3. 13.
                  So being one with him.
                  1 As hee in my nature is full o
                        •
                     
grace, ſo out of his fulneſſe I looke to

receive grace for grace, Joh. 1. 16. Col. 1.
9. &amp; 2. 3, 9, 10.
                  2 My beſt duties are in me damnable,
but in Chriſt Jeſus, God and Man,
my Mediator and Maſter, my perſon
is accepted, and all my actions pleaſing,
Eph. 1. 6.
                  3 I ſee my ſelf ſhut out of Paradiſe,
I have no hope of heaven in my ſelfe,
a dead dog, a damned creature, an heir
of hell; but God which is rich in mercy,
for his great love wherewith hee
hath loved me when I was dead in ſin,
hath quickned me together with
Chriſt, and raiſed mee up with him,
and made me ſit together in heavenly
places with Chriſt Jeſus. So then in
Chriſt I roſe, and in Chriſt now I raign
in heaven being now on earth, (i. e.)
I ſee by faith my own nature in Chriſt
ſitting at the right hand of God, who
is my good and great high Prieſt,
                  
                     In
                     1 Preſenting my perſon to the Father
and making mee pleaſing
unto him, Heb. 4. 14.
                     2 Perfuming my prayers, and
praying for mee to his Father,

                        Heb. 7. 25. Revel. 8. 3, 4.
                     3 Preparing a place for me, and me
for that place by his Spirit, John
14. 2, 16. Col. 1. 12.
                  
               
               
                  §. 5.
                  
                     Q. VVHat are the bleſſings
that Chriſt Jeſus
brings?
                  
                     A. Firſt, Eternall election to life in
his Fathers love, Eph. 1. 4.
                  2 Adoption to become the ſon of
God with himſelfe, Eph. 1. 5.
                  3 Acceptation of my perſon, and
all my actions in him, Eph. 1. 6.
                  4 Redemption of my ſoule and body
by his blood; and juſtification,
whereby I am fully cleared from Gods
judgement, freed from Gods wrath,
my ſins forgiven, and I freely accounted
as juſt, Eph. 1. 7.
                  5 Vocation, whereby I am the called
of Chriſt Jeſus, Rom. 1. 6. in the
Goſpel, wherein he hath abounded to

me in all wiſdome and prudence, having
made knowne unto mee the myſtery
of his will, Eph. 1. 8, 9.
                  6 Eternall ſalvation, and an immortall
inheritance in heaven with all
Angels and Saints that ever were or
ſhall be, Eph. 1. 10, 11.
                  And all this to the praiſe of the glory
of his grace, Eph. 1. 6, 12.
               
               
                  §. 6.
                  
                     Q. VVHat are the graces that
Chriſt Jeſus gives?
                  
                     A. 1. Knowledge, Col. 2. 3. to underſtand,
                  1 The Word of God and meaning
of the Scriptures, Luke 24. 45.
                  2 The will of God, Iohn 15. 15. and
the minde of Chriſt, 1 Cor. 2. 16.
                  3 The myſteries, of the kingdome of
heaven, Mat. 13. 11.
                  4 The miſery, wretchedneſſe, blindneſſe,
poverty, nakedneſſe of my
naughty nature, Rev. 3. 17, 18. Rom.
7. 18.
                  
                     
5 The graces of the Spirit in me, and
the good things which are freely
given unto mee of God through
Chriſt Jeſus, 1 Cor. 2. 12.
                  2 Faith, with the beginning and increaſe
thereof, Mark 9. 24. Luke 17. 5.
Eph. 2. 8.
                  3 Repentance with a mourning
melting ſpirit, Acts 5. 31. for every ſin
in my ſelf and others by Chriſts look
on me, Luke 22. 61, 62. and mine on
Chriſt, Zech. 12. 10.
                  4 Love to God and men, good and
bad, Deut. 30. 6. Rom. 5. 5. 1 Theſ. 4. 9.
Mat. 5. 44.
                  5 The feare of the Lord God, Ier.
32. 40. This covenant is made in
Chriſt, Heb. 8. 8. therefore he gives it,
working it in mee by his Spirit, and
warning me of it by his Word, Luke
12. 5.
                  6 Hope of my inheritance in heaven,
Rom. 15. 13. 2 Theſſ. 2. 16.
                  7 In a word all other graces ſpringing
from the Father, the fountaine of
grace, conveied in Chriſt, through
his fleſh by his Spirit into my heart,

ſhed abroad and ſtreaming on to everlaſting
life, Iohn 4. 14. &amp; 7. 37, 38. Gal.
5. 22, 23, 24.
               
               
                  §. 7.
                  
                     Q. VVHat muſt you doe on
your part to continue
your communion with God the Father
in Chriſt Jeſus by the Spirit?
                  
                     A. 1. Generally.
                  1 Fly for my life every ſin open or
ſecret, and every appearance of evill
that may ſeparate betweene God and
me, or make mee faile of his grace in
Chriſt, or grieve his holy Spirit, Eſay
59. 2. Heb. 12. 15. Eph. 4. 30.
                  2 Follow after holineſſe, and in all
holy occaſions, company and courſes,
commanded by God and commended
by good men, continue and increaſe in
all goodneſſe &amp; all good duties, cleanſing
my ſelfe continually from all
filthineſſe of fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting
holineſſe in his feare, 2 Cor. 7. 1.
                  
                     
2 Particularly.
                  1 I give all diligence alwayes to
make my calling and election ſure,
2 Pet. 1. 10.
                  2 Walke humbly with my God
hourely, with a reverend awfull reſpect
of his preſence, fearing to offend
his Majeſty in any thing, Mich. 6. 8
Pſal. 139. 2, 3.
                  3 Renew my repentance daily for
my hourely offences or frailty, confeſſing
them in particular, and craving
pardon, and purging, 1 Joh. 1. 9.
                  4 I humble my ſelfe weekly in faſting
for ſome ſpeciall ſins and daily
ſlips in his ſervice, or my calling; put
aſide ſome houres, if I cannot a whole
day, Mat. 5. 20. and 6. 17.
                  5 Remember to covenant monthly
with my Lord in the Sacrament of the
Body and Bloud of Chriſt Jeſus, or as
oft as it is adminiſtred, 1 Cor. 11. 26.
                  6 Once in the yeare caſt up all my
accounts, ſee how my Communion is
increaſed, and my corruptions leſſened,
and how far I am gone and grown
in grace, and in the knowledge of

Chriſt, Lev. 16. 34. Once a yeare Merchants
caſt up their whole accounts,
and Husbandmen know their increaſe
of corne and cattell; So they who are
wiſe Merchants and working Chriſtians,
may obſerve in themſelves a
change or increaſe in a yeares ſpace,
what cannot be ſo ſenſibly perceived
in a ſhort time.
                  7 The Chriſtian Sabbaths and Saints
muſt be my delight, holy and honorable,
when, and with whom I have
more opportunity and time to have
communion with thy God, Iſa. 58. 13.
Pſal. 16. 3.
                  8 The Word of God muſt abide &amp;
dwell in me richly, wherein I may acquaint
my ſelfe with my Maſters will,
my Fathers love, and communicate
both to my fellow ſervants and brethren,
Col. 3. 16.
                  9 Take heed of omitting any occaſion
of doing good, or receiving good in
conference or company with men, or
my good duty in publicke or private
before God, Mal. 3. 16.
                  10 Beware of careleſſe and cuſtomary

performance of any holy duty,
but do it in love of Communion with
my God, that by every prayer I make,
every word I heare, &amp;c. I may come
neerer to him in Chriſt Jeſus, Jer. 48.
10. Pſal. 73. 28.
                  11 Weane my ſelfe from the world,
uſe the world as not uſing it, entangle
not my ſelf in other mens matters nor
mine own, draw heavenly thoughts
from earthly things, deny my ſelfe not
only in indifferent, but in lawfull, yea
neceſſary things, 1 Cor. 7. 31. &amp; 6. 12.
                  12 Watch my heart with all diligence,
the riſing of my luſt, the checks
of my conſcience, the motions of the
Spirit, &amp;c▪ 
                     Pro. 4. 23.
                  13 Worke out my ſalvation with
feare and trembling, ſtriving harder▪
running faſter, and preſſing on to the
prize of the high calling of God in
Chriſt Jeſus, Phil. 2. 12. and 3. 14.
                  14 Obſerve ſtill my preſent eſtate▪
the tempter of my ſoule, my ſpirituall
decayes, deadneſſe, dulneſſe, hardneſſe
of heart, ſecurity, ſtrangeneſſe from
God, I ſuffer not theſe to ſtay long upon

me, but ſtir up my ſelfe by repentance
and prayer, and ſtrengthen the
things which remaine and are ready
to die, Rev. 3. 2, 17. and 2. 4, 5.
                  15 Goe forward in good duties,
fruitfull in good works, fervent in ſpirit,
zealous in Gods cauſe, ſenſible of
the leaſt ſinne, and above all things
beward of barrenneſſe and back-ſliding,
and an evill heart of unbeliefe in
departing from the living God, 1 Cor.
15. 58. Col. 1. 10. Rom. 12. 11. 1 Theſ. 5.
22. Heb. 10.
                  16 Stir up my faith continually, ſeek
to the Lord, ſtrengthen it, ſtudy the
promiſes, apply them perfectly, and in
them Chriſt to thy ſelfe, ſticke very
faſt unto the Lord, cleave unto him,
cling about him, depart not from him,
depend upon him, delight in him, and
be thankfull to him, beleeve and live
in the light of his countenance, and of
his Commandements, Iſa. 64. 7. 2 Tim.
1. 6. 1 Pet. 1. 13. Act. 11. 23.
                  17 In my neareſt approaches, and
deareſt imbraces by him, I am not too
bold, but in my ſtrongeſt feelings,

ſweeteſt refreſhments, ſpirituall conſolations
in Chriſt, comforts of the
ſpirit, joy in Gods face and favour, I
feare and tremble before him, Pſal. 2
11. 1 Pet. 1. 17.
                  18 Feare the Lord my God all my
dayes, a feare not of diſtruſt but of diligence
to work, &amp; jealouſie to watch
my ſelfe, a feare not ſervile only of his
juſtice, but ſonnelike of his goodneſſe,
a feare not to drive me from God, but
to draw mee to him; wee cannot beleeve
or love the Lord too much, but
yet God doth not cocker his children,
therefore when thou moſt beleeveſ
                        •
                     
that thou lieſt in the arms of his love,
feare the more, leſt then thou fall aſleep,
ſecure and ſweetly ſin: Satan
ſeeks but this, to find thee thus, hee
cares not then, but rocks, ſits by, and
ſings, and keeps thee faſt aſleep, with
the ſweet ſound of faith and aſſurance
Pro. 28. 14.
                  Oh the ſlights of Satan, the methods,
myſteries, and depths of the Devill,
in our neereſt communion with God
to caſt us fartheſt from him!
                  
                     
19 Continue conſtant in prayer,
watching thereunto with all perſeverance,
preſent my ſelfe oft before the
Lord upon my knees, in my Cloſet, or
ſome corner, if it bee but a word or
two, 'twill increaſe my acquaintance
and my communion with him; have
my heart ever upward, heavenly and
humble, ſending up ſometimes ſtrong
groanes, ſudden ſighs, ſhort ejaculations,
petitions or prayſes in the midſt of
worldly affairs, callings and company,
&amp;c. when they think not of it, ſteale a
ſecret thought to the throne of grace,
and my Father which ſeeth in ſecret,
&amp;c. Luk. 18. 1. Eph. 6. 18. Col. 4. 2. 1 Pet.
4. 7. Neh. 2. 4.
               
               
                  §. 8.
                  
                     Q. VVHat ſhould you eſpecially
pray for?
                  
                     A. 1 That the God of our Lord

                        •
                     eſus Chriſt, the Father of glory may
give unto me the ſpirit of wiſdom and

revelation in the knowledge of him;
The eye of my underſtanding being
enlightened, that I may know what is
the hope of his calling, and what the
riches of the glory of his inheritance
in the Saints: And what is the exceeding
greatneſſe of his power to usward,
who beleeves according to the
working of his mighty power.
                  
                     In
                     1 pardoning all my ſinnes againſt
him, Num. 14. 17.
                     2 Subduing the power of every
ſin in me, Mich. 7. 19.
                     3 Sanctifying me more and more
in ſpirit, ſoule, and body blameleſſe,
1 Theſ. 5. 23.
                     4 Strengthening mee in all hi
                           •
                        
ſervices, Iſa. 40. 29.
                     5 Supporting me in all my ſufferings,
faintings, feares, Iſa. 41. 1
                           •
                        
                     
                     6 Supplying all my wants exceeding
abundantly above all tha
                           •
                        
I can aske or think, Eph. 3. 20.
                     7 Saving me to the uttermo
                           ••
                        
from all evill, Heb. 7. 25.
                     8 Preſerving me to ſalvation, tha
                           •
                        
I fall not from good, 1 Pet. 1. 5▪
                     
                     
                        
9 Preſenting me faultleſſe before
his glorious preſence with joy,
Jude 24.
                     10 Raiſing me at the laſt day, and
changing my vile body that it
may be like unto his glorious
Body, according to his mighty
working, &amp;c. Phil. 3. 21.
                  
                  Which he wrought in Chriſt when he
raiſed him from the dead, and ſet him
at his own right hand in the heavenly
places, far above all principality, and
power, and might, and dominion, and
every name that is named, not only in
this world, but alſo in that which is to
come: And hath put all things under
his feet, and gave him to be the head
over all things to the Church; which
is his Body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth
all in all, Eph. 1. 17, 18, &amp;c.
                  2 That God would grant me according
to the riches of his glory, to be
ſtrengthened with might by his Spirit
in the inner man, that Chriſt may
dwell in my heart by faith, that being
rooted and grounded in love, I may
be able to comprehend with all Saints

what is the breadth, and length, and
depth, and height: And to know the
love of Chriſt which paſſeth knowledge,
that I may be filled with all the
fulneſſe of God, Eph. 3. 16, 17, 18.
                  1 The fulneſſe of the knowledge of
his Will, Col. 1. 9.
                  2 The full aſſurance of his favour,
Col. 2. 2.
                  3 The fulneſſe of all grace in Chriſt
Jeſus.
                  4 The fulneſſe of all joy in the holy
Ghoſt, unſpeakeable and glorious, not
only in the feelings of faith, but of afflictions,
1 Pet. 1. 6, 8. Rom. 5. 3.
                  5 The fulneſſe of glory in his haevenly
kingdome at his right hand,
when he ſits to intercede for mee and
his whole myſticall body, to raigne in
us his members, and over his and our
enemies, till the laſt day, when he ſhall
deliver up the kingdome to God the
Father, 1 Cor. 15. 28. Then God ſhall
be all in all, when wee ſhall bee filled
with the fulneſſe of God, and ſee him
face to face. Now we ſee God the Father
mediately in the face of Chriſt,

then we ſhal ſee him immediately face
to face with Chriſt: yet without a Mediator;
now we are filled with the fulneſſe
of Chriſt only, then we ſhall be
filled with the fulneſſe of God alone.
                  1 We are the fulneſſe of Chriſt who
being his members, he accounts himſelfe
but maimed without us, Eph. 1. 23
1 Cor. 12. 12.
                  2 We have the fulneſſe of God, in
Chriſt, who being our head, ſupplies
by his Spirit all things unto us, that
can be had in God the Father, or from
him, what ever can make us:

                        
                           
                              
                                 1 Holy in him here,
                                 2 Happy with him
hereafter.
                              
                           
                           Ephe. 3. 19.
1 John 1. 3.
                        
                     
                  
                  Now unto him who is able to do exceeding
abundantly above all that we
aske or thinke, according to the power
that worketh in us: unto him be glory
in the Church by Chriſt Jeſus,
throughout all ages, world without
end, Amen, Eph. 3. 20, 21.
                  In him (that is Chriſt) we actually
are by our actuall incorporation into
that ſociety which hath him for their

head, and doth make together with
him one body (he and they in that reſpect
having one name, 1 Cor. 12. 12.)
for which cauſe by vertue of this myſticall
conjunction, we are of him and
in him, even as though our fleſh and
bones ſhould be made continuate with
his. Hooker pag. 123.
                  
                     Ergo gratulemur &amp; agamus gratias,
non ſolumnos Chriſtianos factos eſſe, ſed
etiam Chriſtum. Intelligitis, fratres, gratiam
Dei ſuper nos; capitis, admiramini,
gaudete. Christus facti ſumus; Si enim
ille caput eſt, &amp; nos membra, totus ille homo
&amp; nos. Auguſt. in Iohan. tract. 31. Let
us rejoyce and give thankes, that we
are not onely made Chriſtian men,
but alſo made Chriſts Brethren; yee
underſtand the grace of God, that is
upon us; ye underſtand it, ye wonder
at it. Rejoyce ye, we are made Chriſt.
For if he be the head and we the members,
both he and we are one whole
man.
               
            
         
         
            
            The Myſtery of JESUS
CHRIST, Emmanuel
GOD with us.
            
               The Myſtery of Incarnation.
               God with us: receiving us into himſelf,
uniting our nature with his into
the perſon of his Son, Mat. 1. 23. Ioh.
1. 14. Heb. 2. 16. 1 Tim. 3. 16.
               God with us.
            
            
               The Myſtery of Reconciliation.
               God with us: reconciling us unto himſelfe,
accepting our perſons, not imputing
our ſins by the blood of his
Son, 2 Cor. 5. 18, 19.
               God in Chriſt.
            
            
               The Myſtery of Regeneration.
               God with us: renewing our natures to
bee like himſelfe, partakers of the

divine nature, changing us into his
owne Image by the Spirit of his
Son, Col. 1. 27, 28. 2 Cor. 3. 18. 2 Pet.
1. 4.
               Chriſt in us.
            
            
               The Mystery of mysticall Ʋnion.
               God with us: uniting our perſons to
his Son by his Spirit and our faith,
wherby we are members of Chriſts
body, of his bone, and of his fleſh,
which we feed on, finding life,
grace, and ſpirituall ſtrength, conveyed
through it by the Spirit from
God the Father, Eph. 5. 30, 32. Ioh. 6.
56, 60.
               We in Chriſt.
            
            
               The Myſtery of the Goſpel.
               God with us: who were without God,
without Chriſt, without hope or
mercy, no people, ſtrangers from
the Common-weale of Iſrael, and

covenant of promiſe, enemies of
God, children of his wrath, in the
power of the Devil, ſitting in darkneſſe
and ſhadow of death, dead in
ſins, and the damnation of hell, at
that time we were thus, being Gentiles,
till Chriſt came in the fleſh:
and at this time we are thus, being
as Gentiles, till our effectuall Calling
by Chriſts Spirit, Eph. 2. 12. &amp;
3. 3, 5.
               We with Iſrael.
            
            
               The Mystery of the firſt Reſurrection.
               God with us: in calling home his old
people Iſrael (who are now as wee
were) into one Church with us to
confeſſe, profeſſe and praiſe Chriſt
Jeſus our Lord, together on earth,
Rom. 11. 25. The Jewes reſtoring a
reſurrection, Rom. 11. 15. (that is)
the firſt reſurrection, Rev. 20. 5, 6.
               Iſrael with us.
            
            
               The Mystery of the ſecond Reſurrection.
               
                  
God with us: In calling us all up by
the ſound of a Trump, at the ſecond
comming of Chriſt, changing our
bodies and carrying us up both body
and ſoule to meet the Lord Jeſus
in the aire, where and when the
whole Church militant and triumphant,
the family in heaven and
earth, both Jew and Gentile, and all
the Iſrael of God ſhall meet at once,
and ſo wee ſhall ever bee with the
Lord, 1 Cor. 15. 51. 1 Theſſ. 4. 17.
               All Iſrael, and we with God.
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              The firſt Myſtery was God
with us,
                              The laſt Myſtery ſhall bee,
we with God,
                           
                        
                        And God
All in All.
1 Cor. 15.
28.
                     
                     
                        Though I underſtand all
Myſteries, and have not
love,
                        I am nothing,
1 Cor 13.
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            
            A plaine tryall by the Word of God of Mans ſpirituall estate
whether he be in Christ Jeſus, or no.
            In The ſtate of Nature-Damnation—or In The ſtate of grace —Salvation.
            
               
                  
                     Fleſh.
                     Spirit.
                  
                  
                     1 There is therefore now no condemnation
to—
                     —them that are in Chriſt Jeſus.
                  
                  
                     Who walke not after the fleſh—
                     —but after the Spirit, Rom. 8. 1.
                  
                  
                     They that are after the fleſh do mind
the things of fleſh.—
                     But they that are after the Spirit, mind
the things of the Spirit, v. 5.
                  
                  
                     The carnall mind is enmity againſt
God, for it is not ſubject unto the
Law of God, neither in deed can be:
ſo then they that are in the fleſh cannot
pleaſe God, ver. 7, 8.
                     But to bee ſpiritually minded, is life
and peace, v. 6. but ye are not in the
fleſh, but the ſpirit, if ſo bee that the
Spirit of God dwell in you; but if
any have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he
is none of his, v. 9.
                  
                  
                     Now then Brethren wee are debtors
not to the fleſh, to live after the fleſh,
but yet if ye live after the fleſh, yee
ſhall die, ver. 12.
                     But if through the Spirit yee mortifie
the deeds of the fleſh, yee ſhall live,
v. 13.
                  
                  
                     Now the works of the fleſh are manifeſt,
which are adultery, fornication,
uncleanneſſe, laſciviouſneſſe, idolatry,
witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulation,
wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies,

reſies, envyings, murthers, drunkenneſſe,
revellings, and ſuch like; of
which I tell you before, as I have told
you in time paſt, that they which do
ſuch ſhall not inherit the kingdome
of God, Gal. 5. 19, 20, 21.
                     
                        But the fruit of the ſpirit is love, joy,
peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe,
goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, temperance,
againſt ſuch there is no law;
and they that are CHRISTS
have crucified the fleſh, with
the affections and luſts thereof.
                        If we live in the Spirit, let us walke
in the Spirit, Galat. 5. 22, 23,
24, 25.
                     
                  
                  
                  
                     2 If any man be—in
                     Chriſt, he is a new creature—
                  
                  
                     Old things are paſſed away,—
                     —All things are become new, 2 Cor.
5. 17.
                  
                  
                     If wee ſay wee have fellowſhip with
with him, and walke in darkneſſe,
we lie, 1 Joh. 1. 6, 7.
                     He that ſaith he abideth in him, ought
himſelfe alſo to walke, as he walked,
1 Ioh. 2. 7.
                  
                  
                     He that ſaith I know him, and keepeth
not his Commandements, is a lyar
1 John 2. 4.
                     But who ſo keepeth his word, in him
verily is the love of God perfected:
hereby know we that we are in him,
1 Ioh. 2. 5.
                  
                  
                     He that committeth ſin, is of the Devill,
1 Joh. 3. 8.
                     Whoſoever abideth in him, ſinneth
not, 1 Ioh. 3. 6.
                  
                  
                     Ye are of your father the Devill, and
the luſts of your father ye will do, he
alſo is a lyar, Joh. 8. 44.
                     Whoſoever is borne of God, doth not
commit ſin, for his ſeed remaineth
in him, ſo that he cannot ſin, becauſe
he is borne of God, 1 Ioh. 3. 9.
                  
                  
                     
                        Caine was of the wicked one, and ſlew
his brother; and wherefore ſlew hee
him? becauſe his own works were
evill, and his brothers good, 1 John
3. 12.
                     Marvaile not my brethren if the
world hate you. We know we have
paſſed from death to life, becauſe we
love the brethren, 1 Ioh. 3. 13.
                  
                  
                     The wicked ſhall be turned into hell,
and all the nations that forget God,
upon the ſinners, he will raine ſnares,
fire, and brimſtone, ſtorme and tempeſt;
this ſhall bee their portion for
ever, Pſal. 9. 17. and 11. 6.
                     Bleſſed are they that do his Commandements,
that they may have right
to the tree of life, (Chriſt Jeſus our
Lord) and enter in through the gates
of the City, Ioh. 20. 14.
                  
                  
                  
                     The hypocrites hope ſhall periſh, and
the eyes of the wicked ſhall faile,
their hope ſhall be as the giving up of
the Ghoſt, Iohn. 8. 13. and 11. 20.
                     But the righteous hath hope in his
death; and he that hath the hope
purifyeth himſelfe as he is pure, Pro.
24. 32. 1 Iohn 3. 3.
                  
                  
                     3 Shall I take the members of Chriſt,
and make—
                     —them the members of an Harlot?
God forbid, 1 Cor. 6. 15.
                  
                  
                     Shall I take the tongue of Chriſt and
make it—
                     —The tongue of a ſwearer? &amp;c. Pſal.
12. 4. Mat. 5. 37.
                  
                  
                     Hee that yeelds any one of his members
to—
                     —Sinne, is no member of Chriſt Jeſus,
but—
                  
                  
                     — a limbe of the Devill, of the myſtery
of iniquity,—
                     —and has no part in the Myſticall union
of Chriſt and his Church, Rom.
6, 13. 14.
                  
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

