
   
      
         
            De immensa dei misericordia. A sermon of the excedynge great mercy of god, / made by ye moste famous doctour maister Eras. Rot. Translated out of Latine into Englisshe, at the request of the moste honorable and vertuous lady, the lady Margaret Countese of Salisbury.
            De misericordia Domini English
            Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
         
         
            
               1526
            
         
         Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00356
            STC 10474
            ESTC S109811
            99845455
            99845455
            10357
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00356)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10357)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 67:4)
         
         
            
               
                  De immensa dei misericordia. A sermon of the excedynge great mercy of god, / made by ye moste famous doctour maister Eras. Rot. Translated out of Latine into Englisshe, at the request of the moste honorable and vertuous lady, the lady Margaret Countese of Salisbury.
                  De misericordia Domini English
                  Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
                  Hervet, Gentian, 1499-1584.
               
               [100] p.   
               
                  In fletestrete, by Thomas Berthelet, printer vnto the kynges most noble grace, dwellyng at the sygne of Lucrece. Cum priuilegio,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1531?]
               
               
                  A translation, by Gentian Hervet, of: Erasmus, Desiderius.  De misericordia Domini.
                  Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC (2nd ed.).
                  Signatures: A-L⁴ M⁶.
                  Title within ornamental border (McK. &amp; Ferg. 16).
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               God --  Mercy --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-04
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-05
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            De immensa dei misericordia.
            A sermon of the excedynge great mercy of god / made by ye moste famous doctour maister Eras. Rot. Translated out of Latine in to Englisshe / at the request of the moste honorable and vertuous lady / the lady Margaret Countese of Salisbury.
         
         
            
            
            ¶To the most honorable lady the lady Coūtese of Salisbury Gentian Heruet her humble seruant gretyng.
            
               SEynge and vnderstandynge mooste honourable lady your great mynde and depe affection bothe towarde al maner of lernyng / and specially towarde that / whiche either exciteth or teacheth vertue &amp; goodnes / and concerneth the way of our saluacion / I haue translated out of Latin in to englishe a sermon of Erasmus of the mercy of god: the whiche trāslated for you / and dedicate vnto your ladyshyp, I thought it shuld be a good dede / if for your ladisshyps pleasure it were printed &amp; spred abrode: And where as afore lerned mē only dyd get out both pleasure and great frute in redyng of this boke / nowe euery mā as wel rude as lerned may haue this sermon of the mercy of god as cōmon vnto him as ye mercy of god it selfe is. And as touchyng ye cōmēdacion either of the autor or of ye warke, I knowe the tēdernes of my wyt moche more slēder thā that I can be able to beare the weyght of suche an enterprise, &amp; I rekē to be moche better to holde my tōge vtterly frō y• preysyng / thā of them to speke to littel, &amp; for faute of wyt to minishe their excellēce. Yet nethelesse it semeth expediēt vnto me, yt by your ladishyp brefly other folke may knowe how noble is the autor of this warke / &amp; how moche we be boūde to hym for it. The autor of the boke is Erasmus Roterodamus / 

whom my preyses can no more ennoble / thā the son with a candel may be made clerer. He is the man / to whom in lernynge no lyuyng man may hym selfe cōpare: and nat only passeth them that be alyue / but also from the most part of olde autors hath beraft ye price / and nat onely paynēs and gentyls but also Chrsten doctors. He is ye mā that whan in his fyrst dayes trouth was far hyd in the depe veines of the grounde / and more ouer it was prohibited as a thyng being worthy deth yt no man shulde for her enquere, he dyd nat suffre the worlde to be cōfounded with suche a marueylous darknes, and either he hath dygged vp many 
                  •
               ȳmes of trouth / or at the lest he hath restored vs free libertie to serche her. He is the mā that to Isaac may be compared / the whiche dygged vp the goodly spryngyng welles / that the Philistēs distroied and with dyrte &amp; donge ouerfylled. The clere springes of the holy scripture / that ye Philistiēs had so troubled / so marred / and so defiled / yt no man coude drynke or haue the true taste of the water / they be nowe by his labour and diligence to their olde purenes and clerenes so restored yt no spotte nor erthly fylthe in them remayneth. And though ye Philistiēs dyd al that they coude to disturbe hym from his holy purpose / and yt amōge the people by the reason of them / he was greatly hated and enuied / yet at the last as it chanceth alway vnto them that with a bold stomake in their good dedes do contynue / excellent vertue hath ouercome enuy / whan frō this mā there can come

out nothing but both it is excedyng ꝓfitable and on euery side all perfect / me thynketh yt this litell treatise being in euery poynt as perfect as any other be in profit / nat only giueth no place but also greatly passeth: for where afore the warkes that he made were ꝓfitable but specially to one kynde of men / his Prouerbes / his Newe Testament / and many other treatyses onely to lerned men / of the boke of ye Instruction of princis ye moste profit redūdeth to princes. This boke only with the boke called ye knife or wepō of a Christē 
               
                  •
               owdiour hath so far spredde abrode his fruteful branches, that ther is no mā but great frute gether he may out of it / except he that thynketh that it maketh no matter whether he be dampned or saued. And as for the knyfe of a Christē sowdiour whiche he nameth Enchiridion, it bryngeth a man out of the way of vicis / and leadeth hym in the way of vertue and the path of saluation. This littel treatise of the mercy of god teacheth a man to ascribe nothyng to hym selfe / but all to gether to the mercy of god / seing that the fre wyl it selfe that we be indewed with all / is the fre gyfte of almighty god / and except it were by him made clerer / it shuld be so darke with the rust of the original synne, that ye image of vertue in it shulde neuer be fast printed. And who so euer beyng entred in to ye kyngdome of god by bap
                  •
               yme doth ascribe any thyng to his owne wysedome / to his merites, and to his deseruynges / and nat aknowlegeth euery where his owne feblenes / trusting vpon ye fre grace &amp; mercy

of almyghty god / it is to be drade / leest for mercy that is euery where redy for hym that calleth / he proue the sore and rigorous iustice of god. Nowe let vs se whither it be more expediēt for a mannis saluaciō, either by iustice to be feared from synne, or by mercy to be enticed bothe to loue and to vertue. Iustyce with her sore thretnynges cōpelleth a mā to flee vice / and engēdreth in hym a certayn bōdly feare / that it is an odious thyng vnto hym to cōmit synne / nat for ye hate it selfe of sinne, but for feare of punishemēt. Mercy cōtrary to it putteth before a mannes face the vnspekable loue of god towarde hym, ye whiche so loued him, that he dyd nat spare his onely sonne for his sake / the incredible benefites / the infinite desire of his saluacion / the continuall callyng vpon hym to brynge hym to the euerlastyng blysse. Of ye other side she sheweth hym as if it were in a glasse / the weakenes and feblenes of a man / the perilles that he is compassed about with, the calamites, the miseri, ye wretchednes that on euery side do vtterly hym wrappe, and that in so many mischeues, there cometh no succour but fro the mercy of god / do nat all these engēdre in hym a certaine childyshe loue towarde his father / that he wyl performe his cō
               maundemētes / nat for feare of punishement / nor for loue of rewarde, but for bicause it pleaseth his most louyng father? And that he accompted this a very great rewarde to do the thyng that dothe lyke suche a good father. And where as it is sayd that ye feare of our lorde is the beginnyng of wisedome / 

though the same feare somwhat cōcerneth the drede of iustice / yet I reken that it is nat to be taken for that bondly feare yt maketh vs to drede the sore punyshemētes, but for that that maketh vs to loke about / that we do nothyng that shulde displease our most louyng father, orels feare with out loue longeth to a cruel tyrant / that careth nat for the peoples hatred, so they feare him / and nat to ye most mercifull lorde &amp; father of vs all / whose loue towarde mankynde neither with minde can be comprehended nor with wordes any thyng expressed. The whiche seynge that he loueth vs so moche, and that all our helpe and soccour cometh from hym / let vs set al our trust and confidence in hym, withdrawyng al our trust and our hope frō al mortal thynges / &amp; from al mortal mē. Yf we be in nede / let vs cal vpō him, he is benigne / he is liberal / he gyueth gladlier than other do take / if so y• we make hym nat a nygarde in askyng of smal thȳges &amp; vnworthy of hym to be gyuē. If we be in synne let vs cal vpō his mercy / being sory &amp; repentāt. Whan so euer a synner is truely repētant he forgyueth al maner of synne. Here amōge mē they yt do forgyue syn haue nat al an egall power: som cases be reserued to ye pope / &amp; of ye popes him selle power som do put a great dout: but god him selfe is he yt hath rule both in heuē &amp; in erth, there is no dout yt of his autorite &amp; power can be made. If we desyre to come to the euerlastyng felicite / &amp; eschewe the feareful peynes of hell / let vs beseche his mercy to kepe vs frō sinne / &amp; gyue vs strēgth

to 
                  •
               ulfyll his wyll and his cōmand
                  •
               mētes / and so done / let vs put vs al holle to his pleasure &amp; mercy / &amp; let vs nat trust vpō certayn vayne prayers / the whiche with moche error be spred amōge mē, as though they had this vertue &amp; power / yt who so euer mūbleth them vp shal eschewe euerlastȳg punyshemētes. O subtile serpent / o disceitfull diuel, howe various, howe crafty be thyn imaginaciōs? bicause he seeth yt frō our simple &amp; stedfaste beleue he can nat bryng vs away / he goth about to bring vs in to an odious supersticiousnes / and bicause he seeth that that mā can nat do amisse / yt vpō the mercy of god setteth his holle trust / he ꝑsuadeth rude and ignorant foles to set their trust vpon vaine thȳges, that they shulde set only vpō god. Surely suche he is / and he wyll neuer ceasse to let vs frō our iourney heuēward / out of whiche place he was ouerthrowē. But the mo wiles and subtilties yt he worketh / the more grace &amp; strēgth god giueth vs to withstand hym. But it is tyme most honorable lady to lay by my rude and vn
                  •
               loquēt lāgage, yt ye may here Erasmꝰ speke eloquētly / and in your owne mothers tōge very playnly, the whiche so cōmendeth to the herers ye vnmeasurable and infinite mercy of god / yt who so euer in his hart fast printeth it, he shal finde out of it a marueloꝰ great frute both to know his owne misery / and of god the infinite boūte / yt whiche two thynges be most effectuous to directe vs to the eue
                  •
               las
                  •
               ynge f
                  •
               lycite / that is Christe Iesus / the whiche preserue your lady
                  •
               shyppe and all yours.
            AMEN.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶A sermō of the excedyng great mercy of god made by Erasmus Roterodamus.
            
               FOr as moche as I pourpose this daye to speake of the greatnes of the mercies of our lorde / Bretherne and systerne most welbeloued in Christ / without whose helpe mās frailte and weakenes can naught do: let vs all to gether with a common prayer beseche the mercy of the cōmon lorde of vs all / so to moue the instrument of my tonge / and so to stere and kendell your hartes / that as we shall departe hēce through the mercy of our lorde more plentiouslye endewed with heuenly grace: so euery mā to his neighbourwarde maye more abundantly vse the warkes of mercy. Some vse here to grete the virgin mo
                  •
               her / I denye nat euery where moche honour ought to be gyuen her / but verily to our purpose nowe me semeth more expedi
                  •
               nt / if ye folowe me thus goynge before you:
            Iesus Christe the almyghtye worde of the euerlastynge father / that ꝓmysest to be pres
                  •
               nt / where so euer two or thre were assembled in thy name / thou seest howe many in thy name be here gethered. Uouchesafe therfore accordyng to the ꝓmise / to be amonge this companye: that theyr hartes lyghted through grace of the holy goste / may vnderstande more fully the greatnesse of thy mercy:

wherby we al to gether may with a lustier mynde both yelde to the thākes for thy mercy / that so ofte hath ben to vs shewed / &amp; that more desyrouslye in all our necessites / we maye calle theron for helpe: and lastely that we humble seruauntes maye the mercy of our lorde / that vn vs we haue largely ꝓued / to our power louyngly prosecute on our felowes lyke wyse seruantes.
            If that euery mā (as the rhetoriciens teache) is right diligēt and attentiue to here those thynges / that he vnderstādeth shuld sharpely touche hym: than there oughte none of you to nodde or slepe in this sermō tyme / seyng that the saluaciō of vs allegally dependeth on the mercy of our lorde: Nor there is none so yonge nor so olde / of so lowe or so high byrth / so poore nor so riche / so bōde nor so fre, so counnyng nor so rude, so wicked nor so iuste / but that he hath often tymes bothe proued the mercy of our lorde / and nedeth the mercy of our lorde to all thynges that he rightously goth about. What matter more fauorable may be treated / than that by the mercy of god / euerlastynge helth is prepared for al folkes? Of very right therfore ī this sermon tyme / as many as be here present / ye shulde nat onely take hede, but also be lusty and gladde to here hit: for who so euer doth loue and fauer hym selfe / woll loue and fauer this sermon.
            ¶Amonge the manyfolde yuels / whiche drawe mankynde to euerlastyng dānacion / there be two chiefe and pryncipall myscheues: of whiche they oughte specially to be ware / that loue vertue and

goodnes / and desyre to come to the feloweshyp of euerlastȳg felicite. They be these, To moche trust on ones owne selfe and Dispeire. The one cometh of a presumptuous mynde agaynst god / that the loue of ones selfe hath blynded: the other is engē
               dred one way by pondrynge the great offences / an other way by consydrynge the ryghtous iugemēt of god without r
                  •
               membrance of his mercy. Both these are so pestilent and cursed / that many doubt whiche of them is more to be aborred. For what is greatter madnes or more lamentable than mā that is erth &amp; ashes / whiche what so he is or may do / is for hit all bounde to the goodnes of god: to rebelle agaynst hym / of whom he was created / of whom he was redemed / and of whom by so many meanes he is called to the company of euerlastynge lyfe? Is it nat a point of great vnkyndnes to set nought by hym / of whom thou haste r
                  •
               ceyued so many benefites? Is it nat a poynt of great madnes to wyll to rebelle agaynst hym that may distroye y• with a becke? Is it nat a great poynt of wickednes nat to knowlege thy maker / nat to honour thy father / nat to loue thy sauiour? Unhappy Lucifer was bold to do this fyrst / whiche ascriuyng to hym selfe / yt he frely resceiued of lamighty god / sayd in his harte: I wyl get vp aboue in heuē / I wyll exalte my seate aboue ye sterres of god / I wyll syt vpon the hyll of testimony in the sydes of the Northe wynde / I wyll clyme vp aboue the height of the cloudes / I wyll be lyke to almighty god. But wolde to god yt his vnhappy fall myght

at the leest fray mortal creatures from folowynge of his vngracious example / if the wycked dede it selfe can nat feare them. Truely if god spared nat proude presumptuous āgels / but cast them heedlyng downe in to hell / and ordeyned them straytly boūde in cheynes to be kept tyll the daye of dome / what deserueth mā a sely worme / whiche as now were crept out of the erth / must shortly returne to erthe agayne / is proude presumptuous &amp; testy agaynst god? The more lowe and vyle the cōdicion of mā is / ye more abominable is his presumpcion / desiryng to be egal with god. The ancient poetes feyned / There rose a stryfe on a tyme amonge the goddis / that constrained Iupiter hym selfe to forsake heuen and f
                  •
               ee in to Egypt / and there in an other shap to hyde hym: but a farre more myscheuous dede / was yt the gyantes went about / which confederated to gether agaynst Iupiter / dyd caste hyls vpon hyls / yt they myght so cōquere heuen &amp; expelle Iupiter thence. Ye may wel laughe / these tales that ye here be nat gospel: but yet ye
               
                  •
                erudite olde tyme wolde signifie some what vnder the coueryng of these fables / yt lōgeth to the expre
                  •
               syng of mortall folks maners. Salmoneus was heedlyng throwen downe in to helle / bicause he coūtrefetted thoūder and lyghtnyng of Iupiter. Admit it be but a fable: but howe many sely mortal men haue ther ben / yt in dede &amp; seriously wold haue heuenly honours done to them? Dyd nat god turne Nabugodonosor / that wold haue made hym selfe a god / in to a brute beast / that frō a beast he shulde

retourne to a humayne shappe. Great Alexander wolde be take for Iupiters sōne / and suffred hym selfe to be worshypped at his table. Domitius Cesar in all his letters patentes &amp; pistils / and in his cōmunication wolde be called both god and lorde. Adrian ordeined yt Antinous shuld be worshipped as a god. Why reherse I all this / whan it was a solemne thyng amonge the Romayns / after their Emperours were deꝑted this lyfe / to make them goddis. Some of them a lyue had godly honors / whiche offred to accept is wicked madnes / &amp; to vsurpe is desperate blyndnes. If auctorite of stories be of no great weyght, let vs here what ye apostel Paule to ye Thessalonicēs wrote of Nero / truly some interpretate thus: And ye creature of synne / sayth he / were vncouered / ye childe of ꝑdiciō / whiche is agaȳst &amp; is enhāsed aboue al yt is called god &amp; that is worshipped / so that he sitteth in the tēple of god / shewȳge him selfe as though he were god. But ꝑauenture it shal seme no maruayle if some yt worshypped for goddes / oxen / apes / dogges / and thynges more vile / dōme stones / &amp; wodde / wolde haue them selfe taken for goddes / as farre more excellent than these thinges to whiche the people dydde godly honors. In the actis of the apostles / Herode knowyng ther was but one god / of whose honour no mā coude be partener / suffred ye people to crye to hym in his sermō: This is the voyce of god &amp; nat of a man: Shortly after he was strykē by the angel of god that reuenged that iniury / he the myserable god dyed of the lowsye yuell: than

whiche no disease is more foule stynkyng &amp; peynfull. I wolde to god there were none amōge christie
                  •
               s / that folowed the wickednes of Lucifer / I may nat say passe it. What? Loke ye that I shuld open somwhat of secrete cōfessions? What nede it, whan in some countres in the market place in the churches / at dyner / souper / in playenge and sportyng we here al about they forswere them selfe by the most honorable name of god / this yt I say is a lyght thynge: we here the name of god denyed / ye holy name of Christe with many vile wordes blamed: the fore fynger byttē god thretned / ye thōme put betwene the formest and myddell fynger, that is done agaynst god foūtayne of all glory / that is wont to be done agaynst an infamous ꝑson for riproche and shame. Be there none amonge Christiens / if they may be called Christiēs / whiche for reches yt they must shortly forgo / or foule bodily plesure / or for transitory honours / forsake their owne
                  •
               prince / and make a wicked cōposicion with the
                  •
               r foo Satanas? the fourme of the othe takē, atones they forswere what so euer cōfederaciō was made with Christe / and offre to helle part of theyr body as the fyrste frute / to ye prince wherof they vowed holly theyr soule? These thynges spyed out we se punyshed dayly by open execution. What thynge lyke dyd Lucifer? for hym the son of god dyed nat, and yet he was nat so hardy to blaspheme god: he alonly desyred egal honour. That vnhappy cuntre / wherin somtyme were .v. mighty cites / nowe is a pestylent and abominable lake / for the swete

waters of Iordane bearyng yll fauored claye / the horrible example wherof shall remaine euer in remēbrance to them that come after / had the inhabitāces vtterly gyuen to ryot and lechery / but yet we rede nat that any of them was so wicked / that he wolde blaspheme god / curse and threten hym: and yet they were all distroyed by rayne myngled with brimstone. O thyng horrible / there bē foūde amōge Christē people / that dare do / that Lucifer durst nat / that Gomorra durst nat: whiche also to so many abominable dedes ioyne blasphemynge. I se you most dere bretherne trēble at rehersynge of these thynges / and no meruayle: I my selfe also rehersyng them quyuer &amp; shake bothe body and soule. Neuerthelesse we purpose nat onely in this sermō to declare howe great a synne dispeire of forgyuenes is / but also to shewe howe excedȳg great ye mercy of god is / whiche to preyse we haue this day entreprised: the whiche also spareth suche folkes / and gyueth them space to repent &amp; amende. And ꝑauenture we stande in our owne conceyt / by cause amonge vs the examples of crimes / yt I rehersed nowe / be seldome seen: but what matter maketh it / if the tonge soūdeth no blasphemynge whan of many ye holle lyfe speketh no other thyng but blasphemyng agaynst god? The glouttōs for god worshyp theyr bealy, who cōtinually by right &amp; wrōge gape to hepe riches to gether / whiche by murther, treasō, poisonyng, &amp; enchāting stalke vp to honors / whiche by tyrāny opresse poore people / whiche to haue al thing to their mȳde kēdel al the

worlde to warre: nor perseueryng in these great iuels haue no shame nor repētance / but wt a shameles coūtinance lyke a cōmon womā / reioyse yea in thynges most mischieffull / skornynge &amp; mockyng the good lyuers: do nat y• caytiues by those dedes saye: There is no god / goddis behestis ben false / ye thretnynges of god be vayne / the worde of god is a lye / yeldynge the ioyes of heuen to them that mourne here / that thyrst and hūger Iustice / that be meke / that suffre ꝑsecution / that for iustice ben with vyle wordes rebuked? What can be more abominable than this blasphemyng? And yet if any thynge can be worse than that / whiche is most worse / dispeyre is worse than the holle stynkynge multitude of other synnes. The wicked mā seyng me might do what thyng he wold vnpunished / he was proude of his prosperite &amp; sayd in his harte: There is no god, and there is no knowlege aboue, god careth nat for mortal folkes busynes. And as he is lesse iniurious agaynst a mā / yt beleueth nat he is / thā he that beleueth hym to be cruel or false: So lyke wyse they bene lesse wycked that vtterly say there is no god / than they that beleue he is vnmercifull / takyng away that vertue frō hym / without whiche kynges be nat kynges but tyrātes. But who so euer casteth hope of forgyuenes aside &amp; rolleth hym selfe downe in to the hurlepyt of dispeyre / he doth nat onely beleue yt god is nat almyghty / supposyng some syn so horrible yt he can nat forgyue: but also maketh hym a lyer. He promyseth by the prophet / that he wyll incontinent clene

forgette all maner synnes / assone as the synner bewaylethe th
                  •
               m. Contrary wyse / they that folowe Cain say: My synne is greatter than that I may deserue forgyuenesse. What sayste / thou wycked wretche? If god ouer come with the greatnesse of thy synne maye nat forgyue the / thou pluckest frō hym his power almyghtye: if he wyll nat do that he may / he is a lyer and false / yt wyll nat ꝑfourme that he so many tymes promysed by ye prophetes mouthes. Hit is infinite / what so euer is in god. But .iij. speciall thynges be in hym / most high power / most high wysedome / &amp; most high goodnes. And al be it yt power is wont to be ascribed to ye father as his ꝓpre / wysedome to the sonne, goodnes to ye holy gost: yet there is none of these thynges / but it is egally cōmon to all thre ꝑsons. His highe power he shewed / whan he created these marueylous warkes of the worlde only with a becke / of y• whiche there is no part / but it is ful of miracle / ye the very pysmers and spyders crye out / shewynge the great power of theyr maker. Agayne whā he deuyded the wawes of ye red see: Whan he restrayned the streame of Iordane / &amp; made the ryuer passable for a fote man: Whan whyle Iosue foughte / he made the sonne and moone stynte theyr course: Whā with touchyng he healed lepers: &amp; wt a word reysed deed men to lyfe / he shewed hym selfe lorde of nature. And whan he with egall wysedome cō
               serueth and gouerneth those thynges / whiche he by his power yt can nat be declared hath made / he sheweth hym selfe to be no lesse wise thā almighty.

Al be it that his goodnes euery where shineth / as that same creatiō of angels and this worlde was a poynt of high goodnes / whā he to highe felicite / that he hath of him selfe / lacketh nothȳg yt might be added / yet he made mākynde proprely to thentent / that there in specially he myghte expresse the greatnes of his goodnes and mercy / for in that be halfe god wolde nat alonly be more louynge to vs / but also more marueylous. They marueyle some tyme at a kynges power and myght / that hate or haue enuy at hym. But gentylnes and lyberalite is loued / yea of them that haue no nede / that is to say / throughe consyderation of humayne chance: wher by it may hap any what euer he be / to haue nede. But there is no mā / nor hath ben / nor shalbe but yt he nedeth the mercy of god. Whan / as wytnesseth the olde testament / neyther the sterres be clere in ye syght of god / and in his angels he foūde wickednes. And Paule cryethe to the Romayns: There is no distinction / all haue synned / and nede the glorie of god / that euery mouthe may be stopped / and all the worlde be made subiecte to god. Nowe let is here howe well with hym agreeth ye mystical synger / whiche with a lusty spirite exhorteth all good folkes / yt they with a spirituall harpe with a sautry of .x. strynges / with a newe songe / &amp; with great shouttynge / shulde celebrate the glorye of god / sayenge: Our lorde loueth mercy and iugement / all the erthe is full of our lordes mercy. Ones only is made mencion of iugemēt / but mercy is twyse rehersed with this cōmendacion / that

therof ye erthe is full. I myght boldly adde this / stayeng me by the auctorite of Iob and ye apostle: That nat only y• erthe is full of our lordes mercy / but also heuen and helle. What syngeth the xxxv. psalme: O lorde thy mercy is in heuen / and thy trouth recheth to the cloudes. They in helle ꝑceiued the mercy of our lorde / whan he brake the gates of darknes &amp; broughte out the prisoners in to the heuenly kyngdome. If one wold consydre the warkes of god / whiche after the misticall discussyng of Moyses / he made ꝑfet in ye fyrst .vi. days / he shulde greatly maruayle at his power and ineffable wysedome / yea and crye out in the voyce of all the churche: Pleni sunt celi et terra. &amp;c. The heuens and erth be ful of thy glory. Nor he ne coude absteine hym selfe / but brast out in the hȳne of the thre children: Benedicite omnia opera dn̄i. &amp;c. Blesse ye al the warkes of our lorde / preyse and leape vp for ioy in hym euermore. What so euer is created in ye heuens / what so euer aboue the heuēs / what so euer in erthe / what so euer vnder the erth / what so euer in the water / what so euer ī the ayre / sheweth opēly with voyce continuall the glory of our lorde. But what sayth the psalme. Cxliiii? Our lorde is piteous and mercifull / pacient &amp; moche mercifull. Our lorde is swete to all / and his mercifull pitees passen all his warkes. Ergo some thinge there is more marueylous / than to haue made the heuēs / with so many bryghte sterres / to haue created the erthe with so many kyndes of beastis / of trees / &amp; variablenes of all thynges / to haue created so many

cōpanyes of angelycall myndes. Who durst be so bolde to affyrme hit / excepte the prophet shewed playnely / that the mercyes of our lorde passe the glory of all his other warkes? And yet he shal nat dout it to be true / who so euer with a religious curiosite will cōsider howe moche more maruelously he redemed than created man. Is it nat more wō
               derfull god to be made man / than the angels to be created of god? Is it nat more marueile / that god wrapped in a babis clothes / shuld wayle / and cry / in the cratche or racke / thā to reigne in ye heuēs / yt he made? Here ye āgels / as thyng of greattest wō
               der synge glory to god in the mooste high heuenly māsions. They se the lowlyest humilite / &amp; knowe the most excellent highnes. All the coūsayle of redemynge mankynde / Christis lyfe / Christis teachynge / Christis miracles / afflictiō, crucifieng, resurrection / aperyng / ascention / the sendyng of the holy goste / by a fewe sely poore idiote mē ennewed the worlde: this coūsayle I say / is it nat on euery syde full of miracles / yea that the very āgels cun nat serche out? Wycked spirites se and vnderstāde the reason of the worldis creacion / but the counsayle of the worldes restoryng was hyd frō them: and in this poynt crafte disceyued crafte / the craft of mercy begyled the crafte of malice. The creatiō of ye worlde was the warke of puissance / ye worlde so restored was ye warke of mercy. Thendis of the crosse saythe Abacuc / in his handes / there is his strength hyd. What is more vyle than the crosse? What is weaker thā the crucified? Yet vnder that

weakenes / excedyng power of diuyne mercy laye hyd / that brake / ouer came / and clene distroyed all the tyrāny of the dyuell. The same prophet whan he had eares erudite / whan he had eies very clere by faythe / he herde the holle frame of ye worlde on euery parte shewe the great myght of god / and he was afrayde: he considered his warkes / and was amased. And yet as though in all these thyngis ye great might of god was nat playn inough / he added / that shulde ouercome all these warkes: In ye myddes of two beastis thou shalt be knowen. In the meare of the olde &amp; newe testamēt / he become man / opened playnely that most bashefull miracle of his mercy. Undouted hit is yt the prophet soone after addeth: Whan thou woldest be angry / thou shalte remēbre thy mercy. Of them that do thynges wonderfull / we be wont to say: In those he ouercame al / ī this he ouercame hym selfe. Of god some thyng lyke may well be sayd: God is incomparable in all his dedes / &amp; can nat be folowed / In mercy he excedeth hym selfe. Holy scripture extolleth no vertue in god so moche as mercy / whiche some tyme calleth it great / some tyme ouermoche, and somtyme augmenteth the plentifull abūdāce therof by nombre of multitude. Kyng Dauid the prophet in the same place / cōplecteth ye largenesse and multitude of diuyne mercy: Miserere mei de
                  ••
                secūdū. &amp;c. O god haue mercy on me after thy great mercy / and after ye multitude of thy mercyes do away my wickednes. Where is great misery / there is nede of great mercy. If ye cōsidre how horrible

the synne of Dauid was / ye knowe the largenesse of mercy: If ye caste howe many maner wyse he offended in one trespas / ye maye se the multitude of his mercies. An excedyng great offēce is neuer commytted alone / a faute draweth a faute / as one lynke doth an other in a cheyne. Fyrst he ioyned together two most deedly synnes / māslaughter and aduoutry: eche of them was more greuous in the kynge: whose office is to punyshe other that so offende. For the more princis do amys vnpunysshed amonge men / the more they offende god. He bare a 
                  •
               worde to punysshe manslaughter / and he hym selfe cōmytted manslaughter. By hym women takē in aduoutri were deliuered to be stoned to deth / and he hym selfe compelled to do aduoutry. He also peculierly augmented the same aduoutry / that whan he had flockes of wyues and concubyns at home / yet nat for nede but for wātōnes he coueted an other mās wyfe / yt he wolde seme delite rather ī rauysshyng thā in simple fornication. For he offē
               dethe nat so moche / that nede cōstrayneth to steale somewhat from the riche mā / as he that hath his house plentifully stouffed / &amp; taketh his gowne frō hym / that hath no mo to his backe. This cruel offēce Nathan ye ꝓphet dyd obiect agaynst hym vnder ye parabol of the ryche thefe and poore mā robbed. Nowe no kynde of māslaughter is more cruell / than that yt is nat by chance or sodayne mouȳg of ye mynde / but by a dryft before driuen / wayting cōuenient tyme / is cōmitted. Urias had nothyng deserued / the kynge knewe hym ryght trusty / and

he abused the same trustynes of the man to his distructiō. He wolde in no wise ētre within his owne house to lye with his wyfe / bycause ye arke of god was lyenge in the tentes / and Ioab capytayne of the warre with the people / slept vpon the groūde / and al that great worthines of the man coude nat turne the kynges mynde from the iuell dede. The morowe after he had hym to supper / &amp; made hym drōke / sekȳg occasion to distroy him / if he through dronkēnes shuld hap to speke ought vndiscretely. &amp; yet Urias beȳg drōke wold nat come ī his house to take his pleasure with his wyfe. An other gyle was added / wherby the strōge &amp; trusty warriour muste perisshe. A lettre of murther to hym suspectyng no suche thyng was delyuered: for ye kynge knewe his faythfulnes so perfecte / that he had no dout he wolde open and rede it. In the offence of manslaughter he made Ioab the capitayne partner / lyke as he had Bersabee of aduoutrye. And Urias perished nat alone / but to couer ye gyle / many were broughte in to the same daunger: a great nombre of people was set in the open shot of theyr ennemyes / to thende one innocēt myght be kylde / to gyue place to the kynges foule bodily pleasure. Therfore in one sinne how many are the offences? If hit were one only synne / and excedynge great / hit nedeth great mercy. Nowe Dauid seynge his 
                  •
               yn so many folde &amp; dyuers / he calleth on the multitude of mercies. But howe largely the mercy of god is opened / ye .xxxv. psalme declareth / sayenge: O good lorde thou shalt saue men and beastis / like

As thou haste multiplyed thy mercy. God saueth nat only man / but also he vouchesafeth for mānes beho
                  •
               e to saue bestis. Againe ī an other place how reioyseth the prophettes spirite / whan he saythe: I wyll syng the mercies of god perpetually. And therfore in the heuens ye mercy of god is worshipt &amp; honoured / like as sayth an other psalme: Knowlege your selfe to god bycause he is good / bycause his mercy is in al worldes. The preising of ye mercy of god semed to haue ende / after the ende of all wretchednes came / except the same felicite yt good folkes haue in heuen / were the gyft of mercy / and the punishement of the wicked tempered with the great mercy of god. But what shall we say / whan all the lyfe with a thousande syns / and all the stynkyng see of vices is corrupted? Truly we must cry with Asaph: O lorde remēbre nat our olde iniquitees / but let thy mercy preuent vs quickely / for we be made ouer poore. Againe in an other place: Many be thy mercyes lorde / after thy pleasant speche quicken me. Agayne in an other place Dauid / as he cōplayned wt god / crieth out: Where be thy olde mercyes good lorde? Agayne in the psalme .Cvj. Let the mercies of our lorde be cōfessed / &amp; his maruayles of the sons of men: Whiche verse as enterlyned is oft repeted ī ye same psalme. In ye psalme also that goeth nexte before: And he gaue vs vnto his mercies in the syght of all that toke them. He sayd mercies / bicause he had rehersed many wycked dedes / with whiche he prouoked the anger of god. And Dauid on all partis oppressed with yls / 

sayth: It is better that I fall in the hādes of our lorde: for manifold are his merices / than in to the handes of men. As in one offence often times are many sinnes, so lyke wise in one m
                  •
               rcy many mercies are conteyned. Ones he redemed mankynd / but here in howe manifolde are the mercies? Whiche Esaias beholdynge with the eie of fayth / speketh thus in the persone of god / promysynge our sauiour Iesus: And I wyll make with you a couenant euerlastyng / the faythfull mercies of Dauid. In a lyke figure god being appeased speketh in the prophet Hieromie: And I wyll gyue you mercies / and shall haue pite vpon you. For many greuous synnes, many mercyes are promysed. Lyke wyse after many afflictions / god hauynge pyte of his people speketh thus in the prophet zacarie: I wyll retourne to Hierusalem in mercies / and my house shall be buylded. But why reherse we those thynges / out of bokes of the olde testamēt / in whiche so ofte tymes the name of mercies is encoūtred? And yet some heretykes beleue that ye same lawe procedeth of a 
                  •
               uste and nat of a good god / whan it souneth welnere nothyng elles than the mercies of our lorde. Howe moche lesse is it to be maruailed / if Paule thapostle in the .ii. pistle to the Thessal. accordyng to the prophettis wordes writeth in this wyse: Blessed be god and father of our lorde Iesu Christe / father of mercyes / &amp; lorde of al cōsolaciō / whiche cōforteth vs in al our tribulacion. The apostle somwhat addeth to mercy, for it is a poynt of mercy to ꝑdone offence done: here

whiche is moche more / god of a reuēger is made a cōforter. These thynges we haue repeted of the holy scripture / to thentent that we by that fygure of spekyng myght vnderstande the signified excedyng and vnspekeable mercy of god towarde euery body / and in all yls. The same is shewed by an other figure / whiche is eyther Anadiplosis, that in latin one may calle Cōduplicatio, orels nerest to Anadiplosis. For as the Hebrewes call that good good / that they reken to be excedyng good / and yll yll yt is excedyng yll: so likewise in holy scripture god is ofte called pitefull and mercifull / for the excedyng greatnes of his mercy. So ye rede in the psalme Cxliiij. Our lorde is pitefull and merciful / and as though that also were a small thynge / he addeth: Pacient and moche merciful. Agayne in an other psalme: Our pitefull &amp; mercifull lorde hath made remēbrāce of his marueiles. Lykewyse in Iohel, Rente your hartes and nat your clothes / for our lorde god is pitefull and mercifull, and sorowynge for malices. And in the prophet Ieremie: Therfore my bowelles haue ben troubled vpon hym / I piteynge shall haue mercy on them / saythe our lord. What is piteyng to haue mercy / but to haue mercy out of mea
                  •
               ure? To this poynt ꝑteyneth / that sythe it is infinite / what so euer is in god: yet it that amōge men sowneth vnto vice / holy writte semeth to ascribe vnto hym / certeyne ouer moche and vnmoderate mercy. I wolde your goodnesse shulde so take this sayeng / as ꝑswaded nothynge to be in god that sowueth to any vice / shuld vnderstande / 

that vnder y• figure the holy scripture submyt
                  •
               yng it selfe to mānes ꝑceyuyng / signyfyeth a marueilous &amp; an īcredible excesse of diuine mercy. Whiche thynge yt I may more plainly speake &amp; ye more ꝑfectly ꝑceyue / cōsydre this in your mynde. ¶If a kyng shulde stablyshe rigorous lawes on a mankyller / &amp; after he had cōmytt
                  •
               d māslaughter ones wolde ꝑdone hym / may hap it shuld be ascriued to his cl
                  •
               mency. But &amp; he ꝑdoned hym yt had done yt mischeuous dede .x. tymes or more / wolde nat euery body crie out: The kinges clemēcy is o
                  •
               uer moche, y• ouerthroweth ye strength of ye lawes, &amp; ꝓuoketh ye lewde ꝑsones to do wickedly for lacke of punishemēt? Also a father that ones or twise for gyueth his son for spendyng his money lewdly away, may hap shalbe called ea
                  •
               y and mylde. If ye same father often tymes gyue his sōne money / so lewdly wastyng hit / wyll nat euery body saye: He is to easy / and by his hyndnes marreth his sōne? And moche more southly hit myght be sayd / if he dyd so to his seruant. More ouer / if an husbande shuld take in worth / if his wyfe were takē ones in auoutry, vndouted euery body wolde marueyle to fynde so meke an husbande. But &amp; ye womā soone after breke her wedlocke, &amp; is takē ī auoutry nowe with one nowe with an other / if he thā toke her to hym agayne / wolde nat all the people say he were a starke fole, orels his wiues baude? But god yt is our kynge / our father / our lorde, our spouse, exc
                  •
               pteth no kynde of syn, he prescribet
                  •
                no nōbre of synnyng, as ofte as we amēde he releaseth our peine:

whiche his euerlastynge lawe thretneth / he receyueth vs in to his household / he leadeth vs ī to the chābre of his charite / &amp; he nat onely receyueth vs but also forgyueth all our offēces. The shepe that was lost he carieth home on his shulders to ye cote agayne: he stereth the congregation of holy folke to reioyce to gether / he mereth the riottous childe returnyng home frō far cuntrey / he offereth hym a fayre gowne and a rynge / he cōmandeth to kylle a goodly calfe. What thyng els signifieth all this / but vnmoderate / &amp; 
                  •
               if I may so saye) ouermoche mercy of god. But nowe it semeth lesse marueile / if a m
                  •
               n forgyue a man offēdyng / that also other while doth offēce hym selfe likewise / or may offēd, if a kynge ꝑdone hym / yt somtyme dyd hym good profitable seruice: or if the father forgyue his son / whose cōuersaciō he feleth doth ease his olde age: if a mayster forgyue is seruant / by whose labour he partly lyueth: if the husbāde forgyue his wyfe taken in auoutrie / with whom other while he leadeth his life pleasantly. Amōge men he that some time ꝑdoneth dredeth hym that he forgiueth / and other while can nat auēge hym selfe / if he wolde. But god that hath nede of no mā / that may with a becke distroy vs if he wold / so often tymes of vs despised / forsakē / &amp; denied: suffreth / calleth / receyueth / and enbraseth vs. As no loue is more feruēt nor strayter conioynynge / than betwene man and wyfe: so lyke wyse no anger is harder to appease than it yt ryseth by breakyng of wedlocke. And yet here what our mylde lorde saythe by the prophet

Esaias to his spouse an auou
                  •
               rice / defyled with so many auoutries: It is cōmonly sayd / if a mā forsake his wyfe / and she departed frō hym weddeth an other man / shall he retourne to her any more? Shall nat ye womā be poluted and defiled? Truly thou cōmittest fornication with many louers / and y
                  •
               t returne to me (saith our lorde) &amp; I wyl receiue the. A maried mā wyl nat take his wyfe agayne / whom parauenture he forsoke for a small faute or cause / if she after ye deuorce be wedded to an other mā. For wedlockis loue can nat suff
                  •
               e ye cōpany of an other man. But yet god doth nat disdayne his spouse / for whom he suffred dethe / whiche for him selfe he purified with his bloud / y• so ofte wylfully runneth away / and abandoneth her selfe to so many vncleane wyghtis / if she wyll returne agayne. And it is no marueile / if he haue ouermoche mercy / yt hath ouermoche charite towarde vs. Paule bassheth nat to wryte thus to the Ephesiens: We were by nature the children of anger / lyke as the other were / but god that is riche in mercy / for his ouermoche charite / that he loued vs with / &amp; whā we were deed ī syns, he quickened vs all to gether in Christe. Iohan in his gospell expresseth more playnly ye ouermoche charite of ye father towarde vs. God / sayth he / loued so the worlde / yt he wolde gyue his onely begotten son, that who so euer beleueth in hym shal nat perishe / but haue euerlastȳg lyfe / with whom Paule agreeth tunably / writȳg to y• Romayns: whiche also spared nat his owne son / but delyuered hym for vs all: howe / gaue he

nat vs all thynges with hym? If this grea
                  •
                
               
                  •
               harite / this so great mercy / shulde be conferred to all humayn charite &amp; mercy / &amp; to our merites / wolde hit nat well seme vnmoderate? But 
                  •
               rewly it shall appere moche more veritable / if we cōsyder what he is / that so loueth vs / &amp; so sheweth his mercy on vs / &amp; what we be / that god vouchesafeth so great honour. Let eche loke on him selfe / after the name in baptisme gyuen / after Satanas forsaken with his pompis / howe oft he forsaketh the sacrament and yeldeth hym to thennemy of his spouse, howe oft after absoluciō of his synnis receiued of ye prest he slydeth into more greuous offences / ye how oft ye same day he falleth in to them / that he aborred? Lette no body most dere bretherne dissemble with hym selfe / who so euer stealeth or cōmitteth auoutry / who so euer ēuieth or sklandreth his brother / who so euer coueteth wordly honors / leaueth his spouse Christe / turneth away from his father, forsaketh his king, and fleeth away far frō his lorde. But ꝑauenture we shall haue a littell after a more conuenient place to speke of these thynges. ¶ Nowe to thende ye may more fully vnderstand / howe largely the exceding mercy of god spredeth, ye must vnderstāde / yt in holy writte the cleapyng of mercy signifieth somtyme liberalyte / somtyme grace preuētyng / somtyme auāsynge / other while cōfortyng / agayne other where healyng, but very oftē forgyuyng / orels also punyshynge. For surely after my mynde / that ye our lorde spek
                  •
               th in Luke. Be mercifull like as your father is mercifull / perteyneth

specially to liberalite. For ꝑfecte liberalite is / if one do good to his ēnemes. Mattheus saith hit more playnly in a lyke sayeng of our lorde: Be ye (sayth he) ꝑfect / lyke as your father celestiall is perfect / that maketh his son to shyne on good and yll / and sendeth rayne to iuste and vniuste. But bicause we haue nothyng / that we ne receyued frely of god / what euer we maye or be / what so euer we possesse / it is the mercy of god. Yea that he created angels / and this worlde / is the mercy of god. If he had created hit for hym selfe / the power or wisedome myghte be preysed. Nowe / seynge he hath wroughte all these thynges for vs / knowe nat we the excedyng great mercy of god? For whom mouen ye celestiall bodies aboue? For whom shyneth the sonne by daye / The moone and the sterres by nyght / but for mā? For whose profit were all these thynges wrought / whā they were nothyng? For whom make the hangyng cloudes shadowe / and moyst the feldes? For whom bloweth the wynde? For whom runne the ryuers / the welles sprynge / the see ebbe and flowe / the pondis stāde stylle? For whom engendreth the plētifull erthe so many beastis / and bryngeth forthe so moche ryches / but for man? For he subdued euery thynge vnto man / he wold man shulde onely be subiect to hym: lyke as wytnesseth Paule writyng to the Corinthies. All thynges be yours / but ye be of Christe / &amp; Christe is of god. And it that Moises sheweth in Genesis the .viij. psalme repeteth / marueylyng at ye goodnes of god / that of his mercy hath gyuen to man

so many ben
                  •
               fites. What is man saythe he / that thou remembrest hym / or the sonne of man / that thou visetest hym? Thou haste made hym lyttell l
                  •
               sse thā angels / thou hast crowned hym with glory and honour / and hast set hym aboue ye warkes of thy handes. Thou haste subdued all vnder his feet / shepe and oxen euerichone / yea and more beastes of the felde / byrdes of the ayre / and fyshes of the see. I wyll say yet that is higher: We be boūd to the mercy of god for the heuēly angels. Beleue nat my worde / without Paule teache it playnly / writyng to the Hebrewes / and speking of angels. Be nat saythe he / all spirites seruantes in seruice sent for theyr sake / that receyue the inheritance of saluacion? And bothe in ye olde and newe testamēt we oftē rede yt by ministracion of angels ye hūgry were refreshed / prisoners d
                  •
               liuered / coūtres ouerrōne / ye good folke cōforted with ioyfull tydynges. More ouer our lorde hym selfe in the gospel sayth: Theyr angels beholde alway the face of ye father, that is in heuen. What is more marueilous than this worthynes / angels gyuen to sely men as gouernours to children? Therfore what so euer thou hast man / truely thou hast all thinges while thou remaynest in Christe / thou shuldest reken to haue it al of his mercy. Otherwise Paule wyll stampe &amp; crie out vpon the: What hast mā that thou hast nat receyued? And if thou haste receyued it / why magnifiest thy selfe / as yu dyddest nat receyue hit? Farther / what yuell so euer thou seest in other / aknowlege the mercy of god preuētyng y•: Wherof

Dauid nat in one place sayth: And his mercy shal preuēt me. Thou art no bastarde borne / nor lame / nor blynde / thou art nat poore / nor dulwitted / like as many be borne / gyue thākes to ye mercy of god preuētynge the. What so euer hurtes happē to an other mā myght haue chanced to the / nere that ye mercy of god had defended the. Agayne / thou art none aduoutrer / no false forswere
                  •
                / no mankyller / no churche robber / lyke as (alas) ouer many be, aknowlege the mercy of god, for thou shuldest haue ben / and the mercy of god had nat kepte the.
            A man on a tyme yt coude good skele in phisnomy iuged Socrates to his disciples / to be a man desirous of ryot / &amp; ouermoche gyuen to lechery / they knowyng theyr maisters incredible tēperāce / ꝑtly laughed him to scorne, and partly disdained hym. Socrates blamed them &amp; praysed hym / sayenge. He hath diuined truly / all this had I ben / if phylosophie had nat taught me tēperāce. But moche more southly y• right holy man Francis as
                  •
               riueth vnto diuine mercy / that Socrates yeldeth to philosophie. For on a tyme whā his felowe / of him cō
               manded so to do / had reuiled hym with what so euer wordes a mischeuous caytiue is wont to be rebuked / callynge hym churche robber / mankyller / backebiter / poller / &amp; poysoner, he toke it most paciently / and bewayled him selfe yt he was suche one.
            An other tyme whan his felowe asked him why he 
                  •
               ōpelled hym to make so many lies vpon an inno
                  •
               ēt for none of al these thȳges were ī him he answered: Thou dost nat lye, for al these had I ben / 

yea &amp; moche more / nere yt ye mercy of god kept his seruant frō those synnes. And ye mercy of god doth nat only preuent &amp; prouoke vs to goodnes / but also helpeth vs entprisynge / accōpanieth vs goyng forth, and in conclusion gyueth vs puissance, yt we may ꝑfourme that mannes strengthes coude nat do. Me semeth the apostle Paule signifieth suche a maner of mercy in many places / but specially in gretynges / besechyng grace and peace. In pistils to Timotheus also he addeth mercy. And certes without preiudice of a better sentence / if any haue it to shewe / I thynke grace ꝑteyneth to callynge of vs / for we be called by fayth / yt is beleue. This fayth is the free gyfte of god / and therfore they to whom it happeth, are for it bonde to the diuine mercy. Mercy ꝑteyneth to dyuers gyftes distributed to eche after the measure of his faythe. Peace longeth to the innocēcy of all the lyfe / with out whiche / frēdship with god can nat he had / nor true cōcorde with our bretherne. Ueryly as oft as we be deliuered frō iuels that we be greued with / we shulde nat repute it to the sterres / to Fortune / nor to our prudēce / but we ought to ascriue it al to ye mercy of god. No man tangled in the bo
                  •
               des o
                  •
                syn can be deliuered / excepte he be holpe by diuine mercy. This teacheth the psalme. Cxxix. For our lorde hath great mercy / and in hym is plentyfull redempcion and he wyll redeme Israel frō all iniquities thero
                  •
               . Farther / that the mercy of god delyuereth vs also frō bodily harmes / Paule declareth writyng to the Philippēses: Epaphroditus

was sicke yea nere deed: but god saythe he / pitied hȳ / &amp; nat only hym / but also me / lest I shuld haue had sorowe vpon sorowe. Nor there is no differēce bitwene mercy helpyneg and cōfortyng / saue that we be holpe / whā ye yuels be takē away yt greued vs / but mercy cōforting is at hande / as oft as in ye myddes of afflictions i
                  •
                tempereth the grefe of aduersite with mynglyng of ioy
                  •
               ull thȳges / causing frute with tēptation / as Paule sayth / wherby we may susteyne hit. And the same yuels ofte tymes are sente of god pit
                  •
               ynge / wherby we may 
                  •
               ither purge our yl dedes cōmytted / orels withdrawe vs that we commytte no mo / or to mynistre vs matter to exercise vertue. In suche wyse Abrahā was tēpted / so Iob was exercised in dyuers troubles / so who so euer lyued well in Iesu Christe / werein this worlde proued by dyuers a
                  •
               flictiōs / as golde is by the fyer. Where be they that murmure agaynst god, as oft as to them happeth bodily sickenes / or deth of theyr children or wyfe / or as ofte as they haue losse of househol
                  •
               e stouffe / or as ofte as theyr felde frutes fayle / nat vnderstandynge these to be the most certeyne tokens of god piteyng vs? Let vs rather here what Solomō monisheth vs: My sonne / caste nat awaye the teachynge of our lorde / nor leaue hym nat / whan he correcteth the: For hym yt our lorde loueth he correcteth: and deliteth in him as a father in his childe. Paule to the Hebrewes repeteth this sentence / changyng somwhat the wordes. For whom our lorde loueth he chastiseth: he scourgeth forsothe euery childe that

he admytteth. Therfore mooste welbeloued brethern̄ as oft as ye storme of aduersite assaileth you cōtinue in discipline / as Paule coūsaileth / knoweyng yt god offreth hym vnto you as vnto childrē / here the voyce of the father mercifully correctyng his children in ye psalme. lxxxviij. If they violate my iusticis / and kepe nat my cōmandementes / I wyll visete theyr iniquites by the rodde / and their synnes by beatynges. But I wyl nat throwe my mercy frō hym / nor I wyl nat hurt in my trouth. And lyke wyse Paule thretneth the chyldren that he loueth / sayeng: What wolde ye / shal I come to you by the rodde / or in the spirite of hyndnes and mekenes? But the same Paule saythe: What nedeth me to iuge of them yt be without? No voyce is more bytter and sharpe vnto chyldren / than to here theyr father saye: Do what ye wyll / I care nat. For thus sayth he that myndeth to disherite. Surely this fatherly hyndnes is sharper than any chydynge. Therfore as sufferance is cruell / so correction is mercifull. The iuste man saythe: He shal correct me in his mercy / and shal rebuke me / but the oyle of the synner shall nat grece my heed. Paulus Emilius the Romayn capitayn whiche being prosperous in all his dedes, diuined yt some great iuel was cōmynge. And Polycrates ye tyrā of Samiens went alway about to redeme ye enuy of fortune, flateryng with losse of a ring most precious. Howe moche more ought we drede lyuyng wickedly / lest the iuste vengeance of god hange ouer vs / whan the prosperite of temporall goodes

flater vs longe. For whan god in the prophecies wyll expresse his vnpeasable anger / he thretneth to take away his rodde from them / and that by afflictiōs he wyl nat redresse their sinnes. God kepe vs most dere bretherne from suche felicite. But rather, if ye mercy of our father vouchesafe vs ought of welth / we must thāke hym, &amp; be carefull lest we any where shulde abuse his liberalite. And if aduersite greue vs / we shuld no lesse thankyng hym submit vs holly to his arbitremēt. To haue helth of body, thou submittest the to the phisician a mā, thou sufferest ye surgian to bynde / cut / and burne / wylte nat submyt the to thy maker / lorde / father / and sauiour / that thou maist haue thy soule helth euerlastynge? Thou darst nat lymyt to the leche / thus and by this reason heale me: and shal we cō
               dicion with god / howe he shulde ꝓuide for our soules helthe? Paule thapostle suff
                  •
               ed thangel of the deuyl to assayle hym and gyue hym blowes / for so it was expediēt to reteyne the gyftes that he had receyued. Whan I am weake sayth he / than am I stronge. And he glorifieth gladly in his infirmites / that he myghte possesse the vertue of Christe dwellynge in hym. What be we / that refuse this mercy of god / by dyuerse afflictions / as hit were with bytter playsters / procurynge our helthe?
            The cōmon people whā they se one yt is descēded of high linage / hauing abūdāce of riches, helth of body / &amp; heaped in honors / are wont to say: Howe moche is he boūde to god? Thus iuge they / that esteme felicite in those thing is, yt 
               
                  •
               e seen outward.

But he that examyneth the thynge after the iugemēt of god / shall fynde of
                  •
               ē tymes the lowe byrth / poore / sickely / &amp; ye out cast amōge men more boūde to ye mercy of god than these ioly felowes / that the grosse multitude maketh egall to goddis. Heape to gether as moche of vnwelthynes as thou wylt / touchynge ye worlde / yet if yu by these tēporel yuels redeme felicite euerlasting / yu art abūdātly happy. ¶Nowe forgyuyng mercy / whiche also we cleape Clemency / euery mā knoweth / saue he that thynketh hym selfe gyltles frō all syn. But what sayth thapostle Iohn̄? If we say we be without synne / we be lyers / and there is no treuth in vs. And if ye sterres be nat clere in ye syghte of god / and if in his angels he foūde wickednes / if no creature be pure in the syght of god / yea nat a childe of a day olde / whiche of vs may glorifie to haue a chaste harte?
            Many seme rightous amōge men / before god no man is iuste: but al our iusticis are as it were the clothe of a womā defiled with ye menstruous flixe. Paule ꝑceyueth howe the carnall lawe in his mē
               bres stryueth agaynst the lawe of the mynde / and crieth out: I vnhappy creature / who shall deliuer me from the body of this dethe: Iob with a iuste mans title honoured / is nat foūde clene fautles by the talkynge of god. Also he the prophet Dauid dredeth the iugement of god / nere that it were alayed with moche mercy. Thou shuldest nat ētre good lorde sayth he / in iugement with thy seruāt for truely no lyuyng creature shalbe foūde iuste in thy syght. ¶Nowe let eche of vs entre in to the

chambre of his conscience / and consider howe many wayes / howe ofte / howe greuously he hath offended god / yea with what sondry vices al our benefittes are defiled: and so than he shal vnderstād howe moche he is bounde to the excedynge great mercy of god: that so paciently suffereth our feble
                  •
               es / that by so many occasions stereth vs to repentance / that so swetely forgyueth all our offences / whan we leaue our wickednes. To al these I wyl adde, that shal seme to some nat very ꝓuable.
            Whan god distroyeth ye wycked lyuers / yt rōne to the hiest point of malice / and casteth them downe in to helle / yet than he forgetteth nat his mercy.
            He delyuereth ye Hebrewes / diuidynge ye wawes of the see / and drowneth Pharao with his garde. Mercy was on bothe sydes / helpyng towarde his people / punyshyng toward the kyng ful of desperate malice / lest he shulde / heapyng synnes vpon sinnes / purchase hym selfe more greuous peynes in helle. The healyng mercy was / that god by so many plages stered hym to do penāce. And nowe he, assailed with so many yuels / began to repent: but after he repented hym selfe agayne of his helthfull repentance / &amp; sayd: I knowe nat our lorde / nor I wyll nat let ye people go. Nor yet he moued with so great myracle ceassed nat to pursue them: but blynded with anger / boldly entred in to ye see / God of his mercy oppressed his desperate malice / that whan he wolde nat be healed / he shulde more easily perishe. The 
                  •
               ame ought to be demed of the other examples of cruelte / that be rehersed in bokes

of the olde testament / as of them that the fire burned, the groūde swalowed, ye sword distroyed / the serpentes deuoured. For in the gospels the examples of vengeance are fewer / but all of mercy. Hit was an easy correction / that Elymas stryken with sodayne blȳdnes / was taught nat to stryue agaynst ye worde of the gospell. Paule deliuered a fewe to Satanas in affliction of the fleshe / that ye soule myght be saued at ye day of dome: and they corrected with shame, shulde turne to better frute. There is no example more rigorous than of Ananias and Saphiras / that by Peters correctiō fell downe deed sodeynly / and yet it is vncerteyn whether theyr soules by dethe of the body are saued. Finally the punishement that the damned soules of yll lyuers suffre in helle / is lesse thā theyr meritis. And there be some / yt esteme the mercy of god so great / yt they beleue that ye wicked spirites also and dāned soulis / ones after many seasons gone about, shall be receiued to grace. Though this opinion stayeth on a great autor / yet it hath bē reproued by ye ꝑfect fathers of our fayth: whiche onely we reherse for this entent / that we maye declare / what an excedȳg great opiniō mē most highly lerned conceyued of the mercy of god: whiche nyght &amp; day were occupied in holy bokes / whiche synge / extolle / and magnifie welnere nothynge elles but the mercy of god. ¶ Nowe if it be shewed sufficiently / what euer we be or haue touchȳg goodnes
                  •
                that we be defēded frō iuels depēdyng / that we be delyuered frō hurtes oppressyng, that in the myddes

of tribulacions / refreshed with heuenly comfort, we abyde stronge &amp; lusty, that by temporal afflictions we be eyther instructed to repentance / or exercised to ꝑfect vertue / that our syns done be nat to vs imputed / whereinto so oft we slide / cometh al of the mercy of god: that ye may more clerely perceyue the excedyng heyght / breade / and depenes therof / I pray you that with me ye wyl a lytell beholde your selfe inwardly / fyrst in yt party through whiche ye be most lothsome / &amp; after in that wherby ye excelle / lastely ye muste regarde the yls that outwarde hange ouer and cōpasse you about / and agayne to ȳe bounties, of whom the hope is to you shewed. The contemplacion of all these thynges wyll teche vs the largenes of diuine mercy / wher of verily is neyther measure nor nombre.
            ¶If we beholde this small body the pype or litel house of our soule / vneth one may fynde any beast more weaker / lothsom, ye or more wretched. If ye enquere ye begynnyng / the fyrst of our kynde was of claye. Nowe let euery mā cōsider this / howe litell or nothyng is the great pōposenes / what euer is of the humor / of whose cōielaciō the principles of mankynde take begynnyng / whan as yet it is hyd in the womans wombe. Than howe far that humor distāteth from hipocras and deyntie meates / wherwith the childe nat borne is norished. I wyl nat reherse here ye filthines of mākȳdis byrth only that ye haue ofte seen, call to mynde. What is more wretched thā mākyndis byrth? Howe longe &amp; howe perillous be ye panges of women trauaylyng?

What miserable wailynges? At last ye child hit selfe crepyng forth soone from wepyng &amp; waylyng begynneth the life. And where as Nature to all other beastis as soone as they come forthe / gyueth diuers as coueringis or defenses / shels / barkes / thicke skyns / prickes / heares / bristils / quils / fethers, scales, flissis, &amp; also other while defendeth the stūpes &amp; trees from colde &amp; hete with a double barke: only mankinde naked, &amp; on ye bare groūde the day of his byrth she casteth out / forth with to wepe and wayle, who wold nat iuge in this point ye a chekyn crept out of the broken shell more happy thā mākinde? Farther / se howe he is swadled / his mouth totheles, his touge specheles, his eies can nat suffre ye newe lyght / and fareth as it wold entre the darknes of the mothers wōbe agayne / that he lefte, ye moulde quauereth longe / a tokē amōge al beastis of greattest weakenes, brefely all the litel body is weake / in whiche is no membre yt doth his dewty. Most part of all other beastis as soone as they be brought forth, emplie ye gyftes of their nature. Some are swyft, as horses. As soone as ye buterflie cometh out of the skyn it fleeth: It is no sure wrastling with a leons whelpe. As soone as fyshes be spaumed they swymme: Tadpolles rollen them selfe with great swyftnes before they may be called or haue any shap of frogges: onely what other thynge can mankynde do by course of nature but wepe? Howe longe lerneth he to go? Whan he hath lerned to go on .11. feet / howe longe must he lerne to speke? ye he can nat fede / outcept

he be taught. Adde nowe y• many kyndes of sickenessis / that vneth can be rehersed / and specially ye newe / that it is harde to heale them / howe be it amōge the olde many be vncurable. Som take mā
               kinde soone after the byrth / som also in the byrth / as lepre / fallȳg yuel / wherby many dye or they begyn to lyue. And this whyle I speke nothynge of them that be borne with many defautis of nature &amp; mysshapen. Nowe let eche cōsyder this by hym selfe / what dōmages he hath suffred ī youth / how fugitiue youth is / howe carefull mans state / how wretched / olde age: and so forth howe short ye holle lyfe / though one hap to be olde / whiche yet chanceth to very fewe. Who so euer of you is at mānes state / let hym rekē the course of the life past / &amp; coūt fro what sickenessis / frō what great perils he is escaped / &amp; let him thanke ye mercy of god. Uerily I wolde reken amōge bodily yuels as principal / the sedes of all maner vicis faste routed in vs / howe greatly to āger / to bodily pleasure / to riot / to ēuy / to ābicion / to couetousnes / to robbery / frō our mothers wombe we be enclined: where all other beastis lyuen lowably wi
                  •
               h in the desyres of nature
                  •
                What a labour is it to vs all to wrast
                  •
               ll with these leauynges of olde Adā? to howe fewe lucky? The soule is ouer loded with the weyght of yt erthy body: and whether it wyll or wyl nat / is drowned in these thynges that it aloweth nat. Farther more cōsydre / what rout of yuels 
                  •
               nui
                  •
               on vs without / and ye shal fynde yt many mo perishe by chāce thā sickenes. Howe many be distroyed by lyghtnyng / 

erth quakes / groūde openynges / lakes / floddes of ye see and ryuers / infectous aer / venom / wyld beastis / fallyng of huge thinges, yll phisiciōs: but no way greatter distruction than through warres?
            But all these myscheues thretten to distroye but the body. Howe many dāgers hange ouer ye soule? fro ye fleshe a houshold ēnemy / fro the worlde nowe flattryng that it may strangle / nowe ragyng that it may oppresse / fro wicked spirites yt o
                  •
               her whyle transfigure them selfe lyke angels of lyght. Who dredeth nat of these ye multitude / powers / disceit / malyce / and vnsaciable desyre to distroye? Nowe who amōge these yuels wold it nat nere slee / deth certayne to eche / the day vncertayne / the rigorousnes of thextreme dome / the peynes of hell euerlastynge? I se you tremble at thonly remēbrynge of these so great myscheues / and no wronge: but the more ye here of yuels and dāgers / the more ye be boūde to the mercy of god / whiche amōge al these yls nat onely defēdeth those that trust theron / but also turneth all these thynges to vs in occasion of more felicite. What so euer calamite we haue here we may wyte it the syn of olde Adam: but for the felicite in stede of calamite to vs yelden more plētifully / we ought to thāke the newe Adam / that is Christ Iesu of all creatures preysed ye world without ende. Satanas expelled vs out of Paradyse / Christe for therthly paradise opened vs the heuē
               ly kyngdome. The serpent droue vs to dyuers sorowes of this life / Christ restored vs to ioyes euerlasting of lyfe īmortall. Satanas by his gyle got

vs bodily deth / Christ by his mercy rewarded vs lyfe etnal / to whom who so euer with a pure harte yeldeth hym / nedeth to drede no kinde of ēnemies. He ouercame the worlde / he vanquished all Satanas tyrāny / he turned ye fleshe in to spirite. That he ouercame is of his power: yt he ouer came for vs / is of his mercy. Let vs honour his mercifull myght / and take fruicion of his myghtyfull mercy. All thynges we may do by hym / that maketh vs mighty / if we abide with hym: al thinges we possesse by hȳ / ī whom is al goodnes euery where vs defendyng / aydyng / cōfortyng / &amp; encresyng by his mercy / lyke as the prophet sayth in ye psalme: Mercy wyll enuiron them that truste in our lorde. To what great ils are they subiect / that put their trust in bodily gyftes / in riches / in chares / in horses / in worldly prudēce / in theyr merites &amp; dedes? But by what succours is ye iuste man out of care? Truly sayth he / I trust in ye multitude of thy mercy. And a lytell after: Lorde as with the bucler of thy good wyll hast crowned vs. Whan ye here / Of thy good wyll / ye vnderstāde ye hope of your owne merites to be excluded. Where the strēthes of nature fayle vs / where our merites forsake vs: there mercy succoureth vs. The warriours shyldes cou
                  •
               r but one part of the body / the buccler of diuine mercy dothe fensiuely couer vs all aboute / aboue agaynst the fyrie dartes of wycked spirites / that hange ouer vs frō the celestiens: beneth agaynst the sl
                  •
               ight of the serpent yt wayteth to attrap vs: afore / lest thinges present greue vs: behynde / lest

thinges past ēuade vs agayne: on the right hāde lest prosperite make vs insolent: on the lyft hande lest aduersite ouer throwe vs. Trustȳg in this bucler Dauid crieth out: Our lorde is my helper / I wyll not drede what a man can do to me. And in another place: I wyll nat feare a thousande people cōpassyng me about. But Paule thapostle cryeth out yet more boldly writyng to the Romayns: If god be with vs sayth he / w
                  •
               o shal be agaynst vs?
            That noble warriour armed hym with al ye harneis of the faith / whiche fortifieth vs nat by hope of our warkes / but of diuine mercy. He beȳg bold on this armour, dyd nat only dispise grefe / hūger, pouerte / peril / ꝑsecutiō: but also the tyrās sword / thretning to sle hym by and by. The humayn cruelnes may do nothing / where the mercy of god is redy at hande to defende: yea this is stronger / he dispised beside deth and lyfe / āgels / principalites / vertues / thinges present &amp; to come, fortitude, altitude / depthe / &amp; so forth / if any other creature were in the heuēs / or in erth / or in hell
                  •
               . And this is he, whiche knowing his weakenes calleth hȳ selfe an erthē pot. We haue sayth he / this treasure ī erthē pottes. Fro whens thā hath this britell erthē pot so moche strength? By the grace of god sayth he, I am it that I am. What is the grace of god but ye mercy of god? Let vs gladly glorify with Paule in our infirmites / that the vertue of Christe may dwelle in vs: for so it is more expediēt for vs / that by contēplacion of our miseries / we maye glorifie the mercies of god. And yet the meane while / if it

lyke the / beholde thy selfe thou man / in that parte that thou excellest the other beastis. For if thou esteme thy selfe after the goodnes of the body, thou seest thou art lower than many brute beastis / the camels in greatnes excede the, in swyftnes the tygers / in strength the buls / in colour the swannes, in apparayle pecockes / in helthines the fyshes / ye if we beleue the prouerbe / welnere all beastes / in quicke syght ye beast lynx &amp; egles / in smellyng gripis, in lōge lyfe hartis and crowes. And yet if one cōsydre ye gyftes of the humayn body / he shal here fȳde wherin he may preyse ye mercy of god. What sagasite of the .v. wittis / what great cōformite of mēbres / howe feet instrumentes to dyuers vses? But of those thinges also Lactantius a mā of singuler eloquēce / cōpiled a boke / whiche he nameth De opificio dei. To rede that boke wyl profit vs moche, if we minde what goodnes is in the body, and as hit all cometh from the mercy of god / to be seruant lyke bonde to diuine obeysance. Other wyse he that wyll glorifie in bodily gyftes / shall by &amp; by here: All flesshe is hey / and all glorie therof is as the flower of hey. Why arte proude thou dost and asshes? Neyther in gyftes of the soule / in whiche parte man is more marueylous / he hath oughte / that he may chalenge as his owne. He that made the body / formed ye soule / ye body he made of slyme and put in the soule with inspiryng of his mouth. And therfore of the other beastes the soule &amp; body perishe to gether / ours is alyue after the body / 
                  •
               yl she receyue it agayne in the resurrection ꝓmysed.

Nowe howe effectual a thyng the soule is / ye very deth declareth, which assone as she deꝑteth, there lyeth the carkes vnprofitable: where is the hete / where is the colour / where is the mouyng / where is the myght of all the wyttes? And yet while the soule is holden fast tied to this so vnhappy sely body / doyng nothyng but through the bodily instrumētes / whiche very oft let / yt she can nat put forthe her natiue power / howe maruelous is ye swiftnes and profounde vnderstandynge of mans mynde. What an exceding treasure of remēbrance. What is so hyd in ye secretes of nature / or ī ye heuēs / or in erthe / that mans wyt can nat marke / ꝑceiue / and discusse? It is a great thyng / that many by situacion and mouynge of the sterres shewe what shall fall many yeres to cōme: but it is more that by ye thinges wrought / the euerlastȳg power and godheed of the same worker is founde out / wytnes is Paule: Howe moche is the swiftnes of mās wyt / ī howe short space / howe many thinges doth mās wyt beholde at ones? But howe 
                  •
               xcedeth y• might of memory, that truly obserueth ye shaps of so many thinges / &amp; so many names of thynges cōmytted to her by ye ministracion of the wyttes? I wyll speke nothyng here of them / yt haue lerned so many sciences so harde to knowe / &amp; so many lāgages &amp; that that they lerned / they reteyne styl. Let him that wyll of you thynke / howe many folkes faces &amp; names he remēbreth / howe many shaps of beastis / trees / herbes / places / and of other īnumerable thȳges he knoweth / and memorially cleapeth

them by name. The comon people calle these gyftes of nature / whā ī dede they be gyftes of diuine mercye / whiche are departed to eche nat after our merites / but after his benignite. Al these thinges bicause ye prodigal child abused to ye pleasure of humayn wyl / nat only it is nat withdrawē that was gyuen / but by grace more abundantly beralite of gyftes is added. By lawe he instructed vs / by his son̄e whom holle he gaue to vs / he taught vs the secretes of god / by his spirite he enriched our soules with dyuers gyftes / passyng mannes power. He gyueth vnderstanding of misticall scriptures / that gyue lyght and comfort to vs in all yls, he gyueth forknowlege of thynges to come / he gyueth tonges to speke sondry langages / to cōtempne venom / to heale sycknesses / to reyse the deed / to confo
                  •
               de noyful spirites / he gyueth power to ouercōe hel gates / he graūteth vs to be mēbres of Christ / childrē of god, ꝑteners of the kyngdome celestial / that neuer shall haue ende. Here co
                  •
               t to me wherof thou were made / without dout on the one part claye, thā howe moche vnder ye cōdiction of beastis syn threwe the. Agayne / to what dignite / to what felicite thou art called / &amp; thā thou shalt clerely se / ye mercies of our lorde haue neyther nūbre nor measure. What is more despised thā scarbetes? Yet is a scarbet pure ī cōparison to ye filthines of a sȳner. What is hygher than angels? Were hit nat out of al measure to make an angell of a scarbet? Nowe mā more abiect than a scarbet / he made greatter thā angel / I may boldly say / he made hym a god.

For why shulde nat I dare boldly say it yt the scripture doth: I sayd ye be goddis / and excellent children? What so euer cometh of god is made in a maner god. What so euer is ioyned to the body &amp; spirite of Christe / cometh in to the felowshyp and ꝑttakyng of his name. Here if nothing be that thou to thy merites mayst ascribe / glorifie the mercy of god / worship the mercy of god / enbrace &amp; kysse the mercy of god. If that any go about to claime any part of this to hym selfe / Paule thapostle wyll by &amp; by crie out agaynst hym / yelding all these thynges to the grace of god. All his pistils soūde out ye worde of grace: whiche as oft as thou hereste vnderstāde ye mercy of god to ye cōmended. Of grace it is / that we be purged frō synne / through grace we beleue / of grace it is that by his spirite charite is spredde in our hartes / wherby we do good warkes. For we be nat sufficient by our selfe / as of our selfe: but al our ablenes cometh frō god. If Paule sayd trouthe / where be those shameles felowes / yt selle to euery body theyr good warkes / as though they had so moche at home / that they myghte enryche other? They be miserable / that so selle their good dedes / cursed they be that trust in mēs warkes. Who that is greued with the fyrst disease / let hym here what the churche Laodicēs hereth in ye Apocalyps. Thou sayst: I am riche and plētifull and nede nothyng / and knowest nat that thou art a wretche / miserable / poure / blinde / &amp; naked. But they also syn more greuously / that of thabundāce of theyr good warkes promyse other ryches. But

what coūsaileth the holy gost suche folke? I counsayle the sayth he / to bye firy golde of me proued / that thou mayste be ryche in dede. And thou that knowest thyn owne pouerte / why beggest of beggers? S. Iames sayth: If any want wysdome / lette him aske it of god, that gyueth to eche abundantly / and abraydeth none therof. Euery good gyft / &amp; euery ꝑfect gyft descendeth frō aboue frō ye father of lyghtes. And askest thou of a mā ye garment of good warkes / whiche is ye more piteously naked / the more gayely he rekeneth hym selfe clothed? Aknowlege thy misery / and ye mercy of god is redy. Amōge mē / whiche abrayd one a other of a good turne / whiche for one pleasure loke to haue many / is nohtynge derer bought / than it that is bought with prayers: with god nothyng is so fr
                  •
                as that yt is bought with .ij. litel peces of money / prayer &amp; hope, for he that wyll sell his mercy, hath gyuē vs ye same price to pay for it. ¶we haue spokē many thinges welbeloued bretherne of ye mercy of god / but there is moche more to saye / if we shuld repete all thynges of holy scripture / whiche preyse &amp; cōmēde to vs ye greatnes of diuine merci. The remenāt is / yt I wyl exhort you in fewe wordes / yt none through presumpcion make hym selfe vnworthy of the mercy of god / that is so redy: or through yll corage of mȳde despeyre of ye mercy of god. And after we wyl shortly declare / what thynges ꝓuoke the mercy of god. And so make an ende of our sermō / if the mercy of our lord vouchesafe to be present and fauorable vnto me spekyng to you.
            
               God aborreth nothynge so mo
                  •
               he as pryde &amp; obstaclenes: for he resisteth the proude / and gyueth grace to the hūble. To this blynd madnes &amp; mad blyndnes many are brought throughe ꝓsperite of tēporal goodes / whiche as forgetfull of theyr maker they lyuen after theyr pleasure / so moche vnthoughtfull to amende theyr lyfe / that they boost vngratiousnes / stronge &amp; myghty in wickednes. And as we rede ī an other place: They 
                  •
               oste their yll doynge / and reioyce in most vngratious thynges: Wherof Solomon writeth: The wicked mā whan he cometh to the bottū of yls / he is careles. And of suche folke Paule wrytethe: God gyueth them a peruersed iugement / to do those thynges / that be nat comely. Some of them promise them selfe / that they shall skape vnpunyshed for euer / &amp; despise holsome monyshyon / and wyll nat here of suche thynges as shulde prouoke them to repentance / sayeng: Let god haue heuen hym selfe / let hym leaue vs the erth. Of these speketh Moyses in his canticle / whan a
                  •
               ter many great benefites of god to the people of Israell remembred / he addeth: My welbeloued is waxed grosse &amp; kycketh: he is waxed fat and broode: he hath forsaken god his maker, and is departed from god his sauiour. The psal. 72. peynteth this maner of mē: They be nat in the labour of mē / &amp; they shall nat be scorged with mē. Bycause pride reteineth them / they be couered with iniquite &amp; theyr wickednes / they be gone in to affectiō of hert. They haue thought and spoken leudnes, and they haue talked wickedly

agaynst almyghty god. They haue sette theyr mouth agaynst the heuen / and theyr tōge is gone ouer in erthe. But herke what ende foloweth this vnhappy felicite. But yet for all theyr wyles thou hast begyled them / thou dyddest cast them downe whā they wold ari
                  •
               en vp. Howe were they discō
               
                  ••
               
               ted? they fayled sodaynly / &amp; perished for their wickednes. Good lorde ī thy cite shalt reduce ye image of them to naught / as ye dreame of them that ryse frō slepe. On them that folowing Lucifers example ryse vp agaynst god / shall fall yt our lorde thretneth in ye gospell: I sawe Satanas as lightnyng fal from heuen. And Corozaim through abūdance of transitory thynges wickedly swellyng, hereth: Wo to the Corozaim / for thou that a
                  •
               te nowe lyfte vp to heuen by thy pryde / shalt be plucte downe to helle by the vēgeance of god. Paule also somtyme on trust of his coūtrey lawes was fierce &amp; proude / &amp; thretned to slee the disciples of our lorde / and for 
                  ••
               t by the ryght hande of god ouerthrowen to the erth he hereth: It is harde for ye to kycke agaȳst ye pricke. But bycause in his dede was errour and nat wayward malice / he optayned mercy. Assone as he aknowleged his syn / god forgaue hym / and nat only forgaue hym / but also of a wolfe he made hym a shepe / &amp; of a tyran a postle. But the curse of god hangeth ouer them that continue in synne / at laste beynge indurated and obstinate therin / wyll nat vnderstāde to do well: whiche say to god: Go thy way frō vs / we wyl nat haue knowlege of thy wayes. Agayne they yt Esaie speaketh of / whiche

our lorde calling to wepyng / waylyng, cuttyng of theyr heare / and to weare shertes of heare / they make myrth and reuell / kylling calues / and sacrifieng shepe / yt they may eate the fleshe / and drinke wyne / sayeng: Let vs eate and drynke / for to morowe we shal dye. And they as the same prophet sayth / that scorne the thretninges of god / steryng them to repēt: Byd byd agayne / byd byd agayne, abyde abyde agayne / abyde abyde agayne / a litel there a lytell there. And the whiche say agayne in an other place: We wyll nat here our lorde / but we wyll dye in our synnes: to these as ye olde ꝓuerbe sayth / Pacience oft greued turneth in to madnes: and the mercy of our lorde despised / is turned in to greuouser dampnacion. For our lorde mocked in Esaie answereth after: The sayeng of our lorde to them shal be: Byd byd agayne / byd byd agayne / abyde abyde agayne / abyde abyde agayne / a litel there a lytell there / that they may go &amp; fall backewarde / and be all to rent / and attrapped / &amp; taken. These vnhappy folke go / left in theyr yll desires / alway waxyng worse / they fall in to the pyt of wickednes / they be tangled in the cordes of syn / they be takē in the net of euerlasting dānacion / leading theyr dayes amōge theyr goodes / &amp; in a moment they go to hell. O very wretched creatures / &amp; holly gyuē to distructiō / whiche like as beastis be fatted to be kylde / whom neither the enormite of syn maketh to forgette pryde / nor so great hyndnes of god tēdreth them to repēt. The mercy of god suffreth the so ofte to synne / yt thou shuldest amende / 

he gyueth the space to repent, &amp; in the mean while he taketh nat frō the his benignite / he gyueth the good helth / he gyueth the riches, he gyueth the other cōmodites of ye lyfe, as in maner settyng vp &amp; castyng coles of fire ouer thy heed / yt if thou canst nat hate thy syn, for that it is most shamfull of hi
                  •
                selfe / yet at lest shuldest begyn to hate it / sith it displeaseth so louyng a father. Eschinus a yong mā ꝑceiuing ī a play ye maruelous hyndnes of his father toward hym offēdȳg / was moued / yt frō thēs forth he wolde haue him ī greatter reuerēce / these be his wordes: What thyng is this? is this to be a fader / or this to be a son? If he were my brother or felowe / how myght he folowe more my mynde? Is he nat to be loued? ought he nat to be borne in mynde? Ah he maketh me right careful with his e
                  •
               ynes / leest I shulde vnware do ought contrary to his mynde / for wittingly I wyl beware therof.
            If fatherly hyndnes teche wytty childrē to hate syn / thou vnhappy synner dost thou waxe more &amp; more obstinate for so great goodnes of thy father, &amp; herest nat Paule calling y• agayne frō madnes? Dost thou despise saith he, the riches of thy goodnes / pacience / and mekenes? Knowest nat that ye gētylnes of god leadeth the to repētance? But after thy hardnes &amp; vnrepētant harte / thou getherest vnto the a treasure of anger in the day of anger / and the reuelaciō of the iuste iugemēt of god.
            No beast is so wylde, yt by mēs diligēce &amp; labour is nat tamed, &amp; yu ꝓuoked by so excedȳg benefit of god / art also more fierce agaynst hym? Nothynge

is so harde / that is nat made softe by crafte of mē. Brasse melteth in the furnes / yrō by fyre is made softe / horne with waxe poured in soupleth / the inuīcible hardnes of ye diamond is ouercōe wt gottis blud: And o hart harder than horne / harder than yron / harder thā the diamond / that neither ye fyre of hell / nor the hyndnes of thy moste gētyl father / nor ye blud of the vndefiled lambe shed for the / can mollifie: yea is made more harder than all these. Nowe be ioyfull / make triumphe of wickednes / yu hast ouercome wretche / thou haste ouercōe diuine craft / whiche is most vnhappy victori. Unhappy is the groūde as Paule sayth / &amp; nerest the curse of god / whiche whan it ofte receiueth heuenly moystnes / it brīgeth forth none other thing but thornes &amp; wydes: howe moche more vnhappy is he / that is so ofte moisted with rayne of diuine mercy / and waxeth harde as any rough sturdy stone / that he wyl receyue no print of the holy gost? The fynger of god wrote the lawe to Moyses in stony tables / so that thy hart is sturdier thā these stones, wher in ye holy goost can write nothing of Christis lawe. Who shall cut vs these stony hartes but he / whose dethe cloue ye stones / yt they myght go out of theyr tūbes yt were deed? Who shal giue vs a fleshy hart but ye worde of god / that for vs was made fleshe? But yet they be more desperate thā these / whiche reioysyng in theyr syns / spred abrode blasphemoꝰ &amp; wicked opiniōs denyeng god to be aboue, or if he be / that mortal folkes busynes ꝑteyne nothyng to hym: to be no life after deth of the body: no īmortalite

to be prepared for them / that here lyued dedeuoutly in Christ Iesu: nor helle ppared for them that here serued the deuyll: the thretnynges of holy scripture to be vayne: the ꝓmyses of the gospel to be lyes: or they that by wronge expoundyng of scripture / defēde their mischeuous dedes for good actis: and the worde of god / wherby the yll desyres of the mynde ought to be corrected / they compell to supporte theyr fylthynes / to other crymes they laye the wickednes of heresy / as most worste rebuke. The palenes / whiche for great skele appereth in your faces / &amp; the trēblyng of ye holle body / shewe howe moche ye abhorre that ye haue herde. But wold to god we myght nat here those thȳges amōge christen folke. I haue shewed you Scylla, on whiche rocke many rūne and perishe. Nowe I wyll shewe you Charybdis / a daunger greuouser thā ye most greuous &amp; more ferefull. They be they whiche folowyng Cain &amp; Iudas the traitour / despeyre of forgyuenes swaloweth in to euerlastyng distructiō. There is but one distruction / though ye reason of perishyng be diuers. Pharao indurated sayth: I knowe no lorde / nor I wyll nat let the peple go. What sayth Cain? My syn is greatter thā I may diserue ꝑdon. And what sayth Iudas? I haue synned betraieng ye innocēt blud. Both they aknowlege the greatnes of theyr synne / both they cōfesse it / both repēt theyr mysdede / but both they go away frō the face of our lorde / in whom onely is mercy &amp; plētifull redētion frō synnes. For thus ye rede of Cain: And Cain goynge away frō the face

of our lorde / dwelled a rūne a gate in a coūtrey towarde the Est. &amp;c. And Iudas departyng frō the banket of saynctes / returneth nat agayne: He is vnhappy, that so goeth frō the face of the mercy of god / that he returneth nat agayne. This is he I thynke / that Ieremias meaneth / whan he saith: Wepe nat for ye deed ne mourne nat for hym: with wepyng bewayle hym / that goeth out / bicause he returneth no more agayne. He wil nat ye deed to be wept for / bicause somtyme he must aryse agayne. He with al maner wepyng shuld be wayled / yt turneth hym selfe away from the well of euerlastyng lyfe / and neuer by penance returneth agayne / frō thens he went. That prodigall &amp; riottous chylde went away in to fer coūtrey / he left ye house of his moost louyng father / but he is returned agayne. Peter swarued far frō our lorde / whan he forsoke hym thrise: but shortly aft he came agayne / whā he remēbred the worde that Iesus spake / he begā to wepe bytterly. He had forgotten hym selfe / but whan he came to him selfe agayne / he returned to Iesus. Lyke wise Esaie crieth: Remēbre ye this / &amp; be ye cōfūded and you sȳners come to your harte agayne. Peter remēbred hym selfe / and returned to his hart: the stony hart was takē frō hym / the pomisehart, out of whiche no drop of teares coude be got: a flesshe hart was gyuē hȳ / out of whiche anon sprāge a welle of teares / bytter for ye sorowe of penāce / but holsome for the innocēcy to hym restored. But Iudas is nat returned to Iesus / but he went away to ye prestes &amp; pharisees / he yelded

agayne that woful money / from thens he rōne to ye snare / &amp; brake a 
                  •
               onder. These thinges our lorde suffred amonge his disciples for our instruction. Ye se howe diuers ye ende of two apostles synnyng is. Iudas yt was so oft ꝓuoked by our lordes m
                  •
               
               kenes to be sory &amp; amēde, stacke styll in his wicked purpose. But Peter at the lokyng of Iesus vpo
                  •
                hym / remēbred our lordes sayeng / &amp; by &amp; by knew hym selfe / and as vnworthy of our lordes psence / he drewe abacke / nat to hange hym selfe / but to wepe / that is / nat to despeyre / but to remedy. Iudas folowyng Cain the auctour of this mischiefe / aknowleged truly the greatnes of his syn / but he remēbred nat the wordes of our lorde / that euery where in holy scripture ꝓuoke vs to returne / that stere vs to do penance / and promise vs mercy. For what padge is in holy scripture / that soūdeth na
                  •
                the mercy of god? I speke nat only of the newe testament / that is the lawe of grace / but also of the olde testament / that is thought more rigorous. Let vs here howe gētilly our lorde in ye ꝓphet Ieremy / that vnder the ꝑsone of the spouse leauyng her husbāde, abādoneth her euery where to euery body / he reclaymeth his people to penāce: Turne to me sayth he / ye childrē returnȳg agayne / sayth our lorde, for I am your husbāde. And in Iob our lorde openeth the eare of the sinners, that he may correct them: and speketh / that they shuld returne frō wick
                  •
               d
                  •
               es. But they be wre
                  •
               ches / yt agaynst this our lordes voyce stoppe theyr eares / lyke the de
                  ••
               e edder / that stoppeth her eares for the none
                  •
               
               
lest a shulde here the voyce of the enchanter wysely: To day sayth the psalme / if ye here his voyce / be nat harde harted. To day is ours / as longe as we be in this lyfe / whiche all the while hit lasteth / our lorde cesseth nat to speke to vs / sterȳg vs to do penance / offryng forgyuenes, ppared. What / sayd I forgyuenes? The mercy of god is more whiche promiseth to them that returne a precious gyfte. For thus we rede in Iob: If thou wylt returne to almyghty god / thou shalte be edifyed / and shalte voyde wickednes far frō thy tent: for erth he shall gyue the a flynt stone, &amp; for a flint stone golden ryuers. Let vs here the mercy of our lorde in Esaie steryng vs to repentāce: If ye seke saith he / seke / returne and come: if ye seke thende of yuels / seke hit nat in children of men / in whom is no saluacion / nor of ēchantours / nor by hangyng your selfe / but aske it of me / that alone both may and am redy to forgyue. Only returne from those thynges / that ye fylthily haue loued / &amp; turned / come to me. Agayne in the same ꝓphet / ētysyng al mankynde to hym / he sayth: Am nat I a lorde? and there is no more god but I: God iuste and holy is none besyde me: returne to me / and ye shal be 
                  •
               aued al the costis of the erth / for I am god / and there is none other. These wordes our lorde speketh to gentils, idolworshippers / to mākyllers, churche robbers / 
                  •
               echers, blasphemers: &amp; thou wretche by dispeyre woldest turne away from our lorde? In olde tyme whan synne vnpunished rayned amōge folke / the merry of god semed to be drawen within ye narow

boūdes of Iudee. But by the gospell mercy spred ouer all costes of the worlde: In Ieremye also he thretneth the obstinate / but he offereth them forgyuenes prepared that repent &amp; amēde: If that folke sayth he, wyll do penāce for theyr synne / that I haue spokē agaynst them / I wil also do penāce vpon ye harme / that I thought haue done them. And he yt a lyttel before thretned distruction / pluckyng vp by the rotes / &amp; sparklyng about / promyseth thynges cōtrary, and sodaynly sayth: I wyl
                  •
                speke of the people &amp; realme / that I may edifie it / and that I may plant it. Like wyse in Ezechiel he nat only ꝓmiseth hym ꝑdō yt turneth agayne / but also that he wold forget all the synnes that he had done before: For whan he had afore remēbred euery kynde of myschefes and dānable dedes / he addeth: If the wicked man wyl do penāce for al the synnes that he hath wrought / and wil kepe al my cōmandementes / and wyl do iugemēt and iustice
                  •
                he shal lyue and shall nat dye: I wyll nat remēbre al the iniquitees that he hath wrought. Is it my wyll sayth our lorde / that a synner shulde dye / and nat rather yt he shulde be cōuerted frō his sinnes &amp; lyue? And a lytell lower: Be ye cōuerted and do penāce for all your synnes / and your wickednes shal nat distroye you: throwe away all your offences / wherby ye haue trāsgressed: and make you a new hart and a newe spirite. And why die ye the house of Israel? Bicause I will nat the deth of ye dyeng treature sayth our lorde / turne agayne and come. Why despeyrest thou wretche / sith god for this sēt

downe his son in to this worlde / y• y• shuldest haue good hope? He hym selfe vndouted is the mercy of god, of whom Dauid syngeth: O god we haue receyued thy mercy in ye myddis of thy churche. Be thou ī the churche / and enbrace mercy. He rysyng crieth: I wyl nat the deth of a synner, but rather that he shulde be cōuerted &amp; lyue. Here this voyce thou vnhappy synner / shake of deedly slepe / rise agayne with Christ / that thou mayst lyue in hym. For he reuiued / to thende ye deth of syn shulde nat alway possesse the. And if any body suspect yt this mercy of god is nat ppared / nor redy / but for these that cōmyt fewe &amp; lyght syns / let hym here what our lorde with a clere voyce promiseth: Whan so euer a synner bewayleth his synnes / I wyll forget al his iniquitees. He excepteth no kynde of synne, he pōdreth nat the greatnes or multitude of offences. Be sory only / and forgetfulnes of all thy syns past is redy. For small offences / without whiche mās frailte lyueth nat, we call dayly vpō the mercy of god / sayeng: Dimitte nobis debita nostra. &amp;c. For gyue vs as we forgyue them that offēde vs: And we be herde / if we here our neyghbour prayenge / that we shuld forgyue him. And also amōge deedly synnes is a certeyne order / as amonge mē some slepe nat very soūdly / so that with a litel whistrȳg they awake: there be that slepe more depely / that one must speke loude to wake them: there be that slepe most depely / that vneth with great tuggȳge they wyl awake: so with god som be lighter deed / some more greuously / and some moste greuously.

But no kynde of dethe is so desperate and deedly, yt he with his voyce dryueth nat awaye / at whose voyce also they rise agayne / that were deed ī theyr graues: and no man is takē with so depe sloūbre of deth / that is nat by hym reysed. This threfold difference of synners ye deuout interpreters of holy scriptures suppose signified to vs by thre corses that we rede were reysed from dethe to lyfe by our lorde Iesu. The maister of the sinagogis daughter / a mayde .xij. yere of age / he reysed in ye house / a fewe admytted to se it / &amp; he forbade to tell abrode that was done. These be they / yt fyrste nat of purposed malice / but eyther by sleprenes of age / or by mans frailnes / be so slyden in to som synne / yt they be nat yet obstinate in yll / nor yet no foule rumour rūneth of that mysdede. Our lorde Iesus lightly reyseth those with his hande put for the / hydynge theyr fylthynes / and prouidynge for theyr shamefastnes. But he reysed vppe the wyddowes sonne with more busynes. Nowe the carkeys was caried to the graue
                  •
               and in goyng our lorde met them, he moued with ye sely womās weping / bade them stande styl that bare the biere, he reysed the yonge mā. Fyrst he sittech vp / soone aft he speketh / shortly after he skyppeth out of the coffyn / &amp; is deliuered to his mother agayne. These be they vndouted / that be so fer irōne in synne that they be infamy can nat be reclaymed frō synnyng: they by open penance lytell &amp; lytell be reised agayne to life. He sitteth vp / whiche forsakyng syn, lyfteth vp hȳ selfe to ye purpose of a better lyfe. He speketh, that

cōfessyng his foule synnes / aknowlegeth ye mercy of god. He is yelded to his mother a lyue / that aft al remedies accomplished / is restored to the cōmunion of the churche agayne. Lazarus truly nowe stanke in his graue. He is bewayled onely of his de
                  •
               perate systers and frēdes / here Iesus byddeth to shewe hym the graue / he wepeth / he make the gri
                  •
               ely soune with his mouthe / and is troubled in spirite / he cōmandeth to take away the stone / and with a loude voyce he byddeth hym to come forth: he cometh forth / but he is boūde / he is losed / and so at last he is yelded to his systers agayne. It was no great thyng for our lorde to reyse a carkeys .iiij. dayes deed / it is a greatter maystrie to reyse a synner / that .xl. yeres lyued nat / but lay stynkyng defiled with al maner fylthy synne. A childe saith Esaie of an hūdred yeres shal dye / and a sinner of an hūdred yeres shalbe cursed. And ye same our lorde Iesus wyll vouchesafe to reyse / so yt he at last wyll here hym callyng. He cryeth dayly / aryse maydē / aryse yonge man / come forthe Lazare. But hel as many / more than deed / here nat his voyce callyng vs agayne to lyfe. But what thyng is to here but to beleue? Incredulite or hard belefe stoppeth the eares of wicked folkes / that ye voyce of holy scripture can nat entre ī to theyr myndes. Let vs pray the mercy of god / that he wyll vouchesafe to soūde out aloude his almyghty voyce / and to synge it to those wretched &amp; desperate folke: Thou deffe and dūme spirite / I cōmand the / get ye out of this mā / and entre no more in to hym. Nowe to the ende ye

may se more playnly howe redy the mercy of god is to hym that repēteth &amp; amēdeth / here Dauyd
                  •
                I haue sayd / I wyll aknowlege agaynst me myn vnrightousnes to our lorde: and thou hast forgyuen me the wickednes of my syn. Nat yet cōfe
                  •
               sed but to one only myndyng cōfession ye mercy of god rūneth. Be sory / cōfesse the / but let it be afore god. Many wayle afore mē / they wepe in ye sight of peple / they confesse them to men / they rent theyr clothes / but it is afore ye people, they weare ye heare / they spryncle ashes on theyr heed / but it is afore y• people. Whiche thynges if they were done before god / yt is to say / with all the hart / with pure affection / ye mercy of god cesseth nat. Cut &amp; rent sayth he / your hartes and nat your garmētes. For god wyll nat despise a contrite and an hūble hart. Let vs wepe sayth the psalme writer / before god / that made vs. Many faste / but nat the faste that our lorde wylleth: many change theyr rayment / but they change nat theyr affection. And yet it is so / that these thinges also must be done amōge men / that they / whom our malyce prouoked to synne / may be called agayne by penance to amēde. But these thynges are vnprofitably done amonge the peple / except they be fyrst done in the 
                  •
               yght of god Iudas confessed his syn / but it was to the pharises: if he had cōfessed him to our lorde, by &amp; by the most mild mercy of our lord had ēbraced him. And to thende our cōfession may be more acceptable to god / Osee ye ꝓphet sheweth to vs also ye fourme of confession: Take saythe he with you wordes, &amp; returne

to our lorde / and say to hym / Take away al iniquite frō vs / and receyue good / &amp; we shall gyue the againe the calues of our lyppes. Let vs also / that haue wandred many wayes, returne to hym agayne / that alone taketh away the sinnes of the worlde / ye whiche for our sinnes shed his precious blud / let vs say to hym: Take away frō vs al the yll / that we wickedly wrought. What frely? And receyue good / what good? The calues of our lyppes. We shall gyue thankes to thy mercy / wherto we be boūde for euery good dede we dyd after our fal, thou shalt take frō vs yt is ours, &amp; shalt receiue of vs yt is thyne. Ye but se howe wel with him accordeth the prophet Iohel / expressyng the same sentence with other wordes, for whan god by him had sharply thretned those that regarded nat his mercy to them offered / this he bryngeth in after: Returne to your god / for he is myld &amp; merciful, pacient and of moche mercy / and repētyng vpō malice. The greatnes of sinnes ouerthroweth y• / but ye greatnes of goddis mercy can lyft y• vp agayne. se by howe many wayes the ꝓphet amp
                  ••
               fieth it. He is gentyll, orels as hit is in Greke mercifull. Though this was inough that we shuld nat despeyre / yet he addeth: And hauing pite, yt we may vnderstād, yt he nat only helpeth vs, but also is sory for our iuels. And herwith nat cōtēt / he addeth pacient / that is to say easy / and nothyng hasty to take vengeance / lyke as humayn mercy is lightly turned to dysdayne. And yet o synner thou despeyrest. Herkē therfore yt foloweth. And of moche

mercy. If thy sinnes by many, mistrust nat, mercy is moche. What remayneth nowe / but that yu must be cōuerted / and go to him entisyng ye? But if ye punyshemētes of mercy feare yt, herke &amp; take corage: And taking repentance of his malice. He calleth the peynes and afflictions that are due for our synnes malice. He taketh away synne / He forgyueth euerlasting peyne deserued. What resteth thā? nothyng, but that thou shuldest aknowlege the mercy of god. Undouted this is it yt foloweth in Iohel. And he shall leaue after hym blessyng &amp; sacrifice to our lorde god. Truly this is it yt Osee sayd: The calues of the lyppes / that is to say / sacrifice of preyse and thanke gyuyng. If any greuously and ofte shuld offende a mortal man / howe harde is the making at one, howe mindeth he the wrōges / howe slowly asswageth the anger / howe lightly for a trifyl falleth he in ye old grudge, howe frowardly asketh he amendis for the offence: and yet if they so receiue them in fauour agayne / they be called gentyl. God so oft offēded / willingly prouoketh vs to repentāce / he entiseth vs to forgyuenes, he perdoneth thretninges, he forgyueth helle peyne / he offreth for punyshement benignite / yea and he nat only tu
                  •
               neth his face towarde the synner / mendyng and repentyng / but voluntarily he meteth hym turnyng agayne / &amp; with his armes spred abrode he wol enbrace hym conuerted. Undouted the same is it that he ꝓmiseth in zacarie: Turne ye to me sayth the lorde of ostis, and I wyl turne to you saith the lorde of ostis. What is that

to say
                  •
                Turne ye to me? aknowlege your wretchednes / and desyre my mercy. What is: and I wyll turne to you? By and by I of a reuenger and punysher made an helper / wyll helpe forwarde your purposes / that ye can nat brynge to passe by your owne strēgthes / ye may opteyne it by my fauour. No man coude holsomely hate his syn / but if god granted hit / except he take away the stony harte / and put in a sleshie harte: but if for a defiled hart he worke in vs a clene hart / except for an yll spirite he renewe in our bowels a good iuste spirite. But why take I this labour to reherce some olde places of scripture / whiche declaren the marueylous mercy of god? All the scripture of y• olde testamēt alabout preacheth / syngeth / and layeth before vs the mercy of god. And where be those frāticke foles rather than heretickes / that of one make two goddis / one of the olde testament / that was onely iuste &amp; nat good: the other of the newe / that shuld be onely good and nat iuste / coude they nat at leest wise here this songe / that is so often tymes rehersed in the psalme .Cxvij. Aknowlege to god / that he is good / and that his mercy is in all worldes. Where is mad Manicheus / that taught in his bokes / that he that speketh to vs so louyngly by his prophettes / and that dyd ordeyne Moyses lawe / was no veray god / but one of the wycked dyuels. The selfe same is god of both the lawes / the same trouth / the same mercy by Iesu Christ our lorde / saue that in Moyses lawe be shadowes / in the gospell trouth: in the other was promyse / in this is

ꝑfourmance: in that was moche and great mercy towarde the Iewes / here is the holle well of mercy / or rather the see / that hath flowen ouer all nacions of the holle worlde / by whiche flode the syns of al mortal creatures are washed and skoured away. Surely this was the happy flode of mercy: the olde flode (a fewe saued) distroyed ye synners: this holsome flode washeth away ye syns / &amp; saueth al yt beleue in the sonne of god. He that in bokes of the olde testament promyseth the Hebrewes repē
               tyng &amp; amēdyng / forgyuenes / the same present in the gospel crieth to euery mā: Come to me al that labour &amp; be loden / and I wyll refreshe you. Take my yocke vpon you / and ye shal fynde rest for your soules. For my yocke is swete / &amp; my burthē light. Rede the lyfe of Christe ouer &amp; ouer / what thynge els se ye therin / but cōtinuall mercy toward euery body? He healed sicke folke frely / he fed the hūgry / he succoured them that were in perill / he made lepers holle &amp; clene / he gaue the blynde their sight, &amp; restored ye lame theyr lymmes / he droue away dyuels / he reysed deed mē to lyfe / he assoyled them yt were repētāt. Agayne / serche out al his techyng / what other thing doth it sauer / thā excedȳg great mercy of god? By howe many parables printeth he ye same in our mȳdes, yt we shulde slyde no way
                  •
                For what other thyng sheweth the parable of the shepe brought agayne on ye sheperdis shulders / of ye pece of money lost &amp; foūde / of the holle folke that nede a phisiciō / of ye seruant to whom all his duyte is gyuen / agayne of the vserer / that forgaue both

the dettours, of the publican &amp; pharisee / of ye pylgrym hurt, whom the samaritan healeth, of ye cur
               
                  •
               ese stewarde to his dettours / of ye disceiuer of his maister / of the ryottous childe receyued agayne? And the very cleapynge of the gospell / doth it nat by &amp; by promyse mercy? What promiseth hit? To blinde sight, to prisoners ꝑdon, to ye brokē holnes / shortly to speke a yere acceptable to our lorde / that desireth none other thynge but mans saluacion. Nowe the same name of Iesu / that is of a sauiour / what other thynge ꝓmyseth it but saluacion &amp; mercy? If he had proclaymed hym selfe a iuge / it had bē somwhat why one shuld haue bē afrayd, nowe thou herest sauiour / and despeyrest of saluacion? And so forthe / to thende ye truste of saluacion shuld seme more certaine, bicause it wold seme vnlykely / that so great a lake of synnes / that all mā
               kynde was defiled with / shulde be purged &amp; clēsed with the blud of gottis &amp; calues / he the son of god got vp on the auter of ye crosse / and for our synnes he offred hym selfe most effectuall sacrifice to clēse all our synnes. And hangynge on the same crosse / he prayed for them that crucified hym / for them y• reuile &amp; rayle vpon hym: &amp; thynkest thou aknowlegyng thy syn / &amp; sorowfully besechyng his mercy he wyll deny ye forgyuenes? Trust to hym merciful / &amp; yu shalt fynde mercy, what thyng is it ye faith opteyneth nat of Christe? He that mistrusteth the phisiciō / is his owne let / that he can nat haue his helth agayne. Truely so moche god inclyneth to the prayers of wretches cryenge to hym / yt he gyueth

mercy at one other mans prayer, if he haue a good hope with hym. The Canane crieth to him, and her daughter is made holle: ye Centurion trusteth / and his seruant is restored to his helth: the maister of the Synagoge prayeth / &amp; his daught is reliued: the father desireth, &amp; his son is deliuered of a wicked dyuel. The apostles crie: O lorde saue vs / we perishe / and they be al saued. In many folkes he 
                  •
               aried nat the prayers of the mouth
                  •
                he seeth ye fayth of the cariers / &amp; sayth to the man sicke of ye palsey. Trust son thy synnes be forgyuē the. The mother only / &amp; they that went with her wept / &amp; ye yonge mā yt was deed ariseth / Martha and Mary do nothyng but wepe and Lazer relyueth. Mary the synner wepeth / she annoynteth &amp; kysseth hym / &amp; she hereth: Thy synnes be forgyuen the. He prayeth inough that knowlegeth his sickenes; he prayeth vehemētly that wepeth and hopeth. The womā diseased with the blody flixe / priuely toucheth the garment of Iesu / and forth with she felt ye power of mercy cōming forth. Like wise we rede yt many other were cured by touchȳg ye garmētes of Iesu. So redy his mercy is euery where / &amp; at euery occasiō he succoureth wretches. If yu darste nat call vpon Iesus / if thou canst nat touche Iesus / at lest touche priuely ye skyrt of his garmēt / go to som holy mā / in whom this vertue shyneth / that with his prayers he may cōmende the to our merciful lorde. For by them oftē tymes he putteth forth his power / beyng redy on euery syde to gyue saluacion to euery mā. For yt entēt he

came / this was the food, wherwith he was fedde, yt he might drawe synners to repētāce. And in the boke of Genesis also / whan wicked folke by theyr mischeuous dedes ꝓuoked the wrath of our lorde yet at the prayer of Abrahā our lorde had forgyuē many cities appoynted to be distroied / if he coude haue founde .x. good men amonge the people. The peple of Israel had deserued to be distroied / &amp; our lorde at the prayers of Moyses restrayneth the sworde of vengeāce. O blinde &amp; vnkynd folke / that regarde nat the mercy of our lorde / that is so metyng / &amp; so redy euery where: but more vnhappy be they that wyllingly despeyre of that / ye frely is offered them. He is lightly pleased / whiche nat willing is reuēged. For what other thȳg souneth this voyce: And why dye ye the house of Israel? Agayne in an other place he bewayleth / that he al the day had spred abrode his handes to the people without beleue / &amp; striuyng agaynst him. Agayne in Micheas: My people / what haue I done to ye / or wherin haue I greued the answere me? Lyke wyse in Esaie: What is hit that I ought to haue done more to my vyne / and haue nat done it? Our lorde doth euery thynge / that he myght saue vs / and shal we wylfully cast away hope of saluacion? In the gospell also he wepeth for Hierusalem / the whiche through obstinacy of syn caused distructiō of it selfe. Howe oft / sayth he / wold I haue gethered the to gether / as the henne gethereth her chekyns vnder her wynges / and ye wolde nat? Our most merciful lorde wepeth / that he can nat lefully

saue wretches / &amp; mystruste we hym / as though he wolde nat saue vs? In the gospell all the house rūbleth for ioye / that the childe that was deed / relyued agayn, yt ye perished, was recouered agayn. He the good father exhorteth the holle company of āgels and sainctes to reioyce al to gether, that one synner is brought agayne to penaunce, and thou wretche despeirest / and enuiest thyn owne saluaciō / and to our lorde fo passyng great ioye? Beleue we that he / whom the dethe of synners greueth / whom the conuertyng of wicked folke gladdeth / wyll deny forgyuenes to them, yt be sory &amp; amēde? He calleth euery body to the brydale / he wyl haue his house full / yea he compelleth the blynd &amp; lame to entre in to his house. Why tariest thou behinde wretche? Why canst nat thou be drawen from the draffe of swyne? Why striuest thou agaȳst ye mercy of our our lorde? Christ is the wisedome of god. This wisedome as sayth Solomon departed out of her fathers house / came in to this worlde, preacheth opēly / and her voyce is herde in the stretes. She crieth in the frōte of multitudes / in ye wickettes of ye cite gates, she ꝓnoūseth out her wordes / sayeng: Howe lōge wyl ye loue childhed ly
                  •
               tell babes / and foles, couet thynges noyfull to them / and vndiscrete hate counnyng? Turne you to my correctiō. Beholde I wyl put forth my spiri
                  •
               e to you and shall shewe you my wordes. What thynge is more folishe / than for vayne transitory thinges to be depriued of euerlastȳg goodes? What is greatter wysedome / than by short sufferance to get immortalite?

Therfore they be all mad that cōtinue in synne: they be wyse that chaunge theyr lyfe in to better. With what great labours serche we out the most vile thyng amonge meta
                  •
               s / and so great treasure offered and frely offered we despisen / or yt is more folyshe / we despeyrē? God is riche in mercy. The treasure of humayn riches is cōsumed in gyuynge away: the treasure of mercy can nat be consumed. And this wyll I adde, that I may the more put euery body from despeyre of pardone. God hath boūde his fayth to man / and as Paule 
                  •
               ayth / he can nat deny hym 
                  •
               elfe. He refuse
                  •
               h nat to be rebuked / if he ꝑforme 
                  •
               at / that he ꝓmyseth. For so he speketh in Esaie to the people defyled on euery syde: Be ye washed / be clene / take away frō my syght your yl thoughtes / cesse to do wickedly / lerne to do well / seke iugemēt / succour the oppressed / deale truly with ye orphlin / defende ye wydow / and come ye &amp; rebuke me / saythe our lorde. Thou herest 
                  •
               ynner / what thyng els requyreth our merciful lorde / but onely chāgyng of thy lyfe? And lest thenormite of synnes ouerpresse thy mynde / here the forgyuenes of them all redy. If your synnes sayth he / were as skarlette / they shall be made as white as snowe: and if they were as red as oker / they shalbe as white as wolle. If ye wil &amp; ye may here me / ye shall eate the goodes of ye erthe? Who is so mad / that wyll nat be saued? What is more easy / thā to here our most louyng father / nothing cōmandyng / but that ꝑteyneth to our felicite? If 
                  •
               e wyll sayth he / and ye may here. No man may

saue hym y• wyl nat. Saluaciō is by fayth / fayth is vy hering. The worde is helthfull in thy harte and in thy mouth. Only shut nat ye eares of thy
                  •
                hart. Nowe if a king shuld say thus to his ēmies or to suche as be cōuicted of high treason: What so euer is done or was entended hitherto, I forgyue it you al, mercy is redy for al, so they frō thēs forth wolde absteyne frō lyke yl dedes: wolde nat euery body speke of ye kinges wōderfull mercy, yt neither cruelly punisheth their bodies, nor cōfisketh their goodes? But god yea with reward entiseth vs to amēde our life. Ye shal eate sayth he, the goodes of the erthe. But they be vtterly vnworthy to haue ye fruicion of goodes of this worlde / that by theyr vngratious dedes offende the gyuer of all. But o howe moche more precyous is it that ye gospell ꝓmiseth: I wyl gyue you a newe hart / I wyl gyue you a newe spirite / wherby of the dyuels thrals / ye shall be made the chyldren of god / wherby y
                  •
                shalbe made mēbres of myn only begotten sonne / &amp; wherby ye shal entre into the heretage of the heuenly kyngdome. This is saythe he / my welbeloued sonne / here hym. O thou Iewe / why turn
                  •
               st thyn eares frō trouth / &amp; turnest to the tales of the Talmudicens / &amp; Deuterotis? Thou vnwyse philosopher / why shuttest thyn eares against this techer, &amp; herkenest to Plato and Aristotel? Why herest thou vnhappy progeny of Eue ye serpent with vayne promises entisynge the to distruction / &amp; herest nat the sonne of god callyng the to the company of euerlastynge felicite? Do penance sayth he / 

the kyngdome of heuen is at hande. The son promiseth / the father pledgeth it / the holy gost in the mean while is gyuen as an ernest peny: and doutest thou to take &amp; ēbrace so great felicite offred ye? And there is none other voice of thapostles thā of our lorde, Do penance, &amp; let eche of you be baptised in the name of Iesu Christ in remissiō of your synnes / &amp; ye shal receyue the gyft of the holy gost. And a litel aft: Kepe you frō this vngratious nacion / yt ye may be saued: leaue the spotted, fylthy, wretched lyfe / and take euerlastyng lyfe. Souldiours, publicans, harlottes, idolworshippers, mā
               kyllers, nigromācers, baudes, aduoutrers, rūne hither. None is shut without / the passage to mercy lyeth egally open to all. The lyfe past is nat regarded / so one be repētant. Nor thou shuldest nat suppose this mercy of our lorde / to stretche no farther thā batisme, thoughe Mōtanus shut ye churche dores against them that slyde after baptisme / our lorde neuer shutteth the dore of ye heuēly kingdome. The entrāce in to the churche by baptisme is ones gyuen / the figure wherof the arke of No
                  •
                beareth / but by the mercy of god ye seconde bourde is left to eche after the shyp wracke / yea to come agayne in to ye arke by penāce. For baptyme is nat twise takē / as the deth of Christe is nat renewed / but the water of teares doth remayne / wherwith now the fylthy sinnes ben washed away, ye sope of holsome contricion remaineth / &amp; the herbe of Bo
               
                  •
               ith. Truly they ought / to whom ones all synnes were frely forgyuen, and that buried with Christe

by baptisme rose with hym agayne in a newe life, to cōtynue with hym in that great gyft / that they receiued. But our pitefull &amp; mercifull lorde knowyng the weakenes of mans nature / he wylled remedy of penance to be redy for eche euen to the lyues ende. But bicause the day of deth is certayne to none / all ought to watche / that they despise nat ye goodnes of god: but if they hap to slide agayne / by and by they shulde hast to remedy / before ye disease by cōtinuance waxe vncurable. Some ī olde tyme with right great peril forbare baptisme euē to the last day of theyr lyfe / whom some called bad christiens / and some / yll watered / as christiēs nat very true: but with more ieꝑdy ye synner ꝓlōgeth the remedy of penance / that is euery where redy. The christener is nat alway present / but lyeng in thy bed thou mayst cōfesse thyn vnrightousnes to our lorde / and purpose to amende thy lyfe. One is nat alway present to washe thy body: teares be alway present, with whiche thou mayst washe ye fylthes of thy soule. And nat without a cause a dout is / whether ye baptisme be effectual / wherby whā ther is no hope of life / and were in pāges of deth / were rather spryncled with water than baptised. For they shewed yt they wolde a synned cōtinually if they myght haue lyued styll. But moche more southly great lerned men doute / whether penāce be fruteful / yt is ꝓlōged a purpose / nowe deꝑtyng hēce they take it / and wold nat take it / except deth cōpelled them. For lyke as groūde ofte moysted wt heuēly raine, brȳgeth forth naught els to his tyller / 

than thornes &amp; wydes / is cursed &amp; caste in to ye fyre: so god other while for his goodnes obstacly despised, endueth them with a peruersed mynde. Wherfore ye surest way most dere brethern̄ is / nat to ꝓlonge the mendyng of the lyfe / but by &amp; by at the voyce of our lorde, callyng vs to do of ye old mā with his dedes and desyres / lest our lord so oft nat herde / wyll nat here vs agayne callynge to hym. Dredeful is ye voice, wherwith he thretneth them that wyll nat here him mercifully callȳg. Bicause sayth he I called you / &amp; ye turned away: I reched forth my hāde / &amp; ther was none that wold se it: ye despised al my coūsayle / and set naught by my rebukes: I also wyl laugh and scorne ī your distruction, whā it shal fall on you that ye drad. Whan sodayne calamite ouerthroweth / &amp; ruine as a tēpest dassheth downe / whan trouble &amp; greffe assayleth: than they wyll call on me / &amp; I wyl nat here them. They shal arise yerly / and they shal nat fynde me, bicause they hated my lernyng / and wolde nat cō
               ceyue the drede of their lorde / &amp; wolde nat rest vpō my coūsaile, and wold withdrawe frō al my correctiō. God punisheth diuers wayes, yt he might correct vs. At last whā our obstaclenes hath ouercōe al remedies he forsaketh vs as desperate / and leaueth vs wt our owne fre wyl. Like as a phisiciō assaynge al yt his crafte can to put away the disease / whan he seeth the pacient forsake all medicins / at last he leaueth hym with his sickenes / as he that wyll nat lyue. Mercy sayth the psalme / &amp; iugemēt I wyl synge to ye. The day of iugemēt abydeth al

after they shal be departed this lyfe. As longe as this lyfe lasteth, there is hope of mercy. Therfore while thou lyuest beseche our lorde mercy. But they that lie dyeng / or they that extreme olde age opresseth / nowe in a maner lyue no more. Here ye coūsayle of the wyse Hebrewe / what euer thou be that from day to day drawest the lynde of wickednes / and makest no ende of synnynge: Turne the to our lorde saith he / and forsake thy sinnes. Pray the face of our lorde and mynishe thyn offences. Returne to our lorde, and turne away frō thyn vngratiousnes / and hate cursynge: and knowe the iustices and iugementes of god / and stande in the lot of proposicion and speche of almyghty god / go in to the partes of the iuste worlde with ye lyuyng &amp; gyuyng confession to god. Thou shuldest nat abyde in the errour of wicked folke / cōfesse y• before dethe. The confession of one deed perisheth as nothyng. Thou shalt confesse the liuyng. Alyue and in helth thou shalt confesse / &amp; preyse god / and glorifie in his mercies / o howe great is the mercy of our lorde / and his fauour to them that returne to hym. Thou herest ye great mercy of god is redy / but that is if thou aliue &amp; in heale wylt be cōfessed to our lorde. But what shal we say of them / whose bodyes be vnable to synne / &amp; yet ye mynde putteth nat away the synfull appetite: and whan by reason of age the body is nere deed / that they can nat do wycked and fylthy actes / yet they leaue nat to speke leudly? Howe shulde they be confessed to our lorde alyue / that leaue sooner to lyue thā to synne?

But thou yonge mā in thy flowryng age / why ꝓlōgest the mēdyng of thy lyfe / dayes / monethes / &amp; yeres? If thy body were diseased with the dropsy / and thou haddest before ye redy a certayne sure remedy for yt disease / woldest yu say / The next yere I wyl heale my sickenes? I knowe wel yu woldest nat be so mad / but yu woldest haste most gredily to be healed. And ī ye diseases of ye soule moche more perillous / tariest / driuest forthe frō day to day / frō that day to that / yea thou defferrest thy saluacion to ye day of thy dethe? And who is thy surete, that thou shalt lyue tyl to morowe? But these thinges be nat spokē / to thende that any shulde despeyre of forgyuenes / but to thentēt we wold wrest frō 
               
                  •
               che the careles continuance in synne. There is synne / yt neither in this worlde nor in the worlde to come, is forgyuē. God forbyd yt any of vs shulde swarue so far wyde. And therfore ye most sure thyng is to eschewe synne. The next is, that by &amp; by we put it away by penance / that is wrought vnskylfully. A good man falleth .vij. tymes on a day, but he riseth agayne: al though this be spoken by veniall syns. And therfore our lorde ofte tymes thretneth vs sharply in holy scripture / lest on trust of forgyuenes redy / we shuld walowe in to the myer of vngratious dedes. And therfore ye plaister of penāce is nat gyuen, that we wylfully shulde continue in our disease / but lest he whiche perchaunce falleth shuld be lost for euer. In Amos our lorde oft thondreth agaynst thre or foure wyckednessis: Shall nat I abhorre them? It is wyckednes to thynke

yll. Here by &amp; by we shulde take repentance / but 
                  〈◊〉
                is greatter wickednes to wyl to ꝑfourme it yt thou dyddest mynde: at lest frō ye grice y• fote shuld step to better. But the greuoust offence is / fylthyly to ꝑfourme it yt thou dyddest wickedly purpose. And here we be neither sory nor amende / but we put to it ye fourth wickednes / accustomyng vs in 
                  •
               yns / &amp; heapyng syns vpō syns. Nowe at this poȳt may nat our lord wel abhorre vs? Yes truly / nere yt his mercy passed his iustice. Beholde what foloweth after so sharpe thretnȳges in ye same ꝓphet: This sayth our lorde to the house of Israel: Seke / &amp; ye shal fynd me / seke your lorde &amp; come. Let vs here our lorde thretnyng / lest we shuld syn: let vs here our lorde reclaymyng vs / yt we despeyre nat. Orels wo to vs if he shuld do to vs that he thretneth by the ꝓphete: and after the thyrde or fourth wickednes he shulde turne away frō vs his mercy / &amp; leaue vs alone to our wyl. Yea with many of vs it shulde go yuel / if our lorde shulde turne his face away after the thousande wickednes. But by &amp; by as his rightousnes beginneth to waxe rigorous. Mercy steppeth forth &amp; sayth: O lord god be merciful: I pray the / who shal lyft vp Iacob for he is a babe? And agayne: O lorde god I pray the cesse who shall reyse vp Iacob for he is a babe? Thus Mercy our best defender pledeth the cause of our frailnes. Nowe here howe redy forgyuenes is to one repentyng &amp; amendyng. Our lorde sayth he / hath had pite vpon hym. It shal nat be / sayd our lorde. Ye se howe soone he thretnynge vengeance

repenteth, if we truly wolde repent our misdedes. It shall nat be / sayd our lorde. I praye you, what mother is so lightly pleased with her child? Therfore syth we haue a lorde so easy to please / &amp; an aduocatrice so effectual / what thing is there / why any despeyryng of hym selfe / shulde eyther cōtinue in sinnes / or with Iudas flee to hange hym selfe? Euen for the same purpose our lorde by al meanes myndyng our saluacion / suffered most excellent &amp; most approued mē to fall in greuous synnes / that by theyr example he myght corage &amp; cōforte vs to hope of perdone. What thinge in holy scripture is more laudable thā kynge Dauid? He was a kyng he was a ꝓphet, he was a mā to goddes mynde / of his linage Christe was ꝓmised. But into howe foule / in to howe many folde a synne dyd so great a mā fall? He hereth of Nathan ye rebuke and cruell thretnynges of our lorde. But Dauid with two wordes turneth all this anger of god in to mercy. He sayd: I haue offended agaynst my lorde: And forthe with Nathan sayde: Our lorde also hathe transported thy syn thou shalt nat dye. The thretninges be of a length / yt he may correct / but howe swyft is the voyce of mercy: Thou shalt nat dye? Like wise by Esaie Ezechias he
                  •
               eth: Thou shalt dye, &amp; shalt nat lyue. Ezechias wept &amp; made great lamentacion. The ꝓphet the messanger of dethe was nat yet gone halfe the kynges court / but the mercy of our lorde called him agayne, sayeng: Returne backe / and say to Ezechias capitayne of my people: This sayth our lorde ye god of Dauid thy

father / I haue herde thy prayers / &amp; haue seen thy wepyng / and I haue healed the. The thyrde day after this thou shalt go in to the tēple of our lorde
                  •
                The thyrde boke of kynges wytnesseth ye same of Achab. There was nat suche an other as Achab / whiche was solde to thentēt he might do mischife in ye sight of our lorde. And he hereth: Thou has
                  •
                kylde / &amp; more ouer hast possessed: As whā he had slayne Na both he occupied his vineyarde: but a
                  •
                last he was so afrayde with ye cruel thretnynges yt he rēte his clothes / &amp; ware a sherte of heare, he fa
                  •
               sted, &amp; slept in wollen, &amp; wandred hāgynge downe his heed. A
                  •
               hab was froward, he had oft despise
                  •
                our lorde rebukyng hym, he had heaped syns vpō syns: and at last he was rather feared with drede of mischefes hangyng ouer hym / than myndyng to repēt &amp; amende: and yet our lorde of excedynge mercy speketh to Hely: Hast nat seen how Achab hath hūbled hym before me: bycause he hath hū
               bled him 
                  •
               elfe for my sake, I wyl bringe in no mischiefe in his days. If yt might of false repētāce b
                  •
                so great / that it can wrest the reuēgyng sword out of the hāde of god / what shal the mynde do, truly changed in to a cōtrary affection and nowe nat for drede of punishemēt, but for the loue of god abhorreth yt he miswrought: For that entent he suffred Peter / whiche he had apointed chiefe of his churche / opēly to fall. He wept only / &amp; opteined mercy. Whan he delyuered his shepe to hym to fede / for whiche he suffred deth / dyd he cast in his tethe / y• offence of thrise forsakyng our lorde? No forsothe / 

for nowe al that was so washed away with teares that there remayned nat a steppe in our mercifull lordes remēbrance. Paule ye ꝑsecuter of our lordis churche was ouerthrowen, &amp; was made ye teacher of naciōs. We haue great examples of them that synned / and eke of them that repented / we ought nat by example of any to be ꝓuoked to synne / lest we shulde tēpte our lorde / but if any shulde hap to be attrapped by synne / he hath examples of repē
               tāce / lest he shuld despeire. But they do waywardly / that wyll nat folowe hym in repētyng / whiche they folowed in synnynge. Howe many princes be ther that smyle at theyr auoutres and māslaughters for the example of Dauid? Al though in Dauid were so many excellent vertues / yt this offence myght haue ben forgyuē in recōpēce of them: but wolde to god lyke as they folowe hym offendyng / they wold so folowe hym eke repentyng. He spred abrode his synne through al naciōs of the worlde: and despised ye delectacions of the court / &amp; for purpul he weareth a sherte of heare / and as bread he 
                  •
               ateth ashes / &amp; mingleth his drinke with wepȳg: euery night he wassheth his bed with teares / and moysteth his couerled with weping. And he was nat ashamed to say and synge this verse of penāce to al synners: Haue mercy vpō me lorde after thy great mercy. And after the multitude of thy mercies put awaye my wickednes. He was iuge / and gaue sentēce of deth agaynst hym selfe. For greatly disdaynyng he saythe: Our lorde lyueth / for he is the childe of dethe that hath done this thynge.

He coude nat more euidently be condemned: than by his owne worde. God was iuge / and yet as the ꝑsone were changed / he cōmitted the iugement to hym that was gylty. The iuge was taken with a trip / and he ouercame that cōmitted to hym ye iugemēt: Dauid was happily ouercome / god ouercame mercifully / whā he shewed ye synner to hym selfe / that had forgot hym selfe. Before as a cōquerour / and drōken with vnhappy prosperite / he accomplished his pleasure with ye womā yt he loued, he delited in his moste swete childe / but whan he was conuerted to our lorde / than at laste he sawe where he was: and what difference was bitwene a rightous mā &amp; an vnrightous, like as an other prophecy teacheth. Whā a sinner with al his hart aknowlegeth his fylthynes / &amp; cōfesseth hym selfe worthy of punyshemēt / thā our lorde is iustified / and ouercometh whan he is iuged / that is / whan he offreth the iugemēt to man as to be iuged him selfe. But they that ordeyne theyr owne rightousnes / make god in a maner vniuste &amp; a lier / whiche wyl that his mercy shuld be knowen in euery mā, and reioyceth to turne our vnrightousnes ī to his glory: seyng where synne was plentiful there his fre liberalite abūdeth. The olde Adam dyd nat so, but whan he was called to confession / he laide the blame on his wife. Like wise she called to cōfessiō
               
                  •
                blamed the serpent. If they coude haue song the songe of Dauid, God haue mercy on me, they had nat ben banished paradise. Cain nat goyng out of kynde / what sayth he / prouoked of our lorde to repent.

Am I my brothers keper? If he had sayd, I haue synned / haue mercy: and if he had sayde hit with al his harte, the mercy of god was redy. There is a carnall sorowe / that engendreth deth / suche as Iudas had: but agayne there is a godly sorowe / that bryngeth forth saluacion and sure ioye. Paule tenderly louedde all his / yet he reioyseth that he had caste the Corinthies in suche a sorowe / he damned / that had a do with his fathers wyfe / as out of suche sorow / as after a bytter playster foloweth continual ioye. And in ye mean while sure hope of saluacion myngl
                  •
               d with repentance tēpereth the bitternes of the sorowe. So Dauid / whan he had simply confessed his synne, and ye deserued wreache of god, herke howe moche hope he conceyued of the mercy of god: O lorde sayde he / spryncle me with isope / and I shalbe clensed / thou shalt washe me / and I shalbe made whiter than ye snowe. Nat of his owne good dedes, but by sprin
                  •
               
               lyng of ye īmaculate lābes blud he promiseth hym selfe purenes, and whan he aknowleged hym selfe frō his mothers wombe with spottes defyl
                  •
               d / yet out of yt washing he hopeth to haue fairenes of innocency / that shulde passe the snowe in whitenes. And he dothe nat only hope to opteyne innocēcy agayne / but also that ye wo of penāce shuld turne in 
                  •
               o spiritual ioye. He sayth: Thou shalt gyue ioy &amp; gladnes to my herȳg / &amp; my hūble bones shal lepe for ioye. Yelde to me the gladnes of thy saluacion, and cōfyrme me with thy principal spirite. O wō
               derfull trust of a synner, &amp; yet more largely he promyseth

hym selfe somwhat: And my tonge sayth he / shal shewe outwarde with great mirth thy iustice. O lorde thou shalt open my lyppes / and my mouth shal shewe thy preyse. Whan he hath proued the mercy of our lorde so great / he wyl eke exhort other yt they shuld repent &amp; amende. So our lorde sayd to Peter: And thou cōuerted somtyme confirme thy bretherne. Dauid shulde haue perished / if he had cōmytted hym selfe to Iustice / but he in that part to weake called vpō mercy, &amp; therfore the mercies of our lorde he syngeth for euer. They that plede matters amōge men / as ofte as theyr cause is in ieoꝑdy, if they may, they remoue it in to an other courte / all though they be in dout whether they shall fynde there a more egall iuge. And truly may hap other while / he that appeleth may appele to his dāmage. But to vs moost dere bretherne / hit is a thynge fer fer more sure / nat to stryue with the iustice of god / that is / nat to caste vp our heles agaynst the pricke / but by and by to calle vpon his mercy. And truly in mennes iugementes / they say there is nothynge surer / than i
                  •
                we may by some colour clene deny the cryme / yt is layde agaynst vs: and the rhetoriciens teache the most miserable state of a cause to be: whiche they cleape deprecacion / whan the defendant sayth / I haue offēded / forgyue me. Here cōtrary wise there is nothynge surer for vs than wylfully to aknowlege / what so euer we haue myswrought / and to beseche ye iuge of mercy. Hither syth the goodnes of god in all holy scripture so louyngly prouoketh

vs / sith the exāples of so many noble men exhorte vs hither / why shuld any be foūde / whiche despe
                  •
               
               ryng of hym selfe had leauer waxe olde in synnes? There is nothyng ī god / that is of simple nature / that shulde striue with other, and yet if we behold those thynges that chance vs / a stryfe shulde seme to be betwene goddes iustice and his mercy. Iustice calleth to punyshement / but mercy as saynth Iames sayth, leapeth vp agaynst iugement as a conquerour. Who dyd euer crye: Iesu haue mercy: but by and by he opteined mercy? The Cananee crieth: Good lorde haue mercy / &amp; her daughter is made holle: Euery synner eke shulde crye: Good lorde haue mercy / and his soule shalbe healed. He the blinde begger crieth: O son of Dauid haue mercy / and his cloke cast away he receyued his sight. Let vs eke crye: Iesu the sonne of god haue mercy on vs / let vs crye strongely &amp; cōstātly euen amydmōge the hourlynge multitudes of yl imaginacions / &amp; he of this worldly beggers shall make vs enheritours of the heuenly kyngdome. Who so euer seketh cōmodites of this life, is blȳd, is a begger, &amp; ī a patched cloke beggeth a halfe peny of the people. They yt seke to get a kyngdome / yea though they seme to go about a great thyng / they do no
                  •
               hyng els but wretchedly begge a half-peny of a multitude. They yt hunte for honours / and dignites / be they neuer so great / they crie to ye people / Take pite, gyue an halfepeny. But if any wylerie: Iesu lorde haue mercy / he is redy to gyue vs hym selfe. Our lorde tarieth / he calleth y• to

hym / art nat vnhappy but if yu rūne? why tariest in thyne vnhappy clothes? The alter of mercy is open / and thou tournest thy selfe to the bondes o
                  •
                madnes. The sainctuary of goddis mercy is opened / and thou fliest in to the hurlepyt of vnhappy despeyre. Thy sauiour recheth the his hāde / and thou turnest away thy face. Heuen is open vnto the / and thou rūnest downe heedlynge in to helle. The lappe of goddis goodnes is hold open to the / and thou fliest to the vnhappy halter. The thefe on the crosse hereth / This day thou shalte be with me in paradise / and thou gyueste and byndest thy selfe to hell. But now it is tyme to fulfyl that I lastely promised / by what meanes the mercy of god may be soonest got. For of prayers / wepynge / fastyng / wearing of heare / &amp; ashes / yt is of a contrite hart / is nowe spokē here and there through al the sermō. And truly these thynges opteyne mercy of god: But well doyng to our neyghbour wresteth it out / if I may so say. Suche as euery man wyll haue god be to him / let him shewe him selfe suche to his neyghbour. The grekes prouerbe saythe: Fauour getteth fauour. But with vs mercy getteth mercy. Luce .vj. Gyue, and to you shalbe gyuen: Forgyue / &amp; ye shalbe forgyuē: And by what measure ye haue met to your neyghboure / by the same god shall met to you. And I call mercy or pite / nat only whan vengeance is forgyuen / or nede of our neighbur eased, but what so euer good dede is done to our brother with a good mȳde. He that teacheth him that erreth / that correcteth the misdoer / 

and other while he that with strokes chastifeth one synnyng, if he do it with a christē affectiō, he doth the warke of mercy vpon his neyghbour, he that exhorteth them y• shrynke from their good purpose / that cōfort the wofull / that bring the despeyred / in to good hope he is merciful toward his neyghbour / and eyther he recōpēceth or ꝓuoketh the mercy of god. And truely it is vnsyttynge the mercy of Christiens to be of lytell price &amp; cōmon. A paynym wyl gyue almes to a begger / any man wil helpe his frēde in ieoꝑdy, ye gentiles eke ꝑdone some offēces. But what our mercy ought to be ye gospel teacheth: Be merciful / yt ye may be ye children of your father / that is in heuen. If ye mercy of god toward vs be of ye cōmō sort / mercy of ye cō
               mon sort suffiseth vs toward our neighbour. But if he cōmande his sonne to shyne on good and yll: &amp; suffereth so riche hauiour of this worlde to be cō
               mune to the wel disposed and wicked / if we wyl appere his true childrē / let vs be weldoers / nat only towarde our frendes, kyns folke, and that wel deserued it, but also towarde strāgers, ye to our foes and yt yuell deserued it. If god for vs idol worshippers / and children of helle gaue his only sonne, semeth it a great thyng if we agayn do good to our ennemy, whiche is our brother, in that he is a reasonable creature? And if our rightous lord for our synnes offred vp hym selfe / in ye auter of ye trosse / semeth it a great thyng / if we forgyue our neygh
               
                  •
               our the wrōge he dyd to vs? Howe dare a synner crye / Lorde haue mercy vpon me / yt denyeth mercy

to his brother? Shal nat he worthily here this of ye gospell: O naughty seruant / I haue forgyuē the al thy duty / oughtest nat thou to haue pite on thy felowe se
                  •
               uant with the? What good turne so
                  •
               euer we do to our neyghbour / our lorde suffreth i
                  •
                to be ascribed vnto hym / whan he hath nede of no mā: &amp; al be it yt god hath fyrst bestowed it al on vs most heapyngly / what good so euer to our power we haue bestowed or done to our bretherne / yet as though he were boūde for our good dedes toward our neighbur, he ꝓmiseth to yeld vs agayne good mesure / with moche ēcrease / full &amp; wel heaped vp
                  •
                Is it nat good mesure / whā for herboring a poore man our lorde receiueth the in to the kyngdome of heuē? The best way to waxe riche is to waxe pore by suche liberalite. The wyse men of this worlde wyl nat suffre their money to rust in their chestis / but they leaue it with the bankers / that by vsury they may get more to it. They that wil be riche o
                  •
                heuenly goodes / they must haue ado with ye most liberal v
                  •
               urer. We call them happy that be ryche / and in the gospel the merciful be called happy / bycause they shall opteyne mercy. He playeth ye vsurer with our lorde sayth he the wyse Hebrew / that pitieth ye poure folke &amp; he shal quite hym agayne. And the prophet sayth: Redeme thy synnes with almes dedes: bicause as the prince of thapostles sayth: Charite couereth the multitude of 
                  •
               innes. Ye here th
                  •
               xchange: but it is with a great luker. Like wise he the misticall synger: Happy is that man that piteeth &amp; lēdeth. Therfore with god he

playeth a poynt of vsury / who so euer for the loue of god doth his neyghbour a good turne. Ye here the exchange / ye here the encreasyng / ye here the redemyng. Who so euer hurteth his neyghbou
                  •
                / is in danger of hym that he harmed: Who so euer to his power helpeth his neighour / byndeth hym that he doth the good turne to. Do nat aske vēgeance on hym that offended the, but make exchāge with god: forgyue thy neyghbour a fewe &amp; lyght offences / and god of couenant wyll forgyue the al thȳ. Desire no reward agayne of thy neighbour / to whom thou dyddest a good turne / but aske it of god what so euer thou disposest well / &amp; he for goodes transitory / wyll rewarde the euerlastynge.
            There be dyuers sacrifices / w
                  •
               th whiche god is pleased / spirituall hȳmes / songes / prayers / watchinges / fastinges / homely rayment: but no maner sacrifice is more effectuall than mercy toward our brother. Go saith our lorde / and lerne what it is: I wyl haue mercy &amp; nat sacrifice. He dāpneth nat sacrifices / but he pferreth mercy aboue them al. The same yt our lorde Iesus wit safeth to teche vs wt his owne mouth in ye gospel / he taught lōge before by the mouth of Michee ye ꝓphet. For whā our lorde had rebuked the īuincible obstaclenes of ye people ī yls / ye people being thoughtful by what mean they myght apease god / rightously ꝓuoked with so many cursed dedes / sayth: What thynge worthy may I offre to god? Shal I bow my knees to almighty god? What shuld I offre to him sacrifices, and yerelyng calues? May he be pleased

with a thousande wethers / or many thousandes of fat gottes? Shal I gyue my fyrst begottē sōne for myn offēce / the frute of my wombe for ye synne of my soule? Hitherto speketh ye people / vnderst
                  •
               
               dynge that no sacrifice coude of man be offered to purge away synnes / yea if aboue many thousāde wethers / he wolde offre vp his fyrst bogottē sōne / to him most dere, but the prophet sheweth a more effectuall sacrifice / wher with by and by the āger of god is apeased. O man / I wyll shewe y• / what is good / and what our lorde wold haue of y•, thou muste do iugement / &amp; loue mercy / &amp; thoughtfully walke with thy lord god. What is to do iugemēt? to hurt no man, what is to loue mercy / to do them good yt deserue it nat. Paule thapostle more ouer addeth somwhat to ye preise of mercy. If I shuld sayth he / gyue my body to be burned / and haue no charite / it auayleth me nothynge. Abrahā ꝓfer
                  •
               d a great thyng / that was redy to offre his only son in sacrafice, that he loued specially but he profreth more / if any for ye loue of god deliuereth his owne body to be burned. And yet charite is more acceptable than that sacrifice. And what thynge els is charite towarde our neighbour but mercy? Therfore sythe all we continually in all thynges nede ye mercy of god / our study ought styl to be / howe one of vs may mercifully helpe an other / &amp; one with an other bearȳg ye burthēs to gether, we may fulfyl ye lawe of Christe / that rather requireth mercy than sacrifice / and wylleth vs to redeme his mercy with mercy shewed on our neyghbour. But as

my mynde excedyngly reioyseth whā I cast with my selfe, how great ye mercy of our lord is toward vs / and howe redy for vs he wold it shuld be, so an huge great sorowe ꝑceth myn harte / as ofte as I behold inwardly / how scant the mindȳg of mercy is amōge Christiens. If we were truly mercifull our liberalite wold reche euen to the Turkes / we shuld cast coles of fyre vpō theyr heedes, that they ouercome by our goodnes / at last shulde come to ye felowship of our religion. Nowe we Christiēs by warres, roberies, theftes, oppressions, more cruelly greue &amp; vexe Christiens / than any wyld beast greueth the ennemy therof. If thou beholde the luker / what other thynge do we but one lyue by deuourynge an other / after the maner of fyshes? Who is nat redy for smal auaile to begyle his brother / whose nede he oughte to succoure. Nowe by our brothers pouerte we go about to get our auā
               tage / our brother for faute of meate dyeth, ye more ieoꝑdy I se hym in / the derer I sel to hym in that he nedeth. Howe vnlowly is our stately fiersenes agaynst our inferiours? how great is the rebelliō of thinferiours agaynst the superiours / how feld or in no place is pure charite? All places be full of braulinges, detractiōs, &amp; backebitinges. And we nat only quite a lytel wrong with great vēgeance / but wilfully harme them yt dyd vs no hurte. And the mean while we mynde nat / howe great mercy our lorde hath poured on vs: whiche he wyll calle agayne / except we poure it agayne on our neyghbour that we receyued. If ye seke saith ye ꝓphet / 

seke. If we seke the mercy of god / we must seke it truly &amp; with al our hert. Turne you &amp; come. She turneth her to vs, if we wil turne to her. The mercy of god came to vs / whan the sonne of god descended downe in to erthe: let vs go to her agayne. Our most mercifull lorde inclineth hym / that he may assoyle an aduoutrer / let vs agayne lyfte vp our affectiō to him bowyng to vs. The fyrst grice is, to cast away synne. So phisicions fyrst purge the body / that after they may put in better iuces. So thou synner fyrst cast out of the mynde yll affections / that stryue agaynst god: lechery / couettousnes / riot / pride / anger. Whan the cōtynuer in synne besecheth the mercy of god / doth he nat as though an ēnemy armed / holding his sworde and bucler in his hande / wolde desyre peace? He that asketh receyueth / he that seketh fyndeth: to hym that knocketh the dore is opened. If ye aske mercy / aske it truly: if ye seke, seke aryght: and if ye knocke at the dore of mercy knocke truly. Wyll ye haue example of one truely askyng mercy? He the prodigal childe asketh it aright / but yt was whan he had lefte ye hogges / &amp; whā he was returned to his father. O father I haue offended in heuē and afore the, make me as one of thy labourers. Now here ye publicā / yt for the cōscience of his syns dare nat lyft vp his eies heuēward / dare nat come nere ye auter / but stādȳg a far, he knocketh on his brest &amp; sayth: Lorde haue mercy on me a synner. He asketh whose affectiōs turned cōtrary / of a drōkerd is made sobre / of a rebaude chaste / of a gluttō tē
               perate

/of a bribour beneficial / of a lewde speker a good sayer / of a dissēbler a playn man / of a crabbishe a lowly mā / of cruell mercifull. He knocketh y• with deuoute importunatnes ī a maner cōpelleth ye mercy of god / neuer cessynge to exercise warkes of mercy on his neighbour. Crie to our lord: haue mercy: but &amp; thou wylt be herd / se that thou here hym agayne. He crie
                  •
               h in his membres / the sicke &amp; nedy. Here it thou stoppe thyn eare / he wyll nat herethe agayne calling to hym. He is refreshed in his poure folkes / in them he thrysteth / hungreth / sickeneth / &amp; pyn
                  •
               th: in them he is dispised &amp; offē
               ded
                  •
                But more vnshamefastly saith he to our lord: Haue mercy vpō me, whiche only will nat refreshe his brother / but also vexeth hym vndeserued / oppresseth ye weake / betrayeth the innocent, spoyleth the poure / begyleth the harmeles. Continuynge in 
                  •
               hose dedes / he calleth on the mercy of our lorde in veyne. If they that do nat refr
                  •
               she Christ ī his mēbres / shal here: Go ye cursed folkes in to ye fyre euerlastyng: What shall they here that reuile / 
                  •
               pyt at / mocke / beate / punyshe / sklander / &amp; slee Christe in his mēbres? If I be nat disceyued / ther is a sē
               tence amonge the mymes puplians / worthy for a christen mā: In gyuyng he receyued a benefit / yt gaue hym yt was worthy to haue it. Why styckest at it thou froward ponderer of an others dignite? He gyueth to one worthy of it / yt gyueth to the mē
               bre of Christe: he gyueth to one worthy / yt gyueth to his brother. And so forth / he gyueth to one worthy / who so euer for Iesus loue gyueth to a poure

creature. If thou seke wynnyng / play the vsur
                  ••
                with him: if thou drede peyne / thou hast wherby thou mayst redeme it. After sharpe rebuke / what sayth our lorde in ye gospel? Yet gyue almes sayth he / and se all thinges be clene vnto you. Whan 
                  •••
               pest of the see is redy to drenche the / thou styckest nat to cast thy marchandise in to the see (be hit neuer so precious) to saue thy life: Whan the vengeance of god hangeth ouer the / doth it greue the to dispose a lyttell money on thy neyghbour? What woldest yu leaue vndone / if thy house were a fyre
                  •
                But what burnyng is so dredefull as the anger of god? Whan his anger sodaynly flameth vp / wylt nat vse the remedy that is shewed to quenche hit
                  •
                What, wylt thou say? Who sheweth hit? That very good man Sirach: Water sayth he / quencheth flamyng fyre / and almes dede withstandeth synnes. Almes dede knoweth nat bosting / other wise she loseth her name. They that gyue almes with a trumpe blowynge before / they gyue nat almes but bye glory. For conclusion almes before god is whan thy lyfte hāde knoweth nat what thy right hande doth. Put sayth he / thy treasure in the cō
               mandementes of god / and it shall profit the more thā gold: close thy almes / in ye poure mans hart / and it shall delyuer the frō all yuell. Thy treasure is neuer so sure buryed or hydde / as in the poure mans hart. It is far better locked ther in than in thy yron chestis. Forget that thou hast gyuen: let nat ye poure man knowe / if it may be / who is ye autor of the good dede. Whan thy nede requireth an

intercessor / the almes shall nat be dūme / but shall opteyne of our lorde / that thou yt dyddest succour thy neyghbour in any trouble / shalt be delyuered from all yll. Wyll ye here almes dede speakynge? Come ye blessed children of my father, for whan I hūgred / ye gaue me meate: Whan I thyrsted / ye gaue me drynke: whan I was naked / ye clothed me: whan I wāted lodgyng / ye lodged me: whā I was sycke / ye viseted me: whan I was in pri
               
                  •
               on / ye came to me. They remembre nat theyr benefittes / and say: O lorde whan dyd we se the wā
               tynge those thynges / and succoured the? The other part reherseth theyr vertues / and they here: Go ye into euerlastyng fire. Shal nat almes dede thā be here a good spokes womā, that shal delyuer vs from helle / that is from all mischief: and shall ioyne vs to our lord foū
               
                  •
               aine of al goodnes? What resteth now most dere brethern̄ / but that we must beseche the mercy of our lorde / to graunte vs that we may be mercifull to our neyghbour / lest if we here let naught by his mercy / shall aftward reqre it in vayne / but the more we be prouoked by mercy here / the more sharpe we shall fynde his iudgemēt / Let mercy towarde our bretherne ouercome in vs wordly affectiōs / that in god mercy toward vs maye ouercome iugement. So hit shall come to passe / that we with greable myndes to gether shall synge the mercyes of oure lorde for euer / aknowlegynge his mercies aboue all his warkes. To whom be preise and glory through all costis of the erthe for euer more. Amen.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶A note to the reder.
            
               
                  〈◊〉
                gentyll reder / take in worth my rude translation / though all be na
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                I wolde. And where Stipis is englisshed an halfpeny / I dyd it nat of 
                  •
               wordr
                  •
               nce / but bicause they 
                  •
               se in Englande to gyu
                  •
                halpence in almes.
         
         
            ¶A good table for them that shall rede this se
                  •
               m
                  •
               n and 
                  〈◊〉
               standen at Latin and frenche 
                  ••
               rmes / vsed in 
                  〈◊〉
               
            
            
               ¶A
                     •
                  cribe / to yeld or clayme to one
                     •
                  
               
               Accompted / cast or rekened.
               Assembled gethered to gether.
               Attentyue / inwardly markynge.
               Abominable / lothesome.
               Ancient / aged or olde.
               Accept / to take or allowe.
               Angelicall / heuenly.
               Affliction / peyne or grefe.
               Adde / to put or lay more to.
               Augmēteth / īlargeth maketh more
               Aduoutrice / a woman aduoutr
                     •
                  r.
               Abādonyng is taken for mysusyng
               Arbitrement / wyll or opinion.
               Abiecte / lowe or out cast.
               Accomplysshed / done or fulfylled.
               Amplifieth / maketh more large.
               Aduocatrice / is a woman that pledeth causes or matters.
               Brefely / soone or shortly.
               Benigne is he that well and w
                     ••
                  
                  thily rewardeth.
               Bounte / goodnes.
               Brute / vnwytte dull or slowe.
               Blaspheme / to speke yll or by leude 
                     •
                  ayeng to hynder ones honour
                     •
                  
               
               Concerneth toucheth.
               Confounded / troubled or all out of square and order.
               Compelleth / constrayneth by force.
               Comyt syn / to do synne.
               Calamite / wretche dues or grefe.
               Comprehende / percey
                     •
                  e or vnder
                     •
                  stande.
               Confidence / sure hope.
               Conquered / got by fyght.
               Compo
                     •
                  icion / a treaty.
               Crime / synne blame or sklaunder.
               Cōmendacion / preyse.
               Complecteth / clyppeth conteyneth consydereth or remembreth.
               Clemency / mercy or pite.
               Congregacion / a cōpany gethered.
               Conuersacion / maner in lyuynge.
               Cōferred / one thīge laid to an other
               Celebrate / worshyp or honour.
               Car
                     •
                  all / fle
                     •
                  shy
                     •
                  .
               
                  
                     •••
                  templacion / diligen
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Co
                     •
                  formite semelynes or 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Contemne / set at naught.
               Conf
                     •
                  sketh is whā a prunce
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   on a mans goodes forfayt
                     •
                  d
                     •
                  
               
               Dedicate is a thyng done 
                     〈…〉
                  uen by cause of honour.
               Direct / to leade 
                     •
                  hewe or 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Distruction / marrynge.
               Distinction / difference or 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Diuined / denied or truly 
                     〈…〉
                   well of thynges present 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Discipline / 
                     •
                  ernynge.
               Difficile / harde or vneasy
                     •
                  
               
               Deiecte / cast or threwe.
               Depriued / put from
                     •
                  
               
               Exciteth / stereth vp or awaken
                     ••••
                  
               
               Expedient / profitable good 
                     〈◊〉
                   or behouefull.
               Exp
                     •
                  essed / shewed playnly
                     •
                  
               
               Eloquent / fayre langaged.
               Effectuous or e
                     •
                  fectu
                     •
                  ll is hi
                     •
                   t
                     ••
                   to do a thyng hath power and w
                     •••
                  keth moste.
               Exhalte / to prease vp on high.
               Expelled / dryuen out.
               Erudite / well lerned.
               Eccellent / excedynge.
               Enterprise / taken on ha
                     •
                  de.
               Extolleth / a
                     •
                  anceth e
                     •
                  ha
                     •
                  n
                     •
                  e
                     ••
                   lyfteth vp or preyseth.
               Encountred / met with.
               E
                     •
                  cesse / more than ynough.
               Enbraceth / clyppeth.
               Employe / exercise or put fo
                     •
                  t
                     •
                  .
               Enuiron / compasse or set abo
                     ••
                  .
               Eternall / euerlastynge.
               Enormite / out of measur
                     •
                  .
               Felicite / prosperite o
                     •
                   welth
                     •
                  .
               For
                     •
                  icacion / hore haunt
                     •
                  nge.
               Fugitiue / vanysshynge lyghtly
                     •
                  
               
               Fruicion / frutefull delyt
                     •
                  .
               Fortifieth / strengtheth
               Humayne / is what that 
                     〈◊〉
                   ynto mankynd
                     ••
                  
               
               
                  Horrible / dred
                     •
                  full or erkesome.
               Humilite / lowlynes or mekenes.
               Incredible / vnneth to be beleued.
               Infinite / without 
                     •
                  nde.
               Interpretate / expounde or declare.
               Iniury / harme or wronge.
               Infamous / yll named.
               Inhabitantis / dwellers.
               Incontinent / shortly or by and by.
               Ineffable / vnspekeable.
               Incomparable / without pere.
               Iniquite / vnrightou
                     •
                  ne
                     •
                   / wikednes
               Infirmitees / 
                     •
                  ickenes or diseases.
               Insolent / vnwont or vnused / and is taken for proude pre
                     •
                  umptuousnes.
               Indurate / made harde or hardned.
               Liberalite / free or gentyll.
               Mortall is he that muste 
                     •
                  ye.
               Misery / sorowe or wretchednes.
               Multitude / moche folke gethered.
               Miracle / a ma
                     ••
                  ayle or a wonder.
               Mysticall / figured.
               Mansions / dwellynges.
               Magnifie / to crake or boste.
               Monyssheth
                     •
                  wa
                     •
                  neth.
               Memory / remembrance.
               Mollifieth / soupleth te
                     •
                  dreth or maketh softe.
               Necessites / nedis.
               Odious / hatefull.
               Obiecteth / putteth casteth o
                     •
                   layeth agaynst.
               Prohibeted / let or forbyden.
               Prosecute is whan the mynde is bent towarde one to fauour hat
                     •
                   or loue hym / to folowe the same.
               Preceptes / teachynges.
               Presumtuous is whan one t
                     •
                  keth vpon hym that he ought nat.
               Pondred / wayed or consydered.
               Pestilent / mischeuous.
               Perdicion / losse.
               Perpetuall / styll or contynuall.
               Puissance / myght or power.
               Parabol / a simili
                     •
                  ude or lykenes.
               Preuent / come or take fyrst.
               Procedeth / holdeth on.
               Prescribeth / lymytteth ma
                     •
                  keth or appoynteth before.
               Pleasant / gaye to ones mynde.
               Polluted be durted.
               Preiudice / ha
                     •
                  me.
               Profounde / depe.
               Prodigall / r
                     •
                  ottons.
               Rude / vnlerned.
               Redoundeth / returneth.
               Reproche / reprofe or blame.
               Rep
                     •
                  ted / rehersed or spokē agayn
                     ••
                  
               
               Reconciled / fauourably returned.
               Regarde / beholde.
               Rapine / robbery.
               Resisteth / withstandeth.
               Reduce / to brynge in agayne.
               Subtyle / wyly.
               Superstitiousnes or superstition
                     •
                   is vayne deuocion.
               Seriously / sadly or ernestly.
               Solemne / customable.
               Satanas / the dyuell / whiche is 
                     〈◊〉
                   say an aduersary.
               Stablisshe / surely grounde
               Sagasite / quicke or crafty
                     •
                  
               
               Scarbet / in some places of Englād is called a dorse / in som other place
                     •
                   as hernebod / it is lyke a hūbullber / it is blacke / it fl
                     •
                  eth in the eueny
                     ••
                   and falleth in beast is do
                     •
                  ge.
               Testimony / wytnes.
               Transitory / is it that lyghtly got
                     •
                  
               
               Temporall / duryng a tyme.
               Uile / lyttell worthe.
               Usurpe / to take vpon.
               Ueritable / true.
               Uiolate / breke.
               Uanquisshed / ouercome,
            
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            ¶Thus endeth the sermon of thexcedinge mercy of god. Imprinted at London in Fletestrete / by Thomas Berthelet / printer vnto the kynges most noble grace / dwellyng at the sygne of Lucrece.
            Cum priui
                  •
               egio
                  •
               
            
            
         
      
   

