
   
      
         
            The manuell of Epictetus, translated out of Greeke into French, and now into English, conferred with two Latine translations. Herevnto are annexed annotations, and also the apothegs of the same author. By Ia. Sanford
            Manual. English
            Epictetus.
         
         
            
               1567
            
         
         Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00301
            STC 10423
            ESTC S101652
            99837460
            99837460
            1781
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00301)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1781)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 495:7)
         
         
            
               
                  The manuell of Epictetus, translated out of Greeke into French, and now into English, conferred with two Latine translations. Herevnto are annexed annotations, and also the apothegs of the same author. By Ia. Sanford
                  Manual. English
                  Epictetus.
                  Sandford, James.
               
               [8], 36, [4] leaves   
               
                  By H. Bynneman for Leonard Maylard,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  Anno. 1567.
               
               
                  A translation of: Enchiridion.
                  The penultimate leaf is foliated 37.
                  With a final colophon leaf.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Ethics, Ancient.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            The Manuell of Epictetus,
Tranſlated out of Greeke
into French, and now into Engliſh,
conferred with two Latine Tranſlations.
            Herevnto are annexed Annotations, and
alſo the Apothegs of the ſame Author.
By Ia. Sanford.
            
               
                  OMNIA TEMPVS HABENT
               
               printer's device of Henry Bynneman
            
            Imprinted at London by H. Bynneman
for Leonard Maylard. ANNO. 1567.
         
         
            
            Tetraſticon ad Reginam.
            Scilicet exiguū (Princeps mitiſsima) quicquid
            Expromit liber hic, non tamen exiguum
            Si te reſpicias, magni non muneris instar
            Si libri ſenſum non erit exiguum.
         
         
            
            To the moſt high and
vertuous Princeſſe, ELIZABETH by
the grace of God, of England, Fraunce
and Ireland Queene, defender of the faith,
long health and perpetuall felicitie.
            
               
                  ALthoughe I haue not
attained (moſt ſoueraign
Lady) to that ripeneſſe
in knoweledge and profoundneſſe
in lerning, as
they haue, who bothe in
reding and writing haue
ſpente almoſt the whole
courſe of their age. Yet foraſmuch as paynefull
practize ioyned with diligent ſtudie, bringeth
to effect ſome thing worth the labour, I toke in
hand this little Boke, as a triall in the true trade
of interpreting. Which done, I thought not my
trauaile myſſpent, but worthie to be publiſhed
abrode for a common vſe and commoditie, and
meete that of all eſtates he be vſually read, dayly
to be had in hande, and continually to be had in
remembraunce: for if a man reade this, and in
reading conſider it with a quiet minde voide of
all care and ſolicitude, and being attentiue vpon
one thing wherin he is conuerſant, he ſhal find
(as I ſuppoſe) nothing more excellent, nothing
more commodious, nothing more godly to be
taughte and ſhewed vs, than the ſumme of thys

Boke, and the principal pointes herein comprehended
and contained, which are theſe:
            Hurt no man. Obey God and nature.
Suffer iniuries. Deſerue wel of al men as
nigh as thou mayst. Take in good parte
whatſoeuer chaunce without thy default.
Vſe ſuch things as are giuē for the neceſſitie
of life, as if thou didst not vſe them,
and gladly to reſtore the ſame when God
or Fortune (as we commonly ſay) requireth
the ſame. Repoſe and accompt felicitie
in an vpright and quiet minde. Finally
recreate and content thy ſelf in the
diuine adminiſtration of worldly things,
as very iust and wiſe, and to vs auaileable,
althoughe ſometimes it ſeeme very
grieuous.
            Theſe things ſo great, ſo profitable, ſo needefull
to be knowen, ſo auaileable for well framing of
life, if we ſhut it within the cheſt of our mind,
it is far from that we ſhould be void of all perturbatiōs
and trobleſome motions of the mind,
that we ſhould be in felicitie, and leade our life
both well and wealthilie. You may coiecture
(moſt gracious and ſoueraigne Lady) that in dedicating
this Boke vnto your highneſſe, I mene
to inſtruct one better learned than my ſelfe, and
as the Prouerbe is SVS MINERVAM, the

which doubtleſſe is fartheſt off from my cogitations:
for it is the ſigne of a man bereft of his
witte, and not of a ſounde and perfecte minde,
to carrie wood into the Wood, and to caſt water
into the Sea. What ſhoulde I ſpeake of the
goodly vertues wherewith you are adorned?
            What ſhoulde I ſet forth and with prayſes extol
your excellent endowments both of minde and
bodie, which cauſe in all men an admiration?
            For the Greeke tong you are to be compared to
ZENOBIA Queene of the Palmirians, who
was very skilfull in the Greeke language, and
in the Latin not ignorant. For Eloquence you
may be likened to CORNELIA mother of the
Gracchi. For the embracing of the holy and ſacred
ſcripture you are to be numbred with FABIOLA
and MARCELLA women wel lerned
and ſtudious of the heauēly veritie. In brief▪
you may be reconed as EVSTOCHIVM was,
who in hir time bicauſe of hir litterature and
profoundneſſe in knowledge, was called Nouū
orbis prodigiū. Your knowledge in the French,
Spaniſh and Italian tong I nede not declare, for
vertue nedeth no commendation, nor delighteth
to be ennobled with gay gloſsing communication:
for where the ſunne caſteth his gliſtering
beames, the light of the candell is diminiſhed
and obſcured. This Stoick Philoſopher EPICTETVS
wrote this worke in a large Volume,
in his mother tong, and was abbreuiated by one

ARRIANVS a Grecian into this forme, and
entituled it Enchyridion, than the which there
can be no Booke to the wel framing of our life
more profitable and neceſſary. The Authoure
whereof although he were an Ethnicke, yet he
wrote very godly &amp; chriſtianly, and as he ſpeaketh
in other tongs, ſo nowe he ſhall ſpeake in
the Engliſhe language, and vnder your Graces
protection ſhalbe publiſhed to the commoditie
of many. Moſt humbly beſeeching your highneſſe,
to accepte and take in good parte this
little Booke, offring it as a pledge of
my bounden dutie towards
your highneſſe, &amp; affection
towardes
my countrie.
❧ 
               ❧
            
            
               Your highneſſe moſt humble
and loyall ſubiect Iames Sanforde.
            
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               THis booke (gentle Reader)
is entituled a Manuell,
which is deriued
of the Latin word Manuale,
and in Gréeke
is called Enchyridion,
bicauſe he may be contained 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
that is, in the hand. It is a diminutiue
of Manus, as it were a ſtorehouſe, &amp;
which ought always to be had in hād,
as the hādle in the ſword. This word
Enchyridion doeth not onely ſignifie a
Manuel, but alſo a ſhort dagger, which
is vſed in the warres, or a Poineado.
Wherefore ſome do entitle this boke
Enchyridion, yt is, a ſhort Dagger: for
like as ye Dagger defēdeth a mā from
his enimie, euē ſo this little booke doth
defend one in perfectneſſe of minde, &amp;
ſaueth him frō the filthy fogge of wicked
vices. The title of eyther of theſe
may be wel applied to the boke, ye one
reſpecting the quantitie, the other the
matter in the booke comprehended.
            The wordes contained in him, are of

greate force and full of efficacie, to
moue mennes myndes, for euery man
may knowe his affections in him, and
to the amending of them, he is ſtirred
as it were with a pricke. His ſtile or
maner of wordes is brief, and voyd
of all elegancie in wordes, very
much like the Pithagorean
Precepts, which they
call Diathecae.
            
            Fare wel gentle Reder, and
accept in good part
theſe my labours.
         
         
            
               
               In Sanfordi Epictetum Anglum. E. L.
               IMpiger extremis rediens Mercator ab Indis
               Has inquit merces India fuſca tulit.
               Et ſilet, &amp; vendit, ſatis &amp; laudaſſe putatur
               Et precium nummi nobile pondus habet,
               India fuſca tulit: quid tum ſi Graecia ferret?
               Quid ſi Roma tulit? Gallia ſiue tulit?
               Graecia, Roma, ſuis pretiū num mercibus addūt?
               Gallia ſi quid habet, nū quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   pondus habet?
               Si modo pondus habet, pōdus feret iſte libellus,
               Qui nunc eſt Anglus, qui modo Gallus erat,
               Graecia quem vidit Graecū, quē Roma Latinum,
               Quem
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   nouos docuit lingua Britanna ſonos:
               Impiger ad noſtras quem tu Mercator ad oras
               Attuleras SANFORD, ſic quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſanctus eras.
               Sic quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſanctus erit labor hic tuus, &amp; liber idē
               
               Et ſi ſanctus erit nobile pondus habet.
               Nobile pondus habet ſuauiſsimus ore Britānus,
               At magis ore ſacer nobile pondus habet.
            
            
               Eiuſdem Edmundi Lewkener
Libri ad Lectorem Proſopopeia.
               VErba libri
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   docent ſacrae munimina vitae,
               Virtus eſt clarae nobilitatis iter,
               Eliſij Campi vitae ſunt munera ſacrae,
               At comes eſt magnae nobilitatis honos.
               In me diuinae lucet virtutis Imago,
               Atque ego ſum vitae dux ſine labe tuae.
               Ergo ſi coelos, ſi non contemnis honores,
               Tu face quod iubeo munus vtrumque feres.
            
         
         
            
            Againſt curious Carpers.
            
               CArp not ye cankred zoiles al, the men
               Whoſe labour ſpente in paynfull toyle
hath ben
               To blaſe the badge and banner braue diſplay
               Of noble vertues force and craggie way.
            
            
               The byting Theon &amp; Daphitas bolde
               VVith all the railing rable manifolde
               Of zoilus ſect ceaſe biting chaps to vſe
               Againſt ſuch, who on learnings lore doe
muſe.
            
            
               The learned Homer, and Praxitiles,
               
               To taūting talk, &amp; miſreports wer theſe
               Subiect. Therfore ſhould I eſteme my ſelf
               T'eſcape the iarring iawes of zoilus elfe?
            
         
         
            
            The life of Epictetus.
            
               
                  EPictetus a noble Philoſopher
in the Stoick
profeſſion was born of
ſeruile parents in Hieropolis
a Citie of Phrigia,
who albeit he was
a bond man, lame, and in extreme penurie,
yet he doubted not earneſtely
to affirme that he was a friend to the
Gods, in two verſes very well knowen
among the Gréekes, whiche are
cited both of Macrobius and Aulus
Gellius, and be theſe:

                  
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
               
Which are of a certaine Writer trā
               ſlated
into Latine after this manner:

                  Seruus Epictetus genitus ſum corpore
claudus,
                  Paupertate irus, Dijs &amp; amicus ego.
               
And may thus be Engliſhed:

                  Of ſeruile kinde I borne was,
                  hight Epictete by name,
                  
                     
In ſubſtance pore, to God a friend
                  and eke in body lame.
               
            
            He ſerued in Rome one called Epaphroditus
familiar with the Emperour
Nero. And liued in Rome all the
time of Marcus Antonius raigne.
But when Domitian tooke rule in
hande, he went from Rome to Hieropolis
where he was borne, ſuppoſing
that to be true, whiche is in the Tragicall
Poet. Patriam eſse cuiuſque, vbi
quis recte ageret, that is:

                  A man his countrey is euen there
                  Where of God and man he ſtands in feare.
               
            
            He did reade in Plato (of whome he
was a diligent Reader and follower)
in that Dialogue which is entituled
Primus Alcibiades, or De natura hominis,
that he properly and verily was
a man, whoſe ſubſtaunce altogether
did conſiſte in the reaſonable mynde,
accompting the minde only to be mā,
and ye body but an inſtrument. Wherfore
whatſoeuer was withoute thys
man, he thoughte theſame nothing to
appertaine vnto hym, neyther dyd he

declare that only in wordes or bokes,
but alſo in hys life: for he did ſo withdrawe
himſelfe from the care &amp; loue of
outwarde things, ſo litle regarding
hys body, or any thing thereto belonging,
that at Rome hys houſe had no
dore, for there was nothing at all in it
but a bad beggerly bed of little value.
Lucian the Sirian writeth
that Epictetus was after his
death ſo eſtemed, that
an earthen candleſticke
that he
had, was ſold for fifty
pounds.
         
      
      
         
            
               
               
The Manuel of Epictetus
            
               Cap. 1. ¶What things are in man, and what are not.
               
                  OF al things which are,A diuiſion of things. ſome
are in vs, ſome are not. In
vs are Opinion, Endeuor,
Deſire, Eſchuing, &amp; briefly
al that which is our worke. In vs are
not our Body, Poſſeſſions, Honours,
Souerainties,The natural condition of things. and ſummarily al that
which is not our worke. Then the
things which are in vs are frée and
franke by nature, and can not be prohibited,
empeached, nor taken away.
But ſuch things as are not in vs, bée
ſeruile, féeble, and may be prohibited,
empeched and taken away, as things
vnto other men belonging, and not
ours.
            
            
               Cap. 2. ¶Of the domage which proceedeth of taking
the one for the other, and of the profit in good
Iudgement.The effects of a good and euill iudgement.
               
               IF the thinges which are franke and
frée, thou ſhalte eſtéeme and Iudge

ſeruill, and the thinges which are not
oures, thou thynke proper, thou ſhalt
be ſorrowfull, thou ſhalte be troubled,
thou ſhalt finde thy ſelfe encombred, &amp;
ſhalte miſcontente thy ſelfe with God
and men. But if thou thinke onely the
things thyne, which truely are thine,
and the things other mennes, which
truely are other mens, no man wyll
conſtrayne thée, no man wyll hinder
thée, thou ſhalt blame no body, thou
ſhalt accuſe no body, thou ſhalt do nothing
againſte thy wyll, no man ſhall
hurte thée, and moreouer thou ſhalte
haue no enimy. For in nothing which
is hurtefull thou canſt not be perſwaded.
            
            
               Cap. 3. ¶That other mens matters muſt be omitted,
our owne muſt be ſeene vnto, and that we can
not do both.
               THen if thou deſire ſuch things,
remember that thou oughteſte
not beyng greatly mooued and
troubled, to take them in hand:
but eyther altogether thou oughteſte

to reiecte them,Our conſideration is to be ſtirred vp and a diligēt preparation to be vſed. or for a tyme laye thē
a ſide, and before al things to be carefull
ouer thy ſelfe. But if thou deſire
theſe things, that is to rule, to be rich,
to haue thine to proſper, peraduenture
thou ſhalte not aſpire to all theſe
things,One can not ſerue vertue and vanitie. bicauſe thou doeſt deſire alſo
the chefeſt. So by no maner of means
thou art able to attain vnto ye things
which giue felicitie &amp; libertie to man.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     All theſe things) That is rule, riches. &amp;c.
bicauſe thou doeſt deſire the chiefeſt)
that is, theſe things which Philoſophie giueth,
Libertie, tranquillitie of the mynde, and ſecuritie.
               
            
            
               Cap. 4. ¶Howe we oughte to behaue oure ſelues in
euery ſharpe imagination.
               IN any ſtrong and ſharpe Imagination,We muſt refrain our cō
                     ſent before the matter bee plainely perceiued.
thou muſt accuſtome thy ſelfe
immediatly to conſider, that this is
nothing elſe but Imagination, and
that in déede it is not as thou déemeſt.
Afterward ſearch it out, and examine
it, with theſe rules whiche thou haſte.

Firſt and principally by this, whether
the thing concerne the things whiche
are in vs, or the things which are not.
And if it be of the things whiche are
not in vs, haue incontinently thys in
remembrance: That belongeth nothing
to me.
               
            
            
               Cap. 5. ¶What thing it is that one ought to deſire, &amp;
one ought to flee.
               CAll to remembraunce,A vain flight from diſcommodities maketh a man miſerable, &amp; a depriuing of deſires maketh a man vnfortunate. that the
promiſe and the end of deſire is,
enioying of the thyng deſired:
and that the promiſe and ende
of eſchewing is not to fall into that,
whiche one oughte to flée: He then
which cōmeth not to enioy, but is depriued
of the promiſe of his deſire, is
not happy, but vnfortunate, and whoſo
falleth on ye, which he declineth, is miſerable.
If thē onely thou decline that
which is not agreable to the nature
of the things whiche are in vs, thou
ſhalt neuer chaunce into that, whiche
thou ſhalt flee. But if thou thinkeſt to

erempt thy ſelfe from ſickeneſſe death
or frō pouertie, or altogether ſhunne
them, thou ſhalt finde thy ſelfe vnhappy.One newely entred in the doctrine of vertue ought not to take to much vpō him.
Wherfore thou muſt ſet apart all
the eſchuing, and auoiding of ſuche
things as are not in vs, and tranſpoſe
theſe into them which are againſt the
nature of things, whiche be in vs. As
touching deſire, thou muſt altogether
ſet it aſide at this preſent. For if thou
couet the things which are not in our
power, it muſt néedes be, that thou be
fruſtrate. Howe and after what ſorte
thou muſt deſire the things which are
in vs, thou art yet vncertaine. As for
endeuoure and refraining of ye minde
vſe it ſleightly with reaſon, and a reſted
deliberation.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Promiſe of deſire, It is a certain faining of
deſire ſpeaking with a mā. To the vnlearned ſort
the wordes ſhould be more plaine▪ if he had thus
ſpoken: when thou doeſt deſire any thing, haue
a cōfidence to obtaine it, &amp; to haue thy deſire. &amp;c
that which is not agreable to ye nature
of the things which are in vs, Againſt
theſe things verely do repugne, falſe opinion,

naughtie &amp; corrupt appetite, all the perturbatiōs
of the minde, whiche the Stoicke Philoſophers
would haue to be in mans power: not ſo peraduenture
that they appeare not (for that were
more beſeming God than man) but that they
obeye reaſon. Trāſpoſe theſe into them
which ar againſt the nature of things
which be in vs. Theſe words ſeme vnto the
vnlearned obſcure, which had ben more lighter
and eaſy, if he had written thus: To abhorre falſe
opinions, foliſh and euil deſires, diſhoneſtie, and
diſworſhip. For as thou mayeſt flee theſe thinges,
ſo thou mayeſt eſchewe them.
               
            
            
               Cap. 6. ¶Howe we oughte to eſteme the thinges
wherein we take pleaſure, or which bryng vs
profite.
               IN euery thing, whiche doth eyther
delite thée,The nature of the thing derely loued is to be conſidered. or whiche are profitable
vnto thée, or which thou loueſt, thou
muſt diligently conſider the qualitie,
beginning at the leaſt thyngs. If
thou loue a pot, ſay in thys manner: I
loue a pot, theſame beyng brokē, thou
ſhalte not diſquiete thy ſelfe, for thou
diddeſt well knowe, that he was fragile
and brittle. Likewiſe if thou loue

thy ſonne, or thy wyfe, ſaye that thou
doeſt loue a man: if one or other chāce
to dye thou ſhalt not be troubled, bicauſe
thou dyddeſt conſider well that
he was mortall.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     If thou loue a pot, Albeit Epictet, as a diſpiſer
of riches, bringeth forth examples of vyle
thyngs, as of baynes, lactuce, and other of that
ſort: yet Simplicius hath a more apte worde: If
thou hādell or toſſe a pot: that is, a brittle thing
that cānot abyde or ſuffer toſſyng, or hitting againſt
the walles, as glaſſe, wherof Publiā ſayth,
Fortune is as brittle as glaſſe, whiche when it
ſhineth, it is broken. Peraduenture he alluded to
Diogenes Tonne.
               
            
            
               Cap. 7. ¶How a man ought to take a matter in hand
that we may be voide of perturbation, &amp; firſt by
meditation.
               WHen yu doeſt take any thing
in hande,The circumſtāces of euery buſineſſe are to be conſidered. thou muſte ſet before
thy eyes ye qualitie therof:
as if thou wylt goe to the
baines, cōſider with thy ſelfe diligētly
all that which may happen, &amp; what

they do. Some caſt water, ſome are
driuen out of their places, ſome doe a
thing to the rebuke of an other, and in
the meane ſeaſon other picke &amp; ſteale.
In doyng thys thou ſhalt more certainely
and conſtantly bryng thy matter
to paſſe, if finally thou ſaye I wyll
bath my ſelfe, and obſerue thy purpoſe
vnto nature agréeable, and ſemblably
in all things thou ſhalt not do amiſſe.
For after this ſort if any harme befall
while thou arte in the baine, this ſaying
ſhal be in a redineſſe: I would not
onely obſerue this, but alſo would not
ſwarue from my purpoſe whiche is
agréeable vnto nature, whiche I ſhall
not performe, if I take diſpleaſauntly
the things which happen and befall.
            
            
               Cap. 8. ¶Howe to put awaye our perturbations, thorowe
the conſideration of the nature of ſuche
things,We are troubled with opinions, not with the things them ſelues. as trouble vs.
               THe things do not trouble men,
but the opinions whiche they
conceyue of them, as for example:

death is not terrible (thē it would
haue ſo ſéemed to Socrates) but bicauſe
the opinion of death is terrible,A wiſe man is without complaint.
death ſemeth terrible. Then when we
are brought in the briers, or be troubled,
or that we do bewaile our owne
ſtate, let vs not blame others but our
ſelues, that is to ſay our opinions.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Death is not terrible, If either the ſoule
be extinguiſhed with the body, or be trāsferred
and caried into a better place. But if thou ſhalte
be puniſhed for thy offences, it is a daungerous
matter, and a harde caſe, excepte thou be fenſed
with the buckler of true pietie.
               
            
            
               Cap. 9. ¶The reaſon and proufe of the former precept
with an aſsignation of thre ſorts of men.
               THe vnlerned accuſeth other in
his owne propre faulte. He that
begynneth to haue knowledge
accuſeth him ſelfe. The learned
accuſeth neither an other, neither him
ſelfe.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     
                     The vnlerned, That is he, which conſidereth
not what things are his owne, and what ar
an other mannes: who requireth all things to
be done according to his wil and pleaſure, that
which neither may be done, neither perhappes
ought not. Himſelf for he doth acknowledge
hys faulte, and alſo is intentiue and diligente about
it, leaſte that he ſtumble againe at the ſame
ſtone: that is, leſt that he claime or attribute other
mens right to himſelfe.
               
            
            
               Cap. 10. ¶That the glory in exteriour and outwarde
things is vayne.
               GLory not in thy ſelfe for the excellencie
of an other thing.We muſt auaunt in the riches of the minde, and not in the gifts of fortune. It
ſhoulde be tollerable, if a horſe
aduaunting himſelf ſhould ſay:
I am faire. But thou when in boſting
thy ſelfe, thou doeſt ſay, I haue a faire
horſe: remember that thou doſt glorifie
thy ſelfe for the beautie which is in
the horſe.The vſe of opinion is propre vnto man. What haſte thou then? Nothing
biſides the vſe of opinion.
               Therefore when in the vſe of opinion
thou ſhalt gouerne thy ſelfe according
to nature, then thou ſhalt haue wherwith

to auaunte thy ſelfe, for in any
commoditie which is thine, thou wilte
glorifie thy ſelfe.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     The vſe of opinion, This ſemeth obſcure
to the vnlearned. But it is euen as he ſhould ſays
In all things we ought not to follow appetite,
or the common opinion, but the iudgement of
reaſon. For to vſe well opinion, is nothing elſe
than to iudge well of all things, and to obey
reaſon, not affection.
               
            
            
               Cap. 11. ¶What outwarde things are graunted vs, and
howe we ſhould vſe them, by a ſimilitude.
               EVen as in Nauigation,We oughte in al things principally to be mindful of God. when
men make their abode at any hauen,
if ye Mariner goeth to lande
for freſhe water, and it hapneth
that incidently by the way, he thinketh
to gather cockles or oyſters, yet
neuertheleſſe he ought to haue regard
of the ſhippe, and oftentimes to looke
back, whether ye Maſter calleth: and
if he call thée, leaue all behinde, and
returne to the ſhippe, leaſt that thou

being bond like a beaſt, be not drawen
by force to the ſhippe. Euen ſo it is, in
the courſe of our life, as if for a cockle
or an oiſter, there be gyuen vs a wife
and a childe, or other things, which
we holde deare, and wherin we take
pleſure, they ought not to put vs from
our purpoſe vnto nature agréeable:
But if the maſter do call, run vnto the
ſhippe, leauing theſe things behinde,
not looking backe towards them. But
if thou be olde, go neuer farre from
the ſhip, leaſt that thou being called,
do fail, &amp; that thou be not conſtrained.
For he which willingly followeth not
neceſſitie, by force and maulgre his
téeth ſhe draweth him.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Leaſt yt thou being called doſt fail. He
ſpeaketh not of the outwarde power, but of the
imbecillitie and weakneſſe of the might: which
the greter it ſhalbe whē age cōmeth on vs with
more few things the mind is to be occupied: for
bicauſe it is very difficulte to be voide of theſe,
and to fulfill that which Philoſophie commandeth.
A ſingle perſon (if other things be correſpondent)
may be in his life time, cōtented with

a little, and die with a more pacient minde. A
wife, children, and familie, do more trouble and
diſquiete the husbande and father, being as well
in good healthe, as ſicke, than his life. I vnderſtande
the ſhippe, either to be Philoſophie, or the
trade of our life: the ruler and maiſter of the
Shippe to be GOD: to whom when he calleth,
who ſo obeyeth not either is entreted as a ſlaue,
or elſe is vtterly forſaken.
               
            
            
               Cap. 12. ¶How we may enioy outward things without
fault or trouble.
               WIſh not that the thyng which is
done,We muſte not couet in vaine, that which is impoſſible. be done according to thy
pleaſure and will. But wiſh that it be
done, euen as it is don, and thou ſhalt
be happie. Sickneſſe is an impedimēt
of the body, not of thy purpoſe, except
thou wilt thy ſelfe.A wel framed mynde is diſturbed with nothing. Halting is an impediment
of the legge or foote, and not
of thy purpoſe, and ſo conſider in euerie
inconuenience whiche may befall,
and thou ſhalte finde the impediment
to appertaine to an other, and not to
thée.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     
                     Halting is an impediment of ye foote,
not of thy purpoſe. But thou wilt ſay whē
thou art purpoſed to goe a iourney (namely if
thou want a horſe, or a waggon) halting hindereth
thee. Epictet wil anſwer &amp; ſay: If thou ſhalt
follow my precepts, thou ſhalt begyn no iourney,
whiche thou art not hable to atchieue. So
the more and greater the impedimentes of the
body ſhall be, ſo much the more thou ſhalt ſuppreſſe
appetite, and ſhalte take fewer things in
hande. But thou doſt ſay, that this is the impediment
of purpoſe, and therefore very troubleſome.
Epictet denieth it to be an impediment,
to deſire nothing raſhly and in vaine: but affirmeth
it to be the propre part &amp; office of a Philoſopher.
Verily, euen a foole doth vnderſtande
this, that it is better to make appetite obey reaſon,
than to burne in vaine deſires. The impediment
to appertaine to another and
not to thée) If he would graūt the foote to be
a part of the body, (neither doeth he denie it) &amp;
the bodie to be part of man (which he ſeemeth
to denie) when his foote is poiſtered &amp; ſhakled,
the bodie is alſo cūbred, the body being cumbred,
mā hym ſelfe at leaſt wiſe partely is cumbred,
but if the body be the inſtrument of man,
doutleſſe it cā not be denied, but that the inſtrument
being mutilate and vnperfect, the worke
ſhalbe more vnperfect and vnmeete. For thou
ſhalt haue the ouerthrowe, if thy Sworde or
Dagger lacke hiltes and handle.
               
            
            
               
               Cap. 13. ¶Of the remedies which we haue againſt all
accidentes.
               IN euery accident thou muſt incontinently
conſider what puiſſaunce &amp;
ſtrēgth thou haſt to withſtand that
whiche is hapned.The power of the mind ought to reſiſt aduerſity &amp; naughty deſires. If any miſchiefe
befall vnto thée, thou ſhalt finde vertue
whiche is good and holſome, as againſt
voluptuouſneſſe, continencie.
If laboure be offred thée, thou ſhalte
finde ſtrength: if wrong, pacience: and
if thou ſhalt thus accuſtome thy ſelfe,
thou ſhalt neuer be troubled with ymaginations.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Thou ſhalt not be troubled with imaginations)
That is, thou ſhalt neuer be ouercome
and ſubdued with pleaſure and ſorrowe,
but ſhalt conquere naughtie deſires, and affections,
by the helpe of wiſedome and vertue.
               
            
            
               Cap. 14. ¶What maner of men we oughte to ſhewe
oure ſelues, when we loſe outwarde worldly
goodes.
               
                  
NEuer ſay that thou haſte loſte
any thing,We do neuer loſe our goods, but reſtore thē, to him of whom we receiued them, that is to God. but that thou haſte
reſtored it. If thy ſonne die, he
is reſtored. Thy liuelode is taken
away, haſt thou not reſtored it?
But he which depriued thée of it, is an
yll man. What matter maketh it to
thée, by whome he which gaue it, hath
eftſoones taken it? Haue a care and regarde
to all things, keping and vſing
them (during the time only that thou
haſte them in thy cuſtodie) as things
vnto other men belongyng, euen as
the wayfaring man dothe to his lodging.
            
            
               Cap. 15. ¶That a man ought not to loſe the quietneſſe
of mynde, for exteriour and worldly things.
               IF thou wilt profite thy ſelf,The garniſhing of the minde is to be regarded aboue all things. let paſſe
theſe cogitations. If I ſhall not be
carefull of my affaires, I ſhall not
haue wherwith to liue. If I correct
not my ſeruāt, he will be naught. For
it is farre better to famiſh without ſorowe
and feare, than to liue in abundance

with a troubled minde. And it is
much better, that the ſeruant ſhoulde
bée faultie, than thou whiche art his
maiſter vnhappy. Then thou muſt begin
with the leaſt things, the Oyle is
ſpilte, the Wine is ſtolne. Conſider
with thy ſelfe, that quietneſſe and ſecuritie
of the mind coſt thée ſo much:
for nothing is fréely gotten. If thou
call thy ſeruant, imagine it may ſo fal
out, that he heareth thée not, or hearing
thée, to doe nothing whiche thou
wouldeſt haue him do. But that he is
not worth ſo much, that for him thou
ſhouldſt be troubled.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     It is far better to famiſh. &amp;c. It may be
asked not without a cauſe whether ſo greate
conſtancie may agree with mans nature, that it
may ſuffer and endure extreme hunger?
               
            
            
               Cap. 16.We muſte take paciently the euill opinion of the multitude conceiued of vs. ¶That for the eſtimation of the people we
ought not abandon vertue.
               IF thou wilte profit thy ſelfe, be not
diſpleaſed, if for outwarde things,

thou ſeme to other madde or foliſh.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     If thou wilt profit That is to ſay in Philoſophy
and garniſhing of the mind. For he vnderſtandeth
and meaneth that progreſſiō, wherby
the tranquillitie and libertie of the minde is
increaſed. Be not diſpleaſed, if for. &amp;c. For
who ſo regardeth not pleaſures, riches, &amp; honor,
namely if he may obtaine them: of all men he is
accompted a foole, namely in theſe dayes. But in
times paſt diuers Philoſophers and good mē for
the loue they had to vertue abandoned al worldly
wealth and promotions, as Crates, Diogenes,
and thys our Epictete.
               
            
            
               Cap. 17. ¶Againſt vaine glory.
               SEke not to ſéeme learned and experte
in any thing,It is hard to doe many things at once. and if to any
thou doeſt ſeme, truſt not thy ſelf:
for thou knoweſt it is not eaſy for
a man to kepe hys purpoſe agreable
vnto nature, and to embrace exteriour
things, but it muſt néedes be, that he
which is careful of one, ſhould be negligent
in the other.
            
            
               
               Cap. 18. ¶What things we oughte to deſire, &amp; what
we ought not.
               IF thou wilt haue thy wife,We do in vaine ſeke to kepe thoſe things inuiolable, which are not in our power. thy children,
and thy frends to liue for euer,
thou art a foole. For thou wilt haue
in thy power the things whiche are
not, &amp; wilt haue ye things to be thine,
which are belonging to other mē. And
ſo if thou wilt not haue thy ſeruaunte
to offende, thou art a foole, for yu wilte
haue vice to be no vice. But if thou
wilt not be fruſtrate of that whiche
thou doeſt deſire, this thou maieſt do:
herein then exerciſe thy ſelfe.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     For thou wilt haue vice to be no vice,
He meaneth (as I ſuppoſe) that boyes and al maner
of men, by nature are inclined to vice: and
that vices cannot be repelled, but by philoſophie
which yong and tender age is not able to receyue.
               
            
            
               Cap. 19. ¶What things make vs bonde, and what free.
               
                  
HE is Maſter and Lord of any
man,Who is a maiſter. to whome (nil he will he)
he maye either giue or take awaye.
He then which will be
frée, let him neither deſire, nor flée any
thing, which is in an other man hys
hande, and power, otherwiſe of neceſſitie
he ſhal be conſtrained to ſerue.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     He is Maſter of any man. &amp;c. How many
Maiſters then hath Fortune layed vpon vs?
Howe many more do we laye vpon vs, thorowe
the inſaciable deſire of tranſitorie thinges?
               
            
            
               Cap. 20. ¶A rule to electe and chooſe things preſent▪
paſt, and to come, by a ſimilitude.
               REmēber that thou muſte make
compariſon of thy lyfe to a banket:Such things as are offred are to be taken: ſuche things as are denied vs, are not to be deſired.
where if the meate ſtande
before thée, thou muſte take it
modeſtlie: if he, whiche doth bring it,
doe paſſe by thée, ſtaye hym not, or if
he be not yet come to thée, be not ouer
gredy thereof: but ſtay vntill he come
to thée. In like manner thou muſt diſpoſe

thy ſelf, towards thy children, towards
thy wyfe, towards greate men,
and towards riches, ſo at length thou
ſhalt be worthie the table of ye Godds.
But if thou take not that which is ſet
before thée, but doeſt refuſe it: then
thou ſhalt not only be worthy of their
table, but to be their companion: for
when Diogenes, and Heraclitus and
other like to them did thus, worthily,
and of very good righte they were diuine,
and ſo were accompted.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Worthy the table of the Goddes)
He ſignifieth, that the deſpiſing of outwarde &amp;
worldly things is a certaine heauenly thing, &amp;
that it maketh a man like to God. They wer
diuine, &amp; ſo were accompted. Arrogantly
doubtleſſe, and ignorantelye. For howe farre
doth euen the excellenteſt man that euer was
differ from the leaſt part of the Godhead?
               
            
            
               Cap. 21. ¶By what meanes we muſte gouerne oure
Imagination about ſuch things, as ſeme to be
eſchewed.
               
                  
WHen thou doeſt ſée any man
ſorrowful,We muſte haue regard to humanitie in ſuche ſort, that the quietneſſe of minde be retained. and torment hym
ſelf either bicauſe he hath no
tidings of his ſon, either bicauſe
he is dead, either bicauſe he hath
ſpent all, beware enter not into imaginatiō,
that this maketh him vnhappy:
but haue redilie in remembraunce
that it is not the accident, which troubleth
him (ſeing it tormenteth not an
other) but his opinion conceyued therof.
But if thou fall in talke with him,
accommodate thy ſelf to his perturbation,
and moreouer if the matter ſo require,
wéepe alſo with him for companie:
but take héede that thou ſorrowe
not inwardlie.
            
            
               Cap. 22. ¶That it lieth not in vs to chooſe the ſtate of
our life, but to vſe it euen as it chaunceth, by a
very apte ſimilitude.
               THou muſt remember that thou
arte one of the players in an enterlude,We muſte paſſe the whole courſe and time of our life, according to Gods will.
and muſt plaie ye parte,
which the authour thereof ſhall

appoint, thou muſt play be it lōg, be it
ſhorte. If he appointe thée to play the
begger, ye Creple, ye Prince, or the priuate
perſon, do it well and wittilie, for
it lieth in thée to play that part, whervnto
thou art appointed, and in an other
to chooſe and appoint thée.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Which the authors therof ſhall appoint,
That is, whether he be a comicall, or a
tragical Poet? As concerning the very mater the
Greeke Epigram doth declare.
                  
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        ,
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        .
                  
                  Which may thus be engliſhed:

                        What is our life? a gawiſh game
                        a ſweete delighting play.
                        Then cares in gaming lay a ſide,
                        or liue a miſer aye.
                     
                  
                  
                     Nazianzenus doeth almoſt ſignifie
the ſame, but with a more grauitie and
pietie, in theſe verſes worthy to be

had in remembraunce.
                  
                     Mens age ſuspice, terrenas age despice
ſordes,
                     Corporis à vitijs ne ſubigare caue,
                     Quam breuis est haec vita? beatos ſomnia
ludunt:
                     Sors vaga ſic alios, ſic alios
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         rotat.
                     Vita diu durat, nulla peritura ſub aeuo
                     Sancta: labor fructu non caret ille ſuo.
                  
                  Which may after this ſorte be Engliſhed.
                  
                     O minde ſearch high and heauenly things,
                     deſpiſe this earthelie pelfe:
                     Beware, to laweleſſe luſting fleſhe
                     thou ne ſubdue thy ſelfe.
                     How ſone ar ſpent our brittle dais?
                     they dreame, that ſwim in bliſſe:
                     So thoſe and thoſe not all alike
                     doth fickle fortune kiſſe.
                     A life enſuing godly lawes
                     ſhall neuer cleane decaye:
                     So trauaile ſpent in holie deedes
                     his hired meede doth paye.
                  
               
            
            
               
               Cap. 23. ¶By what meanes we ought to gouerne our
Imagination, in looking for diuers things.
               IF thou take the croking of a crow
to be vnluckie,A wyſe man taketh profite by euery chaunce. lette not that imagination
moue thée, but iudge immediatly
in thy ſelf, and ſay: That portendeth
nothyng to me, but eyther to
my body, or to my poſſeſſion, or to my
eſtimation, or to my wyfe, or to my
children: but as touchyng my ſelfe,
they ſignifie nothing but good, at leaſt
wiſe if I will: for what ſo euer ſhall
chaunce, it lieth in mée to haue the
profite and commoditie of it, if I will.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     If thou take the croking. &amp;c. We haue
in ſtede of diuination by flying and crying of
birdes Aſtrologie: Which if by yerely reuolutions
&amp; progreſsions of the ſtarres, it threatten
damages and dangers, let vs not vſe Epictet his
counſell, but godly prayers.
               
            
            
               Cap. 24. ¶Howe to be vnconquerable, being the cauſe
of the former precepte, and as it were the concluſion.
               
                  
THou mayeſt bée inuincible,We muſte take in hand things agreable to oure ſtrength. if
thou neuer enter into battaile,
for thou art vncertain, whether
it lye in thée or no, to haue the
the victorie.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Thou mayeſt bée vnconquerable.
This ſaying dependeth vppon the diuiſion of
things made in the beginning. They are conquered,
which couet other mens goodes, that is,
ſuche as belong to the body, and are placed in
fortunes hande. They conquere, whiche reſiſte
naughtie opinious and deſires, ſo that they contende
according to the lawe.
               
            
            
               Cap. 25. ¶Which is the readieſt way to vertue.
               TAke héede that in following thy
imaginatiō thou ſay at no time,He that ſeketh for all good things of him ſelfe, he doth neither maruell at any mā, nor enuyeth any.
the man is happie, whom thou
doeſt ſée auaunced eyther to honour,
or authoritie, or renoumed: for
if the ſubſtance of goodneſſe be in the
things, which are ſubiecte to vs, there
nether enuie, nor emulatiō taketh any
place. Then thy purpoſe is not to be

Emperour,There is one way to libertie: the deſpiſing of outwarde things. or King, but frée, &amp; frāke.
But vnto that thing there is but one
certaine waye, that is, the contempte
of ſuch things as are not in vs.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     For if the ſubſtaūce of goodneſſe. &amp;c.
The vnderſtanding of this ſentence is vttered
ſtoicallie in darke wordes. He which ſeeketh all
good things of himſelfe, is of a quiet mind: who
ſo is of a quiet minde, he doeth neither enuie,
nor emulate. For ſeing that lack of paine called
in Latin Indolentia excludeth all perturbations:
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        
                     
verely it excludeth enuie and emulation. But if
theſe affections do rule in any: it is manifeſtlie
gathered thereof, that he is farre from the tranquilitie
of the minde, and doth not obey the
preceptes of Philoſophie.
               
            
            
               Cap. 26. ¶A ſolution of them which ſeme to let the
things before mentioned, &amp; how a man ſhould
not be angrie.
               REmember,No man is hurt, but of himſelfe. that he, which taunteth
or beateth, is not ye author
of reproch, but the opinion conceiued
of ye ſame as reprocheful.
Then when any doeth kindle thée to

wrath, vnderſtande that thou art moued
to anger thorow thine opinion.
Wherefore eſpeciallie endeuoure thy
ſelfe,Delay eſtablyſheth iudgement. that imaginations plucke not cō
                  ſente
from thée, for if thou ſhalte once
ſuppreſſe it for a certaine time, thou
ſhalt more eaſilie be thy own Miaſter.
            
            
               Cap. 27. ¶How to learne, and ſet our minde in highe
thinges.
               SEt before thy eyes, deathe, baniſhment,
and all things which ſéeme
terrible, but eſpecially death: in
ſo doing, thou ſhalt not thinke vpō
baſe and vile things, and ſhalte neuer
be excéeding couetous.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     And ſhalt neuer be exceding couetous.
Syracides affirmeth,Syracides. that the imagination of
death, and God his iudgemente doth feare vs frō
ſinne. Which if it do: we are taught to ſuffer aduerſitie
much more paciently, &amp; to deſpiſe proſperitie,
bicauſe of their ſorrow and profit, which
endureth for a little ſpace.Cicero. So Cicero. All pleaſure
ſayth he is to be eſtemed as nothing, which

when it is paſte, it is as if there had ben none at
all. But in great griefe of the bodie and anguiſh
of the minde, one houre ſeemeth longer than a
whole yeare.
               
            
            
               Cap. 28. ¶The ſeconde part, wherein he doeth pointe
him out which hath already profited. And doth
firſt diſſolue ſuch things, as come in vre to the
ſtudents of Philoſophie.
               AS ſoone as thou haſte determined
to leade a perfect lyfe,A Philoſopher ought not to regarde the mockery of the people. prepare
and addreſſe thy ſelf to be
ſcorned and mocked of many,
and to heare what they ſpeake of thée,
wherof commeth this ſodain ſageneſſe
and grauitie? whereof commeth this
ſadneſſe? laye aparte thy ſadde ſowre
countenance. But yet reteine &amp; kepe
theſe things which ſéeme beſt to thée,
in ſuch ſorte, as if this were the front
where God hath ordained and placed
thée to fight.Conſtancie getteth victorie. And if thou perſiſt in the
ſame things, they whiche before haue
mocked thée, will haue thée in admiration:
but if like one fléeing awaye,
thou gyue ouer thy enterpriſe, thou

ſhalte be double as much mocked and
ſcorned.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Lay apart thy ſad ſowre coūtenāce.
That is, a muſing countenance, ſad grauitie and
hautineſſe of minde. And it appeareth by this
ſhorte and quicke ſentence of Menander,Menāder that
this was the countenance of Philoſophers. They
which loke ſtately, ſay, that Solitarineſſe is mete
for meditation.
               
            
            
               Cap. 29. ¶That boſting deſtroyeth the ſtate of a Philoſopher,
in ſhewyng wherevnto he oughte to
leane.
               IF it chaunce at any time, that thou
giue thy ſelf to the things which are
not in vs, and that thou doſt deſire
to pleaſe any man, vnderſtand that
at the ſame preſent thou art fallen frō
thy ſtate.By this worde Philoſopher is ment a wiſe man. Wherefore in all things let
this ſuffiſe thée, to bée a Philoſopher:
But if thou doſt couet to ſéeme to any
a Philoſopher, let it be to thy ſelf, and
that ſhall be ſufficient.
               
                  
                  Annotations.
                  
                     If it chaunce at any tyme that thou
giue thy ſelf. &amp;c. He forbiddeth the deſire of
glorie, &amp; ſeeking for oſtentation, which affectiō
it will be long before it take place in good and
learned men. He woulde haue a Philoſopher to
kepe him ſelf within the limittes of his conſcience,
as an oyſter within his ſhell, and to iudge
that, the moſt noble ſhew of his vertue. Thou
art fallen from thy ſtate, That is to ſaye,
thou arte vanquiſhed.
               
            
            
               Cap. 30. ¶How to aunſwere to ſuch ſtayes as woulde
hinder a man from wiſedome.
               LEtte not theſe cogitations torment
thée,That a Philoſopher euen of ſmall ſubſtaunce, may muche profit the common wealth▪ by teaching of vertue &amp; hys good example. I ſhall not be in honor
nor in place, where I ſhall be regarded:
for if to bée without honour
is an ill thing, thou canſt not be
in euill for an other thing, no more
than in a diſhoneſt thing. Is it in thée
to beare rule, or to be bidden to a banket?
No. What is this then, but to
be without honour? and howe ſayeſt
thou, that thou ſhalte not be eſtemed,
whom it behoueth to to medle in thoſe

things onely which are in our power,
in which thou mayſt beare a great
ſway and ſtroke. But thou wilt ſay I
can not profit my friends. What doeſt
thou call to profite?How a wiſe man aideth his friends. ſhall they haue no
mony of thée? neither wilt thou make
them citizens of Rome? But who told
thée that theſe things be in vs, &amp; other
mens workes? Who can gyue to an
other that he himſelf hath not? Get it,
(ſay they) that we may haue it, alſo.
If I may get it,We ought to require of euerye mā but ſuch things as he maye and ought to performe. kéeping my ſelfe modeſt,
faithful, and valiant, ſhew me the
way, and I will get it. If ye thinke it
méete, that I ſhould loſe my goods, that
you ſhould get ſuch thinges as are not
good, ſée your ſelues haue vnreaſonable
and vngratefull you are? But if
thou preferre a faithfull and ſincere
friende before money, herein help me,
and thinke it not méete that I ſhoulde
doe the things whereby I ſhould looſe
modeſtie and fidelitie: But I can not
ſuccoure nor ayde my coūtrey.How a wiſe mā helpeth his coūtrey. What
doeſt thou call ſuccoure &amp; aide? That
it ſhall not haue of thée, nor by thy

meanes, faire &amp; ſumptuous buildings,
nor baines? What then? hath it not
ſhooes by the Shoemaker and Armour
by the Armorer? It is ſufficient when
euery vocation doth his work. If thou
get it a faithfull and modeſt member,
doeſt thou thinke, that thou bringeſt
it but a little profit? very great doubtleſſe.
In ſo doing thou arte not vnprofitable
to it. In what ſtate ſhall I be in
my coūtry? in that thou maiſt, keping
alwayes fidelitie and modeſtie. But if
ſuppoſing to aide it thou looſe modeſty
and fidelitie, what profit ſhalt thou do
to it, which arte become impudent and
diſloyall.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Thou canſt not be in euil for an other
thing, This ſentence dependeth vpon the opinion
of the ſtoicks, that only honeſty is good, &amp;
onely vice is naught. The contempt and deſpiſing
of me, if I do my duety, is not my vice, therfore
neither my euill, but theyr vice and euyll
who of a peruerſe iudgement &amp; naughty mind
do contemne, diſpiſe, and miſuſe mee without
cauſe. Shewe mée the way, He ſignifieth
that ryches and dignitie is gotten by nothyng

elſe but by deceit, and for that cauſe a good man
ought to deſpiſe them. Neither doth he ſpeake
of them, which ſhewe themſelues vnworthy of
honoure, and they are the cauſe, that they are not
regarded. A faithfull and ſincere friend,
Nowe a daies moſt men had leiffer to haue money.
Neither do they thinke that a poore friend
may help vs in any thing. So are endowed maidens
preferred before them, who are chaſte, and
well brought vp, if perhaps there be any ſuche,
and doe ſo continue. Wherefore the wowers
peraduenture are to be pardoned, who in ſo vncertayne
a hazarde of chaſtitie, &amp; honeſtie, had
rather to abyde the vnquietneſſe of riche than of
poore wiues. Neither hath it Shooes by
the Shooemaker, nor Armour by the
Armourer. The ſence is: ſumptuous buildings
bains, and the citie of Rome is no more to be required
of a Philoſopher, than weapons of the
Shooemaker, or Shooes of the Smyth: ſeyng
that it is the duety of a Philoſopher, to traine vp
his countrey men in vertue, as it is the Shoemakers
duetie to make Shooes, and the Smithes,
Weapons.
               
            
            
               Cap. 31. ¶A continuation of the ſolution of ſuche
things as do hinder him which doth beginne to
ſtudye philoſophie and wiſedome, in ſhewing
that a man ſhould not moue himſelfe, for that
which chaūceth to an other &amp; that he hath nothing
of an other without giuing of his owne.
               
                  
IS there any placed before thée at a
feaſt?We muſt enuie no man, and reioyce of an others good fortune. or was reuerēce done to him
before it was done to thée? or is
he preferred before thée in coūſaile?
If theſe things be good, thou muſt reioyce,
that thy neighbour hath them:
if they be ill: then be not ſorrowfull,
bicauſe they chāced not to thée. Then
remember in giuing thy minde to nothing
elſe,A benefit cō
                     monly is giuen for pleaſure and ſeruice. but to the things which are
in vs, thou canſt not attaine to the
like things, which other doe in them
which are not in vs. Howe may it bée
done, that a man frequentyng not thy
houſe ſhall haue like thynges as hée
whiche haunteth thy houſe, or he that
ſeketh not friendſhip and fauoure, as
he which doth? or he which doth not
pleaſe and praiſe the, as he which doth
pleaſe and praiſe thée? Thou ſhalte be
vniuſt and vnſaciable if thou haue not
payde for ſuche thinges as thou haſte
bought, but doeſt require to haue them

for nothing. Admit the caſe I could not
buye lectuce for a halfe penny,Who ſo lacketh cōmoditie lacketh alſo coſt and diſquietneſſe if any
then buy a half peny worth of lectuce,
and thou doſt buy none: think not thy
ſelf in worſſer caſe &amp; to haue leſſe then
he, which hath bought lectuce: for as
he hath bought ſo thou haſt not giuen
thy halfpenny. Euen ſo it fareth, thou
art not bidden to a mans feaſt, becauſe
thou haſte not giuen him aſmuche as
his feaſte coſte him. He ſelleth it for
praiſe, he ſelleth it for ſeruice. Giue
him then (if thou thinke it good) the
pryce, for the whiche he ſolde it thée.
But if thou wilte not performe that
and take theſe things, thou arte vnſatiable
and fooliſh. Haſt thou giuen nothing
in ſteade of the feaſt? Yes mary,
for thou haſt not praiſed him, whome
thou wouldeſt, and haſte not ſuffered
him in his portly going.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     If theſe thinges be good, Bycauſe they are
good, they are ſorrowfull that they coulde not

attaine to them: bicauſe they be euill, they are
glad, that they are chaunced to other, And haſt
not ſuffered. &amp;c. Pride and ambitious ſalutations
of riche men do ſeeme to be vnderſtoode
in this place very troublous to a ſimple and
learned man, in like maner ſalutations, retinues,
praiſes. But perhaps rich men giuen to pleaſures,
going in their pompe, were wonte on euery
ſide to leane and cleaue to Paraſites.
               
            
            
               Cap. 32. ¶What thinges are common euen according
to the will of nature.
               THe purpoſe and will of nature,We muſt not iudge otherwiſe of oure owne miſfortune than of other mens.
may be iudged by theſe things,
in which we differ not one from
an other: as for exaumple, if a
mans ſeruaunt breake his Maiſters
cuppe or any other thing, incontinently
it is ſaide this is a thing which oftē
                  times
chaūceth: remember then when
thine is broken, that thou be the ſame
maner of man, as thou were when the
other mans cuppe was broken. And ſo
do in greater thyngs. If a mans child
or wife chaunce to dye, there is no mā
                  
but will ſaye incontinently this is naturall.
Notwithſtanding euery man
when any of his is dead, he doth lamēt
and bewaile pitifully: But we muſte
remember how we are diſpoſed, when
we haue hearde any ſuche thing of others.
            
            
               Cap. 33. ¶Howe one ought to vnderſtande the nature
of yll.
               EVen as the white whereat Archers
ſhoote,It is in our choyſe whether we wil be troubled with the opinion of yl things. is not ſet ther, wher
it may not be ſtricken, ſo it is of
the nature of ill in this worlde,
for it is not ſet out to be embraced,
but to be eſchued: as if goodneſſe were
ſette for the white, and euill were all
that, wher the white were not, beſides
the white, the Archer hath an ample
and large ſpace to ſhoote frō the white:
ſo without the onely marke of goodneſſe
on euery ſide is placed euil, which
is as eaſy to be done and committed,
as it is difficill to hitte the white, or to
doe good.
            
            
               
               Cap. 34. ¶We ought not abandon our minde to wrath
for iniuries done: and how to take in hand our
enterpriſes.
               IF any deliuer thy body to the firſte
he meteth, it wil greue thée excedingly:
but when thou doeſt yelde thy
minde to the firſt that commeth, as
when thou arte wronged, thy mynde
is troubled and heauy, arte not thou
aſhamed?A premeditation and a diligent preparatiō putteth away ignomie and repentance. Before thou take any thing
in hande, conſider firſt the beginning,
and the ſequele, &amp; then take it in hand.
If thou do not ſo thou ſhalte neuer be
certaine and ſure in thy enterpriſes,
not regarding that which may befall,
but after when any diſhoneſt thinges
chaunce, thou ſhalte be aſhamed.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     If any deliuer thy bodie to the firſt he
meteth, He argueth from a leſſe thing to a
more, after this ſort: thou wilt be angrie with
them, which gaue power to any to violate thy
bodie (ſuch is the condition of them whiche are
baniſhed) how much more oughteſt thou to be
angrie with thy ſelfe, whiche art wont to giue

power to euerie man to hurte thy minde, wheras
it lieth in thee not to be hurt of any man at
all?
               
            
            
               Cap. 35. ¶An effectuall example to conſider what
may befall in euerie thing which we ſhall take
in hande.
               WIlt thou cōquere at ye playes
Olimpia?
                  Temeritie is the mother of lightneſſe and inconſtancie. And I by ye faith
of my bodie: for it is a verie
honourable thing, but conſider
wel the beginning, and the ſequele
and then take the matter in hande.
Thou muſt order well thy ſelfe, &amp; vſe
neceſſarie meats, abſtaine frō delicate
and daintie things, and exerciſing thy
ſelfe, according as it is expediente for
the time and houre appointed, be it
hote or colde, not drinking water or
wine, if occaſiō ſo require. And briefly
thou muſt commit thy ſelfe whollie to
the chiefe of the games as to the Phiſicion
in doing that whiche he ſhal appoint
thée. Afterward enter into fight,
and ſometime to haue thy hand hurt,

thy foote out of ioynte, to ſwallowe
downe much duſt, to receiue gréeuous
ſtrokes, and otherwhile after all this
to be vanquiſhed. When thou haſte
conſidered all theſe things, if thou be
willing, go and fight, otherwyſe thou
ſhalt be like the little boyes which are
now wraſtlers, nowe ſwordplayers,
nowe trumpetters, forthwith players
in tragedies. So thou alſo now a fighter,
now a ſwordplayer, afterward an
Oratour, at length a Philoſopher: but
throughly nothing at al, but as an Ape
thou doeſt counterfait and reſemble al
things, and nowe one thing ſhall lyke
thée, now an other: for thou haſt not
done thy enterpriſe aduiſedly, in foreſéeyng
the circumſtances, but aduenturouſlie
following a lighte and colde
deſire. So the greater number, when
they ſée a Philoſopher, or when they
heare ſay that Socrates ſpeaketh wel,
(but who can ſpeake ſo well as he?)
they will incontinentlie diſpute and
reaſon of Philoſophie, and ſearche the
cauſes and nature of things. Man firſt

conſider the thing, &amp; the qualitie therof,
and then enterpriſe it.Bothe the thyng and our nature is to be conſidered and compared together. Afterwarde
trie whether thy nature be able to endure
that whiche may happen. Wilte
thou be a wraſtler? behold thy armes,
thy thighes, and thy loines: For nature
mother of all things, hath framed
euery man to ſome particular thing.
Doeſt thou thinke that endeuouring
thy ſelfe about theſe things yu mayeſt
liue as thou haſt bene accuſtomed? As
to drinke ſo much as thou wer wont,
to be angrie ſo muche as thou were
wont? Thou muſt be vigilante, thou
muſt trauell, thou muſte ſet aſide thy
proper affaires, thou muſte be mocked
of boyes, diſpiſed of all the world, and
in all things to haue leſte authoritie,
be it in honoure, in office, or in iudgement,
and in all other affaires.Conſtancie is to be obſerued. Then
conſider al theſe things, and loke whether
in their ſtéede, thou haddeſt leiuer
to haue reſt and libertie, without
any perturbation. But if thou haddeſt
not leiuer to haue it, ſée that thou take
not in hande many things, to the ende

that (as I haue tolde thée) like little
boyes, thou be not now a philoſopher,
now a lawyer, afterward an aduocate
laſtlie the Proctor of Ceſar. All which
things knitte in one, can in no wiſe agree:
for it muſt néedes be that thou be
either a good or an ill man, that thou
addict thy ſelfe to interiour or exteriour
thinges: that thou poſſeſſe the
place of a Philoſopher and well aduiſed
man, or of a Foole and Ideote.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     At the playes Olympia. Olympia
were playes as running, wreſtling, and ſuche other
faictes of actiuitie accuſtomablie kepte in
the honour of Iupiter Olympicus, at Piſa &amp; Helides
Cities in Greece. Man firſte conſider,
He ſignifieth as to wraſtling, to leaping and rū
                     ning,
al are not meete, ſo neither to Philoſophie,
both haue neede of pacience of bodie &amp; minde.
Of which things, whoſo is deſtitute, he ſhal be
rather a counterfayt then a very wraſtler &amp; Philoſopher.
Thou muſt be mocked of little
boyes,) Verely Philoſophers were wonte of al
men to be diſpiſed, but great ſtoute champions
were in admiration.
               
            
            
               
               Cap. 36. ¶That dueties do ariſe of nature, and that they
are conſidered howe a man ſhoulde behaue him
ſelfe towardes any man, nexte of the dueties towards
men.
               DVtie is meaſured by mutual affections.We muſte do our duetie towards all men, although other mē do not their duetie towards vs.
If thou haue a father,
thou muſt regarde and honoure
him: giue place to him in all
things, and if he chide or beate thée, indure
it. He is a naughtie father thou
wilt ſay. Nature hath enioyned vs the
obedience of the father without mention
of good. Arte thou not ioyned by
nature with a good father? No, but
with a father. Wherfore do thy dutie
towards him, and conſider not what
he doth: but do ſuch things, whereby
thou maieſt kepe thy purpoſe agreable
to nature. No man will hurte thée excepte
thou wilte. Thou ſhalte be then
hurted, when thou ſhalte thinke thy
ſelfe hurt. So thou ſhalt do the dutie of
neyghbour to neyghbour, of Citizen
to Citizen, of lord to lord, if thou accuſtome
thy ſelfe to conſider the mutuall

affections.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     By mutuall affections. Affections are vſed
as a certaine rule to meaſure dueties by.
               
            
            
               Cap. 37. ¶What our dueties are towards GOD, and how
to behaue vs in his doings.
               THe principall point of honoring
God, is to thinke well of him, to
beleue that he is, that he hath
created all things, and that well
and iuſtly he gouerneth them:Their religion is nothing worth whiche do not place felicitie in the riches of the minde. afterward
to obey him, accepting al things
that he doth, as procéeding of a very
good intent. In ſo doing, thou ſhalte
not blaſpheme God, neither ſhalt thou
accuſe him of negligence. Thou arte
not able to do this, otherwiſe, excepte
thou withdraw thy ſelf frō the things
which are not in vs, and placing good
and ill in them which are in vs. But if
thou eſtéeme any of the things, which
are not in vs, to be good or ill, thou
muſt of neceſſity, when thou doeſt not

attaine to that whiche thou wouldeſt,
or when thou doeſt fal into that which
thou doeſt ſhunne, blame and hate the
cauſe of ſuch an accidēt which is good.
All liuing creatures haue this by nature,Tull. 1. Offic.
that they flée and eſchewe ſuche
things, and ſéeme vnto them noyſome,
and their cauſes: but contrarywiſe
they ſearch, &amp; maruell at theſe things
which ſéeme to bring profite, and the
cauſes of them. He then which thinketh
himſelfe hurte, can take no delite
in that which vnto him ſéemeth hurtefull.
So it is impoſſible that a man
hurte may reioyce. And hereof it commeth
to paſſe that the ſon doth checke
the father, when the father maketh
him not partaker of the things, which
ſéeme good vnto him. This is that,
which made diſcorde betwene Polinix
and Eteocles, bycauſe they eſtéemed
rule good. For this cauſe the huſbandman,
for this cauſe the Mariner, for
this cauſe the Marchant, for this cauſe
they which looſe their wife and childrē
do oftentimes defile and deteſt God,

for wheras vtilitie is,Where as vtilitie is, there is pietie. there is alſo pietie.
Wherfore he that doth endeuor to
deſire and flée that, euen as he ought,
by the ſame meanes he obſerueth and
kéepeth pietie.He preferreth the rites of a coū
                     trey before the truthe. As touching offerings
and oblations let euery man doe them
according to the guiſe of his countrey:
purely, without ſuperfluitie, according
to his abilitie, without negligence or
nigardſhippe.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Whereas vtilitie is, there is pietie,
O wonderfull ſentence, and alſo wicked to ſee
to: but ſo applied that it vncouereth the disſimulation
of mans minde, and can ſcarce be nothing
more agreeable to religion. Guiſe of his
countrey. Foraſmuche as pietie conſiſteth in
the mind, he thinketh that we ſhould not much
regarde ceremonies. Which if it mighte be perſwaded
to ſome men which are in theſe dayes,
we ſhould liue more quietlie. It mighte be perſwaded,
if we woulde rather endeuoure to lyue
according to religion, than to diſpute of religiō:
if we were rather deſirers of the veritie than of
vanitie, that is, of ambition, of emulation, of couetouſneſſe,
of reuengemente, and of ſuche like

confuſions and deſtructions of the minde, if
there be any other.
               
            
            
               Cap. 38. ¶What maner of man he ought to be that cō
                  meth
to a Diuinour, and how to vſe diuinations,
wherin reſteth our duetie towardes God, and towardes
our ſelues.
               IF thou deſire and ſeke to knowe
that which is to come of any thing,The diuinour is not to be counſeled of our duetie, but of the ſu
                        •
                     
                     ceſſe of certaine actiōs
firſt thou muſt vnderſtande yt thou
art ignoraunt of that ſhal come, and
therefore thou doeſt goe to the Diuinour
to knowe it of hym. Notwithſtanding
if thou be wiſe thou arte not
ignoraunt what it is, nor the qualitie
therof. For if it be among the number
of the thinges whiche are not in vs,
truelie it is neceſſarie, that it be neither
good nor ill. Remoue then from
thée (if thou go to the Diuinour) al deſire
&amp; eſchuing other thou ſhalte come
to him trembling and quakyng. But
when thou ſhalt vnderſtande, whatſoeuer
ſhall befall to appertain nothing
to thée, and of thée not to be paſſed vpō
                  
thou mayeſt vſe it well, and no man
ſhall forbid thée. Therfore goe &amp; aſke
counſaile of God, as of him who can
giue thée very good, and after he hath
giuen thée counſaile, remember whō
thou haſt called to counſaile, &amp; whoſe
counſaile thou haſt deſpiſed. Coūſaile
may be demaunded of the Diuinour
(as Socrates ſayeth) for ſuch things,
whoſe conſideration is referred to the
end, the knowledge of which ende, occaſion
cannot be giuen by any maner
of meanes, nor any arte. And therfore
thou muſt not aſke counſaile of the
Diuinour, whether thou ſhalt put thy
life in daunger for thy country, or for
thy friend, if nede require, for if he perceiue
any vnluckie ſigne, it is altogether
manifeſt, that it ſignifieth death,
or ſome impedimente of thy bodie, or
baniſhment: but reaſon telleth &amp; perſwadeth
thée, that thou muſte put thy
ſelfe in daunger for Countrey, or for
thy friend whē néede requireth. Giue
eare then to that which the great Diuine
Apollo ſayeth, who did chaſe

out of his temple, the man, which helped
not his frend being in daunger of
death.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Remember whome thou haſt called
to counſaile, It muſt needes be, that the cunning
of the diuinours, ſouthſayers, was in diuination
very great. Otherwiſe a man of ſo greate
grauitie woulde not haue accompted their prophecies,
for diuine aunſwers.
               
            
            
               Cap. 39. ¶Dueties towards our ſelues, &amp; firſte of ſuch
as tende to the conſtancie of maners, and what
thinges let it, and chiefly of talke and ſilence.
               THou muſt preſcribe a rule and
faſhion,We muſt determin who and what maner of men wee will be. which from hence forth
thou ſhalte obſerue when thou
art alone and when thou art in
companie. Let ſilence be kept for the
moſt part: or let neceſſarie things be
talked of, and theſame in fewe words.
But if the time require thée to ſpeake,We muſte rule our tongue.
ſpeake: but not of all thinges, not of
the combate betwene fenſers, not of
rūning with horſes, not of wraſtlers,

not of meates &amp; drinkes triflingly, nor
principally of men, in praiſing or blaming
them, or comparing them with
others. And if thou be able, chaūge thy
familiars Communication into that
which is honeſt and comelie. But if
thou be enuironed with ſtraungers,
holde thy peace.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Enuironed with ſtraungers, He vnderſtandeth
thoſe men, whome bicauſe of their eſtimation
and authoritie he dareth not admoniſhe.
               
            
            
               Cap. 40. ¶Of laughing.
               LAughe not muche,Laughter. nor at all communication,
neither a loude.
            
            
               Cap. 41. ¶Of Othes.
               SWere not,Othes. neither make an othe
if it be poſſible for thée. But if
thou canſt not otherwiſe do, do it

when it ſhall be nedefull.
            
            
               Cap. 42. ¶What conuerſation may do.
               FRequent not the bankets and familiaritie
of the cōmon ſort,Bankets. and
ſtraungers. But if occaſion ſo require,
be mindeful and take héede
that thou become not one of the common
ſort. And vnderſtande thou that
he which wreſtleth with the defiled,
muſt néedes be defiled alſo.
            
            
               Cap. 43. ¶Of the vſe of ſuche things as belong to the
bodie.
               AS touching the body, take ſuch
things as ſhal be to his vſe and
alſo be profitable for the mind,
as meate, drinke, apparell, harbour.
But as touching daintie and delicate
diſhes, thou muſt altogether reiect
them, and baniſhe them from thée.
            
            
               Cap. 44. ¶Of the acte of Nature.
               
                  
TOuching Venerie we ought as
muche as is poſſible, to leade a
chaſt life before mariage. But if
we be cōſtrained, we muſt take
nothing but that which is lawful: not
withſtanding reproue them not which
vſe it, in blaming them, and auaūting
thy ſelfe abroade, that thou doeſt not
vſe it.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     In blaming them. Chriſtian charitie commaundeth
that ſinners ſhould be reproued, and
obſtinate perſons to be eſchued.
               
            
            
               Cap. 45. ¶Againſt anger, and what manner of men we
ſhould ſhewe our ſelues towards backebiters.
               IF any bring thée worde,An yl report is not to bee paſſed vpon. ſuch a man
miſreporteth and backebiteth thée.
Excuſe not that which he hath ſaid,
but make this aunſwere: he is ignoraunt
of many other great faults, and
imperfections which are in me, otherwiſe,
he woulde not onely haue ſayd
this.
            
            
               
               Cap. 46. ¶How to behaue our ſelues in ſhewes and
triumphes.
               IT is not requiſite to frequent often
the ſhewes and turnaments.Shewes are to be ſeene with a quiet minde. But if
at any time occaſion requireth, ſée
that thou ſéeme not to fauoure any
man more than thy ſelfe, that is, wilt
thou onely haue that done whiche is
done: and him only to conquer, which
conquereth? For ſo thou ſhalte not
be empeched. Abſtaine thy ſelf altogether
frō ſhouting, frō conſenting countenaunce,
and let not thy geſture be
ſad and graue, but ſomewhat merry.
At thy returne from the ſhewes, talke
not much of the thinges whiche haue
ben there done or ſaid, ſeing they auail
nothing to thy amendement.
            
            
               Cap. 47. ¶Of the deſire of ſuche as go to heare others
communication.
               APproch not néere them, whom
thou ſéeſt to commen apart, and
be not thou preſent if it be poſſible,

or as ſeldome as thou mayeſt.
But if thou be preſente kepe in ſuche
wiſe thy conſtancie, that thou ſhewe
thy ſelfe voyde of all perturbations.
            
            
               Cap. 48. ¶When one hath to ſpeake with a noble perſonage.
               IF thou haue any thing to do eſpecially
with ſuche as are of noble
blood,In meetings, we muſt folow the examples of wiſe men. and great authoritie. Cōſider
what Socrates or Zeno haue done
herein, or the wiſeſt man yt euer thou
diddeſt knowe, and ſo thou ſhalte not
be in doubte, howe thou muſt behaue
thy ſelfe.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     What Socrates or Zeno,
                      That may be gathered
out of bothe their ſayinges and doings,
foraſmuch as we haue not any thing written of
neither of them. But vnleſſe thou ſhalt be endewed
with the learning and conſtancie of them
both fooliſh imitatiō will turne thee to ſhame.
And perhappes they obſerued not euery where a
ſeemelineſſe and grace.
               
            
            
               
               Cap. 49. ¶How we ought to prepare our ſelues, when
we goe to ſpeake with a man of honoure.
               WHen thou wilt go to ſuch a man
as is of greate honoure,The difficult comming to noble men is to be ſuffered. preſuppoſe
in thy minde, what may chaunce,
that (poſſibly) thou ſhalt not be receiued,
that thou ſhalte be ſhutte oute of
doores, that the gate ſhall not be opened,
or that he will not regarde thée.
Afterwarde ponder with thy ſelfe, if
with all theſe thyngs, it bée expedient
for thée to go to him: and when thou
ſhalte come before him, ſuffer and endure
that which ſhalbe done, and ſaye
not to thy ſelfe: I deſerue not to be
thus entreated: for it is to common a
thing to reproue and blame the thinges
which are not in vs.
            
            
               Cap. 50. ¶When we meete with many men, how to
frame our communication.
               IN company ſpeake not ouermuche,
nor beyonde meaſure, of thy déedes,

neither of thy daungers: for it can
not ſo much contente other to heare
them as thy ſelfe to reherſe them.Laughter is not to bee moued. Sée
alſo that thou moue no laughter by
thy communication, for that (I wote
not how) engendreth diſdaine, and alſo
cauſeth that no reuerence is giuen
to thée by them which are preſent. And
very often leadeth thy communication
to filthy and diſhoneſt talke:Ribauldrie is to be abhorred. But
if it befall, and that the matter and
time require it, reproue him that ſhall
vſe ſuch ribauldrie and filthyneſſe. If
not, at the leaſt ſhewe and declare by
ſilence and ſhamefaſtneſſe, that ſuche
communication doth diſpleaſe thée.
            
            
               Cap. 51. ¶Howe to reſiſt pleaſure.
               IF thou cōceyue any pleaſure in thy
minde,It is better to deſpiſe than to embrace pleaſure. be circumſpecte (euen as in
other things) that ſhée beguile thée
not, but examine the matter, &amp; take
ſpace to deliberate on it. Afterwarde
conſider both the times, that is to ſay,
the time wherin thou doſt enioy pleaſure,

and the time wherein after the
enioying of it thou mayſte repent thée
for hauing enioyed it. And afterwarde
reproue thy ſelf, and conſider how wel
at eaſe and contented thou ſhalte bée,
if thou abſtaine thy ſelfe, and in ſo doing
thou doeſt commende thy ſelfe.
But yf the matter ſéeme to require
thée to doe▪ it, beware that hir flatteries,
hir ſwéeteneſſe, and hir inticements
ouercome thée not, but conſider
how farre better it ſhall be, if thou be
able to winne the victorie of that conflicte.
            
            
               Cap. 52. ¶That we oughte not to leaue off our good
purpoſe, what ſoeuer men ſay.
               WHen thou arte reſolued to do any
thing,Oure duetie oughte to moue vs, and not the communication of the people and haſt not yet done
it, refuſe not to be ſéene in doing therof,
although other may iudge amiſſe
thereof, for if thou do euill, thou muſte
geue ouer thy worke: if thou do wel,
feare them not who wrongfully, and
without cauſe ſhall reproue thée.
            
            
               
               Cap. 53. ¶Of the honeſtie that we ought to keepe at
the table.
               WHo hath ſaid:We muſte not haue regard to our owne luſte but to the Communaltie. it is daye, and
it is night, taking the propoſition
ſeuerally we ought to
agrée, but to vnderſtande it
together, it is not to be receyued. So
at the table to chooſe for our ſelues the
greateſt, &amp; the beſt parte of the meate,
is a greate commoditie towardes the
bodye, but it is againſt the honeſt participation
that we ought to haue at
the table. Then if at any time thou be
bidden to a banket,In feaſtes modeſtie is to be obſerued. remēber that thou
muſte not onely haue regarde to the
meate, for the profite of thy body: but
alſo to honeſtie, and to behaue thy ſelf
at the table, as thou oughteſt.
               
                  Annotations.
                  Wheras before he compared our life to a feaſt,
let this precept be applied to all the parts of our
life: and euery where let there not be a reſpecte
to our priuate deſire and vtilitie, but of equitie &amp;
ſocietie, &amp; let the will of the feaſter, that is God,
be conſidered.
               
            
            
               
               Cap. 54. ¶That we ſhould not vndertake more than
we are able to do.
               IF thou haue taken more in hande,We ought to meaſure our ſtrēgth in al things
than thou arte able to atchieue or
bring to paſſe: thou ſhalt not bring
it to effect, and alſo haſt omitted that
which thou were able to performe.
            
            
               Cap. 55. ¶That we ought to be circumſpect aſwell to
ſaue the minde harmeleſſe, as the body.
               EVen as in going thou doeſt take
héede that thou ſteppe not vppon
a nayle,We muſt endeuour to haue a perfect minde. or that thou wreaſte not
thy foote: ſo in leading thy life
take héede, that thou hurte not thy
minde, the gouerneſſe of all thy doinges,
which if we obſerue in al things,
we ſhall without daunger take them
in hande.
            
            
               Cap. 56. ¶Of the poſſeſsion of ſuche things as belong
to the body.
               
                  
THe bodie is to euery man the
forme of riches,A few thinges are ſufficient for nature, but infinite ſubſtance ſuffiſeth not couetouſneſſe as the foote is of
the ſhooe. If then in thys thou
perſeuer, thou ſhalte kepe the
meane: if thou excede, thou muſt néeds
as it were, fall downe headlong: as if
thou be more curious about the faſhiō
of the ſhooe, then is nedeful for ye foote,
thou wilt make him of golde, after of
purple, laſte of all ſet with ſtuddes of
gold: for there is no end of that thing
which hath once paſſed meaſure.
            
            
               Cap. 56. ¶For maydens vnmaried.
               WOmen after .xiiij. yeares of age
are called of louers Ladies:Modeſtie in women is more to bee regarded, than theyr beautie. for
after this age men (to the end to company
with them) endeuoure wholly to
pleaſe them. To obtaine then mennes
good will afterwarde they become very
curious in trimming and decking
themſelues. Wherfore they muſte be
admoniſhed, that for no other cauſe
we eſteme them, but bicauſe they are
modeſt, wiſe and honeſt, bearing reuerence

and obedience to their huſbandes.
            
            
               Cap. 57. ¶That more care is to be had of the mynde
than of the bodie.
               TO perſiſte and continewe in
things which belong to the bodie,We muſt be ſtow much time in garniſhing of the minde, but a little in the body
for pleaſures ſake, as in
much exerciſe, in muche trimming,
&amp; adorning of the bodie, is ſigne
of an abiecte minde, and verie muche
ſwaruing from nature, and alſo it is
a ſigne of conſenting to ſuperfluitie:
for we embrace pleaſure, and reioyce
in things which we allowe. We muſt
thinke then the excéeding care of the
bodie to be frō the purpoſe: but principallie
we muſte be carefull of that
whereof the bodie is but the inſtrument,
that is, the minde.
            
            
               Cap. 58. ¶A precept to learne pacience
and meekeneſſe.
               
                  
WHen any hath miſuſed thée either
in word or déede, remember that
he doth ſuppoſe it to be done and ſaide
according to his dutie. Wherfore it is
impoſſible for him to followe thy aduiſe
and counſaile, but his own. But
if he iudge amiſſe, he is hurt whiche is
deceyued. For if any do iudge hidden
truthe to be a lye, the truthe hydden is
not hurte, but he which ſhal be deceyued.
If ſo be then thou be perſwaded,
thou ſhalt ſhewe thy ſelfe gentle and
paciente towards him that hath iniuried
thée. And at euerie thing thou
ſhalt ſay, it hath ſo pleaſed him.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     He doth ſuppoſe it to be done according
to his dutie. Pletho putteth vs in mind
of the ſame,Pletho. that alſo we ſhoulde be blamed,
which are able to perſwade one thing, and can
not induce others into our opinion. But thou
wilt ſay, oftentimes vnreaſonable and ſlaunderous
men know that ſuch things as they do are
diſhoneſt and ſhamefull for them to do. Epictetus
maketh aunſwere: they ar ſo much the more
worſe &amp; miſerable: but thou art neuer the more
worſe and miſerable. But their diſhoneſtie is to

me a damage, bicauſe they hurte my eſtimation,
bicauſe they diminiſh my ſubſtāce, bicauſe they
doe afflict my body by violence or witchcraft,
bicauſe they hinder my cōmodities? Epictet wil
make aunſwere, that theſe are none of thine, but
other mens, and to appertaine nothing to thee.
Wherof much is ſpoken of before. The hidden
truth, As it is in Sophocles in Electra, Oreſtes
was not therfore dead, bicauſe he had perſwaded
himſelfe to bring his bones ſhutte in a
coffin to Egiſthus and others.
               
            
            
               Cap. 59. ¶That all things partely do agree the one
with the other, and partly do diſagree.
               EVery thing hath .tj. handels, one
whereby it may be carried,The handle of humanitie and not of immanitie is to be taken. the other
whereby it may not. If thy
brother be yll condicioned, take
him not by that whereby he is yll condicioned,
for it is the handle whereby
he cannot be carried, but take him by
that, whereby he is thy brother, and
whereby he is nouriſhed with thée, in
ſo doing thou ſhalt take him by ye handle,
whereby he ought to be carried.
            
            
               
               Cap. 60. ¶That bicauſe of knoweledge, or hauing
more than other, we cannot inferre that we are
better.
               THeſe words agrée not together
I am richer than thou,We muſte not triūph of the giftes of fortune, but of the riches of the minde. therfore
better. I am wiſer &amp; better learned
than thou art, therfore I am
better: but theſe agrée farre better. I
am richer than thou art, then my poſſeſſion
is better than thine. I am wiſer
and better learned than thou arte,
my words then are better than thine,
but thou art neither thy poſſeſſion nor
yet thy communication.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     But thou art neither. &amp;c. Thou wylte
ſay, yea: but bicauſe of riches, eloquence, and power,
I am much regarded. The ſame doth Epictet
reproue, who thinketh good onely wiſedome
and vertue to be much ſet by. What man
except he were a very naughtie and wicked flatterer,Nero.
hath had Nero the Emperour in greate eſtimation,
although beſides his ryches and Empire,
he were eloquent, a Poet, and a Muſician?
The minde of a perfect man abhorreth to allow
thoſe, whoſe foliſhneſſe and diſhoneſtie is knowen,

in what faſhion ſoeuer honour for a ſhewe
be giuen to them, bicauſe of the giftes of fortune,
and corrupte conuerſation.
               
            
            
               Cap. 61. ¶Of an exact iudgement in things.
               IF any waſhe himſelfe ſpéedily, ſaye
not that hée waſheth himſelf naughtily,Not onely the deede it ſelfe, but the cauſe of the dede is to be conſidered.
but ſpedily. If any drinke much,
ſay not that he drinketh naughtily,
but muche, for if thou knowe not why
he doth it, howe doeſt thou know that
he doth naughtily? So it ſhall chaunce
that we doe receyue and ſupporte the
fantaſies and imaginations of ſome,
and to other we agrée.
            
            
               Cap. 62. ¶Againſt glorie and oſtentation. And firſt as
touching knowledge.
               REpute not thy ſelfe a Philoſopher
in any caſe:Philoſophie is not to be declared by words, but by deedes. nether diſpute
not much of precepts, but rather
put ſome thing in execution, as
at the table, teach not how one ſhould
eate his meate, but eate as it behoueth

thée.Nothyng muſt be ſpoken vnaduiſedly. For remember that Socrates did
ſo ſet aſide all oſtentation. But if at any
time theſe precepts come in queſtion,
ſpeake as little as is poſſible, for it
is daungerous to vomite that which
the ſtomacke hath not well digeſted.
And if it chaunce, that a man tell thée,
that thou knoweſt nothing, and that it
moueth thée not,The Sheepe declare by their wooll and milke how much they haue eaten. vnderſtande that this
is a great entraunce of thy worke, for
the ſhéepe vomiting vp their graſſe, declare
not to ye Shepherds how muche
they haue eatē, but digeſting it within
they ſhewe wtout their fine wooll and
milke. Thou therfore ſhewe not, neither
vtter thy learning to ye rude and
ignoraūt: but declare ſome effects outwardly
of that being well digeſted.
            
            
               Cap. 63. ¶Againſt the boaſting of ſobrietie and ſufferaunce.
               GLory not thy ſelfe to haue mortified,Oſtentation is to be eſchued.
empaired, and weakened
thy body thorough abſtinence:
Neither if thou haſte dronken
nothing but water, ſaye not at euery

occaſion, I drinke nothing but water.
But conſider how much more abſtinēt
the poore are, who craue almes, ſuffering
and enduring muche more than
thou. Furthermore conſider howe many
perfections and vertues thou haſte
not, which other haue. But if thou wilt
exerciſe thy ſelf in paine and pacience,
do it by thy ſelf, and ſéeke not to aduertiſe
other of it, as they do who ſuffring
wrong of great men, ſette images on
fire, &amp; ſay, we are vndone, to the end to
moue &amp; aſſemble the people. For a bragger
is altogether mindefull of worldely
things, and turneth topſie turuie the
goodneſſe of paciēce and abſtinence, bicauſe
he determineth the ende of them
is to haue, the good opinion and prayſe
of many.
            
            
               Cap. 64. ¶The deſcription of a triple qualitie or propertie,
that is, of the vnlearned, of the Philoſopher,
and of him that beginneth to learne.
               THe condicion and ſtate of the vnlearned
is, to looke for of hym ſelfe

neither profite nor damage, but of outwarde
thyngs. The ſtate and condicion
of the philoſopher is, to looke for of
himſelfe all vtilitie and diſcommoditie.
The ſigne of him which beginneth to
profite is,The ſignes of him whiche profiteth that he diſpraiſe no man, that
he praiſe no mā, that he cōplaine of no
man, yt he accuſe no mā, that he ſpeake
nothing of himſelf, as though he were
any body, or knewe any thing. When
he ſhal be at any tyme empeched or diſturbed,
he blameth none but himſelfe.
And if one commende him, he mocketh
him couertly which cōmendeth him, if
he be diſpraiſed, he purgeth nor iuſtifieth
himſelf: but liueth like a ſicke perſon
fearing to moue &amp; troble any thing
within him before he be recouered. He
ſetteth apart all appetite, and fléeth the
thinges which are againſte the nature
of them whiche are in vs. He vſeth a
light endeuour aboute all things, and
paſſeth not whether he be tearmed a
Foole or an Ideote. And (in briefe) he
watcheth himſelfe, as his Enimie and
Spye.
               
                  
                  Annotations.
                  
                     That he dyſpraiſe no man, That is
through curioſitie and too much diligence in other
mens matters, or prouoked thoroughe ſelfe
loue: Epitecte commendeth Agrippinus, but
why? that other ſhoulde follow his example. He
reproueth other, wherefore? that they ſhoulde
be amended.
               
            
            
               Cap. 65. ¶That learning is not only to be expounded
but alſo to liue according as it doth preſcribe.
               IF any do auaunte that he can well
interprete and expounde the ſentences
of Chriſippus,
                  They are Grāmarians not Philoſophers, whiche doe expounde the preceptes of wiſe men, &amp; follow them not. ſay with thy ſelf,
if Chriſippus had not writtē darkly,
&amp; obſcurely, I ſhould haue nothing
wherewith to auaunte my ſelfe. But
Chriſippus hath not written, to the
ende he would be interpreted, but to
the end that according to his doctrine
we ſhould liue. If then I vſe his preceptes,
then ſhall I attaine to ye goodneſſe
of them. But if I maruell at the
interpretation, or if I can well interprete
it my ſelfe, I maruel at the Grā
                  marian,

not at the Philoſopher, or elſe
play the Grāmarian not the Philoſopher.
But what auaileth it to haue
founde written remedies, to vnderſtande
them well, and being ſicke thy
ſelfe not to vſe them?
            
            
               Cap. 66. ¶That we ought to perſeuer in goodneſſe.
               THou muſt be ſtable and firme in
thy good purpoſe and deliberation
of life,Preceptes are to be obeied, and wordes are not to be regarded. euē as in a law. Perſeuer
therfore, euē as if in trāſgreſſing,
thou ſhouldeſt incurre the
crime of impietie. And whatſoeuer mē
talke of thée, regarde it not, for that belongeth
not to thée.
            
            
               Cap. 67. ¶That we ought not to deferre from day to
day, for to leade a perfect life.
               HOw lōg yet wilt thou deferre
to eſteme thy ſelfe at any tyme
worthy of theſe thinges which
are ſo excellēt, and not to trāſgreſſe

one? But if frō day to day thou
doſt deferre ye time, thou doſt not auāce
but hinder thy ſelfe. Then incontinētly
accuſtome thy ſelfe to liue as perfecte,
and to vſe well all accidents and
chaunces. And in euery thing ſuppoſe
that the combate is ready for thée, and
neglecte no time, for that daye in the
which thou doeſt not profit, thou doeſt
receyue damage. After this manner
Socrates became the wiſeſt of al. But
yf thou bée not yet Socrates, thou
oughteſt to liue as, one that would become
Socrates.
               
            
            
               Cap. 68. ¶Three places in Philoſophie, and the order
of them together.
               THe firſte and moſte neceſſarie
place is that which appertaineth
to the practiſe of knowledge:Precepts are better than the cauſe of preceptes, and the Methode of demonſtratiōs. as,
not to lye. The ſeconde whiche
appertaineth to demonſtrations: as,
how commeth it to paſſe that this is
demonſtration? What demonſtration
is? what cōſequence is? what fighting

is? what is true? what is falſe? Therefore
ye thirde place is neceſſarie for the
ſeconde, the ſeconde for the firſt. The
moſt neceſſarie of all, and wherein to
reſt our ſelues is the firſt. But we doe
contrary, for we ſtay our ſelues in the
thirde, and therein beſtow all our ſtudie,
and make no accompt of the firſt,
but are alltogether negligente. And
how? For we make leaſinges, and notwithſtanding
wée haue well néere alwayes
no other thing in our mouthe,
why and wherefore we oughte not to
lye.
               
                  Annotations.
                  
                     Not to lye. And this is the actiue or morall
part. We ſhould not lye. This is called the
iudiciall or naturall part. To demonſtrations.
This is logike and Rhetoricke, wherby
we proue and trie the truthe, and diſproue that
which is falſe.
               
            
            
               Cap. 69. ¶Three ſentences of the auncientes to be had
in minde. Of the which the firſt is of Cleantes,
the ſeconde of Euripides, the thirde of Plato.
               
                  
LEt vs alwayes haue theſe thrée
thinges in memorie and before
 our eyes. The firſt is, Neceſſitie
draweth all thinges (will we nill
we) euē as God hath appointed, wherfore
he which willingly followeth it, is
 wiſe. The ſeconde is if I recoile and
giue back, I ſhal be naughte, &amp; ſpite of
my téeth wéeping and wailing I muſt
 néedes follow. But the third, O Crito
If it ſo pleaſe god, ſo be it. Anitus trulie
and Melitus may well kill me, but
to hurte me, it lieth not in their power.
               
                  Annotations.
                  ¶It is maruell that this morall and auailable
ſaying of Epictetus was omitted, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     ,
that is, Beare and Forbeare, whiche be
vſed very often, and doth in a manner comprehende
al that whereof mencion is made at large
in this boke.
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶The Poeſie of Epictetus
which he vſed as hys badge
or Cogniſaunce.
            
               
                  
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
                  Suſtine &amp; abstine
                  Suſtaine and refraine.
               
            
            The tranſlater vpon the ſame.
            SVſtaine al wrong and iniurie,
            and neuer ſée thou pine
            At any thing, which fortune blinde
            doth claime not to be thine.
            Endure the loſſe of worldlye wealth
            and couet chiefely thys:
            A quiet minde, a godly life
            which makes thée liue in bliſſe.
            Refraine wt pompe to vaunte thy ſelfe
            in fraile externall things,
            Seing to this wearing waſting world
            thou nothing with thée brings.
            Sée thou expell not from thy minde
            and quite from it diſplace
            Al vertuous actes and holie déedes,
            though ſome ſéeke to deface
            Thée, in whoſe minde is fullie fixte
            the trade to vertues way
            
               
By pleaſant ſhewe of filthie vice
            which leadeth men aſtray.
            For ſome there are, who whē they ſée
            one folowing vertues lore,
            From vertue hard, to eaſie vice
            they ſéeke him to reſtore.
            Abſtaine from wrathe in matters all
            from Othes and laughter great,
            From naughtie and yll companie,
            from all delicious meate:
            From giuing eare to ſecrete talke
            and from dame Venus fielde
            Retire thy ſelfe, and take in hande
            of chaſtitie the ſheilde.
            
               Suſtaine, Refraine, theſe ar two words
            which great importaunce haue,
            And if with reaſon thou them ſkan.
            from damage much do ſaue.
         
         
            
            The Apophthegs or quicke
Sentences of Epictetus.
            
               
                  EPictetus ye 
               Stoike Philoſopher
ſeing a certain
fellowe voide of al good
condicions, hauing a
bolde ſpirite to ſpeake
yet to an ill intente, giuing his minde
to the ſtudy of Philoſophie: he with
a loude voyce cryed out on the faythe
of God and man, reprouing the man
in theſe wordes: O man ſée whether
the veſſell be cleane, wherin thou doſt
put theſe things. For if thou ſhalte of
arrogancie poure them in, they wil periſhe:
if they ſhall putrifie, they wil become
vrine, or vineger, or worſe than
theſe, if worſe may be. He ment, that
learning inferreth great hurt and damage,
if it happen vpon a mind which
is corrupted with yll affections: &amp; the
more excellente euery learning is, the
greater hurte it cauſeth if it happen
on a naughtie man: like as there is
no thing more better then a good diuine,

ſo there is nothing more peſtilēt
then an ill diuine. Gellius. lib. xvij. cap.
xix. &amp; Eraſmus. li. vij. Apoph.
            
            He on a time hearing of a certaine
man yt would eaſilie be flattered, ſaid,
the crowes plucke dead mens eies out
of the carkaſſes and that not withoute
a cauſe, for none which is depriued of
life, hath the vſe of hys ſight. But flatterers
corrupting the mindes of them
which are aliue, do take away al their
ſighte. Stob. Antonius in Meliſſa. part.
.j. ſer. lii.
            
            He counſelled that we ſhoulde conſider
thrée maner of wayes: the man
with whome we are conuerſaunte:
whether he be better than we oure
ſelues are, or inferiour, or equall vnto
vs. It is méete to heare diligently, &amp;
obeye him whiche is better then oure
ſelues, modeſtly to perſuade the yonger
or inferioure, and to agrée wt thy
equall. And truly by this meanes thou
ſhalt neuer fall in contention when
thou art in cōpany. Stob. ſerm. iij. de Tē
                  perantia.
Although this be before among

the precepts, yet I thought good
againe to repeate and recken it alſo
in this place. For as the prouerbe is,
Bis &amp; ter quod pulchrun eſt repetendū:
yt is, that which is goodly ought twice
and thrice to be ſayd or repeated.
            He being demaunded, what man
was riche. To whom (ſayed he) that is
ſufficient which he hath. Strob.
            
            He ſayd that the Gods did not hate
ſuch, as in this life doe contende and
wraſtle wt diuers miſeries. The Philoſophers
meaning was, that aduerſitie
was vnto men auailable: to whom
if things do proſper according to their
deſire, they are ſo vexed wt the Furies,
that is, with anger, couetouſneſſe and
luſt, ye through their proſperitie, they
moue ye Gods to wrath. This is foūde
in Bruſonius Conturſin us. li. ij. Exempl.
He being demaunded, by what meane
a man might purchaſe an honeſte reporte,
he aunſwered. If thou wilt haue
a good name, learne to ſpeake well,
when thou haſt learned to ſpeake wel,
endeuoure to do well, and by this

meanes thou ſhalt get a good reporte.
            He being demaunded howe a man
might procure ſorrow to his ennimie,
ſayd: If a man do ſo frame and diſpoſe
hymſelfe, that he do all good things.
            The ſame was accuſtomed to ſaye,
that it was more neceſſarie to cure the
ſoule than the body, ſeing that it is bet
to dye, than to leade an ill life. Antonius
in Meliſsa, part .i. Ser. lviij.
            
            The ſame was wont to call ſuch as
ſhewed thē ſelues to be Philoſophers
by their beard, garmēt, and bragging
wordes, Factis procul, verbis tenus, hauing
their déedes farre of, &amp; their wordes
at hande.
            The ſame was wont to ſay, that a
life ioyned with fortune, was like vnto
a violent floud of water. For it is
troubled, and full of dirte, and
harde to enter into it, it is
violent, roring, and cō
               tinueth
a ſhorte
ſpace.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            Imprinted at London
in Pater Noſter Rowe, by Henrie
Bynneman, for Leonarde
Maylard. And are to be ſold in
Paules Churchyarde,
at the ſigne of
               
the Cock.
1567.
         
      
   

