
   
      
         
            A dialoge or communication of two persons deuysyd and set forthe in the late[n] tonge, by the noble and famose clarke. Desiderius Erasmus intituled [the] pylgremage of pure deuotyon. Newly tra[n]slatyd into Englishe.
            Colloquia. English. Selections
            Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
         
         
            
               1540
            
         
         Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00331
            STC 10454
            ESTC S111331
            99846697
            99846697
            11684
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00331)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11684)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 38:17)
         
         
            
               
                  A dialoge or communication of two persons deuysyd and set forthe in the late[n] tonge, by the noble and famose clarke. Desiderius Erasmus intituled [the] pylgremage of pure deuotyon. Newly tra[n]slatyd into Englishe.
                  Colloquia. English. Selections
                  Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
               
               [100] p.   
               
                  n.p.,
                  [London? :
                  1540?]
               
               
                  Imprint suggested by STC.
                  Signatures: [greek cross] A-D E¹⁰ (-greek cross8).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Dialogues, English --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-02
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-03
            TCP Staff (Oxford)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-03
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
                  Effigiem Desiderij tibj Sculptor ErasmiExprimit; Ingenium, Scripta diserta suum
               
            
         
         
            
            A dialoge
or communication of
two persons, deuysyd
and setforthe in the latē
tonge, by the noble
and famose clarke.
Desiderius Erasmus
intituled ye pylgremage
of
pure deuotyon. Newly trāslatyd into
Englishe.
         
         
            
            
            To the reder.
            AMongest the writinges of all
men, dearly belouyd reder,
not onely of the diuersyte of tongues,
but also the noble drawghtꝭ
of so artificyall paynted figures,
whiche haue so lyuely expressed to ye
quycke ymage, the nature, ordre, &amp;
proporcyon of all states, as concernynge
the gouernaunce of a Christen
comēwealthe, that ther is (as
I suppose) no parte of the scripture,
which is not so e
                  •
               powndyde, furnysshed,
and setforthe, but that euery
Christen man, therby 
                  •
               ay lerne his
dewty to god, hys prynce, and hys
nebure, and so consequently passe
thourough the strayte pathe of the
whiche scripture doth testyfye vpō,
very fewe can fynde ye entrye, wherby
thorough faythe in the redēptyon
of the worlde thorowe ye bloode
of Christe the sone of god, to rayne

with the father and the holy go
                  ••
               e
eternally, accordynge to the promyse
of Christe, sayinge. In my fathers
hawse therbe many placys
to dwell in, we wyll come to hym
and make a mansyon place with
hym and I haue and shall open thy
name vnto them, that the same loue
with the whiche thou louydest
me, may be in theym, and I in thē,
and thys is the kyngdome of god
so often mouyd to vs in holy scripture,
whiche all faythfull shall possesse
and inheret for euermore: where
as ye vnfaythfull, vnryghtswye,
and synner shall not entre in to the
kyngdome of god, bycause, of chaū
               gynge
the glory of gode immortall
in to the ymage of a corruptyble
man, and therfore so lycentiously
he hathe suffrede them to wandre
in theyr clowdes of ygnoraunce,
preferrynge the lyes and corrupte

iudgmentes of man the veryte and
the truthe of god, rather seruynge
the creature then the creator, amongest
all the parties of the whiche
(as was spoken at the begynnyng)
thys alwaye not alonely in
the newe law, but also in the olde
Testament was as a thynge moost
abhomynable and displesant in the
sight of gode prohybyte and forbyden: but
our nature whiche hath
in hym, the dampnable repugnaū
               ce
of synne agaynst the omnypotēt
power of gode, left euyn frome owre
fyrst father Adam, is so enclyned to
vyces, amongest the whiche it hath
not gyuen the least parte to thys
desperate synne of ydolatrye, agaynst
the immaculate, and fearefull
commandement of god. Thou
shalt haue no straunge Godꝭ in my
syght, that it is sore to be dreadde
the same iudgement to be gyuyn

vpon vs that was gyuen vpon the
cytye of Ninyue to be absorped of
the yerthe in to the yre and venge
                  •
               
a
                  ••
               ce of gode, whiche hathe ben
the cau
                  •
               e that so many wryters
b
                  ••
               he of late dayes, and many yeres
passede, haue euyn to deathe,
resisted thes dampnable bolsterers
of ydolatrye, gyuen theyr selues to
the crosse in example of reformacyon
to theyr bretherne, bothe in
wrytinge and cownsell, exhortynge
the flocke of Christe frome soche
prophane doctryne, amongest whome
the noble and famouse clerke
Desiderius Erasmus hath setforthe to
the quycke ymage, before mennys
eyes, the supersticyouse worshype
and false honor gyuyn to bones,
heddes, iawes, armes, stockes, stones,
shyrtes, smokes, cotes, cappes,
hattes, shoes, mytres, slyppers, sadles,
ry
                  •
               ges, bedes, gyrdles, bolles,

belles, 
                  •
               okes, gioues, ropes, raperes,
candelles, bootes, sporres (my
breath was almost past me) with
many other soche dampnable allusyones
of the deuylle to use theme
as goddes contrary to the immaculate
scripture of gode, morouer
he notethe as it were of arrogancye
the pryuate iudgmegt of certayne
that of theyr owne brayne
wolde cast out ymages of the temple,
with out a comen consent and
authoryte, some there be that alway
seke halowes, and go vpon
pylgramages vnder a pretense of
holynes, whervpon thes brotherhoddes
and systerhoodes be now inuented,
morouer they that haue
ben at Hierusalem be called knightes
of the sepulcre, and call one an
other bretherne, and vpon palmesondaye
they play the foles sadely,
drawynge after them an asse in a

rope, when they be not moche distante
frome the woden asse that
they drawe. The same do they conterfayte
that haue ben at saynt
Iames in Compostella. But they
be more pernycyouse, that setforthe
vncertayn relyques, for certayne,
and attrybute more to them than
they oughte to haue, and prostytute
or sett theym forthe for fylthye
lukre. But now whan they perceyue,
that this theyr dāpnableA tresure boxe of ye Iewes Corbane
dothe decay, and that theyr
most to be lamented blyndnes and
longe accustomed errours shuld be
redressed, they, all fayre bothe of
god and man set asyde, rebelle and
make insurrectyones contrary to
the ordynaunce of gode, agaynst
theyr kynge and liege lorde, prouokynge
and allurynge the symple
comynaltye to theyre dampnable
ypocrysye and conspyracy, myndyng

and goynge about to preuente
our most soueraigne lordes iudgment,
not yet gyuē vpon theyr Sodomiticall
actes, and most horryble
ypocrysy. But the worde of the lorde
whiche they so tyrannously go
aboute to suppresse wt all the fauerours
therof shall ouercome &amp; destroy
all soch most to be abhorred &amp;
deceyuable inuegelers &amp; dysturbers
of ye symple people to soch detestable
treason. And that it may so do
to the terryble example of thes and
all other rebelles and most dysloyal
subiectes, and to ye greate comforthe
&amp; cōsolacyō ofh is gracys faythfull
and true comens. I requyre
him which brethethe where he willithe
and raygnethe eternall gode
to graūt vnto our seyde most dradde
soueraygne lorde whose maiesty
as it euydently appereth onely applieth
his diligence to the aduaunsynge

&amp; settynge forthe of the most
holsome documenth and teachyng
of almyghty god, to the redres of
long accustome euylls and damnable
sectes, to the supportacion and
mayntenaunce of godly and alowable
ceremonyes, to the suppressynge
and most to be desired abolishyng
of the deuelishe and detestable
vsurped aucthoryties, dampnable
errours and prophane abuses
brought in by that myghty Golyas,
that obdurated Phareo, that proude
Nembroth (whome god amēde)
the byshope of Rome, to graunte (I
say) vnto hys hyghnes, suche hys
godly ayde and assistence, that hys
grace with hys moost honorable
counsell (agaynst whome this arrogant
conspyracy is nowe moued
and begonne) may ouercome and
debelle the stud traytres as in tymes
paste hys maie
                  ••
               ye hath pruden
                  •
               y

do other, that haue hertofore
attempted to perpetrate and
brynge to passe like sedicyous mishief,
and so to establishe the hartes
of hys gracys true subiectes that
they may wyllyngly and according
to theyr dueties, obey and fulfyll
hys most lawfull and godly ordened
lawes and commaundementꝭ
wherby they shall not onely do the
thyng agreable to goddes wylle &amp;
teachynges, in yt he willeth euery
soule to be subiected to the hygher
power and obedyent to theyr
prynce, but also (to theyr greate
laude and prayse (shall shewe them
selfe to be redy and confirmable to
do theyr dueties in aydyng hys excellent
hyghnes to the reformacyon
of all pernicious abuses &amp; chiefly
of detestable ydolatrye, whiche
is so muche prohibited in holy scripture
and most displeasant to god,

for whiche intent and purpose the
sayd most noble and famous clarke
Dsiderius Erasmus, compiled &amp; made
this dialoge in Laten, as it foloweth
her after nowe lately translated
into our mother the Englishhe
tonge. Auoyd therfore, most deare
readere, all abuses wherby any inconuenyence
may growe, other to the hynderaunce of godes worde,
to the displeasure of thy prynce,
(whome thou arte so straytly commaunded
to obaye, or to the domage
of a publike weale, whiche aboue
all vices is noted most to be abhorred,
not alonely of the most holy
wryteres and expownderes of scripture,
but also of prophane gentylles,
whiche neuer perceyuyd other
thinge than nature enclyned theyr
hartes vnto, and so consequently
to obtayne the fruytion of the godhode
thorowe the faythe that was

spoken of at the begynnynge to the
whiche the lorde Iesus Christe
brynge vs all with a
perfaycte quyetnes,
So be it.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ¶A pylgremage, for pure deuocyō.
            
               MEnedemus.
               
                  Signifieth to forsake. What new
thynge ys it, that I se? doo
I nat see Ogygyus my neybur,
whom no mā could espie of all
thes sex monthes before? yt was a
sayng that he was deed, It is euen
he, except that I be ferre deceyuyd.
I wyll go to hym, &amp; byd hym good
morow. Good morowwas faynyd of an old kynge of Thebanes. Ogygyus.
Good morow to you Menedemus.
            
            
               Mene.
               I pray you frome what contray
do you come to vs ayen so saffe.
For here was a great comunicacyō
that you dyd sayle streght to hell.
            
            
               Ogy.
               No, thankyd be god, I haue
faryd as well syns I went hens, as
euer I dyd in all my lyffe.
            
            
               Me.
               Well,
a man may well perceyue that all
suche rumours be but vanytye. But
I pray you what araye is this that
you be in, me thynke that you be
clothyd with cokle schelles, and be

ladē on euery 
                     •
                  yde with bruches of
lead and tynne. And you be pretely
garnyshyd wt wrethes of strawe &amp;
your arme is full ofSignifyeth bedes. Walsyngam ys callyd para thalass
                        ••
                      by cause it is ny to ye see. snakes egges.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I haue bene on pylgremage
at saynt Iames in Compostella, &amp;
at my retourne I dyd more relygyously
vysyte our lady of Walsyngā
in England, a very holy pylgremage,
but I dyd rather vysyte her. For
I was ther before within this thre
yere.
            
            
               Me.
               I trowe, it was but for
your pleasure.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Nay, it was for
pure deuocyon.
            
            
               Me.
               I suppose you
learnyd that relygyō of the Grecyanes.
            
            
               Ogy.
               My mother in law dyd
make a vowe that if her dougther
shuld be delyueryd of a man chyld
alyue, than that I shuld go to saynt
Iames on pylgremage, and ther to
salute and thāke hym.
            
            
               Me.
               Dyd you
salute saynt Iames alonly in your
name, and your mothers.
            
            
               Ogy.
               No,
in the name of all owre house.
            
            
               Me.
               
                  Uerely I thynke yt your howshold
as well shold haue prosperd, in case
you had not salutyd hym at all. But
I pray you what answer dyd he
make to your salutacyon.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Nothynge
at all. But whā I dyd offre,
me tought he dyd lawghe vpon me,
and becke at me with his hedde, &amp;
dyd reche to me this cokleshell.
            
            
               Me.
               Wherfore dothe he gyue rather suche
schelles, than other thynges.
            
            
               Ogygy.
               For the see, whiche is nye
vnto hym dothe mynystre plenty
of suche.
            
            
               Me.
               O holy saynt Iames,
that bothe is a mydwyffe to women
with chyld, and also dothe helpe his
pylgrymes. But I pray you what
new kynd of makyng vowes is that
that whan a mā is ydle he shall put
the burden apon an other mannes
bakke? In case that you doo bynd
youre selffe with a vowe, that yf ye
matter chaunche happyly whiche
you haue in hande, that I for you

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
shall fast twyse in on weke, do you
beleue yt I can fulfyll youre vow?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No, I doo not beleue it if that
you dyd vowe it in youre awne name.
It is but a sport with yow to
mokke sayntes. But this was my
mother in law, I must nedys obey
her, you know womenes affectyones,
&amp; I must obaye heres.
            
            
               Me.
               If
that you had not perfourmyd your
vowe, what 
                     •
                  opertye had you be in?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I graunt, he could not haue
had an accyon ayenst me in ye law,
but he myght fromhensforthe be
deafe to my vowes, orels pryuyly
send some calamytye or wretchednes
amongste my housholde, yow
know well enuffe the maneres of
great men.
            
            
               Me.
               Tell me now what
that same honest mā saynt Iames
dothe, and howe he farythe.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Moche colder thā he was wontyd
to do.
            
            
               Me.
               What is the cause of it?
His age?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Oh you scoffer, yow

know wel enoghe that sayntes wax
nat olde. But this new learnynge,
whiche runnythe all the world ouer
now a dayes, dothe cause hym
to be vysytyd moche lesse than he
was wontyd to be, for if any doo come
thay salute him alonly, but they
offre lytle or nothynge, and say that
theyr monaye may bettre be disposyd
amongste pore people.
            
            
               Me.
               O
a wykyd comunicacyon.
            
            
               Ogy.
               
                  Ye &amp;
so great an Apostle whiche was wō
                  tyd
to stand all in precyous stones &amp;
gold, now stādythe all of wodde hauynge
before hym skaresly a wax
candle.
            
            
               Me.
               If it be trew that I here,
it is great ioperdy lest that same
chance to all the rest of the sayntes.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I thynk it wel, for ther is an
epistle abrode whiche our lady dyd
wryte apon the same matter.
            
            
               Me.
               What lady?
            
            
               Ogy.
               
                  Our ladi of stone in Raurachia whiche is a certayne cuntre. She yt hathe
her name of a stone.
            
            
               Me.
               I trawe it
is in Raurachia.
            
            
               Ogy.
               That same

is it.
            
            
               Me.
               yow tell me of a stony lady,
But to whome dyd she wryte?
            
            
               Ogy.
               The epistle dothe playnely shew his
name.
            
            
               Me.
               By whome was it sent?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No dowbt but by an angell,
whiche dyd lay the wrytynges apō
the aultre, wherof he prechythe to
whome it was sent. And lest there
shuld be any suspectyō of crafty cō
                  uayence
in you, you shall se the epistle
wryten wt his owne hande.
            
            
               Me.
               Do you know so well the hand of
thangell whiche is secretary to our
lady?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Yee why nat?
            
            
               Me.
               By
what argumēt?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I haue redde
yt
                  Is a scripture wryten on a graue. Epithaphe of Bede which was
grauyd of the angell: and the letteres
agre in all thynges. I haue
reddē also ye obligacyō whiche was
sent to saynt Gyles as dothe aper.
Dothe not thes argumentes proue
that mater to be good enoghe.
            
            
               Me.
               May a man loke apon them?
            
            
               Ogy.
               ye and if you wyll swere to kepe it

preuy.
            
            
               Me.
               Oh you shall speake to a
stone.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Ther be stones now a
dayes of that name very 
                     •
                  lawnderous,
that wyll hyde nothynge.
            
            
               Me.
               you shall speake to a domme man, &amp;
yow trust nat a stone.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Apon yt
condycyon I wyll tell it, loke that
you here with bothe youre eyares.
            
            
               Me.
               So I doo.The epistle of our Lady.
               
            
            
               Ogy.
               Mary the mother
of Iesu toGlaucoplutꝰ desirus of ryches. Glaucoplutus sē
                  dythe
gretynge. Insomoche as you
folowe Luther, you nobly perswade,
that it is but in vayne to call apō
sayntes, do ye well know for that to
be grettly in my fauore. For vntyll
thys day I haue almost be slayne wt
the importunate prayers of men.
Of me alone they askyd althynges,
as who shuld say my sone were alway
a babe, because he is so faynyd
and payntyd apō my breste, that yet
he wold be at my commaundemēt
and durst nat denye my petycyon,
dredynge that if he denye my petycyon,

that I shuld denye hym myte
ate whan he is a thurst: and veryoft
thay requyre that of me, whiche
a shamfast yongman dare scantly
aske of a Bawde, yee they be suche
thynges as I am ashamyd to put
in wrytynge. Now comythe ye marchauntman
and he redy to sayle into
Spayne for a vantage, dothe
cōmytte hys wyues honesty to me.
Than commythe thet lytle preaty
Nunne and she castythe away her
vayle redy to runne away, she leuythe
with me the good name of her
vyrgynytye, whiche shortly she entendythe
to take monay for. Than
cryeth the wykyd soudyer purposyd
to robbe &amp; saythe, blessyd lady send
me a good praye. Now cōmythe the
vnthryfty dyasser and cryethe, send
me good chance Lady &amp; thow shalt
haue parte of my wynnynges: and
if the dyasse runne ayenst hym, he
blasphemes, and cursythe me, bycause

I wyll nat fauor his noghtynes.
Now cryeth she that sellythe
her selffe for fylthye lukre &amp; saythe,
swete lady send me some costomers,
&amp; if I denye it, they exclame ayenst
me &amp; say, thou arte not the mother
of marcy. Moreouer the vowes of
some women be no lesse wykyd thā
folishe. The mayd cryeth &amp; saythe,
O swet Mary send me a fayre and
riche husbond. The maryed womā
saythe send me goodly chylderen.
Now laborythe the woman with
chyld, and cryeth dere lady dylyuer
me of my bondes. Than cōmythe ye
olde wyffe, and saythe flowre of all
women send me to lyue longe withowt
coghe and drynes. Now crepythe
the dotynge oldman &amp; saythe,
lady send me for to wax yonge ayē.
Thā cōmythe forth the phylosopher
and cryethe send me some argumē
                  tis
that be īsoluble. The great prest
cryethe send me a fat benefyce. Thā
                  
saythe the bysshope kepe well my
churche. Thā cryethe ye hye Iustyce
shew me thy sone or I passe out of
this worlde. Thā saythe ye Cowrtyer
send me trwe confession at the
howre of my deathe. The husbondman
saythe send vs temperate wether.
The mylke wyffe cryethe owt
blessyd lady saue our catell. Now if
I denye anythynge by &amp; by I am
crwell. If I cōmytte it to me sone,
I here them say, he wyll what so euer
you wyll. Shall I than alone
bothe a woman and a mayd helpe
maryneres, sawd yeres, marchantmen,
dyasseres, maryedmē, women
with chyld, iudges, kynges, and husbondmen?
ye and this that I haue
sayd is the least parte of my payne.
But I am nat now so moche trobled
with soche busynes, for that I
wold hartely thanke you, but that
this commodytye dothe brynge a
greater discōmodytye with hym. I

haue now more ease, but lesse honor
&amp; profett. Before this tyme I was
callyd quene of heuen, lady of the
world, but now any man wyll skarsly
say a
                     •
                  e Maria or hayle Mary.
Before I was clothyd with precyous
stones and gold, and had my
chaunges, and dayly ther was offeryd
gold and precyous stones, now
I am skarsly coueryd with halffe 
                     •
                  
gowne and that is all beeyten with
mysse. My yerly rentes be now so
smalle yt I am skarsly able to fynde
my pore quere kepar to light a wax
cādle before me. Yet all this myght
be sufferyd, but you be abowt to
pluke away greater thynges, you
be abowt (as they say) that what so
euer any saynte hathe in any place,
to take hyt frome the churches, but
take hede what you doo. For ther is
no saynte without a way to reuēge
his wronge. If you cast saynt Petre
forthe of the churche, he may serue

you of the same sauce, and shite vp
heuyngates ayenst you. Ye saynt
Paule hathe his sworde. Barthylmew
is nat wtowt his great knyffe.
Saynt wyllyam is harnysyd vnder
his monkes cloke, nat withowt a
greate speare. What canst thou doo
ayenst saynt George whiche is bothe
a knyght &amp; all armyd with hys
longe spere and his fearfull sword?
Nor saynt Antony is nat withowt
hys weapenes for he hathe holy fyre
wt hym. Ye the rest of the sayntes
haue theyr weapones or myschefues,
whiche they send apon whome
they liste. But as for me thou canst
not cast owt, except thou cast owt
my sone, whiche I hold in myne armes.
I wyll nat be seperat frome
hym, other thou shalt cast hym owt
with me orels thou shalt let vs bothe be,
except that you wold haue
a temple withowt a Christe.
               These be the thynges that I wold

yow shall know ymagyne you therfore
what shalbe your answer. For
this thinge pleasythe me very well.
Frome oure stony churche the calendes
of Auguste, the yere frome
my sonnes passyon a M.CCCCC.
xiiij. I stony lady subscrybyd thys
with myne owne hande.
            
            
               Me.
               Trewly
that was a soro and fearfull epistle,
I suppose that Glaucoplutus
wyll beware frōhēsforthe.
            
            
               Ogy.
               
                  Ye &amp;
if he be wyse.
            
            
               Me.
               Wherfore dyd nat
that good saynt Iames wryte to yt
man of the same mater.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I can
nat tell, except it be bycause he is so
ferre of, and now a dayes men be
moche searchyd for suche maters, &amp;
in theyr iornaye theyr lettres takē
frome them.
            
            
               Me.
               I pray you, what
god dyd send you into Englōd?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I saw the wynd maruelouse prosperouse
thyderward, and I had almoste
promysyd this to that blessyd
lady of Walsyngā that I wold seke

her within .ij. yere,
            
            
               Me.
               What wold
yo
                     •
                   axe of her.
            
            
               Ogy.
               No newthyngꝭ
at all, but suche as be comen, as to
kepe saffe and sownd my housholde,
to encreasse my goodes, and in thys
world to haue alōge and mery liffe,
and whā I dye euerlastynge lyffe in
another worlde.
            
            
               Me.
               May nat owr
lady grante the same at home with
vs? She hathe at Antwarpe a moche
more lordly temple thā at Walsynganie.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I denye nat but it
may be so, but in dyuers places she
grantes dyuers thynges, wether it
be her pleasur so to do, or bycause
she is so gentle, that as cōcernynge
this purpose, she wyll gyue her selfe
to our affectyōes.
            
            
               Me.
               I haue harde
oft of saynt Iames, but I pray you
describe to me the kyngdome of
Walsyngam.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Uerely I shall
tell you as shortly as I canne. Yt
is the most holy name in all England,
and you may fynde some in

that y
                     •
                  e, that suppose thayr substāce
shal nat prospayre except they vysyte
her with thayr offerynge euery
yere ones as thay be able to gyue.
            
            
               Me.
               Wher dothe she dwell?
            
            
               Ogy.
               At
the vttermost parte of all England
betwyxt the Northe and the Weste,
nat vary ferre frome the see, skarsly
iij myles, the towne is almost susteynyd
by the resort of pylgrymes.
The college is of Canōes, but thay
be suche as hathe thayr name of
the Laten tonge and be called Seculares,
a kynd betwyxte monkes &amp;
Chanones.
            
            
               Me.
               What you tell me of
Amphybyanes be thynges doutfull.Amphybyanes, suche as ye mōstre
Fyber is abeste of ye see &amp; ye land.Fyber is.
            
            
               Ogy.
               No thay be rather
suche as theA Cocatrice wil kyll a man with a loke, Cocatrice. But withowt
dissimulation, I shall put you
owt of this dowte in thre wordes.
To them that thay hate, thay be
Chanones, and to them that thay
loue thay he Monkes
            
            
               Menede.
               Yet
yowe doo nat open thys redle.
            
            
               Ogy.
               
                  
I shall paynte it before youre eyes,
if the bysshope of Rome doo shot hys
thonderbowlt amōgst all monkes,
thay wyll than be chanones, &amp; nat
monkes, but and if he wold suffre
all monkes to take wyues, thā wyll
they be monkes,
            
            
               Me.
               O new partakeres,
I wold to god they wold take
away my wyffe.
            
            
               Ogy.
               But to come
to our purpose, the college hathe
skarsly any otherRēttes. emolumētes but
of the liberalite of our lady. For the
great offeryngꝭ be kepyd stylle, but
if ther be any litle some of monaye
offerid that goith to the comens of
the company, &amp; the mayster whome
thay call pryoure.
            
            
               Me.
               Be thay of a
vertuous lyffe?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Nat to be dispraysyd,
thay be more vertuous thā
ryche of thayr yerely renttes. The
temple ys goodly &amp; goregious, but
oure Lady dwellythe nat in it, but yt
was purchasyd for the honor of her
sone. She hathe her owne temple,

that she may be of the ryght hand
of her sone.
            
            
               Me.
               Apon the righthād?
Whiche way dothe her sonne loke
than?
            
            
               Ogy.
               It is well remembryd.
Whan he lokythe to te West, his mother
is apō his right hand, but whā
he turnythe hym to the Este she is
apon the lefte hand. But yet she
dwelly the nat in that churche, for
it is nat yet buyldyd all vpe, and the
wynde runnythe thorow euery parte
with open wyndowes &amp; dowres,
and also nat ferre of is the Occiane
seye father of all wyndes.
            
            
               Me.
               what
doo yow tell me wher dothe she
dwell thā?
            
            
               Ogy.
               In ye same churche
whiche I told you was nat all fynyshyd,
ther is a lytle chapell seelyd
ouer with wodde, on ether syde a lytle
dore wher ye pylgrymes go thorow,
ther is lytle light, but of ye taperes,
with a fragrant smell.
            
            
               Me.
               All
these be mete for religyon.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Ye
Menedemus if you loke within you

wyll say that it is a seate mete for
sayntes, all thynges be so bright wt gold, syluer, and precyous stones.
            
            
               Me.
               You almost moue me to go thyther
also.
            
            
               Ogy.
               It sh
                     •
                  l nat repente
you of your iornay.
            
            
               Me.
               Spryngithe
ther no holy oyle?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I trowe
you dote, that spryngythe nat but
owt of the sepulchres of sayntes, as
saynt Andrew, &amp; saynt Katerē, owr
lady was nat beried.
            
            
               Me.
               I graūt I
sayd amysse, but tell on your tale.
            
            
               Ogy.
               So moche more as thay persayue
youre deuocyō, so moche larger
reliques wyl thay shew to you.
            
            
               Me.
               Ye and peraduēture that thay
may haue larger offerynges, as is
sayd that, many lytle offerynges
makythe a heuy boxe.
            
            
               Ogygy.
               Her
chaplenꝭ be alway at hand.
            
            
               Me.
               Be
thay of ye Chanones?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No, thay
be nat permyttyd to be with her,
lest that peraduenture by occasyon
of that religyon, thay shuld be plukkyd

frome thayr owne religyō, and
whylst thay kepe that virgyne, thay
regard very lytle thayr awne virgynyte,
alonly in that inner chapell
whiche is our ladyes preuy chābre,
ther standithe a certayne Chanō at
the autre.
            
            
               Me.
               For what purpose?
            
            
               Ogy.
               To receyue and kepe, yt whiche
is offeryd.
            
            
               Me.
               dothe any man gyue
ayenst hys wyll.
            
            
               Ogy.
               No, but many
men hathe suche a gentle shamfastnes,
that thay wyll gyue some
thynge to hym that standythe by,
other thay wyll offre more largely,
whiche that wold nat doo perauē
                  ture
if that he were absent, yt standithe
there.
            
            
               Me.
               You tell me of mannes
affectiones, whiche I my selffe
prouyd very ofte.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Ye trewly
there be some so gyuē to our blessyd
lady, that whan thay apere to putvpe
thayr handes to offre, with a ꝓpre
cōuayance, thay stayl yt whiche
other men hathe gyuen.
            
            
               Me.
               Than

lett no man be there; wyll nat oure
Lady shote her thonderbowlte at
suche.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Wherfor shuld our lady
rather doo so, than God hymselffe,
whom thay be nat affrayd to pluke
owt hys robes, &amp; breake ye churche
walles therfore.
            
            
               Mene.
               I am in a
great doubt whether I shuld, rather
maruayle apon thayre wykyd
boldnes, or Goddys great gētlenes
and longe sufferynge.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Apō the
Northe parte ther is a certayne
gaate, but lest that you should make
a lye, it is nat of the churche, but of
the pale that compassithe a bowte
the churche yarde, and that hathe
a lytle wykyt, suche as be in great
mennes gaates, that who so euer
wyll entre, must fyrst putin hys legge,
nat withowt some ioperdie, and
than bowe downe hys hedde.
            
            
               Me.
               It is ioperdie to goo thorow suche
a dore, to a mannes enemye.
            
            
               Ogy.
               So it is, the sexten dyd tell me that

ther was ones a knyght whiche
fleeynge hys enemye, than aprochynge,
dyd ride thorow ye wykyte,
and than the wretche dispayrynge
in hym selffe, apon a soden motion,
dyd commend hymselffe to ye blessyd
virgyne, whiche was than at hand.
But now commythe the myrakle.
By and by that knyght was all in
the churche yarde, and hys aduersary
was ragynge at the dore wt
                  owte.
            
            
               Me.
               And dyd he tell you so
maruylous a myrakle for a trewthe?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No dowte.
            
            
               Me.
               But I
suppose that he could nat so lyghtely
doo that to you so a great a philosopher.
            
            
               Ogy.
               He dyd shewe to me
in that same wykytte in a plate of
coper, the ymage of the knyght fastenyd
with nayles and wt the same
garmentes yt the Englishmen were
wontyd to wayre at that tyme, as
you may see in that olde pictures,
whiche wylnat lye, Barbourꝭ had

but lytle lyuynge at that tyme: and
dieres &amp; websteres gotte but litle
monay.
            
            
               Me.
               Why so?
            
            
               Ogy.
               For he
had a berd like a goote, and his cote
had neuer a plyte, &amp; it was so litle,
that with strayte gyrdynge it mayd
hys body to apere lesse than it was.
Ther was another plate, that was
in quantyte and fourme like to a
cheste.
            
            
               Me.
               Well now it
                     •
                   is nat to be
doubtyd apō.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Under ye wykyte
ther was a grate of yrne, that no
man cā passe theryn but a footemā,
for it is nat conuenyent that any
horsse shuld tread after apon y• place,
whiche the knyght dyd cōsecrate
to owr lady.
            
            
               Me.
               Nat withowt a
good cause.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Frome that parte
toward the Este, there is a litle chapell,
full of maruayles and thyther
I wēte, ther was I receyuyd of another
of our ladyes chaplenes, ther
we knelyd downe, to make our litle
prayeres. By &amp; by, he broght for the

the ioynte of a mannes fynger, the
greatyste of thre, whiche I kyssyd, &amp;
askyd whose relyques thay were,
he dyd say that thay were saynt Petres.
What thapostle sayd I. Ye sayd
he. Than I dyd better beholde the
ioynte, whiche for hys greatenes
myght well haue be a Gyātes ioynte,
rather than a mannes. Than
sayd I, saynt Peter must nedys be a
great man of stature. But at that
word, ther was one of the gentlemē
that stode by, that could not forbere
lawghynge, for the whiche I was
very sory. For if he had holden hys
pease, we had sene all the relyques,
yet we metely well pleasyd mayster
Sextē, with gyuynge hym .ii. or .iij.
grotes. Before that chapell there
was a litle howsse, whiche he sayd
ones in wynter tyme whan yt there
was litle rowme to couer the reliques,
that it was sodenly broght &amp;
sett in that place. Under that house

there was a couple of pittes, bothe
fulle of water to the brynkys, and
thay say that ye sprynge of thos pittes
is dedicate to our lady, that water
is very colde, and medycynable
for the hede ake and that hartburnynge.
            
            
               Me.
               If that cold water wyll
hele the paynes in the hede and stomake,
than wyll oyle putowte fyre
from hensforthe.
            
            
               Ogy.
               It is a myrakle
that I tell, good syr, orels what
maruayle shuld it be, yt cowld water
shuld slake thurste?
            
            
               Me.
               This may
well be one parte of your tale.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Thay say that the fowntayne dyd
sodenly sprynge owte of the erthe at
the commaundement of our lady, &amp;
I dilygently examenynge althynges,
dyd aske hym how many yeres
it was sythe that howsse was so sodenly
broght thyther. Many yeres
agone saythe he. Yet, sayde I, the
wallys doo nat apere so old. He dyd
nat denay it. No mor thes woden

pyleres. He cowld nat denay but yt
they were sette there nat longe agoo,
and also the mater dyd playnly
testyfye ye same. Afterward, sayd
I, thys roffe whiche is all of rede
dothe apere nat to be very olde, &amp;
he grantyd also, thes greete bemes
whiche lye ouerthwerte, and these
rafteres that hold vpe that howsse
were nat sett longe agone. He affyrmyd
my saynge. Well sayd I seynge
that no parte of the housse is
lefte but all is new, how can yow
say that this was the house whiche
was broght hyther so longe agoo.
            
            
               Me.
               I pray you how dyd the howskeper,
auoyde hymselffe frome your
argumēt.
            
            
               Ogy.
               By &amp; by he dyd shew
to vs the mater by the skyne of a
bayre whiche had hangyd be the
rafteres alonge season, and dyd almost
moke the symplenes of owre
wyttes that could nat perceyue so
manyfeste an argumēte we beynge

perswadyd by this argument, askid
pardon of our ignorance, and callid
into our communycacyon the heuēly
mylke of our lady.
            
            
               Me.
               O how
like to the sone is the mother, for
he hath left to vs so moche blood
here in erthe, &amp; she so moche mylke,
that a man wyl skarysly beleue a
woman to haue so moche mylke of
one chylde, in case the chyld shuld
sukke none at all.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Thay saye
the same of the holy crosse, whiche
is shewyd in so many places bothe
openly, and pryuately, that if ye fragmentes
were gatheryd apon one
heape, they wold apere to be a iuste
fraghte for a shipe, and yet Christe
dyd bere all his crosse hymselffe.
            
            
               Me.
               But do nat you maruayll at this?
            
            
               Ogy.
               It may welbe a strāge thynge,
but no maruayle, seynge that the
lord whiche dothe encreasse this at
hys pleasure, is almyghty.
            
            
               Me.
               It is
very gently expowndyd, but I am

afrayd, that many of thes be faynyd
for lukre.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I suppose yt God
wold nat suffre hymselffe to be deludyd
of suche a fasshion.
            
            
               Mene.
               Yis,
Haue nat you sene that whā bothe
the mother, the sone, the father, and
the holy ghoste hathe be robbyd of
thes sacrile gyous theues, that thay
woldnat ones moue, or styre nother
with bekke or crakke wherby thay
myght fray away the theues. So
great is the gentles of God.
            
            
               Ogy.
               So it is, but here out me tale. This
mylke is kepyd apon the hye aultre,
and in the myddys ther is Christe, wt 
his mother apon hys ryght hand,
for her honor sake, the mylke dothe
represente the mother.
            
            
               Me.
               It may
be sene than?
            
            
               Ogy.
               It is closyd in
crystalle.
            
            
               Me.
               It is moyste thā?
            
            
               Ogy.
               What tell you me of moystenes, whā
it was mylkyd more than a thowsand
and fyue hunthrithe yere agone,
it is so congelyd, that a mā wold

saye that it were chalke temperyd
with the whyte of a egge.
            
            
               Me.
               Ye, but do thay sette it forthe bare?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No, lest so holy mylke shuld be
defowlyd with the kyssynge of men.
            
            
               Me.
               You say well. For I suppose yt
ther be many that kysse it, whiche
be nother clene mouthyd, nor yet be
pure virgynes.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Whan ye sexten
sawe vs, he dyd runne to the aultre,
&amp; put apon hym his surplese, &amp; his
stole about his nekke, knelyd downe
relygyously, and worshipyd it, and
streghtforthe dyd offre the mylke to
vs to kysse. And at the ende of the
aultre we knelyd downe deuoutly, &amp;
the fyrste of all we salutyd Christe, &amp;
than after we callyd apon our lady
with thys prayer, whiche we had
mayd redy for the same purpose. O
mother &amp; mayde, whiche dyd gyue
sukke with thy virgynes teates the
lorde of heuen and yerthe, thy sone
Iesus Christe, we beynge puryfyed

thorowe hys precyous blode, do desyre
that we may attayne, and come
to that blessyd infancye of thy
colombynes meknes, whiche is immaculate
without malice, frawde,
or diseyte, and with all affectyon of
harte dothe couett and stody for the
heuenly mylke of the euangelicall
doctryne, to go for the and encrease
with it into a perfaycte man, into
the mesure of the plentefulnes of
Christe, of whos cōpany thou haste
the fruycyon, togyther with the father,
&amp; the holy ghost for euermore,
so be it.
            
            
               Me.
               Uerely thys is a holy
prayer. But what dyd she?
            
            
               Ogygy.
               Thay bothe bekkyd at vs, excepte
my eyes waggyd, and me thought yt
the mylke daunsyd. In the meanseson
the sexten came to vs, withowt
any wordes, but he held out a table
suche as the Germanes vse to gather
tolle apon bridges.
            
            
               Me.
               By my
trothe I haue cursyd very ofte suche

crauynge boxes, whan I dyd
ryde thorowe Germany.
            
            
               Ogy.
               We
dyd gyue hym certayne monay
whiche he offeryd to our lady. Thā
I axyd by a certayne yonge man, yt
was well learnyd, whiche dyd expownde
and tell vs the saynge of ye
Sextē, hys name (as fere as I remembre)
was Robert alderisse, by
what tokenes or argumētes he dyd
know that it was the mylke of owr
lady. And that I very fayne, &amp; for
a good purpose desyred to knowe, yt
I myght stope the mowthes of certayne
newfanglyd felowes, that be
w
                     •
                  tyd to haue suche holy relyques
in derysyon and mokage. Fyrst of
all the Sexten wt a froward cowntenāce
wold nat tell, but I desyryd
the yong man to moue hym more
instantly, but somwhat more gently
he so courtesly behauyd hymselffe, yt
and he had prayd owr lady herselffe

after yt fashion, she wold nat haue
be dysplesyd therwith. And thā this
mystycall chapleyn, as and if he
had be inspyryd with ye holy ghoste,
castynge at vs a frounynge loke, as
&amp; if he wold haue shote at vs ye horryble
thonderbolte of the greate
curse, what nede you (saythe he) to
moue suche questyones, whan yow
see byfore your eyes so autentycall
&amp; old a table. And we were afrayd
lest that he wold haue cast vs out of
the churche for heretykes, but that
oure monay dyd tempre hys grea,
te furye.
            
            
               Mene.
               What dyd you in
the meaneseason?
            
            
               Ogygyus.
               What
suppose you? We were amasyd as
and if a man had stryke vs with a
clube, or we had be slayne with a
thonderclape, and we very lowly
axid pardon of oure folishe boldenes,
and gote vs frome thens. For
so must we entreate holy thynges.

Frome thens we went in to ye howse
where owre lady dwellithe, and
whan we came there, we sawe another
Sexten whiche was but a
noues, he lokyd famylarly as and if
he had knowē vs, and whā we came
a litle further in, we sawe another,
yt lokyd moch after suche a fashion,
at the last came the thyrd.
            
            
               Me.
               Perauenture
thay desyryd to descrybe
you.
            
            
               Ogy.
               But I suspecte another
mater.
            
            
               Mene.
               What was it?
            
            
               Ogygy.
               There was a certayne theffe yt had
stole almost all owr ladyes frontlet,
and I supposyd yt they had me in suspycyon
therof. And therfore whan
I was within the chapell I mayd
my prayers to ourlady after thys
fashiō. Oh cheffe of all women Mary
the mayd, most happy mother,
moste pure virgyne, we vnclene, and
synners, doo vysyte the pure &amp; holy,
and after our abylytye we haue offeryd
vnto the, we pray thy that thy

sone may grante this to vs, that we
may folow thy holy lyffe, and that
we may deserue thorow the grace
of the holy ghoste, spirytual
                     •
                  y to cō
                  ceyue
the lord Iesus Christ, &amp; after
that conceptyon neuer to be separat
frome hym, Amen. This done
I kyssyd the aultre, and layd downe
certayne grotes for myne offerynge
and went my waye.
            
            
               Me.
               What dyde
our lady now, dyd nat she make one
sygne, that you myght know that
she had hard youre prayeres.
            
            
               Ogy.
               The lyght (as I told you before)
was but litle, and she stode at the
ryght ende of the aultre in the derke
corner, at the last the commumcatyō
of the fyrst Sexten had so discoregyd
me, that I durst nat ones
loke vpe with myne eyes.
            
            
               Me.
               This
                     •
                  
pylgremage came but to smale effecte.
            
            
               Ogy..
               Yes, it had a very good &amp;
mery ende.
            
            
               Me.
               You haue causyd me
to take harte of grasse, for (as Homere

saythe) my harte was almost
in my hose.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Whan dynar was
done, we returnyd to ye temple.
            
            
               Me.
               Durfte you God &amp; be susspecte of felonye?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Perauenture so, but I
had nat my selffe in suspiciō, a gyltles
mynde puttythe away feare. I
was very desyrous to see that table
whiche the holy Sexten dyd open
to vs. At the last we fownde it, but
it was hāgyd so hye that very fewe
could rede it. My eyes be of that fashion,
that I can nother be callyd
Linceus ys abeaste so quike eyed yt it wyll see thorow any wallLinceus, nother purre blynd.
And therefore I instantly desyryd
Alldryge to rede it, whose redynge
I folowyd with myne owne eyes,
because I wold skarsly truste hym
in suche a mater.
            
            
               Me.
               Well, now all
doubtes be discussyd.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I was ashamyd
that I doubtyd so moche, ye
mater was so playne setforthe before
oure eyes, bothe the name, the
p
                     •
                  ace. the thynge it selffe as it was

done, to be breffe, there was nothynge
lefte owte. There was a mane
whos name was Wylyam whiche
was borne in Parise, a man very
deuoute in many thyngꝭ, but pryncypally
excedynge relygyous in
searchynge forthe relyques of all
sayntes thorowo wt all the worlde.
He after that he had vysytyd many
places, contrayes, and regyones, at
the laste came to Cōstantynenople.
For Wylhelmes brother was there
byshope, whiche dyd make hym pryuy
to a certayne mayde, whiche had
professyd chastyte, that hadde parte
of oure ladyes mylke, whiche were
an excedynge precyous relyque, if
that other with prayer, or monaye,
or by any crafte it myghte be gotte.
For all the reliques that he hadde
gotte before were but tryfles to so
holy
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  ylke. Wyllyam wold nat rest
there tyll that he had gotte halffe of
that holy mylke, but whan he had

it, he thoghte that he was richer
than Croeseus.
            
            
               Me.
               Why nat, but
was it nat withowt any good hope?
            
            
               Ogy.
               He went thā streght home, but
in hys iornay he fell seke.
            
            
               Me.
               Iesu
there is nothynge in thys worlde yt
is other permanent, or alwayes in
good state.
            
            
               Ogy.
               But whan he sawe
&amp; perceyuyd that he was in greate
ioperdye of his lyffe, he callyd to him
a frenchman, whiche was a very
trusty companyon to hym in hys
iornay. And commaundyd all to auoyd
the place, and make sylence, &amp;
pryuyly dyd betake to hym thys
mylke, apon this condycyō, that if it
chāsyd to come home saffe &amp; sownde
he shuld offre that precyous tresure
to our ladyes aultre in Paryse,
whiche standythe in the myddys of
the ryuere Sequana, whiche dothe
apere to separat hymselffe to h
                     •
                  nor
and obaye our blessyd lady. But to
make short tale. Wylyam is deade, &amp;

buryed, the Frenchman mayd hym
redy to departe apon hys iornay, &amp;
sodēly fell seke also. And he in great
dyspayre of amendynge, dyd commyth
ye mylke to an Englishmā, but
nat withowt great instance, and
moche prayer he dyd that whiche
he was mouyd to doo. Than dyed
he. And ye other dyd take the mylke,
and put it apon an aultre of ye same
place the Chanones beynge presente,
whiche were yt as we call Regulares.
Thay be yet in the abbaye
of saynt Genofeffe. But ye Englishmā
obtaynyd the halffe of that mylke, &amp;
caryed it to Walsyngā in England,
the holy ghost put suche in hys mynde.
            
            
               Me.
               By my trothe this is a godly
tale.
            
            
               Ogy.
               But lest there shuld be
any doubte of this mater, ye Byshopes
whiche dyd grante pardon to it
thayre names be wryten there, as
thay came to vysyte it, nat withowt
thayre offerynges, and thay haue

gyuen to it remyssyon, as moche as
thay had to gyue by thayre authorite.
            
            
               Me.
               How moche is that?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Fowrty dayes.
            
            
               Mene.
               Yee is there
dayes in hell.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Trewly ther is
tyme. Ye but whan thay haue grā
                  tyd
all thayre stynte, thay haue no
more to grante.
            
            
               Ogy.
               That is nat so
for whan one parte is gone another
dothe encrease, and it chansythe dyuersly
euyn as the tonne of 
                     •
                  anaidus.
For that althoghe it be incontynently
fyllyd, yet it is alway emptye:
and if thou be takynge owt of
it, yet there is neuer the lesse in the
barell.
            
            
               Me.
               If thay grāte to an hunderithe
thowsand mē fowrty dayes
of pardone, shuld euery man haue
elyke?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No doubte of that.
            
            
               Me.
               And if any haue forty byfore dynar,
may he axe other forty at after sou
                  
                     •
                  er,
is there any thynge lest than to
gyue him?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Ye, &amp; if thou aske it
tentymes in one howre.
            
            
               Me.
               I wold

to God that I had suche a pardon
bagge, I wold aske but .iij. grotes,
and if thay wold flowe so faste.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Ye but you desyre to be to ryche, if yt
you myght for wyshynge, but I wyl
turne to my tale, but there was some
good holy man whiche dyd gyue
this argumente of holynes to that
mylke, and sayd that our Ladyes
mylke whiche is in many other places,
is precyous &amp; to be worshipyd,
but thys is moche more precyous, &amp;
to be honoryd, bycause the other
was shauen of stones, but this is the
same that came out of the virgynes
brest.
            
            
               Me.
               How kno you that?
            
            
               Ogy.
               The mayd of Cōstantynople, which
dyd gyue it, dyd saye so.
            
            
               Me.
               Perauenture
saynt Barnard dyd gyue it
to her.
            
            
               Ogy.
               So I suppose. For whā
he was an old man, yet he was so
happy yt he sukkyd of y• same mylke,
that Iesus hymselffe sukkyd apon.
            
            
               Me.
               But I maruayle why he was

rather callyd a hony sukker than a
mylke sukker. But how is it callyd
oure ladyes mylke that came neuer
owt of her breste?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Yes it came
owt at her breste, but perauenture
it light apon the stone yt he whiche
sukkyd knelyd apon, and ther was
receyuyd, and so is encreasyd, &amp; by
ye wyll of god is so multyplyed.
            
            
               Me.
               It is wel sayd.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Whan we had
sene all thys, whyle that we were
walkynge vpe &amp; downe, if that any
thynge of valure were offeryd, so yt
any body were present to see thaym
ye Sextens mayd great haste for feare
of crafty cōuayēce, lokynge apō
thaym as thay wold eate thaym.
Thay poynte at hym with there
fynger, thay runne, thay goo, thay
come, thay bekke one to an other,
as tho thay wold speake to thaym
that stand by if thay durste haue be
bold.
            
            
               Mene.
               Were you af
                     •
                  rayd of nothynge
there?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Yis I dyde loke

apō hym, lawghynge as who shold
saye I wold m
                     ••
                  e hym to spe
                     •
                  ke to
me
                     •
                  , at 
                     ••
                  ste he cam to me, and a
                     •
                  id
me what was my name, I told him.
He axid me if yt were nat I that
dyd hange vpe there a table of 
                     •
                  y
vowe writen in Hebrew, with i
                     •
                   .ij.
yere before. I confessi
                     •
                   that it was
ye same.
            
            
               Me.
               Cā you wryte hebrewe?
            
            
               Ogygy.
               No but all that thay cānat
vnderstond, thay suppose to be Hebrewe.
And than (I suppose he was
send for) came the posterior pryor.
            
            
               Me.
               What name of worshipe is yt?
Haue thay nat an abbate?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No
            
            
               Me.
               Why so?
            
            
               Ogy.
               For thay cannat
speake Hebrew.
            
            
               Me.
               Haue thay nat
a Bishope?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No.
            
            
               Me.
               What is ye
cause?
            
            
               Ogy.
               For oure lady is nat as
yet so ryche, that she is able to bye a
crosse, &amp; a mytre, whiche be so deare,
            
            
               Me.
               Yet at least haue thay nat a presedente?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No veryly. What lettythe
thaym?
            
            
               Ogy.
               That is a name

of dignyte and nat of relygyō. And
also for that cause suche abbayes
of Chanones, doo nat receyue the
name of an abbate, thay doo call
thaym maysters?
            
            
               Me.
               Ye, but I neuer
hard tell of pryor posterior before.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Dyd you neuer learne
youre grāmere before.
            
            
               Me.
               Yis I
know prior posterior amōgst the fygures.
            
            
               Ogy.
               That same is it. It is
he that is nexte to the prioure, for
there priour is posterior.
            
            
               Me.
               You
speake apon the supprioure.
            
            
               Ogy.
               That same dyd entertayne me very
gently, he told me what greate
labure had be abowt ye readynge of
thos verses, &amp; how many dyd rubbe
thayr spectakles abowt thaym.
As oft as any old ancyent doctor
other of deuynyte or of the lawe, resortyd
thyder, by and by he was
broght to that table, some sayd yt
thay were lettres of Arabia, some
sayd thay were faynyd lettres. Well

at the last came one that redde the
tytle, it was wryten in laten with
greate Romayne lettres, ye Greke
was wryten with capytale lettres
of Greke, whiche at the fyrst syght
do apere to be capytale latē lettres,
at thayr desyer I dyd expownde ye
verses in laten, trāslatynge thaym
word for word. But whā thay wold
haue gyuyn me for my labour, I refusyd
it, seynge that ther was no
                     •
                  thynge
so hard that I wold not doo
for our blessyd ladyes sake, ye thogh
she wold commaūd me to bere this
table to Hierusalē.
            
            
               Me.
               What nede
you to be her caryoure, seynge that
she hathe so many angelles bothe
at her hedde and at her fette.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Than he pullid owt of hys pur
                     ••
                  e a
pece of wodde, that was cutt owte
of the blokke that our ladye lenyd
apon. I perceyuyd by and by thorow
the smell of it, that it was a holy
thynge. Than whan I sawe so

greate a relyque, putt of my cappe,
and feldowne flatte, &amp; very deuoutly
kyssyd it .iij. or .iiij tymes, poppyd
it in my pursse.
            
            
               Me.
               I pray you may
a man see it?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I gyue you good
leue. But if you be nat fastynge,
or if you accompanyed with yowre
wyffe the nyght before, I conceyle
you nat to loke apon it.
            
            
               Me.
               O blessed
arte thou that euer thou gotte
this relyque.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I may tell you
in cowncell, I wold nat gyue thys
litle pece for all ye gold that Tagus
hathe, I wyll sett it in gold, but so yt
it shall apere thorow a crystall stone.
And than the Supprioure whā
he sawe that I dyd take the relyque
so honorably, he thoght it shuld nat
be lost, in case he shuld shew me
greater mysteries, he dyd aske me
whether I hadde euer sene our ladyes
secretes, but at that word I
was astonyed, yet I durst nat be so
so bold as to demande what thos

secretes were. For in so holy thynges,
to speake a mysse is no small
danger. I sayd that I dyd neuer se
thaym, but I sayd that I wold be
very glade to see thaym. But now
I was broght in, and as I had be
inspired with the holy ghost, than
thay lyghtyd a couple of taperes, &amp;
setforthe a litle ymage, nat couryously
wroght, nor yet very gorgeous,
but of a meruelous 
                     •
                  tue.
            
            
               Me.
               That litle body hathe smale powre
to worke myrakles. I saw saynt
Christopher at Parise, nat a cartelode,
but as moche as a greate hy
                     •
                  
                  le
yet he neuer dyd myrakles as
farre as euer I herd telle.
            
            
               Ogy.
               At
our ladyes fette there is a precyous
stone, whos name as it is nother in
Greke nor Laten. The Frenchemā
gaue it the name of a tode, bycause
it is so like, that no man (althoghe
he be conynge) can set it forthe more
lyuely. But so moche greater is

the myrakle, that the stone is litle,
the fourme of the tode dothe nat apere,
but it shynythe as it were enclosyd
within that precyous stone.
            
            
               Me.
               Perauenture they ymagyne ye
symylytude of a tode to be there,
euyn as we suppose whan we cutte
ye fearne stalke there to be an egle,
and euyn as chyldren (whiche they
see nat indede) in ye clowdes, thynke
they see dragones spyttynge fyre, &amp;
hylles flammynge with fyre, &amp; armyd
mē encownterynge.
            
            
               Ogy.
               No,
I wold you shuld know it, there is
no lyuynge tode that more euydētly
dothe expresse hymselffe than it
dyd there playnly apere.
            
            
               Me.
               Hetherto
I haue sufferyd thy lyes, but
now get the another what wyll beleue
the, thy tale of a tode.
            
            
               Ogy.
               No
maruayle Menedemus thogh you
be so disposyd, for all the world cannot
make me to beleue yt, not &amp; all
doctoures of dyuynyte wold swere

it were trewe. But that I sawe it
with myne eyes, ye with thes same
eyes, dyd I proue it. But in ye meanseson
me thynke you regard naturall
phylosophye but litle.
            
            
               Me.
               why
so, because I wyll nat beleue ye a
                     ••
                  es
flye?
            
            
               Ogy.
               An do you nat se, how nature
the worker of all thynges, dothe
so excell in expressynge ye fourme
bewty, &amp; coloure of thaym maruylously
in other thynges, but pryncypaly
in precyous stones? moreouer
she hathe gyuen to ye same stones
wonderouse vertu and strēkthe
that is almost incredyble, but that
experience dothe otherwyse testyfye.
Tell me, do you beleue that a
Adam and
                     •
                   stone wold drawe vnto
him stele wtowt any towchynge
therof, and also to be seꝑate frome
him ayen of hys owne accorde, excepte
that yow had sene it with
yowre eyes.
            
            
               Me.
               No verely, nat and
if .x. Arystoteles wold perswade me

to the cōtrarye.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Therfore bycause
you shuld nat say thys were
a lye, in case you here any thynge,
whiche you haue not sene prouyd.
In a stone callyd Ceraunia we see
ye fashon of lightnynge, in the stone
Pyropo wyldfyre, Chelazia dothe
expresse bothe the coldnes and the
fourme of hayle, and thoghe thou
cast in to the hote fyre, an Emrode,
wyll expresse the clere water of the
seye. Carcinas dothe counterfayte
ye shape of a crabfish
                     •
                  . Echites of
the serpente vyper. But to what
purpose shuld I entreat, or inuestygate
the nature of suche thynges
whiche be innumerable, whā there
is no parte of nature nor in the elementes,
nother in any lyuynge creature,
other in planetes, or herbes ye
nature euyn as it were all of pleasure,
hathe not expressyd in precyous
stones? Doo yow maruayle thā
yt in thys stone at owre ladies fote,

is the fourme and fashon of a tode?
            
            
               Me.
               I maruayle that nature shuld
haue so moche lesure, so to counterfayt
the nature of althynges.
            
            
               Ogy.
               It was but to exercyse, or occupye
the curyosytye of mannes
wytte, and so at the lest wyse to kepe
vs frome ydlenes, and yet as
thoghe we had nothynge to passe ye
tyme with all, we be in maner
made apon foles, apon dyesse, and
crafty iogeleres.
            
            
               Me.
               You saye very
truthe.
            
            
               Ogy.
               There be many men
of no smale grauytye, that wyll say
thys kynd of stones, if that you put
it in vynagre, it wyll swyme, thoge
you wold thruste it downe with violence.
            
            
               Me.
               Wherfore do thay sette a
tode byfore our lady?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Bycause
she hathe ouercome, trode vnderfote,
abolyshyd all maner of vnclennes,
poysō, pryde, couytousnes, and
all wordly affectyones that raygne
in man.
            
            
               Me.
               Woo be to vs, that haue
so many todes in owre hartes.
            
            
               
               Ogygy.
               We shalbe purgyd frome
thaym all, if we dylygētly worshipe
owre lady.
            
            
               Me.
               How wold she be
worshipyd.
            
            
               Ogy.
               The most a
                     ••
                  eptable
honor, that thou canste 
                     〈◊〉
                   to
her is to folowe her lyuynge.
            
            
               Me.
               You haue told all atones. But this
is hard to brynge to pass.
            
            
               Ogy.
               You
saye truthe, but it is an excellen
                     •
                  e
thynge.
            
            
               Me.
               But go to, and tell on
as you begane.
            
            
               Ogy.
               After thys to
come to owre purpose, the Supprioure
shewyd to me ymages of gold
and syluer, and sayd, thes be pure
gold, and thes be syluer and gyltyd,
he told the pryce of euery one of
thaym, and the patrone. Whan I
wonderyd, reioysynge of so maruelouse
ryches, as was abowt our lady,
than saythe the Sextē bycause
I percayue, that you be so vertuously
affecte, I suppose it greate
wronge, to hyde any thynge frome
you, but now you shall see the pryuytyes

of our lady, and than he pullyd
owt of the aultre a whole world
of maruayles, if I shuld tell you of
all, a whole daye wold nat suffyse, &amp;
so thys pylgremage chansyd to me
most happy. I was fyllyd euyn full
withe goodly syghts, and I brynge
also with me this wonderous relyque,
whiche was a tokē gyuen to me
frōe our lady.
            
            
               Me.
               Haue you nat it
prouyd, what valewre your woden
relyque is on?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Yis, yt I haue, in
a certayne Inne within thys thre
dayes, ther I fownde a certayne
man yt was bestraght of hys wytte,
whiche shuld haue be bownde, but
thys woden relyque was put vnder
hys nekke pryuyly, wherapon he
gad a sadde and sownd sleape, but
in the mornynge he was hole and
sownde as euer he was before.
            
            
               Me.
               It was nat the phrenysy, but the
dronkē dropsye, sleape ys wontyd to
be a good medicyne for yt dysease.
            
            
               
               Ogy.
               Whā you be dysposyd to skoffe
Menedemus, yt ys best yt you gette
a nother maner of gestynge stokke
than thys, for I tell you it is nother
good nor holsome, to bowrde so wt 
sayntes. For thys same mā dyd say,
that a woman dyd apere to hym,
in hys sleape, after a maruelouse
fashion, whiche shold gyue hym a
cuppe to drynke apon.
            
            
               Mene.
               I suppose
it wasElleborum wyll restore a man to hys senses that hathe lost thē. Elleborū.
            
            
               Ogy.
               That
is vncertayne, but I kno well yt mā
was well broght into hys mynde
ayen.
            
            
               Me.
               Dyd you other come or
goo by Sante Thomas of Cantorbury
that good archebishope.
            
            
               Ogy.
               What els / there ys no pylgremage
more holy.
            
            
               Me.
               I wold fayne here
of yt, and I shold nat trouble you.
            
            
               Ogy.
               I pray you here, &amp; take good
hedd. Kente ys callyd that parte of
England, yt buttythe apon Fraūce
and Flanders, the cheffe cytye there
of ys Cantorburye, in yt there be ij.

Abbayes, bothe of thaym be of Saynte
Benedyctꝭ ordre, but yt which
ys callyd Saynte Augustynꝭ dothe
apere to be the oldre, that whiche
ys callyd now Saynte Thomas
dothe apere to haue be the Archebyshope
of Cantorburys see, where
as he was wontyd to lyue wt a sorte
of monkes electe for hym selffe, as
Byshopes now adayes be wontyd
to haue thayr howses nye vnto the
churche, but aparte frome other canonꝭ
howses. In tymes paste bothe
Byshopes &amp; Chanones were wontyde
to be monkes, as may be playnly
prouyd by many argumentes.
The churche which ys dedycate to
Saynte Thomas, dothe streche
vpe apon heght so gorgeously, that
it wyll moue pylgrymes to deuocion
a ferre of, and also withe hys
bryghtnes and shynynge he dothe
lyght hys neybures, &amp; the old place
whiche was wontyd to be most holy,

now in respecte of it, is but a darke
hole and a lytle cotage. There be
a couple of great hye toures, which
doo seme to salute strangeres aferre
of, and thay dow fyll all the contray
abowt bothe farre and nere, wt
the sownde of great belles, in the
fronte of the temple, whiche is apō
the southe syde, there stand grauen
in a stone thre armyd men, whiche
with thayr cruell handes dyd sleye
the most holy saynte Thomas, and
there is wryten thayr surnames
Tracy, Breton, and Beryston.
            
            
               Me.
               I pray you wharfore doo thay suffer
thos wykyd knyghtes be so had
in honoure.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Euyn suche honor
is gyuen to thaym as was gyuē to
Iudas, Pylate, and Caiphas, &amp; to
the compa
                     •
                  y of the wykyd so wdyeres,
as you may se payntyd in the
tables that be sett byfore aultres.
Thayr surnames be put to lest any
man hereafter shuld vsurpe any

cause of thayr prayse. Thay be
payntyd byfore mennes eyes, bycause
that no cowrtyer after thys
shuld laye violēt han
                     •
                  es other apō
Byshopes, or the churche goodes.
For thes thre of this garde strayght
a
                     •
                  on that wykyd acte, wente starke
madde, nor thay had neuer had
thayr mynde ayen, but that thay
prayd to blessyd saynt Thomas.
            
            
               Me.
               O blessyd pacyence of suche martyres.
            
            
               Ogy.
               At our entre in, lord what
a pryncely place dyd apere vnto vs,
where as euery mā that wyll may
goo in.
            
            
               Me.
               Is there no maruayle
to be sene.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Nothynge but the
greate wydnes of the place, and a
sorte of bokes, yt be bownde to pyleres
wherein is the gospell of Nicodemus,
and I cannat tell whos sepulkre.
            
            
               Me.
               What than?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Thay
do so dylygētly watche lest any mā
shulde entre in to the quere of yron,
that thay wyll skarsly fuffre a man

to loke apon it, whiche is betwyxte
the greate churche &amp; the hye quere
(as thay calle it) a man that wyll go
thyther must clyme vp many stayres
byfore, vndre the whiche there
is a certayne wykyt with a barre yt
openythe the dore apon the northe
syde. There standythe forthe a certayne
aultre whiche is dedycate to
our lady, it is but a lytleone, and I
suppose set there for no other purpose,
but to be a olde monumēt or
sygne, that in thos dayes there was
no greate superfluyte. There thay
saye that thys blessyd martyr sayd
his last good nyght to our lady, whā
he shuld departe hensse. In ye aultre
is the poynte of the sword that styryd
abowt the braynes of thys blessyd
martyr. And there lye his braynes
shed apon the yerthe, wherby
you may well knowe yt he was nere
deade. But the holly ruste of thys
grat I deuoutly kyssyd for loue of ye
                  
blessyd martyr. From thens we wēt
vndre the crowdes, whiche is nat
withowt hys chaplaynes, &amp; there
we sawe the brayne panne of that
holy martyr whiche was thraste
quyte thorow, all the other was coueryd
with syluer, the ouerparte of
the brayne panne was bare to be
kyssyd, and there with all is sethforthe
a certayn leden table hauynge
grauyd in hym a tytle of saynte
Thomas of Acrese. There hange
also the sherte of heyre, &amp; hys gyrdle
with hys heren breches where
with that noble champyō chastnyd
hys body, thay be horryble to loke
apon, and greatly reproue oure delycate
gorgeousnes.
            
            
               Me.
               Ye perauē
                  ture
so thay do the mōkes slotefulnes.
            
            
               Ogy.
               As for that mater I cā
                  nat
affyrme nor yet denye, nor yet
it is no poynte of my charge.
            
            
               Me.
               Ye saye truthe.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Frome thens
we returnyd in to the quere, &amp; apon

ye northe syde be ye relyques shewyd,
a wonderouse thynge to se, what a
sort of bones be broght forthe, skulles,
iawes, thethe, handes, fyngres,
hole armes, whā we had worshipyd
thaym all, we kyssyd thaym, that I
thoght we shuld neuer haue mayd
an ende, but that my pylgremage
felow whiche was an vnmete companyon
for suche a busynes, prayd
thaym to make an end of sethynge
forthe thayre relyques.
            
            
               Me.
               What
felowe was that?
            
            
               Ogy.
               He was an
Englyshmā callyd Gratiane colte
a man bothe vertuouse and well
learnyd, but he had lesse affectyon
toward pylgremages than I wold
that he shuld haue.
            
            
               Me.
               One of Wyclyffes
scoleres I warrante you?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I thynke nat, althoghe he
hadde redde hys bokes, how he came
by thaym I cannattell.
            
            
               Me.
               He
dysplesyd mayster. Sextē greuofly.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Thā was there broght forthe

an arme whiche had yet the redde
fleshe apon it, he abhorryd to kysse
it, a man myght se by hys countenance
that he was nothynge well
pleasyd, &amp; than by and by mayster
Sexten put vp hys relyques. But
than we lokyd apō the table whiche
was apō the aultre, and all hys gorgeousnes,
aftrewarde thos thyngꝭ
that were hydde vnder the aultre.
ther was nothynge but riches excedynge,
a man wold accompte both
Midas and Cresus beggers in respecte
of thos riches that ther was
sett abrode.
            
            
               Me.
               Was ther no more
kyssynge thē?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No, but an other
affection and desyre came apō me.
            
            
               Me.
               What was that?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I syghed
yt I had no suche relyques at home.
            
            
               Me.
               Oh a wycked desyre &amp; an euyl
thought
            
            
               Ogy.
               I graunt, and there
                     •
                  fore
I axyd, forgyfnes of Saynt Thomas
before I remouyd one fote, to
departe out of the churche. After

thes thus we were brought in to ye
reuestry, o good lorde what a goodly
syght was ther of vestmētes of veluet
&amp; clothe of golde, what a some
of candlestykes of gold? We sawe
ther saynt Thomas crosse staffe,
ther was seē also a rede ouerlayed
with syluer, it was but of a smalle
wyght, vnwrought, nor no longer
then wold retch vnto a mans mydgle.
            
            
               Me.
               Was ther no crosse?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I
sawe none at all, ther was shewed
vs a robe of sylke treuly, but sowed
with cowrse threde, garnysshyd wt
nother gold nor stone. Ther was
also a napkyn full of swette blody,
wher with saynt Thomas wypyd
bothe hys nose and hys face, these
thynges as monumētes of auncyent
sobernes we kyssed gladely.
            
            
               Me.
               Be not these thynges showed to euery
body?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No for sothe good
syr.
            
            
               Me.
               How happened it that you
were in so good credens, that no secret

thynges were hyd frome you?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I was well acquyntede with
the reuerende father Gwylyame
warham the archbyshope. He wrote
.ij. Or .iij. wordes in my fauour.
            
            
               Me.
               I here of many that he is a mā
of syngler humanite.
            
            
               Ogy.
               But rather
thou woldest call hym humanite
it selfe if thou dydest well know
hym. For ther is in hym soche lernynge,
so vertuouse lyffe, soche purenes
of maneres, that a mā cowld
wyshe no gyfte of a ꝑfayte Byshope
in him, that he hathe nat. Frome
thens afterward we were ladde to
greater thynges. For behyndethe
hyghe aultre, we ascēdyd as it were
in to a nother new churche, ther
was shewed vs in a chapell the face
of the blessed man ouergylted and
with many precyous stones goodly
garnysshed. A soden chaunse here
had almost marred the matter and
put vs out of conceyte.
            
            
               Me.
               I tary

to knowe what euyl chaunse yow
wyll speke of.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Here my companyō
Gratiā gote hym lytle fauoure,
for he, after we had mad an ende of
praynge, inquyred of hym that sate
by the hede, herke, he seyd, good father,
is it true that I here, yt saynt
Thomas whyl he it lyued was mercyfull
toward ye poer people? That
is very true saythe he, and he begā
to tell greatly of his liberalyte and
compassyon that he shewede to the
poer and nedy. Then sayd Gratiā:
I thynke that affection and good
mynd in him not to be chaungyde,
but yt it is now moche better. Unto
this graunted ye keper of the hede,
agayn sayd he, then in as moche as
thys holy man was so gratyouse
vnto ye poer, whan he was yet poer,
&amp; he hym selfe had nede of monay
for ye necessarys of hys body, thynke
ye nat that he wold be contēt, now
that he is so ryche, and also nedethe

nothynge, that if a poer womā hauynge
at home chylderne lakynge
mete and drynke, or els doughters
beynge in danger to lose ther virginite,
for defaute of ther substaunce
to mary them with, or hauynge her
husbande fore syke, and destitute
of all helpe, in case she askyd 
                     •
                  y
                     ••
                  ns,
&amp; pryuyly stole a way a small porcyon
of so greate riches, to sukkre her
how shold, as and if she shold haue it
of one that wold other leane, or gyue
it to herre? And whan he wold
nat answere that 
                     •
                  epyd the golden
hedde, Gracyane, as he is somwhat
hasty, I, saythe he, doo suppose
playnly, that this holy man wold be
gladde, yf yt he, now beynge deade,
myght sustayne the neces
                     •
                  iye of pore
people. But there mayster parsone
begone to frowne, &amp; byte hys
lyppe, with hys holowe eyes lyke to
A mōster yt hathe snakes for heares apon her hedde.Gorgone ye monstre to luke apō
vs. I doo not dowbte he wold haue

cast vs out of the temple, and spytte
apō vs, but that he dyd knowe that
we were comendyd of the archebyshope.
But I dyd somwhat myttygate
the manes ire, with my fayre
wordes, saynge that Gratiane dyd
nat speake as he thoghte, but that
he gestyd as he was wontyd to
doo, and stoppyd hys mouthe with
a fewe pens.
            
            
               Mene.
               Treuly I do
greatly alow your goodly fashion,
but oftentymes ernestly I cōsyder,
by what meaynes they may be acō
                  pted
without faute &amp; blame, that
bestow so moche substance in buyldyng
churchys, in garnysshynge,
and enrychynge them without all
mesure. I thynke as touchyng the
holy vestmentes, &amp; the syluer plate
of the temple ther ought to be gyuyn,
to the solempne seruys, hys
dygnyte and comlynes, I wyll also
that the buyldyng of the churche
shall haue hys maiesty decent and

conuenyent. But to what purpose
seruyth so many holy water pottes,
so many cādlestyckes, so many ymages
of gold. What nede there so many
payre of organes (as thay call
them) so costely &amp; chargeable? For
one payre can not serue vs: what
profyteth ye musicall criynge out
in the temples yt is so derely bought
and payed for, whan in the meaneseson
our brothers and systers the
lyuely temples of Christe liynge by
the walles / dye for hungre &amp; colde.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Ther is no vertuouse or wyse
man, that wold nat desyre a meane
to be hadde in thes thynges. But
in as moche as thys euyl is growen
and spronge vp of superstityon beyond
mesure, yet may it better be
sufferde, specially when we confyder
on the other syde the euyll conscience
and behauyor of them that
robb the churchys of whatso euer
iuellys ther may be founde, thes ryches

were gyuen in a maner great
men, &amp; of pryncys, the whiche they
wold haue bestowede vpon a worse
vse, that is to say other at the dyce
or in the warres. And if a man take
any thynge from thense. Fyrst of all
it is taken sacrylege, then they hold
ther handes that were accustomed
to gyfe, besyde that morouer they
be allured &amp; mouyde to robbynge &amp;
vaynynge. Therfore thes mene be
rather the kepers of thys treasures
thē lordes. And to speake a worde
for all, me thynket it is a better
syght to beholde a temple rychely
adourned, as ther be some with bare
wolles, fylthy and euyl fauorde,
more mete for stables to put horses
then churches for Chrysten people.
            
            
               Me.
               Yet we rede that Byshopes in
tymes paste were praysede and cō
                  mended
bycause they solde the holy
vesseles of theyr churches, and wt
that money helped and releued the

nedy and poure people.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Thay
be praysede also now in our tyme,
but thay be praysed onely, to folow
ther doynge (I suppose) thay may
not, nor be any thynge dysposede.
            
            
               Me.
               I interrupte and lett yowr cō
                  munycatyon.
I loke now for the cō
                  clusyon
of ye tale.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Gyffe audyence,
I wyll make an ende shortly.
In the meane seson comyth forthe
he that is the cheffe of them all.
            
            
               Me.
               Who is he? the abbot of the place?
            
            
               Ogy.
               He werythe a mytre, he may
spend so moche as an abbot, he wā
                  ted
nothynge but ye name, and he is
called prior for this cause tharchebyshope
is takē in the abbotes sted.
For in old tyme who so euer was
archbyshope of ye dyocese, the same
was also a monke.
            
            
               Me.
               In good
faythe I wold be content to be namyde
a Camelle, if I myght spende
yerely the rentes and reuennes of
an abbot.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Me semede he was a

man bothe vertuous and wyse, and
not vnlearnede Duns diuinite. He
opened the shryne to vs in whiche ye
                  
                     •
                  olle body of the holy mā, thay say,
dothe rest and remayne.
            
            
               Me.
               Dydste
thou see hys bones.
            
            
               Ogy.
               That is
not conuenient, nor we cowld not
come to it, except we sett vp laders,
but a shryne of wod couerede a shryne
of gold, when that is drawne vp
with cordes, thā apperith treasure
and riches inestimable.
            
            
               Me.
               What
do I here? the vilest part and worst
was golde, all thynges dyd shyne,
florishe, and as it were with lyghtnynge
appered with precyouse stones
and those many and of great
m
                     •
                  ltitude: some were greater than
a gowse egge. Dyuerse of ye monkꝭ
stode ther aboute with greate reuerence,
the couer takyn a way, all
we kneled downe and worshyped.
The pryor wt a whyte rodde showed
vs euery stone, addynge therto the

frenche name, the value, &amp; the autor
of the gyfte, for the cheffe stonys
were sent thyther by great prynces.
            
            
               Me.
               He ought to be a man of an
excedyng witt &amp; memory.
            
            
               Ogy.
               You
gesse well, how beit exercyse &amp; vse
helpeth moche, for euyn the same he
dothe oftentymes. He brought vs
agayne in to the crowdes. Our lady
hathe ther an habitacyon, but
somwhat darke, closed rownde aboute
with double yren gratꝭ.
            
            
               Me.
               What feared the?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Nothinge I
trow, except theues. For I saw neuer
any thing more laden with riches
synse I was borne of my mother.
            
            
               Me.
               You show vnto me blinde
ryches.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Whē they brought vs
candellꝭ we saw a sight passynge ye
ryches of any kynge.
            
            
               Me.
               Dothe it
excede our lady of walsyngā?
            
            
               Ogy.
               To loke vpō this, is richer, the secret
tresure she knoweth her selfe, but
this is not 
                     〈◊〉
                  , but to great

men, or tospecy all frendes. At the
last we were brought agayne in to
the reueitry, there was taken out a
cofer couered with blacke lether, it
was sett downe apon the table, it
was sett open, by and by euery body
kneled downe and worshipyd.
            
            
               Me.
               What was in it?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Certayne torne
ragges of lynnen clothe, many
hauynge yet remaynynge in them
the token of the fylthe of the holy
mannes nose. With thes (as they
say) saynt Thomas dyd wype a way
the swett of hys face or hys neke, ye
fylthe of hys nose, or other lyke fylthynes
with whiche mannes body
dothe abownde. Then my companyon
Gratian, yet ones agayn, got
hym but smalle fauour. Unto hym
an Englyshe man and of famyly are
acquayntenance and besyde that,
a man of no smalle authorite, the
Prior ga
                     ••
                   gentylly one of the lynnē
ragges, thynkynge to haue gyuen

a gyfte very acceptable &amp; pleasaunt,
But Gratian there with lyttle pleasede
and content, not with out an
euydent synge of dyspleasure, toke
one of them betwene hys fyngers,
and dysdaynyngly layd it down agayne,
made a mocke and a mow
at it, after the maner of puppettes,
for thys was hys maner, if any
thyng lykede hym not, yt he thought
worthy to be despysede. Wher at I
was bothe ashamed and wonderously
afrayed. Notwithstondynge
the Prior as he is a man not at all
dull wytted, dyd dyssemble the matter,
&amp; after he had caused vs drinke
a cuppe of wyne, gentylly he let vs
departe. When we came agayne to
London.
            
            
               Me.
               What shuld ye do at
London: seynge ye were not farre
from the see co
                     •
                  t, to seale in to yowr
cuntre?
            
            
               Ogy.
               It is true. But that
see cost I refused and gladely dyd
fle from it, as from a place that is

noted and more euyl spoken of it,
for robbyng. stelynge, and vntrue
dealynge, then is of dangerouse ioperdy
in the see, be that hyll Malea
wher many shyppes be drowned &amp;
vtterly destroyed for euer. I wyll
tell the what I dyd se the last pass
                     •
                  
                  ge,
at me commynge ouer. We were
many caryed in a bote frome Calys
shore to go to the shyppe. Amongest
vs all was a pour yōge mā of Fraū
                  ce,
and barely appayrelled. Of hym
he demau
                     •
                  ded halfe a grote. For
so moche thay dow take and exacte
of euery one for so smalle a way rowynge.
He allegede pouerty, then
for ther pastyme thay searched hym,
plucked of hys shoes, and betwene
the shoo and the soule, thay fownde
x. or .xij. grotes, thay toke thē from
hym laughyng at the mater: mockynge
and scornyng the poer &amp; myserable
Frenchman.
            
            
               Me.
               What dyd ye
fellow than?
            
            
               Ogy.
               What thyng dyd

he? He wept.
            
            
               Me.
               Whether dyd they
thys by any authoryte?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Suerly
by the same authoryte that thay
steyle and pycke straungers males
and bowgettes, by the whiche they
take a way mennes pursys, it they
se tyme and place conuenyent.
            
            
               Me.
               I meruayll that they dare be so
bold to doo soch a dede, so many lokynge
vpon them.
            
            
               Ogy.
               They be so
accustomed, that they thynk it well
done. Many that were in the shyp
lokede owt and sawe it also, in the
bote were dyuerse Englyshe marchauntes,
whiche he grudged agaynst
it, but all in vayne. The botemē as
it had ben a tryflyng mater reiosed
and were glade that they had so taken
and handelyd the myserable
Frenchman.
            
            
               Me.
               I wold play and
sporte with these see theues, &amp; hange
them vpon the gallowes.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Yet of such both the shores swarme
full. Here tell me, I pray the. What

wyll great mē do, whē theues take
vpō them to enterpryse soch masterys.
Therfore, her after I had leuer
go fourty myllys aboute, thē to go
yt way, thoffe it be moche shorter.
Morouer euyn as ye goynge downe
to hell, is easy and leyght, but ye cō
                  mynge
frome thens of greate dyffyculty,
so to take shyppynge of this
syde the see, is not very easy, and the
landynge very hard &amp; dangerouse.
Ther was at London dyuerse maryners
of Antwerpe, with them I
purposed to take thesee.
            
            
               Me.
               Hathe
that cūtre so holy maryners?
            
            
               Ogy.
               As an ape is euer an ape, I graūte,
so is a maryner euer a maryner: yet
if thou compare them vnto these, yt
lyfe by robbynge, and pyllynge and
pollynge, they be angelles.
            
            
               Me.
               I
will remembre thy saynge, if at any
tyme I be dysposed to go and se
Englāde. But come agayne in to ye
waye, frome whens I broght the

owt.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Then as we whent toward
London not farre from Canterbury,
we came in to a great hollow
and strayt way, morouer bowyng
so downe, with hyllys of eyther
syde, that a man can not escape, nor
it cannot be auoyed, but he must
nedes ryde that way. Upō the lefte
hand of the way, ther is an almes
howse for olde people, frome them
runnyth on owt, as sone as they
here a horseman commynge, he
casteth holy water vpon hym, and
anone he offereth hym the ouer lether
of a shoo bownde abowte with
an yerne whope, wherin is a glasse
lyke a precyouse stone, they yt kysse
it gy
                     •
                   a pece of monay.
            
            
               Me.
               In soche
a way I had leuer haue an almes
howse of olde folkes, then a company
of stronge theues.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Gratian
rode vpon my lefte hande nerer the
almes howse, he caste holy water
vpon hym, he toke it in worthe so so.

When the shoo was proferred hym,
he asked what he ment by it, saythe
he, it is saynt Thomas shoo. There
at he fumed and was very angry,
&amp; turned toward me: what (saythe
he) meane these bestes, that wold
haue vs kysse ye shoes of euery good
man? Why doo they not lyke wyse
gyue vs to kysse the spottel, &amp; other
fylthe &amp; dyrt of the body? I was sory
for the old mā, &amp; gaue hym a pece
of money to cōforthe hym with all.
            
            
               Me.
               In myn opynyō Gratian was
noe all to gether angry with owt a
good cause. If shoes and slyppers
were kept for a tokē of sobre lyuynge,
I wold not be moch dyscontent
ther wt, but me thynkꝭ it is a shamefull
fashyon for shoes, slyppers, and
breches to be offered to kysse to any
man. If some wold do it by there
owne fre wyll, of a certene affectyō
of holynes, I thynke they were
whorthy of pardon.
            
            
               Ogy.
               It were

better not to thes thynges, if I may
say as I thynke, yet owt of thes
thynges that cannat forthwith he
amended, it is my maner if ther be
any goodnes theryn, to take it out,
and apply it to the best. In ye meanseson
that contemplacyō and sight
delited my mynde, that a good mā
is lykened to a shepe, an euyll man
to a venemouse best. The serpent
after she is dede, cā stynge no more,
notwithstondyng with her euyll sauour
and poyson she infecteth and
corruptyth other. The shepe as lōge
as she is a lyue norrysheth with her
mylke, clothet with her wolle, makyth
riche with her lambes, when
she is deade she gyueth vs good and
profytable lether, and all her body
is good meat. Euen so, cruell men,
gyuen all to the world, so longe as
they lyue be vnprofitable to all mē,
when they be deade, what with
ryngyng of bellys, and pompyouse

funeralles they greue them that be
on lyue, and often tymes vexe ther
successours with new exactyones.
Good men of the other syde at all
assais be profytable to all men, and
hurtfull to noo man. As thys holy
man, whyle he was yet alyue, by
hys good example, hys doctryne, his
goodly exhortatyons prouokyd vs
to vertuouse lyuynge, he dyd cōfort
the cōforthlesse, he helped ye poure,
ye and now that he is deade, he is
in a maner more profytable. He hathe
buylded thys costly &amp; gorgeouse
churche, he hath caused greate authoryte
thorough out all Englande
vnto the ordre and presthode. At ye
last, thys pece of the show dothe susteyne
a company of poure people.
            
            
               Me.
               Thys is of my faythe a godely
cōtemplacyō, but I maruayll greatly,
seyng you ar thus mynded, that
ye neuer dyd vysyte saynt Patryckes
purgatory in Yerlande, of the

whiche the comyn people boost many
wonderouse thynges, whiche seme
to me not lyke to be true.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Of a suerty ther is not so meruelouse
talkynge of it here, but the
thynge it selffe doth fare excede.
            
            
               Me.
               Hast thou bene ther than, &amp; gonne
thorow saynt Patryckes p
                     •
                  rgatory?
            
            
               Ogy.
               I haue saylede ouer a ryuer
of hell, I went downe vnto the
gates of hell, I saw what was dōe
ther.
            
            
               Me.
               Thou dost me a greate
pleasure, if thou wyll wotsaue to
tell me.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Lett this be the prohemy
or begynnynge of owr communycatyon,
longe enough as I suppose.
I wyll gett me home, &amp; cause
my souper to be made redy, for I
am yet vndynede.
            
            
               Me.
               Why haue
you not yet dyned? is it bycause of
holynes?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Noo of a truthe, but
it is bycause of enuy and euyll will.
            
            
               Me.
               Owe ye euyll wyll to yowr bely?
            
            
               Ogy.
               No, but to the couetyse tauerners

euer catchynge and snatchynge
the whiche when they wyll
not sett afore a man that is mete &amp;
conuenyent, yet they are not afearde
to take of straūgers that, whiche
is bothe vnright and agaynst good
consciens. Of thys fashyō I am acustomed
to be auengede vpon thē.
If I thynke to fare well at souper
other with myne acquayntauns, or
with some host somwhat an honest
man, at dyner tyme I am sycke in
my stomacke, but if I chaunce to
fare after myne appetyte at dyner,
before souper also I begynne to be
well at ease in my stomacke.
            
            
               Me.
               Are ye not ashamede to be taken
for a couetouse fellow &amp; a nygerde?
            
            
               Ogy.
               Menedeme they that make
co
                     •
                  t of shame in soche thynges, beleue
me, bestow theyr money euyll.
I haue lerned to kepe my shame for
other purposys.
            
            
               Me.
               Now I longe
for the rest of yowr communycacyon,

wherfore loke to haue me yowr
geste at souper, where ye shall tell it
more conuenyently.
            
            
               Ogy.
               For sothe
I thanke you, that ye offere yowr
selfe to be my gest vndesyred, when
many hertely prayed refuse it, but
I wyll gyue yow double thankes,
if ye wyll soupe to day at home. For
I must passe that tyme in doynge
my dewty to my howsehold. But I
haue counsell to eyther of vs moche
more profytable. To morrow vnto
me and my wyfe, prepare our dyner
at yowr howse, then and if it be
to souper tyme, we wyll not leyue
of talkynge, vntyll you say that ye
are wery, and if ye wyll at souper
also we wyll not forsake you. Why
                     •
                  
claw you your hede? prepare for vs
in good fayth we wyll come.
            
            
               Me.
               I
had leuer haue no tales at all. Well
go to, you shall haue a dyner, but
vnsauery, except you spyce it with
good &amp; mery t
                     •
                  les.
            
            
               Ogy.
               But here

you, are ye not mouyd and styrrede
in your mynde, to take vpon yow
these pylgremages?
            
            
               Me.
               Perauenture
it wyll sett me a fyre, after ye
haue told me the resydew, as I am
now mynded, I haue enough to do
with my statyons of Rome.
            
            
               Ogy.
               Of Rome, that dyd neuer see Rome?
                     •
                  
               
            
            
               Me.
               I wyll tell you, thus I go
my statyons at home, I go in to the
parler, and I se vnto the chastlyuynge
of my doughters, agayne
frome thense I go in to my shope,
I beholde what my seruauntes,
bothe men and women be doynge.
Frome thense into the kytchyn, lokynge
abowt, if ther nede any of
my cownsell, frome thense hyther
and thyther obseruynge howe my
chylderne be occupyed, what my
wyffe dothe, beynge carefull that
euery thynge be in ordre, these be
statyons of Rome.
            
            
               Ogy.
               But these
thynges saynt Iames wold dow

for yow.
            
            
               Mene.
               That I shuld 
                     •
                  e vnto
these thynges holy scripture
commaundethe, that
I shuld commyt the
charge to sayntes
I dyd rede yt
neuer commaunded.
            
            God saue the kynge
            FINIS.
         
      
   

