
   
      
         
            The paraphrase of Erasm[us] Roterdame vpon [the] epistle of sai[n]t Paule vnto his discyple Titus lately tra[n]slated into englysshe and fyrste a goodly prologue
            Paraphrases in Novum Testamentum. English. Selections
            Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
         
         
            
               1534
            
         
         Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00386
            STC 10503
            ESTC S109940
            99845570
            99845570
            10477
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00386)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10477)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 39:10)
         
         
            
               
                  The paraphrase of Erasm[us] Roterdame vpon [the] epistle of sai[n]t Paule vnto his discyple Titus lately tra[n]slated into englysshe and fyrste a goodly prologue
                  Paraphrases in Novum Testamentum. English. Selections
                  Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
                  Cox, Leonard, fl. 1572.
               
               [72] p.   
               
                  Imprented by Ioh[a]n Byddell in London in Fletestrete next to the Flete Brydge],
                  [[London] :
                  [1534]
               
               
                  Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.
                  Title page has border (McKerrow and Ferguson 29) with Byddell's name in type in the sill.
                  Signatures: [A]-D chi⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-07
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-07
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2004-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            The Paraphrase of Erasmꝰ Roterdame vpon ye Epistle of saīt Paule vnto his discyple Titus. lately trāslated in to englysshe and fyrste a goodly▪ prologue
            ¶Cum priuilegio Regali.
            Iohan Byddell.
         
         
            
               〈2… pages missing〉
            
            
            uered his olde bryghtnes / &amp; shyneth so abrode now / yt euen they whose inwarde eyes be blynded with false perswasyons of man and couetyse &amp; vayneglorye perceyue a twynkeling of this light. For they can not deny but yt they haue erred in many thynges and were fer wyde fro ye square / how lothe so euer they be to heare it of laye men / or of suche as beynge good preestes / wolde fayne call theym agayne to his doctryne / who alone is the waye / ye trouth &amp; lyfe. And what can be a more euydent token of ye hye indygnacyon of the godhed agaynste the chyrche of Rome, then that this Pharao and all his egyptiens be so hardened in theyr hertes, that they wyll in no wyse receyue the truthe &amp; doctryne of hym whose folowers they professe themselfe

to be. Of whome may full well be affyrmed the wordes of ye prophete Dauid. Eyes they haue / &amp; shall not se. Eeres they haue, and shall not heare. wherfore no meruayle / for they are so drowned in the desyres of worldly worshyp, yt where as they shold saye with ye apostles to Chryst, Marci. x. lo we haue left all / &amp; haue folowed ye / they can not saye (yf they shall not lye) but the clene contrary / yt they forsake nothyng / but catche all to them selfe and forsake him. wherfore the same prophet Dauid fearyng this displeasure and greate angre of god fallen vpon the papystes / and desyrynge the grace shewed now to vs / prayeth on this wyse. Lord make thy waies knowē to me / &amp; teache me thy pathes. And why prayeth he so▪ For as he writeth in an other

place. Cursed be they good lorde that swarue from thy commaū
               dementes. Now who swarueth more from the cōmaundementes of god / thē he which taketh vpō hym to be an herdes man / and a feder of Crystes shepe / &amp; dryueth them away from theyr mete / nor playeth the good &amp; iust husbond of goddes house / so wynge spirytual thynges &amp; repynge therfore carnall, but he repeth carnall thiges / for ye sowyng of ye vnthrifty cockle of most foule and abomynable errors / and seducynge the people of god after his moste detestable lustes. which word good redar I wold not yt thou sholdest thynke to be spoken generally of all spyrytuall men. For there are among thē thanked be god hyely therfore, men endued with great cōnynge / wysedom / &amp; vertuous

liuing. whose workes according to the cōmaundement of the gospell, do shyne afore all men to the glorye of the father of heuyn. Againe thou must not so interprete my sayenges as I sholde thynke it vnlauful for the clergy to haue ony possessyons at al. Luc. x. euery workeman saythe Chryste is worthy to haue his wages. And the apostle wrytyng to ye Corinthyens sayth / who is he that serueth in warre at his owne coste? who planteth a vyne and eateth not of ye frut therof? who feadeth a flocke and eateh not of ye mylke of the flocke? But I meaned of suche as haue possessyons &amp; domynyons more lyke to kynges &amp; emꝑours then spyritual fathers. not noryshynge with them preachers of goddes worde and theyr nedy bretherne, but for preachers

of Crystes lawes / thei fede suche as p̄ache theyr decrees. And thē ye lyke Annas / Cayphas / Ioēs and Alexandre / of whome mentyon is made in the actes of the apostles forbyd men to speake or teache ī ye name of Iesu / for they will not haue his gospell taught nor spoken of, which Christ wold haue preached vpon houses. To rede ye new testament with them is heresy, which is no thyng elles saue Chrystes wordes &amp; his dyscyples. And for norysshynge of poore folke, they maȳtaine other, litle or nothyng regarding them that they shold regarde / but euen passe them by / as our lorde mencyoneth in the gospell of ye preest &amp; leuyte / that were moued with no pytye to socour the man that laye in ye way robbed &amp; wounded. Agaynste suche preestes / and all

suche as by fayned holynes and hypocrycy seduce goddes people from his teachyng &amp; ye instructyons of his apostles to theyr fayned dremes. Agaynst thē, cryeth scrypture in many places. Harke what Hieremie writeh in ye. xxiii. chapitre. wo be to sheꝑdes which dysperple &amp; all to teare the flocke of my pasture, therfore these wordes sayth the lord god of Israell to sheperdes that fede my people. You haue scatered myne herde &amp; throwne them out and not visyted them. Lo I shall visite vpon you the malyce of your studyes saythe our lorde. And Ezechyell in the .xxxiiii. chapytre. wo be to the sheperdes of Israell / whiche dyd fede them selfe. Be not herdes fed of theyr herdesmen / you dyd eate the mylke and with the wolles you were couered, &amp; what

so euer was fatte / you kylled it. But my flocke you dyd not feade you dyd not consolidate yt which was weake / you healed not that whiche was syk / you bound not to gyther yt whiche was broken / you brought not againe yt which was abiecte / and you sought not that which was lost / but you ruled them with austerite &amp; power. And my shepe were skatered abrode, because there was no shepherd / and they were deuoured of all the beastes of the feelde &amp; dysperpled. My herdes haue erred in all mountaynes / and in euery hy hyll / &amp; vpon all the face of the erthe my herd hath ben all to skatered / &amp; none there was ye wolde seke them. Therfore shepherdes here you the wordes of our lord. I lyue saith ys lord god. Bycause that my flockes haue bene made

in to rapyne and my shepe to the deuouryng of beastes of ye felde / bycause there was no shepeherd / nor the shepeherdes dyd not seke my flocke / but the shepherdes did feade them selues / &amp; they dyd not feade my herdes / therfore shepeherdes heare you the wordes of our lord. This sayth ye lord god. Lo I shall requyre of the shepeherdes myne herde oute of theyr honde / and I shall make them to cease that they feade no more my flocke / nor that ye shepherdes can no more feade theym selues. And I will deliuer my flocke frō theyr mouth / &amp; it shall be no more eatē vp of them. &amp;c. Se here most gē
               tle reader the angre of god enydently fallen vpon the bysshop of Romes tyrannye / and his adherentes whose proude power daylye decreaseth according to ye sayenges

of this prophete / for theyr deuourynge of Chrystes flocke. And se also on the other syde the greate goodnes of god towarde our Englysshe nacyon / whiche hathe delyuered vs oute of his rauenyng mouth / and gyuen vs our hed &amp; herdes man our moste redoubted souerayne / whome he hath made the veray defender of the fayth and an hed shepherd to set suche herdes men vnder hym / which shall fede vs &amp; not deuour vs. Is not this a greate token gentle redar / that almyghty god is well content with this gracyous &amp; veray fortunate maryage / whiche hath sente vs the light of his lawes sens that tyme &amp; hath brought vs out of the thraldome of yll bysshops. And as he made kynge Dauid keper of his herd of Israell as it is expressed of the

prophet in the forsayd chapytre / euen so he hath by the voice of his people / chosen our most noble &amp; vertuous kynge Henry to be hed of his Englishe flocke, as well in spirituall gouernaūce as in erthly domynyon. Let here no man murmour as some do yet / yt his grace is electe to be hedde of the chyrche in his realme / no forther then goddes lawes do permyt / as who saith, there is in yt pointe an obstacle. For why sholde not by goddes lawe our kynge and souerayne lord be our hed herdes man as well as Dauid beynge a lay prynce was hed shepehered to his flocke of Israell? Now wher can ony of them fynde one iote in scripture that proueth theyr most holy father to be aboue kynges or temporall rulers? peraduenture, they wyll brynge forth for them,

that Peter sayde to our lorde, lo lorde here be. ii. swerdes &amp; therof inferre / that he &amp; his successours had giuen to them hy power both ouer spyrytuall &amp; also temporall. In good soth this is a ioyly smal reason and worthy to come oute of a profoūde sophysters mouth, euen as who wold say. Yf when the kynges grace rydeth in to the forest on hūtyng / one shewe him an hart or two, ergo by and by he is chefe foster of ye hole londe. Ad populū phaleras / as ꝑsius saith. Let them blere good sely pore sȳ
               ple folkes eyes / with these gewgawes / for other men seith their lygyer de mayne well ynoughe. what saith Peter him selfe doeth he ascrybe ony such power to him or ony other of his teachyng. Be you obedyente saythe he to euery humayne creature for our lordes

sake / eyther to the kynge as most excellente (marke you he calleth kinges most excellent, &amp; vsurpeth no suche tytle to hym selfe) or to other guydes as sente of hym. Saint Paule sayth that all temporall power is of god / &amp; he byddeth in diuers places to be obedient to temporall prynces. Some hystoryes also make mencyon, yt ye bysshop of Rome toke not vpon hym to be hed of the chyrche tyll ye yeare of our lord. C. x
                  •
               v. Ergo then yf this hystorye be true it is a false tale to saye yt this double power was giuē to Peter of god, seyng that neyther he nor a dosen mo of his successours (graunted yt he was pope) toke it not vpon theym tyll one vyctor waxed so stoute / &amp; yet he vsurped no tēporall power, how that came in I report me to them. Saint Paule

neuer sayde of the apostles that they bare ony swerde, but of temporall prynces he sayd that they here not a swerde without cause. It is meate for vs then to gyue to god that is his / &amp; to our kyng yt is his. who as thou seest hathe the rule ouer vs vnder god &amp; not ye bysshop of Rome. And hyghly we are bounde to thanke the blessed Trinite / that ye eyes of faithfull people be vncouered to se the truthe. wherfore I confesse that I was my selfe a greate whyle blynded &amp; went asyde in the coū
               sell of wycked men. psal. j. &amp; stode a longe season in the way of synners / yea &amp; sate fast in the chayre of pestilence. But I thanke our blessed sauyour whiche dyuerslye calleth whome he lyft to hym / he hath vncouered myn eyes which were blyndfelde with two foule

cloutes of ygnoraunce and false perswasion / &amp; he hathe made me haue an occasyon to loke better on his doctryne / and to perceyue the errour that I was deceyued in / as Horace saythe. specie recti. and thynkynge there to be ryght where none was / &amp; there wrong where the ryght was. wherfore sens as I truste I haue escaped the foule storme of false beleue. For what shall I call els ye trust in papystycall power. I haue to ye entent to help other set forth in englisshe thept'e of saint Paule to his discyple Tyte which techeth howe moche and howe straytly we be bounde to obey next God our kyng &amp; souerayne lorde. For as he writeth in the. xii. chapitre to the Romaynes / who resisteth agaynste them resysteth agaynst the ordinaunce of god. And who

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
resyste agaynst gods ordynaūce, they purchase theyr owne dampnacyon. Agayne yf chrysten men be bounde to obey theyr prynces though thei be miscreaūtes, how moche more be we bounden to obey our most vertuous &amp; christen kyng &amp; lord / which so dyligently laboreth with all his hole entent to haue vs the veraye shepe of Chrystes folde and to delyuer vs also / from ye daūger of rauenyng wolues. wherfore no doubte but god of his goodnes wyll longe preserue hym &amp; defend hym from his enemyes. Besyde this epystle sheweth euery man both spirytuall and temporall, how he ought to vse him selfe, that he may after this lyfe be pertener of that lyfe / wherunto we are all bought / &amp; shall yf we lyue well not fayle to come to, not by pardons bought

from Rome / but by the merytes of Chrystes passion. wherfore I with hole hert and mynde besech the good redar yf thou fynde ony frute herein / as no doubte but y• shalte, and that largely / endeuer thy selfe as nere as god will giue y• grace to liue according to saint Paules doctryne, &amp; next to praye the blessed Trinite to graunt me his grace to leue from hens forth the blyndnes of synne and to lyue after ye lawes of god &amp; my prince. And to thentent yu shalt ye better perceyue what this holy apostle hathe wryten: I haue added to / ye paraphrase of Erasmus which shall make all thyng playne to the. The grace and peace of God be wt the and me and all good chrysten people. Amen.
         
      
      
         
            
            The Epistle of Paule vnto Tytus.
            
               
                  PAule the seruante of God and an Apostle of Ihesu Chryste: to preache the faythe of goddes electe / and ye knowlege of the truthe / whiche truthe is in seruyng god / in hope of eternall lyfe / whiche lyfe god that cannot lye / hathe promysed before ye worlde began / but hath at the tyme apointed opened his wordes by preachynge / whiche preachyng is cōmytted vnto me, by the commaundement god our sauyour, to Tytus his naturall sone in the comen faythe. Grace / mercye / and peace from god the father / and frome the lorde Iesu Christ our sauyour.
               
                  For this cause left I y• in Crete, that thou sholdest pfourme that, which was lackyng and sholdest ordeyne senyours in euery Cytye as I apoynted ye / yf ony be suche as no man can complayn on / the husbond of one woman, hauing faythful chyldren / which are not sclaundered of ryot / neyther are dysobedyent. For a bysshop must be such as no man can complaine on as it becometh the ministre of god / not stubborne, not angrye / no dronkard / no fyghter / nor geuē to filthy lucre / but herberous / one ye loueth goodnes / of honest behaueour / rygtuous, holy / temperat / and suche as cleueth vnto the true worde of doctryne / that he may be able to exorte wt wholsom learnynge / and to ymproue theym that saye agaynste it. For there are many disobedyent / and

talkers of vanyte, and disceyuers of myndes, namely they of ye circumcisyon, whose mouthes must be stopped whiche peruert hole housses teachyng thinges which they ought not because of fylthy lucre. One beyng of them selues which was a poete of their owne, said. The Cretayns are alwaies liars, euill beastes, &amp; slow bellies. This wytnes is true / wherfore rebuke theym sharpely / that they may be sounde in the faythe / and not takyng hede to iewes fables, and commaundementes of men, which turne from ye truth. Unto ye pur / are all thynges pure / but vnto theym that are defyled / and vnbeleuyng is nothing pure, but euen yt very mindes &amp; cōscyences of them are de
                     •
                  yled. They cōfesse yt they knowe god / but wt dedes thei deny him / &amp; are abominable / 

and dysobedient / &amp; vnto all good workes dyscomendable.
            
            
               The seconde chapytre.
               
                  BUt speake thou yt whiche becommeth holsome lear ninge / that the elder men be sobre, honest, dyscrete, sound. in the fayth in loue and patience And the elder women lyke wyse that they be in suche rayment / as becommeth holynes / not false accusars / not geuen to moche dryn kynge / but teachers of honeste thynges / yt they nurter the yong women for to loue theyr husbandes / to loue theyr chyldren / to be of honeste behaueour chast / huswyfely / good and obedient / vnto theyr owne husbandes, that the worde of god be not euyl spoken of. Yonge men lyke wyse exhorte

that they be of honeste manets. Aboue all thynges shew thy selfe an insample of good workes in ye doctryne shewe vncorruptio / honesty &amp; the holsom worde / which can not be rebuked / yt he whiche withstondeth may be asshamed / hauynge nothyng in you that he may dysprayse. The seruauntes exhort to be obedyent vnto theyr owne maysters / &amp; to please in all thinges, not answeryng agayne, neyther be pyckers, but that they shewe all good faythfullnes that thei may do worship to ye doctrin of god our sauiour in all thȳges. For the grace of god yt bryngeth health vnto all men: hath apered and teacheth vs that we sholde denye vngodlynes / and worldly lustes, and that we shold lyue honestly, tyghtuously / and godly in this present world, lokynge for

that blessed hope and gloryouse aperyng of the myghty god / and our sauyour Iesu Christ, which gaue hym selfe for vs / to redeme vs frome all vnryghtuousnes / &amp; to pourdge vs a peculyer people vnto hym selfe / feruently geuen vnto good workes. These thynges speake / and exhorte, &amp; rebuke with all cōmaundyng. Se that no man despyse the.
            
            
               The thyrde chapytre
               
                  WArne them that they submyt them selues to princes &amp; suche as haue power ouer thē to obey theyr cōmaūdment / that they be prompte vnto all good workes, that they speake euyll of no man / yt they be no fyghters / but softe / shewynge all mekenes

vnto all men / for we our selues also were in tymes past, vnwyse, dysobedyent / deceaued / in daunger / to lustes and to dyuers maners of voluptuousnes / lyuynge in malycyousnes / and enuye, full of hate hatyng one another. But after that the kyndnes / and loue of our sauyour to manward apered not of the dedes / of ryghtuousnes whiche we wrought / but of his mercye he saued vs, by the fountayne of the newe byrthe &amp; wt the renuyng of the holy goost / which he shed on vs aboūdantly thrughe Iesus Chryst our sauyour / yt we ons iustifyed by grace / sholde be heyres of eternall lyfe / thrugh hope. This is a true sayenge. ¶ Of these thynges I wold thou sholdest certefy / that they which beleue god, myght be stodiouse to go forward in good

workes. These thinges are good &amp; profytable vnto men. Folyshe questyons and genealogyes and braulynges and stryfe aboute the lawe auoyde, for they are vnprofytable / superfluous. A man that is ye auctor of fectes after ye fyrste &amp; seconde admonysshyon auoyde hym / remembrynge that he that is suche is peruerted and syn̄eth / euen dampned by his own iudge mēt. when I shall send Artemas or Tichicus be dylygent to come to me vnto Nycopolys. For I haue determined there to winter. Bryng zenas ye lawyer &amp; Apollos on theyr iorney dylygently / that nothyng be lackyng vnto them. And let oures also learne to excel in good workes as farforthe as nede requyreth / that they be not vnfrutfull. All that are with me salute the. Grete them that loue

vs in the faythe. Grace be with you all. Amen. wryten frome Nicopolis a citie of Macedonia.
            
         
         
            Here begȳneth the Paraphrase of Erasmus of Roterdame vpō saint Paules Epse to his dyscyple Tytus.
            
               
                  I PAule my selfe the sworne seruant and obeyer / not of Moyses lawe as I was ones / but of the law of god the father / and Embassadour of his sone Iesu Chryst. Of the whyche myne Embassade or cōmissyon the hole effecte is this, that suche as god hathe electe to euangelycal helthe / them I shold exhorte and call / not to ye obseruacyon of ye olde lawe / or to put

theyr trust in theyr workes / but I must moue thē to faith / which only openeth to all men ye entrȳg to euerlastynge lyfe / thrughe the free goodnes of Iesu Chryste.
               And my cōmyssyon is not to call them to faith onely / but also to ye knowleg of trueth which among the gentyles was ouerheaped &amp; doluen in the imagynacyons and fayned Inuentyons of worldly wysdom. And among the iewes it was had in shadowes &amp; wrappinges of figures. I am encharged I say to call men to ye knowlege of truthe / not that whiche ye phylosophers of this worlde do teache / dysputyng on the causes of naturall thynges / but to the knowlege of the truthe, whiche compendiously sheweth in what thynges true chrysten lyuyng is set / whose ende and rewarde is

euerlastyng lyfe / folowyng after this shorte lyfe that we lede here in this worlde, which euerlastig lyfe all good and godly lyuers ought with ye more trust to hope for / in how so euer great tribulations and euylles of this worlde they be. Fyrste by cause he yt promysed them this lyfe euerlasting was not a man that myght both be deceyuyd hym selfe, and also deceyue other / but it was god hȳselfe / which as it can not be chosen / but he must nedes abyde styll god / so can nothynge surely procede from hym / but ye mere truth. And agayne bycause this that he promysed, he dyd not promyse it by chaunce, or nowe of late / but afore that the worlde was made it was fyxed &amp; fully determyned by ye deuyne and vnchaungeable decre of his mynde to do yt which

he now doeth. There is no newe thynge come to his purpose / but that thynge which for secrete causes onely knowen to the godhed he wolde haue hytherto couered and hyd / that wold he haue opened to all the world at this tyme whiche by his euerlastynge wysdome he had afore appoynted to this busynes. Nor he wolde not that there sholde be onely shewed to the Iewes a darke shadow of ye fygures of some blynde thyng and harde to be discussed / but his wyll is to haue a playne truth to be made open by ye open &amp; playne preachynge of the gospell to all men, wtoute ony dyuersyte eyther of nation or tongue. This is the sum and hole effect of ye doctryne of the gospell / ye p̄chyng wherof I haue not takē vpō me of myne owne hed / but it was cōmytted

to me and not by men / but by our sauyour god / who not onely called me to ye occupieng of an apt'es roume and offyce / but also he enioyned it me / yea &amp; so he charged me therwith / yt it was not lauful or free for me to say naye to that whiche he cōmaunded me to do / which wordes I haue spoken to thentent yt no man sholde thynke myn authorite to be 
                     •
                  yhgt / or els theyr authoryte / whome I haue put ony where i my stede. I therfore ye same Paule beyng in suche authoryte do wryte this letter to Titus my true and naturall son / not by bodely generacyon but by the sede of faythe, which I haue so shed in to hym and in ye which he so well resembleth me / that I seme to be renewed in hym lyke as a father is in his owne naturall son. To hym I whissh that

there may come grace and peace from hym / from whome all very goodnes dothe come / that is to saye from god the father and his son Iesu Chryste ye onely author of our helth. For in suche ryches, as grace, &amp; peace are, my desire is to haue my chyldren made ryche. But to speake now to the my son Tytus, syth I dyd knowe ryght well the nature of this Ilonde / and againe I dyd not doubt but that they had nede of a faythfull and dilygēt creanser or ouerseer / I haue for that cause lefte the in Crete as representyng myn own person, bycause that the busynes of the gospell calleth me to other places / yt suche thynges as haue there begō to be corrected by me / thou as my deputye maye make make an ende of thē. And because yt thou alone art not able to ouerloke

so many cytyes as this He is replenysshed wt / yu shalt ordeyn in euery cytye an hedde preest or bysshop as I whē I depted dyd dyd the / But beware that thou admyt no man to so hye an offyce without greate dyscressyon / for he must be a very proued man to whome thou shalte betake this charge / and not all onelye of a knowen and testyfyed honestye / but also he must be clere from all supycyon of any maner of faute what so euer it be. Suche a bysshop or ouerseer to thent ēt that yu mayst ye better and surelyer those out / I wyll set hym forth by certayne sygnes / yea and in maner paynt hym to the. Yf thou know ony man to be of suche maners &amp; that vpryght lyuyng / yt no faut
                     •
                   can prouable be layde to hym. Yf ony man beyng content with one

matrimony geue no token of vnchast lyuyng / if he haue chyldren so instructe and brought vp, that not onely in the knowlaigyng of Chrystes faythe / but also by the innocency of theyr lyuynge they shew them selfe to be chrystē mē / that is to saye not yll named for ryot, as ye cōmune sort of yonge men be / nor dysobedyent to theyr father and mother. For he that shall be counted worthye to be a bisshop must be so fer wyde from all vyce &amp; besyde that fro ye suspicyon of ony vyce / that he muste marke that he not onely kepe his owne honesty / but also of all his householde, for the fautes of the chyldren are wonte cōmunely to be reproched to the fathers &amp; mothers. Now what soeuer hurteth ye good name of a bysshop / it turneth to ye sclaūder of the gospell of

Chryste. It is necessary therfore yt he whiche in a maner stondeth in goddes stede / and to whome ye treasure of the teachyng of ye gospell as to a chosen dispēser therof is commytted be in all poyntes without blame / and a great way from the vyces of theym whiche cōmunely here offycys / that they which be vnder hym, may be vnder him wyllyngly, and with all the hert in theyr body. He muste loke vpon nothyng but the soule helth of the flocke that is betaken to hym / he must study to amende and not to oppresse / to teache not to compell, to lede &amp; not to draw / he muste perswade rather then callynge for dutye / he must ouercom more by benefites and sufferaunce / then by lordlynesse and hy spyryte. He that shall occupye this rome I say must not be stubberne / 

                  
                     〈◊〉
                   angry / nor hasty ī speking / 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  hich thinges men will sooner withdrawe theyr hertes then folow ony doctrine, he must also in ony wyse beware of couetyse and gapynge after lucre for that thynge is vyle and pestylent in ony laye offycer, &amp; moche more to be abhorred in a bisshop or ony spyrytuall man. For he that is infecte with the vyce of auaryce doth nothyng vpryghtly, and as of equyte it shold be done. A bysshop muste besyde these be sober, iust in innocency of lyfe, vertuoꝰ and godly in the obseruacyon of Chrystes faythe and relygion of the gospell, not subiecte to ony yll affectiōs, but ferre aboue all such desyres by whiche the commune sorte of men are led vp &amp; downe. But chefyly he must be a stedfast holder of the wordes of ye gospell,

wherin he is bound to 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  ell instructe / that he may teache suche as be ignorant in those thynges that ꝑteyne to theyr soule helthe, &amp; that he may with holsom doctryne exhorte and call forwarde theym that are slow and repreue them yt speake agaynst the truth. I do not warne the of these thinges causeles / for there be many waywarde parsons / brabelers &amp; deceyuers of mennes myndes / which not geuyng an eere to the teaching of ye gospel, brȳg ī stede of it vayne &amp; vnprofitable fables of ye iewes, wherby they may get them a name of lernyng among ye people, &amp; wynnynge also. And by these fables they entise ye mindes of some symple folke &amp; begile them crawlyng vnder the colour of the gospell in to the mindes of theyr herars, in so moche y• many

tymes they corrupte not one or two, but they ouert̄ne hole householdes and kynredes, teachynge shamefull thynges / &amp; far square from the verite of ye gospell. And yet for al yt they abuse the tytle of the gospell to the lucre / whiche vilanously they daily hunt after / wherfore se yt you rebuke theym sharply and shyt theyr mouthes. There be some of the gentyles yt be combred with this enormyty / but specyally yu shalt fynde them of this malitious secte, which be iewes cōuerted to Chryst, which vntruely teache the gospell / menglynge alwayes ther wt ye lawes of moyses, and wyll not leaue in ony wyse the false superstition of the iewes. And it is no meruaile to haue suche men foūd in Crete, that fede their belies with brabelyng and naughty waies / sythen

mani yeares agone Epimenides the poete, whiche was hym selfe a mā of Crete, did speke of them / which wordes were these, Men of Creete be alwayes lyars / yll beestes / &amp; slothfull belyes which wytnes is so true yt it maye seme well ynoughe to be spokē of goddes own mouthe. Be not they natural lyers which fere not to darken the mooste clere lyght of the truth of the gospell with theyr fables. Be not they noyfull beastes whiche in euery place blow theyr venom on symple persones / that be not ware of them. Be not they slouthfull belyes, whiche had leuer by false doctrine to lyue in Idelnes and rankly, then for ye defence of the gospel to lyue in hungre, &amp; be shrewdly handled many tymes as we be? werfore rebuke suche naughty packes ernestly, yt
                  
they may amend / and leuyng the truste that they haue in the ceremonyes of ye olde lawe / they maigeue theim selfe holy to the truth of ye gospell. And that they geue not theyr eeres to such vnthrifty tales of the Iewes / thrughe the whiche the preceptes of Chryste are let go / and constytutions of men are brought in / of the obseruations of new mones / of the kepynges of the sabbot / of cyrcumcisyon / of wasshynges / of choyse of meates / of clothing, of certeine thȳges that may not be touched / of the house seuen dayes vnclene, &amp; other lyke to these, whiche god for a tyme cōmaunded to be kept of ye Iewes / partly that that nacyon beyng rebell and vnweyldy to be ordered / myght be holden &amp; kepte vnder by the multytude of preceptes or cōmaundementes / 

partely that these thynges shold be as shadowes of true thynges that were to come. But they are now vtterly of none effect so moche yt yf ony man wyll contynew styll to obserue these thiges after the maner of ye Iewes / nothyng can turne them more from the verite of the gospell. For there is no nation yt more stubbernely doeth rebel agaist ye gospel / thā ye Iues doo / which can in no wyse leaue these folyshe tryfles. This meate (say they) is vncleane eate it not. This body is vncleene touche it not / hens awai with these dyuer sytees amonge Christen men / to whom as they be cleane / all thynges are clane / nor they sholde abhorre nothynge yt god hath made for ye vse of man. And as to them yt be pure christē men / nothing is impure or vnclene, so to ye Iewes

whose mindes are filthy and vnclene, nothig is clene, not so moch as they that ye olde law suffereth and doth permyt as clene, for seynge they mystrust hym whiche after the openyng of the gospell wold haue all these thynges not obserued after ye fleshly &amp; litterall sence, but to be referred to the busynesse of the soule. what thynge can be pure to them, whose mind are spotted &amp; infecte wt mistrust / &amp; their liuyng defyled with inordinate wast / ambytion, couetise, and other vyces. They vpholde the lawe with to the &amp; nayle / and yet they wote not what the lawe meaneth. They haue their p̄puce circūcysed / but ye mynd wtin is vncircūcised. They go i to ye tēple wt hōdes &amp; fete wasshed, but ye soule &amp; cōsciēce is vnwasshed. They kepe their sabbot holy from bodely

workes / but in the meane tyme / they haue theyr breste vnquyeted with hate, anger, simony / &amp; other troubles of the soule. They fere to be contamynate yf they taste porke or pygge / but they thynke them selfes clene when they with gredy eeres here foule comunycacion &amp; bakbityng of other. They thynke them selfes fyled yf they touche ony caren / but yet thei abhorre not to touche a quene or stolen geare. They thynke it a foule synne yf they vse onye garmēt of lynen and wollen mengled togyther / but they stōde not amysse in theyr owne conceyte when they haue theyr brest ouercouerd with so many foule vices. It is a great shame therfore to theym to boste them selfe that they alone knowe god seyng that they deny hym in theyr dedes more then ony other.

Do they not deny him, whē they are so spotted with ye fylthyes of the soule, that they are to moste mē abhomynable, and when they be so weake, yea &amp; deed in beleue, yt no man can handle theym. And fynally when in all dedes of true faythe and seruyce towarde god by which we sholde make god to be mercyfull to vs / they be farre wors then other men be.
            
            
               The second chapyter.
               
                  BUt let thē go with theyr fables / let ye naughtines of these men moue the nothynge at all / but for all them remembre thyne offyce and duty, and speke tho thynges that be indede mete for the lernynge of the gospell / yt is to saye whiche may make vs cōmendable to god for

our clene myndes and clene maners / &amp; declare that we be the dyscyples of Chryst. But here peraduenture yu wylt aske me what thiges they be. Thou shalt warne the elders and senyours of the people yt they be sobre / wachfull / &amp; dylygent to all workes of vertue / and that they ouercome the dulnes of theyr age wt the quikenes of faythe. warne them also y• they kepe grauyte and that they play not the foles lyke yong men vncomely in theyr olde age. And that they be of good and sad maners / yt the youth may haue them in reuerence and awe / &amp; temꝑate them selfe that they be not waywarde and soone an angred as ye cōmune sorte of olde men is / and wel commended of other &amp; with out blame not onely for the integryte of theyr feythe / but also in

doynge dedes of charyte / and in suffrynge of incōmodityes &amp; trybulations, namely for the gospell of christ. On ye same maner thou shalt warne olde wemē that they go apparelled after suche maner as becometh theym that wyll be named chrysten folke / they must not blame the lyuynge of other / whiche faulte is peculyer to this sex and age. They muste not be geuen to ouermoche drynckynge of wyne / how be it y• vse of wyne must be permytted to age / so it be moderate. They must teche maydens &amp; yong women honest thinges / no nycenesse or other yll maners and so brynge them vp that they loue theyr owne husbondes and theyr children / and that they be sobre and chaste / and busy at home, and for to se theyr houses well ordered and playe the good

housewyues. For this surely is ye chefest praise yt women can haue, to be knowen subiect &amp; obedyent to their husbondes / that by theyr lewde maners the name of god, (whose relygeon they professe) be not sclaundred. For sythen we se ye wyues of myscreauntes or hethen men to behaue theym selfe ryght womanly in these pointes belongyng to womanhod / what shall suche infydeles say if they se christsten women in ye layd pointes worse then be theyr women whome as they are chrysten / so they ought a great deale to passe them in honestye &amp; vertue. Now what thynge old women muste by thyne instruction teache yong maydens and yong wyues / that same shalte thou thy selfe teache yong men / exhortyng them to be sobre &amp; moderate in theyr affections / 

that ye heate of youth ouerthrowe them not hedlynge in to viciousnes. And that thou mayst with more efficacie ꝑswade these thynges. Fyrst of all be thou thy selfe to theym an exāple of honest dedes, and yt in all office of godly lyfe. For no man doeth sooner or easylyer pswade, then he whiche constantly doeth as he teacheth. Thou shalte therfore teache the youth thus, &amp; in the meane space in teachynge lyue vprightly that thy lyfe be not corrupt with ony vyce / &amp; kepe suche grauyte that it maye make theym to haue thy doctrine in reuerence &amp; awe. And therfore so moderate all thy lyfe &amp; wordes that there can nothing be founde in the / to be despysed &amp; set at naught / so that not onelye they whiche be vnder thy loore / may obey the / but also they that

were afore agaynste the gospell, may be a shamed of theyr yll sayenge / when they shall se all thynges in the so without blame, that they whiche lye in wayte for the, and seke all ye occasyons thei can, to chop at the, can fynde nothyng wherby they cā iustly speake ony thyng agaynst y•. As concerning seruauntes exhorte theym to be obedyente to theyr maysters and dylygente to please theym in all thynges that not by the profession of Christes religion they may seme to be made wors then they were afore / and therby may begynne reproch to be geuen to the gospell / when it is al the frute of naughty parsons. Let them not therfore be full of excuses, and yll wylled to do theyr masters commaūdemētes, nor preny pykers / as the most sorte of yll seruantes

be / that seynge they professe the gospell they declare them selfe in all seruyse to be don to theyr masters, faithful &amp; true / yea though their masters do but litle deserue it of them. So that thrugh theyr honest maners thei may cōmend and set forth the doctryne of our sauyour god / yt by them mo men may be drawen to the folowyng of it / if men se suche as knowlege theym selfe to be christen men / to be therby more gentle and amyable in all theyr lyuynge. For in this thrugh ye gospel hath shined ye goodnes and gentelnes of god our sauyour not afore knowen. And it hathe not shyned onely to the iewes / but egaliy to all men, not that after we be delyuerd fro the burden of Moyses lawe / we sholde lyue after our owne wyll / but we be taught / that after that

by baptysine y• fautes of our lyfe afore past be forgeuen vs / &amp; that we sweryng to abide by Christes wordes haue ones renoūced and geuen vp the wycked relygyon &amp; worshipping of ymages, of ydols and with theym also all worldly desyres / so that after we sholde lede our lyfe here in this worlde that it may appere verely yt we be regenerat or new borne in Christ, and made quyte other men then we were afore. And we whiche serued afore to wyckedness / to vnhappy dedes &amp; dyuers affectiōs / which euen as it were baites drew vs to vyllanye: must from hence forth kepe suche moderatiō that we be in no wyse trobled wt desyres of worldly thynges. Let vs shew in vs iustyce / yt as moch as is in vs, we do for euery man, and hurte no man / that we may

now geue with a true professyon &amp; hole lyfe to god suche worshyp as we gaue afore to deuyls. And though in the mean season we be punished with pouerte / barenes, sclaunder / chydynges / &amp; dyuers other euylles / let vs not thynke that our good liuyng is baraine, nor let vs not therfore hunt after rewardes of this worlde / which be neyther in comparyson great / nor of no longe durance / but lette vs loke for that greate rewarde of euerlastyng lyfe that shal then chaunce when after yt this world is ended. In the which the membres of Chryste be yet busyed by afflyctions and sclaunders. God the father shall open in his worshyppers in his glory &amp; magnifycence / all theyr euylles ouercome not apperyng humble but gloryous and ferefull to wycked men.

And to gither with ye father shall appere in ye same glorie the lord &amp; sauyour Iesus Christ geuyng to his mēbres yt same euerlastīg life in ye which he now shineth, for he by cause yt no man shall mystrust his ꝓmise, wittingly &amp; willingly came to his deth, &amp; holy gaue him selfe to vs / yt he being fre from all synne wold redeme vs by yt pryce of his blode, from ye tyrāny of the deuill / to whō by our soule syn̄es we were subiecte. And after yt he had done away cleane our offences make to hȳ of vs a new &amp; his own people, which after his own exāple shold despise all euilles &amp; ye enticemētes of this world &amp; his reward trod vnder fete, shold laboure to get the enherytaunce of euerlasting life, which cryst doth ꝓmise to all yt kepeth ye profession of the gospel truly &amp; wt clenelyfe.
            
            
               
               The thyrde chapyter.
               
                  THese thynges my Tytꝰ wiche be a greate deale wyde from the fabls of ye Iewes / speake them openly. Exhorte all people to folow them &amp; suche as bend away from them rebuke them with by authoryte / that such men as will not be perswaded by lerning, nor will not be moued by faire exhortations, nor by sharpe &amp; ernestful correction made to refrayne. For there be some fautes that muste be healed by seneryte. Here therfore shewe forth the grauyte and authoryte of a bysshoppe and so behaue thy selfe / yt no man maye haue ony iust cause to despise the. Pryde and hawte countenaunce muste not be in the / but when so euer nede requyreth thou muste

shewe thyne authoryte. Now as I wold haue that all seruauntes sholde be to theyr maysters, yea thoughe they be gentyles / euen suche by thy monycyon wolde I haue all christē men to be to theyr prynces and to suche as are hed offycers vnder them / though suche prices or rulers vnder whom they be, are thē selfe vncrystened. For this muste we in ony maner of wyse take hede vnto / that no man may by our maners, catche ony occasyon to alienat him selfe fro the gospell. But it wolde so chaunce yf they that be heddes &amp; rulers shold perceyue that we by reason of the professyon that we haue taken / were more sedicyous and stately, and lesse obedyent to theyr cōmaundemētes. For they wolde anon ley that to the faute of the gospell / &amp; so more wtdrawe

theyr myndes fro the professyon therof. warne them therfore that beleue in Chryst / yt they be neuer the more for all that free fro the lawes &amp; authorite of the kynges or prynces or other rulers vnder whose domyniō they be / but they muste the rather bycause they be chrysten men, be obedyente subiectes / and gladly do as they be commaunded / and redy &amp; prone to euery good worke / then men may se them do as they ought to do not beyng constrayned therto for feare of punyshment / but of theyr owne fre wyll. For yf the heddes do cōmaunde that which is ryghtfull / it is greate iniquite and a foule ensample to dysobey hym that is heed ouer all other. But agayne yf they cōmaunde &amp; rule otherwyse then ryght is / yf they oppresse theyr subiectes to

hardly / yf they call to fore upon theym: yet gentlenes &amp; suffrance is more comely for no man thē ye folowers of Christe. what so euer they commaunde vs that is not agaynst ye very relygyon of god / we must therin gladly obey. Thei wyll peraduēture take away our goodes / what then? For theym groweth to vs a greate treasure of good vertuous lyuyng. They wil bannishe vs out of ye contrey. It maketh no matter / for Chryst is euery where redy to cōfort his seruātes. Here peraduēture some man wyll say / what &amp; our prynces be hethen men and worshyppars of Idolles / contamynate wt open vyces / enemyes to Christes faythe. They that be suche / be such to theyr owne harme and ieoperdy / it is not our parte to condempne them but to amende

theym. And better they may be induced by obedyence / suffrance / and examples of good lyuynge / then by rebellyon / or opprobrioꝰ sayenges. Let vs leue theym to their iudge / and let vs remembre what is syttynge for vs. Chryst dyd praye for them that blasphemyd him / so fer wide it is that he wolde gyue chek for chek / how is it then conuenyente that his discyples sholde be contumelious agaynste ony man as louers of stryfe and debate? But rather after the example of hym / whose name they do professe / they must be gentle / shewyng all myldenes not onely vnto honest men and suche as haue well deserued it / but also muste be obedyent vnto euery man. To good men bycause they deserue it / to yll men that they amende / and agayne that

they haue not a wors opynion of our beleue / yf they be prouoked and angred for a cause. Chrysten charyte suffreth all thynges / and in al thynges it hath good hope. And if there be ony such yll men / we must rather pytye them, then abhorre theym. And therfore we shall do more yf we call to remēbraunce that we were somtyme such as they be now. Let vs not refuse theym by cause they are yll lyuers, and wycked men / but let vs helpe ye best that we can / that they cease to be as they be▪ and begynne to be lyke vs / who called vs from our blyndnesse? was it not ye free clemencie or swete gentlenes of Chryst And that same gentlenes of chryste may chaūge such men whē he will. And how be it that we which of Iewes be made chrysten men, did not worshyp

Idolles / yet we were afore our conuersyon subiecte to great vices, beyng foles / iobedyent / erryng / geuen to diuerse appetites &amp; pleasures / ful of enui, ful of malice, grudgyng &amp; hatīg one of another. To these so great euylles we were subiecte euē vnder Moises lawe, but that now for foles &amp; dulheddes we be made sobre &amp; wyse / yt for rebelles we are meke and treatable / for men errynge / hauyng knowlege of the trueth / for the seruantes of desyres and voluptuousnes / the wyllynge kepers of iustice, for malycioꝰ / simple &amp; curtes / for enuious / glad to do good / for haters, wel willyng to them that hate vs / this haue we not neyther by moyses lawe nor yet by our owne merites, but by yt free goodnes of god / by the which we coueyte that all yf it be

possible sholde reioyce with vs in a cōmune welfare / and to all mē the verite of ye gospell may shyne, as it hath shined to vs. For afore lyke blynde men we were styll in darkenes as they, but now sens there is opened by the lyght of ye gospell / how great the goodnes and charyte of god (which is autour of our helthe) is to all men / then at the last we gate true lyfe after that we had put away the darkenes of our lyfe that we led afore / not thrugh the obseruatiō of Moyses law / in whome was conteyned a maner of iustice▪ but yet of lytle efficacye to geue euerlastynge lyfe / but thrugh the free mercye of god. For by the holy fonte of baptysme we were regenerat agayne &amp; plāted in Chryst, and by his spirite being renewed we haue ceased to be carnall and

begōne to be spirituall. Therfore what so euer we be / we are holy bounde to hym for it, which in to vs nothynge deseruynge it / shed aboundantly his spyryte / which the law coulde not geue. And by Iesu Chryste he shed his spyryte in to vs, by whō it hathe pleased him to geue vs all thynges / that we being purged by his benefite, frō our olde synnes shold enforce by good workes to be made apte to take ye enherytaūce of immortall lyfe. Of ye which the doctrine of the gospell maketh vs to haue sure hope. Sens that we then were ones myserable / and by the onely aboundante mercy of god deleuered from synne now hope for the crowne of euerlasting lyfe we must haue pyty on other / and go aboute by all meanes that god also may haue mercye on theym.

Let a chrysten bysshop in stede of iewes fables tel these thynges to the people, for they be certeyne &amp; without doubte. There remayneth nothyng more for vs to do / but yt in our liuing we may remē
                  bre ye benefyte of god and lyue accordyng to his pleasure / or elles the professyon of chrystendome &amp; the gospell wyll nothyng auayle vs. wherfore I wyl that yu assure all men of these thynges whiche greatly longe to the purpose &amp; cō
                  fyrm thē therin also / yt thei which ones haue beleued ī god / yt by his free mercifulnes they haue ben redemed fro theyr synnes / &amp; that he will gyue ye croūe of euerlastyng life to all them which by vertuoꝰ and godly lyuyng do study to folow as nere as thei are able Iesu Chryst / yt they I say which haue this beleue so lede ouer theyr lyfe

that it maye seme accordynge to our professyō &amp; not vnworthy so greate promyssys of god. Now they shall declare them selfe to be very christē men / not if they curse or say yll by ye gentyles &amp; iewes / but yf they be beneficiall &amp; gentle to all men / &amp; by the affection that they haue to pyty / they reioyse to helpe euery body. For these thinges shall not onely ornate &amp; commend ye professyon of the christen beleue / as thynges of theym selfe honest / but also ꝓfitable to draw other to Chryste &amp; to helpe other whiche be oppressed with ony calamyte. The chefe poynt of chrystentye is to do good to all men / and by benefites wylde bestes be ouercome &amp; made tame &amp; gentle. Thou shalt therfore on this maner speke &amp; preache of these thynges not makynge ony doubte as thei do which redacte all thinges

in to questyons and seme to haue nothyng perfyghtly to them assured / but teache them wt greate confydence of countenaūce with greate stedfastnes of wordes / yt all men may well perceyue &amp; vnderstonde that yu art well assured of that whiche thou doest labour to perswade to other men / yt oute of these cōmeth ye frute of vertuoꝰ lyuynge. But folysshe and vncō
                  nynge questyons and tangled or intrycate genealogyes and contencyous or brawlyng dysputations or rather warre vpō Moyses law / whiche some folowyng the trade of iewes styrre vp and moue to get them therby a name &amp; aduaūtage / cast them away as superfluous &amp; vnprofytable to ye liuyng after ye gospell. For what hurteth it to good lyuynge yf I know not / why Moyses graue can no where be found / whether

it be as ye iewes say that he shold be called vp agayne by magiciēs? How many yeres Matusale lyued? what age Salamō was of, when he begat Roboam? why Moyses dyd forbed to eate the flesshe of swyne? why ye iewes do suppose that the blode of a wesell must with so greate care be purged / &amp; other thynges they moue doubtes vpon, which be yet more folyshe then these. In the expoū
                  dyng wherof what neadeth him to tary whiche hasteth to the rewarde of good and vertuous lyuing. These thinges must rather be cut away then declared. And thei which professe them as excellent thynges must be blamed and byd to holde theyr peace and not disputed with all. If thei erre by symplenes / when they are admonysshed they wyll amend. But if they do amysse by stubberne and

obstacle malyce / for a name or lucre or ony other foule cause / then wyll they be redye also to defend as well false thynges as trwe. Such men when thou hast ones or twyse rebuked them / yf they cease not / exchew theym as men faccyous and incurable / lest they maye do more, when they be prouoked / then they wolde yf they were let alone as men not regarded / yea &amp; left to / by such eggyng and styrryng of theym▪ it myght come to daūger / that such which cānot be amended, might by dysputations when thei are ꝓuoked draw theyr admonytour into ye same errour. And what auaileth it to geue ony more medycynes when there is no longar hope of recouerynge. An errour cōmyng but onely by the fragilite of man, is remedyed by one or two warnynges but malyce is icurable,

and made wors, by putting to of ony remedyes. And therfore he yt beyng ones or twyse rebuked cō
                  tine with neuertheles to bide stife in his opynyon / let hym alone in his froward mynde a man quite ouerturned and remedyles. Nor it neadeth not ye to labour to condempne hym / sythen he is by his owne iudgement cōdempned. Yf he perische / he is lost &amp; cast away by his owne faute. For he hathe no such bukler to hold afore him. I erred by ignorāce / no mā warned me. For what can one do to a syk man / that wyll take no medycyne / peraduēture yf he be despysed &amp; neglect / he wyll wex wyser / yf he wyll not / yet the fewer that resorte to hym / ye fewer shall ye cōtagyousnes of his disease infecte. I wold fayn haue you with me a few dayes. But I wold yt it sholde not be to the damages / of

ye christē congregations in Crete whiche haue ben but of late conuerted to ye trew fayth, and therfore they haue the more neade of a diligent hed / which may builde vpon the fundations now layed. Se therfore that thou mete with me at Nycopole / but not afore yt I send either Artemas or Tichtcus thyder to be there for ye in my stede, lest thy deptyng sholde leue Crete destytute &amp; as an Orpheline. Thou shalt not nede to feare that I wolde in ye meane tyme go any where els &amp; so thou sholdest lese thy laboure / For I am purposed all this next winter to be at Nycopole which is a citie of the cōtre of Thrace. whē zeno which was sōtyme a ꝓfessour of Moyses law / &amp; now a noble preacher of ye gospell. And Apollo whiche is a mā greatly aproued in ye doctryne of Chryst wyll depart frō
                  
thens bryng them forward with all the humanytye that maye be. And se they lak nothynge yt shall be necessarye for theyr iorney. Yf these offices of humanytie be done of the gentyles / that they will for good maners sake bring him forwarde yf he haue deserued it / and geue hym sufficiently at his deꝑtyng vitayles &amp; other necesaries to his iorney. I thȳke it very ryght that our men also / whiche knowlege them selfe to be christē men sholde lerne to vse suche gentylnes / and to geue due thankes to them that haue well deserued them / not yt they sholde by theyr lyberalyte make them ryche / but yt they gyue them suche thynges as be necessarye for theyr liuyng, when nede shall be. For it is not conuenyent yt sythen they whiche be alyenat from Chryste / be yet taught of nature to geue thākes

to them of whome they haue ben holpen with ony benefite: christē men sholde be baren and vnfrutfull to them of whome they haue receiued ony good turne. As many as be here with me cōmende them to the. Do thou againe cō
                  mēd me there to as many as loue me not with no worldly affectiō, but with euangelycall &amp; chrysten charyte / whiche the cōmune professyon of fayth doth gēdre in vs. The fre benefycēce of goodnes of god be alwayes wt vs all. Amen.
            
            Thus endeth the paraphrase of Erasmus, vpō Paule vnto Tyte,
         
      
      
         
            Imprented by Iohn̄ Byddell in London in Fletestrete next to the Flete Brydge
            Translated by Leonard Cox.
            
         
      
   

