
   
      
         
            [Ye dyaloge called Funus]
            Colloquia. Selections
            Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
         
         
            
               1534
            
         
         Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00329
            STC 10453.5
            ESTC S118122
            99853331
            99853331
            18711
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00329)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18711)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1236:01)
         
         
            
               
                  [Ye dyaloge called Funus]
                  Colloquia. Selections
                  Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
               
               [56]p.   
               
                  By Robert copland, [sic] for Iohan Byddell, otherwyse Salysbury. the .v. daye of Ianuary, and be for to sell lat ye sygne of our lady of pyte nexte to flete brydge,
                  [At London :
                  [1534]]
               
               
                  Title from D2 recto. Imprint from colophon. Publication date from STC.
                  A selection from Erasmus. Desiderius.  Colloquia.
                  Signatures: A-C D⁴.
                  Includes, with caption title: "A good and a godly admonicion or warnynge, very behouefull for euery chrysten man to loke upon". Register is continuous.
                  Imperfect; lacking leaf A1 (title page) and tightly bound affecting text.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Death --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-04
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-05
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
                  •
               
               
theyr hope in the mercy of our lorde, &amp; reprehendynge (as it were somwhat in my way) ye grete folysshe ambycyon of ryche men vtteryng theyr superfluyte and arrogācy after deth, which at the vttermoste, dethe sholde haue fynys
                  •
               hed. Also I somwhat sharpely rebuke theyr vyce, which for theyr own auauntage, dooth abuse y• folyshnesse of ryche men, whiche they ought specyally to 
                  •
               ebuke. For who dare be so bolde to monyss
                  •
               e lyberally men of grete power &amp; rychesse, yf suche as ꝓfesse thē deed from the worlde do flatter theyr vyces / be it there be no suche as I haue dyscrybed, yet notwtstandynge I haue here shewed an example whiche they 
                  •
               ught to eschewe. But &amp; yf there be many thinges spoken comynly among the people moche more detestable than these which I haue wryten / t
                  •
               an men indifferēt may se therin my cyu
                  •
               lyte, &amp; correct theyr owne vyce. &amp; suche as be not culpable may amend &amp; cause to refrayn thē which dooth other

wyse. Truly I haue spoken nothynge to the reproche of ony state, onel
                  •
               sse ye wyll say, that he sclaundrech all ye chrystianite, which speketh ony thyng (&amp; that by way of monytion) agaynst the corrupt maners of chrysten men. But it were theyr parte in especyall: whome the honour of theyr ordre so moche m
                  •
               ue
                  •
               h, to restrayne them whiche wt theyr noughty dedes dooth so moche dishonest theyr ordre. But in so moche now as they acknowlege suche theyr faythfull felawes, and moreouer gretely estemeth, &amp; defēdeth them. How can they than for shame complayne or say that the estymacyon of theyr ordre is ony thynge empeched of hym y• dooth monysshe them for theyr profyte? Here in I suppose good reder the intent of our 
                  •
               utour, in this sayd dyaloge was to shew rather a loue towarde relygyō &amp; all good relygious men, whithe thing caused me the rather to traduct this mater in to our englysshe tonge / than as some (whose iugementes I do not gretely

regarde) sayth yt he wryteth agaynst them / ferre dyfferyng from the opynyon &amp; mynde of ye good relygious father saynt Hierome, in whose mouthe this saynge was often. Where vice is but generally rebuked there no ꝑsone hath iniury or wronge. Whiche lesson after my mynde, were moche more mete fo
                  •
                euery christen man, than vnthankfully to repyne at suche as be studyous to do them good. Folowynge rather the example of ye vnkynd Grekes agaynst theyr good &amp; valyaunt capytayn Agamemnon, than (as we sholde all) the chrysten charyte. But I wyll noo lenger hyndre you from our dyaloge.
         
         
            ¶Mercolphus. Phedrus. Pulcher.
            
               
               
                  MErcolphus.
               Fro whens came hyther Phedrus, suppose ye not from Trophon
                     •
                  us dene.
            
            
               Phedrꝰ.
               Wherfore doost thou aske that questyon?
            
            
               Merc.
               For bycause yu arte moche sadder than thou arte wonte, more deformed, more fylthy, more ferse, to make fewe word
                     •
                  s, nothȳg at all after thy name.
            
            
               Phed.
               If (as we se by experyē
                  ce) they which cōtynew ony space in Foū
                  ders shoppes, draweth to them some blaknesse. What grete cause hast yu to merueyle, yf I beyng contynually so many days with two seke men, dyeng and buryed be more pensyf than I am wont. &amp; also moch the more whan they were bothe my speciall frēdes?
            
            
               Merc.
               Who doost yu tell me was buryed.
            
            
               Phed.
               Dydest yu knowe one George balearyke?
            
            
               Merc.
               Onely I haue herde of him for to my knowlege I neuer sawe his face.
            
            
               Phe.
               The other I am sure thou knowest nothynge at all / He was called Cornelius montius, with whome I had

grete famylyaryte many yeres.
            
            
               Merc.
               It was neuer my chaunce to be ps
                        •
                     nt at ony mannes dethe.
            
            
               Phed.
               I haue ben more of ten thā I wold.
            
            
               Merc.
               I pray the tell me
                     •
                   is dethe so horryble a thyng as it is comȳ
                  ly sayd?
            
            
               Phed.
               The passage toward deth is more harde &amp; paynfull thā dethe it self. but he whiche casteth out of his mynde ye ferefulnesse and ymagynacion of dethe: to hym is released a gr
                     •
                  te parte of ye payne. To speke brefely, all that is paynfull, eyther in sekenesse, or in dethe, is made more tollerable yf a man cōmyt hymself holly to the wyll of god
                     •
                   For as concernyng ye felyng of dethe, (whan the very tyme the soule is departynge from the body) after my iugement is nothing at all / or (if there be ony) that it is very dull / for bycause nature (before that come to passe) brȳgeth in a slombre, &amp; maketh amased all the sensyble partyes.
            
            
               Merc.
               We are all borne wtout felyng of our selues.
            
            
               Phed.
               But not wtout felyng of our mother.
            
            
               Merc
                     •
                  
               
               Why dye we

not in lykewyse? Wherfore hath god appoynted dethe to be so cruciable &amp; paynful a thyng?
            
            
               Phed.
               He so ordeyned yt our natyuytees sholde be paynfull and full of peryls to the mother, that she myght so moche more loue yt, whiche she had brought forthe. Contrary wyse it was his pleasure that dethe sholde be ferefull / leste euery where men shold infere theyr own dethe. For in so moche yt whan we may se dayly many which do slee thēselues, what thȳ
                  kest thou to come, yf dethe had nothynge horryble? as often as a man rebuketh his seruaunt eyther his chylde / yea, as often as the wyfe shold take dyspleasure wt her husbande, as often as ony maner of thīg dyde myscary, or ony thīg chaūced beyng sorowfull to ye mynde, by &amp; by men wolde ren̄e to hange themselues, to kyll them wt swerde, to drawe them to some conuenyent place where they myght cast thēselfes down heedlynges, eyther to poyson / now the bytternesse of dethe maketh vs yt we

loue better our lyfe / in especyal whan physyciēs can not heale a man ones deed. Albeit lyke as we all haue not lyke chaunce in our natyuyte / euen so there be diuers maners &amp; ways of deth. Some short &amp; swyft deth deliuereth hens, some other wasteth awaye wt slowe dethe. Lethargic
                     •
                   yt is to say suche as hath th
                     •
                  sekenes of forgetfulnesse. In lykewyse they whiche be stong of the venymous Aspys altogyder in a slō
                  bryng, dyeth wtout ony felyng of thēselfe. I haue obserued this thyng in especyall, that there is no kynde of dethe so paynful but it is tollerable after yt a man hath wt a fully fyxed mynde decreed for to go hens.
            
            
               Merc.
               Whither of these dethes thynkest yu to be moost lyke the dethe of a chrystyan?
            
            
               Phed.
               Me semeth the dethe of George more honorable.
            
            
               Merc.
               But I pray you hath dethe also his couetousnesse of honoure?
            
            
               Phed.
               I dyde neuer se two persones dyeng so vnlyke a dethe
                     •
                   yf ye haue so moche leysure to here, I wyl shewe you playnly

y• departyng of bothe twayne. but it shall be thy parte to iuge whiche of the dethes is moost to be wysshed to a chrysten man.
            
            
               Merc.
               yea, mary I pray the that yu wylt not thynke it greuous to tell / for I wold
                     •
                   here nothyng more gladly
                     •
                  
               
            
            
               Phed.
               Therfore here first of G
                     •
                  orge. After that deth had shewed certayne &amp; sure tokens of hymself the flocke of phisicions which of longe tyme had take cure of this pacient, nothyng beyng a knowen of th
                     •
                   dispayre of lyfe began to aske theyr stypendes.
            
            
               Merc.
               How many were they?
            
            
               Phed.
               Sōtymes ten, &amp; somtyme twelue, &amp; syx whan they were fewest.
            
            
               Merc.
               There was ynow to kyl a man in good helthe.
            
            
               Phed.
               After the tyme they had theyr money / t
                     •••
                   
                  
                     ••
                  rned they pryuely suche as were about the seke man, that dethe was at hande. And y• they sholde prepayre, and make redy all suche thynges as sholde parteyne vnto y• helthe of the soule / seyng that there was no hope at all of ony bodyly welthe. And

therupon the seke man was louyngly, by suche as were his spaecial frendes, monysshed that he sholde cōmyt ye cure of his body to god
                     •
                   and that he sholde onely mynde those thynges whiche ꝑteyned to departe wel hens. As soone as George herde these thynges: he loked, &amp; that very fers
                     •
                  y, vpō the physicions / and as it were one sore dyspleased that they shold all gyue hym vp, they sayd to hym agayne, that they were physycions &amp; no goddes / &amp; that they had done so moche as they coude by theyr scyence. albeit that there was no medycyne whiche coude remedy agaynst the ordynaunce of god. This doone, they go in to y• next chambre.
            
            
               Merc.
               What? dyde they tary styl after that they had receyued theyr wages?
            
            
               Phed.
               They were not yet agreed what kynde of sekenesse it was. One affyrmed y• it was a dropsy / another sayd it was a tympany. some sayd it was apostome in ye inner partes. some sayd it was one dysease / some another. and all the tyme

they toke in gouernaunce the pacyent they dysputed styfly what maner of sekenes it shold be.
            
            
               Merc.
               O, how happy was the pacyent in y• meane tyme?
            
            
               Phed.
               But bycause at length to ende theyr cōtencyon they desyred his wyfe to aske of suche as were his frendes to suffre an Anothomye or section to be mad
                     •
                   of the deed body. and that it shold cause moche honour to be spoken / and also y• it was so accustomed to be done for honours sake in grete noble men. And moreouer that the thing it self sholde be helthfull to many / &amp; also merytoryous to the seke man. And the rather to optayn theyr purpose they ꝓmised to bye of theyr owne charges a trentall of masses, for the profyte of the deed. This request hardly, but at the length with intreatynge of the wyfe &amp; certayn of his kynsmen was opteyned. These maters doone the garde of physiciens dyde wynde thēselues away / for they say comynly, yt it is not conuenyent that they which be wont to helpe lyfe:

sholde be y• beholders of dethe, or be pres
                     •
                  t at buryalles. Anone was called for one Bernardinꝰ a reuerend father as ye knowe well ynough, keper of one of saynt frā
                  ceys flockes, to here his cōfessyon. Before the confessyon was all togyder fynysshed a multytude of the .iiij. ordres, whome y• people call the beggyng ordres was come in to the hous.
            
            
               Merc.
               So many deuourīg Uultures to one poore pyece of caryon?
            
            
               Phed.
               Than afterwarde the parysshe preste was called for to anoyle the man, and to gyue hym the sacrament of our lordes body.
            
            
               Merc.
               Deuoutly.
            
            
               Phed.
               But there was almoost a blody fray betwyxte ye parysshe preste &amp; the other solytary fathers.
            
            
               Merc.
               At the seke mānes bed?
            
            
               Phed.
               And also Chryst hymselfe lokyng vpon them.
            
            
               Merc.
               What caused all the besynesse so sodeynly?
            
            
               Phed.
               The parisshe preste (after that he knewe the seke man was cōfessed to ye Francyscane) sayd that he wolde neyther mynystre the sacrament of anoylyng

nor of the aulter / or ony buryeng / onelesse that he herde wt his eares the seke mānes cōfession. He sayd moreouer, that he was the parysshe preste / and that he must gyue accompt to god for his lytell shepe. but yt he sayd he coude not do yf onely he were ignoraunt of the secretes of his conscyence.
            
            
               Merc.
               Semed he not to speke reasonably?
            
            
               Phed.
               Not vnto them veryly. For they all cryed agaynst hym, and in especy all Bernardinus, &amp; Uincentius the domynycan.
            
            
               Merc.
               What reasōs brought they?
            
            
               Phed.
               They set vpon the poore preste wt grete rebukes and raylynges
                     •
                   callyng hȳ often asse, and a mete keper for hogges. I sayd Uincentius, am a bacheler of dyuynyte formate / and shortly shall belycencyate / and also shall be promoted with the tytle of a doctour. Thou arte scarcely come to the redyng of the gospell. How is it than possyble that thou canst excuse, and iuge the secretes of ony mannes conscyence? But and yf thou lyste for to be besyed,

goo see what thy harlottes, and bastarde brattes doo at home. and many other obprobryous thynges whiche I am gretly ashamed to shewe.
            
            
               Merc.
               What sayd he / was he domme at those wordes?
            
            
               Phed.
               Domme? yea, thou woldest haue sayd he had ben as the prouerbe sayth. A greshop taken by the wynges. I sayd he, shall make of beane stalkes moch better bachelers than thou arte. The 
                     •
                  utours and capytaynes of youre ordres Domynyke and Fraūceys, where lerned they I pray you Aristoteles phylophy / or the argumentes of Thomas / eyther Scotus speculaciōs? or where I pray you were they made bachelers? ye creped in to ye worlde, than easy to beleue your superstycions / but than ye were but a fewe &amp; lowly
                     •
                   and some also meke &amp; wel lerned men. Than your nestes were in the feldes and poore cotages / but shortly after ye flitted thens, bothe in to ye rychest cytees and in to the fayrest partes of thē. Seyng there be so many poore vyllages

in y• countree abrode whiche can not fynde a shepeherde / there shold ye bestow your labours
                     •
                   there were conuenyent places for you to labour in / but now ye wyll be nowhere but in ye houses of ryche men. ye face &amp; crake vnder the name of popes / but your pryuyleges be not worth a strawe: but where as the bysshop, parsone, or vycare dooth not his duety. In my chyrche shall none of you preche so longe as I am the curate and haue my helthe. I am no bacheler, neyther saynt Martyn was ony bacheler, and yet he played ye very bysshop. yf I lacke lernyng I wyll not aske it of you. Suppose ye yt the worlde is yet so blynd &amp; folysshe, that (whersoeuer they se saynt Domynyke or Fraunceys co
                     •
                  e) they wyll thynke theyr sanctymony and holynes there to be? or is it to you ony mater at all what I do at home at my hous? What pageauntes ye play in your den̄es, &amp; what knauery ye vse with holy nonnes all the worlde knoweth. Also how lytell y•
                  
better or clener be the ryche mennes howses which ye haunt is opēly knowen. yea as the prouerbe sayth, bothe to blere eyed ꝑsones &amp; barbours. To tell the what was more spoken I dare not. truly he handled those reuerend fathers with small reuerē
                  ce. And none ende sholde haue ben, oneles Georgius had sygnyfied with waggyng of his hande, yt he wolde say some thyng. Moche adoo it was to apteyne that theyr chydyng myght cease so longe. than sayd the seke man. Kepe peas betwene you, I wyll confesse me agayn to the my curate / than after thou shalt be payed thy money or thou go out of this hous / bothe for bell ryngynge, dyriges, the herse, for buryall vnd stole
                     •
                   neyther by ony meanes I wyll gyue the occasion to cōplayn on me.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyde the preste refuse so equal a cōdyciō?
            
            
               Phed.
               Nothyng at all onely he murmured moche of the confessyon, which he forgaue ye seke man. What nedeth it, sayd he, in repetyng the same agayn to fatygate &amp;

trouble bothe the seke man &amp; the preste: in repetyng all one thyng? If he had confessed hym to me in season, parauenture he sholde haue made his wyll better for his soule helth, now take ye the charge. This īdyfferency of the seke sore agreued those solytary fathers, no
                     •
                  hyng contented that ony morsell of theyr pray shold be cut out for ye parysshe preste. But I went betwene them &amp; conclud
                     •
                  d so y• theyr stryfe was ended. &amp; the preste anoyled the seke man, &amp; gaue hym our lordes body. And after he was payde his money &amp; went his way.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyde Caromenes than felowe after so grete a tēpest?
            
            
               Phed.
               Nay by saynt Mary, a sharper storme folowed by &amp; by.
            
            
               Merc.
               I pray the what was the cause?
            
            
               Phed.
               Thou shalt here. There were flocked togyther in one hous foure ordres of beggyng freres / the fyfthe ordre the which
                     •
                   be called the croked (the crouched freres I wolde say) came in amonge them. Agaynst whiche as it had bene a chylde

base goten, y• other foure arose all togyder makyng no lytell ado. and they asked the fyfth ordre whan euer they dyde se a charyot of .v. wheles / or how they durst make mo ordres of beggers thā there be Euā
                  gelystes. By the same reason 
                     •
                  they sayd) bryng in hyder all beggers whiche vse to syt at brydges &amp; hye wayes.
            
            
               Merc.
               What sayd ye crouched freres to yt?
            
            
               Phed.
               They asked the other fr
                     •
                  res agayn / how y• charyot of the chyrche went, at suche tyme whan there was no ordre of beggers
                     •
                   and agayn whan there was onely one, &amp; after thre. for truly the nombre (sayd they) of ye euangelystes hath nomore affynyte with our ordres than wt a dyce, which on euery syde shewith .iiij. corners. Who brought y• Austyn freres in to the ordre of beggers? or who y• Carmelytes? or what tyme begged Augustyn or Hely? for these they make the auctour of theyr ordres. These thō
                  derboltes with many other the crossed freres dyde clatter out, &amp; doubtles very manfully.

But bycause they had none to take parte with them / therfore thynkyng thē not able to resyst the violence of .iiii. suche hostes, gaue place / onely thretnyng them very cruelly
                     •
                  
               
            
            
               Merc.
               Than I trowe there was nomore brablyng.
            
            
               Phed.
               No mary. For this parte takynge and atonement agaynst the fifth ordre was torned in to an open fray. The francy scan &amp; the domynycan contended, that neyther the augustynyans nor the carmelytes were proprely called beggers / but rather mungrelles, &amp; chaūgelynges. This stryfe dyde so moche encrease, that playnly I was afrayd leest it shold come to hand grypes and strokes.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyde the seke man abyde all these brablynges?
            
            
               Phed.
               These maters were not done at his bed syde, but in a court by whiche ioyned to the chambre. But all ye wordes came to the seke man / for they dyde not whysper the mater, but it was spoken loude ynough, &amp; wt ful shawmes, as ye prouerbe sayth. And thou knowest moost

comynly y• seke men are sharpe of heryng in especyally.
            
            
               Merc.
               But how ended ye batayle?
            
            
               Phed.
               The seke man sent vnto thē his wyfe, to exhorte them to kepe scylence a lytell whyle, &amp; sayd that he wolde ende this variaūce. And so desyred, that for that tyme the Augustynyens &amp; the Carmelytes wolde depar
                     •
                  e / and ꝓmised that they sholde lose nothyng therby. And sayd more ouer y• so moche meate sholde be sent home to theyr houses: as the rest whiche taryed styll sholde haue. But he cōmaunded y• they shold all foure ordres be at his buryeng, &amp; also the fyfth, and y• they shold euery one haue lyke porcion of money. Neuerthelesse he wolde in no wyse that they shold al syt togyder at dyner, lest ony trouble sholde insue at theyr metynge.
            
            
               Merc.
               Thou tellest me of a ryght good hous keper / whiche at the poynt of dethe coud set in quyetnes so many besy maters.
            
            
               Phed.
               He had bē many yeres a capytayn in warres. there are wont dayly to spryng vp suche

clamoures amonge the souldyours,
            
            
               Merc.
               Was he ryche?
            
            
               Phed.
               Uery ryche.
            
            
               Merc.
               But it was euyl goten, wt spoyling &amp; sacrylege. or robbynge holy places / extorcions &amp; brybes.
            
            
               Phed.
               Suche is the comyn facion of the capytaynes in warres: nor I dare not styfly swere that this man was altogyder clere &amp; differyng fro theyr maners. But as ferre as I can perceyue he gate more good wt, polycy of wyt than with vyolen
                     •
                  e.
            
            
               Merc.
               How so?
            
            
               Phed.
               He vnderstode very wel arythmetike or craft of nombryng.
            
            
               Merc.
               What therof?
            
            
               Phed.
               What than? To the hygh capytayne he wolde somtyme accompt 
                     •
                  xxx. M. souldyers, whā there were scarcely .vii.M. And more ouer he payd to many of them neuer a deale.
            
            
               Merc.
               Certaynly yu shewest me a worthy craft of accomptyng.
            
            
               Phed.
               And somtime he caused the warres by craft to contynue &amp; was wont also to receyue euery moneth money of vyllages &amp; townes: bothe of his enmyes &amp; frendes. of his en
                     •
                  myes:

to saue them harmeles, of his frendes to suffer theym to make peace with theyr ennemyes.
            
            
               Merc.
               I knowe of olde the maners of souldyers. but go forthe in your tale.
            
            
               Phed.
               Bernarde and Uyncent with certayne other of theyr cōpanyons taryed styll with the seke man / the other whiche were departed had vytayles sent theym.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyde not they agre well togyder whiche taryed styll in the house?
            
            
               Phed
                     •
                  
               
               not alway, they like hogges grūted I wote not wherfore, of y• prefermētes of theyr bulles, but leste theyr deuyse sholde not come to passe, they dissembled for that tyme. Here they brought forthe his testament, and certayne demaundes were asked before wytnesses, of suche thynges whiche they had concluded amonge thē
                  selues before.
            
            
               Merc.
               I am very desyrous to here what thynges they were.
            
            
               Phed.
               I shall tell the chyef poyntes, for ye mater is somewhat tedyous. There remayned his wyfe .xxxviii. yeres of aege / beynge

a woman certaynly very commēdable &amp; wyse. Two sones, the eldre was .xix. yeres of aege, and the other .xv. And as many doughters, bothe within aege. Thus was it deuysed by his testamēt / that his wyfe (bycause they coude not enforce her to be a Nonne) sholde take the habyte of a Bighyne, yt is an or
                     •
                  re betwene Nonnes and laykes. The elder sone, bycause they coude not entyse hym to be of ony solitary professyon.
            
            
               Merc.
               An olde foxe is taken but seldon in a snare.
            
            
               Phed.
               Hastely after his faders buri
                     •
                  ng they determyned that he sholde in al haste go to Rome / and there bye ye popes dyspensacyon before his law ful aege to be made a preste, to syng dayly in Uatycanes temple, for his faders soule. And yt he sholde crepe on his knees euery fryday all ye holy stayres in Laterane.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyde he take all this wyllyngly?
            
            
               Phed.
               Euen to be playne, as asses be wōt to take vpon them theyr caryages. More
                  
                     ••
                  r yt the yongest sone shold be professed to

saynt Fraūceys, y• elder doughter to saynt Clare, the yongest to saynt Katheryn. For they coude bryng nomore of theyr purpose 
                     •
                  o passe. for George was mīded, bycause he wold haue god more bound to hym, to haue his wyfe &amp; .iiii. chyldren to be parted amonge the .v. ordres of beggers / and there was grete procurement therto / but the wife and the eldest sone were to olde to agre thereto, eyther for fayre wordes or foule.
            
            
               Merc.
               A propre facyon of dysinherytyng.
            
            
               Phed.
               The inherytaunce altogyder was in suche wyse deuyded, that after y• charges of the buryeng was taken out of all the hole, one parte sholde inure to ye wyfe vpon this cōdycion / that she sholde lyue wt the one halfe therof / the other half shold be put in the place where she shold oblyge herself. Frōwhens, yf she at any tyme hereafter departed, all the same money sholde remayne to yt flocke: Another lyke porcion shold be gyuen to ye eldest sone, to whome by &amp; by after sholde be inioyned a iourney

toward Rome / and as moche as was suffycient to bye his bulles, &amp; to paye his costes of meate and drynke at Rome. And yf he refused to be made preste, his porciō shold than be deuyded betwene the freres of saynt Fraunceys, and of saynt Domynyke / and yet I feare me that he wyll not ꝑforme theyr iniūct
                     •
                  on / the yong man appered to abhorre so moche frō holy ordres. Two porcyons sholde be put in to the monastery which was content to take ye yongest sone. Other two partes also to the .ii. monasteryes where the doughters were but vnder this condycion / yt yf they at ony tyme hereafter refused to ꝓfesse ye lyfe, yet all the money sholde be in theyr custody, sauf, &amp; in no wyse dymynysshed. Agayn on the other syde, the good father Bernardyne must haue one of the porciōs, &amp; Uyncent another / &amp; half of one of the porcyons to ye Charter monkes, for cōmunyon and parte takyng of all good workes, whiche sholde be done in all the ordre, All the rest

sholde be distrybute to poore people yt were pryuely kept / vpon whome Bernardyne and Uyncent thought it best bestowed.
            
            
               Merc.
               yu sholdest haue sayd as ye lawyers do, Quos ve
                     •
                   quas.
            
            
               Phed.
               After the wyll was redde / they asked hī vnder these wordes. George balearike, doost yu beyng on lyue &amp; hole memory approue this testamēt, which yu lately hast made of thyn own mȳ
                  de? He answered / I do apꝓue it. &amp; is this thy last &amp; īmutable wyl? it is. And yu doost īstytute &amp; ordeyn me &amp; fader bacheler Uȳ
                  cent here: executors of thy last wyll? I do ordeyne. Than they cōmaunded hym yet ones to subscrybe it with his owne hand.
            
            
               Merc.
               How coud he, than beyng at poynt of dethe?
            
            
               Phed.
               Bernardinꝰ dyd gouerne y• seke man̄es hande.
            
            
               Merc.
               What dyde he subscrybe?
            
            
               Phed.
               These wordes. ye hygh displeasure of saynt Fraūceys &amp; saynt Domynyke may come to hȳ whiche gooth about to chaūge ony thīg her in.
            
            
               Merc.
               But feared they not ye action called in the lawe

Actio officiosi testamenti.
            
            
               Phed.
               No, no: this action lyeth not in those thinges yt be dedycate to god / neyther I thynke y• ony man is so folysshe to make ony trouble wt god. All these maters fynysshed, the wyfe &amp; the chyldren gaue theyr ryght hādes to the seke man. sweryng that they shold obserue that thyng whiche they had receyued. ¶After these thynges they began to comyn (not without stryfe) of the funeral pompe. At last this sentēce had ye vyctory, that .ix. of of euery one of ye .v. ordres shold be present in the honour of the .v. bokes of Moyses / and of the .ix. ordres of aūgelles. And ye euery ordre sholde haue theyr crosse borne before them / and they sholde synge theyr mournyng songes. Moreouer .xxx. (besyde suche as were kyn̄e to hym) shold be hyred, (for so many pyeces of money was our lorde solde) all in blacke to bere ye torches. &amp; for his honours sake .xii. mourners. (this nombre is in ye honour of ye .xii apostles,) sholde go about the corps. Next

after sholde folowe Georges own hors all in blacke, with his necke so bound doune to his knees as though he wold be sene to seke his mayster on the erthe. ¶It was forthermore procured that the couerynge which shold be cast ouer him, shold shewe on euery party his armes. Lykewise euery torche &amp; blacke garment sholde ye same. The corps they purposed sholde be layde at the ryght hande of the hygh aulter in a tombe of marble, whiche sholde be made iiij. fote hygh fro the the ground. He sholde lye in the top of it grauen in a whyte marble stone / all armed fro top to toe. neyther myght ye helmet lacke his creste. the creste was the necke of an Anocrotale. A target in the left arme / in the which was his armes blased in this wyse, Thre wylde bores heedes all of golde in a syluer felde. A swerde by his syde with a gylted pomell. The gyrdle was gylted, &amp; deuyded with studdes of precyous stones. Golden spurres to his fete, bycause he was a gentyll

mā of cote armour, vnder his fete shold be set a leoperd, the brynk
                     •
                  s of his sepulker sholde haue an epitaphye mete for a worthy man. He was wyllyng y• his hert sholde be buried seuerally in a chapell of saynt franceys. He cōmitted ye other inward partys of his body to the parysshe prest, to be buryed honorably in a chapel of our lady.
            
            
               Merc.
               An honourable buryenge, but very chargeable. At venyce a pore cobler sholde haue more honour for a lytel coste. for company maketh ornate &amp; elygant the bere, &amp; there somtyme syx hondreth monkes: some in sleueles s
                     •
                  oppes, &amp; other some wt copes wyll folowe one corps.
            
            
               Phed.
               I haue sene that myself, &amp; haue somtime laughed at suche folysshe vaynglories of poore mē. there goeth fullers &amp; curriers before: &amp; coblers behynd, &amp; mōkes in ye myddest. thou woldest say they were mōsters / neyther here was ony other thynge yf yu had sene it. It was also ꝓuided by George, ye Barnardyne &amp; Uyncent shold decerne by lottes

whiche of them sholde haue the hyghest place in the grete pompe. And afterwarde other sholde doo soo lykewyse, lest ony rumour or besynesse sholde be for the same. The parysshe preste &amp; his clerkes were apoynted to the moost inferyour place, that was to go the formest / neyther ye solytary fathers wolde suffre it otherwyse.
            
            
               Merc.
               He coude not onely or
                     ••
                  yn an army to batayle / but also other solempne tryūphes and pōpes.
            
            
               Phed.
               It was also prouyded that the masse of Requiem whiche sholde be done by the parysshe preste sholde be in prycke songe, for y• more honour. ¶Whyle these thynges and certayne other were indeuysyng, the seke man shaked very sore, and dyde gyue certayne parfyte tokēs that his laste tyme was nygh at hande. The last acte of the comedy was therfore prepared.
            
            
               Merc.
               Is it not yet at an ende?
            
            
               Phed.
               The popes bull was there rehersed / in the whiche was graunted remyssyon of all his synnes quyte and clene / 

and all the feare of purgatory was taken away. Beside al these al his goodes was iustyfied.
            
            
               Merc.
               Suche as was goten by extorcyon and robbery?
            
            
               Phed.
               Certaynly euen suche as were goten by ye lawe of batayle or sowlderye. But it fortuned to be presēt one Phylyp a man of lawe ye wyfs brother, whiche marked a place in ye bull otherwise set than it ought to be / &amp; caused suspecyon that it was but forged.
            
            
               Merc.
               Nay, that was not done in tyme. he sholde haue rather dyssēbled it, though there had ben errour therin / and the seke man sholde haue done neuer the worse.
            
            
               Phed.
               I thinke the same. For the seke man was so troubled with this mater, that he was not ferre of from disperacion. And there father bacheler Uyncēt played the man. He cōmaunded George to be of a quyet mynde, he sayd that he had auctoryte bothe to correct ony thyng whiche was fals in the bulles, eyther to restore ony thynge y• lacketh. But yf the bull deceyue the, euen very

now I put my soule for thyne / y• thyne may come to heuen, and myne I gyue for euer to the derkest pyt of hell.
            
            
               Merc.
               But wyll god accept suche chaungyng of soules? and yf he wolde, was this prouysion for George with suche a guage suffycyēt? What &amp; yf the soule of Uyncent was (wt
                  out ony chaūgīg at all) due to hell.
            
            
               Phed.
               I shewed you as ye mater was / but Uyncent fynyshed tha
                     •
                   ma
                     •
                  er. The pacyent semed to take a good stomacke to hym / by &amp; by was red ye pardons, wherin was promysed to George to be parte taker of all ye workes whiche sholde be done by the .iiii
                     •
                   ordres &amp; of the Charter monkes.
            
            
               Mer.
               I wolde be afrayde leste I sholde be thurst downe to the botom of hell, yf I sholde bere suche an vnprofitable burden.
            
            
               Phed.
               I speke of theyr good werkes: which dooth no otherwyse aggraua
                     •
                  e the soule redy to departe, than fethers dooth the byrde.
            
            
               Merc.
               To whome bequeth they theyr yll workes?
            
            
               Phed.
               To the landeskneyghtes

of Germany.
            
            
               Merc.
               By what auctoryte?
            
            
               Phed.
               Of the gospell, sayeng to hym that hath: it shall be gyuen / and withall was rehersed the nōbre of masses and nocturnes, whiche shulde accompanye the dead mannes soule / truely it was an vnreasonable nombre. After all these thynges, he was confessed, &amp; had absolucyon.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyed he thus?
            
            
               Phed.
               Not yet. A matte of russhes was spred vpon the grounde, in suche wyse that the vpper parte was lapped togyther, for to make as it were a similitude of a bolster.
            
            
               Merc.
               What mēt they by that?
            
            
               Phed.
               They sparpled it all ouer with asshes, but very thynnely, and there they layde the sycke mannes body. A gray freres cote was spred aboue him, but beyng halowed before with a certeyn prayers &amp; holy water. A cowle was put vnder his hed, for at that tyme it coulde not be put vpon hym, and with all was layde the bull and the pardons.
            
            
               Merc.
               A new maner of dethe.
            
            
               Phed.
               But they affyrme

sty
                     •
                  fely y• he deuyll hath no power ouer them whiche dyeth in suche fasshyon. So they sayde that bothe saynt Martyne and saynte Frauncys dyed.
            
            
               Merc.
               But then theyr lyues were no lesse vertuous. I praye the tell me what folowed?
            
            
               Phed.
               They reachyd the ymage of the crosse, &amp; a waxe candell to the sycke man. At the syght of the crosse he sayd, I was wonte in batayles to be defendyd with myne owne bucklar, but now I wyll put this bucklar agaynste myne enemye, and kyssed it, and put it towarde the left shulder. To the holy candell he sayd: in tyme past I haue ben valyaūt in warres with speare, nowe I wyll shake this speare agaynste the enemy of soules.
            
            
               Merc.
               Euyn lyke a man of warre.
            
            
               Phed.
               These wordes he spake laste / for by and by his tonge was taken with dethe, and with all the pangys of dethe came vppon hym. Barnardyne stode harde by hym on the ryght hande, and Uincent on the left syde, bothe

two lowde ynough / the one shewed y• pycture of saynt Frāceys, the other of saynt Domynyke / the other good holy fathers sparpled abrode about the chambre, mombled vp besyly certayn psalmes. Bernardyne with greate out cryes precelled his ryght eare, and Uyncent the lefte.
            
            
               Merc.
               What cried they?
            
            
               Phed.
               Bernardyne sayd in this wyse. George balearyke
                     •
                   yf thou now approue those thynges, whiche we haue done betwyxt vs: bowe downe thy heed towarde thy ryght syde. He dyde so. Uyncent on the other syde sayd, be nothīg adredde George / thou hast saynt Frāceys and saynt Domynyke thy defenders, care nothing at all. Remembre what a grete sorte of merytes, what a strong Bull. brefely, remembre that my soule is pledged for thyne, If there were ony ieopardy, yf thou vnderstand what I say, and also a lowest ye same, bowe doun thy heed toward the left syde. He dyde so. And agayn with a lyke outcry, they sayd bothe. yf yu thynkest

surely all these thynges thyrste downe my hande / and with the same he thirst doune his hande. And so in bowynge his heed here and there / and puttynge doune hādes, was almoost .iii. houres past. And shortly after whan George began to gaspe, there Bernardyne standyng vp ꝓnoū
                  ced the absolucyon / whiche he coude not parfitely fynysshe, before George was departed. this was a lytel after mydnyght. in the mornyng the Anothomy was made.
            
            
               Merc.
               What noysome thyng was foū
                  de within him?
            
            
               Phed.
               Thou remembrest me in good tyme / for it was gone out of my remembraunce. A pyece of lead cleued in the skyn̄e, which closeth the herte and the lyghtes about, &amp; dooth seperate them from the mylte and the lyuer, called Diaphragma.
            
            
               Merc.
               How came it there?
            
            
               Ph.
               His wyfe shewed that he was ones stryken with a gon̄e stone / and therof the physyciens coniectured that a pyece of ye lead moltyd, taryed styll within his body. By

and by, the corps all to cut and dilanyate aswell as it wolde be, was put in a gray freres cote. After dyner, the buryeng was done with suche and lyke solempnytye, as it was decreed before.
            
            
               Merc.
               I neuer herde of a more curious dethe, nor a corps more ambycyous. But I suppose thou woldest not haue this spoken abroode.
            
            
               Phed.
               Wherefore?
            
            
               Merc.
               Leste the hurnettes wolde be an angred.
            
            
               Phed.
               There is no ieoperdy at all. For yf these thynges be godly whiche I shewe, it is theyr profet that the people do know them / yf they be otherwyse, so many as be good among them, wyll gyue me thankes whiche haue shewed forthe suche, wherby some correcte wt shame, may refrayne lyke dedes. Also such as be sȳple, may take hede lest they be drawen in to like errour / for there be amonge this sorte great wyse men, &amp; very godly, whiche hathe often complayned to me, that by the supersticion improbyte or lewdnes of a fewe, the hole order

is brought to hatred of good men.
            
            
               Merc.
               Thou sayest very ryght, and boldely / but I am very desyrous to knowe, how Cornelius dyed.
            
            
               Phed.
               Like as he lyued greuous to no man, so dyed he. He was euery yere greued with the febre, cōmyng to hym at certeyne tymes. The same (bothe for bycause he was somewhat in age: for he was past thre score yeres) are for other causes more than was wont infebled the man, and it apered that he felt before that his fatall day was at hande. For the fourthe daye before he dyed, was Sondaye, our lordes daye, he wente to the temple, was confessyd to his curate, he herde the cōmune preachynge and masse / and after the masse was done, he was howseled, and so wente home.
            
            
               Merc.
               Used he no Physycyons?
            
            
               Phed.
               Onely one he counselled, but he was no lesse a good mā, then a good Phisycyon, his name is Iacobus Castrutius.
            
            
               Merc.
               I knowe hym very well
                     •
                   There is no more pure man.
            
            
               Ph
                     •
                  d.
               
                  He answered yt his frende sholde not lacke his dylygence / but he thought there was more socoure in god than in physyciens. Cornelius dyde as gladly accepte his sayenge, as though he had shewed moost certayne hope of lyfe. Therfore albeit that after his power, he was always very lyberall towarde the po
                     •
                  re, euen than all that myght be spared frō necessary ayde of his wyfe and chyldren, was dystributed to ye poore and nedy men / and not to the ambycyous beggers, whiche we comynly mete in euery place / but to suche as were to be cōmended, whiche fought agaynst pouerte, with al theyr deuyse and power. I desyred hym to lye hym doune / &amp; rather to call the preste to hym, than to fatygate with laboure his feble body. He gaue answere, that his specyall study was euer to helpe his frendes, yf he myght, rather than to put thē to paynes / neyther he wolde be vnlyke to hymself at the tyme of his dyenge / neyther truely he laye doune ony

more, but y• last day, and parte of y• night, wherin he departed out of this lyfe. Sō
                  tyme for werinesse of his body he walked with a staffe / somtyme reposed in a chayre. He went seldome to bed, but in his clothes, &amp; his heed reysed vpwarde. All this tyme he eyther gaue one thing or other to relyue the poore / but 
                     •
                  n especyall to them which were knowen poore, and dwelled nygh to hym, or e
                     •
                  les 
                     •
                  e redde suche thynges in holy scrypture, whiche prouoketh a mannes conscyence towarde god, &amp; also declareth his charyte towardes vs. And whan he by reason of his werynesse coud not rede hymself, than he herde some frende redyng before hym. Often tymes he exhorted with a vehemēt desyre, his famyly to loue one another, &amp; to loue ye trouthe. He also louyngly conforted them whiche were pensyfe and sorowfull for his dethe. He gaue oftē monycion to suche as he put in trust, that nothyng of his dettes shold be vnpayde.
            
            
               Merc.
               Made he his wyll?
            
            
               
               Phed.
               Yes, longe before, in tyme of his helthe / for he denayed vtterly that they were called testamentes, whiche were made of suche as lye on dyeng: but rather folisshe dotinges.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyd he bequethe nothynge to monasteryes, or to nedy men therin.
            
            
               Phed.
               Nothȳg at all. I (sayd he) haue for my parte distrybute those lytell goodes whiche god hathe sent me. Therfore now as I gyue the possession of them to other: so I gyue also the dispensacyon and orderyng. And I trust that they wyll dyspose thē more vtuously, then I haue done my selfe.
            
            
               Merc.
               Dyd he not call to him suche holy mē as George dyd.
            
            
               Phed.
               Neuer one. Neither was there any body at all with hym, sauyng his owne familie, and two speciall frendes of his.
            
            
               Merc.
               I merueyll what he ment.
            
            
               Phed.
               He said vtterly that he wold be onerous to no mo at his dethe, than he was at his natiuitie.
            
            
               Merc.
               I desyre instantly to here the ende of this mater.
            
            
               Phed.
               Thou shalt here

it by and by. Thursday cam, he laye styll vpon his bed, felynge extreme werynes of his body / the curate was sent for, and anoyled hym, &amp; by and by gaue hym the body of our lorde, without any confession at all. For he sayde there was no scrupe &amp; doubte at all in his mynde, The preste began to aske of hym, with what pompe, and in what place
                     •
                   he wolde be buried. He sayd agayn, bury me in suche wyse as ye wold bury a christen man of the lowest degree. Nor I care not in what place ye lay my wretchyd body, whiche shal be foūde in the last day aswell out of one place as other, where so euer it be hyd / nor I regarde any thyng at all the pompe of burieng. Shortly after, whā mēcion was made of ye ringyng of belles, trētals, &amp; yeres myndes, of bulles, of bying part takȳg of merites. Thā answered he thus, my curate, I shal do neuer ye worse, if no bell at all knoll for me. If it wyll please you to synge one bare masse for me it shalbe more thā nede.

Eyther yf there be ony thynge elles, whiche (bycause of the comyn custome of the chyrche) may without offence of suche as be infyrme persones scarcely be left out, yt I ꝑmytte to be at your aduyse. Neyther I am minded to bye ony man̄es prayers, eyther to bereue ony man his merytes. Haboundaunce of merytes floweth ouer in Chryst / and also I trust that ye prayers and merytes of all thry
                     •
                  ten men, (yf I be a lyuynge membre) dooth prousfyte me / Al my hope is in .ii. bulles &amp; pryuyleges / the one is of my offences, that ye chyef pastour Iesus chryst hath clene taken them away, naylȳg it to the crosse. the other is that which he wrote and sealed with his precyous blode / wherby he put vs in certaynte of euerlasting lyfe, yf so be that we put all our hole trust in hym. God forfend that I armed with merytes, and bulles, sholde prouoke my lorde god, to come in to iugement with his bondman / beyng certayne of this
                     •
                   that all which be lyuynge,

shall not be iustyfied in his syght. I do appele therfore from his iustyce, to his mercy / for so moche as it is without measure, &amp; ineffable. ¶After he had spoken these wordes, the preste departed. Corneliꝰ beyng mery and glad (as though he had conceyued a grete hope of helthe) cōmaunded that suche places of holy scrypture sholde be rehersed to hym, as were wryten to cō
                  ferme the hope of 
                     •
                  esurrection, and the rewarde of īmortalyte. As for example the texte of Esaye declaryng the dethe of Ezechias which was deferred, &amp; the cātycle. Moreouer the .xv. chapytre of ye fyrst epystle of Paule to the Corynthiens. Also out of saynt Iohn̄ the euangelyst of the dethe of Lazarꝰ / but namely ye history of Chrystes passyon, after the euangelystes. With what a mynde deuoured he euery thyng
                     •
                   sighyng at some thynges / &amp; whan he herde some other he (lyftyng vp his handes) gaue thankes. At the heryng of dyuers other thynges, he wexed very mery, and

shewed hym outwardly glad / &amp; at many sayenges, he caste out many shorte prayers. After dyner, whan he had taken a lytell slepe, he cōmaunded that one shulder
                     •
                   herse to hym the .xij. chapytre of saynte Iohn̄s Gospell, vnto the ende of the history. At whiche tyme yu woldest haue sayde the man had ben cler
                     •
                  ly transfigured and afflate wt a new spirite, Now it drewe towardes night, he 
                     •
                  alled to hym his wyfe &amp; chyldren. There (his feble body beynge reryd vp asmoche as he coulde suffer) he spake to them in this wyse: Moste dere wyfe, goddes pleasure is nowe to departe them whome he hathe vnyte before / but this separacyon shal be but bodyly, and y• for a very shorte tyme. All thy dylygence, loue, and pytye, whiche thou were wont in tyme past to bere toward me and those moste dere chylderen, turne all towardes them. Neyther thynke that thou cannest any wise do higher pleasure to god or me, than yf thou nourysshe, brynge vp, and

instytute theym whiche god hathe gyuen vs twayne, as fruyte of our maryage: that they may become Chrystes seruauntes. As towardes them therfore double thy loue, and thynke that the porcyon of my loue is translate all into the / whiche yf thou doest (as I doubte not but thou wylte) they shall in no wyse be sayde Orphanes. But and yf thou doest iterate matrymonye. At that worde the wyfe brast out in wepynge, and began for to swere deuoutely, that 
                     •
                  he wolde neuer thynke of maryenge agayne. ¶Here Cornelius sayde. My mooste dere beloued syster in Chryste, yf our lorde Iesus Chryst wyll vouchsafe for to graunte the this purpose, and spyrytuall strengthe, slake not of thy parte from suche an heuenly calling / For that shall be bothe more conuenyent for thyn own self, and also these chyldren. But yf soo be that the infyrmytye, and weykenesse of the flesshe calle the to marye agayne / knowe thou that my dethe

setteth the at lyberte from the lawe of our matrymony / but yu arte not at large therby from the faythfull promyse, whiche yu hast made in bothe our names: to cure and bryng vp our comyn children. But as touchyng maryage, vse that lyberte whiche god hath ꝑmytted the. Onely I pray and put you in remembraūce bothe, that thou do chuse a husbande with suche maners, and thou also vse 
                     •
                  he t
                     •
                  warde hym in suche wyse that he may be led by his mere goodnesse, or prouoked through thy cōmodite or towardnes to loue his stepe son̄es. Take hede yu doost not bynde thy selfe to ony vowe. Kepe thyselfe at lyberte to god and our chyldren, whome yu must so brȳg vp in al mekenesse, yt thou be no lesse cyrcū
                  spect / and ware lest they do addyct themselues to ony volūtary purposed lyuyng / vnto the tyme it may appere by theyr aege and dyscrecyon, to what maner of lyuyng they be moost apte. ¶Than after he torned toward his chyldren, and exhor
                  
                     •
                  ed

them to the studye of vertue, &amp; obeye theyr moder, &amp; one to loue antoher. These thynges ended, he kyssed his wyfe, and to his chyldren he gaue his blessyng, makynge ouer them the sygne of the crosse, prayenge god to sende them good mynde, and Christes mercye. After this, he loked vpon all that stode by
                     •
                   &amp; sayde: God that rose agayne in the mornyng, wyll vouchsafe to morow before the sōne ryse, to euocate and call out this symple soule from the sepulchre of this bodye, from the darkenes of this mortalitie, into his heuenly light. I wyll not that these yong chyldren shall be fatygate and wery
                     •
                  d with vayne watchynges. Let all oth
                     •
                  r goo to bedde also / one is suffycyente to watche with me, whome I wolde haue for to 
                     •
                  eherse some holy scrypture. ¶Whan the nyght was past, a lytell after foure of the clocke, in the presence of all that were in the house, he cōmaunded one to rede out a 
                     •
                  owde the hole psalme whiche our lorde

prayenge, sayde at the tyme he suffered his pasiyon. That done, he commaunded one to brynge hym an halowed candell, &amp; the sygne of the crucifyxe. He toke the candell in his hande, sayeng, the lorde is my lyghtenynge, and my helthe / whom shall I feare? He also kyssyng the crosse, sayd: The lorde is protectour, and defender of my lyfe, whom shall I therfore be adred of
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  y and by, he helde his handes togyther vpon his breste, as a man in feruent prayer, lyftyng vp his iyes towarde heuen, sayd: Lorde Iesu, take my spyryte. And shortely after, he shytte his iyes, as thoughe he wolde goo to slepe / and therewith, with a softe blast, he yelded vp the goste. Thou woldest rather haue sayd he had ben on slepe, than deade.
            
            
               Merc.
               I neuer herde of dethe more quyet.
            
            
               Phed.
               He was of lyke fasshyon in all his lyfe tyme / bothe twayne were my frendys. Perchaunce I iudge not indyfferently, whe
                  
                     •
                  her of them departed this lyfe more lyke

a christian. Thou Mercolphus, whiche arte not parcyall, shalte more rectetely, dyscerne.
            
            
               Merc.
               So I wyll do, but at a conuenient season.
            
            ¶Finis.
            ¶Thus endeth y• dyaloge called Funus, made by doctour Erasmus.
         
         
            ¶Erasmus.
            
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶A good and a godly admonicion or warnynge, very behouefull for euery chrysten man to loke vpon.
            
               GOd hath apparayled the glory of heuē to them that loue hym, &amp; kepe his cōmaundementes / and to them that (of that they haue &amp; done) prayse not them selfe, ne be not proude therof, &amp; after theyr habilitie departen gladly to the pore &amp; nedy: and set not theyr hertes princypally, but in our lorde: And to them yt the euils
                  •
                the paines, and the tribulacions that com
                  •
                to theym, suffren paciently for the loue of god. And for to haue this great glory, ou
                  •
                lorde admonesteth vs that we be alway
                  •
                redy, and kepe vs fro synne. And that w
                  •
                put not our hertes principally in this ca
                  ••
               tyfe worlde, whiche is nothyng but a ly
                  •
               tell passyng, full of wepyng, of sorowes and of anguisshes, whiche we shall leue
                  •
               
               
And take none hede of the houre without to bere any thyng with vs, saue the good dedes &amp; the euyll that we haue done. And our body caityfe, shal be couered with the erthe, as a foule stynkynge carion, &amp; wormes shall eat and wrote therin. Our lord promyseth not to vs to morow, to thende that our hertes and our principall intention be in hym, and in his loue. For we ought to loue god, and 
                  •
               o remembre ofte &amp; deuoutly how the swete Iesus vouchedsafe to humble hym selfe for vs, and descende fro his glory of heuen, into ye wōbe of the glorious virgyn Mary, and becom a man and our brother, and suffred d
                  •
               the and passion for vs / and howe he made vs of nought, and semblable to him / whiche myght haue made vs (yf it had pleased hym) lyke vnto toodes &amp; other wormes. If we knowe well all the graces that he hath doon to vs, and thanke &amp; gyue hym 
                  •
               aude therfore that is the thyng aboue all 
                  •
               ther, by which we may moost soone and

moost lightely haue his loue &amp; his grace: moche pleasaunt is it vnto god, whan one knowlegeth the graces and the benefites that he hath done for vs, and whan he is remercyed and thanked therfore.
            ¶Example. It is red that the great Chauntre of Paris, founde on a tyme in a felde, a conuerse, 
                  •
                that is to say, a brother, &amp; no preest, of the order of Cisteaulx) kepynge shepe, whiche was contemplatife and deuout towarde god, and wepte ofte in beholdynge a crapaulde or toode. The chauntre demaūded hym wherfore he wepte. He answered to hym, sayenge: I ought well to wepe for my synnes, and gyue thankynges to god, whiche hathe made me to his semblaunce. For yf it had pleased hym, he had well made me lyke vnto this crapaulde or toode. Thus this good man thanked and remercyed god. Than let vs rendre &amp; gyue graces &amp; than
                  •
               kynges to our lorde of all his benefites, &amp; let vs enioy
                  •
                in hym, and syng we in our

hertes with great ioye / for we be y• sones and the doughters of god, made and formed to his semblaunce, bretheren &amp; siste
               
                  •
               en of Iesu Christe, and bought and rede
               
                  •
               ed with his preciouse blood, fed with his preciouse bodye, fellowes to aungels 
                  •
               f heuen, Coheriters (but yf it be longe of 
                  •
               ur selfes) for euer more, without ende, 
                  •
               f the gloryouse royalme / to the whiche 
                  •
               rynge vs the sw
                  •
               te and debonayre Ie
               
                  •
               u Chryste. Amen.
         
      
      
         
            ¶At London, by Robert copland, for Iohan Byddell / otherwyse Salysbury. the .v. daye of Ianuary, And be for to sell at ye sygne of our lady of pyte nexte to Flete brydge. 1.5.3.4.
            ¶Cum priuilegio regali.
         
         
            
            
               
                  Robert Coplande.
               
            
         
         
            
            An epistell of the famous doctor Erasmꝰ of Roterdame / vnto the reuerende father &amp; excellent prince / Christofer bysshop of Basyle / cōcernyng the forbedynge of eatynge of flesshe / and lyke constitutyons of men. &amp;c.
         
      
   

