
   
      
         
            De ciuilitate morun [sic] puerilium per Des. Erasmum Roterodamum, libellus nunc primum &amp; conditus &amp; æditus. Roberto VVhitintoni interprete. = A lytell booke of good maners for chyldren, nowe lately compyled and put forth by Erasmus Roterodam in latyne tonge, with interpretacion of the same in to the vulgare englysshe tonge, by Robert whytyngton laureate poete. Cum priuilegio
            De civilitate morum puerilium. English and Latin
            Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
         
         
            
               1532
            
         
         Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00344
            STC 10467
            ESTC S105527
            99841255
            99841255
            5824
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00344)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5824)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 37:2)
         
         
            
               
                  De ciuilitate morun [sic] puerilium per Des. Erasmum Roterodamum, libellus nunc primum &amp; conditus &amp; æditus. Roberto VVhitintoni interprete. = A lytell booke of good maners for chyldren, nowe lately compyled and put forth by Erasmus Roterodam in latyne tonge, with interpretacion of the same in to the vulgare englysshe tonge, by Robert whytyngton laureate poete. Cum priuilegio
                  De civilitate morum puerilium. English and Latin
                  Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.
                  Whittington, Robert, d. ca. 1560.
               
               [56] p.   
               
                  In the Flete strete, at the sygne of the Sonne, by wynkyn de worde,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  The yere of our lorde god. M.CCCCC.xxxii. [1532] the. x. daye of Septe[m]bre]
               
               
                  Translation of: De civilitate morum puerilium.
                  Latin and English in parallel columns.
                  Imprint from colophon.
                  Signatures: A-C D⁴.
                  The last leaf bears a printer's mark.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Etiquette, Medieval --  Early works to 1800.
               Etiquette for children and teenagers --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-04
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-05
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            DE CIVILITATE MORVN PVERIlium per DES. ERASMVM Roterodamum, Libellus nunc primum &amp; conditus &amp; aeditus.
            Roberto VVhitintoni interprete.
            ¶A lytell booke of good maners for chyldren / nowe lately compyled and put forth by Erasmus Roterodam in latyne tonge / with interpretacion of the same in to the vulgare englysshe tonge / by Robert whytyngton laureate poete.
            Cum priuilegio.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ Erasmus Roterodam saluteth a chylde of noble bloode and of singuler hope / named Adolph. sonne vnto the prince of Uerian.
            
               IF that Paule very excellente was nat abasshed to be made after all fasshyons / to euery ꝑson / to the ende he myght profyt all fasshyons of men: howe moche lesse ought I to be greued to play the childe agayne in lyke case / for lou
                  •
                to helpe youthe. Therfore lyke as late I applyed my se
                  •
               fe to the youthe of Maximi
                  •
               yan thy brother (whyles I fasshyoned the tongue of yonge chyldren) so nowe I applye my selfe to thy childhode / and shall teache the maners of chyldrē: Nat bycause thou nedest these prescriptes and rules / brought vp at the begynnynge of an enfant amonge courtye
                  ••
                / after that obtaynyng so notable a mayster to fasshyon youthe rude and ignorante / 

or 
                  〈…〉
                write perteyneth to the / an
                  •
                that ar
                  •
               e come of princes / and borne to principalyte / but for that ende that all chyldren shall more couragyous
                  •
               y lerne this thynges / bicause it is dedycate 
                  •
               o the a childe of great possessyon / and of synguler hope. Nor it shall nat gyue to al youth a dull spurre / if they 
                  •
               e noble mens sonnes to be f
                  •
               l
                  •
               y gyuen to lernyng fro chyldhode / and renne in the same rase with them.
            The office of fasshyonyng of chyldhode resteth in many par
                  •
               e
                  •
                / of the which that whiche lyke as it is firste / so it is chefe: That is / the tendre wytee shall drinke the seedes of loue to god and his parentes. Secondely that he shall loue and lerne the lyberall scyence. Thyrde / that he shalbe instructe to the order of his lyuyng. Fourth that fro the first 
                  •
               udymen
                  •
                of youth he shall be accustomed to cyuilite and norture. This laste nowe I haue take vpon me as a thing proper / for o
                  •
                th
                  •
                other thre both many oth
                  ••
               
               
               
                  〈…〉
                wri
                  ••
               en m
                  ••
               ny thynges. And al be it this outwarde honesty of the body cometh of the soule well cōposed or ordred / natwithstandyng we se it chaunseth ofte tymes by neglygenc
                  •
                of maysters that we desyre (as a thynge that lacketh) this grace of honest behauour in men of nobylite &amp; lernynge: Nor I denye nat this to be a very notable parte of philosophy / but yet that parte (after the iudgemēt of men in this dayes) auayleth gretly to al
                  •
               re beneuolens / also to represent to the eyes of men these laudable gyftes of the soule.
            It is semely and syt
                  •
               ynge that a man be well fasshyoned in soule / in body / in gesture / &amp; in apparell: and in especyall it besemeth chyldren all maner of temperaunce / and in especyall in this behalfe noble mennes sonnes. All are to be taken for noble / whiche exercyse their mynde in the lyberall science. Lette other men paynte in their shyldes Lyons / Egles / Bulles / and Leopardes: yet they haue more of verye nobylyte / 

whiche for their badge may paynte so many ymages / as they haue lerned sure the lyberall scyēce. Than that the mynde of a chylde well burnysshed may vpon all sydes euydent apere / for it apereth moste clere in the vysage or countenaunce.
            
               ¶Of the eyes.
               Let the eyes be stable / honest / well set / nat frownyng / which is syne of crueltie / nat wāton / which is tokē of malapertnesse / nat wandring &amp; rollynge / whiche is syne of madnesse / nat twyringe and spyeng / whiche is token of suspection and compasynge disceyte / nor hāgyng downe whiche is syne of folly: nor afterwarde twynklyng with the browes / whiche in sygne of vnstablenesse / nor masing as a mā astonyed (And that was noted in Socrates) nor to sharpe / a syne of malyce / nat makyng synes and profers nor besy wanton / a token of yuell chasty
                     •
                  e: but representyng a mynde well enstabled / &amp; amy
                     •
                  ble with honesty. Nor it is nat said with out cause of antique sage mē / that the eye is the seate and place of the soule.
               
                  The antique pyctures she
                     •
                  weth to vs that in olde tyme men were of synguler demure countenaunce / and loked with eyes halfe closed / lyke as in Spayne certayne loke as they were pore blynde / as it semeth to be 
                     •
                  ake as a fayre &amp; amyable countenaūce. Lykewyse we lerne of pictures / ī olde tyme they were narowe and strayte mouthed / a signe of vertue: But that thyng that of his awne nature is semely / it is taken with all men comly. All be it becometh vs somtyme to be lyke the lopster / and to applye our selfe to the maner of the regyon we be in.
               Nowe there be certayne countenaunces of the eyes / whom na
                     •
                  ure gyueth of this fasshyon to one and that to an other / whiche chaunseth nat be vnder my preceptes: saue that gestures out of order do blemysshe nat onely the behauoure and sauoure of the eyes / but also of all the body. And v
                     •
                  on the contrarye parte gestures manerly maketh that whiche of nature is semely to be more comlye:

and that whiche is of reproche / if so be it take it nat awaye / yet it hydeth it and dothe dymynisshe it. It is vnsyttynge to loke vpon a mā and wynke with the one eye: For what els is it but to make blynde hym selfe? Lette leaue that gesture to the fysshes called Thynnes and craftismen.
               Let the browes be set vp / and nat bente / whiche is token of crueltie / nat set vp t
                     •
                   hye / whiche is syne of arrogance and proude hert / nat hāgyng in to his eyen / which is 
                     •
                  yne of yuel ymagynaciō.
               A forheed mery &amp; playne / signifyeth a mynde of clene conscience and a gentyll nature: let it nat be knytte in wrincles as in an olde persone / nat mouynge vp and downe like an hedge hogge / nor croked or wri
                     •
                  hen lyke a bull.
               Let nat the nose thrilles be full of s
                     •
                  yuell lyke a sluttysshe persone: That vyce was noted in Socrates as a reproche.
               To drie or snytte thy nose with thy cappe or thy cote is all of the carte / vpon thy sleue or thyne elbowe / 

is propertie of fysshmōger
                     •
                  . Nor it is nat mo
                     •
                  h
                     •
                   mor
                     •
                   maner to drie with thy bare hande / if so be afterwarde thou daube it on thy clothes.
               It is good maner to drie the fylthe of the nose with thy handkercher / and that with thy heed somwhat tourned a syde / if more honest persones be presen
                     •
                  .
               If any snyt fall on ye groūde after thou haste sny
                     ••
                  e thy nose with two fyngers / by and by treade it out vnder thy fete. It is also agaynste maner to snuffe with thy nose / it is a syne of malyce: It is more leude to snu
                     ••
                  e with thy nose / and a syne of fury if it be vsuall. As for suche as be shorte breathed / that be sycke of tysyke muste 
                     •
                  e holde excused. It is a reproche to speake in the nose / for it is the propertie of crowes and elephantes.
               To wrie the nose is the propertie of scoffers and naturall fooles.
               If snesynge chaunce other beynge presen
                     •
                  e / it is good maner to turne a syde: after whā the passion doth cease / 

to blesse thy mouth with the syne of the crosse / after to take of thy cappe &amp; thanke thē (or desyre pardone) that sayd or were aboute to saye christ helpe: for snesynge as gawnyng is wont to take a waye the sence of herynge.
               It is goodly to say
                     •
                   christe helpe to an other man that sneseth: And it is a chyldes par
                     •
                  e to do of his cappe / if dyuers that be elder be present that saye christ helpe to man or woman. And 
                     •
                  ynally to make a shyrle noyse or a shrike purposely in snesyng / or to itera
                     •
                  e snesyng of purpose / to the 
                     •
                  stētacio
                     •
                   of his strength is leudenesse.
               To stop the snesyng that nature moueth is folly of such that preferreth maner before helth.
            
            
               ¶The coulour.
               Let naturall coloure (and nat counterfet) ornate the chekes: al be it let naturall coloure be so mesured or ordred / that it be nat altered to shamfastnesse / nor make a childe so astonyed / to brīg hī to the deg
                     •
                  e (as it is said)

as it were of a mā that wer
                     •
                   mad. To some children this passion feble is so impressed that it maketh a childe lyke to a dastarde. This leude maner is sone correcte / if a childe be acustomed to lyue amōge his elders / &amp; be exercysed to playe comedies or interludes. To puffe vp o
                     •
                   swell in the chekes / is to
                     •
                  en of a proude hert &amp; sollē. To smyle is token of a mā that sheweth tr
                     •
                  e mynde: the one is Thrafos ꝑte / the other is Iudas the traytours parte.
               Lette nat thy mouthe be stopped / that is syne o
                     •
                   hym that feareth to take the brethe of a nother: nor let it nat gape / that is token of ydio
                     •
                   fooles / but closed the lyppes softe touchynge togyther. It is no good maner to set out the lyppes and make a bowe or ba
                     •
                   / although great mēnes sonnes (goynge there a multytude) vse it: they shal be pardoned / as men in whō what so euer they do is taken as manerly / but I enforme childrē. If the chaūce gapīg / &amp; thou can nat turne away
                     •
                   or go away / close thy mouth with thy hādkerchife or the palme of thy hande / 

after crosse thy mouthe.
               To alowe euery mānes wordes or dedes is the ꝓperti
                     •
                   of fooles: to apply to no mā is propertie of a dastarde. To shewe mery coūtenaūc
                     •
                   to fylthy wordes or dedes / is syne of leudnesse. Grinnyng &amp; laughyng out of mesure / wherwith all the body dothe shake / whiche passyon the grekes call risus syncrusius / that is a shake / is nat semynge to any age / nor yet in a childe. It is vnsyttynge that some laughynge neye lyke an horse. He is vnmanerde and rude that laugheth with wyde mouthe and writhen chekes / shewynge his tethe lyke a dogge that gnarreth: and it is called the laughynge of Sardinia (an herbe / whiche eaten maketh a mā to dye laughyng) Let the coūtenaūce so shewe myrthe that it do nat disfygure the mouthe / nor bring 
                     •
                  eproche of a lyght mynde. These be the sayenges of fooles / I brast for laughter / I leape for laughter / I dye for laughynge / or any suche other folisshe 
                     •
                  utche chaūce / so that he be nat wyllynge 
                     •
                  o shewe suche laughynge / 

he muste couer his face eyther with a napkyn or his hande. To laugh onely with out euydent cause / is sygne of folly or madnesse. And if so be suche thyng chaunce / it is maner to open the cause to other / or if ye thynke it nat mete to be shewed / to bring some coūterfet excuse leste that any man suspecte hym selfe to be mocked.
               To byte with the tethe the nether lyppe is nat maner / but syne of malyce: lyke wyse to the vpper lyppe.
               Also to lycke the nether ꝑ
                     •
                  e of thy lyppes with thy 
                     •
                  ōge. is folly.
               To set o
                     •
                  t the lyppes and ioyned / as to kysse / in olde tyme with the almayns was iudged gentylnesse / as their pictures sheweth.
               To bleare out the tonge and mocke any manne / is poynt of a knaues scoffyng.
               Tourne thy face whan thou spyttest / so that thou spyt vpon no man / or spattell any man.
               
                  In lyke maner to scrubbe or rubbe with the nayles other partes of the body is fylthe / in especyall if it be done of custome and nat of necessyte.
            
            
               ¶The heere.
               Let nat thy heere kyuer thy browes / nor flye vpon thy sholders. Also to ruffle the heere of thy heed with shakyng of thy heed / is the propertie of wanton coltes. To caste backe thy bussh
                     •
                   fro the forheed towarde the crowne / is bare maner: it is more manerly to decke or deuyde it with thy hande. To bende in thy necke and crouche in with the sholders is the maner of s
                     •
                  uggartes: to set out the brest is syne of pride / it becometh to set the body streyght vp. Lette nat thy necke wrie vpō the lyft syde nor on the ryght / it is syne of ypocrisye / except comunycacion or some other thynge require.
            
            
               ¶The sholders.
               It becometh 
                     •
                  o holde thy sholders of a lyke heythe / nat of ye fasshyon of a sayle-cloth / to sēde vp the one &amp; to threst downe the other / for this negligēt behauer ī childrē groweth vnto a nature / 

and disfourmeth the behauour of the body agaynste nature.
            
            
               ¶The body.
               And so they that for slouthe draweth to a custome to croke their body / causeth them to be crouche backed / which nature neuer brought. And they that vse to holde their heed vpon the one syde groweth in to suche a custome / that in olde age they labour in vayne to altre it: For yonge b
                     •
                  dyes be lyke vnto tendre plantes / whiche in to what fasshyon you bende them / lyke a 
                     •
                  orke / or writhen lyke a corde / so they growe and waxe styffe.
            
            
               ¶The armes.
               To caste bothe thyne armes behynde on thy backe / bothe ha
                     •
                  h the fasshyon of slouthe / al
                     •
                  o of a thefe: nor it is nat more comly to stāde or syt and 
                     •
                  et thy one hande on thy syde / whiche maner to some semeth comly &amp; lyke a warryoure / but it is nat forthwith honest that lyketh fooles / but whiche is agreyng 
                     •
                  o reson &amp; nature. Other thynges shall be sayd after / 

whan we come to comunycacion and the table.
            
            
               ¶Priuy membres.
               To disclose or shewe the membres that nature hath gyue to be couered / without necessyte / ought to be vtterly auoyded from gyntyll nature. Also whan nede compelleth to do it / yet it muste be doone with conuenyent honestye / ye though no person be present / for aungel
                     •
                   be euer present / to whom
                     •
                   in children basshfulnesse is a tuter and a folower of chastyte: The syght of the whiche to withdrawe from the eyes of mē is honest. Moch more we ought nat suffer other to touche them.
               To kepe thy water is agaynst helthe / and hurteful
                     •
                   to nature: to make water secretly is honest. There be that teacheth that a chylde shal kepe in his nether wynde / his buttockes fast closed or clynged / but it is no maner whan thou entendest to be take honest / to alure t
                     •
                   the disease and syckenesse: If thou may go aparte do that a lone by thy selfe / i
                     •
                   no (after the olde prouer
                     •
                  e)

Let him close the fert vnde
                     •
                   colour of a coughe: or els why do nat they 
                     •
                  yd a mā by the same maner tha
                     •
                   a man 
                     •
                  hal nat go to the draught / wher as is more daunger to holde the wynde than to refrayne the draught. To 
                     •
                  y
                     •
                   ye knees layd a shoyle / or to s
                     •
                  āde the legges set bowed or croked / is the property of bragg
                     •
                  rs. Let the knees ioyne whan a mā sytteth / whan he stādeth let the fe
                     •
                  e ioyne / or els a lytel seperat thē a sōder. Sō
                  
                     •
                   syt on this fasshyō / that they crosse one leg
                     •
                  e ouer the other 
                     •
                  ne / sōe stāde their legges ioyned / trāplyng &amp; daū
                  syng: 
                     •
                  ha
                     •
                   one is the propertie of pensyue persons / that other of fooles. The rygh
                     •
                   leg cast ouer the lyf
                     •
                   thyg
                     •
                  e / was the maner of olde &amp; antique kinges to syt / but now nat laudable. Some of the ytaliēs set tha
                     •
                   one fote vpon that other bycause of nurture / &amp; stāde vpon one legge af
                     •
                  er the maner of storkes / which whether it become childrē I dou
                     •
                  e. Lykwise ī makīg of cur
                     ••
                  sy / one maner be cometh ī some place / &amp; in sōe place it is nat comly. Some make curtesye with bothe knees 
                     •
                  owed (as yrisshmen)

and on cōtrary wise some do it wi
                     •
                  h vpright body / 
                     •
                  ome w
                     ••
                  h body s
                     •
                  oupyng. Some there be that iudge that the curtesye of women. Some likewyse with vpright body make curtesy / first bowe the right kne / after the lyf
                     •
                   / whiche amonge englysshmen is laudable ī youth. The frēchmen do bowe the ryght kne with a lytel plesant returne of the body. In al suche maners in the which varye
                     •
                  e or chaūge hath no repugnance with honesty / it shall be laufull to vse the maners of our naturall coūtrey / or els to folow the maner of straūgers / whan the maners 
                     •
                  e such as straūge coūtreys doth alow The maner of goy
                     •
                  ge neyther in &amp; out / nor hasty staggryng / of the which that ou
                     •
                   is propertie of wan
                     •
                  ōnesse / the other of men furyous &amp; mad: for this 
                     •
                  olysshe goyng as a hal
                     •
                  yng man / we wo
                     •
                   cō
                  myt to these cleane warryours / &amp; to such as thinke it a gorgyous fasshyon to wear
                     •
                   plume
                     •
                   ī their cap / albe it w
                     •
                  
                  
                  
                     •
                  e that bys
                     •
                  hops take a pleasure in suche gesture. A man that sytteth to play with his toes / is propertie of foole
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  
                  
and to play with his fingers is syne o
                     •
                   lyght mynde.
            
            
               ¶Of apparayle.
               ¶It is fully or suff
                     •
                  ciently sayd of the body / nowe of apparayle somwhat / bicause apparayle is the forme and fasshyon of the body: And of this apparayle we maye coniecture the haby
                     •
                  e and apparayle of the inwarde mynde. Al be it this certayn maner maye nat be gyuen / in so moche that the fortune of all men nor dignyte be nat lyke: no nor the same honest or inhonest maner is in all maner of men: fynally nor in all maner of tymes / the same maners may please or displease. wherfore lyk
                     •
                   as in many other thynges / so in this maner no thynge is to be alowed or praysed / after the comen prouerbe: To the lawe / to the countrey / and to the tyme / wyse men byddeth a man to enfourme hym selfe. yet there is in this chaunges / what thyng in hymselfe is hones
                     ••
                  
                  
or nat / as the thynges whiche haue no profyte to the persone that the apparayle is made for. To drawe after them longe traynes / in women is discorned / in men it is leude. I praye you is it cōmendable in cardynalles and bysshoppes? I remytte that to the iudgement of other. Lyght &amp; wanton gardyng of the breche &amp; lasyng of the bely / was neuer praysed in man nor woman: for this is a straūge fasshyon of apparayle that couereth the secret ꝑtes / that be shamfull to be sene. In olde tyme it was taken nat honesty to go vngyrt or s
                     •
                  yt / in this dayes it is rebuke to many / bicause they be couerd with short petyco
                     •
                   &amp; close hose late foūde: albe it that co
                     •
                  e or kyrtel 
                     •
                  ly open / or els shorter aparell than dothe couer the secrete partes (which shulde be kept honest) whan a person stoupes / is euer dishonesty. To 
                     •
                  agge or to māgle apparayle is property of madde men. To vse paynted and diuers colours / is the maner of ydiots &amp; apes. Therfore a
                     •
                  ter the degre of ye dignyte and substāce / &amp; after the coūtrey

and the maner / let the clennes of aparayle be vsed: nor let it be shamefully daubed with fylthe / nor sh
                     •
                  wyng lechery / wātonnes / nor pride. Homely aparayle becometh youthe / but without vnclennesse. Some distayne the hē
                  mes of their lynen and wollen yuell fauordly with spottes of vrine &amp; pysse. Some barke their bosome &amp; their sleues with a cruste of fylth / na
                     •
                   with perget / but with the fylthe of their nose and their mouth. Some there be whiche let their gowne hāge on that one syde / some let i
                     •
                   slyppe downe to the reynes / and some thīke it becometh them. Lyke as it becometh euery parte of thapparayle of the body to be clenly / so it becometh it to gre vnto the body. If thy frēdes haue gyuen to the apparayle bette
                     •
                   and more gorgious / cast nat thyn eyes backwarde vpon thy body / nor iette nat for ioye and shewe thy selfe to other / for that one is propertie of apes / that other of proude pecockes. Let other prayse / be nat thou aknowē of thy fresshe apparayle.
               The greater that fortune is

the more amyable and gentyll be. we muste pardone meane persons to take a delyte in a meane / to consolacyon of their pouertie / bu
                     •
                   ryche men settyng forth the glorye of their apparayle / sheweth with reproche to other their awne misery / and getteth thē selfe but grudg
                     •
                   and enuye.
            
            
               ¶Of maners in the temple.
               As ofte as thou comest by a churche do of thy cap and make curtesye / and thy face turned towarde the sacrament / salute with reuerence Christe &amp; holy sayntes. And do the same whether it be in the towne or in the feldes / as oft as thou seest the ymage of the crosse. Go nat thorowe a church / but with lyke reuerēce salute Christ with a breue prayer / &amp; that with thy cappe of / and knelynge vpon bothe knees. Whan diuyne seruyce is in doynge it becometh to apply al partes of thy body to honoure god. Thynke that Christ i
                     •
                   there present with innumerable thousādes of angels.

And if so be a man shuld
                     •
                   speke to a mortall kynge / with a multytude that stād
                     •
                   rounde aboute hym / &amp; neyther do of his cap / nor make curtesye / he shulde be tak
                     •
                   of euery man / nat for a carter / but for a madde body: What a thynge is it there to kepe thy heed couered stately standyng / where as he is kynge of kynges / immortall / and graunter of immortalyte / where as honorable angels of heuen stāde roūde aboute hym. Nor it maketh no force if thou se them nat / they se the / and it is as sure that they be ther / as though thou 
                     •
                  awest them with thy bodyly eyes / for the eyes of faythe se more surely than eyes of the flesshe.
               It is nat syttyng that som
                     •
                   vse to walke vp and downe in the churche / and playe lyke Arystotles schole
                     •
                  s / as for walkynge yles / market-place and courtes / be conuenyent / nat churches that be dedycate to preache / to mynystre sacramentes and holy prayers: but lette thyne eyes beholde the preacher / thyder bende thyne eares / 

lette thy mynde be set thyder with all reuerence / as thoughe thou herdest nat a man / but god speakynge to the by the mouthe of a man. Whan the gospell is redde ryse vp / and if thou can here it red / deuoutly whan these wordes be redde in the credo / Et homo factus est / fall downe vpon thy knees / or in that wyse enclyne down
                     •
                   in his honoure that came downe him selfe from heuen for thy he
                     •
                  the / to this myserable worlde. And where as he was god he was contente to become man / to thentent to make the a god. Whyles the masse and diuyne seruyce is in doynge / apply thy selfe with all thy body to deuocyon: let thy face be turned towarde the aulter / and thy hert to god. To touche grounde with the one kne &amp; the other standing vp / vpon the whiche the lyfte elbowe doth leane / is the gesture of the wycked iewes and gētyles / which to our lorde Iesu scornyngly dyd saye / Hayle kyng of 
                     •
                  ewes. Thou shalte knele on bothe knees / &amp; the rest of thy body sōwhat bēte downe to shewe reuerence.

The remenant of the tyme eyther rede somwhat of thy boke / or saye thy beades / or els set thy medytacion vpon celestyall thīges. That tym
                     •
                   to chatte in an other mānes eare / is the propertie of such as thynke that Christ is nat there. To gape this wayes and that wayes / is the maner o
                     •
                   mad men. Iudge that thou arte come to churche in vayne / except thou departe thence more pure and more deuoute thanne thou cam
                     •
                   thyder.
            
            
               ¶Of maners at table.
               At table or at meate lett
                     •
                   myrthe be with the / lette rybaudrie be exyled
                     •
                   sytte nat downe vnto thou haue wasshed / but lette thy nayles be pared before that 
                     •
                   no fylthe stycke in them / le
                     •
                  te thou be called a slouen and a great nygarde: remembre the comen sayeng / &amp; before make water / and if nede requyre ease thy bely / and if thou be gyrde to strayte to vnlose thy gyrdell is wysdome / 

whiche to do at the table is shame. whan thou wypest thy handes put forth of thy mynde all grefe / for at table i
                     •
                   becometh nat to be sadde nor to make other sadde.
               Cōmaunded to saye grace / apply thy coūtenaunce and thy handes to deuoute maner / beholdynge eyther the mayster of the feest / or the ymage of Christ or of our lady: at this name Iesu or his mother Mary virgyne / make curtesye with bothe linees. If this offyce of sayeng grace be put to an other bothe take dylygent hede / and make answere with lyke de
                     •
                  oute maner. Gyue place with good wyll to an other of the hyest place / &amp; if thou be bydde to syt in a hygher place / gen
                     •
                  ylly refuse it / but if a man in auctorite bydde the of
                     •
                  e and ernestly / obeye hym manerly / lest thou shuldest seme shamfa
                     •
                  t for lacke of maner. At the table laye bothe handes vpon the table / neyther ioyned nor vpō thy trenchour / for some vnmanerly holde the one hāde or bothe vpon his bely.
               
                  To leane vpon the table with bothe elbowes or the one of them / is pardoned to them that be weake and feble / by rea
                     •
                  on of age or sicknesse: the same in some courtyers delycious / that thinke all thyng well that they do / it is to be forborne and nat folowed. In the mene tyme thou muste take hede leste that thou trouble hym that sytteth next the with thyne elbowe / or hym that sytteth agayne the with thy fete. Syttyng in the there to mo
                  
                     •
                  e thy buttockes this waye and that way / is lyke a man that letteth a blaste / or is aboute it: Lette therfore thy body sytte vpright egally. If the napkyn be gyuen the laye it on the ryght sholder or the lyfte. whan thou syttest wi
                     •
                  h greater men se thy heed be kembed / &amp; laye thy cappe asyde / except the maner of some deuocyon cause the otherwyse / or els some man of auctorite cōmaunde the contrary / whome to disobey is agayne maner. In some countreys it is the maner that chyldren standyng at their betters table shall take mete at the tables ende

al bare heed. There a childe ought nat come vncalled / nor lette hym nat tary there vnto dy
                     •
                  er be at an ende / but after he hath repasted hym selfe suffyciently / take vp his trenchour / make curtesy and salute them at the table / specyally the greates
                     •
                   person at the table. Let the cuppe stande on the ryght hande / and the meate kny
                     •
                  e cleane wyped / on the lyfte hande breed. To holde the breed in that one hāde / and breake it with thy fynge
                     •
                  s endes / it pleaseth some cour
                  
                     •
                  yers: lette them haue their pleasure / but cutte thou thy breed manerly with a knife / nat pluckyng away the crust aboue and vnder / as swet
                     •
                   mouthed men. In olde tymes men were wonte at all maner of repastes reuerētly as a relyke to handle their breed / by reason wherof nowe in this 
                     •
                  yme a maner remayneth whan breed falleth to the grounde / to take it vp &amp; kysse it. To begyn your repaste with drinke / is propertie of blowbowles that drinke nat for thyrste / but of vse. And this vse is nat alonely vnmanerly / 

but also hurteth the body. Nor ye shall nat drinke immedyately after browes or potage / nor specially after eatyng of mylke.
               A chylde to drinke oftenner than twyse or thrise at the fardest at his repaste at table / is neyther manerly nor holsome. Let him drīke ones after he hath fedde a 
                     •
                  hyle vpon 
                     •
                  he seconde dysshe / 
                     •
                  pecially if it be drie meate / and agayne at thende of the dyner or supper / and that moderately / drinke nat lyke a swylbolle / nat suppynge or smackynge with the lyppes lyke an hor
                     •
                  e. To bolle and drinke bothe wyne and al
                     •
                   superfluously / it bothe hur
                  
                     •
                  eth the helthe of chyldren / lykewyse it dystayneth the maners of children. water is mete for youth and the hote age / or if he may nat awaye 
                     •
                  herwith / or the nature of that coūtrey is nat suche / or any other cause woll na
                     •
                   suffre it / let him vse small ale or small w
                     •
                  rie / and alay it wi
                     •
                  h water: Or els this rewarde foloweth to suche as delyte in pure wyne / rotten 
                     •
                  ethe / bleared eyen &amp; droppynge / dull syght / and dull mynde / 

and in shorte space to loke lyke an olde man / before his olde age. Be
                     •
                  ore 
                     •
                  hou drīke 
                     •
                  ha we downe thy meate / nor put nat thy lippes to the cup but drie thy lyppes before with thy napkyn or hād
                     •
                  ercher / specially if another mā o
                     •
                  fer to the the cup / or whan thou drinkest of the comen cuppe. To loke a syde whan thou drīkest is a rude maner &amp; lyke as s
                     •
                  orkes / to wrie his necke back ward. To drīke al that nothyng remayne in the cup / is the propertie of a 
                     •
                  hor
                     •
                  e. Let a chylde curtessy salute agayne the persone 
                     •
                  hat saluteth hym whan he drīketh / &amp; touche the cuppe with his lyppes and ca
                     •
                  te alytell / shewyng a face as tho he dyd drinke: it is ynough
                     •
                   to lyght person that taketh su
                     •
                  he maner vpon hym. If a 
                     •
                  arterly person woll compell the 
                     •
                  o dr
                     •
                  ke / 
                     •
                  et a childe promesse to answer hym whā he is elder. Some whan they be scātly set / 
                     •
                  orthwith they put their hādes in the d
                     •
                  ssh
                     •
                   that is the propertie of wolues ramyyng / or of suche (as they say) that deuour 
                     ••
                  es
                     •
                  h
                     •
                   out of the boylynge leade / nat yet redy to 
                     •
                  ate.
               
                  Se that thou put nat thy hande first in the dysshe / nat onely bycause it shewth the to be gredy / but bycause it is sōtyme ioyned with parel as whā he taketh any thing scaulding in to his mouth at vnwa
                     •
                   / eyther he must spyt it out agayn / or if he swalow it downe it woll scaulde his throte: on both sydes he shal be laughed at / and take as a foole. A chylde must sōwhat tary / to accustome hym selfe to forbeare his appetyte: by the whiche coūsayle Socrates beyng an olde mā coude neuer forbere / but to drinke as sone as the cup cāe to the table first. If a childe syt at table with his betters / let hī syt lowest / nor let hī nat put his hāde to the dyssh but he be byd. To threst his fīgers in to his dysshe of potage / is the maner of carters: but le
                     •
                   hym take vp the meate with his knyfe or els his forke / nor let hī nat chose out this or that swete morsell out of the hole dysshe / which is the propertie of a lykerous ꝑson but that which chaūseth lye towarde hym / which we may lerne of Homerus / in whom often is repeted this verse
                     •
                  
                  
They russhed the
                     •
                  r hande
                     •
                   in to the dysshe that stod
                     •
                   before them. And if tha
                     •
                   or this morsell be very deyn
                     •
                  is leaue it to an other / &amp; 
                     •
                  ake of that whiche is nex
                     •
                  . And lyke as it is the maner of a gloton 
                     •
                  o threst his hande in to euery parte of the disshe / so it is vnmanerly to turne the dysshe vp so do
                     •
                  ne / to th
                     •
                   ende more deyn
                     •
                  ie dysshes may insue. If an othe
                     •
                   man gyue to the a deynti
                     •
                   morsell / 
                     ••
                  rste praye hym to holde the e
                     •
                  cused / than tak
                     •
                   it / but deu
                     •
                  de parte to thy selfe / than offer to hym 
                     •
                  he remenaunt that gaue it to the / or gyue parte to hym that sytteth next the.
               That gobbe
                     •
                   that can na
                     •
                   conuenyently be take with thy hande / take it on thy trēcher. If any man reache to the of a custarde or a pye any thyng in a spone / eyther take it on thy trenchour / or take the spone offred / &amp; th
                     •
                   meate layde on thy trēcher / gyue hym his spone agayne. If it be lyquide &amp; thy
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  ha
                     •
                   is gyue to the in the spon
                     •
                   to 
                     •
                  aste / take the spone &amp; r
                     •
                  
                  ceyue the meate / &amp; wype th
                     •
                   spone &amp; delyuer it agay
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  
                  
To lycke thy 
                     •
                  yngers greacy / or to drie them vpon thy clothes / be bothe vnmane
                     •
                  
                  ly / that must ra
                     •
                  her be done vpon the boorde clothe or thy napkyn. To swalowe thy mea
                     •
                  e hole downe / is the maner of s
                     •
                  orkes and deuourynge glut
                     •
                  ous.
               If any thynge be cut by an other / it is agayne m
                     •
                  ner to pu
                     •
                   forthe thy hande or thy tren
                     •
                  hour before the ke
                     •
                  u
                     •
                  r offer it to the / lest thou shuldest seme to ca
                     •
                  che tha
                     •
                   whiche was poīted for an other. That that is raught to the muste be 
                     •
                  ake with thre fyngers / or with thy trenchour. If any thyng be offred the that agreth nat with thy stomake / beware thou say nat that Clytipho sayde / I ca
                     •
                   nat away with it father: but gentylly say I thanke you. This is a very manerly maner of refusynge. If he that offreth it the perseuer / saye it gree
                     •
                  h nat with thy stomake / or els thou wolte eate no more.
               The maner of cuttynge of thy meate is to be lerned from the ten
                     •
                  er yeres / nat peuysshe as some vse / 

but manerly &amp; con
                     •
                  enyent. The sholder must be cut otherwyse / and otherwyse the legge / otherwyse the necke pece / otherwyse the syde / otherwyse the capon / otherwyse the fesante / o
                     •
                  herwyse the partriche / otherwyse the malard
                     •
                   wherfore ꝑtyculerly to speke of al were both per
                  
                     •
                  use &amp; also nat profyte. This sūmarily may be taught. It is the propertie of such as be preparers or maysters of bā
                  kettes / to engrosse frō euery syde all that may please the mouth. It is smal honesty to gyue to an other that thou hast bytten of. It is al of the car
                     •
                  e to dyp or put thy breed agayne in to the disshe of po
                  
                     •
                  age that is gnawen vpon. Lykewise to take the meat
                     •
                   out of thy mouche that tho
                     •
                   hast 
                     •
                  hawed / &amp; laye it on thy trenchour / is a leude tutche. For if thou haue take any morsell that can nat go downe / it is maner to tourne thy heed &amp; caste it priuely away. It is reproche to eate agayne the meate that is gnawen or bones layde on thy trenchoure. Caste nat vnder the boorde bones or any other fragmēt defyling the flore / nor 
                     •
                  ast it on ye table clothe / 

nor put it in the dysshe / but laye it on the couer of thy trenchour / or in the voyde
                     •
                   that is set for fragmentes.
               It is noted a folly to gyue meate to straūge dogges at the table: it is more folly to handle dogges at the table.
               To pyll thyn eggeshell with thy fyngers or thy 
                     •
                  hombe is a leude tutche: the same is more leude to put thy tonge in to thegge. with thy knyfe to take it out is more comly.
               To gnawe bones is the propertie of dogges / to pycke i
                     •
                   with thy knyfe is good maner. To take sal
                     •
                  e out of the salte celler with thre fyngers / in a vulgare ieste is called the norter of carters or ploughmen. Salte muste be take as is necessary with thy knyfe. If the salte be farre of it muste be asked.
               To lycke the dysshe wherin is suger or any swete meate / is the propertie of cattes / and nat of men.
               Cutte thy flesshe small or mynce it v
                     •
                  on 
                     •
                  hy trēcher / 

and after take breed and 
                     •
                  haw it a reason before thou let it go downe: and this nat onely is manerly but helthfull.
               Some rather deuoure than eate their meate / non other wyse than suche as be ledde in to prison. This rauenyng and deuourynge is appropred to theues.
               Some cramme so moche in to their mouth at ones / that bothe their chekes stāde out and swell lyke a payre of belowes. Some in eatynge slubber vp their mea
                     •
                  e lyke swyne. Some snuffe &amp; snurte in the nose for gredynesse as though they were choked.
               To drinke or speake with bridelde or full mouthe / is neyther honesty nor surety. Entrechaunge of comunycation by pausynge / dothe interrupte contynuall eatynge.
               Some without pause styll eate &amp; drinke / nat bycause they be an houngred and thurstye / but bycause they can none otherwyse order or behaue them selfe / but if they scratche their heed / 

or pycke their 
                     •
                  ethe / or shew leude gesture with their hā
                  des or their knyfe / or eis coughe / hemme / or spyt
                     •
                  e.
               This maner come
                     •
                  h all of the carte / and hath in a maner a resemblaunce of madnesse. This tedyous maner muste be auoyded / in markynge the comunyca
                     •
                  ion of other / if a man can se no opportunyte to speake. It is an yuell maner to sytte in a study at the table.
               Thou may se some in suche an extasy or stony that they here nat what is sayde of other / nor ꝑceyue that they eate: and if thou call them by name / they seme as men that came from slepe / their mynde is so rauysshed.
               It is no good maner with rollyng eyen to marke what euery man eateth / nor it is nat syttynge to gase longe vpon any that sytteth at the 
                     •
                  able: also it is worse maner to scoule or loke awrie vpon any that sy
                     •
                   vpon the same syde. It is worste fasshyo
                     •
                  
                  
to wr
                     •
                  e his heed and looke behynde hym what they do at an other table.
               To blabbe out what is sayd or done at large / whan men drinke and make mery / becometh no man nor chylde.
               A chylde syttynge with his betters shulde neuer speke / but necessyte compell / or el
                     •
                   he be bydden. At mery wordes let hym somwhat smyle: at rybaudrie let hym shewe no lyght countenaunce / no
                     •
                   roughe / if he tha
                     •
                   speaketh be a man of hye auctorite / but lette his countenaunce so 
                     •
                  empre his behauour / so that it shall seme eyther tha
                     •
                   he herde nat / or vnderstode nat.
               Sylence becometh women / but rather chyldren.
               Some dothe answre before he that speaketh hat
                     ••
                   made an ende / and it chaunseth that he maketh contrarye answere / and is hadde in derysyon / and this olde prouerbe maye be sayde of hym: I asked for hookes / 

an other answered sayeng he had no bootes / answerynge nothynge to purpose.
               Kynge Salomon sayth
                     •
                   thus / he is a foole that answereth before he hereth the ende: he hereth nat that perceyueth nat. If he vnderstande nat him that asketh / let hym cease vntyll he that hath spoke repete his tale. If he do nat so / but cōstrayneth hym to answere / lette the chylde gentylly praye hym of pardon / and desyre hym to shewe the thynge agayne. And the questyon vnderstande / lette hym pause a lytell / after lette hym answere in fewe wordes and meryly.
               At table nothynge ought to be blabbed forth that shulde dimynisshe myrthe.
               To hurte the fame of them that be absente is a great faute: nor no olde sores of any man shulde be renewed.
               To fynde faute with any meate is agaynst good maner / and is displeasure to hym that maketh the feest.
               
                  If the feest be made of thy coste / lyke as it is maner to excuse the syngle fare / so to prayse the feest or to reherce what it coste / is soure sauce to the gestes.
               To conclude / if any thynge be done of any man nat manerly by ignorance / it shulde be dissimuled rather than had in derisyon. Lybertie is me
                     •
                  e at meate and drinke.
               It is reproche as Flaccus saythe / to blowe abrode if any thynge ouerslyppe a man at table vnaduyse
                     •
                  .
               what so euer 
                     •
                  e do
                     •
                  ne or sayde there / shulde be lapped vp in the clothe / leste thou here this: I hate hym that wol reherce that is sayd at table.
               If the feest be lenger than is mete for chyldhode / and seme superfluous / &amp; thou felest that thou hast ynoughe / eyther conuey thy selfe priuely thence / or aske lycence.
               They that kepe chyldehode to hongerly / in my mynde they be madde / 

and lykewyse they that e
                     •
                  
                  gorge them wi
                     •
                  h ouermoche meate. For as tha
                     •
                   one doth enfeble the strength of the 
                     •
                  endre bodyes / the other lykewyse oppresseth 
                     •
                  he w
                     ••
                  : But measure ought to be knowen.
               The body of a childe ou
                     •
                  h
                     •
                   to be fed without full belly / and rather ofte a lytell at ones.
               Some knoweth nat whan they be full / but whan the belly is swollen so that it is in daunger to b
                     •
                  eke / or els by vomy
                     •
                  e he muste pycke ouer the perche.
               They hate their chyldren / that sytting at supper longe vnto late in the night / suffre them to sytte styll by them.
               Therfore if tho
                     •
                   muste ry
                     •
                  e fro lōge supper / take vp thy trenchour with fragmētes / and salu
                     •
                  e hym that semeth the great
                     •
                  st man at the table / and other lykewise / and so dep
                     ••
                  te: but by and by returne / leste thou be noted to departe bycause of playe or of other lyght cause.
               
                  Retournynge / wayte if any thyng lacke / or honestly attende at the table / and loke if any man commaunde any thynge. If thou set downe any thynge or take vp / take hede thou sheade nothynge vpon other mennes clothes. If thou s
                     •
                  uffe the candle / fyrst take it of the boorde / and eyther couer with duste the snuffe / or trede it vnder thy foote / leste some yuell sauour be tedyous to smell.
               If thou reache forthe any thing or poure be ware thou do i
                     •
                   na
                     •
                   wi
                     •
                  h the lyft hāde.
               C
                     •
                  
                  ̄maunded to saye grace / order well thy behauoure / shewynge th
                     •
                   selfe redy vnto the company kepe sylēce / and tyme come to saye.
               In the meane tyme let thy countenaūce be stable / with r
                     •
                  uer
                     •
                  nce regardynge the g
                     •
                  ea
                     •
                  est man at the table.
            
            
               ¶Of metynge to gythers.
               If any man mete the by the waye worshyp
                     •
                  ull / eyther by reason of age / eyther by relyg
                     •
                  on or dignyte / or otherwyse worthy reuerēce / 

lette a chylde remembre to go forthe of the waye and reuerently put of his cappe / and somwhat make curtesy with his knees. Let hym nat thynke thus / what haue I to do with an vnknowen man / what with hym that neuer dyd for me? So reuerence is nat gyue to man for his merytes / but to god. So god cōmaūdeth by Salomon / whiche cōmaundeth to ryse vp to an aged man: lykewise by Paule / to shewe double reuerence to prees
                     •
                  es. To conclude / to shewe reuerence to euery persone / to whome reuerence is due / folowynge also the gentyles reuerence. If so be that the Turke (whiche god forbyd) shuld haue domynion vpon vs / we shulde offende if we dyd nat shewe reuerence to that auctori
                     •
                  e. Of the father and mother I speake nat amonge other / to whom chefe reuerence after god is due. Lyke reuerence to our teachers / whiche lykewise as they fresshen the myndes of men / so they engendre good maner. And so amonge lyke of degree this sayeng of Paule muste take place / 

Preuent you one an othe
                     •
                   with due reuerence. He that preuenteth his egall or inferior with reuerence / he is nat therfore the worse / but more honest therfore &amp; more to be had in reuerence.
               with our betters we muste speake with reuerence / and in fewe wordes: with our peres louyngly and gentylly. And whan a childe speaketh he muste holde his cappe in the ryght hande / and holde his lyfte hande towarde his myddle / or els that is more comly / holde his cappe with both handes ioyned / so that his thombes apere couering his codpece. To holde his boke or hat vnder his arme is take as rudenesse.
               Let basshfulnes be shewed / but as becometh / nat as maketh a chylde amated. Let the eyen loke vpō hym that thou speakest to sadly and onely / shewynge nothynge wanton nor leude.
               To caste thyne eyen downe as a beest called Catoblepas / is a suspectyon of an yuell conscience. To loke a
                  
                     •
                  yde is token of disdayne. To turne this wayes &amp; that / 

is a syne of lyght wytte. It is rudenesse ofte to chaunge countena
                     •
                  ce / as now 
                     •
                  o wrie the nose / nowe to knytte the browes / nowe to set vp the browes / nowe to sette a wrie the mouthe / nowe to gape wyde / nowe to make a narowe mouthe: these be synes of inconstance.
               It is also all of the carte to shake the heed and caste the busshe / to coughe without cause / to hemme or rey
                     •
                  he / lykwise to scratche thy heed to picke thyne eares / to sny
                     •
                   thy nose / to stryke thy face / as a man that wypeth for 
                     •
                  hamfastnesse / to scrubbe or rubbe thy ne
                     •
                  ke / to shrugge or wrigge thy sholders as we se in many ytalyens.
               To deny with touenynge away thy heed / or beckenyng with thy heed to call hym / and to conclude / to speke by gesture and beckenynges as somtyme becometh a man / but nat a chylde. It is no maner to wagge the armes / to play with the fyngers / to stager with the fete / to speke hastely nat with the tonge / 

but mouynge all the body / whiche is the propertie of turtyll doue
                     •
                   or wagtayles / nor moche differēt fro pyes 
                     •
                  hatterynge. Let thy voyce be soft and styll / nat hye and clamorous lyke carters / nor so bause that he to whome thou speakest may nat here the
                     •
                   Lette thy speche nat be hasty and ouer ron thy wyt / but softe and open.
               This also auoydeth naturall stu
                     •
                  tynge / buffyng / and stammerynge / thoughe nat fully / yet for moste partie it demynis
                     •
                  heth / where as hastye speche causeth vyce in many / that came nat by nature. Also in cōmunycacion it is a gentyll maner to repete some honest tytle or name of roume or dignyte of hym that thou spekest to.
               There is nothynge more honest or plesaunt than the tytle or name of father or mother / nothynge more amyable thanne the name of brother and suster.
               If that priuat names come nat to mynde / name all lerned men worshypfull maysters / all preestes and monkes reuerende fathers / 

all companyons / bretherns and frendes: breuely al that be vnknowen / call thē mayster and maystresse.
               Of a childes mouth it is nat honest to sweare / whether it be gamyng or ernest. what is more reproche than this maner in 
                     •
                  ome countreys / to sweare at euery thyrde worde / ye the lytell gyrles / by breed / by salte / by cādle: by what thynge sweare they nat? To foule wordes let no manerly childe make answere / nor laye his eare. Fynally if any thynge be shewed to the eyen / or herds by the eares in honestly.
               If the cause requyre that he muste name any membre priuy / let hym couer it with honest circumstaunce.
               Further / if it chaunce to speke of vyle thinges / as vomyte / a draught / or a 
                     •
                  orde / he muste say before saue reuerence.
               If he must deny any thyng / let hym beware that he say
                     •
                   nat ye say nat truthe / specyally if he speke to his elder
                     •
                  
                  
but first by your fauour say it was otherwyse tolde me of suche a man.
               A well manered chylde shall contende with no man / no nat with his felowes / but let other haue their wyll: if the thynge come to discencyon / let hym referre the mater to arbytrement. Let hym nat presume before an other / let hym nat auaunte his awne dedes / nor reproue the maner of other / nor reuyle the nature and maners of any nacyon / nor publysshe an
                     •
                   secret shewed hym / nor scatter no newe tales / nor defame no man / nor rebuke no honest man of that whiche is naturall / for that is nat onely spy
                     •
                  efull and vngentyll / but folysshe. As if a man call hym that hath but one eye / one eyed: hym that halteth a crypp
                     •
                  e: hym that can nat se bu
                     •
                   nye vnto hym sandblynde / or he that is borne out of wedlocke bastarde. By this meanes it shal folowe that a man with out enuy shall gette prayse / and allure s
                     •
                  endes.
               To interrupt any man in his tale before it be ended
                     •
                   is agayne maner.
               
                  Lette hym beare malyce to no man: shewe gentylnesse to euery persone / lette hym take fewe to his secret counsayle / and those with good discrecion. Lette hym nat shewe that he wolde haue secrete. It is folly to loke that an other man shal kepe close / that can nat kepe close to thy selfe. No man is so close of tonge but he hath some in truste / to whome he woll open his secret mynde. It is moste sure nothynge to do or saye / wherof thou shulde be shamed if it be spoken abrode.
               Be nat ouer besy in other mennes causes. And if thou se or here any thynge / loke thou knowe nat that thou knowest.
               To prie or loke vpon letters that be nat brought to the / is leude maner. If a man open his casket before the / go a parte.
               Also if thou perceyue any secrete counsayle to ryse amonge any persons / auoyde thence thy selfe as thoughe thou knewe no thynge / 

and do nat entremedle to come to counsayle excepte thou be called.
            
            
               ¶Of gamynge and pla
                     •
                  .
               In gamynge and gentyll sporte let mery fasshyon be shewed / lette crafte / cause of stryfe and discey
                     •
                  e be set a parte / also lyes. For thrugh these prīciples a childe groweth to further inconuenyence. He ouercometh better that s
                     •
                  ryueth nat / than he that hath the victorye. Neuer repugne iugement. If thou playe with them that 
                     •
                  e ignorant
                     •
                   / thou mayste alwaye wynne / but be content sometyme to lese tha
                     •
                   the gamynge maye be more mery. If thou playe with mean
                     •
                  r persones / take nat vpon the to be better than they. A man shulde gamen for recreacion &amp; nat bycause of lucte. They say that the inclynacion of a chylde can nat be better knowen than in gamynge. If any be disposed of nature to deceytes / to lyes / to stryues / to vyolence or presūpcion / here the vyce of nature woll apere. Therfore a manerly chyld
                     •
                  
                  
shulde be lyke hym selfe / no lesse in gamynge than at th
                     •
                   table.
            
            
               ¶Of the chambre.
               In the chambre sylenc
                     •
                   is laudable / with honesty. Loude speche and clattryng is nat honest / moche more in bedde. whether thou do thy clothes of or vpon / regarde honesty / beware thou shewe nothynge bare to syght that maner &amp; nature wolde haue couered. If thou lye with a bedfelowe / lye styll / and make nat bare thy selfe with tumblyng / nor vexe nat thy bedfelowe with pullynge of the clothes. Before thou lay thy body downe / crosse thy forheed and thy brest with the syne of the holy crosse / &amp; cōmende the to Iesu Christ with some lytell prayer.
               Do the same in the mornyng whā thou rysest / begyn the daye with some prayer: Thou canste nat begyn with better lucke. And after thou haste be at the 
                     •
                  akes

do no thyng vnto thou hau
                     •
                   wasshed thy handes &amp; face / and thy mouthe.
               To suche as chaunce to be well borne it is to thē shame nat to be of lyke maners as their progenytours were. whome fortune wylleth to be of cōmen sorte / of lowe bloode / &amp; vplandysshe / they muste laboure the more to sette them selfe forthe with auauncement of good maners / in that that fortune hath debarred them.
               No man can chose to hym s
                     •
                  lfe father and mother or his countrey / but condycion wy
                     •
                   / and maners any man maye countrefet. I wyll annexe to this a shorte prece
                     •
                  te as a sure testimonye / whiche semeth to me worthy pr
                     •
                  emynēce. It is the chefe parte of gentyll maner / althoughe thou neuer offende 
                     •
                  hy selfe / yet gentilly to pardon other mennes fautes / nor to loue lesse thy companyon therfore / thoughe he haue some cōdycions out of frame. Nor these thynges be nat here spoken for that entent / as thoughe no man may be honest without thē.

If so be thy companyon do offende by ouersyght / for as moche as he semeth of some reputacyon / to aduer
                     •
                  yse hym bytwene the and hym and with gentyll fasshyon / is good maner.
               This small gyft my sonne wel beloued / I wyll it shall be gyuen for thy sake to all the company of chyldren / that forth with thorowe this rewarde bothe thou shalte allure the good myndes of thy felowes / and thou shalt gyue to them the desyres of lyberall scyence and good maners. The goodnesse of Iesu vouche safe thy noble and vertuous enclynacion / and to encrease to better at all tymes.
            
         
         
            
            ERASMVS Roterodamus generoso cum 
                  •
               rimis &amp; optimi spe
                  •
                puero Adolph. principis Veriani filio S.
            
               SI ter maximū illum Paulum nō piguit oīa fieri omnibus, quo ꝓdesse posset omnibus, quāto minus 
                  •
               go grauari debeo i
                  •
               uāde i
                  •
               uētutis amore subinde repuerascere. Ita
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                quē admodū pridē ad Maxi miliani fratris tui primam adolescentiam memet accommodaui, dum adulescentulo, 
                  •
               um formo linguam: ita nūc me ad tuam attempero pueritiam, de puerorum moribus praecepturus: nō qd tu 
                  •
               isce praescriptis magnopere ege, 
                  ••
               , primum ab incunabilis inter a
                  ••
               icos educatus, mox 
                  •••
               tus tam insignem for
               
                  ••
               dae rudis aetatis art
                  •
               ficem:

               
                  •
               ut qd omni
                  •
                
               
                  〈…〉
               
               mus, ad te pertineant, &amp;c principibus, &amp; prīcipatui nacum sed ut libētius haec edis
               
                  •
               ant omnes pueri, ꝙ amplissimae fortunae, summae
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                spei puero dicata sint. Nec enim mediocre calcar addet uniuersae pubi, si cōspexerīt hero
                  •
               
               ̄ liberos à primis statim annis dicari studijs, &amp; in eodem cū ipsis stadio currere.
            Munus aūt form
                  •
               di pueritiā multis constat partibus, quarū sicuti prima ita precipua est, ut tenellus animus 
                  •
               mbibat pietatis seminaria: proxima, ut liberales disciplinas &amp; amet, &amp; perdiscat: tertia est, ut ad uitae officia instruatur: quarta est, ut à primis statim 
                  •
               ui rudimētis ciuilitati morū assues
               
                  •
               at. Hanc postremā nūc mibi proprie sumpsi. Nā de su
               
                  •
               erioribus quū alij cōplures

               
                  〈…〉
                
               
                  •
               us. Quanq aūt externū illud corporis decorū ab animo bene cōpo
                  •
               ito ꝓsiciscitur tamē incuria praeceptorū nō 
               nunq fieri uidemus, ut hāc interim gratiā in probis &amp; eruditis hominibus desyderemus. Nec inficior hanc esse clarissimā Philosophiae partē, sed ea, ut sunt hodie mor taliū iudicia, plurimū cōducit &amp; ad cōcil
                  •
               andā beneuolētiā, &amp; ad praeclaras illas a nimi dotes oculis hominū cō
               mēdādas. Decet aūt ut homo sit cōpositus aīo, corpore, gestibus ac uestitu: sed ī primis pucros decet oīs modestia, &amp; in his praecipu
                  •
                nobiles. Pro nobilibus aūt hab
                  •
               
               ̄di sūt 
                  •
               ēs, qui studijs liberalibus exco
                  •
               ūt animum. Pingāt alij in 
                  •
               lypeis suis leones aquilas, tauros, &amp; leopardos, plu
                  •
                
               
                  •
               abent uerae nobilitatis,

               q ꝓin
                  ••
               gnibus suis tot possunt imagines depīgere, quot ꝑdidicerunt artes liberales. Vt ergo bene cōpositus pueri aīus undi
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                reluceat, relucet aūt potissimū in uultu sint oculi placidi, uerecūdi, cōpositi nō torui, qd est truculentiae nō improbi, qd est impudētiae: nō uagi ac uolubiles, qd est insaniae: nō limi, qd est suspiciorū et in sidias moliē
               tium, nec immodice diducti. quod est stolidorū, nec 
                  •
               ubinde cōuiētibus genis ac palpebris, quod est incōstantiū, nec stupētes qd est attonitorū. id in Socrate notatū. nec nimiū acres, quod est iracun diae signū. nō innuētes, ac loquaces, quod est impudicitiae signum, sed aīm sedatū ac reuerenter amicum prae se ferentes. Nec enim temere dictū est à priscis sapientibus, 
                  •
               nimi sedem esse in oculis.

Picturae quidē ueteres nobis loquūtur, olim singularis cu
               
                  •
               usdā modestiae fuisse, semi
               
                  •
               lusis oculis obtueri, quēadmodū apud Hispanos quos
               
                  •
               ā, semip
                  •
               tos intueri blandū haberi uidetur &amp; amicū. Itidem ex picturis discimus, o
                  •
               im contractis strictis
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                la
               
                  •
               ijs esse, probitatis fuisse argumentū. Sed quod suapte natura decorū est apud omn
                  •
               s decorū habebitur. Quā
               qu
                  •
                in his quo
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                decet interdum nos fieri polypos, &amp; ad regionis morē nosmet attē
               
               
                  ••
               rare. Iam sūt quidā oculo 
                  •
               um habitus, quos alijs alios addit natura, q non cadunt sub nostras praeceptiones, nisi quod incompositi gestus nō 
               
                  •
               aro uiciant, non solū oculo
               
                  •
               ū uerū etiam totius corporis habitū ac formā. Contra 
                  •
               ōpositi, quod natura decorum est, reddunt decentius,

               
                  •
               uod uiciosum est, si nō tol
               
                  •
               ut, certe tegunt minūt
                  
                     
                  
                  que
               . Indecorū est clauso oculorū al 
                  •
               ero quenquā obtueri. Quid enī hoc aliud est, quam seipsū eluscare? Eū gestū thyn
               
                  •
               is ac fabris relinquaemus.
            Sint exporrecta supercilia, non adducta, quod est toruitatis: non sublata in altū, quod est arrogantiae: non in oculos depressa quod est male cogitantium.
            Fron
                  •
                itē hilaris &amp; explanata, mētem sibi bene cōsciam, &amp; ingeniū liberale prae se ferens, non in rugas contracta, quod est senij, nō mobilis, quod est erinaciorū: nō torua, quod est taurorū.
            A naribus ab
                  •
               it mucoris purulentia, quod est sordidorū. Id uitiū Socrati philosopho datum est probro. Pileo aut ueste 
                  •
               mungi rusti
               
                  ••
               num, brachio cubitôu
                  •
               ,

salsamentariorum, nec multo c
                  •••••
               us 
                  •
               d manu fieri, si mox p tuitam uestis illinias.
            Strophiolis excipere narium recremēta decorū, id
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                
               
                  ••
               ulisper auerso corpore, si qui adsint honoratiores.
            Si quid in solum deiectum est emūcto d
                  •
               obus digitis na so, mox pede proterēdū est. Indecorum est subinde cum sonitu spirare naribus, bilis id indicium est.
            Turpius etiam ducere run
               
                  ••
               os, quod est furiosorum, si 
                  •
               odo fiat usu.
            Nam spiritosis qui laberant orthopn
                  •
               ea, dāda est uenia. Ridiculum naribus uocem emittere, nam id corniciū est &amp; elephantorum Crispare nasum, irrisorū est &amp; sannionum. Si alijs presentibu
                  •
                incidat sternutatio, ciuile est corpus auertere. Mox ubi se remiserit ī petus,

s
                  •
               gnar
                  •
               os crucis imagine, de in sublato pileo resalutatis q uel salutarūt uel salutare d
                  •
                bu
                  •
               rāt: nā sternutatio quē ad modū oscitatio sēsum auriū prorsus aufert, precari ueniam, aut agere gratias. Alterū in sternutamēto salutare religiosū, &amp; si plures adsint natu maiores, qui salutēt uirū aut foeminā honorabilem, pueri est aperire caput. Porro uocis tinnitū studio intē
               dere, aut data opa sternutamentū iterare, nimirū ad uiriū ostentationē, nugonū est. Reprimere sonitū quē natura fert, ī eptorū est, qui plus tribuūt ciuilitati q saluti.
            Malas tingat natiuus &amp; ingenuus pudor, non fucatus aut ascitius color. Quanq is quo
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                sit 
                  •
               emp
                  •
               randus est, ut nec uertatur in improbitatē, nec adducat stuporem, &amp; quartū, ut habet prouerbiū,

               
                  •
               nsa n
                  •
               e gradū. Quihusdam enim hic affectus tā impotēs nisitus est, ut reddat delirāti similimū. Tēperatur hoc malū, si puer inter maiores assuescat uiuere, &amp; comoedijs agendis excerceatur. Inflare buccas fastus indiciū est, easdē demittere, est animū despondētis: alterū e
                  •
               t Thrasonis, alterū Iude ꝓditoris.
            Os nec prematur, quod est metuētis alterius halitū hau rire, nec hiet, quod est morionum, sed leniter osculātibus se mutuo labris cōiunctū sit. Minus etiam d
                  •
               corū est subinde porrectis labijs ueluti poppysmū facere, quanq id magnatibus ad ultis per m
                  •
               
               diam turbā incedentibus co
                  •
                donandū est, illos enim decēt omnia, nos puerū formamus Si 
                  •
               ors urgeat oscitatio, nec datur auerti, aut cedere, 
                  •
               trophio, uol
                  •
               ue tegatur os,

               
                  •
               ox imagine crucis ob
                  •
               igne
               
                  •
               ur. Omnibus dictis aut factis arridere, stultorum est: nullis arridere, stupidorum. Obscoene dictis aut factis arridere, nequitia est. Cachinnus, &amp; immodicus ille totum 
                  •
               orpus quatiens risus, quem ob id Graeci 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , id e
                  •
               t, concussorem appellant, nulli decorus est aetati, nedū ꝑueritiae. Dedecet autē quod quidā ridētes hinnicū aedūt. Indecorus &amp; ille qui oris rictū late diducit corrugatis buccis ac nudatis dētibus qui caninus est, &amp; Sardonius dicitur. Sic autē uultus hilaritatē exprimat, ut nec oris habitū dehonestet, nec animum dissolutum arguat. Stultorum illae uoces sunt, risu diffluo, risu dissilio, risu emorior, &amp; si qua res adeo ridicula inciderit, ut uolenti
               
                  •
               us eiusmodi risū exprimat,

mappa maniue tegenda facies. Solum aut nullam euidentē ob causam ridere, uel stultitiae tribuitur, uel insaniae. Si quid tamen eiusmodi fuerit obortū, ciuilitatis 
                  •
               rit alijs aperire risus causā: aut si nō putes ꝓferendā, cōm
                  •
               nti
                  •
               iū aliquid adferre, ne quis derideri suspicetur. Superioribus dentibus labrū inferius premere, inurbanum 
                  •
               st, hic 
                  •
               nim est minantis gestus: quē aedmodū &amp; īferioribus mordere superius. Quin &amp; labrorū oras līgua circūuolu
               
                  ••
                subinde lambere, inep
                  •
               ū. Porrectioribus esse labris, &amp; uel ut ad osculū composi
               
                  •
               is, olim apud Germanos fuisse blandum indicant illorum picturae. Porrecta lingua deridere quenquam, scurrile est. Auersus expuito, ne quem conspuas, 
                  •
               spergus u
                  •
               .

quemadmodū unguib
                  •
               s reliquū fricare corpus, sordidū est, praesertim si 
                  •
               iat usu, non necessitate. Coma nec frontem tegat, nec humeris inuolitet. Subinde concusso capite discutere capillitium, lasciuientiū est equorū. Cesariē à fronte in uerticē leua retorquere, parū elegans est, manu discriminare, modestius. Inflectere ceruicem
                  •
                &amp; adducere scapulas, pigritiam arguit. Resupinare corpus, fastus indiciū est: molliter erectum, decet. Ceruix nec in leuū, nec in dextrum uergat, by pocriticum enim, nisi colloquium, aut aliud 
                  •
               imile postulet. Humeros oportet aequo libramine temperare, non in morem antennarum, alterum attollere, alterū deprimere. Nam huiusmodi gestus in pueris neglecti, uertutur in naturam,

&amp; corporis habitum praeter naturā deformant. Ita
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                qui prae desidia collegerunt co
                  •
               
               sui tudinē inflectēdi corpus, sibi gibbū conciliant, quē natura non dederat: &amp; qui de fl
                  •
               xū in latus caput habere consueuerunt, in eū habitum ind
                  •
               rescūt, ut adulti 
                  •
               r
                  •
               stra mutare nitātur. Siquidem tenera a corpus
                  •
               ula plantu
                  •
               is similia sunt, quae in quācun
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                s
                  •
               eciem sur
                  •
               a 
                  •
               uniculoue de flexeris, ita cr
                  •
               scunt &amp; indurescūt. Vtrum
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                
               
                  •
               rachiū interg
                  •
               m retorquere, simul &amp; pigritiae speciem habet, &amp; furis. N
                  •
               
               
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                multo decentius est, altera manu in ilia iniecta astare 
                  •
               edereue, qd tamen quibusdā elegans ac mili
                  •
               are uidetur. At nō statim honestum est quod stultis placuit, sed quod naturae &amp; rationi consentan
                  •
               um est. Reliqua dicentur,

quum ad colloquiū, &amp; conuiuium uentum erit.
            Membra quibus natura pudorē addidit, retegere citra necessitatē, procul abesse debet ab indole liberali. Quin ubi necessitas huc cogit, tamen id quo
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                decēte uerecū
               dia faci
                  •
               ndū est, etiā si nemo testis adsit. Nunq enim non adsūt angeli, qbus in pueris gratissimus est pudicitiae comes custos
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                pudor. Quorū aūt conspectū oculis subducere pudicū est, ea multo minus oportet alieno praebere cōtactui. Lotiū remorari uae letudini perniciosū, secreto reddere uerecundū. Sūt qui praecipiāt ut puer cōpressis natibus uētris flatū retin
                  •
               at. Atq ciuile non est, dū urbanus uideri studes, morbū accercere. Si licet sedere, solus id faciat: Sin minus, iuxta 
                  •
               etustissimum prouerbium:

Tusci crepitum dissimulet. Alioqui quur nō eadē opera praecipiūt ne aluū deijciant, quū remorar
                  •
                flatū periculo sius sit, q aluū stringere. Deductis genubus sedere, aut di uaricatis tibijs distortisue stare T
                  •
               asonū est. Sedenti co
                  ••
               ant genua, stanti pedes, aut certe modice diducātur. Quidā 
               
                  •
               oc gestu sedēt, ut alterā tibiā altero genū suspendāt, nōnulli stant d
                  •
               cussatim cō, positis tibijs, quorū alt
                  •
               rum est anxiorū, alterū in
                  •
               ptorū
               
                  •
                Dextero 
                  •
               edeī leuū femur ī
               
               
                  •
               ecto sedere priscorū regum mos est, sed imꝓbatus. Apud Italos quidā honoris gra
                  •
               ia ped
                  •
               
               ̄ alterum altero premūt, uni
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                propemodū insistūt tibiae 
                  ••
               coniarū ritu, qd an pue 
                  •
               os deceat nescio. Itidem in flectèdis genibus aliud apud alios decet dedecetue. Quidā utrū
               
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                pariter iuflectunt,

id
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                rursus alij recto corpore, alij nonni
                  •
               il incuruato. Sūt qui hoc ceu muli
                  •
               bre rati, sinu
                  •
               iter erecto corpore primū dextrū incuruāt genu, mox sinistrū, qd 
               apd Britā
               nos in ado
                  •
               escētibus laudi datur. Galli modulato corporis circūactu dextrū dūtaxat in flectūt, In his in q
                     •
                  us uarietas nihil habet cum honesto pugnās, liberū erit uel uerna culis uti moribus, uel alienis obsecūdare, quādo sunt quos magis capiāt peregrina. Incessus nec fractus sit, nec praeceps, quorū alterū est mollium, alterū furio sorū, nec uacillans. Nam ineptā in incessu sub claudicationē Suiceris militibus relinquamus &amp; ijs qui magnū ornamētum ducūt, in pileo gestare plumas, Tamets
                  •
                uidemus Episcopos 
                  •
               oc gestu sibi placere. Sedētē ꝑedibus ludere stultorū est,

quēadmodū &amp; manibus gesticulari parum integrae mē
               
               
                  •
               i
                  •
                indicium est.
            
               DE CVL
                     •
                  V.
               In summa dictū est de corpore, nūc de cultu paucis, e
                     •
                   quod uestis quodāmodo corporis corpus est, &amp; ex hac quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   liceat habitū animi cō
                  ijcere. Quanq hic certus praescribi modus non potest, e
                     •
                   quod non omniū per est, uel fortuna, uel dignitas, nec apud omnes eadē decora sūt, aut indecora, postremo nec omnibus seculis eadē placēt displicentue. Vnde quemadmodū in alijs multis, ita hic quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   nōnihil tribuendū est, 
                     •
                  uxta prouerbium, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   etiā 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , id est, legi, &amp; regioni, &amp; tempori, cui seruire iubent sapiētes. Est tamen in hisce uarietatibu
                     •
                  , qd per se s
                     ••
                   
                  
                     •
                  onestum,

aut secus, uelut illa quae nullū habēt usū, cui paratur uestis. Prolixas trahere caudas in foeminis ridetur, in uiris improbatur. An Cardinales &amp; episcopos deceat, alijs aestimandū relinquo. Mulctitia nūquam nō probro da ta sunt tū uiris tū foeminis, quādoquidē hic est alter uestis usus, ut ea tegat q impudice ostendūtur oculis hominū. Olim habebatur parum uirile discinctū esse, nūc idē nemini uicio uertitur, quod indusijs, subuculis, et caligis repertis tegātur pudēda, etiā 
                  
                     •
                  i diffluat tunica. Alioqui uestis breuior q ut inclinanti 
                     •
                  egat partes quibus, debetur bonos, nus q nō inhonesta est Dissecare uestē amentiū est, picturatis ac uersicoloribus uti, morionū est ac simiorum. Ergo pro modo facultatum ac dignitatis, pro
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   regione

et more adsit cultui mundicies, nec sordibus notabilis, necluxū, nec lasoiuiā aut fastū prae se ferens. Neglectior cultus decet adolescētes, sed citra immūdiciam. Indecore qda interularū ac tunicarū ora
                     •
                   aspergine lotij pingūt. Sinū brachialia
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   indecoro tectorio incrustant, nō gypso, sed nariū &amp; oris pituita. Sunt qbus uestis in alterū la tus defluit, alijs ī tergū ad re nes us
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , nec desunt qbus hoc uid
                     •
                  atur elegans. Vt 
                     •
                  otum corporis habitū &amp; mundū, &amp; compositū esse decet, ita decet illū corpori cōgruere. Si quid 
                     •
                  legātioris cultus de dere parētes, nec teipsū re
                  
                     •
                  lexis oculis cōtemplere, h
                     ••
                   gaudio gestias, alijs
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   o
                     •
                  tentes, nam alterū simiarum eft, alterū pauonū, mirētur alij: 
                     •
                  u 
                     •
                  e bene cultum esse nescias
                     •
                   Quo maior est fortuna,

                  
                     •
                  oc est amabilior modestia. Tenuioribus in cōditionis so latiū concedendū est, ut moderate sibi placeā
                  
                     •
                  . At diues ostē
                  
                     •
                  ans splendorē amictus, alijs suam exprobrat miseriam, sibi
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   conflat inuidiam.
            
            
               DE MORIBVS in templo.
               Quoties fores templi praeteris, nudato caput, ac modice flexis genibus, &amp; ad sacra uerso uultu, Christū diuos
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   salutato. Idē &amp; alias faciendū, slue in urbe, siue in agris, quoties occurrit imago crucis. Per aedē sacrā ne trāsieris, nisi simili religione saltem breui precatiuncula Chris
                     ••
                  
                  ̄ appelles, id
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   retecto capite, &amp; utro
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   genu slexo
                     •
                   Cū sacra peraguntur, totum corporis habitū ad religionē decet componere. Cogita illic praesentem Christum cum innumeris angelorū milibus.

                  
                     •
                  t si qui regem hominē alloquuturus circūstāte procerū corona, nec caput aperiat, nec gen
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  lectat, non 
                     ••
                  
                  ̄ pro rustico, sed pro insono 
                     •
                  aberet
                     ••
                   ab oībus: quale est illic 
                     •
                  pertū habere caput, erecta genua, ubi ad est rex ille regū immortalis, &amp; immortalitatis largitor, ubi uenerabundi circūstant aetherei spiritus? Nec refert, sleos non 
                     •
                  ides, uident illi te, n
                     •
                  c minus certū est illos adesse, q si uide res eos oculis corporeis. Certius enim cernunt oculi fidei q oculi carnis. Indecentius 
                     •
                  tiam est quod quidā in templis obambulant, &amp; Peripa
                  
                     ••
                  cicos agunt. Atqui deambulationibus porticus &amp; fora conueniunt, non templa, quae sacris concionibus, mysterijs, ac deprecatiōi dicata sū
                  
                     •
                  . At cōcionantē spectent oculi, huc attentae sint aures,

                  
                     •
                  uc inhiet animus omni cum reuerētia, quasi non hominē 
                  
                     •
                  udias, sed deū per os hominis tibi loquentē. Quū recitatur Euangeliū, assurge, &amp; si potes ausculta religiose. Quum in symbolo cani
                     •
                  ur, &amp; homo factus est, in genua ꝓcūbe, uel hoc pacto te submittēs in illius honorē, qui semet pro tua salute, quū esset supra omnes coelos demisit in terras, quū esset deus, dignatus est homo fieri, ut te faceret deū. Dum peragūtur mysteria, toto corpore ad religionē composito, ad altare uersa sit facies, ad Christum animus. Altero genu t
                     •
                  rram contingere, erecto altero, cui laeuus īnitatur cubitus, gestus est impiorū militū, q domino Iesu illudētes dicebant, Au
                     •
                   rex Iudeorū. 
                     •
                  u dimitte u
                  
                     •
                  rū
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , reliquo etiā corpore nō 
                  
                     •
                  ihil inflexo ad uenerationē.

Reliquo tēpore aut legatur aliquid è libello, fiue precularū, s
                     ••
                  e doctrinae salutaris, aut mens celeste qdpiam meditetur. Eo tpe nugas abg
                     •
                  
                  nire ad aurē uicini, eorū est, q nō credūt illic adesse Christū, huc illuc circumferre uagos oculos, amentiū est. Existimate frustra templum adisse, nisi inde melior discesse
                  
                     ••
                  is purior
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  .
            
            
               De conuiuijs.
               In cōuiuijs adsit 
                     •
                  ilaritas, absit petulantia
                     •
                   non nisi lotus accumbe, sed ante praefectis unguibus ne qd in his haereat sordium, dicaris
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , idē sordidus &amp; impendio parcus, uide ꝓuerb. ac prius clam reddito lotio, aut si res ita postulet, exonerata etiam aluo: &amp; si fortē strictius cinctum esse contingat, aliquantulum relaxare uincula consultum est,

                  qd in accubitu parū decore fi
                     •
                  t. Abstergēs manus, simul abijce qcqd aī o aegre est. Nā ī cōuiuio nec tristē esse decet nec cōtristare qu
                        •
                     
                     ̄q, iussus cō
                  secrare mēsā, uultū ac manus ad religionē cōponi
                     •
                  o, spectās aut cōuiuij primariū, aut s
                     •
                   fors adest, imaginē chri
                     •
                  ti, ad nomen Iesu matris
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   uirginis, utrum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   
                  
                     •
                  lecten; genu. Hoc muneris si cui alteri delegatū fuerit, pari religione tū auscultato, tū respōdeto. Sedis honorem alteri liben
                  
                     •
                  er cede, &amp; ad honoratio
                     •
                  ē locū inuitatus, comiter excusa: si tamen id crebro s
                     •
                  rio
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   iubeat aliqs authoritate praeditus, uerecūde obtēpera, ne uideare ꝓ ciuili praefractus. Accūbens utrā
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   manum super mensam habe, non coniūctim, nec in quadra. Qu
                     •
                  
                  dam enim indecore, uel unā, 
                     •
                  el ambas 
                     •
                  abent in gremio.

Cubito uel utro
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   uel altero in
                     •
                  iti mens
                     •
                  e, senio morb
                     •
                  ue lassis cōdonatur: idem in delicatis quibusdā aulicis, qui se decere putant quicquid agūt, dissimulandum est, non imitandū, interca cauendum, ne proxime accumbēti pedibus sis molestus. In 
                     •
                  ella uacillare, &amp; nunc huic nunc alteri nati insidere, speciē habet subinde uētris 
                     •
                  tatū emittentis, aut emittere conatis. Corpus igitur aequo libramine sit erectum. Mantile si datur aut 
                     •
                  umero sinistro, aut brachio laeuo imponito. Cū honoratioribus accubitu
                  
                     •
                  us, capite pexo, pil eū relinquito, nisi uel regionis mos diuersū suadeat, uel alicuius authoritas praecipiat, cui nō parère sit indecorum. Apud quasdā nationes mos est, ut p
                     •
                  eri stantes, ad maiorā mē
                  
                  
                     •
                  ā capiāt cibū extremo loco,

re
                     •
                  ecto capite. Ib
                     •
                   ne puer accedat, nisi iussus, ne haereat us
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ad cōuiuij 
                     •
                  inē, sed sumpto quod satis est, sublata quadra sua, flexo poplite, salutet conuiuas, praecipue qui inter cōuiuas est caeteris honoratior. A dextris sit poculum et cultellus escarius, rite purgatus: ad laeuam pa
                     ••
                  s. Panem una uola pressū, summis digitis refringere, quorundā auricorū delitias esse sinito, tu cultello seca decenter, non undi
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   reuellens cru
                  
                     •
                  tum, aut utrin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   resecās: delicatorū hoc est. Panem uete res in omnibus conuiuijs c
                     ••
                  
                  rem sacrā religiose tractabant, unde nūc quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   mos relictus est, cū forte delapsū in humū, exosculari. Cōuiuium statī à poculis auspicari, potorū est, qui bibūt non quod si
                     ••
                  ēt, sed qd soleāt. Nec ea res solū moribus est ī honesta

uerū etiā officit corporis ua
                  
                     •
                  etudini. Nec statim post sūꝑ tam ex iure ofsam bibendū, multo minus post lactus esū. Puero saepius q bis, aut ad sū mum t
                     •
                  r, in conuiuio bibere, nec decorū est, nec salubre. Semel bibat aliquandiu pastus de secūdo missu, praesertim sicco: dein sub conuiuij finem, id
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   modice sorbendo, non ingurgitādo, nec equorū sonitu. Tum 
                     ••
                  nū, tum ceruis
                     •
                  a nihil ominus quam uinū inebrians, ut pu
                     •
                  rorū ualetudinē lae
                     •
                  it, ita mores dedecorat. Aqua feruidae cōuenit aetati, aut si non patitur, siu
                     •
                   regionis qualitas, siu
                     •
                   alia quae 
                     •
                  iā causa, tenui cer
                  
                     ••
                  sia utitor, aut ui
                     •
                  o nec ardenti, &amp; aqua diluto. Alioqui m
                     •
                  ro gaudent
                     •
                  s haec sequuntur praemia: d
                     •
                  ntes rubiginosi, g
                     •
                  nae defluentes, oculi luscios
                     •
                  , mentis stupor,

breuiter seniū ante senectā. Antequam bibas, praemande cibū: nec labra admou
                     •
                  as poculo, nisi prius mantili aut 
                     •
                  inteolo abstersa: praesertim s
                     •
                   quis suū poculum tibi porrigit, aut ubi de cōmum bibitur poculo. Inter bibendū intueri, illiberal
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  st, quemadmodū &amp; ciconiarum exēplo ceruicē in tergum r
                     •
                  flectere, ne quid herea
                     •
                  ī imo cyat
                     •
                  o, parum est liberale. Salutātē poculo resalutet comiter, &amp; admotis labris cyatho paululum libans bibere si 
                     ••
                  mulet: hoc ciui
                     ••
                   nugoni sa
                     •
                  is erit. Qui si rusticus urgeat, polliceatur se tum responsurum, quum adol
                     •
                  uer
                     •
                  t. Quidam ubi uix bene cōsederit, mox manus in epulas conijciunt. Id luporum est, aut eorum, qui de chytropode carnes nondum immolatas deuorant, iuxta prouerbium.

Primus 
                     •
                  ibum appositū ne at tingito, non tantū ob id quod arguit auidū, sed quod inter dum cū periculo cōiunctum est, dū qui feruidū inexploratū recipit in os, aut expuere cogitur, aut si deglutiat adur
                     •
                  re guld, utroque ridiculus aeque ac miser. Aliquantisper morandū, ut puer assuescat affectui temperare. Quo cōsilio Socrates ne senex quidem unquam de primo cratere bibere sustinuit. Si cum maioribus accumbit puer, postremus, n
                     •
                  c id nisi 
                     •
                  ui
                     •
                  atus manū admoueat patine. Digitos in iusculēta immergere agrestiū est, sed cu
                     ••
                  tello fuscinaue tollat quod uult: nec id ex toto eligat disco, qd solēt liguritores, sed quod forte ante ipsū iacet sumat, quod uel ex Homero discere licet, apud quē creb
                     •
                  r est hic uersiculus:

                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Id quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   si fuerit insigniter elegans, alteri cedat, &amp; quod proximū est accipiat. Vt igitur in temperātis est in oēs patinae plagas manū mittere, ita paerū decorū, patinā inuertere, quo ueniant ad te lautiora. Si quis alius cibum 
                     •
                  orrexerit elegantiorē, praefatus excusatiunculam recipiat, sed resecta 
                     •
                  ibi portiuncula, reliquū offe
                     •
                  at ei qui porrexerat, aut proxime assidēti cō
                  municet. Quod digitis excipi non potest, quadra excipiendū est. Si quis e placenta, uel artocrea porrexerit aliquid cocleari, aut quadra excipe, aut cocleare porrectū accipe, &amp; inuerso in quadram cibo, cocleare reddito. Si liquidius est quod datur gustā
                  dū, sumito, &amp; cocleare reddito, sed ad mantile extersū.

Digitos unctos uel ore praelingere, uel ad tunicam aex
                  
                     •
                  ergere, pariter in ciuile est: id mappa potius aut mantili faciendū. Integros bolos subito deglutire, ciconiarū est, ac balatronū. Si qd ab alio fuerit resectum, inciuile est manū quadr
                     •
                  ue po
                     •
                  rigere, prius q ille structor offerat, ne uidea
                     •
                  e precipere qd alteri paratū e
                     •
                  at
                     •
                   Q
                     •
                  od por
                  
                     •
                  igitur, aut tri
                     •
                  us digitis, aut porrecta quadra excipiē
                  
                     •
                  
                  ̄
                  
                     •
                   Si qd offertur nō cōgruit tuo stomacho, caue ne dixeris illud Comici Clitip
                     •
                  onis. Nō possū pater, sed blande agito gratias. Est enim hoc urbanissimū recusandi genus. Si prestat inuitator, uerecunde dicito, aut non cōuenire tibi, aut te nihil amplius requirere. Discenda est 
                     •
                   primis statim annis secādi ratio, nō sup
                     •
                  titiosa, qd quidā faciūt,

                  
                     •
                  ed ciuilis &amp; cōmoda. Aliter enim insciditur armus, aliter coxa, aliter c
                     •
                  ruix, aliter cratis, aliter capus, aliter phasianus, aliter p
                     •
                  rdix, aliter anas, quadere singulatim praecipere, ut prolixū sit, ita nec operae preciū. Illud ī uniuersū tradi pōt. Apitiorum esse omni ex parte, qdqd palato blā
                  
                     •
                  itur, abradere. Abs te semesca alteri porrigere, parū hon
                     •
                  sti moris est. Panē praerosū iterū in ius immerge re rusticanū est. Sicut &amp; cibū mansū faucibus eximere, &amp; in quadrā reponere ī elegās est. Nā si qd forte suptū est qd deglutiri nō expedit, 
                     •
                  lā auersus aliquo proijciat. Cibū ambesū aut ossa semel ī quadrā seposita repetere, uicio datur. Ossa aut si qd simile reliquū est, ne sub mēsā ab 
                     •
                  eceris pauimētū cōspurcās, 
                     •
                  ec in mēsae str
                     •
                  gulā proijce,

nec in patinā repone, sed in quadrae angulū sepone, aut in discū 
                  q apud nō nullos reliquijs excipiēdis apponitur. Canibus alienis de mēsa pro rigere cibū, ineptiae tribuitur, ineptius est illo
                     •
                   in conuiuio cōtrectare. Qui putamen di gitorū unguibus aut pollice repurgare ridiculū est: idem inserta lingua facere magis etiam ridiculū, cultello id sit decentius. Ossa dētibus arrod
                     •
                  re caninum est, cultello purgare ciuile. Tres digiti sa lino impressi, uulgari 
                     •
                  oco dicitur agrestiū insignia. Cul tello sumendū est salis quantū satis est. Si longius abest saliuū, porrecta quadra petendum est. Quadram aūt patinam cui saccarum aut aliud suaue quiddam adhesit, lingua lambere, feliū est non hominum. Carnem prius minutim in quadra dissecet,

mox addito pane 
                     •
                  imul aliquādiu mandat, priusquam 
                     •
                  raijciat in stomacū. Id non solū ad bonos mo
                     •
                  es, uerum etiā ad bonam ualetudinem pertinet. Quidā deuorāt uerius quam edunt, non aliter quā mox, ut aiūt, abducendi in carcerem. Latronū est ea tuburcinatio. Quidā tātum simul in os ingerūt, ut utrin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ceu folles tumeāt buccae, alij mandēdo diductu labiorum sonitū edunt procorū in morem. Nōnulli uorādi studio, spirant etiam naribus, quasi praefocandi. Ore pleno uel bibere, uel loqui, nec honestū est, nec tutū. Vicissitudo fabularum interuallis dirimat perpetuū esum. Quidam citra intermissionem edunt bibuntue, non quod esuriant sitiantue, sed quod alioqui gestus moderari non possunt, nis
                     •
                   aut scabant caput,

                  
                     •
                  ut sca
                     •
                  pant dentes, aut ge
                  
                     •
                  ticulēter manibus, aut ludät cultello, aut tussiēt, aut screent, aut expuāt. Ea res à ru
                  
                     •
                  tico pudore profecta, nonnullam insaniae speciē habet. Auscultandis aliorū sermonibus fallendū est hoc tedij, si nō datur opportunitas loquendi. Inciuile est, cogitabundū in mensa accumbere. Quosdam autē uideas adeo stupentes, ut nec audiant qd ab alijs dicatur, nec se cōme
                  
                     •
                  ere sentiant: &amp; si nominatim appelles, uelu
                     •
                   è somno excitati uideātur, Adeo totus animus est in patinis. In
                  
                     •
                  rbanū e
                     •
                  t ocul
                     •
                  s circūactis 
                     ••
                  seruare quid quisque comedat, nec decet in quēquam conuiuarum diuitus intentos 
                     •
                  abere oculos: inurbanius e
                  
                     ••
                  am transuersim hirquis intueri, qui in codem accumbunt latere: inurbanissimum,

retorto intergum capite cō
                  templari, quid rerum geratur in altera mensa. Effutire si quid liberius inter pocula dictum factumue sit, nulli decorū est, nedum puero. Puer cum natu maioribus accumbens nunquam loquatur, nisi aut coga
                     •
                   necessitas, aut abs quopiam inuitetur. Lepide dictis modice arrideat: obcoene dictis ne quando arrideat, sed nec frontem contrahat si praecellit dignitate qui dixit, sed ita uultus habitū temperet, ut aut non audisse, aut certe non intellexissi uideatur. Mulieres ornat silentium, sed magis pueritiam. Quidam respondēt, pr
                     •
                  usquam orationem finierit qui compellat, ita saepe 
                     •
                  it, ut aliena respondens sit risui, det
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ueteri locum prouerbio 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , id 
                     •
                  st, falces petebam,

alius non intelligens negabat se habere scaphas, respondens quod nihil ad rem atti
                  
                     •
                  eret. Vide prouerbi. Docet 
                     •
                  oc Rex ille sapientissimus, stultitiae tribuens, respōdere priusq audias: non audit autem, qui non intellexit. Sin 
                     •
                  inus intellexit percōtantē, paulisp
                     •
                  r obticescat, donec 
                     •
                  lle quod dixit sponte repe
                  
                     •
                  at. Id si nō facit, sed respō
                  sum urget, blāde ueniā praefatus puer, oret ut quod dixe rat, dicat denuo. Intellecta percōtatione, paululū interponat morae, deinde tum pau 
                     •
                  is respondeat, tum iucunde. In cōuiuio nihil effutiendū, quod offuscet hilaritatem. Absentiū famam ibi laedere, plac
                     •
                  lū est. Nec cuiquā illic suus refricandus est dolor. Vituperare quod appositum e
                     •
                  t, inciuilitati datur, &amp; in
                  
                     ••
                  atum est conuiuatori.

                  
                     •
                  i de tuo praebetur conuiuiū, ut excusare tenuitatē apparatus urbanum, ita laudare aut cōmemorare quāti constiterint, insuaue profecto condimentū est accumbentibus. Deni
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   si quid à quoq in cōuiuio fit rusticius per imperitiā, ciuiliter dissimulandū potius q irridendū. Decet compotationē libertas. Turpe est, sub dium, ut ait Flaccus, rapere, si quid cui super coenam excidit incogitātius
                     •
                   Quod ibi fit diciturue, uino inscribendū, ne audias 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   (id est, odi memorē cōpotorē. Vide prouerbi.) Si cōuiuiū erit q pro puerili aetate ꝓlixius, &amp; ad luxū tendere uidebitur, simulat
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   senseris naturae factum satis, aut 
                     •
                  lā, aut ueniā precatus, te subducito. Qui pueri
                  
                     •
                  em aetatē adigūt ad inediā, 
                     •
                  ea quidē sentētia insaniūt,

ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   multo minus ij q pueros 
                     •
                  mmodico cibo diffarciunt. Nam ut illud debilitat teneri corpus cult uiriculos, ita hoc 
                     •
                  nim
                     •
                   u
                     •
                  m obruit. Moderatio tamē statim discēda est. Citra plenā saturita
                     •
                  ē r
                     •
                  siciendū est puerile corpus, magis
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   crebro q copiose. Quidam se saturos nesciūt, nisi dum ita distentus est uentriculus, ut in periculū ueniant, ne dirūpatur, aut ne per uomitū reijciat onus. Od
                     •
                  runt liberos q illos et
                     •
                  amnū teneros coenis in multam noctem productis perpetuo sinūt ass
                     ••
                  ere. Ergo si surgendū 
                  
                     •
                  rit à prolixiore cōuiuio, quadrā 
                  
                     •
                  uā cū reliquij
                     •
                   tollito, ac salutato qui uidetur inter cōui uas honoratissimus mox &amp; 
                     •
                  lijs s
                     •
                  mul, discedito, sed mox redditurus, ne uideare lusus aut alterius parum honestae rei gratia, te subduxisse.

Reuersus, ministrato s
                     •
                   
                  qd opus erit, aut reuerēter mensae assistito, si quis quid iubeat expectans. Si quid apponis, aut submoues, uide ne cui uestem iure perfundas. Candelam emuncturus, prius illā 
                  
                     •
                   mēsa tollito, quod
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   emunctū est, protinus aut haren
                     •
                  e immergito, aut solea proterito, ne quid ingrati nidoris offendat nares. Si quid porrigis, infundisue, leua id 
                     •
                  a
                  
                     ••
                  as caueto. Iussus agere gratias, compone gestus, parat
                     •
                  
                  ̄ te significans donec s
                     ••
                  ētibus conuiuis, dicendi tempus ad fuerit. Interim uultus ad cō
                  uiuio praesidentē reuerent
                     •
                  r uersus sit &amp; constanter.
            
            
               De congressibus.
               Si quis occurrerit ī 
                  
                     ••
                  a, uel senio uenerādus, uel religiōe reuerēdus, uel dignitate grauis, uel a
                        •
                     ioq dignus honore,

meminer
                     •
                  t puer de u
                     •
                  a decedere, reuerenter aperire caput, nonnihil etiā flexis poplitibus. Ne uero si cogitet, quid mihi cū ignoto, quid cū nihil unq bene de me merito? Non hic honos tribuitur homini, nō meritis, sed deo. Sic deus iussit per Solomonē, qui iussis assurgere cano, si per Paulū 
                  q presbyteris duplicatū honorē precipit exhibere, in summa, omnibus praestare honorē 
                  qbus debetur honos, cōplectens etiā ethnicū magistratū: &amp; si 
                     •
                  urca, quod absit, nobis imperet, peccaturi 
                     •
                  imus, si honorē magistratui debitum illi negemus. De parētibus interim nihil dico, qbus secundū deū primus debetur honos. Nec minor praeceptoribus, q mentes hoīm quodāmodo dū formant, generāt. I
                     •
                   &amp; inter aequales il 
                     •
                  ud Pauli locū habere debet,

honore inuicē praeuenientes. Qui parē aut inferiorē praeuenit, nō ideo 
                     •
                  it ipse minor, sed ciuilior, &amp; ob id honoratior. Cū maioribus reuerenter loquendū &amp; paucis, cū aequalibus amāter &amp; comiter. Inter loquendū pileū laeua tencat, dextra leuiter admota umbelico, aut quod decētius habetur, pileū utra
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   manu iuncta suspensum, pol
                  
                     •
                  icibus eminētibus, tegat pubis locū. Librū aut galerum sub axilla tenere rusticius habetur. Pudor ad sit, sed qui decoret, non q reddat atto
                  
                     •
                  itū. Oculi spectent eum cui loqueris, sed placidi simplices
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , nihil procax improbū
                  ue pre se ferentes. Oculos in terrā deijcere, quod faciunt catoblepae, male conscientiae suspitionē habet. Transuers
                     •
                  m tueri, uidetur auersantis. Vultū huc illuc 
                     •
                  oluere,

leuitatis argumentū est. Indecorū est interim uultum in uarios mutare habitus, ut nūc corrugetur nasus, nūc cōtrabatur frons, nunc attollatur superciliū nūc distorqueantur labra, nūc diducatur os, nūc prematur, haec aīum arguūt Proteisimilē. Indecorū &amp; illud, concusso capite iactare comā, sine causa tussire screare, quē admodū &amp; manu scabere caput, scalpere aureis, emūgere nasū, demul cere faciem, qd est u
                     •
                  luti pudorē abstergenti
                     •
                  , suffricare occipilū, humeros adducere, qd in nōnullis uidemus 
                     ••
                  alis. Rotato capite negare, aut reducto accersere, &amp; ne per sequar oīa, gestibus ae
                     •
                   n
                     •
                  tibus loqui, ut uirū interdum deccat, puerū minus dicet. Illiberale est iactare brachia gesticulari digitis, uacillare pedibus, breuiter non lingua,

                  
                     •
                  ed toto corpore loq, qd turturū esse fertur, aut motacillarū, nec multū abhorrēs à picarū moribu
                     •
                  . Vox sit mollis ac sedata, nō clamosa, qd est agricolarū, nec tā pressa, ut ad aures eius cuiloqueris nō ꝑueniat. Sermo sit non praeceps, &amp; mētē praecurrēs, sed lentus &amp; explanatus. Hoc etiā naturalè batarismū, aut haesitantiā, si nō in totū tollit, certe magna exparte mitigat, quū praecipitatus sermo mul
                  
                     •
                  is uitiū cōciliet, qd nō dederat natura. Inter colloquēdū subīde titulū 
                  
                     •
                  onorificū eius quē appellas repetere ciuilitatis est. Patris ac matris uocabulo nihil honorificētius, nihil dul
                     •
                  lus. Fratris sororisue no
                     •
                  e, nihil amabilius. Si te fugiunt tituli peculiares, oēs cruditi sūt tibi, praeceptores obseruādi, oēs sacerdotes, ac monachi, reuerendi patres,

omnes aequales, fratres &amp; a mici, breuiter o
                     •
                  
                  ̄s ignoti dn̄i, ignote dn̄ae. Ex ore pueri turpiter auditur iusiurandū, siue iocus sit, siue res seria. Quid enim turp
                     •
                  us eo more, quo apd nationes quasdā ad tertiū quod
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   uerbū deierant etiā puellae, ꝑ panē, per uinū, per candelā, ꝑ quid nō? Obscoenis dictis, nec linguā praebeat ingenus puer, nec aures accōmodet. Deni
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   
                  quicqd in honeste nudatur oculis hoīm indecēter ingeritur auribus. Sires exigat, ut aliquod mē, brū pudendū nominetur, circū
                  
                     •
                  tione u
                     •
                  recūda rē notet. Rursus si quid inciderit, qd auditori nauseā ciere possit, u
                     •
                  lut si quis narret uomitū, aut latrinā, aut oletū, praefetur honorē auribus. Si quid refellendum erit, caue dicat: haud uera praedicas, praesertī 
                  
                     •
                  i loquatur grādiori natu,

sed praefatus pacē, dicat: m
                     •
                  
                  bi secus narratū est a tali. Puer ingenuus cum nemine cōtentionē suscipiat, ne cum aequalibus quidem, sed cedat potius uictoriā, si res adiurgiū ueniat, aut arbitrū prouocet. Ne cui se praeferat, ne sua iactet, ne cuiusq i
                     •
                  stitutū reprehendat, aut ullius nationis ingenium mores ue 
                     •
                  uggillet, ne qd arcani creditū euulget, ne nouos spargat rumores, ne cuius obtrectet famae, ne cui probro det uitiū natura insitū. Id enim non solū cōtumeliosū est &amp; inhumanū, sed etiam stultū. Veluti si quis luscū appellet luscū, aut loripedē loripedē, aut strabū strabū, aut nothū nothū. His rationibus f
                     •
                  et, ut sine inuidia laudē inueniat, &amp; amicos paret. Interpellare loquentē 
                  anteq fabulam absoluerit, inurbanum est.
               
                  Cū nemine s
                     •
                  multatē suscipiat: comitatē exhibeat oībus ꝑ paucos tamē interiorē familiaritatē recipiat, eos
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   cū de lectu. Ne cui tamē credat qd tacitū uelit. Ridiculum enim est, ab alio silentij fidē expectare, quā ipse tibi non praestes. Nullus aūt est adeo linguae continētis, ut nō 
                  
                     •
                  abeat aliquē, in quē trans
                     •
                  ūdat arcanū. Tutissimū aūt est nihil admittere, cuius te pudeat si proferatur. Alienarū r
                     •
                  rum ne fueris curiosus, &amp; si qd forte cōsp
                     •
                  xeris, audieris u
                     •
                   fac quod scis nescias. Literas tibi non oblatas limis intueri, parū ciuile est. Si 
                     •
                  ors te praesente scriniū suū aperit aliqs, subducito te. Nā inurbanum est inspicere: contrectare aliqd in
                     •
                  rbanius. Item si senseris inter aliquos secretius oriri colloquium, submoue te dissimulanter,

&amp; in huiusmodi colloquium ne 
                     •
                  emet ingeras nō accitus.
            
            
               DE LVSV.
               In lusibus liberalibus adsi
                     •
                   alacritas, absit puicacia rixarum parens, absit dolus, ac mendaciū. Nā ab his rudimē
                  tis prosicitur ad maiores in
                  
                     •
                  urias. Pulchrius uincit q c
                     •
                  
                  dit cōtentioni, q qui palmam obtinet. Arbitris ne reclamita. Si cū impitoribus certamē est, possis
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   semꝑ uincere, nōnunq te uinci patere, quo ludus sit alacrior. Si cum inferioribus luditur, ibi te superiorē esse nescias. Animi causa ludendū est non lucri gratia. Aiūt puerorū indolē 
                  nusq magis apparere, q inlu su. Si cui ad dolos, ad mēdaciū, ad rixā, ad uioletiā, ad arrogantiam ꝓpensius ingenium, hic emicat naturae uicium. Proinde puer ingenuus

non minus in ludo, q in conuiuio sui s
                     •
                  milis sit.
            
            
               De cubiculo.
               In cubiculo laudatur silē
                  
                  
                     •
                  iū &amp; uerecūdia. Certe clamor &amp; garrulitas indecora est, multo magis in lecto. Siue cū exuis te, siue cū surgis, memor uerecundiae: caue ne quid nudes aliorū oculis, qd mos &amp; natura tectū esse uoluit. Si cū sodali lectum habeas cōmunē, quietus iaceto, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   corporis iactatione, uel t
                     •
                  ipsū nudes, uel sodali detractis palijs si
                     •
                   molestus. Priusq reclines corpus in ceruical, frontē &amp; pectus signa crucis imaginae, breui precatiūcula temet Christo cōmendans. Idē facito quum mane primū temet 
                     •
                  rigis, à precatiuncula diē auspicans: Non 
                     •
                  nī potes ab omine feliciore. Simul ac exoneraueris aluū,

ne quid agas, nisi prius lota facie manibus
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , &amp; ore proluto. Quibus contingit bene nasci, his turpe est generi suo non respōdere moribus. Quos fortuna uoluit esse plebeios, humiles, aut etiam rurestres, his impēsius etiam adnitendū est, ut qd sors inuidit, morū elegātia pensēt. Nemo sibi parētes, aut patriam eligere potest: at ingenium, mores
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   sibi quis
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   potest fingere. Colophonis uice addā praecepciūculā, quae mi
                     •
                  i uidetur propemodū primo digna loco. Maxima ciuilitatis pars est quū 
                  nusq delin quas, aliorum delictis facile ignoscere: nec ideo sodalem minus habere charū, si quos habet mores inconditior
                     •
                  s. Sūt enim qui morū ruditatē, alijs cōpensēt dotibus. N
                     •
                  
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   haec ita praecipiūtur, quasi sine his nemo bonus esse possit.

Qoud s
                     •
                   sodalis per inscitiā peccet, in eo sanè qd alicuius uidetur momenti, solū ac 
                     •
                  lāde monere ciuilitatis est.
               Hoc quicquid est muneris 
                     •
                  ili chariss. uniuerso puerorū sodalitio per te donatū esse uolui, quo statim hoc cōgiario, simul &amp; cōmilitonū tuorum animos tibi cōcilies, &amp; illis liberaliū artiū, ac morū studia cōmendes. Praeclaram indolētuam Iesu benignitas seruare dignetur, seper
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   in melius proue
                     •
                  ere. Datū apud 
                     •
                  riburg. Brisgoiae, Mē
                  se Mar. An. M.D.XXX.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            ¶Thus endeth this lytell booke of good maner
                  •
               : Imprinted at London in the Flete strete / at the sygne of the Sonne / by wynkynde worde. The yere of our lorde god .M.CCCCC.xxxii. the .x. daye of Septēbre.
            
         
         
            
            
               
                  wynkyn worde
               
            
            
         
      
   

