
   
      
         
            A brieue admonition vnto the nowe made ministers of Englande wherein is shewed some of the fruicte of this theyr late framed fayth: made by Lewys Euans student in Louain. 24. Aug. 1565.
            Evans, Lewis, fl. 1574.
         
         
            
               1565
            
         
         Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00455
            STC 10589
            ESTC S101784
            99837587
            99837587
            1919
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00455)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1919)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 378:25)
         
         
            
               
                  A brieue admonition vnto the nowe made ministers of Englande wherein is shewed some of the fruicte of this theyr late framed fayth: made by Lewys Euans student in Louain. 24. Aug. 1565.
                  Evans, Lewis, fl. 1574.
               
               [32] p. : ill.  
               
                  Typis Æ. Diest.,
                  Antverpiæ :
                  M.D.LXV. [1565]
               
               
                  Signatures: A-B.
                  Running title reads: An admonition vnto the nowe made ministers of Englande.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-09
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-10
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2004-10
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A brieue Admonition
vnto the nowe made
Ministers of Englande:
Wherein is shewed some of the
fruiete of this theyr late framed
fayth: Made by Lewys Euans student
in Louain. 24. Aug. 1565.
            IOAN. 8.
            Vos ex patre Diabolo estis,
&amp; desideriis patris vestri
vultis obsequi.
            Ye are of your father the deuyll,
and the lustes of youre father
yowe wyll doe.
            ANTVERPIAE
TYPIS AE. DIEST.
M.D.LXV.
         
         
            
            
               
            
            The heretikes indeuoure is, by al the meanes they may,
            The memorie of Christ his death, to we and put away:
            And therefore his Crosse, and howe he dyd dye
            To take out of sight, all shameles, they trye.
            But thowe that arte Christian, of Christ his death see
            The passion here printed, as picture to thee.
         
      
      
         
            
            An Admonicion vnto the
nowe made Ministers
of Englande.
            
               WHEREAS yf I had nowe
sett furthe (according as in
my laste translacion I promysed)
to the vewe and
sight of all men, the manie
and sundrie misdemeanour and enormities,
wherwith I can and may most iustlie
accuse and charge yowe: Yf I had
(I saye) therewith sett furthe your names,
then I neaded not to dowbte, but
that your owne doinges, had fullie enforced
anie true meaning or indifferent
man, to marvaile at your more then shamefull
outerage, to dowbte your doctrine,
to mystruste your teachinges, and at
the leangth (not without a iuste cause)
to followe the perfecte fayth of Christe
his Catholyke churche. But, notwithstanding
that I dyd vnderstande and see,
thys waye to be bothe sure and readie,

to rase out from mens hartes the horrible
bloattes, and infection of heresyes,
which in thys our vnhappie tyme, to the
consusion of manye, raygneth with furie
and rage througheout the Realme and
countreys of England: (For, what can
sooner deface vntrue doctrine, then the
detecting of the teachers tyrannous intent,
peruerse purposse, most lewde lyfe,
and more then past impudent an arrogancie?)
Foxe his martyrs were suche fylthie lyuers: as one of theyr nowe preachers was moued to say this of theim: that onles they recanted their synne at the very stake, he was sure they were in hell. Yet, because the factes of some
of yowe, be so dishonest, so detestable,
and so to be hated, as yf your names were
noted in deede, and that they people dyd
once perceaue yt: ynoughe were yt to
drive yowe (yf you be subiecte to any shamefastenes)
in desperacion all lewdelye
to leade and end the remnaunte of your
wreached most woefull lyfes. for thys
cause, I wyll omytte at thys tyme your
names. I will not muche speake of your
priuate deedes and offences.
            Onelye in this briefe treatyse will I trauayle
(lyke a freind) to pulle yowe out

of the clammye claye: wherein your feete
be founde of so long a tyme thus fast.
I will indevour with gentle doinges to
deliuer yowe from thys poreblinde disease,
which so dreadefullye dothe cumber
yowe. And I will trye, whether anye
of yowe recanting from his cursed doctrine,
will in tyme wyselie beware the
euerlasting shame, which otherwise yow
must of necessitie sustayne, to your vtter
and most woorthye defacing foreuer.
For, in case I perceaue yow styll to stand
in your selfe will wanton newe fonde
faythe and waye: I shall be then forced
(for some further admonicion vnto the
people) to sett furthe your names, your
habitacions, the faultes and haynous crimes,
wherewyth I wyll but all truelye accuse
yowe, and also the tyme, the place,
and the personnes, which shall make for
the manifest testimoniall and proofe of
the trothe: which thing (I am sure) yowe
wolde be right sorye to see in printe, and

so published to your perpetuall deserued
reproache. But, there be of yowe peraduenture,
which do litle thinke, that I can
be pryevie to anye poincte of your peruerse
lyfe and behaviour: or at the leaste
doe suppose yt impossible, that I should
haue the full vnderstanding of all your
vnbrydeled beastlynes and follye. In deede,
althoughe that muche of your illaudable
lyfe must needes be vnto mee vnknowen:
Yeat, so muche thereof I am
pryevie vnto, as (truste vnto yt) ys hable
to move and bring anye honest harted
man, to abhorre and myslyke all your licencious,
lewde, and ouerstreached learning.
And yf you wyll knowe, howe I cam
vnto the knowlaige thereof: yt was by
theym of your owne syde, of your owne
sectes, counsaill, and profession, it was
they which wroughte you this woe, vtterered
you outerage, declared your coū
               sailles,
and betrayde the whole effecte of
your vngodlye tryckes and noughtynes.

Now then, yf that vnto me (whoe sholde
knowe least the fruicte of your long laboured
for licencious libertie) suche and
so muche of your disordered dealinges is
made manifest and detected: how thinke
you of others? how muche knoweth other
men? what say you vnto those which
dwell in the other parties of Englande?
do not they likewyse perceaue the vnlaufull
lyuing of your brethern there? yeas
no dowbte. For whether you goe or ryde,
trauaill or reast, what cōpanie soeuer
you keepe, you shall here nothing but of
the noughtynes of these newe Ministers.
All folkes will straight fall to complayne
on the ryotte, ambiciō, auarice, and meere
cruell desyre of Ministers. so that yf you
whiche be Ministers woulde trauayll by
lande or by sea, your selves sholde surelie
here your owne synfull trespasses all trulye
tolde and vttered. For, whereas sometimes
men trauayling accustomed by telling
of hystories and tales, to auoyde the

wearinesse of theyr long wayes and iourney:
in these dayes they haue none other
newes, nor anye other historie, then the
telling of the madde touches of Ministers,
in so muche, that whether he be a
childe, a yong man, of middle age, or aged:
he is sure able to saye, that this Minister,
or that Minister, hathe commytted
thys vyle deede, or that, and one michiefeous
facte, or an other. Moue further to
anye man the misfortune and calamitye
of this present age, wherein, if wee cōfesse
the trothe, we doe rather lynger then
lyue, expresse the imperfection of men,
complaine vpon the wante of vnitie and
peace, sett furthe the fayle and decaye of
charitie, honest loue, and true freindship,
tell the vntrothe, vnfaythefulnes, and vncharitable
shiftes now vsed, yea, bewraye
the whole woe of thys wreached and vnfortunate
tyme: And then yf you inquire
for the cause of all suche our vncompfortable
estate, yt wilbe aunswered, that this

wrye wicked and false religion hathe fettered
vs in the myddest of all these miseries,
that these here &amp; there newe folyshe
professed opiniōs haue imprisoned vs in
suche sundrie puddells of painefull distresse,
and that the newe fatched from
Geneua faith hath mingled our quiete estate
&amp; safetie, with these sought out sectes
of warre, rebellion, schismes, sedicion, and
disobedience. Ys such therefore (o preachers)
the credyte, which you haue purchased?
and is suche the shamefull lowse
lyfe, whiche your preaching vnperfecte
maintayneth? Yea, yea, suche is the holynes
of all your whole professed protestancie,
and suche is the shame, which of
necessytie must ensue and followe you
for the same. This your fayned religion
is not yet full seauen yeares of age, and
for all that, see what a defourmed babe
alreadie it is, beholde what wickednes yt
committeh, and marke what detestable
doinges yt practyzeth. yt perswadeth the

people against theyr Prince, the youthe
against their parentes, seruantes against
their superiours and maisters, one realme
against an other, and whole Chrystendome
against Christe. But in thys, our
made Ministers can reioyce and triumphe,
tearming yt most vngodlye, to be
the Ghospell: whereas in deede, there
neaded no better argument to proue yt
to be, as yt ys, high mynded pestiferous
pleasante heresye: then the readynes of
selfewill youthe, and delicate vnpainefull
personnes to runne so rashelie to imbrace
yt: for from labour vnto luste, from prayer
vnto contempte and pryde, and from fasting
vnto lowse libertie and feasting, wee
see the peruerse nature of man to be ouer
prone and reade. I remember the talke
(as it is written) betwene Socrates the
famous philosophier and Theodota the
bewtiefull queane, she tolde hym that she
was able at anye tyme to allure vnto her
al his schollers &amp; studētes in philosophie:

affirming, that Socrates colde not wythe
all his learning, perswade anie one of her
companions and louers vnto hym. It is
truthe, sayd Socrates, &amp; no meruail, seing
thowe doest drawe theym in a downe
hyll pathe into pleasure: and I compell
theym to clyme vnto vertue, wherevnto
the waye and clyming is highe and full of
difficultie in likewise what wonder is it,
yf manie a thowsande doe nowe thicke
and threefolde, fall from vertue the teaching
of the Catholyke churche, into vice
the verye whyrlepoole of the protestaciō
of heretykes? The Apostle of Chryste
S. Pieter,2. Pet. 2. dyd hym selfe long sythence,
in most playne woordes expresse the same,
saing: Superba enim vanitatis loquentes▪
pelliciunt in desideriis carnis luxuriae, eos
qui paululum effugiunt, qui in errore conuersantur:
libertatem illis promittentes, cùm
ipsi serui sint corruptionis, &amp;c. that ys to say,
For when they haue spoken the swelling
wordes of vanitie, they beguyle throughe

wantōnes, throughe the lustes of the fleashe,
theym whiche were cleane eskaped:
but now are wrapped in errours, they promyse
theym libertie, and are theym selfes
the bonde seruantes of corrupcion, &amp;c.
So nowe in these later dayes, when yowe
(which vsurpe preaching) haue prated
and sett furthe your owne foolish and (as
God doth knowe) inconstante fancies:
thē yowe prouoke and allure others into
the selfe same pitte of deathe and damnacion:this draweth a nomber of doting olde heades, &amp; yong boyes to be of their damnable doctrine.
offering theym the like fruicion
of the luste of the filthie fleashe. And promysing
vnto Priestes, Moonkes, and manye
others, whoe sometimes lyued in sinceritie
&amp; godlines, an open gate into all
vngodlie desire and vanitie: and that in
suche wyse, as what poore Prieste soeuer
dothe at this tyme lyue within the lurche
of your iniunctions and tyrānie, the same
ys not compted honest zelous, nor earnest
in faythe, onles he be clogged with
a queane, to carie him all headlong into

hell. So that the poore man, which lyued
of a long time in chastitie and perfection,
is nowe compelled to compasse the loue
of some light damosell, to leade with her
a loytering detestable lyfe, and so to byd
farewell vnto all his former faythe, promyse,
and fidelitie. Wherefore, may wee
not most iustlie with Seneca saye? Vincit
sanctos dira libido. Vengible or cruell luste
ouercommeth the holye men. Forther,
may wee not adiudge by this oure tyme,
the sayng of Marcus Antoninus Emperour
of the Romaines, to be all ryghtlie
spoken for truthe? whoe alleaged it ouer
harde for anye man, hauing immoderate
libertie, to rule the brydell and rayne of
his raging appetites and lustes. But here
some of yowe will saye, Why? and were
not manie of the Priest yuell in the olde
tyme? Admytte (yf anie to your knowelaige
were) some so to be, and yet, that
shall make nothing to mayntayne your
noughtines. For in those dayes to punishe

suche lewde lyuers as yowe, there were
streight and laudable lawes established, as
the bookes thereof, yf you wolde impudentlie
denye yt, can yet testifie. So that
feare then forced fowle lyfe to flye into
corners, and to forsake the face of the streates
and howses: but nowe puritie of lyuing
is cleane putte awaye, chastitie is
shaken in sunder, the lawes to punish leacherie
is layde vnder foote, vertue is coū
               pted
but a varlat, incōtinencie is creapte
vp and mayntayned in maried Moonkes,
Priestes, and Ministers howses. Also then
the spiritualtie were spirituall and shamefast,
now they be laye men and shameles.
Then they were learned and laudablie instructed
in liberall sciences, nowe they are
rude vnlearned, and for the most parte
but poore labourers of handie craftes.
Then they were deuoute and diuines, but
nowe they haue neyther deuocion nor diuinitie.
Yowe your selfes (o Ministers)
doe knowe, that the most parte of youe

be onlie throughe meere pouertie thus
compelled to putt your selfes so rashelie
in these disordered orders, &amp; youe which
haue consumed and riotouselie wasted
your welthe and goodes, are nowe glad
to professe a peruerse doctrine, thereby
to drawe into some abilitie for to wade
with the worlde agayne. Yf that in anie
paryshe (a pietiefull thing to heare) there
was any pastthrifte and rashe mate which
colde but reade, such an vnrulie runneagate
is nowe, not onlye, in the churche a
reader, but also (which thing passeth all
impudencie) a preacher and a pulpitte
possessor in the holye howse of God.
(I meane in the howse which once was
holye, and rightlie reuerenced throughe
out the Realme of England, but nowe
defaced, and against all godlynes prophaned.)
I knowe my selfe suche as, hauing
forsaken theyr handieworke and former
trade of lyuing, haue afterwardes laboured
to reade, that then they might be Ministers,

               &amp; readers. I know theym who, hauing
some skyll in reading, haue rashelie
forsaken their maisters seruices, &amp; so that
haue not onelye sought thus vnorderlie
for orders, but also which haue obtayned
the same. I know theym who, (being delyuered
out of the Bushoppes pryson,
and whose handes, before the temporall
Iudge, of the yron and fyre haue sufficientlye
fealte.) haue notwithstanding
strayght passed into the next Diocesse,
and there desyryng orders, were furthe
with there charged with the cure &amp; charge
of soules.
            Agayne, yf you marke the yong sorte of
newe made Ministers, you shall fynde in
theym suche follye and pryde, suche wilfullnes
and wantonnes, that woefull yt is
to heare yt. they be in theyr attyre and
apparaill so rooffed, welted, iagged and
stytched, as meeter to be ministrels then
of the ministery. These doe no sooner attayne
this one newe onelye order, but

then busylie seeke they for some bassing
gyrle to make vpp theyr newe godlynes:Mete yōg men, for suche amadde faythe.
they labour so hardelie to gett theym a
huswife, as be she good or bad, vertous or
a varlat: they passe not, this is the ende
of theyr studie, this is it which they seeke,
and this is theyr summum bonum, theyr
chiefe felicitie. Seeke further, what your
grauest fathers and newe named Bushoppes
haue bene,these newe Bushoppes were the basyste sorte of the whole cleargie. and you shall fynde, that
they were the inferiour sorte of the whole
cleargie, that they were for theyr learning
meater to be compared with the laitie,
then with the learned: that they were the
most wantonne lyuers (as by theyr light,
vnaduised, and vnluckie made maraiges
appeareth) amōgest the spiritualtie: that
they were those, for whō the whose cleargie
were accused of incontinencie, that
they were but the riffe raffe amongest the
religious: that they were but truantes in
comparison of the true Catholyke teachers:
that they were the verye worste of

all those which professed Priestehoode &amp;
sanctitie, and that they were but the verye
Dregges of the Diuines and Doctors of
our dayes. Beholde of them some, who
hauing lyued this long tyme without anie
matching in mariage, doe nowe in
theyr olde age fall to suche follye and doting,
as theyr meere madde doinges must
well declare, what kinde of fayth they seeke
to maintayne, and also what maner of
lyfe they heretofore haue leadde.theyr graue fathers be drowned in dotage &amp; dead lye synne. These
be not of theyr simple sortes, for they be
of theyr Bushopes, and they be of theyr
newe godlie, deuoute, and (as the Protestantes
can call theym) most graue fathers.
But is it grauitie for a Bushop with
a graye bearde in his extreme age to waxe
wantōne, and to wade in loue with a light
mayde of his hoaste his kytchynne, with
whom he hathe made suche hast to marye?
I shall not neede to trouble your with
hys name, for the cyttie and countrey doe
well knowe yt. Yet, yf anye farre dweller

hereof doe dowbte, let hym truste, that it
is as true: as that BATHE and WELLES
be within one Bushopryke.Such wantonnesse in the yowth is wicked: but in such olde men, yt ys more then detestable. Is it grauitie
agayne for a man in yeares more thē fowrscore,
a man being a Preacher, and once
aswell as the best a mocke Bushoppe, after
the buryeng of his late bedfellowe &amp;
wyfe, to fall to lasciuire of freshe, to seeke
a yong woman to woe, and to marye one
who for her yeares, were meter to be hys
niece or mayde, then wyfe and mate?
And is it also grauitie, for one taken to be
the profoundest clearke of theyr companye,
who lead hys lyfe hethervnto in studie,
and (as some doe thinke) in chastitie,
nowe hauing throughe heresie heaped together
great store of welthe in a Bushopryke,
to be as busye in wantonnes as the
best, to gett hym a yong dame to stande
at his studie doore, and so in the myddest
of his newe godlynes to marye? Is this a
signe that they seeke for the Kingdome
of God? dothe thys proue that they pray,

fast, mourne, and lament for theyr offences?
shall wee gather by this, that they be
deuoute, holye, chaste, sighing, and sorowyng
for theyre fynnes? No, no, for yf
they dyd perfectlye eyther praye or faste,He is counted to be none of theyr saythe, which will vse oftentymes to faste.
theyr myndes shold not be vpō suche lasciuous
madnes, and yf they dyd playe the
parte of true Apostles, they colde not be
lead so soone, by suche pestiferous mocions,
from godlynes. For wantonne Venus
passeth not for the cōpanie of mourners,
she flyethe from the headdes which
faste and praye, and she putteth no affiaunce
in suche, who by weeping, sorrowe
and heauynes of mynde, doe make so litle
of the lustes of the fleashe as the true Catholykes
doe. But on the other parte, cō
               cerning
the fathers of this late framed faythe,
yf yowe will aske what they do, then
beleue the wordes of the Apostle, who
of suche, saythe thus: They counte it pleasure
to lyue deliciouselye for a season,2. Piet. 2. spottes
they are and fylthynes lyuing at pleasure,

and in disceaueable wayes, feastyng
with yowe, hauing eyes full of aduoutrie
and that can not cease to synne, beguyling
vnstable soules. &amp;c. Iudge thowe then,
whether our Ministers be not they in deede,
whō S. Pieter in these woordes dothe
plainelye paynte out and blame.All theyr intēt ys, to wallowe in the fylthye lustes of the fleashe. marke
(as he tearmeth yt) the fylthynes and lyuing
at pleasure of our preachers, vnderstande
(as by experience thowe mayste)
whether though he be neuer so olde, and
readie to be receaued into hys graue, that
yet he wolde greadelye goe into the worlde
agayne, a whyle to lyue with his loue
and mate in most wantonne waye. Suche
is the perfection, that springeth from thys
vnperfecte faythe, which theyr owne fancies,
and none ells, hath nowe made and
deuysed. I wold learne of them, and namelie
of hym, whose laste maraige I made
mencion of, what shold nowe moue
hym to marye? seing he draweth nere to
fyftie yeares of age, and hathe euer vntill

this tyme without a wyfe lyued (as men
doe thinke) well inoughe: yet his late doinges
doe declare some dowbte in the matter.
I doe vrge hym the more in this, for
that his owne freindes haue founde faulte
with hym for the same. Lett hym therefor
tell, what dyd rather moue hym nowe, thē
at other tymes heretofore, to fancie and
make sute for a minion and sweete harte?
Is it proper to his protestancie, or belonging
to his Bushopryke? he will say, nay.
what then? It was the spirite that moued
hym. O spightefull spirite, cursed, detestable,
and a most daungerous enemye vnto
the best parte and porcion of man. This
spirite is he, which the Poêtes named Cupido,
and yowe the Englishe Ministers will
neades make it the spirite of God: but tell
the people, of what God? of the God (as
the Poëtes fayne) of fylthie luste, loue,
and lothesome leacherie. of whome Seneca
sayth thus:

                  Deum esse amorem, turpiter vitio sauent,
                  
                     
Finxit libido, quo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      liberior foret,
                  Titulum furori numinis falsi addidit.
               
Which hath this sence:

                  A God lewde loue to be, men fylthlye fauoure vice,
                  Uyle lust dyd faygne &amp; that, he might mē more intice
                  Unto hys rage a title her, of false God dyd deuise.
               
            
            With thys spirite an other of theyr captaynes
was so chased, as no other remedie
remayned, but neades he muste in the
myddest of his new mysterie be maryed:
of whom I had LEVER leaue further to
speake, then to trouble the reader with to
manie of theyr rashe made maraiges. But
ys yt not more then maruayll (all theyr
follye consydered) with what face these
men dare professe anye perfection at all?
may not therfore their impudēcie in pulpittes
be wondered at? which promyseth
the people healthe and saluation, yf
they flye from the Catholykes, and followe
theym. Ah las, where shall they followe
you but to the fyerye lake of hell?
and where will you bring them but to the
bottomeles pytte of dreadeful darkenes?

these men wold haue vs to defye our forefathers,
not to leade theyr lyfes, nor to
walke in theyr vertue and godlynes: not
ceasing in theyr prating sermones most
vngodlye and vnnaturallye to saye, our
fathers be in hell, our fathers be in hell.
Here I cā not suffer, but must neade saye,
O you beastes vnnatural,Who can write to vehement against suche varlates? why will you to
your power deface our holye forefathers,
who dyed in the faythe and true religion
of Christ his Churche? why will you
so peruerselye pronounce thys shameles
sentence against so manie thowsandes of
good men, of Christian vertous and godlye
Kinges? of whome we may surelye
with the Prophete saye: In te sperauerunt
patres nostri: sperauerunt, &amp; liberasti eos.
Ad te clamauerunt,
               Psal. 21. 
               &amp; salui facti sunt: in te
sperauerunt, &amp; non sunt confusi. That ys,
In thee haue our fathers trusted: in thee
haue they hoped, and thowe hast delyuered
them. Vnto the haue they cryede, and
they are made safe: in the they haue trusted,

and are not cōfounded. I reade, that
noble Solon one of the. vij. wyse men of
Grece, being on a tyme demaunded: why
he had not established lawes, to punishe
those which had beaten theyr fathers. Because
(saythe he) I adiudged not anye
suche to be, You may hereby see, howe
that Solon thought yt impossible, that
anye should be so pastgrace as hys father
to beate or in anye wyse to greve.
            But our newe noughtie false preachers
will not sticke so to storme against theyr
fathers:We are vnnatural children, yf we forsake not the cō
                  panie of suche enemyes to our forefathers. as from heaven (yf they colde)
to hale theym downe, into the darke resteles
doungeon of hel. I trowe, yf Solon
were nowe lyving, he wolde surelye ordayne
lawes, to punishe suche lewde vnnaturall
personnes. For is it not more
then vnnatural and lewde, to alleage that
their forefathers and oures, that the Sainctes,
Martyres, and all holye men be holden
in tormentes in hell? whiche thyng
they be eyther dryven to affirme: or els to

deface the chiefest poinctes of their new
bastardlie paynted fayth. For it is against
theyr fancied faythe to mayntayne, that
anie man dyeng in the belefe of the Catholyke
churche (as all our forefathers
haue done) can obtayne heaven, or anye
saluacion of soule. Wherefore (o Protestante)
if anie pietie be planted in thy
breast, thow wilte bewayle the miserie of
so many, as these monstrous Ministers be
rulers ouer, yf anye grace and mercy may
move thee, thowe wilte all hartelie lamēt
the loasse and danger, which the people
of Christe be in, And also if there be but
one iote of anye gentlenes or iustice in
thyne harte, thowe wilte haue some indifferencie
to deale withe and to iudge
these thinges. Playe therefore nowe the
worthie parte of Pericles the noble and
valiaunte Captayne of the Athenienses,
vse here his iustice, and with hym saye,
Oportet me amicis accommodare, sed vsque
ad aras. say thow, I must incline vnto my

frendes, the Protestantes, saving my conscience.
Let nowe thy conscience cause
in the some consideracion of honestie,
and then no dowbte the pleasante pestiferous
doctrine of heresye must needes
displease thee: whiche doctrine the elder
that yt ys, the more rotten and fylthie
fruicte yt bearethe. Yt ys a doctrine by
the dyvel devised to snare and delude the
corrupte companie of youthe and others,
who willingelie wold walke in the overlarge,
wicked, &amp; pleasaunte way of theyr
most poysoned appetites. For as Sathan
sometymes on the highe mountayne and
hyll toppe, dyd assaye to tempte our Sauiour
Christe: saing, (after that he had
shewed hym the whole dominion of the
worlde) Haec omnia tibi dabo, si cadens adoraueris
me, &amp;c. that is, All these things will
I give the, if thow wilte falle downe and
worshipp me, &amp;c. So now in this valey or
dale of miserie, he mischievouselye with
the lyke intycementes compasseth, also to

tempte the Christians, saing: The pompe
of the world, the freedome of the fleashe,
riches, power, welthe, wyves, Bushopprykes,
deanries, beneficies, and authoritie: al
these thinges wil I give you, if you imbrace
and sett furthe my faythe, fancie, and
cōmaundementes: and yf you wil be my
disciples, fall downe and worshippe mee.
Well, a great companie of good Cathokes
have forsaken al these baytes, Bushop
prykes, benefices, welthe and wyves, and
they have sayd with our Sauiour Christ,
Abi Sathana, auoyde Sathan. But a fewe
peruerse Englishe preachers, they wyll
praye him to make that offer agayn, and
then more heede shall they give vnto his
woordes &amp; promyse. They can say, Mane
Sathana, tarye a while Sathā. Let vs heare
more of thy mynde, and what thow woldest
fayne have vs to fullfyl: so that at the
leangth, with the sweete singing of Sirênes,
they be soone drawē to performe the
worke and desyre of the dyvel. O wicked

man &amp; Minister: see what a foolishe marquete
thow haste made, thow hast loaste
by thys bargayne (without great repentance)
the best substāce that thow hadst:
And if thow wilt beleve the very wordes
of Christe,so that they may haue the companie of their queanes: hell is as fytte for them, as heauen. then shalte thow sure finde yt
to be so. he sayth, Quid enim profuerit, &amp;c.
that ys, For what shall yt profyte a man,
yf he sholde wynne all the whole worlde,
and lowse hys owne soule? Nowe, what
hast thowe gayned by this giwe gawe
welth and pleasure of the worlde, if after
a daye or twoe, thow must for euer in hel
remayne with weeping and gnashing of
teathe, where thy worme dyeth not, nor
the fyre at anye tyme goethe out? And
therfore, thow which lyest in the horrible
lake of heresie, turne vnto God, and forsake
thyne offences▪
               I wishe vnto them, as vnto my selfe. let vs goe boldelye
vnto the seate of grace, that wee may receaue
mercie, and fynde grace to helpe in
tyme of neade. Thys is the malice nowe,
(Ministers) that I owe you: that I wold

wishe you, to putt awaye your iniquities,
and crave pardon at the handes of God,
for this your swarving frō the true fayth,
that your soules may lyve, and that wee
may then together enioye the gladsome
light, and eternall reaste in heauen: ells,
you shal herein earthe sustayne most worthye
infamye and shame for your offences,
and in hell a iuste plague and punishement
for the same.
            Here haue I passed ouer briefelye some
piece of your peruerse practize and behauiour,
&amp; that the more to make you myndefull
of your vngodly estate and degree,
wherin I haue yeat vsed such modestie, as
willinglye I named not one of you. but
now this cometh last into my mynde, that
manye of you beholding this booke, will
bragginglie saye: If that he cold name vs,
he wolde. hereat I staye, and doe somewhat
dowbte, whether it were best to begynne
of newe or not, and of freashe to
sett furthe your names, fylthie factes and

dwellinges. Well, you shall see that I can
doe it, and yeat will not: hoping that whē
you haue forsaken this your fonde fayth,
you may leade a godlie lyfe agayne. But
to preuent your bragg, you dryue me to
vtter the doinges of one or twoe for example
sake: whose proper names notwithstandyng
I will (according vnto my promysse)
omitte. There is one nowe a preacher,
who, being maried, and his wyfe thē
in the towne fyue or six myles westwarde
from London, was takē neuertheles by a
gentle mā, with an other mans wyfe, and
so brought before the iustice, who boūde
hym to appeare before M. Grindall,they leaue theym vnpunished: least yt sholde els deface their doctrine. at
whose handes he receaued none other punishmēt,
thē to be banished out of his diocesse.
This perfect Preacher now dwelleth
foure myles frō Windsor: where he hathe
gotten for his excellent vertue a vicarage.
There is an other, who (according vnto
the saing of Theodorus the Atheman) receaued
diuinitie in his right hande: but

which delyuereth it vnto the people againe
with the leafte. I cā not well leaue out
his name, &amp; yet I am lothe to name hym.
But,Chrsman is sent to preache this newe Ghospell into the countrey / where he is not knowen, which is a shifte now commonly vsed. inquire for the Archedeacō of West
mynster, learne the cause of his departure
thence, aske with what fauour the lawes
went forwarde, whē he eskaped the carte,
which he had deserued, for ventring lyke
a Hardye man so farre with Venus. Thus,
being lothe further towade with your faultes,
onles I be by you pricked and cōpelled:
I wishe vnto yowe suche harte, as may
hate all haynous pleasaūte heresies, vnto
the people suche perfection and pure iudgemētes,
as maye cōtemne your vngodlie
shameles sermones: wherein yow cōpasse
most craftelie to kyll &amp; slea theyr soules,
And I wishe finallie vnto vs all, perfecte
vnitie, charitie, and true loue, that at the
leangth wee maye like breathren lyue
in the euerlasting ioye which neuer
shall ende. Amen.
         
      
      
         
            fol. 5. pro reade, lege, ready. fol. 3. pro yowe
outerage, reade, youre outerage.
            
         
      
   

