
   
      
         
            The triall of true teares. Or the summons to repentance whereby the secure sinner is taught how to escape the terrible sentence of the supreame iudge. Meditated vpon Christes weeping ouer Ierusalem, very necessarie for these present times. By William Est, Maister of Arts, and preacher of Gods Word.
            Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.
         
         
            
               1613
            
         
         Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00408
            STC 10538
            ESTC S118581
            99853788
            99853788
            19184
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00408)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19184)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 577:21)
         
         
            
               
                  The triall of true teares. Or the summons to repentance whereby the secure sinner is taught how to escape the terrible sentence of the supreame iudge. Meditated vpon Christes weeping ouer Ierusalem, very necessarie for these present times. By William Est, Maister of Arts, and preacher of Gods Word.
                  Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.
               
               [4], 91, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Tho. Creede, for Arthur Iohnson, dwelling neere the great north doore of S. Paules Church, at the signe of the white Horse,
                  London :
                  1613.
               
               
                  A treatise on Luke xix.41-1.
                  Running title reads: The tryall of true teares.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XIX, 41-44 --  Early works to 1800.
               Repentance --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-06
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-06
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE TRIALL OF true Teares.
            Or the Summons to repentance; whereby the ſecure ſinner is taught how to eſcape the terrible Sentence of the Supreame Iudge.
            Meditated vpon CHRISTES weeping ouer Ieruſalem, very neceſſarie for theſe preſent Times.
            By William Est, Maiſter of Arts, and Preacher of Gods Word.
            
               2. Cor. 7.10.
               For godly ſorrow cauſeth Repentance vnto ſaluation, not to be repented of.
            
            LONDON, Printed by Tho. Creede, for Arthur Iohnſon, dwelling neere the great North doore of S. Paules Church, at the ſigne of the white Horſe. 1613.
         
         
            
            
            To the Right worſhipfull, the Ladie Elizabeth Greynuile; all happines in this life, and eternall felicity in the life to come.
            HAuing (good Madam) at the vrgent importunitie of ſome of my beſt Friends, reared vp the walls of this ſimple Edifice, as you fee, and fearing (the weakeneſſe therof being ſuch) that it needed ſome ſupport to keepe it from falling: At length my ambiguous thoughts ſeized vpon your worſhips patronage. I haue long regiſtred in my heart a gratefull acknowledgement of your (and my good patrones benefits extended towards mee:) and wanting worthie meanes in reall requittance to expreſſe the ſame; I preſumed (which is all I could) in this dedication to manifeſt. Not forgetting your worthie and Right worſhipfull Father Phillip Beuile, with your vertuous Mother, whoſe bountifull Hoſpitalitie, charitable liberalitie, religious gouernment of their Familie, plainely ſheweth to the worlde, that they hold thēſelues, not borne vnto themſelues, to liue to themſelues, but as good

Stewards of Gods manifold bleſſings, plētifully powred vpō them, to diffuſe the ſame to the good of manie; which (I aſſure you) hath wonne the loue of the rich, the praiers of the poore, and the applauſe and praiſe of all farre and neere in your country. If the reading of theſe my poore Labours at ydle houres may yeeld you any contēt or comfort, it is the thing I wiſh: yet more then I can promiſe, ſaue only in regard of the ſubſtāce. Small (I confeſſe) is the gift in regard of the Author, but great indeed, in reſpect of the worthines of the ſubiect, which (if no thing elſe) I am perſwaded, will giue it good acceptance with the well inclined. Theſe my labours I commit to your worſhips fauorable protection: promiſing that if time &amp; induſtrie ſhall bring forth more mature fruits of my ſtudies (by Gods aſſiſtāce) hereafter, you ſhall alſo bee partakers of them.
            In the meane time, take (I beſeech you) in good part, theſe my well wiſhings to your welfare, and praiers to the Almightie, that he would cōtinue his bleſſings towards you in this life, &amp; after this mortal race run out, grāt you the fruition of his heauenly kingdome.
            
               Your Worſhips, in all dutie deuoted, W. Eſt.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE TRYAL OF TRVE TEARES. OR THE SOMMONS to Repentance.
            
               
                  
                     Luc. 19. verſ 41.42.43.44.
                  
                  
                     Luc. 19. v. 41. And when he was come neere, he beheld the citie and wept for it.
                  
                     42. Saying, O if thou hadſt euen knowne at the leaſt in this thy day, thoſe things which belong vnto thy peace! but now are they hid from thine eyes.
                  
                     43. For the daies ſhall come vpon thee, that thine enemies ſhall caſt a trench about thee, and compaſſe thee round, and keepe thee in on euery ſide.
                  
                     44. And ſhall make thee euen with the ground, and thy children which are in thee, and they ſhall not leaue in thee a ſtone vpon a ſtone, becauſe thou kneweſt not the time of thy viſitation.
               
            
            
               FIrſt, here is expreſſed the occaſion.
               Secondly, the impulſiue cauſes.
               
                  That which miniſtred occaſion to the Lord of this weeping, was the ſight of the citie: verſ. 41.
               The cauſes impulſiue are two: namely two euills, the one preſent, and the other future.
               
                   The preſent euill was, the euill of the minde: to wit, the blindnes of the Citizens: verſ. 42.
               The affirmation of this blindnes, he amplifieth by an antitheſis of a contrarie wiſh or deſire: when he ſaith: Oh that thou haddeſt knowne at the leaſt in this thy day, thoſe things which belong vnto thy peace! &amp;c.
               
               
                   The future euill pertained vnto their bodies,
                     Verſ. 43. &amp; 44. which was the deſtruction of the citie.
               This deſtruction, againe he excellently deliniateth by the partes thereof: and afterward declareth by the impulſiue cauſe, what mooued the Lord thereunto: namely, their ingratitude toward the gratious viſitation of God:
                     Verſ. 44. 
                  becauſe thou kneweſt not the time of thy viſitation.
               
               
                  Hoſanna: ſaue now, a word of ioy, acclamation, or tryumph, the Iewes calſed ſo the willow brā
                     ches which they bare in their hands, at the feaſt of tabernacles.Our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, in the midſt of the pompe and ioyfull acclamations wherewith he was receiued into Ieruſalem, (ſome ſpreading their garments

in the way, others applauding and ſinging a ioyfull Hoſanna to the ſonne of Dauid) was nothing at all cheared and delighted with this ſolemnitie, neither tooke he any pleaſure in the externall glorie and beautie of the citie, nor in their preſent peace, but caſt the eyes of his minde, into that which inwardly lurked: namely, their ſinnes and abhominations,
                     Mat. 21.7 and foreſeeing the ſeueritie of Gods imminent vengeance for the ſame, this louing Sauiour in tender compaſſion, with his holy teares bewailed their ſecuritie, and deſolation at hand.
               1 Firſt for our inſtruction, let vs note here in this firſt verſe. theſe three things.
               That it is ſaid, he came neare to▪ Ieruſalem.
               
               2 That, he beheld the Citie.
               
               3 That he wept for it.
               
               For the firſt, God in his mercie oftentimes commeth neere vnto ſinners obſtinate in their vices and wickednes, that he might irradiate and diſpierce the darkenes of their minds, with the bright beames of his grace and holy inſpirations. This is it our louing God ſaith: Behold I ſtand at

the doore and knocke,
                        Apoc. 3.20. If any man heare my voyce and open the doore, I will come in vnto him, and ſuppe with him▪ and he with me. But ô wretched men and women which neglect ſo great a proffered ſaluation, reiect his diuine inſpirations, ſtoppe the doore of their  hearts againſt ſo ſweet a gueſt, and refuſe to heare his voyce, and giue a deafe eare to his wholeſome admonitions.
               This obſtinacie of the ſinners, and iniurie offered to their Creator, the Prophet bewaileth and denounceth a woe againſt them:Zepha. 3.1. &amp; 2. verſ. 
                  Woe to her that is filthie and polluted, to the robbing citie, ſhe heard not the voyce, ſhe receiued not correction, ſhe truſted not in the Lord, ſhe drew not neere vnto her God. He approached not ſo much with his bodily feete, as with the feete of loue and compaſſion: whereby we are taught to be tender hearted, towards ſuch as are in miſerie: yea, the rich may here learne to come neere the poore and needie, and in a ſympathie and fellow-feeling of their miſeries, to relieue their neceſſities, if they will be true followers of Chriſt.
               
                   Next it is ſaid, that he beheld the citie: O how happie had they bene if they had made vſe of this the Lords beholding them:
                  
ſo he beheld Peter, Zacheus and Mathew,
                  
                     Mat. 26. Luc. 19. Mar. 9. had mercie vpon them and conuerted them, for ſaluation proceedeth from this mercifull beholding of the Lord: his eyes did flowe with tender loue and compaſſion! as contrariwiſe by the turning away of his face proceedeth perdition and all wretchednes: But if thou hide thy face they are troubled, ſaith the Prophet.
                     Pſal 1
                        •
                     4.29. We ought therefore to pray vnto the Lord that he would vouchſafe to caſt his mercifull eyes vpon vs, and ſay with the Princely Prophet:
                     Pſal. 102.
                  Hide not thy face from me in the time of my trouble.
               
               He wept for it: Here are laide open before  vs theſe two attributes and perfections of God: Mercie and Iuſtice, which alwaies goe together coniunction, and hand in hand, in all his workes. His Iuſtice appeared, in that he tooke ſo diſtrict a reuenge vpon that nation for their grieuous ſinnes againſt him. It was his tender mercie in that he wept, and bewailed (a ſigne of his true humanitie) their extreame miſerie and finall deſolation at hand for their wickednes, the fire of Gods wrath alreadie kindled, and the ſword of his heauenly father readie drawne to ſtrike them. His

mercie is ouer all his workes.
                  
                     Pſal. 145.9. The experience hereof wee plainely ſee in this people: How many bleſſings, graces and benefits, out of the inexhauſt treaſurie of his loue beſtowed he on them? he gaue them a lawe, he miraculouſly protected them, he raiſed vp Prophets, Patriarks, and Apoſtles among them, the Meſſias was promiſed and ſent vnto them, they were his peculiar and choſen people of all nations in the world. But ſee now (brethren) the ſeueritie of his iuſtice, and with feeling hearts learne thereby the true feare of the Lord: when they became vngratefull, hard-hearted, diſobedient, deſpiſed his word, perſecuted his Prophets, polluted themſelues with all wickednes: God vtterly reiected them, they finde now the heauens inclement towards them, God to neglect them, and whither ſoeuer they turne themſelues, they are expoſed to the hiſſings, reproaches, and iniuries of all Nations. Without faith, without lawe, without Religion, without Prophet, without Temple, without God, hauing not ſo much as a litle ſpace of the earth alotted them to inhabite, and fortifie themſelues, being deſtitute of all ſuccour. O the ſeueritie of Gods

iudgement againſt ſinne: and why was all this? Becauſe they knewe not the time of their viſitation: As I ſhall (God willing) vnfold at large when I come to the handling of theſe words.
               Whereby it plainely appeareth, that the Lord did not ſo much bewaile the ruine of the ſtrong walles, the ſtately Towers, the gorgeous buildings, the rich ornaments and beautie of that goodly citie, (all which he foreſawe ſhould be vtterly ruinated for their ſinnes:) their ſinnes (I ſay) the cauſe of al miſery, which they made light of, and leaſt thought vpon, did drawe theſe teares from the ſacred eyes of our Sauiour. We ſee ſometimes a mad man, the neerer he is to deſtruction, the more he laugheth and ſporteth: but his deare friends, knowing the danger he is in, weepe and bewaile him the more. This franticke citie when it was neareſt to ſpoile &amp; vtter deſtruction, moſt laughed and reioyced, but Chriſt ſheddeth compaſſionate teares for them, which he would not haue done, if they had lamented and mourned for their owne ſinnes.
               I here obſerue,Obſer. &amp; doctrin. if Chriſt the true eſtimator of things did bewaile the ſinnes of others, how much more ought euery

true feeling Chriſtian heart wiſh with holy Ieremie:
                  
                     Ier. 9.1. 
                  Oh that mine head were full of water, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night, for the maimes and wounds that ſinne hath made in my ſoule, whereby I haue prouoked the wrath of my louing God, and ſtand in daunger of eternall damnation. If the Iſraelites in the captiuitie of Babell ſate and wept by the riuers ſide,
                     Pſal. 137. when they remembred Sion their beloued countrey, ſo that neither the pleaſant riuers, nor the melodious chirping birds, or any other worldly delight, might cheare vp their drooping ſpirits: How much greater matter of ſorrow is miniſtred vnto all impenitent ſinners, if they would but call to minde their infinite and grieuous ſinnes wherby they haue kindled the fire of Gods wrath againſt them, and are holden vnder the miſerable captiuitie of Sathan, Exiles; Not from the Earthly Ieruſalem,
                  The wretched eſtate or impenitent ſinners. but from the Heauenly: not builded with inſenſible, but with liuing ſtones: by the hand of the omnipotent God. This bleſſed Countrey of Gods elect, from which (though all Infidells, Atheiſts, and wicked liuers are baniſhed) yet can it ſuffer no detriment, nor euer be deſtroyed: againſt

which, neither Chaldean, Babilonian,
                  The happie ſecuritie in the heauenly Countrey nor Perſian, nor all the wicked rable are able to caſt a darte, or ſhoot an Arrow, where is heard no ſound of Hoſtilitie, no crackling of Armour, but the inhabitants ſhall reioyce in moſt ſecure peace and pleaſure for euermore.
               Shall the Sonne of God himſelfe weepe, foreſeeing the extreame miſerie that ſinne bringeth vppon the wicked, and ſhall the heart of Man (whome this onely concerneth) bee ſo hard and inſenſible, as not to ſhead one teare of contrition for his ſinnes?
               Oh that wee would conſider the grieuouſnes of ſinne, and the plagues which God hath in ſtore for the ſame, we would then tremble and feare, and ſeeke by repentance to be reconciled vnto God; we would then choſe rather to be an other Heraclitus in weeping and lamenting for our ſinnes,Heraclitus. then Democritus,
                  Democritus. in vaine laughter and reioycing in our ſinnes.
               Oh that men would remember, and with a feeling heart conſider the torments that God hath reſerued for the wicked; I then perſwade my ſelf that vaine delights would haue no place in your hearts. Surely (beloued,) when in the ſecrete ſilence of my

ſoule I meditate hereupon,A wonder-how a wicked man cā be merie. I muſe with my ſelfe, and think it to be a wonder of all wonders, to ſee an Adulterer, Blaſphemer, &amp;c. to laugh, ſing, and ſporte, being in that ſtate wherein nothing but eternall damnation is to be expected, without ſpeedy repētance. If Dioniſius the Tyrant of Siracuſa, could take no delight in his glorie, ſtately pallace, purple Robes,Dioniſius the Tyrant of Siracuſa. coſtly fare, &amp;c: becauſe (as hee ſhewed Damocles his flatterer) he ſtood euer in feare of the Sword. How is it poſſible yt
                   a wicked man or woman can carry a ſerene countenance or a light hart,Damocles his flatterer. hauing ſo many ſwordes from Heauen drawne againſt them?
               This may well bee called (according to the Greek Adage) Bardónios yélos, the laughter of a mad man:Aiax. or, Aiánteos yélos, Aiax his deadly laughter. But truely it is to be lamented, yea, with a Torrent of teares to be bewailed, that the ſubiect of our ſorrowe is commonly the loſſe of temporal things. Many bewaile the loſſe of the Creature, but fewe of the Creator of all.
               One lamenteth the loſſe of his tranſitorie goods,
                     Gen. 27. like prophane Eſau for his birth-right: Another ſorroweth at the loſſe of his Honour, Fame, and worldly credit: as Saul,
                  
who mourned not ſo much for his tranſgreſſion,vaine teares (in diſobeying the voyce of the Lord, the cauſe of all his miſeries) as for the loue of his worldly honor and reputation: and therefore ſaide to Samuell, Honour me I pray thee, before the Elders of my people,
                  1. Sam. 15 30. 
                  and before Iſrael. But all this ſorrowe is vaine and vnprofitable: For though wee powre out teares in neuer ſo great abundance for the loſſe of Parents, Children, Friendes, or Riches, are they to any purpoſe at all?The true &amp; profitable vſe of teares But when (through ſinne wee haue loſt God) if we ſeeke him by the faithfull teares of Repentance, we may finde him againe. This is the onely ende to which all our ſorrowe is to be directed.
               Tell me, if anie hauing ſore Eyes,Similies to ſhew the vanitie of ſorrow for worldly accidents. ſhould haue a precious and approoued water, that would cure all diſeaſes of the eies, &amp; ſhould, neglecting his Eyes, waſh his Feete with the ſame: were he not iuſtly to be reputed a mad-man? So the teares of Repentance, as an wholeſome Medicine, ſerue onely for the ruptures of ſinne: which being beſtowed vpon any worldly thing,Simile. Lactant. d
                        •
                      ira Dei. cap. 13. are altogether vaine, and of no effect. Euen as the aſhes of a burnt Viper, are a preſent remedie againſt the venemous byting of a Viper: So

the ſorrow that proceedeth of ſinne, is a remedy againſt the puniſhment of ſinne paſt, and a Cautele againſt iterating of ſinne.
               If wee highly eſteeme of the Waters of Hearbs and Flowers, which are approoued for the curing of diuers diſeaſes, &amp; wounds of the body: why do we not more eſteeme of the Teares of contrition, more precious then any Balſamum, for the curing of the Woundes and Vlcers of the ſoule?
               Euen as when an houſe is on fire, they that would quenche it, haue their refuge vnto the waters:Simile. So when the flames of wicked deſires are kindled in the ſoule, the teares of Repentance are a ſoueraigne water for the quenching of the ſame. Euen as when a darke Clowd falleth downe into Raine, the Skie becommeth cleare: So a ſinfull ſoule, the clowde of ſinne (through Repentance being diſſolued into Teares) becommeth the more bright and cleere both to knowe God, and it ſelfe.
               This profitable ſorrow, vpon the conſiderations of their ſinnes, was well knowne to the Saints of God, as it appeareth by the frequent vſe thereof, which in Dauid flo
                     •
                  
                  ed, with ſo plentifull a ſtreame, that he ſaide I cauſe my Bed euery night to ſwimme,
                  
                     Pſal. 6.6. 
                  &amp; water

my Couche with my Teares.
               
               Againe,
                     Pſal. 42.3 
                  My Teares haue beene my meate Day and Night.
               
               Oh that God would lighten our mindes with the beames of his holy ſpirite, that we might ſee the filthines of ſinne, &amp; the danger of the ſinner: As a wayfaring man, that in a darkſome night reſteth his weary limbs in a Caue full of Serpents, and ſweetely taketh his reſt miſtruſting no danger: if one ſhould come in with a Torche burning, that hee might ſee the hideous filthie Serpents hiſſing and crawling about him, he would preſently ſtart vp, and take ſmall delight to ſtay in that place: So (if God of his mercie,) would inlighten our hearts with the beames of his Grace, that we might ſee the filthy and vgly face of ſinne, we would not endure the filthines thereof.
               In that our Sauiour wepte in the midſt of the Honours, Ioy, and applauſe of the  multitude, wherewith they receiued him into the Citie: We are taught to contemne the vaine ioyes and pleaſures of the world,Contempt of vaine delights. Pro. 14.13. which are alwayes mixed with ſorrowe, and ſhall (in ſhort time, bee turned into mourning) Extrema gaudij Luctus occupat: The ende of that mirth is heauineſſe. Miſcentur triſtia

laetis. For what elſe are the vaine pleaſures, honours, and delights of the World? but as one ſaieth, Spuma, Fumus, Somnium: A Froth,The pleaſures of this life are but a fome, a ſmoake, a dreame. Smoke, a dreame. A froth or fume, Quia inflat, becauſe it puffeth vp: a ſmoke, Quia excaecat, becauſe it maketh blinde: a dreame, Quia euaneſcit: becauſe it quickly vaniſheth away.
               Here we haue in the Sonne of God himſelfe,A medicine againſt the loue of the world. both an example and an effectuall medicine againſt the loue of the world, and the pompe and glorie thereof, which our common aduerſary laboureth by all meanes to incite and kindle in our harts: For he knoweth wel, that when we are once blinded with this loue, there is nothing elſe to be required; then is there a Doore opened for him to doe what he will.
               And ſurely it is wonderfull to ſee the ſubtilty of this Iugling Impoſtor: for though the glory of the World be moſt fraile, fleeting, and ſhort, deceitfull, and momentany: Yet this pernitious Painter ſo diſguiſeth it with delightſome and Artificiall colours, that men doubt not to vndergoe all extreamities, to leaue no ſinne vnpractiſed, that they may obtaine worldly glorie.
               Here the Diuell ſeemeth to me, to be

like an Excellent Mathematician, which through skill of his Arte Perſpectiue, draweth certaine lines in a Table, with ſuch proportion and cunning, that it ſeemeth to be the trueth of the thing it ſelfe: and if thou 
                     •
                  ooke through his Geometrical Inſtrumēt (called Dioptra,
                  The diuel like a cunning Mathematician.) thou wilt ſuppoſe that there are moſt beautifull formes &amp; figures of ye
                   whole World, whē in very deede there 
                     •
                  s nothing elſe but ſimple and bare Lines: Such is the crafte of this auncient Serpent.
               For when the glorie of this World is a 
                     •
                  hing ſo vaine and vaniſhing, he delinea
                  
                     •
                  eth, and painteth it, with ſuch diſguiſes and ſhadowes vnto the Eyes of worldlings, that 
                     •
                  t ſeemeth moſt amiable and pleaſant vnto 
                     •
                  hem, that being carried away with the deſires thereof, they ſhould looſe their owne ſoules, and vilely eſteeme of whatſoeuer GOD hath promiſed to his faithfull Seruants.
               We need not ſearch farre for examples: behold the great honour the world here gaue to Chriſt, and we ſhall ſee the fallacie 
                     •
                  hereof, which S. Bernard well obſerued,S. Bernard hādling this place, Quis ſperare debeat in in
                     
                        •
                     erto gloriae temporalis, &amp;c. Who would now 
                     •
                  ruſt in the vncertaintie of worldly glorie,

when he ſeeth in him who neuer did ſinne, the Creator of Time, the framer of the whole Fabricke of this World, ſo great an Exaltation, and yet to follow ſuch an Humiliation? For in the ſame Citie, of the ſame people, and at the ſame time; Now to be honoured with ſuch acclamations, and diuine praiſes: And a little while after, to be laden with Reproches, Torments, and deputed among the wicked: This is the end of tranſitory glorie: So farre S. Bernard.
               
               Oh how ſoone had they chaunged their voyces? What a difference is there betwixt this,
                     Luk. 19.38. 
                  Bleſſed is hee that commeth in the Name of the Lord, Hoſannah in the higheſt: And this, a fewe dayes after, Away with him, Crucifi
                        •
                      him. Now the King of Iſrael: And a little while after, Wee haue no King but Caeſar: What a difference was there betweene the greene branches of the Palme, and Oliue Trees, and ſhortly after, Thornes, Scourges, and the Croſſe? Whome now they honoured with their Garments ſpredde in the way: A fewe dayes after, they diſpoyled him of his owne Garments. To Day the Sonne of God: To morrow, A wicked man, leſſe worthy of life then Barabas, a Theefe, a Murtherer? who would now truſt this deceitfull world?
               
                  This is the loue and friendſhip of the world (as one wiſely meditateth:The loue of this world.) The rich man hath many friends, although in truth, riches haue them and not the man: As the aſſe that carried the Egiptian Goddeſſe, had many bowed knees, yet not to the beaſt, but to the burthen: for ſeparate the riches from the perſon, and thou ſhalt ſee friendſhip leaue the man, and follow that which was euer her obiect: while he may commaund, and can either giue or controll, he hath attendance and proffer of loue at all hands: but which of theſe dare acknowledge him when he is going into priſon for debt? Then theſe waſpes which make ſuch muſicke about this Gally-pot, ſhewe plainely that they came for the honie that was in it. This is the miſerie of the wealthie, that they cannot knowe their friends; whereas thoſe that loue the poore man, loueth him for himſelfe. He that would chuſe a true friend, muſt ſearch out one that is neither couetous nor ambitious: for ſuch a one loues but himſelfe in thee. And if it be very rare to finde any not infected with theſe qualities, the beſt way is, to entertaine all, and to truſt fewe.
               
                  May we not iuſtly reproue the follie of greedie worldlings, with theſe words of the Prophet,
                     Eſa. 55. 
                  Wherefore do ye lay out ſiluer, and  not for bread? and your labour without being ſatisfied? What would you ſay of that man, who in the time of famine, when for want of foode he is euen hunger-ſtarued,The follie of worldlings. and hauing a little monie left, ſhould beſtowe the ſame vpon a plume of feathers to weare in his hatte? And is not this the fooliſhnes of the louers of the world, which when their ſoules are euen ſtarued, deſtitute of all vertues and ſpirituall ſuſtenance, ſpendeth their witts, time, and labour, in plotting and plodding, lying and cogging, ſhifting and ſhuffeling, catching and hunting by all vngodly meanes, after the glorie, riches and dignities of this world, and when all is done, what is it but as it were the purſuing of a feather yea,
                     Pro. 23.5. 
                  a thing of nothing as wiſe Salomon ſaith Wilt thou caſt thine eyes, vpon it which is nothing? for riches taketh her to her wings, as an Eagle, &amp; flieth into the heauen. What is this elſe but to weaue the Spiders webbe, as the Prophet truly tearmeth it?
                     Iſai. 59. ve. 4. &amp; 5. 
                  they cōceiue miſchiefe, and bring forth iniquitie. They hatch Cockatrice egges, and weaue the Spider

webbe: Such as is the conception, ſuch muſt needes be the birth.
               The conception of ſinne,The conception and birth of ſin. is here called miſchiefe: or as ſome tranſlations haue ſorrowe. For ſinne indeed when it is conceiued in the ſoule, is but miſchiefe and ſorrowe. Pleaſures ſeeme pleaſant vnto the ſinner whiles he conceiueth them, and how much the more bitter they are indeed, ſo much the more pleaſant they appeare at the firſt: but when the ende commeth which in ſhort time finiſheth all theſe pleaſures, then there is found nothing elſe but ſorrowes, gall, bitternes and miſeries: They hatch the Cockatrice egges: from whence commeth forth the Regulus or Cockatrice,
                  The nature of the Cockatrice. the moſt venimous Serpent of all the reſt: for whomſoeuer he ſtingeth, he falleth into a ſweete ſleepe, and ſeemeth for a while to feele no paine, but rather a pleaſure: in the meane time the poyſon diffuſing it ſelfe into all the bodie, with horrible torment he endeth his life. So the delights and pleaſures of the world do at once inficere, &amp; interficere, infect, and deſtroy: the poyſon is pleaſant, but the ende is death. Next he ſaith, They weaue the Spiders webbe.
               
               
                  Which ſerueth to no purpoſe, there can no garment be made thereof, with what labour and diligence doth the ſpider euen euiſerate her ſelfe to finiſh her worke, and to what purpoſe is all this? to catch a flie: but before ſhe hath had any fruit of her labour, cōmeth a maide with her broome, ſweepeth downe the web, and killeth the Spider. Here ye ſee elegantly expreſſed, the labour, exerciſes, and deſires of the ſinner, in which he ſpendeth himſelfe, and conſumeth his life, and all is but a Spiders web. What cogitations doth the worldling reuolue in his minde, what meanes doth he deuiſe that he may enioy his pleaſures and delights? How many labours and ſweates doe his riches? How many anxieties and cares doe his delights? How many troubles and vexations doe his pleaſures bring with them? But to what ende doe they weaue theſe perplexed webbes
                  ▪ but to catch flies?Couetous men hunt after flies. Nay oftentimes the reward of their labours when their web is finiſhed, is leſſe then a flie: for death is at hand, that diligent ſcopatrix Gods hand-maide, which ſweepeth them and their webbes away, before they haue reaped any fruite of their labour and toyle, and ſo they paſſe to

iudgemēt, to render an account before the iuſt Iudge, for their wicked liues and vniuſt dealing.
               But ſuppoſe the things of this world were ſolide, certaine and conſtant, yet what can the goods thereof profit vs in the time of our greateſt neceſſitie, at the houre of death, and time of giuing account? What profit, I ſay, then will thoſe Idolls bring vs, which all our life long we haue worſhipped? as are all theſe things, in which we repoſe and place our hope and felicitie. Then but too late the vanitie and deceit of all thoſe things which we ſo much eſteeme will appeare.
               The couetous man (as one pithily writeth) is like a Spider, as in this,The couetous man like a Spider. that he doth nothing elſe but lay his nets to catch euery flie, gaping onely for a bootie of gaine; So yet more, in that whiles he makes nets for theſe flies, he conſumeth his owne bowells: So that which is his life, is his death. If there be any Creature miſerable it is he; and yet he is leaſt to be pittied, becauſe he makes himſelfe miſerable. Such as he is I will account him: and will therefore ſweepe downe his webbes, and hate his poyſon.
               
                  Thirdly, by this example of Chriſt, we are taught to bewaile the ſinnes of others, and to haue a feeling of their miſeries. The offences then of our brethren are not to be ieſted at, but to be lamented, if we be Chriſtians indeed: which not onely the example of our Sauiour in this place, but alſo of all holy men and Saints of God may teach vs. We reade that Moſes and the people,
                     Numb. 25.6. 
                  wept before the doore of the tabernacle for the ſinnes of their brethren and children, wherewith they had offended the Lord: So the Apoſtle, bewailed many that had ſinned,
                  
                     2. Cor. 12. verſ. vlt. Phil. 3 18. &amp; 19.
                   
                  and had not repented of the vncleanneſſe, and fornication, and wantonnes, which they had committed. And again: He wept for them that were enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe ende is damnation, whoſe God is their belly, &amp;c. And againe, he ſaith:Act. 20.31. Ieremy. 9. Iob. 29.
                   
                  That he ceaſed not to warne euery one night and day with teares.
               
               The like we reade of Ieremy, Iob, and the reſt of Gods children of Dauid, Mine eyes guſh out with riuers of waters, becauſe they keepe not thy lawe. But ô good God, (I ſpeake it with compunction of heart) how many are there now found, which take no greater delight then to cauſe others to ſinne, and

to heare of the infirmities of their neighbours. Of this ſort are they which (as the very agents for the diuell) take pleaſure to make their brother ſin in drunkennes, and make themſelues merrie therewith: but let ſuch knowe,
                     Heb. 2.15. that this woe denounced by the Prophet perteineth to them: Woe be vnto him that giueth his neighbour drinke, and maketh him drunken, &amp;c.
               
               Fourthly, here we haue a notable teſtimonie  of theſe two attributes in God, Mercy, and Iuſtice: an excellent mirrour for Magiſtrates, that if in Iuſtice they be compelled to puniſh a malefactor, yet in the midſt of Iuſtice, mercy and clemencie ſhould ſhine forth: which here appeareth in this ſweete Sauiour, who though in ſhort time after he was to inflict, moſt horrible plagues, and finall deſtruction vpon this incorrigible and ſinfull nation, yet he ſhed moſt mercifull and compaſſionate teares for their tranſgreſſions: for otherwiſe Iuſtice looſeth ſuumeſſe, the propertie of Iuſtice, and is conuerted into tyrannie, if it be done with delight, &amp; be not tempered with mercy.Marcus Marcellus. Memorable was the fact of Marcus Marcellus, who being now readie to inuade and repunge the gallant citie of Siracuſa,
                  
gate him vp into a high Tower to behold the euent of the battell,Aug. lib. 1. de ciui dei. and when he beheld the Souldiers valiantly encountering on both ſides, the crackling of the glittering armour beſprinkled with blood, the horrible clamour of thoſe which were ſlaine, the fire flaming vp into the skies, the terrible noiſe of the falling of the ſtately buildings of that glorious citie; he burſt forth into teares, though the victorie went on his ſide, conſidering the miſerie they were in, and that he was enforced to ſacke ſo ancient a citie.
               The ancient Romanes (for in later time they were more corrupt) ſhall riſe in iudgement againſt all cruell and merciles Magiſtrates, which are touched with no Chriſtian commiſeration:Tit. Flam. 
                  Titus Flam: amongſt them, was put out of his office and diſgraded, for that he cauſed a man which was before condemned to be hanged in his Parlour▪ a mans life is not a matter to be plaied with, or ieſted at.
               
                  Sulpitius.Contrariwiſe, Sulpitius was greatly praiſed among them, who neuer iudged any vnaduiſedly, nor tooke pleaſure in the iuſt execution of Iudgement, but his teares were often ſeene to trickle from his eyes,

when he pronounced ſentence of death vpon any.
            
            
               Pars Secunda.
               
                  O that thou haddeſt euen knowne at the leaſt in this thy day, thoſe things which belong vnto thy peace! &amp;c.
               
               HEre our Sauiour amplifieth the affirmationThe Analiſis. of this blindnes of the people (which drew) theſe teares from the compaſſionate Sauiour of the world) by an elegant antitheſis of the contratie wiſh or deſire: O if thou haddeſt euen knowne, &amp;c. Theſe words expreſſe a paſſion proceeding of ſorrow, which if it be vehement, is wont to interrupt and cut off ſome words which ſhould make vp and finiſh the ſpeech: This figure is vſuall among the Rhetoritians, and is called in Greeke Apoſiopeſis,
                  Apoſiopeſis. where ſomething is left out, which muſt be vnderſtood for the perfecting of the ſpeech. As Quos ego,
                  
                     Aeneid. 1. 
                  ſed mot os praeſtat componere fluctus, againe: quanquam ôſi ſolitae quicquam virtutis adeſſet. And:
                     Aeneid. 11. 
                  O mihi praetentos referat ſi Iuppiter annos. So here: O if thou haddeſt euen knowne &amp;c. is to be vnderſtood,

how happie &amp; bleſſed haddeſt thou bene? O Ieruſalem, if thou haddeſt knowne the things that belong vnto thy true peace, as thou art wholy intent, to this ſuppoſed, falſe and tranſitorie peace, which now maketh thee ſecure, ô then how happie haddeſt thou bene, thou wouldeſt then foreſee thy imminent deſtruction for thy ſinnes, and betake thee to repentance and teares, whereas now thou reioyceſt; that thou mighteſt indeed procure thy true peace and ſafetie. O if thou haddeſt knowne: to wit, the ruine which hāgeth ouer thy head, or me thy Redeemer, who am come ſo graciouſly to viſite thee, thou wouldeſt then weepe &amp; bewaile thy grieuous ſins wherewith thou haſt incenſed the wrath of God againſt thee, whereas now thou flattereſt thy ſelfe with vaine ioy, as if all things went well with thee.
               By the word [peace] among the Hebrewes is ſignified, not one ſingular good, but all good things which ye Son of God brought with him into the world: for at his comming, the cateracts of heauen were opened, and a plentifull ſhowre of all graces powred downe on the earth, the firſt fruits thereof the Lord firſt offered moſt gratiouſly vnto

                  
                     •
                  he people of the Iewes, to whom he was 
                     •
                  romiſed, whom he ſought to illuminate 
                     •
                  ith his doctrine, to confirme in the faith 
                     •
                  ith his miracles, to kindle their loue with 
                     •
                  is benefits, to erect them in the hope of 
                     •
                  mmortalitie with his merites, with the ex
                  
                     •
                  mples of his vertues to allure them to 
                     •
                  ollow him, with the maieſtie of his pre
                  
                     •
                  ence to grace them, and laſtly to aduance 
                     •
                  hem into his heauenly kingdome. Theſe 
                     •
                  re the things which they ought to haue 
                     •
                  cknowledged, the want whereof the Lord 
                     •
                  ere bewaileth.
               Firſt, in that aboue all things the Lord  wiſheth vnto them the knowledge of the preſent good, and future euill, we are to obſerue, how great and fearefull is the careles ignorance of men,Obſer. and their ſupine obliuion of the time to come, by reaſon of their preſent peace and proſperitie, which Chriſt here deploreth in the Iewes, which being blinded with the peace, glory and abundance of their temporall and preſent proſperitie, neuer thought vpon the future euils, and miſeries, which for their ſinnes were ſhortly to be inflicted vpon them. For when the ſecure ſinner ſhall ſay, peace and ſafetie: then ſhall ſuddaine

deſtruction come vpon him,
                  1. Theſ. 5. 
                  as trauaile vpon a woman with childe, and he ſhall not eſcape. For as oftentimes ſuddaine trauaile commeth vpon a woman with childe:Simile. So Gods vengeance falleth ſuddainely vpon the ſinner in his deepe obliuion of the time to come, when they will not knowe the things that pertaine to their true peace. And ſo God is wont tarditatem, vindictae grauitate compenſare,
                  Valer. to recompence his ſlownes, with the grieuouſnes of his vengeance.
               
                  Grego.Well ſaith S. Gregorie vpon this place, the peruerſe ſoule being wholy intente to things preſent, and reſolued in earthly pleaſures, abſcondit ſibi mala ſequentia, hideth from himſelfe the dangers following, and refuſeth to foreſee the euills to come, leaſt they ſhould diſturbe his preſent mirth: but whiles he walloweth in worldly delights, what doth he elſe but, clauſis oculis ad ignem vadere? goe blindfolde to hell fire? ſaith he. Leaſt this forgetfulnes ſhould poſſeſſe our mindes, the Apoſtle counſaileth,1. Cor. 7.30. 
                  that they that reioyce, ſhould be as if they reioyced not: that is, as Gregorie expoundeth it, praeſentis temporis it a agenda laetitia, vt amaritudo ſequent is iudicij nunquam recedat a memoria. The mirth and pleaſure of this preſent time are ſo to be paſſed,

that the bitternes of the future iudgement, neuer depart from our mindes.
               In thy good eſtate remember aduerſitie,
                  
                     Eccle. 11. A Simile, ſhewing the vanitie of worldly delights. ſaith the wiſe man. But it happeneth to the ſinner concerning his worldly delights, as it doth vnto a traueller, who to finde ſome ſhelter from the heate of the ſunne reſteth himſelfe vnder the ſhadowe of a tree, and by reaſon of wearines, falleth into a ſound ſleepe, vntill the ſunne in his courſe, going about the ſhadow departeth, and when he awaketh, he findeth himſelfe parched with the Sunne raies, his body ſweating and inflamed, his head a king, and perhaps his body arreſted with a continuall feuer. So the louers of the world, while they catch at the vaniſhing ſhadowes thereof, as honours, riches, pleaſures, and thinke to repoſe their reſt in them, in the meane time the courſe of their life being ſuddenly run out,
                     Pſal. 76.5. when theſe viri diuitiarum dormierunt ſomnum ſuum, rich men haue ſlept their ſleepe, euen in death they finde they were deluded with meere ſhewes, and ſhadowes without ſubſtance, and for theſe momentaine pleaſures to be plunged in the infernall flames, for euer to be tormented.Note. Man being in honour hath no vnderſtanding, he will

not knowe the things which belong vnto his true peace, euen like the fagiuated beaſtes, which are to day in the paſture, to morrow in the ſhambles. O that we would learne to knowe the things that pertaine to our true peace. Chriſt leaues God his Father, heauen his countrey, the Angells his people, to dwell with vs, but we ſcarce allowe him the ſtable, there is no roome for him in the Inne. Pride hath taken the chiefeſt place in the hart: malice and enuie the next in the minde: luſt hath poſſeſſion of the eyes, lying and ſwearing of the tongue, gluttonie of the taſte, theft and murther of the handes, and couetouſnes of our thoughts.
               When the Aſſiſes are at hand, and the Iudge comming, how circumſpect are we that our trialls may paſſe on our ſide? What inſtructing of our counſaile? ſeeing of our Lawyers? informing of the queſt? but Chriſt is at hand, his day is nigh, his ſeate prepared. O then that we did know the things that pertaine vnto our peace at that day, ô that we would ſee and preuent the future danger. Mans corrupt nature is commonly moſt careles, when he ſhould be moſt carefull: and the wicked moſt ſecure,

when they are moſt in danger: moſt negligent, when they ſhould be moſt prouident.
               The day of the Lord ſhall come as a thiefe in the night:
                  1. Theſ. 5.3. 2. Pet. 3.10. therefore the Greeke word Cleptesfur, is deriued Apó tou caloptein, of hiding or couering, or Cléptein, to take away by ſtealth, he commeth in the darke where no body ſees, he treadeth vpon wooll, when no body heares, he watcheth an houre which no bodie knowes. If the good man of the houſe had knowne at what houre, the thiefe would come,
                  
                     Luc. 12. 
                  he would ſurely watch, ſaith our Sauiour; but we knowe that Chriſts day will come, and yet keepe no ward: carefull of our goods, careles of our ſoules. Our bodies are houſes, our ſoules our true goods, our ſences the doores and windowes, the lockes, the word and prayer, the diuell is a thiefe, man is the Houſeholder: death is a thiefe, his comming is vncertaine, be watchfull and wiſe, be alwaies prepared, after death commeth the iudgement. O beloued,
                     Hebr. 9. let vs foreſee this daunger, take heede of the fooles Motto, had I wiſt, leaſt we ſay too late, O that we had knowne the things which belonged vnto our peace.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Ieri. Thren▪
                      1.9.Holy Ieremie bewayling the calamitie of his people ſaith, Her filthines is in her skirts, ſhe remembred not her laſt ende, and therefore ſhe came downe wonderfully.
               
               This [beloued] is the fatall diſeaſe of all ſinners, and their wretched illuſion, they forget their ende, they take ſinne by the head, and not by the taile, they conſider the beginning of their pleaſure, which ſheweth them a faire face; but they thinke not of the ende which concludeth the Cataſtrophe in extreame miſerie. And what (I pray you) is this world, which ſo blindeth vs that we neuer thinke on the future time, and refuſe to knowe the things that pertaine in this our day, vnto our peace? ſurely it may be compared vnto an hollowe nut,Poma virent Sodomis cinerem dant carptaque fumum. or the Apples of Sodome, which haue nothing within but a filthie worme and rottennes: looke into the world, and you ſhall finde nothing but vanities; pleaſures are but forerunners of deſtruction; this life is a channell, the ſweet Riuers do alwaies runne and ende in the ſalte ſea and bitter waters: breue eſt quod delectat, aeternum quod excruciat, ſhort pleaſures, long paine: this is the ende of the world and worldlings: a golden head,
                  
                     Dan. 2. 
                  but earthen feete, like Nabuchadonezers

Image, vaine ioyes ende with mourning, as Herods ioy was conſumed of wormes;
                     Act. 12. Princes Pallaces are but earth, their golde but the filth of the earth, their ſilkes but the dongue of wormes, riches are runa-waies, fauour deceitfull, beautie vanitie,
                  
                     Pro. 31. Iob. 7. 
                  and corruption our mother: And ſhall this deceitfull world make vs forget the things which belong vnto our true peace? O that we did knowe at the leaſt in this our day, the things that belong vnto our peace!
               
               As Iacob when he was borne,
                     Gen. 25. 
                  held Eſau by the heele: So the godly conſidereth ſinne by the ende thereof. O that they were wiſe, then would they vnderſtand this, they would conſider their latter ende, ſaith holy Moſes.
                  
                     Deut. 32. But the preſent plentie of all things, and the flattering face of the world, hideth Gods iudgement from mens eyes. Euen as certaine rich young men, but vnexpert in worldly things,Simile. in their trauell taketh vp their Inne, and ſeeing themſelues chearefully receiued and entertained of their Hoſt, prodigally waſt and conſume all their money, vntill their purſes being peniles, and exhaſted of al, they perceiue the countenance of their Hoſt to be changed, their entertainement grudged, attendance denied,

and themſelues enforced to depart, carrying nothing with them, but ſhame, reproach and pouertie: So the louers of this world, being lulled a ſleepe with pleaſures and worldly proſperitie, and being ignorant of the ſolide &amp; heauenly good things, ſpend all the vigor of their mindes, and cogitations, their ſpirituall ſubſtance, in theſe vanities, and when all is ſpent, they are ſent out of the world, ſorrowfull, naked, laden with ſinne, hauing nothing left but hel and Iudgement. O then that men were ſo wiſe to knowe, in this their day, the things that belong vnto their peace.
               It is worthie the noting, that Chriſt calleth all the pleaſures of this life but one day: Euen in this thy day. For the wicked haue but their day, but Gods Iuſtice hath many daies: and therefore he ſaith afterward, For the daies will come vpon thee: that thine enemies ſhall caſt a trench about thee, and therefore he ſaid vnto the Iewes,
                  
                     Verſ. 43. Luc. 22.53. Simile. 
                  this is your very houre: Euen as the fire according vnto the nature of the ſubiect on which it worketh, endureth either a ſhort or a longer time, as that which is made with firme O
                     •
                  e continueth long, and that which feedeth vpon ſtrawe quickely goeth out: ſo the

ioyes, pleaſures and honours of this life, becauſe the matter thereof, is fluid, caduce, and fraile, ſoone vaniſheth away, but that which is fixed on the ſoliditie of vertue and godlines, endureth for euer.
               
                  Plinie reporteth,Plini. lib. 8 cap. 22. nat. hiſt. that there is a kinde of wolfe called Lupus ceruarius, which is of this nature, that being neuer ſo hungrie, and hauing hardly found his preye, if he looketh backe and eſpieth ſome other preye, he forgetteh his hunger, and the meate he hath preſent before him, and followeth after that which is vncertaine.
               Quaeritat incertam (tanta eſt obliuio) praedom.
               
                  Forgetting ſtill his preſent pray.
                  Vncertaine hopes he ſeekes alway.
               
               So obtuſe and dull is his memorie. Like vnto him are they, which being delighted with the preſent pleaſures of this life, they altogether forget their firſt loue, and the doctrine of heauenly things which they had learned, and purſue vaine and vncertaine pleaſures.
               We haue here a moſt ſweete and comfortable teſtimonie of the inſpeakeable loue
                     Ezek. 18.
                  
and mercy of God, who is ſo farre off from willing the death of a ſinner, but rather that he conuert and line: that he doth not onely lament their imminent deſtruction, and wiſh the conuertion of the wicked, but patiently expecteth their amendment.2. Pet. 3. 
                  He is patient towards vs, and would haue no man to periſh, but would haue all men to come to repentance: for the Lord is patient,
                     Exod. 34.6. &amp;. 7. 
                  ſlowe to anger, and abundant in goodnes and truth, Reſeruing mercie for thouſands, forgiuing iniquitie, tranſgreſſion and ſinne: not that he hates not iniquitie, but that he awaites our amendment. Fortie daies he gaue ſpace to Niniuie, to Nabuch
                        •
                     donezer twelue moneths, three yeares to the barraine figtree,
                     Dan. 4. Luc. 13. Gen. 6. an hundred yeares to the olde world, and fortie yeares to Ieruſalem, before this deſtruction fel vpon them; but how long hath he expected vs?
                     Rom. 2.4. and ſhall we ſtill deſpiſe his long ſufferance which leadeth vs to repentance? We are long in building an houſe, but quicke in pulling it downe; deus cum ſtruit, velociter ſtruit.
               
               But God is quicke in building vp, and ſlowe in pulling downe: he ſets vp in power,Chriſo. ſer. 50. de paen. but deſtroyes in mercy. He would not drowne the world before Noah preached,

nor burne Sodome, before Lot exhorted: he will warne Egypt by Moſes, the Iewes by Ieremie, and Ieruſalem by CHRIST and his Apoſtles, and that with weeping before he puniſheth. O loue! to ſend vs his ſonne: O mercy! to ſtay vs falling: O patience! to attend our returning, deſiring our repentance.
               The vſe of all this is:The vſe. that ſeeing the bountifulnes, and long ſufferance of God leadeth vs to repentance,
                  
                     Rom. 2. that we abuſe not this goodnes of the Lorld, but betime prouide for our peace, by taking hold of repentance. O let vs not be ſlacke herein. In futurum enim nostra diſtulimus, ſaith Senica, we leaue all for hereafter. It is to be feared the diuell will plead preſcription, we are ſo ſlacke in chalenging our inheritance. Cadit aſinus &amp; eſt qui ſubleuat, perit anima &amp; non eſt qui recogitat. The aſſe falleth into the ditch,Ber. and we carefully pull him out, but the ſoule periſheth and we neuer regard it. Teſhuba the Hebrew, Metànoia, the Greeke, reſipiſcentia the latine: conuerſion, the Engliſh, are Synonimies: All teach vs, that repentance is a turning from ſinne. Metanôen conuerti,
                  Ferus. to be turned. The Metaphor is borrowed from a Traueller, who wandring out of his

way, and being admoniſhed, turnes againe into his right way. Auerſion, a turning out of the way, is, when one forſaketh God and ſerueth Sathan; Reuerſion, is, when a man leaues ſinne, and returnes to God by repentance. Sin then, is, per auia errare, to wander through by waies: repentance is, Adviam regiam redire; To returne into the right way again. The prodigall ſonne, went out of the way, when he wandred from his father, but found againe the right way, when he returned to his father. Sinne, is Anoia, follie and madnes. Metànoia repentance, is a chaunge vnto wiſedome. The ſinner whiles he continues in his wickednes, doth as it were, looke without eyes, heares without eares, and vnderſtandes without his heart; but the penitent doth Meta, put them on again, and doth nothing without them. The word recipiſcentia, as it were reſapere, or poſt factū ſapere, teacheth vs, that ſinne is a madnes, and to repent, is to waxe wiſe after follie, to come to his right wittes againe.
               The true repentant, taketh hold of Gods promiſe, and doubteth not of forgiuenes: fides ambiguum non habet
                  ▪ Faith admits no doubt.Ber. Faith cannot be doubtfull: the faithfull,

deferres not repentance, nor returnes as a dogge to his vomite. The Serpent that hath caſt off her skinne, leaues it behind her, and reſumes the ſame no more. The bird that hath eſcaped from the ſnare of the fowler, will afterwards be the more warie of the nette.
                     Cant. 5.3. And the ſpouſe of Chriſt maketh this reſolution, That ſhe hath put off her coate: how then ſhould ſhe put it on? ſhe hath waſhed her feete, how ſhould ſhe defile them?
               
               It is as impoſſible for fire to burne in the water, as the truely penitent to wallowe in wickednes Our ſins (brethren) do daily recrucifie Chriſt, &amp; are no better then treaſons. Impenitent Sathan cannot be ſaued, &amp; they that ſeeke not pardon ſhall not finde it: no repentance, no confeſſion; No confeſſion, no ſorrowe; No ſorrowe, no turning; no turning, no ſaluatiō. Chriſt is the dore of heauen, he opens, if we belieue: and we ſhall enter, if we repent. Faith and repentance goe coniunctim, and hand in hand: Faith reconciles, repentance reformes: Faith receiues the promiſes, repentance renues the man: the penitēt onely are partakers of the bleſſings. All the vialls of Gods wrath ſhall be powred downe, all his plagues ſhall light on the impenitēt, to the vtter perdition of

body and ſoule, began here in the perſon attained, proceeding on the conſcience conuicted, and conſumnate on the partie condemned for euer to endure. Here are Alastores of Alaſtêin tormentors for Nero:
                  I. H. 
                  Plutoes horſes for Oedipus, an euill ſpirit for Saul, and a gnawing cōſcience for Achitophell. Heu quantum miſero poenae mens conſcia donat.
               
                  
                     Lucan.O with what paine and griping ſmart,
                  A guiltie conſcience wounds the hart.
               
               O beloued, if Ieruſalem had repented in that her day, ſhe had then knowne the things that pertained to her peace, then would the Sauiour haue reioyced, and not haue vttered this ſorrowfull Threnodiam, whiles they ſang Hoſanna: O if thou haddeſt knowne the things that pertaine vnto thy peace.
               
               
                  Repentance the ſanctuary of the ſoule.Let vs therfore (good brethrē) linger no delaies, but betime flie to repentance, the ſanctuarie of the ſoule: take heede leaſt ſinne paſſe through his gradation, and ſo get an habite. Leaſt while cuſtome groweth, man fadeth, grace abſenteth, ſin preſenteth, the heart is hardened, and man obdurate: ſo that now God is contemned, his

threatning reiected: heauen cannot winne him, nor hell ſcarre him: ioyes cannot allure him, nor torments affright him. This is Sathans ladder of perdition: ſinne ſteppeth from temptation, to thinking: from thinking, to liking: from liking, to yeelding: from yeelding, to acting: from acting to cuſtome: from cuſtome, to hardnes of heart: from hardnes of heart, to a reprobate minde, full of vnrighteouſnes, fornication, couetouſnes, enuie, murther, back-biting &amp;c. As a learned Diuine excellently obſerueth.
               I would here haue ended,Iacobus Ian
                        •
                     enſit. but I cannot forget an obſeruation of an anciēt Schooleman, vpon theſe words, in this thy day. He calles this their day, wherein the Sauiour of the world, offered them ſo louingly his grace, and ſaluation, their true, and eternall peace: which if they had embraced, then had not the Romanes ſacked their citie.
               Here obſerue,Obſ. that the day of this life is giuen vs, to make prouiſion for our true and eternall peace: but there is an other day, wherein Chriſt will come in iudgement, ſeuerely to puniſh the contempt and abuſe of his proffered grace and ſaluation: in this our day, which we haue ſo vnkindly

reiected. Theſe two dayes are diligently to be pondered and thought vpon in our mindes, the one of theſe daies is Gods day, the other (if ſo I may tearme it) is mans day, becauſe he abuſeth the benefite of this time of grace, not to the will of God, but to ſerue his owne pleaſures and vanities. In this day, the wicked will ſerue their owne luſtes, and doe as they pleaſe: now may Zedekiah perſecute the Lords Prophet,
                  
                     Ier. 3.7. and caſt him into a Dungeon. But in the day of Gods Iuſtice, Zedekiah ſhall be taken,
                     Ier. 39.7. Note.
                   depriued of his kingdome, and his eyes thruſt out. Betwixt the godly and the wicked this is the difference; all the daies of a godly mans life, is the day of God, for he vſeth it to Gods glory, and worketh the worke of the Lord.
               But the wicked maketh it his owne day, for he abuſeth the whole time of his life, to pleaſure luſt, gluttonie, &amp;c and why? Becauſe theſe things are hidden from thine eyes.
                  The cauſe of all euil. Here is now the cauſe of all euill, the wicked ſecurely wallowe in their ſinnes, abuſe Gods patience, growe dayly worſe and worſe, and become more obdurate in their ſinnes, becauſe, Gods iudgements for ſinne, and his imminent vengeance is

hidden from their eyes,
                     Amos 6.3. as the Prophet ſaith: They put farre from them the euill day, and approach to the ſeate of iniquitie.
                  
                     Eccle. 8. This reaſon alſo Salomon giueth: Becauſe ſentence againſt an euill worke is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the hearts of the children of men are fully ſet to doe euill. But let vs (my deare brethren) betime remember the euill day, and knowe the things that pertaine vnto our peace; Seeke the Lord while he may be found,
                  
                     Eſa. 55. 
                  call vpon him while he is nigh.
               
               The time was when Eſau had a birth-right, Diues pleaſure, Ieruſalem peace,
                  
                     Mat. 25. 
                  and the fooliſh Virgins might haue entered. Now is the time that peace is offered, repentance preached, &amp; heauē gates are opened, The time wil come, (if we deſpiſe the patience of the Lord) that we ſhall pray with Diues and not be heard: weepe with Eſau, &amp; not be pittied: knocke with the fiue Virgins, &amp; the doore not opened. The Storke, the Crane, the Turtle, the Swallow, knowe their appointed time. And ſhall we be more ignorant in the things,
                     Ier. 8. 
                  that pertaine to our peace, then the very foules? A traueller being being tolde of a Lyon in the way, will ſtay his iourney: a blinde man hauing notice of a Serpent in the path, will refraine his walking. Sathan is a roaring Lyon,
                  
and ſhall we goe forward in vngodlines? ſinne is a ſtinging Serpent, and ſhall we goe on ſtill in wickednes?
               O then, while this our day laſteth, while Chriſts hands are opened, and the doore of mercy not ſhut, let vs aske, and he will giue vs: let vs goe to him, and he will ſaue vs: in futuro ſalum remuneratio,
                  Aug. 
                  &amp; condemnatio, after this life there is either reward or puniſhment: ſaluation to the godly, deſtruction to the wicked.
               Thus much for the firſt impulſiue cauſe of Chriſts weeping ouer Ieruſalem, Namely, the preſent euill which he ſawe among them, which concerned their mindes, and was the cauſe of all their miſerie: the blindnes of their mindes, becauſe they would not knowe,
                  
                     Verſ. 42. 
                  in this their day, thoſe things which belonged vnto their peace. The other (as I ſaid before) was the future euill which pertained vnto their bodies;The ſecond impulſiue cauſe of Chriſts weeping. Namely, their finall deſtruction, by famine, fire, and ſword, which our Sauiour foreſawe to be at hand, for their grieuous ſinnes committed againſt God and his miniſters. And laſtly, againſt the ſonne of God himſelfe.
               
                  The Analyſis.Which deſtruction he excellently delineateth by the parts thereof. For the daies

ſhal come vpon thee,
                  
                     Verſ. 43. &amp; 44. 
                  that thine enemies ſhall caſt 
                        〈◊〉
                      trench about thee, and compaſſe thee round, 
                        •
                     nd keepe thee in on euery ſide. Laſtly, he declareth the ſame by the impulſiue cauſe which mooued the Lord thereunto, name
                  
                     •
                  y their ingratitude towards the gratious viſitation of God, becauſe thou knoweſt not the time of thy viſitation.
               
               There was neuer any Nation vnder the ſunne, whoſe miſery, calamitie, &amp; deſtruction was ſo great and horrible,Ioſephus lib. 6. &amp; 7. de bello Iudeorum. Egeſippus lib. 5. cap. 10.
                   as this of the Iewiſh Nation, as Ioſephus himſelfe being a Iewe and in the citie at that very time, and therefore teſtis oculatus, an eye witnes of all their miſeries, doth affirme.
               And alſo Egeſippus, who liued in the Apoſtles time, hath committed to writing, and to this very day the wrath of God purſueth them, as their miſerable diſpertion and perſecution through the whole world doth manifeſt, in the time of the ſiege the famine was ſo great, that dogges, cattes, and miſe, were eaten, yea one deuoured an others vomit, and (which I tremble to ſpeake) women did kill, dreſſe, and greedily deuour, their owne children, the extremitie of famine vtterly aboliſhing all motherly compaſſion and nature: eleuen hundred

thouſand periſhed by famine, ſword, and peſtilence, and ninetie ſeuen thouſand, after the deſtruction of the citie, were carried away into miſerable captiuitie. Was euer the like maſacrie heard of ſince the vniuerſall flood wherein the whole world, (Noah and his company onely excepted) periſhed by water? What a fearefull example of his iuſtice, hatred, and ſeueritie againſt ſinne, did God ſhew in this horrible vaſtation of that citie? But how great alſo was his pietie and mercy, in that ſo long before he foretolde and bewailed, with bitter teares, this memorable deſolation? We reade that Chriſt wept for three cauſes, and at three ſeuerall times.
               
                   Firſt, he wept for to confirme our hope and confidence in his mercy, when we conſider that theſe compaſſionate teares of our Sauiour, flowed from his intire mercy and loue.
               
                   Secondly, he wept, that he might mollifie our ſtonie hearts, to relent for our ſinnes, and to teach vs to bewaile our owne miſeries.
               
                   Thirdly, he wept, to inſtruct vs, when is the due time of weeping: which is, when we feele our conſcience moſt ſecure in

our ſinnes,When we are moſt ſecure in our ſinnes, then haue wee greateſt cauſe to weepe. Ioh. 11. litle thinking vpon Gods vengeance, as did the Iewes at this time.
               At three ſundrie times alſo we reade that he wept.
               1 Firſt at the raiſing vp of Lazarus, where he bewailed mans incredulitie, and conſcience dead in ſinne, which cuſtome hath brought to ſuch an obſtinate habite, that neither his threatnings may awake, nor his ſweete promiſes rowſe them vp out of this deadly lethargie.
               2 Secondly, vpon the Croſſe, where with ſtrong crying and teares,
                  
                     Heb. 5.7. he bewailed the diſeaſes of mans ſoule, which needed ſo great a cure.
               3 And thirdly, here ouer Ieruſalem, a little before his paſſion, where he bewailed not ſo much his imminent death, as the future deſolation of that Nation. Which he plainly ſignified vnto the woman that bewailed and lamented him, when he ſaid:
                     Luc. 23. 
                  Ye daughters of Ieruſalem, weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelues and for your children. For behold the daies will come, when men ſhall ſay, bleſſed are the barraine &amp; the wombs that neuer bare, &amp; the paps that neuer gaue ſucke. Which words no doubt the woman vttered at the ſiege of the citie, when the famine was ſo

great, that caſting off the ſence of nature, they killed and deuoured their owne children.
               But as here we may behold the ſeueritie of Gods iuſtice, and the poyſoned nature of ſinne; So in this his vengeance we may ſee the ſparkles of his mercy to ſhine forth: for he gaue to this ſinfull citie, fortie yeares ſpace of repentance, that they might bewaile their ſinnes which had ſo kindled the wrath of God againſt them, in which ſpace alſo he ſhewed many ſtraunge ſignes and wonders among them, (as Ioſephus reporteth who liued in thoſe daies,) that by putting them in minde that the fire of his wrath was kindled, and his ſword readie drawne, to ſtrike them, he might call them to repentance: for it was full fortie yeares, or as ſome ſay, fortie two after his aſſention, before Veſpatians the Emperour of Rome,
                  Vespatianus. Titus his ſonne. and his ſonne Titus, the executioners of Gods iudgement for their ſinnes, vtterly ruinated the walles, ſacked the citie, and brought that Nation to finall deſolation. And ſo this mercifull Lord did temper the rigour of his Iuſtice, with the ſweetnes of his mercy, that to ſuch as would returne from their wickednes, he

gaue ſpace of repentance. So before he ſent the flood, this louing God, for the ſpace of one hundred yeares patiently expected their amendment So before he gaue Ieruſalem and the Temple into the hands of the Chaldaeans to be ſpoyled, he ſent his Prophet Ieremie, a man ſanctified from his mothers wombe, by whom he offered them peace, and excited them to repentance for the ſpace of many yeares, vnleſſe they would runne in their ſinnes to their vtter ruine and deſtruction. But they were ſo farre off frō being reclaimed by ſo many admonitions, that they caſt the Prophet into priſon, perſiſted in their wickednes, vntill they brought the heauie wrath of God vpon their heads. For ſo it is recorded in the ſacred hiſtorie:2. Chron. 36.15.16 and 17. 
                  Therefore the Lord God of their fathers, ſent to them by his meſſengers riſing earlie and ſending: For he had compaſſion on his people, and on his habitation. But they mocked the meſſengers of God, despiſed his words, and miſuſed his Prophets, vntill the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his people, and till there was no remedie. For he brought vpon them the King of the Chaldeans, who ſlew their young men with the ſword in the houſe of their ſanctuarie, and ſpared neither young man,

nor Virgin, ancient, nor aged?
               
               O that we would euer haue before our eyes theſe examples of Gods hatred of ſinne, and the ſeueritie of his Iudgement againſt wicked men: Surely it would much profit vs to the planting of that true feare of God in our hearts, and be an effectuall medicine againſt the dangerous ſecuritie, and vaine preſumption of this looſe and corrupt age, eſpecially to repreſſe the falſe and deceitfull hope of many wicked men, which running out the whole race of their life, in all kinde of leaude and licentious liuing, obſtinately contemning Gods word, and deſpiſing his Meſſengers, and yet they preſume on Gods mercy and fauour, and ſuppoſe that all things ſhall ſucceed well with them; not conſidering, that in God there is not onely mercy in ſtore for the penitent ſinner, but alſo Iuſtice to reſtraine the inſolencie of wicked men. Was the Lord then a ſeuere reuenger of all impietie, and is he now changed? doth he now winke at our wickednes? No, no, he is ſtill the ſame, and in him is no change, as he ſaith by his Prophet.
                     Mal. 3.6. 
                  I am the Lord, I change not. How much better were it for ſuch to hearken

to the wholeſome counſaile of the wiſe man: Say not thou the mercy of God is great,
                  Eccle. 5.6 
                  he will forgiue my manifolde ſinnes: for mercy and wrath come from him, and his indignation commeth downe vpon ſinners. This dangerous ſicknes, I will labour (God willing) in what I purpoſe to ſpeake more vpon this texte, to cure: for I am verily perſwaded, that the number is almoſt infinite, of them that being deluded with this deceitfull hope, doe ruſh headlong into eternall torments; Neither is there any Inginne of that olde cankered Serpent more frequent, or more to be feared.
               And for the performance hereof, I thinke no way more effectuall, then by ſetting downe ſome examples of Gods horrible Iudgements inflicted vpon wicked men, which being attentiuely cōſidered, we may vnderſtand, Gods hatred of ſin, that therby the feare of God being entertained in our hearts, we may growe into a ſerious deteſtation of ſinne, the cauſe of all miſery in this life, and rewarded with eternall torments in the life to come. And to paſſe ouer the three fearefull torments, mentioned by S. Peter, of the Angells that had ſinned,
                  2. Pet. 2.2.4.5.6. 
                  and were caſt downe into hell, and deliuered into chaines

of darkenes,
                  
                     Iob. 4.18. Iude 6. Gen. 7. Gen. 19.24.25. 
                  to be kept vnto condemnation. Of the olde world, of the vngodly which periſhed in the flood: Of Sodome and Gomorah, which were turned into aſhes, and made an example, vnto them which ſhould after liue vngodly.
               
               What a iudgement I pray you, was that wherewith God, after he had waſted all Egipt with ſo many plagues? Laſtly, drowned Pharaoh with his great hoſte in the red Sea,
                     Exod. 14.27.28. ſo that there was not one left aliue to carrie newes what was become of the reſt?
               What a Iudgement was that which a little while after God inflicted vpon his owne people,
                     Exod. 32.28. when they worſhipped the golden Calfe, for which ſinne there periſhed at one inſtant three thouſand men?
               What a Iudgement was that, which the Lord layed vpon the Iſraelites, for committing whoredome with the daughters of Moab, For which there died twentie and foure thouſand of the plague?
                     Num. 25.9.
               
               But leauing now, for breuitie ſake, theſe puniſhments common to many, let vs conſider how ſeuerely God puniſhed King Dauid for committing adulterie with the wife of Vri
                        ••
                     
                     ▪
                   though he were a man entirely beloued of God, yet he winked not

at his wickednes, but ſent the Prophet Nathan vnto him with this meſſage;2. Sam 12. verſ. 9.10.11. &amp; 12. 
                  Wherefore haſt thou despiſed the commaundement of the Lord, to doe euill in his ſight? thou haſt killed Vriah the Hittitie with the ſword, and haſt taken his wife to be thy wife, and haſt ſlaine him with the ſword of the Children of Ammon. Now therefore the ſword ſhall neuer depart from thy houſe, becauſe thou haſt des
                        •
                     iſed me, and taken the wife of Vriah the Hittite to be thy wife. Thus ſaith the Lord; Behold, I will raiſe vp euill againſt thee out of thine owne houſe, and will take thy wiues before thine eyes, and giue them vnto thine neighbour, and he ſhall lie with thy wiues in the ſight of this ſunne: For thou didſt it ſecretly; but I will doe this thing before all Iſrael, and before the ſunne: and though the Lord vpon his peccaui and vnfained repentance, did put away his ſinne; So that he did not die,
                  2 Sam. 12.13. yet to ſhew his hatred of ſinne to all poſterities, what ſeuere chaſtiſements and tragicall croſſes all his life long did God inflict? but how great and extraordinarie was his repentance that followed this ſinfull fact,
                     Pſal. 51. he himſelfe witneſſeth: So that his whole life afterwards ſeemed too little for repentance, that he might be reconciled vnto God, and reſtored

into his fauour. How did he bewaile his great offences, deſiring God that he would forgiue his ſinnes, and renew in him his holy ſpirit, promiſing that he would not be vnmindfull of ſo great a grace ſhewed vpon him? And how vehement was his ſorrowe, he expreſſeth: I am bowed and crooked very ſore,
                  
                     Pſal. 38.6.8.9. 
                  I goe mourning all the day. I am weakened and ſore broken. I roare for very griefe of my heart. Lord I powre my whole deſire before thee, and my ſighing is not hid from thee. Againe, how great was that ſorrowe,
                     Pſal. 6▪6. when he ſaith: I fainted in my mourning. I cauſe my bedde euery night to ſwimme, and water my couch with my teares.
               
               Therefore for the fewe nights which he ſpent in filthie and ſinfull pleaſure; he paſſed the reſt of his time in bitter weeping, ſighing and mourning. And his bedde which he had polluted with vnlawfull luſt, he afterwards waſhed with a large and plentifull flood of teares. And what could be more to expreſſe his ſerious and earneſt repentance? Notwithſtanding this repentance, let them with a feeling heart conſider what followed, which ſport and 
                     •
                  eſt at this ſinne, and tearme it but a tricke of youth, a naturall inclination, &amp;c.
               
                  Though King Dauid were highly beloued of God, as a man after his owne heart, yet the Lord would not ſo lightly paſſe ouer his ſinnes, but by his chaſtiſements and afflictions, would make him a memorable example to all licentious liuers to the worlds end.
               For firſt the children (the fruit of his adulterie) was ſtriken with ſicknes and died.
               2.2. Sam. 12. His daughter Thamar was inceſtuouſly defiled by her owne brother Ammon.
               
               3. Ammon for his inceſt,2. Sam. 13. was ſlaine by Abſolon.
               
               4. Abſolon raiſed warre vpon him, (ambitiouſly aſpiring after his fathers kingdome, and conſpiring againſt him) defiled his concubines, and came to a wofull deſtruction.2, Sam. 15. And therefore for defiling the one wife of Vriah, his tenne concubines were polluted, and defiled, not by a ſtranger, but by his owne ſonne: not in ſecret, but in the open viewe of all Iſrael; according as the Prophet Nathan foretolde: For thou diddeſt it ſecretly,
                  2. Sam. 16. 
                  but I will doe this thing before all Iſrael.
               
               If God ſo grieuouſly afflicted King Dauid, a man after his owne heart, for

the ſinne of adulterie, and that after ſo great ſorrowe and contrition of heart for his offences, Mercifull God, in what ſtate doe they ſtand, which make no conſcience of this ſinne? yea ieſt at it, ſo farre off are they from ſorrowing with holy Dauid
                  ▪ But let ſuch by theſe examples, conſider the fearefull eſtate they are in, and Gods heauie wrath hanging ouer their heads, that (if they be not altogether giuen ouer to a reprobate ſenſe) they may betimes betake themſelues to amendment of life, labour by Dauids example, by ſerious and vnfained repentance to be reconciled vnto God, that they may come out of the ſnares of the Diuell, and eſcape the eternall torments prepared for them:
                     Hebr. 10. 
                  It is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God.
               
               Now (brethren) theſe things are examples vnto vs (as the Apoſtle ſaith) That we ſhould not luſt after euill things as they luſted. For whatſoeuer things are written aforetime; are written for our learning.
                  1. Cor. 10.
               
               
                  
                     Rom. 15.4·Theſe indeed, are manifeſt examples of Gods great hatred, and vengeance againſt all impietie and wicked men: but theſe temporall puniſhments are light, yea but a ſhadowe, being compared to the eternall

torments in the life to come: theſe chiefely afflict the body, but the other ſhall ſeize vpon body and ſoule.
               Theſe are but temporarie, and prefined within the limits of this ſhort life: the other eternall, which neuer ſhall finde ende or limit. If then this vaſtation of Ieruſalem, foreſeene ſo long before, did drawe teares from our louing Lord, with what teares of contrition ſhould we bewaile our ſinnes, which will in the end (without repentance) plunge vs in eternall torments, whereof all other affliction is but an Image or ſhadowe? For ſo the Apoſtle Peter layeth before vs the deſtruction of Sodome and Gomorah, as an example of the eternall puniſhments prepared for theſe which hereafter ſhould liue vngodly.
                  2. Pet. 2.4.
               
               There the damned ſhall ſpiritually ſuffer all theſe things which the Lord here bewaileth, but after a diuers manner of torment.
               There all the rabble of the wicked ſhall be trenched about with their enemies [the Diuells] ſo that they ſhall haue no euaſion to eſcape out of their hands. There ſhall be famine, ſword and peſtilence, that is, diuers kindes of torments proceeding from

the order of Gods Iuſtice according to the condition of euery ſinne. And it may perhaps haue probabilitie, which ſome think, that there ſhall be diuers kindes of torments,Varieties of torments. for diuers kinds of ſinnes: as namely, other torments for the proud, other for the couetous, other for the leacher, other for the enuious, &amp;c.
               So that the proud and high minded, ſhall there be deiected and caſt downe full lowe: the couetous ſhall there be pined with extreame penurie of all things. There the enuious in rage ſhall rent and teare their owne bowells. There the lecher for the ſhort pleaſure of his vncleane fleſh, ſhall be tormented with moſt bitter tortures. There the greedie glutton, who made his bellie his God, ſhall with the rich glutton be tormented with moſt cruell hunger and thirſt, and be denied one droppe of colde water to coole his tongue.
                     Luc. 16. And whereas the Lord ſaith of that ſinfull citie: there ſhall not be left one ſtone vpon an other, which ſhall not be throwne downe. This calamitie alſo ſhall not there be wanting,
                     Luc. 19.44. when there ſhall be no ſence, no member of the body left without his torment: for euen as the wicked haue giuen

their members, as weapōs of vnrighteouſnes, vnto ſinne: So the order of Gods iuſtice,
                     Rom. 6.13. requireth that no mēber ſhould be free from his proper &amp; deſerued puniſhment. So the vnchaſt eyes, ſo the eares which lay open to detractions and ſlanders; So the deceitfull tongue, which vttered ſo many lies, &amp; falſehoods, ſparing neither the ſame of widdowe, wife, virgin, or any other; ſo the body which was effeminate &amp; weakened with ſo many pleaſures and delights, ſhall there receiue their ſeuerall torments, according to the qualitie of the offence. Where that ſhall be fulfilled which the ſpirit of God ſaith: In as much as ſhe glorified her ſelfe and liued in pleaſure,
                  
                     Reu. 18.7. 
                  ſo much giue ye to her torment and ſorrowe: and for euery member vpon which the fabricke of mans body, (as an edifice built with ſtones) conſiſteth, ſhall receiue worthy and peculiar puniſhment.
               If then Gods temporal Iudgemēts in this life, which manifeſt his hatred of all iniquitie, ſhould breede in vs a deteſtation of ſin, how much more ſhould the conſideration of his eternall puniſhments (wherof the other as I ſaid are but a ſhadowe,) be an effectual remedie againſt al vngodlines, &amp; plant the filiall and healthfull feare of God in

our hearts? This is it which the Lord himſelfe requireth of vs.
               
                  
                     Mat. 
                     
                        •
                     0.
                        •
                     8.
                  Feare not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule: but rather feare him which is able to deſtroy both body and ſoule in hell.
               
               What hope is then left for thoſe forlorne wretches inuironed with ſo many torments? what will they doe: whither will they flie? what counſaile will they take? will they flie to the remedie of repentance? but now the time of repentance is paſt, and the day of vengeance is come; will they then ſeeke for ſhelter at Gods mercy, which is the onely refuge and ſolace in all miſeries? but this life onely is the time of mercy and pardon, but then is the time of wrath and iudgement.
               Let vs not (beloued) ſuffer the day of this life which God in his mercy hath lent vs, to ſeeke peace, pardon, and reconſiliation, vnprofitably to ſlippe away, leaſt the day of wrath, vengeance, and irreuocable deſtruction ſurpriſe vs at vnawares: The day of this life is the time of Gods gratious viſitation,
                     Luc. 1.37. allotted vs, to ſerue him in holines and righteouſnes all the daies of our life, ſaith holy Zachariah: not onely omnibus diebus,
                  
all the daies; but omnibus diebus noſtris, (ſaith a writer) all our daies: for the time of this mortall life is giuen vnto vs to ſerue the Lord in all holy conuerſation, making prouiſion for the life eternall; for death will ſhortly arreſt vs, when there ſhal be no more place, nor time of repentance: therefore ſaith our Sauiour; The night commeth when none can worke.
                  
                     Ioh 9.4. 2. Cor. 6.2 
                  Behold now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of ſaluation.
               
               But to returne againe to the words of the texte? why did God inflict this horrible puniſhment vpon Ieruſalem and the whole Nation of the Iewes? The Lord himſelfe giueth the reaſon: becauſe thou kneweſt not the time of thy viſitation. The Lord in his mercy did many waies viſite thē, both by proſperitie and aduerſitie, as in part I haue before diſcourſed. And laſtly,
                     Luc. 1.17. he viſited them from an high, by ſending to them his onely ſonne IESVS CHRIST, who brought with him all good things, by which he illuminated them that ſate in darkenes and in the ſhadowe of death, and freely offered them his graces and ſaluation. Which ineſtimable benefits, they were ſo farre off from acknowledging, that they reiected and crucified the Author of ſo

great a ſaluation, as their forefathers perſecuted all the Prophets before them.
               It may ſeeme ſtrange (will ſome ſay) that in the midſt of this publike ioy and applauſe of the people, CHRIST wept at his comming to Ieruſalem, which at any other time we neuer reade that he did, though he was many times before in the citie: the cauſe hereof is eaſily to be giuen. The Lord came at this time moſt louingly to viſite this citie, and to performe all things which the Prophets foretolde of him, to conſummate whatſoeuer was promiſed of the Meſſias, and to manifeſt his infinite loue to the poſteritie of Abraham: yea towards all men, being now readie to giue his life a ranſome for the ſinnes of the whole world.
               This mercifull viſitation they would in no wiſe knowe, wherefore there was nothing more to be expected, but the ſeueritie of Gods wrath and iudgements to fall vpon them which before he had threatned.
                     
                        
                           •
                        h. 8.21. Luc. 17.22. As, I goe my way and ye ſhall ſeeke me, and you ſhall die in your ſinnes. And, The daies will come, that you ſhall deſire to ſee one of the daies of the ſonne of man, and ye ſhall not ſee it. And againe; O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, which killeſt

the Prophets,
                  
                     Mat. 23.37. 
                  and ſtoneſt them which were ſent vnto thee, how often would I haue gathered thy Children together, as the henne gathereth her chickens vnder her wings, and ye would not: behold your habitation ſhall be left vnto you deſolate. Againe: Ye daughters of Ieruſalem,
                  
                     Luc. 23.28. 
                  weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelues, and for your children: for behold, the daies will come, when men ſhall ſay, bleſſed are the barraine, and the wombe that neuer bare, and the pappes that neuer gaue ſucke.
               
               All theſe euills were at hand, yea euen at the doore, puniſhment could not long be deferred, ſeeing Gods gratious viſitation was contemned. This did CHRIST foreſee as if it were preſent, namely, that Ieruſalem ſhould come with that whole Nation into vtter deſolation: without environed with the enemie: within, afflicted with ſeditions and factions, that ſo many thouſands ſhould periſh with the ſword, famine, and peſtilence, that the remnant ſhould be ſcattered abroad through the whole world, ſolde, and be made a ſpectacle vnto all Nations, this their miſerie, this pittifull Sauiour knewe to be at hand, and bewailed the ſame.
               
                  
                  Two neceſſary obſeruations to be conſidered.This offereth to our view two neceſſarie obſeruations, to be ſeriouſly conſidered of all true feeling Chriſtian hearts:
               Firſt, how fearefully God is wont to puniſh  ingratitude and incredulitie.
               
                   Secondly, from whence all miſerie in the world, as famine, ſword, peſtilence, ſtrange diſeaſes, and all euills both of body and ſoule proceed.
               
                   Will ye know how ſeuerely God puniſheth the ingratitude and incredulitie of men?Ingratitude. Surely with ſpirituall blindnes, a moſt terrible and grieuous plague: and what is that blindnes? The moſt fearefull of all the reſt, when for our ſinnes God taketh the light of his grace and holy ſpirit from vs, and giueth vs not vnderſtanding hearts,A moſt grieuous puniſhment. that we might knowe the time of our viſitation, and the things which pertaine to our peace. When men cannot foreſee, nor ſee in time, neither good nor euill, happines, nor miſerie. Their good they ſee not before it be loſt and gone, their euills they foreſee not, before they fall vpon them, and light on their heads, to their irreuocable deſtruction, ſo that they cannot ſhun or avoide them: and is not this a plague of all plagues? What more vnhappie then when

a man hath many good things, and yet ſeeth them not, nor knoweth them, much leſſe can conuert them to his vſe and profit? what more fearefull, then when all euills, deſtructions and miſeries, hangeth ouer our heads, yea euen at the doore, and yet we ſee them not, nor will knowe them that we might eſcape them? And ſo was it with the people of the Iewes, (as it is alwaies with wicked men) they had CHRIST the Sonne of God, and Sauiour among them, and with him all goodnes, eternall ſaluation, and God himſelfe, yet they did not ſee him, they would not knowe him, they would not beleeue in him, before Chriſt with the kingdome of God and all goodnes departed from them, and all miſeries ouerwhelmed them, warres, famine, ſword and peſtilence, which vtterly deſtroyed the citie and whole Nation;Ioſephus as Ioſephus who was preſent, at that time in the citie during the ſiege reporteth, that one million periſhed with the ſword, and famine, and after the ſacking of that goodly citie (which was ſo ruinated and laide waſte, that there was not left one ſtone vpon an other, ſo that all that beheld it, euen to this day, may ſay:

                     O quam periere ruinae?
               
               How are the ruines ruinated? there were ſolde for ſlaues by the Romanes, 97000. which were diſperſed and ſcattered into all Nations. So ſeuerely did God puniſh this Natiō for their incredulitie &amp; ingratitude, with blindnes, that they could not enioy the graces and fauours which God offered them, nor eſcape his puniſhments denounced againſt them.
                     Heb▪
                      10.31. So fearefull a thing is it to fall into the hands of the liuing God. O how horrible a puniſhment is this Pôroſis Cardhias obduration, hardnes of hart, and blindnes, when God taketh away his grace and light from men, which they refuſe, and wlll not walke therein, and giueth them ouer to Sathan to be blinded, who ſo darkeneth their cogitations, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the Gentiles) that being paſt feeling,
                  
                     Epheſ. 4.18.19. 
                  they giue themſelues to worke all vncleannes, euen with greedines. And the cauſe of this Analgeſias and loſſe of feeling, the Apoſtle teacheth to be obſtinacie, and perſeuerance in ſinne againſt conſcience, ſo that at length they begin obducere callum, to growe to hardnes of heart, that as if their conſcience were ſeared with a hotte yron, they are touched with no ſence and feeling of their ſinnes any

more, nay the wickednes they commit againſt the firſt or ſecond table, they feare not to ieſt at, and defend, as if it were well done, calling good euill, and euill good. And this is the extreameſt degree to perdition, and may well be called, not onely the moſt greeuous of all ſinnes, but alſo the cauſe of all ſinnes,
                     Rom. 11.8 and a puniſhment of ſinne in this life.
               This the Apoſtle calleth; Spiritum Catanózeôs, Spirit of ſlumber, eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and eares that they ſhould not heare. O fearefull eſtate.
               And from whence is ſo great blindnes in the world at this day among ſuch as profeſſe chriſtianitie, that whoredomes, murthers, theft, periuries, horrible ſwearing and blaſphemies, vſurie and oppreſſion, fraude, deceit, and vndermining one of an other, and all other ſins againſt conſcience, are daily practiſed without ſhame or any feeling at all? Surely theſe are manifeſt ſignes of Gods wrath, purſuing vs for our ingratitude and contempt of his graces, giuing vs ouer as incorrigible, vnto the power of Sathan and hardnes of heart. And is not this a miſerable blindnes, that theſe ſins haue brought vs to the very brincke of

the pit of deſtruction, and without repentance muſt needs caſt vs ſhortly therein, and yet we will not ſee it, that we might auoide the danger, nor the ſnares the diuell layeth before vs, that we might eſcape them, but run on ſtill in our wickednes, to our irreuocable ruine, refuſing to knowe,
                  
                     Rom. 2.4.5. 
                  in this our day, the things which pertaine vnto our peace: but, after the hardnes of our heart that cannot repent, heape ſtill vnto our ſelues wrath, againſt the day of wrath. Surely, it is to be feared, that the Lords controuerſie, which he hath with this land, is ſo great as that he had with that ſinfull Nation, becauſe there is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the Land, by ſwearing and lying, ſtealing,
                  
                     Hoſ. 4.12. 
                  and whoring, they breake forth, and blood toucheth blood. The Lord for his infinite mercy ſake lighten the darkenes of our  mindes, and giue vs feeling and vnderſtanding hearts.
               Secondly, we are here taught, from whence warres, famine, ſcarcitie of all things, the ſword and ſtrange diſeaſes, peſtilence and all euills in the world ſpring and proceed: namely, for our ingratitude towards God, becauſe we will not knowe the time of our viſitation, nor the things that pertaine to our true peace. This gratious viſitation

began when the ſonne of God tooke our fleſh vpon him, and was borne in the world: through the tender mercy of our God,
                  
                     Luc. 1.78. 
                  whereby the day ſpring from an high hath viſited vs, ſaith holy Zachariah: which benefite was ſo great, that all the wit of men and Angells is not able to expreſſe it ſufficiently, and this louing viſitation as yet endureth, he ceaſeth not ſtill to viſite vs: but how little doe we conſider thereof? what thankfulneſſe haue we ſhewed? how little are we bettered thereby? how ſmall is our care to ſerue him in holines and righteouſnes all the daies of our life? yet to this very end our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt viſited vs, ſaith his Apoſtle,
                     Tit. 2.14. 
                  who gaue himſelfe for vs that he might redeeme vs from all iniquitie, and purge vs to be a peculiar people vnto himſelfe, zealous of good workes. No maruell then that we haue had ſo many yeares of dearth, vnſeaſonable weather, horrible tempeſts, ſhipwrackes, peſtilence, ſtrange diſeaſes, &amp;c. God hath but now begun, he doth in fatherly affection but ſhake the rodde ouer our heads▪ our ſinnes are the cauſe, which except we remoue, the effects will not ceaſe, patientia laeſa fit furor, except he ſee amendment, his long patience ſhal be conuerted into the furie of his wrath. Let then

                  Ieruſalem and the people of the Iewes, be a warning vnto vs. Happie is he whom other mens harmes can cauſe to beware.
               
                  The vſe.The vſe is, that we applie theſe things vnto our ſelues, and learne to be wiſe by the puniſhments of others.
               A long time now hath the Goſpell bene purely preached vnto vs, but with what fruite? How fewe of vs doe acknowledge as we ought, this gratious viſitation of the Lord? Where is our obedience, reuerence, and thankefulnes due vnto Gods holy word? where is our zeale and loue we owe vnto Gods miniſters? where is our reformation of life? How many ſcoffers are there among vs? How many are there which thinke themſelues, in the arrogancie of their ſpirit, to be wiſer then their teachers? How many are there which come rather as criticall carpers and cenſurers of the Preacher, then fruitfull hearers? What contempt and neglect of the holy exerciſe of publike prayer, the chiefeſt dutie of a true Chriſtian, to which God hath made ſo many ſweete promiſes, and ſo earneſtly commaundeth? How many are there which holde that the whole dutie

of a Chriſtian conſiſteth in hearing onely, without any care to conuert their hearing into knowledge, and their knowledge, into action? How many ſwiniſh Epicures are there to be found de grege porci, which liue rather like hogges then Chriſtians? Shall we thinke that God, the iuſt reuenger of all impietie, will euer be ſilent at theſe and many other ſinnes, which ſorrowe of heart forbiddeth me to vtter? No, no, God will not be mocked, he is the ſame, he changeth not. Let vs therefore yet at length acknowledge the time of our viſitation, and let vs conſider the ſeaſon, that it is now time that we ſhould riſe from ſleepe,
                  
                     Rom. 13.11.12.13. verſ.
                   
                  for now is our ſaluation nearer then when we beleeued, the night is paſſed, the day is at hand, let vs caſt away the workes of darkenes, and put vpon vs the armour of light, ſo that we walke honeſtly as in the day, not in gluttonie and drunkennes, ſtrife and enuying.
               
               Here againe, is ſeriouſly to be conſidered, that Chriſt mentioneth two daies or times,
                  Two daies. but very vnlike to each other.
               The firſt is the time of grace,The time o
                        •
                      grace, the time of wrath. wherein we liue; The other the time of wrath and iudgement. To the firſt time, which is the time preſent wherein we liue, our Sauiour

giueth, three names: he calleth it the time of our viſitation, the day of peace, or which is giuen vs to prouide for our peace: And our day. It is called the time of viſitation, becauſe God in his onely beloued ſonne, of his infinite mercy and loue hath viſited vs. It is called the day of peace, becauſe in it Chriſt hath with his owne precious blood reconciled vs vnto God, and becauſe we ſhould therein ſeeke forth things that pertaine vnto our true peace. He calleth it our day, becauſe our gratious God hath allotted this time for repentance,2. Pet. 1.10. that we might giue all diligence to make our calling and election ſure, to ſerue the Lord in righteouſnes and holines, to lay vp treaſures in heauen, to labour by repentance to be truely reconciled vnto God, to make prouiſion for the eternall day in the life to come, which neuer ſhall haue ende. He calleth this in the ſingular number a day, becauſe the time of this life is ſhort, but a moment, a vapour, ſmoke, a dreame,
                     Iob. 14. a thought, a thing of nothing, which ſhould moue vs (becauſe the time is ſhort) to worke the more earneſtly in the worke of the Lord, to walke the more warily in the way towards heauen,
                     Phil. 2.15. 
                  that we may be blameleſſe and pure as the ſonne of God,

when we ſhall appeare before him, to labour to adorne our ſoules with vertues, to take heed,
                  
                     Mar. 13.33. 
                  watch, and pray, for we knowe not when the time is: After the Apoſtles counſaile, to forget that which is behinde, and ſpeedily to endeuour our ſelues vnto that which is before,
                  
                     Phil. 3.13.14. 
                  and followe hard towards the marke for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.
               
               Leaſt we fall into the other day,
                  The day of wrath and Iudgement. which is the day of Iudgement, the day of wrath, which ſhall be no more called our day, but the day of the Lord, a day of trouble and heauines, a day of deſtruction and deſolation,
                  
                     Zepan. 1.15. Ioel. 2.11. 
                  a day of obſcuritie and darkenes, this day of the Lord is great and terrible, who may abide it?
               
               This day, the Lord expreſſeth in the plurall number [for the daies ſhall come vpon thee] becauſe the puniſhments ſhall be great and without end. This day the Lord hath ordained for them which contemne this preſent acceptable time of grace, the day of ſaluation, the time of his gratious viſitation, and refuſeth to knowe, in this their day, the things that pertaine vnto their peace.
               
               There is none ſo wicked,No man ſo wicked but hath his day. but the louing God, who willeth not the death of a ſinner, giueth him his day, if he had the grace to knowe it.
               
                  Thou biting Vſurer, thou beaſtly whoremonger, thou blody murtherer, thou prowling thiefe, thou cruell oppreſſor, thou couetous Caitiffe, thou ſwiniſh Epicure, thou that liueſt in enuie, malice, &amp;c.
               O conſider, in time I ſay conſider, that the mercifull GOD giueth thee a day: The day of this life, to prouide, by Repentance, for thy peace, whenſoeuer the Lorde by his Preachers out of his holy Word, or by his holy motions, Diuine inſpirations, ſtings of conſcience, &amp;c. knocketh at the dore of thy heart; Thinke then that this is thy day. Oh ſlippe not this occaſion: Let not this time vnfruitfully paſſe away: Open to this ſweete Gueſt, leaſt for thy contempt of his gratious Viſitation, thou fall into the dayes of his fearfull Wrath and terible indignation.2. Cor. 26. 
                  Beholde now is the accepted time, beholde now is the day of ſaluation.
               
               But leauing the Iewes in their infidelitie and hardneſſe of heart, Let vs come vnto our ſelues, (brethren) whom the Lord is wont many times to viſite.
               
                  
                     Pſal. 106.4.Hee viſiteth vs, when by his benefites he exciteth vs to loue him. Viſite vs (ſaieth the prophet) with thy ſaluation. Hee viſiteth vs, when he ſendeth vnto vs, teachers &amp; miniſters

of his word, to ſhew vs the way of Eternall felicitie. So when he raiſed vp the widowes Sonne from Death, the people glorified GOD, ſaying, A great Prophet is raiſed vp among vs, and God hath viſited his People, to whome he ſent ſuch a Prophet and teacher of Righteouſnes.
               He viſiteth vs, being ſecure, careleſſe, and nothing bettered by his Worde and benefites, when he chaſtiſeth vs with calamities, croſſes and plagues, to the intent hee may recall vs into the way of Righteouſneſſe: Of this Viſitation in the perſon of God, ſpeaketh the princely Prophet;
                     Pſal. 89.30. 
                  But if his Children forſake my Lawe, and walke not in my Iudgements: if they breake my Statutes, and keepe not my Commandements: then will I viſite their tranſgreſſions with the Rod, and their inquities with Scourges.
               
               Sometimes he viſiteteth vs by his preachers, which are his Ambaſſadors, to deliuer his meſſage vnto vs: Sometimes by giuing vs good Motions and holie Inſpirations: Sometime by the examples of others, that beholding before our Eyes their puniſhments, we ſhould be the more warie how we fall into ſinne. For ſo the Lord ſaith by his Prophet Ieremie:
                  
                     Ier. 3.8. 
                  When I ſaw how that by all

occaſions, rebellious Iſrael had played the harlot, I caſt her away, and gaue her a bill of diuorſement, yet her rebellious ſister Iudah was not afraide, but played the harlot alſo. And thus the Lord greeuouſly threatneth by his Prophet, that Iudah would not beware by an others harme, and acknowledge Gods viſitation in her ſiſters puniſhment, as it were ſeeing fire in her next neighbours roofe, according to the prouerbe:
               Tunc tua res agitur paries cum proximus ardet.
               
                  
                     Horatius.When fired is thy neighbours wall,
                  Thou knoweſt thy danger is not ſmall.
               
               So that there is no wicked man, but one time or other hath a time of viſitation, as Ieruſalem had her time of viſitation by Chriſts doctrine, examples and miracles: ſo there is no ſinner, at whoſe heart God ſometime doth not knocke, though they doe not all alike receiue his viſitation.
               
               After this manner the Lord is wont to viſite his people, to whoſe voice and gratious viſitation, many giue ſo deafe an eare, that they are neither wonne by his benefites,

mollified by his admonitions, mooued by his inward inſpirations, nor by his plagues and puniſhments will be reduced into the way of righteouſnes. Continuall cuſtome in ſinne, hath conuerted nature into ſo obſtinate an habite, vt callos in anima contrax erint.
               
               (As the prouerbe is) their very hearts are ſo hard as brawne, altogether inſenſible in their wickednes. That ſtrong armed man which beſiegeth the fort of their hearts, diligently laboureth to ſtoppe euery paſſage, that the light of Gods holy ſpirit cannot peirce into them.
               The nature and might of that enemie, is miſtically ſhadowed out by God himſelfe, in the deſcription of the monſter Leuiathan, his ſcales are like ſtrong ſhieldes,
                  
                     Iob. 41.16 
                  and are ſure ſealed, one is ſet to an other, that no winde may come betweene them. Such as this olde Sepent is, ſuch are his children whom he poſſeſſeth: he fortifieth the holde of their heart, as it were with hard ſcales, that no ſpiritual artillerie may penetrate the ſame; lay before them Gods threatnings for ſin, the terrors of hell for the reprobate, the ioyes of heauen for the penitent, &amp;c. They are no more moued quam ſi parieti loqueris,
                  
then if thou ſpakeſt to the Wall, as if Hell and Death had alreadie laide holde and ſeazed vpon them.
               The Booke of God, aſſureth vs that the cauſe of their captiuitie heretofore, was the contempt of Gods Worde and Prophets, when all the people were miſerablie caryed away into Babell;
                  2. Chron. 36.16. 
                  But they mocked the Meſſengers of the Lorde, and contemned his Words, and miſuſed his Prophets, vntill the wrath of the Lorde aroſe againſt his people, and till there was no remedie.
               
               And the Sonne of God ſaieth heere, That the cauſe of their woefull and finall deſtruction, whereof I haue ſpoken, was alſo, becauſe they refuſed to know the time of their viſitation: and therefore perſecuted his meſſengers. And laſtly, the Sonne of God himſelfe, which he bewailed; O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, which killeſt the prophets, &amp; ſtoneſt them which are ſent vnto thee, how often would I haue gathered thy childrē together,
                  
                     Luc. 13.34. 
                  as the Hen gathereth her brood vnder her wings, &amp; ye would not.
               
               But (ô good God) if we compare the ſins of England at this day, with the ſinnes of the Iewes, how can wee chuſe but feare &amp; tremble? Conſidering that not Ieruſalem onely, but alſo England, is plunged in as deepe

obliuion of the Time of her Viſitation, as euer that ſinfull Citie was.
               Surely (Beloued,) griefe of heart willeth me to ſit ſtill in ſilence, and wiſh with holie Ieremie, that my Head were full of water, and mine eyes a Fountaine of Teares, that I might weepe Day and Night for the ſinnes of this Land: Yet ſithe Zeale enforceth mee to ſpeake, I had rather vſe the wordes of a zealous Preacher,M. G. W. in a ſer. at Pauls croſſe. An. 1609. fol. 26.
                   vttered before the greateſt Auditorie in this Land to this purpoſe, then inſiſt vpon mine owne heerein. The Word of God is a reproach vnto men, they haue no delight in it. And this want of delight in the Meſſage, maketh the Meſſengers to be deſpiſed.
               Are not Gods Cryers reckoned but as Caſſandraes propheſies? His Ambaſſadors, worſe then Iustinians Orators? Yea, no better then the Filthe and Offſcowring of all things vnto this Day?
                  1. Cor. 4.13.
               
               Euery curſed Tobiah and Samballat, is enuying at our Spirituall buildings: Euery ſcoffing Michol,
                  
                     Nehem. 4.1. maketh a jeaſt of our preaching: Euery ſacrilegious Ammonite, is clipping of our garments: Euery preſumptuous Chorah and Abiram,
                  
                     
                        •
                     . Sam. 10 is carping at our preferment.
                     Num. 16. It is reported in Eccleſiaſticall
                  
hiſtories, that at what time Conſtantine that worthie Patron of the Church, had inueſted the poore diſtreſſed Miniſters with temporall patrimonies, one was heard to ſay: Hodie venenum cecidit in eccleſiam. But now the Miſcreants of this age haue found a remedie for that diſeaſe, and haue giuen vs tryacle ynough to purge out all this poyſon, which hath neuer ceaſed vntill it hath extracted almoſt bowells and all. What the Palmer-worme Papiſt with his Impropriations; and after him the Graſhopper Athieſt with his preſcriptions; and after him, the Cankerworme Patron, with his reſeruations; And laſt of all, the Caterpiller Cormorant with his illuſions; The Patrimonie of the Church like Pharaoes goodly kine, hath bene deuoured by ill fauoured, leane, and hungrie Nunſcions, and made like the deſcēt of Nabuchadnezzars Image,
                     Dan. 2.31. from golde to ſiluer, from ſiluer to braſſe, from braſſe to yron, from yron to claye. Hence it is that the word of God is no more regarded, becauſe the Meſſengers thereof are ſo much contemned, and the cauſe of all this is our ingratitude, becauſe we will not knowe the time of our viſitation.
               
               If he ſmote with ſo dreadfull a iudgement

                  Ananiah and Saphyrah his wife (ſaith a worthie and a reuerend Father of our Church) for withholding but part of the Church maintenāce which by themſelues was giuen, will he endure for euer, them that take what they neuer gaue? No, no,
                     Act. 5. and that ſhall they knowe, when peraduenture it will be too late to be ſorrie for it. Did theſe men ſee what my ſelfe haue ſeene, and diuers yet liuing, which can witnes the ſame as well as I, what twitching torments of a wounded conſcience, what helliſh gripes of diſpairing feare, neuer to ſee the face of God, but to periſh for euer with caſt awaies, ſome haue had for detaining but a ſmall portion of ſuch maintenance which now is thought the beſt cheat that can be caught, happily it would, nay ſurely it would, except hell and death had alreadie taken poſſeſſion, abate the luſt, and aſſwage the longing that they haue to deuoure the incouragements of learning, that yet remaine vnſpoyled in this land. But what they haue not ſeene in others, they may feele in themſelues too ſoone, and ſharpe, if nothing will perſwade them. Thou art dead O Sunanite, that intreatedſt thy husbād

to builde for the Prophet a chamber and to furniſh it; but thy memorie is bleſſed with God and man, and a witnes ſhalt thou be in the day of iudgement, againſt pullers downe of the houſes built by men and women of deuotion and pietie,2. Kings. 4.16. for the Prophets &amp; children of the Prophets. I ſpeake nothing at this time for breuities ſake, of adulterie, and whoredome, ſwearing, and forſwearing, drunkennes and riot, oppreſſion and crueltie, fraude &amp; deceit in buying and ſelling, which are ſo common in this land; The Lord be mercifull vnto vs, and giue vs grace betime by vnfained repentance, to auert the heauie wrath of God hanging ouer our heads.
               In that which I haue ſaid (brethren) we may behold the fruite that ſpringeth from this poyſoned roote of ſinne, and what is the reward thereof, how hateſome all wickednes is in the fight of God, which cauſed him to plucke vp his people whom he had planted, to caſt euen downe to hell, them whom he had aduanced, aboue all other Nations, and lifted vp to heauen. This ſhould worke in vs a deteſtation of ſinne, yea by all meanes to flie from ſinne as from a

Serpent,
                  
                     Eccle. 21.2. which is the cauſe of all miſerie in this life, and of eternall torments in the life to come; from ſinne (I ſay) an euill ſo full of loſſe and dammage,Sinne is full of loſſe, ſhame, ſorrowe, and bitternes. ſo full of ſhame and confuſion, ſo full of ſorrowe and bitternes, full of loſſe and dammage, becauſe it ſeparateth from God the Soueraigne good  of all: which is the greateſt loſſe that may be imagined: Your ſinnes haue ſeparated betweene you and your God.
                  
                     Eſa. 59 As the widowe and fatherles are expoſed to all wrong and oppreſſion, becauſe there are fewe that will ſtand in their defence,Similes. euen as a ſhip wanting a ſterne, Maſt, and Gouernour, is toſſed with the tempeſt, and at laſt daſhed on the rockes: ſo the wretched ſoule, deſtitute through ſinne, of Gods grace, fauour, and protection, is laide open to the waues of temptations, and toſſed with the tempeſts of the diuell, world, and fleſh, and finally ſuffereth horrible ſhipwracke.
               Sinne is alſo full of ſhame and confuſion: for ſuch is the filthines of ſinne, in it ſelfe, that it ſeeketh corners, walketh masked, and loueth the darkenes: Qui male agit odit lucem, he that euill doth hateth the light.
                  
                     Ioh. 3. Sinne and ſhame be brothers of one birth. Olde

father Adam teacheth,
                     Gen. 3. who as ſoone as he had ſinned, ſought to hide himſelfe from God,Simile. and couered himſelfe with Figge-tree leaues, euen as they which haue vlcerous and filthie bodies, ſeeke by all meanes to hide the ſame, and would not haue their diſeaſe knowne: ſo al wicked liuers, though happily they are not aſhamed at their ſinfull actions, to be wicked, yet they bluſh to be reputed wicked. Diogenes on a time ſeeing a young man in a Tauerne running into an inner roome, for that he was aſhamed to be ſeene, called vnto him; Quo interius fugeris, hoc magis eris in popina, the more thou runneſt inward, the farther thou art in the Tauerne. So a wicked man, the more he ſeeketh to hide himſelfe▪ within himſelfe, ſo much the more is he the ſame that he is.
               
                   Sinne is alſo full of bitternes &amp; ſorrowe; as truely ſaith S. Auguſtine:
                  Aug. conſ. lib. 1. cap. 12.
                   
                  Voluiſti domine &amp; verè ſic eſt, vt paena ſibi ſit omnis animus inordinatus: Thou wouldeſt Lord, haue it ſo, (and indeed ſo it is) that euery inordinate minde ſhould be a torment vnto it ſelfe. Knowe and behold, (ſaith Ieremie in the perſon of God) that it is an euill and a bitter

thing, that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God,
                  
                     Ier. 12.19. 
                  and that my feare is not in thee, ſaith the Lorde God of Hoſts. As Iob in all his miſeries, neuer wanted a Meſſenger that would bring him euill tidings: So in euery ſinne, an euill meſſenger is euer at hand, which woundeth and teareth the conſcience.Simile. Sinne then is like an Harlot, of whom that mirror of wiſedome ſpeaketh:
                     Pro. 5.3. 
                  Whoſo Lips droppe like an honie combe, but her end is bitter as Wormewood, her feete goe downe to death, and her ſteppes take holde on Hell. Sinne is like an itching Vlcer,Sinne like an itching Vlcer. which feeleth a little pleaſure whiles it is rubbed, but at laſt it ſmarteth the more,Simile. and fretteth the Fleſh. Sinne is like poyſoned Wine, which ſeemeth pleaſant to the taſte, but the poyſon killeth in the ende.
               This gnawing of conſcience, an inſeparable companion of ſinne, the Lorde threatneth vnto the wiced:
                     Leu. 16.17.36. verſ.
                   
                  Yee ſhall flie when none purſueth you. Againe, The ſound of a Leafe ſhaken, ſhall chaſe them away. Can any thing bee ſpoken more ſignificantly, to expreſſe the terrors of a guilty conſcience? This plainly proueth if there were nothing elſe▪ how full of bitternes and ſorrow ſinne is: yet in many other reſpects, the euills that proceed of

ſinne may be conſidred, becauſe it bringeth eternall puniſhment; becauſe it weakeneth the powers of the ſoule; becauſe our deſires are accompanied with infinite cares, and troubles: becauſe it onely maketh a ſeparation betweene God and man: it cauſed the ſonne of God to deſcend from heauen, to be made man, and to ſuffer the ignominious death of the Croſſe, becauſe the haynous enormitie of ſinne, was ſuch, that it could be expiated by no other meanes but by the blood of the onely begotten ſonne of God.Timon. 
                  Timon that Miſanthrôpos, and hater of men, being asked why hee ſo hated all men, anſwered, Merito improbos odi; reliquos autem quia improbos non oderunt. I hate wicked men and that worthilie, and the reſt I hate, becauſe they doe not hate wicked men.Publius. Mimus. It was alſo a ſaying of Publius Mimus: Tolerabilior eſt qui mori iubet, quam qui male viuere. He is more tollerable that commandeth vs to die, then he that willeth vs to liue wickedly. Here ye ſee that the very Heathen by the light of nature, ſawe and taught the horrour and filthines of ſinne, and ſhall doubtles riſe in iudgement to our condemnation: which beſide the inſtinct

of nature, haue alſo the light of Gods word, yet make ſmall conſcience of many ſinnes which they ſo deteſted.
               The vſe (brethren) of all that I haue ſaid is,The vſe. that laying before our eyes Gods extreame hatred of ſinne, manifeſted in this wofull ruine and deſtruction of the people of the Iewes, whom he made a fearefull example of his wrath to all poſterities, that we would at length learne to be wiſe by others harmes, walke more warily, take heede how we offend ſo great and terrible a God, beware of ſecuritie in our ſinnes, and betime betake our ſelues to repentance: for theſe iudgements of God, do not onely pertaine vnto them, but much more vnto vs, which by CHRIST the Meſſias haue receiued far greater benefits then they did: For as much as the Goſpell excelleth the lawe, ſo far our benefites exceede theirs. This being ſo, what remaineth, but that we ſhould hearkē to the Apoſtles counſaile:
                     Heb. 2.12. 
                  Wherfore we ought diligently to giue heede to the things which we haue heard, leaſt at any time we ſhould let them ſlip, for if the word ſpokē by Angells was ſtedfaſt, and euery tranſgreſſion and diſobedience, receiued a iuſt recompence of reward, how ſhall we

eſcape which neglect ſo great ſaluation? For if the abuſe of Gods benefites and their ingratitude brought vpon this people ſo heauie a deſtruction: what ſhould not we feare of God the ſame Iudge, which haue receiued farre greater benefites, and yet are bettered nothing thereby: but ſtill remaine vnthankefull? What ſhould we feare doe I ſay? Doe we not ſee the ſame calamitie and vaſtation to haue fallen vpon the greateſt part of all Chriſtendome at this day?
               Once in the flouriſhing ſtate of the Romane Empire, the Chriſtian religion was extended almoſt through the whole world, but at this day, how ſmall a portion is left, the barbarous Turke for our ſinnes ſtill enchroaching vpon vs? Doe we not here plainely ſee, the ſame God, in the ſame cauſe, to haue begun the ſame iudgement among vs? what cauſe then haue we to hearken to this admoniſhion of the Apoſtle,
                     Rom. 11.17.20.21. Noli altum. ſapere. 
                  though ſome of the branches be broken off, and thou being a wilde oliue tree, waſt graft in for them: be not high minded, for if God ſpared not the naturall branches, take heede leaſt he ſpare not thee.
               
               
                  The Iewes once were the naturall branches; the legitimate children of God: we were ſtrangers to the teſtament: they were the naturall branches of the Oliue, we were but graffes: if then God dealt ſo ſeuerely with the naturall branches, when they ſinned againſt him: what ſhould we looke for which are fallen into the like ſinnes? ſurely, we may iuſtly feare greater puniſhments. For ſo ſaith the Lord by his Prophet Ieremie,
                  
                     Ier. 25.29. 
                  For loe I begin to plague a citie where my name is called vpon, and ſhould you goe free? ye ſhall not goe quit, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes. And for the beating downe of ſecuritie, let vs conſider that this miſerie fell vpon Ieruſalem when they were moſt ſecure in their ſinnes; for when they thought that the heauens had buried in obliuion, the blood of the Prophets, and the cruell death of the ſonne of God, then when they leaſt ſurmiſed, God raiſed vp the whole power of the Romaines, vnder the conduct of Veſpatian and Hadrian, which vtterly ſubuerted the Cittie Ieruſalem, with fiftie other fenced Cities,Vide Dione Caſſi in vita Hadriani. and eight hundred foureſcore and fiue walled Townes of the kingdome of Iudea, in which they left

ſcarce one foote of the wall ſtanding. Gods vengeance was neuer ſo neare the rich man, as when he was moſt ſecure; and vaunted to himſelfe, when he ſaide to his ſoule; Soule, thou haſt much goods layed vp in ſtore for many yeares: liue at eaſe, eate, drinke,
                  
                     Luc. 12.19. 
                  and be merrie. Scarce had he vttered, or conceiued in minde this thought, before he heard this voyce: O foole, this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee, whoſe then ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt prouided?
               
               Let vs therefore (beloued) hauing alwaies theſe examples before our eyes, begin yet at laſt to be wiſe by others harmes, and this preſent opportunitie of repentance which God in his mercy hath lent vs, let vs not ſuffer vnfruitfully to paſſe away, let vs neuer forget this ſaying of our Lord: The Night commeth when none can worke: but while the day of ſaluation laſteth,
                     Ioh. 9.4. while the Iudge himſelfe moſt louingly calleth vs, and offereth his free grace and mercy vnto vs, flie chearefully vnto him in ſerious repentance, ſtudying to ſerue him, in holines and righteouſnes all the daies of our life. Which God graunt

for his infinite mercy ſake, to whom with the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons in one moſt glorious Trinitie, one God in vnitie, might, and Maieſtie, be all praiſe, power and dominion, now and for euer, Amen.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            LONDON, Printed by Thomas Creede, for Arthur Iohnſon, dwelling neere the great North doore of S. Paules Church, at the ſigne of the white Horſe. 1613.
            
         
      
   

