
   
      
         
            The Christian conflict and conquest set forth in a sermon at Pauls-crosse, upon Sunday the 19th of Iuly, 1635. By W.E.B.D. of St Mary Hall in Oxford
            Evans, William, b. 1598 or 9.
         
         
            
               1636
            
         
         Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00459
            STC 10595
            ESTC S114790
            99850013
            99850013
            15196
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00459)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15196)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1270:30)
         
         
            
               
                  The Christian conflict and conquest set forth in a sermon at Pauls-crosse, upon Sunday the 19th of Iuly, 1635. By W.E.B.D. of St Mary Hall in Oxford
                  Evans, William, b. 1598 or 9.
               
               [8], 70, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by Leonard Lichfield, and are to be sold by William Webb,
                  Oxford :
                  A.D. 1636.
               
               
                  W.E. = William Evans. To the reader signed: William Evans.
                  Signatures: [A]-K⁴ (-A1 and K4, blanks?).
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-07
            Haley PiersonSampled and proofread
         
            2005-07
            Haley PiersonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
CHRISTIAN
CONFLICT, AND
CONQVEST.
            
               SET
FORTH IN A SERMON AT
Pauls-Croſſe, upon Sunday the 19th
of IVLY, 1635.
            By W. E. B. D. of St Mary Hall in Oxford.
            
            OXFORD,
Printed by Leonard Lichfield, and are to be
ſold by William Webb. A. D. 1636.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE READER.
            
               Chriſtian Reader,
            
            
               IN the entrance of our Chriſtian
profeſsion, we have all promiſed
to fight vnder Chriſts banner, againſt
all Antichriſtian power.
And namely, againſt the fleſh,
the world, and the Devill. To
make good this promiſe, I haue
ventured (being thereunto called) to fight a combate
with theſe adverſaries, in an eminent place, before
many and great ſpectators: Having ſo done, I remembred
that I muſt finiſh my courſe, and keepe the
faith, or elſe I cannot ſay with the Apoſtle, that I
haue fought the good fight,1. Tim. 4. 7. 8. and ſo expect the crowne
of righteouſneſse. Therefore having begun contendere
verbis, to encounter with theſe adverſaries, by
way of preaching; I reſolved further pugnare manu,
to ſet upon them, by way of writing. But here
peradventure you will ſay, Quorſum haec? to what
end is this writing! There are bookes written already
of all kind of arguments, and of this alſo. I grant,
there are ſo. But yet it doth not follow for all that,
that there ſhould be no more written, for as long as
the Devill and his Agents, doe dayly multiply their
temptations, and thereof ſet forth ſtill new impresſions,
and editions, able to ſeduce, if it were posſible,



the very elect; I ſee no reaſon, but that the Miniſters,
and ſervants of Chriſt, ſhould be as forward to
multiply replies, and to ſet forth new anſweres to the
ſame. Sure I am, the Lords will and command is,
that we ſhould reſiſt the Divell;Iam. 4. 7. Epheſ. 4. 27. c. 6. 13. that we ſhould give
no place to his temptations; that we ſhould put on the
whole armour of God, that is, uſe all good meanes to
withſtand his wiles, and to repell his aſsaults. And
S. Auſtin doth instance in this meanes of writing,
ſaying, that in places infected with hereſie (or other
dangerous temptations) all men ſhould write,
that have any faculty therein, though it bee but the
ſame things in other words; that all ſorts of people,
among many bookes, might light upon ſome, and the
enemy in all places might have one, or other, to encounter
him. And the ſame Author further ſaith, utile
eſſe, that 'tis profitable,Vtile eſt plures à pluribus fieoi libros, diverſo stilo, ſed non diverſa fide. Etiam de iiſdem queſtionibus &amp;c. Auguſt. de Trinit. l. 1. c. 3. that there bee many bookes,
of many perſons, made of like matters, in a diverſe
ſtile &amp; method, ſo that they be not contrary, in a diverſe
faith; that from the ſame the truth may more
clearly appeare, to ſome in one manner, to ſome in another.
            Now that which S. Auſtin ſpeakes poſitively, ſaying,
utile eſſe, that it is profitable, that there be many
Bookes of many perſons, made of like matters, &amp;c. I
hope may be ſaid of mine. Certaine I am the matter is
profitable, and neceſsary for any mans study, that deſires
to approve himſelfe a good ſouldiour of Ieſus
Chriſt. And for the manner alſo, though it be not elegant,
yet here is order, which is the maine thing
requiſite in abattell. And for matter and manner, it
hath gained the hearing of honourable, learned, and



judicious auditours. Now if it may alſo gaine your
reading, and liking, I ſhall count my paines well bestowed,
and be the more encouraged to goe on in my
ſtudies, &amp; to ſet forth further, and larger testimony of
my deſire to doe you good. And verily my intention
was to preſent you with a larger teſtimony thereof at
this ſecond time, but I am faine to fall ſhort of that
purpoſe, and to deſire you to accept of this for the preſent,
as from
            
               Your unfained well-willer,
and in that I am able,
your well-doer
WILLIAM EVANS.
            
         
         
            
            Errata.
            PAge 13. line 5. read not for cannot, p. 24. l. 10. r. one Captaine f. our
Captaine, p. 35. l. 31. r. by being for being, p. 40. l. 17. r. overcharged f.
overchared. p▪ 58. l. 30. r. more care of f. more of, p. 69. l. 28. r. finall f. ſmall.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE CHRISTIAN CONflict
and Conqueſt.
            
               EPHES. C. 6. V. 12. 13.
               We wreſtle not againſt fleſh and bloud, but againſt
principalities and powers. Wherefore take unto
you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able
to withſtand &amp;c.
            
            
               STedfaſtneſſe of faith,The ſcope of the text. with
a direction how to ſtand
therein, and to withſtand
all the oppoſers thereof,
is the argument of the
Apoſtle in theſe words.
And this argument (Right
honourable, Right worſhipfull,
and beloved) I
thought the fitteſt for me to treat of, at this time,
in this place; in as much, as ye are all by profeſſion,
the ſervants and ſouldiers of Chriſt. And by
practiſe alſo his faithfull ſervants, for all I know. So
that I have no cauſe to incite you to begin, but rather
to continue in well doing: to continue Chriſts



faithfull ſervants and ſouldiers, unto your lives
end. This continuance is the Apoſtles, and my
ſcope.
            And the occaſion this:The occaſion. The Apoſtle, having in
the former part of this Epiſtle, delivered many
holy, and heavenly exhortations, as that wee
ſhould walke worthy of the vocation wherewith
we are called, c. 4. 1. That we ſhould endeavour
to keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace,
v. 2. That we ſhould put off the old man, even the
corruption of our nature, which is as old as mankind;
and to put on the new man, even Chriſt Ieſus,
with his merits, and manners, v. 22. 23. That
we ſhould have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull
works of darkeneſſe, but rather reprove them, c. 5.
v. 11. That we ſhould traine up thoſe that belong
to our charge, in the inſtruction, and feare of the
Lord, c. 6. 4. In a word, that we ſhould all live in
obedience, performing our ſeverall duties, to
each other, c. 5. 21. c. 6. 1. having delivered
theſe, and many other pious exhortations:
            And withall, perceiving that no man can ſet
himſelfe to follow theſe precepts, and to doe theſe
duties, but that he ſhall find many diſcouragemēts,
many lets and hinderances, ſome from fleſh and
blood within, others from Sathan and the world
without. Yea, and ſuch diſcouragements, as that
man of himſelfe is not able to withſtand, &amp; to ſtand
perfect in all things. Perceiving this, the Apoſtle,
like a faithfull Miniſter, and a good Leader of the
Lord of hoſts, animates and incites his fellowes,
and followers to ſtand faſt in the faith,2. Cor. 16. 13. to quit



themſelues like men, to be ſtrong, ſaying, My Brethren
be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of
his might. v. 10.Heb. 12. v. 1. Runne on with patience the race
(or the conflict) that is ſet before you. Runne on,
notwithſtanding all the wreſtling, and ſtriving of
the fleſh, the world, and the Devill to the contrary.
And this that they might the better doe, he tells
them how to ſtrengthen, and arme themſelues to
that purpoſe, ſaying, Take unto you the whole armour
of God, that ye may be able to ſtand, in the
evill day, and to ſtand perfect in all things. And
thus you ſee the ſcope, and the occaſion of the
words.
            Now that I may goe on in a method,The generall parts of the text. in the further
opening and handling hereof, may it pleaſe
you, to obſerve with me theſe 2 parts. Firſt a conflict.
Secondly a conqueſt.
            
            The conflict in theſe words,A Conflict wherein 3. things. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , we
wreſtle.
            The conqueſt in theſe, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be
able to ſtand. In the conflict, note with me theſe
three things: 1. the combatants. 2. the cauſe of the
combate, and 3. the time.
            The combatants of the one ſide as defendants,
are we, we wreſtle. The combatants of the other
ſide,The combatants of both ſides. as aſſaylants, are the fleſh, the world, and the
Devill. We wreſtle againſt fleſh and blood, againſt
principalities, and powers, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes.
Indeed, the text faith here, we wreſtle
not againſt fleſh &amp; blood, as if that were not an aſſayling
enemy. But the meaning is not ſo; the Apoſtle,



in ſaying, we wreſtle not againſt flēſh and
blood, doth not meane, not at all; but not ſo much,
as Bullinger; not alone, as Calvin and Zanchius upon
the place; not only, as appeares by collation of
ſcripture. For in another place, the Apoſtle ſaith
that the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, Gal. 5. 17. So
then, the fleſh, that is, our owne corrupt fleſh and
blood. And againe, the fleſh, that is, other wicked
men, which are fleſh and blood, as we are, theſe
together with Sathan, here called principalities,
and powers are the enemies that we are to combate
with.
            
                The cauſe of the combate is,
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , in
coeleſtibus,
               The cauſe of the combat. in heavenly things, that is, pro coeleſtibus,
as Chryſoſtome, Oecumenius, aud Muſculus upon the
place. Illud enim in coeleſtibus, eſt pro eo quod est pro
coeleſtibus. The Engliſh renders in coeleſtibus, in
high places, not in heavēly things, but 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                (1.) places:
the ſubſtantive, is not in the originall, but only
the adjective, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                (1.) heavenly, ſo that we
may referre the adjective Coeleſtibus, either to
locis, places, or rebus things, according as our
Church doth elſewhere, Dominicall Epist.
21. and both true, for it is true, that Sathan, the
enemy of mankind, fights againſt us in coelestibus
locis, in high places, for he is the Prince of the aire.
Epheſ. 2. 2. And it is true likewiſe, that hee fights
againſt us in coeleſtibus rebus, about heavenly
things, as Gods glory, our owne ſalvation, the graces
of Gods ſpirit, and eternall happineſſe. And
this, non ut ipſe victoriam adeptus, aliquid conſequatur,
not to doe himſelfe good, ſed ut nos privet, to



doe us hurt. And ſo here, he fights againſt us, in
coeleſtibus, about heavenly things, ut nos illis ſpoliat,
that he might deprive us of them. And this is the
cauſe of the combate.
            The time thereof, is the time preſent, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
ſaith the text, that is,The time of the Combate. there is a wreſtling, ſpeaking 
in the preſent tenſe. And as there is, ſo there
will be, quamdiù nos, &amp; principes tenebrarum, as
long as the ſervants of God, and ſonnes of Belial,
the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the ſerpent
doe laſt together, that is, as long as the world laſts,
that is the limited time of this combate. And theſe
be the particulars of the Conflict.
            In the Conqueſt likewiſe we have three things 
to conſider. 1.A Conqueſt, wherin 3 things. the meanes how it is to be obtained.
2. The manner how the ſaid meanes is to bee uſed.
And 3. the motive.The meanes. The meanes is, the armour of 
God. The manner how to uſe it,The manner. is to put it on. The 
motive is, that ye may ſtand. Theſe bee the parts
and particulars, both of Conflict, and Conqueſt,The motive.
               
of which in order.
            And firſt of the Conflict,Conflict. 1. Part. Combatants of the one ſide, we.
                and therein of the
combatants, we, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , we wreſtle. We, that
is, we that be faithfull in Chriſt Ieſus, Epheſ. 1. v. 1. v. 1.
we that come to ſerve the Lord, Ecclus. 2. v. 1. ſpecially
we that ſerve at the Altar, and are the Miniſters
of Ieſus Chriſt; as S. Paul, we muſt wreſtle,
and fight the Lords battailes againſt his, and our
enemies.
            The condition of the children,A Chriſtians life militarie. and ſervants of
God in this life, is military: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                a warfare
upon earth, as Iob ſaith, c. 7. v. 1. God that is a



man of warre, Exod. 15. 3. made man alſo to be-a
man of warre, Gen. 3. 15. putting enmity betweene
the woman, and the Serpent, and between
the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent,
and ſaying, it ſhall breake thy head, and thou
ſhalt bruiſe his heele. And this breaking and bruiſing,
this warring and wreſtling, which the Lord
did then proclaime betweene the woman and the
Serpent, and betweene her ſeed and his ſeed, hath
gone along, and continued to this very day, even
to us, ſo that nobis Lucta, we wreſtle.
            We, all we that have given up our names unto
Chriſt, and taken the oath of allegeance unto him,
in our Baptiſme, and renewed it by receiving the
Lords ſupper, and ſo profeſſed open hoſtility againſt
Satan, the world, and the fleſh, wee muſt
wreſtle. Hic in castris, ille in roſtris, in ſcholis, in nemore,
in agro, in pelago, in palatio; hic ferro corpus,
ille animum dolis, hit argutiis linguam; hic pedibus,
ille equo, hic currit, ille navigat, omnes militant,
as Petrarch hath it. Whoſoever will live godly
in Chriſt, muſt warre with the Dragon, and his
Angels, Revel. 12. 7. 17.
            Specially if wee bee any thing zealous for the
Lord of hoaſts,Act. 20. 
               As Elijah, 1. Kings 17. or earneſt in
in Gods cauſe, as S. Paul, or forward for the word
of God, and for the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt, as
S. Iohn, Revel 1. 9, then we muſt looke for ſharpe
affronts, and hard oppoſitions, harder then if wee
be remiſſe and careleſſe in Gods cauſe. Sathan is no
oppoſer of ſuch as live ſecurely in their ſinnes. His
kingdome is not divided againſt it ſelfe,Ma
                     •
                  k. 4. 25. he is more



crafty then ſo. His bent is againſt the good, and the
beſt moſt. The greateſt temptation that ever hee
made was againſt Chriſt, and ſo is ſtill againſt
good Chriſtians. He will ſift them, Luk. 22. 31. they
ſhall be ſure to feele his fiery darts, they muſt wreſtle.
            Yea, and this wreſtling or Conflict is not a matter
of ſport, as the word 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                is ſometime taken;
but ſuch as maketh the body of him that ſtriveth
to ſhake againe: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               enim dicitur quia corpus 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
(1) quatitur.
               7 Properties whereby to approve ourſelves good ſouldiours of Ieſus Chriſt. The Chriſtians war is a fierce warre.
            Now this being ſo, that our life is a ſouldiours
life, a warfare upon earth, a continuall wreſtling
and fighting with Sathan and his complices; Let us
conſider our calling, and endeavour to walke worthy
of it, in ſhewing our ſelves good ſouldiours
of Ieſus Chriſt. Let us not thinke it enough to take
preſſe money, and to beare the name, and to receive
the pay of good ſouldiours, but let us approve our
ſelves ſuch, by our good ſervice, and performance
of the parts of good ſouldiours, and amongſt other,
in theſe.
            Firſt in forethinking of the Croſſe, and providing 
for it: Thus a good ſouldiour, hee doth not
thinke to live ſtil in gariſon at eaſe: hee thinks of
ſharpe Conflicts, and hard trialls, and prepares for
them; in the day of peace he prepares for battell, in
a calme he expects a ſtorme, and ſo muſt wee, for
faire weather will not laſt alwayes.
            Aeſtas non ſemper fuerit,Virgil. componite nidos.
            A good ſouldier careth but litle for the world,
no man that warreth, intangleth himſelfe with the



things of this life, that he may pleaſe him who
hath choſen him to bee a ſouldiour, ſaith the Apoſtle,
2. Tim. 2. 4. And ſo, if we be for Chriſts ſervice,
we muſt not be for the world, for wee cannot
ſerve two Maſters, two ſuch contrary commanding
Maſters, as God &amp; Mammon, Mat. 6. 24. yea
to warre a good warfare, we muſt abſtaine not only
from the care of this life, but from every wicked
thing,Deut. 23. 9. ſo ſaith the Lord, when thou goeſt out againſt
thine enemy to fight, abſtaine from every evill
thing. For this weakens us, and turnes God againſt
us.
            A good ſouldiour will endure hardneſſe, hard
 fare, hard lodging,Non eſt in terris mollis ad aſtra via. And ſo muſt we;
if we will approve our ſelves good ſouldiours of
Chriſt, we muſt abate of our dainty feeding, of
our ſoft clothing, and lazy living. We muſt moderate
our ſelves of our too many pleaſures, and
endure hardneſſe. So ſaith the Apoſtle, endure
hardneſſe as a good ſouldiour of Ieſus Chriſt, 2.
Tim. 2. 3. and ſo he did himſelfe, he was in labours
abundant &amp;c. 2. Cor. 11. 23. and ſo Chriſt our captaine
he endured the croſſe, Heb. 12. 1. leaving us an
example.
            A good ſouldiour will keepe his ranke, knowing
 that when the ranks are broken,Ordo eſt mater &amp; conſervatrix rerum omnium. Ariſt. polit. l. 2. the victory is in
hazard: And ſo muſt we, ſaith the Apoſtle; let all
things be done in order, 1. Cor. 14. 40. Let every
one abide in the vocation wherein he is called, 1.
Cor. 7. 20. Study to be quiet, medling with your
owne buſines, 1. Theſ. 4. 11. not with the buſines
of Princes, and prelats, teaching them what lawes



and orders to make, this is to breake our ranke. If
a more be in the eye, the feete is no fit member to
pull it out, the hand is to doe that: And ſo if things
be amiſſe in church, or common-wealth, private
men may not preſume to bee reformers therein,
they muſt leave that to Moſes and Aaron the Prince
and the Prieſt, the two hands of the body politick,
Pſal. 77. 20.
            A good ſouldiour wil obey his captaine, and 
doe as he commands him,
                  Mat. 8. 9. Intenti fuerunt ad Ducis verbum imò &amp; ad nutum. Curt. l. 4. if he ſay come, he cometh,
or goe, &amp; he goeth, or doe this, and he doth it,
ſo the Centurions ſervant, and the ſouldiers of Alexander,
as Curtius writes. And ſo we, if we will
approve ourſelves good ſouldiours of Chriſt, we
muſt obey his commands, in comming, going,
and doing as he bids us. If we be his ſervants wee
muſt obey him, for his ſervants we are, to whom
we obey. Rom. 6. 16.
            A good ſouldiour the more truſt is committed 
to him, and the more he is advanced by his ſoveraigne
Lord above others, the more carefull he is
to approve himſelfe well in his place. Thus Nehemiah,
ſhall ſuch a man as I flye? a man ſo honored,
ſo advanced above others, ſhall I ſo much forget
my Lord, and the truſt which he hath committed
to me, as to ſinne againſt him? I will never doe it.
And ſo we, the more honour, the better place, and
the greater pay wee have, the more faithfull wee
ſhould be, for to whom much is given, of them
much is required. Luk. 12. 48.
            A good ſouldiour will bee helpfull to his fellow
ſouldiours. It is reported of Trajan, that hee



                would cut in peeces his own garments,Xiphlin. in vita Trajan. rather then
his ſouldiours ſhould want a ragge to bind up their
wounds: And ſo if wee will approve our ſelves
good ſouldiours of Chriſt, we muſt helpe and ſuccour
one another.Rom. 12. 13. Gal. 6. 2. 10. We muſt diſtribute to the neceſſity
of the Saints; and helpe to beare one anothers
burden, as the Apoſtle ſaith, wee muſt doe
good to all, ſpecially to them of the houſhould of
faith; and among them to your faithfull Miniſters
and preachers. (Indeed having food and raiment,
we ought therewith to be contented, as the
Apoſtle ſaith.1. Tim. 6. v. 8. And food we have, that are called
to this place, and wee thanke you for it. But raiment,
(1.) a gowne we want, we are faine to ſeeke
for, and ſometime to goe without, at leaſt to bee
content with that which is not fit. If this defect be
for want of information, I pray take this. Having
gone through with the weightier matters, doe not
ſticke at the leaſt: without any more adoe, afford I
pray you, your fellow ſouldiour, a coate fit for his
place.)
            A good ſouldiour is watchfull to foreſee dangers,
 to give warning thereof unto others, and
withall to prevent them as much as he may: And
ſo we muſt have the eye of our minds alwayes awake
to ſee and obſerve what particular temptations
doe ariſe againſt us, either from within or from
without.Mark. 13. 33. 37. Thus ſaith our Saviour often, watch. And
ſo the Apoſtle, be ſober and watch, becauſe your
adverſary the Devill, as a roaring Lion, walketh
about, ſeeking whom he may devoure, 1. Pet. 5. 8.
            
                A good ſouldiour, will fortifie himſelfe there



moſt, where hee thinks the enemy will make his
greateſt aſſault. And now Sathan our deadly enemy
labours moſt to overthrow our faith,Rom. 10. 8. and to oppoſe
the Scripture which is the word of faith.Luk. 22. 31. 32. Hee
labours ſpecially to ſhake our faith,2. Cor. 5. Pſal. 1
                     •
                  6. ſo ſaith Chriſt,
Sathan hath deſired to winnow your faith. And
this, becauſe it is the ſpeciall gift of Gods elect,
Tit. 1. 1. The mother grace, the ground of obedience,
of feare, of joy, our choiceſt weapon, even
our ſhield and buckler, the victory whereby wee
overcome, 1. Ioh. 5. Hee endeavours likewiſe with
great earneſtneſſe to oppoſe the word of God, and
to call in queſtion the truth thereof, and to bring
it out of credit. Thus he dealt in tempting of Eve,
ſaying, hath God ſaid ye ſhall not eat of every tree
in the garden, leaſt ye dye? he knew God had ſaid
it, and that in the day they ſhould eat thereof, they
ſhould dye.Gen. 3. 1. 3. 4. And yet hee labours to make them
doubt of that truth, which hee and they knew too
well. And ſo againe in tempting of Chriſt, whereas
God the Father ſaid, This is my beloved Sonne,
in whom I am well pleaſed.Mat. 3. 17. C. 4. Sathan hee comes
with his, If thou be the Son of God, and ſo would
make a doubt of it.
            Knowing then what Sathan and his agents labour
moſt, even to call into queſtion the truth of
Gods word, and to overthrow our faith therein,
there let us fortifie our ſelves moſt; ſeeing there he
oppugnes moſt, thither let us bring our greateſt
ſtrength.
            A good ſouldiour will rightly diſcerne betwixt
the head of the body, and other inferiour parts, ſo



that if he put any to the hazard, hee will put thoſe
that are leſſe principall. But as for the head, which
like the tower of David, hath a ſuperintendency above
the reſt, this he will be ſure to ward.
            And ſo above all, wee muſt bee ſure to looke to
our head Chriſt Ieſus, that he be not wounded:
ſpecially that he be not put downe, and deprived of
his kingly,
               2. Theſ. 2. 3. 4. 
               prieſtly, and propheticall office, by that
man of ſinne, the Sonne of perdition, who oppoſeth
and exalteth himſelfe above all that is called
God, or is worſhipped. The head, as Plato ſayes, is
the ſeat of life, and being. But certaine it is, in
Chriſt the head of the Church, and of our faith,
is life, and eternall life, as the Apoſtle ſaith. In him
is life,1. Ioh. 11. 12. and no where elſe to bee had, according to
that of the ſame Apoſtle, hee that hath the Sonne
hath life, and he that hath not the Sonne, hath not
life.
            I ſay then with our Saviour,Mat. 10. 16. bee wiſe as Serpents,
in ſaving the head, for therein their chifeſt
wiſdome conſiſts, as Pliny writes. This is the ſure
hold, in capite, to hold the head Chriſt. But alas
there bee too many now adayes that doe not hold
this head. Of this ſort are they who worſhip Saints
and Angels, as the Apoſtle ſaith, Coloſ. 2. 18. Specially
thoſe Qui Mariam Virginem Christo ipſi
anteponunt, dum eam ſic inclamant, roga patrem,
jube natum, jure matris impera. Item dum ei epitheta
Chriſto propria attribuunt, dicentes, felix Coeli
porta, Item regina miſericordiae, vita &amp; ſpes noſtra,
&amp;c.
            
            Theſe doe not hold the head, and ſo doe not



ſhew themſelves wiſe ſouldiours, not ſo wiſe as
Serpents in their kind.
            A good ſouldiour will ſet upon his enemies betimes,
while he is in his beſt ſtrength, in the ſpring
of his youth, and cannot deferre it till the winter of
old age. And ſo muſt we, to approve our ſelues
good ſouldiours, we muſt reſiſt the Devill and his
temptations, while our power is at the beſt, and
not put it off till we be old,Ovid. and decrepit. Turpe ſenex
miles; Old decrepit men are not fit for the field,
A man upon his death-bed is not fit to maſter a
Giant. And no more is a man ſo fit to fight with a
Dragon and his Angels, the Devill and his Complices,
when his power is at the weakeſt.Eccleſ. 12. 1. I ſay
then with the wiſe man, remember thy Creator in
the dayes of thy youth, before the old and evill
dayes, come, or the yeares draw nigh, when thou
wilt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them. Set thy ſelfe to
wreſtle againſt thy adverſaries,2. Sam. 11. 
                     •
                  . when Kings goe
forth to warre, that is, at the begining of the yeare,
in the Prime of thy time, before Sathans temptations
by continuance get ſtrength, and thy power
is leſſened.
            A good ſouldiour will have ſpeciall care to
ſtrengthen himſelfe where he is weakeſt, and there
to lay moſt matter of defence. And ſo it is wiſdome
for us to obſerve our owne weakneſſe, and
perſonall corruptions, and there to fortifie our
ſelves; Though there be in every one of us the ſeed,
and ſpawne of all ſinnes, yet there is none but is
more prone to ſome one ſinne then to another. As
ſome to walke after the fleſh,Suſanna. as the two Iudges of



               Iſrael.
               2. Tim. c. 4. 10. Others to love the preſent world,Iudith c. 12. 20. as Demas.
               Dan. 5. 2.
Others to overcharge themſelves with ſurfeting
&amp; drunkenneſſe,Iſa. 36. 4. as Holofernes &amp; Balthazar. Others
to ſweare and blaſpheame Gods name, as Rabſhaketh
&amp;c. Whatſoever our weakneſſe &amp; perſonall infirmity
is, let us obſerve it and there lay moſt matter
of defence, ſo that we may be able to ſay with
David, I have eſchued mine owne wickedneſſe,
Pſal. 18. 23.
            
                A good ſouldiour will endeavour to repell, &amp; to
withstād the firſt aſſault of the enemy, &amp; not ſuffer
him to come to ſcale the wall, or into the Market
place, with purpoſe to drive him out againe. He
will keepe him out without bullets reach if he can:
And ſo muſt we, if wee be wiſe; wee muſt reſiſt the
firſt motions of ſinne and Sathan, and beate backe
the firſt aſſault, wee muſt breake the head of the
Serpent, hit Goliah in the forehead, treade downe
ſinne in the ſhell, and daſh Sathans brood againſt
the ſtones while their are infants. Sathan is more
eaſily driven back at the firſt, then afterwards,
therefore principijs obſta, put back the firſt aſſault.
            
                A good ſouldiour will command more with a
veni, then an ito. As Circero reports of Caeſar, to his
eternall praiſe, that is, more by patterne, then by
precept: And ſo to prove our ſelves good ſouldiours
of Ieſus Chriſt, wee muſt not only call upon
others, doing nothing our ſelves; but we muſt call
by our own forwardnes and example, which is the
ſtrongeſt authority and the moſt perſuaſive argument.
            
                A good ſouldiour is not aſhamed to weare his



captaines colours; or to confeſſe his name; or of
wounds which he hath received in his ſervice: And
ſo to prove our ſelves fathfull ſervants and ſouldiers
of Chriſt, wee muſt not be aſhamed to confeſſe
the faith of Chriſt crucified, or of his livery
and cognizance, which is the hearing of his word,
and receiving of his Sacraments, or of ſuffering for
his names ſake. The Prophet David did profeſſe
to ſpeake of Gods teſtimonies before Kings, and
not to be aſhamed. Pſal. 119. S. Paul ſaid to the Romans,
that he was not aſhamed of the Goſpell, Rom.
1. 16. or of ſuffering afflictions for preaching the
Goſpell 2. Tim. 1. 12. neither may we; if any man
ſuffer as a Chriſtian, let him not bee aſhamed, but
let him glorify God on this behalfe, 1. Pet. 4. 16.
            A good ſouldiour is primus in pralio, and poſtremus
               
               in fuga, as it is ſaid of Xerxes, that is, the firſt
in the fight, and the laſt in the flight. Nay hee will
not flye at all, except his captaine ſound a retraite,
or otherwiſe command him, knowing that there is
Martiall law, preſent death, if hee ſhould doe ſo:
And ſo if we will approve our ſelves good ſouldiours
of Chriſt, wee muſt bee ready, &amp; forward to
fight under his banner againſt ſinne, the world, and
the Devill. We muſt be forward &amp; continue faithfull
in the fight, &amp; that unto the death. Thus S. Paul,
he fought the good fight and finiſhed his courſe.
2. Tim. 4. 7. And ſo muſt we,Finis coronat opus. 
               Qui fugit huic meritò
nulla corona datur. If any man draw back, my ſoule
ſhall have no pleaſure in him, ſaith the Lord, Heb.
10. 38. There is no ſafety in flying; here is no peece
of armour appointed for the back in all this Panoply,



but only for the fore-parts;Pſal. 78. v. 10. but only for the fore-parts; to ſignify that we,
ſhould not like thoſe of Ephraim, turne our backs
in the day of battell, but looke our enemies in
the face, and, as the Numantine, rather dye then
flye.
            
                A good ſouldiour will take ſpeciall notice of
his chiefeſt enemies, and bend himſelfe moſt againſt
them. For though in battells they fight againſt
the whole army, yet ſpecially againſt the
head and Generall. Thus the King of Siria, being
to fight with an army of the Iſraelites, at Ramoth
Gilead, hee commanded his thirty and two captaines
which had rule over his charets, ſaying,
fight neither with ſmall nor great, but only with
the King of Iſrael, 1. Kings 22. 31. And thus muſt
we in our ſpirituall warfare; we muſt fight againſt
the whole army of ſinne, but ſpecially againſt the
King, and ruling ſinne, againſt chiefe leaders of ſin,
thoſe being taken, the reſt will never ſtand. If Holofernes
be ſlaine, his ſouldiours will flye. Iudith c.
15. 1. 12. If the ſheapheard bee once ſtrucke, the
ſheep will ſoone be ſcattered, Mat. 26. 31.
            Neither need we to goe farre,Combatants of the adverſe part. 3. to take a view of
our chiefer enemies. Here they are neare at hand,
perſonated, and deciphered unto us, in number
three, in quality moſt notorious.
            
                The firſt, that enters the liſt, is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , fleſh &amp;
blood,The fleſh. or blood and fleſh, as the originall runnes.
That is, that corruption of nature, which hath defiled
both body and ſoule, being ſpread and mixt,
with every part of both, even as the light mingled
with darkneſſe, in the twy-light, or dawning of



the day. This corruption and depravedneſſe of nature,
here called fleſh &amp; blood, is one of the chiefe
enemies, that we have to combate, and wreſtle
with in this world. Indeed, the Apoſtle here, doth
prefixe a non to this, ſaying, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
that is, we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood. But
this non, is not to be underſtood, ſimply, as not at
all, but not only, (as is ſaid before) our owne corrupt
nature is one, but not our only enemy. It is one
of our enemies, ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, the carnall
mind is enmity againſt God, Rom. 8. 7. it luſteth
againſt the ſpirit, Galat. 5. 17. it rebelleth againſt
the law of the mind, Rom. 7. 23. 24. Let a man but
will that which is good, and evill is preſent with
him; as the Apoſtle ſaith, Rom. 7. 21. If a man have
a mind to pray, or to praiſe God, to give, or to forgive,
to doe, or to ſuffer any thing according to
Gods will, the corrupt fleſh is ready to contrary it,
and to ſay with the ſluggard,Prov. 6. v. 10. yet a little ſleepe, a
little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands to ſleep,
or to ſay as Peter did to Chriſt ſpeaking of his
death, this be farre from thee, this ſhall not be unto
thee, Mat. 16. 22.
            A mans owne heart is as arch a traytor, as any he
ſhall meet withall, and as dangerous; and the more,
becauſe he is not a forraine but an home-bred enemy,
fighting not as a tall ſouldiour, but as a crafty
traytor rebelling againſt the ſpirit; like Dalilah in
Sampſons boſome, or Iudas in Chriſts company;
like the moth in the garment, it is bred in us, and
dayly cheriſhed by us, and yet frets and deſtroyes
us. The heart is deceitfull above all things, as the



Prophet ſaith, Ier. 17. 9. Yea more deceitfull then
Sathan himſelfe in ſome reſpect, for our owne
hearts can deceive us of themſelves, without Sathan:
but not Sathan without our hearts. Nemo
laeditur niſi à ſeipſo, is a true ſaying. There is no
miſchiefe that we fall into, but we ourſelves are at
leaſt coadjutive cauſes, and doe helpe to further the
matter. Indeed Sathan is as the father begetting,
but our corrupt heart is as the mother conceiving,
and bringing forth ſinne. Sathan the father of ſin,
could doe nothing without this Mother. The Devill
cannot prevaile againſt us but by the helpe of
our owne corruption; he might ſtrike fire long enough,
ere there would bee any burning, did not
we find him tinder. Grande malum voluntas propira,
as Bernard ſaith, Ser. 71. in Cant. a mans worſt foes
are they of his own houſhold, of his own boſome,
even his owne naughty heart and corrupt affections.
Every man is tempted by his owne concupiſcence
as the Apoſtle ſaith, Iam. 1. 14. This
carrieth the chiefeſt ſtroke in our ſinnes. The Devell
hath aſtutiam ſuadendi, a perſuading ſlight, but
he hath not potentiam cogendi, an inforcing might,
as S. Auguſt. in Pſal. 91. He cannot make us ſinne
againſt our wills, if hee plow not with our heifer,Iudges 14. 18.
he can get no advantage over us.
            Behold then and conſider who is your enemy,
it is not ſo much a forrain, as a domeſtick foe, a
mans foes are they of his owne houſhold, the
head-ſtrong paſſions, and the unruly affections of
our owne corrupt hearts, are the greateſt enemies
that wee are to wreſtle with. Wee wreſtle againſt
fleſh and blood.
            
               
Now knowing this to bee ſo, let us put this
knowledge in practiſe, knowledge without practiſe
is nothing worth, ignis fatuus, it is like the blazing
lampe of the fooliſh virgins, that could not light
them to the Bridegroomes chamber, it will doe no
good unleſſe wee doe thereafter.Pſal. 111. v. 10. Let us doe then.
Which is thus.
            Firſt in regard that fleſh and blood,7 Things to be done by us, becauſe the fleſh is an adverſary of ours. that is, our
corrupt nature, is an enemy of ours, hereby let us
learne to take heed of our ſelves. Ita cave tibi ut caveas
teipſum, is the counſell of the wiſe, that is, ſo
take heed to thy ſelfe of other enemies, as that
thou take heed of thy ſelfe as an enemy. A me, me
ſalve, Domine, was the prayer of S. Auſtine, that is,
from mine owne ſelfe, good Lord deliver me. And
ſo we had need to pray; for our owne hearts,
though they would bee taken for our familiar
friends, yet they will deceive us, if wee take not
heed,Quocun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ingredimur ſequitur, unà adeſt in tuis aedibus, unà bibit unà comedit, unà dormit. Terent. as they did the Gentiles. Rom. 1. 21. Yea and
though wee reſiſt never ſo much, yet theſe deceivers
will ſtick cloſe to us, and follow us at all
times, in all places, upon all occaſions, ſtill ready
furniſhed with deceit to beguile us. And therefore
let no man repoſe too much confidence in his
owne heart. He that truſteth in his owne heart is a
foole, ſaith Solomon, Prov. 28. v. 26.
            Secondly, hereby let us learne not to bee overforward 
in conſulting with fleſh and blood, when
any thing is to be done. Will a King counſell with
a traytor, whom he knowes to bee ſo? This were
to ruinate himſelfe, and his kingdome. Will any
man goe to ſuch a Lawyer, whoſe counſell hee



knowes to be meere deceit and conſenage? That
were to overthrow himſelfe and his cauſe. Now
the fleſh is a traytor, and ſeekes thy deſtruction. A
deceiver that gives ill counſell,1 Kings 12. v. 10. as the young men
to Rehoboam. Conſult not then with it, in nothing
follow the counſell of the fleſh. But as S. Paul
when hee was to goe to Hieruſalem, to take upon
him the calling of an Apoſtle, did not conſult
with fleſh and blood, as himſelfe ſaith, Gal. 1. 16.
So when any thing is to be done, be not over-forward
to conſult with fleſh and blood, but with
Gods ſpirit, in Gods word, for the wiſdome of the
ſpirit is life and peace, Rom. 8. 6.
            
                And ſo likewiſe, when any matter of faith and
religion is propoſed, and comes to be weighed and
embraced; Weigh it not in the ballance of humane
reaſon, but in the ballance of the ſanctuary, that is
the word of God, leane not too much to your
owne underſtanding and judgement in theſe
matters. For what good judgement is to bee
expected of one that is an enemy to goodneſſe?
and ſuch is the carnall mind, an enemy, yea enmity
againſt God; it is not ſubject to the will of
God, neither indeed can bee, Rom. 8. 7. it
perceiveth not the things of the ſpirit, 1. Cor. 1. 14.
Men that are dimme-ſighted, and cannot diſcerne
without ſpectacles, if they bee put to deſcry a
thing a farre off, the moſt of them would bee of diverſe
opinions of it; And men enlightned and regenerated
in this life,1. Cor. 13. v. 32. doe but ſee in a glaſſe darkly.
But the naturall man ſeeth not, neither can hee diſcerne
at all the things of the ſpirit. I ſay then with



               Solomon,
               Prov. 3. v. 5. 7. leane not to your owne underſtanding;
ſpecially in matters of religion. Bee not wiſe in
your owne conceits, leaſt in ſeeking to bee wiſe, ye
become fooliſh, as the Gentiles, Rom. 1. 22.
            Fourthly, becauſe fleſh &amp; blood is an adverſary 
of ours, boaſt not neither bragge of your owne
good nature. Is there any good in fighting againſt
the ſpirit of God? in hindring and ſtriving to ſuppreſſe
all good motions. And this is all that the
fleſh doth. This is the condition of our owne nature;
for if we believe &amp; confeſſe Chriſt, no thanks
to our good nature, for fleſh and blood hath not
revealed this unto us, as Chriſt told Peter, Mat.
16. 17. If we haue any good in us, we are not debtors
to the fleſh for it, as S. Paul ſaith, Rom. 8. 12. Let
not any then glory of their owne good nature,Ier. 9. v. 23.
but hee that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord,
from whom commeth every good and perfect gift,
Iam. 1. 17.
            Further, becauſe fleſh blood is an enemy, let 
no man bragge and prate too much of his gentry,
and parentage, be it never ſo great. For what
doe we derive from our naturall parents, bee they
never ſo great and famous in their generations?
Nothing but fleſh &amp; blood: for that which is borne
of the fleſh is fleſh, Ioh. 3. 6. And the fleſh without
a regeneration is but a rebel,Mat. 3. v. 9. 
               Rom. 7. 23. ſay not
then, yee have Abraham to your father unleſſe yee
doe the works of Abraham, boaſt not of great
blood, unleſſe it be great and good: corrupt fleſh
and blood, ſuch as every mans is by nature, being
conceived in ſinne and brought forth in iniquity,Pſal. 51. v. 5.


               
cannot inherit the kingdom of heaven, neither doth
corruption inherit incorruption. 1. Cor. 15. 50. We
muſt be borne againe, having our old corruption
done away, and new grace reſtored, before wee
can ſee the kingdome of heaven.Nobilitas ſola eſt at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   unica virtus. 
               Ioh. 3. 3. therefore
gaudeant bene nati, quando renati. Let no man boaſt
of his birth, except it be his new birth, for therein is
the true nobility.
            
                Againe, in regard that fleſh and blood is an enemy
of ours, hereby let us learne not to feed &amp; pamper
our ſelves by too much eating and drinking, or
ſoft clothing: but to beat down the body, &amp; to keep
it in ſubjection,1. Cor. 9. 27. as the Apoſtle did: plaine fare, and
courſe aray is good enough for an enemy. Bread
and water is ſufficient, if not too much for him
now and then. We miſtake our ſelves too much,
when wee are ſo carefull for our bodies, ſaying,
what ſhall wee eat? and what ſhall wee drink? and
wherwith ſhall wee be clothed? For in ſo doing, we
doe as the Iſraelites did with the Canaanites, even
nouriſh a ſnake in our own boſome. We ſtrengthen
our enemy to cut our owne throates. For our fleſh
is of ſlaviſh diſpoſition. If a ſlave be well uſed; he
will grow ſaucy, and malepert: hee that bringeth
up his ſervant delicatly, hee will bee as his ſonne,
as Solomon ſaith, Prov. 2. 21. Nay hee will overtop
him, as Ieroboam did Rehoboam. This ſlave then, the
fleſh, muſt have a ſtraight hand over it, wee muſt
keepe him ſhort, if wee deale wiſely, ſpecially wee
muſt make no proviſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the
luſt thereof, that is the counſell of the Apoſtle,
Rom. 13. 14.
            
               
Laſtly, becauſe the fleſh is an enemy that wee 
muſt wreſtle with, I beſeech you, with the Apoſtle,
to abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, which fight againſt
the ſoule, 1. Pet. 2. 11. what thoſe fleſhly luſts are,
the Apoſtle ſets downe, Galat. 5. 19. ſaying, the
works of the fleſh are theſe, adultery, fornicatiō &amp;c.
            But there are ſome fleſhly luſts which fight againſt
the ſoule in a ſpeciall manner, which I beſeech
you to abſtaine from. And namely theſe, fury,
fornication, drunkenneſſe, gluttony, avarice,
idleneſſe, pride: fury fights againſt the ſoule like a
mad Turke; the furious mans execrable oaths
are ſo many ſcabbs to the ſoule: fornication like
treacherous Ioab,
               2. Sam. 20. 9. and falſe hearted Iudas doth kiſſe
to kill: drunkennes is the maſter-gunner, that ſets all
on fire: Gluttony will ſtand for a corporall: Avarice
will ſtand for a pioner: Idlenes for a gentleman of
company: And pride muſt be the captaine. All theſe
are ſore enemies to the ſoule, moſt deadly enemies;
to bee carnally minded is death, Rom. 8. 6. Let
us then carefully looke to them, and wreſtle againſt
them, and endeavour to withſtand them. Doe
this, and ſhew your ſelves courageous indeed; for,
Fortior eſt qui ſe, quam qui fortiſſima vincit
            
            
               Moenia, he that is ſlow to anger, is better then the
mighty, he that ruleth his ſpirit, then he that cōquereth
a city, Prov. 16. 32. Againe doe this, and doe all
other commandements, even the hardeſt. The heardeſt
thing in the judgment of Caeſar, is ſeipſum vincere,
for a man to overcome himſelfe; ſo that Tunc
omnia jura tenebis, cum poteris Rex eſse tui. Finally
doe this, and ye are made, made kings to God, Revel.



vel. 1. 6. kings of great rule.
            Latius regnes avidum domando
            Spiritum, quam ſi Libiam remotis
            Gadibus jungas, &amp; uter
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                Poenus
            Serviet uni.
            Of greater rule, then if thou hadſt the heathen to
thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the
earth, to thy poſſeſſion.
            But are theſe all the enemies that we have, to wreſtle
with? not ſo. This is but our captaine, with
his company, even the fleſh, with the unruly affections
thereof.
            
                There is another enemy, which wee have to
wreſtle,The ſecond adverſary of chriſtians, the world. and to encounter with, that is, the world.
Mundus immūdus, the uncleane, unbelieving world,
with the temptations, and allurements thereof. For
we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood only, that is,
our owne fleſh and blood. But againſt fleſh and
blood, that is, other wicked men, which are fleſh
and blood, as we are.
            The wicked world is another enemy, that we,
and all other chriſtians are to wreſtle with.Iohn 16. 33. Of this
our Saviour ſpeaketh, ſaying, the world hateth
you, Ioh. 15. 19. In the world ye ſhall have tribulations.
And ſo doth the Apoſtle, ſaying, in the
world there are many adverſaries, 1. Cor. 16. 9.
There are ſome violent, as perſecuting Emperours:
Others fraudulent, as ſubtill Hereticks. A third
both violent &amp; fraudulent, as peſtilent Antichriſts,
in the kingdome of Popery,The army of the world againſt chriſtians. where the temporall
power, and the ſpirituall are joyned together, againſt
all that is called God, as Luther hath it, Loc.



Com. Tit. de perſecutione verae Eccleſiae.
            
            The army wherewith the world fights againſt
the faithfull ſervants,Aquinas in prima. and ſouldiours of Chriſt,Iohn c. 5. 4. conſiſts
of two wings, as Aquinas notes. One is the wing
of adverſity, on the left hand. And the other is the
wing of proſperity on the right. By the wing of adverſity,
the wicked of the world doe ſet upon the
Chriſtian ſouldiours, diverſe wayes. As ſometime in
their body, ſometime in their goods, and ſometime
in their good name. And in all, many times, they
give them the foile, provoking them, and ſometime
prevailing with them to forget their vow, and promiſe
with God; and to make ſhipwrack of faith and a
good conſcience. By the wing of adverſity Pſeudoapoſtles
were overcome;1. Tim. 1. v. 19. even for feare of perſecution
for the croſſe of Chriſt,Galat. 6. 12. and ſo was Peter alſo,
when he denyed his Maſter, Mat. 26.
            But for one that falls by the onſet of adverſity, on
the left hand, a thouſand more are overthrowne by
the incurſion of proſperity on the right. By this Balaam
was overcome, who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe,
2. Pet. 2. 15. By this Demas was overthrowne,
who forſooke the Apoſtle Paul, for love
of the preſent world, 2. Tim. 4. 10. yea and by this
David was foyled, whom greivous adverſity in the
dayes of Saul, could not overcome. 1. Sam. 11. 2. And
hereby alſo many are foyled in theſe dayes. Worldly
hopes have drawne many from the ſincerity of religion,
whom outward violence could not move.
The ſunſhine of proſperity, hath made many to unbutton,
and to unlaſe themſelves, whom the ſtorme
of adverſity made to gird up their loynes. As thoſe
women of Iſrael ſand of David, and Saul, by way of



joy and gratulation,Sam. 18. 7. ſaying, Saul hath ſlaine his thouſands,
and David his tenne thouſands: ſo wee may
truly ſing, of theſe two, by way of mourning, and lamentation,
ſaying, adverſity hath ſlaine thouſands,Mundus obsidet me utrin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   &amp; per quin
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   portas, quin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſc: corporis ſenſus, ſagitiis ſuis me vulnerat. Bern. medit. 14.
proſperity tenne thouſands. So that looke wee on
what ſide we will; either the left ſide of adverſity or
the right ſide of proſperity, Retia vides, quaecun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   vides.
Wee ſhall find that wee walke in the middeſt of
ſnares, as the wiſeman ſaith, Ecclus. 9. 13. we ſhall
be ſure to finde the world an enemy, at all hands.
            What ſhall we doe then in this caſe? My adviſe
and counſell herein,5 Things to be done, becauſe of the enmity of the world. is that of the Apoſtle, love not
the world, neither the things of the world. 1. Ioh. 2.
15. And that of Chriſt, take heed leaſt at any time
your hearts bee overcharged with the cares of this
life, Luk. 21. 34. ſhould a man deſire much to eat of
choaking fruits? And ſuch are the cares of the world,
they choake the word, Mat. 13. 22. ſhould a man exceſſively
love that, which will doe him much harme,
pricke as thornes, and pierce with many ſorrowes?
And loe,1. Tim. 6. 9. 10. ſo it is with thoſe that love the world, they
pierce themſelves with many ſorrowes, as the Apoſtle
ſaith, they fall into many temptations, and ſnares,
and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which
drowne them in perdition and deſtruction. That
which I ſaid before then, I ſay againe with the Apoſtle,
love not the world, neither the things of this
world. Raiſe your affections from things that are on
earth,Coloſ. 3. v. 2. and ſet them on things above. Some will ſay
with the Phariſees, that they will love their friend,
and hate their enemy. Make that good in this, and ye
doe well, for the world is an enemy, that wee ſhould
hate, and not love.
            
               
Secondly, becauſe the world is an enemy, wonder 
not if good men bee not much reſpected, and regarded
in the world, as other men are; marvaile not
if the world hate you,1. Iohn 3. v. 13. 
               S. Iohn ſaith: or if ye ſee good
men, and good things oppoſed, and keept downe:
Is it any wonder to ſee one enemy oppoſe and keepe
down another?Oderunt hilarem triſtes triſte
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   jocoſi, Sedatum celeres, agilem gnavum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   remiſſi. Horat. lib. 1. epiſt. 19. to ſee righteouſnes &amp; unrighteouſnes,
Chriſt and Belial, light and darkneſſe at diſcord and
diſagreements? ſurely no. Oderunt hilarem triſtes &amp;c.
Contrary diſpoſitions, have alwayes occaſioned contentious
oppoſitions. And therefore I ſay with the Apoſtle,
thinke it not ſtrange concerning the fiery triall,
marvaile not if the world hate you, 1. Pet. 4. 12.
            Thirdly becauſe the world is an enemy, remember 
not to be too converſant with the wicked thereof,
as with idolaters, fornicators, drunkards, ſwearers,
or any wicked perſons. Should a man deſire the
company of his enemies?Amb. Ser. 87. And ſuch are theſe, &amp; all other
workers of iniquity, yea majores ſunt inimici mores
pravi, quā hoſtes infeſti; there are none more deadly
enemies then ill company.Epheſ. 5. v. 11. Avoid then, have no fellowſhip
with the unfruitfull works of darkneſſe: Remēber
that there muſt be alwayes enmity between the
ſeed of the woman, &amp; the ſeed of the ſerpent, Gen. 3.
            Moreover, becauſe the world is an adverſary of 
ours, let us not build our faith upon the judgment or
example of the world: ſhould we build our faith and
ſalvation upon the word and example of an enemy?
And loe, ſuch is the world, an enemy; yea, and a
foole too, ſo ſaith the Apoſtle. The wiſdome of this
world is fooliſhneſſe before God, 1. Cor. 1. 10. let no
man then build his faith and ſalvation upon it: but
upon the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles,Eph
                     •
                  ſ. 2. 20.


               
that is, upon Ieſus Chriſt, for other foundation can no
man lay, to make ſure work, 1. Cor. 3. 11. hee is the
foundation of foundations, he is the ſure rock, the
the chiefe corner ſtone, elect, precious, on whom he
that believeth, ſhall not be confounded, 1. Pet. 2. 6.
            
                Laſtly, ſeeing the world is an enemy, wreſtling againſt
us; let us likewiſe wreſtle againſt it. If an invading
enemy be let alone, and no oppoſition made againſt
him, he will quickly overrunne all, and bring
all under him. We muſt looke to it then, how we let
the world runne on in errours, in prophaneneſſe, in all
kind of impiety, and irreligiouſneſſe. Specially you
that bee the champions of the Lord of hoaſts, the
charrets of Iſrael,
               2. Kings 2. 21. and the horſe-men thereof,Rom. 13. 4. the
Miniſters of God to take vengeance on them
that doe evill, you muſt looke to it, that ye beare
not the ſword in vaine, but that ye truly, and indifferently
miniſter juſtice, to the puniſhment of wickedneſſe
and vice, and to the maintenance of Gods true
religion and virtue. In the entrance of your profeſſion,
you have proclaimed, and vowed warre againſt
the world, witneſſe your Baptiſme, doe not prove
runnagate ſouldiours, and Apoſtates, in leaving
Chriſts colours, to follow the world, away with
ſuch perfidiouſneſſe, bee faithfull, bee men of your
words, and fight manfully under Chriſts banner, againſt
this preſent evill world.
            This is a hard ſervice indeed, to wreſtle and fight,
contra gentes, againſt a world of wickedneſſe. But
yet we muſt ſet to it, and verifie theſe words with
our practiſe, that we wreſtle, if wee will approve our ſelves,
the true ſervants, and ſouldiours of Chriſt.
            
                Yea and we have harder ſervice then all this yet.



Even a ſervice againſt principalities,The third adverſarie Chriſtians the divell. and powers, againſt
the Rulers of the darkneſſe of this world, againſt
ſpirituall wickedneſſe in high places. That is,
in a word, againſt the Devill. Quem Apoſtolus hic
pluribus epithetis inſignit, whom the Apoſtle here
doth ſet forth by many names, and titles, ut intelligant
lectores, quam non ſit hoſtis ille contemnendus,
ſaith Calvin;
               Calvin in ſo that the readers might know, that he is
not an enemy to be ſleighted at, but a chiefe, and an
arch enemy, for ſo it is, he is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the enemy as he is
called, by way of eminence, Mat. 13. 25. he is Coryphaeus,
the chiefe captaine and ringleader of all forces
againſt us. As for the fleſh and the world, qui nobis
moleſti ſunt, who vexe and trouble us, nihil aliud
quam jacula ex Satanae manu emiſſa; They are no other
then the Devils inſtruments, even darts ſhot at
us, by his hand, as Calvin upon the place. Nihil aliud
ſunt omnes impii,
               Gregor. Moral. l. 13. c. 15 Ioh. 12. 31. Epheſ. 2. v. 2 
               quam membra Diaboli, as Gregory in
his Morals: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the Devill is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the prince, yea

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                principalitie, as he is here termed, having rule
and dominion over the children of diſobedience, by
Gods permiſſion, his owne uſurpation, and their ſubjection,
ſo that he is a principall enemy.
            Againe the other titles here given unto him declared
as much, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                powers, this ſhewes that hee is
a potent enemy, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , ſpirituall wickedneſſe,
or wicked ſpirits, this ſheweth that he is a wily
and crafty enemy. And all theſe together, ſhew that
he is a mighty, cruell and cunning enemy. And this
the Scripture doth further witneſſe unto us, calling
him a Lion for his might, a roaring Lion for his malice,
1. Pet. 5. 8. A Dragon for his fury and felneſſe.
A great Dragon for his power and might. A great



red Dragon for his bloody malice,
                  
                     •
                  el. 12. 3. 4. and madneſſe againſt
Chriſt, and his members. A Dragon with 7
heads, for his manifold ſleights and ſubtilties, wherin
he is his crafts maſter. A Dragon with 10 hornes
for his dreadfull power. With 7 crownes upon his
head, for his manifold victories over the world. A
Dragon whoſe very taile drew the third part of the
ſtarres of heauen, and caſt them to the earth, for his
victory over many Miniſters, which ſhined in life
and doctrine as the ſtarres of heauen, by the meanes
of ambition, and covetouſneſſe, and other fleſhly
luſts. Further hee is called a Serpent for his ſubtiltie,
and an old ſerpent for his great ſubtiltie,Gen. 3. 1. 
               Revel.
               
                  20. 2.—Cui nomina mille,
                  Mille nocendi artes—
               
He hath a thouſand names, and a thouſand wayes
to hurt us, as Hierome to Heliodorus de vita eremitica.
            
            Afford your attention a while,9 Stratagems of the Devill to entrap men in. and I will diſcover
ſome of his wiles, and ſtratagems unto you, that you
may the better avoyd them. Mala eius cognita facilius
evitantur. For it is eaſier to ſhunne knowne, then
unexpected dangers.
            
                One wile of Sathan to circumvent us, is to aſſault us
at the firſt by ſmall and light temptations. As a wiſe
Captaine ſends out his ſpies to ſee the ſtate of the
contrary army, their number &amp; ſtrength, and to view
what advantages may be taken; and perhaps ſends a
skirmiſh only, to trie their purpoſe and ſtrength: So
Sathan he begins with light onſets, with ſmall things,
before he comes with his many forces. As thus, firſt
he will tempt us to uſe ſmall and mincing oathes, as
faith, and troth, to uſe a little lying, a little ſtealing,
to giue our eyes libertie to wander a little with



wanton glaunces, to looſe the reines of our tongues to
friske it out a little in ſome idle and laſcivious ſpeeches.
To unſhackle our feet to carry us a little to ſuch
and ſuch places of leud reſort. Thus he begins with
little things. As if a little leaven leavened not the
whole lumpe,1. Cor. 5. 6. as the Apoſtle ſaith. And a little leake
in a ſhippe did not drowne all, unleſſe it be ſtopt: And
ſo a little ſinne did not ſinke us in the pit of perdition,
unleſſe it be repented of.
            A ſecond ſleight of Sathan is to tempt us to yeeld 
to him in one requeſt and that for a little time, at
leaſt for once. As if he that keepes the whole law,
and yet offends in one point (habitually) is not guilty
of all, as the Apoſtle ſaith, Iam. 2. 10. or that one
act of licentiouſneſſe did not engender the deſire of
two, and two the deſire of fowre, and tenne the deſire
of twenty. And ſo,
Quo plus ſunt potae plus ſitiuntur aquae,
The more this ſtolne water is drunke, and this
vice committed, the more the deſire is increaſed.
            A third wile of Sathan, is to promiſe great matters 
of profit,Mat. 4. v. 9. pleaſure, preferment, ſaying, Omnia haec tibi
dabo, all theſe things will I give thee. That is, I will
make thee Pope, as the Centuriators interpret it: Or I
will give thee this Biſhopricke, that Cardinallſhip,
ſuch a living, ſo much money, or maintenance, &amp;c.
All theſe will I give thee, if thou wilt worſhip me, by
idolatry, ſuperſtition, blaſphemie, prophaneſſe, or
otherwiſe by breaking Gods commandements. As
if Godlineſſe were not the greateſt gaine,1. Tim. 6. v. 6 and the
ſweeteſt pleaſure to pleaſe God; even ſweeter then
the hony and the hony combe, yea more delightfull
then all manner of riches, as the Prophet David


               
ſaith, Pſal. 119. 14.
            
                A fourth wile of Sathan is to plead that he hath
many, and great ones of his ſide, euen the greateſt in
the ſtate, and the chiefeſt in the country that be ſwearers,
adulterers, drunkards, oppeſſors, Papiſts, and the
like. Doe any of the Rulers beleeue in Chriſt, ſaith he
by his advocates, Ioh. 7. v. 48. This ſect is every
where ſpoken againſt,Act. 28. v. 22. is their plea in another place,
As if many did not run the broad way, as Chriſt ſaith,
Mat. 7. 13. or that many and mighty were called, 1.
Cor. 1. 26. or if called were choſen, Mat. 20. 16.
            
                A fift wile of Sathan is to obiect the miſeries, and
the reproches, and the many overthrowes that the
the ſervants of God ſuſtaine in the world, and the
proſperitie of the wicked on the other ſide. Thus he
doth Malac. 3. 14. 15. As if Chriſts kingdome were
of this world, Iohn 18. 36. or that being killed for
Chriſts ſake, they were not therein more then Conquerors,
Rom. 8. 37.
            A ſixt ſleight of Sathan is to ſet out foule ſinnes
and errors, with a faire face, colour and countenance,
even with the colour of grace and vertue, even as the
the crafty pyrate doth ſomtime hang out the ſame
colours that the honeſt Mariner doth, thereby to entrappe
him.2. Cor. 11. 4. So Sathan will ſometimes transforme
himſelfe into an Angel of light. As thus, he will ſet
out licentiouſneſſe under the name of libertie, drunkenneſſe
under the colour of good fellowſhip, covetouſneſſe
under the name of good husbandry, fury
under the name of mettle, or manhood, whoredome
under the name of loving a miſtreſſe, Simony under
the name of gratuity, unlawfull ſports under the
name of honeſt mirth and recreation, Poperie under



the name of old Religion, or the Catholicke faith.
Depopulation, and encloſing of commons under the
name of uſing ones owne; or doing with ones owne
as he liſt &amp;c.
            Thus he dies all his bad clothes in good colours,
guilds over his falſe coyne, ſugars over his temptations,
and paints the foule faces of ſinne with the fine
colours of vertues and graces.
            Yea hee will not ſticke to adventure to deceive
Saul,
               1. Sam. 18. v. 14. under Samuels mantle.Prov. 8. O then, what need have
we to flye to Ieſus Chriſt, who dwelleth with prudence.
What need have we not to be carried with every
thing that hath a ſhew of goodneſſe, or indifferency.
But to bring theſe painted ſtrumpets of the
Devill, to the light, yea and to the heat of the word
of God. And then their painting ſhall melt away,
and we ſhall ſee their beauty came out of the Devills
boxe. Beloved, nimium ne crede colori, be not carried
away with colours, and ſhowes. The Devill hath a
faire colour for the fouleſt ſinne.
            A 7th trick of the Devill is to put a vizard of evill 
upon that which is good. As to call the Catholicke
and Apoſtolicke doctrine of our Church hereſie,
and the Profeſſors thereof Hereticks, ſo the Papists:
to call the wholeſome diſcipline of our Church Popiſh
ſuperſtition, ſo the Schiſmaticks. To call conſcience
of ſinne, and a deſire in all things to live honeſtly,
preciſe niceneſſe, ſo the carnall Goſpellers. Thus
by calling evill good, and good evill, hee would
bring it to paſſe that there ſhould be nothing but evill
and ſo in the end nothing but woe? For woe
ſhall be to him that calls evill good, and good evill,
Iſa. 5. 20.
            
               
                Another Stratageme of the Devill is to wound
us with our owne weapons, even with our very
graces; As thus, if he ſees ſome zealous, and fervent
in religion, ſo that he can in no wiſe quench this fire,
then he will throw his Gun-powder into it, and under
the colour of zeale, bring them to prepoſterous
indiſcretion, yea to a blind and bold madneſſe. As
to undertake, being private men, to reforme publick
abuſes, without the Magiſtrates authority, and to
make as great fire for the roſting of an egge, as for
the roſting of an Oxe; I meane to bee as zealous for
the ſmall, as for the weightier matters of the law,
for the ſwadling clothes, as for the body of religion,
for the circumſtance, as for the ſubſtance. A thing
very dangerous to the Church, as we may ſee in the
example of Auda Biſhop in Perſia, who in an exceſſe
of zeale throwing downe a Temple of the Pagans,
was the cauſe that the king thereby incenſed, threw
downe all temples of the Chriſtians, as Theodoret
writes, Lib. 5. Remember then to keep the meane according
to Gods word, Iſa 30. 21. Be not righteous
overmuch, make not thy ſelfe over wiſe, Eccleſ. 7.
16. If ye cannot doe that good ye &amp; deſire, doe that ye
can, and ſo bee zealous according to knowledge,
Rom. 10. 2. If with Paul ye cannot put downe Castor,
and Pollux, the badges of heatheniſme or Papiſme, yet
doe not run out of the ſhippe, S. Paul did not ſo, Act.
28. 11. or if ye dwell in Epheſus an idolatrous place
where the great Goddeſſe Diana is worſhiped, ſo
that with S. Paul ye canot hinder it, yet for all that,
doe not in an undiſcreet zeale leaue your Miniſter,
runne out of Epheſus, S. Paul did not ſo, Act. 19. 10.
I take it, that wiſdome is not from above, when men



will doe nothing, unleſſe they may doe what they
will. Surely ſuch fiery zeale hath ſome of the Devills
powder in it.
            Another pollicy of Sathan to overthrow Gods 
ſervants and ſouldiours, is to perſwade thoſe that bee
great wits, to prie into the counſells, and decrees
of their Generall Chriſt Ieſus, when they ſhould
follow him. And to meddle with his Myſteries,
when they ſhould meddle with their owne buſineſſe:
knowing that to be the way to bring them out
of favour, and to be rebuked with Peter, for curioſity,
with Quid ad te? what is that to thee? follow thou
me, Ioh. 21. 21.
            Many other wiles, and Stratagems Sathan hath,
to enſnare, and entrap us; which I have now no time
to relate, theſe be they which be now moſt in uſe.
And by theſe you ſee what a dangerous enemy you
have.
            What remaineth then, but that we ſhake off all
ſecurity, and provide, and prepare to withſtand him?
What remaineth but that wee ſhould bee ſober and
watch, ſeeing our adverſary the Devill goeth about
and ſeeketh ſo many waies to devoure us? That is the
counſell of the Apoſtle in this caſe, let us follow it,
and watch.
            Specially let us be carefull that wee give him no
advantage againſt us,8 Wayes whereby we give the Devill advantage againſt us. and ſo betray our ſelves into
his hands. There be many waies whereby advantage
is given unto Sathan. And whereby as it were we
tempt the Temptor.
            One is being too wordly minded, ſo much the 
text here doth teach us, for therefore the Devill is
called 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , a ruler of the world. Quia praevalet



adverſus eos qui mundana cogitant. Saith Aretius
upon the place, that is, becauſe he prevailes much againſt
thoſe that are wordly minded. And this the
Apoſtle witneſſeth more plainely, in another place,
ſaying, that they which be rich fall into temptation,
and a ſnare of the Devill. 1. Tim. 6. 9.
            
                A ſecond way, whereby we give advantage unto
Sathan againſt us, is by living in the darkneſſe of ignorance.
This we are taught alſo here in the text, in
that Sathan is here called Rector tenebrarum, (.i.) Ruler
of the darkneſſe of this world, for this is, becauſe
he rules, and domineires moſt over them that live in
darkneſſe, and blindneſſe of mind, in darke and blind
ignorance of the Scripture. And this our Saviour
ſpeakes in more plaine termes, ſaying, ye erre, not
knowing the Scriptures, Mark. 12. 24. ſo that if we
will not fall into errours and the ſnares of the Devill,
we muſt beware how we live in darke ignorance.
            
                A third way, whereby we give the Devill advantage
over us, is by yeelding a little to his temptations,
as to ſweare, lie, or ſteale a little, and the like.
For if he can get us to yeeld to his motions in a little;
he will quickly bring us to more. If this Serpent
can wind in his head, hee will quickly draw his
whole body after. Patente portâ impoſſibile eſt malum
ulteriùs non procedere. Set open but one gate of
a beſieged city, and the enemies will come in as
certainly, as if all the walls were demoliſhed. Let
errour get but once into the belfrey, and it will never
leave till it be in the chancell, as learned Fulk hath
noted. Suffer it to be but in the porch, and it will not
be long, but you ſhall ſee it poſſeſſed of the Church
it ſelfe, yea and jetting in the pulpit alſo. As then



               Moſes would not yeeld to Pharaoh in a hoofe, Exod.
10. 20. or orthodoxall chriſtians to Arrius in a letter,
ſo as to ſay 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                for 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , no more let us
yeeld to any errour in life or doctrine, in profeſſion
or practiſe, ſpecially not to idolatry. No, not for all
the kingdomes in the world, and the glory thereof.
So would not Chriſt, Mat. 4. 8, 9. no not for an
houre, ſo did not Paul, Galat. 2. 5. est leo ſi fugias. If
ye give place but a little to his temptations, on hee
goes.Acriùs urge
                     •
                  
                  hoſtis. And the more we give place to him, the more
he encroaches. Therefore beware how you yeeld to
him in the leaſt motion, in an apple, as Eve, or in a
looke, as Lots wife. Give a hot horſe his head at
firſt, and he will ſurely runne away with you. And
ſo will this beaſt if we give him the bridle, if wee but
a little yeeld to him. Sathan can uſe ſmall finnes, as
the fiſher uſeth ſmall haires, to hold the fiſh as faſt,
or faſter then greater tackling, and ſecret ſinnes to
doe more harme in the ſoule then open.
            A 4th way, whereby wee give advantage to the 
Devill againſt us, is by ruſhing into thoſe places or
companies, where Sathan hath power over our bodies
of ſoules, in regard of the dangerous provocations
to ſinne they yeeld. As ſolitary and ſecret places;
places of idolatry, of whoredome, of exceſſive drinking,
gaming, ſwearing, &amp;c. the company of mockers,
railers, diſſemblers, or any other wicked perſons.
Theſe are the Devills factors, and their dwelling
his ſtaple, his ſchoole-houſe as S. Cyprian, his
throne as S. Iohn calls it, Revel. 2. 13. Now can a man
be ſafe where Sathans throne is? Amongſt the children
of diſobedience where he beares rule?Epheſ. 2. 2. Can a
man take fire in his boſome, or walke upon coales



and not be burnt? Surely the ſweeteſt waters by running
into the ſea, become ſalt and brackiſh: And ſo
men of ſweet natures, and excellent graces have
beene perverted by the company of the wicked.
Witneſſe Ioſeph, who was ſnared to ſweare by the
life of Pharaoh, in the court of Aegypt, And the Apoſtle
Peter who was tempted to deny his Lord and
Maſter, in the Hall of Caiaphas. To give the Devill
therefore no advantage over us, we muſt have no
company with the wicked.
            
                A fift way whereby we giue the Divell advantage
againſt us, is by living idly, 
                  
                     •
                  tium pulvinar Diaboli:
idleneſſe is the Divells pillow, to reſt on, Quem non
invenit occupatum ipſe occupat, he will imploy thoſe
that will not imploy themſelues. The crabfiſh when
as the oyſter doth open, flings into her a little ſtone,
ſo that ſhee cannot ſhut her ſelfe againe, and ſo the
crab devoures the oyſter: Even ſo ſaith Hierome, our
adverſarie the Divell, like the crab, when he finds us
idle, and gaping, like the oyſter, takes his opportunity
to confound us. When we ſleepe and are ſecure,
then he will be ſowing of tares, in the field of the
church, and in the ground of our hearts.Mat. 13. 25. Therefore
let us follow the counſell of Chriſt which ſaith,
occupamini donec veniam, that is occupie or be doing,
till I come. Luke 19. Res age tutus eris.
            
            
                A ſixt way is by playing with the obiects of ſinne,
it is not ſafe for the fiſh to play with the baite. And
no more is it for any man to play with the obiects
of ſinne.
            
                A ſeuenth way is by not looking well to the outward
ſenſes of our bodies, ſpecially the two ſenſes
of learning, Seeing, and Hearing. Can the heart or



market-place of a Towne, or City, be ſafe from the
ſiege of an enemy, if the gates be caſt open, or the
walls demolliſhed, or the ramparts bared of their
fence, and munition? or can a kingdome be ſafe from
an invading enemy, unleſſe the cinqueports be carefully
looked to, and watched? Now the ſenſes, ſpecially
our ſeing, and hearing, are the gates of our
hearts, and the cinque-ports of our ſoules, If we doe
not then looke well to them, and keepe a diligent
watch over them, we make our ſelues a prey to the
enemy, we open the gates for him to come in, and
therefore if we will not give the enemy too much
advantage, let us with David turne away our eyes
from beholding vanitie,
                  Pſal. 119. 37. Vrit videndo foemina, activè, &amp; paſſivè and our eares alſo from hearing
vanitie. Let us looke to all the ſenſes of our bodyes,
as ſo many gates and doores of our ſoules, that
Sathan enter not in that way, locke them, barre them,
bolt them faſt.
            Finally, if you deſire not to giue the divell advantage 
in this conflict, then take heede of the intemperate
uſe of Gods creatures, by too much eating
and drinking. We read in the Goſpell, that the diſpoſeſſed
Divells,Mat. 8. 31. entreated Chriſt that he would ſuffer
them to goe into the herd of ſwine, becauſe the
chiefe place of the Divells reſidence, is the ſoule of
the ſwilling drunkard, as Bonaventure giues the reaſon.
In dry places he finds no reſt, ſaith Chriſt, Mat.
12. 43. that is, in ſober minds he gets no footing, as
the ſame Author interprets it, he dwells in lowe
countries and wet grounds, that is, with ſuch as are
filled with wine, wherein is exceſſe:
Invadunt urbem ſomno vino
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſepultum;V
                        •
                     gil.
               
When the Troians were dead drunke, then the Grecians



did ſet upon, and overcame them, ſaith the Poet.
When Benhadad king of Syria, with two and thirtie
kings more in his company, were comming againſt
Achab king of Iſraell and perceiving Achabs
power to be ſmall in reſpect of his, did fall a banketing
and drinking with the Kings,1. Kings 20, 
                     •
                  2. his aiders, and
made themſelues drunke, Achab with his ſmall power
overcame them all: And ſo when we haue diſtemperd
our ſelues, by eating, or drinking, then inſteed
of over coming the Divell, our enemy, he overcomes
us making us to kill our deare friend Clitus,
with Alexander, or to commit inceſt, with Lot, or to
commit all ungodlineſſe,Gen. 19. 32. euen with greedineſſe, as
the Sodomites. Therfore if you will not giue place
to the Divell, follow the counſell of Chriſt, that is,
take heed leaſt at any time your hearts be over chared
with ſurfetting, and drunkeneſſe, Luk. 21. 34.
            There be many other wayes whereby we giue
place, &amp; advantage unto the Divell againſt us, As by
immoderate anger and wrath, Epheſ. 4. 26, 27. By being
wavering minded, and unſetled in the faith. Iam.
1. 6. By impatience and diſcontent, by pride and ambition,
by yeelding to any corruption, we giue the
Devill ſo much ground, and inſteed of beating him
out of our borders, we let him in, and betray our
ſelues into his hands, and lead our ſelues into his
temptations, contrarie to our forme of prayer.
            And now (Beloued) we haue no need to doe ſo;
we haue no reaſon at all to giue any oddes, or advantage
to Sathan in this combate, by theſe, or any
other wayes, for we are not ſo ſtrong, as that we may
afford it. But eſpecially we may not preſume to encounter
with this adverſarie, naked, or without our



ſword, the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word
of God; as the ſeduced Papiſts are put to, by their
moſt iniurious leaders. No, no, the truth is, let us
looke to our ſelues as well as we can, and arme our
ſelues as ſtrongly as we can, and take all the advantage
and helpes that may be had, we ſhall have ennough
to doe, with theſe principalities and powers,
with the Rulers of the darkneſſe of this world, with
the ſpirituall wickedneſſes, or wicked ſpirits, thoſe
ſecret and inviſible enemies. Yea, and more then wee
can well acquit our ſelves of, as of our ſelves, for of
our ſelves wee are not ſufficient to thinke, much
leſſe to doe it, 2. Cor. 3. 5. ſo that we have no reaſon to
give any advantage herein.
            And beſide, the cauſe or matter of the Conflict,
between Sathan and us,The cauſe of the Conflict. 
               non de parvis quibuſdam rebus,
is no ſmall matter, that we ſhould be ſecure and
careleſſe. Sed de rebus quae ſunt in coeleſtibus, hoc eſt
pro regno coelorum, &amp; adoptione, nobis lucta, ſaith Aretius
upon the place; But a matter of heaven, and heavenly
things, a matter of a kingdome, and our right
and intereſt to it, that is the thing in queſtion, the
matter of the quarrell, and combate betweene us.
And is not this a weighty matter, that we ſhould beſtirre
our ſelves about it? Surely how light ſoever we
make of it, it is a matter of life and death. It is ſuch a
matter, that we muſt either kill or be killed. For if
we doe not crucify the fleſh with the affections
and luſts, the fleſh will bee our death, for to bee
carnally minded is death, Rom. 8. 6. If the world be
not crucified unto us, and wee unto the world, the
world will be our ruine; for the world ſhall bee damned,
1. Cor. 11. 32. If we doe not daſh Babilons children



againſt the ſtones,Pſal. 137. v. 
                     •
                  9. ſuppreſſing the firſt motions
of ſinne, and temptations of Sathan, they will be ſure
to daſh us to death; for the wages of ſinne is death,
Rom. 6. 23.
            So then it concernes us neere to looke to it; being
a matter of ſo great conſequence, and importance, a
matter of life &amp; death, the winning or looſing of our
heauenly inheritance in high places. And that in
ſtrife with ſo potent and politick enemies, let us conſider
then, and thinke of the matter, that we haue in
hand. A high place in heauen is worth the ſtriving
for, ſpecially when it may be had for ſtriving, according
to that, the kingdome of heauen ſuffereth violence,
and the violent take it by force, Mat. 12. 12.
It is worth ſomewhat that Sathan doth ſo much
ſtrive, and ſtruggle to get from us. A theife will not
meddle with a poore begger, that hath nothing to looſe,
a pirat will not ſet upon emptie ſhippes, a
mighty enemy will not invade a kingdome, or lay
ſiege to a City, with great violence to winne it,
where there is no great matter to be had: and ſo ſurely
it is not for nothing that Sathan with all his forces,
doth make ſuch fierce and violent aſſaults upon
the ſervants of God: no, Coeleſtia, theſe high places,
or heauenly things, for which he wreſtles with us,
are great things, and ſo let us with great care contend
for them.
            
                Yea and this let us doe without delay, even this
time,The time of the Conflict. for the time of the warfare &amp; wreſtling with Sathan,
&amp; his forces is now, euen this preſent time. The
Apoſtle here ſets it downe ſo, ſaying, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
we wreſtle, or there is a wreſtling, and as he ſayes it,
ſo we find it indeed, for as heretofore he that was



borne after the fleſh,Galat. 4. 29 perſecuted him that was borne
after the ſpirit, euen ſo it is now. Now the world is
full of ſuch as ſcoffe at Iſaac,
               Act. 7. 51. c. 13. 8. like Iſmael, of ſuch as
reſiſt the holy Ghoſt, as the ſtiffenecked Iewes, of
ſuch as withſtand Barnabas and Saul and ſeeke to
turne the Deputie from the faith, like Simon the Sorcerer;
of ſuch as be accuſers of the brethren, like the
Devill, Revel. 12. 10. of ſuch as greatly withſtand the
word, like Alexander the Copper-ſmith, of ſuch as
warre with them that keepe the commandements of
God, and haue the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt, as the
Dragon,2. Tim. 4. v. 15. 
               Revel. 12. 17. Now the world is full of ſuch
warriers and wreſtlers againſt the true worſhippers
of God, yea and neuer more, for now the Devill
warres with great wrath, becauſe he knoweth he
hath but a ſhort time, v. 12.
            And ſeeing it is ſo that there is ſuch warring and
wreſtling of the enemies ſide againſt us at this time,
Let us of the other ſide be as ready, and forward, to
warre and wreſtle againſt them, ſo that we may truly
ſay, nobis lucta, we wreſtle.
            Yea, and this let us reſolue to doe,Iob. 7. not for a day or
two, but for as long as we liue, for militia vita hominis
ſuper terram, as Iob ſaith, the whole life of a Chriſtian
is a continuall warfare here on earth.
            
               Nunquam bella bonis, nunquam iſſidia ceſſant,
               Et quocum cert et mens bona ſemper habet.
            
            Good men muſt not looke for peace upon earth,
Chriſt came not to ſend it, Mat. 10. 34. The Dragon
and his Angels will fight with the Michael and his
Angells, as long as the world laſts, ſo that we muſt
warre as long as we liue. They will be ſure to warre,
and wreſtle with us, either by inward or outward



temptations, by violent perſecutions, or fraudulent
Hereſies, by ſharpe tongues or ſharpe ſwords, or,
both, and we had not need to lie ſtill, and to let them
alone, without any reſiſtance, ſurely no, we haue
cauſe to warre and wreſtle with them, as well as they
with us, and more too, for if we fight the good fight,
and finiſh our courſe, and keepe the faith, we ſhall
obtaine the crowne of righteouſneſſe, but ſo ſhall
not they. Therefore let us reſolue upon it, and wreſtle
againſt fleſh, and blood, againſt principalities
and powers, againſt Rulers of the darkneſſe of this
world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places,
againſt the Devill, and all his forces, of perſecuting
Tyrants, of ſubtill hereticks, of peſtilent Antichriſts,
of wicked worldlings and carnall Goſpellers, And
this unto the end.
            But (here ſome will ſay) how ſhall we,Ob. that are
weake and fraile, be able to wreſtle and encounter,
with ſo potent and politicke enemies, with ſo many
and malicious adverſaries? or if we doe preſume to
wreſtle and fight with them, how ſhall we prevaile
againſt them?Sol: The truth is we cannot prevaile againſt
them, by our owne ſtrength, we muſt haue ſome other
meanes, even the ſtrength of the Lord. And
therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, be ſtrong in the Lord,
v. 10. We muſt haue other armour then our owne
to fight in, even the armour of God. And therefore
the Apoſtle ſaith,
                  
                     •
                   Generall part (1) Conqueſt wherein 3 things▪
                put on the armour of God, that ye
may be able to ſtand in the evill day, which is the
true meanes of the Conqueſt, and the laſt point.
            
                To overcome in this warre, we muſt put on Gods
armour,The meanes of the Conqueſt▪
                not the armour of the fleſh, for curſed is he
that maketh fleſh his arme, Ier. 17. 5. Not the armour



of the world,Haec ſunt ſarcaſmi Diaboli Chemnitius.
                for our enemies are worldly Governours,
and the chiefe of them the Prince of this
world. Ioh. 2. 31. Not the armour of the Devill, as
Popiſh exorciſme, Superſtitious croſſing, Holy water,
Maſſes, Diriges, Crucifixes, Conſecrated hoſts,
Graines, Oyle, Reliques of Saints, Agni Dei, and
ſuch like trumperie which the Papiſts uſe. Not the
woodden dagger of fabulous hiſtories, or the ruſty
ſcabberd of old traditions, as the ſame Romaniſts
uſe. Theſe are weapons of the Devills owne making,
and forging, not of Gods appointing, here are none
of theſe among the armor of God, &amp; yet here is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
the whole armor of God. Againe, we may
not uſe charmes, and ſuch like, which coniurers uſe,
here are none of theſe mentioned. Theſe are the Devills
watchword, not Gods word, this is to caſt out
the Devill by Belzebub, not by the finger of God,
further we may not uſe wanton ſonets, thundring
oathes, or mad mirth, as carnall proteſtants
doe, nor yet lyes and libels, as undiſcreet ſchiſmaticks
doe, and the Papiſts alſo, who call their lyes and
cheating tricks, Pias fraudes, godly deceits. Theſe are
the Devills weapons and engines, framed in his ſhop,
who is a lyer from the beginning,Ioh. 8. 44. and giuen at his appointment,
and therefore little feared by him.
            Theſe are not the weapons that we muſt fight
with, or if fight that we can over come with; no, no,1. Sam. 17. 9. 10. he
that truſts in his owne ſtrength ſhall proue weake like
Goliah, or in his owne wit, ſhall proue a foole,2 Sam. 17. 23. like a
Achitophell,
               Luk. 18. 13. or in his righteouſneſſe, ſhall prove moſt
unrighteous, as the Phariſees, before whom the Publicans
and ſinners (repenting of their owne unrighteouſneſſe,
and relying by faith on the righteouſneſſe of



Chriſt) ſhall enter into the kingdome of heaven. He
that truſt in Princes, or any childe of man, ſhall find
true,Iſa. 36. v. 6. which Rabſhaka ſpoke of the king of Egypt, that
they are but broken reeds to leane to. He that truſts in
his ſtrong hold, great wealth, in his chariots, horſes,
forces, in any thing beſides God, for his defence and
ſafety, ſhall find as little helpe and comfort in time of
need, as the Prieſts of Baal had of Baal, at their need,
even none at all, 1. Kings 18. 29.
            Outward meanes are good and neceſſary to be
uſed, but in no wiſe to be truſted in. If we ſet them
up in Gods roome, they become very pernicious, or
moſt unprofitable, ſpecially if they be unwarrantable
meanes. While others then ſtrengthen themſelves
in their owne might, lane to their owne wiſdome,
repoſe themſelves on their owne righteouſneſſe,
betake themſelves to their owne freedome, follow
their owne wayes, truſt to their owne forces, let
us (with David) remember the name of the Lord
our God, Pſal. 20. 7. And as the Apoſtle ſaith, ſo ſay
I unto you; My Brethren be ſtrong in the Lord, and
in the power of his might.
            Put on the armour of God,2 Cor. 10. v. 4. that is, the grace of
God. For the weapons of our warfare are not carnall,
as the Apoſtle ſaith; But ſpirituall, even the
grace of Gods ſpirit. By this we are ſaved, Epheſ.
2. 8. By this we ſtand, 1. Pet. 1. 12. This is the armour
of proofe, that is mighty through God, to the pulling
downe of ſtrong holds, to the caſting downe of
imaginations, and every high thing, that exalteth it
ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God, and to bring into
captivity every thought to the obedience of
Chriſt, 2. Cor. 10. 4, 5.
            
               
Give diligence then to arme and furniſh your
ſelves with grace, that you may be able to encounter
with your ſpirituall enemies, and to withſtand
their aſſaults.
            Take unto you the whole armour of God, that is,
the manifold graces of Gods ſpirit, all chriſtian
vertues, and thereby adorne the underſtanding, the
will,Particular meanes of the conqueſt. the affections aud the whole inner man. And
namely, &amp; ſpecially take unto you the graces &amp; vertues
here mentioned, &amp; commended unto us, that is.
            First, take the girdle of truth, that is, the knowledge 
of the truth,Ioh. 17. 17. the true knowledge of the word
of God, which is the word of truth, and thereby informe
and adorne your underſtanding. Danda inprimis
operimis opera eſt, ut Deum noſcamus, quotquot felices eſſe
volumus: The firſt thing that we muſt labour for,
is to know the truth, that is it which is here firſt
commended by the Apoſtle. And it is the firſt
charge which king David gave unto his ſonne Solomon,
ſaying, and thou Solomon my ſonne, know thou
the God of thy fathers,2. Chron. 28. 9. and ſerve him with a perfect
heart, and a willing mind &amp;c. hee bids his ſonne
ſerve God with a perfect heart, but firſt hee bids
him know him, becauſe without knowledge, wee
cannot ſerve him: or at leaſt not rightly and acceptably,
as we may ſee by the example of the Iewes,
Rom. 10. 2. who had the feare of God, but not according
to knowledge. Without knowledge of the word
of truth, we know not where we are, nor which way
to goe to ſave our ſelves, and to eſcape the enemy.
He that walketh in darkneſſe knoweth not whither
he goeth, ſaith Chriſt himſelfe, Ioh. 12. 35. And it is
impoſſible, till wee come to the knowledge of the



truth, that ever wee ſhould come out of the ſnare of
the Devill, ſaith S. Paul. 2. Tim. 2. 25. 26.
            Let us labour then firſt of all to know the truth,
out of the word of truth, that thereby wee may diſcerne
right from wrong. And when we have knowne
it, let us gird our ſelves therewith, that is, ſticke cloſe
to it, and then feare not, Vincet veritas, Truth will
prevaile, for truth is great, and mightie aboue all
things. 1. Eſdras 4. 41.
            
                But this is not all that we muſt labour for, that is, to
know,1. Pet. 1. 22. and to ſpeake the truth. We muſt goe further,
and obey the truth, and with Gajus, walke in the truth
3. Ioh. 3. And namely in this truth, of ſerving the
Lord in righteouſneſſe, ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, in the
next place, put on the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe,
that is, endeavour to keepe a cleare conſcience, voyd
of offence, towards God, and towards man, as S.
Paul did, Act. 24. 16. endeavour to walke inoffenſively
towards all men. Scire, vel de virtute loqui minimum
est. To know, or to ſpeake the truth, and to give
good precepts, is no great matter, it is the leaſt of a
thouſand, who cannot doe it? But, virtutibus uti, to
joyne truth and righteouſneſſe, ſound knowledge
and ſincere obedience together, hic labor, hoc opus eſt.
This is the maine matter, this is a worke of moment,
and to the purpoſe: hic murus ahaeneus esto,
               Nil conſcire ſibi, nullâ palleſcere culpâ.
This is to make a brazen wall, a ſtrong towre of
defence againſt the face of our enemies: even to put
on the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, as well as the
girdle of truth, to joyne ſcience and conſcience together.
With this S. Paul did ſupport, and beare himſelfe
out, againſt the obloquie, and troubles he endured;



in that he had lived in all good conſcience before
God,Act. 23. v. 1. and had his converſation in ſimplicity, and
godly ſincerity, 2. Cor. 1. 12. This made him as bold
as a lion, the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, the teſtimony
of a good conſcience. With this let us alſo
arme our ſelves, joyne to the girdle of truth, the
breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, knowledge and obedience,
ſcience and a good conſcience,Non eget Mauri jaculi
                     •
                   &amp;c. and then wee
need not feare. Qui vadit planè, vadit ſanè, he that
walketh uprightly, walketh ſurely, Prov. 10. 9. walke
on then, walke and march in this armour of truth,
and righteouſneſſe, of ſcience and a good conſcience.
            Moreover, let me adviſe you to take the ſhooes of 
the preparation of the Goſpell of peace along with
you, that is, reſolve throughly and firmely with your
ſelves, to believe and hold, that God is now reconciled
and at peace with you, through the meanes of
Chriſt, according as he hath revealed and teſtified in
his Goſpell. And withall, for this peace with God
made by Chriſt which you believe, reſolve further,
in way of thankfullneſſe, to love, honour and obey
him, according to his word. This reſolution and preparation
of mind to believe, and confeſſe our peace
and reconciliation with God through Chriſt. And
to honour and obey him for it, theſe are the ſhooes
here commended unto us. With theſe king David
did furniſh himſelfe, according to that, I have ſworne,
and am ſtedfaſtly purpoſed to keepe thy righteous
judgements.Pſal. 119. 106. And thus did S. Paul alſo arme himſelfe,
when he ſaid, I am ready, not to be bound only;
but alſo to dye at Hieruſalem, for the name of the
Lord Ieſus, Act. 21. 13. Without this preparation,
and firme reſolution of the heart, to believe and obey



the Goſpell of peace, we ſhall never be able to hold
on in the race of Chriſtianity, and to paſſe through
the many tribulations, that we ſhall meet with, for a
wavering minded man is unſtable in all his wayes,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   1. v. 8.
and ready to be carried away with every wind of
temptation, and therefore let us ballance our hearts
with preparation, and put on a firme reſolution to
believe, and obey the Goſpell of peace.
            
                But yet, this is not all, that we have to doe: The
ſpeciall furniture, and that which we are to take above
all, as being able to quench all the fiery darts
of the wicked, is yet unmentioned, and that is, faith,
the ſhield of faith. That we are to take above all, ſo
ſaith the Apoſtle, above all take the ſhield of faith,
v. 16. That is, after all your knowledge of the truth,
and your righteouſneſſe, according to the knowne
truth, and your reſolution, to walke in this knowne
true righteouſneſſe: Yet reſt not upon all this, but
when ye have done all, deny your ſelves, renounce
all truſt, and confidence in your owne righteouſneſſe,
and lay hold on the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, by the
hand of faith, on the mercy of God in Chriſt for
your ſalvation, according as it is offered in the word,
and preſented in the Sacraments. This righteouſneſſe,
this mercy of God in Chriſt is that ſhield that
can quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. Indeed
faith is here called the ſhield, in the text, but that is
not becauſe it is ſo in it ſelfe, but becauſe it takes
hold of Chriſt, and his righteouſneſſe which is the
true ſhield indeed, and puts it on, and makes it ours.
So that,Ioh. 25. 5. though we can doe nothing of our ſelves, in
this Conflict, yet through him, and his righteouſneſſe
wee are able to doe all things, Philip. 4. 13. to



quench all the fiery darts, and fierce temptations of
the wicked, to overcome the world, the fleſh and the
Devill, 1. Ioh. 5. And therefore put on the ſhield of
Chriſts righteouſneſſe, by the hand of faith, ſhroud
your ſelves under this defence of the moſt high,Pſal. 1. v. 1.
cleave to Gods promiſe of grace in Chriſt.
            And becauſe the promiſes of God in Chriſt,
which are the objects of our faith, and the ground of
our obedience, are not alwayes preſently performed
unto the faithfull, upon their requeſt, ſo that Sathan,
and his adherents take occaſion thereby, to aſſault
their faith, and to ſay where is now their God, Pſal.
115. 2. Here againe, we are to remember to furniſh
our ſelves with another peece of armour, againſt
this aſſault. And namely, with the helmet of ſalvation,
that is, with the hope of ſalvation, as the Apoſtle
expounds it, 1. Theſ. 5. 8. A ſure and certaine hope of
all promiſed good things, which be yet for to come.
This hope and patient expectation of the performance
of Gods promiſes, is very needfull. So ſaith
the Apoſtle, ye have need of patience, that after ye
have done the will of God, ye may receive the promiſes,
Heb. 10. 36. And ſo let your patient mind be
knowne unto all men, as the Apoſtle adviſeth, hold
faſt the confidence of your hope firme unto the end,
for hope maketh not aſhamed, Rom. 5. 5.
            And in the meane ſpace, while we hope and expect 
the performance of Gods promiſes, in the
preſent preſervation, and finall ſalvation of his
Church, &amp; in particular, of us the members thereof,
let us take to our ſelues, the ſword of the ſpirit,
which is the word of God, acquainting our ſelues,
therewith, that when the world, the fleſh, or the Devill



doe aſſault us with their temptations, we may be
able to anſwere &amp; to repell them, as Chriſt did, with
a ſcriptum eſt, a place of ſcripture, and thereby cut
off their temptations, as with a ſword. The word of
God is mighty and powerfull to that purpoſe, being
rightly applyed, as we may ſee by the example of
Chriſt in the fourth of Mat. yea ſharper then any
two edged ſword, as S. Paul ſaith Heb. 4. 12. Take it
then, put it on, farre be it from us, to diſarme you of
the ſcriptures, to wring this ſpeciall weapon out of
your hands, and ſo to turne you naked unto all Sathans
temptations, as the Romaniſh teachers deale
with their people, or inſteed of the ſharpe two edged
ſword of the ſpirit, to put other weapons, of the Divills
forging into your hands to fight with us, as the
holy water, Croſſes, Graines, and dirty reliques &amp;c.
as the ſame teachers deale with their people, no,
no, we teach you with S. Paul to take the ſword of
the ſpirit which is the word of God, and to put it on,
not by ſpells, and charmes, as ignorant people uſe to
doe, but by reading, hearing, meditating and hiding
it in your hearts, and applying it as occaſion is offered,
to anſwere, and to put off any evill temptations.
Thus Chriſt himſelfe did doe, Mat. 4.
Thus he taught Iohn, Ioh. 5. at the 39 verſe, and ſo
doe we ſaying with Chriſt, ſcrutamini ſcripturas,
ſearch the ſcriptures, let the word of God dwell in
you plenteouſly in all wiſdome, Coloſ. 3. 16.
            
                Laſtly to make all ſure, and to furniſh your ſelues
with the compleate armour of God, let us ioyne inceſſant
prayer to all theſe, praying alwayes with all
prayer, and ſupplication in the ſpirit, and watching
thereunto with all perſeverance, as the Apoſtle exhorteth



               v. 18. verè coelestis armatura eſt deprecatio
quae Deo funditur, ſaith Chryſoſtome De orando Deum,
Lib. 1. that is, prayer unto God, is the very armour
of God indeed, a heauenly armour, for by this
we call, and get God &amp; all the hoſte of heaven to be
of our ſide, to helpe us againſt temptations, and to
deliver us from evill. By this Paul obtained helpe
and grace againſt inward temptations, the thorne in
the fleſh, 2. Cor. 12. 7. 8. 9. By this Moſes obtained
helpe of God againſt outward tribulations, the army
of the Amalekites, Exod. 17. 11. and this alſo is
the way for us, to obtaine helpe againſt the enemie,
yea and without this no victory. When we haue
provided all that we can, and all is done, except Moſes
hold up his hands,Exod. 17. v. 11. 
               Amaleck will prevaile. Lift up
holy hands unto God, as the Apoſtle teacheth, 1.
Tim. 2. 8. Pray alwayes with all prayer, and ſupplication
in the ſpirit, pray with private prayer unto
God; and pray with publike prayer. The prayer of
one righteous man availeth much, Iam. 5. 16. but the
prayer of many righteous men availeth more, vis
unita fortior,
               Eccleſ. 4. 9. Mat. 18. 20. two are better then one, a ioynt armie
will doe more then two or three men. Where two
or three are gathered together there is Chriſt, but
where more, there he is more gratiouſly, Act. 2. 1.
forſake not then the aſſembling of your ſelves together
to common prayer as the manner of ſome is,
Heb. 10. 25. but come to the habitation of Gods
houſe, and the place where his honour dwelleth, the
Temple, and their come, not to heare a ſermon only,
but to pray publike prayers, for we muſt pray with
all prayer, and ſupplication, with private, and publike,
in the ſecret cloſet, Mat. 6. 6. and in the publike



Sanctuary, Pſal. 150. 1. and we muſt doe this in the
ſpirit too, as the Apoſtle ſaith, that is, not out of faſhion,
but of pure devotion, not out of fained lips, but
with a true and ſyncere heart,Pſal. 17. 1. 1. Theſ. 5. 17. Mat. 17. 21. 
               Heb. 10. 22. yea, and
we muſt watch hereunto, with all perſeverance; without
this, the Devill will not away, he is not caſt out
but by faſting and prayer, yea, and watching too,
Mat. 26. 41. watch therefore and pray that ye enter
not into temptation, or if ye doe enter, that ye be not
overcome, but delivered from the evil thereof.
Mat. 6. 13.
            Theſe be the ſeverall pieces of the armour of God,
with theſe we muſt arme our ſelues, &amp; fight, if ever we
will prevaile, in this ſpirituall warfare. It is not here,
as in the bodily warfare, illic enim humanis viribus
reſiſtitur gladius opponitur gladio, homo cum homine
confligit, vis vim, ars artem excipit. In the bodily
warfare men doe commonly reſiſt their adverſaries,
with ſuch weapons as their enemies doe impugne
them withall, but here alia eſt ratio, 'tis otherwiſe, as
Calvin notes upon the place.
            In the ſpirituall warfare, if we fight againſt Sathan,
and his complices, with ſuch weapons as they
uſe in fighting againſt us, then we are gone. That is
if we render evill for evill, and rebuke for rebuke,
and give as good as they bring, as the ſaying is, then
we are foyled by Sathan and his power. For, Quid
interest inter provocantem &amp; provocatum? Saith Tertullian,
that is, what difference is there betweene him
that doth provoke to evill, and him that is provoked
to evill, by ill words or deeds? Niſi quod ille prior
in maleficio deprehenditur, &amp; ille poſterior. But that
one ſinnes firſt, and the other next. And ſo both are



foyled by Sathan, cauſing them both to ſinne.
            We muſt not then fight with Sathan, and his
complices, with ſuch weapons as they bring, rendring
evill for evill, or rebuke for rebuke. But if we
will fight to overcome, we muſt not be overcome of
evill, but overcome evill with good, Rom. 12. 21. That
is, if our enemies curſe, as they doe ſometimes with
bell, booke, and candle, we muſt not curſe againe, but
bleſſe. If they perſecute, we muſt not perſecute againe,
but pray for them, and doe good to them, that
hurt us, Mat. 5. 44. Againſt ſpirituall harmes, we
muſt uſe ſpirituall armes. Againſt the works of darknes,
we muſt put on the armor of light, that is, vertues
againſt vices. As David being to fight with Goliah,
did caſt from him the armour of Saul, and tooke to
him weapons farre unlike thoſe that Goliah brought
againſt him: So muſt we, when we goe out, in the
name of God, againſt that uncircumciſed Philiſtine,
we muſt caſt from us carnall weapons, and put on the
armour of God, even the grace of God, his manifold
graces, as a compleate armour. And namely, and ſpecially
theſe graces here mentioned, as the grace
of truth and ſyncerity of religion, the grace of righteouſneſſe
and upright converſation, the grace of preparation
and purpoſe of heart to profeſſe and practiſe
according to the Goſpell of peace, the grace
of faith in the promiſes of God in Chriſt, the grace
of hope and expectation of the promiſes beleeved,
the word of grace, the grace of prayer and ſupplication
to God, both publike, and private.
            Theſe graces are the armour of God, and they
are ſo called by way of compariſon with corporall
armour, as that, becauſe they are given us of



God,Why the graces of God are called armour. for our defence againſt our ſpirituall enemies,
as that is, againſt our corporall, and are defenſive, and
offenſive both, as other armours are, and doe declare
the bearers, and wearers thereof, to be the ſervants
and ſouldiours of Chriſt, as mens armour, and
coates ſhew to what Captaine they belong to, and
they are the meanes which we muſt uſe, and whereby
we muſt fight againſt our ſpirituall enemies, as
corporall armour is the meanes, that we muſt uſe and
fight in, againſt our corporall enemies.
            But herein, as there is a paritie, or likneſſe; ſo there
is a great diſparity, or unlikeneſſe, betwixt theſe, and
other corporall armour, for that many times is not
ſufficient, and therefore broken in pieces, but this is
alwayes ſufficient, ſo ſaith the Lord to this Apoſtle in
another place, my grace is ſufficient for thee, 2.
Cor. 12. v. 9.
            Take then unto your ſelves this whole and ſufficient
armour of God, theſe ſpeciall graces, here
mentioned.
            But here it may be enquired,Q: may not we alſo take
the armour of men, Corporall armour, as well
as ſpirituall?
            I anſwere,R: we may: it is lawfull for Chriſtian men,
at the commandement of the Magiſtrate, to weare
weapons, and to ſerue in warres; according to the doctrine
of our Church,Eccleſ. 2. 8. 
               Art. 37. and alſo according to
the ſcriptures, which ſay, that there is a time of
warre, as a time of peace, that the Magiſtrate is not
to beare the ſword in vaine, Rom. 13. 4. that he
that hath none ſhould buy a ſword. Luk. 22. 36.
That many good men did weare, and uſe humane
weapons, as Gedeon, Sampſon, David, who ſubdued



kingdomes Heb. 11. 33. and Cornelius the Centurion
Act. 10. All theſe did arme the body, and uſe corporall
weapons, and ſo may wee.
            But here I ſay againe, that the body is not the
firſt part that we muſt arme, nor humane weapons
the firſt weapons that we muſt take to our ſelves.
The firſt part that we muſt arme, is the inner man, the
ſoule, which is the life of the body. And the firſt armour
that we muſt arme it withall, is the armour, or
grace of God, which is the life of the ſoule. Thus
ſaith the Apoſtle, in the former chapter, at the 14th
verſe &amp;c. I bow my knees unto the father of our
Lord Ieſus Chriſt, of whom all the family of heaven
and earth is named, that he would grant you, according
to the riches of his glory, to bee ſtrengthened
with might by his ſpirit, in the inner
man. And thus S. Peter, your adorning, let it
not bee outward adorning,1. Pet. 3. 3. 4. but let it bee the hidden
man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible,
even the ornament of a meeke, and quiet ſpirit,
the ornament of faith, and a good conſcience,
here called the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe. Without
this, and the reſt of the ornaments, and muniments
here mentioned, even the ſtrongeſt, and beſt
armed man, will prove a coward, and flye when
none purſueth, as Solomon ſaith Prov. 28. 1. And as
the Syrians did, 2. Kings 7. 7.
            I ſay then unto you (Brethren) arme your ſelves
as well as you can, both for the inner, and outward
man, both with the corporall and ſpirituall armor: but
firſt of all, &amp; above all, arme the inner man, with the
armour of God. Take unto your ſelves the armour of
God, his grace which is ſufficient for you; 2. Cor. 12. 9.
            
               
                Take it to your ſelves, and not only that, but put it
on,The manner how to uſe the meanes of Conqueſt. which is the manner how this meanes is to bee
uſed; and the next point. This armour is not only to
be taken, and hung up at home or ſometime to bee
ſhewed abroad, to be ſeene of men: but to bee uſed
and imployed daily, in the Lords ſervice, which is
meant by putting on. God gives us his gifts and
graces, to the end that we ſhould uſe &amp; employ them.
And therefore he ſaith in another place, ſtirre up the
grace of God that is given you, 2. Tim. 1. 6. occupamini
donec veniam, occupie and employ your talents
till I come, Luk. 19. 13.
            If ye have then the armour,App
                     •
                  re quod ſis, vel eſto quod appares. Parum ſepultae diſtat i
                     •
                  
                  
                  
                     •
                  rtiae caelata virtus. theſe grace of God
in you, ſhew what ye are, ſhew them by your profeſſion,
and practiſe, and appeare in your colours. If
a man hath his armour on, and doth uſe it, it will appeare
and be ſeene on him. So let it be with you, play
not the unprofitable ſervants, to hide your talents,
your armour in the ground, uſe it, put it on.
            Put on the whole armour of God. Not only the
girdle of truth, and the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe,
but all the whole armour, head and foote, for if you
ſhould arme the head only, the Devill happily would
ſtrike at the foot. If the foot only, then he might hurt
the head. If both, and leaue our breſt unarmed, hee
might wound us at the heart. Therefore to make ſure
worke, put on the whole armour, that yee may repel
all the aſſaults of the Devill; lay not open any part to
his blow.
            Or if you will haue more of ſome one part,3 Parts ſpecially to be armed. then of
another; why then looke well to the head, the heart,
and the outward ſenſes, that ye arme them ſtrongly.
            
                Firſt the head, for as a Generall that beſiegeth a



city, laboureth moſt of all to gaine the towre, or the
caſtle; knowing that if he can take hold and poſſeſſe
that, he ſhall inſtantly command the reſt of the whole
towne: So likewiſe the Devill, who daily doth aſſault
our little city, plots ſpecially how he may be
poſſeſſed of our Capitoll, and ſconce. Knowing aſſuredly
that if our head bee tipling, our eyes will bee
wanton, our tongue blaſpheamous, our throate an
open ſepulcher, our hands ready to ſtabbe, our feet
ſwift to ſhed blood.Rom. 6. v. 13 In briefe, all our members at his
ſervice, to become ſervants of unrighteouſneſſe, to
commit all manner of ungodlineſſe, even with greedineſſe;
Therefore it is good for us, to have ſpeciall
care to arme the head, with ſobriety, &amp; watchfullnes.
            And ſo likewiſe for the heart, for that is the hold 
and fort of the ſoule. If that be not true to us, we are
ſure to be foyled in every temptaton.Prov. 4. 23. And therefore,
as Solomon ſaith, ſo ſay I unto you, Omni cuſtodiâ
cuſtodi cor tuum. Keepe thine heart with all diligence,
have it in an holy ſuſpition, ſo as to examine and
ſearch it daily, and to obſerve the treacherous
and deceiveable luſts, that lurke therein. And when
by the light of the word, you have found any, doe not
ſtay till they aſſault you, but doe you aſſault them,
and beat them down with the armour of God, uſing
Martiall law, preſently condemne and crucify them.
            And in like manner, for the outward ſenſes, we 
muſt have a ſpeciall care to keepe the parts of chriſtian
armour upon them alſo, that we lye not too open
there. A valiant captaine knowing that the enemy
is eaſier kept out, then beaten out of a city, hath great
care to plant his Gariſon about the gates and walls,
there he ſets his moſt faithfull watch and ward, there



he plants his chiefe munition and ordnance. And ſo
muſt we keepe a ſpeciall watch and ward, at the gates
of the little city, of our ſoule, even our ſenſes, &amp; there
plant our munition, that the enemy may not enter in
thereat.Iob. 31. 1. Thus did Iob, when he made a covenant with
his eyes, that hee would not looke upon a maide.
And Daniel when he would not taſt of the Kings
dainties,Dan. 1. 8. nor defile himſelfe therewith. And David
when hee vowed that hee would not heare,Pſal. 26. 6. nor ſee,
nor touch any wicked thing, Pſal. 101. 3.
            But though I commend unto you a ſpeciall care
of theſe parts, and paſſages of the ſoule, by theſe reaſous,
and examples, yet I would not have you neglect
the reſt, but to have a care of all, and to put on all
the armour of God, as the Apoſtle here teacheth.
            Yea,Gods armour to be put on in Gods ſervice
                     •
                  
                and remember further to put on the armour
of God, in Gods ſervice, in his warres, againſt his enemies
only, not againſt one another in private grudges
and bickerings, not againſt the faithfull ſervants,
and ſouldiours of Chriſt, Gods owne friends, not againſt
God, but againſt the wiles of the Devill, and
the fiery darts of the wicked. Not in ſuppreſſing, but
in maintaining of true religion, and virtue: Not in
ſecret contentions one with another, but in the publike
quarrell of the Goſpel, againſt the common
enemy.
            Many there be,The abuſe of Gods armour. who put on Gods armour, and imploy
his gifts, not in Gods, but in ſinnes, and Sathans
ſervice.
            Of this ſort are they who-cite ſcripture in defence
of errors in doctrine, as of the ſupremacy, or headſhippe
of the Church in the Pope, of iuſtification by
workes, of tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament, of



invocation of Saints, of worſhipping of images, of
equivocation or mentall reſervation, &amp;c.
            Of this ſort are they likewiſe, who cite ſcripture
in defence of errors in manners, as of ſwearing, of
prophaning the Lords day, of adultery, of drunkenneſſe,
of covetouſneſſe, of uniuſtice, of preſumption,
or any other ſinne.
            Theſe imitate that grand tempter,Mat. 4. the Devill, who
abuſively cites ſcripture, in tempting of Chriſt, and
thought to beate him with his owne weapon.
            Of this ſort alſo are they, who imploy their learning
and wit, in curious prying, and ſearching into
hidden Myſteries, in inventing and ſetting forth vaine
and wanton bookes, and other allurements of ſinne,
or in cheating and deceaving of others.
            Of this ſort are they alſo who make their eyes
windowes of vanities, who haue their eares open to
all filthy talke, ſongs and ribauld ſpeeches, who uſe
their tongues to curſing, and ſwearing, and blaſpheming
of the ſacred name of God which they ſhould
feare and reverence, who imploy their hands in fighting,
filching, and the like, who imploy their feete in
walking in the wayes of ſinners, as to bawdy-houſes
and other ſuch like places of uncleaneſſe, who ſpend
their time in eating and drinking and playing, who
apply their power to oppreſſe, and their authority
to pervert iuſtice.
            Of this ſort alſo are they, who imploy their ſilver
and gold in the ſervice of Baal,
               Hoſ. 2. 8. 9. and to the glory
of God, that abuſe their outward bleſſing to glutto
&amp; drunkenneſſe,Amos. 6. 4. that ſpend their riches on gorgeous
attire, unbeſeeming their places; upon ſtately buildings
for the ſhreeke-owle and bat to dwell in, upon



exceſſive cheere, and vaine pleaſure, ſpending more
at one banquet, then would keepe twenty poore
members of Chriſt Ieſus, in good ſort all their daies.
            Theſe, all theſe put on Gods armour, but not in
Gods, but in the enemies ſervice, they ſhoote in Gods
pieces, but it is in Gods owne face, they draw out
Gods ſword, but they ſheath it in his bowells, they
take Gods gifts, but they give them to the Devill, by
their blaſphemy, drunkenneſſe, pride &amp; uncleanes. O
horrible perfidiouſnes, and treachery, thus to receive
large gifts with the one hand from the Lord, and to
give them with the other unto the Devill his enemy.
            Beloved I hope better things of you, and things
that accompany ſalvation, though I thus ſpeak. And
I beſeech you, in the bowells of Chriſt Ieſus, our Saviour,
after whoſe name you be called, under whoſe
banner you profeſſe to fight, whoſe armour you profeſſe
to weare, that you will weare it in his ſervice,
and uſe it to his glory. Imploy Gods gifts in his
owne ſervice, in ſerving God in your owne perſons,
in ſetting forth his ſervice in others, in maintaining
his ſervice and ſervants, in building, repairing, and
beutifying the place of his ſervice. And here you
haue begunne well, be not weary of well doing, perfect
this worke began,A paſſage of the preacher touching the repairing of Pauls. finiſh it, imploy Gods gifts
and talents, not in ſinnes, but in Gods ſervice, &amp; then
you ſhall never want money, to go through with this
worthy worke, doe but abate dayly one diſh of your
ſuperfluous courſes, and I believe that will doe it.
            And here let every one be an actor in his owne
perſon,Every one is to uſe Gods armour perſonally. let every one put on Gods armour, and imploy
his gifts in his ſervice, for the Apoſtle ſpeakes,
ſaying, put on the armour of God, not only to ſome,



but to all the faithfull in Chriſt Ieſus. c. 1. v. 1. Wee
have all need to arme our ſelves,1. Pet. 5. v. 8. for our adverſary
the Devill,Mat. 25. Rhem. Annot on Luk. 10. 35. 2. Cor. 8. 14. 1. Cor. 9. 16. as a roaring Lion walketh about, ſeeking
whom he may devoure, without exceptiō of any. Let
not any then truſt to the oyle of others, as the fooliſh
virgins, and the ſeduced papiſts, who would make
us believe, that if our owne lampes be without oyle,
we may goe and borrow of our neighbours, to ſupply
our wants: no, no, the beſt haue little enough for
themſelves, and therefore let every one looke to himſelfe,
and arme himſelfe, ſo willeth the Apoſtle, ſaying,
have reioycing in thy ſelfe alone, and not in another.
Gal. 6. 4. Another mans meate cannot nourriſh
me, another mans garment cannot warme me, another
mans eye cannot guide me, neither can another
mans worke ſave me. I muſt worke out mine owne
ſalvation with feare and trembling, and ſo muſt every
one put on Gods armour,Philip. 2. 12. and doe Gods ſervice
not by a Deputy or Attourny but in his own perſon.
            Yea,We are to uſe Gods armour vvithout delay. and we muſt doe this preſently, without delay,
here is no time expreſſed in the text, and therefore
the time preſent is to be underſtood, according
to that legall maxime, ubi nullum tempus praeſcribitur,
praeſens intelligitur. It is to day then, and while it is
to day, that we are to heare his voice, and to put on
the armour of God.Iſa. 5 5. v. 3. Now God opens his armorie
unto you, which is the holy ſcripture, whereby you
may furniſh your ſelves, without money, and without
price.
            Behold, now is the accepted time, now is the day
of ſalvation,2. Cor. 6. 2. wherein you may provide for your
ſelves. And now likewiſe is the day of temptation,
wherein Sathan goeth about like a roaring Lion, and



ſometimes like an Angel of light, ſeeking whom he
may devoure. So that we have cauſe preſently, and inſtantly
to arme our ſelves, even while it is to day,
and this not for a day only,We are to put on Gods armour conſtantly. but every day, as long as
we live. For Sathan is reſtleſſe in his temptations againſt
them that keepe the commandements of
God, and have the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt, he will
never leave tempting them as long as they live in
the faith, and the feare, and the love of God, not
quite leave them,Luk. 4. 13. he will ſometime leave tempting
of them, for a ſeaſon, as he left tempting of Chriſt,
but he will come againe, with a freſh aſſault upon
them. He is called Beèlzebub, the maſter fly; and flyes
though they be never ſo much beaten away, yet they
will come againe and againe to the ſame place, and
ſo will Sathan being repelled, renue his temptations.
This uncleane ſpirit, when he is caſt out, will ſeeke
to reenter, and where he finds a fit houſe, a ſecure
heart,Mat. 12. 44. he will bring in ſeven Devills worſe then himſelfe.
His going away, is but to renue his aſſaults, his
flight is but to draw us out of our holds, to make uſe
of his ambuſhment againſt us. Let us not then at any
time put off the armour of God, let us not be ſecure,
as the Amalekites, having taken a great ſpoile of David,
and burned Ziglag,
               1. Sam. 30. 16. leſt we be ſuddenly ſurpriſed,
and deſtroyed, as they were: As in the fight we
have an eye unto the victory, ſo in the victory let us
have an eye to the fight againe. Let us ſtand ſtill upon
our guard, put on the armour of God, as long as you
live.Pſal. 1. Delight in the law of the Lord, and therein exerciſe
your ſelves day and night. Pray alwayes, pray,
and watch thereunto, with all perſeverance, make a
continuall uſe of all the armour, and graces of God



ſtowed upon you. This is the counſell of our great
Generall, Chriſt Ieſus, here given, by one of his
chiefe commanders, S. Paul, that we ſhould put on
this armour, alwaies, with all perſeverance. And ſo
let us doe, as obedient ſouldiours, of Ieſus Chriſt.
            And this the rather, that we may be able to ſtand 
in the evill day,The motive to uſe the ſaid meanes of Conqueſt. in the day of temptation, which is
the motive, to put on this armour, and to fight this
battell, and the laſt point. And a good motive it is,
for who would not be forward to put on armour,
and to fight in a good cauſe, if he were ſure to ouercome.
And ſo it is here, Dicendo enim, ut poſsitis reſistere,
innuit certò nos ſtaturos, ſi modo armis Dei induti,
alacriter pugnemus id
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   uſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , ad finē, ſaith Calvin
upon the place. That is, in ſaying, that ye may be able
to ſtand, he doth imply, that we ſhall ſurely, and certainly
and overcome in this battell, if being furniſhed
with Gods armour, wee fight manfully
under his banner, and that unto the end. Nil deſperandum
est Chriſto duce, we need 
                  〈◊〉
                doubt, or deſpaire
of victory, if we fight in Go
                  •
                
               
                  •
               rmour, under Chriſts
banner, and conduct, for the 
                  ••
               rd of truth, againſt
the father and favourers of lies. He that overcomes
the ſervants of God thus fighting, muſt overcome
God himſelfe,Nemo nos laedit niſi qui Deum vincit. who is the Lord of hoaſts; &amp; falſify his
word, who hath promiſed that they ſhould as ſoone
overcome and diſcomfit his ſonne, and our Saviour
Chriſt Ieſus 
                  〈◊〉
                is the Generall of the field; yea and
beate in peeces Gods owne armour,Mat. 16. 18. as weake and
unſufficient, which I believe, the gates of hell ſhall
never be able to doe. For let Satan, and all the powers
of hell, doe what they can againſt the Church



and people of God,Gen. 3. 15. they can but calcaneum conterere;
bruiſe their heele, and lame them a little, their
head they can never breake, and quite overthrow.
Though they fall, yet they ſhall not be caſt downe,
for the Lord upholdeth them with his hand, Pſal.
37. 24. Though the Dragon, and his Angels, that is,
the Devill, and his forces, fight with Michael and
his Angels, that is with Chriſt, and his members, yet
they ſhall not prevaile, Revel. 12. 7. Though Sathan
be ſtrong, yet Chriſt is ſtronger, and will binde that
ſtrong man, and ſpoile his houſe, Mat. 12. 29. he will
ſave his ſervants, and ſouldiours, fighting with his
armour, in his battell.
            I,Q: but doth not the Apoſtle ſay, of the ſervants,
and ſouldiours of Chriſt, that they are killed all day
long, &amp; counted as ſheep to the ſlaughter, Rom. 8. 36.
            True,R: and yet in all theſe things they are more
then Conquerours, through him that loveth them,
as it followeth in the next verſe of the ſame chapter.
            This may ſeeme a Paradoxe to fleſh and blood, to
conceive how they that beare away the blowes, and
are killed by their enemies, ſhould bee ſaid to overcome.
And yet, ſo it is, in all theſe things they are
Conquerours, ſaith the Apoſtle, more then Conquerours,
that is, then ordinary Conquerours, even famous,
and noble victors.
            But how doth this appeare,Q: you will ſay?
            I anſwer,R: thus, the ſword whereby we are ſaid to
overcome, is of two ſorts, ſpirituall, and materiall.
The true and faithfull ſervants of God have beene,
and many times are at this time killed, and overcome
by the materiall ſword, ſo Chriſt hath foretold,



ſaying, they ſhall kill you Ioh. 16. 2. And Revel.
11. at the 7th verſe, it is ſaid of the two witneſſes,
that is, of the faithfull preachers and profeſſors of the
truth, that when they have finiſhed their teſtimony,
the beaſt that commeth out of the bottomleſſe pit,
that is, Antichriſt with his adherents, ſhall make
warre againſt them, and kill them, that is, with the
materiall ſword: But not with the ſpirituall. With
that they overcome him, even with the breath that
commeth out of their mouthes, ſo it is ſaid there, at
the fift verſe, if any will hurt them, fire proceedeth
out of their mouthes, and devoureth their enemies,
even the fiery, and powerfull word of God, which is
able, and ſhall conſume the adverſary, 2. Theſ. 2. 8.
ſo that there is a victory on both ſides. The enemy
many times kills, and overcomes the faithfull witneſſes,
and true ſervants of God, with the materiall
ſword. And they overcome the enemy with the ſpirituall
ſword, ſlaying them in their ſoules, though
not in their bodies, for the word is the ſavour of
death unto death, in them that periſh, 2. Cor. 2. 16.
            Againe, the ſervants and ſouldiors of Chriſt, even
in all their tribulations, obtaine a noble victorie: for
what is victory?Tertul. Apol. 
               victoria eſt obtinere pro quo certas,
ſaith Tertullian, victory is to obtaine that which we
ſtrive for. And now, what is the ſtrife, betweene the
Chriſtian and the tormentor, but this? the tormentor
ſeekes to drive the Chriſtian to deny Chriſt, and
his Goſpell, the Chriſtian for all his torments confeſſeth
him the more, the tormentor fumes, and
chafes, and ſighes that he hath not his will, and therefore
is overcome. The Chriſtian rejoyceth that he



is counted worthy to ſuffer for Chriſt,Act. 5. 41. &amp; cap. 16. and is conſtant,
and therefore goes away with the victory.
The tormentors in the execution of a woman, Blandina
by name,
                  
                     ••
                  uſebius. confeſſed themſelves overcome, as Euſebius
writes in the fift booke, and firſt Chapter of
his Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory. And Chriſtians in their
torments, have gloried of their Conqueſt, over
their torments, and tormentors. Thus the Apoſtle
Paul,
               Rom. 8. 35. 37. who ſhall ſeparte us, from the love of Chriſt?
ſhall tribulation, or diſtreſſe, or perſecution, or famine,
or nakedneſſe, or peril, or ſword? Nay, in all
theſe things we are more then Conquerors, through
him that loved us. Of this Conqueſt likewiſe of
Chriſtians, in their afflictions and perſecutions, divers
others have given notable proofe, yea, and
thoſe of our owne Nation, as Glover, Farrar,
Hawkes. This laſt, was deſired by ſome godly
friends, for their confirmation, to give ſome token,
when he was in the flames, whether the paine were
tollerable, or noe: (A ſtrange time, one would thinke,
to attend upon ſignes, or friends) but ſo he did, after
his eyes were ſtarted out of his head, his fingers conſumed
with fire, and when ever one thought him
dead, and did expect the fall of his body. Loe ſuddainly
hee lifts up his ſtumps, and thrice (as famous
Conquerour) he clapps them over his head,Fox. Acts and Mon. p. 1447. in token
of victory and triumph. Thus the faithfull famouſly
conquer, when they ſeeme to bee conquered by
their enemies. Though they be caſt downe one way,
either in body, goods, or good name; yet they ſtand
another way, the beſt way; they ſtand in the faith,
they ſtand in the grace, and favour of God. They



ſtand in their ſoules, before the Son of God, though
they fall in their bodies, before the Sonnes of men.
They ſtand in great boldneſſe, before the face of ſuch
as have afflicted them,Leo ſer. 7. de jejun, 10. menſis. and made no account of their
labours, Wiſdom 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                
               
                  •
               1. formido ſublata eſt, non pugna,
as Leo ſaith, their feare is taken away, though not
their fight; their feare of being overcome, and utterly
caſt downe. So that the ſtate of the faithfull ſervants
and ſouldiours of Chriſt,Mat. 16. is full of comfort, and aſſurance,
though Sathan and all his forces ſet againſt
them, yet they ſhall not prevaile. Let the Dragon,
and his Angels doe what they can, yet Michael, and
his Angels ſhall overcome them, by the blood of the
lambe, and by the world of the teſtimony, Revel.
12. 11. 'tis not here, as in the temporall warre, there,
incertus belli exitus, 'tis uncertaine which way the
victory will goe, till the event declare it. But here in
the ſpirituall warfare, pugna, &amp; certa victoria eſt, ſaith
Tertullian, fight, and be ſure of victory. Having then
ſuch encouragement, let us put on, put on the whole
armour, all the graces of God, here mentioned. And
then, fight the good fight, and finiſh your courſe, in
wreſtling againſt fleſh and blood, againſt principalities
and powers, againſt the Rulers of the darkneſſe
of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high
places, againſt all the fiery darts, and fiery temptations
of the wicked. Doing ſo, ye ſhall not neede to
feare a ſmall fall, ye ſhall ſtand, as the Apoſtle ſaith
here. Ye ſhall ſtand, as in the grace of God here, ſo in
the glory of God hereafter, and receive that crowne
of righteouſneſſe,2. Tim. 4. 7, 8. which the Lord hath prepared for



them that love him. All which the Lord grant
us, for the alone merits of Chriſt Ieſus, to
whom with the father▪ and the holy ſpirit,
be all glory, praiſe, 
                  〈◊〉
                power,
both now, and 
                  〈◊〉
               .
AMEN.
            FINIS
            
         
      
   

