
   
      
         
            The castle of Christianitie detecting the long erring estate, asvvell of the Romaine Church, as of the Byshop of Rome: together with the defence of the catholique faith: set forth, by Lewys Euans.
            Evans, Lewis, fl. 1574.
         
         
            
               1568
            
         
         Approx. 216 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00457
            STC 10590
            ESTC S101769
            99837572
            99837572
            1904
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00457)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1904)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 343:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The castle of Christianitie detecting the long erring estate, asvvell of the Romaine Church, as of the Byshop of Rome: together with the defence of the catholique faith: set forth, by Lewys Euans.
                  Evans, Lewis, fl. 1574.
               
               [12], 72, [4] leaves   
               
                  By Henry Denham,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1568]
               
               
                  Dated at end: Seene and allowed .. 1568.
                  Quires B-I are in two settings, and the others reimposed with minor alterations. B6r line 1 begins (1) "What saith" or (2) "an herein?".
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-06
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-04
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-04
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            The Caſtle of Chriſtianitie, detecting the long erring eſtate, aſvvell of the Romaine Church, as of the Byſhop of Rome: together with the defence of the Catholique Faith: Set forth, by Lewys Euans.
            Eccle. 21.
            Be not aſhamed to confeſſe thine errour: for he that is wiſe will remember himſelfe.
            Hieron. ad Paulam. &amp;c.
            Let men firſt reade, leaſt they ſeeme, not through iudgement, but through the preſumption of hatred, to blame that, which they know not.
            Imprinted at London by Henry Denham.
         
         
            
            
               Peter .2. c.
               Deum timete, Regem honorate.
               Cic:
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
               
            
            
               
                  ¶Est piger ad poenas princeps, ad premia velox.
                  Cui
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      dolet, quoties, cogitur eſſe ferox.
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
                  Viuat deo, ſibi, reip: longum, aeternum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      valcat: regnet latiſsimè, diu, fortunatiſsimè: regat ſe, nos, &amp; regnum, long a in pace, ſplendidiſsima huius imperij regnatrix, Elizabetha: Amen.
               
            
         
         
            
            TO THE MOST gracious, and mightie Princeſſe, Elyzabeth by the grace of God, Queene of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande; defender of the faith. &amp;c.
            
               Your Maieſties moſt humble, and obedient ſubiect Lewys Euans, faythfully wiſheth here on earth long reigne, all honor, much heith, and continuall proſperitie, and in heauen euerlaſting ioye, and blyſſe eternall.
            
            
               THE INCLINAtion of Mankind (moſt graciouſe, and my ſouereigne good Ladye) is diuers, and ſtraunge: ſome are giuen to prouide for their priuate gaine and deſires: ſome for high roome, eſtimation and honor: ſome for the ſafegard of their conſciences: and ſome wholye to profite the common welth. Yea, and beſides theſe, an infinit ſort of others there are, who be diuerſly caried (a thing not vnmete to be thought vpony

ſome liuing at eaſe, and in prodigalitie: ſome wyth payne vſing their induſtrie: ſome delighting in one thing, ſome in an other: euery one following, as his diſpoſition is, the vaine marchandiſe of this brickle worlde. Hence it is, that the moſte famouſe Philoſopher Pythagoras, compared the lyfe of man vnto a marte, or fayre, as in the which ſome are buſie, ſome ydle, ſome byers, ſome ſellers, ſome lookers &amp; gazers on. But of the former ſortes, as I can not ynough commende thoſe, who are all carefull for their ſoules, ſeeking rather wyth loſſe of lyfe to winne heauen, then by reſt here and ioy, in the ende to deſerue ſorowe, and hell: ſo muſt I praiſe ſuch, which employe their continuall care, to the profite, enlargement, and conſeruatiō of the common welth. For, vnto theſe, there is (as Cicero ſaith) a preſcribed place in heauen, wherein they ſhall lyue in blyſſe for euer: vnto the others, remayneth (ſaith Chriſt) the ſaluation of theire Soules, and they

are thoſe (O moſte happie men!) that ſhall haue our ſauiour to be their aduocate and Patrone, he it is, that before his father will acknowledge, receiue, and rewarde them. Yet all are not (O right ſacred Queene) to be accounted for religious, which talke of religion, and in whoſe mouthes onely and lyppes the name of the Lorde is, all are not true confeſſours which can and doe abyde long impriſonment, all are not godlye Martyrs which ſuffer death, yea though they dye vnder colour, and in pretence of defending the true fayth. For, many there are, whome the aduerſarye hardeneth, as the Arrianes, the Anabaptistes, wyth others, many there be that dye in blindneſſe, that are ſeduced, and that defend in a maner meere heathines. Of theſe it is, that S. Augustine ſayth: Quae eſt ista dementia, vt cum male viuitis, lotronum facta faciatis, &amp; cum iure punimim, gloriam Martyrum requiratis? What madneſse is this, when you leade an euill lyfe, when you commit theft, and robberies, and when you are iuſtlye
               
               puniſhed, then to require the glorye of Martyrs? It is not (moſt benigne Souereigne) all that ſaye: we be Catholiques, wee be Chriſtians, we haue Abraham to our father, whom the Lorde our Sauiour will embrace, and defende. For, there be ſome, I woulde there were not many, who vnder the name of deuocion doe vpholde ſuperſtition, and by the colour of godlineſſe and pietie, do pamper vp blindeneſſe and Idolatrie. The proofe whereof (to the inwarde ſorowe of any chriſtiā hart) we may in theſe our dayes beholde, and ſee. For, to defende the pryde of one man, to maintayne the pompe of one prelate, (Lorde) what perſons, and how many be moued, and ſet on? how many be egged againſt Chriſt and his goſpell? howe many be ſtyrred vp againſt their Prince, their friendes, and their countrey? how many are bent againſt the lawes of God, of man, and of nature? neyther yet is this, ſo much to be maruayled at. For, vice and vertue may not agree, light muſte varye from

darkneſſe, good dealings will differ from deceyt, holyneſſe doth hate vngodlyneſſe, true pietie ſhall euer deteſt blinde Idolatrie, to be briefe, heauen is enemie vnto hell. Hence it is that all this hurlye burlie and tumults doe aryſe, hence it is that within one Realme, within one Citie, yea, and within one houſe ſuche diſſenſions doe growe, ſuche ſtryfe doth breede, ſuche hatred doth happen. And yet, this is not, I ſaye, ſtraunge, ſeing that our Sauiour hymſelfe, hath before hande tolde, and ſhewed vnto vs of the ſame. Thinke not (ſayeth Chriſt) that I am come to ſende peace into the earth. I came not to ſende peace but the ſworde. For I am come to ſet a man at variance against his father, and the daughter against hir mother, and the daughter in lawe against hir mother in lawe: and a mans foes ſhalbe they of hys owne houſholde. What playner wordes can be then theſe? ſhewe they not, as in a glaſſe, our tyme? and further, fully to expreſſe our calling, You ſhall (ſayth he) be hated of all men for my ſake. But how the

profeſſours of the Goſpell are hated▪ what whiſpering there is againſt them, what toyes are wrought, what trauaile ſome take, what tryfling newes be deuiſed, what gadding, what dreaming, what inuenting, what hoping, what ymagining there is, as I am loth to vtter, (for let God confounde all fooliſhe deuiſes) ſo am I right ſorowfull to thinke. I my ſelfe haue once drunke (before your Maieſties great clemencie I confeſſe) of the puddell of ignorancy, of the mudde of Idolatrie, of the ponde of ſuperſtition, of the lake of ſelf will, blindeneſſe, diſobedience, and obſtinacie. This did I, this doe all they, which fondlye flee this your realme, which grudge (&amp; yet know not why) at your highneſſe lawes, which (alas) reſiſt the truth, and haue (as the Apoſtle ſayth) a feruent minde to God warde, but not according vnto knowledge. O here how may your ſubiects be glad? How may your highneſſe reioyce, when vnto tranſgreſſours there is ſuch clemencie founde in your grace,

as inuiteth them thus boldly to renoūce their folly, and as offereth, as vnto the prodigall childe, moſte gladly, fauour, forgiueneſſe, and pardon? theſe things (moſt gracious Ladie) conſidered, let others eſteeme their vaine credite as they liſt: for mine owne part I proteſt before God, and your highneſſe, during life to the beſt of my power, to preferre the deuine Scriptures, before the Chaos of mans doctrine, to embrace your moſt godly proceedings, and to performe in all things towardes God, your Maieſtie and my countrie, the part and dutie of a true ſubiect. In token, &amp; pledge wherof, I haue aduentured in moſte humble wiſe, to dedicate theſe fewe leafes vnto your highneſſe moſt imperiall protection, beſeeching of God, to ſaue, keepe, and defend your Maieſtie.
            
               Your Maiesties most humble Orator
Lewys Euans.
            
         
         
            
            Romanes. 1.
            I am not aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt, for vnto all ſuch as beleue, it is the power of God vnto ſaluation.
            Epheſ. 6.
            Put on the armour of 
                  •
               od, that you maye ſtande ſtedfaſt againſt the craftie aſſaults of the deuill. For we wreſtle not agaynſt fleſhe and bloude, but againſt rule, agaynſt power, and againſt worldly rulers, of the darkneſſe of this world, agaynſt ſpirituall wickedneſſe, for heauenly things.
            1. Coloſs. 2.
            Beware leaſt any man come and ſpoile you through philoſophy, and deceitful vanitie, through the traditions of men, and ordinaunces after the worlde, and not after Chriſt.
         
         
            
            To his louing Friendes whereſoeuer, Lewys Euans wiſheth as vn
               to himſelfe.
            
            
               WHen Jweygh, that frendſhip is nothing elſe, (louing friendes) but an eſpeciall agremēt with good wil, and loue, betwene mankinde, as well in matters diuine, as humane: I do then ſomewhat doubt, whether I were best to publiſh this ſmal booke, or not.

The thing that ſeemeth to let me, is the familiaritie, friendſhip, and amitie, which hath bene and now yet is betweene vs. For I cannot but feare (ſo loth am I to loſe olde friends) leaſt by this mine alteration in iudgement, you alſo (though you haue no ſuch cauſe) will alter your loue, and ſo withdraw your good willes. In dede you your ſelues doe well know, that I was neuer chargeable vnto you, that I neuer ſought

friendſhip for gaine, and that at no time I fawned vpon any for prayſe, estimation, or profite. Onelye did I accept the faithfull harts of my friends, and I greatlye esteemed the gentle willing mindes, and affability of mine acquaintance. And this is it that maketh me the more ſorowful, whē I feare to loſe their good willes, whoſe friendſhip I delighted in, but of whoſe wealth and goodes I neyther had, nor deſired. On

the other ſide, my duetie towardes God, mine obedience due vnto the Queenes highneſſe, and the vnfeyned good will that I beare towardes my countrie, theſe do in dede now cōpell me to profeſſe the truth that I ſee, to renounce obstinacie, to knowledge the right way, and to bid defiance vnto Idolatrie. I haue therefore in this treatiſe, though not eloquently, yet faithfully brought forth, reaſon, authoritie and

Scripture, and that to defende the Catholike fayth, and to chaſe away the ſmoke of hell, the mist of Antichrist, and the falſe long mayntayned merchandiſe of Satan. I treade herein, I trust, the path of our perfite forefathers, I defende the Church, I giue a foyle to pride, I commende prayers, penance, and fasting, I cut down peruerſe hypocriſie, deceite, and blind iugling. I extoll honorable mariage and chastity, I

the cauſe, that I labour indifferently: you ſhal plainly perceiue that I ſpeake nothing against holineſſe, but that I endeuour to doe what I can, to further deuotion and godlyneſſe. Why then ſhoulde our friendſhip ceaſe? why ſhould it not (theſe thinges conſidered) increaſe? yet ſome I know there are, whoſe breaſts be ſtopped with ſuch pelting diſdaine and ignorancie, that hauing a ſounde of the Catholike

fayth in their mouthes, they neyther know what faith nor fidelitie meaneth. Some others there are, who thoughe they be worldly wiſe and learned, yet they ſo leane vnto ſelf will and estimation, that they leane not in a maner, but altogither beſides their profeſsion. Theſe be not father Adams children, they are made, as they thinke, of a finer moulde, they carie ſuch a toye in their heads (and yet know not they

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
what) whereby they ſuppoſe themſelues to paſse all other men. Alas, is it not knowen what they are? bee they not terrigeni fratres? bee they not of an earthlye moulde? is not the trade ouer earthly that they leade? yea, and to vtter them further: touching manners, be they not intollerable? and concerning religion, are not their errors in a manner palpable? they will haue no man to be like vnto them, they

thinke that in compariſon of them, there is none worthie to be looked vpon, none meete to be hearkened vnto: they adiudge their owne perſons, their owne dreames and fantaſies to excel, ſurmount, &amp; to paſſe all. Who can away with ſuch Pryde? who can ſuffer ſuche ſelfe will, ſuch diſdayne, ſuche arrogancie? But to omitte theſe: I ſhall craue of you (deare friendes) if for nothing elſe, yet for olde familiaritie,

that you will reade ouer theſe fewe leaues, before you doe infringe our amitie, and that you will reade as friends, and then iudge indifferently. And for my part this promiſe I make, though we diſagree in Religion, and that but for a time, vntill you receyue the grace that God offereth you, the light which ſhineth before you, and the Goſpell which is preached vnto you, yet in friendſhip Oreſtes ſhall find

me Pylades, Damon ſhall trie me to be Pythias, Theſeus ſhall not miſſe Perithous, Patroclus ſhall not want hys Achilles, Niſus ſhall not lacke Eurialus, Lelius ſhall be aſſured of his friende Scipio, Dauid ſhall trie me to be Ionathas. This ſeing I ſpeake from the heart, and faithfully, ſhew your good natures, performe the part of friends vnfeynedly. And thus taking you al to be my friends,

whoſe friendſhippes though I can not deſerue, yet will J during life deſire, I bid you vnfeinedly well all to fare. From London, the iiij. of Nouember.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ A plaine demonſtration of the erring estate of the Romaine Church.
            
               
                  LEWYS DVKE
               Aeneas Sylae. lib. 3. &amp;c. of Bauiere (Chriſtian Reader) is for his conſtancie, and that not wtout good cauſe, had euer ſithence in memorie. For being priſoner, and required to graunt ſome great matter, he vtterlye denying it: Albert then Marques of Brandenburgh, in whoſe handes he at that time was, threatned to deliuer him ouer into the handes of a Prince which was very cruell, and the Dukes moſt enimie. But the valiant courage of ſo noble a man coulde therewith be nothing moued, in ſo much that he thus aunſwered: aſke (ſayth he) that thingNote. at my hands now being thy priſoner, which thou ſhouldeſt demaunde of me if I were at libertie: elſe though my bodye bée in thraldome, yet ſhall my minde haue ſtill his fréedome, it ſhall ſerue and obey me, and not

thée. This is a great and a right worthy example of much conſtancie, it was the ſaying of a valiant hart, and the courage of a mind vnconquered. Hereby we be admoniſhed, that we conſent vnto no vnlawfull thing, through feare, for liuing, for libertie, or for life: but remembring the office of our bodies, what they are, and wherevnto they ſerue: that we kéepe our mindes free from all vnhoneſt ſubiection, that we doe things lawfull with conſent of conſcience and voluntarily, that we reſiſt wrong, and falſhood with fortitude and conſtancie, and that wée yéelde vnto the truth, not through force or friendſhip, but willinglye. And what canAn obiection. (will ſome ſay) this example make for your purpoſe, ſéeing that you nowe write, otherwiſe than you haue written? how maye it defende you, which now ſay otherwiſe than youhaue ſayde? or how ſhall it excuſe you, who nowe thinke otherwiſe than you haue thought? what conſtancie (will ſuch ſay) is this? howe can your alteration ſo ſoone in mynde, in iudgement, be aunſwered? you haue either (ſay they) adiudged amiſſe heretofore, or elſe you now doe: ſo that whether it be the one or the other, offended you haue,

you are to be blamed. Alas, what arrogantieThe anſwere. were it, yea, what lewdeneſſe, eyther to affirme that we haue at no time treſpaſſed, or not to acknowledge that wee haue offended, when the offence was euident, euident, I ſay, vnto others, although not (ſuch is the blindeneſſe of ſinners) vnto vs? Is there any eyther of ſuch impudencie, or elſe of ſuch puritie, that he will or maye in ſuch ſort obiect? For be it by writing, by ſome other déede, by wordes or thought, who is voydeAug. lib. 20. de ciuitate dei. of offence? what mankinde, what humaine nature (our Sauiour Chriſt only excepted) is borne frée from the bondage of ſinne? If we ſaye that we haue no ſinne, and that we1. Iohn. 1. haue not done euill, the truth is not in vs, and we deceiue our ſelues. Whereas, if we confeſſe our ſinnes, the Lorde is iuſt, he is faithful to forgiue them, he is ready to clenſe vs frō all iniquitie. What then? ſhal ſhame let vs from knowledging our faultes? ſhal fooliſh eſtimation hinder vs from confeſſing our ſinnes? ſhal our friends, ſhal the world, ſhall the deuill perſwade vs from detecting our treſpaſſes? GOD forbid. There is a ſhame, and there is a diſorder, which bringethEccleſi. 4. ſinne: that is (as Auguſtine ſayeth)Aug.
               
when one is aſhamed to renounce his wicked opinion, eyther leaſt he ſhoulde ſo ſéeme vnconſtant, or elſe appeare, and that by his owne confeſſion, of a long time to haue erred. There is alſo a ſhame that bringethEccleſi. 4. grace &amp; aduauncement, as when one knowledgeth with repentaunce his miſdéedes, when he lamenteth and confeſſeth that hée hath erred. For thereby winneth he Gods fauour againe, thereby he entreth into eſtimation with all good men and godly. Whether is it then a greater rebuke, a morePhilip. 12. ſhame, to confeſſe our ſelues guiltie with all men of ſinne, or elſe to continue with the wicked, with the reprobate therein? Cuiuſuis
               Cicero. 
               est hominis errare, nullius niſi inſipientis, perſeuerare in errore, it is the propertie of all men (ſayth Cicero) to erre: but it is the propertie onely of a foole, to perſeuere in his error.
                Had not the prodigall child returned vnto his father, acknowledging and confeſſing his fault, full miſerably in hunger and filthineſſe, had he ended his life. O how oft, and how earneſtly doe the Scriptures erhort and perſwade vs to repētance! Let vs looke well vpon our owne wayes
               Ieremie. 3. (ſaith Ieremie) and remember our ſelues,
               
               and turne againe vnto the Lord. And as for the loſſe of our eſtimation and friendes, (which is the greateſt block that men ſtumble at) if we loſe them for Chriſt his ſake, and his Goſpell, we are promiſed the receiteMarc. 10. of an hundreth folde, we ſhall doubtleſſe receiue life euerlaſting. Concerning conſtancy, is a man defending errors though ſtoutly, maintaining vntruthes though earneſtly, or ſuffering tormentes in the defence of falſhode, though (as they tearme it) pacientlye, to be accounted for one conſtant, or yet pacient? Conſtancie is (ſayth Ariſtotle)Eth. lib. 7. in things which be good and laudable. Let none therefore adiudge them to be conſtant, which eyther doe lie in priſon to maintayne blyndeneſſe, or doe ſuffer death to defende wickedneſſe. Elſe maye you tearme the Arrians, the Eutychians, the Marcioniſtes, Ebionites, and ſuch like, to be men as conſtant, pacient and vertuous as anye other. For theſe of their owne impriſonments doe ſéeme to reioyce, of their puniſhments they are thought to be glad, of their death they do triumph, &amp; for the truth it is (ſay they) that they ſuffer. What ſhall we therefore ſay of them, and not of them only, but of the like?

forſooth, Miranda est eorum duritia, neganda patientia,
               Lib. de patientia. 
               Their hardneſſe (ſayth Auguſtine) is to be maruailed at, but that they are pacient is to be denied, that they are conſtant is not to be graūted. If that then, there is no conſtancie vſed or to bee tearmed in blindneſſe, in error, in ſinne, but rather ſtiffneſſe in opinion and obſtinacie, which howe daungerous a diſeaſe it is, S. Auguſtine inAuguſtin. plaine wiſe doth teſtifie: For as conſtancie (ſayth he) ſuffereth not a man to bee depraued, ſo ſtubborneſſe ſuffereth him not to be amended. If alſo it is no inconſtancie to embrace vertue, and to eſchewe vice, to leaue the darkneſſe, and to leane vnto the light, if it be no pacience to ſuffer any puniſhment in the defence of error, dreames and deceiueable opinions, if to continue in ſinne, to be couered ſtill ouer with clowdes, with miſtes, and darkneſſe in a maner palpable, if to erre, to be deceiued, and to dote, is euill, if to be ſorte for our miſdéedes, and to call for grace, is a thing profitable for vs, commaunded of God, and demaunded by ſcriptures, if we and our forefathers, euen from our youth haue ſinned, and that vntill this daye againſt the Lorde, if (to be briefe)

it was no reproche for S. Paule, of a Phariſey to become a follower of Chriſt, of a learned lawyer at Hieruſalem to become a learner of the Goſpell, of a doctor to become a diſciple, of a perſecutour to be perſecuted: why alas, why linger we to turne vnto the Lorde? why gadde we after gloſes? why follow we not the Goſpell? Let vs, of loue vnto all I ſaye, let vs at the length nowe heare the voyce of God, it is louing, mercifull, and full of comfort, by his holye Prophete he pronounceth it: why will you die
               Ezechiel. 18 (ſayth he) O ye houſe of Iſraell? I haue no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth, turne you therefore, and you ſhall liue. Turne ſo ſhall there no ſinne doe you harme. Here notwithſtanding our treaſon, we are offered frée pardon, for the times paſt God offreth forgiueneſſe, our beginnings ſhall not be thought vpon, all our former faultes are releaſed, if nowe we amende, if our ending be good. We ſtande a number in one caſe, to ſtriue againſt our Prince is not commendable, to contende againſt our Creator, againſt Chriſt is not profitable. Fie on the worlde, fie on the deuill, they, they woulde haue vs to delight in

this vaine glorie, of them commeth all this obſtinacie. Alas, what auayleth vs in
               Hieronym. 
               name to be accounted good, if in deede we be euill? awaye with our friendes, nay away with our foes, away with all ſuch by whoſe meanes wée delight in our owne wayes. And ſhall we ſéeke the praiſe of men (with a ſorowfull hart I ſpeake it) to our owne confuſion, to hurt our brethren, to diſpleaſe God? Beware (ſayth Chriſt) leaſt
               Math. 6. 
               ye iuſtifie your ſelues before men to bee prayſed of them. For elſe you loſe the rewarde at your father his handes. If in the defending of dreames, in maintayning mans doctrine, and in ſhadowing the truth, we did ſo deale, as we might ſeeme in mans ſight to deſerue great praiſe, yet weying our owne workes to be weake, ſéeing how fond it is that we defende, howe hollowe is the grounde, and how ſoone it maye be ſhaken, what ſhoulde we abuſe learning anye longer? why ſéeke we to defend with eloquence, with wit, with ſubtiltie, the ſuburbes of iniquitie, the houſes of harlots, the ſhoppes of trumperie, the pallaice of vanitie? it is no rebuke, no ſlaunder, to turn vnto the Lord, it is for our profite to get our fathers fauor

againe, for in ſteade of Acornes, he offereth to féede vs with moſt deintie diſhes, in ſtead of cloutes and ragges, he hath for vs newe clothes. I ſay againe, let vs not be aſhamed, S. Paule began euill, yet ended he well, of a perſecutor, he became ye ſeruant of God, he profeſſed, he embraced, he preached Chriſt, he died in the defence of the faith. God graūt that all we, renouncing fooliſh dreames and light legendes, retracting fonde aſſertions, and rightlye adiudging of mens doinges, may ſo doe.
            Well, to the intent it maye euidently appeare, whether I am thus nowe mooued to write through feare, or by a frée motion, whether I am perſwaded thervnto through the deſire of gaine, of frendſhip, of fauor, or rather in hope of a rewarde at Gods hands, to be receiued with others, for the knowledging and ſetting foorth (according vnto my ſmall talent) of the truth, I thinke it not amiſſe here this much to proteſt: That were my iudgement at hande, the place of execution appointed, the maner of death determined, were I already condemned, yea, were I warned to prepare my ſelfe, yet ſhoulde feare make mee graunt no further,

than I would doe of frée minde, no torment ſhould enforce me to write againſt my faith, againſt the thing I vndoubtedly beléeued. It is true that I meaned before, as I wrote, I followed alwayes my conſcience, I hated flatterie, I loued to vtter what I thought, &amp; that fréely, I folowed as néere as nede were my former example, I woulde not graunt, nor did, to any thing being a priſoner, whervnto I would not agree, or doe not, and that willingly being at liberty. Let no man therfore reprehende mée in that I haue written before in one manner, and now in another, yea, though the one be contrarie vnto the other. For therein (the matter being rightlye weyed) is no inconſtancie, there is no euill meaning in neither, a zeale there is in the one, although not according to knowledge, and a zeale there is in the other, confirmed by authorities, by conſcience, by Scripture. Touching the offence in the one, thoughe I might remoue the fault, and laye the ſame in others, yet to haue offēded I knowledge, I confeſſe, I graunt. Neyther yet ought any to obiect it vnto my reproche, the déede was not ſo haynous, as the repentaunce for the ſame may be gracious. What ſayth Cyprian
               
herein? what ſayth S. Paule? ignoſci poteſt
               
               Cyprian. 
               ſimpliciter erranti, ſicut de ſeipſo Paulus Apoſtolus
               1. Tim. 1. 
               dicit: qui primus fui blaſphemus, &amp; perſecutor, &amp; iniurioſus, ſed miſericordiam merui, quia ignorans ſeci: He that ſinneth, not hauing an euill meaning, may be the rather forgiuen▪ 
                     
                        •…
                     s the Apoſtle S. Paule ſpeaketh of himſelf: when before I was a blaſphemer, a perſecutour, and one that did wrong, but I obtained mercy, bicauſe I did it through ignorance. No man therfore
                (that I may vſe S. Auguſtines words) except he be raſh, will finde fault and reprehend
               Aug. lib. retract▪
                
               me, bicauſe I rebuke and blame mine owne faults. What? should I be ſo arrogant, as to confeſſe that I was neuer ignorant? or ſhoulde I in well doing, bée aſhamed to do that which Auguſtine and others haue done. Let him (ſayth he) that
               Ibidem. 
               might not attaine vnto the chiefe and firſt point of wiſedome, endeuor to obtaine though the ſeconde part of modeſtie, that hauing ſpoken ſome thinges to be repented, he may be ſorie, and knowledge that ſuch things ought not to haue bene ſayde. S. Auguſtine was not aſhamed ſo to doe, and ſhoulde I? if all the Prophetes,

if all the Apoſtles, if all the Doctors haue ſo done, were it not a thing inſolent, yea, a thing impudent for vs ſo not to doe? Let others eſtéeme their credite as they ſée cauſe, I will ſaye what I thinke, by the meanes of man I will neuer bee ſmothered in ignorancie, I will fréelye ſpeake my conſcience, no terror, no threatnings, no death ſhal let me. Were I encloſed vp with Pantaleon, or ſhot into ye hart with Praxaſpis ſonne, yet dreames ſhall be dreames, truth ſhall be truth, a ſpade ſhall be a ſpade, I can giue it none other name. I neuer laboured for gaine, I neuer looked for glorie, what I did, was done fréely, it was and it is done of a good meaning, and voluntarily. For mine owne part, I beare euill will to none, I wiſh well to all, and that faithfully, vnfeynedly. Though I think otherwiſe than they doe, if I thinke the truth, and if good cauſes doe moue me therevnto, why ſhoulde anye blame mée? why ſhoulde they rebuke him, which yeeldeth vnto truth, and giueth place to reaſon, authorities, and holye ſcripture? But what was the cauſe and how came toAn obiection▪
                paſſe (wil ſome ſay) this ſodeine conuerſion, obiections I know, will be deuiſed, flowts

will be framed, ieſtes, &amp; toyes (for ydle walkers, idle dreamers, there are inough) will be inuented. The conuerſion, ſir, is not ſo ſodain,An anſwere. as of ſuch, who ſay Maſſe in ye one day, &amp; ſubſcribe to the contrary, in the other. And yet I ſpeake it not to reprehend them, for S. Paule, I knowe, was conuerted in a moment,Act. 9. c. ſodainelye going by the way to Damaſco. Whether they be likewiſe cōuerted in déede, or no, betwene God, and them I leaue it, I will be no iudge. But what I coulde hereof ſaye, and what I knowe, for ſome cauſes I will omitte. What made me to alter my mynd, and how it happened, you ſhall briefely heare. Heare me then, I pray you, without parciallitie. Hauing alwayes from my childhood deteſted this way, which to doe well, we muſt tearme the reformation, and cleanſing of Chriſtianitye, from vnprofitable cloddes, from wéedes and bryars, wherewith the houſe of God was in a maner ouergrowne, hauing oft heare in talke (as to many can witneſſe) reſiſted the ſame, hauing paſſed ouer the Seas, moued with a vayne zeale, to chunne it, and hauing at the length by tranſlations, &amp; toyes wrytten againſt it, I returned priuilie (as

occaſion ſerued me) into Englande againe of that minde to depart hence as ſoone, and as ſecretly as I coulde. In the meane tyme I was aprehended, and ſo committed to priſon. Being then there, and looking for ſome extreme kinde of dealing, which yet I ſo little feared, as were the puniſhment neuer ſo harde, were it neuer ſo great, I was contented, yea, verye willing felt I my ſelfe to abide it. But in ſteade of extremity, (it is beſt to confeſſe the troth) I founde much clemencie, I founde in thoſe, whome before I lytle regarded, great wiſedome, good learning, much grauitie. Which thing, as I did at the firſt in a maner vnwillinglie (ſo rooted was the diſeaſe) conſider, ſo in time, how I know not, I began ſomewhat better to lyke it. So that oftentimes weying the iudgement of the learned men that talked with mée, to be ſhort, waying all, and indifferentlye wyth my ſelfe, I was diuerſelye minded, a maruaile it was, that one mynde, in one bodie ſhoulde be ſo wauering, my thought was mooued, my hart was in a maner amazed, it made me to thinke vpon the eſtate of Auguſtine, who forſaking the Manichees ſtoodLi. confeſ. 6. at a ſtay, ſomewhat doubting which way to

take. Here what ſhoulde I doe? I deſired méekelie that God woulde ſtrength me in the true fayth, that he woulde vouchſafe of his great mercie to open the knowledge vnto me of the right way. And what folowed? anone I was minded to examine better, and with good héede to conſider (which thing hithervnto I might not away with) the writings of ſuch as before, I miſlyked, deteſted, abhorred. Mée thought alſo that in reading of mans workes (the Scripture onely excepted) men might by good reaſon, vſe the gift that God gaue them, their diſcretion, &amp; their owne iudgement, ſpecially, in things diſſonant from holy ſcripture. Yea, were he Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Hierome, or any other, were he of neuer ſo great antiquitie, neuer ſo learned, had he written neuer ſo great volumes, yet lawfull I ſawe it was, that we might ſay, as Papias the ſcholer of S. Iohn
               Eccl. hist▪ lib. 3. the Euangeliſt did ſay: Non multa dicentibus, ſed vera tradentibus auſcultandum est: we muſt hearken, and obey thoſe, which ſet forth the truth, &amp; not that ſay or write much.
                Wherevnto S. Auguſtine himſelfe did alſo in theſe wordes, much further me: Neyther
               Fortun. Ep. 
               ſhoulde we ſo eſteeme the writinges
               
               of men, although they bee Catholique, and good, as the Canonicall ſcriptures, and as though it were not lawfull for vs, (ſauing the reuerence due vnto ſuch) to reproue ſome things in their writinges, and to refuſe it, if we fortune to fynde that they haue thought otherwyſe than the truth doeth allowe, and the ſame through the deuine helpe, beeing better vnderſtanded by other, or by vs. Againe concerning the reading of bookes, or talke to be had with the contrarie ſide, for all is one: Ye coulde (ſayeth he) at no time allowe anye
               Aug. exhort. 
               thing in vs, your Byſhoppes with whome wee talked, would neuer peaceablye reaſon with vs, flying as it were to talke, with ſinners. Who can away wyth this pride? as though the Apoſtle Saint Paule talked not with ſinners, yea, and wyth men paſſing euill. Touching alſo the wryting and decrées of any Byſhop, yea the Byſhop of Rome is not here excepted, thus he ſayth: We may argue, and doubt
               Lib. 2. de vnico baptiſme. 
               of the writings of any byſhop whoſoeuer he be: but we may not ſo doe of the holy ſcripture. By any thing therefore hither-vnto done, (iudge gentle reader indifferentlie)

may I for alteracion in minde, of rebuke and reproch, be worthily thought guiltie? I follow not mine owne phantaſie, I wauer not with the wynde, the waight of reaſon, of authoritie doth moue me. So it followeth that when I was ridde from that ſuperſtitious ſcrupuloſitie, wherein with others I was before ouer faſt bounde, when I felt my ſelfe at liberty to read with iudgement, and to iudge the things I read with the holy ſcriptures, the very touchſtone of truth, whē I perceyued it lawfull to pervſe ouer the doings of eyther ſide: then felt I loe my minde much eaſed, and my conſcience from that lumpiſh burthen, wherewith it was before much cumbred, nowe in a maner releaſed: Then (ſo can the right hande of the moſt higheſt chaunge all) felt I my ſtudie toPſal. 77. proſper, the blacke cloudes to vaniſh away, and the light of the bright Sunne to ſhine and appeare. I will not ſpeake much of fond gloſes, howe vnſauerie they began nowe to ſeme, how the one contraried the other, how few or none went faithfullye to worke. Of fables, of dreames, of ſpirites, and ſpitefull deuiſes, of iugling miracles, of feyned fiers, of peruerſe prophecies, of chriſtianitie, and

godlineſſe, moſt vngodly prophaned, what ſhould I ſay? truely if we deale indifferently, hauing a regard vnto the blyndneſſe that raigned, and vnto the enormities wherwith the world was ouerwhelmed, we may well ſaye, non est veritas, non est miſericordia, non est
               Oſee. 
               ſcientia dei in terra, there is no truth, there is no mercye, there is none that knoweth God vpon earth.
                For was there any truth when toyes, when ſtones, when ſtickes, when earth, when aſhes were adoured? where was mercy when threatnings, when force, and when tyrannie preuayled? who knew God, when Gods worde was obſcured, and God himſelfe ſcarcelye remembred, when blockes were bleſſed, when mothes, and wormes, when ruſt and canker was reuerenced? Wo vnto him that ſayth vnto aAbac. 2. péece of wood, ariſe: &amp; vnto a dumbe ſtone, ſtande vp: For what inſtruction can ſuch giue? go we then vnto the former time, let truth be ſayde, what finde we there? ſuperſtition, Idolatrie, murther, diſobedience, pride, blindneſſe, deceit, enuye, hate, whoredome, and a verye heape of iniquitie. This I ſpeake, not of heate, but out of hiſtories. I report me alſo to the indifferent conſciences

of good people, whether in the ſeruing of God there was any abuſe, yea, whether any thing was almoſt in his right vſe. I report me to the whole worlde, whether the church of Chriſt hath bene of a long time aſſaulted with diuerſe and great offences, or no: whether ſhe hath bene, and that almoſt from the beginning, beſieged with auarice, hypocriſie, with luſt, and intollerable impietie, to ye loſſe, alas, of many a chriſten ſoule or no. Some there were alwaies, though in number fewe, and though their workes were, throughe the malicious pollicies of the aduerſaries, ſpoyled, burnt, and defaced, that ſpake and wrote againſt wickedneſſe, againſt ſinne, againſt abuſes, and againſt (if I may vſe the tearme honeſtly) the beaſtlye life of the Clergie, all ought to haue ſo done, if any therefore nowe doe it, ſhoulde he be miſliked? ought he to be reprehendeded? is it reaſon that with Phocion he feele ſo much iniurie? The Goſpell was preached here in Englande, euen when the foggie myſt of ydolatrie was thickeſt, which thing thoughe it appéere not ſo playne vnto vs, why ſhould we maruaile? for were not the bookes by the aduerſaries ſpoyled? were not

tranſlations forbidden? incurred not he the penaltie of the greateſt excommunication,Conſt. prou. Oxon. who tranſlated anye booke, chapiter, or ſentence of the holye ſcripture into the engliſhe tongue? and yet for all their burnings, ſpoilings, forbiddings, and excommunicating, we haue teſtimonies inough, that the truth was here preached, that there were preachers that ſpake againſt the lewdneſſe of the Cleargie, againſt the Pope, and other abuſes, they treated de fide, de ſacramentis eccleſiae,
               Statut. Henrici. 4. 
               &amp; de authoritate eiuſdem, of the faith, of the ſacraments of the Chuch, and of the authoritie of the ſame.
                Yea, with ſuch a zeale preached they then, that though they were excommunicated, yet ceaſſed they not, they trauailed from one Dioceſſe vnto another, vntil at length they were hindered and letted (ſo were the Apoſtles of Chriſt) by the extremitie and rigour of mans lawes. InCyprian. &amp;c. elder time alſo we muſt graunt, there were learned fathers who bewailed much the iniquitie of their times, and from the hart lamented the eſtate of the Prieſtes, ſaying: that there was no good religion, no holynes, no faith, no charitie amongſt them. This was a good while agone, it was aboue a

thouſand yeres paſt, the time was then wicked, let vs therefore well weigh what wée receiue at their handes. But afterwardes what followed? forſooth iniquitie ſtill getting the vpper hand, ſinne ouerflowing the whole worlde, euery one followed his owne way, (of the Prelacie I ſpeake) fornication being defended, vices maintained, no impietie in a maner rebuked, the Religion was nothing regarded. Yea, Quidam ſacerdotes
               Io. Peckham Cant. Archiep. 
               Baal potius quam domini ſaluatoris. &amp;c. occidentes animas Christi ſanguine redemptas, euertentes eccleſiasticam diſciplinam: there were of the prieſts
                (O heauen! O earth!) the prieſts rather of Baal than of our ſauiour. &amp;c. murthering the ſoules redemed with the bloud of Chriſt, abuſing and ouerthrowing the diſcipline of the Church. AndGreg. Maur Aug. what ſayth Gregorie of his time? humilium ſumus doctores, ſuperbiae duces, we be the teachers of them that are humble, but we our ſelues are the ringleaders of pride. Sacerdotes
               Ibidem. 
               nominamur, non ſumus, wee are called prieſtes
                (ſayth he) but we are not. WoeGregorie was choſen. Anno domini▪ 591. be therfore vnto ſuch prieſts, through whoſe peruerſe behauiour, and vile licencious life, the Goſpell of Chriſt hath bene ſo hindered,

the ſenſe of holy ſcripture ſo peruerted. Culpa
               Gregor. 
               vestra hostium gladios exacuit, your haynous crime hath ſharpened the ſwordes of the aduerſaries,
                your lewdneſſe hath allured the horrible Turkes to take ſuch enterprices, to inuade Chriſtendome, to conquere the lande, to ſlea the innocents, and to bring into moſte damnable ſubiection, our poore brethren, ſometimes the ſeruantes of Chriſt. What were your prayers? abhominable. One of your owne Biſhops ſo tearmeth them. Quae execrationes potius dicerentur.
               Archiep. Cant. Io. Peckham. You name them the celebrations of Maſſes, but they ought rather (ſayeth he) to be called curſings, a taking and abandoning of your ſelues to the deuill. Doe they then amiſſe (al things, chriſtian reader, conſidered) which labour to purge Chriſtendome from ſo deadlye an infection and poyſon? what? ſhall the reprehenders of vices therfore be called vicious? ſhall ſuch as ſéeke with true doctrine, with their owne death to doe good vnto their countrie, be tearmed ſpoilers of the faith, deſpiſers of the church? ſhall good thinges bée named euill? is the world ſo euill? Peccatores procul dubio tacendo
               Gregor. Venantio. &amp;c. 
               pastor occidit, the ſhepehearde without
               
               
               doubt by holding his peace, murthereth ſinners. Woulde you then haue the Preachers nowe, the biſhops to hold their peace, to ſée ſinne, to ſuffer it, to murther ſoules? the Sée they ſawe the biſhop of Rome his houſe, the verye pallace to peruert ſoules, and ſhall they not once ſaye agaynſt it? ſhall not we, ſhall not Bernarde bewrayeDe conſid. ad Eug. the iniquitie thereof? thy Court, thy pallace (ſayth he) receyueth in good men, but (O lamentable thing!) it maketh none: naughty perſons (O horrible houſe!) thriue there: and the good (O vngodlye palace!) appayre and decaye. Doth it not now by this appeare, vnto any heart not ouer parciall, how profitable, how neceſſarie it is, that wée examine our wayes, that wée call for grace, that we returne vnto ye Lord? I commit my credite into the handes of any honeſt conſcience, let him iudge whether I am in fault bicauſe I flie from ſo foule a profeſſion, from ſo vnperfite a teaching. But is this all? No, you ſhall yet ſée the Goſpell of Chriſt better defended, the Citie of God ſtronglier fortified, you ſhall ſée Rome to be Rome, the vſurped power eaſilye put downe, the ſmoke of Idolatrie let out, and

the miniſters there of miſrule, of miſchiefe, eyther by times to repent, or to ſuſtaine euerlaſting reproch. If they henceforth proue good, their former vngodlyneſſe ſhall not hurt them, if they waxe ſorie for their offences, the truth will not ſhame them. I craue of thē that they will beare with me, though I blot out their paintinges, and bewraye their bugges, their deceiueable Lanternes, their Lemures, with all their abuſes: and that bicauſe the law of nature, of good men, and of God is againſt them. Neither will I write ſo vehemently as the eſtate of the time preſent would require. For the right hande of God is large, he maye turne the great Turke, and he maye conuert Cane of Cathay, he will (it is not to be doubted) deliuer our friendes here out of blindeneſſe. So that it were better to ſée ſome blames déepely buried, than eyther in any thing to diſcredite thoſe, whom God maye yet call, or then to trouble chriſtian eares with the reherſall of ſome offences, peraduenture ouer heynous. I will therefore reaſonably, friendly, charitably, and with modeſtie proceede.
            Let vs then begin with the verie bulwarkSupremacy. and ſtrongeſt holde of the contrarie ſide,

which if wée accordingly doe batter downe, yéelde then they muſt, it is then for them to knowledge their obſtinacie, the reſt they can in no wiſe defende. And what is their chiefeſt fortreſſe? the vſurped title of a ſupreme head, their feyned Popedome, their falſe primacie. Under this banner, a ſinful man beareth in hand, that he may curſe, bleſſe, abandone the ſoules of men to the deuill, vnder this title he taketh vpon him to rule in hell, to raigne in heauen, to cōmaund the whole world, and to be king ouer all. Can man do any more to imitate Antichriſt than this? but (to omit ſuche intollerable pryde and blaſphemie) ſhall wée indifferentlye examine whether the biſhop of Rome (for this is the queſtion) hath any authoritie by reaſon, by good authoritie, by ſcripture ſo to do? In dede many he hath well ſéene in the Latine, Gréeke, and Hebrue, that holde with him: but howe euill ſuch are ſéene in that, which is the ende of good ſtudies, that is in the knowledge of GOD, euerye good man muſt graunt. Are they then vtterlye ignorant? No. For they can make ſmoke where no fier is, in darke places they can proue moſt light, in light they will prooue darkeneſſe,

in deceit truth, in diueliſh men they can make good meaning, and in good men moſt ſinne. They can proue the ſnow to be blacke, the fire to be colde, the blacke cole to be white, the Wheate to be Rie, the Rie to be Ruſhes, ſuch toyes they can doe, declare they not themſelues to be learned? If to defende harlottes, who can doe it fyner? if to maintaine the ſlewes, who kéepeth a more ſturre? if to fauor fornication, they haue no fellowes. Good Orators (I warrant you) they are. But in the defence of the Pope, what is their reaſons? Marrie (ſay they) as in a Citie ought to bee one chiefe Mayor or Magiſtrate, as in a ſhippe ought to bée one Maiſter, as ouer a houſhold ought to be one huſbande, and as in a Realme ought to be one ruler or Prince: ſo in the Church amongſt Chriſtians ought to be (ſaye they) one head Uicar, one Uicegerent or Regent vnder Chriſt. Conſider (gentle Reader) indifferently the ſtrength of the example, wey it with thine owne conſcience vprightly. Is it reaſon bicauſe a Prince, without the aſſiſtance vnder God of others, as of his counſaylers and officers, can not rule well and orderlye his realme, that therefore Chriſt,

without the ayde and helpe of man, may not guide and rightly order his Church? ſhall Gods infinite power bée ſo pinched, and brought into that ſtraightneſſe, as to bee compared with the miſerable eſtate and impotencie of man? ſhall the argument bée good, bicauſe man maye not, therefore God can not? What ſhoulde we ſpeake of theSalomon. mutabilitie of mans hart, or elſe of the ſtedfaſtneſſe of the Lords counſell? Fie vppon that man, and fie vpon that ſpirituall man, which woulde chalenge to rule the whole earth, and that woulde abuſe the name, authoritie and power of GOD, to maintaine ſuch pride. Fie vpon that tyrannicall tryple crowne, chaire, diademe, ſcepter, and the carying of vpon mens ſhoulders. Fie in déede (with dolor of hart I ſpeake) vpon all ſuch popiſh pompe and pompeous poperie. If I be earneſt, beare with me, the cauſe requireth it. What reaſon is it, as though GOD were vtterly abſent, as though he could not be euery where preſent, for a ſinfull man to vſurp the maiſtrie, and ſuch a ſupreme maiſtrie ouer all, ouer Princes, Kinges, and Emperors? but we ſhall ſée, euen with our eyes this pride ſoone to decaye. For the
               1. Pet. 4.
               
               prowde is reſiſted of GOD, and to the humble he graunteth his grace. He putteth
               Luc. 1. 
               downe the mighty from their ſeats, and exalteth them of low degree. Whoſoeuer
               Luc. 14. 
               exalteth himſelfe ſhalbe brought lowe. The biſhop of Rome exalteth himſelfe: what then followeth? therfore he muſt nedes be brought low. And that hée doth exalt himſelfe, you ſhall ſée that moſt euidentlye proued. Chriſt woulde not haue neither his Apoſtles nor diſciples to be called kings or Lords. For know ye not (ſayth he) that
               Marc. 10. 
               they which ſeeme to beare rule among the Gentiles, doe raigne as Lordes ouer them, and they which bee great among them, exerciſe authoritie ouer them: So ſhall it not be among you. &amp;c. If that then the biſhop of Rome doth contrarie vnto this, contrarie vnto Chriſt, contrarie vnto the Apoſtles, doth he not exalt himſelfe? he doth not onely chalenge to be ſupreme in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, but alſo to haue royaltie ouer the Chriſten people. He will bée called Lorde of Lordes, King of Kings, yea, the Pope hath (ſaith his defender) a kingly power ouer his ſubiectes, euen in temporall things. Where is Iames and Iohn
               
the ſonnes of Zebede? where is your mother? why come you not and craue to ſit the one on the right hand of the Pope, the other on the left, in his glorie? good God that the eyes of Chriſten people were once opened, that they might equally diſcerne, what it is for one and the ſelfe ſame man to be called the ſeruaunt (O hypocriſie!) of the ſeruants of God, and contrarie vnto that, to vſe a temporall power, a kinglye maieſtie ouer all, to haue his ſworde, his ſcepter, to haue his guilt ſturrops (fye) to put in his holy féete, and in all defyance of humilitie, to haue kings and Emperors to be his footemen. What reaſon is this? Pride (ſayeth Ambroſe) hath cauſed angels to become
               Ambroſe▪
                
               deuils. Pride (ſayeth all the worlde) hath cauſed the Byſhop of Rome to be called Pope, and of a Pope to procéede further in all the degrées of Antichriſt. Let neither Cardinall, Councell, nor Doctor ſay: who is like vnto the Pope? who is like vnto the
               Apoc. 13. 
               beaſt? who is able to warre with him? For as ſure as God liueth, Babilon that great Citie muſt fall, the walles of Hieruſalem will be raiſed vp, falſhoode muſt flie, truth will ouercome, darkneſſe muſt down,

the light beginneth to ſhine, the deuil maugre his head, muſt yeeld, God will haue the field. Let vs therfore neuer abuſe eloquence to defende pryde, to maintaine the Pope. For who toucheth Pitch ſhall bee filed
               Eccleſi. 13. 
               withall: and he that will communicate with the prowde, ſhall cloth himſelfe with pride. Neuer felt our cuntriemen, neuer felt learned men greater reprofe, than when by ſhewe of ſkill they haue ſought to defende ſhadowes, to defende dreames, and to defende the filthie abhominable abuſes of Rome. Oh it was not without good cauſe, that the Chriſtian Poet then thus ſpake of Rome, of the Prelacy, I ſay, vnder ye name of the Citie.
            
               Si quid Roma dabit, nugas dabit, accipit aurum,
               Mantuan. 
               Verba dat, heu Romae nunc ſola pecunia regnat. If we haue anye thing from Rome, they be trifles. It receyueth our gold, and deceiueth vs. Alas onely mony nowe there raigneth.
                And what is further ſayd thereof? little praiſe I warraunt you, and leſſe it deſerueth.
            
               Quo magis appropias, tanto magis omnia ſordent.
               Ibidem. 
               The neerer you come to Rome the worſe you will like it, the more you loke on it,
               
               the filthier it ſhall appeere. What ſhould I ſpeake of their briberie, ambicion, poyſoning, fornication, and euil liuing? lothſome is the life if all were diſcloſed of their chiefe paſtor, the thing can not bée denyed, his déedes be deteſtable. Shall we graunt then by reaſon, ſhall we be ſo vnreaſonable, that ſuch a monſter ſhould be a maiſter, and that ouer Gods annointed, ouer Kinges andProu. 20. 1. Pet▪ 2. 1. Tim. 2. 1. Reg. 12. Princes? how reuerently doth the ſcripture ſpeake of Emperours and rulers? how vnreuerentlye doth the biſhop of Rome abuſe and abaſe them? and yet ſhall we followe the Pope? Papam imitari debemus: ſuch is the24. q. 1. haec eſt fides. &amp;c &amp;. 35. q. 9. veniam. reaſon that they vſe. Gregorie in reprouing the pride of the Biſhop of Conſtantinople, vſeth this reaſon. There were (ſayth he) of the Biſhops of Conſtantinople, ſome that were great heretikes, therefore if the biſhop there ſhould be called the vniuerſall Patriarch, the eſtate of Chriſtes Church ſhoulde decaye. Here if this reaſon be good, we maye frame the like, if it be not, it is Gregorie and not I that framed it. There were of the Biſhops of Rome, ſome which were great heretikes and verie lewde men, therefore if the Biſhop there ſhould be the chiefe, then

the eſtate of Chriſt his Church ſhoulde decaye. This is the Popes owne reaſon, let him ſée vnto it. Aſke of them what Anaſtaſius, Siſinnius, and Iohn the twelfth of that name were. They were Popes of Rome, the one was an heretike, the ſeconde was a wicked man, and the thirde was a monſter and a very Epicure. Liberius likewiſe was an horible heretike, an Arrian, &amp; yet B. of Rome. I report of them as I finde it in the bookes written by the Popes owne friends. Thus for my parte, touching reaſon, they finde me ſo reaſonable, that I anſwere, and yet vſe their owne reaſon.
            But ſhall we nowe ſée what authoritie they haue, for reaſon (wée perceyue) they haue none, and who the chiefeſt champions be that defende this primacie? you may not thinke but that there are many of them, yet what they are, that is to be conſidered. They be no Apoſtles, nor yet diſciples of Chriſt, they bée the Popes of Rome themſelues, their Cardinals, their Biſhops, their Doctors, their dearlings, their hirelings, they be thoſe whoſe necks were vnder the yoke, either therevnto allured through gifts, faire promiſes and flatterie, or forced throughe

feare, or through ouermuch ſimplicitie blinded and ſeduced, who ſo drewe forth and vphelde the pompous chariot of iniquitie. And that I ſée me not to vtter vntruth, that the thing may appeare, they were Stephanus, Iulius, Pelagius, Symmachus, with ſuch like, all being biſhops of the Sée of Rome. The caſe in controuerſie is their owne, they maye not bee their owne iudges, in that their owne lawe is againſt them. For I am ſure (indifferent Reader) that in a controuerſie betweene thée &amp; an other, thou wouldeſt not willingly be tried by the defendant thine aduerſarie. And could the Pope except he were his owne iudge, maintaine his primacie? No. And therefore being better aduiſed, they make this law, that the Biſhop of Rome may iudge all, but he may be adiudged of none. And who made it? Innocētius, Antherius, Gelaſius. And what were they? Biſhops of Rome. If therefore they prouided for their owne preferment, coulde you blame them? Naye, you may in no wiſe blame them, though they carie (theſe béeEx dictis Bonifaci
                     •
                  . their owne wordes) an innumerable ſort of people with them by heaps into hell. And why? bicauſe they doe iudge al, but
               Ibidem.
               
               none maye iudge them. I vſe (Chriſten reader) no deceit, they be their owne words, wey thē with indifferencie, I aſke no more, it ſhall doe thée good ſo to doe. Doubtleſſe it is both a pleaſure, and alſo a great griefe vnto him that hath eies and vnderſtanding, to ſée their lawes, to beholde their authorities: a pleaſure it is, for that he ſeeth their fonde iuglinges, being himſelfe free from their filthie bondage and trumperie: A great griefe it is, to ſee men, and thoſe men which be our brethren, and are called Chriſtians, to be ſo much giuen to blindeneſſe, addicted to follye, and ſo further ſuch ſubiectes vnto the ſeruitude of ſo intollerable a wickedneſſe. Wel conſider we more of their lawes, and let vs conſider them indifferentlye. For at the firſt beginning of their pontificall prowde kingdome, they thought good to ordeine lawes, that ſo vnto vs at this time, their aunſwere for lacke of reaſon and ſcripture, might yet be: Nos legem habemus. &amp;c. We haue a law▪ and by this law we defend our doings and fréedome, by this we rule, by this we raign. And what be their lawes? ouer vile, to abhominable, I warrant you. They be theſe. The Pope be he neuer ſo
               Ex decret.
               
               euill, yet muſt you coniecture and gheſſe him to be good. Though we know him to be lewd, yet lo, we muſt gheſſe that he is not ſo. O execrable blindneſſe! The Pope graū
                  teth
               Ibidem. 
               the authoritie of the ſword, that is, of a Princely gouernement. Is not this a paſſing pride? The Pope is not only in
               Ibidem. 
               ſpirituall cauſes the chiefe, but alſo in temporall. O mightie ioly Monarch! The
               Ibidem. 
               Pope hath all lawes (O hollow place, and not holie!) conteyned within his breaſt. No man maye hate him. Take héede ofIbidem. that, you may not miſlike him. He may diſpenſe
               Ibidem. 
               in things contrarie vnto the Apoſtles. No maruaile, for that is the right propertie of Antichriſt. All queſtions concerning
               Ibidem. 
               faith, he muſt determine. And muſt he be the very touchſtone? ſhall holye ſcripture be ſo excluded? His mynde is to bee
               Ibidem. 
               preferred before all the biſhops. In déede that is the next waye to reigne. Of manſlaughter,
               Ibidem. 
               or adulterie, he may in no wiſe be accuſed. No, though he be neuer ſuch a whoremonger, though he murther neuer ſo many. Yea, and that we ſhould go into hell in déede, there to beare him companie, their law is, that we muſt follow him, we muſt

kill, if he kill, we muſt do as he doth. Et ſperent te tartararegem? Muſt wée ſerue him in hell? He may not looke for Rhadamanthus place, he is no ſuch Executor of iuſtice. Let him take heede, that he come not vnder Tiſiphones handes. With the reſt of their lawes, what ſhoulde I trouble thée? they are, if it maye be, than theſe, a great deale worſe. I will not much ſcan vppon their impietie, there is no perſon that can reade (the thing vprightlye conſidered) but will, and may regarde them accordingly. Onely thus much I ſay, if pride, if couetouſneſſe, if deſire alone, and onelye to raigne, hath bene the grounde, and was the verie cauſe, why ſuch lewd lawes were made, if Sathan was the ſubtile ſecretary therin, why trouble we our ſelues? why torment we our conſciences? why care we ought for them? we ſee his authoritie, let his pardons alone, haue not to doe with his diſpenſations. Papa quando
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   nimium papaliter dispenſat: The Pope
                (thusBarthol. Brixienſis. ſaieth his owne Lawyer) doth ſometimes too popiſhly diſpenſe. What authorities the biſhop of Rome hath, ſpecially to maintain his eſtate you haue heard: Now what authorities be againſt him, let his friendes

be contented to heare. I will be briefe, I wil not be partiall. To begin I néede not with the primitiue eſtate of Chriſt his Churche, wherein we can finde no ſuch primacie, no ſuperiority amongſt the Apoſtles, who then all hauing receyued the holye ghoſt alike did preache the Goſpell, and ſo faithfully did ſet forth the truth, without pride, without chalence of the higheſt roome, or once mention of any ſupreme heade to be had or exerciſed among them. Let the Popes owne authorities preuayle, let his euidences be ſeene, are not the wordes thereof theſe? Although Peter, Iames, and Iohn were preferred byClomens. our Sauiour in a maner aboue the reſt, yet claymed not they any glorie, or title of primacie: and ſhal then the Pope claime that, which Peter neyther would nor could not? In the time firſt of Cyprian we reade, that certaine lewde Prieſts being worthily condemned by the Biſhops of Aphrica, ranne to Rome, that by the Biſhop there, they might haue the matter farther diſcuſſed. Ciprian findeth great fault with the hearing of them, and writeth thereof vnto Lucius then biſhop of Rome, ſaying that vnto euery biſhop a portion of Chriſtes flock is committed,

who ſhall render accordingly an account for the ſame, and that therefore theſe men ought to be tried, as in dede they were in Aphrica, and that by and vnder their owne biſhops: he writeth likewiſe at large concerning the ſame, and much reprehending it vnto Cornelius. Now what authoritie, or what grounde of ſupremacie, a fewe diſobedient and conuict Prieſtes coulde purchaſe vnto the Sée of Rome, iudging vprightly, I ſée not. But if they be either ſ ignorant, or ſ arrogant, as to frame vppon theſe runnagates, their right, and vſurped title, let them then, and wyth good indifferencie conſider, how Dioſcorus their Pope of Rome being excommunicated, and yet touching no matter of faith, did appeale (for ſo they thēſelues name him) vnto the Pope, the Patriarch of Conſtantinople. Here we finde another Pope, and vnto whome their Pope of Rome hath appealed. Touching the time of Conſtantine, it was he, &amp; not Silueſter, it was the Emperour, and not the biſhop of Rome, that made lawes in defence of the Chriſtians, it was the Emperor that condemned the writings of Arrius, it was he that called from baniſhment

               Porphyrius, and it was onely he that then made an edict againſt heretikes. But if they will haue it that Conſtantine did ordeine ye biſhop of Rome to be the chiefe, then let them goe forward in their hiſtorie, wherein they ſhall finde, how at that time this voyce was hearde, hodie venenum eccleſiae est immiſſum, nowe doth poyſon enter into the Church.
                And that this voyce was true, you ſhall well proue, if you examine throughlye the whole doings of Silueſters ſucceſſours. For (O Lord) what crueltie was amongſt them! what ambition! what ſymonie! what diſobedience! what hereſie was amongſt them! Come wée then vnto the Emperour Iuſtinianus his time. For concerning Marcellus and Anacletus, if the decrées in their names ſet forth, be theirs, (as in déede they ſeme not to be) they were biſhops of Rome, and therefore is their authoritie contrarie vnto the ſcripture, in aduauncing themſelues, nothing worthie of anye reaſonable man, or of anye indifferent Chriſtian to bée eſtéemen. And before we ſpeake of Iuſtinianus, you muſt vnderſtande that there were in his time, and vnder him, among others, fiue eſpeciall Cities, that is Rome in Italy,
               
               Conſtātinople in Thrace, Alexandria in Aegipt, Antioch in Siria, &amp; Hieruſalem in Iudaea▪
                Of theſe fiue, there were fiue chiefe fathers or Patriarches, euery one hauing a 
                  〈◊〉
                and a ſeuerall authoritie in cauſes ſpiritual, ſuch I meane, as Archbiſhops ſhould haue, euery one within his owne and proper Prouince. Neither did anye one Patriarch either intermedle with the iuriſdiction of the other, or clayme a Primacie the one aboue the other. They were ſeuerall Cities, ſeuerall Prouinces, ſeueral Patriarches, ſeuerall in authority, &amp; equall in dignity. And that this is moſt true, the wordes of Iuſtinian himſelfe ſhall teſtifie, who hauing next vnder Chriſt, a kinde of ſupreme authoritie, made certaine Eccleſiaſticall lawes to gouerne and rule them all. So that ſome lawes being made concerning the Clergie, for the due execution of the ſame, he ſendeth his eſpeciall commaundement vnto the ſayd fiue Patriarches in theſe wordes: Iubemus igitur beatiſsimos Archiepiſcopos, &amp; patriarchas,
               Imperator, Petro glorioſ prep. 
               hoc eſt, ſenioris Romae, &amp; Conſtantinopoleos, &amp; Alexandrinae, &amp; Theopoleos, &amp; Hieroſolymorū. &amp;c. we wil therfore that the moſt holy archbiſhops and Patriarches, that is to ſay of
               
               
               old Rome, Conſtantinople, Alexandria, Antioch, and Ieruſalem &amp;c. He writeth not to one alone, leaſt that one ſhoulde chalenge a ſuperioritie. Where was then therfore of Rome the ſupremacie? certaine biſſhops he had vnder him, ſo had the reſt, this was all his authoritie. Iuſtinian his ſtyle vnto the biſhop of Rome was this: Ioanni
               Iustin. Ioanni viro. &amp;c. 
               viro beatiſsimo, ac ſanc̄tiſsimo Archiepiſcopo, &amp; Patriarchae veteris Romae: To Iohn the moſt bleſſed man, and moſt holy Archbiſhop &amp; Patriarch of old Rome.
                And here leaſt any may gather any thing by theſe wordes, moſt bleſſed &amp; moſt holy, you ſhall heare in what order he writeth vnto the Biſhop of Conſtantinople, weygh both the ſtyles, and you ſhall ſée Conſtantinople to haue the greater reuerence, his wordes vnto him be theſe: To the moſt holy Epiphanius, and moſt bleſſed Archbiſhop of this holy royall Citie, and vniuerſall Patriarch. Yea, Iuſtinian in playne words ſayth, that Conſtantinople (Eſt ſanctiſsimamaior eccleſia)
               
               Iuſtin. An
                     •
                   thenio ſanctiſs. &amp;c. 
               is the moſt holy &amp; worthier Church. Iuſtinian, no man can well denie it, was then vnder Chriſt in earth (if they will terme it ſo) the ſupreme heade, he then, and

none other made lawes, and the ſame aſwel ſpirituall as temporall. Unto the Clergie theſe were his words: we commaund: we will not ſuffer: we ordeine: we ſtreightlye prohibite: we appoint: we will: we bidde: Theſe be wordes of greater authoritie than the biſhop of Rome ought to vſe, they be wordes by authoritie commaunding him. And that the Pope ought not to vſe them, Gregorie in manifeſt words bearethGregorius Eulogio epiſcopo Alexandrino witneſſe: for writing vnto the Biſhop of Alexandria, thus ſayth he: Which word of bidding I woulde to bee farre from my hearing, for I know who I am, and who you are. In calling, you are my brethren, in maners, my fathers: therfore I badde not, but endeuored to ſhew what things ſeemed profitable. Princes maye vſe theſe words bidding. &amp;c. in them they be tolerable, and therefore the ſame Gregorie writingIdem Mauritio Augusto. vnto the Emperor, ſayth: Quantum ad me attinet, ſereniſsimis iuſsionibus obedientiam praebeo, In that which appertayneth vnto me, I yelde, &amp; render due obediēce vnto your maieſties moſt roial biddings &amp; cō
                     maundements.
                I would to God, in hart I wiſhe it, that as the Pope did here vnto the

Emperor, ſo al we would do vnto our moſt gracious ſouereigne and moſt royall Princeſſe the Queenes Maieſtie, and ſo vnto hir ſucceſſors. You ſee that there is no cauſe but we ſhoulde doe it, there is no reaſon, no authoritie to the contrarie. Let any indifferent man reade the Chronicles, yea let him reade their owne writings, and it ſhal be euident, that the Biſhops of Rome had not the title of any ſuch Primacie, vntill at length thorow pride and ambicion, contrarie vnto all cuſtome and good order, they vſurped that authoritie. Symmachus and Laurentius, being both at one time choſen Biſhops of Rome (tantaest diſcordia fratrum)
                after much ſtrife and controuerſie, were faine to go vnto Rauenna, there to abide the iudgement, (as in déede they did) of Theodoricus the king. Pelagius the ſecond, how was he choſen? abſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   decreto Principis, contra conſuctudinem,
               Nauclerus. 
               without the decree of the Prince agaynſt all cuſtome. Here they ſee that it was contrarie vnto all former example, that the byſhop of Rome ſhoulde be choſen againſt the decrée and will of the Prince. Bonifacius the third did will, that the election of the B. of Rome ſhoulde conſiſt and be determined

by the iudgement of the Prince, of the Clergie, and of the Laitie, &amp; that for good cauſes. But Phocas (they ſaye, marke well whenAnno domini. 604. their kingdom began) cōmaunded at the requeſt of the B. of Rome, that all Churches ſhould be obedient vnto ye Romain church. And yet was the authoritie of ye biſhop notwithſtanding ſo ſmal, yt he ſhould be ſuffred to do nothing without ye commaūdement of ye Emperor. For Bonifaciꝰ the fourth was glad to aſke leaue of Phocas that he might tranſpoſe the temple Pantheon, to be the Church of our Ladie, and of all Sainctes. Bonifacius the fift, coulde not without the licence of Heraclius the Emperour, not ſo much as be ſuffered to take the tiles from Romulus temple, to couer S. Peter his Church. Neither was this in the time when the Church was perſecuted, it was ſix hundreth and twentie yeres after Chriſt, it was when all Chriſtendome (as they ſay) obeyed the Biſhop of Rome. But what obedience was giuen him, by his obedience vnto the Emperour, it maye appeare. For if it were not lawful for him without ye Emperours leaue, to medle with the tiles or temporall goods of one Church, then it was leſſe lawfull

for him to haue to doe, as he now claymeth with ye whole temporalities of all the Churches in Chriſtendom. If he might not doe ſo litle a thing without the conſent of the Emperour, much leſſe might hée doe greater thinges, much leſſe lawfull it was for him to depoſe Chriſtian Princes, and to tread vnder his féete Kings and Emperors. Let here indifferencie take place, if wée be wiſe, we wil wey theſe things without partialitie. Neyther may I here omit Paſchalis which was choſen to the Biſhopricke of Rome in the yeare of our Lorde. 817. Who for that he was not elected by the authoritie of the Emperour, was faine to ſende vnto Lewys named for his clemencie Pius, then being Emperour, to declare in whome the fault was, and that it was long of the people and the Clergie that he was ſo elected, adding further that he was choſen againſt his will. With this ſatiſfaction Lewys was pleaſed, and therevppon he wrote vnto the people and Clergie that they ſhoulde kéepe the inſtitutions and decrées of their aunceſtours, and that they ſhoulde not offende the imperiall Maieſtie againe. This is ſo manifeſt that what ſhould we néede any more?

and yet ſéeing I am entred into the hiſtorye, I will alledge what Gregorie the fourth did, in acknowledging his duetie vnto the Emperor. He being choſe biſhop of Rome, by the conſent of the people and the Clergy, would in no wiſe take vpon him that digninitie, vntill the ſayd Lewys had confirmed his election. Hath then the Emperour nothing to doe with the choſing of the Biſhop of Rome? who is ſo fonde as to defend ſuch abſurditie? is not this playne? is not this true? is not this in their owne hiſtorie? was not Benedictus the thirde, confirmed Biſhop by Lewys the ſecond? was not Nicholas the firſt, confirmed by the ſame Emperor? &amp; that it ſhould be ſo, was it not the order alwayes, the lawe, and the cuſtome? Concerning their Counſels, in ſpeaking of one, we ſhall eaſily bewray the weakeneſſe of the others, and that if ſpecially we touche any of their chiefe. Their Councell holden at Chalcedon in Aſia, they do in althings ſo reuerence, receiue, and ſo beleue, as they doe the foure holye Goſpels of our Sauiour Chriſt. If then we can prooue errors therein, of neceſſity muſt they acknowledge their Counſell to be erronious, and themſelues

to bée blaſphemous. Let them nowe take héede, for if this go forwarde, their craking of Counſels, their authoritie of fathers, ſhal henceforth not helpe them a farthing. But how ſhall we proue it? Euen by the Biſhop of Rome himſelf, I think his friends will be glad of ſuch a iudge. If he procede againſt them, let them blame none but him, whoſe blames they ſeeke to defende. To be briefe, thus ſhall we proue it:
            All ſuch as haue offered vnto anye man a prophane name, a name of raſheneſſe, of pride, and of blaſphemie, were erronious and wicked.
            But the Counſell holden at Chalcedon hath offered vnto the Biſhop of Rome a prophane name, a name of raſhneſſe, of pride, and of blaſphemie.
            Therefore the Counſell holden at Chalcedon was erronious and wicked.
            Here the Propoſition at large is vndoubtedly true, the leſſe is prooued out of Gregorie Biſhop of Rome, in his Epiſtles vnto Eulogius Biſhop of Alexandria, vnto Iohn Biſhop of Conſtantinople, &amp; vnto Anaſtaſius Biſhop of Antioch. The Concluſion can in no wiſe be denied. Note now

then in what eſtate, in what ſtrength is their Euangelicall Counſell, vnderſtande how ſoone they are diſproued, and how eaſie it is to detect their pryde, their vſurpation, their blaſphemies, &amp; ambicion. I ſée a great deale more, which I might haue ſaide, touching reaſon and authoritie, but to any reaſonable man, to any not drowned in the verie pit of darkeneſſe, thys much may ſuffice. Wherefore, forget not that Gregorie calleth this name of a ſupreme head, of a generalitie, of an vniuerſall Patriarch, of a ſupreme Biſhop (for all is one) the name of pride, of raſhneſſe, of blaſphemie, an vngodly, a wicked and a prophane name, and that he further ſayth: None of my predeceſſors,
               Greg. Eulogio &amp; Anastaſio. 
               no Biſhop of Rome, hath at any time agreed to vſe ſo vngodlye a title. Let not ſuch alſo forget, who take vpō them ſo raſhly, &amp; ſo vnlearnedly to maintain the biſhop of Rome, what Gregorie herein further ſayth, his wordes be theſe, for that they are manifeſt, I may not omitte them. Who is therefore (ſayeth he) in ſo corrupt, and
               Greg. Ioanni epiſcopo Conſtanti. 
               naughtie a name, ſet, except he, before vs to be folowed, which deſpiſing the legions of aungels, appointed with him in
               
               equall fellowſhip, hath leapte out into the higheſt poynt of ſingularitie, to the intent he might obey none, but rule all? who alſo ſaid: I will clyme vp into heauen,
               Eſay. 14. 
               and make my ſeate aboue the ſtarres of the ſkye, I will ſit vppon the glorious mount towards the North, I will clyme vp aboue the Clowdes, and will be lyke the moſt higheſt. Let thoſe which are in blindneſſe, if they haue eyes, ſée, if they haue eares, let them heare, if they haue reaſon, let them iudge, if they haue learning, let them diſcuſſe, whether theſe woordes be ſo plaine, as the Pope in no wiſe, except he renounce his pardones and pride, can auoyde them. Well, ſhal we haue a vew of the ſcriptures? ſhal we ſee what in them ye biſhop of Rome hath, to mayntayne his papacie? One thing (Chriſten Reader) before I beginne, I dare faithfully promiſe thée, that thou ſhalt finde throughout ye whole teſtament, neither Papa, Papatus, Primas, nor Primatus, to be graūted vnto any of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, then much leſſe vnto the Byſhop of Rome. Marry we muſt confeſſe, and we will doe it freely, that there was a fooliſh contention amongſt the Apoſtles, euen in Chriſt hisLuc. 2
                     •
                  .
               
time, before he ſuffred, which of them ſhouldMarc. 10. Math. 20. be the greater. But our Sauiour did muche reprehende them therefore as we reade at large thereof in the Scriptures, where hée ſayth that amongſt the Princes of the Gentiles ſuch worldly power, ſuch dominion is vſed: Non ita erit inter vos, it ſhall not be ſo amongſt you.
                And yet notwithſtanding all this, the Biſhop of Rome will néedes haue Peter (God knoweth little for Peters ſake) to haue the preheminencie, the maioritie, the ſuperioritie ouer all the reſt. Chriſt alloweth it not, the Pope will, belike it ſhall be as he will. That I ſpeake no worſe of him, a wilfull part he playeth thus in abuſing holye Scripture, in peruerting the ſenſe, by his inſenſible reaſons, to ſerue his turne and deſire. But deale he as he liſt, yet dare I lay, that he ſhall be brought down
               Eſay. 14. 
               to the depth of hell. And as for his arrogant &amp; al ignorant arguments, they ſhal bée here layde out, their weakeneſſe ſhall be diſcloſed to their ſhame that ſtill will defende him, and to their praiſe that in time forſake him. I craue of thée (good Reader) in hys name, before whom we al muſt be iudged, yt thou wilt for thine owne ſake, ſée vnto theſe

arguments, conſider their abſurdities, and wey them with indifferencie. Their firſt fonde argument is this: Chriſt ſayd, thouMath. 16. Behold how this place is abuſed. art Peter, and vpon this rocke I will builde my Church. Therefore the Biſhop of Rome is the ſupreme heade. O Lorde what a wiſe reaſon is this / where was Logique, and that I ſpeake not of the reſt, where was cō
               mon ſenſe when this was framed? vppon what will he builde his Church? ſhake off blindeneſſe, confeſſe the truth, ſuper hanc petram,
               Ambroſe. 
               id est, ſuper hanc fidem, vpon this rock, that is to ſay, vpon this fayth.
                Vpon him which rightly confeſſeth that Chriſt is the ſonne of the liuing God, ſhall the Church be builded. And did none euer confeſſe that but Peter? yes, all the reſt of the Apoſtles, Iudas I ſcariotes excepted. Therefore vppon them all, vpon any, whoſoeuer that confeſſeth Chriſt to be the ſonne of ye liuing God, is the Church builded. For what is the building of Chriſt his Church? is it any thing elſe, than the increaſe of faithfull people, confeſſing and acknowledging the faith of Chriſt? what dreame they than, vpon Tues Petrus, &amp; ſuper hanc petram? perceiue they not how that place of ſcripture is moſt playne?

or is it vnto them that the holy ghoſt, by the Prophete Eſay doth thus ſpeake? you ſhal
               Eſay. 6. 
               heare, but you ſhall not vnderſtand, you ſhall ſee, and yet not perceyue. Oh, repent,
               Marc. 1. 
               and beleue the Goſpell. For this argument they themſelues ſée, doth neyther proue in Peter any ſuperioritie, nor yet that their Pope ought to haue anye primacie. Procede we then to their other arguments. Chriſt ſayde vnto Peter, féede my lambes,Ioan. 21. Note how this place is peruerted. féede my ſhéepe, féede my ſhéepe: therefore Peter is the heade of the Apoſtles. I wéene this be to headie an argument, in the iudgement of any reaſonable man, to be graūted. Of Logique I will no more ſpeake, for as all men may ſée, they eyther vtterly lacke it, or elſe they want good matter therein to vtter it, or both. Shall it follow, bicauſe Chriſt bade Peter féede his ſheepe, that therefore he is the heade of the Apoſtles? what is it to féede Chriſt his ſhéepe? is it anye thing elſe than to preach the Goſpel, and ſo to inſtruct men in the faith? ſayde he not then aſmuch vnto the reſt? hos numero. 12. emiſit Ieſus, ChriſtMath. 10. ſent forth euerie of the twelue to preache, ad oues perditas, to call home the ſtrayed ſhéepe, to féede them. He gaue no one iote of authoritie

vnto Peter, which he gaue not vnto all the reſt, he ſent them all to preache the Goſpell, to féede his ſhepe. But why would the Biſhop of Rome haue Peter, ſo plainly againſt the ſcriptures to be the principal or chiefe among the Apoſtles? latet anguis in herba, there is a pad in the ſtrawe: it is not be ye aſſured, to further Peter, it is nothing for Peters ſake: it is to the intent that he himſelfe (O prowde man!) might chalenge a ſuperioritie ouer all. This is the cauſe that theſe blinde arguments came forth, that the ſcriptures be ſo wreſted, abuſed, and belyed. Againe, they thus reaſon. Chriſt ſayth vntoMath. 17. Wey howe this place is wreſted. 
               Peter, thou ſhalt finde in the fiſh his mouth a péece of coyne of foure drammes, paye that for me and thée: therefore Peter hath a primacie ouer all the Apoſtles. A perfite argument I warraunt you, if it be throughlye weyed: there was neuer ſuch abſurd toyes, neuer ſuch boyiſh brawling, I dare ſaye, deuiſed. Doth, I pray you, Chriſt, bicauſe hée then payed tribute, chalenge vnto himſelfe, therefore anye power, did not as manye as were at Capernaum pay the tribute of two drammes? did anye one of them thereby claime an authoritie? how ſhall Peter then

hereby haue any ſuperioritie? is it bicauſe Chriſt payd for him two grotes? good God, a great manye, yea all, (they muſt needes graunt) payd at Capernaum, for their ſeruants the like tribute, and yet did they not therfore attribute vnto their men any chiefe dignitie. The truth is mightie, and theDem. ex orat. de fal. legat. contrarie is weake: the truth hereof is, Peter had neuer a pennie, and therfore Chriſt with that one coyne, leaſt he ſhoulde be an offence vnto them, payd for him. This is the right ſenſe, there is no more in it to ſéeke. What can be plainer than this? what can be more peruerſe, than to ſhadow with lies, with lewdneſſe ſo manifeſt a truth? But O the great ſtrength of veritie, which againſtCicer: pro M. Caelio. the deuiliſh craft and ſubtilty of men, and agaynſt all the falſe guiles of any whoſoeuer, of hir owne force doth defende hir ſelfe! an other of their argumentes is this. Chriſt ſayd vnto Peter, Simon, Simon beholdeLuc. 22. Se howe this place is miſvſed. Satan hath deſired to ſifte you, as it were Wheate: but I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not: therefore Peter hath a maioritie ouer al the Apoſtles, and is their ſuperiour. Suppoſe here (Chriſten reader) what theſe men would doe, if others framed

againſt them ſuch fooliſh and ſelf will arguments. Neuer ſaye that they are learned, except they haue ſome better learning. But I maruayle not ſo much at their blindneſſe, I haue bene in it, I know therof the effects. If I wondered at any thing, it ſhoulde be at this, that there are amongſt ſo many men, not ſo much as one eye. Neyther ſpeake I of corporall eyes, but of thoſe rather which Aungels haue, the eyes of vnderſtanding, the eyes wherewith God is ſéene, wherewith his holy worde is vnderſtanded. Now touching this place of Scripture, whereas Chriſt ſayd vnto Peter, that Satan deſired to ſift them, as it were Wheate, the ryght meaning (marke well indifferent Reader) thereof is, that our Sauiour Chriſt perceyuing the time of his paſſion to approche, and vnderſtanding the frailtie, temptation and feare that his Apoſtles ſhould then be in, he ſayd: all you ſhall bee offended through
               Marc. 14. 
               me this night, for it is written: I will ſmite the ſhepherde, and the ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered▪
                Sée here howe plainly the Euangeliſt S. Marke ſetteth forth that place of S. Luke. The ſhepehearde is Chriſt, the ſhéepe are the Apoſtles, at his taking they

ſcattered: relicto illo, omnes fugerunt, they leftIbidem. him in the handes of his aduerſaries, and fled awaye. This is it that Satan deſired to ſift thē. What followeth? but I haue praiedLuc. 22. for thée (vnto Peter he ſayth) that thy faith fayle not. And what gather wee of theſe wordes: forſooth, that Chriſt ſéeing, conſidering, yea, vttering the eſtate to come of Peter, that is, how in that day he ſhould denie him thriſe, and that before the Cocke crewe, he thought it neceſſarie alſo, as néedfull it was, that Simon by name ſhould receyue ſome words of comfort, that he ſhould vnderſtand, though through feare he denied him, that yet his faith ſhoulde not ſo fayle, but that in hart ſtill he would acknowledge him to be the ſonne of the liuing God, and though that through frayltie he did fall, yet ſhould he through due repentance be rayſed vp againe, and ſo ſhould not his faith fayle. There followeth alſo in the ſame place: and when thou art cōuerted, make more
               Ibidem. 
               conſtant thy brethren. That is, after thou haſt denied me, after thou haſt bitterly wept and repented, call then togither thy brethrē, call thoſe that are fled, confirme them, tell them that you all haue done euil, will them

nowe with thée to repent and to be ſorie. Such is the ſenſe of that text, it ſoundeth (you ſée) in no wiſe to any ſuperioritie. And touching the authoritie of binding and loſing, as it was giuen vnto Peter, ſo was it vnto all the reſt, and that without anye exception. For our Sauiour ſpeaking vnto them al (as S. Iohn witneſſeth) ſaith thus:Ioan. 
               whoſe ſinnes ſoeuer yee remit, they are remitted vnto them, and whoſe ſinnes ſo euer yee retain, they are retayned. Saint Mathew recordeth the ſame, his wordes bee plaine, the ſenſe is euident, the meaning is manifeſt, what would you more? S. Paule himſelfe (a thing to bee marked) being accuſed before. Feſtus, there and then appealed not vnto Peter, but vnto Caeſar, ſhewing thereby vnto vs, that in cauſes, accuſations and controuerſies, it is not vnto the Pope, but vnto the Prince that we ought to appeale. Wherefore theſe thinges with an vpright iudgement, with an honeſt conſcience conſidered, how, by what meanes, ſhall the Popes primacie be defended? the foundation thereof is pride, the fruite is poyſon, it can not be prayſed. Reaſon is wholye againſt it, good authorities do earneſtly withſtand

it, and holye ſcripture doth altogither denie it. If good reaſon therefore maye take place, if right authorities can preuayle, if ſacred Scripture ſhall ouercome, who is he now, where is any that will maintaine, defend, vphold, or aſſiſt either the Pope, or his feyned, painted, hollow Popedome? I will therfore conclude, yea, the kings of the earth (as ſayeth the Prophet Eſay) doe one after another conclude and ſay: How happeneth
               Eſay. 14. 
               it, that the oppreſſor leaueth off? is the golden tribute come to an end? art thou wounded alſo, as wee? art thou become like vnto vs? thy pompe and thy pride is gone downe to hell. Mothes ſhall bee layd vnder thee, and wormes ſhall be thy couering. The Cockatrice which came out of the Serpents roote, we ſée now rooted out, God graunt that it neuer take roote, ſo ragingly to rebell againſt heauen againe.
            Here ſéeing then that the chiefeſt bulwark of vnbeliefe is battered downe, ſéeing the gate of Babilon is broken, ſéeing that the very ſeate of Lucifer is defaced, ſéeing hys prowde pallace is ouerthrowen, wée maye briefly ſpeake of the braunches, which, ſayd we nothing, the roote being deſtroyd, would

elſe of themſelues in verie ſhort time fayle, die, wither, and decaye. For if the Pope bée put downe, how can dreaming Purgatorie ſtande? how can his Bulles liue? how can his Pedlars, and his Pardons preuayle? of theſe things, and of ſuch others, I meane as briefly, ſo in plaine wiſe, and indifferently to ſpeake. Yet firſt I ſée it needefull, that we aunſwere vnto certaine obiections now bellowing in the throtes of the aduerſaries, that ſo their vaine dartes and fooliſh reaſons throughly weied, they acknowledging their diſeaſe, maye with a more moderation of mynde with vs conſider, what things they be, whence they came, and wherevnto they tende, whereof we haue to treate. Shall weAn obiection. (ſaye they) miſlike the fayth which our fathers profeſſed when we were borne? if the common people which knowe not the lawe, and are accurſed, doe follow this newe doc.Ioan. 7. trine, ſhall we be alſo ſeduced? doth any of ye chiefe Rulers, of the Lords, of the Lawyers, or of the learned beleeue it? Oh, ſicut patres
               An anſwere. Actes. 7. 
               vestri it a &amp; vos? as your fathers the Phariſies haue obiected, wil you alſo obiect? if S. Paule had ſtill followed the Phariſaicall law, which his father embraced, and wherin

he was borne, he had not bene worthie to haue the name of an Apoſtle of Chriſt: if Peter, if Barnabas, if the reſt had not forſaken the rites and lawes then vſed whē they were borne, and which their forefathers helde and kept, they had neuer bene accounted the Diſciples and followers of Ieſus. Touching the common people, you knowe how the Phariſies fooliſhlye obiected by the ſame wordes, the ſelfe ſame thing againſt our ſauiour. And as you ſaye: theſe Proteſtants be mad, they haue no learning, ſo ſayd they: turba haec non nouit legem, execrabiles ſunt,
               Ioan. 7. 
               theſe fooliſh people know not the lawe, they are accurſt. But let the Phariſies, let their followers ſpeake what them liſt, wée muſt ſaye: nunquam ſic loquutus est homo ſicut hic homo, there is no preaching like vnto the Goſpell, there was neuer man that ſet forth ſuch doctrine, there is none that may be compared vnto this. S. Auguſtine before his conuerſion vnderſtanding that the poore Chriſtians did preuaile and now ſomewhat better liking their doctrine, ſayth: Quid patimur? what ſuffer wee? ſurgunt indocti, &amp; rapiunt coelum, &amp; nos cum nostris ſcientijs dimergimur in profundum, the vnlearned doe riſe
               
               
               vp, and they get heauen: but we with all our knowledgeſſe are drowned in darkeneſſe. Let none therefore alleadge that wee are vnlearned, for were wée ſo, indocti rapiunt coelum, theſe vnlearned, theſe fooliſh proteſtants doe get heauen. It is they which by perſecution be encreaſed, and by ſuffering of fire, water, and ſworde are ſo multiplied, that they may well ſay: magna est veritas, &amp; praeualet, mightie is the truth, and ſhee ouercommeth.
                And concerning the chiefe rulers (right great praiſe be therefore vnto God.) They were not of a long time ſo deſirous to heare the truth, nor ſo willinglye to embrace it as nowe. If ſome be yet clogged, if their eyes be not opened, what maruaile? When the Prophet Ieremie perceiued that the people would not repent, what ſayd he? for ſit an pauperes ſunt, peraduentureIeremi. 5. they are fooliſh and ſimple, they vnderſtand not the Lordes way: ibo igitur ad optimates, I will goe therefore vnto their heades, and rulers, vnto the chiefe, &amp; ecce magis hi ſimul confregerunt iugum, ruperunt vincula, but loe, theſe in like maner haue rather broken the yoke, and burſt the bandes in ſunder, theſe are worſe than ye other. How ſay you now?

what ſpeake you of the chiefe and Rulers? as for the learned, I will confeſſe the truth, there are in the miniſterie men verie ſimple and of ſmall vnderſtanding, I knowe of thē a number, I wil not denie it, the thing may in time be remedied: but to ſpeake indifferentlye, if we examine the miniſterie with the former prelacy, they are as learned now, yea, better learned than euer they were. For in times paſt, what ſay you vnto Prieſtes, what ſay you vnto Biſhops that coulde not ſpeake anye true Latine? Let none thinke that I ſlaunder them, they were ſuch, and therfore to excuſe themſelues, thus they ſay: If the Biſhops or Preiſtes doe ſpeake amiſſe,
               Dist. 38. &amp;c 
               through ignorance in Grammer, they maye not bee therefore deſpiſed of ſchollers (no marrie) bicauſe the faultes are rather to bee aduoyded in maners, than in wordes: A proper matter, and an arche argument be ye aſſured. The faultes in a mans life are to be rather aduoyded, therefore ſuch Biſhops or Prieſtes as can not ſpeake true Latine, are not to be diſpraiſed. I pray thee of felowſhip, chriſten reader, findeſt thou herewith anye fault? if a poore Miniſter had made any ſuch, ſhoulde he not

haue bene flowted? is this their learning? O learned fathers! Fie vpon ſuch an ignorant time, it was to darke, it was intollerable. Non est deponendus aliquis propter imperitiam,
               X. q. 1. placuit. 
               no ſpirituall man (ſay they) ſhould be depriued for ignorancie. Why ſpeak they then of the learned, they themſelues being not only ignorant, but alſo the defenders of ignorancie? what talke they of learning? the effect of their whole gloſaicall ſtudie is this: Beholde the deceitfull pen of the
               Ierem. 8. 
               Scribes hath ſet foorth lyes. What learning, what wiſdome then can be amongſt thē? An other obiection is this: we ſée (ſayAn obiection. they) the iniquitye of the time, this doctrine cannot be good, there is ſuch vngodlineſſe euery where. In dede we cōfeſſe that ye worldThe anſwere. Iſidor.
                is naught, yea, and that we are naught, we neither wil nor may iuſtify our ſelues, ſilētio culpa creſcit, we hide not our faults, we confeſſe thē vnto God, of him we craue mercie. And what is ye cauſe of this miſchief? let vs be indifferent, let vs tell troth. Satan forſooth of a long time hauing the world vnder his clawes, was quiet, without care, he was negligent. Then loe, though moſt horrible vices raigned, yet had they eyther the title of

vertues, or elſe had the people no eies to diſcerne them, ſo that Satan was animi ſecuri homo, one that feared nothing, he néeded not to be buſie, a better trade than he had, coulde he neuer haue. For Superſtition had put on the name of Religion, hawtineſſe was termed holyneſſe, tyrannie was called a zeale vnto iuſtice, whoredome was named chaſtitie, and (as Gregorie ſayth) vitia virtutes ſe eſſe mentiuntur, vile vices reported thēſelues to be vertues, ſuche was the wretchedneſſe (O miſerie / ) of the time. But in theſe days Satan being pinched, mens eyes opened, darkeneſſe remoued, vices defected, and the deuill in a maner naked, howe on euery ſide beſturreth he himſelfe? he bloweth abrode his poyſon, he ſcattereth euerye where hys newes, he calleth vnto him his mates, it ſtandeth him vpon, he maketh all the troubles that may be. And what of all this? is it a thing ſtraunge? or is not a thing always ſéene, that when the Goſpell is preached, then Satan is moſt moued. For the deuill
               Chryſost. 
               hearing that the ſonne of god deſcended into this world, hearing the fayth of Chriſt preached, he made great haſte againſt him to ſhut vp mens harts in ſinne and infidelitie,
               
               thinking that he coulde deſtroye as much, as Chriſt was able to ſaue. For example therof, what ſhould I ſpeake of the perſecution in the primatiue Church? it ſhal ſuffice, if I ſet before you but a péece of the wickedneſſe, and of the lamentable eſtate of ye Romaine Empire beginning anon after Marcus. Commodus the Emperour (youHerodian. Anno domini. 194. know) cauſed moſt cruelly, all his good fathers friends to be ſlaine, he liued in moſte deteſtable whoredome, and murther, he him ſelfe was in thende, after other great daungers, poyſoned, and ſtrangled. Next him ſucceded Pertinax a verye good man, yet was he ſlaine and murthered of his owne ſouldiors. What ſhoulde I ſpeake onely of murther: what wickedneſſe raigned not? Theſe cut throte ſouldiours, after the death of Pertinax ſolde the Empire vnto a couetous Carle, one Iulianus. But what came thereof? the whole eſtate of ye Empire was troubled, thrée at one time claymed the authoritie, Iulianus, Niger, and Seuerus. Againe of the death of Antoninus, and of Iulia his mother, what ſhould I ſaye? go thorow the whole hiſtorie, and you ſhall finde almoſt nothing but méere impietie. And yet

at this time the Goſpell was preached, wée may not ſay that the doctrine was not therfore good, bicauſe the time ouer flowed with iniquitie. Conſider this, Chriſten Reader, wey it with thine owne conſcience, and thenAn obiection. iudge vprightly. They obiect alſo, that ye life of the Miniſters is naught, that they be vicious, lewde, and I knowe not what. Their lewdeneſſe I will not defende, if they be euill,The anſwere. God amende them. I knowe hereof, more thā for ſome cauſes I will yet write, I know there be within ye Miniſterie, a number of the Popes friendes in Proteſtantes ſkins, I know their trades, I know them. If in the Church now there be ſome lewde men, I maruaile not. So was amongſt and of the twelue a Iudas, there was one naughtie perſon amongſt eight within the arke of Noe, in the houſe of Abraham, in the houſe of I ſaac, of Iacob, of Dauid, there were offenders, and men altogither vnfaithfull, in the heauen it ſelfe many of the Aungels were faultie. What then thoughe ſome, yea, euen of the Preachers be peruerſe? There are ſome which be lewde, I wil graūt it. Were they not ſo in S. Paules
               Philip. 2. time? I haue no man (ſayeth he) which
               
               with a like affection, will care for your matters with me, for all doe ſeeke that is their owne, and not that is Ieſus Chriſt. What ſaye you to this? how ſaye you vnto that time? Touching the Pope and his Prelacie, who can accuſe them? for though they be neuer ſo lewd of themſelues, though they offende in moſt deteſtable filthineſſe, though the Pope doe not one good déede, yetSymmachus papa. the vertues of his Predeceſſors maye ſuffice him. Theſe be their owne words, wey them (I aſke) with indifferencie. In this their owne Doctor, their owne Pope is againſt them, I meane Gregorie. Grace (ſayth he)Gregorie. 
               and not the place doth ſaue the ſoule. Surelye had I here time to ſet forth their lewde and fonde Canons, had I leyſure cō
               uenient to lay out before you their foule fornication, their naughtineſſe and abhomination, you woulde doubtleſſe abhorre them, we ſhould altogither defie them. But would you thinke (vnto their friendes I ſpeake) that they defended whoredome? would you beleue that theſe were their wordes? One hauing no wife, &amp; that hath a concubine
               Concil. To letan. 
               may not be put from the Communion, ſo that he be contented with one woman
               
               be ſhe wife or harlot. O how horrible among Chriſtians is this decrée! Such ſtuffe they haue, ſuch holyneſſe they vſe, ſuch men they be. Loth I am to defile any further my pen, either in their moſt lothſome lawe, or in their vile and lawleſſe luſt. Nowe to the braunches whereof I ſpake, and firſt of the chiefe, which is Purgatorie. This is a placePurgatory. (as they appoint it) wherein onely ſmall offences be remitted in the next life. If you aſke them where this place is, they can not agree, you appoſe them, ſo that quod non inuenit vſquam, eſſe putat nuſquam. They haue ſought heauen, they haue ſought hell, itum est in viſcera terrae, they haue ſought euen the verie bowels of the earth, and yet can not feyned Purgatorie be founde, there is none before the time of darkneſſe, that euer heard of ſuch an Inne. But is there trowe ye, any ſuch place at al? If there be none, then hath it no place of being, for quod non est, nuſquam
               Arist. 
               est: That which is not, is no where.
                The name of Purgatorie in holye ſcripture was neuer read, in ſenſe alſo, there is therein nothing founde, in anye wiſe to confirme the ſame: except you will haue the wreſting of places to be proofes, and the abuſing of Gods

word to be made a warde, a couering, and a bolſtering of iniquitie. Did the Apoſtles of Chriſt euer heare of any ſuch place? heard they once of the name of Purgatorie? no, for it was long after (will the defenders thereof ſaye) before it was borne and chriſtened. Our forefathers (ſaye they) more
               Allen in the defence of Purgatorie. 
               than a thouſande yeares ſince called it Purgatorie. In déede they had néede at the length to name it, béeing of ſo long a tyme before nameleſſe, but who was Godfather? ye Pope himſelf. Well, it was time to hatch it, for it was one of the profitableſt monſters that euer was whelped within the Popes houſe. But (beléeue me) let them garniſhe it neuer ſo much with gold, feyned dreames and with other deluſions, yet ſhall it down, the ſtraw ſtuffing muſt be ſéene, the painted lymmes muſt be looked vppon, and the breathleſſe babe muſt throughly now be ripped vp, and be tried. And what gaue occaſion to our forefathers (I will vſe their owne wordes) of the name of Purgatorie? Marrie (ſay they) the thirde Chapiter of the Prophet Malachie, and the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians. Theſe be their twoo eſpeciall places, vpon the which, you ſhall nowe

ſée, how fooliſhly they builde. The words in Malachie be theſe: Beholde he commeth
               Malach. 3. 
               (ſayth the Lord of hoſtes) and who may abide the day of his comming? who can ſtande and endure his ſight? for he is like melting and caſting fire, and as the waſſhers herbe. And he ſhall ſit, caſting, and trying out ſiluer, and ſhal purge the children of Leui, and clenſe them as gold, or ſiluer. Here we find a maner of purgation, and what is it? forſooth we will vſe plaine dealing, the matter néedes no ſhift. In thys place and in the whole chapiter, theſe things be only conteyned, the comming of S. Iohn the Baptiſt, the deliuerance of the faithfull, through Gods great mercie and grace, from their ſinnes, the iudgement of Chriſt againſt the wicked, of their blaſphemies againſt God, and of Gods moſt benigne care toward the godlye. See then whether your priuate Purgatorie, maye haue hence anye place, any pretence of being, any defence or bolſtring, or not. I néeded not to tell you, oh I woulde it were not néedefull to tell, that we are onely ſaued by Chriſt his death, that we are clenſed by his bloud ſhed, and that we are redemed by his paſſion, it is our Sauiour

Ieſus Chriſt, which gaue himſelf forTitus. 2. vs, to redéeme vs from all vnrighteouſnes, and to purge vs a peculiar people vnto him ſelfe, we feruentlye being giuen vnto good workes. Weigh then, what it is to purge the children of Leui, and ſée whether it be any thing elſe, then that they ſhould be regenerated and renewed by the ſpirite of God, yea, and that ſinne ſhoulde not be imputed vnto them for the loue of Chriſt. Conſider this, it is a more holeſome doctrine, than to hunt we know not where, after a hatefull, phantaſticall and fooliſh pretenced Purgatorie. Thus by the wordes of the Prophet, ſéeing they may not preuaile, ſeeing that the ſame is altogither againſt them, let vs likewiſe▪ ſée what ye Apoſtle ſayth. He alledgeth that the foundation is already layde, which is Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; then he procedeth in theſe wordes: If anye man builde vppon this
               1. Cor. 3. 
               foundation, golde, ſiluer, precious ſtones, wood, hay, or ſtubble, euery mans worke ſhall appeare. For the daye of the Lorde will declare it, and it ſhall bee ſhewed in fire, and the fire ſhall trie euerye mannes worke what it is. If any mans worke that he hath builte vpon, doe abide, he ſhall
               
               receyue a rewarde. If anye mans worke burn, he ſhal ſuffer loſſe, but yet he himſelfe ſhall be ſafe neuertheleſſe yet, as it were through fire. Theſe be S. Paules wordes▪ Now as men not giuen to contention and fonde ſtrife, as men deſirous of the right vnderſtanding of holye ſcripture, as men all free from partialitie and part taking, let vs weigh vprightlye the meaning of the text. Here the Apoſtle would haue vs to be feruent in good workes, and earneſt to doe well, hée wiſheth vs to bee occupied in that labour, which, when the iudge of all ſhall come, may in his ſight be acceptable, may to vs ward be commendable. And that we ſhould well beware, what workes we builde vppon our foundation, he plainlye ſheweth, that at the laſt day all our doings ſhalbe opened, and that then the ſame ſhall be ſo tried, as the Goldſmith in fining hys mettals, trieth out the droſſe and baſe matter, from the pure, perfite, and fine. The day (ſayth he) of our Lorde ſhall declare it,
               Ibidem. 
               bicauſe it ſhall appeare in fire. The daye of our Lorde is the daye of iudgement, the thing is ſo plaine, as no man, though he be very peruerſe, may denie it. But when ſhall

it appere in fire? euen then, at the generall iudgement, ſo is the text. Where is therfore in ye meane time, their place of Purgatorie? Well, will you ſée in fewe wordes, what by the whole text is ment? Here this onelye is ſpoken of thoſe, which ſhall be ſaued, of ſuch as builde vppon Ieſus Chriſt, vppon which foundation, as all can not builde golde, precious ſtones and ſiluer, as all can not be perfite, neyther by martyrdome bée crowned, nor yet by good learning ſhine like the ſtarres ofheauen: ſo thereon building, be it but Wood or Haye, be it but verie ſtubble, though ye work it ſelfe be in the end burned, though he himſelfe receiue no ſuch reward, as the others, yet ſhal he be ſaued, and how? as it were through fire. Not throughIbidem. fire, but through the great feare, wherin he then ſhall ſtande, of the iuſt iuſtice &amp; iudgement of God. O how comfortable is this doctrine? how farre paſſeth it al their painted fires and feyned flames of Purgatorie? You ſée now that the Scripture admitteth no ſuch place, you ſee the right meaning aſwell of the Prophet, as alſo of the Apoſtle, You ſée that their two chiefe and onely places, doe ſerue ſo to their purpoſe, that they

ſtand plainely and altogither againſt them. Howe ſhall then poore Purgatorie ſtande? how ſhall the Pope mayntayne his chiefe Farme? Howe ſhall therein his might, his gaine be befended? to what purpoſe ſhoulde we cloke the matter anye lenger? his euidences be all naught, his writings be counterfeyte, his leaſe is antedated, his witneſſes be prooued partiall, and periured, his Lawyers haue loſt their credite, his intereſt is not good, it is the Lord of hoſtes that ſueth him, the iudgement (ſe iudice) muſt paſſe againſt him. But we ſee (ſay the Purgatorians) the name of Purgatorie often ſet forth by auncient writers. And what I praye you of that? what gathered they, what meaned they by that name? forſooth, ſo farre were they from confeſſing anye ſuch Purgatorie fire, which now men ſo fooliſhly ſéeke to defende, that ſome ſayde the tribulation of
               Allen. &amp;c. 
               this life, and world, muſt trie mens faith and works: ſome ſaid the griefe of mind in looſing that which they ouermuch loued, was the burning fire of mans affections: ſome woulde haue the grieuous vexation of departure out of this life to be a Purgatorie paines: ſome conſtrued
               
               the text, of the fire of conflagration, that ſhall purge the workes of many in the latter daye. Here who is ſo blind, who is ſo ſenſeleſſe, but maye vnderſtande, that the ſcope of their Pargatorie was in thys preſent life, and that it did nothing concerne in any one point, any payne in the world to come? what ſhould I wade herein any further? what ſhould I vſe any more wordes? with one eſpeciall place of S. Auguſtine I will ende. For the ſoules (ſayth he) of the
               Lib. de ciuit. dei. 13. cap. 8. 
               godlye being ſeparated from the bodye, be in reſt: but the ſoules of the wicked, doe ſuffer paynes: vntill the bodies of the one may be reuiued vnto euerlaſting life, and of the other, vnto eternal death which is called the ſeconde. By this, he maketh but two eſtates of the ſoules departed, the one now in paines, who at the daye of iudgement ſhalbe damned, and the other now in reſt, who then ſhall be ſaued. So is their Idea, &amp; Idiot dreamings of Purgatory, by authorities, by ſcripture diſproued. The next thing wherof we mean to treate, is theThe ſupper of our Lord. ſacramēt, the holy remembrance of the body and bloud of our ſauiour Chriſt, which how it hath bene abuſed, of how long a time, and

by whom, we meane here by the aſſiſtance of God, whoſe cauſe eſpeciallye it is, to expreſſe, ſet forth and declare. Wherein if any
               Cyprian. 
               of our elders, eyther ſimply or ignorantlye haue not helde and obſerued, that which our Lord and ſauiour hath taught vs, the Lords pardon may extende vnto their ſimplicitie: but we which are nowe warned by our Sauiour, and inſtructed, may not loke for forgiueneſſe, If we wilfully will refuſe the knowledge of the truth, and the right vnderſtanding of Gods holye myſteries. Manifolde were the errors, wherwith men haue bene blinded, touching the holy ſupper of our Lorde, touching the Cō
               munion of his bodie and bloud But bicauſe I haue purpoſed to be brief, I wil rather labor to ſhew the light, &amp; right ſenſe therin of holy ſcripture, than to ouerthrow (which is very ſoone done) the fooliſh opinion of ſome groſſe and carnall Cauphernaites. Neyther yet may I altogither omit, as occaſion ſerueth, to ſpeake of the fonde iudgement of ſuch, who cannot be contented to enioye the benefites of Chriſt his bodie and bloude, except they further (O wicked follie!) maye teare him with their teeth, and more than

deuour him with their mouthes. Vnto theſe doth S. Auguſtine ſpeake: To what purpoſe
               August. 
               prepareſt thou thy teeth and thy bellie? beleue, and thou haſt eaten. Neither yet let any here ſuppoſe, that I adiudge it not néedfull to eate thoſe holye ſignes, as things inſtituted by our Sauiour, for vs to take and receiue in his remembrance. But that the aduerſaries maye throughlye be ſatiſfied, that the indifferent and welwilling maye rightly be inſtructed, ſhall we ſée in what wiſe S. Paule receiued this inſtitution at our Lords hands? That which I deliuered you, the ſame I receiued (ſayethI. Cer. II. he) of the Lord. For the Lorde Ieſus the ſame night in which hee was betrayed, tooke Bread, gaue thanks, and brake it, ſaying: take, and eate, this is my bodye, which ſhalbe giuen for you, this do ye in the remembrance of me. After the ſame maner he tooke the Cuppe when ſupper was done, and ſayd: this Cup is the new teſtament in my bloud, this doe as oft as you ſhall drinke it, in the remembrance of me. For as often as you ſhall eate this Breade, and drinke this Cup, you ſhall ſhewe the Lordes death vntill he come.
               
               Therfore whoſoeuer ſhal eate the Bread, and drinke the Cuppe of our Lord vnworthily, he ſhall be guiltie of the bodie and bloud of our Lord. Wherefore let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of that Breade, and drinke of that Cuppe. Thus farre ſpeaketh S. Paule, and that verie plainly. Nowe come we then to the ſearch of the text. And firſt, let thoſe who will acknowledge there no breade, way but indifferently the words as they ſtand. Chriſt tooke Breade, he gaue thanks, and brake it. What brake he? Breade. Who will denie it? He ſayde that it was his bodie. That is true: but howe? not fleſhly but ſpiritually. It is (ſayth Chriſt) the ſpirit that quickeneth,
               Ioan. 6. 
               the fleſhe profiteth nothing, the wordes that I ſpake vnto you, are ſpirite and life. Lo, how euidently he aunſwereth the cogitations of ſuch, as thought that they ſhould haue eaten him carnally. Hence it is that S. Auguſtine thus ſaith: The firſt hereſie
               Aug. in expoſition. Pſalm. 8. 
               ſprang amongeſt the Diſciples of Chriſt, as it were through the hardneſſe of hys words. For when he ſayd, except one will eate my fleſhe, and drinke my bloud, he can not haue lyfe euerlaſting.
               
               They here not vnderſtanding, ſayde one vnto another, this is a hard ſaying, who can eate him? and whiles they thus ſaid, they ſeparated themſelues from him, and he remayned with twoo diſciples, whom, when the other were gone, he inſtructed. It is the ſpirite (ſayth he) which giueth life, the fleſh profiteth nothing. The wordes that I ſpake vnto you, are ſpirite and life. You haue vnderſtoode ſpiritually, ſo they are ſpirite and lyfe: You haue vnderſtoode carnallye, ſo yet are they ſpirite and lyfe. But vnto thee they are not ſpirite and life, which vnderſtandeſt them not ſpiritually. Vnderſtande yee ſpiritually the wordes that I ſpake vnto you. You ſhall not eate thys bodie which you ſee, neyther ſhall you drinke the bloud, which thoſe that crucifie me ſhall ſhed. I haue cōmended vnto you a kinde of ſacrament, which being ſpiritually vnderſtanded, doth quicken you, but the fleſh profiteth nothing. But as they vnderſtode, ſo they aunſwered. For they vnderſtoode fleſhe, as that which is ſolde and broken in the ſhambles. But Chriſt perceyuing this, ſayde:
               
               This offendeth you, bicauſe I ſayde: I giue you my fleſhe to eate, and my bloud to drinke. If therefore you ſhall ſee the ſonne of man aſcende thither where hee before was, what is this? Here lo hath he plainly declared that, which before had moued them, here he opened, whence they were offended, here in deede and plainly if they had vnderſtoode it. But they thought that he would giue his bodie vnto them. He ſayd, that he would aſcend into heauen, and that all whole. When you ſhall ſee the ſonne of man to aſcende where he was before, truly then ſhall you ſpecially ſee that he giueth not his bodie in ſuch maner as you thinke: or then you ſhall vnderſtande, that hys grace is not conſumed with mouthes. Vntill the ending of the world, the Lord is aboue, but yet here is notwithſtanding with vs the grace of the Lorde, for the bodie wherein he roſe, can be but in one place, yet his grace, his Godhead, his diuinitie is ſpreade euerye where. O howe plaine, howe full, howe manifeſt be theſe wordes! the naturall bodye of Chriſt that was borne of the virgin Marie, is, and

muſt be in one place, and that in heauen, vntill the ending of the world: therefore his naturall bodie can not be here alſo in earth, it can not be in the material Church, on the altar, in ye Prieſts hands. Concerning their conſecration &amp; tranſubſtantiation, I aſke of them what they do conſecrate, whether it be bread, or ye Lords body? if it be bread, then isThe body of Christ is not conſecrated, nor yet the bread. Aſke them then, what is conſecrated? it not ye bodye of Chriſt, if it be his body, can they make it holyer at one time, than at an other? is his bodie at anye time vnholye? Herevnto they may neuer well aunſwere, their in instanti may ſtand nothing to their purpoſe. I am loth here to heape the innumerable hereſies wherein they are, which would defend this carnall eating. Their inconſtancie, their diſagréementes, their errors be maruailous. For example, and that I ſéeme not to belye them, I will betray one of their abſurdities. It is in queſtion amongſt them (ſo carnall they be, ſuch Cauphernaites they are) whether the bodie of Chriſt may be receiued with his deitie and ſoule or not? H: ſayth that neither the ſoule nor deitie is there receiued: others, as B: do ſaye, that in receiuing the body, they receiue alſo the deitie and ſoule. O Lorde what intollerable,

what horrible controuerſies what hainous abſurdities be theſe? It were hartilye to be wiſhed of euerie honeſt hart, that theſe would giue ouer, thus carnallye to grinde vpon Chriſt his ſoule, vppon his bodie and deitie. And if they cannot be quiet, without altercation in the true faith, then it is rather to bée ſuffered, that they wrangle (as a number of them do and haue done) about ſum, es, fui: hic, haec, hoc: qui quae quod &amp;c. For by the one, they ſet forth much and outragious impietie: by the other they bewray but their iangling nature and great follie. For is it not méere childiſhneſſe, for them to deale, as one of them doth in this matter? With it (ſayeth he) agreeth hoc,
               
               Sand: 
               this: with it, quod, the which: it commeth after the verbe est, is: and goeth before the verbe datur, is giuen. Good God what a doe is this, how is a Doctor here troubled in finding out, in one little ſentence, the nowne ſubſtantiue? Oh, it is eaſie to make great volumes, they maye ſoone make ſuch bookes, they may ſtuffe them without ſtudy, with Gēders, Caſes, Articles, Pronounes, Verbes, Participles, with conſtruing, with parſing, with iffes, with andes, with aſking

and aunſwering, with trifling and lingering, with light queſtions, common talke, and controlling. Well, Chriſt (ſaye they) ſaid, this is my body: why ſhall not we then beleue him? forſooth, that you would beleue him, we verilye doe wiſhe: and that you woulde take heede of that herefie, which
               August. 
               happened, as it were through the hardeneſſe of his wordes, amongſt his owne diſciples, we earneſtlye admoniſhe, perſwade and exhort you. It is vndoubtedly true, that the holye Communion doth conſiſt of twoo things, of the viſible kinde of Elementes, of breade and wine, and of the inuiſible grace. Of which twoo things, the ſpirituall body of Chriſt conſiſting, is receyued of the worthie receyuer, to his comfort and ſaluation. Neyther yet may you here thinke, that his ſpirituall bodie conſiſteth of breade, but that by the receyuing of breade, we be made to vnderſtande of the receit of his ſpirituall fleſhe, and by the receiuing of wine, we are certified to receaue (and all for our inſtruction) his ſpirituall bloude: or if you will haue it brieflier, to receyue his bodye and bloud ſpiritually. And that this is the Catholike faith, S. Hierome ſhall beare me

witneſſe: Two wayes is the fleſh of Chriſt
               In Epist. ad Epheſios. 
               and his bloud vnderſtanded: either that ſpirituall and diuine, whereof he ſayth: my fleſh is meate in deede, and my bloud is drinke in deede, and except you will eate my fleſh, and drinke my bloud, you ſhall not haue lyfe euerlaſtyng: or elſe that fleſhe which was crucified, and that bloud which was ſhed with the ſpeare of the ſouldier. What words can be playner than theſe? who is ſo ſimple, but may now ſée, of what fleſhe and of what bloude Chriſt ment, when he ſayde, My fleſhe is meate in deede? here further to aunſwere ſuch, who thinke it to be his carnall bodye, bicauſe he ſayde, this is my bodie, I thinke there is no reaſonable bodye, that will ſuppoſe it néedefull. Yet to auoyde all that the aduerſaries maye alledge, whereas he calleth it once his body, he many times nameth it bread, ſo doe the Apoſtles, ſo doe the Doctors. His body it is, in reſpect of his ſpiritual fleſh and bloud, which then the faithfull doe receiue: but bread and wine it is, in reſpect of the Elementes, which we eate, taſte off, and digeſt. Alſo whereas the Doctors doe ſomtimes not ſpeake of the bread and wine,

but of the verie bodie of Chriſt, quod in ipſae
               Auguſtin. 
               veritate ſpiritualiter manducatur &amp; bibitur, which in deede is ſpirituallye eaten and dronke:
                that do they yt rather to moue men to lift vp their hartes, &amp; to ſtirre them from the thinking on thoſe ſignes, to think vpon the thing ſignified, to remember that it is not in the bread fixed, which muſt féede vs, but that by faith we be fed from aboue, from heauen, whence we receiue of the Lord, the Cup of the newe Teſtament, whence wée receiue verilye Chriſt his bodie, by whome we liue, and are made fleſh of his fleſhe. So haue you here ſufficiently ſhewed vnto you, the right meaning of the Lordes ſupper, you haue in fewe wordes the effect of the ſame, and the teſtimonie therein, aſwell of Scripture, as of the Doctors. Doe ye therefore the partes of Chriſtians, acknowledge ye truth that you ſée, embrace true and playne doctrine, deteſt falſhood, abhorre fooliſh wrangling and wicked wreſting of Scriptures.
            Hither vnto haue we ſpoken of the abuſes of the Church of Rome, of the vſurped ſupremacie, of their painted vaine Purgatorie, and of their carnall vnderſtanding of Chriſt his wordes ſpoken at his laſt ſupper:

But nowe wee will brieflye treate, of the tranſlation of holy Scripture into the vulgare tongue, of ſinging of Pſalmes, and of ſuch like things, as they ſhal occurre, which now are by Satan reprooued, by his miniſters repugned, and by his chiefe defenders reſiſted. And herein that I maye be indifferent, I will vſe ſuch authorities as (let Satan doe his worſt) muſt néedes be allowed.
            Much a do many now make, bicauſe theyOf the tranſlation of holy ſcripture into the vulgar tongue. ſée the holy Scriptures to be in the Engliſh tongue, and that to the comfort and ſaluation of many a thouſande. But what (trow yée) is the cauſe that they finde themſelues therein ſo much grieued? Oh, therein lieth the verie whole matter, therein hangeth all the marring and making of their market. For if the people once perceiue what ſuperſtition is, will they (thinke you) be ſuperſtitious? if they perceyue what Hipocriſie is, will they be Hipocrites? if they ſée how hainous Idolatrie is, wil they then ſuccor Idolators? if they beholde what blindeneſſe is, will they delight in darkeneſſe? if they doe vnderſtand the ignoraunt abuſes of times paſt, will they perſeuer ſtill in ignorancie? if they were deceyued, blinded, and moſte

ſhamefully abuſed, will they then any longer followe dreames, or delight in the couetous deuiſes of men? when holy ſcripture is heard, reade &amp; vnderſtanded, then are errors afraid, lewd men amazed &amp; the deuil himſelf aſtonied. This moued our forfathers to take great paines, that ye ſcripture might be tranſlated out of one tongue into another, that ſo the more might vnderſtand them, that ſo the more might haue &amp; reade thē. And touching any fault in our Engliſh tranſlations, if in ſome, ſome thing be amiſſe, who will maruel? was not the trueſt &amp; auncient tranſlation in the Latine, corrupted and violated? Doth not S. Hierome himſelf ſo ſay? but IHieron. will anſwere ſuch, as pretende faults in our tranſlation, reade in the Church: and except he defende himſelfe well, he is like to feele (and yet I ſhall deale with him friendly) of hys owne blowes. And firſt I demaunde of him, whether in a tranſlation he would obſerue the true ſenſe, or elſe ſéeke for ye Noune ſubſtantiue, for Genders and Caſes, as hée hath done? in the iudgement of all learned,Hieron. in praefat. in lib. Iudith. and good men, the meaning of the author is to be folowed, &amp; the hunting after words, is not to be liked. But what blameth he in our

tranſlation? forſooth, we haue not rightlye tranſlated (ſayth he) this verbe 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . It ſhould (ſayth he) be engliſhed in the ſixt of Iohn, to worke, as 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,Ioan. 6. 
               worke the meate. Oh ſir, and why not labour for the meate? what I praye you is, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ? is it not victum quaerere, to labour for ones liuing?
                you ſee herein your ignorance, your wylfulnes, the one, or both, you ſée our true dealing, vnderſtanding &amp; plaineſſe. To the reſt. Qui manducat me, &amp; ipſe viuet propter me. How engliſheth he this? Marrie, he that eateth me, he alſo ſhall liue for mee. And what Engliſhe giue we vnto it? he that eateth me, ſhall liue by the meanes of mee. I praye thée (Chriſten Reader) conſider this, and ſée who goeth néereſt vnto the text, yea, who hath the right meaning, he or we. Doe not we liue by the meanes of Chriſt? what? liue we for him? and is not he liuing? fie, why erre ye ſo much by the meanes of the Prepoſition 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ? why ſpeake ye here ſo much of the Accuſatiue caſe? hath it not the ſelfe ſame ſignification ſometimes in the Genitiue? Againe. Qui manducat hunc panem, hee that eateth
                (ſaye we) of this bread. Hee
               
               that eateth (ſayth he) this Bread. What difference, I pray you, is here? what fault is in our trāſlation? yea, it is true (ſayth he himſelfe) to ſaye: he that eateth of thys Breade. Is it true? why iarre you then? why ſéeke you a fault where none is? Alſo Cum accepiſſet Ieſus panem, &amp; gratias egiſſet, fregit, &amp; dedit diſcipulis, &amp; ait: Ieſus
                (ſayth he) hauing taken Bread, &amp; giuen thanks, or bleſſed, brake, and gaue to the Diſciples, &amp; ſayd. Sée (ſo to ſpeak it) how vnſauery, how without ſenſe he tranſlateth. Ieſus (ſay we) tooke Bread, and when he had giuen thankes, he brake it, and gaue it to the Diſciples, and ſayd. How ſayeſt thou (indifferent Reader) who hath here the plaine ſenſe of Chriſt his words plainly vttered, he, or we? but he findeth fault with this worde it: and why? bicauſe it is Chriſt his meaning, and ſo it ouerthroweth all his writing. Let him, for he hath had to doe with his Pronounes and Rules, as late as I, (though yet I teach) let him, I ſay, aſke this queſtion, whom, or what, and he ſhall find that it anſwereth vnto this queſtion. But he is accurſt, which moueth ſuch childiſhe iangling, ſpecially treating of the myſteries

of God. Further. Hoc facite, make
                (ſayth he) this thing. This (ſaye we) doe ye. Doeſt thou (gentle Reader) vnderſtande the Latine? if thou doeſt, without anye doubt thou muſt néedes deteſt his quarelling. But will he compell me to doe as he doth, to fall a conſtruing? facite, doe ye, hoc, this.
                What blame finde you in this? what? ſhall no ſhame moue you? ſhall reaſon condemne you? ſhall no honeſtie worke in you? well what followeth? in meam commemorationem, for
                (ſayth he) the remembrance of me. In (ſaye wée) the remembrance of mee. O Lorde, howe playne this is! be not theſe the Engliſh phraſes? for a mans ſake: in a mans remembrance: and not, in a mans ſake, for a mans remembraunce. Who then giueth the trueſt Engliſh, we or you? Let vs go forwarde. Communicatio ſanguinis Christi, communicatio corporis. Why maymeth he the ſentence? why? bicauſe the Cup and the Breade may not like him. The ſentence is this: Calix benedictionis, cui benedicimus: nonne c
                     •
                  mmunicatio ſanguinis Christi est? &amp; panis, quem frangimus, nonne participatio corporis domini est? The Cup of bleſsing, which wee bleſſe: is it not the partaking of the
               
               
               bloud of Chriſt, and the Breade which we breake, is it not the partaking of the body of Chriſt? What fault woulde he finde here? Marrie, that we Engliſhe it partaking: and haue not they themſelues tranſlated 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , to be participatio? is it not ſo in the old tranſlation? what then can they make of participatio, but partaking? what remayneth? wee being manye, are one Breade. Of (ſayth he) the one Bread: And what ſayeth their owne tranſlation? v
                     •
                  us panis, one Breade.
                Good God! is it not a ſhame for one that would teach, to be blamed in the thing, which he himſelf blameth? I know ye children would here ſay, turpe est doctori. &amp;c. Be theſe ye notes that you would haue remembred? I aſſure you, the remembrance of them is to you no praiſe, to others no profit, to your friends no pleaſure. Alas, what profit is it, eyther vnto the hearer
               Hieron. 
               or reader, for vs to ſweate in labouring, &amp; for others to labour in reprehending? Omit, oh omit fooliſh wrangling, forſake ſelfe will and liking, endeuour to doe good vnto your Countrie, to pleaſe God, giue ouer vnprofitable queſtions, haue regard vnto honeſtie, conſider the truth, take Chriſt

his part, be profitable vnto your ſelues, ſet forth the Lordes name, and labour for the meate which periſheth not. So ſhall you doe, if your writings tend to edefie, and not to ignominie: to conuert, not to peruert: to perſwade vnto holineſſe, not to diſſwade from godlineſſe: to reprehende blindeneſſe, not to reproch righteouſneſſe: to augment deuotion, not to impugne Religion: to redreſſe things being amiſſe, not to carpe that, that true is: to doe well, and not to mainetaine euill. This much concerning their notes to be remembred. Now maye not wée note &amp; reioyce to ſée our trāſlation ſo perfite, as the aduerſaries with all their weapons, may not peerce into, as they may not in any worde (if they deale iuſtlye) reproue? The
               Hieron in Pentateuchū Moyſi. 
               Latine copies (ſayth S. Hierome) are better than the Greeke, and the Greeke better than the Hebrue. So if we ſaye, that the Engliſh copie is better than all three, why ſhould we be reprehended? if we terme it as perfite as any of theſe thrée, ſhould we not therin be allowed? verum haec contra inuidos.
               Ibidem. This I ſpeake againſt thoſe which doe enuie vnto vs the Goſpell of Chriſt, and which are inwardlye grieued, that men ſo

gréedily deſire ye knowledge of Gods word. If they tranſlated the Scriptures, which thing they will not doe, then woulde they haue their doings receyued: but that wée ſhould doe it, that can they in no wiſe abide: as though vertue and vice were not in
               Ibidem. 
               the things, but altered with the author. Haue they not reade the aduiſe of Chilo, whoſe counſayle is, that they egge no man vnto contention, and that they vtter not alwayes their pleaſure, leaſt they happen to heare, that may diſpleaſe them. They ſaye that we haue very many tranſlations. Not ſo many (ſay we) as they haue: maximè cum
               Ibidem. 
               apud Latinos, tot ſint exemplaria, quot codices, ſpecially ſeeing the Latines haue ſo manye copies, as they haue bookes.
                Well, that the Scriptures be tranſlated, it is neceſſarie it is profitable, it is comfortable. Whoſoeuer ſhall call vppon the name of the
               Rom. 10. 
               Lorde, (ſayeth S. Paule) he ſhall be ſafe. And how can they rightlye call vppon his name, if they vnderſtande not what they ſpeake, nor vppon whome they call? is the meaning of the heart inough? No. He that gaue thée a heart, gaue thée alſo a mouth, vſe both. The beliefe of the heart iuſtifieth,
               
               but to knowledge with the mouth, maketh a man ſafe. And how ſhall he acknowledge with the mouth, who in ſteede of one worde vttereth another? who pronounceth ſuch prayers, as in dede are none, ſuch wordes as haue no ſignifications, and ſuch ſentences as be altogither ſenſeleſſe? I ſee the groſſe ignoraunce of times paſt, it might be ſeene, it might be felt, the worlde beareth me witneſſe, it was palpable. And herein I appele vnto ye conſcience of any indifferent Chriſtian, whether the ſimple people had anye vnderſtanding in that which was read in the Churches heretofore? yea, whether the Prieſt himſelfe, whether one of them amongſt twentie, could engliſh you a ſentence of that which they did pronounce? Alas for pittie, alas, our forefathers which might haue ſéene, were depriued of their ſightes, they were led by blind guides into Orcus, into ye darkneſſe of hel, they were kept from true knowledge, and nouſeled in blindneſſe. Fie for ſhame, painted Satannicall pardons were procured them, Gods mercye and remiſſion were reiected, popiſhe papers were bought and ſoulde, deuiſes to releaſe out of Purgatorie were practiſed, no

meanes was left vnſought to withdrawe men from God. Of muddy vnholeſome water then men dranke, and yet golde and ſiluer, great ſummes of monye payde they for the ſame. Vnto ſuch, doth the Prophet Eſay ſpeake: Wherefore doe ye laye out your
               Eſay. 55. 
               monye for the thing which feedeth not, and ſpend your labour about the thyng that ſatiſfieth not? come to the waters all ye that bee thirſtie. Come buy wyne and milke without any monie or monye worth. Why then ſpende we our monie about Popiſh pardons? why about Pelte, Parchment, and paultrie? let vs repent vnfeynedly, and then will our heauenly father forgiue vs, fréelye will hée pardon vs. Who is more to be blamed, the people, or the paſtors, who wéene that Gods gift will be obtained with monye? to proffer monye.Act. 8. is the peruerſe part of Simon Magus, and to receyue the ſame, is not the profeſſion of Peter. But Lord the people were ignorant, and the Prieſtes were couetous, and arrogant. Well, to procéede, how cōmeth fayth? by hearing. What abſolutelye? Nay. By hearing the worde of God, and vnderſtanding the ſame. And how ſhal the vnlearned

vnderſtande the worde of God, ſéeing it is locked from them, and vttered in Latine? why ſhall they not haue it in their owne tongue, that ſo they may heare and vnderſtande, that they maye receyuc faith? why ſhall they not praye in their owne ſpeach? will God heare ſooner (trow ye) the Latin, than he will doe the Iriſh, Welſh, or Engliſh? There is neither ſpeaches nor languages,
               Pſal. 18. 
               but that the voyces of them bee hearde. The Iriſh is aſwell hearde of him as the Latine, the Welſhe as the Greeke, the Engliſhe as the Hebrue. Why then woulde they barre vs from praying in the Engliſh tongue, in the Welſh, in ye Iriſh? why blame they tranſlations? why hinder they the increaſe of knowledge, of grace, of godlineſſe? why? bicauſe the Miniſters of darkeneſſe, will euer by all meanes endeuor to ſhadowe the truth, to ſet vp falſhoode, to caſt a miſt before men, ſo to further their merchandiſe. This made vile Mahomete to eſtabliſh a law, by the which he incurred the paines of death, that woulde reaſon or argue aboute his procedings. This cauſed the Romaine Prelacie to commaunde vnder the paine of excommunication, that no

laye man, were he neuer ſo learned, ſhoulde reaſon, ſpeake or talke aboute the faith of Chriſt. This moued them to appoint the ſeruices to be had and vſed in ſtraunge tongues, and ſo ſtraungely, that the people in ſtéede of ſyncere doctrine, had but doltiſhe ſignes, ſubtile ſilences, lewde mummings, fond meanings, amazed geſtures, and méere trumperie. And hereof, I pray you what folowed? the falling downe vnto ſtockes and ſtones, the creping and knéeling vnto them, the kiſſing and adouring of them. Neyther can here their fayned difference betwéene 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                excuſe them, for theValla. ſignification of both, the meaning and vnderſtanding is all one. Euery pariſh had his peculiar God. Againſt the holy Sainctes, I will not ſpeake, the Sainctes were abuſed. Were it in taking of a iourney, in perill and daunger, I put it vnto your owne conſciences, who were called vpon? was not God in a maner forgotten? and al this happened through ignorance, through the want aſwell of Gods word truely preached, as of the Scriptures to be read in euerye mans language, and receyued. Let all therefore pray and ſpeake in the ſpeach that is vnderſtanded.

               For elſe when thou bleſſeſt with
               1. Corin. 14. 
               the ſpirite, how ſhall he that occupieth the rome of the vnlearned ſay, Amen, at thy thankesgiuing? he vnderſtandeth not what thou ſayeſt, hee is not edified. They further reproue vs for ſinging of Pſalmes, and to ſpeak the thing plainly, they reprehende vs for praiſing of God. O Turkiſh blindeneſſe! O Iewiſh heathenneſſe! O helliſh peruerſeneſſe! Did not Debora and Barak, after the victorie, ſing the ſame daye, and praiſe the Lorde? Heare Kings, Lords, I will ſing and giue prayſe
               Iudg. 5. 
               vnto the Lord God of Iſraell. Who euer blamed them for this? I will ſing (ſayth S. Paule) with the ſpirite, and I will ſing with the minde alſo. Why then will they1. Corin. 14. reprehende our ſinging▪ 
               Be yee (ſayeth he) fulfilled with the ſpirite, ſpeaking amongſt
               Epheſ. 5. Coloſs. 3. 
               your ſelues in Pſalmes, Hymnes and ſpirituall ſongs, ſinging and making melodie vnto the Lorde in your hearts. You heare what the Apoſtle of Chriſt willeth vs to doe. My ſongs (ſayth the ProphetPſalm. 9. 
               Dauid) will I make of thy name, O thou moſt higheſt. Whoſoeuer therefore rebuketh vs for ſinging of Pſalmes, the ſame

doth withſtande the Scriptures and holye ghoſt. But if they themſelues do allow their owne ſingings, why then diſalowe they ours? It is an vniuſt thing (ſayth S. Auguſtine)
               Ad parentiam comit. Arrian. Concil. Toletan. 
               that one ſhould iudge another, and not to be willing to be iudged himſelfe. Yea, they themſelues thus write: Concerning the ſinging of Hymnes, we haue the example of our Sauiour, and of the Apoſtles. Be not therefore any longer obſtinate, the Pſalmes of Dauid we ſing, neuer go about to carpe our ſinging. Many other things there be, which in vs they doe blame. I will touch ouer as manye of them as I remember, and be briefe. I will not be partiall, my penne ſhall defend no vntroth, it ſhall cloke no wickedneſſe. Let Eurybiadas ſhake his ſtaffe, let as manye as thinke it their pleaſure, reprehende me, ſo they bée willing to heare mée. The truth I knowe muſt purchaſe hatred: That made Geminius to be hated of Cleopatra, Praxaſpis of the King Cambyſes, Pantaleon of Lyſimachus, Phocion of the people of Athens, Ariſtippus of Dionyſius. Why were the Apoſtles of Chriſt perſecuted? why were they hated? bicauſe they preached the truth.

Why were a number put to death in the regions of Aphrica? in Antioch and Alexandria? bicauſe they profeſſed the truth. Truly, it is hard to finde one without enimies, who is vnto vice &amp; vntruth a profeſſed enimie. If all then be not my friendes, if all deale not friendly, I force not. The faithful, I truſt, will weygh with indifferencie my worke, they will firſt reade and then iudge. Much contention (ſayth the aduerſaries)An obiection. is amongſt our ſelues, much varietic in opinion, and great diuerſitie in Religion. Some will weare (ſay they) a cornerd cap, ſome will not. What vnitie is amongſt theſe men? This may ſoone be aunſwered.The anſwere. For what is a greater vnitie than altogither (as we doe) to hate blindeneſſe, to forſake ſuperſtition, to renounce Antichriſt, and to embrace true Chriſtianitie? wée all with one minde, doe meane to labour forIohn. 6. the meate which periſheth not, our intent is to ſet forth the doctrine of Chriſt, the ſame which the Apoſtles preached, which he himſelfe pronounced: where can be a greater or a godlier vnitie than this? there is amongſt vs but one fayth, one baptiſme, and oneEpheſ. 4. God. What vnitie then, is to be compared

vnto this: What if one if two or thrée, doe not ſo well like the wearing of a Cap, ſhall therefore for a Cap, the Goſpell of Chriſt be thus carped? Will they not vnderſtande that Theodorus and S. Hierome were not in all things of one minde? Know they not that S. Auguſtine and S. Hierome did once contende? yea, and that Hierome accuſed Auguſtine with theſe termes, ostentare doctrinam, laceſſere, pueriliter certare, with ſuch others? was this no diſcorde? maye it pleaſe them to pervſe their owne doinges, and they ſhall hardly finde any one point, wherin they do not diſagrée. Some of them ſayth, that Chriſt did eate himſelfe, ſome otherwiſe: ſome write one thing, ſome another: ſome alledgeth this, ſome that, ſome ſay they cannot tell what. Is not this a pretie vnitie? and will they néedes condemne vs for a Cap? let them conſider howe amongſt the verye Apoſtles there was ſome diſſenſion, yea, and ſuch as amongſt two of them one was in an error. Quia &amp; Petrus qui
               Aug. lib. de baptiſm. peruul. 
               circuncidebat, ceſsit Paulo veritatem predicanti, for Peter who defended Circumciſion, yelded vnto Paule preaching the truth.
                Came not certaine from Iurie, and taught

the brethren, ſaying: Except you be circumciſed
               Act. 15. 
               after the maner of Moyſes, ye cannot be ſaued. Great diſſenſion, controuerſie, and diſputing was amongſt them, and yet was the Goſpell of Chriſt not withſtanding perfite and good. What? was there not betwene Paule and Barnabas ſuchIbidem. ſharpe diſſenſion, that they parted a ſunder, one from another? you ſée that amongſt the choſen, amongſt the verie twelue, trifling diſſenſion ſometime did happen. Howe then may they require a greater perfection in vs, than in the primatiue Church, than in the Apoſtles of Chriſt? they ſaye further thatAn objection. our Miniſters (which I ſomewhat haue touched before) bée lewde, and that they come into the Church for liuing, and not for loue or zeale vnto Religion. Let themThe anſwere. ſpeake this particularlye of ſome and wée confeſſe it. If they ſay it vniuerſally of all, we denie it. But is their owne profeſſion ſo pure, their monaſteries ſo perfite, that there are none peruerſe therein? be not theſe their owne wordes? Some came to the holye
               Sand. 
               order of Prieſthoode, not for deuotion, but for welth. And ſome went into Monaſteries, rather for eaſe, than for intent
               
               to ſerue God. What further were they? negligent in their offyce, diſſolute in
               Ibidem. 
               their behauiour, ignorant in good learning, ambitious, riche, and couetous. Howe, with what forheades, with what faces can they blame vs, when theſe blames be in themſelues? For our partes we will doe as Philip the father of Alexander was wont to doe. We thanke them for their reprehenſion, we ſhall endeuor thereby to redreſſe that is amiſſe. Yet what ſo euer they alledge againſt vs, let them neuer ſpeake of ignorancie. For none were ſo ignoraunt as they. What was a greater ignorancie, than to vſe ſuch Argumentes as theſe? God is
               Ex decret. 
               my witneſſe, whom I ſerue. &amp;c. therfore the firſt See or ſeate is in the Romaine Church. This is no ignorancie. I ſpeake it in earneſt, I dare boldly auouch, that the verieſt childe in Englande woulde not vſe ſuch reaſoning. Againe. Putrified fleſhe is
               Ex decret. &amp;c. 
               cut with iron: therfore, Peter was chiefe of all the Apoſtles. Here is no putrified argument. Alſo. Conſtantine ſat in a litle
               Hard. 
               lowe Chaire in the middeſt, at the firſt councell of Nice▪ therefore he was not the ſupreme head. And why? what is the

reaſon? Thinke you that the ſupreme
               Ibidem. 
               head of the Church, ſhoulde haue come in laſt, and haue ſitten beneath his ſubiectes? Here is good ſtuffe, if it were prayſed. Doth his comming in laſt barre him from a ſuperioritie? Cōmeth not the Lorde chiefe Iuſtice into Weſtminſter Hall after a hundreth of his inferiors? Commeth not the Prince into the Parliament, after a number of his ſubiectes? he ſate (ſay you) beneath his ſubiectes. With a regarde vnto your eſtimation I ſpeak it, you ſay vntroth: he ſate in the middeſt, which is the higheſt roome, and place of moſt dignitie. As for the lowe Chaire, it was for his eaſe, it was his woont. That did rather encreaſe and confirme, than abaſe and diminiſh his authoritie. Let them therfore neuer brag their learning, neuer boaſt of their knowledge. Their ſkill is ignorancie, their vnderſtanding is méere folly, they ſée no further than another man, for any thing that they can doe, they maye be matched. Let them beware, leaſt it be of them that Gnatho ſayth: Est genus hominum
               In Eunuch. 
               qui eſſe primos ſe omnium rerum volunt, nec ſunt tamen, there is a kinde of men, which thinke themſelues the very chief,
               
               
               and yet they be not ſo. There be, I know, who thinke their owne hoodes, to paſſe all the heads in Chriſtendome, ſome are ſo preciſe, that they will come at no Common prayer, ſome are ſo ſimple, that you ſhall ſcarcely at any time finde them without S. Iohns head in their pockets, ſome are ſuch blinde Prophetes, that they goe about the towne, poaſing and prating in their corners, vpon the Apocalipſe. I am ſorie (when I thinke vpon all) to ſée them in ſuch fooliſh blindeneſſe. And yet theſe be the men, that thinke they haue no fellowes, theſe be they that carie the whole worlde (it is a world to thinke vpon them) in their heades, theſe are they which haue and chalenge the name of learning, but (alas) they are but meanlye learned, their knowledge is ſmall, their iudgement is nothing. Neyther may I here omit to ſpeake ſomewhat of Auguſtine which came into England, and whoſe life, learning and godlineſſe they do ſo much extoll. Of him thus writeth Gregorie vnto Aldibertus then King of Englande, Reuerendiſsimus
               Aldiberto regi Anglorum. 
               frater noster Augustinus, in Monaſterio regulariter doctus, ſacrae ſcripturae ſcientia repletus. Our moſt reuerende brother Auguſtine
               
               
               the Biſhop, being regularlye taught in the Monaſterie, a man right ſkilfull in holy ſcriptues. If this may be credited, he was a man verie learned, if this can not be denied, he is to be credited. Wée will deale vprightlye, let vs conſider his learning▪ Had he ſuch knowledge in holye Scriptures? had he euer reade the firſt Epiſt of S. Paule vnto Timothe? It appeareth no. And yet he was regulariter doctus: then regulariter, was not rightly. And that it may be manifeſt, how he was ignoraunt in the ſcriptures, you muſt note that he was a Biſhop, and yet knew he not what of right appertained vnto the office and dutie of a Biſhop: he knewe not (O ignorancie!) how to vſe his Cleargie. That this was ſo, you ſhall ſee it by his owne wordes vnto Gregorie. Quaero (pater beatiſsime) de Epiſcopis,
               
               Aug. interrog. ad Gregor. 
               qualiter cum ſuis Clericis conuerſentur, I deſire to learne (O moſt bleſſed father) how Biſhops ſhould vſe themſelues towardes their Clergie.
                What is a greater ignorancie, then for a Biſhop to be ignorant in hys calling and profeſſion? no Biſhop was ſkilfull in holye ſcriptures, that was ignorant of his dutie: but Auguſtine was ignorant

of his duetie: therefore he was not ſkilfull in holy Scriptures. What part of this argument could Gregorie nowe aunſwere? what part can anye Gregorian diſproue? Againe he ſayth: opto doceri, an Clerici continere non valentes, poſsint contrahere, I deſire to be taught whether that the Clergie which cannot liue chaſt, may marry.
                This might he haue learned in the Scriptures, if he had before read them. For better it is (ſayth S. Paule) to marrie, than to1. Cor. 7. burne. But hereof I ſhal ſpeake more anon, of Auguſtine I will this much ſaye, that either he had not read the Scriptures, or elſe he had not read and vnderſtanded them: ſo that whether it be the one or the other, he was ignorant, ſuch was their ignorancie. I could rehearſe vp here a number of ſuch like queſtions, that he hath, which, bicauſe they be ouer fooliſh, I will let paſſe. O what a heape could I here bring out of their Canon lawes! O what mountaines of abſurdities could I alledge out of their Legends, out of their owne inuentions and imaginations! But let them paſſe, I truſt to haue more time hereafter. What doe they further condemne in vs? Marrie we contemne (ſayAn obiection.
               
they) faſting, prayers, penance and almes déedes, we haue no regarde (ſo raſhly doe they iudge of vs) vnto any good workes. IfThe anſwere. this were true, it were pitie of our liues. If it be falſe, it is pitie of theirs. Let them remember what Cicero ſayth: if they haue taken any pleaſure by ſpeaking euill of others,in Salust. they maye yet loſe it by hearing their owne euils. As for vs, we be in this of Antiſthenes
               Laert. li. 6. minde. Let them rayle, ſlaunder, backbite and reproch, ſéeing we be not guiltie, we wey not. Firſt touching faſting, IFasting. will prooue that we obſerue it better than euer they haue or doe. The name of faſting is not to be conſidered, the maner and order is diligentlye to be weyed. In Armenia which is a region in Aſia, the people faſt ſo ſtreightly, that therein they paſſe the Pope and all his Prelacſe. And yet is all their faſting not worth one farthing. The Turkes alſo, they faſt, and that moſt ſtraightly, one moneth in euery yeare, and a wéeke. But is it thinke you, true faſting? doth it to their ſoules warde anye thing preuayle? No. I dare boldly affirme it. The maner of faſting in times paſte was peruerſe, it was not right. For what auayleth mée to faſt from

fleſh, if I eate exceſſe of fiſhe, or to faſt from fiſh, if I abounde with daintie and delicate foode? If I only faſt vpon ye Friday, hauing no regard therevnto on the Thurſday, is it to be thought that I do well? if I faſt in the Lent, &amp; feaſt at all times elſe, what helpeth it? if I abſtain from all kind of meates, if I weare on ſackcloth, if I wallow in aſhes, if I would be ſéene therein vnto the worlde, I am but an Hipocrite. When you faſt (ſaythEſay. 58. the holy Prophet Eſay) your luſt remayneth ſtill. Ye faſt to ſtrife and debate. Ye faſt not, that your voice might be heard aboue. Thinke ye that this faſt pleaſeth me? In the reaſt of this Chapiter, doth the lord ſet forth what kind of faſting we ſhould vſe. Togither with our faſting, we muſt releaſe the priſoner, breake the othe of wicked bargains, ſuccour the oppreſſed, and relieue the poore. This faſting is ſo acceptable vnto God, that then if thou calleſt, the Lord
               Ibidem. 
               ſhall anſwere thee: if thou crieſt, he ſhall ſay: here I am. It were to be wiſhed that we would faſt, as Daniel did: and that wee would vnfeynedly ſaye: We haue ſinned,
               Daniel. 
                     •
                  . 
               we haue offended, we haue bene diſobedient and gone backe: yea, we haue departed
               
               from all thy precepts and iudgements. But the Armenians, the Turkes, the Pope, with all his adherents will none of this. The dayes wherein they faſt, muſt be knowen vnto the worlde, from what they faſt muſt be proclaimed, what holineſſe they be of, muſt be euerie where publiſhed, their time of ſadneſſe muſt bée promulgated. What ſayth our Sauiour herevnto? when
               Math. 6. 
               ye faſt (ſayth he) be not ſad, as the Hipocrites are. They will diſfigure their faces, brag of their abſtinence, and boaſt of their faſtinges. Of theſe it is that Chriſt ſayth: Verily I ſaye vnto you, they haue their
               Ibidem. 
               rewarde. But what kinde of faſting ſet we forth? we ſhewe how the fleſh doth rebell againſt the ſpirite: we admoniſh therefore all men to conſider their owne eſtates, and as ſome men be weake of nature, ſome ſick, ſome ſtrong, ſo we wiſh accordingly to kepe vnder and ſubdue the lewde appetites and ſinfull deſires of the fleſh. We will them in their faſting, to ſhunne the rite and trade of Hipocrites. We exhort them to ioyne vnto their faſting, prayer, and almes déedes. And whereas the Popes adherent ſayth: nihil reputatur ieiunaſſe, qui vnum diem non ieiunat; he
               
               Ex 
                     •…
                  ecret.
               
               is in deede accounted not to faſt at all, which faſteth not one whole day. Wee ſay: nihil reputatur iciunaſſe, qui omnes vitae dies non ieiunat, he is in deede accounted not to faſt, which faſteth not all the dayes of his life.
                They require abſtinence for one daye, we during the whole life. Of this faſt S. Hierome thus ſpeaketh: ſint tibi ieiunia
               Hieron. 
               pura &amp; moderata. And what is that? quotidie eſurire, &amp; quotidie prandere, daily to hunger, and daily to dine.
                This is not on Thurſday to feaſt, and vppon the Fridaye to faſt. We ſaye that we ought not to eate, except hunger therevnto mooue vs, and that we ought to riſe from our meat, yet being hungrie. Neither doe we for ciuill policies, adiudge it not neceſſarie that we abſtayne on certaine dayes, and from certaine thinges. But to take it for a Religion, is a mere error, and a verie ſuperſtition. Nowe iudge (gentle Reader) whoſe faſt is purer, whoſe faſt is perfiter, ours or theirs. For prayers,Prayers. I can ſee nothing wherin I may commend them. They prayed they knewe not vnto whom, and in their prayers was conteyned they could not tell what. Alas, if I pray in a1. Cor. 14. tongue that I vnderſtande not, though my

ſpirite prayeth, is not yet my mind without fruite? How falleth it then out, that they will maintaine a prayer for the vnlearned in Latine, for a people that vnderſtandes it not? doe they not by this one thing, bewray their trumperie and deceit? deuiſes they had to keepe men in blindeneſſe, meanes they had to holde men in darkneſſe. They mumbled vp a number of wordes, which by their pronunciation, had neyther ſenſe nor ſignification. They deuided abrode their prayers, ſome to a ſtocke, ſome to a ſtone, ſome vnto this, ſome vnto that, ye leaſt ſome was left vnto God. If with their lippes they prayed Morning &amp; Euening, though ye prayer was altogither vnperfite, yet they thought it inough. What ſhall I ſpeake of the Saraſens? they pray fiue times in euery day, and yet is their prayer wicked and peruerſe. So that we ſée, it is not inough to pray, but we muſte ſpecially conſider vnto whome, and how we ſhould pray. What auayleth (ſaithAuguſtin. S. Auguſtine) the noyſe of thy lippes, if thy heart be dumbe. If thou vnderſtandeſt not thy prayer, if thou prayeſt not aright, what auayleth it? to praye vnto the Sainctes (the remembrance of whom I eſteme)

what helpeth it. They heare not, they vnderſtande not our prayers, to what purpoſe then ſhould we praye vnto them? The
               Ex constitut. 
               Saincts (ſayth the Popes friends) doe not vnderſtand our prayers, except god ſhew it them. O great abſurditie / God muſt go gather togither our prayers, made vnto otuers, he muſt carie and ſhewe them vnto the ſaincts, ſo to be intreated at their hands. O vaine, O miſchieuous, O monſtruous teaching / neuer ſay that you pray vnto the Sainctes, that they ſhould offer your prayers vnto God, they muſt firſt come vnto him by your owne confeſſion. I neede not to ſay that they prayed to be ſéene, for ye whole world did ſée them. It were follie to ſhewe further of their foule errors and abuſes in prayer. Therefore I will ſhewe how we ſhoulde praye, and then we may examine therwith our prayers. That they ſhould be in a tongue which we vnderſtand, by ſainct Paule I haue before proued. Well. When you pray (ſaith Chriſt) you ſhall not bee
               Math. 6. 
               as the Hipocrites are. For they loue to ſtande and praye in the Synagoges, and in the corners of the ſtretes. And why? bicauſe they would be ſeene of men. Verilye
               
               I ſay vnto you they haue their reward. How ſhould we then praye? Marrie, when thou prayeſt, enter into thy chamber and ſhut thy doore to the, and praye to thy father which is in ſecrete, and thy father which is in ſecrete, ſhall rewarde thee openly. Lo here is ſhewed vnto whō we ſhould pray, it is not vnto the Apoſtles, Prophets or Martyrs, it is vnto our father, it is he that will rewarde vs. If we followe therefore the wordes of Chriſt, if we direct vnto him our prayers, who can reprehende vs? if others pray vnto anye other, why may not we blame them? when you pray (ſayth our Sauiour) bable not much, as
               Ibidem. 
               the Heathen doe, for they thinke that they ſhall be heard for their much babling. Be ye not like vnto them. How like vnto them were thoſe, who prayed they knew not what, though they prayed neuer ſo long? Howe vnlike vnto them be we (I ſpeake it to defende the truth) which praye in a ſpeach which we knowe, and that vnto Chriſt▪ Alas for pittie, an infinite number were in times paſt, who had a greater regarde vnto their Beades than vnto their Breaſtes, vnto the number of prayers, than

vnto any ende or purpoſe, vnto the knéeling and knocking, than vnto the knowledging of their ſinnes, and vnto the vſe &amp; cuſtome, than vnto true confeſſion &amp; praier. I wil not trouble thée herein (indifferent Reader) any longer, God hath endued thée with reaſon, vſe his gift, iudge vprightly. ConcerningPenance. penance or repentance, which they apply rather to the bodie, than to the mynde, howe ignorantlye they therein deale, it is manifeſt. Their barefoote abuſes were great, their gadding vnto pilgrimages was horrible, their hearing and bewraying of ſecretes, their preſumption in pardoning of offences, was intollerable. So farre were they from true repentance, that they had pointed it in wordes onelye, outwarde meanes, and in dayes. For did not a thouſand thinke, if they had gadded to this or that Pilgrimage, that then they were perfite? if they faſted certain dayes, thought they not their ſinnes to bée forgiuen? if they had confeſſed their faults vnto the Prieſt, thought they not thēſelues wholy diſcharged? yea, and which is moſt abhominable, bought they not repentaunce with money? was it not ſolde them? had they it not for twentie pence, for ten pence,

for twoo pence? ſome receiued twentie dayes pardon, ſome thirtie, ſome fortie. O filthye merchandiſe! Well. What was further taught by ignoraunt and vnlearned men, touching penance, I neede not to ſay. Onely this I dare auouch, that therein the Pope himſelfe was deceyued, and that he deceyued others, or deceitfully abuſed them. The confeſsion (ſayth Leo) which is firſt offered
               Leo. 
               vnto god, and then vnto the Prieſt, is ſufficient vnto a repenter. What? the only confeſſion, the bare wordes, and no compunction? O how childiſh, how fooliſh, howe falſe is this doctrine! is it inough with our lips to confeſſe our ſinnes? is it ſufficient to tell them vnto the Prieſt? is not repentance, to be ſorie for our ſinnes
               Ambroſ. in ſerm. quaedrageſ. 
               paſt, and afterwards to commit none to be ſorie for? Here is no telling vnto the Prieſt, no ſecret whiſpering, no auricular confeſſion. Poenitentia vera, est dolor, &amp; amaritudo animae, pro malis, quae quiſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   commiſit, vel
               Ibidem. 
               conſenſit. True repentaunce is the griefe of the hart, and bitterneſſe of the ſoule, for ſuch euilles, as one hath eyther committed or conſented vnto.
                This is (ſayth Ambroſe) the true repentance, we ſée what

it is truly to repent, and that we maye the better ſée it, we ſhall herein conſider what S. Auguſtine ſayth. He ſpeaketh of thréeAug. ad Felicianū. kindes of repentaunce, the one in them, which before being heathens, haue a mynde to be baptiſed. The ſecond is after baptiſme, the whole life of one led in prayers, charity, humilitie and ſuch like vertuous &amp; laudable déedes: the thirde is, the repenting for thoſe ſinnes, which through mās frailty we haue howſoeuer committed, as the breaking of any of al the commaundements. We ſée here our whole life ſet forth, and how we ſhould at all times repent. But let vs come vnto the holy Scriptures, vnto whome confeſſed the Prophete Dauid his ſinnes? I will
               Pſalm. 32. 
               knowledge (ſayth he) mine offence, and accuſe my ſelfe vnto the Lord. If we béePſalm. 34. contrite in hart, then is the Lord nye vnto vs, if we be humble in ſpirite, he will helpe vs. Repent (ſayeth our Sauiour) for the
               Math. 3. 4. 
               kingdome of God is at hande. And can we not repent, except we ſhewe it vnto the Prieſt? was not auricular confeſſion condemned, was it not aboliſhed, and that for good cauſes, more than twelue hundred yeres paſt? did not Nectarius the Biſhop,

reprehend &amp; put it down? what? Unto whō I pray you ſhewed Daniel his grief? I turned
               Daniel. 9. 
               me (ſayth he) vnto God the Lorde, I prayed before the Lord my God. What ſhoulde any moue vs therefore with mediators, can we haue any more than one? doe the Scriptures allow any more? There is (ſayth S. Paule) one God, and one meditour
               1▪ 
                  Tim. 2. 
               betwene God and man, which is the man Chriſt Ieſus, who gaue himſelfe a raunſome for all men. S. Paule ſayth, there is but one mediatour: the Pope ſayth, there are more: whome we ſhoulde credit, I referre that (Chriſtian reader) vnto thine owne conſcience. All herevnto that they can obiect, is this: there are of the Doctors (ſaye they) that defende auricular confeſſion. What is this elſe, I pray you, than to ſay, there are men, there are of their own companie that defende it? with a good meaning I ſpeake it, I woulde to God that wée weyed the writings of men as they be, and that wée woulde preferre none before the Prophetes and Apoſtles of Chriſt. I would to God that men would conſider what men were, and what they haue written. Elſe religion ſhall be hindered, great abſurdities

ſhall growe. S. Hierome I knowe was a good man, yet if they will ſtand in all things vnto his iudgement, then will I manifeſtly proue, that ye Pope that now is, is not of theHieron. church of Chriſt. No man (ſayth Hierome) that is ſpotted with any vncleanneſſe, is of the Church of Chriſt. But the Pope is ſpotted with ſome vnclenneſſe: therefore he is not of the Church of Chriſt. Here is a heauie thing, they muſt eyther denie Hierome, or deface the Pope. You ſée what it is, to ſtande ſo much vppon the Doctors. What néedeth manye wordes? the repentance that is allowed by Scripture, the penance that is approued by the Apoſtles, the ſame that is ſet forth by the Propetes, and by Chriſt, the ſame allow we, the ſame we embrace and followe. This if they (as they doe) will reprehende, then carpe they not vs, but the Scriptures of God: Go we thenAlmes. further to ſée their almes. Wherein what they gaue, is to be conſidered, and alſo howe they gaue it, is to be noted. Neyther may we omit, howe they came by the money which they gaue. They came by their riches not rightly, they got it by the meanes of Purgatorie. If then the foundation bée naught,

               nullius boni operis est ſupereaeficium, no good
               
               Gregor. Antiochen. epiſcopo. 
               worke can be builded thereon. Yea, it is not to bee accounted (ſayth Gregorie) almes deedes, if we giue vnto the poore,
               Idem Syagrio epiſ. 
               of that which is vnlawfully gotten. You ſée it then playne, that if they defende not Purgatorye, their almes was no almes, their deedes did nothing auayle them. Why will ſome ſay, haue they not builded houſes of religion, Colleges and Hoſpitalles? and what of that? I will not aunſwere with mine owne wordes, but with the authoritie of Gregorie. Gregorie diſprouing the almes giuen of goods vnlawfully gotten, ſaith thus: vnde etiam certum est, quia &amp; ſi monasteria
               Ibidem. 
               vel xenodochia, vel aliquid aliud, ex pecunia quae pro ſacris ordinibus datur, construatur, non proficit mercedi, whence it may euidentlye appeare, that though Monaſteries, hoſpitalles, or any ſuch like thing be builded with mony giuen for holye orders: ſuch yet doth nothing auayle. But peraduenture
               
               Auguſtin. 
               one will thinke and ſay: there are many Chriſtians which are rich niggardes, and couetous: I ſhall not ſinne, if I take from them, and giue vnto the poore, ſuch thought (ſayeth Auguſtine)
               
               commeth through the ſuggeſtion of the deuill. For be it that he woulde giue all vnto the poore which he had taken, yet doth he rather encreaſe his ſinne, than diminiſh it. If then the Prieſtes tooke monye for Dirges, Trentals, Prayers, Pardons and Maſſes, which euen by their owne law is vnlawfull, and by Gods law is wicked, how maye they ſaye, that they gaue almes, or had (if we iudge indifferently) anye deuotion? but if they liſt, we will leaue the Doctors, and they ſhall haue their fained almes condemned by Scriptures. Unto Abel
               Gen. 4. they know God looked, his offering he receyued: But vnto Cain and his offering, he had no regarde. He looketh not vpon the almes, ſacrifices, and burnt offeringes of the wicked, the Lorde abhorreth them. He that
               Eccle 34. 
               giueth an offering of vnrighteous good, his offering is refuſed. But who doubteth whether the goodes of the Prieſt were vnrighteous, ſéeing they got them by polling the poore, by abuſing Gods worde, by dreames, by ſubtile deuiſes, by ſelling abſolutions, by deceitfull whiſperinges, by hypocriſie, by hereſie? then what followeth, they themſelues may ſée. What ſhould I alledge

more examples? the Lord abhorreth the ſacrifice
               Prouerb. 15. 
               of the vngodly, but the prayer of the righteous is acceptable vnto him. Reade the whole Scriptures, and you ſhall not finde one ſentence to defende ſuch as thinke they giue almes of goods vnlawfully gotten. Let this ſuffice of their counterfaite almes. We for our partes doe ſet forth and teache, that we ought to ſell of our owneLuc. 12. goodes, and giue vnto the poore, that wée ought of our owne ſubſtance to impart vnto the needie. Howe oft doe our Preachers ſpeake hereof vnto the people? how oft doe they ring theſe words of S. Paule into their cares? while wee haue time, let vs doe
               AdGal. 6. 
               good vnto all men, and ſpeciallye vnto them which are of the houſhold of faith. We further exhort men, that they forgiue thoſe who haue offended them. For that is a ſpirituall kinde of almes. Wee perſwade all to get their liuings truly, we admoniſhe the poore, that he labour to his power, wée counſell the rich, that he aide and ſuccor the néedie, we teach all, that they giue their almes not to be ſéene of men, but in ſecrete. Such is our doctrine: howe can they diſpraiſe it? let good Chriſtians iudge, who

followeth therein the Scriptures, we or they: Who ſet forth true prayers, who commende due faſting, who allowe perfite repentance, who beſt thinketh of almes déedes, we or they. This conſidered, let the worlde iudge. They ſaye alſo that we denie one ofAn obiection. the articles of our Crede, vpon which ſlaunder they builde ſharpe and rigorous wordes againſt vs, and all to bring Gods worde in contempt, and to procure vnto the profeſſors thereof the hatred of the people. Let as manyThe anſwere. as can read, pervſe but with indifferencie the bookes which wée haue ſet abroade, and if they find not in the Crede, the twelue articles fullie and truly tranſlated, then let them blame vs and condemne our doings. Likewiſe, if they there finde them, then let them diſcredite our aduerſaries, reprooue their malice, and reprehend their falſhoode. What if we proue that it is they, who haue abuſed the Crede, and that it is the verye Pope which hath denied that Article? AſkePeckham Cantuar. of them, who in our faith, of twelue articles, haue made fourtene? Who ſayth that there be ſeuen articles which concerne the myſterie of the Trinitie, and ſeuen which belong vnto Chriſt his humanitie? who take vpon

them to correct the Apoſtles, they or wée? who ſayth that the Biſhops be not boundeLindewode. to aunſwere vnto the articles of their faith, without deliberation? is not this a moſte heynous ignorancie? this is ſo groſſe, that it can neuer excuſe them (to vſe their owne wordes) à tanto, nec à toto. Pervſe the Crede made by Gregorie, of that name, the firſt Pope of Rome, and you ſhall finde that it is he, who hath left out one of the articles of our Crede, the diſcenſion into hell. Why then blame they vs without cauſe? why accuſe they not him that is guiltie? you ſée their equitie, their iuſtice, their indifferencie. We doe further (ſaye they) contemneAn obiection. good workes, maintaine bare words, defend naked faith, and ſo teach a doctrine that is licencious, lewde and naught. What theyThe anſwere. ſhould ſay, we knowe, but what they dare ſay, all the world maye ſée. Were they not ouer fooliſh, they woulde herein holde their peace. For I pray you, what faith is it, that we teach? preach wée not the verie ſame which S. Paule doth in this wiſe define? Faith (ſayth he) is a ſure confidence of
               Heb. 11. 
               thinges, which are hoped for, and a certaintie of thinges which are not ſeene.
               
How ſay they then, is this to be blamed? as for our workes, what be they, but witneſſes that we are righteous? was it not ſo inIbidem. 
               Abel? And touching iuſtification, the eſtate of the queſtion betwéene the Pope and vs,Iuſtification. is this: he ſayth, that man is made iuſt, not onely by faith, but alſo through the obſeruation of the lawe. We ſay that we are iuſtified by fayth alone, by no merites of ours, by no workes. We ſay that a iuſt man maketh the workes good, and not that the good workes doe make a man iuſt. And as by faith alone without workes we be iuſtified, ſo by grace alone without our deſertes we be ſaued. And what ſayth S. Paule herevntoRom. 3. 
               we ſuppoſe (ſayth he) that a man is iuſtified by fayth without the deedes of the law. Lo, what can be plainer than this? Let them which haue eyes ſee, the wordes be euident, let ſuch as haue heartes vnderſtande. If you (vnto the Pope, not I, but Paule ſayth) be iuſtified by deedes, then
               Rom. 4. 
               haue you wherein to reioyce, but not with God. Goeth not this text verie plainlye to worke? but haue I no power (will one ſaye) to doe any good déede? of thy ſelfe not at all, neyther one. Wilt thou knowe

what is in thy power? it is in thy power, not to doe ſome deede that is euill, and yet is it not in thée to doe that which is good. How ſo (will one ſay) doe not I that which is good, if I doe not the thing which is euill? No. And therefore marke it. For were it ſo, then did the Heathens, and Ethnickes good déedes, which thing, who is he that will graunt? ſhall we ſaye, that the heathens were iuſt men? or that they were vertuous? God forbid. And why? bicauſe they wanted this faith which maketh the worke good,Auguſtin. which iuſtifieth a man. For the whole lyfe of the vnfaythfull (ſayeth Auguſtine) is ſinne. And therefore though we may ſaye that one hauing faith, hath, doth, or if hée haue time, would doe good workes, yet can not we ſay, that all which ſeeme in our eyes to doe well, haue faith. For manye Hipocrites there be, a mans faith we know not, his hart is ſecret, his déedes we ſee. No man
               Ad Iren. (ſayth Ambroſe) ſhall be iuſtified by his workes Some man (ſayth the Pope) ſhall be iuſtified by his workes. The firſt propoſition is true: therfore this laſt, being the contradictorie is falſe. Here they will obiect againſt vs the wordes of S. Iames. But I

would to God that they vnderſtoode them. S. Iames moued with many, who bragged in their fruiteleſſe fayth, is enforced in the prayſe of workes, to ſay thus: as the bodie
               Iam. 2 
               without life is deade, ſo is faith without works. What is this elſe to ſay, than if one haue true faith, it is impoſſible but he (hauing time) ſhould haue good works? What doth he elſe here, but exhort them to ſhewe their fayth by their workes, to ſhewe that they haue true fayth? I will be briefe, and ſo bring them herin to knowledge the truth. Whatſoeuer purifieth the heart, by that aAct. 15. man is iuſtified: but fayth purifieth ye hart: therefore by fayth a man is iuſtified. Howe commeth a man to be iuſtified? Marrie, as S. Auguſtine ſayth) non per ſuas vires, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  per
               De ſpirit▪ &amp; litera. 
               literam ipſius legis, quod fieri non potest, ſed per fidem, not through his owne ſtrength, not through the letter of the law, which can not be but by faith.
                What further teſtimonies thē nede we? why ſhould any arrogātly arrogate vnto himſelf any ſupererogatiō? We knowe (ſayth S. Paule) that a man is
               Gala. 2. 
               not iuſtified by the dedes of the law, but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt. And therfore we haue beleued on Ieſus Chriſt, that wée

might be iuſtified by the ſaith of Chriſt, and not by the dedes of the law, for by the dedes of the lawe, no fleſhe can be iuſtified. Theſe authorities bee ſo full agaynſt the aduerſaries, the places bée ſo playne, that will they, nill they, they muſt yéelde, and therefore in theſe wordes they ſubſcribe: Theſe witneſſes
               Alfonſ. Virueſ. Hiſpanus. 
               doe not onely moue, but alſo ſo farre further, that we muſt confeſſe, that wee haue the remiſsion of our ſinnes, and iuſtification through faith by Chriſt. Yea, and that before faith, there was in vs no good workes, whereby we ſhould deſerue that faith, which is the free gift of God. Now we here ſée that in this they confeſſe ye truth, and that they knowledge the Scriptures, if thē they afterwards deny it, be that to their own daunger, not to our deluding, be it to their owne perill, not to our poyſoning: if they to ſhewe their follye, or to vtter their arrogancie doe paſſe this ſcope, ſéeking by wreſting the ſcriptures, by ſhifts, and ſubtilties to ſhadowe the truth, let that redounde to their falſe dealing, not to diminiſhe out faith, to their iugling not to our vndoing. Let this be vnto thée (Chriſten Reader) a watch worde, wander not wyth

them into the wylderneſſe, ▪ſtaye with the Scriptures at the ſtandarde of truth, let Paule perſwade thée, let not the Pope allure thee, let an Apoſtle of Chriſt▪ inſtruct thee, let not an Apoſtata deceiue thée. This much of iuſtification. The next thing and the laſt which we nowe will defende, is mariage,Mariage. 
               wherein (ſayth S. Auguſtine) if puritie
               De bono vid. 
               bee kept, damnation is not to be feared. Deus maſculum &amp; foeminam, propagandi generis cauſa, nuptiali castitate coniunxit, GOD
               Idem contra aduerſ. legum &amp; prophet. (ſayeth he) coupled man and woman togither, for the increaſe of mankynde, in chaſt wedlock. But what (will one ſaye) néede you to write in ye defence of mariage? is there anye man that maye, or meanes to impugne it? yes. Elſe had not the holye ghoſt ſpoken in Paule, that in the latter1. Tim. 4. times ſome ſhoulde giue héede vnto the ſpirite of errour, and deuiliſh doctrine of them, which ſpeake falſe through hypocriſie, and haue their conſciences marked with an hote yron, forbidding to marrie. We wil therfore bring forth ye teſtimonies of holy ſcripture, and that from the firſt inſtitution of mariage, againſt this deuiliſhe doctrine, againſt theſe ſpirites of error, againſt ſuch as

forbid to marrie. After that Heauen and Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is, were made, after the creation likewiſe of man, the Lord God caſt a ſlumber on Adam and of one of his ribbes he made a woman, and then he ſayde: For this cauſe ſhall a man leaue his father and mother, and
               Gen. 2. 
               cleaue vnto his wyfe, and they ſhall bee one fleſh. Such was the firſt eſtate of mariage, it was inſtituted in Paradyſe. Here is no exception of anye man, no excluding of any woman, no cauſe is here ſhewed, no prohibition is made, but that all men maye marrie. This holye inſtitution was ſo allowed of all, and euery where with ſuch ſinceritie receiued, that if a man ſhould be foūd lying with a woman that had a weddedDeut. 52. huſbande, then they both ſhoulde be put to death. The Prophet Malachie doth bitterly reproue him that putteth awaye or deſpiſethMalach. 6. his wife. Neither in Moyſes nor yet in Malachie can we finde anye one worde to prohibite matrimonie. Reade from the firſt of the Geneſis vnto the laſt of the Apocalipſe, reade the firſt, reade the laſt, you ſhall finde in no place mariage prohibited, or any kinde of perſon, of what calling ſo euer, excluded.

O how godly is the ſtate of mariage ſet forth, and howe to marrie, in Tobias!
               Tob. 6. O that aſwel the maried, as the vnmaried, woulde reade and well weigh it! Conſider chaſte Sara, who though ſhe kept not companyeIbidem. with thoſe that paſſe their time in ſport, yet an huſband conſented ſhe to take, not for hir pleaſure, but in Gods feare. TheHebr. 13. Chamber vndefiled is commendable, the eſtate of mariage is honorable. But amongſt whom? amongſt a ſort, a certaine, a fewe? No. Inter omnes, amongſt all.
                This is ſpokenIbidem. vniuerſallye, not particularlye. If amongſt all, then why forbiddeth the Pope to marie? why defendeth he that deuiliſhe doctrine? why maintaineth he in any, rather fornication, than lawfull coniunction? with what face can he ſet forth, that it is lawfull for one to haue, (loco vxoris (ſi coniux
               Iſidor: de dist: nou: &amp; vet: teſtamen. 
               d
                     •
                  est) concubinam) in the ſteade of a wife (and if he haue no wife) a harlote?
                If the Reader be indifferent, then will hee deale indifferently. For my part, I promiſe before hand, I will not be partiall. I like the vnmaried, I miſlike not the maried, I commend both, if they follow their calling. But yet be he Prieſt or anye other perſon, the1. Cor. 7.
               
fleſh is frayle, if he cannot abſtaine, let him marrie. For it is better to marrie, than to burne, it is better to haue an honeſt wife, than a wicked harlot, it is better to liue in holineſſe than in whoredome. If one marrie onelye to aduoyde fornication, non tamen ideo
               Hieron. 
               nuptiae malae iudicantur, yet is not mariage therefore counted euill.
                Well, when began this deuiliſh doctrine, through which men are prohibited to marrie? had it anye place within ye compaſſe of holy ſcriptures? No. And that the Pope knoweth well ynough. The queſtion was moued in theTripart. hist. Councell of Nice, there they laboured that Prieſtes mariages ſhoulde not be lawfull. But at that time ſtoode vp Panutius the confeſſor, he there expreſſed the Scriptures, he perſwaded the whole Councell, he cauſed them to reuoke their opinion, ſo was it left in euery mans will, mariage was ſtill lawfull. What? was not this a decrée ofConcil. Gangren. their owne? If anye doe this thinke of a maried Prieſt: that he ought not by the meanes of his mariage to miniſter the Communion, and ſo doth therfore miſlike his miniſtring: let him be accurſt. Here is the propoſition at large framed, if

we procéede, I thinke we ſhall proue aſwel the Pope, as thoſe which ouer popiſhly doe take his part, to be accurſt. The argument is made, if we ſaye: that the Pope and his adherentes doe ſo thinke, and for that cauſe miſlike his miniſtering: therefore they bée accurſt. Such is the concluſion. In this argument, if they denie any thing, it muſt bée their owne Propoſition, which was made at a generall Councell, by the aduiſe of ſo manye fathers. Gregorie the Pope and theAnno domini. 1073. ſeauenth of that name, who vſurped vnto himſelfe (as ſome doe write) the authoritie, kept a great ſturre, and laboured earneſtly to forbid the mariage of Prieſtes. But the whole Clergie reſiſted him, in ſo much that the Popes deputie in that behalfe, the Biſſhop of Mentz, had great a doe, much trouble, and no ſmall perill in dealing therein. So odious vnto all was the prohibition of matrimony, ſo vſurped, yea, ſo wicked then, ſéemed that deuiliſh doctrine. But what? whoſe ſonnes were O ſius, Bonifacius, Agapitus,
               Damaſ. Hieron. 
               Theodorus, Siluerius, Deuſdedit, Felix, Gelaſius, with a number more, who were Popes of Rome? were they not all Prieſts children? how then can they excuſe,

but that either their fathers were maried, or elſe that they were filthie fornicators, and verie leſude liuers? Concerning the Apoſtles, ſpecially ſuch as were maried, is it to be thought, thinke you, that they neuer came where their wiues were? the Popes friends ſay, they came not. And how prooue they it? forſooth, bicauſe there is no mention thereof made in the Scriptures. A proper proofe. Bicauſe we reade onelye byMath. 8. name, of Peters mother in law, which laye ſicke in his houſe, therefore ſhall we thinke that ſhe lay ſuccourleſſe? that her daughter was gone? that there was none in the houſe but ſhe? Came not Peters wife, came not his daughter Petronella with him into Rome? hereof I report me vnto their owne hiſtories. S. Paule, when he wrote vnto the Corinthians, was unmaried, but what if afterwards he had a wife? and that I come not with bare iffes, I will alledge mine authoritie: it is Leo the Pope of Rome himſelfe,Leo. 9. contra epistolam Nicet. Abbatis. that ſo ſayth. They muſt eyther blame his holineſſe, or elſe knowledge Paule to haue bene a maried man. This is a harde choyſe. What ſhall I ſpeake of the deuiliſh diuorcementes, and moſt vngodly ſeparations,

vſed in theſe later dayes, euen in leſſe than ſixtene yeares paſt? why were at that time the maried Prieſtes ſeparated from their wiues? bicauſe (ſayth the Pope) their mariage was no mariage, bicauſe they were adulterers. What? bicauſe of their former vowes? O Auguſtine, were thou now liuing, thou wouldeſt laye this hereſie vowne. But though he be dead, doe not his writings yet liue? wrote he not againſt this before he died? yes. And theſe are hisDe bono coniug. ad Iul. wordes. Quidam nubentes post votum aſſerunt adulteros eſſe, ego autem dico vobis, quod grauiter peccant, qui tales diuidunt: There are ſome which ſay that thoſe which marrie after their vow, be adulterers, But I tell you that they offende grieuouſlye which ſeparate ſuch.
                Nowe if they be adulterers, how doe they offende that ſeparate them? But if they do amiſſe which ſeparate them, then be they no adulterers. Whoſoeuer (ſayeth Auguſtine) will ſeparate ſuch, hée doth grieuouſly offende: but Calixtus the Pope doth ſeparate ſuch: therefore he doth grieuouſly offende. I dare boldlye ſaye that they haue nothing herevnto to aunſwere, I am playne, the argument is good, it cannot

be denyed. Montanus est qui docuit nuptias
               Nauclerus. 
               ſolui, it is Montanus the heretike, who firſt taught that mariage ſhoulde be diſſolued, they are Montani, they are of his ſect, they are heretikes that doe it. What other authorities néede we? the thing is playne, what would we more? in the ende let thys one authoritie ſuffice. Si quis docuerit ſacerdotem
               Canon Apoſtolorum. 
               ſub obtent u religionis propriam contemnere vxorem, anathema ſit: if any ſhall teach, that a Prieſt vnder the pretence of Religion, may in any wiſe contemne his own wife, let him be accurſt.
                What? is not this a decrée of their owne ſinode? Non in perpetuum, ſed tempore oblationis, à complexu ſuarum vxorum ſacerdotes abſtineant. Their Latine is ſo embracing, as let them engliſh it that like it. We will (ſayth that ſinode) that henceforth
               Syn. 6. 
               the mariage of ſpirituall men ſhall be in force and good. Thus haue I paſſed ouer, firſt the miſerable eſtate of ſuch as bée in blindeneſſe, then haue I diſproued the vſurped primacie of Rome, I haue battered downe the rotten walles of Purgatorie, I haue defended the right vſe of the Lordes ſupper, I haue proued that there are no faultes in our tranſlation, I haue ſhewed

that the ſeruice and prayer ought to bee in the Engliſhe tongue, I haue declared the true vſe of faſting, prayers, repentance, and almes deedes: I haue ſet forth the right doctrine of iuſtification, I haue defended the honorable eſtate of matrimonie, I haue alſo (as occaſion ſerued) without partialitie anſwered all the obiections of the aduerſaries. All which things as they are briefly done, ſo wiſh I the reader to conſider of them indifferently. I wiſh that odious termes may ceaſe, I deſire that charitie in vs all maye increaſe, It is not inough to terme men heretikes. Remember what Gregorie ſayth:
               Theotist. patrit. 
               there are many euen of the faythfull, which are puffed vp with an ignoraunt zeale: and manye times while they hate others as heretikes: they are the cauſe of hereſies themſelues. Awaye with your excommunications, renounce your curſings, leaue off your threatnings, your weapon is naught, your authoritie is nothing. Haue in memory what S. Hierome ſaith: If any be
               Hieron. in Leuit. 
               put out and ſent forth not through the right iudgement of ſuch as rule in the Church, if he before went not out, that is, if he did nothing whereby he deſerued
               
               to go foorth, it is not hurtfull vnto him at all, though hee ſeeme to be throwen out by the vnright iudgement of men, and ſo it happeneth oftentimes, that he which is caſt foorth, is within: and he that ſeemeth to be within, is without. Weigh this well, and you ſhall eſteeme the bannings of Rome, as they be, you ſhall if you haue eyes, ſée, that you were abuſed, and holden vnder the heauie yoke of a moſt bitter bondage. Shake off therfore ſelfe wil, caſt away ſelfe loue, away with eſtimation, care not for a vaine credite, conſider your eſtate, helpe to redreſſe that is amiſſe, wee ſéeke but the putting awaye of ſhadowes, vanities, errors, blindeneſſe, ſuperſtition, arrogancie, and abuſes. That this may bée done, ioyne handes, helpe forwarde the building of Gods houſe, deſerue well of your countrie: whervnto God exhorteth you, our Princes your moſte gracious Quéene prayeth you, your friendes doe deſire you, your countriemen doe beſéeche you, your natiue ſoyle, your countrye it ſelfe, this floriſhing realme of Englande, doe togither, and moſt earneſtly entreate you.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ A briefe vewe of the erring estate of the Biſhops of Rome.
            
               IF the gates of Hell itMath. 16. ſelfe, if all the power and force of Satan ſhall not preuayle, as in déede they can not, againſt the Church of Chriſt: howe then, and with what face, may ye biſhop of Rome, in whoſe perſon ſinne hath triumphed, and in whoſe religion hell hath reioyced, how may he chalenge himſelfe to be the head, ſupreme and chiefe of that Church, whome the holye ghoſt ruleth and ordereth, whom he directeth vntill the conſummation of the worlde, in the waye of all perfection and truth? if the Biſhop of Rome be the head, in what eſtate (O Lord) are the limmes, what a monſtruous bodie would that be? And not to ſpeak of the firſt heretike Nouatus, qui à quibuſdam
               
               1 Nauclerus. 
               ſibi adherentibus ſactus est Papa, who by certain of his adherents was made Pope:
                did not Marcellinus being biſhop of Rome
               
offer ſacrifice vnto the Idols? did not 2 Silueſter (which is a great fault, for a hyreling flieth, when he ſeeth the Woolfe
               Ioan. 10. 
               come, and forſaketh his ſhepe) Did he not for feare of Maxentius, flie vnto the hil Soracte, which is .xx. myles from Rome? did he not with a few of his Clergie, neither he, nor yet they, regarding their poore ſhéepe, there in a maner hide themſelues? was not 3 Liberius baniſhed, 4 and Foelix choſen Biſhop? was not Foelix diſplaced, and Liberius againe receyued? ſubſcribed he not vnto the hereſie of Arrius? betwéene 5 Damaſus which was accuſed of adulterie, and 6 Vrſicinus, much ſlaughter there was, whiles both of them laboured with force and armes, to enter into the Biſhopricke. Did not 7 Victor offende in cutting (as they ſay) from the vnitie of the Churche, ſo great, and ſo manye Churches? doth not Ireneus reprehende him therfore? the ſtrife was great betweene 8 Bonifacius and 9 Eulalius, they at one time both being choſen biſhops of Rome. To let paſſe 10 Sixtus which was accuſed by Paſſus, did not 11 Anaſtaſius fauor the heretike Achatius? died he not in his error, and miſerably? did

not the Clergie withdraw themſelues from him? 12 Simmachus and 13 Laurentius were both choſen to be Biſhops, great contention was amongſt them. The lyke ſturre was betwéene 14 Bonifacius and 15 Dioſcorus. Yea, did not Bonifacius contrarie vnto all order chooſe 16 Vigilius to be his ſucceſſor? was not 17 Siluerius choſen by ſimonie? was not 18 Pelagius elected contrarye vnto all former cuſtome? what broyle was there in the chooſing of 19 Sergius? what wickednes was wrought betwéene 20 Siſinius and 21 Dioſcorus? 22 Conſtantinus came to be biſhop through ambition. 23 Sabinianus was a very lewd man. As for Pope 24 Ioane, an honeſt woman ſhe was. What was 25 Stephanus? an example of much miſchiefe. What crueltie vſed he towards the deade bodie of 26 Formoſus? what a wolf was 27 Chriſtophorus? what crueltie was in 28 Sergius? it is horrible to heare what wickedneſſe was committed in a maner by twentie &amp; eyght Byſhops of Rome. Did not eyght Biſhops raigne within the ſpace of twelue yeares, who had togither forſaken the ſteps of S. Peter? What was 29 Iohn? a verie

monſter: he was ſlaine (they ſay) in his filthie adulterie. What adoe was betwéene 30 Leo, and 31 Benedictus? Was not 32 Bonifacius a murtherer? Was not 33 Iohn the .xv. a lowd man? as for 34 Iohn the .xvij. his wickeducſſe is horrible. What was 35 Silueſter the ſecond? a Coniurer. In 36 Benedictus (if his friendes write truly) there was great fault. What? were not 37 Benedictus the .ix. 38 Silueſter the .iij. and 39 Gregorie the .vi. at one time Biſhops of Rome? led they not yll lyues? the one played the Biſhop at S. Peters, the ſecond at S. Maries, the third at S. Iohns. 40 Damaſus (if they write the thing as it was) intruded himſelfe into the Biſhoprick with méere force. I will not ſpeake of the warrier 41 Leo, as he was a lewde Capitaine, ſo had he euill lucke. Betwéene 42 Benedictus, and 43 Nicholas, what ſturr
                  •
               , what a doe was kept? the like was betwéene 44 Alexander, and 45 Cadolus. Touching 46 Gregorie, he was excommunicated by the Biſhops of Italie? and why? for ſimonie, manſlaughter, and adulterie. How great was the diſſenſion betweene 47 Guibertus, and 48 Paſchal?
               
               49 Gelaſius offended. 50 Honorius became Biſhop through ambition. 51 Innoſentius, and 52 Anacletus contended for the dignitie. 53 Eugenius forſooke his flocke. So did 54 Paſcall. 55 Adrianus was to blame. Lorde, what debate was betwéene prowde 56 Alexander, &amp; 57 Victor? what ſhould I ſhewe howe one Pope curſed another? 58 Innocentius dydde lewdly. 59 Caliſtus was a verie theefe. I will omit dreaming 60 Iohn, who promiſing vnto himſelfe a long life, was ſodenlye ſlain with the fall of a chamber. What was 61 Nicholas, and 62 Bonifacius? the one was vnthankful and cruell. They both preferred rather their friends, than ſuch as feared God. 63 Clemens was choſen by ſimonie. What diſſenſion was betwéene him and 64 Vrbanus? 65 Bonifacius was yong and vnlearned. With him did 66 Alexander contende. What? were not 67 Innocentius, 68 Benedictus, and 69 Gregorie, all three at one time, clayming and chalencing the dignitie? Was not 70 Iohn a verie foole? did not 71 Martinus, and 72 Clemens contend at one time? Did not 73 Eugenius
               
forſake his flocke? was not 74 Foelix a wicked and an ambicious man? was not 75 Paulus lewde? was not 76 Xyſtus vnprofitable? I recken not vp one name twiſe, if I haue declared that many of one name were lewde, they were ſo, they were ſundrie men, and ſundrie Biſhops. Well, is here all that were wicked biſhops of Rome? No. For a great number beſides there were, but touching theſe, they are tried in a maner without ſtudy by their owne authorities to be ſuch. And ſhall theſe be the head of Chriſt his Church? O Chriſt, I commit the iudgement thereof to ſuch as doe knowledge thée, to ſuch as in déede be Chriſtians, to ſuch as vſe ſome indifferency.
            
               
                  P:
                  
                     Vae miſero mihi, mea nunc facinora
                  
                  
                     Aperiuntur, clam quae ſperaui fore.
                  
                  My hidden faults be vttered now, a wretch, alas, I am:
                  By Pride and fonde deſire to raigne, to paſsing ſhame I cam.
               
            
            Pſalm. 1.
            Beatus est vir, qui non abijt in concilio impiorum:
            Happie is the man that followeth not the way of the wicked.
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               YOV haue ſeene here what a number of lewde men, were Biſhops of Rome. And yet ſome peraduenture will ſaye, that their liues and wickedneſſe can ſtand in no force, to barre them of their dignitie, of their vſurped title of primacie. No can? Can any bee a member of Chriſt his Church, who is ſo voyde of the holye Ghoſt, that hee hath in him dwelling the right riches of Satan, ſimonie, I meane, ambition, pride, murther, and crueltie? if ſuch then maye not bee called a member, howe ſhall wee tearme him, how ſhall he claime to be the chief, the head, the ſupreme? Iudge indifferentlye, for ſo you ſhall profite your ſelues, and eaſily be eaſed from the clog of bondage, wherewith▪agaynſt all reaſon, good authoritie, and Scripture, you haue bene tyed. Farewell, and iudge of me as theſe my writings deſerue.
            
            Examini, &amp; iudicio verae eccleſiae, quae fidelium, ſanctorum, &amp; electorum ſocietas est, &amp; communio, constans fide, ſpe, dilectione, ac ſpiritu Christi, hoc ego opuſculum humiliter ac demiſsè ſubijcio:
            I doe with humilitie, and lowlineſſe ſubmit this ſmall worke, to the iudgement and examination of the true Church, which is the ſociety, and communion of the faithfull, holy, and elected, the ſame being knowen, and agreeing in fayth, hope, charitie, and the ſpirite of Chriſt.
            Appollodorus.
            Good men vſe fewe wordes: neytherStobaeus ſerm. 34. needeth the truth much babling.
         
         
            
            ¶ A Copie of a Letter, ſent by the Emperor vnto the Pope
            
               ¶ Fredericke by the grace of God, theNauclerus. Romaine Emperour, alwayes imperiall, 
               vnto Adrian biſhop of the catholike Church, ſendeth greeting, willing him to ſtand vnto all thoſe things, which Chriſt began to doe, and to teache.
            
            
               THe law of Iuſtice, doth reſtore vnto euery mā, that vvhich is his ovvne, neyther doe vvee anye iniurie vnto our parentes, vnto vvhome vvithin this our Realme, vve doe exhibite due honor, and from vvhō as our progenitors, vve haue receiued

the dignity of our realm and crovvne. Is it founde that Silueſter Byshop of Rome in the time of Conſtantine the Emperor, had any Kingly poſſeſſion, or authoritie? for thorovv the permiſſion of the Emperors godlye affection, the liberty of the church vvas graunted, peace vvas reſtored, &amp; what Princelye thing ſoeuer, your popedome is knovvne to haue, the ſame you do hold through the liberalitie of Princes. Therfore vvhen vve vvrite vnto the Bishop of Rome, by good right and of olde, vve doe vvrite firſt our ovvne name, and that he ſo

doe, as the rule of iuſtice is, vvriting vnto vs, vve graunt. Pervſe the chronicles, and if you haue neglected the thing you reade, that vvhich vvee alledge, you shall finde it there. But of thoſe vvhich belong vnto God by adoption, and doe holde anye Kingly thing of vs, vvhy maye not vve demaund homage, and othe due vnto a prince? ſeeing the appointer of vs, and of you, receyuing nothing of a man that is a king, but yeelding euerie good thing vnto al, payd for himſelfe and for Peter, the tribute due vnto Caeſar, giuing therby vnto you example to do

the like, and ſo he teacheth you ſaying: learne of mee, for I am meeke, and humble in heart. VVherefore let ſuch eyther reſtore vnto vs our princelye poſſeſſions, or if they adiudge theſe things profitable, let them pay vnto God that vvhich is Gods, and vnto Caeſar that vvhich is his. Alſo vnto your Cardinals, the Churches be shut, the cities are not open, and that bicauſe vvee ſee them not to bee preachers, but ſpoylers, not peacemakers, but mony catchers, not the redreſſers of the vvorld, but the vnſatiable ſcrapers of gold. Yet vvhen vvee shall perceyue

them to be ſuch as the churche requireth, vvhen they proue to be peacemakers, vvhē they vvill giue light vnto their countrie, and vvhen they vvill aſſiſt the cauſe of the humble in equitie, then loe shall vvee ayde them vvith neceſſary ſtypendes, and ſafecōducts. But you haue not a little offended agaynſt humility, vvhich ought to be the keper of your vertues &amp; meeknes, vvhen you ſet forth vnto ſecular perſons ſuch queſtions as are very ſmall furtherance vnto religion. VVherefore, let your fatherhoode foreſee, vvhiles you moue thinges vvhich vvee adiudge

vnvvorthy, leaſt you bee an offence vnto thoſe, vvho as vnto a latevvard shoure, are deſirous to yeelde their eares vnto your mouth. For vve can not, but aunſvvere the things vvee heare, vvhen vvee ſee the deteſtable beaſt of Pryde, to haue crept, euen vnto the ſeate of Peter. And in thus doing vve doe alvvaies vvel prouide for the peace of the Church. Fare you alvvays vvell.
            FINIS.
         
         
            Seene and allowed according to the order appointed. Anno. 1568.
         
      
   

