
   
      
         
            Somewhat vvritten by occasion of three sunnes seene at Tregnie in Cornewall, the 22. of December last. With other memorable occurents in other places.
            Everard, John, 1575?-1650?
         
         
            
               1622
            
         
         Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00462
            STC 10599
            ESTC S114622
            99849847
            99849847
            15019
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00462)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15019)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 788:10)
         
         
            
               
                  Somewhat vvritten by occasion of three sunnes seene at Tregnie in Cornewall, the 22. of December last. With other memorable occurents in other places.
                  Everard, John, 1575?-1650?
               
               [4], 20 p.   
               
                  Imprinted [by N. Okes and T. Walkley],
                  [London] :
                  M.DC.XXII. [1622]
               
               
                  By John Everard.
                  Printers' names from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Marvelous, The --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-05
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2003-05
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Somewhat:
VVRITTEN BY OCCASION
OF THREE SVNNES
seene at Tregnie in Cornewall,
the 22. of December last. WITH
Other memorable Occurrents
in other places.
            
            Imprinted M.DC.XXII.
         
         
            
            
            Beleeuing Reader:
            
               YOu are saluted, by (I thinke)
you know not whom: I would
be sorrie you should; for a
beggerly generation of mercenarie
liers haue drawen an
ineuitable suspition vpon
the reporters of all truths in
this kinde: But as it is your vertue that hath exempted
you from the number of ordinarie censurers,
so let your charitie excuse mee from being
of the number of ordinary writers.
            The Seller of these presents entreated I would
speake a word or two to you in his name: but I
thought it most necessarie to be mine owne aduocate;
lest, if it should happen this concealement
to be found out, (as
Multa fidem promissa leuant.
The largest promises come from the longest
tongues) I might be exposed to the tyrannous rage
of them, who by my expence of two houres, are anticipated
in their proiect, importing at least two
peeces, and twentie or thirtie coppies. Beleeue
this therefore, as y would beleeue any thing that

               
                  •
               s not de fide, that what I haue written, is the
truth as I beleeue; and I thinke I haue iust reason
to beleeue it, for it hath beene confirmed by
the voluntarie oathes of many, the truth of which
none can doubt of, but such as vse themselues to
sweare vntruths, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . I confesse,
I heard not of it (how could I?) till it was too
late to see it; but if I had, there motenesse of the
place would peraduenture haue perswaded me (according
to the prouerbe) rather to content my selfe
with beleeuing it, than to goe to see it. But that I
may not be too light in so graue and waightie a
matter, I will conclude with that common excuse,
You haue it as good cheape as I, and cheaper;
for it cost me thrice as much time in writing, as it
will doe you in reading; yet the losse of that is the
greatest hazard you can make, in so poore an adventure.
         
      
      
         
            
            Somewhat:
            Written by occasion of the report
of three Sunnes seene at Tregnie in
Cornewall, the 22. of December last.
            
               WHen I consider the
present state of
things, with how
strong and powerfull
delusions the
great enemie of
mankinde goeth about
to ouerspread
the whole Church, labouring
by all meanes, that the flouds of vntruths,
belched from his wide throat, might
carrie away that Glorius woman cloathed
with the Sunne, crowned with Starres, and
treading vpon the Moone; I haue iust reason,

with all humilitie and becomming reuerence,
to take into consideration that gracious
instruction, which his Maiestie, in his Meditations
vpon the 20. chapter of the Reuelation,
raiseth and enforceth by occasion of the
Deuils loosing, by the rising of Antechrist,
namely, that Whereas the iustice of God, in respect
of mans falling wilfully from the truth (as
Paul saith) iustly did send to the world the great
Abuser with efficacie of lies; as well to tyrrannize
spiritually ouer the conscience by heresie, as
corporally ouer their bodies, by the ciuill sword.
Therefore we must feare to fall from the truth reuealed,
and professed by vs, that we may be free
from the like punishment. For assuredly, though
I dare not say, that euerie falling away from
the truth, with what circumstances soeuer it
may be qualified, is a sinne against the Holy
Ghost; yet I thinke I shall not stray from the
iudgement of the most and best Diuines, if I
affirme that the sinne against the Holy Ghost
is neuer committed, but there must necessarily
concurre a wilfull and obstinate deniall
of a knowen and inwardly confessed truth,
or A withholding and keeping of it backe in vnrighteousnesse.
            
            Which sinne of sinnes, because lamentable
experience teacheth euery man whose eies
are open, that it is stealing vpon vs: The
Lord in mercy hath not only frequently protested

against it in his word, denouncing
iudgement without mercie, to all them who
shall dip hands or hearts in the guilt thereof:
But also by signes and wonders, by strange
and vncouth prodigies, hee giues warning
that he folds not his hands together like a
sluggard, loth to pull them out of his bosome,
or like such a God as the wicked faine
(because they would faine haue it so;) seeth
not, neither vnderstandeth any thing. But
that his eyes behold all the wickednsse that
is done vpon all the earth; as if hee had no
more than one particular person to attend
vnto: and that hee is whetting his sword,
and making ready his quiuer full of arrowes
against impenitent sinners, and such as will
not feare his name.
            His aboundant mercies indeed will not
suffer his iustice to take vengeance of sinners,
before hee haue (according to his owne Law,
in case of Israels making warre against other
cities and nations) offered peace and reconciliation
vnto vs: But for all that, when he
seeth his loue despised, his long-suffering contemned,
and all his couenants trodden vnder
foot; Hee is at length accustomed to shew
himselfe the Lord of his promise; and that all
his former patience proceeded not (as it fals
out many times with men) from feare of opposition,
or the greatnes of the delinquents;

but only and meerely from his immeasurable
loue, which hateth nothing that he hath
made, and is so loth to punish, that if all had
continued in their primitiue order and created
puritie, the verie Word had neuer beene
named, nor had the thing it selfe euer beene
created.
            I should not haue spoken so much, nor
with so much confidence vpon this occasion,
had I not knowen that the same God who
alwayes hath written the texts of these predictions
with his owne hand, hath likewise
ordinarily giuen this Interpretation of them;
and withall that admonitions, whether in
season, or out of season, cannot hurt; It being
a happy occasion, whatsoeuer by any
meanes draweth vs to amendment of life.
Let not Philosophie wrangle with me for neglecting
her, when I am employed in the seruice
of our common Mistresse, Diuinitie; I
willingly giue vnto her the knowledge of
immediate and second causes; but shee her
selfe hath taught me, to giue vnto God the
ordering and disposing of Nature, and a constant
influence into the least effects, which
she produceth.
            It were an hard matter for me to say, that
Parelij (so the Gracians call an appearance of
many Sunnes together;) and Paraselenai
(which are when it seemes that many Moons

appeare at the same time) are caused by the
reflexion of the beames of those Planets, from
an equally condensed cloud interposed betweene
them and vs; as Rainebowes are (by
the refraction of their beames) from an hollow,
waterish, or dewie cloud, vnequally condensed
or thickned (which is the cause of the
varietie of colours) as is plaine by a three
square glasse, which representeth more colours,
or at least more liuely than are in the
Rainebow. Of which who so are desirous to
see more, may read Seneca largely discoursing
thereof, in the first booke of his Naturall
questions, the 11, 12, 13 chapters, and diuers
others.
            And was there none among the many
thousands of Israel, that could satisfie the amazed
multitude, concerning the causes of
thunder and raine; but that they must fall to
such a deiection vpon the sight and hearing
of them, as is expressed, 2 Sam. 12. 18, 19.
Certainly, the vnsafe curiositie of mankinde,
when it hath gained credit in some things,
scornes to acknowledge his ignorance in any
thing, as we see by them, who being beleeued,
or thought to speake probably in the disclosing
of the causes of Snowes, Dewes, and
Raines, haue from thence assumed vnto themselues
to bee able to giue naturall reasons of
the Deluge, of raining of Bloud, Milke, Wheat,

Stones, Woll, Iron, and such like, whereof many
histories written by credible Authors doe
make mention. How much better and safer
is it for vs, though these things bee granted
possible by Nature; yet since it cannot bee
denied that they are not ordinary in Nature,
to take the aduantage of them for the preuenting
of that wrath, which, whether it be prognosticated
by these ostents, or no, will surely
be reuealed from Heauen vpon vs, when the
measure of our iniquitie shall be filled.
            Were wee at that point with God, where
we should be; we needed not to be affraid at
the signes of Heauen; simply and positiuely
wee need not feare them; as though they
could hurt vs, without the impulsion of his
hand which made Heauen and earth; or as if,
though hee had commanded his Army Royall
of all creatures to march against vs, and the
Heauens themselues to fight against vs, as
against Sisera, yet it were not in his power,
vpon our repentance to sound the retreat, and
make them all retire, and againe to renew the
league betweene the stones in the street and vs.
But when wee see the signes the same, and
know our sinnes the same, God will, without
doubt, rather accept of an humble feare,
that trembles at the hand, that shakes the
rod, than of a presumptuous and vnreasonable
confidence, that he who punished the periury

of Troy, should loue the lies of Rome, (to vse
S. Augustines words) or to vse the phrase of
Scripture, that hee who punished Iudah for
three transgressions should winke at Israel for
the multitude of her rebellions.
            When there were three Sunnes seene at
Rome, which by little and little did all grow
into one bodie, It was answered by the Colledge
of Southsayers, that it portended the
vniting of the three parts of the world,
(which then were only knowen) Asia, Africke,
and Europe into one Empire; Grande spectaculum
(saith mine Author) &amp; quod grandia
significauit; This was in the yeare after the
worlds Creation 3923. and after the building
of Rome, 711. about 41. yeeres before the incarnation
of our blessed Sauiour, M. Aemilius
Lepidus, and L. Munat. Plancus being
Consuls. The successe proued it true; for
shortly after, so much of the world, as was
either knowen, or worth conquering, acknowledged
the Soueraigntie of the Romane
Empire: Had these lately seene three Sunnes,
(whereof I am to speake) appeared but twentie
yeares sooner, wee might peraduenture
haue hoped they had but foretold, what wee
haue since found true, The happie vnion of
these three mightie Kingdomes, in our blessed
Peace-maker: But seeing they come too
late to foretell it; let vs hope they come not

too late to confirme it vnto him and his posteritie,
as long as the Sunne and Moone endure.
            Notwithstanding, euen at that time, there
were some that on the other side did stiffely
maintaine, that these three Sunnes could not
presage any good vnto the Romane Empire;
but rather a diuision and distraction of that
Imperiall power, as indeed it proued true;
for the yeare following began the Triumvirate
of Lepidus, Caesar, and Antonie, which
made way vnto Caesars Monarchy, the period
of the Romanes libertie, and the beginning of
the decay of their greatnesse. And certainly,
it hath not been often seene or obserued, that
such Prodigies haue beene fore-runners of any
good vnto the place where they were seene:
howsoeuer, vpon a turning of the hearts of
the people vnto God, without question, God
can turne the threatned plagues vpon the
heads of the Heathen, and such as haue not
knowen his name.
            The like apparition of three Sunnes and so
many Moones which happened in Italy in the
yeare of Grace 1164. was thought to presage
the great dissension of the Princes Electors in
chusing the Emperor, and the schisme which
lately followed in the See of Rome. And
what the three Sunnes which three yeeres after
were seene in Poland might seeme to fore-shew,

the Chronicles of that Countrey doe
sufficiently demonstrate.
            And to passe by many other; those three
Sunnes which were seene at Magdeburge vpon
the 21. of March 1551. about seuen of the
clocke in the morning, accompanied with seuen
Rainebowes: and the three Moones appearing
the night of the same day: the three
Sunnes appearing againe in the same place,
the 21. of Aprill following, accompanied only
with three Rainebowes, might probably bee
thought to fore-shew the straight siege,
which (by the command of Charles the fifth)
Maurice the Duke of Saxony▪
                and Albert Marquisse
of Brandenburge laid against that Citie
by the space of fifteene moneths; whereby
the Citizens were driuen to great extremities,
though afterward they made their peace
vpon good conditions.
            What should I speake of the three Sunnes
appearing ouer Vinarium a little Citie in Doringia
the tenth of Februarie 1555. Or of the
like in France before the battell of S. Quintins?
Because according to the Spanish prouerbe,
Da lueng as vias, lueng as mentiras; From farre
countreyes, foule lies: I will come close to
our owne times, and our owne home; nay, as
our Sauiour sayd, Regnum Dei est intra vos,
The Kingdome of God is within you: So
will I say, It is not beyond the seas, that thou

shouldest say, who shall goe ouer the sea for vs,
and bring it to vs, and cause vs to heare it, that
we may doe it? But the thing is very neere vnto
thee, yea euen before thine eyes to see it: And
therefore the more inexcusable are they, that
either will not beleeue it, or reflect no more
vpon it, than if they beleeued it not: Howsoeuer,
thus it was.
            Vpon Saturday the 22. of December last,
at Tregnie, a market-towne in Cornewall, well
knowen to Cornish men, in respect of his
neerenesse to Falmouth, about eleuen of the
clocke before noone, the Sunne being vnder a
cloud, it was obserued that from the bodie
of the Sunne there proceeded a more scattered
and dispersed light than was wont, as if
the bodie of the Planet had beene greater
than it had formerly beene: But this being
attributed only to the brightnesse of some
cloud betweene him and vs, little notice was
taken thereof, till about a quarter of an
houre after, this diffused light seemed to concenter,
as it were, and gather to three heads,
which in short space appeared to the view of
the beholders to be three Sunnes, of equall
lustre and brightnesse, and placed as neere as
could bee ghessed in a Triangle; all shining
cleere, and scattering their beames with so
great light, as that the eye of man could not
fasten vpon any one of them more than another.

And yet which is remarkable, the
light of the day was not increased, otherwise
than in a cleare Suune-shine day, at
such time of the yeere it is accustomed to
be; so that they who were in their houses
could not, by reason of any such symptome,
take notice thereof.
            This strange and extraordinarie sight
made the people (who were assembled
there in great number that day, as being
market-day) to forsake the streets and other
places, where any thing might interpose
it selfe betweene it and them, and to
betake themselues into open places,
whence they might the better discerne it;
where they, with feare and amazement, did
a great while gaze vpon it, not being able
to discerne which was the naturall Sunne,
and which his aduentitious and Mimicke
reflections. They that were of better iudgement,
ghessed them to be distant one from
the other about two degrees, or two and
one third.
            Nor were they only that were at Tregnie
partakers of this fearefull and preternaturall
oftent; but as many as dwelt within
foure or fiue miles round about were, or
might haue beene eye-witnesses vnto it;
peraduenture, not in so plaine and conspicuous

a manner, because the cloud was not
either of height or largenesse: but it is auouched
by some Gentle-men of good
worth and qualitie, that being that day
foure miles from Tregnie into the landwards,
about twelue of the clocke, they did
plainly see and discerne it.
            At the same time, and so long as these
three Sunnes appeared, there were seene in
the aire, iust opposite vnto them, and almost
due North three Rainebowes, two of
which were the one within the other, but
the third, against the course of nature, had
his center in the Zenith of that place, and
was almost contiguous vnto the other
two, hauing his backe almost ioyned to
theirs. That Rainebowes should appeare,
we know it to be no wonder, and that so
many Rainebowes as Sunnes, wee beleeue it
possible; but that any Rainebow should
bee greater than a semi-circle, or haue his
center aboue our Horizon, is a thing
which elder times haue not beene so well
acquainted withall.
            These Sunnes and these Rainebowes continued
in the manner abouesayd, from a
quarter of an houre after eleuen, vntill
halfe an houre after twelue; at what time
the light of the Sunnes, beginning by little

and little to grow weake, the thicke cloud
got the victory ouer them, and tooke them
away from the eyes of the beholders; and
at the same time also the Rainebowes their
attendants vanished, and left the day a little
troubled, (but much more the mindes
of the people;) yet about one of the
clocke, or soone after, the Sunne brake out
againe in his wonted and accustomed manner,
and the rest of the day was cleere and
free from clouds.
            Since this strange apparition, namely
vpon the tenth of Ianuary last, there happened
in Deuonshire, yet not farre from the
other place, being on the edge of Cornewall,
another wonder, which did as much
affright the eares of men, as this did their
eyes: For in the afternoone of that day,
being the Thursday after Twelfth day, there
were heard in the aire, vnusuall cracks or
claps of thunder, resembling in all points,
the sound of many Drums together, sometimes
beating Charges, sometimes Retreats,
sometimes Marches, and all other
points of warre: which after it had continued
a good time, it seemed that the same
thunder did most liuely expresse many volleyes
of Small-shot, and afterward the like
volleyes of Ordnance, with so great, and yet

so distinct noyse, that many of them who
dwelt neere the sea, went toward the shore
to see what it might meane, as verily supposing
there had beene some great sea-fight
neere vpon that Coast. These seuerall
fearefull noyses were againe and againe renewed
in the same order, till at length,
with an horrible and extraordinary cracke
of thunder, there fell in a ground of one
Robert Pierce, where there were diuers
worke-men planting apple-trees, (which
ground lay neere the house of one Master
George Chidley) a thunder-bolt, if I may so
call it, being a stone of three foot and an
halfe in length, of two foot and an halfe in
bredth, and one foot and an halfe in thicknesse,
the substance whereof was in hardnesse
and colour not much vnlike a flint, as
appeares by many peeces thereof, which
are shewed vp and downe by many credible
and honest Gentle-men, who with their
own hands brake them off from the maine
stone. After the fall of this stone, which
with the weight thereof was cleane buried
in the ground aboue a yard deepe, the
thunder ceased, and people began as much
to wonder at that which they now saw, as
they had lately done at that, which with so
much feare &amp; amazement they had heard.
            
               
You haue now heard a simple, plaine, and
short narration, of some great and fearefull
wonders, what the causes of them
were, we all may peraduenture coniecture,
though none of vs can demonstratiuely
shew: What the effects of them shall be, I
scarse thinke any man can coniecture; sure
I am, no man can certainly tell; It is neither
safe nor good for vs to be Polimanticks,
but in all patience and prepared resolution,
to submit our selues to the will of
God, we may well determine it the dutie
of euerie Christian.
            I had here put an end of this short and
vnpollisht discourse; but that being in
hand with it, there was brought vnto me a
briefe (but excellent) and simple narration
of the massacres committed by Papists, vpon
the persons of more than 400. men, women,
and children, of the Reformed Religion,
in the Valletelline (a place in the Grisons
Countrey among the Rhaetian Alps, of good
importance for many respects) both in Tirano,
Teglio, Sundrio, and Malenco, and diuers
other places of the Countrey neere
adioyning: the ninth, tenth, and eleuenth
of Iuly 1620. wherein, though I confesse
there be such examples of crueltie and inhumanitie,
as a Turke, Infidell, Iew, or any

other sauing a Papist, would blush and
tremble at; yet not conciding so aptly
with this purpose, I will for the present omit
them, and (which agreeth better with
this argument) only touch vpon such Prodigies,
as the Author of that Treatise, who
as an eye-witnesse reporteth what he saw
and felt,
Et quorum pars magna fuit.
affirmeth, to haue beene seene and heard
in those places, both before the Massacre
and after; and thus they are word for
word with the Italian coppie.
            
               
                  
                     
                        Signes and Prodigies which happened before
the massacre in Valletelline, the ninth of
Iuly 1620. after the old account.
                        THere being thorow out all the Valletelline,
Guards or Sentinels set in euerie
Steeple or Bell-fray; together
with certaine others appointed to seuerall
places, to giue warning by fire, to the intent
that all the Valley, as well by the fires,
as by the correspondence of the sounds of
the bels, might be in an instant aduertized
to take armes for their owne defence, against
such enemies as pretended to assault
the sayd Valley: About the Calends of

May, 1620. In Sondrio, the Sentinels that
were (as aforesaid) appointed to watch in
the steeple made relation, that in the night
they heard in the Church of S. Geruais, a
great murmuring and noyse, as if it had
beene of many people, earnestly reasoning
and disputing about some great and serious
matter: and that from the bodie of
the Church, there shone vp into the steeple
a great light; whereupon the Sentinels,
lighting their candles, went to goe downe
into the Church, to see what the matter
was: But as they were going downe, their
light was blowne out, and they going
backe to light it againe, it was againe
blowne out, with greater noyse and violence
than before. And suddenly, the
light which was in the Church ceased, and
the waits 
                              •
                           f the clocke fell downe, and the
bell was tolled ten times, as it is accustomed
to be done, in case of giuing an Allarme,
which thing was heard of many.
                        In Tirano likewise there were some such
blowes giuen to the greater bell; In so
much, that the Magistrate sent suddenly to
see what it meant: but hee found that it
was not done by any man: And as the
messengers returned home from the steeple,
the bell of the Palace it selfe was heard

to ring; and they of the place wondring
and looking diligently what it might bee,
they saw descending by the rope of the
said bell, somewhat in the likenesse and
proportion of a Cat.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        Signes and prodigies heard and seene in Valletelline,
after the horrible massacre: As it
is affirmed by diuers credible persons, that
haue since come from thence, and were
there, at, and aft
                              •
                           r the massacre.
                        IN the Churches which were formerly
vsed by them of the Reformed Religion,
and principally in Teglio and Tirano,
there hath many times been heard a voice
to cry, Woe, woè vnto you, vengeance from
God for the bloud of Innocents.
                        
                        There hath also beene often heard the
bell of the Church of them of the Reformed
Religion in Tirano, to toll without any
mans hands, at the time that the Sermon
was wont to be; and in the same Church
there hath beene often heard a voyce, as if
it had beene of the reuerend Antonio Basso,
late Minister of that place, and there massacred,
when hee was wont to preach. Of
this Antonio Basso it is likewise reported,
that being slaine be the rebellious and seditious

Papists; they not satisfied with this,
cut off his head, and carried it into the
Church, and set it vpon the Pulpit, where
hee had beene accustomed formerly to
preach, and then mocking, cryed vnto
him, Cala a basso, Basso, cala a basso, c'hai predicato
assai, &amp;c. that is, Come downe, Basso,
come downe, thou hast preached long enough.
                        
                        In Sondrio there was seene comming
downe from the Mountaines, as it had been,
an host of armed men; whereupon many
going out of Sondrio, were about to runne
away to saue themselues by flight; but in
the end this apparition vanished like a
cloud; yet it hath beene so great a cause of
feare among the people, that many haue
forsaken their dwellings in the Valley, for
feare of the diuine punishment.
                     
                  
               
            
            To make an end now where I began, at
home and amongst our selues; though this
briefe narration was not by me intended,
as a pious fraud, to make men afraid where
there is no cause of feare; yet howsoeuer the
truth of it bee, (for I will not engage my
faith vnto you for the certaintie of it,
though in my selfe I bee well enough satisfied
thereof, in respect of the credit of such
as reported it, as hauing beene eye-witnesses:)
Let others please themselues in

the perswasion, that, 
                  Nihil est in istis terribile
nisi ipse timor,
                (as Seneca speakes) There
is nothing fearefull in these things, but the
feare it selfe: yet the wise will bee admonished
by euery occasion, 
                  Et quod aequum est
sperare, &amp; ad id quod iniquissimum est se compararet;
               
both (as wee say in honest English)
to hope the best, and to prouide for the
worst; which how to doe, as becommeth
Christians, no man hath better taught vs,
nor in fewer words, than our Soueraigne
himselfe in the end of his Meditation vpon
1 Chron. 15. vers. 25, 26, 27, 28, 29. First,
by constant remaining in the puritie of the
truth, which is our most certaine couenant of
saluation, in the only merit of our Sauiou
                     •
                  :
And next, by reforming our defiled liues, a
                     •
                  
becomes regenerate Christians, to the great
glory of our God, the vtter defacing of our aduersaries,
the wicked, and our vnspeakable
comfort, both here and
also her
                     •
                  after.
            
            Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

