
   
      
         
            A briefe chronicle, where in are described shortlye the originall, and the successiue estate of the Romaine weale publique the alteratyon and chaunge of sondrye offices in the same: the order and successyon of the kinges, consuls and emperoures therof, together wyth sondry gestes &amp; actes of many famous princes and valiaunt captaines, from the first foundatyon of the city of Rome, vnto the. M.C. and. xix. yeare there of consequently: ryght plesant and profitable to be red, marked and folowed of all men. Collected and gathered first by Eutropius, and Englished by Nicolas Havvard, studiente of Thauies In. Anno. 1564.
            Breviarium ab urbe condita. English
            Eutropius, 4th cent.
         
         
            
               1564
            
         
         Approx. 290 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 137 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00446
            STC 10579
            ESTC S101794
            99837597
            99837597
            1929
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00446)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1929)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 223:06)
         
         
            
               
                  A briefe chronicle, where in are described shortlye the originall, and the successiue estate of the Romaine weale publique the alteratyon and chaunge of sondrye offices in the same: the order and successyon of the kinges, consuls and emperoures therof, together wyth sondry gestes &amp; actes of many famous princes and valiaunt captaines, from the first foundatyon of the city of Rome, vnto the. M.C. and. xix. yeare there of consequently: ryght plesant and profitable to be red, marked and folowed of all men. Collected and gathered first by Eutropius, and Englished by Nicolas Havvard, studiente of Thauies In. Anno. 1564.
                  Breviarium ab urbe condita. English
                  Eutropius, 4th cent.
                  Haward, Nicholas.
               
               [11], 96 [i.e. 113], 107-129, 122-126 leaves   
               
                  In Fletestrete, near to Saynt Dunstons Churche, by Thomas Marshe,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  [1564]]
               
               
                  Translation of: Breviarium ab urbe condita.
                  Publication place and printer's name from colophon.
                  Leaf 96 misnumbered 113.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Newberry Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Rome --  History --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-07
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-07
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ A briefe Chronicle, where in are deſcribed ſhortlye the Originall, and the ſucceſſiue eſtate of the Romaine weale publique, the alteratyon and chaunge of ſondrye Offices in the ſame: the order and ſucceſſyon of the Kinges, Conſuls and Emperoures therof, together wyth ſondry geſtes &amp; actes of many famous Princes and valiaunt Captaines, from the firſt foundatyon of the City of Rome, vnto the. M. C. and .xix. yeare there of conſequently: ryght pleſant and profitable to be red, marked and folowed of all men.
            Collected and gathered firſt by Eutropius, and Engliſhed by Nicolas Havvard, ſtudiente of Thauies In.
            
               Anno. 1564.
            
               Fais ton deuoyr,
            
            
               Selon ton pouuoyr.
            
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHTE worſhipful and excellent yong Gentle man, mayſter Henry Compton Eſquier, his faythful and dailye Orator Nicholas Hawarde, wiſheth longe helth, with encreſe and affluence of all worſhyp.
            
               ALthough of long tyme ſithe, (ryghte worſhipfull,) I had in my hart profeſſed a greate zeale and reuerens towardes you, whiche from time to time, day by day. I ſought menes to ſignifye to your good maſterſhip, yet there neuer wanted ſom occaſion which might wthold me from yt mi ſaid intēt &amp; purpoſe.

For why, waying mine own caſe and condition of fortune, and cō
               ſidering your worthye eſtate and degree of worſhip, I did alwaies with my ſelf yet hitherto, diſalow my former attempted enterpryſe. But on the other ſide, ſetting before mine eyes, and beholding the exceding great gentlenes, whych from your very youthe ye haue aboundauntly towards all men in all places declared, (whiche you as inheritaunce claime from your auncetors,) and alſo the no ſmall fauoure and zeale which you continually haue profeſſed towardes learning, where in I my ſelfe am able not a litle to teſtify how you haue profyted. For omitting here, your diligent ſtudye employed at Oxford, whyche is to diuers not vnknowen, I my ſelfe doo well remember that longe tyme before that, ye had attayned the Laten

tounge, (and that well nyghe in your verye childhoode:) whyche thinges being ſo, I was emboldned,) preſuming vpō your paſſing great fauour) now at laſte wyth certaine confidence to declare to your goodneſſe my pore harte to you long time ſince wholy addicted: vpon which ſnre affiaunce ſo repoſed in your worſhyp, I haue here preſented vnto you this ſmal treatiſe. Vppon the fyniſhinge wherof, I haue employed for the moſt part ſuche vacant time as I had, (not defraudinge my other ſtudies,) bering in memorye therample and ſaying of Plinie, who thoughte all that his time to be loſt, whyche hee beſtowed not at booke. Nothinge doubtynge but your lenity, being ſuche as it is, ye wil gratefullye with fauoure accept the ſame, and ſo enboulden

my baſhfulneſſe in this behalf, as did Octauius Auguſtus to one, who whē he had finiſhed a boke, (like as I this,) which he would haue deliuered to Auguſtus, and was come in preſence before him, with trembling hand, he did both profer and withdraw yt hys boke again, which thing Auguſtus apperceiuing, accepted the gift, and reprehending ye baſhful and timorouſneſſe of the geuer, ſaid: what thinckeſt thou, yt thou doeſt nowe erhibite a mite to an Elephante? Such clemency and familiaritye was there in y• mighty Emperor. The like of which, alſo promiſeth this your worſhips countenance: which hath now exiled, and clean put to flight, the cloudy miſtes of my former baſhfulneſſe: So that now wythout feare or drawinge backe, I haue heare preferred to your worſhip theſe my ſymple trauailes,

which I choſe amonge others to employ vpō this author, as chefe for ſondry cauſes. Thone is, for the ſubſtaunce and matter, which he writeth of, whiche as it is of time and cōtinuans antique, ſo is it of all men far before other hiſtories to be embraced &amp; deſired to be knowen. An other cauſe is, for ye where diuers Hiſtoriographers aſwell Grekes as Latines haue vttred to their poſteritye in wryting therploits &amp; feats atcheued by the Romaines, as well in peace, as in warre, yet among thē al, are there few which in ſo good order haue placed the ſame: and as for breuitye and compendiouſneſſe, I am aſſured noone there are, but of force muſte graunte hym the pryce. And all be it that as Tullye ſayeth, and as experyence teacheth vs, dyuers there are endued wyth very excellente

wittes by nature, whyche wittes are aided by preceptes and perfyted by experience, which experiēs is alone the maiſtres of al things, who inſtructeth and teacheth vs how to demene and gouern both our ſelues and our doings by iudging thynges preſent, and calling to memory thynges whyche are paſt: yet amonge all thoſe whych are indued with ſuche pregnante wittes by nature, eche one hathe not attained ſuche perfectyon in learning, that they of them ſelues are able inough to attain fully to the knowledge and vnderſtandinge of the geſtes and factes of dyuers moſte victorious nations &amp; peoples: the examples of whom may aminate and encourage others to endeuour and laboure to purchaſe and attaine ſuche lyke fame and praiſe, as thoſe others haue done, ſo muche as nothynge

canne more. The knowledge of which examples, had to diuers euen to thys daye lien hidde, bene vnknown, and vnattained vnto, had not that theyr default in learning, bene aided by ſome others, able to further thē in this behalfe. Which imperfection of many, diuers here to fore vnderſtandyng, (to whome the talent of lernynge hath ben more aboūdantly graū
               ted,) endeuoringe them ſelues, to remedy &amp; ſupply yt want &amp; defalt in others, haue to theyr great cō
               mendation and praiſe immortall, by their induſtry and paines taking in tranſlating diuers Hiſtories and Chronicles, (as in theyr myndes beſt ſeemed to them) out of ſondry languages into this out mother tounge, made perfect and healed that maime, which otherwyſe the want of knowledge of

the ſame Hiſtoryes for wante of learninge, had bred to dyuers of thys our country. By whiche example of theirs, I was the more hardye to attempte thys enterpryſe, as one ryghte gladde if by oughte that lyeth in me, (whyche eaſelye I confeſſe, and graunte how ſlender it is,) any one myght take eyther furtheraunce or pleaſure. Which my ſimple trauayles I haue preſumed to exhibyte to your worſhip, not for any the cauſes afore ſayde, (knowinge that you are in ſuche ſtudies, as ye are alſo in all other good ſcyences verye exactlye ſeene and parfecte,) but onelye to ſignifye, and as argumente to teſtifye the good wyl whyche to my power my poore harte vnto your worſhyppe, as of duetye doothe owe: whyche then at lengthe ſhall be fullye ſatiſfyed,

and adiudged it ſelfe verye happye, when it ſhall ſeeme to haue doone anye thynge whyche maye appeare acceptable to your good maſterſhyppe.
            And all thoughe it maye be graunted that experyence of thinges maye bee attayned wythout learnynge, yet is experyence purchaſed by learnynge, to be preferred before that other ſo muche as quietneſſe is more to be regarded then trouble.
            For as Phillip de Comines a Frenche wryter affyrmeth: a manne ſhall ſee more experyence in three monethes, by readynge of bookes, then twentye menne ſhall in Proceſſe of tyme, the one of theym lyuynge after the other: Where by a manne ſhall allſo vnderſtande the vſage and

and faſhions of ſondrye realmes and countries, aſwell in peace as in time of warre, the ordinaunces and lawes of ſondry nations, the wayes and meanes by whyche they haue enlarged their kyngedoms, and the cauſes of the decay of the ſame, and howe thoſe ruinous Empires haue bene agayne reſtored, and haue recouered their former eſtates. All which things like as they are plentifullye, ſo are they chefly contained in ye deſcription of good hiſtories, whiche hiſtoryes of Cicero are moſt worthelye called the wytneſſe bearers of time, the lyghtes of veritye, the liues of memorye, the regentes of life, and the ambaſſadors of antiquity: by whiche we maye learne how to bear all manner fortune, as well aduerſe as proſperous, whyche ſhall adminiſter vnto vs the very true and certain experyence

of thinges, ſo that wee maye certainly know howe to attayne and purchaſe praiſe and fame immortall: whiche with greate encreaſe and long contynuaunce of the ſame, God of hys infinite goodneſſe, graunt to your worſhip for euer. From Thauies Inne the xxii. day of Iune.
            
               Your faythful and daily Orator
Nicholas Haward.
            
         
         
            
            ¶ To the Reader.
            
               COnſidering wyth my ſelfe (gentl
                  •
                reader) wyth how infinite payne and labo
                  •
                diuers here tofore me
                  •
                of moſt excellent wits and of paſſyng knowledge haue compyle
                  •
                theyr bookes, &amp; wyth what heede and cyrcumſpectneſſe they haue examined and perfited theyr ſayde trauayles and wyth what fear and warineſſe they haue publyſhed the ſame, (nor that wythoute good cauſe why.) For there by they exponed themſelues, theyr name and fame to no ſmal daungers and haſardes. Namelye to the vewe iudgement, and report of all men. For which cauſes (me ſemes) I haue taken vpon mee a
                  •
                thys preſent a hard enterpriſe: A burden ouer heauy for theſe ſlender ſhoulders to ſuſtayne, who haue at length ſhewed my ſelfe ſo hardy as to publiſhe abrode thys ſmall booke to the ſkanning and trying of ſo many touch ſtones. Amonge whome like as thoſe other mooſt famous men haue doubted to credit theyr wrytrnges (dreading how they might eſkape the cloſe carpinge of diuers ſlaunderous and p
                  •
               ruers detractors:) ſo I who now haue wayed the ſafe ankers) of cloſeneſſe, and hoyſted vp the ſayles of fearfulneſſe, to receiue the blaſtes of rumours and reports, haue launched forth thys ſymple ſhip to take his waye amyd the ſapde gulfes, where as nothing elſſe is to be looked for, but captayne perdition, wythoute

the ſinguler lenitye of the beneuolente Readers doo ſupplye the Pylottes ſteade to ſafe conducte hym alonge thoſe daungers, and defende hym from thoſe violente and ſurgynge waues whych ſhall ſ
                  •
               ke to ouerwhelm him: who ſhoulde well haue contented my ſelfe to haue gratified only that excellent yong (gentleman my ſinguler good maſter, maſter Cōpton (whome I here name for hys worthines ſake) wythoute hazardynge my ſelfe by farther daungers, to ſeeke ſuche aduentutes as myght betide.
            Neuertheleſſe, ſith it hath pleaſed hym to wyll me to attempte thys enterpryſe (whoſe requeſt to againe ſaye, or commaundement to wythſtand in no caſe I might,) I haue the boldlyer, vnder the banner of his Protectyon aduenturxed to endaunger theeſe firſte fruites of my trauayles. Where in I doo as yet adiudge my ſelfe to ſtande in farre more ſafetye and leſſe daunger, then thoſe others doo, of whome I made mertyon before: for that if in theyr doinges any errour might haue happely bene eſpiſed, it could hardelye haue beene wyncked at, eyther for theyr ſinguler knowledge and learnynge where in they did excell, or for theyr tipeneſſe of iudgemente, whyche well nigh paſſed all mennes credite.
            But as for me, if oughte there bee doprehended in thys ſmall treatyſe, worthy reprehenſion (as one ſubmittynge my ſelfe to the iudgemente of others,) yet I deſire of thee gentle Reader, graunte of fauourable ſkannynge: whyche I truſte eaſelye wythout repinynge, I ſhall at thy handes obtayne: For

that what ſo euer hathe chaunced to eſcape me, maye bee adſcribed to my imperfectneſſe, (whome I yelde to thy iudgement) or imputed to youthe, and ſo the eaſlyer be remytted, or at leaſte diſſymuled. Neyther thyncke I that I coulde be ſo incircumſpecte in ſit placynge of wordes, ne ſo exacte a tranſlatoure, that I coulde (thoughe mooſte I couetie it) pleaſe and ſatiſfye of eache one hys fantalye: Suffiſeth it me therefore, if amonge ſuche a companye, ſome: amonge ſo many, ſhall ſeeme all together not to reiect theſe my ſimple trauayles.
            And to the end I may indue the frendlye Reader to conceyue the better opynyon of thys ſmall booke, I ſhall ſhewe to thee what profitte and commoditye is annexed to the ſame, and howe muche doothe auayle the readynge of good hyſtoryes. And then haue I to ſpeake to the obloquy of certayn perſones, whyche ſeeme greatly to diſalowe the tranſlatynge of Hiſtoriographers, and other good authoures, foorthe of diuers languages into hys owne mother tounge: where by they detracte and depriue the trauaylers in thoſe affayres of theyr prayſe whych moſte worthely oughte to enſue theyr ſayde laboures.
            And as touchynge the firſt poynt, which is to expreſſe the profitte and commodytye whyche doo enſue the reuoluynge and often peruſyng of hyſtoryes, and to declare of what force and effecte they are to quycken and encourage others to atcheue the lyke, the ſaying of worthye Themiſtocles ſeemeth to proue ſuffycyently: who in hys firſt youthful yeres

gaue hym ſelfe wholye to followe luſte and ſenſualitye, regardynge nothing but ryotouſneſſe and ſatiſfying hys fantaſy, but ſo ſoone as Melciades obtained oportunity, and wan throughe hys proweſſe and manhode greate victoryes of Themiſtocles, who alwaye before had bene drowned in folly (and wantonneſſe) conferrynge the life of Milciades with that of hys, dyd in ſhorte ſpace ſo aultare himſelfe, as if he had neuer bene anye ſuche kynde of perſone. Where at diuers muche meruaylyng, demaunded of hym the cauſe of that hys ſo ſodayne chaunge. To whome Themiſtocles aunſweared that the victoryes and conqueſtes of Melciades would not permit hym anye longer to ſleepe or ſlumber.
            Of ſuche force and efficacy, and the examples of others, that of one who to fore was a member ſkante worthye to lyue in a common welth, the example of that other made a valyaunt and mooſte victoryous conqueroure. Whyche thynges beinge ſo. who dothe dou
                  •
               e howe requiſite and neceſſarye hiſtoryes are: in whyche are contayned ſuche noumber of notable examples, of men more famous farre then was Melciades. Whyche hiſtories like as they are to be had in eſtimation, and greatly to be regarded for the worthineſſe of them, whoſe actes they recount, ſo are they highlye to be hadde in pryce, for that by mean of them onlye thoſe geſtes of ſuche menne are ſo ryfe in memory, that in manner they doo yet lyue, and ſeme preſentlye to put them in practyſe. For why, hath not Virgill that deuyne Poet by his worthye verſes geuen Troye ſuche

perpetuitye, that it doothe as yet ſeeme to burne, wyth an inextinguible fire: whych elſſe doubtleſſe had peryſhed together with the fadynge of that conſnmynge flame.
            Who ſhoulde nowe haue bene able to recite the worthye proweſſe of famous Achilles, if Homere hadde not crowned the ſame wyth eternitye? And that whych is more, (that I maye ſaye wyth mightye Alexander,) what hadde it auayled that worthy Achilles? what hadde it auauntaged dyuers other valyaunte menne to haue aduentured theym ſelues to ſuche daungers, to haue attempted ſo hearde enierpryſes, Finallye to haue declared theym ſelues alwayes inuincible, if ſuche theyr victoryes, that theyr manhoode, thoſe theyr excellen
                  •
               e vertues ſhoulde haue beene wyth theym ouer whelmed in the earthe, and peariſhed in that ſmall coffen? Whyche doubtleſſe hadde hapned, if the worthyneſſe of wryters hadde not chalenged and deliuered them from that lamentable deſtiny. Where hadde the renowne, the fame and glory of the Romaines. the Grecians, the Macedonians, the Perſians and dyuers other victoryous Natyons beene nowe become? They hadde certeſſe ben quite worne oute by antiquity, decaied by deſcent of ages, and geuen place to tyme, if the fame of them ſo deceaſſed, had not ben ſhrowded in the pardurable ſeereclothes of famous wryters, (as Lyuius, Plutarche, Curtius wyth others whome I here paſſe ouer,) and theyr ſayde factes farſed wyth the pure poulders of the wrytinges, and monumentes of

ſuch men as thoſe wer moſte ſoueraign preſeruatiues agaynſte ſuche putrefactyons.
            And thus muche as touchynge the commodious and well nyghe requiſite knowledge of Hiſtoryes. Nowe reſteth it to ſpeke a worde or two to ſatiſfye the miſlikynge of certayne perſonnes, wyth ſuche as haue trauayled in tranſlatinge dyuers authoures foorthe of other languages into thys our mother tonnge. For the aucthoriſinge and defence whereof, (me ſeemes) the woordes of the famous Oratoure Apollonius doothe auayle not a lyttle. Who commyng by chaunce into the ſchole where Tullye was, beynge but a chylde as yer, and apperceiuing his for wardneſſe in lernynge, and hys naturall inclinatyon to the ſame, ſayde: Truelye Cicero I commende thee, and bewail grestly the chaunce and caſe of the Grecians. For why, ful wel that worthy Orator apperceiued that Tully ſhould in proceſſe of time bereft ye Gretians of theyr exacineſſe in all ſciences (where in they myghte worthely at thoſe daies claim ſingularitye to thē ſelues) and communicate the ſame with y• Romains and others. Which thyng though Culli did not as an interpretor of any, yet did he it ſo, that he ſemed as an erpoſitor to mani. For looke what abſoluteneſſe or perfection anye of the Grecians, the Hebricians or any other ſtraunge nations hadde throughe their laboure and trauayle attayned vnto in leatnynge, and lefte wrytten in theyr languages, for the prolytte and behoufe of theyr country menne, whyche was neyther commodious or profytable to bee knowen. All that hathe

he by hys induſtry left moſt eloquentlye publiſhed in the Laten tounge, a language more rife and familiare then thoſe from whence he deſumed them. And lyke as manye had failed of that knowledge whych they nowe haue aſpyred vnto, had not Tully txoden forth vnto them ſuche eaſy pathes, tyghte had there bene no fewe among vs in thys our region, which had not as yet attayned vnto any vnderſtandyng of ſo many hiſtories, and wyth them ſō
               drye other thynges worthye to be knoweu, had not the diligence of Tranſlators, &amp; theyr paynes imployed in that behalf, remoued and cleared the thycke miſtes of theyr ignorans, where by it may appeare that ſuche as buſye them ſelues for the furtheraunce and commodity of others, are not only worthy to be void of reprehenſyon vndepryued of theyr wel deſerued prayſe, but are alſo to bee encouraged to perſeuer in thoſe theyr well doinges. And where as ſome theyr be whyche obtecte that throughe theſe tranſlatyons, the affectynge and deſyre of the attaynynge of the Greeke, Latyne, Italian and other tounges dooth decay, and is the leſſe ſoughte after, who ſeeth not howe friuolous and vaine that theyr ſaying is. For as it is very abſonant that anye one who hath the perfect vſe of corn &amp; grain, and taſted the pleſauntneſſe there of, woulde refuſe the ſame to be fed wyth Acornes, ſo is it no leſſe diſſonant to ſay, that anye man hauing ones taſted the pleaſaunte puritye of the Greke and Latine tounges, woulde (for ſaking the ſame,) fal to the barbarouſneſſe (in reſpect) of thys oure Englyſhe tounge. But

lyke as Ce
                  •
               es hathe not ſo indifferently delt wyth all men, to inſtruct and ſhewe them the vſe of corne, for whyche ſome muſte of force content them ſelues to be fed wyth Acornes. So for that eche man hathe not attayned the knowledge of thoſe languages, in whych notwythſtandinge many thinges are worthy to be knowen, ſome muſt neades contente themſelues to wade only in the troubled ſtreames of Tranſlators: for that they are not able to attayne to the well ſpryng it ſelfe: with tranſlations if they had any manner waye ſounded to the decay or hinderaunce of learnynge or knowledge. Doubtleſſe in thoſe ſo manye ſo famous menne, whyche haue ſuſtayned ſo greate paynes in that behalfe greate folly and ouerſight might haue bene imputed that they wold haue buſied them ſelues ſo many yeres about ſo harmfull ſtudies. But ſo muche are the mindes of men nowe depraued with malyce, and puffed vp wyth pride, that they can not only broke the wel meanyng mindes of any, but narowly examine and try the errours of others. Being ſure in the meane time that they them ſelues wyll attempt no ſuch enterpriſe: (warely preuentyng what men myght fortune to report by them,) worthy to be reſembled to Eſopes dogge. Who lying in the Oxes racke, would not onlye not eat the haye hym ſelf, neyet wold permyt the Oxe, who 
                  •
               ould gladlye haue fed. Whoſe ouer hedeful 
                  •
               eades I paſſe ouer wythout regarde, deſyringe thee gentle Reader, (for whoſe cauſe I haue ſuſtained theſe laboures, and endaungered my name) to conceiue of thys my rude

enterpryſe accordingly. Exhortynge thee alſo earn eſtly, daily to reunlue and peruſe the nomber of good hiſtories whych eyther are all redye, or ſhall here after happen to be publyſhed for thy behoufe. Wyſhinge thou mayſte lyke as Themiſtocles,) pexceyue there by ſuche fru
                  •
               e and profit, that thou mayſte be animated by readinge thoſe worthye actes and exployees of others, to purchaſe and gayne lyke praiſe and fame to them, whome thoſe theyr factes commend to thee.
            ☞ Farewell 
from my chamber in Cha
                     •…
                  es Inne.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
            ¶ The firſt booke of the Breuiary of EVTROPLVS.
            
            
               THe Romain Empire, which was at the fyrſt beginnīg Romulushis birth and parentage. Rhea Siluia mother to Romulus. therof, of all other the ſmaleſt, and in proces of time dyd become the moſte Virgins veſtals wet thei whiche minyſtred to Veſta daughter to Saturn, who ſe order was to keepe themſelues virgis vntil. 30. yere of age, and thē they wer licē
                  ſed to marye. The foundation of Rome laid, the. 729. yere beforethe birth of chriſt and the. 3101. yere after the creatiō of the world, &amp; continued in that ſtate aboute a 1300. yeares. ample, and ſurmounted in circuit all other Empires, that any man could euer remember, was founded by Romulus. Who (as it was ſuppoſed) was the ſonne of a birgin Veſtale, be gotten by Mars, &amp; borne at one birthe with his brother Remus. This Romulus when he had oflong time accuſtomed amonge the ſhepherdes to pray and ſpoyle abrode. At laſt being of the age of .xviii. yeres, he layed the ſyte of a ſmall citye, in the hyl Pallatinus, the eleuenth day of May, in the xxxiii. yere after that the plaies called Dlimpici

were firſte begon. And after the deſtruction of the city of Troy: according to the ſuſt computation of al wryters, the. CCC. lxxxx. &amp; fourth yeare. When he hadde builte this Citye, whiche after to hys owne name he called Rome, he wroughte Rome named theſe feates wellnigh as they follow. Fyrſt he gathered together into his city a great nōber of ſuch as wer Rome inhabited. borderers ther about to furniſhe this citi. Amōg whō he choſe anC. of ſuch as wer moſte anctent of yeres, after whoſe aduiſe he minded to order hys affaires: whome he for that thei wer ſo aged, called Senators. Then for yt bothe he and his people were as yet Senatoures in Rome. The cauſe whye playes wer fyrſt inuented in Rome. deſtitute of wiues, vppon a tyme he did inuent certaine plais and ſhewes within the Citye, requeſtinge ſuche as were inhabitauntes neare aboute Rome, to come and ſee thoſe playes. At which time the Romains by force berefte them their daughters &amp; maidens.

Wher vppon, warre was proclaimed againſte the Romaynes for that rape: in which battail, Romulus War againſt the Romains ſubdued the Ceninenſes, the Antennates, the Cruſtumyes, the Fidenates, the Veientines and the Sabines: which people enuironed the city of Rome. Within a while after, ther aroſe ſodenly a great tempeſt, in whiche Romulus vaniſhed in a tē
                  peſt forthe of Caprea medow, wher he toke the vew of hys ſouldy oures. Romulus being abrode, vaniſhed away ſo that he was not after ſeene: Where vppon when hee coulde not be founde, his people ſuppoſing that he was raught vp to the ſkies, canoniſed him in the .xxxvii. yeare of hys raign. Romulus canonyſed. After ye, the ſenators bare rule by ye ſpace of .v. dais, during which time of their raign, was accompliſhed Interregn
                     •
                  , the time betwene ye deth of one kynge, and the treate on of another. Numa Pompilius the .ii. kynge a Sabine borne. one whole yere. Thē was Numa Pō
               pilius created kinge: who during the hole time of his raign, waged no batel, &amp; yet was he no leſſe profitable to the city of Rome thē Romulus was. For whye he eſtabliſhedde Lawes,

and framed to good order the conditions No warrs in Rome, which chaunced vnt two tymes more in Rome, one after the firſt Carthaginiā battail, ones in Auguſtus Ceſares time. The yere deuided into xii monethes. Numa, hys raigne. of the people of Rome, which for that they had ben ſo long accuſtomed to battailes, wer now iudged as robbers and rude people. This Numa deuided the yere into .xii. monethes, being before but a confuſed noumber of daies, and a thinge not able to be accompted. And innumerable rites and ceremonies, and temples founded he beſides at Rome. And deceaſed by ſickenes in the. 43. yere of his raign. After him, Tullus Hoſtilius beinge Tullus Hoſtilius the third king. Martiall pollicy renued. made kinge, did againe put in vre the feates of armes, and renued battails: which during the raign of Numa had bene laid aſide. He conquered the Albanes, whiche were diſtant .xii. miles from the city of Rome. He alſo ſubdued the Veientines and Fidenates, of Alba longa deſtroyed in thys kynges raygne. Rome enlarged. which thone were .vi. miles, thother were .xviii. miles diſtant from Rome. He enlarged the city annexing therto the hil Celius, &amp; being ſtrycken wyth

lightning, both he and his houſe was Tullus hys raigne. burned, when he hadde raigned .xxxii. yeres. After him Ancus Martius gouerned the citye of Rome. Who was Ancus Martius, the .iiii. kinge, he was before the Incarnatyon of Chriſte. 642. yeres, he made the brydge ouer the riuer of Tyber, whych ran by Rome, &amp; built a gail or priſō in Rome for the runiſhyng of offenders. ſonne to Numa Pōpilius his daughter. He waged battail againſt the Latines. He enlarged tbe city, by taking into it the hils Auentinus and Ianiculus. He built a city faſt vpon the ſea ſhore at Dſtia, whiche was .vi. miles diſtaunt from the citye of Rome. And being viſited with ſickneſſe, he deceaſed in the .xxiiii. yeare of his raigne. Then Priſcus Tarquinius, obtained the Empire, he doubled the noumber Priſcus Tarquinius the v. kynge. of the Senatoures. He built the place of playee in Rome called Circus: and The number of the Senators doubled. inſtituted alſo diuers games there, which as yet to this day do remaine. He ſubdued the Sabines. And berefting Circus built. them of a great portion of theyr lande, annexed it to the territorye of the Romaines. He was the firſt that entred the Citye of Rome with anye Priſcus Tarniquinius triuinphed fyrſt at Rome.
               
triumph. He builded the walles of ye city, and ſinkes alſo to auoid ye filthe and ordure of the City. He began the Capitoll, and when he had raygned xxxviii. yeres, he was ſlayne by the The capytoll 
                     〈…〉
                   ſlayn. ſonnes of king Ancus whome he ſucceaded in the kingdome. After hym, Seruius Tullius was kinge, whoſe mother was a noble woman borne: Seruiꝰ Tullius the .vi. kyng. but yet was ſhe a captiue and a hādmaide. He ſubdued the Sabines, and annexed to the citye, theſe three hils, Quirinalis, Viminalis and Eſquilinus. He entrenched rounde the Romewalles entrenched. wals of the City. He was ye firſt that inuented muſtring of men, which before his time was not known throughe the whole worlde. In his raigne Muſtryng 
                     〈◊〉
                  . the names of all the inbabitantes in Rome wer takē, and ther wer found 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . in the City of Rome .lxxx. and .iiii. M. citizens able men with thoſe whiche inhabited about ye city. He was ſlain in the .xlv. yere of his raign, through Seruiꝰ Tullius ſlayne.
               
the wickednes of his ſon in law Tarquinius who was ſon to ye laſt kinge before him (whō this Seruius Tullius ſucceded) and the naughtines of his own daughter, whō he had eſpouſed to the ſaide Tarquinius. Lucius Lucius Tarquinius, Superbus ye vii. kyng. Tarquinius, Superbus was the .vii. &amp; the laſt king that raigned at Rome He ouercam the Volſcians in battel, whiche are ſituate not far diſtant frō Rome (as mē go frō thence towards Campania, He ſubdued the Citye of Gabios, &amp; Sueſſa Pometia. He made peace with the Thuſcians, and built Iupiter, his temple built. Iupiter his temple in the capitol. Afterward, as he was laying ſiege to ye city of Arde, whiche was .x. miles diſtant frō the city of Rome, he was depoſed. Lucius Tarquinius depoſed. For whē his ſon Sextus Tarquinius had forſt &amp; poluted the noble woman, &amp; therwithal the moſte chaſteſt Adultery the cauſe of the fyrſt alteratyon of the ſtate of the weale publique in Rome. Lucretia wife to Collatinus, &amp; ſhe had of this iniury complained to her huſband, &amp; other her frendes, in ye preſens of them all, ſhe ſlue her ſelf.

Where vpon they kindled the hartes of the people againſte Tarquinius, &amp; depoſed him from his kingdome: and The ſeuerity of the Romaines in punyſhing adulterye. ſone after, the whole army whiche at that time laid ſiege to the city of Arde together with ye king, forſoke him. Where vpon when the king retourned, and would haue entred the city, Lucius Tarquinius hys raygne. ye gates wer ſhut againſt him. Thus when he hadde raigned .xxv. yeres, he fled with his wife and children. In this wiſe raigned .vii. kinges ouer the city of Rome, by the ſpace of. CCxliii The time that kynges gouerned Rome. yeres: at which time Rome extended not to aboue .xv. miles, where it was largeſt. From this time began there to be created in the place of one kyng ii. conſuls for this conſideration, that Two conſuls created in Rome. Conſuls ordained in rome ye 3450. yere after the creatiō of the world. The raign of the conſuls. although the one of them were diſpoſed to naughtineſſe, yet the other hauing the like authority, might bridle the affection of his companyon. And it was decreed that they ſhoulde not rule aboue one yere, leaſt the continuaunce

of theyr bearinge rule ſhoulde make thē waxe hauty, wheras otherwiſe The order of the cōſuls cō
                  einued after it was fyrſt inſtituted vntil Iulius Ceſares raigne, which wxas by the ſpace of 464. yeres they wold demene them ſelues more curteouſly, knowinge that after theyr ycare expired and determined, they ſhoulde become priuate perſons againe. In the firſt yere after the expulſing of the kings forth of the city, Lucius Iunius Brutus, who hadde moſt of others procured the baniſhing Lucius Iunius Brutus and Tarquinius Collatinus fyrſt conſuls. of Tarquinius, and with him Tarquinius Collatinus, who was huſbād to Lucretia, wer choſen cōſuls. How be it Collatinus was forth wyth depriued of his Conſulſhip. For why it was agreed that none ſhould remain in the Citye, that bare the name of Tarquinius. wherevpon Collatinus Tarquinius Collatinus depryned of hys conſulſhip. taking with him all hys ſubſtaunce, departed forth of the City, and in hys roume Valerius Publicola was created conſull. Neuertheleſſe kinge Valerius Publicola cōſull. The fyrſt battaile that any Romain euer waged agaīſt Rome. Tarquinius who a lyttle before was baniſheda ſſembling togethera great

army to aid him to recouer his kingdome, waged batail with the Citizēs of Rome. In the very firſt front of ye batail, Brutus the conſul and Aruus Tarquinius his ſonne ſlue one another. Brutus and Aruus ſlayn. How be it the Romains obtayned the victory in that battaile: &amp; the Romain matrones bewailed ye deth of Brutus by the ſpace of one whole Brutꝰ death bewayled. yere, as the defender of their chaſtities. After the death of Brutus, Valerius Publicola choſe Spurius Lucretius Tricipitinus, who was father Spurius, Lucretius, Tricipitinus conſul. Lucretius dyed. Horatius, Puluillus conſull. Fiue conſuls in the i. yere. to Lucretia to be conſul, who died by ſicknes: &amp; Horatius Puluillus was created conſull in his roume. Thus wer .v. conſuls created in ye firſt yere. Of whome, Tarquinius Collatinus loſte the citye for his name. Brutus was ſlain in battail, Spurius Lucretius ſickned and died. Then in the ſecond yere after, Tarquinſus agayne War agayne attempted by Tarquinius agaynſt the Romaynes. made warre vppon the Romaines, to the ende he mighte recouer hys

kingdome, whome Porſenna kynge 
                  •
               f Thuſcia then aided, and wel nigh he hadde taken Rome. Howe be it at this time, was he alſo ouercome. In the iii. yere after the kings wer baniſhed forth of the City, when Tarquinius apperceiued that he ſhould neither be receiued again of the Romaines, nor yet that Porſenna wold ſuccour him anye longer, he departed to Thuſculus a city not far diſtāt from Rome, &amp; ther by the ſpace of .xiiii. yeres Tarquinius lyued as a priuate man at Thuſculus. he liued with his wife, as a private man. In the. 4. yeare after yt the kings wer baniſhed ye city, the Sabines The Sabins warred on the romaines again warred vpō the Romains: at which time, they wer alſo ouercōe &amp; the Romaines triumphed ouer thē. In the .v. yere Lucius Valerius, who was felow in office with Brutus, &amp; thother. 4. conſuls, deceaſed in ſuche extreme pouerty, yt mony was fain to A collectyon of monye for the burial of Valerius the conſull. bee gathered amonge the people, to bear the expenſes of his funeras.
            
               
Whoſe death the Romain matrones did by the ſpace of a yere, bewaile, as they did the deathe of Brutus before. In the .ix. yere after the baniſhyng of the kinges, when Tarquinius hys ſonne in law had aſſembled together Preparatyon for warre agaynſte the Romaines by tarquinius his ſon in lawe. The offyce of dictatura fyrſt inſtituted. Titus Largius dictator a great army, to the end he might reuenge the reproche whiche his father in law ſuſtained at the Romains handes, There was a newe office created in Rome, called Dictatura in authority, excelling farre the office of the conſuls. That ſame yere was there alſo ordained in Rome an other Offycer called Magiſter Equitum: who was deputed to be attendant vpon the dictator. To this office of Dictator was Spurius Caſſius. fyrſt magiſter Equitum. firſt deputed at Rome Titus Largius. And Spurius Caſſius ſupplyed firſt the offyce of magiſter Equitum. In the .xvi. yeare did the commons of Rome make a commotion, pretēding A commotiō at Rome by the commōs. the cauſe to be, for that the ſenatours and Conſuls woulde haue oppreſſed

them: At which time, they created ii. whome they called Tribuni Plebis, Tribuni Plebis created: whiche were after, abrogated by Sylla, and reſtored agayn by Pō
                  peius. and aſſigned them to be peculier deciſers and determiners of their cauſes only: by whoſe meanes they might be in ſafety, and defended againſt the cō
               ſuls. In the yere folowing the Volſtians renued battaile againſte the Romaines, The Volſtianes renued war agaynſte the Romains they were ſubdued: and loſte moreouer theyr firſt city called Corioli. In the .xiii. yere after that the kynges were baniſhed, Quintus Martius Rome inuaded by Quintius Martius a Romayne. a famous capitain of the Romaynes, who wan Coriolis a citye of the Volſcians, vppon diſpleaſure conceyued, went to the Volſcians, and toke part with them, who alſo aided him agaīſt the Romaines. By meane wherof, he putte the Romaines oft times to the worſte. He camped wythin .v. miles of the city of Rome. And regardinge nothing the Legates, which the Romaines ſent to hym to entreate for peace, he determyned to haue inuaded hys

owne country, had not hys own mother Veturia, and his wife Volumnia come forth of the citye to intreate him: throughe whoſe requeſt myxte with teares, he was ouercome, and ſo withdrewe his armye. In that yere that Ceſus Fabius, and Titus Virginius were conſuls, three hundreth noble men of the houſe &amp; ſtocke of the Fabianes, toke vppon them alone Battayle taken in hand a gaynſt ye Veientines, by ye houſe of the Fabianes alone. to wage battail againſt the Veientines, offerynge the ſenatoures and the people of Rome, that they thē ſelfs wold fight the field. Whervpō, al theſe noble mē according they had before decreed, went forth to ye battel ward, of which eche of thē was well worthy to haue ben a captē for theyr ſinguler proweſſe: and wer all ſlayn there: ſo that of that ſo great a family The ſtocke of the Fabians neare cleane extynguyſhed. &amp; line, there was left none a liue but one, who for that he was but a child, was not then able to go to warfare. After theſe things, ther was another

muſter taken within the city, &amp; the citizens amounted to ye nombre of a C. The ſeconde muſter at Rome. &amp; .xix. M. able menne. The yere folowing, when tharmy of the Romaines was beſeged in ye hil Algidus, which The romain army beſeged was wel nigh .xii. miles diſtant from ye city of Rome. Lucius Quintus Cin Lucius Quī
                  tus Cincinatus being Dictator, called ſtraight from the plough handle. cinnatus was made dictator, who being ſeiſed of a cloſe or field which cō
               teined ſo much groūd as one yoke of oxen was able to ear in .iiii. dais: called in latin. Quatuor vgera: (whiche contained .ix. C .lx. fote in length &amp; in In how ſinal citimatyon ample poſſeſſyons wer in Rome. bredth. CCCC. &amp; .viii. ſcore fote,) tilled that ground with his owne handes. And beynge ſent for to ſuccor the Romains, they found him buſily occupied in plowing: he then wiping onlye the ſwet from his browes, and (as the manner was) caſtinge vppon him the garment (whiche was aſſigned for the Dictator to weare) called Toga pretexta: tooke his iourney forthewith agaynſte hys ennemyes: Toga pretexta.
               
and putting them to flight, deliuered the army of the Romaines beſieged. In the yeare after the foundatyon of the citye of Rome thre hundreth and one, the office of the conſulles ceaſed The offyce of Conſuls ceasſed. for a time. And in the place of the .ii. Conſulles, there were choſen tenne which ſhould beare chefe authoritye in the citye, and they were called Decemuiri. But when in the firſt yeare Decemuiri fyrſt inſtituted. after their creation they had well demeaned them ſclues, in the ſeconde yere of their bearing rule, one of thē 
               Durynge the raygne of the Decemuirs certayne of that order, wer ſent into Grece, to ſee the vſages of the mooſt famous cityes there, who vſyng there in the aduiſe of the moſt learned in thoſe partes wrate certain lawes whych were called the .xii. tables, and The Decemuirs depriued of their authority, they raigned. 3. yeares. named Appius Claudius wold haue forſt &amp; defloured a maid, which was doughter to one Virginius: whyche Virginius at that time ſoulded for honeſt wages in the hill Algidus againſte the Latines. But when Virginius vnderſtode the pretens of the Decemuirs, he choſe rather to ſlaye daughter as he did, then he ſhould be polluted by the Decemuir: and returning backe to his ſouldioures, he began

a commotion: for which fact the Decemuirs were depriued of theyr authority, and they them ſelues condempned. In the. CCC. and .xv. yere after Rome was builte, the Fidenatss rebelled againſt the Romaines: wheme the Veientines aſſiſted. Tolumnius The Fidenates rebelled. was at that time kynge of the Veientines, bothe which Cityes were ſituate nigh to Rome: For Fidene was but .vii. miles and Veientes .xviii. miles diſtante from Rome. The Volſcianes in like maner toke Parre with thoſe other people. How be it they ſuſtained the ouerthrow by Marcus Emilius Dictator. Lucius Q. Cincinatus magiſter Equitum. Tolumnius ſlayne. The Citye of the Fidenats taken and ouerthrowen. Furius Camillus Dictator. Marcus Aemilius then Dictator, &amp; Lucius Quintus Cincinatus, Magiſter Equitum. In that battayle they loſt their king. The city of the Fidenaies was won and quite deſtroyed. Twenty yeres after that, the Veientines rebelled agayne: and ther was ſent againſt them, Furius Camillus the Dictator: who at the firſt, diſcomfited

them in battayle: and eftſones when he hadde beſieged the Citye a good ſpace, he wanne it: whiche was The city of the Veiētins taken. the mooſte auncient and the rycheſt through all Italy. After that, he wan alſo Faliſci, a Citye no leſſe notable thē that other was. But the peoples Faliſci won. hartes were kindled agaynſte hym, through the procurement of certain perſons whiche ſurmiſed that he had Camillus banyſhed. not well and indifferentlye deuided the ſpoyle: Vppon whiche cauſe, hee was condempned and baniſhed the City. Immediatly herevppon, the Rome inuaded by the frenchmen, in the. 360. yere after the citye was built, about. 350. yeres before the byrth of chriſt Frenchmen inuaded Rome and purſued the Romaynes vnto the floude Allia, whiche was xi. miles dyſtante from the citye of Rome, whan they had thus diſcomfited and vāquyſhed the Romaynes, they wan the citye it ſelf: of which no part was able to be Rome taken. defended againſt them but the Capitoll only: whiche when they had alſo of longe tyme beſieged, ſo that the

Romaynes whyche were included, began now to fayle of vyttayles, Camillus who liued as a baniſhed mā, in a city neare adioynyng, ſet vppon the Frenchmen, and wyth muche a doo put them to flyght. Whervppon Rome reſkued by Camillus, and the frēchmen put to flyght. the Frenchmen whiche layde ſyege to the capytoll, brake vp their ſiege, receyuyng gold of the Romaines for the ſame intent. But Camillus ſtyll purſued, and made ſuch ſlaughter of them, that he recouered not only the golde whyche they had receyued, but ſuche anncientes alſo and enſignes of warre, as they hadde gotten. And thus returnyng to Rome agayne, he entred into the citye with his thyrde Camillus called the ſecond Romulus. triumphe, and was called the ſecond Romulus: as thoughe he allſo had ben a founder of that hys countrey.
         
         
            
            ¶ The ſeconde boke of the breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               IN the three hundreth thre ſkore and v. yeare after the buyldynge of the citye of Rome, and in the firſte yeare after Offyces changed agayne in Rome. that it was ſo taken by the Frenchemen, the offices were agayne altered, and in ſteade of the two conſuls, two were created, whych wer called Tribuni Militum: of no leſſe authoritye Tribuni militum created. then the Conſuls were. From this time, began the welth of Rome to increaſe. For that ſame yere, Camillus wan the city of the Volſciās. The city of ye Volſcianes wonne by Camillus. which by the ſpace of .lxx. yeares had waged battayle with the Romains: he wan alſo the cities of the Equies and Sutrines, and diſcomfited all theyr armies: and got thre triumphs together. Tytus Quintius Cincinatus purſuinge at that time allſo the

Preneſtines whych came to the very gates of Rome to wage battaile, and ouercame them at the floud Allia, and annexed to the Empyre of the Romaines thoſe cities whiche were vnder the dominion of the Preneſtines. Than gaue he the aſſault to the citye Preneſte it ſelfe: whiche was Great proweſſe of Cincinatus. yelded vp to him: All whiche feates hee did within .xx. dayes ſpace: and a triumphe was graunted vnto hym. How be it the dignity of the Tribunes The offyce of Tribunes ceſed. did not longe indure: for after a while, it ſemed good to the Romaines to create no mo of that order. And ſo by the ſpace of three yeares, thei ſtode in dout whether thei ſhuld make any great offices agayn or no. Neuertheleſſe the Tribunes at laſt, The Tribunes recouered agayn theyr dygnytye. by common conſente obtayned againe theyr former dignity, and that they ſhoulde alſo haue the authority of the Conſuls beſides, and continued ſo by the ſpace of three yeres.

Then were there conſulles created againe. In the yere that Lucius Genutius, and Quintus Seruilius wer Conſuls created agayne. conſuls, Camillus died, vnto whom moſt honor was attributed nexte after Camilius deceaſed. Romulus, of anye that euer was in Rome. About this time Quintius the Dictator was ſent forth agaynſt the Frenchmen which were aryued in Italy, and had camped on the farther The frenche men againe a riued and camped in Italy. ſide of the floud Auienes, wher Titus Manlius the worthieſt of all the Senators, ſlue one of the French men, which prouoked him to fyghte hande to hande. And when he hadde ſlayne hym, he pluckte of a chayn of gould which his enemy ware about his necke, and put it about his own: whereof bothe he and hys poſteritye were called Torquati, for a perpetuall memory of that fact. The reſidue The original or the name of Corquati. of the Frenchmen wer put to flight: and eftſoones ouercome by Caius Sulpitius the Dictator. Wythin a

whyle after, the Thuſcianes were The Thuſcians diſcomfited by Marius. ſubdued by Caius Marius: and .vii. thouſand of them were led priſoners in one triumphe. There was againe a muſter had in Rome, and whē the Latines whome the Romaynes had The thyrde muſter at Rome. before ſubdued, refuſed to aſſiſte thē with any power of mē againſt theyr enemies, they wer enforced to choſe among them ſelues yong ſouldiours onlye, and ſuche as before that time had neuer bene at warre, to the nomber often legions. So muche preuailed the Romaines in Warlike feats and cheualry, although their wealth and ſubſtaunce was as yet but verye ſclender. Thys armye went forth agaynſt the Frenchmen, and Lucius Furius was appoynted generall therof: At that time, one of the french campe chalenged into the fielde hym whom the Romaines accompted the mooſt valyaunt among them al. Vpon whyche bragges Marcus Valerius

being at that time Tribunus Militume profered himſelfe to fight the combate: and as he marched forward Mar. Valer. did battayle wyth a french man. into the field ready armed, a Crowe lyghted vppon his ryghte arme, and ſate there ſtil. Afterwarde when hys aduerſarye and hee came to handy grypes, the ſame Crowe ſmote the Frenchman vpon the eyes with hys winges and tallaunts in ſuch ſorte, that he coulde not ſee forthrighte, by meane wherof he was ſlain hy Valerius. And the Crow gaue him not only the victory, but his name alſo, that he was after called Coruinus. The originall of the name of Coruinus. M. Va. Cor. Conſul. And for this fact he was created conſull, duringe the ſpace of .xxiii. yeres. Then the Latines who beefore had refuſed to ayde the Romaines wyth anye ſouldioures, made requeſt that one of the Conſuls myght be choſen amonge them, and the other among the Romaines, whiche demaunde of theyrs was denyed, and battayle by

the Romaynes prepared againſt thē, wherin they were ouercome, and vppon theyr ouerthrow the Romaines Battayle agaynſt the Latines. triumphed. The pictures of the conſulles were ſet vppe at the barres: (whyche was the place where the Orators pleaded mennes cauſes) for The Images of the Cōſuls erected. this victory atchieued. Now the Romaines waxed mighty: they warred wyth the Samnites well nyghe an C. and .xxx. miles diſtant from Rome whiche are ſituate in the mid waye betwene Picennm, Campania, and Apulia. Lucius Papirius Curſor went to that battail being fyrſt created Dictator, &amp; retournyng through cauſe of buſyneſſe from thence to Rome, gaue charge (at his departure to Quintus Fabius Maximus, who at that time was Magiſter Equitū, that during his abſence, he ſhuld not fyght with his ennemies. How be it he vppon occaſyon geuen, with merueylous dexterity of fortune foughte

with the Samnites, and vanquiſhed them. For whyche facte the Dictator Lucius Papirius after hys retourne gaue ſentence of deathe vppon hym, for that he had foughte contrarye to Quintus Fabi. Max. adiudged to deathe. hys commaundemente. But yet hee was deliuered through the paſlynge great fauour of the ſouldiers, which they pretended toward hym. Aboute which matter there was ſuch diſſention bred by Papirius, that hee was nighe ſlaine himſelfe there in. After this, the Samnits ouercam the Romaines The Romaines vanquyſhed by the Samnites. The yoke y• they called Iugſt was made wt ii. ſpeares, ſtucke in the earth. and the third on their poynts like a galowes: vnder which for reproch vanquiſhed men were led. to theyr great reproche, and cauſed them to crepe vnder the yoke at whiche time Titus Veturius and Spurius, Poſtumius were conſuls. Howe be it the Senators and people of Rome forthe with infringed that league, which a litel before they wer conſtrained to make with the Samnites. Then Lucius Papirius hadde the vpper hande ouer the Samnites, and ſent .vii. thouſand of them vnder

the yoke: and Papirius tryumphed ouer them. At that time Appius Claudius being Cenſor conueyed into the The Sānites diſcomiyted. city, the ſtreame which is nowe called Claudia water, and made ye high way which is yet called Appia way. The Samnites renewed battayle. Not long after the Samnites renued battaile, and ouercame Quintus Fabius Maximus, and ſlewe .iii. M. of hys men. Afterward whan his father Fabius Maximus was ſente to Quin. Fab. Max. vanquiſhed. aide him, he did not only ſubdue the Samnites againe, but wan alſo dyuers of theyr townes. Then were Publius Cornelius Rufinus, and Marcus Curius Dentatus created Conſuls: and were bothe ſent forthe Publi. Cor. Ruf. and M. Cur. Dent. Conſuls. againſt the Samnites, and in an exceding greate battayle they vanquiſhed theym: and thus ended they the battaile, which the Samnites hadde continued againſt the Romaines, by the ſpace of .xlix. yeares: which nation far aboue all the reſidue through

out all Italy, did moſte diminiſh the force of the Romains. Within a few yeres after, the armies of the french men ioyned wyth the Thuſcianes, and Samnites againſte the Romaines: but as they marched towardes Rome, Cnaine Cornelius Dolabella encountringe wyth them, ſlewe them: At that time warre was proclaymed Warre proclaimed agaīſt the Tarentines. agaynſte the Tarentines whiche inhabited the fartheſt partes of Italye, for that they had iniuryed the Legates of the Romaines. The Tarentines deſired Pyrrhus kynge of Epirus to aſſyſte theym agaynſte the Romaines, who forth wyth came to Italye.
            Thys Pyrrhus was deſcended of the line of Achilles. Thys was the fyrſte battaile that the Romaynes The fyrſt battayle that the romaynes waged wyth forrayn enemye. waged with anye foraine ennemye. To this battaile was Publius Valerius Leuinus ſente: who when he had apprehended the eſpyes of Pirrhus,

he willed that they ſhoulde be led through the camp, and that al the armye ſhoulde be ſhewed to them, and ſo be diſmiſte, to the ende they might recount to Pirrhus howe the The ſtoutnes of the romaynes. Romaines did demeane them ſelues in all poyntes. Soone after the armies ioyned battayle, and Pyrrhus was at the poynte to haue fled, had not hys Elephantes bene, throughe Pyrrhus ouercame the romaynes, by meanes of his Elephantes. whoſe meanes he gotte the victory: of whome the Romaynes (for that they hadde not earſte ſene, ſuche beſtes) were diſmayed and ſtoode in feare.
            Howe be it the nyghte fyniſhed their ſkyrmiſhe for that time. Leuinus the Conſull fledde that nyghte: Leunius the Conſul fled. and Pirrhus tooke priſonners about 
                  •
                thouſande and eyghte hundreth Romaines, whome he entreated ve
               
                  •
               ye honourablye, and ſuche as were 
                  •
               aine in the battayle, hee buryed,

whome when he ſawe they were all wounded in the fore partes, and after they were dead, keping ſtil theyr Pyrrhus hys princely behauyour. grim lokes, whiche while they liued they yet hadde, as one agaſte at the ſyght, lifting vppe his handes to the ſkyes, he ſayde: were it my chaunce Worthy commendation of the Romains. (quod he) to haue ſuche ſouldioures as theſe were, I could eaſely wythin ſhorte whyle conquere all the whole world. After this, Pyrrhus aſſociated vnto him the Samnites, the Lucanes and the Brutians, and marched ſo forward toward Rome deſpoiling all as he went with fier and ſworde. He prayed through all Campania, &amp; came to Preneſte whiche was diſtāt but .xviii. miles from Rome, then retired hee backe againe to Campania for dreede of the Conſuls, who came wyth a great army againſte hym. The Romaynes then ſente their legates to Pirrhus to entreate aboute the ranſomynge of their priſoners,

whome he receiued honourably, and ſent to Rome ſuche priſoners as he had, wythout receiuinge anye raunſome for them. And amonge the reſidewe of the Romaine Legates, Pyrrhus was ſo muche affectyoned towardes one Fabricius, that wher as he vnderſtode the ſayd Fabricius to be but a very pore man, he profered to geue him the fourths parte of his kingdome, if that he woulde forſake Howe dear the Romains eſtemed theyr country. Rome, and come to hym. But Fabricius refuſed that hys offer, Where vppon Pyrrhus not a lyttle meruailinge at the Romaines, ſente the chiefeſt of all his bande, one called Cyneas on embaſſade to Rome, Pyrrhus prayed peace. to intreat for peace, vpon indifferent conditions, ſo that Pyrrhus myghte ſtyl detayne that part of Italye whiche he had ſubdued by battail, which profer of peace miſliked the Romaines: and woorde was ſente backe to Pyrrhus from the Senate, that vnleſſe

he would depart forth of Italy, he could in no wyſe haue peace with the Romaynes. Then the Romains The ſtout anſwer of the romaynes. commaunded that all thoſe whyche Pyrrhus had taken priſoners, ſhuld be reputed as infamed perſones, for that they would be taken priſoners The ſeuerity of the Romaynes. when they might haue defended thē ſelues by force of armes: And more ouer, that they ſhould not agayne be reſtored to theyr former eſtate, vntyl ſuche tyme as they broughte wyth them the like ſpoiles of theyr ennemies. With this anſwer retourned Worthy praiſe of enemyes mouthes. the Legate of Pirrhus: of whome when Pyrrhus demaūded what maner of place Rome was, he anſweared that he had there ſene a countrey of kinges: affirming that in manner euery one there, was ſuche a one, as Pirrhus alone was counted to be at Epirus, and through all Grece. Thē there were ſent forth agaynſte Pyrrhus, Publius Sulpitius and Decius:

who wer then Conſuls. In a ſkirmiſh Pub. Sul. and Decius Conſuls ſent againſt Pyrrhus. which he made againſte them, Pyrrhus was wounded, his Elephantes ſlaine, and of his armye hee loſt twentye thouſande. There were ſlaine of the Romaines onlye v. M. Thus was Pyrrhus diſcomfitedde. Pyrrhus put to fiyght. The yere after, Fabricius was ſent forthe againſte Pyrrhus: This was he, whome before amonge the other Fabricius ſēt agaynſt Pyrrhus. Legates of the Romaynes, Pyrrhus could by no meanes allure to forſake Rome and come to him, vppon promiſe to depart with the fourth parte of his kingdome vnto him. When he and king Pyrrhus had pitched theyr tentes neare the one to the other, Pyrrhus his Phiſition cam by night to Fabricius, offring that he woulde deſtroy Pirrhus with poyſon, if Fabricius would geue him any thynge for his laboure: whome Fabritius The Romaines hated treſon. apprehended, and cauſed to be bound and caried to Pyrrhus, and to be dedeclared

vnto hym what thyngs hys Phiſition hadde conſpired againſte hym. Where at the kynge all agaſte ſayde. Vndoubtedly this is that Fabricius (quod he), who wyth more difficulty can be made to forſake honeſty, then the Sunne can be ſtopte to run hys courſe. And ſo the kynge departed into Sicilie. Fabritius after Pyrthus went into Sicilie. Fabritius triumphed. that he had ſubdued the Samnites and the Lucanes trpumphed. Afterward, Marcus Curius Dentatus and Cornelius Lentulus being then Conſuls, were ſent forthe agaynſte Pirrhus, Curius foughte the battayle wyth hym. He ſlewe hys army, hee draue hym to Tarentum, and Pyrrhus diſcomfyted. ſackt hys tentes. He ſlewe that daye of hys ennemyes three and twentye thouſande. Curius Dentatus tryumphed in hys Conſulſhip: he brought Elephantes fyrſt brought to Rome. foure Elephants to Rome: whiche were the fyrſte that euer were there. Not longe after, Pirrhus departed

from Tarentum, and at Argos Pyrthꝰ ſlain a citye of Grece he was ſlayne. When Caius Fabritius Luſcinus, and Caius Claudius Cinna were conſulles, whyche was in the yeare after the foundatyon of the citye of Rome, four hundreth thre ſkore and one, ambaſſadonres were ſent forthe Legats forth of Alexandria ſēt to Rome. of Alexandria by Ptolomeus too Rome, to ioyne frendſhyp and amyty wyth the Romaynes: which thing they obtayned. Whileſt that Quintus Gulo, and Caius Fabius Pictor were conſuls, the Picentines ſtirred vp war agaynſte the Romaynes, Pub. Sem. &amp; Ap. Clau. Conſuls. but they were ouercome by Publius Sempronius and Appius Claudius, (which wer next cōſuls) &amp; triumphed ouer them. About this tyme, the Romains The cityes Ariminum &amp; Benenentū built by the Romaynes. Mar. Attili. Regu. &amp; Lu-Iuni. Libo Conſuls. built the cities Ariminum in Fraunce, and Beneuentum in Samnio: when Marcus Atti. Regu. &amp; Lu. Iu. Libe wer conſuls, war was procilamed againſt the Salē. in Apulia:

The Brunduſians wer vanquiſhed, The Brunduſians &amp; the city taken. and their City wonne: and triumph was had ouer them againe.
            In the. CCCC .lxxviii. yeare after the buildinge of Rome, the name and renoume of the Romaynes became now famous, and yet had they neuer waged any battaile forthe of Italy. To the end therfore that they might vnderſtande what power they were able to make, there was a muſter A m
                     •••
                  er again in Rome had, and the names of the Romaines were taken: who being nombred by the pols, amounted to .cc. xc .ii. M. 334. citizens, all he it ſithe the firſt foundation of the citye, warres had at no tyme ceaſed: Thē was the The fyrſt battayle whyche the romaines waged agaīſt the Carthaginiens was in the 480. yere after the buyl dynge of the citye, &amp; laſted xx
                     ••
                  . yeares wythoute intermiſſyon. firſt battayle attempted agaynſt the people of Affricke: Appius Claudius and Quintus Fuluius beinge then Conſuls: battail was fought againſt theym in Sicille: where as Appius Claudius triumphed ouer them, and ouer Hieron king of Sicilie.
            
               
In the yere folowing Martus Valerius, Appi. Clau. &amp; Quin. Ful. Conſulles. Mar. Vale. and Octacil. Conſuls. and Octacillus beynge then Conſuls, the Romains wrought very great enterpryſes. For whye, the Taurominatanes, and the Catanenſes, and beſides them, fiftye other cityes, were receiued vnder obediens.
            In the third yere after, preparation for warre was made againſt Hieron in Sicilie. But he, together with Wax pretended agaynſte Hieron. the reſide we of hys Nobilitye, made peace with the Romaines, and gaue vnto them in conſideration thereof, CC. talentes of ſiluer. The Affricanes were ouercom in Sicilie, which The ſeconde triumph ouer the Affricans was the ſecon̄de time that the Romaines triumphed ouer them.
            In the fifthe yeare after that the Romaines firſte waged battayle againſte the Afers, (Caius Duillius, and Cneus Cornelius Aſina beyng Ca. Duil. &amp; Cne. Cor. Aſi. Conſuls The fyrſt battaile whyche the romaynes waged on the ſee. Conſuls,) they fought vpon the ſea: Againſt whiche battaile, they hadde prepared light ſhyppes, whych they

called Foyſtes. The Conſul Cornelius was deceiued by a trayne. But Duillius fought the battail out, and ouercame the captain of the Carthaginiens. He toke .xxxi. ſhips. He ſonk The Carthaginiens dyſcomfyted. xviii. He toke .vii. M. men priſoners, and ſlewe .iii. M. There was neuer victorye more acceptable to the Romaines, then this was. For where before they had ſhewed them ſelues to be inuincible vpon the lande, they had now alſo experimēted that they wer of great force vpon the ſea, whē Caius Aquilius Florus, and Lucius Scipio were, Conſulls, Scipio wan Caius Aqui. Flo. &amp; Lu. Sci. Cōſuls. Corſica and Sardinia won. Corſica, and Sardinia, and led wyth him from thence many thouſand priſoners, and triūphed. Lucius Mālius Volſo, &amp; Marcus Attilius Regulus, being Conſuls, war was again trāſpoſed Luci. Man. Vol. &amp; Mar. Atti. Regu. Conſuls. into Africke againſt Hamilcar a captain of the Carthaginiēs: This battail was alſo fought vpon the ſea The ſecond battail on the ſea. and Hamilcar was diſcomfyted. For

when he had loſt .lxiiii. ſhips, he retired backe. The Romains loſt in that battail .xxii. ſhips: but whē they wer A great ouer throwe of the Carthagini. Clipea yelded to the Romaynes. ariued in Affrick, Clipea the chefeſt Citye in Affricke was yealded vp to them. The Conſulles then marched forward toward Carthage: and whē they had deſpoiled manye Townes, Mālius returned to Rome, &amp; brought Manlius returned wyth victorye to Rome. with him .xxvii. M. priſoners. Attilius Regulus remaininge ſtill in Affricke, prepared his army to withſtand the force of the Affricanes: and Regulus remayned in Affricke. Regulus worthy actes. ioyning battail with iii. captaines of the Carthaginiens at ones, he obtained the victorye. He ſlewe .xviii. M. of his enemies. He toke priſoners fyue thouſand men, and eyghte Elephantes. He receiued vnder obeyſaunce lxxiii. Cityes. The Carthaginiens when they were thus dyſcom
                  •
               ited, deſired peace of the Romains, which Peace deſired by the Carthagini. when Regulus wold not graūt, but vpon ſtraight conditiōs, they deſired ayde

ſuccoure of the Lacedemonians: to The Carthaginiens deſyred ayd of the Lacedemonians. whom ye Lacedemonians ſent Xantippus with a band of menne, throughe whoſe meanes, Regulus was ouercome, ſo that of all the armye of the Romaines, there eſkaped but ii. M. only, xv. M. were taken priſonners, A great ouer throwe of the Romaynes. and theyr captaine Regulus al ſo: xxx. M. were ſlaine. Regulus hymſelfe was caſt into priſon. Thē were Regulus taken and caſte into pryſon. Mar. Emili. Pau. &amp; Ser. Ful. Cōſuls. Marcus Emilius Paulus, and Seruius Fuluius the nobler created Cō
               ſuls: bothe whyche paſſed ouer into Affricke wyth a nauy of .iii. C. ſayle. Firſte they ouercame the Afers in Battail renued by the Romains agaīſt the Cartha. The thyrde battayle on the ſea. A great diſcō fyture of the Carthagini. battail vpon the ſea: Emilius ſonke a hundreth and foure ſhyppes of hys enemyes. He toke xxx. together with the men that fought in them. He ſlue and toke priſonners beſides .xv. M. of his ennemies, and enriched his ſouldioures with a
                  •
                exceadinge greate ſpoyle. And at that time, had all Affricke beene ſubdued, had not thers

chaunced ſo great a dearth, that the ſouldioures coulde not anye longer remaine there: As the Conſulles retourned A great derth in Affricke. home with theyr victorious nauy, they ſuffred ſhypwracke about the coaſte of Sicilie. Whereas there a roſe ſo great a tempeſt, that of .iiii. The Romaines 
                     〈◊〉
                   greatly by ſhipwrack C. lxxriiii. ſhippes, vnneth lxxx. could be ſaued. Whyche tempeſt was ſo terryble, that the lyke therof had not at anye time before beene hearde of, vpon the ſea. Neuertheleſſe the Romaynes forthwyth renued two hundreth The inuincible and ſtoute courage of the Romaynes. newe ſhippes, (whoſe myndes were not a whit diſmaied with thoſe former miſhappes.) Then were created Conſuls, Cneus Seruilius Cepio, and Caius Sempronius Bleſus Cne. Serui. Ce. and. Ca. Sem. Bie. Conſuls. who with two hūdreth and .lx. ſhips, tooke their byage towardes Affricke where they wan certaine cityes. And as they retourned thence homeward The fourthe battail on the ſea.
(bringing a great ſpoyle with them) they ſuffred ſhipwracke, Whervpon

they ſuffred ſhipwracke, wherevpon The romaynes. ſuſtained ſhipwracke agayne. the Romaynes finding them ſelues agreued with theeſe continuall and often damages which they ſuſtained vpon the ſea, the Senators thoughte good, to geue ouer that kinde of battaile, The romaynes purpoſed to geue ouer battail on the ſea. Luci. Ceci. Me. &amp; Caius Furi. Pla. Conſuls. and to kepe no mo but lx. ſhips onlye, to defend Italy wythall. Whē Lucius Cecilius Metellus, and Caius Furius Placidus wer Conſuls, Metellus ouercame in Sicilie, the captayn of the Carthaginiens whiche came agaynſt them with a hundreth and .xxx. Elephantes, and a great power of men beſides. He ſlew The Cartha. dyſcomfyted. xx. M. men, and got .xxvi. Elephants. The reſidue of his ennemies which wer ſkatred and diſperſed amōg the Numidians, (whome he had to ayde him,) he got together &amp; brought thē priſoners with great triūph to Rome and as they wente, the herd of Elephants, whiche were a. C. and .xxx. in nomber ouerlayde all the way. The

The Carthaginiens after theeſe ſo great miſchances, required Regulus a captayne of the Romaynes (whom The Carthaſente regulus a romayne to 
                     •
                  ntreate for peace. before they hadde taken pryſonner,) that he would goo to Rome, and get peace for them of the Romains, and alſo exchaūge of priſoners. But Regulus when he was coe to Rome, and was broughte into the Senate, did in no poynt behaue himſelfe as a Romaine, affirming that frō the day that he firſt fel into the hands of the Carthaginiens, he gaue ouer clene ye deſire to be any longer a Romayne: in ſo much that he refuſed the cōpani of his owne wife at Rome: and perſwaded the Romaynes that peace ſhoulde by no meanes bee graunted to the Carthaginiens: alledgynge that their myndes were ſo quaylte wyth thoſe ſo manye miſchaunces, that they were quyte voyde of hope, that they ſhould euer be able to recouer againe their former eſtate.
            
               
And as for him, he was not worthye to be ſo muche eſteamed (being now very aged) that for his cauſe, and the redeminge of a fewe others whyche A notable example of loue towarde hys countrye. were detained priſonners, at Carthage, ſo many thouſand of their ennemies ſhould be reſtored. Whyche requeſt of his, at laſt the Romaynes aſſented vnto. In ſo muche that they woulde not geue eare to the petytyon of anye whiche came from Carthage, to entreat them for peace. Regulus ſone after, retourned to Carthage: whome the Romaynes offered to detaine ſtil at Rome. But hee denied that hee woulde remayne in that city, in which he could not now haue the name of an honeſt Citezen, ſith that he had ſo long bene among the Carthaginiens. Whome (after his retourne to Carthage,) the Carthaginiens with moſt cruel tormēts Regulus put to death. put to death. When Publius Claudius Pulcher, and Caius Iunius

were conſuls, Claudius in an euyll Pub. Clau. Pulcher, and Ca. Iunius Conſuls. Theromains dyſcomfyted. tyme, wyth no leſſe euill ſucceſſe, loughte a vattayle: and was ouercome by the Carthaginiens. For ſettynge forthe with two hundreth and twenty ſayle, he fled with .xxx. ſhyps only, lxxxx. wer taken together with the men whiche fought in them: and the reſidue were ſonke. There were beſides, xx. thouſand of the romaines taken priſoners. In lyke manner alſo The romaye nauy periſhed by ſhipwrack the other Conſull loſte his nauye by ſhipwracke: howe be it he ſaued hys armye, for that the ſhore was neare. At what time Caius Luctacius Catulus, and Aulius Poſthumius Ca. Luctatiꝰ Catu. &amp;. aul. Poſthu. albi. Conſuls. Albinus were conſulles, (whiche was in the .xxiii. yere after that battaile was fyrſte waged with the carthaginiens,) battail was committed to the guiding and orderinge of Catalus agaynſte the Africanes: who toke his viage into Sicilie, with thre hundreth ſayle: agaynſte whome the

Afers had prepared .cccc. ſayle ready furniſhed. This Catulus was ſome what ſickly when he toke ſhypping. For why, he was wounded in a battail a litle before. The battayle was fought ouer agaynſt Lylibeū a citye of Sicilie, with paſſyng greate valiantneſſe of the Romains. They toke lxxiii. of the Carthaginiens ſhippes: They ſanke a .c. and. xxv, they tooke The great ouerthrowe of the Carthaginians. xxxii. M. men priſoners: &amp; ſlue .xiii. M an infinite deale of golde and ſiluer broughte they to Rome: and of the Romayne nauye, only .xii. ſhips miſcaried, whyche wer ſonke. This battaile was done the .vi. of the Ides of Marche. The Carthaginiens forthe with deſired peace, and it was graū
               ted Peace graunted to the Carthaginiens. to them. Suche priſonners as the Carthaginiens had taken of the romaynes wer reſtored. And they deſired that they might raunſome ſuche priſoners as the romaynes had takē of theirs. The Senate therfore commaunded

that ſuche of the carthaginiens, as were priſonners in the cō
               mon holdes, ſhould be deliuered and ſent home without any raunſome: &amp; ſuch of them as priuate perſons had taken priſoners, ſhoulde be diſmyſte alſo: and that their raunſome ſhould bee anſwered (to thoſe whiche tooke them) forth of the common treſorye, The greate largeſſe of the romaynes. rather then the carthaginiens ſhuld be charged therwith. After this, wer Q. Luctatius, &amp; Aulus Manlius created conſuls. They waged battaile againſt Faliſci: which had bene ſome Q. luctatiꝰ &amp; Aulus Man. Conſuls. time a welthye city of Italye. Thys city they wan, within .vi. dayes after Faliſci beſieged and won. they layde the aſſaulte therto. They flew there .xv. M. men: to the reſidue they graunted peace, but they depriued them of the one moitye of theyr landes.
         
         
            
            ¶ The thyrde booke of the breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               WHen the battayle agaynſte the Carthaginiens was thus determined, which hadde continued by the ſpace of .xxii. yeres, the Romaynes (who were nowe become famouſe,) ſente Legates to Ptolomeus kynge of Egypt, proferynge to ayde hym, Ayd profered by the Romaynes to Ptolomeus. for that Antiochus kynge of Syria, warred agaynſte hym: hee thanked the Romaines for theyr gentleneſſe: howe be it hee receyued no ayde of them, for that the battayle was all ready finyſhed. About the ſame time Hiero the mighty and puiſſant kyng of Sicilie, came to Rome, to beholde Corne geuen among the romaynes by Hiero. the Enterludes there, and diſtributed among the people of Rome, two hundreth thouſand buſhels of wheat

Lucius Cornelius Lentulus, &amp; Fuluius Lu. Corne. Len. &amp; Ful. Flac. Con. Flaccus being Conſuls (during whoſe raigne Hiero came to Rome) battayle was waged againſt the Ligurians wythin Italy: and tryumph Battaile agaynſt the Ligurians. was had ouer them. At that time all ſo, the Carthaginiens attempted to renue battail: and perſwaded in like War renued by the Carthaginiens. manner the Sardinians to rebell, who ſhould haue bene ſubiect to the Romaines, for as muche as peace was concluded betwene them &amp; the Romayns vpon the ſame condition. Neuertheleſſe they ſente theyr Ambaſſadoures to Rome, and confyrmed Peace graunted to the Carthaginiens. Ci. Mau. Tor. and Ca. Atti. Balbus Conſuls. A triumph ouer the Sar. the peace againe. When Titus Manlius Torquatus, and Caius Attilius Balbus were Conſulles, the Romaynes triumphed ouer the Sardinians. Then the Romaynes concluded peace wyth all natyons, ſo ye now they had no maner batel in hād: which thinge neuer happened vnto them ſyth the firſte buildinge of the

citye of come, but at one time onlye: (whiche was) duringe the raygne of Numa Pompilius. When Lucius Poſthumius Albinus, and Fuluius Cneus Centumalus were conſulles Lu. Poſthu. Albi. &amp; Ful. Cueꝰ. Cen. Conſuls. they waged battayl agaynſte the Illyrians: and when they had takē manye cityes there, the kynges yelded them ſelues. And that was the fyrſte tryumphe that the romaynes euer The firſt triumphe ouer y• Illyrians. had ouer the Illyrians. Durynge the tyme that Emilius was Conſull, great armies of the Frenchmen wer Emilius conſull. Italy inuaded by the Frenchmen. come ouer the Alpes. Howe be it, all Italy ſtoode together in the defence of the romaynes. For as Fabius the Hiſtorician dooth report, (who was hymſelf preſent at that battai,) there were eyght hundreth thouſand men in a redineſſe for to haue fought that battayle. Neuertheleſſe the Conſull hym ſelfe ended that battail wyth greate dexteritye of fortune. He ſlew in that battayle forty thouſande ennemies:

and there was a tryumphe decreed vnto Emilius. A fewe yeres after, a battayl was fought againſt Emiliꝰ tryumphed. the Frenchmen wythin Italye, and it was doone by Marcus Claudius Marcellus, and Cneus Cornelius Scipio, beynge then conſulles. At Battayle agaynſte the Frenchmen. Mar. Clau. Mar. &amp; Cne. Corne. Sci. Conſuls. that ſame tyme, Marcellus hauynge wyth hym but a very ſmal troupe of horſemen, ſlewe the kynge of the Frenchmen (called Viridomarus,) wyth hys own hands. After he, and Viridomarꝰ kynge of the Frenchmen ſlain by Marcellus. Millayn conquered. his fellowe conſull, ſlewe greate armyes of the Frenchmen. He conque
               
                  •
               rd Millaine. He broughte an excea
               
                  •
               yng great ſpoyle with him home to Rome, and in his triumph he faſtned 
                  •
               he ſpoyles whyche he had gotten of Marcellꝰ tryumphed. the Frenche kinge, to a longe ſtaues 
                  •
               nde, and ſo bare it vppon hys owne 
                  •
               houlders. In the time that Mar
               
                  •
               us Minutius, and Publius Corne
               
                  •
               ius Mar. Min. &amp; Pub. Corne. Conſuls. War with y• Iſtrians. were Conſulles, warre was 
                  •
               aged ſore agaynſte the Iſtryans,

for that they had robbed and deſpoyled the ſhyppes of the Romaynes, which ſerued them with grayn. And they were quyte ſubdued. The ſelfe ſame yeare, the Carthaginiens waged The ſecond battayl of the Carthagi. againſt the Romains, in the 560. yeare after the citye was buylt, whych duted by the ſpace of .xvi. yeres. Saguntum aſſaulted by Annibal. theyr ſecond battayl againſt the Romaynes, by Anniball their capytaine, who attempted to aſſault Saguntum a city of Spayn, whych was in league and frendſhip whyche the Romaines. This Annibal was then of the age of .xx. yeres, and had in his army a hundreth and fifty thouſand horſemen, and twenty thouſand fotemen. The Romaines ſent ambaſſadoures to him, to wyll him to ceaſe from battayle. But hee woulde not ſpeake with the Legates: whervpon the Romaynes ſent likewiſe to Carthage, Howe lothe the Romains were to vſe force. deſiring that commaundemēt might be geuen to Anniball, that he ſhoulde no more warre vppon ſuche people as were frends and in league with the Romaynes. But they has

ſhreud anſweres geuen them by the Carthaginiens. In the mean ſeaſon the Saguntines were famiſhedde, whome Anniball (after he had gotte The Saguntines famiſhe by Annibal. the conqueſt ouer theym) afflyeted wyth extreme puniſhments. Vppon this, Publius Cornelius Scipio, wēt into Spayne wyth an army, and Tiberius Two armies ſent forthe by the romains. Sēpronius into Sicilie with an other, warre was proclaymed agaynſt the Carthaginiens. Anniball (leauinge his brother Aſoruball in Spayne,) hymſelfe paſſed ouer Pyreneus, makinge his waye ouer the Alpes: at which place as yet, no way laye. It was reported that he had in Annibal paſſed the alpes. hys army whiche he broughte wyth him into Italy, lxxx. M. footemenne, xx. M. horſemenne, and, xxxvii. Elephantes. In this ſpace, diuers Ligurianes and Frenchmen had aſſocyated them ſelues with Annibal. Sempronius Gracchus aſſone as he vnderſtode that Annibal was come into

Italy, he conueyed his army ouer Ariminus forth of Sicilie. Pub. Cor. Scipio firſt encountred with Annibal: his Scipio diſcō
                  fyted by Anniball. men wer put to flight, &amp; himſelf returned wounded to his tentes. Sēpronius Gracchus in like maner fought with him at the riner Trebia Semproniꝰ Gracchꝰ dyſcomfyted by Anniball. and was diſcomfited. Whervpon diuers in Italy for fear yelded thē ſelues to Annibal. And as he departed thence to Thuſcia, he met with Flaminius the Conſull whom he ſlewe. Flaminiꝰ the Conſul ſlayn by Annibal. There wer at that time .xxv. M. Romaines ſlain. The reſidue fled. After theſe things, Q. Fab. Max. was ſent by the Romaynes agaynſt Annibal. He by tracting the time and dalying brake the violence and force of Annibal: and efcſones finding oportunity, ſet vpon him and gaue him the ouer throw. In the .ccccc. and. xleyere after that the city of Rome was built, Lucius Anniball ſuſtayned the ouerthrowe by Q. Fa. max. Emilius, and Publius Terentius Varro, were ſent againſt Anniball,

and ſucceaded Fabius, whyche Fabius aduertiſed bothe the Conſulles that they could not otherwiſe Lu. Emiliꝰ and Publi. Terē. Varro Conſuls. ouercome Anniball (who was a hot and a haſtye warryoure,) but onlye by deferrynge and prolongynge the battayle. Howe be it, Varro verye raſhlye: contrary to the mynde of the other Conſull ioyned the battayle, and foughte at the Towne called Canne in Apulia: Wheras both the Conſulles were ouercome by Anniball. There were ſlayne in that battayle Bothe the Conſuls ouer come by Anniball. three hundreth Africanes: and a great parte of Anniball hys armye was wounded. But no battayle that The greateſt diſcomfyture that euer the Romains endured by the Carthagini. the Romaynes euer hadbe wyth the Carthaginiens, endamaged them ſo muche as this.
            For whye, there wer ſlain in that battaile, Emilius Paulus then conſull, and twentye other of the order of Conſulles and Pretoures:

of the Senators ther wer taken and ſlayne .xxx. noble men, to the nomber of three hundreth: ſoldioures to the noumber of .xl. M. and .iii. M. and fiue hundreth gentlemen beſides. For al whych great miſchaunce, there was not yet anye one among the Romaines whiche made anye mentyon of The greate ſtoutneſſe of the romayns. peace makinge with the Carthaginiens. The bondmen in Rome were made free, and appoynted for ſouldioures: The bondmē in Rome manumiſt. whyche thynge neuer hapned erſte there. After that battaile, many cities in Italye whiche before were vnder the obeyſaunce of the Romaines, fell from them to Anniball.
            Then Annibal profered the Romaynes that they ſhoulde redeame ſuche Annibal profered the Romaynes to redeme theyr pryſoners. The greate ſtoutneſſe of the romayns. ſouldioures of theyrs, as he had taken pryſonners. To whome the Romaynes and the Senators aunſwered that thoſe wer not to be accompted as neceſſary citizens, which whē they were armed, woulde bee taken

pryſonners: vppon whych aunſwer, Anniball ſlew them all wyth ſondry puniſhments, and ſent home to Carthage three buſhels full of rynges, which he pluckte of from the handes A paſſynge great murther of the romaynes. of the Gentlemen and Senatoures, and ſouldioures of the Romaynes. Aſdrubal alſo hys brother whom he lefte behynde him in Spaine wyth a greate armye (to the ende he myghte brynge all that country in ſubiection to the Africanes,) ſuſtained an ouerthrowe by the two Scipios whyche were captaines of the Romaines, he Aſdrubal ouercom by the ii. Scipioes. loſt in that battaile .xxxv. M. men, of whyche the Romaynes toke priſonners, x. M. and ſlewe .xx. M. But the Carthaginiens to ſtrengthen hym agayn, ſente him out of hand .xii. M. footemen, and. iiii M. horſemen, and xx. Elephants. In the .iiii. yere after that Anniball inuaded Italye, Marcus Claudius Marcellus then Conſul Mar. Clau. Marcel. Conſul. fought againſt him with paſſyng

good fortune at Nola a city of Cāpania. Annibal had by this time gotten many cities ther frō the Romains in Apulia, Calabria, &amp; among the Brutians. At that time, Phillip kynge of Macedonie by his Legates (whome he ſent to Anniball) profered that he Phillyp profered to ayde Anniball againſt the Romaynes. wold aid him againſt the Romains: Vpon condition that after he had ouercome the Romains, he mighte in like manner haue aſſiſtence of Anniball againſt the Grecians. But the Romaines by chaunce apprehended the Legates of king Phillip, and vnderſtode by them the whole matter. Where vppon, they willed Marcus Valerius Leuinus to go into Macedonie: and Titus Manlius Torquatus then being Proconſul, into Sardinia: for that Prouince alſo through the alluring of Anniball, was fallen from the Romains. And thus at one Battail waged in four ſeueral places by the Romaynes. time, fought the Romaines in foure ſeuerall places rogether. In Italy againſt

Annibal. In Spaine agaynſte his brother Aſdrubal. In Macebonie againſt Phillip. In Sardinia againſt the Sardinians, and an other Aſdruball a Carthaginien. This Aſdrubal was taken by Titus Manlius the Proconſull, who was ſent into Sardinia againſt him: he alſo ſlew there xii. M. of his ennemyes, and tooke a M. and D pryſonners. Thus was Sardinia ſubdued by the Romains, and Manlius as a conqueror brought Sardinia ſub dued by the romaynes. Aſdruball and thoſe other priſoners with him to Rome. In this whyle, Philip was alſo ouercome by Leuinus in Macedonie. And Aſdrubal the Phyllip ouer come. ſecōd brother to Annibal, and Mago his third brother wer by the ii Scipiocs Aſdrubal and mago ouercome. ouercome in Spain. In the tenth yere after yt Anniball inuaded Italy, at what time. Pub. Sul. &amp; Cne. Ful. wer conſuls, Annibal aproched with in. 4. miles of the city of Rome: &amp; his Pub. Sul. &amp; Cne. Fulu
                     •
                  ꝰ Conſuls. horſmē wer come to the very gates.

But forthwith for dread of the Conſuls whiche came againſt hym wyth a great hoſte, he retired back to Cā
               pania. Soone after, hys brother Aſdruball flewe hothe the Scipioes in Spayne: whyche by the ſpace of many The .ii. Scipio
                     •
                   ſlayn by Aſdruball in Spayne. yeares hadde bene conqueroures there. Neuertheleſſe, their army remayned whole. For why, they were rather beguiled by traine, then vanquiſhed by manhode. At this tyme, a great parte of Sicilie was recouered by Marcellus the Conſull: whyche countrey the Afers began as than to poſſeſſe: and from Siracuſa the moſt famous Citye therof, he broughte an exceadinge greate ſpoyle to Rome. Leuinus made league and ioyned frendſhip wyth Philippus Macedonie: Frendſhyp ioyned wyth Phillip by Leuinus. and with diuers other cityes in Grece beſides: &amp; with Attalus kinge of Aſia. And by the way as he wente marching toward Sicilie, he diſcomfyted and tooke priſoner Annones a

captain of the Carthaginiens, at the Annones taken priſoner. city Agrigentum, together wyth the city it ſelfe: and ſent him to Rome amonge thoſe other priſoners. There were yelded vp vnto him .xl. cityes. He conquered .xxvi. other cytyes. Thus when all Sicilie was recouered, and Macedonie in ſuch ſort ſhaken and quailde, hee retourned to Rome wyth greate renowme. Afterwarde Anniball aſſaultinge Cneus Cneus Fuluius ſlayn by Annibal. Fuluius at vnwares beinge then in Italye, ſlue him and viii. M. men beſydes. In the meane ſpace, Publius Pub. Corne. Scipio ſente into Spayne. Cornelius Scipio ſonne of Publius Scipio, was ſent into Spayn: where (after that the two Scipioes were ſlayne,) no captaine of the Romains was lefte. He waged battaile there, beinge but of the age of .xxiiii. yeres. One who of all the Romaynes that were eyther in his dayes or anye Great commendation of Scipio. tyme ſith, might worthely be adiudged the chiefeſt.
            
               
He wan Carthage in Spayn, where the Affricanes hadde all theyr golde and Siluer, and furniture for warre Carthage in Spayn won. remayninge. Furthermore he ſente to Rome, the mooſte noble hoſtages which he had receiued of the Spaniardes. He toke alſo priſonner, Mago Annibal his brother, and ſent him to mago ſent prisoner to rome Rome with the reſidew. There was great myrth demeaned at Rome after theeſe newes. Scipio reſtored to theyr parentes, theyr ſonnes whom he had receiued for pledges before. Where vppon, in manner all the Spanyardes wyth one aſſente tooke part with Scipio againſte Anniball. After theſe thynges, he ſubdued and put to flight Aſdruball Anniball hys brother, and got ther a great ſpoyle. Aſdrubal diſcomfited. In this meane ſpace, Quintus Fabius Maximus the Conſull, (beynge as then in Italye) recouered Tarentum, in whiche wer then remaining Tarentum recouered. greate armies of Annibal: and there

he ſlewe alſo Carthalon captayne to Anniball. He ſold .xxv. thouſand priſoners, and deuided the ſpoyl among Carthalō ſlayne. his ſouldioures, and the mony which he receiued for the men whyche hee ſolde, he brought to the common treſor of the Romaines. Then many cities of the Romaines whiche earſte had yelded them ſelues to Anniball, did againe ſubmitte them ſelues to Fabius Maximus. The yere following, Scipio wroughte notable feates Scipio, hys good ſucceſſe in his affairs in Spain: there he (what through the ayde of his brother Lucius Scipio, &amp; what throughe hys owne valiauntneſſe,) recouered .lxx. cities. Howbeit they had euil ſucceſſe in that battaile which they fought in Italy. For why Claudius Marcellus being then conſull) Clau. mar. conſul ſlayne. was ſlayne there by Anniball. In the third yere after yt, Scipio wēt again into Spain, and atcheued worthy things there. He vanquiſhed the kynge of Spayne in a great battail, The kyng of Spayne dyſcomfyted.
               
and afterwarde concluded frendſhyp wyth him, wythoute requyryng any pledges of him after hee was ſubdued, wheras all others vſed after they had vanquyſht anye, to take pledges of them whome they hadde ſo ouercome. Then Anniball fearynge that he ſhould not be able anye longer to detayne Spain againſt Scipio, or to wythſtande hys force, ſente for hys Aſdrubal ſent for forthe of Spayne. brother Aſdruball withall his army from thence. And as Aſdruball wold haue paſſed that ſame way as Anniball did forthe of Spayne into Italy warde, he fell into the embuſhmētes whyche of ſet purpoſe were layd for hym by Appius Claudius Nero, and Aſdruball ſlayne. Marcus Liuius Salinator: at which place manfully fightinge and defendyng hym ſelfe, hee was ſlayne: and hys great army whyche he had wyth hym, was al together taken eyther or ſlaine: and a greate quantitye of treaſure was brought to Rome.

after thoſe thynges, Anniball began cleane to deſpaire of the ſucceſſe of the battail: and courage accrewed &amp; grew to the Romains. Whervppon they ſent for Publius Coruelius Scipio Scipio ſent for forthe of Spayne. forthe of Spaine: who came to Rome wyth greate glorye. When Quintus Cecilius and Lucius Valerius were conſuls, all thoſe cityes amonge Q. Cecilius and L. Valeriꝰ Conſuls. the Brutians, whiche before fell from the Romaines to Annibal, yelded them ſelues again to the Romaines. In the .xiiii. yeare after that Annibal had inuaded Italye, Scipio who had luckely atcheued things in Scipio created Conſul. Spayne: was created conſull, and ſēt into Affricke. This Scipio was adiudged to be inſpired with ſome deuine ſpirite. In ſo much that menne thought he had conference with the celeſtiall powers. He foughte in Africke againſt Annon a captayne of the Carthaginiens and ſlew hys army. In the ſecond battayl he toke his

tentes, and .iiii. M. and .v. C. ſoldiers, and ſlew .xi. M. He tooke Siphar. the king of Numidie priſoner, who had ioyned himſelfe in ayde wyth the Afers: and inuaded his tentes &amp; ſackte Syphar king of Numidie take pryſoner. them: and ſent Siphar together with the mooſte noble men of Numidie to Rome and an infinite ſpoyl: whiche thynge ſo ſone as it was vnderſtode, all Italy wel nygh forſoke Annibal, whome the Carthaginiens wylled to retourne and ſuccoure Affrycke, Annibal willed to retourn home into Afrycke. whyche as then Scipio deſpoyled. Thus in the .xvii. yere all Italy was deliuered from the terrour of Anniball. The Legates of the Carthaginiens deſired peace of Scipio: and by him they were ſente to Rome to the Peace deſired by the Carthaginiens. Senate. Truce was made with thē duringe the ſpace of .xl. daies: vntyll ſuche tyme as they might repayre to Rome, and retourne from thence agayne. In conſideratyon where of, they gaue the Romains .xxx. thouſād

poundes. And when they hadde exponed their cauſe to the Senate▪ anſwer was made to them, that accordinge to the aduiſe of Scipio, peace ſhould be graunted them, referryng the matter wholly to Scipio: by whō it was graunted vpon theſe condityons. That they ſhoulde geue the Romains fiue C. thouſand pounds of ſiluer: and that they ſhould moreouer, The conditions of peace with the Carthaginiens. raſtore to the Romaynes ſuche pryſoners as they had taken of theyrs, and ſuche as were fled from the Romaines to them.
            While theſe things wer in talk, Annibal as he retourned into Africk, infringed the league, for he and hys armye wroughte diuers thynges by The lege broken by Anniball. the way as they wente, contrarye to the peace concluded vppon, and as ennemyes. The Legates of the Carthaginyens were apprehended by the Romaynes: as they retourned from Rome.
            
               
But they were by the commaundement of Scipio ſtraightway diſmiſte againe. Not long after, Annibal himſelfe being ſore wearyed with thoſe contynuall battailes, deſired peace: Annibal deſired peace. whiche when it came to bee treated of, it was graunted vppon the ſame conditions as it was before: and to the precedent conditions of payment of .v. M. poundes of ſiluer, was annexed the penaltye of paymente of a C. M. poundes beſides, for that newe breche of league by him committed. The conditions diſpleaſed the Carthaginiens. Wher vpon they willed Annibal to fighte it out. Warre was waged againſte the Carthaginiens, The condityons of the peacemiſliked the Carthaginiens. by Scipio, and Maſiniſſa kynge of the Numidians, who hadde ioyned frendſhip with the Romaines. Annibal ſent three eſpies to the tentes of Scipio: whiche when they were apprchended by the Romaines, Scipio commaunded they ſhould be ledde about

through the tentes, and that all hys army ſhould be ſhewed them. Then that they ſhuld be feaſted, and ſo diſmiſt, to the end they mighte recount to Anniball, what they hadde ſeene amonge the romaynes. In the meane time, preparaunce of battaile was made by the captaines on cche partye, ſuche as vnneth anye man coulde euer remember the lyke. At whyche time bothe thoſe expert men of warre and valiaunte captains led forthe theyr armies into the fielde. Scipio retourned conqueror: and at that time hadde he well nyghe taken Anniball gretly diſcōlyted. Anniball him ſelfe alſo: who at the firſt eſkaped and fled wyth a greate company of horſmen: but being purſued, they were all ſlaine, ſauing .xv. Annibal ſuſtaind a great ouer throw. only. And at the laſt, he fled but with iiii. alone. There was founde in the tentes of Anniball, xx. M. poundes of ſiluer, and of golde eyghte hundreth Peace graueted to the Carthaginiens. thouſand: of other ſtuffe great ſtore.

After that ſkirmiſhe, peace was concluded with the Carthaginiens: Scipio retourned to Rome, and wyth Scipio tri
                     ••
                  
                  phed and was called Affricanus. The ſecond battayl wyth the Carthaginiēs finiſhed. greate glorye triumphed: and from that tyme was he called Africanus. Thus was the ſeconde battail with the Carthagidiens finiſhed in the .xix. yere after the firſt commencement therof. ¶ (⸫) ⁋
         
         
            
            ¶ The fourth booke of the Breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               WHen the battaile againſt the Carthaginiens was finyſhed, there enſued battaile in Macedonie agaynſt Phillip who was kig ther. In the .ccccc. and .li. yere after ye buildinge of the Citye Titus Quintius Flaminius was ſent againſte kyng Titus Quintius Flaminius ſent agaīſt Phillip. Phillip, and hadde good ſucceſſe. He graunted peace to Phillip vpō theſe conditions: That he ſhuld not make war vpon any of thoſe cities whyche were by ye Romains receiued vnder Peace graunted to Phillip protection: y• he ſhould moreouer reſtore al ſuch Romains as he had takē priſoners, &amp; ſuch as had fled alſo frō thē to him: &amp; that he ſhould kepe but l. ſhips only: the reſidue of his fleete he ſhuld deliuer vp to the Romains.

Furthermore, that he ſhoulde yerely by the ſpace of .x. yeres, pay to the romaynes .iiii. M. pounds of ſiluer, and deliuer him his ſonne Demetrius for a pledge, for performance of theſe couenauntes. Titus Quintius waged battel alſo agaynſte the Lacedemonians, and vanquiſhed their captaine Battayle agaynſt the Lacedemonians. Nabides: who ſubmitted hymſelfe to Quintius vpon what condityons he would. And as he returned Nabides yelded himſelfe. thence homeward with great glory, there were led before hys charyotte, the worthy hoſtages whyche he had gotten, (that is to wete) Demetrius ſonne to king Phillip, and Armenes Nabides hys ſonne: After that the Macedonian battayle was finyſhed, there enſued warre in Siria againſt Warre in Syria. kynge Antiochus: During the tyme that Publius Cornelius Scipio and Marcus Attilius Glabrio wer Conſuls. Pub. Corne. Scipio, and M. Attilius Glabrio Conſuls. Annibal toke part wyth Antiochus, forſakynge hys owne countrye

for feare leaſte that hys renuynge of battaile mighte ſeme to haue bene a breche of the league before made betwene hys country men and the Romaynes. Marcus Attilius Glabria had good ſucceſſe in Achaia: He inuaded and tooke the tentes of kynge Antiochus by nyght▪ and put hym to flyght: and for that Phillip ayded the romaynes againſt Antiochus, he deliuered vnto him his ſonne Demetrius. Demetrius reſtored to his farther kyng Phillyp. when Lucius Cornelius Scipio and Caius Lelius were conſuls, Scipio who was alſo ſurnamed Africanus was ſente vnto his brother Lucius Cornelius Scipio, then conſull, to aide him againſt Antiochus: Anniball who was wyth Antiochus on hys ſyde, was dyſcomfited in battel vpon the ſea. Afterwarde, Antiochus Annibal diſcomfyted in battayl on the ſea. hymſelfe was put to flyghte in a very greate battaile, by Cornelius Scipio the Conſul at Sipilus Magneſia a City of Aſia. Eumenes king Antiochus put to flyght.
               
Attalꝰ his brother, who builded Eumenia in Phrigia, aided ye Romains in ye battail. There wer ſlain in that battaile on king Antiochus his ſide, l. M. footemen, and .iiii. M horſmen. Then king Antiochus deſired peace, whych the Senate graunted hym vpon Antiochus deſired peace. the ſame conditions as they dyd tofore, (thoughe he was nowe ouercome:) which was that he ſhoulde auoid forth of Europe and Aſia, &amp; medle no farther but wythin ye precinet of Taurus: Moreouer ye he ſhoulde geue to the Romains .x. M. talentes, and .xxx. pledges for thaſſurans of his promeſſe. And finally that he ſhould deliuer Anniball to them, who had bene the only procurer of ye battaile. Then the Senate gaue to Eumenesal The liberality of the Romaynes. thoſe cities of Aſia which Antiochꝰ had loſt in battel: and diuers other cities wer alſo graūted to ye Rhodians for yt they had aſſiſted the Romains againſt Antiochꝰ. Scipio thē returned

to Rome, and with great glory triū
               phed: and obtained alſo a ſurname like as his brother had before: which Scipio triumphed, &amp; was called Aſiaticus. was, to be called Aſi
                  •
               a
                  ••
               ꝰ for the ſubduīg of Aſia, like as his brother was called Africanꝰ for that he conquered Affrick. When S. Poſthumiꝰ Albinꝰ and Q. Martiꝰ Philippꝰ wer Cōſuls, Marcꝰ Fuluius triumphed ouer the S. Poſthumius Albinꝰ, and Q Martius Philippus Conſuls 
               
                  ••
               etolians. Aſſone as Antiochꝰ was ouercome, (Annibal fearing leaſt he ſhould be deliuered to the Romains) fled to Pruſias kinge of Bythinia: at Anniball fled to Pruſias kyng of Bithinia. whoſe hands he was required again by T Quintus Flaminiꝰ. Whervpon, when he ſaw ther was no remedy, but that he ſhoulde come into the handes of the Romaines: he dranke Annibal poyſonned hymſelfe. poyſone, and ſo died: and lyeth buryed at Lybiſſa, whiche is in the bor
               
                  •
               ers of the Nicomedienſes. Sone after Phillip died alſo: who had bothe 
                  •
               varred agaynſt the Romaynes, and Phillip dyed. aſſyſted them alſo againſt Antiochꝰ:

Thē his ſonne Perſeus rebelles in Macedonie: where he had aſſembled a greate army readye appoynted and furniſhed for warre: whome Cotis Warre renued in Macedony by Perſeꝰ kyng there. king of Illiria, aided againſt the Romaines. But the Romaines had to aſſyſt them, Eumenes king of Aſia: Atlarates kinge of Cappadocia: Antiochus kynge of Syria, Ptolomeus king of Egipte: and Maſiniſla kynge of Numidia. But Pruſias kynge of Bithinia, although he had eſpouſed the ſiſter of Perſeꝰ, yet he demeaned himſelf indifferently betwene bothe partes, helping neither of thē bothe. Publius Licinius who was then Conſul, was deputed captayn on the P Licinius the Conſull vanquyſhed. Romains ſide, and was vanquiſhed by the kinge, in a great battaile. Yet would not the Romaines graunt the kinge peace when he deſired it, (all though they them ſelues had ſuſtained the ouerthrowe at his handes,) but vppon condition that he woulde

ſubmit him ſelfe, and all his, to the Senate and the people of Rome. Sone after, Lucius Emilius Paulꝰ the Conſull was ſent againſte him, L. Emilius Paulus Conſull. and Caius Anitius the Pretor was ſente into Illyria againſte Gentius. But Gentius was eaſely ouercome in one battail: and ſhortly after, yelded himſelfe. His mother, his wyfe, hys two ſonnes and his brother, wer taken priſonners by the Romaynes. And thus wythin the ſpace of .xxx. dayes, was that battayle ended. For the Romaines knew that they ſhuld haue the vpper hande ouer Gentius or euer that they had ioyned battayle wyth him. Paulus Emilius the Cō
               ſul, fought with Perſeus the fourthe Perſeus ouercome. day of Septēber and ouercame him. There were then ſlaine on Perſeus his ſide .xx. M. fotemen. But ye whole troupe of horſe men remained ſafe with the king. The Romains loſt in that battaile a hundreth ſouldiours.

All the cityes of Macedonie whyche the kynge poſſeſſed, ſubmytted themſelues to the Romaines. The kynge when he vnderſtode, ye his frends had forſaken him, yelded himſelf to Paulus Perſeus yelded hymſelf to the Romaynes. Emilius, by whō he was entreted honorably, &amp; not as a vanquiſhed man. For when the king wold haue proſtrate himſelf at Paulꝰ his feete, he did not onli refuſe that he ſhuld ſo Notable clemency of Emilius. ſubmit himſelfe, but placed him in a chaire faſt beſides him. He graunted ye Macedonians and the Illyrians, yt they ſhould from thence forwarde befre. And that they ſhould be charged with the payment but of thone moity of thoſe tributes and impoſitions whyche they were before aſſeſſed to paye to theyr kinges: To the ende it mighte appeare, that the Romaines The Romaines contented myndes wyth ſmal lucre. warred more for equity (&amp; iuſtice, thē for auarice and deſire of luere: which words, Paulꝰ pronounced a great aſſemble of people: and at that time he

deſired thambaſſadors of ſondry nations which were with him to an exceding ſumptuous feaſt: affirming yt it appertained to a man to ſhew himſelf not only victorious in battayle, but that it was alſo ſitting for him to be neat and expert in feaſtynge and entertaining of ſtraūgers. Sone after, he receiued againe vnder obeyſaunce .lxx. cityes of Epirus, whyche before had rebelled. He diſtributed ye ſpoyle among the ſouldiours. Then returned he again to Rome, in a ſhip of king Perſeus, whiche was reported to be of a meruelous greatneſſe, ſo y• as the report went, it had .xvi. rowes of ores. He triūphed royally, caried in a golden chariote with his .ii. ſonnes ſtandyng on eche ſide of him. Ther werled before his chariot, the kings .ii. ſons &amp; Perſeꝰ himſelf being Emilius triumphed. of thage of .xlv. yeres. Ther folowed lying in y• triūph Caiꝰ Anitius, who then alſo triūphed ouer y• Illirians.
            
               
Gentius and his brother, and hys ſonnes, were led before his charyot. There came to Rome kynges for the of ſondrye countries to beholde thys ſight. Amonge whome wer Attalus In what admiratyon the Romaines were had of ſtraungers. and Eumenes kinges of Aſia, and Pruſias king of Bithinia, who were receiued and entreted by ye Romains very honorably: and through the permiſſyon and ſufferaunce of the Senate, the giftes and preſents whiche they brought with them, were ſet vp in the Capitoll. And Pruſias cōmitted his ſonne Nicomedes to the gouernment and ordering of the Senators. In the yeare folowing, Lucius Manlius fought a battaile in Spain, wyth good ſucceſſe. And after hym, Marcellus the Conſull hadde good chaunce there alſo. Then was the thirde battaile taken in hand againſt the Carthaginiens, in the yere after The thyrde battail agaīſt the Carthaginiens. the building of Rome, ſixe hundreth and one: at which time, Lucius Manlius

Cenſorinus, and Marcus Manlius were Conſuls: whiche in the .li. yere after that the ſecond battaile againſt them was finiſhed. The Conſuls toke then their viage to inuade Carthage. Aſdruball a captain of the Carthaginiens was ſente forthe againſt them, and Famea an other of theyr captaines had the conductynge of the horſmen: At that time, Scipio who was neue we to Scipio Africanus, was by the Romaynes deputed generall of the army. Hym did al the army bothe reuerence and feare. For why, he was a captaine paſſing redy Notable cō
                  mendation of Scipio. in battail, and therwithal very cyrcumſpect. Through whoſe pollicyes the Conſuls atcheued many thinges very fortunately. And there was nothing that ether Aſdrubal or Famea ſo much ſought to auoid, as they did to fight againſt that wing of the Romaine Miſiniſſa deceaſed. armye where Scipio was. Aboute this time, died Miſiniſſa, who

was in league wyth the Romaynes, after that he had liued .lxxxxvii. yeres and lefte behinde him .xliiii. ſonnes. Amonge whome, he appoynted Scipio, to diſtribute his kingdōe. No we when as the name and renowne of Scipio waxed famous, he was created Conſul, being as yet but a yong man: and was ſent forthe to aſſaulte Carthage. He wan it and pluckte it Carthage aſſaulted by Scipio. downe to the ground. Suche ſpoyles as he founde there, (whych the Carthaginiens before time had gottē at the ſubuerſion of diuers Cities,) together wyth the monuments of ſondry townes of Sicilie, he reſtored again to thoſe cityes, from whence ye ſaid ſpoils wer taken: Amōg which, euery city knew ſuch things as ſomtime had ben their owne. Thus was Carthage ouerthrown in the .vii. C. yere after that it was firſt built. Scipio Scipio merited to be called Africanus the yonger. merited to haue the name which hys graundfather before him wan,

(whych was, for his valiantnes and proweſſe to be called Affricanus the yonger.) In this mean ſpace, one vſurping falſly vpon him the name of Phillip, attēpted war againſt ye. Romains in Macedonic: &amp; gaue Publiꝰ Iuuencius pretor of Rome, the ouerthrow, who was ſent againſt hym: &amp; Iuuencius diſcomfyted. made ſuch ſlaughter of his men, that ſkāt he let one eſkape a liue of al hys army. After him, Q. Ceciliꝰ Metellꝰ was deputed captain, &amp; ſent forth againſt this falſ named Phillip. Who when he had ſlain .xxv. M. of his mē, recouered Macedonie, and toke pryſonner the ſayde Phillippe. At this tyme warre was alſo proclaymed agaynſte Corinthus, the worthieſt citye of all Grece, for thal they had iniuried Corinthus ouer throwne. the Legates of the Romains. Mummius the Conſull wan it, and pluckte it downe to the ground. And ſo were ther thre notable triumphes Thre tryumphes at ones at Rome. had together at one tyme at Rome.

The one by Scipio, forth of Affrick: before whoſe chariot Aſoruball was led. An other, by Metellus forthe of Macedonie, before whoſe charyotte Andriſcus was led, whiche was that falſe named and counterfaited Phillip. The third triumph was by Mū
               mius ouer the Corinthiaus: before whome were caried the braſen enſignes, and painted tables, and other the ornaments of that moſte famous city. There was yet againe another, who falfly named himſelfe Perſeus in Macedonie: affirminge that hee was ſonne to that other Perſeus of whome we ſpake before: whē he had aſſembled an armye of bondmen, to the nomber of .xvii. M. men of armes he was conquered by Tremillus the Perſeus conquered by Tremillus. Queſtor. At the ſame time, Metellꝰ atcheued notable enterpriſes in Biſkay awong the Spanyardes. Quintus Pompeius ſucceaded him there. And not long after, Quintus Cepio

was alſo ſent forth againſte one Viriatus, which waged battail in Portugale againſte the Romaines. But Battaile in Portugale by one Viriatus Viriatus his men, dreadinge ye force of the Romaines, ſlewe Viriatus: which was he that had ſtirred vp the Spaniards to warre againſt the Romaines, by the ſpace of xiiii. yeares. This Viriatus was firſt a ſhepherd, ſone after, he became a Captayne amonge robbers and theues: And at ye laſte, he ſtirred vp ſuche nations to warre againſte the Romaines, that he became to be called Protector of Spaine againſte the Romaines.
            Then they who ſlewe this Viriatus, The Romaines deteſted treaſon. demaunded of Cepio the Cō
               ſull, what reward they ſhoulde haue for their fact. Who anſwered that it neuer pleaſed the Romains, to haue any captaine ſlaine by his own ſouldioures. Q. Pompeiꝰ the Conſul ouercome Then was Quintus Pompeius, who was alſo Conſul, diſcomfited by the citezens of Numantia:

whiche was the worthieſt Citye of Spain: and made with thē a reprochful peace. After him Caius Hoſtilius I reprochfull league. Mancinus the Conſull, made againe with the Numantines, an infamous Caius Hoſtiliꝰ Mancinꝰ the Conſull dyſcomfyted. league. But the Senate &amp; people of Rome, cōmaunded forthwith that y• peace ſhuld be infringed, &amp; that Mancinus ſhould be deliuered to his enemies, to thend they might wreke the iniury of the breche of peace on hym who was ye autor of making ye ſame. After this ſo great infamye, that the people of Rome wer twiſe diſcōfited by the Numantines, Publius Scipio P. Scipio Conſul. (who was alſo named Affricanus,) was created Conſul the ſecond time: and was ſent to Numātia: He by exerciſing and wel trading vp the Romaine Souldioures rather then by puniſhinge them, refourmed theym very wel, who through the guidinge of euill captaines were now become ſlouthfull and cowardly. Sone after

be gotte manye cityes in Spayne: of which, ſome he wan in battayl: ſome were yelded vp to hym. At lengthe, after that he had of long time beſyeged Numantia, he famiſhed it, and ſo wan it. The reſidue of that prouince, he receiued vnder protection. At that time, Attalus king of Aſia brother to kynge Eumenes died, and made the people of Rome his heire: And ſo by Teſtament was Aſia annexed to the Empire of the Romaines. Not long after, Decimus Iunius Brutus, triumphed with greate glorye ouer the Caleſianes and the Portugals: and Publius Scipio Africanus had hys ſeconde triumphe whiche was ouer the Numantines in the .xiiii. yere after that he had firſte triumphed ouer Affricke. In this meane ſpace, Ariſtonicus ſonne to Eumenes whome Warre in Aſia by Ariſtonicus. he begat vpon his concubine ſtirred vp warre in Aſia. That Eumenes was brother to kyng Attalus.
            
               
There was ſene againſt this Ariſtonicus, Publius Lucinius Craſſus, who was aided of ſondrye kinges. For whye, Nicomedes kinge of Bythinia, Mithridates king of Pontus, (betwene whome and the Romains was waged afterwardes moſt ſharp and cruel warre), Ariarathes kynge of Cappadocia, and Pilemenes king of Paphlagonia aſſiſted the Romaines. Howe be it, Craſſus was ouercome and ſlaine in that bataile, hys head was ſtricken of and brought to Craſſꝰ ſlayn. Ariſtonicus: and his body was buried at Smirne. Afterward Perpemia Conſull of Rome, (who ſucceaded Craſſus) hearinge of the ſucceſſe of the battaile, haſted towardes Aſia: he vanquiſhed Ariſtonicus in battail Ariſtonicus vanquyſhed. and enforced him to flee to the citye Stratonice: where famiſhinge hym he cauſed him to yelde. This Ariſtonicus was thratled in priſone by the commaundement of the Senate, for

that Perpenna coulde not tryumphe Perpenna the Conſul dyed. ouer him, becauſe he died at Troye, by the waye as he retourned homewardes. Lucius Cecilius Metellus, and Titus Quintius Flaminius being L. Cecilius Metellus &amp; T. Quintius Flaminius Conſuls. Carthage reedefyed. Conſuls, Carthage was by the commaundement of the Senate reedified in Africke: (which doth yet to this daye remaine) in the .xxii. yeare after that it was ouerthrowen by Scipio. Thither wente dyuers Citizens of Rome to dwell, In the .vi. C. and .xxvii. yere after the buyldinge of the city of Rome, Caius Caſſius Lō
               ginus, and Sextus Domitius Caluinus, were created Conſuls. They waged battayle agaynſt the Frenchmen, Battayle agaynſte the Frenchmen. which inhabited on the farther ſide of the Alpes: and agaynſte the mooſte noble city of the Auernians: and againſt Bituitus kynge there. They ſlew an infinite multitude of A greate ſlaughter by the Romaine of frenche men. frenchmen, faſt by ye riuer of Roane. There was broughte to Rome a

great treſor of the very chains only, which wer gottē at the deſpoiling of ye frenchmen. Bituitꝰ yelded himſelf to Domitiꝰ, and was by him brought vnto Rome: &amp; with great glory both the Conſuls triūphed. When Marcꝰ M. Portius Cato, and Q. Mar
                     •
                  ius Conſul. Portiꝰ Cato, &amp; Quintꝰ Martiꝰ Rexwer Conſuls, which was in the .vi. c. and .xxxiii. yere after the building of the city of Rome, Narbona in Fraū
               ce, Narbona inhabited. was inhabited and ſtored wyth people. Afterwarde when Luciꝰ Metellus and Quintus Mutius Sceuola L. Metellus and Q. Mutius Sceuola Conſuls. were Conſuls, they triumphed ouer a great part of Slauonia, which is now called Dalinatia. In the vi .c. and .xxxv. yere after the buildynge of the citye of Rome, Caius Cato then Caius Cato Conſul. Conſul, warred againſt the Scordiſcians, wyth great reproche to hym. When Caius Cecilius Metellꝰ, and The two Metelli tryumphed. Ca. Cecilius Metellus. &amp; Cne. Carbe Cenſuls. Cneus Carbo wer Conſuls, the two brothers Metelli triumphed both in one day. The one ouer Thracia, and

the other ouer Sardinia. About that tyme, newes came to Rome, that the Danes and people of Norway were The Danes aryued in Italy. ariued in Italye. When Publiꝰ Scipio Naſica and Lucius Calphurnius Beſtia were Conſuls, warre was P. Scipio Naſica, &amp; L. Calphurnius Beſtia Conſuls. waged agaynſte Iugurthe kynge of the Numidians, for that he had ſlain Adherbal and Hiempſal, Micipſa his ſonnes, and brothers to Iugurthe, whyche were eache of them kynges and frendes to the Romains. There W
                     ••
                   agaynſt Iugurth. was ſent agaynſt him, Calphurnius Beſtia the Conſull: who beinge corrupted wyth money which the kyng gaue hym, concluded a dyſworſhipfull peace wyth him: whiche was by the Senate forthe wyth infrynged agayne. In the yeare folowyng, Spurius Albinus Poſthumius was alſo ſent agaynſte Iuxsgurth: who foughte likewyſe agaynſte the Numidians with greate diſhonoure, committing the battaile to his brothers guiding.

Then thirdlye there was deputed to goo againſt him, Quintus Cecilius Metellus the Conſul, who reformed Q. Cecilius Metellus Conſuil. the armye with greate ſobrietye and wiſdom: vſing no manner of rigour or cruelty to any man: but by lenitye reduced them to the valiant courage of the Romayns. He diſcomfited Iugurth in ſondrye battailes: He ſlewe and tooke all his Elephantes: and when he was now at the very poynt Iugurth diſcomfyted. to haue finiſhed hys battayls, Caius Marius ſucceded him, and ouercame bothe Iugurthe, and alſo Bocchus kyng of Mauritania, who aſſiſted Iugurth. Iugurth and Bocchus vanquyſhed. He wan ſondry towns in Numidia, and ſo finiſhed hee thoſe battayles: Then Iugurth was taken by Lucius Sylla lieuetenaunt general of the army: a man of greate proweſſe and ſtoute courage, to whome Bocchus delyuered Iugurth: whoſe Iugurth taken. part before he had taken agaynſt the Romaynes. At this tyme theeſe tryumphes

were had at Rome. One, by Marcus Iunius who vanquiſhed the Danes in Fraunce. An other, by Minutius Rufus, who ouercame the Scordiſcians and Triballiās in Macedonie. And an other by Seruilius Fiue tryumphs at Rome together. Cepio, who ſubdued the Portugales in Spayn: and two other triumphes whyche were gotten ouer Iugurth. The one by Metellus, and the other by Marius. But Iugurthe with hys two ſonnes was led pryſoner before the charyot of Marius fettred in Iugurth thratled in pryſon. chains: and within a while after, he was by the cō
               maundement of ye Conſuls thratled in pryſon. ¶ (⸫) ⁋
         
         
            
            ¶ The fyfthe booke of the Breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               IN ye meane while that battaile was waged in Numidia agaynſte Iugurth the Romain Conſuls Marcus M. Manliꝰ and Q. Cepio Conſuls. Manlius and Quintus Cepio were ouercome by the Danes, the Almaines, the Swyſers, and Ambroues: whiche (were people of Germanye, and Fraunce.) They had thys ouerthrow faſt beſides the riuer of Roan: where was made ſo greate ſlaughter of them, that there eſkaped ſkant one away a liue. And well nigh they had loſte at that time, theyr tentes A great ouer throw of the Romaynes. and the moſt parte of theyr armye. Here vppon, ſo greate feare inuaded the Romaines, as vnneathe they ſuſtained the like whileſt Anniball liued,

and the Carthaginian battayle yet endured: (doubtynge not a lyttle, leaſte the Frenche men ſhoulde agayne haue gotten the Citye of Rome).
            Where vppon, Marius after that Marius aſſined to fight battaile with the Danes. he hadde gotte the victorye ouer Iugurthe, was created Conſull the ſeconde tyme, and appoynted to goo forthe to battayl agaynſt the Danes and Almaynes: And for that this battayle with the dayes contynued ſtill, he was made Conſul the thirde and fourthe time alſo. But in the fourthe yeare of his Conſulſhyppe, Quintus Luctatius Catulus was deputed to be his collegue. Where vppon, he ioyned battayle wyth the Danes: and in two battayles he ſlewe two hundreth thouſande of The Danes greatiye diſcom
                     •
                  yeed. hys ennemyes. He tooke foure ſkore thouſande pryſonners: and their captayne Theutobodus wyth them priſonners.
            
               
For whyche facte, he was in hys abſence, made Conſul the fifth time. In this while, the Danes and Almains of whome there remayned as yet great ſtore in thoſe parties, wer paſſed ouer into Italy: with whom Caius Marius, and Quintus Catulus encountred agayne: but the matter fell forthe more luckely on Catulus his ſide. For in that battayle whyche Marius and Catulus fought ioyntly together, there were ſlayne of theyr aduerſaries, (what in fighte, &amp; what as they fled,) to the noumber of a C. and .xl. M. men. And there wer taken priſonners lx. M. beſides. And of the Romayne ſouldioures, were ſlain of eyther army, no mo but .ccc. men only. There were won in that battayle from the Danes .xxxiii. auncients: of The battayle wyth the Dance and Almaynes finyſhed. Bothe the Conſuls tryumphed. whiche Marius hys hoſte wan two, and Catulus hys armye .xxxi. Thus was that battayle finiſhed, and a triumphe graunted too eyther of the

Conſuls. When Sextus Iulius Ceſar and Lutius Martius Philippus were Conſuls, in the .vi. C .l. and lr. S. Inlius Ceſar, and L. Martiꝰ Philippus Conſuls. yere after that the citye was built, &amp; that now all other battayles were almoſt fully ended, the Picentines, the Scithians, and the Pelignians began a greuous battaile in Italy: who A greuous battayl in Italy. when of longe time they had beene ſubiect, and vnder the obeyſaunce of the Romaynes, they began nowe to clayme equall and like libertye with the Romaynes them ſelues. Thys was a very daungerous battayle. In it Publius Rutilius the Conſull ſlain. Cepio a worthy yong man and P. Rutilius, and Portiꝰ Cato Cōſuls and Cepioſlayne. Portius Cato the other conſul were ſlayne alſo: Captaines agaynſte the Romaines on the Picentines and Seythians ſide, wer Titus Vietius, Hierus Aſinius, Titus Herennius, and Aulus Cluentius. And Caius Marius on the behalf of the Romaines, Marius vi. times Conſul a rowe. ſought againſt them with exceding

proſperous fortune. Mariꝰ had now bene .vi. times Conſull. There was ſent with him alſo Cneꝰ Pōpeiꝰ But eſpecially among other, L. Corneliꝰ Sylla wrought at ye time notable feats: Among which his famous geſts, this is one worthy to be had in mory: yt he diſcomfited in ſuche ſort ye army of Cluentiꝰ which was very populous, yt of his own men, he loſt not one. This war continued by ye ſpace of. 4. yeres, not without great damage and loſſe to either party. At laſt, it was finiſhed in the. 5. yeare after it was firſt cōmenced, by L. Coruelius L. Coruelius Sylla Conſul. Sylla then Conſul: who in the ſame battail, worthelye behaued hymſelfe ſondrye wayes, when as yet he was but pretor. In the .vi. C. and .xlii. yere after the buildinge of the city, began The fyrſt ciuil battayl at Rome. the firſt ciuil battaile in Rome: And that ſame yere alſo, began ye battaile againſt Mithridates. Thoccaſion of Battayle agaynſt Mithridates. the ciuil battaile proceded of Caius

Mariꝰ who had ben .vi. times Cōſul. Marius cauſer of ye fyrſte ciuil warre at Rome vppon indignation takē, that Silla was preferred to fight yt batail againſt Mithridates For when Silla (who was now Cō
               ſul,) was ſent forth to war agaynſte Mithridates, (who had alredy gotten Aſia &amp; Achaia,) &amp; ſtayed his army for a while in Cāpania, Mariꝰ (to thend the memory of ye battel which before Silla and he waged ioyntly in Italy, myght be extinguiſhed and decaye,) made iaboure to the Senate that he might himſelf alone haue ye ordering and diſpoſinge of that battaile ſo attempted againſt Mithridates. Wher vppon Sylla conceyuing diſpleſure, retourned againe backe to the Citye withall his army, and foughte there againſt Marius and Sulpitius. Hym ſelfe firſte entred the citye of Rome, Sulpitius ſlayn, &amp; Marcus put to flyghte. and ſlewe there Sulpitius: and forſt Marius to fle thence. And ſo whē he had appointed Cneus Octauius and Lucius Cornelius Cinna to be Conſuls Cne. Octauius. &amp; L. Cornelius Cinna Conſuls. for the yeare following, he toke his iourney towarde Aſia.
            
               
For Mithridates kynge of Pontus, had gotten nowe bothe Armenia the leſſe, and al the ſea called Ponticum in compaſſe, and Boſphorus alſo. This Mithridates would firſte haue driuen Nicomedes forth of Bithinia, The prefence of Mithridates battayle. who was frende to the Romaines: And vpon that, gaue the Romayns to vnderſtand that he woulde make warre vpon the ſayd Nicomedes, for that he had ſondrye wayes endomaged The aſſured frendſhyp of the Romains him. To whōe the Senate made anſwer, that if it wer ſo that he warred againſt Nicomedes, he ſhould alſo feele the force of the Romaynes. Whervpon Mithridates beinge moued with anger, forthwith inuaded all Cappadocia, and expulſed from thenſe, king Ariobarſanes, who was friend to the Romaines. Sone after, be ſet vppon Bythinia and Paphlagonia, and exiled thence Pilemenes and Nicomedes who were kynges there, and likewiſe frends to the Romaines.

From thence he went to Epheſus, and ſent letters throughe all Aſia, that where ſo euer any citezens of Rome might be found, they ſhuld be all ſlaine forthe of hande. In the mean ſpace Athenes a city of Achaia Athens yelded 
                     •
                  o mithridates. was yelded vp to Mithridates by one Ariſton an Athenien. For Mithridates had all readye ſent Archelaus hys captain with a. C. and .xx. M horſmen and foremen to ouer runne and bringe all Greee in ſubiectyon. Sylla be ſieged Archelaꝰ at Pireneꝰ, not far from Athens, and wanne the citye. Afterwarde, he ioyned battayle with Archelaus: in whyche he diſcō
               fited him in ſuche ſorte, that of hys C. and .xx. M. men, ſkant .x. were lefte Great diſcomfyture of mythridates. a liue with Archelaus: and of Sylla his armye, were ſlaine but .xiiii. perſons onlye. When Mithridates had vnderſtāding of thys chaunce of battaile, forth of hand, he ſent to Archelaus .lxx. M. well appoynted menne,

whome he choſe as chefeſt throughe out all Aſia. Againſt whō, Silla fought again. And in the firſt battayl he ſlewe .xx. M. of his enemies, and Diogenes alſo. Archelaus his ſonne. In Diogenes Archelaus hys ſonne ſlayne. the ſeconde battayle, all the whole force and power of Mithridates was quyte diſcomfited. Archelaus himſelf was conſtrayned to flye, and to hyde hymſelfe naked in the fennes and Archelaus narrowly eſkaped. maryſhes by the ſpace of thre dayes, when Mithridates hearde theeſe tydynges, he began to treat wyth Sylla for peace. In this while alſo Sylla had partlye ſubdued in battayle, and Mithridates deſired peace. partlye receiued againe vnder obeyſaunce, the Dardanians, the Scordiſcians, the Sclauonians, and the Moeſians. But when the Legates were come from Mithridates to him whyche deſired peace, Sylla anſwered that he would not graunte peace in anye wyſe, vnleſſe the kyng wold departe thence to hys owne country,

and yelde vppe ſuche Prouinces as he nowe deteyned there. Neuertheleſſe, Peace concluded betweene Mithridates and the Romaynes. at lengthe bothe the partyes them ſelues came to talk, and peace was concluded betwene theym. For Silla feared leaſte that if he ſhoulde retourne to repreſſe the ciuil warres at Rome, he ſhoulde alſo ſtande in ieoperdye of inuaſion, at hys backe by Mithridates.
            For durynge thys whyle that Silla warred vppon Mithridates in Aſia and Achaia, Marius (whome Silla hadde before conſtrayned to flee the citye,) and Cinna one of the Conſuls, renued battaile in Italye, and entrynge into the city of Rome, they ſlewe the mooſte noble menne Marrius his great crueity. of the Senate and Conſuls: and manye they baniſhed. They deſpoyled Silla hys houſe, and draue hys wyfe and hys ſonnes, to flye foorthe of the Citye.
            
               
All the reſidue of the Senate, leauing the city of their own acord, fled to Sylla into Grece: and beſoughte him, that he woulde without farther delaye ſuccoure his countrye. Sylla Sylla retourned to pa
                     •
                  ifye things in Italy, du
                     •
                  ynge whyche tyme marius dyed. therfore forthwith tranſpoſed his army from thence into Italy: minding to wage a ciuil battaile againſt Norbane and Scipio the Conſulles. He foughte the firſt battaile with Norbane Narbane and Scipio Conſuls. not farre from Capua, where he ſlew vii. thouſand of Norban hys army: and toke vi. M. priſonners: and loſt of his owne men, to the nomber of a. C. and .xxiiii. ſouldyours. From thence, he turned his armye agaynſt Scipio: and or euer they cam to handye gripes, all Scipio his armye yelded them ſelues to Sylla without any bloudſhed. Then were the Conſuls chaunged at Rome: and Marius Marius, and Papiriꝰ Carbo Conſuis. ſonne to that other Mariꝰ, (who was cauſer of this ciuil warre) and Papirius Carbo were made Couſuls.

Sylla foughte againſte Marius the yonger, and ſlewe .xv. M. of his men, and loſt .cccc. of his own. Sone after, he entred the city: and p
                  •
               rſuing yōg Marius vnto Preneſte, beſieged him there, and ſlewe him. He had agayne Marius the yonger ſlayn. an other battaile with Lamponius &amp; Carinates, which were captains on Marius his ſide, at Collina gate. There were by reporte aſſembled in that battaile againſte Silla .lxxx. M. of whiche .xii. M. yelded them ſelues to Silla. The reſidue what in fight, what in their tents, and as they fled, were all ſlaine, through the inſacyable haſtineſſe of the conquerors. In like manner Cnous Carbo the other Conſul fled from Ariminus into Sicilie: Cne. Carbo Conſul. where he was ſlaine by Pompeius: whiche Pompeius beynge as then but of the age of .xx. yeres, Sylla (for that he apperceiued hys proweſſe Cneus Carbo the Conſul flayn. and fierſ courage,) deputed to be lieuetenaunte ouer his garryſon, to

the ende he ſhould be had in eſtimatyon next after hymſelf. Thus when Carbo was ſlayn, Pompeius appeaſed Siliice pacifyed. Sicilie, and departing frō thenſe towardes Affricke, he ſlewe Domitius a captayne of Marius hys ſyde, and Hiarbas kynge of Mauritanie who ayded Domitius. After theeſe thynges, Sylla triumphed ouer Mithridates Sylla triumphed ouer Mithridates wyth great glorye. Cneus Pompeius alſo (whych was neuererſt graunted to anye Romayn,) beynge but .xxiiii. yeres of age, triumphed ouer Affricke. Thus were finyſhed two moſte deadly battayles: the Italyan battayl: (whiche was alſo called the war betwene confederates and allyes,) and the ciuyl war. Both which, endured by the ſpace of x. yeres, whiche battayles conſumed aboue an. C. and .l. M. ſouldyoures, xxiiii. Conſuls .vii. Pretors, xl. Ediles, and wel nyghe. CCC. Senators beſides.
         
         
            
            ¶ The ſyxthe booke of the Breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               WHen Marcus Emilius Lepidus, and Quintus Catulus were Conſuls, and Sylla had now appeaſed and ſette in order the weal publique, battayles grew agayn a freſh. One in Spaine: An other in Pamphilia and Cilicia. The third in Macedonie: The fourthe in Sclauonia. For whye Sertorius, who toke part Four battel in ſondry places at one tyme agaynſt the romayns. wyth Marius, fearynge what ſhould become of hym, for that hee ſawe what hadde betyded to others of the ſame factyon, ſtyrred vp the Spaniardes to battayle agaynſte the Romaynes.
            
               
Quintus Cecilius Metellus, ſonne of that Metellus which ſubdued king Iugurth, and Domitius the Pretor were ſent forthe captaines agaynſte him. Domitius was ſlayne by Hyrtuleius captain of Sertoriꝰ his hoſt. Domitius ſlayne. Metellus fought with Sertoriꝰ hymſelf with greate vncertaintye of fortune. But at lengthe when the Senate Pompeius ſente to ayde Metellus againſt Sertorius. ſawe rhat Metellus was ouermatched in battayle by Sertorius, they ſent Cneus Pompeius alſo into Spaine: and ſo Sertorius fought againſte bothe thoſe captaines of hys aduerſaries with greate varietye of fortune. But at laſte, in the eyghte yere after that the battaile was firſte begon, Sertorius was ſlayne by hys Sertorius ſlaine by his owne ſouldyoures. own ſouldioures, and ſo that battail was finiſhed by Cneus Pompeius, (who was as yet but a yong mā) and Quintus Metellus Pius. And well nigh all Spaine ſubmitted them ſelues to the Romaines at that tyme.

Appius Claudius after that his Cō
               ſulſhip was expired, was ſente into Macedonie. He fuſtained but eaſye battailes againſte diuers whiche inhabiied Thracia: and there fallynge ſicke, dyed. There was ſente to ſuccede Appius Claudius dyed. him, Cncus Scriboniꝰ Eurio, ſo ſoone as he had likewiſe finyſhed his Conſulſhip. He ſubdued the Dar danianc, and paſſed forwarde tyll be came to the riuer Danubius, and merited a triumphe: and within .iii. yeres he finiſhed his battailes. Then was Publius Seruilius ſente into Cilicia and Pamphylia. This Seruilius (taking him for a Conſul) was a paſſyng ſtout and valiant man. He ſubdued Cilicia. He aſſaulted &amp; wan the worthieſt cities of Licia: among which, theſe were ſome, Phalilides, Olimpus, and Coritū. And wythin a while after, he gaue the aſſaulte to Iſauros an other citye, and enforced it to yeld, and within .iii. yeres ſpace,

He finyſhed thoſe battayle▪ He was the fyrſte Romayne that made anye viage to Taurus. When he retourned P. Seruiliꝰ the fyrſte Romain whyche made any viage to Taurꝰ thence, he tryumphed, and merited the name to be called Iſauricus. Aboute the ſame tyme, was Caius Coſconius alſo ſente into Illiria, in Seruiliꝰ tryumphed, and was called I ſanricus. the Conſuls ſteade. He broughte in ſubiectyon a greate part of Sclauonia. He wanne Salone, and when he hadde finyſhed thys battayle, he retourned to Rome after that he had beene abſent thence, by the ſpace of two yeares. At the ſame tyme, the Conſull Marcus Emilius Lepidus, M. Emilius Lepidus Conſul. who was collegue to Catulus, wold haue commenced a ciuyl war. Howe Ciuyl warre pretended agayn. be it that vproure was appeaſed agayne wythin one ſommers ſpace. Thus were .iiii. ſondrye tryumphes had at Rome together at one tyme. The one by Metellus ouer Spayne, Four triumphes at Rome together. the other by Pompeius, (&amp; that was hys ſeconde triumphe) ouer Spayne

alſo. The thyrd by Curio, ouer Macedonie. The fourthe and laſt, by Seruilius ouer the Iſaurians. In the ſixe hundreth three ſkore and ſixtene yere after the building of the city of Rome, Lucius Licinius Lucullus, L. Licinius Lucullꝰ, and M. Aureliꝰ Cotta Conſuls. and Marcus Aurelius Cotta beyng Conſuls, Nicomedes king of Bithinia died: and appoynted by his teſtament Romaines to be hys heyres. About this time Mithridates (infringing the league before made,) wold haue again inuaded Aſia &amp; Bithinia, War renued by Mithridates. but the Conſuls wer forthwith ſent againſt him, &amp; of long time they experimēted vncertain fortune in battell. Mithridates ouercam Cotta in fight Chalcedon, &amp; forced him ye city, wher Cotta the Cō
                  ſul dyſcomfyted. he beſieged hym. But when Mithridates remoued hys power frō thence towardes Cizicus, (thinkynge that if he hadde ones gotten Cizicus hee myght eaſly inuade al Aſia,) Lucullꝰ thother Conſul encoūtred with him.

And whileſt that Mithridates ſtayed to lay ſiege to Cizicus, Lucullus had enuironed him behinde: and ſo keepynge him from comminge by vyttails, vanquiſhed him in ſondry ſkirmiſhes. At that time he eſkaped and fled to Bizantiū: (which is now called Conſtantinople,) his captaynes Mithridates diſcomlyted. were diſcomfited in battail vpon the ſea. Thus in one winter and a ſommer ſpace, Lucullus ſlew on the kinges ſide, wel nyghe an. C. M. meu. In the. Dc .lxxviii. yeare after y• buildinge of the citye of Rome, Marcus Licinius Lucullus, who was coſyn germayne to that Lucullus whyche warred agaynſte Mithridates, was deputed to haue the gouernment of Macedonie. At thys time ſodainly in Italye a freſhe battayle was begon. For why .lxxiiii. of thoſe which were accuſtomed to play at wepons, (called Battayle a freſh in Italy Gladiatores) brake forthe of the ſcholes at Capua, and made to them

ſelues, Spartachus, Chriſus &amp; Denomannus. And as they roued throughe Italy, they commenced battayle there no leſſe daungerous then was that other whyche before Anniball waged there. For when they had diſcomfited diuers Romain captaines, and the two Cōſuls alſo, they aſſembled an army well nigh of lx. M men wel appoynted. How be it, they wer ouercome in Apulia, by Marcus Licinius Craſſus the Proconſull. And ſo after ſondrye calamities ſuſtained in Italye, this battayle was fiuyſhed in the thirde yeare after that it was firſt begon. In the yere after that the city was built .vi. C .lxxxi. there were but only two great battayles waged within the Romain Empire, (that is Two battels only waged againſt the Romains through the world. to ſay) the battail againſt Mithridates, and the battaile againſt the Macedians, both which battails the two Lucullies, (which is to wit) Lucius Lucullus, &amp; Marcus Lucullꝰ fought.

For Lucius Lucullus after he had finiſhed the battail at Cizicꝰ, in which he ouercame Mithridates: and after the other battaile vppon the Sea, in whiche he vanquiſhed the captaines of Mithridates, he purſued Mithridates hymſelfe. And when he hadde recouered Paphlagonia and Bithinia, he inuaded Mithridates owne kingdome. He wan there Sinopes and Aniſus, two of the mooſte noble cityes of Pontus.
            In the ſecond battaile whych was waged at the citye Cabira, Mithridates hadde prouided .xxx. M. menne, Thyrty M. vanquyſhed by .v. M. Romaynes. whome he did chuſe and picke forthe throughe all hys kingdome, whyche when they were vanquiſhed by v. M. of the Romaynes, Mithridates fled Mithridates fled. and hys tentes were ſackt. The leſſe Armenia likewiſe, whiche he hadde Armenia recouered. gotten, was recouered agayne from hym. But Mithridates after he was thus fled, was receiued by Tigranes

kynge of Armenia, who raygned at thoſe dayes in great renowne. This Tigranes oft times had ſubdued the Perſians. He wanne Meſopotamia, Mithridates ſuccoured by kyng Tigranes. Siria, and a piece of Phenicia.
            Sone after, Lucullꝰ required him to deliuer his ennemy, whom he had put to ſlyght. Whiche requeſt when he withſtode and denyed the deliuerye of Mithridates, Lucullus forthewith inuaded kynge Tigranes hys realme, and wanne there Tigra nocerta the chiefeſt citye of Armenia, and hauinge but .xviii. M. ſouldiours to ayde him, he gaue king Tigranes a paſſinge great ouerthrow, which Tigranes came againſte hym wyth vi. M. men on barbed horſſes, and an huddreth thouſande Archers, beſides other menne of armes. He ſlewe the A great ouerthrow of kīg Tigranes. greater parte of the Armenians, and remouynge from thence to Niſibis, looke that Citye alſo, and the kinges brother in it.
            
               
But they whome Lucullus had left behinde in Pontus with parte of hys armye, to the ende that they ſhoulde keepe vnder to the behoufe of the Romaynes ſuche people as he hadde all ready ſubdued there (demeanyng them ſelues very rechleſly, and with great cruelty) gaue oportunity to Mithridates Battayle renued by Mithridates. to inuade Poneus againe: and ſo battayle was renued there a freſhe. Ther was one ſent to ſuccede Lucullusrwho after that he had won Niſibis, made preparatyon for hys viage againſte the Perſians. The other Lucullus who had the gouernmente of Macedonie, was the fyrſte Romain that waged battail againſt the Beſſians: whome he ouercame in a greate battaile vpon the hyll Emus. Lucullus the fyrſt Romain that waged battel againſt the Beſſians Vſcudama won. He wā alſo Vſcudama: a town which the Beſſians did inhabite the ſelfe ſame daye, that he gaue the aſſault to it. He toke in like maner the city Cabiles, and marched ſtil forthe

til he came to the riuer Danubius. After that he inuaded diuers cityes Cabiles take Both the Lucullies triumphed. whiche were ſiiuate vppon the Sea coaſt of Pontus. There he deſtroyed Appollonia, and wan Calatis, Partenopolis, Tomos, Hiſtrus, and all Buzia. And when thoſe battails wer Battayle in Creete. finiſhed, he retourned to Rome wher either of them triumphed. But yet ye Lucullus who had waged battail againſt Mithridates, triumphed wyth greater glorye, for that he retourned conqueror of ſuch ample kingdoms. After the battayle was finyſhed in Macedonie, the battayle agaynſt Mithridates as yet endured: which battail Mithridates renued, aſſembling together all the power and force of men he coulde make after that Lucullus was nowe departed backe. About this time began there alſo battayle in Creete, Cecilius Metellus was ſente thyther, who after that he had fought great battailes ther, with

in the ſpace of .iii. yeares he wan the whol prouince, and for this fact was called Creticus. He triumphed ouer Crete won by Metellus, and he called Creticus. that Ilande. At this time alſo, Libia was by the bequeſt of Appio kynge there of, annexed to the Empire of ye 
               Libia anexed to the Romain empyre by Appio. Romaines. In which prouince, theſe were the nobleſt Cities, Beronice, Ptoloneais, and Cyrene. Whyle theſe thynges were in hand, Pirates began to anoy the paſſengers throughe thoſe parties by ſea. So that the Romaines who hadde ſubdued well nyghe all the whole worlde, wanted now nothing, ſauing that they hadde not now ſafe courſe and recourſe by the ſeas, where vppon that vyage againſt Battayle againſt the pirates committed to Cneus Pompeius. thoſe pirates, was commytted to Cneue Pompeius, who wythin a few monethes ſpace, finiſhed it with great celerity, and no leſſe derteritye of fortune.
            Not long after, the ſame Pompeius was alſo deſigned to go agaynſte

Mithridates, and Tigranes whyche viage when he had taken in hand, he ouercame Mithridates in battayl by Mithridates ouercome in battayle by nyghte. night in Armenia the leſſe, &amp; ſackte his tentes. He ſlewe there .xl. M. of the kinges army, and loſt of his own hoſte, but .xx. menne, and two of his captaines. After this euyll ſucceſſe, Mithridates fled being accompanied Mithridates fled. but wyth his wyfe &amp; ii, other to wait vpon them, and eftſones in a tumult whyche fell amonge his ſouldioures through the procurement of his ſōne Pharnaces, he was forſed to deathe, whiche he executed on him ſelfe by Mithridates poyſoned himſelf. drinckinge of poyſon. This ende had Mithridates: he died at 
                  •
               oſphorus, a manne verye polliticke, and wittye wyth all. He raaigued .lx. yeres, he lyued three ſcore and twelue yeres. He Mithridates hysage and tyme of hys raygne. warred agaynſte the Romaynes by the ſpace of forty yeres. Then Pompeius adreſſed hys battaile agaynſte Tigranes, who yelded hym ſelfe. Tigranes purſued.
               
And ſo ſone as he was entred within Pompeius hys tentes, whyche were pitched .xvi. myles dyſtante from Artaxata, he fell proſtrate at Pompeius hys fete, and deliuered vp his crown into the handes of Pompeius: but Tigranes ſubmytted hymſelfe. Pompeius repoſed it again vpon his head, and entreated hym verye worthely. Neuertheles, he depriued him of a portion of his kingdome, and aſſeſſed hym to pay a great ſumme of The worthineſſe of Pompeius. mony beſides. There was taken frō him Siria, Phenices, and Sophenes and he was aſſeſſed to paye .vi. M. talents of ſiluer, for that he warred agaynſt the Romains without cauſe. Not lōg after, Pompeius alſo made warre vpon the Albanes, and ouercame War againſt the Albanes. Orodes king of th Albanes ouercome. Orodes kinge of the Albanes, in three ſondry battails. But at laſt, beinge requeſted by letters and preſents, he bothe pardoned hym, and graunted hym peace. He ouercame Arthaces kyng of Iberia vāquiſhed in lyke manner Arthaces kynge of

Iberia in fight, and at laſt, receyued him vnder allegeaunce. He gaue Armenia the leſſe, to Deiotarus kynge Armenia geuen to Deiotarus. of Galacia, for that he had aided hym in battaile againſte Mithridates. He reſtored Paphlagonia to Attalꝰ, and Attalus and Pilemenes reſtored to theyr kyngdomes. Pilemenes. He deputed Ariſtarchus kyng ouer Colchos. Sone after, he ouercame the Iturians and Arabiās. And when he cam into Siria, he enfraunchiſed Seleucia, a citye ſituate Seleucia enfranchyſed. A peece of neare to Antioche, for that they dyd not ayd, ne ſuccour king Tigranes. He redeliuered to the Antiochians, their pledges whyche they gaue to hym. He gaue the Daphuenſes a per cell of lande, for the enlargemente of theyr groues or copyes, for that hee was delighted with the pleaſaunte ſite of that place, and the greate plentye of waters whych abounded ground geuen to the Daphuenſes. there.) From thence, he paſſed forthe takynge his waye towardes Iudea. And in the thyrde moneth after hys

arriuinge there, he wan Ieruſalem the chiefe citye of that countrey. He ſlew there .xii. M. Iewes, the reſidue he receyued vnder allegeaunce.
            Theſe things being thus finiſhed, he wente into Aſia, and ſo ended he the war, which had long continued. whē 
               M. Cullius C i. and Caiꝰ Antonius Conſuls. This Cicero was lireally deſcended frō the kinges of the Volſci
                     ••
                  , whyche were leng before ye city of Rome. a mā of ſinguler wy
                     •
                   &amp; clemency, and of a paſſing z
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  
                  te his coūtry he was called of the Father of his coūtry for yt he hadſo ſtudie 
                     •
                  ſly preſerued it. He flouryſhed about xi. yeres before the Incarnatyon of Chriſt. Marcus Tullius the Orator, &amp; Caiꝰ Antonius wer Conſuls, in the .vi. C. lxxxix yere after the city was builte, Lucius Sergius Catiline, a mā deſcended of a noble ſtock, but yet of an euill diſpoſityon, conſpired wyth dyuers other noble menne of like raſhneſſe and naughtineſſe as he was, Catiline was expulſed forthe of the city, by Cicero. His confederates wer apprehended and thratled in priſon. Afterwarde Catiline himſelfe was ouercome in battaile, and ſlayne by Antonius the other Conſul.
            In the ſix hundreth and ninetenth yeare after the buildinge of Rome. When Decius Iunius Sillanus,

and Lucius Murena were Canſuls, Metellus triumphed ouer Crete, and Pompeius tryumphed for the battaile D. Iunius Sillanꝰ. and L. Murena Conſuls. which he had ouer the Pirates on the ſea, and for that other battaile whyche he waged wyth Mithridates. The pompe and pride of no tryumphe, was euer lyke to that of Metellꝰ and Pompeius trfumphed. Pompeius. There were led before hys charyot, the ſonne of Mithridates, and the ſonne of kynge. Tigranes, and Ariſtobulus kynge of the Iewes. Ther was caryed moreouer before hym greate ſtore of wine: and an infinite deale of golde and ſiluer beſides. At thys time, the Romaines waged no greate battayles through all the whole worlde.
            In the ſixe hund, eth nineteth, and thirde yeare after the buildynge of Ca. Iulius Ceſar, and L. Bibulus tryumphed. the Citye, Caius Iulius▪ Ceſar, who afterwarde became Emperour, was created Conſull, and Lucius Bibulus with hym.
            
               
Fraunce was committed to hys gouermēt, and the coaſt of Illiria (now called Sclauonia,) together wyth .x. legions of ſouldioures Fyrſt he ſubdued the Heluetians whych are alſo called the Sequanes or Burgoniās. Then he paſſed forth ſtil conquering and ſubduing as he went, with greuous battayles, vntyll he came to the Englyſhe Ocean ſea. And with in the ſpace of .ix. yeres, he broughte wel nyghe all Fraunce in ſubiertyon, ſo muche as is ſituate betweene the Alpes, the riuer of Roan, the floud of Rheyn and the Occean ſea, whiche in circuit extendeth to .ccccc. miles. Sone after, he warred vppon the Britaynes whyche before his aryuing Brytain whiche is nowe called England, inuaded by Iulius Ccſar. The Britaines tributaryes to the Romaynes. there, had neuer anye cogniſaunce, nor at anye tyme harde ſpeakynge of the Romaines. When he had ſubdued them, he made them tributary to the Romaynes, and tooke hoſtages of them. But he did exacte

of Fraunce vnder name of Tribute, cccc. Seſtercios. Then he aſſaild the Germaines, which inhabited on the farther ſide of the riuer of Roan, and vanquiſhed them in moſt ſharp battayles. But amonge all theſe ſo many ſucceſſes and chaunces of fortune he fought thriſe vnluckelye. Ones agaynſte the Auernians in Fraunce, Thre vnlucky vattailes of Iulius Ceſar. at whyche battaile he was preſente hymſelf, and twiſe in Germany whē he was abſent. For his two Legates Titurius and Aruneulus wer ſlaine ther by a train. About the ſame time▪ in the .cccccc. xcvii. yere after the city was builte, Marcus Licinius Craſſꝰ fellowe in offyce with Cneus Pompeius the great, in the ſeconde yeare after that he was made Conſul, was ſent on a viage againſte the Parthians; and ioyning battaile with them in an euill houre at Carras, he was M. Licinius Caſlus ſlam. ouercome by Surena captayne to kynge Drodes: and at laſte, he was

ſlayne and hys Sonne alſo, a valyaunte and a worthye yonge man towardes. The reſidue of hys armye, was preſerued by Caius Caſſius Aciuii diſſention ſprong in Rome, after which enſued a moſt ſharpe ciuill war betwene Pompeius and Iulius Ceſare, where vppon grew thalteration of the weale publyque of Rome, and an vtter decay in manner of ye ſame, the occaſyon of the battayl was butlight For Ceſar after he was returned forthe of Fraūce, requeſted to bee made Cōſul, for ſo it ſtode hym in hand, for that certē had conſpired ſoone after to haueprocured his bannyſhment through whoſe inueglyng Pompei us chaunged hys former mynd, and reuoked hys former promeſſe made to Ceſar, and added beſides cer
                     •
                  en threatnynges to Ceſar wardes, vpō which the grudge grew. Thys battail began in the. 3914. yere after the creatyō of the world, and in the 706. yere after the citye was builte, &amp; in the 47. before the byrth of Chriſte, it laſted v. yeres in al, then was Rome fyrſtea monarche. lieuetenaunte of the hooſte, who throughe hys ſinguler and paſſynge greate manhoode reduced to ſuche good paſſe thoſe matters ſo farre endaungered, (whyche were nowe well nyghe paſte cure and hoope of recouerye,) that conueyinge his armye ouer Euphrates. He vanquyſhedee the Perſians in diuers ſkyrmyſhes.
            When theſe thynges were thus finiſhed, there enſued an horryble and lamentable battaile: By meane whereof, (beſides dyuers other calamityes whyche chaunced in the Romain weale publique) the condition &amp; wonted eſtate of that famous Empire was aultered. For when Ceſar returned conqueror forth of Fraūce he required to be created Conſull agayne.

Whyche thyng when it was by diuers of the Romaines wythout contradictyon graunted vnto hym, Marcellus (who was then Conſul,) Bibulus, Pompeius, and Cato, dyd openlye wythſtande it, and ſente commaundemente to Ceſar that he ſhoulde diſmiſſe hys army, and come home to the citye. Vppon whyche aunſwere Ceſare conceyuinge dyſpleaſure from Ariminus (where he had hys armye aſſembled) towardes Rome to inuade it.
            Where hppon the Conſull, the Senate, and all the Nobilytye of Rome together with Pompeiꝰ, fled forth of the citye, and paſſed ouer into Greece, and made preparaunce for warre agaynſte Ceſar, at Epirus Macedonie and Achaia, and thoſe Pompeius to be theyr Captayne. When Ceſar was entred the vacaunte and forſaken Cytye,

forthwith he made himſelf Dictator. From thence, he went into Spayn. There he diſcomfited the moſt ſtrōg Iuli. Ceſar made himſelf Dictator. and valiaunte armies of Pompeius, and thre of hys capitaynes, (that is to witte,) Lucius Afranius, Marcus Pompeiꝰ his captaynes diſcomfyted. Petreius, and Marcus Varro. Returninge from thence, he paſſed ouer into Grece, and pitched his field, and foughte againſte Pompeius. In the Pompeius &amp; Ceſar fought firſte battaile he had the ouerthrow, &amp; was put to flyght. How be it he eſkaped, Iuliꝰ Ceſar diſcomſyted. for that (the night approching ſo nere,) Pompeius would not purſue him. Where vppon, Ceſar whan he was thus eſkaped, ſaid: that neyther Pompeius wiſt how to cōquere him, and that that was the only day in which he myght haue had the vpper hand ouer hym. After that, they bothe met again at Paleopharſalus in Theſſalye: whereas eche of them ledde forthe to fighte, theyr paſſynge great armies, Pompeius had in hys

band, xl▪ M. fotemen in the forefront, vii. M. in the left winge, and .ccccc. in the ryght wing.
            He hadde ſuccour beſides, forthe of all the Caſto parties: and moreouer innumerable Senators and pretors, and others of the Conſuls, and almoſt all the nobilitye of Rome on his ſide, and ſuche as ere that tyme had bene conquerors of verye ſtoute nations. Ceſar had in his armye not full oute .xxx. M. footem on, and a. M. horſmen. The force and ſtrengthe of the Romains was neuer before that day aſſembled either in greater number, or vnder more worthy captains, ſo that nowe they coulde eaſtye haue ſubdued all the whole world, if they ſhould haue fought againſt the Barbarians. The battaile was handled with greate proweſſe and manhode on both parties. And at length Pompeius was diſcomfited, and his tents Pompeius diſcomfited. were ſackic. Himſelf fled to Alexandria:

where he thought he ſhoulde haue gotten ayde of the kynge of Egypte, vnto whome he was by the Pompeius 
                     〈◊〉
                   to Alexā
                  dria. Senate, ſomtyme appoynted to be a tutoure and gouernour duryng the time of his minority. But the yonge kinge hauinge more regarde to the An example of great vnkyndnes and ingratytude. time preſente, then reſpecte or conſideratyon to the paſſed frendſhyppe whyche he had founde at Pompeius hys handes, ſlewe Pompeius. And when he had cutte of hys heade, he pluckte of his ringe from hys hande, and ſente them together to Ceſar. whyche whan Ceſar ſawe, he braſte forthe on weepinge to beholde the heade of ſo worthy a manne, whyche alſo was his ſonne in lawe.
            Not longe after, Ceſar came to Alexandria, where Ptolomeus alſo conſpyred agaynſte him: vpon which occaſyon, Ceſar made warre on the kyng, who when he was ouercome,

drowned hym ſelfe in the ryuer of Ptolomeus drowned himſelfe. Nilus: in whyche place, bothe hys bodye was founde afterwarde, and hys coate of plate alſo, whych was gilded and verye ryche.
            When Ceſar hadde on thys ſorte obtayned Alexandria, he gaue that kyngdome to Cleopatra, ſyſter to Alexandria geuen by Ceſar to Cleopatra. Ptolomeus, whome he after vſed as hys peramoure, As Ceſar retourned from thence, he ouercame Pharnaces ſonne of Mithridates the greate, Pharnaces diſcomfited &amp; purſued to death. who hadde ſuccoured Pompeius at Theſſalie, and eftſones rebelled himſelfe in Pontus, and had wonne ſondrye prouinces from the Romaines, and purſued hym to deathe. Retournyng Ceſar made hymſelf Conſul the thyrde tyme. from thence to Rome, he made hym ſelfe Conſull the thyrde tyme, and Marcus Emilius Lepidus with hym, who was Magiſter Equitum in the yere before, when Ceſar was Dictator.
            From thence, he went into Affrick,

where as a greate noumber of the nobility, together wyth Iuba kynge of Mauritania renued battail againſt Warre in Africk by Iuba kynge of mauritania againſt Ceſar. him. The Romaine captains in that battaile, were Publius Cornelius Scipio, (who was deſcended from the moſte aunciente ſtocke of Scipio Africanus, whiche Scipio was alſo father in law to Pompeius ye great:) Marcus Petreius, Quintus Varus, Marcus Porcius Cato, and Lucius Cornelius Fauſtus (ſonne to Sylla, which was ſometime Dictator.) Ceſar diſpoſed his battailes in order againſte theeſe capitaynes, and after ſondrye ſkirmiſhes, he obtained the victory. Cato, Petreius, Scipio, and Iuba, ſlewe theym ſelues. Fauſtus who was ſonne to Silla, who ſometime was Dictator, and ſonne in law to Pompeius, was ſlaine by Ceſar. The yeare after, Ceſar retourned to Ceſar created hymſelf Conſul the 4. tyme. Rome, and created hymſelf Conſull the fourth time, and went forthwith

into Spaine, where as Cneus and Sextus, ſonnes to Pompeius, renued battayle wyth great force. There Warre in Spayne agaynſt Ceſar. wer many ſkirmiſhes betwene thē. The laſt battaile was fought at the city Munda, in whiche Ceſar was ſo nygh ouercome, that his men fledde Ceſar driuen to a neare ſtrayte. from him: for whyche cauſe he determyned to ſlea hym ſelfe, rather then (after that he hadde gotten ſuche renowne and fame in Martial feates), he would now fal into the handes of yong men and be vanquiſhed by thē, when he had liued .lvi. yeares wyth great honor. Neuertheleſſe when he had recouered his men again, he obtained the victori againſt them. The elder ſonne of Pompeius, was there ſlaine. The yonger ſonne fled, and ſo eſkaped.
            Afterwards, whē as now ciuil wars The cyuyll warre agaiſt Pompeius &amp; hys adherēts finyſhed by Iuliꝰ Ceſar. wer clean appeaſed, Ceſar returned to Rome where he began to demean himſelf very diſorderly and againſte

the vſage of the Romaine libertye. Where vppon, when he beſtowed the digniries and Offices in Rome vpon ſuche perſones as pleaſed hymſelfe, whyche offyces were accuſtomed to haue beene graunted by the aduyſe and conſent of the commons of Rome, and moreouer woulde not vſe any familiaritye or ſalutatyon to the Senate, when they came to him, Cefar his diſorderly demenor in Rome. and did ſondrye other actes beſydes, whyche were vſed in the tyme of tyranny by the kynges, at what tyme they bare rule and authoritye as yet in the citye of Rome, by meanes of whiche factes he began very muche to growe in hatred of the commons A greate conſpiracy agaynſte hym. and Senate, there conſpired agaynſt him .xl. or moe, Senators and gentlemen of Rome. Among whome, theſe were the chiefeſt: the two Bruti, (whyche were deſcended from the ſtocke of that Brutus, who was the firſte Conſull that was created at

Rome, and hadde procured then the baniſhing of the kings from thence, Caius Caſſius, and Seruilius Caſca. And when Ceſar on a daye, wyth the reſt of the Senate, were at theyr Seſſyon in the councell houſe, the Ceſar ſlayne by the ſenate. Senate roſe againſte him there, and ſlewe him, and ſmote him in with thre and twenty deadly woundes. ¶ (⸫) ⁋
         
         
            
            ¶ The ſeuenth boke of the Breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               WHē Ceſar was ſlayne, whyche was in the .vii. C. and .ix. yeare after the building of Rome, Tiuyl war
                     •
                  s renewed in Rome by Antonius. ciuil wars wer againe renewed. For whye, the Senate toke part wyth them which had ſlayne Ceſar. But Antonius the Conſull who fauoured Ceſar, endenored (what in him lay), to oppreſſe them by ciuil battail. Where vppon when the weale publique was thus greatly diſquieted, Antoniꝰ wrought at that time diuers hainous actes: for the whyche, he was by the whole Senate counted as an open ennemy Battayle agaynſt Antonius. of the common welth. Where vpon

there were ſent to purſue him, Panſa and Hircius the two Cōſuls, and Octauianus a yonge man of the age Panſa and Hircius Conſuls. of .xviii. yeres, neuew to Ceſar, whō Ceſar had adopted, and by hys laſte will deſigned to be his heire, and to beare hys name. This was that Ceſar who was afterwarde called Auguſtus, and became ruler ouer al the whole world. when theſe three capytaines were gone forthe againſt Antonius, they gaue him thouerthrow. Antonius dyſcomfyted. How be it it chaunced ſo, that both ye Conſuls died, aſſone as they had obtained this victory, ſo that all the .iii. armies were then attendaunte vpon The two Cō
                  ſuls dyed. Ceſar alone. when Antonius was thus diſcomfited, and had loſte hys army, he fled to Lepidus who hadde bene Magiſter Equitum before vnder Ceſar, and at that preſente, had Antonius ſue coured by Lepidus. great bandes of men redy aſſembled: if whome he was receiued. Sone after, throughe the procuremente and

earneſt ſute of Lepidus, Ceſar made Legue made with Antonius. league with Antonius. Then Ceſar retourned to Rome wyth al his hoſt, makinge ſemblaunce as though he woulde haue reuenged the deathe of hys father whyche adopted him, and Ceſar compelled the Romains to create hym Cō
                  ſull, when he was but .xx. yeres of age, aboute the 710. yere after the citye was built. of fine force cauſed the Romaynes to create hym Conſull, beinge as yet but of the age of .xx. yeares. Then by the aduiſe and counſailes of Antonius and Lepidus, he banyſhed diuers of the Senate, and beganne to detayne the weale publique, by force of armes. By theyr means, was Cicero The ontcagiouſneſſe of Ceſar, throughe euil counſell. the Orator ſlayne, and dyuers other noble men.
            In this meane while, Brutus and Caſſius whyche were two of them that ſlewe Ceſar, prepared a greate battaile, hauynge aſſembled manye armies through Macedonie and the Eaſte partes. There went forth agaynſte them Ceſar, Octanianus,

Auguſtus, and Marcus Antonius. Battail pretēded againſt Ceſar, by Brutus and Caſſius. But Lepidus was lefte behynde to defende Italye. They ioyned battail wyth Brutus and Caſſius at Philippos a city of Macedonie.
            In the firſte battayle Ceſar and Antonius were diſcomfited. How be Ceſar and Antonius diſcomfyted. Caſſiꝰ ſlayn. it Caſſius captaine of the nobilitye was then ſlaine.
            In the ſeconde battayle, Brutus was ſlayne alſo, and an infynyte noumber of the Nobylytye, whyche Brutꝰ ſlain. toke parte with him againſt Ceſar. Then did Ceſar and Antonius departe the Romayn Empire betwene The Romain Empire deuided betwene Ceſar and Antonius. them on thys ſorte. That Auguſtus ſhoulde poſſeſſe Spayne, Fraunce, and Italye. Antonius ſhoulde haue Aſia, Pontus, and the Eaſte partes. At this tyme, Lucius Antonius A ciuyl war by Lucius Antonius. who was brother to that Antonius whyche tooke parte with Ceſar

againſt Brutus and Caſſius began a ciuill warre wythin Italy. He was ouercom at Perowſe a city of Thuſcia, and was taken, but was not ſlaine. In the mean ſpace, by Sextus Pompeius, who was ſonne to Cneus Pompeius the greate, there was another greate battaile attempted in Another battayle by Sextus Pompeiꝰ Peace concluded. Sicilie: at whiche battaile, all thoſe were aſſembled, whiche as yet were left a liue, of them that aided Brutus and Caſſius. The battel was fought by Ceſar Auguſtus Octauiꝰ againſt Sextus Pompeiꝰ. And at laſt, peace The Perſians vanquyſhed. was concluded betwene them. At y• ſame time, Marcꝰ Agrippa had good ſucceſſe in his affairs in Guyon whiche is that parte of Fraunce, that is now called Aquitain. Lucius Ventidius Baſſus ouercame the Perſians whiche inuaded Siria, in three ſondry battailes. He ſlewe Pacorꝰ kyng The fyrſt tryumphe ouer the Perſians Orodes his ſonne, the very ſame dai that Surena captain to Orodes, ſlew

Craſſus. He was the firſt which merited a moſte condigne tryumphe at Rome ouer the Parthians. In thys meane ſpace, Pompeius infrynged the peace, and was diſcomfited in batel Pompeiꝰ infrynged the peace, &amp; was ſlayne. on the ſea, and as he woulde haue fled from thence to Aſia warde, he was ſlaine. Antonius to whom Aſia, and the Eaſt partes wer allotted, beinge deuorced from the fiſter of Auguſtus Ceſar, eſpouſed Cleopatra M. Antoniꝰ eſpouſed Cleopatra. Quene of Egipt. He warred on the Perſians, and ouercame them in the firſte battailes. And as he retourned homewardes, there fell great ſkarſity and penury of victuals among his The Perſians oyſcomfyced by Antonius. ſouldioures. But when the Perſiās purſued hym harde as he retourned, he got the victory ouer them at that tyme alſo. This Antonius began a greate ciuill warre through the procurement A cyuyl war by M. Antonius. and egging for ward of his wife Cleopatra, affectyng to attayne the gouernment of the city of Rome,

that ther by, he might ſatiſfy the inceſſant requeſts of his wife. He was vanquiſhed by Auguſtus in battaile vpon the ſea at Actiu in, which town is ſituate in Epirus. From thence, Antonius vā
                  quyſhed by Auguſtus. he fledde into Egypte: and there beinge exempte from all hope of good chaunce, and deſpairing that hys affaires ſhould euer take good ſucceſſe agayne, (ſo that all men nowe tooke part with Ceſar) he ſlewe hymſelfe. Antoniꝰ and Cleopatra ſlewe themſelues. Cleopatra alſo his wife, procured to be ſtriken of an Adder, by meane of whoſe poyſon ſhe died. Then was Egypt alſo annexed to the Romaine Empire, by Octauian Auguſtus, Egipt adioyned to the Romain empyre. and Cneus Cornelius Gallus, was appoynted lieuetenaunte there, who was the firſte of the Romaines whiche decided or determyned matters
Cneus Gallus lieuetenaunte ouer Egypt. in Egypte.
            Thus when warres were pacified throughe the whole world, Octanian Auguſtus retourned to Rome

in the twelfthe yeare after that hee was firſte created Conſul, and from that tyme he gouerned the Romaine Empire him ſelfe alone, by the ſpace of foure and forty yeres. For duryng the other twelue yeres before, he adminiſtred it ioyntlye together wyth Antonius and Lepidus. So from the The tyme of Auguſtꝰ hys raigne. firſt commencement of his Empire vnto the end there of, wer .lvi. yeres. He deceaſed in the foure ſkore and ſyxe yeare of hys age, by ſyckeneſſe Auguſtꝰ hys age. at Atella a towne of Campania, and lyeth buryed at Rome, in Campo-Martio. Auguſtus Ceſar died in the ii. yere of the 198. Dlim
                     ••
                  
                  ▪ whyche was in the. 767. yere after the city was built, and in the yeare of our Lord god the .xv. Auguſtus canonyſed. Auguſtus hys worthye demenor. A man who in mooſte thynges, and that righte worthely, was deemed as a God, For lightlye there was none eyther more fortunate in battayles then hee was, or in tyme yf peace whiche ruled more diſcret
                  •
               
               lye. Ourynge thoſe .xliiii. yeares in whyche he raygned alone, hee lyued verye ciuillye, behauynge hym ſelfe very liberally towardes all 
                  〈◊〉
               ,

and to his frendes excedinge truſtye and aſſured, whome he aduaunced to ſo greate honoures, that almoſte he made them equall wyth his owne eſtate. The Romayne Empyre at no ſyme before his raign, did more floriſhe. For beſides the ſuppreſſing of the ciuill warres in whiche hee alwayes was inuincyble, he annexed alſo to the Romain Empyre, Egipt, Biſkay and Dalmatia which is parcel of Sclauonia, (whiche countrey was by the Romaynes before hys raygne ofttymes ouer run, but by him it was fully conquered,) &amp; Hungary, The Romain Empyre gretlye enlarged by Octauian Auguſtus. Guyō, Illiria, Rhetia, the Vā
               dales, and the Thalaſſians whyche inhabited among th Alpes, together wyth all thoſe cityes whyche were ſituate alonge the ſea coſtes of Pontus. Amonge whiche, theſe were the chiefeſt, Boſphorus and Ponticapeos. He vanquiſhed the Danes in battaile, and ſlewe greate armyes of the

Germains, and draue them ouer the floude Albis, whiche is in Barbarie farre beyonde the riuer of Rheyne. He foughte this battaile by Druſus, who was his wiues ſōne by he
                  •
                firſt huſbande, like as he did that other battaile againſt the Hungarians, by Tiberius an other of hys wyues ſonnes. After this battel, he brought forth of Germany .cccc. M priſoners, and placed them in Fraunce, a longe Fraūce repl
                     •
                   ſhed with inhabitantes by Octanian. vpon ye bankes of the riuer of Rhein. He recouered Armenia from yt Parthians, and the Perſians gaue hym hoſtages, whiche they neuer did to anye Pledges taken of the Perſians. before him. They reſtored more ouer ſuch enſignes to the Romains, as they had got from them, at what tyme they vanquiſhed Craſſus. The Scithians and Indians, who before had not hearde ſpeakinge of the Romaines, The Corinthians &amp; Indians ſent legates to Auguſtus. Galacia made a prou
                     ••••
                  . ſent both Legates and preſentes to Auguſtus. In his raygne, Galacia was alſo made a prouynce,

whiche was a kingdome before, and Marcus Lollius gouerned it in the ſtead of the Pretor. Beſides this, he was ſo well beloued of the Barbarians, that ſuche kinges as had ioyned frendſhippe with the Romaines, (to the end they might augment the honor of Auguſtus) builte diuers cityes which they called after his name, Ceſaree. As king Iuba did in Mauritania, Towns built and named after the name of Ceſar. and in Paleſtina (which is now a famous and faire citye.) Moreouer many kinges lefte their owne kyngdomes and came to Rome, to the end they might attende and do theyr ſeruice to Ceſar, and in ſuche lyke apparell as the Romains vſed to wear, (that is to ſay in gownes) they folowed his chariot, or horſe as he rode. After his death he was called a God. He lefte a mooſte fortunate common 3. Claudius Tiberius, ſonne to Liuia Auguſtus hys wyfe, by her welth to Tiberius his ſucceſſor who was his wiues ſonne by her former huſband, and became after that, to be

ſonne in lawe to Auguſtus by adoption, and the eſpouſing his daughter. fyrſt huſband began his Empyre in the. 3976. yere after the creatiō of the worlde. in the 768. yeare after the buylding of Rome and in the yere of our Lord God .xvi. Tiberius gouerned the Empyre by greate cowardiſe, greuous crueltye, vnmeaſurable auarice, and filthye luſte. Hee waged battayle no where hym ſelfe, but warred alwayes by hys Prouoſtes and ſubſtitutes. Dyuers kinges whome he hadde procured throughe greate flattery to come to hym, he woulde neuer permitte to departe againe. Amonge which, Archelaus kynge of Cappadocia was one, whoſe kyngdome he did alſo reduce into the forme of a Prouince: and the chiefeſt citye therof, he commaunded ſhoulde bee called by his name, whyche at this daye is called Ceſarea, where as before it was called Mazaca.
            In the .xxiii. yere of his raigne, hee deceaſed in Campania with ye great Tiberlꝰ hys raigne. reioyſing of all the Romaines, when he had liued .lxxx. and .iii. yeres. Tiberius deceaſed.
            
            
               
After him ſucceaded Caius Ceſar, 4. Caligula the 4. Emp
                     •
                  ror, ſonne to Germanicus, began his Empire. 3999. yere after the beg
                     •
                  nnyng of the world, in the. 701. yere af
                     •
                  er Rome was b
                     •
                  il
                     •
                  e, in the yeare of our Lord. 39. who was ſurnamed Caligula, neuew to Druſus and Tiberius, Auguſtus his wiues ſonnes, a verye naughty and cruel man, whoſe facts were ſo hainous, that if they had ben conferred with the doinges of Tiberius, they mighte make thoſe of Tiherius, to ſeeme tollerable. He warred againſte the Germaines, and inuaded Sweuia. But he atcheued ther no manly act. He had carnall copulation The diſhono
                  
                     ••
                  bl
                     •
                   raign of Caligula. wyth hys owne ſyſters, and hys owne daughter whome he begatte vpon the one of his ſiſters, he had in likewiſe carnall company wyth all. When he had thus vſed greate auarice, fleſhly luſt, and horrible cruelty towardes all men, he was ſlaine in his palaice in the .xxxix. yeare of hys Caligula 
                     •
                  layne. Caligula hys 
                     〈◊〉
                  . age, when he had raigned, iii. yeares x. monethes and .viii. daies.
            After him ſucceded Claudius, vncle by the fathers ſide to Caligula,

and ſonne to Druſus: (vnto whyche Claudius, there was a mooſte honorable 5. Claudius 
                     •
                  he v. Emper
                     •
                  r of Rome. ſon to Druſus, whyche was brother to 
                     ••
                  
                  berius, began his Empire, in the. 4003. yere after the creatiō of the worlde, in the 795. yeare after the b
                     •
                  ylding of Rome and in the yere of out Lord 41. he rai
                     •••
                   13. yeres and ix. monethes, he was poyſoned, in the. 11. yere of his raigne. tomb created at Menſe in Germany), whoſe neuewe alſo Caligula was. He raigned ouer Media, and did many things there very quietly. And yet ſome thinges did hee verye cruelly, and withoute diſcretyon. He made warre vppon the Britaynes: whyche countrey ſith the time of Iulius Ceſar, none of the Romaynes had euer had any thing to do withal. And when they were ouercome by Cneus Sentius, and Aulus Plantiꝰ, two famous and worthy men, he had a great triumph ouer them at Rome. Furthermore, he annexed alſo to the Empire of the Romaines, certain Ilandes ſituate in the Occean ſea beyond Britaine, called Orcades, and Warre vpon the Britain
                     •
                  , now called Englande. ſurnamed his ſonne 
                  •
               ritannicus. He behaued himſelf very curteouſly towardes diuers of his frendes, in ſo muche that when Plautius, (a notable

man), who in his viage which he made into 
                  •
               ritain, atchieued diuers notable actes, &amp; ſhould triumphe for the ſame, the Emperor himſelfe accompanied him, and (the vſe beynge ſuch that with his triumph he ſhould goo vp into the Capitoll,) Claudius gaue him the preheininence, &amp; went The term of Claudiꝰ hys 
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  gne. on his lefte hande. This Claudius liued. lxuii. yeres, and after his death was canoniſed. Claudius canonyſed.
            
            After him, ſucceaded Nero, who 6. Nero who was ſonne in law to Claudius, who adopted him to be his ſucceſſor in the Empyre. began his raign in the. 40
                     •
                  7. yere after the creatiō of the worlde, the 809. yere after Rome was builte, &amp; the 5. yere after Chriſt, he had carnal copuia
                     •
                  ton with his own mother, and eftſones 
                     ••
                  ewe her, and hys wife, and dyuers other wor thy mer. He was a great perſecutor of chriſtian religien, &amp; put diuers Sainctes to deth. did verye muche reſemble his vncle Caligula. He did greatlye dyſgrace and diminiſhe the Romaine welthe and ſubſtaunce: A man geuen to vnwonted ryot, ſtraunge luſt, and great expenſes and charges, ſo that after the manner of Caius Caligula, hee bayned hym ſelfe wyth hot and cold Oyntmentes. He fyſhed wyth golden ne
                  •
               tes, the ropes of which, wher with they were drawen foorth of the

water, were of Pnrple ſilke. He ſlew a greate noumber of the Senate. He became ennemy to all good menne: and at laſte, did habondone hymſelfe whollye ouer to ſo great diſworſhip, that hee woulde daunce and ſinge o
               
                  •
               penly in the apparaile of common mynſtrelles, and ſuche as are accuſtomed to play in enterludes. He cō
               mitted diuers mu
                  •
               thers vppon hys owne kinſfolkes.
            And when he had ſlaine hys owne brother, his wife, and his mother, he ſet the citye of Rome on fire, that he Rome ſet on fyre by Nero and burned 6. dais ſpace. mighte thereby (as by demonſtratyon) ſee after what faſhion Troy burued, when it was taken and ſette on fire by the Gretians. In feates of armes he durſte doo nothinge at all. The cowardiſe of Nero. He hadde almoſte loſte Britain. For duringe hys raigne, there were taken Brittaine nighe loſte. there and deſtroyed quite, two notable townes.
            
               
The Parthians did berefte hym of Armenia, and broughte the Romain armies vnder ſubiectyon. How be it, there were two Prouinces created during his raigne, Pontus Polemoniacus, Two prouinces created. by the aſſent of kinge Polemon, and Alpes Cotie, king Cotius being now deceaſſed. For thoſe hys actes, waxed he to be abhorred of the citizens of Rome, and cleane forſaken of all menne, and of the Senate was adiudged as an ennemy of that weale publique. Where vppon they ſought him, to haue beene reuenged on him, whoſe puniſhment was appoynted on this manner. That hee Puniſhment deuiſed by the Romaines for Nero. ſhould firſte be drawen naked throughe the citye, then hauynge a forke thruſte into his heade, he ſhoulde ſo hange, and be whipped tyll he were deade: after that, he ſhuld be thrown down hedlong from the rock.) which whiche when he vnderſtode,) he fled forthe of his palaice, and in a farme

er graunge of one, who had beene ſometime his bondman and was by him lately enfranceiſed, he ſlew himſelfe. Thys farme was ſituate betwene Nero ſlew
                     •
                   hym ſelfe. the two wayes Salaria and Numentana, (whiche wer .iiii. miles diſtant from Rome. He founded the bathes at Rome, which duryng hys Bathes in Rome. raigne, were called Neroniane, and nowe are called Alexandrine. He deceaſed in the .xxxi. yeare of hys age, Nero his age and raygne. when he had raigned .xiiii. yeres, and with him, almoſt all the progeny of Auguſtus was put out of memory.
            Afterward, Sergius Galba ſucceded 7. Sergius Galba the. 7. Emperour. in the Empire. A Senator of ancient nobleneſſe, who was choſen Emperoure by the Spanyardes and Frenchmen, when he was .lxxiii. ye
               
                  •
               es of age, and eftſones was gladlye 
                  •
               eceiued of the whole armye. For whileſt he was yet but a priuate mā, 
                  •
               e demeaned his life worthely both 
                  •
               n Martiall actes, and alſo in ciuyll pollicy.

He had beene ofte Proconſul, exerciſing the offyce of Conſul, for others. At ſondry times had he beene a captayne in mooſte perillous battayles. Hys Empire was but of very ſhorte continuaunce, proceding of meruailous good beginninges, ſauing that he ſeemed ſomewhat ouermuche geuen to ſeueritye. He was ſlayne thoroughe the treaſon of Otho, in the Galba ſlayn. ſeuenthe monthe of his raigne. Hys throate was cut in the market place at Rome, and lieth buried in his gardain
                  •
               s whyche are ſituate along the waye called Aurelia, not farre dyſtante from the citye of Rome.
            When Otho had thus ſlayne Galba, he inuaded the Empyre, and detained 
                  
                     •
                  . Otho the. 8. Emperour. it hym ſelfe. Hys ſtocke was more noble by his mothers ſide, then by his fathers, and yet was it by neither of them bothe, very baſe. When he was yet a priuate manne, hee behaued

hym ſelfe verye gentlye and tractablye.
            In his Empire he could not ſhew anye greate experimente of hys doynges, for that at the ſame time that he ſlew Galba, Vitellius was made Emperoure by tharmyes of the Germaynes, (who attempted battayle agaynſt hym. And Otho was diſcomfited in a very lighte ſkirmiſh at Bebriacus, (notwythſtandinge that hee had with hym a great band of men,) where hee ſlewe hym ſelfe, whome when hys Souldyoures requeſted, that hee woulde not ſo lyghtlye deſpayre Otho ſlewe hym ſelfe. of the ſucceſſe of the battayle, he aunſwered that he was not wōrthye, ne ſo muche to bee eſteamed, that for hys cauſe anye ciuyl battayl ſhould be waged, and there wyth al, ſmote himſelf in with his dagger in the .xxxviii. yere of his age, when hee The raigne of Ottho. had raigned foure ſkore and fiftene dayes.
            
               
Then Vitellius obtained the Empire, 9. Vitellius the ix. Emperor. deſcended of a familye whyche was become worſhipful through aduauncementes and promotions, rather then by nobleneſſe of birth. For his father whiche came neither of any notable line, was created Couſul thriſe a rowe. This Viteliius raigned with greate diſworſhip, beynge merueileuſly noted for his great cruelty, The diſord
                     •
                  rly ra
                     •
                  gne of Vitellius. but eſpeciallye for his exceſſyue glotony, and vnmeaſurable eatyng. In whiche he did ſo exceede, that (as report wente,) he feaſted .iiii. or v times in one day. But amonge all the Vitellius his exceſſiue glotony. reſidue of his bākets, this one is had in memory, whiche hys brother Vitellius prepared for him: in whyche, beſides other charges and expenſes, (as it was ſayde,) there were ſet before An example of vnineaſurable gluttony. him at one time, two thouſande fiſhes, and vii. thouſand birds. Thys Vitellius affecting very much to reſemble Nero his doinges, dyd ſo expreſlye

ſhewe this his ſayde purpoſe and intente, that he laboured (what in him laye,) to honour the exequies and funeralles of Nero, who at that time, lay but very meanely buryed. He was ſlayne by the captaynes of Vitellius ſlayne. Veſpaſian. But firſte he ſlewe Sabinus, Veſpaſian hys brother, whom he burned in the Capitoll, whyche he ſe
                  •
               te on fire. When Vitellius was thus ſlaine, he was wyth greate reproche and ignominie drawen naked openly along the city of Rome, The reproche ful death of Vitellius. with his bearde and hear of his head ſtaring, and a naked ſword ſet vnder his chin. And as he paſſed throughe the ſtreates on this ſorte, euerye one whiche met him, threwe dong in his face and boſome. Thys doone hys throte was cut, and he throwne into the ryuer of Tiber, that he myghte want the worſhip of burial, whyche In what eſtimation burial was amonge the Romains. is graunted to euerye man, yea euen to the ſimpleſt. He was ſlayne in the

lvii. yeare of his age, when he hadd
                  •
                raigned .viii. monethes and one day. Vitelliꝰ hys age &amp; raygne.
            
            After him ſucceaded Veſpaſiane, who was created Emperour at Paleſtina: 10. Veſpaſianus the tenthe Emperor began his raign in the. 4032. yere after the creation of the worlde, in the 824. yere after come was built, and in the. 71. yeare after th
                     •
                  ncarnatiō of chriſt A Princeendued wyth moſte excellēt vertues, a maintainer of ciuill order, and learnynge in Rome, ſo that he aſſignd certain ſtandyng ſtipends to Phiſitions &amp; profeſſors of other ſciēces at Rome. one in verye dede baſe born, howe be it worthye to be compared with the beſt and chefeſt Emperors. A man who for hys priuate lyfe was worthye to be hadde in memorye. For in that tyme, hee was ſente by Claudius into Germanye, and from thence into Brytaine, hee pytched fielde and foughte fyue tymes wyth hys ennemyes. Hee annexed to the Romaine Empyre two mightye nations, twentye townes, and the Ile of Wighte nighe adioyning to Britayne. Hee behaued hymſelfe in the Romaine Empire very moderately, but he was ſomewhat to muche deſirous of monye. Neuerthcleſſe he got the ſame in ſuche ſorte, that he wron ged no man for it.
            
               
And lyke as hee dyd wyth earneſt meanes and diligence, ſtudye to gather it together, ſo dyd he verye cyrcumſpectlye diſtribute the ſame abrode, eſpetiallye to ſuche as hadde great nede there of. So that vnnethe any man canne fynde eyther greater liberalitye, or more iuſtly employed of anye Prince that euer was before his tyme. He was verye pacyent and gentle: In ſo muche that he woulde not lightlye punyſhe anye ſuche as The great lenity of Veſpaſiane. were accuſed and openlye conuycted to haue conſpired treaſon agaynſte him, with anye greuouſer penaltye, then by baniſhment only.
            In the tyme of hys Empyre, Iudea and Ieruſalem, the mooſte famouſe and notable Cities of Paleſtina, were annexed to the Romaine Empire.
            Moreouer he reduced Achaſa, Licia, Rhodus, Bizantium, (whiche is nowe called Conſtantinople,)

and Samos, whiche before wer free cities,) and likewiſe Trachea, Cilicia, Thracia and Comagenes which were vnder the dominion of ſondrye kinges, ſuche as were frendes to the Romaines, into the fourme of Prouinces. He would quickly forget diſpleaſures and grudges of minde. He woulde pacientlye ſuffer and heare the rebukes and tauntes of Philoſophers, and of thoſe whyche pleaded mennes cauſes tofore him. But hee was an earneſt reformer of Martiall pollicy. He and hys ſonne Titus triumphed Veſpafian triumphed ouer Ieruſalem with hys ſon Titus. ouer Ieruſalem. Thus whē he was by theſe means beloued and well lyked of the Senate, and other the commons of Rome, and in fine of all men, he was ſtricken wyth a flixe, and ſo died at a Manor of hys owne, whiche was amonge the Sabines, Veſpaſian died of a flyxe. in the .lxix. yeare of his age, when he had raigned .ix. yeares and vii. daies, and was canoniſed. Veſpaſian his age, and tyme of 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
            
            
               
He had with ſuche obſeruation di
                  •
               
               gentlye marked the naituityes and byrthes of his ſonnes, that when ſon drye conſpiratyes were pretended againſte him and were deſeried, hee Credit to the caſting of natiuities. woulde alwayes diſſimule and neglect them: affirminge to the Senate, that either hys ſonnes ſhuld ſuccede him in hys Empire, or elſſe no man. After his deceaſe, Titus his ſonne ſucceaded him: who was alſo called 11. Titus Veſpaſ
                     •
                  an
                     ••
                  e .xi. Emperour began his raign in the. 4041. yere after the creatiō of the worlde, the 833. yere after Rome was ballte, 
                     •
                   the 
                     •
                  o▪ yereafter Chriſt his incarnation. Titus Veſpaſian a good archer. Veſpaſianes a man worthy of great
                  •
                admiration, for all kynde of vertues. In ſo muche that hee was called ſhe loue and delices of mankynde. He was very eloquent, and an 
                  ••
               tedyng ſtout warriour, and one of paſſynge
                  •
                greate ſobrietye. He pleabed cauſes himſelfe in Latine. He made diuers Poeticall inuentions and tragedies in Greke. At the aſſaulting of Ieruſalem (where he ſo
                  •
               loed vnder hys father,) he ſhot of .xii. arowes whych he beſtowed in ſuche ſorte, that with

eche of them hee ſlewe a manne, of them whyche ſtoode on the walles, in the defence of the Citye. Hee vſed ſuch lenity in hys Empire at Rome, The great lenity of Titus that he neuer punyſhed any one man at all. Such as were conuict to haue conſpired againſte him, bee diſmyſte and pardoned in ſuche ſort, that forth wyth he woulde agayne vſe and accept them in like familiaritye, as he did before. He was ſo eaſye to ve entreated, and there wyth alſo liberal, The liberality of Titus. that he neuer denied requeſt to anye manne. For whiche cauſe when hys frends rebuked him, for that his largeſſe and liberality: he made theym this goodly anſwer. From an Emperour An example of a ryghte princely hart. quod he, none oughte to departe ſorowful, for not obtaining theyr requeſtes. And for thys cauſe ones, as hee ſate at Supper, and bethoughte him that hee hadde that daye geuen nothynge to anye manne, hee ſayde: O my frendes I haue loſt this daye,

(accounting that for no day, in whiche The Theatre built, a place made halfe round, where the people aſſembled to be hold playes. he gaue not ſome thinge away.) He builded the Theatre at Rome, a place made round, very good to beholde playes and enterludes. And at the fyrſte erectinge thereof, he ſlewe ſiue thouſande wilde beaſtes.
            When he was throughe thys demeaninge hym ſelfe paſſyngly well beloued of all men, he fell ſicke and died at the ſame Manor place where hys father dyd, after that hee hadde Titus died. raigned two yeres, eight monethes, and twentye daies, and in the fortye yere of his age. There was no leſſe Titꝰ his age and raigne. mone and lamentation made for him after his death, then if euery manne had bewailed his owne priuate loſſe and aloneneſſe. The Senate hearing of his deceaſe, forthwith in haſt wēt that ſame night in the eueninge tide into the counſaile houſe, and there rendred vnto him (being now at this time dead) ſo greate praiſe &amp; thankes

as they did neuer the lyke to hym at any time. While he yet liued, &amp; was conuerſaunt amonge them. He was Titus canoniſed. alſo canoniſed. After his deceaſe, Domitianus 12. Domitianus the .xii. Emperor brother to Titus began his raign in the. 4043. yere after the creatiō of the worlde, in the 835. yeare after the buylding of Rome and in the yere of our Lord 83 he expulſed the Philoſophers and ſtudiers of the mathematicall ſciences forth of Rome he was the ii. emperor that perſecuted ye chriſtians, whō he put to deathe like as Nero dyd. The crueltye and pryde of Domitianus obtained the Empire, beinge yonger brother to Titus: but he reſembled more Nero or Caligula, or Tiberius, then he did eyther hys father or his brother. In the firſte beginnyng of hys Empyre, he behaued hymſelf with great temperance and modeſty: But ſoone after, being enfected wyth the vices of fleſhly luſt, anger, cruelty, &amp; auarice, he ſo kyndled the hatred of all mē againſt him, that he dyd in manner quite aboliſhe and blot out of memory, the good deſertes of hys father and brother. He ſlew the moſt worthy of the Senate. He was the firſte whiche commaunded hym ſelf to be called a God: He would not permyt the Romaynes to ſet vp anye pictures of hym, vnleſſe they were of golde or ſiluer. He ſlew

his owne coſen Germaine. He was moreouer of an horrible pryde. Hee made in his time .iiii. viages onlye. One agaynſt the Sarmatians, an other agaynſt the Cattianes, and two into Dacia, (whyche is nowe called Denmarke.) He tryumphed twiſe ouer the Dacianes and the Cattianes. When he had ſubdued the Sarmatianes, he ware but a garlād of baies only. He ſuſtained ſondrye damages in thoſe battailes: for in Sarmatia his Legiones and captain wer ſlain. And by the Danes, Appius Sabinus one of the Conſuls, &amp; Cornelius Fiſcus, captayn of the Emperours gard were alſo ſlayne, and great garyſons of men with them beſides. Hee finyſhed ſondry pieces of work at Rome: among which, was the Capitoll, the place for Muſicians and ſinging mē, the two gallaries called Iſium and Serapium, and the Tilt, (a place for men to run in.)
            
               
At length, beinge abhorred and deteſted of all menne for diuers hys wycked doinges, hee was ſlayne in Domitianus ſlain. his palaice by his owne men, in the xiv. yere of his age, and the .xv. yeare Domitianus his age and raigne. of hys raigne. His corps was caryed forth to buriall by ſuche onlye, as vſually cary the bodies of other mean men in Rome to buryinge, and ſo he was buryed verye dyſworſhipfullye.
         
         
            
            ¶ The eyghte boke of the Breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               IN the eyght hundreth &amp; fifty yeare after the building Vetus &amp; Valens Cōſuls. of ye city of Rome, at what time Vetus and Valens, were Conſulles, the weale publique When common welthes floriſh. of Rome aſpyred to a meruaylous proſperous eſtate agayne. For that nowe wyth greate good happe, the 13. Nerua the 13 Emperours began his Empyre in the. 4058. yere after the creatiō, of the worlde, in the 850. yeare after the buylding of Rome and in the yere of our Lord God. 98. adminiſtrynge there of, was committed and betaken to the guidaunce of good rulers.
            For after the deathe of Domitianus that deadlye tiraunt, Nerua ſucceaded: a manne whyche in hys priuate life, behaued hym ſelfe verye ſoberlye, and yet was he both ſtoute and manfull.
            
               
He was deſcended but of a meane line of nobilitye. 
                  •
               y the procur emēt of Petronius Secundus, who was captayne of the garde, and Parthenius whyche was he that ſlew Domitianus, he was choſen Emperor, beinge then berye aged. He demeaned hym ſelfe very vprightlye and curtuouſly. He prouided very 
                  •
               ire uniſpectlye for the weale publique, by adopting Traianus to hys ſonne. Nerua Nerua deceaſed. Nerua hys age &amp; raygn. died at Rome, after that he had raigned 14 Vlpius Traianus the. iiii Emperor began his raign in the. 4060 yere after the creation of the worlde, in the 8
                     •
                  1. yere after come was built, and in the. 100. yere after thincarnatiō of chriſt he was then. foreyner that was created Emperor, he was a Spaniard borne and no Italian. adopted to the ſucceſſyon of the Empyre by Nerua. he was the third emperor that perſecuted ye chriſtians. But in his time it was decreed yt they ſhould not be called to examinatyon, except they had bene fyrſt accuſed. Armenia renued. one yere, iiii. moneths, and .viii. dayes, in the .lxxvi. yeare of hys age. After his death, he was canoniſed.
            After him ſucceded Vlpius Traianus Crinitus, who was born at Italica in Spayne, whoſe parentage was more auncient of time then noble of birthe. His father was fyrſte Conſul: thē after he became to haue gouernmēt of thother Agripina a city in Fraunce. He gouerned ye weale publique in ſuche ſort, that he might

worthelye be preferred aboue all other Princes. He was one of paſſyng great ciuility and ſtoutneſſe wythal. Hee enlarged bothe in lengthe and bredthe, the borders and marches of the Romaine Empire, whyche ſithe the tyme of Auguſtus, was rather but defended and onlye conſerued, then worthely augmented. He repaired thoſe cities which were ruinous and fallen in decaye on the farther ſide of Rheine in Germany. He ſubdued Dacia, and vanquiſhed Decibalus. Hee created a Prouince on the farther ſide of Danubiꝰ, in thoſe parties where as now ye Taiphalianes inhabite. That Prouince extended to a thouſand miles in cixcuit. He recouered Armenia, which the Parthiās had won, and ſlewe Pharnaces the Sirian who deteined it. He appoynted one to be king ouer the Albanes. Hee receiued vnder obeyſaunce, the kynges of the Spaniardes, the Moſcouites,

the Boſphoranes, the Arabiaues, the Dſdroenes, and of the inhabitaunts of Cholchos. He conquered the Adiabenes and Marchomedes. He ſubdued Antemuſiū a greate region of Perſia. He wanne Seleucia, Cteſiphontes, Babilone, and Ediſſios, and broughte that countrey in ſubiection vnto the borders of India, and marched ſtill forwarde, vntill he came to the redde ſea, where he founded three Prouinces, Armenia, Aſſiria, and Meſopotamia: together Thre prouinces made. wyth thoſe people whyche border vppon Macedonie. After that, he reduced Arabia alſo into the forme of a Prouince. He prepared a nauye for the red Sea, minding there with A vlage prepared ok the red ſea. to ſpoyle the coaſtes and borders of India. But his curteſye and ſobriety excelled farre all thoſe hys Martiall The paſſyng ſame of Traianus. feates. He behaued himſelf at Rome and elſſe where through all his Prouinces, fellow like to all men.
            
               
He went oftentimes to hys frendes houſes to ſalute the
                  •
                and viſit them if they were ſicke and diſeaſed.
            If they feaſted one an other, he woulde alſo banket amonge them, without putting anye difference betwene them and hym ſelfe.
            Often woulde he ride wyth them in theyr chariottes. He would Meuer harme anye Senator, nor commit anye thinge contrarye to iuſtice, for the augmenting of his treaſoure. He vſed greate liberalitye towardes all menne. Bothe openlye and ſecreatlye enryched hee all perſonnes, and aduaunced to honoures diuers ſuche as he hadde but very ſmall acquayntaunce and familiaritye wythall. He buylte in manner a whole worlde hym ſelfe. He enfraunchiſed manye cities. In fine, he did nothinge, but it was very quietly done, and voyde of all trouble.
            For during all hys whole raigne,

there was but onlye one Senatour condempned, whome the reſidue 
                  〈◊〉
                the Senate adiudged to deathe, vnwittynge to Traianus. For whyche cauſe, he was throughe al the whole worlde reputed of all men moſt lyke to a God. So that both whileſt he ye
                  •
                
               Traianus reputed for a God. liued, and after his death alſo, he demerited immortall honour. Amonge the reſidue of al his worthy ſayings, thys one of hys, deſerueth eternall memory. When his frendes hapned once to reprehend him, for that he behaued hym ſelfe ſo gently towardes all men, he made this aunſwer: that when he was nowe Emperoure, he ſhewed hym ſelfe to be ſuche towardes A worthy ſaying of an Emperoure. hys ſubiects and populer people, as he (when he was as yet a ſubiect) wiſhed the Emperoure to haue bene to him wardes. When he had thus purchaſed great glory and renowne bothe for ciuil and alſo Martiall pollicy, as he retourned from Perſides,

he ſickned and died by the way, at Seleucia Traianus deceaſed. a town of Iſauria of the flixe: when he had liued .lxii. yeres, ix. monethes and .iiii. daies, in the .xix. yere Traianꝰ his age &amp; raygne. vi. moneth, and .xv. day of his raigne. He was canoniſed, and of all other, Traiane the fyrſte Emperour whyche was buryed wythin the city. he alone was buried within the city. His bones were put in a golden cup, and ſette vnder a piller, in a ſtreate whyche hee builte himſelfe, whiche piller amounted in heighte to an C. and .xliiii. fote. The factes of Traianus are ſo rife in memory, that euen in theſe oure daies in the Senate or Councell houſe, the fortunate acclamations and well wiſhynges to the Prince by his commons, at his elections, are vſed to be theſe. That hes myght proue in his affairs more fortunate then Anguſtus, and in behauioure and demeanor of hymſelfe, to excel Traianus. So much preuailed in him the fame of perfect goodneſſe, that whether men flatter him, or doo

in deede commend him, he gaue vndoutedly iuſt occaſion to be accompted a moſt worthy exāple to others.
            When Traianus was deceaſſed, Elius Adrianus was created Emperoure, 15. Elius Adrianus the .xv. Emperoure, begenne his raigne in the. 4079. yere after the creatiō of the worlde, the 871. yeare after Rome was builte, &amp; the 119. yeare atfer Chriſte, he gaue hymſelf wholly to purchaſe peace &amp; quietnes, there was no one Emperor ſence Auguſtꝰ time, whyche aduantaged ye common wele ſo much as he did, he was verye experte in Aſtrenomy he made prog noſticatyons, yerely for his owne ſelf. He perſecuted the chriſtians at the fyrſte, but after he had red diuers b
                     •
                  
                  kes which certain Chriſtians that wer learned men, wrate to him, he wild that none ſhuld be apprehended for religyons ſake. not for that Traianus willed it ſhoulde be ſo, but throughe the onlye procuremente of Plotina wife to Traianus. For ſo longe as Traianus was yet liuinge, hee woulde neuer adopte hym, nor make him his heire: althoughe hee was his owne ſiſters daughters ſonne, and coſen to hym. He was alſo borne at Italica in Spaine.
            This Adrianus enuyinge at the glorye of Traianus, yelded vppe the keepinge of thoſe three Prouynces whyche Traianvs hadde annexed to the city of Rome, and remouing hys armye
                  •
                from Aſſiria, Meſopotamia, and Armenia, hee mineded that hys Empire ſhuld not haue extended any further that way, thē to the riuer Euphrates.

But when hee purpoſed to geue ouer Dacia alſo, which then ye Romaines kept, his frendes diſſwaded him from that (fearinge leaſte by that meanes, many Romain citizens ſhuld haue ben endangered to fal in to the handes of the Barbarians.) For Traianus after that he had ſubdued Dacia,) remoued thither great plenty of people, whome he aſſēbled together throughe all the Romayne Empire and dominion, to inhabyte there, and manure that lande. For that Dacia was through the continuall warres of Decibalꝰ, become now voide of inhabitauntes, and cleane wythout ſtrength, He had peace during the whole time of his Empyre. Only one battail waged he and that One bettayle only durynge the raigne of Adriands. by his Prouoſt. He went ouer all the Romain Empire hymſelf, and built manye places there. He was verye eloquent in the Latine tong, and exceding well ſene in the Greke tong.

He was not greatly commended for any clemēcy which he vſed. He was exceding circumſpect about the treaſory, and Martiall policye. He deceaſed in Campania, beinge aboue the Adrianus deceaſed, hieage and raygne. age of .lx. yeares, when he had raigned .xxi. yeares .x. monethes and .xix. dayes. The Senate would not canoniſe him. Neuertheleſſe his ſucceſſor Ditus Aurelius Fuluius requyred very earneſtly that he mighte be canoniſed: whiche thing al the Senate did openly withſtand. Howe be it at length, he obtained it. Than after, Adrianus there ſucceded Antonius Fuluius Boionius who was called 16. Antoniꝰ Fulnius Boioniꝰ the. 16. Emperor, whom Adrianus adopted, began his raygne in the. 140. yere after the Incarnatyon of Chriſt. alſo Pias: he was deſcended of a noble familye, but yet of no longe antiquity. He was a notable man, and ſuche one as might worthelye be cō
               pared with Numa Pompilius, like as 
                  ••
               aianus mighte bee conferred wyth Romulus. Whē he was as yet a priuate man, he behaued hymſelfe

very well, and in his Empyre farre better. He ſhewed cruelty to no mā. He exhibited greate curteſye to all men. In Martiall feates he obtained meane glory, endeuoringe euermore rather to defend, then to amplify and enlarge his prouinces: aſſigning the iuſteſt men that hee coulde finde, to heare office in the common wealth. He aduaunced alwaies to promotyons ſuche as were good men, and deteſted ſuch as were leud and naughty perſonnes, without vſinge (for all that,) any rigor or cruelty to anye of them. Amonge ſuche kynges as had ioyned frendſhippe and amitye with the Romaynes, he was not onlye reuerenced, but feared alſo. In ſo much that diuers nations of the Barbarianes A notable argument of inſtice and indifferency. (ſetting warres and force aſide) would bring their controuerſies and matters in debate, to bee decided before him: yelding them ſelues wholly to abide his determinate ſentence

there in. And wher as before thaccep taunce of thempire, he was exceding riche, and of paſſing great welth, yet during his ſayde raigne, he did wonderfullye diminiſhe and abate hys ſayde ſubſtaunce, and greatly impoueryſhe hymſelfe by augmentynge the wages of his ſouldioures, and vſinge ſo greate liberalitye towardes his frendes. Howe be it he lefte the common treaſoure well ſtored and welthy. He was called Pius, for the great pity and gentleneſſe whych he vſed. Hee deceaſed at Lorium a Manor Antonius deceaſed of a feuer. place of his owne, whiche was ſituate .xii. miles diſtant from Rome, when he had liued .lxxiii. yeares, and raigned .xxiii. yeres. He was worthely canoniſed.
            Nexte after him, Marcus Antonius 17. M. Antonius Verꝰ the 17. Emperor began his raign in the yeare of our Lord 163 he was paſſig wellearnd, he adminyſtred the Empire ioyntly wyth his brother L. Antoninꝰ. In his time a pece of England receyued the fayth. Verus attained the Empyre: A man whiche doubtleſſe was come of a very noble houſe. He conueyed hys diſcent by the fathers ſide, from Numa

Pompilius, and by his mothers ſide from kynge Salentinus. There raigned with him alſo as Emperor, Lucius Annius Antoninus Verus. At that tyme firſte began the weale publyque of Rome to be adminiſtred by two Emperors at one time, who with like and indifferent authoritye gouerned the ſame, whereas before that tyme, it was gouerned by one alone.
            Theeſe two were bothe of one kindred and aliaunce. For why, Verus Annius Antoninus eſpouſed the daughter of Marcus Antoninus, and Marcus Antoninus, was ſonne in lawe to Antoninus Pius, by meane of his wyfe Galeria Fauſtina the yonger, which was his ſiſters daughter, and coſen germaine to hym.
            They waged battayle agaynſte the Parthianes, whyche neuer erſte Battayle againſt the par thians. rebelled, ſith the victory that Traianus had ouer them.
            
               
Verus Antonius tooke on him that viage, and ſtaying for a time in Antioche, and in the borders of Armenia, hee atcheued ſondrye and thoſe worthy feates there, by meane of his captaines. He wan Seleucia a verye Seleucia wan. famous City of Aſſiria, and toke priſoners v. C. M. men in it. He brought a triumphe with him forthe of Parthia and ſolempniſed it with his brother, who was alſo hys Father in lawe. But as hee departed from the citye Concordia, minedinge to go towardes Altium, (whych is now called Torrine,) he died. For as he rode in chariot with his brother, hee was ſodainlye ſtricken wyth an iſſue of bloude, by meane of a diſeaſe, which the Gretians call 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . (The Antoniꝰ Verus deceaſſed force of the diſeaſe is ſuch, that thoſe whom it taketh, it depriueth of their ſenſes,) he was ve rye witty. Of hym ſelfe, hee was diſp oſed and enclyned to no great ciuility e. But yet for the

rence whiche he ſtode in of hys brother, he durſt neuer attempt any cruel fact. When he was deceaſed, whiche Antoninus Verus hys age &amp; raigne. was in the .xi. yere of his raigne, he was canoniſed. After his deathe, Marcus Antoninus alone gouerned The romaine Empire reduced to yt forme of a Monarch againe. the Empire, being ſuche one as men mighte rather meruaile at, then but praiſe only. For from the beginnyng of his raigne, he was very ſober and graue. In ſo muche that in his childhode, hee woulde neuer aultare hys countenaunce, either for mirth or for ſorowe. He was whollye addicted to the Philoſophy or doctrin of the Stoikes, profeſſing him ſelfe not only in outward demeanor and kinde of lyuinge, but by his learning alſo, to be a right Philoſopher. When he was as yet but a very yong man, hee was had in ſuche admiration, that Adrianus purpoſed then with himſelfe, to leaue him as his ſucceſſor in his Empire. How be it he adopted Antoninꝰ

Piꝰ minding ſo to cōtriue the matter that Marcus ſhould be ſonne in law to Antoninus Pius whō he adopted, and that ſo, by order of ſucceſſion, he might at laſte aſpyre to the Empyre. In Philoſophye hee was inſtructed by Apollonius the Chalcedonian. He was traded vp in the Greke tounge by Sextus Cheroneſus, who was neuew to Plutarch. He was taughte the Latine tounge, by Frontus a notable Orator. He delt withal men vp rightlye at Rome. He was nothynge Worthy commendatyon of a prynce. the higher minded for all the pompe of his Empire. He was exceading liberall. Hee entreated the Prouynces which were vnder his gouernmente with great gentleneſſe &amp; moderatiō. Matters tooke very good ſucceſſe in Germany, during the raigne of thys Prince. He waged one battayle hymſelf againſte the Marcomanes: (who are ſuppoſed to be the people of Bohemia.) A battayle by the Bohemians. This battell was ſo great &amp;

cruel, that almoſt no mā can euer remember ye like, ſo that it might well be compared with thoſe whych were waged againſt ye Carthaginiens. It was ſo much the more ctuel and greuous, for in that battaile all his armye died. For durynge his raigne, there fel ſo greate a Peſtilence, that after the victory whiche he got ouer A great Peſtilence in Italy. the Perſians, the greateſt part of the inhabitauntes of Rome and Italye, and other the Prouinces, and well nigh all the ſouldioures died.
            Where vppon when by the ſpace of three yeares continuallye wythoute intermiſſyon, he hadde continued his battayle at Carnuntum, he finyſhed at length his battayl againſt The battayle which the Bohemians finiſhed. the Marcomannes, whych the Quadianes, the Vaudales, the Sarmatianes, the Swyſſers, and all Barbarye hadde maintained againſt the Romaynes.
            
               
He ſlewe there many thouſandes of men: and when he had deliuered the Hungarians forth of bondage, he triumphed againe at Rome wyth hys M. Antoninus triūphed at Rome. ſone Commodus Antoninus, whom he created Ceſar. And when through the charges and expenſes of the ſaid battail, he hadde exceadingly waſted and nighe ſpent all his treaſure, and had nowe nothinge lefte whiche hee mighte geue abrode as he had accuſtomed, he would not yet for all that, exact any thing among the Senators or others aboute the Prouinces, but did chuſe rather to ſell all his wardrobe by peece meale, in that ſtreate whiche Traianꝰ made. There made Themperour ſolde all hys ſubſtaunce rather then he would charge his ſubiectes with exactiōs hee alſo open ſale of all his plate of golde, cuppes of Criſtal, &amp; Murrhine ſtone: He ſold moreouer, the apparel whyche belonged to him ſelf and his wife, and diuers other Iewels &amp; ornamentes of precious ſtones. The foreſaid ſale laſted by the ſpace of .ii.

whole monethes. By this meane, he got againe muche gold into his treaſury. But ſo ſone as he had obtained the victorye, hee repaired to ſuche as had bought any part of his ſaid ſubſtaunce, their mony againe, to ſuche of them as would departe wyth the thinges whiche they had all readye bought. And thoſe which deſired rather to deteine ſtil that whyche they had bought, then to take their mony again, he neuer moleſted or diſquieted for it. He llcenſed ſuche as were noble men to feaſte with like ſumptuouſneſſe and furniture, and to bee ſerued with like ſeruitors as he was himſelf. When he had gotten the victorye, he was ſo liberall in dealinge gifts, that in one day (as the reporte went,) he gaue away an C. Lyons to gether. Thus when hee had reduced The greate largeſſe of Antoninus. the weale publique, to a moſt fortunate eſtate, bothe for manhoode and curteſy, he deceaſed in the .xviii. yere

of his raigne, when hee had liued .lx. yeares and one, and was canonyſed, (all the people earneſtly laboring to haue it ſo,) After him ſucceded Luciꝰ Antoninꝰ Cōmodus his ſonne, who L. Antoninꝰ Cōmodus, ye 18. emperour began hys raigne in the yeare of oure Lord. 181. in one thing reſēbled his father, but only that he had alſo good ſucceſſe in battaile againſt the Germaines. He wold haue chaunged the name of the moneth of September, and called it Cōmodꝰ after his own name. He defamed himſelfe with riot &amp; ribaudry. He plaid oftentimes in thopē ſcholes of fence, &amp; ſometimes alſo vppon the theater or ſtage, with ths maſters of defence them ſelues. He died ſodenly Antoninus Commodus died ſodenly. ſo y• men did iudge that he was ether thrailed or poyſoned, when hee had raigned .xii. yeres and .viii. monthes after the deceaſe of his father, he was ſo abhorred of all men, that euen after Commodus Antoninus his raigne. his deceaſe, he was demed as an enemy of mankinde. After him ſucceded 19. Pertinax the 19 Emperour beganne his raign the 194 yeare of oure Lord. ded Pertinax, who was then very aged,

for why he was lxx. yeres of age and at that time called Prefecturoo: And when he had raigned .lxxx. dais, he was ſlaine in an vproure whiche fell amonge the garde, throughe the Pertinax ſlayne. treaſon of Iulianus.
            Nexte after him Saluius Iulianus got the Empire, a noble manne Saluius Iulianus the 26. emperour began his raigne in the yeare of oure Lorde. 194. and one whiche was very experte in the lawes: neuew to that Iulianus, who durynge the raigne of Adrianus the Emperoure, (whom the Romaynes worſhypped for a GOD,) made alwayes the Proclamatyons and other thedictes and ordinaunces of the Emperor. This Iulianꝰ was diſcomfited by Seuerus, at ye bridge Iulianus diſcomfyted. called Miluius bridge, and beynge purſued, was ſone after ſlaine in hys palaice. He liued .vii. monthes after Iulianus ſlayne. the tyme that hee fyrſte beganne to Iulianus his raigne. raygne. From that time, Septunius Seuerus tooke the rule and gouernmente of the Romayne Empyre:

Who was born at a town called Lepus, whiche was in Tripolinata, a prouince in Affrick. He was the only Emperor, (after as any man can remember,) The onlye Emperoure created forth of Affricke. either before that tyme, or ſith, whiche was create Emperoure forth of Affricke. He had firſte the ordering and ouerſight of the treaſor, ſone after hee was made Tribunus Militum. Frō thence, paſſing throughe diuers offices and preferments: At laſt he became to haue the admyniſtration of the whole weale publique. He willed that men ſhould cal him Pertinax, for the great zeale and good wil whiche he ſemed to owe to that Pertinax whyche was flaine by Iulianus: He was very ſparyng and nere him ſelfe, and by nature cruell. He waged ſondry battails, and thoſe with great dexterity &amp; good ſucceſſe. Seuerus his valiauntnes. He ſlewe Percenius Niger at Cizicus, who rebelled in Egipte and Siria. He oueacame the Parthians. He

ſubdued the Arabians ſo nyghe, that he made a prouince there. By meane wherof, he demerited to haue the names Sextinus Seuerus called Parthicꝰ and Arabicus to be called Parthicus and Arabicus. Hee repaired manye thynges throughe out the Romain Empyre. In this time alſo Clodius Albinus, who had aſſociated hymſelf wyth Iulianus Clodius Albinus created himſelf Ceſarium France. to helpe him to 
                  •
               lea Pertinax, created hymſelfe Ceſar in Fraunce, and was vanquiſhed at Louane, and ſlayne there. But Seuerus beſides yt he did excell in glorye, purchaſed by feates of armes, he was alſo reuerē
               ced for his ciuil policy. He was hothe Worthy praiſe in a prince. learned, and had attained beſides the perfection of the knowledge of Philoſophy. The laſt battaile whych he waged, was in Britaine. And to the Seuerus ſubdued Brytaine. end that hee mighte make ſure wyth defence al ſuche prouinces as he had won there, he cauſed a trenche to be caſt from ſea to ſea a long, the lēgth of .xxii. miles. He deceaſed at Yorke,

being very aged in the xviii. yere and Seuerushys age &amp; raygne. iiii. month of his raign, &amp; was canoniſed. He left his ſonne Baſſianus &amp; Geta to ſuccede him in hys Empire. But he willed the Senate that they ſhould cal his ſonne Baſſianꝰ, Antoninꝰ. Whervpon he was named Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Baſſiainꝰ, 22. Antoninus Baſſianꝰ the 22. Emperor, after his fathers deathe, begā his Empire in the 213. yere after Chriſtes Incarnation, he ſlew his brother in law at his mothers breſtes. &amp; ſucceded his father alone. For Geta who was counted as open enemy to ye weale publique, dyed forthwith. Thus was Marcus Aurelius Antoninꝰ Baſſianꝰ, who was alſo called Caracalla, created Emperor. He was wel nigh like of conditions vnto hys father, but ſomewhat ſharpe &amp; more ful of threatninges. Hee founded the bathes at Rome whiche were called Antonians, a notable pece of worke. Beſides that, he did nothing worthy Autoniane bathes founded at Rome. of memory. He was out of meſure geuen to ſenſuality, and carnall concupiſcence: in ſo much that he eſpouſed hys mother in law Iuba. He dyed in

Oſdroenes at Edeſſa, as hee made preparacion for his viage againſt the Parthians, in the .vi. yere and ſecond month of his raign, when he had liued ſkant .xliii. yeres. He was buried very ſimply, after the commō ſort of people. There were Opilius Macrinus, and his ſonne Diadumenꝰ created Emperors. This Macrinus was ſomtime captaine of the gard. They did nothing that was worthy of memory, for ye ſhort time of their raign, whiche endured but by the ſpace of one yeare and two monethes. They wer ſlain both together in a ſedityon which fell amonge the ſouldioures. Next after them was Marcꝰ Aureliꝰ Antoninus created Emperor, whom men ſuppoſed to be the ſonne of Antoninus Garacalla. Hee was one of the prieſtes of the Temple of Heliogalus. When he was come to Rome beinge long loked for, bothe by the Senate and ſouldioures.
            
               
He diffamed and proſtituted himſelf to all kinde of ſhame and reproche. He liued very vnchaſtly and filthily. And about two yeares and .viii. monethes afterward. Hee was ſlaine in Aurelius Antonius ſlayn. an vproure whyche the Souldioures made, and hys mother Semia Sira wyth him.
            After him, Aurelius Alexander be 2. Aurelius Alexander the xxv. Emperor, was choſen Emperor whē he was but .xii. yeres of age. He was a verye vertuous prī
                  ce &amp; one that fauoured all good men, he was the fyrſt Emperoure that fauored Chriſtians, he began hys raigne, the 225. yere after Chriſtes incarnatyon. Magiſter Scriuii. came Emperoure, whome the ſonldiors named Ceſar, and the Senate created Auguſtus, beinge as yet but a very yonge manne. In the battaile which he attempted againſt the Perſians, he vāquiſhed with great glory their king Xerxes, with great diligēs he gaue himſelf to martiall pollicy. Certain legions of ſouldiours which made vproures and were vnquiet, he diſmiſte and put forthe of wages. He aſſociated with him to aſſiſte hym in iudgement and geuing of ſentence, Vlpianꝰ who made the lawes, who alſo ſupplyed an O ffyce in Rome,

which was called magiſter Scriuii, an office (much like that) whithe we call here the maſter of the Rolles.) This Emperour demeaned himſelf very gently at Rome. He was ſlaine Aurelius Alexander ſlain in Fraunce in a tumult that grew among the ſouldiours, iv the .xiii. yere and .viii. day of his raigne. Who ſhewed during his whole life time very greate godlineſſe towardes all men: eſpeciallye toward his mother Mamea.
         
         
            
            ¶ The ninthe booke of the Breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               AFter that Aureliꝰ 26. Maximinꝰ ye 26. emperour beganne hys raigne in the yeare of oure Lord. 237. he was fyrſte a ſhepherd in Thracia, and became after to be a ſouldioures. was dead Maximinꝰ obtained the Empire, being deſcended of a mene parentage: for why, his father was a ſouldioure. Hee was the firſte that aſpired to the Empyre, by meane of the ſouldiors only, not being authoriſed by the Senate, &amp; one who had bene neuer him ſelf Senator before: when hee had with good ſucceſſe fought againſt the Germaines, and was by the ſouldioures nominated Emperour, he was ſlain by Pupienus at Aquileia, (and his ſōne Maximinus ſlayne. with him, who was as then but a very childe.) when hee had raigned by

the ſpace of three yeares, and a fewe Maximinus his raigne. dede daies, at which time his owne ſouldiors forſoke him, and fled from him, then were there three whyche at one time in Rome bare the name of Auguſtus, whych were Pupienus Thre Emperors together at Rome. Balbinus, and Gordianus: of which the .ii. firſt were deſcended of a verye baſe line, but Gordianus was come of a noble progeny: for whye, his father ſhould haue bene choſen Prince by the ſouldioures, at what time hee ſupplyed the offyce of Conſull in Africke: duringe the raign of Maximinus. So ſoone as they were come to Rome, Balbinus and Pupienꝰ wer Balbinus &amp; Pupienus ſlayne. ſlaine in the palaice: and the Empire was reſerued for Gordianus alone. Who being as yet but verye yonge, 27. Gordianꝰ the 27 Emperour beganne his raign the 241 yeare of oure Lord. eſpowſed Tranquilliua at Rome, and warred in two places together at ones.
            And toke his viage from thēce into theſe parts, he waged battel agaīſt ye 
               He raygued vi. yeres.
               
Parthians who were nowe readye to iſſue forthe of their citye againſte him. This battail in ſhort ſpace toke very good ſucceſſe. And he in ſondry great ſkirmyſhes dyd ſore afflyct the Perſiās. But as he returned, he was Gordianus ſlayne. ſlaine, not farre from the borders of the Romaynes, through the treaſon of Philip, who ſucceaded hym in the Empyre. After hys death one of hys ſouldioures erected a monum ent for a memoriall of him, about .xx. myles diſtant from Circeſſhus (whyche is now a caſtel of the Romaines): near adioyninge to Euphrates His funerals Gordianus canoniſed. were ſolempnized at Rome, and hee was canoniſed. Then the two Philips, the father and the ſōne toke 28. Philip the 28 Emperoure, beganne his raigne with his ſonne, the yeare of oure lord. 247. the yeare of theyr raign was the 1000. yere after Rome was built. on them the gouernment of the Empire, after that Gordianus was thus ſlaine, and returned into Italye, leading backe with them the army forth of Siria. It was accompted the M. yere after the building of the citye of

Rome, at what time they began firſt their raign: which yere was celebrated with great ſolempnity and preparation of games and ſhews. Not lōg after they were bothe ſlaine by tharmy. The ii. Phillips ſlayne. The elder Philip at Verona the yonger was ſlaiue at Rome. They raigned by the ſpace of v. yeres, and were canonized both. After their deceaſe, 29. Decius the 29. Emperer begāhis raign in the yeare of our Lord. 252 he was the. 8. Emperoure whiche perſecuted the chry ſtiās, he made an act that all that worſhipped Chriſte, ſhuld be ſlain. Some iudged he was ſwalowed vp in an earthouake. Decius (who was born at Bubalia in Hungarie) obtained thempire. Hee repreſſed a eiuill battayle which was commenced in Fraunce. He creaied his ſonne Ceſar. He foū
               ded a bathe in Rome. But bothe hee and his ſonue were ſlaine in Barbarie: after that they hadde raigned by the ſpace of two yeres and were canoniſed. There were then created Emperoures, Gallus Hoſtiliauus: and Voluſianus his ſonne.
            During the time of their Empire, 10. Gallus Hoſti Itanus the. 30 Empiror, began his raign in the yeare of our lord. 254. together with his ſonne Voluſianus. He was alſo a perſecutor of the chriſtians they raygned ſkant ii. yeres Emilianus attempted new conſpiracies in Moeſia, and when they bothe

wente to ſubdewe hym, they were ſlayne at Iteramna, and ſo raygned not full oute two yeares. They committed no fact worthye of memorye. Their Empire was for thys cauſe only remembred, for that during the time there of, there fel great plagues and ſondrye other diſeaſes and mala dies with in the Romaine Empyre. Emilianus like as hee was of baſe Great plages in the romain Empyre. ſtocke deſcended, righte ſo was the time of his Empire verye obſcure, and wythout fame: when bee hadde Emilianus emperours. raigned .iii. monthes he was ſlayne.
            After him Lucinius Valerianus, who had the gouernment of Rhoetia and Norſeus, and was lieuetenaunt 31. Lucius Valerius the 31. Emperor, begā his Empire in the 256 yereafter Chriſtes Incarnation, he was a perſecutor of the chriſtians, &amp; vſed them ſo extremely that many of thē forſoke the faith for feare of death. there, was by the army created Emperoure, and eftſones made Auguſtus. At that time, was Galienus alſo made Ceſar at Rome by the aſſent of the Senate. The raygne of theſe two was very pernityous and hurtful, and in māner an vtter decoy

to the fame and renowne of the Romaines, what for the miſfortune and euill luck which they had in their affairs, and what for the cowardneſſe of the ſaid princes. The Germaynes were entred within Italy, and aproched vnto the city Rauenna. Valerianus waginge battall in Meſopotamia, Valerianus diſcomſyted &amp; takē priſoner by Sapor
                     •
                  s. and vſed very vily, for when Sapores woulde take his horſe, hee made Valerianus to lie on the ground that he might tread on hym while hee got vppon hys horſebacke in ſtead of a blok or ſoteſtole. was diſcomſlted there, by Sapores king of the Perſians, and ſone after was taken priſonner: and ended his life among the Perſians in moſt ſeruil boudage, Galienus (who was made Auguſtus) beinge as yet but a very yong man. At ye firſt he did with great derterity gouern ye weale publique: Sone after, indifferently wel, and at the laſt, meruailous naughtily. For when he was but yong, he at cheued and brought to paſſe ſondrye things in Fraſice &amp; Illiria 
                  •
               ery ſtoutly. He ſlew Iugenuꝰ at Murſia, (one of ye peres of y• country) &amp; Treballinnꝰ. Long time after that, he behaued himſelf meruailous ſtil and quiet.
            
               
Afterward geuing himſelf wholy ouer to wantonneſſe and ryot from thēce forth he gouerned y• weal publique, with exceadinge great cowardiſe, ſo that things fell into paſſynge greate deſperation. The Almaines when they had deſpoiled Fraunce, The Romaynes annoyed the Romaine empyre. they inuaded Italy. And Dacia, whiche was ſituate on the farther ſide of the riuer Danubius, and by Traianꝰ was annexed to the Romaine Empire, was then loſte. Grees, Macedonie, Pontns, and Aſia were ouer run by the Gothes. Hungary was deſpoiled by the Sarmatians, and the Bohemians. A great parte of the Romain empyre won by foreyners. The Germaines proceded ſtil forward vntil they cam to Spain, where they conquered the worthye city Tarracon. When the Parthiās had no we gotten Meſopotomia, they began alſo to pretende atytle and of claime to Syria. Thus when things were welnigh paſt all hope of reconerye, and the Romaine Empyre almoſte

wholly extinguiſhed, Poſthumius a Frenche man borne, beynge Poſthumius vſurped the eſtate imperial come of a verye baſe ſtocke, intruded into thempire, and gouerned ye ſame by the ſpace of .x. yeres, in ſuche ſort, that through his great p
                  •
               oweſſe and manhode, he recouered thoſe prouinces, whiche were then almoſte quite loſte. But wythin a while after, hee was ſlaine in a tumult, in which the Poſthumius ſlayne. ſouldiours roſe againſt him, for that he would not licence and permit thē to rifle and ſacke the city Moguncia, which rebelled againſt him: at which place, Lollianus alſo begā new conſpiracies. After him, Mariꝰ a handicraftes Marius vſurped the imperiall eſtate. man, of a very vile and reiect occupation, got the Empire, and the next daye after he was ſlayne. Then Victorinus gouerned Fraunce. Victorinus toke on him the gouernment of Fraunce: he was a meruaylous ſtout man of courage, but ouermuche geuen to carnall concupiſcēs. And when he fel to deflour and forſe

other mens wiues, he was ſlayne at Victorinus ſlayne. the city Agrippina in the ſecond yere of his raigne, through the treaſon of one Acturiꝰ. After him ſucceded Tetricus the Senator, who being lieuetenaunt Tetricus choſen emperour ouer y• part of Fraūce, which is called Aquitany or Guion, was in his abſence by the whole conſent of his ſoldiors choſen Emperor, and at Burdeux he toke eſtate vppon hym. He ouerſtode ſondry tumultes of the ſouldioures. But whileſt that thoſe thinges toke this ſucceſſe in Fraūce, the Perſians were vanquiſhte in the Eaſt partes by Odenatꝰ. Syria was The Perſians vāquiſht defended againſte ſuche as inuaded it, and Meſopotamia was againe recouered. Odenatꝰ proceded forward, vntil he came to Cteſiphōtes a town in Parthia. Then when Galienus had reſigned and geuen vp the gouernemente of the weale publique, the Romaine Empire was adminyſtred by two at ones. The Eaſt partes

by Odenatus, and the Weſt partes The romayn Empyre gouerned by .ii. at ones. by Poſthumius.
            In this meane ſpace, Galienus &amp; Valerianus were ſlaine at Millaine, in the ninthe yere of their raign, and Claudius ſucceaded after them, who was choſen by the ſouldiors, and by 32. Claudius the 23. Emperoure, began his raign in the yeare of our Lord. 271 a very worthi man, he recouered agayne things which were gone to decay duryng the raygnes of Valeriauꝰ and Galienus the Senate created Auguſtus. He ouercame in ſharpe warres ye Gothes, he wan Illiria, and diſcomfited &amp; put to flight ſuche as deſpoiled Macedonie. He was a very ſparing man, and a ſober. A maintainer of iuſtice, and ſuche one, as was fyt to gouernea weale publique. Within .ii. yeres after that he began firſt his raigne, he ſickned and died, and was canoniſed. The Senate attributed greate honours vnto him. For why, they cauſed to be hanged vp, a golden Target or ſhielde in the Councel houſe: and in the Capitoll, a golden Image to be created for a perpetuall memory of him.
            
               
Next after Quintiliꝰ brother to that ſame Claudius, was by the whole conſent of the ſouldiours nominated Quintilius nominated emperour. Emperor, a man of ſinguler ſobriety &amp; gentlenes, worthy to be compared with his brother, or rather to be preferd before him. By the aſſent of the Senate, he was made Auguſtꝰ, and Quintilius ſlayne. was ſlain within .xvii. dais after that he began his raign. Then Aurelianꝰ accepted the gouernment of the Empire. 33. Aurelianus the. 33. emperour preferred to that dignity by Claudius, begā his raigne in the yeare of oure Lorde. 213, he was the tenth emperor that deltexttemely with Chriſtians. He was borne at Dacia Ripenſis, (which is now called Denmark.) He was a ſtout man in warre, howe be it his minde was enclined to vnmeſurable crueltye. He ſubdued alſo manfully the Gothes. He reſtored ye Romain Empire to the wonted and auncient precinctes, after longe and vncertain fortune of battail. He vanquiſhed Tetricus at Catalaunos in Fraunce, where Tetricus betrayed Tetricꝰ vanquiſhed and depoſed .l. hys owne army vnto him, for that he could not endure the dayly ſedytions

and diſcenſions whyche ſpronge amonge hys ſouldioures. Whervpon he requeſted Aurelius by letters ſeacreatly, that he woulde rid him from thoſe calamities. In hys ſayd letters he vſed this vearſe of Virgil. eripe me his muicte malis (which is). Deliuer me forth of theſe miſeries thou victoryous, and inuincible conqueroure. He toke Zenobia priſnoner in an exceading greate battaile, almoſt faſte by Antioche, when he had firſt ſlain her huſbande Odenatus: who had nowe got all the Eaſt partes vnder his dominion. Odenatus ſlayne. And when he cam to Rome, he triumphed worthilye, as he, who had againe recouered both the Eaſte and Weſt partes of the Empyre. Aurelianus triumphed at Rome. There went before his charyot in y• triumphe, Tetricus, and Zenobia. But Tetricus was afterward deputed to haue the refourminge and redreſſyng of Lucania, and lyued as a priuate perſon there, of longe tyme.

And Zenobia atter her deceaſe, lef
                  •
                her poſteritye at Rome, whiche deo as yet to this daye remayne there. Duringe the raigne of Aurelianus, the coyners of money rebelled wyth Coyners rebelled in Rome. in the city of Rome. They depraued the coyne, and ſlewe one Foeliciſſinnus Rationalis. But Aurelianus when he had ones ſubdued them, he kept them vnder with great extremitye of puniſhment. Diuers of theyr Principals, he put to deathe. He demeaned hymſelfe wyth great cruelty, and as a bloud thyrſter. Manye reuerenced hym more for the dignitye and roume whyche he ſupplied, then for anye zeale or loue that they bare to hym. Hee practiſed alwayes horrible rigoure. In ſo muche that he
                  •
                ſlue his owne ſiſters ſonnes. How be it he endeuored by all meanes to refourme martial policy, and to reduce and frame to good order the diſſolute and corrupted conditions of the people.

He enuironed the City of Rome Rome walles new made. with ſtronger walles. He founded a temple there, whiche he dedicated to the Sunne. Vpon which he beſtowed The temple of the Sunne founded at Rome. an infinite deale of golde and pretyous ſtones. He ſurrendred and gaue vp the keping of the prouince of Dacia: Dacia yelded vp. whiche Traianus founded vpon the farther ſide of the riuer Danubius, and deſpoyled al Illiria, and Moeſta for that he ſtode in doubt how he ſhould be able to defend the ſame any longer.
            And conueying all the Romaines 
                  ••
               et
                  •
                of the Cities and Countries of Dacia, he planted them in the myddeſt of Moeſia, which is new ſituate lying on the right ſide of Danubius, where the lea hath hys courſe, which before lay more on the lefte ſide. Hee was ſlain through the treaſon of hys Aurelianus ſlayne. own ſeruants, who falſly &amp; traiterouſly counterfaiting themperors hand, made in a rol y• names of ſōdry men,

(which in dede were ſuche as themperdure fanſied, and was very much affectioned vnto) affirminge to them that the Emperor had decreed theyr deathes. Whervpon they thinkynge to preuent that pretence of the Emperoure, ſlewe him in the myddeſt of his iourney vppon the cauſye waye, whiche was betwene Conſtantinople and Heraciea. The place was called Cenophrurium. Howe be it, hys death was not vnreuenged. He was canonized, he raigned by the ſpace of v. yeres and .vi. monethes. Aurelianus hys raygne.
            
            Next after him, Tacitus obtayned thempire, a man of excedinge good 34. Tacitus the 34. emperour began hys raigne in the yeare of oure Lord. 279. conditions, and ſuche one as was mete to gouerne o weale publyque. Neuertheleſſe he could not ſhewe anye document of his worthineſſe, for that wythin vi. monethes after the commencement of his Empyre, hes T
                     •
                  acitus deceaſed. was preusnted by death.
            Then Florianus, who ſucceaded 35.
               
Tacitus, adminiſtred the Empire by 35. Florianꝰ the 35. Emperor, begā his Empire in the 279 yere after Chriſtes Incarnation. the ſpace of two monethes and .xx. dais: who in like maner did nothing which was worthy of memory. After him, Probus a man ſingulerlye expert in warfare, became Emperour. He recouered Fraunce, whyche the Barbarians had won before. He vanquiſhed 36. Probus the 36. Emperoure, began his raign in the yeare of our Lord. 279 in ſondry ſkirmiſhes, diuers which attempted to vſurp the eſtate imperial: as Saturninus in the Eaſt partes, and Proculus, and Bonoſus at Agrippina. He licenſed the french Fraunce reconered. men and the Hungarians to haue vineyardes. Hee cauſed the hyll Almus adioyning to the city Sirmium, and the hil Aureꝰ in Meſia the higher, Uineyardes permiited in Fraunce and Hungary. to be planted with vines by the handes of his ſouldioures, and after gaue them to men of the ſame Prouinces, to be tilled and huſbanded. After that he had waged innumerable battailes, and had at the laſt purchaſed peace: and that all the countreſs

round about were nowe quyet, he ſaid that within ſhort ſpace, ſouldioures ſhoulde not be requiſite ne nedeful. He was a very erneſt, ſtout, and a iuſte manne, and ſuche one as was hable to matche Aurelianus hys predeceſſour for renowne atcheued by cheualrye, and as for ciuility and curteous behauioure, he excelled hym farre. He was ſlayn at Sirmium Probus ſlain in an vproure (whyche grew among the ſouldioures) in an Iron tower, when he had raigned .vi. yeares and Probus hys raygne. iii. monthes.
            After him Carus was created Auguſtus, who was borne at Narbona 37. Carus the. 37. Emperour beganne his raign the 286. yeare of oure Lorde. in Fraunce. He immediatlye vppon his ſaide creation made Carinus and Numerianus his ſonnes, Ceſares: and with theym hee raigned by the ſpace of two yeares. But when hee tooke battayle in hande agaynſte the Carinus and Numerianꝰ Ceſars. Sarmatians (hauyng vnderſtanding of the inſurrection of the Perſians,)

he chaunged his vyage into the Eaſt The Perſiās ſubdued. partes, where hee atcheued thynges manfully againſt the Perſians, &amp; ſubdued them in battail. He wan Seleucia Seleucia and Cteſiphontes won. the chiefeſt city of Siria, and Cteſiphontes a towne in Perſia, and being in his tentes whiche wer pitched faſt vppon Tigris, he was ſtrycken Carus ſlayne with lightnīg wyth lightnyng from heauen, and ſo died: Numerianus alſo hys Sonne, (whome he toke to that battail with hym, whyche he waged agaynſt the Perſians,) beinge a yonge man of a wonderfull towardneſſe, for that he was payned with a griefe in hys eyes ſo that he coulde not ride, was caried in an horſe liter thronghe the perſwaſion of Aper hys Father in Numerianus ſlayne. lawe, by whoſe treaſon he was there ſlayne: and his deathe concelde vntil that Aper mighte haue oportunitye to gette the Empire. But throughe the ſtenche of his carkaſſe, his death was bewrayed.
            
               
For why, the ſouldioures whych folowed the horſe liter wherin he was caried, beyng anoyed with the ſmel, plucking of the coueringes from the bed, foūd him dead, and within ſhort while after vnderſtode how he was ſlaine. In this meane while, Carinꝰ whō Carꝰ his father (when he made his expedition againſt ye Perſiās) had deputed Ceſar ouer Illiria, Fraunce and Italy, gaue him ſelfe ouer to all kinde of miſchief. He put diuers innocents to death for verye ſmall crimes. He forſed and defloured dyuers noble mennes wiues, and harmed oft times ſuch his ſchole felowes as reproued him gently, and wyth faire woordes for certaine miſdemenures which he vſed in thauditory or place wher they hard theyr lectures, throughe which occaſious, he grewe to be hated of all men, and not long after, ſuffred condigne puniſhmentes for thoſe his factes. For when the army

was retourned forth of Perſia, after theſe diſcomfitures (that is to ſaye,) when they had loſt Carus Auguſtus by lightning, and Numerianus Ceſar by treaſon, they created Diocleſianus 38. Diocleſianus the. 38. Emperour beganne his raign the 288. yeare of oure Lorde, a man for policy and ciuill gouernment, he was an exceding ſore perſecutor of chriſtians, in hys raigne there were ſlayne within .xxx. dayes ſpace to the number of 17000. chriſtians. Emperoure, Who was borne at Dalmatia. He was deſcended of a very baſe ſtocke: for diuers adiudged that he was a ſcriueners ſonne: Others there were that thoughte hym to be bondman to Anulinus the Senator, and by him made free: he toke an othe in the open aſſemblye of the ſouldioures, that Numerianus was not ſlain by any his treaſon: and ther with all, in the preſence of all the ſouldiours, drawing forth his ſword he ran Aper through, who ſtode faſt by him, which was father in lawe to Numerianus, and had ſlaine him. After that, he ouercame Carinꝰ, who yet liued, being hated and deſpited of all men, whome his own army, whiche was of great power &amp; ſtrength,

betrayed, forſakynge hym betweene the two hils Viminatius and Aureus, when Carinus had on this ſorte obtained the Romalne Empyre, the peiſauntes of Fraunce began a commotion, and called that their conſpiracye Bagande. They choſe Amandus, and one other called Elianus to A commotion of the peſants of Fraunce. be theyr captaines. Againſte theym, was ſente Maximianus Herculius, then Ceſar: who in eaſye battailes vanquiſhed the ſayde peyſaunts, and repreſſed and quieted agayne that parte of Fraunce. After this, Carauſius alſo (who thoughe hee was deſcended Fraunce pacified. of a very baſe parentage, and yet had attained vnto great renoum, for that he demeaned hym ſelf manfullye in warres,) tooke vppon him at Bononia to bring in quiet and to appaiſe the ſea alonge the coaſte of Brittaine, and that part of Fraunce, called Gallia Belgica, which as thē the Frenchmen and Saxones did anoye.

This Carauſius when hee had oft times apprehended ſondrye Barbarians, of whome he neither reſerued the ſpoyl whole, nor yet was accoumptable for it, to thoſe whyche had the ouer ſighte of the prouinces, ne to the Emperoures them ſelues for that time being: it grew to be ſuſpected, that of ſet purpoſe, he permitted the Barbarians to haue recourſe that waye,) to the ende that as they paſſed by fraighted, he mighte borde and rifell them, and by that meanes enriche hym ſelfe. For whych cauſe, Maximtanus commaunded that hee ſhoulde be putte to deathe. But hee hauynge vnderſtandinge ther of, fled Britayne detayned by Carauſius. into Brittaine and kepte it by fōrce. Thus when as through the world al places were in an vprour, Carauſius The romayn Empyre throughout diſturbed. rebeld in Britain, Achilleꝰ in Egipt, ye Quinque gentiās moleſted Africk, &amp; Narſeꝰ waged battel againſt thEaſt parts, Diocleſianꝰ made Maximianꝰ Hercuculiꝰ

Auguſtus alſo, who before was but Ceſar. And Cōſtantius, and one other Maximinꝰ, he created Ceſars. Maximianus Herculius made Auguſtus, and aſſociated felow to Diocleſian in thempyre. This Conſtantius was thoughte to be Claudius his daughters ſonne. And Maximianus Galeriꝰ was born in Dacia not farre from Sardica. To the ende therfore that he might knyt thoſe two in alliaunce, he cauſed Cō
               ſtantius to eſpouſe Theodora daughter in law to Herculius: vpon whom he begate .vi. children whyche were brothers to Conſtantinus. Galerins tooke to wife Valeria doughter to Diocleſianus. They were inforced bothe, to deuorſe their wiues which they had before. Battayle was then attempted againſt Carauſius. A mā 
               Battayle againſt Carauſius. of ſinguler experience in matters of warfare, but they tooke no good effecte. Where vppon peace was concluded betwene them. And thē in Peace concluded with Carauſius. the .vii. yeare after, Carauſius was ſlaine by Alectus his companion, Carauſius ſlayne.
               
Who then kepte Brittayne himſelf Alectus detained Bretain. by the ſpace of three yeares, and was ſubdued afterwarde by Aſclepiodoiꝰ captaine of the gard. Thus was Britaine recouered within .x. yeres after Britaine recouered. that Carauſius ūrſt tooke it. Aboute the ſame time, a battail was fought by Conſtantius Ceſar in Fraunce, Warre in Fraunce. neare about the Langrecians: &amp; that time he experimented bothe aduerſe and proſperous fortune. For when the Barbarians aſſailed hym verye haſtelye, hee was enforced to retyre backe againe to the City, where hee was ſo hardly beſtead, that (ye gates of the city beinge ſhut) he was fayne to be drawen vp the wal with ropes. And within leſſe then .v. hours ſpace A great ouer throw of the Almaynes. after when he had aſſēbled his army together, he iſſued forth againſt thē, and ſlue almoſt .lx. M. Almaines. By this time, had Maximinus Auguſtus in lyke manner finiſhed his warres in Affricke, where he ſubdewed the

Quinquegentianes, and made peac
                  •
                
               Peace concluded with the Quinquegentians. with them. About .viii. monethes after, Diocleſianus ouercame Achilleꝰ of Alexandria and ſlewe him, and demeaned the victory which he had go
                  •
                
               Achilleus ſiayne. very cruelly. For why, he poluted all Egipt with great ſlaughter of men, and baniſhed a great nōber beſides. Neuertheleſſe he eſtabliſhed dyuers thinges verye circumſpectlye there: which continue yet to theſe our dais. Valerius Maximianus experimēted at the firſt vnlucky fortune, and ſone after, he had very good ſucceſſe: For when he ioyned battail, and foughte rather vnaduiſedly then cowardlye at Callinicum and the citye Carre geuinge the onſet with a very fewe vppon an exceadyng populous army of his ennemies, he was diſcomfited there, and enforced to retire. Where vppon he retourned backe forthwyth to Diocleſianus for aide, whome hee met by chaunce in the mid waye as

he came. And Diocleſiane (as it was ſayd) welcomed him after ſuch wanton and effeminate fation, that (being then clad in his magiſtrates robes,) he a lighted and ran on foote by Maximianus his chariot, as he rode. But ſo ſone as Maximianus had aſſembled an army forth of Illiria and Moeſia, he pitched a field and fought again with Narſeus, graūdfather to Ormiſda and Sapores in Armenia ye greater with paſſynge good fortune: and no leſſe circumſpectnes and valiaunt courage for taking with hym two horſmen forthe of hys garryſon, he kepte the ſkoute watche hym ſelf. When he hadde vanquiſhed Narſeus, and putte hym to flyght, he ſackt hys tentes. He tooke his wyues, hys ſyſters, and his children priſonners. And a greate parte of the Nobilitye Thr Perſiā put to a great foyle. of the Perſians, tooke he priſonners there.
            
               
He get moreouer great plenty of the Perſians treaſoure, and forſt ye king to flee to the vttermoſt deſert places of his Empire. Thus returning with great ioy he was again receiued very honorably by Diocleſiane, who taried him in Meſopotamia with ayde there, redy if nede hadde bene. After that they bothe together, and eache of them alone, waged ſondrye battailes. They ſubdued the Carpianes and the Baſternes, and conquered ye Sarmatians. From amonge whiche nations, they brought a great noumber of ſuch as they had taken priſonners, and placed them in the borders of the Romaine Empire. Diocleſianus ordered his doinges verye cyrcumſpectly, as one that was of a very ſharpe wit, and ſuche one as could The cloſe workynge of Diocleſiane. make other menne inſtrumentes to wreke his ſeueritye and rigoure by. He was a very diligent
                  •
                
               
                  •
               nd a wyſe Prince. He induced into the Romain

Empyre ſome vſages whiche were acuſtomed and put in practiſe, rather duringe the bondage of the kynges, then agreable wyth the libertye of the Romains. He commaunded men to worſhip him, where as before hys time, the vſage was only to ſalute ye Emperoure. He garniſhed his apparel and ſhoes, with precious ſtones, Diocleſianus geuen ſomewhat to pride where before his raigne, the habite imperiall conſiſted but in a purple cloke. The reſidue of the Emperors apparaile, was better then the other peoples of Rome. But Herculiꝰ dyd outwardly demeane hymſelfe wyth great cruelty, declaringe the ſame al ſo openly, by the terror of his countenaunce, he applyed hym ſelf wholly to followe the appetite of Diocleſianus, whoſe minde hee accomplyſhed in all crueltye. But when Diocleſianus apperceiued that hee waxed vnweldye to gouerne the Empyre, for that he now grew in age, hee began

to perſwade with Herculiꝰ that they Diocleſianus perſ
                     •
                   ad
                     •
                  d with Herculius to reſigne the ſtate imperyall. both ſhould become priuate perſons againe, and reſigne the gouernment of the weal publique, to ſuch as wer both yonger and luſtier men, to whiche aduiſe of his, with muche a doo Herculius would aſſent. But yet neuertheleſſe at length, eyther of them bothe vpon one daye chaunged theyr eſtate imperiall, and reſumed agayn Herculiꝰ and Diocleſianus became priuate men agayne. the apparel of priuate perſons, Diocleſiane at Nicomedia, and Herculius at Millaine, ſo ſone as they had ſiniſhed the noble triumphes which they kept at Rome with great pomp and ſolemnity of pageants: In whiche the concubines, the ſiſters, &amp; the children of Narſeus were led before their chariots. When this tryumphe was finiſhed, the one of them wente to the city of Salona: and thother into Lucania. Diocleſian paſſed forthe his life worthelye in quiet, as a pryuate man in a towne not far diſtante

from Salona, demeaning hym ſelfe vertuouſlye there. He was the onlye firſte whyche fithe the foundatyon of the Romaine Empire, was willyng to reuerte againe from ſo hyghe degree, to a priuate eſtate and condityon of lyfe. For whyche cauſe, there was graunted to him, that whyche neuer ſithe anye man coulde euer remember did chaunce to anye other: which was, that though he deceaſed Diocleſianus canoniſed after his deceſe. thoughe he was apriuate man. a priuate perſone, yet he was canoniſed, that notwythſtanding.
         
         
            
            ¶ The tenthe booke of the Breuiary of Eutropius.
            
               WHen they hadd 39. Conſtantius the 39. emperour, beganne hys raigne with Galerius in the year of oure Lorde 308. thus finiſhedde theyr bearynge rule, ther were choſen Emperours, Conſtantius and Galeriꝰ: and to them was committed the gouermente of the weale publique, and the Romaine Empyre was deuided betwene them: So that Conſtā
               tius ſhould poſſeſſe Fraunce, Italy &amp; Affricke. Galerius ſhould haue Illiria, Aſia, and the Eaſt parts. whiche done, they ſubſtituted vnder them .ii. Ceſars. But Conſtantius holdynge hym ſelfe content with the dignitye of Auguſtus, refuſed to ſuſtaine the trouble whyche he ſhoulde haue endured through the adminiſtration of

the affaires of Italye and Affricke, wherein he declared his worthines &amp; paſſing great modeſty. He ſoughte by all meanes howe he might enrich Worthy ſtudies of a Prince. the popular people of thempyre, and ſuch as inhabited the Prouinces. He did not much affect the augmentyng or increſing of the common treaſour, ſuppoſinge it farre better and more profitable, that the welth of ye whole Empyre ſhoulde be poſſeſſed and remaine among priuate perſonnes, rather then the wealth of priuate men to be included and ſhutte vp, in one place together. Hee was hymſelfe ſo ſklenderly ſtored of things neceſſary for houſhold, that if it chaunced hym to feaſt any nomber of his frends, he was enforced to borow plate abrode here and there, to furniſh hys tables wythall. He was not onlye beloued, but hadde in great reuerence alſo amonge the frenchmen, for yt through his ſaid accepting of the empire, they

had now eſhaped the ſuſpected wittines of Diocleſiane, and the bloudye haſtineſſe and cruelty of Maximianꝰ. He deceaſed at Yorke in Brittain, in the .xiii. yere of his raign, and was canoniſed. Conſtantius deceaſed at York in England. Galerius who was endued with very good qualities, and was of greate proweſſe in martiall pollicye beſides, (when hee vnderſtode that through the permiſſion of Conſtantius, Italye was alſo annered to hys Empire,) he created two Ceſars: but when Conſtantius was deceaſed, his Two Ceſers created vnder Galerius. ſonne Conſtantius being baſe born, was created Emperor in Brittain, &amp; 40. Conſtantinꝰ the. 40. Emperor began his raign in the yereof our Lord 310. He was the firſt Emperor that profeſſed the name of chriſt he eſtabliſhed the goſpell in his Empire. Maxentius, Herculiꝰ hys ſonne nominted Auguſtaꝰ became gouernour of that country in his fathers roume, (which thing al ye people laboured earneſtly to haue it ſo.) In this mean ſpace, the gard began a commotion at Rome, where they nominated Maxentius ſonne to Herculius Auguſtus, which Herculiꝰ dwelt not far from the city of Rome, nigh to the high waye as men goo to

Rome wardes. At whiche tidinges, Maximianus Herculius conceyued a good hope that he might again recouer ye eſtate which to fore by perſwaſion Herculius cam againe to Rome. of Diocleſian, &amp; far againſte hys own wil he had forgon and reſigned. Whervpon, with great ſpede he haſted to Rome wards, forthe of Lucania. Which place he had before choſē (being a moſt pleſant ſoyl to remain in,) where he had alſo ſpent a greate Herculius perſwaded Diocleſian to reſume the ſtate unperial part of his time, after yt he had reſigned firſt his Empire. Thē Maximianꝰ ſo ſone as he was come to Rome, he begā to perſwade with Diocleſian bi letters, yt he ſhuld likewiſe reſume his former eſtate: which thīg he neglected to do. Thē was Seuerꝰ Ceſar ſēt to Rome with an army to repreſſe Seuerus ſent agaynſte the garde. &amp; aſſwage the commotion which the gard had made. But as he laide ſiege to the city, his own ſouldiors forſoke him, by meane wherof ſtrength and power accrued &amp; grewe to Maxentiꝰ. Seuerus ſlayne.
               
Seuerus (as he wold haue fled thēs) was ſlaine at Rauenna. After that, Herculius Maximianus in an aſſemble of the ſouldiors, made ſemblance as if he would haue depoſed his ſōne Maxentius: for which his ſaid enterpriſe, hee ſuſtained reproche and rebuke of the ſouldiours. From thence he departed to Fraunce, fayning that hee was expulſed by his ſonne, and A cruell pretens of Herculius. forced to flye: (thinking by this meanes) he ſhoulde get to be receiued of his ſonne in law Conſtantinus: whō he minded to ſlaye, if he mighte finde time and oportunitye conueniente: which Conſtantinus at that preſēt, raigned in Fraunce with greate fauoure and loue, bothe of his ſouldyours and other the inhabitauntes of thoſe prouinces. And when hee had ſlain the French men and Almains, and taken their kinges priſonners, (aſſembling a great companye to behold A cruell facte of Herculius. the ſight) he ſet them forth to be

deuoured of wilde beaſtes. But hys doughter diſcloſed to her huſbande Conſtantinus, the wicked enterpryces of her father &amp; reueled vnto him, what treaſon her father had pretended againſte him. Whiche thinge ſo ſone as Maximianus vnderſtode, hee fled to Maſſilia, (thinckinge to haue paſſed ouer from thence, to his ſonne Maxentius againe,) and was there Herculius ſlayne. ſlaine: ſuffring condign puniſhment for thoſe his demerits: one who was euermore prone to all rigor and cruelty. A man without faith, very pernitious and hurtfull to all men, and void of all ciuility and courteſy.
            Aboute the ſame time, Licinius was created Emperoure by Galerius. Licinius created Emperor. He was borne at Dacia, and paſſinge wel knowen of Galerius, for yt he had of long time bene of familyer acquaintaunce with him. He eſtemed him greatly for the earneſt trauaile and payns which he ſuſtained in the

battail yt he waged againſt Narceus, &amp; for other ſeruiceableneſſe &amp; good endeuor, which he apperceiued to be in him. This don, ſhortly after, Galeriꝰ deceaſſed. Then was the Empire adminiſtred Galerius deceaſed. by .iiii. at ones. By Conſtā
               tinus and Marentius, whoſe fathers Four Emperours at once in Rome. had ben Emperors before, and Licinius &amp; Maximinꝰ which were newly created Emperors. But Conſtantinꝰ in the .v. yere of his raign, attempted a ciuil battail againſt Marentius. He diſcomfited his armies in ſondry ſkirmiſhes. A ciuil battel by Conſtantinus. And at laſt, vanquiſhed hym at Miluius bridge, and ſo got al Italy vnder his obeiſaunce. Maxentius vanquiſht.
            
            At this time, Maxentius exerciſed great tiranny vpon diuers the peres of his Empire. Not longe after that, Maximinus attempted warresin the War pretended by Maximinus agaīſt Licinius. Eaſt partes alſo againſt Licinius.
            But when he apperceiued yt he was like to be diſcōſited, he preuented the miſchiefs imminent, by dying ſodēly Maximianus deceaſſed.
               
at Tarſus. Thē Cōſtantiꝰ being one of a hauty ſtomak &amp; corage, affecting to accōpliſh &amp; bring to paſſe ſuch thinges as he had once cōceiued in his fā
               taſy, coueting to become Emperor ouer ye whole world, made war vpon This warre was againſte Licinius by Conſtantius for religions ſake chefelye. Licinius, although he was his frēd. For this Liciniꝰ had eſpouſed his ſiſter Conſtantia. He vanquiſhed hym firſt in Hungary: the ſecōd time he ouercame him at Cybale: wheras Liciniꝰ In the tyme oſ Conſtātius Scotlande receyued the ſayth. began to renue battel with great preparation. whē he had thus got all Dardania, Meſia &amp; Macedonie, he wā
               diuers other prouinces beſides. After that, there were ſondry battailes waged betweene them, and peace concluded, and broken agayne. At laſte, Lycinius was cōquered at Nicomedia Licinius conquered. a famous city of Bithinia, in battayle bothe by Sea and lande. Hée yelded himſelf: and yet contrary to ye integritye of the othe and promyſe made betwene them, he was ſlayne. Licinius ſlayne.
               
At that time, (which neuer earſt hapned) was the Romaine Empire ſubiect One Emperor and .iii. Ceſars at Rome. to one Emperor and .iii. Ceſars. At this time, Conſtantinus his children had the gouernment of Fraūce, the Eaſt partes, and of Italye. But this vnketheneſſe of paſſinge greate good fortune &amp; ſucceſſe in his affairs, did ſomewhat chaunge and aultare Conſtantinus from that his wonted gentle &amp; flexible minde. In ſo muche that he perſecuted his owne bloude, and thoſe whiche were of his allyaunce. He ſlewe his own ſiſters ſon, a notable yong mā and very towardly. Eftſones he put his wife to death and after that, ſondry of hys frendes alſo. In the firſte beginninge of hys raign, he was worthy to haue beene compared with the beſt and chiefeſt princes of the Romaines that euer were: and at the end therof, to be reſembled to ſuche as were of the meaner ſort. He was endewed with ſondry

and thoſe excellent vertues. Hee was very muche geuen to purchaſe praiſe and fame by feates of cheualry. He had exceding good chaunce in battaile, and yet not ſo good chaunce but that his induſtry and endeuoure excelled it farre. Hee vanquiſhed and put to flight at ſondry times the Gothes. After that he had repreſſed the ciuil warres, he vanquiſhed the Gothes in diuers places, and graunted them peace at laſte: and wan greate memory of praiſe and worſhip amōg the Barbarians. He was paſſing deſirous to attaine learning, and applied him ſelfe wholly to the ſtudye of the liberall artes. He endeuoured to gaine the loue of the people, through his well deſeruinges, ſeking ye ſame by his great liberality, and facillity. Who like as he ſemed to ſome of his frendes vnſtedfaſte and ſuſpected, ſo was he to the reſidue of them paſſing frendly and aſſured: ſuffring no way

ne mean eſkape, by which he could imagin how to enrich &amp; aduaūce thē. He enacted &amp; eſtabliſhed ſōdry laws. Some groūded vpō equity &amp; iuſtice: diuers ſuperfluous &amp; to no purpoſe, &amp; many repleniſhed with ſeuerity &amp; rigor. The city which he built, he ertolled to ſo great port and eſtate, that he made it able to cōpare (ī maner) with the citye of Rome it ſelfe. And as he made preparation for battail againſt the Parthians, he died at Nicomedia Conſtantius 
                     •
                  eceaſſed. in thopen town ther, in the .xxxi. yere of his raign, when he had liued .lxvi. yeres. His death was prognoſticated by a Comet or blaſing ſtarre, whych was ſene by a certain ſpace being of Conſtantius hys deathe prognoſiicate▪
                a greate bigneſſe, (whiche ſtarre the Grecians cal 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . After his deth he was canoniſed. He lefte behinde him .iii. ſonnes of his own, that is to wit Conſtantinus, Conſtans &amp; Cō
               ſtantiꝰ to ſuccede him in his Empire, &amp; one other which was hys brothers

ſonne. But Dalmatius Ceſar which was his brothers ſonne, a yong man of a meruelous towardnes was ſlain Dalmatius Ceſar ſlayne. in an vprour whiche fel amonge the ſouldioures, (his coſen Conſtantius 41. Conſtantinꝰ the. 41. Emperor began his raigne in the yeare of oure Lorde 340, and with him his father Conſtantinus Magnus had apointed by his laſt will, that hys two brothers Conſtans &amp; Conſtantinꝰ ſhould perticipate and haue theyr portyon of thempyre. permittig only, rather thē procuring his deathe.) Not longe after, when Conſtantinꝰ attempted war againſt his brother at Aquileia, and demened hym ſelfe vnaduiſedly there in, he was ſlayne. Then was the Empyre of the Romaynes reduced vnder the gouernemente of two onlye. The raign of Conſtās endured for a time valiant, which he adminiſtred wyth great iuſtice. Sone after, when he began to fail of his health, he aſſociated vnto him in ſtede of frends euil diſpoſed perſōs to aſſiſt him about th Empire, through whoſe euil counſailes, Conſtantinꝰ ſlayne. he declined into horrible vices. By meane wherof, waring ſkante tollerable of thinhabitāts of ye prouinces &amp; nothing regarded of his ſouldiors,

hee was ſlaine at Magnenſium in a Conſtans ſlayne. commotion there, in a caſtell called Helena caſtel not farre from Spain, in the .xvii. yere of his raigne, when he had liued .xxx. yeares. In his life time, he had atchieued diuers things very proſperouſlye, and duringe hys whole raigne, he vſed no greate cruelty towardes his ſouldioures. But Conſtantius experimented very vncertaine and variable fortune in hys battayles. For why, he ſuſtained dyuers, and thoſe greate damages by the Perſians. They ofte times wan his townes, beſieged his Cities, and ſlewe his armies: to be briefe, he neuer waged any battaile againſt Sapores, in whych he had good ſucceſſe but only one which he fought at Singara, where he loſt that victory alſo, whiche vndoubtedly he myght haue gotten, had it not bene for the outragious fierceneſſe and ouer haſty courage of his ſouldioures: whiche vnaduiſedly

without any regard, cōtrary to all order of warfare, would nedes ioyne the battail, when as nowe the day was cleane ſpente. After the death of Conſtans, whē as now Magnentius poſſeſſed Italy, Affricke, &amp; Fraunce, new matters begā to grow in Illiria, where the ſouldiors by the whole conſent, choſe Veteranio to gouerne the Empire, being now verye Veteranio choſen prynce by the ſouldioures. aged, but yet well be loued of all men, for the good ſucceſſe whiche he hadde of long time experimented in martiall affaires. There was aſſygned vnto him, the gouernment of Illiria. This Veteranio was both witty, and a very good man. In condityons, much refembling toe auncyent Emperours of Rome, and one which was greatly enclined to the auncient vſage of the Emperors, and paſſing tractable hym ſelf. How be it he was nothing at all learued. In ſo muche, that he knewe not the Alphabete or

croſcow, but as he lerned it in his extreme age after ye he was created emperor. This Veteranio was depoſed Veteranio depoſed. frō thempire, by Conſtantiꝰ, who to reuenge ye deth of his brother, begā a ciuil battail, and Veteranio after an vnkethe &amp; ſtraunge ſort (was by the conſent and agrement of ye ſoldiors, enforced to relinquiſhe and reſigne his eſtate imperial. At the ſame time was there a commotion at Rome: at Nepotianus got thempire. which time Nepotianus, Conſtantinus hys ſiſters ſonne, inuaded thempire, being aided by a bande of them whiche vſe to playe at the weapons (called gladiatores.) But accordyng to hys cruell beginninges, ſo had he an ende correſpondente. For in the xxviii. day after his ſaide enterpryſe, he was ſlain by the captains of Magnenſius: Nepotianus ſlayne. and ſo ſuffred puniſhmēt fit for his demerites. His hed was ſmitten of, &amp; ſet on theud of a tauelin, and ſo caried about the city. There were

great baniſhments, and merueylous great ſlaughters of noble men thē cō
               mitted. Within a while after, Magnenſius was alſo diſcōfited in battel at Murſa: &amp; was well nighe taken. A great nōber of ye Romains wer ſlain Magnenſius ſlayne. in y• battall, which were men able to haue withſtode all forain inuaſiōs of enemies, and ſuch, as the Romains, (through their prowes,) might haue gayned manye tryumphes, and bene in ſafetye and ſecurity agaynſt theyr aduerſaryes. Shortly after, Conſtantius deputed Gallus hys fathers brothers Gallus made Ceſar. ſonne, Ceaſer ouer the Eaſte parts. Magnenſius after that he had bene diſcomfited in ſo many battels, ſlewe hym ſelfe at Louane, when he Magnenſius ſiue hymſelfe. had raygned three yeares and ſeuen monethes. In lyke manner delte hys brother Senonis alſo, whom he had made Ceſar, and ſente to defende Gallus Ceſar ſlayne. Fraunce. Aboute this time, was Gallus Ceſar ſlaine by Conſtantius

after that they had waged diuers ciuil warres together: a man of cruell diſpoſition, and very prone to tirāny, (if he might haue ruled according as himſelf hadde liſted.) Siluanus alſo who attempted other newe matters Siluanus ſlayne. in Fraunce, was within .xxx. dais after ſlain. Then Conſtantius himſelf alone, enioyed the Romain Empire. Conſtantius Emperour alone. Soone after, he appoynted Iulianus his vncles ſonne, and brother to Gallus, Ceſar ouer Fraunce, and ſente him thither, eſpouſing firſt his owne Iulianus made Ceſar. ſiſter vnto him. Now when the Barbarians had won diuers townes, and beſieged other ſome, and that euerye where ther was a pitiful ſpoyl made by them, ſo that the Romain Empire conſiſted in no ſmall haſard and danger, Iulianus ſlue greate armyes of the Almaines at Argentine a city of An ouerthrowe of the Almaynes. Fraunce. Theyr mighty and worthy kinge, was there taken priſonner, Fraunce was againe recouered. Iulianus

was by the conſente of the Iulianus Auguſtus. ſouldiors made Auguſtus: who with in a yere after, made a viage toward Illiria: Conſtantius who was buſied in battail againſt the Parthians, when he hard of this, returned home wardes to pacify that commotion, &amp; died by the waye betwene Cilicia, Conſtantius deceaſſed, his age &amp; raigne. and Cappadocia: in the .xxxviii. yere of his raigne, when he had liued .xlv. yeres, and was adiudged worthye to be canoniſed. He was a very peaſible and quiet man: but ſuch one, as gaue ouer muche creadit and affiaunce to his frendes, and thoſe whiche were his familiers. And folowed to muche his wyues councell. Yet in the fyrſte commencemēt of his Empire, he demeaned himſelf with great ſobriety, endeuoring by all meanes to enrich ſuche as were of his acquaintaunce, and would not ſee them vnpreferred to honoures and promotions, whoſe painful diligence and endeuoure be

hadde ones experimented. How be it wyth greate ſeueritye and crueltye, he puniſhed ſuche as he ones appertained to affect ſoueraintye in ſuche ſorte, that hee woulde ſecke to depriue him of his Empire. Otherwiſe he was very quiet and gentle: whoſe fortune and good chaunce, was more to be commended in ciuill warres, then in thoſe whyche he waged forth of his Empire.
            After that Iulianus was Emperoure, who wyth greate preparation 42. Iulianus the 42. Emperor began his raign in the yere of oure Lord 362. one ſene paſſynge well in the liberall ſciences, but an earneſt aduerſary of chriſtian religyon. made warre vpon the Parthianes, at which viage I my ſelf was preſent, diuers townes and holdes were peaſibly yelded vp, and other ſome won by hym. And when he hadde deſpoyled Aſſiria, hee pytched his tentes, and entrenched them, and ſoiourned there for a ſeaſon. And retournynge from thence a conqueroure, hee was ſlain by his ennemies, as hee preſſed ſom what vnaduiſedlye into the

battailes, in the .vi. of the kalends of Iuly, in ye .vii. yere of his raign, whē he had liued .xxxi. yeres, and was canoniſed. He was a notable man, and ſuche one as would paſſinglye well haue gouerned the weale publique, if deſteny wold haue permitted him to haue liued. He was exceadinglye wel ſene in all the liberal ſciences. He did excell in the Greke tounge, in ſo muche that his knowledge in the Latin tounge was nothing to be cō
               pared with that which he had in the Greke tong. He was very eloquent, and of a very redy &amp; prompt memory. In manye thynges, hee reſembled muche a Philoſopher. He was lyberall to hys frendes, but not all together ſo hedefull aboute hys affayres, as it was ſittinge and fitte for ſoo myghtye a Prince: whyche fault dyuers obiected to hym, whereby hys fame and glorye was ſomedele ſtayned in that behalfe.
            
               
He delt very vprightly with thinhabitauntes of the Prouinces, whyche were vnder the Romaynes. He charged his ſubiectes to pay as few tares and tributes as mighte be. Hee was very ciuil and curtuous to all men. He ſought litle to augment hys own treſure. He was very deſirous to attaine glory and renoum: In ſo much that he did affect it ſometimes wyth out meaſure. He was an exceadinge Iulianus a perſecutor of Chriſtians. great perſecutor of Chriſtian religion, but yet in ſuche ſorte, that he abſtained from ſheding their bloud. He was not muche vnlyke to Marcus Antonius, whom he did alſo earneſtly endeuor him ſelfe to immitate and folowe. Next after him, Iouinianus who as yet had neuer ben trained vp 43. Iouinianus the. 4
                     •
                  z. Emperor 
                     〈◊〉
                   hy
                     •
                   r
                     ••
                  gne in the. 367 y
                     •
                  re of our Lorde he was a veri good prince, a fauourer of ye goſpel, and cō
                  feſſors therof he inſtytuted that tythes ſhuld be payd to churches. in warfare abrode, was by the cōſent of the army, choſen to haue the adminiſtration and the rule ofth Empire: of whome the ſouldioures had better notyce throughe the commendatyon

and good reporte of hys father, then for anye triall and knowledge they hadde of him ſelfe. Thus when the weale publyque of the Romaynes was diſturbed, and the ſouldioures brought to extreme pouertye, ſo that they were deſtitute of al thinges neceſſary, Iouinianus was vanquiſhed in a battail or ii. by the Perſians, and Iouinianus ſuſtayned a ſhameful ouerthrowe. forſt to make a very reprochful peace for graunting wheref, he was forced to them, with a great portion of hys Empire: which thing ſence the fyrſt foūdation of the city of Rome, (whiche was wel nighe a M. C. and. xviit. yere,) neuer erſte happened. In lyke manner alſo, the Romayne Regions were diſcomfited and ſuſtained an ouerthrow by Pontius The leſinus at Eaudium a towne of the Samuites, The Romaines put to great foyles. and in Spaine at Numantia, and at Numidia and ſent vnder yoke. But at that time they departed wyth no part of the Empire to their aduerſaries.

Nor yet that former concluding of peace on that condition, had bene greatly to be miſliked wythal, if that afterwarde, ſo ſoone as he had bene able, he had infringed that league againe, whiche before of neceſſity and force, he was conſtrayned to make: lyke as the Romaynes dyd in all thoſe battailes whiche I haue before recited. For after anye ſuche peace made, they renewed battayle againe forthe wyth againſte the Samnites, the Numantines, and the Numidians, ſo ſoone as the peace was concluded.
            But Iouinianus (dreadynge that he ſhoulde haue beene ſupplanted in the Empire,) helde hym ſelfe ſtyll in the Eaſt partes, geuing in the mean time ſmall hede or regarde to his r
                  •
               
               nowme.
            After that, as he tooke his iourne
                  •
                from thence to warde Illiria, he dye ſodenlye in the borders of Galacia

one who in no other his affairs was eyther ſlouthfull or neglygente, or wanted any wyt. Of ye hys ſo ſodayn deathe, dyuers coniectured diuerſly. Some thoughte that he tooke it by eatynge rawe meate, for in deede he had ſurfited ouer nyght.
            Other ſome ſuppoſed that it proceaded throughe the vnholſome ayre of the chamber, whyche for that that it was newlye pargeted wyth lyme, was verye noyſome to him lyinge there in.
            And other ſome adiudged that it 
                  •
               ame by reaſon of the vnmeaſurable burnynge of charcoles in his chamber, of whyche, for ye it was extreme colde weather, hee wylled there ſhuld be burned great plenty. He de
               
                  •
               eaſed in the .vii. yere of his raigne, 
                  •
               he .xxiiii. of ye Kalends of March, in ye 
               
                  •
               xxiii. yere of his age: &amp; throughe the 
                  〈◊〉
                neuolens of them which ſucceded 
                  •
               im in the Empire, was canoniſed.

He was geuen very muche to ciuility, and was by nature very liberall. Suche was the ſtate of the Romaine Empire, at what time the ſayd Iouinianus, and Verouianus gouerned it (which was) in the M. C. and .xix. yere after the firſt building of the city of Rome. (⸫)
            ¶ Thus endeth the Breuiary of Eutropius.
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London in Fleteſtrete, near to Saynt Dunſtons Churche, by Thomas Marſhe.
            
         
      
   

