
   
      
         
            The stage of popish toyes conteining both tragicall and comicall partes: played by the Romishe roysters of former age: notably describing them by degrees in their colours. Collected out of H. Stephanus in his Apologie vpon Herodot. With a friendlie forewarning to our Catelin Catholikes: and a brief admonition, of the sundrie benefites we receiue by hir Ma: blessed gouernement ouer vs. Compyled by G.N.
            Apologia pro Herodoto. English. Selections
            Estienne, Henri, 1531-1598.
         
         
            
               1581
            
         
         Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00423
            STC 10552
            ESTC S101744
            99837550
            99837550
            1877
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00423)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1877)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 378:23)
         
         
            
               
                  The stage of popish toyes conteining both tragicall and comicall partes: played by the Romishe roysters of former age: notably describing them by degrees in their colours. Collected out of H. Stephanus in his Apologie vpon Herodot. With a friendlie forewarning to our Catelin Catholikes: and a brief admonition, of the sundrie benefites we receiue by hir Ma: blessed gouernement ouer vs. Compyled by G.N.
                  Apologia pro Herodoto. English. Selections
                  Estienne, Henri, 1531-1598.
                  North, George, gentleman.
               
               [6], 65 [i.e. 95], [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Henry Binneman,
                  [London] :
                  Anno Domini. 1581.
               
               
                  G.N. = George North, who signs the dedication.
                  Compiled from: Apologie pour Hérodote.
                  At foot of title: Cum priuilegio.
                  Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: [par.]⁴ A-M⁴ (-[par.]1).
                  P. 95 misnumbered 65.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-08
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-08
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
               
The Stage of Popiſh toyes: Conteining both Tragicall and Comicall partes: played by the Romiſhe royſters of former age: notably deſcribing them by degrees in their colours.
            
               Collected out of H. STEPHANVS in his Apologie vpon HERODOT.
            With a friendlie forewarning to our Catelin Catholikes: and a brief admonition, of the ſundrie benefites we receiue by hir Ma: bleſſed gouernement ouer vs. Compyled by G. N.
            Printed by Henry Binneman. ANNO DOMINI. 1581. Cum Priuilegio.
            
            
               
               
            
         
         
            
            
               TO THE RIGHT HONOrable, Sir Chriſtopher Hattō, Knight, Captaine of hir Maiesties Garde, Vizchamberlaine to hir highneſſe, and of hir Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Counſaile.
            
            
               SAge Sibilla (right honorable) ſaid to Aeneas that no way could be cloſed againste Vertue: affirming that al actions happily ſucceeded whatſoeuer the attēpt be, Virtute duce. And Theodorus Biblian der defineth Vertue to be inuested with diuers titles, according to the diuerſity of hir proper motions, as in diſcerning the deceit of mans traditions, in chooſing the veritie, and in flying falſe Hipocriſie, ſhe is called Prudence: in maintayning Gods glorie, in withstanding the Popes tirannie, and in defending the true felowſhip of Prudence. Christian ſocietie, ſhe is named Fortitude: in ſuppreſſing Idolatrie, in embracing mercie, and in aduauncing the ministers of his heauē
               lie Fortitude. maiestie, ſhe is ſaide to be Iuſtice, in moderating Romiſh furies, and weake affections, in qualifying Popiſh quarrels, and peruerſe cō
               ditions, Iuſtice. &amp; in vſing either to bring both to the true vſe of Gods word, ſhe is tearmed Temperance. A Prince with theſe pillers doth euer preuaile: a tree with theſe brāches, doth euer bloſſom, &amp; a body with Temperāce. theſe members ouercommeth the labours of Hercules. Beſids theſe general graces of Vertue, there are two ſpecial precedents chiefelie to be loked into, the cauſe, and the execution, both which, your honor (whoſe forward fauour to al Christs profeſſors (vnder hir Maiesty) among the rest of right honorable) long ſince conſidered of, performing, confirming, &amp; executing the effect, in ſuch famous ſort as the whole Worlde is amazed and mated at hir Maiesties moſte happie and bleſſed gouernement, whereby you haue hitherto proued in your noble perſon, Sibillas ſayings to be true, that nothing can preuaile againſt this diuine Vertue: which ſome define to be God himſelfe.

And now, ſeing his auntient and oppoſite enimie the Pope, hath foysted in among vs Petifoggers, who (like ſheete stealers, tinckers, or Connyſkin buyers) creepe in corners to vtter their traſh, my fortune being (by a French man) to meet with a packe of their paultry, I preſume in humble ſort to preſent the firſt ſhew therof to your honor, wherin if I play the bad Pedler (ſo your honor pardō me) I force not, for truelie I am not their feed Broker. I haue entituled it The Stage of Popiſh toyes, as a moſt meet tearm for the matter. the ſum &amp; ſubstance wherof I confeſſe to haue collected out of H: Stephanus in his Apologie vpon Herodot, who coateth thē in theyr Couchanele colours: and therfore if any part haue his wrong dye, I muſt yeelde to the fault, and excuſe my Author. But my ſelfe (without vaunt) a martial profeſſor, and continuallie armed to the proofe with a ſeruiſable &amp; dutiful hart to your honor: I hope my errors ſhal paſſe for the eaſier payment, and be the better born with, for that hereby I affirme this auntient Emblem, In vtrumque paratus, and vow my daylie prayer, for the proceeding and encreaſing of that which God at the first placed in you, and is according to the ſaying of Plato, No man to be noble without a heauenly inſpiration.
            
            
               Your Honors moſt bound ſeruaunt in all humble duetie.
GEORGE NORTH.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ The Stage of Popiſh toyes.
            
            
               THe Locretians had a ſpeciall law, worthie to be noted of all good gouerned common wealthes, and chiefely of vs Engliſhmē, in theſe dangerous times, if euery one would looke into his dutie as he ought: For whoſoeuer preſumed to call in queſtion, any thing that paſſed, by the decrée of thoſe, who were authorized by the Prince, to deuiſe, publiſh and eſtabliſh good lawes among them, ſhould be fréely heard, ſo he came collered with a halter about his necke, to the end, that deliuering probable argument to maintaine his preſumption, confounding (in reaſonable iudgement) the ſame he argued on, and approuing his Councell to ſtand more with a common wealth: he was vnarmed of his Hempe, highly commended and preferred, both by Prince and people. But if he were conuicted in his arrogancie, and found more buſie to reproue, than wiſe to maintaine: he was ſtraight truſſed vp according to deſerte, whiles his fault and follie was in memorie.
            
               Socrates gaue leſſe libertie to his Citizens, for he woulde haue no lawe diſputed of openly, not of thoſe that had the authoritie to reforme them: much leſſe that any other (eyther publikely or priuately) ſhoulde dare maintaine argument of them: For he conſidered how lawes are ſcanned, when they come to the diſcuſſing of the common ſort.
            If Englande (whoſe gouernment by Gods great bleſſing, executed in the perſon of our moſt ſacred Soueraigne) had the lawes of Locretia, or the ſharpe preceptes of Socrates, our Papiſtes durſt not (for the rope) contende ſo openly, nor for feare of due iuſtice, preſume ſo boldly (of their errours) as

they doe. But ſuch hath bin hir Maieſties mercie to them all, in pardoning, prolonging, bearing and forbearing, hoping that God woulde conuert them, or dutie reclaime them, couering with equal care to confirme hir louing ſubiects, in one minde, in one obedience, and in one profeſſion, as they (abuſing hir gratious clemencie) wax more indurate, and wilfully runne into all the ylles that may be:
            If they would deſire God to giue them the true knowledge of his worde, and ſtedfaſtly perſeuer in prayer, to be inſtructed by his holy ſpirit: no doubt but his diuine Maieſtie would ſo open the eyes of their reaſon, as they ſhoulde ſée what daunger they dwell in, to the euerlaſting deſtruction of their Soules, and what cunnyng hath kepte them in their errour from the beginning: which true iudgement can no waye bee attayned vnto, vnleſſe wée conſtantly continue in prayer, till we perfectly féele and iuſtly finde (in our ſelues) his heauenly bleſſing confirmed in vs.
            Howe manye in all ages (euen from the firſt creation of man) haue deliuered (in the teſtimonie of their bloud) the moſt abhominable abuſes of that Romiſhe Antichriſt, on whome you ſo much depende? howe manye of all Nations, moſte excellent and learned wryters (by the authoritie of the ſacred Scriptures) haue publiſhed infinite volumes, ſhewing &amp; approuing the moſt ioyfull fruites of the true &amp; perfect profeſſion of Chriſt crucifyed, and howe theſe two doe differ (in all degrées) no true Chriſtian but knoweth, ſo farre as God may excell man, is not to be doubted: But ſo farre as his wickedneſſe may match with ye hatefull ſinne of Lucifer, to the malice of the heauenly Maieſtie, this proude beaſt preſumeth on. Haue the cloudes of errour ſo couered you as you cannot ſée? hath the myſtes of ignoraunce of meſhid you, as you will not vnderſtande? or doeth the furie of Pharao ſo bewitch you as you are become deſperate? wyl not Moyſes moue you, wyll not Gods worde wynne you, nor his threatnings reclaime you, excepte you haue myracles? can nothing but a Pope and his Pardons pleaſe you: your Pilgrimage to Saintes of

both kyndes content you, and a muſter of Maſſes, wyth a worlde of Monkes make you to ſéeme Chriſtians? Haue not wée more good aduertiſementes, more manifeſt ſignes and tokens, more ſharpe rebukes, more gentle warnyngs, and more mylde admonitions than our elders had? Is not vice now better diſcouered, all ſortes of ſinnes reproued, and more liuely (to the quicke) both by worde and writing touched, than euer it was? yet what was colde in them, is froſen in you: where they innocently halted, you are willingly lame: where they were (by ignoraunce) dimme ſighted, you are (by wilfulneſſe) altogither blinded: &amp; where they were harde of hearing, hauing no remedie, you are ſtarke deffe in your ſtubborne obſtinacie. How hateful and dangerous it was in thoſe dayes, to deliuer the truth (vnleſſe they woulde by fire alter into ayre) ſundrie that ſuffered their tormentes teſtifyed. But you that haue the frée ſcope of the Goſpell to entreate on, whereby you are taught the true waye to our onelye Sauiour, whoſe errours may bée eaſed, whoſe doubtes maye bee cleared, and (frée of all feare) may ſéeke, aſke, knocke, bée reſolued and receyued, doe ſtubbornely ſtande on your owne conceites, holding dreames for deuotion, and dwel in a moſte hatefull hope of alteration. By Chriſt you are called, by the Prince commaunded, and by your brethren entreated, to enter into a ſafe vnitie among thē: the Banket is prepared, gods word doth inuite you, &amp; (bringing your wedding garmēts) no gueſts more welcome: let no ſhame withholde you from ſo ſacred a feaſt, grudge not to go, and the holy Ghoſt will guide you. There is more comfort (ſaith Chriſt) in one ſinner truely repenting, thā in many that from their beginning haue continued conſtant. If to yéeld (in worldly cauſes) be wiſedome, profit, and policie, howe much more will it benefite the health of our Soules, to returne (in ſingleneſſe of heart) to his heauenly Maieſtie, if to bende, bée better than to breake, let 
                  ••
                plye and applye, our liuing to his liking, that hath power to bruſe euerye bone, and to conſume vs as chaffe before fire: let not our old Adam
               
(whoſe knobbed and knotted braunches, will rather rende than cleaue) cauſe the whole body to bee caſte into an euerlaſting and vnquenchable flame. It wil then bée too late to ſaye with Diues, ſend to my brethren that they maye knowe the diſtreſſe of the paine and tormentes I am in: you will truely bée aunſweared, they haue the Prophetes and Preachers among them, &amp;c. You can no waye excuſe your ſelues by ignoraunte: for as the Sunne (excelling all other lyghtes) doeth ſhyne both on good and bad: ſo doeth the bright beames of Gods worde (farre ſurpaſſing the Sunne in cleareneſſe) extende an equall comforte (thoughe the vſe bée not equall) as wel vpon the ſinner, as the iuſt liuer.
            Yet as the Ethyopians doe curſe the Sunne for ſcortching them: ſo do the deſperate, that are giuen vp to their owne luſt, hate his heauenly word for rebuking them.
            I haue hearde ſundrye of your coate ſaye, that the looſe lyuing of ſome our Prelates and Preachers, doeth make you the more to miſlike their doctrine: deceiue not your ſelues, it wyll paſſe for no payment: They lyue as fleſhe, into are as men: wee muſte direct our lyues to their ſayings, and not to their doyngs. And it is alſo written, if an Angell come out of Heauen, and denuer you other doctrine, than is contained in the Teſtament of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, reiect him and beléeue him not. More, if they receiue not that you teach in my name, leaue them, &amp; ſhake the du
                  ••
                of their dwelling 
                  Paule to the Gala. 1. 8. 9. from your feete. It ſhall be better (in the generall iudgement) for Sodome and Gomorha then with thoſe.
            Heare wée haue no commaundemente to followe their lyuing, but we are hardly threatned to obey their Preaching, ſo long as they kéepe within the compaſſe of the Goſpell, ſhewing vs of no ſaluation beſides Chriſt crucified, &amp; that none may come to the Father, but by him.
            You will obiect the ſayings of Chriſt in the. 5. of Matthewe Sic luceat lux vestra coram hominibus, vt, &amp;c. Let your light 
               
                  Math. 5. 
               ſo ſhine before men, as they may ſee your good workes; and glorifie your Father that is in heauen. It is a good, and ghoſtly

admonition, and I wiſhe it were ſo, yet no direct doctrine for vs, that if they liue not accordingly, to condemne their ſayings, by theyr doings: for if that be authoritie to confirme the one, or conſounde the other: your ſelues ſhoulde looke into the liues of your Auntient fathers (ſo tearmed) as Abbots, Pryors, Monkes, Nunnes, and Friers, of all fethers: Biſhoppes, Prebends, and Prieſts, of all ſortes, with the liues of ſundry Saintes, canonized by your Pops, and euen the Popes themſelues (with al their Colledge of Cardinals) in whoſe damnable trace you deſire to drawe, without regarde to God, your Prince, profeſſion, or Countrey, whoſe great abuſes, from the beginning (founded on all filthy hipocriſie, reſpecting neyther perſon, place, nor times) manifeſted their liues to their learning, confirmed their doctrine to their doing, with ſuch, and ſo hatefull examples, as I ſorrow to know them, ſhame to think of thē, &amp; am much more haſhfull to write them. Yet leaſt you ſhould ſay, I ſuppoſe more than I can proue: I will (in pardon of the learned) deliuer you ſomewhat, teſtified by the true auth
                  •
                and of ſundry. Wherin, if I kéepe not the order of a perfect 
                  •
               ut bring 
                  •
               apher: impute it rather, to the imperfection of my 
                  〈◊〉
               , than to the baſeneſſe of the matter: whoſe had ſubſtaunce (I cōfeſſe) may abhorre any Chriſtian to read it, yet no more than is méete to be known. And therfore firſt I addreſſe me to theyr ſuperfluous exceſſe in gourmandiſe, the ſurſe and ſinke of all ſinne. The French prouerbe ſayth, Apres la panſe, vient la danſe, After meate comes mirth: for gluttonie is the chiefe nouriſher and leader to all inceſte and letcherie: if you then ioyne the qualitie with the quantitie, of that they commonlye fed on: that is, to compare the fineſſe of their meate, to the filling of their paunches: you ſhal finde then, that vnder the title of Holy pouertie, they were as curious and daintie mouthed as might be, accounting of no God, but of the Pope, and their bellies.
            As a Prior of Prouance, playing with his Minion, in the morning after he had gaped, ſtretched, belched and ſpitted, hée commanded a coople of Partridges to be roſted for his breakfaſt:

whych when he had deuoured, with a pot of the beſt (half in a paſſion) ſaide, good Lord giue me patience, for we of the Church ſuffer ſundry croſſes, Affirming the furie of a Cardinall, that at a generall counſel grewe in a great chafe, bicauſe he was ſerued with Patridges and Wodcocks, without Orenges, 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 
                  
                     •••
                  . ſaying, what penaunce do we endure, and what perſecution do we paſſe for our Mother Holy Church? So as, the marke wherevnto all thoſe groſſe creatures of the Popes did tende theyr trauayles, was only to make good cheare, and to liue at eaſe and pleaſure.
            We reade of one, that before he was Pope (in ſigne of humilitie 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 
                  
                     •
                  27. and deuotion) would euer féede vppon a nette: but ſo ſoone as he hadde attayned the Papacie, he commaunded hys man, to ſet thoſe bourde clothes aſide, for he hadde gotten that he fiſhed for. It was in thoſe days, a familiar ſaying, to name a Frier or a Monke, a righte brother: which (in effect) was a good companion, one that loued to fare well, and to haue good fellowſhip: whereof procéeded this prouerbe, He lokes like an Abbot, he is as fatte as a Monke or Frier, he is as great as an Abbie lubber, and as wel in larde, as a hogge. As though there had byn ſome ſecret Sympathie, betwéen Hogs and Monkes, I meane, in puris naturalibus, In their own nature, for Sainte Anthoni
                     •
                  
                (a founder of their fraternitie) was firſt a Swine-heard, and then a Monke-heard: which truely appeared in hys profeſſors, for they wente aboute, crying, giue ſomething of your charitie, to the Porklings of Saint Anthonie. And a certaine Scot writing an Epigram, concluded his reſolution, in theſe Verſes.
            
               Credibile est Circen, mutaſſe potentibus herbis
               In Monachoſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  ſues, in
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  ſues Monachos.
            
            
               
                  No doubt but Circes coulde, 
                  
                     Apo. Ste Fo. 329. 
                  by Hearbes of vertues hie
               
               
                  Make Monkes of Hogges, and Hogges of Monkes, as fat as Bore in ſtye.
               
            
            And in trueth, what condition of life, could be more reſembled to ſwine, than theirs, that commonly fed on the Church?

whoſe order of liuing (beſides their brutiſhe behauiour) was as careleſſe of religion, as hogges are ſenſeleſſe of reaſon. One of theyr owne profeſſion, who knewe their nature by a true meaſure, and coulde ſhape a Monke by the ſhadowe of a beaſte, or a beaſt by the ſubſtaunce of a Monke, deſcribeth thē thus: he muſt be naſtie, a glutton, ſlouthful, a whoremonger, ill giuen, a foole, blockiſh, a drunkard, and ignoraunt of al good Artes, drinke like a Pigge, and féede like a Hogge: So that, if he can a little ſing, it ſuffiſeth to be an Abbot. Another more abruptly, though as aptly, making a ſimilitude of a thrée footed ſtoole, by a Frier, ſayth: he is rounded like a foole, clothed in graye like a Woulfe, and girded with a corde like a théefe: and yet is no foole but a Frier.
            Our ſimple Prieſts, yt profeſſed not ſo ſtrict a life, whoſe profits only cōſiſted in ye merits of the Maſſe: had ſpecial care (how good ſoeuer theyr breade were) to drinke ſtil of the beſt, &amp; good reaſon they had, to dry vppe raw humours, leſt in celebrating theyr Maſſe, ſome rumaticke matter mighte drop from theyr drowſie braynes: as alſo deuotion is ryper, in a warme ſtomacke than a colde: And according to the opinion of our olde As the father the ſon, the holy Ghost, the twelue Apostles, Marie, the Theefe, the Centurion the Publicā &amp; others 
               Poets: Post pocula fluit ſermo. Therefore he that ſhould play ſo many parts alone as thoſe in their maſking Maſſings do, had néede drinke of the beſt, and in a full cuppe: for if it be tollerable to ſaye hoc est naſum meum: This is my noſe, in lieu of hoc est corpus meum, this is my hody: ſo it be done, cum intentione conſecrandi: or no ill to caſt a child into a tubbe of Water, ſo it be cum intentione Baptizandi: as ſūdry their gloſes cōfirm: what error can there be in a poore Maſſing Prieſte, to drinke drunke, when it is done cum intentione miſſificand
                     •
                  : 
               
                  Ap. Ste Fo 330. Fo. 330. Fol. 331.
            
            As a Curate at Fere in Tartenoys had drunke ſo déepe ouer night: that the next day in lieu of Chriſtening, he miniſtred to the infant his laſt vnction.
            And another prieſt at Ansterdā
                in Hollād, yt ſlept in his Memento, 
               
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 331. being ſodainly wakened cryed ye king drinks: dreming he had bin in the company, he was drunk in the night before. 
                  Ap. Ste Fo. 592.
            
            As alſo a Perſon of Vittre in Brytaine (ouerwatched

at Poſt and Paire) dwelte ſo long in his Mement
                     •
                  
                that being haſtily wakned, he cryed fluſh, and began to rake the Chalice to him.
            A Curat of a village called old Slough, (betwéen Hamburge and L
                     •
                  becke) ſlepte ſo ſoundely in hys Memento as the partye 
                  Ap. Ste. 
                        •
                     o. 37. who helped him to Maſſe (in the meane whyle) ſtole away the Chalice and the plate: And when the Prieſt wakened he ran after hym in hys robes, crying ſtoppe the théefe: who was worthyly mocked of euerye man, for that he did not firſt 
                  •
               argaine with him, what he woulde haue for helping hym to Maſſe.
            Among thys good companye, I muſt (in pardon) place a 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 592. Chaplaine of the Lord de Bies. who ſetting in a corner of the aulter a draught of the beſt (reſeruing it for his Vltimum vale, after he had ſayde Maſſe) in the middeſt of his Memento, he ſpyed his boy about it: to whome he ſodainely ſpake aloude, let it alone you villaine, it was not ſet there for you: whereby you may ſée, what a ſpeciall care theſe Maſſe Merchauntes had, to a cup of good Wine.
            If I ſhould from the Prieſt to the Pope, loke into al their exceſſe in delicacie and gluttonie: it woulde make a more volume than my muſe pretēdeth. But you may imagine of their meate by the men, and of their dyet by their degrees: For if the poorer ſort (euē to beggers) could féede fat, ful and fine: you muſt ſuppoſe, the mytred, redde hatted, and triple crowned, cate not of the worſt: but as their ſtomackes longed, ſo would they euer haue their luſt aunſwered.
            Pope Iulie the thirde, otherwiſe called Iohn Maria de Mō
                  te, 
               
                  Apo Ste 
                        ••
                     . 
                  
                     ••
                  56. commaunded to haue a Peacock that was dreſt for dinner, to be kept colde for his ſupper: whiche not being done accordingly, he grewe in a great rage for it: a Cardinal, then being with him at ye bourd, perſwaded his holyneſſe not to be angry: to whom the Pope replied, ſaying: if God were ſo highly offē
               ded in Paradiſe, to caſt out our firſt father Adam frō thence, and only for eating an Aple: why ſhald not I (being his vicar on earth) be more furious for a Peacocke, knowing how farre

it is in value aboue a rotten Aple.
            The ſame Pope louing Bacon very wel, and wanting it at his bourd (in anger) aſked hys Steward, howe it happened 
                  Fo. 356. he had not his Gammon of Bacon? to whom he anſweared, your Phiſitions charged me, to bring none before you, wherat his holyneſſe entred into ſuch a raging Paſsion, as he ſaid: Porta mi quel mio piatio, al despetto de Dio, Bring me my Bacō, in deſpight of God.
            
            Heare you haue their diſordinate deſire, to liue delicately: for the which, they ſpared no degrée, nor reſpected any perſon, but Epicure like, liued only to eate.
            Which truely was the chiefeſt cauſe, why they entertayned the World in ſo great abuſe, and yet doe, where their authoritie &amp; antient credite hath place: for all their endeuour and Studie from the loweſt to the higheſt, was to bring water to their Mill: To the ende, their téeth might want no griſte to grinde on. And Turpe lucrum that which all Ethnick authours condemned and baniſhed their common wealthes: Theſe ſeeming Chriſtians, founde ſuch ſauour in, as theſe fooliſh toyes voyde of all reaſon (to the iudgemente of the wiſe) wroughte them the eaſieſt and readieſt way to infinite wealth. And all that hath bin or may be alleged to the contrarie, is but winde and labour loſt, for that it is ſpokē to their bellies, which haue no eares: for they kepte this prouerbe, as a principle among them, Lucri bonus odor ex re qualibet, that is, The ſmel of gain is good of euery thing. For thoughe by worde and writing, they were ofte reproued for their ſhameleſſe ſpoyles called péelers of the Church (in lieu of pillers) Crucifix Cormorāts, Maſſe féeders, Diſſemblers, Grypers, Ipocrites, and rauening wolues: yet they forced no more of it, thā ye couetous Athenian did, of whom Horac
                     •
                  
                maketh mention thus: Populus me ſibilat, at mihi plaudo, ipſi domi ſimul ac nummos contemplor in arca. The people do hiſ
                     •
                  e at me, I reioyced at it, for at home I doe glorie at the ſight of my golde in my Coffers. And truelye, notwithſtanding they carryed the onely countenaunce of the world, yet were they mocked of ſundry, but their faces were

ſo braſen as they forced not of it. As a Monke of Bloyſe replyed to one that ſcorned him: we maye well, and on an eaſie price, giue you leaue to mocke vs, ſéeing we gaine ſo much, by mocking of you, who anſwered, not ſo outragiouſly, &amp; wt ſuch blaſphemie, as Pope 
                  
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  n the 10. did to Cardinal Bemb
                     •
                  e where 
                  Apo. Ste. Fo. 358. he alleaged a text of Scripture vnto him: what ritches do we acquire and get by this fable of Chriſt? where if he had ſayd, by abuſing the name of Chriſt he had ſpoken the truth. For it is incredible to conſider what welth thoſe of the Romiſh church did wallow in: As B
                     •
                  ptiſt Fulgoſa (a great fautor and fauourer 
                  Baptist Fulgoſa li. 9. c a. 1 of their profeſſion) doth mentiō vnto vs an example of one named Pete
                     •
                   Riarus which was firſt a Frier Minor, and after made Cardinall by Pope Sixtus the fourth. For (ſaith he) this Riarus was not alone content to weare cloth of gold in his houſe, but his hangings and couerleds were likewiſe of clothe of golde, he alſo made a feaſte to Ellenor of Arago
                     •
                  
                (that paſſed by Rome to marrie with Hercules de Eſt duke of Ferrara) that continewed in ſeruice ſeuen houres: with ſuch magnificence, as at euerye courſe his ſeruauntes chaunged themſelues into newe Liueries. All which Pompe was nothing to the pryde and brauerie of his Concubine named Tireſia, whom he kept in ſuch ſort openly, as hir ſhooes were all couered ouer wyth pearls and pretious ſtones, whiche Hiſtorie more at large is extant in Fulgoſi
                     •
                  
                booke, intituled De hominum l
                     •
                  x
                     •
                   at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   delitijs in the ninth booke and firſt Chapter.
            And as the forenamed Pope Leon did wonder at the welth that the fable of Chriſte broughte them (as he moſte blaſphemouſly doeth tearme it) ſo is it iuſtifyed by a Frier of Millian (named Sampſo
                     •
                  ) that by one croyſarde gathered to himſelfe 
                  Fo. 
                  
                     •
                  36. 120. thouſande Duckets, whiche he after offred for ye Papacy.
            What greater contempt could be committed againſt the glorie A ſpecial pardon giuen by the Pope, by carrying a croſſe aboute named a croiſard
                     •
                   which commonly came forth vnder the pretence of going against the Iurke &amp; other infidels. of God, or how could his poore members be more abuſed or bewitched, than they were by the colourable and cunning pretext of this croyſarde. For they perſwaded the people, that if their beneuolence were bountiful to this croſſe offring, they ſhould be ſaued, with theyr fathers, their mothers, and theyr

chidren: And to be ſlacke in giuing (or not to giue) was a ſinne vnpardonable, and wrought their aſſured damnation. Which broughte the porer ſorte into ſo deſperate an error, as it cauſed them to guage or ſell their ſoules to the Diuell in procuring money for them by all vnlawfull meanes, rather than they would loſe the benefite of ſo large a bleſting, and incurre the daunger of ſo certaine deſtruction, ſuppoſing in their ſimplicitie, that this pardon preuayled, both againſt God and the Diuel. In the time and Article of death, they would giue no hope of ſaluation to any, vnleſſe they made Saint Francis, S Dominicke or ſome other Saint their heyre being patron of theyr profeſſion. For they knewe howe to charme, the conſcience of thoſe, they confeſſed, as they would be ſure to glean a good part of that, which the poore widow &amp; hir children (in right) ſhould liue on.
            It is written, yt one of theſe holy fathers, moſt ſhameleſſely 
                  Apo. Ste Fo 3
                     •
                  4. affirmed in his Sermon at Burdeaux: yt when as often as any mony was giuē for thoſe yt wer in purgatorie: their ſouls (hearīng it ſoūd tinck, tinck, in the baſen) did al in great ioy, laugh the muſicke of it. And ſince I haue made mention of Purgatorie, I craue pardon of the reader: to note a pleaſaunt example or two, touching the credite of it.
            Pope Clement ye eight (with certain Prelates his friends) being beſieged in ye Caſtel of Saint Angel in Rome a gentlemā 
               
                  Fo. 417. of the ſame Citie ſaide: If his holyneſſe (vppon whom all the world haue ſo long builded their opinion) can not frée himſelf, and his faythfull followers, from this place of impriſonment: I muſte (for my parte) be conſtrayned to beleeue, that he is of much leſſe power, able to deliuer poore ſoules out of Purgatorie. A Florentine being earneſtly ſolicited by certain Friers, to redeeme the ſoule of his ſon out of Purgatorie, promiſed, that 
                  Fo. 519. if they would take vpon them, and yt he might be aſſured they did it, he would (for their merit) giue thē a Ducket. After they had ſaide theyr charmes &amp; ſolemne Maſſes for him, they came for their gold: to whō ye good mā anſwered, whē you ſhew me ſome aſſured ſign, of his deliuery: I wil hold my word wt you,

Thoſe rauening mates, not ſo content (hoping by extremity, to obtaine their purpoſe) complayned to the Duke, who ſente for the partie, and aſked why he performed not his promiſe to them: to whom he aunſwered, it reſted on this condition, yt it ſhould appeare to him, they had deliuered his ſon out of Purgatorie: &amp; ſeing it was at the firſt, their own ſéeking, he (knowing them to be ſuttle) was loth to looſe his money, without good &amp; true teſtimonie: the Duke ſmelling ye myſterie, turned to ye Friers, &amp; told thē he had reaſon: And therfore ſaid, if you wil ſend ye ſame ſoule to me, or two others, to witneſſe his deliuerie, or bring me ſome writing vnder his own hād ſubſcribed by Chriſt, I wil ſée you ſhall be anſwered ye vttermoſt: otherwiſe I ſhould wrong him too much, &amp; ſhew my ſelf partial in Iuſtice.
            A gentleman of Fraunce playing the ſame part, when they came to demaund money for the Maſſes they had ſaide for the 
                  Fo. 393. ſoule of his friend: he aſked, if there were any daunger of hys returne again to Purgatorie, being once (by their good prayers) deliuered from thence: they anſwered no: why then quoth he, it were a needleſſe charitie, to giue any thing for him yt is alredie in ſafetie: &amp; therfore I thinke it a godly policie, to kepe my money in ſtore, to pleaſure ſome other poore ſoule, not yet deliuered, &amp; ſo ſent thē away faſting. A Venetian told ye Popes legat, yt his holineſſe was euil councelled at the firſt, for it had bin more wiſedom (ſaid he) to haue publiſhed, yt he could haue deliuered ſoules out of hel, rather than out of Purgatory: for touching Purgatorie, it is to be conſidered whether there be ſuch a place or no: but for Hell there is no queſtion, ſince the whole world beléeues there is one. What treaſure this toye of Purgatorie brought to your mother holy church, the pride of your Pope holy father, with al his marked traine, of Coules, crownes, and tippets, haue in all ages teſtifyed.
            The French king being at Rome where ſéeing the pompe of 
                  Fo. 468. the Popes court (and ſpecially of the Cardinals) aſked ye Cardinal of Autgnion if the Apoſtles of Chriſt went ſo ſūptuouſly apparelled: he aunſwered no: but your Maieſtie muſt conſider

(ſayd he) that ſtates with time do alter, for the Apoſtles were fiſhers, &amp; liued in thoſe dayes when Kings were ſhepheards.
            If you ſuppoſe it a reproofe to our profeſſion, the lacke of ſounde learning in ſome our ordinarie Miniſters: looke into your Romiſh religion, and you ſhall ſée examples of ſundry to be more ſottiſh, vnlearned, and leſſe witted, thā the worſt and ſimpleſt of our ſorte. As one commended to a Biſhop to be made a Maſſing Prieſt, whom he finding at dinner, the Biſhop 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 403. to proue his Latine, ſaide: Es tu dignus? he anſwered, no ſir I thanke you, I will dyne with your ſeruauntes, beléeuing that Dignus had bin to dyne.
            An other comming to be Prieſted, and aſked who was father to the foure ſonnes of Amon, was ſet a ground, and anſwered 
                  Fol. 403. he could not tell, and therefore was refuſed. Who at his comming home ſhewed how hardly he was handled: his father to inſtruct him ſaid: Ball my dogge hath foure whelps and who can be father to my whelps (thou beaſt) but Ball. This ſetled ſo great reaſon in his ſonne, that he was aſſured now to be admitted: And ſo being aſked the ſecond time, who was father to the foure ſonnes of Amon, he anſwered readily and wittily, Ball my fathers dogge. An other of the ſame 
                  Fol. 404. ſtampe, being demaunded, what parte was beſt of a roſted Pigge, anſwered the ſkinne, which was well lyked, and he admitted. A byrd of ye ſame neaſt ſtanding by being likewiſe 
                  Fol. 404. aſked, what part of a Calfe was moſt delicateſt and daintieſt, ſaid the ſkinne, for he ſéeing the others anſwere to paſſe for good payment, ſuppoſed his coyne euery way as currant.
            A certaine Frenchman that had ſerued a Scot, was perſuaded 
                  Fol. 501. (bicauſe he could a little reade) to become a Prieſt. When he ſhould take orders, the Biſhop ſpeaking Latine to him, he anſwered that his maiſter vnderſtoode Scottiſhe very well, but for his part he had not yet learned it, ſuppoſing the Biſhop had ſpoken Scottiſh to him.
            An other (of more learning but of leſſe wit) being aſked in 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 501. Latine, Quot ſunt ſeptem Sacramenta, anſwered, Tres, Aspergillum, Thuribulum, &amp; Magnum Altare: which is in Engliſh,

               How many be the ſeuen Sacramentes, the anſwere, Three, the Holye water Sprinckle, the Senſar, and the highe Altar.
            
            And ſéeing occaſion offereth it ſelfe to make mentiō o
                  •
                holy water (in pardō of the patient reader, &amp; to iuſtifie ſo neceſſarie a matter as holy water is to your holy mother Church) I wil not let ſlip the teſtimonie of thrée ſpeciall authorities.
            A certaine pleaſant reproued bicauſe he did not put off his 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 572. Cappe when the Prieſt ſprinckled him with holy water, anſwered, if it haue power (as you preache) to paſſe to Purgatorie, ſurelye it muſt haue muche eaſier paſſage throughe my Cap.
            A Gentleman of gallant ſpirit (named Godon) a Councellor 
                  Fol. 573. of ye Parliamēt Court in Fraunce, being preſent, whē king Francis the firſt of that name, was deuiſing (with others) the readieſt meane, how he might ſtaie or encounter the Emperour, who (as the report went) was cōming againſt him with a great power. Godon hearing ſome wiſhe they had ſo many thouſand Gaſcoynes and ſome ſo many thouſand Launceknights (with other ſundrie wiſhes) ſaid to ye King: ſéeing it is in queſtion to wyſhe, if your Maieſtie will pardon mée, you ſhall heare my wyſhe, which ſhal be ſuch as will coſt you nothing, where all the reſt of theirs depende on great charges, the King knowing his pleaſant humor, wylled to ſhewe what he woulde wiſhe, ſir ſayde Godon I woulde wiſhe to become a Diuell, but for one quarter of an houre, that I might goe directly to the Emperour, and breake his necke. Truely (quoth the King) I ſée nowe you are no better than a foole, as thoughe the Emperour had not holy Water in his Countrey to chaſe awaye Diuels, aſwell as wée haue here in Fraunce, In pardon of your Maieſtie (replyed Godon) it may ſo be, and I beléeue ſome young Diuell (not ſkilfull of his crafte) woulde flye the holy Water: but ſuch a Diuell, as had at any time bene a Godon, all the holy Water in the worlde, coulde not feare him, wherein he pleaſantly touched the ſuperſtition of it.
            A regiſter in Paris named Lory hearing a Cardinall bemone 
                  Fol 573. his Minion, for that ſhée was poſſeſſed of an euill ſpirit,

and could by no ſkill or cunning be fréed nor eaſed, ſaide, I can ſhewe you a readie remedie. The Cardinall thrice glad, offered any recompence he woulde deſire: Lory replyed, my rewarde ſhall be no more then my coſt, and that is not muche, you néede not to giue hir but one Cliſter of holy Water, and that will chaſe all yll Spirites out of hir, if the force and vertue of it be ſuch, as you ſaye we muſt beléeue.
            I haue one pleaſant proofe more of ye ignorance of your lacke Straparole. latines, worth the remēbrance, which is of a profeſſed Prieſt of Normandie that would néedes trauell to Rome, for a licence to haue two Benefices, who deſired his Biſhop to write to the Pope in his commendation, imagining vpon his cōming what his holyneſſe would ſay to him: and as he vnderſtoode by others (of his owne marke) that had bin there for the like purpoſe, he learned thrée Latine wordes, ſufficient as he ſuppoſed to ſerue his turne, which for that it hath the beſt grace in Latine, I am enforced ſo to deliuer it: for after he had ſaluted the Pope, &amp; ſaide, Salue ſancte Pater, the Pope woulde aſke, Vnde venisti, then he ſhould anſwere è Normandia: next his holineſſe would demaunde, Vbi ſunt litterae tuae, he ſhoulde ſay In manica mea, and ſo take his letters out of his ſléeue and deliuer them, for Prieſts in thoſe dayes commonly carried al their traſhe in their ſléeues. This gallant glorying in his learning, &amp; triumphing of his Latine, mumbled ſo much of it, as he did forget the firſt part, which put him into ſuch diſpaire, as he ment to returne, yet hoping that the image of our Ladie (whoſe chaplaine he was vowed) would do him ſome good, he went into a Chappell to performe his deuotion, where by ye appointment of our Ladie (as he after reported) the Prieſt in his Maſſe recited, Salue ſancte parens, which was to our Norman the greateſt ioy that might be. For when he came to the Popes preſence, he ſaide Salue ſancte parens, the Pope amazed at this new ſalutation, anſwered, Non ſum mulier: ye Prieſt (dwelling vpō his inſtructions) followed with his leſſon è Normandia, ye Pope thus croſſed, ſaid, Diabolum habes, the poore Prieſt replyed, In manica mea, ſuppoſing he had ſaid well.
            
               
If men could be more ignorant than theſe Maſſing maies were, let the wiſe iudge: and no maruel, for their onely ſtudie conſiſted in a ſpeciall care howe to liue eaſilye and dai
                  •
               tily. Was it not ridiculous to ſée thoſe, that ſéemed moſt proſounde and wiſeſt, to vſe in their Sermons ſo great abſurdities. 
                  •
               or one alledging the authoritie of Seripture, to confirme the credite of the Maſſe, enterpreted, Inuenimus Meſſiam, We haue founde the Maſſe. An other to proue their croſſing by Scripture, 
                  Fol. 586. affirmed, that Signa autem eis qui crediderunt, Make the ſigne of the Croſſe on thoſe that haue beleeued. Among which braue interpretations, is to be remembred a Curate in the Countrey of Artoys, that had a proceſſe againſt his pariſhioners for pauing of the Church, who alledged this text of Scripture for his purpoſe: Paueant illi &amp; non paueam ego: 
               
                  Ieremie the 17. Chap.
                whereby he affirmed that S. Hierom ſaid, that they ſhoulde paue the Church and not he. Alſo what way their gloſe had gotten, vpon this place of Scripture, Confitemini alter vtrum, Confeſle your ſelues to the Prieſt, all the world doth knowe. Truely in this abuſe conſiſted their greateſt glorie, for althoughe their ſhameleſſe liues (ſéene to the open viewe of the wiſe) were ſufficient to reproue them and confound them, yet in this priuate confeſſion, they practized more villanie, than any honeſt Chriſtian can endure to heare or reade: which ſhall be hereafter partly touched in his place. Yet to ſhewe you in ſome ſort, their abſurditie and vaine glorie, I will deliuer you two examples ſhort and pleaſaunt.
            A certaine Maſon comming to be ſhriuen by his Curate, Straparole. who had learned great wordes to countenaunce his credite with his Pariſhoners, to the ende that he would ſéeme a profound clearke and wiſe among them: demaunded of him (you muſt ſuppoſe with open mouth) whether he were Auaritious, who anſwered no: art thou (quoth he) Luxurious, he anſwered no: art thou not Superbous he anſwered no: Art thou not Inuidus or Irous? The poore man (ignorant of theſe termes) ſtill anſwered no: ye Prieſt in a rage ſaide, what art thou then? a ſimple Maſon ſir (quoth he) as you may ſée by my Trowell.
            
               
A poore ſhepheard being likewiſe aſked by his ghoſtly father, whether he had kept the commandements of God, anſwered Straparole. no: whether he had kept the commaundementes of the Church, he anſwered (likewiſe) no: what haſt thou kept then (quoth he) nothing ſir ſaide the poore ſhepheard but my ſhéepe. Although the Pope thought it requiſite that theſe Maſſing Prieſtes ſhould haue no more learning than née
                  •
               e
                  •
                them: yet (ſauing their honour) ſome of the greateſt, could miſtake their Latine, aſwell as the reſt. For Henrie the. 8. of famous memorie, ſending (among other things) to Francis the French King and the firſt of that name twelue great Maſtiues, as parcell of his preſent, writing thus: Mitto tibi duodecem moloſſos twelue degges: which Prat his Chauncellor and a great Sorboniſt Doctor tooke to be Duodecem muletos twelue moyles: and therefore deſired his Maieſtie to giue him him the twelue Moyles that King Henrie had ſent. It is ſtraunge ſayde his maiſter, that Moyles ſhoulde be ſent me out of Englande, and therefore willed to ſée the letters: where the king founde the errour, and Prat perceiuing it, ſaid he miſtooke Moloſſos for Mulettos.
            
            And ſéeing I haue occaſion to call this Prat into the play, the more to manifeſt vnto you his couetous life matched with tyrannie, &amp; his miſerable death ioyned with blaſphemie, being of the Church of Rome a profeſſor, and of ye poore members of Chriſt a cruell perſecuter: I will deliuer you the ſame which is written of him, ſimply as I finde it.
            This Prat after he had bailded a faire Hoſpitall (which 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 379. the king ſéeing ſaide it was not large yn
                  •
               ugh, to lodge all thoſe that Prat had made poore) fell ſicke of ſuch a horrible diſeaſe, as the wormes did guawe and pearce throughe his ſtomacke, not without curſing &amp; deſpiting of God, both for payne and extreme impatience: occaſioned aſwell by the griefe he felte, as of the hatred he had, to ſée all his Cofers ſealed vp: that he ſayde, thus it is to ſerue the King both with bodye and ſoule. This Prat was the firſt in Fraunce, that brought and preſented to the Parliamente houſe the

Inquiſition of Hereſies: he gaue forthe the firſt Commiſſion to execute thoſe that ſpake againſt the Romiſhe Church, whoſe blaſpheming death confirmed the crueltie of his life, for cleane forgetting God and his mercie, he manifeſtly ſhewed what Saint he ſerued.
            Alſo Ponchar Archbyſhop of Toures, following the erection of a burning Chamber, he was (by the fire of God) 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 379. burned himſelfe: which beganne at his héeles and féete, and increaſed ſo vpwarde throughe all his bodye, as they were fayne to cut his members by péece meale away.
            One Iohn Ruze, a Councellor alſo of the Parliament, ye cruelleſt perſecuter of Chriſtes profeſſors in his time, was 
                  Fo. 
                  
                     •
                  79. likewiſe puniſhed by ye ſecret fire of God, yt he felte himſelfe burne as in a furnace: &amp; ſhewyng no ſigne of remembring God, his whole body conſumed withal, and ſo dying in moſt horrible blaſphemie, he refuſed to call to God for mercie.
            And as the Diuine iudgement was executed vpon this, ſo 
                  Fol. 380. was it vpon another Councellor of ye Court, named Claude de Aſles, for the ſame day yt he gaue ſentence for ye burning of two true profeſſors, immediately after, vſing ye companie of his harlot (in the verie act) was taken with an Apoplexie and ſo ſodainely dyed. Likewiſe one Iohn Menier Lorde of Oppide, a follower with all his force, for the burning &amp; Maſſacring 
                  Fol. 380. of Chriſt in his mēbers: was taken himſelfe with ſuch a burning ſtrangurie, as with the paine thereof he fell into ſo extreme impatience, yt he blaſphemed God euen to his laſt breath, ſaying, why ſhould not I curſe him, whom thoſe damnable Lutherans did glory and praiſe in the middeſt of their tormentes? By this the reader may iudge in what miſerie thoſe men dwell, whoſe conſciences giue them ſuch horrible aſſaults, as a late Chaūcellor of Fraunce, mightily combatted by his conſcience, at the inſtant of death cried, Ah thou Cardinall thou Cardinal, thou doſt cauſe vs all to be damned. An example of Gods great iuſtice, on thoſe that ſéeke the Innocent bloud of his profeſſors.
            I did at the firſt craue pardon of the mildeſt minded Papiſts,

to beare with my error, if I placed not my authors as I ought, which I confeſſe may manifeſt my ignorance, yet truely they néede not feare, that it will marre the credite of their matter, the ſubſtance is ſo good: and therefore to confirme old prouerbes, Sine Cerere &amp; Baccho friget Venus, I wil ſhewe you ſome examples, what fruites followed the hatefull exceſſe of the Crucifix cormerantes, who ſed onely on their holy mother Church.
            A certaine Gentlemā of Perigourd in Fraunce, held in his houſe a Frier, his confeſſor, whō he fauoured for his coūcel, 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 303. and reuerenced for his profeſſion. This Gentleman (whoſe wife had lien in childe bed the ſpace of thrée wéekes) determined one night to haue hir company, which our Frier perceiuing, ſo vſed ye matter, as he preuented his maiſter, enioyed his place, &amp; (kéeping himſelf ſilent) 
                  •
               ūningly (vnknowē) departed from hir, which done, he haſted to his houſe, called ye porter, &amp; fled the puniſhmēt of his fault. The huſband cō
               ming to his wife (as he had pointed) &amp; ſhe ſimply ſuppoſing he had bin wt hir before, deliuered ſuch ſpéeches vnto him, as he perceiued ye treaſon committed againſt them both. Then conſidering how none laye in ye quarter of houſe, except hir brother &amp; his confeſſor, entred into ſuſpition of him, &amp; went ſtraight to his Chāber, where he foūd him not, which greatly increaſed his ielouſie: but whē he had ſpokē wt his porter, he was aſſured of ye villanie, &amp; returning to his wife, manifeſted ye circumſtance of ye miſchiefe vnto hir, wherat ye poore Gentlewoman was ſo abaſhed, &amp; grieued, ye it brought hir into extreme diſpaire, as being left alone (hir huſband gone after ye Frier) hir innocent heart yéelded to hir féeble hand, &amp; ſtrāgled hir ſelf, who wreſtling wt the agonie of this cruel death, did (with hir foote) kill hir little infant that lay by hir: and giuing a great crie (at hir laſt gaſp) wakened hir maide that foundly ſlept in the ſame Chamber: when ſhe ſawe this pitifull ſpectacle (paſt all remedie) ſhe called hir Maiſtreſſe brother, who beholdyng the lamentable condition of hys ſiſter and hir child, demaunded of the maide who it was had

committed this cruell Acte: ſhe anſweared ſhe coulde not tell, vnleſſe it were hir maiſter, for ſhe certainly knew none but he had bene there. This Gentleman, ſought his brother in his owne chamber, and finding him gone, he exclaimed againſt him for ye murder, and with reuenging minde he tooke his horſe to followe him, ſuppoſing he had bin fled for the horribleneſſe of the fact: whom when he heard returning (for the darkeneſſe of the nighte had taken frō him the author of all his woe) he violently flew vpon him (with wordes of reproch, calling him moſt wicked wretch &amp; tirā
               nous traitor) ran him through with his rapier. The gentleman hauing no leaſure to enquire the occaſion of ſo ſodaine aſſault, being wounded to death, yéelded vnto him. But when he vnderſtoode the villanie, with his brothers innocencie, he ouer late craued pardō for the harme he had done him, remount
                  •
               d him aſwell as he might, and brought him home to his houſe, where the next day following he likewiſe dyed. By this tragedie we ſée, how the leud luſt of a Frier was the occaſion of the murdering of thrée innocent perſons.
            In the time of the Emperour Maximilian the firſt, there was in his countrey a Couent of Friers, highly renowned 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 337. for the opinion that euery one had in their holy profeſſion. Néere vnto which Abbey there dwelled a Gentleman of great worſhip and credite, who fauoured theſe Friers, wi
                  •
               h a ſeruent zeale of deuotion, and was a ſpeciall benefactor vnto them Among which companie, he choſe to himſelfe a confeſſor, to whom he gaue full power and authoritie ouer his houſe and houſholde. This lecherous lubber became ſo enamored on the Gentlewoman, as (reſolued to put his luſt in execution,) comming to hir houſe, and finding not hir huſbande at home, he demaunded of hir whether hir huſbande was gone, ſhée anſweared, to a Farme that hée had, where he ment to make his abode for thrée or foure dayes, but if hée had anye ſpeciall matter to doe wyth hym, ſhée woulde preſently ſende a Meſſenger for hym:

wherevpon he taking occaſion to performe his damnable pretence, walked vp and downe about the houſe, as one ye had ſome matter of importance, or ſome greate miſchiefe hammering in his head. The gentlewoman perceyuing it (for that his countenance argued, he was not content) ſhe ſent one of hir maydes to know, if any of hyr houſe had offended him, or that he lacked his deſire in any thing. This mayde doyng hir miſtreſſe meſſage, the Fatherly Frier, or rather Helliſh fiende, toke hir (in ſigne of curteſie) by the hande, and leading hir aſide into a corner of the Court, he cut hir throate. In the meane while there arriued a Tenaunt of the gentlemans that brought him rent, who hū
               bly ſaluted the Frier, &amp; he embraſing him (with the ſame knife he had murdered the mayde, which was ſkant cold of hir bloude) he likewiſe cut his throate, and after cloſed the Caſtel gate vnto him. The gentlewomā muſing yt hir chā
               ber mayde returned not, ſent hir companion to cal hir, and to know the cauſe of hir ſtay, which the Frier (in ſort as afore) toke hir by the hande, and with the ſame bloudie ſtratageme, ſent hir after hir play-fellow. Then when he ſaw himſelfe alone in the houſe, he came to the gentlewoman, and deliuered hir the effect of his diuelliſh deſire: ſhewing how long he had earneſtly loued hir, &amp; that now the houre was come, that ſhe muſte néedes yéelde vnto his will. She that neuer had any euil opinion in him, and leaſt loked for any ſuch ſalutation, anſwered, my good Father, I beléeue if you knew me to be ſo euil diſpoſed, or yt you thought I had ſo bad a conceite in me, you would be the firſt yt would either reclaime me, or diſcouer my ſhame for it. The Frier (to cut of al circumſtaunces, and to preuent that might follow) flatly perſwaded hir, there was no remedie: willyng hir to go into ye Court, where ſhe ſhoulde ſée the ſū of hys pretence. When the gentlewoman beheld hir two maids and hir tenaunt lying in that pitiful caſe, ſhe was ſo aſtonyed and ouerſet with feare, as ſhe remayned ſpéechleſſe. This villaine (who made no account to enioy hir companie

for one time, but to haue the abuſe of hir body for euer) woulde not force hir, and therfore ſayde: Miſtreſſe be ruled by me, and doubt of no daunger, for you are in the handes of him, that loues you aboue al ye men in the world: and ſo taking forth the gowne of a Nouice (which he had brought with him for the ſame purpoſe vnder his lōg robe) he willed hir to put it on, otherwiſe ſhe ſhold paſſe the ſame paine thoſe had done, which lay before hir eyes. The gentlewoman ſéeing hir owne peril (as well to ſaue hir life, as to gaine time, in hope that hir huſbande woulde come to hyr reſcue) ſhe fayned willingly to obey him: and at the commaundement of the Frier, vntyred hir heade, wherein ſhe vſed as much delay as ſhe might. But in the end, when ſhe was in hir haire, the Frier (not regarding the beauty of it) did haſtily cut it off, and further cauſed hir to ſtrip hir ſelfe to hir ſmocke, and to put on the little frock he brought with him: whych done he made al the haſte away that he could, carrying wyth hym his heauye and ſorrowfull Nouice, whoſe companye he had (in beaſtlye luſt) ſo long deſired. But it pleaſed God, that hyr huſbande, (who had diſpatched hys buſineſſe ſooner than he ſuppoſed he ſhoulde before his going) returned home by the ſame waye, that hys diſtreſſ
                  •
               d wife and thys murder
                  •
               us mate was comming. When the Frier perceyued him a far off, he ſayde to hir: beholde where commeth youre huſbande, who I know, if you make any countenaunce to diſcouer your ſelf, hée wil take you from me: Therfore go you before me, and ſée that you turne your face on the contrarye ſide, that he perceiue you no
                  •
               : for if you make anye ſigne or geſture vnto hym, I will ſooner cutte your throate, than he ſhall be able to frée you out of my handes. In whiche diſcourſe, the Gentleman approched, who, after he had ſaluted him, aſked him from whence he came: to whome he boldly and ſhameleſlye aunſweared, from your houſe ſir, where my Miſtreſſe youre wiſe is verye well, and doeth earneſtlye looke for you. The gentleman rode on, not

perceyuing anye thing: but hys ſeruaunte, who was accuſtomed to entertayne thys Fryers companion (named Frater Iohn) ſuppoſing it hadde bene hée, called vnto him. The poore gentlewoman, perplexed in all the paſſions of minde that might bée, durſte not turne hir heade towardes hym, nor aunſwere anye one word: notwythſtanding, the fellowe to ſée hys vizage, croſſed the waye of hyr, to whome (ſo farre as ſhée durſte) ſhe made a ſorrowfull ſigne, wyth hyr trembling eyes, that were ful of teares: The ſeruaunte ſuppoſing ſome myſterie in it, and geſſing at a glaunce who it ſhoulde bée, he haſted after hys Mayſter, and tolde hym, that the Fryers companion was not Frater Iohn, but ſéemed to bée hys Miſtreſſe, who hée affirmed (wyth a face all couered wyth teares) ſhée dyd caſte a pitifull regarde towardes him. The Gentlemanne, halfe offended at hys follye (as he thoughte) ſayde hys manne was madde, and made no accounte of hys wordes: yet he ſtill continewed in hys requeſt to hys Maiſter, deſiring leaue to returne, and to ſée the trueth of that hée imagined. Wherevnto the Gentleman agréed, and ſtayed to heare what newes his man would bring him. The Fryer looking back, and hearing hym call Frater Iohn, doubted leaſte he had diſcouered hys Miſtreſſe: and therefore with a long armed batte (a common weapon for thoſe mates to martch wi
                  •
               h) hée ſo reached at the fellowe, as he felled him off his horſe, and ſtraighte leaping vppon hym cutte hys throte: hys maiſter, who ſawe a farre off hys man ouerthrowne, ſuppoſed hée hadde fallen by ſome miſchaunce, and therfore haſted to helpe him vppe againe. But when he came nere to thys deſperate and ſturdie Frier, with the ſame bleſſing that he vnhorſed the man, he vnhorſed the maiſter, and caſt himſelfe vpon him, with al the violence he might: and if ye gentlemā had not bin both bolde &amp; ſtrōg, ye Frier had there ended the Tragedie. But by his ſtrength, he helde him ſo harde in hys armes, as he coulde doe him no more hurte:

And withall forced him to forgo the knife wherewith hée had performed all this miſchiefe, which his wife ſéeing it fall from him, toke it vp, and put it into the hande of hyr huſbande. The caſe béeing altered, the gentlewomans courage encreaſed: for in the moſte furious manner that ſhe myghte, ſhe beſtyrred hyr to plague hym, that hadde ſo muche puniſhed hyr: And in the meane tyme the gentleman ſo ſtabbed in the Frier, as he was fayne to yéelde, &amp; confeſſed the trueth of hys faulte. The Gentleman would not kyll hym, but kepte hym to diſcouer more, and to receyue ſome ſharper correction, for hys ſo horrible an offence: and ſo carryed hym to the Emperours iuſtice in Flaunders, where he vttered the order of the execution of this miſchiefe, wyth the cauſe, ſhewing what a number of Gentlewomen and beautifull may
                  •
               s (by the like murders and treaſons) were cloſely kepte in theyr Monaſterie, which proued true, by commiſſioners appointed, they firſt deliuered for the all ſuche women as they found moſte pitifully cloſed in theyr Cloyſters, and (for an euerlaſting memorie to their poſteritie) they ſhut vp all the Friers in the Abbey, and burned both the houſe and thoſe damnable wretches togither.
            Here you haue a manifeſt mirror of all the miſchiefes that may be, whiche ſheweth no ſingle ſinne, and in one priuate, but by a moſte bloudy and common conſent of the whole Couent: the like neuer heard nor redde off afore, cō
               mitted by any Barbariā, Iew, Turke, or Heathen. I ſhold (in troth) do double iniurie to our new found Ieſuites, and depriue them of the honor they deſerue, if I ſhould not appoint them (as gueſtes twice welcome) a ſpeciall place in theſe bloudy banckets: for albeit neither Saint Francis, Saint Dominick, nor Saint Anthony, was acquainted wyth thē: yet are they cloth of the ſame wool, and wil proue no worſe in the wearing though dyed into an other colour, for you ſhall finde them as ignoraunt as Monkes, as imputente and ſhameleſſe as Monkes, and as miſchieuous &amp; profane

as Monks: and therfore, for affinitie, fraternitie, and ſocietie, they haue all vowed their deuotion to one Saint. And where they be (indéede) auntient, and can claime their antiquitie from the fall of Lucifer, yet as politicke children, following the ſuttletie of their Father (to deceiue the iniquitie of time) do maſke vnder a ſtraunge viſarde. By whiche pretext, they haue promiſed, to reſtore England to their Romiſhe mother holy Church agayne. And therefore to further theyr ſayling, that they may the ſooner be ſet a ſhore at Wapping, I will ſhewe you a créedible example or two (cō
               mitted by ſome of their profeſſion) as horrible as the reſte.
            A Gentleman of Lymoſin (Lord of Saint Iohn de Lygours) abuſing his wiues mother, and hauing children by hir (vnder benedicite,) diſcouered his fault to one of this fraternitie: who to proue their profeſſion frée of no ſin, exerciſed the craft of coyning, and now toke occaſiō (hauing this gentlemās head at his foote) to perſwade him to ioyne in making of counterfaite money with him. After they had practiſed this matter long betwéen them, the Ieſuit ſéeing the in
                  •
               eſt to preſſe the gentlemans conſcience (as it dayly vnquieted him) for all the ordinarie abſolutions he had giuen him: and finding, that he toke greater pleaſure in the mother, than in ye daughter, he perſwaded him to marry hir: ſhewing that the marriage was moſt lawful in hir, in whome he moſt delighted: confirming yt the matrimonie he dwelt in, and all that came of it was accurſed. And therfore hée toke in hande, to frée him from this care: whiche he executed in the abſence of the gentleman, thoughe his conſente were with him. So, entring on a night into the Caſtell according to his cuſtome (hauing coltes of his owne coate with him) wente ſtraight to the gentlewomans chamber, whoſe throat he cut in hir bed, and after murdered hir two little infants that lay by hir: the one of them, calling him by his name, held vp his hands, and leapt into his armes for mercie, as he confeſſed at his execution. Not ſatiſfied with this (with the helpe of his companions) he maſſacred

all that he founde in the houſe: and to couer the fault, meaning to burne them, he brought their bodyes togither into one chamber, and ſet fire on the whole Caſtell. But God, whoſe prouidence would not ſuffer the fire to conſume neither the one nor the other, they were pitifully founde, the murderers taken, and the fault confeſſed, whiche the gentleman hearing, fled to Sauoye, and paſſing for Gene, was knowne vpon the way, followed to Lauſanne, and there executed. Oh wretched condition more than damnable, deuiſed without malice, performed without mercie, and by a Ieſuit of the Popes profeſſors.
            A foule of the ſame feather, in Vienna in Austrie méeting vpon the way a poore yong mayde of the age of nyne or ten 
                  Apo. Ste Fol. 306. yeares, whoſe beautie, and bodie (though in bare tearmes) was not to be miſtiked: he taken in a ſodaine luſt to hyr, perſwaded the yong thing that he woulde better hir ſtate, if ſhe woulde be ruled by him. The Girle ſéeing him to ſéeme a holy Father, and like a maiſter in Iſrael, ſuppoſed ſhe had founde good fortune, beléeued hys perſwaſion, &amp; wēt to hys Cloyſter with hym, where ſhe was for a time cloſed in hys Cabinet, and in the end, deſiring to enioy a more libertie, ſhe was rounded, crowned, and veſted in Saint Ieſus habit, and ſo continewed many yeares, in ſort as a Nouice. In Anno. 1569. a gentlemans ſonne of the Citie, accuſtomed to come among them, happened to breake a glaſſe Windowe, belonging to thys holye Father: who layde hande vpon him for it, had him in, &amp; hanged the poore childe by the hoeles, with as many ſcourges, as he and his darling coulde (in charitie) beſtow vpon him. Which known to the Father, deſirous to be reuenged of the harme done to hys ſonne (without any threats) he inuited them to ſupper: who being arriued, and entertayned into ſundrye places of the houſe (attending in hope, the time of theyr good cheare) they were at laſt brought into a greate chamber where certaine gallants wer ready to receiue them of purpoſe to performe the pleaſure of theyr maiſter: who after they had vſed a

long admonition, touching the iniurie done to hym and hys Chyld, they did read our Ieſuit ſuch a whipping Chapter from the heade to the héeles, and baſted him ſo on bothe ſides for burning, as they toke his ſtomacke cleane from hys ſupper. And when they wente about (wyth the ſame leſſon) to teach hys Nouice to ſpell and to put togyther: our olde leachor on both hys knées entreated for hym, offering to ſuffer as much more (though it were painefull to hym) ſo they would ſpare him. Notwithſtanding, ſeeing hee was a partner at the childes puniſhmente, they ſtripped hym, whereby the myſterye of hys lewde life was diſcouered: whyche being deliuered to iuſtice, he boldlye, and ſhameleſlye aunſweared, it is written that it is not good for a man to be alone, and therefore he hadde choſen hyr for his companyon.
            By thys is ſhewed not alone the order of theyr liues being a principle of theyr profeſſion, and a generall rule to all of their Courte: but alſo it manyfeſteth theyr ſhameleſſe doyngs, adding ſinne to ſinne (by blaſphemie) applying the Scripture to theyr beaſtly &amp; more than abhominable behauiour.
            A Widowe of greate wealthe in Padua, hauing one 
                  Apo. Ste. Fo. 308. of this cloth and colour to hir cōfeſſor, in whoſe holineſſe ſhe repoſed the whole hap of hir age, as wel for the good opiniō ſhe had in him (for theſe fellowes haue the fetche according to the ſuttlety of the firſt Serpente to creepe into the conſciences of women) as for the deuotion ſhe bare to his order. Thys gentlewoman on a time, bemoned hyr ſelfe vnto him, ſhewing howe hyr greateſt c
                  •
               re was, for ye marriage of hir daughter, hir only chylde. He who had for al paymēts his aunſwere ready coyned ſayde: ſurely Miſtreſſe I thinke your motion happeneth verye well: for God who forſéeth the petitions of the iuſt, euen as he ſent his Angel Raphael to Tobias, ſo hathe hée broughte me a ſpeciall Huſbande for your daughter, and ſuch a one as your own hart would wiſhe or deſire. For I aſſure you, I haue nowe in

my hands, the moſte honeſt yong gentleman of all Italie: who hathe heretofore ſéene your daughter, loueth hir perſon, and greatly commendeth hir behauiour: ſo, as thys daye (being in the beſte parte of my prayers) this gentleman moued by the holye Ghoſte (as he tolde me) came to craue my counſel, and declared the good affection he hathe to marrie wyth hyr. And I that knowe hys houſe, hys friendes, and himſelfe, to be of a fayre liuing, promiſed to ſpeake vnto you of it. This Ieſuit, or this Sathan in the ſhape of a man, to auoyde ſuſpition, the cunninger to carrie at befo
                  •
               e him, and with the more fineneſſe to abuſe this poore widowe: did affirme his worthineſſe euerye waye, if one inconuenience, were not the let to ſo good a motion, and that none in the Cittie dyd knowe of it but hymſelfe. Whiche was, where he would haue ſuccoured his friend, that another ſoughte to murder, he drewe his Rapier, meanyng onlye to parie them, and it happened his friend to kil hys aduerſarie: wherfore he (although he ſtrucke neuer a ſtroke) is fledde from hys Countrey, bycauſe he aſſiſted the manſlayer. And by the Councel of his friends, he is retyred to this Citie, in ye habit of a ſcholler, where hée meaneth to continewe vnknowne, vntil hys kindered and friendes haue taken order in the matter for his libertie, whiche hée 
                  •
               op
                  •
               th will bée verie ſhortelye: So that for this reaſon, if you like of the partye vppon my faythfull perſwaſion, the marriage muſte be made in as ſecrete ſorte as maye 
                  •
               e: and withall, you muſte be contente in the day, to ſuffer hym to repayre to the common Lectures, the more to couer the ſuſpition: And euery night to the comfort of you and your daughter, hée ſhall accompanye you to your beſt pleaſure. The good gentlewoman, who was eaſily bewitched to beléeue theſe counterfaite Gods, thought hir daughter better prouided for, than ſhe coulde otherwiſe by any mean deuiſ
                  •
               : 
                  •
                therfore toke ſo great pleaſure to heare the deuiſe (according to ye p
                  •
               ouerb: It is eaſie to deceiue the ſimple and true meaner) as vppon thoſe conditions, thys

Minion was brought, and they fianced the ſame day: and after midnight (for the more haſt to receiue of the olde woman fiue hundred duckats in lieu of hir daughters dower, which like falſe harlots they parted without any broker) he ſaide Maſſe and marryed them: after which marriage, they liued a certaine tyme together with equall contentment, to the great comfort of hir mother, who highly thanked God and hir confeſſor, for the good happe of hir daughter. But in the end, a Dominus vobiſcum (pronounced by this For all other were in reſpect but beggers to theſe Ieſuites. honeſt young Gentleman, who was both a Iewe, a Ieſuit, and a Prieſt) ſo diſcouered the matter, as their knauerie began to appeare in their kinde: for this newe married wife following the deuotion ſhe bare to this proude profeſſion, waiting on hir mother to heare Maſſe at their Couent, euen as this companion turned to ſay Dominus vobiſcum, ye poore young womā, ſtoode more aſtonied than a founder of Bels. And after ſhe had a little recouered the extacie that this ſodaine ſight brought hir into: ſhe ſhewed hir mother plainely that he which ſaid Maſſe was hir huſband, or at the leaſt one that reſembled him muche. The olde woman making very daungerous to heare it, woulde not be perſuaded that any ſuch mockerie coulde be committed by thoſe that were ſo holy, accounting it the greateſt ſinne that might bée, to haue ſo harmefull a thought of them: and therefore ſought to remoue that damnable opinion from hir daughter. But the Ite miſſa est, manifeſted the whole miſchiefe, for then it did not alone confirme ye daughters feare, but it alſo brought a doubtfull imagination to hir mother: notwithſtanding ſhe ſuſpended hir earneſt beliefe, vntill ſhe might ſée more proofe of it: and therefore ſhe concluded, that at night when he ſhould come to lie with his wife, the mother ſhould (as it were in a ieſt) holde both his handes, whileſt the daughter pulled of his coife, which practized and performed accordingly, they found his crowne faire ſhauen, that bewrayed the knauerie. Then there was no more queſtion whether he were a Prieſt, but they both bethought, how they might

be reuenged of ſo great an iniurie, for ſhe was robbed, hir daughter ſpoiled, &amp; both infamed, and all by the lewd abuſe of hir confeſſor, for whom ſhe preſently ſent, faining to haue ſome great ſecrete to ſhewe him. And calling hir friendes vnto hir, they apprehended them both, and deliuered them to iuſtice: who quitted them on eaſie conditions, for Temporall Iudges durſt not lay violent hand vppon ſo ſacred a profeſſion, they had ſo bewitched the worlde, and ſo blinded the eyes euen of the greateſt Princes, as they forced of no fault, for their ſuperſtitious &amp; proude tyrannie was euer a bulwarke to all their villanie, which they onely preſumed on, by the authoritie of their Popiſh libertie, as this example doth manifeſt the ſame.
            ACurate of Clauenie, in the Dutchie of Guyen, did ſéeke to 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 172. ſubborne the daughter of an honeſt man of the ſame towne, to his lewd iuſt &amp; pleaſure, whom he haunted in all places where ſhe went, notwithſtanding ſhe ſtill flatly &amp; conſtantly denied him, which bred the greater fire to his beaſtly deſire. And therefore one day the maide going to hir Fathers Farme (ſomwhat out of the towne) this Minion maſked in blew ſarſnet, ſet al ouer with little ſtarres of golde, hauing a fine Lawne ouer his face, &amp; his armes and legges bare, but couered likewiſe with Lawne, in this atfire he appeared vnto hir on the way, &amp; (with a counterfeit voyce) ſhewed hir, yt he was the virgin Marie, declaring vnto hir, howe ſundry afflictions ſhould fal on ye towne, for the Lutheran hereſie yt was entred among thē (againſt which this Prieſt was a great Preacher) wt ſundry other purpoſes, touching ye ſame, and further willed hir to ſhew it to ye towne, that they might celebrate hir feaſt with faſting &amp; prayer, telling hir withal how ſhe had refuſed ye friendſhip &amp; loue of a holy perſon, who in the ſame place (not long before) made ſute vnto hir, for yt ſhe denied him: and therfore if he ſought any thing at hir hands hereafter, yt ſhe ſhould obey him, &amp; there would great happineſſe followe hir by it: charging hir that ſhée ſhoulde not diſcouer this laſte parte to anye Creature.

The ſimple wench beléeued all for truth, and deliuered it as a propheſie, to forewarne them of that ſhoulde happen to Clauenie: for the which cauſe (at the firſt) the inhabitantes feared much: &amp; in the meane time this poore ſoule yéelded to his villanie, which was ſhortly after ſpyed, the practize diſcouered, and he executed, as well worthie.
            In a village neare vnto Coignacke called Shernes, the perſon 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 318. there abuſed his owne Siſter ſo long, as in the ende he gat hir with child: which the Curate ſo couered, as ſhe (being holden verie holy, through hir déepe hipocriſie) was taken to be as chaſt a virgin as might be: and therefore when this fault was ſpied, he ſhamed not to publiſhe, that it procéeded of the Holy Ghoſt, and that ſhe was a ſecond virgin Marie: the brute whereof comming to the hearing of Erle Charles of Angoleme, he ſent of purpoſe to ſée how it was, for that he ſuſpected ſome abuſe in it: in whoſe preſence the ſuppoſed virgin (of ye age of. 13. yéeres) being ſolemnly charged by hir brother vpon the damnation of hir ſoule, to deliuer them the truth (repeating the ſecond time the ſame admiration) ſhe anſwered, I take this holy Sacrament to my damnation before you all here preſent, that neuer any man did carnally knowe me, or in that ſort of ſinne touch me, no more than you my brother haue done: they hearing ſo vehement a vowe, returned and confirmed the ſhameleſſe report that was afore: but the Erle being wiſe, and noting the order of hir othe nearer than they did, founde the fire by the ſmoke, and therefore ſent againe, commanding they ſhoulde be ſeuerally committed, and ſeuerally examined, whereby the truth was confeſſed, and they both altred into aſhes and dedicated to Vulcan. An example of a horrible inceſt ioyned with blaſphemie, which witneſſeth among ye reſt of theſe hiſtories, the continent and chaſt liues of thoſe that were vowed from Matrimonie, approuing the godly furie of the Cardinal of Tournon, who hearing that a Biſhop was ſecretely married, ſaide, I maruell how theſe villaine Lutherans haue giuen themſelues to all the diuels to marrie,

ſéeing they haue libertie otherwiſe at liking, to ſatiſfie their luſt at their owne pleaſure, which he generally ſpake of all thoſe that liued then of their holye mother Churche. For what was it, thoſe wretches would not attempt, to perform (after their inſaciat gluttonie) their beaſtlike &amp; tompwood lecherie, hauing this priuiledge, Si non castè, tamen cautè.
            
            A Frier in Paris, hauing part of his lewd life ſo knowne 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 509. as ſome common ſpéeches went of it, ſhamed not (in his ſermon) to ſay, my Miſtriſſes of S. Martins I am ſo great a mote in your eye, that you prattle of me in euerie place, and for a matter that is leſſe than nothing? Ah good Ladie, is it ſo ſtraunge a caſe, for a holy Frier, to get his Hoſtis daughter with childe? I am glad it was no worſe, for I perceiue you would haue made it a more wonder, if ſhe had gotten me with childe. Oh ſhameleſſe ſort of Sodomits, that would ſo abhominably abuſe the place prepared to preache ye word of God in: but howe could you deliuer better matter from you, when there was no better ſubſtance in you.
            As is further manifeſted by the example of a Prieſt of 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 545. 
               Orleance, who hauing his concubine in a ielouſie, called hir to a Tauerne, where after he had ſhewed hir the countenance of continuall friendſhip, in his good cheare: he dyd leade hir into a priuie Chamber, where laying hir vppon a bed, with a razer (that he brought for ſo wicked a purpoſe) he cut hir throte, for the which murther he was onely condemned to perpetuall priſon.
            A ſearcher of Venice, ſéeing two Friers goe a borde a ſhip 
                  Fol. 254. with a fardell or ſmall packe, he ſuppoſing it had bin ſome forbiddē Marchādize or elſe ſome goods vncuſtomed (which ought by their lawe to be forfeited) he woulde néedes ſée, what it was they carried. But the Friers (contending with him) would not ſuffer him by no meanes to open it, vntyll by force he was faine to vndoe it himſelfe, wherein he found the heades of two men newly cut off, which was ſodainely ſhut vp, after they had enchaunted a worde or two into the ſearchers eares, notwithſtanding the matter being after

known it, made a queſtiō whether thoſe wares were cuſtomable or no. Such was the ſecret Merchandize of theſe holy fathers, &amp; one of the chiefeſt cōmodities they gathered their treaſure by. And further, to proue their tyrannous minds, ye beſt mean they had to hold al ye world in feare of thē) &amp; at whoſe hands ther was no redreſſe, except it were ſought at the Sea of Rome) I will tell you of an vnthankful and trayterous Prelate, excéeding any ſpoken of before.
            The Duke of Limburge deceaſſing without heires, there 
                  Fo. 346. grewe great warres betwéen the Duke of Brabant and the Count of Gelderland, which of them ſhould enioy the ſame, both claiming to be next in ſucceſſiō to it. In ye end, fortune gaue the Duke of Brabant the victorie, who tooke the Byſhoppe of Collen priſoner, (for that he had ayded the Count againſte him) and deliuered hym in cuſtodie to the Earle of Mounte in Henault, where he was kepte captiue ſeauen yeares, vntill he hadde yéelded to all ſuche conditions as the Duke demaunded of him. After the Biſhoppe was deliuered, he requeſted the Count to accompanie hym to Tuits, a village ioyning to the Rhene, ouer againſt Collen, the which he granted to willingly. But as they paſſed the Bridge ouer the Rhene, the Counte miſtruſting no falſhoode in his holineſſe, was taken by a certaine ambuſh of horſſemen, that the Biſhoppe had appointed there for that purpoſe. And to acquit the Counties curteſie, &amp; good entertainment (whiche was euery waye as honorable as might be) he cauſed a Cage of yron to be made, and ſet it in the Sunne: And after, annointing the pore Prince ouer with hony, forced him naked to enter into it, where hée long time endured the greateſt languor and torment in the worlde, with ſwarmes of flies that dayly fed on hym, and in this ſorte, with paine and famine ended his miſerable life. Thys was the Biſhoppes crueltie (a vowed Prelate to the Pope) ioyned with treaſon: excelling the tyranny of Bucris and Phalaris. 
               
                  Apo. Ste. Fo. 347.
            
            An other Biſhop of Collen named Henry, hauing Count

               Frederike his captiue, cauſed him to be brokē vpō a whéele, his legs, his thighes, his armes, his backe, and his necke, 
                  Apo. Ste. Fo. 347. and after laid him out to be a pray to Rauens.
            There were two Canons in Collen, that vnder the coulour of great friendſhip, inuited a Lorde of the ſame Citie 
                  Fo. 436. to dinner (named Harman Grin) whom notwithſtanding they mortally hated. And ſéeming in courteſie to ſhew him a lion (which they noriſhed for the honor of their Biſhop,) they trayterouſlye trained him into the Cage, where the beaſt was, to be deuoured: But the gentleman ſéeing himſelfe brought into ſuche daunger, tooke courage vnto him: And wrapping his cloake aboute his lefte arme, thruſte it into the Lyons throate, and with his right hand drew out his dagger, and killed him: whereby he ſaued himſelfe, and the treaſon diſcouered.
            In the time of the Emperour Otton the great, the Biſhop of Magence ſéeing the famine that fell in the Countrie, 
                  Fo. 347. had ſuch a compaſſion on the pore, as he aſſembled a great number of them into a Barne, (the poore ſoules hoping to haue had ſome reliefe at the hands of his holineſſe in that time of penurie) which he cauſed to be ſet on fyre, &amp; burned them al, affyrming, that they were but as Rattes and Mice in a common wealth, that deuoured the graine, &amp; ſerued to no purpoſe. A charitable tyrannie, procéeding from a godly care of a Popiſhe deuotion, withoute anye cauſe or occaſion of reuenge, for the miſerable creatures deſerued no harme of him.
            I had almoſte forgotten a certaine Ieſuite in Viena in 
                  Apo. Ste. Fo. 317. 
               Austrie, who made it no conſcience to abuſe a merchantes wife (whome he had vnder confeſſion) before al the Saints of eyther kinde, not ſimply in the Church, but behinde the high aultar, and on good friday, who being taken with the manner (althoughe the faulte deſerued as vile a death as might bée deuiſed) yet he was only enioyned for penance, to forbeare the ſaying of Maſſe thrée moneths: which their Legate (comming from Rome) thoughte it ſo ſharpe a puniſhment,

as he preſently abſolued him of it. Whoſe ordinarie Maſſes were after founde of as good ſauour, taſt, and digeſtion (to thoſe that willingly deuoured thē) as if they had bin ſaid of the moſte maydenlieſt Prieſt in the world. So as, if one would ſearch the euils of all ſortes, committed by theſe rauening rabble that fed on the Churche, hée ſhoulde finde them innumerable. But, as touching theyr puniſhments, it was ſeldome, or for the moſt part ſo light, that it ſéemed (indéede) but a mockerie. Where, on the other ſide, if any were only ſuſpected to couet the true way to their ſaluation, fire and ſworde was layde vpon them, with al the rigor and violence that might be.
            Was it not a pitiful condition, that the pore members of Chriſte dwelled in, when they were as faine (and with as muche feare) to hide themſelues in caues, corners, and other deſolate places, for reading of the Bible and ye new Teſtament: as thoſe that carryed counterfaite money, or committed a worſer crime. For, whoſoeuer was taken with Gods Booke (the onely Pilote to the Porte of oure redemption) eyther in his hande, or in his houſe, hée was ſure to ſuffer death without al fauour (ſpecially) if the holy Ghoſt confirmed him in it. But ſuch was the ſubſtance of his bleſſed worde, and the heauenly fruits of the ſame: as the more they perſecuted, the more zealous profeſſors, and faithful willing Martyres encreaſed by it. For, as our Sauiour Chriſte ſaith, they helde the keyes of knowledge from vs, neither entring themſelues, nor would ſuffer others to enter by them: By whych their willing and wilful blindeneſſe, bothe the one and the other fell into the bottomleſſe Pitte of euerlaſting darkeneſſe: yet in their Pulpittes (to féede the ſimplicitie of the tyme) they would giue vs part of the Texte, enlarged by their owne gloſes. And therfore to approue their learning to their lynes, and theyr liues to the learning of thoſe forefathers, vppon whoſe doctrine the Papiſtes depend, although I haue already ſaide ſufficient, to terrifie the ſtowteſt, to reclaime

the fainteſt, and to winne the weakeſt in conſcience, if Gods grace haue not vtterly abandoned them: yet I wil Menot. Maleard. bring in place for their better credite, Oliuer Maleard a Frenchman, and Mychell Menot an Italian, two of the moſte famous, renowmed, and learned preachers in their time. Whoſe Paraphraſe (or rather ſporting toyes) vppon ſundrie textes of the Scripture, worde for worde (firſte in Latine, and Engliſhe mingled, as my Author in Latine and Frenche hathe pelmelled) euen as I haue read it, ſo I ſimply here deliuer it.
            As for example, we reade in the new Teſtament how Marie Magdalene acknowledged hir ſin, waſhed Chriſtes féete with teares, and dryed them with hir haire, &amp;c. which they haue by their gloſing diſcourſe, framed into a monſtrous 
                  Mathew the 27. Chap.
                forme, as followeth.
            
               Quoad primum Magdalena, erat domina terrena, de castro Magdalen, tam ſapiens quod erat mirum audire loqui de ſapientiaeius 
               
                  Ser. Me. Fol. 160. 
               &amp; prudentia: O ergo Magdalena, quo modo venistis ad tantum inconueniens, quod vocemini magna peccatrix? Et non ſine cauſa: quod fuistis male conſiliata. Data est tribus conſiliarijs, qui eum poſuerunt in tali ſtatu: Scilicet primus, corporalis elegantia: ſecundus temporalis ſubstancia: tertius fuit libertas nimia. Primum ergo, quid fuit cauſa huius mulieris perdicionis? Fuit elegantia corporalis. Videbatur pulchra, iuuenis, alta. Credo quod non erat niſi 15. aut 16. annorum quando incepit ſic viuere, &amp; 30. quando redijt ad bonitatē Dei. Quando pater fuit mortuus, plena erat ſua voluntate. Martha ſoror nō audebat dicere ei verbum, &amp; videbatur ei quod faciebat magnum honorem illis qui veniebant ad illam. Quicquid faciebat erat viuere at hir owne pleaſure, and to make banquets, and good cheare Hodie inuitare, &amp;c. And within a little while after this poore foole abandoned erat in castro ſuo: The rumor ran throughe all Iurie, and the country of Galelie, Omnino bibendo &amp; comedendo, loquebatur de eo, &amp; de eius vita. Martha ſoror timens Deum &amp; amans honorem of hir houſe, aſhamed of the ſhame of hir ſiſter, videns quod omnes loquebantur of hir ſiſter, and of hir

myracles, venit ad eam dicens, O ſoror ſi pater adhuc viuer et qui tantum vos amabat, &amp; audiret ista quae per orbem agitantur de vobis, truely he woulde thruſte death into youre téethe. Facitis magnum dedecus progenij nostrae. And wherefore? quid vis dicere? Heu ſoror, non opus est vltra procedere, neque amplius manifestare. Scitis bene quid volo dicere, &amp; vbi iacet punctus. Why do you trouble your ſelfe good Gentlewoman? In all the great diuels name, God be prayſed, nonne estis magistra mea. Quis dedit mihi this valiant dame to controll my life. Vadatis precor ad domum vestram: ſcio quid habeo agerei ta bene ſicut vna alia. Habeo ſenſum &amp; intellectum to knowe howe to gouerne my ſelfe. This is a goodly matter, that I ſhoulde care for none but my ſelfe. Martha rogabat eam vt iret ad ſermonem, &amp; conſuleret aliquam hominem bonae vitae. Magdalena dixit Ianitori, non dimittas mihi intrare hoc castrum, this mad ſiſter of mine, that brings nothyng hither, but brawling, chiding, and vnquietneſſe, vbi non conſueuit niſi cantus gaudij. And after hée maketh a greate narration of the meanes that Martha made to haue hir come to the Sermon of our Lorde: not telling hir what, or who he was, but vſing alluring ſpéeches, ſaid he was a faire yong man, &amp; of a goodly perſonage: O ſoror eſſetis valde foelix, ſi poſſetis videre vnum hominem qui praedicat in Ieruſalem. Est pulchrior omnibus quos vnquam vidistis, tam gratioſus, tam honestus, he hath ſo faire a countenance, ſo good a grace, &amp; ſo goodly of body, you neuer ſaw his like. Credo firmiter ꝙſi videretis eum, eſſetis amoroſa de eo, est in flore iuuētutis ſuae. And a little after, illa coepit pulchra indumenta ſua, aquā roſaceā prolauando faciem ſuam: coepit ſpeculum. Videbatur quod eſſet vnus pulcher Angelus. Nullus eam aspexiſſet, qui non fuiſſet amoroſus de ea. Ipſa ante ſe miſit mangones portantes manye Cuſhions of Crimoſon veluet, vt disponerent ſibi locum. Martha videbat haec omnia, fingens nihil videre: &amp; ſequebatur eam ſicut ſi fuiſſet parua ancilla. Christus iam erat in media praedicatione, vel forte in ſecunda parte. After he ſawe howe they dydde honoure and reuerence to Magdalena, euerye one wondering to ſée

hir come to a Sermon, which when Chriſte perceiued, he beganne to preache, that pompe, pride, and brauerie, was a moſte deteſtable matter. Tunc (ſayde he) ipſe coepit deteſtare vitia, bragas, pompas, vanitates, &amp; ſpecialiter peccatum luxuriae: &amp; contra has mulieres, &amp;c. After this he reciteth how Magdalen was touched to the quicke with that ſhe hearde in this Sermon, and then thoughte on nothing ſo muche as on Repentaunce: yet was in daunger to be turned by hir companions and cuſtomers, and to be broughte to hir firſte courſe of life. venerunt (ſaide he) galandi amoroſi &amp; ruſtici, theſe Royſters qui dixerunt, Surgatis, ſurgatis: facitis nunc the hipocrite: vadamus ad domum. Quae dixit, O amici mei, rogo dimittatis me, non audistis quid dixit ille bonus praedicator de poenis inferni, vobis &amp; mihi preparatas niſi aliud faciamus? And a little after habebat in ſuo armariolo aquam of ſwéete ſmels, quae vendebatur pondere auri. Coepit querere de loco in locum, de platea in plateam, de domo in domum. Quis hodie dabit prandium praedicatori? Dictum est ei quod in domo Simonis. And then he ſetteth forth the Oration ſhée made before ſhée kiſſed Chriſtes féete, &amp; in the waſhing of thē with hir teares, and in the ende, howe ſhe lay vnder the table like a dog: and that our Lord ſaide: O Mary, I praye thée riſe: And that ſhe anſwered, I wil neuer remoue from this place, vntil thou haſte giuen me remiſſion for al my ſinnes, and your holy bleſſing. And then he ſaide, my loue, riſe, thy ſinnes are forgyuen thée, thy fayth hathe ſaued thée. And in the ende, he concluded howe Martha preſented Magdalena to the Virgine Mary: before whome ſhée fell on hir knées, and ſaide, good Madam pardon me if it pleaſe you, that I may ſpeake to you, I haue bin of an euil life, and a great ſinner, but now by the grace of God I will doe no more ſo. Your ſon hath this day forgiuen me: Lord, how happy are you to haue ſuch a ſon. Here you may ſée how this gentle preacher hath diſciphered this hiſtory, making of the Scriptures a ſhippemans hoſe, or a tale of Robin Hood.
            
            
               
But now let vs looke into the ſubſtance of Maleard, who hath with no leſſe grauitie &amp; wiſdome paraphraſed vppon the hiſtorie of the forlorne ſon in the 15. chapter of S. Luke than our Menot hathe done afore: which text he hathe enriched with al ſortes of circumſtances forged of pleaſure, &amp; couched with terms, rather for laughter, thā for educatiō, as foloweth.
            
               Pater quidam habebat duos filios, quorum iunior ſe ostendit 
               
                  Ser. Me. Fol. 119. 
               magis fatuum, quia inconstans fuit. This was a childe of his owne pleaſure, light headed, a minion, and a royſting gallant. Ipſe erat vnus puer, plenus ſuo velle, verſatilis &amp;c. qui quando venit ad cognoſcendum ſeipſum, ſuā fortitudinem, ſuam iuuentutem, ſuam pulchritudinem, &amp; quod ſanguis aſcendit frontem, his ſtrength, his youth, his beautie, and that the bloude beganne to riſe in his forehead, venit ad patrem reſolutus ſicut Papa, &amp; dixit ei, Pater da mihi, &amp;c. Pater ſumus tantùm duo filij: ego non ſumbastardus: &amp; ſic, quando placeret deo, to doe ſo muche for your children, to take you oute of thys worlde, non exhaeredaretis me, ſed haberem partem meam ſicut frater meus. Scio conſuetudines &amp; leges patriae, quodte viuente nullum ius habeo in bonis vestris: tamen ſum filius vester, &amp; me amatis rogo detis, &amp;c. When this fooliſhe childe, and euill counſelled habuit ſuam partem de haereditate, non erat quaestio de portando eam ſecum, ideo ſtatim he ſent for a Broker, priſed it, and ſolde it, &amp; ponit the ſale in ſua burſa. Quando vidit tot pecias argenti ſimul, valde gauiſus est, &amp; dixit ad ſe, ho, non manebitis ſic ſemper, Incipit ſe respicere. Et quomodo? vos estis de tam bono domo, &amp; est aparelled like a pore knaue? Super hoc habebitur prouiſio. Mittit ad querendum Drapers, Embrotherers, Mercers, and brauely apparelled hymſelfe from the head to the foote. Quando vidit, emit ſibi pulchras caligas of Scarlet, faire drawne forthe with Satten, a fine ſhirte gallauntlye gathered at the collar, and a minion dublet of Veluet wyth hys Ierkin of Florence ſilke, and hys haire paynted. Et quando ſenſit this Damaſke to rattle aboute hys ſhoulders, and to flée vppon hys backe,

               vt ſenſit hunc damaſcum volātem ſupra dorſum, haec ſecum dixit, Oportetne mihi aliquid? non &amp;c. Doe I lacke any thing? no, thou haſte al thy feathers. And after he ſheweth howe hée ſaide hée muſte goe ſée the worlde, and that thoſe, who neuer were out of the armes of their mothers, were no better than dolts and patches. And to be briefe, he that hathe not frequented ſtrange countries, nihil vidit. My father hath layde the raines of my bridle on my necke, pater meus laxauit habenam ſupra collum. And then he reciteth howe as he trauelled by the way, he made banquets and good cheare to euerie man, and that he kepte a rounde Table, hauing euery day in his Innes, players, Iuglers, &amp; Tomblers. And in the ende, Postquam nihil amplius erat fricādū, when there was no more to ſpend: mittitur pulchra vestis domini bragātis, caligae, bombicinium: quiſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  ſecum ferebat peciā
                of oure young Maiſters pride, of hoſe and dublets euerye one carryed away his parte: ita quod in breui tempore, oure gallant was made like a gatherer of Aples, and apparelled as a burner of houſes, or a chimney ſwéeper: For hée was left as naked as my naile, and as nigh worne to the ſkinne as a worme, hauing hardely a ſhyrte to couer hys poore carcaſſe with, whych was as bright as a gammon of Bacon, or like a Lincke new put out, he had ſo wiſely gouerned and vſed his proſperitie by hys pride, pompe, and glorie. And further, to proue his wit, as one that was neuer without matter to pleaſe his audience: he courſeth and diſcourſeth a gallant gloſe on the euangeliſt of S. Mathew 
               
                  Chap. 14. where the Apoſtle ſayth he fed 5000. perſons, &amp;c. the ſame Maliard paraphraſing vpō it, affirmeth, that where ye text doth teſtifie of 5000. men beſides women &amp; childrē: it muſt néeds folow, that the number was much greater. And firſt he compareth it to the dinner of a Lymoſin, who commonly do eat much, but drink little. Then he maketh a queſtion, where Chriſt learned to prepare his dinner: adding, that he ſuppoſed he had not frequented the Banquettes of Paris, where they do not forget to drincke with theyr meate.

And after he argueth whether it were not in Lent, bycauſe euerie one did eate as much fiſhe as he would: and where Chriſt did ſhewe his firſt myracle in a marriage to prouide wine and no bread, ſo nowe he prepared bread and no wine: wherein he commendeth the wiſedome and good huſbandry of Chriſt, for that he kept a rounde table for all commers, it is not mentioned that the Virgin Marie was there, for I beléeue (ſayde he) if ſhe had bin preſent, ſhe would haue remembred him as ſhe did at the marriage, ſaying, they haue no wine, &amp; ſéeing they féed with ſo good a ſtomacke, it is pitie they lacke drinke to moyſten their meate with: and truely it is not for your reputation, credite, nor honor, to call ſuch a companie togither and giue them no wyne: but (ſaid he) if any would make queſtion why our Sauiour prouided not drinke, aſwell as meate, I woulde be his Atturney, and anſwere: Propter aquarum aproximationem, miraculi maiorem declarationem, Sacramenti Eucharistiae praefiguratio: that is, For that the water being at hand, he woulde the better declare the myracle, prefiguring the Sacrament of the Euchariſt: ſo it is written, they were by the Sea of Galile, &amp; ſat vpon faire and ſwéete graſſe: ſo as when they had eaten their fil, they might goe drinke as much as they liſt. I could haue enlarged this place if I had followed ye groſſe courſe of Maliard, but this is more than ſufficient, to ſhew how they vſed both abrupfly and abſurdlye to ieſt with the ſacred Scriptures, prophaning them at their doltiſhe pleaſures. And further 
                  Barrelet. Fol. 367. 
               Barrelet affirmed, that rather than Chriſt ſhoulde not haue bin crucified, Marie his mother would haue crucified him with hir owne handes, for (ſaid he) there was no leſſe charitie in hir, than there was in Abraham, who was readie and prepared to kill his onely ſonne. And bycauſe it may ſéeme incredible that any woulde be ſo lewde to deliuer in their Sermons ſo blaſphemous ſpéeches, I wil ſet it downe word for worde as he himſelfe did both preache it and write it. Quia temporepaſſionis, quanuis ſuae dolores eſſent intenſi, videndo 
               
                  Serm. fol. 115. Coloſ. 2. 
               filium afligi, tamen volebat filium ſuum mori prohumanae generationis
               
               ſalute Et vt dicit Archiepiſcopus, Si alius modus non fuiſſet ipſamet filium proprium occidiſſet. Quia non minor erat charita
                     •
                  
                
               
                  M
                        •••
                     t affirmeth the ſame fol. 169. Coloſ. 3. Fo. 367. 
               ſua, quam Abrahae qui filium ſuum erat paratus occidere.
            
            And the ſame Preacher ſheweth how the Apoſtles came to Marie, ſaying, ho, thy ſonne did promiſe to ſend the holye Ghoſt among vs, &amp; now it is tenne dayes ſince he aſcended, &amp; we heare nothing of him. To whom ſhe anſwered, doubt not but this day he will ſend him, &amp;c. And theſe are his owne words, Vnde isto maneiad Maria veniunt, dicentes, Heu filius tuus nobis promiſit mittere ſpiritum Sanctum, hodie ſunt decem dies quod aſcendit, &amp; adhuc ſpiritum Sanctum non miſit. Et virgo, non dubitetis quod hodie omnino mi
                     •
                  tet, nec ante mittere debuit. Et ration, Quando Deus traxit populum de captiuitate Aegipti, quinquageſimo die deſcendit informa ignis in monte Sinn, dando legem, fuit figura quod quinquageſimo die reſurrectionis ſuae, nos liberaret &amp; viuificaret. Vnde ponamus nos in oratione. Petrus cum alijs ſe ad vnam partem poſuit: Lazarus cum. 72. ad aliam, &amp; Magdalena cum alijs mulieribus ad aliam, &amp; virgo Maria in medio. In caeleſti palatio facta est diſſentio inter Patrem &amp; ſpiritum Sanctum. 
               
                  Serm. Bar. Fo. 178. Coloſ. 1. Apo. Ste. Fol. 368. 
               O Pater (inquit Filius) promiſi Apostolis m
                     •
                  is paracletū &amp; conſolatorem, tempus aduenit vt promiſſionem attendā. Cui Pater, ſum contentus, indica ſpiritui Sancto. Cui ſpiritus Sanctus, Dic mihi quomodote tractauere. Cui filius vide me per charitem, ostendit ei lat us &amp; manus &amp; p
                     •
                  des perforatos. Heu mihi. Sed vadam in aliā effigiem, quod non and
                     •
                   bunt me tangere. Qui diſcendit cum magno ſtrepitu. Factus est de c
                     •
                  lo ſonus tanquam aduenientis, &amp;c.
            
            I muſt deſire the patient reader, to heare a little further of this Preachers blaſphemie, more incredible than ye reſt, wherein he doth prophane the principalleſt myſterie of our Chriſtian religion. And is, Quamuis ab aeterno Deus praedestinauerit, 
               
                  Serm. Bar. Fo. 229. Coloſ. 4. 
               &amp;c. Although (ſaith he) that God of his eternall power, did at ye firſt predeſtinate ye Incarnation of his Sonne, &amp; the ſaluation of mankind, yet he would (notwithſtanding) that ye ſame ſhould be ſought at his hands, by the prayers of vs, &amp; of other the holy Patriarkes, ſo as the holy fathers wt teares deſired ye day, which is manifeſtly ſhewed vs in the

ſcriptures, as by Adam, Eno, Enoch, Mathuſalem, Lamech, &amp; Noe (who liued euery one of them ſo long time) &amp; yet could
                  •
                not obtaine that they ſo much looked for, and therefore deſiring to haue an abſolute reſolutiō, they ſent their Embaſſadors, as firſt Eſai, who ſaith in his. 16. Chapter Lorde ſende downe the Lamb yt ſhall gouerne the world, (for he writeth Agnum dominatorem terrae) &amp; in his. 45. Chap. you heauens ſend downe your deaw vpon vs, &amp;c. And the. 4. Chapter, O that thou wouldeſt breake the heauens and come downe. And after the Prophetes they ſent Moyſes, Exod. 4. Chap. Obſecro Domine mittere quem miſſurus es. I pray thee (O Lord) ſend him whō thou wilt ſend, which is as much to ſaye (according to his gloſe) thou haſt ſent me before, but this is but for a particular deliuerance, ſend nowe I pray thée for a generall deliuerance. Then the kings ſent Dauid, who ſpake thus, Lord ſhew vnto vs thy mercy, and graunt vs thy ſaluation. Aaron came after all theſe and was ſente by the Prieſtes, who ſaide, O Lorde bow downe the heauens and deſcend among vs. And laſt of all came the Churche, which ſaid, lift vp thy puiſance &amp; might, and come (O Lord) lift vp thy ſelfe. And when theſe Patriarkes coulde not obtaine 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 369. their requeſts, they ſent women to be petitioners for them. The firſt was Madam Eue, who vſed theſe ſpeeches: Thou haſt condemned vs for our ſinne, but thou (O Lorde) haſt no reſpect there vnto, deliuer me out of this darke and obſcure priſon: to whom God anſwered, Eue thou haſt ſinned, and therfore not worthy of my Sonne. The ſecond was Madam Sara, who ſaid, O Lord helpe vs: to whom God anſwered, thou art not worthye, for thou waſt harde of beliefe, touching thy Sonne Iſaak. The thirde was Madam Rebecca: to whome God ſayd, thou ſhe wedſt thy ſelfe partiall betwéene Iacob and Eſau. The fourth was Madam Iudith: to whome God anſwered, thou waſt a murtherer. The fifth Madam Heſter: to whome he ſayde thou diddeſt (by thy glorie) loue vanitie too much, when thou ſo ſumptiouſly apparelledſt thy ſelfe to pleaſe Aſſuerus.
            
            
               
In the end, they ſent a waiting maide of ye age of fourtéen Yeeres, whoſe countenance was lowly and verie ſhamefaſt, who vpon hir knées ſaide, let my welbeloued come into his garden, and eate of the fruite of the Orchard: The garden, was the wombe of the Virgin. The ſonne hearing theſe wordes, ſayde to his Father, Father I haue loued this Virgin from my youthe, and haue hitherto ſearched the meanes to haue hir for my Spouſe. At the which inſtant, God called Gabriell, and ſayd, goe thy wayes with ſpéede to Nazareth to Marie, and carrie hir this preſent and theſe letters from me: and tell hir that I haue choſen hir for my Spouſe. And the Sonne ſayd, commende me to hir, and tell hir from mée, that I haue choſen hir for my mother, and that I will take fleſhe of hir entrailes, &amp; I wil be hir ſonne, and delyuer hir theſe letters. After theſe two the holye Ghoſt ſpake: I will dwell in hir, and ſhée ſhall be my temple: and giue hir theſe letters from mée. Gabriell beyng come to hir, ſayde: Aue gratia plena, &amp;c. Shée hearing the 
                  Ser. Bar. Apo. Ste Fo. 370. Angel, was greatly troubled, and hauing thrée damſels in hir companie, Prudence, Virginitie, and Humilitie, ſhe adreſſed hir firſt to Prudence to haue hir councell: ſaying, my ſwéet companion, ſhew me your opinion, what I were beſt to doe: Prudence anſwered, Marie I conſider what is written in the. 29. Chap. of Eccle. that light beléeuing argueth an vnconſtant and w
                  •••
               ering heart. Marie thinking in hir ſelfe what this ſalut
                  •••
               n ſhould meane, remembred the. 32. Chap of Eccle. Audi tacens, &amp; pro reuerentia accedit tibi bono gratia, Hearken in ſilence, and for thy reuerence great good grace ſhall come vnto thee. The Angell ſéeing hir ſo troubled, ſayd vnto hir, Marie feare not, but ſhewe me the cauſe of your vnquiet, and I will ſatiſfie you. Marie aſked counſell of hir ſecond damſell, Virginitie, who willed hir to know of the Angell, the meane howe this childe ſhoulde be conceiued, for if he ſaye, it muſte bée by the ſéede of man, beate him out of the dores with a cudgell, ô Iunenculae quando veſtri amatores nominant impudica, &amp;c. Howe maye this bée,

ſéeyng I neuer knewe man? The Angell anſwered, the holy Ghoſt ſhall come vppon thée, &amp;c. And after he affyrmeth there grewe an argument or diſputation betwéene the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, who ſhoulde performe this redemption of mankinde: and in the ende, it was concluded, that it ſhoulde be the Son, and the reaſon why, &amp;c.
            If I maye in pardon praye the gentle Reader to haue ſo muche patience to peruſe this one parte more of theyr blaſphemy: I wil entreate him to reade thys diſcourſe of the ſame Preacher, for that it ſhal appeare, howe much it is like to himſelfe, and to all thoſe, that dwel in the obedience of the Churche of Rome: whereby he ſhall manifeſtly perceiue, how one error (or rather wylfull blaſphemie) draweth on an other. Where he ſaieth, Altercatio facta est 
               
                  Ser. Ber. Fol. 371. 
               quis debebatire ad matrem nuntiare hanc reſurrectione. Adam dixit mihi incumbit, &amp;c. The effecte and circumſtance wherof is thus. It was in controuerſie and contention, who ſhoulde goe to ſhew this reſurrection to Mary: Adam ſaid, this charge belongeth vnto me: for, as I was the firſte cauſe of euill, ſo nowe I woulde be a meſſenger to the contrarie: to whome Chriſte aunſwered, no, you ſhal not go, for it may be you wil ſtay by the way to eate Aples. Abell ſaide it belonged to him, no aunſwered Chriſte, for thou mayeſt by chaunce méete with Caine, who will kill thée. Noe likewiſe preſented himſelf to the ſeruice, ſaying that that honor was due to him: to whome Chriſte anſwered, thou ſhalt not go, bicauſe thou loueſt to drinke ouer much. Iohn Baptiſt requeſted the credite of that meſſage: No truely ſayde Chriſte, thy apparell is too baſe, for thy robe is only of ſkinnes, and Herode may happe to knowe thée againe. The Thiefe deſired to haue that office: Chriſte refuſed him, ſaying, thy legges he broken. So, in the ende, there was ſent an Aungel, who did ſing: Regina coelt laetare, alleluia, reſurrexit ſicut dixit: alleluya. And immediatelye Chriſte came with al his Saints to the Virgin Mary, &amp;c.
            
            
               
There are many more blaſphemous matters that were publiſhed and preached by theſe great Doctours: whoſe dā
               nable errors (like vnto Mahomets Alcaron among the Turks) had that credite then in the worlde, as it was death to reproue them or controll them. And as theſe Sorboniſts by theyr Romiſh authority, would ſcan the Scriptures to their own lyking, Metamorphoſing ye texts into what ſenſe or forme beſt pleaſed them, holding the world in that ignoraunce, as they beléeued all they ſayde to be the onely true &amp; vndoubted word of God: euen ſo the common ſort, choſing ye Pulpit as a place more to ſport in, than to profit the people, would fil vp time with all the vanities that might be.
            As a Preacher in the towne of Iper in Flaunders (named Bonauenture) ſhamed not to ſaye in hys Sermon, that after 
                  Apo. Ste Fol. 441. Chriſt grew to ſome ſtrength, Ioſeph beganne to teach him hys occupation. And one day among others, he ſette him to, ſaw a péece of Tymber, but Chriſt not regarding the mark he ſhould haue ſawed it by, he cutte it too ſhort: whereat Ioſeph was very angry and would haue beaten him, if he had not haſtily taken vp the one ende, and crauing hys Fathers helpe to holde the other, drew it out to the ſame length that Ioſeph woulde haue it, whiche the Monke iuſtifyed to bée true: and that he had read it in the Euangeliſte of Sainte Anne.
            
            Alſo a Frier (named Bardotte) preached at Burdeaux, the reaſon why God gaue to the good Théefe Paradice, and ye 
               
                  Fol. 441. cauſe that he went ſtraight thyther, without firſt paſſing to Purgatorie, for (ſayde he) I haue red in a certayn Euangeliſt, that when Chriſt was carryed to Egypt (with his mother by Ioſeph) the ſame Théefe would not ſuffer his companions to robbe Chriſt, nor any that was with him: And that he ſayde to Chriſte remember this good turne I haue done thée: which was then promiſed him, and performed, when they met both at one execution.
            Whereby you may ſée, that theſe holye Fathers coulde neuer lack good matter, hauing ſo many and ſo ſundry ſorts

of Euangeliſtes, as they liſted themſelues, taking out of ſome, pleaſant ſubſtance to make their Auditours merry: and out of others; ſome miraculous matter to bewitch thē with wonders: hauing withall, a readie reſolution for anye obiection ſhoulde be made vnto them. Yet ſuch whoſe ſimplicity deliuered the beſt Iewels they founde in the Treaſure houſe of theyr iudgemēt, were more to be borne with in reſpect of theyr ignorāce, than the cūning knauerie of thoſe, who not alone in words, but by ſhameles geſture and déeds prepared thēſelues of purpoſe to abuſe both place &amp; cōpany.
            As a Fryer in Bruxels layde a wager to make one halfe of his Auditours to wéepe, the other to laugh: For the whiche 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 480. purpoſe, he put on a garment that was very ſhorte behinde (and without anye bréeches) he entred the Pulpit vpon a good Friday: where in the middeſt of the Churche, he did ſo vehementlye ſet forthe the paſſion of Chriſt, that the whole aſſiſtaunce were in teares at the pitiful remembrāce of it. Which our fryer ſéeing, ye more to aggrauate the matter, layde hys hands a croſſe, and ſéeming to ſhew a great deuotion, he bowed his heade ſo lowe, and lifted hys tayle ſo hye, as he diſcouered his backeſide, prouoking al that ſaw it to laughter: a ſhameleſſe parte to winne a drunken wager, and a great blaſphemie to Gods glorie.
            A Monke of Mantua, named Coſſolaro: preaching the paſſion; 
                  Fol. 355. and ſéeing his audience to ſhed aboundance of teares, at his pitiful exclamations vppon the cruel death our ſauiour endured (after he had a whyle made a maygame of it) he ſayde, holde your peace good people, wéepe no more, peraduenture it was not true: affirming the blaſphemie of Pope Leo the tenth mentioned of afore.
            One Roullie a Monkepreached at Orlians, who in his ſermon 
                  Ap. Ste Fo. 485. (among other bad matter) ſaid to his audience, he wold ſhew them a Cuckold: and ſodainely ſtouping into the Pulpit, as though he would take vp ſomething, ſéemed at his riſing to caſt a ſtone among them, whereat they all doucked down with their heads. Oh fayde our deuoute Preacher.

I thought there hadde bin but one Cuckolde among you, where nowe I ſée you be all of one feather.
            A Ieſuite (by Baden in Germanie) preaching in a meddow, after he had mightily exclaimed againſte the Lutheranes, 
                  Fol. 485. he ſaide to his Auditors, that he greatly doubted, leaſte ſome of them were infected with that diueliſhe doctrine, and therefore deſyred them, that as manye, bothe men and women, as were not touched with that hatefull hereſie, but were indéede good Catholikes, euerye one to take a blade of graſſe in their mouths, for the loue and honor they bare to their mother holy Churche. Which when they had with gret deuotion done, he ſaid in a loud laughter: Since I was firſte borne I neuer ſaw ſo many beaſts paſture at one time togither. When they were in a chafe, or ſéemed to be impatient againſt their pariſhioners, they woulde not let to remember the Diuell vnto them: As witneſſeth one Fouet ſometime Vicar of Villers in Tartenois, who ſaide in his ſermon: Séeing you haue no more 
                  Fol. 485. regarde to the amendment of your liues, the Diuel take you all, and me after you. And alſo an other preaching to his Pariſhioners, ſaide: You make no accompte of that I teache you, but rather growe daylye worſe and worſe: 
                  Fol. 485. yet notwithſtanding, I haue cure of youre ſoules, which I woulde the Diuel had charge of, ſo I were ridde of you.
            And ſéeing I haue touched the charge that Curates haue of their Patiſhioners ſoules: I ſhoulde doe double wrong to forget one Fōtanus that ſometimes was Vicar of Peerrebuffiere, in high Lymoſine. For this good fellowe, the better to exhorte thoſe of his eure to liue well (among other graue ſentences) ſaid: When the latter day of Iudgement 
                  Fo. 485. is come, God (I knowe) wil haue me to make accompte for you, and wil cal me, Vicar of Peerrebuffiere, what haite thou done with thy ſhéepe? but I wil ſtande mute, and anſwere nothing: And this I am ſure he will ſay
                  •
                to mée thrée ſeuerall times, and I not a worde, yet in the ende I knowe what I wil anſwere, Beaſts thou didſt giue them

me, and beaſtes I reſtore them againe: which ſimple Hiſtorie hath not ſo good a grace in my tranſlation, as it hath in the proper Lymoſin language, wherein it is more liuely and more aptly couched than in Engliſh, and therfore I wil deliuer it you in his own nature: Quan ſe vendro louiour deu iugamen, Diou me demandero que you ly rendo compte de vou autre: &amp; me apelero, chapello de Peyrebuffiero, en qual eytat ſon ta olia? Et you ni mot. Et eu ma pelaro enquero, &amp; diro, chapelo de Peyrebuffiero, en qual eytat ſonta olio: Et you ni mot. Et eu ma pelero enquero eu mediro chapelode Peyrebuffiero en qual eytat ſon ta olio? Iuque a tre viage. Et you lyreypondray, Seigne, beytia la ma beylaaa, et beytia late rendi.
            
            A Monke at Bloyſe named Baſtianus preaching on Alhallonday 
                  Fo. 486. ſomewhat late, and in an obſcure place, cauſed hys Nouice (ſtanding behinde him) to lift vp the ſkul of a deade man (vppon a ſtaffe) with a little lighte in it, to the end to make his Auditours haue the greater feare of death: which put ſundry women in ſuche a fryght, as ſome there preſente (being with child) fel in ſtil trauel, at the feareful ſight of it.
            A Frier named by Eraſmus Robertus Licienſis hauing a louer allowed him, by the diſpenſation of Saint Frauncis, 
               
                  Fo. 481. who ſaide vnto him, that ſhe liked hys perſon, and all the reſt wel, ſauing his habite. What habit woulde you haue me weare (ſayde he) to performe youre whole liking towards me? ſhe anſwered, the apparell of a ſouldiour: Then fayle not (quoth he) to be at my Sermon to morrowe, &amp; you ſhall ſée, how I will pleaſe you. The next day, he entred into the Pulpit with a Rapier, and all other furniture (belonging to a ſoldiour) vnder his long robe: where he began hys argument, to perſwade al Princes to make wars vpon the Saraſens, and Turkes and vpon all others, that were enimies to ye Chriſtian religion: affirming, that it was great pitie, ye no perſon would aduaunce himſelfe, to be a chiefe of ſo honorable an enterpriſe. But if it reſt (ſayd he) only on ye, behold how ready I am to ſhake off this garmēt of S. Francis, and to ſerue either for a Captain, or for a ſimple ſouldiour.

and therewithal let fal his Friers habit from of his ſhoulders, and remayned preaching halfe an houre after, in the braue apparell of a Captayne. The cauſe being aſked him (of certaine Cardinals his friendes) why he vſed the newe faſhion of Preaching? he told them the truth, as you haue hearde afore, and it paſſed for a pleaſaunt payment among them.
            This Licienſis preaching before the Pope, and all hys Court of Cardinals, conſidering their pomp and pride, and 
                  Fo. 482. ſpecially how they did honour the Pope: he ſayd nothing in the Pulpit, but fie Saint Peter and fie S. Paule, and when he had oft recited thoſe words, ſpitting firſt on the one ſide, thē on the other (as thoſe commonly do that haue ſome grief at theyr hartes) he ſodainely departed the Pulpit, leauing his Auditours wonderfully aſtonyed: wherefore ſome thought, he had not bin wel in his wits, &amp; other ſome imagined, he was not ſounde of Religion: ſo as they ment to cōmit him. But one Cardinal amōg the reſt, that knew partly his humor: cauſed hym to be called before the Pope, who commaunded him to render ſome reaſon for that he had done, &amp; to ſhew what he ment by his horrible blaſphemy: he anſwered, that (in truth) he was determined to entreat of another matter: but conſidering (ſaide he) that you poſſeſſe all the pleaſures of this world at will, and that there is no ſtate or magnificencie comparable to yours, and waying againe with what pouertie, pain, and miſerie, the Apoſtles liued: I thought (with my ſelfe) that eyther they were great fooles, to chooſe ſo ſharpe a life, to goe to heauen, or that you were in the hye way to Hell: and as for you that holde and haue the keyes of heauen in your hands, I cannot by any opinion, but approue your wiſdomes, commend your iudgemēts, and thinke wel of you: marry as touching the Apoſtles, I will neuer eſtéeme them of any value, but diſdain them for the greateſt ſots in the world, who might with the like delicate courſe of life, come to heauen as you do, and yet wold chooſe ſo troubleſome, ſo ſtrayght, and ſo paineful a way vnto 
                  Fol. 579.
               
it, approuing the ſayings of a Paynter in Rome, who had made the Images of Saint Peter and S. Paule, and a Cardinal comming into the working houſe, foūd fault that he had painted them with too hie a colour, for their faces (ſaide hée) were too red, to whom the Painter aunſwered: this redneſſe cōmes of ſhame, for they bluſhe to ſée the proude ſtate and traynes that you haue, in reſpect of the low and poore countenaunce they carryed.
            A Monke beginning his ſermon with theſe words By the 
               
                  Ap. Ste. Fol. 487. 
               bloud, by the fleſhe, &amp; by the death of God, we are all redemed &amp; ſaued, did at (the firſt) wonderfully amaze his Auditors, for they ſuppoſed he had vſed them for horrible othes, conſidering the pauſe or ſtay he made betwéene euery word. Whiche bringeth likewiſe to memory, the knauerie of certaine Chanons in Bloyſe, who Chriſtened two children of one Iohn Gods (the one a ſon the other a daughter) naming the ſon Death, and the daughter Vertue. This hath a kynde of blaſphemy in it, which is hateful to the hearer, and damnable to the ſpeaker, conſidering with what grace they deliuer it. But a Ieſuite (named Hoghſteen) at Hornburge in 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 487. 
               Germanie, vſed his ſermon in playner termes who made it no conſcience to ſweare by God, in deſpight of the Proteſtantes: affirming that he woulde proue, how they were worſe than ye Diuel. For (ſayd. he) if I méete with ye Diuel, &amp; bleſſe my ſelfe but wc the ſigne of a Croſſe, he wil ſtraight flye from me: But if I make the ſigne of a Croſſe to a Proteſtāt, by God he wil fly vpon me, &amp; be redy to ſtrangle me.
            Another Ieſuite being ſore hurt (by chāce) wt the ſtroke of 
                  Fol. 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . a horſe: a friend of his, yt knew his blaſpheming humor, ſayd to him: this wil make you leaue your ſwearing? who anſwered, By the bodye of God I wil take héed hereafter howe I ſweare.
            Not vnlyke to the Abbot whō 
               Barelet (the preacher afore ſpoken off) friendly admoniſhed, ſaying: reuerēt father many 
                  Fo. 734. haue ſhewed me, yt you can not talke wythout an othe or remembring the Diuell: who preſentlye aunſweared, what

is he in the Diuels name that ſayth ſo of me? By the bodye of Chriſt it is not true.
            A Monke of Bloiſe in a greate rage wiſhed the bloudye flixe to the Aſſe that bare Chriſt into Ieruſalem. 
               
                  Fo. 263.
            
            And another Religious abuſed by his harlot, curſed the Woulfe, and one hearing hym, aſked wherein the Woulfe 
                  Fo. 264. had offended him, for that (ſaide he) he deuoured not Chriſt when he was a lamve. Certaine Iewes being in Rome and hearing the Cardinals blaſpheme Chriſt ſo bitterly, ſaide, they maruelled how they could beléeue, that he dyed for thē, &amp; vſe ſuch outragious ſpéeches againſt him, euen as though they would ſpit in the face of God.
            As what Diuel coulde deliuer more damnable ſpéeches, than was vttered by a Prieſt there (his Concubine putting 
                  Apo. Ste. Fo. 354. him in a choller) Al dispetto di quel can che pendeua nella Croce: In diſpight of the dog that hanged on the croſſe. Oh horrible and hateful words, ſpoken by the Diuel in the ſhape of a Prieſt: and in that place, where commonly no better fruite coulde growe. As Paule the thirde going on his ſolemne Proceſſion, in the honor of theyr Corpus Christi daye, ſayde in a rage (for that his company martched very ſlowe afore him) if they did not make more haſt, he woulde denye Chriſt and all that come of hym.
            And the ſame Paule being told (in open conſiſtorie) that he could not with a ſafe conſcience giue to his kindred Parma 
               
                  Fo. 462. and Placentia, aunſweared: if Paule the Apoſtle did bear ſuche affection to thoſe of hys nation (whom he called brethren) that he deſired to be ſeperated from Chriſte, to the ende they might be ſaued: why ſhoulde not I with like affection to my ſonnes and cooſins, offer my ſelfe to damnation, to the end to make them greate and honorable perſonages? Which kinde of blaſphemie is not alone to be attributed to his holyneſſe, but to the whole genealogie of thoſe triple crowned tyraunts, and to all others of theyr marke, if we may iudge their hartes by theyr actes.
            
               
The ſame Pope Paule (to ratifie the ruine of his Soule) 
                  Fo. 582. ſent worde to Charles the fift (who was not onely a fauourer, but alſo a protector of their ſuperſtitiō) that if he would not render Pleſantia, he woulde excommunicate him: To whom the Emperour anſweared, that he would thunder; and lighten as loude, and as faſt with his Cannons, as the Pope ſhould thunder and lighten with his terrible excommunications: and then (ſaid he) let thoſe two trie who ſhall carrie the cauſe away.
            By theſe threatning meanes they wonderfully terrified the world: for the very breath of thoſe Romiſhe 
                  •
               eaſtes, did ſo Eclipſe the bright beames of the truth, as it became as dimme and darke as their dreames. And if any (at any time in ſingleneſſe of he art) did arme himſelfe with Gods worde to defend his honour and glory, they would encounter them with curſing, excommunication, fire, famine; and ſworde, and with all the tormentes of Phalaris, Bucyris, and Nero, being ſtil in the combat both iudge &amp; partie▪ And truly they had great reaſon, to kéepe this mightie ſtull, for they foared (as furious as they were) that if this little lyght of ye Goſpell ſhoulde haue any way in the world, it woulde in ſmall time after quench the groſſe fire of their greaſie k
                  •
               tchen.
            And now ſéeing I haue preſumed ſo farre on the eurious follie, or fooliſh curioſitio of bad Preachers, I will (in pardon) followe the traine, and deliuer you as an any as I can remember.
            One to whom God (by the witneſſe of himſelfe) had ſhewed 
                  Fol. 487. ſundry ſpeciall graces, deliuered theſe ſpéeches in hys Sermon of his owne commendations, I can not tell howe it happeneth (ſaid he) that others of great countenance and fame, are not ſo wel learned, nor can not preach ſo profoūdly or gallantly as I doe: ſome ſay they lacke the knowledge I haue, and that they are nothing ſo wiſe, which I beléeue to be true. For al you can witneſſe, that it is not yet a yéere, ſince I had neither iudgement, nor vnderſtanding, and now you ſée me preach to the pleaſing of you all. In which

Sermōn he proued his chaſtitie, by ye witneſſe of his ſiſter. For (ſaid be) it is reported that I abuſe my continence with ſome in my houſe, beholde my ſiſter (pointing to hir with his finger) who muſt nédes knowe it, if it were ſo, for I paſſe euerie nyght throughe hir Chamber to myne: and therefore let hir ſpeake hir woorſt and openly if this be not true. This ſame Doctor, that in one yeere was become 
                  Fo. 488. ſo wyſe, receyued a certayne ſcedule or little ſcroll, from the Byſhoppe of Paris and the Officiall, wherein was written the names of ſundry yt he ſhoulde excommunicate, which (by chance) he let fall into a little hole of hys Pulpit, for remedie whereof he helped himſelfe with this peſtilent practize, as one ye with the loſſe of the Paper, had lykewiſe loſt the remembrance of their names whom he ſhoulde excommunicate. And therefore ſayde, I excommunicate all thoſe, that are within that hole: and yet in the ende (remembryng himſelfe better of the matter) he excepted the Byſhoppe, and the Officiall, who had ſubſcribed to the ſame. This gallant, who gloried not a little in his rotten 
                  Fol. 489. lerning before it was ripe (being but of one yeres growth) approued in his Sermon Purgatorie, by the example of of his Male horſe, confoundyng all thoſe that woulde ſaye the contrarie: although ſundrie others had (by great ſtudie and trauell) collected manie authors, out of great and ſmall Doctors, and euen from the moſt famous Saint Patricke himſelfe, and by the witneſſe of ſundry ſoules that returned from thence, and yet the world would ſcant beléeue it. This holy, profounde, and learned Preacher, ſpeaking of the Lutherans, that ſought to ſhut vp all mens mouthes, by denying of Purgatorie, ſaid, I will deliuer a true teſtimonie of it, yt the proudeſt of them all ſhall not reproue. You knowe (quoth he) that I am ſonne to olde Maiſter Steuen, and that we haue a fayre place by ye bridge of Saint Antonie, where riding one Euening ſomewhat late, my Male horſe ſtayed contrarie to his cuſtome, and played puffe, puffe: I commaunded my man to ſpurre him: he anſweared ſo I doe ſir,

but ſurely he ſéeth ſomewhat more than I doe: and then I remembred my mothers reporte, howe ſhe had ſhewed me that there had bene ſéene at ſundrie times, the appearance of ſome ſpirit, therefore I ſayd my Pater noster and my Aue Maria, but my horſe fearefully treading, would not go forward, playing ſtill puffe, puffe: and then I added to my deuotion, De profundis, the vertue whereof did leade my horſe a little further, and when the thirde time he vſed his puffe puffe, I had no ſooner ſayde, Auete omnes Animae, &amp; requiem aeternam, but he went praunſing for the without any ſtaye. And thoſe wretches that will not haue vs praye for the deade, and ſaye there is no Purgatorie, let them goe to my Male horſe, and he ſhall learne them their leſſon.
            I would not that this worſhipfull father ſhoulde haue all 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 490. the honor of theſe ſubtilties, for a Iacobin (named Diuolaye) vſed the lyke compariſon, wherby he proued one point, that all the foregone Doctors coulde not fynde the lyke Latine for. Theſe ſhameleſſe Lutherans (ſayde he) wyll not beléeue that the bodye and bloud of Chriſt is in the Sacrament of the Aulter, vnleſſe they ſée it: when you haue a Paſtie of Veniſon, doe you not ſaye, it is a Paſtie of ſuche a thing, and yet ſée not what is in it: here you haue (quoth he) you groſſe beaſtes, a manyfeſt example to proue your wilfull errour.
            A Moncke in Paris (named Burdelet) preaching on good 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 490. Frydaye at the Pariſhe Churche of Sainte Germins, ſhewed howe Chriſt béeyng on the Croſſe, and ſéeyng hys mother wéepe ſo bitterlye, ſayde to Saint Iohn, my good Nephew and gentle Couſin, I commende this poore Gentle woman my mother vnto you: and laying his hand vpon his breaſt, he dyd ſweare by the faith of a Gentleman, that he woulde be thankefull for it. And ſo procéedyng to the texte, ſpake in the commendation of Ioſeph of Aramathia, howe hée came to take downe the bodye of Chriſt, ſaying, This was not a man of meane parentage, nor a

baſe companion, but a Councellor at the lawe, one of much honor and credite apparelled in a long gowne, &amp; mounted on a Moyle, all couered with blacke from the eare to the hoofe.
            Maiſter Adrian Begwin (a Curate of Saint Germins in 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 497. 
               Noyon) ſaide to his Pariſhoners in a Sermon, my friendes you muſt haue patience, and beare with my briefe brawling at this time, for I am bid to dinner to a fat Pigge, but truely if I had tarried, I would haue played the madde man among you, and haue taught you, Ronge, rage en rage with al the rigge r
                  •
               gges of round Robin, which bycauſe it hath a pleaſant Emphaſis in the French, I leaue it in the proper termes as I founde it.
            A Prior of the Iacobins in Bloyſe, preaching one daye in 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 492. his Couent, and taking his Theame againſt the cauillations of the Lutherans, ſayd, they would haue vs ioyne with them to the word of God: by my faith I ſweare to you all, I knowe not what they meane by it, but I knowe wel that to mingle a little water to a good deale of Wyne, is a good coniunction: wherat his audience began ſo hartily to laugh, that our fatherly Fryer was fayne to ſay, you haue laughed ynough: and then after he had taken a new breath, he continued his purpoſe, ſaying, I remember that this great King Francis being in his good Cittie of Roane, a Gentleman of his complayned, that there were two clockes in the towne of ſuch diſcord, that when the one would ſtrike. 8. the other would ſtrike. 9. which came by the faulte of thoſe that kept them. And therefore the King commaunded that the clocke kéepers ſhould be brought to drinke togither, which done, their clockes accorded, and their charge went orderly. And ſo my maiſters, if the King (at the laſt méeting and conuention at Poiſſi) had brought vs and the Hugenot miniſters to haue once drunke togither, I beléeue, by my faith, wée had nowe bin friendes, and at a good vnitie and agréement: which made his audience to laugh more than at the firſt. But ſuch as deſire to heare theſe kinde of compariſons, no

doubt but if he addreſſe himſelfe to our aged men that he of good memorie here in England, he ſhall finde of their olde ſtore, approued among our foregone Fathers as pleaſant as theſe.
            It was wont to be a common prouerbe, It is as true as God is in the Maſſe, which was ſo generally vſed, as the world thought there was no article of religion ſo certaine, nor that there was any leafe in the Bible or newe Teſtament, but it made mention of it. And ſome (to proue the antiquitie and troth of the ſame) ſhamed not to preache that 
                  Fo. 433. 
               Cayne reſembled the damnable Lutherans, for yt he coulde neuer be perſuaded to heare Maſſe, where his brother Abell would neuer faile to be at Maſſe. To the better confirmation wherof, a Prieſt of Sauoy, vſed to admoniſh his Pariſhioners, ſaying, Take héede you followe not that reprobate wretch Caine, who would neuer pay his Tythes nor heare Maſſe as he ought to doe, but rather followe his good brother Abell, who did both with a good will paye of the beſt, faireſt and fatteſt, and neuer miſſed daye to heare Maſſe: whiche argumente if it bée true, proueth that Maſſing Prieſtes, were then married: for ſéeing there was onelye foure perſons at that time in the world, Adam, Eue, Caine, and Abell, it is to be beléeued, that Caine ſaide no Maſſe, for that he hated to come to it: and Abell could not ſaye Maſſe alone, and therefore it muſt néedes followe that Adam was the Maſſing man, Abell did help him, and Eue held ye torch, whereby is proued that the firſt prieſt was married.
            Vnto this Curate I may compare as a companion, the 
                  Fo. 434. 
               Ieſuit that ſaid in his Sermon, that when the Angell Gabriel came to the Virgin Marie, he founde hir on hir knées, ſaying our Ladie Mattins: and alſo that Abraham, Iſaak, and Iacob, and other the Patriarkes, neuer layde them downe, before they bleſſed themſelues with the ſigne of the Croſſe, ſaying their Pater noster and Aue Maria. But if one ſhould demaunde howe they know this to be true, it muſt paſſe for currant coine, to anſwere, he heard it of ſome great Doctor.
            
               
Who doubteth of the great ſuperſtition, that thoſe dreamed on, who (at the firſt) framed ye ſundry partes &amp; patches of the Maſſe: which wrought &amp; brought to perfect medley, was made more vendible, than all their traſhe beſides. By what braines it was deuiſed, by whoſe cunning augmēted, &amp; by what perſons performed, ſundry auntient authorities do witneſſe: yet truly no portion of their religion more to be embraced for mirth than this: it hath ſo many pleaſant dumb ſhewes, ſo many ſtrange myſteries, and ſo gallantly maſked, that during the play, they ſtande at a gaze, and are amazed, as it were looking for wonders, vntill Ita miſſa est, 
               Farewell and be hanged. biddeth them Valete, &amp; plaudete. Although the glory of this game was ſo great, as al knées bowed at the hearing of it: yet in the beſt world, &amp; when it had moſt credite, there were ſome of al ſorts, could ſay it without Booke: and euen the Maſſing mates themſelues would ſometimes ieſt at it.
            As a Prieſt in Louein, (named Sanders) confeſſed he knew not the deuiſion of Maſſes, for all ſoules, &amp; for al ſaints, &amp;c. But for a common Maſſe he coulde courſe one, and it were for the Diuels good grace. Much like the good fellow, yt bad 
                  Fo. 357. ſir Iohn come and ſay Maſſe, in the name of a hundred thouſand Diuels: for his Maiſter was angrie. And as a Gentleman of Loraine, who loued the Maſſe well, and knewe his ſonne did not greatly like of it, ſaid to him: To Maſſe in the Diuels name, to Maſſe, his ſonne beléeuing that his Father ſpake truer, than he winned for.
            A poore Prieſt in a village, not farre from Amsterdame 
               
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 592. (in Hollande) findyng in an olde Almanack, Sol in Cancro, written with red letters, ſuppoſed it had bene the name of ſome ſolemne Saint: and therefore endeuored to ſearche out what Maſſe ſhoulde ſerue for that day. But in the ende, when he had well turned and returned (twice or thrice) his Maſſe Booke ouer, and coulde fynde no ſuche Saint there, he ſayde, what a Diuell is this for a Saint? Wherevpon he concluded (in choller) thus, Sol in Cancro, Sol in Cancrus, nec est virgo nec martyrus, venite adoramus: which bycauſe it

hath no good grace in the Engliſh, I leaue it to maiſter parſons expoſition, and will for his better credite accompanie 
                  Fo. 651. him with his owne Countrey man, a Prieſt of Dort, whoſe ignoraunce was ſuch, as he knewe not what was ment by the name of Lutheran, whether it were the name of a man, or of a beaſt, or of any thing elſe: for beyng ſo called, (bycauſe he ſayde In nomine Patria, &amp; filia, &amp; ſpiritua Sancta) he ſo grieued at it, as he deſired his friende to ſhewe him what that name myght ſignifie, who perſuaded hym, it was a diſeaſe tenne times worſe than the Leproſie: whereat hée tooke ſuche a conceite (ſuppoſing it to be ſome vnknowne maladie) as he ſent his water to the Phiſitions, willyng him in any wyſe to ſende him worde if he were not ſicke of a Lutheran, and to ſhewe him the remedie.
            Theſe morrow Maſſe mates (who commonly had more good fellowſhippe in them, than eyther witte or learning) were endowed with one ſpecial conditiō, worthie to be commended, for they had Maſſes of all ſortes, for all diſeaſes, of all priſes, and for the humours of euerie man: and therefore they knewe (if they dyd not vnbrydle it wyth ſpéede, to thoſe that loued a ſhorte grace) what fauour they ſhoulde haue of them. As certayne Gentlemen of Fraunce, bleſſed their Chaplaine, who hauyng haſt of their iourney, deſyred the Prieſt (in lieu of a hunting Maſſe) to giue them the Maſſe of a Souldior, ſuppoſing it to be one of the ſhorteſt. The Parſon peruſing his Portas, coulde not fynde anye Goſpell that made mention of men of warre, excepte in the Paſſion, where it is written. Cum fustibus &amp; armis, with Clubbes and other Weapons, &amp;c. And therefore brought the whole Paſſion in his Maſſe: which made his audience in ſuch a rage at hym, as they curſed both the ſacrifice, and the ſacrifycer: for they were booted and ſpurred, and their horſes readie to founder at the Church dore, ſtaying for them. The onely madneſſe that holdeth the world in this Maſſing Frenſie, conſiſteth in the vaine hope they haue to frée their friendes out of Purgatorie: wherevnto

they haue ſome reaſon, when the Memento of one Maſſe alone (and at one inſtant) deliuered. 99. Soules from thence. And the Parſon being aſked why he lefte an odde behynde, 
                  Fol. 620. anſwered, that if the clappe of the Church window had not ſo ſodainely ſtarted him, he would haue performed the iuſt number of a hundred.
            And if it may be tollerable (amōg ſo many bad matters) 
                  Fo. 463. to recite one part played by a Prouoſt in Fraunce, yet perſited by an opinion of the Maſſe, I wil ſhew you the hiſtorie. This Magiſtrate meanyng for money to ſaue a notable Théefe, and to auoyde the ſlaunder in iuſtice, cauſed an honeſt poore man to be brought before him, whom he ſaide he had long ſought for, and that he had committed ſuch &amp; ſuche ſundry crimes worthy death: the poore ſoule ſtanding vpon his innocencie, ſtoutly denied al. But this Prouoſt reſolued in his wretched purpoſe, perſuaded him, ſaying, if he did confeſſe it, he would cauſe ſo many Maſſes to be ſaid for him, &amp; ſo his ſoule ſhould be ſure of Paradize: but if he denied it, he ſhould notwithſtanding be hanged and goe ſtraight to ye diuell, for he would ſuffer no one Maſſe to be ſaid for him: the poore man hearing of hanging and going to the Diuel, was greatly afraide, &amp; ſuppoſed if he muſt néedes die, it were better to gaine thoſe Maſſes and goe to God: ſo in the ende he anſwered, that he did not remember he had committed any ſuch faultes as they charged him, but if they knew it better than himſelf, &amp; that they were aſſured it was true, he would (ſo the Maſſes might be ſayd for him) take his death in good part: who had no ſooner ſpoken that word but he was caried to execution in the place of the théefe. The perſuaſion of the Maſſes to kéepe him out of Purgatorie led this innocent to his death.
            To the maintenance whereof Eraſmus reciteth howe a 
                  Fol. 147. Prieſt on All Soules night faſtened to the bodies of ſundrie ſmall Creuices certaine waxe lightes, ſcattering them among the graues in the Church yarde (which ſéemed verie

terrible to behold in the dead of the night as all the lookers on were aſtonied at ye feareful and ſtrange ſight of it, whervpon this Prieſt in his Sermons publiſhed that they were the ſpirites and ſoules of ſuch, as ſought to be deliuered frō the pain they endured in Purgatorie, by Maſſes and almeſdéedes, which craft was ſhortly knowne, for ſome of thoſe ſpirites were found with their Candels cleaning to them: and that vnripped the packe of this Popiſh knauerie.
            And the ſame Eraſmus in the two and twentith booke of his epiſtles, ſheweth further how a night ghoſt was conſured: 
                  Eraſmus lib. 22. of his Epi.
                ſor (ſayeth he) there was a certaine Prieſte that helde his Néece in the houſe with him, who had good ſtore of money: and to the ende to drawe ſomewhat from hir, he lapped himſelfe in a ſhéete, and towardes midnight entred hyr Chamber, counterfayting a ſpirite: the woman yt was wiſe, perceyued in part the miſtery, and therefore cauſed another of hir kinſemen the nexte night to come and lye ſecretlye in the Chāber by hir: who in lieu of a coniuring booke brought a good cudgell, filling hys heade with drinke to be the hardyer: the ſpyrite appearyng (as afore) beganne wyth hys fearefull noyſe pitifullye to cry, when the Coniurer (who had not yet diſgeſted hys Wine) ſodainely ſette vppon him, and ſo baſted hym on both ſides, ſaying if thou be the Diuel I am hys Damme, as he had vtterly ſpoyled him if he had not the ſooner diſcouered himſelfe.
            In the yeare. 1569. there was in Auſburge in Germanie, 
               
                  Apo. Ste Fol. 147. certayne ſeruaunts belonging to one of greate worſhippe, who made no accounte of the ſuttle ſecte of the Ieſuites. Wherevppon a foule of the ſame feather, promiſed theyr Mayſter hée woulde eaſilye remoue that opinion from thē, to the performaunce whereof, he diſguiſed himſelfe into hymſelfe, and putte on the habite (of hys firſte founder) the Diuell: And after hyding hym in a corner of the houſe, to the whyche place one of the mayde ſeruauntes by hyr Mayſters appoyntment was ſent, thys Ieſuite in the forme

of a diuel ſo feared hir, as ſhe had like to haue gone oute of hir wittes: whiche ſhe preſently reported to one of hir Maſters men, perſuading him in no caſe to come neare that way. The felow notwithſtanding thought to proue whether hir feare procéeded of any aſſured cauſe, wente to trye it: vppon whome this Ieſuite diuell, or Diuell Ieſuite (in the moſte horribleſt manner he might) faſtened his counterfaite tallants. The fellowe partely prouided afore (looking for ſome ſuch mater) drew out his dagger, &amp; wrought a myracle, by killing of the diuell.
            Thus you may ſée, that the opinion whiche euerye one had in their holineſſe, furniſhed them with all diueliſhe inuentions to maintaine the ſame: And therefore we ought greatly to reioyce (in God and our Quéene) that the true profeſſion of the Goſpel hathe ſo opened the eyes of Englande, that we may beholde all their abuſes, in their perfect kind. For now God wil not ſuffer, that ſuch (which purely (in faith and ſinceritie) call vppon his holy name in Ieſus Chriſte his ſon) ſhall feare or doubt any of thoſe damnable deuiſes: where before they were wont (by their daily familiaritie with the Diuel (to haue him continuallye conuerſant among them:) p
                  •
               actiſing by ſpirites (his inſtrumentes of darkeneſſe) to holde the worlde in blind errors. Whiche a Proteſtant alleadging to a Papiſt, for the better ſigne and token of our true profeſſion, ſayde: You maye the ſooner vnderſtande by this, that our re
                  •
               igion is good and ſound doctrine: For ſince Gods word was preached among vs, we haue not ſéene nor heard of any night ghoſts to trouble vs. The other ſuppoſing this argument to ſerue beſte for his purpoſe, replyed, ſaying, it is rather a token that God hath taken his grace from you, for that nowe the Diuell hath no more to do, conſidering he doth accompt you al his owne. Alleadging this example, written by Eneas Siluius ſometime Pope Pius the 2. whiche hée tooke out of the Legend of Saint Benet, and the hiſtorie is thus: Saint Benet trauailed to a Couent of Monkes,

where he founde a heape of vncleane Spirites combatting with the holy Fathers of that place: and all to remoue them from theyr good workes. Sainte Benet at another time returning to the Abbey, found an euil ſpirite ſitting idlely wagging his legges, and beating his héeles togyther with cold: whom he coniured to ſhew him the cauſe of hys idleneſſe: he aunſweared, we are to make wars wyth Cloyſtermen and ſuch as be the ſeruauntes of God, and not againſt thoſe whoſe dreames, trumperies, and blaſphemies do already ſerue the Diuel.
            This was well applyed, if Sainte Benet had bene by to haue paraphraſed further vppon it: for none wil deny but that the ſuttletie of the Diuil is ſuche, as he ſéeketh to encreaſe hys kyngdome by all the meanes he may: and howe can hys glorie be greater, than to kéepe that carefully which he hath gotten cunningly: And alſo it is a general rule, that a conqueror doth triumph in nothyng more than in holding in due obedience, thoſe that are become his vaſſals, which muſt be by the preſence of him ſelfe, or by his chiefeſt miniſters. And ſeing the Diuel wanteth no experience, hauing as much foreſight as ſo proude a Spirite may haue if we be ſo aſſuredly hys owne as that Papiſt would make vs, he woulde not be from vs in perſon as a friend to fauor vs, or in power as a iealious foe to loſe vs, conſidering ye holy league (ſo termed) by the cōſent of ſo mightie Papiſts, haue promiſed to make vs reuolt (if it be as ye petie Papiſt ſayeth) frō him. But, as it is only natural reaſon that thoſe groſſe creatures of the Popes deſire to be ſatiſfied by, ſo in reaſon they know it is as much wiſedome &amp; policie to kéep, as it is prayſe &amp; glorie to get, whiche in my opinion, ye féend would foreſée as a principle, if he held vs ſo dear, as this his darling (winning yt gole, in his own conceyt, wt one ſtroke) alleageth he doth: &amp; therfore it is to be beléeued, ye Diuel wil not dwel but where he hath ſome intereſt, and may be welcome: And ye which is moſt true, the Pope his beſt beloued, as he cannot forbear him, ſo he dare not ſpare him ſo far of,

ſéeing Gods warriours are comming with a rolling crench towards him. And as in al martial marches, there are euer ſome ſtraglers, who care neither for Country, Captain, nor cauſe, but follow only to pray vpon the ſpoyle of others: ſo the Papiſtes of preſent time, that ſéeme to muſter vnder the banner of true Chriſtians (vexed with the frenſie of theſe forlorne ſpirites in the image of Engliſhmen) come rogyng and ſtragling among vs, (as a newe founde Ieſuite of late did) who couet nothing more than the ruine of theyr Country, that they mighte (with the Diuell theyr Maiſter) haue a part in the bloudye bootie. But to proue indéed, howe Sathan the chiefe Maiſter of ſinne, dare not be where the word of God is truelye taughte, the ſacred Scriptures in euerye text doe teſtifye: As in Matthewe the 8. Marke the 5. Luke the 8. Paule. 2. to the Corin: 6. Chap. &amp;c.
            Although the inuention of man be greate, whoſe proude iudgement hath preſumed on many things: yet truely, hys iniquitie (in his own nature) did neuer deuiſe a more damnable blaſphemie againſt God and his Saints, than yt booke entituled Legenda Aurea. Wherein there are many paſſages ſo far from Decorum, that if the reader be tender harted or ſqueamiſh ſtomacked, it wil make them Seaſicke to peruſe them.
            As for a firſt example: Frier Iuniperus (whom Saint Frā
                  cis helde for a very holy and moſt perfit godly man) woulde to ſhew his ſingleneſſe in deuotion be cooke one daye to the whole Couent: where ſetting a great Caudron of water ouer the fire, he put thereinto certaine Pullets, neither plumed, drawne nor waſhed: and al other kinde of fleſh as wel freſhe as ſaulte, with ſundrye ſortes of Hearbes, and with Peaſe, beanes, and al maner of Pults, picking nor clenſing any thing. And hauing boyled al this braue broth togither, he ſerued it in the ſame comely ſort to his company: whych was taken for ſimplicitie ſake to be the true part of a ſaint.
            The ſame Iuniperus, being (in reſpect of hys deuotion) layde in a good bedde and a fayre payre of Sheetes, dyd

ſo dungnifie them with durt, as his hoſteſſe was faine to take it for payment, without a farewell. Theſe two religious partes, were to his ſingular praiſe (for ſimple holineſſe) ſet forth, in the Conformities of Saint Frauncis, in the 62. and 63. leaues. Whiche honeſte hiſtories are there recited, to ſhewe the humilitie of this holy Fryer. And it may be there was more myſterie in the naturall courſe of thoſe Crucifire Cormorants, than in anye other common creatures: For Fryer Ruffin (mentioned of in the ſame Booke) made the Diuell more afraid, by threatning that 
                  Fol. 95. Where it is ſhamefully recited in plain
                        •
                      termes.
                he would vntruſſe a point in his throate, than with al the holywater he had: which argueth, that thoſe groſſe mates fed on ſome ſacred ſubſtance: otherwiſe, the Diuel would neuer (with ſuch feare) haue fled ſo filthie a perfume.
            Pardon me good Reader, for my vndecent ſpeeches, for I muſte accommodate my termes in parte to the purpoſe: And it is an o
                  •
               de Prouerbe, that it is hard to apply honeſt words to vnhoneſt workes: and as Chaucer ſaith, a plaine tale muſte haue plaine termes. Who can forbeare to laugh and reade the life of Saint Dominike, howe he beſieged certain Diuels within the body of a man, frō whence he woulde not ſuffer them to departe, before they had gyuen him pledges to returne no more thither? And howe Saint Frauncis to proue his virginitie did ſtrippe himſelfe 
                  In confor. 211. ſtarcke naked before the Biſhoppe of Aſſiſe, and gaue the Biſhop his bréeches for a relique.
            Euen as he was, ſo were his Diſciples: for Fryer Leonard comming to the gate of Viterbe, pulled off all his 
                  Fo. 62. apparell, putte his bréeches on his head, and hys ſhyrte, with the reſte of his clothes, he bounde vppe in a fardell and hanged it about his necke. And in this braue beaſtlye ſorte he paſſed throughe moſte places of the Citie, enduring (in the meane time) all the ſhameleſſe mockes that might be. And in the ſame naked ſhewe he went to the Abbey (a felowſhip of hys owne Fraternitie) where they cried vppon him for this moſte impudent parte: But thys

good frier was ſo clothed in Holineſſe, as he made no accompt of all their reproches. You ſhall likewiſe findethe greate wiſedome and grauitie of that Arche Saint Francis himſelf in the 114. leafe of his Conformities, how he ſaluted fléeing fowle, ſpake to them, &amp; called thē his brethren, commaunding them to heare the worde of God, whereat they reioyced ſo much, as they ſtretched forth their necks, and opened their villes, and behelde him very attentiuely: And after the Sermon, he paſſed through the middeſt of them, and then gaue them leaue to departe in peace: which they did with great deuotion, diuiding themſelues into foure parts, whereby they did ſignifie, that the orders of Saint Frauncis ſhould paſſe, &amp; be placed in al quarters of the world: and that he ſhoulde be renowmed on the earth aboue all other profeſſors. Alſo that Saint Frauncis and a Nytingale did ſing togither a whole day the one aunſwering 
                  Fol. 149. the other. And in the leafe 114. is mentioned, howe by making of the ſigne of the Croſſe onely, he charmed a madde Wolf, that had hurte manye, and concluded thys bargaine with him, ſaying, my brother the Wolfe, thou ſhalt promiſſe me, that thou wilt be no more ſo rauenous, as thou haſte bin, and I will warrant thée, that thoſe of the Citie ſhall féede thée: whiche the Wolfe affirmed to hold by enclining his head to him: and for his more faith &amp; credite, he gaue his right foote into Saint Francis hand, who commaunded the Wolfe (as his good brother) in the name of Ieſus Chriſte to goe with him, which he did. We reade likewiſe of many other Saints that had a ſpeciall felicitie to be conuerſant &amp; to deuiſe with beaſtes, but I beléeue that the fraternitie and felowſhip of Wolues, was onely peculiar to Saint Frauncis. Is it not a mockerie to reade, that Saint Macaire did 7. yeres penance among thornes &amp; bryars, for killing of a flea? And who can forbeare to laugh at an other part of Saint Dominike recited towards the end of his legend? which is, that a Nunne named Mary, hauing a griefe in hir thigh, that had greatly troubled

hir the ſpace of fiue months, (&amp; in the end acknowledging hir vnworthines to pray to God, or to be heard of him) ſhe prayed to Saint Dominike, that he woulde be a mediatour betwéene God and hir, that ſhe might recouer hir health. After which deuotions, Saint Dominike came to hir in hir ſléepe, and with an ointment that he tooke from vnder his Cope (which was of excelling ſauor) he anointed hir thigh &amp; made hir whole: And when ſhe aſked the name of ſo ſoueraigne a remedy, he anſwered it was the ointment and balm of Loue. For the further iudgement thereof, I leaue it to the diſcretion of the reader, whoſe imaginatiō, I ſuppoſe, wil ioine with mine: which truly is no worſe, than ye ſame that was betwéen friendly S. Frauncis, and louing S. Clare mentioned of in the 84. leafe of his Conformities.
            We haue the like hiſtorie (thoughe more blaſphemous) Sprenger. publiſhed by one Sprenger, an Almaine Writer: who ſhamed not to put in print, ye where a Iacobin named Alaine, did forge our Ladies Pſalter, ſhe, in recōpence of it, came to his chamber, &amp; made him a ring of hir haire, wherwith ſhe married him, &amp; how ſhe kiſſed him, and offered him hir paps to play with, &amp; that ſhe was as familiar with him, as any wife coulde be with hir huſband. In the Legend of S. Germaine is ſhewed how the king of Denmarke denying to him and his company lodging, he was fain to ſéeke it at the Neatherds hand, who receiued him gently, broughte him to his houſe, and hauing but one Calfe did kil it for S. Germaine and his company, that were like to periſh with hunger &amp; cold. But after ſupper he cauſed the ſkin &amp; bones of ye Veale to be brought togither to him, whervpon when he had made his prayers, the Calfe did riſe into his firſt proportion of life againe. And the next morning he went to the king, vſing great &amp; groſſe ſpéeches vnto him, commaunding him out of his kingdome, &amp; eſtabliſhed the cowherd in his place, which he &amp; his ſucceſſors enioyed for euer after. He that deſireth to heare more of theſe fables, ſhall find his fil of them in the Legend of ye Saints liues:

where this, &amp; much worſe matter is written for a truth of them. And alſo Nicephorus reciteth, that manye yeares after Nicephorus. the death &amp; burial of S. Iohn Chriſoſtome, his body did dayly ſpeake, &amp; would both aſke &amp; anſwere to queſtions. And that the Emperour Theodoſius did write letters to him. But the Booke called the Conformities of S. Francis with Ieſus Chriſt, mentioned of ſo oft afore, was neuer compiled without the aide and conſent of the Diuell himſelfe: For, one of the greateſt myracles that Chriſte héere on earth didde, was the rayſing of Lazarus from deathe to life: which was as common and eaſie to S. Francis and his Diſciples, as it was to drincke a glaſſe of Wine. And S. Francis vſed it as a ſporte, to kil: to the end he would ſhew his power to quicken againe, as is recited in theſe proper wordes, in the leafe 120. Locus est dictus de Nuceria, in quo beatus Franciſcus fecit illud inſigne miraculum, quod cuiuſdam medici filium primogenitum prius occidit, &amp; contritum ſuſcitando restituit. The valor ſay they of Chriſt, was nothing comparable to the myracles of S. Francis for Chriſt was tranſfigured but once, S. Francis 20. times: Chriſt changed water into wine but once, he thrice: Chriſt ſuffred the griefe of his woundes but a little while, he whole two yeare togither: And as concerning myracles to make the blind to ſée, the lame to goe, and to driue Diuels oute of the poſſeſſed, Chriſte cannot compare with S. Francis and his followers. For they haue giuen ſight to more than a thou
                  •
               ād blind, they haue reſtored the limmes to more than a thouſand lame (as wel men as beaſts) and they haue forced the Diuel to flye out of more than a thouſand menne and women. Is it poſſible that any Chriſtian eare coulde heare them preach theſe horrible blaſphemies in open Pulpit, &amp; not ſpit in their face, or rather teare them in péeces? Yea, when they were not aſhamed to conclude, that Chriſte was but a counterfaite to S. Frauncis, and in theſe damnable termes, that he was not worthy to pull off his hoſe: affirming with full gorge, that he did far excel &amp; ſurpaſſe ye
               
Apoſtles, the Saints, &amp; al the Angels: And in the 17. leafe it is ſaid he was a Patriarke, a Prophet, a Poſtle, a Martyre, a Doctor, a Confeſſor, a Virgin, an Angell, &amp; a Saint moſt conformed to Ieſus Chriſt. And in ſo. 49. they name the 12. Apoſtles of S. Francis, Petrus Chatanei, Iohannes de Capella, Philippus Longus, &amp;c. And as Iudas Iſcarioth was reiected out of ye felowſhip of the Apoſtles, for betraying their Maiſter Chriſt: ſo Iohannes de Capella was deiected from S. Frauncis, bicauſe he was proued to deteſt his profeſſion. And further, they do aſcribe vnto hym the title of Ieſus of Nazareth King of the Iewes: For firſte they inueſted hym wyth the title of Ieſus, bycauſe he was in nature, qualitie, condition, and conformitie, moſte like vnto him: And of Nazareth, for that he was a moſte pure virgin: They called him King bicauſe he kept both the inward and the outwarde laws: And for that he was full of melodie and ioy, ſoliciting all the world to the prayſe &amp; honor of God, they ſayde it was a ſpeciall ſignification of the Iewes.
            
            Beholde the concluſion of this moſt diueliſhe and infernall inuention of the Popes Saints, which aſcended to ye higheſt degrée of moſt vngodly blaſphemie.
            It is no maruel though they helde him (and others hys like) in that curſſed credite: when they ſo bewitched the wits of all men, as they thought no reuerence too muche, to be (with great deuotion) done, to any parte or parcel of them: yea, and it were but to a patche of their apparell. As at Tryer in the Abbey of S. Symon, they helde the Pantaphles of S. Ioſeph for a great relike: And at Aix in Germanie his bréeches, and our Ladies ſmocke: The ſmocke greate ynough for a Giant, and the bréeches too lyttle for a Dwarffe: And in ſome places they reuerenced for relikes their pottes and their ſpoones: And at Gennes they honored the Aſſes taile that carryed Chriſt: and in Loraine the holy Hay that was in the racke where Chriſt was borne: At Arles among the Auguſtines, at Vigand in Languedock, and at Florence the ſtones that ſtoned S. Stephen were hadde in

great price: They alſo honored the Arrowes that were ſhot at S. Sebaſtian in Poictiers, and at Lambeske in Prouance. And in my opinion, ſéeing the Stones and arrowes were accompted ſo holy, the Archers and Stone-caſters were worthy ſome glorie.
            But to the ende the Reader ſhal not muſe ouer much vpon theſe ſuttleties, to ſhewe that the world had no eyes, neither in their heads, nor in their vnderſtanding, but as willingly or wilfully blinde ſuffered themſelues to bed led into all abſurditie: I wil recite a certaine hiſtorie, whereby you may the better beholde their ſimple follie.
            When Nicodemus tooke our ſauiour Chriſte from the Croſſe, he ſaued ſo muche of hys bloude as filled one of the 
                  Fol. 612. fingers of his gloue: with the whyche hée wrote ſundrye myracles. By reaſon whereof, being hardly perſecuted by the Iewes, he was compelled in the end to conuey it awaye by a maruellous meanes. For he didde write in a péece of parchment, al the myracles he had done, with the whole circumſtance how the miſterie ſhoulde be vſed, and cloſed the bloud with the parchment in the bill of a bigge water fowle (for my Author maketh no mention of his name) and hauing bounde it and trimmed it in the beſte manner he myght, he caſte it into the Sea, and commended it to God. Whoſe bleſſed wil was, that after this Saint Bill (by the time and terme of 1000. or 1200. yeares) had ſayled through al the Weaſterne and Eaſterne ſeas, it ſhoulde in the ende arriue in Normandie, where at this day doth ſtande the Abbey of Bill: And beyng by the boyſterous billowes caſte aſhoare among other baggage, on a heape of buſhes, it hapned a good Duke of Normandie (one that was a founder to ſuch follies in thoſe daies) to be hunting of a Hart in thoſe quarters, where ſodainely he hadde loſte bothe Déere and Dogges, til at laſt he ſpyed them before thys buſhe all on their knées, the Hart firſt, and the houndes harde behinde him: and as ſome write, they were at theyr prayers. This ſight moued the Duke to greate deuotion, who reuerentlye

ſought the place, where he founde thys pretious Bill with the contents thereof: whych cauſed him to build an Abbey in the honor of it, naming it the Abbey of Saint Bill, where this beautifull myracle is yet to be ſéene, adorned wyth ſuch ſundrye riches, as this Bill doth now féede a number of bellies.
            Here is to be noted, howe euidentlye and impudentlye they didde mocke the pore Idiots in that age: For, when they did opē the ſhop of their ſhameleſſe relikes, how boldly would they brag of their rotten merchandize? As behold here in this viole the bloud of our ſauiour Chriſt gathered togither vnder the Croſſe by the virgin Mary: And in thys other viole, is the teares of our Redéemer, that hée dydde ſhedde on the Croſſe, when he behelde his pitifull mother: Here is the milke of our Ladies breaſtes, the haire of hir head, and the ſooadling bandes wherewith ſhe firſte rolled Chriſte at his byrth: And in this bottle (whyche may not in any wiſe be opened) is the very breath of Ieſus Chryſte curiouſly kepte by his mother euer ſince hée was a lyttle one.
            As a Prieſt at Gene, returning from Iewrie, affyrmed he brought wyth him of the ſame breath, and from Mount Synay the hornes of Moſes. Theſe ſhameleſſe ſhewes of theyr trumperie, if anye did finde faulte or ſpeake againſt them, be was condemned for an heretike: For it was (they wold ſay) allowed and confirmed by the Popes Holineſſe, to be moſt true, and therefore damnable to thinke the contrary. I leaue to recite their infinite ſtore of traſh, which by their runnagate Pardoners were made as vendible as theſe.
            As one that carried about the relikes of Saint Hubart (to 
                  Fo. 555. iuſtifie the vertue of them) baſhed not with moſte blaſphemie to affyrme, that if the holy Ghoſt were bitten with a mad dog, he would come to Saint Hubart to be healed. Among this rabblement of Relickes, I muſt néedes intrude 
                  Fol. 559. one myracle performed in the perſon of a Ieſuite, who, to obſerue the ſtraight lawes of their religion, had his Concubine

cloſe in his bed to help him ſay his Mattins at midnight: And his boy or Nouice comming vp in the morning (by chance they both aſléepe) he ſaw foure naked féete hang out of the bed, whereat he was ſo amazed, as he ſodainely put his head out at the windowe, and mainely cryed: ho, come ſée a myracle, for my Mayſter hathe foure legges.
            And further, to ſhewe their aucthoritie for the proofe of their Images, which they honored with reuerēce due only to God, it will euery way appéere to be as bad &amp; as abſurde as ye reſt. For a Legate of the Popes to the orientall Churches, didde alleadge for Saintes, the texte of Moſes: God created Man to his owne Image: and therefore hée affirmed, we ought to haue Images. An other to proue that Images muſte be vppon the Aultare: brought in the 5. of Mathewe for a witneſſe: where Chriſte ſayeth, that none lighteth a Candle, and couereth it with a buſhell, but ſetteth it vppon a candle ſticke, to light al the houſe with. An other alleadging, that the ſight of Images was profitable, bringeth the 4. Pſalme for proofe: The light of thy countenaunce, O Lorde, is marked vpon vs. And Theodorus brought in this ſuttletie, It is written, that God is maruellous in his Saintes: And therfore he would haue vs to contemplate his glory in Images: And one affirmed this ſimilitude, that as the Patriarkes vſed the ſacrifice of the Infidels, ſo Chriſtians ought to haue Images, in lieu of their Idols. Here you may ſée their faire allegations, approued by ſome of their generall counſels and preched in their common ſermons: by which places of Scripture they abuſed ſundrie of good capacitie and iudgement: And yet the ſimpleſt might ſée how farre they erred from the true meaning of the Text.
            
               A Sorbonist Doctor named Demochares (of late yeares at the Conuention of Poiſſi in Fraunce) pleading in the defence of Images, agaynſte a miniſter of Gods worde, when he was ſette agrounde and ſawe hys owne ouerthrowe, he ſhamed not to take holde on this allegation:

gation: That the Church of Saint Benets in Poiſſi was builded in the time of Saint Deniſe, and there was images in the glaſſe Windowes: Ergo there were Images in Sainte Deniſe time: you haue wel aunſweared ſayd the Miniſter, with a good grace like a Doctour, and with matter ſufficiēt, pertinent to the purpoſe: but that the beſt ſubſtaunce of your brittle authority is altogither of glaſſe.
            With what ſorts of ſuperſtition dyd they leade the world when they made ſo deare ſale of theſe fantaſtike ſightes, or rather infernall vanities, compelling the ſimple people ſometime, to honor the preſence of hys image here, whoſe ſoule was with the Diuell elſewhere: As an auntiente Doctour writeth, Multorum corpora adorantur in terris, quorum animae cruciantur in infernis How were they blinded with the filthy and moſt ſtinking ſinne of Idolatry, when in time of moſt peril, and at the inſtant of their deathes euery one had ſome peculiar Saint to call vpon: and ſuch they were commonly, as in theyr liues they did moſt deuotion and honor vnto: cleane forgetting God in the merite of hys ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. As Eraſmus making mention of a ſhipwracke, ſheweth, that when the maiſter of the ſhippe ſaw no remedy Eraſmus Coloq. but the loſſe of all, and willyng euerye man (paſſengers with him) to prepare to dye, declaring the aſſured peril they were in, ſome called vppon one Saint, ſome vpon another, euery one according to ye hope he had in theyr priuate help: and one among the reſt deſired hys S. Chriſtopher to remē
               ber hym, promyſing, that he would preſent him with a Taper light, as long and as great as the Maſte of the ſhip: another ſtāding by &amp; hearing his offer (who knew his termes and ſtate very wel) ſaid, how canſt thou performe thy vow, when al ye welth thou haſt is not worth ſo much waxe as ye Maſt is big: to whom he replyed, ſpeaking it ſoftly (that S. Chriſtopher ſhoulde not heare hym) ſaying, hold thy peace friend, I wil promiſe much to haue his helpe now, but if I get once to ſhore, I will ſcant giue him a Candle as big as my finger.
            
               
Not much vnlike vnto this was ye pleaſaunt parte of a Tayler of Florence, who had a long time (with great deuotion) 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 118. honored the Image of Saint Baptiſt, and one daye on both his knées, he hūbly deſired to know whether his wife (at any time) had wantonly abuſed him, and what fortune ſhould folow his only ſon. A yong Nouice (trayned vp to al knauiſhe toyes) happened to ouer-heare his petition: who ſtepped behinde the Aultar, and fayning the voyce of Saint Iohn, aunſwered him: My deare friend and faithfull folower, for thy long reuerent worſhipping, &amp; deuotion thou haſte done vnto me, I will truely tell thée: thy wife hath ofte horned thy head, and thy ſon ſhal be ſhortly hanged: wherefore departe in peace, ſince thy Prayers be hearde: whereat our Florentine entring into a great rage, did riſe &amp; toke his leaue wythout a farewel, but when he was a little paſt from him (vſing no reuerence of Cappe or knée) he turned and ſaide: what art thou for a Saint? the Nouice aunſwered, I am thy Saint Baptiſt: My Saint (quoth he) thou art the diuel, a lier, foule mouthed, and a ſlaunderer, which thou haſt vſed from the beginning. For that babling falſe tong of thine, cauſed Herode worthyly to cutte off thy head. I haue prayed 
                  Matthew the. 14. cha.
                to thée this 25. yeare and haue offered more light before thée, thā I am worth: But now holding vp his fiſt towards him, &amp; offring him the Italian fig) I wil ſée thée hanged, as ye waſt headed, before I wil come to thée againe.
            A certaine Cooke in Florence, accuſtomed to make his ordinarie prayers &amp; Candle offrings to a very yong Image of 
                  Apo. Ste Fol. 576. Chriſt, entertayning himſelfe in his grace the ſpace of xx. yeares: about which time, it fortuned a Tileſtone to fal frō the houſe vpon his childs head, &amp; wounded him to the death, which the Father perceyuing, came to hys yong S. Chriſt, &amp; brought him a fayre waxe light for a preſente (where hée was wont to offer only a tallow Candle) vſing this prayer: my moſt ſwéete litle Lord Ieſus Chriſt, I pray thée reſtore my ſon to helth, thou knoweſt it is now more than xx. yeres ſince I firſt faithfully ſerued thée, during which time, I neuer

deſired any pleaſure of thée, but now, ſéeing my ſon is in danger of death, I am come to commend vs both vnto thee, deſiring thée to helpe him, as wel for the deuotion he bears thée (being yong like thy ſelf) as for the continuall ſeruice I haue done thee. After he had ended theſe prayers, he wente home, where finding his ſon deade, he returned in a ſurie to his little Chriſt, to whom (without anye knée or curteſie) &amp; with his cap on his head he ſaid, I do vtterly renounce thée, with aſſured promiſe, that thou ſhalt neuer ſée me more: I haue with true deuotion ſerued thée long, and neuer requyred any good turne at thy hand til now: and thou haſt bothe denyed me and deceiued me. I confeſſe I ouer-late finde my own folly, for had I done halfe the ſeruice to the gentleman that good old Roode thy Father that ſtāds by thée, as I haue done to thée, I am ſure he wold not ſo childiſhlie haue refuſed me. And one thing more I will promiſe thée, it ſhall be a warning for me for euer hereafter, to haue to do either wt thée, or wt any boy for thy ſake, adding this prouerbe Chis' 
               
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 577. 
               vnpaccia confanciulli, confanciulli ſiritroua: He that hath to do with children, ſhal be childiſhly handeled, which may well agrée with this that followeth: For where one praying to our Lady (with hir little infant Chriſt in hir armes) hadde hys anſwere made in a childiſh voyce (by one that ſtoode behinde hir Image) whyche lyked hym nothyng, and iudgyng by the voyce that it was not the mother that ſpake, but hyr ſonne, ſayde, holde thy peace prettie babe hold thy peace, &amp; let thy mother ſpeake who hath more wit than thy ſelfe.
            But the Burgonion vſed brauer ſpéeches to a yong Crucifixe, ſon to an old that had almoſt killed him, for he comming 
                  Ap. Ste. Fol. 577. into the Churche, and ſéeing a fayre yong Crucifixe made wyth a ſmyling countenaunce, and ſet in the place of the olde, he ſayde to him: it is not thy diſſembling face, nor all the flattering ſhewes thou canſt make, ſhall deceyue mée, for I wyll neuer truſte thée: And I warraunt
                  •
               
               
if thou liue to the age of a man, thou wilt proue as falſe as thy father, that meant to murder me. Not muche vnlike the ſpéeches that a Flēming vſed to a roode in Rochel, though in another ſenſe: for he comming thyther to ſell Herring, and finding a badde Market for his purpoſe, he wente into the Church, where ſéeing the Roode wyth his head hanging on the one ſide, and looking very pitifully, he ſayd: ah good Lord, didſt thou (likewiſe) bring hither Herring to ſell? Theſe Hiſtories do witnes, that as the Pope &amp; his prelacie, brought all the world into damnable Idolatrie, touching the worſhipping of Saintes, ſo it ſéemed that ſome in all ages, wold ſhewe thoſe Idolles their Leſſons, when they pleaſed them not.
            As not long ſince the inhabitauntes of a village called Neutonne by Paris, for that theyr vines were froſen on Saint 
               
                  Fo. 578. 
               Georges day: did not alone ſpeak bold &amp; opprobrious words vnto hym, but preſumed on his perſon, and threw hym into the riuer of Seine, to the end he ſhoulde be as wel frozen as their Vines, which act was ſo much the more hardye, for yt they durſt attempt it againſt him, who is a Mars among all the Saints.
            And a Fryer in Artoys in Henaulte, Preaching of the ſtatue of golde, that Nabuchodonozor cauſed to be ſet vp, 
                  Fo. 467. wherof Daniel maketh mention in hys thyrd Chapter, hée ſayde, thys Image was as great a villayne as our Sainte Euſt
                     •
                  ce is, but he was all of Maſſie gold, I woulde to God our Saint Euſtace were ſo to.
            Wherby, as we may ſee that ſome would be ſauſie with theyr Saints, ſo truely in al worlds there were that would touch their Hipocriſie with termes apt for them.
            For Laurence de Medecis who knew the beſt honor due to 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 578. theyr deſart, being aſked by the Turkes Embaſſadour how it hapned he could not ſée ſo many mad men, fooles &amp; Idiots, paſſe through the ſtréetes of Florence, as were commonly to be ſéene in Caire &amp; other Cityes of hys Country, he anſwered, we hold them all encloſed in ſtrong houſes, euerye one

according to the qualitie of his madneſſe or frenſie: wherevpon the next daye (accompanying him out of Florence) he ſhewed him a number of Monaſteries, which he ſaid were ye places for their fooles and mad men of all ſorts, and were called Monkes, Friers and Nonnes. All this is nothing, nor that which hath bin publiſhed by our predeceſſors, againſt the pettie ſort of the Clergie, in reſpect of ye which hath bin ſpoken againſt the Popes their owne perſons.
            For Paſquin from the beginning and euen at their dores would touch them ſo to the quicke, &amp; deſcipher euery ſmall 
                  Fol. 580. artier or vaine of thē ſo naturally, as no Anotomiſer could doe better: whoſe ſkill was the more, for that he was acquainted with the beſt witted, gentilleſt ſpirited, and moſt of iudgement in al Rome. This Paſquin to ſhewe in one word, what the whole Etimologie of the Popes vertue and name did ſignifie, fained to die in diſpaire, of an vnkindneſſe, yt one had ſlaundered him. Why (quoth his friend) haue they called th
                  ••
                Théefe, murtherer, or poiſoner? he anſwered no, but they haue termed me much worſe: haue they called thée a robber of Churches, a killer of thy Parents, a Bouggerer, or an Atheiſt? Alas no ſaid Paſquin, they haue touched my credit with a worſe report thā all this. His friend grieuing to ſée him in that wofull caſe, deuined at all the greateſt and moſt infamous names that could be deuiſed, he ſtill affirming it was worſe, and ſo bad, that I knowe you can neuer geſſe at it: Why then ſaid his friend, I pray thée ſhewe me what it is, that hath brought thée into this diſpaire? In the end Paſquin deliuering a déepe ſigh, anſwered: alas &amp; twice alas, they haue called me Pope: confirming the ſayings of Pope Leo the. 10. before mentioned.
            For the ſame Pope, reproued by certaine of his Cardinalls 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 457. for his euill gouernment, and hatefull life to all men, (as one that was wonderfully chaunged, after he became Pope) anſwered: if I be euill giuen now, it is you that are in the faulte, for it is your ſelues that haue made me as I am. They wondring at theſe words, deſired to know how

that might be: Bicauſe (quoth he) you haue made ine Pope, and I haue in my owne perſon by proofe tryed it, that it is vnpoſſible to bée Pope and a good Chriſtian togither, and to dwell both in one ſkinne: which is eaſie to bée beléeued by the courſe of their whole lyues, who would prophane (as well by their workes as their wordes) thoſe things they accounted moſt holy.
            As Pope Iulie the. 12. who did caſt into Tyber the keyes of Saint Peter, and tooke in hand the ſword of Saint Paule, 
               
                  Fol. 586. iuſtifying that the keyes in regarde of the ſworde was of no value or force, to maintaine his warres with. According to theſe verſes following.
            
               Quum tibi non aetas habilis ſit Caraphe bello,
               Et castris habeas cognita claeustra magis:
               Quum decet miles belli
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   pecunia neruus,
               Quis te praecipitem, cogit ad arma furor?
               Infirmis humeris damnata quid induis arma?
               Quae tibi quum libeat ponere, non liceat.
               Cur reſpirantem &amp; curantem vulnera mundum
               Concutis, &amp; Martem ſolus ad arma cies?
               Da miſeris requiem, &amp; ſpacium concede malorum
               Si nobis Pater es ſi tua cura ſumus?
               Conde Senex Gladium, &amp; Chriſti reminiſcere verbi:
               Quod dixit Petro, dixit &amp; ille tibi.
            
            
               RESPONSIO.
            
            
               Quod dixit Petro Christus, nolim eſſe putetis
               Dictum (pontificum pace Petri) mihi.
               Nam neque ſum Petri ſucceſſor, nec quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   talem
               Agnoſcit bona pars Christicolarum hodie
               Pauli ego (ſucceſſu caeptis meliore deinceps,
               Dij faueant) ſumpſinomen &amp; arma ſimul.
               Et Christi verbi memor intrepiduſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   minister
               Non veni pacem mittere, ſed gladium.
            
            What greater mockerie could there be, or rather damnable blaſphemie (to their owne profeſſion) than the ſame yt 
               Gregorie the. 7 (firſt named Hildebrand) did: for he, bicauſe

his Aultar God (called the Sacrament) would not anſwere to ye he demaunded, he caſt him into the fire in ye preſence of 
                  Apo. Ste. Fol. 587. a nūber of his Cardinals, and in great deſpight ſaid, there was no ſubſtance in him, yt could not doe as much as Apollo the God of Infidels, who anſwered euery man by Oracle.
            This your Pope and viſible God on earth (to obtaine the Papacie) gaue himſelf, his ſoule, and all to the Diuel, which appeared by his ſkill in cōiuring, witchcraft, and ſorcerie.
            If the Pope, with all his companie of groſſe creatures, had beléeued any heauenly vertue to haue bin in that miſterie, where vnto they made all the world (with bowed knées) to doe godly reuerence, and to beléeue it was God in déede vpon their damnation, how could they haue bene ſo full of impietie to prophane it as they did.
            For a Prieſt of Loraine holding in his hand a great boxe of theſe Wafer cakes, not yet conſecrated: ſhaking them togither, ſaide, ho you prettie knaues and falſe harlottes which of you ſhall be a God to day?
            From Loraine I muſt come to Prouance, where a Prieſt at the eleuation, did hold ye féete of his God vpward &amp; the head downward, &amp; being aſked ye cauſe, why he did ſo? anſwered: for yt I woulde not haue his bréeches fall about his héeles. Confirming the report of a Sacrificer in Sauoye, who vaū
               ted in his mirth, that they vſed their God, as the Cat vſeth the Mouſe, for when they haue ſported and played at their pleaſure with him, they deuour him.
            A Gaſcoine named Gotrene, ſaying Maſſe, &amp; ſéeing his goſſyp (who then ſerued the turne) very ſlow to anſwer Amen, he ſaide, ſaye Amen in the name of the Diuell, to whom he anſwered Amen in the Diuels name: adding more, ye Cankar conſume you goſſyp, for if you had not ſpoken ſo haſtily I had taken a Mouſe: which you muſt ſuppoſe came either to heare Maſſe, to be canonized, or to ſéeke his praye, as at Lodoue in Gaſcoine a Mouſe came vpon the Aultar, whileſt ye Prieſt ſlept in his Memento, &amp; ſtale a péece of his God from him, for ye which he was canonized, &amp; called Saint Mouſe.
            
               
An other Curate being in the beſt part of his Maſſe (whē his Aultar God was aloft) ſpying a boy clyming his Therrie trée, he cryed aloude, come downe in the Diuels name, come downe, his Pariſhoners ſuppoſing he had ſpoken to him betwéene his handes.
            Whereunto I muſt adde this ſhorte remembrance of a 
                  Fo. 593. Curate of the Cittie of Aubnias in Viuieres, who ſaying hys high Maſſe in a Churche which was not well couered, by reaſon whereof the winde blew away his Wafer God frō him, the Prieſt being badly ſighted, ſought him about the Aultar, and patting with his hands to féele him, ſaid, where the Diuell art thou become, or whether the Diuell art thou gone? Which argued there was ſome affinitie, or elſe ſome great league of amitie betwéene the Diuell and their Idol. And yet here reſteth a queſtion: for if they had bin of ſuch friendſhip, how durſt euerie Prieſt at his pleaſure, to haue threatened him with the Diuell? As for example, A common mate hauing a good minde to beate a Prieſt in Loraine, the firſt time he mette him, he was going with his Wafer God a viſitation. Well (ſaid this companion) and it were not for reuerence I owe to that in your handes, I woulde coniure you. The Prieſt ſtanding in termes of his valure, anſwered, I am readie when thou dareſt, and therefore forbeare me not for him, for beholde my God is on the ground (which in déede he had ſet downe to be iudge betwéen them) and I giue him to the Diuell, if he take parte eyther with the one, or with the other. By which threates it ſhould appeare he ſtoode in awe of the Diuell.
            There was alſo a Vicar of a village called Felniag (beſides Bonne in Sauoy) to whom his Pariſhoners came and requeſted him to ceaſe a ſtorme, for that he had oft vaunted he could caulme the worſt weather that might be: and therfore to approue his credite, he firſt vſed certaine coniurations, which he had by hart: then he brought forth his Portas, and his Maſſe Booke, wherin he did reade the moſt curſed ſentences he coulde finde, himſelfe being in the meane

while vnder a trée, which kepte him from the force of the ſtorme. In the ende, when he ſawe none of thoſe charmes would ſerue, he fet forth his holy Sacrament, wherevnto he vſed theſe ſpéeches: Courdi, ſe te ne ple fort, que le Diablo, ze te zetera de guen placo: that is, By the heart of God, if thou bee not ſtronger than the Diuell, I will caſte thee into the durt.
            
            What horrible blaſphemie was this of a Prieſt, and in deſpight of that, which they all ſéemed (with diuine reuerence) ſo much to honour?
            Theſe examples (in my opinion) are more than ſufficient, to proue that the ſame whiche our Papiſtes call thei
                  •
                holy mother Church, did not hid their wickedneſſe to our predeceſſors, but ſo manifeſted it by their dayly doings, that thoſe which were not willingly deaffe or blind, muſt néedes both heare and ſée them: ſhewing withall, how they did ſpecially prophane that which they held for a true, ſound &amp; holy religion. Notwithſtāding where one found fault at their falſe doctrine, a thouſand were offended at their wicked lyuing, for the whole world complained of their ordinarie crymes, being nothing to ye they otherwiſe moſt hatefully cōmitted againſt the Maieſtie of God, in their daylye blaſpheming him in the horrible abuſe of his holy word.
            For the diſordinate and curſed lyues that they continued and kept in the Court of Rome, was ſuch, ſo hateful &amp; abhominable, that Petrach ſpake of it both in his Italian &amp; Latine Epiſtles: affirming that Chriſt was baniſhed from thence, &amp; Antichriſt receiued, &amp; made campe maiſter among them: and that vnder the banner of Chriſt they made wars with Chriſt: for the Pharaſeis (ſaith he) did neuer ſo muche villanie to him as thoſe dayly doe: ſhewing by their words and workes, that they holde the aſſured hope of eternall lyfe, for a fable: for he that was the man of moſt miſchiefe among them, had for honour and prayſe the higheſt &amp; chiefeſt place. And touching their couetous catching and gathering of gold, it was ſo vnſaciat, as they ſet to ſale their own

ſoules: and made vendible Marchandize of the Church of all the Saintes of heauen and of Chriſt himſelfe. According to the ſaying of Pope Leo the. 10. whoſe confeſſor in ye time of death, perſuading him to feare nothing, conſidering that he had ye keyes of Paradiſe, &amp; the managing of all the meri
                  •
               es of Chriſt &amp; of the Saintes, at his pleaſure: he anſwered, you knowe yt he which once ſelleth any thing, is no more maiſter of it: and I yt haue ſold Paradiſe &amp; al the reſt, how ſhal I acceūt to haue any part or portion in them? Approuing ye ſūme &amp; ſubſtance of theſe verſes following, which ſheweth their monſtrous impudencie, ioyned wt moſt abhominable impietie: and were grauen with Gothicall letters in a table of ſtone, which not long ſince did hang in ye Churche of S. Steuens in Burgis, at a piller harde by the Aultar where the Cardinall was wont to ſay his ſolemne Maſſe.
            
               
                  Hic des deuotè, coelestibus aſſociote.
                  Mentes aegrotae, per munera ſunt ibi lotae.
                  Ergo venitote, gentes à ſorde remotae.
                  Qui datis, estote, certi de diuite dote.
                  Te precor, accelera, ſparg as hic dum potes aera.
                  Et ſic reuera, ſecure coelica ſpera.
               
               
                  O ſi
                        •
                     u ſcires, quantum dataproſit ibires,
                  Tu iuxta vires, donares quod dare quires.
                  Te miſer à poena, dum tempus habes, aliena.
                  Huc dare te pena, veniae ſit aperta crumena.
                  Conſors coelestis fabricae quiporrigit estis.
                  Ex hoc ſum testis, hic vos mundare potestis.
               
               
                  Fratres haurite de trunco pocula vitae:
                  Hic aliquid ſinite, veri velut Iſraelitae.
                  Crede mihi, crede, coeli dominaberis aede.
                  Nam pro mercede Christo dices, mihi cede.
               
               
                  Hic datur exponi Paradiſus venditioni.
                  Currant ergo boni, rapientis culmina throni.
                  
                     
Vis retinere forum? mihi tradas pauca bonorum.
                  Pro ſumma quorum, reſerabitur aula polorum.
               
               
                  Hic ſi largè des, in coelo ſit tua ſedes:
                  Qui ſeret hic parcè, parcè comprendit in arce.
                  Cur tardas tantum? nummi mihi des aliquantum.
                  Pro ſolo nummo, gaudebis in aethere ſummo.
               
               
                  Denos ſume quater, vnum ſemel, haec ſacra mater.
                  Annos condonat, ſanctus pater ista coronat.
                  Tot quadragenas, dat &amp; abluit hic tibi penas
                  Mille miſſis decies ſocius, ſi des, ibi fies.
               
            
            Theſe verſes, for yt they be in Latine rime, I cānot frame any good grace to them in Engliſh: but ye effect &amp; ſubſtance conſiſteth: in yt, who ſo euer did offer or giue to their woodden image, ſhould goe into Paradiſe: and ye more they gaue ye better place ſhould be prepared for thē: and thoſe ye gaue nothing ſhould be aſſured neuer to come there. For Hic datur exponi Paradiſus vendi
                     •
                  ioni, is as much to ſaye, as here is Heauē or Paradiſe to be ſold. But to the end the vnlearned Reader ſhall not looſe the knowledge of ſo good a market, (the ſumme of all conſiſting in theſe two verſes)
            
               Crede mihi, crede, coeli dominaberis aede:
               Nam pro mercede Christo dices, mihi cede.
            
            I haue tranſlated them as neare as I can to the true ſenſe word for word.
            
               Beleeue me, beleeue me, thou ſhalt for mony gouern heauē, And in recompence of that thou giueſt, thou ſhalt cōmand Chriſt to giue thee place.
            
            Sée here the faire leſſ
                  •
               n theſe ſcholemaiſters of perdition would learne vs, according to the ſayings of Plutarch, that if Iudas came to Rome with his. 30. Pence (the price of our Sauiours bloud) he ſhould be receiued and Chriſt reiected, affirming further, that truth could haue no credite or countenance there, where the aire, the earth, the temples, yea their Palaces, houſes and buildings, was full of treaſon, urther, falſhood, blaſpheming, and lying.
            
               
Nowe oure Romiſhe Catholikes (whoſe conuerſion to Chriſt in heart I craue) that ſo muche deſire by wilful ignorance to ſuppreſſe God and his glorye, and to aduaunce the Pope and his Prelacie, and woulde haue theſe Tragicall partes (beautified with gluttonie, adorned with lecherie, &amp; de
                  •
               ked with all ſinne and iniquitie) to triumphe vppon our Engliſh Stage, before the play begin, conſider ye infamous falſhood, &amp; the traiterous trumperie, that thoſe of ye Churche of Rome doe holde you in: and gather into your memorie, ye ſumme &amp; effect of theſe examples, which I haue rudely and diſorderly diſperſed in this booke, to ye better vnderſtanding of the ſimpleſt ſort of you: and looke into the infinite number, that ſundrye others (moſt learned Authors to your behoofe) haue collected and publiſhed: wher you ſhal ſée (if God haue not vtterly ſealed vp the eyes of your iudgement) the manifeſt abuſes of that Romiſh beaſt, how he ſéeketh your deathes in the errour of your liues, and would haue you deuour your ſelues, in the wicked workes of your handes.
            For is it not a maruellous folly, &amp; a quinteſſence of blaſphemie, to honour fleſhe and bloud, a man, a ſinful creature, one that ſtandes with vs all vnder the ſentence and curſe of God (if it were not for the mercifull redemption of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt) with that diuine reuerence, that his heauenly Maieſtie hath reſerued onely for himſelfe? And to beléeue that ſo baſe a perſon ſomtime procéeding from poore parentage, that after he be once a Pope, (which conſiſteth only in mans election) to be ſtraight a God? Further, to beléeue that he hath the keyes in his handes of heauen and of hell: how he can place and diſplace in eyther at his pleaſure: and that for money he can ſell both to thoſe that will buye them of himſelfe or of his Miniſters? What weakeneſſe can be more, than to beléeue, that it is leſſe ſinne to kill a man, than to eate fleſhe on a Fryday or on a faſting day, or to breake any of the leaſt commaundementes of this earthly God: If you alſo (in the bowels of your conſcience) conſider the ſubſtance of your Maſſe Sacrifice, and the great abuſe

that is hidden vnder the pretext of that Popiſh deuiſe: you cannot deny, but that you haue (from the beginning) bin couered wt the cloud of iniquitie: for how hath ye whole world bin ſtrāgely bewitched (the moſt part yet continuing ſo) to beléeue that there was a Purgatory, from whence no ſoules could be purchaſed or chaſed but by the batterie and blowes of their maſking Maſſes: and to builde theyr ſaluation on the ſentence of an ignoraunt Idiot: that after hée had pronounced certaine Sacramental wordes ouer many Cak
                  •
               s of one marke, to make ſo many Gods of them, whiche ſhoulde (in déede) be holden the more ſuſpected, for that both the fleſh and bloud of them, if anye were, haue bin inſtruments of poyſon: The bloud to William Archbiſhop of Yorke, in the time of Pope Anaſtaſius the fourth: and the fleſhe to the Emperoure Henrie the ſeauenth, by a Iacobin named Bernarde of Mount Politaine, one of the faction of the Guelphis? But I haue too long dwelled in theſe Tragicall diſcourſes, and therefore I will no more remember them: truſting that I haue to your good contentmēt, performed (in ſome part) my firſt promiſe for examples.
            Yet to the end you ſhall not obiect (without reply) that I fetch my authorities from far, and ſette the honor of other countreys to cōmon ſale of ſlaunder, as one that mayltaine on forraine nations what he liſt: I will openly confeſſe that more than abhominable abuſes (remaine in record) committed by our forgone holye fathers of the ſame marke here in England. For at their firſt viſitation of the Monaſteries, Couents, Churches, Colledges, and other profeſſed places of thys Realme, theyr villanies, whoredomes, aduouteries, inceſt, buggeries and murders, were found ſo manifeſt, as they noted infinite numbers by name, whiche were conuicted in all the ſinnes that may be named. And ſéeing ye ſame is already extant in print, I leaue the particularities to ye ſearche of thoſe, that deſire to knowe euerye one in hys colours.
            At their ſuppreſſion (whiche ſurely was Gods ſecrete

iudgement vpon them) they were accounted foure hundered Eouents, of ſundry ſorts of Monckes and Nunnes, beſides the Fryer beggers, neare in nūber to two hundred houſes, whoſe lewde, lubberlye, letcherous and lazie liues, was ſo hated and abhorred (of the better ſort of men) as he withheld his holy and heauenly word from vs, vntil Henrie the eight (of ſacred memory) did put his hands to Gods plough, and ſtubbed vp all thoſe rablement of moſt filthy and ſtyncking wéeds, pretending truely to haue procéeded, and to haue tilled it with good corn: but he in whoſe iudgement refreſh the foreſight of all things, who knoweth the end before the beginning, preuented hys princely purpoſe, in no worſe ſorte, than as his mightie Maieſtie dearelye loued his ſeruante Dauid, yet reierued the building of his holy Sanctuarie, to hys ſonne Salomon: euen ſo, our godly late king Edwarde, (ſéeing the worthyneſſe of his Fathers worke and hauing ſo happy a waye prepared) entred on Chriſtes huſbandry: where finding the weather fayre and ſeaſonable to ſow, be ſlacked no time (by hys heauenly hyndes) to put Gods word into the grounde of all true engliſhe hartes. But, before the ſame coulde grow to his perfecte rypeneſſe, the appoynted time of our continual comfort by our ſauiour not yet come, or our vnthankful ſin, or both, cauſed that careful huſband, to be taken from vs: whereby both Cockell and Darnel, wyth all other ſorts of ſowre wéedes, ſo ouerlayed ye corne, as the thouſandth grain come to no profit. The field of thys flouriſhing realme (encloſed with the pale of ſafetie) was made common and caſt open: wherinto entred droues of deuouring beaſts, conſuming all before them, &amp; whole heards of vnringed ſwyne: who digged déepe to turne vp the rootes of our conſcience, by altering our earthly bodies into a firie Element.
            Then the Buls of Baſan ouer ran vs al, Rome tryumphed vppon our Engliſh Stage, and who but the Pope and his Prelacie? what grauing, what cutting, what caruing, and what gil
                  •
               ing was there of Images? where no coſt was too

much, to welcome this Antichriſt.
            The poore Gaſcoigne might then haue had entertaynment, who hearing a Monke in hys Countrey preach, that when Apo Ste. Fol. Antichriſt came he would bring infinite treaſure with him, and to winne the hartes of the worldlings, he woulde ſo we gold and ſiluer euery where, which bountiful ſpéeches, made the water flow ſo fréely to ye 
               Gaſcoignes mouth one of his auditors, as he cried, Ediu quan biera ed a quet bon Segno 
                     ••
                   Antichrist. O God, whē wil yt good gentleman Antichriſt come?
            Thus this Idol had once more (with his gloſe of golden ſhew) the principal place among vs: whoſe worldly whelps crept out of euery corner, and like Adders that had long line hiſſing in the hoales of dunghils, came 
                  •••
               tining abroade: And who but Maiſter perſon and his Portas? for the conſtant were crucified, the ſimple and weake bewitched, God in a ſtraunge language mocked, and the lighte of Engliſhe prayer (the pathwaye of the ignoraunte) cleane extinguiſhed.
            But Chriſt in his mercie, beholding our ſundry mournefull mindes, who (in patience) continued al perſerution and puniſhments, and hauing a ſpeciall regarde to the place, of hys elect, as Saint Auſtine long ſince propheſied of vs, whē he ſaw certaine children to be ſolde in Rome, aſking of what Countrey they were, was aunſweared of England, he ſayde Bene dicuntur Angli, quia nitent vt Angeli, in quo regno Euangelium deiflorebit. So his heauenly Maieſtie loking into our obedient miſerie (for his owne ſake) did cut off the cauſe of our calamities, and called our Sereniſſima, our moſte ſacred ſoueraigne into hir right, to reuenge his wrongs, and to redreſſe our general afflictions. Nowe you graceleſſe Papiſtes, that haue bene an eye witneſſe to all theſe wretched woes, among your brethren and Countreymen, what true replye can you make to theſe heapes of enormities? If my learnyng and condition, were Diuinely, as my profeſſion and argumentes be Naturallye (the chiefe Rules and precepts you couet to be perſwaded by) I doubt

not but I woulde (in pardon of my farre betters) ſo deliuer you your own ignoraunce: as eyther you ſhoulde yéelde to your errors, or ſtand mute to defend them: yet as I am (the more to your ſhame, that Martiall mindes can ſhew you, on whych foote you halt, as finely as you ſéeme to tredde) I muſt ſhew you that you will not ſée how God performes in hyr Princely parſon, the ſame he denyed to hir prediceſſors.
            She hath réedifyed the wals of Ieruſalem, and rayſed his holy temple to the higheſt: not ſhe, but God in hir gouernement, hath made a brazen wal about you: hir earely ryſing and late watchyng (I meane in the Image of hir honorable inſtruments) preſerues you, kéepes you, defendes and protects you from all perill, you néede not languiſhe in vncertaintie of life, as other nations doe: youre houſe is youre Caſtell, your Beds your Bulwarks, your goods your glorye, your wiues your worſhip and comfort, your daughters not rauiſhed, and your ſelues not ſlaued at the tyrannous pleaſure of ſtraungers: all theſe bleſſed giftes you forget, &amp; ſéeke by ſecrete ſedition a hatefull innouation among vs.
            Wiſedome willeth you to loke into your owne ſafetie, and reaſon ſheweth you no rule ſurer, thā to dwel in duety: The Lords of hir maiesties Counſel. by the one you are taught foreſighte, by the other obediēce: which conſidered, kepte, and followed, you may triumphe among good ſubiects. To loue God ſincerely, &amp; your Prince faythfully, is the aſſured protection both of body and ſoule: then if you offende the firſt, howe can you iuſtly ſay you fauour the laſt? when you know hir Maieſtie only ſéeketh to ſet forth hys glorie, doe you deſire the dayes of the Popes victorie (a common calamitie to your Country) which cannot be, but by the ouerthrow of our ſoueraign? doth priuate malice by the prouoking of Sathan ſo poſſeſſe you, as you are contented to commit al to hazarde? Wil you willinglye loſe one eye (and doubtfull in the ende to kéepe the ſight of that) to haue your Countrey made blinde? Do you thyrſte for hyr death, whoſe life hath bene and is a ſafetie to vs al? you will denye it, and yet your practiſes approue it. What

hope is to be had of you, when neither hir Maieſties goodneſſe, nor your owne daunger can driue you from youre deuiſes? They are dayly diſcouered, and no ſooner pardoned, but a new miſchief is a managing. Hir greate clemencie hitherto, muſt ſharpen hir ſword of Iuſtice to correct you: You brag there is no lawe to touche youre liues, and that maketh you ſo bold and venterous as you are. You conſider not, that the ſoule is more pretious than the body: And what is not in preſcription agaynſte you, by the Princes fauourable procéedings, may be your deſtruction, by the ſecrete iudgement of God. But if it were offered you, you would ſay with Menot: Can we be more aſſured of ſaluation than Saint Paule was, who was choſen by Chriſte, and rapt vp into the thirde Heauen: and that he ſayde, I deſire to be deliuered, and to be with Chriſt: yet when there was a queſtion of his death, and that he ſhoulde dye, he appealed to Caeſar: So I doubte not if death were offered you, you would appeale to the Pope. Or if any ſuche deſperate humor ſhould poſſeſſe you (as God forbid) I truſt you would ſend his Holineſſe the ſame commendation the Italian dyd to the Frenche King, being 
                  •
               laine in his warres, who vtterly forgetting God, commended both his bodye and ſoule to the King, ſaying, he had loſte a good ſeruant of him. But to frée you from any ſuch frenſie, and the better to perceiue your true duetie: In Chriſtian Charitie looke into thys that foloweth, where you ſhall ſée your owne ſhame, which may with ſpéedie repentaunce mollifie your Pharaos heart, &amp; make you reclaime your ſelues from your dangerous obſtinacie. Conſider the ſtate of oure Quéenes moſte royall Maieſtie at the firſte (a mirror within your own memorie) pace the pathes of hir Pilgrimage hitherto, and accompany with diſcretion hir famous actes and yeares by degrées, beginning at the time when hir Princely perſon was in moſt hazard of perſecution: and you ſhall finde howe ſhée hathe bin preſerued, kept, continued, called, and reſtored: more by a heauēly prouidence, than by any mans foreſight, a

or worldly diligence.
            Who was hir Bulwarke, when (lyke a Lambe among Wolues) ſhe was wrongfully ſuſpected, falſly accuſed, innocently committed, and the houre of hir ſlaughter moſte tyrannouſly appointed? did they not ſéeke by all ſecreate ſorte to haue bereaued hir bleſſed life from vs? But ſhée (moſte nobly) dwelling in teares, as well for the pitifull perſecution of others, as for hir owne imminent perill, appealed with harte and minde to him, in whoſe heauenlye handes reſted the redreſſe of all. She wofullye wepte with Heſter for hir people, in whome ſhe knewe ſhe hadde ſome intereſt. She bewayled with Ionas in the deapth of the waues, and in the forrowe of hir ſoule mourned for oure diſtreſſe. Was it the might of man, or the prouidence of God, that (in the middeſt of all theſe miſeries) deliuered hir from deuouring? Was it worldly pollicie, or the foreknowledge of his heauenly Maieſtie, that wrought ſo mightily for hir? Your ſelues can witneſſe, howe ſhe was fréed from the Lions den like Daniel, called like Dauid to kil Golias, and placed in Salomons ſeate, to reſtore the liuing child to his true mother. After hir ſacred Maieſtie receiued Iudiths ſword, to take the head frō your Romiſh Holofernes, if you diſcipher all hir doinges in true order as they are, and make queſtion of euerye point and parte of hir procéedings, the worſt minded among you (though he would ſet aſide al duty) cannot deny, but that hir gratious gouernement, euen to this houre, hath bin miraculous.
            When ſhe firſt entred the ſtage of hir triumph, did ſhée not find euery corner of this realme infected? ſome ſmoked, 1558. 17. Nouem. 
                        ••
                     eare.
                ſome ſcorched, and ſome ſmoothered, with burning of poore Martyres? were not all youre martyred men and holy Fathers (with moſte of the better ſorte) embrewed with the bl
                  •
               ude of innocents? did not ſundry of honeſt life and good credite (in ſorrowe of heart) abandon their Countrie? was any ſubiect in ſafetie, when ſome were priuily pyned, ſome ſecretly ſtrangled, and no torment (openly) left vnexecuted,

the glorie of God defaced, Chriſte (in his choſen) continually crucifyed, hys word vtterly baniſhed, &amp; the Popes traſh made the beſt ware among vs?
            In lieu of all theſe calamities, libertie for bondage, faynneſſe for feare, ſolace for ſorrow, life for death, and mercye for tyrannie, entred with hir. And where ſhe found the holy Sanctuarie with ſinne and pride p
                  ••
               luted, ſerued with blaſphemie, decked with Idolatrie, &amp; adorned with all kinde of Hipocriſie: ſhe beganne hir at the Church, and ioyning hyr manly indgemente to hir maydenlye mercie, (ayded by the higheſt) ſo purely purged it from all degrées of ſuperſtition, and that without perſecution, bloud, fire, or any other force, as ſome of your ſelues, then ſéemed greatly to reioyce at it. Was not this a ioyefull chaunge, to be broughte from the bondage of Sathan, to the libertie of the Goſpel? from the feare of Hel, to the faynneſſe of Heauen? from the ſorrow of our minds, to the ſolace of our ſoules? from the death of the ſworde, to the life of Gods word? &amp; from the tirannie of the Pope, to the mercie of hir Maieſtie?
            And ſuch as dwelled in their obſtinate error (cōfirming yt 
               
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 355. conſtancie of Cardinal Andreas to his holy Vicar) who being in the tearms of death, and perſwaded by his confeſſor, to honor one only God, aunſwered I doe ſo, but that is the Pope, for ſéeing hée is our God on earth, and that it is an abſolute commaundement for me to honor but one, I will rather worſhip him that is viſible, than he that is inuiſible: his confeſſor replyed that the Pope was neyther God nor Chriſt, although the world helde him for hys Vickar: howe ſo ſayde the Cardinal? if you account the Pope to be onely Chriſts Vickar, it muſt then follow that Chriſt ſhoulde be greater than the Pope, and that cannot be: for if God come viſibly to Rome, the Pope will not knowe him, nor receiue hym, before he haue humbled himſelfe vnto him, and kiſſed hys Pantophel.
            Accordyng to the Sermon of a reuerende Father 
                  Apo. Ste Fo. 355. at Toures, who in a brauerye ſayde, theſe villaine Proteſtauntes,

do vtterly reiect the Pope, and woulde haue vs to hold only on Ieſus Chriſt: but for my part, I aſſure you, if they were both here preſent to commaunde: it is ye Pope aboue all that I would obey. Euen ſo, thoſe headſtrong Papiſts, who continued in the like damnable determinations, and could not by milde admonition be remoued from theyr wilful errors, were (to the hoped time of a more grace) only committed, and not by rigor of death hatefullye murthered.
            Conſider the due courſe of all, how it was begun, confirmed, procéeded, and how it is continued (your ſecret conſpiracies, and open treaſons, practiſing to pull it downe) you can not otherwiſe truely ſaye, but that God is the ſupporter and protector of the one, and the diſcouerer and ouerthrower of the other.
            Thus the glorie of the almightie eſtabliſhed, all offences pardoned, priuate malice reconciled, and a general vnitie confirmed: to ſhew hir motherly care ouer vs, to heape all hir bleſſings vppon vs, and to manifeſt the meſſage of hym that ſent hir, which is moſte laudable peace: ſhe eſtabliſhed a common concorde betwéene Fraunce and this our Countrey 1559. hir Realme of England, to the vnſpeakeable ioy and cō
               fort of al hir louing ſubiectes.
            Since which time, what Straunge ſtratagemes, what Martiall miſchiefes, and what vnnaturall partes haue bin practiſed, almoſt within your own view? wt what mournefull Maſſacres, with what pitifull perſecutions, hath al our eares bene daylye filled? no newes but broughte hys bloudye reporte: for fire, famine, and ſlaughter, was the cō
               tinuall occurrances of euerye forraine Packet. The remembraunce whereof myghte ſuffice to ſinke your Soules in ſorrowe, to ſée ſo manye of Chriſtes congregation cut in péeces. If it, were cauſe to procure a trembling feare to any Chriſtian harte that only heard it in what condition of crueltie (ſuppoſe you) dyd thoſe innocents dwell, that endured the terrible execution of it.
            
               
Oh lamentable ſtate, who preſerued you, who protected you, who defended you, and who hath hitherto couered you from all theſe calamities, but God and our Quéene? Shée is ſtil in Vtrum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   paratus: hir forſight, pierceth into all perils, ſhe makes you hearers, and not féelers of theſe afflictions: ſhe hath ſet you vpon a ſure Rocke, to be ſéers and not ſufferers of theſe barbarous broyles: and you forgetting all theſe good partes in hir Princely perſon, miſuſing hir mercie, and contemning your owne ſafetie, ſéeke to fall wyth Satan, to be his children of perdition, and to become Butcherly inſtrumentes to your brethren and Countrey. You denie to be of Caines kinred, and yet perſiſt in the perſecutition of Abell, hath not that triple Crowned monſter, (to whoſe deuotion you are vowed) ſet this Royall Realme, to the common ſale or rather ſacking, of any tyrant that dare intrude vpon vs? Is it not a manifeſt ſigne of ſuſpition, and a plaine argument of pretexed Treaſon (and therefore a warning to all faithfull ſubiectes that loue our Soueraine, to holde you in ielouſie) ſéeing your are vnder an othe to ſuppreſſe hir religion? howe can you then be true to hir Maieſtie vnleſſe you be falſe to your Maiſter? But it may be you are of the poore womans opinion of Perigourde, that offered one Candle to S. Michael, to the end he ſhould doe hir good, and an other to the Diuel, to the ende he ſhoulde doe hir no harme. So you ſéeme to be Chriſtians yt the Quéene may fauour you, and you honor the Pope that his curſes maye not hurt you: for otherwiſe (I feare) there is no truſt at all to be had in your duetie.
            Howe much you diſhonor God, breake his commaundements, and blaſpheme the bleſſed Trinitie (by your wilfull diſſembling with him, who ſéeth the ſecretes of all heartes) your conſciences doe accuſe you, your déedes detect you, and your wordes doe witneſſe and bewray (ſo farre as you dare vtter) the ſumme of that you ſéeke. Is it not hir Maieſties perſon, and (this ſhouell full of earth as it hath pleaſed them to terme it) hir Realme of England, that they haue vowed to

correct and roote vp? Is not the ſentence of their crueltie concluded and pronounced aſwell vpon you as againſt vs? how can you then ſhun their ſharpe tyrannie, but taſte the edge of the ſword with vs, if their Romiſh pretences ſhould preuaile? but I doubt you would for a ſhift ſay, Non noui hominem, and denie both Prince and profeſſion. Be it that the ſame would ſerue for a vizard on the ſodaine to maſke your Hipocriſie: in the ende you ſhoulde be accounted traitors, &amp; with the hatefull horror of your conſcience be accompanyed with all curſed calamities to your graue.
            The moſt eloqu
                  •
               nt Cicero after he had diſcouered the ſecrete conſpiracies of Catelin, before the body of the Senate and in open counſell, to his face deliuered him the deuiſes &amp; driftes of all his treaſons, approuing his houſed practiſes to tend to encampe robberies, to the murthering of the nobilitie, &amp; to the burning of their Citie, and ſhewing howe hys confederates attended his comming. What cauſe could procure ſwifter iuſtice? they knew it they had him in hand, &amp; yet then (in Princely pollicie) they willed him to depart the Citie: ſuppoſing it more perill to haue him among them, than in the field with diſplayed bāner againſt them. Catelin a Pagan, prouoked by pouertie, kindled by priuate grudge, and heaued vp by an Ethnick hope, to better his wretched ſtate, as a deſperate man conſpired againſt men: But you Chriſtians, preſſed with no penurie, wallowing in wealth, fréed from all cauſe of contention, ſitting in ſafetie, &amp; dwelling in that happie condition as no age did euer ſo floriſhe nor any of your innouation can continue the like for all degrées, conſpire againſt God, againſt your louing &amp; moſt fauourable Quéene, &amp; againſt the foyle &amp; ſeate that firſt gaue you 
                  •
               ire and fuſtenance, which ſurely ſo long as you continue vnder the ſeruitude &amp; yoke of Papiſtrie, is a moſt true principle of your pretence.
            Therefore (in the bowels of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt) I humbly deſire you, as brethren by one Father, ſeruantes to one Maiſtreſſe, and children of one moulde, to ſearche the

Scriptures, to looke into the mercie of his heauenly Maieſtie, to remember hir Graces ſwéete and reclaiming countenance to you all, and in pittie to beholde your moſt deare mother, on whoſe knées you haue bin dandled, &amp; at whoſe England. breaſt you haue bin nouriſhed euen from your byrth.
            But if you be minded to perſiſt in your peruerſe opinions, and that no milke or meate can pleaſe your pallets, vnleſſe it come from Rome: if you cannot abide the bleſſed light of hir Maieſties life: if you cannot endure the heauenly countenance of hir ioyfull regard: or if you account hir Princely Perſon to be the eye ſore to your ſorrow: I ſay with Cicero to Catelin, flie to your Pope, leaue both Court &amp; Countrey, and ſhunne the light of the Sunne, that ſo much doth dazell your ſight, and let good ſubiectes enioy the benefite of that you are ſo much vnworthy of. Your owne experience ſheweth that no practize will preuaile to harme one haire of hir head whom next God you hate moſt: for the Lord of hoſtes doth kéepe hir, he hath ſet legions of Angels about hir, they houer ouer hir, they marche with hir, they goe before hir, and garde hir from all treaſons: they make knowne your wayes, they deliuer hir your drifts, and they diſcouer your very thoughtes vnto hir. This you aſſuredly ſée, that the whole courſe of hir Maieſties life is myraculous: and yet your Pharao like wilfulneſſe will not obſerue any parte of it. When you haue turned the houre Glaſſe of your owne errours, you ſhall finde how many ſandes of ſorrowe doth runne in miſchiefe to the laſt minute. But God of his mercy make you to know him, to loue our gratious Quéene, and in the duetie of true ſubiectes to honour hir and obey hir, and to giue hir a Mathuſalems age to gouerne vs. Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

