
   
      
         
            The triall of true friendship or perfit mirror, wherby to discerne a trustie friend from a flattering parasite. Otherwise, A knacke to know a knaue from an honest man: by a perfit mirrour of both: soothly to say; trie ere you trust; beleeue no man rashly. No lesse profitable in obseruing, then pleasant in reading. By M.B.
            M. B., fl. 1596.
         
         
            
               1596
            
         
         Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00401
            STC 1053
            ESTC S110413
            99845963
            99845963
            10896
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00401)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10896)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 195:04)
         
         
            
               
                  The triall of true friendship or perfit mirror, wherby to discerne a trustie friend from a flattering parasite. Otherwise, A knacke to know a knaue from an honest man: by a perfit mirrour of both: soothly to say; trie ere you trust; beleeue no man rashly. No lesse profitable in obseruing, then pleasant in reading. By M.B.
                  M. B., fl. 1596.
               
               [36] p.   
               
                  By Valentine Simmes dwelling on Adling hill at the signe of the white swanne,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1596.
               
               
                  Signatures: A²  B-E⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2006-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE TRIALL of true Friendſhip; Or perfit mirror, wherby to diſcerne a truſtie friend from a flattering Paraſite. Otherwiſe, A knacke to know a knaue from an honest man: By a perfit mirrour of both: Soothly to ſay; Trie ere you trust; Beleeue no man raſhly. No leſſe profitable in obſeruing, then pleaſant in reading. By M. B.
            Imprinted at London by Valentine Simmes dwelling on Adling hill at the ſigne of the white Swanne. 1596.
         
         
            
            
            
               
                  〈…〉
                
               Walter Flude, Gentleman V.S. wiſheth all happineſſe.
            
               TO recognize (ſir) in multitude of wordes, how much charged I ſtand vnto your bountie, were to your wiſedome, I knowe, but friuolous, who better reſpecteth the inward ſeruice intended of any one (wherof I humbly beſeech you on my part to ſtand aſſured) than an outward behauior, the validitie whereof manie wayes may be doubted. Yet neuertheleſſe, in that the thoughts of men are onlie in word or action to be deſciphered, let it, I beſeech you, ſtand with your good fauour, that I may by this litle mite of my friendes labours confeſſe my ſelf bound vnto you: and for the reſidue, when it ſhal ſeeme good vnto you to commaund mee, I will not

haue life or abilitie that ſhall not bee yours, in all it may pleaſe you to vſe me. Thus much to haue deliuered, may, for the preſent, ſatisfie my mind but thus much to haue perfourmed, would content my ſoule, for that in al actions of the body inwardly to be effected, the minde is pleaſed with ſpeach, and the heart only is repleniſhed by the dooing. Much more to haue proteſted, were no more than ſufficient, though more than wherewith your modeſtie will be pleaſed, for which, I remaine in heart more than in abilitie to anſwere the ſame: humbly ſubmitting my poor ſeruice to the cenſure thereof, and recommending you vnto the protection of the Almightie, and to the happy poſſeſsing of your hearts beſt content.
            
               Yours euer affectionate, Valentine Simmes.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               The triall of true Friendſhip, Or, A Knacke to know a knaue from an honest man.
            
            
               THe gods deſirous (as Poets faine) to ſhew forth the omnipotencie of their deity &amp; their incomparable cunnings vnited in one, to the intent they might purchaſe themſelues ſome great commendations and honour vppon earth, determined to carue a peece of ſome curious perfection, wherein might be expreſſed the ſubſtance of the gods, and beautie of the graces: whereupon they framed a man ſo angelical in forme &amp; exquiſit in feature, that as for the lineaments of his face, or the proportion of his body, it was impoſſible to ſay the leaſt thing imaginary to be any where wanting. This demie-god being perfected and ſent vpon the earth, when as none could condemn either the creature of want, or the creators for lacke of ſkil; Momus at length found this fault, that the gods had not made a window in his breaſt through which to perceiue the inward thoughts and ſecrets of his heart (meaning as I coniecture) that as the glitteringſt Diamond being broken diſtilleth the deadlieſt poyſon, as the ſtone Ceuranon burneth without when it freezeth within, and as the Nightingale hath a moſt ſweete voice, but vnfauourie fleſh: ſo there is none ſo comely in his body, but may be corrupt in his mind, none ſo fine in his feature, but may be faultie in his faith, nor any ſo louing in his looke, but may be lowring in his heart. Whereupon I thinke that Tully in his booke de Amicitia, conſidering the double dealing of men, how they carried moſt commonly two faces like

               Ianus vnder one hood, hauing as wel wrinkles in the one to prognoſticate miſhap, as dimples in the other to ſignifie proſperity: and like the leaues of the Seaulpher, to be greene and beutiful in loue and affection outwardly, when their rootes or hearts were withered and dead in good wil inwardly, counſelleth Scaeuola and Fannius vnder the perſon of Laelius aboue al other things, as the cheefeſt principal belonging to finde a friend, that they ſhould firſt multos modios ſalis ſimul edere, &amp;c. meaning that they ſhould be ſo farre from chooſing a friend at the firſt ſight, that they ſhould neither giue any their hearts, nor hands, vntil by reaſon of their long acquaintance and conuerſation together they might haue had time to haue eaten many buſhels of ſalt. For ſeeing there is nothing more neceſſary vnto the life of man then to be enuironed with faithful and vnfained friends, into whom he may tranſport his affections, repoſe his ſecrets, and commit his enterpriſes, ſo he ought to beſtow the greateſt paines and careful induſtry in the finding of them, eſpecially in theſe our preſent times wherein flatterie is become ſuch a common arte and ſo much practiſed of moſt men, that almoſt euery ruſticall companion &amp; illiterate peſant can repreſent like a looking-glaſſe what mans quallities and conditions he wil: So that good cauſe hath euery one with Vliſſes to feare the inchāting harmony of ſweet ſinging Syrens, ſeeing vnder the faireſt flower often lurkes the fouleſt ſerpent and thoſe that profeſſe moſt liberal affection in words, are oft proued the deadlieſt enemies in deede. Wherfore not without good reaſon did Darius eſteeme more of his faithful Zaphirus then of his conqueſt of an hundred chiefe-taines of his Babilonian enemies, for kingdomes may be gotten by pollicie, and enimies ſubdued by the ſword, but an vnfained friend by neither to be obtained, wherefore Zeno the philoſopher was of this opinion that the loſſe of a friend was only to be lamented: which Ageſilans the Greeke ſeemeth alſo to affirme, who being demanded why he did more lament the heauines of his friends then the death of his children, made anſwere, I do not bewail the want of my wife, the loſſe of my goods, or the death of my children, for al theſe are but parts of my ſelfe: but I bewaile the death of my friend which is another my ſelfe, whoſe

like I am not likely euer to light vpon, ſeeing true frendſhip is ſo ſeldome ſeene, and being ſeene, ſo greatly admired, ſo that we reade of Alexander, who for his noble conqueſts and ſpatious regiment, was ſurnamed the great, that in al the prouinces kingdomes, and empires, which moſt victoriouſly he paſſed through, he found but one faithful and vnfained friend named Caliſtenes: The like we reade of Xerxes, Nero, Dioniſius, &amp; many other renowmed peers and potentates in the world, who are not reported to haue had any more then one friend. And if we allow of the counſel of Seneca a wiſe and diſcreete man, if he might haue many (as he cannot) yet wil not admitte any more then one: for if there be danger (ſaith he) in enemies, there can be no ſurety in the multitude of friends, ſeeing in reſpect of their number they breede difference of conſent and wil, with variety of conditions: and where is no conformitie of manners, there can be no perfectiō in friendſhip. Furthermore one friend ought not to ſay to another, I wil not, or, I can not, ſince it is a priuilege in friendſhip to find nothing impoſſible: therefore who ioynes friendſhip with another, binds himſelfe not to deny the thing that his friend requires him to do, ſeeing in this conſiſts the ful office of frendſhip, to owe to our friends our ſelues and al that we haue. But how can a man that is ſaid to haue many friends, execute this office of true friendſhip, when in the ſame inſtance one friend inuites him to a banket, and another ſends for him being ſicke: one requeſts him to pleade his cauſe againſt his aduerſarie at London, and another to ride with him about other affaires to Douer, where you ſee he can do his dutie to no more but one, and conſequently al the reſt do ſeeme to be deſpiſed, &amp; their friendſhip little or not at al regarded: wherby it appeareth, that true friendſhip can bee onely in the duall number, namely an vnfained conſent of two mens willes and affections, &amp; a tranſportation of two hearts into one body: and therefore a frend is called alter idem, another moity, or another ſelfe. The riuer that is diuided into many brookes, experience ſhewes vs the ſtreame to be very ſlowe and ſhallow: ſo loue which is deuided amongſt many cannot bee ſo great as that which hath but one ſubiect to worke on: and therefore Homer ſpeaking of a child whom his, father entirely loueth indeede,

calleth him Solum, atque in ſenio natum, that is, his fathers only ſonne, and borne when his parents were paſt hope to haue any more. Wherefore ſeeing thou canſt haue but one true friend, whoſe boſom muſt be a place of retract for al thy counſels, opinions, actions, and interpriſes, what care and circumſpections oughteſt thou to haue in chooſing this one. They that trie poyſon by the taſte, deſtroy themſelues therewith, and he that wil admit a friend before he knoweth him, moſt commonly hurts himſelfe whileſt he proueth him, as the Satire thought the fire to bee ſome great goddeſſe, by reaſon of the brightneſſe and warmth that it gaue, &amp; therefore would needs imbrace it, and kiſſe it, hauing burnt his venturous lips, Prometheus tolde him the nature and force thereof: ſo paraſites or flatterers becauſe their words are pleſant to the eare, many imbrace them &amp; commit themſelues and al that they haue vnto them, til hauing tried their more ſecret operation they beginne to crie Caue when their coyne is conſumed, and to be chary whē they haue nothing whereof to take charge, then they can tell others, that mens harts and tongues, are no perfect relatiues, and that it is not alwaies true, that what the heart thinks, the tongue clacketh, &amp; can verifie it with a probatum of their owne. It were better to be wiſe too ſoone then repent too late, and to looke before we leape, leſt we fall into their ditch, for if we are once downe, there are few that wil lend vs their hands to help vs vp againe and carry vs through al the ſtormy waues of our diſtreſſe, as the dolphin did Arion, but euery one almoſt will anſwere as they did the young man in Plautus in his neceſſity, with a Non eſt, that is, faith friend you come to a wrong box, I ſtand in as much need as your ſelfe, or as the crow did the kite, when it happened the one to be bare of feathers, the other anſwered, that to him were no more then ſufficed him to flie, and yet they wil promiſe one in his proſperity neuer to forſake him, as Peter promiſed Chriſt, who in a while after did vtterly denie him, and forſweare too, therefore not vnfitly did Plinie compare men vnto the fifh Palerna, which being paſſing white in the calme, yet becommeth blacke at euery ſtorme, and like vnto the Heban bloſſomes, which open with the dew and ſhut with the ſunne: ſo in proſperitie they fawne, but in aduerſitie

they fade, they honor the ſunne at his vpriſing with the Egyptians, but curſe him at his going down, yea thoſe on whom we beſtow the greateſt benefits, if opportunitie ſerue, wil requite vs with the deadlieſt hate. The Troians neuer ſhewed more fauour vnto any then vnto wretched Sinon, who afterward betraied their citie vnto the Gaecians: and none was more welcome vnto Carthage, then ſtraggling Aeneas, and yet hee repaied them with moſt ſhameful abuſes: Seuerus the Emperor neuer beſtowed more benefits vpon any, then on his ſeruant Plautianus, for he made him copartner with him in thempire, who ſhamed not for all this to hire Saturninus trecherouſly to murther his frend ſo faithful and lord ſo louing, Seuerus: The Babilonians neuer truſted any more then the forenamed Zopirus who moſt villanouſly betraied them into the hand of Darius: And Thraſo in Terence, neuer affected man more then his paraſite Gnatho, by whom he was deliuered vp as a prey to his enimies, with an hunc ego comedendum &amp; bibendum vobis propino. But if theſe and the reſt whom we reade to haue taſted of the ſame ſauce had prudently pondered the ſugered ſubtilties of the world, they needed not to haue locked the dore when the ſteede was ſtolen, nor by their owne harmes to haue learned to beware. Therefore ſeeing we perceiue the trap, let vs not fooliſhly follow the traine, nor ſwallow the bait, wherin is ſhrowded the intent of our bane, neither let vs thinke with the pike to caſt vp the hooke which we haue ſwallowed, when wee pleaſe without preiudice to our perſons, for if we haue once entertained a knaue we ſhal not eaſily be rid of him, but preſently hee becomes like fulſome meate which wee cannot keepe in our ſtomackes, without hurting vs, nor vomit it vp alone as it went in, but mingled with other meate, which would haue nouriſhed and cheriſhed vs: So when we haue receiued a counterfait and harbored him, with our hindrances we can neither continue with him but he wil hurt vs, neither ſhake him off ſo clearely, but heiwil go better away then he came, therefore Principijs obſta, take heede at the firſt, and thou ſhalt do wel inough, beleue not at the firſt that it is gold becauſe it gliſtreth, neither ſweare that the Polipus is white, becauſe he ſeemed ſo once vnto thee, nor that ſuch a one is an honeſt man, becauſe

thou neuer foundeſt him otherwiſe: for Proteus can turne himſelfe into more ſhapes then one, and Iupiter if he would compaſſe the loue of a faire ladie, can turne himſelfe from a bull, into a ſhowre of gould to deceiue ſimple Danae: ſo a paraſite hath more cranckes in his budget to deceiue then one: he hath one for the ſcholler, another for the courtier, one for the marchant, another for the yeoman, one for this good fellow, another for that. If he chaunce to meete with a ſcholler in the Vniuerſity troubled with an heauie purſe, preſently he calles to mind the ſaying of S. Paul, that willes vs to beare one anothers burden, and therefore without delay whileſt the ſpirit knocks he wil open, leſt be find not ſo much grace at another time, and therefore (becauſe birds of a feather wil flie together, and the ſcholler wil truſt or beleeue the ſcholler, rather then another) he begins to be as preciſe as a knaue in a cage: firſt he puts on the blacke cloake &amp; the falling hand, then he walkes like Bellona in her equipage, with his eyelids cloſe, hee ſpeakes nothing without Propterea quod, to conclude, all the day he is in contemplation, or rather meditation how hee may beſt eaſe his brother of his burden, but if he perceiue that hee hath met with a wilie brother that hath read ouer Plutarch de diſcrimine adulatoris &amp; amici, then off goes the blacke cloake &amp; the long picardeuaunt, and hee muſt be cut againe according to the faſhion, then he makes rimes on Platoes crooked ſhoulders, and tries how he can ſcoffe at Ariſtotles ſtammering voice. If he chance to meete Bias ſomewhat whitteld in an alehouſe as hee walkes alone, as Struthias did, he commends him highly for ouercomming ſo many pewter-Iohns, and tells him how Alexander is as much famous for his quaffing, as Thales, Solon, Periander, Cleobulus, Chilon, and Pittacus were for their wiſedome, yea as Miſon himſelfe, whom Apollo ſaid to be wiſer then him. Furthermore he ſhewes him that a man is not borne onely for himſelfe, but alſo for his neighbours, and therefore it is a good deede of charitie to helpe a poore ale-wife away with a dozen of beere next his heart in a morning, alſo it is good to increaſe bloud, to quicken the ſpirit, and ſo to ſpeake more wiſely, and conſeqúently, to be more eſteemed, and therfore wils him to call in the other halfe dozen, till at the laſt hee

hath brought into his fooles paradiſe (his bed I meane) where he ſtrips him as cleane of his come as an ape of a taile, before drunken Bias can get out of his memento. Againe if he fal acquainted with an idle and ſhameful magiſtrate, which cares not (as they ſay) which end goes formoſt, hee tells him magiſtracie is but a troubleſome toiling in other mens buſines, and the moſt profit that a man ſhal reape thereby, is but a wind of mens mouthes, and the moſt buſie bodies haue leaſt thankes, for their labours, and therefore it were as good, to neither medle nor make, as to troble himſelfe and be neuer the better, but if hee perceiue him to be very laborious and painefull in his office, hee alſo beginneth to change his note, and tells him that it is a pleaſant thing to bee idle, but verie ful of diſcredit, and a man that hath loſt his credit, is halfe hanged &amp;c. If hee companie with ſome liberal ſeruing creature hee can geſſe at his conditions, which are moſt commonly to ſweare, drinke, and hunt after whoores, if hee be a young practiſioner he teacheth him to ſwill it in, and ſweare it out, he reproues him friendly if he ſweare any baſe or beggarly oath, as by faith and troth, and as God ſhal iudge him, he telles him if hee loue his credit he muſt thunder them out like Iupiter, or elſe he ſhames himſelfe and al his friends. If he ſee him not wel at eaſe, he wiſhes him to purge himſelfe, if he underſtand not this myſtery, he tells him more plainly, that for a peece of money he wil fetch him a ſuppoſitiue out of petticoate lane that ſhal make him purge out all the groſſe humours in his body. But if hee perceiue him better diſpoſed, hee tells him that he plaies the part of an honeſt man, and al that he ſaid was naught, but to trie him, and if he had bin bent that way, friendly to haue diſwaded him from it, by which meanes he wins the loue and friendſhip of al men vnto himſelfe. But it were a world to ſay as much as might be ſaid, and altogether vnneedeful, ſeeing wee may gather by Hercules his foote, the greatnes of his whole body, &amp; by theſe few things that flattery is a miſtery, which euery foole cannot vnfolde at the firſt. But if thou wouldeſt know the ſafeſt and ſureſt way to eſcape their fingers, then harken vnto the counſel of Epicarmus ſaying, Eſto ſobrius ac memento nulli temerè credere, that is, be wiſe and circumſpect in thy dealings,

and beleeue no man raſhly. Into which counſell before we go any further, let vs looke more narrowly: of whom doth he bid vs beware? What? of our enemies? why there is none ſo fooliſh except he be ſtarke mad (I thinke) as was Aeſops cocke that would beleeue the fox, to folow his counſel, of whom he knowes he is deadly hated, therefore belike he biddeth vs to beware of our friends, neighbors, and alies, whom no man miſtruſts, euery one beleeues and wil ſweare for their fidelitie. Therefore let vs call to mind whether our manifeſt, ſworne, &amp; profeſſed enemies haue done vs moſt miſchief, or our ſuppoſed friends, our kinſmen, and allies. Surely if we would ſearch into hiſtories (witneſſes of former times) we ſhall perceiue more caſtles ouerthrowne, cities ouercome, kingdomes and empires vtterly waſted and extinguiſhed, by falſe hearted frends, and outwardly ſworne brethren, then by the mightie hand of proclaimed ennemies, as Troy ſuffered more dammage in one night by Sinons fained teares, then by the power of the Graetians in ten yeares, and more complaints in aduerſitie of acquaintance and frends, then accuſations of enemies, for againſt our enemies we furniſh our ſelues by ſea and land, wee erect ſtrong and mightie caſtles on the bordures, wee furniſh them with men, and munition, and al things requiſite for the defence of our liues, and liuing, and therefore we ſeldome are aſſaulted, and if we be, we eaſily ouercome, but among fellow citizens qui ijſdem ſacris ac fames vtuntur, there is continuall iangling and brawling, often going to law, yea betweene brother and brother, for iniuries offered: ſo that the miſerly father who hath bin a ſcraping together a little pelfe al his life time, caring not which way he came by it, ſeemeth to haue liued to haue ſet folkes together by the eares at his death; namely, the deuills for his ſoule, and his children for his goods, what then ſhould a man do to liue a quiet and peaceable life, and ſafe from the ſnares and engins of all men? ſhould hee ſeuer himſelfe from the company of all men as Timon the Athenian did? or els ſhuld he haue no eares like the picture of Iupiter in Creet, whereby he might be deceiued? ſhould hee ſcratch out his eies with the Biſhop of Alexandria for feare of Venus charmes? or with Lewes the ſecond ſonne of Charles, king of Fraunce
               
hide himſelf in corners, to the intent he might neuer be intrapped? rather let him harken to the counſel of Pythagoras, who wiſheth one gaudere potiùs repugnantibus quam aſſentantibus, rather to truſt his profeſſed enemie whome hee knoweth hates him, then his trencher-friends and pedantical paraſites that ſeeme to loue him, which will praiſe him as the foxe did the fooliſh crow, and cal him a white bird as white as the driuē ſnow, that they may make him open his mouth to ſing after their pipe that they may deceiue him of the meate therein: and when they once haue it, will not ſticke to ſay, Nec vocem ſtulte, nec mentem habes, that is, friend, you might looke better to your goods when you had them, and ſeeing you were ſuch a foole to lauiſh them out ſo fondly, you are like to haue a fooles reward, which is a flap with a foxe taile. Thinke not therefore with the ſwallow, euery ſun-ſhine to be a ſummers day, and euery one that ſhewes thee a faire face, to beare thee inwardly a faithfull heart, but thinke that the leaues of the Date tree wil change their colour if the wind be not alwayes in the ſame quarter: that Dedalus images wil flie away if they be not alwaies tied, &amp; that flatterers wil fade if thou bind them not daily with the bands of thy purſe ſtrings, therefore Dioſcorides compareth them to the Celedony ſtone, which retaineth his vertue no longer then it is rubbed with gold, and vnto the Marigold which openeth her leaues as long as the Sunne ſhineth, but with the leaſt cold begins to cloſe: So when fortune fauoureth a man, they laugh, when ſhe frowneth on him, they lowre. In proſperitie their loue is as hote as Aetna, but in calamitie as cold as Caucaſus, therfore truely ſaid Iuuenal:
               
                  In pretio precium nunc eſt, dat cenſus honores,
                  Cenſus amicitias, pauper vbique iacet:
               
that is, as long as fortune fauoureth thee, thou ſhalt not want fellowes, or as long as thou haſt any ſubſtance thou ſhalt not want accidental adherents, which wil not leaue thee ſine interitu ſubiecti, that is, before al thy ſubſtance be waſted and conſumed: therefore not vnfitly may their loue be compared to the loue of the Iuie to the Oake, the Iuie roundeth it ſelfe as it were for pure loue about the oake, and neuer leaueth to creepe vp til it hath aduaunced it ſelfe to the higheſt of all, and ſuckte

out the ſap leaues, and dried it vp, the greene leaues in the meane time make a faire and glorious ſhew, but in the end whē it hath clunged cloſe and climed aloft it marreth al both top and truncke: So whileſt thou haſt any coine thou ſhalt not want copeſmats which wil make a ſhew that they loue thee as their owne ſoules, but vpon this conditiō, that they may grow vp by thee, and liue brauely by thy meanes, for they are not euery knaues companions, they ſcorne thoſe poore, baſe and beggarly brats which are ready to drowne themſelues with Theognes becauſe they haue no meate to put in their mouthes, and they eſteme no more of fine Thraſo without pence, then a horſe doth a faire ſtable without prouender, this is their final ſcope, which is, primum in intentione, the firſt and principalleſt thing they aime at, and therefore they hie themſelues thither where it is to be had, namely, among noble and wealthie perſonages, who hauing their cloſets watred with the Indian or Pactolian fountaines, &amp; ſtored with ſuch trees as Aeneas pluckt a bough off, when hee went to viſit his father in the Elifian meades, theſe they flatter and ſooth vp in all that they do, do they neuer ſo bad, about theſe they ſwarme as thicke as flies about butchers ſhambles. What a goodly company of them (think you) had the gold-glutted Midas waiting at his heels, when he was indued with that ſpirit-gladding gift of Bacchus, that al which he touched ſhould turne to gold. I warrant ye Caſſandra ſtriued not halfe ſo much to ſing vnto her father Ileons deſtruction and Queene Helens rape, as theſe thronged and ſtriued, who ſhould be next him, for quid non mortalia pectora cogit auri ſacra fames, what wil not the omnipotencie of Gold make a mā to do, it is the neceſſarieſt thing that a man can haue, as Liſander ſaid, what more requiſite in warres, and what more needful in peace? it hath entred thoſe cities which neither the thundring threats of fiery Iupiter, nor the roaring ſhot of bloudie Mars could euer ouercome, it is a friend to al good arts, and a nurſe to all notable exploits, for as Ariſtotle ſaith impoſsibile eſt, vt quis praeclaras res agat, cui facultates deſunt, it is as impoſſible that a man ſhould do any excellent act or worthie of commendations without the helpe of money, as to builde a church without ſtone or timber, therefore quaerenda pecunia

primum, firſt get money, and then all things elſe ſhal be giuen vnto thee: whereas pouertie is an enemie to all goodnes, an enimie to honour, and an enemie to honeſtie, for what cauſeth ſo many now a daies to get their liuing by robbing, and ſtealing, but onely pouertie? what prouoketh many women to ſell their honeſty at ſo low a rate, as vſually they do, but only pouerty? what cauſeth the marchant to lie, the coiner to clip, the tailour to ſteale, the vſurer to oppreſſe, and the paraſite to purloine, but onely pouertie? name but onely pouertie, and thou haſt named almoſt the roote of al euils, therefore is it ſhunned as a Baſilike of al men, whoſe ſight preſently killeth, wherefore few or none at al wil lend a looke on a poore and needy man, but wil ſhun his companie as neare as they can, yea euen the lice the ſenceles creatures of all will auoide a man when his bloud is gone, and the fleſh is cold, which was their foode: how then canſt thou perſwade thy ſelfe, that a man which is a reaſonable creature wil ſtay thee? when thy purſe is colde, thy cheere is cold, and his entertainment therefore of neceſſitie is colde. Moreouer, it is ſome mens opinion that the Deuil wil haunt ſuch as haue no croſſe about them, how then wilt thou thinke that any man wil ſtay with thee, if thou haſt neuer a croſſe about thee to keepe the diuel away, doubt not then but they wil leaue thee when thy croſſes are ſpent in thy extremitie, and therefore truſt them not too much in thy proſperitie, when they flatter and ſpeake thee faire, but remember that after the greateſt calme will follow the ſuddeneſt ſtorme, that Nilus is moſt quieteſt againſt a deluge, that the feathers of the Halciones gliſter moſt againſt foule weather, and that when men ſpeake moſt faire, then they intend moſt miſchiefe. It is not ſo common a ſaying as true, aliquid latet quod non patet, euery man is not as he ſeemes to be, the arrant knaue is often taken for the honeſter man, and Critius ſometimes wil chooſe a gilden boxe full of bones, before a leaden one ful of pretious gems, for men iudge onely by the outward appearance and proteſtations of men, and ſo chuſe an empty barrel for his louder ſound, before a full veſſel of pleſant liquor, and beleeue ſubtil Rodeyan becauſe ſhe can tel the ſmoother tale before ſimple Cordeill, and prefer deceitful Vliſſes for his eloquent tongue before faithful

               Aiax a mirror of manhood. But as the Troians bewailed their raſhnes in beleeuing too late, when their citie was metamorphoſed into aſhes, and the Graetians repented their iudgement when their valiant captaine was turned into a flower, ſo vnles thou art more conſiderate then the Troians, and leſſe raſh then the Graetians, thou maiſt haue iuſt cauſe one day to rue thy leaping when thou lieſt in the ditch. Miſerrimum eſt (ſaith one) fuiſſe bearum it is the greeuouſeſt thing in the world for a man in his miſery to remember his former felicitie, labour therefore to auoide this helliſh dolour, which vnleſſe thou takeſt heede, thou art like to fal into. The deere knowing Tamariſke is deadly to his nature, wil not come neere the tree. The Vnicorne wil not brooke to reſt vnder the Citron tree, for that it is hurtful vnto him, neither wil any beaſt come neare the Panther for al his faire ſkin, ſince they know by experience that he is a murtherer, theſe beaſts auoid what nature tells them is perilous, be not therfore leſſe ſenceles then the beaſts of the field, but let experience be thy guide when affections perſwade the contrarie, remember what credulous Phillis wanne, by beleeuing demure Demophoon, but onely her death, what got Craſſus by truſting his paraſite Andromachus, but to be betraied to the Parthians? and what wanne Catiline by opening his conſpiracie, but the loſſe of his life and honor? and what are thou like to get by truſting of flatterers, but the loſſe of thy goods, the extinguiſhment of thy armes, the deriſion of thy enimies, and the curſe of thy poſteritie? therefore caſt them off from thee as infectious vipers, and ſalute them a farre off, as Hippolitus did Venus, becauſe he would not be intangled, &amp; if thou muſt needs company with them, if their words be like Adamant, whoſe nature is to draw, then ſprinkle thee with goats bloud, which reſiſteth his operation: and if their faces haue power to incenſe thy mind, then take the hearbe Lupinar to coole thy deſire, if the Syrens allure thee, let the maſte withhold thee, if Circes perſwade thee, let reaſon diſſwade thee, if thou wouldeſt kiſſe the Bee, becauſe ſhee hath honny in her mouth, yet let her alone, becauſe ſhe hath a ſting in her taile: if thou wouldeſt embrace Pallas, becauſe ſhe ſhewes thee her librarie, yet be not too bold, becauſe ſhee weares a ſword: and if

thou loueſt a man for his affection towards thee now, yet truſt him not ouer boldely leſt he hate thee to morrow, and make open thy ſecrets: what is more common then deſſentiō amongſt friends, and variance betweene brethren, ſo that they that loue to day as truely as Turtles, to morrow vpon the leaſt occaſion, as if they had drunke of the fountaine of Ardenia, their hot loue wil be turned to as cold a liking? We neede not borrow examples from former ages or antiquity, for (alas) euery citty. towne, and village, can lend vs whole legions of them, how one friend hath ſlaine another, how the father the children, and children haue ſlaine their fathers, yea they do not onely not abſtaine from murthering their deareſt friends and neareſt in bloud, but alſo if they be defeated of their wil, or iniured of one of whom they know not how to be reuenged, they wil not feare to kill themſelues, as Aiax did being defeated by Vliſſes of Achilles armour. Therefore how ſhould we thinke that they wil alwaies loue vs, when they wil hate themſelues, ſeeing euery one loueth himſelfe better then another, according to the old prouerb, Neere is my petticoate, but nearer is my ſmocke, I loue thee wel, but I loue my ſelfe better: thinke not then that there is any ſuch a Gordian knot of vnfained friendſhippe knit ſo faſt to day, but there may be an Alexander to cut it in peeces at one time or other: nor any ſuch a ſolemne league made betweene Priamus and Menelaus, but there is a Pandorus ſomewheare or other that wil breake and diſſolue it: nor any ſuch a Simpathy of affections to day, but there may be an Antipathy by ſome chance or other, ere the yeare is gone about. The ſea ſometimes is ſo calme and quiet, that the fearefulleſt that is will ſeeme to deſpiſe and contemne the force thereof; but therefore haue the ſailers leſſe neede to carrie with them their ankors and cabelles and other things needefull, when windes ſhould ariſe? no ſurely, for although Aeolus ſleepe for a while and wil diſquiet no man els, and ſuffers Phoebus to domineere as ſole Regent, yet if he perceiued him waxe too hote in his pride, he beginnes to moderate his affections commonly with a cooling card or twaine, by his tempeſtuous embaſſadours to put him in mind that he is a king as wel as himſelfe, and although ſometimes in his anger he roareth and is teſtie, yet he

wil not altogether be ſhut out for a wrangler. In like manner they that follow thy humors for a while in flattering thee with the Panther, in ſmiling on thee with the Hiena, and weeping with the Crocodile at thy miſhaps, and that are ready to make themſelues thy footeſtoole in lowly obedience as the Ciprian women were to the Syrian dames, which would cower downe and become footeſtooles for the Ladies to aſcend into their choches (for which cauſe they were called Climacidae of Climacha, which the Aſſirians name a ladder) but when they ſee their time they wil of ſteps become ſteppers, til they are got ſo high that they are become as good men as their maſters, and then for one taunt wil not ſticke to giue them twaine. I cannot reſemble them better, then vnto the lake in the fartheſt part of Affrica amongſt the people Troglotidae which in the forenoone is ſo ſweet and pleaſant to the taſte, that the gods themſelues might ſeem to loath the celeſtial Nectar in reſpect therof: but when the ſunne is gone paſt, the meridian climate it wil be as bitter and vnſauourie as our welles are in Nantewich, which are good for nought but to make ſalt: So whileſt the glorious ſunne of thy proſperitie continues his aſcenſion, whilſt riches increaſe and fortune looketh fauourably, they wil kiſſe thee with Iudas, and ſtoope to thee with diſſembling Adraſtus: but when the golden beames of thy beutiful Sunne, begin to decreaſe, and thou art not able any longer to make thē ſtoope vnto thee, with the golden ſcepter with Aſſuerus, they wil begin to deſpiſe thee, and forſake thee, or elſe lay hands on thee for a vagabond, as they did on Chriſt when he walked alone in the darke. Then mought he haue ſaide with the Poet:
            Qui color albus erat nunc eſt contrarius albo.
            Now I perceiue when the angels crowned me with glory and honour in the mount, they were deſirous to make their tabernacles there to dwel with me, and when I rode triumphantly toward Ieruſalem, theſe pluckt off their garments to ſpread them in my way, and to runne before like heraulds crying, Hoſanna, Hoſanna, bleſſed be he that commeth in the name of the Lord. But going on foote, my diſciples to whom I reuealed al my ſecrets which I kept from the wiſe and prudent men of the world, whom I thought would rather haue beene rackte to

death with Horatius Secundus to haue manifeſted their conſtancie, haue now either forſaken me, or betraied me, or ſworne they neuer knew me: theſe other ſpit at me, take my garments from me, and curſe me, or crucifie me: ſo vnles thou takeſt the better heed whom thou truſteſt, thou maieſt haue cauſe one day to ſay; thoſe to whom I cōmitted al the thoughts and ſecrets of my heart, whom I thought would neuer haue bewraied me, do now ſeek to kill me if they could, thoſe who flattered me in my proſperitie, and were readie to run through fire &amp; water to get my fauor or good wil to grace them, do labour only to diſgrace me, thoſe whom I fed with my goods as long as I could, as willingly as the Pelican doth her yong ones, with her owne bloud, do now teare my heart with taunts like as yong Vipers gnawe their dams guts which bred them. Res eſt ingenioſae dare, I was an honeſt gentleman as long as I had anie money in my purſe, but now hauing ſpent al vpon them, they turn me out of their company as a ſhake-ragge, as the Athenians turned Theſeus out of Athens which hee builded on his owne charges and beſtowed vpon them, which things do more vex &amp; trouble me, then thoſe greeuous gripes of the Eagle do Tantalus in hell, hee was puniſhed iuſtly becauſe he bewraied the ſecrets of the gods: but I moſt vniuſtly, ſeeing I neuer diſcloſed any thing which they told me in counſel and put me in truſt with, they are not vnlike the ſtone Siphnius, which being heated in oyle waxeth hard, but being let alone becommeth ſoft, ſo the more I haue pleaſured them, the more doe they now diſpleaſe me, and the more I haue beſtowed vpon them, the more is their hearts hardned againſt me. Now I perceiue that the ſweeteſt muſke is ſower to be taſted, the fineſt pills, moſt bitter to be chewed, and the flatteringſt friend moſt fickle being tried: and now I vnderſtand that the faireſt promiſes haue leaſt performances, and that words are but wind, and therefore not ſufficient pledges for ſuch an inſeparable knot of friendſhip. But alas, ſerò ſapiunt Phriges, what good wil my ſalue do me when my ſore is incurable? what auaileth it me to know a couert, my ſhip being ſunkt, and to diſcerne a diſſembler, when my coine is conſumed. Although this bee but a fained ſpeech, yet thou that flouriſheſt now in thy peacocks plumes, and haſt

angels enow to keepe thee from pouertie, and haſt as many friends (as thou ſuppoſeſt) as Prometheus euer had ſhapes, &amp; do daily increaſe like Hidraes heads, yet if thou takeſt not heed whom thou truſt, thou maiſt walke alone one day like a ſhorne ſheepe, bleating forth ſuch a complaint of thine owne. Remember the example of Edward the ſecond, I warrant thee he would once haue ſworne that he ſhould neuer haue ſtood vp to the eares in the filthie kennel of Killingworth, till hee was readie to ſtarue for meate, and laſtly ſhould haue beene murthered ſo beaſtly and baſely. But his too tender heart toward his yonkers and wanton flatterers brought him to this, who made him abhorre like Rohoboam, the counſell of his deare friends and graue ſenatours, and ſo to runne headlong into all vices and villanies, vnbeſeeming a Prince or gouernour of a common wealth who is a rule vnto al his ſubiects, after which they ſquare out their actions and affections, as the Poet ſaith, Regis ad exemplum totus componitur orbis, that is as we ſay, Like maſter, like man, if the Prince be vicious, al his ſubiects (for the moſt part) are as bad or rather worſe, as when Traian was iuſt al his ſubiects loued iuſtice, and in Heliogabalus daies, al were wanton and giuen to gluttony and leachery, in that he was a glutton, and a drunkard, and one that loued a whoore as wel as his life: but againe to our matter. Let Edwards example teach vs to beware how we liſten to any Calipſoes that ſeeke nought but our downefal, and how we entertaine al faire faces that come vnto vs like capons, vpon ſops and ſugar, ſeeing ſo many an vnſauoury weede beareth a faire bloſſom, and a ſound looke ſo often couers a hollow heart, but let vs looke into the inward man, as Diogenes did into Platoes capon, to ſee if he were a man in al reſpects, which if wee do, no doubt we ſhal find many a wolfe walking in a ſheepes coate, many a ſtinking carcaſe incloſed within a glorious ſepulcher, and many a Tigers heart ſhadowed ouer with an Hienaes face. Conon the Athenian was a curteous gentleman in countenance, yet a counterfait knaue in conditions: Galba was gentle in ſhew, yet trecherous in proofe: and Vliſſes had a ſaire tongue, but a falſe heart, wherefore it behooueth vs to looke that the inſide of the cup be clean, aſwel as the outſide, to

ſee that the Amber ſtone freeſeth not within, when it frieth without, and to trie whether a mans properties be agreeing to his profeſſion, leſt like Ixion we take hold on a cloud when we thinke to embrace Iuno, and chooſe grapes in ſhew like thoſe of Darius vine, and looſe grapes in ſubſtance like thoſe of Vermandois, and abound with friends in words when we thinke to be inuironed with friends indeede. A man is as his mind is, not that forme and figure which may be pointed at, we ſee many a proper mans hand ſtrocke off for a traitor, and many more ſhould be, if we could know them by the faces, but their countenance ſhal be great, when their conditions be without grace, they wil talke of vertue, when their mind is about ſame other villanie, like as our maidens do now a daies, which with their tongues wil ſacrifice perfumes to Veſta, when their hearts are offering ſmoking thoughts to Venus, ſo that without good trial it is almoſt impoſſible to know of what mettall they are made. Zancthus the Philoſopher ſurely bought not Aeſop before Cappadox and Cantor, for his outward perfections, but for his inward perfection, not for the ſhape of his body, but for the qualities of his mind, not for that he was the faireſt of the three, but the faithfulleſt of them all, not for that he promiſed much, but that he ſaw he could performe moſt: eſt virtus placidis (ſaith the poet) abſtinuiſſe bonus, it is better ſomtimes to take the rugged Iem, before the pearle, &amp; to buy the fowleſt face before the faireſt viſage. Perhaps Cantor and his companion were not vnlike the Seaſter, whoſe ſhell ſtaineth the iuory, but the meate is blacker then Iet: ſo they were not ſo faire without, but they were as foule within, and they had not ſo comely countenances, but they had as curriſh conditions. So chooſe thou not a friend by the outward ſhapes if thou bee a Philoſopher or a louer of wiſedome, but as nere as thou canſt by his inward graces, which knowing, thou maiſt ſee whether thou canſt frame thy mind, according vnto his mind, wherein conſiſteth the perfections of friendſhip, which if thou canſt not, then looke for nothing in contraries but alwaies repugnancie, and in diuers conditions nothing but variancie. The tygres bloud wil not be mingled with the wolfes. Zethis and Amphion wil not agree as long as the delight of the one be a

deſpight to the other. Venus alſo and Veſta haue alwaies bin at ſtrife; and neuer was good fellowſhip long ſeene ere yet betweene a vertuous huſband and a vicious wife, but the deuils for their likenes do eaſily agree, and good men with good men do liue together in vnitie, therefore to diſcerne the inward qualities it is neceſſarie that thou put off thy Moles eies, and take vnto thee the eies of the ſharpe ſighted Linx, elſe thou ſhalt neuer diſcrie with Palamed Vliſſes mad counterfaiting, nor diſcern Achilles from a chambermaid if he be once decked with a ſpindle and a diſtaffe, nor iudge of Androgeni (thoſe flattering copeſinates I meane) that can counterfeit the ſhape of either kind, who when they are indeede thy enimies, are in countenance friends, when they are in name mothers, are in deede murtherers, by birth brothers, but in life lothers and haters one of another. Medea was in name a mother vnto her three children, and oftentimes praied vnto the gods for the proſperous and long life of them al, yea many times ſhe tormented her ſelfe, and tore her haire for very griefe when ſhe perceiued them a litle ſicke, but do theſe things make that ſhe murthered them not with her owne hands? but thou wilt ſay ſhe did it in her anger, which doth depriue vs of the vſe of reaſon, that we do wee know not what, therefore wilt thou thinke that he that is now thy friend, may not hereafter be as much thy foe, ſeeing there is no man but may be angry if he haue any life in him, as Plutharch ſaith?
            Iram non habet, qui mentem non habet.
            Therefore if mothers become murtherers and butchers of their owne children when they are angry, thinke not but the hotteſt loue may be ſoone cold, and he that is now ready to go with thee through al dangers, as Achates went with Aeneas, and Perithous with Theſeus, yet if they ſee any preferment to be gotten an other way, they wil leaue thee in al thy ſorrowes as Aeneas did Dido, although he promiſed neuer to forſake hir when his ſhips were vnrigged, and his men without victuall, but ſome man wil ſay, this man was a ſtranger vnto her, and therefore ſhe was ſerued wel inough to beleeue on whom ſhe neuer ſaw before, but I wil beleeue none but mine owne acquaintance and thoſe that I know. But hath euery hurt bin

offered by ſtrangers? haue none but ſtrangers ſpoiled thee of thy goodes? haue none but ſtrangers murthered and ſlaine one another? haue not kinſmen and brothers, fathers and children, murthered and ſpoyled one another, was not Atreus brother vnto Thieſtes and vnckle vnto the children whom he ſlew and cauſed the father to feede on? was not Herraclus the Emperour ſonne vnto Phocas whom hee cauſed to bee ſlaine? was not Geta the Emperour brother vnto Baſsianus whom he ſlue in the temple in his mothers armes? but if conſanguinitie could haue preuailed, theſe ſhoulde haue loued more then anie elſe: and if conſanguinitie could haue preuailed, Artaxerxes ſhould not haue bin ſlaine with the whole conſent of his 115. children, nor Phrahartes woulde haue ſlaine his father and his 30. brethren, nor Remu
               ▪ ſhould haue bin ſlaine by Romulus for ſo ſmall an occaſion as leaping ouer a wall, nor Clytemneſtra would haue murthered her huſband for the loue of a ſtranger. But let vs paſſe ouer theſe examples, for it is impoſſible to reckon vp al which hiſtories haue notified, but much more impoſſible to recapitulate howe many vnknowen Atrei and Baſsiani and vnnatural Phrahartes, how many Aeropes, Clytemneſtraes, and falſhearted Sthuebaeas haue &amp; do daily lurke in the world, when as euery towne and village is ſtuffed almoſt as full with them, as the Troian horſe was with butchering Graecians. The world is far changed from that it hath bin (if it be true Plutarch reportes) when men would offer violence to none but hurtful beaſts, yea &amp; thought it an hainous offence to lay hands on any other: but in awhile after they began (ſaith he) to kil the innocent birds, and ſilly fiſh, of which when they had felt the ſweetnes, they ſpared not the oxe which laboured for them, nor the ſimple ſheepe which gaue them clothing; ſo that in the end they began to lay hands on mankind alſo, beginning with the worſt, as we read: the firſt that euer was ſlaine in Athens was one Epitedeus, a moſt wicked ſycophant; ſuch alſo were the ſecond and third: but when their hands were ſomwhat inured therewith, they ſlew the vertuous Niceratus, the noble emperor Theramenes; and the moſt learned philoſopher Polimarchus, &amp; in thend, the ſonne ſpared not the father, nor the father the ſon, the brother the ſiſter, nor ye daughter the

mother, ſo that vſe hath made them ſo cunning, that men now adayes make it an occupation, and wil glory in the deede with the barbarous Scythians, who are wont (as Bohemus reporteth) to make them handkerchefs of the ſkinne which they flea from the head of man, and of the ſculles to make meaſures or goblets to drinke in, and when any gheſt comes, they vſe to ſet before him as many ſculles full of wine as they haue, and declare it for a great bragge of their valiantneſſe, that ſo many they haue ſlaine. Wherefore ſeeing conſanguinitie is made ſuch a trifle, how fooliſh or rather ſtarke mad may wee thinke thoſe men are, that ſuppoſe by the meeting ni the market place, or the communing together ouer a pot in an alehouſe, a perpetuall friendſhip to be ioyned from that day forward betweene them? They thinke that veſtis virum facit, that a ſute of ſilkes make a right worſhipful gentleman, and a Mercurian-gloſing tongue a faithfull and vnfained friend: but they remember not that Simia eſt ſimia etiamſi aurea geſtat inſignia, that an ape is an ape although he weare a chaine of gold about his necke; and a knaue is a knaue, although his tongue diſtilles nothing but Nectar, they hold it for a general rule that Sermo eſt animi index, that a filthy fountaine can ſend forth no pleaſant water, and an enuious heart no frendly words, and therefore that the dog neuer biteth but onely when he barketh, nor the ſerpent neuer ſtings but onely when ſhe hiſſeth, nor that any man is their enimie, but hee that reproues or chideth them for their faults: which indeede is the propertie of an vnfained friend, namely to do that that is behoueful, to order his words like a ſkilful phiſition, doth his medicines as he ſeeth occaſion, who ſometimes wil cut and launch the fleſh, and when neede ſo requireth will annoint it with ſoft &amp; pleaſant oile, but both waies tending to one end, viz. that the patient may be healed: ſo one friend ſometimes wil praiſe and highly commend the other when hee ſeeth him doe wel that hereby hee may bring him to loue, and long after thoſe things which are honeſt, &amp; profitable: for honos alit artes (as Tully ſaith) omneſque incenduntur ad ſtudia gloria, honor and praiſe are ſpurs vnto vertue, and cauſe vs to think nothing difficult to be atchieued, nor impoſſible to be performed, and therefore men vndertake ſo great burdens vppon

them in the common wealth, onely to get the praiſe and commendations of men, and to be renowmed after their death, but neglect thoſe things oftentimes which are diſhoneſt, although they be perhaps farre more profitable, and therefore when he ſeeth him do amiſſe he reprehends him ſecretly for it, and laies before him the ſhame and diſhonour which he ſhould reape if it were knowen, yea ſometimes he ſeparates himſelfe from him, and wil not ſuffer him to come into his companie, as Menedemus did ſhut his ſonne out of doores for his riotouſnes, vntill he was more ſober, or Arceſilaus railed on Battus, &amp; banniſhed him the ſcholes, becauſe he made verſes againſt Cleantes: but afterwards when Battus was ſory for his fault and made Cleantes amends, he tooke him into his fauour againe, and vſed him more curteouſly then euer hee did before. Therefore as Ageſilaus could not abide to be praiſed of any, but of thoſe that would diſpraiſe him ſometimes if occaſion required: So is he to be eſteemed a true and faithful friend, which hath learned to reproue as wel as ſoothe, and to make vs ſad, as wel as glad, and therefore we ought to haue thoſe in ſuſpition, which alwaies are pleaſant with vs, and ſooth vs vp in al that we ſay or do, and to haue at our fingers end that ſaying of the Lacedemonian, Quomodo hic bonus eſse poteſt qui ne malis quidem acerbus eſt? how can this man be a friend vnto me for my vertues, and is not an enemie vnto me for my vices? This therefore is a marke to diſtinguiſh betweene a friend and a flatterer, whereas the one is our friend onely in things honeſt meete and requiſite, the other in al things whatſoeuer to the intent hee may not diſpleaſe vs. But ſome man perhaps thinketh that he liueth ſo vprightly that he needeth none to reprehend him, and therefore to go the ſureſt way to worke, his companion and he wil be ſworne brothers by ſome deepe oath which they thinke no man wil wittingly or willingly breake, ſith the gods themſelues as Iupiter ſaid to Semele, dare not in any wiſe violate their oath, or go backe from their vow which they made to any one. But men nowadaies are ſo farre to be like the gods, that they are almoſt as bad as deuils, for of all things that belong to the inlargement of their liuing they thinke nothing more neceſſarie then an oath whereby they may deceiue. By this

meanes Phillip king of Macedonia wanne more citties in a moneth, then he ſlew men in the open field manfully in a yeare, and therefore was wont to ſay, that his ſouldier Periurie did him more ſeruice then al his armie beſides. The like opinion held Liſander the Lacedemonian, when any obiected againſt him his cowardly coſoning of his enemies by othes, a thing which Hercules nor any valiant man could euer abide, was wont to anſwere them Si quò non pertingerit pellis leonina afſuendum &amp; vulpinam: If I think them too good for me in open field I wil put in practiſe, my ouer-reaching pollicy. Yea not only kings and men of the more diſſolute ſort do defend and offend in this hainous ſinne of periurie, but alſo prieſts, prelates, and religious men, yea euen Gods vicar himſelfe (the Pope I meane) who hath taken vpon him the name to ſit in Gods feate (if he do, it is to keepe God out of it) but indeede weares the deuils badge or coliſon, which is lying and periury. In their baptiſme they faithfully promiſed to ſtand vp againſt al the deuils in hel, but at receiuing their popiſh degrees, they haue and do daily forſweare the verity of God, they haue ſworne to obey their temporal magiſtrates, and ciuil gouernours, but when they come to the papall degree, they breake both oath and alleagance to al, whatſoeuer. Search but the chronicles and thou ſhalt find as many examples as euer there were popes: but leſt wee ſhould ſay any more then we could prooue, let vs looke into the life of twaine of the godlieſt that euer were among them, namely Paſchalis and Alexander the third: Paſchalis ſware moſt deepely to be true vnto Henry the fourth Emperour, but in a while after when he ſaw his opportunitie, he called a generall ſinode, whereas by the help of his ſpirituall ſorcerers breaking both oath and vow of allegeance, excommunicated the good emperour, raiſed his ſonne againſt him, depoſed him, impriſoned him, murthered him, and finally cauſed his body to be taken out of the ground at Leodium, and in a prophane place to be buried. The like did Alexander the third, who made the good king Fredericus Barbaroſſa his footeſtoole at Venice, to the ridiculous ſhame and rebuke of al the world, and the next day to hold his ſtirrop, and like a page to waite on his mule, to whom he had once ſworne al homage

and obedience: but if a man ſhould reprehend them for it, I thinke they woulde haue none other excuſe but that of Euripides, iuraui lingua, mentem iuiuratam gero, I ſweare with my lips, but not from my heart, and therefore I do not offend, for God onely regardeth the heart and inward man, beleeue not therefore any man the ſooner for his ſwearing, for as it is an infallible axiome that omnis homo eſt mendax, euery mā is a liar, ſo euery liar before he would be found to trip in his tale, wil not ſticke to vphold it with othes enow, if it be a matter of importance, and ſtand on his bare affirmation or negation. But perhaps thou wilt obiect vnto me the example of Regulus, who rather then he would incurre that hainous ſinne of wilful periurie, would throw himſelfe voluntarily into moſt miſerable captiuitie, and to be hewen in peeces by his moſt ſauage and vnmerciful enemies. But I thinke if thou wouldeſt go forward in recapitulation of examples, thou wouldſt quickly be brought to a non plus, ſeeing few of theſe Phaenixes are to be found in the world, eſpecially in theſe our preſent times: perhappes in former ages ſome were to be found when lawes were made for puniſhing ſwearers, therefore it were good that thoſe laudable conſtitutions of penalties which were made in former times, were renued againe, leſt cuſtome grow into nature, and ſo neuer be rooted out. King Alonſo amongſt many other laudable and notable lawes made this alſo, that knights of the band ſhould maintaine their wordes and keepe fidelitie vnto their friends: &amp; in caſe it were proued, that any knight of the ſame band had not accompliſhed his oath, although it were giuen to a very baſe perſon, and vpon a matter of litle weight, yet ſuch a one ſhould go alone in the Court and vnaccompanied, nor ſhould preſume to ſpeake or to approach nere any knight of the ſame band. Henry the fift made a law ſomewhat more generall, which touched, not onely knights of the band, but all other degrees and conditions of people within his court whatſoeuer: namely, that if he were a duke that did ſweare he ſhuld forfeit for euery oth forty ſhillings, to the aiding of poore people: if he were a lord or baron twenty ſhillings: if he were a knight or eſquire tenne ſhillings: if hee were a yeoman tenne groates: if hee were a page or a ſlaue, to be ſcourged naked

with a rod or a whip: which being for a while ſtrictly executed, cauſed ſwearing to be greatly abated in the court, but it did no good at all in the countrey. And therefore king Edmond decreed, that all men of all degrees, and of al places whatſoeuer, which were prooued to haue ſworne, ſhould for euer be ſeparated from Gods cōgregation: but Donaldus king of the Scots perceiuing this law to be little eſteemed, and for that men then (as they now) cared not how ſeldome they went to the church, made this act, that all periurers and common ſwearers ſhould haue their lippes ſeared with a hote burning yron: which lawe ſaint Lodowike king of France did put in execution at Paris vpon a citizen for blaſpheming the name of Chriſt to the example of all others, and ſo cauſed it to be proclaimed throughout his whole realme for a generall puniſhment. In a while after Philip earle of Flanders hearing that the French men had baniſhed ſwearing cleane out of their coaſtes, thought good that ſome were made in like maner in his land for the reformation of his people, and therefore (becauſe hee woulde not ſeeme to borrowe any of the lawes of the French men his profeſſed enemies in thoſe daies) hee purpoſed to ordaine ſome other as greeuous as that, which without delaie he did, which was, that he that did ſweare or forſweare himſelfe, ſhould looſe his life and goods, and his children ſhould be diſinherited: which law if it were kept in theſe daies, I thinke there ſhould ſo many looſe their liues that there ſhould be few or none at al left aliue to inherit their goods, that were of age to know what to doe with them, but they are now al laid aſide, and we count him no gentleman except he can ſweare by creature and creator, the tale ſhal want his due circumſtance if it be not garniſhed and poliſhed with othes and blaſphemy. We reade that the Iewes when they heard Gods name blaſphemed, were wont to teare their haire and rent their garments for greefe, but who now a daies ſhewes any token that hee is diſcontented therewith? the pope himſelfe who would faine be eſteemed the holieſt of al, is not onely content that men ſhould ſweare and forſweare themſelues, but alſo when hee ſeeth them ſomewhat flacke, he hireth them to forſweare themſelues; as for example he hireth the ſubiects to breake their oathes of allegiance to

their Princes, as Zachary the firſt hired the French men to riſe vp againſt their louing prince Hildericke, and Honorius the third, and Iohn the 22. hired the Germans to breake their oths which they had made vnto their emperors; and Innocent the third procured the Engliſhmen to go from their allegeance which they had made vnto their good king Iohn; and of late daies we haue oftentimes bin intiſed with manifold promiſes, by his damnable ſenat and vngodly Catholikes, to renownce our oathes of duetie and obedience to our moſt gracious and vertuous princeſſe that now is (whom God long preſerue and continue amongſt vs) and hath promiſed by his meſſengers, as doctor Harding, and diuers others of late days, that they ſhuld haue ful pardon for al their ſins (which is to be feared he will neuer get himſelfe) that could by any means rid her of her life, which cauſed many of that curſed ſeed of Cham, as Weſtmerland, Northumberland, the duke of Norffolke, Sanders, Briſtow Campion, Parry, Sauage, and many other firebrands of hel, to put in practiſe this diuiliſh decree. When he bare the ſupremacie here in Q. Maries daies, his perſwaſions ſo perſwaded them▪ that the cheefe ſort made no conſcience of ſwearing, becauſe by their money they thought they might be pardoned when they would, and the poorer ſort folowing the example of their ſuperiors, liued as they did, and ſo like ſinful Sodomites liued together in darknes, bringing forth moſt plenteouſly the works of darknes, which were ſo faſt rooted in the hearts of moſt men, as they could not to this day be ſo cleane rooted out, but that their venall ſin of blaſphemie hath flouriſhed to this day, ſo that now we are become far worſe then the heathen periured Glaucus, for he went to the oracle of Apollo, to know if he might forſweare the pawne which was deliuered him to keepe: but who now adaies conſults, either with Apollo, or Minerua, or any god elſe, about periury? yea they feare not to ſweare and forſweare themſelues for ſingle mony, though the God of gods command the contrarie: therfore beleeue not any the ſooner, for that he ſweares loue &amp; fidelitie to thee, but think that if he could ſee his opportunitie, he would deale no better with thee then Achilles did with his olde companion Licaon, whom he hewed into as many peeces with his fawchon, as he

ſware to him oathes of perpetuall brotherhood, by Ceres when they were chamber-fellowes togither in Greece, he had rather quarter him then looſe a quarter of ſo faire a prey, whoſe exāple the falſe Aegiſtus imitated, who thought it better to diſpatch Agamemnon of his life, euen when he was offering ſacrifices to the gods, then his loue to Clitemneſtra ſhould be any whit cut off, or diminiſhed, which hee did not onely of his owne accord, but by the conſent of cruel Clitemneſtra, who would not ſuffer his eies to be ſhut, or any other ceremoniall rite to bee performed: how farre vnlike was ſhe vnto the women amongſt the Indians called Catheis, who when the huſband dieth, al his wiues aſſemble before the chiefeſt iudges of the citie, and there each one alleageth her wel deſeruing towards him, how dearly ſhe loued, and how much ſhe tendered and honored him, and ſhe that is iudged to haue borne her ſelfe beſt in that behalfe decketh her ſelfe in the beſt manner, and the moſt gorgeouſly ſhe can, triumphing and reioyſing, getteth herſelfe vp vpon the funerall pile where her huſbands corps lie to be burned, where imbraſing &amp; kiſſing him, ſhe is burned with him. But Clitemneſtra is of a right contrarie opinion, wherefore the poets faine, that Agamemnon meeting Aeneas in hel, greeuouſly complaineth of her vnnatural fact, and wiſheth him neuer to beleeue a woman in any wiſe, neither was Clitemneſtra ſo cruel vnto her huſband becauſe ſhe was a woman, but becauſe ſhe was a moſt wicked and vnnatural woman, therefore we may beleeue a woman as wel as a man: but ſuch as mans naturall condition and qualitie that hee alwaies hates him, and bids others beware of any thing by which hee hath bin endamaged or receiued any euil, as whom a ſerpent hath ſtung, hee wil alwaies feare and bid others beware of the ſerpent, and whom a dog hath bitten hee wil alwaies auoid the fawning of dogges. In like manner are we affected one towards another, haue we beene hurt by a woman, then we exclaime againſt and bitterly ban al woman kind? hath our friend bin murthered or our ſelues ſpoiled by our gheſts, as Euritus was ſlaine by Hercules, Lucrece deflowred by Tarquine, &amp; Menelaus robbed of his wife and goods by Alexander, from that day forward we wil ſcarſe lodge any more gheſts, another hath bin hurt by his brother, an

other by his children. But it is but a folly to reckon vp particulars, ſeeing not onely brothers, and kinſmen, ſtrangers and acquaintance are wont to endamage and deceiue one another, but almoſt al men in general. Wherefore if thou bee wiſe miſtruſt al whatſoeuer. Do as the Eſſeis which were a kind of ſects amongſt the Iewes, who admitted no man into their ſect vnder a yeare of probation, and after what time they had receiued him, yet had they two yeares more to proue his manners and conditions: ſo make not any of thy counſel ouer haſtely. Doth he ſay he is thy brother? yet ſee thou miſtruſt him, doth he tel thee of his honeſt behauiour and vertuous life? yet ſee thou miſtruſt him, haſt thou found in him ſome properties of an honeſt man, and vnfained frend? yet take ſome more time of trial and watch him neuer the leſſe narrowly in the meane while: for that which is ſaid of fortune may be ſaid more fitly (in my opinion) of man, that none knoweth whether hee ſhalbe like himſelfe to morrow or no. Therefore if a man by truſting another hath receiued any hurt, he is to bee counted a very aſſe, if hee ſhould blame him that hath deceiued him, when there is none to be blamed but himſelfe and his owne fooliſhnes. Threſſa might very wel haue laughed at Thales, when he fell into the ditch, if he had beaten the ſtones, or found fault with his feet when he ſhould haue bin angrie with himſelfe, that had not an eie vnto his ſteps: and Darius might iuſtly haue ſcoffed at Goraldus, when he had neuer a penney in his purſe, if hee had laied the fault vpon his companions, who allured him to lauiſh, when the fault was his owne that would not beware of them. But ſome man wil ſay, thou ſeemeſt to bid mee liue ſolitarie like a beaſt void of al companie when thou wouldeſt haue me to beleeue any man? No, I counſel thee not to leave thy life in ſolitarineſſe, but to liue warily &amp; circumſpectly, as one that hath learned to liue wel and happily: otherwiſe it is farre better to liue in the deſert amongſt brute beaſts, then to liue in the cittie without circumſpection and warines in al thy actions, and affections, but by theſe two thou maieſt liue as ſafely as if thou were alone. There is no hearbe to perillous which hath not ſome one vertue that is pretious, nor no ſerpent ſo infectious, which is not moued with ſome one quallitie which is commodious.

What is worſe to the thirſtie then the briniſh Sea water, and yet what more commodious to the painful fiſhermen? and what more hurtfull to the fooliſh ſwaines, then the venemous viper? but to the ſkilful druggiers, what more profitable? ſeeing from her they haue the moſt wholſome triacle: ſo although company keeping be very hurteful vnto ſome, yet to otherſome it may be very profitable, and a ſchoolemaſter to wiſedome. The wiſe and prudent man when he ſeeth euery one as an enemie readie to deuour him, he wil then be more warie and looke better about him, &amp; when he ſeeth euery one prying like Momus into his life and conuerſation, he wil then begin to liue as vprightly as Io leſt watchful Argus ſhould find him tripping: but the foole miſtruſting no man is quickly eaten vp aliue amongſt them. What is the reaſon that Saturne of all the other gods lay bound in the bonds of Briareus, but becauſe he was the moſt blockiſh and witles of al the other, and could ſcarſely looke about him in the ſpace of thirtie yeares? if thou art ſuch a one, thou wilt quickly lie inſnared in the traps of paraſites, and lie faſt fettered in the chaines of penury. If Acteon haue loſt the outward ſhape of a man, his own dogges will deuoure him, and if thou haſt loſt the inward ſhape of a man, which is reaſon or pollitike prudence, thine owne friends will not ſpare to deuoure thee, or ſpoile thee of thy goods. Nothing prouoketh the theefe ſooner then negligencie: if the Athenians had tied care and circumſpection to their words and actions, they had neither fallen into the mouthes of the Lacedemonians nor had cauſe to feare their malice, and therfore Iob ſaith factus ſum mihimetipſi grauis, meaning, that the euils which do happen vnto vs (for the moſt part) our ſelues do procure them, Phaeton by his owne fooliſhneſſe was ſtricken from heauen with a thunderbolt, and Icarus by his owne folly was drenched in the Ocean, and the Scythians by their owne vnaduiſednes in drinking the wines (which Cirus pretending flight had cauſed to be left behind him) were in their drunkenes ouercome by the Perſians. Vulcanes nets were not made for Apollo, Mercurie, or Pallas, but for heady Mars, and loue blinded Venus, theſe lay quickly intangled therein, and were made a laughing to al the other gods: ſo flatterers vaites are not

laid forth to catch wiſe men and circumſpect, but to inſnare fondlings and idiots, who preſume ſo much of their honeſtie, that they thinke it would go againſt any mans conſcience to eooſin them, but ſo long goes the pitcher to the brooke that at the length it comes broken home, &amp; ſo long do they truſt, that in the end they can ſcant finde any one to truſt them when they are fallen into pouertie for the woorth of a dodkin: the faire promiſes, which were made them once, wil not any whit profit thē, Pollicitis diues quilibet eſſe poteſt, ſaith Ouid, if promiſe would make a man the richer, we ſhould haue but few beggars, poore Codrus would frolicke it out, as brauely as Craeſus, and needy Thraſo when he went a begging ſhould haue as many attendants as euer he had before, but now he perceiueth that the poet ſaid true, Tempora cum fuerint nubila ſolus eris, that no penny, no pater noſter, that a man cannot bee a free man in Wales although he hath ſacrificed a whole bed of Leekes vnto ſaint Dauie, nor that a man can be entertained in his pouertie, amongſt whom he hath ſpent al that euer he had in his proſperitie. Dioniſius wiſhed that hee might be poore and diſtreſſed one yeare before he died, to trie who would proue conſtant of al thoſe manifold troups of men, which vowed him ſuch ſingular affection; it was to be feared that he ſhould haue found as few as Perithous did when he was perſecuted by the Lapithans, namely, one onely Theſeus, or as few as Eurialus had when he fell amongſt the ſouldiers of Turnus, many promiſed neuer to forſake him, but only Niſus ſtoode to his word; the reſt preſently changed their notes, as the bird Acanthis doth her fine white colour at the firſt ſtorme: they could haue bin content to haue bin partakers of their liberty, but not of their bondage: of their wealth, but not of their woe: of their proſperous ſucceſſe, but not of their diſtreſſe: wherefore ſhunne the company of ſuch kinde of men, and if thou art acquainted with them vnawares, ſhake them off preſently as Paul did the viper, leſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee, and ſtop thy eares againſt their inticements▪ as Vlyſſes did againſt the inticements of Circes leſt thou be tranſformed from wealth into woe, from bliſſe into bale, and from ioy into annoy. Tantalus apples had a gallant ſhew, but being touched, turned into aſhes: and hee that

ſhews himſelfe outwardly a demi-god, who tries him inwardly, ſhall find him but a ſolemne ſaint. Their lippes (ſaith Salomon) drop as an hony comb, and their mouthes are more ſoft then oile, but the end of them is as bitter as gall, and as ſharpe as a two edged ſword: and Dauid ſaieth, the poiſon of aſpis is vnder their lippes, which killeth a man when it hath caſt him into a pleaſant ſlumber. But if thou wouldeſt auoide this euill, then take away all the occaſions: keepe not company with them: company keeping is the occaſion of moſt euils: he which handleth pitch can not chuſe but be defiled therewith, and he that keepeth company with euill men, can ſcarce chuſe but he infected with their manners: God neuer appeered vnto Abraham as long as he dwelt with the wicked in Hu
                  •
               , but afterward when he went to dwell elſe-where, he oftentimes appeared vnto him: and Iudas Machabaeus as ſoone as he entred friendſhip with the wicked Gentiles, he was ſoone ouercome: ſo if thou ſuffer thy ſelfe to be lulled in the cradle of flattering Calipſo, and giue thy hand vnto euery one that flatters thee, be ſure the God of goodes will preſently forſake thee, and ſuffer thy wealth in a moment to bee wracked. Yet doe I not condemne company keeping altogether with our enemies: for ſometimes we get much good by them, and learne to knowe our owne imperfections by them, which otherwiſe wee ſhould neuer haue knowen. Hierons enemy could quickly ſmell his ſtincking breath, and mocke him with it, which made him preſently ſeeke a remedy; whereas his wife that had liued with him many yeares before could neuer perceiue ſo much, for amor cecutit in eo quod amat, loue wa
                  •
               eth in bloud in thoſe things that he loueth, as two men walking in a miſt, can not perceiue that they are in it, but he that is out of it, may eaſily perceiue that they are in it: ſo an enemy can more eaſily diſcrie our errors th
                  ••
                our friends, and therefore ſaieth Tully, it is good to haue enemies in the cittie. The huſbandman grieueth that his 
                  〈◊〉
                ſhould haue a better crop of corne than himſelf, and therefore 
                  •
               e riſeth more earely than otherwiſe he woulde, that 
                  〈…〉
                might be as fruitfull as his ennemies: and wee thinke it again 
                  •
               lami
                  ••
                to be 
                  〈◊〉
                with any vice by them of all others, and therefore we ſtraine our ſelues to liue more vprightly

than otherwiſe we would haue done, if we had none to emulate. Scipio Affricanus was of no account in Rome before Cyrus proweſſe and manhoode was blazed in Italy, emulating whoſe fortitude (as one angry with himſelfe that his enemy ſhould goe beyond him) he atchieued that fame of wiſedome and valour as few had attained before him: and Themiſtocles was wont to ſay, that he could neuer ſleepe or take any reſt, bicauſe the victory which Miltiades got was alwaies in his mind: and Caeſar had neuer aſpired to ſo great renowme, but by emulating the example of Alexander, whoſe victories when he read, he preſently burſt foorth into teares, for that at the ſame age wherein Alexander liued himſelfe, had done nothing worthie of memorie. Therefore as Alexanders renowne was the cauſe of Caeſars trauels, &amp; Miltiades victory the cauſe of Themiſtocles watching: ſo let our enemies vigilancie be a ſpurre to rouze vs from negligencie and flatterers engins, to make vs more circumſpect. Oceamademus had neuer beene honoured with ſo manie triumphs, if he had not alwaies beene beſet with enemies, for it is ſaid of him, that when he had ſubdued al his enemies, he gaue commandement that there ſhould not be aboue halfe of them put to the edge of the ſword, the reſt would he place neare the confines of his campe, which might keepe his ſouldiours from idlenes and ſecuritie, which cauſed him to haue ſo many ſo expert and ſkilfull ſouldiours, that not twiſe he is reported to haue euer beene ouercome. Therefore we ſee it is better to liue amongſt our enemies whom we are ſure do hate vs, then amongſt flatterers whom we ſuppoſe to loue vs, for we are neuer more neere drowning then when we ſaile neere the ſhore, nor neuer oftner indamaged then when we think our ſelues without danger. Sampſon liued ſafely inough among his enemies the giantly Philiſtines, but in his wiues lay where hee thought himſelfe ſafeſt, hee was quickly ſubdued: and Hercules was not ſo much tormented by the dragons in Heſperidos, as by the ſhirt which Deianira had ſent him in token of her faithfulnes. Many of Sampſons wiues poſteritie are yet liuing in the world, who are in ſhapes angels, but in qualities deuils, that to worke their deſires can turne themſelues into as many ſubtilties and ſugred humilities,

as the Camelion into colours, or the iuggler into ſtrange deuices to deceiue the beholders, that can preſent a man breade in one hand, and his bane in the other, a fine ſhel and a rotten kernel, whoſe words are like alminacks that decipher nothing but vncertaintie, or like Pithias oracles which ſpeake one thing, and meane another: as Herod did to the wiſe man of the Eaſt, who promiſed to worſhip Chriſt, when he purpoſed to murther him, for if they had not by a viſion beene counſelled to haue turned another way, ſhould haue found vnder the ſhape of a Lambe, the ſubſtance of a Lion, vnder flouriſhing words diſſembling deedes, and vnder moſt curteous countenance, moſt curriſh conditions. Therefore to ſhut vp al in a word, ſeeing the moſt glittering ſands are found ſo fickle being tried, the eie pleaſing Echates ſo infectious being handled, and the greateſt promiſes to haue ſo ſmal performances, that we cannot ſafely beleeue friend or foe, kinſman or aliant, by his word nor his oath, let vs trie ere we truſt, and proue ere we put in practiſe, let vs go as the ſnaile faire &amp; ſoftly, ſeeing haſte makes waſte, and the Mault is ſweeteſt when the fire is ſofteſt, ſo ſhal wee the better diſcerne the true ſterling from the counterfet coine, the pretious medicine, from the perilous confection, the loyal louer from the fading flatterer, but then let vs not ſing Medeas ſong, which ſaid I ſee and allow the better, but I wil follow the worſe: ſeeing Pallas gift or Iunoes proffer to be more profitable, let vs not giue our apple to flattering Venus, as fooliſh Paris did leſt ſhe be our confuſion, nor let vs ſetle our affections, on faire tongued paraſites, leſt like lightning they breake our bones, before we can perceiue our ſkinne to be hurt, but let vs try ere we truſt, after good aſſurance, let vs not truſt before we trie for feare of repentance.
            FINIS.
            
               Praemonitus praemunitus.
            
         
      
   

