
   
      
         
            An exhortation vnto prayer thought mete by the kinges maiestie, and his clergy, to be read to the people in euery church afore processyions. Also a letanie with suffrages to be said or song in the tyme of the said processyons.
            Church of England.
         
         
            
               1544
            
         
         Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00483
            STC 10620
            ESTC S109485
            99845132
            99845132
            10017
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00483)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10017)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 49:02)
         
         
            
               
                  An exhortation vnto prayer thought mete by the kinges maiestie, and his clergy, to be read to the people in euery church afore processyions. Also a letanie with suffrages to be said or song in the tyme of the said processyons.
                  Church of England.
                  Church of England. Litany. 1544.
               
               [40] p.   
               
                  In Fletestrete, by Thomas Berthelet printer to the kinges highnes,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  the. XXVII. day of May, the yere of our Lorde. M. D. XLIIII. [1544]]
               
               
                  Imprint from colophon.
                  The litany and suffrages printed in red and black.
                  A6r catchword: him.
                  Signatures: A-B C⁴.
                  Formerly also STC 10625.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Prayer --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            An exhortation vnto prayer, thoughte mete by the kinges maieſtie, and his clergy, to be read to the people in euery church afore proceſſyons.
            Alſo a Letanie with ſuffrages to be ſaid or ſong in the tyme of the ſaid proceſſyons.
         
         
            
            
               
                  coat of arms or blazon
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               FORASMVCHE as prayer is the veray true meane ordeyned of almightie god, and taught vs playnly in his holy word, wherby not onely we may, but alſo by gods holy cōmandement be bounden to haue a recourſe and a refuge for helpe and ayde of almightie god our heauenly father, not onely in all our neceſſities, and tribulations of this world, but alſo vniuerſally in all our affaires and buſineſſes, what ſoeuer ſhalbe fall vnto vs, orels what ſoeuer thing we ſhall enterpriſe or take in hand. And foraſmuch alſo as our father in heauen, of his mere mercie and infinite

goodnes, hath bounden him ſelf by his owne free promiſe, and certified vs of the ſame, by his owne ſonne, our onely ſauiour and lorde CHRIST IESV, in his goſpel, that what ſoeuer we ſhall aſke of him, we ſhall haue it, ſo that we aſke ſuch thinges, and in ſuche ſorte, as we ought to doo. For theſe cauſes good chriſtian people, beynge thus grounded vpon the ſure foundation of goddis holie &amp; bleſſed word, which can not deceiue vs, We are here at this time gathered togither, to make our comon prayer to our heauenly father. But nowe good chriſtian people that by the true vſe of praier we may obteine and enioye his gratious promiſe of aidé, comforte

and conſolation, in al our affayres and neceſſities, two thinges, concerning prayer, are ſpecially to be learned. The firſt is, to knowe, for what thynges we ought to make our requeſt and petition in our praier. The ſecond is, in what wiſe we ſhuld make our prayer, in ſuche ſorte as it may be acceptably hearde, and graciouſly graunted of our heauenly father.
            ¶ As for the firſt, we ought inſtantly to aſke of our heauenly father, his holy and bleſſid ſpirite, godly wiſedome, faith, charitie, and to feare and dreade him, and that his holy name in al thingis, and euery where thorough al the hole world may be glorified, that his kyngedome

maye come vnto vs, that is to ſaye, that here he may reigne in vs, by the faith of his welbeloued ſonne our ſauiour IESV CHRIST, and after this lyfe alſo to reigne in vs, and ouer vs euerlaſtingly in glorye.
            We ought to pray, that his bleſſed wyl may be fulfylled here in this world emōges vs his mortall creatures, as it is of his immortall angels, and of al the holy company of the heauenly ſpirites. We muſte pray for our dayly breade, that is, for our neceſſary fode and ſuſtenāce bothe of body and ſoule. Of body, as meate, drinke, and neceſſary apparaile, peace, helthe, and what ſoeuer god knoweth to be neceſſary for the behofe and conſeruation

of the ſame, that we may do to our lorde god true ſeruice therwith, euery man in his ſtate and vocation, wherevnto god hath called hym. Of the ſoule, as the word of god, and the true knowledge of the ſame, the true conſeruation of our heauenlye fathers holy and bleſſid cōmandementis, the liuely bread of the bleſſed body of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte, the holy and ſacrate cuppe of the precious and bleſſed bludde, whiche was ſhed for vs vpon the Croſſe, to purchaſe vs pardon and forgyuenes of our ſynnes. Furthermore we muſt pray for the forgiuenes of our ſynnes, that our heauenly father wyll be mercyfull vnto vs, and forgyue vs our ſynnes

bothe many and great, wherby we offende againſte his infinite goodnes, as we do forgiue the offences of them that offend vs. whiche, howe great ſo euer they appere vnto vs, yet in compariſon of the offences that we do againſt god, they be bothe ſmall and fewe. We muſte pray, that oure heauenly father ſuffre vs not to be ledde into temptation, for without his continuall aide and protection, we are but weke and ſoone ouerthrowen. Our goſtely ennemy is ſtronge, violent, fierſe, ſubtyll, and exceding cruell. And therfore we muſte cōtinually pray, with all inſtāce that in al his aſſaultes we may be deliuered by the mighty hāde of our heauenly father, from al

euyll. Fynally, and before all thing, as ſaint Paule exhorteth vs in the fyrſt epiſtle to Timothe, Let vs make our prayers, and ſupplycations, rendrynge and gyuyng of thankes for all men, and namely for kynges, princis, and al other ſet in chief dignitie and high roumes, that by theyr godly gouernāce, their true faithfull and diligent execution of iuſtice and equitie vn to all their ſubiectes, our heauenly father may be gloryfied, the common welth may be daily promoted and increaſed, and that we al, that are theyr ſubiectes, may liue in peace and quietnes, with al godlines and vertue, and our chriſten princis &amp; heades in vnitie and concorde

emonges them ſelfes, euer callyng vppon theyr heauenly father, whiche is the king of all kynges, and the lorde of all lordes, which ſhall iudge without reſpecte of perſone, accordynge to euery mās doing or workes, at whoſe hande the weake ſhall take no wronge, nor the myghty may not by any power eſcape his iuſte iudgement. That our princes I ſay, thus calling vppon theyr heauenly father for grace, maye euer in all their affaires be directed and gouerned by the holie ſpirite of god, and bothe rule, and be ruled, by his holy feare, to their owne endles ioye, comforte, and conſolation, and to theyr owne euerlaſtyng ſaluation, thorough our ſauiour

Ieſus Chriſt.
            ☞ AND here ſpecially let vs pray for our moſte dere and ſoueraigne lorde the Kynges maieſty, who dothe not onely ſtudy and care dayly and hourely for our proſperitie and wealth, but alſo ſpareth not, to ſpende his ſubſtance and treaſure, yea redye at all tymes to endaunger hym ſelf for the tender loue and fatherly zeale, that he bereth towarde this his realme, and the ſubiectes of the ſame. Who at this preſent tyme hath taken vpon hym the great and dangerous affayres of warre. Lette vs praye, that it may pleaſe almyghty god, lorde of hoſtes, in whoſe handes is onely wealthe and victorie, mercifully to aſſyſt

him, ſending his holy angell, to be his ſuccour, keper, &amp; defender frō all his aduerſaries, and from all euyls. Let vs pray for our bretherne, that bende them ſelfes to batail for goddis cauſe and our defence, that god maye grant them proſperous ſucceſſe, to our comfort, and the increaſe of his glory. Let vs praye for our ſelfes that remain at home, that almyghty god defende vs from ſynne, ſickenes, derth, and all other aduerſyties of bodye and ſoule.
            The ſeconde thynge to be lerned, concernynge praier, is to know, howe we ſhal make true prayer, ſo that it may be graciouſely harde, and mercyfully graunted of oure heauenly father.

Fyrſt of al we muſt, vpon conſideration of our heauenly fathers mercy and goodnes towardes vs, and of his euerlaſtyng trueth, and free promyſe made vnto vs in his owne holy worde, conceyue a full affiance hoope and truſt: and that without waueryng or doubtfull miſtruſtyng, eyther in his trueth, his goodnes, or in his almightie power, certainely aſſuring our ſelfe, that both of his omnipotencie, he may do what ſoeuer ſhall pleaſe his goodnes, and alſo for his infinite goodnes, and fatherlye affection towarde vs, that he woll both here and graunt al our lauful and godly requeſtes, after that meaſure, ſort, and degree, as he of his infinite

and incomprehenſible wiſdome knoweth the thynge to be mooſt mete, mooſt conuenient, and behofeful both for his own glorye and honour, and for the profit, behoufe, and commoditie of vs his children.
            Furthermore alſo it is neceſſarily requyred to that, that our prayer may be acceptable vnto our heuenly father, to haue charitie, and brotherly loue betwixt neighbour and neighbour, and towarde all our euen chriſten. So CHRISTE him ſelfe teacheth vs, ſayinge, whan you ſtande to praye, forgyue, if you haue any dyſpleaſure agaynſte any perſonne: that your father, whiche is in heauen, maye forgiue you. It is a true ſaying

that ſaint Auguſtine ſayeth: There is no good fruicte, no good deede, no good woorke, whiche ſpringeth not out of the roote of charitie. And ſaincte Paule teacheth plainely, that where as charitie lacketh, nothyng can auayle vs.
            And moreouer we muſt in our prayer, be ware of vayne glory and prayſe of man, outwardly ſhewing a great pretence of holynes, and being vayne of true godlynes inwardly, onely to haue the commendation of men before the world. for if we ſo do, we ſhall loſe the reward and benefit of our prayer, as our ſauiour CHRIST ſaieth his owne ſelfe. We muſt take hede alſo, that we thincke not the vertue

of prayer, to conſiſte in multiplying of many wordes without faythe and godly deuotion, thynckyng as the heathen doth, that for our many wordes or moche ſpeking, we ſhalbe herde of our heauenly father. Who ſo euer doth thinke ſo, he ſhall deceyue him ſelfe. for god doth not regarde neither the ſwete ſound of our voice, nor the great num ber of our woordes, but the erneſt feruentnes and true faythful deuotion of our hartes. Fynally we muſte beware in our praier of that common peſtilent infection, and venemefull poyſon of all good prayer, that is to ſay, when our mouthe prayeth, and our hartes praye not. Of the whiche the prophete Eſaie

complayneth ſore. And our ſauyour in ſaynte Mathewes goſpel rebuketh the phariſees, for the ſame, ſaying thus: O hipocrites, Eſaie the prophet prophected well vppon you, when he ſayde thus: This people draweth nighe me with theyr lyppes, but their hartes are farre from me, that is to ſaye, they ſpeake with their tongue and lippes, the wordes of praier, but in theyr harte, they mynde no thyng leſſe then they ſpeake, as that the goodnes of the prayer ſtode in the outwarde ſpeking onely of the woorde, and not in the inwarde, true and faythfull requeſt of the harte. And to the intent therfore your hartes and lyppes maye god together in

praier, it is verye conuenient, and moche acceptable to god, that you ſhuld vſe your priuate prayer in your mother tongue, that you vnderſtandyng what you aſke of god, may more erneſtly &amp; feruētly deſyre the ſame your hartes &amp; myndes agreing to your mouthe and woordes. Wherfore let vs eſchewe (good people) in our prayers, al the afore reherſed vices, for elles we ſhall not obteine our petitions, and requeſtes, but contrarye wyſe we ſhall hyghly diſpleaſe god and greuouſly offende him. Therfore good Chryſtian bretherne, ſeynge we are come togyther to praye, let vs do it accordyng to our bounden duetie, and as it ought to be done. Let

vs truly praye with a faithfull harte, and a ſure affiaunce of our heauenly fathers infinite mercy, grace, and goodnes? let vs make our prayers, beyng in loue and charitie with all and euery one of our neighbours, euer hauing in our herte an erneſt requeſt and deſyre of thoſe godly benefyttes, which are appointed in goddes worde, that we ſhulde pray for, and yet not preſcribing vnto god, either the tyme, place, meaſure, or degree of his gracious benefittes, but holly committing our ſelues to his bleſſed wil and pleaſure, receyuyng in good woorthe, and with thankes giuinge, what ſo euer, and when ſo euer, it ſhall pleaſe his gracious goodnes,

to beſtowe his gracious gyftes vpon vs. Let vs alſo fourniſhe and beautifie this our prayer, that it may pleſe god the better, and delite the eares of our heauenlie father, with faſting and holſome abſtinence, not onely from all delicious liuing in voluptuouſe fare, and from all exceſſes of meate and drinke, but alſo to chaſtyſe and kylle the ſynfull luſtes of the bodye, to make it bowe and redy to obey, vnto the ſpirituall mocions of the holye gooſte. Let vs alſo furniſh it with almes dede, and with the woorkes of mercie and charite. For praier is good and acceptable vnto god, when it is accompanied with almoſe dedes, &amp; with the workes of mercy,

as the holy man Thobye ſayth, with the whiche, and vſyng the vertues afore reherſed, and alſo eſchewyng dyligently the foreſayde vices, our prayers ſhalbe of muche price and value, as was the prayers of Hely, Danyel, &amp; Moyſes, before our heauenly father, and that for our ſauiour Jeſus Chryſtes ſake, whiche hathe redemed vs with his preciouſe bloude, and hathe ſigned &amp; ſealed vs vp to euerlaſting life. To whom both now and euer, with his father and the holy gooſt, be glorie and honour without ende.
            AMEN.
         
         
            
            
               
                  AS THESE holye prayers and ſuffrages folowynge, are ſette furthe of moſt godly zeale for edifying and ſtirring of deuotion of al true faythfull chriſten hartes: ſo it is thought conueniente in this cōmune prayer of proceſſion to haue it ſet furthe and vſed in the vulgar tungue, for ſtirringe the people to more deuotion: and it ſhalbe euery chriſten mās part, reuerntly to vſe the ſame, to the honour and glory of almighty god, and the profit of their own ſoules. And ſuch among the people, as haue vokes, and can reade, may reade them quietely and ſoftly to them ſelfe, and ſuche as can not reade, let them quietly &amp; attentifely gyue audience in tyme of the ſaid prayers, hauynge their mindes erect to almighty god, &amp; deuoutly praying in theyr hartes, the ſame petitions which do entre in at their eares, ſo that with one ſounde of the hart, and one accord, God may be glorified in his churche.
               And it is to be remembred, that that whiche is printed in blacke letters, is to be ſayde or ſonge of the prieſt with an audible voice, that is to ſay, ſo loude and ſo playnly, that it maye well be vnderſtande of the hearers: And that which is in the redde, is to be anſwered of the quiere ſobrely and deuoutely.
            
            
               
               O GOD, the father of heauen, haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſinners.
            
               O god, the father of heauen, haue mercy vppon vs myſerable ſynners.
            
            O god, the ſon, redemer of the world, haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſinners.
            
               O god, the ſon, redemer of the world, haue mercie vpon vs miſerable ſinners.
            
            O god, the holy gooſt, proceding from the father and the ſon, haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſinners.
            
               O god, the holy ghoſte, procedyng from the father and the ſon, haue mercie vppon vs miſerable ſynners.
            
            O holye, bleſſed, and glorious

trinitie, one God, haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſinners,
            
               O holy, bleſſed, and glorious trinitie, one god, haue mercy vppon vs myſerable ſynners.
            
            Saint Mary, mother of god our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte, Pray for vs.
            
            All holy aungels and archangels, &amp; all holy orders of bleſſed ſpirites, Pray for vs.
            
            All holy patriarkes, and prophetes, apoſtels, martyrs, confeſſours, and virgins, and all the bleſſed company of heauen, Pray for vs.
            
            Remembre not lorde, our offences, nor the offences of our forefathers, neyther take thou vengeance of our ſinnes, ſpare vs good lord, ſpare thy people,

whom thou haſte redemed with thy moſt precious bloud, and be not angrye with vs for euer. Spare vs good lorde.
            
            From all euyll and miſchief, from ſinne, from the craftis and aſſautes of the deuyll, from thy wrathe, and from euerlaſtynge dānation, Good lord delyuer vs.
            
            From blyndnes of hart, from pryde, vaynglory, and hypocriſy, frome enuy, hatred, and malice, and all vncharitablenes, Good lorde deliuer vs.
            
            From fornication, &amp; al deadly ſynne, and from all the deceites of the worlde, the fleſſhe, and the deuil, Good lorde deliuer vs.
            
            From lightnyng and tempeſt, frome plage, peſtilence, and famine, frome battayle and murder,

and frome ſodayne deathe, Good lorde deliuer vs.
            
            From all ſedition and priuey conſpiracy, from the tyranny of the byſhop of Rome, and all his deteſtable enormities, from all falſe doctrine and hereſy, from hardnes of hart and contempte of thy word and cōmandement, Good lorde delyuer vs.
            
            By the myſtery of thy holy incarnation, by thy holy natiuitie &amp; circunciſion, by thy baptiſme, faſtyng, and temptation, Good lorde delyuer vs.
            
            By thyne agonie and bluddy ſweat, by thy croſſe and paſſion, by thy precious deathe and buriall, by thy glorious reſurrection and aſcenſion, by the commyng of the holy goſte,

               Good lorde deliuer vs.
            
            In all time of our tribulation, in all tyme of our wealthe, in the houre of deth, in the day of iugement, Good lord delyuer vs.
            
            ¶ We ſynners doo beſeche the to heare vs, O lorde god, and that it may pleſe the to rule and gouerne thy holy churche vnyuerſall in the right way. We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleſe the to kepe HENRY the. VIII. thy ſeruant &amp; our kyng and gouernour, We beſeche the to here vs good lord.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to rule his hart in thy faithe, feare, and hole, that he may euer haue affiance in the, and euer ſeeke thy honour and glory, We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            
               
That it maye pleaſe the to be his defendour and keeper, gyuyng hym the victorye ouer all his ennemies, We beſeche the to here vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to kepe our noble quene CATHERINE in thy feare and loue, gyuynge her increaſe of all godlynes, honour, and children, We beſeche the to here vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleſe the to kepe and defende our noble prynce EDVVARD, and al the kynges maieſties chyldren, We beſeche the to here vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to illuminate all biſhoppes paſtours and minyſters of the churche, with true knowlege and vnderſtandyng of thy word, and that

both by theyr preaching and lyuyng, they may ſet it forthe and ſhew it accordingly, We beſeche the to here vs good lorde.
            
            That it maye pleaſe the to endue the lordes of the counſaile, and al the nobilitie, with grace, wyſedom, &amp; vnderſtandyng, We beſeche the to here vs good lord.
            
            That it maye pleſe the to bleſſe and keepe the magiſtrates, gyuyng them grace to execute iuſtice, and to maynteyne truthe, We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleſe the to bleſſe and kepe all thy people, We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to gyue to all nations vnitie peace and concorde

               we beſeche ye to here vs good lord.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to giue vs an harte, to loue and dreade the, and diligently to lyue after thy cōmandementes, We beſech the to heare vs good lord.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to giue all thy people increaſe of grace, to here mekely thy word, and to receyue it with pure affection, and to bring forthe the fruites of the ſpirite, We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleſe the to bring into the way of truthe, all ſuche as haue erred &amp; ar deceiued, we beſeche the to here vs good lord.
            
            That it maye pleaſe the to ſtrengthen ſuche as do ſtande, and to comforte and helpe the weake harted, and toraiſe vp

them that fall, and fynally to beate downe Satan vnder our fete. We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleaſe the, to ſuccour helpe and comfort all that be in daunger neceſſitie and tribulation, We beſeche the to here vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to preſerue all that trauaile by lande or by water, all women labouryng of chyld, all ſycke perſons and yong children, and to ſhew thy pitie vpon al priſoners and captiues, We beſeche the to here vs good lord.
            
            That it maye pleaſe the to defend &amp; prouide for the fatherles children and wydowes, and all that be deſolate &amp; oppreſſed, we

beſeche the to here vs good lord.
            
            That it maye pleſe the to haue mercy vpon all men. We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            That it maye pleaſe the to forgiue our enemies, perſecutours and ſclanderours, and to turne their hertes, We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.
            
            That it may pleaſe ye to giue to our vſe the kindly fruites of the erthe, ſo as in due tyme we maye enioy them: &amp; to preſerue thē. We be ſeche the to here vs good lord.
            
            That it may pleaſe the to giue vs true repentance, to forgyue vs all our ſinnes, negligences and ignorances, and to endue vs with the grace of thy holy ſpirite, to amende our lyues according to thy holy word, We beſeche

the to here vs good lorde.
            
            Sonne of god, we beſeche the to heare vs.
            
               Sonne of god, we beſeche the to heare vs.
            
            O lambe of god, that takeſt awaye the ſynnes of the worlde, Graunt vs thy peace.
            
            O lambe of god, that takeſt away the ſynnes of the worlde. Haue mercy vpon vs.
            
            O Chriſt, heare vs.
            
               O Chriſt he are vs.
            
            Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.
            
               Chriſte haue mercy vpon vs.
            
            Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.
            Our father whiche arte in heauen. with the reſidue of the Pater noſter.
            
            And ſuffer vs not to be ledde into temptation.
            
               But delyuer vs from euyll. Amen.
            
               
The verſicle.
            lorde, deale not with vs after our ſynnes.
            The anſwere.
            
               Neyther rewarde vs after our iniquities.
            
            Let vs pray.
            O GOD, mercyfull father, that diſpiſeſt not the ſighing of a contrite harte, nor the deſyre of ſuche as be ſorowfull, mercifully aſſiſte our prayers, that we make before the in all our troubles and aduerſities, when ſo euer they oppreſſe vs.
            And graciouſely heare vs, that thoſe euyls, which the craft and ſubtiltie of the deuyll or manne worketh againſt vs, be brought to nought, and by the prouidere of thy goodnes, they may be diſperſed,

that we thy ſeruauntes, being hurt by no perſecutions, maye euermore gyue thankes vnto the, in thy holye churche, through Ieſu Chriſt our lorde.
            
               O lord, ariſe, helpe vs, and deliuer vs for thy honour.
            
            O god, we haue hearde with our cares, &amp; our fathers haue de clarid vnto vs the noble workis that thou diddeſt in their daies, and in tholde time before them.
            
               O lord, ariſe, helpe vs, and deliuer vs for thy names ſake.
            
            O lory to the father, the ſonne, and to the holy goſte, as it hath ben from the beginning, is, and ſhalbe euer world without end. Amen.
            From our enemies defend vs, O Chriſte.
            
               
               Graciouſely looke vppon oure afflictions.
            
            Pitifully beholde the dolour of our harte.
            
               Mercyfully forgyue the ſynnes of thy people.
            
            Fauourably with mercy heare our prayers.
            
               O ſonne of Dauid haue mercy vppon vs.
            
            Both nowe and euer voucheſaufe to here vs Chriſt.
            
               Graciouſely here vs, O Chriſt, Graciouſely heare vs, O lorde Chriſte.
            
            The verſicle.
            O lorde, let thy mercie be ſhewed vpon vs.
            The anſwere.
            
               As we do put our truſte in the.
            
         
         
            
               
Let vs pray.
            WE humbly beſeche the, O father, mercifully to loke vpon our infirmities, &amp; for the glorie of thy name ſake tourne from vs all thoſe euilles, that we mooſt rightuouſly haue deſerued. Graunt this o lord god, for our mediatour and aduocate Jeſu Chriſtes ſake. Amen.
            O God, whoſe nature &amp; propertie is euer to haue mercy, and to forgyue, receyue our humble petition, &amp; though we be tied and bounde with the chaine of our ſynnes: yet lette the pitifulnes of thy great mercye leuſe vs, for the honour of Jeſus Chriſtes ſake, ourmediatour and aduocate. Amen.
            
               
               ALMIGHTY and euer lyuynge god, whyche onely workeſt great meruailes, ſende downe vpon our byſſhops and curates, and al congregations, commytted to their charge, the healthfull ſpirite of thy grace, and that they may truely pleaſe the: powre vpon them the contynuall dewe of thy bleſſynge. Graunte this (O lorde) for the honour of our aduocate &amp; mediatour Jeſu Chriſte. Amen.
            
               WE beſeche the, O lorde, to ſhewe vpon vs thyne exceding great mercy, which no tongue can woorthily expreſſe, and that it may pleaſe the to deliuer vs from al our ſinnes, and alſo from the paynes, that we

haue for them deſerued. Graunt this, o lord, thorough our mediatour &amp; aduocate Jeſu Chriſt. Amen.
            
               GRAVNT, we beſeeche the, O almyghty god, that we, in our trouble put our hole confidence vpon thy mercy, that we may againſt al aduerſitie be defended vnder thy protection. Grant this, O lord god, for our mediatour and aduocate Jeſu Chriſtis ſake. Amen.
            
               ALMIGHTY god, whiche A prayer of Chſoſtome. haſte gyuen vs grace at this time with one accorde, to make our cōmune ſupplicatiōs vnto the, and doſt promiſe, that whan two or thre be gathered in

thy name, thou wilt graūt their requeſtes: fulfyll nowe, O lord, the deſires and petitions of thy ſeruantes, as may be moſt expedient for them, graūting vs in this worlde knowledge of thy trueth, and in the world to come lyfe euerlaſty ng. Amen.
         
      
      
         
            IMPRINTED at London in Pleteſtrete, by Thomas Berthelet printer to the kinges highnes, the. XXVII. day of May, the yere of our Lorde. M. D. XLIIII.
         
         
            Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.
            
         
      
   

