
   
      
         
            Sathans sowing season. By William Est minister and preacher of Gods word in Bydeford.
            Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.
         
         
            
               1611
            
         
         Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00405
            STC 10536.5
            ESTC S118580
            99853787
            99853787
            19183
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00405)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19183)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 577:20 or 2115:3)
         
         
            
               
                  Sathans sowing season. By William Est minister and preacher of Gods word in Bydeford.
                  Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.
                  Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625. Mirrour of mercy.
               
               [4], 7-101 p.   
               
                  Printed by Nicholas Okes for Richard Bonian, and are to bee sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Floure de Luce,
                  London :
                  1611.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-F8, G4 (first and last leaves blank?).
                  Printers' device on t.p. (McK. 381); initial.
                  Formerly part 2 of: Est, William.  The mirrour of mercy.
                  Identified as STC 15035 on reel 577:20.
                  Imperfect: faded, with considerable loss of text.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Devil --  Early works to 1800.
               Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
SATHANS Sowing Seaſon.
By William Eſt Miniſter and Preacher of Gods word in Bydeford.
            
               1: PET. 5. 8.
               Bee ſober, and watch, for your aduerſary the Diuell as a roaring Lyon walketh about, ſeeking whom he may deuoure.
            
            
               LONDON Printed by Nicholas Okes for Richard Bonian, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Floure de Luce. 1611.
         
         
            
            
               
CLARISSIMO, ET OMNIBVS VERAE NOBILITATIS ORNAMENTIS HONORATISSIMO DYNAſtae, Domino Guilielmo Comiti Bathonienſi, bonarum Literarum, &amp; verbi diuini Proeconum Patrone ſingulari: GVILIELMVS ESTVS HVNCSVVM LIBELLVM, IN GRATI ANImi teſtimonium, dedicat, conſecratque.
            
         
         
            
            
            To the Chriſtian Reader.
            
               IT is not long ago (courteous Reader) that I handled the ſame ſubiect in ſubſtance, as in this ſucceeding Treatiſe in my Booke intituled The Scourge of Security, or the expulſion and returne of the vncleane ſpirit: which after it paſſed the peruſing of ſome of my learned and ſincere friends, they wiſhed that I had beene more copious, and ſharpe, then therin I was, in ſcourging the carnall ſecurity that is ſo farre ſpread abroade, in all ſorts, in this pampering and ſelfe louing age. Which ſparingneſſe in reprouing, I haue in this following diſcourſe in part amended, according to my ſimple and ſingle talent, not hiding it in the earth, or keeping it to my ſelfe, but opening

it to thy view, and deſiring the exchange of thy feruent and faithfull prayers for this my well wiſhing to thy ſaluation, and that it may, at the generall account, be returned to him that first gaue it, with increaſe of true zeale and knowledge, both in thee and me. And I humbly pray, that I, who reproue this ſinne of ſecurity in thee, (which is the open gap to let in all thy ſpiritual enemies into thy body &amp; ſoule) may my ſelfe flye it, and thereby bee the more carefull how wee diſpleaſe ſo gracious a God, and grieue ſo louing a Father as we haue in heauen.
            
               Thine in the Lord
WILLIAM ESTH.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            SATHANS Sowing Seaſon.
            
               MAT. 13. 24. vnto ver. 39.
The kingdome of heauen is like vnto a man which ſowed good ſeed in his field, &amp;c.
            
               THIS parable conſiſteth in genere didaſcalico, for inſtruction, &amp; doctrine, painting out the eſtate of the Church militant in this life, in which the good and the euill, the wicked and the godly, are mixed together, and ſuffered vntill the end of the world, when they ſhall for euer be ſeparated by the Lord.
            
               The generall diuiſion.The whole may bee reduced in general into a 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                a propoſition,

and application. The propoſition is contained in the whole pericope of the parable, the application is added by Chriſt himſelfe, from ver. 36. vnto verſ. 44.
            
               The particular diuiſion.But more fully and particularly all may be diſtinguiſhed into theſe foure heads or members.
            The firſt expreſſeth with what prouident care this heauenly houſeholder watcheth ouer his Church, in manuring, tilling, and dreſſing the field thereof, and in ſowing the ſeede of all vertues therein, verſe 24.
            The ſecond ſheweth the wonderfull induſtry and ſubtilty of the enemy of mankinde, in ſeeking and labouring by all meanes to worke our deſtruction, by ſowing in our hearts the poyſoned and noyſome ſeede of all iniquity, and the fit oportunity hee watcheth for the effecting therof, v. 25
            The third containeth a queſtion▪ with an admiration of the ſeruants about

the plucking vp of the ſame, v. 27.
            The fourth expreſſeth the anſwere concerning the time when God ſhall ſeparate and diuide the good from the euill, and the different ſtate of them both, verſ. 29. and 30.
            Euery part thereof I will (for your better edification) explane and apply by a ſeuerall Protaſis and Apodoſis, and afterward ſet downe the obſeruations and doctrines.
            
               The firſt part.Now for the firſt part the Protaſis, or propoſition is thus: Euen as a man that ſoweth good ſeede in his field, and vſeth all meanes that it may fructifie and bring forth good fruites. Apod: So Chriſt the ſonne of man ſoweth in his Church the good ſeede of his word, that it may bring forth good fruit to the ioyfull harueſt of eternall life, that he may purge vs, to be a peculiar people vnto himſelfe, zealous of good workes, Tit. 2 Tit. 2. 14.14. And herein is the Father glorified, that ye beare much fruite, and become my Diſciples, ſaith our Sauiour, Io. 15. Ioh. 15. 8.
            
            
               
               The kingdome of heauen whatBy the kingdome of heauen is vnderſtood the ſtate of the Church militant in this life: for all things which are ſpoken in this parable, are expreſly ſaid of Chriſt to go before the time of harueſt, or of the end of the world▪ It is called the kingdome of heauen, by a metaphor taken from an earthly kingdome, becauſe God by the preaching of the Coſpell, beginneth his kingdome in the hearts of men, which 
               Luk. 17. 12.
               is within vs, Luk. 17. 12▪ &amp; is righteouſnes 
               Rom. 14. 17
               peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt, Romans 14. 17.
            Secondly, hee is compared vnto a man ſowing good ſeed in his field: This is the Sonne of man, verſe. 37. that is, Pſal. 8. 4. Dan. 7. 13.
               Chriſt, who is called the Son of man, Pſal. 8. 4. Dan. 7. 13. becauſe hee is the onely begotten Sonne of God, from all eternity very God, who in time tooke fleſh of the virgin Mary, and was made man.
            Thirdly, the field is the world, where per metonymiam ſubiecti, are vnderſtood

the men liuing in the world. Againe by a Synecdochen generis pro ſpecie, not promiſcually euery man, but the Church to whom the Goſpell is preached, is ſignified.
            Fourthly, the good ſeede are the children of the kingdome, verſ Ibid. that is, the faithfull and elect which are called here the good ſeede, per metonymiam effecti, for the inſtrumentall cauſe, becauſe by the word of God, that immortall ſeede, they are borne anew, 1. Pet. 1. 23. 1. Pet. 1. 23 Ioh▪ 1. 12.
               and are made the ſonnes of God, Ioh. 1. 12. And they are called the children of the kingdome, becauſe in this life by faith they enioy the kingdome of grace, and the benefites thereof, and in the life to come, they ſhall be heires of the kingdome of glory.
            
               Obſer▪ and doctrines.Firſt, we here learne in this the Lords husbandry, that our heart by nature is that barren and vnfruitful field, which bringeth forth nothing but the thorns, brambles, and weeds of vices, For it is euill from his youth, Gen. 8. which 
               Gen. 8. 21.
               
               drinketh iniquity like water, Iob. 15. in it dwelleth no good, Rom. 7. 18. out of it proceede murthers, adulteries, fornications thefts, ſlanders, &amp;c. which defile the man Matth. 15. 19. But Chriſt is the good husbandman, which ſoweth the good ſeed in the field of our ſoules, &amp; maketh it grow and increaſe therein.
            1. By plowing and turning vp this ſpirituall field, when hee ſtirreth vp in our minds the knowledge of our ſins, &amp; rooteth vp the thornes &amp; brambles of vices by the preaching of the law.
            2. He dungeth and dreſſeth the ſame, when with the ſweet ſhower and heauenly dew of his Goſpell hee reuiueth our hearts, nouriſheth vs with his holy ſpirit, and irrigateth and watereth vs with the coeleſtial influence of his graces and bleſſings, that wee may bring forth the fruits of faith, piety, and all other chriſtian vertues, and fruits worthy Luke. 3 8of repentance, Luk. 3. 8. And this he worketh by the means, and faithfull diligence of his miniſters &amp; preachers

of his word, for they are 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                ſome way or other labourers with God in this husbandry. Ye are (ſaith the Apoſtle) 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Gods husbandry, wee are 1 Cor. 3. 9. 2 Tim. 4. 2 Phil. 2. 13. Ioh. 15. 16.
               Dei cooperarij, we together are Gods labourers. Their office the Apoſtle ſetteth downe: Improue, rebuke, exhort. And all this by the grace of God which worketh in vs both the will and the deed, who hath ordeined vs that we ſhold bring forth fruit.
            
            2. Wee haue here a ſtrong motiue of thankfulnes to our louing God for this his fatherly care of his Church, which gratitude the Lord expecteth at our hands, &amp; which wee muſt manifeſt in bringing forth good fruit. We ſhould reſemble the good ground (ſaith Seneca) 
               Sene
                     •
                  
                  ▪
               
               quae vno accepto dat centū, which rendreth an hundred for one it receiueth. God ſoweth his ſeed plentifully, &amp; requireth of vs a plentifull harueſt. For euen as wee ſeeke fruit of the ground whereon we beſtow our ſeed, &amp; curſe hat ground which yeeldeth no recō
               ence: ſo God requires but the fruit of

obedience, piety, and holy conuerſation, which if we yeeld not, we are ſubiect Heb. 6. 7.to the curſe, Heb. 6. 7. For the earth which drinketh in the raine that cometh oft vpon it, and bringeth forth hearbes meete for them by whom it is dreſſed, receiueth a bleſsing of God: but that which beareth thornes and bryars is reproued, and neere vnto curſing, whoſe end is to be burned.
            
            
               And I would to God that curſed 
               Deut. 32.
               fruit were not found amongſt vs mentioned Deut. 32. verſ. 32. Their vine is the vine of Sodome, and of the vines of Gomorah, their grapes are grapes of gall, their cluſters bee bitter. Adeſt dominus Amb▪ ſuper Luk. 3.
               qui fructum expectat, facundos viuificat, ſteriles damnat, Amb ſuper Luk. 3. The Lord is preſent which reſpecteth fruit, the fruitfull he quickeneth, the barren he condemneth.
            
            Surely, there is no ſinne that more diſpleaſeth God then ingratitude for benefites. The firſt ſinne wherewith the Prophet Eſay by Gods commanddement,

               Againſt ingratitude.vpbraided the people of the Iewes was vnthankfulneſſe for ſo many benefites receiued. For thus he beginneth his propheſie: Heare O heauens, and hearken, O earth: For the Lord hath ſaid, I haue nouriſhed and brought vp children, but they haue rebelled againſt me. 
               Eſay. 1. 1. 3
               The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his maisters cribbe: but Iſrael hath not knowne, my people haue not vnderſtood, Eſay. 1. verſe. 2. 3. As the memory of no vertue is more firme then of a benefite receiued: ſo ſcarce is there any vice worſe then ingratitude.
            Among the Romanes, if a bondſlaue were ſet free, and afterwards found to bee iuſtly taxed of ingratitude, it was lawfull for this fault to reuoke his libertie againe, and to retaine him in his former ſeruitude.
            Wee wonder at monſters, as repugnant to nature, as are the Centaurs, Satyres, a man with foure heades, and ſuch like, but wee wonder not at

Dogges, Wolues, Foxes, Hares, Cats, &amp;c. becauſe their forme and proportion An example.is agreeable to nature: So we maruel not at other vices which proceed of our frailty, and are incident to our naturall corruption (though we loath them) as gluttony, drunkenneſſe, luſt, wrath, enuy, &amp;c. and ſuch other damnable Simile.vices: but ingratitude, as an odious monſter, an vnnaturall vice, a prodigious exorbitant, all good men deteſt and wonder at. For as it is a thing naturall, amantem redamare, to repay loue for loue, becauſe loue is onely requited with reciprocall loue: So it is a monſtrous thing not to loue againe, and ſhew our ſelues vnthankful to our louing God, who is ſuch an infinite benefactor to mankinde.
            The very Ethnikes and Paganes ſhall riſe in iudgement againſt Chriſtiſtians, and condemne them for their ingratitude towards God. When the Tarentines were beſieged of the Romanes, and were in danger (through

famine) to yeeld themſelues and their Cittie into the hands of their enemies, the Rhegians (ordeining a feaſt euery tenth day) ſent reliefe vnto the Tarentines, for which benefite (when they were deliuered from the Romanes) and in memory of their former miſery, they inſtituted an yearely feaſt, which they called Ieiunum (ſaith Elianus 
                     〈◊〉
                   hiſt. lib. 5.
               
               Aelianus variae hiſt. lib. 5. Prophane hiſtories are full of ſuch like examples. And is it not a ſhame that Ethnikes, and men without God in the world, ſhould condemne Chriſtians of ingratitude, and that the ſparkles, and darke glimſe of reaſon and honeſty, ſhould worke more with them, then the light of faith, and bright beames of piety can preuaile with vs?
            Whoſo is thankfull for ſmall benefites receiued, deſerueth to receiue greater of his friend: and God hateth ingratitude not ſo much for his owne, as for our ſakes, becauſe t doth as it were cloſe vp Gods hands

of liberality, and turneth his face from vs. For the hope of the vnthankfull 
               Wiſ. 16. 29.
               ſhall melt as the winter yee, and flowe away as vnprofitable waters, ſaith the wiſe man, VViſdome. 16. 29. Qui grate beneficium accipit primam eius penſionem ſoluit. Hee that thankfully receiueth Seneca de benefic.a benefite, hath made the firſt requital, ſaith Seneca.
            
            Nothing did more winne the loue of Auguſtus Caeſar to Furnius, and made him facile, and willing to grant other thinges vnto him, then that when hee had obtained pardon for his Father, who tooke part with Anthonie, hee ſaid: Haec 
               Eraſ. apoph. lib. 
                     •…
                  
               
               vna (O Ceaſar) abs te mihi facta est iniuria, effecti, vt viuerem &amp; morerer, ingratus. This onely iniury (O Caeſar,) thou haſt done mee, in that thou makeſt mee liue and dye as an vnthannkefull man. Signifying that ſo great was this benefite, that hee was inſufficient euer to requite

it. Eraeſmus Apophth lib. 7. Take wee heede therefore brethren, of this barbarous ſin of ingratitude towards God.
            Thirdly, all Paſtours are here taught by this example of Chriſt, who ſpake vnto the people by eaſie and familiar parables and ſimilitudes, ſtudiouſly and wiſely to frame their Sermons according to the capacity of the people, and not to affect a a ſtrange, ſtile and phraſe of ſpeech, or to vſe verbis ſeſquipedalibus, (as Euſebius, Libr▪
                4. Cap. 11. writeth of the Marcionites) high and loftie Euſeb.words. For, nihil frigidius doctore qui verbis duntaxat philoſophatur. Neque enim hoc doctoris ſed hyſtrionis eſt, ſaith Chryſoſtome. Homil. 1. Act. 1. Nothing is more cold and fooliſh, then that Chryſ. hom. 1. act. 1.
               Teacher which diſputeth onely in words: neither is it the part of a Teacher, but rather of a player. And verbis ludere, &amp; apud imperitū vulgus admirationē ſui facere indoctorū hominū est.
               
               Hier. in epiſt ad Neop.
               Hier. in Epiſt. ad Neop. By playing and dallying in words, to bring the vnlearned people in admiration of him, is the property of ignorant and vnskilfull men.
            
               1. Cor. 2. 1. 3.Far otherwiſe did the Apoſtle Paul, which came not in excellency of words, nor in enticing ſpeech of mans wiſedome, but in plaine euidence of the ſpirit, and of power, 1. Cor. 2. 1. 3. Praedicator enim (ſaith Bern.) plus intendere debet ad imbuenda 
               Ber ſer. 16. in Cant.
               corda, quam ad exprimenda verba. For a preacher ſhould ſeeke rather to inſtruct the heart, then to expreſſe eloquent words, which is but to feede the eare.
            
                Out of this whole parable in generall, in that our Sauiour ſhadowed out the kingdome of heauen by many parables, it was 1. that it might be fulfilled which was ſpoken by the Prophet. Pſal. 78. 2.
               Pſal. 78. 2. I will open my mouth in a parable, which the Euangeliſt alſo alleageth to the ſame purpoſe in this chapter, ver 3
                  •
               . 2. That (as Greg. ſaith) ex his
               
               quae animus nouit ſurgat ad incognita quae nō nouit. That the minde by the things it knoweth might mount vp to thoſe things which it knoweth not. Theſe parables therefore are not careleſly to be paſſed ouer, but zealouſly and religiouſly to be pondered, that wee may obſerue the doctrine thereof, to our comfort, inſtitution, and inſtruction.
            
               The ſecōd part.The ſecond part ſetteth downe the malice and induſtry of Sathan, in corrupting the good ſeed with the darnel and tares of vices. And this is the Diuels ſeed which he ſoweth in the furrowes of iniquity. The protaſis or propoſition is: euen as a man ſowing good ſeed in his field, his enemy whiles hee ſlept, ſowed tares among the wheate. Apodoſis: Euen ſo Chriſt the ſonne of man, ſoweth his word the good ſeed, in his Church, but men being ſecure, careleſſe, and negligent, the Diuell came and ſowed hereſies, deprauation of good doctrine, ſcandals, and all kind of vices, that hee might corrupt the

               The tares▪ what.ſame. By the tares are ſignified the children of the wicked, verſ. 38. that is, all hypocrites, and the whole rabble of wicked men, which are the children 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               illius mali, of that wicked, that is, of the diuell, which 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Synecdochicā
                is called wicked, a cauſa efficiente procreante, becauſe he is the principall cauſe of all euill, both to himſelfe and to otherrs. The wicked are called the children of the diuell, not from the efficient procreant cauſe, as if the diuell▪ had created them, neither from the formal cauſe, as thogh their very eſſence were deſtroied &amp; changed into euil: but firſt ab adiunctis, becauſe in their malice and wickedneſſe they reſemble, and are compared to the Diuell. Secondly, ab effectis, becauſe in their liues and conuerſation they imitate the Diuell.
            
               Obſeru. &amp; doctrine. Firſt, wee heere learne that Sathan is the infatigable enemy of mankinde, and that this is his perpetuall

practiſe, by all meanes to worke our deſtruction. And that he may the better effect this, hee laboureth chiefly to ſupreſſe the firſt beginnings of godlilines, to corrupt the very ſeed, and to choke vp the corne in the blade, that it neuer may growe to maturity and ripeneſſe. Semper primordia pulſat, captat 
               Chryſoſt. in Mat.
               rudimenta virtutum▪ ſancta in ipſo ortu feſtinat extinguere, ſciens quod ea fundata ſubuertere non poſsit, (ſaith Chryſoſtome.) His pollicy is euer to bee ſtriking at the beginnings of goodneſſe, hee catcheth at the firſt rudiments and principles of vertues, holy deſires, at their firſt budding, and ſpringing hee haſteneth to extinguiſh, knowing that if they take deep roote, he ſhall not be able to ſubuert them.
            
               1 Pet. 5. 8.And therefore hee walketh about like a roaring Lyon, 1. Peter chapter 5. verſe 8. Yea, among the Sonnes of God, Iob. chapter 1. verſ. 6. hauing 
               Iob. 1. 6.
               great wrath, knowing that he hath but a
               
               Apoc. 12. 12.
               ſhort time, &amp; the neerer the end of the world approacheth, the more fiercely he rageth, as it appeareth by the ouerflowing ſeas of all iniquity vpon the whole face of the earth in theſe later times. And euen at the beginning, as ſoone as God had ſowne original righteouſneſſe, he caſt in the ſeed of originall ſinne, wherewith hee infected the recent purity, and choaked with his tares the ſeed of God, which was the ſeminary of all euill. And this he effecteth not onely by inward ſuggeſtions, but alſo by outward enticements of wicked men, and that not by their filthy and corrupt communication onely, but alſo by the peſtilent ſeed of euill examples he laboureth to infect the minds of men, and to catch them in his net: yea, in thoſe that heare The Diuell three maner of wayes hindreth the fruit of the word.the word of God, hee hindereth the fruit thereof three maner of waies: Either through wandring and idle cogitations, whereby he taketh away the attention of their mindes from the

word, or through the tumults of perſecutions, or at leaſt through couetouſneſſe, and the cares of this life: and which is worſt of all, hee permitteth not the ſeede that fell in the good ground (if by any means he may) to be long vncorrupted: and to this end he hath many falſe Apoſtles which wreſt and peruert the ſacred Scripture, and in ſtead of the naturall milke it giueth, wring out the bloud of ſubtile &amp; violent interpretation, and cauſe it to walke a mile or two further for their fancy, then euer the holy Ghoſt meant it: as it is vſuall this day with the Papiſts, for the ſupporting of the kingdome of Antichriſt.
            
            He doth alſo captare occaſionem, take his opportunity, and therfore it is ſaid: while men ſlept, a metaphor taken from the bodily ſleep, in which all the ſenſes are conſopited, ſecure, and at reſt. The definition of ſleepe.This ſleepe is not a corporall, but a ſpirituall ſleepe of the ſoule, which is ſhadowed out by the bodily ſleepe,

which Ariſtotle, and out of him Galen thus defineth: Somnus eſt quies virtututum animalium, per antiperist aſin ob fumos in caput aſcendentes, vnde frigiaitate cerebri repercutiuntur, hinc redeuntes ad cor, obſtruunt ſenſuum organa, that is: Sleepe is the reſt of the animall powers, through an Antiperistaſis, or repulſion on euery part, (whereby heate or cold is made more ſtrong in it ſelfe, by the reſtraining of the contrary) by reaſon of the fumes or vapours aſcending into the head, from whence returning backe to the heart, they ſtoppe the organs of the ſenſes.
            This then is the ſpirtuall veternum and lethargy, when men are altogether careleſſe, negligent, and ſecure of their ſoules, and as if their ſenſes were aſleepe or dead, they haue no feeling of any godly motions in their heart.
            
               Two things to be conſidered.But for your better edification, let vs firſt ſee what ſleepe is in this place. Secondly, how great a ſinne and detriment

this is vnto vs.
            Firſt, men ſlept, hauing reeeiued the good ſeede in the fieldes of their heart, when in vaine they receiue the grace of God. Therefore the Apoſtle rowſeth vp the Corinthians, that they ſleepe not: As workers 
               2 Cor. 6. 1.
               together we beſeech you that yee receiue not the grace of God in vaine▪
                1. Cor. chap. 6. verſ. 1. A thing is receiued in vaine, when it is not applyed to that end for which it was ordained. In Simile▪
               vaine doeſt thou buy a garment, if thou neuer putteſt it on. In vaine haſt thou receiued thy ſoule, the grace of God, the good ſeede, if thou directeſt not the ſame to the deſires of heauenly things, to the fruite of good workes, for the obtaining whereof the ſoule was created, &amp; other graces giuen of God. But to come to ſome particular men are ſaid to ſleep when they neglect &amp; abuſe the grace of God, &amp; the good ſeed, whiles they hearken not to the coūſel of the Apoſtle: Take heed that no
               
               Hob. 12. 15
               man fall away from the grace of God, Heb. 12. 15. that is, that hee abuſe not the good ſeede, and neglect the vſe thereof▪ 
               Let no roote of bitterneſse ſpring vp and trouble you (ſaith he) For euen as through the negligence of the huſband mā many noy ſome weeds ſpring vp, which hinder the growth of the good ſeed, and fret away the corne: ſo the growth of the tares of vices hinder the operation of grace. Wherfore ſaid the Apoſtle a little before. Lift vp 
               Verſe 12.
               your hands which hang downe, and your weake knees▪
                that is, ſhake off all drow▪ſineſſe, and negligence. Who would not iudge that their faith ſleepeth, yea that it is dead, which neuer ſheweth forth the vitall motions of godlineſſe? Eph. 4. 14.which are wauering, &amp; ſuffer themſelues to be carried away like children with euery winde of vaine doctrine, by the deceipt &amp; eraftineſſe of men▪ whereby they lay waite to deceiue, Epheſ. 4. Of which number are they that reuolt from the Goſpell to Papiſtry, and wreſt religion and the

Scriptures, vt Lesbiam regulam (as the prouerbe is) or frame their profeſſion as a noſe of waxe vnto all faſhions, to pleaſe mens humours, and to ſerue their turne. Doth not their hope ſleep which is not fixed on the inuiſible &amp; heauenly good things, which ſhould allure them to the loue of a good life? Seemeth not their charity to bee extinct, which kindleth no ſparkes of the loue of God, and of their neighbour in their hearts? Doth not their wiſedome and reaſon, only proper to man, ſleep (whoſe office is to foreſee imminent dangers, diſcerne betwixt good and euill, and to prouide for the life to come) when they liue ſo ſupine and careleſſe of their ſoules, and willingly ſuffer themſelues to be caught in the ſnares of Sathan?
            He ſleepeth, yea he is in a dangerous ſleepe, which liueth in enuy, hatred, and malice of his neighbour: Hee that 
               1 Ioh. 2. 11.
               hateth his brother is in darkneſſe (ſaith Saint Iohn.
            
            
               
The carnall, filthy, lecherous, and licencious liuer ſleepeth, which is not aſhamed to commit that filthineſſe, Eph. 5. 12.which a good Chriſtian ſhould bee aſhamed euen to name (ſaith the Apopoſtle) Eph. 5. 12.
            
               The couetous worldling▪ ſleepeth, yea and that ſweetly, as he thinketh, 
               Luk. 12. 19.
               when he ſaith: Soule, liue at eaſe, eate, drinke, and take thy pleaſure, thou haſt much goods laid vp in ſtore for many yeares, Luk. 12. 19. but the ſpirit of God intituleth them by the name of fooles ſaying: Thou foole, this night ſhall they fetch away thy ſoule from thee, and then whoſe ſhal thoſe things be which thou haſt prouided? verſe 20.
            
            The glutton, drunkard, whoſe God is his belly, ſleepeth, whom the Apoſtle Peter ſtirreth vp with the conſideration 1. Pet. 5. 8.of his danger, ſaying: Be ſober, and watch, for your aduerſary the Diuell, as a roaring Lyon, walketh about, ſeeking whom he may deuoure.
            
            The negligent, ſecure, and ſluggiſh

Chriſtian ſleepeth, who taketh no care of his ſoule, but ſetteth it vpon ſixes and ſeuens, of whom ſaith Salomon: 
               Pro. 22. 13.
               The ſlothfull man ſaith, a Lyon is without I ſhall be ſlaine in the ſtreete. Pro. 22 to him all things ſeeme hard, all things pertaining to godlineſſe and deuotion, ſeeme vnpoſſible: hee can finde no time as yet to ariſe from his ſins, no time with him is fit for repentance.
            But (beloued) the ſpirit of God, who beſt knoweth the importance heereof, is in nothing more frequent and earneſt, then in exhorting vs, vs (I ſay) which are regenerate in Chriſt, the good ſeede, the children of the kingdome, to vigilancy and watchfulneſſe, that we giue not place vnto the Diuell. Chriſt cryeth out, and repeateth it againe, that hee might impreſſe it in our memories: VVatch (ſaith he) and what I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto all mē: watch. 
               Mar. 13. 37.Againe, if the good man of the houſe had
               
               Luk. 12. 39.
               knowne what houre the thiefe would come, hee wold haue watched, and not haue ſuffered his houſe to bee digged through. Luk 12. 39. So that veſſell of election, Saint Paul, reaſoneth and exhorteth Gods children, ſaying: Yee are all children of the light, and of the day: we are not of the night, neither of darkneſse. Therefore let 
               1 Theſ. 5. 5. 6.
               vs not ſleepe as other doe, but let vs watch and be ſober. 1. Theſſ. 5. 5. 6. And our Sauiour againe counſaileth, ſaying: Bee 
               Luk. 12. 36
               yee like vnto men that waite for their maiſter when hee returne from the wedding, Luk. 12. 36. Nothing truly might more ſignificantly be ſpoken to incite vs to perpetuall vigilance. Seruants doe neuer with greater carefulneſſe waite for their maiſter, then when the ſolemnity of his mariage being ended, he returneth home to dinner, that nothing bee wanting, but all things neceſſary bee prouided, and in reedineſſe for ſuch a feaſt: So ſhould all true Chriſtians be euer vigilant, waiting for the coming of the Lord, that they

be not found vnprepared: For the ſon 
               Luk. 12. 40.
               of man will come at an houre when yee thinke not.
            
            Now let vs ſee how dangerous and hurtfull it is vnto vs, not to watch, but liue ſecurely, whiles we are in the warfare of this life. The enemy now ſeeing our ſupine negligence, aud ſtupide careleſneſſe of our ſoules, now beſtirreth him, hee will not looſe this fit oportunity, this is Sathans ſowing ſeaſon, now he caſteth abroade his tares, now he prepareth his ground, that is, the hearts of the wicked to receiue his peſtilent ſeede, as thou mayeſt eaſily perceiue if thou obſerue the manners of wicked men, if thou ſeekeſt at that time to awake them, &amp; admoniſh them of their dangers, they will (perhaps) heare, &amp; approue thy ſayings, but being preſſed downe with the weight of wicked cuſtome, they betake them againe to their ſleep, &amp; as the wiſe man ſaith, who ſo telleth a foole of wiſedome 
               Eccleſ. 22.
               is as a man that ſpeaketh to one that is aſleepe,
               
               Eccleſiaſticus, chap. 22. As one that is ſicke of a feuer, to whom Simile.ſleepe is very hurtfull, if thou pull him, and with noyſe ſtirre him vp, and tell him that ſleepe nouriſheth and increaſeth his diſeaſe, hee lifteth vp his drowſie eyes, and heareth thee, but being ouercome with the force of the hurtfull humour, hee is drowned againe with ſleepe: So it happeneth to thoſe that are plunged in the ſleepe of ſinne, and pleaſures of the world: if wee call vpon them, lay before them death, iudgement, hell, perpetuall torments, prepared for the wicked, their ſinnes committed, the danger of ſuddaine death, &amp;c. Heauen, and the moſt bleſſed reward prepared for the godly, &amp;c. they will heare this, and confeſſe it to bee true: but being ouercome with the violence of euill cuſtome, they ſtill proceede in their ſinfull courſes.
            The enemy all this while is ſpreading his net, he knoweth his oportunity:

now is the time hee may moſt preuaile: he entreth thy houſe like a theefe when thou ſleepeſt. Bleſsed therefore (ſaith the Spirit of God) is Apo. 16. 15.
               hee that watcheth, and keepeth his garments, leaſt he walke naked, and men ſee his filthineſse, Apoc. 16. 15.
            Conſider (beloued) and with a carefull heart conſider, that none were excluded from the mariage of the bridegrome, the heauenly ioyes, but ſuch as were not prepared, which ſlept, and wanted oyle in their lampes, Math. 25. If Matth. 25.thoſe ſeruants bee bleſsed (as the Lord witneſſeth) whom the Lord, when hee cometh, 
               Luk. 12. 37.
               ſhall finde waking, Luke. 12. 37. Then ſurely, curſed, &amp; moſt wretched ſhall he be whom the Lord ſhall finde ſleeping, ſecure, and careleſſe. If thou wilt not watch, I will come vpon thee as a Theefe, and thou ſhalt not know 
               Apoc▪ 3. 3.
               what houre I will come vpon thee (ſaith the Spirit of God) Apoc. 3. 3. As the bird is hardly taken wich is flying, and in motion, but when ſhe ſitteth, ſhee is

in moſt danger: ſo the aduerſary catcheth none but ſuch as are negligent and careleſſe of their ſoules. As the ſweet waters are euer in motion and running: ſo the ſtanding waters are neither ſweet nor holſome, and ingender nothing but hurtfull and poyſoſoned Simile.things. In a forſaken houſe, where none doe inhabite, vncleane beaſts increaſe, as rats, mice, ſerpents. Beaſts which lye long on the ground, and walke not (they ſay) looſe their hooffes. The birds which ſit long in their neſts, looſe their feathers. And it is a prouerbe: Priuilegio non vtentes vel abutentes perduni illud. A priuiledge may be loſt by not vſing, or abuſing it: So he falleth from Gods grace, is depriued of the good ſeede, eaſily admitteth the tares of wicked deſires, which ſleepeth, is idle, and negligent to keepe carefull watch ouer his ſoule.
            Now for how many cauſes this ſpirituall negligence is dangerous, let vs

briefly vnfold. Hee that is to make a In how many reſpects this negligence is hurtfull.long iourney, and the time ſhort, hee cometh not to his iourneyes end except he keepe continuall walking. We are all trauelling towards heauen, our Similiun congeries.eternall country, the way is long, becauſe many temptations and difficulties are to bee ouercome, many good deeds are to bee done in the worke of the Lord, many euils are to bee ſuffered in the way before wee come thither. Our time is the time of this life,  which is very ſhort, but a moment, a vapour, a thing of nothing, inſtans eſt, momentum est, ictus oculi eſt, but an inſtant, a moment, the twinckling of an eye: yea, the time wherein wee liue, (which is but the preſent time) is ſo ſhort, and fleeting, that it cannot bee circumſcribed. Why then are we careleſſe? why loyter we? why ſleepe wee in the way? why are we ſo negligent in our iourney?
            Againe, when a man is expected  and looked for of his Lord, it is not

meete that hee ſhould make haſte, be carefull and vigilant? but all the Saints of God, yea God himſelfe, expecteth vs in our heauenly countrye.
            
                If a man bee inuited of a great man to a feaſt, were hee not worthy iuſtly to be blamed, if he ſhould linger by the way, and come too late? were hee not in danger, that coming out of ſeaſon, bee ſhould bee excluded and ſhut out? But our Sauiour calleth vs all to his great Luk. 14. 16Supper, the banquet of eternall glory, the euerlaſting feaſt of all bleſſedneſſe, and ſhall wee ſhewe our ſelues careleſſe, and not rather haſten with all alacrity, and cheerefulneſſe of heart?
            
                Againe, when there are many impediments in the way, either becauſe it is hard to finde, or infeſted with Theeues, and ſuch like difficulties, is it not meete that the Traueller ſhould walk ſo much the more warily

and expeditely? But in the way towards heauen are many temptations, many diuels lye in waite, many difficulties laid before vs: let vs therefore caſt away all ſleepe and negligence, and ſpeedily go forward in the way of eternal life.
            If thou ſhouldeſt haue a friend  who kindely ſhould offer thee his friendly helpe and meanes to eſcape any imminent perill, ſhouldeſt thou not greatly offend ſuch a friend in neglecting theſe meanes? But God freely offereth his grace and holy ſpirit to all that by faithfull and feruent prayer craue the ſame at his handes, by which meanes we may aſſuredly eſcape all perils obiected in the way of ſaluation.
            Laſtly, hee that omitteth the oportunate  time allotted him for the obtaining of any thing, doth not he deſerue grieuouſly to bee taxed of great negligence? Fronte capillata, poſt eſt occaſio calua: Occaſion hath

               Old father Time hath haity locks before, but not behindlong locks before, but is bald behinde, to teach vs not to ſlip the preſent occaſion, leaſt being paſt, we can take no hold to pull it backe againe. And this life is the time that God hath in mercy Cato.giuen vs to worke in: The night (of 
               Ioh. 9. 4,
               death) cometh, when no man can worke, Ioh▪
                9. 4. Behold now is the accepted time, 
               2 Cor. 6. 2, 2 Theſ. 5. 6.
               behold, now is the day of ſaluatiō, 2. Cor. 6. 2 Let vs therfore watch and be ſober, 1. Theſ. 5. 6. For while men ſlept, the enemy came and ſowed tares, ſaith this text.
            
               The third obſeruatiō.Thirdly, I obſerue, in that it is ſaid this enemy of mankinde watched his oportunity to ſow his tares while men ſlept: That our owne negligence and ſecurity giueth the diuell aduantage and victory ouer vs: for not by his owne power, but through our ſlothfull careleſneſſe he ſowed tares among the wheate. Therefore ſaith S. Iames: 
               Iamees 4.
               Reſiſt the deuill and hee will flye from you. Iamees 4. If any man by his aduerſary ſhould be called into the law, and bee in danger not onely of his goods, but

alſo of his life, the which aduerſary hath no power of himſelfe, but is ſuch a one that if he reſiſt and oppoſe himſelfe againſt him, hee is eaſily vanquiſhed: Who is ſo mad, ſo blockiſh and ſlothfull, as not no reſiſt, and ſtoutly withſtand ſuch an aduerſary? who is ſo ſottiſh to feare ſuch an enemy, and to ſuffer himſelfe to be ouercome? but ſuch an aduerſary is the diuell, by his temptations and ſuggeſtions hee laboureth to bring vs to the barre, and tribunall of Gods ſeuere iuſtice: but if we hold vp the ſhield of faith, the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God, the breaſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, continuall and deuoute prayers, &amp;c. and other parts of our Chriſtian panoplie, mentioned Epheſ. 6. like a Epheſ. 6.daſtard he betaketh him to his heeles, and flyeth from vs. It is therefore our owne fault, and negligent ſlothfulnes that we are ouercome, that he ſoweth his tares in the field of our ſoule. And therefore the Apoſtle Peter ſaith to

               Ananias, Acts 5. 3. VVhy hath Sathan filled thine heart? He doth not ſay, why did Sathan tempt thee? for that is his perpetual practiſe, but why diddeſt thou giue way to him? why didſt thou ſuffer him to enter in, and to fill thine heart? And as Ieremy ſaid once of the rebellious Iewes: That they had taught their enemies to bee captaines ouer them▪
                (ſpeaking of their captiuity. The ſame may bee ſaid of vs, wee our ſelues doe teach the diuell which way to aſſault vs, becauſe wee bee ſleepy and negligent, Simile.fearefull, and diſtruſtfull of Gods prouidence, couetous, and carnall liuers, and ſo it chanceth to vs, as vnto the birds, which gaping greedily after their prey, are caught in the ſnare before they ſee it. Hence it cometh, that our deſires, and inordinate affections expoſe vs to the ſnares of the enemy, and we are caught inconſiderately in his net, whiles we are greedily gaping to ſatisfie our ſinfull luſtes and affections, hauing no other

minde, but vpon the fulfilling therof.
            
               Obſer. 4.When Sathan had ſowne his tares, (it is ſaid) hee went his way: For when hee hath ſowne his peſtilent ſeede, hee faineth to depart, he knoweth well the operation thereof, how it will worke, it will in his time grow ſo ranke, that it will corrupt quickly the ſeede of godlineſſe. Hee ſoweth the ſeede of pride in thine heart, and goeth his way, knowing that in time it wil grow ſo high that the ſpirit of God will take no pleaſure there. He caſteth in thy minde the ſeed of luſt, and goeth his way, hee aſſureth himſelfe, that at laſt it will breake forth into the fire of fornication, and all vncleanneſſe. He caſteth abroad the ſeed of enuy, &amp; goeth his way, he knoweth wel that in time it will grow to malice, ſtrife contentions, &amp; murthers, ſo fruitful is this noiſome ſeed where it hath once taken root. Take heed therefore how thou once admitteſt this ſeede into thine heart, caſt it preſently out, ſuffer it

to take no roote, for if it ſtay there, i
                  •
                will ſpring vp, and yeeld moſt peſtilent fruit. Vigilat hoſtis, &amp; tu dormis? ſaith Auguſtine,
               Auguſtine, thy enemy euer watcheth Greg. lib. 32 moral. cap.and doeſt thou ſleepe? yea, great is the malice of this enemy, that as Gregory ſaith: Arte ſeſe palliat vt ante decept
                     •…
                   mentis eculos, culpas virtutes fingat, vt inde quiſquam quaſi expectet praemia vnde dignus eſt inuenire aeterna tormenta. He maketh himſelfe by art, that before the eyes of a deceiued minde, vice might ſeeme to be vertue, that a man might expect a reward for that, for which indeed hee deſerueth eternall torments, he ſo vaileth himſelfe vnder the vizard of vertue. Diabolus eſt ſerpens lubricus, the diuell is a ſlippery Iſidor, lib. 3. de ſummo bano.ſerpent, whoſe head, that is, his firſt ſuggeſtion, if it bee not reſiſted, totus in intimacordis, dum nōſentitur illabitur, ſaith Iſidor, he windeth himſelfe wholly in before thou be aware. Semper viſcoſa ſunt carnis deſideria, fleſhly deſires be euer viſcous, for of ſuggeſtion, if

you giue way, ſpringeth cogitation, from cogitation (if ye reſiſt not there) he proceedeth to affection, from affection to delectation, from delectation to conſent, from conſent to action, from action to cuſtome, from cuſtome to obſtinacy, from obſtinacy to hardneſſe of heart, from hardneſſe of heart to boaſting, from boaſting to deſperation, from deſperation to damnation. And thus by degrees he climbeth to the toppe of perdition. Reſiſt therefore (brethren) betime his fury and ſuggeſtions, ſtedfast in the faith, 1. Pet. 5. 1 Pet. 5
               putting vpon you the whole armor of God 
               Epheſ. 6. Iames 4.
               Epheſ. 6. and he will flye from you, Iame. 4 If in keeping our riches againſt the lying in waite of theeues, againſt ſuperfluous expences, againſt future wants, that we may haue whereby to ſupport our ſtate, we beſtow a thouſand cares, we vſe great circumſpection. If we ſo carefully ſtoppe, binde, hoope, and place, our wine, or oyle veſſels, leaſt they ſhould leake, or bee corrupted.

If we ſo diligently looke vnto our garments, and other houſhold ſtuffe, that they be not conſumed of the mothes, ſpotted with any liquor, ſtained with the duſt: what an abſurd thing is it, &amp; vnworthy of a Chriſtian, not to haue the ſame care of the good ſeed of graces which we haue receiued of God to our ſaluation, and eternal glory, that it be not choked and corrupted with Ser. 12 ſup. Pſal. 91.
               the tares of Sathan▪ 
               Viae diaboli (ſaith S. Bernard) ſunt circuitio &amp; circumuentio, circuit terram &amp; perambulat eam, vt nos circumueniat. The wayes of Sathan are circuition, &amp; circumuention, he compaſſeth the earth, and walketh through the ſame, that hee might circumuent vs. Neither if ſometimes he ſeeme to ceaſſe, ſhould we therefore bee vnprepared?
            
               SimileThe wiſe Captaines in the time of truce, do fortifie their holds, and repaire their bulwarkes▪ ſo ſhould the Chriſtian Souldier do in the peace of his conſcience. It is true that hee that
               
               keepeth Iſrael doth neither ſlumber nor ſleepe; but neither doth hee ſlumber nor ſleepe which impugneth Iſrael. Shall wee bee ſecure (ſaith Bernard againe) becauſe we be aſſiſted on euery ſide? Nay, for this cauſe ſhould we the more ſtudiouſly watch, for God would neuer take ſuch care of vs, if hee did not know our neceſsity and danger to be great. Non 
               Ibid. Ser. 11
               
               tam multiplex nobis cuſtodia, niſi ob multiplices inſidias poneretur. Gods cuſtody and ſuccours would neuer bee ſo manifold towards vs, if the ſnares of Sathan were not manifold. Laert. lib. 1.
               
            
            
               Solon made a lawe, that hee that liued idlely ſhould bee expoſed, for euery one that would to accuſe him. The like law hath God made, that hee that followeth idleneſſe, and is negligent of his ſaluation, ſhould bee laied open to all temptations, and accuſations of the Diuel.
            
               Obſeru. 5. Two cauſes of all euill.Seeing this enuious man the diuell, ſowed his tares whiles men ſlept, we learne that there are 2. cauſes of all euil

that is in the world: the malice of Sathan, and our owne negligence. Euill Lib, 1 de ſummo bono. cap. 2.
               (as Iſidor ſaith) non est a Deo creatum, ſed a diabolo inuentum, is not created of God, but deuiſed by the Diuell. Hee 
               Ioh. 8▪
               
               was a murtherer from the beginning, and the father of lyes, Ioh 8. As I liue, ſaith the 
               Eze. 33. 11
               Lord, I deſire not the death of the wicked, Ezek. 33. 11. Neither is there any fatall neceſſity to be imagined: for God in calling, ſo calleth, that withall he inclineth God not the author of euill.the will, hee ſo forſaketh the reprobate, that they themſelues otherwiſe will not. And this is manifeſt in Paul the Apoſtle, which was a perſeſecuting enemy of Chriſt, til the houre came of his calling: then Chriſt ſo called him, that withall he gaue him a minde to will, and hee cryed: Lord, what wilt thou haue me to doe? Contrariwiſe, hee ſo forſooke Iudas▪
                that his will was ſtill delighted in his wickedneſſe. So that here is no conſtrained neceſſity, for the nature of cut will is not hindered: yea it aſſenteth to good

or euill: thoſe being willing, he draweth: others, being alſo vnwilling, he paſſeth ouer, neither of them againſt their wils he conſtraineth. Farre be it from vs therefore that by any meanes, directly or indirectly we ſhould affirme God to be the author of euill. Optimi eſt optima facere▪
                it is the property of the beſt, to do alwayes the beſt things: but God is optimus, the ſoueraigne good, for he is eſſentially good, of whom are all other good things, therefore it is of the nature of the diuine goodneſſe, to doe alwaies that which is good.
            
               Obiect.But why then (wil ſome ſay) is God ſaid in ſcripture to harden the heart of Pharaoh, for thus it is in the Hebrue, Exod. 4. 21
               Exod. 4. 21. Vaani achazek. I will harden his heart. Againe, vatachazek, the Lord 
               Exod. 11. 10
               hardened Pharaohs heart, Exod. 11. 10. This is attributed vnto God, not that Anſwer.God is the author of induration, inſomuch as it is euill, and worketh that which is euill: but becauſe God vſeth

well theſe euils, and doth gouerne them that are hardened to ſome good end.
            Sathan hardeneth by ſuggeſting, and perſwading: man hardeneth himſelfe when hee conſenteth to the entiſements of Sathan, and by his owne will turneth himſelfe from God. God hardeneth by forſaking. So ſaith Saint Aug. con. Fauſtum.
               Auguſtine: Diabolus ſuggerit, homo conſentit, Deus deſerit. The diuell ſuggeſteth, man conſenteth, and God forſaketh. And this to a modeſt minde may ſuffice.
            
               Obſeru. 6.Here note that the deuil ſoweth three moſt peſtilent ſeedes in the world. which are ſignified in the nature and property of tares, which the Arabians call Zizania, the Greekes 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                in Latine Lolium, in Engliſh Tares, Iuray 
               
                  Iefoelix lolium 
                        ••…
                     r ſteri
                        ••
                      
                     
                        ••
                     minant
                        ••
                      au
                        •
                     
                     
                     
                        •
                     e.
                  Virg.
               or Dainell. The Phyſitions ſay, that tares haue theſe three properties▪ 
               vim acutam, ventoſam ac vene
                     ••
                  ſam, an acute, a windy, and a venemous qualicie.
            
               
In that they haue an acute or ſubtile quality, they reſemble couetouſneſſe, which euer carieth with it the very myſtery of deceit, fraud, and ſubtilty, to deceiue the ſimple. They are Hoſ. 5. 1.compared vnto Fowlers, Hoſe. 5. 1. the ſimple and plaine meaning men are but as birds for their nets: VVhoſo flattereth 
               Prou. 29.
               his neighbour with his lips, ſpreadeth a net for him. They are like a ſharpe raſour, which quickly ſhaueth away the haire: ſo the crafty couetous man ſoone ſpoyleth the ſimple of all that he hath.
            So great at this day is the growth of this peſtilent tare in the world, that it hath almoſt choaked vp the good wheate of ſimplicity and plaine dealing among men. Such hath been the wonderfull induſtry of the enuious man in ſowing his tares.
            But let theſe crafty Foxes remember, yea, let them with a feeling heart remember the terrible wo pronoūced by God himſelf againſt them, Hab, 2. 9

VVo be vnto him that coueteth an euill coue Mab. 2. 9. 11 12.touſneſſe into his houſe, that hee may ſet his neſt on high, and eſcape the power of euill. For the Hone ſhall cry out of the wall, and the beame of the timber ſhall anſwer it: wo vnto him that buildeth a Towne with bloud, and erecteth a Cittie by iniquity.
            
                In that they haue a windy property: is ſignified pride and ambition, which alſo is one of the Diuels principall tares: for he knoweth well how true Eccleſ. 10, 14.this ſaying of the wiſe man is: Pride is the originall of ſinne, and he that hath 
               1. Pet. 5. 5. Iames 4.
               it ſhall powre out abhomination vntill hee bee ouer th
                     •
                   own, Eccleſ 10. 14 Fo
                     •
                   God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to the humble. 1 Pet. 5. 5. Which, if wee conſider the different end of pride and of humility, we may plainly ſee in proud Lucifer, and in humble Chriſt, in aſpiring Eue, and in the lowly virgin Mary, in the high minded rich glutton, and in vlcerated poore Lazarus, in the proud Phariſie, and in the penitent

Publicane. In theſe we may eaſily ſee Matth. 11.how well God liketh of this filthy tare of pride. There was not a greater by Chriſts owne teſtimony, among womens children, then Iohn Baptist, yet behold his wonderfull humility: hee anſwered to the Iewes in negatiues, Ioh. 19. 20 21.
               Non ſum non ſum, non ſum, (ſaith a Father) I am not, I am not, I am not. But contrariwiſe, the proud man and woman (which are indeede the worſt and leaſt among all womens children.) ſtand all vpon affirmatiues, and ſay ſtil in their owne conceits: I am, I am, I am: they will not looſe one inch of their conceiued reputation. Wel (ſaith Auguſtine) Excelſa eſt patria, humilis eſt 
               Auguſtinus ſuper Ioau.
               viatqui quaerit patriam, quid recuſat viā? Our heauenly country is high, but the way is lowly, hee that ſeeketh his country, why refuſeth hee the way? Againe, O quam excelſus es Domine, ſed 
               In Epiſt.
               humiles corde ſunt domus tuae. O how high art thou O Lord, yet the humble in heart are thine houſe. O that theſe

proud peacockes would ſet before their eyes the example of the Sonne of Phil. 2. 6. 7. 8.God: VVho being in the forme of God, made himſelfe of no reputation, and tooke vpon him the forme of a ſeruant, he humbled himſelfe, and became obedient vnto the death, &amp;c. Philippians, chap. 2. verſ. 6. 7. 8. Quid tumeſcis homo? (ſaith Auguſtine.) 
               Augustiue
               O pellis morticina quid tenderis? O ſanies foetida cur inflaris? why art thou proud O man? why art thou extended O thou dead skinne? thou ſtincking corruption, why art thou puffed vp? thy Prince is humble, and art thou proud? thy head is lowly, and ſhall the members bee high minded? A certaine Phyloſopher being asked of one, Quid ſum, quid fui, quid ero, what I am, what I was, what I ſhall bee, anſwered: Sperma foetidum, vas ſtercorum, &amp; eſca vermium. Stinking ſperme, a veſſell of dung, and meate for wormes. Surely, me thinkes, it ſhould bee ſufficient to cut the combe of pride, and ſtrike

the ſailes of ambition, if wee would but call to minde that our conception is ſin, our life miſery, and our end rottenneſſe and corruption.
            In that the tares haue in them vim venenoſam, a poyſoned quality, (as it may appeare, in that whoſo taketh the ſame into his body, it maketh the head light, and the body to ſwell) is noted the infectious ſinne of whooredome, and fleſhly luſt, another filthy tare wherewith the Diuell hath poyſoned and killed much ſeede of vertue in the world: This noyſome tare ſo infecteth the minde, and choaketh all graces, that it breedeth a conſumption of all goodneſſe in the ſoule where it is ſowne.
            
               In corpore Lentum protrahit, heu moriens qua carperis hectice febrim. Iob. 20.
               It is as Lenta phtiſicorum febris, like a feuer hectike, which cleaueth to the marrow of the bones, conſumeth the body, and neuer endeth but with life it ſelfe: His bones are full of the ſinnes of his youth, and it ſhall lye downe with him in the duſt, (ſaith Iob.) chap. 20.

which is by the iuſt iudgement of God, that they which haue beene the deſtuction of many ſouies by alluring them to the conſent of their filthines, ſhould alſo make wrack of their owne ſoules, and ſo animam pro anima reddāt, pay ſoule for ſoule. Hereof ſpeaketh a certaine Father, that the Diuell hath eſpouſed iniquity to himſelfe, and of her he hath begoten many daughters, as Hypocriſie, which he hath marryed to all diſſemblers and falſe brethren: Rapine and oppreſſion, to great men: Vſury to Citizens: Craft and deceit to Aduocates: Pride to rich men, &amp;c. But his daughter Letchery he hath appropriated to none, but proſtituted her vnto all, that ſo ſhe might draw the the more vnto hell with her.
            For the rooting vp of this hurtfull tare, it ſhall greatly profit, if (among many other places of holy Scripture, which ſhew Gods hatred of this ſin) we would diligently ponder in our mindes the Apoſtles moſt patheticall

reaſons, 1. Cor. 6. The ſumme whereof is: By whooredome great iniury is done to Chriſt our head, to whom Reaſons why wre ſhould flye fornicatiō.our bodies are ſanctified: great reproach to God, who ſhall raiſe vs vp to glory, as hee hath done the body of Chriſt: Great indignity done to the holy Ghoſt, whoſe temple we are, and which dwelleth in vs. Our bodies themſelues are hereby diſhonoured &amp; damnified, which are by whoredome pulled from Chriſt our head, ioined to an harlot, and made one body with her. To conclude, thereby wee are made ſacrilegious theeues, in defiling &amp; giuing of that vnto another which is not in our power. This is the ſumme The horribleneſſe of this ſinne.of the Apoſtles reaſons, which ſhewe the horriblenſſe of this ſinne, and the incomparable loſſe that cometh to the whoore monger thereby, and ſhould be ſufficient to win the moſt refractary minde, if there be left in it one ſpark of the feare God.
            Hauing in ſome ſort delineated the

malice and induſtry of Sathan the enemy of mankinde, in corrupting the good ſeed with the tares of vices, and the oportunity hee watcheth for the ſame.
            Now the order of proſecution requireth that I ſhould ſet downe alſo the weapons and armour which euery good Chriſtian ſhould haue in readines to reſiſt the fury of this enemy, and withſtand his aſſaults, which the bleſſed Apoſtle, and expert Champion of Ieſus Chriſt, out of Gods armory moſt excellently preſcribeth, Epheſ, 6. 14
               Epheſ. 6. verſe. 14. vnto verſe. 19. Stand therefore (ſaith he) with your loynes girt about you with verity, &amp;c The Apoſtle ſaid before: Take vnto you 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : the whole armour of God. Now particularly hee expreſſeth the parts of this armour. He ſetteth downe two kindes of armory neceſſary to euery Souldier againſt his enemy. Some which are needfull for the defence of our ſelues, and other to ſtrike and repell

the enemy. Of the firſt kinde he ſpeaketh, verſe 14. 15. 16. and part of the 17. Of the other, verſe 17. and 18. Hee armeth the whole man from the head to the feete, that hee might in no part bee hurt of his enemy, and of this kinde of armour hee nameth fiue. The Girdle, the Breaſt-plate, the Shooes, the Shield, and the Helmet.
            Hee beginneth with the loynes, which muſt bee ſtrengthened with the girdle; and the breaſt, as the principall parts in which the life and ſtrength conſiſteth, and which the enemy chiefly aſſaulteth; and therefore the ſouldier is wont eſpecially to arme thoſe parts in which the ſtrength and life abideth.
            He ſaith therefore, Stand: he requiquireth here three things.
            Firſt, that euery one ſhould keepe himſelfe in his ſtation or calling, that hee yeeld not, nor turne his backe to the enemy. And this calling is two-fold, Caſling two-fold.the one generall, whereby

we are all called into the Church militant, that is, to the army of Chriſtian Soldiars, vnder the conduct &amp; enſignes of Ieſus Chriſt. The other is a ſpeciall calling whereby a certaine ſtation and office is aſſigned to euery man in the Church, as it is in a military army. Euery one ought eſpecially to keepe himſelfe in the army of the Church, and next in his priuate ſtation. Firſt therefore he requireth that euery one abide in the Church, and that hee depart not from the army for if hee depart, actum est, farewell to him: as to him that going from the army is either ſlaine of the enemy, or of his owne company by the command of his Prince.
            
                Secondly, hee requireth that euery man ſhould conteine himſelfe within the limits of his owne ſtation or calling: for in an army nothing is more pernicious then ataxia and confuſion. Firſt therefore euery man muſt conſtantly remaine within the limits and

bounds of the Church: and next, in his owne proper condition, to which he is peculiarly called, and not to giue place to the Diuel, which diligently laboureth to draw him from both.
            Thirdly, vigilancy and watching is  ſignified by this word ſtand. This is neceſſary alſo, and oppoſed to ſecurity: For while men ſlept this enemy came, and ſowed tares. Bee ſober and watch, 
               1. Pet. 5. 5.
               for your aduerſary the Diuell as a roaring Lyon goeth about, ſeeking whom hee may deuoure. Therefore wee muſt watch, euery one in his ſeuerall ſtation, leſt Sathan oppreſſe vs at vnawares.
            
               The firſt part of the armour.But that we may ſtand in the battell and ouercome, theſe things are required.
            Firſt, Conſtancy in doctrine, or in the  truth: this is the baltheus or girdle wherewith the Apoſtle would haue our loynes girded. The loynes are as the foundation whereon the inferiour and ſuperiour parts of the body doe reſt and leane. For againſt the Diuell

this firſt is neceſſary, that we ſtand faſt in the truth of religion, grounded vpon the word of God, for this is the firſt thing which Sathan ſeeketh to ſhake, and take from vs, namely, the truth of doctrine, and obtrudeth vnto vs lyes, and falſe doctrine.
            This then is the firſt part of the armour of God, the Girdle of truth, vpon which the Church is founded: to 1 Tim. 1.which pertaineth this of the Apoſtle, 1. Tim. 1. 19. Hauing faith, that is the truth of doctrine, vpon which faith reſteth: and a good conſcience, which is the ſecond part of this armour.
            
               
                  The ſecōd part.
                  The Breaſt-plate of righteouſneſſe,
               The ſecond part he calleth the Breſt-plate of righteouſneſse: for after that the minde is fortified with the verity of doctrine, there muſt follow the Breaſt-plat of righteouſneſſe, and of a good conſcience, that is, of a holy life. For euen as the breaſt-plate defendeth the breaſt of the Souldier, ſo the care of righteouſnes &amp; holines fortifieth the minde of a Chriſtian man, and conſerueth his

heart againſt the aſſaults of the Diuell, that hee bee not wounded with his darts. The Saints of God do ſlide and ſinne, they receiue wounds, but not to the heart, they ſinne, but not from the heart, according to this of Saint 1 Ioh. 3. 9.
               Iohn. VVhoſo is borne of God, ſinneth not, and why ſo? becauſe his heart is armed with the loue of righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, and of a good conſcience. Dauid which at firſt had his heart fenſed with the knowledge of the truth, and did ſet his loue vpon righteouſneſſe, yet hee fell, and that ſhamefully, and was wounded with the weapons of the diuell: but theſe weapons did not pierce ſo farre as his heart, they remained but in his fleſh, and why? becauſe his heart was fortified with this Breaſt-plate of righteouſneſſe. This place of the Apoſtle agreeth with that of Chriſt, Luke. chap. 12. Let 
               Luk. 12. 35.
               your loynes bee girded about and your lights burning. Theſe lightes are the holineſſe of life, and the workes

of righteouſneſſe, and a good conſcience. And this is the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe.
            
               The third part our feet ſhod.The third part of this Chriſtian panoplie is expreſſed in theſe words, ver. 15. And your feete ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace. The metaphor is thus: They that go to the warres prouide themſelues of good bootes and ſhooes, and with them do fence and arme their legges and feete from the cold, wet, and ſtripes of their enemies, and that they may bee the more prompt and ready to fight: So the Chriſtian Souldier ſhould arme the feete of his minde with theſe ſpirituall ſhooes, to wit, readineſſe in all places, to confeſſe (and if we be called of God) to preach the Goſpell to all men. It is called the Goſpell of peace, becauſe it preacheth reconciliation with God through Ieſus Chriſt, and becauſe by the name peace among the Hebrues, are ſignified all felicity, and all good things, and the Goſpell

bringeth all happineſſe vnto vs.
            
               The fourth part of the armour.
               And aboue all, take the Shield of Faith, wherewith yee may quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. Here is the fourth part of the ſpirituall armour. In the warre (ye know) that the ſhield is neceſſary, with which the whole body is couered, the ſtrokes repelled, and the darts receiued, if a man knoweth in battell how to vſe it. And in our ſpirituall fight the ſhield of faith is moſt neceſſary aboue all the reſt, but to what end? The Apoſtle addeth, wherewith ye may quench all the fiery darts of the wicked? (that is of the Diuell) When hee ſaith fiery darts, he alludeth to the ancient manner: for in old time (as it is yet in vſe among the Indians, and other barborous nations) they were wont to caſt their darts infected with poiſon againſt their enemies, by which the bodies of the wounded were ſo inflamed that they might hardly bee cured. The darts of the Diuell are all temptations, and his tares wherewith

hee laboureth to draw vs vnto all manner of ſinnes, againſt which wee pray in the Lords prayer: And leade vs not into temptations, but deliuer vs from euil. They are called fiery, becauſe they are dangerous, and deadly if they bee admitted, and do eaſily kindle the heart vnto infinite ſinnes, ſo that it cannnot eaſily bee cured: for one ſinne inflameth the heart vnto another: as drunkenneſſe, to wantonneſſe, wantonneſſe to murther. We ſee in Dauid, who for 2 Sam. 11.the loue of Bathſhaba, he deuiſed how to ſlay her innocent husband Vrias, 2. Sam▪
                11. The darts of the Diuell therefore are indeed fiery, but they are quenched with a ſound faith in Chriſt 1 Pet. 5. 5.Ieſu: VVhom reſiſt strong in the faith, ſaith the Apoſtle Peter. And Saint 1 Ioh. 5. 4.
               Iohn: This is the victory that ouercometh the world, euen our Faith, 1. Ioh. 5. 4.
            Heere wee ſee that all temptations of the Diuell are as artificiall fires, more to bee feared then all the

fires or fireworkes in the world, which if they enter once into our hearts, they kindle a moſt deadly fire. Marke but them that are wounded with malice, or wrath, doe they not burne with a deſire to bee reuenged? And thoſe whoſe hearts auarice hath ſeized, how they are inflamed with a deſire to haue all? Thoſe who once are pierced with the flames of fornication and whooredome, doe wee not ſee how they burne to haue their fill of their moſt infamous, filthy, and inordinate luſts? Thoſe, who are inflamed with anger and wrath, doe they not caſt out fire out of their mouthes? their eyes do ſparkle, their noſthrils ſmoake, their mouthes breath out fiery threatnings, and rayling ſpeeches. And thoſe who are caried away with ambition, deſire of honour, or vaine-glory, &amp;c. But if thou Queſtion▪
               ſay, that thou neuer didſt feele any paine, but rather pleaſure in thy paſſions, how then can they bee ſo fiery?

               Anſwer, I anſwer, ſo much the worſe is it with thee, for this argueth thy wound to be incurable, when thou art paſt feeling, and that this fire wil draw vnto it another, to wit, the fire of Gods wrath and heauy diſpleaſure, which will precipitate and throw thee downe headlong into the fire of hell. They then that yeelde and are ouercome with theſe fiery darts of Sathan, ſhew plainly that they are deſtitute of this impenetrable ſhield of, Faith, wherewith we may eaſily driue backe and extinguiſh all his fiery darts on which ſide ſoeuer they be. For if by faith wee haue feeling of Gods fauour and loue towards vs, and are fully aſſured that he will be a good and mercifull father vnto vs, then his loue which is kindled in our hearts by faith, &amp; his ſpirit, which he hath giuen vs, doth cauſe vs to hate, abhor, and deteſt all euill, and ſtrongly reſiſt temptations.
            
               The fifth 
                     •
                  rt.Next he cometh to the Helmet: Take the Helmet of ſaluation, verſ. 17. It is

called Galea 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               of ſaluation, 
                     •
                  er metonimiam, becauſe it bringeth ſaluation, or is ſaluta
                     •
                  is, holſome, for it defendeth the head. But what this ſpirituall Helmet is, the Apoſtle teacheth, 1. Theſs. 5. 8. Putting on the hope of ſaluation 
               1. Theſ. 5. 8.
               for an helmet The Diuell by all meanes laboureth to bring vs to deſperation, for then hee thinketh himſelfe ſure of vs. The Apoſtle therefore willeth that euen as in earthly battels Souldiers couer their head with an Helmet: So we ſhould fortifie our heart and minde againſt all the inſults of the Diuell, with a ſure hope of eternall ſaluation obtained freely for vs by Chriſt, without our merites And moſt certain it is that there is no kinde of temptation which may not be ouercome if we hold faſt the moſt certaine hope of eternall ſaluation, and therefore Rom. 
               Rom. 8. 24.8. We are ſaued by hope They that deſpaire of the victory fight no more, but yeeld themſelues into the hands of the enemy: as they that conceiue an aſſured

hope of the victory, fight couragiouſly and ſtrongly. And as the Helmet, or head-peece is very neceſſary for him that is in the brunt of battell among ſo many arrrowes, and ſhot which flye on euery ſide: for without the ſame hee ſhould quickly bee wounded and ſlaine: So is hope moſt neceſſary for vs, (which is the companion of patience) to withſtand and beate backe all the aſſaults of Sathan. For the aſſurance of ſaluation that wee haue promiſed vnto vs in Chriſt, doth make vs inuincible in this fight.
            Take heede therefore (brethren) that in any caſe the diuell ſhake not our hope of ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt, but ſtill let vs go armed with this Helmet, that wee bee not wounded Aug. ſuper Pſal. 3.
               by this enemy. Vita vitae mortalis, ſpes eſt vitae immortalis, (ſaith Saint Auguſtine,) The life of our mortall life is the hope of the life immortall. Spes animum in aeternitatem erigit, &amp; idcirco
               
               nulla mala exterius quae tolerat ſentit, 
               Greg. in mora.
               Greg. Hope erecteth our minde into eternity, and therefore it feeleth no euils which it outwardly ſuffereth.
            
               
                  The ſixth part of this armour.
                  The word of God.
               The ſixth part of this ſpirituall armour, is the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God. Now hee cometh to deſcribe that part of armour wherewith we muſt ſtrike and expel the enemy from vs, as are Sword;, Speares, Gunnes, &amp;c. which the Apoſtle comprehendeth vnder the name of ſword. Hee calleth it the ſword of the ſpirit, becauſe it is ſpirituall, and from the mouth of God: becauſe our enemy is a ſpirit, our fight muſt alſo bee ſpirituall. Hee willeth vs to bee furniſhed with the word of God, and teſtimonies of holy Scripture, whereby wee may expell and driue backe our enemy from vs. And how wee ſhould vſe this ſword, Chriſt by Mat. 4.his owne example teacheth, Matthew. chap. 4. in his encountring with the Diuell.
            
               
When he tempteth vs to pride, drawe 1. Pet. 5.we againſt him this ſword: God reſisteth the proud, 1. Pet. 5. When he tempteth to couetouſneſſe, ſtrike him with this ſword: The couetous man is an idolater and hath no inheritanc in the kingdome 
               Epheſ. 5. 5.
               of Chriſt, and of God, Epheſ. 5. 5. If hee tempt to adultery, lay at him with 1 Cor, 6, 10this ſword: No fornicator nor adulterer ſhall inherite the kingdome of God, 1. Cor. 6. 10.
            Likewiſe, when he tempteth to heriſi
                  •
               s: as, Chriſt is not the true God, 1. Ioh. 5. 19let vs boldly daſh him on the face with this ſword, ſaying: This ſame is very God and eternall life, 1. Ioh. 5. 19. and his bloud clenſeth vs from all ſinne, 1. Ioh. 
               1 Ioh. 1. 7.1. 7. If hee ſaith, wee are not iuſtified by faith only, let vs draw this ſword againſt him, ſaying: VVhoſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhall not periſh, but haue euerlaſting 
               Ioh. 3. 16. Rom, 3. 28
               life, Ioh. 3. 16. Againe a man is iustified by faith without the workes of the law Rom. 3 28. Againe, if he tempt ſaying: that by reaſon of the perſonall vnion, Chriſt in

his body is vbique, euery where, obiect againſt him the words of the Angell: He is not here, he is riſen, Math. 28. 6. Againe, the very words in the Article Math. 28. 6of our faith: He aſcended into heauen, &amp; from thence he ſhal come againe, &amp;c. If he ſay the body of Chriſt is in the bread really, reply, that Chriſt ſaid not, my body is in the bread, but this (that is the bread) is my body And ſo let vs vſe this ſword of the ſpirit in all other temptations.
            
               The ſeuēth part of this armour.Laſtly, he concludeth with prayer, which is the ſeuenth part of this ſpirituall armour, verſ. 18. And pray alwaies. This is a continuall and feruent ſupplication to Almighty God, that he will bee preſent and aſſiſt vs and all the Saints, in this fight againſt Sathan. With this kinde of armour let vs defend our ſelues againſt this enemy, and ſtrike him, and driue him from vs. I his is a moſt excellent and effectuall kinde of weapon, which the Apoſtle therefore placeth laſt, becauſe except God

and our Emperour Ieſus Chriſt, (by our praiers) be preſent to protect vs, all the reſt of our armour little preuaileth.
            After therefore that the Chriſtian Souldier bee on euery ſide armed, the Apoſtle willeth, that turning to his Emperour, and acknowledging his weaknes, he deuoutly craueth ſuccour, and aid, and not once or twice, but continually, for we ſtand in continuall neede of his defence. And this wee ſhould doe, not coldly, faintly, and with the lippes onely, as did the Iewiſh people, of whom the Prophet in the perſon of God complaineth, Eſay. chap. 29. This people honoureth 
               Eſay. 29,
               mee with their lippes, but their heart is farre from me, but with a feruent ſpirit, not careleſly, and negligently, as if wee ſtood in no feare of the enemy, but watching with an earneſt affection in this duty of prayer.
            
               
And that not onely for our ſelues, but for the whole Church, that is, for the whole army of Gods Saints, and Souldiers of Chriſts band in the Church militant.
            To conclude, there are none therefore vanquiſhed of the enemy, but ſuch as forſake this their impregnable armoure, and depart from their inuincible Captaine, Ieſus Chriſt. The victory ſhall bee ours, through him who hath vanquiſhed Sathan, and ſhall breake his head, treade him vnder foot, and make vs reigne and triumph wlth him for euer.
            
               Obſeru. 6.Laſtly, I heere obſerue, that the Church militant in this world, is not a congregation abſolutely pure, without ſpot or blemiſh, contagion of ſinne, ſcandals, vices, and imperfections, as the tares ſowne among the wheate, and growing together, plainly euinceth againſt the Donatiſts

Anabaptiſts, and ſuch like. For alwaie in the viſible Church in this life, the good and the bad, the godly and the wicked, the elect and the reprobate are mingled together. The Church Aug. de bapt. lib. 5.
               (ſaith Auguſtine) eſt velut lilium inter ſpinas, bonis &amp; malis permiſta, as a lilly among thornes, mixed with good and euill, as it may appeare by the example of the Church of the Corinthians, 
               1. Cor. 1. &amp; 5, &amp;c.1. Cor. 1. and chap. 5. and other places, which may bee proued by this argument, taken from the ſcope of this parable, thus:
            As it is with the tares and the wheat, ſo it is with the viſible Church: but thus it ſtandeth with the tares, and the wheat, they both grow together vntill the time of harueſt.
            Therefore in the viſible Church the good and the euil are mixed together vntil the time of harueſt, or of the end of the world. The antecedent is proued out of this parable; the conſecution is illuſtrated by this rule in logike,

               ſimilium ſimilis eſt ratio, of like things is the like reaſon.
            
               Cyprian lib. 3. Epiſt. 38.
               The vſe which the godly ſhould make hereof S. Cyprian teacheth, that becauſe tares ſeeme to bee in the Church, this ſhould not hinder our faith and charity, that becauſe wee ſee tares in the Church wee our ſelues ſhould depart out of the Church: but we ſhould rather indeuour, vt frumentum eſse poſsimus, that wee may bee the good come, that when the corne ſhall begin to bee laid vp in the Lords barnes, wee may receiue the fruits of our workes. For in a great houſe are not onely veſſels of gold, and of ſiluer, but alſo of wood and of braſſe▪ ſome to honour, 
               2. Tim. 2.
               and ſome to diſhonour, 2. Tim. 2.
            
               The third part
               
                  The third part▪
                  
                  Then came the ſeruants of the houſholder and ſaid vnto him: Maiſter▪ ſowedſt not thou good ſeed? From whence then hath it tares? verſ. 27. Here is thirdly contained the queſtion of the ſeruants concerning the rooting vp of the tares,

ioyned with an admiration: Sowedst not thou good ſeed? The Protaſis or propoſition is: euen as the houſholder would not that the ſeruants ſhould pluck vp the tares, but that they ſhould grow together till the time of harueſt. Apodoſis: So wicked men and heretikes ſhal euer be in theviſible Church vntill the end of the world, when they ſhall be ſeparated and vtterly rooted Aug in queſt ſuper Mat.out. This Houſholder is God, the ſeruants (according to Auguſtine) are ſuch Chriſtians as are carryed with a 
                     Proſopopoeia is a faining of a perſon to ſpeake.more feruent zeale to haue the church purged. Their ſpeech, with the anſwer of the Houſholder, is figured by an vnperfect Proſopopoeia. verſe. 28. Obſeru. &amp; doctrine.29. 30.
               
                   In that the ſeruants wondred at the increaſe of the tares, we are taught the iuſt cauſe of admiration is giuen to the godly (if they duly conſider) how ſo many tares of vices ſhould ſpring vp in the Lords field? from whence are ſo many impieties, falſe religions,

monſters of iniquities, ſo many periuries, blaſphemies, adulteries, among men profeſſing Chriſtianity? This the Prophet in the perſon of God admireth, Eſay. 5. when after he had deſcribed Gods goodneſſe and diligence in dreſſing his vineyard, hee ſaith: VVhat 
                  Eſay. 5. 4.
                  could I haue done any more to my vineyard that I haue not done? VVhy haue I looked that it ſhould bring forth grapes, and it bringeth forth wilde grapes? And Ieremy. 2. 21. Yet I had▪ planted thee a 
                  Ier. 2. 21.
                  noble vine, whoſe plants are all naturall▪ how then art thou turned into the plants of a strange vine? From whence hath it ſo many tares, ſeeing that ſinne fighteth againſt Almighty God, of whom wee receiue all good things, and in whom we moue, liue, and haue our being, from whence then are ſo many tares?
               If nothing bee ſo hurtfull vnto man as ſinne, if of ſinne cometh death and eternall damnation: if of ſinne

proceedeth all miſeries and plagues in this life, why are men ſo eaſily induced to ſin? from whence are theſe tares? If 
                     Aug. in Rom. 7.(as Auguſtine ſaith) vnuſquiſque peccando, animam ſuam Diabolo vendit: by ſinning a man ſelleth his ſoule to the Diuell, receiuing as the price thereof, a little tranſitory pleaſure, how ſpring ſo many tares? If wee demand of the Philoſophers what man is, they will anſwer: Animal rationale, a reaſonable creature. If man then be a reaſonable creature, what ſhould be more agreeable to the law of nature, then to frame his life according to the rule of reaſon▪ But if ſin be not onely againſt the law of God, but alſo contrary to the light of reaſon, how ſhould a reaſonable creature commit daily and hourely ſo many ſins? Why (I pray you) did the Son of God take vpon him our fleſh? why did he preach, teach, do, and ſuffer many great things? was it not that he might deſtroy the works of the diuell? and what are the workes of the diuell,

but ſins? and why gaue he himſelfe for Tit. 2. 14.vs? was it not that hee might redeeme vs from all iniquity, and purge vs to be a peculiar people vnto himſelfe, zealous of good workes? They therefore that ſerue ſin, what doe they elſe but crucifie againe 
                  Heb. 6. 6.
                  to themſelues the ſonne of God, and make a mocke of him. Heb. 6. 6. From whence then are theſe tares? from whence is this aboundance of iniquity in the world? how are men ſo eaſily ſeduced by Sathan to receiue this peſtilent tare into the ground of their hearts? And ſurely ſo great at this day is the corruption of Chriſtian manners, that as in the time of peſtilence we do not ſo much wonder at them that dye, as at them which remaine aliue: ſo now adaies we may not ſo much maruell at hoſe that liue wickedly, as at the gody, Simile▪
                  honeſt, deuout, &amp;c. as if it were a miracle to ſee them vnſpotted of ſo great corruption. So that this place ehemently reproueth the negligence  
                     •
                  ngratitude, and extreame impiety of

men, and ſerueth to exaggerate the filthineſſe and and abſurdity of ſinne.
               
                  Obſeru. 2.In that the Diuell is called the enuious man: Homo humanitatem ſignificat, 
                  Note the ſubtilty of Sathan.(ſaith a Father) the word [man] ſignifieth humanity. And as God ſo wing the good ſeed is called a man, ſo the diuell ſowing his tares, is here termed aman, not that hee is a man, ſequia humanitatem ſimulat, becauſe he Mat. 4. Mark. 1. 12 Luk. 4. 8.faineth himſelfe to bee thy friend that hee might deceiue thee, when indeed hee is thy moſt fraudulent enemy. The ſame arte hee vſed in deceuing of Eue, as if he tendred her good and wiſhed her felicity. The like cra he vſed in tempting of Chriſt, ſpeakin friendly vnto him: but better (ſaith S
                        •
                     
                     lomon) are the wounds of a friend, then t
                        •…
                      kiſſes of an enemy. He knoweth that he can effect little if hee walke vnmasked and therefore hee reacheth his poyſo vnder the colour of goodnes. But tal heed of him, he is the enuious man. H reſembleth a thiefe in ſubtilty, whic

knocketh at thy dore in the night, thou askeſt who is there, hee changeth his name, altereth his voice, pretendeth to Simile.be thy friend, that thou maieſt open the dore vnto him at vnawares, and ſo he ſpoileth thy houſe, and killeth thee. But what doth this enuious man? hee ſoweth ſeed, ex diametro, contrary to the ſeed of God. Chriſt ſowed pouerty of ſpirit, from whence then ſprang The Diuell contrary to Chriſt.auarice? Chriſt ſowed contempt of the world, from whence then ſprang ſo great loue of the world? Chriſt ſowed humility, from whence then hath pride gotten that growth? Chriſt ſowed chaſtity, from whence then hath whooredome, fornication, adulteries, &amp; all licentious liuing ſo ouergrowne the world? Chriſt ſowed ſanctifying of the Sabboth, from whence then came ſuch prophaning of the Sabboth in carouſing, drunkennes, dauncing, dicing ſtage playing, and ſuch like heatheniſh prophannes? Surely the enuious mā hath done this, theſe are the prints of his feet,

he hath beene heere, learne to know him ex vnguibus Leonem, as the Lyon by his pawes.
               
                  Obſeru. 3.Learne here, that all enuy is of the  
                  The gate of iniquity Enuy a diueliſh ſin.diuell, it is a diabolical ſin. Enuy is, firſt Oſtium iniquitatis, the doore of iniquity: for by it death entred into the world. By this was Iacob vexed of Eſau, Ioſeph ſold of his brethren, Dauid perſecuted of Saul, Chriſt deliuered to the Iewes.
               
                   
                  The bane of charity.Secondly, it is toxicum charitatis, the bane of charity: for were it not for enuy, euery one would reioyce at anothers good, as if it were his owne, &amp; Auguſtine.be ſoary for anothers harme. Tolle inuidiam (ſaith Auguſtine) &amp; tuum eſt quod habeo, &amp; meum eſt quod habes. Take away enuy, and that which I haue is thine, and that which thou haſt i mine.
               
                   
                  The corruption of health.Thirdly, Enuy is putredo ſanitatis, the corruption of health: for, doe not the enuious man or woman hurt themſelues moſt? doe they not eate their

owne heart, and by fretting and enuying at others, conſume themſelues? Therefore God (ſaith a father) ſhould do great iniury to the enuious man, to place him in heauen, where there is nothing but ioy: for anothers proſperity is the obiect of enuy, which euer tormenteth the enuious man, and increaſeth his ſorrow. Therefore hell is the place alotted to all enuious caitifs, where they ſhall ſee nothing that they may enuy at, but weeping, howling, gnaſhing of teeth. Let Chriſtians therefore far abandon, and expell this peſtilent vice, the expreſſe image of the diuell, and embrace brotherly loue, the true badge of a Chriſtian.
               
                  Obſeru. 4.Fourthly, wee are here taught, that the wicked doe not onely hurt themſelues, but are alſo offenſiue vnto others, and do corrupt them. For euen as the tares do draw and ſucke out the humor that ſhould nouriſh the wheat: ſo the wicked by little and little, conſume the iuice of vertue in them with

                  Eccleſ. 13. 1 Cor, 5.whom they conuerſe. He that toucheth pitch, ſhall bee defiled therewith, and a little leauen leaueneth the whole lumpe. Vuaque conſpect a liuorem ducit ab vua: one rotten grape corrupteth the Iurenal. Sa. 2.
                  whole cluſter. Res maximi pretij est inter malos laud abiliter conuerſari. It is a thing of great price to liue laudably among wicked men. And as it is a great ſin inter bonos, bonum non eſſe, not to be good, conuerſing among good men: So it deſerueth great praiſe, Greg. Mor. lib. 1.
                  
                  bonum inter malos extitiſse, to be good, liuing among wicked men, ſaith Gregory. Flye therefore the ſociety of wicked men, and feare rather leaſt they ſhall peruert thee, then that thou ſhalt conuert them.
               
                  
                     Greg. Hom. 12. in Eze.Out of the 28. verſe I note, that it was well ſaid of Gregory: Zelum animarumeſſe ſacrificium deo omnipotenti, The zeale of ſoules is a ſacrifice to Almightie God: yet all zeale is not to bee reputed ſuch a ſacrifice, as it is plaine by the example of theſe

ſeruants, which with an in tempeſtiue zeale would haue plucked vp the tares. Such was the zeale of Iames 
                  Luke 9. 54and Iohn, Luke. 9. againſt the Samaritanes. Let the godly learne heere alwayes to retaine a holy zeale, but let it be 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ioyned with the knowledge of God, and not 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , according vnto ignorance, an inconſult, Rom. 10. 2or bloudy fury, Rom. 10. 2.
            
            
               The fourth and laſt part.
               But he ſaid nay, leaſt while yee go about to gather the tares, yee plucke vp alſo with them the wheate, let both grow together vntill harueſt, and in the time of harueſt, I will ſay to the reapers: Gather yee firſt the tares, and binde them in ſheaues to burne them: but gather the wheate into my Barne, verſ. 29. 30.
               
               The laſt part expreſſeth the anſwer of the Houſholder, concerning the time when God ſhall finally ſeparate &amp; diuide the elect from the reprobate,

and the different ſtate of them both. Protaſis: Euen as at the time of harueſt the tares are bound together in ſheues to bee burnt, but the wheate is gathered and put into the barne. Apodoſis▪
                   So at the end of the world, all infidels, impenitent ſinners, workers of iniquity, and all things that offend, ſhall bee vtterly rooted vp by the Angels, and caſt into eternall fire for euer to bee tormented. But the elect and faithfull ſhall be gathered into life eternall, and ſhall enioy euerlaſting felicity in the kingdome of their heauenly The expoſition.father. The harueſt is the end of the world, the reapers are the Angels, which out of the kingdome of Chriſt ſhall take away all things that offend, that is, (per metonymiam effecti) all ſuch as by their filthy life haue giuen offence to others. ver. 42. 43.
               
                   
                  Obſeru. &amp; doctrines.Firſt, heere is laid before vs the exceeding mercy and clemency of our heauenly father in his long ſuffering of the wicked. For the diuine nature,

ſaith Hierome) is more prone to mercy Hiero
                        •
                     .then reuenge: For hee will not the death of a ſinner, but that hee conuert and liue, 
                  Ezech. 33.
                  Ezech. 33. Deus opus miſericordiae cito facit, (ſaith Chryſoſtome) God ſheweth Chryſoſt. ſuper Mat▪
                  his mercy ſpeedily, becauſe this is moſt agreeable to the naturall propenſion of the deity: Sed opus iuſtitiae punientis, eſt deo alienum, ergo tarde facit: but the worke of his iuſtice in puniſhing, is more remote from God, and therfore he doth this more ſlowly.
               The idolatrous Gentiles in old time were wont to ſay in praiſe of their falſe Lactantius.Gods (as witneſſeth Lactantius) Quod dij habent pedes laneos, that their Gods had feete of wooll, becauſe they did not preſently powre downe vengeance vpon wicked men, but did proceed pedetētim ſlowly to puniſhment, But more truly may this be ſpoken of our moſt milde and louing God, for he hath indeed pedes laneos ad vlciſcendum, woollen feet in coming to vengeance oftentimes againſt ſinners, who

notwithſtanding hath pedes alatos, winged feete, in ſhewing mercy, and conferring benefites vpon men. But conſider here, and with a feeling heart conſider, that how much the greater is his lenity in expecting thy conuerſion, ſo much the heauier ſhal be his ſeuerity when it falleth: which the very heathen by experience wel perceiued, as it appeareth by the ſaying of Valerius: 
                  Valer lib. 1 cap. 2.
                  
                  Diuina
                        •
                     ra lento quidem gradu ad vindictam procedit, ſed tarditatem grauitate ſupplicy compenſabit, Valer. lib. 1. cap. 2. The wrath of God cometh with a ſlow pace to vengeance, but his ſlowneſſe hee recompenceth in Pſal. 7. 12,the grieuouſneſſe of the puniſhment. And therefore Gods wrath is compared by the Prophet vnto a bow: If a man will not turne, hee hath whet his ſword, hee hath bent his Greg. M
                        •
                     r. 19. cap. 21.
                  bow, and made it ready; and Gregory giueth the reaſon: Becauſe the bow (ſaith hee) the more it is drawen, with the greater violence it ſendeth

forth the arrow: So the day of reuenge, the longer it bee deferred, the more ſtrict ſhall the iudgement be when it cometh.
               The Adamant, which of all ſtones is the hardeſt, if it bee broken, it is diſſolued into ſo ſmall a duſt, that it cannot be diſcerned: So Gods patience is like the Adamant, it may for a while ſuffer the wicked to follow their ſins: but in the day of vengeance the fire of his wrath will breake forth, hee will let looſe all the raines of his fury, and be reuenged vpon his enemies. O let this conſideration ſtirre vp all carnal, ſecure, &amp; careleſſe liuers, which without any feare drinke iniquity like water, let this rowſe them vp out of their deadly lethargy, &amp; dangerous ſleepe of ſecurity, that yet at length this long ſufferance of God, may allure them to repentance, leaſt through the hardneſſe of their hearts, they heape vnto themſelues wrath against the day of wrath, Romans. 2. when the 
                  Rom. 2.
                  
tares ſhall be gathered together, and caſt into the furnace of fire, where ſhall be wayling and gnaſhing of teeth ver. 42.
               
               
                   
                  Verſ. 29. 30▪ A queſtionHeere may a queſtion ariſe, whether it bee not lawfull to excommunicate wicked men out of the Church, yea for the Magiſtrate to inflict puniſhment vpon malefactors, and (according Anſwer.to the quality of the offence) de medio tollere, to cut them cleane off? I anſwer, this parable is to bee extended no further then the ſcope thereof requireth: for it is to be vnderſtood, firſt Rom. 13. 4(according to Gregory and Hierome) non de manifeſte malis, ſed de occultis &amp; ambiguis: not of open and manifeſt offenders, but of things that are ſecrete and doubtfull.
               Secondly, not of the publicke execution of iuſtice of the Magiſtrate againſt malefactors; but of the priuate, intempeſtiue, and prepoſterous zeale of certaine men. For the Magiſtrate, for the puniſhment of offenders lawfully conuicted, beareth not the ſword
                  
                  in vaine, Rom. 13.
               It is the duty of the miniſtery to labour to plucke vp the tares, and all offences, not by the ſword, but by the preaching of the word: for this was the Apoſtles charge, 2. Timothie. 4. 2▪ 
                  Preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, and 
                  2 Tim. 4. 2.
                  out of ſeaſon, improue, rebuke, exhort, manifeſt wicked and ſcandalous liuers, leaſt by their euill examples they 1 Cor. 5. 5. 1 Tim. 1. 20ſhould corrupt others, to cut off ſuch by the cenſure of excommunication.
               And to the ciuill Magiſtrate it appertaineth, as iuſtice requireth, to vſe the ſword for the taking away of euill Exod. 21. Leuit. 24. Deut. 12. 19. 21.doers, Exod. 21. Leuit. 24▪ 
                  Deut. 12. &amp; 19. 21. Rom. 13. 4. Otherwiſe wicked men are to be tollerated with lenity in the congregation of the godly, and not by and by without diſcretion to bee plucked vp, as this Houſeholder heere teacheth, who forbade his ſeruants to pull vp the tares. The ſame Apoſtle counſelleth Timothie, 2.

                  2 Tim. 2. 24. 25. 26.
                  Timothie. 2. 24. 25. 26. and that to this end: Prouing if at any time God will giue them repentance, that they may knowe the truth, and come out of the ſnares of the diuell. For he that is wicked Niſi patienter cum mali ſunt tolerentur ad laudabilem mutationem non perueniunt, &amp;c. Aug. queſt. in Matth.to day, may (perhaps) to morrow bee conuerted. And if wicked men bee not patiently ſuffered, they will neuer come to a laudable change (ſaith S. Augustine.) Itaque ſi euulſi fuerint, ſimul etiam triticum eradicabitur, quod futuri eſsent ſi eis parceretur. If therefore they bee plucked vp, the wheate together will be plucked with them, which wheate the wicked alſo might be, if they had bene ſpared.
               
                  Ex verſ. 30. 41. 42. Obſeru. 5.There remaineth a laſt iudgement, and eternall puniſhment for the reprobate▪ when the tares ſhall bee bound together, and caſt into eternall Gregorius.fire: that is, Pares paribus ſociare, vt quos ſimilis culpa coinquinat paretiam poena conſtringat: To ſociate like with their like, that they that haue beene polluted with the ſame ſinne, may

bee tormented with the ſame puniſhment (ſaith Saint Gregory) They ſhall bee cast into the lake that burneth 
                  Apoc▪ 21.
                  with fire and brimſtone for euer Apoc 21. Into eternall fire, Matth. 25. VVhere they 
                  Matth. 25.
                  ſhall haue nor eſt day nor night, Apocalips 2. Theſ. 1.14. They ſhall bee puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition from the preſence of God, and from the glory of his power. They ſhall bee caſt into vtter darkneſſe, there ſhall be weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth. Mat. 22. They ſhall ſay vnto the 
                  Math. 22.
                  Mountaines, fall on vs, and hide vs from the preſence of him that ſitteth vpon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe, Apoc. 6 There ſhall be fire inquenchable, Apoc. 6.the worme immortall, howling lamentable, ſtinke intollerable, aſpect of diuels horrible, the wrath of God implacable▪ the malice of the tormentors inſatiable, deſperation inſuperable, and▪ death eternall. O then (beloued) that this golden ſentence were ingrauen in our hearts, that it neuer

                  Aug. Ser▪ 
                     26. ad frat. in Erem.might bee forgotten: Momentaneum eſt quod hic delectat, aternum quod illi
                        •
                      excruciat. The thing which here delighteth vs, is but momentanie, ſhort, and fading: but the puniſhment for theſe ſhort pleaſures of ſinne, in the life to come, are eternall, and neuer ſhall haue an end.
               
                   Laſtly, out of the thirtie and forty three verſes, the ſweet and moſt comfortable promiſe of the ioyes in the life eternall, is confirmed by our Sauiour vnto his faithfull and elect children. They ſhall bee gathered as the good wheate into the barne of their heauenly Father, and ſo 1 Theſ. 4. 17.
                  ſhall they be euer with the Lord, 1. Theſſalonians 4. 17. Then ſhall they ſhine as the Sunne in the kingdome of their heauenly Father, verſ. 43. as the brightneſse 
                  Dan. 12. 3.
                  of the firmament, Daniel. 12. 3.
               O ſweete conſolation! the godly then through the anguſt ſtraites of this mortall life, paſſe to the Auguſt

and ample glory: by death they are not ſo much conſumed, as conſummated: Death to them is to bee reputed not ſo much a graue, as a gaine: when death doth launce, their hearts doe laugh: a bleſſed and true life followeth ſuch a death, according to this of the Poet:
               
                  Frigida mors vitam, mortem rapit altera vita:
                  Mors vanae vitae finis, origo bonae.
                  Cold death takes life away,
                  True life yet death ſubdues,
                  Death ends this brittle life,
                  Whence happy life enſues.
               
               Why then ſhould not the godly, moſt cheerefully, and with a zealous heart, cry out with a learned Father: O mortem beatam, quae vitam etſi adimit, non tamen perimit, adimit quidem, ſed ad tempus, reſtituendam in tempore, duraturam ſine tempore!
                  
O bleſſed death, which though it taketh away our life, yet it doth not deſtroy it, it taketh it away for a time, to be reſtored in time, to indure without time.
               It is ſowen heere in corruption, 1▪ Cor. 15.but it ſhall riſe againe in incorruption. They that ſow heere in teares, Pſal. 126.ſhall reape there in ioy. There ſhall bee eternall health, and healthfull eternitie, ſecure tranquilitie, and ioyfull ſecuritie, happy eternity, and eternall felicity. The ioy of that life ſhall neuer decreaſe, nor the loue euer waxe cold: ſuch a bleſſedneſſe 1 Cor. 2. 9.as the eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not heard, neither hath entred into the heart of man. It ſurmounteth all ſpeech, exceedeth humane ſence, and goeth beyond all our deſires.
               Let vs ſtriue therefore (good brethren) to bee the good wheate in this life, that in the life to come we

may bee gathered into to the Lords Barne of euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe: which God grant, for the merits of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with the holy Ghoſt be all honour and glory both now and for euer.
               Amen.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
   

