
   
      
         
            An extract translated out of the French copie and taken out of the registers of the French kings priuie councell.
            France. Conseil du roi.
         
         
            
               1600
            
         
         Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00499
            STC 10634.6
            ESTC S3032
            29733692
            ocm 29733692
            28092
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00499)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28092)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1861:54)
         
         
            
               
                  An extract translated out of the French copie and taken out of the registers of the French kings priuie councell.
                  France. Conseil du roi.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.).   
               
                  By Simon Stafford, dwelling on Adling hill, neere Carter-lane,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1600]
               
               
                  Judicial decree in the appeal of John Potter and other English cloth merchants in a dispute with the Company of Drapers of Rouen.-- Cf. STC (2nd ed.)
                  "Done in the privie Councell of the King, holden at Paris, the one and twentieth day of Aprill, 1600. subscribed thus, Desbaigneaulx."
                  Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Woolen goods industry --  France --  Rouen.
               France --  Commerce --  England.
               Great Britain --  Commerce --  France.
               Broadsides --  London (England) --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-09
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-09
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            AN EXTRACT
Tranſlated out of the French Copie, and taken
out of the Regiſters of the French Kings
Priuie Councell.
            
            
               BEtweene Iohn Potter, William Woolleſtone, Henry Morris, and Thomas Church, Engliſh Marchants, as well for themſelues,
as for the other Engliſh Marchants, trading in the towne of Rouan, appealing from the ſentence giuen by the Bayliffe
of the ſaid towne, the ſeuenth of Aprill 1598. on the one partie, and the Maſters and Wardens of the Art and Miſterie
of the Companie of the Drapers, as well in the whole ſale, as retaile, Cloth-workers, &amp; Shearemen of the ſaid towne intimated,
on the other partie, By the King in his Councell being ſeene the ſaid ſentence, whereof appeale is made, the aduertiſements &amp; euidences
of the ſaid parties, the decree of the ſaid Councell, by the which the examining of the ſaid appeale is referred to the ſaid Councell
of the foure and twentieth of Nouember 99. the product
                  •
               o
                  •
                of the ſaid parties, on the which the ſaid ſentence is made, Another decree
of the ſaid Councell, by the which it is ordained, that the Maſters &amp; Wardens of the art and miſterie of the Companie of the Drapers of
the towne of Paris, ſhall bee called before the Commiſſioners in that behalfe appointed, to giue their aduiſe on the difference of the ſaid
parties, and articles by them deliuered, to the end that this being done, and their aduice ſeene, right to bee done vnto them according to
reaſon, of the ſeuenteenth of March 1600. the verball plea of the ſaid Commiſſioners contayning the ſayd aduice, the requeſt of the
Ambaſſador of the Queene of England to moderate the ſaid ſute, the meanes of the moderation of the ſaide Ambaſſador, and all that
which by the ſaid parties hath beene produced before the Commiſſioners thereunto appointed. His report being heard, The King in his
Councell hath made, and doth make voyde the appellation, and that whereof appeale is made, and in mending the Iudgement,
hath ordained, and 
                  •
               oth ordaine, that within three moneths after the ſignification which ſhall be made of this preſent decree, all ſorts of
woollen cloth which, ſhall be brought by the ſaid Engliſhmen or Strangers, white, or died, in wooll, &amp; not otherwiſe, before entering into
this Realme, ſhal be wet &amp; ſhrunke, not drawne out vpon the Tenters with pullies, engines, wheeles, not made of diuers ſorts of woolles,
barred, ſtriped, cockled, &amp; filled with flocks, on paine of confiſcation, according to the ordinances. Which marchandizes being loyall, &amp; of
ſuch condition as is aforeſaid, may bee ſolde in whole-ſale by the ſayde Engliſh or Forraine Marchants, after hauing beene duely viſited
by the ſaid Maſters and Wardens of the ſayd art and miſterie of the Companie of the Drapers and none others: which marchandizes
ſhall bee put in the halles and publike places, if there bee any, and not elſe-where. And if in caſe it ſhould bee found, that there
were no publike place, (viſitation beeing formerly made) a place ſhall bee demaunded of the Iudges of the places: and it ſhall not bee
lawfull for the ſaid Engliſh or Forraine Marchants to open their Bales, before they haue called thereunto the ſaid Maſters &amp; Wardens
of the ſayd art and miſterie of Drapers, who alſo ſhall bee ſubiect within twice foure and twentie houres, to make the ſaide viſitation
gratis. And in caſe the ſaid Marchants doe not ſell their ſaid marchandizes in the ſame places, after the ſaid viſitation, and after three market
dayes, in the which the halles ſhall haue beene opened, and that the ſaid marchandizes ſhall haue bene expoſed to ſale, it ſhall be lawfull
for the ſaid Marchants to carrie them where they ſhall thinke good, for to make ſale of them: And touching the meaſuring of the
ſayde marchandiſes, the ſaide Councell hath ordained, and doth ordaine, that the Edict thereupon made in the yeere 1543. ſhall be
kept and obſerued, &amp; without expences.
            
               Done in the priuie Councell of the King, holden at Paris, the one and twentieth day of Aprill,
1600.
                
               ſubſcribed thus, Des baigneaulx.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Imprinted at London by Simon Stafford, dwelling on
Adling hill, neere Carter-lane.
         
      
   

