
   
      
         
            A learned and godly sermon preached on the XIX. day of December, anno Dom. MDCXXXI. at the funerall of Mr. Robert Bolton Batchelour in Divinity and minister of Broughton in Northampton-Shire. By Mr. Nicolas Estvvick, Batchelour in Divinity, and sometimes fellow of Christs College in Cambridge, and now minister of Warkton in Northampton-Shire. Revised and somewhat enlarged by the author, and now at the importunity of some friends published
            Estwick, Nicolas.
         
         
            
               1639
            
         
         Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00426
            STC 10558
            ESTC S122205
            99857357
            99857357
            23080
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00426)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23080)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 834:1)
         
         
            
               
                  A learned and godly sermon preached on the XIX. day of December, anno Dom. MDCXXXI. at the funerall of Mr. Robert Bolton Batchelour in Divinity and minister of Broughton in Northampton-Shire. By Mr. Nicolas Estvvick, Batchelour in Divinity, and sometimes fellow of Christs College in Cambridge, and now minister of Warkton in Northampton-Shire. Revised and somewhat enlarged by the author, and now at the importunity of some friends published
                  Estwick, Nicolas.
               
               [2], 70 p.   
               
                  Printed by George Miller dwelling in Black-Friers,
                  London :
                  1639.
               
               
                  Running title reads: A sermon preached at the funerall of Mr. Bolton.
                  Usually found as part 2 of STC 3245.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bolton, Robert, 1572-1631.
               Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
LEARNED
AND
GODLY SERMON
Preached on the XIX. day of December,
Anno Dom. MDCXXXI. at the Funerall of
Mr. ROBERT BOLTON Batchelour in Divinity
and Miniſter of Broughton in
Northampton-Shire.
            
            
               By Mr. NICOLAS ESTVVICK,
Batchelour in Divinity, and ſometimes fellow of
Chriſts Colledge in Cambridge, and now Miniſter
of Warkton in Northampton-Shire.
            Reviſed and ſomewhat enlarged by the Author, and now
at the importunity of ſome friends publiſhed,
               
            
            LONDON,
Printed by GEORGE MILLER dwelling in Black-Friers, 1639.
         
         
            
               
                  〈1… pages missing〉
               
               
flock of ſheep without a particular ſhepheard; and if
thou hadſt leave to name his ſucceſſour, thou mighteſt
ſeeke from one end of the land to another in thy
choice, and yet not find in all points a man matchable
to him; he was a bright and a ſhining lamp, if any of
thy inhabitants doe ſit in darkneſſe, their ignorance
is altogether inexcuſable: hee lifted up his voice in
this place many yeares together like a trumpet; if any
of thy inhabitants are not awakened out of the ſleepe
of ſinne, they may now goe on more ſecurely in this
dead ſleep;The loſſe of a good Miniſter. but wo to them, it will be eaſier for Sodome
and Gomorrah at the day of judgement than for
them. I pitie your caſe (good friends) and bewaile
your loſſe: but why do J name your loſſe? It is my
loſſe, and a common loſſe, we are all of us ſharers,
though not all alike in this judgement. LORD, that
thou ſhouldeſt ſuffer ſuch a wretched ſinner and an
unprofitable ſervant of thine as I am yet to live, and
deprive the viſible Church of ſo worthy an inſtrument
of thy glorie as M. Bolton! Holy Father, we may
think, had it ſtood it with thy holy pleaſure, that it had
been good for thy Church, if his life had been ſpared
with the loſſe of many of ours: he was a deep channell,
in whoſe juſtly deſerved commendations the
ſtreames of eloquence which in former ages flowed
from thoſe great and godly Orators, the two Gregories
both of Nazianzum and Nyſsa, from great Baſil
and golden-mouth'd Chryſoſtome, from S. Ambroſe
and S. Austin, might have emptied themſelves, and
yet not over-flowed the banks: and what do I then
come hither with my diſtracted thoughts and trembling
heart, which if ever I had any gift in encomiaſticall

and laudative Orations have many years ſince
willingly neglected it, and ſo loſt it. As Gregory Nazianzen
ſpoke of his Baſil, I have for my part as great reaſon
to ſpeake of our ſometimes deare and now bleſſed
M. Bolton: J admired him while he lived, and honoured
him in my heart; &amp; to ſpeak of his excellencies wherwith
the LORD had plentifully inriched him, is a burden
too heavy for my ſhoulders, and a very hard task
for thoſe who doe nothing els but ſtudy Oratory: all
that I can ſpeak in the praiſes of this godly man, falls
ſhort by many degrees of his worth, whoſe memory
is precious, and ſhall be kept greene and flouriſhing as
the rod of Aaron laid up in the Tabernacle.
         
      
      
         
            THE TEXT.
            
               
                  PHIL. 1. 23, 24.
                  I deſire to be diſsolved—
               
               
                  THe Apoſtle S. Paul was in a ſtrait,Pauls ſtrait. or divided
betwixt two affections, carried
to different objects, and they were in a
ſort contrary; one way he was drawne
with a deſire to be with CHRIST, farre
from the Philippians, even as farre as Heaven is from
earth; another way he was drawne with a deſire to
continue with his beloved brethren warring on
earth, and to bee for a time farre remooved from
CHRIST; the neceſſity of his brethren did move
him to deſire the latter; his great love to CHRIST

did incite him to long for the former: betwixt theſe
two affections the Apoſtle had a conflict, and he was
ſo perplexed, that he knew not whither to turne him,
he knew not what to chuſe. He was as iron betwixt
two load-ſtones, drawne this way firſt, and then that
way. We read that David was on a time in a great
ſtrait,
                  2 Sam 24. 14. but apparent were the differences betwixt the
preſent perplexity of this our Apoſtle, and that of
David; Davids was in regard of evills propoſed, this
was for the enjoying of good; his neceſſity was touching
evill which could not be avoided, but the Apoſtles
was free and voluntary; his perplexity ſomwhat
concerned himſelf, the ſhunning of his own evill; but
the Apoſtles was for the good of others, which was
joyned with his own hurt. Behold here as in a perſpective
a heart truly Apoſtolicall, wherein he ſhewed
at once both great love to CHRIST, deſiring to be
with him, and withall great love to his brethren, deſiring
to abide with them for their profit.
               I begin with the firſt of theſe,Summe. 
                  Pauls deſire in reſpect
of himſelfe; wherein are obſervable three particulars.
               1.Parts. The deſire it ſelfe, and that was to depart or die.
               2. A reaſon implied of this his deſire, for then hee
ſhould be with CHRIST.
               3. His cenſure or judgement of that eſtate, to bee
with CHRIST, it's beſt of all: Let us open the words
firſt, and then raiſe Obſervations out of them for our
edification.
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) it is word for word,Expoſition. 
                  having a deſire,
and this is ſomewhat more than ſimply to deſire, for
it noteth a vehement, earneſt and continued deſire,

a deſire which is in action and working till wee have
our deſire accompliſhed, wheras to deſire ſimply may
be a ſudden motion or momentany paſſion.
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) Some tranſlate the word paſſively, Tertullian
renders it recipi, l. de patientia, pa. 8. others to be
diſſolved or looſed, and it is done when things mixt
and compounded are reſolved into their parts and
principles, now becauſe the ſoule is (as it were) included
in the body, and cannot enjoy CHRIST fully till
that compoſition by the body be reſolved by death,
therfore doth S. Paul earneſtly deſire this reſolution.
               2. Or it may ſignifie to return, as the word is taken
elſewhere,Luk. 12. 36. 
                  the LORD will returne from the wedding,
which ſenſe is not diſſonant from the ſcope of this
place; for the ſpirit being freed from the body, returneth
to GOD that gave it, and what els doth the
Apoſtle now deſire, but to returne unto CHRIST by
whom he was ſent to preach the Goſpell?
               3. It ſignifieth to looſe anchor, or as Chryſoſtome
renders it, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   to flit or to change our place, and
ſo it's a metaphor from marriners, importing a flitting
or ſailing from the ſtate of this preſent life by the
ſhip of death to another port, to ſaile (as it were) from
one bank to another.
               It is not much materiall which reading we follow,
they all of them doe agree in the maine point and
ſubſtance, and doe affoord an obſervation which
might be enlarged and ſet foorth with variety of colours,
and ſtrengthened with long diſcourſes, but as
they which have a long journey to goe, and but a
ſhort time allowed them, muſt make but a ſhort ſtay
in any one place, and as Painters many times uſe only

to draw out the heads and ſuperiour parts of men, leaving
all the other parts &amp; lineaments to be proportionably
ſupplied by the wiſe beholders, even ſo muſt
J at this time propound only ſome generall heads of
ſeverall points without any large amplifications, and
leave them and the reſt to your private devotions.
               
                  Death will unavoidably ſurpriſe us:
                  Doct. 1. Which is a reſolution
or diſſolution of this exquiſite frame of man,Death cannot be avoided.
it is the diſſociation of parts united together, it is the
taking away the ſtructure and the faſhion of this
houſe of clay,2 Cor. 2. 5. 
                  We muſt needs die, and then we are as water
ſpilt on the ground which cannot be gathered up againe,
                  2 Sam. 14. 14.
as the wiſe woman of Tekoah ſpoke to the
King;Eccleſ. 8. 8. 
                  No man hath power over the ſpirit in the day of
death, neither is there any diſcharge in that warre, all
muſt fight with death, and death will conquer all; our
ſoules and bodies now met together in this neare
conjunction, though deare friends muſt be ſeparated
each from other untill the day of the generall reſurrection,
and keep them now as charily from dangers
as we can, yet will theſe earthen brittle, veſſells be
broken aſunder, which all ſorts and ranks of men are
bound to looke for at all times,Pſal. 62. 8, 9. 
                  Surely men of low degree
are vanity, and men of high degree are a lie, to bee
laid in the ballance they are altogether lighter then vanity,
a marvellous debaſing of all men! Let men be put in
one end of the ballance, and vanity in the other, and
the Pſalmiſt doth aſſure us that vanity will weigh
downe man, and man is lighter than vanity it ſelfe. Iob
ſets out his life by comparing his daies to a ſwift ſhip,
and to an Eagle that haſteth to the prey,Life ſwift. yea and hee
further ſaith,Iob. 9. 26. v. 25 they are ſwifter than a poſt, then the

birds in the ayre, the ſhips on the ſea, &amp; the ſwift poſt
on the land, all theſe do proclaime and preach a Sermon
to us of our mortality, and that this lamp many
waies may be extinguiſhed; experience ſheweth us
that death puts no difference, the young do die as wel
as the old,Job 3. 14, 19. the ſtrong as well as the weake, the Kings
and Counſellours of the earth as well as beggars, the
Phyſitians themſelves as well as their patients, and
death is haſtned by infinite diſeaſes, whereunto all
the living are ſubject, and theſe are within us, and a
thouſand accidents to further death without us, and
which is the foundation of all our evils, by our own
ſins, whereby we do provoke the LORD of our lives
to anger, and do walk every day over a mine (as it
were) of gun-powder, ſubject every moment to be
blowne up by the LORDS diſpleaſure:Cyprian de mortal. and S. Cyprian
excellently ſheweth the declining ſtate of the world,
how the ſtrength of the husband-man in the field, of
the marriner on the ſea, and the ſouldier in the camp is
weakened;Benefits of ſhort life. 
                  canos videmus in puer is: and it is well for us
that our lives are ſhortned, and that our daies do not
ordinarily attaine to the tenth part of thoſe that lived
before the floud, and that both in regard of the wicked,
and the godly. Firſt touching the wicked, to repreſſe
their outrage and impudencie in ſinning; this
very thought that they may die ere long, and cannot
live very long, in reaſon ſhould abate their violent and
exorbitant courſes, if they are tranſcendently wicked
now when death is at hand, what Nimrods would they
be if they had in the ordinary courſe of nature, eight
or nine hundred yeares before them to live in? If
their damnation now ſhall be moſt dreadfull, how

much more intollerable would it then be,Chryſoſt one obſerves it as a worke of mercy to ſinners to die ſpee dy, Hom lib. 29. in Gen. the number
of their ſins adding fuell (as it were) to the fire of hell,
and the LORD in juſtice meaſuring out to them a proportionable
degree of vengeance to their ſins▪ hence
will their accounts be ſo much the eaſier,Quo e
                        •••
                     t vita diuturnior, co fieret culpa numeroſior. Amb. de Bono Mortis. c. 4 &amp; longe illis plus damnatio profuiſſet ne incrementa facerent peccatorum idem ca 7. ejuſdem libri. and their
ſtripes ſo much the fewer. And this makes likewiſe
very much for the exceeding comfort and good of
diſtreſſed Chriſtians; infirmities, temptations, poverty,
reproaches, griefe of paſſion for their owne and of
compaſſion for their brethrens miſeries are a great
burthen to them, how much heavier would it be if
this burthen was to preſſe them down many hundred
yeares together? this much allaies their ſorrow, that
all theſe evills are but as clouds which ſoone ride away,
or as a tempeſt though violent yet not permanent,Heb. 10. 34. &amp; 37.
a ſharpe yet but a ſhort winter, here is our Scripture
comfort,Vſe 1. the time to beare them is but ſhort.
               This conſideration of our mortality ſhould in reaſon
move us to ſeek to Heaven for helpe that we may effectually
remember our condition:Mortality fits for Heaven. the holy ſervants
of GOD our preſidents herein have prayed to the
LORD for this purpoſe: thus did Moſes, teach me to
number my daies,
                  Pſal 90. 12. thus did David, make me LORD to
know mine end:
                  Pſal. 39 4. in their bleſſed ſteps let us tread, and
their example let us follow; it is a wonder that we
ſhould need to be remembred hereof, that we ſhould
be ſuch ſtrangers in the world, but there is need of
that proclamation ſtill to ſound in our eares, all fleſh is
graſſe,
                  Eſay 40. 
                  and the beauty of it as the flower of the field: were
we indeed as Adam was at the beginning of the world
who ſaw no ſpectacle of death before his eyes, wee
might have ſom probable excuſe if we thought not of

our departure: but what can we alledge for our ſelves
when we have had the experience of all ages? Go into
any part of the world,Zach. 1. 5. and aske them in the Prophets
words, your fathers where are they? and doe they
live for ever? Even this place and this meeting doe
preach unto us our mortality. Where are thoſe Epicures
in Eſay, which promiſe to themſelves continuance
in their deſperate waies,Eſay 56. 12. 
                  To morrow ſhall be as this
day and much more aboundant, nay and which is more
abominable, doe take occaſion by the ſhortneſſe of
their lives to eate and drinke, becauſe to morrow they muſt
die:
                  Eſay. 22. 13. 
                  Come on therfore (ſay they) let us fill our ſelves with
coſtly wine,
                  Wiſd. 2. 6. 
                  and ointments, and let no flower of the ſpring
paſse by us, let us crowne our ſelves with roſe-buds before
they be withered, let none of us go without part of our jollity,
let us leave tokens of our joyfullneſse in every place, for
this is our portion. Theſe ſinners are likely to ſee the
daies when they ſhall wiſh themſelves toads, ſerpents
or any loathſome creatures, rather then men and
women, and yet as deſirous as they ſhall be of that exchange
of their eſtate they ſhall not have it, but ſhall
remaine wofull men and women for ever.
               This Doctrine ſerveth likewiſe for the reproofe of
thoſe who neglecting principally to depend on the
immortall GOD,2. A vanity to depend on mortall men. do ſinfully relie on others which are
mortall like themſelves; thus the Subject relieth on
the Soveraigne, the ſervant on his Lord and Maſter,
the wife relieth on her husband, and the children on
their parents, and all this is done contrary to our duty?
Truſt not in Princes nor in the ſons of man,
                  Pſal. 136. 3. and why
ſo? There is no helpe in them: their breath goeth forth,
and they returne to their earth. Truly they are like the
running waters, our dove, i. e. our faith can find no

reſt for the ſoles of her feet in any of the ſons of men,
ſuch hope is like the houſe of a ſpider,
                  Iob. 8. 13. one ſweep of GODS
beſome will eaſily make both the objects of their
hope and their hopes to be in the duſt: it is as a broken
reed to leane on; it will both deceive and pierce
them:Ezek. 10. 19. the whole world runs on wheeles, look Eaſtward,
or in the Weſt, North or South, you ſhall ſee
nothing but inconſtancy in all the parts therof. Oh
how ſafe and happy then are they which make the God of
Iacob their help,
                  Pſal. 146. 4. 
                  and whoſe hope is in the Lord their God.
whoſe hearts and eyes are fixed upon him; how hard
ſoever the world goeth with them for the preſent, all
ſhall be well aſſure your ſelves with ſuch in GODS
good time; he will provide all ſhall be well, he will
helpe the husband, hee will comfort the wife, hee
will guide the ſervants, hee will preſerve the
goods; yea rather than it ſhould bee undone,
(with reverence be it ſpoken) he will rock the cradle,
they are the words of the learned Martyr B.
Hooper.
                  Fox Acts, page 1480.
               
               This doctrine doth check all vain glorious &amp; proud
perſons,3. Vaine-glory checked. which Narciſſus-like, do dote on themſelves;
their own beauty, or ſtrength, or any ornament of the
body, which may like Ionas his gourd in one night be
withered. Who is more odious in our ſight than a
proud beggar? and nothing is more hatefull in GODS
eyes than a proud man or woman, who are but meat
for the ſilly crawling wormes to feed upon, and if
thou knoweſt not thy ſelfe,Greg. Nyſſ. in Mat. 5. Beati pauperes spiritu. Ser. de Beat. go to the graves of thoſe
which have been moſt lovely and beautifull in their
daies; in that picture and glaſſe maiſt thou view thy
ſelf, there maiſt thou behold the myſteries of our nature,
as Gregory Nyſsen ſpeaketh, and excellently inlargeth

this point. Haſt thou not (ſaith he) ſeen a heap of
dead mens bones? haſt thou not ſeen their skuls without
fleſh, a grim ſpectacle to behold, the very eyes being
waſted and turned into duſt? Haſt thou not ſeene
their mouthes (as it were) grinning and ſhewing their
corrupted teeth and their other bones lie ſcattered in
the grave? If thou haſt ſeene theſe thou haſt in them
ſeen thy ſelfe: where are the tokens of flouriſhing age?
where are thoſe beautiful cheeks? where is bloud and
colours in the lips? what is now becom of thoſe ſparkling
and lovely eyes? what of the comely noſe placed
in the midſt of the cheeks? where are thoſe locks
of haire which were wont to adorne their heads, &amp;c.
what is become of all thoſe things which do increaſe
thy pride? Tell me, what dreame is more vaniſhing,
what ſhadow more flitting than is thy beauty, or any
other thing whereof thou glorieſt?
               Fourthly, thoſe alſo are to be reproved which are
earth-wormes,4. Covetouſneſse checked. and do labour inordinately and immoderately
for tranſitory riches, which are carefull
for very trifles, and careleſſe for matters of greateſt
conſequence, which toile unceſſantly for an eſtate to
leave to poſterity, and are compared by Bartholomeus,
to children following butter-flies, they muſt ſometimes
goe out of the way in their purſuit, they may
miſſe,Job. 1. 20. and if they catch, it's but a flie to beſmeare their
hands, Naked we came into this world, and whatſoever
we have gotten here, we muſt leave it all behind, for
naked ſhall we go out of the world.
                  Knolls Turkiſh Hiſt. p. 73. 
                  Saladine a Mahometan
the great Turke may teach Chriſtians a good leſſon;
he cauſed a Proclamation to be made by one of his
Prieſts, a ſhirt faſtned to a ſpeare in manner of an enſigne,

ſaying, this is all that Saladine Conquerour of
the Eaſt caries away with him of all his riches: indeed
it is not all, they carry with them a guilty accuſing
conſcience, which will extort from parents curſes to
their children, becauſe that they to make them rich,
became Uſurers, unmercifull Land-lords, deceitfull
in their dealings, and worldly minded, we can pitie
others in their miſeries, and ſhall we have no compaſſion
on our owne ſoules? ſhall our owne ſoules now
be vile to us, in compariſon of which al the kingdoms
of the world are but trifles? for what ſhall it profit a man
to win the whole world and to looſe his owne ſoule? or what
recompence ſhall a man give for his ſoule?
                  Mat. 16. 26. if the ſoule periſheth,
then all the world is gone with us.
               This Doctrine ſhould teach al ſinners a point of ſpirituall
wiſdom,5. Deſerre not repentance. not to defer their repentance and ſeeking
to make their peace with God: the children of this
world are wiſe in their generation, that if they be tenants
at will and courteſie, and certain ere long to be
thruſt out of their houſes, they would looke abroad
to provide elſewhere, they would run all the country
over to get an aſſurance of an earthly houſe, and will
not thou while thou maieſt provide for the eternall
welfare of thy ſoule? if a man was hungry, and had
twenty or thirty diſhes ſet before him, and he knew
poyſon was in one of them, the danger of that would
make him be afraid of the reſt; &amp; thou haſt a deſire to
live twenty or thirty yeares that in poſſibility are before
thee; which thou maiſt happily live, but in one of
them, thou knoweſt not which, death in probability
will come to thee, ſhould not this prepare thee for
death alwaies? men that are wiſe and have enemies,

keepe continuall watch &amp; garriſons in frontier towns
for feare of a ſudden ſurpriſall: death continually
ſhootes his arrowes abroad; ſometimes he mortally
ſmites thoſe above thee, ſometimes thoſe below thee,
and thou ſeeſt ſome fall dead hard by thee: if thou giveſt
thy ſoule to Satan in thy life, how canſt thou
hope that GOD will entertaine it at thy death? O then
why ſhouldeſt thou for the pleaſures of unrighteouſneſſe
for a very few daies (little doſt thou know how
few) deſtroy thy ſoule for ever? do thou whip thy
ſoule with the laſhes of divine ſentences to follow after
GOD,Aug. Conf l. 8. c. 7. as Saint Auſtin did his, when it was backeward
and reſiſted this heavenly work of thy converſion,
and let not thoſe nugae nugarum &amp; vanitates vanitatum,
of thoſe antient ſins which did ſhake his coate
and whiſpered in his eares,c. 11. doſt thou leave us now,
and muſt we part for ever? let not theſe boſome ſins
I ſay, detaine thee in the priſon of the divell, but ſhake
them off as Saint Paul did the Viper,Acts 18. that they may
doe thee no hurt.Renew Repentance ſpeedily. Neither doth this concerne the unregenerate
only, but thoſe alſo which through the policy
of hell have diſgraced their profeſſion; inſtantly
to ariſe from their ſin by unfained repentance, a duty
praiſe-worthy in any, and to be practiſed by the greateſt
men on the earth. Many heroicall vertues were in
King David, for none is he more to be honoured then
for his repentance: it is a goodlier ſight to ſee a King
on his knees feeding upon the bread of ſorrow, and
mingling his teares with his drink, then to utter divine
Proverbs with wiſe Salomon: and what our Saviour
ſpoke of watching, the ſame doe I ſpeake of
repentance, I ſay unto you all repent, if you are in the

field, remember Abel, if you are a feaſting, remember
Iobs children: when you goe to bed, that you
might holily compoſe your ſelves to reſt, that you
may commit the keyes of your doores, much more
your lives into the hands of GOD, remember the
firſt-borne of Egypt which were ſlaine at midnight
by the Angell of the LORD: let Adulterers remember
Zimri and Cozbi,
                  1 King. 16. 9. and drunkards, King Ela ſlaine
by another Zimri; if you walk in the ſtreets, remember
thoſe on whom the tower of Silo fell, if your
hearts begin to turne to the love of the world, remember
Lots wife: that which befell them may befall
us; it will be then our wiſdome by GODS grace to
prevent ſin, and if we fall into ſin, our next wiſdome
will be to repent of the ſin we have fallen into.
               Another duty which naturally doth ariſe from this
Doctrine is,6. Take the opportunity of doing good. to loſe no time in doing and in receiving
all the good we can; this is the day (appointed to
worke) and how ſhort this day is,Gal. 5. 10. the LORD alone
doth know,Joh. 9. but this we know, the night commeth wherin
none can work. Shall the Sun ſtand ſtill for thee, as it
did for Ioſhua? or go back as it did five houres for Hezekiah?
doe we thinke we can doe good in another
world, when we do no good to ſpeake of in this? be
not deceived with this dangerous errour, and hurtfull
pretention of doing good hereafter, whatſoever thy
hand findeth to do,
                  Eccl. 9. 10. 
                  do it with all thy might, and the reaſon
is good, for there is no device, nor work, nor knowledge,
nor wiſdome in the grave whither thou goeſt. Vaine
hope of future performances hath undone many: ſow
thy ſeed whiles the ſeed time laſteth, if thou looke to
have a crop and harveſt. We may learne this from the

birds of the ayre,Jer. 8. 7. 
                  the Turtle, the Storke, the Crane and
Swallow, know their appointed times; the waifaring man
he travels whiles it is light, then he knowes he is under
the protection of the Lawes, the ſea-faring man
he obſerves the wind, the Smith he ſtrikes whiles his
iron is hot; nay we may learne this wiſdome from
the divell himſelf,Apoc 12. 12. 
                  he rageth and doth all the miſchief
he can, becauſe his time is but ſhort. Thus of doing good,
and ſo likewiſe muſt we let no opportunity ſlip of receiving
good, lay hold of every ſeaſon which may
be an advantage to get heaven, to ſtrengthen and increaſe
ſpirituall graces, be glad if thou canſt heare
the Word preached on a working day.Baſil. 3. Ser. i
                        •
                      Hexaem. Saint Baſil he
preached on a working day, and tels his Auditors
their thoughts &amp; deſires, that he would be ſhort that
they might go about their labour. If ſuch thoughts
poſſeſſe our hearts, at this or any other time, let us repell
them, and remember what the holy Father there
ſpeaketh, the time ſpent in GODS ſervice is not loſt,
for GOD (to recompence them) removes troubleſome
buſineſſe, gives promptitude of minde, or
ſtrength of body, ſends cuſtomers to buy their wares,
and if he doth none of theſe, yet (are they no looſers
by their paines, for) he gives them a rich treaſure in
heaven.
               Laſtly, this point may teach GODS children patience
in all diſtreſſes,7. Short life a ground of patience. and afford them ſound comfort
in all eſtates: they are nearer heaven now, ſalvation
now is nearer to them then when they began to believe;
ſin and Satan do now diſquiet them,Rom. 13. 11. but they
ſhall not do ſo for ever. Many a one can be content to
endure hardſhip a few yeares, nay to be a galley ſlave

under the Turke ſeven yeares, if he had aſſurance of
a great Lordſhip after that time was expired, and
chooſe rather to be a bondman upon thoſe termes,
then to be a free man without them: exerciſe longſuffering
(good Chriſtian) there may be but a day or
moneth, or yeare, but a little time betwixt thee and
the joyes of heaven. Who would not admire the
ſtate of ſuch a beggar, who every houre was in poſſibility
of a Kingdome? but behold a greater reward
by GODS promiſe is due to all his children, then this
earth can afford; more glorious things ſhall be theirs,
then ever eye hath ſeene,
                  1 Cor 2. 9. 
                  or eare hath heard, or the heart
of man can conceive, which without all doubt by compariſon
at leaſt, are true of the joyes of heaven. Why
then ſhouldeſt thou O Chriſtian ſoule be caſt downe,
or why ſhouldeſt thou be in vaine diſquieted? ſurely
if thou wouldeſt ſeriouſly conſider, that thy heavineſſe
ſhall be ſuddenly turned into unſpeakeable joy,
that all thy teares ſhall be for ever wiped from thy
eyes,2 Cor. 4. 17. and that theſe momentany afflictions do proportionably
work unto thee, an exceeding weight of glory, thou
haſt no reaſon to be much dejected for them.
               Thus much of the firſt Doctrine, the ſecond followeth;
but that we may build upon a good foundation,
we muſt firſt declare the meaning of thoſe
words on which we muſt ground our enſuing Obſervation.How Saints are with Chriſt.
               
               
                  I deſire to depart and to be with CHRIST) To be with
CHRIST. Why, was not Saint Paul with CHRIST?
was not his converſation now in heaven?
                  Phil 3. 20. and was not
the ſtreame of his affection carried to CHRIST? was
not he with him in the ſpirit as with the Coloſsians,
                  Coloſ. 2. 5. rejoycing

and beholding his happineſſe? doubtleſſe he
was. But this being with CHRIST was not that preſence
which he deſired; it was a neerer preſence, to
be where he was in the higheſt heavens,John 17. 24. and to behold
the glory which GOD the Father had given him;
deſire is the daughter of indigence and want ſome
way, and himſelfe doth plainely tell us, whileſt we are
in the body,
                  2 Cor. 5. 6. as now Saint Paul was, we are abſent from
the LORD; you may be pleaſed to obſerve a difference
betwixt theſe phraſes of CHRIST his being
with us, and our being with CHRIST, it is one thing
for CHRIST to be with us, this benefit is enjoyed in
this life,Mat. 28. 20. he promiſed to be with the Apoſtles, and
his Succeſſors, and ſo by Analogy, he is with all his
myſticall members to the worlds end; but it is another
thing for us to be with CHRIST; this honour is
reſerved for the world to come, and it is a ſtate of
bleſſedneſſe as he ſpoke to the theefe on the Croſſe,
this day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.
                  Luk. 23. 43. Whence I doe
obſerve, that
               
                  The faithfull ſoule when it departeth out of this life is
immediatly after death with CHRIST.Doctrine 2. If the ſoule of
Paul,
                  Saints immediatly aſcend after death to Chriſt. why not the ſoule of other faithfull ones? Saint
Paul I know, whileſt hee lived, was a man indued
with ſingular zeale for CHRIST and holineſſe of life,2 Cor 11. 23.
and exerciſed with more then ordinary miſeries and
perſecutions; himſelfe reciteth a Catalogue of many
of them, but as it is not the degree of faith, but faith
that juſtifies, nor the meaſure of graces, but the having
ſaving graces in truth, that aſſures us of GODS
gratious acceptation of us in this world, ſo doe they
alſo by GODS free promiſe obtaine reward in heaven,

inſtantly upon the diſſolution;Cypr. de mortalit. ad finem fere. as Saint Cyprian
ſpoke to Demetrian us, though a blaſphemous Ethnick,
that if he would at the end of his life pray to GOD for
the pardon of his ſins, beleeve and confeſſe him, he
ſhould be tranſlated ſub ipſa morte to immortality,
why not? the ſoule being purged clearely from the
impurity and ſtaine of ſin by the completion &amp; ſtate
of grace, which gets full dominion in the very moment
of her departure out of the body, as Alexander
Halenſis, Durandus, and other learned Schoolemen
have reſolved, and it is not defined in that Church
whether the deordination of the will, and whether
vitious affections (as too much love to wife and children)
remaine in the ſoule,Lib. 4. diſt. 21. Sect. 3. ſaith Eſtius, yet doe we
grant this to be true, that the more gracious any man
is in this world, the more is he now reſpected of
GOD, &amp; the more glorious ſhall he be hereafter. The
point it ſelf is clearly proved by the New Teſtament,Rom. 8. 1.
                  There is no condemnation to ſuch as are in CHRIST JESVS.
None,Againſt Purgatory. and therfore not to purgatory paines. For
the name damnation extendeth to Purgatory, ſaith
Th. in 4. Senten. diſt. 45. q. 2. Sixtus Senenſis l. 6. Annotat.
47. No condemnation ſaith the Apoſtle, yes, that
there is damnation to the fire of Purgatory, ſaith the
Jeſuite Malon.
                  Malen againſt B. Vſher. p. 493 2 Cor. 5. 1. Whether will you beleeve? againe, Wee
know that if the earthly houſe of this our tabernacle ſhall be
deſtroyed, we have a building not made with hands, but
eternall in the heavens. S. Chryſoſtome rendreth 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  if, by
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  when, to note the time immediatly after death, he
ſaith 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   not 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   we have not I know not after how
many years, we ſhall have: which may further appeare
by the Apoſtles ſcope, which was to adminiſter conſolation

to the afflicted, as appeares by the end of the
former Chapter, that they ſhould after death goe to
an eternall houſe, ſtatim post mortem acquirenda, forthwith
to be poſſeſſed after death, as Eſtius ſheweth out
of Photius,
                  Lib. 4. diſt. 25. 
                  Anſelme and Thomas, which elſe could be
but ſmall comfort unto them,Sect. 2. if they believed they
ſhould be detained in a fiery priſon, farre hotter and
more intollerable then any puniſhment in this world
can be; and that the ſoules of the faithfull were in a
ſtate of happines before the Aſcenſion of CHRIST
into Heaven is cleare, (though neither they nor the
Angels were ſo happy for degree, as after the incarnation
of our Saviour, is generally concluded, and by
cleare demonſtrations confirmed:) the point I ſay is
cleare, I build not my faith on the book of Wiſdome,
though it binds Papiſts to the beliefe thereof, that
ſaith,Wiſdome 4. 1, 2, 3. 
                  the ſoules of the righteous are in the hands of GOD,
and there ſhall no torment touch them: no torment, then
not the torment of Purgatory; but behold a cryſtall
ſtreame which is able to quench the flames of Purgatory;
if a wicked man will turne from all his ſinnes,
                  Ezek. 18. 22. 
                  &amp;c. he
ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die: all his tranſgreſsions that
he hath committed ſhall not be mentioned to him. How
doth he not remember, if he doth ſo ſeverely puniſh
that it paſſeth the imagination of man to conceive the
greatneſſe thereof? can there be a back reckoning for
that which ſhall never be remembred? and ſaying,
that not a few but al his ſins ſhall be forgotten, will he
yet puniſh them to ſatisfie for any ſins at all? and is it
not an eaſie thing unto the LORD in the day of death
to reward a man according to his waies?Eccleſ. 11. 26. Call you
this a reward, for a good man to be thruſt into a place

of torment? this preſent life is a time of working, ſtriving,
running, ſowing, and godly living, after death is
the time of reaping, of receiving wages, garlands and
crownes; an unjuſt thing it is to detaine the labourers
wages, which reaſon I ſuppoſe is as ſtrong againſt
Purgatory,Alphonſo à Caſtro contra baer. baer. 5. Bell. l. 1. de beat. c. 3. as againſt thoſe Armenians whom our
Adverſaries do worthily confute; and how is it imaginable
that if he good in the old Law ſuppoſed then
dead, went firſt to torment, that they did not tremble
for feare of death? how could they (as they did) depart
in peace? and how is it imaginable that GOD
who appointed ſacrifices for all ſorts of ſins and pollutions,
ſhould appoint neither expiation nor ſacrifice
nor ſatisfaction to be made for the ſoules of the dead!
ſurely there appeares not to us any token of any ſuch
thing, and therefore we may fairely conclude, that all
the ſoules of the righteous then were tranſlated into
a ſtate of happineſſe.
               This Doctrine being thus briefly cleared, we may
from hence draw many concluſions.
               Hence it followeth that the ſoule dieth not with the
body,Vſe 1. as the Sadduces that peſtiferous ſect amongſt
the Jewes did damnably maintaine;The ſoule immortall. for as they denied
the reſurrection and the being of Angels,Acts 23 8. ſo did
they ſay, there was no ſpirit, no ſpirituall ſubſtance at
all,Exercilat. ſaith Scaliger, which without all doubt, is the truth
in the judgement of Scultetus;
                  Eva
                        •
                     g l. 1. c. 23 ſo groſſe were theſe
Sadduces in their apprehenſions: and as a wicked
branch of this ſottiſh ſtock of Sadduces there ſprung
up certaine Arabians which held that the ſoule periſhed
together with the body,Euſeb. Eccleſ. as witneſſeth Euſebius.
A fit doctrine for enlarging the kingdome of the divell:Hiſt. l. 3. c. 36.
                  
but that the ſoule is immortall my Text proveth,
how elſe could it part from the body and be with
CHRIST, unleſſe it was a ſeperable ſubſtance, ſith the
body is not with CHRIST till after the generall reſurrection?
whence is there is naturall confcience that
accuſing power for ſin, that feare of wrath, but from
this principle that the ſoule is immortall? never make
any queſtion of this, when thou dieſt, thy ſoule which
is thy better part dieth not, but is taken out of thy body,
as a candle out of a lanthorne, and immediatly placed
either in bliſſe or in torment.
               Hence may we in the ſecond place conclude againſt
the Anabaptiſts and Socinians,
                  2. The ſeule ſleeps not as the body. which though they
went not ſo far as the Sadduces to deny the reſurrection,
yet did theſe fantaſtiques dreame that the ſoule
ſleepeth till Doomes day,Bullinger cōtra Anaba l. 4. c. 10 and is in a ſtate of incenſibility
like ſome creatures in Winter, inſecta▪
                   till they be
quickned and revived by the heat of the Sun, ſo they
of ſoules, till they be raiſed by the power of the LORD
at the laſt day? but how then could Saint Paul be with
CHRIST? but to ſay no more againſt theſe ſilly dreamers,
I proceed.
               In the third place, that conceit alſo falls to the
ground,3. Soules departed immediately ſee God▪
                   which prevailed with many of the antient Fathers
and with ſome later writers, that the ſoules of
the righteous ſee not GOD till the laſt day, but are kept
in certaine receptacles in expectation therof. I ſee
no profit to the Auditory by naming them; the learned
if they pleaſe may read many of their names in
Sixtus Senenſis.
                  Sixtus Senenſis bibl. San. lib. 6. But how then (ſay I) could Saint Paul
be with CHRIST?Annotat. 345. this opinion is an unworthy conceit
condemned by the Church, as robbing heaven

for the preſent of its bleſſed inhabitants.
               Fourthly, hence alſo doth it follow, that though
CHRIST as touching his divinity is every where preſent,4. Chriſt abſent in body.
for elſe he were not GOD, yet to us in this world
he is abſent as touching his bodily preſence. For,
what is it to be with CHRIST, but to be preſent
where CHRIST is bodily preſent? and againe, whiles
we are in the body,
                  2 Cor. 5. 8. 
                  wee are abſent from the LORD: the
Apoſtle then was ignorant of that unhappy perplexed
point which ſome ſeeme to defend, the ubiquity of
CHRISTS body, for howſoever his humane nature
(eſpecially in the ſtate of glory) is adorned with admirable
gifts, and advanced to the higheſt dignity,
honour and domination, yet doe the natures of
CHRIST perſonally united remaine diſtinct both in
eſſence, properties, and operations. Yea, and the mſelves
confeſſe that the divine properties belong to
the humane nature, not by any phyſicall transfuſion
from one ſubject into another,Hannius tracta. de perſonâ Chriſti, p. 12. but it is only perſonall
and communicated to the humane nature by the grace
of perſonal union inſomuch that the humane nature (as
they ſay) is omnipreſent not in being but in having,Philip Nichol. l. 1. de omnipraeſentia bominis Chriſti, c. 6.
not in it ſelfe but in the perſon of the word, and thus
do they in words at leaſt deny what they ſeem to contend
for.
               From whence likewiſe it followeth that there is no
Popiſh Purgatory;5. Againſt Purgatory. the fault is clearely remitted, and
ſo there can be no ſatisfactory torments required.
GOD ſhould (me thinks) but mock us, if they ſay true,
as if he ſhould ſay, I pardon thee thy offence, but I
will puniſh thee for it, I acquit thee of the debt thou
oweſt me, but not of the paiment: but why ſhould not

the ſoules of the righteous dying in faith be caried inſtantly
into heaven, as well as the ſoule of a man newly
baptized comming to that holy Sacrament in due
manner, and dying before he hath committed a new
ſin, although he was full of ſinne before? there is no
queſtion of this latter, and why ſhould there be of the
former? And if they cannot go to Heaven becauſe
GODS juſtice muſt be ſatisfied, what will becom of all
thoſe that die a little before the judgement? &amp; much
more is the difficulty increaſed in thoſe which paſſe in
a moment from mortalitie to immortalitie at the very
comming of JESVS CHRIST. But I marvel not if Papiſts
do contend for this Purgatory, as being indeed
one of the beſt fires that ever the Pope and his Clergie
have had for the heating of their kitchins. For let
this be granted that there is ſuch a fire, and that the
torments there and in the place of the damned differ
but in duration, and there are no torments in this
world comparable to thoſe in Purgatory; let their
Preachers tell their people ſuch a ſuppoſition as this
is, if a foule had beene tormented in Purgatory thirty
yeares,Diſcipulus de tempore ſer. 60. litera B. and had by an Angell a choiſe either to ſtay
in Purgatory one day long, or to returne into the body
and do this penance a hundred yeares together, to
tread only on iron nailes which will pierce the feet,
to drinke gall mingled with vineger, and to eat the
courſeſt bread, to be cloarhed with Camels haire, to
lie on the ground, and inſtead of a bolſter to have a
hard ſtore for a pillow, the foule would rather do this
penance a hundred yeares together,Apoc. 9. 5. then to endure in
Purgatory one day, faith their Preacher. By this and
ſuch like doctrines, the conſciences of their diſciples

are ſtung as with Scorpions; and it is like a gift whither
ſoever it turneth,Pro. 17 8. it proſpereth, then may they
work them like ſoft waxe by their charitable promiſes
to apply the meanes for their eaſe and reliefe out
of the place of torments. What a wofull ſpeech was
that of our Richard 1.Fox Acts pag. 249. who committed his ſoule to
Purgatory till Doomes day.
               Sixthly, this Doctrine overthroweth their Popiſh
prayers for the dead,6. Againſt praying for the dead directed unto GOD to eaſe them,
and free them from the paines of Purgatory, yea and
that kind of kindnes too which many that do profeſſe
the Orthodox doctrine, doe unwarrantably uſe in
words, and further, as a more durable monument of
their miſtake,Balthaeſar Lydius Nota in diſputat. Taber. pag. 202. do write upon the grave ſtones of the
dead, GOD be mercifull to the ſoule of this dead man.
For are they with CHRIST? then doe their prayers
bring no profit to the dead, but hurt to the living.
For to ſpeake the faireſt of them, 1. Such prayers can
be no better than an idle word,
                  Mat. 12 36. 
                  for which we must give
an account at that day. 2. They are an injury to the
dead, and do vertually imply, that ſuch as pray for
them are not perſwaded they are in happineſſe for
whom they pray. 3. This practiſe although it might
be perhaps by ſome qualification juſtifiable in the
intention of the ſpeaker, yet may it breed danger in
the conceit of the hearer, who may turne thy voluntary
devotion to harden him in the dangerous error
of that opinion; if then no benefit redounds either to
the dead, thy ſelfe, or the hearer, its beſt to leave
thoſe formes of prayer which are made for the dead.
But ignorant perſons being reproved are bold to reply
in this fooliſh manner, what would you have us

ſay of the dead, would you have us to revile or curſe
them? Oh perverſe minds! as though neceſſitie lay
upon you, either to pray for them or to curſe them?
Belike what diſpleaſeth GOD pleaſeth you paſſing
well: let us ſpeake of the dead as GODS Word teacheth
us to ſpeake of them; ſure I am, it no where enjoyneth
us to pray for them, nor furniſheth us with
the example of any Saint to that purpoſe, and yet were
their affections to the dead as good as yours. Cannot
you uſe ſuch formes of ſpeech when you fall into
mention of them, they are with GOD, they are at reſt,
they are happy, their memorie is bleſſed, unleſſe you
pray for them.
               But leaving now theſe Uſes of confutation, I come
to thoſe of inſtruction, which are indeed more profitable
for our edification, and more ſutable to this preſent
occaſion, and the firſt is,
               Feare not death (O thou righteous ſoul) overmuch;Vſe of Inſtruction.
its one benefit we reape from the death of our bleſſed
Saviour, to be freed from the feare of our own death;
death is called indeed by Bildad in Iob,
                  1. Death not to be feared. 
                  the prince ofterrours,
&amp; by the Philoſopher,Heb. 2. 15. of all formidable things,
the moſt terrible,Iob. 18. 14. ſo it is to the wicked, or at leaſt there
is good cauſe it ſhould be ſo, for to ſuch as live without
CHRIST, death is as a purſeivant ſent from hell
to fetch them thither: but they that live conſcionably,
may thinke of death comfortably, and they may
ſing that triumphant ſong,1 Cor. 15. 
                  O death where is thy ſting!
they may take this all-devouring ſerpent without any
hurt at all into their boſomes: they that have their
debts paid, dare go out of doores, and are not afraid
to meet the Sergeant; they dare looke on death, and

welcome him as the King of heavens officer to give
them poſſeſſion of an everlaſting-inheritance; wee
feare our friends when they have a vizour on their faces,
but put it off and we rejoyce in them. Excellent
was the ſpeech of S. Ambroſe to the Nobles of his city,
which with threats and flatteries were ſent to him
by the Count Stilico, to perſwade him to pray unto
GOD for the continuance of his life, which when the
holy Biſhop heard he anſwered divinely,Paulinus in vita Ambroſij ad B. Auguſt. J have not
ſo lived amongſt you that I am aſhamed to live longer,
nor am J afraid to die, becauſe we have a good
Lord. Doubtleſſe had we (beloved brethren) as much
faith on earth as there is joy in heaven, we would not
be afraid of death: this is the narrow paſſage betwixt
this life and our countrie: on this ſide the bridge we
have many troubles, many ſins, many feares, many
temptations of the Divel, which ſhould make us think
the worſe of our lives, and very willing to leave them:
but on the other ſide, we ſhall be freed from all trouble,
from all ſin, from al moleſtation of the divel, and
ſhall be filled with all the joy our hearts can poſſibly
deſire. So that hitherto we may apply Sampſons riddle,
Out of the enter came forth meat,
                  Judg. 14. 14. 
                  and out of the ſtrong came
forth ſweetneſse.
               
               Secondly, this may ſerve to moderate our exceſſive
mourning for our friends which die,2. Mourne not immoderatly for the dead. we hope in
the LORD. David exceeded in his ſorrow for Abſalon,
and was there not a cauſe? He did not ſo at the
death of the infant. Let us rejoyce, Saint Chryſoſtome
ſaith,Chryſ. in locum. 2 Sam. 12. 23. for the juſt both living and dead, becauſe they
are happy, let us not in an unſeemely manner bewaile
them by pulling off our haires, baring our armes, tearing

our faces, or putting on mourning garments, ſo
ſaith the father; and I ſay, happy are they which have
exchanged a baſe earthly tabernacle for a princely
Pallace, ſorrowes for joy, and earth for heaven; and
me thinkes our bleſſed brother now deceaſed, if he
had intercourſe with us mortall creatures, would ſay
to his deare wife lying in her teares, children and
friends, as our Saviour did to thoſe pious women that
followed him;Luk. 23. 28. 
                  Daughters of Ieruſalem weepe not for me
but weepe for your ſ
                        •
                     lves, you know my faſtings, my
meditations, my watchings (and know you brethren
that godly Miniſters do purpoſely watch and meditate
for you, when you are or would be a ſleep.) You
know my griefe for my owne calamities and for the
calamities of GODS Church, and by your owne experience,
you may know what ſharpe combats I have
had with that raging enemie the Divell, and what
wounds I have received in the conflict; now do I
feare no perils on the land or ſea, no perils in the
houſe or in the field, now am J victorious over Satan
and have trampled him under my feet, and now he
hath nothing at all in mee, and now am J crowned
with glorie, and would you (my deare friends) be ſo
unkind to me to wiſh me alive againe, and to run the
former hazards? Kings and Queenes are willing to
marrie their daughters to forraine Princes, and never
looke to ſet their eyes onthem againe, and ſhould we
mourne too much for his abſence, and not rather rejoyce
with him for his happier eſtate then this earth
can afford?Gen. 45. 27. When Iacob heard that his beloved Ioſeph
was alive, and governour over all the Land of Aegypt,
his fainting heart revived, no leſſe ought the conſideration

of the glorie of departed ſervants of GOD,
cheere up our drooping and ſad hearts for them, and
excite us to deſire the fruition of the ſame glorie.
               And this is my next point to be handled, I deſire,
ſaith S. Paul, to be diſsolved and to be with CHRIST.
               
                  It's the fore-ſight of heavenly glory and being with
CHRIST,Doctrine 3. Foreſight of being with Chriſt makes willing to d
                        •
                     e. 
                  that makes a man deſire to die: Some men
indeed would die, becauſe there is nothing in this
world for them to expect but miſerie and ſhame, and
theſe do little leſſe ſometimes then call for the rocks to
fall upon them, that they might end their wretched
daies as Iob ſaith,Iob. 3. 21, 23. 
                  they long for death, and dig for it more
then for hid treaſure, which rejoyce exceedingly, and
are glad when they can finde the grave, this motive
ſwaied not Saint Paul, but onely this that he might be
with CHRIST. I grant to deſire death ſimply, as death,
is againſt the Law of GOD and the law of nature,
death is our enemie, and is not from GOD creationes by
creation,Death ſimply not deſired. though it be truly from him ultione to revenge
the ſins of man,Florus cited by B Vſher in hiſt. ſaith Florus de praedeſt: or as
others ſay, it is from him ordinatione, becauſe in juſtice
he ordained death corporall as one part of the
puniſhment which was due for the ſinne of man,Goteſol. p 132. and
hence our Saviour CHRIST himſelfe who knew no
ſin at all, viewing death as it is in it ſelfe conſidered,
declined it,2 Cor. 5. 4. 
                  let this cup paſse, and ſo did Saint Paul too,
we will not (ſaith he) be uncloathed, the parting of theſe
good friends body and ſoule without ſome further
end, is a grievous ſeparation; this harmeleſſe innocent
nature teacheth; and as death is further a meanes
to cut off all poſſibility to profit others, and to helpe
the poore Church of CHRIST with our labours 
                     ••…
                  us

piety and grace may move them to pray with David,
LORD let my ſoule live.
                  Pſal. 119. 175. Theſe cautions are premiſed
to prevent miſtaking in the point; but now, which is
to my purpoſe, Conſider death as it is a way &amp; meanes
to bring us to the preſence of CHRIST, ſo it may be
holily deſired, our Saviour CHRIST, who ſaid, let this
cup paſſe,
                  Luk. 12. 50. ſaid alſo as his death was our life, I have a
Baptiſme to be baptized withall, and how am I pained till
it be accompliſhed?
                  2 Cor. 5. 4. and nót only I Paul, but we that are
faithfull that are in this tabernacle, do groane earneſtly,
ver. 2. not for that we would be uncloathed, but cloathed
upon, that mortality might be ſwallowed up of life; and after,
we are willing rather to be abſent from the body and
preſent with the LORD.Ver. 8. Its the love that a child ſhould
be borne into the world, not the love of paine that
makes the mother deſire the travell in child-birth;
excellently ſaith Saint Baſil,
                  Baſil de laudibus Iuſtitiae. 
                  properanti ad coebeſtem paetriam,
&amp;c. to him that makes haſt to the countrey
which is above, the ſtay in the body is more grievous
then any paine, or any priſon: and it is ſaid that
Peter and Andrew welcomed their croſſes, as they
were wont to doe their deareſt friends, and imbraced
them in their armes, and ſaluted them with kiſſes
of peace. Ignatius encouraged wild beaſts to devoure
him that he might be bread for CHRIST; Martyrs
went to their death with cheerefullneſſe and ſongs,
and ran to the ſtake as to a garland,2 Sam. 10. 22. and who would
with Saul hide himſelfe in the ſtuffe, when he is called
to be crowned a King?
               If Abraham ſaw his day by faith when he was but promiſed,
and rejoyced,
                  Ioh. 8. 56. what cauſe of joy muſt it needs be
to ſee the Saviour of the world when he is exhibited?

If Saint Iohn Baptiſt did leape at his preſence when
he was in the wombe of his bleſſed mother. What
will his glorious preſence effect in them who ſhall
behold him in al his Royaltie? if the Wife men of the
Eaſt went a long journie,Luk. 1. 44. and rejoyced to ſee the holy
Babe CHRIST in the houſe; what cauſe of joy
will it be to ſee him ſit in his glorie at the right hand
of his Father, far above all Principalities and powers?
If many Kings and Princes longed for that day to ſee their
Saviour mortall,Luk. 10. 24. what reſemblance is fit to expreſſe
the joy of thoſe that behold him crowned with glory
and immortalitie? it is a paſſing glory to be admitted
to the ſight of CHRIST his face, and to receive glory
from the brightneſſe of his Majeſtie, and if we were to
ſuffer torments every day, yea the very torments of
hell for a time, therby to gaine the ſight of CHRIST,
it were nothing in reſpect of the reward.
               This Doctrine ſhewes us the extreame folly of all
licentious livers and impenitent ſinners;Vſe 1. when they
looke upon their wicked courſes,Wicked ones cannot bee with Chriſt. what for ſight can
they have but of hell as their juſt reward they would
be with CHRIST (as they ſay) hereafter, and yet
they will not have CHRIST to be wi
                     •
                  h them now,
and to rule over them▪ they will ſow unto the fleſh,
and yet would reape unto the ſpirit; they are ſtout and
will have their ſinne though they be damned for it:
we will (ſay thoſe rebels in Ieremy) walke after our
owne devices,
                  Jer. 18. 22. 
                  and we will every one doe the imaginations
of his evill heart. Experience ſheweth us that you cannot
cruſh oyle out of skins, nor ſweet wine out of
ſower grapes, and if you be the ſeedeſmen of darnell
and cockle, you ſhall have no harveſt of wheat 
                     •…
                  or

good graine; you will not live conſcionably, and yet
you would die peaceably; and though you ſpeake
CHRIST faire, yet you wil looſe nothing for his ſake;
the chaine will make your profeſſion afraid, and reproach
will make it aſhamed: you love him well you
ſay; but you will be adviſed not to diſpleaſe ſuch and
ſuch friends for his love; your fore-ſight of Heaven
hath no hands to do good works corporall and ſpirituall,
nor eyes to ſhed teares for your ſins and the ſins
of others, nor ſtomacke to abide a holy and a religious
faſt, nor fleſh to endure this mortification and
zealous revenge, nor tongue to ſpeake the language
of confeſſion, and zealous, devout and faithfull prayer;
if then in your extremities and when your feares
approach, you ſend for us, as Pharaoh did for Moſes,
and never till then,2 King. 6. 26, 27. and cry unto us helpe us and comfort
us, as that ſtarved woman did, to the King of
Iſrael: Wee anſwer as hee did that diſtreſſed creature,
if the LORD doth not helpe you, how ſhould we? And
now by this time I ſuppoſe you are brought to that
paſſe, that GODS ſervants, whom you have in your
proſperity deſpiſed may ſay to you concerning all
your daubers whom you then reſpected, where are
they now that will propheſie peace peace unto you?
your conſciences which before were aſleepe, being
now awakened to heare the crie of your ſinnes, and
theſe glaſſes formerly covered with duſt as it were,
being wiped cleare to repreſent unto you the disfigured
and odious face of your ſinnes; when theſe evill
daies ſhall come upon you (as they will or that which
is worſe) you muſt needs confeſſe to the terrour of
your ſoules,Gen 42. 12. that we GODS Meſſengers have told you
of theſe things, and you would not heare us, as Reuben
                  
ſaid to his brethren. Your ſins which you tooke to
be your friends (as GOD himſelfe hath threatned)
are ſuddenly turned to be your foes, and now do appeare
as a marſhalled army comming in a terrible
manner againſt you,Pſal. 50. 21. and when GOD ſpeakes to your
conſciences,2 King. 9 33. as Iehu did to the Eunuchs, who is on my
ſide? who? even they will caſt you downe and daſh, as it
were, your blood againſt the wals, and make you to be
trampled upon; and then can you caſt your eyes noway
without horrour, if upwards unto heaven, they
will tell you that you are juſtly excluded out of that
happy place, if you think upon hell, the mouth thereof
(as you feare) is open every moment to receive
you when theſe evill daies ſhall come, &amp;c.
               Second Uſe of inſtruction is, that we would ſtudy
our ſelves,2. Get aſſurance of Chriſt. and ranſacke our ſoules, and be of good
grounds, and to have certaine evidence that our
change ſhall be for the better: mans wiſdome teacheth
him in Summer to provide for Winter, in
youth for old age; if GOD be better then the world
and heaven better then earth, and the ſoule better
then the body, ſhall we not labour while we live to
get full aſſurance of being with CHRIST, as S. Paul
had, when we are dead? but here is the maine doubt,
how I ſhould know and be aſſured thereof.
               Firſt, if thou art aſſured hereof, then haſt thou faith,
the maine and fundamentall grace,1. Faith gives aſſurance of Chriſt. not fundamentum
quod, that is, CHRIST, but cui as a learned Schooleman
doth diſtinguiſh, immediatly laying us upon
CHRIST, and as a Captaine, I ſay not making the graces
as heavenly Souldiers, but as bringing them forth
to fight according to their ſeverall operations; thou
haſt I ſay a lively faith both in that direct act whereby

it juſtifieth, and alſo by a prudent obſervation of
the worke of faith in thy ſoule; thou doſt by faith believe
that thou art juſtified by faith; thou haſt alſo the
attendant companion upon faith, that Chriſtian hope
whereby thou waiteſt on GOD till he accompliſh
all his gratious promiſes;Heb. 3. 6. if we come againſt the Divell
as David did againſt the Philiſtine,
                  1 Sam. 17. 45. 
                  not with ſword,
ſhield and ſpeare, but in the name of the LORD of Hoſts, we
are ſure to conquer. If we have theſe graces and by
the uſe of holy meanes do hold them faſt, how happy
are we! Bleſſed is he that beleeveth the Lords words
to be all of them true, and bleſſed is he that waiteth
on him, till he manifeſts the truth of his words, that
believeth by faith that GOD is his Father, and expecteth
by hope that he ſhould ſhew a fatherly affection to
him; who believes that ſalvation belongs to him, and
waites by hope til he enters into poſſeſſion of it: if this
then be the bleſſed frame of thy ſoule, that thou reſolveſt
and hopeſt to live, and thou reſolveſt and hopeſt
to die in the armes of thy ſweet Saviour, thou art in a
happy caſe.
               Secondly, if thou haſt this holy affection to die, and
aſſurance of being with CHRIST when thou art dead,2. Aſſurance of being with Chriſt what it works.
then doſt thou labour for the true ſenſe and feeling
of thy reconciliation with GOD,Mat 5. 25. and doſt make
thy peace with thy brother whom thou haſt wronged
by word or deed; if thou lookeſt to ſee the face of
CHRIST the righteous Judge with comfort thou wilt
abandon fooliſh ſhame, and fond ſelfe-love, thou wilt
make reſtitution, and returne goods in thy hands to
the right owner;Ezek. 33. 15. thou wilt not ſuffer ſin to lie upon
thy ſoule,Iob. 31. 38. 
                  nor let thy furrowes in thy field to cry out against

thee, nor by proportion, the stone and timber of thy
houſe to complaine of thee, Zach 5. 4. for this would bring
a curſe to conſume them: thou wilt often make thy reckning
even with thy GOD, for this makes friendſhip durable,
if CHRIST be gone, as he ſeemes to be at ſome
time from his children, thou wilt ſeek for him ſorrowing
as Mary his mother did, and thou ſhalt in GODS
good time find him in the Temple (as ſhe did) I mean
in the uſe of his holy ordinances.
               Thirdly,3. Spiritual watch alwaies be vigilant and watchfull; this ſpirituall
watch is nothing but the carefullneſſe of the
ſoule to keep ſpirituall graces in their vigour and activity,
and though GOD hath appointed watchmen over
us, yet hath he not appointed watchmen for us,
their watching is not in our ſtead to give us leave to
ſleepe, but it is to keepe us waking, what I ſay to you, I
ſay to all,
                  Mar. 13 37. 
                  Watch. And very good reaſon, You know not
(ſaith our Saviour) what houre your LORD will come;
                  Mat 24. 42.
and our drouſie diſpoſition will be ſoone rocked a
ſleepe by Satan, who beſprinkles the temples of our
head with his ſpirituall opium of wicked motions and
ſuggeſtions, if we do not lawfully ſtrive againſt them;
take heed leaſt thine owne corrupt heart the greateſt
enemy thou haſt beguileth thee not, be prudently vigilant
to deſcry dangers before they come, to prevent
all occaſions whereby thy happy eſtate might
be loſt; the dumbe beaſts, as Oxe and Mule, that are
without underſtanding, will not come neare the place
where they have eſcaped danger, and ſhouldeſt thou
adventure to the hazard of thy ſoule? in knowledge
be not like the horſe and mule, in avoiding dangers
be like them. Conſider the Divels policy, he is a

theefe; a beggar may ſafely paſſe by him, his aime is
to rob the wealthy paſſenger: rub thine eyes often,
frequently ranſacke thy heart, keep GODS feare freſh
in thy ſoule. Iacob could not ſleepe when he heard of
Eſau his comming againſt him, and Sampſon had little
liſt to ſleepe in Dalilaes lap when he heard the Philiſtins
were comming on him;Gen 32. delight in the ſociety
of the Saints,Iudg 16. 19, 20 good company keepes us waking; all
theſe are ſoveraigne helps to keepe us ſpiritually
watching.
               Fourthly, often meditate on death, die as it were
daily in the diſpoſition of thy ſoule,4. Frequent meditation on death. and preparation
to death; forgetfullneſſe of death makes life to be ſinfull,
and death to be terrible as a deſtroying Lyon,Lamen. 1. 9.
whereas the ſight of ſavage beaſts is not terrible to
thoſe that converſe with them;Mat. 24. 48. looke on death as on
the Sun in an opticke glaſſe, though it be far off, yet it
ſeemes neere at hand, and ſo in truth it may be neere
us, being as a pit covered with ſnow into which wee
may ſuddenly fall; that which many carrie in their
rings, carrie thou in thy heart, memento mori; be like
to thoſe that in their life time had their ſcpulchers in
their gardens, and places of pleaſure, and that they
might be mindfull hereof, ſome had dead mens skuls
before their eyes in their moſt delicious banquets;
by ſo doing, we ſhould prevent a great deale of ſin, &amp;
it would be as a bitter pill to purge out many noiſome
humours,Deut. 32. 29. and prove that we are truly wiſe, alwaies
ready for death: its an excellent thing when death approacheth,
to have nothing elſe to do but to die.
               Fifthly,5. Continuall prayer. it is a comfortable ſigne, if thou doſt heartily
pray to GOD for this very end as the Saints of

GOD have done:Pſal. 39. 21. &amp; 90. 12. prayer is our beſt guard when we
are at home and when we are abroad; GOD will not
denie our ſuits made in CHRIST his name,Luk 2. 32. becauſe
this was one benefit which CHRIST merited for us.
Alas what elſe ſhould we do when we are every day
for ought we know going to judgement? ſhould we
not intreat the Judge to pardon us? ſhould we not
with ſighes and ſobs cry continually unto him to be
mercifull unto us?Sozom lib. 1. 
                  Hier. reports in the life of Paul a
Diſciple of Anthony the firſt Monke,Hiſtor. cap 13. and that not ſimply
for devotion, but to avoid perſecution, that this
religious man was found dead kneeling upon his
knees, holding up his hands, lifting up his eyes, the
ſoule was ſo devout that the very dead corps ſeemed
to pray unto GOD, now this humble ſeeking to GOD
by prayer that he would make us alwaies ready for
death, argues a ſoule ſenſible of its owne weakeneſſe
and of GODS goodneſſe.
               Sixthly, if thou art ſincere and ſound at the heart,
and walkeſt with GOD in the uprightneſſe of thy
ſoule,6. Sincerity. and makeſt this the crowne and garland of thy
life, which will never wither and decay, that thou hateſt
all knowne ſins, not the outward onely whereof
men may be witneſſes, but all inward corruptions, as
hardneſſe of heart,Eſay 55. 7. wanton revengefull thoughts
and ſuch like, whereof the world can take no notice,
if thou magnifieſt GODS graces, and gracious perſons,
and canſt be content out of thy love to CHRIST,
to ſuffer any thing for CHRIST, this is ſincerity: I
ſay not legall ſincerity, that is a perfection too high
for us to attaine unto, nor onely naturall and morall
integrity, whereby an unregenerate man is guided by

the light which is in him without hypocriſie (this
may the very heathens have) but Evangelicall integrity,
whereby the perſon being accepted for
CHRIST, the heart though failing in ſome particular
actions, yet manifeſts habituall grace by a conſtant
courſe (in the generall) of a holy converſation.
               Laſtly,7. Thankes for Redemption from death. to name no more, if we are truly thankfull
unto GOD for making away for us to goe by death
to heaven (by the death of his Son) whoſe portion
by due deſert was hell; how Iudith and Eſter were
magnified for procuring deliverance to their countrymen
from outward enemies, the Bible ſheweth:
how the Grecians honoured Flaminius the Romane
for prevailing againſt Philip of Macedon,
                  Plutar. in vita Flami. and proclaiming
their liberty,Florus Hiſt. is regiſtred in heathen ſtories,
with what applauſes and acclamations of all the Romans,
men,Rom. li. 2 7. women, and children Conſtantine was received
into that Queene of Cities,Euſeb. lib. 1 de vita Conſt. c. 33, 34. 
                  Euſebius the Hiſtorian
doth relate, for vanquiſhing the Tyrant Maxentius,
calling him their deliverer, their conſerver, their
bountifull Patron, a common good thing, &amp;c. here
was love and thankfulneſſe we ſee moſt earneſt; GOD
knowes and our owne conſciences teſtifie unto us this
day how far we exceed thoſe Grecians and Romans
in mercies beſtowed upon us, not by a mortall man
but by our JESVS, not from temporall ſervitude, but
from the power of the divell; if then our cries and
acclamations be to our JESVS conſtantly, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , as
theirs were to their deliverers, and we can joyfully
ſound forth S. Paul 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , O death where is thy ſtingthankes
be to GOD who hath given us victory through JESVS
CHRIST our LORD, this is a good ſigne of a bleſſed

man; and if theſe are in you, I do aſſure you that
your eſtate is now good, and by perſeverance in
them, ſhall be farre better hereafter, and theſe will
comfort you,What comforts in death. when all the comforts of the world will
faile. What will all friends, riches, and pleaſures profit
when you are on your death-bed? unleſſe you have
this foreſight of joy in CHRIST, you live (for ought
you know) under GODS curſe, the curſe both of the
Law, and the curſe of the Goſpell, and you can have
no ſolid joy in any thing under the Sun, no more then
a condemned man can have in his wealth &amp; fore-paſſed
honour; but have and keep theſe fruits of the holy
Spirit, and when death ſhall come to thee, and take
thee (as it were) by the hand, thou haſt no cauſe to
ſhrinke for feare, but maiſt ſay with Babylas ſlaine by
Decius that perſecutor, in the words of the Pſalmiſt,
Returne unto thy reſt O my ſoule, for the LORD hath beene
beneficiall unto thee, now my griefes farewell, &amp; all my
wrongs adieu, and now my ſoule be glad, for now
commeth thy reſt, thy ſure reſt, thy ſweet and never
fading reſt; and that which comforted Hezekiah on
his ſuppoſed death-bed,Eſay 38. 3. 
                  Remember LORD how I have
walked before thee with an upright heart; that alſo was
a great comfort to this our deceaſed brother, that he
could ſay to mee in his laſt ſickneſſe, when I viſited
him,Note. that he had walked in ſincerity, and performed
his Miniſteriall duties (ſetting humane unavoidable
defects aſide) with an upright heart, and ſo I doubt
not but GOD ſent his Angell to waite at his beds head
to carry his ſoule when it parted from the body, into
Abrahams boſome.
               You have heard (beloved) what was Saint Pauls
                  
deſire, that was to die; and a reaſon implied of his deſire,
for then he ſhould be with CHRIST: hearken
with the like Chriſtian attention to Saint Pauls judgement
or cenſure of that eſtate of being with CHRIST;
this is ſaith he far the better, or (as ſome expound the
words) which is beſt of all:Queſt. which occaſions a Queſtion,
Whether is it better to be with CHRIST in his
humane nature,How it is beſt to be with Chriſt. then to be with GOD, whoſe beatificall
viſion is ſaid to be the chiefe object of happineſſe?
To which I anſwer, that the Apoſtle doth not
compare theſe together,Sol. I meane the enjoying of
GOD and CHRIST, as though his chiefe happineſſe
did conſiſt rather in beholding the body of CHRIST
then the face of GOD, but his being with CHRIST,
and that eſtate in glory is compared to his being in
this preſent world, and he mentioneth CHRIST becauſe
he in his humane nature had purchaſed this
great happineſſe for him, which conſiſteth principally
in the viſion of divine excellency: our happineſſe
is chiefely in GOD,Aquin. 1, 2. q. 3 art. 8. ſine contradictione. but by CHRIST his merit: do we
not thinke that many poore exiles ſtripped out of
their inheritance, and baniſhed out of their native
ſoile; do deſire to ſee that day, and that bleſſed man
that ſhould bring them out of their captivity, and ſettle
them in their former habitations, and rejoyce in
him as the author of their happineſſe? hence I note,
               
                  A life in heaven with CHRIST,Doctrine 4. 
                  is farre better then
a life on earth with men.
                  Chriſts glorious preſence the beſt. It is better for the wife to be
with her husband then in other company, and is it
not much better for the Spouſe of CHRIST to be
with her LORD, whom ſhe worthily eſteemeth as the
chiefe of ten thouſand? this preſent life of nature is

good, the life of grace is far better, but the life of glory
is beſt of all; it is good to be a babe in CHRIST, it
is better to be a ſtrong experienced Chriſtian, but to
raigne with CHRIST is beſt of all; it is good to ſigh
and ſob for ſin, it is better to mortifie and to prevaile
againſt it, but it is beſt of all to be perfectly ſanctified,
and purged from it.2 Sam. 14. We know that Abſolon recalled
from exile, and not admitted to ſee his fathers face in
Court, was impatient of all delayes, and ſo are GODS
children after they are called to GODS favour, long to
ſee their Saviour which is far better, which may further
appeare by theſe differences betwixt theſe two eſtates.Reaſon I.
               
               Is it not far better to have the wayward old man in
our boſome,Sin in the beſt on earth. the moſt ſpitefull enemy and falſe friend,
I meane all the remainders of corruption, the leproſie
and poiſon of ſin quite aboliſhed then to have them
ſtill in us? while we live they will be in us do what
we can, we ſhall find much ignorance of GOD and
all his waies, much folly which keepeth us from taking
any thing to heart which reſpecteth GOD or our
ſelves, much uncircumciſion of heart which makes
us that we cannot be holily poore in ſpirit though
conſcious of innumerable motives which ſhould induce
us hereunto, much droſſe of ſelfe-ſufficiency
which will not let us perceive what need we have of
GODS preſence for the quickning, ſtrengthening,
comforting, directing and proſpering of us in all our
wayes, though the breath of our noſtrils be not more
neceſſary for our naturall being, then his grace is for
our ſpirituall welfare and comfort; theſe evils do renue
their aſſaults on us every day, and notwithſtanding

we renue daily our indeavouring againſt them,
yet cannot we get that full conqueſt over them. If we
could aſſemble all the Saints together, and aske them
whether they were without ſin,Aug. de natura &amp; gratia c. 36. what do we thinke
would they anſwer? whither that which Pelagius ſaith,
or that which Iohn the Apoſtle ſaith? How great ſoever
their excellency was, if they could be asked, they
would cry out with one voice,1 Joh. 1. 8. 
                  If we ſay we have no ſin,
we deceive our ſelves, and there is no truth in us, and
would they perhaps ſay ſo more humbly then truly?
GOD placeth not the commendation of humility in
any part of falſity: and therefore if they ſpoke this
truly, they had ſin, becauſe they humbly confeſſed it,
and the truth was in them; &amp; if they ſaid they had ſin
when they had none at all, they did lie, and ſo did ſin
in lying, and the truth was not in them, but when we
are in CHRIST all our ſins are quite aboliſhed, and not
till then, and therfore to be with CHRIST is far better.
               Secondly, is it not far better to be in ſuch a condition,
where we ſhall be freed from all troubles,2. Death freeth from all croſſes. miſeries,
diſeaſes and diſcontents, then to live in poverty,
debts, diſeaſes, diſgraces, diſcontents and infinite
croſſes? even thoſe things often which we love the
beſt, and expected the greateſt comforts from them
may prooue our greateſt croſſes, or at leaſt we live in
feare and expectation of changes and evils to come;
now they that are with CHRIST are then and not till
then, freed from all thoſe evils which ſhould make
our life not over-pleaſing to us, and they are not
onely freed from thoſe evils, but ſet in high places
out of the gunne-ſhot and danger of them, and

therefore to be with CHRIST is farre better.
               Thirdly, is it not farre better to live in ſuch ſtate
where we ſhall live without feare of diſpleaſing our
good GOD,3. Death freeth from all feare. and of looſing his favour, which is better
then life it ſelfe, then to live in feare of diſpleaſing
him? from this feare in this life we can never be freed
in truth, nor without great danger in our conceit, and
it is a great bitternes to the ſoule to diſpleaſe our beſt
friend in the world; from theſe feares we are fully freed
when we ſhall be with CHRIST, and therefore to be
with CHRIST is far the better.
               Fourthly, is it not far better to be there, where we
ſhall be freed from the moleſtations and temptations
of the Divell,4. Death freeth from all temptations. who as he is crafty, ſo is he cruell, then
to be encumbred with them?2 Tim. 4. 8. S. Paul we know triumphed,
when he had finiſhed his courſe and fought that good
fight againſt them, and ſhall not we? theſe infernal ſpirits
are every where about us: when we are at our beſt
devotions in the Church, one Divell or other ſtands
at our right hand as at Ioſhuahs,
                  Zach. 3. 1. to intice us to ſin, they
have no place in heaven to trouble us when wee are
with CHRIST, and therfore to be with CHRIST is far
better.
               Fiftly, and laſtly, is it not far better to be in heaven
with CHRIST where no ſin is committed,5. Death freeth from ill company. where are
no falſe brethren to betray us, then to live in this
world which is a very peſt-houſe and Sodome full of
filthineſſe, and where perhaps we have not one entire
good friend in this world? This is the condition of
them that are with CHRIST,Pſal. 120. 5. they are freed from that
woe of the Pſalmiſt; VVoe is me that I am constrained to
dwell in Meſech, and from the company of all the

wicked, and ſhall ſee with unſpeakable joy and comfort
the bleſſed Angels, and the ſpirits of all the faithfull
departed, the glorious company of Martyrs
which ſhine now much brighter then the flames
wherewith they were burned, they ſhall ſee the bleſſed
Virgin Mary the mother of our LORD, they ſhall
ſee the moſt ſacred humanity of our Saviour, and his
comely face, fairer then the ſons of men; and above
all this, they ſhall immediatly enjoy the glorious preſence
of GOD, and have a cleare ſight of the divine
face: and conſequently to be with CHRIST is the
beſt of all.
               Firſt,Vſe 1. if to be with CHRIST, is beſt of all, then (by
the law of contraries) to be with the divells in hell is
worſt of all; to be borne in ſin is bad, to live a ſlave of
ſin is worſe, but to die in ſin is worſt of all: to live in a
deep dungeon and priſon, to be tormented with the
ſight of ugly divels, &amp; that with everlaſting fire without
all eaſe, intermiſſion and hope of remedy, what a
wofull thing is it? if ſome have loſt their wits by
meanes of ſome dreadfull ſight, yea if the very ſuſpition
of divels hath cauſed many men to tremble, and
the haires of their heads to ſtand upright, what ſhall
then the terrour and feare of that dark lake be, which
is full of many horrible fiends and dreadfull helliſh
monſters? the appearing of divels in horrible ſhape,
is a far greater evill then is imagined: ſome body ſaith
(he beares the name of Cyrill) that one would chooſe
rather to burne in a hot fire,Cyril de vita B. Hieronymi ad finem Epiſt. B. Hieron. then endure their fearefull
fight. Good LORD that any Chriſtian ſhould live
in the danger hereof, and yet be ſenſeleſſe? what to
be a fire-brand of hell and not to be moved? this ſtupidity

may make our hearts to quake, and our fleſh
to tremble, and aſtoniſh our ſenſes; O then pity your
owne ſoules, pity the ſoules of wretched ſinners, and
be intreated (brethren) by the ſweete mercies of GOD,
by all the ſufferings of our Saviour, by all the joyes
of heaven to ſeeke the LORD while he may be found: if
the danger of ſin was onely to be bond-men and bond-women,
as Queene Eſter ſaid to Ahaſhverus,
                  Eſter 7 4. 
                  I would have
held my tongue, or I would have beene leſſe importunate
with you, but the puniſhment is a thouſand times
greater, and I am at this time GODS Meſſenger, to
bring heavy tidings unto ſinners, and I will tell you
what you ſhall find true by experience hereafter, that
you who are deſpiſers and contemners of GODS Ordinances,
formall profeſſors having a ſhew, not any
power of godlineſſe, malicious perſons, &amp;c. ſhall after
a little time, yea a very little time, cry out, Wo, wo,
wo. Ah what an unfortunate wretch am I, that have
loſt all hopes of heaven! time was when happineſſe
was offered to me, but I (foole that I was) rejected it,
now alas ſhall I weepe and waile for ever. A little City
as I have ſomewhere read, reſiſted Alexander, he
lighted a torch and vowed that if they ſubmitted not
themſelves before the torch was burnt, he would
burne their City into aſhes; our life is like the burning
of a torch; now muſt thou yeeld up thy ſelfe to
be ruled by the LORD, or burne in hell, not as that City
for a ſhort time, but for ever: the everlaſting flames
of hell cannot burne out one ſtaine of ſin out of thy
ſoule: What great benefits didſt thou receive of the
world to allure thee to looſe heaven? and what if
thou hadſt gained much riches and many pleaſures,

and enjoyned them a hundred yeares? all thoſe are
gone, and all are nothing in compariſon of the leaſt
torment which thou there muſt ſuffer; then wilt thou
cry out, oh unhappy pleaſures, oh unfortunate riches,
oh miſerable time wherein I fooliſhly blinded my
ſelfe!Guliel Melmeſ Continuator Bedae, c 3. 
                  Ethelburga wife of King Iva a Saxon King in
this Land, Anno Dom. 709. by a godly policy won her
husbands heart from carnall delights: on a day they
had all outward ſolaces that heart could wiſh, the
roome richly furniſhed with plate, they had ſweet &amp;
pleaſant muſicke and delicate cheere; ſhe cauſed the
ſame place to be ſtrewed with dung, and to be as
loathſome as they could make it, ſhe intreated and
prevailed with the King to repaire thether, &amp; beholding
it, he muſed in his mind of the change, ſhe took
the opportunity, and thus ſaid unto him, where are yeſterdaies
delights, good cheare, and rich furniture?
are not all ſuch things as wind and vanity which paſſeth
away? and with theſe and the like ſpeeches ſhe
drew her husband to a mortified life. Oh that this or
the like conſideration could reduce the lovers of
pleaſures to the love of the ever-living GOD! If the
damned in hell could have but another life in this
world, nay if thoſe which have but ſeene them, or
rather (as I believe in my inſtance) the ſtrong imagination
of ſuch a terrible ſight; I would not wonder
if they proved the greateſt Saints on earth. Venerable
Bede tels (as he thinks) a true ſtory, of one Drithelme
by name,Beda Hiſt or. Aug l. 5. c. 13. (the man lived in Northumberland)
who was raiſed from death to life, and reported wondrous
things which he had heard and ſeene both of
joy and paine, which wrought this great effect (as

there is chronicled) that he utterly deteſted this preſent
life, and abandoned all worldly cares, chaſtiſed
his old impotent body with daily faſting, plunging
himſelfe in Winter ſeaſon into the cold water, ſinging
of Pſalmes and devoutly praying, and when the
beholders ſaid, Brother Drithelme, this is a marvellous
thing that you can poſſibly ſuffer ſuch bitter and
ſharp cold; marvell not (ſaith he) for I have ſeene
places colder then theſe. Let this move thee to ſeeke
the LORD while he may be found, the benefit of this life
you cannot long enjoy, and when it is once paſt, it is
ever paſt, you cannot recover it though you had in
your power a thouſand worlds to give to redeeme it.
               And as for us fellow ſouldiers and deare Chriſtians,
let us hold faſt that goodneſſe which we have,Courage againſt death. let us
play the men, let us be couragious, conſtant, and never
weary of well-doing; let neither divell nor man take
our crownes away from us, never looke to enjoy a
ſtate which is beſt of all, without much oppoſition,
Pharaoh will purſue you with all his power to bring
you back into ſervitude, but do you like ſtout Champions
repell the temptations of the divell, as Gregory
Nyſſen inſtructeth you.Gregor. Nyſſen Sancto Bapti. Oratio. Avant thou curſed and unhappy
creature, I am a dead man, a dead man loves
not bodily pleaſures, a dead man is not caught with
riches, a dead man ſlandereth not, a dead man is no
lier, &amp;c now have I another kinde of life, and another
rule of life then formerly I had. I have learned
to contemne earthly things, and to ſet my mind on
heavenly things.Hier Epiſt. ad Euſtachium. That which Saint Hierom ſpoke of
judgement, we may apply to the joyes of heaven, let
them be painted on the walls of our houſes, and in

every corner thereof, that they may be alwaies before
our eyes: as Captaines do encourage their Souldiers
to fight for their country, lives, profeſſion, &amp;c. ſo doe
I ſay to you brethren, it is the LORD of Hoſts whoſe
battailes you fight, it is your own ſalvation which is
in hazard, your enemies would rob you of grace, and
deprive you of happineſſe; if you give up your weapons
you are undone and firebrands of hell, be valiant
therefore and keepe this treaſure, this pretious treaſure
which CHRIST (ſaith S. Bernard) did judge to
be more pretious then his owne blood;Bernard ſer. 3. de Adventu Dom. if I had kept
the blood of CHRIST which dropped from him as
he hanged on the Croſſe in a glaſſe, how carefull
ſhould I be to keep it? and muſt I not be carefull of
my ſoule which is a pretious treaſure kept in an earthen
veſſell? if thou art poore in thine outward eſtate,
and CHRIST be thy portion, thou art rich enough,
care not for outward poverty, be the LORDS ſervant
now, &amp; thou ſhalt be with CHRIST hereafter, which
is beſt of all. If thou art afflicted in thy body with any
grievous diſeaſe, care not for that; if afflictions work
kindly to mortifie thy ſinne now, thou ſhalt be with
CHRIST hereafter, which is beſt of all; if thou art
baſely eſteemed and perſecuted by wicked men, care
not for that; if this be for righteouſneſſe and out of a
deſire to keep a good conſcience, thou ſhalt be with
CHRIST hereafter, which is beſt of all. If thou haſt
but weake indeavours and a litle ſtrength to goodnes,
if thou ſtriveſt to be better, &amp; art a conquering thy ſin,
be not daunted hereat, thou ſhalt be with CHRIST
hereafter, which is beſt of all. And to reflect upon our
deceaſed brother, now haſt thou happy ſoule that

which thou haſt ſo much longed for; thy death is
the death of all thy defects, &amp; the beginning of everlaſting
happineſſe; thy faithfullneſſe thy integrity, thy
zeale have procured to thee a crowne of glory, now
haſt thou thy fill of happineſſe; O bleſſed art thou
that maiſt ſee the LORD face to face, that thou maiſt
enjoy the happy ſight of thy ſweet Saviour; thou beholdeſt
thouſands of Angels, the Aſſembly of our
firſt Parents, the ſeates of the Apoſtles, the tribunals
of the Prophets, the ſcepters of the Patriarkes, the
crownes of the Martyrs,Baſil. de Bapt. fol. 147. and the praiſes of all juſt men
made perfect, as Saint Baſil ſaith.
            
            
               
                  VER. 24.
                  Nevertheleſſe to abide in the fleſh is more
needfull for you.
               
               Our Apoſtle hath made it knowne unto us,Coherence. why in
reſpect of himſelf he deſired to die, and of this I have
already ſpoken: now doth he in this verſe acquaint
us with the reaſon, why he ſhould deſire to live, becauſe
his life made more for the profit and advantage
of the Philippians, then his death could doe. For making
the way to the maine point which I doe onely
aime at, five things are to be cleared.
               1.Expoſition. What is meant by Fleſh? the mortall body in
which the ſoule dwelleth by a Synecdoche, fleſh being
a conſpicuous part thereof.
               2. What is it to live in the fleſh? it is to live a naturall
life preſerved by naturall meanes, as eating, drinking,
ſleeping, &amp;c. we walke in the fleſh though we
do not warre after the fleſh;2 Cor. 10. 3. yet take him not as if he
meant to abide alwaies in the fleſh, and by a priviledge

to be exempted from death which is appointed
for all men,Phil. 1. 12. but he meanes deliverance from thoſe
preſent bonds, and the continuance of his life for a
time to the furtherance of their faith and joy.
               3. Marke here and in the former verſe that our
Apoſtle ſpeakes as if his ſoule was himſelfe, and as if
his body was no eſſentiall part of man, this is not true
in propriety of ſpeech, and therefore is to be taken
improperly by a Synecdoche, Integri promembro, the
whole is put for a part, &amp; here for a principall part of
Paul, the ſame trope in the like phraſes touching our
Saviour CHRIST,John 3. 13. &amp; John 6. 62. is by a kind of Appropriation called
by Divines the Communication of properties;Acts 20 28.
and theſe arouſefull termes happily invented to cleare
theſe and many obſcure Texts of Scripture touching
our Saviour. But to returne to our Apoſtle: Saint Paul
conſiſteth of fleſh and ſpirit, or ſoule and body, and
yet Saint Paul ſaith, for him to abide in the fleſh is
more profitable for them. When hee died he was
with CHRIST; how? not with his body, but with
his ſoule: Saint Paul is dead and hath ſeene corruption.
How? in body, not in ſoule. Saint Paul in propriety
of ſpeech abideth not in the fleſh, but his ſpirit a
principall part of Paul that is it which during the
terme of his naturall life abideth in the fleſh or body.
               4. More neceſſary] This is not ſpoken ſimply but
comparatively, it was not abſolutely neceſſary for
the Church that S. Paul ſhould live, for GOD could
even then, as after his departure he did, provide other
Inſtructours to build his Church and Houſe, but yet
it was more neceſſary for their profit that he ſhould
live then die.
               
                  
5. For you] But why more neceſſary? was it not
becauſe his appointed time to die was not yet come?
this is true, but perſonall. He mentioneth that which
concernes the Philippians, that they might take notice
how carefull he was for them, and how thankfull
they ought to be to GOD for him.
               My life is more needfull for you, for the furtherance
of your faith and piety.
               
                  Q. Did Saint Paul deſire to live only for the good
of the Philippians?
               
               
                  Sol. He neither ſaith it, nor thinketh it. He ſaith
his life was more needfull for the Philippians, ſo it
was, but he ſaith not only for them.
               
                  Q. Why then doth he only name them?
               
                  Anſw. Becauſe he only writeth to them.Good Shepheards preferre the welfare of their ſheep to their own glory.
               
               Behold a patterne of admirable love in a Shepheard
to the ſheep of CHRIST, preferring their welfare
to his own preſent glory. What Merchant (ſaith
Saint Chryſoſtome) having his veſſell fraught with
rich commodities,Chryſoſt. in locun. if he could ſafely arrive at a haven
would doubt to do ſo, rather then be ſtill toſſed in
the ſea? What Champion would-ſtrive for the maſtery
when he might weare the corruptible crowne?
What Commander when he might reſt at home in
glory after a triumphant victory, would rather ſtill
continue the fight to the hazard of his life and honour?
and yet this is S. Pauls choiſe, wherein he reſembles
a woman that hath husband &amp; children, her husband
is in a far country &amp; ſhe is with her children; ſhe
may go to him whom her ſoule doth chiefely love,
and there ſhe ſhall be abundantly provided for, but
then ſhe muſt leave her children behind her, and what

then will become of you my poore children? it would
be better indeed for me to be with my husband, but
it would be worſe with you then now it is, for your
ſakes therefore it is that I neglect mine owne preſent
honour to do you good. Leaving this diſcourſe, the
words do naturally yeeld us this Doctrine, which I
will handle being pertinent to our preſent purpoſe.
               
                  The life of a faithfull Minister doth more good,
                  Doctrine 5. 
                  and is
more profitable for GODS people then his death:
                  A Miniſters life more profitable then his death. This
doth S. Paul witneſſe of himſelfe, yet from this particular
and worthy example, the grounds and reaſons
of his aſſertion being common, and the ſame in others
that they were in him, the doctrine is generally true
of every faithfull Paſtour, that they doe more good
to the living Saints while they themſelves doe live,
then when they are dead. The Word of GOD in the
mouthes of the Miniſters is not weake, but mighty
in operation, able to caſt downe ſtrong holds and
whatſoever oppoſeth it ſelfe to it: though Satan be
the ſtrong man that keeps poſſeſſion, yet the LORD is
ſtronger and can caſt him out. See the efficacy and
wonderfull working of the Goſpell,Rom. 15. 19. that Saint Paul
could ſay for his part only, that from Ieruſalem round
about unto Illyricum,
                  Mat. 24 27. he had fully preached the Goſpell
of CHRIST, and as the lightening commeth out of
the Eaſt, and ſhineth to the West, and as the Suns going
forth is from the ends of the heaven,
                  Pſal. 19. 6. 
                  and his circuit to the
ends of it, and there is nothing hid from the heat thereof:
ſo in Saint Pauls time the Goſpell was come into all
the knowne parts of the world,Coloſſ. 1. 6. and brought forth
fruit, as it did amongſt the Coloſsians; thus did the Goſpell
ſtrangely ſpread it ſelfe by the preaching of

GODS ſervants, even while Saint Paul himſelfe was
alive, and after the Apoſtles by their Succeſſours as
they were Paſtours; as the ſoule in the body, ſo were
Chriſtians diſperſed in the world, even the Getulians,
Moores, Spaniards, Galls, and the Britans, the
Sarmatians alſo, Germanes and Scythians do believe
in CHRIST, before whom the gates of all Cities are
throwne open, and none are ſhut againſt him, before
whom alſo the iron locks are broken, and the brazen
gates are opened, i. e. the hearts of very many that
were holden faſt locked by the divell, are now unlocked
by the faith of CHRIST,Tertul adverſus Iudaeos. ſaith Tertullian. What
inſtrument was ever too weake to effect GODS will,
if he tooke it in hand? though the Apoſtles preſence
was but weak, and their ſpeech rude, and their words
diſtaſtfull and unwelcome to the world, yet did they
prevaile, or if they had been to preach to Infants and
children not ſeaſoned with inveterate idolatry, it had
beene no great maſtery to have brought them to the
faith of CHRIST, as it was no great glory to the Spaniard,
to vanquiſh the Indians, when Benzo the Italian
reported that he durſt be one of the 25. that would
fight with ten thouſand, nay with twenty thouſand
of that naked people: but the caſe is altered now, for
1. The Apoſtles were but few for number and of no
great reckoning in the world: 2. For the ſame men
to teach a ſtrange doctrine to believe on CHRIST
crucified, and to be ready to lay downe their lives
for him, if they looked to go to heaven. 3. To preach
to the world when many of them did ſeeke after wiſdome
and ſecular Philoſophy,2 Cor. 10. 5. as did the Grecians,
many after ſtate policy and war, as did the Romans,

and all of them trained up in a long continued will-worſhip,
and damnable idolatry of a deepe die, yet
the Goſpell by the preaching of it, as Aarons rod
amongſt the ſerpents of the Magicians devoured
them all, and brought them to acknowledge allegiance
to it; ſurely this ſhould make us cry out, as the
people did upon the proofe that Elias made,2 King. 18. 39. 
                  the
LORD he is GOD, the LORD he is GOD. Now the
LORD doth this great worke by the Miniſtery of living
men, and ſometimes by weake men, that the excellency
of the power may be aſcribed to GOD and
not to man: and thus you ſee in generall the great
profit which accompanies the work of the Preachers
in the plantation and foundation of Churches: let us
conſider ſome particular benefits which redound to
them which are actuall members of a viſible Church;
and they are either 1 in regard of the bad, or 2 in regard
of thoſe that are good, or 3 in regard of all ſorts
both good and bad.
               Firſt,1. I ſay their life is more needfull in regard of
thoſe that are actually as yet in the ſtate of unregeneration,
and that in a double reſpect:
               Firſt, to be a powerfull meanes of converting the
Elect,1. Miniſters convert ſoules. and to bring them to all the degrees of ſalvation:
other profeſſions do aime at the good of this life;
the Phyſician at the health of the body, the Lawyer is
for the right of his Client, but the end of the Miniſtery
alone, is chiefely to ſave mens ſoules; Vocation,
that is by the preaching of the Goſpell;
                  2 Theſſ. 2. 14. Justification another
degree of ſalvation,Rom. 10. 14. that is for CHRIST his ſake
by faith which is given by hearing the Miniſter; Sanctification
another degree of ſalvation in this life, is by

preaching of the Word, in regard of dying to ſin▪ the Miniſter
is as the ſalt of the earth,
                  Mat. 5. 13. in regard of living to
righteouſnes, its the Word of grace by which we are ſanctified.
What had become of Paulus Sergius,
                  2 Cor. 3. 8. of Oneſimus,
of Lydia, and of many Churches if they had not
beene called to GOD by the preaching of S. Paul, who
reſtored thoſe to life, ſaith S. Chryſoſtome, which had
ſixe hundred ulcers by ſin? but what need I inſtance
in particulars; the conſciences of millions converted,
can witneſſe that Miniſters have beene their ſpirituall
fathers, their preaching hath beene the key to open
the Kingdome of Heaven, and they are appointed by
GOD for the gathering of the Saints.
                  Epheſ 4 11.
               
               Secondly,2. Miniſters reſtraine mens corruptions. their life is profitable, if not to convert,
yet to civilize people, and to reſtraine the corruption
of nature; even reaſon and Philoſophy over-ruled
Pythagorus,
                  See Bradward, de cauſa Dei, l. 2. c. 3. by nature the worſt of men, as Philemon
the Aſtrologer conjectured, to conquer his naturall
propenſions to vice, and to become (as his Schollers
thought) the beſt and the moſt worthy man that lived;
much more effectuall ſure is the Word preached to
produce morall vertues, and to enable ſome to doe
morall workes rationally, out of the ſway of right
reaſon, though not obedientially with a pure intention
to obey and glorifie GOD; preaching is a banke to
hinder the inundation of ſinne, and to keepe men in
outward conformity, this keeps calmeneſſe upon the
face of the Church and mankind, which otherwiſe
might degenerate into ſavage brutiſhneſſe. Herod was
better by hearing Iohn, and reformed many things
that were amiſſe, and by their meanes they may have
many graces of the ſpirit, it is the influence of the ſame

Sun which ripeneth both the grape and the crab, it is
the ſame ſpirit alſo which helpeth the wicked in their
morall, and the godly in their ſpirituall workes, thoſe
I ſpeake of may have illumination and a taſte of the
heavenly gift, and may propagate GODS truth to others,2 Chro. 24. 21.
as Ioaſh the King did all the daies of Iehojada
the high Prieſt,2 Chron. 26. 5. and Vzziah in the daies of Zachariah
the Prophet: and who ſees not that the preſence of a
godly man doth bridle the tongues of the wicked
from wicked ſpeeches, though ſore to their griefe,
as Iob ſaith,Iob 29. 8, 9, 10 
                  in my proſperity the young men ſaw me and
hid themſelves, the Princes refrained talke, the Nobles
held their peace, &amp;c. and the ſame is reported of Cato,
that they would forbeare to ſpeake uncomely things
on the ſtage while he was preſent: and if ſwearers
rap out unawares prophane oathes in the preſence of
a grave man, they checke one another, know you
not that ſuch a one heard you? the divell dares not
ſhew himſelfe a divell in his colours in the preſence
of ſuch a reverend man as this our brother was.
               Secondly,2. the life of a Miniſter is more needfull
then his death, in regard of thoſe that are effectually
called.
               Firſt,3. Miniſters mortifie reliques of ſinne. becauſe there is after converſion much corruption
and ſinne in GODS people to be mortified,
whereof they may juſtly complaine as did Saint Paul,
Rom. 7. the beſt Chriſtians are like peeces of gold,
they are too light and muſt have their graines of allowance
to make them currant,Pro. 20. 9. 
                  Who can ſay my heart is
cleane? he propoſeth the point in his armour by way
of demand, making his chalenge to all the world with
his triumphant negative, knowing that no man durſt

ſtep forth, none could juſtly ſay, I am entirely innocent,
I am as good as I ought to be, as good as the holy
Law requireth that I ſhould be. Private helps I
know, as prayer, faſting, meditation, have their force
to abate the ſtrength of ſinne, but yet the lively two
edged ſword, the ſword of the Spirit in the mouthes
of GODS Miniſters, hath the preheminence, that is
the fire to waſt it,
                  Jer. 23. 29. 
                  and the hammer to bruiſe a hard heart.
               Secondly, their Miniſtery is needfull to diſcover
ſins after renovation:4. Min
                        •
                     ſter diſcover ſecret ſins there are ſecret darke corners
in our hearts which are deceitfull, wherein wickedneſſe
doth lurk.Pſal. 19. 12. 
                  Who can tell how often he offends? cleanſe
me from ſecret ſins. If unknowne ſins were in David,
who was a man of an excellent ſpirit, of great underſtanding,
and a ſtrict examiner of his owne heart, can
any man ſay in truth he is free from them?Baſil inſtitutio aſpiran ad vitam perfectam. Saint Baſil
ſaith, it becomes all men to acknowledge that they
are not worthy to ſpeake before the divine Majeſty,
becauſe they are ſinners: we are guilty of many faults
which we know not, in that reſpect we may ſay with
our Apoſtle, I know nothing by my ſelfe, yet am I
not juſtified thereby, that is, I ſin greatly, but I do not
underſtand it. Hence the Prophet ſaith, Who underſtands
his faults? thou wilt confeſſe if thou art wiſe, that
thou art a greater ſinner then other men: ſo Baſil; private
meanes ſuch as are the looking into the law of
liberty,1 Cor. 14. 25. friendly reproofes, and inſtruction, and ſuch
like, are much availeable, yet that which doth moſt
lively diſcover it, is propheſie, that is it which unbowels
corruption, and beſt diſplaies the hidden nakedneſſe
of old Adam,
                  Heb. 4. 12. and which doth exceedingly advance
the honour of the Miniſtery by the praching

of the Goſpell, Angels, yea chiefe Angels, as Principalities
and Powers have learned, what formerly
without ſin they did not know,Epheſ. 3. 10. 
                  the manifold wiſdome
of GOD in the diſpenſation of the vnſearchable riches
of CHRIST to the Gentiles.
               
               Thirdly, many are the ſteppings aſide out of GODS
way,5. Miniſters revoke men into the right way. in regard of actuall ſins even in the moſt ſanctified,
in many things we ſin all. David did ſo, and Peter
did ſo,Iam. 3. 2. and what ſheep of CHRIST doth not ſo?
checks of conſcience, I know, and GODS fatherly
chaſtiſements are good helps to reduce us into the
right way; the one is our boſome remembrancer, and
the other is like to Ionathans arrow, which hath GODS
meſſage in the feathers, yet neither conſcience nor
croſſes have power comparable with CHRIST his
voyce in the preaching of the Word, to procure our
revocation into GODS waies.
               Fourthly, Chriſtians ought to be confirmed in
their gracious eſtate,6. Miniſters confirme grace begun yet whoſe faith is ſo conſtant,
that it admits no wavering? whoſe patience is ſo fixed,
that it admits no ſtaggering? the cleareſt Suns of
the Church have been more or leſſe eclipſed in their
faith, their patience and their piety: of all outward
meanes to make us hold out, preaching is the principall,
that is as goods to pricke men forward that are
under the yoake of CHRIST, that is as ſalt to ſweeten
them and to keep them ſavoury; it is with our
hearts as with our ſoile, which is not like the Land of
Canaan,
                  Mat. 5. 13. 
                  the former raine after ſeeds time at the fall of
the leafe, and the latter raine at the ſpring, to ripen the
fruit ſufficed, inſomuch that Saint Hierome living in
Canaan, rarely ſaw raine there in Iune and Iuly,
                  Hiero in Amos. but

our ſoile though now well watered, yet except it be
well refreſhed and often comforted with drops of
raine from heaven, will parch and wither.
               Laſtly, to name no more,7. Miniſters increaſe grace. they are notable meanes
to increaſe the vigour and lively-hood of ſaving graces;
they are bellowes to increaſe the flame, as a ſweet
raine to make the LORDS inheritance to thrive in
goodneſſe, they are as milke and wine, and meate to
make the children of GOD to ſhoote up to their juſt
ſtature, and as a ſtrong gale of wind to carry their veſſels
to the deſired haven,Hiero. ad Demetrium. as Hierom ſaith, Pugilum fortitudo
clamoribus incitatur, though Champions fight
valiantly, yet their courage is enflamed by the acclamations
of the by-ſtanders, ſo is it with you; when
we pray, exhort, beſeech that that which you doe
well, you do it continually, more ſincerely and zealouſly,
What good ſoule by experience findeth not
graces excited, good motions kindled, holy reſolutions
furthered and gracious operations intended by a
profitable Miniſter?
               The third Reaſon why the life of a godly Miniſter
is more profitable,Reaſon 3. is in regard of all both good and
bad,Miniſters cauſe bleſſings. as touching the continuance of bleſſings. For
he is as Eliſha ſaid of Elias,
                  1 Kings 2. 12. and King Ioaſh of Eliſha,
the chariots and the horſemen of Iſrael;
                  2 Kings 13. 14 he fights while
he lives, and bends his forces againſt all manner of
ſins,Exod. 32. 25. which make a people naked and expoſe them to
the wrath of GOD,Num. 16. 47. 
                  he ſtands in the breach betwixt the
living and the dead, to avert the plague, and to make an
atonement for the people, as Aaron did: and doubtleſſe
the man of GOD muſt be a good part of thoſe
righteous ones for whoſe ſake the Sun is darkened,

and that the Moone gives her light, that the frame of
heaven and earth continues as we ſee this day, as Iuſtin
Martyr ſheweth;Iuſtin Martyr Apog. 1. pro Chriſtian
                        •
                     . they are a good part of thoſe
impregnable bulwarkes againſt all enemies, as Theodoret
ſhewes in a memorable example when Conſtantine
the great was dead. Sapores the King of Perſia did
ſtrongly beſiege Niſibis;
                  Theod Sanctor. Patrum hiſtoria Iacobus. there was a holy man of
GOD, Iacobus by name in that City, the Citizens beſeech
him that he would ſhew himſelf upon the walls
of the City, and pray againſt the enemies, which he
did, and the LORD ſent a cloud of flies and gnats amongſt
the beſiegers, which diſperſed them. Behold
a whole City ſaved by the meanes of one religious
man, and hence alſo it is a ſigne of GODS wrath and
heavy diſpleaſure, and a forerunner of farther judgements,
to have excellent inſtruments of GOD taken
away,Eſay 3. 2. and therefore the LORD purpoſing to viſit the
Jewes for their iniquities,Eſay 57. 1. threatens to take away from
them the Judge and the Prophet; and the LORD
uſeth as himſelfe ſpeaketh,Cum aliquis (vul
                        •
                     u &amp; ſpecie gravitatis reverendus) decidit afficior, quia deſtituitur grex juvenum muro ſenili: de
                     
                        •
                     ique periturae urbis aut malorum imminentium vel futura labis hoc primum indicium eſt, &amp;c. S. Amb. de Cain &amp; Abel, l. 2 c 3. 
                  To take away the righteous,
that their eyes may not behold the evil to come, though this
be little laid to heart as there is ſaid, When we ſee a
gardiner take away the wall and fence, plucke up the
choiſeſt plants, take away the ornaments and beauty
of it, and lay it open for the beaſts to enter, we may
ſuppoſe he intendeth not to continue, but to deface
his garden; ſo when we ſee the evident footſteps of
GODS wrath, and the fire of his jealouſie (as it were)
breaking out by the ſmoake; beginning to appeare
by taking away profitable men as plants of his garden,
which his owne right hand hath planted, we
muſt lay it to our hearts, as a probable token preceding

a heavy judgement; by which it doth appeare,
that the wicked do enjoy temporall bleſſings by the
life and prayers of a good Miniſter.
               
                  Vſe 1.Vſe 1. Is of Confutation to the Church of Rome,
which do maintaine the invocations of Saints departed,Againſt invocation of Saints
and ſay that their favour with GOD (which we
deny not) is improved, and that their affectionate
notice of the peoples neceſſities, continues greater
after death then when they were alive; if ſo, the ſpeedy
diſſolution of Saint Paul, had beene as expedient
for the Churches which he had planted, as for himſelfe,
for ſo (to uſe their owne language) they might
have had a new Patron in the Court of Heaven, and it
would be expedient for the benefit of the Church
militant, that the godlieſt Miniſters ſhould die the
ſooneſt and the faſteſt, for ſo they may become more
then Apoſtles, able to heare the prayers and undertake
the Patronage of many thouſands with whom
they had no commerce while they lived; but it was
never profitable for the Church to be deprived of the
godly Paſtours bodily preſence in this reſpect;Ioh. 14 13. &amp; 16. 23. this
is to rob CHRIST of his prerogative,Rom. 8. 34. ſitting at the
right hand of his Father; in the Tabernacle of this
world, as was in the firſt Tabernacle, we may find
many Prieſts to imploy as Agents for us with GOD,Heb. 9. 6, 7, &amp;c.
but in the Sanctum Sanctorum, the ſecond Tabernacle,
there is but one Agent who hath Royall commiſſion
to deale betwixt GOD and men.Rollok on Col. fol. 17 1 lin. 9. I dare be
bold to ſay, that if the Angels and Saints would take
the honour that the Pope and his Clergy would give
them, they ſhould all go to hell and leave the joyes
which they now have.
               
                  
This point ſerves for the reproofe of ſuch perſons,
which feele no ſorrow for the loſſe of the chiefe
ſtayes of the Church,2. Loſſe of Miniſters not regarded by many. which are like a Dove without
a heart,Hoſ. 7. 11. and like the drunkards are ſtriken and yet
feele nothing,Pro. 13. 35. &amp; Ier. 5. 3. which looſe an eye and are ſenſeleſſe
in this loſſe, which have their maſter-pieces and poſts
that hold up their houſe removed, and yet lay it not
to heart, which have the pawnes of their peace, and
the pledges of their poſterity taken from them, and
regard it not: theſe mens affections had need of the
ſpurre, which have ſtony hearts, and bowels of braſſe,
which are not penſive at all for the loſſe of a deare
brother, which perhaps as Saint Auſten complaines,
can weep when he read the ſtory of Dido and of Troy,
and ſuch fabulous reports, but he could not do ſo for
the miſeries of GODS Church, theſe men are as far
from ſympathy towards the miſeries of GODS people,
as from an inward feeling of the tender mercies
of GOD to their own ſoules; the harder the heart is,
the worſe it is, and the worſt of all is hardeſt to
mourne for ſo great a loſſe.
               Thirdly, and much more doth this Doctrine condemne
their practiſe,3. Hatred of powerfull Miniſters blamed. that if their Paſtour be a faithfull
teacher, one that keepes nothing backe from
them,Acts 20. 27. but delivers unto them the whole counſell of GOD,
as Paul did to the Epheſians; if he denounceth the
judgement of the LORD againſt ſinners, if he layeth
the axe to the roote of the tree, and launceth their
feſtered ſores to the very bottome, they do even for
their worke ſake, eſteeme them as Ahab did Micaiah
to be their enemy, and the more he loveth
them, the leſſe he is beloved of them, and doe wiſh

from their hearts that hee might not live amongſt
them, but do labour to make him weary of his life by
vexing him, caſting many times the very name of
a Prieſt, as a terme of reproach upon his face; the
abundance of this Manna and bread from Heaven,
makes them to loath it and the Meſſenger that brings
it. The reaſons of both: 1. Becauſe ſuch men feele
not their ſin nor their miſery for ſin. 2. Nor taſt the
comfort, ſweetneſſe and power of grace. 3. Nor doe
conſider that Presbyters are GODS hands to conveigh
graces to them; hence do theſe fellowes ſcorne
them in their hearts, and ſo have as it were a brand ſet
upon them to be 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Atheiſts, irreligious perſons
and deſpiſers of CHRIST,Ignat. Epiſt. ad Trallian. as that ancient and holy
Father Ignatius phraſeth them.
               Fourthly, this conſideration that the life of a good
Paſtour is more profitable then his death,4. The death of good Miniſters to be lamented. ſhould put
us in mind of a duty to mourne and grieve for the departure
of an eminent member in the Church: GOD is
not like to the Perſian Kings,Eſter 4 2. 
                  in whoſe preſence no mourners
were ſuffered to come, but godly mourners are alwaies
welcome to GOD. See the practiſe of this duty
but in one example,Acts 8. 2. 
                  the devout men that buried Stephen
made great lamentation over him, though Stephen was a
Martyr, and which was his honour, the firſt Martyr
too, and if I well remember, a Martyr ſaith, if there be
any way to heaven on horſebacke, it is by Martyrdome;
                  Bradford.
yet did devout men make great lamentation over Stephen.
See the bowels of men indued with GODS Spirit,
they are full of affection, full of tenderneſſe, ſo
that the ſtreames thereof do overflow the banks; and
good reaſon, they have fewer friends remaining,

and fewer helpers, fewer prayers are made unto
GOD, and fewer remaine to whom they may doe
good, and from whom they may receive good. And
according to this preſent occaſion let us practiſe a
duty which we owe in regard of our deceaſed brother,
even to mourne: away with that Stoicall opinion
which allowes not their wiſe man to ſigh or
change countenance at any croſſe accident, this neither
ſorts with religion nor reaſon. No, we have
cauſe all of us to mourne, not you only of this Towne,
but your neighbours round about you, nay this
whole Country; and ſay as Eliſha to Elija, my father,
my father, the Chariots and the horſemen of Iſrael;
he by his faſtings, often and extraordinary prayers,
often hath ſtood in the gap, and mightily wraſtled
with the LORD to keep away judgements; and like
another Elijah hath left his mantle, or Dorcas her garments
for the poore, ſome godly works, the fruits of
a ſanctified heart and braine behind him, and many
no doubt are ſtrangled in the wombe by his death
which ſhall never ſee light.
               Touching the beginning of his ſtudies,Maſter Boultons life. they were
not ſo commendable as could have beene wiſhed, he
was tainted by his Schoolemaſter in his youth, and
continued a Papiſt in heart at Oxford certaine yeeres,
and reſolved with oneSometimes a Cantabrigian and ſtudent in Chriſts Colledge. 
                  Anderton his ſchoole-fellow,
to have gone to the Seminaries beyond the ſea: but
GOD happily croſſed that deſigne, and effectually
calling him to the ſight of his ſins, and the light of
his truth, drew good out of that evill, and taught him
ſo much the more to deteſt Popery, and to diſcover
hypocriſie and diſſimulation in GODS worſhip and

in ordinary converſation above the ordinarie ſtraine
of Writers.
               How induſtrious a ſtudent he was in the Univerſity,
his many note bookes left behind him will beare
witneſſe, and how well reputed he was for his learning,
as his other exerciſes, ſo his publike diſputations
before King JAMES will teſtifie.
               But Learning is nothing, Induſtry is nothing to be
praiſed before GOD without grace; grace hath the
preheminence and gives the luſter to all the reſt; the
LORD enriched his heart with a great meaſure of
grace, hence is it that his life was unſtained and without
reproofe; though he was not freed from infirmities,
yet he was from crimes.
               Hence it was that he was ſo laborious in his Miniſtery,
a true ſtudent he was all his daies, as appeares
by his library though great, yet very few bookes in
it which were not read over and noted in the margent,
and he attained that high ſtraine of grave eloquence,
familiar to him, ſcarce imitable by any others;
you were twiſe a weeke ordinarily fed with
Sermons and Catechiſmes, and with the Expoſition
of Scripture on Holy daies which would have beene
acceptable, wholeſome foode I am ſure, to the moſt
learned auditory of the Land.
               And though he was ſo great a Clerke, and ſo famous,
yet was not he ambitious nor ſought great
matters for himſelfe, and he doth beſeech an honourable
Knight,Epiſtle Dedicatory to Sir Robert Carre.
                   to whom he dedicated his laſt booke,
and all others in him to doe him that favour, nay that
right, nay that honour, not to conceive that he had a
thought that way.
               
                  
His heart was ſet on the right object, and the bent
of his ſtudy was for matter of Sanctification, both
of himſelfe and of his hearers,Note. for himſelfe he could
profeſſe (and O that all Prieſts and Paſtors could do
the like!) he did I ſay profeſſe to his comfort on his
death bed, that he never taught any godly point, but
he firſt wrought it on his owne heart; towards others
he was a powerfull inſtrument to batter the kingdome
of the divell, he was a downe-right Preacher and ſpared
no ſins, he made many an unconverted ſinner to
quake and to tremble at his diſcourſes, as Felix did at
Pauls, and caſt them into a ſtrong fit of legall humiliation;
he was an inſtrument to pull many captives
out of Satans ſnares, many of you can ſtep forth and
ſay he was my ſpirituall father; he had a ſearching
Miniſtery to diſcover the hidden abominations of
ſin, to ſtrengthen and increaſe the graces of thoſe
that did ſtand, to quicken thoſe that languiſhed; many
have cauſe to bleſſe GOD for him,Philemon 19. and do owe even
themſelves unto him, as Philemon did to Paul.
               
               From this ſpectacle before our eyes all of us may
learne ſomething for our imitation: doth any one
prophane GODS ordinances by a diſſembled religion?
let him forſake it, and flie from it as from a ſerpent,
(for, I ſpeake to the glory of GODS mercy, turning
his face from Babylon to Ieruſalem) ſo did our deceaſed
brother; doth any one walk before GOD with
an upright heart, let him hold out to the end, run his
race and finiſh his courſe both in health and ſickneſſe,
for ſo did our deceaſed brother.
               A great man, great in worth is fallen in our Iſrael,
&amp; there will be a great loſſe of him, his wife ſhall find

the loſſe of a gracious husband; his children ſhall find
the loſſe of a gracious father; his ſheep ſhall find the
loſſe of a gracious ſhepheard, we of the Miniſtery ſhall
find the loſſe of a grave, learned, &amp; a gracious brother;
the devout Chriſtian that deſires to have all his ſinnes
unbowelled and diſcovered, ſhall find the loſſe of a
gracious ſoule-ſearching Miniſter, he that would
have rules to avoid particular ſins, and to make progreſſe
in all vertues, ſhall find the loſſe of a copious
and experienced directour; he that is wounded in
conſcience ſhall find the loſſe of a skilfull Surgeon,
who in that art was one of a thouſand to reſtore righteouſneſſe;
the vertuous, rich, and humble poore
Chriſtians that feared GOD, ſhall find the loſſe of a
loving friend and a gracious ſupporter, thoſe that are
in wants and truly religious, ſhall find (to my knowledge)
the loſſe of a liberall reliever and comforter,
nay poore condemned Chriſtians ſhall find the loſſe
of a charitable inſtructour: and what ſhall I ſay
more? the whole Land ſhall find the loſſe of a zealous
pillar and of a powerfull prevailer with GOD for the
continuance of our happineſſe: ſo that all had cauſe to
pray not as the dreſſer of the barren fig-tree, but as
for a fruitfull tree,Luke 13. 8. LORD let it ſtand one yeare, nay many
yeares longer; but the greater our loſſe is of him,
the greater is the gaine unto himſelfe, and as he is
crowned with glory in heaven, ſo his remembrance to
many of us, will be like that of Ioſias to the Jewes, It is
ſweet as honie in all mouthes,
                  Eccleſ. 49. 1. 
                  and as muſicke at a banquet
of wine.
                  
                     Ʋſes to be made of the death of Miniſters.
               
               This conſideration may be of good uſe for GODS
people; Firſt that they would ſet a high price on good

Miniſters, and afford them a ſingular meaſure of love as
to ſpirituall fathers,Miniſters to be highly prized. GOD honouring them ſo highly,
as joyning them with himſelfe as co-workers in the regeneration
and ſalvation of his people;1 Theſſ. 5. 12, 13. againſt whom
Satan and his inſtruments are moſt enraged:1 Cor 3. 9. towards
ſuch let the affections of GODS people be moſt enflamed;
though their perſons may be contemptible, yet
in regard of their high calling as they are CHRISTS
Ambaſſadours they are venerable, they are deare unto
GOD; you cannot contemne nor reverence them,
but this reacheth unto heaven, and in the laſt reſolution
reflects on CHRIST himſelfe,Luke 10. 16. CHRIST is intereſſed
both in the contempt and in the reſpect you
ſhew towards them.
               Secondly, it ſhould teach them another duty, to
pray heartily to GOD for them,2. Miniſters to be prayed for. that GOD would
give his Vrim and his Thummim to his holy ones; this
was the prayer of Moſes for the Tribe of Levi:
                  Deut. 33. 8. think
of them as Saint Iames ſaid of Elias,
                  Iam. 5. 17. 
                  That they are men
ſubject to like paſsions that you are, conceive us not to be
of. Laodicean temper,Revel 3. 17. 
                  to ſtand in need of nothing; we are
no better, nor ſo good as Saint Paul, and yet good
Saint Paul is frequent in his exhortations to the people
to pray for him; brethren we had need of your
prayers, none more need then we: ſomething it is
that Saint Paul in his prayer for the Churches, uſeth
this forme, Grace be unto you and peace, but when he
writes to Timothy and to Titus, ſeparated for the ſervice
of GOD, he prayes for Grace, Mercy, and Peace,
for them. They in ſpeciall manner it ſeemes do ſtand
in need of GODS mercy; pray for ſuch then, and for
their continuance, that they may live, be guides to

the blind, lights to them that ſit in darkeneſſe, Inſtructors
of the ignorant, and by a godly life examples
to the flocke over which the LORD hath made them
Over-ſeers.
               Get now all the good you can from profitable
Miniſters while you enjoy them,3. All the good that may be to be reaped from Miniſters. heare them every
LORDS day, as though it was the laſt day you ſhould
heare them; whiles the yeares of plenty laſt, ſtore
up with good Ioſeph proviſion which may preſerve
your lives if a dearth ſhould come; like the ſhel-fiſh,
ſucke in that moiſture while you are in the waters,
which may preſerve you on the dry land. When Nilus
over-flowed the bankes, the Egyptians were ſo
wiſe, to dig pits to retaine the water to ſerve their
turne, when the water of the river returned into its
channell. Doe thou ſo for thy ſoule in regard of the
waters of life, ſtore now thy ſelfe with the bread of
heaven, leaſt thou finde to thy griefe the greatneſſe
of a benefit in the loſſe thereof: unwiſe they are that
know not the true worth of bleſſings but by wanting
them, which wiſemen had rather learne by keeping
them.Euſeb. Eccl Hiſt. l. 5. c. 18. O carry thy ſelfe towards them as Saint Irenaeus
did towards that bleſſed Martyr Polycarpus, many
yeares after he did keep freſh in memory the diſputations
of Polycarpus, his goings out, and commings
in, his manner of life, the ſhape of his body, his Sermons
to the people, how he converſed with Saint
Iohn the Apoſtle, and with others which ſaw the
LORD, he could recite what he reported as ſpoken
by them, &amp;c. ſuch a deepe impreſſion in his ſoule
there was left many yeares after Polycarpe was a glorious
Saint in heaven; and I beleeve that this our brothers

unaffected gravity, his wiſe carriage, and many
of his gracious ſpeeches are written with the pen of
an adamant in ſome Chriſtians which will be legible
in them ſo long as they live.
               Laſtly, let us of the Clergie while we live, do all
the good we can,4. Doe good while the day laſt. and put forth our ſelves with all laboriouſneſſe
before the day of harveſt;1 Cor. 12. 7. the gifts of the
Spirit are given to profit withall, Gods gives theſe
miniſteriall talents to this end; and let us imploy our
talents to attaine this end, while we continue in this
Tabernacle, let us not ceaſe to put men in mind of
their duty,2 Pet. 1. 12, 19 as Saint Peter profeſſed he would doe; let
us pity the caſe of all diſobedient perſons: let other
fiſhers, if they thinke good, fiſh for riches, or for
vaine applauſes; but let our chiefe aime be to deliver
a ſinner from the pit of deſtruction, and rather to
ſpeake five words in compaſſion to ſave a ſoule, then
five thouſand for any ſiniſter end whatſoever: the
ſoule of the pooreſt man is very pretious, and the loſſe
of it cannot be redeemed with a world, it is ſinne that
looſeth the ſoule. O how unhappy are all ſinners, how
miſerable! which would make GODS ſervants ſhed
rivers of teares if they thought adviſedly thereof,
and mourne over them as our Saviour did over Ieruſalem,
                  Luke 19 41.
when he beheld their preſent ſecurity, and
foreſaw their future ruine,Mat. 23. 
                  If thou hadst knowne theſe
things that concerne thy peace, how happy hadſt thou
then beene? let us then be faithfull and laborious,
and ſo much the rather now ought we to be laborious,
to make up this breach for the loſſe of our
brother, if GOD enables us; the LORD himſelfe is the
heavenly teacher of this leſſon by a juſt proportion

in a like caſe. Moſes my ſervant is dead, now
therefore ariſe Ioſhuah—be ſtrong and of a good courage;
                  Ioſh. 1. 2, 6.
this our brother GODS ſervant is dead, let us therefore
who doe by the goodneſſe of GOD remaine yet
alive in a better degree then formerly, be faithfull in
our callings, let us be more induſtrious in reading, in
meditating, in conſcionable preaching, and in a holy
walking in the feare of GOD, that ſo we may repaire
what we may our great loſſe by the death of
him; and truly we have great encouragements ſo to
do:Ioſh. 1. 5. for as GOD was with Moſes, and promiſed to be
with Ioſhuah, ſo will the ſame GOD, if we continue ſo
doing, make the ſame word good unto us, he will be
with us, He will never leave us nor forſake us; and when
this ſhort uncertaine,Heb. 13. 5. vaine and wretched life is ended,
we are already aſſured, that every one of us ſhall
heare to our everlaſting comfort, that bleſſed ſentence,
Well done thou good and faithfull ſervant, thou
haſt beene faithfull over a few things,
                  Mat. 26. 23. 
                  I will make
thee ruler over many things: enter thou
into the joy of thy LORD. Which he
for his mercy ſake grant unto
us all, Amen.
               
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

