
   
      
         
            The right way to goe to worke: or, a sermon seasonable and vsefull in these stirring times containing matter of direction in all actions, and presenting meanes of supportation vnder the weight either of publike or priuate, dangerous or difficult seruices and employments. Vpon Proverbs 16. 3.
            Balmford, Samuel, d. 1659?
         
         
            
               1623
            
         
         Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00541
            STC 1068
            ESTC S101518
            99837330
            99837330
            1646
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00541)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1646)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 820:08)
         
         
            
               
                  The right way to goe to worke: or, a sermon seasonable and vsefull in these stirring times containing matter of direction in all actions, and presenting meanes of supportation vnder the weight either of publike or priuate, dangerous or difficult seruices and employments. Vpon Proverbs 16. 3.
                  Balmford, Samuel, d. 1659?
               
               [8], 52 p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Haviland for William Bladen, and are to be sold at the great north doore of Pauls,
                  London :
                  1623.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: S.B., i.e. Samuel Balmford.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-07
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               The right way to goe to Worke: OR, A SERMON SEASONABLE AND VSEFVLL IN theſe Stirring Times: Containing matter of direction in all Actions, AND Preſenting meanes of ſupportation vnder the weight either of publike or priuate, dangerous or difficult ſeruices and employments. Vpon PROVERBS 16.3.
            
               
                  PSAL. 57.1, 2.
               
               In the ſhadow of thy wings (O God) will I make my refuge, vntill theſe calamities be ouerpaſt. I will cry vnto God moſt high, vnto God that performeth all things for me.
            
            
            LONDON, Printed by Iohn Haviland for William Bladen, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the great North doore of PAVLS. 1623.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, THE MASTER, WARDENS, and ASSISTANTS, of the Company of Carpenters in London, with others his late Bountifull BENEFACTORS.
            
               
                  SOlomon giueth this prudent aduice to all builders:
                  Prou. 24 27▪
                
               Prepare thy worke without, and make it fit for thy ſelfe in the field, and afterward build thine houſe. To mee therefore, amongſt others, as to one hauing manumiſſion and freedome of that Society, is it directed. But how is it by mee followed? Now that you ſee me building me thinks I heare you queſtioning, whether my worke be well prepared, and fitted before

hand? Yea, or I my ſelfe well prepared, and fitted for this worke? Firſt, for my ſelfe, I anſwer (and ſhould ſo continue anſwering yet a while, were I left to my ſelfe) as Plutarch reporteth Pericles and Demoſthenes vſed to doe in ſleighter caſes, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , I am not ready; for if they (ſo eloquent) thought themſelues vnready to ſpeake in any weighty matters, how then can I (ſo rude) with modeſty be ſo ready to ſpeake (and in print too) about more weighty matters than any whereof they could ſpeake? Againe, for my prouiſion before hand, I anſwer as the wiſe Virgins did, by way of confeſſion,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , There will not be enough for vs and you. For if they (ſo prudent) feared they had not oyle in ſuch plenty as they might gratifie others with a portion, how then can I (ſo ignorant) with humility thinke, I haue ſuch ſtore of ſtuffe by me, as to proffer matter of light vnto others, already better furniſhed? If I haue prepared any worke without, (inter ſyluas Academiae, in the field, I meane of the Vniuerſitie) ſurely I haue fitted it, as yet, onely for my ſelfe (according to the letter

of that aduice) and not to build an houſe in the City, or (as it were) in the common roade, obuious to the eies of all paſſengers. But you may quickly reply, If your priuy wants of preparation be ſuch, why take you this publike way of edification? I wil tell you ingenuouſly how the caſe ſtands with me. My reuerend father deſirous of ſome triall of my Theologie, required mee to make this Diſcourſe, and when hee had heard it, was as deſirous that your Worſhips, and other my worthy Benefactors might bee partakers thereof, in token of thankfulneſſe for your exhibition to me, whiles I was at Cambridge; and this deſire cooled not preſently, but continued with inſtant importunity, and encreaſed out of diuers conſiderations of gratefull equity. Now how could I croſſe him whoſe deſires are commands? Or what could I oppoſe againſt his reaſonable perſwaſions? I might haue ſaid ſome I feare will ſay) that this ſeemes not to bee the right way to goe to worke, to fall into the Preſſe as ſoone as to ſtand in the Pulpit. Might I haue ſaid thus? Nay, I did ſay ſo, &amp; ſo long withſtood his pleaſure, till I perceiued

the gathering clouds of his diſcontent. But then I yeelded, (though by yeelding I runne my ſelfe vpon the pikes of many ſharpe cenſures) calling to minde that of the Poet,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                
               In vitium ducit culpae fuga: by ſhunning the fault of Vaine glory, I muſt needs fall on the vice of diſobedience: and being confident that (what euer others thinke or ſpeake) yee will conceiue (as the truth is) that my willingneſſe to doe my duty, ouercame much vnwillingneſſe to be in print. Wherefore (Right Worſhipfull) in imitation of my Reuerend Father, who many yeares ſince, dedicated a Catechiſme to the Company, out of like reſpects, I here preſent you with this poore modell, my firſt in this kinde, wiſhing it were worthy to be an encouragement vnto that pious charity which ye not only extended to me, but to my Father before me, and to others with mee, and will (I doubt not) to many after mee; That ſo ye may helpe to traine vp ſuch as may be able not onely to ſhew you the right way, but alſo to point out to you the right worke, and to comfort and ſtrengthen you in it, till yee receiue the glorious

reward of it. But in meane time, how doe I ſhew the way? I confeſſe I haue not reared ſo faire a ſtructure, as the large foundation would haue borne vp, yet ſhall you finde (I hope) firmneſſe ioyned with plaineneſſe in this little Frame. Which plainneſſe I vſe, both to ſhew what I am, (a Carpenter, not a Caruer,) and what I ſhould be too in this kinde of building; ſubſcribing to Cyprians iudgement, as conſonant to Gods will, which is to this effect, In iudic
                     ••
                  s in concione pro roſtr
                     ••
                   
                  
                     •
                  
                  pulenta facundi
                     •
                   volubili ambitu
                     ••
                   iactetu
                     •
                  
                  ▪ cum de Dumino Deo vox eſt, vocis para ſynceritas non eloquentiae veribus nit
                     •
                  t
                     ••
                   ad fidei argumenta ſed rebus, &amp;c. 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  1. ep. ad Donatu
                     •
                  . 
               Volubility of eloquence is requiſite in legall pleadings, and ciuill orations; but in ſpeeches concerning God and his matters, it becommeth vs to vſe onely purity of words with ſimplicity of truth, as moſt powerfull to beget faith. His minde and meaning will bee more fully exemplified in the following diſcourſe; which I leaue to your fauourable conſtruction, and kinde acceptation: your ſelues alſo to Gods more abundant retribution, my ſelfe euer remaining,
            
               Your Worſhips in all gratefull Obſeruance, S. B.
               
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE RIGHT WAY to goe to VVorke.
            
               
                  PROVERBS 16.3.
               
               
                  Commit thy workes vnto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſhed.
               
            
            
               THeſe words as they proceed out of the mouth of the wiſe man, ſo they come vnto vs clad in the habit (as it were) of a graue aduice, or counſell; which, to the beſt of mine apprehenſion, ſuteth with all circumſtances. I need not tell you the conueniencie betweene this place, and my Text. Is not this the houſe of God? are not his Oracles heere vnfolded? are wee not heere made acquainted with his Will? Now where elſe ſhould we receiue direction for our proceedings than where wee meet with reſolution for our enterpriſes? where

ſhould we make that reſignation (which my Text importeth) but where we receiued our Commiſsion? For the time, ſurely, as it cannot but bee alwayes vſefull to thoſe that are doing, and deſirous to ſpeed in their doings: ſo, more eſpecially at this time when we haue ſo great cauſe to commit the common publique affaires of the Churches of God (whoſe actions, and agitations are, in ſome ſort, our owne) and all their deſignes in behalfe of the Goſpell, vnto the Lord. But to come nearer. When can wee more ſeaſonably learne than when we are preſently to practiſe? And when haue we more inſtant need to practiſe, and follow this counſell in my Text than when we are about ſo ſacred a buſineſſe? If euer, Beloued, we commit our worke vnto the Lord, let vs now when we are conuerſant in the Lords worke. As for Perſons, I hope heere are none but will yeeld to the neceſſity of this dutie. Who hath not this ſpeech commonly in his mouth? By Gods helpe I will doe this or that; Thereby acknowledging (as there is cauſe) a diſability to doe any thing without Gods helpe. How much more aſſiſtance then, need wee to craue of God in theſe matters? For which (ſaith the Apoſtle) who is ſufficient? 2. Cor. 2.16. We ſee then all of vs, the ſpeaker, eſpecially, who is now to enter vpon ſo waighty an employment, how much it ſtands vs vpon to commit our ſeuerall workes vnto the Lord, that our thoughts may bee eſtabliſhed. But leſt my preface ſhould ſeeme to vſurpe Application before Doctrine be deliuered, I draw toward my Text.
            
            For the explication of the words, it is not requiſite

heere, as in other places of Scripture, to haue recourſe vnto the context, and to conſider the dependance vpon former, or the coherence with following verſes; For that part of the will and wiſdome of God which is reuealed in this booke, is laid downe for the moſt part (eſpecially from the tenth chapter to the end) in ſentences perfit, and entire, there being no continued ſeries or proceſſe of matter cloſely hanging together, but each axiome abſolute in it ſelfe, and independent. So that theſe Prouerbs may be not vnfitly compared,
                  Peret▪
                   id eſt 
                     〈…〉
                  
                me thinkes to thoſe 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                thoſe ſingle grapes (according to the Hebrewes expoſition Leuit. 19.10.) which were not to be gathered and impropriated by the owners, but left in common for the poore. They are, firſt, as grapes that pleaſant and heart-chearing fruit, and therefore called mingled wine, Prou. 9.5. and ſaid to be life to thoſe that finde them, and health to all their fleſh, Prouerb. 4.22. Then they are ſingle grapes (which is to our purpoſe) in that they are not ioyned one vpon another in ſenſe, but diſſeuered, whilſt other parts of Scripture are like cluſters of grapes compacted together, and linked in Logicall argument. But if any will be curious to ſearch out a dependency of theſe words vpon the former, ſomewhat may be ſaid according to the opinion of ſome judicious, who hold this verſe to be an inſtruction, or document inferred, and deduced from both the former verſes, as from arguments vrging, and preſſing it.
            In the firſt verſe, Solomon tels vs that the preparations of the heart are in man, but the anſwere of

the tongue is from the Lord, that is, Howſoeuer man hath powers of minde to premeditate, and conſult, yet hee cannot expreſſe what hee hath thought without Gods direction and aſſiſtance. Whence the wiſeman concludeth; If we cannot ſo much as vtter with our tongues what we haue premeditated, without Gods aide, then wee ought to commit our more weighty workes vnto the Lord: But we cannot doe the former; Ergo &amp;c. The argument is thus drawne from the leſſe to the greater: otherwiſe it may be thus framed, taking in our ſpeeches into the number of our workes (as they may well be:) If all our actions, euen the leaſt, as our ſpeeches, be from God, then are they to be committed to God; but they are from God: Ergo. So we ſee how this third verſe hangs vpon the firſt. In the ſecond verſe his meaning (I take it) is this, that howſoeuer we are naturally ſo ready to flatter and ſooth vp our ſelues in our owne doings, that wee imagine all to be right, and as it ſhould bee, which we goe about, eſpecially if it haue but a ſpice or appearance of good in it: Yet God is not alwayes pleaſed with that wherein we ſo pleaſe our ſelues; he many times either allowes not of the matter, or manner of thoſe performances which wee ſo applaud, and magnifie: why? Becauſe he lookes not onely on the outſide of the action, but takes notice out of what grounds we doe it, and vnto what ends, weighing and diſcerning the ſecret working of our ſpirits. Heereupon he inferrs in my Text, that becauſe God doth ſo, therefore we ſhould commit our workes vnto him, that is, lay them to the rule of

his word, for the approbation and warrant of them, and then ſo do them as we may confidently put our ſelues, and our manner of performing them to Gods ſcanning, and judgement: Thus working vpon a ſure ground wee ſhall haue them eſtabliſhed. And ſo I come to the words read.
            The parts whereof appeare at the firſt view to bee two, and but two; hauing only one terme of connexion [And] The firſt we may either call A counſell and aduice (as I ſaid in the beginning:) and the ſecond anſwerably, A promiſe or ſucceſſe in following it: Or elſe we may conceiue the latter to be an end propoſed by euery man to himſelfe; and the former as the way and meanes by which it may be attained vnto. Of theſe as they lye in order. For our better proceeding, the words are to bee explained before any point be obſerued; and the only word which needeth opening is [Commit] We are therfore to know that in the originall it is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Colcomming from a root ſignifying To route or turne, &amp;c. ſo that according to ſtrict tranſlation the words are to be read, Roule thy workes to, or vpon Iehouah. The ſpeech is metaphoricall, and importeth thus much, that euen as men when they cannot lift or weild a thing well, tumble it to another that can better, or as when they haue lifted it, if it bee ſo burden ſome that they cannot vndergoe the weight, they will ſeeke helpe, and lay it vpon anothers ſhoulders: ſo wee being vnable of our ſelues to manage our affaires, are to turne them ouer vnto God, and being preſſed with the weight of any charge, or duty lying vpon vs, are to expect aide from him and looke

that he ſhould ſuſtaine either it for vs, or vs vnder it. In a word, we are aduiſed heere to doe no other thing, than what men doe in thoſe caſes, wherein they alone are inſufficient. What doe they? They goe to ſome body, of whoſe ſufficiency and faithfulneſſe they are aſſured, and tell them that they know not what to doe themſelues, they cannot goe through with the buſineſſe, and therefore they relie and depend wholly vpon him, committing it to his ordering and diſpoſing. Mee thinks Pharaohs cariage towards Ioſeph, ſhadoweth out our duty towards God in this point: He hauing weighed the interpretation of his dreames, and the neceſſity of taking ſome courſe for preſeruation of himſelfe &amp; his people, caſts himſelfe vpon Ioſeph (whoſe ſufficiencie he had well proued) and left the whole buſineſſe to his wiſdome and prouidence. Thus ought wee confidently to entruſt God with all our workes, and much rather than any man. This is enough for the diſcouery of the Metaphor: the fuller meaning we ſhall haue afterwards. In the other words there is no obſcurity. Vnder [Workes] we are to comprehend Words, being one kinde of our operations, though wrought only with the tongue: as alſo our Intentions and reſolutions are heere to bee vnderſtood, and taken in: By [Thoughts] then in the ſecond part of the verſe we are to vnderſtand, both our Act of deliberation, and the Obiect or thing whereon we thinke, and whereabout we deliberate and reſolue. In ſumme, Commit thy workes, is as if he had ſaid, Commit the choice, the ordering, and the ſucceſſe of thy workes to Iehouah; and ſo the laſt

word [establiſhed] intimates, ſignifying (in the originall 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) as well aptabuntur, as firmabuntur; prepared and fitted, as well as confirmed, eſtabliſhed.
            
            The words thus, in ſome ſort, vnfolded, I come to the point of inſtruction taught plainly in the words, viz:
               
                  
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  t. 
               Euery one ought to commit their workes vnto the Lord. It may not be amiſſe, firſt generally to proue it, and then to lay out the particulars comprized in the generall. For proofe we haue ſundry parallel places to this. Dauid giues the ſame counſell, Pſal. 37.5. Commit thy way vnto the Lord, &amp;c. And what counſell he giues to others, we finde recorded he tooke himſelfe, Pſalm. 22.9. He truſted in the Lord, &amp;c. ſaid his very enemies. The ſame word for Rouling is vſed in both thoſe places which is heere. We finde the ſame kinde of Metaphor for ſenſe in other places, though the words be ſomewhat different, as Pſal. 55.22. Caſt thy burden vpon the Lord, &amp;c. And 1. Pet. 5.7. Caſt all your care vpon God. &amp;c. Where the words tranſlated [Caſt] though they note properly another motion from Rouling, which wee know by that name; yet doe they as clearely illuſtrate this duty in my Text, which chiefly imports a transferring, or remouing from our ſelues our waighty workes, or burdens, or cares, vpon another that is ſtronger than we are. For more full explication of which duty ſo manifeſtly and ſtraitly enjoyned vs, deſcend we to the particulars therin contained. There are three things which ſeeme to take vp the whole nature of this Committing: 1. A ſenſe, and acknowledgement of ſelfe-inſufficiencie for the worke. 2. A faithfull dependency

on God for the appointing and effecting of it. 3. An actuall recommending of it vnto God in prayer. Theſe three, were this an aſſembly of Schollers, I would liken vnto thoſe three principles of naturall things which Philoſophers tell vs of, Priuation, Matter, and Forme. The deniall of our owne abilities, I may call in ſome ſort a Priuation. for vnleſſe wee confeſſe our want of them, and ſtrip our ſelues naked (as it were) out of all conceits of our owne ſufficiency, we ſhall neuer be diſpoſed to looke vnto God in our actions. Yet is not this (indeed) eſſentiall to this duty, though neceſſarily preceding, and making way for it. Secondly, our faithfull dependency vpon God, and impoſing the weight vpon him, may be termed the matter, of which this duty conſiſteth. Thirdly, our actuall recommending of our workes vnto God in prayer, is as it were, the forme of this duty, by which it is compleat in the e
                     ••
                  e, or being of it: Now for the explanation of theſe ſeuerals.
            Firſt we muſt finde our ſelues vnable to vndergoe the burden, and acknowledge our weakneſſe; And this in a threefold reſpect, 1. of Iudgement, 2. of Wiſdome, 3 of Power. We muſt deny our owne Iudgement to direct in matter of reſolution what to doe. For how great cauſe haue we to confeſſe our folly, and our blindneſſe in chooſing? True it is which the wiſe man ſpeaks, Verſ. 2. All the waies of a man are cleane in his owne eyes, and (cap. 21.2.) right in his owne eyes. Yet ſee what good judges our eyes are, Verſ. 25. There is a way that ſeemeth right vnto a man, but the end thereof are the waies of death.
               
And, indeed, not one only, but euery way, euery worke that is of our owne finding out, of our owne deuiſing, is ſinfull, and tendeth to death, vnleſſe we haue warrant for it elſewhere, from God. Fearefull is that Irony of the Preacher, Eccleſ. 11. verſ. 9, 10. Walke o young man in the wayes of thine heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes, but know, &amp;c. I need not tell you how ſharply God reproued the people by his Prophets, for walking in the peruerſe and crooked wayes of their owne hearts. Doubtleſſe no greater judgement could befall euen the beſt of vs, than to eat the fruit of our owne wayes, and be filled with our owne deuices, Prouerb. 1.31. But to lay aſide theſe more weighty conſiderations, let vs examine our actions, by the meere grounds of morality; and (alas!) how ſottiſh, how blinde are we when we are our owne Councellors! What groſſe miſtakings, what ſilly choiſes make we? How great failing in judgement do we bewray in ciuill actions? Was it not a fooliſh project to thinke to perpetuate ones name by a building, as they did at Babel? Gen. 11.4. No better projects many times do we lay, but ſuch as will end in confuſion: At the beſt, we ſtudy, and imploy our ſelues, for the moſt part, but about toyes, and trifles, and things that profit not. We rather chooſe Marthaes encombrance, than Maries better part. So that we haue great cauſe to renounce our owne judgement in chooſing.
            Againe, in the ſecond place, for wiſdome in managing and diſpoſing of a matter reſolued on, ſuppoſe the reſolution bee good, wee lacke that too.

There are but two wayes (we vſe to ſay) a right and a wrong, and do not wee generally take the wrong? In ſpirituall matters, we would worſhip God: but how? Our owne wiſdome would faine intermeddle too farre in the manner, &amp; intermingle the inuentions of our braines, which are very louely &amp; decent in our owne eyes, how contrary ſoeuer to Gods word: when in the meane time we marre all, corrupting our ſeruices, &amp; making them odious to God. It was certainly a godly mind in Dauid &amp; the Iſraelites, that moued them to bring the Arke out of the houſe of Abinadab, and their ſolemnity in making a new Cart for it, made a faire ſhew for the time, of diſcretion, and wiſdome; but afterwards they found their folly to their griefe, and that they had not ſought the Lord in due order, 1. Chron. 15.13. why? Becauſe they thought themſelues wiſe enough to manage that action, without following and obſeruing Gods order. In worldly matters alſo we ſaile either in not vſing right meanes or not in a right manner: Wee either leane on a Reede which will breake, and pierce our hands (as Aegypt is called, Eſa. 36.6.) or elſe wee take the wrong end of a good ſtaffe. Either we take thoſe courſes which will hinder, and prejudice our intentions, or we worke ſo prepoſterouſly, ſo vnſeaſonably, that we are not a whit the neerer, to that which we would effect. Surely, vnleſſe an higher prouidence leade, and guide vs, we may all vſe the words of Eliphaz, Iob. 5.13, 14. Our counſels are carried headlong; wee meete with darkneſſe in the day time, and groape at noone day as in the night. Eſpecially

in a caſe of extremitie, and in diſtreſſe wee are ſo diſtracted that we are at our wits end, and know not which way to turne our ſelues. So that in this reſpect we haue good reaſon to take Salomons counſell, Leane not vnto thine owne vnderſtanding, Prou. 5.5. And let vs ingeniouſly acknowledge vnto God with Ieremie (cap. 10 23.) O Lord I know that the way of man is not in himſelfe; it is not in man that walketh to direct his owne ſteps.
            
            In the third place wee are to deny our owne Power to accompliſh any worke though neuer ſo well conceiued, though meanes are neuer ſo well ordered, and the buſineſſe in very great forwardneſſe. Who is he (ſaith Ieremie, Lamen. 3.37.) that ſaith, and it commeth to paſſe when the Lord commandeth it not? I may adde; when he aſsiſteth not, proſpereth not; For, poore impotent creatures that we are, if we looke vnto ſpirituall actions, we cannot ſo much as will to doe good of our ſelues, much leſſe can we carry our ſelues through any holy duty with comfort, and ſucceſſe: Without mee (ſaith Chriſt) ye can doe nothing, Ioh. 15.5. which is true alſo if we looke to temporall affaires, and emploiments. For what can we ſay we will doe? God can interpoſe when he will, and ſtay our proceedings a thouſand wayes. He can either ſuddenly cruſh vs, and turne vs into duſt: or blow vpon our labours, or ſuffer others to croſſe and cleane ouerthrow our enterpriſes. So that, in matter of profit no man can ſay, my power, my labour, the might of my hand hath gotten me this wealth,

               Deut. 8.17. Nor in point of honour, By my policie I haue builded my neſt on high: by the ſtrength of mine arme I haue gotten the victorie, Pſalm. 44.3. Therefore (to ſhut vp this firſt preparatiue act to into duty) we are in euery action to take notice of our weakneſſe, and to groane vnder euery imploiment, as vnder a burden inſupportable, ſhould we haue no helpe: We may bee in continuall motion, rouling and tumbling our actions vp and downe, but ſhall neuer finde reſt, and firme ſetling of them, before we lay them vpon God: ſeeing before wee come to him, it is with vs as Mathematicians tell vs it is with a Globe vpon a plaine, impoſſible to ſtand ſtill, and as impoſſible to ſtirre to any purpoſe. If then we ſet vpon ſpirituall duties, ſay with the Apoſtle Paul, We are not ſufficient of our ſelues to thinke (much leſſe to doe) any thing as of our ſelues but our ſufficiency is of God, 2. Cor. 3.5. And neither is he that planteth, any thing; nor he that watereth, but God that giueth the increaſe, 1. Cor. 3 7. If we goe about any worke of our worldly callings, humbly acknowledge with Dauid, Except the Lord build the houſe they labour in vaine that build it, Pſal. 127. 1. So, except he proſper other our handy-workes, in vaine do we think in our owne ſtrength to bring them to a wiſhed end: eſpecially when any more important affaire is in hand; as when preparations are made for warre, and publique ſeruice is to be done for the Church of God; then let vs be moſt ſenſible of our owne weakneſſe, and confeſſe with Iehoſhaphat, That we haue no might againſt our enemies, nor know we what to doe, 2. Chron. 20.12.

But had not Iehoſhaphat a great Armie, and valiant men? Yes, yet in them was no might. Did not he know that he had no way but to lead out his forces? yes, and yet he knew not what to doe. Only this, Our eyes (ſaid he) are towards thee, that is, ſeeing we cannot worke effectually for our ſelues, we roule (not our eyes only, but) our worke vpon thee ó Lord, &amp;c.
            
                And thus we paſſe on from the firſt preparatiue, vnto the ſecond, an eſſentiall act of this duty: from the act of acknowledgement in humilitie of our ſelfe-inſufficiencie, to the act of Faith in dependencie on God, and his efficiencie. Now in this reſting and relying vpon God conſiſteth principally this deuoluing or committing our worke vnto God, and this is manifeſted in ſo many acts as there were particulars wherein we diſcouered our owne weakeneſſe. Firſt then, he that commits his worke to God, muſt depend as well on his wil and allowance before he begins it, as on his helpe and aſsiſtance afterward; he muſt out of that ſuſpicion he is to haue of his owne iudgement in choice, referre his determinations to God, conſult with him, and as he willeth, and preſcribeth, ſo doe, and not otherwiſe. This was the courſe which Gods people tooke of old; they would neuer attempt any matter, eſpecially of moment, without a warrant, Thus the Iſraelites, when Ioſhua their Generall was dead, before they ſtirred to elect another, asked of the Lord, who ſhould goe vp firſt for them, &amp;c. Iudg. 11. They conſulted againe with God before they would take armes againſt the children of Beniamin,

Iudg. 11.18, 23, 28. Thus did Dauid ſundry times, 1 Sam. 23.12. &amp; 30 8. Thus did many others of Gods ſeruants in ſuch like caſes, and all in obedience to Gods ordinance, Numb. 27.21. that the Prieſts ſhould aske counſell for them after the judgement of Vrim before the Lord, and at his word they ſhould goe out, and come in, &amp;c. But what tell I you of this extraordinarie courſe of taking reſolution? We in theſe times can haue no recourſe vnto a vocall Oracle, yet notwithſtanding we muſt looke that all our actions be lawfull, and warranted by that written Oracle which is among vs; Why elſe hath God left vs his word? Why are we called To the Law and to the Teſtimonie, Eſa. 8.20. Whatſoeuer we commit to the determination of that word, we commit to God himſelfe. Obiect. But the Scripture (ſome will ſay) doth not mention thouſands of particular actions, about which men are imploied. Anſwer. True, yet it giues ſuch rules and directions, as may be applied to euery action that we can poſſibly fall vpon, and are able to ſatisfie him that rightly applieth them. If therfore we intend any holy worke or ſeruice, let vs commit it to God, and examine we our ſelues whether he hath licenced vs to meddle thus, or thus in his holy things, whether he hath called vs, and ſent vs, and ſet vs about them. If we go about any other ciuill actions, put each of them likewiſe to the queſtion, Is it lawfull? haue I any ground for it? and be reſolued from God before we aduenture on it. Wherefore we are to take Dauids courſe in ſubmmitting our ſelues to God, and waiting on

him continually to know the way wherein we ſhould walke, Pſal. 143.8. So that this is the ſumme; we are not to be our owne caruers, but leaue it to God to chalke out our way, and appoint our worke; otherwiſe we cannot worke in faith; and whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne, Rom. 14.23.
            
               
                  Reaſ. 1 Grounds why we ſhould thus depend on God for his licence, and approbation are many: But, beſides his command, and his childrens practiſe (of which we haue heard) take only theſe two: Firſt, his Will is the rule, and patterne of holineſſe, and juſtice, and therefore are our actions holy and juſt, and good, becauſe agreeable to his will: From which if we ſwarue, and doe that which neuer came into his minde, though it may ſeeme glorious, it is abhominable.  Secondly, we owe vnto God that reſpect, that obedience, he being our Soueraigne Lord, and Gouernour, and Commander, as to doe nothing (as neare as we can) but what he giues leaue to doe, and which we know is acceptable to him, &amp;c.
            
                We proceed on to the ſecond act of dependency, viz. A reſting on God for the diſpoſing, and ordering of our actions, the warrantableneſſe whereof (let be ſuppoſed) we are perſwaded of, and are now entred vpon them: And heere is ſeene a ſtrong worke of faith, and confidence on God, in attributing ſo much vnto him as to put ouer all our buſineſſes into his hands (as it were) and in a manner out of our own. For we muſt truſt to him for the prouiſion of meanes, for the diſpoſition of them; yea though all meanes ſeeme to faile, yea further,

though all ſeeme to make againſt our proceedings, ſtill reſt vpon him. Fit for our ſtrengthning in this 
                  〈◊〉
                are thoſe preſcripts of Chriſt, one in Matt. 6.25. Take no thought for your life, what yee ſhall eate, or what yee ſhall drinke, nor yet for your body, what ye ſhall put on: For (as it followeth in that place) your heauenly father will feed and cloath you. &amp;c. The other in Mat. 10.19. where Chriſt foretelling his Diſciples of their enſuing troubles, he biddeth them, when they are deliuered vp to Councels, and Gouernours, not to take thought how, or what they ſhould ſpeake; for it ſhall be giuen you (ſaith he) in that houre what 
                     〈◊〉
                   all ſpeake. As if he had ſaid, when we are called to confeſſe my name, do not lay the taske vpon your naturall parts, as your wit, your learning, your eloquence, and fluency of ſpeech, thinking they muſt ſaue your credit, and be the meanes to doe that worke as it ſhould be done; no, rather caſt your ſelues vpon me, and expect fit matter and words, of my prouiſion, and ſuggeſtion.
            But heere (before we goe on further) a ſcruple muſt be reſolued, and taken away, both for the clea
                  •
               ing of theſe places, and of my Text; for ſome may be ready to gather from thence, this concluſion: If I muſt 
                  ••
               ule my worke on God, and take no thought for any thing, then need not I ſtirre, but may ſit ſtill, and let God doe all. We are therefore to know that this doctrine is farre from miniſtring my plea to any ſupine lazineſſe, or careleſſe idlene
                  •
               ſ
                  •
               ; it only ſheweth vs the way how our actions may become both lawfull, and ſuccesfull: it giueth no exemption from imploying our own induſtrie,

and endeuour. For the better cleering of the point I lay downe two propoſitions; 1. That we are ſo to commit our workes to God, as that yet they may remaine our workes. 2. We are ſo to doe our workes, as not to buſie our ſelues with Gods worke. Firſt, I ſay, we are ſo to roule our workes vpon God, as yet to vndergoe ſomewhat our ſelues. Otherwiſe, how could the Text ſay [thy worke] if we had no finger in it? How other where could it be called [our way] if we neuer ſtirred a foot in it? Againe, for the laſt alleadged places; Can any dreame that Chriſt forbids all premeditation, and conuenient preparation before hand, when a man is (perhaps) to ſpeake in publique, and there where are both curious, and captious hearers? Would not ſuch boldneſſe be preſumption? Or can any imagine that hee forbids all prouidence, and prouiſion of neceſſaries, when in other places we are commanded to labour, that we may eat, and to be painfull in our callings? Would not ſuch idleneſſe be Sathans illuſion? Yes ſurely; for no precept rightly vnderſtood, contradicts another. God that workes for vs, will yet haue vs worke with him. We muſt be like Pilots at Sea, who though their eyes are lifted vpward, obſeruing the ſtarres, yet hold their hand on the Helme to direct the Sterne: And we muſt imitate Nehemiah and his people, who as they made their prayer to their God, ſo they ſet a watch day and night to defend themſelues, and their worke, Nehe. 4 9.
            The ſecond propoſition will make the point plainer, viz. That God would haue vs ſo to doe

               our owne worke, as not to buſie our ſelues with his worke: What now is our worke? To be induſtrious and diligent in vſing the meanes which God offereth vs, and employ thoſe talents which he hath giuen vs, after the beſt ſort we can. What is Gods worke then? To diſpoſe of all things according to his owne counſell, and to giue the ſucceſſe of the action according to his will: So that, if we either vex, &amp; diſquiet our ſelues with needleſſe feares, or torment our ſelues with ſolicitude and exceſſiue cares about the accompliſhment of our buſineſſe, we incroach vpon Gods worke, and that only is there forbidden.
            This now being cleered, it is apparent that our diligence, &amp; our repoſe on Gods prouidence may ſtand together; of which repoſe we now ſpeake, and it is to be practiſed in two reſpects: 1. In regard of our ſelues; 2. of other meanes. Firſt, for our ſelues, we muſt yeeld as inſtruments to bee fitted, and prepared for the worke, and to be directed, and guided in it, by him. Our eyes muſt be towards him that he may inſtruct, and guide vs with his eye, Pſa. 32.8. And we finde that the eye of God was vpon the Elders of the Iewes in their worke of building, ſo that their enemies could not make them to ceaſe, Ezra 5.5. If our buſineſſe bee in ſpeech▪ we are to beleeue that God who made our mouthes, will be with our mouthes, and teach vs what to ſay, as he did Moſes, Exod. 4.11, 12. If it be in action otherwiſe, conſider that God giueth abilities, and a ſpirit fit for the worke, as he did Gideon, Iudg. 6.16. Againe, for other meanes

we muſt reſt on him to bee borne vpon the wings of his prouidence, and to haue ſuch meanes miniſtred as may moſt aduance our deſignes and deſires. Dauid, when it was told him that Ahithophel was among the conſpirators with Abſalom
                     •
                  , Lord (ſaid he) I pray thee turne the counſell of Ahithophel into fooliſhneſſe, 2. Sam. 15.31. When he prayed thus, going vp the hill, he knew no meanes how God would effect it, only he referred it to him who could either infatuate Ahithophel, or confound his counſell, as pleaſed him; but we finde how that God preſently as ſoone as he was gotten to the top of the hill, preſented vnto him a meane whereby it was poſſible Ahithophels counſell might be rejected, viz. The ſending of Huſhai vnto Abſalom to mate Ahithophel with his wiſdome, &amp; that proued effectuall. Gideon, when God had called him to fight againſt the Midianites, and had cauſed him to ſend home the greater part of his Army, and afterwards of the remnant, choſe only 300. men, knew not (queſtionleſſe) how God would worke with thoſe men, or after what manner they ſhould aſſault the enemie, yet beleeued he that God would ſome way employ them: and we finde that God taught him, at length, how they ſhould be armed, how appointed, not with weapons, but with Trumpets, and fire-brands, and pitchers, Iudg. 7.16. Very pertinent to this point, is that worthy example of Abrahams ſeruant going to get a wife for his young maſter Iſaak, Gen. 24.13, 14. He not only truſted God with the ſucceſſe of his journey, but commited to his diſpoſing the meanes
               
alſo, as the comming forth of the damoſel, her ſpeech to him, &amp;c.
            Many inſtances might be giuen to ſhew the dependance of Gods children on him to carry them through their employments; and there are good grounds why they ſhould doe ſo.
            
               
                  Reaſ. 1 Gods wiſdome is ſo exact, ſo infinite, that hee knoweth what meanes will be fit to be vſed now, and what not, both for his glory, and the eſtabliſhing of the thing in hand: He knowes what may hinder, &amp; can either preuent, or fruſtrate it. He both knowe how to open a doore for Paul to do good in his miniſterie; and for Peter to eſcape imminent danger. In a word, he knoweth how to knit ſecondary cauſes, one vnto another, and to make them conſpire together in an admirable harmony, which we our ſelues cannot doe. Therefore, rely on him, and in faith make vſe of that ſpeech of the Apoſtle, Rom. 8.28▪ which though he ſpeaketh to another purpoſe, yet may bee applied to ours in hand, viz. God will make all things worke together for the beſt.
            
                Gods prouidence is in euery particular thing that falls out; he is not ſuch a God as ſome of the heathen make their Iupiter; of whom they ſay, Non vacat exiguis &amp;c. Iupiter is not at leaſure to attend petty matters: But the truth is, he hath a ſtroake in minimis, euen the leaſt matters. Not a Sparrow falls to the ground but by his will. He feeds the fowles of the arre, and cloathes the flowers of the field. How can we then thinke but that he diſpoſeth of euery thing that concernes vs, or our affaires? Mans goings

are of the Lord (ſaith Solomon) Prou. 20.24. how then can he vnerſtand his owne way? And, A mans heart deuiſeth his way, but the Lord directeth his ſteps, verſ. 9. of this chapter. Yea God numbreth our ſteps, Iob. 14.16. Great reaſon then haue we, Beloued, to commit our workes to his managing, and ordering, &amp;c.
            
                And now we are come to the third, and laſt act of Dependency, viz. A reſting, and waiting on God for the ſucceſſe of our buſineſſes, and endeuours. Which is ſo neceſſary, that the promiſes annexed to theſe precepts ſeeme more eſpecially to aime at it. Commit (ſaith my Text) thy workes vnto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall bee eſtabliſhed: what doth this ſound elſe, but, Commit the eſtabliſhment of thy workes to God? So is that, Pſalme 37.5. to be reſolued: this wee are taught to doe, when wee are in any holy worke, or ſeruice, by Paul, and Barnabas, Acts 14.23. They commended the Elders vnto the Lord, &amp;c. that is, the Miniſtery and ſucceſſe of the Miniſtery of the Elders, chiefly. Likewiſe by the Prophet Iſaiahs owne example (Iſay 49.4.) who though he feared his labour was in vaine, yet herein findes comfort, that his worke was with his God, that is, the ſucceſſe of it, &amp;c. When wee are vpon other affaires, this duty is alſo commended vnto vs. Ioab when hee went out againſt the Ammonites and Syrians, and had marſhalled his Army, and ſet his troupes in the beſt order he could, for greateſt aduantage; and omitted no part of a wiſe and diſcreet Generall; what ſaies hee to Abiſhai his brother? Be of good courage, and let vs play

the men, and the Lord doe that which ſeemeth him good, 2 Sam. 10.12. He thought his part was only to play the man: it was Gods part to incline the day, and giue the victory to this or that ſide, and to him he left it. Nehemiah when he had reſolued to ſpeake to the king his Maſter, in behalfe of his people, troubleth not himſelfe what anſwer he ſhould haue, but leaues that to God; Proſper I pray thee (ſaid he, cap. 1.11.) thy ſeruant this day, and grant him mercy in the ſight of this man. So Heſter, &amp;c. Heſter 4.16.
            But what doe I heaping vp knowne examples? Call to minde with mee but one more, namely, that of Abraham; God had called him to doe a worke, a ſeeming vnnaturall worke, of ſlaying and ſacrificing his only ſonne, (Gen. 22.) What doth he? He goes about it preſently, without queſtioning the nature of the fact or Gods promiſe, and had done it if God had not ſtayed him. O wonderfull ſtrength of faith! O matchleſſe confidence! We may well thinke that this father of the faithfull, as he told his deare Iſaak (verſe 8.) that God would prouide a Lambe, ſo was perſwaded that God would prouide in other reſpects that the ſucceſſe and conſequent of this act ſhould bee ſuch, as might ſtand both with Gods mercy, and faithfulneſſe, and alſo the encouragement of his owne Faith in aſſurance of poſterity. But to leaue examples, conſider with me what ſtrong grounds we haue whereon to build this dependance for ſucceſſe on God.
            
               
                  Reaſ. 1 Gods abſolute Power requireth thus much at our hands; He is both Omnipotent, able to doe all

things; and alſo Soli-potent, only able to doe what him pleaſeth in heauen and in earth. Who hath not found that true which the Preacher found true, Eccleſ. 9.11. The race is not alwaies to the ſwift, nor the battell to the ſtrong, neither yet bread to the wiſe, &amp;c. And what elſe are we to conclude thence, but that there is another ſupreme Ruler, and Gouernour ouer man who giues the iſſue, not according to the ſeeming abilities of the perſons, or likelihood of meanes vſed, but according to the good pleaſure of his owne will. The three children therefore, though it was a ſore burden of care, and feare, and doubting, that lay on their necks when they were either to be caſt into the fiery furnace, or to worſhip an Idoll (call it what you will, a worke or a ſuffering) committed the euent to God; and vpon what ground? The power of God; Our God (ſaid they) is able to deliuer vs, &amp;c. Dan. 3.16. So did Aſa, 2 Chron. 14.11. Lord it is nothing with thee to helpe whether with many, or with them that haue no power; helpe vs, O Lord our God, for wee reſt on thee, &amp;c.
            
                The Decree of God is a maine prop and pillar of this confidence. He hath fore-determined, and appointed whatſoeuer commeth to paſſe; All our times are in his hand, and all the actions and motions in thoſe times. Whatſoeuer we doe therefore, let vs wait in ſilence, and patience, for that euent which God hath decreed. Many deuices are in a mans heart (ſaith Solomon) neuertheleſſe the counſell of the Lord that ſhall ſtand, Prou. 19.21. Hence that faithfull ſpeech, Iſay 26.12. Lord thou wilt ordaine peace for vs, &amp;c.
            
               Now, becauſe fleſh and bloud findes this an hard taske, to depend thus on God, though there be very many thinke it an eaſie leſſon, and will ſay that they hope in God, and now they haue done what they can, will not trouble themſelues further, therefore let vs examine how the caſe ſtands with vs, by a ſigne or two, taken from the nature of this act.
            
               
                  Signe 2 Know then, that confidence on God for the euent, caſts out both carnall feare, and diſtracting care. Theſe two, Feare and Care, I may not vnfitly compare vnto thoſe two brethren Rechab and Baanah (of whom we reade, 2 Sam. 4.5, 6.) For as they ſlew Iſhboſheth while he lay on his bed in his houſe; ſo theſe will take away the life of our Faith, if once they get into the houſe of our hearts, while wee thinke it reſteth it ſelfe ſecurely on God. So that, firſt, the faithfull man feares not; (I will truſt and not be afraid, Iſay 12.2.) though he finde many wants in himſelfe, no ſuccours from others, yea though there ariſe impoſſibilities in his conceit, yet hee is like Abraham, Rom. 4.18, 19, 20. Hee beleeueth in hope, aboue hope, not ſtaggering at the promiſes of God, &amp;c. And thus he giues glory to God, euen the glory of his power and omnipotency, as is there teſtified of Abraham.
            
            
                Againe, the faithfull man is not carefull, that is, diſtracted with immoderate, and exceſſiue care, as if his caring, and muſing could any thing alter the caſe; No, he knowes that what God hath determined ſhall be effected, though he caſt about neuer ſo many waies to fulfill his owne deſires, and therefore he anſwereth either his owne ſoule or others,

as the three children did the king, Dan. 3. We are not carefull to anſwer thee, that is, we are not ſolicitous to finde out ſhifts, or wayes about to eſcape, that which is our dutie we will doe: let God alone for the concluſion. Sure it is, that Rouling our burden vpon God, and loading our ſelues ſtill with a burden of cares and feares, cannot well meet together.
            
               
                  Signe 2 Secondly, faith, as it caſts out feare, and care, ſo is it accompanied with cheerefulneſſe, and cauſeth a man to encourage himſelfe in God. So wee finde Dauid affected, 1. Sam. 30.6. While he was in danger of being ſtoned by his owne people, and had all the diſheartnings that (almoſt) could be, yet euen then he encouraged himſelfe (ſaith the text) in the Lord his God. And therefore in Pſal. 37.4, 5. Delighting our ſelues in the Lord, and committing our way vnto him, are joyned together as companions, hauing the ſame promiſe in effect made to both.
            
               
                  ¶ 3 There remaineth only the laſt thing required to this Commiting &amp;c. viz. Prayer. For, as we muſt deny our ſelues, and depend on God for a warrant when we are in conſultation, for aſſiſtance, and meanes when we come to reſolution, and for ſucceſſe when the buſineſſe is to bee ripened, and brought to perfection: So we muſt make a ſolemne recommendation of our worke to God, in Prayer, which I called the formall act (that is, the ſet manner) of Commiſsion, becauſe whereas by faith and dependance we doe, indeed, really, and truly roule our burden vpon God, by this prayer that faith (as many

other graces beſides) is acted forth, and cleerely manifeſted.
            I explaine my meaning by an ordinary courſe in Law (as I take it) viz. When a man puts ouer his eſtate to another, or eſtates another in any thing, there muſt be, beſides the writings drawne, a formall deliuery of them to the party: To theſe writings, wherein is contained the ſubſtance of the conueiance, I liken Faith: to the deliuery of theſe writings, in the manner of conueiance, I liken Prayer. Now for prayer, that it is included in this duty, is without queſtion. Some would haue it only, or at leaſt principally, meant in the text, and therefore tranſlate it (in ſtead of Roule thy workes) Reueale thy workes vnto the Lord. But that they are miſtaken, both the proper ſignification of the Hebrew word ſheweth, and the nature of the thing.
            For, will my bare telling another that I am burthened, eaſe me any whit, or keepe my burden from falling? No, vnleſſe I lay it vpon him, and he helpe to ſupport it: Will my faire words to another, how I will entruſt him with ſuch an eſtate of mine, either better mine eſtate, or keep it from decaying? No, vnleſſe by a due legall proceeding I reſigne it ouer vnto him, and ſo giue proofe that I truſt him. No more will a bare acquainting God with mine intentions, or actions, or griefes, further my deſignes, or ratifie my deſires, vnleſſe I repoſe my confidence in him.
            Yet muſt we take in Prayer within the compaſſe of this Rouling, though not ſhut out the other for

its ſake: But what ſhall I, or need I now ſpeake of it? If we looke backe to the examples of thoſe afore mentioned, we ſhall finde diuers of them diſcouering their faith in the prayer of Faith. It was in prayer that Iehoſhaphat confeſſed his weakneſſe and committed his worke of warfare vnto God: It was in prayer that Dauid asked God what hee ſhould doe, and in what way he ſhould walke: It was in prayer alſo that hee be truſted God with the meanes to be foole Ahithophel; as did Abrahams ſeruant to find out a wife for his yong maſter. Laſtly, it was in prayer that Nehemiah commended his ſpeeding with the king his Maſter vnto the Lord. What need I adde any inſtances to theſe? I wil only commend to your generall imitation that act of Hezekiah, Iſa. 37.14. He went to God, and ſpread the letter of Sennacherib before the Lord: So let vs in all our occaſions, whether ordinarie, or extraordinarie, when wee are to doe any worke, when we would be eaſed of any burden, goe vnto God, lay open our caſe, offer vp our petitions, and in faithfull prayer, poure out our ſoules before him. O what maruellous encouragements and forcible motiues haue we ſo to doe!
            All the grounds for each of the former points ſerue joyntly to beare vp this too.
                  Reaſ. 1 It is firſt his good will and pleaſure that we ſhould pray in this caſe: and then his wiſdome ſhould inuite vs to haue recourſe vnto him: and thirdly, his power ſhould be a ſtrong argument to moue vs to runne vnto him, Prou. 18.10. But I cannot inſiſt on theſe, but muſt haſten towards an end.
            
               
                Yet I will adde one more to the former, which may aboue all other motiues encourage vs to pray, viz. The conſideration of Gods Loue and mercy to vs, and readineſſe to put forth himſelfe for vs. This is that argument which is vſed in my Text and like places by way of promiſe: Caſt all your care vpon God (ſaith the Apoſtle Peter) why? For he careth for you, 1. Pet. 5.7 Yea, God tendereth vs as a father doth his children. Pſal. 103.13. And will a father let his childe ſinke vnder a burden when he entreats his helpe? No, hee will either beare it for him, or ſuſtaine him vnder it. If earthly parents doe for their children, ſhall not our heauenly father doe for vs? Much more ſurely, as Chriſt concludeth, Matt. 7. And therefore will Dauid call vpon God, becauſe hee is the God that performeth all things for him, Pſal. 57.2. I conclude then with the words of the Apoſtle, Phil. 4.6. Be carefull for nothing; but in euery thing by prayer, and ſupplication with thankſgiuing, let your requeſts be made knowne to God.
            
            The Doctrinall part of this counſell being explained; ſee we in briefe what may be thence collected.
            
               
                  Vſe. 1 Firſt, here is a word of Exhortation, that wee would all take this courſe, and follow this counſell. But his may be ſpared (in reſpect of our priuate workes) becauſe the doctrine it ſelfe was exhortatorie, and many exhortations were intermixed among the explanations of it. Yet let vs all be perſwaded to caſt an eie vpon the Churches of God, I meane eſpecially the diſtreſſed parts of it, and commend

their workes and deſignes for their owne ſafety, together with the workes of others in their behalfe, vnto the Lord. We may in charity, ſuppoſe that they haue committed the choice of their enterpriſes vnto him, and haue a warrant for them: Let vs now commit the meanes and the ſucceſſe vnto God. Howſoeuer matters goe hard in many places, meanes faile, the caſe ſeeme almoſt deſperate, God giues ſucceſſes to the enemie, ſuffers his children to be cruelly and iniuriouſly handled, ſcattered, ſlaughtered; (So that wee may take vp for them that complaint of thoſe, Pſalme 44.10, 11. Thou makeſt vs turne backe from the enemie, &amp;c.) yet let vs ſo carry our ſelues that we may ſay with them there, Verſe 17 all this is come vpon vs, yet haue not we forgotten thee, &amp;c.
            
               
                  Vſe. 2 Againe, heere is a word of rebuke to as many as will not be aduiſed by the wiſe man: And they are of diuers ſorts.
            
                1. They that make their owne ſufficiencies the fundamentall baſe, and prop of their actions. As Papiſts, who make the ſtrength of nature able to worke diuers good actions: And generally, all proud perſons, who pride themſelues in their owne might and power, as if they could doe what they liſt, and God not able to hinder them. The cariage of many, though haply not their ſpeeches, bewray ſuch arrogant thoughts.
            2. They who will not endure to commit the choice of their actions to God, nor ſtay for a warrant, but runne on vpon their owne heads: ſuch as they, Deut. 1. who would needs fight when God

forbade them, ſo farre were they from demanding leaue of him: Or as they, Ierem. 42.20. who would ſeeme to commit their iourney to God, but in hypocriſie, hauing reſolued what to doe before hand, let Gods command be what it will.
            They that dare not depend vpon God for meanes. Such are they that faint in themſelues, and make themſelues more vnfit for the worke than God hath made them, by their diffidence of euer being enabled for it. Herein was Moſes faulty, Exod. 4.10. Secondly, they that diſtruſt God if ſuch and ſuch meanes doe not take, and at ſuch a time. Such were the Iſraelites who are ſaid to limit the holy one of Iſrael, Pſal. 78.41. Thirdly, they that rely vpon their owne procurement of meanes, as they that truſted on the ſtrength of Aegypt, Iſa. 31.1, 2. Againſt whom both a woe is denounced, and Gods Wiſdome oppoſed: yet (ſaith the Prophet) he is wiſe; i. though you ſo leane to your owne wiſdome in contriuing meanes, and to Aegypt in affording them, God will outreach you. Of this ſort we finde many who will thinke to make all ſo ſure, and order euery thing ſo wiſely, that Gods prouidence ſhall be (in ſeeming) cleane ſhut out, as if he could not make a change, &amp;c. Fourthly, they are moſt to blame who vſe indirect meanes, and ſo by conſequence commit their workes to the Deuill. Saul did ſo palpably, in conſulting with the Witch at Endor, 1 Sam. 28.8. Others doe it couertly, &amp;c.
            
                They that truſt not God with the euent and ſucceſſe of their buſineſſe; but peremptorily conclude

what their feare ſuggeſteth. So Moſes, Exod. 4 1. Behold (ſaid he) they will not beleeue mee &amp;c. And Dauid, 1 Sam. 27.1. I ſhall one day periſh by the hand of Saul, &amp;c. But wee muſt know that howſoeuer God allowes vs to be Hiſtorians, or recorders of thoſe workes which he hath done for vs: yet he will not haue vs be Prognoſticators of future euents, ſo as to determine what he will doe, eſpecially when wee conclude againſt our ſelues, and the glory of his mercie.
            
               Thus much for the Counſell, or precept in the Text.
            
            
               And thy thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſhed.
               THeſe words appeare plainely to be a Promiſe ſubioyned to that counſell which the Wiſe man gaue in the former part of the Verſe; and containe that end which is aimed at by all agents, and eaſily obtained by taking that courſe, and following that way which was premiſed. Heere, for our orderly proceeding, wee are firſt to ſeuer the words in explication, and then ioyne them againe in a generall obſeruation, which when wee haue branched forth into particulars, and fenced from obiections, we will ſhut vp with application.
               Two words are to bee opened [Thoughts] and [Eſtabliſhed.] Thoughts in the ſoule of man are properly the inward agitations, or workings thereof, beating as it were, vpon an obiect fomerly apprehended; and we ſhall finde the greateſt vſe of them in matters either of weight or difficultie, and

the more wee are poſſeſſed, or preſſed with any thing, the more they are multiplied. O what a world of them, in ſuch caſes, throng in one vpon the necke of another to the diſquieting of our ſpirits▪ The beſt men of the beſt tempers are ſubiect vnto them; euen Dauid himſelfe is heard to complaine of the multitude of his thoughts within him, Pſal. 94.19. And indeed, this ſwarming of thoughts is a maruellous grieuance vnto a man, for they hinder and interrupt the cleare diſcourſe of reaſon, and raiſe as it were, ſuch a miſt in a mans minde, that hee is not able to diſcerne one truth from another. This noted by the way, I paſſe on to other acceptions of thoughts: For in Scripture they are often put for the effect of thoughts, that is, for counſels, and reſolutions taken after the working of the thoughts; and ſo Ierem. 11.19. They haue thought a thought, or deuiſed a deuice againſt me. &amp;c. The word is the ſame which is vſed heere. Which acception bordereth very neere vpon another, viz. when thoughts are put for the obiect of thoughts, or the matter it ſelfe deuiſed and purpoſed, whether outward, or other; ſo Exod. 35.35. Bezaleel and Ahol
                        •
                     ab are ſaid to be filled with the wiſdome of thoſe that deuiſe cunning worke, or (according to the Hebrew) that thinke thoughts; the word is the ſame likewiſe with this in the Text. Now in both theſe latter acceptions, I thinke the word is to be taken here, and ſo the meaning of this promiſe is, Thy counſels, deuices, or worke thought on ſhall be eſtabliſhed.
               
               Before we paſſe further, it will be neither impertinent,

nor vnprofitable, to cleare a ſcruple which may ariſe from the change of the word [Workes] vſed in the forepart of the text, into this word [Thoughts] in the latter part of it. One would thinke the promiſe would haue better anſwered the precept if he had ſaid, Commit thy workes vnto the Lord, and they (i. thy workes) ſhall bee eſtabliſhed.
               
               
                  
                     Queſt. 
                   May we not gather hence, that we our ſelues are ſufficient for our thoughts, and it will be needfull onely, to refer our workes to God? Eſpecially ſeeing it is ſaid, Verſe the ninth of this chapter; A mans heart deuiſeth his way, but the Lord directeth his ſteps: Which ſeemeth to intimate that we haue power of our ſelues to will, though not to worke.
               
                  
                     Anſw. 
                   It is true, a Papiſt and an Arminian will be ready to catch at ſuch ſhadowes; but ſhadowes are no good couerlets for errors. I will not drench my ſelfe into the bottome of Free-will, no nor wade into it, ſeeing I may keepe my ſelfe on the banke and reſolue this doubt. This then I take to be the truth in a word: Wee cannot thinke or deuiſe any thing meerely of our ſelues; for euen in naturall operations of the minde and heart about naturall and ciuill things, there is a generall concourſe of Gods prouidence. In God wee liue, and moue 
                     Acts 17.28., not our feet onely, but our hearts alſo; He it is by whoſe leaue and licence we will euery thing, and who putteth this or that into our hearts, when we will or affect any good thing. Thoughts are likened to conceptions: Words and workes to births; and as births vſually are not, ſo conceptions cannot

be without others helpe. To this purpoſe the firſt verſe of this chapter runneth thus in the laſt tranſlation; The preparations of the heart in man, and the anſwer of the tongue is from the Lord. We queſtion not now whether the will hath freedome in naturall, and ciuill actions, nor deny it, but this is certaine, that the actuall exerciſe of this freedome is gouerned by God, who can make vs either ſuſpe
                        •
                     d our act of willing, or diuert our thoughts from one thing to another, or incline vs to thinke vpon this or that, now or then, at his pleaſure. For inſtance; we finde God promiſing the Iſraelites that whilſt they went vp thrice in the yeare to appeare before him, no man ſhould ſo much as deſire their land, Exod 34.24. What? was it not in the power of the heathen borderers to haue inuaded that diſpeopled country at ſuch a time? Yes in ſome ſenſe it was, and had not God hindered, it is likely they would ſoone haue beene tampering with Gods inheritance: But we ſee that though they ſuppoſed they had ſtated themſelues, (perhaps out of ſome politique reſpects) yet it was God indeed that ſtayed them. Againe, we finde Iſa. 7.18. that God would hiſſe for a flie from Aegypt, and a Bee from Aſſyria: and Iudges 4.7. that he would draw out Siſera to fight, &amp;c. But did the Aegyptians heare any ſuch hiſſing? Did Siſera feele any ſuch drawing? No ſurely, they thought they had by their owne meere aduice put themſelues into thoſe iourneys. So that we ſee when man thinkes hee reſolues of himſelfe, then God hath his ſtroke in that reſolution. Now to anſwer

this queſtion; why it is ſaid (notwithſtanding all this) that man deuiſeth his way? I anſwer;
               1. It is ſo ſaid to ſhew that though God in his counſell hath determined, and moderated our counſels, yet our naturall liberty in conſulting is not taken away.
               2. The firſt thoughts, and purpoſes of the heart may be attributed to man, rather than other acts comparatiuely; for thoughts and meditations, being the firſt productions, and the moſt ſimple acts of the faculties in man, his worke is moſt ſenſible therein, and leſſe of Gods worke is diſcerned. Whereas the more our operations are compounded, the more are the acts and ioynt workings of diuine prouidence manifold, and doubled. I expreſſe my ſelfe more clearely thus: In the motions of the will or minde, there God workes only vpon the will or minde, and that inwardly, and very cloſely: but when we come to execute our deſignes, there God muſt not only concurre with the ſoule, but with the parts of the body likewiſe, as with the tongue in ſpeaking, with the hand in working, with the feet in walking, and that more palpably: And hence it is that in ſpeciall manner the anſwer of the tongue is from the Lord, and our ſteps directed by him. And now I hope, we may proceed without ſtumbling blocke vnto the laſt word.
               
                  Eſtabliſhed] is in the vulgar Latine read [directed.] But the word in the Originall (as I formerly noted) is more full, ſignifying both to be prepared, or fitted, and to be confirmed or accompliſhed; and therefore a tranſlation into another language,

                  French S
                        ••
                     ont 
                        •
                     gencee
                        •
                     
                   rendreth it excellently by a word importing to be accommodated, dreſſed, fitly diſpoſed, rightly matched, or iuſtly applied, &amp;c. So that more is aimed at than the bare effecting what we would haue done, and our guidance what to doe, and how to doe it, muſt needs alſo be vnderſtood. Briefly, this eſtabliſhment is oppoſed to that breaking off of thoughts, and purpoſes, Iob 17.11. as it were a rooting of them vp, and plucking them aſunder, when as, namely, there is diſtraction, and perplexitie, and infelicity of ſucceſſe.
               
                  
                     Doct. 
                   To leaue the words then, wee come to the point, which you ſee, at firſt, breathes out comfort, and encouragement, that He who commits his workes vnto the Lord, ſhall haue his thoughts eſtabliſhed. For generall proofe wee are to looke againe vnto like places, Pſal. 37.5. Commit thy way vnto the Lord, and he ſhall bring it to paſſe; and Pſal. 55.22. Caſt thy burden vpon the Lord, and hee ſhall ſuſtaine thee. Prou. 3.6. In all thy wayes acknowledge him, and he ſhall direct thy paths. See how God is all in all to them that commit themſelues vnto him. Suppoſe we can goe lightly away with a charge of buſineſſe, yet we may haue rubs, and fall in our paſſage; why then, if we truſt him, hee will addreſſe our way, and bring vs proſperouſly to our journies end. Yea, ſuppoſe that we are heauily burdened in the way, why then hee will graciouſly eaſe vs, if wee lay it vpon him. But now left any ſhould thinke we are aduiſed to any fruitleſſe, or hopeleſſe performance, and that we may perceiue the extent of this promiſe, we will branch it forth into particulars,

and lay them ſide by ſide (as it were) vnto thoſe duties formerly commended vnto vs. Obſerue therfore, that as we are bound to commit our reſolutions, and our proceedings, and the ſucceſſe of all to God; ſo heere are incouraging promiſes anſwering to each of theſe.
               
                   Firſt, he that conſults with God for his warrant, and dares not attempt any thing before hee hath good ground for it, ſhall be inſtructed in the beſt courſe and the ſafeſt he can take. If we aske for the old way, which is the good way, Ierem. 6.16. and if we aske where we ought, viz. at Gods Oracle, the Law, and Teſtimony, Iſa. 8. then ſhall that be verified to vs which is promiſed, Iſa. 30.21. Thine eares ſhall heare a voice behinde thee, ſaying, this is the way, walke ye in it, when ye turne to the right hand or to the left. If wee hearken vnto the commands of God, and attend on him, then our peace ſhall bee as a Riuer, for God teacheth vs to profit, and leadeth vs by the way that wee ſhould goe, Iſa. 48.17, 18. Hee is the beſt counſellor (we heard before) and the wiſe man tells vs, that by counſell (Gods counſell then eſpecially) euery purpoſe is eſtabliſhed, Prou. 20.18.
               Now that this is ſo, we find both his people laying hold on theſe promiſes, and him alſo fulfilling them to his people. Dauid beſeecheth God to order his ſteps in his word, being confident that hee ſhould not be aſhamed when hee had reſpect vnto Gods commandements, Pſal. 119.6. By not being aſhamed, hee meanes that he ſhould not bee led into errour, nor be deluded, or fruſtrated of his

hope: for what cauſeth ſhame, but to be ſeene to haue fooliſhly, and idlely enterpriſed a buſineſſe? Againe, Pſal. 25.9, 10. he tels vs the Lord will teach the meeke his way, that is, thoſe who humbly yeeld themſelues to his teaching, and are not preſumptuouſly puffed-vp in ſelfe-conceit. And what way is it which he will teach? His wayes are mercie, and truth. As for experiences of the fulfilling of this promiſe, firſt take his (namely, Dauids) at Keilah once, at Ziglag another time. 1 Sam. 13.12. &amp; 10.8. So that no maruell hee was with God continually, and ſaid it was good for him to draw neere vnto God, Pſal. 73.28. The like experience we reade Vzziah the king had, who ſo long as he ſought the Lord (viz. by way of inquiry what to doe) be proſpered, 2. Chron. 26.5.
               
                   To paſſe on to the ſecond (becauſe I muſt bee ſhort in the confirmation of the truth of theſe promiſes) it is this: He that depends on God in the vſe of meanes, ſhall haue them fitted, and ordered for the beſt. Take but one, or two experiences, wherein this hath beene made good. Abraham, committed his ſeruants journey to God, and his ſeruant alſo, the diſpoſition, and proſpering of the meanes, Gen. 24. Now ſee there how admirably thoſe meanes were applied, which he referred to God. Iacob in faith made vowes to God, on condition that he would be with him in his way, Gen. 28. and ſee how God prouided the meanes of his kinde entertainment by his Vncle, as that he ſhould come to the Well, and Rachel about the ſame time, that he ſhould ſo opportunely doe her a curteſie,

&amp;c. Gen. 29. See this againe in the ſame Iacob, Ge. 33.10, 11. where God put into his head that moſt politicke courſe of ſending preſents to his brother. Who ſeeth not there an euident fulfilling of this gracious promiſe? Nay (to appeale to our ſelues) who is there of vs that walkes with God, and acknowledgeth him in his wayes, who hath not found it fulfilled vpon himſelfe? Many wayes doth God manifeſt his aſſiſtance in our working, as, 1. By giuing vs wiſdome to goe the right way to worke. 2. By bleſſing the inſtruments which we imploy. 3. By making times and ſeaſons and all occurrences to ſuit with our deſires. Wee are certainly either blinde, or very forgetfull, if we cannot ſay thus much out of experience. Yea, many times is not that true of vs, which is but fained of Timotheus the Athenian Captaine? Are not wee little better than aſleepe (as is ſaid hee was) when all things are brought into our net which we fiſh for? Doe not our buſineſſes thriue well vnder our hands, we cannot tell how, but only that prouidence will haue it to be ſo? How then ſhould this hearten vs, to wait on God, and truſt in him? ſeeing that the ſteps of a good man are ordered by the Lord, Pſal. 37.28.
               
                   The third branch of the promiſe hangs vpon the former, namely, that he that referreth the ſucceſſe of his actions to God, ſhall haue a good iſſue of them. They ſhall not only be ordered but perfected. The Scripture is plentifull in giuing aſſurances of this promiſe. Many examples formerly alleaged might be here repeated. Abrahams ſeruant

truſted God would eſtabliſh his thought, and God did ſo. Ioab committed the ſucceſſe of the battell to God, 2. Sam. 19.12. and obtained the victorie. Heſter depended vpon God, for her finding of fauour with king Ahaſhueroſh, and found it. 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   What ſhould I ſay more? Dauid and others in caſes of difficulty &amp; danger, haue found the proofe hereof: I waited patiently for the Lord, and he ſet my feet vpon a Rocke, and ſtabliſhed my goings, Pſal. 40.1, 2. Againe, when the Pſalmiſt had asked this queſtion; Who will riſe vp for me againſt the euill doers? (a queſtion ſubordinate to this, Vnto whom ſhall I commit my worke?) hee anſwereth, Vnleſſe the Lord had beene mine helpe, my ſoule had almoſt dwelt in ſilence; but when I ſaid, my foot ſlippeth, thy mercy O Lord held me vp, Pſal. 94.16, 17, 18. And yet ſomewhat more plainly: Becauſe thou haſt made the Lord, euen the moſt High, thine habitation, therefore no euill ſhall befall thee, for he ſhall giue his Angels charge ouer thee to keepe thee in all thy waies, Pſal. 91.9, 10, 11. How many ſuch probates of this truth might we finde in this booke! I will inſiſt no more vpon any of them, but will only propound the experience of Peter as a cleare confirmation of this promiſe, laid downe Luke 5.5, 6. Peter and others of his fellowes had beene toyling all night at their fiſhing worke, and had caught nothing: Chriſt bid him caſt out his net for a draught; at Chriſt his word (though otherwiſe he had little hope) he did it; thus committing his worke to Chriſt for the ſucceſſe of it, (yea another time euen for the ordering of the meanes, as caſting on the right ſide of the ſhip,

                  Iohn 21.6.) and what wonderfull ſucceſſe he had both times we may there reade. As it was with Peter in the worke of his fiſhing, ſo ſhall it be with Miniſters in their ſpirituall fiſhing, and with all of vs, in our ſeuerall emploiments, if we doe as he did, let God haue the managing of our worke, and beleeue him. Faith well grounded may wax bold, for it cannot but be welcome to God. O then let vs delight our ſelues in the Lord ſo ſhall we be ſure to haue our hearts deſire, Pſal. 37.4.
               
                   The certainty of this promiſe, as it is made to faith, is apparant: It is a
                     •
                   ſure looking to Prayer made in faith. Iehoſhaphat commended his worke to God in prayer, 2 Chron. 20. Nehemiah alſo his worke: and Ezra his, and the Iewes their way toward Ieruſalem, Ezra 8.22, 23. And all of them had their thoughts eſtabliſhed, as a multitude of Gods Saints beſides, whoſe well-ſpeeding ſhould be our ſpurre to their imitation. I neede not ſpeake more largely of this, becauſe it is but an expreſſion of our dependance on God.
               Now, by this time I doubt not, we haue drawne in the ſweetneſſe of this promiſe: yet for further ſatisfaction, ſearch we out the grounds why ſuch a promiſe of eſtabliſhment ſhould be annexed to our faithfull dependance on God: and ſurely as the reaſons why we ſhould truſt in, and pray to God, were taken from the Properties of God: ſo the reaſons why faith and praier haue this power with God may bee taken from the nature of faith and Praier.
               
               
                  
                     Reaſon. 
                   Firſt for Faith: That which carieth to God moſt

glory, that is the beſt meanes to bring backe to man the aſſured grant of a bleſſing: But it is faith whereby we moſt of all glorifie God (Abraham, being ſtrong in faith, gaue glorie to God, Rom. 4.20.) And the glory it giues him is manifold, viz. the glory of mercy, the glory of wiſdome, the glory of omnipotency, and the glory of truth.
               
               1. It aſcribes Mercy to him; otherwiſe durſt we be ſo bold with him, as to roule our burdens vpon him, did he not pitty our weakneſſe?
               2. It attributeth wiſdome to him; otherwiſe, would we put ouer difficult, and intricate affaires to him, did we not thinke he knew how to winde vs out of them?
               3. It builds vpon his omnipotency; how elſe durſt we truſt our weightieſt enterpriſes in his hand, did we not rely on his ſtrength?
               4. It celebrates his Truth, and ſets to its ſeale that God is true in this promiſe of eſtabliſhment. Now then Faith glorifying God ſo many waies, he who aboue all things tendereth his owne glory, cannot but make that good vnto vs wherein we thus honour him. Whereas on the other ſide God ſhould loſe much of his glory from vs and others, by giuing repulſe to our confidence; for thoſe attributes of his would ſoone bee queſtioned, yea much eclipſed. But ſhall it euer bee ſaid that the mercifull Lord ſhakes him off that depends vpon him? ſhall it euer be ſaid that the moſt wiſe Iehouah miſleads a man that followes him? Shall the vngodly haue cauſe to ſay that our God, who called Aegypt, and all humane ſtrengths, 
                     Ezek. 29.6, 7. 
                  broken reeds,

himſelfe deceiueth him that leaned on him? Shall it be ſuſpected that he who committeth a buſineſſe to God, is as he that ſendeth a meſſage by that fooliſh meſſenger (Prou. 26.6.) Who cutteth off the feet, and drinketh dammage? Or ſhall it be feared that he, who is called the fountaine of goodneſſe, and a ready helpe at all aſſaies, ſhould become, as waters 
                  
                     Iob 6.15. 
                  that faile? Or he who is a man of warre, a rocke immoueable 
                  
                     Pſal. 18.2.31, 32., ſhould bow vnder thoſe burdens we roule vpon him? No; farre be it from him: As his name is, ſo ſhall be euer his praiſe. Hee will not loſe a whit of his honour; And for that his honours ſake we may claſpe with his promiſe, and apply Dauids words, Pſal. 56.9. vnto our Text, When I commit my workes to God my thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſhed; this I know, for God is with me.
               
               
                  
                     Reaſon. 2 To the ſame effect we may reaſon for Prayer; For as Faith ſped well becauſe it brought glory to God: ſo ſhall the Praier of Faith ſpeede well, that wee may glorifie God afterward in praiſe and thankſgiuing. I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me, Pſal. 50.15. So, I will finiſh thine affaires for thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me. Shall men of ability take a faithfull care of orphanes, and other impotent creatures who caſt themſelues vpon them, and make ſuit for their tuition? and will God reiect our ſutes? If it was Auguſtus his praiſe that none came at any time diſcontented out of his preſence, ſhall it not be Iehouahs much more? Neuer was any Petition put backe where Chriſt is Maſter of requeſts to preſent it: neuer any cauſe caſt out of that Court where he is Aduocate to plead it.
               
                  Before any application can bee made, the doctrine muſt heere bee cleared of ſome exceptions taken againſt this indefinite propounding of it.
               
                  
                     Obiect. 1 For me thinkes I heare theſe demands: 1. May not that commiſsion be made to God, and yet this eſtabliſhment not follow vpon it? 2. May not this eſtabliſhment be found where no ſuch commiſsion went before it? The firſt of theſe queſtioneth the generality of this point; the ſecond, the peculiarity of it. To each of theſe a word.
               Firſt, whether all that practiſe this duty are partakers of this promiſe. It ſeemes not. For did not the Iſraelites conſult with God in that important affaire of theirs (Iudges 20.) and were they not twice diſcomfited; and almoſt diſheartened? Againe, doe not the people of God profeſſe their boaſting in God all day long, that is, their confidence in him (Pſal. 44.8.) and yet complaine in the next verſe that God had caſt them off, and went not forth with their armies? Beſides, how many faithfull prayers haue beene made in other particular caſes, and yet not this ordering, and accompliſhment enſued?
               
                  
                     Anſw. 
                   I anſwer: The promiſe may be ſure, and yet the time of fulfilling it vncertaine. God doth not limit himſelfe when to bring to paſſe our deſires, nor muſt we limit him. And many times indeed, hee ſuffereth our lawfull actions, and thoſe wherein we depend on him, to bee interrupted, and croſſed for a long time. But what then? Shall wee ſuſpect his faithfulneſſe? By no meanes. If wee doe ſo, it is a ſigne we doe not truſt him with our

buſineſſe as we ſhould: for will not he that thinks any one able, and wiſe enough to doe the thing it ſelfe, leaue the time of doing it to him alſo? Doubtleſſe if wee cannot effect what we would preſently, it is either becauſe in the ordinary diſpenſation of Gods prouidence, it cannot be done ſo ſoone, or if it could, it would not be ſo good for vs.
               Now for the Beniamites, we ſee that at length their worke proſpered, and why it did not ſooner wee may well gueſſe. For (ſay our Diuines) it is probable, that they had not throughly denied themſelues, but ſomething was defectiue, in their humiliation; and therefore we finde that whereas the firſt time they but inquired, the ſecond time, inquired and lamented, the third time they more ſolemnly faſted, and thereupon got the victory. Againe, it is not vnlikely that their enemies being ſo few, they were too confident in their ſtrength: God therefore, to let them know that all preparations without him are but vaine, let them a while ſee their weakneſſe. So that we may rather gather a leſſon of continuall dependance vpon God from them, than a cauill to infringe a promiſe. And as for the other inſtance, we ſee that for all Gods hiding himſelfe a long time, yet they forgot him not, but ſtucke cloſe to him, in their confident dependance.
               
                  Obiect. Yea, but ſometimes mens counſels are vtterly diſappointed, and this promiſe neuer made good. I anſwer, this promiſe neuer faileth if men faile not in any part, or circumſtance of their former

duty. But here is vſe of a diſtinction. Promiſes are either generall, or particular. Generall promiſes, made to all perſons; of which number this is one: but now ſome of theſe doe not hold in all caſes, for in ſome they are abſolute, in others conditionall. This in ſome caſes is but a conditionall promiſe, as namely when our workes, or affaires are ſuch as touch not our ſpirituall eſtate in the maine hold of it, but only this or that ciuill employment; and all conditionall promiſes haue their fulfilling reſerued to the pleaſure of God.
               To the point then, whether it be vncertaine I ſhall proſper in this worke or no, I ſay this, ſuppoſe I doe not proſper in it, yet the text remaineth good in theſe reſpects: 1. If wee commit our workes to God, wee muſt looke to the nature of them. If they be not ſuch as are abſolutely promiſed, we ought not abſolutely to beleeue the accompliſhment of them. Now to apply this by turning of it: Then only ſhall our thoughts bee eſtabliſhed abſolutely, when wee can abſolutely commit our workes to God without doubting. 2. If we fully roule our workes vpon God, our thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſhed, if not in the forenamed, yet, at leaſt, in another ſenſe, viz. our after thoughts and counſels; for if Gods working for vs be not according to our firſt thoughts, yet our ſecond thoughts ſhall be conformed, and fitted to his working, that is, hee will ſo ſatisfie vs in that particular that our thoughts ſhall be ſetled and we contented.
               To the ſecond doubt, whether none but theſe reſigners ſhall haue their thoughts eſtabliſhed, I

anſwer, yes, and that ordinarily. We finde it a ſcandall to the godly that the wicked do ſo proſper in their way, Ierem. 12.1. And they who are ſo farre from truſting God with their workes, that they aske what God can doe for them, yet haue their houſes filled with good things, Iob 22.17, 18. But what of all this? The promiſe only belongeth to the faithfull, and none but they can preſume, or with any reaſon looke to haue their thoughts eſtabliſhed. 2. The eſtabliſhment of thoughts, is vouchſafed in mercy only to them: to others, in judgement. The wicked are thereby more puffed vp in conceit of their owne power, and prudence, and policie: but the godly haue their eyes opened to ſee God the better, and the rather to acknowledge his prouidence. 3. They that worke without God, haue not their counſels and thoughts fully eſtabliſhed: for firſt they cannot be ſo eſtabliſhed when they are troubled, and diſtracted with cares, and feares; but ſo troubled they muſt needs be, when they want faith, which is it that ſetleth and compoſeth them. Secondly, how can their thoughts bee properly ſaid to be confirmed, when the Scripture tels vs, their expectation is ſuddenly cut off, and themſelues ſoone cut downe, yea gone in a moment? We find their eſtates called ſlippery,
                     Pſal. 73.18, 19 Iob 8.14. Pſal. 37.38. their workes, Spiders webbs, ſoone blaſted, ſoone ouerturned, ſoone vaniſhed, yea their name, and their poſteritie, and the inheritances which they leaue behinde for others, ſoone worne out, and ſcattered. Iudge we now whether their portion bee in this promiſe. Thus I hope, the doctrine is cleered.
               
                  
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   application then. As we formerly found out wha
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      were, that did not commit their workes to 
                     〈◊〉
                  , i
                     •
                   here we may deſcry their folly, for they that 
                     〈◊〉
                   the dutie, cannot haue the comfort of this 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Againe, committing our workes to God, 
                     〈◊〉
                   commended vnto vs as the beſt way, and ſureſt courſe for the attaining to thoſe ends which wee had in our thoughts, and therefore they muſt needs bee deemed vnwiſe, and fooliſh, who dreame of eſtabliſhment by other meanes, or without vſing theſe meanes. Diſcouer we their folly in particulars.
               Firſt, how can they looke for eſtabliſhment who deny not themſelues, but are confident in their owne ſtrength, and ability to carry their owne burden? God hath pronounced, that he reſiſteth the proud, 
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   and certainly their actions can neuer proſper whom God reſiſteth.
               As it is one point of his omnipotency to be able to doe what he will without let or hinderance: ſo it is another, to bee able to hinder whatſoeuer he is not pleaſed with. Now if they be not proud (and ſo of the number of thoſe whom hee will hinder) who hold themſelues able to moue without him, in whom they both liue, and moue, and who acknowledge no powerfull concurrence, or prouidence of him in their worke, who indeed, ſuſtaines both them, and it, if, I ſay, theſe be not proud, I know not who are.
               Yet more particularly, how can they looke for eſtabliſhment who enterpriſe any worke without Gods warrant, and approbation? Gods promiſes

are made to obedience, not to heady preſumption. He that asketh not Gods leaue, nor hath his conſent, hath none of his company. So hee told them that would needs goe vpon a peece of ſeruice without his command, Deut. 1.42. I am not among you, &amp;c. And he who is without God, and left alone to himſelfe, is likely to haue ſuch ſucceſſe as they had in that action.
               Againe, what a folly is it for a man to preſume that his affaires can be well managed or diſpoſed of when he runs vpon his owne head, and neuer hath any reſpect vnto God nor his guidance? It is not a ſufficient ground that ſuch an enterpriſe ſhall bee effected, to be aſſured that it is warranted or approued: He that giues vs leaue, vnleſſe he ſet vs in a right courſe and direct vs, we cannot but faile and falter in the manner of doing it. And will not he (thinke we) let vs alone when we thinke our ſelues able enough to contriue the only courſe, and deuiſe the beſt way to compaſſe it? Surely, we may looke that he will either infatuate our counſels, and beſot our minds, or elſe croſſe thoſe meanes which might otherwiſe, with his bleſſing, haue beene effectuall: Either wee ſhall goe the wrong way to worke, as Abſalom, in reiecting Ahithophels, and embracing Huſhai's counſell 2 Sam. 17.14.: or leane vpon poore tottering props, as the Philiſtims, committing their worke to Goliah who deceiued them, and could not make good his vndertakings 1 Sam. 1
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     .: Or if we vſe good meanes (without dependance on Gods bleſſing) and at length obtaine our deſires, yet wee are commonly like the children of Iſrael, going that iourney forty

yeeres, which perhaps might haue beene diſpatched in forty daies.
               Laſtly, who can expect eſtabliſhment, that thinke themſelues ſufficient to make an end of their buſineſſe, and depend not vpon God for the ſucceſſe of it? Will God ſuffer himſelfe to bee robbed of the praiſe of his wiſdome and power? He will not, but will lay open the weakneſſe of theſe men by ſcattering their deuices, and confounding their purpoſes, that they may learne, that with him onely are power, and ſtrength, and wiſdome, to eſtabliſh mans thoughts, and that though they take counſell together, it ſhall not ſtand but come to nought, Iſa. 8.10.
               Now if they cannot proſper who wait not on God, what ſhall we thinke of them that are angry both with God and others, when their actions are but a little croſſed? We read of Xerxes King of Perſia, who hearing that his bridge ouer Helleſpont was broken downe with the waues of the Sea, cauſed three hundred ſtripes to be giuen to the Ocean in way of reuenge. It may bee all will wonder at this madneſſe of his; and yet they are as mad who when their actions are croſſed, fall out with the inſtruments of their grieuance; For what doe they but behaue themſelues frowardly toward God? and therefore may feare that he wil be froward to them, and euen ſet his face againſt them for euill.
               
                  
                     Vſe. 2 Let vs, in the ſecond place, bee exhorted to beleeue this promiſe made to faithfull dependance on God, as before we were exhorted to that dependance. Giue we to God the glory as of his power and prouidence, ſo of his faithfulneſſe, and

ſet to our ſeale that God is true. He loues to bee truſted, and thoſe that truſt in him, knowing (as the Apoſtle ſaith) whom they haue truſted 
                  2 Tim. 1 1
                        •
                     . 
                  ſhall neuer be aſhamed of their confidence. Whether therefore our affaires be publike or priuate, let vs commit them to God. Commit we our trades vnto him, our ſtudies vnto him, the adminiſtration of euery office and function vnto him, eſpecially buſineſſes of greater either difficulty or danger vnto him. And becauſe I cannot ſtand to inſtance in particular caſes, let vs all as members together of one and the ſame body, commit the common affaires of the whole Church vnto God, and our ioynt deſires touching them, perſwading our ſelues that in ſo doing, the thoughts of our hearts ſhall be eſtabliſhed.
               
               What though many deſignes and ſeruices for the Church, are not for the preſent ſucceſſefull? Yet expect Gods worke. And the rather becauſe it is his vſuall courſe in theſe caſes, not to be ſeene till the laſt. Euen as the Roman Tria
                        •
                     ij (who were the ſtrength of the Army) neuer fought till the victory ſeemed to be hazarded: So the Trinity (in whom is the ſtrength of the Church Militant) make our extremity their opportunity. Now then cum ad Triada deuentum fuerit: when it is time for God to worke; as, Pſal. 119.126. no queſtion the wheele ſhall turne and the enemies of the truth ſhall be vndermoſt.
               Suppoſe the enemies get the better for a time, and many times foile the Lords hoaſt, yet they may ſay as Pyrrhus once did when he had conquered the Romans, Etiamſi deinceps &amp;c. Though we▪
                  
againe and againe ouercome (the Proteſtants) yet the finall ruine and downefall ſhall be our owne. In a word, Dauid hath no cauſe of fearing he ſhall fall one day by the hand of Saul: but Saul may be aſſured hee ſhall fall before Dauid; and when the time of eſtabliſhment commeth, then they that truſt in the Lord ſhall be as mount Zion which cannot be remoued, Pſal. 125.1.
               
                  
                     Vſe. 3 Whenſoeuer we finde this promiſe fulfilled, and that our actions haue thriued vpon our committing them to God, then forget not to be thankfull, and to acknowledge by whom our workes were wrought. And not onely ſo, but let our experience teach vs ſo much the more confidently to depend vpon him for after times. Obſerue this in Gods people, Iſay 26.12. Lord thou wilt ordaine peace for vs, for thou haſt wrought all our workes for vs: Faith here drawes an argument of aſſurance for time to come from time paſt.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

