
   
      
         
            An oration of Ihon Fabritius Montanus VVherby he teacheth that Christian men cannot resorte to the Councel of Trent, without committing an haynous offence. Englyshed by L.A.
            Fabricius, Joannes, Montanus, 1527-1566.
         
         
            
               1562
            
         
         Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00522
            STC 10657
            ESTC S111789
            99847059
            99847059
            12066
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00522)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12066)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:09)
         
         
            
               
                  An oration of Ihon Fabritius Montanus VVherby he teacheth that Christian men cannot resorte to the Councel of Trent, without committing an haynous offence. Englyshed by L.A.
                  Fabricius, Joannes, Montanus, 1527-1566.
                  L. A., fl. 1562.
               
               
                  Newelye set forth and allowed, accordynge to the order appoynted in the Quenes Maiestyes Iniunctions. Anno. 1.5.62.
               
               [64] p.   
               
                  In Powles Churcheyard by [J. Cawood for] Humfrie Toye, dwellynge at the sygne of the Helmet],
                  [Imprynted at London :
                  1562.
               
               
                  Translated from Latin by L.A.
                  Imprint from colophon. Printer's name from STC.
                  Cawood's initials, "IC", are in a factotum at the bottom of the title page--STC.
                  Running title reads: An oration agaynst the Councel of Trent.
                  Signatures: A-D.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Council of Trent (1545-1563) --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ¶ AN Oration of Ihon Fabritius Montanus.
VVherby he teacheth that Chriſtian men cannot reſorte to the Councel of Trent, without committing an haynous offence.
Englyſhed by. L. A. ☜ (⸫) ☞
            ¶ Newelye ſet forth and allowed, accordynge to the order appoynted in the Quenes Maieſtyes Iniunctions.
            
               Anno. 1. 5. 62.
               
                  I C
               
            
         
         
            
            
            ¶ The Preface of the Tranſlatour to the Reader.
            
               
                  IOHN Fabritius Montanus, a man as it appeareth both lerned and zelous, at what time this laſt generall Counſell was ſolemly proclamed and publyſhed to be holden at Trent by thaucthoritie of the Pope, ſeing ſuch large placardes and priuileges of ſafeconduicte, for al nations to reſorte thither, ſo formally by him ſent abroad in euery quarter, and fearing leſt emongeſt the people of God ſome ſuch as were ſimple, might thereby eaſelye be entrapped, and vnder the glorious name of their priuileges, fall into their enemies handes, thoughte it good yea to be his duetie alſo beynge him ſelfe a miniſtre of the Churche of God, not onelye to publyſhe to the chriſtian worlde, that if they ſhould ioine them ſelues with thys denne of theefes

and Sinagoge of Sathan where Antichryſt himſelf. 
                  •…
               etteth as Iudge it ſhould not be onelye perillous for theyr owne perſons, but alſo contumeliouſe to the maieſtie of God, hurteful to theyr neyghbours, yea and iniuriouſe to Gods truth. The whych thyng truly (in my opinion) he hath ſo fully, ſo eloquently, ſo compendiouſlye, and ſo ſufficientelye done in this ſhorte oracion, that this onelye maye wel ſuffice to harneſſe anye man agayne the ſubtil perſwaſions of oure aduerſaryes, and to ſtrengthen otherwyſe the weake conſciēces of Gods people, who thoughte it theyr bounden duetye, to be preſente at ſuche aſſemblyes there to dyſpute of matters of Religion, or at the leaſte wyſe to propone or make proteſtacion of theyr ſaith. This oracion althoughe it were by Iohn Fabritius Montanus publiſhed in Latin, to al that vnderſtode that tonge in due tyme before the councell was fullye aſſembled, ſo that thereby ſome fruit and commoditie was or myght haue been taken thereof, yet I thou ghte it not altogether vnprofitable nowe alſo to tranſlate the ſame into our Engliſhe tong to thend

that ſuch as are vnlearned and ignoraunt in thother may ſée the cenſure and iudgement of this learned man, in this behalfe eſpecially ſeing euen thunlearned of our aduerſaries do ſo much at thys daye crye out for generall Councels, for the ſtabliſhment of religion, and geue ſo muche credyte and aucihoritie to them as to the moſt holy worde of God.
            Take this (gentle reader) for the fyrſte fruictes of my labour, vntyl ſuche tyme as God by hys heauenly dewe ſhall multyply and increaſe the ſame.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ¶ An Oration of Ihon Fabritius Montanus, whereby he teacheth that Chriſtien men can not reſort to the Councell of Trent, without committing an haynous offence.
            
               HAuinge alwaies wythdrawen my mynde from trouble ſome conſultations, in this ſo great a broyle both of mindes and ſtudies, I thought it good to be in quiet and at reſt vntill ſuch time as I might frely both in truth and conſcience do the ſaine, eſpecyally becauſe I knewe well enough that men both of excellent wit and learninge haue he therto pleaded &amp; defended this oure common cauſe mightelye, and with ſuche greate

force, as was ſufficient and able to breake the fearcenes of our aduerſaries. But this notwithſtandyng, their malapart and leude bragges haue at the length vanquiſhed and broken of thys my longe ſylence.
            They are now aſſembled at Trent wherevnto they do call verye arrogantly by a cercayne wryting publickely to that ende ſet forth at Venyſe, all and euery of vs whiche do profeſſe the Goſpell of Chryſt: whiche thing truelye is not at all to be meruailed at, ſeing they (according to their aucthoritie which to themſelues they do chaleng and vſurpe) do imperiouſly tryumph both ouer Kynges and Monarches. But yet they handle this their cauſe ſo craftely &amp; ſubtilly that vnleſſe their put poſes be preuented it is a great halſard, &amp; to be feared leſt there wt thei begile ſuch as be ſimple. Now therfore

the time requireth that good men ſhoulde arme them ſelfes and ioyne their powers and force together. In thys armye or expedicion if I were aſſigned only to go with the cariage, truely I woulde willingly take it vpon me. But forſomuch as we are ſet vpon and aſſalted of our enemies by ambuſſhes, I thinke it good yt we fight aloofe, the whyche thinge I woulde the Chriſtian reader (to whom I now ſpeake) to vnderſtand leſt any man ſhould ſclaunderouſlye ſay yt I did refuſe againe yt battaile which euen nowe I ſemed ſo haſtly to requyre.
            Our enemies haue choſen Trent as a place for theyr am buſhes, in my opinion truelye not much vnlike to the forkes or Gibettes of Caudis, wherinto whē the Romaine hoſtes had ron hedlong being entrapped by the pollicie of theyr enemies, thei

made amendes for theyr folye with theyr old accuſtomed manhod and proweſſe. Thoſe forkes of Caudis, thoſe Dennes I meane of Counciles haue ſondrye tymes deceaued and endomagid oure menne. It is tyme therefore that wee ſhoulde at the length awake, and wyth wyſedome take head of and foreſee thoſe wyles whyche once or twyſe we haue alreadye felte. Yet notwythſtandynge in the meane tyme ſuche as are ſimple muſt be taughte, why we ſeynge oure enemyes wyll not encounter wyth vs in playne batcayle, oughte not to goo into their campes leſt we ſhoulde ſeme by forſakynge oure ſtandinge to forſake alſo the ryghte of oure cauſe. If I therefore ſhall alſo take vpon me to teache this thinge, what teacher of ye goſpell cā accuſe or blame me but he muſte alſo accuſe and blame himſelfe

of neglectynge and lettynge paſſe his owne office and dewety. For howe manye ſoeuer wee bee in nomber, we are called euerye one vnto this Councile, what meruaile is it then if I thinke that whyche we al and euery one of vs are equal lye carged with, to be alſo common to me aſwel as to the reſt of the miniſters of the church, (that is to ſay) to wytneſſe and declare to the Chriſtyan worlde that there can no iuſte and mete cauſes be founde for vs to go to this Councile, but rather that innumerable and great cauſes may be ſhewed to eſche we and fiye the ſame. For there is none ſo doltiſhe, who dothe not ſee, that there canne be no iuſt cauſe, why any mā ſhould haſſarde and caſt himſelfe into open peryll which is ioyned with the damage of the truth, the contumely of God &amp; the harme of his neighbour.

In a matter ſo playne and manifeſt, I neade not longe to ſtand aboute the profe thereof. The holye men of God do knowe that all Chryſtian actions, are chyefelye to be referred to thonely Glorye of GOD as to a marke, from the whiche if they go a wrye it muſt neades be that both ye truth muſte be in haſſarde and the healthe of the ſoule alſo in daunger and ieopardye. But here ſome may doubt whether our going to Trent (if we mynded to goo thither) doo bringe therewith theſe diſcomodities or not. I therefore haue taken in hande in this preſent Oration to proue that this iourney whenſoeuer we ſhould take it vpō vs (whiche God almighty of his clemency defende) ſhalbe not onelye ful of peril and daunger, but alſo contumeliouſe and iniuriouſe both againſte Goddes truth, yea God him ſelfe,

and alſo oure neyghboure. And as touching the greatnes of the peril, truely I would ſay nothing therof, if it were ſuche a kinde of perill as had in it any profyt or deutie, for it is manifeſt that the holy Martyres of God when nede required haue willingly ſuffred euen deathe. But nowe wher there is a manifeſt daū
               ger ioyned with a manifeſt impietie the matter is not like. Concerning therefore the perill thereof I wil breefely recite that which ſhall ſuffyſe. And here firſt of all I haue to ſpeake of the place appoynted for the Counſel, for the which the Chriſtian Princes haue long yea &amp; that earneſtly trauailed but all in vaine that ſome free Citie of Germanye ſhould be aſſigned. But ſeinge that they cannenot hetherto be gotten forth of the boundes of Italie, noo not to thoſe places which are ſurely

defended with thaucthoritie and faythfull promiſe both of Themperour, and alſo of all the Princes of Germany, who (I beſech you) ſhall cauſe vs to go to them which haue ſhewed ſo many lamentable examples both of breach of fayth and alſo of crueltie. But ſome peraduenture will ſay, that thaucthoritie of the princes or of Themperour will cauſe theſe felowes to kepe thē ſelues within their boundes. He is deceyued truelye that ſo thinketh, for their is noo lykelyhode that they who hitherto haue made of kinges and Princes a ieſtinge ſtocke▪ wyll nowe do any thing at their requeſt or for their ſakes. But what ſaftye or truſt can there be repoſed in thē who be perſwaded that it is no ſin at al to kyll vs, who alſo although againſt their will they ſhoulde abſtaine from doing vs open violence

and force, yet can eaſely finde other ſlightes, wherof the Romiſh Court hath of long time profeſſed her ſelfe to be a Scolemaiſtres. This much ſhall ſuffiſe concerninge the place: Nowe let vs come to thē who haue gaged their faith in this matter, &amp; who wil ſeme to haue prouided for vs, &amp; warrented vs by publicke ſatiſfaction or inſtrumēt. Dimmortal god with what &amp; howe vaine titles do they boſt them ſelues moſte ambiciouſlye abroad, A ſmall nomber of Byſhops, yea and amonge them ſome counterfaicte and diſguiſed, and yet al of them beynge the creatures of the Biſhop of Rome, and ſuche alſo as be accuſed of vs, both of forſaking of Religion and alſo of oppreſſyng and treadynge vnder fote ye truth, dare cal themſelues general, holy &amp; Apoſtoloque, &amp; finally chaleng to thēſelues al wholy ſuche

thinges whereof it is euidente they haue not one iote. But who wyll truſte them any whit at all, whyche ſtumble ſo ſhamefullye euen in the verye begynnynge of theyr ſafetye whyche they promyſe. Do not they the lyke (I beſeche you) as thoughe a certayne rable of moſte wycked raſkalles whoo were themſelues accuſed to be worthye to loſe theyr lyfe and goodes ſhould call Themperoure himſelfe and all the eſſtates of Thempyre to a generall dyet and aſſemblye promiſing them a mooſte large ſafe conduicte and appoynte vnto him a daye to aunſwere to his playnte. If then the title of a generall Councell cannot iuſtelye be attributed vnto a certen few perſons who be accuſed of corrupte religion, thē is it not laweful alſo for them vnder the name of a general Councell to geue forth any

lawefull warrant of ſafetye. Now therefore it is not in queſtion of the forme of the warraūte, but whither they haue ryghte or power to make any ſuche warraunte or not. For if ſome olde craftye foxe ſhoulde geue forthe pryuilegies were they neuer in ſo good a form, yet forſomuch as he had no power at all to graunte anye ſuche, the forme thereof muſte neades bee in daunger wyth the ryghte. It fauleth not therefore in conſideracion onelye what euerye one promiſeth, but with what right &amp; aucthoritie he promiſeth. I know well enoughe that they referre all their doinges to the Romyſhe Byſhoppe as chiefe and heade who is one all accordynge to the commen ſayinge. Vbi Papa, ibi vniuerfalis Synodus. Where the Pope is, there is alſo the general Councell, but howe falſely and how wickedly this Romiſhe

Byſhop dothe vſurpe al theſe things it is ſo wel knowen yt there neadeth no profe thereof. As for me trulye, wyth howe muche the more aucthorytye they forniſhe this their Byſhoppe and their Counciles, ſo muche the leſſe hope and confidence I haue in their promyſe. For if the Romiſhe Byſhoppe maye do what he liſte, and he onelye maye (by his hyghe power whyche is geuen to him) acquyte and ſette free Kynges and Emperours from theyr others promiſſes, and covenauntes, what ſhoulde let him not to vſe thys his righte in his owne cauſe, and to order and meaſure the rule of his promyſe accordynge to his owne luſte. And who is hee that knoweth not that the Byſhoppes of Rome haue hitherto wyth theyr othes and bulles mocked vs and that Scotfree. Moreouer that clauſe whyche concerneth

the penaltye agaynſte the breakers of theyr ordynaunces ſemeth to be verye obſcure and full of doubtes and ambiguitie. What yf they (ſuche is theyr good wyll towards vs) ſhal complaine then chiefelye that we do hurt them when thei wyllynglye do wrong and Iniurie vs, who ſhall then ſpeake for vs, who ſhal take oure matter in hand, who ſhal defende oure cauſe in that place whyche is ſo noy ſome to oure menne wyth the Byſhoppe of Romes Garriſons. They beare the name of a generall Councile, and of Apoſtolique men, but yf anye man couvince them of a lye doubteles he ſhall be accuſed of breakinge and violating the ſame. They catche to thē ſelues alone ye title of ye Church, but yf anye man ſhould take in hand to proue thē the ſworne enemies of the Churche, or reproue theyr fylthy life

and conuerſacion he ſhould be foūd faultye of treſpaſinge agaynſt their ſafeconduicte. Ther be many other thinges lyke to theeſe, whyche we cannot kepe in ſilence wtout doing greate harme, and whyche they on the other ſide cannot heare without great rage and madneſſe. For how meke and how gentle theſe fathers be, Fraunce witneſſeth. Englande beareth recorde, and this execrable bocherye ſo latelye executed vppon oure brethren at Vaſſye ſheweth forth a good teſtimonye. Theſe holye Fathers I ſaye do ſo thirſte for our ſoule healthe, that they do euen therewyth ſuppe vp oure bloude alſo. This alſo is not to bee let paſſe, that that forme of promyſe whyche was laſt printed at Brixia, by what Inquiſitours lycence I cannot tell, doth muche vary and diſſent from that whych was printed at Veniſe.

For in that of Brixia, there is a certayne addicion ioyned thereto entituled Extenſio ad alias naciones, yt is to ſay a thing touchyng other nacions, whyche retracteth and calleth backe agayne all that a litle before was licenced to al nacions in comō, yea and whyche more is, in the ſelfe ſame addicion, all other nacions ar warraunted by the ſelfe ſame forme and the verye ſame wordes wherewhythe the Germaynes are, and yet this is added, that this fourme pertayneth not but vnto ſuche onelye as wyl repente their erroures, and come home agayne into the boſome of the Churche whyche oughte to be open to al menne. Who that hath anye wyt in his head perceiueth not theſe gyles and deceyies. The ſelfe ſame forme whereby the people of Germanie are warraunted pertayneth indifferentelye and equallye to

alother nations, and yet no ſafety is graunted to thother nacions vnleſſe they be mynded to retorne to the Romyſhe Churche. Therefore conſequently neither to the people of Germany vnleſſe they vnyte thē ſelfes to the Churche of Rome. For the publique promyſſe endeth with the forme wherein it is coutayned. And thus muche I thinke ſufficiently ſpoken touchinge the perill &amp; daunger of the Iorney, for this matter requireth no lenger de batynge ſeyng that reſpect muſt be had not ſo much to the peryll and daunger, as to the truthe and the glorye of God.
            It remayneth therefore that I ſhoulde couſequenlye declare, that with this certaine and aſſured daū
               ger, there is alſo ioyned a moſt manifeſt and plaine abiuring and denying of the truth. And leaſt anye

man ſhould doubt hereof, let hym thinke and conſider, that al Chriſtian actions ar to be referred to ther determinate endes. And that this is thend of Councels that the faultes of doctryne and manners ſhuld be reformed and finallye peace and concord (reſeruing alwaies the rule of pietie) ſhoulde be reſtored in the Churche. Seing therefore the caſe ſtandeth thus, a Chriſtian manne ought to ioyne hym raſhely to no aſſembles, which he ſhal vnderſtād to be occupied about anye matters repugnant vnto this ende. If then I ſhall nowe plainely declare that theſe fathers of Trent, are aſſembled together not to open &amp; make manifeſt the truth, but to hide and darken the ſame, not to reforme &amp; amend the church but to deforme &amp; deface ye ſame, I haue alſoſufficiētly proued that Chriſtian men cannot

wythoute committing an haynous cryme ioyne themſelues to ſuche. And here fyrſte of all thynges conſider wyth me (I praye you) who is he that hath appoynted and called together theſe aſſemblyes and meetinges, Truly the Biſhop of Rome, who in this buſines hathe vſed all ſtudye and diligence, and ſpared no labor nor coſte. And to what ende (I beſech you) doth he al theſe thinges? To that ende (thinke you) to ouerthrowe or diminiſhe hym ſelfe or his power? Who ſo truely can ſuffie him ſelfe to be perſwaded in this poynte, ſemeth to me to be madde and contrary to reaſonne. For it is notlykely that the Biſhop of Rome will wittingly and willinglye procure his own deſtructiō. What meneth than this great preparation of Councels? Truely to ſhore vp to eſtablyſhe and as long as they can

by any meanes, to reſtore to his old dignitie and brauery, the Papacye which now meanaceth ruyne and decaye and hath a good whyle ſence begonne to fall thorough the great hewgines and monſtruous byggenes therof, and alſo to make the whole Chriſtian world ſubiect to their lawes and ſtatutes.
            For if the Germans were ſubdued then do they thinke it lyght.
            The reſt of Europe for to yoke and bring in bondage quyght.
            And ſo as Lordes of mydde earth ſea. the rule to clayme aryght.
            Or at the leſt wiſe if the Byſhoppe of Rome perceaued hys hope to be fruſtrate therein, and powre alſo to faile him to bring that enterpriſe to paſſe, yet notwithſtanding he wold ſet Chriſtian menne and eſpecially the Germannes at deadely hatred one with another, and then would he ſet ſtill in his chayre, and behold thys miſerable Tragedie. For this

ſemeth to him the redieſte waye to dryue awaye this Lutheranicall maddeneſſe (for that is theyr phraſe of ſpeache) from Italye. And here I call to remembraunce certen verſes of Virgill feately ſeruinge to this purpoſe.
            A Councel great he calls, and from the toppe of ſtable hye. 7. Aeneid.
            
            The ſhepardes watche and herdmans blaſt he blewe with Hellyſhe crye.
            In cryncled horne, whereat a heape forthwith without delaye.
            Of Chriſtianes ſtirted with weapons thicke runne armed euery waye.
            When he his promyſe thus performed with bloud the warre hath fylde,
            And fynyſht eke of battayle fyrſt the funeralls as he wyld.
            The fathers of the Councell all he proudely ſayth vnto.
            Beholde what diſcordes I haue wrought. with heauy warre and wo.
            Bidde them in frendeſhip ioyne, in league eche one to other bounde.
            For I with bloud of Germans ſlayne haue ouer ſpreade the grounde.
            This more I adde (for your good will. ryght well nowe do I knowe.)
            In border townes with rumours blowen great battayles wil I ſowe.
            And kindle eke there hartes with heate

and loue of raginge warre.
            And ſcatter armoure in eche fielde that aydes may come from farre.
            Theeſe thynges truelye woulde I neuer haue ſpoken vnleſſe they wer both euident and manifeſt enough. And I neade not to fetche my witneſſes farre hence wher the thinge it ſelfe is ſo apparaunte. For the Byſhoppe of Rome him ſelfe dothe not hide or diſſemble that his onely entente is, to brynge all men at the lengthe to the feloweſhyppe and ſocietie of the Churche of Rome, but he exhorteth earneſtely al Prynces and Kynges to be readye to aſſiſte him therein. And yf anye manne be yet in doubte of the Popes wyl and mynde, let him reade thoſe thinges whyche he propoſed by his Ambaſſadours this laſte monethes paſſed vnto the Common wealth of ye three Leagues, &amp; he ſhal plainly perceaue yt I haue told the truthe. Moreouer the Pope doth not hūble himſelf or

acknowledge hym ſelfe ſubiecte to thaucthoritie of a Councell, but hath the fathers of the Councel ſub iecte vnto him and bounde alſo vnto him by a moſt ſtraight oth, wher of I thought good to ſhewe here a coppy, that al men maye the better vnderſtand, that theſe Romaniſtes haue theyr myndes buſely occupyed not about the reforminge of the Churche but about theſtabliſhing of their tyrannicall kyngdome.
            
               The forme of the othe.
               I Beinge elected Biſhop, from thys howre forewarde wilbe faithfull &amp; obedient to Saincte Peter, and to the holy Apoſtolique Churche of Rome, and alſo to our Lorde the Pope and hys ſucceſſours which entre that rome canonicallye. I will be in no Counſayle, no conſente nor deade, whereby they ſhoulde loſe theyr lyfe, or any membre of their body, or yet be taken, or elſe that anie

forte or violence ſhould anie maner of wai, bi what pretēce orcolor ſo euer doune vnto them. But ſuche ſecretes wherwyth they ſhal credite me, eyther by themſelues theyr meſſaungers or theyr letters, I wil not open to anye manue to endomage them wyſtyngelye. I wylhe a helper and an ayder to them agaynſte al men to kepe and defende the Papacy of Rome and the royaltyes of Sayncte Peter. I wyll honorablye vſe the Legate of Thapoſtolique See both goinge and cominge, and helpe him in all his neceſſityes. I wyll doe my dylygence to keeye, defende, encreaſe and ſet for warde the ryghtes, honoures, Pryuileges, and aucthoritye of the church of Rome, oure Lorde the Pope and his ſucceſſoures aforeſayde, I wyll bee in no councile no facte, nor treatie, wherin any thynge ſhalbe deuyſed ſiniſtre or preiudiciall to theyr perſons, theyr ryghte, theyr honor theyr eſtate, or theyr power. And if I ſhall knowe anye man to goe aboute or procure anye ſuche thynges, I wyl to my power hinder theyr enterpryſes, and ſo ſoone as I canne conuenientlye I wyll notifye the ſame to oure Lorde, or to ſome

other by whom it may come to his know ledge. I wil with all induſtrye and end euor obſerue and kepe the rules of our holy fathers, thapoſtolique decrees, their ordinaunces, their ſentences, their appoint ments, their exceptions, their Prouiſos and commaundemētes, and cauſe others alſo to obſerue and kepe the ſame. I will alſo to my power perſecute and reſiſt heretyckes, ſcyſmatykes, and ſuch as are re bells agaynſt oure Lorde and his ſucceſſours aforeſayde, when I am called to a Synode I wyll come. And this is the forme of the othe, Nowe therefore ſeing that the Biſhop of Rome doth call and referre allawes to him ſelfe alone, and ſeing alſo yt the fathers of the Councell doo frame them felues altogether to his becke and commaunde mente, as one that beareth aboute with him in ye ſecretes of his breſt the determinations both of Gods lawe and mans lawe (for theſe and other ſuch monſtruous and execrable

ſayinges are red emonge theyr lyes and inuentions) it mighte be iuſtly demaunded to what ende or what nede there were of this maſking preparation of Councels, vnleſſe ye matter it ſelf ſemed to ſpeake and experience did alſo teache that Councels are nothing elſe but a certaine forme and maner of declaration of the Popes wil, and (as one would ſay) a ſhorte and compendious way to procede againſt the Lutherans. For thus it is red in their bokes, that it is not neceſſary to cal Councels to ye entent yt any of thoſe opinions whervpon the Heritikes deſire to diſpute (and who knoweth not that we are accuſed of them of hereſye) ſhoulde be defyned, but that it is neceſſary to cal Councels notwithſtāding to thend that ſuch as are Heretikes may be declared made manifeſte, and condemned.

Thys might be euident enough vnto vs euen by thactes done in their Councels, althoughe they woulde ſpeake nothing therof. For beſides that they haue hitherto mooſt deſpiteſully aggrauated our cauſe wt moſte vniuſt ſentences, they haue alſo geuen vp oure liues &amp; goodes as a pray to the crueltie of others, and they referre this their boocherye to the right and lawe of execution, the which they haue hitherto vſed as a thefe engine to weaken &amp; ſhake vs all to peeces. For it hath bene alwayes a ſolempne cuſtome with theſe good felowes to begyn their Councels backeward &amp; prepoſterouſly (that is to ſay) firſte with execution, ſo that al men might eaſslye perceaue yt they did make there reckoninge of warre before they thought of peace. And theſe latter yeares paſt after al their promiſes

ſo manye and ſo noble made vnto our men, whyle the Councile was yet dependinge, they beganne to rage agaynſte the diuines of Germanye, and doubteleſſe they hadde ſhewed forthe theyr madneſſe yet further, had not the troubles of Germanye cauſed bothe the Councile &amp; ther enterpriſes alſo to ende. And yet in the meane tyme althoughe it be moſte apparaunte and manifeſte that the Churche of Rome is foulye and ſhamefullye defaced both wyth corrupt doctrine and manners, and that this complainte hath bene euer ſythens the memorye of man, and from our aunceſtres hath diſcended vnto vs, as though by inheritaunce yet notwythſtandynge in ſo greate a corrupcion of all thynges, not ſo muche as the leaſte kynde of reformacion coulde bee optayned or by anye meanes wreſted from our aduerſaries,

yea experience alſo hath taught, that thoſe alſo, which at any tyme haue bene ſo bolde to preſent vp this requeſt to the fathers, haue not onely bene moſt vnworthelye entreated, but alſo moſt deſpitefully repulſed. And as touching the lyfe of the cleargye, I wyll not muche diſpute, for I maye iuſtlye doubt whether I may with honeſtie ſpeake ſuch things as they moſt ſhamefully do commit, and yet notwithſtandyng albeit the caſe ſtandeth thus and euery man alſo ſeeth it ſo to be, yet neuertheleſſe, they do glory of the holy Ghoſt, as of ſome vile ſlaue or bondman, whom they haue made ſo much thrall vnto thē ſelfes, that although he woulde neuer ſo fayne, yet maye he not once be frō theyr elbowe, whoſe marke they carrye in theyr bodye that neuer canne be put oute. But howe

farre, yea howe moſt fartheſt of all they haue gone aſtraye from the doctryne of the Prophetes &amp; Thapoſtles, no man is ignoraunt, if he haue bene but meanely exerciſed wt any ryght iudgemente in the wrytynges of the Prophetes and Apoſtles. Theſe felowes haue Heauen, Earth, Hell, and all thynges elſe to ſale, ſo that the ſayinge of the Poete maye be iuſtlye veryfied of the Churche of Rome.
               She ſtandeth to ſale, and like a whore
               ſitteth making her gaine of her body.
               And yet neuertheleſſe they ſaye it is not lawefull to make anye enquyrye agaynſte theyr Doctryne, without cōmitting an hainous ofſence, &amp; therfore in ye publiſhinge of

theyr Councile, they ſpake of a continuacion thereof and not of a full and perfecte doynge. The whyche they interprete in this wyſe. That theyr former doinges muſte be confirmed ratified and concluded ſo as they neither maye nor oughte hereafter to be called in queſtion. Theſe and ſuche other lyke be the thynges whereby the Chryſtian faith is pulled vp by the rotes. The forme alſo whythe they preſcrybe to the reſt of theyr treatye dothe manifeſtlye declare what workemen they be and what they frame. That which is thus.
               
               
                  And to be noted that ſuch matters as are in controuerſie ſhalbe handled and entreated of in this foreſayde councile of Trente accordyng to the holy Scriptures, the tradicions of Thapoſtles, thapproued Counciles, the conſent and agremente of the Catholicke Church, and thauctorytyes of the holy Fathers.
               
               
                  
By this meane as by a pryuye vndermininge engine the cloſelie proceade to ouerthrow the doctrine of Godlines. For from the Scripturs they go aboute to ſende vs backe to tradicions, from a thynge moſt certayne to a thinge more vncertayne. But yet they do this verye craftelie and with greate diſſimulacion. For they ſpreade abroade into the common peoples eares, that al theyr diſputacion is not about thaucthority of ye Scripture, but about ye maner of thinterpretaciō therof, &amp; therfore yt this appendix or addicion was to be added, that it mighte playnelye appeare that the true and naturall ſence of the Scripture ought not to be taken forth of any mans pryuate brayne but of the conſent and agremēt of the whole Churche. Se how theſe felowes haue al at ones caſt of al ſhame. We do not refuſe thagremente

of the pure Churche conſentyng wyth the Scripture, but reuerentlye embrace the ſame. But oure chefeſt controuerſy with our aduerſaryes whyche abuſe the woorde or name of the Churche, is about the certaynetye and aucthorytye of the Scripturs. For they whē they haue once preſumed to take the Scripture to be vnperfecte, they do forthe wyth inferre that it is alſo vncertayne, and therefore they ſaye that it hathe neade not onelye to be ſupplyed wyth tradicions, but alſo to be determined and eſtabliſhed by the Churche. We on thother ſide do teache that the holye Scryptures, the very word of God (I ſaye) comprehended in wrytyng, doth perfectly and ſufficiently contayne in it ſelf al the chiefe poyntes of our ſalnaciō, and therfore that this is thonlye certayne and infallible rule to examine

al doctrynes &amp; opinions. And thus it is playne and manifeſt vpō what poynt this controuerſie dependeth. For the queſtiō is whether the ſcripture be of greater perfectiō certaintie, &amp; aucthoritie or yt tradicions, by what name ſoeuer they cal thē whiche notwtſtāding they haue boūded &amp; limitted almoſt wt the lyuely wordes of Thapoſtles, ye cuſtome of the Church, yt anſwers of ye biſhops and ye determinacions of ye fathers, but by what ryghte or wronge it is not now to be ſpokē. But if ye Scriptur which we preſently haue, be ye voyce of yt prophetes &amp; apoſtles lefte vnto vs in writing, If the Church be gathered together, knowen &amp; preſerued by this doctrine whiche is the word of God. If Coūciles haue for ye more part erred, &amp; maye yet erre
                     •
                   and as it were doe kill one another wyth mutuall decrees, If the Biſ
                  
                     •…
                  ops of Rome for the ſpace of ſome

hundrethes of yeres paſt haue done nothing well, nor from henceforth perchaunce can do any thinge well, ſo longe as they occupye and enioy this peſtilente See, If finallye the fathers them ſelfes, which be of the better ſort do ſende vs to the ſcryptures. Tell me (I beſeche you for Gods ſake) what cauſe can their be any more, why we ſhould ſuffre ourſelues to be caryed and ledde away from the Scriptures vnto tradicions, from a thinge certaine to that which is more vncertayne. And albeit the caſe ſtandeth thus as you ſee, yet theſe vnholye felowes are not aſhamed yet ſtil to ſai that ther controuerſy with vs is onelye touchyng thinterpretation &amp; not thaucthoritie or certentie of the Scryptures. The which thing if they wyll graunt vnto vs, they muſt neades alſo confeſſe them ſelfes to be dryuen

awaye from theyr chefeſt bulwarke. For yf we muſt wholye reſt in thaucthoritie of the Scripture, then away with al other by waies and ſtartinge holes wherein they put al the whole ſtrength and ſome of their diſputation. But (you wyl ſay) the Scripture hath nede of interpretaciō. I agre therto. Againe, it maketh much to ye matter what ſenſe euery man frameth thereto. True it is in deade. But ſeing the Scripture doth interprete and expounde it ſelfe, we wil alſo vſe that rule of interpretation which it ſelfe hath heretofore taught vs, and we will not herevnto bryng any other thinge, then faith and loue ioyned with ſobre and ſyncere dexteritie. But I am gone further thē I purpoſed, for to entreate hereof requyreth both an other place and alſo tyme, But this one thing I ſaye.

If theeſe felowes take the Scriptures to bee of ſuche aucthoritie as they make a ſhew and countenaūce of. Whye do they not leaue that to vs as an onelye rule, whye do they reſtrayne it wyth ſo manye impedimentes and lettes, why do they call backe agayne with their craftie triflynge, that whyche they did once graunte, fynallie why do they torne and chang themſelues into ſo many formes and ſhapes at once. For if they go about to bryng al the whole controuerſie to thinterpretacion of the Scripture onely, go to in Gods name, let vs haue equall iudges, let vs encountre together, and let it alſo be knowen whither parte doth folowe or refuſe thooſe lawes of interpretynge whyche we haue receyued of Chriſt and his apoſtles. But ſeynge that hitherto we coulde obtayne no ſuch thing of our aduerſaryes,

it is manifeſte that they doe mocke vs wyth iouglyng wordes, &amp; haue ſome other ſecrete meaning then they ſeame openlye to ſhew. But this is no newe or vnacuſtomed thyng, vnder ye clocke of truthe to go aboute to ſuppreſſe the truthe. This chaunceth hereof that Satan (who tranſformeth himſelfe often times into an Angel of lyghte) hath bene accuſtomed to ſet goodly &amp; gloryous titles before his wickednes. For yf all aſſēblyes whatſoeuer they be whiche are reckoned vnder the name of Coūciles, had neuer erred, nor cold at this daye erre, then moſt woorthelye and of moſte righte, the chefeſt iudgemente ought to conſiſt in Counciles, but now ſeing yt honorable name of a Councile may alſo fal vppon the Sinagoge of ye deuil, it ought not to be ſo. But becauſe in al matters, exāples be of great force

ſo that there be an equal and indifferent reſpect to the thinges which be compared together, me ſemeth it ſhal not be beſydes our mattre &amp; purpoſe, if I ſhould ſet forth here be fore your eyes, a ſhewe and declaration of that Councell, wherof mē
                  tion is made in this wiſe in thiſtorye of the Goſpell.
               
                  When Eaſter was at hand the cheefe Preeſtes, Scrybes and elders of the People were gathered together into ye Haule of the hygh Preeſt that was called Cayphas, and they ſayd what ſhal we do, for thys man doth many myracles. If we let hym thus alone, al mē wil beleue in him and the Romaines wyll come and take away both our place and the nacion.
               
               And ſo forth as foloweth in the texte of Thiſtorye.
               Here I praye the (Chriſtian reader) fyrſt of all to conſyder well the fathers of this Councell. They be aſſembled together which excell other both in aucthoritie and alſo in

opinion of holynes, &amp; vppon whoſe ſhoulders the Churche which was at that tyme did reſt euen as thoughe it had bene ſhored vp with pillers. And the highe prieſt him ſelfe by whoſe aucthoritie thys aſſembly is gouerned woulde ſeme ſo to be touched with Gods glorye as he that was moſt touched, for he witneſſed with the rentyng of hys clothes the greefe of his harte whiche be conceiued of the blaſphemy. But let vs come from the fathers vnto the forme it ſelfe, and conſider the proceſſe of the lawe (as they call it) Thoſe holy fathers woulde ſeme to do nothing vnaduiſedly or by vyolence. They cal a Councell, they laye their heades together, they pretend the ſafegard of theyr countrye, whiche they crye oute to be in daunger, vnleſſe thenterpriſes of Chriſt be quickely ſtopped, but whē
                  
they came to the pointe of the matter they examine Chriſt of his religion and Doctrine, the knowledge whereof they chalenged as proper to thē ſelfes. And becauſe the lawe of God forbiddeth that anye man ſhould be puniſhed by death vnloſſe he be fyrſte conuicted of ſome haynous crime by ſufficient witneſſes, they take this charge alſo vpon thē and thei be very diligēt to take hede that they be not ſuſpected of anye man of breaking iuſtice, they geue libertie alſo to Chriſt (leſt any man ſhould ſclaunderouſlye ſay that he was condemned his cauſe beynge neuer hard) to anſwer in his owne behalfe, yea and more thē that, they compel him by wordes &amp; binde him with an othe ſo to do. Truely thys is a great libertie, &amp; ſuch a one as is wonte to get no ſmale aucthoritye to lawefull Councelis. At the lengthe

after long and earneſt canuaſyng of the lawe, they fynd Chryſt gyltye of Hereſye, ſedicion, &amp; moſte haynous crimes and worthy to be puniſhed of the Ciuill Magiſtrate. Nowe if this bee not a forme of a Councile wel ſolemnized. I cannot tell truelye what other canne ſatiſfye theſe Lutherane heretikes. To go aboute to cal in queſtion thautoritye and credyte of theſe Fathers, what other thynge is it then to accuſe the Churche it ſelfe, the whiche truelye thou ſhalte neuer ſeparate well frome this ordinarye Succeſſion of Byſhoppes whereunto it cleuethe vnſeparablye, vnleſſe peraduenture thou meane alſo vtterlie to ouerthrowe the ſame. But here let vs ſtaye awhyle and conſider more narowly thoſe which be aſſē
                  bled in this Councel, Theſe holy fathers becauſe they were altogether

corrupt with auarice and ambicion were nothyng leſſe in deade then they ſeemed to bee they were taken for the highe prieſles of the truthe and religion, and yet they weare in deade the ſworne enemyes bothe of the truthe and alſo of religion. Thei thought it meete therefore to perſecure vnto the deathe as manye as were agaynſte them. Chryſte therefore, which in his ſermons vnto the people did inuey againſt theyr counterfaycte and cloked holynes prouoked theyr madneſſe and hatred agaynſt himſelfe. What meruayle is it then if they whyche were iudges of his cauſe were found and proued to be his moſt cruell enemyes. And albeit they hadde iudged Chryſt before worthye of deathe yet becauſe they neaded the ciuil Magiſtrate to this matter thei vſe the forme of the lawe verye formallye and ſolemnly,

but they abuſe the law of God contrarye to the lawe and they ouerthrow iuſtice vnder the color of the lawe. But libertie truely was farre from this Councile, for Chryſte did anſwere to his playnte beynge tied like a pryſoner. And althoughe thei did exhorte him to ſpeake, yet they wreſted his woordes very captiouſlye, and when he ſpake not to theyr fantaſye then they reuyled him and did alſo beate him. This is the ſome of theyr Councile.
               
               Now vnder what good Scolemalters oure Fathers alſo haue profited, I leaue it to be diſcuſſed of menne of good conſideration. Wyth what kynde of Iudgement Iohn Hus, Hierome of Prage, and manye other good menne wer deceyued manye yeares agayne, it hath bene approued by the teſtimonyes of many and alſo by the bloud of oure men. Wel it is tyme to leaue

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
of this matter &amp; to retorne againe, to that which properly pertaineth to vs. For euē as I thinke it beſt to ſuffer the Popes adherentes to do what they liſt becauſe they be incurable, ſo alſo I iudge it good for vs earneſtly &amp; diligentlye to take hede we defile not nor pollute our ſelfes wt ani ſpot or blemiſh gottē by other mēs faults. Foraſmuch as therfore it is euidēt enough, what our aduerſaries entētis, we muſt alſo ſearche what we our ſelfes haue to do, leſte peraduēture we ſhall ſeme to haue bene more curious &amp; diligēt in iudging others thē about our own diſciplie. That is raſhly takē in hād which is laid a ſide again wtout ani deliberatiō. That is alſo daūgerouſly enterpriſed which is forſakē not wtout gret ſhame. If ye Cobler or ye Deluer can tel thend of his labour, what thinke we yt we muſt do vpon whō ye charge of religion reſteth, in

whiche alone both Gods lawes &amp; mans lawes ar alſo cōtained. Let vs go to Trent (ſome wil ſai.) But to what ende &amp; purpoſe? That we may be ſōe part of that aſſēbly, &amp; debate ma
                     •
                  ters of religiō together wt the fathers: nothing truely can be more glorious or profitable thē this oure iourney. This peraduenture ſome wil alleage. But I praye you good Sir came it neuer into youre mind once to thinke yt we (althoughe we wold neuer ſo faine) cā not be admitted vnto any part of that cōſultatiō, nor albeit we were admitted therto, yet eyther coulde or would be a parte of that Councell, whoſe aucthorytie dependeth onelye of the Byſhop of Rome ye ſworn enemy of Chriſt and hys Churche? You vnderſtande (I trowe) howe hardelie we are beſette euen in the verye doore. But where neceſſitye

ruleth there is no place left for deliberacion, and it were but vayne to aſke what one ſhoulde doe when he hathe not yet conſidered what hee maye do. And ſo where oure aduerſaryes do leaue vs no place in theyr aſſemblye, they doe alſo vnburden vsof the care that we ſhoulde haue of diſputing there. They truly whō they diſdayne, do alſo lykewyſe diſdayne them. They deſpiſe vs, and we ſet nought by thē. They forſake vs dryue vs awaye and reiecte vs frome theyr familiaritye, and we agayne eſchewe them, flye from them and voluntarilye abhorre them. Bleſſed is that man ſaide to be that Pſalm. hathe not walked in the councell of thungodlye, nor ſtode in the way of the ſynners, nor ſat in the chayre of ſkorners. I haue not haūted (ſaith Dauyd) wyth vayne perſons, neyther xv. Pſal compayned wyth diſſemblers, I haue hated thaſſemblye of the euyll,

and haue not kepte companye wyth the wycked. In this Pſalme the holye man of God maketh a declaracion of his lyfe, and ſheweth for the hymſelfe to bee folowed of all godlie perſons. But battayles haue beene diuerſe tyme foughte indifferentelye one both partes not wythoute their prayſe, and theyr bee alſo whyche accounpt it more noble and gloryouſe to keepe theyr owne, then to inuade other mennes, and ſoe we by defendinge oure owne cauſe manfullye, ſhall fighte wyth oure aduerſaryes aloofe. But the clauſe of continuacion dothe ſhut vs quite from that libertie, and caſt a banke (as it were) agaynſt oure enterpriſes. Euen ſo not many yeares paſſe the Ambaſſadoures and Diuines of the moſte noble Prynces of Germanye, after many large promiſſes, yea and the dayelye interceſſion of the moſt myghtye Monarche Charles

the v. by ye ſpace of many monethes cold hardly at the length be admitted to ye aſſembly, which not wt ſtanding in deſpite they termed a cōgregation, as though a mā ſhould call yt a troubleſome or tumultuous cō
                  pany, which is ſaid to be appointed about matters not very waighty. We may wel thinke how far the diuines of Germanye were from the chefe point of diſputatiō, whē they were not ſuffered ſo much as to entre into ye dore therof. But graunt that we ſhould be better vſed (whiche neuertheleſſe is not credible) what ſhalbe or can be the cōditions of this diſputation, ſo long as theſe lawes which our aduerſaries preſcribe do ſtād, Or what certentie cā we haue, whē thonly rule of certain tie is taken awaye. But admit yt al things are redy, &amp; that both Gods lawe &amp; mans lawe agree to vs yet who ſhalbe our iudges, who ſhalbe

our vmpires. Truely euē they whō experience hath taught long ſithēs to be our deadly &amp; mortal enemies, &amp; who alſo haue ſolemnly ſworne &amp; expreſly cōſpired oure deſtruction, what equitie or iuſtice cā any man loke for at theſe iudgeshāds. What if the Papiſtes, ſuch is their boldenes, do forthwith write thactes of the Councel, what if they faine yt a matter is lawfully diſcuſſed, &amp; after diligent knowledge therof had, do decree that we ſhould be publiſhed for moſt greuous heretikes, &amp; worthy of moſt ſeuere &amp; ſharpe puniſhment. Truely we ſhall neuer hereafter ſo wel wipe away this crime, but that ſome ſuſpition therof wyll for euer remayne in the mindes of the ſymple. Here peraduenture ſome of oure menne wylbe earneſt, and thynke thus with hym ſelfe, that althoughe all other thynges be denyed vnto theym, yet at the

leaſt wiſe they ſhall haue liberty to propone and ſet ſorth our doctrine before theyr eyes, and that this propoſicion ſhal containe a forme of proteſtacion (as they cal it) or rather of confeſſion. But I truelye do not ſee what it profiteth to doble repete or witneſſe one thynge ſo often tymes to theſe felowes eſpeciallye whyche of the thynge it ſelfe haue geuen vnto our men the name of Proteſtāts, becauſe they forſothe often declared by profeſſinge alwayes on thyng, of what opinion they were. We reade alſo yt the holy Martyrs of Chriſte, haue defended their cauſes beefore wycked Iudges, but we neuer read that they haue wyllyngly preſented theyr cauſes before them. Our Lord alſo wylleth his to beware of thoſe 
                     
                        •
                     . Math.
                   menne whych ſhal delyuer them vp to the Counciles and ſcourge them in theyr Sinagoges. He dothe not then ſaye, thruſte youre ſelues willyngelye

into their Councels, and take them to be Iudges of you and your cauſes, whom you knowe wyl be enemyes and Iniuriouſe bothe to you and youre cauſe alſo. Paule the apoſtle, rather then hee woulde cōmit his cauſe to the Iewes whō he knew to be his enemies thought it better to appeale to ye Iudgment of Themperour. This exāple folowed Athanaſius, Cirillus, &amp; Nazianienus, and wyth al diligence eſchewed the conuenticles of Heritykes. Therefore where ſo manye and ſoo greate difficultyes be, I cannot ſee what we haue to do at Trente, this one thinge excepte, that is to ſaye to offre agayne wyllyngelye to our enemyes that thing for thobtayning and gettinge by force whereof wee haue beene at this great and continuall warre with them ſo long. For if the right of Calling Sinodes doe not pertayne to the Popes neither

by the lawe of God nor manne. No more trulye (although ſome tyme it had appertained) it is now to be permitted or graunted to them in their owne caſe beyng called vnto Iudgement, to be bothe Iudges and parties. We therfore which are not called to a Coūcile, but to the dragges and filth of the Courte of Rome, wil neuer ſo behaue our ſelues, that we ſhall be ſayd by oure Obedience to haue deliuered and as it wer ſealed into their hands, that power which bothe the lawes of God and alſo of men haue cleane taken from them. But if the obedience of ſubiectes be limitted wyth the power and right of the Superioure, and yet ſuche as we oure ſelues are do cal forth Kinges and Emperours to Counciles, by our preſence trulye to our power and as muche as in vs doth lye we ſhoulde arme the Pope alſo againſt Chriſtin Princes and thorough our

moſt vniuſt iudgemēt we ſhold not only offēd al other Chriſtiās which vpō waightie occaſions haue abſtained frō this meeting, but alſo make thē both hate vs and alſo to be more hated of ye Papiſts. This ye Princes of Germany vnderſtod wel enough who in their laſt metig at Neoburgh did ſtoutly reiect ye ſtinking requeſt of the Pope. They ſayde that they meruayled much to ſe him ſo ſhameleſſe that he was not a baſhed to preſcribe things alſo to them, of whō he was him ſelfe accuſed of treadinge religion vnder foote, who alſo had made a violēt &amp; vniuſt title to ye poſſeſſiō of ye Church, wherfore that he ſhold mocke others who knewe not as yet the Romiſh fraudes &amp; guiles, as for thē ſelues who knew thē ſufficientelie enoughe they would not ſeine onelye to knowe them but alſo to foreſee them. Mooreouer this is not to be omitted, that if at any time wee ſhoulde be admitted to theyr

aſſemblyes we muſte vouchſaufe to terme this rable of mitred felowes by the name of Fathers, yea and that moſte holye or at the leſte wyſe moſte reuerende Fathers. For it is not mete that any man ſhould come to ſpeake his minde withoute ſome Preface of dignitye and honor, eſpeciallye in their preſence whoſe pride and ambicion wil neuer be ſatiſiied. But with what countenaunce or cō
                  ſcience ſhall wee ſpeake vnto them reuerentlye, to whome what honor or reuerence ſo euer we ſhewe, wee pull that all frome Chryſte and his Churche. I haue nowe proued (I thinke) ſufficientelye, that there bee no iuſte cauſes at all why we ſhould go to Trent but rather verye many and thoſe moſte wayghty occaſions to be agaynſte this Iorneye, and ſo conſequentlye that oure menne can by no meanes goe to this Councile withoute committinge a moſt haynous

cryme. And albeit we do condemne and eſchewe theeſe Romiſhe Sinagoges, we doe not alſo therefore abhorre and flie from all Chriſtian aſſēblyes, but we acknowlege and confeſſe moſt playnely that if anye excellynge others in Learning Godlynes and Iudgement be dewlye called to a lawful Councile, thei cannot refuſe this charge laid vpon them withoute incurringe the greuous indignacion of God and alſo ye iuſt diſpleaſure of al eſtates of mē. But yt there may be a good ende of Counciles, it is alſo requiſite that ye things tending to this ende ſhould be wel ſet in order. If therfore Chriſtian Prynces to whom this charge doth chiefeli pertaine, do ſettle their myndes earneſtelye to reforme the church, they wil ſet to their helping hāds al together, ſo that ye Councel may bein very deade Catholicke as it is in name termed. But it as the

tymes be nowe theyr godlye enterpryſes cannot haue good ſucceſſe, then it remayneth that euery one of them ſhoulde employe that care and diligence in his one kingdom &amp; countrye which they purpoſed al at once to beſtow in general. Let thē therefore endeuor to call nationall or prouinciall aſſemblyes, the whyche not wythſtanding I woulde not ſo reſtrayne, but that ſtraungers alſo ſhoulde haue free acceſſe thereto, ſo that they were ſuche men by whoſe preſence the companie might be adourned and helped. Lette them alſo prouide that the place maye be free and voyde from al kynde of feare &amp; dreade, let there alſo bee ſufficiente Pryuileges and warrauntes of ſafe conducte. Let the voyces and elections be alſo free, Let the wayes be alſo ſafe, and not perillous thorough Ambuſhes and wiles. And yet lette all this libertye bee bounden and limytted

with the lawes of equitie ſo that no manne maye do anye thing more then the rule of piety ſhal permytte. And that this maye the better be doone, this Councile muſt be Chryſtian, whyche notwythſtanding ſtretcheth farre &amp; wyde. For ye cānot be Chryſtian, whych doth not referre all his doings to the rule of Chryſte and his Apoſtles comprehended in holy Scriptures, whiche doth not alſo agree altogether &amp; in al poynts, whych Chryſtiā manners and finallye wyth the Chryſtian examples of the pure Churche. That this Coūcel alſo ſhuldbe Chriſtiā, let ye matters which are incontrouerſy be debated not wt hatred, but modeſtly according to Chriſtiā charity, &amp; bi ſuch lawes as ſeme to be apoynted for tho pening of the truthe &amp; not for the darkening thereof. But how far am I gone, mine entente was to teach you ye we ought vpon greete

conſideracions not to go to Trent. The whyche thynge yf I haue broughte to paſſe, then haue I alſo fyniſhed and accomplyſhed that whyche I toke in hande. And thus I make an ende.
            
         
      
      
         
            Imprynted at London in Powles Churcheyard by Humfrie Toye, dwellynge at the ſygne of the Helmet.
            
               Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.
            
            
         
      
   

