
   
      
         
            A sermon preached at Ashby De-la-zouch in the countie of Leicester at the funerall of the truely noble and vertuous lady Elizabeth Stanley one of the daughters and coheires of the Right Honourable Ferdinand late Earle of Derby, and late wife to Henrie Earle of Huntingdon the fifth earle of that familie. The 9. of February. Anno Dom. 1633. By I.F.
            I. F., fl. 1633.
         
         
            
               1635
            
         
         Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00510
            STC 10644
            ESTC S116875
            99852090
            99852090
            17395
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00510)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17395)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1379:13)
         
         
            
               
                  A sermon preached at Ashby De-la-zouch in the countie of Leicester at the funerall of the truely noble and vertuous lady Elizabeth Stanley one of the daughters and coheires of the Right Honourable Ferdinand late Earle of Derby, and late wife to Henrie Earle of Huntingdon the fifth earle of that familie. The 9. of February. Anno Dom. 1633. By I.F.
                  I. F., fl. 1633.
                  Fletcher, Joseph, 1577?-1637, attributed name.
               
               [2], 44 p.   
               
                  Printed by William Iones dwelling in Red-crosse streete,
                  London :
                  1635.
               
               
                  Leaves B2 and D4 are cancels in most copies of this and STC 10545 and STC 10646. Most copies also have an extra leaf with epitaph by L. Cary, 2nd Viscount Falkland. Some copies have a portrait of the countess engraved by John Payne.
                  Sometimes attributed to Joseph Fletcher.
                  The copy catalogued contains the cancels (D4r catchword "from". Variant: D4 is cacellandum; D4r catchword "part"), but lacks the epitaph and the portrait of the countess.
                  Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Huntingdon, Elizabeth Hastings, --  countess of, 1586-1633.
               Funeral sermons.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-04
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2005-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
A SERMON PREACHED AT ASHBY DE-LA-ZOVCH IN THE COVNTIE OF LEICESTER: At the Funerall of the Truely Noble and Vertuous Lady ELIZABETH STANLEY one of the Daughters and Coheires of the Right Honourable FERDINAND late Earle of Derby and late Wife to HENRIE Earle of Huntingdon the Fifth Earle of that Familie. The 9. of February. Anno Dom. 1633. By I. F.
            
            
               LONDON. Printed by William Iones dwelling in Red-crosse streete. 1635.
         
         
            
            AN EPITAPH VPON THE EXCELLENT COVNTESSE OF HVNTJNGDON.
            
            
               THE cheife perfections of both Sexes joyn'd,
               With neithers vice nor vanity combin'd.
               Of this our age the wonder, loue, and care,
               The example of the following, and dispaire.
               Such beauty, that from all hearts loue must flow:
               Such maiesty, that none durst tell her so.
               A wisdome of so large and potent sway,
               Romes Senare might haue wisht, her Conclaue may.
               Which did to earthly thoughts so seldome bow,
               Aliue She scarce was lesse in heaven, then now.
               So voyd of the least pride, to her alone
               These radiant excellencies seem'd vnknowne.
               Such once there was: but let thy greife appeare
               Reader, there is not: Huntingdon lies here.
               
                  By him who saies what he saw FALKLAND.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A FVNERALL SERMON.
            
               Iohn. XI. XXV.
               He that Beleiveth in mee though he were Dead yet shall he liue.
            
            
               THE hopes of those which are strangers unto the Covenants of promise, cannot fixe any setled ayme, and expectancie beyond the short line of life: when that is drawne out unto the utmost point, Death at the best is apprehended by them, but as it was by Adrian, to be incerta Peregrinatio, a Race of very doubtfull issue, doubtfull whether in the end thereof, the

head shall be crowned or cut off; so that of all men most miserable that they are, their hope is onely in this life. Tantisper sperant dum spirant; But the hope of the children of the promise, doth not vanish into emptines with their breath, etiam dum expirant sperant; Though there be no more breath in their mouthes and their nostrills, yet their hope is layd vp in their bosome. Iob 29. Though we die, yet saith Job, We know, that our Redeemer 
               Iob. 29. 17. 
               liveth.
            
            Though we be hid and closed vnder the ground, like the seed in the garden bed, yet he whom Mary saw Iob. 20. 15. like the Gardiner, this Gardiner, will looke, that the seede shall have its spring againe: He will, saith the Prophet, poure vpon vs a dew, like the dew of bearbes, and the earth shall yeeld forth 
               Es. 16. 19. 
               her dead And of thus much doth he here ass
                  •
               re the sister of Mary, who was almost as deepely swallowed vp of griefe, as her deceased brother

               Lazarus was of the Grave. Comfort thy selfe Martha, he shall rise againe; and doubt not Martha, I my selfe am the Resurrection, and the life, the issues of Death belong unto me. The keyes of Psal. 68. 20. the Grave are at my Girdle, and he that beleeveth in me, Though he were dead yet shall he live.
            
            The wordes are in summe, a Stipulatio Conventionalis, consisting of a

                  1. condition.
                  2. promise.
               
            
            1. First, the Condition thus insinuated, He that beleeveth. 2. the promise thus proposed and pronounced, though he were dead yet shall he live.
            
            First, The Condition upon which the promise is suspended, is faith, that 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                that fulnesse of our hopes, that 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                that solace of our lives, as Philo calleth it, nay that our life it selfe, or at least that upon which our life lies; for by it the just shall live, or by nothing, He that beleeveth in me, and he onely that beleeveth, he shall live.
            
            
               
And here seeing this Action is so properly specified, by its object; we may observe, That the principall obiect of our faith, is God, considered in the unitie of his essence and a Trinity of persons, and therefore in the Symboll of our beleife, the Creede, is there a particular Credo, or at least the particle (in) premitted apart before every one of the three persons, importing, that upon them we fixe, and build, our first assent, and assurance.
            As for those other subordinate principles of our faith, such as concerne the Catholique Church, the Communion of Saints, these being but Creatures, are not assented unto for themselves, but for God, the uncreate, and first truth, and therefore have no such Credo, nor particle set apart before them, but onely prefixed before one of the three persons.
            Now, this obiect of our faith is considered diversly; either, as the Act of beliefe and assent hath respect unto

the understanding, and in that consideration, the obiect of faith is twofold, either formall, in which respect the Act of Faith is credere Deo, we beleeving God as the first truth, and for him fixing a setled assent upon all second and subordinate truthes, they be the maine Characters of divinity Power, and wisdome imprinted on them, apparently manifesting, the hand, the finger of the Lord to have written them.
            Or else it is materiall, and so the Act of faith is credere Deum; we that beleeve beleeve that God is, and that he is a rewarder of those that seeke him.
            Or secondly, the obiect of faith is considered, as the Act of beleefe and assent hath respect unto the will moveing the understanding to render its assent, and in this respect the Act of faith is Credere in Deum, as it is here delivered; for the will having pitched the end of all its hopes, in the goodnesse of this exceeding rich and precious promise

uncessantly plyeth the understanding to give its assent to the truth of that which so much imports and concernes its peace and satisfaction.
            And these different considerations, doe not importe any such various difference of the Acts of faith, but rather signifie the divers respects of one and the same Act unto the obiect of faith.
            The summe of all may be collected thus. First, we beleeve that God is, and a rewarder of all those that seeke him: 2. We beleeve his counsells and Covenants manifested, and dispensed unto us. 3. We beleeve in him, adhaere unto him, relie on him; our Soule being with absolute Complacencie satisfied in him, cryeth out, Pars mea Dominus, It is enough the Lord is my portion, how then can I lacke any thing? we give our assent unto his counsells, and Covenants, because we are assured that in what he delivereth, or promiseth, he is wise and cannot be deceived himselfe, he is faithfull and will not

deceive us; Though we discerne a propension, and flexiblenesse in our selves to waver with every contrarie Ayre, yet let God be true, though all men 
               Rom. 3. 
               be lyars. The Aegyptians as Aquinas notes adventured to make the promise alterable; I know not what feates they had, like unto those of their moderne counterfeits, to play fast, and loose with such a firme, and sealed knot as this. But whatsoever they! we, saith the Apostle, beleeve what we know, and we know whom we have beleeved, and if we be deceived, certainely as the Prophet saith, Thou Lord hast deceived 
               Ier. 20. 
               us; But God for bid saith Abraham the father of all beleevers, that the Iudge of all the world, should not do righteously; And unto this well-grounded Gen: 17. assent, succeedes our firme adhaerence unto the covenants of promise, by which we cleave unto, and close with our Redeemer in this manner.
            The proposition of the promise is

furnished by the Gospell; The Redeemer died for those that are dead unto sin &amp; rose againe for the justification of them which are planted into the similitude of his resurrection. Now an assumption must be fitted unto the proposition by that assent which our understandings give unto the truth, and that adherence which our wills fasten upon the goodnesse of these exceeding rich and precious promises. If we be able thus to limit the generall proposition, I am dead unto the world by the Crosse of Christ, or I was dead, but now I am alive in Iesus Christ, the conclusion will follow inevitably.
            I doe not alwayes expect in such a limitation certitudinem Evidentiae: where I finde but certitudinem adhaerentiae, such a one as sometime feeles some 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                some declinations and abatements of its firmenesse, and fervor. Even that faith howsoever it seeme to come no neerer unto

Christ then the very hemme of his garment yet is able to derive vertue from him.
            Thus have I in a verie narrow modell represented unto you the whole figure of that grace, which gives us Title unto this promise. Give me then leave to question you, as the Apostle did Agrippa, Beleevest thou the prophets? Beleeve you in the Lord Iesus? I would I could answer for all, as he did for Agrippa. I know that you beleeve.
            But this I know: Many will make a boast of faith (saith Salomon) but Prov. 20. 6. where shall we finde a faithfull man? If you beleeve indeed, your faith will give evidence of it selfe by the exercise of an adhering and an apprehending vertue: By the first we are inserted into him; by the second we derive a quickening influence from him
            Doest thou then beleeve in the Lord Iesus? shew mee then the power of the Lord Iesus. The Angell gave a reason

of his name, He shall be called Iesus, saith he, for he shall save his people from their sinnes. But art thou yet in thy sinnes? I cannot then beleeve that thou beleevest: No! It is fitter for thee (according to that elegant observation of St. Bernard) to feare the name of Christ, then to be confident upon the name of Iesus. It is fitter for thee in such a case to dread him as he is Christ, a King, a Iudge, then to presume upon him as he is Iesus, a Saviour, a Redeemer.
            Doest thou beleeve in the death of Iesus Christ? shew me then the power of his death, whether it worke in thee mightilie, as it did in the Apostle to the subduing of every corrupt affection. Doest thou beleeve in his Resurrection? shew me then the power of his resurrection, Resurrectio Christi habet virtutem in se, sed operationem in nobis, shew me then what new effect it hath wrought, what new life it hath quickened in thee. No man came unto

Christ, that went away in the same estate that he came in:
            Some came lame, and paralytike, and went backe restored to the integritie of their limmes and strength; some came leprous and were dismissed cleane some came blinde and deafe, and went went away restored to the integritie of their sences, None were dismissed in the same estate wherein they came: And hast thou beene so neere unto Christ, as to say, I am in him, and of him, and yet art neither cleansed, nor enlightened, nor healed, who can beleeve it? Whatsoever thou boastest of beleeving, I cannot beleeve that thou beleevest at all, no certainely thou never wert so neere him, as the very skirts of his clothing, thou never camest so neere, as the very smell of the oyntments of this our Aaron, If thou hadst certainely that name, which is as an oyntment powred forth, that name, wherein thou pretendest to beleeve, would powerfully have healed all

these wounds and sores, and swellings
            But doest thou indeed beleeve, and art able to give evidence thereof by such comfortable Testimonies, as are here implied? Then doubt not of the promise as Christ said unto Martha. Beleevest thou this? why then he that beleeveth in me, though he were dead yet shall he live; and so I passe from the condition, to the consideration of the promise suspended upon the condition, Though he were dead, yet shall he live. The labour of man in this life, is, to turne up the face of the Earth in the sweate of his owne face, seeking for foode and fewell in her bowells, and in the closing up of the weary day of his Travell, the earth receiveth man himselfe for a recompence into her bosome to fill up those wounds and rents, But the earth receaveth back no more then it lent, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . Naz: 
               Nazian:
            
            The spirit breathed from above, returneth to God that gave it. Dissolutio 
               Aug: 
               corporis, est Absolutio animae. As the snare

being broken the Bird escapeth, so the bodie being dissolved, evadit intus inclusa Columba, our soule is escaped Col. 3. 1. as a Bird out of the snare of the fowler; so that in our departure we suffer but aliquid mortis, not a whole death. Our life is not lost, but hid. The Serpent which hath the power of death can doe no more, but manducare terram nostram, licke our dust; and indeed but licke it; devoure it, consume it, annihilate it he cannot, there must still be ex defectione refectio, after a decay a reparation.
            The Earth indeed receiveth the dust backe againe, which it lent, but yet it receiveth it not as payed, but as lent; it must be given up, and returned backe againe; It receiveth our bodies to make up those wounds and wants, which partly our wants, partly our wantonnesse have made in her face, and wombe; and it retaineth them for a recompense of her sufferings and losses, till in the generall restoration, it

selfe be restored. But then when it selfe is renewed, when there is a new heaven, and a new Earth what need hath the Earth to reteine our bodies any longer for satisfaction? In that day Oh Earth, Earth, Earth, thou shalt heare the voice of the Lord, and render up thy dead, and even the dead themselves shall heare the voyce of the son Ioh. 5. 25. of God, and they that heare it shall live. This is the hope of Israell, and indeed the hope of all the world, after al those evills which presse and persecute man to the last earthly evill death, there is yet this hope left in the botteme of the Grave, as in the bottome of Pandora's Boxe But it is but hope, not sight, and therefore the doctrine which concerned this hope, received such sleight intertainment; for whereas the Apostle saith, hope that is seene is not hope, cleane contrary with him that lookes onely with the eye of nature, hope that is not seene, is no hope at all. Hope that is not founded upon the Evidence

of reason is with him but a 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                a citie in the cloudes, a Castle in the ayre; hence was it that the doctrine of the Resurrection, amongst the Epicureans &amp; Pithagoreans of Athens was receved Act. 17. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . but as a mater of mockery; though the Iudgement seate were in the Arcopagus, yet they sate downe in the seate of scorners, not as Iudges of Paules Sermon; But allowing that the Athenians had some reason to be ignorant, as perhaps, had they not so much reason, they would not have had so litle faith.
            It is not strange that in the first 300. years after Christ, divers even in Christ should gainesay this hope of all the world being spoyled through the same vaine Philosophy. Many of those ages, having not seen any example of a Resurrection, but only received it upon relation and reading, began to scanne the possibility of such a restoration according to the principles of Nature, &amp; reason. It is well observed of Minutius non minoris est sceleris ignorare quamsaedere
            
            
               
These men sinne as highly by denying Gods Power through their ignorance, as if by their disobedience they had resisted it: Malè Deum norunt qui illum putant non posse quod non putant; I may pronounce them ignorant which conceive, that God is able to do no more, then they are able in reason to conceive. But though they, though all the world gainsay this hope of all the world, yet this is the victory that overcometh all the world, even our faith: we will not draw all unto reason but leave something for faith.
            Our contemplation of matters of this straine which are above the comprehension of reason, and beyond the bounds of experience doth not arrive at knowledge but at wonder: which is nothing els but Contemplation broken off, or loosing it selfe; It was aptly said by one of Platoes schoole, the sense of man resembleth the Sunne, which openeth and reveileth the Terrestiall Globe, but obscureth and concealeth

the Celestiall, so doeth the sense discover naturall things, but darken, and shut up, those which are beyond the verge of nature: for all things proceeding in the Invention of knowledg is by similitude, but those things are onely selfe like and have nothing in common with naturall things otherwise then in shadow, and trope. Give therefore unto faith, that which unto faith belongeth; for indeed it is more worthy to beleeve then to thinke or know; considering that in knowledge the minde suffereth from the impression of inferior natures; but in all beliefe, the minde suffereth from a spirit which it holdeth superior, &amp; more Aug. authorised thē it selfe; Nolumus igitur intelligere ut credamus, sed credereut inteligamus, we wil not therfore seeke to under stand that we may beleeve, but beleve that it may be given us to understand
            The mystery of the Resurrection was delivered not by Pihlosophers, but by simple fishermen: and here the

most subtill of us, must leave to be disputants, and learne to be disciples. And yet if any list to dispute, let me aske as St. Paul did, why should it seeme an impossible thing, to raise up one that is dead? It was well argued by the Iew Pesisa, Si quod fuit, est, ergo, quod fuit erit. whether is it harder to restore a body mouldred into the dust from whence it was taken, then to creat all things out of nothing! Is it thought impossible in nature? why, nature her selfe is a mistrisse able enough to informe us of the contrarie. Operibus Resurrectionem perscripsit antequam literis, viribus praedicavit antequam vocibus: se we not the vicissitudes of night and day, the revolutions of winter and summer, the riseing and setting of the Starres, the wane and increases of the Moone, the Quickening of the dead graine under the Clod, to beare a lively resemblance of this Restoration.
            
               
The whole Creation which grones for the generall resurrection, practiseth a yeerely, a monthly, yea a daily Resurrection in its severall parts. And all this for Man! And shall man onely not rise, for whom all these things rise in their periods and seasons? what should withhold him from being restored? The powers of the grave are shaken, and disabled, Christ himselfe hath broken open the Gates thereof, and loosed his Prisoners from the brinkes of the pit: death it selfe hath by his last conflict received its deaths wound: he had foiled it before, by the ministry of his servants, by Eliah recalling the Sarephtans son, by Elisha recovering the Shunamits son. So David foiled his enemies of Ammon by the valour of his servants Ioab, and Abisha, but himselfe was faine 2 Sam 12. to appeare before Rabbah for the perfecting of the victory and conclusion of the warre; so the Sonne of David appeared personally to give his

Enemie the last stroke to swallow up death in an utter victory. The victory is thus atcheived. Death it selfe though he be the King of feare, and have as many Provinces of his dominion, as there be paines, perills and snares of death, yet hath no more dominion over us, then what our sinne betrayeth us unto. The arrowes of death are fledged with the feathers which grow upon our owne wings. Now therefore if we conceive man to be without sinne, death hath no more dominion over him: Death then haveing seized upon our Saviour, who was without staine or guilt, it was found equall in the Iudgement of God, that it should loose all power over us that were sinfull, because it exercised a power which it had not over him that was innocent. For in regard of the iniury offered unto him and patiently susteined by him, God adjudged him all power over him that had the power of death, giveing him liberty

to restore unto liberty the Prisoners of the Grave.
            And indeed he hath reason thus to restore them, for according to that of Bernard, Christus solus resurrexit, sed non totus; Christ alone is risen, but all Christ is not risen, till all that are of, and in Christ be risen likewise. Thus though other Graves be the houses of death, this of Christ is unto us, (now the stone is removed from it) the Gate of everlasting life; Although death be the king of feare yet we see of his kingdome there is an end, he raigned indeed under the law, but now the Scepter of righteousnesse is transferred unto one, of whose kingdome there is no end. And observe the procession and Pompe of his Triumph over his vanquished foe: Death, saith the Prophet, shall goe before his face pale and trembling as a Prisoner before his Triumphall chariot. He saith no longer now as he did once, O Death, I will be thy Death, It is not seasonable to threaten

now, death hath already felt his vanquishing armes, he spareth not now therefore to reproch him with this glorious insultation, O death where is thy Sting? O grave, where is thy victorie? Since thou didst once loose thy sting upon mine innocency, I have taken away the sinnes of the world, so that now thou canst not fit thy selfe with any new sting, to wound either mee, or mine. Thus death it selfe is dead, and the dead live againe; death is swallowed up, and the dead are rendered up: this is the hope of humaneflesh: but he must be more then flesh, whosoever attaineth to the end of this hope, for flesh and bloud shall never inherit the 1 Cor. 15. kingdome of heaven.
            As there is a flesh which shall see the salvation of God, so there is a flesh Es. 52. Es. 4. 1 Thes. 4. 17 which is as grasse. Grasse which groweth to day, and tomorow perhaps is to be cast into the fornace, there to be tormented in aeterno Dei, because it sinned in aeterno suo. During the eternall

pleasure of God, because of its owne eternall pleasure it tooke in displeasing of God; As there are some qui rapientur in occursum, so there are some qui convertentur retrorsum. Those which have turned their backes unto me, and not their face, those shall be Ps. 9. 17. turned backward. They shall rise againe, but it shall be for their greater depression. Their bodies shall be delivered from the first death, but it shall be to be delivered up unto the second death, their soules and bodies shall be united, but both devided from God, in such manner that they shall wish the bodie had beene rather extinguished, then thus united. Sed ad augmentum 
               Gr
                     •
                  g. 
               tormenti, ut hic de corpore nolens educitur, itidem et illic in corpore tenetur in vitus. To aggravate the vengeance, as here the soule parted out of the bodie against its will; so there its held in the body against its will. Marveile not at it, though 
                  〈◊〉
                be de suo optomus, yet he is de nostro Iustus. As he is gracious by the Tertull: propriety of his nature; so he is iust for

the necessity of the cause. And it is equall and iust, that if we taste of the sweetnesse of sinne against the will of God, we shall taste of the bitternesse of punishment against our owne will. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . &amp;c. It is equall if we be here subiected unto that evill one, that we should hereafter be possessed of him, saith that excellent Homilist Hom: 
               Macarius. If we make our bodies Prostibula and not Templa, rather Temples of Chemosh and Ashtaroth then Domus patris mei, they will become rather blockes of hell-fire then Pillars in the Temple and the Courtes of the house of our God. Let us therefore spare our Bodies (my beloved) and not use them as if they were borrowed garments, we must give accompts of things done in them. And as the scarrs of wounds, so the scarrs of sins will appeare therin after death, which will be Characters of evidence plaine enough to testifie their un
                  •••
               blenesse of Glorie, let us therefore here seeke

to take them away, by taking the Cyrill. catech. 18. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                by being washed, by being sanctified here. Would we so rise from death, that we may not sinke into the second death, let us remember, that Corpora nostra huic Resurrectioni per Regenerationem Spiritus 
               Tertull: 
               inaugurantur, Our bodies must be here intituled unto the Resurrection of glory, by the Resurrection of Grace.
            Nature exposeth us all dead, dead in the uncircumcision of the flesh, dead in the dead workes of the flesh; Man, who had not knowne sinne, should have felt no power of death in his Bodie, by sinne contracted a death even of his soule, for as the soule is the life of the bodie, so is grace the life of the Soule; As then when the soule departeth the bodie dies, so Grace having abandoned the soule, the spirit it selfe is dead. And how many doe we discerne everie where, in whom

the tokens of this death are sensibly apparent, men dead in themselves, onely Satan moveth in them, Satan walketh in them, so that they move but like prodigies, like the bodies of those which Satan is said to make use of for the atcheiving of his wicked illusions. St. Aug: observes three sorts of dead persons whom Christ raised up unto life, representing three distinct sorts of his spirituall death: first the daughter of the Ruler of the Synagogue, which was dead in the house, resembling those that are dead-hearted, senselesse of the impressions of life &amp; grace, such as sit as dead in these Assemblies, as if we were preaching at their funeralls.
            Secondly, The young man which was caryed out of the Gates of Natin, resembling those whose hearts and hands are engaged in the outward practise of the dead workes of the flesh
            Thirdly, Lazarus that had layen long putryfying in the grave representing

those that have layen from the very wombe, overwhelmed with the body of death and over-set with a cloud of ignorance, &amp; insensiblenes so many dead in all these conditions and degrees do we observe every where that we have reason to wish as Ieremie did: oh that our eyes were as Rivers of water, that we might weepe for the dead, for the slaine of our people, now then oh wretched men that we are, who shall deliver us from the body of this death? If we be raised, we must be raised by the voice, and vertue of the same Christ which raised up these he that in the Gospel bad the yong man, arise, must by his Gospel bid the new man arise in us. As we are sūmoned unto the second Resurrection, by the voice of an Archangel, so are we here unto this, by the voice of the Angel of the covenant, in the mouths of the angels of the churches, the ministers. &amp; here both that voice which sounded from mount Sinai, and that which sounded

from mount Sion, have their part in the action. The law startleth, the Gospell awaketh &amp; quickneth us. Christ sent the law by his servant, as Elisha sent his staffe, by which yet the dead child was not raised up till Elisha himselfe came in persō. The terrors of the law quicken in us so much sence, as may make us sigh for our restoration, the refreshings of the gospel quickē in us so much light, &amp; life as to make us se and run into the arms of our Restorer The law seemes to remove the stone from the mouth of our hearts, as it was removed from the mouth of Lazarus Sepulchre; but the voice of Christ in the Gospel sumoneth us to awake &amp; arise that he may give us light, wherin we may be enabled to know &amp; follow him, that hath visited us, &amp; done so great things for us &amp; now I would that we had made such an advantage of our Attention, to that powerfull voice, that I might have occasiont 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                after a visible, &amp; evident

Resurrection to loose you, as Lazarus was, from the bondes of the Grave, or to say with the father of the prodigall, loe these my sonnes were dead, but now they live: we were dead saith the Apostle, but now we are alive in Iesus Christ, now we feele the pulse of spirituall life beate in the Arteries of our faith, which assureth us that our life is prepared for us; of our hope which is resolute that it is preserved for us; of our love, which upon these well-grounded perswasions, is continually running in a cheerefull prosecution and chase thereof. My beloved though we have 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                earth to our father and dust to our Sire, yet let us not have 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                dust-creeping soules: surely our hope is higher then the dust, let our conversation then be as high as our hope is. Though we be made of the earth, yet we are not made for the Earth. We may observe, that he that requires the erection of our affections, doth

with great iealousie withdraw from us all those ensnarements upon which they may fasten here below. He is such a Bridegrome, as will not that we preferre the king before himselfe; this circle the world, before the compasse of his Armes. All these counterfeit delights, which this empty dust is able to yeeld us, they are as of purpose, made either not to rellish at all with us, by reason of their shortnesse and fleetingnesse, or to distate us by the admixture of some calamitie and Bitternesse: for if we will be children in understanding insteed of being children in Innocency, if we will still be sucking here, we must be used as 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                great babes, we must have the breast be smeared and sowred, to weane out childish longing from it.
            But the withdrawing of any of these earthly things from us, doth not so much withdraw us from the Earth as the calling away of those deare-ones in whose bloud, or love we have any interest,

the wives of our youthes, the children of our delight. These are they with whom we reioyced and they being gone, the remainder of our life seemes bitter unto us, and we thinke with our selves, what further use is there of us? or what portion have we left upon the Earth? we crie like children, that have their delights and rattles taken from them. And at last as when the nurse makes the child beleev she hath layed them in the Cradle to sleepe, the childe cries to sleepe likewise, that he may be neere them: so we when our deare ones are layed downe and composed in their beds of dust, we are weary of waking any longer, our eyes grow as heavy as our hearts, we see nothing to reioyce in, or take comfort in; we desire as Iacob, to goe downe to the grave to our sonnes, we desire to sleepe by the sides of our beloved ones, that with them we may awake againe, after the likenesse of him who layeth us and them unto our rest,

and shall raise us againe unto our refreshing.
            Thus should ye (Right Honorable) looke after this renowned Ladie, who is now composed unto her rest in the Bed of Earth; suspiring and longing after the same refreshing, the same hope that hope which is now no lōger hope with her but sight and sense, &amp; possession it selfe. But if you would have your soule find the same rest with hers, let your soule seek it as she did. If with her you would find the kingdome of God seek with her the Righteousnes therof.
            Let us awhile looke into the Grave with which these deare ashes are entrusted, for in that house 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                as the Septuagint reades that of Eccles: 13. Though the Grave be the house of death, yet we Septuag. shall derive from hence, an example of a gracious life, and of such a death as undoubtedly ushers in a glorious life.
            Anciently there were great treasures hid in the Sepulchres of great ones, &amp;

if we looke into this we shall finde a treasure too, a treasure of rich example to us all.
            As she was derived of a very noble princely extraction, so she ennobled her selfe much more by endevouring to assure her selfe of her regeneration and adoption, than by her birth. That was the honor by which she valued her selfe, and indeede the true and genuine Honor of you all, Right Honorable. He that called Abraham father was everlastingly accursed because Luke. 16. God was not his father. It is a good observation of Philo, upon that of Gen: 6. These are the Generations of Noah, Noah was a iust man and walked with God. &amp;c. Moses, saith he, setting downe Noahs Genealogie insteed of recounting his Ancestors, reckoneth his vertues. It were easie for me to name many noble names like unto these, to prove that nobility by which she esteemed her selfe principally honored. She had a mind of a most excellent cōposure, of a noble &amp;

generous height, but attempered with an admirable sweetnesse, and humility, so that I may affirme, that she made use of the greatnesse of her Spirit in nothing so much, as either in the magnanimous contempt of unworthy iniuries, (for some such were aymed at her though none could fasten, her vertue had so Oyled her name, that no Inke would sticke upon it) or else in the patient tollerating of worldly occurrences, and afflictions, and of them she made this happy advantage that as a thred besmeared with any filth, must be drawne through some narrow hole for the cleering of it, so the pressure of some afflictions seemed to cleere her from many corruptions, through which nature, &amp; custome, and fashion and greatnesse, do yet draw the lines of others lives.
            Her understanding was of great perspicacity, and as she fayled not to imploy the same for the comprehending of such occasions and affaires, as

might advantage &amp; susteine the estate of her house, and procure and reinforce the content and comfort of her noble Lord: So principally she directed the strength thereof for the enabling her selfe with the knowledg of the misteries of Redemption, her delight was in the law of God, she was an unwearied reader of the Oracles of Gods sacred word, she that aimed at a living againe though she must die, sought not the tree of the knowledge of good and evill, which made us all obnoxious to die, but the Tree of the knowledge of God, which is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                the Tree of life it selfe, as Thala
                     •
                  ius calls it in Biblioth. Patrum. And as she had the knowledge of truth to give light unto her Religion, so she had the truth of Religion, to give life unto her knowledge. I make no doubt but the State thereof hath beene much advanced, by her instruction and incouragement in this house, which hath beene long honoured, for honouring of God. It hath

pleased her Lord more then once to make profession, not onely what refreshing her comforts, what support her Counsells have brought him, but now much he hath in the estate of the minde beene bettered by her.
            I am perswaded, they have beene 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                yoke-fellowes in this worke, &amp; I trust they shal be hereafter 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                fellow heires of one and the same Grace. From him, and her selfe, she made a diffusion of her goodnesse to all hers, educating them in such puritie, and inocency, as is admirable, in those, who (I know not how) are lyable to be betraved by their Birthes and fortunes unto great depravations, and exorbitancies, so that we may say of her as Greg: Naz: said of his Sister Gorgonia, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . Nazian.
            
            She made the fruite of her Bodie, to become the fruite of the spirit. And of the same goodnesse there was a proportionable diffusion amongst those

that depended on her. How many that lived neere her, hath the Elixar of the same goodnesse, rendered of the same qualitie, and propertie? her charitie and Courtesie was large and open unto all. I name these as strictures of that fire of zeale, which she had to goodnesse. She was not like those which esteeme themselves onely members, and others but 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                apostems congenite and connaturall partes with themselves, her zeale was farre from being 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                a bitter zeale, such as we see in some, like a salt-light, which burnes indeed but spits withall; while she had health she made advantage therof thus to demeane her selfe, not deferring the taking up of good purposes 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                &amp;c. Greg: Naz: till the artlesse Physitian takes upon him to Greg: Naz: dispense what houres of life and continance he pleaseth unto us, weighing us out either sicknesse or health with his severe-rod, and commonly discoursing and concluding of the disease that

brought death, after death it selfe. But the greatest part of her life was a Parasceue, a preparation to her dissolution, as if she had beene sensible, that as Christ dyed upon the parasceue, the day of preparation; so none have any advantage by the death of Christ, but those which premit such a preparation before their owne death, and dissolution. Is it not admirable that she who had runne through some hard lessons, in the Schoole of affliction, loved the rod so, for the healing, and sanctifying benefit, which she found in it, that it was her frequent prayer, that God would be pleased when he called her hence, he would be pleased to call her by a consumption, rather then by any other way. And accordingly it was so: she conceived, that many had been shaken with the whirlwinde of a convulsion, and perhaps the Lord God was not in that winde: many consumed with the fire of adustion and choller, &amp; perhaps the Lord God

was not in that fire: but whereas many have beene summoned away by the still soft voice of consumption, the Lord God is frequently in that voyce. And certainly the Lord supported her, the Lord perfected his strength in her weaknes, for she susteined that afflictiō with such admirable moderation, with such strength and vigour of spirit that if any man had entred her Chamber, if he had not read the truth of her sufferings in the decayes and weaknesse of her person, hee would have thought there had been none sicke there; whatsoever she suffered, there was nothing in her mouth, but thanks to that gracious hand which lay so light vpon her, and made her suffer no more.
            As before, so in her sicknesse especially, it was her uncessant practise, to commend her selfe continually unto God, and that in the most conceived, and feeling formes in 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Words winged with affection, and zeale not like those Estriches wings

wherewith our sluggish devotions are usually fledged, which as the estriches make a faire offer at flying toward heaven, but are held down by the grossnes of their bodies, so howsoever we seeme to soare, yet are we restrained by our carnall heavinesse. But her wordes were winged so, as to carry her spirit there where her hope was, farre above the reach of Satan, though he be planted high too, as high as a Prince of the aire So that no marvell if her spirit during her last affliction, were in such a composed settlednesse, it was out of the enemies reach. She was not in the aire lyable to be shaken with Tempests, and windes, but even in heaven it selfe, which cannot be turmoyled with any such agitations. She vsed 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                to seale vp her bosome against temptation by continuall prayer, so that Satan durst not attempt her, seeing what impression seeing whose Image, and superscription, she bore; Hence was that often comfortable

profession, how firme and stedfast she found her faith! yet shee was iealous of her selfe because shee seemed to finde no greater measure of sorrow in her selfe when shee looked backe from her future to her former life: Put she ever used to accuse her want of sorrow with such a measure of sorrow, as well witnessed the truth thereof. For this respect she did with exceeding diligence search, and with great Iudgement choose, whatsoever the Scripture could afford her for the establishing of her Spirit, and the building up of her assurance in the Lord Iesus, committing with her owne hand, even in 
                  ••
               at weakenes
                  •
               e, to writing what she had observed, and contin
                  •
               ing that pr
                  •
               ctise till within very few dayes before her death, before which she became most peaceably setled, and r
                  •
               solved, that God according to that of Greg: Naz: 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Greg: Naz: 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                God desireth that our

hearts should be pricked, but not stabbed thorough; And her faith being thus strengthened, and established, by continuall prayer and hearing, and by frequent communicating that Sacrament which Ignatius calls 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                she preserved it in such strength and vigor, that the day of Ignatius. her dissolution, I comming to her, she professed, that whatsoever her sufferings were, yet she did nothing but claspe her selfe about her-sweet Saviour. And againe the same day, I see Satan hovering over me, but though he be the Prince of the Ayre (they are her owne words) yet he doth but hover like a bird in the Ayre not being able to seize upon me, I still feele the advantage. And thus she passed as she was passing away, in the same calme behaviour that she had ever shewed, rendering her selfe into the Armes of her redeemer: And she having lived thus, and died thus, now she is dead, shall we thinke she doth not live; No

no! It is not impertinent what I have read in Spartian of Hadrian. Signa mortis 
               Epus: de char: chap: 27. 
               haec habuit. Annulus sponte de digito delapsus est, but the Ring of faith as Bernard calls it, never slipped from her, she tooke it with her, to be maried for ever in it, unto the Lambe, who hath graven her in the palmes of his hands, and hath set her as a Scale upon his Arme there to remaine for ever. Vnto which honor the Lord with her bring us all that we may so live, &amp; so die, &amp; then so live for ever, without dying any more
            Amen.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            PErlegi hanc concionem funebrem in Cap. 11. St. Ioha 1. ver. 25. in quâ nihil reperio bonis moribus, aut sauae doctrinae contrarium quo minus cumutilitate publicâ imprimatur; ita tamen, ut si non intra tres menses proximè sequentes typis mandetur, haec licentia sit omninò irrita.
            
               
                  Prid: Calend. Iunii. 1635
               
               Guil: Bray.
            
            
         
      
   

