
   
      
         
            The widowes petition delivered in a sermon before the iudges at the assises held at Northampton, Iuly 25. 1633. by Antony Fawkner, parson of Saltry All-Saints, alias Moygne in Huntingtonshire.
            Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.
         
         
            
               1635
            
         
         Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00586
            STC 10724
            ESTC S101885
            99837688
            99837688
            2026
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00586)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2026)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 834:08)
         
         
            
               
                  The widowes petition delivered in a sermon before the iudges at the assises held at Northampton, Iuly 25. 1633. by Antony Fawkner, parson of Saltry All-Saints, alias Moygne in Huntingtonshire.
                  Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.
               
               [6], 28 p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and are to be sold by Elias Peerse, at his shoppe in St Maries Church-yard,
                  Oxford :
                  Anno Dom. 1635.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Unjust judge (Parable) --  Sermons.
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
THE WIDOWES PETITION, Delivered in a Sermon before the Iudges at the Aſſiſes held at Northampton, Iuly 25. 1633. by ANTONY FAWKNER, Parſon of Saltry All-Saints, alias Moygne in Huntingtonſhire.
            
            
               
                  Ieremiah. 22. 3. 4. 5.
               Thus ſaith the Lord; Execute ye Iudgement and Righteouſneſſe, and deliver the oppreſſed from the hand of the oppreſſor, and vex not the ſtranger, the fatherleſſe, nor the widow, doe no violence, nor ſhed innocent bloud in this place.
               For if you doe this thing, then ſhall the King (ſitting vpon the Throne of David) enter in by the gates of this houſe, and ride vpon charets and vpon horſes, both he and his ſervants and his people;
               But if ye will not heare theſe words, I ſweare by my ſelfe, ſaith the Lord, that this houſe ſhall be waſt.
            
            
               OXFORD Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and are to be ſold by Elias Peerſe, at his ſhoppe in St Maries Church-yard. Anno Dom. 1635.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, MY MVCH HONOVRED PATRON, Sr LEVVIS VVATSON, KNIGHT AND BARONET, His Maieſties High SHERIFE in the County of Northampton for the time being, Grace, Mercy, and Peace &amp;c.
            
               Right Worſhipfull
            
            
               TO three Benefactors are wee of the Engliſh Prieſthood principally engaged. To God for his providence over vs; to our moſt Gratious King for his protection of vs, and to our bounteous Patrons for their munificence vnto vs. God giues vs what is his owne and from

no other, the King what is his owne but yet deriued from God, but the Patron calles to that portion which is neither his nor any others, ſaue only Gods. So that God is our Grand Patron, which giues vs our maintenance, our good Prince his vicegerent to defend it, and our Patrones (to whom by their and the Lawes permiſſion belongs the right of advocation or calling) are his ſtewards to diſpence it. To every one of which by the Law of gratitude belongs both the Dication of our ſelues, and the Dedication of our Chriſtian labours. In this my poore piece though I cannot finde enough to ſatisfie all, yet ſomething out of it I may ſhare to each, ſo (of what it is) not defrauding any. To God then I dedicate that ſufficiency it hath; for from his ſpirit and aſſiſtance it came; to my Soveraigne the benefits of Peace, Iuſtice, and Obedience there-from accruing, for to him in the firſt place they belong, and to you the Booke, for to you it appertaines, as occaſioned by your Commaund. Truth only therein I can promiſe, eloquence I dare not: it agrees not with our Site, where the daily obiect Ariſtoph. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  .of our eares are the Comedians 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and the frequenteſt Prototypes of

our imitations, the obſtreperous cadencies of gnats and froggs. Plaine it is, and ſo, like my ſelfe; and indeed ceremonious I would not bee, becauſe I would be what I ſhould bee, Reall. For ceremonies are but ſupplements in the place of realities, a tiſſue coate to cover a blacke skinne: and therefore I haue alwaies eſteemed their immoderate vſe ſuperſtition, as well in the expreſſion of loue and duty, as in religion. I thinke I need no Apology to the reader: For though my endeavours be weake, yet are they honeſt. Wherefore if he be good, hee will pardon mee, and if he be bad, I will neglect him. Accept them I beſeech you, Noble Sir, what they are. The beſt I can ſay of them, is to ſay, they are the embleme of your ſervants duty; and with them you ſhall receiue the zeale of
            
               Your obſervant Chaplaine ANTONY FAWKNER.
               Saltry All-Saints, alias Moygne. Iuly 30. 1633.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
To day is a day appointed for the adminiſtration of Iuſtice, and a fit time therefore to preferre petitions. I haue one (Right honourable) to preſent vnto your Lordſhips acceptation. It is the Widowes in the Parable.
            
               LVKE 18. 3.
               
                  Doe mee Iustice againſt mine Adverſary.
               
            
            
               1 And he ſpake a Parable vnto them that they ought alwaies to pray and not to wax faint,
            
               2 Saying: There was in a City a Iudge which feared not God, neither reverenced man.
            
               3 And there was a widow in that City, and ſhee came vnto him, ſaying, doe mee Iuſtice againſt mine adverſary.
            
               4 And he would not for a time; But afterward he ſaid with himſelfe, Though I feare not God nor reverence man;
            
               5 Yet becauſe this widow troubles me, I will doe her right, lest at last ſhe come and make me weary.
            
               6 And the Lord ſaid heare what the vniust Iudge ſaith.
            
               
               7 And ſhall not God avenge his Elect, which cry day and night vnto him, yeathough hee ſuffer long for them?
            
               8 I tell you that hee will avenge them quickly; But, when the ſonne of man comes, ſhall hee finde faith on Earth?
            And there was a Widow in that Citty, which came to him, ſaying, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Doe me Iustice againſt mine Adverſary.
            
               THough God hath made man in his image, yet hath hee not framed him his ſtatue. Some lines indeed of his figure he hath given him, but the pitch of his ſtature in the whole extent of infinity, hee hath iuſtly denied him. Like a skilfull painter, who ſhewes the curioſity of his cunning in purtraying the Lanſkip of himſelfe: which like a dwarfe ſtandes a loofe off, ſhadowed in a miſt or cloude, bearing indeede ſome reſemblance of his feature, but no proportion at all, nor paralell to the ſize or bigneſſe of his body naturall. So that, as the eye of man, which is the Sunne of the leſſer world, though it repreſent the eye of heaven, the Sun of the firmament, yet is ſo diſproportioned in regard of excellency, that it is not only eclipſed, but alſo dazelled by the greaters glory: our vnderſtanding likewiſe, the cleareſt eye of the ſoule, and the beſt pourtraitures ſolis juſtitiae, of that Sunne of righteouſneſſe, Almighty God, in man, is but oculus noctuae, the dimme ſight of a purblinde owle, which

waters at the Maieſty, at the brightneſſe, at the ſunne of his countenance: and ſees him beſt after ſun-ſet when he declines the luſter of his face: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , his back-parts, Moſes ſaw no more. Exod. 33. 23. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                in the darke, in twilight; St Paul ſaw him no clearer 1. Cor. 13. 12. If then Gods eſſence be of ſo inſcrutable a ſecrecie, it is but fitting its revelation ſhould be hallowed with myſtery. Wherefore Satan (who was alwaies ambitious to vſurpe and counterfet the magnificence of his glory) ever hooded his Oracles with the reverend vaile of ſacred obſcurity. The Prieſts muſt interpret what they alone could heare in their ſecret Adyts: and Sphinx in porticu, the Sphinx painted in the porch, was the infallible Embleme of divine riddles, and holy myſteries in the temple. And in all this Satan is but Gods Ape, arrogating vnto himſelfe by a preſumptuous imitation, what is only due to the Almighties perfection. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Heb. 1. 1. God ſpake of old in diuers manners &amp;c. by Dreames, P. Fagius in Exod. 28.by Prophets, and by Vrim; but all obſcure: Vrim requires an accurate obſervation, Dreames their interpretation, and Prophets their expoſition. They were all 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Parables, high Sentences: ſo the Prophet expounds the former by the latter: I will open my mouth in a Parable, and declare high ſentences of old. Pſal. 78. 2. Yea and Chriſt too (who came after him though he was before him) preached the doctrine of his Kingdome to the multitudes in Parables, &amp; without Parables ſpake he nothing vnto them. S. Mat. 13. 13. For as we cannot ſee the Divinity but only 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , winking and with infirmity, apprehending rather what he is not by the negation of his creatures, then comprehending what hee is by the poſition of

his Nature: ſo alſo (for otherwiſe then our ſelues know him we cannot reveale him) we can only treade veſtigia, thoſe footſteps which hee hath imprinted in his creatures, and ſo, ex pede Herculem, coniecture the brightneſſe of the creator, by the glimps of his glory ſhining in the creature. The divinity which the man heard in the third heaven, were 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , words ineffable. 2. Cor. 12. 4. And the doctrine S. Paul taught on earth contained 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               ſome things hard to bee vnderſtood. 2. S. Peter 3. 16. So tranſcendent is the ſubiect, that its expreſſion muſt needs bee difficult. The chamber of his Maieſtie is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Light inacceſſible. 1. Tim. 6. 16. A light that illumines the humble back-ſtanders, and a light that dazels the ſaucy intruders. The diſciples could ſee. S. Math. 13. 16. The multitudes could not ſee. verſ. 13. Ioh. Maldonatus in S. Math. 18. 23.and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                (ſaith the text) therefore ſpake hee to them in Parables. In all which Parables Maldonate obſerues two things remarkable: Partes ad neceſſitatem, &amp; Emblemata ad ornatum: the neceſſary parts of which they are compoſed, and the emblematicall Accident with which they are garniſhed. The neceſſary parts (to inſtance in the Parable wee haue in hand) are the Iudge, and the Widow; without which could not conſiſt in the Parable, the Analogie between thē, &amp; God, &amp; his Elect. The ornament are the Accidentall concomitants; as the City, the forme of the Iudges ſelfe-communication, &amp; the ſet compoſure of the Widowes petition. Which had they beene omitted, yet had not the Parable in its ſubſtance beene at all vnioynted. The Parts as reſpecting the Allegoricall ſcope we paſse by, as not proportioned for this occaſion. But ſtay with me a while (I beſeech you)

vpon part of the ornament, viz. The ſet forme of the Widowes petition. For, by reaſon that Quod ſignificativum 
               Dom. à Soto paru. Log. in Significate.
               est alterius cuiuſpiam in ſenſu tralatitio, primò ſignificativum eſt ſui ipſius in ſenſu primaeuo; whatſoever ſignifies another thing, firſt ſignifies it ſelfe. Nero firſt expreſseth the Emperours perſon in his owne name, though ſecondarily any barbarous, or inhumane tyrant. Though this petition in ſenſu Allegorico, in the Parabolicall ſcope and figuratiue ſenſe includes the prayers of the Elect to God: yet in ſenſu Primauo, in its firſt and literall ſenſe (ſaluâ ad Scriptur as ſacr as Analogiâ) without violence at all to holy Scripture, it expreſseth what it ſelfe is: the ſupplicacion of a diſtreſſed Widow for reliefe vnto the Magiſtrate, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : Doe mee Iustice againſt mine adverſary. Evill I know it would agree both with this place and my calling (Right Honourable) if I ſhould performe, what ſome (I queſtion not) promore ſuo, according to their ill wont, may expect, S. Auguſtin. ſerm. 36. de verbis Domini in S. Lucam 2. lib. 2. qq▪Evangelic.c. 45.in converting the reverend modeſty of a Sermon, into the ſnarling petulancie of a Satyr. The vniuſt Iudge in the Parable, adminiſters noe matter to cavill againſt your equity, nor covertly to traduce your vndoubted innocencie: S. Auguſtine abſolues mee from the ſuſpicion, and fruſtrates their expectation, in his judicious warrant of the Parables interpretation. For the ſcope of this Parable includes an argument, à Minori ad Maius, or à Diſsimili, from the diſproportion 
                  S. Luke 18.of an vnjuſt Magiſtrate to the juſt God. The gradation is this. If a man ſold to injuſtice and obdurate, hardned in cruelty, yet at length by inceſſant cries, and continuall ſuit bee mollified and inclined to lenity, and a iuſt commiſeration of the Orphans

miſery, and avenge vpon the oppreſſor, the wrong of the poore orator; if he, if ſuch, if ſo bad a man doe ſo, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , will not God? The words are equivalent with, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , yea much more will God avenge the cry of his Elect. verſ. 8. Let then the ſenſe be (as we take it) literall If an vniuſt Iudge haply vſurping, haply abuſing his lawfull power, yet overcome at length with importunity of petitions and requeſts, doe Iuſtice to the Widow, and deliuer her from her oppreſſors; if hee, if ſuch an one doe it, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                will not God? will not you who are Gods? yea 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , much more, will you doe ſo; You who are the worthy ſubſtitutes of a moſt Religious, and indeed a matchleſſe Prince, who himſelfe is the vicegerēt of the moſt righteous God. Dixit Dominus, Dij estis, God hath ſaid that you are Gods, the protectors of his poore, and the Iudges of his people, to whom then but to you, ſhould the Widow cry? Doe mee iuſtice againſt mine adverſary.
            
            Concerning the words (beloued) poyze them but judiciouſly, and you ſhall apprehend a whole court of Aſſiſe in the Church, before you come to the Bench. Firſt then let the order of words and conſtruction, giue place vnto the order of Legall proceſse in trials: and then plainely ſee Actorem the plaintife in the perſon of the Widow; and vnder it comprehend the neceſsary ſupporters, Teſtes or witneſses, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Guli. Bodaeus com. graec. col. 195. lin: 29.ME, doe MEE iuſtice: In the ſecond place view, Reum, the defendant; Qui litiganti ſe opponit, which oppoſeth the Plaintife (ſo Budaeus interprets 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , or Adverſary) and vnder that title againe implie, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the Advocates, counſell, pleaders or defenders of the cauſe. And when all theſe haue ſpoken what can

be expected, ſaue a Verdict from the Iury, and ſentence from the more eminent Iudge, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , doing Iuſtice according to the petition: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               doe Iuſtice: Loe ſix requiſite perſons to this grand-Court in three words are eminent, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Doe iuſtice; there is the Iudge, and the Iury: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Mee, there is the Plaintife and the witneſſe: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , or Adverſary: Ther's the Defendant, and his cauſes patrons his counſell. Of theſe God aſſiſting, and firſt of the Plaintife and her witneſſe, in the perſon of the Widow, expreſſed in the Pronoune
            
               
                  ME, MEE.
               I beginne with the Plaintife, for indeed ſhee beginnes the ſuit, or action: and inſomuch as ſhee is oppreſſed petitioneth, but as ſhe is a ſubiect, challengeth the priviledge of Iuſtice. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Vidua, A Widow though the plaintife bee, yet a naturall liege-woman ſhe is: and our lawes are no leſſe comfortable then were Solons, remouing 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , the burthen of oppreſſion, from the ſhoulders of the innocent. If thoſe 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   in the commonwealth of Athens, the Great ones, intruded vpon the aunciently moſt wretched 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , the poore Plebeians right, the Tribunall of Solon was immediatly their Sanctuary: and the glory of his wiſdome, was the wiſdome of his government: 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; he weighed Iuſtice equally vnto them all. The honour of great perſons might indeed chalenge a reverence; but in foro Iuſtitiae, in the court of Aſsiſe there was no difference. As the offenſiue poore were never pitied, neither were the iniurious Potentates ever priviledged. If then the Widow be wronged, ſhe is priviledged to complaine without leaue: I ſay no more in the behalfe of the Plaintife,

then what a great Iuſtice, Adrian the Emperour himſelfe Pompon Feſtus de Magiſtrat. Roman. c. 25.hath taught mee, in the caſe of the Defendants; who, craving licence to anſwere, receaued this anſwere: Hoc non peti, ſed praestari ſolere, that their petition was frivolous, ſith they might demaund what they craved. For indeed that is the armour which God left vs, when he diſarmed vs of private revenge. Hee keepes that to himſelfe: vengeance is mine ſaith the Lord. Deut. 32. 35. But liberty to complaine hee grants vnto vs: When they haue a matter, they come vnto mee, ſaith Moſes Exod. 18. 16. yet though God giues vs leaue to complaine of our oppreſſours, hee doth not grant vs liberty to bee Baratours againſt our neighbours. An humble Plaintife, is a terme expreſſing an injured innocency: but a common quarreller, or accuſer, a note of infamy. Abel was a Plaintife: Clamavit vox ſanguinis, &amp;c. The voice of thy brothers blood cries vnto me Gen. 4. 10. But the Divell himſelfe is no worſe then a common ſute-monger: 'tis one of his hatefull names; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , The accuſer of our brethren. Rev. 12. 10. Two things therefore Pyrrh. Pe
                        •
                     ottus in Mart. Epigr. lib. 1. Epi. 10. Col. 639. lin. 53. Ioh, de ſacra quereu. in verb. obſolet Iouo. Guli. Lindwodus provin. conſtit. tit. de conſuct. cap. ſtatutum eſt. §. quod ſi duo verb vidua.are to be enquired in the Widow complaining. 1. whether ſhe bee 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Vidua, a Widow at all, 2. whether ſhee be 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   a Widow indeede. For the firſt then, if wee examine the Quid nominis, the definition of the Latine name, from that Etymon wee ſhall eaſily expreſſe the nature of the thing. Vidua quaſi a viro idua, from Iduo (Hetruſco verbo) an obſolete word, for which both Gellius and Varro are quoted authors; ſignifying to divide, ſeparate, or part. So that Vidua is mulier a viro iduata, a woman ſeparated from, or deprived of her husband. And ſuch a one, if a Widow at all, muſt the Plaintife bee, one ſo

within the virge of the Iudges dominion, that ſhee is 
                     S. Gregorius in Deut. 23. ſi▪ intraucris ſegetem. &amp;c.vtterly deſtitute of all other protection. For elſe if his tuition belongs vnto anothers iuriſdiction, Quis te conſtituit Iudicem? Who made you a Iudge there? Falcem iudicij mittere non potes in eam rem quae alteri videtur eſſecommiſſa. S. Gregory determines it a main errour in Iudgement, to put a ſickle in another mans harveſt; to wreſt and ſcrue that cauſe vnto a lay inquiſition, which properly pertaines to the ciuill Iurisdiction. The plaintife here is no widow, no, no more thē that wife is, a wdow which is not forſakē, but forſakes her husband. A protectour ſhe hath, but ſhee reiects his aide; and a Widow if ſhee ſeeme to be, ſhee doth indeede but ſeeme ſo to be; or at leaſt 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 1. Tim. 5. 6. a laſciuious widow ſhee is, who delights, as in multiplicity of courts, ſo in plurality of husbands; and ſo can never be, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , a widow indeed, 1. Tim. 5. 3. which is the ſecond quaerie. And here againe the Apoſtle helpes vs. For 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , a widow indeede, is expreſſed by 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  verſ. 5. that is, deſolate, or left alone: and is farther noted in the ſame verſe by workes of piety. So that, to make the Plaintife, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , a widow indeede, two things againe a re requiſite: a deſolate Pouerty, and an oppreſſed innocency. For Poverty of it ſelfe alone as a Species of miſery, is the obiect of compaſſion and mercy. Miſericordiae ſedes Miſeria eſt: St Bernard tels vs, S, Bernardus de conuerſ, ad Clerum. cap. 10,that mercy lookes not ſo much vpon what is vniuſt, as vpon what is vnhappy; but Iuſtice on the other ſide takes little or no notice of generall calamity, and wholly fixeth its vnpartiall eye, vpon an indifferent equality. So that miſery in its community, as not pertaining to Iuſtice, is only the motiue, and Obiect of

                  mercy: but where calamity complaines of oppreſſion, there euen Iuſtice hath bowels too; and with mercy to the innocent avengeth in equity. Thus the poore in the eye of Pitty, is in generall every one that wants: but the poore in the ſight of juſtice, is hee &amp; only he, that wants his Due. So that oft times the rich man becomes the Widow; and a poore ſnake of farre meaner fortunes, is juſtly intituled the oppreſſour. For in the eſtimation of Iuſtice, he only is the Widow, not which hath the leaſt eſtate, but the moſt wrong. If therefore the Plaintife be an vniuſt caviller, hee does but vſurpe the widowes place; he is not ſo, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Indeede. And then though his miſery pleade never ſo pathetically for Pitty, yet Suâ ſponte ſe obſtringens ſceleribus, 
                  Philo-Iudaeus lib. de officio Iudicis.
                  non infelix, ſed iniuſtus cenſendus eſt (ſaith Philo) hauing both voluntarily, and vniuſtly accuſed the innocent, he is not ſo much to be commiſerated, becauſe vnhappy, as puniſhed becauſe vnrighteous. And therefore God himſelfe excludes his poverty from mercy, Thou ſhalt not eſteeme a poore man in his cauſe. Exod. 23. 3. As then the Widow indeede is to be relieued, ſo the counterfeit petitioner is to bee reiected. 5. Thom. Aquinas. 22. q. 68. art. 4.The ſchooleman alots a Talion for the one, and that from the great Biſhop Adrians decree, qui non probaverit quod obiecit, paenam quam intulit ipſe patiatur: let him that accuſeth, and cannot proue what he ſuggeſts, vndergoe that puniſhment, which the defendant ſhould haue ſuffered, if the ſuggeſtion had beene proued. A iuſt ſentence no doubt it is, as well in controverſies, as criminalls. And to this end wiſely, Guli. Poſtellusde Magiſtrat. Athen. c. 1.though more gently did the Athenian Magiſtrates demande 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  ab Actore &amp; Reo: Mony-pledges proportioned to the quality of the cauſe, from both

demand, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  ab Actore &amp; Reo: Mony-pledges proportioned Guliel. Poſte
                        •
                      lus de Magiſt. Athen. cap. 7.to the quality of the cauſe, from both the Plaintiffe, and the Defendant, at the beginning of each ſuit. Vt qui cauſa caderet, &amp;c. ſaith my Author, That he which after the triall, was caſt, might by this over
                  plus of loſſe, be taught never after, ſaucily to trouble the Iudge, or perverſely to moleſt his quiet neighbours with cauſeleſſe ſuits, or frivolous complaints. And againe, the Apoſtle preſcribes an honour to the other; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : Honour thoſe that are widows indeed. Honour them with the honour from the huſband due vnto the woman, the honour of Protection; So the wiſe man counſels in the widowes, in the Plaintiffes caſe. Deliver them that ſuffer wrong from the hand of the oppreſſour: and bee not faint-hearted when thou iudgeſt. Be as a Father vnto the Fatherleſſe, and as an Husband vnto their Mother; ſo ſhalt thou bee as the ſonne of the moſt high, and hee ſhall loue thee more then thy mother doth. Ecclus. 4. 9. 10. Obſerue (I beſeech you) the vnparalleld reward of Aſſimilation. In being tanquam Pater, as a Father to the poore, they ſhall bee ſicut Filius altiſsimi, as the Sonne of the most High, who is the Father of the Fatherleſſe, and the ludge of the Widowes. Pſal. 68. 5. And ſo I deſcend vnto the ſecond part of the Aſſiſe, contained vnder the Widowes Title,
            
            
               
                  Teſtes: the Witneſſes.
               All Demonſtration, and conſequently all perfect knowledge, we muſt confeſſe to be Derebus neceſſarits 
                  A
                        ••…
                     t. Poſtet. Anal. lib. 
                        •
                     
                  &amp; aeternae veritatis (as the Philoſopher inſtructs his ſchoole) about thoſe things which are in themſelues of an invariable conſtancie, and 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , or materialls in propoſitions of eternall truth, and conſequence infallible.

So that in thoſe things, without the ayde of externall information, reaſon can eaſily conclude the neceſſity of the effects and acts, from the conſtant influx, and vnchangable operation of their cauſe. But in all free Acts (and ſuch are all mans Actions) there is ſuch a variable contingencie, that a certain knowledge of their particulars can never bee attained, themſelues continuing Pro libitu for ever ſo vncertaine. Things that muſt be done, all men may knowe; but to thoſe things which either may, or may not be done, only the Actors, in whoſe liberty they are, are conſcious. Wherefore (becauſe of all humane actions, about which Iuſtice principally is converſant, there can bee in the Iudge no certaine knowledge demonſtratiue) God, for the better proceſſe of equity and right, hath allowed 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , a kinde of notice of their outward Acts, from the probability of externall teſtimonie. There is indeed aboue every mā, Teſt is intuens, a great and cleere-eyed witneſſe that viewes the heart and reynes, and fore-ſees our ſecreteſt actions before they come to Act. And there is too in every man, Teſtis internus, an inward witneſſe, which wee can no more eſchew, then we can runne from our owne ſelues; That Conſcientia, that intimate &amp; ioynt-knowledge, or conſcience of our Good or Evill, ſo ſoone, yea in the firſt inſtant it is done: And theſe two commonly, though they knowe moſt, ſpeake leaſt: God of his mercy forbearing, &amp; Conſcience bridled by him (in whoſe liberty for a time it is) for that time not openly convincing or accuſing. But the third witneſſe is Extra Hominem, without the man: who, becauſe the ſpirit of man is onely conſcious of what is in man, (according to the Apoſtle) can ingender no certaine knowledge in vs, but a probability

of truth by his accuſation; God frequently expreſſeth this his knowledge, in Vindication; conſcience hers, in Confeſsion; and our neighbour his, in Accuſation. God from his moſt infallible ſcience, both accuſeth, ſo he did Ely. 1. Sam. 2. 29. and condemneth, as in the blaſpheamers caſe, Levit. 24. 14. and avengeth without either accuſation, or conviction. For firſt hee puniſhed Iſrael, and after told the cauſe, Ioſh. 7. 11. Then conſcience is the beſt evidence next God, and both accuſeth, as S. Iohn. 8. 9. and condemneth. Rom. 14. 22. But the outward witneſſe, the neighbour, onely can accuſe. So then, God is Witneſſe, Iury, and Iudge; Conſcience, Witneſſe and Iurie; but Man, the witneſſe S. Th. Aquin. 2a 2ae. q. 70. art. 2.only. Wherefore, becauſe the witneſſes accuſation, as being moſt infirme, breeds onely the vncertaine evidence of probabilitie, God gradually betters and confirmes the truth of this probability, by the perſons multiplicity. If one onely accuſe, and one defend, it is probable the defendants anſwer may be as true as the Plaintiffes objection: but if two, or more witneſſe, and but one deny, the probability inclines to the part of the plaintiffe. Wherefore, at the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall the matter be eſtabliſhed. Deut. 19. 15. Two or three witneſſes, ſaith the old Teſtament, in the generality of caſes; and two or three witneſſes, ſaith the new, in an Elders accuſation at the leaſt, 1. Tim. 5. 19. And ſure I am, that if one had ſerued the turne, Suſanna, who is now ſo celebrated for her vertue and chaſtitie, had for her goodneſſe died, branded with the diſgracefull note of ſinne, and advoutries. One man hath but one ſoule; and therefore as conſcious of his owne thoughts, may bee irreuelably conſtant to his own villanie: but two or more men haue as many ſoules, and

thoſe ſoules, as diverſe thoughts, &amp; thoſe thoughts, as various expreſſions. So that what one falſely averres for truth, the other as ignorant of his thoughts, may contradict. For if both thoſe witneſſes againſt Suſanna had had but one ſoule, and had conſequently beene conſcious each to others thoughts, both ſurely would haue ſtood to one tale; and the ſecond would never haue called that a Prime tree. Dan. 13. 58. which the forme had before averred to be a Lentiske. verſ. 54. And therefore One witneſſe ſhall not testifie againſt a perſon to cauſe him for to dye, ſaith that firſt, greateſt, &amp; juſteſt Law-giuer, The Lord. Num. 35. 30. It is a Negatiue Sr Walter Raleygh hiſt. of the world, part. 1. lib. 2. cap. 4. §. 16.precept which in Morals bindes Adſemper: and the Author of our Engliſh Hiſtory of the World, quotes Forteſcue, ſpeaking of a great Iuſtice an acquaintance of his, who kenned well enough the common diſtinction, of a generall inconvenience, &amp; a particular miſchiefe, yet confeſſed vnto him, that vpon the conſcience of omiſſion of this negatiue precept in one caſe of life, he bare (I may ſay what himſelfe confeſſed) the guilt, &amp; conſequently the trouble to his graue. But all this we paſſe vnto the diſcuſſion of the Schooles; only this caveat let me leaue to thoſe it may concern, That he who carries his neighbours life, and fortunes, on ſo tickliſh a point, as the tip of his tongue had need be another Cato, &amp; vndequa
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      rotundus, a very perfect honeſt man. Or if one witneſſe be good, which in ſome caſe, and eſpecially when the defendants evill life is an evidence againſt himſelfe, I may not altogether contradict, as perſwading obedience to the Law; yet this I may be bold to ſay without the leaſt ſuſpicion of a crime: In this caſe, if in any, Two are better then One, Eccleſ. 4. 9. But a threefold cord is not eaſily broken, ver.

12. From the quantity then of the Witneſses, if wee deſcend vnto their quality, wee ſhall eaſily obſerue, that their teſtimony onely ingendering a probability, (as you haue heard) whatſoever defects may impaire that probability, detract, by conſequent, from the evidences ſufficiencie; As the defect of reaſon in children, mad, or diſtempered men, inferres a probability, that their evidence is but vanity. And againe, the defect of moderation in his paſſion or affection, makes an enimy iuſtly ſuſpected of malice in his accuſation. And if I ſhould ſay, that a moderate reſpect ought to bee had to the Mercenary baſeneſſe of the penurious, and the both fawning &amp; revengefull nature of the ſervile perſons Thom. Aquin 2a 2ae. q. 71. art. 3. 4. Boetius de conſol. Philoſ. proſ. 4.condition, I could both vrge the Roman Laws for my defence, and the Schoolemans Theſis, together with Boetius his complaint, for my protection. Si minus accuſati innocentiae, at accuſantium vilitas pudori eſse debuiſset. If Theoderick would not be perſwaded that the Defendant was innocent, yet well might he haue bluſhed at the baſeneſſe of the complainant. And indeed if wee doe but looke into our owne Courts of Iuſtice, we may two plainely (God knowes) conclude, that it is not ſo rare for men of meane condition, to be Mercenary in this accurſed kinde; when we ſo daily behold the fraternity of the Poſt, who almoſt hourely in their ſeaſons, make no bones of morgaging their ſoules to be knighted of the Divell. A knighthood they call it, (wretched Caitiffes as they are) and indeed it wants not ſome enſignes of the order: for their Periuries are their Spurres, which prick their guilty ſoules Poſt, Poſt haſt vnto Hell. I paſſe by the infidelity, and infamous courſe of life in the witneſſe, both impairing his evidence in the iudgement of the meaneſt Iurie. But let

theſe mercenary perjurers to their terrour knowe 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : Heſiod. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                  He that ſweares falſe hath a ſharpe tongue, that with one word murthers his neighbours body, &amp; Plato de Legum Iatione. dial. 6.his owne ſoule. Morte plectatur, was Plato's ſentence, Let him die the death; But Gods iudgement of Talion in parity of caſe is juſter, though not much eaſier, Doe vnto him as he thought to doe vnto his brother, Lev. 19. 19. 'Tis worthy the obſervation, that, notwithſtanding by Vrim and Thummim, Exod: 28, 3. the generall Philo Iud. de 10. Praeceptis.ſtreame of Interpretors conſtrue Light and Perfection; Yet Philo Iudaeus renders them, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : Truth and its manifeſtation. For indeed, Truth is Light: and he that was the Light, S. Iohn. 8. 12. Was the Truth 
                  Horat. carm. lib. 4. od. 9.too; cap. 14. 6 Now, Paulum ſepultae diſtat inertiae Celata virtus—valour without expreſſion, hath no more honour then ſluggiſh daſtardy: and A ſimili, Truth, that is ſilent, looſeth its owne, both reward, and beauty. No man puts a candle vnder a buſhell, S. Matth. 5. 15. Manifestation then, is Perfection too, Truths perfection: and witneſſe is no more then Manifeſtation, in Salv. de guber. Dei, lib. 2.
                  Salvians opinion; Teſtimonium eſse dicitur, quo rerum veritas approbatur; Evidence is nothing but an approbation of Truth. So that in Aarons garment, God made expreſſion of his loue to Truth, and her manifeſtation, placing them in Loco Sacerrimo iuxta pectus 
                  Philo Iud de 10. praecept.(faith my Author) vbipars animi eſt, qui principatum obtinet; vpon the moſt ſacred part of that Hallowed perſon, and the chiefe manſion of his ſoule, his Breaſt, as the moſt pretious ornament, and moſt proportioned to that part, which aboue all others is eſteemed moſt precious. Heare therefore and tremble, who ere thou art, that haſt whetted thy enuenomed tongue with falſhood

to thy brothers prejudice; learne, I ſay, with trembling whom thou haſt grieuouſly offended, and whom therefore thou muſt anſwer in the moſt dreadfull Iſid. de ſummo bono. cap. 59.day of the laſt iudgement. Iſidore tells thee thou muſt anſwer three: Deo, quem contemnis; Iudici, quem decipis; Innocenti, quem laedis: Thou muſt anſwer God, whoſe ninth great Commandement thou haſt violated; Thou muſt anſwer the Iudge too, whom by thy falſehood thou haſt deceaued, and thou muſt anſwer thy innocent Brother, whom by thy calumny thou haſt wounded. But when Periury is added to thy Philo Iudaeus de 10. praeceptis. Plutarch. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
                  Lie, Scelus prorumpit ad impietatem (exclaimes Philo) Sinne breakes forth into ſhameleſſe impiety. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c. Pericles loued his friend withall his heart, and was his ſervant too, Sans complement, in what he might, to be commanded; yet this friendſhip had an honeſt limitation too: 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : you ſhall giue him leaue to loue God beſt: hee will bee a friend vnto his friend; but not periured for him, no nor for his owne father. Erubeſce Chriſtiane, Bluſh O thou Salvian▪ de Gubern▪ Dei▪ lib 4.falſe Chriſtian: This Infidell, this Heathen man in reverend Salvians iudgement, is better farre then thou, Qui ſub tam magnae profeſsionis nomine vivis, &amp; poſitus in religione peccas. He never heard the precepts of the Goſpell; thou art taught them: Hee never ſaw the Law of Life; but thou haſt read it. In the midſt of life thou art in death. Perdidiſti vim tantinominis, Thou haſt loſt the glory, the weight of ſo great a name, as Chriſtian; 
                  Ezek. 18. 21. 22.
                  and art worthy to be beaten with many stripes, S. Luk. 12. 47. Who ever thou art therefore that haſt offended, knock thy breaſt, and petition with the Publican for mercy. At what time ſoever, &amp;c. Ezek. 18. 21. Remember the reſt, and deſpaire not of remiſſion. But

Thou whoſe purer ſoule is cleare from this offence, this bloudy crime, goe on in the peace of God, and good luck haue thou in the name of the Lord. Speake the troath, and ſo honour God: ſpeak the whole troath and ſo preſerue thy hurtleſſe neighbour; and ſpeake nothing but the troth and ſo help thee God. Make not a lye of nothing, as did the ſonnes of Belial▪
                   againſt guiltleſſe Naboth. 1. King. 21. 13. Make not a lye of the truth, as did the witneſſes againſt our ſpotleſſe Saviour, Matth. 26. 61. This man ſaid, I can deſtroy the Temple of God: and build it againe in three daies. For truth it was indeed that he did ſay, Deſtroy this Temple, and in three daies I will raiſe it vp againe, St Iohn. 2. 19. Yet were thoſe witneſſes by the infallible teſtimony of the holy Ghoſt 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Falſe witneſses. Mat. 26. 60. And S. Origen. S. Chryſoſtome. S. Hieron. Beda. Theophylact. Euthym. &amp;c. Forteſcue lap. 53.for their falſhood, three reaſons by the Fathers are alleaged. Firſt, becauſe they gaue their evidence Malo animo, with a malitious intent, and for reward, and not for manife ſtation of the Truth, &amp; benefit of the common wealth, which was evident by their long concealement. Secondly, they did it Alijs verbis, in other and not the ſame words which he ſpake himſelfe, as by comparing places may appeare. Thirdly, and principally, they did interpret what he ſaid, Diverſo ſenſu, in another ſenſe then that which himſelfe meant, which is the greateſt injury of all. For in the order of Nature, Eius eſt exponere, cuius eſt componere: Words are but the ſignes of thoughts, and hee that ſpeakes them, knowes his owne thoughts beſt, and therefore in a rationall conſequent ſhould be his owne interpreter, as beſt knowing to expound them trueſt. They expound his words of the great Materiall Temple of Hieruſalem, but he meant them of the Temple of his Body, Iohn. 2.

21. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , therefore, Falſe witneſſes they were; and ſo are all ſuch as doe the like. But puniſhment hath overtaken them; Gods vēgeance ſticks faſt vnto them; they are ceaſed from being a nation, and according to their deſperate imprecation, St Mat. 27. 25. The better part of this two thouſand yeares, His blood hath beene vpon them and vpon their Children. Nor need we wonder, for otherwiſe it could not bee. The wiſdome of God hath ſpoken it, A falſe witneſſe ſhall not be vnpuniſhed, and he that ſpeaketh lyes ſhall not eſcape, Prov. 19 5. Long (Beloued) I knowe I haue inſiſted vpon this Point of the Witneſſes, and not without ſome cauſe. For the moſt inſtructions belong properly to thoſe who are the Keyes of all controverſies, opening or ſhutting at their own conſciences direction. Now the Defendant, I knowe would haue his place too▪ but ſeeing the time haſtens Vs, and wee haue beene buſied ſo long about the Plaintiſe, as in courſe of Law hee anſwers by his Counſell, it will not bee amiſſe if in the proceſſe of this diſcourſe we comprehend him in his Counſell, 
                  Pars 2. D. Th. Aquin. 2a 2ae. q. 69. art. 1. 2, 3. 4.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : From my Adverſarie.
               A long thread we might eaſily ſpinne, if wee intended to weaue the Schoolemans webbe in the enquiry of the lawfulneſſe of the Defendants ſelfe-protection by Falſhood, Calumny, App
                        •
                     ale, or open Force, all concluded vnlawfull in ſome caſe, as repugnant to the ordinance and glory of God. The time therefore preventing any long diſcourſe, and Your weighty affaires calling to the Practick part of what in this place you are to learne, as in the Texts diviſion we intimated the Counſell vnder the Defendants title; here verſo ordine, wee will include the Defendants inſtruction in his

Counſell, or Advocats. Whoſe right of living by their D. Th. Aquin 2a 2ae. q. 71.deſeruing Faculty, was never yet in my ſmall reading called to queſtion, ſaue by the Schooleman, and that for no other reaſon, thē that (for which all truth is queſtioned) S. Auguſt. ad Maced.its farther illuſtration, S. Augustine yeelds, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   the Honour of maintenance, as well as to any, to their lawfull calling; neither can the honour of Reverence bee by any meanes denied, which all nations Aeſchin. cont. Cteſiphont.haue iuſtly pay'd to their protecting Advocates. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   the Orator ſtiles them, the Guard and Armie of defence vnto their Clients: and therefore in my iudgment, that Lex Cincia Muneralis, the Law that M. Cineius preferred amongſt the Romanes, cutting from Counſellours their lawfull Fees, argues the Law propounder himſelfe to haue had but a gouty fiſt. Mart. Epig.
                  Nil patrono porrigit, haec Chiragra eſt. Surely his fingers ioines were knit with that covetous diſcaſe, that he could never open his hand with a reward of gratitude, to his protecting Advocate. S. Auguſtine with a more impartiall ſentence, both decrees to them, and S. Auguſt. ad Maced.confines them to their due. Extorta per immoder atam improbitatem repeti ſolent, data per toler abilem conſuetudinem non ſolent. What injuriouſly they exact, they are bound to reſtore; but what iuſt cuſtome allowes, they may with conſcience receaue. Our Sav ours determination is Indefinite &amp; Equipollent to an Vniverfall: Iuv. Sat. 1.
                  The Labourer, that is, Every Labourer is worthy of his hire, Luk. 10. 7. Labour then they muſt, they muſt plead, as neither mute for feare, Vt. Lugdunenſem Rhetor dicturus ad aram: For ſo through the impotencie of his cowardly paſſion, he betrayes the iuſtice of his Clients actions: nor ſilent for reward; for indeed Plu
                     
                        ••…
                     
                   that blind mony-monger, hath too oft an imperious

power over an orators tongue, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Ariſtoph. in 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .So the Comedian expreſſeth it: He ſo ſtops and bungs vp his mouth with a morſell of clay, that there is not a cranie left for a ſentence to crowd forth to the defence of the Innocent. Speake then they muſt. And then againe, two things let them ſeriouſly obſerue in their office of pleading, and ſo ſhall they well deſerue the Labourers hire; &amp; as an overplus of recompence, merit that Grande 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   or generall approbation of all their Audience. Now becauſe, Oratoris virtus 
                  Plato in Apolong. Socrat.
                  est vera dicere: An Orators beſt eloquence in Plato's iudgement is to ſpeake the truth, theſe two things are requiſite. Firſt, That they ſpeake that Truth, Substantially: then, That they ſpeake it Syncerely. In a word, That they deliver it with a good tongue, and from as good an heart. To render the truth Subſtantially, is to ſpeake it plainely and ſuccinctly, or briefely: neither trifling away the Iudges time, with too long, or too impertinent enlargements; nor preoccupating hiseares Gaſp. Contarenus de Venet. Repub. lib. 4.with tinfoiled, or gilded ſentences. In the Veneti
                        ••
                     
                   Iudiciarie Courts of Controverſies, a certaine time is limited to the Advocates, Vltra quod orationem protendere non poſſunt, (as a Gentleman of that City teſtifies) which by Law they can in no caſe exceed. Hee that ſpeakes Truth, ſpeakes enough in two lines: Sed tu, Goſconi, 
                  Mart. Epig.
                  diſ
                        •
                     ica long a facis: But how many are there in our liſts that are too too tedious in but two lines? Philem. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                  
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . A whole volume of ſolid expreſſions never wearies the hearers; but nothing to the purpoſe is tedious, though but two words. If then a word be ſo tedious, ſure many of thoſe impertinent ſcroles are burthenſome vnto exceſſe, that in a whole Centurie of lines cō
                  taine

nothing pretious ſaue their price, which (God knowes) ſo wrings the poore petitioner, that ſo long as hee liues after, hee hath experimentall cauſe to approue our Saviours counſell, as well in common Politie, as Divinity: Agree with thine Adverſary quickly, Mat. 5. 25. No bauling Act. 2. 24. Guil. Poſtel. de Megiſtrat. Athen. cap: 4.
                  Tertullus could be heard of in Athens, where their honeſt proverb, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , as mute as a Lawyer or Iudge, condemnes many of our Pleaders importunity, in the proverbiall proteſtation of theirs, at leaſt the Iudges (their examples) Modeſty. 
                  Gaſp. Contarenus de Rep. Venet. lib. 3.Brawlings at the barre are diſproportioned inſtrumēts of peace▪ 
                  Nam qui maledict is indulget, potius inimici, &amp; pravi hominis officium facere, quàm Reipub: cauſam agere videtur. Contarenus of Venice juſtifies, that malignant words from an impotent, and paſſionate Advocate, are a pregnant witneſſe that hee forgets his office, which is by manifeſtation of Truth to advance Peace, not by contentious tearmes to kindle ſtrife. The Second requiſite is to ſpeake Syncerely, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   (ſo did the Athenian Baristers) neither decking a bad cauſe with Rhetoricall flowres, nor procuring a perverſe, and vniuſt pittie to the oppreſſour, by patheticall, or paſſionat expreſſion. For the iuſtification of the wicked as much as the condemnation of the Iuſt, is an abomination to the Lord, Prou. 17. 15. Againe to ſpeak ſyncerely, is to ſpeake Down night; without either vaile of Hypocriſie, or ſquint eye of prevarication: which we doubt not but too many glance, their faces turned towards their Clients, but their eyes bent backe vpon themſelues alone, whilſt they ſeemingly plead the Widowes cauſe, but without ſatiety gape at their owne Iucre, worſhipping their God, as the Epheſians did Diana, Act. 19. 24. Then beſt when they ſee him in a: ſilver
                  
                  ſhrine, and then are they eaſily ſeduced to miſtake the Divell for God, when hee transformes himſelfe into the ſhape of an Angell, 2. Cor. 11. 14. Theſe be thoſe Iuris Coctiores, inſteed of doctiores, (ſo the Comedian Plautus in Paenulo. Act. 3. Scaen. 2.facetiouſly miſtakes) qui lites lites creant—&amp; ſi nihil eſt litium, lites emunt: thoſe Non-proficients in the Lawe, who patch vp their trewantly inſufficiencies with diſhoneſt quirkes, and progging ſubtilties: boyling, as it were, their own inventions to maturity of cunning, &amp; mixing potions of fraud. Baratry, to protract old, or forge new queſtions and ſuits among contentious neighbours. Potions they are, like thoſe of Circes, metamorphoſing Homer. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .Men to Beaſts. And Pottage if they bee (for ſo the Poet by Iuris coctiores, meanes) ſure I am, they are as deare as Iacobs: and he that ſups them hath the better fortune, if he buy them not at as deare a rate as did Eſau his meſſe, at the price of his Birth-right. But let them that vſe this art of confection bee circumſpect: For this is that ſubtilty which is fine, but vnrighteous: and theſe are they that wreſt the open, and manifeſt Law, Ecclus. 19. 24. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : Philem. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .The Heathen ſaith as much: Fraudulent Pleaders are the diſgrace of their worthy profeſſion: and are indeed no Lawyers, but their enemies; wreſting by the ſecret violence of their too fine ſubtilty, that Law, which They defend and keepe inviolate▪ yea, &amp; therefore, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c. Woe be vnto you Lawyers (I meane thoſe who are ſuch▪ 
                  for yee lade men with burthens grievous to be borne, and you your ſelues touch not the burthens with one of your fingers. S. Luk. 11. 46. Dixit. The Orator, Defendant, or Advocate hath done. The Iuries verdict, &amp; the Iudges Sentence are the next. They are but ſhort: ſo ſhall be their Diſcourſe.
            
            
               
               
                  Pars. 3. Iuratores. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : Doe Iuſtice.
               The Iury haue their name, and denomination from their Oath: and therefore as often as they are called by that name, ſo often are they put in minde of that bond betweene God, and their owneſoules, being Viri iurati, ſworne men. The weight &amp; obligation of that oath, with the fearefull puniſhments inflicted on Blaſpheamous wretches, for this guilt of periurie to the preiudice of the innocent, I could willingly to my power expreſſe, did not the time prevent. Something I haue ſaid thereof in the witneſſes diſcourſe; all which if you remember not, yet keepe in minde (I beſeech you) this one menace of the Prophet; I will come neere to you in iudgement, &amp; will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt your Soothſayers, and adulterers, and againſt falſe ſwearers, and against thoſe that wrongfully keepe back the hirelings wages, and vex the widowe and the fatherleſſe, and oppreſſe the ſtranger, and feare not me, ſaith Dominus exercituum, The Lord of hoasts, Malach. 3. 5. Remember this denunciation of Gods iudgement againſt your ſelues, if you faile in your dutie herein, and feare: For it is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God, 
                  Ex Varrone Hotoman. in com. in orat. Cic. pro Q. Roſcio.Heb. 10. 31. But from this Denunciation, I paſſe vnto the laſt and greateſt part of this Aſſiſe; The Iudge: who, as the Iurie receaue their names from their Oath by which they are bound, takes his alſo from the Law by which himſelfe is guided. Iudex the Iudge; a cōpound of two languages, Ius, &amp; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   (as my Author, none of the meaneſt Criticks, will diduce it) intimates a neceſſary reſpect from the Iudge, vnto the Law, which he receaues from a ſuperiour Magiſtrate, as his rule and Iudge Hutton at Okeham Aſſiſes.ſquare: on which I haue heretofore, before one of theſe Right Honourable Iudges, in another place vpon

the like occaſion, more largely diſcourſed. When alſo ſome precepts, Ex officio, I rehearſed, deriued from the book of God, cōcerning the Iudges office, notwithſtanding I did not doubt that his, as now both your wiſdomes, might prevent the neceſſitie of my inſtruction. Yet giue me leaue, Right Honorable, this once againe to caſt my Mite into your Treaſury, remembring too that it is the Widowes Mite; whoſe petition this day I doubt not but you will reſpect: that as you imploy your fiue talents to a greater increaſe, I alſo may in ſome ſort too husband the but two committed to my charge, to both yours, and my great Maſters glory. I remember I haue read that Themiſtocles compares the Magiſtrates office, to a skilfull Muſitians art: who muſt in his ſong, be ruled by his meaſure: I remember his application too, but willingly omit it, becauſe I had rather approue and follow the Prophets, then his; who being a Magiſtrate as well as he, calls it a ſong too, and that compoſed of two ſweet ayres; Mercy, and Iudgement, I will ſing mercy and iudgement, Pſalm. 101. 1. And every Iudge that will be Davids like, muſt caroll the ſame tune, if ever he meane to be a ſweet ſinger in Iſrael. Now in the ſong of Iudgement, two Straines are of a tranſcendent Harmony, Equality, and Purity. The one excludes acceptation of Perſons, the other of Rewards. Againſt violation of the firſt, God himſelfe giues an expreſſe command: Thou ſhalt not favour the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty, but thou ſhalt iudge thy neighbour iuſtly, Levit. 19. 15. And againſt tranſgreſſion of the ſecond, even morall heatheniſh politie hath in all ages been eſpecially provident. Witneſſe the Magiſtrates oath at Athens adminiſtred to him for more caution, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , once every

                  Xenoph. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , bib. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Guil. Poſtell. de Magiſt. Athen. c. 14. month: And againe their 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Magiſtrates of accoūt for the adminiſtration of Iuſtice at the Seſſion of each Iudge in the period of his deputed time the publike Crier openly proclaiming, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , If any man could accuſe him of iniuſtice in the time of his commiſſion, Aeſchines in orat. contra Demoſt. &amp; Cleſiphont.he ſhould be freely heard. And in the Commonwealth of Iſrael, Samuel (in whoſe ever bleſſed &amp; memorable integrity may all our Samuels, Iudges, and Magiſtrates depart) provokes the people to the triall of himſelfe. Behold here I am, beare record of me before the Lord, and before his Anointed: whoſe Oxe haue I taken? or whoſe Aſſe haue I taken? or whom haue I done wrong vnto? or whom haue I hurt? or of whoſe hands haue I receaued any bribes, to blind mine eyes with? and I will reſtore it you. 1. Samuel. 12. 3. And the people as freely acquit him by a generall voice▪ 
                  Thou hast done vs no wrong, nor hurt vs, neither haſt thou taken ought of any mans hand, verſ. 4. As for the ſong of Mercy; God forbid our Lawes, our Chriſtian Lawes ſhould be of Dracoes Crimſen die: Non atramento ſcriptae, ſed humano ſanguine as not written with Inke, but mans blood. For two things to all, both wiſe, and good men, Aquin. in Boet. de conſol. Philoſ. proſ. 4.are eſpeciall Motiues to compaſſion and lenity; Metus ignorantiae in Iudicio, &amp; incertus eventus humanae fortunae. Feare, leaſt they ſhould erre in iudgement, and ſo though vnwittingly, ſtaine their ſoules with the blood of the innocent:: and Doubt ariſing from the vncertainty of all humane frailty; to day glittering on the Pinacle of honour, and to morrow ſinking in the gulfe of wretchedneſſe. For then muſt you onely expect what your ſelues vpon others in your proſperity beſtow: Bleſſed therefore are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercy, S. Matth. 5. 7. Come then, O come yee

Iudges of the earth, come before the preſence of the Lord with a ſong, with a ſong of Mercy &amp; Iudgement: With a ſong of Pitty, &amp; Equality, mixing the Widows threnes, her mournful dities, with your ſweeter notes, &amp; tuning &amp; reducing to melodie, her harſh laments, by your harmonious skill in Doing her iuſtice againſt her enemie. Which if without Hypocriſie or Prevarication you performe, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ſhall not God? ſhall not the Iudge of all the World doe right? Gen. 18. 25. Yea, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , much more will God reſpect your cauſe, when in that dreadfull Aſſiſe, at the laſt iudgement, both your, and all our ſoules, all naked, ſhall bee ſummoned to appeare, and ſtand before his Tribunall, at the barre of his Iuſtice, as poore guilty Defendants, trembling and ſhiuering, guarded by thouſands, &amp; ten thouſands Angels: Satan our Adverſary accuſing: our tranſgreſſions witneſſing: our conſciences convincing: and God himſelfe an angry Iudge, without the Mediation of our but one only Advocate Chriſt Ieſus, irrepealably condemning. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ! O God, how fearefull would that iudgement be, did not that Advocate aſſiſt vs moſt vnthankfull Clients, ſatisfying for our tranſgreſſions, &amp; interceding for vs to that Iudges Mercy? To Thee therefore O powerfull Advocate wee call: To Thee, O bleſſed Mediatour we direct our crie; not in the Widowes petition, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Doe vs iuſtice, for then our portion ſhould be in the fiery Lake: but in the guilties ſupplication, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Doe vs mercy O Lord, Be mercifull vnto vs against our adverſary: and in the Houre of death, and in that day of Iudgement, By the myſtery of thy holy Incarnation, by thy holy Nativity, and Circumciſion, by the Baptiſme, Faſting, and Temptation, by their Agonie

bloody ſweat, by thy Croſſe and Paſſion, by thy precious Death, and Buriall, by thy glorious Reſurrection, and Aſcention, &amp; by the comming of the holy Ghoſt.
               
                  Good Lord deliver vs.
               
               That ſo in the company of thy Saints Elect, wee may ſing a new ſong, a ſong of Mercy, and a ſong of Iudgement; a ſong of Thankſgiuing, and a ſong of Praiſe, Hoſannaes &amp; Haliluiahs to thee O bleſſed Lord God, with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, in the fulneſſe of Ioy for ever more. AMEN.
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  .
               AMEN.
               
            
         
      
   

