
   
      
         
            [Diuers &amp; sundry waies of two parts in one, to the number of fortie, vppon one playnsong]
            Farmer, John, fl. 1591-1601.
         
         
            
               1591
            
         
         Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00563
            STC 10698
            ESTC S111790
            99847060
            99847060
            12067
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00563)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12067)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:10)
         
         
            
               
                  [Diuers &amp; sundry waies of two parts in one, to the number of fortie, vppon one playnsong]
                  Farmer, John, fl. 1591-1601.
               
               [48+] p. : music  
               
                  T. Este, the assigne of W. Byrd, sould at the authors house,
                  [London :
                  1591]
               
               
                  Title and imprint from STC.
                  Signatures: A⁴ B-C D⁴.
                  Imperfect; lacks title page and all after D4.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Part-songs, English --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-08
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2005-08
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            To the right honorable my very good
lord &amp; maſter Edward de Vere Earle of Oxenford,
vicount Bulbecke, lord of Eſcales &amp; Badleſmere,
&amp; Lord great Chamberlayne of England.
Iohn Farmer wiſheth long and happie life with
encreaſe of honor.
            
               IT was mine exerciſe, right
honorable and my ſinguler
good Lord, to make
vppon a playnſong not
long a goe fortie ſeuerall
waies of 2. parts in one,
with what cōmendation,
I ſhall then perceiue, when other ſhall haue
iudged, with what ſtudy, my ſelfe am priuie:
neither long, nor ſerious. This poore conceit I
haue preſumed of your honorable fauour to
preſent vnto your Lordſhip: vnder couerture
of whome, to the view of the world: not but
that I knew it, vnworthie of ſo high a perſonage,
but rather that it needed the more noble
patronage, the leſſe is in it to recōmend it ſelfe,
which how litle it is, I am greatly in feare Hervnto,
my good Lord, I was the rather emboldened
for your L. great affection to this noble

                  ••
               ience, hoping for the one you might pardō
               
                  〈◊〉
                other, &amp; deſirous to make knowē your inclination
this way. For howſoeuer my ſkill be

nothing ſuch, as in leaſt part to expreſſe the
dignitie of the art, yet this I am ſure of, if graue
auctors haue rightly informed mee, that the
wiſest men as Pythagoras &amp; Plato, haue made
it their ſtudie, and moſt honorable perſons as
Hercules and Achilles, their earneſt practiſe.
Beſides this, my good Lord, I beare this conceit,
that not onelie my ſelf am vowed to your
commaundement, but all that is in me is dedicated
to your Lordſhips ſeruice: ſo that, albeit
I am vnable to make ſhew of my deuty in ſuch
ſort, as I wiſh: yet to tranſport to other, what I
owe to your Lordſhip I demeed not to ſitte
with ſuch a profeſſion. Onelie if it ſhall pleaſe
your honorable minde to meaſure my deede
by my deſire, it may happily ſeeme ſomewhat,
which of it ſelfe is leſſe then nothing. Which
beſeeching your Lordſhip with all inſtancie,
and as before hoping, ſo now moſt humbly
crauing pardon of my preſumption, I reſt in
prayer for the preſeruation of your honour in
long life, and great happyneſſe, in the one to
match the oldeſt, in the other the bleſſeddeſt.
            
               Your Lordſhips moſt bounden
ſeruaunt, and at all commaundement
moſt ready.
Iohn Farmer.
            
         
         
            
            
               Philomuſicis.
            
            
               MAruaile not gentlemen, who
ſoeuer ſhal ſee this little book,
that Muſicke ſhewes hir ſelfe
in this vnuſuall vayne. For if
in other arts it be a common
practiſe (and yet not ſo ordinarie
as commendable) euerie
way to deuiſe to further the
ſtudie of each perticuler, why
ſhould Muſicke be denied that, which is graunted
the reſt? Certes how men do thinke of hir, I do not
know (I doubt but baſſely) how they ſhould I am
out of doubt, that is moſt honourablie. No man can
denie, but that God is authour, as of all other excellent
qualities, ſo of this (for ſo euen the Philoſophers,
who had not right knowledge of the heauenlie
maieſtie, by inſtinct of nature did ſee and confeſſe)
and as of the 7. liberall ſciences, which therefore haue
that name, becauſe they are befitting men of moſt
free birth, ſhe is one in number, ſo peraduenture,
nay, without peraduenture not the laſt, if not the
firſt, in dignitie: for delight wonderfull, for depth
infinite, for commoditie it may happilie be doubted,
whether any more neceſſarie. Were it not ſo, it
had not beene to write, which Tullie writes truelie
of the countrie of Graecia, where being the
fountaine of all learning, and the verie ſeate of wisdome,
ſic Muſici floruerunt, as he ſaith, vt omnes id
diſcerent, nec, qui neſciebat, ſatis excultus doctrina putaretur.
In the ſame countrie Themiſtocles a Prince of

               Athens, for that at a feaſt he refuſed to play on the
Harpe, an inſtrument at that time of higheſt credit,
although in other reſpects in a maner peereleſſe, onely
for this defect, was thought ſomewhat rude. The
ende of my ſpeech and purpoſe is this, that the ſcience
being ſo excellent, and yet ſo couldlie followed,
euerie one that knowes any thing of her, ſhould euerie
waie be doing for her aduauncement, and ſuch
as are not, are greatly in her debt, ſuch as are, are
fauorably to be accepted, howſoeuer it be not each
mans fate to performe what is ſinguler. I profeſſe (if
any leſſe wiſe, then I could wiſh them, miſconstrue
my meaning) to doe nothing of oſtentacion (for alas
what is this, nay what haue I in me, whereof iuſtlie
to boſt?) I was in hope that ſtudents in this art, ſuch
as may learne, as my ſelfe may, and haue not yet proceeded
ſo farre as I haue, might finde ſomthing heere
not vnworthie their labor. If it ſo fall out, I ſhall be
glad, if otherwiſe, it was the error of myne opinion,
which I deſire may be pardoned to my good will, ſo
ſhall I endeuour my ſelfe to continue my poore labours,
without repentance for this I haue done. Fare
yee well.
            
               Iohn Farmer.
            
         
         
            
            
               1
               WHo ſo delights in Muſickes ſkill
               and thereof iudges right,
               May here perceiue a ſtraunge deuiſe
               moſt plainly in his ſight.
            
            
               2
               Two parts in one vppon a ground
               in number fortie wayes,
               A thing moſt rare ſurpaſsing farre
               moſt ſongſters now a dayes.
            
            
               3
               If this in youth performed be
               as plainly you may ſee,
               What fruite hereafter may wee hope
               to haue of ſuch a tree.
            
            
               4
               As farmer good or buſye bee
               ſtill laboreth in the field
               So doth this Farmer that he may
               to others much fruite yeeld.
            
            
               5
               Farewell with praiſe and good report
               of thoſe that know thy ſkill
               What thou deſernest in Muſicks art
               this booke will witnes ſtill.
            
            
               Richard Wilkinſon.
            
         
         
            
            
               1
               VVHether in Muſickes prayſe to wright
               In generall, or of the ſkill,
               That did conduct this auctors quill:
               I feare I pearch aboue my might.
            
            
               2
               Since then I can not, as I would,
               I ſpare to do it as I can,
               Leaſt I do wrong both art and man,
               Not giuing either, as I ſhould:
            
            
               3
               The rather, cauſe it's to well knowen,
               What Muſicke is without my pen,
               And he, among the ſkilfull men,
               Wanting my praiſe, will worke his owne.
            
            
               4
               Onely, for that I loue not ill
               The arte it ſelfe, and arts man both,
               To lend my hand I was not loath
               Both waies to witneſſe my good will.
            
            
               Francis Yomans.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            I
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the fourth, a ſembriefe after the other:
the plainſong beneath.
         
         
            
            II
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the fifth, a minom after the other, The plainsong
in the midſt, the Treble before.
         
         
            
            III
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the fifth, a ſembriefe after the other, the
plainſong beneath.
         
         
            
            IIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the fifth, the Baſſe before, the Treble follow
a minome. The plainſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            V
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, the Baſſe before; the Treble follow
a ſembreefe the painſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            VI
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, the Treble before, the Baſſe
low a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            VII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the eight the Treble before? the Baſſe follow
a minom, the painſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            VIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the eight, the Baſſe before, the Treble follow
a minem, the plainſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            IX
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ninth, the Baſſe before, the Treble follow
a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the midſt
         
         
            
            X
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ninth, the Meane before, the Baſſe follow
a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            XI
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ſeuenth, the Baſſe before, the Mean
follow a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            XII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ſeuenth, the Treble before, the Baſſe
follow a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            XIII
            The plainſong, 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, Tripla to the minom, beginning
both to gether, the Baſe being the proporcion: the Meane ſinging
all minomes, the verie ſame, the plainſong in the midſt,
likewiſe minome time: this is a very pleaſant way.
         
         
            
            XIIII
            The plainſong, 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ninth, a ſembreefe after the other,
the plainſong beneath.
         
         
            
            XV
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ſeuenth, a ſembreefe after the other,
the plainſong beneath.
         
         
            
            XVI
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fourth, a minom after the other,
plainſong beneath.
         
         
            
            XVII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, a minom after the other, the
plainſong beneath.
         
         
            
            XVIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the eight, the Treble before, the Baſſe
low a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the midſt.
         
         
            
            XIX
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            
               2. parts in one. 
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               2 parts in one. 
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               2 parts in one, Counterpoint in the fifth, the plainſong beneath
minom time.
            
            
               2. parts in one. 
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               2 parts in one. 
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               2. parts in one, Counterpoint, in the fifth, the plainſong
in the midſt, likewiſe minom time.
            
         
         
            
            XX
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the tenth, the plainſong in the midſt
ſembreefe following after the other.
         
         
            
            XXI
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ſixt, a ſembreefe after the other, the plainſong
beneath beginning at the end, &amp; ſo forward ſembreefe time.
         
         
            
            XXII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, the Baſſe before, the Tenor follow a ſembreefe after, the plainſong in the higheſt.
         
         
            
            XXIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fourth, the Baſſe before, the Tenor follow a
ſembreefe after, the plainſong in the higheſt.
         
         
            
            XXIIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, the Tenor before, the Baſſe follow
a ſembreefe after, the plainſong in the higheſt.
         
         
            
            XXV
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fourth, the Tenor before, the Baſſe follow
a ſembreefe after, the plainſong in the higheſt.
         
         
            
            XXVI
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the eight, the Tenor before, the Baſſe follow
a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the higheſt.
         
         
            
            XXVII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the eight, the Baſſe before, the Tenor follow
a ſembreefe after, the plainſong the higheſt.
         
         
            
            XXVIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ſeuenth, the Tenor before, the Meane
follow a ſembreefe, the plainſong in the hieſt, ſing the plainsong
8. notes hier then it ſtands, if the voice will ſerue.
         
         
            
            XXIX
            The plainſong, 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ſeuenth, the Meane before, the Tenor
follow a ſembreefe, the plainſong the hieſt, ſing the plainſong
8. notes hier then it ſtands.
         
         
            
            XXX
            The plainſong, 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the eight, the Baſſe before, the Tenor follow
a minom, the plainſong the higheſt, ſing the plainſong
eight notes hier then it ſtandes.
         
         
            
            XXI
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the ſixth, a ſembreefe after the other, the
plainſong the higheſt, ſing the plainſong as it ſtandes
         
         
            
            XXXII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the tenth, a ſembreefe after the other, the
plainſong the hieſt, ſing the plainſong 8. notes hier then it
ſtandes, the Baſſe before, the Treble doth follow.
         
         
            
            XXXIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the ſixth, the Meane before, the Baſſe fol
               
                  ••
               w
a ſembreefe, the plainſong the higheſt.
         
         
            
            XXXIIII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one in the tenth, the meane before, the Baſſe follow
a ſembreefe, ſing the plainſong as it ſtandes; this is a verie
difficult way to make.
         
         
            
            XXXV
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the eight, if you would know how this can
be, turne the booke vpſide dounward and looke on the Baſſe,
there ſhall you perceiue it, but ſing it as it is prickt downe
before you, ſing the plainſong as it ſtandes.
         
         
            
            XXXVI
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2. parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, if you would know how to ſing this,
you muſt turne the plainſong vpſide downeward, &amp; then ſing
forward to the ende, the other 2 beginning both to gether,
the one deuiding deſcant wiſe, the other ſinging the verie
ſame all ſembreefes like the plainſong.
         
         
            
            XXXVII
            The plainſong. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one in the fifth, if you would know how to ſing
this, you muſt turne the plainſong vpſide downward, and begin
backward and ſo to the ende, &amp; ſing it with a b. Cliffe
eight notes lower then it ſtandes, the other 2 as they be
prickt, then ſhall you gree, though ſomewhat hard, becauſe
of hardneſſe.
         
         
            
            XXXVIII
            The plainſong, 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            2 parts in one. 
                  〈♫〉
               
            
            This 2 parts in one is backward and forward, the one part to
begin at the beginning and ſo to the ende, and the other
part to begin at the ende, and ſo forward to the beginning,
the plainſong likewiſe, is to be ſung forward and backward,
the firſt note a ſembreefe the next a minom, and ſo forward
in order to the ende, and then begin at the ende, ſinging one
note a minom the other a ſembreefe, and ſo backward in
order to the beginning.
            
         
      
   

