
   
      
         
            Canzonets to fowre voyces, with a song of eight parts. Compiled by Giles Farnaby Bachilar of Musicke.
            Farnaby, Giles, ca. 1565-1640.
         
         
            
               1598
            
         
         Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00566
            STC 10700
            ESTC S122324
            99857476
            99857476
            23219
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00566)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23219)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 379:4)
         
         
            
               
                  Canzonets to fowre voyces, with a song of eight parts. Compiled by Giles Farnaby Bachilar of Musicke.
                  Farnaby, Giles, ca. 1565-1640.
               
               [112] p. : music  
               
                  Printed by Peter Short dwelling on Bredstreet hil at the signe of the Star,
                  London :
                  M.D.XCVIII. [1598]
               
               
                  Four partbooks, each with separate dated title page and register. At head of title, part 1, "Cantus."; part 2, "Altus."; part 3, "Tenor"; part 4, "Bassus.".
                  Signatures: A²  B-D⁴; A²  B-D⁴; A²  B-D⁴; A²  B-D⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  Cantus and Bassus only.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Part-songs, English --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-03
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2003-03
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  
                     
                        CANTVS.
                        CANZONETS
TO FOWRE VOYCES,
With a Song of eight parts.
                        
                           COMPILED BY
GILES FARNABY
Bachilar of Musicke.
                        LONDON.
Printed by Peter Short
dwelling on Bredstreet hil
at the signe of the Star.
M.D.XCVIII.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                  TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL
MAISTER FERDINANDO
HEABVRN, GROOME OF HER
MAIESTIES PRIVIE
CHAMBER.
                  
                     PIthy &amp; pleasaunt was that inuētion of our
auncient English poet Ieffray Chaucer, in his
booke intituled (the parliament of Birdes)
wherein hee describeth the straunge and
sweete harmonie amonge the fowles of all
kindes, no one refusing to vtter such melodie
as nature in her course affoorded. The consideration
whereof (right worshipfull) enboldneth
me to shew my simple skill in these poore
Canzonets. Although many excellent and
famous musicions haue sette foorth in Impression many and excellent
workes, yet as the sillie sparrow presumeth to chirpe in presence of the
melodious nightingall, so bluntly and boldly as a poore member among
the musicall sort, I make bold to intrude these sillie works as the first
fruits of my labor, crauing your gentle acceptaunce, whome I chose
for their patrone, both for your worthines &amp; excellency in iudgemēt,
your manifold courtesies and louing kindnes, at all times, which binde
me in dutie to loue you: To shewe the effects thereof, I know no waie
but this simple meane proceeding (ex abundantia Cordis) And to
auoide tediousnes, wishing you all peace of mind, worldly prosperitie &amp;
euerlasting felicitie: I take my leaue.
                  
                     Yours in all dutie,
GYLES FARNABY.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Anto: Holbornus ad autorem.
                  CAepisti benè, perge modos componere gratos,
                  Et quantum poteris numen in arte doce.
                  Caelestes videor (nisi maxime fallor amore)
                  Exaudire tuis in numeris modulos.
                  Mille aures Dea fama tibi iam surrigit, ora
                  Tot quo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      diuinum carmen ad astra ferant.
               
               
                  M. Io. Dowland to the Author.
                  THOV ONLY SHALT HAVE PHYLLIS,
                  Only thou fit (without all further gloses)
                  Crouned to be with euerlasting Roses,
                  With Roses and with Lillies,
                  And with Daffadoundillies,
                  But thy songs sweeter are (saue in their closes)
                  Then are Lillies or Roses:
                  Like his that taught the woods sound Amaryllis.
                  GOLDINGS; you that haue too too dainty NOSES,
                  Auaunt, go feede you themels where on ROSES.
               
               
                  M. R. Alison in praise of the Author.
                  AS Treasure hidde within the golden Myne,
                  Such is the state of Musiques art vnknowne,
                  The ore digde forth the workeman maks it fine,
                  Till which performde the vertue is not showne:
                  So Farnaby had left this worke obscured,
                  And drownd deserte of praise belonging to him,
                  Had he not bin by speciall friends procured,
                  With tycing speech and filed phraise to wooe him;
                  These works had quaild and he from vse had swaru'd,
                  But well performde and therefore well deseru'd.
               
               
                  M. Hu. Holland to the Author
                  I Would both sing thy praise, and praise thy singing:
                  That in the winter nowe are both aspringing.
                  But my Muse must be stronger,
                  And the daies must be longer,
                  When the sunne's in his hight with ye bright Barnaby,
                  Then should we sing thy praises gentle Farnaby
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  4. voices. I. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     MY Ladies collor'd cheeks, weare like

                        〈♫〉
                     
the damaske ro-ses, which clad in damaske mantles

                        〈♫〉
                     
spred the ar-bors: but thrise more pleasant weare her

                        〈♫〉
                     
sweet supposes, thise more pleasant were her sweet supposes, but

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. suppo-ses, proceeding from her lips,

                        〈♫〉
                     
where sweet loue harbors, whereij. for vewing those, for

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. her cheeks &amp; roses sprowting, for vewing those her cheeks

                        〈♫〉
                     
and roses sprowting, the iudgmēt of ye sweetest breeds a doubting.
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. II. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     CAarters, now cast down your whips, Carters,

                        〈♫〉
                     
now cast down your whips, your whips,

                        〈♫〉
                     
and shepheards put off your scrips, &amp; ij. whilst that

                        〈♫〉
                     
your sheep are grazing, behold faire stars blazing, behold, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
faire stars blazing, Ambrosia talking with Amarillis, and Coridon
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
walking with faire Phillis, and, ij. Coridon, Coridon
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
walking with faire Phillis, to set your eyes, your eyes agazing:

                        〈♫〉
                     
and Coridon.
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. 
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        PHili-da bewaild the want of Coridon, and

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Herpulus of Philida complained, for Corine
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
often would she sigh and grone, for Corine often would she sigh

                        〈♫〉
                     
but Herpulus that lou'd her she disdained, poore Herpulus, why

                        〈♫〉
                     
should not rigor moue, not rigor moue thee, to hate her thrice, to

                        〈♫〉
                     
to hate her thrice, that once disdaind to loue thee. poore.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        DAphne on the rainebow,

                        〈♫〉
                     
ri-ding, on the rainebow riding, when all the gods

                        〈♫〉
                     
weare chiding, were chiding, ij. when all the gods were chiding, were

                        〈♫〉
                     
chiding, fell soden-ly amazed, full gastly then she gazed and

                        〈♫〉
                     
presently the god of ang- er frownd, and in his fury down he flang her,

                        〈♫〉
                     
down he flang her, and in his fu-ry down he flang her, in ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
her down he flang her. and
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. V. CANTVS
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     BLind loue was shooting, &amp; losing of his arrow,

                        〈♫〉
                     
he kild his mothers sparrow, he ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
and tracing forth his footing, his mother Venus spide it, before

                        〈♫〉
                     
the boy could hide it. and

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4.Voices. VI. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        PEarce did loue faire Petronel, because she sang &amp;

                        〈♫〉
                     
danced well, and danced well, and gallantly could

                        〈♫〉
                     
pranckit &amp; ij. he puld her and, he puld her and he

                        〈♫〉
                     
hauld her, and oftentimes he cald her, and often times he cald her, primrose

                        〈♫〉
                     
pearles, primrose peatles prickt in a blanket.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. VII. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        PEarce did daunce with Petronella, Lasiamizan and

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Laduncella, pretty Almans that weare new,

                        〈♫〉
                     
such he daunst and nothing true, but when Parnel daunst without

                        〈♫〉
                     
him, without him, all the maids began to floute him, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
all the maids began to floute him.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. VIII. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     THe wauering planet, ij. the wauering

                        〈♫〉
                     
planet, the wauering planet most vnstable, goddes

                        〈♫〉
                     
of the waters flowing, of the waters flowing, that beares a sway in each

                        〈♫〉
                     
thing growing, &amp; makes my La-dy variable, oft I seeke to vnder-mind

                        〈♫〉
                     
her, oft I seeke to vnder-mind her, oft I seeke to

                        〈♫〉
                     
vnder-mind her yet I know not where not where, yet I

                        〈♫〉
                     
know not where, yet I know not where to find her.
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. IX. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LAdy, the silly flea of all disdained, because

                        〈♫〉
                     
it hath com
                        ••••
                     ed: I pitty, I pitty that

                        〈♫〉
                     
poore creature, I pitty, I pitty, I pitty ye poore creature, both black &amp;

                        〈♫〉
                     
small of stature, were I a flea, ij in bed, in bed, I would

                        〈♫〉
                     
not bite you, ij. I would not

                        〈♫〉
                     
bite you, not bite you, but search some other, some other way for to

                        〈♫〉
                     
delight you▪ were I a flea

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices X. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     THrice blessed be the giuer, be the giuer, thrice ij

                        〈♫〉
                     
be the giuer, that gaue sweet loue that

                        〈♫〉
                     
golden quiuer, and liue he long, and liue he long among the gods anointed,

                        〈♫〉
                     
that made the arrow heads, that made the arrow heads

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. sharpe pointed, if either of them both had quailed,

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. had qua-led, qualed, she of my loue,

                        〈♫〉
                     
she of my loue, ij. of my loue, and I of hers, and I of

                        〈♫〉
                     
hers, of hers, had failed. if either
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. XI. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     THe curtaine drawn I saw my loue, I saw my

                        〈♫〉
                     
loue lie sleeping, thrice happy was that pee-ping,

                        〈♫〉
                     
thrice happy was that pee-ping, for vewing her sweet lying

                        〈♫〉
                     
her sweet, her sweet lying, preserues my life and keeps my soule

                        〈♫〉
                     
from dying, and keeps my soule from dying, of thousand ioyes missing

                        〈♫〉
                     
her I had mist all, whose sight reuiues me more, reuiues me more,

                        〈♫〉
                     
whose ij. whose sight reuiues me more, reuiues me more

                        〈♫〉
                     
then ruby, pearle, then ruby, pearle, or cristall.
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices XII. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     SVsanna faire somtime of loue requested,

                        〈♫〉
                     
Susanna faire somtime of loue requested,

                        〈♫〉
                     
by two old men whom her sweet looks al-lur'd, was in her

                        〈♫〉
                     
hartfull sad and sore molested, ij. ful sad and sore mole-sted,

                        〈♫〉
                     
seeing the force her chastity en-dur'd, to them

                        〈♫〉
                     
she said, if I by craft procur'd, do yeeld to you my body to abuse it,

                        〈♫〉
                     
I loose my soule, ij. and if I shall refuse it, you will me

                        〈♫〉
                     
iudge to death reprochful-ly, but better it is in innocent to

                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
chuse it, then by my fault t'offend my God on hye, then by my

                        〈♫〉
                     
fault, ij. t'offend my God on hie.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. XIII. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LOue shooting, loue shooting among many,

                        〈♫〉
                     
by chance he hit not any, ij. because

                        〈♫〉
                     
the shaft, the shaft, rebounded, and loue himselfe was wounded

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. and loue himselfe was wounded, loue himselfe was

                        〈♫〉
                     
wounded, when Siches saw the dart had mist her, when Siches saw the

                        〈♫〉
                     
dart had mist, had mist, had mist her, when ij she

                        〈♫〉
                     
smild and said that all the gods had blest her, said that all the gods had

                        〈♫〉
                     
blest, had blest her. when Siches
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. second part. XIIII. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LOue shooting at another, shooting at another,

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. loue, loue shooting at another,

                        〈♫〉
                     
a-nother, he mist that marke, and chanst to hit, and chanst to hit his

                        〈♫〉
                     
mother, but as the Lady fainted, god Mars did start, ij. did

                        〈♫〉
                     
start, and there with was, and there with was, and ij. attainted

                        〈♫〉
                     
when Vulcan saw the shoot, when Vulcan saw, when Vulcan saw, the

                        〈♫〉
                     
shoot did freat him, he curst the boy, he curst the boy, and sweare that

                        〈♫〉
                     
he would beat him,
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. XV. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     AY me poore hart, since loue hath plaied

                        〈♫〉
                     
his part, my sences all are lost, my

                        〈♫〉
                     
mind eke tost, like waues that swell, sweet god of loue, of loue

                        〈♫〉
                     
thou dost excell, thy passions moue, my mind to proue, that turtle

                        〈♫〉
                     
doue, she flies, my loue she tries, helpe gods that sit on hie

                        〈♫〉
                     
Oh send me remedy, oh send me remedy.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. XVI. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     SOmtime she would and somtime not, &amp; somtime

                        〈♫〉
                     
not, the more request, the more disdained, the ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
each woman hath her gift god wot and,

                        〈♫〉
                     
euer had since Venus raignd, ij. and

                        〈♫〉
                     
euer had since Venus raignd, and euer had since Ve-nus raignd, though

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Vulcan, though Vulcan, ij. ij. though Vulcan, ij. did to

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Ve-nus yeeld, ij. I would haue men to winne ye field

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices XVII. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Among the Daffadillies, and faire white splendant

                        〈♫〉
                     
Lillies, the God of loue, the god of loue came

                        〈♫〉
                     
creeping, where Dians nimphs lay sleeping, lay sleeping, he bent his bow,

                        〈♫〉
                     
he bent his bow, but mist his sooting, mist his sooting, ii.

                        〈♫〉
                     
and loosing lost, both labor shaft and shoo-ting, he bent

                        〈♫〉
                     
his bow, ij. but mist his sooting, ij. he bent his bow, but mist

                        〈♫〉
                     
his foo-ting, and loosing lost both labor shaft and shoo-ting.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. XVIII. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        SImkin said that Sis was faire, and that he ment

                        〈♫〉
                     
to loue her, he set her on his ambling Maire, all

                        〈♫〉
                     
this he did to proue her, all this he did to proue her, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
all this he did to proue her, when they came home Sis floted cream

                        〈♫〉
                     
and pourd it through a strainer, pourd it through

                        〈♫〉
                     
a strainer, ij. ij. and pourd it through a strainer,

                        〈♫〉
                     
pourd it through a strainer, but sware that Simkin should haue none

                        〈♫〉
                     
because he did, he did dis-daine her.
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices XIX. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LAdy, when I behold your passi-ons, so diuers

                        〈♫〉
                     
and so oft constrai-ned, vpon such slight

                        〈♫〉
                     
or no occasi-ons, such slight or no occasi-ons

                        〈♫〉
                     
as though you were with griefe sore pained, ij as

                        〈♫〉
                     
though you were with griefe sore pained, I enter in-to these perswasi-ons,

                        〈♫〉
                     
A man might saile from Trent vnto Daun-by, and yet

                        〈♫〉
                     
not find so strange a peece as you be. A

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. XX. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     COnsture my meaning, wrest not my method, wrest

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. good wil craues fauor, witnes

                        〈♫〉
                     
the high God, the high God, if I haue ment well, haue ment well, if

                        〈♫〉
                     
I haue ment well, good will re-ward me, when I deserue ill, no

                        〈♫〉
                     
man regard, no man regard me, what shall I say more, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
speech is but blasting, still will I hope for life euerla-sting, for life

                        〈♫〉
                     
euerla-sting.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. eight parts. XXI. CANTVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     WItnesse yee heau'ns, I vow to loue the

                        〈♫〉
                     
fai-rest, to loue but how? for vertue

                        〈♫〉
                     
not for lust, for vertue why? because she is the rarest. Come

                        〈♫〉
                     
life, come death, in her I only trust, hap death, hap life, I force not

                        〈♫〉
                     
which betide, I force not which betide me, by her I liue from

                        〈♫〉
                     
death I cannot hide me, hap death, hap life, I force not which betide,

                        〈♫〉
                     
I force not which betide me, by her I liue, from death I cannot

                        〈♫〉
                     
hide me.
                  
                     
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     WItnes, ye heau'ns, I vow to loue the

                        〈♫〉
                     
fairest, ij. to

                        〈♫〉
                     
loue but how? to loue but how, ij. for vertue

                        〈♫〉
                     
not for lust, for vertue why? because she is the rarest, come life

                        〈♫〉
                     
come death, in her I only trust, hap death, hap life, I force not which

                        〈♫〉
                     
betide me, ij. by her I liue, frō death

                        〈♫〉
                     
I cannot hide me, hap life hap death, I force not which betide me

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. by her I liue, from death I cannot

                        〈♫〉
                     
hide me, hide me.
               
               
                  
                  A TABLE OF ALL THE
CANZONETS
contained in this
BOOKE.
                  
                     MY Ladyes collor'd cheeks. I
                     Carters now cast downe your whips. II
                     
                        Philida bewaild the want of Coridon. III
                     
                        Daphne on the rainebow. IIII
                     Blind loue was shooting. V
                     
                        Pearce did loue faire Petronel. VI
                     
                        Pearce did daunce with Petronel VII
                     The wauering planet. VIII
                     Lady, the sillie flea of all disdained. IX
                     Thrice blessed be the giuer. X
                     The curtaine drawne I saw my loue. XI
                     Susanna faire sometime. XII
                     Loue shooting among many. XIII
                     Loue shooting at an other. XIIII
                     Ay me poore hart. XV
                     Sometime she would and sometime not. XVI
                     Among the dafadillies. XVII
                     Simkin said that Sisse was faire. XVIII
                     Ladie when 'I behold your passions. XIX
                     Consture my meaning. XX
                     VVitnes ye heauens. XXI
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                     
                        BASSVS.
                        CANZONETS
TO FOWRE VOYCES,
With a Song of eight parts.
                        
                           COMPILED BY
GILES FARNABY
Bachilar of Musicke.
                        LONDON.
Printed by Peter Short
dwelling on Bredstreet hil
at the signe of the Star.
M.D.XCVIII.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                  TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL
MAISTER FERDINANDO
HEABVRN, GROOME OF HER
MAIESTIES PRIVIE
CHAMBER.
                  
                     PIthy &amp; pleasaunt was that inuētion of our
auncient English poet Ieffray Chaucer, in his
booke intituled (the parliament of Birdes)
wherein hee describeth the straunge and
sweete harmonie amonge the fowles of all
kindes, no one refusing to vtter such melodie
as nature in her course affoorded. The consideration
whereof (right worshipfull) enboldneth
me to shew my simple skill in these poore
Canzonets. Although many excellent and
famous musicions haue sette foorth in Impression many and excellent
workes, yet as the sillie sparrow presumeth to chirpe in presence of the
melodious nightingall, so bluntly and boldly as a poore member among
the musicall sort, I make bold to intrude these sillie works as the first
fruits of my labor, crauing your gentle acceptaunce, whome I chose
for their patrone, both for your worthines &amp; excellency in iudgemēt,
your manifold courtesies and louing kindnes, at all times, which binde
me in dutie to loue you: To shewe the effects thereof, I know no waie
but this simple meane proceeding (ex abundantia Cordis) And to
auoide tediousnes, wishing you all peace of mind, worldly prosperitie &amp;
euerlasting felicitie: I take my leaue.
                  
                     Yours in all dutie,
GYLES FARNABY.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Anto: Holbornus ad autorem.
                  CAepisti benè, perge modos componere gratos,
                  Et quantum poteris numen in arte doce.
                  Caelestes videor (nisi maxime fallor amore)
                  Exaudire tuis in numeris modulos.
                  Mille aures Dea fama tibi iam surrigit, ora
                  Tot quo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      diuinum carmen ad astra ferant.
               
               
                  M. Io. Dowland to the Author.
                  THOV ONLY SHALT HAVE PHYLLIS,
                  Only thou fit (without all further gloses)
                  Crouned to be with euerlasting Roses,
                  With Roses and with Lillies,
                  And with Daffadoundillies,
                  But thy songs sweeter are (saue in their closes)
                  Then are Lillies or Roses:
                  Like his that taught the woods sound Amaryllis.
                  GOLDINGS; you that haue too too dainty NOSES,
                  Auaunt, go feede you themels where on ROSES.
               
               
                  M. R. Alison in praise of the Author.
                  AS Treasure hidde within the golden Myne,
                  Such is the state of Musiques art vnknowne,
                  The ore digde forth the workeman maks it fine,
                  Till which performde the vertue is not showne:
                  So Farnaby had left this worke obscured,
                  And drownd deserte of praise belonging to him,
                  Had he not bin by speciall friends procured,
                  With tycing speech and filed phraise to wooe him;
                  These works had quaild and he from vse had swaru'd,
                  But well performde and therefore well deseru'd.
               
               
                  M. Hu. Holland to the Author
                  I Would both sing thy praise, and praise thy singing:
                  That in the winter nowe are both aspringing.
                  But my Muse must be stronger,
                  And the daies must be longer,
                  When the sunne's in his hight with ye bright Barnaby,
                  Then should we sing thy praises gentle Farnaby
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  4. voices. I. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     DAmaske roses, damaske ro-ses, which

                        〈♫〉
                     
clad in damaske mantles, spred the arbors, in

                        〈♫〉
                     
damask mantles, spred the arbors, arbors, but thrise more plesant

                        〈♫〉
                     
were her sweet supposes, proceeding from her lips, where

                        〈♫〉
                     
sweet loue harbors, her lips, where sweet loue harbors, for vewing those,

                        〈♫〉
                     
for vewing those her cheeks &amp; roses, for vew-ing those her

                        〈♫〉
                     
cheeks and roses sprowting, breeds a doubting.
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices II. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     CAarters, now cast down your whips, cast down

                        〈♫〉
                     
your whips, and shepheards put off, put off your

                        〈♫〉
                     
scrips, and shepheards put off your scrips, behold faire stars blazing,

                        〈♫〉
                     
blazing, faire stars blazing, Ambrosia with Amarillis, and

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Coridon walking with faire, with faire Phillis, and Coridon
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
walking with faie Phillis, to set your eyes, your eyes a gazing:

                        〈♫〉
                     
and Coridon
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. III. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     ANd Herpulus of Philida complained, for

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Corine often would she sigh and grone, but Herpulus
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
that lou'd her she disdained, poore Herpulus, why should not

                        〈♫〉
                     
ri-gor moue thee? 
                        •••
                     ate her thrice, ij that once disdaind

                        〈♫〉
                     
to loue thee, poore Herpulus
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices IIII. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        DAphne on the rainebow

                        〈♫〉
                     
riding, were chiding, were chiding, when

                        〈♫〉
                     
al the gods were chiding, fell sodenly amazed, full gastly then she

                        〈♫〉
                     
gazed, and presently the god of anger frownd, and in his fu-ry down

                        〈♫〉
                     
he flang her, down he flang her, and in his fu-ry down he flang her.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. V. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     BLind loue was shooting, &amp; loosing of his arrow,

                        〈♫〉
                     
he kild his mothers sparrow, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
and tracing forth his foo-ting, his mother Venus spide it, before

                        〈♫〉
                     
the boy could hide it. and tracing

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. VI. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        PEarce did loue faire Petronel, Petronel, and

                        〈♫〉
                     
gallantly could pranck it, could pranck it, he

                        〈♫〉
                     
puld her and he hauld her, ij and

                        〈♫〉
                     
often times he cald her, primrose prickt in a blanket. he puld her

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. VII. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        PEarce did dance with Petron
                           •
                        l-la, pretty

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Almans that weare new, ij. such he

                        〈♫〉
                     
daunst and nothing true, but when Parnell danst, but ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
all the maids began to flout him, all the maids began

                        〈♫〉
                     
to flout him. but when Parnel
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. VIII. BASVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     GOddes of the waters, goddes of the waters

                        〈♫〉
                     
flowing, that bears a sway in each thing growing, and

                        〈♫〉
                     
makes my Lady varia-ble, oft I seeke to vnder-mind her,

                        〈♫〉
                     
oft I seeke to vndermind her, yet I know not where,

                        〈♫〉
                     
to find her, yet I know not where to find her.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. IX. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LAdy, The silly flea of all disdained, I pitty,

                        〈♫〉
                     
I pitty, I pitty, I pitty, that poore creature,

                        〈♫〉
                     
both black &amp; smal of stature, were I a flea, were I a flea in bed, I

                        〈♫〉
                     
would not biteyou, bite you, bite

                        〈♫〉
                     
you, bite you, but search some other way for to delight

                        〈♫〉
                     
you. weare I a flea,

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. X. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     THrice blessed be the gi-uer, the gi-uer,

                        〈♫〉
                     
that 
                        〈◊〉
                      sweet loue that golden quiuer, among

                        〈♫〉
                     
the gods anointed, that made the arrow heads, ii.

                        〈♫〉
                     
ii. that made the arrow heads sharp pointed, if

                        〈♫〉
                     
either of them both had quai-led, if either of them both had qualed

                        〈♫〉
                     
she of my loue, she of my loue, she of my loue, ii, and 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
had failed. i
                        •
                     
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. XI. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     THe curtain drawn I saw my loue lie sleeping,

                        〈♫〉
                     
thrice happy was that peeping, for vewing her sweet

                        〈♫〉
                     
lying, her sweet lying, preserues my life and keeps my soule from dying,

                        〈♫〉
                     
from dying, of thousand ioies missing her, missing her I had mist al,

                        〈♫〉
                     
whose sight reuiues, reuiues me more, ii. then ru-by,

                        〈♫〉
                     
pearle, and cristall.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices XII. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     SV-san-na faire somtime, Susāna faire, Susanna

                        〈♫〉
                     
faire somtime, ii. of loue requested,

                        〈♫〉
                     
somtime ii. somtime of loue requested, by

                        〈♫〉
                     
two old men, ii. by two old men, sweet looks allur'd, was

                        〈♫〉
                     
in her hart full sad, was in her hart, was in her hart full sad, ii.

                        〈♫〉
                     
and sore molested, full ii. fulsad &amp; sore

                        〈♫〉
                     
molested, seeing the force, ii. seeing the force her chastity,

                        〈♫〉
                     
endur'd, to thē she said, by craft pro-cur'd, do yeeld

                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
to you my body to abuse it, do yeeld to you my

                        〈♫〉
                     
body to a-buse it, I loose my soule, I shal loose

                        〈♫〉
                     
I shal loose my soule, and if I shal refuse it, you will me iudge, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
reprochfully, better it is, but better it is in innocency to chuse

                        〈♫〉
                     
it, for to chuse it, then by my fault to offend, ii.

                        〈♫〉
                     
then by my fault to offend, ii. then by my fault to offend

                        〈♫〉
                     
my God on hie, ii. offend my God on hie.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. XIII. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LOue shooting among many, by chāce he hit,

                        〈♫〉
                     
by chāce he hit not a-ny the shaft, rebounded

                        〈♫〉
                     
and loue himselfe was wounded, and ij. and loue

                        〈♫〉
                     
himselfe was wounded, when Siches saw the dart had mist, had mist

                        〈♫〉
                     
her, when Siches saw the dart had mist, had mist her, she smild and said

                        〈♫〉
                     
that all the gods, and said that all the gods had blest her, when

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. second part. XIIII. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LOue shooting at another, and chāst

                        〈♫〉
                     
to hit his mother, but as the Lady fainted, god Mars
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
did start, and therwith was attained, attained, when Vulcan saw, when

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Vulcan saw, when Vulcan saw the shoot did freat him, the shoot did freat,

                        〈♫〉
                     
did freat him, he sweare that he would beat him, when Vulcan

                        〈♫〉
                     
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. XIII. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     AY me poore hart, since loue hath plai-ed his

                        〈♫〉
                     
part, since loue hath plaied his part, ii.

                        〈♫〉
                     
my sences all are lost, ij. are lost, my mind 
                        •
                     ake tost, like

                        〈♫〉
                     
waues that swell, sweet god of loue thou dost excel, thy passions mo
                        •
                     e, my

                        〈♫〉
                     
mind to proue, that turtle doue, she flies, ij. ii. she flies, she

                        〈♫〉
                     
flies, my loue she tries, oh send me remedy, remedy, ii.

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. oh send me remedy.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. XVI. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     SOmtime she would, and somtime not, and

                        〈♫〉
                     
somtime not, the more request, the more disdaind,

                        〈♫〉
                     
each woman hath her gift god wot, her gift god

                        〈♫〉
                     
wot, and e-uer had, and euer had since Venus raignd, Venus raignd, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
euer had since Venus raignd, though Vulcan, ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
though Vulcan, did to Venus yeeld, I would haue men to win the field.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. XVII. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     Among the Daffadillies, and faire white Lillies,

                        〈♫〉
                     
the God of loue, ii. of loue came creeping,

                        〈♫〉
                     
the god, the god of loue came creeping, lay sleeping, he bent his

                        〈♫〉
                     
bow, but mist his footing, ii. and loosing lost, both labor,

                        〈♫〉
                     
la-bor shaft and shooting, he bent his bow, but mist his footing,

                        〈♫〉
                     
ij. &amp; loosing lost both labor labor shaft &amp; shooting.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. voices. XVIII. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     HE ment to loue her, he set her on his ambling

                        〈♫〉
                     
Maire, al this he did to proue her, all this he did to

                        〈♫〉
                     
proue, all this he did to proue her, al this he did to proue, to proue her,

                        〈♫〉
                     
whē they cāe home, cam home, Sis floted creā, when they cāe home Sis

                        〈♫〉
                     
sloted cream, Sin floted cream, and pourd it through a strainer, pourd ij.

                        〈♫〉
                     
and ii. pourd it through a strainer, but sware that Simkin
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
should haue none because he did disdaine her.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices XIX. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     LAdy, whē I behold your passions, so

                        〈♫〉
                     
diuers &amp; so oft constrained, vpon such flight or no

                        〈♫〉
                     
occasions, as though you were with grief sore pained, as though you

                        〈♫〉
                     
were with griefe sore pained, I enter in-to these perswasions, A man

                        〈♫〉
                     
might saile from Trent vnto Danuby, and yet not find so strange a

                        〈♫〉
                     
peece as you be.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. XX. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     COnsture my meaning, wrest not my method,

                        〈♫〉
                     
wrest not my method, good will craues fauor, witnes

                        〈♫〉
                     
the high God, if I haue ment wel, good wil reward me, when

                        〈♫〉
                     
I deserue ill, no man re-gard me, what shall I say more,

                        〈♫〉
                     
speech is but blasting, but blasting, still will I hope for life euer-lasting,

                        〈♫〉
                     
stil will I hope for life euerlasting.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  4. Voices. eights parts. XXI. BASSVS.
                  
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     WItnes, ye heauens, I vow to loue the fairest

                        〈♫〉
                     
to loue but how for vertue not for lust,

                        〈♫〉
                     
ii. because she is the is the rarest, her I only

                        〈♫〉
                     
trust, hap death, hap life, I force not which betide me, not which betide

                        〈♫〉
                     
me, by her I liue from death I cannot hide me, hap death,

                        〈♫〉
                     
hap life, I force not which betide me, not which betide me, by her

                        〈♫〉
                     
I liue, from death I cannot hide me.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                     WItnes ye heau'ns, I vow to loue the fairest,

                        〈♫〉
                     
to loue but how, for vertue not for

                        〈♫〉
                     
lust, for vertue not for lust, not for lust, for vertue why? because she is

                        〈♫〉
                     
the rarest, come life, come death, in her I on-ly trust, hap death,

                        〈♫〉
                     
hap life, I force not which betide me, by her I liue, from death I

                        〈♫〉
                     
cannot hide me, hap death, hap life, I force not which betide me,

                        〈♫〉
                     
by her I liue, from death I cannot hide me.

                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  A TABLE OF ALL THE
CANZONETS
contained in this
BOOKF.
                  
                     MY Ladyes collor'd cheeks. I
                     Carters now cast downe your whips. II
                     
                        Philida bewaild the want of Coridon. III
                     
                        Daphne on the rainebow. IIII
                     Blind loue was shooting. V
                     
                        Pearce did loue faire Petronel. VI
                     
                        Pearce did daunce with Petronel VII
                     The wauering planet. VIII
                     Lady, the sillie flea of all disdained. IX
                     Thrice blessed be the giuer. X
                     The curtaine drawne I saw my loue. XI
                     Susanna faire sometime. XII
                     Loue shooting among many. XIII
                     Loue shooting at an other. XIIII
                     Ay me poore hart. XV
                     Sometime she would and sometime not. XVI
                     Among the dafadillies. XVII
                     Simkin said that Sisse was faire. XVIII
                     Ladie when'I behold your passions. XIX
                     Consture my meaning. XX
                     VVitnes ye heauens. XXI
                  
                  FINIS.
                  
               
            
         
      
   

