
   
      
         
            The difference betwene the auncient phisicke, first taught by the godly forefathers, consisting in vnitie peace and concord: and the latter phisicke proceeding from idolaters, ethnickes, and heathen: as Gallen, and such other consisting in dualitie, discorde, and contrarietie And wherein the naturall philosophie of Aristotle doth differ from the trueth of Gods worde, and is iniurious to Christianitie and sounde doctrine. By R.B. Esquire.
            Bostocke, Richard.
         
         
            
               1585
            
         
         Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00508
            STC 1064
            ESTC S104447
            99840185
            99840185
            4661
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00508)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4661)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 195:07)
         
         
            
               
                  The difference betwene the auncient phisicke, first taught by the godly forefathers, consisting in vnitie peace and concord: and the latter phisicke proceeding from idolaters, ethnickes, and heathen: as Gallen, and such other consisting in dualitie, discorde, and contrarietie And wherein the naturall philosophie of Aristotle doth differ from the trueth of Gods worde, and is iniurious to Christianitie and sounde doctrine. By R.B. Esquire.
                  Bostocke, Richard.
                  Bostocke, Robert, attributed name.
               
               [192] p.   
               
                  [By G. Robinson] for Robert VValley,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1585.
               
               
                  Attributed to Richard Bostocke; sometimes also attributed to Robert Bostocke.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: * A-L.
                  Running title reads: Of the auncient and later phisicke.
                  The last two leaves are blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Aristotle --  Early works to 1800.
               Medicine --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.
               Medicine, Ancient --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-06
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-07
            Andrew KusterSampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Andrew KusterText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE difference betwene the auncient Phiſicke, firſt taught by the godly forefathers, conſiſting in vnitie peace and concord: and the latter Phiſicke proceeding from Idolaters, Ethnickes, and Heathen: as Gallen, and ſuch other conſiſting in dualitie, diſcorde, and contrarietie.
            And wherein the naturall Philoſophie of Aristotle doth differ from the trueth of Gods worde, and is iniurious to Chriſtianitie and ſounde doctrine.
            
               Natura naturam continet &amp; ſuperat, &amp; ſua natura ſolùm latatur &amp; emendatur, &amp; eius propinquitatis res commiſceri &amp; coniungi facit.
            
            By R. B. Eſquire.
            Imprinted at London for Robert VValley.
            
            1585.
         
         
            
            
               〈2… pages missing〉
            
            
               Ca 8.
               Certaine differences, betweene the auncient Phiſicke and the Phiſicke of the Heathens.
               Ca. 9.
               The cauſes why this Arte is euill ſpoken of, and findeth fewe fauourers.
               Ca. 10.
               The firſt Authors of the auncient Phiſicke, and of the ſucceſſion and progreſſion therof, to Hermes Triſmegeſtus, and howe he left writinges thereof yet extant.
               Ca. 11.
               What was the Phiſicke of Apollo, Aeſculapius, Machaon, and Podalirius, and of the knowledge of Thales Mileſius.
               
               Ca. 12.
               Of Pythagoras and his knowledge in this Art, and that he taught in Italy. And of his ſcholers and folowers. And of the medicine of Empedocles. And of the 70. Bookes that Eſdras was commaunded to keepe.
               Ca. 13.
               That the Phiſick which Hypocrates left in writing, was not deſcended from Aeſculapius.
               
               Ca. 14.
               That Democritus Abderites a Thracian did write of this art, whoſe Bookes are yet extant: &amp; of his teachers, ſcholers and followers: and of ſome of their workes yet extant.
               
                  Ca. 15.
               That in Plato his time, the Prieſts of Aegipt, were very skilfull in this art. And that Plato did finde that fault with the Phiſitions of Greece, in his time, as the Chimicall Phiſitions doe now with the Ethnicke Phiſitions, and their folowers. And how Aristotle and Plato do differ in the naturall cauſes of Effects.
               Ca. 16.
               Of diuers Poetical Fables ſhadowing &amp; hyding the ſecretes of this Art.
               Ca. 17.
               Of certaine Phiſitions that vſed Chimicall medicines. And of the three ſects of Phiſitions, that were betweene the time of Hypocrates and Gallen. And that the Chimical Phiſitions, ought rather to bee called Rationales, then the Galeniſts. And that Galen following Hypocrates 600. yeres, did comment vpon him againſt his meaning and wordes. And how Hypocrates agreeth with the Chimicall Phiſitions.
               Ca. 18.
               Of the continuaunce of this Art in Aegipt, vntill the tyme of Dyocleſian the Emperour: And a notable monument thereof in Italy. And the ſpreading of this Art into other Countries. And of diuers writers of this Art betweene Galens tyme and Paracelſus.
               
               
                  Ca. 19.
               That Theophrastus Paracelſus was not the inuenter of this art, but the reſtorer thereof to his puritie: And that hee hath giuen more light thereunto, then any other before him. And the teſtimonies of great cures that he did by this Art. And of diuers writers &amp; learned Phiſitions, which ſince his tyme haue written of this Art.
               Ca. 20.
               The true meaning of Paracelſus in dedicating his Booke, intituled Philoſophia magna to the Athenians: wherewith Erastus one of his aduerſaries is ſo greeued.
               Ca. 21.
               How materia prima and myſteriam magnam, was the beginning of all thinges, according to Paracelſus his meaning: And how all things created were at one time in the increate.
               Ca. 22.
               Of the ſeparation of viſible and materiall bodies.
               Ca. 23.
               Certaine notes and cautions giuen, for the better vnderſtanding of this Chimicall Phiſicke.
               Ca. 24.
               Of the coeleſtiall medicine of Paracelſus: and matters toucking his perſon and ignoraunce.
               Ca. 25.
               The Concluſion of the Author.
            
         
         
            
            The Authors obteſtation to almightie God.
            
               
                  O
                GOD the father almighty, the true light O Chriſt, the light of the light, the wiſedome, miſterie, and vertue of GOD. O holy Ghoſt that knitteſt all thynges together in one, which ſuſtaineſt, and quickneſt all thyngs by this deuine power, &amp; giueſt ſtrength to liue and to moue, and alſo to continue, and to be preſerued and nouriſhed. O the holy Trinitie, three perſons and one God, which of nothing, that is hauing no matter, preexiſting, or goyng before, haſt created al the world, that is, all thyngs that are, to ſet forth thy glorie, wiſedome, power, &amp; goodneſſe: I beſech thee teach, ayd, &amp; aſſiſt thy ſeruaūts againſt the heathniſh and falſe Philoſophie of Ariſtotle, which teacheth that the world had no beginning, neither ſhall haue endyng. And that of nothyng, nothyng can be made, whereby it maketh the world
            
               〈2… pages missing〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            So likewiſe thy moſt excellent creature man was created to thy Image, in pure vnderſtandyng, perfect memorie, ſincere will without any care, or without all feare of death or perrilles. But (O moſt iuſt God) after his fall, death crept in as it were a leaproſie, and the Image of God was darkened, blemiſhed, and almoſt blotted out: Yet by thy mercifull goodneſſe O God, this Image is repaired by thy goſpell, becauſe wee be renewed by faieth into the hope of euerlaſtyng life, that wee maie liue in God, and with GOD, and maie bee one with hym. And whereas man after the eatyng of the Apple forbidden, had the knowledge of good and euill, yet the euil men doe detaine thy trueth O God, in vnrightuouſneſſe, and doe refuſe thy vocation and callyng, which by thy trueth doeſt continually call vs vnto thee, yet this thy trueth naturally grafed in vs continually doeth indeuour as much as it may to appere in action, but it is let and hindered by concupiſcence, which ſome ſay is in the nether part of the ſoule▪ others ſay it is in brutali ſpiritu or Anima, therfore thou haſt giuē vs, O God, that what we knowe, we ſtudy to make manifeſt &amp; ſhewe forth, which if we doe not wee be reproued by our owne iudgement: for the better part of the Soule or Spiritus, which ſome call ſintereſis,
               
doeth perſwade to that is good. Hereby appeareth the wonderfull power and ſtrength of conſcience: which in great offenſes cannot be perfectly quieted. Wherefore, it is written, the Gentiles which haue not the lawe, by nature, doe the workes of the lawe, and doe ſhewe the worke of the law written in their hearts: their conſcience bearing thē witneſſe: their thoughts either accuſing or defending them. This propertie to perſwade to doe good, ſome call ſintereſis, which thy word calleth conſcience, which is a liuing lawe, which cryeth, ſtirreth, and moueth to doe good: for thou O God, art ſo mercifull and good to vs, that thou haſt giuen this knowledge to our minde: which like a Schoolemaſter doth inſtruct and teach vs: ſo that cō
               ſcience, is as it were a certaine lawe in thinges ſubiect to ſence and reaſon. But (O good God) omnipotent, Ariſtotle his heathniſh Philoſophie, very abſurdly teacheth, that all the Orbes, be bodies ſubiect to no corruptiō, and that they and their motions be eternall: and he aſſigneth to certaine myndes, Intelligentis, or vnder ſtraunge natures and eſſenties, and ſeperated their ſeuerall and ſinguler motions of the ſayd Orbes: And he aſſigneth one Orbe to the high God, which is moued by him. Whereby he maketh all thoſe eſſenties ſeperated, among whō
               
thoſe Orbes are diſtributed to bee equall and like ſubstaunce: but he alloweth that mynde or eſſence which is the elder: that is, God to bee onely ſo much the more excellent then the reſt, by how much the orbe aſſigned to him, is more excellent then the other Orbes. That Philoſophie alſo teacheth, that it is an abſurde thing and againſt reaſon, to ſay that any thing eternall had any beginning: therefore becauſe thoſe Orbes be eternal they had no beginning. Likewiſe, it teacheth that God medleth not vnder the Moone, and that he is not the maker nor the creatour of any thing, but onely the mouer of the heauen: and it maketh God to be the finall cauſe onely of motions, and not of the nature of ech ſeueral thing: neither doth his Philoſophie teach any agent cauſe of thoſe thinges which it affirmeth to be eternall. And by this doctrine it muſt needes follow, that becauſe the world is eternall without beginning &amp; ending, and incorruptible, therefore it needeth not thy prouidence, either that it ſhould be, or continue, nor that it needeth thy helpe. And becauſe it hath no other efficient cauſe of any other but of it ſelfe, therefore it needeth none other to prouide for his being or well being. It alſo teacheth that thou O GOD medleſt not vnder the Moone, but that thou ruleſt vnder the Moone

onely with a cōmon influence and vſuall courſe of ſecond cauſes, though ſome doe vntruely goe about to excuſe this doctrine: in ſaying, that it accompteth Nature to be God, or at leaſt Gods Ʋicar or deputie: which neither needeſt any ſuch, nor yet haſt any deputie. O moſt mightie God, creator of all thinges, ſtrengthen thy people againſt theſe and all ſuch doctrines, tending to the derogation of thine honour, goodneſſe, mercie and wiſedome: and by reaſon it appeareth that no body of it ſelfe is immortall, becauſe each body conſisteth of his partes, therefore it may be diſſolued: but the ſoule of man is immortall, and the body is made immortall at the laſt reſurrection, by reaſon of the preſence of the ſoule: But Ariſtotle maketh no mention of the immortalitie of the ſoule, neither doth he attribute any felicitie to it after the death of man: whereby Alexander Aptrodiſienſes concludeth, that he denyeth the immortalitie of the ſoule: Alſo reaſon teacheth, that many diuers and contrary thinges can not bee ioyned together by themſelues, without the helpe of an other, and be not brought to one certaine forme, vnleſſe they bee vnited together by the helpe of ſome other. The worlde therefore, conſisting of ſo many diuers and contrary partes: in which, colde, heate, drineſſe, and moysture, are ioyned

together, and other thinges of contrary nature
                  •
                and vertues, doe agree together in one forme. And the Orbes and celestiall bodies of contrary motions from the Eaſt to the Weſt, and from the Weſt to the Eaſt, and in retrogradation and direction, and ſtationarij, their motions in the Epicycle, in the Auſt. &amp; opoſito angis, doe make no diſcorde, but keepe a regular order in all thoſe contrarieties. Therfore, we muſt bee compelled to confeſſe, that there was and is one that hath coupled, vnited, and ioyned together, ſuch and ſo diuers contrary things: otherwiſe, ſuch diuers and contrary things and motions, by their owne ſwing, courſe and mouing, would bee diſſolued one from an other, vnleſſe they were preſerued by ſome others. Can there be a table painted with diuers colours and pictures, or pots of diuers ſorts and faſhions, without a workmaſter? Can any thing that lacketh a gouernour or ruler, be moued by it ſelfe continually in a regular or certaine order? Therefore, by reaſon it appeareth, that the worlde is gouerned and ruled (O God) by thy diuine prouidence: And thou (O God) that ruleſt all the vniuerſall worlde, doeſt alſo gouerne, rule, and prouide for each parte thereof: for he doth nothing well, that neglecteth the leaſt parte of that thing.
            
               Likewiſe, O almightie God, that heathniſh Philoſopher doth teach, that homo &amp; Sol generāt hominē, whereby (O good God) it muſt needes followe, that man and the Sunne muſt be eternall and infinite. Though heate nouriſheth and cheriſheth our bodies, yet for all that it is not the cauſe of generation and begetting, but thy worde, O mercifull God, ſo commaunding, that the blood of this or that man ſhalbe made male or female. Reaſon can not comprehende this worde, therefore it muſt needes childiſhly trifle off the cauſes of ſuch things. So the Phiſitions following the Philoſophers, doe referre the cauſe of generation (O God) to a cōuenient mixture of qualities, which doe worke in the matter ordeyned before, what colour ſoeuer reaſon doth beare herein: yet for all that, they doe not attaine to the firſt cauſe thereof. For, the holy Ghoſt (O God) doth leade vs into a higher cauſe then to nature, then to qualities, and their temperature, when it ſetteth before vs thy worde, O omnipotent God, in which all things are created and conſerued. Alſo, O moſt high God, this heathniſh Philoſophie doth not admit any Metaphiſicall principle in naturall thinges, in which aſcending by the doubtfull care of naturall thinges, being remoued from diuine, mans minde is turned from them. And

ſurely ſuch naturall Philoſophie is the next way to make men forget thee, O God, and to become Atheists: for it teacheth men to cleane and ſticke faſt vnto the nature of thinges, not aſcending nor conſidering the Creator: And ſo it tyeth thee (O God) to the ſeconde cauſes, and doth not attribute to thee any actions, but according to that nature of thinges: whereby it doth bewitch men in ſuch ſorte, and make their mindes ſo mad, that they neither do aske neither looke for any good thing at thy hande: for the euent and ſucceſſe of each thing muſt of neceſſitie bee anſwerable to the naturall cauſe. And by that doctrine thou (O God) doeſt followe the nature of thinges created: whereas contrariwiſe all thinges created muſt followe thee: ſo that it placeth the effected cauſe in the ſteede of efficient, and the instrumentall cauſe for the agent. And further it teacheth, that matter and forme is the firſt principle of naturall thinges: which doctrine draweth thy people (O God) from true honoring of thee, for the creation and prouidence of thy creatures. It is not enough to confeſſe that thou didſt create all thinges, if it bee ſayd alſo that thou haſt forſaken thoſe thinges as ſoone as thou haſt created them: as the Carpenter leaueth the houſe when he hath once made it: for ſo ſhould the worlde

ſone periſh and come to ruine: but thou, O moſt mercifull God, doeſt direct all thinges that bee or ſhalbe by thy vnderſtanding and knowledge to meete and conuenient endes, ſuch as pleaſeth thee to thy honour and glory. For, in thee wee liue, moue, and haue our being: and all thinges be of thee, and in thee, and by thee. For, we can not moue our tongue, which is the lytiſt part of our body, without thy prouidence: Man may prepare the heart, but thou (O God) ruleſt the tongue: neither doth a Sparrowe light vpon the ground, without thy good will O almightie father: And all the heires of our head be numbred, thou c
                  •
               ri
                  •
               ſt all things by the word of thy power: thou art the Lorde of all fleſh: thou art the Lord of all ſpirites: thou workeſt all things according to the decree of thy will. Therefore, O God, graunt we may caſt our care vpon thee, that thou may nouriſh vs: take thou care ouer vs: touch the apple of our eye: be thou our ſhield and braſen wall: Bee thou our helper and wee care not what man may doe to vs. Giue vs a newe heart and a newe ſpirite: as thou haſt giuen vs thy Commaundements, ſo make vs to walke in them. By theſe and ſuch like testimonies of thy moſt ſacred and holy worde, O good God, we learne thy diuine prouidence ouer man and all other thy creatures, and that thou doeſt

not leaue nor forſake them when thou haddeſt made them, but doeſt of thy moſt tender goodneſſe gouerne not only man, but alſo whatſoeuer thou haſt created: whoſe infinite power worketh euery thing in euery thing. And thy ſeruaunts doe acknowledge (O God) that a peculiar force and vertue was giuen to euery thing at the beginning by thy worde, voyce, and commaundemēt: which yet are in continuall force: but yet the ſame bee but onely ſeconde and inſtrumentall cauſes, not working of themſelues, not principally, but depend vpon thy power and commaundement, without which thou workeſt the ſame effects when thou pleaſeſt: which thou art wont to do by meanes of the ſecond cauſes. And all thinges which are in this world, and which are ſeene, doe not onely take their beginning from thee to bee thinges, but alſo to haue ſuch power and vertue, and to be ſuch maner of thinges as they are. Therefore is the worlde a looking glaſſe, in which thy wiſedome is perceiued: If wee aſcende into heauen, thou are there: If we deſcende into hell, thou art preſent. And though th
                  •
               ſe vertues and powers haue in them great ſtrength and e
                  •
               f
                  ••
               acie, and thou (O God) 
                  〈…〉
                often tymes worke by them, as thou doeſt▪ by th
                  ••
               e Angels thy miniſters which doe thy will: yet are they all but the ſecond cauſes

and inſtruments of thy diuine prouidence, and can doe nothing vnleſſe thou bee preſent to gouerne the things, and helpe and bring forth the effect: For thou (O God) doeſt not ſo giue force to thinges, nor doeſt ſo ſend thy Angels thy ministers, that thou art abſent thy ſelfe: for thou reacheſt and toucheſt from end to end mightely, and dispoſeſt all thinges ſweetely and profitable to thy glory. Therefore art thou (O moſt mightie God) the firſt and efficicient cauſe of all things. For, thou (O God almightie father) art the reſting and quiet fountaine of al things that be, perfect of thy ſelfe, needing none other: Thou art the firſt action, and workest inwardly: thou art the true light. Thou art not onely all in each ſeuerall thing, but all in all, ſpiritually in power and eſſence: ſo thou art euery where: thou art the being, firſt, cheefe, and principall liuing and parent of life: hauing quiet motion in thy ſelf, and mouing thy ſelf inwardly, being not moued by motion. Thou art the being and beginning of all other things: Thou art ſilence, thou art quietneſſe, or resting, abyding in thy ſelfe: that is, ſecret mouing, or ſecret action. Wherefore, thou art ſayd (as it were) to ſit in the Center of all thinges that bee, from whence with an vniuerſall eye: that is, with the light of thy ſubstance, by the which each

thing hath his being, life, and knowledge: thou doeſt beholde them: thy will is the ſtill worde. Thou (O Father) art the beginning of being of all ſubstaunces, which from thee that is the being it ſelfe, doeſt giue (being power of life and ſubstaunce) to all thinges according to the power and capacitie of the receiuer. All thinges dwell in thee, potencially: thou art the parent of all things in power. Thou art omnipotent: thou art all in all in thoſe thinges: whereof thou art the originall and cauſe in vertue and power. Thou filleſt heauen and earth, and thy ſpirite hath filled the whole world yet it is in ſecrete: that is, in power. For, there muſt bee a certaine might or power, wherwith all things are quickened into liuely Spirits, as it were from a liuely fountaine, that they may liue of that: and becauſe they do liue, they obteine their being. For there muſt be an Actor before there be action, the Agent bringeth f
                  •
               orth action. Therefore, thou (O Father) which art the principall and firſt liuing, doeſt bring forth life.
            Thou (O God the Sonne) by whom all thinges were made, and without whom nothing is made, art the f
                  •
               ood or riuer running from the Father the fountaine: thou art the light of the worlde: for by reaſon of thee all worldly things liue: Thou art the Image of the Father, the

word, the wiſedome of the father, and the vertue and power of operation and working. Thou (O God the Sonne) art the apparent and manifeſt motion or mouing, moued by motion, the actiue motion or action, and actiue worde: for the manifeſting of the power is action: which action hauing all thinges that bee in power liuing and knowledge according to motion, doth bring forth and make manifeſt all thinges: not by locall motion, neither by transferring into place, but by a better and diuine motion, ſuch as belongeth to the Spirite▪ which by his owne motion doth giue life, and bringeth foorth vnderstanding 
                  〈…〉
                in it ſelfe, and not cut from the firſt power in the operation. Thou (O Chriſt) art life hauing life in thy ſelf, appearing outwardly in quickning: And becauſe thou art life, therfore thou art motion quickning al that is quickened▪ for life is cauſe of motion. And becauſe thou art manifeſt motion, comming from ſecrete and inwarde motion, and life taking life from liuing, and the principall life and beginning: therefore life is begotten of liuing or principall life, and thou art the Sonne of the father, and by thee all thinges are made. Thou art life in al things▪ ſeing thou art euery where: all fulneſſe doth inhabite in thee corporally: that is, in operation ſubſtantially. And becauſe

the very life had no beginning, being alwaies of it ſelfe, to it ſelfe, of the father: therfore it neuer c
                  •
               aſ
                  •
               th, and it is alwaies infinite: and there is no life which in ſo much that it is life, doth not pertaine to the riuer of life: it giueth life &amp; breath to all thinges, and in all thinges, from ſuperceleſtiall thinges to coeleſtiall and to heauenly bodies, to 
                  ••
               yall, waterie, and earthly thinges, and to all thinges that the earth doth bring forth, and to all other thinges: therefore, euery matter whereof the worlde conſisteth is indewed with life, and Chriſt is in the life, by whoſe power all things doe come forth and proceede into generation, and conſiſt according to their matters and ſubstancies, to the which thou giueſt ſuch propertie and vertue as they haue. Thou art the vniuerſal word remayning impaſſible and not turning: yet life is before the ſoule: for the life of the ſoule is of the power of liuing: Thou art the ſeede of all thinges that be in operation and made manifeſt: for nothing can come nor proceede from the Elements of parents nor of any ſeede, if thou (O Chriſt) worke not: if thou withdrawe thy working power from things, they periſh immediatly. Thou (O GOD the holy Ghoſt) art the ſpringing knowledge and vnderstanding, flowing and proceeding from the Father and the Sonne.

Thou art the ſpirituall voyce of the manifeſt voyce or Sonne, as the Sonne is the voyce of the voyce in ſilence, therefore thou art of the Sonne and of the Father: yet but one voyce, one word: that is, one actiue power agreeing together before it maketh any thing to bee. Thou art the Spirit of God, the power of Chriſt: and the Spirite of God is God: therefore, all three of one ſubstaunce: All thinges be in thee, as al things be by the Sonne, and of the Father. Thou (O God the holy Ghoſt) art (as it were) the miniſterie of God, and doeſt deuide the graces and miniſteries in the operation of life: ſo that by thee the firſt ſeedes of things are nouriſhed and ſustayned, and now alſo be continually moued: and firſt bring foorth rootes and blades: after ſtalkes, eares▪ flowers, bloſſomes, ſ
                  •
               edes, and fruite, of each thing in his degree, according to thy distribution and diuiſion of the giftes. As the Father is the cauſe of the operation▪ and the Sonne the manifeſt operation: ſo all three are one action and ſubstaunce. Thou coupleſt and k
                  •••
               eſt the Father and the Sonne in one, and art coupled with them: and all other thinges thou ioyneſt in vnitie and band of peace. And becauſe in God to knowe, is as much to ſay, as to vnderstande, and to knowe that one liueth, and to knowe himſelfe is to liue: therefore, to

knowe or vnderstande, and to liue, is all one: And becauſe they be one, and becauſe to bee, is all one with life and vnderstanding: (for true being can not bee without life and vnderſtanding: neither can life and vnderstanding be without ſuch being) therefore they be three, yet one ſubstaunce and one God. So the ſoule of man, in that it is a ſoule hath his being, giuing life and vnderſtanding, &amp; is there in one. And as God the Father is a Spirite ſubstancially, and the Sonne is a Spirite and motion moued, and working openly: ſo thou the holy Ghoſt art the ſecrete ſpirite and motion: Thou implanteſt and giueſt ſtrength to liue and to moue, and alſo ſuſtayneſt all things that they may exiſt and liue, and alſo continue and be preſerued. And becauſe thou art God, thou art a Spirite: and becauſe thou art that Spirite thou doeſt quicken: for it is the Spirite that quickeneth: and becauſe thou quickneſt, thou haſt power of life: (for the Spirite is life) therfore thou liueſt and art life, and ſubstancially quickeneſt or giueſt li
                  •
               e to all thinges, or makeſt life in all thinges. But this Spirite and life which is in thee (O God) is not that which is in man, beaſtes, Angels, or other thinges created: but all thinges of the worlde created whatſoeuer they bee, and of what ſorte ſouer they bee, doe receiue life and

liue of that life, according to their kinde of being, and as that life doth breathe power and giue power of liuely vertue and ſtrength to thē, as the thinges be made able to receiue it. For, there muſt be Agens before there be Actio: ſo in all thinges there is proper being, life and vnderstanding or feeling, according to their ſeuerall capacities, which they doe receiue of being life and vnderſtanding: which three be all one: that is, of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, three perſons &amp; one God: in euery one of which three, all theſe three, vz. being life and vnderſtanding are, by which all thinges are made. For, though certaine thinges be attributed vnto the ſeuerall perſons, to bee proper to each of them in diuine thinges: yet it is to bee vnderſtanded, to be the inſeperable and agreeing operation of the three or Trinitie together: for there is but one beginning, and one cauſe of all thinges that be: and parte of diuine thinges alwaies is the ſame that is the whole.
            By theſe (O mercifull God) it may appeare how iniurious (and contrary to thine honour and glory, in creating of the worlde, and to thy prouidence ouer the creatures that thou haſt made) is the heathniſh Philoſophy of Ariſtotle, which admitteth nothing, that cannot be demonstrated: And alſo how falſely that Philoſophi
                  •
               
               
maketh priuation to bee the third beginning of all naturall thinges: and that it aſſigneth no Author nor propagator vnto the eſſences or natures which a ſaith be eternall: and that, that Philoſophie will not allowe any cauſe of their being beſides their motion: and that ſome thinges that bee done are done without cauſe: as deliberation, &amp;c. From theſe and ſuch other blinde and iniurious doctrine taught in that Philoſophie (good and mercifull God) deliuer thy people and ſeruaunts. And (O moſt mercifull God) becauſe the heathniſh Phiſicke of Galen, doth depende vppon that heathniſh Philoſophie of Ariſtotle, (for where the Philoſopher endeth, there beginneth the Phiſition) therfore is that Phiſicke as falſe and iniurious to thine honor and glory, as is the Philoſophie. For, that heathniſh Phiſicke (O God) doth not acknowledge the creation of man, whereby it doth not rightly knowe why he is Microcoſmus, or little worlde: which is the cauſe why they neither knowe his deſeaſes rightly, neither prouide medicine for him aptly, nor prepare it fitly, neither miniſter it accordingly. This heathniſh Philoſophie and Phiſicke, doth attribute thy workes (O God) to heate, colde, and ſuch cauſes, which it calleth falſely naturall: So it teacheth, that natural heate doth chaūge

meate receiued into mans ſtomacke into blood, fleſh, bones, braines, ſine
                  ••
               es, vaines, and artires: And that the like meare receiued of a dogge, horſe, beaſt, or birde, &amp;c. by heate of that beaſt or fowle, is turned into his fleſh, blood, bones, &amp;c. Much vnlike vnto that which is in man: which operation and tranſmutation, in trueth commeth of thee, (O God) and not of any nature of heate: and whereby in ſeeking for like cure in ſuch defects, their Phiſicke muſt needes erre, in not ſeeking helpe at thy handes, nor praying to thee, nor giue thankes to thee: No more doth that heathniſh Philoſophie and Phiſicke acknowledge, that all ſeedes did receiue by thy diuine worde the power of multiplying, of tranſplantation, the eſſence and properties: of which, all Philoſophie, Phiſicke, and Alchimie doth conſiſt: Therefore they muſt needes erre, both in the cauſe &amp; effects of thinges in the great worlde and in the little world.
            Likewiſe, becauſe the heathniſh Philoſophie doth not knowe out of thy worde, that thou (O God) haſt made all thinges in weight, number, and meaſure, therefore that Phiſicke doth not knowe the cauſe nor cure of thoſe deſeaſes that bee either originally or inflicted into the inuiſible parte of man Anima or Limbus, nor to helpe them: which error Plato reproued in the

Greeke Phiſitiōs long ago which Plato taught, that Anima curat corpus. And becauſe the heathniſh Philoſophie doth attribute the cauſe of thinges to dead qualities, of heate, cold, &amp;c. and not to the liuely vertues and powers in thinges, therefore that heathniſh Phiſicke ſeeketh by like dead qualities, to cure liuely and mechanicall ſpirites: And becauſe they vnderſtand not, that deſeaſes doe proceede of the mechanicall ſpirites and tinctures of impure ſeedes ioyned to the pure by thy curſe, O iuſt God, therefore they ſeeke not their medicines in the pure ſeedes. And becauſe (O merciſull God) the heathniſh Phiſicke and the heathniſh Philoſophie doth not acknowledge, that it is thy power and vertue that bringeth forth all thinges that growe, and that thy working power doth preſerue and maintaine all thinges: and that it is thy curing vertue that helpeth and cureth all deſeaſes, greeſes and infirmities, by ſuch meanes as it pleaſeth thee, or without meanes: therefore they cleaue faſt to their falſe imagined naturall cauſes and meanes of helpe, forgetting thee: whereby many of them become Atheists. And becauſe the heathniſh Phiſick of Galen, doth not knowe how thou (O God) haſt ordeyned all thinges in vnitie peace and concorde, therefore it ſeeketh the cure in dualitie

and contrarietie. To bee ſhort, becauſe (O moſt merciful God) the heathniſh Phiſick doth not knowe that the pureſt, beſt, and medicinable parte of each thing is in his Center, therfore it neither doth ſeeke, neither haue his fauorers learned, nor doe knowe, how to finde that pure parte, nor to ſeparate the pure from the impure: they cannot digeſt, nor make ripe that is rawe: they cannot chaunge ſower into ſweete: they cannot mittigate the lothſomneſſe of heates, taſtes, ſmelles, coagulations, &amp;c. neither make any medicine volatile: For which cauſe, therefore doe they not knowe the power of the mechanicall ſpirites, by meanes of their ſubtiltie, fineſſe, pearcing, and moueableneſſe: neither do they knowe the fineſſe and pearcing, by meanes of ſeparation of thinges mixt with them: neither the ſeparaetion by meanes of digestion and circulation: wherefore, they doe not knowe how the mechanicall ſpirites of deſeaſes doe differ among them ſelues, and one from an other in power, pearcing, moueableneſſe, fineſſe, groſneſſe, in eaſie or vneaſie reſolution and alteration, and ſuch like tokens: whereby they are ignoraunt of the true cauſes of the pangs, fits, and paſſions of deſeaſes: and how and in what maner, bodies and partes of bodies doe differ one from an other, and among themſelues. For, ſeedes do differ

in partes of the body: and as the ſeedes doe differ, ſo the bodies and partes of the bodies doe differ one from an other, and their natures and properties: of which difference of the ſeedes cō
               meth the difference of the mechanicall ſpirites conteyned in them, in which the giftes and offices of the ſeedes doe floriſh. Likewiſe, might they know of the fits, panges, and paſſions of deſeaſes, the difference of the ſeedes, and of the fruites of the ſeedes being knowne, the ſeedes or rootes of deſeaſes are knowne: euen as the Peare tree is by the Peare: becauſe the fruites, vz. the panges, fits, paſſions, and maner of the deſeaſes, are brought forth like to the rootes. Neither haue they any skill to reiect the Bynary, and to bring the Ternary, to the ſimplicitie of vnitie, where by the medicines may bee purged from their carcaſes and impediments: and the ſpirit Anima, be brought out of darkneſſe into light: by meanes whereof, the corrupt body of man may bee ſo purged, and purified, that the troubled minde and oppreſſed memorie may bee quickned and releeued, by thy gift (O God) and be made more able to vſe the talent by thee giuen 
                  •
               t the beginning, and the more ſtrongly to reſiſt the wicked deceiuer, and be better diſpoſed to honeſt life and conuerſation, pleaſing to thee O God.
            
               Becauſe (O moſt mercifull God) I doe finde theſe faultes and ſuch like in the heathniſh Philoſophie and heathniſh Phiſicke, I do know that by the fauorers and followers of that Philoſophie and Phiſicke, I ſhalbe mocked, laughed at, had in deriſion, and my ſayinges and words ſhalbe wreſted, racked, writhed, diſmembered, pulled from their partes, and turned from their right ſence and meaning. And the more vnskilfull the aduerſaries be in the true Philoſophie and Phiſick, and withall wilfull, the more buſie (O God) wil they be to replye with taunts, quippes, ſcoffes, and gibes: but ſuch deſerue no place nor time of anſwere. Wherefore, O moſt wiſe God, author of all wiſedome, I pray thee instruct thy people and ſeruaunts in the true Philoſophie and Phiſick: and open the eyes and mollifie the hearts of the followers of the heathen, that they may ſee and followe the ſame for thine honor &amp; glory▪ And from lying lippes and deceiptfull tongue, deliuer me O God.
            
               R. B.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
               
               
               
                  Chapter firſt. What the auncient Phiſicke is. And what the phiſicke of the Ethnikes or heathen is. And that there is no trueth that is not deriued from Chriſt the trueth it ſelfe.
               
                  THE true and auncient phiſicke which conſiſteth in the ſearching out of the ſecretes of Nature, whoſe ſtudy &amp; vſe doth flowe out of the Fountaines of Nature, and is collected out of the Mathematicall and ſupernaturall precepts, the exerciſe whereof is Mechanicall, and to be accompliſhed with labor, is part of Cabala, and is called by auncient name, Ars ſacra, or magna, &amp; ſacra ſciētia, or Chymia, or Chemeia, or Alchimia, &amp; myſtica, &amp; by ſome of late, Spagirica ars. Which ſheweth foorth the compoſitions of all maner bodies, and their diſſolutions, their natures &amp; properties by labour by the fire, following Nature diligently. So that Philoſophie naturall and ſupernaturall, the Mathematicals Chimia and Medicina be ſo combined together,

that one of them can not be without the other. I doe meane the true and right vſe of Chymia, and not the abuſe thereof, which promiſeth golden mountaines vnder the vain title of Philoſophie and Wiſdome, the wiſedome whereof is conſumed and waſted in ſmoke, by force of the fire. This auncient and true phiſicke conſiſteth of Medicines of two ſorts. The firſt is Vniuerſalis or vnarii. The ſecond is ternarii or particularis. Theſe two are founded vpon the Center of vnitie, concord and agreement, their ſcope and end is to bring the ſicke perſon to vnitie in himſelfe, they doe agree with the rule of Gods worde, they depend vpon the fountaine of trueth. The Eth
                     ••
                  kes or heathen haue of their own braynes deuiſed a third kinde of phiſicke or Medicine which is binarii or vulgaris. This is moſt groſſe and worſt, and is that phiſicke which is moſt commonly vſed, and moſt ſtoutly mainteined and defended. This phiſicke is founded vpon a contrary Center to the other, therefore a falſe Center. For it conſiſteth in dualitie, diſcord and contrarietie. It maketh warre and not peace in mans bodie. It is not founded vpon the rule of Gods worde, but vpon the authoritie of men reprobate of God, &amp; ſuch as were Idolaters and ignorant of the

trueth, conſiſting onely in God (whome they knewe not) and in his Chriſt the trueth it ſelf, whome Galene the prince of that phiſicke, in his workes hath blaſphemed of ſet purpoſe and by expreſſe wordes. And therefore he and the reſt his folowers, were ſeduſed with the ſpirit of contradiction and error. Yet their folowers thinke wee doe them great wrong in ſaying, ſuch haue not ſayde nor written the trueth. As though Artes and Sciences may be poſſeſſed and exerciſed by mans braynes and inuētions without God that made them. This may well be called blaſphemie. Herein Plato may be ſufficiēt witneſſe againſt them, ſaying that no man can rightly vnderſtande and haue knowledge of things belonging to man, if he be ignorant in things parteyning to God: and doe not firſt know things diuine. For ſeeing Chriſt is the way by the which we ought to begin, proceede, goe onward and to the ende in all our actions, artes and Sciences, we ought to walke in this way, aſwell to attaine knowledge, health and life in this world, as life in the world to come. The heathen Phiſitions not walking in this way, muſt needes erre and ſtray, not receiuing the key of wiſdome, which is ſcience of GOD himſelfe, who giueth wiſedome to the wiſe.

And ſeeing that all things which the Father hath, be his ſonnes Chriſtes: and ſeeing wiſdome and ſcience be the riches of God, and all wiſedome is of him, and the power of God is wiſdome and ſcience, and the working power of GOD is Chriſt, and Chriſt is the trueth, therefore hee that ſwarueth from Chriſt neither hath the treaſures and riches of the wiſdome and ſcience of God, neither is lead into the trueth by the trueth it ſelfe, therefore hath not trueth. And ſeeing Chriſt is life it ſelfe, which is the power of life to himſelfe and to al others, by whome all things are made and moue, and by whome life is in all things, frō things celeſtiall to things in the heauens, ayer, water and earth, and to all matter in the world which hath life, and he is in the life, and is the power of the ſeede of all things, which become and proceede to be manifeſted and come to action, of whom euery body brought forth by touching, and coniunction doth grow and increaſe, and by whome all thinges are one, not as a heape of Corne or graine is one body, onely by lying together, but becauſe all partes doe hang together, and be as it were one chaine. For God, Chriſt, the holy Ghoſt, the ſoule, Angels and all corporall things is as it were this chaine, and the Father is the

principall life and cauſe of life, and al things in the world haue bèing and life of Chriſt, the life it ſelfe which giueth them to all things, and is in the life, and all in all. Who alſo is the light of the light, that is of God which ſitteth in the Center of all things that be, from whence with his vniuerſall eye, that is with the light of his ſubſtance, whereby he is their being, and life, doeth behold all things. For from the Center all things are ſeene at once, and alike. Therfore all perſwading ſpeaches and fayre and plauſible arguments, hauing great ſhewe and colour of reaſon, being deriued out of mans braines, or corrupted or mingled with the leuen of mans inuētions, ſwaruing from Chriſt or not reſting in him, or leauing nothing or very litle to him, in whoſe power and gouernement all things are: from whome health and life is deriued, in whom all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge are hidde, muſt needes be not onely confuſe and vayne, but alſo erronious, fooliſh, deceitfull, falſe and counterfeit, though they beare neuer ſo gay titles of Philoſophie, wiſedome or phiſicke. Such is the Philoſophie whereof S. Paule giueth vs warning, Col. 3. ſaying, beware leſt there be any man that ſpoyle you through the tradition of men, according to the

rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt: for in him dwelleth al the fulneſſe of the Godhed bodily. Such Philoſophie and phiſicke hang not together in the chaine aforeſaid, nor yet bee illuminated from the right Center, nor ſeene from the ſame, but be founded vpon diuers Centers, whereby their Circles doe cut one another, or touch ech other, therefore they doe not conſiſt in vnion, but are contrary to eche other. Such Center is the Center of dualitie, contrarietie and diſcord. The originall thereof is worthely called Binari, the author of diuerſitie and contrarietie, which alwayes maketh ſedition and diſcord, as vnitie is the band of concord. For concord is the vnion of diuers appetites of thoſe things that doe deſire, whereby they be of one minde. Therefore euery thing in the worlde doth ſo long indure and abide as long as it is one: but it dieth and is diſſolued as ſoone as it ſeſſeth and leaueth to be one. Vnquietneſſe beginneth in things, where Meum &amp; tuum, is become to be knowen in them: whereof commeth griefe, which is a ſenſe or feeling that can not abide deuiſion or corruption. Whereby it appeareth how deſirous Anima (which is medium inter corpus &amp; ſpiritum) is of vnitie in his body, which bendeth it ſelfe and

ſtriueth againſt that paſſion or griefe of his body, by the which it greeueth him, that his vnitie and integritie ſhould be weakened.
            
            
               
                  Chapter ſecond. The originall cauſes of all diſeaſes in the greate worlde, and in the little worlde, which is man.
               
                  GOD almightie the creator of al things, did ſee the angels which he had created fall from vnitie, and he made all the world to the image and ſimilitude of vnitie wherein it did conſiſt. Alſo by his bountifull goodneſſe and prouidence he created Microcoſmum or little worlde, vz. man, his ternarium and laſt creature, and ſubſtituted him in the place of his other creatures which were caſt out of heauen. From this one did God deriue all mankind. And hee did not create the woman which ſhould bee cowpled to man, as he made him but out of him, that al mankind ſhould ſpring out of one, to the commendation of vnitie and concord. The worlde did perſiſt in this vnion, and did obſerue the nature of vnitie, vntill that wretched creature Binarius,

which fell from vnitie, and made a dualitie &amp; contrarietie, enuying the ſtate of man, that perſiſted in vnitie, by captious ſophiſticall reaſon did perſwade him to eate of the Apple forbidden, whereby he brake vnitie, and fell headlong into diſobedience, dualitie and contrarietie. Then was he ſpoyled of perfection, and of the health of his ſoule and body, and purchaſed to himſelf all the filthineſſe of vice, infirmitie and ſickneſſe. Alſo the Seedes of all things of the world, which by vertue of the word of God at the beginning, had receaued power of generatiō and multiplication, were perfect and ſound without corruption, aud did perſiſt in vnitie, vntill ſuch time as by the ſaid counſel of Binarius, man fell into diſobedience and brake vnitie. Whereupon by the curſe of God impure Seedes were mingled with the perfect ſeedes, and did cleaue faſt to them, and doe couer them as a garment: and death was ioyned to life. So imperfection and impuritie, is ioyned to puritie, and death to life, ſickneſſe to health, not onely in man, but alſo in all liuing creatures, Hearbes, Plants, Mynerals: and in the fruites of the Firmament and ayer. By this meanes the Mynerals haue their ruſt and canker, which worke their deſtruction and ende. The vegetables,

as hearbes, trees and plantes, haue their corruptions of diuers ſorts, ioyned with their pure balme &amp; ſeedes, which in their time work their putrification, withering &amp; cōſumption, according to the Science and propertie of their impure ſeedes, beſides the alteration which they receiue by the nature of the ſoyle wherin they growe, as may be taſted, felt and perceiued, by wheate ſowen in ſome ground, which will manifeſtly taſte of Garlicke, and be much like in propertie. And ſome grounde will make tranſplantation of one ſeede into an other, as from Wheate to Drake or Darnell or ſuch like. The beaſtes alſo, Cattell and ſuch liuing creatures, becauſe they liue and be nouriſhed with the vegetables and minerall reſolutions, haue like impurities as they haue, according to the nature of the ſoyle whereupon they feede, &amp; of the water which they drinke. As appeareth by the Meadowes neere the Riuer Potheus in ye Ile of Candie, neere the Cittie Cortina, wherein groweth ſuch graſſe and hearbes, that the Cattell which be fedde therwith will haue no apparēt Spleene. Some countreys &amp; ſoyle do infect the Liuer, others the Lungs, other places, other parts of the Cattell which be there fed, as experience teacheth. Which partes of the

Cattell our forefathers did diligently vewe and ſearch before they layde the foundation of their houſes, townes or Cities, and that they did oftentimes, becauſe they would knowe whether thoſe parts were infected with ſickneſſe, with their foode and by the often ſight of them, they iudged whether the Cattell fed there were holſome for their victuall and foode or no. And becauſe man receiueth his nouriſhment out of all the reſt, therefore hee hath infinite ſortes and kinds of diſeaſes, and therefore no other Creature hath ſo many meanes to bring it to ſickneſſe, nor to his death. But the foode and nouriſhments for mans body, though they haue in them mingled, venemous, ſickly or medicinable properties, yet for all that, by reaſon of that mixture with their good ſeedes, as long as vnitie and concord is kept betweene them, they be tempered, ſeperated, reſolued and expelled out of mans body. But if man doe take them out of meaſure, or if the firſt ſtomake, or the Stomake of any part of the body be faultie in attraction, ſeparation, reſolution, digeſtion, diſtributiō or expultiō, the ſeedes of diſeaſes do then take roote in mans body. And that euery thing hath his impure ſeede ioyned with his pure, and death to his life, though it be neuer

ſo holſome or pleaſant to mans nature, is manifeſted and made plaine to the eye, touch and taſte of them that haue ſkill to ſeperate the pure from the impure, by his auncient Phiſicke or Chymia. They finde in Hony &amp; Sugar, as veuemous impuritie as in Arſnicke, and in Roſes, Violets, Balme, Betony, gold, Siluer, &amp;c. there be impurities. They alſo finde by this arte, as there is nothing ſo good, but it hath in it alſo ſome impure thing and vnholſom, which they ſeparate from the pure, ſo alſo there is nothing ſo vnholſome, perilous nor venemous, but it hath in it alſo ſome good thing and pure which hath vertue and power to cure and helpe thoſe diſeaſes and hurtes which be cauſed and procured by them and by others alſo. As out of Quickſiluer is drawen medicine which can helpe diſeaſes by him cauſed, and by other meanes alſo. They finde in Arſenicke excellent medicine for diuers griefes. So Lead hath in it remedie for thoſe diſeaſes which bee cauſed and bread in the Miners of Leade. Out of Tartar alſo is drawen excellent medicines for thoſe diſeaſes which come of the Tartar of Wine, and ſo forth of others. Therefore all diſeaſes do proceede of their impure Seedes, which are indowed with ſcience and knowledge of generation

and tranſplantation of impure fruits, vz. of ſickneſſe and diſeaſes, according and agreeable to their gift and ſcience: Which do appeare and proceede into action by ſeparation, breache of vnitie, peace, concord and agreement, whereby they are inabled to ſtriue for the ſuperioritie wt nature &amp; pure ſeedes in mans body. Seeing therefore yt firſt original of diſeaſes in man did proceede frō the breach of vnitie, therefore it muſt needes be that all health muſt conſiſt only in vnitie. And in and by this vnitie health is to be ſought, and not in contrarietie, as the Ethnikes doe.
            
            
               
                  Chapter third. Of the vniuerſall Medicine, And how the darke ſpeaches of the writers thereof, did deceaue couetous men, wherby the right vſe of this Phiſicke was not vnderſtoode, but by abuſe it grewe to bee deſpiſed.
               
                  THE firſt of the Medicines aforeſayde of the auncient Phiſicke which is the vniuerſall Medicine, is ſuch, as by that onely, all and al maner diſeaſes of what ſort and kinde ſoeuer

they be, are cured. It is ſo perfect, temperat, pure and incorruptible, that it is able to correct, amende aud conſume all corruptions in mans body, euen as fire doth conſume the impure part, and ſeparateth it from the pure. It increaſeth the vitall ſpirites, and defendeth and preſerueth the body from corruption, becauſe it is ſeparated from all corruptible ſubſtance, from all qualities of heate, colde, &amp;c. It is not moyſt, could, drie nor hotte, but it is Aethereall, ſeparated from the inferiour Elements: and it is of an incorruptible nature in reſpect of the bodie from whome it is taken. And becauſe it is agreeable with our Anima (the Medium aforeſayd) it nouriſheth, fortifieth and ſtrengtheneth it, whereby it is made able to digeſt, conſume and expell, all the corruption and impedimentes of mans body, wherewith it is ouerwhelmed and let, that it was not able to exerciſe, performe and accompliſh his office, duetie and actions. If this naturall liuely fire in man like to the Aethereal fire, were not continually nouriſhed, it would conſume it ſelfe and alſo that is ingendered of it. Therefore when nature in the ſtomacke hath ſeparated the pure from the impure, of meates which we eate, and of our drinke, hee doth expell the impure partes by their proper

paſſages, but it reteineth and keepeth the fine and pure bodies, that be the cariers of the heauenly vertues, for nouriſhments of two ſorts, the one is of all the members of the body, the which nouriſhment alſo is ſeparated into the nouriſhment of the three ſubſtanties, whereon we conſiſt. That is of our Salt, Sulphur and Mercury. The other which is the liquor of the heauenly Luna, is the nouriſhmeut of our naturall fire or Anima. But if this be oppreſſed, ſtopped, or let of his operation or working by the corruptiō of our bodies, then is it to be nouriſhed, holpen &amp; fortified with this Philoſophical and Aethereal medicine, in which is no groſſeneſſe, impuritie, nor any thing ſuperfluous. And our Anima liuely and naturall fire doth take and receiue to it this Aethereall medicine, vertue, and heauenly power like to it ſelfe, Whereby it is holpen, ſtrengthened and made able to bee deliuered from his impediments and lettes, and to conſume and expell ſuperfluitics of the bodie, whereby the body is compelled to agree and to bee changed into the like nature, voyde and clean from corruption and ſuperfluitie. Becauſe nature delighteth to bee ioined with her like, with peace rather then with warre, with vnitie and concord, rather then with diſcord. And

all naturall bodies deſire in their kindes to be perfected: which naturall deſire is the cauſe of all perfection. This Medicine Vnary, among the Philoſophers and Chymicall Phyſitions, is called by diuers and many names, and couered vnder diuers parables &amp; darke kinde of ſpeaches, which brought the right vſe of this Arte into obliuion, and deceiued worldly men, and brought many from rich eſtate to extreme beggery. For whereas the Philoſophers were louers of wiſdom and not of the world, nor of worldly riches, but deſired to haue ternam atque quaternam beatitudinem, vz. mentem ſanam in corpore ſano. Therefore they vſed this vniuerſall medicine, wherewith they diſgeſt and expell the corruptions out of their naturall bodyes, wherby the body was ſo prepared, that therein was made a perfect vnion betweene Corpus, Anima &amp; Spiritus, and tranſitus ab extremo perfecto per medium ad imperfectum. Whereby the body was made ſubiect to the ſoule, whereof ſeperatio mentis à corpore might enſue. This ſurely they accounted pureſt Golde and chiefeſt riches, as appeareth aſwell by other Philoſophers, as by them that write of this arte. But they that did write of this Medicine, did it ſo couertly,

that men thought that thoſe Philoſophers promiſed in their writinges mountaynes of Golde, and ſuch a Stone or fixed matter that could conuert and turne al other baſe metals into materiall Gold, wherein (I thinke) they were greatly deceiued. For though ſome ſay that they doe finde by experience, howe to take out of an ounce of Gold, a ſmall quantity, wherewith they wyll turne an Dunce of Duick ſiluer or Leade into perfect Golde, yet they get nothing thereby, for by this meanes they make no more Gold, then that weight of Gold was, ftō whence they tooke their medicine, becauſe the medicin had no more goldiſh nature, then ſerued onely for an ounce, therefore could giue no more to others, but may ſlightly colour more metall, but then it is no Golde. The probable and likely reaſons of concockting, digeſting, purging and ſeparating of the rawe and impure mettals, and ſo to make them pure by arte, as nature in the earth doth make perfect Golde and ſiluer, by conquocting and purging of Sulphur and Mercury, becauſe arte is the folower of Nature, hath deceaued and vndon many men. But if there may be ſuch trāſmutation made into gold, as men imagine and hope for, yet I would aduiſe no man, to ſtudy this Arte to

that end, nor yet to aſſay or practiſe that way, leaſt he doe repent to late, as others haue don before. For in my opinion, the Philoſophers Gold is ſuch a temperate medicine as I haue declared, which in deede is Aſtrum ſeperated from his impediments and groſſe ſubſtance, and brought to ſuch puritic that it worketh in mans body, euen as the vertue and power of the Starres worke in any matter prepared therefore, by nature. For this cauſe the Philoſophers called the Mynerall diſeaſes and inſtrmities of mans body, by the name of imperfect metals, as of Leade or Saturne, of Coper or Venus, of Iron or Mars, &amp;c. like as the Aſtrologians doe, aſwell by reaſon of their place in mans body, as for their nature and properties. For there be double Excrements in mans body, the one proceding of his Balme which is his Gold, the other proceeding of nouriſhment. The excrements comming of his Gold be called Myuerall excrements, of the likeneſſe of the droſſe which is about the Gold, before it be fyned with Antimony. Theſe Mints are as it were Starres or Seedes, therefore they make influencies &amp; blomings, which are the fruites of Starres and Seedes. Therefore they call bealth and ſickneſſe in man, Minerals, that is the fruits

of man. Such diſeaſes in mans Gold are called Mynerall diſeaſes, which be purged onely with Mynerall Medicines. For Mynerall excrements are onely purged with Minerall medicins, which conſiſt in the vniuerſall medicine and in the tinctures of Gold, Mercury &amp; Antimony, which purge mans Balme▪ and remooueth it from all filth, which being purged, all other filth will eaſely be voyded. But if theſe myneral excrements be not purged, then they hinder the operation and working of mans Gold or Balme, into the three Principia, of mans body aforeſayd. Whereof followeth their corruption, and of the corruption of the Salts in man, followe Boyles, Vlcers, Impoſtumes &amp; griefes not outwardly diſcerned, moſt paynefull, &amp;c. So that whē any man yt had any of theſe infirmities, was brought to perfect temper by this vniuerſall medicine, then they ſaid, that thoſe imperfect metals were turned into Golde. And by this meanes, was this great treaſure of medicine hidden, ſo that very fewe Phiſitians and profeſſors of Philoſophie did vnderſtand it, though the Philoſophere themſelues in their writings exhorted al men that did reade their bookes, that they ſhould not credit the bare letters of their writings, but ſhould rather

make an allegorical expoſition thereof. This ſeeking of materiall golde by this Arte, did bring it out of the right vſe of phiſick, and did (as I ſaid) bryng many rich folke to extreme beggery, whereby they grewe to ſophiſtication of mettalles, and ſo when they had waſted their owne ſubſtance they proceeded to exerciſe deceite, lying and deuiſes to bring others into like ſtate &amp; caſe vnto them ſelues, which mooued princes in their countreyes to make Lawes agaynſt Multiplyers as they were termed.
               The auncient Chymicall Phyloſophers and Phiſitions, did vſe ſuch darke ſpeeches and parables in their writings, becauſe Secretes are to be reueyled onely to the Godly, and vnto the children of doctrine and knowledge, and vnto the wiſe, therefore they did write vnto ſuch, that the ſecrets might be hidden from the vngodly, fooliſh, ſlouthfull and vnthankefull hypocrites, whereby the wiſe and diligent with trauayle and labour might attaine to the vnderſtanding thereof, as one of them ſayde, it is not meete to prouide for a man, a Pigion, and to roſt it for him and alſo to put it vnto his mouth, or chawe it for him. The auncient Aegyptians did vſe no letters in holy and ſecret matters, but pictures,

figures and charects grauen of things and beaſtes, leaſt the Secrets and myſteries ſhould be prophaned among the vulgare people. Such was the maner of the wiſe men of the oldeſt age, to deliuer the profund and deep inquiſition and ſearch of wiſedom, by allegogories of ſecret Letters, and by Myſteries. Therefore all the wrytings of the auncient Philoſophers and Poets are full of Riddles, darke ſpeeches and parables, to auoyde the contempt of the common people. Such were the often teaching of our ſauiour Chriſt. So in the Primatiue Church, thoſe that were Catechymeni and Energymeni, and thoſe that had penance enioyned them, might heare the Pſalmes and the reading of the holy Scriptures, but they might not be preſent at the miniſtration of the Sacraments, nor at the holy workes which were done afterward, but they onely were preſent which were thought worthy.
               
                  ¶ An example by an excellent particular Chymicall Medicin, vnder the title, to conuert ☽ into ☉
                  TAke the greene dragon and bath hym in warme liquor, ſo long vntill all his blood be come out of his vaynes, take

out the purer part of this blood according to arte, and diſtill it, then c
                        •
                     hobate the ſame three time, take this liquor and diſtill it with the Liuer of Mars, and keepe it for a precious thing. For it will turne the Calces of Luna, into perfect Sol, that is to ſay, it will turne ſiluer into Gold.
                  But the true meaning hereof is, that this medicin will conuert and turne thoſe partes of mans body affected, which be ſubiect or attributed to the moone into perfect health.
               
            
            
               
                  Chapter 4. Of the Medicine Ternarij or perticularis.
               
                  BVt becauſe this vniuerſall medicin and knowledge thereof is gr
                     •
                  ūted of ye almighty God but vnto very fewe, and is rather to be wiſhed and praied for, then to be looked for, therfore the particular medicin called Ternarii, as is aforeſayd, is diligently to be laboured for and ſearched out, which often times performeth and worketh the effet of the vniuerſall medicin, euen in greeuous diſeaſes, in conſuming the impure ſeedes of

diſeaſes, and in confirming and fortifying the power of our inwarde and naturall Balme. This medicin of Ternarii cōſiſteth in ye three ſubſtāties, which are to be foūd in euery body▪ that is to ſay in Sal, Sulphur and Mercuri. For as eche body is compounded of theſe three, ſo they be cauſes of all diſeaſes and not humors. In theſe three conſiſteth all mans health and ſickneſſe, as long as they doe agree together, the body is in health, but as ſoone as they diſagree, and vnitie is broken betweene them, and if any of them be exalted or breake vnitie the body is ſicke. Therefore there be three generall kinds of diſeaſes, and eche of them haue their eſpeciall ſortes of infirmities, as there be ſundry ſorts of Sal, Sulphur and Mercuri of diuers and ſundry natures. There be like wiſe three kinds of medicine required, and eche kinde of ſondry nature to preſerue or reſtore mans body to health. So that if any of theſe three be exalted to much and paſſe their meane, or breake vnitie, he muſt be amended and reduced to perfect ſtate by his owne kinde, and not by a contrary kind, by way of traſmutation. If the diſeaſe be mixed or compounde of any of theſe (for there is no diſeaſe almoſt but is mixed by ſome meanes, yet it hath one of theſe

three that is chiefe) then muſt ſuch diſeaſe bee holpe with oue or two of theſe taken out of ſome other fit body or ſubſtance. per propriū ad ſuum innatum, becauſe nature cou
                     •
                  teth his like nature, and deſireth much to be coupled ioyned and chaunged into his like. This naturall deſire is cauſe of all perfection. As long therefore as the three ſubſtanties aforeſayd, doe abide in vnitie peace and concord in mās body, and in their owne proper degrees, without pride doing their office, their body continueth in health. But becauſe nothing is perpetual nor continueth in eſtate long, among creatures conſiſting of fleſhe, therefore by reaſon of the diuerſitie of the giftes, vertue and power which be in them, and by reaſon of the impure ſeedes ioyned with our noriſhment, they abide not long in their office, they abide not long in their degrees, they exalt themſelues, they breake vnitie peace and concorde, the badd is ſeperated from the obedience and mixture of the good: which breach of vnitie and ſeperation doth ſhew thoſe ſickneſſes and deſeaſes in mans body, which before by reaſon of the vnitie concorde and obedient mixture could not breake forth appeare nor be made manifeſt. The which thinges as they come to paſſe in man, that is Mycrocoſmus,
                  
ſo doe they likewiſe in the great world. Which therefore is called Mycrocoſmus or the little world, becauſe after God had made all thinges in the great world of nothing, he made man in whom ſpiritually be conteyned all thoſe thinges that is the properties of all thoſe thinges which bee really in the greate worlde, as the auncient Philoſophers haue taught by theſe and like wordes, homo naturaliter habet naturam omnium tincturarum. Therefore that this Mycrocoſmus may bee inwardly knowne to the Phiſition, he had neede to haue lumen naturae, that is the knowledge of thinges in the great world, how all of them doe grow increaſe be chaunged and dye, whereby he may by the inſight of his minde vnderſtand the inward and hidden nature of man. Wherefore he that would perfectly knowe what inward thinges be in man, he had need to compare the vertues and properties of the naturall things in the great worlde with the inward thinges of man. As you may perceiue by wine (for this purpoſe) which as long as his ſpirite doth abide in him mingled with the tarte vineger in vnitie and peace, the wine is ſounde pleaſaunt and perfect, but as ſoone as the ſpirite of the wine is ſeperated from the mixture of the ſharpe vineger,

then the vineger doth appeare is manifeſted and may bee taſted. Likewiſe when the vineger is ſeperated from the tartar, thē doth the tartar appeare. So is it in all thinges when they growe to corruption putrifaction and diſſolution, then the good that was in them is ſeperated from the bad ſeedes, the bad doe no longer abide in obedience of the good, but haue broken peace, concord, vnitie and obedience, whereby thinges doe growe to corruption &amp; death. This auncient Chimnicall Phiſicke doth teach ſuch ſeperation of the good from the bad out of all thinges, and to make them manifeſt to viſible and palpable experience, which the Ethnicke Phiſicke hath nothing to doe with, nor his followers hath any ſkill thereof, yet they barke and bite againſt this ſkill through their ignoraunce.
            
            
               
                  Chapter fifth. How deſeaſes ought to be cured by peace and not by diſcord in mans body.
               
                  THerefore, as when the ſeede of the diſeaſe or corruption in man is ſeperated from his temperature cō
                  corde and vnitie of the body, or of

the good ſéede in the body, then the bodie feeleth griefe &amp; ſickneſſe: ſo on the other ſide, to ſeperate the impure ſeed that hach gotten the mayſterie from the pure that is mayſtered, is the way to get health, therefore ſweate which is the ſeperatiō of the vncleane frō the cleane is wholeſome, for it purgeth by the pores and tranſpirations, ſo it maketh the good ſeede able to mayſter the badd, by ſeperating the bad ſeedes in vapors, through the pores and tranſpirations in the tyme of ſweating, and with the ſweate, whereby the vnitie and concorde is reſtored in the body, whileſt nature and the good ſeedes bee made ſo ſtrong that the badd doe not exalt themſelues aboue the other. Likewiſe al medicines miniſtred into the body, ought to bee ſuch as haue propertie to bring the ſicke body to vnitie and concord: therfore like is to be miniſtred to that which is like in our nature, which order doth depende vpon the true Center of vnion. And contrary thinges are not to be cured by their contraries, vnlike to our nature, which maner of proceeding is from the Center of diſcorde, contrary to the Center of vnitie, and therefore a falſe Center. For ſeeing that all thinges doe hang together in one chayne (as is aforeſayd) &amp; man is partell of that chaine,

and Mycrocoſmus hauing in it the properties of the great world ſpiritually, therefore there is in the greate worlde, that which is agreeable to the nature of man, in what parte ſoeuer it be weakened, or not able to reſiſt his enemy, which becauſe of the conueniency and agreement with our nature, doth deſire to be ioyned with it. Wherefore it muſt be miniſtred in due order, fineſſe and proportion, it is able to fortifie, comfort and ſtrengthen nature and our naturall balme, and it wilbe as it were a weapon for nature againſt the enemy or diſeaſe, whereby nature by him ſelf wil become and be his owne phiſition. Therefore the Phiſition ought to miniſter ſuch things, which nature in the place afflicted doeth require for the cure that is like to it ſelfe, and not contrary qualities, ſuch as will make peace in the body and not warres, vnitie and not diſcord, ſuch as will helpe nature and not trouble it, and will ſtrengthen it and not weaken it. Such medicines for the loue and liking they haue to our nature afflicted haue a deſire to be ioyned and coupled together, as a hongry and thirſtie man deſireth meate or drinke, which nouriſh well. And as one friend coueteth and deſiereth the company of his deere frends long abſent, which natural loue

is the cauſe of perfection. Therefore his proper and ordinary medicine, is to be miniſtred to eche thing. So ſhall we not neede of the Ethnikes directories. And ſuch like are to be ioyned to their like in right Anotomie. We ought not to ſeeke helpe in things contrarie and repugnant: who findeth medicine for the Liuer in Gratian, Agarick, or Colocinthis, or who findeth medicin for the Gall in, Manna, Hony, Sugar or Polipody? therefore like are to be ioyned with their like in right Anotomy, Miniſtering of contraries perteyneth rather to diet then to medicin, and they may ſerue to mittigate the payne, but not to take away the roote of the diſeaſe. Humors and qualities, to the which the folowers of the Ethnikes doe ſo much cleane, and in the whiche they ſpende their ſtudy and labour, are but onely dead accidents, without power of lyfe. They be conditions, signes, tokens, and as it were onely flowers and colours of diſeaſes and not the very matter, cauſe, ſubſtance, or nature of the diſeaſe, they are cauſed and not the cauſes. Wherefore when they go about to cure the humor or qualitie, they fiatter the payne and griefe, but they leaue the diſeaſe vncured. For the ſignes of thyngs are not the matter or ſubſtance it ſelfe. Therefore

he that wil be a perfect Phiſition, muſt know eche diſeaſe by his right Anatomie, that is to ſay, by the matter, property and nature of the true ſubſtance of the diſeaſe, as which of the three ſubſtances haue broken vnitie, and not by the ſigne of it. Alſo he muſt haue the right Anatomie of all diſeaſes, and of all naturall thynge before his eyes, ſo ſhall he apply to eche infirmitie his apt remedy. For by the concordance and agreement of the Anatomy of the herbe or other naturall thyng for medicine, and of the diſeaſe, the Phiſition knoweth what things haue affinity together, and ought to be coupled and ioyned together in vnitie. For the right Anatomy cōſiſteth not in cutting of the body, but in the knowledge of the Amitie, concord and nature of all naturall externe things, with man, which doe agree, imbrace and receaue eche other, and cō
                  cord together in mutuall agreement, in vertue, power, propertie and eſſenſe, to defend nature. So that by the right concord of theſe two Anatomies, vz. of the diſeaſe and of the medicine, true cure doth proceede and growe, whereby is declared, that lyke are to be ioyned with ther like, &amp; like are cured with their lyke: and that all health conſiſteth in vnitie and agreement, in which of neceſſitie

health is to be ſought for. And that ſickeneſſe can not be taken away from the third creature by Binarius the Author of diſcorde and contrarietie, but by vnari ruling equally in three.
            
            
               
                  Chater 6. Of the medicin Binarii or Vulgaris, howe iniurious it is to the body.
               
                  By theſe aforeſayd it doeth appeare how the medicines of the auncient Phiſicke doe diſagree with thoſe medicines which be commonly in vſe, which be conteined vnder the third kinde of Medicine called Binarii or vulgaris, For theſe medicines do more agree with the body (becauſe bodyes are nouriſhed with bodyes) then with Anima wherein Fons vitae conſiſteth. This medicine helpeth little to long life, or to the reliefe of Anima, if it be feeble or hindred in his worke. Becauſe theſe medicines bee miniſtred with their bodies, the worke vertue and power in them that ſhould do good is hindered: ſo that it doth litle good, eſpecially in partes of the body, a farre of frō the Stomache. For all things that ſhoulde ſerue for medicine, ſhould be purged firſt from

their groſſe ſubſtance, becauſe whileſt the heauenly vertues be wrapped, hidden and clogged in the matter or ſubſtance of their bodies, they abyde and cleaue faſt to them, &amp; can not eaſely be parted a ſunder, vnleſſe nature haue help thereunto prepared by Arte, which may ſeparate the pure from the impure, otherwiſe the working of that heauenly vertue is hindered. For it is the vertue of eche thing that is medicinable and not the body. So that ſeeing ſeparation of the pure from the impure muſt needes be made in the ſtomache, if it be not made before, becauſe euery thing hath his corruption ioyned with it, and becauſe the vertues of eche thing be ſmall in quantitie, &amp; tyed and clogged with the maſſe of his body, (as is aforeſayd) it is better this ſeperation be made before the medicine come neere to the ſtomache then after, in the ſicke mans Stomache which is to weake to make ſuch ſepation. Beſides this, by ſuch groſſe and rawe medicine, the patient receiueth rather nouriſhment then medicine, centrarie to their owne rules, Omne medicamentum quod tranſit in alimentum, ceſſant eſſe medicamentum. For when the medicine miniſtred with his body or ſubſtance, commeth into the Stomach, it is ſeparated into treble nouriſhment,

that is of our Salt, Sulphur and Mercury, and into double excrement. So that when theſe medicines be rightly conſidered and compared together, there ſeemeth to bee as great diuerſitie betweene the rawe and groſſe medicines, and thoſe that be purged by fire, as is betwixt the true doctrine of Chriſt and the Romiſh doctrine, For as the doctrine of Chriſt for the health of the Soule, is altogether ſpirituall, and the holy Scriptures of God do inſtruct the ſoule of man and ſpeake to it, whereby the euill affections and the actions and filthy workes of the body be taken away, and amendement of life foloweth. So do theſe auncient medicines for the helth of the body conſiſt in heauenly vertues, which are to be miniſtred and ioyned with the liuely Spirits of mans body, that they may therby be fortifyed and made ſtrong, or rectified &amp; brought to vnitie, whereby foloweth the help and cure of the diſeaſes of the body. And as the Romiſh religiō is mixed with impurities, &amp; ſtādeth in outward ceremonies &amp; traditiōs, corporal exerciſes which be lets to the works of the ſpirite, whyleſt it is occupied about them. So theſe corrporall and groſſe medicines, which ſerue for the body, conſiſt in bodyly groſſe and rawe ſubſtances, whereby the

worke of the heauenly vertues be let and hindered. And theſe bodies doe reſiſt digeſtion, which is occupied about them, by meanes whreof the weake and faint partes that deſire reliefe, can not drawe to them theſe vertues for their ſuccour, being bound and faſt tyed to their groſſe ſubſtance. And euen as the Romiſh religion teacheth that in the Euchariſt, there is no ſubſtance of bread and wine, but onely accidents, and that our bodies be nouriſhed with the accidents of the Sacrament, euen ſo the Ethnicke Phiſitions and their folowers doe teache, that accidents, vz. heate, cold, &amp;c. be cauſes of al diſeaces. And that by them diſeaſes are cured, and health reſtored, whereby they attribute vim vitae, to accidents &amp; dead qualities which are cauſed, raiſed and ſtirred vp, by other things, &amp; bee them ſelues onely Simptomata morborum. So that in curing thoſe accidents and qualities, they doe as if a man would goe about to ſtop the flame and ſmoke of the fire, and leaue the hot coles burning.
            
            
               
                  Chapter ſeuen. One cauſe why the Author did write this treatiſe.
               I Was the laſt Parliament time before this that is now ſommoned at the table of a reuerend

Biſhoppe of this land, which was not vnſkilfull in Phiſicke, in the companie of a Phiſition, which inueying againſt this auncient Phiſicke, by the name of Paracelſus his Phiſicke, ignorantly attributing to him the firſt▪ inuention thereof, pleaſed himſelf and ſome of his audience, in telling that the ſame Phiſicke, had no ground nor foundation, neither any being. Whereupon he tolde a tale that a man came to a Phiſition and ſayd to him that he was ſicke, but he could not tell where, neither how he tooke his ſickneſſe, nor how it held him. The Phiſition aunſwered him, that he▪ had a Garden he could not tell where, it was full of ſimples he could not tell their properties, and that he would helpe him but he could not tell when: And concluded that this Paracelſicall Phiſicke (as he called it) was like, in that, it was vaine, had no ground, nor being. I aunſwered him with an other tale of a Poet, which diſdayning that Paynters and Poets were compared together and ioyned in one prouerbe, pictoribus atque poetis quidlibe
                        •
                      addendi ſemper ſunt equa poteſtas, came to a 
                     •
                  ūning Painter and aſked of him whether he could paint a man, ſhooting at a birde ſitting vppon the top of a tree, with a Sunne, and the bird therwith

killed and falling downe, yet the man ſhould not be ſeene nor appeare. The Paynter aunſwered he could doe all that he required, ſauing the noyſe of the Gunne and the ſmell of the powder: which being excepted, the price was agreed on, the daye ſet for the deliuerie of the worke and for the payment of the money, and bandes made of each ſide for performance of couenauntes on both ſides. The Poet at the day prefixed ſeeing and vewing the peece of Paynting, could not finde the man with the Gunne, but all the reſt of the worke he found very artificially wrought: whereupon he entereth the Paynters bande into the lawe: He pleadeth performance of couenauntes: the condition of the band being read and the paynting vewed, the Gunner could not bee founde: whereupon the action was like to paſſe againſt the Paynter. Then ſayd he, it is parcell of the condition of ye band that the Gunner ſhould not be ſeene: But yet ſayd he, turne ouer the leafe, which cunningly was couched in the peece of painting: then appeared the Gunner very artificially paynted, and alſo a greate ſorte of the fables and tales of the Poets, before his time very cunningly wrought. And among them he had made very artificially a little Ant or Piſiner,

with a Poets hood about his necke, creeping out of a Caue vnder a greate huge Mountaine. I left the applying of the tale in both the po
                     •
                  utes thereof to him. I do confeſſe that newe vayne confuſed and vnperfect doctrine, without grounde is odiouſe and a ſigne of r
                     •
                  ſhe wit and greate follie. But ſeeing that both ſides do clayme trueth, perfection, aunciantie and continuance, on their ſides their methoodes and opinions beeing ſomewhat briefly layd abroad to the indifferent Reader, and after the originall progreſſion and continuaunce of both theſe Phiſickes likewiſe being ſet downe, I doubt not but he wilbe able to iudge hetwixt them. The chiefe pointes therefore be theſe.
            
            
               
                  Chapter eight. Certaine differenſes, betweene the auncient Phiſicke and the Phiſicke of the Heathens.
               
                  THE Ethnick Philoſophers lay the foundation of their Philoſophie vppon Ariſtotle a Heathen and ignoraunt Mayſter and teacher of the true knowledge

of God and of his trueth.
               The Chymicall Philoſopher layeth the foundatiō of his Philoſophie in Gods booke, and alloweth none other principles of Philoſophie, but ſuch as be there ſounde, or ſuch as may bee deduced out of the ſame, or bee not contrary to it.
               2 The Ethnicke Philoſophers aſcribe the efficient chiefe and principall cauſe of thinges vnto nature, which is in them, wherby they tye and bind God to the ſecond cauſe, and take away his prouidence ouer his creatures.
               The Chymicall Philoſophers affirme, that all nature of things be onely inſtrumentall cauſes, not working of them ſelues nor principally, but depending wholly vpon the power and commaundement of God.
               3 The Ethnicke Phiſitions doe ſeeke with mortall medicines (that is to ſay) ſuch medicines as haue corruption ioyned with immortalitie, whereof muſt needes followe diſſolution, whereof commeth death, to cure and helpe the heauenly and Aethereall vertue in mans body. And they ſeeke to cure the materiall body ſubiect to the worker and mouer, and leaue the worker and mouer and his arte and cunning vnthought on, and not prouided

for, becauſe his arte and cunning is not to them knowne.
               The Chymicall Phiſition teacheth for the perfect Philoſophicall medicine, to ſeperate the gift of nature, the life, the Science, cunning and arte 
                     ••
                   the worker &amp; mouer, (which he calleth immortall) and the artificer worker and mouer, in a metaphiſicall body, from the corruptible materiall body, ſubiect to the worker, into which it moueth and worketh therewith 
                     •
                  o cure and helpe the Aethereall and heauenly vertue &amp; power in man, which is the ſubiect wherein life conſiſteth and ſhineth, by whoſe power and vertue the body ſubiect to the mouer is preſerued and maintayned, and by it reſtored, when the corruption thereof doth oppreſſe, let, and hinder his operation. So that it appeareth that the followers of the Ethnicke Phiſitions in miniſtring of their medicines, do as if they would go about to reſtore a fire, where is remayning a fewe ſparkles, vnder greene wood, by heaping on more greene wood, thinking therby to make the ſparkles to kindle and burne, but they will not put more fire to the ſparkles, nor yet vſe any meanes to blowe then▪ to make them burne. And as if they would miniſter medicines to a ſicke mans houſe

wherein he dwelleth, and not to the man that is ſicke.
               4 The Etnick Phiſitions lay their foundation vpon the falſe Center of Binarii and dualitie, which is the Roote of contrarietie diſcorde and diſſention, therefore moſt commonly they teache that contrary things are to be cured by their contraries.
               The Chimicall Phiſition layeth his foundation vpon the true Center of Vnarii or vnion, which is the roote of concord and vnitie. So that when any contrarietie in mans body that is to ſay, any infirmitie or weakeneſſe of nature muſt be remooued or amēded, which did riſe, beginne and growe by reaſon of the contrarietie and inwarde diſſention of the three ſubſtanties of Sal, Sulphur, and Mercury, whereon mans body conſiſteth, which haue broken vnity and concord among them ſelues, or exaited themſelues one aboue an other, it muſt be done with peace and concord, and not with diſſention &amp; diſcord. One diſeaſe may not be added to another. And the Monarchie of mans body muſt be preſerued by harmony, conſent and agreement, and not by Mono
                     •
                  nachie. Therefore the Medicine ought to be ſuch as may bring the ſicke body to vnitie, which can not be done by Binarii
                  
the author of diſcord and contrarietie
                     •
                  , but by vnarii ruling equally in three. But this doctrine the folowers of the Ethnikes can not digeſt, becauſe they knowe not the three ſubſtanties aforeſayd, though by arte they may be made manifeſt out of eche thing to the eye and touche: neither doe they knowe the concordance and agreement of the three in one, nor their exaltation.
               5 The followers of the Ethnicke Phiſitions, be ruled by the doctrine and principles of Galen, Auicen, and ſuch other.
               The Chymicall Phiſition in his phiſicke firſt and principally reſpecteth the worde of of God, and acknowlegeth it to be his gifte, next he is ruled by experience, that is to ſay, by the knowledge of three ſubſtanties, whereof eche thing in the great world and man alſo conſiſteth, that is to ſay, by their ſeuerall Sal, Sulphur and Mercury, &amp; by their ſeueral properties, vertues and natures, by palpable and viſible experience. And when he knoweth the three ſubſtanties and all their properties in the great worlde, then after ſhall he knowe them in man. For man is Microcoſmus for this cauſe, that hee might haue the good and bad ſickneſſe &amp; health of the great world. The right way to come to this knowled is to trie

all things by the fire: for the fire teacheth the ſcience and arte of Phiſicke. It is the Phiſitions maiſter: it teacheth the Phiſition experience, by digeſting, fixing, exalting, reſoluing, reducing, compounding, and ſuch like. By this experience ſhall he find out the three ſubſtanties of all creatures in the worlde, of what nature, facultie, propertie and condition they be of. So ſhall he knowe all things by viſible and palpable experience, ſo that the true proofe and tryal ſhal appeare to his eyes &amp; touched with his hands. So ſhall he haue ye three Principia, ech of them ſeparated frō
                  ▪ the other, in ſuch ſort, yt he may ſee them, &amp; touch them in their efficacie and ſtrength, then ſhal he haue eyes, where with the phiſition ought to looke and reade with al. Then ſhal he haue that he may taſte and not before. For thē ſhall he know, not by his owne braines, nor by reading, or by reporte, or heareſay of others, but by experience, by diſſolution of Nature, and by examyuing and ſearch of the cauſes, beginnings and foundations of the properties and vertues of thinges, which he ſhall finde out not to be attributed to colde or heate, but to the properties of the three ſubſtanties of each thing and his Arcanum. Then may he vſe Lumen Naturae, and by meanes of that

vſe his eyes in thoſe thinges that hee to bee ſeene. This is the ſure way as one of their owne coate ſayth, it is in vayne to leaue the vſe and helpe of ſences for reaſons ſake. And an other of the ſame ſtamp, ſayth: Experience is the mayſteries of thinges.
               6 The followers of the Ethnickes in the nature of Simples, as Hearbes, Plantes, Rootes, &amp;c. father themſelues vpon Gallen, Meſue, dioſcorides, &amp;c. and ſay it is written that in their Bookes. So that who is learned in their Bookes may proceeve Doctor of their Phiſicke.
               The Chymicall Phiſition trieth all thinges by fire, whereby the vertue, nature, and propertie of each thing appeareth to the palpable and viſible experience. By this is foūd in Honey a venomous tartiſ
                     •
                  neſſe, and much filthineſſe in Surgar. And in Arſenicke excellent good medicine, wholeſome and frendly for man
                     •
                   body, when the impuritie is ſeperated and caſt away. By this meanes bee found eſpeciali thinges euen of one kinde only to differ from an other of the ſame kind. As the Roſine of one Countrey is not of that nature as the Roſine of an other Countrey. Wheate that groweth vpon ſome grounde hath the propertie of Garlicke, or ſome other

propertie according to the nature of the ſoyle or grounde either wholeſome or vnwholeſome. And the things growing vpon Mountaines doe differ from their like, or from thinges of the ſame kind growing on the plaine. And generally ech Countrey moſt commonly hath his proper deſeaſe (beſides them that be cauſed of Influencies) by reaſon of ye foode which wee receiue for nouriſhment, either of the vegetables which receiue their nouriſhment of the reſolued ſpirites of the Myneralles, or of the Animals which be nouriſhed of the vegetables, in the ſoyle wherupon they feede. Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that if a Phiſition do follow the opinion of Writers of other Nations, or be cunning onely in his owne Countrey and Region, he ſhal erre in his medicine. So that Nature made manifeſt by fire and the right applying it to medicine, maketh a Phiſition according to this Arte. He that liſteth to leane to Bookes, let him learne of thoſe Bookes which Paracelſus hath moſt Godly and learnedly expreſſed in his Labyrinth. In compariſon of which al other Aucthorities in thoſe matters are ſmall or none. Ars Signata alſo hath his place to giue euidence of the properties of things.
               7 The Ethnickes themſelues that write

of Symples, &amp;c. meaſure (as the plowe man doth) the nature of them by their outwarde taſtes and accidentes, which periſh in digeſtion, ſo fewe outward things keepe their degrees, which the Hearbals deſcribe, for the middle bodie doth blinde the phiſition.
               The Chymicall Phiſition in triall of the nature of thinges, firſt ſpoyleth them of all their outward formes, qualities, impurities, and accidents, which be couerts and clothes of the vertues and garments, or ornaments of nature, becauſe ſuperfluities, impurities, &amp;c. doe come to bodies accidentally and not borne in them, in their firſt nature, nor bee in them radically, therefore they are fugitine, by reaſon whereof it is poſſible to ſpoyle them of their accidents, and by the fire artificiall to purge and cleanſe them, and to take away all their ſuperfluities and externe things, meete for the plowman to iudge vpon, leauing only their Arcana, inward and ſecret things remayning for the phiſition to iudge vpon. For mortification is the beginning of diſſolution and ſeparation of good from euill. Whereby the inwarde Nature and arcana thereof doeth remayne free from his accidentes which then do ſhewe the verie properties and nature of things. Aron called in engliſh Coccowpint,

hath a very hotte taſte in the leaues and roote. Wormewod hath a bitter taſte, yet by light digeſtion, preparation and ſeparation of their vertues and properties from their bodies, they vaniſh away and be loſt. It is otherwiſe in Ginger, becauſe his heate is ſtable, liuely and foū
                  
                     •
                  ed in his naturall ſeede, vertue or propertie, and cleaueth to it ſtedfaſt. The Vitrum of Antimonie is without any taſt, yet for all that is vehement Purgation. Lead like wiſe hath no taſte, yet notwithſtanding, a pleaſaunt ſweete Sugar wilbe drawen out of it, comfortable or pourging medicines, or ſuch as cauſe ſleepe, can neuer be found out by their taſte of heate or cold. The practiſers in this arte doe finde by experience by healpe of the fire, that eche thing hath two natures, that is occultum and manifeſtum, and that manifeſtum is commonly contrarie to occultum. By this meanes of the fire, they find Quicſiluer in manifeſto is cold and moyſte. and within his occultum, is hotte and drie, And farder that in ech thing is good and bad: of the bad doe diſeaſes riſe, by the good being ſeparated from the bad, the ſame diſeaſes are cured &amp; holpen. This good thing is Arcanū
                   of that thing, and is in the inner parte of the thing in occulto, and is not taſted before ſeparation,

as in Arſnick and poyſons. And diſeaſes cauſed by Quickſiluer, Lead, or any other thing bee cured by Arcana taken out of them. Hony and Sugar haue good in manifeſto, but in occulto they haue ſharpe poyſon, which can not be taſted before ſeparation, Glaſſe is hidden in aſhes &amp; Glewe in leather, Therefore the outward taſtes of the inwarde body of any thing doeth not, nor can trie the inwarde nature, vertue or propertie of any thing, which ſhould ſerue for medicine. Euen as the Stomache doth prepare all things put into it, and diſſolueth, ſeperateth, and breaketh all the accidents of heate, colde, &amp;c. and ſearcheth out all their Arcana and ver
                     •
                  nes of the meate, becauſe all other thinges dye in the ſtomack: euen ſo the Herbe▪ Plant, &amp;c. muſt putrifie and dye in putrifaction, and bee borne againe before it be a medicine. But the ſ
                     •
                  cend life which is after putrifaction is profitable for medicine. For a Graine doth not bring forth fruite vnleſſe it bee firſt caſt into the grounde, and ſuffer putrifaction: ſo the ſtomacke leaueth nothing whole or vnputrified, but ſeperateth, digeſteth, and putrifieth all thinges put into it, but if they dye not and putrifie in the ſtomacke they doc no good: but it is a ſigne of weakeneſſe thereof. So what

ſoeuer of the Hearbes, Plantes, &amp;c. dyeth or goeth away with the life thereof (as the outwarde ornamentes doe) whatſoeuer doth not remaine after putrifaction, nor doth paſſe in regeneration that is not ſubiect to the Phiſition. Therefore thoſe thinges that let putrifaction let health. And vnleſſe all the outward thinges bee ſpoyled there can bee no knowledge of their natures. And vnleſſe all the olde nature of things doe paſſe into regeneration, there will bee no right medicine. Therefore all the Phiſitions labour and endeuour ought to be bent about the ſeperation of the pure from the impure, and about regeneration. For from thence 
                     •••
                  w Tynctur
                     •
                  s, Arcana, Quintum eſſe, in which be repoſed and hidden all miſteries, the whole foundation true labour and care of the Phiſition.
               8 The Heathen Phiſitions and their followers ſay there be fower humours in man, and according to thoſe humours they attribute to man fower complexions.
               The Chymical Phiſition ſayth, ech member hath his proper humour not like to any of the fower, but according to the c
                     ••
                  itution of the members, and their effect, ech member poſſeſſeth his owne humour. and that ech diſeaſe conſiſteth vpon one qualitie, and not vppon

two or many. And that there is but one heate, one colde, one moyſture, and one dryneſſe: becauſe it cannot bee proued that there is a dubble or treble colde, ſubſtaunce, hott, moyſt, or drie ſubſtaunce. Neither doe thoſe humours receiue any anatony, nor yet can they bee ſhewed as the three principia can. And humors are dead thinges without life or power of life.
               9 The Heathen Phiſitions and their followers take vpon them to diſcerne the deſeaſes in man, by the complexions, humors, and qualities.
               The Chymicall Phiſition teacheth, if the Phiſition couet or deſire to know the nature of mā, with al his deſeaſes, he muſt firſt know the deſeaſes of all thinges which nature ſuffereth in the greate worlde, by reducing thoſe bodies into their three ſubſtanties: So then ſhall he ſee one deſeaſe in this kinde of thing, in that kinde an other deſeaſe, but in man he ſhall ſee them all. For by the Anatomy of the three ſubſtanties, the Seedes, Rootes, foundations, cauſes, ſimilitudes, and likeneſſes of the effects, panges, griefes, and fittes, which appeare in deſeaſes &amp; ſickneſſes are knowne and eſpyed. If he ioyne theſe thinges together, he ſhall be indowed with the knowledge

of all deſeaſes. And the knowledge of the nature and effect of deſeaſes of the great world pertayneth to the Phyloſopher. Thereby therefore ſhall he bee a perfect Phyloſopher. And where the Philoſopher endeth, there beginneth the Phiſition. And he that can know the nature of man and his deſeaſes, and the efficient cauſes of them, as the Phyloſopher knoweth the cauſes of deſeaſes of externe thinges (for that which hurteth Hearbes and Plantes, &amp;c. that cauſeth the like in man) and can bring nature to that point and paſſe, that it may bee made fit and apt to helpe and cure the deſeaſe by extracting out of things in the greate worlde that which is wholeſome and fit, and by caſting away that which is vnprofitable, and knoweth the efficacie, ſtrength and vertue thereof, and doth ſo apply and miniſter the ſame, that it cureth the deſeaſe, ſuch an one is to bee accompced a Chymicall or Spagyricall Phyloſopher and Phyſition. For Chymia and Medicina may not be ſeperated aſunder, no more thē can preparation or ſeparation from knowledge or ſcience.
               10 The Heathen Phyſitions and their followers, attribute the cauſes of all deſeaſes to dead accidents, vz. to the firſt and ſeconde qualities, &amp;c. So they make no difference betwixt

fire and ſmoke, betwixt ſeedes and their fruites, betweene ſubſtanties and their accidents, betweene the thing it ſelfe and his excrements.
               The Chymicall Phyſition proueth, that there bee ſpirituall Seedes of all maner deſeaſes, indowed with liuely power, which bring forth thoſe qualities, &amp; all other fruites of deſeaſes, and their ſundry kinds of griefes in our bodies, as ye earth bringeth forth fruite by meanes of ſeedes in it. And that thoſe qualities be onely ſignes, colours and Symptomata of deſeaſes. And though ech deſeaſe be either hot or colde, &amp;c. yet they be but ſignes and conditions of the deſeaſe, and not the deſeaſe it ſelfe. But all deſeaſes are in the three ſubſtanties of Sal, Sulphur, and Mercury. For the ſpirites or ſpirituall eſſent
                     •
                  es being kindled, reſolued, ſublimed, and brought to action, doe aſcribe the cauſe of their operations and actions to thoſe principia. Yet it is to bee vnderſtanded, that ſome greeſes doe come to man which be not properly deſeaſes but leſiones or hurtes.
               11 The Heathen likewiſe meaſure their medicins according to thoſe accidentall qualities aforeſayd.
               The Chymicall Phyſitions in their medicines

conſider the eſſentiall vertues and actions of the medicines not the qualities accidentall. But the followers of the Ethnickes them ſelues in taking one hott thing before an other, as Pepper before Camamil, &amp;c. and one cold thing before an other, doe teſtifie ſufficiently that they ſeeke not heate nor cold, but Arcana which they thinke to be degrees. Therefore the Chymicall Phyſitions conſider the nature of things, and not the humors or qualities, their ſeedes and the effects of their Mechanicall ſpirites: As whether they be Attractiua, Anodymae, Abſtergentia, Aperitiua Conſtringentia contrahentes. Quale membrum principale reſpicientia: or in carne cartilagine oſſibus ſanguine Synouia, &amp;c. operantia condenſantia, conglutinantia, Corroſiua confortantia, coagulantia digeſtiua diuretica, dyaphoretica, dormire facientia diſcuſſiua expulſiua eracuantia, extenuantia, famen morentia grauedinem morētia, horrorem morentia, renouantia incidentia, incraſſantia, inflamantia, incarnatiua mundificatiua mollificatiua maturantia, mortificatiua, morbos quoſdam reſpiciētia Martialia Narcotica Nitroſulphureae nutritiua oppilantia purgatiua penetratiua, retentiua
                  
                  regenerantia repellantia repercuſſiua reſoluentia trahentia vlceratiua venenum repugnantia vomitum morentia and ſuch like. Some curing of a wounde they take things that haue propertie to bring or ingender fleſhe, without conſideration of heate or colde. And for the Dropſie thoſe thinges are to be taken which doe expell Sal reſolutum without conſideration of heate or colde. And in Purgatiōs Colocynthis doth purge without reſpect of the qualities. So in all Purgations the Ethnicks them ſelues are driuen away from their qualities accidentall. Hereby appeareth the cauſe, why the followers of the Heathen often tymes, yea after their conſultations, either knowe not what to doe, or els determine often the worſt rather thē good for their patient: as when in a Mynerall deſeaſe the toe or foote is growing towardes mortification, becauſe Balſamū humanum that ſhould keepe vnitie betweene the three principia, in that parte is oppreſſed with impediments, as Gold in his Myne, and faileth there and is not mingled with that parte, wherefore it cannot preſ
                     •
                  rue it from putrifaction: whereby that parte groweth firſt to a ſ
                     •
                  n
                     ••
                  l
                     •
                  ſſe Aduſt
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  : 
                     •
                  nd after if an vnnatural heate doe come to it, then it groweth to Gangreua:

for cure whereof the naturall Balme inwardly ought to be clenſed, and outwardly preſeruantia, as Mumy or Balme taken out of other fit matter ought to bee applyed to it. Then regenerantia and renouantia, &amp; not that paynefull cutting and mangling of that parte of the body. Likewiſe in Caukroſe and corroſiue Vlcers they pur
                     •
                  e and 
                     •
                  uacuate moyſture out of the body which ſhould mitigate the corroſiueneſſe of the Salt, and ſo increaſe the deſeaſe. Alſo when any corroding Salt in the bloud exalted hath frett through ſome vayne within the body, whereby ſometime the patient auoydeth pure bloud douneward they vſe Purgations, the next way to make an ende of them, or els that ſhipmans hoſe and ſuprema aucora of the diet, the profitableſt thing that euer they could deuiſe for their purſes, and not alwaies for their patients, whereas ſanguinē renouantia, dulcedines out of apt things rightly extracted, and potiones vulnerariae and conſolidātia ought to bee vſed. Finally, all thinges haue their power and vertue, not of the qualities but of their nature which excelleth in them. Wherfore all vertue of things are their Arcana, that they may heale the deſeaſes after that maner as they be cauſed.
               
                  12 The Ethnikes doctrines ſtandeth vpon contemplation, Sophiſtrie argument, opinion and probabilitie of reaſon without proofe, and commonly fighting againſt experience.
               The Chimical doctrine ſtandeth and foū
                  ded vpon experience ioyned with knowledge of the propertie, vertue and nature of euery thing, and not vpon the knowledge onely of his operation and working, nor vpon contemplation onely but in action, not vpon reaſon onely, but vpon experience, whereby his workes bee made perfect and trueth tried. Thereby he learneth what man is, what the medicine is, howe they agree in right Anatomy. For medicin conſiſteth in nature, ſo that nature is medicin, which ought to be learned in nature: and nature hath brought forth medicine by experience, ſo that by fire and labor the phiſition maketh nature manifeſt, wherefore without the doctrine of fire, there is none other ſchole, by the which we may learne phiſicke. So that experience and practiſe ought not to proceede of ſpeculation, but ſpeculation ought to be deriued out of practiſe. This practiſe and experience teacheth that a medicin prepared by the heate of the Sunne, hath an other power then that which is prepared by the fyre Coles and dung, and that the heat

of water and ſand doe worke diuerſly, though they be outward heates: and that one medicin or ſimple, by preparation may be made to worke diuers operations, and made fitte for diuers purpoſes, as appeareth by experience. So that probabilitie of reaſon onely againſt true and perfect proofe, found out by practiſe and experience, maketh the folowers of the Ethnikes to ſay, that all medycins prepared by this Arte, doe get a fretting corroſiue and hurtful property by the fire. For it by the fire the medicin doth get at the firſt any euill corroſiueneſſe, yet by operation and by degrees of working (to the ſkilful knowen) it ſhal not only loſe that &amp; haue it cleane takē away, but alſo it may bee brought to the higheſt degree of operation and working, and made moſt perfect like to ye Aethereall fyre, which nouriſheth and quickeneth mans body, whoſe property is to conſume all corruptions, cauſed hy the elementall fyre, and with his batefulneſſe to reſtore the naturall moyſture which was conſumed by the Elementall Fyre. In theſe things labour and diligence is required which the followers of the Ethnicks for the eaſe ſake loue not to heare of. Yet God which hath created medycine, would that the Phiſition ſhould prepare it by his labour and diligence.

For he ſelleth all things to vs for the price of our labour: &amp; he willeth vs we ſhould eate our bread in the labour and ſwette of our face. There like probabitie of reaſon without knowledge of the working by this Arte, maketh them to inueigh againſt medicins taken out of Mettals, becauſe they knowe not that before they be medicin, they are not reducible into mettall againe, but bee volatill ſpirits: and they themſelues being ignorant to get out ſuch their nature, vertue and propertie by Arte, are glad to ſeeth Golde, and ſteale in Drinke or Brothe, and to giue Golde beaten into fiue leaues in medicin, and to vſe Pearls and Precious ſtones (which be Mynerals alſo) in power (which is their body) for medicin and ſometimes the very bodies of ſome Mettals: which is contrary to the Rules of this auncient Chymycall Phiſicke, and thinke they doe much good therewith.
               13 The folowers of the Ethnikes do call the names of diſeaſes only the humors, heate, cold, &amp;c. which be onely the ſignes of the diſeaſes, not the matter or cauſe of them. So is the Agewe by them called and Agewe without any foundation in reaſon. For this name is deriued of his heate, which is onely the ſigne of the diſeaſe.
               
                  The Chimical Phiſition taketh the names of the diſeaſes of the matter, property and nature of the true ſubſtance (for all diſeaſes are in the three ſubſtanties aforeſayde) therefore the Agewes ought to be called the diſeaſe of Sulphur, of ſalt peter kendled, for this cauſe diuers diſeaſes are called tartareall diſeaſes, becauſe of the likeneſſe of the propertie, that thoſe diſeaſes haue vnto the Salt of Tartar, which is moſt ſharpe: but the followers of the Ethnikes not knowing that Salt, are ſore grieued for that name, and becauſe the Chimical Phiſitions doe lay tartar to be the cauſe of diuers diſeaſes. Or els the name is to be taken of the Medicin yt healeth &amp; cureth ye diſeaſe: ſo by this meanes euery diſeaſe hath his right name, and is rightly vnderſtanded.
               14 In the medicins of the followers of the Etnickes, no Anatomy is obſerued, but phantaſie, for qualities accidentall receaue no Anatomie.
               In the Chymycall Medicins the Anatomy of the diſeaſe and medicine doe agree and ioyne together. Hee conſidereeh the amitie, concord and agreement of nature of externe and outward things with man, and how they doe receiue and embrace eche other, ſo is hee cunning and ſkilfull of the Anatomy: and of

the concordance of the two Anatomies the Phiſition doeth growe: ſo man is taught of the great world and not of man. This Anatomy maketh a perfect Phiſition when he knoweth the great worlde, &amp; of that knoweth the diſeaſe in man, by the diſeaſe of externe things: and the▪ Medicin by the medicine, by the helpe of the Anatomie.
               15 The Medicins of the Ethnickes and their followèrs doe conſiſt in groſſe and rawe ſubſtancies, in which the vertues of the medicine be faſt tyed, bound and incumbered with hurtfull baggage, and therefore hard to be ſeparated in the ſtomache, and commonly they prouoke the pacient to vomite, or at leaſt his ſtomache abhorreth them.
               The Chymycall Medicines for the moſt part be purifyed and pourged by the fire, and the impure ſeparated from the pure. And the vertue and pure part onely miniſtred, and therefore may be receaued without offence: and that in ſmall quantitie, (becauſe the vertue of eche thing is ſmall in quantitie) but he miniſtreth not the ſubſtance and groſſe quantitie or bodyes as the other doe, vnleſſe it bee in ſome Alimentary diſeaſes.
               16 The followers of the Ethnickes in diſccening diſeaſes, &amp; the original of them are

merueilouſly trobled wt the cauſes antecedēt and conſeqnent, and with ſignes repugnant, and agreeing, and ſuch other very doubtfull cauſes, tokens and ſignes. And ſo likewiſe in curing, they proceede without reſpect of the right difference betwixt diſeaſes, vehement, long, circulated, rooted, and in places hard to bee remooued, and their contraries, with medicins groſſe, groſſe, groſſe, and ſickly, euen in ſuch rooted diſeaſes and in ſuch places.
               The Cimycall Phiſition teacheth that the right cauſes ſignes and tokens of diſeaſes, be founded in the properties of nature: their originals be by them rightly diſcerned. And that ſome diſeaſes be Caeleſtes, other ſome be Terreſtres, by reaſon of the lower and vpper globe in mans body. And they that be in the vpper globe are made mighty and vehement, and harder to be remooued then thoſe that be in the lower globe. Wherfore thoſe Alimentary diſeaſes of the lower Globe, may be cured with Arcana of vegetables, but if they be in the vpper Globe, they require medicins of higher degrees of preparation. Likewiſe if the cauſe of the diſeaſe proceede of the Minerals or metals, they muſt be cured with Arcana of Mynerals, becauſe ſuch will not

yeeld to Arcana of vegetables, that is of hearbes and rootes, &amp;c. But if the diſeaſe bee cauſed by influencies of the heauens, neather of the other Arcana will ſerue, but they are to be cured by A
                     ••
                  ronomy and influencies. But thoſe Diſeaſes and griefes that come by ſupernaturall meanes, will not be holpen by any meanes aforeſayde, but by ſupernaturall meanes. Likewiſe the agreement of the Medicin with the diſeaſe in one degree, is thus by thoſe Phiſitions cōſidered, that the Midicine that hath the pure onely ſeparated from the impare, may agrée in one degree, with the diſeaſes of the loweſt degree, of leaſt danger, and in places of leaſt parrell, and of leaſt continuance. And Medicins that haue that pure body ſublymed, and a purer thereby ſeparated from it, may agree with diſeaſes more ſtubborne, of longer continuance, &amp; in place more perilous. And medicins ſo ſublymed, after diſtilled in the Sunne, may agree in degree with diſeaſes, moſt ſtubburne, and of longeſt continuance. For vnleſſe the Mecicine doe agree with the diſeaſe in oue degree, he can not preuayle, becauſe the weaker can not drawe, conſume, nor expell the ſtronger. In this ſort doth the Chimycall Phiſition proceede from medicins fyne and pure, to purer, fyner, and

moſt excellent, and maketh choyſe of his medicins as occaſion ſerueth, by the reaſon of the cauſe, place, vehemencie and continuance of the diſeaſe. Such medicins doe not moulde and putrifie, but will continue in the vertue, a mans lyfe. Furthermore, by operation and working according to this Arte, you ſhall ſee with your eye, and perceyue the reaſon, why one diſeaſe is vehementer then an other, why in one place it is more painefuller then in an other, why in continuance of time the diſeaſe is harder to bee remooued then at the firſt: why ſome diſeaſes be vehement and yet continue long: why ſome be ſuddenly vehement and ſeone gonne: Why other bee long in growing: why ſome be extreame: why ſome be not, why in ſome places of the bady they he more eaſely remooued, then in an other, wherby you ſhalbe led into the knowledge of that parte of the body wherein the roote of the diſeaſe lurketh.
               17 The folowers of ye Ethnikes in iudgement of Vrin. (moſt of them) take vpon them to pronounce of al diſeaſes in any part of mās body, by looking on the water. Other ſome of them confeſſe, that they bee able to iudge of thoſe diſeaſes onely, which be in thoſe partes of the body, through the which the Vryn paſſeth.

And ſome of them affirme that the Urin is Meretrix and deceitfull, yet all of them are contented to make gaine of the looking vpon the Urin.
               The Chymicall Phiſition affirmeth that ſuch iudgement of vrine is monſtrous, and that the right iudgement is to bee had after due ſeperation thereof be made by fire: ſo ſhal he ſee the matter of ech deſeaſe and his medicine and touch it with his hande, whereby he ſhalbe able to giue a perfect iudgement if he bee able to iudge as becommeth a Phyloſopher and a Phyſition. By this meanes ſhall hee finde the vrine not to bee Meretrix nor lyar.
               18 The followers of the Ethnickes, to purge ſpirituall tyncturs of deſeaſes, doe miniſter rawe and indigeſted medicines, which drawe from the ſtomacke and other partes thinges neceſſary for them, aſwell as excrements: And alſo ſuch Purgations do withall purge humidum radicale, and thereby doe ſhake the body and weaken it, and leaue behinde them much venenoſitie, for lacke of due ſeperation. But in ſuch deſeaſes greeuous and deepely rooted, or in places principall, or parts where deſeaſes are hard to be remoued, ſuch Purgations doe vexe and torment the

bowels (which haue not deſerued it) in vaine, without any helpe or eaſe, becauſe the ſtronger is not drawne of the weaker.
               The Chymicall Phiſition knowing, that onely the ſuperficiall and groſſe impurities, in primis officinis alimentorum will yeeld to Purgations, and be expelled by ſeege and ſtoole, therefore to purge ſpirituall tyncturs of deſeaſes, and alſo againſt deſeaſes in places farre diſtant from the firſt receptacles of our meates, or in principall partes of the bodie, he vſeth ſpirituall tyncturs for Purgations, which doe purge radicitos, within and without: that is to ſay, they take away not onely, the ſuperficiall impurities by ſeege and ſtoole, but alſo the deepe rooted ſpiritual tyncturs, of long continuaunce and fine circulation, either by abſolute and perfect conſuming of them, without any ſenſible auoyding or expulſion, or els by mundifying and clenſing of Balſamum, and the Spirites and Elementes of man, and renuing of blood, or els by diſſoluing, clenſing &amp; ſending abroad, the rooted ſpirituall tyncturs of deſeaſes by vrine, ſweate and inſenſible tranſpirations.
               19 The followers of the Ethnickes in their medicines, credite Recipe of Gallen Auicen, and ſuch other, though in theſe daies

the bodies of men bee not ſo ſtrong as they were in their time. And though deſeaſes in nature doe dayly alter, and newe are bredd, which were not in their time knowne. And if they doe not followe thoſe olde receiptes of their Authors, but make newe medicines of themſelues, yet they haue none other ſkill, but to trie them, and make their experiment vpon men.
               Thè Chymicall Phiſition calleth ſuch receiptes, decipe, and willeth their followers to leaue ſuch receiptes, and to prouide that the medicine doe agree with the deſeaſes in one degree. For if it fayle in degree it fayleth in cure. And as in manuall operation he willeth his followers not to worke before they know the nature of the worke which they intende. So in miniſtering of medicines, he willeth thē not to miniſter, before they know the cauſe and nature of the deſeaſe, and what and how much it wanteth of his proper nature, and what and how much it hath gotten of an other nature. For incognita cauſa, à caſu procedit cura, to the knowledge wherof wee ought to come, as the Alkimiſtes doe come to the knowledge of the body that is to them vnknowne, and not by trying of the medicine in man. For, Ve his qui neſciunt experiri
                  
                  niſi in hominibus, as that worthie Chymicall Phyloſopher and Phyſition Roger Bacon ſayth, and per effectus facta, &amp; ſigna, cauſa tuenda eſt.
               
            
            
               
                  Chapter. 9. The cauſes why this Arte is euill ſpoken of, and findeth fewe fauourers.
               
                  BY theſe cōtrouerſies thou maiſt ſee gentle Reader, that moſt of the matters wherein the Chymicall Phyſition doth differ frō the Ethnickes, and their followers bee ſuch as doe not conſiſt in opinion or dunſicall wrangling and arguing, as thoſe of the Ethnicks doe, but in palpable ſenſible and viſible experience, which is the mayſteries of Artes and Sciences, of which maner of experiences and operations the followers of the Ethnicks are vtterly ignorant: wherefore it is no maruaile that they inueigh ſo vehemently againſt this Arte. For therein they verifie the old ſaying, Ars non habet inimicum preter ignorātem. It is an vniuſt dealing for any man to reproue, hate, and with

deſpightfull wordes to inueigh againſt that whereof he is ignorant. For loue and hatred ought to proceed of knowledge, whether the thing deſcrueth to be loued or not, and not of chaunce. But when a man knoweth not whether the thing be worthy to be loued or hated, how can he giue a 
                     •
                  uſt reaſon of hate thereof, eſpecially when the thing wherof he is ignorant may be good. Therefore it is great reaſon that a man ſhould knowe what the thing is whereunto it leaneth, and app
                     •
                  rtayneth, before he hate it, or if he be ignoraunt thereof then not to hate it. Which of them knoweth what way to begin to ſeperate the Salt, Sulphur, and Mercury, from Hearbes, Plants, and all other thinges as it ought to bee artificially, according and agreeable to the properties and ſeueral natures of ech Herbe, Roote &amp;c. For diuers and ſeuerall Hearbes require ſeuerall maner of ſeperations. Plantes haue their peculiar ſeperations: Mynerale theirs: Marcheſies theirs. &amp;c. Which of them doth knowe the ſeuerall maners of Calcination, Reuerberation, Cementation, Inceration, Imbybytion, Pa
                        •
                     tation, Liquefaction, Ablution, Sublymation, Exaltation, Contrition, Reſolution. Putrifaction, Circulatiō, Inhumation, Diſtillation, Aſcention, Fixation,
                  
                  Lauatiō, Coagulation, Aſſation, Cō
                     gelation, Fermentation, &amp;c. And the natures and properties of theſe ſeuerall works and operations, whereby Regeneration, Tvncturs, Arcana, Magiſteria, Quintum eſſe, and Elixirs be had and gotten. Which of them can tell what tranſmutation of Elements meaneth: Eau any of them make ripe, the rawe medicine, ſeparate the pure frō the impure, turne bitter into ſweete, mittigat corroſions, heates, taſtes, ſmelles, Coagulations, &amp;c. of medicines, and make them volatill and ſpirituall, to helpe and cure ſpirituall and long circulated diſeaſes? For this cauſe Eraſtus and others not conceauing a right the meaning of Paracelſus, doe imagine a conſtruction of their owne heads ond braines of that they read in him, which is not agreeable with his meaning: and vpon ſuch an abſurditie of their owne deuiſe, they make long diſcourſes, and goe about to diſprooue that, which is not affirmed, or that which they can not ſkill of. I would ſuch folowers of the Ethnickes did in this followe their Prince &amp; Captayne Gallen, as they doe in the reſt of his doctrine, which being demaunded at any time of any Sect (being himſelfe addicted to noue) whether it were ſound or good or no, vſed

to ſay, that he could not make any anſwer there unto, vnleſſe he had firſt learned all their decrees and determinations perfectly, and had gotten a briefe method to iudge them, for no man ſayeth he can iudge of things to him vnknowen. But alas, herein the cauſe of this Chimicall phiſicke conſiſteth in a deſperate ſtate, for though this Arte be ſhewed by worke and experience: and experiēces which doe agree with nature, and do bring forth like actions, by the cauſe of all certeintie, yet it may not come to that triall: for in the ſcholes nothing may be receiued nor allowed that ſauoreth not of Ariſtotle, Gallen, Auicen, and other Ethnickes, whereby the yong beginners are either not acquainted with this doctrine, or els it is brought into hatred with them. And abrode like wiſe the Galeniſts be ſo armed and defended by the protection, priuiledges and authoritie of Princes, that nothing can be allowed that they diſalowe, and nothing may bee receiued that agreeth not with their pleaſures and doctrine: &amp; whatſoeuer is miniſtred to any perſon according to their rules and Canons, although it be to the deſtrunction of the patient, muſt be reputed, accepted, ratifyed, allowed and accompted learnedly well and rightly done, and they are

excuſed and diſcharged of their fact, by the lawe called Lex Aquilia. But as long as the vnſ kilfull and fluggiſh Phiſition may enioy that immanitie and freedome, and as long as it ſhalbe allowed in the Scholes to be hereſie and foule ignoraunce to ſpeake againſt any partof Ariſtotle, Galen, Auicen, or other like heathens doetrine: as long as the Galeniſts may ſhrowde themſelues vnder the Wings and protection of Princes, Priuiledges and Charters, the cauſe of the Chimycall Phiſition muſt needes lye in a deſperate ſtate. And no man almoſt ſhalbe able to attayne to the perfection in true Phiſicke. As long as Scotus or Thomas Aquinas, and ſuch other were ſo priuileged in the ſcholes, that no interpretation of Gods worde was allowed, but ſuch as was brought out of them, or agreed with them, the cauſe of true Religion, and ſeruing of God was in deſperate ſtate, and it lay oppreſſed and hidden. And as long as thoſe that were noſeled in ſuch puddle, were mainteyned, defended and priuiledged by princes and potentates, it was hard for trueth to ſhewe his face abroade openly. Wherefore if the Chymicall doctrine agreeing with Gods worde, experience and nature may come into the Scholes and Cities in ſteade of Ariſtotle,
                  
                  Gallen, and other heathen and their followers. And if it were lawfull I and commendable for euery honeſt ſtudent to labour in the Philoſophicall ſearching out of the trueth, by the fire or otherwiſe, and thereby either confirme and make manifeſt the trueth by this Arte tought, cather to adde newe things wel tried to the old that be good, and then to reiect the other vaſtard, adulterat, ſophiſticat ſtuffe, and ſo ioyne words and deedes together, then ſhould there be no time ſpent in vayne, and vain glorious bable and ſophiſticall diſputations, without due triall by labor and worke of fire, and other requiſite experiments, then ſhould it eaſely be ſeen whether Gallen and other heathen or the Chimeſts were moſt to be folowed and allowed. And whoſe writings and trauailes were more auaileable for mans health, either conſeruing or reſtoring, &amp; who ſeeketh more paynefully, faythfully, ſincerely, charitably and Chriſtianlike, for the certeine helpe of his neighbour, and not for lucre or veine glory and pompe, the auncient Chimical Phiſition or Gallen and his folowers. Then as Galen the prince of their Phiſicke ſayeth, if men would not bee ſworne to the wordes of any maſter or teacher, they woulde chooſe out of eche thing that were beſt, and

would not be ſlaues to followe or name them ſelues either of Hypocrates, Praxagoras, or of any other man.
            
            
               
                  Chater 10. The firſt authors of the auncient Phiſicke, and the Succeſsion and Progreſsion thereof, to Hermes Triſmegeſtus, and how the reſt writing thereof yet extant.
               
                  FOR the Authros, Inuentors, originall ſucceſſion and progreſſion of this auncient Chimycall Phiſicke, whoſe ſtudie and vſe doeth flowe out of the fountaines of nature, and is collected out of the Mathematicall, naturall, and ſupernaturall precepts (as is aforeſaid in the beginning hereof) it is to bee vnderſtanded, that Adam by diuine reuelation, or by arte giuen to him of God, did foretell of the vniuerſall deſtruction of the worlde, one by water, the other by fire. And no doubt he was indowed with ſingular knowledge, wiſedom and light of nature, that aſſoone as he did behold any beaſt, he by &amp; by did ſo exactly know all their natures, powers, properties and vertues,

that he gaue them names, apt, meete and agreeable to their natures and properties, whereby it appeareth he knewe the natures and properties of things better then we, whē we haue ſpent all our life time in ſearching out their natures, which was a ſinguler gift of God &amp; pleaſed him mightely. The ſonnes of Seth which were his Nephewes, receyuing wiſdome &amp; knowledge from the hands and deliuery of their Auncitors, leaſt that the Mathematicals and that knowledge they had ſo learned ſhould periſh with the fludde, did erect two Pillers, in which they did 
                     •
                  ngraue their learning, knowledge and inuētions, out of the which they that ſhould be preſerued from the fluddde, might learne thoſe knowledges, cunning and Arte, ss Ioſepus writeth in his firſt booke Chap. 13. of Antiquities, which did ſee one of the Pillers that was of ſtone in his time ſtanding in Syria as he writeth.
               
                  Abraham the Prince of faith was borne in that Countrey, where thoſe Mathematicals and other knowledges &amp; learning was thus preſerued, and continued 292. yeres after the Flood, in the yeare of the world 1949. This Abraham hauing knowledge in the Mathematicalls, which in his Countrey were preſerued

as is aforeſayd, by the wonderfull harmony of the worlde did aſcende to the knowledge of the one onely God, as ſome ſay. But rather, thereby he did ſee and perceiue, the inuiſible thinges of GOD, that is, his eternall power and Godhead, by the creation of the world. And he being the mightie and renowmed father of the elect nation, no doubt was a greate Deuine, as hee was excellent in the Mathematicalls and other learning. But becauſe the Chaldeās, Meſapotamians and Aſſyrians were moued and ſ
                     ••
                  rred againſt him, for Religions ſake, he left his Countrey and kinſfolkes by the Commaun
                     •
                   ement of God, and went to ſoiurne in the lande of Canaan. From whence ſhortly after through great Famine, he was conſtrayned to goe in to Aegipt. He there as Ioſephus writeth, declared God to bee the Creator of all thinges, teaching them the Sciences and Mathematicalls. By this meanes was the true knowledge of God and of the Mathematicals and Sciences brought into Aegipt, the which knowledges the Prieſtes of Aegipt, ſucceſſiuely, did after that profeſſe. And they had deuided among them portions of land, by Pharoes appointment, for their maintenance and ſtipende, as appeareth Gene. cap. 47. After

that Abraham returned into the land of Canaan, where ye Godly fathers did ſucceſſiuely profeſſe theſe Artes and knowledges. After this in the yeare of the worlde 2355. Moſes that was ſo acceptable vnto God was borne in Aegipt, and was learned in all the wiſedome of the Aegiptians, as S. Luke writeth in the Acts of the Apoſtles Cap. 70. And he doth there ſett downe and make mention of that his learning for his excellent praiſe and honors ſake. Sainct Auguſtine ſayth in his Booke, de Ciuitate dei lib. 18. cap. 39. that the wiſedome of the Aegiptians wherein Moſes was inſtructed was Aſtronomy, Geometry, and Arithmetike, and ſurely it was that which before they had learned of Abraham. And although ſome of the Aegiptians, as ſome of the Chaldeans did wander and ſtray aſide in many fooliſhe vayne and ſuperſticious ſpeculations, yet ſome were contented, with the ſimple order of Nature, profitable to be learned and praiſe worthie, which is to bee conſidered and marked in the wonderfull worke of God, not onely in the places of the Starres, and in ſo goodly and beautifull diſtinguiſhed varietie of thē, but alſo in their motions, powers, and ſecret offices and operations: whereof it is like that Moſes made

choyce, abandoning and forſaking the other ſuperſticious and vayne doctrine, not deſeruing the name of wiſedome. After theſe liued Hermes, or Mercurius Triſmegeſtus in Aegipt not long after Moſes: For alas ye great A
                        •
                     tronomer liued in Moſes his time, &amp; was grandfather on the mothers ſide to Mercury the great, whoſe Nephewes ſonne was this Hermes Triſmegeſtus, as S. Auguſtine writeth in his Booke, de Ciuitate dei lib. 8. Cap. 26. and lib. 18. Cap. 39. In his tyme ſayth Saint Auguſtine, in Aegipt the ſtudie of Phyloſophie, which did promiſe to teach that, whereby m
                     •
                  n might be made bleſſed or happie did 
                     •
                  he
                     ••
                  ly 
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  riſhe. This Hermes or Mercurius was called Triſmegeſtus, as ſome ſay, becauſe he was the greateſt Phyloſopher, the greateſt King, and the greateſt Prieſt. But Guydas ſayth, that he was called Triſmegeſtus, becauſe he held opinion of God nere agreeable with the right doctrine of the Trinitie. He did write diuers workes, as one Dialogue in whiche Aſclapeus is brought in to thinke that one onely God is the maker of all thinges, and confeſſeth the errors of them which founde out the ſuperſtition of Idols, &amp; doth propheſie in that Booke that they ſhall periſhe. And in his Booke dedicated

                  
                     〈1 page missing〉
                  tion amōg the Aegiptians at that time. Now concerning his knowledge in prophane Sciences, &amp; in this Arte which we haue in hand, for his excellencie in Philoſophie (as is afore ſayd) he had one of his titles after Maximus. For in his time did the ſtudie of Phyloſophie chiefly floriſh, as writeth Volateran, lib. 15. Alſo in his firſt Booke of 15. intituled libri Hermeicorum, he bringeth in a Prieſt ſaying thus. Doeſt thou not heare that our Hermes hath deuided Aegipt into his bounde
                     •
                  , and lotted ech mans ground aſunder, that he meaſured with a corde, and deuided dikes for to water the groundes, and that he hath ordayned, lawes and rules, and that he hath named gouernors out of thoſe ſtatutes and ordinaunces, and hath appointed chaunges of buying and ſelling, and hath ſat downe the briefe doctrine of the courſe of the Starres, and hath deuided the Hearbes. And that he hath inuented, founde out and taught with numbers or Arithmetike and Geometrie. Alſo all Aſtronomie, Aſtrologie, Muſicke and Grammer. Others write of him that he attayned at the full, to all the partes of Phyloſophie. Bradeus in primo Epigrammatū
                   ſayth, that Mercurius found out th
                     •
                  ſ
                     •
                   fower, that is, Letters, Muſicke, Geometrie, and
               
                  
                  Wreſtling. Dioderus ſayth, that this Mercury founde out Phyſicke among the Aegiptians. This Hermes did alſo write diuers other Bookes, as one intituled Pymander, of the power and wiſedome of God. And other thinges in Iamblicus proctus, and prophirius. Alſo an other Booke intituled, Latromathematica, that is to ſay, meditations applied to Aſtrologie, and diuers fragments and little peeces be by him written, which be alledged and cited by other Writers, which be not extant. But among others his excellent worke intituled, Tabula Smaragdina, or Sermo veredicus Hermetis, or Mercurii Triſmegeſti patris vere metaphycices doth ſufficiently declare his excellent ſkill and knowledge in this Arte, whiche is extant hitherto thou haſt heard gentle Reader howe the true knowledge of God and the Science of Chymia (from which medicina may not be ſeparated) haue bene deriued from Abraham the renowmed father of faith, vnder the title and names of the Mathematicall ſciences, whiſedome and Philoſophie, vnto the Prieſtes of Aegypt, and from them, vnto Mercurius or Hermes, Triſmegeſtus the Aegyptian, which as hath bin ſaid, was called three times great, whereof two of thoſe titles

ſleepe with Apollo his golden Harpe, that is by equal ſweete and temperate motion in the ſayd fire. By this meanes doth the Chymical Phyſition diſſolue, make thinne, eleuate, and conuert natures, and make perfect medicins: It ſhould ſeeme therefore that the Phyſicke of Apollo was exerciſe of the naturall vertue and power in man like to the Aethereall fire, or els that it was not the groſſe Phiſicke of the followers of the Ethnicks now in vſe, but ſome pure medicine like to the Aethereall fire, or a very ſimple fine and pure medicine, wherof the Binarii Phiſitions haue no ſkill. And then ſurely it was not of his owne inuē
                  tion or deuiſe, but he had learned the ſame in ſome other Countries and brought it into Greece, and there practiſed it: wherefore it was accompted his inuention there, or els he learned it of ſome that had beene in ſome other Countries. For Euſebius and others do teſtifie that Greece was barren and bare of all good Artes and doctrine before the tyme of Pythagoras, which liued about the yere of the world 
                     •
                  4
                     •
                  6. And whatſoeuer good learning and knowledge they had, they got it frō other Nations. As Pythagoras, Plato, and others did trauaile out of Greece, for to get learning and knowledge into Syria, Iudia,
                  
                  Aegipt, Perſia, and other Nations, which the Grecians doe call Barbarians. And ſurely if his Phyſicke was of his owne and not proceeding from the Children of God, then was it not worthie the name of true Phyſicke: becauſe as Plato ſayth, he that is ignorant in diuine thinges, cannot haue right vnderſtanding in prophane learning. As Apollo and Aeſculapius, &amp; all the Grecians at that time were without the true knowledge of GOD, and were Idolaters, and both they were honored as Gods, and ech of them had a temple dedicated to him. But it ſhould ſeeme by that Plato hath written, and Plinie alſo, that their Phyſicke was altogether Surgery. Wherevnto Cicero doth ſeeme to cōſent in his third Booke de Natura deorum, aſcribing to Aeſculapius the firſt inuention of bynding and healing of woundes. Sabellicus alſo &amp; Strabo, do write that the old Phyſicke was rude, and their medicines were ſuch onely as were found out by chaunce, to haue holpen any bodie, and ſuch they did miniſter vnto thoſe that were ſicke of like deſeaſes. Aeſculapius did not meddle with bodies infected with inward ſickneſſes, but onely preſcribed to ſuch a dyet about meate and drinke: as one did to Euripilus that was wounded at the ſiege of Troy,
                  
in the preſence of his two ſonnes Machaon and Podalirius: and as they two did to Menataus whom Pandar woūded there, becauſe they thought deſeaſes did commonly come to man, either by externall hurtes, as by pricking, cutting, or bruſing, or els did chaunce to him by euill dyet, lacke of exerciſe, and euill order of his liuing: therfore they thought it neceſſary to helpe them that were ſo hurt. But they thought as long as men vſed good dyet, exerciſe, and good order of life, they cō
                  tinued in health, and prolonged their life at eaſe. Therefore Phocilides vſed to ſay, that the liuely vertue and power of the body muſt be exerciſed whileſt wee bee able. But Plato ſayth, that Aeſculapius and others were of this opinion, that he which would not liue in the appointed and accuſtomed rule and order of life, but by incontinencie of liuing, did fall into deſeaſes, was not profitable for himſelfe nor for others, and that the Arte of Phyſicke had nothing to doe with ſuch, nor ſerued for them: and that ſuch ought not to bee cured, though they were richer then Midas. And that it was againſt reaſon to thinke that men ſhould neede Phyſicke for Rewmes, Diſtillations, and for the griefes of the ſwellings of the inwarde ſpirites, which come through

delicacy of liuing and ſlouth, and lacke of good order in liuing, and therefore proueth that thoſe deſeaſes were not knowne to Mahaon and Podalirius, at the ſiege of Troye. Aſclepyades alſo the Phyſition ſayd, that health conſiſteth in abſtinence of meate and drinke, and in ryding, walking, and running. Then reſteth to conſider what maner medicines they vſed in Surgery. I doe reade in Plato in the 31. Booke and 3. Dialogue de iuſto, that when Pandarus had woūded Menalaus at the ſiege of Troye, after Mahon and Podalirius had dried vp the blood of his woundes with their handes, they did anoynt the woūd with mitigating Balmes or Oyntments, and preſcribed him a certayne order and forme of dyet in his meate and drinke. Wherby it appeareth, that the maner of their Surgery, was like vnto that of the Chymicall Surgions, whoſe maner is with Oyles and Balmes to pacifie nature, and to keepe the wounde defended from accidents, and to leaue the cure to nature which is able then to be his owne Surgion. And more playnly to proue their doctrine, one Petrus Haſardus is ſufficient witneſſe, who in his French Epiſtle before the great Surgery of Paracelſus, writeth that as he trauailed through the

Countrey of Lyuonia, he ariued in a certaine Monaſtery there, where he taried two daies in peruſing the Lybrarie, and there he found two peeces of the workes of the ſame Mahacon and Podalirius, which intreated fully that Chymical forme and maner of doctrine. About the tyme of Apollo, that is the yeare of the world 2697. liued Orpheus the Thracyan, and was the firſt that is remembred to haue written of Hearbes (as ſome ſay) exactly, and he founde out remedies for many deſeaſes. After hym followed one Muſaeus, his Scholler. After them liued Heſiodus in the yere of the world 3111. After him liued Pronopis the Maſter of Homer, which likewiſe had knowledge of Hearbes in the yere of the worlde 
                     •
                  258. Thales Mileſius liued in the yeare of the worlde 3379. and before Chriſt 584. He trauayled into Aegipt, and brought into Greece greate knowledge in the Mathematicalls. Ameriſtus or Mamercus ſucceeded him. Before this tyme was one Siſiphus, otherwiſe called Theoſophos, a famous Phyſition.
            
            
               
               
                  Chapter 12. Of Pythagoras and his knowledge in this Arte, and that he taught in Italy, and of his Schollers and folowers: And of the medicin of Empedocles. And of 70 Bookes that Eſdras was commaunded to keepe.
               
                  ABout the yeere of the worlde 3434. liued Pythagoras, a Grecian famous for his wiſedome and diuine knowledge, and for his learning in the Metaphiſickes and Mathematicals, he labor
                     ••
                   much in Arithmetick, he brought Geometrie to perfection as Laertius writeth. He leſt diuers rules of Aſtrologicall proguoſlic
                     •
                  tion, and of this arte ſome what, he found out Muſicke in the ſtarres, and deriued the ſame to mittigate the affections of the mynde: he did write of the effect of herbes. He trauayled into Perſia, Arabia, Aethiopia and Aegypt for learning and knowledge: he was conuerſant with the Prieſtes of the Jewes, after he had once profeſſed their Religion. After his returne

hee taught in Italy. Hee was a great Cabaliſt. Some ſay that one Phericides was his teacher, which did firſt write de Natura. After Pythagoras in this learning &amp; knowledge ſucceeded as his ſcholers and folowers Telanges his ſonne, after hym Xenophanes, Archilas, Philolaus, Liſias, Parmenides, Leno, Eleates, Anaxagoras, Leucippus, Democritus, Nauſiphales, Naucides, Epicharmus, Alchmeon, Epimenides. For Aeliames lib. 9. writeth that all the Pithagoreans were ſtudious in Phiſicke, and many auncient kings and others before the time of Pythagoras were ſtudious in phiſicke which I doe omit, putting you firſt in remembrance of Empedocles a ſinguler Philoſopher and notable Phiſition, about the yere of the world 3308. Suidas writeth of a medicin that hee vſed to miniſter, called Apnus, which was of that nature, yt it would preſerue a mans body 30. dayes without meat, that was ſpeachleſſe and ready to giue vp the Ghoſt, for ſo doeth the word 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   ſignifie. I thinke the Phiſitions the folowers of the Ethnickes wil confeſſe that it is no part of their profeſſion to make ſuch a Medicine, and that their groſſe medicins can haue no ſuch vertue, becauſe the knowledge of ſuch medicins doth depend vpon

                  Metaphiſicke and ſupernaturall principles, which Empedocles, Pithagoras, Democritus, Plato, and diuers others doe maintaine in naturall things, contrarie to the groſſe Phiſicke. About the yere of the worlde 3503 liued Eſdras, to whome the moſt high gaue vnderſtanding and commaundement to write, and to whom the moſt high ſpake thus. The firſt bookes that thou haſt written publiſh openly, that the worthy and vnworthy may reade. But the laſt ſeuentie bookes kepe, that thou mayſt giue them to the wiſe among the people. For in them is the veine of vnderſtanding, and the Fountaine of wiſdome, and the riuer of knowledge, in which 70. bookes as ſome thincke, be contayned the vnderſtanding of this arte, out of the which the worthy from time to time haue receaued the vayue of vnderſtanding of this Arte.
            
            
               
                  Chapter 17. That Phiſicke which Hypocrates left in writing was not deſcended from Aeſculapius.
               
                  NOwe are wee come to the time of of Hipocrates of Cous in Greece which liued at the tyme of the wars of Peloponenſus which began

about the yere of ye world 3536. Geſnerus and Andreas Lacuna for credit of their Phiſicke, ſay that he was deſcended from Aeſculapius, and that Apollo taught Aeſculapius Phiſicke, which likewiſe did teach his ſonnes which were called Aſclepiades after their father Aeſculapius, and ſo Phiſicke by inheritance ſucceſſiuely did deſcende from the Parents to the Children vnto Hypocrates. And that it was not lawfull for them to communicate the ſame to any man that was not borne of that family or kinred, therefore they that were cunning in that arte, were called the ſonnes of Phiſitions. And though his anceſtors &amp; kinred before him did deteine their arte in their families, &amp; did not cōmunicate ye ſame to others, yet he reduced it into method, and did commit it to writing, that it might be common to all men. And therefore he is ſayde to be author of method and princeps naturalis medicine, and the firſt that did write of Phiſicke.
               That Hypocrates was deſcended from Aeſculapius, I will not contend, becauſe it ſhould ſeeme by auncient writers to be ſo, or els for reputations ſake they did terme him of that progenie. But that the Phiſick which Hypocrates did leaue in writing, was in all

poynts the ſelfe ſame which Aeſculapius did learne of Apollo his father, and which he did teache to Machon and Podalirius, and was deliuered ſucceſſiuely by tradition downe the right lyne from them, to Hypocrates by the ſpace of 800 yeres (for ſo long time was betweene Aeſculapius and Hypocrates) is hard to be proued, becauſe tradition of doctrine without writing, not coſ
                     •
                  ſting vpon naturall practiſe, nor continuing in one place certeine, but at large, is no faithfull preſeruer of the trueth therof, ſo many yeres, neither is it like that the iſſue of Aeſculapius line could bee knowen, and did not fayle in 800 yeres, nor ceaſe nor degenerate from the ſteps and ſtudious loue of that arte of their Aunceſtors, neither is it lyke that Hypocrates woulde haue broken his oth if it were true that goeth vnder the name of iuſiurandum medicorum Aſclepiadarū, or Hipocraticū iuſiurandū, and would make that common which ſhoulde haue bene kept ſo ſecret. But if the Phiſicke of Apollo &amp; Aeſculapius was any other then exerciſe of Surgery, (as is aforeſayd) then no doubt was their medicins ſimple, pure, and like to the Aethereall fire, and therefore altogether vnlike vnto groſſe medicins that be nowe ſtoutly defended, (as is before declared)

And that it may appeare, that the phiſick which Hypocrates had learned, was not ſo precious, nor kept ſo ſecret in one kinred, line and family, as we are borne in hand, thou muſt vnderſtand gentle Reader, that Plinie in his 29 booke, cap. 1. and Strabo in his 8. booke doe write, that from the time of Aeſculapius, Phiſicke laye hidden and couered in moſt thicke darkeneſſe, vntill the time of Hypocrates, which did bryng it to light by this meanes. For whereas it was the maner and faſhion of thoſe that were cured and deliuered from any ſickneſſe, to write in the Temple of Aeſculapius which was in Cous, the maner &amp; forme of their remedie, and cure thereof, to the ende, that the like diſeaſes might be by them cured, Hypocrates did write out theſe Medicins, and out of them began Phiſicke. Here thou ſeeſt, gentle Reader, that the Phiſicke of Aeſculapius was not knowē at Cous, at the tyme of Hypocrates, but he out of the experiments of olde wiues, men and women of the Countrey and Citie, which were not kept ſecret, but by cuſtome and vſage were written and faſtened to the wall of Aeſculapius, his Temple openly to be ſeene, he deriued his Phiſicke: He wrote out thoſe experienſes of men and women of all ſortes, he

brought them into order. Out of the which afterward he drewe Aphoriſmes and briefe Rules of Phiſicke. Beſides this, it hath bene ſayd of ſome, that Hypocrates for enuie that he bare to Aeſculapius, did ſet a fire his temple, and ſo conſumed the writings of the auncient Phiſitians. And beſides them that bee folowers with them, it appeareth by Sudas and other writers, that before Hypocrates, diuers did write of Phiſicke, though we haue not their works extant among vs, as Democritus the Sonne of Caliphon, which was Aeſculapius his Prieſt. Nichomachus the Sonne of Machaon, did write ſixe bookes of phiſicke and one of Philoſophie. Alſo Hypocrates the firſt of the ſeauen, which Suidas ſpeaketh of, did write of Phiſike, Orpheus alſo did write of hearbes, and ſo did Pithagoras and diuers others, whereby it appeareth, that Phiſicke was not kept ſo ſecret in one famely, but it was at libertie for euery man to ſee their writings. But this is true, yt they which did write of ye right, true aunciēt phiſick Chimical, did write darkly and in figuratiue kind of ſpeaches, to the entent they would only be vnderſtoode of the children of their Science. And therefore they did write filiis ſcientie. So they which were cunning in that Arte,

might well be called the Sonnes of Phiſitions, as is before declared. But to what purpoſe ſhould any man write darkely of that Phiſicke, which is ſo groſſe? whoſe medicins be ſo common to olde wiues, and men and women of all ſorts. And why ſhould any man be called the Sonne of a Phiſition, for ſuch Medicins, rather then the man or woman of the Countrey, which had done the like good with ſuch a medicine as the profeſſor of Phiſicke did.
            
            
               
                  Chapter. 10. That Democritus Abderites a Thacian did write of this arte, whoſe bookes are yet extant, and of his teachers, Scholers and followers, and of ſome of their workes yet extant.
               
                  
                     DEmocritus Abderites of Thracia, was in the tyme of this Hypocrates: He was olde whē 
                  Hypocrates was young, Anaxagoras and Lacippus were his teachers. Alſo he trauayled into Caldea, Aegipt, and Perſia, for to learne their knowing and knowledge. He had a notable Scholler called Metrodorus,
                  
whoſe Scholler was Anaxarchus: He did write two Bookes, one called Magnus diacoſmus, that is to ſay, of the gouernment and diſtinction of the nature of thinges: and one other de natura mundi. He was ſkilfull in all kinde of Phyloſophie naturall, morall Mathematikes, Metaphyſicks, and Logick. He alſo did write one excellent worke, intituled, Democritus de Arte Chimica, vel de Arte ſacra, ſiue de rebus naturalibus &amp; miſticis, intreating of this Art, in effect like vnto that of Hermes Triſmegeſtus aforeſayd, which is yet extant among vs. Sineſius Pelagius, Stephanus, Alexandrinus, and Olympiodorus, fower famous Chymiſtes and Philoſophers, did write Commentaries and Expoſitions vpon that worke of his. After him of this Arte did write Blemida Zoſimus, and Archelaus.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Chapter 15. That in Plato his time, the Prieſtes of Acgypt were very skilfull in this arte. And that Plato did finde that fault with the Phiſitions of Greece, in his time, as the Chimicall Phiſitions doe now with the Ethnicke Phiſitions and their followers. And howe Ariſtotle and Plato doe differ in the naturall cauſes of Effects.
               
                  AFter theſe about the yere of the worlde 3586. followed Plato in the Mathematicalls, Phyloſophie, wiſedome, knowledge, vertue, and Eloquence, farre exceding al others in his time: He was borne at Athens, he did not onely heare the famous Phyloſophers &amp; Geometricians in Greece, but alſo wēt into Italy, Affrike and Aegipt, to learne the miſticall Sciences. Strabo writeth that the Prieſtes of Aegipt, were ſo much eſteemed and reuerenced in the olde time, for their wiſedome and knowledge, that the moſt famous, and beſt Phyloſophers of Greece, did trauayle to them for learninges ſake. They excelled in ſecrete Seyences,

which they called Cabaliſticae, and did communicate the ſame to others, that were deſirous to learne. All the Prieſts of the Aegiptians, were Phyſitions, as Homer and Plato doe teſtifie. Plato himſelf when he trauayled to them, with his companion Euripides, was taken with ſickneſſe, and was cured by thoſe Prieſts. The opinion of Plato was this, that the Phi
                     •
                  tions of Greece, had no knowledge nor vnderſtanding of many deſeaſes in mans body, becauſe they were altogether and wholy ignorant in that which they ought cheefly to cure: the which if it be not well at eaſe, it is not poſſible for any parte of the body to be in health. For all thinges either good or bad, be deriued and doe flowe from Anima, (before declared) into the body and to euery parte of man, as they doe from the head into the eyes. And as a man cannot cure the eyes, without that he firſt doe cure the head, nor the head before the body bee cured, euen ſo the body can not be cured without you begin with Anima. For Anima corpus curat, is his doctrine in diuers places. This he learned out of Greece by his trauayle. The lacke of knowledge hereof, was in his tyme the cauſe of error of the Phyſitions of Greece, and ſo hath hetherto continued. This is the doctrine of the

Chymicall Phyſitions, which the followers of the Greekes and Ethnickes, haue no ſkill of, and therefore ſo much impugne it.
               
                  Ariſtotle was in the tyme of Plato, and was his vngrate and vnkind ſcholer. Wherfore Plato vſed to call him a Moyle, whoſe propertie is whē he hath filled his belly with his dams milke, then to kicke at her with his heeles. He did not onely kicke at Plato, but he omitted no man whom he did not taunt, reproue, or find fault with: thinking to gaine and deriue to him ſelfe ſo much glory, as he had taken from others, although hee were more high and more excellent thē others, and could ſee farther then any man els. Ariſtotle contrary to his Maſter Plato, referreth naturall cauſes of effects, onely to certayne Elimentall qualities, and ſo vaynly he doth attribute the power of life to dead thinges, and reſteth in ſuch a beginning and ending, in which aſcending, by the doubtfull care of naturall thinges being remoued from diuine, mans mynde is turned from them, which is the right way to Atheiſme. But Plato vſeth his naturall knowledge in deſcent and not in aſcent: for he doth demonſtrate and ſhewe the naturall beginnings in deſcent by the diuine cauſes of naturall thinges.
            
            
               
               
                  Chapter 16. Of diuers Poetical Fables ſhadowing and hyding the ſecretes of this Arte.
               
                  DIuers Poets before the tyme of Plato, and alſo after his time did wrapp and hide this Arte in Ridles, darke ſpeeches and fables. As by the fable of the golden Fleece brought from Colchos by Argonautae, the companions of Iaſon, in the yeare of the worlde 2694. by their perrilous nauigation, by the place where it was kept, which was the fielde called Martius, or dedicated to Mars, by ye plowing of it with Oxen, that breathed &amp; blowed out fire at their noſethrills, by the ground which ſhould be ſowne with the teeth of the Dragon that watched and kept the golden Fleece, by the bringing the Dragon a ſleepe, and obtayning the golden Fleece, they ſignified the practiſe of this Arte, daungers and perrills in this worke, the purging and preparing of the matters and ſubſtaunce of the medicine, in the furnaces that breath out fire at the venteholes continually in equall quantitie: the Quickſiluer

and Mercury ſublimed, which ſhould bee ſowen in Mars his fielde like ſeede, which by often ſublimation, doth ſo riſe out of the matter cōtained in the Alembeck, into the helme or head, and in it maketh diuers formes, figures and faſhions, as if men were fighting, and one killing an other. By theſe finally they ſignifie the medicine obteyned by labor, wherwith Medea reſtored Aeaſon the father of Iaſon to his youth agayne. The Poeticall Fables and darke tales of the Stones which Pyrra &amp; Dewcalion did caſt from thē, which were conuerted into women and men. The Fable of Gorgon, which turned all thinges that he did ſee into ſtones. The Fable of Ganimedes whom Iupiter did turne into an Egle and caried hym vp to heauen. The Fable of Dedalus, and his ſonne Icarus, incloſed in Laberinth, and the winges which were made for them of feathers faſtened together with waxe to flye out of the Laberinth. The golden Bow which Virgil doth ſpeake of, which being cut of, an other like to it did immediatly riſe in his place. The Fable alſo that Iupiter being angry with his father Saturne, did cut of his prime members with a ſharpe Cycle, of the blood of which when it was fallen into the Sea, Venus was begotten. The

Fable that Iupiter did ſhake his head, wherby Minerua lept out of his brayne. The tale how Minerua eſcaped from Vulcan, taken with the loue of Minerua, when he followed her haſtely. The tale how Io (whom Iupiter loued) was compaſſed with a groſſe and dark Cloud, whereby ſhe was ſtaied when ſhe was running from Iupiter. The blacke ſayles of Theſeus, which his father did ſee, for ſorrowe whereof he drowned himſelf in the Sea. The Serpent alſo that was ingendred after the great Flood, whom Apollo did kill with an Arrowe. The Fable of the Gardens of Heſperides, out of the which Hercules tooke the golden Apples, which were kept by a Dragon. And the Fable of Cadmus the ſonne of Agenor, which killed the Dragon that deuoured his companions, whoſe teeth he did pull out and ſowed them, of which men did riſe, which did immediatly kill ech other. And his building of Thebes in Boetia, after the maner of Thebes in Aegipt where he was borne (as ſome ſay) with money which he got by this Arte: whereby it is ſignified that this Arte did ſtill floriſhe in Aegipt. All theſe and ſuch other Poeticall Fables, darke ſpeeches and coloured tales, doe ſecretly hide and couer this whole Arte, taught by the Poets in

Method and wrapped in Ridles: namely after Plato by the Poets Ouid and Virgill, which liued in the yeare of the world 3959. and fower yeares before Chriſt was borne, which did chiefly excell in this Arte, and did hide the ſame in ſecrete ſpeeches and darke tales.
            
            
               
                  Chapter 17. Of certeine Phiſitions that vſed Chymical Medicins: aud of the three ſects of phitions that were betweene the time of Hypocrates &amp; Gallen. And that the Chimical Phiſitions ought rather to be called Rationales, then the Galeniſts. And that Galen folowing Hypocrates 600. yeres did comment vpon him againſt his meaning and words. And how Hypocrates agreeth with the Chymicall Phiſitions.
               
                  A 
                  Echines of Athens did vſe to helpe &amp; cure the diſeaſe called ye Qwinſcie, the kernels growe in ye mouth, and the inflammation that commeth by the ſame, and the Canker in the

mouth, with the Aſhes of a brunt man. This medicin he called Botrion, as Plini writeth, lib. 28. ca. 4. Artemon alſo did helpe the falling ſickneſſe with the Aſhes of the Skull or brayne panne of one that was killed, and burned in the fire, by giuing the ſame to the pacient in water, in the night time as Plinie writeth, lib. 28. cap. 1. Aeſchrion did helpe them that were bitten with a madde dogge, with the Aſhes of S
                     •
                  acrab
                     •
                  . Theſe and ſuch other experiments depending vpon the foundation and principles of this Chimicall Phiſicke, doe prooue that the ſame hath had his continuance, vntill Chriſtes tyme and after. For this Aeſchrion was Empericus and Gallens maſter, who liued in the yeere of the world, 4139. which was after the incarnation of Chriſt 178. yeres, and after the time of Hypocrates about 600. ye
                     •
                  res. In which ſpace of tyme betweene Hypocrates and Gallen, our newe Phiſi
                     •
                  ions ſay were three kinds &amp; ſects of Phiſitions, yt is, Rationales the Prince and chiefe whereof they woulde haue Hypocrates to be. The ſecond ſort bee the ſect of Emperici. The differēce betweene theſe two ſects they ſay is this, that Rationales doe vſe both reaſon and experience, to ſ
                     •
                  nd remedy for diſeaſes agreeable to them, but

the other are onely contented with the vſe of thoſe things, which by often obſeruation, they haue found to doe good. Although any man would enterpriſe firſt to make medicin, vnleſſe hee were before thereunto mooued by ſome reaſon, that the experiment thereof would take ſucceſſe. The third ſort were Methodici, which as the new Phiſitions ſay, doe refuſe to ſearch out the ſecret cauſes, nor yet doe allowe of particular experiments which Emperici doe cleane vnto. But they reduce all particalar affects, vnto two generall, that is to ſay, to Aſtructum and Laxum: and they doe affirme that all maner cure doth conſiſt in binding the looſe, &amp; in looſing that is bounde. Yet theſe ought not to be condemned to haue tought this without ſome reaſon, ioyned with ſome experience, before they eſtabliſhed their doctrine. Therefore the Galeniſts doe very preſumptuouſly chalenge to them ſelues only the name of Rationales, whoſe foundation doth depend vpon a falſe Center of dualitie and contrarietie, contrary to the true Center of vnitie, and vppon the falſe and vncerteine iudgement by the ſuperficiall and outwarde taſte and ſmell of things, whereby they take vppon them to iudge of the nature of them, leauing the inward and hidden nature of the

thing vnſearched, and not reached vnto, they ſearch, conſideratiō, and knowledge wherof, doeth onely make a reaſonable Phiſition, wherof they are vnterly ignorant as is aforeſayd. Therefore the Chimicall Phiſitions to whome this ſearch and knowledge doth apperteine, ought rather to be called Rationales medici, then their aduerſaries: and their phiſicke ought to bee accounted vayne, falſe, and vncerteyne, and not this Gallen following Hypocrates 600 yeares as is aforeſaide, tooke vpon him to Comment vpon Hypocrates, and contrary to his maſters doctrine, ſet downe in his booke, de antiqua medicina, he attributeth ye cauſes of diſeaſes &amp; their cures, to bare dead qualities of heat could, &amp;c which be cauſed and not cauſes. And ſo our later Phiſitions, following their Prince and Captaine Gallen that heathen and profeſſed enemy of Chriſt, in ſteade of Phiſitions and healers or curers of ſickneſſes and griefes, are become warmers, or coolers and bathers, whereas Hypocrates teacheth plainly and expreſſely that diſeaſes are not cauſed nor cured by the bare dead qualities of heate and cold, &amp;c. but by ſuch things yt haue power to worke, which he calleth 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Wherein he agreeth with the auncient and true phiſick

of the Chimiſts, which teacheth that diſeaſes are cauſed, and all naturall actions are performed by liuely and ſpirituall vapors and Eſſenties, which they call by the name of ſtarres &amp; diuers other names. And that they are to bee cured by ſuch as they are themſelues, in fineſſe, power and ſtrength, according to this Chimicall rule. Neceſſe eſt vt aſtra fiant medicamenta, &amp; aſtris ipſis, que morbos creant accommodentur.
               
            
            
               
                  Chapter. 18. Of the continuance of this arte in Aegypt vntill the time of Dyocleſian the Emperour, and a notable monument thereof in Italy: and the ſpreading of this art into other Countreys: and of diuers writers of this arte betweene Galens time and Paracelſus.
               
               
                  AS you haue heard of the continuaunce of this Arte in Aegipt vntill Plato his tyme, and from thence how it hath bene deriued into Greece and into other places: ſo alſo you ſhall vnderſtande, that it floriſhed

mightely in Aegipt, in the tyme of Diocleſian the Emperour of Rome, which liued in the yeare of the worlde 4252. and after the Natiuitie of Chriſt 292. as Swydas &amp; others doe write. And as this Arte was brought into Italy by Pythagoras, and there continued by his Schollers and followers, ſo no doubt as the Romaines did get and gather the vſe of the beſt lawes of thoſe Countries which they conquered, ſo did they alſo the beſt Artes Sciences, learning &amp; knowledge out of all partes of the worlde, which they ſubdued to their dominion: as appeareth by the ſkil that Ouid and Virgill had in this Art, and diuers others after them. And alſo by that moſt auncient Monument and wonderfull proofe of this Arte of Chymia, that was found at Padway or Pauie in Italy, that is in an earthen pot, wherein were theſe verſes written.
               
                  Plutoni ſacrum munus ne attingite fures,
                  Ignotum eſt vobis hoc quod in vrna latet,
                  Nam
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      elementa graui clauſit digesta labore
                  Vaſe in hoc modico Maximus Olibius:
                  Adſit foecundo custos ſibi copia cornu,
                  Ne pretium tanti depereat laticis.
               
               An other litle pot of earth was within this,

                  mulierū, and Ludus puerorum, Roſarius▪
                   and diuers workes intituled, de Alchymia, and de magni lapidis compoſitione. The names of their Authors bee vnknowne, and many others aſwell in Print as in written hande.
            
            
               
                  Chapter 19. That Theophrastus Paracelſus, was not the inuentor of this Arte, but the reſtorer thereof to his puritie: and that he hath giuen more light thereunto then any other before him: and the teſtimonies of great cures that he did by this Arte: and of diuers writers and learned Phyſitions, which ſince his time haue written of this Arte.
               
                  AFter all theſe followed that famous and worthie Phyloſophicall Chymiſt Theophraſtus Paracelſus, whoſe paynes were intollerable in ſearching out the ſecrets of Nature, and in ſetting forth and amplifying this Arte, and in practiſe wonderfull.
               He was not the author and inuentour of this

arte as the followers of the Ethnickes phiſicke doe imagine, as by the former writers may appeare, no more then Wicklife, Luther, Oecolāpadius, Swinglius, Caluin, &amp;c. were the Author and inuentors of the Goſpell and religion in Chriſtes Church, when they reſtored it to his puritie, according to Gods word, and diſcloſed, opened and expelled the Clowdes of the Romiſh religion, which long time had ſhadowed and darkened the trueth of the worde of God. And no more then Nicholaus Copernicus, which liued at the time of this Paracelſus, and reſtored to vs the place of the ſtarres according to the trueth, as experience &amp; true obſeruatiō doth teach is to be called the author and inuentor of the motions of the ſtarres, which long before were taught by Ptolomeus Rules Aſtronomicall, and Tables for Motions and Places of the ſtarres and by others, whoſe Tables of motions of the ſtarres by long exceſſe of time grewe to be vnperfect (which imperfections by Copernicus his obſeruations were diſcloſed, opened and brought to the former puritie, nor yet is the lawe of nature in the ſtarry motions, now though newly and lately we haue the old tables reformed, and trueth liuely reſtored. Neyther was any Countrey or people

at any tyme tyed and faſt bound to one kinde of Salue, Oyutment or Medicin, but it was lawfull and needefull for men to ſearch and find out, and to adde better to that was in vſe, and to altar the ſame, though it were vnlike and contrarie to that was before vſed. So that latter ages haue alwayes added ſomewhat to the former and newe diſeaſes require newe Medicins. And ſo much the rather, for that by the Ethnickes phiſicke, old and common diſeaſes haue not their certeine remedies, as the Goute, the Leproſie, the Dropſie, the falling ſickneſſe, nay now and then the Quarteyne and blacke Jaundies, yea, what adoe ſometime doth the ſeely toatheach make among them to cure it, nay what diſputations and mutes are to be maintained about the cauſe of it by their doctrine. Therefore true ſearche and true proofe by him made and reuiued, and true principles by him reſtored, are and ought moſt ioyfully of others to be embraced &amp; folowed. But after the trueth is found and eſtabliſhed, then to ſeeke or goe about to alter, that is to ſeeke after lacſings.
               His moſt enemies can not denie, but in Surgery and alſo in Phiſicke he did great cures: and had great ſkill in preparation of Medecins. Eraſtus his greateſt enemy, in the

Preface of his firſt volume to ye Reader, hath theſe words. Studiū &amp; diligentiā, quam in preparatione medicamentorum certorū adhibuit, nequaquam reprehendimus, ſed vehementer commendamus. Againe hee ſayth. Laude eum ſua fruſtratum non velimus, dum artem preparandi &amp; deſtillandi, quaſi reuocare ad vſum conatus fuit. Such like commendatios I finde in him, and in other of his enemies, though in trueth this is no cōmendatiō of Paracelſus, in Eraſtus his mouth which can no ſkill of preparations of Medicins, according to this Chymicall arte. But in this that his moſt enemy is compelled to confeſſe the trueth of preparation of his Medicins, by reaſon of the ſucceſſe that followed in the miniſtring of them to his Patients. This Epitaphe grauen in a Marble ſtone, reared againſt the outſide of the Church wal of S. Sebaſtian at Salsburge, at the fote of a payre of Staires, going downe vnto the Churchyard, there yet to be ſeene, doth ſhewe and prooue what opinion they had of hym which knew him, concerning his knowledge in Phiſicke, which is as foloweth.
               
                  Conditur hic Philippus Theophraſtus inſignis medicine doctor, qui dira illa

vulnera, Lepram, Podagram, Hidropiſin, aliaque inſanabilia corporis contagia mirifica arte ſuſtulit, ac bona ſua in pauperes diſtribuenda collocandaque ordinauit. Anno Domini 1541. die Septembris 24. Vitam cum morte mutauit.
                  
                     Pax viuis requies aeterna ſepultis.
                  
               
               
                  He in his life time was had in ſuch reuerence, (as it is written of him) that ſome called him Rabbi Moyſes: Some called him Hypocrates: ſome Eſculapius: ſome Monarcham perpetuum. Otherſome called his doctrine a natural Goſpell, the ſtorehouſe of trueth. Otherſome did not ſtick to affirme that the world had not his like. It is credibly wri
                        •
                     ten of him yt he healed twelue Leapors at Norymberge opēly brought to him. Cyriacus Iacobus Typographꝰ, in an Epiſtle dedicatory to the mightie Prince Otto, Coūtipalatine of Rhene, and Duke of Bayerland, writeth this, if his Latm be Engliſhed: They which haue the thinges yet in freſhe remembraunce, doe reporte that not long agoe there was one Theophraſtus of Tranſſiluania, who hauing knowledge in the ſecrete miſteries

of this arte, founde out a matter (which without doubt the old and auncient Phyloſophers, the ſerchers out of nature, hidyng by darcke parrables, and couert ſpeches: woulde ſignifie and giue the world warning of) and in appliyng &amp; miniſtering the ſame to mans body he hath performed wouderful, &amp; almoſt diviue thyngs: for he d
                        •
                     ubted not by the means of yt thing, to cure thoſe three moſt greuious dezeſes (that is to ſay) the Goute, Leproſie, &amp; fallyng ſickneſſe, beſides all other dezeſes, wherein he did wonderfull cures. There bee a great number of learned Philoſophers and Phiſitions, aſ well ſuch as weare Galeniſts, as others, which at this daie doe embrace, follow, and practiſe, the doctrine, methods and wayes of curyng of this Chimicall Phiſicke. As D. Petrus Seuerinus in Denmarcke Philoſopher, and Phiſition to the Kyng of Denmorke now raigning. An other is D. Albertus Wimpineus a Phiſition alſo and Philoſopher, whoſe patron is that noble Prince Alberte Paltzegraue of Rhene, Duke of high and lowe Bauaria. Hee in his Epiſtle dedicatorie before Archidopa of Paracelſus by him publiſhed in douche, doeth reprehend the folowers of the Ethnicks, whō hee calleth wenyng great Docters, becauſe

they giue ſo muche praiſe to Ariſtotle Hipocrates Galen, &amp;c. for ther labour and trauailes, onely to Theophraſus Paracelſus, they are not onely vuthankeſull, but withall they ſpeke ill of him, and reuile him, although he hath exerciſed him ſelf more then any of the Philoſophers or Phiſitions in the hid ſecrets of Nature, ſerched them out, knowne them &amp; publiſhed them for the preſeruation and furdering of the long life of man, which their doyng he iudgeth rather worthie to be accompted wilfull blindneſſe, then iudgement agreable to knowledge and manhode. And he giueth this farder reaſon of their doyngs: For they perceiue (ſaith he) when ſoeuer this Triſmegeſtus Phiſicke ſhall winne credit and furderauce, that their authoritie ſhal fall to the ground: For thei are aſhamed after their docterſhipp, and long exerciſed weening practiſe to learne any more of Paracelſus and his folowers, not withſtandyng in greuious deceaſes, they haue no knowledge, either to councell or to helpe: Againſt all whiche dezeaſes Theophraſtus hath left to his folowers, true and approued remedies. After his Epiſtle he hath placed Paracelſus his picture, and his owne by it, hauyng Sentenſis in lattin adioyned. In the right hande of his picture he

holdeth a Serpente by the breſt the reſt of his bodie writhing about his armes and handes: Ouer the picture, is the lattin of this engliſhe placed. Queſtions framed vppon thy principles (ſpeakyng as it were to Paracelſus) taken out of the pith of nature, wee will in the light of Nature (beyng from God illuminated) reſolue expound and wee will eſtabliſhe the verities. Under this picture is this ſentence. Sophiſters alwaies writhing, trimbling and ſhouing to heare the voyces of them whiche wiſely charme them, neither are wee afraied of, nor make any accompt of you, nor yet with their vnlearned rayling, are we any thing moued, ſtandyng on the rocke of verity: others there be many like wherof I wil name ſome as Adam Bodeſten, Gerardus Doru, Michaell Toxites, Iohannes Huerius, Leonardus Turneihiſſerus, Ioſephus Quercetanus, Iohannes Chriſippus, Michael Neanger, Theodorus Suingerus, Theodorus Brickmanus, D. Rochefort and Lieband, Iohannes Gwinterus Andernacus: And a number of others fauourers and folowers of this Arte, aſwell of them that haue written thereof as haue not written ſence the tyme of Paraſelſus.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  Chapter 20. The true meaning of Paracelſus in dedicating his booke entituled Philoſophia magna to the Athenians, wherewith Eraſtus one of his aduerſaries is ſo greued.
               
                  BEcauſe ye folowers of the heathniſhe Phiſitions doe ſeeke to de
                     •
                  ace this auncient t
                     •
                   Chimicall Phiſicke, by ſlaunderyng Paracelſus (to whom the ignorant doe attribute the firſt invention thereof) obiecting againſt him, aſwell hereſie coniurations, lacke of learnyng, as alſo hurt and danger of mynerall medicines and obſcuritie in writyng, I will breefly explicate ſome obiections that be made againſt him, ſuch as maie giue ſome lyght to the better vnderſtandyng of him: And alſo ſett downe ſome cauſes why he is not vnderſtoode, by reaſen whereof his aduerſaries run at large, when vpon matters not by hym thought nor ment, they perſecute onely his ſhadowe and not him. One greate fault is found with him for that he dedicated his booke intituled Philoſophia magna vnto

the Athenians, whichr Eraſtus ſayeth bee barberuſſe Tnrckes and Mahumetans. His meaning herein was that all Arts and Philoſophie ought of neceſſetie to haue their foundation in light of the holy Scriptures as expreſly in the 119. leafe of that book and in the 38. leafe and in the 45. leafe, and in the 48. &amp; 84, leafe of the ſame booke, he plainly teacheth and expreſſeth. And to be ſhort in his book de Vermibus cap 5. he hath theſe words: In diuinitie eſpecially in the books of Salamon, Prophets, and in the new teſtament al Artes both naturall and ſupernaturall be conteined, out of them we may learne them. For in them is hidden the high treaſure of the whole world though it be hidden from the ſimple men: And becauſe the originall &amp; cauſe of all creatures doeth proſede onely from God, therefore God onely is to be ſought for, in him onely Arte doeth conſiſt, he onely is to bee conſidered, of hym and his worde all Arte is to be learned. Wherefore Paracelſus conſidering that the blindneſſe among vs Chriſtians, in the true foundation of Philoſophie (whiche ſeeke it of the Heathen whiche bee onely geſſers at the trueth beeyng not taught by Gods worde) is as great, as the ignoraunce of the Athenians was in the tyme of Sainct Paule, in the true

worſhipping of God, therefore be calleth vs Athenians: And therefore he layeth the foundation of Philoſophie in the light of the holy Scripture. The effect of that doctrine which Saincte Paule did preache to the Athenians Acts 17. was that God made the worlde and all thinges therein &amp;c. ſeeyng he giueth to all life and breath and all things: And hath made of one bloude all mankynd to dwell in all the face of the earth and hath aſſigned the tymes whiche weare ordained before, and the bands of their habitation, that they ſhould ſeeke the Lord, if ſo be they myght haue groped after hym, and found him, though doubtleſſe he bee not farre from euery one of vs: for in hym we liue, moue and haue our beeyng, as alſo certaine of your owne Poets haue ſaide &amp;c. how the doctrine of Paracelſus doeth agree with that of Saincte Paule, appereth by that foloweth: For in the ſame booke, the firſt wordes of the ſame treatiſe be theſe, All thinges are of God, therfore the power &amp; vertue of herbes be of God. The bringing forth of the Herbes is natural, but the bringing forth of his vertue is not naturall: For as God is not naturall, neither be the vertues naturall. All power and vertue is increate, becauſe God is without beginnyng increate. For all vertues and power

weare in God of heauen and earth, when the ſpirite of God was carried vppon the waters, euen ſo likewiſe when the heauen and earthe ſhall periſhe, all vertues ſhall returne to God againe, becauſe they had no beginning, but the viſible matter of ech thyng is increat for they were not in the begynnyng with God, for he created them of nothing, &amp; endued them with life and vertue.
               Sainct Auguſtine in his thirde booke De trinitate, hath the like doctrine, ſaiyng, virtus dei in terius operatur iſta creanda, againt, he ſaieth, Deus interius creans &amp; formaus. Alſo the firſt words of the prologe of the ſame booke, be theſe. There be two ſortes of influences of thinges, one is of the creatures, as of Heauen. Spirites &amp;c. the other procedeth &amp; commeth to vs emediately from God, whiche is the true influence. The firſt is Nature it ſelfe, and whatſoeuer God hath put in it. Alſo in his booke de occulta Philoſophia, he ſaiteh: The vertue &amp; power of God is the cauſe and originall of all creatures, and gouerneth all things: therefore we ought not to atribute and / giue the power of God to cratures, as the heathen do and, their folowers. And in the ſaid booke dedicated to the Athenians, fol. 13. he ſaieth the vertue and power of Stars, Herbes

&amp;c. be of God, yea, the vertue &amp; power is giuē only of God to al thinges, wherfore he calleth Annimam and the ſecretts of Nature which be in Miſteriis, whereby a man is healed and ſuche like Magnalia dei, becauſe thei procede onely from God. And the influen
                     •
                  is of God his giftes and vertues be in Arcanis, and the influence and ſeede together bring forthe all thinges by the grace of God. All vertues and power of thinges be of God onely, The work of ſtarres is like to the worke of the fire which doeth ſeethe the fleſhe in the pott, and giuethe no vertue to the fleſhe, it doeth onely ſeeth and prepare that which is in it: euen as the Carpenter which buildeth the houſe to be dwelt in, but he maketh not the dweler, he faſhoneth only the forme, and the outwarde houſe with his ſignes, by the whiche eache thing maie bee knowne accordyng to his forme and fation. By theſe and ſuch like teſtimonies whiche in many places, yea, euery where almoſt in his workes be found he ſheweth that the Philoſophie which he teacheth is agreable to yt which S. Paule teacheth ye 
                  Athenians, yt God dwelleth not farre from euery one of vs: ſo ſaiethe the pſalmiſt, thou arte nere vs O God, and al thy commandiments are trueth. The Prophet likewiſe ſaienh, I am God nere at hand,

and not God a farre of, ſateth the Lorde. Yet the great
                     •
                  elle of the d
                     ••
                  me power is not ſtreightened in ſpaces or limites, but is euery where, as the inuiſible and incorporall ſoule is diffuſed and diſper
                     •
                  ed into all the members &amp; partes of the bodie, and is not abſent from ā
                  ny ſeuerall parte, although it haue one priuate and principal ſeate in the whole bodie, yet it is diffuſed and diſperſed into the vaines, fingers and other partes: And if any member of the bodie be corrupte, and neede to be cut of, becauſe that member beeng dead by defect, hath not his proper vſe, that f
                     ••
                  ſhe which is rotten and▪ corrupte is cut of, without any detriment of the Soule, euen ſo the inviſible, incorpe
                     •
                   all and immeſurable God, we doe vnderſtande to be in this corporall &amp; cu
                     ••
                  mſcriptible world, and ſuf
                     •
                  erith no detriment, by the death or rather diſſolution of any thyng therein: he paſſe the through all thynges and ail thinges are full of him: Therefore both heauen earth ſhew forth his glorie: how is heauē yt ſcate of God, &amp; the earth his footeſtole, as the Pſalmiſt ſaieth: But that bothe in heauen and in earth his vertue might &amp; power repleniſheth al things. So therfore is God the parent of al thyngs, repleneſhing all the worlde, in the fulneſſe of his vertue. This kynde of Philoſophie certain

of the Poets before Sainct Paules tyme haue confeſſed, as Sainct Paule ſaiethe, for their great god Iupeter or 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   they cawhed 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   ſignifiyng by this worde that we liue by hym, for 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   is as muche to ſaie as to liue: Aratus alſo the Poet ſaied the waies, markets, gates and all thinges are Iouis Plena, ſo ſaide Democritus omnia plena diis ſunt, all thinges are full of gods. Therefore Chriſtians ought not to attribute the vertues power and worke of God to Nature or other creatures, or toOrigenes contra Celſum. lib. 4. 
                        •
                     o. 2. Fol. 84
                        •
                     . dead qualities, nor yet the office of life to dead thynges: For this cauſe Selſus the hereticke is worthely reprehended for attributyng the creation and generation of one thyng out of an other, as Bees out of ane Oxe, Waſpes out of a Horſe &amp;c. to the temperature of qualities of heat, cold, moiſture, and drineſſe &amp;c. and not to the workes of God: For to giue life or to quicken belongeth to no creature, but onely to the Diuine nature, onely God quickeneth all thyngs, and the ſpirite of God giueth life to all thinges. For firſt there muſt be, quod eſt Viuere afterwarde Vita, becauſe that Viuere is the cauſe of life, and life is the effect of liuyng: for Viuere bringeth forth life by force of Nature there muſt be Actor, before ther be Actio, for Agens begetteth Actionem, wee

muſt therefore confeſſe that there is a certain might and power, wherby al thyngs doe liue,, and as it were with a liuyng ſpring, be watered and erected into life, to the ende that they may liue: And becauſe they doe liue they obteined their beyng. God the Father whiche is principal Viuere, and Potentia viuendi, and tht Sonne whiche is Vita, is that might and yower and cauſe of all life, the fountaine and originall of liuing things, the which from him that is, Eſſe, doeth giue Eſſe and beyng to other thynges accordyng to the power of that whiche receiueth, and that moderateth the power of liuing and ſubſtance accordyngly. But this cauſe of life doeth neuer forſake life: for his inuiſible thynges vz. his vertue, power, and prouidence, doeth gouerne things viſible, liuyng and created, otherwiſe without that eternall and inuiſible vertue, nothing can abide nor continue ſtedfaſtly in his eſſence beyng &amp; life: for whē that vertue of God is taken away that gouerneth and quickned the thyng viſible, then it liueth nor moueth any longer, then hath it no beeyng longer, then is it ſubiect to corruption: therfore to giue life, to liue and to maintain life belōg to the diuine nature, ſo thē they be eternall. For this cauſe the nature of the Elementes, haue not of them ſelues: that

they cann avoyde corruption, neither doe they conſiſt of themſelues, but by the wordes and ſpirite of God: If to liue and to giue life and to maintaine life be immortall and eternall of their owne nature, then were thei not created neither can they ſuffer corruption: And if at their creation thynges be inſpired with life (for life is the cauſe that thynges haue their beeyng) and creation he the worke and vertue of the higheſt nature, and of the onely God of all thynges: for immittit ſpiritum &amp; creantur then it ſeemeth to be cheifly againſt the diuine glorie, to ſay that God hath giuen to nature or to any thing created and ſubiect to corruption the office of creatyng and giuing life and to bring forth things that were not: Likewiſe the ſecret operatiō and working of God giueth increaſe and noriſhment to all things, and the inner power of the creator, whiche filleth both heauen &amp; earth, giueth forme, figure and mouing to all things, yea, all thoſe thnigs whiche we call natures of thyngs whiche doe worke in this ſorte or that faſhion, do not proced outwardly nor are the workyng of creatures, but are the workes of the highe God whoſe ſeecrete power perſeth all thynges and cauſeth to be what ſoeuer is by any meanes. For vnleſſe he make it to be ſuch, or in ſuche

ſort, it ſhould be nothyng: Therefore it is not lawfull to ſaie that thoſe thinges that be proper to the diuine and vnſpeakable Nature, can naturally be in any thyng made by hym, or to attribute the power of God, to creatures, or dead accidents: vnleſſe you will vnderſtand, naturally to be the workyng of ſumma natura in his creatures, for this cauſe ſaieth Paracelſus the vertues of thinges be not naturall: And not only in that we are begotten and liue but alſo in that wee moue, wee haue it of the might and power of God, ſo ſaieth the Pſalmiſt thou haſt put thy hand vppon me, that is thou gouerneſt, conteineſt, makeſt, ordereſt, and beareſt me. And if thynges liue not and haue not motum vitulem, or ſtuendi refluendi naturam, they bee nothyng: And that which lacketh to be ſome what, doeth not hold and kepe his being ſo that truely it maie by no meanes be ſaied to haue being: for quies, bringeth forth nothing but motus, &amp; agendio operatio doth frame to it felf, that thing which is, or in what ſort it is: And ſeing Vita is motus quidam, hereof commeth beyng, and that whiche is exſtant, and the ſubſtance. Hereof it folowith that the liuely might 
                     •••
                   and power flowyng from the worde, which is life that is to ſay from the Sonne, doeth cauſe the materiall

thynges to be ſeene, to haue their beyng, and guieth to this beyng, in eache thyng, that which belongeth and is proper to it. Furthermore all thynges that bee begotten or made, bee made or begotten ex motu, but motus ipſe, quo motus, before it be moued, is quies for it is a rule that contrarius ortus contrariorum fit, ita vt contrario ortu contrariorum, vnde hoc ortum eſt pereat: as death folowith life, and of deathe, life riſeth, and of eſſe commeth non eſſe, and of non eſſe riſeth eſſe likewiſe of quies riſethe motus, and of motus, quies. Uppon this reaſon ſemeth to bee grounded that opinion whiche ſome doe hold, that thoſe things which ſeme here to dye. doe paſſe or goe, ad non eus: But the trueth is that the thynges whiche ſeeme to dye haue their beyng: For ſeeyng life is to haue beyng, whereof riſeth death, death alſo hath his beeyng, if life riſethe of death, likewiſe, if of that which is, is made that whiche is not, of neceſſity that whiche is, muſt not bee, if that which is riſe therof, in like maner if there be ceaſing, or leauing of, or quiet, of neceſſatie ther muſt be ceaſing of mouing, if mouing be engēdered This ſemeth to be a ſtrong argument, tothē which haue not taſted true Philoſophie: For hereby it ſemeth, yt by riſing of the contraries,

the contrary doeth either dye or els is to bee thoughe not to haue beeyng: but in truthe it is not ſo, but cleare contrary: For they bothe doe abide, neither doe they dye concernyng their eternall vertue: For in thinges vizible and materiall, if there be any death, it is the death of the bodie. But yet to come nerer to the truth, neither is there death of ye bodies, in that they be materiall, but there is made a diſſolution in that figure and forme whiche is now, by a certain departure: therfore only the faſhion &amp; forme of the body is diſſolued. But thoſe thyngs doe remaine &amp; haue their beeyng whereof thoſe thinges whiche ſhall liue, 
                     •
                  e repaired renewed and riſe. For ſeeyng the firſt and principall liuyug, by his omnipotencie is the cauſe that all thynges, that be or can be, haue their life beeyng and mouyng according to the capacitie of the thyngs ond ſubſtancies, as they bee parted and deuioed, for euery one hath his proper beeyng, his owne life▪ his proper mouing from 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   and 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : from Viuere &amp; Vita, what can death preuaile againſt cloſe vertues and powers which flowe and are deriued from that fountaine and line: Therefore ſeeyng they be eternall, whileſt they 
                     •
                  e in the matter or ſubſtance, if death doeth onely looſe the compoſition of them, and ſeparate them

aſonder, nothyng dieth and periſheth vtterly. Wherefore it is well ſaied that of life commeth death, becauſe there is a diſſoluyng of that bodie from the power &amp; abilitie of liuyng: And likewiſe there is a repairyng and a renuyng from death by thoſe guides into an other compoſition and thynges that is newly raiſed and ſprong: For God doeth create, when by his worde, he calleth things into beeyng. So the Father worketh euen vntill this tyme, as our ſauiour ſaieth: But the gentle reader muſtIohn 5. knowe that I doe not here ſpeake of man, that his ſoule after the diſſolution of it from the bodie doeth paſſe in to another bodie: For his ſoule is created by God, therfore thoſe thyngs can by no meanes be vnderſtanded of it.
            
            
               
                  Chapter. 21, Haw materia prima and miſceria magna was the beginnyng of all things according to Paracelſus his meanyng: and how al create were at one time in the increate.
               ONe other great falt doeth Eraſtus finde with Paracelſus, for that he ſaiethe that

                  Prima materia and Miſterium magnum was the beginnig of al thinges by ſeparation. Aud this miſterie he ſaieth to be increate hereof doeth Eraſtus conclude, that accordyng to Paracelſus creation, is nothyng but ſeperation. Though in this place and many other places of the ſame booke ad Athenienſes he doth intreate of the influencies which proceed from God (as in the firſt entery of the ſame booke he plainly confeſſeth) and of inwarde generations, &amp; fruits, and of inward ſeperations (for deepe and ſecrete purpoſe) yet if Eraſtus had delte indifferently with hym, he myght eaſely perceiue his meanyng in other of his workes, and alſo in this, where he findeth this horible herecie, concernyng the creation of vizible bodies to bee accordyng to Gods worde. For in his booke intituled Paramirum lil. 1. cap. 2. he confeſſeth accordyng to Gods holy worde that Prima materia mundi was Fiat: Aud in the ſame booke to the Athenians he ſaieth that Materia prima can net be perceined by ſenſes: Alſo in that booke Lib. 1. cap. primo he plainely affirmeth that the vizible matter of ech thing was create, for thei were not with God at the beginning: For God created them of nothing, and inſpired into them life and vertue &amp;c. So are we taught by Gods worde

that in the beginnyng after God had created the heauens and earth, the earth was rude, voide and emptie, that is to ſaie, it was imperfect and vnfruitfull, it brought for the no Herbes, Trees, nor Flowers, of diuers collours 
                     •
                  or ſweete ſmelles, nor yet any other thyng, whiche afterwarde did growe or ſpryng in it. The heauen alſo at the firſt lacked his ornaments, and ſo did the water. The earth continued baren vntill God by vertue of the word had commaunded it to be fruitfull, whereby it brought forth Herbes, Trees, and Plantes, which haue ſeeds eche of them in themſelues accordyng to ther kynd. The firmament was emptie vntill ſuche tyme God the creator of al thynges had by his word made the Sunne, Moone, and Stars, and appointed them their office, duetie, and propertie. The water alſo was baren vntill the ſame worde had made it fruitfull, of liuyng creatures in their kindes and made likewiſe foules in their kyndes, and bleſſed them, and gaue them commaundemēt to increaſe and multiplie. Alſo God created and made catell, beaſts and all creping things of the earthe accordyng to their kyndes, and likewiſe gaue them propertie to increaſe and multiplie. For as Sainct Auguſtine ſaieth, if wee conſider the nature of thinges properly

without Allegerye, this worde increaſe and multiplie doethe belong to all thynges which doe grow and come of ſeeds. Theſe leeds ſaith Paracelſus haue receiued by the diuine worde the power of multipliyng and tranſplant action their eſſence and properties. As Sainct Baſill ſaieth, nothyng is in any herbe or plante, which is not planted by the commaundement of the Almightie. Of theſe Semina Eſſentiae of their naturs, vertues, &amp; properties, &amp; their ſeperations doth he here intreat. The vertues of thinges, ſaieth he, were in God, when theTract. 1. Fol 10. Spirite of God was caried vpon the waters. And they be of God and are not naturall but God ſendeth forth his influences, euen as the ſunne doeth his beames, whiche be deuided in to diuerſe and wonderfull vertues. And God repleniſheth all thyngs with his vertues: And God did inſpire life and vertues into thoſe thinges whiche he created of nothyng. By theſe places and others to the like effect, it appeareth that he teacheth, that in the beginning the vertues of vizible thynges were vnited in their fountaine, neither were they ſeperated in diuerſity and multitude of offices: but after that by the vertue of the ſpirite, whiche was caryed vpon the waters, they were commaū
                  ded to doe their offices in the worldly miniſtration,

they were ſeperated and deuided in offices, life, eſſenties, and beyngs: We neede not here to imagine that theſe did proceede of Chaos, but out of the treaſures of the diuine wiſedome: but euen as the inuizible vertue in a carnell hath a might, ſcience, and power, able to worke and bryng forth diuerſe and ſundrie effectes, which in winter doe not appere but lye quiet, and in appointed and due tyme, bringeth forth the roote, bodie, pith, barke, and bowe, twige, leafe, fruite, and all theſe things, belongyng to the Tree, and deuideth and ſeperateth them in iuſt and true order, proportion, forme, ſigure, and qualitie,: So in the beginnyng were all the vertues vnited in God, their fountaine, vntill ſuch tyme as by the vertue of the word, they were commaūded to doe their ſeuerall officies in the worldly miniſterie. And as a man holdyng his peace doeth ſecretely reaſon with hymſelfe, and doeth comprehende in his reaſon all thoſe wordes which after he vttereth and ſpeaketh perticulerly in diuers ſeueral ſentences, words, and ſillables, which wordes be receiued of diuers hearers: So in the begynnyng all the might, vertue, and power, of thyngs were in God, vntill the word proceeded from God, wherby they were diſtributed to ech as ſeemed beſt to the diuine

wiſedome. But theſe vertues and power of God are not inuizible thynges, as the harte is in a beaſt, or as it is parte of a beaſt, but they be in thynges, as the beames of the Sunne be in thoſe wherevppon it ſhineth, yet the ſubſtance of the Sunne is not in them, neither is God in part any where but in ſingulis totus and in onibus omnis. And as the ſoule diſperſed through the whole bodie, is wholy in euery member, and yet doeth not giue to eche member his giftes, of his office worke and miniſterie, but to the eye he giueth onely the office of leyng, and not to heere, to the eare he giueth heeryng and not to ſee, and to other members likewiſe: ſo god beeyng Diffuſus in ſingulis, repleniſheth all thynges eſſencially, both aboue and benethe, within and without, and round about, and doeth ſeperate &amp; diſtribute, to euery thing, as it pleaſeth hym: As to a tree he giueth life to growe, &amp; not to feele, to beaſts he giueth feeling &amp; not to diſcerne: to Aungels &amp; to ye ſoule he giueth to deſerne, &amp; if God do withdraw any of theſe things frō any thing, immediately it ſhall be come vnprofitable in the vniuerſall body, euen as ye member of the body wil be vnprofitable, &amp; without vſe, from which God hath withdrawen his gifte &amp; vertue: Likewiſe God hath ſeperated

perated &amp; parted the vertues of herbs &amp; plants among them elues, gyuyng to ſome vertus ſtipticke, to others vertues lax
                     ••
                  iue &amp;c. AndPeri A
                        •
                     chō Lib 2. Cap. 1. Fol. 
                        •
                     74. T
                        •
                      1. Pſalm 102. De cognitione verz vitae Cap. 23. To. 9. ſo i
                     •
                   Mineralle
                     •
                  , A
                     ••
                  nailes and at thyngs vizible, b
                     •
                   they deuided in 
                     ••
                  ueralvertues one from an other: ſo ſaieth olde Father Origen God the parent of all things, for the health of al his creatures hath deuided and ſeperated to eche thing here, ineffabilem rationem of his word and wiſedome: And the Pſalmiſt ſaieth all his vertues be his miniſters and workers doyng his will. Therefore ſaieth Sainct Auguſtine, every creature doth feele God to be in it by ſomewhat. And becauſe Paracelſus attributeth the beginning of thyngs, aſ
                     •
                   ell to Materia prima, which as is aforeſaid, is fiat, which I iudge to be the diuine will, &amp; the firſt councell of the ſpirituall motiō, as to Miſterium magnum, which he meaneth to be Chriſt accordyng to theſe old verſes.
               
                  Adeſto lumen rerum, pater omnipatens deus
                  Adeſto lumen luminis, miſterium et Virtus dei
                  Adeſto ſanct
                        •
                      ſpiritus, patris &amp; filij copula
               
               It is manifeſt by theſe words, he meaneth God the father, and the ſonne whome he confeſſeth to be the creator of all thynges viſible, and from whom all Miſteries did proceede. For it is not to be vnderſtanded that God the

father, did create all thynges without the wiſdome, word, and vertue, that is to ſaie, without the onely begotten or God our Lorde Jeſus Chriſt. For ſo God ſaied of the perſon, of the wiſedome, vz I was with hym making all thinges, ſei mone eius coeli confirmati ſunt, &amp; ſpiritu eius omnes vires eorum: For the workes of the ſonne be the workes of the father: and the father worketh in the ſonne for ſo he ſaieth, the father which is in me o
                     ••
                  h his worke: and againe I doe the workes of the father: So the father worketh onely, workyng in hym and by hym whome he hath begotten. In this ſorte Chriſt that great miſtery was the beginnyng of all thynges. And becauſe all thoſe vertues wherewith God hath inſpired, thyngs viſible and materiall, do proceed and are deriued from that fountaine and line vz from the great Miſterie, he calleth them likewiſe Miſteria ſaiyng, that greate Miſterie, hath giuen, ſeperated, and deuided, to all thynges their generall Miſteries. And ſometymes he calleth the ſeedes, the receptacles of the vertues, by the name of Miſteria like wiſe: But Eraſtus faſly &amp; corruptly ſaieth, that he affirmeth that all thynges did proceed out of Miſterium magnum, whereas his words be, that all miſteries did proceede out

of Miſterium magnum: And that great Miſtery doth giue to al things their general Miſteries &amp;c. And that whiche is eternall, is the cauſe of all thyngs viſible and materiall. God created viſible thyngs, and inſpired into them life and vertues: ſo all thynges be of God, aſwell thynges materiall and vizible, as alſo the vertues power and might of thynges, which he often calleth Miſteria.
               
               Fordermore, whereas Paracelſus ſaieth all thyngs created were together at one time in the increate, as butter and cheſe be in the milke and wormes in the cheſe, whiche after growe in it, and as the Image is in the wood before the Keruer hath made it. Eraſtus ſaieth that this muſt needes be the Chaos of Anaxagoras. The true meanyng of Paracelſus herein is, that euery creature maie iuſtly bee ſaide to be in God, becauſe without God there is nothyng: but yet they be not ſo in God, that they be of his ſubſtance, or parte of hym: For it followith not, that the thyng that is in an other, is that thyng in which it is: For wine is in the botle, yet the wine is not the botle: The ſunn is in the glaſſe and the glaſſe in the ſoun,De cognitione verz vitae Cap. 25. 10. 9. yet neither of them is that ye other is. Sainct Auguſtine teacheth by expreſſe wordes, that euery creature is in the creator, and God is in

euery creature: for ſaieth he euen as if a man were at Rome, if he doe thinke vppon the whole Cittie, and comprehended, and included all the Cittie, with all the people thereof in his mynd by immagination, it may very well be ſaide, that Rome is in his mynde, and his mind is in Rome: ſo is it truely affirmed, that God is in euery creature, and euery creature is in God: But to goe a little nerer to the matter euen as in a little corne or grane, all thynges be inuizible at one tyme, whiche in proceſſe of tyme doe appere in the ſtalke and eare, as the roote, ſtalke, knottes or ioyntes, blade eare, bloſſom, chaffe, briſſels, and corn, and nothing riſeth, commeth or is in the ſtalke or eare whiche is not deriued, or deſended frō the ſecret treaſure of the corne or graine: For all thoſe thynges were firſt in the graine not in the hu
                     •
                  ge quaintitie, but by vertue and power whiche cauſeth all thoſe things, and hath the commyng to worke all thoſe ſeuerall formes, figures, and thynges, belongyng to the ſtalke and eare, in iuſt and true order and proportion, by dewe ſeparation and diuizion: as in the ſame graine all thynges were inuizible whiche in tyme did growe in to the ſtalke and eare, ſo is it to be thought, in the beginnyng when God created all thynges of

nothyng, he had all thynges together in hym which were made.
            
            
               
                  Chapter 22. Of the ſeperation of vizible and materiall bodies.
               
                  AS concerning the ſeparation of materiall and vizible bodies Paraſelſus in his booke de meteoricis axpreſſionibus ſaieth, that in the beginning God created the iiii. Elements of nothing by his word, fiat: and that nothyng was made ſomewhat by hym, and was made into one ſubſtance and one bodie, ſo that all thynges were included in that one vz materia prima. After that he ſeparated ech of them out of that as pleaſed hym, wherefore God did woorke ſix daies, vntill he had drawen out, ſeperated and formed, out of Materia prima materiàs vltimas, yt is to ſaie all creatures, and had put in eche of them peculierly his proper nature condition and ſtate, and placed and ordeined hym in his place and mantion, ſo that after that he ceaſed from creatyng: and all places were repleniſhed

with the number of creaturs of all kinds and their Eſſentiis: Euen as the Potter hath his earth or claie before hym, in which be contained diuers formes of veſſelles and inſtruments, for he maie out of one lumpe of claye frame and faſhion a thouſand and more ſondrye faſhions of pots and veſſelles: Likewiſe the Carpenter and image maker maie forme out of one peece of timber what he liſt, ſo that he knowe how to ſeperate from it, that which is ſuperfluous and not meete for the Image, ſo God did drawe and ſeperate all creatures out of one lumpe and matter which he made of nothyng: And as the earth in the winter is bare rude and baren, without beautie, but yet hath in it al colours, as greene, blewe, white, with all other fine and noble colours and all other things, which in the ſpring and ſommet doe appeare and come forth, whiche a man woulde not beleue to be in it vnleſſe he did ſee thē, euen ſo all the diuerſitie of bodies did proceed out of materia prima: This doctrine doeth ſeeme to agree with that place of the holy Scripturs whiche ſaiethe God made the worlde de materia infromi vel inuiſa. And with Sainct Baſill and others which affirme that there was ſome what before this vizible world: And it auoideth certaine obiections,

whiche certaine heretikes did make againſt Gods holy worde, and did aſke from whom the water was, vpon which the ſpirite of God was caried: for it was not written before that God made the waters and ſuche like queſtions: for the water is not ſo called in this place that we ſhould thinke it to be ſuche as we can nowe ſee and touche, neither was the earth which is there called voide and inuizible, ſuch as this whiche maie bee ſeene and handled, but where it is ſaide in the beginnyng God made heauen and earth, vnder the name of heauen and earth, all creatures are ſignified, which God made and created out of it afterwarde: For prima materia was made, confuſed, and without forme, out of the which all thynges were made, whiche were ſeuerally formed: And therefore it is rightly beleeued that God made all thynges of nothyng: For though all thynges were made of that prima materia, yet that was made of nothyng: and that prima materia whiche God made of nothyng was calle Co
                        •
                     lum &amp; terra, as it is ſaied in the beginnyng God made heauen and earth not becauſe it was ſo preſently, but becauſe it was ſo potentia for it is written that God made heauen after: Euen as we maie ſaie of a kernell of an aple, that in it bee the

roote, bodie, bowes, leues, and fruites, notSapient. 
                        ••
                     . In hexam
                        •
                     . ho
                        ••
                     il. 
                        •
                     . becauſe they be ſo preſently, but becauſe they wilbe ſo after. So it was ſaide in the beginnyng God made heauen and earth, as it were the ſeede of heauen and earth, whileſt the matter of heauen and earth was therein confuſedly. And becauſe it was certaine, that the heauen and earth ſhould thereof be made, therefore the ſame matter was called the heauen and earth. This is the opinion of Sainct Auguſtine in diuers places of his workes: and in his xii. book Confeſſionum he ſaieth God made this world de materia informi which he made of nothyng out of which he made all thynges which be in this world: And an auncient Chimiſt likewiſe ſaiethe de ſimplici ſubſtantia, primordialis cuiuſlibet elemē
                     tii elemēta que ſunt materia naturae, fuerant pure creata cum diuina ſeparatione.
               
            
            
               
                  Chapter 23. Certaine notes and cautions giuen for the better vnderſtandyng of this Chimicall Peiſicke.
               THus I haue giuen thee gentle reader a taſte of the dealing of Eraſtus aganſt Paracelſus,
                  
he hath ſtuffed fiue volummes with the 
                     ••
                  ke ſtuffe, for ſuche matters in
                     •
                  einyg againſt hym as either he is ignorant and vnſkilfull in, and which he doeth not vnderſtand, or ſuch as he hath miſtaken and for ſuch as by hym be falſly gathered, or peruerſly re
                  
                     •
                  eited or craftely handled, and maliciouſly mangled, hauyng either ſomethyng cut from them, or ſome more added, or racked out of their place, or wreſted to a wrong meanyng whiche the place giueth not, or elſe whiche in ſome other place of his worke he him ſelf doth better expound and declare, and by ſuch as be perfect and true principles of true Philoſophy agreable with the puritie of Gods word, contrarie to the rules of the Ethnickes, Paracelſus bo
                     ••
                  eth the riddles, parabels, &amp; dark ſpeches wherewith he ſhadowith and hireth this Arte, and the matter whereof the vniuerſall medecine is made, and the operation and workyng thereof out of the Scriptures: And becauſe in ſuche writyng he muſt obſerue the ſence of the Scripturs, and alſo therein comprehend the Doctrine he hath in hande, therefore be thoſ
                     •
                   phraſes, ſentences, and ſpeches, darke and ſubiect to cauilation. Therefore who ſo euer wil rightly vnderſtand hym wher he writeth of our creation, conception▪ &amp; birth

and alſo of Babtiſme, regeneration, both kindes of death, reſerection &amp;c. Muſt know and vnderſtand this auntient Chimical rule, that the Chimicall worke in parte, ex creatione hominis deriuatur: Generally in other places. where he doeth not purpoſly intreate of Diuinitie he that will vnderſtand hym rightly, muſt know and vnderſtand that he teacheth Metaphiſicall principles in naturall thyngs, then ſhall he vnderſtand how all thynges participate in nature, whereby the nature of the thyng that is left perfect, doeth deſire and couite his perfection, and the one is made perfect by an other by reaſon of their concordance and agrement, whiche doe participate together in nature for Natura, natura delectatur &amp; coniungi appetit which is ye cauſe of perfection. Then ſhal he perceiue what doth ioyn the Elementes together in the worke of Nature beeyng ſo contrarie, and wherewith they be quickened. Then ſhall he perceiue howe God woorketh in his creatures, and how all parts hang together as it were in one chaine. Then ſhall the reader perceiue and find in his great Philoſophie dedicated to the Athenians (wherein Eraſtus doeth finde ſo many faults) a treatiſe of the right &amp; true obſeruing the Sabbaoth daie, wherein he hath taught

deliuered, and ſet doun many good and wholeſome preceptes for the keepyng of the Sabbaoth rightly in the plaine letter ther written: yet couertly and darkely, hath he hidden as many rules and preceptes of true naturall Philoſophie in that treatiſe, as of the kepyng the Sabbaoth, though in the bare letter no ſuche thyng appeareth, but filii ſcientiae maie vnderſtand them: Therefore gentle reader in readyng of hym and other Chimicall writers follow their owne counſell and warning, that is ſearch out their meanyng and cleeue not to the bare letter of their wordes, ſticke not in the barke and rinde, but finde out the pithe, haue not regarde to the bodie, but to the ſoule and life of that which is written, otherwiſe thou ſhalt doe the Author great wrong and thou ſhalt neuer vnderſtand hym: and if in one place the Author write darkly, in ſome other place ſome particuler thyng maie bee found that ioyned with the other may explicate the meanyng, for they diſperſe their meaning in ſeuerall places, to the ende they would be vnderſtode onely of the deligent and painfull reader and not of the vnworthie. As concernyng his ſtraunge wordes and phraſes of ſpeche in his medicines and practiſe, they are to be learned, by manuell experience and practiſe

by the fire, which is the Chimicall Phiſitions Scholemaiſter, ſo ſhall he vnderſtand his ſtraunge wordes and phraſes of ſpech by his meanyng, but he muſt not thynke to finde his meaning by his ſtraunge words and phraſes: as for example he that would learne what this worde Alcool meaneth, he muſt knowe what Contritio Philoſophica is, ſo ſhall he find that it doth not ſignifie a powder ſtamped and moſt finely ſerched, though he did waſh it in water, and take the powder after the water be dried awaie. Againe he that knoweth what Circulation meaneth doeth knowe that theſe figures 3000. do not ſignifie three thouſand yeres: Likewiſe he that can ſkill to reſolue ech thyng into his three ſubſtancies, and hath reſpect to the liuely vertues of thynges and not cleaue to the ded qualities, maie finde what Sanguinea, Cheri, Anthos, &amp; ſuch like be in Paracelſus▪
                   &amp; would not call his darke words Diabolicall as Eraſtus and others doe, beſids this he that knoweth that by diuerſe operations by the fire one thyng maie bee made to woorke diuerſe effects, ſhal find the difference betwene Arcana, Eſſentiae Miſteria &amp;c. And ſhall finde this rule true that Medicus in ſecunda vita averit a
                        •
                     tem ſuam. Likewiſe he that knoweth the worke and effect of Putrefactio
                  
                  Philoſophica, would not ſaie that medicines prepared by the fire do get a Corroſiue Nature or hurte by the fire, though it be by Calcination, yea the Chimicall Phiſition knoweth by Fixation to take awaie all venenoſitie from thynges: And to take awaye their ſharpeneſſe, by ablution, and ſolution. Beſides this he that is inſtructed, that it is againſt the grounds and principles of the Chimicall Phiſicke to miniſter any Marcheſitt or metall, to any pacient inwardly, before it bee made Volatile and Spirituall, ſo that it can not bee reduced into Metall againe, will not ſaie that Vitrum antimonii (which purgethe and ſhaketh the bodie ſo ſore, or the common Aurum potabile and ſuch like) be mediciens warranted by this Arte, or by Paraſelſus, whiche ſo laborreth to teach the ſeparation of the pure form the impure. But he would perceiue that he is taught fuſtio ſpiritum &amp; non corporum, but they would rather turne this accuſation vpon the Ethnicke Phiſitions and their folowers whiche ſticke not to miniſter the ſcales of Iron and Braſſe in powder inwardly,Aetius Lib. 14. Ma
                        •
                     heolus in dioſcoe Lib. 5. Rōdolerius Some ſticke not to miniſter Quickſiluer raw, ſome when it is burned into aſhes: So do thei miniſter gold in leaues, &amp; pretious Stones, brimſtone &amp; vitriell alſo in powder.
            
            
               
               
                  Chapter. 24. Of the Coeleſtiall medicynes of Paracelſus: and matters touchyng his perſon and ignorance.
               
                  
                     ERaſtus doth beſids theſe things finde great falte with the celeſtiall medicine of Paracelſus, ſaiyng they haue their ſtrenthe and power of the deuilles and euell ſpirites, and not af God nor by the miniſterie of good Aungels, this he would haue vs beleeue vppon his bare reporte, but in truith Paracelſus excludeth from the true, pure, and auncient Magike, and from his coeleſtiall medicine, all Nigromancie, Sorcery, Ceremonies, Coniurations, and all maner of inuocations of deuilles, Demones &amp; euill ſpirits: And he giueth an eſpeciall charge that this Arte be onely vſed to doe good, and not to the preiudice nor hurte of any bodie: and that it be done without Ceremonies, Coniurations, Inuocations, Conſecrations, Bleſſinges, and allmaner ſuperſtytion whereby it becometh vngodly. He ſaieth that the diuell

can not cure nor helpe an ague, nor the toothePhiloſophia magna tr
                        •
                     c 3. O
                        •
                     cul
                        •
                     a▪ Philoſo. Cap. 2. ache: And that the diuell hymſelf with all his legions hath not ſo muche power nor authoritie, that he is able to breake one po
                     •
                  t, muche leſſe is he able to make him: alſo he ſaieth that euell ſpirites are Gods butchers and executioners, which doe execute nothyng beſides the commiſſion of their magiſtrate, that is to ſay, of the diuine Mageſtie, therefore he concludeth, that all coniurations be againſt Gods worde, the diuine lawe and light of Nature, whether they bee vſed to Spirites, Rootes, Herbes, Stones, or any thynge els: And that Nigromantiers, and Conturers, are like to theues, liuyng in woodes, whiche robbe and kill ſo long as God permitteth them, and no longer, but when the time is come when their wickedneſſe ſhal bee made manifeſt, and the hower of their puniſhment is at hand, then by one meanes or other, they come into the hangmans handes, which giueth them the reward of their worke, ſo is it with the nigromantier and coniurer whiche receiue iuſtly their rewarde bothe in this worlde, and in the worlde to come: beſides this he ſaieth the diuell is the pooreſt of all creatures, and moſt miſerable,Occulta Philoſo. Cap. 
                        •
                     . and that he hath no money, neither hath he any power ouer money, therfore can not giue that

he hath not, nor hath power ouer: to this purpoſe I coulde alledge out of hym a number of teſtimonies, but you ſhall vnderſtand that the cauſe why he ſometyme vſeth 
                     ••
                  dicines drawen out of Vegetables, and ſometyme out of Mineralles, and ſometyme theſe heauenly medicines is this: It the deceaſes haue light originalls, or beginnyngs, of meat and drink, or other fruites of the earth, thoſe maie be cured by ſuch medicines drawen out of herbes, or rather with their Arcana: and in ſuche deceaſes if they be not long circulated nor in the remote parts but in primis officinis ciborū
                   the groſſe medicines of the heathens maie preuaile or at leaſt thei may flatter ſom diceaſes: But if the deceaſe be cauſed by Minerals, Metalles, or Markeſits, in the principall partes of the body, or in the Balſamum of man, then they muſt be cured by medicine drawen out of Metalles, or Markeſits, becauſe ſuche deceaſes will not yealde to medicines drawen out of herbes or rootes, &amp;c. Becauſe the roots of thoſe deceaſes are not ſo ſoone reſolued as the other: therefore they neade pure ſpirites, for paſcimur nutrimur, curamur natura Mercurii id eſt ſpiritu, ſaieth an auntient Chimiſt. Likewiſe if diſceaſes be cauſed by influencies of ſtarres, they are to be holpen

by influencie: And cauſes of inuiſible deceaſes in the inuiſible parte of man: and thoſe grefes and paines whiche be cauſed by ſupernaturall meanes, will not be holpen by any meanes aforeſaied, but they muſt be remedied by ſuch meanes as they were cauſed, that is by ſuche maner of cure as hath power to worke in to the inuiſible part of man. If Paracelſus ſome tyme woulde be dronke after his Countrey maner I can not excuſe hym no more then I can excuſe in ſome nations glottenie, in other pride, and contempt of all others in compariſon of themſelues, in others breach of promiſe and fidilitie, in others diſſimulation, triflyng and muche babling: but lett the doctrine bee tried by the worke and ſucceſſe, not by their faultes in their liues.
               As for lacke of methode in his woorkes, I ſaie his bokes intituled Paramirum, his boks de vita longa, lacke no methode. But if in any other of his works he did not obſerue methode, he did it becauſe he would diſperſe his minde in ſeuerall partes, to the ende he would be vnderſtoode onely of the Children of the Arte. The ignorance in the lattin tongue is vntruly obiected againſt hym: as appereth by his bokes de Tartare written in latten, and his epiſtles written to Eraſmus in latten and

by diuerſe his lectures: and by his commentaries vppon Hipocrates &amp;c.
               
            
            
               
                  Chapter 25. The conclution of the Author.
               
                  THus thou haſt harde gentle reader, how this Auncient Chimicall Phiſicke, had his begynnyng from Abraham, or at leaſt from Hermes Triſmegeſtus, and after in the Aegiptian prieſts which were kynges, or of the kynges bloud, it had his continuaunce. From whom it hath beene deriued amongſt the godlieſt and beſt learned Philoſophers, in to diuerſe partes of the worlde, which haue ſhadowed and hidden it in parables, and darke ſpeaches to auoide contempte among the fooliſh and vnworthy readers, and yet ſo that it ſhould not be hidden from thoſe whiche were meete to heare and vnderſtande ſuche ſecreets and miſteries: Alſo thou haſte harde how the newe Phiſicke of the heathen hadd his begynnyng of late yeares, in compariſonne of the other from the heathen and Idollaters whiche were without the true

knowledge of God. Thou haſt harde alſo the difference between theſe two Phiſiks, whereby thou maieſt be able to iudge, whether this auntient Phiſicke be vaine without beginnyng, as it hath been obiected. Thou haſt hard the explanation of certaine obiections laied againſt Paracelſus, whereby thou maiſt the better iudge of the reſt, wherewith he is charged. Now I doe craue of thee gentle reader as I haue taken this in hand to do thee good, ſo thou wilt interpret my meaning to the beſt, if any thyng mi
                     •
                  like thee, doe not picke at euery ſillable and worde, but conſider whileſt mine eye was bent to the matter, which I did folowe and intreate of, wordes may eſely eſcape and be miſplaced, eſpecially with hym which lacketh eloquence, &amp; vſeth not to write. If thou vnderſtand not ſomewhat that is here written, doe not therefore condemne it, but kepe ſilence, as Pithagoras his ſcholars did, and be quiet, or elſe learne of others. If any thyng herein ſhall ſeeme to be abſurde &amp; contrary to thy mynde, becauſe it is contrary to Ariſtotle Galen Auicen &amp;c. doe not therefore reiecte it, but waye it with an indifferent iudgement, and take not all thynges for Oracles which the heathen haue taught. And if any thyng herein be amiſſe (for no mans writynges

can be warranted in all,) doe not giue iudgement and pronounce definite ſentence agaiuſt the whole, by reaſon of ſome one perticuler. And if thou perceiue my meanyng to be Godly and ſound, doe not condemne me of error by reaſon of wordes, not rightly placed, nor aptly vſed, for error conſiſteth in ſence and meanyng, and not in ſound of wordes. And though I write not to the latter Phiſitions the folowers of the heathens, that be practiſioners, and wilfully bent againſt this Chimicall Phiſicke, becauſe thei be like knottie and burſ
                     •
                  e woode, not fit for framyng timber, but will gnawe the line wherewith they bee ledd, and girne erre and ſhew their angrie teeth at their leaders, and will not now become ſcholars: Yet becauſe this my writyng can not eſcape their handes, neither can they well digeſt it, therefore I doe admoniſhe them that if they take in hand to anſwer it, that they anſwer ech part therof, and doe not diſmember it, nor put any thing to it, nor take any thing from it, and that they do not aunſwer with railing ſcoffes, quippes, mockes, tauntes, and lies, as ſome ignorant vſe in their talke againſt this Arte: And as Eraſtus vſeth in his writing: And as Bernar dus Deſſ
                        •
                     ius a Doctor of Phiſicke of Colen, vſeth againſt one Fedro a Chimiſt,

after he was ded, which by his writyng as ſemeth may teche a ſchole of ſcoldyng and railyng: For ſuche maner eloquence may not paſſe for proofe amōg the indifferent readers, neither is it worthie to be aunſwered, neither may the bare auctoritie of Ariſtotle, Galen, Auicen, and ſuche like ſerue for aunſwer againſt the Scripturs of God, nor againſt the liuely artificiall proofe by fire, followyng Nature, but with charitable wordes, and ſounde arguments dependyng vppon Gods worde, the true touchſtone that can not erre, and vppon vnfallible experience by the fire, the Phiſitions maiſter, let the matter be tried: then no doubt ſome good may come by this contention to the ſicke, and deceaſed, which hath need of the Phiſition: and the doctrine of Phiſicke, will exalt and lift vp his hed, and the trueth of it ſelf will appeere, as fire doeth by knockyng of two flintes together: whiche the moſt high God of whom cōmeth all healyng, and which hath created the Phiſition becauſe of neceſſity, graunt for his deare ſonne Jeſus Chriſte his ſake, which is the life and trueth.
            
            Amen Valete 1585.
            
            
         
      
   

