
   
      
         
            A briefe refutation of Iohn Traskes iudaical and nouel fancyes Stiling himselfe Minister of Gods Word, imprisoned for the lawes eternall perfection, or God's lawes perfect eternity. By B. D. Catholike Deuine.
            Falconer, John, 1577-1656.
         
         
            
               1618
            
         
         Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00535
            STC 10675
            ESTC S114688
            99849912
            99849912
            15085
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00535)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15085)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 789:22)
         
         
            
               
                  A briefe refutation of Iohn Traskes iudaical and nouel fancyes Stiling himselfe Minister of Gods Word, imprisoned for the lawes eternall perfection, or God's lawes perfect eternity. By B. D. Catholike Deuine.
                  Falconer, John, 1577-1656.
               
               102, [2] p.   
               
                  English College Press],
                  [Saint-Omer :
                  Imprinted with license M. DC. XVIII [1618]
               
               
                  B. D. is a pseudonym for John Falconer--STC.
                  Place of publication and printer from STC.
                  Includes index.
                  Apparently Falconer gained knowledge of Traske's views when both were in prison; for Traske's later recantation of his views see STC 24178--STC.
                  Running title reads: A briefe refutation of Io. Traskes Iudaisme.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Traske, John, d. ca. 1638.
               Jews --  Dietary laws --  Early works to 1800.
               Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-02
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-02
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A BRIEFE REFVTATION OF IOHN TRASKES IVDAICAL AND NOVEL FANCYES.
            Stiling himſelfe Miniſter of Gods Word, impriſoned for the Lawes eternall Perfection, or Gods Lawes perfect Eternity.
            
               By B. D. Catholike Deuine.
            
            
               Gal. 3. Verſ. 13.
            Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for vs.
            Imprinted with Licence, M. DC. XVIII.
         
         
            
            
            THE PREFACE.
            
               THE Controuerſies handled in this short Treatiſe are two: The firſt is of the Iewes Sabaoth, Apoſtolically tranſlated into the euer memorable day of our Sauiours Reſurection. The ſecond, whether al forts of meates may be lawfully now eaten by Chriſtiās: diſputed againſt Iohn Traſke, of a Puritan miniſter lately grown halfe a lew in his ſingular opinions concerning the old Sabaoth, and Moyſaical difference of meates, held by him &amp; many other men and women, obſtinately profeſſing and practiſing the ſame doctrines, as morall Lawes

vnreapealed by Chriſt, and neceſſarily now to be obſerued by Chriſtians. His only learning is a litterall knowledge of Scriptures, and ſome little Hebrew and Greeke lately learned for the better vnderſtanding of them: which alone he holdeth ſufficient, not only to inſtruct vs in al points of faith, but to direct vs alſo in our particuler thoughtes, ſpeaches, &amp; actions; ſo as no māner of ſpeach is by Chriſtians to be vſed, no meate to be eatē, no kind of apparell to be worne &amp;c. not particularly expreſſed and warranted in Scripture. Humāe iudgment &amp; experience (wherby we are originally taught to diſcerne the naturall goodnes and euil of al our actions, and to make a conſcience of them) being ſo little regarded by him, as he ridiculouſly deemeth it not to be any rule at all to direct Chriſtian men in common manners and morality of life; God himſelfe hauing by a higher law contayned in the old &amp; new Teſtament, particulerly inſtructed them in

all holy and needfull knowledge.
            Out of which ground he deduceth, as I shall haue ſeuerall occaſions to declare afterwards, ſtrange Concluſions &amp; Diſtinctions not eaſy to be diſtintly knowne &amp; refuted by any learned man that hath not from his owne mouth hard them. This was my chiefe reaſō to write theſe two Controuerſies againſt him, wherby ſōe of his diſciples may peraduenture be reclaymed from his groſſe doctrines; and other itching eared people now inclinable to his Sect, may be moued vtterly to forſake him. And one ſoule ſo happely gayned to a neerer degree of truth, will make me thinke a few ſpare houres well beſtowed from better ſtudies. Learned men alſo will gladly, perchance, ſpare an idle houre or two to read a new Controuerſy, breifly, as I could contriue it, and plainly expreſſed. Smaller errours, and of leſſe conſequence then theſe nouell fancies of Traske haue

been by ſundry holy Fathers anſwered in large volums, which may well ſerue to shew my labours not wholy needles.
            Little ſparkes of fire not timely quenched, ſoone grow into flames, that deuoure houſes and Citties. Small wounds waxe feſtered ſoares, when they are not ſpeedily cured. Single ſeedes of tare and cockle ſowne in fields amongſt good Corne make great bundles in harueſt, fit only for combuſtion. And the miſerable experience of theſe latter times abounding with nouel &amp; heretical doctrines, witneſſeth, that as plaguy people are for feare of infecting others carefully to be ſecluded; and ſmall leakes in a ship are ſpeedily to be ſtopped for the ſafety of ſuch perſons as ſayle in it: ſo all morall and pious diligence is by Gouernours and Guiders of ſoules to be vſed for the timely preuention and ſuppreſſing of pernicious opinions, with which Traſke is ſo ſtored, as he is in very few pointes of our Chriſtian

fayth rightly perſuaded.
            He hath 8. arguments to proue that Melchiſedech was the holy Ghoſt mentioned Geneſ. 14. Hebr. 7. He is infallibly aſſured, that he himſelfe hath truly repented, and is made ſure of his eternall election in Chriſt: and that he can in this life neither ſinne, nor repent any more. Likewiſ, he is able to collect out of Scripture when Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob and other Saints were truly. penitent and iuſtified in Gods ſight: and will often preſume to tell his diſciples, whether at all, or when, they truly repented. Yea he is able, as I haue heard, by Phiſiognomy, to make certaine gheſſes whether particular perſons ſhal be damned or ſaued. His owne and his diſciples prayers are commonly roaringes, and ſuch loud out-cries as may be heard in diſtant roomes and houſes, voluntarily framed, and filled for the moſt part with frequent imprecations, that God would confound the aduerſaries and

perſecutors of his little flocke, ſuch as walke in the luſt of their owne fleſh, eating like the Idolatrous Gentiles all prohibited and vncleane meates; prophaning his holy Sabaoth, and changing it into another day neuer comanded by him, but by themſelues inuented; Frequently rendring thankes to God for keeping them ſo holy as hitherto he hath done, and deſiring him according to their vprightnes to bleſſe and protect them.
            Pretended reuelations alſo are not wanting amongſt them. He will tell you of ſtraung abſtinences from food and other great auſterities vſed by himſelfe, notwithſtanding his cheekes ſeeme full, and his body ſtill fatt and in good liking. He will with great glory vtter the ſingular approuement made of him in his Miniſteriall ordination, when other Countrey Schollers were reiected, himſelfe hauing neuer byn more thē a gueſt in any Vniuerſity. His excellency aboue others was chiefly

occaſioned by a perfect Summe of all Diuinity, only abſtracted by his owne Confeſſion out of Muſculus his cōmon Places. When he was a ſchoolmaſter at a Gentlemans houſe in Somerſetshire to a few Grammer ſcholers, he could write and ſpeake pure latin, as he grauely tould one of his fellow priſoners, which in his riper and maturer ſtudies ſince of Diuinity, he hath quite forgotten, and altered his Ciceronian wonted ſtile into the humble and plaine phraſe of Scripture; and indeed much more barbarous. When he was reprehended by an Aduerſary for denying the minor of an enthimeme, he produced in excuſe of his groſſe ignorance Rhamus logique, only affirming an enthimeme to be an imperfect ſillogiſme, and ſayd, that Ramiſts and Ariſtotelians could not vnderſtand each others termes and manner of diſputing but after much practiſe togeather. He will bragge of many bookes written, and ſome of them dedicated by him to his

Maieſty, who becauſe he eateth not willingly ſwines flesh, he ſuppoſeth by his Princely nature halfe framed and fitted to imbrace and profeſſe his doctrines, which he is confident to haue generally one day held in our English, and all other Proteſtant Churches.
            Hearing that Maiſter Howes the Continuer &amp; Augmenter of Maiſter Stowes cronicle was deſirous to ſee him, out of a vaine deſire to haue al circumſtances of his perſon and opinions hiſtorically blazed, he wrote a letter to Maiſter Howes fully to informe him of both, mentioning therein the day, order, &amp; continuance of his impriſonment, if he liſted ſo to recount them. He wil tel you how many publique Lectures he made weekly with great applauſe during his aboad with Maiſter Drake in Deuonſhire, and how his chamber lay open beſides to all comers, day and night for priuate inſtruction, ſhewing himſelfe a Foole, if not a Phariſy, in affecting humane prayſes ſo palpably,

in all his ſpeaches and actions.
            Two of diſciples only vnderſtand Latin aſwell as himſelfe: the one a poore ſeduced Gentleman, better ſkilled in Hebrew then himſelf, and equally conuerſant in Scripture: the other a Comfit-maker, who lately vndertooke by Traſkes directions, as is probably gueſſed, to publiſh his doctrinall concluſions, &amp; to defend them againſt M. Crashaw who hath writē an idle &amp; looſe refutation of them. For contrary to his common Pulpit-doctrine, and raylinges againſt Catholikes, for admitting traditions and pointes of faith not contayned in Scripture, he ſuppoſeth without further proofe, that Chriſt in conuerſation with his Apoſtles after his Reſurrection, taught our keeping of the Sunday in place of the Sabaoth, that being a meere Tradition no where mentioned in Scripture. Which ſortes of aduantage are craftely obſerued by Traſke in all conferences of learned Proteſtantes with him,

&amp; he will not ſticke in anſwering their arguments deduced from the authority and vniuerſall practiſe of Chriſts Church in all ages before him, to tell them, that they fight againſt him with the Catholikes borrowed weapons, and in their ſtrokes at him, wound themſelues more deeply, ouerthrowing moſt opinions of their own faith, which are as ſtrange and vnheard of, till within the laſt 100. yeares, as his doctrines, and equally repugnant to the ancient authority and knowne practiſe of all Chriſtendome in times paſt. So that if his ground of admitting no doctrine not expreſſed in Scripture be shaken, their Religion will totter alſo. For the ſame authenticall teſtimonies of antiquity which ſerue to proue the Apoſtolicall obſeruation of the Sunday, do likewiſe mentiō Liturgies &amp; Maſſing Sacrifices celebrated by Chriſtians in their publique ſinaxes and meetings on feſtiuall and dominicall dayes, teſtified by

S. Auguſtine ſerm. 251. de tempore, by S. Cyprian de oper. &amp; eleemoſyn. by the Fathers of the Agathen Councell cap. 47. by the 6. Oecumenicall Councell cap. 8. and ſundry other ancient authors.
            His Ipſe dixit, and ſole aſſertion is a ſufficient rule of fayth to all his diſciples, among whom if any chance to grow wiſer (as many of them lately haue done) and to depart from his doctrine, he will ſeeme to haue formerly feared &amp; foreknown that mans frailty and finall reprobation. Thus not long ſince he dealt with one of them, who notwithſtanding then proteſted that Traske had heertofore vnder his owne hand warranted his true repentance, and eternall election in Chriſt Ieſus, though paſſion at that time tranſported him to make a contrary iudgement of him.
            There is nothing more troubleſome to him and his diſciples, then to be tearmed ignorant or abſurd in any of their aſſertions. And albeit himſelfe

ſeemeth modeſt and temperate in his ſpeaches and carriage: yet anger and malice hidden in his hart, ſoone breaketh out, vpon very ſmall occaſions, into rayling and ill tearmes, ſuch as himſelfe will condemne in others by many Texts of Scripture. Which his dangerous diſpoſition tryed by one of his Proteſtant fellow-priſoners and other perſonall facts I purpoſely heere forbeare to relate, hauing more authenticall teſtimonies againſt him.
            His frequent Soleciſmes when now and then he boulteth out a word or line of Latin, as to ſay: Index expurgatorium &amp;c are for quietnes ſake to be accounted but lapſus linguae, vnfit to be tould him. His barbariſmes in ſpeaking or writing muſt paſſe currently as Hebraiſmes and Scripture-phraſes: and all his arguments are to be accounted no other then formall and conuincing demonſtrations. Among which for proofe that S. Peter and the Apoſtles

ſtill obſerued the legall difference of meates, this one for example is his Achylles, written to my knowledg by him in three ſeuerall diſcourſes ſent to one of his fellow-priſoners.
            
               Qui ambulat in praecepto veteri recepto à Patre, ambulat ſecundum legem diſcriminis inter animal quod comeditur, &amp; animal: quod non comeditur.
               Sed Petrus ambulauit in praecepto veteri recepto à Patre.
               Ergo ambulauit ſecundum legem diſcriminis inter animal quod comeditur, &amp; animal quod non comeditur.
            
            
               Thus Englished.
            
            
               He that walketh in the old Commandment receaued from the Father, walketh according to the Law of difference between the liuing creature that is to be eaten, and the liuing creature that is not to be eaten.
               But Peter walked in the old Commandment &amp;c.
            
            If you tell him firſt that his ſyllogiſme is tedious and compoſed in barbarous Latin, vnfit to come from the

pen of an ancient ſchoolmaiſter and profeſſed Grammarian: He wil falſely tell you that Praecepto veteri recepto à Patre &amp;c. is the expreſſe phraſe of S. Iohn in his firſt Canonicall Epiſtle.
            If you further tell him, that his argument is ridiculous in ſenſe and forme, as hauing no medium at all in the premiſes to proue the concluſion; to walke in the old Commaundement &amp;c. and to walke according to the law of difference &amp;c being in ſenſe all one, in wordes only changed. He will more abſurdly tel you, that by the old Commandment &amp;c. he meant Gods precept giuen to Adam in Paradiſe, which all learned men know to haue byn a perſonall precept of abſtayning from the fruite of one tree, not cōcerning S. Peter afterwards or any Chriſtian, more then to the generall knowne doctrine of Adams tranſgreſſion therof fearefully punished in his poſterity. And to deterre his aduerſary from laughing at this argument, and other more ridiculous

paſſages of his papers, he added this Caueat for a graue concluſion, or memorable ſentence of inſtruction.
            
               Si fortè dum loquutus fuero, poſtmodum verò ſermonem meum ſubſannato. If when peraduenture I shall haue ſpoken; but afterwards laugh at my ſpeach. Wherein any learned man may plainely ſee indeed his wonted Ciceronian ſtyle ſtrangely altered.
            By reading in Euſebius hiſtory lib. 1. cap. 22. how Saint Policarpe and other holy Bishops of Aſia obſerued the Iewes time of keeping Eaſter, he and his diſciples are lately therein reſolued to imitate them. And that which he neuer read of S. Policarpe or any Chriſtian Doctor before him, he hath added to his Eaſter the feſtiuall obſeruance of Azimes, as is probably gueſſed by all his fellow priſoners; ſeing him and his diſciples after the fourtenth of March moone to eate contrary to their cuſtome at other times, white vnleauened loaues, and ſeeming in his ſpeaches to

allow of the obſeruance of that feſtiuity, albeit of the manner he be ſomthing doubtfull, as peraduenture, whether it muſt be with a Phaſcall Lambe eaten &amp;c.
            He eſteemeth it no arrogancy or pride of iudgment in him to diſſent in his doctrines from all known Chriſtians, either liuing now, or in any age before him. Neither will he yield it to be a dangerous nouelty and notable giddines in him to change, and coyne at his pleaſure weekly doctrines; defending them with ſuch peremptory pride of iudgment, as if he had receaued cleare and certaine reuelations therof.
            The order of my diſcourſe is eaſy to be diſcerned by the titles of my queſtions in both Controuerſyes. My manner of writing is to declare and refute his aſſertions with as much breuity and plaineſſe as I could contriue ech queſtion. I cite not many authors for any opinions, both becauſe my aduerſary

contemneth ſuch proofes, as alſo for that I want the cōmodity of a Library to collect them. I haue intentionally written this Preface to diſcouer Traskes opinions, not to diſgrace his perſon, further then I conceaued perſonall circumſtances fitly vttered to expreſſe fully the grounds and occaſions of his doctrines: hauing to authorize me therein ſundry examples of great Saints, not ſparing to relate groſſer paſſages, then heere I haue done, of their Hereſiarchicall Aduerſaryes, who as Diuells in their fearefull apparitions by platter-eyes, clouen feete, or ſtinking ſmells are wont to be diſcerned: ſo they truly wolues in sheeps garments, are by leuity of Doctrine, pride of iudgment, and other perſonall demeanours eaſily diſcouered to want the innocent humble nature of lambes, conterfaited by them. And as he that putteth himſelfe on a ſtage to play the Fooles part, muſt patiently expect laughter

from his beholders: ſo Traske broaching his hereticall fancies, muſt prudently prepare himſelfe to be more then ſmiled at by iudicious Readers.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               THE I. CONTROVERSY.
               
                  
                     QVESTION I. Of the ſeauenth Day before Moyſes.
                  
                     
                        IOHN Traske ſeemeth falſely to ſuppoſe, and Maiſter Cra. his Aduerſary as lightly to graunt, that a Sabaoth, or ſeauenth daie of reſt from bodily labour was from the beginning of mans Creation cōmanded by God, &amp; by faithfull people continually obſerued: grounding as it ſhould ſeeme this their aſſertion vpon the holy text of Gen. cap. 2. v. 3. wherein God is ſayd to haue reſted from his laboures, bleſſed and ſanctified the ſeauenth day. As if for God to ſanctifie and deſigne a day to be holy afterwards, obſerued in his eſpeciall honour and ſeruice, were all one as to make it a ſabaoth, or day of reſt from externall labours; which is moſt falſe, and may be eaſily diſproued by ſundry plaine examples in the Moyſaicall feaſts of Azimes, Tabernacles &amp;c.

Wherein amongſt eight holy ferialls or feſtiuall dayes celebrated with peculiar ſacrifices and cerimonies cōmanded in them, Leuit. 3. verſ. 8. 36 37. the firſt &amp; eight ōly were to be obſerued as ſabaoths and daies of reſt from corporal labours.
                  So that God might ſanctifie and deſigne the ſeauenth day to be holy, and eſpecially honored therein by Adam and his faithfull poſterity, and yet not make it ſuch a ſabaoth, as afterwards he cōmanded Exod. 20. verſ. 8. 9. that ſtrict manner of reſt from eternall labours, being no eſſentiall condition, but only a cerimoniall ſolemnity of a ſanctified day, as thoſe already instanced textes of Leuiticus do import: in which it is ſaid of the firſt and eight daies, that they ſhould be more ſolemn thē: he other ſix; &amp; immediatly God commanded in them abſtinence from all ſorts of bodily labours, which notwithſtanding when they are either neceſſary in themſelues, or charitably expedient for others, cannot bee accounted morall breaches, prophaning that day in which they are, with due honour and praiſe otherwiſe giuen to God, moderatly performed: That repreſentation of Gods reſt by ours on the ſeauenth day which is cheifly reſpected and often inſtanced by Iohn Traske, being only a typicall or figuratiue reſpect, hauing no holines or morality in itſelfe further then moderate reſt from ſeruile and continuall labours, as needfull and conuenient for all men to performe their thankfull duty and ſeruice towards Almighty God, and

leſſe oftentimes interrupted and hindered by externall exerciſe of the body, then by ſuperfluous ſleepe, idle words, or diſtractiue thoughts not expreſly forbiden in the precept of the Sabaoth, which according to the ſtrict and ceremonious obſeruance thereof from corporall labours is no where in the whole hiſtory of Geneſis intimated to haue ben obſerued by Abraham and other Patrarches, whoſe labours, iournies, māner of ſpē
                     ding their liues, altars erected, ſacrifices offered, exequies celebrated, couenants and lawes giuen by God, &amp; holily by them obſerued, are without any inſinuation of ſuch a Sabaoth particulerly recounted.
                  Moreouer many paſſages of that ſacred hiſtorie ſeeme euidently to import, that before Moyſes time their was no ſuch Sabaoth cōmaunded by God, or by holy people practiſed, as Geneſis 31. verſ. 40. 41. Where Iacob pleading his faithfull &amp; diligent ſeruices done to Laban, he teſtifieth him ſelfe to haue indured laborious dayes &amp; ſleepleſſe nights for twenty yeares togeather, making no exception of Sabaoth daies, as he would haue done no doubt if ſuch had then ben obſerued by him. And Exod. 5. verſ. 19. the labours of his children are ſaid to haue ben per ſingulos dies, euery day prefixed and exacted by Pharaos officers, without any inſinuation of Sabaoths interpoſed. And to ſay, as Iohn Traske ſeemeth in his conference to do, that as the firſt inſtitution of mariage was by degrees corrupted.

with bigamy and diuorcing one wife to marrie another afterwards, Math. 19. verſ. 8. So the Sabaoth likewiſe in proceſſe of time grew neglected by gods people, vntill in his law he renewed the old inſtitution thereof, is coniecturally only affirmed, Chriſt himſelfe hauing taught vs the firſt inſtitution of marriage to haue byn ſo depraued: but no mention is made in ſcripture at all of the old Sabaoth neglected.
                  Who likewiſe ſeeth not, that neither the Patriarches themſelues nor their holy progeny being knowne to haue obſerued any Sabaoth, but that it were a far more pious and profitable coniecture thence rather to inferre, that no Sabaoth was then cōmanded, then that ſuch holy perſons neglected the dew obſeruance thereof, and liued Idolaters of Gods precept againſt his owne expreſſe teſtimony giuen of Abraham Geneſ. 26. verſ. 5. Where he is ſayd to haue obayed Gods voice, kept his precepts, comandements, ceremonies, and lawes; amongſt which Iohn Traske groundleſly and idly ſuppoſeth to haue been included the obſeruance of the ſabaoth, ſithence no ſuch precept giuen to Abraham, or practiſe thereof can be found mentioned in ſcripture, vntill the Iſraelites returning out of Egypt cam into the deſert of Sin, and began to be feed on the Manna rayned downe vnto them Exod. 16. verſ. 5. of which they were cōmanded to gather only ſix daies, and on the ſixt day they were willed to gather a double meaſure to ſerue the day following; Moyſes
                     
then firſt begining to tell them, verſ. 23. &amp; 26. that God had ſpoken vnto him, that on the morrow, which was the ſeauēth day of gathering that miraculous food, the reſt of the Sabaoth was to be ſanctified to our Lord.
                  And when the Iſraelits either not crediting or not vnderſtanding that which Moyſes had tould them, went out to gather Māna on the 7. day as they had done on the other ſix daies before (which is an euident ſigne that as yet they held not ſuch labours of prouiding corporall foode vnlawfull any day) they found none. And Moyſes ſayd vnto them: Behould, God hath allotted you a Sabaoth, giuing you double prouiſion of food on the ſixt day to ſerue you the ſeauenth day, wherfore let euery man remayne with himſelfe, or in his owne tent, and let him not go out on the ſeauenth day: and the people then ſabathized, or began to obſerue the Sabaoth on the ſeauenth day; firſt then being taught (ſayth Philo lib 1. de vita Moyſis) not only by Propheticall inſtruction, but alſo by a moſt manifeſt argumēt of the Manna ceaſed to be rayned downe that day, and continuing incorupted which was gathered in a double meaſure on the ſixt day, that the ſame was the ſeauenth day wherein God reſted from his labours, they hauing longe before deſired to know the day of the worlds firſt creation, and could not till then learne it: which obſeruance God afterwards cōmanded, &amp; wrote in the firſt Table of the Decalogue, willing his

people not only to ſanctify and keepe holy the ſeauenth day, but expreſly alſo forbidding them all ſorts of externall labours, in memory that him ſelfe had reſted from his labours on that day, calling it therfore in hebrew Saphath of the word Sacath, which ſignifieth to reſt.
               
               
                  
                     QVESTION II. VVhether the precept of the Sabbaoth were Morall, or Cerimoniall.
                  
                     IOHN Traske ſeemeth not in any of his ſpeaches or writings rightly to vnderſtand wherein the morality of any Law or Precept conſiſteth; neither doth Maiſter Cra. his ſuperficiall aduerſary indeauour in his confuſed anſwere to inſtruct him in the true vnderſtanding thereof, as he ought ſpecially to haue done, conſidering that all Traskes ſinguler opinions are chiefly grounded in a wrongefull conceyuing of ſome Moyſaical precepts to haue ben morall, and ſo conſequently not abrogated by Chriſts coming, which were indeed morally cerimoniall, according to that preciſe figuratiue and myſterious manner, at the leaſt comaunded to the Iewes, in the obſeruance of them.
                  Heere therfore for both their inſtructions I define the morality of a law or precept, to conſiſt in that conformity which it hath to the naturall

light of humane vnderſtanding and iudgment, taught in all true Philoſophy, to be the rule of naturall and morall actions, and rightly tearmed by the Apoſtle ad Rom. cap. 2. verſ. 14. &amp; 15. A Law written by God, euen in the hartes of ſuch Gentills, as had no knowledge of any other ſupernatural law, approuing them in good, and reprehending them in euill actions, cauſing in them that practicall internall knowledge called Conſcience, and iuſtly ſeruing to condemne all ſuch as contradict, and do againſt it.
                  So that only ſuch lawes and precepts are ſaid to be morall which are conformable to this Syndereſis, and naturall light of humane iudgment, perfected by grace, aſwell in the knowledge of naturall obiects, as of ſupernaturall &amp; reuealed verities: amongſt which ſome are purely ſpeculatiue, and do only require a faithfull, pious, and firme aſſent of our iudgment vnto them: and others contrarily are in their owne nature practicall precepts and diuine directions or laws, commanding or forbidding things to be done by vs, which if they be ſuch, according to the ſubſtance or manner of the act commaunded or forbidden by them, as do appeare to humane vnderſtanding and iudgment voluntarily to haue ben commaunded by God, and exacted in due obedience from vs his Creatures for ſuch myſterious reſpects, as naturall iudgment cannot apprehend to be neceſſary or any way belonging to our direction in manners, and

morality of life towards God, our ſelues, or our neighbours; thoſe precepts are not to be accounted morall, but myſterious and ceremoniall abrogated by Chriſt, as Iohn Traske willingly confeſſeth.
                  Which true ground ſuppoſed briefly declaring the nature and condition of a morall law, I anſwere thus to the difficulty of my Queſtion heere propoſed, that the Commaundement giuen to the Iewes of keeping a Sabaoth, or weekely day of reſt, was according to the ſubſtance and chiefe intention of that law morall: Becauſe naturall vnderſtanding, illuminated by faith, teacheth it to be fit and expedient that all ſorts of perſons ſhould abſtaine from corporal labours, ſo far forth as to allot certaine daies of their life to the eſpeciall ſeruice and honour of Almighty God: but the determination rather of the ſeauenth day in which God reſted frō his labours, then of the ſixt in which man was created for to ſerue his creatour here in this world, and to inioy him afterwards, meerly depended on Gods free choyce and election miſteriouſly reſoluing to make the day of his owne reſt the Sabaoth, and reſting day of his people alſo from corporall labours, ſymbolizing therby that eternall day of clarity and reſt, which they were to inioy with himſelfe afterwards.
                  As touching likewiſe the preciſe manner of reſt from all ſortes of labours, euen ſuch as were eaſily performed and belonged in a ſort

to the conuenient health and nouriſhment of their bodies, commaunded to the Iewes on their Sabaoth, as to light fire, prepare meate &amp;c. I affirme and proue it to haue beene meerly cerimoniall; naturall experience teaching vs firſt that the lighting of fire, and ſuch eaſy labours of preparing food on the Sabaoth for our ſelues or for the charitable releife of our brethren, are no way repugnant to the morall end and intention for which the Sabaoth was chiefely ordayned, to wit of yealding due honor and praiſe to God for his continuall bleſſinges and benefits towards vs, which only requireth moderate reſt from ſeruile and paineful labours, wholy diſtraſting mens minds; and making them vnapt for holy exerciſes of piety and deuotion. Secondly experience likewiſe teacheth vs, that mens dulnes and vnablenes ordinarily to be actuated any whole day togeather in prayer and prayſes to God without ceaſing, is ſuch, as eaſy walking and other needfull or charitable exerciſes moderately vſed, do help rather then hinder the frequent and feruent vſe of mental and deuout exerciſes, and ſerue to honour God and ſanctify the Sabaoth, more then ſuperfluous ſleep, idle thoughts, vnprofitable conuerſation with others, not expreſly in that commaundement prohibited.
                  Which morall obſeruation of the Sabaoth euen ſince Chriſts time, religiouſly and vniuerſally practiſed by Chriſtian paſtours &amp; people

on the weekly day of our Sauiours Reſurection, was intimated by our Sauiour himſelfe in many paſſages of the Ghoſpell, doing for example many miracles on that day, albeit he ſaw them by the Scribes and Phariſies ſcandalouſly apprehended to haue beene breaches of the Sabaoth, Luk. 6. verſ. 9. Matth. 12. verſ. 10. &amp;c. commaunding ſuch as he had cured to take vp theyr beds and go home to their owne houſes, which ſeemed a worke of toyle and labour forbidden to the Iewes on their Sabaoth, Io. 5. verſ. 8. 10. defending his diſciples for rubbing the eares of corne to eate, Matth. 12. verſ. 1. Luc. 6. verſ. 1
                           •
                         Marc. 2. v. 23. which the Iewes preſent reputed to haue beene a certaine laborious preparatiō of food ſeemingly forbiddē by God, Exod. 35 verſ. 3. in Moyſes declaration of that precept; inſtancing againſt thoſe captious accuſers of himſelfe &amp; his diſciples, the exerciſes of Prieſts labouring about ſacrifices in the Temple, yet not violating the Sabaoth, the practiſe of Circumciſion on the eight day, albeit it happened on the Sabaoth, their vſuall cuſtome of leading out their cattle to water, and drawing them out of pittes and places of daunger on the Sabaoth day, without any ſinfull breach thereof, as may be gathered out of our Sauiours manner of ſpeach, Luke 13. 14. importing no reprehenſion of them for ſuch facts, but produced rather by him as fit examples apt to authorize his miraculous workes, done with leſſe labour and more charity and vtility

to ſuch as were by his voice, or a touch of his hand or garment, in ſoule and body perfectly cured.
                  So that Iohn Traske and other Puritanes in their cerimoniall and preciſe manner of obſeruing the Sabaoth, are rather ſuperſtirious imitators of the Iewes, our Sauiours aduerſaries, then humble and faithfull members of Chriſts Catholike Church, euer knowne to haue practiſed a morall, and not the Iewiſh and cerimonial obſeruance of the Sunday.
               
               
                  
                     QVESTION III. Concerning the abrogation of the Iewes Sabaoth.
                  
                     IOHN Traske adhering more conſtantly, and conſequently then other Proteſtants do, to their dangerous ground of beleeuing nothing not expreſly mentioned in Scriptures, or thence neceſſarily deduced; hath of late vpon conference with others, and more diligent ſearch then he had made before of many texts in the old and new Teſtament, like a weather-cocke, turned with euery blaſt of his owne ignorant fancy and iudgment, hath determined himſelfe, and drawne his diſciples to a moſt ſtrict keeping of Saturday the Iewiſh Sabaoth, comaunded, ſaith he, by God out of fire, and written with his owne finger in

the firſt Table of the Decalogue, holily likewiſe by Chriſt and his diſciples afterwards obſerued, as a ſacred memoriall of Gods reſt on the 7. day, and therfore now alſo as a morall and diuine precept ſtill to continue▪ Preſſe him with the vniuerſall practiſe of Chriſts Church preſent &amp; paſt ſince the Apoſtles, certainely knowne to haue reiected the Iewiſh Sabaoth, and inſteed thereof to haue obſerued the firſt day of the weeke in continuall memory of our Sauiours Reſurection, and he will in horrible pride and pertinacity of iudgment affirme it to haue ben a corrupt and abuſiue practiſe, little by him regarded, as not being at al grounded in Scripture but repugnant vnto it. Vrge him with Chriſts promiſes of being preſent with his Church to the worlds end, Matth. 28. verſ. 20. of eſtabliſhing it ſo ſurely on a rocke, that hell gates ſhall neuer preuaile againſt it, Matth. 16. verſ. 18. of comforting it with his ſpirit of loue, &amp; leading it into all truth Iob▪ 14. verſ. 16. 17. 26. which fitly therfore is ſaid to be Colum
                           ••
                         &amp; firmamē
                        tum veritatis, the ſuporting pillar and foundation of true faith, 1. Tim. 3. verſ. 15. to whoſe holy obedience all Chriſtians are tied vnder paine of being by their brethrē accounted as Ethnickes and Publicans, Matth. 18. v. 17. he will ridiculouſly tell you as he did to one of his fellow priſoners conferring with him on this very point, that the true Church of which theſe and the like texts were written, is

knowne to very few, conſiſting of 2. or 3. gathered togeather in Chriſts name, himſelfe promiſing to be in the midſt of them Matth. 18. verſ. 20. that is to ſay, a ſmall number of ſuch little ones as haue truly repented, and are made ſure of their election in Chriſt, hated and perſecuted by men, but beloued by God &amp; guarded by Angells, ſeeing the face of their Heauenly Father. Matth. ibid. verſ. 10. And examining him further on this point, he will in proceſſe of ſpeach, tell ſuch as he will be confident with all, that himſelfe and his brethren are thoſe little ones, the only Gnostiks, &amp; illuminated members of Chriſts Church, others belonging therunto no further then true faith, repentance, and morality of life ſhall lead them, and ignorance with all excuſe them, for not actually profeſſing his ſingular doctrines.
                  So he fooliſhly ſeeketh with Ebion and other ancient Heretikes to breath life and ſpirit into the ceremonious carcaſſe and buried rites of the Iewiſh law, feeding his groſſe children with ſuch vnſauery excrements, for ſo the Apoſtle tearmeth them ad Philip. 3. verſ. 8. as Chriſt long ſince in the ending of that Law hath caſt out of the myſtical body of his church, as not conteining any true noriſhment of ſoules in them; &amp; vainely endeauoureth to illuminate thoſe which obſerue ſhadows, who haue happily ſince Chriſts time liued in the cleere ſunſhine of heauenly graces, planting like a fooliſh builder

ſuch new points of his faith on the ſandy &amp; fleeting foundation of the Iewiſh law, and ſeeking to ſet vp againe medium parietem maceriae, that parting wall of ceremonies, which diſtinguiſhed Iewes and Gentills ſubuerted and quite ouerthrowne by Chriſt, ad Eph. 2. verſ. 14. &amp; 15. euacuating al ſuch legall decres and ceremonial comandements that he might build on himſelfe the foundation and corner ſtone both people in a Holy Temple and habitation of God &amp;c. purifiyng alike their hares by faith. Act. 15. verſ. 9.
                  And that amongeſt other cerimoniall precepts and decrees of Moyſes Law abrogated by Chriſt, the Sabaoth was one, holily rrāſlated by the Apoſtles themſelues into our Sunday, as ſhall bee proued in my next Queſtion, is by S. Paul ad Coloſſ. 2. verſ. 16. 17. expreſly affirmed willing his diſciples not to be iudged or diſcouered in their faithfull profeſſion in meate, or drinke, or new moones, or any part of a feſtiuall day or Sabaoth, which are ſhadowes of future good thinges. By which Sabaoth cannot be meant the feaſts of Trumpets, Tabernacles, Expiation, and other ſuch ceremoniall and Iewiſh feſtiuities, as Traske heretically cōmenteth. For albeit thoſe feaſts be called indeed (Leuit. 23.) Sabboths, or daies of reſt, becauſe all externall workes were alike forbidden in them, as on the ſeauenth day: yet the Apoſtle reſt rayneth the word Sabaoth in this place, to ſignifie the weekly Sabaoths of the Iewes, as appeareth firſt

in that hee numbreth ſuch Iewiſh feſtiual daies diſtinctly from the Sabaoth, equally forbiding the obſeruance of them both.
                  His ſecond reaſon why he prohibiteth them conteyned in that part of the text, quae ſunt vmbra &amp;c. which are ſhaldowes of future good thinges, equally agreeth to them both: for as thoſe feaſts were ſhaddows and types, ſo were the weekly Sabaoths alſo. Wherfore Ebion and his diſciples, the firſt hereticall obſeruers of our Lords day and the Iewiſh Sabaoths togeather, as witneſſeth S. Epiphanius haerſ. 30. S. Irenaeus lib. 1. cap. 26. preſſed with the authority of this place, and perceauing the vnanſwerablenes therof, rather then they would therunto conforme their doctrines, abſolutly reiected all S. Paules Epiſtles, and accounted him an Apoſtata from the Iewiſh faith: The which Iohn Traske ſeemeth not yet to do, albeit hee dared once to ſay of S. Paul, that he ſought to pleaſe men, ſo conſequently could not be the true ſeruant of Chriſt.
                  Secondly, I deduce out of Scripture this Theological argumēt. The Iews for the like reſpect, &amp; memory of Gods reſt, were as well bound to obſerue ech Sabaoth of years, &amp; the Sabaoth of that yearly Sabaoth, called the Iubily, or 50. year, as to keep the weekly Sabaoth of daies, Leuit. 25. But thoſe yearly Sabaoths, are certainely (I ſuppoſe in Traskes opinion) abrogated: wherefore the weekly Sabaoth is no longer to bee obſerued:

Gods precepts thereof deliured out of fire to the people, and written wit his owne ſinger in the Decalogue, eſpecially inſtanced by Traske, being meere circumſtances impertinent to the morality therof, further thē is in my former queſtion already declared: Gods comaundement whether giuen out of fire, or not being ſufficient of it ſelfe to oblige his creatures to the perpetuall obſeruance of any Law for morality of life fit to be obſerued. And no learned man will deny but that many precepts, neither deliuered out of fire, nor written in the Decalogue Tables were morall, and as ſuch, are now to be obſerued by Chriſtians: as for a man not to marry his Fathers wife, his ſiſter, his daughter &amp;c. The prohibition of vſury and ſundry other like moral precepts, amongſt which (though falſely) Traske numbreth the legall difference of meates, albeit it was neither commaunded out of fire, nor written in the Decalogue Tables.
                  Thirdly I argue, that Iohn Traske hath no ſufficient authority of Scripture, prouing the cōtinuance of the Iewiſh Sabaoth: for our Sauiours obſeruance thereof little importeth for this purpoſe, the Law wherunto he voluntarily &amp; in obedience to his Father ſubiected himſelfe, being not before his death determined, ſo that he practiſed likewiſe Circumciſion, and many other cerimoniall rites, now vnlawfull to Chriſtians. The practiſe alſo of the Apoſtles, entring commonly, after Chriſts death, into

the Temple, and other Iewiſh Sinagogues on their Sabaoth, maketh as little as our Sauiours example to proue the continuance thereof, this their practiſe being in no text of their holy Acts teſtified. Wherein likewiſe the holy Euangeliſt inſinuateth not, the motiue &amp; end of this their Cuſtome to haue ben not ſo much a religions obſeruation of that Sabaoth, as a more commodious and generall inſtruction of the Iewes cō
                     cerning the Law &amp; Prophets, fulfilled in Chriſt their expected Meſſias, they being in thoſe dayes and places chiefly aſſembled and beſt prepared to haue ſuch ſpirituall doctins propounded vnto them by the Apoſtles: Who for celebration of Chriſt ſupper, preaching, and other publique exerciſes of Chriſtian piety and deuotion, were accuſtomed to meete on the firſt day of the week, called therefore our Lords day Apocal. 2. becauſe our Lord had then ſanctified the ſame by his reſurrection, and commaunded the religious obſeruance therof, as ſhall in my next Queſtion bee fully diſcuſſed.
                  If Iohn Traske will further contend, that the Apoſtles for other religious reſpects beſides preaching of Chriſt, entred the Temples and Sinagogues on the Sabaoth, and feſtiuall daies, as Act▪ 21. verſ. 23. 24. 25. where S. Paul not to auert the whole nation of the Iewes from Chriſt, did by the counſell of S. Iames purify him ſelfe with other Nazaretts, and ſo enter the Temple, that he might ſeeme to obſerue the

Law as other Iewes conuerted vnto Chriſt thē commonly did. I anſwere, this conditionall obſeruance of the Sabaoth and other cerimoniall rites for a time by the Apoſtles, was only permitted by Chriſt, as a charitable meanes the better to vnite the Iewes and Gentills in the vnity of one Church: The giuer of the Law (ſaith S. Auguſtine writing to S. Hierome Epiſt. 19.) hauing ſo determined to end the ſame with his owne death, and afterwards honorably to bury it, by permitting the conuerted Iewes for a while to practiſe it, vntill his Ghoſpel were ſufficiently promulgated. For (ſaith this holy Father) thoſe legall obſeruaunces were not ſudainely to be deteſted, as the diueliſh ſacriledges of Gentills, when Chriſts grace began to be reuealed, which was in ſuch ſhadowing rites prefigured; but to be permitted for a ſeaſon to their poſterity, who firſt receaued them, which after their exequies honorably performed, were by all Chriſtians to bee vtterly forſaken.
                  If Traske wil preſſe me further to know the preciſe time, when the ceremoniall obſeruation of the Sabaoth, and other rites of Moyſes Law wholy ceaſed, and became vnlawfull to be practiſed any more by Chriſtians. I anſwere him, that peraduenture vntill the very deſtruction of Ieruſalem, and ſubuerſion of the Temple, more then 40. yeares after our Sauiours paſſion, the old Sabaoth and other ceremonious rites of the Law, might be by ſome faithfull Iewes, without

any touch of infidelity, and falling from Chriſt, albeit vnneceſſarily and improfitably, obſerued: Gods prouidence (ſaith Origen homil. 10. in Leuit) wiſely ordaining, that the Citty, Temple, and all things els belonging to the former glory of that Law and nation, ſhould be altogeather deſtroied, leaſt ſucklings and weaklinges in faith, ſhould be longer allured by thē, and drawne away from purely imbracing Chriſtian verities ſhadowed in them. So that when our Sauiour willed his diſciples, Math. 24. verſ. 10. to pray that their flight might not happen in winter, ſaith S. Ierome, becauſe extremity of could would hinder their laſting aboad in mountaines &amp; deſert places; nor in the Sabaoth becauſe the religious reſt therof would hinder their flight: which had ben idly ſpoken, ſaith Traske, if Chriſtians to whome theſe wordes were vttered, had not ben bound to a ſtrict obſeruance of the old Sabaoth, when Ieruſalem was ſacked.
                  I anſwere firſt this obiection, that albeit it might be gathered out of this text, that many Chriſtian Iewes did obſerue their old Sabaoth as before, vntill the deſtruction of Ieruſalem: yet can it not thence alſo be inferred, that ſuch Chriſtians obſerued it in like manner afterwards, when they had ſeene the perfidious cruelty of their whole nation againſt Chriſt, ſo examplarly puniſhed, their citty ſacked, their Preiſts ſlaughtered, and Temple ſubuerted, neuer againe, by

Chriſts ſpeaches, to be reſtored, which could not but be taken by faithfull people as certaine ſignes of that law and religion wholy abrogated by Chriſt and ended, the cheifeſt exerciſes whereof conſiſted in prayers made in the Temple togeather with miſterious rites and ſacrifices therein only performed. Secondly. I anſwere, that theſe words were vttered by Chriſt to his diſciples who were naturall Iewes and members of that Commonwealth, wherein the Sabaoth was by moſt people ſtrictly ſtill obſerued. Wherefore our Sauiour might well take an occaſion to vtter this ſpeach to them, which cheifly concerned the generality of vnbeleeuing Iewes, liuing togeather with them and obſeruing the Sabaoth, as may be inſtanced in many other examples of like ſpeaches in Scripture. Thirdly. I anſwere, that Chriſt vttered that ſpeach, as fore ſeeing that the very day in which Titus ſhould beſiege the Citty, ſhould be no other then the Paſchall ſolemnity, and great Sabaoth, wherein multitudes of people repayring to Ieruſalem from all places, ſhould be ſodainely ſo incloſed, as they ſhould haue no meanes to fly, hauing the gates ſhut vpon them by ſuch captaines and people as vndertooke to defend the citty, and ſo narowly watched by the Romā ſoldiars, as when any were taken to fly they were vſually crucified before the walles, and being reſtained by ſuch multituds, they ſuffered vnſpeakeable famine, plague, and ſlaughters, by

externall foes and inteſtine diſſentions, which being forknowne by our Sauiour, he might wel wiſh, them to pray that their flight or cauſe of flying, to wit, the approach of Titus army, might not happen in winter, or on the Sabaoth, not that they might not lawfully fly thereon for ſafeguard of their liues, or fight againſt their enimyes, as we read of Iudas Machabaeus ſouldiers 1. Machab. 3. but becauſe all meanes of flight ſhould be hindred by the ſodaine approach of their enimies without, &amp; Iewiſh captains within the Citty, and their miſeries be multiplied by occaſion of ſuch multitudes aſſembled on the Sabaoth.
                  Finally if Iohn Traske for continuance of the Sabaoth, ſhall obiect, as one of his diſciples ſeemed to do, that the celebration of the ſame is called, Exod. 31. A ſempiternall Couenant betwene God and his people, to be obſerued with perpetuall honour in all their generations Exod. 12. I anſwere, that the like manner of ſpeach is vſed of the old Aaronicall Preiſthood, Exod. 28. now tranſlated into the Prieſthood of our Sauiour ad Heb. 7. v. 11. 12. 15. 16. and abrogated by Traskes owne confeſſion. Wherfore we are to interprete the eternal duration of ſuch rites, to import only a continuance of them, till the Law fully ended, or becauſe they ſtill remaine according to the morall &amp; eternal things ſignified by them, as S. Auguſtine ſolueth this obiection quaeſt. 46. 124. &amp; 131. in Exod.
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     QVESTION IIII. Of the Sabaoth tranſlated into the weekely day of our Sauiours Reſurrection
                  
                     SAINT Augustine epiſt. 118. rightly termeth it a moſt inſolent madnes for any particuler man to reproue that which the whole Church of Chriſt generally obſerueth for in ſo doing, with vnreaſonable pride he practically prefereth his owne ſinguler opinion before the iudgements of all other Chriſtian Paſtours and people, as doth Iohn Traske in his nouell obſeruance of the Iewiſh Sabaoth, abrogated by the Apoſtles themſelues, as I haue proued in my former Queſtion, and tranſlated into the holy &amp; euer memorable day of our Sauiours Reſurrection, as is plainely teſtified by the 65. Apoſtolicall Canon, by S. Ignatius the Apoſtles diſciple, in his Epiſtle ad Magneſianos, by holy Iuſtin Apologia 2. by Tertullian de Corona militis &amp; Apologia cap. 16. by Clemens Alexandrinus lib. 7. ſtromat. by Origen homil. 7. in Exod. by S. Athanaſius in illa verba, Omnia mihitradita ſunt &amp;c. by S. Hilary praefat. in pſalm. by S. Ambroſe epiſt. 83. &amp; ſerm. 62. by S. Hierome in cap. 4. ad Galatas, by S. Augustin contra Adimant. cap. 16. lib. 22. de ciuitate dei, cap. 30. &amp; ſerm. 252. by S. Leo epiſt. 81. ad Dioſcorum, by S. Gregory lib 2. epiſt. 3. by the Laodicean Councell cap. 29. Wherein

Chriſtians are expreſſely forbidden to play the Iewes, and to be idle on the Sabaoth, and willed with all to obſerue and prefer our Lords day before it. So as if any teſtimonies of antiquity might be by Traske and his Companions admitted, and held ſufficient to proue the Apoſtolicall tranſlation of the Sabaoth, there would need no other arguments to refute, and reduce them from their idle and ſinguler fancies, then thoſe former vndoubted authorities of ancient &amp; learned Fathers. But as he &amp; his companions are wholy ignorant &amp; vnacquainted with their workes, ſo are they fully bent to contemne all ſuch Teſtimonies, which they find not warranted by plaine texts of ſcripture, as themſelues only are pleaſed to expound them.
                  For whereas not only the Ancient Fathers, but Ebion alſo himſelfe, and his diſciples acknowledged their hereticall doctrine of Iewiſh feaſts and Sabaoths neceſſary to be obſerued by Chriſtians, togeather with their owne Dominicall daies and proper feſtiuities, to haue beene expreſly contradicted and condemned by S. Paul ad Coloſſ. 2. reiecting thereupon all his Epiſtles from the Canon of Scripture; theſe new Ebionites, by ſhifting comments, and abſurd gloſſes of their owne deuiſing, ſeeke to delude the text, and drawe it againſt all ancient expoſitions therof, to be only vnderſtood of cerimoniall feaſts mentioned in the 23. of Leuiticus, only becauſe they are there called Sabaothes.
                     
Whereas the Apoſtle diſtinguiſheth ſuch feſtiuall daies from the weekly Sabaoth, and equally in this text forbiddeth the obſeruance of them both to Chriſtians. Which true expoſition heere ſuppoſed, I conclude this argument. One day of ſeauen is ſtill as a morall precept to be holily obſerued by all Chriſtians. But the obſeruance of the old Sabaoth is prohibited by the Apoſtle to Chriſtians, and no other day introduced in place thereof, but the day of our Sauiours Reſurrection. Therfore that day only, and not the Iewiſh Sabaoth, is ſtill as a morall precept to be holily obſerued by Chriſtians.
                  Secondly, becauſe Iohn Traske is moſt delighted with Sillogiſticall collections, albeit himſelfe be ſo little skilled in Logique, as writing lately againſt an Aduerſary, he denied the Minor of his Enthimeme, ſuppoſing that Chriſt was, as he tould the Iewes, Dominus Sabati, and had full power either by himſelfe, or his Apoſtles to abrogate and alter as well as to inſtitute &amp; approue the obſeruance thereof; I frame this argument. That day of the ſeauen is by Chriſtians now weekly to bee obſerued, which the Apoſtles themſelues allotted for their holy Aſſemblies, and other publique exerciſes of their Chriſtian faith. But the day which the Apoſtles ſo allotted &amp;c. was the firſt day of the weeke, and not the Iewiſh Sabaoth. Wherfore the firſt day of the weeke, &amp; not the Iewiſh Sabaoth is to be obſerued by Chriſtians.
                  
                     The Maior, or former part of my Argumēt is certaine, becauſe ſuch publique aſſemblies and exerciſes of faith, are the chiefe end, for which the Sabaoth, and other feſtiuall daies were firſt ordayned. The Minor, or latter part is clearely proued by the practiſe of the Apoſtles Act. 20. v. 6. 7. where S. Paul, &amp; many other Diſciples, of ſeauen whole daies which they ſpent in Troas, are read only to haue aſſembled themſelues for preaching &amp; frequenting Sacraments, which are the moſt publike exerciſes of faith, on the firſt day of the weeke, and not on the Iewiſh Sabaoth. Likewiſe on that day, the Apoſtle 1. Cor. 16. verſ. 1. 2. willed the Chriſtians at Corinth to make their Collects, or cōmon gatheringes for the poore brethren at Ieruſalem, which is an euident ſigne that Chriſtians vſed to aſſemble themſelues on that day, there being no reaſon to be yealded why ſuch common collections of almes ſhould be rather on the firſt day of the weeke, then any of the reſt, but that Chriſtians vſed only therein to make their holy Sinaxes &amp; conuents for praier, preaching, almes, frequenting Sacraments &amp;c. mentioned by holy Iuſtin in Apolog. 2. to Marcus Antoninus, and other Gouerners of the Empire in behalfe of Chriſtians, and ſundry of thoſe holy Fathers formerly mentioned.
                  Thirdly, I make this Argument for obſeruance of the ſunday in place of the Sabaoth. That day of the weeke is chiefly to be obſerued

by Chriſtians, which our Lord was pleaſed to make, and haue called his owne day. But our Lord did make and call his owne day, the firſt day of the weeke, and not the Iewiſh Sabaoth. Therfore the firſt day of the weeke, and not the Iewiſh Sabaoth, is eſpecially to be obſerued by Chriſtians. The maior is certaine, becauſe as Chriſtians are bound by their faithfull profeſſion to honor Chriſt himſelfe with thankefull &amp; humble ſeruices; ſo doth the wiſdome of faith teach them alſo eſpecially to honor and eſteeme that day of all others moſt holy, which their Lord himſelfe moſt reſpected, and did chooſe to make, and haue called his owne day. For as to name any day, the day of a King, importeth that day to be ſpecially regarded by the king himſelfe, and feſtiually obſerued by his ſubiects in memory of ſome victory obteyned, or memorable good, happened to himſelfe or his people on the ſame: ſo for ſuch holy and memorable reſpects, the firſt day of the weeke is called our Lords day, Apocalyp. 2. 5. worthieſt of all other daies of the weeke to be honored, and feſtiually obſerued by Chriſtians as ſhall be particularly proued in my next Argument. My minor is proued cleerely by that former text of S. Iohn, expreſly calling one day of the weeke or yeare as a familiar name knowne to all Chriſtians in his time▪ 
                     Diem Dominicum, our Lords day, to wit, a day eſpecially ſanctified by Chriſt, &amp; deuoted to his ſeruice which was not the Sabaoth

of the Iewes, no where els in Scripture ſo called, nor any other day but vna, or prima Sabbati, the next after the ſabaoth, as S. Ignatius S. Iohns ſcholler teſtifieth epist. 6. ad Magneſianos, ſaying: that after the Sabaoth ech louer of Chriſt celebrateth Diem Dominicum, our Lords day, conſecrated to our Lords Reſurrection, regina &amp; principium omnium dierum, the cheifeſt and principalleſt of all other daies &amp;c. els where Epiſt 8. ad Philippenſes, he conteſteth, that if any Chriſtian celebrateth his Eaſter with the Iews, or their other Symbolicall feſtiuities, amongſt which the Sabaothes are included, he maketh himſelfe partaker with thoſe who killed Chriſt and his Apoſtles. S. Auguſtin alſo to omit many other like teſtimonies of ancient Fathers, ſerm. 251. de tempore, teacheth the religions ſolemnization of our Lords day to haue beene inſtituted by the Apoſtles themſelues, becauſe our Sauiour therein roſe from death to life, and to haue beene by them called our Lords day, that we might learne by that name to abſtaine therein from ſin, and earthly labours, attending to diuine ſeruices. And after much honourable mention made of that day, he ſaith, that therefore the holy Doctors of Chriſts Church, meaning the Apoſtles, decreed to transfer on that day al the glory of the Iewiſh Sabaoth, that what they celebrated in Types we might celebrate in Verities &amp;c.
                  Fourthly the precept of the Sabaoth obligeth

Chriſtians no further then it can be proued to conteyne a moral law, neceſſary to direct them in their religious duty, and thankfulnes towards Almighty God for benefitts. But the obſeruance of our Lords day is fitter to direct Chriſtians in their duty towards God, &amp; to put them in mind of his gracious benefitts towards them, then the obſeruance of the old Sabaoth. Therfore our Lords day, not the old Sabaoth, is now commaunded, and fitteſt to be obſerned by Chriſtians. The maior is certaine becauſe all cerimoniall and iudiciall precepts are confeſſed by Iohn Traske to haue beene abrogated by Chriſt; and no law of the old Teſtament bindeth Chriſtians which is not morally expedient and neceſſary to direct them in their Chriſtian duty and ſeruice. My minor may be beſt proued by examining and comparing the inſtitution and ends for which our Lords day and the old Sabaoth were firſt ordayned and obſerued.
                  The old Sabaoth was cheifely ordayned in memory of Gods reſt from his labours, of creating all things in ſix daies, and therefore Philo lib. de opificio mundi, wiſely calleth it the worlds birth-day, ſeruing for a continuall inſtruction of Gods people in the knowledge of their creator, and to exclude the error of Philoſophers commonly teaching the world to haue had no beginning. Secondly it ſerued to repreſent vnto the Iſraelites that reſt, which God had giuen vnto them after their Egyptian ſeruitude,

and painefull labours ended, as is expreſly affirmed Deut. 5. verſ. 15. Thirdly it declared them to be a peculiar people, ſanctifyed by God and deuoted to his ſeruice Exod. 31 verſ. 13. Fourthly the Iewes Sabaoth allegorically prefigured Chriſts reſt in his ſepulcher, after his paynefull labours for mans redemption ended, as is inſinuated by S. Paul ad Hebr. 4. verſ. 10. Fifthly in a tripologicall ſenſe it ſignifyed the ſpirituall reſt of ſoules, after the ſeruile workes of ſinne by Chriſts grace ended, as S. Auguſtine teacheth vs tract. 30. in Ioan. and in ſundry other places. Sixtly is was Anagogically a figure of that reſt which holy ſoules after this labourſome life ended, were to enioy in Abrahams boſome, as is inſinuated by S. Paul ad Hebr. 4. verſ. 6. &amp; 11. and is alſo taught by S. Auguſtine epiſt. 119.
                  For all which holy reſpects and myſterious ſignifications it was expedient and neceſſary that the old Sabaoth ſhould be changed by Chriſt into that bleſſed day, on which himſelfe was borne for mans redemption, to wit, the firſt day of the weeke, as may be Mathematically demonſtrated by ſearching backwards the Cicle of Dominical letters, which will be found on the 25. of December in the ſecond yeare of the hundred and ninty fourth Olympiade; of Rome firſt built 754. from Ceſars death 42. from the Triumuirate began by Auguſtus 41. of Herods raigne. 29. when our Sauiour was certainly borne, to haue beene B. Secondly on that firſt▪
                     
day of the weeke he roſe, and began humanely to lead his glorious immortall life, as may be expreſly gathered from the laſt chapter of all 4. Euangeliſts. Thirdly, on that day he viſibly infuſed his holy ſpirit on the Apoſtles, in the day of Pentecoſt, to wit, the fiftith day after the ſecond of Azimes whē the Iews began to number their day of Pentecoſt, which happened to be cō
                     pletly ēded in the yeare of our Sauiours paſſiō on ſunday, as is learnedly proued by Ribera de feſtis Iudaeorum Cap. de Pentecoſte, by Bellar de Cultu Sanctorum lib. 3. Cap. 13. and ſundry other authors. So as three of the greateſt myſteries of our Sauiours life, and moſt ſingular benefitts that God could deuiſe to beſtow on mankind happened on our Lords day, to ſanctify and make it more worthy then the Iewes Sabaoth, to be by vs Chriſtians weekely celebrated, and obſerued.
                  To which holy reſpects we may add alſo theſe, that God created the earth, the heauens &amp; Angelicall creatures on that day, graciouſly ſo therein preparing the locall place of our eternall Beatitude and heauently repoſe, ſignified better by ours, then the Iewiſh Sabaoth, prouiding our companions therein an earthely habitation in the meane while to honour him in this life, and make our ſelues by his graces worthy of our future glorification. All Types of the old Sabaoth are in the myſteries of this fully accompliſhed. This day is a gracious Symbole, or

ſigne of our ſpeciall deuotion towards Chriſt, a holy memoriall of ſpirituall graces receaued from him, as the other was chiefly of Gods temporall benefits towards his creatures. So as they ſeeme to be Iewes rather, then Chriſtians, who againſt the vniuerſall and known practiſe of Chriſts Church, ſince the Apoſtles tyme, eſteeme the old Sabaoth more holy, and worthy to be obſerued, then our Lords day, made for ſuch high and myſterious reſpects, memorable to Chriſtians.
                  Laſtly, the Apoſtle S. Paul ad Hebr. 4. plainely ſuppoſeth Chriſt to haue inſtituted a new Sabatiſme, or day of reſt for his people in memory of his reſt, after the labours which he ſuſtayned for our redemption ended, as God ordayned from the beginning, a holy day in memory of his owne reſt after his workes of creation perfected. And from the myſticall ſignification of theſe two diſtinct Sabaothes ſucceding ech other, and ſimbolizing a double reſt of Gods people, the one in Abrahams boſome, as our Sauiour tearmeth the place, wherein the Patriarches before him reſted, and the other in heauen with himſelfe after his Reſurrection; he taketh an occaſion to exhort the Hebrewes, that ſithence their Forefathers entred not through their incredulity into Gods reſt, figured by the firſt Sabaoth, they ſhould haſten to enter into the reſt of Chriſt, by the day of his new Sabaoth repreſented, from

which Text litterally, ſo, and truly explicated, I make this argument.
                  The firſt Sabaoth repreſenting that reſt which God gaue to his people before Chriſt, of which it is ſayd Geneſis 2. he reſted the ſeauenth day from his workes &amp;c. is ended according to the Apoſtle verſ. 7. &amp; 8. and a new Sabaoth, or Symbolicall day of reſt was fortould by Dauid, and ordayned by Chriſt after his labours ended verſ. 9. 10. But no new Sabaoth or Symbolicall day of reſt, diſtinct from the ſeauenth day can be vnderſtood to haue beene mentioned by Dauid, and inſtituted by Chriſt after his labours ended, praeter diem Dominicum, beſides the day of his glorious Reſurrection. Therefore the old Sabaoth figuring the reſt, whereunto God inuited holy people before Chriſt, is now ended, and the Dominicall day, ſymbolizing the new reſt which Chriſtians inuited holy ſoules vnto is in place thereof happily ſucceeded.
                  
                     Iohn Traske lately entred into a humor of reading hiſtories that he might ſeeme skilled in ſome other good ſtudies, beſides the knowledg of Scriptures, may chance to ſtumble vpon an obiection ſeemingly ſufficient to proue the continuance at leaſt of the old Sabaoth, togeather with our Lords day. For example S. Gregory Niſſen in his Oration againſt ſuch as brooked not reprehenſions, asketh an Heretike, with what eyes he ſaw our Lords day, who deſpiſed

the Sabaoth, theſe dayes being brethren, ſo as he that reproacheth the one wrongeth the other alſo. Socrates lib. 6. hiſt. cap. 8. affirmeth the Sabaoth and our Lords day to be the weekly feaſts of Chriſtians, wherein they were wont to aſſemble themſelues. And Anaſtaſius Nicenus lib quaest. 77. affirmeth thoſe two dayes to be holy and feſtiuall. The Apoſtolicall Church alſo of Aethiopia doth at this day religiouſly obſerue both Sabaoths: ſo as the old Sabaoth by theſe hiſtoricall paſſages, and other authenticall teſtimonies of antiquity, ſeemeth not to haue beene abrogated by the Apoſtles.
                  Whereunto I anſwere, that albeit the Apoſtles abrogated the old Sabaoth, and introduced the obſeruatiō of our Lords day in place thereof, as is already proued in this and my former queſtion, yet afterwards Chriſtian Biſhops, occaſionally, and for a while only in many Eaſterne Churches renewed a feſtiuall and Chriſtian obſeruance thereof, not that they held the Moyſaicall precept ſtill to oblige them thereunto, as doth Iohn Traſke and his diſciples, or that as Ebion, they held it neceſſary for all Chriſtians equally to obſerue both Sabaothes, whoſe opinion all the ancient Fathers are knowne generally▪ to haue deteſted. But for a holy and zealous refutation of the Symonians, Menandrians, Cerinthians, Carpocratians, Baſilidians, Marcioniſtes, and other like Heretykes, who to reproach the Author of the old

Teſtament, whom they tearmed An euill God &amp; leaſt they might ſeeme to honor him in any ſort, feaſted on the Sabaoth, as S. Epiphanius recounted haereſ. 42. the holy Paſtours and people of Chriſts Church in a zealous deteſtation of their blaſphemies, and to ſhew the ſame God to haue beene author of both Teſtaments faithfully and fittly for a tyme obſerued both Sabaothes, forbidding any Chriſtian vnder grieuous penalties to faſt on Saturday more then on our Lords day, one Saturday only excepted wherein our Sauiour lay dead in his ſepulcher, as is expreſly mentioned in S. Ignatius Epist. ad Philipenſes, in the 55. Apoſtolicall Canon, and in ſundry other ancient Authors. Which Chriſtian and occaſionall obſeruance of the old Sabaoth is knowne not to haue beene generally practiſed, but only in particuler Churches, wherein ſuch heretikes liued: and as thoſe Hereſies ceaſed, the feſtiuall keeping of the Sabaoth ceaſed alſo, and Chriſtians feaſted aſwell on it, as on friday in memory of our Sauiours death, and the Apoſtles ſorrow continued vntill his ioyfull Reſurrection, as is expreſly affirmed by Innocentius epiſt. 2. c. 4. Hieron. epiſt. 97. August. epiſt. 86. &amp; 18. by Caſſianus collat. 3. cap. 10 &amp;c. As for the Aethiopians ſtill obſeruing the Sabaoth, I anſwere, that they are knowne to haue byn corrupted ſince their Apoſtolicall conuerſion with many Hereticall and Iudaical doctrines, practiſing circumciſion and ſundry other rites of Moyſes law, vnlawfull

to Chriſtians.
                  An other Argument much vſed by Traskes Diſciples is, that if circumciſion were by an expreſſe decree of the Apoſtles Act. 15. repealed, with much more reaſon was the Sabaoth by their like decree to haue ben abrogated alſo, conſidering that the Commandement thereof was included amongeſt the other morall, and ſtill continuing precepts of the Decalogue tables &amp;c. Wherunto I anſwere firſt, that Circumciſion was indeed by the Apoſtles declared to be a burdenſome and vnneceſſary precept, to be impoſed on the Gentills. But to the Iewes it was abrogated only, as generally the Sabaoth was, by the contrary doctrine of the Apoſtles, ſufficiently warranting and ſecuring the conſience of any good Chriſtian, to belieue and practiſe any point of Religion taught by them, albeit we read of no Apoſtolicall Synode purpoſely made to determine the ſame.
                  Secondly I anſwere, that an expreſſe decree was more neceſſary to haue ben made by the Apoſtles of abrogating the practiſe of Circumciſion then of transferring the Sabaoth to an other more myſterious and memorable day; the determination of the ſeauenth day rather then any other being as I haue els where declared, immateriall to the religious obſeruance of Gods Commandement, binding only according to the morall end, and intention thereof, faithfull people to abſtaine in one day of ſeauen from

ſeruile labours, and to deuote the ſame to Gods eſpeciall honor and ſeruice: whereas the practiſe of Circumciſion giuen before Moyſes, as a couenant and ſigne, diſtinguiſhing Abrahams holy poſterity from other faithleſſe people, was wholy to be repealed, notwithſtanding the Iewes ſo highly regarded it, as not to conuerſe or admit into their Temple any one that wanted that holy ſeale, and ſigne of Gods couenant with them.
                  Other arguments more friuolous &amp; leſſe important I willingly omit, being loath to detaine my Reader needlesly, and impertinently in them, wiſhing heere for a finall concluſion of this queſtion, that Io. Traske and his bretheren would maturely conſider the finall iſſue of their vnchriſtian and exorbitant doctrines, disliked by our Soueraigne and State, contradicted by all learned men comming to heare of them, and vtterly as yet vnheard of in other partes of Chriſtendome: ſo as the firſt Inuenters and obſtinate Profeſſers of them can truly belonge to no Chriſtian Church, preſent now, or paſt in any age before them.
               
               
                  
                  
                     QVESTION V: VVherein is proued that Chriſtians are to celebrate the yearly day of our Sauiours Reſurrection on Sunday, and not on the 14. day of March-Moone, as the Iewes celebrated their Paſchall.
                  
                     IOHN Traske in his humor of Iudaiſme &amp; Hereticall innouation, is lately growne ſo great an enemie to the weekely obſeruance of our Lords day, as he ſeemeth alſo to deny the yearely feaſt of our Sauiours Reſurrection to be lawfully celebrated on any other day in the yeare then the 14. of March-moone, wherin the Iewes were commaunded by God to celebrate their Paſſouer. And vpon his late reading in Euſebius lib 5. hiſt. cap. 22. Policrates epiſtle directed to Victor Biſhop of Rome concerning the Aſian cuſtome of keeping eaſter with the Iews, &amp; S. Irenaus his iudgment that Victor did with ouer much ſeuerity excomunicate many Eaſterne Churches, for perſiſting in that wonted Quartadeciman manner of celebrating the yearly day of our Sauiours Reſurrection, togeather with the Iewes Paſchall; he will arrogantly preſume to call Victor that holy Biſhop &amp; Martyr, famouſly mentioned in ancient hiſtories, a proud Prelate, and not ſticke to accuſe other ancient

Fathers of ignorance in cenſuring afterwards, and condemning for heretikes the Quartadeciman obſeruers of Eaſter: God himſelfe, ſaith he, hauing expreſly commanded, &amp; Chriſt himſelfe with his Apoſtles celebrated on that day his Paſchall feſtiuity.
                  And not contented with this hereticall temerity of renewing the Quartadeciman hereſy, he ſurpaſſeth Blaſtus himſelf in his Iewiſh manner of keeping Eaſter. For as I haue touched in my Preface, he by his eating of vnleuened bread ſeauen dayes togeather after the 14. of March-Moone, and by ſundry ſpeaches vttered to ſome of his fellow priſoners, hath giuen great ſuſpitions that lately he hath obſerued the feaſt of Azimes, togeather with his diſciples. The next yeare peradueuture they will haue profited in Iudaiſme ſo far, as to ſacrifice a Paſchall Lambe alſo. And laſtly it is to be feared, that falling more and more from their Chriſtiā profeſſion, they will with Adam Neuſerus, Bernardinus Ochinus, and other Puritan Deuines finally forſake Chriſt, and imbrace Iudaiſme, or Turciſme, the fearefull ſequell and iuſt puniſhment of ſuch fantaſtical ſpirits, as will imbrace no Religion but of their owne deuiſing, nor be obedient children to any Church, but of their owne raiſing.
                  But let Iohn Traske, and his Diſciples celebrate what Paſchall they will, and on what day they pleaſe, our Paſchal-Lambe according

to the Apoſtle 1. Corinth. 5. verſ. 7. 8. is Chriſt ſacrificed in the euening of the world, for our redemption: and our feſtiuall azimes are to be as neere, as by the aſſiſtance of diuine graces we ſhallbe able to arriue vnto, the ſincerity of holy actions, and verity of doctrines, whereby our ſoules may be happily nouriſhed after their ſpirituall flight out of Aegypt, and conducted towards the eternal inheritance of heauen through the merit of Chriſts holy life and paſſion prepared for vs; humbling our ſelues heer, to be els where eternally exalted; eſchewing any temper, as neere as we can, of that Phariſaicall leauen, with which Traskes ſpeaches, and actions are as it may be probably gheſſed in Gods ſight abhominably corrupted, who with his diſciples will not ſeem to be ſicut ceteri homines in any thing, ſhewing all thoſe ſimptoms, wherby the ſpirituall Phiſitian of ſoules was pleaſed to deſcribe the infection of the Scribes and Phariſyes, rightly by him compared to dead mens ſepulchers painted and poliſhed without, but internally filled with all guile and malice.
                  The Apoſtle telleth the Galathians cap. 5. verſ. 2. &amp; 3. that whoſoeuer circumciſeth himſelfe, maketh himſelfe a debtour of the whole law, and Chriſts death profiteth him not: and ſo it may be proportionably auerred of Traske, that in teaching the feſtiuall obſeruance of Azimes he is conſequently alſo bound by the ſame

reaſon, to obſerue the entire Law of Moyſes, &amp; ſo cannot be longer a Chriſtian. He was wont heeretofore to vnderſtand that text of the Apoſtle ad Coloſſ. 2. Let not man iudge or diſcouer you in meate or drinke, or new moones, or part of a feſtiuall day &amp;c. of the Ceremoniall feaſts of the Iewes mentioned Leuitic. 23. abrogated by Chriſt, amongſt which the feaſt of Azimes is firſt mentioned. But he hath as it ſhould ſeeme ſince altered his iudgment, &amp; (as Ebion &amp; his diſciples were wont) little I feare doth he regard any doctrine contayned in S. Paules Epiſtles. Policrates Epiſtle neuer taught him to conioyne the Iudaicall feaſts of Azimes with our Chriſtian Paſſouer, only that ancient Biſhop of Epheſus in a prepoſterous zeale of obſeruing the yearly memory of our Sauiours reſurrection, as S. Policarpe and other great Saintes had done before him in thoſe partes of Aſia, wrote very erneſtly in the defence of that Quartadeciman Cuſtome. Whoſe authority hath, as it ſhould ſeeme, much moued Iohn Traske, who either out of ignorance had neuer before read, or out of raſhenes neuer marked, far more conuincing proofes for the Dominicall obſeruance of Eaſter.
                  For long before Victors decree thereof, Pius his holy predeceſſor, as. Euſebius recounteth in his Chronicle, declared it to haue byn an Apoſtolicall doctrine that Chriſtians ſhould keep their Eaſter on the Sunday, and not on the 14. of March-moone, as the Iewes celebrated their

Paſchall. Socrates alſo lib. 5. hiſt. cap. 21. expreſly affirmeth, that S. Peter &amp; S. Paul taught in the Roman and other Weſtern Churches the like Dominicall obſeruaunce of Eaſter, which is alſo teſtified by S. Protenius, Patriarch of Alexandria in his Epiſtly to S. Leo, wherein he teſtifieth alſo, that S. Marke introduced the ſame manner of keeping Eaſter in the Egyptian Churches S. Ignatius who ſaw our Lord himſelf in fleſh, who alſo conuerſed with many of the Apoſtles, and was the ſecond Biſhop of Antioch after S. Peter, in his epiſtle to the Magneſians, not only taught them to keepe holy our Lords day, as the queene and chiefeſt of all other daies conſecrated to our Sauiours Reſurrection, but alſo he conteſteth Epiſt. ad Philip. that any Chriſtian celebrating his Paſchall with the Iewes, maketh himſelfe thereby a partaker with thoſe who killed our Lord himſelfe, and his Apoſtles.
                  Neither was the decre of keeping Eaſter on the Sunday lightly made in Victors tyme, but grauely and maturely determined in many holy and learned Synods of Biſhops, aſſembled by Victors appointement, before he proceeded to excōmunicate the Aſian Biſhops, as Euſebius in his chronicle alſo teſtifieth; in ſo much as beſids the Councell which Victor himſelfe called at Rome, Theophilus metropolitan of Ceſaraea, Narciſſus Patriarth of Hieruſalem, Palmas Biſhop of Pontus, S. Irenaeus Biſhop of Lions, Barchillus Biſhop of Corinth, and many Biſhops of other

Prouinces aſſembled Synods, and with one conſent from no other fountayne then the certaine doctrine &amp; tradition of the Apoſtles themſelues determined the Dominicall obſeruance of Eaſter. So that Policrates aſſertion hauing byn taught by S. Iohn, the Quartadeciman manner of keeping the yearly feaſt of our Sauiours Reſurrection, ſeemeth to be againſt S. Iohns owne writing, Apocal. 2. calling Sunday, Diem Dominicum, our Lords day, for the reaſon formerly aſſigned by his ſcoller Ignatius, to wit, becauſe it was ſanctified, and chiefely aboue all other dayes obſerued by Chriſtians for our Sauiours Reſurrection which theron hapned. And if in a feſtiuall and holy memory of that ſacred myſtery the Apoſtles themſelues inſtituted a weekely obſeruance of that day; how can it be wiſely thought that they would haue the anniuerſary day it ſelfe of our Sauiours Reſurrection not celebrated on that determinate day alſo? Wherfore, as we may ſuppoſe, that which S. Iohn only permitted in Aſia for the peace of thoſe Churches, touching their Quartadeciman obſeruance of Eaſter, Policrates partially and miſtakingly affirmeth it to haue beene taught by the Apoſtle.
                  As for S. Irenaeus agreeing with Victor in his doctrine, yet ſeeming to blame him for ouermuch ſeuerity vſed in excommunicating the Aſian Churches for a practiſe tolerated in thē long before by his holy predeceſſours; I anſwere,

that Irenaeus peraduenture knew not Victors motiues of doing ſo, which was to reſiſt Montanus errours then newly begun to be broached in Aſia, and to cut quickly off Blaſtus Iudaicall innouations, riſing euen in Rome it ſelfe, and much confirmed by that legall manner of keeping Eaſter, which made holy Victor to vndertake a violent remedy to cure a dangerous wound then begining to corrupt the purity of Chriſtian doctrine in many Churches: the caſe of the Aſian Biſhops being not the ſame then, as it was in S. Policarpes dayes. For wheras before they only by permiſſion obſerued Eaſter with the Iewes, in Victors time they held it to be an Apoſtolical inſtitutiō, neceſſary to be imbraced by all other Churches. In which decree Victor was according to his name truly Victorious, the whole Church of Chriſt taking afterwards part with him, and numbring the Quartadecimans amongſt other Iudaizing heretikes: and the Nicen Councell, as S. Athanaſius writeth in his booke of Synods, reclaymed multitudes of them, renewing Pope Victors decree of keeping Eaſter on the Sunday, and ordayning that the Patriarches of Alexandria for the Aegyptian skill aboue other Nations, in computing yeares and dayes, ſhould be appointed to order yearly the Paſchall Cicles, and by their Epiſtles firſt directed to the Roman Biſhop, and by him to other Churches, to determine the Sunday, on which Eaſter day was yearly to be obſerued by

Chriſtians, as is teſtified by S. Leo Epiſt. 64. ad Marcianum Imperat. and is to be ſeene in the Paſchal epiſtles themſelues of Theophilus Biſhop of Alexandria, tranſlated by S. Hierome, and yet extant Tom. 1. Biblioth. Sanct. PP. All which &amp; many other authentical teſtimonies of antiquity for proofe of our Chriſtian manner of keeping Eaſter on the Sunday, Io. Traske is likely to regard as little in this as he doth in other controuerſies, a ceremoniall precept of the Moyſaicall Law, being apter to conuince his fantaſticall iudgement, and immoueably determine him in any opinion, let all Chriſtian Churches preſent and paſt, teach and practiſe what they will againſt him.
               
            
            
               
               THE II. CONTROVERSY.
               
                  
                     QVESTION I. Of the vncleaneſſe of meates before Moyſes Law.
                  
                     
                        IOHN Traske and his diſciples hold the Legall difference of meates mentioned Leuit. 11. Deutron. 10. to be ſo morall in it ſelfe, and religiouſly from mans firſt creation by faythfull people obſerued, as our firſt Parents themſelues in Paradiſe had the ſame in a ſort commanded to thē, and their holy poſterity euer afterwards 
                        ••
                     actiſed it: as may be gathered (ſay they) by that difference of cleane &amp; vncleane beaſts entring the Arke Geneſ 7. verſ. 2. 3. their vſuall argument being this following. That which was from the beginning commanded by God, and by holy people obſerued, is no doubt a moral precept ſtill to continue: But the Law of meates was from the beginning

commanded by God, and by holy people obſerued: Therefore it is as a morall precept ſtill to continue.
                  Which argument before I proceed fully and particulerly to anſwere, I purpoſe heere orderly to ouerthrow the doctrinall groundes thereof. Firſt abſolutly denying, that Gods precept of not eating the forbidden fruit giuen to our firſt parents in Paradiſe, was any Law at all of vncleane meates, as ridiculouſly they ſuppoſe it to haue beene, but only a commandment of abſtinence, impoſed by God for a holy exerciſe, and triall of their obedience towards him, that hauing 
                        •…
                     eir ſoules illuminated and ſanctifyed with abundant graces, and all ſenſuall and diſordered motions of their inferiour fleſhly nature happily reſtrayned, and ſuppreſſed with the golden bridle of originall iuſtice, ſo as all other morall precepts were eaſily, &amp; connaturally as it were in that harmonious vnion of nature and grace obſerued by them: God was pleaſed only in an extrinſecall &amp; indifferent matter, to exact their due obedience &amp; ſubiection towards him; which did no more concerne the Moyſaicall difference of meats afterwards commanded, then if he had forbidden them to touch the ſame tree, or to eate of any another fruit in Paradiſe; nor was the tree, but the willfull tranſgreſſion of their Creators cōmandment vncleane, &amp; aſwell in thēſelus as in their vnhappy poſterity fearfully puniſhed.
                  
                     As for the difference of birds and beaſts, cleane and vncleane entring the Arke, which is another chiefe ground of Traskes former argument: I anſwere, that this vncleanes was not then vnderſtood in reſpect of their vſe for food, but for the ſacrifyces of thoſe former times before Moyſes, wherin no birds or beaſts but ſuch as were legally afterwards reputed cleane in Moyſes Law, could be offered, as may be gathered out of Abels ſacrifice Gen. 4. verſ. 4. of Noahs, cap. 6. verſ 20. of Abrahams, cap. 15. verſ. 9. of Ioabs, cap. 42. verſ. 8. &amp;c. God himſelfe no doubt hauing giuen ſome eſpeciall ordinance or inſpiration thereof to Adam himſelf or Seth his holy ſonne, who is ſaid to haue begun to inuoke Gods Name, Geneſ. 4. verſ. 26. which muſt neceſſarily be vnderſtood of ſome peculiar rites, and order of celebrating ſacrifices, firſt taught and practiſed by him.
                  But that thoſe birds and beaſts are not ſayd to haue beene then vncleane for food and vnlawfully to be eaten, as afterwards in Moyſes Law they were declared to be, I proue, becauſe before the floud they ſeeme not at all to haue beene by holy people vſed for food, and after Noahs tyme vntill Moyſes Law giuen, all meats, but ſtrangled and bloud, were freely permitted. The former of theſe two aſſertions, I proue by this vnanſwerable argument. Holy people before the floud did only eate ſuch meats as God had licenſed and appointed them

for food. But before the floud no fleſh or fiſh was by God licenſed, &amp; appointed vnto them for food, but only hearbs &amp; fruits of the earth as Gods owne words do expreſly import, Gen. 1. verſ. 29. ſaying: Behold I haue giuen you all kind of hearbs that ſeed vpon the earth, and all trees that haue in themſelues ſeed of their owne kind to be your meate &amp;c. not mentioning fiſh, birds, or beaſts, as afterwards he did to Noah and his poſterity cap. 9. verſ. 2. 3. Wherefore only hearbs &amp; fruits of the earth were then eaten by holy people.
                  And a double reaſon may be yealded, why ſuch hearbes and fruites of the earth were more ſufficient for mans ſuſtenance before the floud then after. Firſt for that the earth was by the deluge of ſalt▪ waters corrupted, and altered from the former fertility therof, and yealded not ſuch wholſome and nouriſhing fruites as it did before, whilſt it purely remayned in that eſtate wherein God created it, and whilſt the firſt progeny, as I may terme it, of hearbes and trees remayned, which God himſelfe had out of the earth produced Secondly alſo for that mens nature in proceſſe of time became weakned, and leſſe able by the fruites of the earth to be ſuſtained, then it was before, when it newly came out of Gods own omnipotent hands, that did temper and frame the ſame in all naturall perfection, and ordaine it no doubt long after ſo to continue, as it appeareth by the laſting liues of our firſt humane progenitors, and their naturall

force to beget childrē after they had liued many hundreds of yeares. Wherfore holy Iacob tould Pharao demaunding his age Gen. 47. verſ. 8. &amp; 9. that his daies were ā hundred &amp; thirty yeares, ſhort and euill, to wit, ſubiect to infirmity and diſeaſes, and not ariuing to the daies of his fore-Fathers.
                  Likewiſe that after Noah vntill Moyſes Law giuen (which is my ſecond aſſertion here to be proued) all meates, but ſtrangled and bloud, were freely permitted, may euidently be gathered out of Gen. cap. 9. verſ. 2. 3. 4. where God firſt licenſing men to eate fiſh and fleſh, Euery thing (ſaith he) which moueth and liueth ſhall be to you for food, as growing hearbes, I haue deliuered thē vnto you, excepting that you ſhall not eate fleſh with bloud. Out of which text I argue thus againſt Iohn Traske. Holy people from Noah vnto Moyſes tyme might lawfully eate al meates licenſed vnto them by God to be eaten: But all meates, except ſuch as were ſtrangled &amp; bloud were licenſed by God to be eaten by them. Therfore they might lawfully eate them. The firſt propoſition is certaine, and graunted by Traske. The ſecond likewiſe is euident, becauſe ſtrangled meates and bloud are in that generall Law and appointment of Creatures for food, only excepted; which kind of exception in ſuch an vniuerſall rule as that text conteineth, authorizeth all other particulers not therin expreſſed, or out of the ſame neceſſarily deduced.
                  
                     So that the Minor of Ie. Traskes aboue mentioned argumēt is falſe, to wit, that the Moyſaicall difference of meates was from the begining cō
                     maunded by God, and by holy people obſerued. And were it graunted to be true, that the Moyſaicall difference of meates had ben ſo cōmaunded by God, and by holy people euer vntill Chriſts time obſerued: yet doth it not thence neceſſarily follow, that now alſom like manner it is to be practiſed by Chriſtians all cerimonies and figures of former times, aſ well before Moyſes Law, as after, being by Chriſt fulfilled, and wholy ceaſed: amongſt which the legall vncleaneſſe of meates was one, as ſhall be afterwardes fully declared.
                  The firſt Propoſition alſo of that great argument is clearly falſe, to wit, that euery religious rite from the beginning commaunded by God, and by holy people obſerued, is doubtles a morall Law euer to continue amongſt Chriſtians: becauſe bloudy ſacrifices, for example, were from the begining inſpired by God, and practiſed by Adams faithfull poſterity, and yet as types of Chriſts bloudy ſacrifice they were now with the ſame wholy abrogated &amp; ended; ſo that, it is no ſuch certaine ſigne, as Traske would haue it, of a morall and euer continuing Law that the ſame was from the beginning inſpired or commaunded by God, and by faithfull people, vntill Chriſts comming obſerued.
               
               
                  
                  
                     QVESTION II. Of the Moyſaicall law of meats, and myſterious endes why God commaunded it.
                  
                     IOHN Traske willingly admitteth the common diuiſion of the old law into Morall, Iudiciall, and Cerimoniall Precepts, mentioned by Moyſes himſelfe, Deut. 2. verſ. 1. and taught by all moderne and ancient Writers, treating of the two later ſortes of Precepts abrogated by our Sauiours comming. So that if it may by euident circumſtances of the text be proued heere in this queſtion by me, that the legall obſeruance of meates commanded to the Iewes Leuit. 11. Deut. 14. was meerly cerimoniall, and for typical &amp; myſterious reſpects only impoſed, ſuch as can haue now no morall end to be ſtill cōtinued &amp; practiſed by Chriſtians; I ſhal eaſily ſhake and ouerthrow the ſandy and fleeting ground of my Aduerſaries doctrine.
                  And to proceed orderly in this queſtion, and fitly for my purpoſe. I proue firſt, this Law of meates to haue beene meerely cerimoniall, becauſe it is not at all mentioned, but joyntly &amp; commixt with other Cerimonies of Moyſes law. For in Leuiticus it is immediatly anexed to the Typicall rites of ſacrifices and oblations, &amp; hath ſubſequently following it the cerimonious law and order of cleanſings and puriſications

&amp;c. In Deutron. likewiſe it hath before it many Iudiciall precepts, and that whole cerimonial ordinance of celebrating feſtiual yeares, daies, Sacrifices after it &amp;c which is a ſigne at leaſt, that this differentiall law of meates is cerimoniall alſo, and no morall part of Moyſes law. Secondly the endes for which this diſtinction of meates was holily ordained by God, do ſufficiently declare it to haue byn cerimoniall then, and in no ſort now appertaining to the morall obſeruance of our Chriſtian duties. The firſt &amp; chiefeſt end therof expreſſed by God himſelfe, Deut. 14. verſ. 2. was, that this obſeruance of meates might be a note and diſtinctiue ſigne of his people. Becauſe (ſaith Moyſes) thou art holy to thy Lord God, and he hath choſen thee amongſt all other nations of the earth to be his peculiar people, eate not things vncleane. So that this Iudaicall difference of meates was part of that middle vnmortered wall of Cerimoniall and Iudiciall Precepts, ſeparating for a time Iewes and Gentills, vntill our Sauiour threw it downe, conioyning in him ſelfe the foundation &amp; cornerſtone both people in the ſpirituall edifice and building of his Church, ad Epheſ. 2. verſ. 14. &amp; 15. ſo that now as there is no diſtinction further made betweene Iew and Gentil ad Rom. 3. verſ. 9. &amp; 29. Act. 15. verſ. 6. and as circumciſion, and other diſtinctiue ſignes, cauſing enmity and diuiſion betweene thoſe two people, now vnited in Chriſt, are by his death on the

croſſe taken away and deſtroyed: So is the law of difference impoſed for that end, euacuated alſo.
                  Secondly, as marriage with Gentills was forbidden to the Iewes, for that it was foreſeene by God to be an occaſion to ſeduce and drawe them from their faithfull profeſſion, Exod. 34. verſ. 16. as was lamentably experienced in Salomon 3. Reg. 11. v. 1. &amp; 2. and many other Iewes by that meanes corrupted: So for the ſame cauſe, Almighty God was pleaſed to inioyne them ſuch a ſtrict abſtinence, and horrour of ſundry meates, vſed by the Gentills round about them, and ſuch purifications for any that did either touch thoſe meates, or ſuch perſons as had eaten them, that the Iewes for a neceſſary obſeruance of their law, were inforced in a manner to abſtaine from all ciuill commerce and conuerſation with ſuch Gentile nations as might be powerfull to ſeduce them, accounting it a great abhomination euen to enter into them, as S. Peter tould Cornelius, Act. 10. verſ. 28. Which reaſon of forbidding meates is now taken away by the happy conuerſion of Gentile people to Chriſt.
                  Thirdly theſe vncleane foules and beaſts forbidden in Moyſes law, figured the impure manners and abhominable rites of the Gentills, as appeareth by S. Peters viſion Act. 10. verſ. 11. by which our Sauiour myſtically taught him to account no man vncleanē, as

before he had done, ibid. verſ. 8. Wherfore as the Gentils ſpirituall vncleaneſſe was cleanſed by their faith in Chriſt, Act. 15. verſ. 9. ſo was the figure therof to ceaſe alſo. And conſequently this, and all other endes of the cerimoniall law of meates, ceaſing at Chriſts comming, the obligation of the law it ſelfe was abrogated alſo. A third Argument to proue the legall difference of meates to haue beene cerimoniall &amp; appertaining to the Iewes only, whilſt they remayned diſtinguiſhed from other people, may be gathered from theſe wordes ſo often repeated by God in the ordinance of that law, They ſhalbe vncleane to you, abhominable to you, execrable to you &amp;c. which manners of ſpeach import that in themſelues and to other nations they were not ſo, but by his forbidding of them only made ſo.
                  Fourthly, the ſame arguments by which Iohn Traske vſually proueth this law of meates to be morall, and not cerimoniall, proue many other Iudiciall partes of Moyſes law morall alſo, and ſtill to be obſerued by Chriſtians. Traskes common argument is, that the Scriptures being perfect, muſt expreſly containe a ſufficient and particuler rule to direct Chriſtians in all things, concerning their duty towards God, and ciuill conuerſation amongſt themſelues, as what to eate, what to weare &amp;c. but this particuler rule &amp; direction of meats, for example, to be eaten or not eaten by Chriſtians, is no where expreſſed,

but in the 11. Chap. of Leuitic. and 19. of Deutr. Therefore the Law of meats conteyned in thoſe Chapters is morall, &amp; ſtill to be obſerued by Chriſtians. The Maior of which argument is falſe, that the Scriptures muſt expreſly &amp; particulerly inſtruct vs in all naturall actions as what to eate, what to weare &amp;c. For God hath giuen vs a naturall Law to direct vs ſufficiently in ſuch particuler actions, according to moral and generall precepts of auoyding ſinne in them, as to eate only ſuch meats as are wholſome &amp; neceſſary to ſuſtaine our bodily forces, humbly thanking, and intending to ſerue our Creatour by them; to weare only ſuch garments as are conuenient for our eſtate, &amp; needfull to couer and keep our bodyes healthful &amp;c. leauing vs to holy liberty to exerciſe religious abſtinence and mortification in them: ſo as no other ſupernaturall rule is neceſſary to appoint either the particuler faſhions of our garments, the kinds of meats which are to be eaten, the manners of dreſſing them &amp;c. the Scriptures teaching vs not to be good Cookes or Taylers, but to be good Chriſtians, and to carry our ſelues morally, and without ſinne in all our actions, whereunto the ſpeciall nature of meats is wholy impertinent, as I ſhall declare more fully in my next Queſtion.
                  
                     Iohn Traske out of the generall promiſes of Chriſts graces and mercies, plentifully ordayned for faythfull, righteous, and penitent

perſons, arrogantly preſumeth aſſuredly and infallibly to collect the particuler election of himſelfe, &amp; others of his diſciples, els why wil he ridiculouſly deny the ſufficiency of generall precepts and inſtructions to direct vs in moral and particuler actions? Or why doth he admit of many vnneceſſary trades imbraced by ſome of his chiefe diſciples, as the trade of Comfitmaking, Perfuming &amp;c. tending in their own nature to luxury, and no where expreſly mentioned in Scripture, no not in ſuch places, wherein the delicacies of Kings themſelues are expreſſed, as Samuel 1. cap. 8. Paralip. 2. cap. 9. 3. Reg. cap. 10. &amp;c. Moreouer as there is no particuler appointment of meats, but in thoſe Chapters of Leuitic. and Deutr. ſo is there no particuler determination of iudgmēts againſt malefactours, and particuler lawes to be obſerued for the ciuill gouernement of people, but ſuch as are contayned in Moyſes Law: yet will not Traske I ſuppoſe, be ſo very a Iew, as to introduce amongſt Chriſtians a neceſſary practiſe of ſuch Iudicial, and ſundry other cerimoniall precepts, ſeeming more pertinent to the morality of Chriſtians, then the legall obſeruance of meates, neither vncleane in themſelues, as the Minicheans and other hatefull Heretikes ſuppoſed them, nor defiling in any fort the ſoules of ſuch as do eat them, with thanks and a holy intention to honour God by a temperate vſe of them. Laſtly Iohn Traske
                     
admitting the legall difference and vncleanes of meats yet to continue amongſt Chriſtians, is conſequently alſo bound to admit legall purifications appointed to be vſed by ſuch as had eaten, or touched them, as waſhing of their cloathes, ſecluding themſelues from humane ſociety, till the euening &amp;c. which he ſeemeth not to do, but reiecteth them as cerimonious, and impertinent now to the morall direction of Chriſtians.
               
               
                  
                     QVESTION III. VVherein the proper and perfect rule of moral Actions is briefly declared: and how according to the ſame no meates are now vncleane, and vnlawfull to Chriſtians.
                  
                     IOHN Traske and his diſciples are ſo abſurd in their doctrine of meats, as they wholy in a manner reiect humane reaſon, from being any direction or rule at all to guide them in morall actions. The Law of Nature, ſay they is a rule only for naturall and carnall perſons to liue by, Gods children hauing a higher Law contayned in the holy Scriptures, teaching them what to eate, and making them perfect in all things els belonging to Chriſtian manners and humane conuerſation, 2. ad Tim. 3. verſ. 15. &amp; 16. My purpoſe therfore is in this Queſtion

briefly to declare what the naturall light of reaſon is, more fully then I haue done in the 2. Queſtion of my firſt Controuerſy, ſhewing it is perfected by ſupernaturall knowledge, and ſtill remayneth a full and perfect rule to direct vs in all naturall and morall actions.
                  Naturall Reaſon is in it ſelfe the eſſentiall &amp; internall clarity of mans ſoule, by the vſe wherof we are diſtinguiſhed from bruit beaſts, taught to know what is morally good and euill in our actions, &amp; made capable of grace and all ſupernaturall perfection. So that whilſt we continue naturally men heere in this life, we muſt guide and gouerne our ſelues thereby in humane and morall actions: Faith being a ſupernaturall light, graciouſly by God infuſed into our ſoule, not to deſtroy naturall knowledge in vs, but to perfect the ſame two Wayes. Firſt by helping vs to a more eaſy and certayne knowledge of ſundry naturall verities, then we can ordinarily in this life attayne vnto, from the bare experience of our ſenſes. Secondly by notifying vnto vs the intellectuall power of our ſoule, &amp; inclining it firmely and piouſly to beleeue many reuealed myſteries far aboue the naturall reach &amp; capacity thereof to be diſcouered or thought vpon by vs: yet are they alwayes found ſo conformable thereunto, as no point of faith is to be accounted credible and worthy of our faithfull and deuout aſſent, which is in true diſcourſe repugnant to naturall reaſon &amp; iudgment in vs.
                  
                     So that Iohn Traske and his diſciples ſeeme to deale vnreaſonably, and without iudgment, in excluding naturall reaſon and iudgement from being any rule at all in morall and humane actions; contrary to the expreſſe doctrine of S. Paul ad Rom. 2. verſ. 24. 25. 26. where he affirmeth, that the very Gentils who wanted all knowledge of a written law, were a law to thē
                     ſelues, being naturally taught to obſerue that law, and to ſhew it written in their hartes (to wit, according to the morall precepts thereof) their owne conſciences ſufficiently ſeruing to approue them in good, and to condemne them in euill actions, and ſo conſequently to be a proper rule to guide and direct them in all morall and humane actions. The ſupernaturall direction of fayth, being graciouſly by Chriſt ordayned, as I haue formerly ſayd, to facilitate and explane naturall knowledge many wayes corrupted, and obſcured in vs, and happily to conduce vs to a higher degree of heauenly knowledge and Euangelicall perfection, is idly and ignorantly confounded by Traske with naturall morality, and falſely made the only and proper rule of humane &amp; morall actions, which Gentill people wanted not, according to the Apoſtle, who notwithſtanding are knowne not to haue had the light of heauenly knowledg &amp; euangelicall perfection reuealed vnto them.
                  Which true diſtinction of a morall and ſupernaturall law ſuppoſed, I heere vndertake to

proue the law of meates mentioned Leuit. 11. &amp; Deutr. 14. to haue ben meerly cerimoniall, and no way now to appertaine to the morall or ſuſupernaturall law and direction of Chriſtians. And that the Iudaicall obſeruance of meates appertayneth not to that internall law of reaſon written by God in the hartes of all men, and ſuficiently teaching them to knowe the morall good and euill of their actions, and to make a cōſcience of them. I proue it firſt, becauſe neuer any Philoſopher, or Wiſeman among the Gentills can be proued to haue taught or practiſed, amongſt many other morall and excellent precepts deliuered &amp; obſerued by them, this difference of meats: but they are contrarily knowne to haue indifferently eaten all ſortes of meates, which experimentally they found wholſome, &amp; fit to ſuſtayn their bodyes, as Connies, Hares Swines fleſh, and other meates, prohibited to the Iewes. Which naturall and daily experience 10. Traske ridiculouſly denieth, falſely pretending them to be not only legally vncleane, but vnwholſome alſo for corporall ſuſtenance, and no more created by God for food, or leſſe forbidden by any law to be eaten, then toades and ſerpentes, which by the naturall precept of not killing our ſelus, we are taught to refraine from; not for that they are in themſelues naturally vncleane, but becauſe they are in experience found to be inconuenient and hurtfull to our nature, not nouriſhed but deſtroied by them: yet was neuer

wiſe Iewes or Chriſtians ſo abſurd before, as to teach that, for the like moral reſpect of preſeruing our naturall life, Swines fleſh was as toads and ſerpents forbidden in that precept.
                  Secondly holy people after the floud obſerued, no doubt, the morall law and diuine directions giuen them, &amp; yet as I haue proued in my former Queſtion, were no other meats but ſtrangled and bloud, and thoſe alſo for myſterious and figuratiue reſpects, expreſly vntill Moyſes tyme prohibited vnto them.
                  Thirdly our Sauiour Matt. 15. verſ. 11. 16. 17. from common reaſon and naturall vnderſtanding collecteth this vniuerſall rule and morall poſition, that nothing entring the body can defile a man, who is only made impure by ſinneful acts proceeding from his ſoule &amp;c. S. Paul alſo ad Rom. 14. verſ. 17. morally teacheth vs, that the kingdome of heauen, or the meanes of gaining heauen is not, or conſiſteth in meate and drinke, but in iuſtice, peace and ioy in the holy Ghoſt, and he that in this ſerueth Chriſt, pleaſeth God, to wit, what meats ſoeuer he eateth. For (ſayth he, 1. ad Corinth. cap. 8. v. 8.) meate commendeth vs not to God. Out of which holy texts I frame this argument. Nothing is morally vncleane, and vnlawfull to Chriſtians that defileth not their ſoules: But no meats entring their bodyes can according to our Sauiours owne words defile their ſoules: Therefore no meates are morally vncleane

and vnlawful to Chriſtians. The Maior of my argument is certaine, becauſe Chriſtian morality conſiſteth in freedome from ſinne. The Minor likewiſe is out of reaſon it ſelfe deduced by our Sauiours blaming his diſciples for conceauing that any meate eaten by the mouth can of it ſelfe defile the ſoule, and ſo conſequently for any natural vncleanes be vnlawfull to be vſed: wherefore the legall prohibition of them, cannot be morall but myſterious and cerimoniall. Secondly I frame this argument. That which neither commendeth men to God, nor appertayneth to the gayning of heauen, as Iuſtice and other vertues do cannot belong to the morall or ſupernaturall duty of a Chriſtian: But meats according to S. Paul do neither of themſelues commend vs to God, nor ſo appertayne to the gayning of heauen, as Iuſtice and other vertues do: Therfore meats of themſelues cannot belong to the morall or ſupernaturall duty of Chriſtians, and conſequently no Chriſtian is now bound to the legall obſeruance of them.
                  Fourthly S. Paul 1 ad Tim. 4. v. 3. 4. &amp; 5. ſpeaking againſt Heretiks teaching people to abſtaine from meats which God created to be receaued with thankeſgiuing by faythfull perſons, and ſuch as know the truth, yieldeth this reaſon of his doctrine. Becauſe euery creature of God is good, and nothing to be reiected (to wit for meat) which is receaued with thanksgiuing: for it
                     
                     is ſanctifyed by the word of God and prayer. In which Text albeit it ſhould be graunted that the Apoſtle chiefly diſputed againſt the Symonians, Saturnians, Marcionites, and other like Heretiks, who in, and ſoone after the Apoſtles times, taught many Creatures to be ill in their owne nature, as hauing been by an euill God created, and ſo to be deteſted by Chriſtians: yet the reaſon of his doctrine is moral and ſufficient to ſhew the legall impurity of meats abrogated by our Sauiour, which I proue by this argument.
                  Euery Creature of God that is good, and not to be reiected, being receaued with thanskgiuing, may lawfully be eaten by Chriſtians: But euery Creature of God is good, acording to the Apoſtle, and not to be reiected being receaued with thanskgiuing: Therefore euery creature may lawfully be eaten with prayer and thanskſgiuing by Chriſtians. Secondly I argue thus. No creature is to be accounted impure for food which is or may be ſanctified by him that eateth it: But S. Paul affirmeth, euery Creature to be ſanctified with the word of God, and by the prayer of him that with thankſgiuing receaueth it. Therfore no Creature is to be accounted impure for food, being with prayer and thankſgiuing ſo receaued. If Traske aske me how it is to be vnderſtood, that all creatures may be ſanctified with the praiers &amp; thankſgiuing of ſuch as receaue them; I anſwere, that thoſe words of

                     S. Paul in their true ſenſe, do only importe, that whoſoeuer eateth any creature with prayer and thankſgiuing, maketh a holy vſe thereof, and ſo that Creature may rightly be called holy, or a cauſe of holynes to him that ſo receaueth it.
                  If he aſke me whether it be not alſo required to the holy vſe of any creature, that it be wholſome of it ſelfe for food, and created by God to be ſo with prayer and thanksgiuing receaued; I anſwere yes, becauſe no vnwholſom creature, poyſonous, and hurtfull to our bodyes can for food be holily vſed, but wickedly againſt the naturall precept of not killing our ſelues &amp;c. And thoſe words of S. Paul, Euery creature of God is good, and nothing is to be reiected &amp;c. contayning an vniuerſall ſenſe, without limitation or exception, do neceſſarily inferre euery wholſom creature apt to noriſh our body, and to be conuerted into the naturall ſubſtance thereof, to haue beene created for that purpoſe by Almighty God, who hath giuen vs naturall iudgment and experience to know what creatures are wholſom and apt to feed and ſuſtaine vs: els were the naturall knowledge of man indiuidually to preſerue himſelf by the externall vſe of creatures, more defectiue and imperfect then the naturall inſtinct which beaſts and other liuing creatures haue to chooſe wholſom food for themſelues, and to auoid thinges harmefull and contrary to their nature. And whereas eating and other acts tending to mens indiuiduall preſeruation

are of all others belonging to our human condition and eſtate meaneſt in themſelus and moſt connaturall vnto vs, Io. Traskes barbarous folly may be worthily admired, in excluding naturall reaſon from being any rule at all, to guide and direct vs in them. And it may fitly be tearmed a deſperate and frantick kind of ignorance and impudency in him, to deny, againſt the generall experience of men, in all ages and countries of the world, that Swinesfleſh, and other beaſts, foules, and fiſhes legally prohibited, being dreſſed and eaten, are apt to nouriſh and ſuſtayne our bodyes.
               
               
                  
                     Qvestion IIII. Prouing by ſundry texts of the New Teſtament the law of meates abrogated to Chriſtians.
                  MY firſt argument prouing the differentiall law of meates to haue beene repealed by our Sauiour and his Apoſtles in the new Teſtament, ſhall be deduced out of S. Peters viſion Act. 10. v. 11. 12. 13. 14. &amp; 15. wherein he was willed to kill, and eate thoſe vncleane beaſts and foules repreſented vnto him, and by a ſecond voyce taught not to tearme that cōmon or vncleane which God had cleanſed. Which purification of vncleane beaſts and foules, as I deny not but that myſtically and

chiefly it imported the cleanſing of the Gentills hartes by faith in Chriſt and ſupernall graces conferred equally on then and the Iewes (as is plainly teſtified ibid. verſ. 18. act. 15. v. 7. &amp; 14.) So likewiſe I affirme, that as S. Peters horrour and deniall of hauing euer eaten any vncleane thing, was litterally meant by him; ſo was Gods commaund likewiſe that he ſhould kill and eate them, and his diuine warrant of their being cleanſed, litterally to be vnderſtood, and made a chiefe ground of that Apostolicall decree Act. 51. wherein all ſortes of meates, not ſtrangled, ſacrificed to Idolls, and bloud, were freely licenſed to the conuerted Gentils. For as by this viſion S. Peter was inſtructed firſt concerning the generall and actuall vocation of the Gentills: ſo in like manner was he taught not to impoſe on them the cerimonious, and burdenſome law of meates, further then a neceſſary abſtinence from theſe three for a time already mentioned.
                  My ſecond argument ſhalbe collected out of the Apoſtles decree Act. 15. wherein againſt ſuch as taught to introduce Circumciſion, and the obſeruance of Moyſes law verſ. 5. it was after a diligent conquiſition made of this queſtion, ioyntly by all the Apoſtles determined, that the heauy and inſupportable burden of the old law ſhould be no further impoſed vpon the conuerted Gentills, then that they ſhould abſtaine from meates ſtrangled, ſacrificed to Idolls, bloud, and fornication; and in ſo

doing they ſhould do well. Whence I argue thus.
                  The Apoſtles determined in their decree all neceſſary abſtinence from meates to be obſerued by the Gentils: But the Apoſtles in their decree licenſed vnto them all ſortes of meates except ſtrangled &amp;c. Therfore only thoſe meats were neceſſary to be abſtained from by the Gentills. The maior of my argument is certainly proued by the mayne drift and intention of the Apoſtles, expreſſed in the text it ſelfe, which was to determine how far Moyſes law did oblige the conuerted Gentills particulerly about meates, and vſing many women, as they had beene accuſtomed to do before their conuerſion: ſo that as the Apoſtles in their decree did tye them to the matrimoniall knowledge of one lawfull wife; ſo did they alſo fully inſtruct them in ſuch an obſeruance of meates, as they ſaw needfull to be impoſed for a time, to make faithfull Iewes and Gentills to liue peacefully togeather in the vnity of one Church. The minor of my argument is euident by the decree it ſelfe, wherin it ſeemed good to the holy Ghoſt, and the Apoſtles, to impoſe no other burden on them then that they ſhould aſtaine from thoſe 3. ſortes of meates, and fornication: which decree had beene an inſufficient rule to direct them concerning meates lawfull or not to be eaten, if other meats prohibited in Moyſes law had ſtill remayned ſo.
                  
                     Secondly out of that Apoſtolicall decree, I frame this argument. If the legall difference of meats had continued after Chriſt as before, and equally obliged faythfull Iewes &amp; conuerted Gentills to the wonted obſeruance thereof, then was the Apoſtles particuler and expreſſe prohibition of bloud, meats ſtrangled, and offered to Idols, needles and ridiculouſly impoſed to the conuerted Gentils, &amp; they were falſely tould, that in abſtaining from thoſe meats they ſhould do well: becauſe according to Iohn Traske, they were by God equally commanded to abſtayne from other meats alſo. But it were blaſphemy to affirme this Apoſtolicall decree, to containe any falſe, abſurd, or ſuperfluous doctrine: Therefore thoſe meats mentioned in the decree, were only and determinatly prohibited to the conuerted Gentills. Thirdly neuer any ancient Father, or Chriſtian Deuine did before Traske vnderſtand other, then that the Apoſtles intended in their decree to eaſe the Gentills from ſome burdenſome obſeruances of the law beſides Circumciſion, which the Iewes had beene before Chriſts comming tyed vnto, as may be playnly gathered from the whole ſcope of S. Peters and S. Iames ſpeaches aſſented vnto by the other Apoſtles. But if the Moyſaicall Law of meats did generally oblige al Chriſtians after this decree as before, then were the Gentils nothing at all eaſed thereby from the burdenſome obſeruances

of Moyſes Law &amp;c. Therefore the Apoſtles certainely meant in that decree to repeale the Moſaicall Law of meats, and prohibite to the Gentills only ſuch as that decree particulerly mentioned.
                  My third argument ſhallbe the words of S. Paul. ad Galat. 2. whereas S. Peter is ſayd to haue eaten at Antioch with the Gentills verſ. 12. but afterwards being fearefull to offend certaine Iews ſent by S. Iames from Hieruſalem▪
                      he withdrew himſelfe, for which ſimulation S. Paul publiquely tould him verſ. 14. If thou being a Iew didſt liue Gentillike &amp; not Iewiſhlike, how doſt thou inforce the Gentills to Iudaize? which could not be vnderſtood of the Iewes in reſpect of Circumciſion, whereof no mention is made in that place, nor in reſpect of conuerſation wherin it cannot be conceaped how the Gentils could Iudaize or imitate the Iews: therfore it muſt neoeſſarily be vnderſtood of the Iudaicall obſeruance of meats wherein they imitated S. Peters example. Likewiſe when S. Peter eating with the Gentils is ſayd to haue liued Gentillike and not Iewiſhlike, it cannot wel be vnderſtood, but in regard of eating ſuch meats as the Gentills did, and his not obſeruing that difference of meats which the Iewes obſerued.
                  My fourth argument to conuince Iohn Traske in his Iudaicall obſeruance of meats, may be taken out of S. Paul ad Hebr. 9. verſ. 10. numbring the obſeruance of meates amongſt other

cerimonious rites, and carnall inſtifications of Moyſes Law impoſed only vntill the tyme of correction or reformation, which Chriſt was ordayned to make: Wherefore ſuch wonted obſeruances of meats are abrogated now by Chriſt and no longer to continue.
                  My fifth argument may be collected out of the ſame Apoſtle, who hauing in his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians cap. S. giuen them a liberty to eate or abſtaine from meats offered to Idols, as their owne conſciences ſerued them, obſeruing mutuall charity therein, cap. 10. verſ. 25. he willeth them to eate without exception, all meats ſould in the ſhambles of the Gentill Citty, asking no queſtion for conſcience ſake, that is to ſay, not regarding whether ſuch meats had beene offered to Idolls or not: For the earth (ſayth he) is our Lords and the plenitude therof, and if any Gentill inuite you to a feast, and you will go, eate all things ſet before you &amp;c. In which place albeit S. Paul treateth only of meats offered to Idols, yet his licence is generally vnderſtood of all meats and a fortiori proueth all other things not offered to Idolls lawfully eaten, which I proue by theſe vnanſwerable arguments. Meats offered to Idols were not only prohibited to the Iewes as were other vncleane meats but alſo by the former decree of the Apoſtles Act. 
                     
                        ••
                     . forbidden to all Chriſtians: But S. Paul licenſed the Corinthians to eate ſuch ſacrificed meats without ſcruple or queſtion▪ Therfore

other meates legally only prohibited may be eaten alſo.
                  Secondly S. Paul willeth the Chriſtians of Corinth to eate all thinges ſould in the ſhambles; or ſet at Infidells tables: But it cannot be reaſonably doubted that in the ſhambles, and at Infidells tables many meates forbidden in Moyſes Law were vſually ſould, and eaten: Therfore S. Paul licenſed the Chriſtians at Corinth to eate thoſe meates alſo. Io. Traske and his diſciples wil not ſticke ridiculouſly to retort the Maior of my argument, and to tell me, that if the Chriſtians at Corinth might eate all thinges ſould in the Gentills ſhambles, they might eate hornes and skinnes alſo. They will alſo foolishly deny that meates prohibited to the Iewes were eyther ſould in the Gentills ſhambles or ſet at their tables making ſo the differentiall law of meats particulerly giuen to the Iewes, to haue byn naturally obſerued by all other nations alſo. And for a ſhift they wil flatly deny meats prohibited to the Iewes, to be food at all for men, more then toades, or ſerpentes. Which fooleries againſt common experience, learning and iudgment are to be derided, and charitably compaſſioned in them, rather then anſwered.
                  Thirdly the reaſons why Chriſtians were licenſed by S. Paul to eate Idoll offeringes, are two expreſſed in the text it ſelfe; the firſt is becauſe an Idoll to him that hath iudgement to diſtern it is nothing in the world able to pollute

the creatures therunto offered; the ſecond is becauſe the earth is our Lords, and the plenitude thereof; that is to ſay, all creatures therein contained are good and created by him. Which later reaſon is effectuall alſo to proue other meates prohibited to the Iews to be good in themſelues and lawfully eaten by Chriſtians. Laſtly S. Paul ad Rom. 14. like a moderator, or peace-maker betweene the firme Chriſtians, who were the Gentills, and the infirme who were the Iewes weakely &amp; ſcrupulouſly ſtil inclined to obſerue the differentiall law of meats, &amp; feſtiuall dayes cōmanded by Moyſes, be exorteth the Iew not to condemne the Gentill, vſing his liberty in eating al ſorts of meats; &amp; the Gentil in like mā
                     ner not to condemne the ſcrupulous Iew, but rather to abſtaine from vſing his liberty, then offending the Iew, to be an occaſion to him of ſcandall and falling from his faith▪ 
                     Him that it weake (ſaith the Apoſtle v. 1) take vnto you, not in diſputation of cogitations: for one beleeueth that he may eate all thinges: But he that is weake, to wit the ſcrupulous Iew that will neither eate meates prohibited in Moyſes Law, nor ſacrificed by the Gentils, let him eate hearbes. Let not him that eateth diſpiſe him that eateth not, &amp; he that eateth not, let him not iudge him that eateth, to wit, all ſortes of meates, for God hath aſſumed him to himſelf &amp;c. and he eateth to our Lord (verſ. 6.) for he giueth thinkes to God. &amp;c. Why iudgeſt thou thy brother (ſpeaking to the Iew verſ. 10.) for his liberty of
                     
                     eating all thinges? And (ſpeaking to the Gentills) why deſpiſeſt thou thy brother for his weakneſſe in putting a differnce betwene meates? I know (ſaith he verſ. 14.) and am perſuaded in our Lord Chriſt that nothing is common or vncleane of it ſelfe. But to him that ſuppoſeth any thing to be como or vncleane, to him it is common (to wit; for the errour of his conſcience, making it-ſeeme ſo.) All things indeed are cleane (verſ. 20) but it is ill for the man that eateth with offence &amp;c. (to wit of his weake brother:) concluding thus his advice to Iew and Gentill▪ 
                     Haſt thou faith (that is to ſay, ar
                        •…
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      firmely perſuaded of the lawfulnes of al meates) haue it with thy ſelfe befor God &amp;c. But he that diſcerneth, or maketh a difference of meates, is damned or cōmitteth a damnable ſinne if hee 
                           •
                        ie, becauſe 
                           〈◊〉
                         of faith, or becauſe he is not fully perſuaded of the lawfulnes of that meate which he 
                           〈◊…〉
                        ; for all that is not of faith, is ſinne, to wit, euery thing that a man doth againſt his owne knowledg and conſcience is ſinne.
                  Which diſcourſe of S. Paul is ſo cleare in ſelfe for refutation of Traskes doctrine, and ſo vn
                        •••••…
                     lly vnderſtood by ancient Fathers and m
                        •
                     de 
                        ••
                     e Expoſitours, aſwell Proteſtantes as Catholikes, that the 
                        〈◊…〉
                      and 
                        〈◊〉
                      deuiſes wherby ſome of Traskes difciples haue ſought to delude ſo many playne paſſages of this Chapter, may well ſeeme to learned men, not iudiciouſly, imbraced, but in an hereticall pride, and a deſire of nouelty and ſingularity

purpoſely affected by them▪ In ſo much as one of them being preſſed with the litterall plaines of ſo many texts, concluding in expreſſe termes &amp; directly againſt his contrary doctrine; firſt he ridiculouſly deuiſed a new argument of this Chāpter, and pretended that S. Paul endeauoured therein to inſtruct ſuch Chriſtians, as being inuited to mourning and lamentation, might thinke it vnlawfull to eate any meates at all; idly citing many Propheticall textes, commending
                        •…
                      ſuch ti
                        ••
                     
                     ▪ abſtinence from nouriſhing and delightful meates▪ Whereas S. Paul ſpeaketh no one word in that Chapter of inuiting Chriſtians to mourning and lamentation, but only endeauoureth to compoſe controuerſies and occaſions of offence betweene Iewes and Gentills, and to make their ordinary conuerſation particulerly about meates and feſtiuall dayes peacefully and charitably togeather. They ſeeme alſo to haue ſundry other fancies to auoyd the preſſing authority of theſe textes, but ſo grosſly as I hold them▪ not w
                        ••••…
                      to be heere recited, much leſſe particulerly refuted: whippes being the beſt anſwere to ſuch arguments, &amp; Bedlam
                        •
                      or Bridewell the fitteſt ſchoole for ſuch a Sectmaiſter, and diſciples to diſpute in.
               
               
                  
                  
                     QVESTION V. VVherein is proued, that Bloud and ſtrangled meates may be lawfully now eaten by Chriſtians.
                  MY purpoſe in this Queſtion is not ſo much to refute Iohn Traske in his Iewiſh and abſurd doctrine of meates, ſufficiently already in my former Queſtions diſcuſſed, as particulerly to ouerthrow the Puritanicall abſtinence of ſome perciſe people, who wholy grounding their faith vpon he authority of Scripturs, &amp; litle crediting any Chriſtian practiſe or doctrine not expreſſed in them, are in many places knowne ſtrictly to obſerue the Apoſtolicall decree Act. 15. commaunding Chriſtians to abſtaine from ſtrangled meates bloud &amp;c. Which (ſay they) was a precept expreſly giuen by God in the law of nature Geneſ. 9. and renewed by the Apoſtles, a a law neceſſary to be obſerued by the Gentills conuerted, and is not found to haue beene repealed, as was the like prohibition of meates offered to Idolls (1. ad Corin. cap. 8 &amp; 10.) by any latter doctrine or practiſe of the Apoſtles. But contrarily it may be by many ancient and authenticall teſtimonies of antiquity certainely proued, that many hundred yeares togeather after Chriſt, holy people obſerued this abſtinence from ſtragled

meats and bloud, as a doctrine taught them by the Apoſtles. Tertullian for example in Apologia cap. 9. expreſly affirmeth Chriſtians not to 
                        〈◊〉
                      bloud at all but to abſtaine for that cauſe from beaſts dying of themſelues or ſtrangled, leaſt they ſhould be defiled with bloud &amp;c.
                  
                     Blandina alſo in her Martyrdome mentioned by Euſebius lib. 5. hiſt. cap. 1. telleth the Gentils that they did much erre in thinking Chriſtians to eate the bloud of infants, who (ſayd ſhe) vſe not the bloud of beaſts, which is teſtifyed alſo of Chriſtians by Minutius Felix in Octauio, by Origen contra Celſum lib. 8. &amp; ſundry later Councells haue vnder great penalties forbidden the eating of ſuch meates, Apoſtolically prohibited to all Chriſtians. So that their doctrine and practiſe is not Iewiſhly grounded, as Iohn Traskes opinions are, on a cerimonious precept of the old law, certainly abrogated, as is already proued: but they obſerue it as a precept giuen to Noah by God himſelfe in the law of nature, repeated in Moyſes law, and renewed by the Apoſtles.
                  The difficulty alſo of this queſtion is increaſed and made more hard, and vneaſy to be ſolued, by reaſon, that the Aduerſaries againſt whome I am to diſpute, admit no infallible authority of any ancient or moderne Church, guided by Chriſts holy Spirit, and lead into all truth, ſo that faithfull people may ſecurely and without danger of erring imbrace her communion,

follow her directions, &amp; reſt in her iudgment, as the ſupporting pillar &amp; foundation of Truth, according to the Apoſtle 1. Tim. 3. They admit no Apoſtolicall Tradition or certayne rule to know any vnwritten doctrin to haue byn held and practiſed ſince Chriſt ſucceſſiuely and vniuerſally by Chriſtians. Finally they little regard any reaſonable diſcourſe or Theologicall deduction, not litterally and playnely expreſſed in Scripture, the only Rule of their faith and Iudge of controuerſies betweene vs. According to which their vſuall and vnreaſonable manner I cannot more forcibly endeauour to diſproue this their Puritanicall abſtinence from bloud and ſtrangled meates, then by orderly prouing three thinges. 1. That this precept giuē to Noah (Gen. 9. verſ. 4.) was myſterious and not morall in it ſelfe. 2. That it was not but for a time only, and for ends now wholy ceaſed, decreed by the Apoſtles (Act. 15. verſ. 20. 28.) 3. That it hath beene ſince by a holy and lawfull practiſe of Chriſts Church generally repealed, ſo as it is a ſingular fancy for Chriſtians now againe to renew the obſeruance thereof.
                  And that this abſtinence from bloud and ſtrangled meates was not a morall precept, I proue firſt by the reaſon for which God prohibited thoſe meates to Noah and his Poſterity, which was chiefly by this horrour of bloud to make them deteſt man-ſlaughter, and bloudy cruelty, as appeareth by Gods wordes immediatly

annexed to that precept, Geneſ. 9 verſ. 5. 6. 7 that ſinne of murder hauing beene firſt committed by Cain (Geneſ. cap. 4. verſ. 8.) afterwards by Lamech (ibidem v. 23.) Nomrod alſo and other mighty men in thoſe firſt ages of the world, ouer eaſily multiplyed that horrible offence againſt Gods intended propagation of mankind: whereas now to vs Chriſtians the example of our Sauiours meekenes, his expreſſe prohibition of killing, ſtriking, or miſcalling our Neighbours, his doctrine of pardoning ſeauenty times ſeauen our enemyes, of being quickly reconciled vnto them, of doing good for euill, and praying for ſuch as perſecute vs &amp;c. do ſufficiently inſtruct vs to abſtaine from effuſion of bloud and cruelty: ſo that ſuch a horrour of bloud in meates cannot for that end be longer neceſſary to be continued by Chriſtians. Secondly, if this precept had byn a morall law, neceſſary to direct vs in humane conuerſation and manners towards God, or between our ſelues, it had no doubt byn included in that natural law, by which Noah and his faithfull poſterity were ſufficiently inſtructed, and taught to know the morall good and euill of their actions, &amp; to refraine from ſinne in them: So as this precept had byn vnneceſſarily impoſed if perfect reaſon and naturall iudgment had otherwiſe taught it vnto them, as it did other morall precepts. Thirdly, neuer any Philoſopher or wiſe Gentill, ignorant of that poſitiue precept

giuen to Noah, either taught or practiſed after Chriſts dayes or before, abſtinence from bloud &amp; ſtrangled meats, as a morall &amp; natural precept; neither can it be, as I haue els where declared out of naturall reaſon, the rule of naturall lawes, iudiciouſly conceaued, that bloud or ſtrangled meates entring the body, can defile the ſoule &amp;c. Neither was the Apoſtles Decree (Act. 15.) concerning abſtinence from ſuch meates, impoſed on the Gentills as a morall law perpetually to continue, but only as an eaſy obſeruance neceſſary for a time, the better to vnite Iewes and Gentills, in the vnity of one Church. For the Iewes hauing an eſpeciall horrour of Idoll-offerings, ſtrāgled meats, &amp; bloud, would haue abhorred al manner of ſociety with Gentils, if they had not obſerued ſome kind of order and conformity in meates with them.
                  And this is to be proued firſt out of the decree it ſelfe Act. 15. verſ. 28. wherin it ſeemed good to the holy Ghoſt and the Apoſtles, to lay no further burden vpon the Gentills then that they ſhould abſtaine &amp;c. By which wordes (no further burden) is plainely inſinuated vnto vs, that the prohibitiō of ſuch meats was a part of that burden which the Apoſtles would not haue wholy laid on the Gentills neckes, to wit the cerimonious obſeruances of Moyſes Law, ſo many in number and ſo hard in practiſe, as few amongſt the Iewes obſerued them, ibid. v. 10. and ſo conſequently it was no morall precept

included in Chriſts law formerly imbraced and profeſſed by the faithfull Gentills. Secondly, the Gentills were by the ſame Apoſtolicall authority, and for the like reſpects commaunded to abſtaine from Idoll-offeringes, as they were taught to refraine from meates ſtrangled and bloud. But the ſame Gentills were authorized afterwards by S. Paul ad Rom. 14. 1. ad Corin. cap. 8. &amp; 10. to eate Idoll-offeringes without ſcruple or queſtion, as hath byn in my former Queſtion already declared: wherefore then might they not afterwards in like manner be licenſed to eat indifferently meates ſtrangled and bloud? For (ſaith S. Auguſtin cont. Fauſtum lib. 32. cap. 13.) albeit the Apoſtles then cōmaunded Chriſtians to abſtaine from bloud and ſtrangled meates, chooſing for a time an eaſy obſeruance, and not burden ſome to the Gentils, that the Iewes and they might be built on the ſame corner ſtone &amp;c. yet after the Church of the Gentills became ſuch, as no natural Iſraelite appeared therein, what Chriſtian now obſerueth it ſo as not to touch black birdes, and other leſſer birdes, vnleſſe their bloud be effuſed, or not to eate a Hare or Conny killed only with a blow giuen in the necke, without any other bloudy wound? and if perchance ſome feare to touch thoſe meates, they are derided by other Chriſtians: ſo that in S. Auſtines dayes, eſpecially in thoſe Weſtern Churches, as Iews (for whoſe ſatisfaction and better gayning to Chriſt that

cerimoniall Abſtinence was conditionally and for a time only impoſed) ceaſed to imbrace the Chriſtian faith, ſo the obligation of that precept ceaſed alſo, &amp; began to be no longer obſerued by Chriſtians. And as the Eaſtern Churches were neereſt to Hieruſalem, &amp; moſt ſtored with Iewiſh Conuertites; ſo the Apoſtolicall precept of abſtayning from ſtrangled meats and bloud was in thoſe Churches longeſt obſerued.
                  And in thoſe firſt ages after Chriſt, becauſe Chriſtians were by occaſion of the Carpocratians and other wicked heretikes, eating children ſacrificed, with abhominable rites, for their Euchariſt, exceedingly traduced and infamed to the Gentill magiſtrates; therefore to ſhew thē
                     ſelues innocent and fre from ſuch horible ſlaunders, they holily, whilſt thoſe monſtruous Sects continued, tyed themſelues to a Chriſtian obſeruance of that Apoſtolicall decree, as the aboue mentioned authorityes of Tertullian, Euſebius, and other producible teſtimonyes of antiquity do certainely teſtify; which maketh nothing at all to proue the ſtill continuing obligation of the precept generally anulled by the contrary practice of Chriſtiās in after ages.
                  If my aduerſaryes obiect, that as the decree of the Apoſtles was according to the prohibition of Fornication therein contayned, a moral Law ſtill continuing: ſo was the ſame decree morall alſo according to thoſe inioyned abſtinencyes from meates &amp;c. I anſwere, that

the prohibition of Fornication was a morall precept; reducible to the Commandment of not committing Adultery, contayned in the Decalogue, neceſſarily impoſed at that tyme to inſtruct the Gentils newly conuerted in the Chriſtian law of Matrimony, and to deterre them from Concubiniſme, and vſing any more then one of thoſe many women whome peraduenture they had ben accuſtomed carnally to haue known before their conuerſions: wheras their inioyned abſtinence from bloud and ſtangled meates, was no more decreed as a morall and euer continuing law, then was their like prohibition of meates ſacrificed to Idolls, plainely repealed in the Apoſtles time by a contrary and lawfull practiſe of Chriſtians. And whereas S. Paul ad Rom. 14. verſ. 1. &amp;c. accounted it only weaknes in the Chriſtian Iewes of thoſe times to tye themſelues to the legall obſeruance of meates, and to be ſcandalized at the liberty of the Gentills, eating indifferently all thinges, it is now to be worthily reputed an extrauagāt folly &amp; fancy for our pure Profeſſours of ſpiritual Sanctity and Euangelical Perfection to tye themſelues to ſuch a Cerimoniall, and burdenſome obſeruance of meats, neuer dreamed of in many ages paſt by their Chriſtian &amp; Catholike Predeceſſours, and nothing pertinent to their pretended adoration, and ſeruice of God in ſpirit and verity.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               THE CONTENTS.
               THE Preface, declaring the Authors ſcope and intention in this Refutation. pag. 3.
               
                  
                     I. CONTROVERSY.
                     
                        QVEST. I. Of the ſeauenth day before▪ Moyſes. pag. 21.
                     
                        Queſt. II. Whether the precept of the Sabaoth were Morall or Cerimoniall. pag. 26.
                     
                        Queſt. III. Concerning the abrogation of the Iewes Sabaoth. pag. 31.
                     
                        Queſt. IIII. Of the Sabaoth tranſlated into the weekly day of our Sauiours Reſurrection. pag. 42.
                     
                        Queſt. V. Wherein is proued, that Christians are to celebrate the yearly day of our Sauiours Reſurrection on Sunday, and not on the 14. day of March-Moone, as the Iewes celebrated their Paſchal. pag. 57.
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     II. CONTROVERSY.
                     
                        QVEST. I. Of the vncleaneſſe of meats before Moyſes Law. pag. 65.
                     
                        Queſt. II. Of the Moyſaicall Law of meates, and myſterious ends why God commaunded it. pag. 71.
                     
                        Queſt. III. Wherein the proper and perfect rule of morall Actions is briefly declared: and how according to the ſame no meates are now vncleane, and vnlawfull to Chriſtians. pag. 77.
                     
                        Queſt. IIII. Prouing by ſundry texts of the New Testament, the law of meats abrogated to Chriſtians. pag. 85.
                     
                        Queſt. V. Wherein is proued, that bloud and ſtrangled meates may be lawfully now eaten by Chriſtians. pag. 95.
                  
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

