
   
      
         
            Nicodemus for Christ, or The religious moote of an honest lawyer: deliuered in a sermon, preached at the assises at Okeham, in the county of Rutland, March. 10. 1627. By Antony Favvkner, Master of Arts, and late student in Iesus Colledge in Oxford
            Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.
         
         
            
               1630
            
         
         Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00584
            STC 10722
            ESTC S101884
            99837687
            99837687
            2025
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00584)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2025)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 791:07)
         
         
            
               
                  Nicodemus for Christ, or The religious moote of an honest lawyer: deliuered in a sermon, preached at the assises at Okeham, in the county of Rutland, March. 10. 1627. By Antony Favvkner, Master of Arts, and late student in Iesus Colledge in Oxford
                  Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.
               
               [6], 24, [2] p.   
               
                  Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for Robert Allott, and are to be sold at his shop in S. Pauls Churchyard at the signe of the Beare,
                  London :
                  1630.
               
               
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Identified as STC 10721 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-11
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2008-11
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            NICODEMVS FOR CHRIST, OR THE RELIGIOVS MOOTE OF AN HONEST LAWYER: DELIVERED JN A Sermon, preached at the Aſsiſes at Okeham, in the County of Rutland, March. 10. 1627.
            By ANTONY FAVVKNER, Maſter of Arts, and late Student in Ieſus Colledge in Oxford.
            
            
               IOB 29. 16.
               I was a father to the poore, and the cauſe which I knew not, I ſearched out.
            
            LONDON Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for Robert Allott, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S. Pauls Churchyard at the ſigne of the Beare. 1630.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE WORSHIPFVLL MY HONORED GOOD FRIEND MOSES TRYON ESQVIRE, Grace, Mercy and Peace.
            
               SIR,
            
            
               A Godly liberality is not much different from a frugall prouidence; 'tis but a letter of Returne, by which we ſhall receiue in heauen what we haue wiſely laid out on earth: for hee that hath pitie on the poore, lendeth vnto the Lord; and looke what hee layeth out, it ſhall be payed him againe, Prou. 19. 17. So that the practiſe of this piety, is the moſt aduantagious vſury: for we lend but temporals, but we ſhall receiue both the Principall and Intereſt in

Eternals. Happy might all Gods temporall Stewards be, if they would ſo imploy their golden Talent. Concerning your owne particular, I will onely thus much ſay, The prayers of the poore for you will ſooner preſent your charity to God, then the prayſes of my Pen can vnto the World. And as for the no meane apprehenſion of your fauour and good meaning towards my ſelfe, I can returne no other, ſaue the poore mans tribute, prayers and thankes: of which this ſlender Preſent, the thinne gleanings of a Country Labourer, is a faithfull, though vnproportioned teſtimony. Which if you but as kindly accept, as it is freely offered, you ſhall accipiendo dare, be bounteous in receiuing, and ſo deſerue new thankes abundantly gratifying him, who alwaies vnfainedly deſires
            
               By you and yours in all Chriſtian
ſeruice to be commanded,
Anthony Fawkner.
               
            
         
         
            
            EGREGIO VIRO PETRO TRYON, ORNATISSIMI VIRI MOSIS TRYON Armigeri filio natu maximo 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
            
               REi priuatae ſatago: Nec humili fortunae competit inuitâ quodammodo Lucinâ, faetum quem vix peperiſſe auſa eſt in apricum ſeueriori Criticorum fronti exponere. Satiùs familiari gratandum eſt lari, tutiuſque tyronibus domeſtic â declamare in porticu. Equidem lubentiùs labiorum vitulos feciſſem in ſalutem Maecenatis quàm literas haſce publicâſſem in ipſius gratiam; niſi quòd nobis, dignitatem tuam (Generoſe vir) 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                iſtius noſtrae vectigal iure proprio vendicâſſe, ſolutumque parumper in hoc Xeniolo cenſuque modico tributum aequi conſultum iri, meridianâ luce clariùs innotuiſſet. Ad teipſum quod attinet, ne quae è caſto &amp; ſyncero deprompta ſunt pectore, adulterina videantur &amp; fucata adulantis ingenij deliramenta, rem paucis expediam. Depoſitis collo Bullâ Laribuſque adhuc ſub vmbonis candidi priuilegio mediâ iuuentute egiſti virum, adeoque ſubitaneo virtutis incremento minutatim defluentes annorum &amp; aetatis fefelliſti moras,

vtpraecoce quâdam matureſcente indole gradatim quaſi &amp; pedetentim ſequaces Naturae greſſus praeueniſſe videaris. Mucos ergo emungant proprios rugoſae Hypercriticorum ſannae. Vacillans adhuc noſtrae Theologiae ſololes haec &amp; decidua, pene dixerim primis infantiae vagiens incunabulis, ſub tuis modò ſuccreuerit auſpicijs, abundè mihi videbitur conclamatum 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , fruarque votis vſque ad inuidiam foelicibus
            
               Sigillatim tuus,
                  Antonius Fawkner.
               
               Ex Muſaeo meo vndecimo Kalend. Septemb. 1629.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            NICODEMVS FOR CHRIST, &amp;c.
            
               
                  Ioh. 7. 51.
                  Doth our Law iudge a man before it heare him, and know what he hath done?
               
            
            
               MAieſty is an embleme of Diuinity, and Magiſtracy the viſible character of an inuiſible Deity. So that as men are the beſt of Mortals, Iudges alſo are the beſt of men, and are by ſo much liker their Creator, by how much his Warrant authorizeth them aboue his creatures. Men indeed are like God by a benefit in their creation: Iudges more like him by the addition to their creation of the preheminency of their function. Men are like him in the fabrick of their ſoules, they, more like him, becauſe both in that, and the excellency of their Office. If then Melancthon may tearme men Earthly gods, in reſpect of inferiour creatures, why may not Dauid ſtile Iudges tranſitory gods, in regard of inferiour

men? I 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſaid, you are gods, Pſal. 82. 6. The Lord indeed is God of gods, but he hath ſelected theſe to be gods to men. Yet though God permit them to partake of his Authority, tis with a condition, that they ſhall partake of his Iuſtice too. God workes all for his owne glory, and his infinite glory is his infinite Iuſtice. Now becauſe power is the ſupporter of Iuſtice, God makes thē great, not becauſe they ſhould be great, but becauſe by being great, they might dare to be iuſt. Thoſe then whom God makes great, wee deeme to be good, ſo that their place begets a reuerence; their reuerence, feare; and greatneſſe mixt with goodneſſe produceth imitation: inſomuch that Honour becomes Example, and Iudges liues, the peoples rules. So that they liue not their owne liues alone, but other mens; and the perill of their ſoules hazzards others. As then there is no deformity ſo vgly as corrupted beauty, ſo no Calling ſo wicked, as the beſt turned bad. Bad in it ſelfe, worſe by example; worſt, if at all bad, becauſe it ſhould be beſt; moſt dangerous, becauſe moſt eminent. Adam indeed ſinned, yet ſtill continued man; but if Angels tranſgreſſe, they can be no leſſe then Diuels. Peaſants may turne Pagans, and none take notice: but if Iulian become an Apoſtata, an Empire is in danger. Ieroboams tranſgreſſion made Iſrael to ſinne; and though the people compell Aaron to make an Idoll, yet if he doe it, being a Magiſtrate, he brings the ſin vpon them, Exod. 32. 21. He that beleeues in me, ſaith Chriſt, out of his belly ſhall flow riuers of waters of

life, Ioh. 7. 38. An ample reward of the Iewes beliefe, if they had belieued. And (poore ſoules!) many had belieued, had not the example of their Rulers hindred their beliefe. Many reſolued that he was the Prophet, Verſ. 40. Some confeſſed he was the Chriſt, Verſ. 41. Yea, and the frozen conſciences of the barbarous Officers, which went with a full reſolution to arreſt him, were ſo thawed, that, let the Magiſtrates thinke will or ill, they muſt needs confeſſe, that Neuer manſpake like this man, Verſ. 46. Their conſciences acknowledged him, their tonges confeſſed him: yet (for the force of example from Authority!) the wicked thinke to ſtop their mouthes with this owne queſtion, Doth any of the Rulers or Pharifes beleeue on him? Verſ. 48. Nay, immediately with open mouth, according to their old faſhion of balling Templum Domini, Templum Domini; The Temple 
                  Ier. 17. 4.of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord: or, Wee 
               
                  Iob. 19. 7.
               haue a Law, and by our Law hee ought to dye, they would condemne him vntried againſt the Law: and in the next verſe out-law him and his, with a dire Anathema, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               ▪ This rout, this Many which know not the Law is ourſed, Verſ. 49. So would they haue ſterned the Law by their owne paſſions, till Nicodemus returnes the curſe vnto the heads of the curſers, and mauger their bragging of their skill in the Law, conuicts them of iniuſtice by a queſtion from their owne Law; 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ; Doth our Law iudge a man before it heare him, and know what he hath done? Not to

               De ſimili quaeſtione vide Beza in S. Mat. 7. 22.
               be tediouſly curious vpon the words. The Verſe is ſuch a queſtion, as may be naturally reſolued by a Negatiue poſition; and that eaſily done by the Metatheſis of the particle interogatiue, transferred from the ſubiect to the implicite Copula▪
                ſo that 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , &amp;c. Doth our Law iudge a man before it heare him, and know what he hath done? is equiualent, and the ſame with 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , &amp;c. Our Law doth not iudge a man before it heare him, and know what he hath done. And my Text ſo vnderſtood, may ſeeme to be Solſtitium ſolis Iuſtitiae, The Solſtice of Iuſtice. It muſt not bee idle, but proceede thus farre: nor is it boundleſſe, it proceeds no further. It muſt iudge, elſe 'twould not be Iuſtice: it muſt iudge within the limits of theſe conditions, elſe 'twould be iniuſtice. The queſtion is already become a poſition; let vs once againe turne the Negatiue poſition to an affirmatiue propoſition; and that not by the diſlocation of one Negatiue particle, but the exemption of them all. If then our Law doth not iudge a man before it heare him, and know what hee hath done; it followes, à contrarijs, that our Law doth iudge a man, if it heare him firſt, and know what he hath done. And the Text thus taken, points at two things, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ; the Law in the firſt part; Our Law doth iudge a man; and the Iudge in the ſecond; If it heare him before, and know what hee hath done. The firſt part ſhewes vs 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the rule of Iuſtice, the Law dead without the Iudge. The ſecond points out 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the liuing Law, the Iudge, corrupt without the

Law. Againe, the firſt part containes two things. Firſt, the Rule of Iuſtice, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the Law; noted by her coate of difference, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , our Law, the Iewes Law, Gods Law. Secondly, the act of Iuſtice, Iudgement, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Our Law doth Iudge; and that againe attended with its obiect, circa quod, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , a man. In the ſecond part are euident two eſpeciall neceſſaries to a good Magiſtrate: The firſt is diligence, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , hee muſt heare; and that both 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , before hee proceede to ſentence; and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , of him that is accuſed. The ſecond is knowledge, and that both of the fact, and the manner of the fact, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : And know what he hath done. Of theſe (the God of Truth aſſiſting) and firſt of the firſt, the Rule of Iuſtice.
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , The Law.
               
                  Gilbertus in Cantica. Ier. 30.
                   
                  Sine lege ſunt quae ſine ordine ſunt, ſaith an Ancient; Order is one end of the Law, God the Author Philo Iudaeus de Fabric. Mundi.of all Order. Hee might haue created the World as well in one day, as ſixe; and all at once as eaſily, as Heauen firſt, and Man laſt: but by his wiſedome were all things made, and the God of Order would be the example of Order. Now as all is made, all muſt be ſuſtained, leſt Order ſhould againe be ſwallowed vp in confuſion. So that as all was created in order, all muſt bee ſo created, that it may remaine in order. Wherefore God will at once be 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   and 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , a Creator and a Lawgiuer; and with the ſame Fiat rouze from confuſion and command to obedience. Each creature is ſo made it ſelfe, that it cannot be ought

ſaue it ſelfe. The wiſedome of his bounty giues it a Beeing; the wiſedome of his order giues it but one Beeing. Nor is this order in eſſence only, but in the conſequents of it, its qualities. The nimble fire will be aboue, and not below; the ſullen earth onely below. The two great Lights haue their alternate courſes. The Sea may threaten, cannot Domincere; it muſt ouerflow ſo much earth, and but iuſt ſo much. Thus the Decree of God checkes all Natures: his Word created by a ſecret power; his Wiſedome gouernes by an eternall Law. By the Word of the Lord were the Heaven's made, Pſalm. 33. 6. and he made a Decree for the name, Iob 28. 26. Now though all things are, and are guided by this eternall Law, yet this Summa ratio, (ſo S. Auguſtine ſtiles it) this ſupreme directiue S. Auguſt. de lib. arb. c. 6.
                  rule, though it bee aliqualiter (as the Schooleman limits) in ſome ſort in all creatures Aquin. 12. q. 92. Art. 2.ſubiect to the Diuine prouidence; yet I ſay more eſpecially, more eminently it ſhines in man. So that by this more excellent impreſſion of the eternall Law, there followes a participation of that Rule in man; by which hee hath an inbred inclination to the accompliſhment of his proper acts and ends. Which participation of the eternall Law is defined to be the Law of Nature. By the light of which wee may eaſily view what ſhould be done, by our naturall inclination to what wee would doe. God hath made vs to be men, and the nature of men conſtraines vs to be ſociable. Yet is not Nature ſo blind a guide, nor ſo vniuſt a Miſtriſſe, as to command ſociety, and not to inſtruct

vs how to conſerue it. Wherefore ſhe hath written in our vnderſtandings one wiſe leſſon, from which our working intellectuals may deduce the reſt of all her precepts. And this generall Statute is Eligere bonum &amp; vitare malum; The common inſtruction of Nature is, that wee ſhould imbrace what is good, and ſhunne euill. Tis an euill againſt Nature to deſtroy the worke of Nature; from thence is concluded the Law, Thou ſhalt not kill. The conſeruation of humane ſociety commands, that euery man ſhould haue his owne; from thence is enacted the Law, Thou ſhalt not ſteale. So that that generall maxime is inuiolable. Dianyſius knew it, when he confeſſed, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plutarc. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . 
                        •
                     .The conſtitutions indeed of publike eſtates may be violated, the generall Law of Nature cannot. But from it, as from a common ſource, proceedes in ſome ſort the whole ſtreame of morall vertues, which, as the Law, are what they are, by the rule and ſquare Rectae nationis, of a directiue reaſon. So that Plato 
                  Plato de legibus lib. 12.
                  ſtept not much awry, when hee would haue 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   the Law receiue its Etymologie from 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , or 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , the mind, conſidering the Law is indeed dictarnon nactae rationis, the conſtitution of Reaſon, the proper faculty of the diſcourſing minde. This Law of Nature then is the image of the Eternall, and from it may ariſe the principles of morall vertues. S. Amb. in epiſt. ad Rom. c. 5.
                  Saint Ambroſe in other words ſaith as much, if not more, diuiding this Law of Nature into three parts. The firſt teacheth to giue, and ſo to giue honour to our Creator, as not to impart or

ſhare it to any of his creatures. The ſecond part is morall, inſtructing vs to liue by the rule of modeſty and vertue. The third, Preceptiue, commanding vs to furniſh others with the knowledge of our Creator, God, and ſeaſon them with the precepts of vertue and morality. And ſo the Gentiles which had not the Law, did by Nature the things contained in the Law, and hauing not the Law, were a Law vnto themſelues, Rom. 2. 14. Now becauſe, by reaſon of the imperfect eſtate of our depraued nature, our paſſions will ſwell to perturbations, and can receiue ſuch ſtrength from the Law of ſinne, that they are able impetuouſly to rebell againſt the Law of Nature, it is neceſſary that from the common precepts of Nature (as particular and vnknowne concluſions are drawne from common and apparent principles) mans vnderſtanding ſhould deduce and enact other ſeuerall Canons for the more particular diſpoſition of the community in order: which ſhould deterre thoſe from vice by feare of puniſhment, whom the inſtructions of Nature cannot perſwade to be good by loue to vertue. And ſuch like particular conſtitutions drawne from the Law of Nature, which is deriued from the Eternall, receiue a third denomination, diſtinct from both the former, and are intituled, Lex Humana, or Poſitiua, the Humane, or Poſitiue Law. Such as Rud. Com. Graec. fol. 1033.
                  were amongſt the Heathen, Draco's Decrees, which (as Budaeus notes) were more eſpecially termed 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Theſes, Poſitions, ſetled or determined ordinances: which though in regard of the

Law-giuers, and the acts of men, to which onely they are a rule, they may be termed Humane; yet after iuſt and due enacting by the authoritie of Poſtellus de Magiſtrat. Athen. cap. 5.
                  the publike aſſent, or publike perſon, and the open receipt of thē after promulgation in the time and place of concourſe, as amongſt the Athenians, and Die trinundino in Foro, in the open Market place amongſt the Romanes; then Religion tels vs, that Lex the Law takes its name from its owne Etymon à ligando from binding. So that whatſoeuer is ſubiect to the ſuperior power, is conſequently ſubiect to the Law of that power. Which inſomuch as it partakes (though but mediately and remotely) of the eternal Law, binds the inferior ſubiects to its obſeruance, yea, in foro conſcientiae, by the tye of Religion and Conſcience. There is no power but of God, Rom. 13. 1. Wherefore yee muſt bee ſubiect, not becauſe of wrath onely, but alſo for conſcience ſake, Verſ. 5. By me (faith the Lord) Kings reigne, and Princes decree iuſtice. By me Princes rule, and the Nobles, and all the Iudges of the earth, Prou. 8. 15, 16. Whoſoeuer then reſiſts the power, reſiſts the ordinance of God, Rom. 13. 2. It followes then, that none, no not the righteous are exempted from obedience to this Humane Law, as it is a directiue Rule, or guiding power; though in reſpect of its coactiue authoritie they are priuiledged, as preuenting compulſion by voluntary obedience. And in this ſenſe indeed the Law is not giuen to righteous men, but to vngodly, 1. Tim. 1. 9. And Saint Paul may bee an exegeticall Commentator on this place in another: For Princes are not to bee feared

for good workes, but for euill, Rom. 13. 3. Nor are we onely bound to ſubmit our ſelues to the iudgement of this Law, but Magiſtrates are as much required, to frame and proportion their determinations according to this Law. The Xenophon 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .ſquare then of our actions muſt bee the rule of their iudgements, and that 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   muſt be as definitiue of their cenſures as our deeds. Xenophon tels, that Cyrus learnt of his Tutor, that there was no difference betwixt 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   and 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , lawfull and iuſt, and as little betwixt 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   &amp; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , lawleſſe and violent; ſo that hee ſeemed to confine Iuſtice to Law, and would alwaies proceed according to Law, leſt at any time he ſhould ſeeme vniuſt. Such force then is in the Law, that it binds all proceſſe in Iuſtice to be according to the Law. So that he which in the adminiſtration of iuſtice ſtrayes Poſtellus de Mag. Athen. c. 6.
                  from the order of the Law is as much an offendour, as he whom he condemnes as a tranſgreſſor of the Law. And therfore the Athenians thought it a ſmall conuenience to their Commonwealth to prouide 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Law-giuers vnleſſe they had alſo appointed 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , a ſort of ſuperiour Gouernours to receiue an account from the Iudges Plato de leg-Dial 111.
                  of their common and ordinarie proceeding according to the Law. Plato would haue the Law as a picture, by whoſe proportion, as by Varro de ling. Latin. lib. 5.
                  a patterne and exemplar, Magiſtrates ſhould Chriſtoph interp. Philon. Iudaei. de offic. Iudicis.forme their cenſures. Iudex, the Iudge is but In
                        •
                      dicens, not the maker, but the ſpeaker of the Law; Adminiſtrator Iudicij (as an interpreter of Philo) The iudgement is Gods, hee is but the pronouncer;

and amongſt the Romanes, Suetonius ranking the moſt choiſe and honourable titles which the Emperour Auguſtus beſtowed vpon his beloued Tiberius, regiſters Ducem 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , That hee was a Gouernour preciſely obſeruing the preſcript of the Law. And no leſſe honour might Foelix ſeeme to haue deſerued, who would not for fauour deliuer Saint Paul to death againſt the cuſtome of the Romanes, Act. 25. 16. And Ahaſhueroſh might haue been an example to them both, not giuing ſentence according to his owne angry humour, but the Nations decrees; What ſhall wee doe with the Queene Vaſhti according to the Law? Eſter 1. 15. Sure I am that ſuch a one was Nicodemus, who askes not in my Text 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Doth the Iudge? but 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Doth our Law iudge? As if the Iudge could not decree, but the Law; or if the Iudge, yet as onely directed by the Law. Or if the Heatheniſh Romanes, vnder whoſe dominion they then were ſubiect, had had ſuch a barbarous Law, as to iudge a man before accuſed or heard: yet ſith the Iewes were vnder the Couenant, and immediately directed by the Law of God, hee inquires further, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Doth our Law ſo? which is the next conſiderable.
            
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Our,
               
                  The Law of the Lord is an vndefiled Law: Pſal. 19. 8. Moſes might heare it from God, as accepted for holy; Iſrael might heare it onely from Moſes, as but onely called to bee made holy. Iſrael muſt not touch Mount Sinay, no not touch it leſt

they die, though it bee to heare the Law, by the performance of which they ſhould liue. Gods Maieſty would promulge it in thunder and darkneſſe, that all might heare and tremble: his Mercy would ingraue it in Tables of ſtone, that all might ſee and reioyce. Here Ius Gentium becomes Ius Iudaicum, and the inuiolable decree of Nature made ſtronger by the promulgation of God. Falſe witneſſe is a fault againſt Nature, yea, and a ſinne againſt God. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe against thy neighbour: Exod. 20. 16. God is truth; falſehood is his enemie. God is Iudge: Pſal. 50. 6. And ſhall not the Iudge of all the World doe right? Gen. 18. 5. No man muſt be condemned by his Law indict â caus â, his offence not proued; but at the mouth of two or three witneſſes the matter muſt be eſtabliſhed: Deut. 19. 16. Moſes deliuered this Law to the Iewes when they dwelt in tabernacles, and Ioſep. de Antiq. Iud. lib. 4. c. 8.
                  it was yeerely repeated by the High Prieſt, faith Ioſephus, at their Feaſt of Tabernacles. Loe then how malice may peruert Iuſtice! This Law was deliuered by God to Moſes, by Moſes to their forefathers, by the High Prieſt yeerely with folemnity to themſelues, and by themſelues daily according to Gods precept to their children, Deut. 6. 7. and might not Nicodemus then iuſtly wonder, that being Maſters in Iſrael they knew not this? Let them then but checke their heady choller, or ſhake off their lingring malice, and they may through halfe-cloſed eies perceiue, that God forbids falſe-witneſſe, not witneſſe. Probabilities indeed may be the ground of a ſuſpicion, but they

muſt proue ere they can iudge; which is the next conſiderable, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Doth our Law Iudge, &amp;c.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Iudge.
               
                  
                     Ʋarr. de ling. Lat. lib. 4. &amp; Non. Marcel. de prop. Serm. 
                  Virtus à vi, ſay the Latine Critickes, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   from 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   as the Greekes. Both Rome and Sparta ſo honoured warlike proweſſe, that they eſteemed it as the Soueraigne of Vertues: yea, ſo much, as that they would haue the name of Vertue in generall to bee deduced from ſtrength and warre. Yet Ageſilaus, a Spartan Prince, no leſſe honourable for Proweſſe then Iuſtice, would notwithſtanding meaſure his greatneſſe by Iuſtice, not Proweſſe. For hearing ſome name the Perſian Monarch according to his affected title, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , the Great King, he taunts the ſwelling title by a queſtion of compariſon, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Plut. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
                  I pray you in what can he be greater then my ſelfe, if he appeare neither wiſer, nor iuſter. And although hee knew well enough which way the ſtreame would goe in the Lacedemonians iudgements, honouring valour aboue all vertues, yet being demanded which was the Nobler, Fortitude or Iuſtice, he gaue ſentence on Iuſtices ſide, and ſhewed his reaſon in his anſwer, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Fortitude is but the guard of Iuſtice; and were 
                  Plut. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
                  there no Traytors that would violate her, we needed no 
                  Ambr. de offic. lib. 1. cap. 28.
                  
                  valour to maintaine her. Saint Ambroſe makes good her excellency by comparing, if not preferring her to another vertue, of no leſſe eminencie in a Chriſtian, then valour in a Spartan▪ Beneficence.

Diuiding the whole frame of humane ſociety into two parts, Iuſtice and Beneficence, of the two (ſaith he) Iuſtitia mihi excelſior videtur, Liberalitas gratior: illa cenſuram tenct, illa bonitatem. They are not vnlike the two ſiſters, Leah and Rachel; Birth-right preferres the one, Nature the other: Iuſtice is royall, Liberality beautifull. A Scepter becomes the one, Mercy adornes the other: Authority is the Crowne of Iuſtice, Bounty, Bern. Serm. paru. Ser. 11.
                  of Liberality. S. Bernard anatomizeth Iuſtice ſome what more curiouſly; diuiding her, not as a ſiſter from Beneficence▪ but as the whole into her two parts, Beneficence and Innocency. Now, ſaith he, Innocentia Iuſtitiam inchoat; Beneficentia conſummat. To doe no wrong is the beginning of Iuſtice; to doe right the perfection. It begins in Innocency, it ends in Charity. So that Ageſilaus 
                  Xenophon. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .his 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , To abſtaine from oppreſſion, was but Iuſtice in its Innocency: it muſt be the Suum cuique tribuere, to giue each man his due: to helpe the oppreſſed that can crowne it with Beneficence. And indeed Iuſtice in this her perfection, is the Queene of Vertues, excelling all the reſt, by how much a common good which ſhe onely reſpects, exceeds a priuat, or perſonall, in which the acts of all, (at leaſt, the moſt of all) the reſt are terminated. But this Theame of Iuſtice is too large a field to runne ouer in the few remaining minutes of an houre: wherefore we will paſſe by it to view, and but view its act, Iudgement. Briefly 
                     Aquin. 22. q. 60. ar
                        •
                     . 2.then, the Learned haue as ſufficiently, as conciſely determined, and confined iuſt Iudgement vnto

three conditions; by the defect of any of which, the Iudgement becomes vnlawfull. Firſt, it muſt be according to the rule and ſquare of Iuſtice; otherwiſe it is peruerſe, and ſo vniuſt. Iudicium Iustum iudicate; Iudge righteous iudgement: Ioh. 7. 24. Secondly, it muſt proceed from iuſt authority; elſe it is vſurped, and then the party accuſed may iuſtly demand of ſuch a Iudge, as the Egiptian did vniuſtly of Moſes, Quis te conſtituit Iudicem, &amp;c. Who made you a Iudge ouer vs? Exod. 2. 14. For he can haue no power, except it be giuen him from aboue: Ioh. 19. 11. Thirdly, it muſt be ſecundum rectam rationem prudentiae, by the approbation of reaſon and prudence: elſe if it proceed from ſuſpicion or doubtfull, and not manifeſt proofes, it is vnlawfull, becauſe raſh. And in that ſenſe our Sauiour forbids vs at all to iudge: Matth. 7. 1. and the Law in my Text agrees with the Goſpell; Doth our Law iudge a man before it heare him, and know what he hath done. But becauſe this may ſeeme to conduce to the office of the Ivdge, it may leade vs to the ſecond part of my Text, the ſecond neceſſary requiſites to a good Magiſtrate. Which becauſe according to the Apoſtles grant, I may exhort an Elder as a Father, I will touch: 1. Tim. 5. 1.and againe, leſt by a rude petulancy, or indiſcreet preſumption, I might ſeeme, againſt the Apoſtles rule, to rebuke an Elder, I will but touch, and ſo draw to an end. Firſt then of the firſt; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , hee muſt heare; the Iudge muſt
            
            
               Heare.
               
                  Diligence. The order of Nature in the manner of our ſenſitiue

knowledge ſeemes to me to be a patterne of the order of Iuſtice in Iudgement. Let then common ſenſe be Queene in the part ſenſitiue, the vtmoſt confines of the world of man. The outward ſenſes are the witneſſes infallibly preſenting their obiects vnto her; of which after euidence preſented from them, and not before, ſhe can onely iudge. Tis eaſily applied by the termes in the ſimilitude. Tis the witneſſe that condemnes the man, the Magiſtrate can but iudge after witneſſe; yet muſt he make diligent ſearch: Deut. 19. 18. He muſt ſtop one eare with Alexander againſt the witnes, and reſerue it for him that is 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , and ſtands accuſed. Neither muſt he only heare, but heare 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , from him. His eares muſt not bee in his hands, that ſo by receiuing bribes, againſt the Ambr. de of fic. lib. 1. cap. 28.
                  rules of Nature and Iuſtice, he ſhould confound Hearing with Feeling. Quomodo poteſt eſſe iuſtus alteri, qui ſtudet eripere alteri quod ſibi quaerat? Saint Ambroſe would faine haue been reſolued how it could poſſibly be, that a couetous man ſhould bee iuſt, ſith his care is onely to inrich himſelfe, no matter by whoſe goods. Wherefore Gods command is, that they take no gifts, Exod. 23. 8. Again, neither muſt his eares bee in his eyes, when hee reades any of my great Lords letters, either to the fauour or preiudice of the priſoner. Cato was not more ſeuere then iuſt, when he would haue Iudicem nec pro Iuſtis orandum, nec pro iniaſtis exorandum: A good Magiſtrate neede not be intreated to fauour the guiltleſſe, and ſhould not be ouerintreated to ſuccour the guilty. Wherefore if for

feare of any great Ones the Magiſtrate peruert Iuſtice, hee is in Ioſephus opinion iniurious to the Almighty, and blaſphemous againſt God. Quaſi 
                  Ioſeph. Antiq. Iud. lib. 4. cap. 18
                  
                  verò (ſaith he) is infirmior ſit habendus quam illi, quorum potentiae metu, praeter ius fertur calculus. Nam Dei potentia eſt iuſtitia. Gods Iuſtice is his Power; they then which leſſe feare to oppoſe it, then diſpleaſe men, feare men more then God▪ and conſequently eſteeme them greater then God. Nor may the poore, if guilty, claime a pitty. It is due to his aduerſitie, not to his ſinne. Qui autem ſuâ 
                  Philo Iud. de offic. Iudicis.
                  ſponte ſe obſtringit ſceleribus, is non infoelix ſed iniuſtus cenſendus eſt: Hee which voluntarily mancipates himſelfe to iniquitie, muſt not be pittyed becauſe poore, but puniſhed becauſe wicked. So Philo Iudaus inſtructs and receiues his warrant from the Lawgiuer; Neither ſhalt thou countenance a poore man in his cauſe: Exod. 23. 3. Yee muſt therefore decree 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , according to Gods iudgement, 1. Pet. 1. 17. and according to his command; Reſpect not any perſon: Deut. 16. 19. Againe, hee muſt not onely heare 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , from him that is accuſed, but alſo 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   before hee proceed to ſentence. Set. Munſter. Coſmog. de Vngari
                        •
                     .Not according to that barbarous cuſtome reported of Clagen, a Towne in Carinthia, where vpon ſuſpicion they condemne the man, and after trie the carcaſe: but according to the laudable manner of the Romanes mentioned in holy Writ; It is not the manner of the Romanes for fauour to deliuer any man to death, before he that is accuſed, haue the accuſers brought before him, and haue place to defend himſelfe concerning the crime, Act. 25. 16. But of

                  Budaus com. Grac. fol. 1349.
                  this before. To returne then: Budaeus notes two other ſignifications of 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . The firſt is, Interpretari, to interpret. Notwithſtanding, indeed the Law written hath been heretofore ſaid to bee 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , for the moſt part the guide of Iudgement; yet becauſe mens actions by their ſeuerall multiplicity may ſeeme to bee infinite, and from thence may ariſe ſundry particular caſes, which the Law in its generall mandates ſeemes not directly to aime at, nor foreſee, by reaſon of diuers circumſtances, perchance extenuating the nature of the fact, it would ſeeme harſh, that theſe ſhould Ariſtot. Eth. 5. c. 15.
                  be cenſured by the rigour of the letter. Wherefore in the Iudges breaſt there may reſt an 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                  ▪ or middle equity, tempering Iuſtice by the milder interpretation of her Law, leſt ſhee ſhould ſeeme ſeuere, yea, euen to iniury: yet ſo proportioning the Law to the fact, that it may not ſeeme 
                     Eſth. 1. 19.violated, but mitigated; not neglected, but perfected. Artaxerxes could not recall his ſentence by the Perſian Law, but hee would oft-times aſſwage 
                     Eriſſonius de Regibus Perſ. lib. 1.
                     
                     Tertul. Apol. aduerſ. Gent. cap. 4.
                     
                   it, cutting off the head-tyre for the head. And no leſſe humanity was in the Emperour Seuerus, whom Tertullian teſtifies, Suffundere maluiſſe ſanguinem quam effundere; Hee had rather puniſh rubore, then morte, by ſhame then death; and it was eſteemed a better tempered iuſtice for a light offence, by a bluſh of ſhame to bring the Hugo Card. in Eccleſ. 7. 18.
                  blood into the offenders face, then by the axe of execution to ſpill it on the ground. And this equity the Preacher approoues, by diſallowing its contrary; Be thou not iuſt ouermuch: Eccleſ. 7. 18.

he ſhewed his reaſon in the precedent verſe; For there is a iuſt man that periſheth in his iuſtice: Verſ. 17.
               The other ſenſe of 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   is Intelligere to vnderſtand, or know which leades me to the next generall requiſite to a good Magiſtrate:
            
            
               Knowledge.
               
                  Knowledge. How neceſſary knowledge is to a Iudge, may bee ſomewhat euident by the meaning of the word 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   in my Text, which is to Iudge; but hath a neerer ſignification, ſecerno, to ſeperate, or diuide one thing from another by election or refuſall, which intimates a knowledge. After God had promiſed Salomon his requeſt, 1. King. 3. 5. he anſwers by asking in the ninth verſe, Giue vnto thy ſeruant an vnderſtanding heart, that I may diſcerne betweene good and euill. Wherefore becauſe experience is the mother of knowledge, and age moſt grounded in experience, the Iewes Gouernours were the Elders of their Cities. Not vnlike which Magiſtracie, was the Athenians 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , not to bee better expreſſed then by a third example, the Romans Senate. But, not to walke vpon this beaten tracke, my Text briefly appoints two things moſt eſpecially to be knowne. The firſt is 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , what it is that is done; whether an eaſie ſlippe, or a foule tranſgreſſion; and (as Hugo Cardinalis comments) Hugo Card. in. S. Job. c. 7. v. 51.
                  
                  ad quem finem, for what intention, for that meaſures the action. The ſecond, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , what is done, in act, not intention, for that makes the intention compleate. But the time checkes. A word of exhortation, and ſo an end.
               
                  To the Iudge Iuſtice Hutton
                   Though I doubt not (Right Honourable) that

your wiſedome may preuent my admonition, yet I know a vocall warning, eſpecially from a Pulpit, the Oratory of God, hath its ſpecial force and peculiar energy. Philip of Macedon knew well enough that he was a man, yet he would euery day be told ſo. Wherefore I beſeech you, and not onely you, but all the inferiour Iudges, euen to Iurours, and the like, to whom the whole ſcope of my Sermon is as applicable, as vnto your ſelfe, that you will beare a few words of exhortation. They are but a few. To day is Dies Criticus, a blacke and gloomy day of Iudgement: a little Doomeſday, a type of the great one. When yee therefore iudge, conſider with your ſelues ſeriouſly theſe few particulars. Firſt, what you are that iudge. Sure youle bluſh when you call to minde: Duſt of duſt, a clayie lumpe, a heape of 
                     Pſal. 82. 6, 7.aſhes. Terraterram iudicat, Earth iudgeth earth. Now yee are gods, but you ſhall die like men: to day you take away life, to morrow you may loſe your owne. Nor are you exempted from the common lot of humane miſery. Now is the priſoners courſe, very ſhortly may bee the beſt of ours. If then you peruert iuſtice while the ſtaffe is in your hand, expect a deſerued miſery; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , 
                     H
                           •
                        m. 
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .God will puniſh you, legetalionis, by a iuſt Law of paritie. Vae qui pradaris, &amp;c. Woe vnto thee that deſtroyeſt: When thou haſt made an ende of doing wickedly, they ſhall doe wickedly againſt thee: Eſay 33. 1.
               Goe too then, grind the face of the poore; accept perſons in iudgement, oppreſſe the widdows

and fatherleſſe crying for iuſtice; ſhed innocent blood. But ſtay, and heark, the Preachers trumpe ſummons thee before God by a fearefull Scito, Know that for all this thou ſhalt come to iudgement: Eccleſ. 11. 9. Thou mayeſt indeed kill the innocents body, but ex ore tuo condemnaberis, thy ſentence ſhall rebound, and by a mortall recoyle pierce thine owne ſoule. Secondly, conſider in whoſe place you ſit. In the ſeat of God, the iuſt God, and the mercifull God. Sing therefore with Dauid in your actions both mercy and iudgement vnto the Lord. Deſtroy betimes all the wicked out of the land: Pſalm. 101. 8. yet be mercifull alſo as your Father is mercifull: Luk. 6. 3. 6. Thirdly, remember in whoſe preſence you iudge: againe, in the ſight of God, a iuſt God, a iealous God, a terrible God, a God that will auenge vnto the third and fourth generation. Hearken then vnto the caueat of Malachies memento; Remember yee the Law which he commanded, with the Statutes and Iudgements: Malach. 4. 4. For it is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God: Heb. 10. 31. Neither deceiue your ſelues with a vaine ſecrecy, ſaying, The Lord ſhall not ſee, nor the God of Iacob regard. Shall not he which planted the eare heare? or he which formed the eye, ſhall not he ſee? His eyes are ten thouſand times brighter then the Sunne; darkeneſſe is to him as the noone day; yea, the righteous God ſearcheth the heart and reines: Pſal. 7. 9. Iuſtice is Gods honour, and the Lord is iealous of his glorie. If therefore you tranſgreſſe, hee will ſurely find it

out. The offendours indeed of mans Law may eſcape the puniſhment, ſaith the Heathen Xenophon) 
                  Xenop. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ſome by a priuiledged greatneſſe; ſome by a ſubtile priuacy: but they that tranſgreſſe againſt Gods Law, muſt needs vndergoe the cenſure, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , 
                     Wiſd. 16. 15.(as the ſame Author) which a man can by no meanes auoide: for it is impoſſible to eſcape Gods hand. Can any hide him in ſecret places, that I ſhall not ſee him, ſaith the Lord? Do not I fill Heauen and Earth, ſaith the Lord? Ier. 23. 24. If therefore yee are rebellious, and companions of theeues, euery one louing gifts, and following after rewards; if yee iudge not the fatherleſſe, neither ſuffer the widowes cauſe to come vnto you, Thus ſaith the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts, the mighty One of Iſrael; Ah, I will eaſe me of mine aduerſaries, and bee auenged on mine enemies: Iſai. 1. 23, 24. Fourthly and laſtly, thinke ſeriouſly whom you iudge: the anſwer to which brings me to a point in my Text, hitherto of purpoſe ouer-paſſed, that the Law and Iuſtice might bee handled together. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , A man. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c. Doth our Law iudge
               
            
            
               A man? &amp;c.
               
                  A man? Nec ampliùs dicam, nec opus eſt; I can ſay no more, nor neede l. A man; the Image of God; a walking world; the worke of a Trinity: Let vs make Man, Gen. 1. 26. A man: thy brother the begotten ſonne of thy naturall father Adam; thy brother, the politique ſonne of thy Ciuill Father,

the Prince; and againe, thy brother, the adopted ſon of thy heauenly Father, God. Veſpaſian had a combat betweene his Office and Nature: Iuſtis ſupplicijs illachrymauit &amp; ingemuit, as Suetonius; He was an Emperour, therefore muſt needs iudge and condemne; he was a man too, and therefore by as great a neceſſitie hee muſt ſigh and pitie. Learned Athens, was not void of a morall pietie, and euen that is alwaies attended with mercy. Suet. in Veſpaſ. Poſtellus de Mag. Athen. cap. 25.
                  Their chiefe ſeate in their 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , their iudgement-hall was 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Iouis liberatoris: Their chiefeſt God was their pardoning God; the crowne of ſoueraignty is mercy. Holy Scripture honours it as much, nay more, making it a title of the true God, yea, and that a great title, for, His mercies are aboue all his workes. Himſelfe will bee ſtiled, Pater miſericordiarum, the Father of mercies, 2. Cor. 1. 3. And to induce vs Patrizare, to bee like our Father in an eaſie clemency, he leaues vs mercy as an inheritance, and reward of our mercy: Bleſſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercy: Matth. 5. 7. Yet, as man indeed beares the Image of his Creator, and ought therefore to bee ſeriouſly tried before condemned; ſo alſo a notorious malefactor beares the marke of Satan: hee hath defaced the Image of God in himſelfe, and ought therefore to bee puniſhed. Vice corrupts his Nobilitie, ſinne depriues him of pitie; Thine eye ſhall not ſpare him. Deut. 19. 13. For he which iuſtifieth the wicked, and he which condemneth the iuſt, euen they both are an abomination to the Lord, Prou. 17. 15. To conclude. Bleſſed is that ſoule which

can be the ſeate of God. Which is that, ſaith Saint Bernard? Himſelfanſwers, The ſoule of the iuſt: for Iuſtice and Iudgement are the eſtabliſhment of his Throne: Pſalm. 89. 14. Doe iuſtice therefore in theſe three things; Redde ſuperiori, Redde inferiori, 
                  Bern. de Aduen. Dom. Serm. 3.
                  
                  Redde aequali, cuique quod debes &amp; dignè celebras aduentum Chriſti parans in Iuſtitiâ ſedem ſuam: Giue to thy ſuperiour, giue to thy inferiour, giue to thy equall; to euery of them what is their due: ſo ſhalt thou religiouſly welcome the graces of God into thy heart, and thy ſelfe in iuſtice bee eſtabliſhed the holy Temple of God. Where if thou prepare him a reſidence in this life, hee will prouide an eternall manſion for thee in his new Ieruſalem of the World to come, whither hee of his infinite mercy bring vs. Amen.
               Deo Trino Vni Gloria.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            Errata.
            In the Latine Epiſtle, the ſecond page, line 4. for ſololes, r. ſoboles. p. 3. l. 9. r. well. l. 12. r. lo
                     •
                  , p. 5. in the marg. r. Gillibertus in Cantic. Serm. 30. p. 10. l. 7. r. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
            
         
      
   

