
   
      
         
            The Fisher catched in his owne net
            Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645.
         
         
            
               1623
            
         
         Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00596
            STC 10732
            ESTC S120857
            99856050
            99856050
            21566
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00596)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21566)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 792:6)
         
         
            
               
                  The Fisher catched in his owne net
                  Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645.
               
               [2], 26 p.   
               
                  s.n.],
                  [London :
                  M.DC.XXIII. [1623]
               
               
                  By Daniel Featley.
                  Place of publication from STC.
                  A report of a conference that Featley and Francis White had with John Fisher and John Sweet.
                  In this edition A2r line 2 of text begins "yeares".
                  Reproductions of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sweet, John, 1570-1632 --  Early works to 1800.
               White, Francis, 1564?-1638 --  Early works to 1800.
               Fisher, John, 1569-1641 --  Early works to 1800.
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-01
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2004-01
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
FISHER
CATCHED
IN
HIS
OWNE
NET.
            M.DC.XXIII.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE OCCASION
AND ISSVE OF THE LATE
CONFERENCE HAD BETWEEN
Dr. White Deane of Carleil, and Dr. Featly,
with Mr. Fisher and Mr. Sweet, Iesuites,
was this as followeth.
            
               EDward Buggs Esquire, about the age of 70
yeares, being lately sick was solicited by some
Papists then about him to forsake the Protestant
faith, telling him there was no hope of saluation
without the Church, there was no Catholik
Church but theirs, and to beleeue the Catholike
Church was the Article of his Creed, and by it could
no other Church be meant but the Church of
Rome, because it could not be proued by all the
Protestants in the kingdome, that they had any
Church before Luther.
            
            This Gentleman being much troubled in his
mind with these and the like suggestions, who all
his life time had bin and professed himselfe a religious
Protestant, became now more sicke in minde
then body; and if by Gods mercifull goodnesse he
had not recouered of this sicknesse, it is to be feared
hee had falne both from his Mother Church
and his former faith, as some of the nearest of his
owne blood (to his great griefe) haue lately been seduced
by like inticements.
            After his recouery, being much troubled in mind

with these former suggestions of the popish Priests,
he repaired to Sir Humfrey Lynde Knight, who by
reason of his alliance and long acquaintance vvith
him, gaue the best satisfaction he could to his said
cousin Mr. Buggs, who seemed to take content in
such his conference, and to be well satisfied by him
in all points.
            But the Popish Priests and Iesuites not desisting
to creepe in further where they had once made a
breach, perseuering still in questioning him, where
his Church was before Luther. Whereupon he repaired
againe to Sir Humfrey Lynde, and required
some further satisfaction of him concerning that
demand. And thereupon Sir Humfrey Lynde tolde
him, it was first in Christ and the Apostles, consequently
also conspicuous in the primitiue Church
for 600 yeares after Christ, after which time some
errors crept into the Church, as diseases into a mans
body; so that the Church which Luther and we
acknowledge, was in generall the same Christian
Church, as his body was the same substantiall body,
being now well, and lately sicke, though different
in the qualities.
            And for the better strengthening of his mind, the
said Sir Humfrey Lynde inuited him to his house in
the countrey, thereby the better to preuent the daily
sollicitation of those dangerous seducers. And
after his returne to London, the said Sir Humfrey
Lynde going to Mr. Buggs his house in Drury lane
to visite him, found Mr. Fisher the Iesuite there,
where after some debates about Religion and the
visibilitie of the Church, Mr. Fisher called for pen

and inke, and set downe this question in terminis;
thereby adding vnder his hand, that he would answer
vpon it negatiuely, as chalenging and expecting
opposers, deliuering also the paper into the
hands of the said Sir Humfrey Lynde, who vpon view
of it, answered, that it was an historicall question,
and not so proper for disputation. But Mr. Fisher.
vrging it, Sir Humfrey told him, if he would go to
Dr. Whites, where formerly he had been, the said
Doctor would easily resolue those doubts. Which
being refused by the Iesuite, the said Sir Humfrey
did then returne him his paper againe, and so left
him.
            About two dayes after, Mr. Buggs repaired to Sir
Humfrey Lynd, and intreated him (for his satisfaction)
to giue Mr. Fisher a meeting, saying, that Mr. Fisher
had againe told him, that he would maintaine
what he had set downe, and that our Diuines
could not proue our Church visible before Luthers
time. Whereupon Sir Humfrey told him, that Dr.
White and Dr. Featly were to dine with him on Friday
following; and if after dinner Mr. Fisher would
come thither with foure or six at the most, they
should be admitted for his sake and his wifes, who
(by reason of such sollicitation) were troubled in
their minds, and satisfaction should be giuen as occasion
required. And these were the true causes of
the meeting, as is before declared. Vpon which
Friday, being the 27 of Iune 1623. Mr. Fisher, Mr.
Sweet, Iesuites, and some others with them, came to
Sir Humfrey Lynds house, into a little dining roome,
where they found the aforesaid Mr. Buggs, his wife

and children, and others of Sir Humfreys friends
that had then dined with him, together with some
others also; whose comming in, as the said Sir Humfrey
did not expect, so he could not with ciuilitie
put them forth his house, but did instantly cause
his doores to be locked vp, that no more might enter
in; notwithstanding which his command, some
others also came in scatteringly after the Conference
began.
         
         
            
            A RELATION
OF WHAT PASSED IN A
CONFERENCE TOVCHING
the visibilitie of the Church.
Iun. 27. 1623.
            DOctor White and Doctor Featly being inuited
to dinner by Sir Humfrey Lynde, and staying
a while after, had notice giuen them that Mr. Fisher
and Mr. Sweet, Iesuites, were in the next roome ready
to conferre with them touching a question set
downe by Mr. Fisher, vnder his owne hand, in these
words: viz.
            Whether the Protestant Church was in all ages visible,
and especially in the ages going before Luther:
2. And whether the names of such visible
Protestants in all ages can be shewed and proued
out of good Authors.
            This question being deliuered to the parties aboue
named, and it being notified vnto them that
there were certaine persons who had been solicited
(and remaining doubtfull in religion) desired satisfaction
especially in this point, they were perswaded
to haue some speech with the Iesuites touching
this point, the rather because the Priests and Iesuites
do daily cast out papers and disperse them

in secret, in which they vaunt, that no Protestant
Minister dare encounter them in this point.
            At the beginning of his meeting, when the disputants
were set, Dr. Featly drew out the paper, in
which the question aboue rehearsed was written,
with these words in the margent, viz. I will answer
that it was not; and demanded of Mr. Fisher whether
this were his owne hand; which after he had acknowledged,
Dr. Featly began as followeth.
            
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
                  D. Featly. To this vniuersall demand, requiring
rather an Historicall large volume, then a Syllogisticall
briefe dispute, we answer:
            1. That although diuine infallible faith is not
built vpon deduction out of humane history, but
diuine reuelation, as is confessed by your owne
Schoole-men, and expresly by Cardinall Bellarmine:
Historiae humanae faciunt tantum fidem humanam, cui
subesse potest falsum: Humane stories and records
beget onely an humane faith, or rather credulitie
subiect to error, not a diuine and infallible beliefe,
which must be built vpon surer ground.
            2. Although this question be grounded vpon
vncertaine and false supposals; for a Church may
haue been visible, yet not the names of all visible
professors thereof now to be shewed and proued
out of good Authors; there might be millions of
professors, yet no particular and authenticall record
of them by name. Records there might be many
in ancient time, yet not now extant, at least for vs
to come by; yet we will not refuse to deale with you
in your owne question, if you in like maner will vndertake
the like taske in your owne defence, and

maintaine the affirmatiue in the like question, which
we now propound vnto you here in writing:
            Whether the Romish Church (that is, a Church holding
the particular entire doctrine of the now
Romanists, as it is comprised in the Councell of
Trent) was in all ages visible, especially in the first
600 yeares: And whether the names of such visible
or legible Romanists in all ages can be shewed
and proued out of good Authors.
            
            Here Dr. Featly reading this question, through a
mistake, in stead of out of good Authors, read out of
Gods word. Whereunto Mr. Fisher replied, No, I will
proue it out of good Auhors.
            
            Then said one that sat at the table: By no means
can Mr. Fisher endure to demonstrate his Church
out of Gods word.
            
               
                  Dr. Featly.
               God is a good Author, Mr. Fisher,
but it is true I did mistake; what say you to the condition,
will you vndertake to name visible Papists
in all ages out of good Authors?
            
            
               
                  Mr. Fisher.
               I will so you proue the visibilitie of your
Church.
            
            Here an order was set downe, that Dr. Featly
should for an houre and a halfe oppose M. Fisher in
this question; and afterwards M. Fisher for the last
houre and halfe should oppose D White in the contrary
question for the visibilitie of the Romane
Church.
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               Before you proceed to dispute, I desire
these conditions may be assented vnto on both sides:
               1. That all bitter speeches be forborne.
               2. That none speake but disputants. Which conditions

were well approued of by the whole companie.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               I desire a third to be added thereunto:
viz. that both the Opponent and Respondent be
tied to Logicke forme.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I hold not that condition fit, because the
companie vnderstands not Logicke forme.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               There are of the companie that vnderstand
Logicke as well as you or I, and the rest are
men of vnderstanding and reason; therefore I am
resolued to keepe Logicke forme, and expect from
you direct answers.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               You your selfe confesse, that this question
is not to be handled Syllogistically.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               I said indeed, that it required rather
a large Historicall volume, then a briefe Syllogisticall
dispute; the more you too blame to propound
such a question, and my taske the harder; yet being
propounded as a question, I will keepe my selfe to
Logicke forme. But before I propound my argument,
I craue leaue in few words to lay open the vanitie
of the vsuall discourse, wherewith you draw
and delude many of the ignorant and vnlearned.
You beare them in hand, that there was no such
thing in the world as a Protestant before Luther;
and that all the world before his time beleeued as
you doe. That your Church hath not been only visible
in all ages and all times, but eminently conspicuous
and illustrious; which is such a notorious vntruth,
that I here offer before all this companie to
yeeld you the better, and acknowledge my selfe ouercome,
if you can produce out of good Authors,

I will not say any Empire or kingdome, but any Citie,
parish or hamlet, within fiue hundred yeares
next after Christ, in which there was any visible assembly
of Christians to be named, maintaining and
defending either your Trent Creed in generall, or
these points of Popery in speciall, to wit,
               1. That there is a Treasury of Saints merits, and
superabundant satisfactions at the Popes disposing.
               2. That the Laity are not commanded by Christs
institution to receiue the Sacrament of the Lords
Supper in both kinds.
               3. That the publicke Seruice of God in the
Church ought or may be celebrated in an vnknowne
tongue.
               4. That priuate Masses, wherein the Priest saith,
Edite &amp; bihite ex hoc omnes, and yet eateth and drinketh
himselfe onely, are according to Christs institution.
               5. That the Popes pardons are requisite or vseful
to release soules out of Purgatory.
               6. That the effect of the Sacrament dependeth
vpon the intention of the Minister.
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               These are Scholasticall points, not fundamentall.
            
            
               
                  D. White.
               Those things which are defined in
your Councell of Trent, are to you matters fundamentall.
               Whatsoeuer article denied makes a man in hereticke,
is fundamentall.
               But the deniall of any of these, makes a man an hereticke.
               Ergo, euery one of these articles is fundamentall.
            
            
               
To which argument nothing being answered, D.
Featly proceeded.
            
               7.
                     D. Featly. That Extreme Vnction is a Sacrament properly
so called.
               8. That we may worship God by an image.
               9. That the sacred Hoast ought to be eleuated,
or caried in solemne procession.
               10. That Infidels and impious persons, yea Rats
and mice may eate the body of Christ.
               11. That all Ecclesiasticall power dependeth of
the Pope.
               12. That he cannot erre in matter of faith.
               13. That he hath power to canonize Saints:
               14. To institute Religious Orders: 15. to depose
Kings, &amp;c. which latter points and the like, I leaue
to D. White to maintaine against you, when (according
to your promise) you doe vndertake to name
visible and legible Romanists in all ages.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               After you haue proued your Church visible
in all ages, and named the professors thereof, I will
satisfie you in your particulars.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               In the meane while name but one Father,
but one Writer of note, who held the particulars
aboue named, for 500 yeares after Christ. To
which instant demand of D. Featly, nothing was answered.
            
            
               Sir Humf. Lynd.
               M. Sweet, proue me but this one
point out of Saint Augustine, namely, Transubstantiation;
or satisfie such arguments as I shall bring
you out of Saint Augustine to the contrary, and I
will promise you to go to Masse.
               To which M. Sweet made no other then this answer,

                  That is not now to the question.
               
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I expect your argument D. Featly.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               There are two meanes onely to proue
any thing by necessary inference, to wit, a Syllogisme
and an Induction: other formes of argument haue
no force, but as they are reducible to these. I proue
the visibilitie of our Church by both; and first by a
Syllogisme:
               That Church whose faith is eternall and perpetuall,
was euer visible in the professors thereof.
               But the faith of the Protestant Church is eternall and
perpetuall.
               Ergo.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               You conclude not the question.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               There are two quaeres in your question;
first, whether the Protestant Church were in
all ages visible; and secondly, whether the names of
such visible Protestants in all ages can be shewed. I
haue concluded in my Syllogisme the first Quaere.
               
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               There are not two quaeres or parts in the
question; it is but one question.
            
            
               
                  D. White.
               Where there are two propositions
with two distinct vtrums, there are two questions:
But here are two propositions with two distinct vtrums,
to wit, Whether the Protestant Church, &amp;c. and
Whether the names, &amp;c.
               
               Ergo.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Conclude any thing syllogistically D. Featly.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               You your selfe make the first part a
question by it selfe: for at the margent ouer against
the first part, Whether the Protestant Church was euer
visible, you write, I will answer, it was not. Which

words can haue no Grammaticall construction, if
you refer them to both parts, or at all to the latter
part, to wit, Whether the names can be shewed.
               
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Let vs heare a Syllogisme.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               In this copulatiue proposition which
you offer for a question, and require me to proue; either
you denie both parts, or one onely: if both,
I am to proue both, one after the other; if one only,
then you grant the other. A copulatiue is not true
vnlesse both parts be true; doe you denie both, or
one onely?
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I say they are but one: for the latter part
is to expound the former: for I meane by visible, so visible,
that the names of such visible Protestants may be
shewed.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               This is to confound two distinct questions
in one. For a Church may haue been visible,
and yet the names of such visible professors not now
to be shewed.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               They are my words, and I am best able to
expound my owne meaning.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               An exposition which the construction
of the words will not beare, is not to be receiued.
But the construction of the words will not beare
this your exposition. Therefore it is not to be receiued.
And is a coniunction copulatiue, and must
adde somewhat to that which goes before. It is all
one, as if you should expound the words of the Apostle,
Prouide honest things before God and men, before
God, that is, before men.
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               What need you stand so much vpon this;
if there were visible men, certainly they may be named.

Name your visible Protestants,A Romanist standing by. and it sufficeth.
               Name visible Protestants in all ages.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               It seemes you are nominals rather then
reals; you stand so much vpon naming: will you vndertake
to name visible Papists in all ages?
               If neither you nor we can name visible professors
of our Religions in all ages,The same Romanist standing by. for ought I know, the
best way for vs is, to be all naturall men.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               This is the right reason of a naturall.
               
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               If there were visible Protestants in all ages,
certainly they may be named.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               That is a non sequitur, for the reasons
before named by me. What say you to a people of
Africa, who (if we may beleeue Plinie) haue no
names at all.
            
            
               
                  M. Boulton.
               Yet they haue descriptions, and may
be knowne by some periphrasis.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               What say you then to the heretickes
called Acephali, who are so called, because their head
and author cannot be named, nor particularly described,
yet the Author was a visible man. Are all
visible mens names vpon record? Are all the records
that were in former times, now to be produced?
            
            Here diuers of Mr. Fishers companie, called,
Names, names, names.
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               What, will nothing content you but a
Buttery booke? you shall haue a Buttery booke of
names, if you will stay a while.
            
            Here diuers of the auditors wished Dr. Featly not
to proceed any further in the disputation, vnlesse
Mr. Fisher would suffer him according to the lawes
of all disputation, first to conclude the first part of

his copulatiue question, and then the second: yet
D. Featly desirous to bring the disputation to some
better issue before he left it, was content to yeeld
to M. Fishers vnreasonable demand, and conclude
both parts of the copulatiue question in one Syllogisme.
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               That Church whose faith is eternall and
perpetuall, is so visible, that the names of some professors
thereof may be shewed in all ages.
               But the faith of the Protestant Church is eternall and
perpetuall.
               Ergo.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Faith eternall, who euer heard of faith eternall?
Saint Paul saith, that faith ceaseth.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               You haue a purpose, M. Fisher, to cauill;
you know my meaning well enough, by the
terme perpetuall, to wit, that Christian faith which
hath continued from Christs first publishing it till
this present, and shall continue vntill his second coming.
The Church which holdeth this faith, you
beleeue shall be so visible, that the names of the
professors thereof may be shewed in all ages.
               But the Protestant Church holdeth this perpetuall
faith.
               Ergo.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Your argument is a fallacie, called, petitio
principii.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               
                  A demonstration à causa, or à priori, is
not petitio principij.
               But such is my argument.
               Ergo.
               Is it not a sounder argument to proue the visibilitie

of the professors from the truth of their faith,
then as you do the truth of your faith from the visibilitie
of professors? Visible professors argue not
a right faith. Hereticks, Mahumetans and Gentiles
haue visible professors of their impieties; yet will
it not hence follow, that they haue a right beliefe.
On the contrary, we know by the promises of God
in the Scripture, that the Church which maintaineth
the true faith, shall haue alwayes professors
more or lesse visible.
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               You ought to proue the truth of your Church
à posteriori, for that is to the question, and not à priori.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               Shall you prescribe me my weapons?
Is not an argument à priori, better then an argument
à posteriori? This is, as if in battell you should enioyne
your enemie to stab you with a knife, and not
with a sword or dagger. I will vse what weapons
I list; take you what buckler you can.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               A proofe à posteriori is more demonstratiue
then à priori.
               
            
            Here Mr. Fisher sheweth his Academicall learning,A Protestant sitting by.
in preferring a demonstration à posteriori, before
that which proceedeth à priori. Is not a demonstration
of the effect from the cause, more excellent
then of the cause by the effect?
            From this place and so forward, it was agreed by the disputants, that the
Arguments and Answers should be taken by one common writer, and that
the Opponet D. Featly should set his hand to each seuerall Syllogisme; and
the Respondent M. Fisher to his seuerall Answers.
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               That Church which is so visible as the Catholicke
Church ought to be, and as the Popish Church is
pretended by M. Fisher to be, is so visible, that their

names may be produced and shewed.
               But the Protestant Church is so visible, as the Catholik
Church ought to be, and as the Popish Church is pretended
by M. Fisher to be.
               Ergo.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I denie the minor.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               That Church whose faith is eternall and
perpetuall and vnchanged,Minor probatur. is so visible as the Catholike
Church ought to be, and the Popish Church by M. Fisher
is pretended to be.
               But the faith of the Protestant Church is eternall, perpetuall
and vnchanged.
               Ergo the Protestant Church is so visible as the Catholicke
Church ought to be, and the Popish Church is pretended
by M. Fisher to be.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I distinguish the maior. That Church
whose faith is perpetuall and vnchanged so as the names
can be shewed, is so visible as the Catholik Church ought
to be, and as M. Fisher pretends the Romane Church to
be, I grant it.
               That Church whose faith is perpetual and vnchanged,
yet so as the names cannot be shewed in all ages, is so visible
as the Catholick Church ought to be, and as Mr. Fisher
pretends the Romane Church ought to be, I denie it.
To the minor I apply the like distinction; and consequently
to the conclusion in the same maner.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly
               What? answer you to the conclusion also?
This is a straine of new Logicke.
            
            
               
                  Mr. Fisher.
               Tolle distinctionem.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               
                  All this was spoken, but not committed to the writer. A strange distinction of the eternitie
of faith by professors to be named and not to be named.
What are professors nominable or innominable
to the eternitie of faith?
            
            
               
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Conclude that which I deny, That the Protestant
Church is so eternall, as the names of all visible
Protestants in all ages may be shewed.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               That Church whose faith is the catholicke
and primitiue faith once giuē to the Saints without which
no man can be saued, is so perpetuall as the names may
be shewed in all ages.
               But the faith of the Protestant Chruch is the primitiue
and catholik faith once giuen to the Saints,Tollitur distinctio. without which
none can be saued.
               Ergo the faith of the Protestant church is so perpetuall,
as the names may be shewed in all ages.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I answer to the minor. If this proposition
be taken simply in it selfe, I absolutely deny it; but if this
proposition be considered (as it must be) as related to the
first question and the end thereof, I further adde, that
it is not pertinent to that end for which the whole dispute
was intended, to wit, to shew to those who are not able
by their owne abilitie to find out the infallible faith necessary
to saluation, without learning it of the true visible
Church of Christ; and consequently the visibilitie of
the Church is first to be shewed before the truth of doctrine
in particular shall be shewed.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               First, what speake you of those who
are not able by their own abilities to find out faith?These words were also spoken but not set down by the writer.
is any man able by his owne abilitie, without the
help of diuine grace? 2. What helpeth the visibilitie,
to confirme the truth of the Church? Visibilitie
indeed proues a Church, but not the true Church.
               Here M. Fisher alledged some words out of D. Field of the Church, supposing
thereby to iustifie his former answer; whereunto D. Featly promised answer
should be made when it came to their turne to answer; now he was by order
to oppose M. Fisher.
               
            
            
               
               
                  D. Featly.
               The summe of your former answer
was, that the minor of my former Syllogisme was
both false and impertinent. It is neither false nor
impertinent. Ergo, your answer is false and impertinent.
And first, it is not false.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I answer to the antecedent, That it is
both false and impertinent; but I adde, that for the present
it must first be proued to be pertinent, or else it diuerteth
vs from the chiefe end of our dispute, which was,
as I said before, That infallible truth may be learned of
the true visible Church, and not the true visible Church
by first finding euery particular infallible truth, and by
that to conclude which is the true visible Church.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               
                  I proue that the minor is pertinent.
That minor proposition which together with the maior
doth necessarily and directly inferre the conclusion
of the minor last denied, is pertinent to the probation
of that minor denied.
               But the minor proposition of the third Syllogisme, doth
necessarily and directly inferre the conclusion of the minor
last denied.
               
                  Ergo the minor of that Syllogisme is pertinent.
            
            Note that M. Fishers answers to euery one of these Syllogismes were penned
by him verbatim, with the aduice of M. Sweet and one other, aduising
priuatly and amending what they thought fit, which breeding much delay, irksome
to the hearers; and the Opponent then saying, You are very long M.
Fisher. A stander by said, Let him alone, for he and his learned councell
are not yet agreed.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I distinguish the maior. That minor proposition
which together with the maior doth necessarily
and directly inferre the conclusion of the minor in such
manner as it may serue for that purpose to which the

whole dispute is ordained, I grant it to be pertinent. But
if it do inferre the conclusion, yet not in such maner as it
may serue for that purpose for which the whole dispute
was ordained, I denie the maior.
               
            
            Here the disputants iarred, and so the writer ceased; yet that which followeth
was then deliuered by them.
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               That minor which together with the maior
inferres the proposition last denied, the whole processe
hauing been per directa media, is pertinent to that purpose
to which the dispute is ordained.
               But this minor together with the maior directly and
necessarily inferres the Proposition last denied, the whole
processus hauing been made per directa media.
               
               
                  Ergo it is pertinent to that purpose to which the dispute
is ordained.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Your media in your Syllogismes were directa,
but they tended not ad directum finem.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               
                  This is a B
                        •
                     ll, Mr. Fisher. Media directa,
yet not ad directum finem, that is, direct and not direct:
for media are said to be directa only ratione finis.
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               Is there not a fault in arguing, called
transitio à genere in genus? when a man by arguing
quite leaues the maine question and subiect.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               I acknowledge that transitio à genere in
genus, is a fault in disputing; but I neuer heard, that
the inference of the effect by the cause was transitio
à genere in genus: such was my argument. For faith
in a right beleeuer produceth profession and confession
thereof, which makes a visible member, and
the like profession of many members a visible
Church. Where the cause is perpetuall, the effect
must needs be perpetual. Therefore where the faith

is perpetuall, the profession thereof must needs be,
and consequently the visibilitie of the professors
thereof. Is this transitio à genere in genus?
               
            
            
               A stander by.
               M. Sweet, you once learned better
Logicke in Cambridge then you shew now.
            
            Here againe those of M. Fishers side calling for names, D. White said,
Where are your names?
            
               
                  D. White.
               This is nothing but an apparent tergiuersation.
You will not answer any argument directly,
nor suffer vs to proceed in our arguments; and
therefore I require you Mr. Fisher, according to the
order mentioned in the beginning, for each partie
to haue an houre and a halfe, that you now oppose,
and suffer me to answer. Proue by Christ and his
Apostles, or by any of the Fathers, for the first 600
yeares, these present tenets of the Roman Church:
viz.
               1. That all power of order and iurisdiction in respect
of the Churches, is to be deriued from the
Church of Rome.
               2. That no Scripture, sense or translation thereof
is authenticall, vnlesse the same were receiued from
the Romane Church.
               3. That the Romane Church onely was and is
the authenticall custos of vnwritten traditions?
               4. That all generall Councels were called by the
sole authoritie of the Pope; and that he might ratifie
and disanull whatsoeuer pleased him in them.
               5. That the Pope onely had power to canonize
Saints.
               6. That the Pope had or hath power to depose
Princes. Proue all or any of these, and we will neither

carp nor cauill about names, but answer directly,
without all delayes, cuasions or tergiuersations.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               When you D. White or D. Featly haue
proued your Church to be visible in all ages, and named
visible Protestants, then I promise you to proue the visibilitie
of the Catholike Romane Church; but that is not
done by you yet.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               It had been done but for your delayes
and tergiuersations; answer briefly and directly to
my former argument, and I will descend to my induction,
and produce the names of such eminent
persons as in all ages haue maintained the substantiall
points of faith, in which we differ from your
Romane Church.
               That Church whose faith is the catholike and primitiue
faith once giuen to the Saints, without which none
can be saued, is so visible, that the names of the professors
in all ages may be shewed &amp; proued out of good authors.
               But the Protestant Church is that Church, whose faith
is the catholicke and primitiue faith once giuen to the
Saints, without which none can be saued. Ergo.
               The maior is ex concessis. What say you to the
minor?
               
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I distinguish the minor.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               Vpon what terme do you distinguish.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I distinguish of the proposition, not of any
terme.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               Here is againe another straine of new
Logicke, to distinguish of a proposition, and apply
the distinction to no terme: howsoeuer, I am glad
to heare you distinguish, and not simply to denie

that the Protestant faith is the Catholike primitiue
faith. Mark, I beseech you, you that are present, that
Mr. Fisher demurres vpon the proposition; his conscience
will not suffer him simply to denie, that the
Protestant faith is the Catholike primitiue faith;
we simply and flatly, and in downright termes denie
that your present Tridentine faith is the Catholike
primitiue faith.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I answered you before, that your minor
is false and impertinent.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               I haue proued already, that it is pertinent:
what say you to the truth of it?
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               This is to diuert the question: the question
is not now, whether our faith or yours be the catholicke
primitiue faith, but the question now is of the effect, to
wit, the visibilitie of your Church, which you ought to
proue out of good authors.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               May not a man proue the effect by the
cause? Is there no other meanes to proue the effect,
but by naming men and producing authors for it?
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               An effect is posterius; the question is about
an effect; therefore you ought to proue it à posteriori.
               
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               What a reason is this? May not an effect
be proued by his cause? Must an effect be needs
proued by an effect? or à posteriori, because an effect
is posterius?
               
            
            
               
                  M. Sweet.
               Leaue these Logicke disputes; bring the
names of your Protestants; that is it we expect.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               If I should relinquish my former argument,
to which yet you haue giuen no manner
of answer, you Mr. Fisher would report that I was

                  nonplussed, as you slandered D. White in a former
conference, who (I tell you M. Fisher) is able to teach
vs both. Whereto Mr. Fisher replied nothing.
            
            To preuent all such misreports to the wrong of either, it was moued by the
hearers, that is should be written downe by the common writer of the conference,
that both the Disputants being willing to proceed, D. Featly was defired
by the companie (because it was late) to produce the names of such Protestants
as were extant before Luther in all ages. This being written and
subscribed by them both, D. Featly proceeded to his induction.
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               An Induction is a forme of argument
in which we proceed from enumeration of particulars,
to conclude a generall, after this manner:
               It is so in this and this, &amp; sic de caeteris.
               
               
                  Ergo it is so in all.
               According to this forme of arguing, thus I dispute:
               The Protestant Church was so visible, that the names
of those who taught and beleeued the doctrine thereof,
may be produced in the first hundred yeares, and second,
and third, and fourth, &amp; sic de caeteris.
               
               
                  Ergo it was so in all ages.
               First I name those of the first age; and I begin
with him who is the beginner of all, our Lord and
Sauiour Iesus Christ, blessed for euer, at whose Name
all knees must bow both in heauen and earth, and
vnder the earth, (at which words all the companie
expressed an holy reuerence;) after Christ I name
the twelue Apostles, and Saint Paul: and because
there were few writers in the first age, at least whose
vndoubted works haue come to our hands, I name
onely I gnatius after the twelue Apostles and Saint
Paul.
               
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               These are enough for the first age, Christ,
the twelue Apostles, Saint Paul and Ignatius.
               
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
               
Here at the name of Ignatius some of M. Fishers side seemed very glad
and confident, saying, We are sure enough that Ignatius is on our side.
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               I meane not the new Ignatius Loyola,
but Ignatius the Martyr, betweene whom there is
more difference in qualitie, then distance in time.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Name of all the ages, or else you do nothing.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               I cannot name all at once: wil you haue
me name men of so many ages with one breath?
will you haue me eate my whole dinner at a bit?
can I name twelue seuerally, but I must name first
one, then two, then three, and so forward. I name
(as I said before) in the first age for our Religion,
our blessed Lord and Sauiour the Founder of all
Religion, the twelue Apostles, and after them St.
Paul and Ignatius the Martyr. For the second age, I
name Iustin Martyr, Clemens Alexandrinus, and Saint
Cyprian; and I begin first with Christ &amp; his Apostles.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               You shall not begin with Christ and his Apostles.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               You are not to make my Induction; I
will begin with Christ and his Apostles; where
should I begin but in the first age, and with the first
of it: shall I make a catalogue of the Christian
Church, according to the seueral ages, and leaue out
Christ and his Apostles in the first age? Answer
first to them, and I will proceed to others.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Name the rest in all ages, and then I will
answer you.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               First answer to the first age, and then I
will proceed to the second. If you grant me the first
age, then I will proceed presently to the second; otherwise
I must stay in the first.
            
            
               
               
                  M. Fisher.
               Vnlesse you giue me a catalogue of names
throughout all ages, I will not answer.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               Will you not answer Christ and his
Apostles in the first place?
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I will not before you haue named the rest.
            
            
               D. Featly.
               Will you not be tried by Christ and
his Apostles?
               That which Christ and his Apostles taught in the first
age, was taught by succeeding Christians in all ages;
this is confest on both sides.
               
               But the doctrine of the Protestants was taught by
Christ and his Apostles in the first age. Ergo.
               Answer this Syllogisme, if you will not answer
my former Induction.
            
            
               
                  M. Fisher.
               I will not answer you any thing till you
haue made your catalogue.
            
            
               
                  D. Featly.
               Mr. Fisher, I charge you, as you will answer
it before Christ himselfe at the dreadfull day
of iudgement, answer now vpon your conscience
before all this companie, whether you beleeue that
Christ and his Apostles taught our faith or yours;
this is the maine point of all; answer directly to my
Induction.
            
            Notwithstanding this deep charge, M. Fisher still refused to answer to the
argument of instance in Christ and his Apostles; whereupon diuers thereupon
expressing their distast at such refusall, desired D. Featly to surceasse, telling
him that he ought not to talke any longer with such a one who refused to answer
Christ and his Apostles. And so the Conference brake vp.
            This Conference though it tooke not that progresse
which was desired, by reason of the Iesuites
tergiuersation, not permitting Dr. Featly to come
to the ripenesse of any argument; yet it hath not bin

fruitlesse: for since that time, the aforesaid Mr. Buggs
came to Sir Humfrey Lynde, and gaue him many
thanks for the said meeting, and assured him that
he was well resolued now of his Religion; that he
saw plainly, it was but the Iesuits bragging, without
proofes▪ and whereas formerly by their Sophistical
perswasions he was in some doubt of the Church,
he is now so fully satisfied of the truth of our Religion,
that he doth vtterly disclaim the Popish priests
companie, and their doctrine also.
            Vpon Monday following, M. Fisher and M. Sweet
came vnsent for to the house of Sir Humfrey Lynde,
to know of him, whether the parties that had formerly
conferred, would proceed or no; who answered,
that if they might confer priuatly with leaue
in some other place, they would easily make good
their cause; and so they parted without further resolution
of place or meeting.
            Since which time, notice being giuen by my Lord
Bishop of Durham of his Maiesties pleasure, that the
truth of the late Conference should be certified to
his Maiestie, and further meetings staid; a Romanist
hath confidently auerred to Mr. Buggs, that our
side hath laboured to haue all future meetings touching
this occasion forbidden, because we durst not,
nor are not able to make good our assertions against
them.
            And this is the true relation of the Conference
it selfe, together with the occasion thereof, and the
effect which it produced.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

