
   
      
         
            Pluto his trauailes, or, The Diuels pilgrimage to the Colledge of Iesuites. Lately discouered by an English gentleman
            Fennor, William.
         
         
            
               1612
            
         
         Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00650
            STC 10785
            ESTC S105565
            99841292
            99841292
            5866
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00650)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5866)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:05)
         
         
            
               
                  Pluto his trauailes, or, The Diuels pilgrimage to the Colledge of Iesuites. Lately discouered by an English gentleman
                  Fennor, William.
               
               [6], 24, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by N[icholas] O[kes] for Ioseph Hunt, and are to be sold at his shop in Bedlam, nere More-fields,
                  London :
                  1612.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: William Fenner.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  With a title page woodcut.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Jesuits --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-11
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2005-11
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Pluto his Trauailes. OR, The Diuels Pilgrimage to the Colledge of Ieſuites.
            
               Lately diſcouered by an Engliſh Gentleman.
            
            
               LONDON, Printed by N. O. for Ioſeph Hunt, and are to be 
                  〈…〉
               
            
         
         
            
            
            
               To the High and Mighty Prince, Prince Henry, by the grace of God Prince of great Brittaine, and Heire apparant to the Imperiall Diadems of England, Scotland, Fraunce, and Ireland.
            
               EXCELLENT, and moſt vertuous Prince, my bluſhing boldneſſe aſketh forgiueneſſe for preſuming the preſentation of theſe ill taſting lines, to the Princely view of your high excellency. There are three eſpeciall reaſons that moued me to this raſhnes; The firſt, in regard I haue writ to diuers Princes in Germany, &amp; the Netherlands, in a borrowed Language, and haue taſted the fruites of their gratious fauours: And therefore my hopes can be no leſſe here in my natiue Countrey, vſing my mother tongue: Secondly, I haue beene a Souldier, and write the truth in a plaine ſimple ſtile, which my owne eyes haue beene witneſſe of, and mybeſt courage ſhall affirme: Thirdly, to ſhewe ſome part of my

duty to my Prince, and Countrey, whoſe loues may commaund the beſt imployment of my life, for both their ſafeties: I hope your moſt gratious acceptance of this ſimple trueth, will rather incourage, then diſcomfort him, that had rather beare the rigor of his enemy, then the diſcontent of his friend: Thus mighty Prince, with my beſt wiſhes of earthly ioyes, and Heauenly felicity, I continue your high borne Excellencies vnworthieſt Souldier, whilſt I haue life.
            
               WILLIAM FENNER.
            
         
         
            
            To the Capable, not Captious Readers health.
            
            
               I Haue to thy eye (courteous Reader) ſet forth a direct courſe, that is at this day vſed in their diueliſh Pilgrimage: I reſt aſſured ſome will much diſtaſt me, but for their diſlikes, I paſſe not, in regard they are fauorites of this deteſted Society, heere diſcouered: Yet thus much Ile ſpeake for my ſelfe, if the cunningeſt Equiuocator of them all ſhould accuſe me of vntruth in th
                  •
                leaſt, I ſtand ready to cram the lye downe their malitious throats, for I proteſt I write no heereſaies, or old wiues reports, but that my ſelfe hath ſeene and proued, to my griefe; contrarywiſe, my hopes are theſe: Firſt many reformed Chriſtians here in England, haue trauelled theſe parts, and ſeene the moſt of what I haue reported, and will reioyce at the diſcouery: Secondly, many that haue not ſeene them, haue heard of many of them, and I doubt not, but will be ready to beleeue, and allow of it; And though herein be ſome particulars which carry a ſhew of immodeſty, yet chaſt eares beare with them, I intreat you, in regard of their trueth, for indeed they were more vnciuilly acted, then I haue to the worlds vulgar eare

reported, I doubt not but many will reape content from my labour, and I hope the Learned will wink at ſmall faults; as for the obſtinate, and Ignorant I haue diſpenſt with their cenſures beforehand: Thus expecting an vniuerſall curteſie, I leaue my labour to your loues, &amp; cōmend my ſelfe to your well wiſhing thoughts.
            
               Your Friend, W. F.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               Pluto his Trauailes: or the Diuels Pilgrimage to the Colledge of Ieſuits.
            
               BEFORE Wee ſhew the Ieſuites bald Crowne, or diſcouer his plottes, it will fal neceſſary that we let you vnderſtand this perilous Pilgrimage of the Diuell, nay, rather to ye Diuell. And for the better proceeding of the Writer, and larger vnderſtanding of the Reader, I haue diuided this Iourney into fiue parts, purpoſing to ſpeake particularly of them in their ſeuerall places: The points are theſe: viz. The Pilgrimage; ſecondly, the Pilgrime; thirdly, the Saint whereto they trauell; fourthly, the things they offer fifthly and laſtly, ye fruites of their Iourney.
            
               The firſt part of the iourney.The word Pilgrimage ſignifieth a iourney of penance, or rather, a kinde of baniſhment for a certaine ſpace: Indeed it is a fearefull baniſhment, not for a certaine ſpace, but (without repentance) an euerlaſting excluding of the Soule from grate. And of this word there be thrée kinds ſpoken by a figure. The firſt, is the life of man vpon Earth, or the time of his life compared to a Pilgrimage. The ſecond, is a iourney into a farre

country. And the third, is that of which we now ſpake, a perſeuering in blinde ſuperſtition, by which we make with euery ſtep that we tread, a fearefull Pilgrimage towards the Diuell. But vnderſtand me, it is not the vſe of the word that makes it odious before God, and good Chriſtians: But the vſe and abuſe of the matter, meant by the word, as for example: The Pilgrimage of our Sauiour.The Conquerour of Sinne, Death, and Hell, trauelled his Pilgrimage in meane eſtate; he had not his Chariot drawn with foure or ſixe Palfreys, rarely trapped, three or foure Lackies running by, whilſt he ſate briſling in ye company of beautifull Ladies, in a Ueluet Seate, to ſport at the poore panting Boyes; he was not attended with ſuch obſeruance in his Pilgrimage: But contrary wiſe, he trauelled on foote, and the beſt Beaſt that euer he mounted was a ſilly Aſſe: At this glorious laſt Supper, he ſate not alone, feeding like a Churle, whilſt his twelue Apoſtles waited at the Table, but like a kinde Lord and Maiſter, cauſed them to keepe him company: Me thinkes the vſe of his humble Pilgrimage, is of force ſufficient to reprooue a number of our Epieures in this age, that are ſo gréedy, they will ſcarce keepe men to waile vpon them, but where they trauell in their Pilgrimage, they trouble the whole houſe with attending them; and no Countrey in the world ſo vild for that as Italy, and France; England cannot altogether excuſe her ſelfe of this culpable guilt; the excéeding many vanities that are vſed in this ſuperſtitious Pilgrimage, laſt ſpoke of, were much labour to write, and it would prooue tedious for you to reade, therefore paſſing ouer many, we will onely touch a few that are now in vſe in Flaunders, and Brabant, our neighbour Countries (as it were) And I feare me too many here in England knew thē too well before they read them: But to our purpoſe.
            
               Note this Story.There are two great and eſpeciall Pilgrimages in the Countrey of Brabant, the one is to our Ladie of Seerpenhowell:
               
the other is to S. Sceruias at Maſtrike, which is a Cittie ſcituated vpon the famous Riuer the Maſe, and borders on the Land of Luke; which Country is gouerned by a Biſhop.
            Their Pilgrimage to our Lady of Scerpenhowell is in this manner: The place where the Chappell ſtands was a thicke wood, where they affirme many robberies haue been done to the great indamaging of Paſſengers.
            It Chaunced vpon a night, about the yere of our Lord 1597. A flocke of Sheepe belonging to a Farmer of a little Towne not farre off, were ſtrayed from their accuſtomed walks, to the place where now the Chappell ſtands; the Sheepheard miſſing them, told his Maiſter, who preſently tooke one way, and the Shepheard the other, to looke the ſtrayed flocke; but it was the Sheepheards chance to light on this place, where all his Sheep ſate round about a great Oake: The Shepheard aſſayed to driue them away, but could not; muſing what might be the reaſon, he caſt his eyes vp in the Tree, and ſawe the Image of our Lady, which preſently he tooke down, and preſently the Sheepe came all bleating, and running about him: The amazed man could not lay downe the Image, but haſted home wards, the Sheepe following him, bleating as if they had accuſed him of theft. When he was come into the Towne, the people wondered, and preſently ſent for their Paſtor, who cauſed the Image to be ſet in the Church; and the Sheepe were driuen to their Coats. The next morning the Sheepheard miſt onely one Sheepe: And the Paſtor going to the Church to ſay Maſſe, miſt the new-come Image; whereupon he requeſted the Sheepheard to bring him to the place where he firſt found it, and taking ſome of the ſufficienteſt men in the Towne, they approched heere the place, where they found the Image in the former place, and the Sheepe lying bound at the roate of the tree, and in the Barke of the tree in Romane letters

was this Ingrauen, Offer this Sheepe, build heere a Church, and call it Scerpenhowell: The Prieſt amazed at this ſtrange accident, put on his Roabes, and did commande y• company of his pariſhoners, where a ſolemne Maſſe was ſung; ye ſheepe ſacrificed, &amp; the day and place conſecrated, for a remebrance of this much admired Miracle: preſently this was rumord to the gates of Rome, &amp; many thouſāds came in deuotion to this moſt holy place, &amp; did offer their bounteous beneuolēce, towards yt erecting of a Chappell: where by ye infinite number of People that came, &amp; daily do come, the place is now become a populous Towne: 8. Prieſts are there richly mainteined, of eight countries, termed by ye name of ſecular Prieſts, to aduertiſe all ſtrangers of this ſheepiſh Miracle.
            
               Note this.This ſtory before written, I haue read in Latine, French, and Dutch: and this vpon my own knowledge I can affirme. There are in priuate two Chirurgions kept, of the moſt ſkilfulleſt men in the Countrey; and many bring ſicke and lame Children thithet, which by the cunning of theſe ſkilfull men are cured, and the praiſe aſcribed to our Lady of Scerpenhowell. This groſſe crime is ſo cloſely, and cunningly carryed; &amp; euery Sabaoth two Sermons made, in ye affirming of this Miracle, ye it remaines currant, as ſterling money: and ye place is much inriched we gold, &amp; ſiluer; nay corne, wine, wool, eggs, or any other cōmedity is receiued in good part: But neuer any fruits come from thence, but ye Prieſts abſolutions.
            If I ſhould recite euery thing particularly, it were to much black colour for a quire of paper; onely let this ſufſice, to proue it no other, but a plaine &amp; direct path, where the Diuell, or his ſeruants walke their Pilgrimage.
            Now for the ſecond: although it is not ſo ſheepiſh, yet it is more ſottiſh; and that is this. In Maſtricke, in the yeere of our Lord 1542. there liued, &amp; died a reuerend Biſhop, who for his almes, and chaſtitie, it pleaſed the Pope, and the Councell of Trent to Cannoniſe for a

Saint; preſently his portrature was rayſed in braſſe, gilded with gold: to whom all the countrey come twice euery yeare, and bring aboundance of wealth. In this yeere 1611. there came an exceeding drought, &amp; what happened by the pollicie of the Ieſuits, you ſhall at large hears when I come to pluck off ye foure cornerd cap from their politike pates: I could deſcribe the holy bloud of Buxall, and ye three Kings of Cullin; both which are two great frequented Pilgrimages at this day: Saint Lewes in France, S. Iaques in Spaine, &amp; many in Italy; but they ſauour of one taſt; &amp; therefore I ſhould cloy your ſtomacks excedingly But prepare your appetites, for heere cōes a freſh diſh, or ye ſecond courſe of ye Pilgrimes. The ſecond part of this Iourney.This word Pilgrime is deriued from Peregrin, which ſignifieth a Stranger, and of theſe three are three ſorts, as for example: The conſtrayned Pilgrime; ſecondly the diſſembling Pilgrime; and laſtly ye needy Pilgrime. The conſtrained Pilgrime is this, one y• is appointed penance, for ſome certaine ſin, by his, or her Confeſſour. Here may be an obiection made, in defence of the Prieſt, by any fauorite of their traditions: They may aſke what cōmodity the Confeſſor ſhall gaine, by ſending his offendant on Pilgrimage, but only the diſcharging of his conſcience: To this I anſwere; It is no ſmall profit that this brings to the Church of Rome. For conſider who theſe are they ſend foorth, not their needy Pilgrimes, but their richeſt Benefactors, &amp; with this prouiſo they are ſent; firſt they muſt offer a certaine ſūme of riches to ſome Saint in his Confeſſors Church; ſecondly he muſt giue ſo many ſhillings, for Maſſes to be ſaide in his abſence, to the end he may haue a proſperous iourney: thirdly he muſt viſite ſo many Shrines in his Pilgrimage: Fourthly, heare ſo many Maſſes by the way: Fifthly, giue ſo much to the Saint he trauailes to, in honour of the fiue wounds of our Sauiour Chriſt: Sixthly, he muſt viſit the Ieſuits Cloyſters in his iourney, and go to confeſſion ſo

many times. Seuenthly, and laſtly, at his returne, Father confeſſors muſt not be forgotten. Thus you ſes many wicked egges are hatched, vnder the diſſembling habite of holyneſſe, and the conſtrayned Pilgrims muſt pay for the breeding of the Chickens.
            Now for the ſecond ſort of the diſſembling Pilgrims, I feare me there are too many: but omitting the ſecret, we will onely diſcouer the notorious and capitall ſort. The third Edward of England had a faire Siſter, called Philip, matched to the Duke of Sauoy, who at a certaine time ſtanding before her gates, eſpied a Spaniſh Lady going in deuotion to Saint Lewes in Fraunce, And in curteſie deſired her to take the entertainement of her Court; The Spaniſh Lady noting gracious ſpeach and delicate beauty, tooke occaſion to compare the beautie of the Dutches to the beauty of her Brother in Spaine, where at the Dutches burnt in ſuch deſire to ſee him, that was ſo highly commended by his owne Siſter, that ſhe diſſembled her health, and lying ſicke of a feyned diſeaſe, vowed to God (before the ſorrowfull Duke) that if God ſhould reſtore her to her former health, ſhe would goe in deuotion to Saint Iaques in Spaine, and offer for her health.
            Upon this Ladies returne, ſhe Dutches recouered, and according to her vowe, ſhe trauailed to Spaine for the ſight of a Spaniſh Lord. At their enteruiew their ſights were pleaſing to each other, and their beauties admired of each other; and after ſome amorous conference, he vowing to ſerue her as her Knight, and ſhe moſt willingly accepting, ſhe returned, but with heauy ſucceſſe, for the neuer ſawe her wedded Lord after: He being imployed in wars, againſt the Duke of Burgundy, left a Lord of his Countrey as Deputy in his place, who vpon the returne of his Lady, burned in luſtfull Loue with her beauty, and deſired her to graunt him fauour for his affections: The chaſt Lady deſpiſing his motion,

derided him for his folly, at which the villaine grew ſo enuious, being poiſoned with the Diuels baite, that he ſought all occaſions to defame her, and by meanes of a ſilly Kimſman, he found way to bring her within the compaſte of the law. And being by him accuſed for adulterie, ſhe was condemned to fire, if none within the ſpace of fifteene weekes ſhould come to fight in her cauſe: this Spaniſh Lord hauing receiued a Letter of her wrongs, ſent her word backe he could not, neyther would he come. Then ſhe repented her long Iourney, and being voide of earthly hopes, prepared her ſelfe for death, expecting no deliuerance: But contrary to expectation, the Spaniſh Lord came in the habite of a Frier, and confeſt her in Priſon, and afterwards ſought for her, ouerthrew Pendoſta, and freed her from death, and ſhame; and after the Dukes death marryed the Dutches.
            Although this kind of diſſimulation was euill in the Dutches, yet it comes not neare the cloſe diſſimulation that is vſed in theſe daies. I will giue you a taſt of ſome in the Cittie of Cades in Spaine. There is a great Monaſtary of no ſmall acount. where in many Gentlemen doe incloſe their Daughtes: And ſo it was, there liued a Gentleman in the famous Cittie of Antwerpe,
               Note this 1603. who had a great deſire to ſend his onely Daughter thiether, for he had no more: The Girle was about ſixteene yeeres of age, and often ſollicited by a Marchants ſonne of the ſame Cittie; the Maide alſo grew inclyning to his will, and did much affect his ſute, but in regard of her Fathers mind ſhe could allow him no conference, but in priuate: And in ſhort time they wrought ſo priuately together, that they ouerthrew the voyage; for thus it was: the Father made all prouiſion neceſſarie for his Girles tourney; And the young couple being loath to part, practiſed how to keepe company ſtill, in a diſguiſed faſhion: So at the laſt, after long ſtudie, Lady Laſciuious, with her Beldame Opportunity, growing acquainted

with their ſuite, gaue them this counſell: the yong man to transforme himſelfe into an effeminate ſhape, &amp; ſo vnſuſpected hee might ſafely trauell as a ſhe Pilgrime in her company: but for the more ſafety it was agréed vpon betweene them, that hee ſhould take the name of Dalinda, and preſent himſelfe to the Gentlewoman ſo, in the ſhape of an attendant or poore Gentlewoman, ſéeming by her ciuill ſhew to be more rich in vertue then in beauty: all which was acted in ſuch quaint manner that they ſeemed to ſurpaſſe the boyes of Blacke-fryars. Thus now muſt we leaue to call him by the name of a Merchants ſonne, but pray you remember Dalinda, and all is well. Imagine you ſee the father and child parted with teares: ſhe trauelling towards her holy life, being accompanied with her waiting maide, and the father hauing brought her a little on the way returned homewards, ioyfull that his child was ſo accompanied, for it ſeemed to him that his daughter tooke much delight in the ſociety of her maide. But before wee purſue theſe two louely Pilgrimes any further, I muſt intreate you to bend your thoughts towards the Merchant, whoſe heart was much perplexed for the loſſe of his ſon. Many times would he go to the Gentlemans houſe &amp; blame him exceedingly, for ſending away ſo rich a iewell as his child that was in his power to kéepe; but I qnoth the Merchant haue loſt that which if I could attaine to, it would make me young againe, but O my ſonne, my ſon, I haue loſt thee for euer: then would a freſh fountaine of teares bedew his manly chéekes, that mée thought it a pitty to behold, the other Gentleman would then giue him comfort, and tell him it was the cuſtome of woemen to bewray their griefe with teares. Thus will we leaue the two childrenleſſe fathers comforting each other, and ouertake the Gentlewoman and her maide Dalinda, for they are but new ſet forth,
            The louely Pilgrimes accompanied each other &amp; made

the way ſhort with their pleaſing talke, each commending others wit in the ſeuerall acting of their parts, till at length the blacke eyed night lookt from the Eaſt, and Phoebus tooke his reſt in Thetis lap, and this yoake of Pilgrims alſo according to the cuſtome of trauellers, deſired repoſe. Hauing takē vp their Inne they cauſed ſupper to be prouided, and after ſupper with-drew themſelues into a faire chamber, where the maide counſelled the Miſtreſſe to accept of a bed fellow, telling the dangers of ſpirits, catching cold, idle thoughts, and panting greiſe that often haunted the minde of a ſole &amp; weake woman. Dalindas words were of ſuch force that he preuailed, &amp; the kind Gentlewoman affected her maide ſo much, that ſhee accepted of her ſociety in bed: for theſe words ſhee ſpoke. Kind Dalinda although in this iourney you are to accompany me for a hand-maide, yet vpon the condition you will ſweare to do me true ſeruice by night as you haue done by day, and ſerue me in bed as well as abroad I heere accep̄t of you for my choice bed fellow. In concluſion Dalinda agreed to all her kind Miſtreſſe propoſed, And ſo to bed they went: from whence I thinke ſhee roſe diſcharged of the Art of honeſty. Thus this yong couple paſt away their iourney merrily, vntill their long way had brought them to ye ports of Cades, where they were louingly receiued &amp; brought to ye Abbeſſe of yt Monaſtery. Shée without further tryal of their intents preſented them ye oath of chaſtity which they both ſolemnely tooke deepely vowing to kéepe themſelues as they were. Thus they were accepted for ſiſters, but ſiſter Dalinda ſhifted bed fellowes ſo often ye three of the ſiſters grew ſick of ye double diſeaſe, which when Dalinda heard, for feare of puniſhment, found meanes to eſcape, and with ſhipping came to Amſterdam in Holland, where hée is wealthily married to the Burgomaiſters daughter of the Citty. The 3 ſiſters were thruſt out of the Monaſtery, &amp; came home to their fathers, each of thē bringing ye honourable

badge of chaſtitie breeding in their bellies.
            There are too many of thoſe diſſembling Pilgrimes now a daies. Some I could write of, that would proue too ſhamefull for the Writer, and cauſe the Reader to bluſh; but leauing theſe cloſe diſſemblers to their moſt abhorred ſhame, that waits on wantons luſt: Trouble your ſelues to turne ouer theſe leaues, and you ſhall find the dangerous eſtate of the needy Pilgrimes. Let this ſuffice for the ſecond, &amp; alſo to proue that all thoſe that walke in this path, are without doubt the Diuels Pilgrimes, or at leaſt, going Pilgrimage vnto him.
            This needy Traueller is almoſt in the nature of an Engliſh Rogue, there is ſmall difference, and he is as ranke a diſſembler as ye other. There are of all Nations that profeſſe this needy life, but of all, there are moſt Iriſh, and I can not blame them, for by nature they are borne to be lowſy, ſtraglers and ſtirrers vp of rebellion; And ſince it hath pleaſed God of his mercy to plant his peaceable word, and by the meanes of his Seruant, our moſt gratious Soueraigne Lord, King Iames (whome God long preſerue) to make a ciuill Countrey, of the moſt barbarous parts in Ireland: There are many that haue harkened to ye Diuels whiſpering, &amp; ſworne their true ſeruice to his adopted Sonne, the Romiſh Prieſt. No meruaile though they cannot content themſelues vnder a quiet gouernment, but had rather eate of the Scraps of Spaine, and Italy, then feede of the plentie of their reformed Countrey: they are borne wild of brute bringing vp, and ſo they meane to continue: they neuer knew what reformation meant, neyther do they purpoſe euer to know, for as they were brought vp, ſo they bring vp their Children, onely to ſhamefull begging, in the manner of Pilgrims, with their Letters of Confeſſion in a Tinne Boxe, which they hang by their ſides: They walke in the name of the Popes Seruants; and indeed the needy Hipocrites do thriue in their vile profeſſion

exceedingly. But there is the miſchiefe; what they g
                  •
                with impudent begging, they ſpend with immodeſt abuſes. There are alſo many of our countrymen, of this intreating trade, which for ſome offence are conſtrained to leaue the ſweet and wholſome aire of their natiue country, and liue in the abhominations of the Babilonious Miſtreſſe. And how the Engliſh Ieſuits of Louaine do intreat them, you ſhall plainely ſee when their caps are of, and their crownes diſcouered. But courteous reader, feaſt no longer vpon the needy diſh of Pilgrimes meat, but turne thy gentle eye, and ſee the Saint deſcribed whereto they trauell.
            
               The third part of this Iourney.The Saints whereto they trauell are diuers, and according to the nature of the crime committed, or otherwiſe the neceſſity of the buſineſſe they take in hand, for theſe are the principall vſes of Pilgrimage, but wee are not to reaſon of the voyage, but of the ariuall, for after many a weary ſteppe with ioyfull hearts they enter the Temple, where their Saint ſtands, nay rather an abhominable Idoll or image of ſtone, onely it retaineth the ſhape of a dead man or woman, according to the pleaſure of the Caruer, and after the Caruer hath moſt artificially finiſht his Arte, comes the Painter, and daubes it ouer with his liuely colours. Some of their Saints ſeeme to ſmile, promiſing with an auſpicious eye, grace (as it were) to the penitent petitioner: others are framed (by the Painters Arte) with a ſhew of wéeping, and to your thoughts the dead eye of the image will preſent teares, as though it did delacrimate mans miſery, or ſeeme to weepe with a grieuing ſorrow for the ſinnes of the ſolemne ſuiter: Who can bee ſo blind except the diuell hath blinded him, to put any confidence in the Caruers ſkill, or the Painters Art? And who is not ſo blind (but thoſe whom God hath opened their eyes that they may diſcerne the cleare light of the

Goſpell, and giue credit to this moſt heathen like and deuiliſh doctrine; this is all that I can deſcribe of their Saint, a carued ſtone, or a painted, or guilded péece of wood. And the concluſion of my cenſure is this, that all thoſe y• ſtraggle in deuotion to viſite theſe Saints, cannot miſſe the way towards the diuell, and ſome trauell barefoote too, becauſe they will take the more paines in this deteſted Pilgrimage. I am loath my pen ſhould vrge ſo bare a ſubiect any further, yet one thing gentle Reader with thy patience I muſt vnfold concerning their Saints, the much honoured image of our bleſſed Lady is in moſt places richly deckt with robes of diuers colours, as for example, where the Angell ſaluted her ſhee is ſet forth in a white lawne robe in token of chaſtity, with her golden treſſes of haire hanging downe her backe, and a modeſt bluſhing beſpread her virginlike cheekes. After her conception, ſhe is adored with ſcarlet. After the birth of our Sauiour, in blacke veluet: and at his paſſion ſhe is pictured in a blew vaile: thus after their owne inuentions, they forme the image of the bleſſed Uirgin, and alſo of all other Saints, which I here omit.
            
               The fourth part of this Iourney.The fourth part of our iourney conſiſts in the things they offer, which briefly we will touch, becauſe we long to vncap the diſſembling Ieſuite. The things they offer are of three kinds: viz. firſt, Oriſons; ſecondly, Gifts: and thirdly Thanks: as for their Oriſons, they are in this manner: they commonly kneele on their bare knees, or elſe proſtrate all along with their beades in their hands, they ſay ſo many Pater-noſters, Aue-Maries, and Creeds as their Ghoſtly father hath appointed them, then they bleſſe the image, deſiring the Saint in heauen to looke downe and ſee in what humble deuotion hee honours his or her image, then they croſſe themſelues which they call bleſſing themſelues▪ and departing into a celler or a vault vnder ground, where they ſay the Saints bodies lie buryed, they firſt doe their deuotion in prayers and

after offer ſuch gifts as they bring, be it gold, ſiluer, veluet, ſilks, cambrike, linnen, wollen, leade, corne, wine, oile, egges, or any other commodity, but gold and ſiluer is the pleaſingſt gifts that the Saints accept of, and bringing good ſtore of that, no doubt but all ſhall goe wel with their ſuits: This being laid vpon the Altar the Prieſt conſecrates it, abſolues the party, and prayes to the Saint for him that he may haue his deſire: the Pilgrime ſufficiently contented, returnes to the former image, and there powring forth a million of thankes for his good ſucceſſe, in that the Saint hath vouched ſafe by his Prieſt to accept of their vnworthy offerings, and ſo they returne diſcharged of their golden burden.
            Let this ſuffice for their offerings. Now concerning the fruits of this iourney before rehearſed, it is of two kinds, that is general and particular. The general fruite is deceipt which the poore Pilgrimes plucke with greedy appetites, the tree whereon this fruite groweth, is ye Romane Church, and it neuer miſſeth bearing▪ for neither ye heate of Summer, nor the cold of Winter can deſtroy it, it is a forbidden fruite, and whoſoeuer deſireth to taſt thereof muſt needes be deceiued, it ſhewes faire to the eye, and promiſeth life, but within it is corrupted and bringeth death, this is the generall fruite they reape for their trauell. My reaſon is this, the diuell is a common deceiuer, and thoſe that poſt Pilgrimage towards him muſt needs taſt of this deceiptfull fruite.
            The ſecond fruite they reape is particular, according to the diſpoſition of the party that deſires it: this tree is generall but it beares particular fruits, as vaine hope, wilfull ignorance, blind zeale, corrupt beleife, falſe worſhip, and laſtly death and damnation. It would ſeeme idleneſſe in me to diſcourſe of theſe ſeuerally, or to ſeeme to diſſwade men from this, therefore. I will leaue it to your owne iudgement, and to the learned Diuines counsell,

which is of farre more force, then my ſimple perſwaſions can bee. Thus much for this diueliſh Pilgrimage.
            Friendly Reader, if this long iourney hath not wearied thee, goe on a little further, and thou ſhalt ſee my honeſt ſimple ſkill in vnmaſking the Ieſuits plots, let thy heart be as free from enuy, as my pen, which ſhall put downe nothing but truth, and what I haue ſeene, and dare affirme by oath, were it to their téethes. Therefore I hope none will taxe mee of malice, for I had rather be conuicted of ſimple plaineneſſe, hauing truth on my ſide, then commended for an artificiall writing where the truth is wronged by falſe ſuggeſtions. But leauing all to thy kind conſiderations, I am purpoſed to go forward with my vnlearned ſtile, relating their learned approued practiſes.
            
               Heere endeth the Diuels Pilgrimage, and here beginneth the bare-headed Ieſuits.
               
               THere are diuers Orders in the Romiſh religion, as namely ye 
                  Benedicts, ye 
                  Dominictes, the Franciſcans, the Auguſtines, the Carthuſians, ye 
                  Carmelites, ye 
                  Capucines, and laſtly the Ieſuits, of whom wee purpoſe to ſpeake, In Latine they are called ſocietatis Ieſu: in Dutch, Ieſuiter, which ſignifieth Ieſus fellowes, or at leaſt the fellowſhip of Ieſus. This Sect is but of ſmall continuance, or but of yong growth, yet neuer Sect in the world hath flouriſht ſo for the time, for in them the Diuell ſhewes himſelfe to bee a true Politician, and they as his faithfull inſtruments, ſpread his pollicy through the greateſt part of Europa:
               
               
                  In Louaine a Citty in Brabant, eight leagues diſtant from Antwerpe, is crected a Colledge at the King of Spaines charges for Engliſh Ieſuits, wherin at this preſent inhabits father Taubut, which is the Superiour, father Ioſeph, father Kempe, father Anthony, father Miniſter, &amp; many more, beſides punies &amp; nouicies, They haue their Colledge allowed them, for theſe purpoſes. Firſt, to reconcile or conuert any of their countrimen that happen into their hands. Secondly, to diſguiſe themſelues, and like Gentlemen to come into England, and pry into Court and Counſels to know the ſtate of ye land and Church, &amp; to tranſport their news to ye Pope, &amp; their Spaniſh Lord. For theſe two purpoſes they are maintained, but wee'l come a little nearer. Note this.If a Gentleman chance to goe ouer, their cinque port deſcries him preſently, then with letters they inuite him thither where they ſo worke him, that hee ſhall hardly eſcape the ſnares and baits are laid to entangle him: when hee is caught they bring him to confeſſion, where they know his quantity of ſubſtance, and quality of minde, which beeing knowne, they ſhriue and eaſe him of his ſubſtance, if hee bee learned they accept of him in their ſociety, otherwiſe ſend him to the Carthuſians in Mackelyn, or elſe to Saint Omers in Flanders, or to Rome, to make him the fitter for their purpoſe. This is their vſage to Gentlemen. If a poore man come to them, they accept him willingly, and examine him concerning his conſcience, if they finde him not currant, they admoniſh him ſhewing him bookes of inſtruction in the principles of religion: if this catch him not, they allure him with promiſes, not onely of a heauenly crowne, but of ſome earthly crownes: the needy ſnake cannot chuſe but nibble at this charitable baite, and rather then faile they will then venture a crowne or two, and with comfortable workes

tell him that if he continue he ſhall not want, and to the furthering of this comfort they giue him letters of atteſtation, where and when he was conuerted, from a loathed heriticke, to a godly and bleſſed Catholique, then diſmiſſing him the houſe, they tell him it is no ſhame to begge and bid him be bold. Thus he that could liue in his owne country by his honeſt labour, is conuerted, or rather by them peruerted to an impudent and ſhameleſſe beggar: this is one of their priuy pollicies, to ſhadow their deteſted couetouſneſſe, for if they beſtow an Angell of a beggar, they begge a brace of hundreds from a gallant, thus they buy and ſell their conſcience but they will be ſure to gaine by the bargaine.
               This abhominable ſect is luld in the lap, and ſnuggles in the breaſts of the ſeuen deadly ſinnes (as they call them) yet they haue artificiall maſkes to ſhadow all from the vulgar eys of the world. Their pride is couered with humility, as appeares by their plaine habit, and courteous ſpeeches, yet their hearts heape vp ambitious thoughts: here may be a queſtion aſked, how I know the heart? I will reſolue you, I haue ſeene them in their Gentlemanlike ſuits, ſwagger in more proud faſhion then a Spaniard: ſecondly, I haue obſerued pride in their ſpeeches, for they haue a kind of puryfied ſpeech, exceeding al mens in their owne thoughts: Héere I muſt compare them to many of our hypocriticall profeſſors in England, which take more care of their words, then their deedes, I haue noted them to ſcorne all others that ſeemed any way to diſtaſte their Sect, and as I take it theſe are true notes of pride: for rouetouſneſſe they couer it with a ſhew of pouerty, for they alwaies profeſſe themſelues poore, proteſting if they had it, no man ſhould want it, when as indeed they will haue it though all others ſhould want it. You ſhall hears the proofe of this hereafter, when I ſpeake of their baniſhment out of Venice, their enuy is coloured with a ſhew of deſire

to make the world wiſe with their learning, and indeed they do grudge that any wiſedome or learning breathes out of their Colledges, they hate all good workes that are not made by Ieſuites, they cloake wrath with méekneſſe, and in outward ſhew are very gentle and milde, but their hearts more feirce then Lyons: It is not vnknowne to many, what Péeres and Princes their wrath hath brought to vntimely ends, and yet theſe tyrants thirſt in their ſoules for more royall bloud to quench their feirce wrath. But he is aboue that preuents their deſires and deſtroyes their daily plots. Their ſloath is hidden from the eye of any, but God and themſelues, and I thinke in this ſinne they haue leaſt and moſt ſhew: for as the old prouerbe is, they are neither idle, nor well occupied, for they are euer buſy but it is in the diuels ſeruice. And for gluttony, hee dwels in their kitchin, but you ſhall neuer go thither to ſee him. Laſt Lady letchery puts on this maſke, no woman of what degree ſoeuer may enter their ſecond parts or inward dore, but by your leaue the Ieſuits enter priuately within their inward dores, and doe the deeds of darkeneſſe with them when they pleaſe. But this may be thought a ſlander, therefore giue me leaue to free my ſelfe from this ſuſpicion. In Louaine there is an Engliſh Cloiſter of Gentlewomen, and the Lady Abbeſſe much reſpected for her hidden vertues, in which Cloyſter their dwelleth a young man called Raph, which loued a waiting Gentlewoman, whoſe Lady often frequented the company of the Lady Abbeſſe, by which meanes, Raph and the maide had opportunity to conferre. It chanced one of the Engliſh Ieſuits, a young man repaired thither often likewiſe, and in ſhort time grew into ſuch inward acquaintance with the maide, that Raph tooke his loue with her belly full of young bones, which afterwads confeſt were of the Ieſuits making. Raph made his complaint to the Cloiſrer, and told father Talbut one of

their holy Family had enioyed too much homely familiarity with his wife, and made him a father before his time; proteſting if they would not make him amends, hee would publiſh it through the whole Country. But the Ieſuits agréeing amongſt themſelues, ſtopt his mouth with an hundred Angels: whereupon Raphe was content to father the Ieſuits childe. Thus you ſée, though they are not content a woman ſhould enter their Cloyſter, yet they themſelues will vouchſafe to enter their cloſets. But wee will leaue to ſpeake more of theſe louing labourers in the Diuels harueſt, and write briefly of the Venetian villaines, which ſhall anſwere my promiſe in the leafe going before, to proue their cloked couetouſneſſe.
               In this famous Cittie of Venice inhabited certaine Colledges of Ieſuits, to whom all the chieſe Merchants wiues went to confeſſion, and were appointed ſuch horrible penance, that their huſbands riches, which was excéeding great, began to waſte, in ſuch ſort that the Merchants began to take a ſeuere account of their ſeruants, but to ſmall effect; till at laſt, one perceiued his wife to purſe vp great ſtore of gold in an euening whileſt ſhee thought he had ſlept: and being ready to iſſue out of the the chamber doore, belike to hide it againſt the next confeſſion day, her huſband ſtept out of his bed, and ſtayed her, vſing theſe words: Stay ſwéet wife, I muſt talke with you. The amazed woman made no reply, but ſtood as it were in a Traunce. The Merchant hauing her in a priuate chamber, lockt the doore, and taking his naked ponyard, placing the poynt to her breaſt, threatned with oathes her preſent death, if ſhe would not reueale the occaſion of purſing vp that gold. The poore woman affrighted with theſe words, confeſt all what ſhe knew of herſelfe and others. This night paſt away, and on the morrow the Merchant ſent for the men whoſe wines his wife had accuſed, and relating the whole ſtory which

ſhe before had demonſtrated, and then before them all affirmed. They all agréed to ſhrowd themſelues in ye chamber behinde an Oras, whilſt his wife by a priuate token ſent for her Confeſſour, who preſently came, aſking the cauſe of her importuning him there. She, with many diſſembling ſighes, told him about a thing which much troubled her conſcience. Be of good cheare (quoth he) it ſhall go hard but I will vnload your conſcience of any ſinne whatſoeuer. Therefore ſpeake your minde. Alas (quoth ſhe) in my ſleepe I chanced to dreame of you, and in my dreame ſpake of the maſſes of gold and ſiluer that you haue had of me: my huſband being awake, ouerheard me, and tooke hold of my words, caſting it in my teeth daily. I denied it ſtrongly. He affirmes tis truth, and vrges me to the reuealing of it, with perſwaſions &amp; threatnings, ſo that I know not longer how to diſſemble, or defend it, neither can I furniſh you with any more treaſure, by reaſon of his ſtrict accounts, and narrow prying into my doings: therefore (holy father) moſt intirely I doe entreate you to reſolue me in this moſt dangerous caſe what is beſt to be done, and I ſhall moſt willingly do my indeuour to follow your often aproued good counſell. You ſay well (quoth the old Foxe) and for your ſoules good reſt conſtant, and confeſſe nothing, no though you ſhould incurre the greateſt diſpleaſure of your huſband; but rather count it a bleſſing that you are worthy to ſuffer reproofe for the Mother Church. Goe forward in your holy worke, and to bring treaſure to the Church, where neither ruſt nor moth ſhall corrupt, nor théeues breake through and ſteale. So ſhall you bee bleſt, and receiue for your corruptible gold, an incorruptible crowne of glory. But if you faint and ſlacke in this good worke begun, you ſhall be tormented in your ſoule. Whereat the Merchants ruſhed forth, laying hold of the Ieſuit, &amp; told him they meant he ſhould be tormented in 
                     〈◊〉
                   body. And drawing a ponyard the womans huſband

ſpake as followeth: Uillaine, either diſcloſe thy plots in receiuing our ſubſtance, or preſently prepare for Hell: for this reſolued hand ſhall ſend thee paſt Purgatory. And bending his ponyard at the amazed Ieſuits breaſt, the quaking ſlaue fell downe on his knées praying for mercy, and he would diſcouer all, and reſtore them their ſeuerall wealthes double. They all affirmed, you are not worth ſo much. Yes (queth the Ieſuit) I will make a ſhift to keepe my word: therefore I pray you tell me on your conſciences, what may the ſumme amount vnto that you miſſe. They anſwered, eighteene thouſand pounds ſterling. Peace (quoth the Prieſt) if you will promiſe me faithfully neuer to report it, you ſhall goe and receiue the ſumme double. It is enough (ſaid the Gentlemen:) So they agreed, and marched together to the Ieſuits Cloyſter, where they were admitted, and a moſt rich banquet prouided. But the Father Superiour cauſed a mortall potion to be tempered for them all; and taking a beaker of Ipocras, drunke a health to them all: and powring forth the infectious wine with great curteſie, he had them all heartily welcome, affirming they ſhould poſſeſſe the fore-written ſumme with expedition. The Gentleman (whether miſtruſting the deceipt, or rather God was not pleaſed that this villany ſhould proceed) tooke a Stone ſhell ſtanding by him, and powring the poyſon therein, the ſhell brake in peeces. Upon this ſight the other Gentlemen drew to their weapons, the Ieſuits likewiſe armed themſelues: and in meane while the Gentlemen plaid the men, and got out into the ſtreets, crying, Treaſon, Treaſon, with their weapons drawne. At length they got into the Market-place, vnto whom reſorted all the States, and moſt ſufficienteſt Merchants to know the cauſe of this clamour. So one of them got vp on the Stage, where their Comedies are acted, and vttered this ſpéech: Renowned States, and worthy Citizens, whom all ye world admires for polic
                     •
                  
                  
why will you ſuffer your ſelues to be vndermined? you your wiues and children, know this, we are all deceiued &amp; ouer-ruled: not by the gracious directions of you the Honourable States, but by the cloſe diſſembling Ieſuits; which (if it be not reformed) will bee the ruine of this moſt famous Citty. I ſpeake the truth, which ſome of my brethren here can witneſſe, and moſt of our wiues, by whom our wealth is tranſported to the Ieſuits: which when we knew, they inuited vs to a banquet, affirming vs our money double; but there they ſought to poyſon vs: but God hath deliuered vs out of their hands to diſcouer their villany. Therefore worthy States, ſearch their Cloyſters, and you ſhall finde infinite ſtore of treaſure there. This vpon my ſoules ſafety, and liues perill, I affirme it for truth.
               Upon this report, the States taking theſe Merchants along with them, repaired where all was at full related. Whereupon, the Duke aſſiſting the States, they were all baniſhed the Citie, hauing nothing allowd them but their Bookes and Habits. After their departure, their Colledges were ſearched, wherein was found infinite treaſure. And by a publique proclamation of the Duke and States, the Merchants were ſummoned to the Colledge, where (vpon their oathes) euery man ſeized on his owne, and the ouer-plus, that no man challenged, came to the Duke and States, to the value of fiue hundred millions, beſides plate and veſtures: yet theſe diſſemblers profeſt themſelues poore.
               Thus were theſe Ieſuits baniſht from Venice, which diſpleaſed the Popes holyneſſe not a little; neuertheleſſe theſe ſtragglers were by their falſe fellowes preſently planted and inriched. Theſe Ieſuits are much like the Iewes, for let them come where they will, they thriue by their place. Nay that which is more, let them be now in extreame pouerty, yet with one yeares dealing they will grow exceeding rich, that other men ſhall ſmart for their

proſperity, I thinke this point of knanery hath ſet his cap on the one ſide and diſcouered halfe his head, but this plot following ſhall quite disfurniſh him of his cap, I pray you note it, for it is the fulfilling of a promiſe that I made, when I ſpake of the Pilgrimage at Maſtricke, concerning the drouth of this years, and ſo I meane to conclude my little volume, with that moſt abhominable villany
               In Maſtricke, as I ſaid before, there is a frequented Pilgrimage, to Saint Sceruias. You know this yeare there was an exceeding drought. It was my chance to be there at ye preſent, (therefore I will report but what I haue ſeene) And many a hundred came in blind deuotion and offered guifts to ye Saint in hope of raine: notwithſtanding the drouth continued. The Ieſuits of ye City being loath to let ſo faire and profitable a game ſlip without chaſe, let looſe their dogs, which faſtned on this faſhion. One of their ſmotheſt tongues, annointed with the Diuels oile, ſteps vp into the Pulpit, and vtters his Sermon to the people in this ſort. This drouth (quoth he) is ſent from heauen to plague the earth for ye peoples vnthankfulneſſe and neglecting of their duties. Heere (quoth he) you bring offerings to this bleſſed Saint, but it is preſented wt vnhallowed hands, &amp; polluted hearts, therfore to preuent the Lords wrath, and the Saints fury, bring your gifts to vs, &amp; our holy Society will conſecrate them, and with pure hearts and vnſpotted hands offer them vp to this moſt holy Saint, who no doubt but will be pleaſed in loue to accept them. Moreouer (quoth he) your gifts are defiled with couetouſneſſe, but Beloued you muſt bring it willingly, and according to your ability; &amp; then no doubt but heauens drops will quench the thirſty earth. This was ye marke he aimed at in his Sermon, which as the Diuell would haue it tooke effect, and profited ye Ieſuits very much. For after this al offerings were firſt brought to them, which they firſt vnder

ſhew of ſanctification ſtole the moſt and beſt part away, the Cannons in Saint Sceruias Church got the reſt, but the Picture and the Pilgrimes were both cheated. After along time of drouth it pleaſed God to ſend raine; then they ſent plackets out to warne the country to a thanks offering, where after Maſſe a Sermon was made in honour of this worſhipfull image, afterwards they were let into a ſecret wide roome, adioyning to the Church, where his Portrature ſtands, raiſed in liuely coulours, two Prieſts kept the dore, and euery man gaue his deuotion to ſee their tragicall ſhew. It appeared much like our ſtage-players, but onely they wanted a foole in the ſhew. Yet ye two Foxes made géeſe of all them y• came to behold it: thus their monſtrous abuſes are made manifeſt. For what will not theſe men deale in for gaine, that ſet price of the weather.
               So farre hath truth ventured to vncap the Ieſuits, ye all may plainely diſcerne a bare-headed cunning knaue. I would wiſh all my friends and countrimen to take heed of their company, for their Society is dangerous, &amp; their ſnares &amp; baits are many; their religion was brought in by Ignatius, but it ſhall go out with eternall ignomy, when the Almighty is pleaſed either to conuert, or vtterly roote them out. I could proſecute their polliticke cloſe plots further, and ſhew the manner of their helliſh Inquiſition, cōmon, &amp; priuate Counſels, their Libraries, and confeſſions, but ſo much hath bene heeretofore written, therefore I will not enter into their works. Let him yt ſowes reape, and thoſe that plant eate of their owne fruite. As for this I proteſt it was mine owne obſeruation, which I haue willingly ſet forth, for the good of my louing countrimen.
               To ſpeake of one generall point briefly, I hope ſhall neither tyer me nor weary you. I pray you obſerue it. In the Empire of Chriſtendome for one Proteſtant there are tenne Papiſts, and it were 
                     〈◊〉
                   
to
thinke there are no well conditioned people amongſt thē, this I dare affirme vpon my conſcience, that without doubt there are many godly men and woemen, truly deuout &amp; zealous, ye would willingly come to ſée the cléere ſhining light of truth, but theſe men of darkenes ſtand betwéene them &amp; the light, &amp; barre the truth from them. But for the Ieſuits, thus I cenſure them generally vpon my conſcience, that of a hundreth there are ſcarce two iuſt dealing men. For breach of oathes they call equiuocation, &amp; all their villanies they can diſpenſe with. But alas their ending illuſions without Gods mercy, will turne to their endleſſe confuſions, where they ſhall curſe their tutor the Deuill, for inſtructing them in theſe and many more their deceitfull and pollitick 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Let vs giue thanks to him y• ſuffers none 
                     〈…〉
                   wolues to deuoure his choſen Flock heere in 
                     〈◊〉
                  . And laſtly you iocond Ieſuits, that ſtrut it out in your diſſembling holy habits, look to it, I haue onely diſcouered your bald crownes, but I feare me, if you come masking here into England in your former and accuſtomed diſguiſes, the excutioner will rip vp your bloudy breaſts, and diſcouer your treacherous hearts, And then the Popes Bull will reare at T
                     ••
                  orne. Till then Farewell.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

