
   
      
         
            The supplicacion: that the nobles and comons of Osteryke made lately by their messaungers, vnto kyng Ferdinandus, in the cause of the Christen religion Item. The kynges answere to the same. Vvherpon foloweth the wordes that the messaungers spake vnto the kyng agayne at their departing.
         
         
            
               1542
            
         
         Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00673
            STC 10808
            ESTC S105580
            99841307
            99841307
            5882
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00673)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5882)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 40:04)
         
         
            
               
                  The supplicacion: that the nobles and comons of Osteryke made lately by their messaungers, vnto kyng Ferdinandus, in the cause of the Christen religion Item. The kynges answere to the same. Vvherpon foloweth the wordes that the messaungers spake vnto the kyng agayne at their departing.
                  Coverdale, Miles, 1488-1568.
                  Ferdinand I, Holy Roman Emperor, 1503-1564.
               
               [48] p.   
               
                  Printed by M. Crom,
                  [Antwerp :
                  1542?]
               
               
                  German original not traced.
                  Translator's preface headed: Myles C. [i.e. Miles Coverdale] to the reader.
                  Place of publication and printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC.
                  Signatures: pi⁴ A-B C⁴.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Reformation --  Austria --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-03
            Taryn HakalaSampled and proofread
         
            2006-03
            Taryn HakalaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
               ❧ The Supplicacion: That the nobles and comons of Oſteryke made lately by their meſſaungers, vnto kyng Ferdinandus, in the cauſe of the Chriſten Religion.
            Item. The kynges anſwere to the ſame.
            Vvherpon foloweth the wordes that the meſſaungers ſpake vnto the kyng agayne at their departing.
         
         
            
            
            Myles .C. to the Reader.
            
               THis laſt moneth of marche (moſt deare Reader) was delyuered vnto me in the hye Almaynes lāguaige a copie of this preſent ſupplicaciō in prynt, wherof trulye I was right glad: Not onely to heare of ſo many noble men &amp; ſo great a multitude of comen people thus feruently hongring and thirſting after Gods holy worde, but alſo it dyd me good at my hert, to reade of the moſt humble &amp; gentle faſhions, that they vſe toward the ſame. For firſt they rūne not raſhly together on head, nether take they their clubbes in their handes, to bring in Gods trueth by violence, but lowly &amp; with due ſubiectiō ſeke they ſuch cōueniēt meanes, as are of Gods ordinaunce: knowinge, that the cōmen refourmacyon of euery realme

coūtre, or citie, ought to be myniſtred by the office of the king, prince, or ruler of the ſame, and not by anye priuate perſonne. Secondly, whā they haue their anſwere, though they can not obteyne their iuſt ſute, yet make they no murmuringe ner grudginge, but committe their cauſe vnto God, and remayne in their ſupplicaciō. Thirdly, though the kinge be of another mynde, and willeth them to be as popyſh in their beleue as their fathers were afore thē, yet in that behalfe they preferre the worde of God aboue all the preceptes of men, allbeyt they ceaſſe not from prayeng for their prynce, ner frō ioperding their bodies &amp; goodes with him and for him.
            Such holy &amp; vertues enſamples (gentle reader) doth god ſet forth for our inſtruccion, &amp; all to

gyde vs in his right waye, to moue our hertes vnto erneſt repentaunce, to make vs honger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, to plā
               te in vs all louyng obedience, &amp; peaceable behaueour towarde our heades and rulers, &amp; to ſhame thoſe wycked Babilonians &amp; ſedicious Coraites, that diſturbe all ordinaunces of God, euē thoſe murmurers &amp; complayners, that had rather ſitt in Egypte by the fleſh pottes, &amp; to enioye the pleaſures of ſynne for a ſeaſon, then to be refourmed &amp; fed of God in the wilderneſſe. O vnthankfull and flowe bellyes. O where is now among vs ſuch feruentneſſe towarde Gods glorie, ſuch erneſt repentaunce &amp; amēdment of life, as the prophet Ionas deſcribeth in the Niniuites &amp; as this preſent ſupplcacion declareth planely to be in this people?

which though thy cā not be ſuffred to haue Gods trueth ſyncerely preached among thē (excepte it be by ſtealth) yet are they feruent toward his glory, thirſtie after the water of life, waſh their chekes with teares for lacke therof, vnfayned in their requeſt, true &amp; faithfull vnto God and their countre, &amp; euen ready with ten handes (as they ſaye) to receaue a right Chriſtē refourmaciō, &amp; that in al vnite &amp; peaceable behaueour. Lorde what ſhall worth of vs then, that hauyng ſuch delite in oure old wicked cō
               uerſaciō, ſhame not to refuſe all honeſt amēdmēt of lyuinge? Full litle remebre we, that the goodneſſe of God doth call us to repē
               taūce. And what els do mē procure &amp; heape vp vnto thē ſelues by ſuch obſtinate hertes, then the wrath of God agaynſt the greate daye of his appearinge?
            
               Now (gētle reader) that thou mayeſt take ſome edifiēg by this preſent ſupplicaciō, cōſidre thou theſe poyntes therin: Firſt, that for all the multytude of dogges which go againe to their vomite the lord ceaſſeth not yet frō rayſing vp ſome to call vpō his holy name, as thou maieſt ſe here in this people, whom the lord hath turned (as he daylye doth many other moo) vnto his trueth. Secōdly, lerne at their enſāple not onely to deſyre &amp; wiſhe for amēdmēt of all abuſes, but alſo take ſome paynes &amp; labour thy ſelfe in helping therto, and be content to beſtowe thy body and goodes for the ſame. Thirdly, make thy firſt complaynte and ſute to Allmightie God, and then remembre, that in ſeking this precious perle and iewel of refourmacion at the office of the hyer powers,

thou forget not the frutes of humanite &amp; loue. Fourthly though thou canſt not haue thy laufull requeſt, yet leaue not thy dewtie vndone, make no diſturbaunce▪ be peaceable, cōmitte the cauſe to God, ād conſidre, that our ſynfull lyues haue deſerued no better, &amp; that it is euen the heuy indignacion of God, that ſo many Prynces and rulers had rather be diſceaued with ypocrites (as Achab was with his foure hundreth chaplēs) then to haue pitie on their owne ſoules, thē to haue cōpaſſion on their poore ſubiectes, thē to haue Gods glorie ād his holy word to floriſh in their countrees, thē to be lerned be tymes, and to embrace the deare ſonne of God: whoſe wrath whā it is kyndled (as the .ij. Pſalme ſayeth) then bleſſed are all they, that put their truſt in him. Amē
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               ❧The ſupplicacyon, whych the lower countres &amp; cyties of Oſteryke, made by theyr meſſaungers vnto the Kynges Ma. of the Romaynes, Ferdinandus, in the cauſe of the Chriſten Relygyon.
            
               MOſt noble and mightie Prince, oure moſt gracyous ſoueraine Lord, 
                  •
               n moſt hūble wyſe beſech youre royall Ma. the meſſaūgers of your true &amp; faythfull countre, to tendre gracyouſly their vnfayned and hartie meaninge, Supplicatiō and requeſt whych they and their affynyte that haue ſent them, do with inward ſighynge hertes &amp; Chriſtē ſtomakes make continually vnto Allmyghtye God, To the intent

that he maye be prayſed of hys people thorowe true repentaunce, thorow aſſured vndoubted hope, &amp; thorow the ſtedfaſt fayth of his godly worde: To the intent alſo that he maye gracyouſly &amp; fatherly graunt your Royal Ma. a proſperous victory agaynſt the ſoreſt enemye of hys Chriſtendome, and that he maye lende youre grace &amp; youre faythfull countrees a perpetuall peace, accordyng to the hartye requeſt of youre ſayde faythfull ſubiectes. Thys they moſt humbly beſeche youre Royall Ma. to tendre and conſidre, and in moſt gracyous and fatherly wyſe to accepte it, accordyng to the erneſt expectacyon of youre ſayde ſubiectes.
            Fyrſt, the meſſaūgers of youre ſayde faythfull coūtrees do ſignyfye to youre grace with hartye

lamentacyon, that (for all theyr faythfull &amp; contynuall iopardyng of their bodies, goodes and bloude) the deſtruction of youre ſayde countrees is ones ſo manifeſt, that (yf amendement ſhuld not folow thorow the mercye of god) ther is nothing more certayne, then the pyteous wayſtyng and fynall deſolacion therof. And euen ſo muſt it enſue, yf we all from oure whole hertes, do not turne vnto hym by true penaunce and vnfayned receauynge of his godly worde.
            Now for as muche as youre graces ſayde faithfull ſubiectes (of the very naturall loue that they beare toward youre Royall Ma.) are greatly deſyrous and well wylling, to ioperde and beſtow all thier power, that the countre maye remayne to your noble Grace and to youre yſſue,

in good vnderſtondinge, &amp; in all dewties of obediēce vnſeparable, &amp; that youre graces lōdes &amp; people may be helped to their welth &amp; maintenaūce: Seing alſo that of loue which of dewtie we beare toward God &amp; youre grace with moſt hūble &amp; faythfull hertes, we cōſidere not onely the vowe that we fyrſt made vnto God in baptyme touching oure ſynfull lyfe but alſo oure bownden dewtie which we owe vnto youre royal Ma. as to oure ſuperiorite ordeyned of God: And pondrynge lykewyſe oure eternall &amp; temporall lyfe together, we knowlege it oure dewtye to ſygnyfye vnto your hyghneſſe, oure faythfull &amp; true meanyng, how this intollerable burthē &amp; deſtruccion of the coūtre (which is ye very ſcourge of god) may be takē awaye, &amp; euery thinge reſtored agayne

vnto true vnderſtondinge, &amp; as it ought to be. And conſideringe that all oure intent, counſaill &amp; hādling is dyrecte onely to your graces worſhippe &amp; increace of honoure, and to the welth and proſperite of the londe, we truſt your highneſſe wyll moſt gracyouſly accepte the true and faythfull dealynge of youre ſayde coū
               trees, and ſo tendre the ſame, that now, in thys extreme neceſſyte, all ſuch thynges may be taken in hand, as make for the comen peace, and the coūtrees welfare: And agayne, that all ſuch thinges maye be put downe, as geue occaſion to dyſturbaunce and deſtruction of the publyke weale. Vvhych yet can not ſo come to paſſe, vnleſſe your Royall Ma. ſhew it ſelfe in moſt gracyous wyſe towarde youre ſayde countre. And alſo excepte

youre hyghneſſe do fatherly accepte and tendre thys matter, whych they haue proued neceſſary to be a good meane or begynnynge o
                  •
                good thynges to come, &amp; maye turne to the proſperite both of youre hyghneſſe and alſo of the londe.
            For and yf the origenall cauſe of the deſtruction of the coūtre, and the occaſion of the manifeſt ſcourge of God be well wayed, it maye eaſely be perceaued, that it commeth for owre vnrepentaunt ſynfull lyues: &amp; that it foloweth, firſt becauſe we diſpiſe Gods commaundements and his holy word: &amp; ſecondly becauſe that in all eſtates ther is in maner no good politike or cyuile faſhion, but too wilfull a kinde of lyuīge agaynſt all good maners, ordre and right: &amp; by reaſon that in priuate houſkepinge

there is vnmeaſurable waiſtynge and miſpendynge, &amp; no good nurtoure. But the moſt principall occaſion and greateſt offence is, the deſpyſinge of God and his wholſome worde: for the which God layeth this ſcourge vpō vs. For thorowout all the ſtories of the Bible and of the Heythen it is euydent, that Allmightie God puniſhed all Monarchies or empyres &amp; kyngdomes, not ſo much for the dayly ſynnes of the people (to the whyche oure fleſh is naturall geuen) as for ydolatrye and deſpyſing of hys godlye worde. Of this is teſtimonye ſufficiēt the captyuyte of Babylon among the Iewes, whych came becauſe they receaued not the Prophetes, and becauſe they ſet vp a new ſeruyng of God contrary to his worde. This was teſtified alſo at the laſt in their

fynall deſtruction at Hieruſalē which folowed, becauſe they crucified the ſonne of God, and deſpiſed his doctryne.
            The ſame is euydent lykewiſe by the mightie Monarchies (or empyres) or the Aſſyrians &amp; Grekes, which all were ſuppreſt by the Turkes (being firſt but a ſmall ſimple people) and ſet from all their Gods ſeruyces, lawes. dominions, &amp; ſo vtterly deſtroyed, that there is now in a maner no demonſtracion of their Empyre, ſuche worthy punyſhmēt haue they receaued. For ſeinge they wold not embrace allmightie god and his word, but fell from him after they had knowne him, they were therfore cōſtrayned by force to fall in to this deuelyſſhe darckneſſe and captiuite of the Turke. Vvhich bōdage yet neuertheleſſe, Allmyghtye

God dyd not ſodēly ſende amōge them. For ſixe hundreth yeares had the Turcke ynough to do with the empyre of the Grekes, with continuall warre, or euer he cōquered it. But ſeynge that God Almightie dyd thus allure them vnto true repentaunce &amp; to his wholſome word, and they wolde receaue none of hys fatherly monycyons, he therfore ſuffred them to be fynally deſtroyed. Vvherfore yf we cōſidre well the power and riches of the ſayd Monarchies or Empyres (and the famous prudent men that were amonge them) &amp; compare the ſame to the beeſtlye regyment of the Turkes, we ſhall perceaue, that ſens the great floude, there came neuer a ſorer plage vpō the worlde. All which thynges ought indifferently to be wayed of euery Chriſtē hert.
            
               Conſyderinge then that the power and ryches of thoſe Monarchies or Empyres, and the excellent wyſe men whych were in them, myghte not wythſtand ſo ſmall a people as were then the Turkes, onely becauſe they deſpyſed Gods word: For aſmuch alſo as the Allmightie power of God hath now layed this euidēt plage vpon your graces Realme &amp; londe, in ſo much that for oure like tanſgreſſion &amp; vnrepentaūt lyuing, he hath vyſyted youre realme of Vngarye, with the enemies Tyrānye in ſondry terrible maner, as namely in ſpoylinge youre Royall ſeate Buda, (other wiſe called Offen) &amp; with cruell burnynge in this kyngdome of Behem, with horrible infections alſo, death &amp; honger in the lower coūtrees of Oſterike (whēce youre graces moſt noble

progenye dyd ſpringe) beſyde all other aduentures, how manye thouſande Chriſten mens bloud hath bene ſhed now more thē ſixtene yeares, and brought in to beeſtly bondage: Theſe thinges conſidred, what will happen to the thirde and laſt Monarchye or empyre, namely of ye Romaynes, which ouer and beſyde this greate decaye, is alſo in like trāſgreſſion toward God? For the Turke with the other Monarchies or Empyres, hath exalted and increaced his might aboue all Chriſten heades. And out of his proſperous ſucceſſe and victories which he hath had agaynſt the Chriſten, he maye coniecture that he is the ſcourge of God, &amp; that nomā can wythſtande his puniſhmēt. Whē this ſore ſynne then lyeth vpō vs, alas therfore that we will not receaue Gods

worde offred vnto vs▪ ner entre in to true Chriſten repentaūce, how is it poſſible for vs reſiſtyng al good reformaciō, to eſcape this plage, or to defende our ſelues wt the power of all Chryſtendome?
            But ſeinge that the mercye of God hath no ende, and conſyderynge that he requyreth no thynge more of vs, then a ſure hartye truſt in hys wholſome worde: For aſmuch alſo as all kyngdomes and regymētes are made and preſerued by hym, &amp; that to ſet vp a people or head or to deſtroye it, is his onely doinge: And ſeing he hath alwaye offred his godly worde vnto the people from whom he thought to turne his plage and preſerue them, ſo that yf they gaue credēce vnto it, he delyuered them from all euell, as wytneſſe the Niniuites, whyche beleued the

Prophet Ionas: &amp; as teſtyfyeth alſo the kynge of Aſſiria at the preachynge of the Prophet Daniel, which he receaued without folowyng of any new or ſtraūge Gods ſeruyce, conuertyng vnto God, and applyeng hymſelfe vnto repentaunce of lyfe, &amp; ſo was preſerued therby: youre graces ſayde faythfull countre therfore pondryng theſe thinges, knowe none other meane for the delyueraunce of theyr ſoules &amp; bodies, then this, that Gods worde after Chriſten vnderſtandyng be preached euery where, wherby the people may be moued vnto Chriſten repentaunce, and ſo encouraged to withſtonde the Turke.
            The matter then conſyſteth onely in this, that mēs myndes be kepte in ryght vnderſtāding to almyghtye God and their rulers, in true nourtoure &amp; ordynate

lyuyng, and yet neuertheleſſe, the more pitie, an exceadinge erroure is crepte in touchinge the righte true vnderſtondinge of Gods holy worde, wherin youre hyghneſſe (as a Chriſten kyng) hath bene put to ſondrye great paynes now theſe many yeares, to bringe the ſame Scyſme to an vnyte: The matter alſo beynge finally ſo far reſet forth in the laſt aſſemble, that ſondrie articles were diſcuſſed, and a generall peace in the cauſe of Religion concluded vpō, vntill the tyme of farther agrement, which doutleſſe foloweth here of, euē becauſe that manye articles (yea and that the principal) are come to the right Chriſten vnderſtondinge: and alſo becauſe that as touchinge outwarde behaueoure and abuſes crepte in amōge the ſpiritualte, they

muſt in a tyme appoynted, be brought to reformacion, &amp; that by them ſelues.
            But yf this generall peace in in the articles (which ought as Chriſten poyntes to be kepte) do not concerne youre graces ſayd faithfull ſubiectes, or yf a man muſt ſtōde in ioperdy of loſynge body and goodes, whan he kepeth the ſame articles, your Royall Ma. maye moſt graciouſly conſidre, how tedyous a thing it is, and to what inconvenience it will growe. Vvherfore the coū
               tre in moſt hartye and humble wiſe prayeth and beſecheth youre highneſſe, to bringe ſo to paſſe by the ordynaries and all ſprituall offycers, that the holy Goſpel in true Chriſten vnderſtondinge maye be preached, &amp; likewyſe the hyeſt article of oure ſaluaciō: namely, that we haue forgeueneſſe

of ſynnes thorow ye onely merites and death of Ieſus Chriſt: and alſo that the loue of the neghboure and all good workes may be taught as frutes &amp; ſure declaracyons of the inwarde fayth, with the commaundementes of God, for a contynuall true amē
               dement, as for the reſyſtynge of euell ſynfull affeccions or inclynacions, &amp; to geue thankes for this excellent grace, in that we thorowe the onelye merytes of Chriſt, are delyuered frō death &amp; hell, and become children of eternall ſaluaciō: And alſo by occaſiō therof, to rendre all dewties of faithfull obedience to youre Royall Ma. as to the hyer power ordeyned of God, and to ſhew vnto oure neghboures all loue lykewiſe: And ſo to opteyne the rewarde that neceſſarely foloweth out of this faith and out of the

frutes therof, And that the worthy Sacrament of the Altare maye be miniſtred vnto them that Chriſtenly deſyre it, acordinge as it was obſerued certayne hundred yeares in the begynnyng of Chriſtendome. Item that the Ordynaries or ſpiritualtie (acordinge to the determinacion of the laſt Perliament) do put downe all other abuſes in the churches, and brynge thē in to good Chriſten ordre, prouidinge the pariſhes with good honeſt ſoule ſhepardes, &amp; not perſecutinge them which preach Gods worde in other places, as they haue done hitherto. And though the ſame abuſes be ſo ſore rooted, that we ſuppoſe verely it will be hard to refourme them in a ſhorte ſeaſon, yet the ſayde myniſtracion of the ſacrament and preachinge of the

worde (wherin conſiſteth oure ſaluacion, and that ought to be purely done, and vnperuerted) maye not therfore ceaſſe, yea neceſſary is it, that all this be moſt erneſtly prynted in to the people, that thei maye ſo be brought from their rude ſynfull lyuinge and inſtructed vnto right true repētaūce in the faith of Chriſt. For now (the more pitie it is) they are come from all knowlege of God: And many curates there be, which are nothing leſſe thē curates or true ſhepherdes wherbye the comen people are become ſo vngodlye and rude, that it is in maner vnpoſſible to brydle them: And thus commeth it to paſſe, that they dye lyke brute beeſtes without eny Chriſten inſtruction or Sacrament.
            Vvherfore the meſſaungers of youre Graces ſayde coūtrees,

with whole Chriſten myndes, &amp; with ſighing he hertes, moſt humbly beſeche youre Royall Ma: to tendre theſe thinges in moſt gracious wiſe, and as a Chriſten kynge to conſente vnto this waightye article, acordinge to their expectation in youre hyghneſſe: whom they alſo moſt humbly requyre, in no wiſe to thinke, that youre Graces ſayde londe wolde herebye ſeke the more occaſion of diſobedience or of any carnall libertye. For they knowe, that we haue forgeueneſſe of ſynnes in the true vnfayned faith, only thorow the paſſion and merites of Ieſus Chriſt: and that we than in thankfulneſſe for ſuche excellent grace, are detboūd with oure whole hertes to ceaſſe from all ſynfull lyuynge, to bringe forth all good workes in true repentaunce, and alſo with

oure bodies and goodes to declare all wyllinge obedience towarde youre Royall Mageſtie.
            Conſidering now, that for our delyueraunce ther can be none other meane, then to take ſuch a Chriſten life in hand: And ſeynge it is not poſſible for anye man with good hert and fre conſcience to go agaynſt this enemye (which is the ſcourge of God and puniſhment of vs all) vnleſſe he firſt be reconciled to God, and ſure thorow the certayntie of faith and confidence in his godly promes, that he ſhall be delyuered from ſuch plage, and that they ſhall eſcape in this hooſt, which are in daunger eyther thē ſelues or theyr wifes, childern, or other frendes, thorow youre graces generall proclamaciō lately made &amp; commaunded, The meſſaungers therfore of youre

Graces ſayde londe and the parties that ſent them, moſt erneſtly with ſighinge hertes &amp; in moſt humble wiſe, beſeche youre highneſſe for the loue of God, to accepte this their Chriſten and reaſonable ſute moſt graciouſly, ād to promes a generall peace vnto all ſuch as behaue them ſelues acordinge to oure forſayde ſupplicacion and ſute. And then doutleſſe will it come to paſſe, that (yf ſuch a Chriſten life be embraced) Allmightye God ſhall mercifully cauſe this preſent plage to ceaſſe: and ſo ſhall it folowe alſo, that many well lerned and vertuous men ſhall take vpon them the worthy office of preſthode, which then with Chriſtes doctrine ſhall bringe the people vnto true repentaunce, to the feare of God, and to all obedice: And thus ſhall euery man with faithfull

hert towarde youre royall Ma: do his beſt agaynſt this enemye, ād declare all louynge obedience with body and goodes in this and all other thinges.
            Where as the ſayde articles then beynge much more excellently wayed, are comprehended in the concluſion of the laſt Perliament, and ſeynge it hath pleaſed God to make vs youre Graces ſubiectes (which therfore do knowlege youre highneſſe nexte Allmightie God to be oure owne deare Soueraigne lorde, hauynge all expectation of felicite and goodneſſe in the ſame) for theſe cauſes are we in no maner of doubte, but iour royall Ma: in moſt gracious and fatherly wiſe carynge for youre ſayde faithful countrees, will ſuffre them to come in to the ſame eſtate (appoynted in the ſayd concluſion of the

Perliament) and conſente vnto vs here in: Acordinge to oure moſt humble ſupplication, which we make vnto your highneſſe (with continuall ſighinge and teares euen from oure hertes) for the loue of God and for his worſhippe ſake. And here with moſt humblye committe we vs vnto your royall Ma: in all dewtie of louynge obedience, wherbye (to the thankfull recompencinge of ſuch a gracious benefite in youre hyghneſſe) we will beſtowe oure ſelues with our bodies, goodes, and bloude. Geuen, At Prage the .xiij. daye of Decembre. Anno. M.D.xli.
            
               
                  
YOure Graces moſt humble ſubiectes,
The meſſaungers of the lower countrees of Oſterike.

                     Piligram lorde of Bucheym chefe debyte in Oſteryke.
                     Chriſtofer, Baron of Eytzinge.
                     Sigiſmūd Ludwig, lorde of Bolham.
                     Eraſmus, lorde of Starhēberg.
                     Iohan Vngnad, Baron of Suneck, chefe captayne of Steir.
                     Reinprecht lord of Eberſdorf, chefe chamberlayne of Oſteryke.
                     Otto, lord of Lychtenſteyn, chefe marſhall of Kernten.
                     Iohn, Baron of Vveyſprach.
                     George, Baron of Herbſteyn.
                     George, of Vvolmirſtorf, knyght
                     Sigiſmund Vvexelberger, knyght.
                     Chriſtofer Rembſchuſſel, knyght
                     Abel of Kolneck, knyght.
                     Eraſmus Scheyrer, knyght.
                     
                        Balthaſar Gleyntzer, knyght.
                     Bonauenture of Eckē, knyght.
                     George of Berckham.
                     Martyn of Veſtreych.
                     Vvilliam of Bibrach.
                     Erenreich of Rynſperg.
                     Eraſmus Hochelperger.
                     George Memmynger.
                     Achatz Hohenfelder.
                     Vvolfgang Hohenfelder.
                  
                  
                     The names of the cities.
                     Vienna. Gretz. Lyntz. S. Vitus. Steyn. Steir. Rochelſpurg Kornnawenburgh. Lawbach. Ems, Oſterike beneth &amp; aboue the water Aniſus. Kernten. Krain, and the pryncely Erledome of Gortz.
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            The anſwere of the kynges Ma: Of the Romaynes Ferdynandus, to the meſſaungers of the lower partes and cities of Oſterike.
            
               WHereas the appoynted meſſaūgers of the kynges Graces countrees of lower Oſterike haue preſented vnto him a wrytinge (concernynge cauſes of religiō) ſhewinge and declaringe at large, how Allmightie God hath doubtleſſe now this longe ſeaſon ſuffred all theſe plages to come vpon his Chriſten people, aſwell thorow the Tyrānye of the Turcke, as with death and burnynge, becauſe ſubiectes do lyue in no repentaunce, deſpiſinge Gods worde and not receauyng

it, and how that this is the cauſe why ther coulde hitherto no victory be had agaynſt the ſayde archenemi of Chriſtendom, with other moo articles: All the ſame hath the kynges royall Ma. of the Romaynes oure moſt gracious Seueraigne lorde, conſidred, with their humble ſute and ſupplicacyon▪ which is, that it wolde pleaſe his highneſſe to ſuffre them and their affinyte for to come in to the generall peace, which (at the laſt Perlyament) was made in cauſes of religion. And his Ma: hath a gracious &amp; hartie compaſſyon of his ſayde obediēt and faythfull ſubiectes (and that no leſſe then is expreſſed by the meſſaungers in theyr wrytinge) becauſe of the ſayde greuous plages. His highneſſe alſo conſydreth lykewiſe, that the ſame puniſhmētes do folowe

becauſe of the manifold ſynnes and vyces, wherwith Chriſten people are defyled.
            Wherfore his Ma: ſens the begynninge of his raigne hither to, deſyred neuer thinge more effectouſly (nether yet doth) then the aboliſhinge of ſuch manifolde vyces and blaſphemies, as are crepte in (the more pitie) amō
               ge many men of hye and lowe eſtate, yea the longer ye more, wherbye almightie God doutleſſe is moued vnto wrath agaynſt his Chriſten people. And therfore (as it is openly knowne) his Royall Ma. in his graces owne countre hath ſent forth erneſt cō
               maundmentes and proclamacions, and geuen erneſt iniunctions vpon the ſame (ſpecially vnto all preachers &amp; curates) that they in moſt effectuous and diligent wiſe, ſhall exhorte the people

to turne from ſuch ſynnes &amp; vyces, vnto a Chriſten and repē
               taunt lyfe pleaſynge vnto God. Now where as ſuch his Ma: gracious &amp; fatherly monicyon hath not brought forth frute acording to the Chriſtē requeſt of his highneſſe, his Royal Ma. is the more ſorye, and the ſame was the cauſe that moued his grace (now lately at Lintz afore his departinge) to renew the ſayde proclamaciōs, as the meſſaungers thē ſelues do knowe right wel. Againe his Royall Ma. hath neuer denyed hitherto (nether will do hereafter) but that the word of God ſhulde be publiſhed acording to the Chriſten vnderſtonding therof, and preached as it was of the Apoſtles &amp; doctours, which are approued and receaued of the holy Chriſten church.
            His Royall Ma. alſo can not

remembre, that his hyghneſſe hath euer cauſed ought to be taken in hand agaynſt any man that ordreth him ſelfe after the preachinge afore ſayde. Morouer his Ma: offreth himſelfe in moſt gracious wyſe to geue erneſt iniunctions vnto the Ordinaries of ſuch ſpirituall iuriſdiction as extendeth thorow out his graces londes, to make reformacion among the clergie (acordinge to the concluſion of the laſt Perliament) to put downe abuſes, and to prouyde the deſolate pariſhes with good and lerned curates and ſoule ſhepherdes: to the intent that his ſubiectes maye be inſtructe with the true worde of God, &amp; in all other Chriſtē ordinaunce beſide. Likewyſe the appoynted meſſaūgers do knowe well ynough, that for the puttinge awaye of contēciōs in the cauſes of religion, and to

bring the ſame to an vnyte, the kynges Ma: hath taken ſpeciall diligent and erneſt paynes, and that he hath ſpared no trauayle ner laboure at eny tyme: like as his Royall Ma: will likewyſe with all benignite diſpoſe himſelf hencefurth (and is allready of a gracious hope) that acordynge to the cōcluſion of the ſayde Perlyament of Regenſpurgh, this Scyſme maye be brought to an vnyte &amp; agremēt, by one of thes thre waies, that is to ſaye, by a generall counſaill, bi a counſail prouinciall, or els by another comen Perlyament. Wherfore the kynges highneſſe doth right graciouſly truſt &amp; doubteth not, but his faithfull comens &amp; ſubiectes of his lōdes of lower Oſterike (and theſe appoynted meſſaungers of the ſame) wyll tarye and wayte obediently for the ſayde lyklyode of vnyte in the olde

Chriſtē religion, and in the meane ſeaſon not to ſeke ner medle with any alteration or chaunge but in Religion and in all other thinges toward his Royal Ma. to behaue and ordre thē ſelues. as theyr awncient fore fathers haue done toward God and to his Graces noble progenitours in all obedience, and in no wiſe to ſtoppe from ſo doynge, ner to take occaſion of hinderaunce at that peace made at the Perliament of Regenſpurgh: conſideringe that the ſame peace was ordeyned onely betwene both the eſtates of religion the one toward the other, and not betwene the eſtates and their ſubiectes: ſo that vntyll the nexte counſaill generall, nacionall, or comen Perlyament (which within the ſpace of eyghtene monethes after the date of that

concluſion made at the Perlyament of Regenſburgh, ſhall in the cauſe of Religion be proclamed) the catholike ſorte muſt kepe the olde religion: and the eſtates of the proteſtantes muſt holde them vnto it, wherin they were founde at the makyng of the ſayde peace. Which peace the kynges Ma: doth knowlege him ſelfe bounde to manteyne, and therfore will his hyghneſſe in no wyſe permytte his ſubiectes to make anye new alteracyon agaynſt the ſame. This hath it pleaſed the kynges Ma: of a gracious mynd, to ſignifie vnto the ſayde meſſaūgers. Geuē at Prage the xiij. daye of Ianuarij. Anno. M.CCCCC. xlij.
         
         
            
            
               ❧ The Concluſion and laſt ſentence of wordes, that the meſſaungers of the countrees and cities of lower Oſterike, made vnto the anſwere of kynge Ferdinandus
            
               MOſt noble and mightie Prynce, oure moſt gracious Soueraigne lorde: Where as your royall Ma: (vpō oure moſt humble and erneſt ſupplicacyon) hath graciouſly geuen vs a wrytinge touchinge the cauſe of Religion we haue in moſt hūble wyſe conſidred the ſame, and pondred it with Chriſten, louynge and feruent myndes. And allthough we afore, in oure wrytinge haue knowleged (as the glory of God requyreth) that we euery one of

vs, haue deſerued this preſent plage, yet is it mencioned there alſo, that Almightie God (which is the infinite wiſdome) doth ſend theſe ſharpe puniſhmentes, not ſo much for daylie ād corporall ſynnes (which we truſt are not ſo rife in youre Graces londes, as in other countrees and Prouincies) as for the head ſynne of ydolatrie, and becauſe the true commaundementes of God are turned to the honoure ād filthy lucre of men, and for that the word of God is not preached, as God hath taught and commaū
               ded it: For herof ſprange the origenall of all ſuch ſcourge ād plage of God, as it is euydent out of ſondry hyſtories. And for aſmuch then as there hath bene here now this long ſeaſon (the more pitie) great aduerſite and loſſe of victory, and ſo foloweth

on more and more, oure moſt hū
               ble ſupplicacion is (acordinge as we haue be ſought youre Royall Ma: vpon oure knees) that youre highneſſe will for the loue of God haue reſpecte vnto this moſt waightie matter, &amp; erneſtly to manteine the waye of God (as he hath ordeyned and commaū
               ded it) and to geue iniunctions therein. For els verely maye we loke for no proſperite, but be ſure of decaye. Nether do we doubte any thinge at all, but youre Ma. doth graciouſly accepte oure Chriſten ſute in the cauſe of Religiō, as the articles therin are Chriſtenly recyted, and acordinge vnto Gods word. And yet neuertheles in oure countrees are not the preachers permitted to ſhew the worde of God, purely and ſyncerely, but exyled for it, and ſpecially for preachinge

the moſt waightie article of iuſtification or righteouſ makyng, namely, that the remiſſion of ſynnes commeth thorow the onely merytes and paſſyon of Ieſus Chriſt: &amp; that we (onely of thākfullneſſe for this vnout ſpeakeable grace) are dett bounde to lyue in true Chriſten repentaunce as eſchuyng of ſynne, and exercyſynge of brotherly loue and other good workes.
            Vverfore oure moſt humble &amp; erneſt ſupplicacion is, that youre Royall Ma: (acordinge to youre hye and ſuppreme offyce) wyll haue gracious reſpecte here vnto, that the preachers which do ſincerly ſet forth thes articles &amp; the word of God likewiſe in other thinges, maye be ſuffred. For yf the preachers ſhulde by the rulers be baniſhed, or otherwyſe vexed by the meanes herof (as

they be in certayne countrees) &amp; yf youre Graces faithfull comēs and ſubiectes ſhulde be excluded frō the peace of the Empyre, and frō the articles conteyned in oure wrytinge, or ſtonde in daūger by the reaſon therof, your highneſſe maye graciouſly ād fatherly cōſidre, how tedious it will be to the ſame youre Graces faithfull ſubiectes. For we proteſte before God in the trueth, that this oure moſt humble ſupplicacion which we make, is of no curioſyte, ner for anye other intent, thē onely for the honoure of God, &amp; ſaluacion of oure ſoules, &amp; that with all ſubiection. Here with (in hope of a right louing anſwere here after) we committe oure ſelues in moſt humble wiſe vnto your Royall Maieſty, as to our moſt gracious doare ſoueraigne Lorde.
            
         
      
   

