
   
      
         
            King Iames his welcome to London With Elizaes tombe and epitaph, and our Kings triumph and epitimie. Lamenting the ones decease, and reioycing at the others accesse. Written by I.F.
            I. F.
         
         
            
               1603
            
         
         Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00663
            STC 10798
            ESTC S105576
            99841303
            99841303
            5878
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00663)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5878)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:07)
         
         
            
               
                  King Iames his welcome to London With Elizaes tombe and epitaph, and our Kings triumph and epitimie. Lamenting the ones decease, and reioycing at the others accesse. Written by I.F.
                  I. F.
                  Fenton, John, fl. 1603, attributed name.
                  Ferrers, John, attributed name.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  [By R. Read?] for Thomas Pauier,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1603.
               
               
                  Sometimes attributed to John Fenton and to John Ferrers.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-C⁴.
                  Printer's name conjectured by STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Poetry.
               Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Death and burial --  Poetry.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            KING IAMES
HIS WELCOME
TO LONDON.
With Elizaes Tombe and Epitaph,
And our Kings triumph and epitimie.
Lamenting the ones deceaſe,
And reioycing at the others acceſſe.
Gaudia cum lachrymis iungamus, ſeria ludis.
Written by I. F.
            Imprinted at London for Thomas
Pauier. 1603.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ¶King Iames his welcome
to London.
            
               
                  HAyle England? I ſalute thee with a toung,
               By whom thy fortunes with applauſe are ſoūg,
               I greete thee in the pride of all thy boaſt;
               And in thy hope, whereof thou glorieſt moſt.
               Yet, am I not ſo pampered in my ſtraines,
               As to exclude all diſcontented vaines?
               And yet not diſcontented but bewayling,
               The loſſe of her, for whom my pen is fayling.
               Let then Melpom
                        •
                     ne amongſt the reſt,
               Tune models fitting for a greeued breſt.
               Some melancholly intermixt with ioy:
               Hinders that too much mirth not ouercloy.
               Sweete, ſweetely mingled with ſome ſharper taſt:
               Makes that the ſweeteneſſe doth the longer laſt.
               As pleaſing onely fit's the preſent ſeaſon;
               So ſhall our notes complaine not beyond reaſon?
               
                  
Onely we will remember our late Queene,
               Whoſe like before was neuer heard not ſeene.
               Leaſt we forget whom many haue forgot,
               Who while ſhe liu'd we lou'd, but dead, recke not.
               Such is our nature, we no longer care
               For gems, then whiles they ſhew richly and rare.
               Wee fancy ſtraight forgoe within an houre.
               Yet let vs not doe ſo by this faire floure?
               Who was the very honour of true fame,
               In hir did ſhine the light of vertues name,
               Shee was the pride of matchleſſe pietie;
               For feruent zeale ſhe was a dietie.
               She was the hope, wherein true hope did truſt,
               She was the burniſht blade without all ruſt.
               She was the ancour of firme ſetled peace,
               She learnings ſtipend onely did increaſe,
               She was the loue of theſe whom loue did loue,
               In her the Planets of all grace did moue.
               She was the wonder of all forraigne nations,
               For louing truth and hating reprobations. She was,
               Fames pride, hopes ancour, loues loue, wonders wonder,
               From liuing fame, hope, loue, now put aſunder.
               What neede I ſpeake in termes ſo knowne and plaine,
               But in a word vertue did in her raigne;
               In vertuous wedlocke ſhe was true begot,
               Borne, taught, brought vp in vertues throne ſhe ſat.
               
                  
And while ſhe liu'd ſhe gaue God vertuous praiſe,
               And vertuouſlie ſhe ended hath her dayes.
               O happy Iewell whilſt God lent her vs?
               But happier we who haue inioy'd her thus.
               Had we but thought vpon our happie ſtate,
               We would haue more accuſd our hapleſſe fate.
               'Tis not ſo great a pleaſure once to chooſe,
               As hauing chos'n againe his choice to looſe.
               I muſe at thoſe who with a double face,
               Did honour paſt, but preſent times embrace?
               I wonder how theſe Ianus-Scicophants,
               
               Whoſe two toungd mouthes onely colloging haunts?
               Can with ſuch boldneſſe, and ſuch enuies ſtore,
               Seeke to diſgrace her whom they did adore.
               O thoſe who haue an oare for euery boate,
               Whoſe long hang'd toungs with euery thought doth float.
               They which can change their tunes with euery winde,
               And with each gull ſeeme to reſolue their minde,
               What peſt's they are, how much to be reiected,
               Let wiſemen iudge, by whom they are detected.
               Theſe flattering Paraſites, theſe fawning curs,
               (Whoſe policie diſhoneſt dealing blurs)
               Could ſay in times paſt; then the golden time
               Then, then, the golden age did onely ſhine:
               And now can proudly ſpeake, that Saturns prime,
               Was neuer truely till this preſent time.
               
                  
Peace buzzing drones? your humming is harſh muſicke,
               You miniſter dregg's, where is no neede of Phiſicke.
               Confeſſe with ſhame, Elizaes happy raigne
               Will neuer ouer-matched be againe.
               But yet farre be it from my erred ſcooling?
               To make compare with high King Iames his ruling?
               Whoſe wiſedome well I vnderſtand is ſuch,
               As at Elizaes prayſe he will not grutch,
               Whoſe peacefull regiment (as his owne booke ſayes)
               Was neuer matched ſince Auguſtus dayes.
               What neede we ſeeke an author of more worth?
               When by our King himſelfe it is ſet foorth?
               Sleepe then Elizabeth in peace and reſt?
               Sing loud amongſt the Angels with the beſt?
               For in his booke we now thy praiſe may reade,
               Who doth thee in thy ſeate by right ſucceede.
               Now riſe my muſe ſing with a louder voyce?
               And let thy ſong make a more ioyfull noyſe?
            
            
               HAile then King Iames? I greete thee with a toung?
               Euen that whoſe meaning is from duty ſproung,
               Nor can my muſe doe mee a greater pleaſure?
               Rather then ſing thy welcomes without meaſure
               I will by that ſhew how my minde is loyall,
               Elſe ſhould I much forget a Prince ſo royall.
               
                  
Thee to ſalute with clap's of hands, my quill
               Hath now extended euen her vtmoſt skill.
               O that I had but Homer's ancient vaine?
               Making my verſes prayſe my labours gaine?
               And had I elſe but Horace his wits ſprings?
               Singing Maecenas borne of ancient kings?
               Excuſe me yet great prince? Ile reape a gleaning,
               Deuiſing artleſſe welcomes with true meaning.
               Willing to ſhew my willingneſſe of minde,
               Although ability ſmall meanes can finde,
               Ritch is our hope, and our aſſurance great,
               Doubt is expul'ſt, giuing reſolue the ſeate.
               Ignoble breach of promiſe fit's with clownes?
               And kingly promiſes kings and kingly crownes,
               Nor ſhould a Prince harbour a baſe intent,
               Excepting not his ſpeech but what he meant,
               
                  Elizabeth? now I remember thee?
               
                  Richard the third and thou did diſagree?
               She what ſhe promis'd ſhe perform'd, but he
               Vſed naught but breach of word and treachery.
               She? ô me thinkes my pen could neuer ſlide:
               And in her praiſes euer could abide,
               Nor could I euer any other ſing,
               Nor thinke on ought but her, except our king,
               I am ſurpriſed with her Idea ſtill,
               Oft ſtudying how I might augment my skill.
               
                  
Huſht? I am ſilent? I will ſpeake no more?
               Adding no Razors to a new cut ſoare.
               Nor neede I a Phiſition, all prooues eaſe:
               Nought miniſtreth occaſion to diſpleaſe.
               Except much reſt, much peace, much good, much quiet,
               Security and ſafety growes a riot.
               For all the hopes which Papiſtry expected,
               Or elſe the triumphs to reuenge erected,
               Roiſters and murtherers, are cleane put downe:
               Diſpayring, when they heare Iames weares the Crowne.
               Enmity, vproares, hope of ciuill broyles,
               Sedition, mutiny, domeſticke coyles.
               Are now made voide; they haue tooke needeleſſe paine,
               Lurking conſpirators conſpir'd in vaine.
               Leaſt then conſtraint ſhould praiſes due importune,
               Loe thus great King I doe applaude thy fortune.
            
            
               IN ancient times, Kings that poſſeſt this throane,
               Firſt fought to get, then to defend the Crowne.
               
                  Richard the ſecond, that vnhappy Prince,
               By Henry Bullinbrooke was driuen thence.
               But in the third degree, Bullinbrookes race,
               From out the throne the Duke of Yorke did chaſe.
               Great were the troubles, bloody the debate,
               Twixt Lancaſter and Yorke, but more the hate.
               
                  
The Duke himſelfe was ſlaine, but then his ſonne,
               
                  Edward the Earle of March new wars begunne.
               Soone he attain'd his hope, when moſt vneuen,
               Crooke-backe gaue Henries ſoule apaſſe to heauen.
               So dyed the Prophet by the fatall hand:
               Of the remorſeleſſe butcher of this land.
               After whom, Yorkes heire, Edward was proclaimed,
               And by the fourth of that name he raigned.
               But yet in trouble, hazard, doubt, and feare,
               For mocking VVarwick, that firſt brought him there.
               Whom when he had o'rethrowne, and liu'd in peace:
               Yet could not priuate grudge, and enuie ceaſe.
               His brothers ſcorn'd his marriage, ſcoft his Queene,
               For that of higher bloud ſhe had not beene.
               Enuying his iſſue after him ſhould ſway:
               But Richard Gloſter made them ſure away.
               And for an eaſier paſſe his will to further,
               His elder brother Clarence firſt did murther.
               And after Edwards death (the King his brother)
               The two young Princes he in the Tower did ſmoother.
               When loe he got the crowne: but with what feare?
               When he had got it he the ſame did weare?
               And with what tyrannie? well it is knowne,
               And in the Chronicles moſt plainly ſhowne.
               Till worthy Richmond, pittying Englands ſtate,
               Sued for his owne, reſolu'd to trie his fate.
               
                  
When he in battayle ouerthrew this deuill,
               And looſed England from a peerleſſe euill.
               Hee married Edwards daughter, ioyn'd in one
               
                  Lancaſter and Yorke, the houſes of renowne.
               Th
                     •
                  n was all peace concluded, all ſtu
                     •
                  s ceaſed,
               Contention grew faint, onely truce increaſed:
               In time of which, this worthy Richmonds Earle,
               Had two young Princes, and one Princely gerle.
               
                  Margret by name, from out whoſe lineall race
               Thou didſt diſcend, and iuſtly claim'ſt thy place.
               Enioy it to thy ioy: gladly confeſſe:
               How from thy Font run ſtreames of happineſſe?
               For Kings which I haue named, firſt attain'd
               Their ſeats with blood, and ſtill in feare they raign'd.
               Yea Richmonds worthy ſelfe ſate not ſo ſure:
               But traytors ſtill rebellion did procure.
               And Henry his ſucceſſor (though renown'd)
               Sought how to make his weake religion ſound.
               When with much toyle he did from England baniſh,
               The Popiſh crew, whoſe fraud like ſmoake did vaniſh,
               Leauing his heire in Proteſtancie learned:
               Who after his deceaſe the ſame confirmed.
               But ſoone was he cropt off, ſuch was his courſe,
               Death had on peereleſſe Edward no remorſe.
               When after him, came Mary to the crowne,
               Religion then, and former rites went downe.
               
                  
Sword, death, blood, fire, ruled then this Ile,
               No gracious fortune lent a gracious ſmile.
               Trouble on trouble, griefe did weigh downe griefe,
               In vaine the guiltleſſe cride, without reliefe.
               Till God our former libertie did inlarge:
               Yeelding the Scepter to Elizaes charge,
               Who whiles ſhe ſway'd it ſway'd it with like hand,
               As did Titania ſway the Fairie land.
               Whome Poets faine a Virgin pure and chaſt,
               As by the name of Goddeſſe ſhe was graſt.
               Then faire Eliza, as bound by dutie,
               Receiue this lateſt farewell to thy beautie.
            
         
         
            A ſorrowfull Epitaph on the death
of Queene ELIZABETH.
            
               
                  
                     HEere lyes ELIZA dead, who liu'd in fame,
               
               
                  Conſum'd in body, but refreſht in name.
               
               
                  Shee liu'd to age a glaſſe, to youth a mirror;
               
               
                  Vnto her friends a ioy; to foes a terror.
               
               
                  Shee was the Souldiers captaine, the law's life,
               
               
                  The Churches deereſt ſpouſe, the Churchmans wife,
               
               
                  Learnings greene Lawrell, vertues chiefe refector:
               
               
                  Peaces maintainer, onely Truths protector.
               
               
                  The Orphants parents, and the ritchmans ſtay:
               
               
                  The poore mans comfort, and the nights cleere day.
               
               
                  
                  The tradſman fauorer, and the marchants gaine;
               
               
                  The ſea mans night ſtarre, and the lyers ſtaine,
               
               
                  The pride of all her ſex, all womens boaſt:
               
               
                  The worlds wonder, that they wondred moſt;
               
               
                  The Courtiers glory, entertaining all
               
               
                  Louers of truth young, old, in generall.
               
               
                  She dy'de bewayld, ſhe iuſtly liu'd admir'd,
               
               
                  Her body ſunke her ſpotleſſe ſoule aſpir'd.
               
            
            
               THus (King) the troubles haue I open layde,
               Which in the times of former Princes ſwayde:
               How happy then art thou? who with ſuch peace
               Haſt entered Englands front? whiles turmoyles ceaſe.
               Thou art applauded by the vulgar route:
               Who put to flight the thoughts of former doubt.
               Loe London hath held ope her willing armes:
               To ſhadow thee from falſe conſpired harmes,
               What they indeuour, onely is to finde,
               How they with Pageants may content thy minde.
               The Northren gates fly ope to entertaine
               A happy guider to a happy raigne.
               The buſie ſcholler throwes aſide his booke.
               Glutting his halfe ſuncke eyes at thee to looke.
               The Marchant lets his getting gaines goe by:
               Finding more hope of gaine within thine eye.
               
                  
The ſouldier lets his weapons now to ruſt:
               Nor to the ſpilling of more blood dooth truſt,
               But pleaſeth moſt in peace, and craues a place
               Whereas he may behold thy princely face.
               The plowman leaues his oxe to graſſe, whiles he
               Thy countenance indeuoureth to ſee.
               The poore artificer now growes ſo bolde
               To ſlacke his worke, thy preſence to be hold.
               The Gentleman, the matron, maide, and wife,
               The aged man, and youth, prayes for thy life,
               The nobleman, the comminalty, and all
               Reioyce at ſight of thee in generall.
               The Phonix that of late fled to the skies
               Hath left her aſhes, from whence doth ariſe
               Another Phoenix, rare, vnmatcht, vnpeered,
               Vnto whoſe loue, loue is it ſelfe indeered.
               Then welcome (noble Iames) with my owne voyce:
               Thinke thy whole monarchy ioyntly reioyce.
               More welcome neuer Sylla triumph't Rome,
               Then (mighty King) thou dooſt to London come.
               O now ſuch Prophets as in ancient times,
               Foretolde of things to come (in broken rimes)
               Me thinkes ſuch ſouth-ſayers ſhould againe reuiue,
               Telling how happily Englands choyce ſhould thriue.
               O would my toung auguriouſly could ſpeake?
               Or into fortunate predictions breake?
               
                  
That I might Merlin like foretell ſuch things,
               Whoſe iſſue truth to follow ages brings.
               Yet rightly this I boldly dare avow:
               
                  England was neare eſtabliſhed till now.
               Now may we proudly boaſt we neede not feare,
               We haue a King, and this ſame King an heire
               A toward Prince (if fame be true) or rather
               A vertuous ſonne ſprung from from a vertuous father.
               Long may he liue, a furtherer of our ioy,
               And when he raignes, raigne ſtill without annoy.
               Bleſt be his match, his iſſue ſo increaſe,
               As we may ſtill inioy an endleſſe peace.
               By which we may tryumph thou tookeſt in hand,
               The gouernement of this our Engliſh land.
               So as the Romanes Romulus did call,
               The firſt foundator of their City wall.
               Or as Aeneas Latines term'd to be,
               The chiefeſt father of their progeny:
               And firſt found Captaine of their Italy:
               Or Bruite the Patron of our Brittany:
               So after ages may in time to come,
               Call thee the Romulus of their Engliſh Rome,
               Thou ſhalt be our Aeneas the firſt grounder,
               Of all our ſetled ſtay, our hopes firſt founder.
               We thinke nor Samothes, nor on Bruits name:
               But attribute their entrance to thy fame.
               
                  
For as ſome worthy man which hath effected,
               Some worke of charity, or a houſe erected.
               To loue imploy'd in ſome religious vſe:
               Where vertue may be paiz'd without abuſe.
               As he (I ſay) is highly to be praiſed,
               And haue his worth with glorious trumpet raiſed.
               Yet if the ſame decay and with much charge,
               Another do the ſame againe inlarge.
               Then is the benefactor onely thought,
               The onely ſole foundator and as oft.
               As it decayes and is repai'd, by lot,
               The laſt is praiſed, the former is forgot.
               Yet ſure 'tis better ſurely once to found it,
               Then many times vncertainely to ground it.
               Euen ſo (great prince) it doth befall with thee:
               For well we now coniecture thou art he.
               Who art the benefactor to our land,
               Who when it would haue fallen thou mad'ſt it ſtand.
               For as for Samothes, we let him paſſe,
               Nor doe we call to minde what Bruite once was:
               But thee we thinke to be the very ſame,
               That didſt not onely chaſe but kildſt the game.
               We thinke thee mortall, ſubiect to the ſtroake,
               Of ſure vnpartiall death, and to his yoake.
               But yet we hope thy iſſue will ſo ſtretch,
               As that it will euen to the worlds end reach.
               
                  
For we haue neither cauſe to doubt or moane,
               But now may build our houſe of lime and ſtone.
               Fulfild the Prophecie is now at laſt,
               The fleete of Norway is both come and paſt.
               Then frolicke England, ſport in lawfull games,
               Make roome to entertaine matchleſſe king Iames,
               
               Shine bright with bonfires: let Bels ring aloude,
               And of our fortunes let vs all be proude?
               Trumpets fill all the ayre with your high voyce,
               And let the Cornets make a ſweet ſhrill noyſe.
               Mourners put hence your weeds of black: put on
               Garments of Red and Yellow your backs vpon.
               Let vs no more deſpaire? lets ſeeke to pleaſe,
               Our fate is firmer then chaunce can diſeaſe.
               I muſt confeſſe that in Elizaes prime,
               We neuer did enioy a happier time.
               But yet we were vncertaine, how our ſtate
               Might after her diſceaſe be wrongd by fate.
               Shee was a Maiden Princes, and her life
               Was neuer faſhion'd to be chriſtned wife:
               But now (O bleſſed now) we haue a King:
               From whom both grace, peace, hope, and heires doe ſpring.
               A King like to the Sunne, whoſe courſe doth ſtay,
               Darkned to night, but ſhines againe next day.
               Or for his iſſues certaintie, I dare
               His off-ſprings firmneſſe to the Moone compare.
               
                  
Who hauing long time gloriouſlie aduaunſt,
               Hir choiſeſt brightneſſe, and a great while daunſt,
               Within the ſpherie circle of the skie,
               Doth mildly at the laſt decreaſe and dye.
               Yet not ſo vtterly extinguiſhed,
               As that ſhe is for euer dim'd and dead,
               But ſhe at length at euery open view,
               Doth riſe againe, and former light renew.
               So may thy heires continue, though by courſe
               Death crops them one by one, without remorſe,
               Yet the one dead, the other ſhall ſucceed,
               And as the old doth die, the young ſhall breed.
               Whoſe race (if like to thee) may ne're be done,
               Before there be an end of Moone and Sunne.
               Thus much (high Prince) I doe prognoſticate,
               As one fore-tolde by an aſſured fate.
               The firſt beginning, likewiſe waranſt the ending,
               Thy fortunes will be happily extending-
               
                  Eliza died in Winter, left the Spring,
               To entertaine (with greater ioy) a King.
               At whoſe arriuall, loe the trees do bud,
               Saying our fruites in harueſt will prooue good:
               The Nightingale doth ſing, ſo chirps the Larke,
               The aged Oakes put on a freſher barke,
               The day growes longer-ag'd, the night growes old,
               Withering by flouriſhing is now contrould.
               
                  
Looke how the Vine who hath a great while droopt,
               Looke how the Graſſe who hath a great while ſtoopt:
               Looke how each flower long time withered?
               And looke how all theſe haue freſh colours gathered?
               Who onely doe reioyce to this intent,
               That they might gratulate thy late aduent.
               If therefore Plants and birds haue watcht their ſeaſon:
               Far much more cauſe haue men which haue more reaſon.
               If God to ſenceleſſe things ſuch turnes appointed?
               Shall not we greete him whom God hath annointed?
               O yes, come let vs ring a peale of thankes?
               Setting aſide all toyiſh minicke prankes?
               And let vs ſeriouſlie imploy our toungs
               With crying welcoms, ſinging ioyfull ſongs.
               That euery ſillable may diſtinctly ſound:
               And like an Ecchoes voyce againe rebound.
               No doubt it is a pleaſure to a King:
               To ſee his ſubiects welcoms to him ſing.
               So (mightie Iames) do thine, as doth appeare
               By all the troopes which are aſſembled heere.
               See how in cluſters they march through the ſtreets,
               To welcome (louing) thee with loyall greets.
               London growes proude this wiſe to entertaine,
               And thee within her maiden walls containe.
               Looke how the Engliſh nation thether ſwarme?
               As like a Hiue to keepe the Bee from harme.
               
                  
The Bee, the matchleſſe Bee, that brings ſuch hony,
               Whoſe like can ne're be found for gem nor mony.
               He that brings honie to the emptie hiue:
               By whoſe whole induſtrie ſlothfull we thriue.
               Which to requite, thy rewarde is the hearts,
               Of all thy ſubiects, which their loue imparts:
               The aged matron, and the ancient men,
               Doe as it were aſſume their youth agen.
               Onely to welcome thee, and with one voyce
               In loue and zeale all ioyntly to reioyce.
               Yea which is more, the babes by tokens greete thee:
               And as by ſignes of loue in loue doe meete thee.
               Giuing to Maieſtie his lawfull dew:
               As propheſing of gladneſſe to enſue.
               Wherefore haile (worthy King) the end ſhall proue,
               How much our dutie will diſplay our loue.
               And for thy care, onely our obedience
               Shall be a meanes to make thee recompence.
               Our tender of thy health, our loyaltie,
               Shall ſhew how we adore thy royaltie.
               Our long and tedious ſtreets, ſhall ſeeme but ſhort:
               The length of way ſhall be beguild by ſport.
               The day in pleaſure ſhall be ſpent, the night
               In pleaſing ſlumbers ſummon ſhall the light.
               So ſhall thy long breath'd iorney be repaide
               With ſweete delights, and wearineſſe allaide.
               
                  
Kinde wholeſome ayres ſhall wihſper in thine eare,
               And wary guard chaſe all ſuſpect of feare.
               As ſleepes the Larke ſafe in the hollow ground:
               Voyd of ſuſpition euer to be found.
               So ſhall thy guarders thee from harme protect,
               Vaine ſhall they ſtriue who giue cauſe of ſuſpect.
               The greedy Dogge in Aeſop vainely ſnatch't at,
               When as the ſeeming piece of fleſh he catcht at.
               The fooliſh cur that at the Moone did lurke:
               Or he that tooke the sky as a faire marke.
               To ſhoote at, was deceiu'd, ſo both in vaine,
               Did take an idle and a thankeleſſe paine.
               So (honour'd Maieſty) I thinke twill be,
               With thoſe that aime at ſuch a marke as thee.
               I meane thoſe traitors, who through enuies ſpight,
               When moſt they fawne, doe chiefely fawne to bite.
               And yet when all is done, their owne intent,
               Still proues vnto their owne deſtruction bent.
               I ſpeake not that I iudge or know of any:
               Although the like haue hapned oft with many.
               But what I ſpeake my duty doth me mooue,
               And I am linked with a bond of loue.
               Who ſeemed to Darius more amorous,
               Then Beſſus? yet who proou'd more trecherous?
               Whoſe loue to Caeſar euer ſeem'd more ſound,
               Then Brutus? yet who gaue a deeper wound?
               
                  
So often fal's it out that deereſt friends,
               Be they that moſt malicious hate pretends.
               AEgiptian theeues are ſaid for to imbrace men,
               That they with leſſe ſuſpition might downe race them.
               So Philiſt's low in hope at length to ſtrangle,
               And they who ſeeme moſt ſpruce oft times moſt wrangle.
               But why ſtand I vpon ſuch points preciſe,
               When (King) I know thy ſelfe art far more wiſe.
               Experienced how to auoyd allures:
               Whoſe hony curteſie but gall procures.
               I am to fond: yet King ſuppoſe my loue,
               And inward duty doth theſe paſſions mooue.
               No paſſions, but integrity, and zeale,
               Tendering by thy welfare the common weale.
               For why? vpon thy ſafty doth depend,
               The publicke loſſe, thy loſſe, thy health our friend.
               Thou art the Sunne that melt's our Winter ſhewers,
               The pleaſure that mak'ſt ſhort the tedious houres
               The hope of all our ſpring, our Authums crop:
               Our faulters crutch: our onely ſtay and prop.
               Thy gladneſſe is our ioy, thy ioy our gladneſſe,
               Thy ſorrow is our griefe, thy griefe our ſadneſſe.
               And if thou ſhouldſt miſcary (which far be it,
               That euer any ſubiect liue to ſee it.)
               We likewiſe then are fruſtrated, and loſt:
               And like a maſtleſſe ſhip amid'ſt waues toſt.
               
                  
Thou muſt be our ſhips maſt, our ſun-ſhines day,
               Our Spring, our authum, and our pleaſing May.
               What we delight in, muſt be to behold,
               The bloſſom's of thy vertue vncontrould,
               Thy peacefull gouernement muſt our chiefe hopes nouriſh,
               And like to watred plants vnder thee flouriſh.
               Much like to wandring ſheepe which ran aſtray,
               From out their limits of their wonted way.
               Or like to ſouldiers that haue marcht headlong:
               And in diſordered troupes togeather throng.
               The firſt becauſe a ſhepheard they did lacke,
               The laſt for wanting Captaines went to wracke.
               Euen ſo in very like ſame caſe ſhould we,
               Runne without order, were it not for thee.
               Thou art our kingdomes ſhepheard, and our guide,
               A breſt plate and a captaine to our ſide.
               Now as for Rome, or proud inſulting Spaine,
               We holde contemptible in high diſdaine.
               We feare no threatning of our forraine foes,
               But are moſt ready preſt to worke their woes.
               Then let vs all reioyce, and once againe,
               And euer bid Iames welcome to his raigne.
               Then welcome (map of worth) behold my pen,
               Is armed with the greeting tongues of men.
               Who with a liuely noyſe throw vp their caps:
               Filling their harts with ioy their hands with claps.
               
                  
All crie God ſaue thee. Poets with their quil's,
               To welcome thee, haue ſhowne their chiefeſt skils.
               An on heroyicke art man, more to grace thee,
               Drawing thy diſcent, with former Kings doth place thee.
               Another with Encomius doth praiſe thee,
               And with a Princes meriting trumpe doth raiſe thee,
               Another in a ſouldiers wiſh doth greete thee.
               Another ſends his welcomming looke to meete thee.
               Another weeping, yet in teares reioyced,
               Others in Eligyes laugh when thou art noyſed,
               Another bids thee welcome in Englands name,
               In thy ariuall another tells the ſame.
               Another with great ioy doth gladly ſing,
               
                  His aue Caeſar: or God ſaue the King,
               Another in Melpomenes weeping teares,
               Euen at thy name abandons former feares.
               Another cries out againſt Atropos,
               
               For ſweete Elizaes death, and Delias loſſe.
               Yet ioying in thee, another all to torne,
               Greets thee'n a garment thats by ſhepheards worne.
               A proper worke of learned Poetry?
               Of Oratory: Proaſe? and Heraldry?
               A rare conceited piece of worke no doubt?
               Whoſe ſharpe conceite younger conceites doth flout,
               Well he is learned, and were I but able,
               He ſhould eate bread from out Auguſtus ſtable.
               
                  
But many worthier Poets more beſide,
               With health and happineſſe may thee betide.
               And limping I come laſt: amongſt the reſt,
               Wiſhing like welcoms to thee with the beſt.
               Though I vnable yet this giues reliefe,
               To welcome thee aſſwageth former griefe:
               I muſt confeſſe, my Pen hath tooke a nap,
               But newly in the Muſes ſugred lap.
               The firſt it dropt was teares, but my reflection,
               Soone gaue her weeping notes, a ſweete refection.
               Which to regreet, the laſt and leaſt it kept
               To ſalutations, and no more it wept.
               But being almoſt dull, amaine it cride:
               Haile Kingly Iames, foes terror, Englands pride.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

