
   
      
         
            The worth of women
            Ferrers, Richard.
         
         
            
               1622
            
         
         Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00699
            STC 10832
            ESTC S118347
            99853554
            99853554
            18941
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00699)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18941)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 885:12)
         
         
            
               
                  The worth of women
                  Ferrers, Richard.
               
               [56] p.   
               
                  Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse streete,
                  London :
                  1622.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Richard Ferrers.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-C D⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Women --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Celeste NgSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Celeste NgText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
THE WORTH OF WOMEN.
            
               LONDON, Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-croſſe ſtreete. 1622.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, VERTVOVS AND TRVE RELIGIous Dame, the Ladie ANNE WENTWORTH.
            
               MAruell not Madam that I haue made choice
               Of you amongſt all other Princely Dames,
               Whoſe ſecret vertue challengeth each voice,
               And my poore zeale beyond all ethers flames.
               The firſt oblation of my morning Muſe,
               Lo here I offer at your ſacred Shrine:
               Which if you pleaſe but graciouſly peruſe,
               And ſanctifie with thoſe pure ſtarres diuine,
               Whoſe radiant rayes and bright reflecting flame,
               May purifie the moſt impoliſht rhime:
               And bearing but the Liuery of your name,
               Shall liue, deſpight the cankred iawes of time,
               And flouriſh like the euerliuing Bay,
               When monuments of Marble ſhall decay.
               
                  Your Ladiſhips humble and deuoted ſeruaut,
Richard Ferrers.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the curious Readers.
            SVſpend your iudgements, cenſure not in haſte:
            But ere you iudge the firſt, firſt ſee the laſt.
            
               
                  May 28. 1622.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE WORTH OF WOMEN.
            
               1
               MY infant Muſe that ſlept in ſilence long,
               Reſolu'd no more her vntun'd notes to ſing,
               Aſham'd to heare the ignominous wrong,
               Detracting idle heads did daily bring
               Vpon that noble ſexe of women-kinde,
               Prepar'd her ſelfe ſome Antidote to fince.
            
            
               2
               Within an humble valley where ſhe lay,
               That was with loftie hils inuiron'd round,
               Through wch a pleaſant chriſtal brook did play
               With pibble ſtones that roled on the ground,
               Where chirping birds melodiouſly did ſing,
               To entertaine the ſweet refreſhing Spring.
            
            
               3
               There Philomela did bewaile the rape
               Of wicked Terius that inceſtuous King:
               And louely Laeda in her Swan-like ſhape,
               Hid her blacke foote vnder her ſnowie wing.
               The mateleſſe Turtle you might alſo ſee
               Sit mourning by vpon a Willow tree.
            
            
               
               4
               Vindictiue Progne by her ſelfe alone,
               Vpon an old decayed Trunke did keepe,
               Vnder the which Halcyone did moane
               Vpon a buſh, whoſe dolefull note was, Weepe;
               And Pyres daughters in thoſe pleaſant vaies,
               Would oft be chattering prety wanton tales.
            
            
               5
               From hence among the lowly Mirtle boughes,
               Oretopt with Pines and loftie Cedars tall,
               She pearcht her ſelfe and made a ſtately rouze,
               Wherewith a quill ſhe from her wing let fall,
               Intending now to take a higher flight,
               She bids me make a pen, ſit downe &amp; write.
            
            
               6
               Which I obeying, had no ſooner done,
               But all the carping-critick-ſquint-eyd rout,
               Like dogs to carion did about me runne,
               And fortie faults in twentie words found out:
               Each ſeuerall humour muſt his cenſure giue,
               And at their verdict I muſt die or liue.
            
            
               7
               Their great god Momus did no ſooner ſpie
               My books rich title, but in heart repining,
               Began to draw his goodly mouth awrie,
               As if his worſhip had on Plaice bin dining;
               Reades ſome few lines, &amp; in a furious ſnuffe
               Caſts it aſide, and ſweares 'tis ſimple ſtuffe.
            
            
               
               8
               Which Zoilus ſtraight ſnatcheth vp againe,
               And viewing but a vertuous womans name,
               Cries, fie vpon this poore mans ſilly vaine,
               To reade his booke, it were a burning ſhame:
               Whereat the rout of giddie headed geeſe,
               Did all beſtow at leaſt a word a peece.
            
            
               9
               One cries, a woman is compoſde of feather;
               Another ſweares, their faith is like the winde;
               A third, their zeale is made of froſtie weather;
               The fourth, a chaſte one neuer yet could finde.
               A fig for theſe, ſince better ſpirits know,
               Saue ignorance, true knowledge hath no fo.
            
            
               10
               Emboldned thus my daring Muſe goes on,
               Attir'd with naked Truths vnſpotted robe,
               And Eagle-like beholds the dazeling Sunne,
               Euen in the Apogean of his globe,
               To teach theſe Criticks that haue err'd in this,
               To know hereafter what a woman is.
            
            
               11
               Know then the woman, God did firſt create,
               And with the man in Paradiſe did place,
               Was for an helpe when he was deſolate,
               Coequall with him in the ſtate of grace.
               Out ſtrait cries the multitude, 'twas ſhe:
               That pluckt the fruit frō the forbidden tree.
            
            
               
               12
               Euen heere this rable haue deuiſ'd a lie,
               The Serpent pluckt, ſhe gaue the man to eate,
               VVho had free will this weake attempt to flie,
               Knowing the heauy vengeance God did threat
               VVhat time ſoeuer hee this fruite did taſte,
               That he ſhould die the death &amp; be diſplac't.
            
            
               13
               Which ſurely followed, for when God did call
               For Adam as he vſually had done,
               He now perceiuing his moſt wretched fall,
               From his all-ſeeing preſence would haue run
               But finding no eſcape, cry'd out, and ſaid,
               I heard thy voice O Lord and was afraid.
            
            
               14
               VVhy haſt thou eate of the forbidden tree,
               Which I cōmanded thee thou ſhouldſt not ſtir,
               He ſaid the woman hath deceiued me;
               She pleades the Serpent had beguilled her:
               Whē God in iuſtice ſaw their fault was euen,
               Both with a curſe from Paradiſe were driuen.
            
            
               15
               Yet ſhortly after ſee how God did bleſſe,
               Obedient Sarah, Abrahams faithfull wife,
               And fruitfull made her aged barrenneſſe,
               Euen in her latter dying daies of life:
               A ſon ſhe doth conceiue within her wom be,
               From whom ſhall Kings, &amp; realmes, &amp; nations come.
            
            
               
               16
               A bleſſed mother of a choſen ſonne,
               VVith whom the Lord hath promiſed he will
               Eſtabliſh his couenant now beguune,
               VVhich Iſack is ordained to fulſill
               And as with him ſaith God I haue decreed. Gen. 24 25.
               
               So after him for euer with his ſeed.
            
            
               17
               This promiſe God inuiolate will hold,
               Which to confirme he doth Rebeccha chuſe,
               A vertuous woman more eſteem'd then gold,
               Whom Iſack for his wife doth not refuſe:
               From Eſau ſhe the bleſſing did obtaine,
               To Iacob where the couenant doth remaine.
            
            
               18
               And as to Iſack, ſo did God prouide
               For Iacob faithfull women full of zeale, Gen. 29. 30.
               
               
                  Rahell and Leah are to him affi'de,
               With whom the Lord moſt graciouſly doth deale:
               For being barren, by their prayers conceiue,
               Childrē, which they vnto ſucceſſe ſhal leaue.
            
            
               19
               Though wicked Pharoh ſtrictly did command Exo. 1.
               
               The Mid wiues all men children to deſtroy,
               This practiſe they would neuer take in hand,
               But did his vild iniunction diſobey:
               And durſt no child of his deare life depriue,
               But fearing God, preſeru'd them all aliue.
            
            
               
               20
               Whereat the King with anger them purſues,
               Saying, How durſt you my cōmandmēt break?
               Which matter they ſo wiſely did excuſe,
               As that the King had not a word to ſpeake.
               Wherfore God proſper'd thē in all things wel.
               And built thē houſes wherin they might dwel.
            
            
               21
               Now ſee how God miraculouſly wrought, Exod. 2.
               
               By Pharohs daughter this poore child to ſaue,
               Who vnto her by ſtratagem was brought,
               Euen by the mercie of a ſenſleſſe waue:
               She fearing nought her fathers ſterne decree,
               Gaue ſtraight cōmand, it ſhould preſerued be.
            
            
               22
               And by the ſecret prouidence of God,
               This infant to his mother doth commend;
               The miracle effected by his rod,
               His poore oppreſſed people to defend:
               The Oceans parting teſtifieth moſt,
               Wherein did periſh Pharoh and his hoaſt.
            
            
               23
               Behold, the Lord a woman chuſeth out,
               In all the towne, his ſecret Spies to hide; Ioſ. 2.
               
               Who being ſtraight examin'd thereabout,
               With conſtant zeale ſhe ſeruently denide,
               And cloſely them into a roofe conuayd,
               Who otherwiſe their liues had ſurely payd.
            
            
               
               24
               And euen about the deadeſt time of night,
               Out at a window ſhe doth them conuay,
               And to the woods aduiſd them take their flight,
               That ſo the ſpies might miſſe them on the way:
               For wch good deed (as God had thē inſpir'd)
               They faithfully performe what ſhe deſir'd.
            
            
               25
               His care of women he doth here expreſſe, Exo. 22.
               
               With ſpeciall charge the widowes to defend,
               And not to hurt the children fatherleſſe,
               For I ſhall heare (ſaith he) their cries aſcend;
               Then with ye ſword I wil your liues bereaue,
               And children orphants with your widows leaue.
            
            
               26
               A moſt renowned woman next we find, Iudg. 4. 45.
               
               A famous Iudge and ſacred Propheteſſe;
               She vnto euery Iſraelite aſſign'd
               His equall portion, were it more or leſſe:
               Vnder a Palme in Ephraim ſhe abode,
               And iudg'd according to the will of God.
            
            
               27
               To field ſhe doth the Prophet Barak call,
               Againſt the King of Canans mightie band,
               Foretelling him that Siſera ſhould fall;
               For God will ſurely giue him to thine hand.
               And Barak anſwering, ſaid, I will not go,
               Except thou likewiſe go with me alſo.
            
            
               
               28
               Then Deborah with Barak went along
               Vnto mount Tabor where a while they ſtay,
               Till Siſera with men and chariots ſtrong,
               Did call him downe where Deborah did ſay
               To Barak, feare not, God for thee doth fight
               And Siſera this day ſhall put to flight.
            
            
               29
               But to a woman he ſhall giue the fame,
               For thy weake faith, which elſe thee was due
               The wife of Heber, Iael was her name,
               That with a naile this famous Captaine ſlue:
               For which the Lord hath ſaid, ſhe ſhalbe bleſt
               Aboue all women that in tents doe reſt.
            
            
               30
               Thus God deliuered Canan to the hands
               Of Iſrael, to Deborahs great fame,
               Who while their townes depopulated ſtands,
               An happy mother ſhe to them became,
               For many kings went forth with her to fight
               And Iſraell grew happy in her ſight.
            
            
               31
               A cheerful ſong ſhe with the King doth ſtrait,
               Vnto her God with warbled notes record, Iudg. 5.
               
               Hearken ô Kings giue eare you Princes great,
               The mountaines melted from before the Lord:
               Yea euen Sinai at his voice did melt,
               The heauens did drop, the earth his thunder felt.
            
            
               
               32
               The wife of Monoah being barren long,
               God by his Angells moſt diuinely bleſt,
               With ſuch a ſonne as is not found among
               The Nazarites with heauenly ſtrength poſſeſt:
               Where with he ſhal begin to break the bands
               And Iſraell ſaue from the Philiſtians hands.
            
            
               33
               Now Monoah, (as the Angell did commaund)
               Vnto the Alter with his offering came,
               Where while it burnt, his wife &amp; he did ſtand,
               The Angell loe aſcended in the flame:
               And Monoah told his wife there ſtanding by
               We haue ſeene God and wee ſhal ſurely die.
            
            
               34
               The faithfull woman comforts him and ſaies,
               And if the Lord intended vs to kill,
               He would not then accept the thanks &amp; praiſe
               Wee offer here according to his will:
               Now God did bleſſe this child to be a man,
               And made him mighty in the hoſt of Dan.
               
            
            
               35
               Of Naomy and Ruth what tongue can tell, Ruth. 34.
               
               The tender loue they each to other beare,
               Together would they goe, together dwell,
               Together they the Lord did ſerue and feare:
               Together they would laugh, together cry,
               Together liue, and eke together die.
            
            
               
               36
               And Naomy with feruent zeale did pray
               Vnto the Lord, that of his mercie great,
               He would on Ruth his louing fauour lay:
               Who heard her prayer from his tribunall ſeate,
               And graciouſly his bleſſings he beſtowes,
               As ſhe was gleaning in the field of Boez.
               
            
            
               37
               A mightie man with riches great poſſeſt,
               VVhom God inſpired with an ardent flame
               Of faithfull loue, which could not be ſuppreſt,
               Vntill an husband he to Ruth became:
               Frō whō (by his decree, whoſe acts are wiſe)
               A bleſſed generation doth ariſe.
            
            
               38
               A liuely patterne of rare faith indeed, 1. Sa. 1.
               
               In barren Hannah we may here behold,
               With teares which frō a contrite heart proceed,
               Vnto the Lord ſhe doth her griefe vnfold,
               VVith feruent prayer ſhe might a ſon obtain,
               Vowing to giue him to the Lord againe.
            
            
               39
               God heard her praier, and granted her requeſt,
               She doth conceiue and eke bring forth a ſonne,
               Wch brought her diſcontēted thoughts to reſt,
               She magnifide the Lord for what was done:
               And to the Altar where all knees do bow,
               She brought the child, &amp; there performd her vow.
            
            
               
               40
               A true Idea of a vertuous wife,
               In Abigail is worthily expreſt, 1. Sam 25.
               
               VVho by her wiſedome ſau'd her husbands life
               From Dauids iuſt reuenge, and all the reſt,
               Whē he had vowd of Nabals houſe, there ſhal
               Not one be left to piſſe againſt the wall.
            
            
               41
               And ſhortly after, God did Nabal ſmite
               VVith ſickneſſe, whereof preſently he died:
               Then Dauid ſaid: Bleſt be the God of might,
               That hath my hands to ſhed his blood denide,
               By her aduice, whoſe loue he now purſues,
               And for her vertue to his wife doth chuſe.
            
            
               42
               Vnſpotted Tamar in a brothers power, 2 Sam. 13.
               
               On whō ſhe thought ſhe might her life depend,
               Whilſt he inhumanely did her defloure,
               See how ſhe mourns for what ſhe cānot mend:
               Her clothes the rent, &amp; duſt &amp; aſhes throws
               Vpon her head, thus deſolate ſhe goes.
            
            
               43
               
                  Bathſheba by the Prophet is inſpir'd,
               To moue the King that Salomon might raigne 1. Kin. 1.
               
               Alone (no doubt) the higheſt heauens deſir'd,
               Ordaining her the ſubiect to obtaine:
               VVhich well appear'd by his diuine ſucceſſe,
               God did with wiſedom, riches, honor bleſſe.
            
            
               
               44
               So rare that from the wild Arabian ſouth,
               The Queene of Sheha iournied many daie s, Kin. 10.
               
               To learne ſage wiſdom frō that ſapie nt mouth
               To her immortall euerlaſting praiſe:
               Wch whē ſhe did with wonder great behold
               She gaue him ſpices, precious ſtones &amp; gold.
            
            
               45
               And bleſt, ſaith ſhe, be God which doth delight
               In thee O King, and of his mercy great,
               That ſo his people may be iudg'd aright,
               Hath thee inueſted in the iudgment ſeate:
               This womā ſhal (ſaith God) in iudgment riſe Luk. 11. 10. 31.
               
               Againſt thoſe people did their Lord deſpiſe.
            
            
               46
               How highly God of women doth eſteeme,
               The widow of Sarepta ſheweth plaine, 1. Kin. 17.
               
               Wch widow poore ye Lord doth worthy deeme
               The holy man Eliah to fuſtaine:
               When famine ſore the country did oppreſſe,
               By miracle he doth this woman bleſſe.
            
            
               47
               A little oyle ſhe had within a cruſe,
               And meale likewiſe to make a cake withall,
               VVhereby herſelfe ſhe iuſtly doth excuſe,
               Vnto the Prophet who for bread doth call:
               Loe this is all is left my ſonne and I,
               VVhich I am dreſſing, we may eate and die.
            
            
               
               48
               
                  Eliah ſaid, woman be not afraid,
               Make firſt a cake and bring it vnto me,
               The meale is in thy barrell God hath ſaid,
               Nor yet the oyle ſhall euer waſted be,
               Vntil the time the Lord doth ſend forth raine
               The earth with plenty to poſſeſſe againe.
            
            
               49
               And ſhe vnto Eliah brought a cake,
               Then for her ſelfe &amp; ſonne did likewiſe dreſſe,
               And many daies did this prouiſion make,
               And yet her meale and oyle was not the leſſe:
               And to confirm her faith ſtil more &amp; more,
               Her ſonne deceaſt, he doth to life reſtore.
            
            
               50
               An other widow ſtraight the Lord hath found
               On whom he doth moſt plenteouſly beſtow, 2. Kin. 4
               
               A miracle for euer to be crown'd,
               Her veſſells all with oyle doth ouerflow:
               And ceaſed not vntill the woman ſaid,
               My veſſells all are full, and then it ſtaid.
            
            
               51
               Then came ſhe to the man of God, and told
               The bleſſings which ſhe had receiu'd that day,
               
                  Eliah ſaid, ſtraight let the oyle be ſold,
               Wherewith thou mai'ſt thy creditors go pay:
               And as the Lord this day thy ſtate hath bleſt
               So keepe thy ſelfe &amp; children with the reſt.
            
            
               
               52
               The faithfull Shunamite deſerueth well,
               To be recorded with this ſacred crue,
               Who did the holy man of God compell,
               To eate with her at euery ſeaſon due:
               And ſeriouſly her husband doth inuite,
               To build a roome, where he might lodge all night.
            
            
               53
               Wherefore Eliah prayed vnto the Lord,
               She being barren, and her husband olde,
               To make her fruitfull, and he doth accord,
               The Prophet cald the Shunamite, and told:
               For this good deed, wch thou to me haſt done
               Thou ſhalt conceiue, &amp; eke bring forth a ſon.
            
            
               54
               And in due time this miracle was wrought,
               By his great power, that rules the ſtarrie skie,
               A ioyfull ſonne into the world ſhe brought,
               Which ſhortly after happened to die:
               Hereby to ſhow his loue doth neuer ceaſe,
               To life he doth this child from death releaſe.
            
            
               55
               What title ſhall I giue this happy Queene,
               Whoſe ſacred worth, her ſtate doth far exceed, Heſt. 14
               
               No eare hath heard, nor wādring eye hath ſeen
               An act more bloudy, then is here decreed:
               Her people all ſhould be deſtroyd and ſlain,
               Whoſe prayer and faſting did their liues obtaine.
            
            
               
               56
               Of Prouinces one hundred twenty ſeuen,
               The Iews ſhould die, the King had giuē &amp; ſeald
               Which was oppoſed by the powerfull heauen,
               And at this gracious Queenes requeſt repeal'd:
               And to a ſhamefull end the man ſhe brought
               That ſhould this bloudy maſſacre haue wrought.
            
            
               57
               Thus Heſter by the Lords out ſtretched arme,
               Who neuer failes them that in him doe truſt,
               Preſeru'd her people from this wofull harme,
               And brought their foes euen down in the duſt:
               For as they thought ye Iewes to deale withall,
               The ſame reuenge vpon their heads did fall.
            
            
               58
               When Sarah whom her fathers maides diſpiſe, Tob. 3.
               
               Was ouercome with hearts oppreſſing griefe,
               Vnto the Lord for ſuccour ſtrait ſhe flies,
               Who heard her prayer, &amp; granted her releife:
               And husband of his grace, he doth ordaine,
               Wch into mirth, her mourning turn'd again.
            
            
               59
               If wiſdome, valor, worth, and zeale were loſt, Iudith. 13.
               
               And this rare patterne onely did remaine,
               The world can ſcarce, of ſuch another boaſt,
               Whereby it might redeeme them all againe:
               Who by her prayer, obtain'd from Gods high hand,
               To ſaue a Cittie, and preſerue a Land.
            
            
               
               60
               Firſt duſt and aſhes on her head ſhe throwes,
               And all in ſackcloth ſhe doth faſt and pray,
               Then into Olofernes campe ſhe goes,
               Where ſhe this famous Captaine doth betray:
               With courage ſtout, &amp; wiſdom rare ſhe vſ'd,
               His head ſhe brought, wch al the land excuſ'd.
            
            
               61
               Then did ſhe call the Elders of the Towne,
               Saying behold what God for you hath done,
               With ſtately wreathes, they did her ſtraight way crowne,
               And euery where with ſhoutes of ioy did run:
               The riches great of Olofernes tent,
               With one accord they doe to her preſent.
            
            
               62
               Thus while ſhe was extold, and magnifi'd,
               Whom euery eie with wonder did behold,
               Vnto the Temple of the Lord ſhe hi'd,
               And off'ring all this wealth of plate and gold:
               With humble zeale before the Alter bowes,
               Vnto the Lord, &amp; thus perform'd her vowes.
            
            
               63
               A mirrour of a chaſt religious wife,
               Is faire Suſanna, being fore diſtreſt,
               Who rather choſe to looſe her deareſt life,
               Then yeild vnto the Elders vild requeſt:
               Loe thus reſolu'd, aloud for helpe did cry,
               And falſe accuſ'd, ſhe is condemned to die.
            
            
               
               64
               But ſee how God did graciouſly prouide,
               To ſaue this woman by a childes decree,
               Who did the Elders ſeuerally deuide,
               And found them both in ſeuerall tales to be:
               For wch vnworthy deed, their liues they pay
               To her great honor, who they did betray.
            
            
               65
               A woman more then wonderfull behold,
               Whoſe reſolutions ſo vndanted are,
               As by no earthly power, can be control'd,
               More permanent then any fixed ſtarre
               Within the Spheare, of that celiſtiall round,
               To whom fames trumpet giues the loudeſt ſound.
            
            
               66
               Seuen ſons ſhe had, who by the Kings cōmand,
               Becauſe they would not his beheſts obey,
               To violate the cuſtome of their land,
               Were all adiudg'd their deareſt liues to pay
               By ſundry tortures, which ſhe ſeeing plaine,
               Imboldned them, ſtill conſtant to remaine.
            
            
               67
               When ſix of them, the Tirant had deſtroy'd,
               He wild his mother, moue the ſeuenth to turne
               That ſo he might this cruell death auoid,
               In ſtead whereof, ſhe bids him boldly burne:
               And Martyr-like, the Tirants rage defie,
               Thus with his brothers he doth brauely die.
            
            
               
               68
               Like Hecuba for death of Pryam old,
               The mother now all tearmes of life defi'd,
               VVith courage greater then Sheuola bold,
               And thus this euer honored Martir di'd:
               Where we wil leaue thē to ye world to mourn,
               And to our Grandame Eue, againe returne.
            
            
               69
               And there behold, the race poore man had run
               VVhen God &amp; Angells did him both forſake,
               Fit for precipice thou wert vndone,
               And could'ſt no way, a good attonment make:
               Till this rare creature thou diſpiſeſt ſo,
               VVas choſen out, to mittigate thy woe.
            
            
               70
               Aſſiſt me now ye ſacred Siſters nine, Luk. 1. 10. 27. 28. 29. 30.
               
               That I with reuerence may her praiſes ſing,
               VVho was elected by the powers deuine,
               A ſanctifi'd and bleſſed birth to bring:
               VVhen man to ſin was ſubiect, &amp; to thrall,
               Became a ſweet redemption for vs all.
            
            
               71
               For euer bleſſed be that glorious name,
               Which God &amp; Angells haue pronounced bleſt
               Frō whoſe deare loins, our happy Sauiour came
               That to the world brought loue, ioy, peace and reſt:
               And did not ſpare his precious bloud to ſpil
               Condemned mans ſaluation to fulfill.
            
            
               
               72
               All honor praiſe and glory due be done,
               To her whoſe ſeed hath conquered death &amp; hel
               A happy mother of a royall ſonne,
               Before whoſe throne, ſhe doth in glory dwell,
               Where ſhe with Angells, &amp; Ark-angells ſings
               Sweet haleluiah to the King of Kings.
            
            
               73
               This bleſſed woman if I could not find,
               An other ſubiect to defend their caſe,
               Might well perſwade men, if they were not blind,
               With enuious malice, vold of humaine grace:
               To ſtriue as much, their honor to maintaine
               As they purſue thē with ſuch foule diſdaine.
            
            
               74
               A ſecond Mary doth this firſt ſucceed, Mat. 28. Ioh. 20. Mar. 16.
               
               Whoſe loue &amp; zeale, throughout the world is ſpred
               The teares would make a marble heart to bleed,
               VVhich for her deare deceaſed Lord ſhe ſhed:
               Deep plung'd in woes, in ſorows great oppreſt
               Her minde amaz'd, her ſences diſpoſſeſt.
            
            
               75
               In this ſad paſſion to the place ſhe goes,
               VVhereas ſhe thought our bleſſed Sauiour lay
               No pen ſo dolefull can expreſſe her woes,
               VVhen ſhe perceiu'd the body ſtolne away,
               A freſh ſhe wept, &amp; down her head ſhe hung
               Like lapwings yt are robbed of their yong.
            
            
               
               76
               The precious ointment yt with her ſhe brought,
               That glorious body to imb
                     •
                  lme and keepe,
               She nought reſpects, ſince it was gon ſhe ſought
               She ſighes &amp; ſobs, &amp; doth not ceaſe to weepe:
               Like Niobe this wofull womans feares,
               As if ſhe would diſſolue herſelfe in teares.
            
            
               77
               Then came the good Apoſtles to the graue,
               Frō whēce they foūd his corpes cōuai'd away;
               Feareing the Iewes, were glad thēſelues to ſaue
               And ſoone return'd, not daring long to ſtay:
               Whē 
                  Mary ſtil ſtood weeping at the tombe
               And would not ſtirre for deaths moſt cruell doome.
            
            
               78
               But down her head ſhe bowed into the graue,
               Scarce giuing credit to her wofull ſight,
               Where loe at either corner of the caue,
               She ſaw an Angell cloathed all in white:
               Whereat agaſt ſhe would a ſide haue ſtept,
               Had they not ſpake &amp; aſkt her why ſhe wept.
            
            
               79
               For him I wept, ful fraught with greife ſhe ſaid,
               Whoſe like on earth, ſhal neuer more be foūd,
               VVhom curſed Iewes moſt cruelly betray'd,
               And now haue ſtoln him frō this bleſſed groūd
               They comfort her, &amp; ſay, thy teares refraine,
               For he thou ſeek'ſt, is raiſ'd to life againe.
            
            
               
               80
               But ſhe continues ſtill her wofull cheere,
               And to her woes no comfort would allow,
               Vntill our Sauiour did himſelfe appeare,
               And aſkt her, woman, wherefore weepeſt thou:
               She taking him, the Gardner ſure to be,
               Said ſir, if thou haſt hid him, giue him me.
            
            
               81
               And Ieſus anſwered, Mary, I am he
               Thou ſeekeſt ſo, wherefore be not afraid,
               Goe to my brethren, and report of me,
               That thou haſt ſeene, &amp; heard what I haue ſaid:
               And will them into Galile to goe,
               VVhere I will ſhortly meete with them alſo.
            
            
               82
               Twixt greife and ioy ſhe ſtood amaz'd a while,
               Then downe ſhe falls, and worſhips at his feet,
               And with a louing entermixing ſmile,
               VVith teares of mirth ſhe doth our Sauior greet
               And to perform his wil with reuerence due,
               She roſe, ſhe went, ſhe ranne, ſhe rather flue.
            
            
               83
               Vntill ſhe came where the Apoſtles were,
               Deep plung'd in ſorow, &amp; with griefe oppreſt,
               To whom ſhe did this ioyfull newes declare,
               All ſhe had heard and ſeene, ſhe there expreſt:
               VVhich done, ſhe ſtrait returned back to find
               The company that ſhe had left behind.
            
            
               
               84
               Another ſacred Mary with her came,
               And with them alſo many women more,
               For ſaue the Apoſtles (to their laſting fame)
               VVere none but women did his death deplore:
               Earely they roſe before the breake of day,
               Meaning frō thence to take the corps away.
            
            
               85
               A fourth moſt ſacred woman of this name,
               Doth with the reſt preceding well agree,
               A woman filled with religious fame,
               At Ieſus preaching ſhe would euer be:
               In humble maner, ſeated at his feete,
               To heare his wiſdome, &amp; his doctrine ſweet.
            
            
               86
               Her ſiſter Martha muſt not be forgot, Ioh. 11. 15.
               
               A moſt renowned woman full of faith,
               Whoſe loue vnto our Sauiour ceaſed not,
               And as the holy Scripture plainly ſaith:
               Chriſt Ieſus likewiſe loued them againe,
               Whō men would ſeem ſo ſlightly to diſdain.
            
            
               87
               One only brother theſe two ſiſters had,
               Who accedentally fell ſicke, and di'd,
               But hearing Chriſt was cōming, they were glad
               For on his power, theſe women much reli'd:
               Which did alay, and mittigate their griefe,
               Hoping by him, they might yet find releife.
            
            
               
               88
               
                  Martha went forth her louing Lord to meete,
               And humbly proſtrate at his feete ſhe fell,
               Saying ô Lord, and my redeemer ſweet,
               Hadſt thou bin here my brother had bin well:
               But this I know vndoubted truth to be,
               What ere thou askeſt, God will giue it thee.
            
            
               89
               Then Ieſus ſaid, thy brother ſhall ariſe,
               Yes at the reſurrection Lord know,
               I am the reſurrection he repli'd,
               Both of the liuing and the dead alſo:
               Who this beleife ſhall ſtedraſtly retaine,
               Though he were dead, yet ſhal he liue again.
            
            
               90
               Beleiu'ſt thou this? Lord I beleeue it all,
               And that thou art, that Sonne of God now ſent
               That ſhould redeem poore ſinful man frō thral
               If he beleeue, becomming penitent:
               O rare beleife, and faith of women kind,
               Proceeding from a pure vnſpotted minde.
            
            
               91
               Then backe ſhe came and did her ſiſter call,
               Who haſtely went forth her Lord to meete,
               And with an heart oppreſt with griefe doth fal
               With bitter teares before her Sauiours feete:
               And with a mournful voice, O Lord ſhe cri'd
               Had'ſt thou bin here my brother had not di'd.
            
            
               
               92
               Be preſent with me euery wofull wight,
               Whō doleful griefe hath turn'd to duſt &amp; mold,
               Euen in your ſaddeſt, &amp; moſt mournfull plight,
               Let me your gaſtly viſages behold:
               I may expreſſe the agonie he felt,
               And marble hearts into compaſſion melt.
            
            
               93
               VVhen in the ſpirit he did grone with paine,
               VVhich did his ſad and heauy heart moleſt,
               How with a troubled ſoule he gron'd againe,
               Oh wherewith can his torments be expreſt:
               VVho could not be diſburthned of his cares,
               Vntill his paſſion burſt it ſelfe in teares.
            
            
               94
               Oh ye mine eyes to conduit pipes would turne,
               I might his teares perpetually deplore,
               VVeepe ſinfull man, &amp; do not ceaſe to mourne
               Chriſts tears, although thou neuer weptſt before
               Shed now a teare from thy obdurate eye,
               Or elſe hereafter be for euer dry.
            
            
               95
               In this ſad plight vnto the tombe He went,
               VVhereas deceaſed Lazarus was laid,
               VVhere firſt he pray'd to God which had him ſent,
               Then Lazarus come forth, alow'd hee ſaid,
               who ſtrait came forth, boūd hand &amp; foote alſo
               Chriſt willed them to looſe and let him goe.
            
            
               
               96
               Who can expreſſe the faithful thanks they giue
               To magnifie this miracle he wrought,
               Whereby they ſaw their deareſt brother liue,
               Which was a worke impoſſible they thought:
               With ioyfull harts they doe not ceaſe to ſing
               Continuall anthems to their heauenly King.
            
            
               97
               Now ſhortly after Ieſus came againe
               To Maries houſe as he had done before,
               With heauenly ioy ſhe doth him entertaine,
               Who for her brother lou'd him more &amp; more:
               And as at meate with Lazarus he ſat,
               Vnder the table to his feete ſhe gat.
            
            
               98
               Whereon ſhe doth a coſtly oile beſtow,
               VVherwith ſhe waſht thoſe euer hallowed feet. Ioh. 12.
               
               Too pure ſhe thought on mortall groūd to go,
               And kindly giues him many kiſſes ſweet:
               Not knowing how ſhe ſhold her loue declare
               This done ſhe takes and wipt them with her haire.
            
            
               99
               But his Diſciples murmuring, him told
               This precious oile ſhould be eſteemed more,
               VVhich for 3 hundred pence might haue bin ſold,
               And better far bin giuen to the poore:
               But Ieſus ſharply them rebuking ſaid,
               Let her alone, why trouble you the maid.
            
            
               
               100
               The good that ſhe had done he doth vnfold,
               Saying, the poore ſhall daily on you call,
               But me you ſhortly ſhall no more behold,
               She brought this balme to bury me withall:
               Where ere mē preaching ſhal ye Goſpel name,
               This ſhalbe ſpoken to her laſting fame.
            
            
               101
               The faith of women all men may behold,
               As in this following ſubiect well appeares,
               Who had a bloudy iſſue long, and could
               Receiue no helpe by phiſicke many yeares:
               Beleeued if ſhe might leſus garment touch,
               She ſhould be whole, her faith &amp; zeale was ſuch,
            
            
               102
               With this ſtrōg hope ſhe thruſt into the preaſe, Mat. 15:
               
               And touching but his very garments hemme,
               Immediatly ſhe felt the iſſue ceaſe,
               O famous faith, in eſtimable iemme:
               He knowing what was done, lookt back to ſee,
               And miſſing her, askt who hath touched me?
            
            
               103
               But ſhe that knew, what miracle was wrought,
               VVith feare and trembling at his feete did fall,
               And for his mercies ſake, ſhe him beſought,
               To pardon her, and therewith told him all:
               He ſaid O woman, with a voice moſt free,
               Great is thy faith, and it hath ſaued thee.
            
            
               
               104
               Next ſee the woman that in Canan dwelt,
               By faith beleeues his mercies to obtaine,
               How earneſtly ſhe with our Sauiour dealt,
               Haue mercy on me Lord, ſhe cri'd amaine:
               And heale my daughter being ſore perplext,
               VVho with a diuell cruelly is vext.
            
            
               105
               He heard her well, but did no anſwer make,
               Till his Diſciples ſaid, ſend her away,
               She followed ſtill, and would not him forſake,
               Though he to her with bitter words did ſay:
               It is not lawfull woman I ſhould giue,
               To dogs the childrens bread whereby they liue.
            
            
               106
               True Lord ſhe ſaid, and yet the dogs doe eate,
               The croms which from their maſters tables fal,
               And ſtill for mercy ſhe doth him intreate,
               VVho wondred at her faith, and ſaid withall:
               O happy wight with heauenly faith inſpir'd,
               Be it vnto thee as thou haſt deſir'd.
            
            
               107
               And in yt houre her daughter was made whole,
               Vnto her euerlaſting ioyes increaſe,
               VVith faith as ſtedfaſt as the fixed Pole,
               According to his will ſhe went in peace:
               Oh faith moſt rare, ye like hath not bin found
               Worthy in leaues of marble to be crown'd.
            
            
               
               108
               The ſinfull woman of the cittie Nain,
               Doubts not by faith but ſhe ſhal purchaſe grace Luk. 7.
               
               And weeping at his backe ſhe doth remaine,
               A little while in moſt perplexed caſe:
               Then down ſhe falls, and with a ſea of teares
               His feete ſhe waſht, and wipt them with her haires,
            
            
               109
               Anointed them, and gaue them many a kiſſe,
               VVhere at the Phariſe in himſelfe did ſay,
               VVhere he a Prophet, as men ſay he is,
               Hee'd know this ſinner, and not let her ſtay:
               When Ieſus knew his thought, Simon ſaid he,
               There is a queſtion I muſt aske of thee.
            
            
               110
               A certaine lender, lent a little ſumme
               To one; and to another lent a great,
               But neither able when the time was come
               To pay: forgaue them both their ſeueral debt:
               Now which of theſe think'ſt thou, will loue him better?
               He anſwered, I ſuppoſe the greater debter.
            
            
               111
               VVell haſt thou ſaid, our Sauiour then repli'd,
               Seeſt thou this woman that by faith is led,
               Yet ſince I came, thou neither didſt prouide
               To waſh my feete, nor yet anoint my head:
               She hath done both, no kiſſe of thee I got,
               Thy faith is great, ô woman goe in peace.
            
            
               
               112
               Wherefore this woman thou doſt here behold
               Whoſe firme beleife, and conſtant faith is ſuch,
               As by no mans expreſſion can be told,
               Hath much forgiuen her, for ſhe loued much:
               To her he ſaid, from ſin I thee releaſe,
               Thy faith is great, ô woman go in peace.
            
            
               113
               
                  Elizabeth old Zacharias wife, Luk. 1.
               
               A rare example wherein men may ſee,
               The bleſſing followeth a religious life,
               A faithfull woman ſhe is found to be:
               Whom God the Father by his Angells bleſt,
               In barren age, and with a ſonne poſſeſt.
            
            
               104
               A child adopted of his ſpeciall grace,
               And ſanctifi'd euen in his mothers wombe,
               Elect to goe before his glorious face,
               And propheſie that he ſhould after come:
               To ſtrengthen thoſe whoſe faith was weake and fraile,
               The glory of his people Iſrael,
            
            
               115
               Old Anna then a ſacred Propheteſſe,
               Who ſerued God with faſting night and day.
               Came forth and did her bleſſed Lord confeſſe,
               While yet within his mothers armes he lay:
               Redemption preacht, to her immortal fame,
               To all that did beleeue in Ieſus name.
            
            
               
               116
               VVhen as our bleſſed Sauiour did caſt out,
               The feind wher with ye dumb man was poſſeſt, 
                     
                        •
                     k. 36.
               
               Incompaſt with a misbeleeuing rout,
               Whoſe wicked thoughts their euill minds moleſt:
               To whom whilſt he did wholeſome doctrine preach,
               Which to amend their ſinfull life did touch.
            
            
               117
               A certaine woman lifted vp her voice,
               And ſaid the wombe had bleſt &amp; happy lucke,
               That broght thee forth, &amp; let thoſe paps reioyce
               Which in thy infants daies did giue thee ſucke:
               This faithfull woman he doth well approue,
               Among the reſt with deere and tender loue,
            
            
               118
               VVhich loue he doth moſt manifeſtly ſhow,
               By miracles he wrought from day to day,
               Firſt vnto Peters mother he doth goe, Mat. 8. 14. 15. 16.
               
               Where of a feauer very ſicke ſhe lay:
               And meerely of his grace it doth him pleaſe
               To cure her of that dangerous diſeaſe.
            
            
               119
               The Ruler then moſt humbly him beſought,
               To heale his daughter in extreameſt neede,
               VVho now was at ye point of death he thought, Mat. 9. 23. 24. 25.
               
               And ere he came the maide was dead in deed:
               But Ieſus vnto Iairus ſpake and ſaid,
               Beleeue thou only and be not afraid,
            
            
               
               120
               And forth with into Iairus houſe he goes,
               VVhere did attend him many weeping eies,
               The multitude firſt out of doores he throwes,
               Then to the maide he went and ſaid ariſe:
               And ſhe aroſe with feare and wonder great,
               He ſtrait commanded they ſhould giue her meate.
            
            
               121
               The woman like wiſe that was eighteene yeares
               Tormented with a moſt infernall ſpirit,
               Bound altogether as moſt plaine appeares,
               And could by no meanes lift herſelfe vpright:
               Our Sauiour ſeeing ſtraight way did appeaſe,
               And freely freed her of that ſtrong diſeaſe.
            
            
               122
               He had compaſſion of the widowes teares,
               The which at Nain in Galile he did meete, Luk 7. 10. 13. 14.
               
               For her dead ſonne expreſt with many cares,
               VVho now to death had pai'd his lateſt debt:
               In ſuch a meaſure he could not refraine,
               To raiſe to life, and giue him her againe.
            
            
               123
               The Phariſes and Scribes vnto him brought,Iob. 3.
               
               The woman in adultery was found,
               T'intrap him ſaid, by Moſes law ſhe ought,
               For to be ſtoned dead vnto the ground:
               But Ieſus ſaid, let him that hath no ſinne,
               To execute this vpright law begin.
            
            
               
               124
               Whereat they all began to ſteale away,
               Leauing her ſtanding by her Lord alone,
               VVho turn'd a out, and vnto her did ſay,
               VVoman, where now are thy accuſers gone:
               No man is left ſhe ſaid, was here before,
               And I accuſe thee not, go ſinne no more.
            
            
               125
               His loue to women neuer can be told,
               See how he doth the widowes mite commend,
               Aboue them all that offered pearle and gold,
               Saying from ſuperfluitie they ſpend:
               When ſhe poore wight from penury was glad,
               To offer to the Lord euen all ſhe had.
            
            
               126
               
                  Ioanna with Suſanna, and the reſt,
               For there were with them many women more
               The which our bleſſed Sauiour diſpoſſeſt?
               Of wicked ſpirits, being vexed ſore:
               Wherefore moſt gratefully they him beſought,
               He would accept the ſubſtance they had brought.
            
            
               127
               Now laſt of all, as to the croſſe he goes,
               To finniſh there his deareſt virall breath,
               A multitude of people ſaw his woes,
               But none ſaue women did lament his death:
               They weepe and waile, with ſhreekes and piteous cries, Luk. 1. 3 27. 28.
               
               As if they would pull vengeance frō ye skies.
            
            
               
               128
               Vpon thoſe curſed misbeleeuing Iewes,
               Their bleſſed Lord and Sauiour did betray,
               And for reuenge on thoſe that thus abuſe,
               This holy Lambe, they neuer ceaſe to pray:
               Such gracious loue they did frō him obtain,
               They know not how to ſhow their loue againe.
            
            
               129
               And after his deceaſe, the Apoſtles found
               Moſt vertuous women ſtill in euery place,
               
                  Priſcilla was a woman much renown'd.
               VVho taught Apolloes rare &amp; heauenly grace:
               For as this good Apoſtle plainly ſaith,
               She tooke him home, &amp; made him ſtrong in faith.
            
            
               130
               Saint Peter alſo doth as much commend,
               
                  Tabitha for her charitable deeds,
               Of almes that ſhe vnto the Lord did lend,
               Which frō her loue vnto good works proceeds
               Who being dead, by prayer he doth obtaine Act. 9.
               
               She is reſtored vnto life againe.
            
            
               131
               Behold what wonders God by womē wroght, Act. 16.
               
               As holy Paul doth worthily declare,
               To Macedon he is by viſion brought,
               VVhere thoſe yt heard him only women were:
               'Mongſt whom with admiration he doth tell
               Of Lydia, who there did purple ſell.
            
            
               
               132
               A ſaithfull woman, one that God ordain'd,
               To ſaue a kingdome by her good deſert,
               VVho in the ſeruice of the Lord remain'd
               For it is ſaid God opened her heart:
               And ſhe beleeu'd our words &amp; was baptiz'd
               With all her houſhold as we them aduiſ'd.
            
            
               133
               This done we were determined to goe,
               Along the coaſts to make ſome further tryall,
               But ſhe coniur'd vs not to leaue her ſo,
               Her earneſt ſuite would ſuffer no deniall:
               And lo together as we went to pray,
               A certaine virgin met vs on the way.
            
            
               134
               Poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of diuining,
               By which her maſter much aduantage got,
               To vs ſhe was with feruent zeale inclining,
               And for her maſters proffitt cared not: Act. 16. 16.
               
               She follow'd vs and cride, theſe men are they
               That to ſaluation teach the ready way.
            
            
               135
               And many daies continued in the ſame,
               Till Paul was grieu'd for her, and turn'd about,
               And to the Spirit ſaid in Ieſus name,
               I charge thee from this woman get thee out:
               And it obey'd that all commanding power,
               Departing from her at that inſtant houre.
            
            
               
               136
               An other woman he doth ſtraight recite,
               He did in Athens at his preaching find. Rom. 1. 16.
               
               Cald Damaris a moſt beleeuing wight.
               VVith whom Triplena may be wel combin'd:
               
                  Triplena doth with Perſiis well accord,
               All faithfull women labouring in the Lord.
            
            
               137
               Amongſt this crue he highly doth commend,
               
                  Phoebe a ſeruant of the Lord ſaith he,
               For whom he doth vnto his brethren ſend,
               That in the Lord we might receiued be:
               And ayded by them in what ere ſhe needs;
               For ſhe hath done moſt charitable deeds.
            
            
               138
               The bleſt Euangeliſt Saint Iohn doth write,
               Vnto a Lady whom he calles elect,
               A virtuous woman who doth much delight,
               The lawes of her Redeemer to reſpect: 2. Ioh. 1.
               
               And taught her children likewiſe to fulfill,
               Our bleſſed Lord and Sauiours holy will.
            
            
               139
               For which ſaith he I doe not onely loue,
               This moſt renowned woman of our dayes,
               But all thoſe Saints that loue the truth approue
               Her zealous workes with euerlaſting praiſe:
               Which they in greater eſtimation hold,
               Then Tagus wealth, or Ophirs pureſt gold.
            
            
               
               140
               Thus in this ſacred booke of bookes we ſee,
               The bleſings God on women did beſtow,
               VVhich worthyly they did deſerue ſaith he,
               From whom ſuch faith, ſuch loue, ſuch zeale did flow:
               Such courage braue, ſuch reſolutions rare,
               As monuments of marble ſhall out weare.
            
            
               141
               The hiſtories that doe their praiſe recite,
               In euery age ſo plentifull appeares,
               That if I had ability to write,
               I ſhould not finiſh, liuing Neſtors yeares:
               Such monumēts vnto their fame they build
               A magaſine might with the bookes be fil'd.
            
            
               142
               Yet to auoid the captious baſe report,
               Of Puritant or Bible bearing poet,
               As likewiſe to content the wiſer ſort.
               On whom alone I freely doe beſtow it:
               I will inſert of womens vertues rare,
               A ſtanze, or two what hiſtories declare.
            
            
               143
               For chaſtitie behold that Roman dame, Iuſtin.
               
               That proud Tarquinius baſely did ſubdue,
               Diſdaining to out liue her forced ſhame,
               Did in her deareſt bloud her hands imbrew:
               For wch ſhe is throwout the world renownd
               And by the pens of Lawreat Poets crown'd.
            
            
               
               144
               Vnmatched Ouid doth as much commend,
               
                  Penelope Vliſſes conſtant wife, Ouid.
               
               Whoſe widowed hands the hanging web doth rend,
               Whilſt he in Lacedemon leades his life:
               Euen like the Turtle that hath loſt his mate,
               She doth bewaile her deſolate eſtate.
            
            
               145
               Vnſpotted Daphue would not be allur'd, Ouid.
               
               By powerfull loue, from whom amaine ſhe flies
               When fainting breath, her honors loſſe aſſur'd,
               Alowd for chaſte Dianaes helpe ſhe cries:
               Whoſe iuſt conſent, vnto her earneſt prayer
               The lawrell doth perpetuall witneſſe beare.
            
            
               146
               The daughter faire of Agamemnon King, Thucidides.
               
               Whoſe loue and beauty was deſir'd of many,
               Held chaſtitie ſo virtuous a thing,
               That ſhe would neuer condiſcend to any:
               But conſtantly their ardent ſuites deni'd,
               And thus this ſpotleſſe virgin liu'd and di'd.
            
            
               147
               The virgin Lucia doth all praiſe exceed, Domitian.
               
               With whom the tirant King was far in loue.
               VVhen ſhe perceiu'd it was ſo ſure decreed,
               What friendſhip could not force at laſt ſhoud proue:
               Her ſtar-like eyes ſhe to the tirant ſent,
               That thus ſhe might her honors loſſe preuēt.
            
            
               
               148 Thucidides.
               
               Sage Fedons daughter doth amaze my minde,
               VVhoſe father being at a banquent ſlaine,
               By ſauage men, who likewiſe had combin'd,
               This vertuous virgins chaſtitie to ſtaine:
               She to auoid this Tyrants fury fell,
               Did headlong caſt herſelfe into a well.
            
            
               149
               Saint Ambroſe of Pelagia writes as much,
               VVho with her famous ſiſters and her mother,
               That no rude hād her honors worth might tuch
               Themſelues did likewiſe in the water ſmother:
               Such deare reſpect to chaſtitie they owe,
               Their precious liues they doe for it beſtow.
            
            
               150
               The Lady Bona to her laſting honor, Guice
                        ••
                     
                     din.
               
               Whoſe husband to the holy warres was ſent,
               Diſguiſ'd to follow him ſhe tooke vpon her,
               Both ſhield &amp; ſpeare, mou'd with a chaſt intent
               Wher brauely ſhe his faithles foes did threat
               And reſcued him from many dangers great.
            
            
               151
               Braue Francis Sforſas ſouldiers to him broght,
               A virgin rare of birth, &amp; beauty great,
               Whom ſhe with friendſhip prayer &amp; words beſoght,
               Then tyrant like the ſilly maide did threat:
               But finding nothing could her honor ſtaine
               With gifts &amp; praiſe he ſent her home againe.
            
            
               
               152
               The women of Tutonicaes requeſt,
               When noble Marius had their husband ſlaine
               VVas yt they might haue leaue to ſpend ye reſt,
               Of their vnhappy liues in Veſtaes traine:
               Where they like chaſteſt turtles wold deplore
               Their fatall loſſe, beholding men no more.
            
            
               153
               In Rome a woman being made aquainted, Cor. Tac.
               
               With treaſon was 'gainſt Nero great conſpir'd,
               VVhereof ſhe happened firſt to be attainted,
               Of whom the Iudges all the reſt inquired:
               With cruell torments ſhe her life did pay,
               Yet neuer any party would betray.
            
            
               154
               Renowned Loena did in ſunder bite
               Her tongue, and ſpit it in the tyrants face,
               Becauſe ſhe would no ſecret bring to light,
               For which th' Athenians to her laſting grace: Plime.
               
               From whom ſuch rare vnmatched virtue ſprung,
               A Lioneſſe ſet vp without a tong.
            
            
               155
               Rare Nicoſtrata mother to Euander,
               
               Did firſt vnto the Latins ſhew their letters,
               VVho till her time in ignorance did wander,
               Yet afterwards acknowledge none their betters
               In Hiſtory, Philoſophy, or Phraiſe,
               Of eloquence deſeruing worthy praiſe.
            
            
               
               156
               
                  Aretha was in learning ſo profound,
               That ſhe in Athens publike ſchoole did read
               Philoſophie with iudgment graue and ſound,
               VVherein ſhe did the learnedſt man exceed:
               VVhoſe Auditors as Pollio doth declare,
               Philoſophers aboue a hundred were. Pollio.
               
            
            
               157
               VVhen Lucius Scilla was condemn'd to die,
               Who falſely had three thouſand Romains ſlaine
               That did vpon his word their liues relie,
               His daughter Loelia did his life obtaine:
               With one oration which ſhe made in Rome
               Whereat the Senate did reuoke their doom. Cicero.
               
            
            
               158
               
                  Senobia was in learning ſo repleate,
               Both Greeke and Latin to her ſons ſhe taught,
               And did a rare epitome repeate, Pollio.
               
               Of all ye warres wherwith the Eaſt was fraught:
               
                  Athenian Pericles, who ſoar'd ſo high
               Did from Aſpaſia learne Philoſophie.
            
            
               159
               
                  Cornelia a famous Roman dame, Cornelia the wife of Africanus &amp; Mother to the Greechi.
               
               Such eloquent Epiſtles vſ'd to write,
               That Cicero a man of rareſt fame,
               Cōmends her workes with wonderful delight:
               With Pallaes help to end rare Lucan broght
               The battaile Caeſar and great Pompey fought.
            
            
               
               160
               
                  Alexandra, the wife of Alexander,
               
               In Iury liu'd a Biſhop many yeares,
               Whoſe learned wiſdom like a wiſe commander
               Was reuerenc'd both of common-wealth and Peeres: Eicſebius
               
               
                  Dona the daughter of Pithagoras,
               
               In ſciences a famous ſcholler was.
            
            
               161
               Two Gretian women deepely learn'd indeed, Plato. Laſterna Axiothe.
               
               The loue of Plato did ſo highly win,
               That ſeated in his chaire about to read,
               Before they came he ſeldome would begin:
               In them ſaith he, ſage wiſdom doth remaine,
               And memory graue maxims to maintaine.
            
            
               162
               In France a ſect of women did remaine,
               Cal'd Druides, to whom Aurelian came,
               From Rome to France their counſells to obtaine
               So much their wiſdom was renownd by fame:
               
                  Mirrha Queene of Lydia men did call, Strabo.
               
               Agiant for her wit, in ſtature ſmall.
            
            
               163
               In Rhodes a Roman and a Greeke fell out. Eutropius.
               
               Who both deſir'd their cuntries worth to raiſe
               The Greeke cōteſt ye Romans were more ſtout
               But vnto Greece for learning gaue the praiſe:
               Wherin ſaid he our women more doe know
               Then you in armes, whereof you boaſt of ſo.
            
            
               
               164
               Vpon which words a mortall warre inſu'd,
               'Twixt Rome &amp; Carthage, til the Rodians came,
               VVho earneſtly intreate they would conclude,
               To make them empires in this worke of fame:
               To whoſe requeſt whē they had both agreed
               The noble Rhodians in this wiſe proceed.
            
            
               165
               Ten Greacian women they in Rhodes ordaine
               VVith ten of Rome ſhall diſputation hold,
               Wch they with ſuch rare learning did maintain,
               In leaues of braſſe deſerues to be inrol'd:
               For with the Rhodiās to their great renown,
               with Lawrell wreathes theſe famous women crown'd.
            
            
               166
               For ſollid ſentences and learning graue,
               Vnto the Grecians they the praiſe decreed,
               True eloquence they to the Romans gaue,
               Wherin they thought they did ye Greeks exceed
               But from each ſide ſuch vertue rare did flow
               As mē could hardly who were victors know.
            
            
               167
               The worthy Rodians in perpetuall praiſe,
               That after ages might their vertues ſee,
               To each of them a monument did raiſe,
               VVhereby their loue ſhall intermixed be:
               Twenty huge Pillers of victorious fame,
               Whereon was writ each ſeuerall womans name.
            
            
               
               168
               Two famous Theban virgins being told,
               The Oracle had ſaid they ſhould enioy,
               A conqueſt from the Orchymenians bold,
               If two chaſt virgins ſhould thēſelues deſtroy:
               Their country with victorious praiſe to kill,
               Coragiouſly their deareſt bloud they ſpill.
            
            
               169
               Braue Celia, that King Porſenna tooke, Saluſt.
               
               VVith whom in hoſtage diuers virgins were,
               With courage ſtout, by night his camp forſook,
               Gat horſe and ſwame a riuer, void of feare:
               VVhereat the King amaz'd without delay.
               Did raiſe his ſiege, and went with ſhame away.
            
            
               170
               
                  Hermonia a Siracuſan maid,
               To ſaue her country did her life defie, Plime.
               
               The wife of Aſdruball was leſſe afraid,
               VVhen Scipio conquered then himſelfe to die:
               Great Mithridates wife and ſiſters three,
               Shew'd farre leſſe feare of death then he.
            
            
               171
               Reſolued Portia hearing this ſad newes,
               Her husband, and her father both were ſlaine, Portia the wife of Brutus.
               
               That tyrannizing ſorrow ſhould abuſe,
               Her noble ſpirit did ſo much diſdaine.
               The burning coales to eate ſhe doth deuiſe,
               Thus made herſelfe a liuing ſacrifice.
            
            
               
               172
               The pride of Aegipt that moſt glorious Queen
               Did ſo much ſcorn great Caeſars campe to grace
               With captine bands, wher ſhe ſhold ly between
               Diſpaire and hope in a contemned caſe:
               With poiſoned Aſps, whoſe touch to death doth hie,
               Brauely reſolu'd ſhe rather choſe to die.
            
            
               173
               
                  Philip proclam'd at Scyo euery ſlaue, Herodat.
               
               That would come forth &amp; with his army hold
               With liberty their maſters wiues ſhould haue,
               Which when the women heard, like lions bold
               They ſally out, and to their great renowne,
               Beate Phillip and his army from the towne.
            
            
               174
               The Scyots by th'Egiptian ſore oppreſt,
               Vnarm'd to leaue the towne, with them agree, Iuſtine.
               
               Wch when the womē heard they could not reſt
               Vntill they made them change this baſe decree:
               With ſheild and ſpeare vncloth'd they march away,
               Telling their foes that this was their aray.
            
            
               175
               Among the Amaſons two Queens they choſe
               The forraigne and domeſtique ſtate to guide,
               Abroad Marpeſia did ſubdue their foes,
               At home Lampeda all things did decide:
               VVith equall iuſtice void of loue or hate,
               VVhich made them floriſh in a happy ſtate.
            
            
               
               176
               Conſtantinople being round beſet,
               With furious Gothes that ment it to deſtroy, Caſſads.
               
               The Empreſſe bold to the wall did get,
               VVhere valiantly ſhe did them ſo annoy:
               That many by her noble hands did die,
               The reſt were forſt to raiſe their ſiege &amp; fly.
            
            
               177
               
                  Simeramis deſerues to be inrold, Iuſtine.
               
               In braſen leaues of euerlaſting praiſe,
               Who by her vallour like a Tygreſſe bold,
               Her hardy foes inforſt their campe to raiſe:
               From Babilon they ſurely thought to take,
               Which ſhe with ſhame compeled them to forſake.
            
            
               178
               
                  Senobia forſt Aurelian to confeſſe;
               With whom a famous war ſhe long maintain'd
               To conquer Xerxes was a taske far leſſe,
               Whoſe greatneſſe with the name of feare was ſtain'd
               Thē ſtout Senobia who with ſpeare &amp; ſheild,
               Came like the God of bataile to the field.
            
            
               179
               
                  Penthiſelia that couragious queene,
               Encountered braue Achilles hand to hand,
               Then which a brauer combat nere was ſeene,
               
                  Hippolita ſtout Theſeus did withſtand:
               In ſingle fight their honors to maintaine,
               VVhereby they did immortallglory gaine.
            
            
               
               180
               The Queene of Carryall, like the God of war,
               Did chaſe ye Rhodians like a hare with hounds,
               Againſt whoſe valor nothing was a barre,
               She burnt the wals, ſackt their cheifeſt townes,
               Whereby ſhe forſt thē to her endleſſe fame,
               To build her image, and inſcribe her name.
            
            
               181
               Immortall Taſſ
                        •
                     
                   thou canſt neuer die,
               So worthily Clornidaes fame to write,
               Who boldly durſt that champion braue defie,
               Renowned Tancred, euen at ſingle fight:
               And ſo perform'd yt men could hardly know
               The conqueror ſuruiu'd his conquered foe.
            
            
               182
               Vndanted Hector hadſt thou liued now,
               Howmuch thy hardeſt ſoule wold bluſh to ſee Iuſtine.
               
               That earths great monarch ſhould be made to bow,
               And by a womans hand ſubuerted be:
               Whoſe valiant head, ſhe frō his body drew,
               And did ye ſame in his owne blood imbrew.
            
            
               183
               Euen a
                     •
                   a Lyoneſſe doth range the coaſt,
               When ſhe perceiues her whelps are made a pray
               
                  So Thamaris doth breake through Cyrus hoſt,
               And brauely with her ſword did make her way
               And to her friēds his royal head ſhe brought,
               Like Pallas with the ſpoils of Gergon fraught.
            
            
               
               184
               Amongſt theſe Queenes oh let me not forget,
               That Queen of Queenes, which in our age did raigne,
               Who like a Comet in the skie was ſet,
               Vnparalleld for euer to remaine:
               To write her praiſe, I neuer ſhall aſpire,
               Whom euery eye with wonder did admire.
            
            
               185
               The worlds great Artiſt, nature did complaine,
               Such beauty rare the earth did not enioy,
               And that no other might the like obtaine,
               She doth againe this heauenly ſtamp deſtroy:
               Then all the powers ſupernall freely came,
               And gaue perfection to this matchles dame.
            
            
               186
               Imperious Iuno at her feete did lay,
               That all commanding Scopter which ſhe bare,
               Wherewith ſhe did the pride of Spaine allay,
               Supported France the Royall crowne to weare
               And Belgia her peereleſſe praiſe may ſing,
               Whoſe famous acts all Chriſtendome doth ring.
            
            
               187
               
                  Arete for her Temple choſe her breaſt,
               And with faire vertues did it freely fill,
               Religious Veſta with chaſt thoughts her bleſt,
               
                  Minerua gaue her ſacred wiſedome ſtill:
               And royall Ceres who with a liberall hand,
               With great aboundance did inrich her land.
            
            
               
               188
               The faithleſſe Pagan, miſbeleeuing Turke,
               Virginian heathen, with the Indian Moore,
               In whō doth nought but ſecret miſcheife lurk,
               They all with reuerence did her ſtate adore:
               Great giftes they offer to her ſacred ſhrine,
               So was ſhe bleſt, euen by the powers diuine.
            
            
               189
               An happy fight this bleſſed woman fought,
               Whilſt here ſhe liu'd &amp; wore the royall crown;
               Her ſubiects all to peace and loue ſhe brought,
               The humble ſpar'd, &amp; beat the haughty down,
               Thus left her thron, wch time ſhal quit deſtroy
               An euerlaſting kingdome to enioy.
            
            
               190
               But now me thinkes I heare ſome whiſpering ſay,
               This fellow ſure is fearefully in loue,
               Whilſt other ſtraight vnto my charge doe lay,
               Some mercinary hire doth him moue:
               No, no, my friends, it is a caſe more cōmon,
               Wch you forget, my mother was a woman.
            
            
               191
               Whom nature taught me tenderly to loue,
               And thinke it is a duty which I owe,
               To her and women for her ſake to proue,
               The praiſe on them both God &amp; men beſtow:
               No art ſo excellent hath euer bin,
               But women haue bin famous actors in.
            
            
               
               192
               Tis true ſay, they there was a time of olde,
               When women ſure were better far then now,
               Through this opinion diuers men doe hold,
               I doubt not but the wiſer will allow:
               This coſtome nature doth to all men giue,
               To thinke yt age is worſe wherein they liue.
            
            
               193
               
                  Virgill and Ouid many yeares agoe,
               Do teſtifie that then the world was nought,
               In ſtately ſtile of verſe from them did flow,
               Their ſober leſſons publickly they taught:
               
                  Homer might come with muſike to his whores
               Yet wanting mony, get him out of dores.
            
            
               194
               Either theſe men haue ſpirits of diuining,
               Or elſe the world ſtands now as then it did,
               If worſe, it is by enuious mens repining,
               Which if they would conuert from ill to good,
               Thouſāds of womē this bad age might name
               That want rare pens to eternize their fame.
            
            
               195
               Like Romes Colaſſae I might write a booke,
               Or the Egiptian Piramid of old,
               If I ſhould ſtrictly ſtriue to ouerlooke,
               The vertues rare that are of women told:
               Which I referre to men of better skill,
               Who can this taske more worthily fulfill.
            
            
               
               196
               VVherein my pen already is growne dull,
               VVanting that tinckture of heroicke ſtraine,
               VVith which braue ſpirits of our age are full,
               Let this but animate their flowing vaine:
               While my poore Muſe ſhal wel contented be
               Her humble valley once againe to ſee.
            
            
               197
               Where ſhe with pleaſure, did behold the Beare
               The Wolfe, the Swan, ye Dragons head &amp; taile,
               The no meane Lion, and the fearefull Hare,
               The dart which 'gainſt the Griffen did preuaile:
               The King of Egipt and his ſtately Queene,
               Who for her beauty now in heauen is ſeene.
            
            
               198
               The crowne which Ariadne did obtaine,
               From Venus, for becomming Bacchus loue,
               The harpe of Orpheus, whoſe melodious ſtraine
               Made careles beaſts, &amp; ſenceles trees to moue:
               The ſonne of Danaae that Meduſa ſlue,
               The waggener that luſtfull Phedra flue.
            
            
               199
               The ſon of Ioue whō Satan would haue ſlaine,
               The ſerpent holder bright Appolloes ſonne,
               The fiſh that ſau'd Orion in the maine,
               
                  Alcides after all his labor done:
               The horſe of Bacchus forſt his maſters loue,
               The bird yt brought faire Ganymede to Ioue.
               
            
            
               
               200
               The flying horſe ſprang from Meduſaes bloud,
               
                  Bellepheron did vndertake to ride,
               Who for his paines, was drenched in the floud,
               The horſe flew vp to heauē, wher he doth bide:
               The triangle which Ceres did requeſt,
               The Gods to place in heauen amongſt the reſt.
            
            
               201
               The wife of Perſeus, and the monſtrous whale,
               The crow which by the wel the ſerpent found,
               
                  Ixions wheele, with Venus daughter pale,
               The riuer wherein Phaeton was drownd:
               
                  Chyron that taught Achilles great in Greece,
               The ſhip that brought home Iaſons golden fleece.
            
            
               202
               The Rambe with Phirxes and her ſiſters went,
               Ore Helleſpont: Europaes roring Bull,
               The twinns of Loeda: Iunoes crabe ſhe ſent,
               To Hercules, who did in peeces pull
               The Lion: iuſtice ſlue from earth to Heauen,
               Who by her ballance found mens acts vneuen.
            
            
               203
               The Scorpion ſlue Orion with his ſting,
               
                  Euthemiaes Sonne that with the Muſes ſlept,
               Diſguiſed Pan, the Boy Ioues bird did bring,
               The fiſhes Venus from the Giant kept:
               All theſe the Gods haue ſtellifi'de in heauen,
               With Pleiades, whoſe number once was ſeuen.
            
            
               
               204
               Vntil Electra ſeeing Troian fire,
               Shrunke in her head, and neuer ſince was ſeen
               Whoſe griefe doth make my pittying Muſe  
                     •
                  tir
               Caſting her eies vpon the louely greene:
               Where ſhe will mourne, among the ſhepheards ſwaine
               Admires high hills, but loue ſhe lowly plaine
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

