
   
      
         
            A counter-poyson modestly written for the time, to make aunswere to the obiections and reproches, wherewith the aunswerer to the Abstract, would disgrace the holy discipline of Christ.
         
         
            
               1584
            
         
         Approx. 244 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00637
            STC 10770
            ESTC S101936
            99837739
            99837739
            2079
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00637)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2079)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 224:08)
         
         
            
               
                  A counter-poyson modestly written for the time, to make aunswere to the obiections and reproches, wherewith the aunswerer to the Abstract, would disgrace the holy discipline of Christ.
                  Fenner, Dudley, 1558?-1587, attributed name.
                  Stoughton, William, fl. 1584, attributed name.
                  Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624, attributed name.
               
               [16], 80, 90-195, [6] p.   
               
                  Printed by Robert Waldegraue,
                  At London :
                  [1584]
               
               
                  Variously attributed to Dudley Fenner and to William Stoughton; sometimes also attributed to Henry Jacob.
                  An answer to: Cosin, Richard.  An answer to the two first and principall treatises of a certeine factious libell, put foorth latelie, without name of author or printer, and without approbation by authoritie, under the title of An abstract of certeine acts of Parlement: of certeine hir Majesties canons, &amp;c.
                  Publication date from STC.
                  The last three leaves are blank.
                  Running title reads: Of the certaine forme of ecclesiasticall gouernment.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Cosin, Richard, 1549?-1597. --  Answer to the two first and principall treatises of a certeine factious libell, put foorth latelie, without name of author or printer, and without approbation by authoritie, under the title of An abstract of certeine acts of Parlement: of certeine hir Majesties canons, &amp;c.
               Church of England --  Government --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-01
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-01
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ A COVNTER-POYSON, Modeſtly written for the time, to make aunſwere to the obiections and reproches, wherewith the aunſwerer to the Abſtract, would diſgrace the holy Diſcipline of CHRIST.
            Luke 19. verſ. 40.
            ¶ I tell you, if thoſe ſhould holde their peace, the ſtones woulde crye.
            
            AT LONDON; Printed by Robert Waldegraue.
            
         
         
            
            
            The Authour to the Reader.
            
            IT is ſayde of Solomon (who had no ſmall experience in the courſe of al things) that much reading is wearineſſe vnto the
               Eccleſ. 12. 
               fleſh; but it is moſt true, euen in our owne experience, that to deale with the vntamed and vntaught reaſon of man, is a vanity &amp; vexation of ſpirit, vnto thoſe who loue the truth. For what cunning ſhiftes and exquiſite variety of ſubtleties haue they, to decline the mighty ſtrooke of the word of God? And it is no maruaile, if we poore dullardes be not only made blunt, but almoſt worne awaye with encountring with ſuch tough ware. The onely comfort we haue is, that when the diuell diſputed, yea, continued diſputing ſo long with the Son of God him ſelf, hee was at the length made to retire with thoſe milde, and yet moſt powrefull wordes: The Lord rebuke thee Sathan. WhichIud. 9. moſt auncient example, as it hath greatly ſuſtayned me in this toyle of this tedious time, wherein I haue had occaſion to goe bare-foote through this quicke-ſet hedge of thornes, which the aunſwerer to the Abſtract
               
hath ſet in our way: ſo it doth not a little grieue me, that I am iealous ouer my ſelfe, that I haue not followed in ſuch meaſure as I ought, that moderation which the ſonne of God; The prince of Angels kept, when he encountred with the deuil, notwithſtanding, I deale (as I hope) with a brother. My comfort is, that it ſhall be manifeſt, that in ſteede of taking occaſion where it was not giuen, I haue ſwallowed downe that, as ſweet, which is moſt loathſome and bitter: I haue alſo ſtayd my courſe within the compaſſe of the firſt treatiſe, and the daungerous appendix annexed to the ſame; partly becauſe I ſuppoſe he wil not abuſe ſo much the Scripture, as to wreſt the defence of pluralities of Ciuill offices, in Miniſters of God his word, of ſole excommunication (which is already handled in this treatiſe by the ſcripture) and partly becauſe the reſt will for the moſt part pertaine properly to the worthye Lawyer, who hath begun this controuerſie, and ſhall by the grace of God ſee a good end of the ſame. The Lord bring vs all to be of one minde and hart in the truth.
         
         
            
            A FAITHFVLL BROTHER to the Chriſtian Reader.
            
            
               THE FEAREFVL CONDItion (in regard of our ſinnes) of this our age, and in this our Noble Countrie, may make thee (good Chriſtian reader) and all, who loue the peace of SION, &amp; the flowriſhing eſtate of this cōmonwealth; vvith heauie ſoule, and deepe ſighes of heart, to bevvaile the horrible wickednes of this land, euen yet to this day increaſing; if thou doe but conſider, that the hard and ſtonie hearts (being continually vvatered vvith the ſvveete and heauenly devv of Gods moſt fatherly admonitions &amp; forethreatnings, from day to day dropping dovvne by his meſſingers, riſing earlye), is rather hardened then any whit mollified or humbled. So that neither the fearfull ſignes in heauen and other creatures, as it were, by the breach of nature weeping ouer vs; nor the horrible howling and quaking of the earth, trembling and fearing vnder vs, hath as yet brought forth anye further ſorrowe of our ſinnes, then, that being amazed and aſtoniſhed at the ſuddaines, woondring at the ſtraungenes, and for a time, while our heartes did beat, lightly ſorrowing at the fearfulnes thereof, we made a ſhew

as though we would haue turned to the Lord; but alas, we ſoone became like the children of Iſraell; vvho beeing put in feare with the greate terrour which God ſhevved in pronouncing the Lawe in mount Syna, did promiſe to heare &amp; obey Moſes, vvho being but fortie daies and fortie nights abſent from them, and for them vvith the Lord: they fel avvay to their owne imaginations. Since this, hath the Lorde vvith ſtraunge ſickneſſes, at diuers times, diuerſly viſited vs in our bodies; yea, our very hearts haue bene ſmitten vvith the fear of foraine practiſes, yet vvho is it that hath rightly ackovvledged the hand of the Lorde? Aboue all other thinges, this is to be ſoberly vvaied with the equall ballaunce of an vpright conſcience: that euen novv, on the one ſide, the common enemy to the ſtate and Church of God among vs, hath very villanouſly and traiterouſly, vovved himſelfe, to put out the happy light of this moſt peaceable kingdome, euen by deſperate and ſlauiſhe bloud-ſuckers, (allured and beſotted, vvith the fayre and favvning face of a man hayred like a VVoman, of theſe Locuſtes the Ieſuites, who haue ſtinges in their tailes, beeing like vnto Scorpions,) to take away the precious life of our moſte gratious Queene ELIZABETH, our moſt dear ſoueraigne, the ioy and peace of all this Land: (the Lord for his Sonnes 
                  •
               ake continue her bleſſed dayes among vs, and cōfound al their horrible practizes:) on the other ſide, (like as it was in Hieruſalem vvhen Titus beſieged it) vvhat little faith and true loue, (euen from the tankard-bearer to men of high degree)

he that ſeeth any thing, muſt needes behold and tremble. But O that I vvere able to povvre oute my very heart: and that riuers of vvaters mighte flovv out of mine eyes, that I might ſufficiently bevvaile the deſolation of Sion among vs: yea, I coulde vviſhe that my life though it vvere by a thouſand deaths, might redeeme the breaches of the Church of God among vs. VVhoſe hart doth not bleede to thinke that in ſo peaceable daies &amp; ſo bleſſed a time, vnder ſo Godly and religious a Princeſſe, euen when the fire of our neighboures moſt rufull miſeries, doth flame about our eares: yea, and that the Lorde hath almoſte drawne out his vvrathfull ſvvord againſt vs: euery man follovveth the pride, couetouſneſſe, vvhoredome, drunkenneſſe and luſtes of his own heart, and no man remembreth Ioſeph? The barres are filled vvith pleadinges, and the ſtreetes are full of the cries of the poore: fulnes of meat and contempt is among vs, and vvho conſidereth? Yet, if this our ſin vvere only againſt men, and not againſt God, there migh be ſome hope; But vvhen the mouth of the blaſphemous ſvvearer, is not tied vp, &amp; the handes of the idolatrous generation of Atheieſtes, &amp; prophane perſons be not chained: VVhen the moſte holye and precious vvorde of God is manifeſtlye contemned, the ioyfull and heauenly tydings of ſaluation, ſo negligently and vngratefully troden vnder foote: the true and faithfull meſſengers purſued, atained, and diuers wayes afflicted: then if the olde worlde for malitious imaginations, Sodom and Gomorrha for pride, fulneſſe of meate and vnmercifulneſſe: If

Ieruſalē for abuſing Gods prophets, &amp; wilfulnes were wofully diſtroyed, vvhat may wee poore careles people look for, if we do not repent (but as it is almoſt vniuerſally feared) ſpeedy ruine &amp; vtter deſolation? O ye ſhepherds of Iſrael be wiſe and vnderſtand, kiſſe the ſonne leaſt he be angry,Pſalme. 2. ſeeke the Lorde whilſte he may be founde, make attonement with him, reſt yee on God, and follow his wayes [For the eyes of the Lord behold2. Chro, 16. 9 all the earth, to ſhew him ſelfe ſtrong with them that are of perfect hart toward him.] And you ye reuerend fathers, which take vpon you to rule the ſterne of God his ſhip, to your conſciences be it appealed, whether you thruſt not out of your brethren, faithful &amp; ſkilful marriners, nouriſhing the idle &amp; vnfit: wherby it is come to paſſe, that thouſands of ſoules are like to be drowned. Let be appeled vnto your cōſciēces, whether this your dealing, be not the only cauſe that this church of England hath ſuffred ſuch diſquietnes? and whether you ar not folowers of ſuch as haue bin diſturbers of the churches in other countries? cōpare I pray you, your cauſe with their cauſe, and your proceding with their proceeding: as namely, let the practiſes of the diuines of PERGA in Germany, (for the maintaining of the errour of conſubſtantiation, and vbiquity of Chriſte his bodie) beSee admon. ad lib. concord de mod agend. compared with your ſtriuing againſt the wholeſome diſciplin of Chriſt [they were few] (as namely about ſix) &amp; one bare the cheefeſt ſvvay: &amp; you are not ſo many, as that for your willes, all the Churches ſhould be troubled in England, [they helde the foundation] and ſo doe you; [they had

to doe with their godly brethren] and ſo haue you; [they ſhrowded themſelues vnder the ſhadovve of moſte famons men; as of Luther and Melancthon] and ſo do you, euen of moſte bleſſed martyrs, and very learned fathers: [they hauing tried diuers wayes to eſtabliſh their errors: at length deuiſed a ſubſcription to a book called (Liber concordiae,) thereby to drawe a ſecrete allovvance of that which openly they could not ſo vvel ſet one foote]: You after many moleſtations and vexations of your brethren, euen to the turning avvay of many good ſchollers, godly affected, from the ſtudy of diuinity, haue at the lēgth contrary to allavv of God and man, offered violence to the conſciences of your brethren▪ by a forced ſubſcription; [they firſt won the magiſtrat, and made him their pretence, vvhere their ſubtilty vvas eſpied]: and I pray God it be not layd to your charge, for your like dealing &amp; pretences: [the Magiſtrates vvere hardly dravvne to like of their purpoſe &amp; maner of proceding]: ſo am I perſwaded that yours cannot long bee couered [they pretended vnity and intituled their ſubſcription, a Booke of Concord, and by that meanes made great diſcord and diſſention] you cry out for conformity and good order, and nothing leſſe is the iſſue of your proceedings: you cry the peace of the Churche, and vvho knovveth not, that if you vvoulde be humble to God, and louing to your brethren, and diſcharge your duetye to her Maieſty, but that theſe ſtumbling blocks and meanes of diſſention, might long ago haue bene remooued. For vve are aſſured, [that as the Magiſtrates

vvith them, did ſomevvhat ſtaye their fury], ſo if her Highneſſe, of her Godly diſpoſition and accuſtomed clemencye, vvith her honourable Counſellers, had not bene ſome Bridle to your vnvviſe indeuors, there vvould hardly haue bin, ere this time, any peace for a faithfull miniſter. [But how proceeded they? &amp; vvhat did they obtaine? Euen by feare and authority, they forced ſome to ſubſcribe; ſome they woone by faire vvords: to ſome they granted in ſecreat limitatiō, which after they in open denied: ſome hauing ſubſci bed, aftervvarde vvith great ſorrovve and anguiſhe relented: ſome they remooued from their charges, and ſome they continued vvith long and variable moleſtation: and finallye, this vvas the good they brought to paſſe, that the people were diſtracted, many churches vntaught, &amp; great broiles &amp; confuſion in many places.] So I wold to God that euery of thoſe (that I may not ſay vvorſe) vvere not too too true in you: onely let it be appealed vnto your conſcience, that you ſuſpended and depriued them, whom by lavv you ought to haue firſt reſolued, or endeuored your ſelues to haue ſo don; and that by articles interrogatory you vvēt about, &amp; indeed intangled ſome of your brethrē: vvith that pretence of law, which othervviſe ſeemed to be vvanting. And vvas this either charitable to your brethren, or agreeable to iuſtice to your aduerſary, meete in a Biſhop to thoſe of his charge, that one ſhould be puniſhed before his cauſe be equally heard? And that hee may not haue a copye of the thinges layde to his charge, but be driuen vpon an oth to anſvvere ſodainly,

&amp; being depriued in a chamber, to be ſent avvay vvithout anye certayne knovvledge of the cauſes of his depriuation. Let all men iudge hovv this may beſeme Chriſtian Biſhops, and graue fathers. But hovv haue you made vnity &amp; conformity? euen as one vvould open a doore to al horrible cōfuſion &amp; vprore, if by the merciful prouidence of God it had not beene ſtaid and preuented. It is high time therefore for you to repent and to ſhewe your ſelues as true Elders, caſting downe your crovvnes before the Lambe. It is hard for you to kicke againſt the prick. RememberMat. 24. 48 vvhat is written, [If the euill ſeruant ſhall ſay in his hart, my Maſter doth deferre his comming, and begin to ſmite his fellowes, and to eate and drinke with the drunken, that ſeruants maſter will come in a day, vvhen he looketh not for him, &amp; giue him his portion vvith hypocrites, there ſhal be vveeping and gnaſhing of teeth.] And all ye the inhabitantes of this lande turne yee to the Lord before it bee too late: humble your ſelues before the throne of his mercye: let euerye one chaunge his heart and amend his ovvne vvaies, that the Lorde may haue pittye vppon vs, and our enimies preuaile not againſte vs. Pray yee for the peace of this Lande, they that loue the Lorde, ceaſe not crying till he haue mercy vppon vs: And let the remembraunce of our bleſſed ſoueraigne be in all your ſupplications, that by the continuaunce of her happy &amp; proſperous reigne, his glorious Goſpell may ſhine more and more, (as in the dayes of king Ioſias) in brightneſſe &amp; beauty among vs. And let this little treatiſe bee

vnto thee (gentle and Chriſtian reader) as a light and profitable glaſſe from day to day to looke in, that it may be a meanes to teach thee and ſtirre thee vp to praye for, and to ſeeke by all lawfull, quiet and Godlye meanes, the refourmation of ſome things in our Church. For it is not the purpoſe thereof, (as God knoweth) to miniſter matter of ciuill contention, or that any man ſhoulde reioyce in the ſtrife of brethren, but with as much care as could be, tendring the peace of the church, to make apparant, ſimply and briefly the truth of godlineſſe, in the thinges mentioned in this book, according to the worde of God. And here vve deſire all men, and you the reuerende Fathers of this land, &amp; all godly brethren, to whom this may come, to iudge charitably of this woorke, vvhich tendeth to no other end, but that the truth being found, we might al ioin togeather in godly peace, &amp; an holy vnion, to ſerue him ioifully together, frō generation to generation. The reaſons which ſpecially did cauſe this mater to be taken in hand, are either in reſpect of the ſubſtaunce of ſeuerall points in queſtion, or of the time wherin they are brought in queſtion. For firſt, conſidering that the queſtion is not (as the aunſwerer would beare the world in hād, &amp; as in publike ſermons, it is euery day vncharitably vpbraided) about trifles, &amp; things of no vvaight, as of variable ceremonies &amp; matters of circumſtances, which yet are to be ſquared by the ſacred Canons of holy Scripture; but about matters of no ſmall importance, euen of the great and waighty cauſe of Chriſtes kingdome, by vvhat lavves and offices, his heritage is

to be gouerned &amp; protected: that is, of the whole Diſcipline of the Church of Chriſt, whether it be to be ordered by the vncertayne and deceiueable waights of humane conſtitutions, or by the infallible Oracles of Gods moſt holy teſtimonies. And that the aunſwerer doth very confidentlye challenge (as thogh not only by vs, but byal churches reformed in manye writinges verye well knowne, he vvere not already aunſvvered): that by the worde of God, vve vvoulde prooue a certaine gouernement of the Church vnder the time of the Goſpell: and that this he doth very cloſlye and colourablie at his pleaſure, adding to, and detracting from the queſtion (as in the treatiſe ſhall appeare,) and vvith ſmooth vvordes and artificial euaſions, (though ſometimes vvith more gaule then comelynes, and more ſcoffing then ſubſtaunce,) labouring to caſt a myſt before the eyes of the Reader, and to beare dovvn the cauſe with ſvvelling vvordes of vain oſtentation. And concerning the time, ſeeing that novv by the meanes of the vnaduiſed ſtirre, vvhich by the reuerende Fathers is made in this Church of England, al the faythfull ſeruauntes of Chriſte Ieſus, are in ſome ſort called to beare vvitneſſe vnto the truth: and that vvithout verye good grounde it vvere not meet, that any reaſonable thing ſhoulde be refuſed of ſuch men as vve be, not onely to ſatisfie the expectation of all men, deſirous to knovve the truth, but alſo to diſcharge our dutie, to our Lord and Maſter Ieſus Chriſt, and to her gracious maieſty, and all her good ſubiectes: vve coulde not keep the pen from paper, but vvere, as it were inforced

to beare this neceſſary vvitnes to a truth, not ſo much by the reaſon of man impugned and reſiſted, as by manifeſt and plaine places of ſcripture to be approoued and confirmed; and for the dayly profite of the Church, moſt behooſefull of euery man to be rightly vnderſtood, and in euery Congregation vvith all reuerence and diligence, to be practiſed and religiouſly obſerued. For, what man indovved vvith the feare of God, and a reuerent loue of his Prince, continually beholding the diligent hand of the ſeditious papiſts to waxe ſtronger and ſtronger, through the ſtopping of the mouths of the ſincere miniſters, and ſo many (I might ſay innumerable) ſoules, for whome Chriſte Ieſus ſhed his moſte precious bloude, to remaine in miſerable captiuity and bondage of blindneſſe and ignoraunce, the very chaine of darkneſſe and iniquity, for lacke of teaching and inſtruction, and theſe non-reſidents and blinde guides, which in ſome ſort make a pray of God his heritage, to bee ſo cunningly vnder-propped and maintained: and ſo many thinges, of ſo euil nature in themſelues, ſo pernicious to the church of God, ſo dangerous to the ſtate of this commō wealth, ſo offenſiue and burdenous to all people of any conſcience and knowledge, to be ſo mightily backed and defended: what man I ſay, hearing and ſeeing the daily and pitiful complaints of the poore people for lack of good paſtors, and of the reioycings of vvicked &amp; euill men, in the trouble of the faithfull Miniſters, to the great diſhonour of almighty God, and contempt of many moſt wholſome Lawes, by her moſt excellent Maieſty

ſet foorth and eſtabliſhed▪ can be ſo careleſſe and vndutifull, as not to applye him-ſelfe in ſome ſort or other, that theſe great enormities may be detected and remooued. Accept therfore (gentle reader) the godly labours which were employed in ſetting foorth this little Treatiſe, &amp; thinke it not ſtraunge, that it commeth foorth ſo ſoone or ſo ſodenly, but take it as a ſtay &amp; an help vnto thee, till ſome more larger diſcourſe ſhalbe aduē
               tured, wherin the holy ſcripture is made the onely iudge of this cōtrouerſy, &amp; ſo much as cōcerneth the reaſons of the lavves of this land is nothing at al touched, as wel becauſe the purpoſe of this reply, vvas to inſtruct the cōſcience by the proper means thervnto ordayned of God; as becauſe the ſhortnes of time could not ſuffer any more, &amp; the pen vvhich vvrote this, is of an other profeſſion. vveigh vvell and examine the reaſons here inſerted, vvith the iuſt and euen ballaunce of God his holy ſanctuary, and let thine eye be ſingle in iudging, and no doubt but (thorovv God his grace) though peraduenture the ſtile may be ſomevvhat harſh, and euery point not ſo finely adorned with the flovvers of mans eloquence; yet the plaine &amp; ſimple euidence of the truth, euen in her nakedneſſe and proper beauty, ſhal ſo ſhine and caſt her bright beames into thy conſcience, that if thou reape not ſo much profite as vvere to be vviſhed, at the leaſt vvyſe, this cauſe may receiue more fauourable interpretation, and be eſteemed as a thing vvorthy of due conſideration. Thus hoping of the bleſſing of God tovvardes thee, and of thy charitable receiuing of the labours vvhich were

enterpriſed to do thee good; I ceaſe anye further to hold thine eyes from the vvorke it ſelfe: moſte humbly beſeeching God, euen the father of our Lord 
                  •
               eſus Chriſt, to be mercifull vnto this land; to giue vs ſpeedy and vnfayned repentaunce, to turne his plagues from vs, to ouerturne and confound the diuiliſh and blouddy treacheries of all ſeditious, popiſh, and other traiterous vndermyners of the ſtate, to plant true and godly loue among vs, and to ſet vp the kingdome of his ſonne according to his vvorde, to the proſperous continuance of the moſt honourable and peaceable eſtate, of the Queenes highnes; to the reioycing of all faithfull and true hearted ſubiectes, and to the glorie of his moſte holye name for euer. Amen.
         
         
            Faults eſcaped.
            Page 32. line 12. for Nicodemia, read Nicomedia. pa. 43. lin. 5. for would, read should. pa. 56. lin. 6. for rotted, read rotten pa. 80. l. 11. for. from, read after. p. 91. l. 11. for by, read of. pa. 92. li. 1. after God, read doth pa. 120. li. 7. for he, read they. pa. 105. li. 6. after vpon, read vs. pa. 128 line. 10. read exerciſe ceaſing. pa. 131. li. 20. for commit read commute. pa. 133. li. 3. for railing, read calling. pa. 146. li. 1. for haſt, read his own heart. pag. 157 li. 13. for trueth, read. fruite.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               ❧ Of the certaine forme of Eccleſiaſticall Gouernment, preſcribed by the Word of God, and perpetuall for all ages.
            
            
               FOR as much as the purpoſe of this treatiſe, is with all modeſty and peace to giue cleare euidence to the trueth; it was thought fitteſt for the cauſe, and moſt profitable for the Chriſtian Reader, to ſet downe vnder certaine heades, the ſeuerall aſſertions and reaſons, which are here and there ſcatteringly inforced by the anſwere to the Abſtract, againſt the ſeuerall braunches

of the holye gouernement, which Chriſt Jeſus hath aſigned for the ordinarie policie of his Church. Amongeſt which, that requireth the firſte place, which is the grounde of all the reſt, concerning the certaine forme of gouernement, which he hath preſcribed for his Church. His wordes be theſe.
            
               I doe therefore ſay and offer in the name of the learned, to him or other to conſider of, that it is taken by vs for an vndoubted trueth, the contrary whereof, by no proofe we doe aſſure our ſelues can bee ſhewed, that there are not ſet downe in perticuler by Scripture, or by neceſſarie collection to be gathered, all circumſtaunces of pollicie, gouernement, Diſcipline, and ceremonies neceſſary and vniformally to bee vſed in euery ſeuerall Church: and that the Chriſtian Magiſtrates and gouernours, are not in the ſayd former points (wherof ſomthing is touched in Scripture) of neceſsitie tyed to that preciſe forme that is there ſet downe, but to the generall Doctrine concerning them,
               
               to wit, that al be done to edifying, orderlye, comely, and ſuch like, page. 33. And againe, aſking whether all reformed Churches are diſciplinated alike he ſayth, Nay; they neyther are, can be, nor yet neede ſo to be: ſeeing it cannot be prooued, that any ſet &amp; exact perticuler forme thereof, is recommended to vs by the Worde of God, pag. 58. And againe, pag. 60. To the former aſſertion he addeth this reaſon: For elſe how could the Primitiue Church without any preſcript word, (I doe not onely ſay, haue brought in a newe ceremonie) but haue altered the Sabboth day by God appoynted at the firſt, and being our Satterday to the firſt day of the week, in the Scripture twiſe or thriſe called the Lordes day, and with vs Sunday: or yet the time of receiuing the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, being according to the inſtitution vſually receiued after Supper, to haue it receiued as it is in the morning, faſting.
            
            In which aſſertions, there is ſo little plaine dealing and ſo much vntruth, as

of y• one ſide they ſauour of ſubtletie, ſo on the other ſide they haue very ſmale taſte of ſound diuinitie. For firſt, when as the Queſtion was of Diſcipline, to be adminiſtred as the Lorde commaunded, that is, of the ſubſtantiall forme of Chriſtes gouernement, he carieth it to the ceremonies and circumſtances of Diſcipline, as if when the Apoſtle commaundeth to keepe the forme of wholeſome doctrine: one ſhould aunſwere, it is not certaine, becauſe the circumſtances rites, &amp; times of it are variable. Which alſo caſteth a ſtrong ſent of the Romiſhe practize, who to make a way to their additions and detractions in the matter of the Sacrament and otherwiſe, flie vnto the circumſtances of time, number, perſons, and ſuch like. Teſt. Rem. in annot. John. 6. verſe 58. the which they ſay the Church may alter and chaunge. The ſecond ſubtletie is, that when the ſtate of the queſtion is propoūded, as that which is the difference betweene vs, the verye poynt of it is ſo obſcurely and doubtfully ſet down, as one can hardly attaine vnto his meaning. For when he ſaith the Magiſtrates

are not in ye ſayde former points tyed to the preciſe forme, &amp;c. He leaueth it doubtfull, whether by points are ment the particular circumſtaunces of policy, gouernment, diſcipline and ceremonies, (which if they be, he commeth no nearer the queſtions, then thinges variable to thinges certaine and vnchangeable): or whether he meaneth the thinges themſelues, to wit, policie, gouernment, diſcipline, which if he do, then he is become an ouerturner of all the aſſertions of former diuines whatſoeuer. For then, if the Magiſtrate think it for order and comelines, Eccleſiaſticall cenſure ſhall be adminiſtred by ciuill perſons, layemen, as he ſpeaketh, men may be excommunicated before they be ſummoned, in a priuate corner, not in the Congregation: then the Magiſtrat may cauſe the Deacons forme to become the forme of the Biſhop, and the Biſhips forme the form of a Deacon. Finally, then the ſeuerall members of Chriſtes bodye their formes, and ſpecificall differences maye be altered and changed as ſeemeth good vnto men: then Princes maye ordayne

Biſhops, as Biſhoppes ſometimes annoynt Princes: Finally, then the ſoueraigne Magiſtrates may them ſelues become Eccleſiaſticall officers, and Church-miniſters, which at once vndermineth not onelye the Church-diſcipline of God, which we require to bee exact, according to God his worde, but alſo euen the formall deſtinction of offices, cenſures and matters Eccleſiaſticall, which all other Churches and euen ours haue eſtabliſhed, are made arbitrarie and changeable, ſeeing they are not tyed to the preciſe forme of theſe things. It is palpable darkneſſe alſo which hee ſayth, that all Churches are not diſciplinated alike, becauſe anye ſet and exact particuler forme thereof, is not commended vnto vs in God his worde. Which if he meane of the ſet forme ofBeza praefat. before the new Teſtament. Hermonia confeſſ. page 53. gal. confeſſ. art. 29. eccleſiaſtical gouernment, all reformed churches acknowledge it, &amp; either haue it or ſeek it, and diſtinguiſh it in al their writings from the variable ceremonies or circumſtances of the ſame, as appeareth by ye places quoted in the margent: if he meane it of circūſtances of places,

times, numbers and ſuch like, he calleth that to queſtion, which none euer made doubt of. Nowe, beſides this confuſion in propounding the Queſtion, the reaſons of the aſſertion are full of vntrueth. Firſt, the allegation of ye alteration of y• Saboth, borowed from y• Jeſuits annot. Apo. 1. 10 (ſauing y• thei haue for ſhame limitted that which he left at large, ſaying, they did it wtout al cōmā-dement of Chriſt which they read of) is not as he ſetteth downe iuſtifiable by ye Scriptures: namely, y• they did it without preſcript cōmandement frō Chriſt. For ſeeing the Apoſtles hauing by God his commaundement, kept the Jewes Saboth for the weeke gone afore, whenGeneſ. 2. the time of the alteration of the ceremony of that particuler day was come, did for obſeruation of the morall commaundement of celebrating one day in ſeuen, ordaine and keepe the next day for the weeke following, calling it and making it the Lordes day, as the otherActes. 20. 7. 1. Cor. 16. 1. 2 was the Lordes Saboth: it is manifeſt that when this cannot be altered, without breache of the morall proportionReuel. 1. 10.
               
of one in ſeuen, that therein they had direction from Chriſte: according to thoſe words: Teaching them to keepe what ſoeuer I commaund you. Mat. 28. 20. If it be aſked where in the Goſpell this is commanded and preſcribed of Chriſt: let him ſhew the like of thoſe which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, 1. Cor. 11 2. &amp; cap. 14. 37. Concerning the change of the time in the Lords ſupper, as it is a meere circumſtance of time, ſo the alteration hath grounde in the ſcripture, becauſe one and the ſame time is not alwaies kept: Act. 3. 42. Act. 20. 7. 11. &amp;c. Neither can that be ſaide to be according to the inſtitution, which being done vpon a particuler cauſe (as all Diuines agree) ſhold not be obſerued wher that cauſe ceaſeth. Thus his aſſertions &amp; reaſons being touched, heere followeth a plaine declaration of the truth, as to ſatiſfie his requeſt or chalenge: Namely, that the whole ſubſtance of the ordinary gouernment of the church, that is to ſay, the vnchaungable lawes of the holy things, of Offices, callings, examinations, abdications, executiōs, &amp; of the

reaſon and diſtinction of euery one of them, is preſcribed of God in his holy Worde, as a perpetuall Lawe vnto his Church: And although euery particuler rite &amp; order (which are variable according to the circumſtance, be not ſo particulerly mentioned) yet are they by certaine generall rules ſo limitted and preſcribed, that no Churche can vſe themExod. 35. 36. &amp; 39. 42. 43. 1. Chron. 13. 2. 10. 11. 1. Chron. 15. 13. 1 chron. 29. verſ. 12. 13 2. Chron. 13. 9. 10 11. 2. Chron. 9. 26., 2. Chro. 29. 25. Neh. 10. 29. at their pleaſure, but ought to frame thē within the boundes ſet vnto them of God, which may appeare by theſe reaſons following. Firſt, ſeeing vnder the Law, God by the miniſtery of Moſes did preciſely this thing for the gouernment of his Church then, ſo that neither Dauid nor Nehemias might alter any thing, but by eſpecial reuelation from God by his Prophets, it were to make God leſſe carefull of his Church vnder the goſpel, &amp; to make the miniſtery of Moſes more excellent then that of Chriſte, vnleſſe in like manner he had performed the ſame. For Chriſte being a King, hath preſcribed1. Cor. 12. 4. Heb. 3. 1. 2. 3. 4. &amp;c. Lawes for his gouernment, and as he is a Lorde, hath ordained the diuers adminiſtrations of his Church, and in

this reſpect, was faithfull as Moſes inHeb. 3. 1. 2. 3. 4. &amp;c. all his houſe. Againe, ſeeing the Apoſtles hauing beene taught of him by the ſpace of forty dayes, the thinges which pertaine to his kingdome, Act. 1. 3. that is, (as the Jeſuites them ſelues are compelled to confeſſe) the whole regiment of Chriſtes Church, did thereuppon ſet down ſuch orders for the ſame. 1. Tim. 3. 15, and giue charge that they ſhoulde be kept vnblameably. 1. Tim. 5. 21.Ta leiponta epithiorthoſe hos ego ſoy dietaxamen. otherwiſe then which, neither Timothy nor Titus might perfect that in the gouernment of the Churche, which the Apoſtles had begun: and ſay, that they which are ſpiritual, muſt acknowledge their orders in this behalfe to bee the commaundementes of our Lorde. 1. Corin. 14. 37. and will their ordinaunces in this behalfe to bee kept, as they deliuered them, 1. Cor. 11. 2. and euen in the matter of the maintenaunce of the miniſtery, woulde ſpeake not according to man, but according to the Law of God and the ordinance of the Lord, 1. Cor. 9. 8. 14. then euery one that is ſpiritual, muſt acknowledge the former

poſition to bee true. Thirdly, ſeeing Chriſte hath expreſly in his Word, ſet downe ſufficient ordinary Miniſteries, of Rom. 12. 5. 6. 7. 1. Cor. 12. 28 Ephe. 4. 11. 1. Tim. 3. &amp; 5. 17. Exhorters, Teachers, Elders, Deacous, with their proper Rom. 12 7. 8. 1. Cor 2. 4. 8 gifts and workes, of exhorting, teaching, diligent watching, &amp; diſtributing, for the adminiſtring of the Act. 3. 42 Math. 18. 17. 18. 1. Cor. 5. 12. Luke. 21. 4. Actes. 6. 3. holy things, as ye word, Prayer, Sacraments, cenſures and treaſury, and hath ordained the Math. 18 17. 18. 1. Tim. 5. 17. 1. Tim. 4. 14. Elderſhip, for y ioynt gouernment in euery particuler Congregation with Actes. 15. 6. &amp; Synodes for matters common to manye Churches: it followeth, that the former aſſertion is vndoubtedly true. Fourthly, ſeeing the Apoſtle Paule (who receiued this as y• reſt of ye Goſpel by reuelation) did vniformally plant ye ſame gouernmēt in all churches, as appeareth by comparing the ſtory of the Actes wt Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 12. 1. Tim. &amp; epiſt. to Titus, it is manifeſt, they had a forme preſcribed thē by Chriſt to follow, euē as Moſes did all things according to y• pattern ſhewed him in the moūt. Againe, ſeeing it is not in the power of man to alter or change theſe offices by addition or detraction,

becauſe they cannot gyue nor take awayRom. 12. 4. 5 1. Cor. 12. 3. 4. 5. members to and from Chriſtes bodie, but all the gyftes are from one ſpirite, the faculties from one God, the adminiſtrations from one Lorde: and finally, all Church Miniſteries muſt be frō heauen and not from earth, as Chriſt ſayth, &amp; the Scribes them ſelues confeſſe. Then isMath. 21. 25. Iohn. 1. 25. there in the worde of God, ſuch an vnchaungeable rule of gouernment, as is before declared? Laſtly, ſeeing God in altering the outward face of his church vnder the Goſpell, diuerſe from that vnder the law, in regarde of ye ceremonies aboliſhed, and of things according to the riches and ſimplicitie of the Goſpell, inlarged: did as well keep the ſubſtance of the Churches adminiſtration, (namely, in ordayning for Deut. 31. Ephe. 4. 11. Prieſts, Paſtors; for teaching Nehe. 8. Ephe. 4. 11. Leuits or Doctors of y• law, Teachers; for 2. Chron. 2. King. 6. 32 Act 13. 15. and. 4. 8. 1. Cor. 12. 28 rulers of y• Sinagog, Churh-gouernors or Elders; for their Ne. 13. 4. Actes. 6. 2. Chron. 23 leuitical lokers to y• treaſury, Deacons, for their Ezra. 10. 8 Luke. 22 66. Act. 5. 27, 1. Tim. 4. 14▪
                preſbytery, the elderſhip). As he kept the holy thinges to be adminiſtred, that is, for the lawe and the Prophets, together with them ye writings of

the new Teſtament for the Paſſeouer, &amp; Circumciſion Baptiſme, &amp; the ſupper of the Lorde; Lu. 21. 14 1. Cor. 16. 1. for their giftes of God, gathering for the Saintes, or Churchtreaſury; for their Leu. 7 18 Ierem. 36. 5. Math. 5. 23. 1. Cor. 11. 28 ſuſpenſion from the Tēple-ſacrifices, our ſeparation from y• Lords ſupper: for Ge. 27. 14. Iohn. 9 34. 22. Mat 18 17. 1. Cor. 5. their caſting out of y• Synagogue &amp; cutting off from the people, our excommunication. It is euident that that which God kept for the time of the Goſpell, he did in perfect wiſdom ordayne and preſcribe, and that which Chriſt did inrich and inlarge, he woulde not haue men cut of and aboliſh. Wherfore, if they will ſtill rowle the ſtone of mans power, to alter and chaunge this order of God, let them ſhewe how men can take away that which God hath ſet1. Cor. 12. 28 in his Church: let them ſhew how that is not perpetual, which is grounded vppon thoſe gyftes which ſerue for the ordinarie neceſſityes of the church in al times and places, yea, let them ſhew how they can more wyſely inſtruct the people with doctrine, feede them wirh exhortation, rule their ſoules with ſpirituall power, chaſtize them with an holy rodde,

and prouide for their earthlye neceſſities: then the Lorde hath done, and ſtill offereth to doe by the worde of knowledge in his Teachers, by the worde of wiſedome in his Paſtors, by the continuall watche of his Elders, by the ſpirituall keyes of his kingdome, and by his mercifull and liberall prouiding for the needie. And if it be a ſhame to preferre mans wiſedome before the wiſedome of God, at the leaſt let them declare by what authoritye they will compell the Church to refuſe the ſtrong arme of God, for the weake arme of fleſhe and bloude. To theſe reaſons maye be added the teſtimonies of the Fathers, as of CYPRIAN. IN SERMONE DE BAPTIS. CHRIST. The Chriſtian religion ſhall finde that out of this Scripture, rules of all doctrine haue ſpronge, and that from hence doth ſpring and hither doth retourne, whatſoeuer the Eccleſiasticall diſcipline doth contayne. And the ſame authour, DE PRESCRIPT. ADVERS. HERET.
               
               We may not giue our ſelfe the liberty to bring in any thing that other men bring of their will, we haue the Apoſtles for Authours, which themſelues brought nothing of their owne will, but the Diſcipline which they receiued of Chriſt, they deliuered faythfully to the people. Which ſentences, ſeeing they can not be vnderſtoode of the circumſtaunces, muſt be taken of the Subſtantiall poyntes which wee haue declared. So the ſame Authour ſpeaking of the like matter, EPISTOLA LIB. 1. EPIST. 8. It is adulterouſe, it is wicked, it is ſacriligious, whatſoeuer is ordayned by humaine fury, that the diuine dispoſition ſhoulde be violated.
                To the lyke effect LIBERIVS the Romane Biſhop, requyreth of the Emperour, To leaue the trueth as it is in this behalfe, or elſe to make all newe. THEODORET
                in the ſixeteene Chapiter of the ſeconde booke of the Eccleſiaſtical hiſtory, which their iudgment ſhall be moſte manyfeſtly auouched in the particular parts of this diſcipline of God, which followe.

And thus much for the firſt and moſte generall point, which giueth both light and ſtrength vnto the reſt. Now becauſe him ſelfe willeth the particuler plat to be layed and prooued in the particulers which hath long ago beene done in many bookes, and namely in the booke of Eccleſiasticall Diſcipline, which hath receiued no anſwere as yet, as whatſoeuer on their ſide (of any worthineſſe) hath ſeene the light hath beene aunſwered, it ſhal be very profitable both to aunſwere him and to maintaine the trueth in thoſe particulers wherein hee ſeeketh to vndermine the ſame: and firſt of the generall property of the Offices, and then of the Offices themſelues.
            
               Of Election with conſent of the people.
               COncerning Election, the wordes of this anſwerer be theſe, Pag. 83. I doe thinke verily that in no Church the whole number of the people are permitted to haue a free Election of their Paſtor, &amp;c. Pag. 88. Alſo her Maieſtie,
                  
                  being the head member of this church, whether ſhe ſhall be alowed a voice by her highnes proctor, among the people of one pariſh alone, or in al pariſhes in the realm, in choſing their miniſter, &amp; what voice? whether a negatiue, coūtermāding al others or no? or whether her highnes ſhal haue no ſuffrage therein at all? Both which, if they be not to the derogation of her highneſſe prerogatiue royall, let indifferent and wiſe men iudge. And a little before in the ſame page: I will only put this great canoniſt in minde, of the 13. chap. of the counſell of Laodicea, which doth forbid theſe elections by the multitude or people, which, as Origin ſayth, is pricked forwarde or caried away, with clamors, fauour or rewarde. And to the ſame effect, page. 97. Item page 99. he obiecteth thus. So that by this reckoning, men women and children (for all the faithfull bee intereſted:) ſhall haue voyces in election of their Miniſters; If any diſſent, all muſt be daſhed if we followe that rule. Againe page 100.

                  For his flocke is but an handfull in compariſon of hypocrites, and many are called but few are choſen: neither are al true beleeuers always indowed, with ſuch meaſure of wiſedome and diſcretion, as that they are able to ſounde the aptneſſe of a man in learning for the miniſtery: nor yet haue all ſo profited in true mortification, as that they can weane them-ſelues from thoſe diſordered affections, which cleaue faſt to euery one of vs, either more or leſſe, ſo long as we remaine in this world, and therefore in ſuch caſes the mo that do deal in any actiō, the more diſorderly &amp; troubleſome for the moſt part it falleth out to be. To the ſeconde I ſay, it contayneth a promiſe of ſuch quietneſſe and peaceable iſſues of this populer election, as if you turne ouer eccleſiasticall hyſtories, neuer or ſeldome hath happened but the clean contrary. And a little after. Now it had beene very requiſite that our Authour, for the appointing of theſe democratical elections the better vnto vs, ſhould with
                  
                  proofe out of ſcripture for euery particuler, haue ſhewed whether Women or children of ſome reaſonable diſcretion, ſhoulde haue voyces in the election of their Miniſter? whether he ſhould be choſen by all, by the greater part, or by the better part? Whether the wiues voyce ſhoulde bee accounted ſeuerall, or but one with her husbande, or whether ſhee mght diſcent from her husband, or the father from the ſonne? Whether the Patron not dwelling in the Pariſh ſhall haue a voyce, or dwelling there but a ſingle voyce? Whether the greater number of voyces ſhall bee accounted in reſpect of all the Electors, or onely in reſpect of him which is to bee choſen, hauing more voyces then anye other hathe? Whether all abſent, ſhall bee accounted to diſcent, or to aſſent? Whether ſicke men or other neceſſarily imployde that would come and cannot, maye ſende the Proctor beeing no Paryſhioner, or compromit their voyce to a Pariſhioner? Item Page 94. Diſcourſing
                  
                  largely about the places of Scripture alleadged to this purpoſe. He ſayth: that courſe of election mentioned in the Actes, was not vndertaken for ſatisfying anye expreſſe commaundement by Chriſt, but vpon an eſpeciall occaſion of the mutiny of the Greeks againſt the Hebrewes. Againe in that page 94. that of the Actes, ſpeaketh of Deacons onely, and is not read elſewhere in all poynts to haue been obſerued, either in choſing of an Apoſtle Act. 1. of Miniſters, Acts. 2. or of Biſh. Titus. 1. There alſo the whole multitude made choiſe without the Apoſtles, who mēt therby to auoid al ſuſpicion of corrupt dealing. Which two circumſtaunces, no man will I hope require, in the choſing eyther of a Biſhop or a Miniſter: eſpecially that the Biſhop and other of the Cleargie ſhall bee debarred from any ſtroke in that action, ſeeing therein there cannot be the lyke cauſe of ſuſpicion. Alſo the Apoſtle calleth them togeather, and preſcribed vnto them what they ſhoulde doe in that poynt of externall

policie, and that according to the preſent occaſion offered, without any preſcript worde, but onely by the inſtinct of Gods ſpirite. Further, that the Apoſtles ſet out the qualitie of the men to be choſen, but tied them to no certayne forme of election to be obſerued, neither doe we reade what forme of election they then vſed. Againe, that the Diſciples were to looke out and choſe ſuch, as they thought fitte to be truſted with the Church-ſtocke, but the Apoſtles reſerued to them-ſelues the appoynting of them to their office, if they ſhould be founde to be ſuch as were deſcribed. Moreouer, that the Deacons were appoynted for the further eaſe of the Apoſtles in ſome part of their function. Laſtly, that the diſciples preſented them to the Apoſtles cenſures: who by impoſition of handes did as it were conſecrate and authorize them to the function of Deaconſhip. Now if by this act our authour mind ſo hard to curbe vp al churches, as that he will accuſe thē to

giue a counterbuff to the holy ghoſt, which in their ordinations doe not agree herewith in all circumſtaunces: or that he will tell vs that ſomething extraordinary was here in this action not to bee followed, then muſt hee ſhewe by direct Scripture what was ordinary and what was extraordinary, and muſt reconcile other places of Scripture concerning like action, which doe not agree in all poyntes with this. In the firſt of the Actes, two were preſented, one is choſen by lot and no impoſition of handes: heere ſeuen are choſen, the manner not ſet downe by the multitude, and being preſented to the Apoſtles, they all appoynt them and lay their handes on them. In the 14. of Actes, Paule and Barnabas are ſayde Chirotoneſaſthai autois preſbuterois, and to haue faſted, but no mention is made of impoſion of handes: heere all the Apoſtles did appoynt thē 
                     Hous kataſteſomen. In the firſt to Titus, he onely is willed to appoint prieſtes, Hina cataſteſes preſbuterous, according as Paule preſcribed

vnto him. Nay, let him ſhewe vnto me any two refourmed Churches of diuers nations, iumpe in all circumſtaunces heereaboutes, or anye one of them which permitteth this action, (without intermedling of the cheefe Paſtours) vnto all the Diſciples or multitude of beleeuers in the ſayde Church, which yet haue an intereſt in hauing a good Miniſter, but as I take it, the cheefe ſwaye and moderating of ſuch actions, are in all other refourmed Churches in ſuche men, to whome this truſt is eſpecially recommended. And hath not likewiſe (for auoyding of ſundry inconueniences) the whole Churche and Realme of Englande by Parliament (whereunto euery man in the eye of the law is ſaide to haue conſented) repoſed this truſt in a fewe choſen men of eccleſiaſtical functiō? Euen M. Beza him ſelfe, concerning the place of theLib. confeſ. cap. 5. Actes, doth ſay, There is no cauſe why hereof anye man ſhoulde preſcribe anye ſpeciall rule, but if the conſcience be vpright, it will be eaſie

to ſet downe what is expedient, according to the circumſtaunces of tyme and places. The reply vnto the former words.
               Although the aunſwerer in this large and tediouſe diſcourſe, hath brought no new matter in ſubſtance, which hath not alreadie beene ſufficiently refelled, ſo as no new encounter by publike writing (as a ſupply) hath beene made againſt the ſame, yet ſhall it not be without fruite to the reader: Firſt, to note out his tumultuous and inſincere dealing, his contrarietie with him ſelfe, his agreement with the Papiſtes, and then (hauing particulerly layd
                     •
                   open the nakedneſſe of his ſeuerall obiections) briefly as before, to ſet downe the plaine &amp; ſimple trueth out of the Scripture. His tumultuous and inſincere dealing appeareth, in that, pretending to haue greatlye ſifted the wrytinges of this controuerſie, and to haue exact knowledge of the orders of reformed Churches in this behalfe, hee is not aſhamed in ſtead of incountringe with the truth, to frame him ſelfe an vnknowne aduerſary,

that is, in ſteed of ouerthrowing the conſent of people in Church-elections, to make warre againſt a meere populer Election, not gouerned with the fore-direction of the Elders, which hath no ground in the ſcriptures, and was neuer maintained (as him ſelfe confeſſeth) but by Anabaptiſtes: and in ſteede of manly buckling with the ſubſtantiall pointes of Church-election, with the foreleading of the Preſbytery, with the due conſent of the people, cowardly to betake himſelf vnto the changeable circumſtances of the ſame; as who ſhould preſent, the Elders or the people; howe the people ſhoulde ſignify their conſent by lifting vp their handes, or otherwiſe by themſelues or by proctors, and diuers ſuch other. Which in the particuler anſwere following ſhall be declared, howe according to the word of God they may vpon diuers circumſtances, be diuerſly carried. His contrariety to him felfe is apparant by theſe three partie-coloured aſſertions. Firſt, that the people did choſe without the Apoſtles. Secondly, they were to chooſe, but the Apoſtles
                  
                  reſerued to themſelues the appointing of thē to their office, if they ſhold be found to be ſuch as were deſcribed. Thirdly, that the people preſented them to the Apoſtles cenſures. For, that hee ſayth, they choſe without the Apoſtles, is directly contrary to that he ſayth, they preſented them to the Apoſtles Cenſures, ſo that their Election was to be diſanulled and made none, vnleſſe by the examination of the Apoſtles they were founde aunſwerable to their deſcription. His agreement with the papiſts, and namely with the Romiſh Remiſts Teſtament, doth notably appeare, in that they appoynting, (as he doth) the fift verſe of the 1. of Titus, to the conſent of the people in the Election of their Miniſter, they doe more breefly, but as fully and plainly, and with more curteſy to the trueth ſet downe both his aſſertions, reaſons and auncient Teſtimonies, in theſe fewe words following.
               
                  And here it ſeemeth that he did not only conſecrate them whom the people had elected before, but him ſelfe alſo made choyſe of the perſons, no
                  
                  mention being heere made of any other election populer, which though it vvere long vſed in the primitiue Church, yet for diuers cauſes, and ſpecially for continuall tumults, partialities, and diſorders which Saint Auguſtine much complaineth of in his time, was iuſtly taken away, and other better meanes of their deſignement appointed. See concil. Laodic. cap. 12. 13. So much the Papiſts. Again, how he iumpeth with the ſpirite of theſe Jeſuites (ſauing that ſtill they yeelde more to the trueth then he) in ſaying, That the Apoſtles ſhewed the people what to do, without any preſcript worde, but onely by the inſtinct of Gods ſpirite: may appeare by their words which they vſe vpon the like occaſion of Peter, in their annotation on the 15. verſe of the 1. Chapter of the Actes: Which Peter (ſaie they) did, not vpon cōmaundement of Chriſte written, but by ſuggeſtion of God his ſpirit, and by vnderſtanding of the Scriptures of the old Teſtamēt to that purpoſe. So far the papiſts: And thus much generallye of his diſcourſe.

Now of his particuler obiections, the firſt is, that he thincketh in no Church the whole number of people to haue free election of their Paſtor. If by free election he meane the due conſent of the people, either he ſpeaketh againſt his knowledge, or he knoweth not that he pretendeth, ſeeing their confeſſions other their writinges and practize, do (in the knowledge of all thoſe which know any thing in this matter,) euidently conuince him, as may appeare by the quotations in theHarmonia confeſ. pag. 43. Sect. 11. Hel. 1. Art. 16 Beza confeſ. 5 point cap. 35. P. Mart. in 1. Cor. 16 Muſc. in title of the Miniſters. margent. If he meane, that the people ſhould beare the whole ſwaye without the gouernment and direction of the Elders, hee miſſeth the marke whereat hee aymeth. Concerning the Queenes Maieſties prerogatiue royall, which he would gladly oppone againſt the cōſent of the people in Church-elections: Firſt, he could not be ignorant but that all acknowlege that the Chriſtian magiſtrat as a principal member of ye congregatiō where he is, ought to haue an intereſt in ye election anſwerable to his place, aſwel for aduiſe as conſent. Secondly, the ſupreme magiſtrate, according to the high

authority which God hath committed vnto him ouer all Churches in his dominions, both lawfully may &amp; by duety ought, not onely to diſanull what-ſoeuer election the Elders and people haue vnlawfully made, but alſo by his ciuil preeminence to compell them to make a newe election according to the Worde of God. Which, as it is as much as the ſole election by the Byſhop, giueth to the Prince, yea or rather more: ſo if they can ſhew any further thing due vnto the Magiſtrate, all ſuch as with a ſincere minde, ſeeke for the reformation of the Church, are alwayes as readye with all humbleneſſe to giue it, as they will be willing with ſingleneſſe to ſhew it. To the place of the Councell of Laodicea and Origin, let this be the aunſwere. The meaning of the Councell, in thoſe words, Non populo concedendum electionem facere, &amp;c. We ought not to giue leaue to the people to make electiō,
                   is, they ſhold not bear ye whol ſway without the gouernment or direction of the Elders, and not to ſhut out the due conſent of the people, as is manifeſt, by

the counſelles going afore, as ſhall hereafter appeare, againſt which, this counſell woulde not haue decreed, vnleſſe it had repealed the ſame or ſhewed ſome reaſon, but moſt of all by Counſelles following, who haue authorized the conſent of the people: and namely, the 4. of Carthage, which was confirmed in the ſixt generall Counſell at Trullum, together with that of Laodicia, which would not haue confirmed contrary decrees. The wordes are theſe, When he (ſpeaking of the biſhop) ſhal be examined in al theſe and founde fully inſtructed, then let him bee ordayned with the conſent (Clericorum &amp; laicorum) of the Clearks &amp; lay men. As for that of Origin, it is nothing to the purpoſe, which hee ſayth of the people, except there could be ſome priuiledge ſhewed that partly the ſame, or ſuch like as daungerous infirmities were not to be founde in a Byſhop. The next reaſon maketh as much againſt the election of Byſhops as of the people, ſeeing they may bee hypocrites as well as the people, &amp; in all mens iudgement one man is ſooner carried with ambition &amp;

couetouſneſſe, then an whole Church of godly Elders, and Chriſtian people vnto diſorder. And if for the contentions &amp; ſtriuings of y• people, ye church may abrogate the conſent of ye people in Eccleſiaſtical elections, thē may ſhe by the ſame authority, diſanull Synods and Counſelles, which as often haue beene full of rage and vprores: and of which Nazianzen ſaith, He neuer ſawe good iſſue, but that thorough merueilous ambition &amp; deſire of contention, thinges out of order were not remedied but made worſe. Epiſt. 42. ad procopt.
                   Neither for this cauſe, as the promiſe of God made to counſels is not lightly to bee regarded, ſo ought hee not thus prophanely to reiect it when it is brought to vphold yt conſent of ye people, Further, wher as he ſaith that Churches both of elder &amp; later times, haue for that cauſe abandoned ſuch elections, it is to be thought he can bring as much for the proofe of it, as hee hath already alleadged, which is nothing. Whatſoeuer hee can doe, the Doctrine of the auncient Fathers, and the examples of the elder Churches is farre otherwiſe.

For Chryſoſtome vpon Actes 1. aunſwering the Queſtion, why Peter communicated the election with the Diſciples, ſaith, Leaſt the matter ſhould be turned into a brawle, and haue fallen to a contention. For the elder Churches he cannot be ignoraunt, how many haue beene troubled with ſuch inconueniences, and yet haue not ſought ſuch extream remedies; nay, the example of good Conſtantine the Emperour is notable, who when the citizens of Nicodemia had choſen an Arrian, a runnagate and a rayler on the Emperour, he did not take awaye the Churches conſent, but by his Letters according to his duety, mooued them to a newe. Theodoret lib. 1. Cap. 19. Againe, if theſe infirmities of the people bee a good reaſon to take away their libertye in the Election of their Miniſters, then the contrary vertues, which oftentimes haue beene found in them, in ſtaying the rage of the Scribes and Phariſies, Mat 21. 26. Actes 3. 26. in preferring catholique perſons before Arrians, and in being themſelues catholiques when their Byſhops haue been heretiques, Zozo.
                  
                  lib. 7. cap, 7. Theodo. lib. 2. cap. 7. is a good reaſon to maintaine their liberty 
                     •
                  till. As concerning his queſtions following, which as they declare rather a mind giuen to cauell at that which he cannot by ſound reaſon auoyde, ſo are they eaſilye aunſwered out of the courſe and proportion of trueth in the Scripture. Women not being in the ſeate of Magiſtracy are forbidden by the Apoſtle to ſpeak in ſuch publique aſſemblies, and exerciſe authority ouer men. Which rule being ſpoken of y• mother, doth alſo barre children and ſuch as ſhall bee in greater ſubiection, vntill by yeares and Chriſtian knowledge, they ſhall by the iudgement of the Church, growe vnto the liberty of Chriſtians in that behalfe: and then if they followe the greater and better part, their ſentence ought to preuaile. As for the Question of the Patron, ſeeing it is a conſtitution not of God but of man, let the wiſe and ſkilfull lawyers define, ſo they do no iuiury to the holie trueth of GOD and his Church. The next Queſtion is vayne and friuolous. For firſt, by due authoritye,

diuers be propounded and the Church conſent to haue one of them, it muſt needes bee, that hee which is approued of the Elders and hath moſt voices, muſt receiue the charge, ſeeing that can not be ſayde to be done with generall conſent (which thing the Scripture giueth to Church-elections) where the feweſt, but where the moſte directed aright, do agree. And as for them that be abſent, ſicke, or imployde, if they haue any thing of waight to ſignify to the Church, the Church is to harken vnto them by whome ſoeuer they ſende their aduiſe. And as it is no reaſon that when eyther ſickneſſe or theire duetie to the Church, doe withhold them that ſhoulde abridge that libertie: ſo if by negligence or wilfulneſſe, they bee abſente after competent warning, the whole Churche is not to depend vppon them, who doe not ſo much looſe as caſt awaye theire intereſt in the election. Laſtly, who ſeeth not that anye idle brayne may make theſe and ſuch like demaundes, both againſt the rules in the Scriptures, and the obſeruation in

the primitiue Church. Where he ſayth, that, in the ſixth of the Actes, was not done by anie expreſſe commaundement of Chriſte, but vppon the mutinye of the Greekes agaynſt the Hebrewes: as it is to bee graunted, that it was an occaſion why the people did preſent, ſo, that was no cauſe of their free conſent, is manifeſt by the other places, where that is maintained without any particuler cauſe, Actes 1. and Cap. 14. If Actes 6. ſpeake of Deacons onely, yet Actes 1. Actes 14. ſpeake of Apoſtles and Elders and theire election by the conſent of the people. And if the peoples conſent is not to be ſhut out in the Deacons, which leſſe importeth their libertye and ſaluation, much leſſe are they to be debarred in their Paſtors and Elders, vppon whome, as Peter ſayth, the flocke dependeth. Where hee ſayth the1. Peter. 9. people choſe without the Apoſtles, it is ſhewed already, howe his owne wordes checke him, and the trueth is plainly to bee ſeene in the Texte, that neyther the people without the Apoſtles directing them, nor the Apoſtles without the

people conſenting vnto them, made that Election. As for ſhutting out of the Byſhops and Church-gouernours it is meruaile why hee ſhoulde feare it, vnleſſe iealouſy which is fearefull where no feare is, hath blinded his eyes. That of the Apoſtles doing without any expreſſe worde from Chriſtes commaundement, is aunſwered before in that alleadged concerning the Saboth Cap. 1. and is further manifeſt by the example of the Apoſtle Paule, who beeing not with the other Apoſtles, yet followed that rule, Acts 14. That he ſaith, there is no certaine forme of their Election: hee is refuted by his owne wordes following, where he ſheweth out of the Text, their election to haue beene of this ſort, that vppon the inſtruction of the Apoſtles the people in preſenting them, neceſſarily therewithall gaue their conſent, as the Apoſtles did in accepting them to their ordination. As for agreement of all Churches in all circumſtances of this point, he hath his aunſwere before, but that he willeth to be ſhewed what is ordinary, and what is extraordinary.

His aunſwere is, that the Apoſtles inſtructed the people, and they conſented, which is ordinary, as appeareth in that it is kept in all Elections of the Church, Actes 1. Actes 14. and 2. Cor. 9. 19. but that which was extraordinary, was the preſentation of the people, the ſpecial cauſe whereof him ſelfe hath declared out of the text. In the reſt, it is ſtraunge, that hee requireth reconciliation where there is no repugnaunce, but all the places ioyne hande in hande together. For ye firſt in ye election of the Apoſtle, it lay in the liberty of ye church, onely to chooſe ſome. For the Lot beeing the voyce of God, was to aſſigne which of them ſhould bee the Apoſtle: and this circumſtance maketh ſtrongly for the trueth which is mayntayned. For, if where God is to ſtrike the principall ſtroke, yet the peoples conſent is to bee taken as farre as may bee; howe muche more is the authoritye of the whole Church to be ſought for, where the Election is onelye to bee done by men as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh Galat. 1. The obiection of the manner of the

election, Actes 6. is aunſwered before. As for the number of 7. who is ſo ſimple, as not to knowe that the number is to be varied, according to the ſpreade and greatneſſe of the Churches where they are: and the multitude of cauſes &amp; affayres to be dealt withall? As for no impoſition of handes in the firſt and 14. of the Actes, it is too ſimple and ſcarſe tollerable in a catechiſt, ſeeing ſuch thinges are to be gathered out of other places: otherwiſe one may thinke there were no praiers in the celebrating of the Communion, Acts 20. becauſe there is no mention of it in that place which yet were very abſurd, conſidering that the order which S. Luke deſcribed in the Churche at Hieruſalem, prooueth thatActes. 2. 42. they continued in breaking of bread and praier. And if ſuch ſeely obiections need to bee aunſwered, as inforcing diuers formes of elections, then alſo wee may proue diuerſities of Communions, ſome of the cup and bread together, ſome of the cup alone, ſome of breade alone, by Act. 2. Act. 20. 1. Cor. 12. Wher he ſaith Titus only is willed to appoint prieſts,

belike the Jeſuites tranſlation was before him, when he tranſlated Preſbyterous; Prieſtes and that ſo dazeled his eyes, that hee coulde not conſider the wordes following, that he ſhoulde do as hee had ſet him an order, which was not to do it without the conſent of ye church, except Paul would lift vp Titus aboue himſelfe &amp; Barnabas, who choſe Elders by voices. And if the anſwerer had beneActes. 15. ignorant of ye vſe of ye ſcripture, which oftentimes giueth y• action to ye principal directer, which yet belongeth to many more, as Paule in one place ſaith, Tim. receiued grace by the laying on of his hādes: 2. Tim. 6. (which in 1. Tim. 4. he declareth to haue beene done by ye laying on of ye handes of the Elderſhip) yet his ſkil in Logick ſhould haue ſhewed him ye deceit of this Sophiſm. Titus appointed Elders, therefore he appoynted thē without the conſent of ye people. Of this kind are al the reaſons following: As: al reformed Churches iumpe not in al circumſtaunces, therefore they ſhut out the conſent of the people. In other Churches the Elders of euery congregation

haue the chiefe directiō in the electione yet not without the conſent of ye people, therfore it is fitly according, to their example ordered, that the Church ſhoulde once for all, gyue vp their intereſt into one mans handes, for the continual election of many Churches. The ſentence of Maiſter Beza doth very fitly require an vpright conſcience, to ſet down what is expedient, according to the circumſtance of time and place. Which if it had beene found in him at this time, and in this matter, he would not haue ſhut his eies, againſt the manifeſt light of words going before, which declare manyfeſtly that it is a perpetuall and vnchaungeable poynt in Church-elections, which neither Church nor magiſtrate may alter, that they be made with the conſent of the people. His wordes in that place are theſe: Then therefore, not in Churches buylded vp, muſt all thinges be committed vnto the ſuffrages of the multitude, neither yet are the Paſtours to be choſen without the conſent of the whole Church: But all thinges are ſo to be moderated of the Elders and Christian Magiſtrates, that neither
                  
                  they bring in tyrannie into the Church, (which ſurely ſhould be done, if they ſhoulde call any vnto publike function of their owne wil, neglecting the conſent of the multitude, neither that the popular ſtate of the Church degenerate into popular rule. Neither are theſe wordes of Beza, onely ſufficient to ſhew his corruption, but the title of the chap. where he taketh this obiection, doth miniſter ſufficient aunſwere, ſeeing it declareth that Beza in all that place, ſpeaketh not of the conſent of the people, which he made perpetuall in the chap. before, but of the maner how he gaue their voyces, which is but a circumſtaunce. And thus much both generally and particularly, for the vnfolding of his vnfit and ſlender allegations. Now followeth a confirmatition of the trueth it ſelfe, which is. It is ſubſtantiall &amp; vnchaungeable in churchelections, that they be made by the body of euery Churche, the Elders directing the people, and them-ſelues to giue their free conſent. The reaſons of which aſſertion are theſe. Firſt, what ſoeuer are the wayes of the Apoſtles in

ordinary Church-gouernement that is thus to be followed, that which they did ordinarily &amp; vnchangeably, is ordinarily &amp; vnchangeably to be done, that which they did vpon circumſtances, when thoſe circumſtances fall out, as appeareth by theſe places 1. cor. 4. 17. Which ſhall put you in remēbrance of my wayes in Chriſt, as I teach euery where in euery Church. And 1. Cor. 11. 2. I praiſe you brethren, that you remember me in all thinges, &amp; hold faſt the ordināces as I deliuered thē vnto you. And Phi. 4. 9 Which you haue learned &amp; receiued, &amp; heard &amp; ſeene in me, thoſe things do, &amp; the God of peace be with you. 2. Tim. 3. 10. But thou haſt ſtep by ſtep attained vnto (or fully known) my doctrine, &amp; courſe, purpoſe, faith, long-ſuffering, loue, patience, &amp;c. Tit. 1. 5. Appoint Elders as I haue ſet thee an order. 1. Tim. 3. 17. Theſe thinges haue I written, that thou maiſt know how to behaue thy ſelfe in the howſe of God. Now that theſe were the vnch hangeable waies of the Apoſtles in elections, is cleare by the examples which haue been touched before. For in the 1. of the Actes, the Apoſtles by Peter directing the action, &amp;

in the ſixt by him or ſome other (for they could not al direct &amp; ſpeak at once) what ſoeuer were the variable circumſtaunces, they kept this inuiolable, that they people woulde giue their conſent in the election: And in the 14, chap. ſuch circumſtaunces ceaſing, they obſerued this thing inuiolable Katapolin, Church by Church. Secondly, If it were not ynough for a temporary charge to haue praiſe in the Goſpell thorowe all the Churches,: but as the Apoſtle ſayth, ſuch a one was alſo choſen by the conſent of the Churches, to be a fellow with him-ſelfe, in carying the liberality of the Churches: then much leſſe can it be ynough in a perpetuall charge of ſuch waight vnto the Church, to depend vppon the iudgement of one or many without the conſent of the Church: but ye firſt is true. 2. cor. 8. 19. therefore the ſecond. Thirdly, if in euerye matter of great waight and importaunce, belonging to the whole body of the Church, whether ſeuerally in one particuler congregation, or ioyntly in many, the conſent of the people by the whole courſe of Churchgouernment,

in the obſeruation of the Apoſtles was requyred, then the ſame is to be kept in this action, which concerneth the particuler Church and common aſſemblye as much as anye other. Now that the peoples cōſent was ſo requyred, is euident by this induction following. So Peter yeeldeth an account to them of the circumciſion, of his going into the Gentiles, and ſatiſfieth them before the Church. Acts. 11. 2. 18. The Church ſent foorth Barnabas to Antiochia, ver. 22. The churches of Antiochia, Actes 15. ſent Paule and Barnabas to Hieruſalem, about the controuerſie of Circumciſion. And when they came to Hieruſalem, they were receiued by the Church, and of the Apoſtles and Elders verſ. 4. And after the Apoſtles and Elders had come togeather to looke to that matter, and had diſcuſſed the ſame: then it ſeemed good to the Apoſtles and Elders, with the whole Church, to ſende choſen men of their owne companye to Antiochia with Paule and Barnabas: then they wright the decree vnto the churches after this maner: The Apoſtles,
                  
                  Elders and the brethren. So in excommunication their conſent is required 1. Cor 5. 4. 7. 12. So in abſolution, the Church doth forgiue ye offenſe &amp; ratify their loue towards him who hath offended, 2. Cor. 2. 7. 8. So in calling vppon the Miniſter to execute his charge, the Apoſtle woulde not him ſelfe, but willeth the Churrh to ſay to Archippus: Take heede to thy miniſtery which thou haſt receiued in the Lorde, that thou fulfill it. Coloſ. 4. 17. Laſtly, ſeeing in the iudgement of all interpreters, according to the trueth, the Apoſtle reckoning vp three manner of callings: the firſt of man, that is, mās ordinaunce: the ſeconde by man, that is, from Gods ordinaunce by the meanes of the Church: the third by Jeſus Chriſt that is immediat without the meanes of the Church, doth therby ſignify that the two latter only belong vnto church-elections, becauſe that in the Church none muſt take any honor but he which is calledHeb. 4. as was Aaron: it followeth neceſſarily, that their ſole-election which by their own confeſſion is the ordinance of man, to be vnlawful; and that which is by the

conſent of the people, according to the Apoſtles obſeruation (as they themſelues cannot deny) to be the onelye ordinary full way of calling allowed of God. This point alſo hath ſuch manifeſt witneſſe of antiquitie, as before all equall Judges, the cauſe muſt paſſe on our ſide, For Counſels theſe twoo following ſhall witneſſe, not onely them-ſelues, but by their mouthes the Decrees and cenſures of the Church from time to time. 2. Tom, concil. can. 8. The councell of Paris. Let none be ordayned againſte the will of y• citizens: but to whom the election of the people, and of the Clearkes with moſte full conſent, haue requyred. And before they ſay of this, it is their decree, that according to the Canons of the decrees it be obſerued. Orleans. Canon. 10. 11. Let it not be lawfull to get anye Biſhopricke by rewardes, or by other procurement: but by the will of the King, according to the election of the Cleargie, and of the people. And after: beſides this according as the old Canons haue decreed, no Biſhop maye
                  
                  bee giuen vnto the people againſte their will. Ignatius ad Philadelp. It is meet that you as thoſe which be the Church of God, ſhould chooſe by voyces your Biſhops.
                  Chierot
                        •
                     
                     neſai. And the Greeke ſcholiaſt on the 14. of the Actes ſaith, it is to bee noted, that the Diſciples with faſting and prayers, did make election by voyces. Cyprian,
                   hauing labored to prooue that the Church ought not to communicate with their Miniſters which had ſacrificed to Idols, becauſe they had power to chooſe new, ſayth: God commaundeth the Prieſt to be ſet before the whole Synagogue, that is, doth ordayne and ſhew that brieſtly ordinations ought not to be made, but with
                  Mathetai. Plebe. 
                  the conſcience of the people aſſiſting, that the people beeinge preſent, eyther the crimes of the euill ſhoulde be detected, or the good ſhoulde be publiſhed, and that ſhoulde be a iuſt and lawefull ordination, which hath beene examined by the ſuffrage and iudgement of all men, which afterwarde according to diuine inſtitutions, is obſerued in the Actes of the Apoſtles,
                  Magiſteria. 
                  &amp;c. Epiſt. Lib. 1. Cap. 4. So Gregor. Naz. in apologet. Chriſoſt. lib, 3.

                  Sacerd. So much for election, the church offices follow.
            
            
               That euery Miniſter, of diuine ſeruice in the publique Congregation, ought to be apt to preach.
               COncerning this poynt, the wordes of the aunſwerer are theſe. page. 2. And as it ſeemeth ſuch as Paule propoundeth to euery Miniſter, as a perfect idaea which is requiſite in him: which is, that he bee able to teache ſounde doctrine, to comfort, to correct, to inſtruct, to conuince any errour. And page. 3. For the iſſue ought to haue beene to this effect, whether it be ſimplie vnlawfull, that one ſhold be admitted to miniſter the Sacramentes, which is not ſufficiently inabled Orthotomein, that is, to deuide the Worde of God aright, and is alſoRom. 15. 4. 1. Tim. 3. 16. 1. Tim. 3. 26. Tit. 1. 9. 
                     Didacticos Kai elegticos, able to teach the truth and conuince errours, and to correct ſinne, &amp; to inſtruct to vertue and good life, and to comfort the weake, or elſe, whether it be expedient

that all the pariſhes in Englande, either not able to ſuſteine ſuch a learned Miniſter, or for the ſcarſitye of ſuch ſo wel qualified, not able to procure one, ſhoulde be deſtitute of publique prayer, and adminiſtration of Sacramentes, tyll ſuch a Preacher be procured vnto thē or no? And the like page 14. where a little before he hath theſe wordes. If he reply that the Biſhop ſhould not then haue made him Miniſter, I reioyne, that peraduenture he was none of his making: it maye be alſo, that he was fitte for the cure he was appoynted vnto, though not ſo fitte for ſome other populous Congregation, or troubleſome people: Laſtly, that if none ſhould be aſſumed to the miniſtry, but with thoſe eſpeciall indowmentes, ſurely all the learned of all profeſsions in England, if they were in the miniſtery, woulde ſcarce be able thus to ſupply one tēth part of the pariſhes. Item page 25. Neither are ſuch of them thogh they be no Preachers, to bee accounted dumbe and ſilent, who in their Churches
                  
do exhort, dehort, rebuke, comfort, and alſo in ſome degree inſtruct their pariſhioners, as their ability ſerueth, &amp; occaſion is offered. Which I know they may as profitablye doe, as ſome, who of as meane gyfes but of more audacity then they, dare take vpon them to expound &amp; deuide the Scripture by preaching vppon ſome text, vnto which they in their whole diſcourſe do come iuſt as neere as Iarmans lippes, are ſayd to come togeather. Page 34. Further, if they haue ordayned ſome of mean ability, it hath been in reſpect of their ſlender portions of liuing, allotted out in moſte places for the finding of Miniſters, which places otherwiſe ſhould be deſtitute wholly, whereby the people wold be in ſhort tyme become as heathen &amp; Painims, or be as ſauage as the wilde Iriſh, to the great daunger of their ſoules, and hazard of this ſtate. Againe page 45. But he is angry alſo with their bare reading and very peremptorily aſſureth vs that they ſhall neuer be inſtrumentes of the holye

Ghoſte, to woorke fayth in the hearers, but he limiteth it with this word ordinarily, which he ſeeketh to eſtabliſhe by that of Sainct Paule: And how ſhall they heare without a Preacher. Truely as it muſt needes be confeſſed, that the plaine reſolution and vnfolding of the Worde in Scripture called Orthotomia, the right cutting thereof, and the grauing of the due and fitte allotment in ſeaſon, which is perfourmed by diſcreete and pithie preaching, is an ordinarye and the moſte excellent meanes to ingender fayth: So is it a great errour in diuinitye, to thinke that God neuer bleſſeth the reading or the hearing of his Worde read, but extraordinarily: for then why is it commaunded that the law of GodDeut. 6. ſhoulde be rehearſed continually to our children, that we ſhould talke of the commaundementes in oure houſes, &amp;c. That we ſhould meditate therein daye and night, that all the daye long our ſtudie ſhould be in his law, &amp; that we ſhold ſearch the ſcriptures.

Alſo why was Moſes reade in the Synagogues euerye Sabboth day, and they of Theſſalonica commended for their reading of Scripture, &amp; conferring it with that they heard? ſhall we ſaye that ſo many thouſands, as in late tyme of perſecution were conuerted from idolatry, by reading of Scriptures and diuine treatizes, obtayned not fayth by ordinarye meanes? or that without eſpeciall miracle, and by extraordinary working, none are ſaued in this Church of England, where the Miniſter is no publique Preacher? and is not the declaring and publiſhing the Worde in the Mother tongue, wherein (as Auguſtine ſayeth) in thoſe thinges that are playnely ſet downe, is ſufficient for fayth and conuerſation, a kinde of declaration and preaching the Lordes will vnto vs. Page 70. Neither in vaine is preaching ſpoken off at the firſte ordering, both to put them in minde what ought to bee their principall indeuour, and to giue vs to know, that meere laye-men be

not inabled to this office, ſo is it not conuenient, that a licence to preach be giuen to anye, but to ſuch as beeing in ſome function Eccleſiaſticall, haue addicted them-ſelues to ſerue the Church according to their abilities in all their functions incident to that calling. And page 63. and the 4. iniunction addeth here-vnto. That if he be liſenced herevnto, he ſhal preach in his owne perſon, at the leaſt euerye quarter of a yeare one Sermon, for the which ende, the Ordinaries in moſt places doe requyre of ſuch as be not fitte to be licenſed to preach, that they procure ſuch dutye to be done by an other which is able to perfourme the ſame, &amp;c. Where he asketh whether the meaning of the Parliament were to haue the Biſhops Iudge the reading of Homilies to bee preaching: it maye bee ſayde that reading of Homilies, in a ſtrickt ſignification can not bee accounted preaching, yet they ſerue to edifying, and are a kinde of publiſhing the Lordes will, euen as well as

a Sermon beeing penned, is, and vttered foorth to the people. Page 121. Truly, I wiſh vnfaynedly, that the gifts of Gods ſpirit were doubled and redoubled vppon all that function: yea, that all the Lordes people could propheſie. Yet can I not without intollerable vnthankfulnes to God, &amp; great touch of her Maieſties gratious care, for the inſtructing of her people, ſo debaſe al Miniſters abilities which be no Preachers, as to ſay, they know not either for what they ought to praye, or that the worde of God is the only food to the ſoul of man: Or ſhal we ſay that none knoweth any thing, nor is able to catechiſe, or to exhort &amp; dehort in any reſonable meaſure, but he that is a Preacher publikly licēſed, ſeeing it is notorious, that euē in the reformedArt. 8. des ma
                        •
                     iages en ta diſcipline du Fraunce. churches of Frāce, according to which our men, that haue their heades ſo full of Church-plots, would ſeeme to haue ſquired out all their frame; there be certaine Congregations tollerated, where they haue no publike ſermons, but praiers and certaine

exhortations. It hath been the hope of al the godlye minded, that after the cleare light had ſhined ſo gloriouſly, both by zealous preaching and learned writings of many worthy men, to the manifeſt diſcouery of the vnlawfulneſſe of an vnpreaching Miniſtery: ſo that not onely moſt of ſound religion, but alſo euen the very impugners of this, haue after a ſort been driuen to an open confeſſion of the ſame: that no man indued with any true care of religion, or minding to defend a cauſe worthy of anye account, would once haue aduentured, eyther colourably or plainly, directly or indirely, with proteſtatiō or without to defend, or any way vphold ſuch a baſe miniſtery. But ſeeing it is the righteous iudgement of God vpon all our vnrigteouſneſſe, but eſpecially vppon their ſinne, who haue admitted, tollerated, and defended ſuch vnſauory ſalt, that inſtead of putting them to their right vſe, whichMath. 5. our ſauiour ſayth, is to bee caſt on the dung-hill, and to bee troden vnder the feet of men, they do not only not remoue the ſtincking ſnuffe out of the candleſticke,
                  
to place the bright-ſhining candle in their roome: but alſo hauing caſt downe a third parte of the ſtarres from Heauen vnto the earth, doe ſtill by publique writing, vnderprop ſuche crazed and rotted pillers: It ſhall be expedient before the particuler examining of his ſeueral allegations, to let the world ſee, how that, while they are ſtrugling with the light of their owne conſcience, the Lorde (as the Apoſtle ſayth) hath made
                     
                        •
                     . Tim. 3. 8. 9 their madneſſe manifeſt to all men. For when as they ſhould haue bene mooued with the pitifull bowels of our SauiourMath. 9. Chriſte, who had compaſſion on the people (though they came to his preaching and had their doctors and teachers of the Lawe, ſuch as they were in euerye Towne and Uilladge) as ſheepe ſcattered without a ſhepheard: they haue made themſelues a laughing ſtocke vnto the prophane, but a pitty and heart-bleeding to the godlye, by their ridiculous aunſweres, open ſhiftings, contradictiōs, aſſertions and by ſuch poſitions as come nearer to the prophane ſpirite of the Jeſuites, then to the holy Doctrine of any

old or new writer, of whome this queſtion hath beene handled. For how vnſauory is it: For, to decline the ſharp ſtroke of Gods worde, hee is faine to turne the rule of the Apoſt. 1. Tim. 3. Which by Councels and Fathers, is made an ordinary rule for the examination of thoſe which ſtande to bee admitted into the miniſtery, into a Platonical Idaea, which ſhould neuer be found in any: And to ſhift of the plaine forme of their ordination wherein they are willed to receiue authority to preach the word, he ſayth, that It is not in vain, but to inſtruct vs (forſooth) that mere lay-men, are not inhabled to this office, as though ther were no booke to learne that leſſon, vnleſſe the Byſhop taught it by giuing authority to ignoraunt men to open their mouthes in preachiuge: which after, by a ſtraight charge he is faine to ſowe vp. And laſtly, (to leaue out other which the wiſe reader maye eaſilye ſee) going aboute to prooue reading to bee a kinde of preaching, he is dryuen to demaunde, whether declaring of the Worde in the mother tongue, be not a kinde of declaration.
                  
                  &amp;c. Secondly, what open ſhifts are theſe, to couer the ſhame of thē who ordained ignoraunt Miniſters? hee is compelled to aſke, What if hee made him not? or that the Pariſh were little or poore, When in his own conſcience he dareth not deny, and all the worlde knoweth, ſuch are dayly made, and as though feweneſſe or pouertie deſerued a blinde guid, that they might both fal into the ditch. Againe, how ſimple and naked was that, where to excuſe the colde exhortatious of the ignorant Miniſters, he is forced to ſay, that they are as profitable, as they who through more audacity take vpō thē to preach, &amp; come iuſt as nere the text as Iarmās lips are ſaid to come together; as if one to ſhew y• goodnes of y• peſtilent feuer ſhould alledge y• commodities of the plague. Alſo how is this whole diſcourſe at war with it ſelfe? for to defend vnpreaching Miniſters, he challengeth mē to proue it ſimply vnlawfull, to ordain men miniſters of the Worde and Sacramentes, which cannot preach, when in another place, he is driuen to confeſſe, yt they receiue authority

to preache, to teach thē that they are addicted to the ſame, as a thing incident to their office. Which is as much to ſay; Al miniſters muſt receiue authority to preach, as a thing incidēt to their calling, &amp; yet ſome miniſters may be ordained to the miniſtery of the Word &amp; Sacraments only, yt is, muſt receiue no authority to preache. Nowe, what concord ther is betweene him &amp; the Ieſuites, let this compariſō following declare. They ſay vpon 17. verſ. of 1. Tim. cap. 5. Wee may note that all good Byſhops and Prieſtes of thoſe dayes, were not ſo well able to teach as ſome others, and yet for the miniſtery of Sacramentes, and for Wiſdome and Gouernment, were not vnmeete to be Byſhops and Pastours. He ſayth that they may bee Miniſters of the Word &amp; Sacraments, though they cannot preache. They ſay: Although it be due high commendation in a prelate to be able to teach, as the Apoſtle before noteth, yet al cā not haue the like grace therein, &amp; it is often recompenſed by other ſinguler giftes no leſſe neceſſary. He ſaith, y• the aptnes to teach, is an high &amp; eminent Idaea of ye Apoſtle, rather declaring what

is requiſite in a Miniſter, then what is neceſſarily required. They ſay, ſome times and countries, require more preaching then others. He ſaith, vnpreaching Miniſters are fitt for ſmall Congregations, though not for populous and troubleſom people. In all which, let the reader mark whether the Jeſuits be not one ſtep nerer the trueth then he. Now, although this be bee ſufficent to bewray the aunſwerers halting: yet becauſe a great muſter of faint Souldiers is thought to bee a mighty armye, till being incountered withall, they bee ſeuerally ſcattered and put to flight: it is neceſſary to meet euery one of this valiant hoſt, hand to hand. And firſt, we ouerthrowe his Idaea, which ſerueth for nothing elſe, but to ſet out the holy Cannons of the Apoſtle to the laughter of all prophane men, by theſe reaſons following.
               1 Whatſoeuer the Apoſtle inferreth vpon the worthy worke of a Byſhop or Miniſters office, as that which muſt be in him for y• neceſſity of that work, or for the neceſſary adorning of it, the ſame cannot be ſuch an Idaea:
               
               
                  2 But the Apoſtle hauing ſaide, that hee that deſireth a Biſhoppes charge, deſireth a worthy worke; thereon concludeth:
               3 Therefore, he muſt be apt to teach. Wherefore ſeing he ſayth, Dei einai didacticon, yt is, he muſt be apt to teach, how dare he ſay it is onely good and requiſit, or an Idaea, which a Miniſter cannot attaine vnto? for if he can not be ſo apt to teach, as is there required; thē it followeth, he muſt not be apt to teach, ſeeing in ye gouernment of y• Church, a man muſt not be y• he cannot be, althogh in the perfection of God his Lawe, which was giuen to ſhew man his ſinne, and that man could fulfill the ſame, yet in the rules of the church-gouerment, it is farre otherwiſe, which are ſet downe for a direction to the Church in their triall, who are fit to ſuch or ſuch offices. Secondly, if that property of being apt to teache, bee an Idaea, (that is an imagination which cannot be reached vnto) then to be ſober, to be Coſmios, that is, comely in attire, to bee no fighter, are ſo likewiſe, ſeeing that is not onely bounde vp by the Apoſtle

by the ſame bond of neceſſity, but alſo is the onely quality which the Apoſtle requireth: wherein a man fit for the miniſtery differeth from anye other good &amp; ſounde Chriſtian, or from thoſe which are to be choſen Deacons. Further, ſeeing y• Apoſtle requireth, that he muſt hold faſt the faithfull word, which is according to
                  Tit. 1. 7. 9. 
                  doctrine, that he may be able to exhort with ſound doctrine &amp; conuince the gainſayers, And therein plainly deliuereth, not only wherein they may, but wherein they muſt be able to doe theſe thinges, he directly ouerthroweth this mans building in the aire which hee thinketh no man can reach vnto. Laſtly,
               1 That which holdeth proportion with the proper actions of diuers members of a naturall body, y• cannot be accounted an Idaea, ſeeing nature doth not only tend, but attaineth vnto that:
               2 But that proper teaching which is the peculier work of the teacher, and that proper exhorting which is the peculier worke of a Paſtor, doe holde that proportion as is manifeſtly ſet downe by the Apoſtle. Rom. 12. 4. 7. 8.
               
                  3 Therefore muche leſſe can this aptneſſe to teache which is common to them both, be reckoned for an Idaea.
               
               Now this thus neceſſarily concluded being granted, notwithſtanding it wold follow therupon, that the iſſue which he tendereth, is alſo therwithal eſtabliſhed: namely, that it is ſimplye vnlawfull to admit them to be miniſters of y• Sacramentes which cannot teach: yet to ſhewe the riches of the truth, it ſhall be further confirmed by theſe reaſons following.
               1 That which is contrary to the whole courſe of y• ſcripture, both of y• old and new Teſtament, is ſimply vnlawfull.
               2 But to admit the adminiſtration of ſigns to ſuch as are vnfit to adminiſter y• doctrin by preaching, is contrary to the whol courſe of the Scripture.
               3 Therefore it is ſimply vnlawfull.
               The 2. part of which reaſō, is manifeſt by this inductiō. Noe ye preacher of righteouſnes had the building of the Ark, toGeneſ. 6. which our baptiſm anſwereth. So Abra ham was y• miniſter of Circūciſiō, being1. Peter 3 
                        ••
                     
                   alſo a prophet of God. So y• Jews were baptized vnto Moſes, who preched ye law.1. Cor. 10. 1.
                  
So the Prieſtes offred Sacrifices, who were commaunded not to drinck ſtrong drincke, That they might teach the children
                  Leuit. 10. 11. 
                  of Iſraell all the ſtatutes, which the Lorde had commaunded them by the hande of Moſes. So all they which were Miniſters of propheticall ſignes, were alſo Prophetes. So in the Goſpell, the baptiſme of John, implyed the miniſterie of his doctrine. For the text ſayth: Thoſe
                  Actes. 19. 5. 
                  which heard him were baptized. So the general commiſſion of the Apoſtles is,Math. 28. Mark. 6. 12. Iohn. 4. 2. 38 to preach and Baptize. And when they were ſent to baptize in Judea, they were alſo ſent to preach. So in ye ordinary miniſtry, whatſoeuer Elders went further then ruling onely, were occupied in the Word and doctrine: diuers from which1. Tim 5. 17, ſeeing he can ſhew no worthy example out of the Scripture, the former induction is full. Secondly,
               1 It is ſimply vnlawful, to admit ſuch to be Miniſters of the Sacramentes, which the Lord reiecteth from being Miniſters of the Sacrifices:
               2 But ſuch as are ſo vnapt to preach, as by that meanes the people lacke

knowledge, the Lord reiecteth from y• miniſtery of the ſacrifices. Oſe. 4. 6.
               3 Therefore we ought much more to reiect them from the miniſtery of the Sacramentes; becauſe the ebbe of knowledge vnder the law, ought to be full Sea vnder the goſpell. Thirdly,
               1 If the Lorde in the ſcriptures of the new Teſtament, hath giuen no commandement to the ordinary Miniſters of the Word to adminiſter the Sacraments, but vnder the commandement of preaching the Worde, then is it vnlawfull to admit a Miniſter not apt to teach:
               2 But hee is not able to ſhewe any one place of a commaundement of an ordinary miniſtry of the Sacraments, not comprehended vnder the commaundement of the preaching Miniſtery:
               3 Therefore vnleſſe he would bring into Gods harueſt ſuch an one as he hath not hyred, it is ſimply vnlawfull to admitte him to adminiſter the Sacraments, which cannot preach.
               If he obiect theſe words of Chriſt, Do this: we anſwere, that it is not to be

referred onely to the deliuery of breade, but to al the actions going afore of preaching, bleſſing, and breaking, &amp;c, and therefore the Apoſtle ſayth, that when we adminiſter the Lordes Supper, we preach Chriſts death till he come. Laſtly,1. Corin. 11. ſeeing by Epheſ. 4. verſe. 11. all the ordinary offices which ſerue for the gathering together and the building of the Church, by the publique miniſtery of diuine ſeruice, is eyther the office of a Paſtor or a Doctor: it followeth that none be admitted to adminiſter the Sacraments which can not preach, becauſe propheſying (that is preaching) is the worke that is proper and common to them both. Rom. 12. 6. From whence alſo floweth their ſeuerall duties of exhortation peculier to the Paſtour, and of an eſpecial manner of teaching proper to the Doctour, Rom. 12. 6. 7. To his demaunde following, Whether ſo many Churches as cannot obtaine learned Miniſters, ſhould be deſtitute of publique Prayers and adminiſtration of Sacramentes, And to y• after, That ſo they would become in
                  
                  ſhort time as heathen and Painims, or as ſauadge as the wilde Iriſh. And againe, that the French Churches, Tolerate certain congregations, wher they haue no publike ſermons but prayers with certaine exhortations. To theſe ioyntly we aunſwere, the church can follow no better direction then the holy Apoſtles haue deliuered vnto them in this behalfe, who hauing by the preaching of the goſpell gathered many churches, did not ordain inſufficiēt miniſters, becauſe at the firſt they had not thoſe which were ſufficient, but leauing them partly to the miniſtery of others, where they mighte find it, &amp; partly to the quickning of their faith, by their graue and ſober meetings for praier and mutual exhortation, they then returned and ordained them Elders church by church, whē men were grown fit and meet for the ſame. Act. 14. 21. 22. 23. So in the old Teſtament, when for y• ſins of ye people, ye work of preaching was rare &amp; precious; ye prophets of God ſent not forth reading &amp; vnlearned Leuites, but rather gathered ye people to thē on y• ſaboths &amp; new-moons, to be inſtructed of

them. 2. King. 4. 22. and in this ſenſe and no other, is the conſtitution of the French Church to be taken, ſeeing they make no mention of the Sacramentes, but of Prayer and Exhortations, which in another manner may bee done with due caution of priuate perſons in priuat aſſemblies. Which thing, if it were ſo carried of the Apoſtles in their times of perſecution and troubles, howe much more oughte it to bee among vs in the time of peace: where beſide the dayly increaſe of preaching Miniſters, if thoſe already which we haue, may be ſuffered freely to execute their office, matters may be ſo ordered (till thorough the bleſſing of God all Churches bee repleniſhed,) that no man neede to goe aboue fiue myle to heare a ſermon: and for the adminiſtration of the Sacramentes, the Church with the conſent of the Godly Magiſtrates may take ſuch order, (if it ſhall ſo pleaſe them) that euerye Pariſh may haue the Sacramentes miniſtred by a preaching Miniſter, and ſo they maye bee ſtill edified in the holy fayth, and not as hee groſely and vngodlye

imagineth of the people of God, become more ſauadge then Painims and wilde Iriſh. The next is worthy of no other anſwere, then is already made. But where hee ſayth, They are not to bee counted dumb and ſilent, who in their Churches doe exhort, dehort, comfort, and in ſome degree inſtruct their Pariſhioners. If he meane thoſe dueties as the Apoſtle vnderſtandeth them, to be peculier to the man of God. 2. Tim. 3: wee graunt he ſaith true, for ſo they cannot be ſeperated from the true reſoluinge and opening of the Scriptures. But if he meane, as his words import by comparing with the raſhe dealing of ſuche as take vppon them to preache beeing not inabled thereunto, then muſt wee needes ſay, that that voyce which is lowde ynoughe in the houſe, euen in the mouth of the Miſteres of the family, who muſt Open her mouth with wiſdome, and haue the doctrine of grace in her lippes, Is not lowde ynough for the Paſtors of Gods church, who muſt lift vp their voyce alowde to ſhewe Iſraell their ſinnes, and Gods

people their tranſgreſſions: and that the riches of the Worde, with wiſedome to admoniſh and exhort one another,Colloſ. 3. 16 which the Apoſtle maketh common to all grounded Chriſtians, is not competent for the Scribe, who ſhoulde
                  Math. 13. 
                  bee prepared for the Kingdome of God, and bring out of his storehouſe thinges bothe newe and olde, that hee may bee a Pastor
                  Ierem. 3. 
                  according to God his heart to feede them with knowledge and vnderstanding. Touching the want of liuing in ſome Pariſhes, for which cauſe (hee ſayth) The Byſhoppes haue ordered ſome of meane ability. If they obſerued the rule of the Apoſtle, that at this time Their aboundaunce mighte ſupply others
                  1 Cor. 8. 15. 
                  lacke, that alſo others aboundance might be for their lacke, that as it is written, hee that gathered much hath nothing ouer, and hee that gathered little had not the leſſe: Then that obiection neede not bee made. In his large diſcourſe to ſalue the ſore of the vnpreaching miniſtry, wherein hee laboureth to diſprooue the Abſtractors aſſertion, who affirmeth that preaching of the Word is the ordinary meanes to

worke fayth: hee hath many wordes but no reaſon. For as one wel beatē, leaueth him that maſtereth him and turneth to ſome eaſier match, in ſteede of proouing out of the Scriptures, that reading of the word is ordinarily ſo honoured, that it ſhould bee an ordinary inſtrument to worke fayth; hee prooueth by many places of Scripture a cleane other thing: namely, that the reading of the Worde receiueth ſome other bleſſing then that which is extraordinary, which euerye one will graunte him. For they are no ſmall bleſſinges, that by publique reading &amp; priuate exerciſe of the word, men are prepared &amp; made fit for the publike miniſtry: and afterwards are continually quickned in al Chriſtian holines, and confirmed in the publike doctrine, which is al the ſence of the places which he alledgeth. And it is as if one ſhold reaſon: Apollo watered y• 
                  Corinthes, therfore Paul only did not plant thē. Where he aſkethActes. 15. why Moſes is read euery Sabboth in the Synagogues: we anſwere, to the former ends, and more fully with S. Iames, that euery ſabboth day he might be preached.

Neither doth he in any ſort ſatiffie that which is obiected out of the Apoſtle, Rom. 10. ſeeing hee ſpeaketh of ſuch Preachers as are publikely and ſolemnly ſent. verſe 15, which we hope he will not vnderſtande of bare reading, and of ſuch as the Prophet Eſaie, with admiration of the bleſſing of the Goſpel crieth out: How beautifull are the feete of
                  Eſay. 52. 7. 
                  thoſe which preach peace, of thoſe which preach good thinges. As for his obiection, Of many thouſandes in the tyme of perſecution by bare reading conuerted: and that we are not to ſaye that the people where they haue no preaching Miniſter, be ſaued by myracle: It is not worth an anſwere. For beſides, that the bleſſing of God is extraordinary, by rayſing vp the light of the Goſpell in ſo palpable darkeneſſe, which had couered the whole earth: in ſtead of a thouſand he can not ſhew one, who by bare reading, without the preachinges then vſed in ſecreat, and the open publiſhing of the truth by the Martyrs at their death: or by ordinary preaching going afore, (as in the dayes of

King Edward of bleſſed memory,) haue beene truly conuerted vnto the Lorde. In the other poynt he is forced to goe againſt y• wool. For whereas elſe-where, though to an ill ende, namely, to dazell the eyes of the people that they ſhoulde not ſee the plague of an ill miniſtery, he doth worthely commend the running of the Goſpell vnder her Maie
                     ••
                  ies happy gouernment: yet heere he is fayne to as ill a purpoſe, farre more vnworthely to abaſe the ſame, as though preaching were ſo ſcant, (as the Lorde knoweth it is very ſcant, and both Country and Citie doe lament the rarenes of it), as that men can not haue fayth but by reading onely: which is farre otherwiſe, ſeeing they ought to haue at the leaſt foure ſermons euery yeare: &amp; it is as if complayning of a great dearth, one ſhould aſke how they liue that ſtarue not? As good is his reaſon out of Anguſt. The ſcriptures containe all thinges neceſſarye to ſaluation, therefore men may ordinarily haue faith by bare and naked reading. As materiall is his demaund following, whether the declaring and publiſhing

of the Worde, be not a kinde of declaration and preaching of the Lordes will vnto vs. And that which he ſayth afterwardes of Homilyes, that although in a ſtrickt ſignification they be not preaching, yet in ſome ſence, they are as well as a Sermon penned, is vttered forth to the people: for ſo it may be replyed thatPſal. 19. the inſenſible creatures preach and publiſhe God his will, and that the ſheepehardesLuk. 2. preached, though not as he ſayth, in a ſtrikt ſignification. So women and Children may make a declaration of the wil of God, and yet not apt to preach as the ſcripture requireth of euery Miniſter. Further, if he had remembred that the Apoſtle maketh ſo great a difference between his owne writing &amp; preaching: as when he writeth to the Romanes, he deſireth earneſtly to preach vnto them alſo: he need not haue maruailed if good men make ſuch ſeperation between the reading of good writinges of men, &amp; the liuely preaching of the holye worde of God: eſpecially conſidering he can not be ignoraunt, that the one proceedeth onely from the common gyftes of the

knowledg to read, &amp; of an audible voice, and the other from the eſpeciall gyftes of interpretatiō, of doctrine, &amp; exhortation, giuen by the holy ghoſt, as peculierly for the Church-miniſterye. Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 12. Epheſ. 4. And if he had not forgotten the ancient queſtion after ye reading of Demoſtenes oration, O what if you had heard him ſelfe ſpeake it, He would not haue maruayled y• God hath attributed the firſt fruits, or rather firſt ſpring of our fayth to ye liuely preaching of the Worde. James 1. which in that reſpect is compared to ſowing. Mat. 13 to begetting. James 1. to grafting 1. Cor. 3. This trueth, that all Miniſters ought to be apt to teach, as it is moſte manifeſt and cleare by the Scriptures, ſo it hath witneſſe from the Church, euen when it was fallen almoſt to decay, but ſpecially when-ſoeuer any worthye ſeruice of God floriſhed, as may appeare by their decrees, canons &amp; ſentences following, few only of many being ſparingly takē for breuities ſake. Concil. Carthag. 4. in ye rules of examining a Biſh. according to the 1. Tim. 3. amongſt the other

proprieties there mentioned, it is required to be ſought, If he be learned, if he be inſtructed in the law of God: If he be Cautus ſenſibus ſcripturae, warie in the ſence of the ſcriptures: ſi in dogmatibus exercitatus, it he be exerciſed in doctrines, opinions or ſentences, meaning of all ſortes, that he may be able to put difference.
                   And in the Canons of Pope Celeſtine the 1. Can. reproouing a ſuperſtition in Miniſters, in ſquaring their outwarde attire to the phraſe of certaine places of Scripture, We haue learned (ſayth he) that ſome Prieſtes or Miniſters of God, do ſerue or giue them-ſelues to a ſuperſtitious kinde of ſeruice, rather then to the puritye of the minde and faith, who beeing cloked, hauing their loynes girt, beleeue that they ſhall embrace the faith of holy Scripture, not by the ſpirit but by the letter. And hauing ſhewed that we muſt not do the thinges, but that which is ment by ſuch ſpeaches: he ſaith further, We are to be diſcerned from the people or others by doctrin, not by garments. Now when they haue no more ſoundnes in faith and abilitiy to admoniſhe, then is requyred in Chriſtians: how are they

diſcerned from the common people and others by doctrine? Concil. Toletan. 4. Ignorance the mother of all errours is eſpecially to be auoyded in Prieſtes or Miniſters, who haue taken on them the dutey of teaching among the people of God. For Paul doth commaund Prieſtes or Miniſters to read the Scriptures often, ſaying to Timothy attend to reading &amp; exhortation: let Prieſts or Miniſters therefore know the holy ſcriptures, and let them meditate the Canons:
                     Polu ſunteles. 
                     let all their worke conſiſt in diuine preaching and doctrine, and let them edifie all as well with the knowledge of faith as with the diſcipline of works.
                   And Chriſo. 1. Tim 5. 17, For this is much for the edification of the Church, and very requiſite that the Elders be apt to teach, for this cauſe with the reſt, with this, that they ſhould be giuen to hoſpitality, they ſhoulde be moderate that they ſhould be vnblameable, he alſo numbreth this ſaying, he muſt be didacticos, apt to teach, for this he is ſayde to be a Teacher. Which teſtimony, declareth euidently that aptneſſe to teach is no more an Idaea, then all the reſt ſpecified by the Apoſtle. So Auguſt. Homilia de paſtor.
                  
                  
Hauing prooued at large all the dueties of preaching to lye vppon the Paſtours of the Church, ſheweth how by the Apoſtle, they muſt not only preach, but be inſtant in it, ſaying. For here the Apoſtle ſayeth, preach the Worde, be inſtant, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon. To whom in ſeaſon? To whom out of ſeaſon? In ſeaſon to thoſe who will, out of ſeaſon, to thoſe who will not. And thus much for an vnpreaching miniſterie.
            
            
               Miniſters fallen to idolatrie from their Miniſterie, ought not to be receiued to their miniſterie.
               HItherto hath beene handled the1. Timot. 3. principall cauſe of the Miniſtery, as it were the proper glorye of the man of God, that he be apt to teach. Now it is meet in the next place, to maynetayne alſo that truth which the aunſwerer impugneth, that Miniſters fallen to idolatry, ought not to be admitted vnto the miniſterie of the Goſpell by anye ordinary authoritie of the Church: that ſo the glorye which God hath appoynted vnto the miniſterie might be mayntayned,

both for ſufficiencie, and the authoritie which they ſhould gaine by being voyde of all ſuſpicion of inconſtancie in that religion which he ſhoulde deliuer, with much full perſwaſion of the truth to liue and die in the ſame: and to be willing to deale their owne liues1. Theſ. 1. Iohn. 10. for their flocke. For notwithſtanding it muſt be true, that aboue all thinges the Godly Miniſters are to take diligent heede, that they doe not in confidence of their ſtrength, or with a ſpice of free-will as Peter did, boldly promiſe ſuch conſtancie: yea, when we are by Chriſte his voyce admoniſhed of our owne frailtie: yet in all humbleneſſe, trembling, and feare, (reſting vpon God his promiſe to miniſter ſtrength to the weake, and courage to the faint hearted) they ought as the chiefe captainesHeb. 13. of the Lordes army, and conductors of his hoſt, not onely be free from probable ſuſpicion of ſuch foule cowardlineſſe, yea, of execrable high Treaſon; (ſeeing ſuch doe not onely flee, before the enimies of God, but vnto them, and that betray the ſtrong tower of God his

pure and holy ſeruice, into the hands of the diuell his ſworne enemy) but ought alſo to be examples &amp; patterns of al readines to ſuffer for the truth. His wordes for the impugning of this manifeſt truth are: The contrary of this Doctrine of his, may bee prooued by the example of Aaron, who was an Idolater or an abbettor of idolatry in the golden Calfe, and yet was not from his repentance put from his prieſthood. Likewiſe by Peter, whoſe reuolt and temporary Apoſtaſy in denying his Maſter Chriſte was no leſſe heinouſe, then the ſinne of our idolatrouſe prieſts, who for the moſte part ſinned but of ignorance in that generall blindeneſſe. Likewiſe Auguſtine, afterward a famous Byſhoppe, was by the ſpace of many yeares, a deteſtable Manachy. And after he alleageth many teſtimonies of the Concil. Meldenſ, &amp; the glo. out of the Nicen, and out of Leo. And Auguſtin, that Heretickes as namely Nouatians and Donatiſtis, returning from their Hereſies may be receiued. And out of Viret, that From
                  
                  Popery, men maye be receiued to the Goſpell. Peter Viret in dialog. la diſcipline eccleſ. des egliſes reformes du royaulme de Fraunce. pag. 128. 129. Now all theſe allegations, although they carrye ſome ſhew to him who vnderſtandeth not the cauſe, yet to him that ſhal but once conſider of the queſtion, as it is before with out ambiguitie ſet downe, it is manifeſt that his allegations touch not the queſtions. For the examples of Aaron and Peter were without the compaſſe of the ordinarye power of the Church, who beeing immediatelye called of God, coulde not be demiſſed by the Church. For ſeeing no calling can bee made voyde, but by the authority which made it, that which hath immediately proceeded from God, can not be repealed but by his voyce. Now ſeeing the immediat voyce of God and Chriſt, did not onely not make voyde, but further eſtabliſh the calling of Aaron and Peter: how could ye Church meddle with that? Or how coulde the rule giuen to the Church, for to direct their mediate elections, rule the immediate calling of

God? And if this be not playne inough to cauſe him to ſee the difference which is as greate, as that which is betweene GOD and his Churche, the voyce of man, and the voyce of GOD: Let him vnderſtande it by an other example of lyke reaſon. It hath beene prooued alreadye, both by the Scriptures and Fathers, that none ſhoulde be admitted to the Miniſtery by the Church, but ſuch as were ſufficiently qualified by ordinary meanes, or gyftes giuen them alreadye of God vnto the ſame function. Now, if to defend the Biſhoppes, in admitting Taylors, Shomakers,
                     For this, if need be, we can name the perſons and prooue it. Amos. 7. 14. Weauers, Chaundlers, Harpers, beeing alſo men furniſhed with no gyftes: one ſhoulde alleadge the calling of Amos, who by God was taken from the ſheepfolde, beeing neyther a Prophet, nor ſonne of a Prophet: woulde it not be a manyfeſt dallying in the ſight of God and man? But rather as the ordinary power of the Church can not heerein imitate the Lordes prerogatiue, becauſe they

can not, as God with their calling powre in gyftes into the perſonnes, whereby they ſhoulde bee inabled to their office: So they muſte not followe the prerogatiue of GOD in this, becauſe they are rather to bee gealouſe and ſuſpicious for the Churches ſake (though other-wyſe they are bound to hope the beſte of a repentaunt Sinner) ouer him, leaſte he ſhoulde agayne betraye the cauſe of GOD; which in God is farre other-wyſe, who not onelye knoweth the heartes of men, but alſo what ſtrength he will after gyue him: and if hee let him fall, hee knoweth how to tourne it to the profitte of his Church. Now, as theſe examples in this reſpecte approche not vnto the matter in debate. So the example of AVGVSTINE a Manachie or ſuch lyke, becauſe the queſtion is not of ſuch as were before their miniſterye ſuch, or carryed away with the common ignoraunce before they knew the trueth: but of ſuche as firſte ſeruiuge GOD in his

appoynted ſeruice, doe not onely leaue the holy altar and fire, but renouncing that, betake them-ſelues to a prophane and idolatrous ſeruice and prieſthoode. Wherin he receiueth anſwere alſo vnto his allegations of the fathers and counſels, which if they ſhould ſpeake of ſuch as fell in capitall pointes from the true ſeruice of God, of which, ſomtimes they were Miniſters: they ſhould then be directly contrary to the fathers and general counſels, which ſhal anon be brought as direct and manyfeſt on our ſide. The lyke is to be anſweared vnto Viret, and the example of the French Churches. Hauing thus aunſweared his obiections, the truth is confirmed ſufficiently by the reaſons following, out of the Scriptures and auncient witnes from the councels and Fathers.
               1 Whatſoeuer God hath commaunded to be done in the lawe, to declare the honour he hath of his right ſeruice, &amp; how he will haue his Miniſtery beautified and fenced, againſt the cauilles of all (which are perpetuall equityes of ſuch their preſcription. 1. Tim. 3. 7)

that is ſtill and perpetuallye to binde the Church:
               2 But ſuch is the order which now we ſpeake of, as may appeare by the 1. King. 23. 9. and by the 44. of Ezech. 13. 14. 15. &amp;c:
               3 Wherefore this order muſt be kept holy and vndefiled.
               We know it will be obiected, that theſe commaundementes be in the olde Teſtament, not in the new: and that they are ceremoniall. They who ſhall ſo obiect, muſt conſider the old Teſtament is of equal authority with the new, and therefore ſeeing God hath once eſtabliſhed this law for the Church-miniſtery, they muſt not repeale it but by the ſame authoritie, vnleſſe they will make with y• Manichees, one iuſt God for the law, and an other mercifull for the Goſpel: So that vnleſſe it maye be ſhewed, eyther that this law was onely a ſhadowe for a tyme to come, or was made for ſome cauſe peculier for that tyme and thoſe perſons (which they can not doe, becauſe of the perpetuall equityes before aſſigned): It followeth, that this

muſt ſtande for an holy and induring conſtitution of God. And in trueth ſuch aunſwere vndermineth at once, both the glorye and perfection of God his holy Scriptures, not onelye in our iudgement, but in the iudgement of all wryters, holy and prophane, who haue continually alleadged the ſentences, and commaundementes of the olde Teſtament, euen for the matters of the gouernment of the Church. The Apoſtle prooueth the mayntenaune of the Miniſterye for preaching of the Goſpell, by the lawe made for the maintenaunce of the Prieſtes, in the 1. Cor. 9. he prooueth women ought not to exerciſe authority, by the places of Geneſis. and in the firſt of Tim. 2. Cyprian, as all know that read him, prooueth the election of the people by the place of Numbers; and that men are not to attempt further then their calling, by the places of Dathan, Abiram, Uzza in the carrying of the Arke, and ſuch lyke. If this exception ſerue, howe ſhall we any longer with the Fathers and Godly wryters of our age, ſtoppe

their mouthes, for the proofe of the Baptiſme of Children, with the reaſons from Circumciſion, drawne out of the lawe? Nay, that they maye ſee they can not vndermyne the gouernment of Chriſte with ſuch aunſwers, but they muſt alſo ſhake the brazen Pyllers of the Sacred authoritye of the Magiſtrate: Let them ſhew with what Argumentes they can ſtoppe the Mouthes of Papyſtes in maintayning the Supreame authoritie of the Prince, and our moſte gratious Soueraigne in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, to reforme religion, according to Gods word: to plant Church-officers by the rules of the ſame, and according therevnto to depoſe Abiather, and ſet vp Sadotk, to call ſynodes Eccleſiaſtical when need is, or when the Church-gouernours neglect their dutye, other then by the examples of Ezechias, Solomon Jehoſhaphat, Joſias, and by the pregnant reaſons drawn from them. Wherfore let them leaue theſe euaſions and ſhifts vnto popiſh diuines, to whom they appertaine. But leaſt they ſhould thinke

we haue but one piller to vpholde this trueth: and that onely in the olde Teſtament, let them anſwere the reaſons following out of the newe. If Paule did rightly think It ſo vnlawfull to take Mark
                  Exiou. 
                  ſuch a one as went from them from Pamphilia, and accompanied them not vnto the worke, y• he would rather be at ſharp ſtrife with Barnabas the ſonne of conſolation, andActes. 15. 38 be ſeperated from ſo worthy a companion in all his labors, then accept Mark: herein being iuſtified aboue Barnabas by S. Luke, both in aſſigning of theſe iuſt cauſes of S. Pauls refuſall, and giuingVerſ. 38. the Teſtimony of the Churche to Paul, who commēded him to ye grace ofVerſe. 40. God, of both which cōcerning Barnabas he keepeth ſilence: Then by how muchCaluin on this place. more right may and ought we to ſtriue with ſuch, as haue not only left the work of the Lorde, but haue beene annointed with the filthy greaſe of the vncleane prieſthoode, and haue receiued the balde marke of the beaſt, and haue in continuall miniſtry blaſphemed the moſt holy, that they ſhould not be taken againe into the fellowſhip of this worke and ſeruice

of the Goſpell. Laſtly, when as the Apoſtle requireth y• all Miniſters muſt haue a good Teſtimony of thoſe who are without, leaſt he fal into the reproch andDiabolou, ſo taken verſe, 11. ſnare of the caueller. 1 Tim. 3. 7. howe cā they auoid this reproch, who are to be taunted with their back-ſliding, with the turning of their coates, and with high treaſons againſte their GOD? how are not they in danger of the ſnare, who haue opened a way vnto Sathan and the world, how they may deal with them already? Nowe vnto this deuine voyce of the Prophets, we add the reuerend, (though humane) teſtimony of auncient time. Wherein the ſentence of the generall Councel of Carthage, alleadged before vs by Cyprian, is of moſt reuerend account. Cyprian, lib. 1. epiſt. 4. And there be other both many and grienous faultes, wherewith Baſilides and Marſhall are inwrapped: ſuch do in vaine go about to occupy the place of a Byſhop, ſeeing it is manifeſt that ſuch men may not gouern the Churche of Chriſt, nor offer vp Sacrifices vnto God; Eſpecially when of late both with vs, and with all the byſhops in the worlde, euen Cornelius
                  
                  alſo our fellow in miniſtry peaceable and iuſt, and whom the Lord vouchſafed the honour of a Martyr, decreed that ſuch men might be admitted to repentance, but ſhould notwithſtanding be kept from the cleargy or miniſtery. By which alſo it is manifeſt, y• this Counſel was not that prouinciall which concluded rebaptization, whereunto Cornelius neuer conſented. And how Cyprian himſelfe mainteineth our reaſons, may appeare by his diſcourſe in the 7. Epiſt. lib. 1. and his wordes following. How dare he challenge vnto him the miniſtery which he hath betrayed: as though it were lawfull after hauing beene at the Alter of the diuell, to come vnto the Alter of God. And againe: Seeing therefore the Lorde threatneth ſuch tormentes and puniſhmentes in the daye of his wrath, to ſuch as obey the Deuill, and ſacrifice to Idolles: howe can hee thinke, that he may doe the office of the miniſter of God, which hathe obeied, and ſerued the prieſts of the deuils? or howe doth hee thinke that his hand can be tranſlated to the ſacrifice &amp; praier of the Lord, which was captiue to ſacriledge &amp; ſuch a crime. Theſe may

ſuffice for this point: that after we haue mainteined the due honour of God his Embaſſadors, we ſhould alſo maintain the iuſt, lawfull and holy authority committed vnto them of God.
            
            
               Of the authoritie of Ministers of the Worde.
               COncerning the authority of Miniſters, he ſpeaketh thus. Page. 53. And heereuppon I woulde bee reſolued by the Authour or ſome other, whether hee thinke this indowment of euerye Miniſter with the execution of all dicſipline, admitting but not graunting it to be ſo by law, to be a conuenient pollicy, for the vnity &amp; quiet of the Churche? And whether he him ſelfe had not rather be vnder the forme now in practize, in regard of his owne contentment, then vnder the infinite dictatorſhip of his owne miniſter? or elſe whether ſhoulde appellations frō the iudgement of the miniſter in this reſpect be allowed of? and whether to the byſhoppe or to
                  
                  whome? and whether the Byſhop by this interpretation of lawe, ſhall not retain his authority of executing the Diſcipline of the Church vpon euery particuler miniſter, and in euery ſeuerall pariſh as afore time, ſeeing the authour ſayth, as well as the Byſhop in his dioceſſe? And if he ſhall, what if the Byſhop vppon good cauſe, and for abuſing of the authority, ſhall ſuſpende the Miniſter from his iuriſdiction of executing Diſcipline, is hee not at the ſame point he was before? what if the Byſhop him-ſelfe dwell in the pariſh, who ſhall then haue the preheminence? and what if the miniſters diſcretion ſerue him, vpon ſome ſmall or ſurmiſed cauſe to excommunicate ſome great pear or noble counſeller of his pariſh, whoſe indignation may turne the whole Church to greate miſcheefe? or to proceede againſt his Patrone, who peraduenture hath a bōd of him to reſign. And a little after. page. 54. The author ſeemeth to me to deuide the diſcipline of the Church, which he would intitle euery
                  
                  Miniſter vnto, into admonition, denuntiation, and excommunication. If by denuntiation, he meane the publiſhing of Excommunication done by him ſelfe, then is it a part thereof. If (as I rather think) he mean the ſecond degree of proceeding vpon faults not publike, ſpecified in the 18. of S. Mathew, then is this common with the miniſter vnto all other Chriſtians, euen as admonition is, being, the firſt degree: And where the miniſter is the party offended, and hath not preuayled, neither by his admonition in priuate, nor his denuntiation before two or three, to whome ſhall hee tell it in the third place, where he himſelf hath the authority to excommunicate? and a little after in this reſpect hee calleth the Miniſters priuate and inferiour. And againe, pag. 59. Yes truely, as was touched afore, they doe and may execute the diſcipline of declaring by doctrine, according to the Worde of God, mens ſins to be bound or loſed, and the cenſure of rebuking and prouing openly, thoſe that doe freeze in
                  
                  the dregges of theire ſinnes, which are not the leaſte partes of diſcipline: which is as much (as for auoiding intollerable inconueniences, which otherwiſe would inſue) as is expedient to bee attributed to euery one &amp;c. A little after: And if no eſpeciall preeminence might be attributed in matter of execution of diſcipline to one miniſter aboue another: why is it ſayde by S. Paul, excommunicating the inceſtuous Corinthian, Abſens decreui, being abſent I decreed, ſeeing they had Miniſters of their own, and willed the denuntiation afterward to be done openly in the Church? And at the time of his abſolution Paul being abſente ſaith, to whom you forgiue any thing I forgiue alſo: likewiſe ſpeaking of the Anathematiſme of Hymenaeus and Alexander: I haue giuen them vp vnto Sathan, not naming their owne Miniſter, or any ſegniory. Againe. fol. 61. But if hee meane the diſcipline paſſiuely, I thinke hee and his fellowes haue had ſome wrong at the cheefe prelates hands a great while. If actiuely,
                  
                  that euery miniſter without check might haue the execution of all diſcipline in his owne Pariſh, I do verily beleeue that this man, and others, who ſo earneſtly call for they knowe not what, If they might not be them ſelues alſo Elders, auncientes, or what you will ſauing Prieſts of the Seigniory, would be the the firſt weary of it; For if I knowe their diſpoſition, they are as vnpatient as any men, to bee at controlment, and moſte of all by a poore Miniſter.
               
               It hath alwaies bene the practiſe of ye ſubtile Serpent, who, that hee might vndermine the authorye of Gods Embaſſadours, and bring the Meſſengers of the moſt higheſt vnto diſgrace, to lift vppe ſome, who neglectinge the moſte eſſentiall duetyes of a Paſtoure and Elder, in feeding the flockes; and being a Pattern in their whole life and example vnto them, are wont to climbe into the ambitious throne of exerciſing a vſurped eccleſiaſticall Dominion, and a Lordſhip ouer their fellow-miniſters; that whilſte by their place and pompe,

they might amaze the people, as beeing men of great learning and wiſedome, and might alſo by their authority make the poore Miniſters as the aunſwearer ſayth, Priuat Miniſters, to ſpeake when they wil, wryte to what they liſt, and to be their Commiſſaries cryer, yt is, their mās man to promulgat his ſentence of excommunication at his pleaſure, hee might alſo bring to paſſe that which the Prophet Jeremy complayneth of in both. The Prophets propheſie for reward,
                  Veha cohanim iirdu Gnal iedahem * or by their hādes 
                  and the Prieſtes exerciſe dominion * by their meanes: and my people loue it ſo, and what will they doe in the ende? Which we ſee hath not onely won much vnto the cauſe of Sathan in popery, but alſo it keepeth much power vnto him amongeſt thoſe, who do profeſſe the Goſpell: For by this meanes it commeth to paſſe, that they will goe 5. mile to heare a Lord preach, when they will hardly come to Church to heare their owne Paſtour: By this meanes they becomme ſo irreuerent, or rather ſawcie with their Paſtour, that they care no more for his admonition and rebuke, then for the bleating of a

ſheepe: by this meanes they maye call him before a Commiſſarye, a lay-man (as he ſpeaketh) they may fetch out Excommunications thicke and three-folde if hee appeare not, and ſo not only not haue him not to exerciſe dominion ouer them which Peter forbiddeth, but alſo1. Peter. 5. be Lordes ouer their Paſtour beeing but priuate perſonnes, which the lawe of reaſon diſaloweth. Which pollicy of Sathan, although it become odious in the ſight almoſt of all men, but eſpecially of true and louing ſubiects, who are greeued that ſome not onelye exerciſe Lordſhip ouer theire fellow-miniſters, but alſo pearche ſo high, as they pray vpon the right of princes, whilſte they (forſoothe) may not eate fleſh in Lent, or on a Fryday, but by a Byſhoypes lycenſe: yet this man who hath giuen his tong leaue to reuile the Miniſters with diuers ſlaunders &amp; reproches, cannot content himſelfe with that, but muſt open his mouth againſt the due authority of the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſte. In which reſpect wee account our ſelues bounde by the Canonicall obedience,

which we owe vnto ye Archbiſhop of our ſoules Jeſus Chriſt, according to ye Canons1. Peter. 5. which he hath made in his worde: firſt to ſhew how this man diſordereth ye queſtiō according to his maner, voweth conſent (as it ſeemeth) with the Jeſuits in theſe his aſſertions &amp; proofs, and then hauing diſcuſſed his allegations, to confirm the plain truth by holy authority of ſcripture, and worthy witnes of ancient times. In the entrance therfore, the Anſwerer is not content only to fly from ye iſſue, (whether according to the word of God, the miniſter ſhold exerciſe the cenſures of the Church according to y• word of God, which with vs is executed by Commiſſaries, meere lay-men,) vnto another thing, namely, what inconueniences the excommunication committed to the paſtor might bring, but alſo to ſet vpon a matter neuer affirmed by vs, that a miniſter ſhould without the reſt of the eccleſiaſtical ſenate perform this thing. His agreement with the Papiſts may appeare manifeſtly by their Annotation, the 4. ver. of 5. cap. 1. Cor. Their wordes are theſe: Though he commanded the Acte
                  
                  ſhoulde be done in the face of the Church, as ſuch ſentences and cenſures bee at this day executed alſo: yet the iudgement and authority of giuing ſentence was in himſelfe, and not in the whol multitude, as the Proteſtants and populer ſects affirm. Wherfore ſeeing his cauſe is that, which is betweene the ſworne enimies of GOD and his Church: we are not to fear, but the truth which hath preuayled ſo often againſt them, ſhall alſo carry the Garland from this newe Wreſtler. His firſt reaſons are drawne from the inconueniences, which hee thinketh will come vnto the Church by this means, as requiring rather (like a Ciuilian not a diuine) what is ſafe, then what is according to God his wil: Amongſt which, he demaundeth whether the Authour had not rather be vnder the forme that nowe is, then vnder the infinite dictatorſhip of his owne miniſter? which I aunſwere by another Queſtion: why ſhould the miniſters cenſures proceeding by the equall authority of an Elderſhip, vpon cauſes determined by God his worde in a ſmall volume, be more infinite then ye Commiſſaries, who

cannot but proccede according to the infinite and contradictorye Canons of their Law, who can excommunicate vpon non apparaunce for a matter, of 12▪ pence. Is it liker that one Miniſter ſhal haue many elders more tied to his wil &amp; pleaſure, then one Commiſſary his own affections: Againe, may not their appeale from one Elderſhip, to a Conference or aſſemblie of many Miniſters and Elderſhips, be as ſafe as from the Commiſſary to another Byſhop? And if it were granted that the Byſhop ſhould haue authoritye in euerye particuler Churche: yet with the Miniſters conſent (vnleſſe he will iuſtle one lawe againſt another) why were it not more reaſonable &amp; ſafe, then as it is nowe in the Byſhoppe alone: Seeing then the Miniſter might haue more particuler knowledge of the cauſes in his Congregation then the Byſhop, and yet if hee were raſh, the Byſhops wiſedome might ſtay him. And if the Byſhoppe ſhoulde ſuſpende the Miniſter vppon abuſe of his authoritye, yet hee were not at the ſame poynt he was before, becauſe then

they which did not abuſe their authoritye, mighte exerciſe it ſtill. And if the Byſhoppe dwell in the Pariſh and had preheminence, yet hee ſhoulde not draw the execution of Diſcipline to himſelfe onely, but to holde it in common with him. But what doe I anſwering his cauelles agayuſte the Lawe, ſeeing I doubt not but the Abſtractor will ſoone aunſwere his cauill in this behalf. For the fountayns which are in his Booke already, are not yet dammed vp by the anſwerer: Wherefore, I paſſe to his incōuenience, which he fetcheth from the want of diſcretion in y• Miniſter, which is; What if hee vpon want of diſcretion, doe excommunicate ſome greate peere of his Pariſh vppon ſome ſurmized cauſe, whoſe indignation may turne the whole church to great miſcheefe? To this I anſwere, that vnleſſe the Byſhops ſeat aboue a Paſtors, be ſo ſanctified (as Hierome ſayth) by humain conſtitutions, as that it can alwaies proceede with diſcretion and Wiſdome, when the Paſtors ſeate ſanctified with God, and ordained with ſo many pretious

promiſes, ſhoulde bee ſubiect to more follye and headineſſe, then the chayre of the Byſhoppe: this inconuenience is as likelye to fall into the Byſhoppe as the Miniſter. Further, whether is more likely, that the Byſhop hauing by reaſon of his countenaunce and Ciuill authoritye, bothe more heart-burning betweene the Noble Counſailers and himſelfe, and being in leſſe feare, as thinking him ſelfe better able to ſhoulder amongeſt them, would be more bold in his conceit, then a poore Miniſter (as hee calleth him) who neuer woulde for feare, but vpon moſte neceſſary and ſufficient cauſe vrged in conſcience, aduenture ſuche thing? neither if hee woulde, could many graue Elders, without whom he coulde do nothing, bee drawne vnto it, eſpecially conſidering; that their feare woulde preuayle, where greate Conſcience of theire duetie ſhoulde not ouercome it. And maye not this man when his opinion as a Canker ſhall frette ſo farre, turne all this agaynſt the euery of publique rebuking, aſ-well as agaynſte

the Myniſters execution of Diſciplyne: for maye he not alſo demaunde, whether the Byſhoppe ſhall retayne his authoritye to preache in his Dioceſſe? and if hee bee in that Pariſhe, who ſhall haue the preeminence? If hee ſuſpende the Miniſter from preachinge: whether hee bee not at the ſame poynte hee was before? And what if the Miniſter vppon ſome diſcretion woulde rebuke openlye ſome Peere of the Realme, vpon bare conceyte, or ſome ſurmiſe: ſhall then the duetye of the Miniſter in Preaching for ſuche vnitye of the Churche ceaſe and bee counted inconuenient? If hee ſaye no, this is the commaundemente of GOD, and neceſſarye for Chriſtian inſtitution: ſo wee ſaye, this is the commaundemente of JESUS CHRISTE, and neceſſarye for holye correction. In the nexte place hee aſketh to whome the Paſtour ſhall tell it, when hee doth admoniſhe him him-ſelfe▪ I aunſwere for the Paſtour, eaſely to the whole Elderſhip, as our ſauiour willeth. But this queſtion in deed

cleane daſheth the ſole authority of the Biſhop out of countenaunce. For to whom ſhall he tell? not to the Congregation of Elders, as our Sauiour commandeth but to the Church, which ſtandeth of him-ſelfe only as he deſireth▪ not aſcending by the ſtayres of Chriſt, from one to two, from two to manye GodlyChriſoſt. in Math. 18. 
                  Preſidents, as Chriſoſtome ſpeaketh, but by the ſtayres of Rome, to deſcend from two to one, and to take the matter wherin he is a party, into his own hands, and proceed in cenſure Eccleſiaſticall as liketh him-ſelfe beſt? In the next, to blear mens eyes with all, he graunteth they may rebuke in publike doctrine, bynde and looſe by preaching, which is a great part of Diſcipline: as though any man were ſo blynd, (as when the booke maketh three partes of the Miniſters Office miniſtring of doctrine, miniſtering of the Sacraments, and miniſtring of Diſcipline) as not to ſee what violence he doth; Nay, what folly he imputeth to the booke, as though they ſhoulde make three of two. For if Diſcipline be nothing but the open rebuking in preaching,

and binding and looſing by the ſame, that beeing a parte of miniſtring the Doctrine by preaching, is manifeſtly contained vnder it: and ſo not onelye maketh one two, but carrieth one halfe from one end of the ſentence to another, placing a thirde betweene, and for an vmpier belike, leaſte they ſhoulde fall out, or elſe being ioyned orderly togeather, ſhould to much annoy him. But his reaſons, which the Jeſuites haue ſhaken againſt the trueth hefore him, do follow. Unto which I aunſwere, that it followeth not, that if the Apoſtle mighte by ſole authority excommunicate, therefore the Byſhop may: for an Apoſtle is of far greater authority then a Byſhop is. Secondly, it is falſe that the Apoſtle did onely command vnto them to pronounce the ſentence as the Byſhop doth, the miniſter giuing them no further authority. For although as an Apoſtle whoſe duety was to deliuer ordiaunces, which the Churches were to obſerue and keep, hee did iuſtlye decree as the voyce of Chriſte, and ſo commaunde them what they ſhould do: yet he doth not excommunicate,

or take it vnto him-ſelfe, but willeth that by the authority of Chriſt, they ſhould caſte out (not pronounce his ſentence of eiection) they ſhold Seperate frō
                  
                  1. Cor. 5. ver. 7. 12. 13. 
                  amongſt them ſuch, that they Should iudge thoſe within that is vnder their authority, not that they ſhoulde only pronounce his ſentence of ſeperation and iudgement, which is alſo moſt manyfeſt by his other allegation, out of the ſecond to the Corinthes, where heſheweth that hee alone2. Cor. 2. 10. would not forgiue, but whomſoeuer they forgaue, he would forgiue: he calleth it the rebuke or cenſure of many, not ofEpi
                        •
                     imia. Chariſaſthai. Curoſai. him-ſelfe; He ſheweth, now they ought freely to forgiue, he did exhort them to ratifie, and by authority confirme their loue towards him. Let him therfore take this neceſſary collectiō cleane againſt him, y• if y• Apoſtle wold not, nor durſt not take vnto himſelf the ſole anthority of excommunication &amp; abſolution, but left it vnto the church: How ſhal any one biſhop preſume to ſhut out y• Miniſters and elders, &amp; carry it wholy vnto himſelf? His next reaſon is of as great force. The Apoſtle ſaith he did deliuer vnto ſathan, &amp; mentioneth

neither their Miniſtry nor ſegniory, therfore he did alone. Upon which example I reaſon thus. Paule ſaith that Timothy receiued grace by the laying on of his hands, making no mention of y• elders: therfore it is falſe that he ſaith in the 1. Tim. 4. that he receiued it by the laying on of the hands of the Elderſhip. James Act. 15. ſaith. I determine or iudge Therefore it is falſe, which is after ſetAct. 15. 19. Crino. ctA 15. 22. down, y• 
                  this was the decree of the Apostles &amp; Elders, with the conſent of the Churches. But what neede I ſtande to aunſwere this argument, which was by a reuerent ſeruaunt of God, aunſweared openly at Paules croſſe, that although the actionM. Doctor Day at Paules croſſe. Nouember. 17 be giuen to one who moderated, yet neither Peter nor James, nor anye Apoſtle aboue Apoſtles, nor Biſhop aboue Miniſters had any authoritye ouer others, and that as the Senatours were equall in authoritye, notwithſtanding he moderated, ſo is it amongeſt the Apoſtles and Biſhops. And thus much for his reaſons. Ours follow, that it belongeth to the Paſtor &amp; the Elderſhip, to excommunicate by the conſent of the people.

If our Sauiour Chriſt. Math. 18. when hee ſayth tell the Churche, meane not one Biſhop, becauſe one can not be a number, nor one alone a Church, and he goeth vpwarde from one to 2. from two to moe, not contrarywiſe, from twoo to one: neither can it be meant of manye Churches, for then it muſte bee all the whole Church (in the phraſe of the ſcripture) and it were a confuſion and vnpoſſibility for many Churches, or the whol people to heare all ſuch Eccleſiaſticall cauſes: but do meane vpon theſe reaſons a particular Congregation, then our aſſertion is moſt true and certaine. The firſt we haue proued, therfore the ſecond is true.
               1 That which the Apoſtle maketh the iudgement of a particular Congregation, that muſt needes appertaine to the Paſtor and the reſt of the Elders, as the gouernours, and to the people as conſenters:
               2 But this the Apoſtle plainelye expreſſeth 1. Cor. 5. 12. Why iudge you not thoſe who are within? Seperate him therefore from amongſt you:
               
               
                  3 Therfore it is true which we affirm.
               If it be the eſpeciall dutye of the Paſtor, by the authority of the Elderſhip, to deliuer the holye Sacramentes to the worthy, and detayne them from the vnworthy: Then vnleſſe he ſhould be compelled to gyue them to the vnworthye, and with-hold them from the worthy, excommunication muſte belong to him with his fellow Elders. But the firſt is manifeſt by theſe Scriptures. Leuit. 10. 11. Zephan 3. 3. They haue polluted
                     Quodeſh. 
                     the holye thinges.
                   And 1. Cor. 11. 26. 27. Wherefore our aſſertion is true. The conſequent of the firſte part is manyfeſt, becauſe he muſt deliuer them to all, not ſuſpended and excommunicated, and to the reſt hee muſt not. The conſent of the auncient tymes agree vnto this. The counſell of Arles. 2. Can. 30. authoriſeth the ſuſpencion which the Elders and Clearkes decree againſt the Biſhop. And they doe it by the authority of auncient decrees. Alſo, ſeeing the councels conclude both generallye that the Biſhop ſhall not proceed in any cauſe of gouernment Eccleſiaſticall

without the Elders: and that they ſhall not ordayne without them, and that they alone can not ſo much as gyue leaue to any of the Cleargy to goe vnto the Widowes or Uirgins, but with the conſent of the Elders: it followeth much more, that they mighte not excommunicate without them. Now the firſt ſort are directly prooued by theſe Canons following. Concil. Carthag. 4. cap. 23. That the Biſhops heare no cauſe, without the preſence of his Clearkes, otherwiſe the ſentence ſhall be voyde, vnleſſe it be confirmed by the preſence of the Clearkes. And the 22. That the Biſhop ordayne not Clearks without the counſell of his clearks, ſo that he ſeeke the aſſent and leaue, or conniuence &amp; teſtimonie of the citizens. Canon. 3. An Elder
                  Conninentiam. 
                  when he is ordayned, the Biſhop bleſſing him, holding his hand vppon his heade, let alſo all the Elders which are preſent, holde their handes by the handes of the Biſhop. That the Clearkes or thoſe who containe, come not to the Widowes or Virgins, but by the commaundement or permiſſion of the Biſhops and Elders. And Can. 32. That the Elder reconcile not the penitent, not hauing
                  
                  asked councell of the Biſhop. Ierom. ad demetri. 1. Epiſt. The Elders in other cenſures of the Church, and the Church hath intereſt in excommunication. Cyprian. lib. 3. Epiſt. 19. Speaking of excommunication, of which vntill we ſhall haue vnderſtanding, what he haue done after, which thing when it regardeth the Counſell and ſentence of vs all, I dare not preiudicate the matter and draw it only to my ſelfe, And lib. 3. epist. 14. epiſt. 15.Traditione dominica. 
                  epiſt. 16. and Auguſt. ſpeaking of the elders ſaith, becauſe all thinges in tradition of the Lord, are done by the holie Ghoſt, therefore when a rule and forme of this Diſcipline is deliuered vnto them, it is ſayde vnto them, receiue the holy ghoſt: &amp; becauſe it doth truly appertaine to eccleſiaſticall righte, whoſe ſinnes you forgiue. &amp;c.
               
            
            
               Of the Doctor or teacher, that he is an ordinary and perpetuall officer in the Church of Chriſt, diſtinct from the Paſtor, by the Worde of God.
               COncerning which, y• words of y• anſwerer are theſe: And I hope that
                  
                  the authour will not heereby gather, that by law nowe in force, a man is vtterly &amp; ſimplie forbidden, to haue an other preach in his cure, for then all our new doctours De robe curté, who iutrude themſelues vppon, muſt bee faine to giue ouer their cloakes, and put vp their Pipes. fol. 41.
               If this had bene directed againſt the particuler perſons of ſome, it had beene beyond the rule of charitie and modeſty, though he ſhould be a Doctor who ſpake it, thus to ſlaunder any with intruſion, and hauing nothing to ſaye to their doctrine and lyues, to gybe at the apparel which they weare in iourney, or otherwiſe vpon occaſion, being both ſober and graue, yea when as commonly they vſe a gowne with as much grauitie, &amp; leſſe flanting then the moſt of their Doctors conſecrated according to the order of men, and not of God. But now, that it is brought to deface (as ſhall be proued) the ordinaunce of God, thus without all proofe to flout and to taunt the officers of God, beſeemeth neither the grauitye of a Cambridge Doctor, nor the modeſty

of a Chriſtian, nor the ciuility of an honeſt man. Their intruſion, forſooth, is this, that hauing firſt (according to the order of the Church of England) authority to preach, they come vpon the earneſt deſire of the Congregatiō, with the conſent of the Paſtor (vnleſſe being no preacher and ignoraunt, for enuy he can not beare him) to inſtruct the people with wholſome doctrine, out of the true interpretation of the Scriptures, their Pipes, which he ſayth prophanely, they may put vp, is the Vtteraunce of knowledge, a gift of the holy Ghoſte, which1. Cor. 12. is more ſweete to GOD his Children, and acceptable to the Lord, then al the gilded Organes and Pipes in the Realme. For in the ſpirituall battell, their Sound is vncertaine, when as theſe as the Siluer trumpets of Gods ſauctuary1. Cor. 14. giue certayne warning to the people to ſerue the Lorde aright. Thus hauing in a worde, with as much patience and modeſty as the Lord woulde giue me, touched not the Salt, but vnſauory brine of his floutes: hauing no reaſon of his toColoſ. 4. deale withall, I ſet downe theſe following,

firſt for profe out of yt ſcripture, then for witnes out of ancient wryters.
               1 Whatſoeuer (the Apoſtle ſetting downe the ordinary &amp; perpetual members of Chriſts body, in euery particuler Congregation) doth make an ordinarie member in the ſame, diſtint
                     •
                  t in his proper workes and action from all the reſt, the ſame is a perpetuall ordinary Church-officer:
               2 But he maketh the Doctor (in that reckoning) a diſtinct member, hauing a diſtinct action from all the reſt, to wit, teaching diſtinguiſhed there from exhortation, from gouerning, from diſtributing:
               3 Wherefore it is plaine, that he is a Church-officer, ordinary and perpetuall (for his giftes and vſe are ordinary and perpetuall) and alſo diſtinguiſhed from the Paſtor.
               1 Whatſoeuer Chriſte hath giuen to his Church, with an ordinary and perpetuall gift, for the perpetual work of the miniſtery, gathering and building vp of the Church vnto perfection, that is an ordinary Church-officer:
               
                  2 But ſo he hath giuen Paſtours and Doctors. Epheſ. 4. 11.
               3 Therefore both are perpetuall, and ordinary officers, and by conſequent diſtinct.
               Unto this argument, they obiect, becauſe the Apoſtle hauing ſayde, ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Euangeliſtes, he ſaith in the laſt place, ſome Paſtors and Teachers, which becauſe they are coupled by and, they ſay they are one and not diſtinct. To which I aunſwere, they may as well prooue hope and charity to be one and not diſtinct, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, theſe three remaine, faith, hope, and charitie, becauſe he coupleth them with and. But if theſe men haue not learned either that and, though ſometymes it rather repeateth or interpreteth, then coupleth diuers thinges: yet that moſt properly and commonlye it doth not ſo, or that it is an elegancie with the Grecians in ſuch long diſtributions, to ioyne the twoo laſte members, eſpecially if they bee of greater kindered and familiaritie then the reſt, to ioyne them with a copulatiue

coniunction in the ende: If, I ſay, they haue not obſerued this in Homer and others, Let them learne it of Paule, Galath. 3. where beeing about to ſhew, that in Chriſte there is no difference of theVerſe. 28. outward diſtinctiō of kindes in this life: he maketh a diſtinction, or numbring vp of the diuers ſorts, and ioyneth the two laſt moſt like in nature and kindred, yet not one and the ſame togeather, ſaying: There is neither Iewe nor Grecian, ther is neither bond nor free, there is neither male and female. Hauing anſwered this obiection, I proceede to other argumentes.
               1 Whatſoeuer is ſet as Church-officer in the Church by God, with a diſtinct and proper ordinary gift, that is ſuch as we haue aboue deſcribed:
               2 But God hath ſet in the Church Doctors, and giuen them their peculiar worke and gyft, The Worde, or vtteraunce of knowledge, diſtinguiſhed from the Paſtors worke and gift, the Word or vtteraunce of Wiſdome in exhortation:
               3 Wherfore the Doctor is ſuch a one as we haue deſcribed.
               
                  The ſecond part is manifeſt by theſe wordes. And theſe God hath ſet in his Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondly Prophetes, thirdly teachers, after powers, thē the gifts of
                  1 Cor. 12. 28 
                  healing, helpers, gouernors, ſorts of tongs: are all Apoſtles? are al propehts? Are all teachers. And ver. 8. To this is giuen by the ſpirit, the word of wiſdom, to an other the word of knowledge according to the ſame ſpirite. If they ſay, the Worde teacher, is heere taken generally, not properly for the Doctor: beſides the 8. verſe, which doth manifeſtly refel them, theſe reaſons confute them: Firſt, becauſe he diſtinguiſheth them from apoſtles and Prophets, which in that generall ſignification ſhould comprehend them, and if it ſhould comprehende anye more then Doctours properly, yet it were no reaſon to ſhutte out thoſe who are ſo called. Laſtly, ſeing they can ſhew no place where it is ſo taken, but alwayes is generall of all Miniſters of the Word, as the Apoſtle calleth him-ſelfe A teacher of the Gentiles. And Timothy is willed to teach, as alſo is euery Biſhop; or els it is proper for the peculier Church-officer ſo called: it

were againſt al rule of interpretation, to ſhut out the proper, which here agreeth with the circūſtances of the text, &amp; take a ſtraunge &amp; vnwonted ſignification, as to ſignifie a Paſtor by a Doctor. Our laſt reaſon is: Seeing the Prophet Eſay, propheſying of the calling of the Gentiles by the miniſterie of the Apoſtles, doth alſo propheſie, that of theſe called to the faith, he would take of them to be Prieſtes and Leuites, meaning (according as the Prophets vſe to ſpeake, by offices and holy thinges of the lawe, to note out ſuch offices as had ſome ſimilitude, &amp; proportion with thoſe vnder the Goſpell) them to be Paſtors, who in adminiſtring of the Sacraments, &amp; ſleaing by exhortation the old man, &amp; offring vp the new man acceptable to God, holde proportion with the Prieſtes: and to be Leuits, whoſe office concerning y• ſubſtantiall poynt of deliuery of doctrine, is one &amp; the ſame with theirs, that it muſt needs be, that according to the ſcriptures of the new Teſtament, this propheſie ſhold be fulfilled in the office of Doctors as well as of Paſtors. And this was that

which the Fathers ment in their cōmon
                     Ciprian. lib 1. epiſt. 9. ad furitanos. Ambroſ. lib. 1. off. c. 50. Aug. queſt ex vtroq: teſt. mixt. q 101. reſembling of Paſtors to Prieſtes. Euſebius declareth this moſt plainly in ſetting down the duties of y• Doctor to catechiſe them, &amp; as a maſter his ſchollers by continual reading to them, or exerciſing to aduance them in knowledge. For writing of y• perſecution of y• church vnder Seuerus, &amp; ſpeaking of Origin, he ſaith: 
                     
                        •
                     he exerciſe of teaching, or the ſchole exerciſing, as ſome where euen himſelf maketh relation in writing, &amp; none ſerued or was ſet to catechiſe at Alexandria, but all were driuen
                  Hiſt. lib. 5. cap. 3. Scholazon ti de tei diatribe. Toi Katechein anakeimenou. Toutes katecheſeos proeſte didaskaleiou.
                   
                  away by the threatning of perſecution: ſome of the Gentils came vnto him to heare the word of God. And a little after: Origin was then 18. yeare old, when he was ouer the ſchoole of catechiſing or inſtructing. And Nazianzen ſaith in Orat. Pros tous politeuomenous. The ſeruants muſt be ſubiect to their maſters, the wiues to their huſbands, the Church to the Lorde, the Diſciples to their Paſtors and Teachers.
               
            
            
               Of the Elders and Elderſhip.
               HAuing ended the treatiſe of the Doctor his office; we are to proceede vnto the Elders, and Elderſhip

with whom he dealeth as prophanely as with the others: his wordes are. fol. 43. But why are Preſbyteri, ſuch as expoūd in the Church, tranſlated Elders? I truſt he mindeth not hereby to ſhut out all lay-men from the Elderſhip or ſeigniory which is dreamed of, leaſt peraduenture he him ſelf be Excluſiſſimus.
                   And Pag. 57. And doth our Author thinke that this man heere doth meane their laye Presbiteries, neuer heard nor reade of from the beginning of the worlde, till within theſe fortye yeares or little more, becauſe he nameth them Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrates. In which wordes of our author, wee ſee his cheefeſt reaſon againſt the Eccleſiaſticall Preſbyterie is, that the Elders are lay, and the Preſbyteries lay, and therefore there hath not beene heard til within this forty year, of them in the world. To which we anſwere, if y• Elders which ioine with the Paſtor &amp; Doctor were lay men, yet it followeth not, that the Elderſhip is lay. But can his degree of Doctor (if he bee ſo much) giue ſuch credite vnto his bare word, as

though all y• Chriſtian Churches (which by the grace of God do exerciſe this diſcipline) ſhoulde bee beleeued to haue a Preſbitery of ſuch as are not elected and ordained Eccleſiaſtically to their office? If I be not deceiued herein his lawes may teach him if he wil not learn it out of the Scriptures, that whoſoeuer is called with due examination and trial, with the conſent of thoſe to whom it appertaineth, and are with faſting and prayers, or prayers onely and with impoſition of hands ſeperated or put a part to that office, that they are Eccleſiaſtical perſons and not lay-men (as he calleth them) otherwiſe, there is no rule in the Scripture to deſcerne betweene men priuate, and betweene Church-officers. Nowe, if hee conſider either the order which we maintaine out of the Scripture, or that which is practized in al reformed Churches, he ſhal find, that theyActes. 14. Actes. 6. 1. Tim. 4. 1. Tim. 5. are duely examined by the Elders, elected of the whole Churche, ordeined of the Elderſhip, yea, hee ſhall finde this to be true of Deacons, much more of Elders. But if this exception were true, as

it is moſte falſe, who can chuſe, but hee muſt abhorre the hypocriſy of theſe men, who can deface the ordinance of God, which they want, which they themſelues haue not. For their Commiſſaries and Chauncellors, who ſuſpende, Excommunicate, and adminiſter the diſcipline of our Church vnder the Byſhops, what are they? who calleth them▪ the Byſhop: who ordaineth them▪ or annoynteth them▪ his Letters Patentes: By whoſe prayers doe they looke to obtaine comfort in their calling? by the byſhops bleſſings without prayer, without faſting. To what office are they put apart▪ to mingle heauen and earth together, matters of God and matters of men: to excommunicate, &amp; take probats of teſtaments: to admoniſh eccleſiaſtically &amp; commit penance: to be Lord ouer ye miniſters, themſelues hauing taken no degrees. Thus though their calling bee neither eccleſiaſtical, becauſe they come to no church-election, nor haue any ſuch ordination: nor ciuil, becauſe they be called by y• biſhop only as he is biſhop, put a part neither to adminiſter eccleſiaſtical

things only, nor things ciuil only, but to both and to ſome which are neither; as to giue men ſpiritually leaue to mary, and eat fleſh in Lente, as though they were made to goe beyonde all good eſtate of mankinde, beyonde y• body, becauſe they meddle with the ſoule, beyond the ſoule, becauſe they meddle with that which pertaineth vnto it: nay, ſomtimes which is hurtful. Wherfore, althogh this were ſufficient to ſtop his prophane mouth: yet that it may appeare that the gray haires of this order, are more auncient then the very hoarie head of his Chauncellors and commiſſaries: I will prooue it to be the ordinaunce of GOD out of the Scriptures, that there ought to bee an Eccleſiaſticall Senate of Paſtors, Doctors and Elders gouerning onely, to haue the adminiſtration of Churchmatters, and that they ought to bee adminiſtred Eccleſiaſtically.
               1 If the Apoſtles ſet downe two ſorts1. Reaſon. of Elders which rule the Church wel, and are worthy of double honor: the one ſort of them only ruling, the other labouring alſo in the Worde and

doctrine (which are as hath beene proued before the Paſtors and Doctors); then it is plaine that theſe raiſing only muſt be added vnto them:
               2 But the firſt is true by the expreſſe wordes of the Apoſtle. 1. Tim. 5. 17.
               3 Therefore the former aſſertion is certaine.
               To this place ſome are wont to obiect that the firſt ſort are ſuch as are occupied in the Word and Sacraments, thogh they preach not. But this will not ſerue, both becauſe we haue prooued that none are to be admitted to that, but they ought to preach, and alſo becauſe thoſe ſhoulde yet be occupyed in the Worde, and therefore comprehended vnder the latter ſort. Now, when they perceiue this will not ſerue (beeing men willing to learne of anye) they haue learned of the Jeſuites to aunſweare, That ſuch
                  
                     Ieſuites Teſtament Rheimes. 1. Tim. 5. 17. 
                  Prieſts ſpecially and Prelates, are worthy of duble, that is more ample honour, that are able to teach and preach, and do take paines therein. And therefore they make, that all for their office, are worthy of double honour: but ſpecially thoſe which labour

diligently and painfully in the Worde.D. Cop. ſer. lat. in con. But this ſhift is manifeſtly diſcouered by the text. Firſt, becauſe the Apoſtle ſhoulde then haue ſaid thus: they which are occupyed in Word and doctrine, are worthy of double honor, eſpecially thoſe which labour: but he doth not make the miniſtery of word and doctrine common to both, but the miniſtery of gouerning. Secondlye, the Apoſtle by theſe mens goodly deuice, ſhoulde not proceede, but ſhould go backwarde in his compariſon: for he had then ſayde more in the firſte part, when he ſayd, They which do it well: or (as he might ſaye) with worthineſſe of praiſe, which he that doth, muſt not onely do it with labour, paines, &amp; diligence,Calos. but alſo with purity, wiſdome, zeale, power, ſoūdnes, fitnes, &amp; many other things beſides labour. So this ſenſe cleane ouerthroweth the Apoſtles increaſe by the worde Eſpecially. Thirdly, by this meanes the Apoſtle muſte make three ſortes of Miniſters of the worde, ſuch as are occupied in the Word, but not well, (belike their ignoraunt Miniſters). Firſt, they which ſhoulde haue ſome honour

for their office ſake, then ſome that doe it well, but not with labour or diligence, which muſt haue double honour though they labour not; &amp; the laſt, which doe it more then well, which muſt haue more then double honour. If this be not to dally with the Lordes word, what is? Fourthly, If the difference were not in thinges wherein they are occupied, but in the labour aboue others, or the ſlouthfull labouring of others, this difference ſhould be none at all, ſeeing the Apoſtle in other places giueth watchfulneſſe, which is more then labour, for it is aHeb. 13. 17. continuaunce of labour, with great regard, not onely in preaching, but otherwiſe for their ſoules health. Yea, he giueth this very word, Copiōtes, which labor, to all that are ouer them in the Lord, and
                  1. Theſ. 5. 
                  admoniſh them, which they muſt reuerence and acknowledge. Laſtly, their diſtinction and interpretation is cleane deſtitute of conference of Scriptures, which are not wont to giue double honor to any but to thoſe which are painfull, &amp; which labor in their worke: but ours haue moſte manifeſt witnes out of other places, as ſhall

appeare by the other reaſons following.
               1 If the Apoſtle Rom. 12. ſetting2. Reaſon. downe y• ordinary members of Chriſts Church, which differ in their proper action, doe ſet downe the Elder to be ouer the people with diligence, and not to be occupied in the miniſtery of the Worde, eyther by exhortation or doctrine, but to admoniſh them and rule1. Theſ. 5. them: then our aſſertions muſt needes be certain:
               2 But the firſt is manifeſt. Rom. 12. 6. 7. &amp;c.
               3 Therefore this hath beene ordained by the Apoſtles.
               1 If the Apoſtle ſay in the 1. cor. 12.3. Reaſon. that beſides the Miniſters of y• Word, God hath ſet in his Church, Gouernours, then our Poſition is true:
               2 But he ſayth, God hath ſet firſt Apoſtles, Thirdlye, Teachers, Gouernors. &amp;c:
               3 Wherefore our Doctrine is not vncertaine, but the liuely trueth of God his Worde.
               Unto theſe two they doe obiecte, that by theſe, Magiſtrates are meant,

but that is plainelye confuted by theſe reaſons oute of the Text. Firſt, becauſe the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of them as of Church-Officers, and which wereRom. 12. 6. 1. Cor. 12. 13. 14. 27. then the members of Chriſtes bodye, which then theire Magiſtrates were not. Secondlye, he ſpeaketh of them as of ſuch giftes as came then newly by preaching of the goſpel to the Gentiles, and ſuch as they ſhould then with zeale followe after. Rom. 12. 6. 1. Cor. 12. 31. Which the Apoſtles would neyther ſay nor exhort them to doe concerning the Magiſtrates office, for they neuer were ſo Annabaptiſtical, as to exhorte theire churches to be zealous, to become Magiſtrates. Thirdly, the Apoſtle doth after ſpeake of the Magiſtrates and their dutie, and of the churches duetye to them. Rom. 13. Laſtly, the Gouernours wee ſpeake of, in their gouerment are placed as farre vnder the Paſtors and Teachers, as they are vnder the Apoſtles and Prophetes, which if they dare ſay it of y• Magiſtrates they are them-ſelues become plaine Annabaptiſts, and do cleane ouerthrow the moſt rightfull ſoueraigntie

of Princes ouer all perſons and cauſes, as well Ciuill as Eccleſiaſticall. A fourth reaſon is, ſeeing oure Sauiour Chriſt, in ſetting downe the Eccleſiaſticall Preſbytery, ſpeaketh according to the Jewes, for otherwiſe the Apoſtles could not haue vnderſtood him, when he ſayde, tell the congregation or Churche, which was the title then giuen vnto the1. Cor. 13. 2. 9 Beza on this place.
                   Eccleſiaſticall Senate, and his wordes of hauing as a Publican and Heathen, doth manifeſtly prooue he ment to ſpeak according to their cuſtome: It muſt needes be that hee did according to the places afore brought, ordayne a Preſbytery of Paſtors, Teachers, and Elders,Marke. 15. 1. Luke. 22. 16. like vnto theirs of Prieſtes, Scribes, or Teachers of the Law, and their Elders which gouerned onely.
               In y• fift place, y• precept of S. James, which willeth them to ſende for the Elders of the Church, when they be weak,Iames 5. therby plainly declaring, that y• Church ought not onely to haue a Paſtor and a Doctor, whoſe cheefe attendance muſt be
                  1. Tim. 4. 
                  on reading, exhortation and doctrine: But alſo many who ought alwayes to bee

ready at the inſtant calling of diuers and many at once, that none in y• neceſſary worke bee neglected: it followeth thereby, that beſide them, there ought to be ſuch other elders, as may admoniſh the vnruly, comfort the weak minded, &amp; patient
                  1. Theſ. 5. 
                  towards all. Laſtly, all thoſe places which ſay, Elders were ordayned Churche byActes. 14. Church, that an accuſation muſt not be taken againſt them vnder two witneſſes1. Tim. 5. and ſuch like, doe eſtabliſh theſe; for ſeeing the wordes are generall to both, as haue bene prooued before, and no circumſtance doth reſtraine them: nay, the circumſtances vphold y• general becauſe in the firſt place, Lukes purpoſe is to declare howe the Apoſtles broughte the Churches to a perfect and full order of Church-gouernment; and in the other, the Apoſtle had ſpoken immediately before of both ſorts. Wherfore vnleſſe they will ouerthrowe all certayne ſenſe of theſe places, and that notable rule of interpretation, that the wordes and ſenſe of places, are not to be reſtrained but vpon repugnance of places, or playn circumſtaunces of Text, they muſt here

vnderſtande both ſortes of Elders. And thus much out of the Scriptures: nowe out of the Fathers. IGNATIVS AD TRVLL. There is no Churche which can ſtande without her Elderſhippe
                  
                  Preſbiterion Kai ſynedrion. 
                  or Councell. Tertull. Apoll. Cap. 39. If there bee anye that hath committed ſuch a fault, that hee bee put away from the partaking of the Praiers of the Church, and from all holy affayres or matters: there bee preſidents, certain of the moſt approued auncientes and Elders. Theophilact. on the place of Mat. interpreteth tell the Church, tell the Gouernours thereof. Ambroſe 1. Timoth. 5. Complayneth that the Teachers and Miniſters of the Word, ſuffered this to weare out of the Church, or rather of pride, whilſte they onely would ſeeme to doe ſomwhat. Nowe all knowe that the Elders, which they called Sacerdotes, Prieſtes, were not worne out of vſe, therefore hee may meane this, and this ſheweth what the Fathers meant. And CIPRIAN confirmeth that as manifeſtlye, that it remayned in his time: where (he ſayth) Lib. 4. Epi. 22▪ whē either examining whether al things agreed
                  
                  to them which ſhould be in thoſe, who were prepared for the Eccleſiaſticall function. We gaue it to Optatus, we with the Elders,
                  Clerum. 
                  Doctors, and readers, ordain him Teacher of thoſe which heare. Which ſheweth there were Elders for Gouernment, which were not occupied in any publike diuine ſeruice, diſtinguiſhed not onelye from the Preachers but Readers. Ierom alſo ſaith, The Chriſtian Church alſo hath her Elderſhip. Ier. 2. lib. in Iſa. Which when he meneth it of ſuch as the Jewes had, it is plain hee meaneth thoſe which we doe, as may appeare by his wordes of the Jewes Elders, Ad Galaſ. queſt. decim. They chose (ſaith he) of the wiſeſt of their company for gouernors: which ſhoulde aſwell admoniſh thoſe that had any corporall pollution to abſtaine from the aſſemblies, as to reprooue the breakers of the Sabboth.
               
            
            
               A reply to the variable collections following, againſt the Diſcipline.
               HItherto we haue had whatſoeuer force he coulde make againſt the

ſeuerall pointes of Church-gouernment handled before. Now, becauſe he thoght the ſtenche of the former dung was not ſtrong ynough, to ouercome the ſweete ſauour which the Worde caſteth vppon the Diſcipline; hee hath tumbled together (as hee thinketh) a great many diuerſities and contrarieties, drawn from the writinges of thoſe, which ſeeke the Church-diſcipline: whereby he woulde faine faſten vppon it, that it is not to bee yeelded vnto, becauſe the Authors arePage. 191 not At any accorde or reſolution amongſt themſelues, nor yet with other learned men: Alſo vppon hie olde ſong, that theſe matters are in the liberty of the Church, it is a very nice and a dangerous ſcrupuloſity, rather then to vſe that aright, which hath beene once abuſed, that a man ſhoulde goe aboute to deuiſe, and to laye oute new plat-formes in Church-matters,Page. 191 in which of necesſitie ſuch difficulties will daylye ariſe, that cannot by anye192 reache of mans wit bee forecaſt, and will breede not only a continuall toil, but alſo infinite daungerous innonations,

both in the Church and common-wealth. Concerning which ſlaunderous dealing of his, I will firſt generally ſpeake of it, and then make aunſwere to his ſeuerall collections, adding vnto euery one of his, open contradictions &amp; inconueniences of their ſide, not only drawn from the diuerſitie of mens iudgement, which in the beſt thinges are through humane infirmity, at oddes; but ſuch as ſhew the cheefe defendors to bee at warre with them ſelues, in the points which they mayntayn, &amp; with the holy doctrin which they muſt needs confeſſe. Now may it pleaſe the Reader, in the firſt place to conſider, what iniutye this man doth, not onelye to the Diſcipline, but alſo to our holy Religion in this manner of dealing. For by this reaſoning of his, it ſhall come to paſſe that the Religion when it was firſt preached by the Apoſtles, becauſe it was ioyned with contrarieties and ſtrifes, as of thoſe of the Circumciſion
                  Act 11. &amp; 15 Galat. 4. 
                  with the reſt, and ſometimes with bitterneſſe and difference betweene the Miniſters, whilſte one woulde haue one
                  
                  that had forſaken the worke go with them another woulde not: ſometimes tumultes and diſorders following the ſame; it might well haue beene refuſed and eaſt away: ſeeing the Profeſſors were at variance, contended, and many inconueniences (in the reaſon of man) followed their preaching. By this meanes, the whole religion (which is in truth maintained of vs, and of our brethren whom now they call Lutherans, as an vncertain and vngrounded religion, becauſe of contrariety between vs in the matter of the Sacrament, of the vbiquiti &amp; other points) may be reiected of ye papiſts, and their reaſon muſt be held as good, becauſe they haue as learnedly and truly gathered our diuerſities betweene our ſelues, inconueniences following vppon our Doctrine, as this man hath doone in the matter of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline. Next vnto this fowle iniury done vnto religion, his iniury done vnto ſo many worthy lerned men, which haue ſo well deſerued of the Church of God: nay, his inuiry done vnto all the reformed Churches, in ſetting them together

by the eares, in ſlaundering them to like of, vphold and maintain, ſuch a gouernment as hath no witneſſe of the Scriptures or ancient times, thogh they main tayne it by both) ſuch as bringeth withConfirmation de la diſcipline eccleſiaſtique. it, not onely a maze and labarinth vnto all common-weales, but which is at flat ennemity with Princes, ouerthroweth their gouernment in Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, and by ſudden alteration, turneth euery thing vpſie-downe. Which reproch though it be ſo apparaunt, as his owne conſcience ſmote him with the gylce of it, ſo as he would fayne auoyd the ſhame of it by colourable proteſtation, andPage. 191. that before God, not to derogate from any tollerable order eſtabliſhed in theſe externall matters, yet he cannot chuſe but charge them, that they make Princes raunge with the reſt of204. their Seniours and Church-gouernours, and that they debar princes of that right of gouernment in matters and ouer perſons Eecleſiaſtical, which the word of God, &amp; al the examples of godly kings of Iudae doe aford vnto vs. The falſehoode of which is not

onely manyfeſt by this witnes of haſte, as good as a thouſand agaynſt him: but alſo by the teſtimonye which ſo manye worthy wryters, nay Princes and Magiſtrates in their practiſe and confeſſions haue giuen to the ſame. Now, when the Chriſtian Reader hath conſidered of this iniurye donne vnto GOD and his Church, to vnderſtande alſo, firſte that theſe are but Rapſodies gathered at leaſure, boaſted of &amp; caſt in the teth of ſome long ſince, ſuch as had other-wyſe been vttered ere this, but that no market would ſerue ſo well this. Secondly, that although He do as Sanballet, ſend vs
                  Nehem. 6. 6. ver. 7. 8. 9. 
                  in wryting, worde, that we woulde builde vp the wall of Ieruſalem, and make our ſelues kinges, when theſe thinges come to paſſe: and that we ſet vp Prophetes which may preach of vs at Ieruſalem, there is a King at Iuda, euery Paſtor will be Pope: yea, and aboue the Prince in his Preſbytery: Yet with good Nehemias we can truely aunſwere, There is none of theſe thinges done, but thou doſt inuent them in thine hart, and that all this is but to caſt a feare vnto vs: for they ſay their handes ſhall be weake from this
                  
                  worke that they perfect it not. And therefore that our remedy is, ſeeing we vſe no meanes but by ſupplication, but by manyfeſtation of the truth, and ſeeke for nothing but Diſcipline, which by the booke of ordination we promiſe to further according to our power, euē to pray with the ſayde Neh. Confirme (O God) our hands. The firſt contradiction (interlaſed with a lie, that they make him Antichriſt,
                     Page. 193 
                     which refuſeth the Presbytery.) is y• we vrge this as perpetual out of the place of Timothy, which Caluin doth referre to his miniſtery. which is no contradiction, ſeeing if it be referred to his office, yet it being a peece of Timothies office, to procure that the thinges which he had learned of Paule, ſhoulde be kept according to their nature and difference perpetually in the Church, it ſufficiently prooueth the matter in hande, otherwiſe how Could he keepe it vntill the comming
                     2. Tim. 2. 
                     of Chriſt? Like to that is, the allegation out of the French diſcipline, that thoſe articles which were there contayned touching diſcipline, are not ſo ſetled amongſt vs, but that the vnity (he
                     
                     ſhould ſay) vtility of the church ſo requiring, they may be chaunged. which I ſaye, is a meere cauill, for they ſpeak not, nor meane not it of the ſubſtance of diſcipline contained in y• word, but their maner of ſetting it downe according to the circumſtaunces of their time, as is plaine by Their title which calleth it
                     Primier proiect. 
                     but the firſte caſt, brought of the ſubſtance of it, as it is contayned in the Scriptures of the Apoſtles: Which ſubſtaunce, they were not ſo mad to change, though they iudged they might alter thē in many points of circūſtances. For theſe ſily contradictions, let him take theſe monſtrous ones proceding from this, y• they wil not acknowledge the perfection of y• ſcriptures cōcerning diſcipline. One nū
                     bring vp as a circumſtance to come clothed or naked to the ſupper of the Lord, ſaith of thoſe circūſtances, None of theſe
                     D. Whit. booke. Page. 24. page. 25. 
                     circumſtances are commauded in the Scriptures, nor can by neceſſary collectiō be granted, yet he knoweth it doth neceſſarily appertaine to comelines. The next is that the Abſtractor ſaith, the Miniſters ought not to
                     
                        Page-194 
                     wreſt any thing into the gouernment of the
                     
                     church, without due authoritie from the magiſtrate, which he would haue contrary to that of the admonition &amp; M. Cartwright, that our life muſt not be deare, as thogh we can not by ſuffering (if need were, for ſo the condition is put) aforde, that, without doing any thing which hath not due authority from the Magiſtrate. His mingling of our ſentence with Brownes, 
                     Page. 214. is but a malitious proceeding: Seeing him-ſelfe teſtifieth after, that wee doe more then miſlyke his doinges and writinges in reſpect of ſuch proceedinges. Like to this, is that he alleadgeth out of Iunius, that if the Prince doe hinder the building of the Church, the people may by force of armes reſiſt him. Which as it is not in the Page which he noteth, nor in all his booke of Diſcipline: ſo how malitious a ſlander it is brought vp, vpon ſo worthy a ſeruaunt of God, maye appeare by his whole treatiſe of the ciuill. Magiſtrat, Lib. 3. cap. 5. Where hauing ſhewed how the Magiſtrate cannot alter the ſubſtantiall poyntes of Diſcipline, and handled that queſtion to one obiecting, What ſhall the Church
                  
                  doe if it be (by the Magiſtrates authoritye, commaundement, threatning, and violence) compelled. Hee aunſweareth, If the Magiſtrate ordayne any thing contrarie to God his worde, that the Miniſters ſhoulde plainly and modeſtly declare with Paule, that they can do nothing againſt, but for the truth. But if the thinges be not contrarye to the truth and neceſſitie, that the Churches
                  Page. 207. 
                  are bound rather patiently to beare it, then to bring the holy ordinaunce of God, their body, and the common peace into daunger. Concerning excommunication, ſhall be ſpoken after. The booke he nameth of obedience I haue not. The other matter out of the book deiure Magiſtratum, as not pertayning to vs, I purpoſe not to meddle with, eſpecially conſidering he handleth it more like a Lawyer then otherwiſe. But after he hath alleadged teſtimonies to prooue that, Which none but Papiſtes and AnnabaptiſtesPage. 196. will deny, that it is traiterous to teach the people that they ſhoulde owe no ſeruice to euil kinges, he addeth, leaſt this long treatiſe ſhoulde ſeeme altogeather impertinent, that he could not
                  
                  chuſe but oppoſe to the fanaticallPage. 197. ſpirites and traiterous allegations, both of theſe dangerous innouators, &amp; of the rebellious Papiſtes. But alas, why are we poore Miniſters (as he calleth vs before, whom a man of meane eſtate wil not regard) ſo dangerous? He anſwereth, becauſe we would haue our ſoueraignes kingdome to be holden at the chiefe inferior magiſtrates, the people or Presbyteries deuotion. Oh heauen, O earth, O Lorde our God, the ſearcher of the ſecreats of all hearts, the author of the holy diſcipline we ſeek, reueale (we beſech thee) our horrible treaſon: bring vpon vs &amp; our children for euer vtter cōfuſion in this life, &amp; in y• life to come, if this wickednes be either intended, thought vpon, or be likely to follow vpon the diſcipline which we ſeeke, or vpon our deſire of the ſame. If you, O you holy fathers, and miniſters of God, which haue writetn for, defended, mayntained, &amp; with great danger attained vnto this, may not cleare our cauſe by y• vn fained fidelitye which you haue ſhewed to chriſtian Princes: yet let your wiſedome

&amp; experience, Oh you Princes and Magiſtrates, which haue receiued it, honored it, tried it, beare witneſſe vnto the innocēcie of this cauſe. Shal that which hath bin a friend to magiſtrates, when they were enemies to it, be enemies to Magiſtrats, when they ſhould be friends vnto it: Shal that which D. Whitgift himſelf confeſſeth (namely, That ſuch Seniors
                  D. Whit▪ laſt booke. 161. 
                  were, but long ago worne out of vſe. For which he alleadgeth, the ſentence of Ambroſe before alleadged) ſhal, that I ſay, called for of that holye man, become traiterous &amp; pernitious to the ſtate? Can the office of an Archbiſhop in the ſecond place of the land, doing al that alone, and more in Church-matters then the ſeniours, hauing with it ciuil power and authority be free from this ſuſpition: and cannot Miniſters and Elders of baſe account in the world, medling onely as the Apoſtles, with ſpirituall matters &amp; that according to the word of God, be void of al ſurmize of ſuch vilanous practiſe: can their counſels be accounted ſafe, where none come but themſelues, whō they wil &amp; who are deuoted to their honor &amp; kingdome

eccleſiaſticall? And ſhal the miniſters conſultations be ſo fit for ſuch practiſes where ſo many Elders (as he ſayth lay men) of all degrees may be preſent, where the Magiſtrates may haue both their eyes &amp; their eares? Whoſe decrees in al matters of greateſt waight, of Excōmunication, Election, Abdication, ending of common controuerſies, muſt come vnder the conſcience of all men: yea, whoſe whole acts and counſels may eaſily be ſeene, by the Magiſtrate, who may force them to a new courſe, if they doe any thing preiudiciall to the eſtate? The good king Iehoſhaphat, according to the Word of God, and the example of his father Dauid, ordeined beſides the1. Chron. 27 30. Prieſts and Leuites in all Cities, the cheefe of Families for the iudgementes of the Lord, and for the matters of God beſides
                  2. Chro. 19. 8. 11. 
                  others appoynted for ciuill matters, called the kings matters. Now, ſhall wee thinke, that hee coulde not ſee into the matters of a kingdome and the ſafety thereof, aſwell as this man? The Princes of Iuda at their returne, when their ſtate was ſubiect vnto ſo many dangers,

when their Prophets conſpired againſtHeſr. 10. 8. them, yet vphelde the Eccleſiaſticall Preſbytery to threaten excommunication and ſeperation from Gods people, to the obſtinate ſinners, as wel they thē-ſelues did confiſcation of goodes and ciuill puniſhment: neither were they euer iealous ouer their eſtate. Wherefore, ſeeing we haue ſuch a cloude of witneſſes of theſe tymes and of former, both vnder the law and vnder the Goſpel, we need not feare but their lying &amp; irōforhead in charging vs with ſuch traiterous opinions, ſhalbe manifeſt to all, and ſhall tourne vppon their owne heades. For manifeſtation whereof; let the Magiſtrates conſider what is written of them highly derogatorie vnto their eſtate and freedome, which they make them beleue that they maintaine. First they ſay the forme and maner of Church gouernment may be altered
                  
                     Page. 192. 
                        〈…〉
                     . 3
                        •
                     9. 
                  by the Magiſtrate▪ then they ſay the externall gouernment of the Church vnder a Chriſtian Magiſtrate must be according to the forme of gouernment uſed in the common-wealth. Which is flat contrary to that, that the Chriſtian Magiſtrate

                  may alter at their good pleaſure. Which alſo driueth the Queenes moſte excellent maieſty, eyther to part her Crowne with ſome other, or elſe muſte make one Archbiſhop not only of byſhops, but alſo ouer Archb. y• in the Church there maye be a Monark, as wel as in the commonwealth. Againe, when they ſay y• Archb. is contayned vnder S. Paules Biſhop, they leaue it not in the Magiſtrates power to take away his iuriſdiction, how daungerous ſo euer it be to her eſtate. Agayne, let them conſider into what a low place they bring the Magiſtrate into, in the Church, when expounding the place of the Corinthes of him, they makeD. Whit. laſt. b. deuiſ. 6. 7. page, 631. him go after the teacher, &amp; therfore much more after the Archbi. Hauing therfore noted theſe their open contradictions &amp; moſt abſurd opinions, preiudicial indeed to her maieſties authority: let vs ere we paſſe from this general, (what the forme of eccleſiaſtical gouernment is) conſider once againe of his aſſertion, and ſee whether it bewray not manifeſt ignorance, containe not cōtradiction &amp; repugnance in it ſelfe, and be not highly derogatory

to Chriſt &amp; his ſcriptures. His words are theſe pag. 192. Now as concerning the inward gouernment of the Church of Chriſt by his ſpirite, God working in his children, by the Miniſters of his writtē reuealed word: &amp; alſo touching the eſſential poynts of the outwarde policy &amp; gouernment of the church, conſiſting in the true teaching of the word of God, in the due adminiſtration of ſacraments according to chriſts holy inſtitution, in the aduancement &amp; furthering of vertue, with the beating downe of ſinne and impiety, and in keeking the Church in a quiet vnity and good order, there is no difference of opinion amongſt vs. And a little after, we affirm that no ſuch preciſe &amp; exact forme of external gouerment of the Church by diſcipline, as they depaint it out, is ſo much as by any exāple recōmended vnto vs in ſcripture: but much leſſe commanded, as a continuall platforme for euer to be followed. In which aſſertion omitting the nakednes of it, armed with no proofe out of the ſcripture or any good reaſon,

let vs ſee how it ſheweth ſuch groſſe ignoraunce as is not to be lucked for in a man of his gifts, for it deleareth that he can not diſtinguiſh betweene the cauſe, inſtrument and meanes of a thing, and the thing it ſelfe, betweene gouernment and the eſſentiall partes of gouernment and the fruits of it. For gouerment Eccleſiaſticall, that is, the ſpirituall adminiſtration of Chriſt by the order, and inſtruments of his Church which he hath ordayned, is a different thing from the truth of it, which is the aduancement of vertue, the beating downe and ſuppreſsing of ſinne and impietie, the keeping of the Church in a vnity and quiet order: which beeing the effect of Chriſtes kingdome and his gouernement,Eſa. 31. 1. 2. 3 hee maketh them the eſſentiall partes of it. So that he hath not learned yet to put a difference Betweene the kingdome of God, and Gods righteouſneſſe eſtabliſhed by it, Nor betweene the twoMath. 7. petitions of the Lordes prayer, that his kingdomr may come, and the fruite of this, That his will may be done in earth as in heauen. Againe, he graunteth the eſſentiall

partes of Chriſtes kingdome▪ 
                  and outwarde policie of the Church, but he denyeth any exact forme, as though there can be eſſentiall poy
                     •
                  tes of outwarde gouernment perpetuall, and yet they ſhal haue no perpetuall forme. Can there be an outwarde eſſentiall thing without a forme? Or can the eſſence be perpetuall and changeable, and the form variable and mutable: Can there be an immutable outward gouernment without immutable outward callinges, offices and workes: This is to giue a man without members, a ſkinne for a bodye without bones and fleſhe. Laſtly, how iniurious is this vnto Chriſt? he wil acknowledge the benefit muſt be had, but he will not acknowledge the hand wherby it is giuen. Chriſt is wiſe inough, ſtill to adminiſter and rule, and that he will gyue him leaue to doe. But y• he is wyſe inough to doe it by his owne1. Cor. 12. 2. 4. &amp;c. meanes, that hee being The onelye Lorde ſhould appoynt the diuers adminiſtrations of his Church alwayes, y• his ſpirite Shoulde miniſter fully ſufficient diuerſitie of giftes: that one God ſhoulde
                  
                  worke the ſufficient diuers faculties alwayes, That is vntollerable, falſe, ſeditious, hurtfull to the eſtate. He can allow the people ſhoulde bee taught, and exhorted, and haue the Sacramentes: but whether by Readers or by Teachers, by reading Homilyes, or by Paſtours,Eph. 4. 11. Rom. 12. 6. 7. by men or women, God his word doth not define; the people muſt be ruled, but whether by Gouernours appoynted by Chriſt, or by men: He muſt1. Cor. 12. relieue his pore with almeſſe, but whether by his Deacons or others: that he muſte ſeperate betwene the cleane,Actes. 6. and vncleane caſt out the wicked, but whether by his Church and ElderſhipMat. 18. or ſome other, muſte by no meanes be determined. As if one ſhould ſay, it is eſſentiall and perpetuall, that we haue our enteraunce into Chriſte and his Church, our growing and nouriſhing in the ſame ſealed vp perpetually, but that it ſhall be done onelye by Baptiſme and the Lordes Supper, and not alſo by confirmation that, maye not bee graunted. Chriſt was wyſe inough, and willing inough to ordayne the effects,

but not the inſtrumentes. If he ſaye he commaunded them ſaying, Baptize, doe this: So we ſay he commanded the other ſaying, I haue ſet Teachers, Gouernours,
                  1. Cor. 12. Rom. 12. 6. Mat. 18. ſaying, let the Doctor abide in Teaching, the Paſtour in exhortation, the Elder in ruling, the Deacon in distributing,
                  ver. 7. 7. 8. 
                  the Church euen the Elderſhip to be tolde and to excommunicate. Laſtly, it is as if one ſhould ſay, I can wel allow her moſt excellent maieſty for her excellent wiſedome, to ſee the commonwealth adminiſtred, iuſtice executed, matters rightly pleaded, &amp; determined: but y• this ſhalbe don by her moſt honorable coūsel, by her chief iuſtices, by her iuſtices of peace, by her Shiriefes and Balifes, by her Sergeants at the lawe, that I can not like or allow of. As for y• place of Tertulian, it is plaine, he meaneth it of the diſcipline in the courſe of life, which is chā
                  geable, as may appeare by the teſtimenies alledged in the firſt point. His next contradiction is concerning y• means of liuing, that y• French church wold haue, the rentes and reuenewes deliuered to the Deacons, ſo the miniſter receiue his ſtipend,
                  
but the booke of Diſcipline, T. C. and the Admonition ſpeaketh earneſtly againſte thoſe who gape after Church-liuings and turne it to their purſes and pleaſure,
                   asPage. 197 Page. 198 though theſe could not ſtande together, that they ſhoulde bee deliuered to the Churche onely, and turned to holy vſe, &amp; that it ſhoulde bee adminiſtred by the Deacons: or as though the playneſſe of the one in reproouing an abuſe, bee contrary to the good order taken by the other. Howſoeuer it be, ſo the Chriſtian Magiſtrate ſee the poore cared for by the Deacons, and that they who preach the Goſpell liue of the Goſpell, and that the
                  1. Corin. 9. Prouerb. 4. Galath. 6. 
                  Lord be thus honoured with our ſubſtance, we acknowledge he doth his duety towardes the Church: But if theſe want and the thinges giuen to that vſe, bee turned to the priuate commodity of ſome, there is a defect in that behalfe.
               But nowe this valiant champion will ouerthrowe the Elderſhip by ſuch weapons as followe, for T. C. Doth teach it from the Iewiſh Synedrion and out of the Talmud, which according to Bonauentur and Danaeus handled ciuill thinges: which
                     
                     our preſbytery may not doe.
                   To which I aunſwere that T. C. doth not fet it from ye Talmude, but from the word of God, as his whole diſputation doth ſhew in that pointe: onely hee ſheweth that this preſbytery hath beene continued vnder the Lawe and vnder the Goſpell, which is true and agreeed vppon by all three which he ſpeaketh of. It is alſo as falſ yt 
                  Bonauenture ſpeaketh ſo of the Eccleſiaſticall. Senate by it ſelfe, for that which
                     Boneuen. cap. 18. fine. Danaeus. c. 10. lib, 2. Iſag. 2. part.
                   he noted is of the ciuill and politike ſynedrion, Cap. 13. but hee maketh afterward when he handleth the Eccleſiaſtical pollicy of that time beſides the prieſt and beſides the Teachers in euery Sinagogue Senetors, which inquired of theire manners: which is manifeſte by Exod. 4. 29. Exod. 17. 5. 2. King. cap. 6. 32. Ier. 19. 1. Ezech. 8. 1. and Neh. 8. 5. Where are Elders occupied in Eccleſiaſticall matters, aſſistant to the Prophets and teaching Leuites, and yet diſtinguiſhed from them, ſo as they medled not with the Word. Danaeus in deede ſayth they medled ſomtimes wt ciuil adminiſtrations which ours do not, which

thing yet maketh no contradiction to vs, ſeeing we ſay with him, that to ours is giuen by Chriſt Eccleſiaſtical authority only. But the truth is, yt they were then plainly diſtinguiſhed, ſome being for the
                  1. Chr. 27. 30 2. Chron. 19. 8. 11. 
                  matters of God, and ſome for ciuill cauſes, the matters of the king. Now, the cauſe of this which Danaeus ſpeaketh of was, that in waighty matters both came together, becauſe the politike lawes of the Jewes were for the moſte part defined and ſet downe in the Worde of God, they, the Prieſt, Leuites, and Eccleſiaſticall Elders, were there to pronounce the ſentence Eccleſiaſtically: that is, to pronounce ye ſenſe of Gods word in yt cauſe: the Princes, cheefe of the people, and ciuil Senate, were to pronounce Ciuilly and iudicially the ſentence of death, or ſuch like according to the ſenſe of the Scriptures. Secondly by the cauſes, that when the Eccleſiaſticall Senate commeth to the Ciuill, the matters are thus mixt, as Jeremy 26. 16. But when the matter is Ciuil meerely, and no Queſtion of the ſenſe of the Scriptures, then it is of Magiſtrates onely:

as 1. chro. 28. 1. 1. chro. 13. 1. Or when the matters were meerely Eccleſiaſticall, then was the Eccleſiaſticall Senate onely brought together, as in conſultatiō. 2. king. 6. 32. As in matters to be done in the congregation. Act. 13. 15. For Excommunication John. 9. 22. 10. 40. For interpretation, the Prieſts and Leuites only, Math. 24. And laſtly by this, that Peter being before both the Senates Eccleſiaſticall and Ciuil, doth plainly diſtinguiſh them, calling ye oneArchontes tou laou. Preſbyteroi. 
                  the cheefe or rulers of Iſrael, the other the Elders of Iſrael. Wherefore this proueth not that they did exercize ciuill authority: and although our lawes political, are not in this reſpect like vnto the Jewes, yet if the Magiſtrate will call the Elderſhip to declare the will of God, or pronounce duely an Eccleſiaſticall ſentence, when hee will pronounce a Ciuill, it may well be done without the confuſion he ſpeaketh of. The next that he ſaith out of Caluine, ye Preſbitries of ye Jews was from men, not frō heauen is falſ: for Caluin ſaith only, ſince the captiuityDilecto. 
                  it was choſen for the cenſure of manners,
                  
but he ſayth alſo in that place that that
                  Dilecto. 
                  regiment was lawfull and allowed of God, and that Chriſt did worthily prayſe the order deliuered of the fathers, and that which was kept vnder the law Chriſt ſent vnto vs. Now the Fathers vnder the law, did not any of thoſe thinges and leſſe then theſe, but by God his commaundement, by his
                  2. Chr. 29. 25 
                  Prophets: yea, this was commanded both that in euery City and that for more difficult cauſes at Hieruſalem ſuch Senate ſhoulde bee appointed. Deut. 1. 8. 9. &amp;c. The like vntruethe is it that Muſculus vnderſtoode it of the whole Congregation. for euen as D. Whitgift alleadged him, pag. 633. He ſayth, It was by Seniors in Eccleſiaſticall aſſemblie. As vntrue is the other y• 
                  Caluine ſayth, Neyther in Chriſtes time, nor 22. yeares after, this Chriſtian Elderſhip was eſtabliſhed: for he ſayth in that place, Where Chriſte a little after erected his Church, the corruption beeing taken away, he did reſtore the pure vſe of Excommunication: And that there is no doubt but this order of diſcipline, which flouriſhed vnder the kingdome of Chriſt, ſucceeded into the place of that old, and it is playn by the

Scripture as ſoone as there was an ordinary ſet Congregation, there were Elders which ioined with the Apoſtles in Church-gouernment. Act. 12. 30. Actes. 15. 6. Acts. 21. 18. Neither muſt they by example of the Jewes haue but one for a Nation only, ſeeing it hath bene ſhewed, ſuch were in euery City and Synagogue,Mark. 5. 22. Acts. 13. 15. Act. 18. 8. 17. wheras if we ſhould ſquare it after this his patterne, we ſhould haue one only for y• whol Church. That he ſaith y• 
                  Apoſtles wold not haue executed the deacons office al Chriſts time, He bableth fables which he knowth not, for ther office in Chriſts time was only to preach and baptize in Iudaea, and to be witneſſes of
                  Marke. 3 14. Ioh 4. 2. 28. Act. 1. 21. 22. 
                  Chriſts life, doctrine, death, reſurrection and aſcention: That which they did at Hieruſalem, was but to take care for y• pore, till they had fit perſons and occaſion to eſtabliſh the order which Chriſte ordained: neyther did they it only becauſe they were withdrawn (which if they were, being ſo many, how much more ſhall Miniſters and Byſhops bee, if they looke to theſe and to ciuil affayres alſo) but alſoAr
                        •
                     ſton. becauſe it was not acceptable (meaning

to God) thus to doe, when they had by God his bleſſing both ſuche perſons, place and time as he required. Al the reſt of his ſome of words that neither father, Councel, nor Scripture hath left in memory where, when or by whom it was first erected &amp; put in practize, is worſe then nothing. For it was done of the Apoſtles at Jeruſalem, long before the councell, as is proued out of Act. 12. 30. But this ſheweth their giddineſſe, y• ſay ſomtime, y• it hath no teſtimony, either of ſcripture or antiquity, and yet again, confeſſe and alleadgeD. Whitgifts ſ. book page. 651. 
                  Ambroſe, to proue that Seniors haue beene, and that they were extinguiſhed before Ambroſe his time, which they will not ſay of Elders which miniſter the Word and Sacramentes, for they were not extinguiſhed before Ambroſe his time neither yet are. Alſo that they ſay the Byſhops differ, and are aboue other miniſters, for pollicy and order only, andIbid. Page. 385. yet make them differ in the Miniſtery of grace as in the ſentence of Exco
                     •••
                  ucation, of Abſolution, (and according to their Doctrine) of miniſtring ſtrength againſt temptations by confirmation:

For theſe they make proper to the Byſhop and not common to euery miniſter, and notwithſtanding the Miniſter muſt read the Excommunication: yet y• word, ſentence and authority doth come from the Byſhop, and for Abſolution it is ynough to goe to him or his Delegate. The nexte contraryetyes agree like friends: for, both all Is not expreſſed in the Scripture as the booke of Diſcipline ſayth, and yet all may be prooued by direct Scripture, Seeing whatſoeuer is neceſſarily collected thence, (though it be not expreſſed) is directlye prooued. Alſo the next is of as little value, for both Miniſters and Preachers, as Caluine ſayth, may be vnderſtood, and alſo gouerning Elders, as Beza noteth.Beza on that place. The next is an open lye, for Beza ſayth on that place of Tim. 5. 17. Therefore there were two ſortes of Elders, When
                  Duplices. 
                  one ſort ſhould attend on gouernment, the other on the Word &amp; prayer. Of ſuch force is the next, for the booke of Diſcipline agreeth in iudgment with M. Cartwight, that in the place of the 1. Tim. 3. vnder Deacous are comprehended both thoſe,

properly ſo called, and the Elders. For M. Cartwright referreth him ſelf to that obſeruation. Pag. 54. and prooueth it becauſe the qualities there ſet downeS. rep. S. part.
                   are common to bothe, and there are none touched proper to either, and the Word Deacons is taken in diuers places for all thoſe Miniſters which are not occupyed in the Worde as Rom. 12. 6. 1. Pet. 4. 11. The next is like to that of the 14. of the Act, and ſo to be anſwered. Alſo one may gather The Elderſhip out of the. 1. Cor. 12 (For of the 14. none doth) and out of the other places both, vnles he be ſo learned in diuinity yt he thinke diuers places cānot proue one thing. His other cauil is not worth a ruſh: for in one reſpect Deacons ſignifying ſomtime all Miniſtries not occupyed in the Worde, may be a Genus or generall to Elders and Deacons ſo called. Alſo the name Biſhop beeing generally giuen of their work of watching or our-ſeeing Act. 20. vnto Elders, may be commō both to miniſters and gouerning Elders, which diſagreeth not with this that Elders be teaching and vnteaching. It is true

alſo which is obſerued by the booke of Diſcipline, that the name of Elders is not giuen to thoſe Deacons which are diſtributers, and his written booke may be ouer-ſeene in ſo ſmal a thing as that. And ſo hauing ſeene his watr
                     •
                  ſh obiections let vs ſee howe his ſide, being drunk with the thirſt of honour, doe contrary them ſelues in one and the ſame point. For when the place of the Epheſians is broght againſt an Arrchb. as numbring vp all the Miniſtries of the Word, &amp; yet leauing out that, the aunſwere is, it is not
                  D. Whitg. ſ. booke. Page. 309. 
                  perfect, for Deacons are left out: and in the next page, that he ſpeaketh onely of the miniſters of the word in the place of the Epheſians. And again in the place of the 1.Ibid. Cor. 
                     •
                  2. The Apoſtle leaueth out Euangellūs, and yet in the next page, out of doubt the diuiſion of the Apoſtle there is perfect, And yet again. pag. 317. It is perfect. Heere note that to ſaye, It is not perfect, it is perfect, it is not perfect, of one and the ſame place, and in the ſame reſpect are euidently contrarie. There is no contradiction betweene this which isPage. 203. ſayd, that Byſhops liuings, &amp;c, be turned

to maintain the miniſtery, and yet that noble men being Elders haue no maintenaunce of the Church, I can finde no ſuch thing in the ſixt Art. of French diſcipline, &amp; if there were, their meaning is, yt they may not exercize any dominiō or cheefedome ouer the Deacons. Neither is it any diſorder if in an Eccleſiaſticall Senate and in the church, the miniſter be preferred before his Lorde, to conceiue prayer, to propound matters: For it is not abſurd for one to be ſuperiour and inferiour in diuers reſpectes: the Father inferioure to the Sonne, which is aboue him in deliuering the Worde. The firſt place out of Simler is not greatly materiall, if they chooſe ſome elder to moderate, though it belong vnto the Paſtour, yet it prooueth not, but that hee is Superiour in opening the Worde vnto them in choſe matters which are debated. The next though it bee a geeate blemiſhe and mayme, not to haue an Eccleſiaſticall Preſoyterye: yet it inforceth no contradiction, ſeeing that can-not bee the Preſbyterye ſpoken of in the ſcripture,

where by his owne interpretation miniſters are vnderſtoode. His concluſion which hee woulde inferre out of the Diſcipline of Fraunce, that becauſe Magiſtrates are of the conſiſtorie, and to be directed by the Paſtour, therefore they woulde raunge Princes with their Seniours, is diuerſly vayne. For firſte it is no reaſon, ſeeing the Prince may bee ſubiect to the Miniſtery of the Paſtor and Elders, and yet neuer Subiect or inferiour to theire perſons. Secondlye, it is manifeſt by their conditions, that they meant not the ſupreame Magiſtrates when they ſay: If one ſhall not hinder the exerciſe of the other, Which muſt needes bee in Princes, conſidering theire multitude of affayres. In the Booke of thePage. 205. 206. 
                  Souldier of Barwicke, If their bee any vnreuerent ſpeache, we allowe it not: yet if anye Prince will doe anye thing without Gods warrant in Church-matters, It muſt not bee obeyed, otherwiſe whatſoeuer is beyonde this, wee condemn as vndiſcreete. In the next, that he mighte make the Diſcipline enemye

to Princes, hee turneth vp againe that which ſober men long agoe haue left and conſented vnto. The firſt is, that we wold haue the Eccleſiaſticall Senate to adminiſter Eccleſiaſtical matters. Would not Jehoſephat alſo haue the Prieſtes1 Chro. 19. and Leuits to adminiſter the matters of God? And what hath he brought of our bookes, which is not as fully ſet down by thoſe reuerent men of God, B. lewell &amp; M. Nowell. Seeing they ſay, as long as
                  Defenſe of the Apol. 6. part. Ch. 11. deuiſ. 11. &amp; 12. Ch. deuiſ. 4. M. Nowel. tom. 2. part 35. 38. 
                  the Ministers bee Godly and learned, it is neceſſary they ſhoulde deſide theſe matters: that the Prince is commaunded to haue recourſe vnto them in doubtfull matters, that it belongeth to the Byſhops office, to decide of ſuch cauſes: but Chriſtian Princes haue rather to doe with theſe matters, then ignoraunt and wicked Prieſtes and that in caſe of neceſſitye the Prince ought to prouide for conuenient remedye. As for his ſlaunder that we agree with the Papiſtes to giue Chriſtian Princes power of fact, but not of Lawe and authoritye to promote and ſet forwarde, not to intermeddle in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall. Wee eſteeme it

no more then a fowle vntrueth, which euery, man of iudgement can conuince For if they haue authority in our iudgement by the Worde of GOD, to ſee to their Miniſtrye, and to cauſe them to make ſuch Lawes, as they knowe agreeable to Gods Worde: to authorize ſuch, and diſanull the contrarye: cauſe them to make good, when they woulde make yll: or orderlye to procure ſuche as can and will bee preſent in the action, and giue their conſent if it pleaſe them, (all which are giuen by T. C.
                  b. ſecond. p. 167. and by vs all vnto the Magyſtrate,) then doe wee graunte them no more then power of fact? then to promote matters? And in ſpeakinge agaynſt vs heerein, dothe hee not direct him ſelfe agaynſte the verye Lawes, and orders of the Churche? Which is, that the Conuocation-houſe doe make Eccleſiaſticall Lawes: and if they bee good, the Queene giueth her royall aſſent, and then they muſt be obeyed; if not, then that they are no Lawe? His ſeconde poynte whereby hee woulde make vs odious, is, that wee thinke

the Prince maye bee Subiect to Excommunication, that is, that hee is a Brother. Deutr. 17. 15. Math. 18. 15. that hee is not without but within the Churche. 1. Corinth. 5. 12. 13. If this be daungerous, why is it printed and allowed in the famous writinges of Byſhope Iewell: in that the Prieſt doth his
                  Def. apol. part 6. Page. 720. 
                  office, when hee excommunicateth and cutteth off a deade member from the body: ſo farre foorth the Prince, bee hee neuer ſo mighty is inferiour to him: yea, not onely to a Byſhoppe, but to a ſimple Prieſt? Why is it ſuffered which Maſter Nowell hathTom. 2. fol. 53. written: The Prince ought patiently to abyde Excommunication at the Byſhoppes handes? Why are not the examples ofEuſeb. lib. 6. Cap. 14. Theod. 5, 18. worthy Emperours raſed out of the Hyſtories, ſeeing they haue beene ſubiect to this cenſure? Why did the reuerend Father, B. of L. reckon vp ſuch examples not long ſince at Paules Croſſe? The next cauill is not worth the aunſwere: for they of Fraunce may call whomſoeuer they thinke good, to giue them light in any Queſtion, and therefore much more profeſſours of
                  
                  Diuinity. So is the next, for both they and Bullinger, may make teaching generally incident to the Paſtors office, for ſo it is common both to Paſtour and Doctor; yet to apply his ſpeciall gift and labour that way, maye bee proper to the teacher or Doctor, as is prooued in the treatize of that poynte before. The Booke of Bertram I haue not, neyther is it materiall if hee differ from trueth in ſome poynt, thorough humane infirmity: For they them ſelues ſay, they condemne the errour of thoſe, who ſaye that Children are damned,D. Whit. b. ſ. pag, 52 which dye without Baptiſme as much as wee, and yet is it written of their ſide, that wante of Baptiſme is a probable ſign of reprobation: Whē as we ſay it is no ſign at al of reiectiō. This opponing of y• Admonition and Bertram, and ye Church of France, is ridiculous. For thogh they ſay that Miniſters, Elders, and Deacons, are for Church diſcipline (whereby diſcipline they mean ye order of ye ChurchPage. 7. 8. generally) yet in the gouernment of the Preſbytery they ioyne onely the Elders with the Miniſters, and to the Deacons

they giue nothing, but the care for the poore and to giue aduiſe as the French Churches ſay, is not onely graunted to Deacons, but vnto all, as 
                     •
                  u
                     •
                  re occaſion ſhall ſerue. Concerning the difference of widowes, T. C. ſaith. Where the conditions fall out, which are ſet downe in 1. Tim. 
                     •
                  . there they ought according to that rule to be eſtabliſhed. Wherin he agreeth with Daneus: and the booke of Diſcipline doth not deny but that where there are ſuch women and cauſes, they maye, and ought to bee ſo founde of the Church, and are to ſerue the Church, in ſuch ſeruice as they ſhall put them to, onelye he findeth no one peculier and proper ſeruice wherevnto they are tyed, but are to bee imployed by the Deacons, vnder whom they are contayned, and in all this there is no difference worth the ſpeaking of, much leſſe contradiction. In the next, ye queſtion is only of a circumſtance how long they ſhold continue: wherein if Berna differ ſomewhat from vs, what is that vnto the matter in hand? what hurt to the ſubſtaunce of the cauſe? The next obiection

doth aunſwere it ſelfe, that as they vſed them then in ſome reſpects, as the Deacon, to Catechiſe, and ſuch like, which they thought the ſtraightes of the Church draue them vnto: 
                     •
                  o otherwiſe for their office we do ſee they do in their confeſſion acknowledge, That the church muſt he gouerned with the policie, which
                  Harm. confeſ. Gal. confeſ. page. 53 art. 30 La confirmation de La Diſcipline eccleſiaſtique obſeruee, es egliſes reformees du Royaulme du Fraunce page. 7. 
                  Chriſt hath ordayned: &amp; that the offices of elders, and Deacons are part of that policie. Alſo yt it is a part of his Gospel, &amp; is confirmed to (be perpetuall to haue ſuch a gouerment) in their publike writing to y• ende. As fond is the next out of Daneus, which declareth, that although the Churches after the Apoſtles, choſe the Elders and Deacons to be perpetuall: yet it alſo ſayeth there is no ſuch thing defined of in the Scriptures, which proueth, that it is a circumſtaunce which may be altered according to the eſtate of the Church. In the next he quoteth Bucer as repugnaunt to T. C. but nameth no place where we ſhall finde it. Daneus doth not contrarie him, but acknowledging it the order of God, doth onely ſhew what was done in ſmal churches,

adioyned to the great and populous, there beeing ſufficient perſons in the one, which were not at the firſt in the other, notwithſtanding the Apoſtles ordayned it Church by Church Actes 14. And euery Church muſte haue them to ſend for, Jam. 5. and the cauſes of themNeh. 8. 1. Theſ. 5. Rom. 12. which are to be aſſiſtaunt to the Paſtor, to adminiſter the eccleſiaſtical cenſures, to watch ouer the people and admoniſhe them, are a like euery where. Now if the Churches be too little, the bodyes of ſeuerall congregations ought ſo to be ordred,Rom. 12. 5. 6 7. 1, Co. 12. Eſay. 62. 8. as they may haue all the members which Chriſt hath ſet, for the perfection and beauty af his body: vpon all the wals of Hieruſalem there muſt be watch-men, and vpon Euery habitation of mount Syon,
                  Eſay. 4. 5. 6. 
                  vppon her meetinges and Congregations, there muſt be this preſence of God, as a cloude by day, and a fire by night: For looke what places they can bring for the perpetuity, and for the right of euerye Church for a Paſtour: The ſame or lyke may be brought for the Elder. Whereof it commeth▪ that Ignatius ſayde, as he is alleadged before, No
                  
                  Church can ſtande without her Elderſhip. And Iuſtinus made his apologie, wherein this Elderſhip is mentioned for all Churches. Wherefore, whatſoeuer Daneus graunt was done for a tyme, till the Churches might conuenientlye bee brought to a conuenient ſtature, neither beeing too high nor too ſhort, and to be beautifull bodyes, neyther wanting a member, nor hauing one too much, that muſte not preiudice the inſtitution of Chriſt: which Daneus confeſſeth, When
                  Part. 2. Iſag. lib. 2. c. 10. page. 191. 192. 
                  he ſayth they muſt looke to the Church, houſe by houſe, and publikely alſo, to the whole and to the ſicke. Of two Conſiſtories in a city it may be he hath reade of, but in one particular Church, of two Eccleſiaſticall Senates, I will then beleeue it, when he bringeth vs a more certaine direction, then yet hee hath done to finde it: and if they did, ſeeing the inconueniences (as he ſayeth) bring it to the right order: what preiudiſe is that to the trueth? In the next poynt of counſels, there is no contrarietie betweene the admonition, and the French Churches order: For they
                  
                  ſay they may definitiuely define cauſes in a prouintiall Synode, (although I can not find thoſe wordes by his quotation): And the admonition ſaythe ſo, except there be a generall counſell, and they will haue it there. For there is no reaſon if they will order it fitly at hoam, to carry it to a generall counſell. And I pray are theſe two ſo contrary? They may ende it, and they may ende it, except they thinke it better to referre it to a generall counſel. In paſſing from this difference to the next, he ſetteth peremptorilie, that it is manyfeſt, that there is no certayne forme of electing Eccleſiaſticall officers vſed by the Apoſtles, but reaſon he ſheweth none whereby it maye appeare: So that if his Doctorſhip ſaye it, we muſte take it from him as vndoubtedly, as if he had it by reuelation. For confutation of which folly, we may ſay thus much: That ſeeing in the Miniſters, examination is to be had, of knowledge, of doctrine, of ripe neſſe to expound the Scriptures, and in a worde of aptnes to teach; it is manyfeſt, that as the gouerning of this action belongeth to the Elderſhip, and is to be

done with publike prayers, that beſidesActes. 14. the gouerning Elders there muſt be miniſters, who maye be able throughly to iudge and examine, to conceiue publike prayer, and to deliuer to the Church by doctrine, exhortation, whatſoeuer is expedient in this caſe. Which thing is euident, not onely by the perpetuall reaſon of it, but alſo by the conſtant and vnchaungeable practiſe of the Apoſtles, in the firſt of the Actes, in the ſixth of the Acts, in the 14. in the 1. Tim. 3. of Tit. 1. Onely it is to be noted, that it is not committed to one, no not ſo much as to1. Tim. 4. ordayne, much leſſe to elect, but the ordination is by the Elderſhip. And Timothy could not carry the matter away, but had a charge for his owne part, To keepe him-ſelfe pure, and not to communicate
                  1. Tim. 5. 
                  with other mens ſinnes whatſoeuer other Elders did in this caſe. Now, as this order is certayne and vnuariable, both in the reaſon and practiſe of it: ſo the circumſtaunces, whether it ſhall be by 6. or by 7. Miniſters: by a conference only, or by a ſynode (ſauing where it may be, the more the better) is left to the diſpoſition

of the church. Wherefore it is not only without reaſon, but alſo ſence, &amp; contrary to his profeſſed knowledge, to proclayme warre amongſt the Churches for this matter of circumſtaunce, when they all haue the ſubſtaunce, agreed vppon in Gods worde, and doe not tye them-ſelues or others to the particuler circumſtaunces. It is alſo as abſurde, that he ſetteth downe as a contrarietie to the election of the Elders and people, that they allowed the Officers choſen by the Conſiſtorye, or by voyces of the people, or by one Miniſter, as thogh that were derogatory to a right order, to ratifie that by good authority, which was at the firſt imperfectly donne. Yet that is moſt abſurde which he doth obtect againſte the authour of the Abſtract, as though he were contrarye toPage. 211. this order, becauſe he woulde haue the people giue their conſent, ſeeing as hath beene ſhewed theſe may not only agree, but ought vnſeperably to be ioyned togeather in Church-lections. For if eyther by ſilence, or otherwyſe they ſignifie their conſent, and the election be

not made, but ſufficient deliberation be giuen them to ſhew iuſt cauſes of theirPage. 212. diſlyke, or gladly to accept them: It is all one, as hath beene prooued in the treatiſe to that purpoſe. In the next obiection he muſt firſt prooue, that we diſſent before he haue an anſwere for to haue it done by the Conſiſtorye, and to adioyne a conference are not contrary. The next is anſwered in the treatiſe of the election of Church-officers. The next is an vntruth. For the confirmation De la diſ. Eccleſ. ſheweth, that the people giue their conſent and approbation, according to the 14. of the Actes. Page. 233. The next we take but for a poore cauil, grounded (vnleſſe hee make it appeare which he ſpeaketh of ſome which hold it lawfull to picke a quarrel and leaue the miniſtery) vpon a ſlaunder. In deed if at one mans pleaſure for truthes ſake, they be put out, to ſeeke an honeſt way to lyue is not vnlawfull, nor contrarye to the decree of the French Churches, that they be choſen to be Ministers their whole life, vnleſſe they be diſcharged lawfully, vnto which decree all agree. The next of

depoſitions receiueth the ſame anſwere which the elections doe: for the authority which electeth, muſt be that which depoſeth, and the Diſcipline of Fraunce meaneth no otherwiſe: And of Excommunication, ther is the like iudgement. The Author of the Abſtract can beſt expound his meaning, and his words bear no ſuch collection as hee gathereth. For in ſaying the Miniſter may do it, and that by Lawe in his charge, aſwell as the Byſhop in his Dioceſſe: He doth not authorize the Byſhoppe to doe it alone, but with due conſent to whome it doth appertaine. In the nexte, when hee ſheweth who that ſome bee, which make deciſion of controuerſies incident to euery Preſbytery, otherwiſe then if they can with contentation agree of the trueth amongſt themſelues: we will giue his aunſwere to it: In the meane time we iudge of it as of the reſt: that it is, vntrue. The like of the two other (excepting Brown, for whome he hath his aunſwere) and of the next about God-fathers. Concerning the next poynt, the which he ſayth of the Churches of Fraunce, that they think it

lawfull to baptize without an aſſembly: I can not beleeue it, vnleſſe I haue better direction then the 7. article of their Diſcipline, in which I can finde no ſuch thing, though I finde ſome other articles there, which he hath aledged thence: wherefore I feare that it is a fiction. Concerning Holy-dayes, let him firſte ſhew, that the Churches obſerue them in maner of a Sabboth, wholly to reſt from their labour, and then T. C. with his reaſons, or the churches with theirs, muſt giue place to the truth. The diuerſity about popiſh Prieſtes is aunſwered before in the tretiſe of that matter. The next are but ſlaunders, to which he gyueth no credite by anye teſtimonye, and are confuted before in the treatiſe of the Doctor. It is alſo a manifeſt vntruth, that T. C. miſlyketh wholly That anye are ſuffered to preach nor hauing a Paſtorall charge. For he ſpeaketh generally of ſuch as haue no charge, neither Paſtorall, nor Doctorall. For he would haue both tyed to a certayne place, yea the Elders Preaching in other mens cures or charges, wherevnto men are not lawfully

called, wee condemne according to the iudgement of the French Churches neither doth he note any wher we might finde the contrarie. In ordaining of ceremonies, the admonition meaneth no otherwiſe than the Frenche Churches: for though the Elderſhippe abolliſhe thoſe which are vnprofitable, yet it may be don with conſent &amp; alowance of other Churches; for which cauſe hee entreateth of conferences page. 30. 31. &amp;c. That hee ſaith of the admonition, as though they miſliked a preſcript forme of prayer, is an vtter vntruth, for there are not anye wordes which ſhewe they miſlike a preſcript forme of prayers. As for vnleauened bread, it is but proper to Geneua onely, &amp; now our Church hath alowed the other: why ſhould he then make any difference or ſtrife about it? The matters of mariage or ſuch like heere named, as they are handled with vs are ciuil; but as they become doubtfull in any queſtion of God his worde, or what is expedient for the Church to doe, for auoyding of offence, belongeth vnto the Eccleſiaſticall ſeigniorie: and ſo that difference

is aunſweared. In the other alſo it is defended, as vnlawfull for a Miniſter of the Worde, to be occupied in Ciuill affayres. Againſte this, he in vaine bringeth an exception in Elders, which rule onely. Neither is it ſimplye a Ciuill thing to giue teſtimonies in writinges for to doe it, for matters Eccleſiaſticall: as for ſoundneſſe of fayth, for aſſuring them to be receiued which were excommunicate, or ſuch like, it is an Eccleſiaſtical, not a Ciuill action. Touching the order of the French Church, for publiſhing of Bookes, we conſent, that where the Diſcipline is eſtabliſhed and an order taken, that men with modeſly in a Synode may be ſufficiently heard, and ſatiſfied, that it ought to be in force, and as an Eecleſiaſticall order obeyed; from which yet a man may ſwarue, being dryuen to gyue defence to the truth of God. The next ſetteth his conceits in the laughter of all men. For maye we not miſlyke, that he which ordayneth, ſhoulde bydde the ordayned, receaue the holye Ghoſte, which he can

not gyue, nor hath promiſe that his impoſition of handes ſhall diſtribute auye gifts, and yet alow that that place for inſtruction be repeated and intreaſed of? Concerning his long ſrory of ſubſcription, this may be ſufficient ſhortly to aunſwere, both to ſhew our 
                     •
                  uitye in iudgement with the Churches, and alſo to ſatiſfie the Church of England. Firſt therefore we ſay, that we haue alwayes beene readye, according to our dutye to ſubſcribe to her Maieſties ſupreame authority, and to the Articles of religion, concerning the doctrine of fayth and of the Sacramentes, which is all that is requyred by law. Secondly, when (as it is in Fraunce) the ſubſtaunce of Diſcipline ſhall be out of the worde confirmed, and the controuerſies betweene vs equally and orderly decided: We will alſo be bounde to ſubſcribe as they are. His firſt quotation out of the Adm. doth ſet down that in a different letter, which is not there to be found. Which practize is done onely to diſgrace vs vniuſ
                     •
                  
                  ly with the Magiſtrate. The other two ſentences, though we iudge them

ſomewhat hardly ſet downe, yet they muſt be charitably interpreted, according to the courſe of their Booke; the firſt of the trueth of Diſcipline, not of doctrine, the other of Miniſters, ſo called and inabled as God his worde doth allowe. The reſt is worth no aunſwere, the matter beeing handled before, andOn the Act. 1. &amp; 6 Gualter being a party with you againſt M. Iewell and M. Nowel in that point, though againſte you in the queſtion of Church election. Now, in ſtead of this heape of diſagreementes which are at one with them ſelues, let him accorde theſe following, drawne from the wrytersD. Whitg. ſ. booke. Page. 146. who are of his iudgement. No man for any crime is to be ſecluded from any law fall vocation, if he repent him and become a new man, and there be no generall commaundements contrary herevnto: But this doctrine is conſonant to the whole courſe of the Goſpell, Yet we all hold that Traytours are not to be admitted Byſhops, or of the Queenes Guarde. They maintain this ſpeach of Ambroſe
                  Ibid. page 191. on the 4. of the Epheſ. In the beginning it was permitted to euery one to preach the
                  
                  Goſpel, baptize and expound the Scriptures; but when the Churche was enlarged, certain Pariſhioners were appoynted, and goucrnors, and other officers ordayned in the Church. Yet now Miniſters maye not preach without a liſence. It is defended by the former Booke, that The worde of God is as effectuall when it is read, as when it is preached, and reading is preaching, yet the Booke of Common-prayer preferreth Preaching before Homilies. And himſelfe ſayth, that Preaching is the moſt excellent meanes to ingender fayth. This man condemneth and reiecteth Doctours as new, yet the former booke Page 425. ſayth, that by auncient wryters. A Catechiſtes office was neceſſarie in the Church, and diſtinct from the Paſtour. The ſame booke fol. 700. in the marginall note hath, Nothing ought to be reade vnder the name of Scripture but the Canonicall,
                  In the rubrick howe the reſt of holy ſcripture. &amp;c. Iewel apol. p. 2. p. 122. Contrary to the booke of Common prayer which appoynteth the Apocripha to be reade vnder the name of holy ſcripture. Iewel ſaith, that for one biſhop to haue authority ouer an other, is neyther by Chriſt, Peter, nor Paule, nor by any right of
                  
                  God his word. Yet they do by preaching and wryting ſtill maintaine it by the examples of Peter, Timothy, and Titus. In the aunſwere to the authority of Peter Martyr, it is ſayde that in our Church
                     D. whit. in the end. 
                     religion is onely reformed to the quicke.
                   But the examiner ſayth, they ſee weightyer things in the Church, wherat they may
                  Page. 35. 
                  be greeued as other good men are. Now we come to his queſtions, which althoghQueſtions. they he captious, and therefore by lawe they are not to bee aunſweared: yet to ſhewe our ſincerity in that which we holde, we will make him an aunſwere. To the firſt we ſaye, Diſcipline, touching1 the ſubſtaunce, is fully deſcribed out of the worde of God, in the booke of diſcipline, &amp; the treatiſe of eccleſiaſtical gouernment, and in the moſt of the ſoundeſt writers of our time. The ſecond is2 anſwered, partly by the former, &amp; partly by this treatiſe. In ſteed of this we aſke him what be y• writings which haue cō
                  futed by the ſcripture, all thoſe foreſayd godly &amp; learned writings? To the third3 we aunſwere, it is no ſounde diuinity to exclude Chriſtian Princes from their

gouerment in Church-matters. Concerning Excommunication he hath his anſwere before. To the two other clawſes, let the Papiſts anſwere, for they are malitiouſly imputed vnto vs. And we demaund of him, whether it be ſound diuinity, that when the Prince will eate fleſh in Lent or do ſuch like, ſhee muſt haue a Diſpenſation from an Archbyſhop? And that the writes of his Courts euen in cauſes ciuill, and matters of inſtaunce ſhould be in his owne name, and not in the name of her moſt excellēt Maieſty? The fourth is aunſwered in the Treatiſe of the Elderſhip: And we aſke4 of him what pregnant proofe he hath either from ſcripture or Father, that Eccleſiaſticall Gouernment ſhoulde be exerciſed in a wholle Dioceſſe, by a Chancelor or Commiſſarye beeing a meere lay-man? To the 5. and 6. both, wee5. 6. aunſwere: That rebaptization is condemned by the Worde of God, and that thoſe hee ſpeaketh of be maried folkes: And wee require him to prooue by the Worde of God, that in caſe of the neceſſity which they pretend, a Woman

may baptize: And to prooue by the ſame that men may be forbidden to mary in Lent or ſuch like times. The ſeuenth7 is aunſwered in that to the 5. and 6. And we demaunde of him how they can prooue it lawfull to admit a Popiſh prieſt, fallen from the Goſpell and ſtill vnapt to teach? To the eyght we aunſwere,8 there is the like reaſon of the Supper and of Baptiſme: And we require him to prooue by the Worde of God, that a Deacon may baptize? and when he hath proued that, let him proue why hee may not miniſter the Supper alſo? To the ninth we anſwere, that to9 the Miniſters, there may be diuerſity of rewardes giuen, ſo long as none haue to little, nor any too much. And we require him to prooue by the Word of God, that a Miniſter of the Goſpell may carry the pompe of men of eſtate. To the10 tenth we aunſwere, as is ſet downe in the Treatiſe, that a Miniſter ſhould be apt to teach: We would haue him proue that any other may preache, who is not apt to teach. To the Eleuenth we anſwere11 affirmatiuely, and require him to

prooue by the Scriptures, that an Archbyſhop may put Preachers to ſilence, for not ſubſcribing to that which is not required by the lawe. To the twelfth12 we aunſwere: it is not lawfull for one to be thruſt out of his Miniſtery, for ſhewing modeſtly in his ſermons, the inconuenience of vnleauened breade in the Lords Supper: that all vſury as wee ſpeake it, whither biting or nibbling is vnlawfull. And we require of him to prooue by the Worde of God, that it is tollerable to ſuffer Drunkardes, whoremongers, ignoraunt men of occupation in the Miniſtry, and for not ſubſcribing (where Law doth not enforce it) or for the not vſing of ſome ceremonie to turne out godly learned Miniſters. And make a pitifull ſeperation of the Paſtor and the flocke. The Lorde giue vs to be of one minde, and wherein we agree, let vs proceede by the rule of loue.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

