
   
      
         
            A defence of the reasons of the counter-poyson, for maintenance of the eldership against an aunsvvere made to them by Doctor Copequot, in a publike sermon at Pawles Crosse, vpon Psal. 84. 1584. VVherein also according to his demaunde is proued syllogisticallie for the learned, and plainlie for all men, the perpetuitie of the elders office in the church.
         
         
            
               1586
            
         
         Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00639
            STC 10772
            ESTC S112582
            99847829
            99847829
            12891
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00639)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12891)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 224:10)
         
         
            
               
                  A defence of the reasons of the counter-poyson, for maintenance of the eldership against an aunsvvere made to them by Doctor Copequot, in a publike sermon at Pawles Crosse, vpon Psal. 84. 1584. VVherein also according to his demaunde is proued syllogisticallie for the learned, and plainlie for all men, the perpetuitie of the elders office in the church.
                  Fenner, Dudley, 1558?-1587, attributed name.
                  Stoughton, William, fl. 1584, attributed name.
                  Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624, attributed name.
               
               [32] p.   
               
                  Printed by R. Schilders],
                  [Middelburg :
                  1586.
               
               
                  Variously attributed to Dudley Fenner and to William Stoughton; sometimes also attributed to Henry Jacob. In the preface (A2 verso) the author speaks of himself as distinct from the author of the, likewise anonymous, book which it supports ("A counter-poyson, modestly written for the time, to make aunswere to the objections and reproches, wherewith the aunswerer to the Abstract, would disgrace the holy discipline of Christ" (STC 10770)), which is also variously attributed to Fenner, Stoughton and Jacob.
                  Place of publication and printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-B.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Copcot, John, d. 1590.
               Church of England --  Government --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-10
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-05
            Taryn HakalaSampled and proofread
         
            2006-05
            Taryn HakalaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A DEFENCE OF THE REAſons of the Counter-poyſon, for maintenance of the Eldership, againſt an aunſvvere made to them by Doctor Copequot, in a publike Sermon at Pawles Croſſe, vpon Pſal. 84. 1584.
            VVherein alſo according to his demaunde is proued Syllogiſticallie for the learned, and plainlie for all men, the perpetuitie of the Elders office in the Church.
            1586.
         
         
            
            
            To the Chriſtian Reader.
            
               I Muſt (gentle &amp; Chriſtian Reader) declare two things for iuſtifying of this treatiſe following. Firſte, why it came not out before, then why it commeth out nowe. Before, the trueth is, the author of the Counterpoyſon neuer coulde gette the anſweres in writing as nowe I haue got them. He ſawe notes of them taken by a Doctor of the ciuill Lawe, which (as he then ſaide) made him rather thinke howe to contemne them, then to anſwere them. So this was the cauſe the author let it alone. Since that time I my ſelfe haue fallen vppon the whole Sermon in writing: ſo that it ſeemeth it goeth from hande to hande amongſt thoſe who delight in it. It may be ſome perceyue not the weakenes of

the anſweares. It may be, ſome beleeue the ſlaunders and lies made in it, both againſt the cauſe and the perſons. Wherefore to ſhewe the trueth of the cauſe and her ſtrengthe againſt all her enimies newe or olde, continued or relapſed, to cleare the trueth from olde &amp; newe ſlaunderers, I haue made the Defence following. The Author of the Coū
                  ter-poyſon I am ſure will take it in good part. This Defence the Author of the Aunſwere may confute if he can. Thou mayeſt iudge of both, as Euidence of Reaſon ſhall leade thee. The Lord graūt vs firſt to vnderſtande his wil, then to practiſe it.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶That part of his ſermon which concerned Diſcipline.
            BVT what is ſaide of the Church of Englande? Truely that it is no Church but after a ſorte: and why? Becauſe it lacked Diſcipline, for ſo ſay the Papiſtes, that it is not the true Church, but ſecundum quid, after a manner. But what of this? This is but a ſlaunder giuen to the church by them, as a citie can not ſtande without Walles, no more can a Church without Diſcipline, yet ſayeth the holy Father Maiſter Gualter, writing vpon the Epiſtle to the Corinthians: For lacke of Diſcipline, no man ought to depart from the Church. The ſame Father writing vppon the Epiſtle vnto the Galatians, whiche is applied to Iames King of Sicile, Ego, ſi quis Diſciplinae formam interrogat, in omnibus gentibus eandem conſtitui non poſſe exiſtimo. I doo thinke that if any man doo aske of the forme of diſcipline, that the ſame cannot be appointed in all Countries and Nations through the worlde. In a Catechiſme printed here at London not long agoe, the Scottes Catechiſme, the queſtion is asked, What may the Elderſhip doe in the Church? The anſwere is made againe, Admitte vnto the Sacramentes, and exclude from them according to God his worde. Nowe as concerning Prieſtes, it is ſaide that they are worthie of great prayſe, which doo their office

iuſtlie. And Saint Paule ſaith in his 5. Chap. 1. Timoth, The Elders that rule well, were worthie of double honour, eſpecially they which labour in the worde and doctrine, we ſay the place is vnderſtoode of the Preachers of the worde. Peter Verides and Nicholas Emingius in the 133. pa. of their booke ſay, That ſuch Preiſtes are worthie of double honor. There is one noted, that when he was about the ſame matter and buſines that there is ſpokē of, he affirmeth the Teſtament of Reames neuer came into his hands, and in deed I dare be bolde to ſay, it did not, for he inteprreteth the place, that they Which labor are worthie of double honour: but he did not ſpeak of any Miniſters, ſaue only thē which preached the worde ſincerilie. Therefore he ſpeaketh and maketh difference betweene Preacher &amp; Preacher. I ſay not by the authoritie of the Teſtament of Reames, but by the authoritie of holy Fathers or Prophetes, which the Apoſtles doe note. S. Auguſtine he asketh the queſtion, Qui non bene p
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ſunt? but they, which do not labor in their calling Chriſoſtome ſaith, Bonus paſtor vitam ponit pro ouibus: A good Paſtor will lay downe his life for his ſheepe. And againe ſaith Ciprian, Boni &amp; fideles diſpenſatores, duplici honore digni ſunt. S Ambroſe ſayth, Praesbiteri, &amp; qui bene praeſunt vita &amp; doctrina, duplicem moerentur honorem à ſubiectis quibus praeſunt: Presbiters, and they that doe gouuerne well, bothe in life and doctrine, doe deſerue double honour of thoſe ſubihctes, whome they rule: ſo that here we may ſee, he doth vnderſtande the places of the preachers of the worde of God. But they ſay, if we ſhould ſo expound it, we ſhould make the Apoſtle to goe backwarde and not forwarde. Surelie, nothing leſſe: for this is the ſence, that they which labour, are worthie of double honour: they which do not, are worthy of none. So that here we may ſee that the interpreter doth not

expound this place after the Church of Rome or of Reams
               ▪ but S. Ambroſe, Chriſoſtome and Auguſtin. Here we ſee that the Apoſtle doth ſeeme to make twoo kindes of miinſters: The one which were occupied in the word, but not wel: &amp; why ſhould that ſeme ſtraūge to make two kindes of preachers or miniſters? For my part I wiſhe with all my harte that al that are placed in Englande, were better then my ſelf, and that it were ſo through all Nations where the worde of God is preached, and I pray to God, that the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſte were preached throughout the whole world. The Apoſtle ſayth, that in his time there were many which laboured not ſo much as he. I thanke God (ſaith the Apoſtle) I laboured better then they all, yet they deſerued honor: but not ſo much as he, becauſe they laboured not ſo much as he, for God hath not giuen to euery one the ſelf ſame gifte. Furthermore they define this worde (labour) is ſpoken to all, as well that are able to doo moſt, as thoſe that are able to doe leaſt: Therefore the Apoſtle writinge to the Theſſ. calleth them labourers, although there were ſome which were wicked amongeſt them. Furthermore, they adde this diſtinction is diſſolute, and cleane voyde of true diſcipline, if they bee but Miniſters, and take not ſo great paynes, yet they are worthie of honour, though not ſo great as the reſt, but of the honour of Widowes, and he ſpeaketh of honour of Widowes in Chap. 5. ver 1, 2. Honor the elder women as mothers, the yonger as ſiſters. Honor Widowes whiche are widowes indeed. The Apoſtle ſaith, Rom. 12.6.7. Seing then that when we haue gifte, &amp;c. And agayne in Epiſt. 1. Cor. Cap. 12.28. God hath ordeined ſome in Churches, as firſte▪ &amp;c. Therfore they ſay, there muſt be presbiteries in the Churche: but I doo not

allowe of this their argument, as they had Elders in the Church then, ſo it muſt be nowe. For the learned Father M. Gualter ſayth, That there are certaine which would erect a presbiterie, they muſt proue they haue the ſame giftes as the presbiterie had then, Propheſie, working of miracles, and other giftes written in 1. Cor. Cha. 12. They that do theſe things are thought to trouble the order of the Church of God, and to bring in contention, the ciuill Magiſtrates went to get vnto them ſelues eccleſiaſticall authoritie, but this turned into popiſhe tyrannie. There was a little booke printed in the yeare of our Lord 1558. that is called The admonition of Englande and Scotlande, you ſhall finde as much there. And if it do
                  •
                pleaſe you agayne to looke into the concluſions of that booke, ye ſhall finde that there is one whiche doeth conclude heauier againſt Englande, then doeth Doctor Sanders.
            
         
         
            
            The defence.
            THE vvhole vvhich he ſpeaketh of Diſcipline, conſiſteth in two pointes, The one againſt vs: the other, A defence of him ſelfe. Where the one is not ſo falſe and friuoulouſe, but the other is as vayne and feeble. To begin, lett vs ſee howe he maketh vs charge the Church: then his Defence he maketh for it. Hee layeth to our charge, that we make the Church of Englande but a church ſecundum quid, after a ſorte.
            Where that he ſlaundereth vs in ſaying we ſlaū
               der the Church: we proue it by double witnes, on our part our wordes and deedes: on his part, by his owne allegation in this place. For our wordes, our preaching and writings haue alwayes witneſ
                  •
               ed, that we holde the Churche for a true Churche of Chriſt, from which no member may ſeparate him ſelfe: although he muſt diſallowe the wantes in her. We haue alwayes when ſubſcription was vrged, bin readie to ſubſcribe to the Article of her Maieſties authoritie, and to the ſubſtance of doctrine, in as large a manner as the Statut in that behalfe required. This wee haue declared by proteſtation and by writing, not onely to them, but to the moſt honourable Senate of her moſt Excellent Maieſties priuie Counſell. Wee haue by writinge defended the cauſe of the Church and our Prince, as much as they, that we ſay no more. From our actions howe many Demonſtrations might bee broght to approue our right judgement, reuerend account, and ſincere affection toward the Church of Englande▪
            
            
               Haue we not (yea when we were vniuſtly againſt all law of God and man, depriued for not ſubſcribing) adioyned our ſelues to the Church in all the actions of the miniſterie of the word preached, of prayer, &amp; of the Sacraments? Haue we not by perſwaſions continued many in the boſome of the church? yea whē through weaknes, becauſe of many abuſes they would haue departed. Haue wee ſought redreſſe by any other meanes thē by hūble ſupplication towards our ſuperiours according to dutie? Thus our actions approue vs to the church. His accuſation hath bin heard, let vs heare alſo his witnes: which as we ſaid, ouerthroweth his accuſation. He maketh vs to ſay, that as a citie can not ſtande without walles, no more cā a church without Diſcipline. We replie, there was neuer any that denied a citie with out a wall, to be a citie, an orched without defēce, to be an orchard, a cornefielde without a hedge to be a cornefielde. Neither will any manne forſake his citie, caſt away his corne, deſtroy his vineyard, for lacke of a defence.
                  Pſal. 80.14 Nehe. 1. Neuertheleſſe the wante of theſe things muſt be cōplained of in time. Behold how his own witnes ſpeaketh for vs. We haue ſeen how he faineth vs to charge the church, mark how wel he defendeth her. What maner of defence doth he make? not with the Word, but with 2. ſentences of M. Gualter. Is M. Gualter a more holy, learned, &amp; ancient Father then Peter Martir, Viret, Caluin, Beza, Bullinger, and ſuch other, Who by preaching, writing, &amp; other good meanes, haue mainteined this cauſe? We acknoledge Gualter to be a ſhining ſtarr: but we make not his glorie like vnto the glorie of God in all thoſe men. Howbeit let the ſtrength of his light ſhine out, and it ſhall not hurt vs, but melt away his aſſertion as waxe, and the Biſhops authoritie which he maintaineth as pitche. For want of Diſcipline (ſaith he in the firſt place) no man ought

to departe from the Churche: we confeſſe it, allowe it, ſubſcribe vnto it. What is the ſecōd voyce? I thinke that the ſame forme can not be appointed in all nations. Lo it is a thought, no demonſtration. Wil you allow his iudgement in this M. Copquot? Dare you doo it? Shall ſweete and ſower come out of your mouth in one ſermon? Haue you not twiſe or thriſe in this ſermon made Diſcipline a note of the Churche, in theſe wordes: The notes of the Church are three, the firſt. The word of God truly preached. The ſecond, The right adminiſtraetion of the Sacraments. The laſt, True Diſcipline. And hauing alleadged Mat. 28.18.19. you ſay, By whiche place of Scripture, we may eaſilie perceiue, that theſe are the true tokens of the Church, where the worde is preached, The Sacramentes truly ministred, and where is true Diſcipline. Now, if Diſcipline be one note of the Church, ſhal it not be the ſame in all places as touching the ſubſtance, as is the doctrine? Shall there not be a certaine forme of it, as S. Paule ſaith,2. Tim. 1. there is of the doctrine, your firſt marke? Againe, how wil theſe wordes of Matthew, Goe teache all nations, baptiſinge them that beleeue, and teache them to obſerue all thinges, which I haue commaunded you, proue your Diuiſions? Is it not becauſe all men muſt not onely be taught and beleeue the doctrine, as the firſt and principal marke, nor onely be baptized and vſe the Sacraments, which is the ſecōd, but alſo muſt be taught to obſerue all conſtitutions, for elections, abdications, for the eſſentiall difference of offices for the cenſures and ſpirituall corrections, which you call true Diſcipline, the thirde marke? Howe then, is not this commanded Diſcipline certaine in nature and forme? And is it not cōmanded to al that beleeue and are baptized? What thē, ſhall M. Gualters ſentence ſtand, &amp; yours fall? After you haue ſeene this diſagrement of M. Gualter, with him ſelfe, beholde how he diſagreeth in this ſentence with the Biſhops and orders which you maintaine. In his cōmentarie on the 1. Cor. 5

where he hath the verie wordes you alledge: hee ſaieth, That the Miniſters haue no Diſcipline further then rebukes by worde: That there muſt be no Eccleſiaſticall ſuſpenſion from the Sacraments: No excommunication: Finallie, there muſt be no Diſcipline but ciuill, at the appointement af the Magiſtrate, and that by ciuill perſons. Will the Biſhops allowe this, that by the worde of God Eccleſiaſticall Gouuernours haue no authoritie to ſuſpende, to excommunicate? Will our lawes, will the Articles of the Conuocation houſe, will the booke of ordayning Biſhops, Prieſtes and Deacons ſtand with this? Thus Gualters breathe poyſoneth and choketh the Biſhops ſweete and pure Gouuernement. Thus farre his accuſation. His anſwere to our reaſons followe. Where firſte I pray the Reader to conſider well the queſtion betweene vs: which is one theſe worde of S. Paule in 1. Tim. 5. The Elders which rule well, are worthy of double honour, eſpecially thoſe which labour in the worde and doctrine. We ſay, this place mētioneth two ſortes of Elders, one which doo onely gouerne in the Church: the other which alſo are occupied in the miniſterie of the worde. He denieth this, and ſayeth it mentioneth onely two ſortes of Preachers, ſome whiche preach well, and ſome which take greater paynes in it then others. Thou ſeeſt the queſtion betweene vs (good Reader) wherein thou mayeſt thanke Maiſter Copquot (as we alſo doo) for making his meaning playne without any feare. For it argueth a good courage, openly at Pawles croſſe to iuſtle out the Arch-biſhops interpretation, to bring in his owne.
                  Doctor Whitgift pag. 626. The Arch-biſhop vnderſtandeth it of two ſortes of Miniſters: ſome that are Miniſters but preache not: ſome that preache and labour in the worde and doctrine. Well did Maiſter Copquot conſider that it was farre from the

true meaning of the Apoſtle, which neuer would account an ignorant Miniſter, vnſauerie ſalte, a blinde watchman, a dumme Dogge, and an Idoll ſhepheard, worthie either of double honor, or the name to rule well. Well alſo did he conſider that it was a ſmall piece of gouernement, to reade a fewe prayers or part of the Liturgie, and to doo all as he is preſcribed. Vppon good reaſon he left that corrupt meaning, I would he had as eaſilie receyued the full and proper meaning of the holy Ghoſt. But let vs come to the matter in hande: Hee thinketh him ſelfe iniuried that he is charged to haue learned his aunſwere of the Ieſuites, which he had (he ſaith) from holy Fathers and Prophetes. If you bringe the interpretatiō of the Prophetes for you, we will put our hande to our mouth and giue glorie to the trueth and to you, although we muſt ſtill acknowledge that we redde it in the Ieſuites papers, before we heard it out of your mouth. But how is it that we heare a ſounde of Prophetes, but finde the ſentences onely of Fathers? Lette vs examine them notwithſtanding, to ſee if they diſcharge you from being the Ieſuites ſcholler. The ſentences which are alledged, make nothing for you, ſome are expreſlie againſt you. The firſt 2. are made to ſay, Such Prieſtes are worthie of double honour as do rule well, admit they ſay it: but do they ſaye this place maketh two ſortes of Preachers, whiche is the queſtion? Haue you no other Fathers then theſe firſte? Yes, Auguſtin, Ciprian, Ambroſe, Chriſoſtome, theſe are worth the hearing, let them ſpeak. S. Auguſtin ſaith, They onely non bene praeſunt, whiche doo not labour in their calling. Ergo, the place of the Apoſtle is to be vnderſtoode of Preachers only not of gouerning Elders. I am not worthy for learning to beare Doctor Copquot bookes: yet I

know the man whom he now ſeeketh to confute, would laugh at ſuche a reaſon. For all that I will vouchſafe an anſwere. Auguſtine in giuing no more for the interpretation of theſe wordes, whiche rule well, then that they do it which labour in their calling, doth applie it no more to Preachers onely, then to Deacons, Kinges, yea Shipmaiſters, who all muſt labour well in their calling. Nay, by vſing ſo generall wordes in interpreting the firſt part of the verſe, he manifeſtlie declareth, that hee vnderſtood it was general to both ſorte of Elders, both teaching and vnteaching, and ſo he might applie it to which ſoeuer ſorte of Elders he had occaſion to ſpeake of. The ſame anſwere may ſerue the words which he ſayeth are Ciprians, who yet can not bee founde either ſo much as to alledge that place, much leſſe fully to interprete it. And if he thinke that Ciprian was ſuch an enemie of vnteaching Elders, let him reade againe his Epiſtles, and he ſhall finde almoſt in euery Epiſtle, that hee is a great friende vnto them. He will ſay peraduenture, thoſe Elders were preachers: we anſwer, it is not credible that in one Church there could be ſo many as hee there nameth and paynteth out, eſpecially in the time of perſecution. But to put the matter out of doubt, his owne wordes are alledged, where hee ſaith,
                  Cyprian lib. 3. Epist. 22 
               He with the Elders, Teachers, and Readers, gaue the degree of a Teacher vnto Optatus: Or if you will haue the reading as it is newly caſt in a popiſh moulde, Quando cum praesbiteris doctioribus, lectores diligenter probauerimus, Optatum inter lectores doctorem audientium conſtituimus, when with the lharneder Elders wee diligentlie tried the Readers, wee made Optatus amongſt the Readers a Teacher of thoſe who heare, it ſhall make yet more againſt you: becauſe here Elders are not onely diſtinguiſhed from Ciprian the Biſhop of that particular church
                  •
                as from the Paſtor, &amp; frō
               
the teachers and readers, but alſo from ſome other vnlearned Elders, who although for gouernement they were apt men: yet were not ſo learned as eyther they were fitt to reade in the Church, or iudge of thoſe who could reade and pronounce wordes and ſentences according to their iuſt meaſure, and proper grace. We haue ſifted Ciprian, let vs looke in to Chriſoſtome: He is made to ſay, A good Paſtor layeth dewns his life for his ſheepe. He doeth ſo ſaye, but the 
                  Num. 27 Actes 20name of ſhepheard both in holy and prophane write, is cōmon to gouernours, both ciuill and eccleſiaſticall, as well as to Teachers. Further, if one do wel marke the courſe of Chriſoſtomes cōmentarie in that place, he ſhall finde him againſt you:
                  Poimenes laon in the Poet.
                becauſe when he ſpeaketh of the firſte part of the verſe, he vrgeth no neceſsitie of doctrine: but comming to the ſecond, he ſheweth that thoſe kinde of Elders which are occupied in the worde, are moſt to be honored, becauſe they ſuſteine great labour in teaching. His wordes are: Quid eſt autem bene praeeſſe? audi dicentem Chriſtum: Paſtor bonus animam ponit pro ouibus. Bene igitur praeeſſe, hoc eſt, nulli parcere illorum regiminis gratia: maximè inquit, qui laborant, in verbo &amp; doctrina: vbi modo ſunt qui dicunt ſermone &amp; doctrsna non opus eſt: &amp; hos omnium maximè iubet honorari, cauſamque addit, dicens: Nullum enim laborē ſuſtinent: that is, What is it to rule well? heare Chriſt ſpeaking or telling it: A good ſhephearde layeth downe his lyfe for his ſheepe. Therefore to rule well, is this, to ſpore none, or nothinge, for the ſake of their gouernement: eſpecially (ſayth he) thoſe which labour in the worde and doctrine: where are they nowe which ſaye, there is no neede of the worde and doctrine: and he commandeth that theſe be chieflie honoured, and ſheweth the cauſe, ſaying: becauſe they ſuſteyne much labour. By all whiche is manifeſt, firſt that the firſt part of the verſ. he vnderſtādeth onli of gouernement (for giuing the ful sēſe of it, he maketh it to be to ſpare none in reſpect of their gouernment) &amp; ſo maketh with vs Elders which

gouerne onely: and Elders whiche alſo teache. Secondlie, ſeeing he doeth by the ſeconde parte confute thoſe who ſayde, there is no neede of doctrine: he ſheweth that although ſome are to gouerne onely, yet ſome which muſt haue great honour, muſt teache alſo. Yea, if he had vnderſtoode your ſenſe of this place, he would haue ſaide vpon the firſt part of the verſe: All muſt teache well, therefore there is neede of doctrine in euerie place: this argument could not haue bin left out, and had bin more neceſſarie, if he had ſeene that to be the meaning of the Apoſtle. Laſtlie, in confutinge by this reaſon their negligence, becauſe they muſt labor in the worde, and not with yours, becauſe they muſt labour more then others: he ſheweth your interpretation neuer came in his minde. Thus three of his witneſſes haue done him much more harme then good. What ſayeth the laſt? Ambroſe ſayeth, Presbiters .i. Elders, and thoſe whiche gouuerne well, both in life and doctrine, deſerue double honour, of thoſe who are vnder them. Is this to proue that Ambroſe vnderſtandeth the place of Preachers only: when beſides thoſe which gouerne both in life &amp; doctrine, he ſpeaketh of Elders and Auncientes? If you wil ſay that (and) doeth not here couple diuers thinges, but interpret only, what reaſon haue you to proue it? Seeing he doeth alledge the texte expreſſely as we doo▪ What goeth before, what followeth after to proue it? Nay, in the laſt wordes he would then haue ſaide. They deſerue double honour, of thoſe whom they teache, but becauſe hee woulde make it generall to both, hee ſayeth of thoſe that are vnder them: which may haue relation to both ſortes of Elders. If Ambroſe had miſliked this office, or not counted it perpetual, you had had ſome reaſon to interprete Et (and) by theſe words that is:

But ſeeing he calleth for it and cōplaineth for the decay of it, as we doo: ſeeing he proueth it by the ſame places wee doo: his interpretation hath no coulor to mainteine it ſelf. The firſt is manifeſt by his wordes on 1. Tim. 5. Vnde &amp; Synagoga, &amp; poſtea Eccleſia ſeniores habuit, quorum ſine conſilio nihil agebatur in Eccleſia. Quod qua negligētia abſoleuerit, neſcio, niſi fortè Doctorum deſidia▪ aut magis ſuperbia, dum ſoli volunt aliquid videri: that is, Whence alſo the Synagogue, and after the Church had Elders, without whoſe counſell nothinge was done in the Church: which, by what negligēce it is worne out of vſe, I knowe not, vnleſſe perhaps by the ſlothe of the Teachers, or rather their pride, whileſt they alone will ſeeme to be ſomewhat. The ſecond is manifeſt by his interpretation of the 1. Cor. 12. which we alledge (Hee hath ſet in his Church gouernors) of which wordes his whole interpretation (after he had ſpoken vppon the former wordes of the Teachers) is: Sunt &amp; gubernatores qui ſpiritualibus retinaculis, hominibus documēto ſunt: There are alſo gouernors which with ſpirituall bridles order mē. Where, in ſaying, there are alſo, he ſheweth beſides the teachers, there are alſo rulers: and ſuch as rule with ſpirituall bridles, not with the ciuill ſworde. Thus the Fathers are heauie friendes to this interpretation. It may be notwithſtanding he can ſo confute our reaſon brought againſt his miſinterpretatiō, as we muſt of force yeelde it into his handes. For triall ſake therefore, we come to his anſwere. Wherein obſerue two faultes whiche are generall: then you may the better deale with the particular deceites of his anſwere. The one is, that he cleane paſſeth by one principall reaſon, which is made againſt him, and it is this: If the Apoſtle had ment to haue made two ſortes of Preachers, hee ſhould haue ſaide, They which rule well in worde and doctrine, are worthie of double honor, eſpeciallie thoſe which labor in it, or labor more th
                     •
                  n others: but the Apoſtle hath no wordes nor circumſtance, to make the word &amp;

doctrine cōmon to both. For by what law of interpretation, will you doo it? Will you interprete, Ruling by teaching? gouernement by doctrine? One diuers thing by another? Is that to interprete, or to confounde? An other faulte is, that hee repeateth the fourth reaſon, but maketh no aunſwere at all vnto it. The cauſe peraduenture is, for that it was concluded in a connexiue ſyllogiſme, not a ſimple or 
                  •
               ategoricall. I will therefore doo ſo much for the author (or rather him) as turn it to his liking Thus:

                  What ſoeuer is a common duetie of all Elders that can not be aſsigned by the Apoſtle, as a proper cauſe of an eſpeciall honor in ſome ſorte of good Preachers.
                  But Copiazein to take great paynes in their office, &amp;c. is a common dutie to all Elders, 1. Theſ. 5.12. Heb. 1
                        •
                      17.
                  Ergo, Copiazein to take great paynes, can not be aſsigned of the Apoſtle as a cauſe of eſpeciall honor in ſome ſorte of preachers.
               
We will nowe expect his anſwere, although without cauill he can hardly anſwere it. Thus we haue beheld the common vertues of his aunſwere, let vs looke into the proper ſtrength in the particulars. To the ſecond reaſon his anſwere is, that is this interpretation, they doo nothing leſſe then make the Apoſtle go backward and not forwarde. For this is our meaning which we giue (ſaith he) That they whiche labour, are worthie of double honour: they which do
                     •
                   not, are worthie of none. A ſounde anſwere, which is contrarie to him ſelfe, and toucheth not the force of that obiected againſt him. Shewe the firſte. It is manifeſt by that which after he ſaith: that this place is ment of ſuche as preache well and of ſome that in preaching well, take more labor then other. Here he vnderſtādeth it of thoſe which take any paynes, and ſetteth them againſt thoſe whiche take none So he maketh the higheſt degree of honor due to that which if it be not done, he ſaith, is worthy of no honor
               ▪ How cā that deſerue or haue an excelencie

of honor, which is cōmon to all that may haue any honor in their office? Beſides this cōtradictiō which is euident in his owne words, he toucheth not the force of the obiectiō. The obiectiō is: Whatſoeuer ſenſe maketh the Apoſtle, in the ſecond member of the verſe, giue more to the part, then in the firſt to the whole, maketh him go backward nor forward in his word eſpecially. But this ſenſe of theirs maketh the Apoſtle giue more to him that laboreth in preaching, which is but a parte, then to him which doth it wel, which is to do it with great paynes, puritie, wiſdom, zeale, power, ſoundnes, fitnes, &amp; many other things beſides labor. Therefore this ſenſe maketh him goe backewarde not forwarde, in his worde eſpecially. This reaſon is playne. What ſaith the anſwer? Doth it diſtinguiſh? No. Doth it denie the firſt part? No. What then? It denieth the concluſion, againſt all rule of reaſon. Yet by what reaſon doth he denie it? By giuing an interpretatiō, which doeth not make, either two ſortes of Elders, or of ſincere preachers, but only two ſortes of preachers, one good &amp; worthie of honor, an other euil, whiche take no paynes, worthie of no honour. So that this hauing no degrees of compariſon (which are manifeſtly expreſſed in S. Paules words) can not ſo much as reſemble the ſentēce of the Apoſtle, much leſſe interpret it. His meaning here peraduenture is as after, that al that do it wel, ſhal haue double honor: but they eſpecially, who take yet more paines in doing it well. This his meaning hath two fowle ſpots in it, as faire as he would make it. The firſt is againſt the rule of reaſon, becauſe he beggeth the queſtion: for to proue his denial of the cōcluſion of our reaſon, he bringeth this meaning of his, which is the queſtion we diſpute about. The ſecond fault is againſt plaine dealing in interpreting the ſcripture, &amp; that in two reſpects: one is in interpreting ruling well, or being ouer others well, by preaching well. Which is to interprete the generall by the eſpeciall.

If he ſay, one may do ſo where there is a Trope or an vnproper ſpeache: he muſt firſte proue by euident reaſon out of his text, or other ſcripture, that there, is a Trope, elſe he ſeeketh a knotte in a ruſhe. Beſides this, a figure can not ſtande here, becauſe the Apoſtle doth ſpecifie the general, of being ouer others, into the ſpeciall of being ouer alſo in doctrine: ſo that he can by no meanes enter here vpō ſuch an vnproper ſpeache, but muſt be content to reade, ruling wel, ruling wel, not teaching well. After this ſtraunge interpreting, before this new coyned meaning (carying the very ſtampe of the Ieſuites) enter, he muſt (not without great blame if he look not to it) adde to the wordes of the Apoſtle. For, all the force of his interpretation ſtandeth vpon an addition, to the wordes of the holy Ghoſt: which is, to make him ſay, he that taketh more great paynes then they whiche preache well: All whiche wordes, more then others which doo it well, are neither in the Apoſtle in expreſſe wordes, nor in any of like force to them, neither hath he, or can he With any Syllogiſme conclude it out of his wordes. If he can, let him ſhewe his cūning. The worde Copiazein, whiche ſignifieth, to take great paynes, will not here helpe him: For it doeth not include a compariſon with others.1. Theſ. 5.12 For it is common to all Elders, much more good preachers. For the Apoſtle in makinge cōpariſon, ſaith, en copois, in labors more aboūdant: and ſo by adding the worde of cōpariſon to it, ſheweth it is not conteyned in the very word it ſelf.2. Cor. 11.23 In his anſwere to the thirde reaſon, where he made three ſortes of Preachers, and euen thoſe that doo it not wel, worthie of ſome honor for defence: he ſayth, he ſeeth not why ſuch as take paines, may not haue an honor ſuch as is dew to Widowes: Wherin firſt he trifleth, fleeing frō the matter in hand to another. For he ſhould haue proued that his interpretatiō gaue not a ſingle honor to ſome whiche did not preache

well. Secondly, he is contrarie to him ſelfe. Before he ſaide, here were vnderſtood only two ſortes of Preachers, good and euill: after he ſaide, good and excellent: Now, three ſortes are vnderſtood, ſingle ones, ſuch as may haue the honour of Widowes: double ones, ſuch as may haue double honor: and treble ones, which may eſpecially haue double honor. Wherefore (as the Author of the Counterpoyſon ſaid before, ſo I ſay againe, this is dallying, &amp; not interpreting: And What ſoeuer he ſaye, this Diſcipline of his, is diſſolute. 
                  •
               or if men preache well, they are worthie of double honor, whiche is more then the Widdowes honour. if oteerwiſe they are worthie (as he ſaide before) of none. His anſwere followeth to the laſt reaſon out of Roma. 12.6.7. Where the Elder for gouernement onely, is made a proper member of the church, differing in his proper action from the Teacher, Exhorter, Diſtributer: And out of the 1. Cor. 12. where God is ſaide (beſides all other miniſteries and giftes) to haue ordeyned gouernours in his Church: wherevnto he ſaieth, he denieth the argument, there were ſuch then, therfore there ſhould be ſuch nowe Becauſe (as M. Gualter ſaieth) We muſt firſt proue they haue ſuch giftes of propheſying, doing of miracles, and diuers ſuch like as are there mentioned. To all which we replie, firſt with thankes that hee yeeldeth to the trueth, &amp; graunteth that ſuch were ordeyned of god. In the ſecond place we wil proue they are perpetuall, and then that it is vnreaſonable to demande of vs, to proue that now they haue ſuch giftes as he ſpeaketh of. We mainteyne out of theſe places, that they are perpetuall. Firſt, becauſe they are members ordeyned of Chriſt, hauing actions for the profit of the whole body. For vnleſſe he can proue God hath repealed them, who ſhall cutt them off from the body? Secondly, the Apoſtle in the 12. to the Rom. reckoneth vpp none but perpetuall, as Teachers, Exhorters, Rulers, Diſtributers.

Nowe, him ſelfe (I dare ſay) will acknowledge the giftes of doctrine, exhortatiō, abilitie to diſtribute, &amp; gouerne, with the actions proceeding from thē, to be perpetual, &amp; ſtill neceſſarie If thē the proper actions (as the Apoſtle there ſpeaketh) of the members be perpetual, ſhal the members be momētarie? Doth Chriſt now giue doctrine,
                  Ephe. 4.10. 1, Cor. 1
                     •
                  , 28 exhortation, gouernement, and not Doctors, Feeders, and Gouernors? Or doeth he giue teachers for doctrine, and not gouernours for gouernement?
                  Mat. 28.19. Further, if the Churche daily need theſe for gouernement, and ſeeke orderly for them, and yet haue them not: howe is Chriſt preſent with his Church, to inable her to doo all he commaundeth? In the ſeconde place, doeth not S. Paul ſay he hath ſet gouernors in his Church. Howe can any man ſet them out then? They will ſaye, hee ſaieth, there alſo hee hath ſette Apoſtles, which yet are not perpetuall. It is true: there are mentioned alſo teachers and helpers whiche are perpetuall. So this obiection miniſtreth vs occaſion of a double reaſon: the one by equal compariſon, as the teachers office (whereof the gifte &amp; neceſsitie is perpetuall) for that cauſe remayneth, and the Church ought continually to call for men which are fitt for it, becauſe God hath ſet them in his Churche. So for the Elders office, ſeeing their giftes of watchfulnes, abilitie to admoniſhe, and to aduiſe and gouerne doeth remayne, the Church is continually to cal mē fit for the ſame office into it, becauſe God hath ſet them in his Church. Further, as no authoritie of men could haue remoued the extraordinarie, vnleſſe God had denied their extraordinarie giftes and calling: ſo no man can remoue theſe where the giftes remaine, &amp; an ordinarie way of examination, &amp; election doth remayne for their calling. Thirdly, the Apoſtle writing vnto Timoth. doth giue as general a charge for this ſort of Elders and their continuance, as for the other whiche are 
                  ••
               aching: therfore if you cā proue one perpetual▪
               
you may alſo proue the other to be ſo likewiſe. For the precepts for their honor, their reaſonable immunitie from accuſations, their iuſt rebuke, their carefull ordination, are ſet downe, as common to both ſortes, though, as in the firſt of honor, ſo in the reſt the teaching Elders are eſpecially to bee regarded. Laſtly, they can finde no cōmandement, reaſon, or other groūd in the ſcripture, why the Paſtor in his place ſhuld be perpetual, but we will bring the like for the Elder in his. One is more neceſſarie, wee graunt, but not more perpetuall then another: as the eye, or the tongue, or the hand is more neceſſarie thē the foote, the right ones more then the left, yet alike ordinarie &amp; perpetual. Theſe are our reaſons to proue thē perpetual, which being ſet down for the vnlearned more groſely, we will alſo ſet thē down with ſome other in ſyllogiſmes, that he may the better deale with them, out of Rom. 12.
            No mēbers of Chriſtes body hauing actions for  the profit of the whole, may be thruſt out or put to an ende by any humane authoritie. The Elders and Deacons are ſuch members, Rom. 12.4 8. Ergo,
            
            Al offices whoſe giftes and proper actions are ordinarie  and of perpetuall vſe, they are perpetuall. The offices of Elders &amp; Deacons ar ſuch, as whoſe giftes of abilitie to gouerne, &amp; diſtribut, &amp; actions of diſtribution and gouernement, are perpetuall by  their owne graunt. Ergo, They are offices perpetual Out of the 1. Cor. 12.28. No offices whiche God hath once ſet in his Church, may be put to an ende by humane authoritie. But the offices of Elders &amp; Deacons, haue bin once ſet in the Church by God, 
               Ergo, they may not bee putt to an ende, and conſequently are perpetuall. Whatſoeuer offices haue the ſame cauſe of continuance, are alike perpetuall, though not alike excellent. The office of teachers, &amp; of church gouernors &amp; Deacons, haue the ſame cauſe, as the ordināce of god, the cōtinuāce of their gifts, &amp; of power of the church to cal thē, 1. Cor. 12 Rō. 12.

               Ergo, they are alike perpetuall. Whatſoeuer haue the like cauſe of ceaſing and remayninge, the cauſe of remayning being continued, they remayne, as the cauſe being ceaſed, they ceaſe. But the offices of Church gouernors &amp; Deacons with the offices of Apoſtles, workers of miracles, haue the like cauſe of ceaſing &amp; remaining, to Wit the wil &amp; ordināce of God in continuing the giftes, and the ordinarie and mediat calling of the Church for the one, and his will in withholding the extraordinarie giftes, and immediat calling of the other. Ergo, they do by the like cauſe remaine that the other are takē away
            
                Whatſoeuer haue the ſame general cōmādement, and rules of examination, traill, ordination, abdication, honor, reproſe, without ſpeciall exemptiō for any: are alike perpetual. But the offices of teaching and vnteaching Elders and of Deacons, haue the ſame generall commandement, &amp;c. 1. Ti. 5.3, 10. 1. Tim. 5.17.18, &amp;c. Ergo, they are alike perpetuall.
            Whatſoeuer offices are neceſſarie in euerie cōgregation  for Diſcipline after the ſeconde priuate admonition: they are perpetuall: otherwiſe the remedie Chriſt hath appointed for ſinners, is not perpetuall. But an aſſemblie of Gouernours in expreſſe wordes of Chriſt, are neceſſarie in euery cōgregation for Diſcipline, after the ſeconde priuat admonition, Mat. 18.17. Ergo, ſuch an aſſemblie is perpetuall.
            Whatſoeuer offices were ordeined for ordinarie  and perpetuall gouernement of the Church vnder the lawe, &amp; hauing continued frō 
               Moſes to Chriſt, haue as the other offices of teaching &amp; exhorting, bin newly increaſed and augmented by Chriſte to the Church vnder the Goſpell: thoſe are perpetuall: becauſe there can be no cauſe ſo great, found of altering offices of ordinarie giftes and vſe ſince Chriſt, as was betwene Chriſt and Moſes. But the office of gouerning Elders adioyned to Teachers

and exhorters are ſuch. Ergo, the aſſumption is proued by theſe places, Leuit. 4.13, 14, 15. (Where the Elders, as bearing the perſon and ſins of the whole congregation, are diſtinguiſhed from the Prieſt &amp; the Magiſtrate.) Iere. 19.1. Where the ciuill and eccleſiaſticall Elders are diſtinguiſhed▪ 2. Chron. 19.8.11. Where for the matters of God, to the Prieſtes and teaching Leuites, are adioyned Elders, Heſr. 10.8. Where the counſell of the Elders for excommunication is ioyned, though (diſtinguiſhed from it) with the counſell and decree of the Princes touching confiſcation of goods. Nehem. 8.5.8. Where the Elders in gouerning the Aſſemblie, are diſtinguiſhed from the Prieſtes and teachinge Leuites. For counſell they are adioyned euen with the Prophetes, 2. Reg. 6.32. Out of the newe Teſtament the places are pregnant and many, Act. 4.5. &amp; 6.12. &amp; 5.21. Act. 13, 15. &amp; 18.8. So that this proueth the ordinance and continuance of them from Moſes to Chriſt. That Chriſt cōtinued them and augmented them with giftes, as he did the offices of teaching and exhortinge, the place of Mat. 18. Tell the aſſembly, and if he heare no
                     •
                   it, lette him bee a Heathen and publicane, doth proue it: for by vſing expreſſe wordes, proper to that order of theirs, hee doeth manifeſtly eſtabliſhe it. The places whiche haue proued them ordeyned in the Church, proue this point alſo. Laſtly, them ſelues graunt Chriſte ordeyned ſuch, only they denie them to be perpetuall.
            Nowe, if they demande humane witnes, what can they haue more cleare then that Ignatius, who (as they ſay, was S. Ihons Scoller) writing to ſeuen Churches, in euerie Epiſtle ſpeaking only of ſuch offices as were ordinarie and perpetuall, Biſhopps, Elders and Deacons, doeth ſay (as hath bin alledged) that No Church can be without her Elderſhip. And leaſt any man ſhould ſay, he ment teaching Elders.

Lette them marke that hee defineth their office to be a Senate of Counſelers, and aſsiſtants to the Biſhoppe in euery Church: ouer which Biſhop he acknowledgeth no Church-officer but Chriſt, without which Biſhop it is not lawfull to adminiſter the Communion, Baptiſme, or performe any action in the Aſſemblie. His wordes are theſe· What is the Elderſhip, but a holy Senat, the Counſellers and aſsiſtantes of the Biſhop. And a little before: The Elders are as the Senat of God, and the hande and ſinewe of the Apostles of Chriſt, without theſe the elect Church is not, no Congregation of Saintes, without theſe, Epiſt. 2. ad Tralleſ. Here the office is defined, as conſiſting onely in gouernement. That in the Sacramentes they might only aſsiſt the Biſhop, and not adminiſter them, or doo any publike action, is manifeſt by theſe wordes: It is not lawfull with out a Biſhop, eyther to Baptize, or to offer, or to prepare the offring, (in the Communion) or perfect the gifte or diſtribution, but that which ſeemeth good to him, according to the good pleaſure of God, that what ſoeuer you doo, may be ſafe and ſure. Ignat. Epiſt. 2. ad Smyrnaeos, and in the ſame Epiſtle, Therefore let all things be done of you, according to good order in Chriſt. Let the laye men be ſubiect to the Deacons,
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     ute th
                        •
                     ſian proſcem ze
                        〈…〉
                      oute d
                        •
                     chen epitilem.
                
               the Deacons to the Elders, the Elders to the Biſhop, the Biſhop to Chriſt, as he to his Father In the time of Cyprian, they remayned. Ambroſe, when they were fallen away, doeth complayne of it, and doeth make the cauſe of their falling awaye, not becauſe they were not perpetual, nor yet becauſe they might not continue, but the negligence and pride of the teachers.
            Nowe that wee haue proued that hee required of the perpetuitie of theſe offices: lett vs come to his reaſon, why he denieth them to be perpetuall, whiche is, becauſe wee can not firſte proue the Elders to haue ſuch giftes of prophecying, dooing miracles, &amp;c. But wee bidde him proue firſte this ſtrange and monſtrouſe aſſertion: that it is neceſſarie

for vs to proue it. Secondly, we will ſhew him the vanitie and deteſtable abſurdities which folow this his demande. The vanitie may appeare by theſe reaſons out of the text. The gouernours and the gift of gouernement are as much diſtinguiſhed frō Prophetes &amp; doers of miracles, as they are from teachers: therfore to require ſuch neceſſarie for gouernement more then doctrine, is to ouerthrowe the purpoſe of the Apoſtle, which is to ſhew howe euery office hath his ſeueral &amp; proper gift. Secondly, if the vſe of ſuch giftes as he ſpeaketh of, be no part of gouernemēt, what neceſsitie is there of thē in Elders as they are Elders? Thirdly, we demaūd of him, whether he require theſe giftes in al Elders or in ſome, &amp; in whom he doth require thē, whether he would haue all thoſe giftes to be in them or ſome only. If he require them in all, he muſt proue firſt that they were in al the Elders in the Apoſtles time, which he ſhall do ad graecas kalendas, that is, neuer. If he require all thoſe giftes in any, let him proue that any Elder was furniſhed with them al, which he ſhal neuer do. If ſome only, let him ſhew whiche are neceſſarie, and which not. And let him out of the ſcripture proue his ſaying, and we will yeelde. Thus we haue ſeene the vanitie of the demande, marke the abſurdities following. Firſt, that they make themſelues wiſer then the Apoſtle, who requireth no more in the dutie of an Elder, then to be ouer the flocke with diligence, Rom. 12.5.6. Secondly, they require more in the Elders thē the Apoſtle required in a teaching Elder or a Biſhop, when he giueth the rule of his examinatiō, 1. Tim. 3. Thirdly they may by the ſame rule throw out teachers, ſeeing in this place the Apoſtle giueth ſuch giftes no more to the Elders then to the teachers: eſpecially this conſequence is neceſſarie, becauſe the principall ende of thoſe giftes, being eyther to deliuer doctrine, or giue credit to it, is more neceſſarie for the teacher then the gouuernor.
            
               Fourtly, ſeeing they vnderſtande by Elders thoſe who preach, and will haue none gouerning only, it remaineth that by his reaſon we muſt firſt proue thoſe giftes to remayne in them,
                  Iames 5. eare we can proue ſuch to remayne.
                  Marke 16.17 Acte. 2.16, 17, 18, 19
                     •
                   
                  Act. 21.8. 1. Cor. 14.26.34. Laſtly, ſeeinge theſe giftes were cōmon to priuate perſons, yea to women, euen to all ſortes of beleeuers, we muſt firſt proue (by their reaſon) theſe giftes to remaine, eare wee can proue there be any church or faithfull men in the world. Theſe are the deteſtable abſurdities which followe vpon this reaſon of theirs, wherby the anſwer to it is euidēt, that the Apoſtle ſetteth down there, both offices, as Apoſtles, Teachers, Prophetes, Elders, Deacons, and alſo ſome giftes, which were cōmon to all, as ornamentes to confirme for a time, Chriſtian Religion: Now, althogh theſe giftes are long ſince ceaſſed, yet the offices may remayne without them: eſpecially the offices of teaching, exhorting, gouerning, which are for their vſe, &amp; the giftes required in them, perpetual: euery part of which anſwere hath bin before cōfirmed in the particulars. Hitherto he hath labored againſt the trueth, to ouerthrowe it: Nowe, fearing that all the inſtrumentes he had, would not throttle the cauſe, ſo as ſhe ſhould no more open her mouth: hee ſeeketh to diſguiſe her with a ſlaunder. Where we will firſt ſee what he bringeth: then we will mainteyne the contrarie. The ſumme of that he obiecteth is, they which ſtande for Diſcipline, are thought to bringe in contention, and to vndermine the power of the Magi
                     •
                  trate. In this accuſation firſt you muſt well obſerue, hee doeth not, nor dareth not ſay, it is ſo, but that it is thought ſo. To which it may be anſwered, that it is thought, that the other ſide ſeeke to driue out the ſufficient miniſterie, that they alone may reigne, pille the people af her Maieſtie; abuſe thē &amp; grind them, without hauing any of their filthines diſcouered. It is thought of ſome alſo, that they make a

way to Atheiſme, Poperie, and all confuſion, whyleſt they thruſt our ſo many worthie and paynfull laborers out of the L. Vineyard, and bring in ignorant, vngodly, riotouſe, idle and couetous perſons, in their ſteede. Nay, ſome of theſe are not onely thought, but manifeſtly by experience in manye places felt. Secondly, you may obſerue howe the light of his conſcience ſtroue with his affections againſt the cauſe. His affection and deſire was to diſgrace the cauſe it ſelf, as preiudiciall to the peace of the Church and ciuill Magiſtrate. Now, When in his cōſcience he found he could deduct no ſuch thing out of the matter of Diſcipline, hee turneth from the matter to the perſons, and ſayth, they are thought ſo to do. Why doth he not ſhew who they be that ſo thinke of them, vpon what groundes, by what ſignes and tokens, by what counſelles, writings, examples or deedes they haue giuen likelihood of it? If hee can neither conclude any ſuche matter out of the cauſe it ſelf, nor proue any thing againſt the perſons which ſeeke it. How, Is it not the maintenance of a malitious ſlaunder? We haue haue harde what he ſayth: will he adde no ground of it? Yes, An admonition to Scotlande, printed An. 1558. cōteineth cōcluſions as ſtraunge againſt the Eſtate, as D. Sanders (that traytors booke) doth. What doth it? Doeth it conteyne flat treaſon, that the Prince by any Eccleſiaſticall power may be depoſed or reſiſted? That the Queens moſt Excellent Maieſtie is an heretike, or receyueth not Diſcipline, and thetefore muſt be excommunicated, and after accounted no lawfull Queene? Hath any fauouring Diſcipline writtē theſe things, or the like? If he can not ſhewe any ſuch thing, what is he but a Preacher of ſlaunders at Pawles Croſſe? The booke he ſpeaketh of, to my knowledge, I haue not ſeene: neyther knowe where to haue it. Yet I aſſure my ſelfe, he can bring foorth no ſuche concluſions

from any which hath ſpokē or written for Diſcipline. But be it that ſome one man had written without ground or reaſon contrarie to the ſcriptures, ſhal that or any mannes abuſe, blot out the credit which ſo many Churches in France, Scotlande, Germanie, the lowe Countries, hath brought to it, as finding it holy, peaceable, and no ſmall pillar, both of the peace of the Church and ciuill gouernement? When we conſider what inconueniences followe any matter, we muſt not conſider what ſome (whiche hold the cauſe) would haue, but what the cauſe of his owne nature will inferre. For, as the good meaning of a good man will not make a perilouſs cauſe ſafe, ſo the ill meaning of a noughtie mā, will not make a ſafe and iuſt cauſe dangerouſe. I maruaile what cauſe may be found out to make Diſcipline hurtfull to the common wealth: or what reaſon why the Magiſtrates authoritie and it,2. Chro. 19.11. Iere. 19.1. Heſ. 10.8. 2. Reg. 6. 1. Sam. 30.27 28, 29, 30. Actes 4.5. &amp; 6, 12. &amp; 5.21 Act. 23.14.15.16. &amp; 25, 15. ſhoulde not dwell peaceably togither. The Kings and Rulers of Iſrael found it not ſo: The Romanes after them found it not ſo, they being Heathen, more curious to looke into ſuche matters then any: more ielouſe, more politike, moſt ielouſe ouer the Iewes of all others, becauſe of the King which they looked for to come in worldlie glorie, could neuer yet finde out any ſuch ſuſpition. In all their times it was quietly practiſed. The Kings and Princes, both Proteſtant, which haue allowed it, and popiſh (as in France) which haue permitted it, they haue founde no ſuch thing in it. For the ſeconde point▪ By what reaſon ſhould the Magiſtrats authoritie be at ſuch enimitie with Diſcipline, or diſcipline with it? Is it becauſe the Magiſtrat will or can doo that, which the Elders doe, or the Elders will or can doe that which he doth? Will the Magiſtrat watche ouer particular flockes, admoniſhe euery ſinner they finde out, followe menne by ſpirituall meanes, till they bring them to repentance? will they them ſelues

execute the ſpirituall cenſures of ſuſpentiō, excommunication, and ſuch like? Is this his office, or can his conſcience beare this burthen? Doeth the Elders meddle with any ciuill cauſe, or vſe anye oher meanes then which are ſpirituall? Shall they doe things ſo cloſely, that al their actes may not be ſeene of the Magiſtrate, if he ſuſpect any thinge? Nay, muſt not all thinges they doo, come to open knowledge, if they paſſe a priuate admonition? Will they bring no good to the common wealthe: meete with no ſeedes of ſedition? Shall they not be able to giue notice of the diſpoſitions of al men? Shall they not finde out Ieſuites and all heretikes, and bring them to light? Shall not the ſmaler vices and ſometimes foule ones alſo, whiche the lawe nowe meddleth little with, by this meanes bee cu
                  •
               t off? In deede, then mens purſes ſhoulde not bee picked, as they are nowe. Then ſo manye Veluet coates ſhould not be maintayned by ſpiritual reuenewes. But I will ſpeake no more of theſe matters. Only I conclude, ſeeing men haue in the tyme of proſperitie more neede of admonition and wholſome Diſcipline: ſeing the Elderſhip doth nothing which the Magiſtrat doeth, nor can any way hurte him, but he may ſee it better ordred then in perſecution: that as this order is neceſſarie alwayes, ſo eſpecially in the time of peace. The Lord giue vs all to be of one minde, to ſee the trueth, and practiſe it.
         
      
   

