
   
      
         
            Lessons for 1.2. and 3. viols. By Alfonso Ferrabosco
            Ferrabosco, Alfonso, ca. 1575-1628.
         
         
            
               1609
            
         
         Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00694
            STC 10828
            ESTC S117687
            99852898
            99852898
            18253
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00694)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18253)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 834:15)
         
         
            
               
                  Lessons for 1.2. and 3. viols. By Alfonso Ferrabosco
                  Ferrabosco, Alfonso, ca. 1575-1628.
               
               [46] p. : music  
               
                  Printed by Thomas Snodham, for Iohn Brovvne, and are to be sould at his shop in Saint Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleetstreet,
                  London :
                  1609.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-M²  (-M2, blank?).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Viols --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-07
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-05
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-05
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  COR⸫ ✚ MVSICA ✚ LAETIFICAT ✚
                  
                  LESSONS FOR 1. 2. and 3. Viols.
BY Alfonſo Ferraboſco.
                  
                  
                     LONDON: Printed by THOMAS SNODHAM, for IOHN BROVVNE, and are to be ſould at his ſhop in Saint Dunſtones Church-yard in Fleetſtreet.
                  1609.
               
            
         
         
            
            
            TO THE PERFECTION OF HONOVR, My Lord HENRY, EARLE of South-hampton.
            
               WHilſt other men ſtudy your Titles (Honourable Lord) I doe your Honours; and finde it a nearer way to giue actions, then words: for the talking man commonly goes about, and meetes the iuſtice at his errours end, not to be beleeu'd. Yet, if in modeſt actions, the circumſtances of ſingularitie, and profeſsion hurt not; it is true, that I made theſe Compoſitions ſolely for your Lordſhip, and doe here profeſſe it. By which time, I haue done all that I had in purpoſe, and returne to my ſilence:
            Where you are moſt honor'd by
Alfonſo Ferraboſco.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE WORLD.
            
               LEaſt I fall vnder the Character of the vaine-glorious Man, in ſome opinions, by thruſting ſo much of my induſtrie in Print; I would all knew, how little fame I hope for, that way: when beſide his, for, and to whom they are, I aym'd at no mans ſuffrage in the making; though I might praeſume, that could not but pleaſe others, which I was contented had pleaſed him. But, as it is the errour, and misfortune of young Children, oftentimes to ſtray, and looſing their dwellings be taken vp by ſtrangers; and there lou'd and own'd: So theſe, by running abroad hauing got them falſe Parents; and ſome, that, to my face, would challenge them; I had beene a moſt vnnaturall Father, if I had not corrected ſuch impudence, and by a publique declaration of them to be mine (when other meanes abandon'd me) acknowledg'd kind. This is all the glory I affected, to doe an act of Nature and Iuſtice. For their ſeale, they had it in the Mint, or not at all: Howſoeuer, if they want it, I will eaſe my ſelfe the vice of commendation.
            
               Alfonſo Ferraboſco.
            
         
         
            TO MY EXCELLENT FRIEND, ALFONSO FERRABOSCO.
            
            
               WHen we doe giue, Alfonſo, to the light
               A worke of ours, we part with our owne right.
               For then, all mouthes will iudge; and their owne way:
               The Learn'd haue no more priuiledge, then the Lay.
               And, though we could all men, all cenſures heare,
               We ought not giue them taſte, we had an eare:
               For, if the humerous World will talke, at large,
               They ſhould be fooles, for me, at their owne charge.
               Say, this, or that man they to thee preferre;
               Euen thoſe, for whom they doe this, know they erre:
               And would (being ask'd the truth) aſhamed ſay,
               They were not to be nam'd, on the ſame day.
               Then ſtand vnto thy ſelfe, nor ſeeke without
               For Fame, with breath ſoone kindled, ſoone blowneout.
            
            
               Ben: Ionſon.
            
         
         
            Jn lode dell'arte, &amp; dell' Authore, SONETTO.
            
               S'Ogni arte tanto piu da noi s'apprezza,
               Quanto ha piu nobil ſenſo per oggetto,
               &amp; quanto n'e peu degno il ſoggetto,
               
                  Ʋince l'altre arti harmonica dolcezza,
               Quella a dar gusto &amp; contento s'auezza
               Al noſtro vdir, de ſenſi il piu perfetto;
               Per ſogetto h'a numero vguale, &amp; retto,
               &amp; di bella aria, &amp; tuoni la vaghezza.
               Questa arte dungue eſsendo di tal merto,
               Alfonſo mio, chi d' Orpheo ports il vanto,
               Conuien pregiarti, &amp; queſts tuoi concenti▪
               
               Tanto piu ch'eſsi con doppio concerto,
               A gl'iſtromenti attando il dolce canto,
               Di piacer doppio ne appagan le ment
                     •
                  .
            
            
               Gual: Quin.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            Leſſons for the Lyra Violl.
            
               1
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  The firſt Tuning. ALmaine.       Coranto.    
            
            
               
               2
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.    Coranto.    
            
            
               
               3
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.    
            
            
               
               4
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               5
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.   Coranto.   
            
            
               
               6
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.    
            
            
               
               7
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.   
            
            
               
               8
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  The ſecond tuning. PAuin.       Coranto.   
            
            
               
               9
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.       Coranto.   
            
            
               
               10
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  PAuin.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               11
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.       Coranto.  
            
            
               
               12
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.    
            
            
               
               13
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  PAuin.      Coranto.    
            
            
               
               14
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  PAuin.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               15
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  The first tuning. ALmaine.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               16
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               17
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  The third tuning. ALmaine.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               18
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               19
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               20
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.    
            
            
               
               21
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  PAuin.       Coranto.   
            
            
               
               22
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.    
            
            
               
               23
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               24
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               25
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.      Coranto.   
            
         
         
            
            For two Viols.
            
               26
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  The firſt tuning. ALmaine.       Coranto.   
            
            
               
               26
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                   
                  ALmaine.      Coranto.    
            
            
               
               27
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                   The firſt tuning GAlliard.        Coranto.   
            
            
               
               27
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.      Coranto.   
            
            
               
               28
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.   
            
            
               
               28
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                   
                  ALmaine.       Coranto.   
            
            
               
               29
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  The firſt tuning GAlliard.      Coranto.    
            
            
               
               29
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.     Coranto.    
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
            
            
               
               30
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  The third tuning. GAlliard.       Coranto.   
            
            
               
               30
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  GAlliard.     Coranto.   
            
            
               
               31
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.     Coranto.    
            
            
               
               31
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
                  ALmaine.       Coranto.    
            
         
         
            
            
               32 A Fancie for three Viols.
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
            
            
               
               33 A Pauin for three Viols.
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈♫〉
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            34 Prelude.
            
               
                  〈♫〉
                 Prelude.   Prelude.    
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

