
   
      
         
            The prayer and confession of Mr. Felton, word for word as hee spake it immediately before his execution. Novem. 29. 1628
            Felton, John, 1595?-1628.
         
         
            
               1628
            
         
         Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00626
            STC 10762
            ESTC S120506
            99855702
            99855702
            21204
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00626)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21204)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:10)
         
         
            
               
                  The prayer and confession of Mr. Felton, word for word as hee spake it immediately before his execution. Novem. 29. 1628
                  Felton, John, 1595?-1628.
               
               [2], 6 p.   
               
                  s.n.,
                  [London :
                  1628]
               
               
                  Place and date of publication from STC.
                  Felton was excuted for assassinating the Duke of Buckingham.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Buckingham, George Villiers, --  Duke of, 1592-1628 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-01
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-01
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
Prayer and Confession of Mr.
FELTON, word for word as
hee spake it immediatly before
his Execution. 
                  Novem. 29.
1628.
            
            
            
               
OH God, I humbly and heartily
thanke thee gracious Father,
that thou hast giuen me
so long a time of Repentance. Lord,
I humbly thanke thee, I praise my
God, and blessed bee thy holy name.
Oh Lord, my glorious God, that thou
hast beene so good and gracious to
mee, as to take away the feeling of
the sence of death from mee, I thanke
my God, I haue no feare of death, Iesus
I thanke thee.
            I thanke the noble Duchesse of Buckingham,
and I wonder at her great
worth being of so good a disposition,
that shee should forgiue mee so foule
a fact, so foule and horrid a sinne;
Oh God, forgiue mee likewise; and I
hope in Iesus, he hath.
            Likewise, I humbly and heartily
craue of the meanest of all her Seruants,
from a sincere relenting heart, I

craue forgiuenesse of them all for that
horrid fact that I haue committed,
Lord thou knowest it pierceth mee
much, and afflicts my soule exceedingly?
Oh Lord, I haue dishonoured thee,
I haue brought a scandall vpon my
Religion, for which fact O Lord,
I haue deserued Ten thousand punishments
to be inflicted vpon me.
            Oh God, I doe wonder at thy mercie,
that thou hast beene so good and
gracious to me, seeing I haue committed
so foule, and so horrible a sinne.
Oh Lord, thou hast shewed mee mercie
many times; Lord thou art wonderfull,
I cannot expresse thy wonderfull
mercies towards me. In deliuering
me from many single combates
and diuers other perils and dangers,
for which I giue thee most humble
thankes.
            I beseech God to blesse my gracious
King, and that hee may long liue
O Lord, and that the Parliament may

agree, and bee vnited in one for Iesus
Christs sake, Lord I beseech thee.
            That which drawed mee to this
horrid sinfull fact, was some foule reports,
which though they had beene
true it was damnable in mee, in committing
and acting so foule a sinne,
Oh Lord forgiue me for it, though it
had bin so, I haue dishonoured God,
in taking the Iudgement from him.
            Gentlemen, I am a Souldier, and
I cannot speake, I pray God forgiue
mee what is past, and receiue my soule
Oh Lord I beseech thee, Lord forgiue
me.
            Then the Marshall asked, haue you any
more to say Mr. Felton.
            
            He answered, I know not what to
say, the Lord haue mercy on my soule.
            Then he spake to the People concerning the
Executioner, as followeth.
            I beseech you now all of you, that
the poore man heere suffer no wrong
I beseech you, for he doth but his office.
            
               
Then after they had sung the 51. Psalme,
hee sayd.
            God blesse the Kings Majestie, and
the Queene, the King of Bohemia and
the Queene, and all their Noble issue;
Lord Iesus receiue my soule.
            Gentlemen, to satisfie you; Know
that in this Bloody and haynous fact
that I haue committed, I was seduced
by the Diuell, such a foule thing
could not haue proceeded from mee
else; Lord forgiue mee, and bee mercifull
vnto mee.
            Lord blesse the Noble Dutchesse of
Buckingham; If I had had the disposing
of mine owne life, shee should
haue had it as it had pleased her selfe,
and not thus fauourably.
            Lord Iesus forgiue mee this horrid
and vile sinne; Lord Iesus forgiue me
this vile and bloodie sinne.
            Lord I thanke thee, that thou hast
taken away the feare of Death? Lord,
the sentence was terrible.
            
               
The hearing of Death yesternight,
affrighted me much, but I praise God
I haue now no feare of Death.
            I beseech you, none of you thinke
that the fact was done well; it was
abhorrent, I haue much dishonoured
God in it, Lord forgiue me this bloudie
sinne, and all my other sinnes.
            I beseech you Gentlemen pray for
mee.
            Well, I praise my God, I haue no
feare of death, Lord Iesus I thank thee
I haue no feare of death I praise my
God.
            Lord blesse the Duchesse of Buckingham
that noble Ladie, Lord bee
mercifull to her.
            Truely, they are wonderfull mercifull
to me, I did not thinke but that
I should haue come to a crueller
death, as I haue deserued.
            Oh Lord! I thanke thee, that thou
hast taken mee away, I pray my God,
that the death of his Sonne may take

away all feare and horror▪ Lord I beleeue,
I haue full assurance, receiue my
soule, oh Lord.
            Then he asked if any of the Duchesses
Seruants were there, they said yes:
and asked what hee would haue. Hee
said.
            I pray tell her, That I desire with
all my soule to bee forgiuen, Euen of
the meanest seruant, of the veriest
Skullian in her Kitchin.
            Lastly, he desired the people, for
Gods sake that they would not misvse
the poore man, The Executioner.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

