
   
      
         
            A brief treatise vpon the first table of the lavve orderly disposing the principles of religion, whereby we may examine our selues. Written by Maister Dudley Fenner, Minister of the Gospell.
            Fenner, Dudley, 1558?-1587.
         
         
            
               1588
            
         
         Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00634
            STC 10768
            ESTC S118184
            99853393
            99853393
            18776
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00634)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18776)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1270:32)
         
         
            
               
                  A brief treatise vpon the first table of the lavve orderly disposing the principles of religion, whereby we may examine our selues. Written by Maister Dudley Fenner, Minister of the Gospell.
                  Fenner, Dudley, 1558?-1587.
               
               [44] p.   
               
                  Printed by R. Schilders,
                  [Middelburg :
                  1588?]
               
               
                  Imprint from STC.
                  Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .
                  Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Ten Commandments --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-01
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2006-01
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A brief Treatiſe
vpon the firſt Table
of the Lavve, orderly
diſpoſing the principles
of Religion, whereby
we may examine
our ſelues.
            
            
               Written by Maister DVDLEY
FENNER, Miniſter
of the
Goſpell.
            ROM. 7. 7.
            I knewe not ſinne, but by the
Lawe.
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            GEntle Reader, thou hast heare a briefe and
plaine expoſition of the firste Table of the
Lawe of God. Made by Master Dudley Fenner,
for the profite of his own particular charge
and ſome other his friendes. The whiche comming
to my handes, I thought good to make the
profit thereof more generall. And the rather,
in that it was the first fruites of his labours, being
made by him before the twentieth yeare of
his age: Whereby thou mayest ſee with what
an excellent ſpirit he was indued, euen in his
tender yeares. Accept it therefore as it is men
                  •
               
thee: and if thou reape thereby any profit, giue
God the glorie.
         
      
      
         
            
            A ſhort and plaine Table
orderlie diſpoſing the Principles of
Religion, and first of the first Table of
the Lawe, whereby vve may examine
our ſelues.
            
                ALl being loſt in Adam by  our nature
corrupted,  and much more
by the fruites thereof, they who
ſhal be ſaued, muſt bee reſtored by beinge
 one with Chriſt, and ſo with God,  Rom.
3. ver. 9. to 20.  Rom. 5. 14. Ephe. 2. ver. 3.
 Rom. 5. 12. 14. &amp; 6. 21. 23.  1. Iohn. 1. 3.
To obtaine Chriſt 2 meanes are ordained.
            the

                  Lawe preached, 2. Cor. 3. 5. 6.
                  &amp; Goſpell preached, 2. Cor. 3. 5. 6.
               
            
            By theſe two Inſtrumentes the holy Ghoſt
worketh  two things neceſſarie to be in vs
for the obtayning of Chriſt.  2. Cor. 3. 6. 7.
Rom. 8. 15. 8. &amp;c.
            By the firſt,  a true knowledge and feeling
of ſinne, &amp; the puniſhment due to the
ſame,  whiche maketh vs ſeeke Chriſte,
 Rom. 7. 5. to the 15. Mat. 5. 6.  Gal. 3. 19.
to the 25. Mat. 9. 12. 13.
            By the ſecond,  a true knowledge and
feeling of grace,  with power by faith to
receyue Chriſt.  Ephe. 3. 8. to the end, and
4. 11. to 17. Rom. 10. 14. 15. 16.  Gal. 3. 26.
to the ende.
            
               
The Lawe is a doctrine  giuen of God,
 commaunding  to the whole man,  perfect
obedience, in doing thoſe things  onlie
which in the Lawe are commaunded,
and fleeing thoſe only which there are forbidden.
 Deut. 5. 28.  Rom. 10. 5.  ſoule
and body, &amp;c. Deut. 26. 16. &amp; 30. 2.  Deu.
6. 24. 25. and 28. 5.  Deut. 12. 32. Num. 15
39. Eccle. 12. 15. Deut. 12. 28.
            2 Giuen) And therfore euery thing taught
out of the Lawe rightlie interpreted, is to
be receyued, Rom. 7. 7.
            2 Commaunding to doo) One difference betweene
the Lawe and the Goſpell, which to
apprehende Chriſt, and ſo iuſtification, &amp;c.
asketh but beliefe, Rom. 10. 15. Galat. 3.
10. 11. 12.
            3 Wholeman) Therefore in the commaundementes,
not the body onely, but the iudgement,
will, and affections, in the ſoule
muſt be taught what to doe, and leaue vndone.
            4 Perfect obedience.) A ſeconde difference
of the Law and Goſpell is gathered: for the
Goſpell asketh but a true faith, not perfect,
Marke 9. 24. 1. Theſ. 3. 10. Alſo by this, not
onely the thing, but the neceſſarie meanes
to the things is commaunded and forbidden,
Prouerb. 31. 5. and 8.
            
               
5 Commaunded forbidden) So that euerie
precept doeth not onely commaunde the
good, or forbid the euill, but both, Mat. 22.
            That the firſte worke may better bee
wrought, the Lawe hath two properties,
Deut. 28. 3. 15.
            
               Curſe or puniſhment, whiche is the firſte,
which puniſheth the leaſt offence with the
wrath of God to be felt for euer ſin ſoule &amp;
body, called death, Gal. 3. 10. Rom. 6. 23. &amp;
5. 12. 13. Deut. 27. 26. Gene. 2. 17.
            
               Bleſſing or rewarde, which is the ſeconde,
giuing to the perfect obedience of all, the
fauour of God to be felt with all bleſſing in
ſoule and body for euer, called life, Deut. 6.
24. 25. Leuit. 18. 5. Deut. 30. 19. 20.
            Thus much of the Lawe, with the properties
and vſe of it. Nowe followeth the
interpretation of it, where is declared what
is commaunded and forbidden.
            In the interpretation of the Lawe, muſt
be ſeene what is commaunded and forbidden,
Prou. 2. 9.
            
               Generally Iointly in the whole body
of the law ioyned togither,
and in the generall, diuiſion
of the Lawe of God.
               Specially what is in euery particular cō
                  mandement.
            
            
               
In the whole body of the Lawe iointly
conſidered, two thinges are commaunded:

                  Knowledge 1. Col. 10.
                  and Practiſe, 1. Col. 10.
               
            
            Concerning the firſt, is commanded the
true knowledge of good and euill, which is
for the age of euery man. Col. 1. 9. 10. Phil.
1. 9. Heb. 5. 14. Luke 2. 52. To  deſire it,
 delight in it, loue it,  Pro. 2. 3. 4. &amp; 4. 10. 
Pro. 2. 10. Pſa. 119. 24. Cōrarie is  forbidden
generall ignorance of good and euill.
 Hoſ. 4. 6. Ephe. 4. 17. To loue it, deſire it,
delight in it. Prou. 1. 22.
            Practiſe is the following or flying of the
thing known to be cōmanded or forbiddē
               ▪
            
            it hath

                  Inwarde feeling. Phil. 1. 9. &amp; 2. 13
                  Outward workes. Ephe. 5. 10.
               
            
            By feeling of the heart we chooſe, loue,
deſire, delight, are zealous in the good thing
it ſelfe, that it may be done, to refuſe, hate,
abhorre, and are zealous againſt the knowne
euil. Amos. 5. 14. Phil. 1. 9. 1. Theſ. 21.
Amongſt theſe, zeale is an earneſt affection
of the minde, whereby we doe followe the
good, or flee the euill, ſo much as wee are
vehementlie grieued with that which hindereth
it, 2. Cor. 7. 11. Mat. 3. 7. 1. King. 19.
10. Act. 18. 25. Num. 25. 13. Here is forbidden
the contrarie, as no feeling. Ephe. 4.
17. Zeph. 1. 12. In zeale forbidden, wante

of true zeale. Apoca. 3. 15. Zeale for euill.
Mat. 10. 21. Zeale for good beyonde knowledge.
Luke 9. 53.
            In feeling, the affections muſt bee ſo ordered,
as that they may bee equally more
ſlacke or ſtronge, as the good or euill ſhall
be greater or leſſer. The order of the Lawe
confirmeth this, when God is prouided for
firſt, than man: firſt particular boundes, thē
generall. Hee that loueth Father and Mother
more then me. Mat. 10. 37. So we muſt
deſire more the preſence of God in the life
to come, than his fauour in this life. 1. Corint.
17. And loue and reuerence more the
teaching Elders than gouerning onely. 1.
Tim. 5. 17. &amp;c. For the better doing of this
            is required

                  Perfectiō Mat. 12. 37. and 37. vers 5.
                  &amp; Sobrietie. Mat. 12. 37. and
37. vers 5.
               
            
            Perfection is, when the affections in dooing
are both ſtrong enough, and alſo ſincere
or vpright. 1. Chro. 29. 9. Strength is,
whē according as the good or euill is, there
lacketh no earneſtnes of affection. Deut 6.
5. Mat. 22. 37. Here is forbidden the leaſt
remiſſion or weaknes. Reuel. 2. 4. Vprightnes
is, when the affection loueth, deſireth,
&amp;c. In a ſingle heart, onely becauſe GOD
commaundeth, and for that endeWhich he cōmandeth generally to all thinges, the ſettinge forth of his glory. 1. Co. 10. 32. and Chap. 6. 20. this is
called ſimplicitie, trueth, a ſingle hearte,
Deut. 18. 13. Iohn 1. 47. Ephe. 6. 14. and 6.

6. 1. Chron. 29. 5. Forbidden hypocriſie,
vaine glorie, &amp;c. Mat. 6. 5. 1. Cor. 13. 3. Phi.
1. 16. and 2. 3.
            Sobrietie in affection, is to holde them
in, ſo that they paſſe not meaſure. 2. Tim. 1.
6. 1. Tit. 8. Thus much of feeling.
            The ſecond thing in practiſe, is the outward
work, when from the inward feeling,
the members of the body execute. Rom. 6.
12. 13. Rom. 12. 1. The want of this forbidden.
Iam. 1. 26. 27. To all this is commaunded

                  Perſeuerance Eph. 6. 10.
                  &amp; Watchfulnes, Eph. 6. 10.
               
            
            Perſeuerance is alwayes to continue and
goe forwarde in dooing good, and fleeing
euill. Ezech. 18. 25. 1. Coloſ. 10. To this is
contrarie a ſtay, or going backwarde, Gal. 5
            Watchfulneſſe is a continuall care with
ourſelues, that wee be readily prepared, as
we ought, to practiſe good, and reſiſt euill,
which is ſet foorth, Ephe. 6. 10. 18. 1. Cor.
16. 13. 1. Theſ. 5. 6. Marke 13. 35. In this is
forbidden no continuance, no care, too little,
to ſlake, &amp;c. Gen. 3. Eue. Dauid. 2. Sam.
11. 1. 2. 3. 1. Theſ. 5. 3. 6.
            The remedie of our ſinnes in theſe, is
Chriſt his death, with his knowledge. Luk.
2. 52. With his feeling, Iohn 4. 34. With his
zeale. Iohn 2. 17. His continuance in obedience
throughout his life. Iohn 17. 4. His

watchfulnes. Mat. 4. 4. 10.  as well to take
away the guiltineſſe and puniſhment of the
ſinne, and to impute freely the obedience
and bleſſing:  as to giue power to kill the
ſinne, and quicken vs to obedience.  1.
Cor. 5. 21.  Rom. 6. 2. 3. 4. 5. &amp;c.
            Thus much of that whiche is generallie
forbidden and commaunded in the body of
the Lawe. Nowe followeth what is generally
in the diuiſion generall of the lawe.
            The whole Lawe is diuided by the Lord
him ſelfe into two tables.
            The firſt doeth contayne thoſe dueties
which we owe to him directly in his ſeruice
Deut. 4. 13. and Exod. 34. 1. 2.
            The ſecond which we owe vnto our brethren.
Mat. 22. 36. Rom. 13. 8. 9.
            In this diuiſion wee are charged twoo
thinges. Firſt, that to perfect obedience of
the Lawe, we ſhould bring theſe two ſortes
of dueties ſounde and whole, as thoſe whiche
then onely are pleaſing vnto God, when
they are found togither. Mich. 6. 7. 8. 1. Ioh.
5. 2. and 4. 20. 21. Here then is forbidden,
the ſeuering of them, as ſome will ſo delight
in exerciſe of religion, as they will neglect
other dueties towardes men, as Maiſters,
Fathers, Magiſtrates, &amp;c. And ſome
ſeeke ſo to pleaſe theſe in ſeuerall dueties,

as they neglect too much the other, as reading
of the Lawe of God, hearing the word
preached, and calling it to minde beeinge
hearde, &amp;c. Both which are condemned as
vngodly and vniuſt. Rom. 24. 26. Tit. 1. 4.
The forgiueneſſe of this ſin is had in Chriſt,
who was condemned as a blaſphemer, this
righteouſnes is imputed to vs from him.
Iohn 17. 1. 34. 5. 6. &amp;c. Heb. 5. 7. 8. And with
this grace, the other, to be godly and iuſt, is
alwayes giuen. Tit. 2. 13. aud 12. 13. Hence
we are taught, that feeling ſome readines
vnto godlineſſe, we ſhould turne our ſelues
alſo to endeuour to worke iuſtice: and contrarie,
the ſeconde thing commaunded in
this diuiſion, is, we ſhould preferre loue, delight,
&amp;c. The dueties we owe to God, before
thoſe we owe to men, Mat. 22. 36. 1.
Sam. 13. 11. 12. The remedie in Chriſt accuſed
as a blaſphemer, yet ſought the glorie
of his Father, not his, Iohn 2. 17. 18. This
mercie maketh vs come to this duetie,
Actes 4. 18. 19. Here we muſt often marke
howe by ſtealth we ſhall be drawne to the
ouer louing, fearing, &amp;c. of men, &amp; in time
reſiſt it. Hitherto what is commanded and
forbidden generallie in the Lawe. Nowe
followeth the particulars in the firſt table.
            In the firſte Table are commaunded duties
vnto the Lorde,

                  
                     which we owe euery day, that are

                        to his perſon directly. Com. 1.
                        or to his worſhip.

                              the partes. 2. cō.
                              
                              the true maner of vſing thē. 3.
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  or one in ſeauen.
               
            
            In the firſt commaundement, Exod. 20.
2. 3. verſe, we muſt conſider firſt the reaſon,
then the precept. I am the Lorde thy God.
I take this to be a reaſon of the next verſe:
F
                  •
               r if it were a precept, it ſhould redounde,
ſeeing the cōtrarie being forbidden in that
which followeth this, is cōmaunded thereby
alſo. 2. It is not like the other 3. hauing
reaſons annexed, this the firſt and the
chiefeſt ſhould wante. 3. A generall authorizing
of the lawe went before. Wee maye
note the reaſons are added, to ſhewe vs our
ſinne the better, when we ſhall ſee we haue
broken not a bare precept, but a precept
perſwaded by ſuch vnanſwerable reaſons.
Alſo that when we riſe by Chriſt, we might
not onely be taught what to doo, but bee
allured to it. Thy Lord. This worde Iehoua
noteth out his being eternall, infinite, beginning
and ending of all thinges. Exod. 3.
14. Reuel. 1. 8.
            By this it appeareth, this Lawe appertayneth
to all; becauſe he is the Lorde of all.
Thy God: that is, one who doeth vouchſafe
thee a peculiar fauour, when in thy creatiō
               
he indued thee with corporall and ſpirituall
benefites, and doeth enritch thee vnto
eternall life, Pſal. 144. 15. Heb. 8. 10. Ezec.
36. 26. 32. Luke 37. 38. Heb. 11. 16. By
this appeareth, that neither we nor the Iewes
had promiſes of this lyfe onely: laſtly,
that the true fountaine of ſubiection vnto
God, is this aſſurance, He is our God, Ioſua.
24. 16. Rom. 12. 1. 1. Pet. 2. 1. Which broght.
By this we are taught the better to nouriſhe
the former roote of obedience, to call often
to remembrance the particular benefites
of God. By this appeareth that the
Lawe was giuen to the Iewes, &amp; vs, not onelie
to bring vs vnto Chriſte, but alſo to allure
&amp; inſtruct vs to obedience when Chriſt
is receyued. Thus much of the reaſon.
Nowe followeth the commaundement:
Thou ſhalt haue no ſtraunge or other Gods before
me. To haue an other God, is to ſett
vp an other whom we will acknowledge to
be of power, of goodnes, iuſtice, of ſome excellent
nature, and therefore feare, loue, reuerence,
hang on him in all eſtates, Deut.
26. 17. 18. As they looke for him to bee
their God, as aboue, ſo that where this is
wanting, eyther on the part of God, or the
people, they are called without God, Ephe.
2. 12. Not his people, Oſe. 1. 9. This the
Lord forbiddeth to be attributed vnto any

but his owne Maieſtie, becauſe he onely is
the Lord our God, and by this forbiddinge
commaundeth the contrary, that he onely
ſhould be acknowledged God, hee alone ſo
loued, feared, reuerenced, &amp;c. In this commaundement
therefore we are  firſte commaunded
the true knowledge of one true
God, then the confidence and loue &amp; feare,
&amp;c. whiche is to bee giuen to his perſon.
The true knowledge of the true God, is to
knowe his  nature ſpirituall, infinite, pure,
conſtant, moſt ſimple, &amp;c.  his properties
of power, goodnes, iuſtice, &amp;c.  the diſtinction
of three perſons in one Godhead, the
actions or workes of God,  his conſtant decree
from before all time of all things, his
wiſe and perfect execution of the ſame in
the creation &amp; the gouerning of the world,
 Iere. 24. 7. Ephe. 4. 13.  Iohn 4. 24. Iam.
1. 17.  Eſay. 33. 13.  Iohn 1. chap. ver. 8. 9.
 Dan. 4. 21. Rom. 11. 36. In this we ſhould
delight and growe as the chiefeſt knoweledge,
Iete. 9. 23. 24. Here is forbidde, firſte
Atheiſme, to perſwade our heart there is no
ſuch true God in heauen, Pſal. 14. 1. Exo. 5.
2. Mockers of him and his workes, 2.
Pet. 3. 4, 5, &amp;c. 3. Thoſe that oppone them
ſelues to the true knowledge of God, Matt.
12. 21. Actes 6. Not to acknoweledge the
loue, grace, power, &amp;c. of God, Mal. 1. 2.

Pſal. 82. 6. To denie his Iuſtice, Mal. 3. 13.
There forgiuenes of this ſinne was bought
by the ſlaunder of ignorance and blaſphemie
layde on Chriſte, and the anguiſhe of
his ſoule, whiche he felt for our erroures
laid on him: by which alſo we die vnto this
ſinne, and rayſe this part of obedience, Eph.
4. 13. After this true acknowledging of the
Lorde out of his worde, muſt proceed: firſt
a ſure confidence in the Lorde, with the
fruites of the ſame, Pſal. 100. 3. Then the
other affections of loue, reuerence, feare of
the Lorde: Alſo a ſure confidence in the
Lord, is from the aſſurance of his fauour,
to be aſſured from him onely for continual
defence, deliuerance, and ſuccour in ſoule
and body, Pſal. 27. 1. 3. and 3. 7. 9. Prou. 14.
26. From this confidence ſpringes truſt or
hope, whiche is to waite and looke for the
helpe, which in confidence wee aſſure our
ſelues of from the Lord, Pſal. 33. 18. 19. 20.
21. Yea although meanes be wanting, wee
giue glorie vnto God, Rom. 4. 20. 2. Kings,
6. 16. From hence commeth it, that we feare
not in greateſt daungers, Kin. 6. 16. Pſal. 3.
7. and 27. 3. That in the time of afflictiō, we
are patient, Prou. 20. 22. Hebr. 10. 33. Without
all murmuring to holde our peace,
Pſal. 39. 10. Receyuing them as from a father,
Iob. 1. verſe 21. Pſal. 89. 39. 49. Reioycing

in them aſſuredly, Iam. 1. 2. Hence alſo
in euery condition of lyfe to glory and
reioyce vnſpeakeably, Pſal. 13. 6. and 16. 7.
8. 9. Ioel 2. 23. Zepha. 3. 14. Here is forbidden
firſt the want of theſe, and the contrarie,
as to wauer or doubt, Pſal. 13. 1. 3. &amp; 88.
15. To leaue our hope, Heb. 10. 39. To diſpaire,
Gen. 8. 13. Impatience, Ierem. 20. 14.
18. To haue truſt in ordinarie meanes; and
to make fleſhe our arme, is forbidden, Iere.
17. 5. 6. 7 &amp;c. To glorie in theſe, and bee
proude of them, Deut. 8. 17. 2. Chron. 16. 1.
Ierem. 49. 3. 16. &amp; 2. 13. Ezech. 28. 2. 3. Eſaie
30. 12. Diffidence in binding God to means
Gen. 16. 2. Num. 14. 3. 2. King. 7. 2. Luke 1.
To feare for the ſignes of heauen, Iere. 10. 2
To cleaue too much to the holineſſe of places
and perſons diſtinct, Ierem. 7. 49. 1. Kin.
12. 18. To hope in Aſtronomers, Interpreters
of Dreames, Witches, &amp;c. Dan. 2. 2. In
Southſayers, &amp;c. Leuit. 20, 6. 7. Planet gaſers,
&amp;c. Deu. 78. verz 11. To vſe euil meanes
to doo good, 1. Kings 12. 25. 26. Rom.
3. 4. Out of this confidence farther proceedeth
a continuall carefulnes, that in all our
wayes, that is, thoughtes, wordes &amp; deedes,
&amp;c. we ſee his will, and approoue it, and ſo
for that cauſe looke for hiis blſſing and direction,
Prou. 3. 6, and 16, 3. Gen. 5. 22 and
17, 1. and 48. 15. Pſal. 146. 9. Numb, 15. 39

Here is forbidden to walke according to
our owne iudgement and wiſedome, Num.
15. 39. Gene. 11. 4. Alſo a diſtruſtfull care,
Math. 6. 25. Luke 12. 26. To this laſt of all
is adioyned humilitie, when emptying our
ſelues of all, we giue God the whole glorie
of all good thinges, which are in vs, Gene.
18. 27. 1. Pet. 5. 5. Eſai 40. 3, 4. Forbid loue
of our honour, Mat. 18. 3. 4. Vaine glorie,
Phil. 2. 3. Boaſting of any thing in vs, 1. Co.
4. 7. Preſumption, Zeph. 3. 11. 12. Hitherto
of a ſure confidence commanded in the
lawe, with thoſe things which ſpring from
the ſame, the affections commaunded here
the vſe whereof is perpetuall, are the true
loue &amp; reuerence of God. The true loue of
God is whan with all our ſoule, ſtrēgth. &amp;c.
we cleaue to the Lord aboue all, Matt. 22.
36. Hence is commanded to deſire his preſence
more viſible in heauen aboue all, and
reioyce in it aboue all, Pſal. 16, 10. 11. 2. Co.
5. 8. Here is forbidden, the loue of men,
wyues, children, or any thing of this life, to
deſire it more then the Lorde and his preſence,
Phil. 4. 18. Iohn 12. 43. Reuerence
of God, is when being ouerwhelmed with
the infinitnes and excellencie of his being,
wiſedome, ſtrength, goodnes, mercie, iuſtice,
puritie, &amp;c. we are drawne to behaue
our ſelues more ſhamefaſtlie and vprightly

in his preſence, then before the greateſt
maieſtie in the worlde, Heb. 12, 28. By this
is forbidden no reuerence, leſſe reuerence
vnto the Lord, then vnto men, as afore in
loue. The laſt is the feare of God: the feare
of God is when our  heartes are moued &amp;
troubled with this aboue all, leaſt by offence
wee ſhould  diſpleaſe our gratious Father,
and ſo purchaſe his wrath and puniſhment
proceeding from it,  Phi. 2. 12. 1. Pe.
1. 11. and 2. 17.  Heb. 4. 1. This feare differeth
from the feare of the wicked: Firſte, in
that it proceeding from faith, hath alwayes
comfort with it, and ſure hope in perſwaſiō
of the loue of God, Actes 9. 31. whiche the
wicked haue not. Secondlie, this is chiefly,
leaſt by our infirmitie, we ſhould iuſtly diſpleaſe
our God, where the wicked only trē
               ble,
becauſe of the puniſhment, 2. Cor. 7. 1.
Here is forbidden hardneſſe of hearte, &amp; no
feare, to feare any thing, as the loſſe of lyfe,
goods, friendes, diſpleaſure of men, &amp;c. equally
or more then the diſpleaſure of the
Lord, Mat, 10. 26. 28. 13. 1. Phil. 1. 18. Act.
16. 9. Apoc. 21. 8. And the vſe of this ſhall
ende when all infirmitie &amp; weakneſſe ſhall
be taken away, Apoc. 21. 4. 5. 6. Our remedie
for this our ſinne, is in the death and
righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, who beinge condemned
as proude, making him ſelf equall

with God, as louing him ſelfe more then
God, was founde meeke, humble, faithfull
and reuerent towardes his Father at all times,
1. Pet. 2. 22. 25. yet ſo as when wee receyue
him thus our righteouſnes, wee muſt
receyue him our ſanctification, that in all
theſe things we may be holy, 1. Cor. 1. 30.
1. Pet. 1. 13. to the end. Thus much of that
commandement, whiche hath preſcribed
dueties, directly teachinge to the perſon of
the Lorde.
            Now followeth that we owe him, but in
the outwarde worſhip which he hath commaunded.
And firſt of the partes of it, in the
ſeconde, then of the true vſe in the thirde.
            
               The ſeconde commaundement.
               In the ſecond commandement we haue
firſt to cōſider the precept, then the reaſon:
The Precept hath two partes, the firſt in the
fourth verſe, Exo. 20. Thou ſhalt not make
to thy ſelfe any grauen thing, or Image, or
likeneſſe of any thing in heauen aboue, &amp;c.
In which part by a vſuall maner of the law,
a part being put for the whole, as in the 6. 7
8. commandements, &amp; that one of the fowleſt
looke, to note the filthines of the reſt,
we are forbiddē generally to acknowledge,
loue, delight in, deſire, make or vſe beinge
made, any inuention of men, eyther to preſent
God, or to declare howe hee is affected

towardes vs, or to do any maner of worſhip
vnto him by, &amp; is called the whoring after
our own heart, Ier. 13. 10. &amp; 16. 13. &amp; 18. 12
&amp; 19. 5. Col. 2. 22. 23. Eſa. 29. 13. Mat. 15. 8.
Now by the cōtrarie is commanded, to acknowledge,
loue, deſire, delight in, and outwardly
practiſe all thoſe partes of his worſhip,
which he in his worde hath commanded,
Deu. 12. 32. Ioh. 4. 22. 2. King. 17. 26.
In the ſecond in like maner is forbidden by
one ſorte to acknowledge, loue, &amp;c. any other
vſe of any rite or outward meanes vſed
in the worſhip or ſeruice of god, thē he hath
ordained, Ioh. 4. 22. 2. kin. 18. 4. By the contrarie
cōmanded to acknowledge, loue, &amp;c.
only the proper vſe of euery rite &amp; outward
meanes which the Lorde hath ordayned: ſo
to receyue the Sacraments as pledges of our
coniunction with Chriſt, the remiſſion of
ſinnes in him, &amp;c. not to make them a ſacrifice
for the quick &amp; dead, not to bow down
&amp; worſhip thē: ſo to receiue the Miniſters as
the meſſengers of God, to recōcile vs by the
goſpel, to forgiue vs our ſinns by the word,
to command vs our dutie, &amp;c. But yet as inſtruments,
2. Cor. 5. 18. Matth. 18. 18. And
therefore may not worſhip thē, ſacrifice to
them, &amp;c. Acts. 10. 16. &amp; 14. 13. And this is
the true ſenſe of the commaundement.
               Nowe let vs ſee what particulars are forbidden,

and what commaunded. Firſt wee
ſee forbiddē in the firſt part, the making of
Images, to liken God, or to worſhip him,
whether grauen or painted, Rō. 4. 12. Ezec.
8. 10. Ioh. 5. 21. No Image of God muſt bee
made,  becauſe he is a ſpirit, nor of Chriſt
 becauſe pictures &amp; images are teachers of
lies, neither thoſe nor any other ſuch ſhold
be ſuffered in the Church, or at home,  becauſe
wee are inſtructed ſufficiently in the
Goſpell,  Exod. 33. 24. Rom. 1. 23.  Ier. 10
8. Aba. 2. 18. 19.  Gal. 3. 4. 1. Cor. 4. 6. 2. Ti.
3. 17. Forbidden in the 2. parte, to worſhip
Images, to ſet them vp, to gilde them, or anie
maner of way to ſerue them, Mat. 4. 10.
Apo. 19. 20. Alſo here is forbidden all additions
of Sacramentes, as the papiſtes made
matrimonie, and ſo gaue it a ſigne of the
wedding Ring, all additions vnto them, 1.
Cor. 11. 13. All additiō of miniſteries in the
ſeruice of the Lorde, as the papiſtes added
prieſtes to ſacrifice, exorciſts to coniure, &amp;c
Luke 20. 6. Iohn. 1. 21. 22. 23. Alſo mens
traditions &amp; ceremonies brought into the
church, not being to edifying, not for comlines,
not for order, &amp;c. 1. Cor. 14. &amp; 10.
Mat. 15. 8. Secondly, in this commaundement
other ſortes of particulars are forbidden,
as al meanes, occaſions, or appertenances
of Idolatrie, whereby ſome ſhewe, or remembrance

or reuerence is kept, Pſal 16. 4.
As all mariages, coniunctions, or neare familiaritie
with Idolaters, 2. Cor. 6. 14. Deut.
17. 3. 4. 2. Chro. 19. 1. 2. Gen. 24. 3. &amp; 28. 1.
&amp; 34. 14. Likewiſe all reliques of Idolatrie,
which we muſt pollute and marre, not dooing
any ſeruice or honor, no not giuing thē
any eſtimation, 2. Cor. 6. &amp; 17. Eſai. 30. 22.
2. Chron. 29. 5. Hitherto of certaine particulars
forbidden. Nowe followe ſome
commaunded, as the outwarde meanes,
which the Lorde hath commaunded in his
worde: They are of two ſortes,
               eyther

                     ſuch as the Lorde commandeth
vs to giue him for his honor:
                     or thoſe whiche he giueth vs to
vſe in his ſeruice, Eſai 45. 23.
                  
               
               Of the firſte ſorte, are

                     ordinarie, which are ſeueral actions of
our body, chriſtiāly according to the
cuſtome of the church, cōmanded in
the worde of God, and orderly and
reuerently ordered in his ſeruice.
                     Speciall, the fruite of the lippes, in

                           Prayer and Thankſgiuing Heb. 13. 15. Dan. 6. 11. Pſal. 55. 18.
                        
                     
                     Extraordinary faſting.
                  
               
               Of the actions of the bodie orderly and
reuerently vſed, are bowing of our bodies,
Eſa. 45. 23. Reuerent attention declared

ſometimes by riſing vp, Ge. 49. 33. 1 Chro.
28. 2. Num. 23. 22. 2. Kin. 23. 2. 2. Chron. 34
31. Neh. 8. 6. Alſo lifting vp of the hands &amp;
eyes, &amp;c. Pſa. 123. 1. &amp; 141. 2. For euen as a
huſband looketh that he alone ſhold haue
not only the heart, but alſo the reuerent &amp;
louing behauior of the body, 1. Pet. 3. 6. Ge.
26. 8. So the Lord requireth theſe, both as
teſtimonies of our ſinceritie, as alſo helpes
of our infirmitie, when wee may cōuenientlie
vſe them, and forbiddeth to doe in like
maner to any beſides him. The great careleſneſſe
and negligence in theſe, and the
fruite of the lippes in prayer, and prayſe of
the Lord, is condemned by the example of
Salomon, 1. King. 8. 22. Dan. 6. 11. And of
Chriſt, Mark 7. 34. Matth. 26. 36. To theſe
ſometimes alſo to helpe when our prayers,
and confeſſions, and hearings, &amp;c. muſt bee
more earneſt and liuely: becauſe our great
ſinnes, neceſſities, &amp;c. Then is faſtinge added,
which  is a profeſſiō of our repentāce
by abſtinence,  inſtituted of the Lorde, for
 better humbling of our ſelues in prayer,
for ſome eſpeciall grace, as is ſet foorth in
the booke intituled, The deſcription of the
exerciſe of faſtinge,  2. Sam. 12. 16. 17.
Eſd. 10. 6. Leui. 23. 23. Iudg. 20. 26.  Leuit.
23. 14. 27. Ioel. 2. 15. Luk. 5. 33. Acts. 13. 2. 3.
 Math. 9. 15. Ioel. 2. 12. 17. 1. Sam. 7. 6.

And thus much of thoſe which the Lorde
in mercie and wiſedome receyueth of vs.
Nowe followeth thoſe meanes whiche hee
hath giuen vs, and they are

                     either attributed vnto the Lord him ſelfe directly,
as his titles to be
vſed 
                           either ſimply, Rō. 95 1. Tim. 1. 17.
in an oth, deu. 6. 13. Ier. 12.26. Eſa. 18. 18.
                           Or his
workes.
                        
                     
                     or giuen of him by mā his miniſtrie his word, Sacraments,
&amp; order of the Church.
                  
               
               His workes are giuen, not to worſhippe
them, which is forbidden, Deu. 4. 12. But to
ſee and beholde and praiſe in them his wiſdome,
goodnes, power, &amp;c. Pſal. 67. 13. and
104. 1. &amp; 107. 42. Pſal. 64. 10. 11. His word
he hath giuen, that we ſhould read and meditate
in the ſame day and night, to confer
of it with our wyues, children, ſeruauntes,
priuately at home, Deu. 6. 7. Pſal. 1. 1. &amp; 119.
55. The Sacramentes alſo hath he giuen
not to be neglected, as moſt excellent pledges
of his ſure fauour and mercie in Chriſt
Rom. 4. 11. and 6. 3. 4. Ephe. 5. 26. 1. Cor. 11
23. The order of his Church ſet downe in
his worde, Heb. 3. 2. 1. Chron. 28, 12, 19. &amp;
2. Chron. 29. 25. and 1. Chro. 15. 13. 1. Co.
9. 8 For ruling of his Church, by his worde,

Rulers who haue the care of ſoules committed
to them, Heb. 13. 17. Iames 5. 14.
Actes 14. 23. And ſome of them  to labor
alſo in the worde,  one by teaching, an other
by exhorting,  ſome to attende vnto
maners, watchinge ouer the people to admoniſhe
them, to comfort them, to praye
with them when they bee in diſtreſſe, &amp;c.
 and to ioyne with the others in the reſt of
the gouerning of the Church.  1. Tim. 5.
17. 1. Cor. 12. 28. Rom. 12. 8.  Ephe. 4. 11
 1. Theſ. 5. 12. 13. 14. Iames 5. 41.  1. Tim.
4. 14. Act. 15. 6. &amp; 21. 18. Mat. 18. 17. Alſo
for the better relieuing of the poore, diſtributers
of the Church reliefe, Act. 6. 2. Rō.
12. 8. 1. Tim. 3. 7. &amp;c. All which wee muſte
knowe, delight in it, procure, and euerie
one according to his calling ſett forwarde,
as Pſal. 27. 4. &amp; 42. 23. 1. Chron. 13. 1. &amp; 29
6, 7, 8, 9. &amp;c. 2. Chron. 15. 3. 12. 13. &amp; 29. 30
Hag. 1. 4. &amp; 14. In all theſe thinges commaunded
&amp; forbidden we may eaſily feele
ſeuerall ſinnes and corruptions, by due examination
of our ſelues ſeuerallie in euerie
one: but Chriſte hath by his death ſatisfied
for our ſinnes, Rom. 4, 25. and  hath bene
zealous in the obedience of the partes of
this lawe, that in him we may haue perfect
obediēce,  yet ſo, as by his death, we more
and more dye vnto theſe ſinnes, and by his

reſurrection be made liuely to ſerue the
Lord ſincerely according to his will.  Ioh.
2. 14. 15. Mark. 7. 34. Math. 26. 38. &amp; 27. 30.
 2. Cor. 6. 14. to the ſecond verſe of cap.. 7
Hitherto of the commaundement it ſelfe.
               Now foloweth the reaſon, which is drawn
from a double propertie of the Lorde:
his Ielouſie in wrath, and his mercie. For I
the Lord thy God. i Euen then being ioyned
vnto thee by my mercifull couenaunt, as a
huſband to his wife, Chap. 19. 6. A ſtrong
God. The firſt title is added to note his great
power, to doe what hee will, ſo that being
preſwaded in the firſte propertie of his readineſſe
to puniſhe, and in the ſecond of his
readines to reward. And firſt in this of his
power we neede not to doubt at all, &amp; ſuch
vſe we ſhould make of his Titles. Pſal. 2. 12.
115. 3. 10. Iealous. This is a kinde of ſpeach
taken from married folkes, Hoſ. 2. 2. Ezech
16. who cannot abide their wiues, ſhoulde
giue either in affectiō, or in geſture, countenaunce
or any manner of behauiour to others,
that which appertaineth to them onely:
and by this wee gather the greatneſſe
of the ſinnes, eyther of groſſe Idolatrie,
or any countenaunce vnto it.
               This Ielouſie he ſetteth further forth by the
fruite that the Lord puniſheth ſeuerely this
ſin. Viſitinge iniquitie. i puniſhing this ſinne

or the tranſgreſſiō of this law in diſſoluing
this holy bande: for ſo the generall worde
Iniquitie, and euill is taken ſomtimes for
ſome ſpeciall great ſinne, as Deut. 17. 2. Pſal.
78. 39. And here it appeareth that it muſt be
ſo taken, becauſe it is not a reaſon of the
whole lawe, but of this cōmandement only
This is further declared by the perſons
on whom it falleth. The thrd and fourth generation.
which is both becauſe by the fathers
ſinne diſanulling the couenaunt by Idolatrie,
the child falleth out of the ſame,
&amp; continuing in that fall, is puniſhed iuſtly
for his owne ſinne, and his fathers both.
Mat. 23. 25. And therefore that which is added
declareth thoſe which are puniſhed.
Thoſe that hate me. That is thoſe that ſecurely
cōmit ſpiritual whoredom againſt this
cōmandement: and ſo this is nothing contray
to that. Ezech. 18. Exerciſing benignitie.
This is the ſeconde propertie wherein the
Lorde declareth his reward towardes the
keeper of this Law, that is, free liberalitie or
bountie (for ſo the word ſignifieth) in receiuing
them into a couenant of lyfe and
bleſſedneſſe, yea &amp; that eternall. Act. 2. 37.
Out of this wee learne that as a childe to his
father, when wee ſhall do all that is commaunded,
wee are  but vnprofitable ſeruants,
and haue done but our dutie: &amp; as if

our father leaue vs no patrimonie, are wee
leſſe bound to do our duetie, ſo if the Lord
had not bound himſelfe by his couenant,
which came from his free and vndeſerued
goodnes, could we haue claymed any thing
by fulfilling, becauſe wee did but our dutie,
for the mercie of creating vs in great dignitie
according to his owne likenes in holines
and righteouſnes. But now hauing ſo many
times offended ſince the knoweledge of his
grace, and lying in his wrath, both by natural
corruption and continuall ſeruing of ſinne
from the ſame dailie, how is it not mercie
onely, without all deſeruing, when he
giueth vs by  imputation the righteouſnes
of his Son, and ſo eternal life: and thē tranſforming
vs vnto his likenes againe, when
we are firſt ſet freely in poſſeſſion of eternall
ioy?  Luke. 7. 6. 7. 8.  Rom. 6. 15. to the
20.  Tit. 2. 12. 13. 14. This is enlarged by
the perſons to whome this is graunted. To
thouſand generations, which ſheweth that the
Lorde in reſpect of vs ſetteth his mercie aboue
his iuſtice. But hee ſetteth them forth
by their fruites that be pertakers of it. That
loue him, and keepe his commandements. By
loue hee noteth that this ſhould bee the
fountaine from which the outwarde obedience
of this commandement ſhould ſpring,
ſo that if that we loue not, delight not, in

the partes of his worſhip, becauſe in trueth
we loue him and his glory. Theſe thinges
are abhominable. Iohn. 14. 23. His commandements.
Here as iniquitie was put for the
ſpiritual whordome againſt this cōmaundement,
ſo commaundementes are put for
the ſeueral parts of obedience in this precept
as the circumſtance of the place doth ſhew,
by which wee ſee all good intentes are ſhut
out. As they haue bene ſeuerely puniſhed of
the Lord. Deut. 4. 15. Eſay. 30. 21. 1. Chron.
15. 13. &amp; 2. Chron. 13. 10. 11.
               Hetherto of that commandement which
hath preſcribed vs the ſeueral partes or outward
means which we muſt loue, deſire, &amp;c.
in his worſhip, which we giue him.
            
            
               3. Commaund.
               In this commandement as afore we muſt
conſider, firſt the percept, then the reaſon.
The precept is, Thou ſhalt not take the
name of the Lorde thy God in vaine.And ſo by ſimilitude is applied to the taking of his name with. ourtongue, handes. or any vſe of it. 
                  Take,
that is: make any vſe: for the word ſignifieth
to take up, or lift vp on our ſhoulders.
The name of God is his memorial amongſt
men which being in his titles moſt properly
is geuin to them, whether drawne from
his nature as Iehouah the Lorde, or his properties,
iuſt, holy, mercifull, &amp;c. The God of
Abraham, Iacob, &amp;c. Exod. 3, 15. Hence becauſe
the Lorde in excellencie is remēbred

in his workes, by likenes they are called his
name. Pſal. 8. 2. 2. Chro. 6. 32.. Much more
his Goſpell. Acts. 9. 15. His Sacramentes.
Mar. 5. 6. Alſo true praier is the honouring
of his name, &amp; euil the prophaning of the
ſame. Ge. 4. 26. Mal. 1. 11. 12. Therfore here
he comprehendeth al theſe, and forbiddeth
to vſe vainely, that is, vnreuerently &amp; raſhly
falſly, or hypocritically, lightly and vnprofitably,
all which are vttered by the Hebrew
word: ſo that by the contrary here is commaunded
to know, allowe, loue deſire, and
practiſe the true vſe of GOD his name in
all the outward meanes of his worſhippe, by
being prepared reuerently to take it vp, by
bringing the proper affections in the vſe of
it, and by ſhooting at that moſt profitable
end, which he hath appointed for euery one
Al which we muſt conſider in euery of them
ſeuerally and firſt in thoſe things, which hauing
imprinted his name in them, hee hath
giuen vs, and thoſe which are directly attributed
to him, his titles, and workes. His
titles according to the double vſe of them
ſimply, or in an othe hath double caution
ſet downe in the word. In the ſimple vſe we
muſt be prepared either by premeditation,
or els by ſome occaſion going afore, which
doeth ſtirre vp the ſeuerall affections of the
heart in the vſe of them. Rom. 9. 5. 1. Tim. 4▪
                  
17. 2. Chron. 24. 22. Here is forbidden the
vſuall taking vp of the titles of God, not
hauing our affection prepared to the reuerent
vſe of them: by any of theſe meanes, the
proper affection here muſt be according to
the title and vſe of it, as in the example of
Zach. 2. Chron. 24 22.. Being lead by the
occaſion of their vniuſt &amp; vnmercifull dealing
with him, had a full perſwaſion &amp; feeling
of the ſight and iuſtice of the Lord. &amp;
ſo made vſe of that glorious title the Lord
to terrifie them, &amp; to bring them to repentaunce.
The vſe of his titles muſt bee eithet
to ſet forth directly the honour of God: his
nature, power, mercie, iuſtice, &amp;c. as Rom.
9. 5. Tit. 2. 13. Or to make profitte vnto
men either our  ſelues, or others  to bee
more moued with the feeling, of the  mercie,
 iuſtice,  power,  authority of the
lord in any weightie matter, to be ſtrengthned
amongſt vs.  Pſal 3. 4. &amp; 20. 8. &amp; 118.
12. 1. Chron. 17. 27. Acts. 10. 33.  
                   1.
Chron 29. 20. Luke 1. 28. Eſay. 12. 2.  2.
Theſ. 2. 8.  Gen. 17. 1.  Exo. 3. 15. 1. &amp; 1. 10
Here is forbidden the vſe of the name of
God, when we haue no ſuch end, as wee do
commonly at euery trifle, if but vnawares
wee let fall a thing, or when wee vtter ſome
troubled affection, as Gene, 15. 5. Or a falſhood
is cōfirmed, as Gen. 27. 22. 2. Sam. 16

Or in blaſphemy. Leuit, 14. 11. When wee
vſe the name of God in an oath, according
to the excellencie of this dutie, wee muſt be
diligently prepared by earneſt &amp; ſufficient
conſideration of the perſon of the Lorde, to
whoſe iudgement we commit our ſelues, of
the cauſe &amp; matter where about we ſweare
with all other circumſtances appertaining
thereto. Eccle. 5. 2. Gene. 24. 5. Wherto appertained
the ceremonie of lifting vp their
handes vnto the Lorde, which called them
to minde with whom they had in this cauſe
to deale. Gene. 14. 22. So ſomtimes they
added or put it ſteede of the creatures of
lyfe, heauē, earth, afflictions, or ſnfferings
not to giue the honour of an oath vnto thē
which were abhominable. Deut. 6. 13. Eſay.
18. 18. 1. Kings. 8. 31. Heb. 16. 17. But to affect
their hearts the more with reuerence of
him, his glory of power, or mercy, or iuſtice,
which were moſt ſenſible in thoſe thinges.
1. Sam. 20 3. Math. 5. 34. 1. Cor. 15. 31. To
which, if the names of Idolles be added, as
it taketh away this vſe, ſo it is abhominable.
Hag. 8. 14. Zephan. 1. 5. Here is forbidden
all careleſſe ruſhing to othes, without due
conſideratiō, yea though the cauſes be iuſt.
Eccle. 9. 4. Iere. 4. 2. The ſecond thing is,
with all reuerent behauiour in the action it
ſelfe, to haue a ſincere and vpright hart, as

wel in the feare of God to hallow his name,
as to helpe the trueth in neceſſitie: which is
called ſwearing in trueth. Iere. 4. 2. The
ende is to make knowne a very weightie
trueth, which cannot by any other meanes
bee ſo conueniently knowne, And this is
to ſweare for a iuſt cauſe. Iere. 4. 2. Hebr. 6.
16. Here againe is forbidden raſh and common
oathes, not taken vp for ſuch a cauſe.
Eccle. 9. 4. Math. 5. 34. Falſe oathes, Periurie.
Leu. 19. 12. Deu. 5. 11. And thus much
of titles. Now followeth of the workes
of God. For the workes of God, any
ſpeciall preparation, beſides that which is
not generall, I haue not found. The affectiō
which is proper in the diligēt conſideration
of thē is great reuerence and ſweete feeling
of the glory of God, which any manner of
way is found in them. Pſal. 64. 9. 10. &amp; 104.
34. Wee contrariwiſe either wholly neglect
thē, as Eſa. 6. 12. or elſe in lightnes, ieſting,
&amp;c. in which ſort wee ſpeak ſomtime of women,
ſomtime of holy matrimonie, yea
ſomtime of the ioyes of heauen, &amp; paines of
hell, making fooliſh &amp; vaine playes of theſe
thinges. The vſe or ende of all the worke
of the Lorde towardes him, to preach and
ſet forth the power and glory of the eternall
kingdome of God. Pſal. 145. 11. 12. To vs,
that wee and our poſteritie may better

know, truſt, loue, and feare the Lorde, Pſal.
78. 7. Deut. 4. 9. But contrariwiſe, we neuer
make any ſuch vſe, but harden our hartes
againſt all his workes, both of iuſtice and
mercie, thereby declaringe our palpable
blindnes in ſuch light, Pſal. 111. 2. &amp; 92. 6.
7. &amp; 10. 5. And thus much for the true ſanctifying
of the name of god, in thoſe things
which are directlie attributed vnto him.
Nowe followeth the other in the priuate
exerciſe of his worde in reading, cōferring,
&amp;c. We muſt be prepared in our hartes, by
a great reuerence of the moſt heauenlie,
moſt conſtant and profitable wiſedome of
the Lorde for vs, conteined therein, Pſalm.
119. 129. By a ſure hope to finde vnderſtā
                  ding
in the plaine light of the Lorde, Pſal.
119. 130. Pro. 8. 9. By an earneſt prayer vnto
the Lord for the true vnderſtanding, feeling,
and practiſe of the ſame, proceeding
frō a hungry ſoule after theſe graces, Pſal.
119. 131, &amp;c. Here is condemned our great
want in all theſe things, which come commonly
at all aduenture, without any due
conſideration of this moſt holy exerciſe, in
the reading, conferring, &amp;c. it ſelfe, we muſt
drawe our whole ſoule to marke, weigh, &amp;
attende vpon wholy, which is ſet foorth by
lifting vp our hands vnto the Lawe, to meditate
in it, by ſearching and 
                     •••…
                  inge, &amp;c.

Pſal. 119. 48. Alſo a bowing down to looke
vnto it, Iam. 1. 25. Pſal. 119. 15. To encline
our heart to vnderſtandinge, to crye after
wiſedome, to ſearch for it as for hidd treaſure,
Pro. 2. 3. Here againe our great coldnes,
wauering mindes, and multitude of other
like infirmities is condemned. The end
is. that we may apply all vnto ourſelues, examine
our hattes by it, and ſo in callinge on
the Lord, wholy to endeuour our ſelues to
put it in practiſe, Pſal. 19. 26. 27. and 59. 60.
Pro. 2. 1. Here is condemned the prophane
abuſinge of the ſame in ieſtes, playes, &amp;c.
Pro. 13. 13. 14. In the order of the Church,
as the meanes are more glorious and exellent,
ſo wee muſte prepare our ſelues more
earneſtly on euery ſide, Eccle. 5. 1. To the
Lord, in the perſon of the Miniſter whō wee
muſt receyue as the Lorde, Rom. 10. 15. 2.
Cor. 5. 19. 20. Speaking his worde truely,
Deut. 18. 18. 19.  Or admoniſſing, or  interpreting,
 or cenſuring,  1. Theſ. 5. 12.
 Deut. 17. 10. 11.  Mat. 18. 17. In them ſelues,
that they ſifte their heartes to receyue
with pure affection, the true vſe of them ſeuerallie
in the exerciſe it ſelfe, reuerentlie
behauing our ſelues accordinge to the nature
of it, and in our heartes to feele the power
and force of them: afterwarde alſo to
vſe all this to the ſeuerall profit and end for

which theſe are ordained, as wee will ſhewe
in ſome of the principall particulars. In the
exerciſe of the worde preached, beeing the
way to  open trueth to our iudgement and
vnderſtanding, to  plant it, and roote it in
our harts and affections. We are commanded
to put away all other things out of our
minde, and all ſuperfluitie, or malice, or filthines
whatſoeuer, and be readie and ſwifte
to heare, yea and to receiue the word of the
Lorde by his miniſter his huſbandman is
readie to engraft in our ſoules, Iames. 1. 18.
Luke 8. 18.  Luk. 14. 27. 32.  Rom. 10. 15.
and 12. 8. Act. 26. In the action it ſelfe, wee
muſt with  all attentiuenes ſo giue our
hartes, as we muſt haue a preſent  touch &amp;
feeling of thoſe things whiche are deliuered,
that  in promiſes wee may reioyce, receyue
comforte and ſtrength: in his threatninges,
we may throughly feele our owne
eſtate and miſerie, &amp; ſo be humbled for the
ſame,  Pſal. 78. 1.  1. Theſ. 2. 13.  Nehe. 8.
8. 10. and 13. Actes 2. 37. The vſe afterward
is  by repeating, examining by the ſcripture,
and applyinge to bring to practiſe of
life and conuerſation.  Theſ. 5. 20, Act. 17.
11.  In the preparation is forbidden the
great looſenes, and careleſnes of men once
to thinke about what they are,  The vnreuerence
&amp; little regarde of the mightie furniture

of the Lorde in his ſeruants,  yea &amp;
ſometimes the captious, proude, ſtuborne,
and malicious purpoſe in hearing,  Eccl. 5
1. Exod. 19. 9.  2. Cor. 10. 5. 6.  Act. 2. 13.
1. King. 21. 20. and 22. 28. In the action it
ſelfe, we ſee by that is forbidden, our heades
full of other matters, running vpon our profites,
pleaſurs, &amp;c. the great hypocriſie of manie,
who taking ſome delight in the thing
outwardlie, haue no true feelinge wrought
by it, when they heare, Ezech. 33. 31. 32.
The brawny and fat heart, which being neuer
a whit moued, neuer or to ſmall purpoſe
repeateth, examiēth, applyeth, or practiſeth,
Ezech. 33. 31. Zeph. 2. 1. 2. Sam. 12.
Marke 6. 20. In the Sacramentes, the preparation
is an examination of our fayth in
Chriſt, 1. Cor. 11. 28. Iob. 1. 5. Of repentance.
Eſa. 1. 16. &amp; 66. 2. Specially alſo in reconciliation
of our brother. Math. 5. 2.
Here great ignorance, ſlouthfulnes, blokiſhnes,
which without all awe and reuerence to
preſume to partake the ſame to our great
iudgement. 1. Cor. 11. 28. Gene. 4. 5. 7. In the
Action or worke it ſelfe, wee muſte feele a
moſt ſweete and ſure confirmation of our
faith of receyuing of Ieſus Chriſt with his
wiſedome, righteouſnes, ſanctification and
redemption, that by the liuely feeling of
this, we ſhould bee throughly inflamed to

giue prayſe and thankes vnto the Lorde
with the Church. Mat. 26. 30. The vſe is after
in all temptations to receyue comfort &amp;
reliefe by them, Pſal. 51. 9. Of one correction,
for the reſt, as of excommunication: the
preparation is by the authoritie and maieſtie
of Chriſt, the action a fearfull ſentence
with Maieſtie, iuſtly prouounced, the
vſe for the ſleaing of the fleſhe, that the ſpirite
might be ſaued in the day of the Lord,
1. Cor. 5. 4. 5. The reaſon followeth: for he
will not holde him innocent that taketh
his name in vaine. That is, he will condemne
him, as Saint Iames and Saint Paule
write, the one againſt raſh ſwearing, &amp; the
other of the abuſe of the Sacramentes interpreteth,
Aboue all things ſweare not my
brethren, &amp;c. leaſt you fall into condemnation,
Iam. 5. 12. 1. Cor. 11. 29. 34.
            
            
               4. Commaund.
               Hitherto thoſe precepts, which cōmand
dueties in the worſhip of the Lorde, whiche
we owe euery day vnto him.
               Nowe followeth that duetie whiche one
day in ſeauen muſt be giuen vnto the Lord,
in the ſanctification of his Saboth. Remember,
So he ſeemeth to ſpeake, becauſe when
as this commandement was before giuen,
they had neglected the ſame. The Saboth
day to ſanctifie, that is, to ſeparate it from a

common vſe, and dedicate it to a peculiar
and holy vſe vnto the Lord. So the golde,
the veſſels, &amp;c. were ſaide to be holy and dedicated
for the holy vſe of the Temple, and
might not be giuen or put to any other vſe:
To ſanctifie a Saboth therefore, is to call
our ſelues, not from our owne ſinful wayes,
which we muſt doe euery day, but frō out
honeſt and lawfull callings, that giuing our
ſelues to godly and chriſtianly exerciſes of
our fayth, wee may bee ſtrengthened in the
wayes of God, and ſo in thought, word, and
deede conſecrate a glorious Saboth vnto
the Lord. Therefore it is called the Saboth
of God, Exod. 20. 10. and Leui. 23. 3. He calleth
it a holy conuocation, that is, dedicated
to holy meetings. So Eſai 58. 13. Hereby
is confuted their opinion that take it a
Saboth kept, if thei reſt from their labours,
ſo in the meane time they labour in playes,
dauncings, vaine ſonges and enterluds, &amp;c.
as though the Lord had called vs from our
profitable labour commanded, to diſpleaſe
him in theſe vanities. Againe others alſo
who if they be better then the former, abſtayning
from thoſe things, haue notwithſtanding
their heades, hartes, and mouthes,
ſo full of worldly things, as they doe not in
deede performe the trueth of the Saboth,
when as it ſhould be kept as the reſt of the

Lawe, not onely in action, but alſo in the
thoughtes of the heart and wordes of the
mouth. Eſa. 58. Amos. 8. 5. But before wee
come to the proper and peculiar exerciſes,
we will ſet downe reaſons that proue it perpetuall
for the Church in this worlde, to
haue one ſuch day in ſeauen to bee dedicated
vnto the Lord, that ſo we may haue the
vſe of it in our conſcience, and of the ceremonie
ceaſed I will ſpeake in the ende.
Firſt becauſe of the couenaunt of the lawe,
which biddeth vs doe and ſo liue thereby,
driuing vs vnto Chriſt, Rom. 10. 5. There
are ten partes, called ten wordes or ſentences,
of which if we take away this, there wil
be but nine, Exod. 34. 18. Secondly, if Adam
being in his ſoundnes, becauſe his
minde not being infinite, could not doe
 his worke,  and prayſe God, pray to him,
meditate in his creatures of his wiſedome,
mercie, &amp;c. had neede for that purpoſe,
wholy to giue him ſelfe ouer more fullie
then he did by times in other dayes once in
ſeauen dayes: howe much more hauing in
vs ſo much ignorāce, hardnes of heart, &amp;c.
that wee might helpe our weaknes, and
growe forwarde?  
                   Gene. 2. 3. 15. Thirdly,
when this was a piece of the image of God
in him, that he did not onely thoſe daily duties
after mentioned togither with tillinge

and keeping the garden, Gene. 2. 15. euery
day, but was further able one whole daye in
ſoule and body to giue ouer him ſelfe to the
former Saboth, exerciſe of praying, prayſing,
&amp;c. eyther wee muſt not knowe, and
not be borne againe to this piece of excellencie,
or els we muſt haue this peculiar cō
                  maundement
to humble vs, and in this
poynt to driue vs vnto Chriſt, afterward alſo
be a rule and ſquare vnto vs of the ſame.
Fourthly, the Apoſtles in taking this daye,
and giuing it the name of the Lordes day,
Apoc. 1. 10. as before that was called the
Lords Saboth, and ordayning publike exerciſes,
Actes 10. 7. and priuate, 1. Cor. 4. 2.
As they did ſhewe that in the particular ſeauenth
day it was ceremoniall: ſo in the cō
                  mon
neceſſitie it was perpetuall accordinge
to the foreſaide equitie. Laſt of all, as Caluin
ſayeth vnto the papiſtes, of the ſeconde
commaundement, who alſo ſaide, that was
ceremoniall and aboliſhed▪ as long as wee
feele the groſenes of our nature to inuente
falſe worſhip, framing Images of God: ſo
long that muſt remaine to humble vs, euen
ſo, as long as we doe feele our corruption,
in accounting the Saboth vnpoſſible, and
ſo omitting and prophaning it, ſo long wee
will holde it to be perpetuall. Now the
Lorde to helpe our infirmities, hath giuen

vs varietie of profitable exerciſes to bee occupied
in, and to recreate vs as it were in an
other, being weary of one.
               They are either

                     Publike Nehem. 8. 5. 13.
                     or Priuate. Nehem. 8. 5. 13.
                  
               
               Publike is to ioyne with the church from
the beginning to the endinge in the hearing
of the word preached, in praying, and
adminiſtring of the Sacramentes. Eze. 46. 1.
2. 3. 10. Nehe. 9. Eſd. 3. Act. 15. 20. 21. &amp; 17.
1. &amp; 18. 4. Luke 4. 11. 2. Kings 4. 23. Priuate
exerciſes are for our ſelues to encreaſe godlines,
for others their comfort. Nehe. 8. 13.
               Of the firſt ſort are reioicing in the worde
receyued, and profiting by that. Alſo meditations,
conference, &amp;c. on the workes of
God, that ſo wee might not onely by doctrine,
but by experience be taught, and ſo
be brought to greater feeling, as is commaunded,
Deut. 5. 20. For other, we are cō
                  manded
dueties of loue in relieuinge, and
comfortinge the needie, as well bodily by
our helpe, as ſpiritually by comfort and cō
                  ference
out of the worde, edifying one another
in our moſt holy fayth, 1. Corin. 14. 2.
Mat. 12. In theſe things our contempt, and
neglect both of the mercie of the Lorde,
who hath ordayned ſo many good meanes
to increaſe our knowledge, our feelinge in
the faith and good workes, his wiſedome,

who hauing regarde to our weaknes, hath
giuen vs ſuch great varietie, that alwayes
being wearie of the one, we may breath our
ſelues in the other. In this as in the reſt,
and the commaundement going before, we
muſt haue the ſinnes forgiuen in the ſonne
of God his obedience here, Luk. 13. 10. to
the 18. verſe, Luke 13. 4. 5. In him alſo wee
muſt receyue power with this former grace
to die vnto this ſinne, and riſe vnto this part
of obedience.
               Nowe followeth the reaſon whereby he
doeth both make plaine the obedience, and
allure vs vnto it. He allureth, becauſe hee
giueth this equitie perpetuall, that ſeeinge
in ſixe dayes wee may doe all our worke,
which is neceſſarie for the maintenance of
this life, and prouiſion of our families, whiche
is declared by theſe oppoſitions in the
9. and 10. verſes. Six dayes thou ſhalt work,
but the ſeauenth is the reſt or Saboth of the
Lorde thy God. In ſixe dayes doe all thy
worke, in the ſeauenth doe no worke, but
of the Saboth. Mat. 12. 5. The Saboth vnto
the Lorde, Here, as in that afore, are the papiſtes
confuted, who ordayned Saboths to
Saintes and Angels, a worſhip due to the
Lorde onely, who alſo tooke away this libertie
of ſixe dayes wholy, and too often.
               
                  No manner of worke, except for frugall neceſſitie

of putting on of appareil, of meate,
drinke, &amp;c. whiche muſte bee as meanes to
helpe and ſuccour the weakenes of tender
and olde age, the ſtrength of ſtrong men in
this exerciſe, who if they ſhould ordinarely
abſtayne on that day from theſe thinges, it
would make them much vnable to accompliſhe
that worke of the Lorde, and ſo it is
expounded, Luke 13. 15. Wherefore that of
Exod. 35. 3. was a rudiment ceremoniall,
whereby they were inſtructed to the reuerence
of the ſame, when as otherwiſe they
might doe great things. This is further declared
by a diſtribution of the efficient cauſes.
Thou, nor thy Sonne, nor thy Daughter, nor
thy Seruaunt. By which wee ſee we doe not
rightlie obſerue the Saboth, except all with
in our gates, that is, our authoritie, (ſo called,
becauſe they bound the proper place of
euery man where he exerciſeth any authoritie)
doe likewiſe ſanctifie the ſame. The
ſecond reaſon is drawne from the example
of the Lorde him ſelfe, the more to allure
vs and moue vs, who contende to come
neere the excellent. ſo Chriſte gaue an example
for vs to followe. For the Lord made
heauen and earth in ſix dayes, but the ſeauenth
he rested. By that ſeuenth day, hee poynteth
out the Iewes Saboth, the ſeauenth from
the creation, to the which day they were

neuer preciſely tyed, becauſe being the ſeauenth
it carried a note of perfection, and ſo
did ſhadowe out the excellencie of our reſt
vnder Chriſt, Heb. 4. 20. and therefore becauſe
that was ceremoniall, that proper day
was pointed out to Adam, Gen. 2.
               Whereas if this had not bin ceremoniall, he
had not needed, becauſe the morall equitie
of one in ſeuen, was written in his heart, as
aboue hath bene noted. And thus as it was
a figure of our ſanctification and adoption,
it was not a piece of the first table, but rather
generall to the whole lawe, and therefore
in that reſpect is aboliſhed. Col. 2. 16.
               The end of the firſt Table.
               All glorie to the Lord.
               
            
         
      
   

