
   
      
         
            Resolues, diuine, morall, politicall b Owin Felltham
            Resolves
            Felltham, Owen, 1602?-1668.
         
         
            
               1623
            
         
         Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 175 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00619
            STC 10755
            ESTC S101827
            99837630
            99837630
            1966
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00619)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1966)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 925:03)
         
         
            
               
                  Resolues, diuine, morall, politicall b Owin Felltham
                  Resolves
                  Felltham, Owen, 1602?-1668.
               
               [20], 327, [3] p.   
               
                  Printed [by George Purslowe] for Henry Seile,
                  London :
                  [1623?]
               
               
                  The title page is engraved.
                  Printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  With a final errata leaf.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Ethics --  Early works to 1800.
               Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-10
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  Deo Amicis
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     
                  
                  Amor
                  Innocentia
                  Prudentia
                  Resolues Diuine, Morall Politicall by Owin Felltham 
                  
                     Hor. ser. lib. jo.
His ego Comodius, quam tu praeclare Senator millibus at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      alijs Ʋiuo.
                  London Printed for Henry Seile
                  LEX 
                  EVAN
                        •
                     
                  
                  FIDES
               
            
         
         
            
            
            TO THE MOST VERTVOVS, DISCREET, AND Noble; the Lady DOROTHY CRANE, daughter to the right Honorable, and Religious, the Lord HOBART.
            
               MADAME,
            
            
               IF euer Reſolutions were needfull, I thinke they

be in this Age of looſeneſſe; wherein, 'twere ſome vnhappineſſe to bee good, did not the Conſciouſneſſe of her owne worth, ſet vertue firme, againſt all diſheartnings. This makes her of ſo ſpecious a glorie, that though ſhee need not the applauſe of any, to adde to her happineſſe; yet ſhe attracts the hearts of all that know her, to Loue, Seruice, Admiraration.

That I haue ſacred this offertory of my thoughts to your Ladyſhip, this is reaſon inough; if not, your Loue to my deareſt friend, may ſecond it. To apparell any more in theſe paper veſtments, I ſhould multiply impertinents; and perhaps diſpleaſe. For I haue euer found facecommendation to dye Wiſedomes cheeke of a bluſh-colour. Diſcreet

Nature is alway modeſt, and deſeruing beſt, loues leaſt to heare on't. This onely I will truely adde: that I know not the thing of that value, ſhould make me ſhrine vp a worke of this nature, to any, in whom I could obſerue, the poſſibility of a faile in Vertue. Such a Dedication were to put Vertue to a Stepdame, that would not nurſe, but ſtifle her. With your Goodneſſe, I

am ſure, ſhee ſhall finde the tenderneſſe of a maternall loue. And if in theſe weake extractions, your Iudicious eye light you to ought, increaſing that affection (all by-reſpects put away) my next Petition will bee: that it may pleaſe you to command
            
               Your immutable ſeruant, OW. FELTHAM.
            
         
         
            
            
            TO THE PERVSER.
            
               TO beginne with Apologies, and intreate a kinde Genſure, were to diſparage the Worke, and begge partialitie: equall with Ostentation I ranke them both. If thou

bee'ſt wiſe, pleaſing words cannot blinde thy iudgement from diſcerning errors, whereſoeuer they appeare. If thou bee'ſt fooliſh, they can neither blāch thy folly, nor make thee thinke better, than thy indiſcretion leades thee to. Requeſts from others, may ſway our words, or actions; but our mindes will haue their owne free thoughts, as they apprehend the thing. Internall iudgement is not eaſily

peruerted. In what thou ſhalt heere meete with, vſe the freedome of thy natiue opinion: Et Lectorem, et Correctorem liberum volui. I ſhall euer profeſſe my ſelfe his debtor, that greets me with reprehenſions of Loue. The nobleſt part of a friend, is an honeſt boldneſſe in the noting of errors. He that tells me a fault, ayming at my good; I muſt thinke him wiſe and faithfull: wiſe, in ſpying that which

I ſee not: faithfull, in a plaine admoniſhment, not tainted with flattery. That I haue made it publique, I pleade not the importunitie of friends: that were to play at Hazzard for folly, if it prooue not. I writ it without incouragement from another; and as I writ it, I ſend it abroade. Rare, I know it is not: Honeſt, I am ſure it is: Though thou findeſt not to admire, thou maiſt to like. What I aime at in

it, I confeſſe, hath moſt reſpect to my ſelfe; That I might out of my owne Schoole take a leſſon, ſhould ſerue mee for my whole Pilgrimage: and if I ſhould wander from theſe rests, that my owne Items might ſet me in heauens direct way againe. We doe not ſo readily run into crimes, that from our owne mouth haue had ſentence of Condemnation. Yet, as no Phiſician can be ſo abſtemious, as to follow

ſtrictly all his owne preſcriptions: So I thinke there is no Chriſtian ſo much his minds maſter, as to keepe preciſely all his reſolutions. They may better ſhewe what hee would be, then what he is. Nature hath too ſlow afoote, to follow Religion cloſe at the heele. Who can expect, our dull fleſh ſhould wing it with the flights of the ſoule? He is not a good man that liues perfect; but hee that liues as well as he

can, and as humane fraileties will let him. He that thus farre ſtriues not, neuer began to bee vertuous; nor knowes he thoſe tranſcending ioyes, that continually feaſt in the noble-minded man. All the externall pleaſures that mortality is capable of, can neuer enkindle a flame, that ſhall ſo brauely warme the ſoule, as the loue of vertue, &amp; the certaine knowledge of the rule we haue ouer our own

wild paſsions. That I might curbe thoſe, I haue writ theſe: and if in them, thou find'ſt a line may mend thee; I ſhall thinke I haue diuulg'd it to purpoſe. Reade all, and vſe thy mindes libertie; how thy ſuffrage falls, I weigh not: For it was not writ ſo much to pleaſe others, as to profit my ſelfe.
            Farewell.
         
         
            
            
               
               Ad Librum:
               —Quid miſer egi?
               Quid volui? Dices.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            RESOLVES: DIVINE, MORALL, POLITICALL.
            
               I.
               
                  IDLE bookes are nothing elſe, but corrupted tales in Inke and Paper: or indeed Vice ſent abroad with a Licence: which makes him that

reades them, conſcious of a double iniurie: they being in effect, like that beſtiall ſinne of brutiſh Adulterie. For if one reades, two are catched: hee that angles in theſe waters, is ſure to ſtrike the Torpedo, that in ſtead of beeing his food, confounds him. Beſides the time il ſpent in them, a two-fold reaſon ſhall make me refraine: both in regard of my loue to my owne ſoule, &amp; pitie vnto his that made them. For if I be corrupted by them, the Compriſor of them is mediately a cauſe of my ill: and at the day of Reckoning (though now

dead) muſt giue an accoūt for't, becauſe I am corrupted by his bad example which hee leaues behinde him; So I become guilty by receiuing, and hee by thus conuaying this lewdneſſe vnto me: Hee is the thiefe, I the recieuer; and what difference makes our Law betwixt them? If one be cut off, the other dyes; both I am ſure periſh alike. I will write none, leſt I hurt them that come after me. I will reade none, leſt I augment his mulct that is gone before me: neither write, nor read, leſt I proue a foe to my ſelfe. A lame hand

is better then a lewde pen: while I liue, I ſinne too much; let me not continue longer in wickedneſſe, then life. If I write ought, it ſhall be both on a good ſubiect, and from a deliberated pen: for a fooliſh ſentence drop't vpon paper, ſets folly on a Hill, and is a monument, to make infamie eternall.
            
            
               II.
               The humble man is the ſureſt Peace-maker: of all morall vertues, Humility is the moſt beautifull; ſhee both ſhunnes Honor, and is the way to it: ſhe rockes

Debate aſleepe, and keepes peace waking, nay, doth foſter, doth cherriſh her: which is well expreſſed in a pretty ſtory of two goats, that met at once, on a very narrow Bridge, vnder which there glided a deepe, and violent ſtreame: being both met, the ſtraitneſſe gaue deniall to their Iourney; get backe they could not, the planke was too narrow, for their returning turne: ſtand ſtill they might, but that could neither bee continuall, nor to purpoſe: and to fight for the way in ſo perillous a place, was either to put a

wilfull period to their liues, or extremely hazard them. That they may therefore both paſſe in ſafety, the one lyes down, &amp; th' other goes ouer him: ſo while their paſſage is quiet, their liues are ſecure, from death, from danger. I haue euer thought it idle to continue in ſtrife; if I get the victory, it ſatiſfies my minde, but then, ſhal I haue his malice too, which may endamage me more: ſo my gaine will bee leſſe then my hindrance: If I be ouercome vnwillingly, thē is the diſgrace mine, and the loſſe: and though I haue not his malice, yet

ſhall I not want his ſcorne. I will (in things not weighty) ſubmit freely: The pureſt gold is moſt ductible: tis commonly a good blade that bends well. If I expect diſaduantage, or miſdoubt the Conqueſt, I thinke it good wiſedome, to giue in ſooneſt; ſo ſhall it be more honor to doe that willingly, which with ſtiffeneſſe I cannot but hazard vpon compulſion. I had rather be accounted too much humble, then eſteemed a little proud: the Reede is better that bends, and is whole; then the ſtrong Oake, that not bending,

breakes: If I muſt haue one, giue me an inconuenience, not a miſchiefe: the lighteſt burthen, is the eaſieſt borne.
            
            
               III.
               To make a perfect man, there is requiſite both Religion &amp; Nature. Nature alone we know too looſe: religion alone will ſeeme too hard; ſome for Religion haue I knowne formall, ſtrict; yet haue ſo wanted the pleaſing parts of a good nature, as they haue beene feared, but not loued: for being of a fiery ſpirit, euen ſlender occaſions haue

made way to the divulging of their own imperfections: either by too ſeuere a reprehenſion, or elſe by too ſoone ſodaine Contempt: both which make much for the harbouring of hate againſt themſelues, by making them eſteemed either raſh Cenſurers, or angry proud ones: and wee all know, that as Iudgement is neuer ſhot ſuddenly but from a fooles bow; ſo blind Choller broke into expreſſion, is the true marke of an intemperate minde; others there yet reſt, whom it tickles much to chatter of their own merits, and they

cannot lay an egge, but they muſt cackle, or like the boaſting PHARISEE, trumpet out the report of their owne praiſes: if not out of an affected ſingularity, and an ouerweening opinion of their owne excellence; yet for lacke of an humble and diſcret nature, that ſhould cauſe their obſeruation bee buſied at home. And this is that makes the world diſdaine, contemne them: ſelfe commendation is an arrow with too many feathers: which, we leuelling at the marke, is taken with the wind, and carryed quite

from it. Some againe for nature, I haue found rarely qualified: ennobled with ſuch a mild affability, ſuch a generous ſpirit, and ſuch ſweetneſſe of diſpoſition, and demeanour, that their humble &amp; courteous carriage haue preuailed much in the affection of thoſe with whom they haue had commerce: yet becauſe they haue wanted Religion (that like a good ſubiect ſhould make an elaborate worke rare) they haue, onely in a ſuperficiall applauſe, wonne the approbation of the vnſteady multitude: who loue them more for ſuffering

their rudeneſſe, then for any noble worth, that's obuious to their vndiſcerning Iudgements. But in all this they haue got no reuerence, no reſpect at all. Thus Religion without Nature (in men meerely naturall) begets a certaine forme of awfull regard: but to them 'tis like a tyrannical Prince, whom the people obey more for feare of an auſtere rebuke, then for any true affection, they beare to his perſon. Now Nature without Religion oft wins loue: and this is like a Maſter too familiar with his ſeruant: that in the beginning gains

loue, but ſhall in the end find contempt: and his toleration will be made an allowance of ill. Both together are rare for qualification. Nature hath in her ſelfe treaſure enough to pleaſe a man; Religion a Chriſtian: the laſt begets feare, the other loue, together admiration, reuerence. I will like, I will loue them ſingle; but conioyn'd, I will affect and honour.
            
            
               IIII.
               I finde, to him that the tale is told, beliefe onely makes the difference betwixt a truth, and lyes: for

a lye beleeued, is true: and truth vncredited, a lye; vnleſſe he can carry his probation in's pocket, or more readily at his tongues end: for as he that tels a ſmooth lye, is iudged to ſpeake truth, till ſome ſtep forth to contradict his vtterance: ſo hee that tels an vnlikely truth, is thought to broch a lye, vnleſſe he can produce conuincing reaſon to proue it; onely the guilt, or iuſtice of the thing reſts in the knowing conſcience of the Relator. In the hearer I cannot count it a fault: 'tis eaſie to bee deceiued in miracles, in probabilities: albeit

the iudgement that paſſeth on them, bee both honeſt, wiſe, apprehenſiue, and cleere. In the teller iuſtly; if it bee a lye, there needs no text to confute it; if it ſeeme ſo, and he cannot purge it, diſcretiō were better ſilent. I will tell no lies, leſt I bee falſe to my ſelfe: no improbable truths, leſt I ſeeme ſo to others; If I heare any man report wonders, what I know, I may haply ſpeake; what I but think, ſhal reſt with my ſelf; I may aſwell be too ſuſpicious, as ouer credulous.
            
            
               
               V.
               Three things are there which aggrauate a miſerie, and make an euill feeme greater then indeede it is. Inexpectation, Vnacquaintance, want of Preparation. Inexpectation, when a miſ-hap comes ſuddenly, and vnlooked for: it diſtracteth the minde, and ſcares both the faculties and affections from their due conſultation of remedy: whereas an euill foreſeene is halfe cured, becauſe it giueth warning to prouide for danger. Thus the falling of a houſe is more perillous, than the riſing

of a floud: for, while of the former, the hurt is more vnauoydable, by reaſon both of the violence, and precipitation: The latter, through the remiſſenes of comming, is leſſe dangerous, leſſe preiudiciall; there being time, either to auoyd the place, or to countermure. If this ſuffice not, think but how odious treaſon would ſhew in a deare friend, from whom we only expected the ſweet embraces of loue: the conceit onely is able to kill, like a madde Dogg's biting, that not onely wounds the body, but inſaniates the ſoule.

Secondly, Vnacquaintāce. Familiaritie takes away feare, when matters not vſuall, proue inductions to terror. The firſt time the Fox ſaw the Lyon, hee feared him as death: the ſecond, hee feared him, but not ſo much: the third time hee grew more bold, and paſſed by him without quaking. The Imbellicke peaſant, when hee comes firſt to the field, ſhakes at the report of a Musket: but after he hath rang'd thorow the furie of two or three Battels, he then can feareleſſe ſtand a breach; and dares, vndaūted, gaze death

in the face. Thirdly, want of preparation. When the enemie beſiegeth a Citie, not prepared for Warre, there is ſmall hope of euaſion, none at all to conquer, none to ouercome. How much more hard is the winter to the Graſhopper, then the Piſmire, who before, hauing ſtor'd her Garner, is now able to withſtand a famine? Leſt then, I make my death ſeem more terrible to me, then indeed it is; I will firſt daily expect it: that when it comes, I may not be to ſeeke to entertaine it: if not with ioy, as beeing but fleſh: yet without ſorrow,

as hauing a ſoule. Secondly, I will labour to be acquainted with it, often before it come, thinking it may come: ſo whē I know it better, I ſhal better ſuſtaine it: with leſſe feare, without terror. Thirdly, I will prepare for it, by caſting vp my accounts with God, that all things euen and ſtreight betwixt vs, whenſoeuer he ſhall pleaſe to call for me, I may as willingly lay down my life, as leaue a priſon. Thus ſhall I make my death leſſe dreadfull, and finiſh my life before I dye. He that dyes dayly, ſeldome dyes dijectedly.
            
            
               
               VI.
               A good beginning haue I oftē ſeen cōclude ill. Sin in the bud is faire, ſweet, pleaſing: but the fruit is death, horror, hell. Something will I reſpect in my way, moſt in my Concluſion: in the one, to preuent all wilfull errors; in the other, to inſure a Crowne. For as Iudgement hath relation to the manner of dying; ſo hath death dependance on the courſe of liuing. Yet the good end hath no bad beginning; it once had. A good conſequence makes the premiſes ſo eſteemed of, and a ſweete relliſh at the

leauing off, makes the draught delightfull, that at the firſt did taſte vnpleaſant. That is well that ends well: and better is a bad beginning that concludes well, then a proſperous onſet that ends in complaint. What if my beginning hath been ill? ſorrowes ouerblowne, are pleaſant; that which hath beene hard to ſuffer, is ſweet to remēber. I will not much care what my beginning be, ſo my end be happy. If my Sunne ſet in the new Ieruſalem, I haue liu'd well, how-euer afflictions haue ſometimes clouded my courſe.
            
            
               
               VII.
               Extreme longings in a Chriſtian, I ſeldome ſee ſucceed well: ſurely God meanes ſo to temper his, as hee would not haue their affections violent, in the ſearch of a temporall bleſſing: or elſe hee knowes our frailety ſuch, as wee would be more taken with the fruition of a benefit, then the Author. Proſperities are ſtrong pleaders for ſinne: Troubles be the ſureſt Tutors of goodneſſe. How many would haue dyed ill, if they had liu'd merrily? GOD hath ſeuerall

wayes to reduce his to his own orders, among which, I am perſwaded none is more powerfull, then reſtraint of our wils. It ſends the ſoule to meditation, wherby ſhe ſees the worlds follies in ſuch true colours of vanitie, that no ſound diſcretion can thinke them worth the doting on: and though our diſcontentments ſo tranſport vs, as we ſee not the good we reape by a Depriuation: yet ſure wee are happier by this want: for wee are all like women with Child, if wee had the things we long for; how ſoone ſhould we eate

and ſurfet? When nature findes her ardent deſires fulfilled, ſhee is rauenous, and greedy; yea then ſhee hath ſo little moderation, as 'tis not ſafe to ſatisfie her. If I can, I will neuer extremely couet: ſo though I meet with a Croſſe, it ſhal neither diſtemper, nor diſtract mee: but if my deſires out-ſtrip my intention, I will comfort my ſelfe with this, that the enioyment might haue added to my content, and endangered my ſoule: but the want ſhall in the end be a meanes to embetter them both. Gods Saints ſhall with ioy

ſubſcribe to his wil: though heere for a time it may ſeeme to thwart them.
            
            
               VIII.
               A worthy Act hath hee done, that hath learned to refraine his tongue: and ſurely much euill hath hee preuented, if hee knowes when to be well ſilent. Vnkindneſſes breed not ſo many Iarres, as the multiplying of words that follow them. How ſoone would theſe coales dye, if the tongue did not enkindle them? Repentance often followes ſpeaking; ſilence either ſeldome, or neuer:

for while our words are many, ſinne is in ſome, in moſt. Goe to the Crane, thou Babbler, reade her ſtorie, and let her inform thee: who flying out of Sicily, puts little ſtones in her mouth, leſt by her owne garrulitie, ſhe bewray her ſelfe as a prey to the Eagles of the mountaine Taurus: which with this policy, ſhe flyes ouer in ſafety: euen ſilence euery where is a ſafe ſafeguard: if by it, I offend, I am ſure I offend without a witneſſe: while an vnruly tongue may procure my ruine, and prooue as a ſword to cut the thrid of my life

in two: 'tis good alwayes to ſpeake well, &amp; in ſeaſon: and is it not as ſafe ſometimes to ſay nothing? hee that ſpeakes little, may mend it ſoone: and though hee ſpeakes moſt faults, yet hee exceedes not, for his words were few. To ſpeake too much, bewrayes folly; too little, an vnperceiuing ſtupiditie: I will ſo ſpeake, as I may be free from babbling Garrulitie: ſo bee ſilent, as my Spectators may not account me blockiſhly dull. Silence and ſpeech are both as they are vſed, either tokens of Indiſcretion, or badges of Wiſedome.
            
            
               
               IX.
               'Tis a hard thing among men of inferiour ranke, to ſpeak to an earthly Prince: no King keepes a Court ſo open, as to giue admittance to all commers: and though they haue, they are not ſure to ſpeede; albeit there bee nothing that ſhould make their petitiōs not grantable. Oh how happy, how priuiledged is then a Chriſtian? who though he often liues heere in a ſlight eſteeme, yet can hee freely conferre with the King of Heauen, who not onely heares his intreaties, but delights

in his requeſts, inuites him to come, and promiſeth a happy welcome; which he ſhewes in fulfilling his deſires, or better, fitter for him. In reſpect of whō, the greateſt Monarch is more baſe, then the baſeſt vaſſaile in regard of the moſt mighty and puiſſant Emperour. Man cannot ſo much exceede a beaſt, as God doth him: what if I be not known to the Nimrods of the world, and the Peeres of the earth? I can ſpeake to their better, to their Maſter; and by prayer bee familiar with him: importunity does not anger

him; neither cāanything but our ſins make vs goe away empty; while the game is playing, there is much differēce between the King and the Pawne: that once ended, they are both ſhuffled into the bag together: akd who can ſay whether was moſt happy, ſaue onely the King had many checks, while the little Pawne was free, and ſecure? My comfort is, my acceſſe to heauen is as free as the Princes; my departure from earth not ſo grieuous: for while the world ſmiles on him, I am ſure I haue leſſe reaſon to loue it then hee. Gods fauour

I will chiefly ſeeke for; mans, but as it fals in the way to it: when it proues a hindrance, I hate to be loued.
            
            
               X.
               The vertuous man is a true wonder: for it is not from himſelfe, that hee is ſo. But that I ſee ſo many wicked, I meruaile not. 'Tis eaſier running downe the hill, then climing it. They that are this way giuen, haue much the aduantage of them, that follow goodneſſe. Beſides thoſe inclinations that ſway the ſoule to vice, the way is broader,

and more ready: hee that walkes through a large field, hath onely a narrow path, to guide him right in the way: but on either ſide, what a wide roome he hath to wander in? Euery vertue hath two vices, that cloſe her vp in curious limits: and if ſhee ſwerues, though but a little, ſhe ſuddenly ſteps into errour. Fortitude hath Feare, and Raſhneſſe: Liberalitie, Auarice, and Prodigalitie: Iuſtice hath Rigor, and Partialitie. Thus euery good miſtreſſe, hath two bad ſeruants: which hath made ſome to define vertue, to

bee nothing, but a meane betweene two vices, wherof one leads to exceſſe, the other to defect: making her like the roofe of a Church, on whoſe top, wee ſcarce find roome to turne a foote in: but on either ſide, a broad road to ruine: in which, if we once be falling, our ſtay is rare, our recouery a miracle. The man that is rare in vice, I will neuer admire: if he goes but as hee is driuen, hee may ſoone be witty in euill: but the good man, I will worthily magnifie: he it is can ſaile againſt the wind, make the thorny way pleaſant,

and vnintangle the incumcumbrances of the world.
            
            
               XI.
               What ſinne is there, that we may account or little, or veniall, vnleſſe comparatiuely? ſeeing there is none ſo ſmall, but that (without repentance) is able to ſinke the ſoule in eternall Damnation? Who will thinke that a ſlight wound, which giues a ſodaine Inlet to Death? But ſhould wee grant this errour, yet theſe of all other, I obſerue the moſt dangerous, both for their frequency, and ſecrecie; the one increaſing

them to a large heape, the other ſo couering them, as we ſee not how they wrōg vs: The raine that fals in ſmalleſt drops, moiſtens the earth, makes it mire, ſlimy, and durte: whereas a hard ſhowre, that deſcēds violētly, waſheth away, but ſoakes not in. Euen the ſmalleſt letters are more hurtfull to the ſight, then thoſe that are written with a text pen. Great ſinnes, and publicke, I will auoide for their ſcandal &amp; wonder: leſſer &amp; priuate, for their danger, and multitude: both, becauſe my God hates them. I cannot, if I loue him, but

abhorre, what hee loathes.
            
            
               XII.
               Memory and forgetfulneſſe, are both in friendſhip neceſſary. Let me remember thoſe kindneſſes my friend hath done to mee, that I may ſee his loue, and learne gratitude. Let mee forget thoſe benefits I haue performed to him, leſt they ſhuffle out the effect of my loue, and tell mee hee is requited. Thus may we together increaſe our friendſhip, and comforts: otherwiſe, a man may haue many acquaintances, but no friends; though vnthankefulnes

baniſheth loue, Gratitude obtaines a repealement.
            
            
               XIII.
               I obſerue, beſides the inward Contents of a peaceable cōſcience, two things, wherein a Chriſtian excels all other men. In true Valour: In Fidelitie. In true Valour; that is, in a iuſt quarrell: for if his cauſe bee naught, there is none more timerous then hee; and indeed to ſhew much Courage, in a bad matter, is rather a token of deſperate folly, then any badge of a magnanimous minde; but in a iuſt cauſe, he is bold

as a Lyon. Nothing can daunt his euer vndaunted minde. Not Infamy, for he knowes in this, his ſhare is not worſe then his Maſters; &amp; while it is for his names ſake; he knowes he is in it, bleſſed. If there bee any Nectar in this life, 'tis in ſorrowes wee indure for goodneſſe. Beſides, hee weighes not how he fals to the world, and men; ſo he may ſtand firme, to his heauenly Father. That God we fight for, is able enough to vindicate al our wrongs. Not afflictions; how many did Iob, and the Apoſtles wade through with Courage,

with Content? Theſe he knowes are heere but for a time, tranſient, and momentany; neither ſhall the Iſraelites liue alwayes, vnder the tyranny of Pharaoh, or the trauels of the Wildernes: He knowes alſo, the more abundant in ſorrowes heere, the more abundant in ioyes hereafter; His teares ſhall returne in ſmiles, his weepings in a ſtreame of pleaſures. God doth not recompence with a niggardly hand; hee ſhall finde his ioyes as an ouer-flowing Sea; and his glory beyond thought, exuberant. Not Death; for he knowes, that

wil be his happieſt day; and his bridge, from woe, to glory. Though it bee the wicked mans ſhipwracke, 'tis the good mans putting into harbour: where ſtriking ſayles, and caſting Anchor, he returnes his lading with aduantage, to the owner; that is, his ſoule to God; leauing the bulke ſtill mored in the Hauen; who is vnrigg'd, but onely to be new built againe, and fitted for an eternall voyage. Had not Chriſtians had this ſolace; how ſhould the Martyrs haue dyed ſo merrily, leaping for ioy, that they were ſo neere their home,

and their heauen? dying often like Samſon among his enemies, more victory attending their end, then proceedings. Ah peereleſſe Valiance! vnconquerable Fortitude! Secondly, in Fidelitie. There is no friendſhip like the friendſhip of Faith. Nature, Educatiō, Benefits, cannot all together, tye ſo ſtrong as this. Chriſtianitie knits more ſure, more indiſſoluble. This makes a knot, that Alexander cannot cut. For as grace in her ſelfe, is farre aboue nature; ſo likewiſe is ſhe, in her effects: and therefore vnites, in a far more durable bond.

And a Chriſtian, though he would reſolue with himſelfe, to deale double; yet if he be ſincere, in ſpight of his reſolution, his conſcience will rate him, checke him, and deny him to doe it; nay, though he would, he cannot reſolue. He that is borne of God, ſinnes not; and the Spirit of ſanctification will not let him reſolue vpon ill. This is that Fidelity that wee finde, and admire in many, that haue choſen rather to embrace the flame, &amp; dye in ſilence, then to reueale their Companions, and Brethren in Chriſt. Tyrants ſhal ſooner

want inuention for torments, then they with tortures be made treacherous. The League that heauen hath made, hell wants power to breake. Who can ſeparate the coniunctions of the Deitie? Againe, as well in reproofe, as in kindneſſe, doth his loue appeare. For howſoeuer hee conceales his friends faults, from the eye of the world; yet hee affectionately tels him of them, in priuate: not without ſome ſorrow on his owne part, for his brothers fall. He ſcornes to be ſo baſe as to flatter: and he hates to bee ſo curriſh as

to bite. In his reprehenſions, he mingles Oyle and Vineger: hee is in them, plaine, and louing. Inuiolable amitie! Inualuable loue! Heere is met Courage and Conſtancy; one to withſtand an Enemie, an other to entertaine a friend. Giue me any foe, rather thē a reſolued Chriſtian: no friend, vnleſſe a man truely honeſt. A father is a ready treaſurie; a brother an infallible comfort; but a friend is both.
            
            
               XIIII.
               I will in all loſſes, looke both to what I haue loſt,

and to what I haue left. To what I haue loſt: that if it may be, and be good, I may recouer it: if not, that I may know what I haue forgone. To what I haue left: that if it be much, I may be thankefull, that I loſt no more, hauing ſo much, that I might haue been depriued of: if little, that I may not repine; becauſe I haue yet ſomething: if nothing but my life, that I may then be glad: becauſe that will bee the next thing I ſhall loſe. Which whenſoeuer it happens will with double Ioy recompence all the reſt. Gods preſence is aboundant

plenty: hauing that, I know nor want, nor loſſe, nor admiſſion of ill.
            
            
               XV.
               A man that would eſtabliſh a troubled gouernment, muſt firſt vanquiſh all his foes. Factious heads, muſt bee higher by a Pole then their bodies. For how will the Folds bee quiet, while yet among them, there bee ſome Wolues? Hee that would rule ouer many, muſt fight with many, and conquer: and be fure, either to cut off thoſe that raiſe vp tumults: or by a Maieſticke awe, to

keepe them in a ſtrict ſubiection. Slackneſſe, and conniuence, are the ruines of vnſettled Kingdomes. My paſſions, and affections are the chiefe diſturbers of my Ciuill State: What peace can I expect within mee, while theſe Rebels reſt vnouercome? If they get a head, my Kingdome is diuided, ſo it cannot ſtand. Separations are the wounds of a Crowne; whereby (neglected) it will bleed to death. Them will I ſtriue to ſubdue. If I cut them not off, I will yet reſtraine them. 'Tis no cruelty, to deny a Traytor libertie.

I will haue them be my Subiects, not my Prince: they ſhall ſerue mee, and I will ſway them. If it cannot bee without much ſtriuing; I am content with a hard combate, that I may haue a happie raigne. 'Tis better I endure a ſhort skirmiſh, then a long ſiege: hauing once wonne the field, I will hope to keepe it.
            
            
               XVI.
               Death to a righteous man, whether it commeth ſoone, or late, is the beginning of ioy, and the end of ſorrow. I will not much

care, whether my life bee long, or ſhort. If ſhort; the fewer my dayes bee, the leſſe ſhall bee my miſery, the ſooner ſhall I be happy. But if my yeeres be many, that my head waxe gray, euen the long expectation of my happineſſe, ſhall make my ioy more welcome.
            
            
               XVII.
               'Twas anciently ſaid, that whatſoeuer good worke a man doth with labour, the labour vaniſheth, but the good remaines with him that wrought it. And whatſoeuer euill thing hee doth

with pleaſure, the pleaſure flyes, but the euill ſtill reſteth with the Actor of it: goodneſſe making labour ſweet; euill turning pleaſure to a burthen. I wil not care how laborious, but how honeſt; not how pleaſurable, but how good my actions be. If it could bee, let mee bee good without pleaſure; rather then lewd, with much ioy. For though my good bee at firſt tedious; I am ſure in time it will yeeld me content: whereas the euill that now is delightfull, cannot but prooue a woe to my ſoule. The ſweeteſt liquor,

is not alwayes the moſt wholeſome. The Limon is more tart, yet excelleth the Orenge, that delighteth the taſte: poiſon may a while ſeeme pleaſant, and a weake ſtomacke thinke a Cordiall fulſome.
            
            
               XVIII.
               What if I were the worlds chiefe Fauourite? endowed with the choyceſt ornaments her Treaſury could affoord mee, adorn'd with beauty, imbelliſht with a faire proportion, in policie ſubtill, in alliance great, in reuenue large, in knowledge rich,

famed with honor, and honored with attendants; and to all theſe, had adioyned the prolonged yeeres of Methuſalah, yet if I wanted grace to vſe theſe graces right, they would all turne to my greater diſgrace and confuſion. Good parts imployed ill, are weapons, that being meant for our owne defence, we madly turne their edges, and wound our ſelues: they might make mee faire in ſhow, but in ſubſtance more polluted: they would bee but as a ſaddle of gold to the backe of a gall'd horſe; adorne mee, they might,

better mee they could not. Grace onely can make a man truely happy: what ſhee affordeth, can content ſufficiently; and with eaſe furniſh the vaſt roomes of the mind: without her, all are nothing; with her, euen the ſmalleſt is true ſufficiencie: how fully can ſhe bee rich, in the penury of theſe outward royalties? ſomething indeed they adde to her ornament, but 'tis from her, that they aſſume their goodneſſe. For though heauen hath made them ſo in their owne nature, yet is it from her that they proue ſo to me. Doe we not oftner

finde them, lights to blind vs, then to direct vs? I will neuer thinke my ſelfe neerer heauen, for hauing ſo much of earth. A weake houſe with a heauie roofe is moſt in danger. He that gets heauen, hath plenty enough; though the earth ſcornes to allow him any thing: he that failes of that, is truely miſerable; though ſhee giue him all ſhee hath. Heauē without earth is perfect. Earth without Heauen, is but a little more cheerly hell. Who haue beene more ſplendent in theſe externall floriſhes, then Heathen? but in the other, 'tis

the Chriſtian onely can challenge a felicity. Hauing theſe, I might winne applauſe with men; but the other wanting, I ſhall neuer gaine approbation vvith God. And what wil all their allowance auaile, when the Earths Creator ſhall Iudge and Condemn? 'tis a poore reliefe in miſery, to be onely thought well of, by thoſe that cannot helpe me.
            
            
               XIX.
               Is not man born to trouble, as the ſparkes flye vpward? is not his time ſhort, and miſerable, his dayes few, and euill? What madneſſe

then were it in me, to hope for a freedome from ſorrowes, or to thinke my ſelfe exempt from the common appointment of the moſt High? It hath beene cenſured as phrenſie, to vndertake to expell nature; what ſhall I thinke it, to hope to fruſtrate the deſignement of the Lord of Nature? Humanitie, and miſery, are alwayes paralels: ſometimes indiuiduals: and therefore when wee vvould put ſorrow in an Embleme, we paint him a man. If I haue but few Croſſes, I vvill truely then account my ſelfe fauoured:

if I haue many, and be ſomtimes free, Ile thinke I eſcape well, beeing ſo vntoward. If I haue nothing but troubles; yet may I not complaine: becauſe my ſinne hath deſeru'd more, then heere I can bee able to ſuffer. Had I but a being, though full of woe, yet vvere I beholding to God for it. His very leaſt, and meaneſt gift, exceedeth much, euen all, my beſt deſert. I doe infinitely want, how to merit a permiſſion to liue.
            
            
               XX.
               To haue euery man ſpeak

vvell of me, is impoſſible: becauſe howſoeuer I carry my ſelfe, ſome Cynick will barke at my courſe. Who can ſcape the laſh of Cenſure? If I ſhould be vitious, and profuſe, I ſhould bee loued of ſome; but not the beſt, not the good. If I ſhould Camelion-like, change my ſelfe to euery obiect, if I were not extraordinarily vvarie, I might ſoon counterfet ſome mans humour falſe, and that would bane my drift. For both to Vertue, and to Vice, is Flatterie a falſe glaſſe, making the one ſeeme greater, the other

leſſe then it is: and if it lights on a noble diſcretion, it is euer ſo vnhappy, as to beget the ruine of it ſelfe. But I imagine I could doe it with ſuch exactneſſe, that euen the eye of Lyncaeus could not eſpy it: yet when one ſhould commend mee for one thing, and another for the contrary; vvhat vvould the vvorld thinke of mee, that could thus in one, bee hot, and cold? ſhould I not be cenſured as a Tymoriſt? Yes ſurely, and that iuſtly: neither could it but be iuſt with God, at laſt to vnmaske my Flatterie, and vnrip my folly, in

the view of the multitude. Priuate ſinnes are puniſht with a publike ſhame. A ſuppoſed honeſt man found lewd, is hated as a growne Monſter, diſcouered by the blabbe of Time. Sinne is a concealed fire, that euen in darkneſſe will ſo worke, as to bewray it ſelfe. If I liue vertuouſly, and with piety, the world will hate me, as a Separatiſt: and my Reputation will be traduced, by the Ignominious aſperſion of maleuolent tongues. To be good, is now thought too neere a way to contempt: That which the Ancients admired, wee

laugh at. A good honeſt man is a foole. What then? ſhall I, to pleaſe a man, diſpleaſe a Chriſtian? I had rather liue hated for goodneſſe, then bee loued for Vice. Hee does better that pleaſeth one good man, then hee that contents a thouſand bad ones. I would, if it could be, pleaſe all: yet I would winne their loues vvith honeſty: otherwiſe, let their hate wound mee, rather then their loue imbrace. What care I for his friendſhip, that affected not vertue? hauing his hate, he may hurt mee outwardly: but inioying his loue, I will

iuſtly ſuſpect my ſoule of ſome ill. For if his affection be toward me, 'tis ſure becauſe hee ſees ſomthing in mee, that pleaſeth himſelfe: but while hee ſees euery thing vnlike him; how is't poſſible I ſhould bee beloued of him? ſince diuerſities breed nothing but diſvnion: and ſweet Congruitie is the mother of Loue.
            
            
               XXI.
               Who admires not the Wiſedome of Demoſthenes, in the anſwere hee returned to Corinthian Lais? [Poenitere tanti non emo.] Certainely, had hee not

knowne it from a ſelfe experience, 'tis not poſſible a Heathē ſhould haue ſpake ſo diuinely. All our diſhoneſt actions, are but earneſts laid downe for griefe. Vice is an infallible fore-runner of wretchedneſſe. Let the Worldling tell me, if he findes it not true, that all his warrantable aberrations, wherein he hath dilatedly tumbled himſelfe, end at laſt, either in anguiſh, or confuſion; Sinne on the beſt condition, brings repentance: but for ſinne without repentance, is prouided hell. 'Tis not folly, but madnes, euen the higheſt,

that makes a man buy his vexation. I wil force my ſelfe to want that willingly, which I cannot enioy without future diſtaſte. Though the Waſpe falles into the hony, that after drownes her: yet the Bee chuſeth rather, to goe to rhe Flowre in the field, where ſhee may lade her 
                     •
                  highes ſecurely, and with leiſure; then to come to the ſhop of the Apothecarie, where ſhee gets more, but makes her life hazardable.
            
            
               
               XXII.
               Workes without faith, are like a Salamander without fire, or a fiſh without water: In which, though there may ſeeme to be ſome quicke actions of life, and ſymptomes of agilitie: yet they are indeede, but fore-runners of their end, and the very preſages of death. Faith againe without Workes, is like a bird without wings: who, though ſhe may hop with her companions here vpon earth; yet if ſhe liues til the world ends, ſhee'l neuer fly to heauen. But when both

are ioyn'd together, then doth the ſoule mount vp to the Hill of eternall Reſt: theſe can brauely raiſe her to her firſt height: yea carry her beyond it; taking away both the will, that did betray her: and the poſſibility that might. The former without the latter, is ſelfecoozenage: the laſt without the former, is meere hypocriſie: together, the excellencie of Religion. Faith is the Rocke, while euery good action is as a ſtone laid; one the Foundation; the other the ſtructure. The Foundation without the walls, is of ſlender value:

the building without a Baſis, cannot ſtand. They are ſo inſeparable, as their coniunction makes them good. Chiefely will I labour for a ſure Foundation, Sauing Faith: and equally will I ſeeke for ſtrong wals, Good Workes. For as man iudgeth the houſe by the edifice, more than by the Foundation: ſo, not according to his Faith, but according to his Workes, ſhall God iudge man.
            
            
               XXIII.
               'Tis a rare thing to ſee a rich man religious; we are told, that his way is difficult:

and not many mighty are choſen. For while the earth allowes them ſuch ioyes, 'tis their heauen; and they looke for no other: Their pleaſures are ſufficient vnto them, both for honour, ſolace, and wealth: who wonders to ſee them careleſſe of the better, when they dote vpon the worſe? neither the minde, nor affection, can bee ſeriouſly diuided at once. Againe, euen low Commons whom they thinke meanely of, are higher often in vertues of the minde; are dearer vnto God then they: &amp; ſhall ſit in heauen aboue them.

Are there not many ſeruants, that in life haue born the burthen now crowned with vnending Ioyes, while their maſters are either in a lower degree glorious, or excluded that coeleſtiall ſocietie? I dare make it a part of my faith; yet auouch my ſelfe no Hereticke. Euen in meaneſt things GOD ſhewes his mighty power: Impoſſibilities are the beſt aduancers of his Glory. For what we leaſt beleeue can be done, wee moſt admire beeing done. Yet in this obſerue the mercy of God, that though the Worldling hath

not pietie in his thoughts, yet God giues him all theſe good things that hee hath no right to: albeit by his owne ill, he, like enuy, extracts euill out of good; ſo they proue in the end, nothing but paper pillars and painted fruite. Let all men bleſſe God for what they enioy: they that haue wealth, for their riches: I will praiſe him, that he hath kept them from me. I haue now what is good for me: and when my time comes, my ioy ſhall abound.
            
            
               
               XXIIII.
               A vertuous man ſhining in the puritie of a righteous life, is a Lighthouſe ſet by the Sea-ſide, whereby the Mariners both ſaile aright, and auoyd danger: But he that liues in noted ſinnes, is a falſe lanthorne, which ſhipwrackes thoſe that truſt him. The vertuous man by his good carriage winnes more to godlines, and is the occaſion of much good, yea it may bee, ſo long as the Moone renewes: For his righteouſnes dyes not with him: thoſe good examples which he liued in, and thoſe

pyous workes which hee leaues behind him, are imitated and followed of others, both remayning and ſucceeding. So they are cō
                  ueyed from one generation to another: and he, next God, is a primary cauſe of a great deale of the good they atchieue. So wee cannot but grant, that while here his memory weares out, his glory in a better world augments daily: either by his good preſidents, his pious inſtitutions, his charitable deeds, or his godly works; each of which with Gods bleſſing, are able to kindle ſome heat in

the cold zeale of poſteritie. Examples are the beſt and moſt laſting lectures; vertue the beſt example. Happie man that hath done theſe things in ſincerity; Time ſhall not outliue his worth: He liues truely after death, whoſe pious actions are his pillars of remembrāce: though his fleſh moulders to droſſe in the graue, yet is his happineſſe in a perpetuall growth: no day but addes ſome graines to his heape of glory. Good workes are ſeedes, that after ſowing returne vs a continuall harueſt. A man liues more renowned by ſome

glorious deedes, then euer did that Carian, by his Mauſolean monument. On the contrary, what a wofull courſe hath he runne, that hath liued lewdly, and dyes without repentance? his example infects others, and they ſpread it abroad to more; like a man that dyes on the plague, he leaues the infection to a whole Citie: So that euen the ſinnes of thouſands, hee muſt giue an account for. What can we thinke of ſuch as haue been the inuentors of vnlawfull games, and callings that are now in vſe? ſure they haue much to anſwere for, that

thus haue occaſioned ſo much ill: yea better had it beene, they had not beene at all, then being, to be loaden with the ſinnes of ſo many. Miſerable man! that when thy owne burthen is inſupportable, thou yet cauſeſt others to adde to thy weight; as if thou would'ſt be ſure deſperately to make thy riſing irrecouerable: are the waters of thy own ſinnes ſo low, that thou muſt haue ſtreames from euery place, to runne into thy Ocean? Who can without a ſhowre of teares, thinke on thy deplorable ſtate, or without mourning,

meditate thy ſad condition? Oh! Let me ſo liue, as my life may be beneficiall, not hurtfull to other. Let my glory increaſe, when my life is done: I am ſure, ſatietie in heauen, is not capable of either complaint, or diſcontent: but as for ſpoyling others, by my owne confuſion, ſinne: I ſhould think death a faire preuention. I loue not that life which makes death eternall. I haue ſin enough of my owne, to ſigh, and ſorrow, and mourne for: I need not make others mine by my owne bad actions. A little of this is too too

much; yea, he hath enough, that hath none; hee hath too much, that hath any at all.
            
            
               XXV.
               Hee deſerues not commendation, that for beeing commēded growes proud: euery good thing, a good man ſpeakes of mee, ſhall, like the blaſt of a trumpet in warre, incite and incourage me, to a cloſer purſuit of more nobler vertue: not like Bucephalus trappings, blow mee vp in a higher conceit of ouerprizing my owne weaknes: So while ſome ſpeake well, let my

deeds exceed their tougue. I had rather men ſhould ſee more thē they expect, then looke for more then they ſhall find.
            
            
               XXVI.
               When a man hath the proiect of a courſe in his mind, 'tis good wiſedome to reſolue of ſecrecy, till the time his intent bee fulfilled: neither can hee but be fooliſh, that brags much, either of what he will doe, or of what hee ſhall haue: For if what hee ſpeakes of, falls not out accordingly, then will the world mocke him with deriſion and

ſcorne: and oftentimes his liberall tongue, may be occaſion of ſome ones ſodain intercepting his aime: divulged intentions ſeldome proceed well: multitudes make a iarre in buſineſſes; their opinions, or Councels either diſtract Iudgement, or diuert reſolution: But howſoeuer, if what wee boaſted of commeth to paſſe, yet ſhall we be reputed vain-glorious, boaſters, vnwiſe. Bragges lift vp expectation ſo high, that ſhee ouerthinkes the birth: and many times, the childe which indeed is faire, wee thinke not ſo, becauſe wee

were poſſeſt with hopes of finding it rare. Secrecy is a neceſſary part of policie: things vntold, are yet vndone: then to ſay nothing, there is not a leſſe labour. I obſerue, the Fig-tree whoſe fruit is moſt pleaſant, bloomes not at all: whereas the Sallow that hath glorious palmes, is continually found Barren. I would firſt be ſo wiſe, as to bee my owne Councellor: next, ſo ſecret, as to bee my owne Councell-keeper.
            
            
               XXVII.
               Some men read Authors as our Gentlemen vſe flowers,

onely for delight and ſmell; to pleaſe their fancy, and refine their tongue. Others like the Bee, extract onely the hony, the wholeſome precepts, and this alone they beare away, leauing the reſt, as little worth, of ſmall value. In reading I will care for both; though for the laſt, moſt: the one ſerues to inſtruct the mind; the other fits her to tell what ſhe hath learned: pitty it is, they ſhould be deuided: he that hath worth in him, and cannot expreſſe it, is a cheſt keeping a rich Iewell, and the key loſt. Concealing goodneſſe, is

vice; vertue is better by being cōmunicated. A good ſtile, with wholeſome matter, is a faire woman with a vertuous ſoule, which attracts the eyes of all; The good man thinkes chaſtly, and loues her beauty, for her vertue; which hee ſtill thinks more faire, for dwelling in ſo faire an outſide. The vicious man hath luſtfull thoughts; and he would for her beauty, faine deſtroy her vertue: but comming to ſollicite his purpoſe, findes ſuch diuine lectures, from her Angels tongue, and thoſe deliuer'd with ſo ſweet a pleaſing

modeſty, that he thinks vertue is diſſecting her ſoule to him, to rauiſh man with a beauty which he dream'd not of. So hee could now curſe himſelfe, for deſiring that lewdly, which he hath learn'd ſince, onely to admire, and reuerence: Thus he goes away better, that came with an intent to bee worſe. Quaint phraſes on a good ſubiect, are baits to make an ill man vertuous: how many vile men ſeeking theſe, haue found themſelues Conuertites? I may refine my ſpeech without harme: but I will endeuour more to reforme my

life. 'Tis a good grace both of Oratory, or the Pen, to ſpeake, or write proper: but that is the beſt work, where the Graces, and the Muſes meet.
            
            
               XXVIII.
               Wee ſee in the Moone a threefold condition, her Wane, her Increaſe, her Full: all which, I liuely ſee reſembled in a Chriſtian, three cauſes working them: Sinne, Repentance, Faith. Sinne; vvhich after the act, vvhen he once conſiders, it makes him like the Moone in her Wane, or ſtate of Decrement, obſcuring, and

diminiſhing that glorious light of the ſpirit, vvhich vvhilome ſhined ſo brightly in him: nay, ſometimes as the Moone in her lateſt ſtate of Diminution, hee ſeemes quite gone, reſting for a time like a man in a trance, like a tree in Winter, or as fire buried in concealing Embers, vvithout either ſence, or ſhew, of either light, or heat. But then comes Repentance, and caſts water in his face, bedewes him vvith teares, rubbes vp his benummed ſoule; that there is to bee ſeene ſome tokens, both of life, and Recouery: This

makes him ſpring, cauſes him to begin to bud againe, vnburies his loſt light, and by little and little, recollects his decayed ſtrength of the apprehenſion of Gods Spirit: ſo ſets him in the way to ioy, and renued courſes. But laſtly, Faith appeares, and perfects vvhat Repentance beganne, and could not finiſh: ſhe cheeres vp his drooping hopes, brings him againe to his wonted ſolace, ſpreads out his leaues, blowes vp his fainting fire to a bright flame: makes him like the Moone in her full glory, indues him with a plenteous

fruition of the preſence of the Almighty, and neuer leaues him, till he be reſettled in his full ioy, contentment, happineſſe. Thus while he ſinnes, he is a Decreſſant; when he repents, a Creſſant; when his faith ſhines cleere, at full. Yet in all theſe, while hee liues heere, hee is ſubiect to change: ſometime like a Beacon on a Hill, he is ſeen a farre off, and to all: ſometime like a Candle in a houſe, neerer hand, and only to his familiars: ſometimes like a Lampe vnder a buſhel, he is obſcur'd to all; yet in all he burnes: though

in ſome, inſenſibly: and is neuer without one ſound conſolation, in the worſt of all theſe: for as the Moone when ſhee is leaſt viſible, is a Moone as well, as when wee ſee her in her full proportion; onely the Sunne lookes not on her vvith ſo full an aſpect, and ſhee reflects no more, then ſhe receiues from him: So a Chriſtian in his loweſt ebb of ſorrow, is the Childe of God, as well, as when hee is in his greateſt flow of comfort, onely the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe darts not the beames of his loue ſo plentifully, and hee ſhewes

no more, then God giues him. When God hides his face, man muſt languiſh: his with-drawings, are our miſeries: his preſence, our vnfailing Ioy. Sinne may caſt mee in a trance, it cannot ſlay mee: it may bury my heat, for a time, it cannot extinguiſh it: it may make me in the wane, it cannot change my beeing: it may accuſe, it ſhal not condemn: Though GOD depriue mee of his preſence for a time, hee will one day re-inlighten mee, polliſh mee, and crowne mee for euer: where the Moone of my inconſtant ioy ſhall

change to a Sunne, and that Sunne ſhall neuer ſet, beclouded, or eclypſed.
            
            
               XXIX.
               In expences I would bee neither pinching, nor prodigall: yet if my meanes allow it not, rather thought too ſparing, then a little profuſe: 'tis no diſgrace to make my ability my Compaſſe of ſaile, and line to walke by. I ſee what I may doe; others but what I doe: they looke to what I ſpend, as they thinke mee able; I muſt looke to what my eſtate will beare: nor can it be ſafe, to ſtraine it at all:

'tis fit I ſhould reſpect my owne abilitie, before their forward expectation. Hee that when hee ſhould not, ſpends too much, ſhal when he would not, haue too little to ſpend. 'Twas a witty reaſon of Diogenes, why he asked a halfe-penny of the thrifty man, and a pound of the prodigall; the firſt, hee ſaid, might giue him often, but the other e're long, would haue none to giue. Yet ſay I had to diſpend freely; as to bee too neere hauing enough, I eſteeme ſordid: ſo to ſpend ſuperfluouſly, though I haue abundance, I account one of

follies deepeſt ouer-ſights. There is better vſe to bee made of our talents, then to caſt them away in waſte: God gaue vs them, not to ſpend vainely, but to imploy, for profit, for gaine.
            
            
               XXX.
               As the Needle in a Dyall remoued from his point, neuer leaues his quiuering motion, till it ſettles it ſelfe in the iuſt place it alway ſtands in: So fares it with a Chriſtian in this world; nothing can ſo charme him, but hee will ſtill minde his Sauiour: all that put him out of the queſt of Heauen,

are but diſturbāces. Though the pleaſures, profits, and honours of this life, may ſometime ſhuffle him out of his vſuall courſe; yet he wauers vp and downe in trouble, runnes to and fro like Quick-ſiluer, and is neuer quiet within, till hee returnes to his wonted life, and inward happineſſe: there he ſets down his reſt, in a ſweet, vnperceiued, inward content: vvhich though vnſeene to others, hee eſteemes more, then all that the world cals by the name of felicity: they are to him, as May-games to a Prince; fitter for children,

then the Royaltie of a Crowne. It ſhall not more grieue me, to liue in a continued ſorrow, then it ſhall ioy mee, to finde a ſecret perturbation in the worlds choyceſt ſolaces. If I finde my ioy in them, without vnquietneſſe, that vvill proue a burdenſome mirth: For finding my affections ſettle to them without reſiſtance, I cannot but diſtruſt my ſelfe, of truſting them too much. A full delight in earthly things, argues a neglect of heauenly. I can hardly think him honeſt, that loues a Harlot for her brauery, more then his

Wife, for her vertues. But while an inward diſtaſte ſhewes mee theſe Cates vnſauourie, if my ioy bee vncompleat in theſe terrene felicities, my inward vnſettledneſſe in them, ſhall make my content both ſufficient, and full.
            
            
               XXXI.
               Strange is the inchantment that the world works on vs, when ſhe ſmiles, and lookes merrily: 'tis iuſtly matter of amazement, for a man to grow rich, and retaine a minde vn-altered: yet are not all men changed alike, though all in ſomething

admit variation. The Spider kills the man, that cures the Ape. Fortunes effects are variable, as the natures ſhe works vpon: ſome, while their baskets grow more full, their mindes are higher, and riſe: they now know not thoſe friends, that were lately their companions: but as a Tyrant among his Subiects, growes haughty, and proud: ſo they, among their familiars ſcorne, and contemne: ſpurning thoſe with arrogant diſdaine, which but of late, they thought as worthy as themſelues, or better: high fortunes are the way to

high mindes: pride is vſually the child of riches. Contempt. too often ſits in the ſeat vvith Honour. Who haue we knowne ſo imperious in Offices, as the man that was borne to beggery? As theſe riſe, ſo ſome fall: and that which ſhould ſatiate their deſire, increaſeth it: which is euer accompanied with this vnhappines, that it will neuer bee ſatisfied: this makes them baſer, by beeing wealthier: profit (though with drudgerie) they hugge with cloſe armes. All vices debaſe man, but this makes a Maſter a ſlaue to his ſeruant,

a drudge to his ſlaue; and him that GOD ſet ouer all, this puts vnder all. Pittifull! that man when good things are preſent, ſhould ſearch for ill: that he ſhould ſo care for riches, as if they were his owne: yet ſo vſe them, as if they were anothers: that when hee might bee happy, in ſpending them, will bee miſerable in keeping them: and had rather dying, leaue wealth to his enemies, then beeing aliue, relieue his friends. Thus as one aſpires, the other deſcends: both extremes, and iuſtly blameable. If my eſtate

riſe not, I hope my minde will bee what it is, not Ambitious, nor Auaricious. But if euer the Diuine prouidence ſhall, beyond either my deſert, or expectation, bleſſe mee, I will thinke, to grow proud, is but to riſe, to fall: and to proue couetous, onely to poſſeſſe wealth, that the nobler mindes may hate, and ſcorne mee. For what is there they eſteeme more ſordid, then for a mans minde to bee his moneyes Mercenary?
            
            
               
               XXXII.
               A weake Chriſtians life, is almoſt nothing but a Viciſſitude of ſinne, and ſorrow. Firſt, hee ſinnes, and then he laments his folly: like a negligent ſchooleboy, he diſpleaſeth his maſter; and then beſeecheth his remiſſion with teares. Our owne coruptions are diſeaſes incurable: while we liue, they will break out vpon vs; wee may correct them, wee cannot deſtroy them: they are like the feathers in a fowle, cut thē they will come againe: break them, they will come againe: plucke them out, yet

they will come again: only kill the bird, and they grow no more. While bloud is in our veines, ſinne is in our nature; ſince I cannot auoide it, I will learne to lament it: And if through my offences, my ioy bee made obſcure, and vaniſh: that ſorrow ſhall new beget my ioy; not becauſe I haue beene ſinfull, but becauſe, for ſinne, I finde my ſelfe ſorrowfull. All other ſorrowes are either fooliſh, fruitleſſe, or beget more: onely this darke entry, leades the way to the faire Court of happines. God is more mercifull in giuing repentāce

to the Delinquent, then in granting remiſſion to the Repentant: He hath promiſed pardon to the Penitent, no Repentance to the Peccant.
            
            
               XXXIII.
               In chuſing friends there be two ſorts of men, that I would for euer auoyde: For beſides the learning of their vices, I dare not truſt them with a ſecret. There is the Angry man, and the Drunkard: The firſt in his fit is meerely mad, hee ſpeakes not a word by reaſon, but by brutiſh paſſion: not vpon premeditated

termes, but whatſoeuer his memory on the ſudden catches, his violent paſſion driueth out, bee it knowne, or hidden: ſo oft in a braule he blabbes out that, which being cooled, hee much repents to haue named: committing that in his ſparkling fury, which his appeaſed ſoule will tremble to think of. Anger is the feuer of the ſoule, which makes the tongue talke idle: it puts a man into a tumult, that he cannot heare what Counſell ſpeakes: tis a raging Sea, a troubled water, that cannot be wholeſome for the vſe of any: and if it

be true which Hippocrates tels, that thoſe diſeaſes are the moſt dangerous, that alter the habit of the patients countenance: this muſt needs bee moſt perillous, that voyce, colour, countenance, pace, ſo changeth, as if fury diſpoſſeſſing reaſon, had ſet a new Garriſon in the Citadell of man. This he knew that gaue vs that precept, Make not friendſhip with an angry man. The other hath no memory at all: For the aboundāce of wine, hath drown'd vp that noble Recorder: and while Bacchus is his chiefe god, Apollo neuer

keepes him company: Friends and foes, familiars, and ſtrangers are then all of equall eſteeme: ſo he forgetfully ſpeakes of that in his cups, which if he were ſober, ſhould bee buried in ſilence. Firſt he ſpeakes he knowes not what, nor after, can he remember what that was he ſpake. Hee ſpeakes that he ſhould forget, and forgets that, which hee did ſpeake. Drunkenneſſe is the funerall of all intelligible man, whom onely time and abſtinence can reſuſcitate. A Drunkards minde and ſtomach are alike; neither can retaine, what they

receiue. I would bee loth to admit of a familiar ſo infectious as either; more vnwilling to reueale my ſelfe to any ſo open. What friēd ſoeuer I make choiſe of, I will bee ſure hee ſhall haue theſe two properties, Mildneſſe, Temperance: otherwiſe tis better to want companions, then to be annoyed with either a madman, or foole. Clitus was ſlaine by a Drunken Maſter: The Theſſalonians maſſacred by an angry Emperour: and the deaths of of either, lamented by the Agents.
            
            
               
               XXXIIII.
               I ſee, liberty makes licentious, and where the reines are giuen too looſely, the affections run wildely on, without a guide, to ruine: For mans will without diſcretion, that ſhould adde limits, is like a blind horſe, without a bridle, that ſhould guide him aright: he may goe faſt, but runnes to his own ouerthrow, and while hee mends his pace, he haſtens to his owne miſchiefe. Nothing makes vs more wretched, then our owne vncontrolled wils. A looſe will fulfilled, is the

way to worke out a woe. For beſides this folly in beginning wrong, the greateſt danger is in continuance: when like a Bowle running down a hill, he is euer moſt violent, when hee growes neereſt his Cēter &amp; period of his aime. Theſe follies are prettily ſhaddowed in the ſports of Acteon, that while he ſuffer'd his eye to roue at pleaſure, and beyond the pale of expediēce, his Houndes, euen his own affections, ceaze him, teare him, proue his decay. Let it be my vigilance to curbe my beginning deſires, that they may not wander beyond

moderation; if my owne will be a blind conductor, good precepts to an ingenious nature, are bitts that reſtraine, but hurt not. I know, to follow a ſoothing fancy, cannot be but ridiculouſly ill: and this inconuenience beſides haue I ſeene; That hee which may doe more then is fit, will in time doe more then is lawfull. He that now exceedes the meaſure, will ere long exceed the manner. Vice is a Peripatetick, alwayes in Progreſſion.
            
            
               
               XXXV.
               Euen between two faithfull friends, I thinke it not conuenient that all ſecrets ſhould be imparted: neither is it the part of a friend, to fiſh out that, which were better concealed. yet I obſerue ſome, of ſuch inſinuating diſpoſitions, that there is nothing in their friends heart, that they would not thēſelues know with him; and this, if I may ſpeake freely, I count as a fault. For many times by too farre vrging, they wring bloud, from whence onely milke ſhould flowe:

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
knowing that by their importunitie, which not only breedes a diſlike in them to heare, but alſo when their conference is ended, begetes a repenting ſorrow in him that told it: and makes him wiſh, hee had lock't vp his lips in ſilence, rather then haue powred out his heart with ſuch indiſcretion. How many haue bewailed the vntimely diſcloſures of their tongue? how many haue ſcrew'd out ſecrets, that would haue giuen thouſands to haue return'd them vnknowne? If I haue a friend that I care not to loſe, I will neuer ingage

my ſelfe ſo much, as to be beholding to him to know all. If I haue one that is faithfull, I wil not wrong him ſo much, as to wreſt that from him, ſhould cauſe him be ſorrowfull. If hee reueales ought vn-vrged, my aduice is faithfull, and free: otherwiſe, to preſſe out a ſecret that may proue preiudiciall, I eſteeme as the beginning of the breach of Amity, and the primary breeder of a ſecret diſlike.
            
            
               XXXVI.
               We know 'tis ſometimes better to ſound a retrait, &amp; ſo retire, then 'tis to ſtay in

the field, and conquer: becauſe it may ſo fall out, that the prize we win, cannot counteruaile the loſſe, that by this Warre we ſhall ſuſtaine: ſo like the fooliſh Mariner, that ſeeing a Fiſh in the Sea, leapes into water to catch that, which together with his life hee loſeth. Wee often loſe an eternall Kingdome, for the gaine of toyes, and vanities. Who is there that hazzards not his ſoule, for the pleaſures, or the profits of ſin? which when they haue, what haue they got, but ſhaddowes, or vexations? The wealthy man is like a

powder-maſter, who hath prouiſion againſt an enemie, but is euer in danger of being blowne vp. As for pleaſure, 'tis at beſt but a hilded veſſel; which though it pleaſe the palate for a cup or two; yet the Lees are at hand, and they marre it: a little diſturbance turnes it into diſtaſte. What a foole were I to caſt away my ſoule on ſuch tranſitorie trifles? which when I haue, I am neither ſure to enioy, nor to find commodious: what I cannot keep without danger, I will neuer earneſtly ſeeke: to loſe a Crowne of gold, for a counterfet, is

more then a childiſh fondneſſe. I had better ſit ſtill, and be quiet in peace, then riſe to conquer a petty Village, when my loſſe is a large Citie.
            
            
               XXXVII.
               Chriſt healed diſeaſes three manner of wayes; with meanes, as the Leper in the eighth of Mathew: without meanes, as the ten Lepers in the ſeuenteenth of Luke: againſt meanes, as the man borne blind, in the ninth of Iohn. I will looke to meanes as beeing more ordinarie, more reuealed: but if my blind eye ſees not

that preſent ſuccour, my feare is not more, nor my griefe. 'Tis as eaſie to God to worke without meanes, as with them: and againſt them, as by either: 'Tis all one to him, Bee cleane, or Go waſh. Yea, though euery argument concludes danger, let not my hopes faile mee yet, his omnipotency is beyond that feeble ſtay of the ſoule: nor yet will I ſo depend on his will hidden, as I neglect to practice his will reuealed. For as to diſ-regard his appointed meanes, is a ſupreme contempt: ſo to depend too much on things vnſearchable,

is rather a badge of raſh preſuming, then any notable courage of faith. I muſt looke to my way, and let him alone in his.
            
            
               XXXVIII.
               'Tis a Capitall miſery for a man to bee at once both old, and Ignorant. If hee were onely old, and had ſome knowledge, he might abate the tediouſneſſe of decrepit age, by the diuine raptures of Contemplation. If he were yong, though he knew nothing, yet his yeeres would ſerue him, to labour, and learne: whereby in the Winter of his

time, hee might beguile the wearineſſe of his pillow and chayre. But now his body beeing withered by the ſtealing length of his dayes, and his limbes wholly diſabled, for either motion, or exerciſe: theſe together with a minde vnfurniſhed of thoſe contenting ſpeculations of admired Science, cannot but delineate the pourtraicture of a man wretched. A gray head with a wiſe minde, is a treaſurie of graue Precepts, experience, &amp; iudgement. But fooliſh old age, is a barren Vine in Autumne: or an Vniuerſitie to

ſtudy folly in: euery action is a patterne of infirmitie: while his body ſits ſtill, hee knowes not how to finde his minde action: and tell mee if there bee any life, more irkeſome then idleneſſe. I haue numbred yet but a few dayes; and thoſe I know, I haue neglected. I am not ſure they ſhall bee more, nor can I promiſe my head, it ſhall haue a ſnowy haire. What then? Knowledge is not hurtfull, but helpes a good minde: any thing that is laudable, I deſire to learne. If I dye tomorrow, my life to day ſhal bee ſomewhat the ſweeter

for knowledge: and if my day proue a Summer one, it ſhall not be amiſſe, to haue prouided ſomething, that in the euening of my Age, may make my minde my Companion. Notable was the anſwere that Antiſthenes gaue, when hee was asked what fruit he had reaped of all his ſtudies? By them, ſaith hee, I haue learned, both to liue, and to talke with my ſelfe.
            
            
               XXXIX.
               There is a two-fold way to honour: Direct, when God cals: Indirect, when man ſeekes it, without the Lords warrant. Dauid went

the firſt, and his Crowne departed not frō his head, till nature had payed her debt, and his life diſſolued: And when hee is gone, his Iſſue ſucceedes him. Abſolon went the other, but his ſinnes pulled him down with vengeance; and onely a dumbe pillar ſpeakes his memory. God cannot indure the aſpiring ſpirit, that would clime the hill of preferment, without his leaue. Theeues of honour, ſeldom finde ioy in their purchaſes, ſtability, neuer. Beſides, I obſerue the man that is fit for a place of note, neuer ſeekes it ſo much, as hee is

ſought for, for it: whereas euer the Bramble, that is low, and worthleſſe, cryes out aloud, Make me a King: 'tis incident to a weake minde, to ouer-value it ſelfe. How many would be Magiſtrates, that know not how to bee men? Moſes obiects much, when God himſelf impoſeth a charge: For a man of vnderſtanding knowes, that 'tis better to liue in the Valley, where the times tempeſts blow ouer him: then to haue his ſeat on the Mountains top, where euery blaſt threatens both his ruine, and fall: howſoeuer others meaſure

him, hee knowes his owne height; and will not exceed it. Yet beeing placed by an Almighty hand, hee that ſet him there, can keep him ſecure. But hee muſt then beware, that he makes not that his King, that ſhould he his Subiect: that he giues not the reines, where he ſhould vſelthe checke: and that he playes not the Ape too much, either by too idle imitation, or by doting too fondly, on his darling Honour. Thus cautelous, may he liue ſafe: When he that reacheth promotion without Gods calling him, may flouriſh awhile, but not

thriue. In aſcents, thoſe are the ſafeſt, that are broadeſt, and leaſt ſudden, and where the light is open: how ſoon is a fall caught in thoſe ſtaires that are darke, narrow, &amp; quickly riſing? I wil as well look to the way, as the thing: There is no path to happy preferment, but that which vertue treades: which was well noted by the Heathen, when they built the Temple of honour ſo, that none could enter it, but they muſt firſt paſſe through that of vertue. I had rather liue honeſtly, though meanely: then by vnlawful practices vſurp a Crow ne.
            
            
               
               XL.
               Nothing more diſworthes a man, then Cowardice, and a baſe feare of danger: the ſmooth way it makes difficult, the difficult inacceſſible. The Coward is an vnfiniſht man; or elſe one which nature made leſſe then others: If euer he did any thing well, fortune was his guide, not wiſedome. His feare in him begets delay, and delay breedes that he feares, danger: the ſouldier that dares not fight, affoords the Enemie too much aduantage for his preparement; both

for directing his ſouldiers, plotting his Stratagems, ſtrengthening his files, ordering his Campe, or doing any thing may turne diſaduantage vpon his foe: when as the valorous warriour giues moſt diſcomfiture, in his ſodaineſt onſet, where hee takes away the time for fortification. If it bee by ſpeech a man is to act his part, feare puts an ague in his tongue, and often leaues him, either in an amazed diſtractiō, or quite elingued. For the too ſerious apprehenſion of a poſſible ſhame, makes him forget that, ſhould helpe him

a gainſt it: I meane a plaine boldneſſe, bequeathing a dilated freedome to all his faculties, and ſenſes: which now with a cold feare, are frozen and congealed. If not this, out of an vnmeaſured care to doe well, it driues a man into affectation: and that like miſſhapen apparell, ſpoiles the beauty of a well limb'd body: For nature will not endure the racke; when you ſet her too high, ſhe proues vntuneable, and in ſtead of a ſweet cloze, yeeldes a cracke: ſhe euer goes beſt in her owne free pace: I will neither ſtay her ſolong, as to meet

delay: nor runne her ſo far, as to doe ought affectedly. I had rather be confidently bold, then fooliſhly timorous; he that in euery thing feares to doe well, will at length doe ill in all.
            
            
               XLI.
               Many haue much lamented the loſſe of trifles, when they might haue gained by ſuch damages, had they not with them, loſt themſelues: I meane, their quiet minds, and patience. Vnwiſe ſo to debarre themſelues of reſt, when their vexation cannot yeeld them profit; if teares could either recouer

a loſſe, or recall time, then to weepe, were but to purpoſe; but things paſt, though with prudence they may be corrected, yet with greateſt griefe, they cannot bee recalled: make them better wee may, but for to make them not to be at all, requires more then a humane ſtrength, or a finite power. Actions once done, admit a correction, not a nullity. Although I will endeuour to amend what is gone by amiſſe, yet will I labour, neuer to grieue for any thing paſt, but ſinne: and for that alwayes. A ſmall loſſe ſhall neuer trouble

mee: neither ſhall the greateſt hindrance, make my heart not mine owne. He ſpake well that ſaid, He which hath himſelfe, hath loſt nothing.
            
            
               XLII.
               Some men are of ſo noble, and free a diſpoſition, that you cannot beeing a friend, aſke ought, to receiue a deniall: it being one part of their happines, to pleaſure the man they loue. Yet theſe in the end, and theſe times, are the only vnhappy men. For being exhauſted by the neceſſities of others, and their baſe

working on a free nature; an vnwelcom want, at once vndoes them, and the goodneſſe of their diſpoſition. pitty ſuch willing courteſies ſhould be caſt away in ſuch vngratefull ground; that like an vnbottomed Gulfe, ſwallowes, but returnes not: or that a mans firme loue ſhould make him doe that, ſhould kill himſelfe in future. Contrarie to theſe, you haue another ſort are faſt, and holding: and though ſometimes they might pleaſure a friend, without a ſelfe preiudice: yet their inbred crabbedneſſe reſerues all, with a

cloſe hand. And while the other ruins with a faire affection; hee thriues with a vulgar hate, and curſes; ſuch as the firſt, are beſt to others: ſuch as the laſt, to themſelues. I will ſo ſerue others, as I iniure not my ſelfe: ſo my ſelfe, as I may helpe other.
            
            
               XLIII.
               As there is no feate of Actiuity ſo difficult, but being once done, a man ventures on it more freely the ſecond time: ſo there is no ſinne at firſt ſo hatefull, but being once committed willingly, a man is

made more prone for a reiteration. For there is more deſire of a knowne pleaſure, then of that which onely our eares haue heard report of. The horſe that hath fed on prouender, will looke and long for it: but the iade that hath only had hey, expects no more then his racke. So farre is ignorance good, that in a calme, it keepes the minde from diſtraction; and knowledge, as it breedes deſire in all things, ſo in ſinne. Bootleſſe therefore ſhall euer be that cunning fetch of Satan, when hee would induce me once to make a triall

of ſinne, that I might thereby know more, and be able to fill vp my mouth with diſcourſe, my minde with fruition; bearing mee in hand, I may at my pleaſure giue it the hand of parting, and a finall farewell. Too often (alas) haue I bin deceiued with this beguiling perſwaſion, of a power to leaue, and a will to returne at my will. Henceforth ſhall my care bee to refraine from once. If I grant that, ſtronger perſwaſions will plead for a ſecond action: 'tis eaſier to deny a gueſt at firſt, then to turne him out, hauing ſtayed

a while. Thou knoweſt not, ſenceleſſe man, what ioyes thou loſeſt, when thou fondly laſheſt into new offences. The world cannot repurchaſe thee, thy priſtine integrity: thou haſt hereby loſt ſuch hold of grace, as thou wilt neuer againe be able to recouer. A mind not conſcious of any foule enormities, is a fair temple in a durty ſtreet: at whoſe dore, Sinne, like a throng of rude plebeians, knockes inceſſantly: while the doore is ſhut, 'tis eaſi to keep it ſo, and them out▪ open that, but to let in one, thouſands will ruſh in after

him, and their tramplings will for euer ſoyle that vnſtained floore, while thy conſcience is vnſpotted, thou haſt that can make the ſmile vpon the racke, and flames; 'tis like Homers Nepenthe, that can baniſh the ſadneſſe of the minde. But when thou woundeſt that, thou burieſt thy ioyes at once: and throweſt a Iewell from thee is richer then the wealth of worlds. Foole that thou art, that wandring in a darke wilderneſſe, doſt wilfully put out thy candle; and thinkeſt cold water can ſlake thy thirſt, in the burning

fit of an Ague; when it onely breeds in thee a deſire to powre in more. Hee that neuer taſted the pleaſures of ſinne, longs leſſe, after thoſe banefull diſcontenting contents. What ſweets of ſinne I know not, I deſire ſtill to bee vnexperienc't in. I had rather not know, then by knowledge be miſerable. This Ignorance will teach me Knowledge, of an vnknowne peace. Let mee rather be outwardly maimed, and want diſcourſe: then bee furniſht of that, and poſſeſſe a wound, that bleedeth within.
            
            
               
               XLIV.
               'Tis fooliſh, and ſauors not of common policie, to purchaſe friends by large gifts: becauſe hauing once vſed them to rewards, they will ſtill expect more: and cuſtome that pleaſeth, is ſeldome omitted, without either diſcontent, or danger. If then our loues tokens ſhall ſeem to diminiſh, friendſhip likewiſe will decreaſe: and if not quite conſume, yet eaſily be drawne to allow harbour to baſe diſ-reſpect: which what a thorne it is to an affectionate minde, I deſire rather

to know by iudicious obſeruation, then by reall experience: but ſure I am, it no way can bee ſmall: yet moſt true muſt it needs be, that friendſhip wonne by large gifts, reſembles but the ſtraw fire; that hauing matter to feed vpon, burnes brightly: but let new fuell be neglected; it dyes, conſumes, and quite goes out. Nor further can this amity be euer approued, or ſure, or ſincere. For hee that loues me for my gifts ſake, loues my gifts, aboue my ſelfe: and if I ſhould happen to light on aduerſitie; I ſhould not finde him then

to appeare: there being no hope of a gainefull requitall. If I giue any thing, it ſhall be becauſe hee is my friend: not becauſe I would haue him ſo: not ſo much that I may haue his loue; but that already, hee hath mine. I will vſe them ſometimes to continue friendſhip, neuer to begin it. I doe not hold him worthy thankes, that profeſſeth me a kindneſſe for his own ends.
            
            
               XLV.
               Nothing more ſaddens the ſoule of a good man, then the ſerious apprehenſion

of a iuſt ſhame. If it were falſe, his own cleereneſſe would bee a ſhield ſtrong enough, to repell the darts of ſlander. For man is neuer miſerable, till Conſcience turnes his enemy. If it were but the loſſe of riches, there were a poſſibilitie of a recouerie: if of friends, hee might finde more, or content himſelfe with the knowledge of their happineſſe, in that glorious Manſion of the Saints: if of corporall anguiſh, a quiet minde might mitigate his paines, or induſtry with time, take a truce with ſorrowes: but

this miſery is immedicable. Credit once loſt, is like water ſo diffuſiuely ſpilt, that 'tis not in humanitie to recollect it. If it bee, it hath loſt the purity, and will for euer after, be full of ſoile: and by how much his honeſty was more noted; by ſo much will his ſhame bee more, and his griefe. For ſee what a horrour he hath before him; all will bee now ready to brand him with the odious, and ſtigmaticall name of an Hypocrite. His Reputation (which though it bee not dearer then his ſoule, yet he prizeth aboue his life) will be

blacked with an eternall ſtaine: which nor abſence, time, endeuour, nor Death can waſh away. If he liues, and could in himſelfe forget it: yet the enuious world will keepe it vpon record: and when hee mindes it not, rub it on his galled ſoule. If he could fly from his Countrey, that would like a Bloud-hound follow him: if he dyes, that will ſuruiue him, and make his very graue contemptible: nay, ſo farre will it ſpread, as ſomewhat to infect his friends: and though haply in himſelfe hee may bee bettered, by ſo raſh a

fall: yet the cruell, and vncharitable world will euer thinke him worſe. In this I dare not follow it: in doing that may cauſe this, I hope I ſhall not. I will firſt ſtriue to be void of the act might bring ſhame, next, not to caſt it in the diſh of the penitent. If my ſufferings bee vniuſt, I am ſure in the end I ſhall find them comfortable. If God hath pleaſ'd to remit offences, why ſhould I commemorate them? A good life is a fortreſſe againſt ſhame: and a good man's ſhame, is his benefit: the one keepes it away; the other when it

comes, makes it proue profitable.
            
            
               XLVI.
               The will for the deed, is oft with God accepted: and he that is a thankefull Debtor, reſtores a benefit. Many benefits, nay, all I poſſeſſe, O Lord, from thee I know I haue receiued: requite them I cannot, returne them I may not, and to reſt ingratefull, were a ſin inexcuſable. Since then I cannot retaliate thy loue, or retribute thy fauours: yet Lord will I owe them, with a deſire to pay.
            
            
               
               XLVII.
               There is not any thing eates out friendſhip, ſooner then concealed grudges. Though reaſon at firſt produceth opinion, yet opinion after, ſeduceth Reaſon. Conceits of vnkindneſſe harboured and beleeued, will worke euen a ſteady loue, to hatred. And therefore, reſerued diſpoſitions, as they are the beſt keepers of ſecrets: ſo they are the worſt increaſers of loue. Betweene friends it cannot be, but diſcourteſies wil appeare: though not intended, by a willing act, yet ſo

taken by a wrong ſuſpect: which ſmothered in ſilence, increaſe dayly, to a greater diſtaſte: but reuealed once, in a friendly manner, oft meet with that ſatisfaction, which doth in the diſcloſure baniſh them. Sometimes ill tongues, by falſe tales, ſow Diſcord betweene two louers. Sometimes miſtakes, ſet the mind in a falſe beliefe. Sometimes iealouſies, that flow from loue, imprint ſuſpition in the thoughts. All which may find eaſe in the vttering: ſo their diſcouerie be in mildneſſe; otherwiſe, choller caſts a miſt before

the eyes of the minde, and when it might ſee cleerely, will not let it. If betweene my friend, and my ſelfe, a priuate thought of vnkindneſſe ariſe; I will preſently tell it, and bee reconciled: if he be cleere, I ſhall like him the better when I ſee his integritie: if faulty, confeſſion gaines my pardon, and binds mee to loue him: and though we ſhould in the diſcuſſion iarre a little, yet will I bee ſure to part friendly. Fire almoſt quench't, and laid abroad, dyes preſently: put together, it will burne the better. Euery ſuch breach

as this, will vnite affection faſter: a little ſhaking prefers the growth of the tree.
            
            
               XLVIII.
               I haue ſometimes wiſh't my ſelfe in ſome high ſeate of honor: with what folly, I haue after ſeene, and been diſpleaſed, with my ſelfe, with my deſires: ſo vnbefitting vviſedome, ſo diſſonant from Chriſtianity. For what can a high place conferre vnto mee, that can make my life more truely happy? if it addes to my ioyes, it increaſeth my fear; if it augments my pleaſure, my care is more, and my

trouble. But perhaps I ſhal haue reuerence, weare rich apparell, and fare deliciouſly: alas! cold flames, wet raymēt. Haue I not known ſome inioying all, and neuer found other fruit, but enuie, beggery, and diſeaſe? ſo haue in the end, wiſhed to change, for lower Honors, for meaner dignities, accounting themſelues as the flag, on the top of a ſhipmaſt, as more high, and more viſible; ſo more, and euer open, to the wind, and ſtormes: being as a worthy Iudge once anſwered one, that gaue him his title of Honor: True, Honorable

ſeruants: to poſt through the toyles of a circuit, and thinke on any mans buſines but their owne. Ah Tiſſue couer, to a ſtraw Cuſhion! But I ſhal haue more means, ſo ſhal I do the more good: I grant; but may I not doe as much good, with leſſe meanes? 'Tis a queſtion who ſhall haue more reward, of him that does moſt in quantity, or moſt according to the proportion of his meanes; If Chriſt may be admitted as arbitrator, the poore Widdow gaue more, then al the rich ones. I feare, if I had more, I ſhould ſpend more in waſte:

ſure I am, I ſhould haue more to anſwere for. Beſides, who knowes what a change wealth might work in me? what a ſnare hath it proued to many, that like the Sunne, haue in the morning of their time, mounted themſelues to the higheſt pitch of perſpicuity, and brightneſſe? which when they haue once attained, they decline, fall, vaniſh, &amp; are gone; leauing nothing behind thē, but darke night, blacke reputation. If not this, what can I tell, but that I might gather like a ſpunge, to bee ſqueezed out againe, by ſome grinding

oppreſſor? So bee more vexed with an vnexpected loſſe, then pleaſed with my ſhort inioyment. The thiefe that meets with a full purſe, takes away it, and returnes a ſtabbe; while the empty pocket makes the life ſecure: then perhaps we could wiſh to be poore, but cannot: that ſo vvee might leſſen our griefe, by the ſorrow for our loſſe. Tell me then, O my ſoule! vvhat ſhould make thee wiſh to change? I liue in a ranke, though not of the higheſt, yet affoording as much happineſſe, more freedome: as beeing exempt

from thoſe ſuſpitious cares, that pricke the boſome of the wealthy man: 'tis ſuch as might content my better, and ſuch as heauen ſmiles on, with a gracious promiſe of bleſſing, if my carriage be fair and honeſt; and without theſe who is well? I haue neceſſaries, and what is decent; and when I deſire it, ſomething for pleaſure. Who hath more that is needfull? If I be not ſo rich, as to ſowe almes by ſackfulls, euen my Mite, is beyond the ſuperfluity of wealth: and my pen, my tongue, and my life, ſhal (I hope) helpe ſome

to better treaſure, then the earth affoords them. I haue food conuenient for mee: and I ſometimes find exerciſe to keepe my body healthfull: when I doe, I make it my recreation, not my toyle. My rayment is not worſt, but good; and then that, let mee neuer haue better. I can bee as warme in a good Kerſey, as a Prince in a Skarlet robe. I liue where is much means of true ſaluation: my libertie is mine owne, I can both frequent them, and deſire to profit by them. I haue a mind can bee pleaſed vvith the preſent; and if time

turnes the wheele, can indure a change, without deſiring it. I vvant nothing but abundance; and this I neede not, becauſe want herein, I account much better then reall poſſeſſion: if it had beene fit for mee, I know, my God would haue beſtowed it on me. He neuer was ſo careles of a child of his, as to let him miſſe that, he knew might make for his good. Seeing then, hee ſees it inconuenient, it ſhall bee my ioy to liue without it; and henceforth, will I not long any more to change. He is not a compleat Chriſtian, that

cannot be contented vvith that he inioyes. I will rather ſettle my minde to a quiet reſt, in that I finde: then let her wander, in a wearied ſollicitude, after vngotten plenty. That eſtate that God guies mee, euer vvill I eſteeme beſt: though I could not thinke it ſo, I am ſure it is ſo: and to think againſt knowledge, is a fooliſh ſuſpition.
            
            
               XLIX.
               'Tis a precept from a perfidious mind, that bids vs thinke all knaues vve deale vvith: ſo by diſtruſting, to hinder deceit. I dare not

giue my mind that liberty, leſt I iniure charity, and run into error. I will thinke all honeſt, if ſtrangers: for ſo I'me ſure they ſhould bee; only let me remember, they are but men: ſo may vpon temptation, fall with the time; otherwiſe, though they want religion, Nature hath implanted a morall iuſtice, which vnperuerted, will deale ſquare. Chriſts precept was found in the mouthes of Heathen. Doe not to another, what thou wouldſt not haue done to thy ſelfe.
               
            
            
               
               L.
               Though the bodies excretions grow but inſenſibly, yet vnleſſe they bee dayly taken away, wee ſee, they make men monſtrous: as Nabuchadnezzars haires were like Eagles feathers, and his nayles like birds clawes, in his ſeuen yeeres beſtialitie. So that thoſe things which nature with due ordering, hath made for vſe and ornament: with a careleſſe neglect, grow to miſchiefe, and deformitie. In the ſoule I finde it yet worſe: and no Vice ſo ſoon ſteales on vs, as the abuſe of

things in themſelues lawfull: For Nature euer ſince her firſt deprauation, without a corrigible hand to reſtraine her, runs into wide extremities. I know, 'tis good the Vine ſhould flouriſh, but let it alone, and it ruines it ſelfe, in ſuperfluous branches. Our pleaſures wee ſee, are ſometimes the enliuenings of a drooping ſoule: yet how eaſily doe they ſteale away our minds, and make vs with a mad affection, dote vpon them? none ſuſpecting in ſo faire a ſemblance, a Sinon, that ſhould gull vs, with ſuch diluſiue poſtures: but becauſe

we know them lawfull, we boldly, and heedleſſely vſe them: and as Prouidence is the mother of happineſſe: ſo negligence is the Parent of miſery. I will euer bee moſt circumſpect, in things veiled with either goodneſſe, or ſweetneſſe. Nothing ſteales more ſoules frō God, then lewd courſes that are outwardly glorious. Reaſon hath not ſo dull an eye, but ſhee may ſee thoſe things, that are apparantly ill: but thoſe that are ſo, onely by their accident, haue power to blind her ſight: ſo require more care, more vigilancy. I'le

only vſe them, to make me better: whē they leaue that, I'le leaue them: and deale with'vm in a wiſe diſcretion, as the Emperour Commodus did with his ſeruants, in a wicked ieſt, baniſh them: not for the ill they haue done mee; but for the harme they may doe. Since all my goodnes cannot make one ſin good: why ſhould an accidentall ſinne ſpoile that, which is good in it ſelfe?
            
            
               L I.
               There is no man that liues well, but ſhall be ſuſpected for ſelfe-conceited,

vnleſſe hee can liue like a Hermite, in a Cell: or like ſome Satyre, in an vnfrequented Deſart. He cannot for his life ſo carry himſelfe, but he ſhall ſometimes light on lewd company: ſuch as hee neither loues, nor cares for. If hee continues ſociety with them, he endangers his ſoule: either by participating of their bad actions, or elſe by conniuing at thoſe offences, he ſees they delight in: either of which, not onely caſt a preſent guilt on the ſoule, but euen worke it to ſuch a temper, as makes it apt to receiue the impreſſion

of any ill; So ſecretly inſinuating, till it come frō toleration, to alowance, Action, Cuſtome, Delight. Bad Companions are like Traitors, with whom if we act, or conceale, wee are guilty: this Pitch will defile a man. If he ſhall out of an honeſt care of his ſoules welfare, and his loue to Religion, labour to auoid ſuch bad aſſociates: or beeing vnhappily fallen among them, ſeeke for a preſent eſcape: Then pride, and a high conceit of himſelfe, is gueſſed the onely motiue of his bodies departure: when indeed 'tis onely

goodneſſe, that importunes his abſence. But tell mee now, is't not better I leaue them, &amp; be thought proud wrongfully: then ſtay with them, and be knowne bad certainly? He's a foole that will ſell his ſoule, for a few good words, from a bad mans tongue. What is't to me, how others thinke me, when I know, my intent is good, and my wayes warrantable? A good conſcience cares for no witneſſe: that is alone, as a thouſand. Neither can the worlds Calumnies, worke a change in a minde reſolued. Howſoeuer heere my Reputation

ſhould be ſoiled vnworthily, yet the time is not farre off, when a freedome from ſinne will bee more worth, then a perpetuated fame from Adam, till Doomes day. While heauen and my Conſcience ſee mee Innocent, the worlds ſuppoſitions cannot make mee culpable. Hee that is good, and ill ſpoken of, ſhall reioyce, for the wrong is done him by others. Hee that is bad, and well reported, ſhall grieue for the iniury hee does himſelfe. In the one, they would make mee what I am not: in the other, I make my ſelfe what

I ſhould not. Let mee rather heare ill, and doe well: then doe ill, and bee flattered.
            
            
               LII.
               For iniuries, my opinion is with Socrates: 'Tis better to ſuffer, then to offer them. He may be good that beares them: he muſt be ill that proffers them. Saul would ſlay Dauid, when himſelfe only is vitious, and ill. Vice, is accompanied with iniuſtice; Patience, is an attendant on Vertue.
            
            
               
               LIII.
               In all nations, two things are cauſes of a common proſperity: Good Gouernment: and good Obedience: A good Magiſtrate, ouer a peruerſe people, is a ſound head, on a ſurfetted body. A good Communaltie, and a bad Ruler, is a healthfull body, with a head aching: either are occaſions of ruine: both ſoūd, preſeruatiues. A good Gouernour is a skilfull Shipmaſter, that takes the ſhorteſt, and the ſafeſt courſe: and continually ſo ſteeres, as the Rockes, and Shelues

which might ſhipwracke the ſtate, be auoided: and the voyage euer made, with the ſooneſt ſpeed, beſt profit, moſt eaſe. But a wicked Magiſtrate is a Wolfe made leader of the fold: that both ſatiates his crueltie, and betrayes them to danger. To whom if you adde but ignorance, you may vpon certain grounds, propheſie deſtruction. The Iudges inſufficiencie, is the Innocents calamitie. But if the Common-wealth be obedient, &amp; the Ruler worthy: how durable is their felicitie, and ioy? Solon might well ſay, That Citie

was ſafe, whoſe Citizens were obedient to the Magiſtrates, and Magiſtrates to the Lawes. What made the Maior Scipio ſo victorious, but his wiſedome in directing, and his Souldiers willingneſſe, in obeying, when he could ſhow his troopes, and ſay, You ſee not a man among al theſe, but will, if I command him, from a Turret throw himſelfe into the Sea? The inconuenience of ſtubbornneſſe, that Conſull knew, who meeting vvith an obſtinate Youth, ſold both him, and his goods, ſaying, Hee had no need of that Cittizen, that vvould

not obey. As it is in the larger, and more ſpacious vvorld; ſo is it in the little world of Man. None if they ſerue their true Prince, but haue a Gouernour completely perfect. Criticiſme it ſelfe, cannot find in God to cauill at. He is both iuſt, and mercifull, in the Concrete, and the Abſtract, he is both of them. Who can taxe him with either crueltie, or partialitie? though my obedience cannot anſwere his perfection; yet will I endeuour it. If Chriſt bee not my King to gouerne, he wil neither be my Prophet to forewarne, nor

my Prieſt to expiate. If I cannot come neere it, in effect, as being impoſſible: I will in deſire, as being conuenient: ſo though leſſe, yet if ſincere, I know, he wil accept it: not as meritorious, but reſpecting his promiſe.
            
            
               LIIII.
               'Tis an Aphoriſme in Phyſicke, that they which in the beginning of ſicknes eate much, and mend not, fall at laſt to a generall loathing of food. The Morall is true in Diuinity. He that hath a ſick conſcience, and liues a hearer vnder a

fruitfull Miniſtery, if hee growes not ſound, he will learne to deſpiſe the word. Contemned bleſſings leaue roome for curſes. Hee that neglects the good hee may haue, ſhall find the euill he would not haue. Iuſtly hee ſits in darkneſſe, that would not light his Candle when the fire burned cleerely. He that needs counſell, and will not heare it, deſtines himſelfe to miſerie, and is the willing Author of his own woe. Continue at a ſtay he cannot long: if he could, not to proceede, is backward. And this is as dangerous to the ſoule, as the

other to the body. Pittifull is his eſtate, that hates the thing ſhould helpe him: if euer you ſee a drowning man refuſe helpe, conclude him a wilfull murtherer. When God affoords mee plentifull meanes, woe bee to mee if they proue not profitable: I had better haue a deafe eare, then hear to neglect, or hate: to the burying of ſuch treaſures there belongs a curſe, to their misſpending, Iudgements.
            
            
               LV.
               God giues three kinds of gifts, Temporall, Spirituall,

and Eternall; Temporall, as Wealth, Pleaſure, Honour, and ſuch like. Spirituall, as Sauing Faith, Peace of Conſcience, and aſſurance of Saluation. Eternall, as Glory and happines in heauen for euer. The firſt is common to the wicked, as well as the godly, and they moſtly floriſh in theſe terrene beauties. For who ſo great in fauour with the world as they? They liue, become old, and are mighty in power, as Iob ſpeakes in his 21. yet all theſe ſweetes paſſe away like a vapour, and though they reuell out their dayes

in mirth, yet in a moment they goe downe to the graue. The two other God beſtowes onely vpon his Elect: all that heere hee often giues them, is onely one of theſe: ſome ſpirituall fauours hee beſtowes vpon them, the other he reſerues for them, when Earth cannot cal them her Children. One he giues them not, till they be gone from hence; the other when they haue it, the world ſees it not. What differēce can a blind man perceiue, betweene a ſparkling Diamond, and a worthleſſe peble? Or what can a naturall man ſpie, in

an humble Chriſtian, that euer hee thinkes may make him be happie? Afflictions heere are the Lot of the righteous, and they dimme thoſe ſplendid beauties, that ſpeak them faire in the eye of the Almighty: they are ſports of the priuie Chamber, that theſe Kings ioy in: the vnciuill vulgar ſee not the pleaſures of their Crown: Whereas the wicked, and Godforſaken man ſpreads out his plumes, and ſeemes euen to checke the Sunne in his glory. Vice loues to ſeeme glorious, yea more to ſeeme, then to bee. What a Luſtre theſe Glowwormes

caſt in darkneſſe, which yet but touched, are extinct? a poore reckoning alas in the end! when all theſe counterfet Iewels ſhal be ſnatched from him, and he anſwere for all ſtrictly, at the vnauoidable barre of the laſt Iudgement. They had neede haue ſome pleaſure here, that can haue nothing but woe heereafter. Fleſh, rebellious fleſh, would ſometime ſet me to murmur at their proſperity; but when my minde in her Cloſet reuolues their fickle eſtate, and findes all their good in preſēt, &amp; outward, I ſee nothing may be a midwife

to the leaſt repining enuie. When my ſoule ſolaceth her ſelfe in thoſe rauiſhing delights that exhilarate a Chriſtians mind, how poorely can I thinke of thoſe lamentable ioyes? the ſpirituall man lookes on the flouriſhes of this life with pitty, not deſire. If God giues the wicked one, and me two, why ſhould I complaine? but when the leaſt of mine, is infinitely better then his all, let mee neuer grudge him, ſo poore, and ſo ſhort a heauen. If God affoords mee his childrens fauours, (though oppreſſed with pouerty) I am richer,

then all their gawdy Adulations can make me: becauſe I haue already the earneſt of a World of Ioy, which the wicked ſhall neuer obtaine.
            
            
               LVI.
               I wonder what ſpirit they are indued withall, that can baſely libell at a man that is falne! If they were heauenly, then would they with him condole his diſaſters, and drop ſome teares in pitty of his folly, and wretchedneſſe: If but humane, yet nature neuer gaue them a mind ſo cruell, as to adde weight to an ouercharged

beame. When I heare of any that fall into publike diſgrace, I haue a mind to commiſerate his miſ-hap, not to make him more diſconſolate. To inuenome a name by libells, that already is openly tainted, is to adde ſtripes with an Iron rod, to one that is flayed with whipping: and is ſure in a mind well-temper'd, thought inhumane, diabolicall.
            
            
               LVII.
               Our yeeres at full are foureſcore and ten: much time compared to a day; but not a minute in reſpect

of eternity: yet how few liue to tell ſo large a ſucceſſion of time? One dyes in the bud, another in the bloome, ſome in the fruite, few like the ſheafe, that come to the barne in a full age; and though a man liues to inioy all, ſee but how little he may call as his owne. He is firſt Puer, then Iuuenis, next Vir, and after Senex; the firſt hee rattles away in toyes and fooleries, ere hee knowes where he is, ſpends a great part of his precious time: hee playes as if there were no ſorrow, and ſleeps as if there would neuer bee ioy. The next,

pleaſures and luxurie ſhorten and haſten away: vnchecked heat makes his nimble ſpirits boile; hee dares then doe that, which after he dares not thinke of: he does not then liue, but reuell; &amp; cares not ſo much for life, as for that which ſteales it away, Pleaſure. Hee hath then a ſoule that thinkes not of it ſelfe, but ſtudies onely to content the body: which with her beſt indulgence, is but a piece of actiue earth: when ſhe leaues it, a lumpe of naſtineſſe. The third, Cares of the world, and poſterity, debarre of a ſollid content:

and now when he mounted to the height of his way, he finds more miſery, then the beginning told him of. What iarres, what toyles, what cares, what diſcontentments, and what vnexpected diſtractions, ſhall he light vpon? if poore, hee's miſerable, and ridiculous: if rich, fearefull &amp; ſolicitous: this being all the difference betweene them, the firſt labours how to liue, the other ſtudies how to continue liuing. In the laſt, nature growes weake and irkſome to her ſelfe, venting her diſtaſte with Salomon, and mournes that now ſhee

finds her dayes, that be vnpleaſing. He that liues long hath onely the happineſſe, to take a larger taſte of miſery: what before hee thought hurled about with more then a ſphericall ſwiftneſſe, hee now thinks more tedious, then a tyred Hackney in foule wayes: Time, that before hee hath wooed to ſtay for him, now he could on his knee ſue to, to haſte him away. But if (that honey of all humanity) Learning, hath taught him a way to coozē his ſorrowes, he could then with old Themiſtocles, find in his heart to weep, that he muſt

then leaue life, when he begins to learne wit. Thus all mans ages are ſo ful of troubles, that they filch away his time of liuing. The firſt is full of folly: the ſecond of ſinne: the third of labour: the laſt of griefe. In all, he is in the Court of this world, as a ball bandyed between 2. rackets, Ioy, &amp; ſorrow: If either of thē ſtrike him ouer, he may then reſt: otherwiſe, his time is nothing, but a conſtant motion in calamitie. I haue onely yet runne through the firſt, and paſſed my Puerilia; whether my life, or my youth ſhall be ended firſt, I

neither know, nor care. I ſhall neuer bee ſorrowfull, for leauing too ſoone, the tempeſts of this tumbling Sea. But if I ſee my Summer paſt, I hope in Autumn God will ripen me for himſelfe, and gather me; if my Maker, and maſter ſaw it fit, I could bee content neither to ſee it, nor winter, I mean the winter of age: but if he ſhall appoint mee ſo large a time, I ſhall willingly pray as my Sauiour hath taught mee, His will bee done: though I wiſh not the full fruition of all, yet doe I deſire to borrow a letter from each: So in ſtead of Puer,

Iuuenis, Vir, &amp; Senex; giue mee the foure firſt letters, which will make mee PIVS.
            
            
               LVIII.
               Two things in my apparell, I will onely aime at; Commodiouſnes, Decencie: beyond theſe I know not, how ought may bee commendable; yet I hate an effeminate ſpruceneſſe, as much as a phantaſticke diſorder. A neglectiue comlineſſe is a man's beſt becomming ornament. Sardanapalus was as baſe in his Feminine veſtures, as Heliogabalus was mad, when hee

wore Shooes of Gold, and Rings of Leather: the one ſhew'd much pride, the other more wantonneſſe: let mee haue both theſe excluded, and I am pleaſ'd in my Garments.
            
            
               LIX.
               Though an enemy bee not a thing neceſſarie; yet is there much good vſe to be made of him: yea, ſometimes he doth a man a greater pleaſure, then a dearer friend. For wheras a friend, out of a feare to diſpleaſe, and a kinde of conniuing partialitie, ſpeaks only Placentia, &amp; ſuch as he thinkes,

may not giue a diſtaſte, an enemy vtters his opinion boldly, and if any act, miſbeſeeming vertue, ſpring from a man, he will be ſure to finde it, and blowe it abroad. So that if a man cannot know by his friends, wherein he offends; his enemie will bee ſo much his friend, as to ſhew him his folly, and how hee fayles. 'Twas a good ſpeech of Diogenes, Wee haue need of faithfull friends, or ſharpe enemies. Euery man hath vſe of a monitor: yet I ſee in all, ſuch a naturall and wilfull blindneſſe through ſelfe-loue, that euery man

is angry when his enemy reuiles him, though iuſtly: and all pleaſed, when a friend commends, though his Encomion be falſe, and deſertleſſe. I will entertaine both with an equall vvelcome: neither, without ſome meditation, and good vſe. If one praiſe me for the thing I haue not, my firſt following endeuour ſhall bee to get what hee commends mee for; leſt vvhen the time comes that I ſhould ſhew it, hee reape diſgrace, by reporting vntruths, and I loſe my credit, by wanting that, I am ſuppoſ'd to poſſeſſe. If for that I haue:

I will ſtriue to attaine it, in a meaſure more large: ſo ſhall his words be truth, and my deeds prooue them. If my enemy vpbraids me, let mee ſee if it bee iuſtly. It was an argument of much worth, in that renowned Macedonian, which made him (when he was told Nicanor rayled on him) ſay, I beleeue he is honeſt, and feare I haue deſeru'd it. If it bee ſo, I will labour to ſhake off that corruption, and be glad I haue ſo diſcouer'd it. But if iniuriouſly hee reports foule, it ſhall bee my ioy to beare contentedly, the vniuſt aſperſions of malicious

Cenſure: who euer was, that was not ſlandered? Though hee ſhould be beleeu'd awhile: yet at laſt, my actions would out-weigh his words, and the diſgrace reſt, with the intender of the ill. So that webbe of ſcandall, they would iniect vpon me, my life ſhal make a garment, for themſelues to weare. That ſtone that iniury caſts, euer in the end, lights on her ſelfe.
            
            
               LX.
               Two things a man ought to reſpect while hee liues heere; his inward integritie, and his outward vprightneſſe:

his piety toward God, and his reputation among men. The one is by performance of religious duties; the other by obedience to the lawes publike; the one makes his life famous; the other, his death happy: ſo both together, bring credit to the name, and felicitie to the ſoule. I wil ſo be alone, as I may be with God: ſo with company, as I may pleaſe the godly; that, report from good men, may ſpeake me vertuous. Thus whenſoeuer my breath ſhall bee made but aire, they ſhall beleeue, and I know, my ſelfe to bee

bleſſed. The death of a good man, is like the putting out of a wax perfumed Candle; hee recompences the loſſe of light, with the ſweet odour hee leaues behinde him.
            
            
               LXI.
               As it fareth between two friends, that haue been ancient familiars, yet dwelling aſunder, the one out of a careleſſe neglect, forgets and omits his vſuall duty of viſitation; and that ſo long, that at laſt he forbeares to goe at all: ſo their loues decay, and diminiſh: not proceeding from any Iarre, but

onely out of a ſtealing neglect, of renuing their loues: Euen ſo it fals out between God, &amp; the careleſſe Chriſtian: who when hee hath long omitted the duty of Prayer, and perhaps hath ſome ſmall motiues of a happy returne; the Diuell askes him with what face hee can now repaire vnto him, hauing been ſo long a ſtranger, both to him, and that holy duty. Diſ-reſpect is the way to loſe a friend: Hee that would not continue a friend, may neglect him, and haue his aime. Experience hath taught mee how dangerous neglience

hath beene, how preiudiciall: how ſoone it breeds cuſtome; how eaſily, and inſenſibly, cuſtome creepes into Nature; which much labour, and long endeuour cannot alter, or extirpate. In this cauſe there is no remedy but violence, and the ſeaſonable acceptance of opportunitie: The vigilant Mariner ſailes with the firſt winde, and though the gale blow ſomewhat aduerſely, yet once lanched forth, hee may either finde the blaſt, to wombe out his ſailes more fully, or elſe helpe himſelfe, by the aduantage of Sea-roome: whereas he,

that rides ſtill anchor'd in the Riuer, and will ſayle with none, but a wind faire, may either lye till hee loſe his voyage, or elſe rot his Barke in the Harbour. If a ſupine neglect run me on theſe ſands, a violent blaſt muſt ſet me afloat againe. In things that muſt bee, 'tis good to be reſolute. I know not whether I ſhall haue a ſecond call, or vvhether my firſt motion ſhall die Iſſueleſſe. I am ſure I muſt returne, or periſh: and therefore neceſſitie ſhall adde a foot to my weake deſires; yet I will ſtriue more to preuent this, by frequent

familiaritie; then beeing an eſtranged friend, to renue old loues: not that after errour, I would not returne; but that I would not ſtray at all.
            
            
               LXII.
               The good man hath many ſorrowes, that the wicked man neuer knowes of: his Offences, the ſinnes of the Time, the diſhonour of God, the dayly increaſing of Satans kingdome, and the preſent miſery of his fathers children: So that many times, when the prophane man is belching out his blaſphemies, hee inwardly

drops a teare in his ſoule, and is then petitioning heauen for his pardon. But to ſtrengthen him vnder the burthen of all theſe, he hath one ioy (that were all his ſorrowes doubled) could make him lightly beare them: and this is the truth of Gods promiſes. If I haue more troubles then another, I care not; ſo I haue more ioyes. God is no tyrant, to giue mee more then my load. I am well in the midd'ſt of all, while I haue that, which can vphold me in all. Who deſerues moſt honour of the ſluggard that hath kept his

bed warme, or the man that hath combated a monſter, and maſter'd him? Iob was not ſo miſerable in his afflictions, as hee was happy in his patience.
            
            
               LXIII.
               The enuious man is a ſquint-ey'd foole; and muſt needs want, both wit and honeſty: for as the wiſe man hath alwayes his mind fixed moſt on his owne affaires: ſo on the contrary, hee obſerues other mens; while thoſe that are propper and pertaining to himſelfe, inioy the leaſt of his counſell and care. He ſees

others, &amp; is blind at home; he lookes vpon others as if they were his, and neglects his own as if they were anothers. Againe, that which he intends for miſchiefe, &amp; a ſecret diſgrace; euer addes ſome ſplendour to the brightneſſe of his worth, he doth ſo vniuſtly maligne: as if wiſhing him infamous, he would labour to make him famous: or deſiring to kill him, would preſcribe him a Cordiall. Enuie, like the worme, neuer runs but to the faireſt and the ripeſt fruit: as a cunning Bloud-hound, it ſingles out the fatteſt Deere of the Herd:

'tis a pitchy ſmoake, which whereſoeuer we finde, wee may be ſure there is a fire of vertue. Abrahams riches were the Philiſtims enuie. Iacobs bleſſing bred Eſaus hate. He's a man of a ſtrāge conſtitution, whoſe ſicknes is bred by anothers health; as if nature had made him an Antipathite to vertue; If hee were good, or meritorious, hee would neuer grieue to haue a companion: but being bad, and ſhallow himſelfe, hee would damme vp the ſtreame, that is ſweete and ſilent: ſo by enuying another, for his radiant luſtre, he giues the

world notice, how dark and obſcure hee is in himſelfe. Yet to all theſe blurres, if it were a vice, that could adde but a dramme of content, there might ſomething bee ſpoken in way of Apology; But whereas all other vices are retained, either for pleaſure or profit; this only like a barren field, brings forth nothing, but bryars, and thornes: nothing but a meager leaneneſſe to the pined corps, accompanied with griefe, vexation, madneſſe. If another excell me in goodneſſe, I'le make him my example to imitate: not my blocke to ſtumble on.

If in wealth, I ſhall with him bleſſe God for his plenty, neuer grudge at thoſe faire fauors of heauen, God hath enough, both for mee, and him: but if he deſerues better, let mee applaud the diuine Iuſtice, not taxe it. If the vice it ſelfe ſhall not cauſe me to ſhunne it; yet the folly of it ſhall awe mee ſo much, as not to ſhake hands with a Serpent ſo foule: 'tis only the weakeſighted, that cannot endure the light. A ſtrong eye can vnhurt gaze the Sunne.
            
            
               
               LXIIII.
               The Councell the Philoſopher gaue the young men of Athens, may with much profit, be appli'd by a Chriſtian: viz. That they ſhould often view themſelues in a glaſse, that if they were faire, and well featured, they ſhould doe ſuch things, as ſhould bee beſeeming their amiable ſhape: but if foule, and ill fauored, that then they ſhould labour to ſalue the bodies blemiſhes, by the beauties of a mind, accoutred with the ornaments of vertue, &amp; good literature. The Law is the Chriſtians looking glaſſe;

which will ſhew all, without either flattery, or partiality. 'Tis a globe hung in the midd'ſt of the roome, vvhich will ſhew thee euery durty corner of thy ſoule. If thou haſt wandered in a darke way, this will tell thee thy aberrations: and put thee againe into true path. In it vvill I often behold my ſelfe: that if I bee free from the outward, actuall violation of it, any thing faire, or haue ſome beauties, I may ſtudy dayly, how to maintaine them, how to increaſe them. But if I find my ſelfe like a Leopard in his ſpots, or an Ethiopian
                  
in his hiew naturall, blacke and deformed (as I cannot be otherwiſe in my ſelfe) it ſhall yet make mee ſee my defects, and ſtriue to mend them. Knowne deformities incite vs to ſearch for remedy: The knowledge of the diſeaſe, is halfe the cure.
            
            
               LXV.
               There is no man ſo badly inclin'd, but would gladly bee thought good: no man ſo good already, but would be accounted ſomewhat better: Which hath oft made me ſit down with vvonder, at the choiſe excellēcy

of religious vertue; that euen thoſe which in heart contemne this Princeſſe; yet cannot but think it an honour, to be counted as attendants to her. Such a diuine, and amazing Maieſtie there is in Goodnes, that all deſire to weare her Liuery, though few care to performe her ſeruice: Like proud Courtiers, they would faine bee Fauorites, but ſcorne to attend. If then they cannot but affect her, that are her enemies; how ſhould they loue her that ioy to be friends? If I bee bad, let my care bee to bee good indeed, not thought

ſo. If any good parts already ſhine in me; I had rather in ſilence know my ſelfe better, then haue the vnconſtant world deeme me, either rare or excellent.
            
            
               LXVI.
               It was well ſaid of Dauid, The vvicked man ſhall not liue out halfe his dayes: for by his intemperancy, hee puls on himſelfe either diſeaſes, or iudgements; which cut him downe, before hee bee fully growne. And though his dayes bee multiplyed, he makes thē ſeeme much ſhorter, then indeed they are. For beſides the

beeing taken away by vntimely accidents, there bee two things that ſeeme to contract time, in a more compendious ſcope. Either exceſſiue and ſecure ioy: or elſe a ſure expectation of ill. One of theſe in euery wicked man hath reſidence: The former is too ordinarie: the latter not ſo common, nor fully ſo dangerous. The firſt hath his conſcience ſo caſt in a ſleepe, that it feeles not thoſe priuy and perillous wounds, that ſinne impaires it withal. All is frolicke, iocund, merry: and he ſwimmes in the fulleſt delights inuention can

procure him: his eye's inchanted with laſciuious obiects; his eare charmed with ſcurrilous talke; his taſte glutted with luxurious ryots; his ſmell filled with artificiall perfumes; and his armes heated with the wanton imbraces of luſt: euery ſence hath his ſeuerall ſubiect of ſolace: and while in all theſe, his affections are wholly taken vp in the preſent apprehenſion of pleaſure; how can hee count of the precipitate pace of time, that like an Arrow, from a ſtrong bent Bow, ſings with the ſpeed of his courſe? If his delights

would giue him leiſure, to meditate a little on this, he might be ſo much himſelf, as to know how his time poſteth: But letting it paſſe, as a thing vnthought of, his end ſteales on him, vnlook't for, vnwelcome, vnawares: and all thoſe voluptuous merriments, wherein in his life-time, he imbathed himſelfe: now ſeeme as a day that is paſt, whoſe Sunne declin'd at noone. But if otherwiſe, this ſenſualitie blinds him not, or that his conſcience be awake alreadie: then alas! how timerous and terrifi'd he is, with the expectation of his

doome, and finall confuſion? wiſhing that hee were either ſome ſenſleſſe ſtone, that the bitter throes and pangs of deſpaire might not feelingly pierce him; or elſe that he had ſuch wings, as could procure his eſcape from death, and marrowſearching Iudgement. So like a condemned man, that knowes the date of his dayes, hee lyes telling the clocke, and counting the houre; which he ſpends, in wiſhing euery day a yeere, euery houre a day, euery minute an houre, that ſtill he might awhile inioy the ſweet poſſeſſion of his deare

and beloued life. Thus either while his ſoule cleaues to the midd'ſt of his mirth, his way beguiles him: or elſe while he quiuers with the conſideration of the ſhame that attends him, he ſailes with ſuch feare, that he mindes not his voyage; ſo is ſuck't into Gulfe, e're euer hee be aware. A full ſwinge in pleaſure, is the way to make man ſenſeleſſe: A confident perſwaſion of vnauoidable miſery is a ready path to deſpaire. Theſe potions that are good but taſted, are mortal ingurgitated. Pleaſure taken as Phyſick, is like a cordiall

to a weakened body: and an expedient thought of our diſſolution, may bee as a corroſiue plaiſter to eate away the deadneſſe of the fleſh. Both are commendably vſefull. I will neither be ſo Iouiall, as to forget the end; nor ſo ſad, as not to remember the beginning of life, God.
            
            
               XLVII.
               Though Prayer ſhould bee the key of the day, and the locke of the night: yet I hold it more needfull in the morning, then when our bodies do take their repoſe. For howſoeuer ſleepe

be the Image, or ſhadow of death, &amp; when the ſhadow is ſo neere, the ſubſtance cannot be farre: yet a man at reſt in his chamber, is like a ſheepe impenn'd in the fold; ſubiect onely to the vnauoidable, and more immediate hand of GOD: whereas in the day, when hee roues abroad in the open and wide paſtures, he is then expoſed to many more vnthought of accidents, that contingently and caſually occurre in the way: Retiredneſſe is more ſafe then buſineſſe: who beleeues not a ſhip ſecurer in the Bay, then in the middeſt

of the boyling Ocean? Beſides, the morning to the day, is as youth to the life of a man: if that be begun well, commonly his age is vertuous: otherwiſe, God accepts not the latter ſeruice, when his enemy ioyes in the firſt diſh. Hee that loues chaſtity, will neuer marry her, that hath liued a Harlot in youth. Why ſhould God take thy dry bones, when the diuell hath ſuck't the marrow out?
            
            
               LXVIII.
               GOD hath left three books to the world, in each of which hee may eaſily be

found: The Booke of the Creatures, the book of Conſcience, &amp; his written Word. The firſt ſhewes his omnipotency. The ſecond his Iuſtice: the third his mercy, and goodneſſe. So though there bee none of them ſo barren of the rudiments of knowledge, but is ſufficient to leaue all without excuſe, apologies: yet in them all, I find all the good, that euer either the Heathen, or the Chriſtian hath publiſht abroad. In the firſt, is all Naturall Philoſophy: in the ſecond, all Morall Philoſophy: in the third, all true Diuinitie. To thoſe admirable

Pillars of all humane learning, (the Philoſophers) God ſhew'd himſelfe in his omnipotency and iuſtice, but ſeemed as it wete to conceale his mercy: to vs Chriſtians he ſhines in that which out-ſhines all his workes, his Mercy: Oh! how ſhould we regratulate his fauours for ſo immenſe a benefit, wherin ſecluding himſelfe from others, hee hath wholly imparted himſelfe to vs? In the firſt of theſe I will admire his workes, by a ſerious meditation of the wonders in the Creatures. In the ſecond, I will reuerence his

iuſtice, by the ſecret and inmoſt checks of the conſcience. In the third imbrace his loue, by laying hold on thoſe promiſes, wherein he hath not onely left mee meanes to know him, but to loue him, reſt in him, &amp; inioy him for euer.
            
            
               LXIX.
               If the fault be not in the miſapplication, then is it true that Diogenes ſpake of Learning; That, It makes yong men ſober, old men happie, poore men rich, and rich men honorable. Yet in any, without grace, it proues a double miſchiefe; there is

nothing more peſtilent, thē a ripe wit applyed to lewdneſſe. Becauſe hee that knowes himſelfe to bee quicke and acute, relyes on his own braine, for euaſion from all his villanies; and is drawne to the practice of much vice, by the too much preſuming on his own dexteritie. Ability &amp; a wicked will, is fuell to burne the world with; wit and wantonneſſe are able to intice a chaſte one. Reſolution and policy can caſt broyles in Chriſtendome, and put ciuill men into ciuill warres; if you beleeue not this, examine the Ieſuite. On the

contrary, where grace guides knowledge, and Religion hath the reines of Art: there, though on earth, the man is made heauenly; and his life is truely Angelicall, He does good by the inſtinct of Grace, and that good hee doth well, by the ſkilfull direction of Learning. Religion is as Grammar, that ſhewes him the word, and the ground: while knowledge, like Rhetoricke, doth polliſh it with beſeeming ornaments. He that giues almes, do's good, but he that giues willingly to the needy, and in ſeaſon does better. I vvill ſet my

ſelfe to attaine both: for as he can neuer be a good Orator, that wants either Grammar, or Rhetoricke: So there is no man can bee a compleat Chriſtian, without Grace, and ſome knowledge. Vzzah intended vvell, but did not know ſo; &amp; want of goodnes ſpoil'd Achitophels Councell. How can wee either deſire or loue him that wee doe nor know? ſince affectus motus eſt Cordis, à notitia &amp; cognitione obiecti, ex
                        •…
                     citatus.
               
            
            
               
               LXX.
               The couetous man cannot bee a true or faithfull friend to any: for while he loues his money better thē his friend, what expectation can there bee of the extent of his liberality? In aduerſity, and the time of tempeſt, when he ſhould be a hauen to reſt in, and an Alter Idem; he will either like the Crocodile ceaze on him in the fall, and take the aduantage of his neceſſities: or elſe out of a lothneſſe to loſe any thing by his disburſement, rather ſee him macerated by a conſuming

want, then any way ſend him a ſalue for diſtreſſe. Words from a dead man, and deeds of charity from a man couetous, are both alike rare, and hard to come by. 'Tis a miracle if he ſpeakes at all; but if hee doth breake ſilence, 'tis not without terrour &amp; amazement to the hearers. A couetous mans kindneſſe, is like the fowlers ſhrap wherin he caſts meat, not out of charity, to relieue them; but trecherie to inſnare thē. He reaches thee bread in one hand and ſhewes it; but keepes a ſtone in the other and hides it. If yet his courteſies were

without danger, I would rather indure ſome extremitie, then bee beholding to the almes of Auarice. He that ouer-values his benefit, neuer thinkes hee hath thanks ſufficient. I had better ſhift hardly, then owe to an inſatiable Creditor.
            
            
               LXXI.
               I haue ſeene ſome high minded royſters, ſcornfully contemne the lowly poore of Chriſt; as if they were out of the reach of the ſhattering wind of Iudgement, or thought it an impoſſibility, euer to ſtand in need of the helpe of ſuch humble

ſhrubbes. Fooles ſo to contemne thoſe, whoſe ayde they may after vvant: 'tis no badge of Nobility to deſpiſe an inferiour. Magnanimity and humility are Cohabitants: Courteſie is one of the faireſt Iems in a Crowne; 'twas Caeſars glory, to ſaue his Countreymen, which liues ſtil in that ſpeech, vvhich ſayes, he pardoned more, then hee ouercame: True Honour is like the Sunne, that ſhines as well to the Peaſant in the field, as the Monarch in his throne: he that withholds his clemency, becauſe the ſubiect is baſe, denies a remedy

to his wounded foot; becauſe 'tis an inferior part ſo he may iuſtly after complaine and want it: when the Lyon was catched in a ſnare, 'twas not the ſpatious Elephant, but the little Mouſe, that reſtor'd him his wonted liberty: though the head guides the hand, the hand defends the head.
            
            
               LXXII.
               As ſudden paſſions are moſt violent; ſo ſudden occaſions of ſinne are moſt dangerous: for while the ſences are ſet vpon by vnthought of obiects, reaſon wants time to call a Counſell

to determine how to reſiſt the aſſault: 'tis a faire booty makes many a thiefe, that if he had miſſed of this accident, would perhaps haue liu'd honeſtly. Opportunity is a wooer, that none but heauen can conquer. Humanity is too weake a ſpell for ſo powerfull a charme: ſhee caſts a fury into the bloud, that will teare out a way, though the ſoule bee loſt by it. The racke is eaſier then her importunity; flames are ſnowbals to it: ſure if the Diuell would change his properties, he would put himſelfe into this ſubtill thing: ſhe

puls vs with a thouſand chaines; at euery nerue ſhe hangs a poize, to draw vs to her ſorcery: and many times in our gaine, wee are loſt for euer. What, tortures cannot force vs to, ſhe will ſmoothly perſwade: ſhee breakes all bonds, lawes, reſolutions, oathes. Wiſe was the abſtinence of Alexander, from the ſight of Darius his daughters; leſt their beauty ſhould incite him to folly: ſhee runnes vs into forbidden errors, &amp; makes vs ſo deſperate, as to dare any thing: If ſhee offer mee her ſeruice to ill, Ile either kicke her as a bawd to vice,

or elſe vvinke, vvhen ſhee ſhewes mee her painting. Occaſion is a witch, and I'le be as heedfull in auoyding her; as I vvill bee vvary to eſchew a ſinne. But if I bee conſtrained to heare the Syren ſing, Vliſses was wiſe, when hee ty'd himſelfe to the maſt.
            
            
               LXXIII.
               My hatred to my enemy ſhall be but in part, my loue to my friend, whole and intire: for howſoeuer I may hate my enemies vices, and his ill conditions; yet will I loue his perſon, both as he is a man, and my

brother. His deteſtation is too deepe, that will burne his linnen, becauſe 'tis foule; they may both returne to their former purity, and then to hate, is ſinfull. But as for my friend, I will loue both his perſon, and his qualities: his qualities firſt, and for them his perſon. Yet in neither will I ſo hate, as to bee a foe to goodneſſe; nor ſo loue, as to foſter Iniquity: 'Tis a queſtion which is the worſt of the two, to bee vices friend, or vertues enemie.
            
            
               
               LXXIV.
               Next God, the good man is the onely friend; for when all other ſlinke out of the way, hee onely is a ſecure harbour for a ſhipwrackt ſoule to ride in; If he be vpright that be falne in diſtreſſe, he then relieues him, as a brother, as a member: If lewd, yet neceſſity induceth a commiſeration, and ſeeing the glorious Impreſſe of the Almighties image in him, hee can not, but for his Fathers ſake, affect him. If hee be poore, of God's making, by the

vnauoidable deſignement of a ſupreme prouidence, nature incites a reliefe: For he knowes not how ſoone, a like lot may fall in his owne ground. The ſame ſunne ſaw Iob both rich, and poore to a Prouerbe. If his owne ill courſes haue brought his decay; hee is not ſo obdurate, and flinty, but that hee can afford him a hand of compaſſion, to ſtrengthen him a little, in the midd'ſt of diſaſters: hoping that his charitie may either worke his returne, or ſtay him from ſpeedy ruine. If he be ill, he is a Magiſtrate, to correct and reclaime

him: if good, he is a father, to vphold, and loue him: if rich, he reades him a lecture of moderation, and diſcreet diſpoſure; tels him, not poſſeſſion, but vſe, diuitiates a man more truely: if poore, he ſets him to Schoole with Paul there to learne, Content is plenty; tel's how that Pagan Cynick could laugh at riches, when he call'd them nothing but fortunes vomit; if wiſe, hee is his delight, and ſolace; euen the Granar, where he leaues his load, and lockes his ſtore: if ignorant, hee inſtructs him with the Oracles of God, dictitates ſentences

vnto him, &amp; ſpeakes all, tanquam ex tripode. Euery way I finde him ſo beneficiall, that the pious vvill not liue, but with him: and the badde man cannot liue without him. Who had ſalu'd the offending Iſraelites, had not Moſes ſtood vp for to intercede? it ſhall more ioy mee to liue with Chriſtians, then men.
            
            
               LXXV.
               The hard-hearted man hath miſery almoſt in perfection: and there is none more wretched, then a man with a conſcience feared. Other ſinners march in the

high-way to ruine; but hee as hee goes, builds a wall at his backe, that hee cannot retire to the tent. Neither Mercies, nor Iudgements, winne him at all. Not mercies: thoſe his pride makes him thinke but his due, and while they are but common ones, they paſſe away with his cōmon thoughts. Benefits ſeldome ſinke deepe in obdurate minds: 'tis the ſoft nature that is ſooneſt taken with a courteſie. Not Iudgements; for either he reuerberates them back, before they pierce, as a wal of ſteele doth a bluntheaded arrow: or if they

doe perhaps find entrance, like the Elephant, with the convulſion of his nerues, &amp; his bodies contraction; hee caſts out the ſhaft that ſticks within him: ſo ſtill he reſts vnmollified, for all this raine, and haile. Warnings to peruerſe diſpoſitions, are the meanes to make them worſe: Thoſe plagues, and wonders that would haue melted a milder ſoule, only reduced Pharaoh's to a more hard, and deſperate temper. Strange! that hee ſhould locke out of his own good, with ſo ſtrong a key, ſo ſure a Ward; when euery vice that defiles the minde,

findes both ready and free welcome. If I liue in ſinne, God's firſt call is mercy; I had better goe willingly, then be led by conſtraint: 'tis fit hee ſhould know the ſmart of torture, that nothing will cauſe to confeſſe but the Racke: if I finde God whips mee with any ſenſible ſtroke, I will ſearch the cauſe, then ſeeke the cure: ſuch blowes are the phyſicke of a bleeding ſoule: but neglected, my ſinne will be more, and my puniſhment: 'tis in vaine to bee ſtubborne with God: hee that can cruſh vs to nothing, can turne vs to any

thing: let mee rather returne ſpeedily, and preuent Iudgements, then ſtay obſtinately and pull downe more: as 'tis a happy feare, which preuents the offence, and the rod: ſo that is a miſerable valour; which is bold to dare the Almighty.
            
            
               LXXVI.
               Some mens Cenſures are like the blaſts of Rammes Hornes, before the walles of Iericho: all the ſtrength of a mans vertue they lay leuell at one vtterance: when all their ground is onely a conceited fancie, without any certaine baſis
                  
to build on. What religious minde will not vvith amazement ſhudder, at the peremptorie concluſions, where they haue ſet their period? Wondring, Man that knowes ſo little, ſhould yet ſo ſpeake, as if he were priuy to all. I confeſſe, a man may roue by the outward lineaments, what common inclinations rule within: yet that Philoſopher did more wiſely, that ſeeing a faire face, with a tongue ſilent, bade him ſpeake that he might ſee him. For the cheeke may be dimpled with a pleaſing ſmile, while the heart throbs with

vndiſcerned dolors: and as a cleere face ſhewes not alwayes a ſound body: no more is an ingenuous look, alwayes the enſigne of a minde vertuous I wil onely walke in Chriſt's path, and learne by their fruits to know them: where I want experience, charitie bids mee thinke the beſt, and leaue what I know not, to the Searcher of heart's. Miſtakes, Suſpect, and Enuie, often iniure a cleere fame, there is leaſt danger in a charitable conſtruction;

                     In part hees guilty of the wrong that's done,
                     Which doth beleeue thoſe falſe reports, that runne.
                  
               
               
                  
I will neither beleeue all I heare, nor ſpeake all I beleeue; A mans good name is like a milke-white ball, that will infinitely gather ſoyle in toſſing. The act of Alexander in this cauſe, merits an eternall memory: that hauing read a Letter with his Fauorite Hephaeſtion, wherein his mother calumniated Antipater, tooke his Signet from his finger, and appreſſed his lips with it: Coniuring as it were, the ſtrict ſilence of anothers diſgrace: Oh Alexander! this very action was enough to make thee famous, who ſhould not in

this admire, and imitate thee? A deſire to diſgrace another, cannot ſpring from a good roote: Malice and baſeneſſe euer dwell with calumnie. I will iudge well of euery man, whom his owne bad life ſpeakes not ill of: if he be bad, I'le hope well; what know I ſhow his end may proſper? I had better labour to amend him to himſelfe, then by publiſhing his vices, make him odious to others. If hee be good, and belongs to God, how can I chuſe but offend much, when I ſpeake ill of a child that is indeared to ſuch a fathers affection?

God loues his owne tenderly; and whoſoeuer offers a diſgrace to them, ſhall be ſure to pay for't, either by teares, or torment.
            
            
               LXXVII.
               There are three things eſpecially that a Chriſtian ſhould know: His owne Miſery: Gods Loue: his owne thankefull Obedience. His miſery, how iuſt; Gods loue, how free, how vndeſerued; his own thankfulneſſe, how due, how neceſſary. Conſideration of one, ſucceſſiuely begets the apprehenſion of all: Our miſery ſhewes vs his Loue:

his Loue cals for our acknowledgement. Want makes a bounty weightier: if wee thinke on our needs, wee cannot but admire his mercies: how dull were we, if wee ſhould not value the reliefe of our neceſſities? he cannot but eſteeme the benefit, that vnexpectedly helpes him in his deepeſt diſtreſſe: That Loue is moſt to be prized, whoſe onely motiue is goodneſſe. The thought of this, will forme a diſpoſition gratefull: who can meditate ſo vnbottomed a loue, and not ſtudy for a thankefull demeanour? His minde is

croſſe to Nature, that requites not affection with gratitude. All fauours haue this ſucceſſe, if they light on good ground, they bring forth thankes. Let mee firſt thinke my miſery, without my Sauiours mercy: next, his mercy, without my merits: and from the meditation of theſe two, my ſincerer thankes will ſpring. Though I cannot conceiue of the former as they are; Infinite, and beyond my thought: yet will I ſo ponder them, as they may enkindle the fire of my vnfained, and zealous thanksgiuing. That time is vvell

ſpent, wherein wee ſtudie thankefulneſſe.
            
            
               LXXVIII.
               Though the fooles of the world think outward beauty the only Iewell that deſerueth wearing; yet the wiſe man counts it but an accident; that can neither adde, nor diminiſh, to the worth of vertue, as ſhe is in her ſelfe: ſo as hee neuer eſteemes her more, or leſſe, but as he findes her accompliſht with diſcretion, honeſty, and good parts. If my friend be vertuous, and nobly-minded, my ſoule ſhall loue him, howſoeuer

his body be framed: and if beauty make him amiable, I needs muſt like him much the better: the Sunne is more glorious in a cleere sky, then when the Horizon is clouded. Beauty is the wit of Nature put into the frontiſpice. If there be any humane thing may teach faith reaſon, this is it: in other things, we imagine more then wee ſee: in this we ſee more then wee can imagine. I haue ſeene (and yet not with a partiall eye) ſuch features, &amp; ſuch mixtures, as I haue thought impoſſible for either Nature to frame, or Art to counterfet;

yet in the ſame face, I haue ſeene that, which hath out-gone them both, the Countenance. Oh! if ſuch glory can dwell with corruption, what celeſtiall excellencies are in the Saints aboue? who would not gaze himſelfe into admiration, when he ſhall ſee ſo rich a treaſure, in ſo pure a Cabinet, vnmatched vertue, in matchleſſe beauty? But if my friends body hath more comelineſſe, then his ſoule goodneſſe; I like him the worſe, for beeing but outwardly faire. Wickedneſſe in beauty, is a traytor of the Bed-chamber; poiſon

in ſweet meates. A vitious ſoule, in a beautifull body, I account as a Ieſuite in the Roabes of a Courtier; or ſomewhat more fitly, a Papiſt, that will goe to Church.
            
            
               LXXIX.
               As I thinke there are many, worſe then they ſeeme; ſo I ſuppoſe there are ſome, better then they ſhew: and theſe are like the growing Cheſnut, that keepes a ſweet, &amp; nutrimentall kernell, included in a rough, and prickely huske. The other, as the Peach, hold a rugged and craggy ſtone,

vnder the couer of a Veluet Coat. I would not deceiue a good man either way: both offer a wrong to vertue: The one ſhewes her worſe then ſhe is; dulling her beauty with dimme colours, and preſenting her, with a harder fauour then her owne: The other doth varniſh ouer the rottenneſſe of Vice, and makes goodneſſe but the vizor for hypocriſie. Either are condemnable: painting the face, is not much worſe, then wilfull ſoiling it. He is as well a murtherer, that accuſeth himſelfe falſely, as he that did the act, and denies

it. One would obſcure goodneſſe, with Vice; the other would palliate Vice, with goodneſſe. Fraud is in both: and I am ſure no Plea can make deceit allowable. I will therefore ſtriue to auoid both; and with Chryſoſtom either ſeeme as I am, or bee as I ſeeme. But if I ſhould erre on one ſide, I had rather reſemble a plaine Country-man, that goes in ruſſet, and is rich in reuenues; then a riotous Courtier, that weares glorious apparell, without mony in's purſe.
            
            
               
               LXXX.
               A Chriſtians voyage to heauen, is a ſentence of three ſtops; Comma, Colon, Periodus. He that repents, is come to the Comma, and begins to ſpeake ſweetly, the language of ſaluation; but if he leaues there, God vnderſtands not ſuch abrupt ſpeeches: ſorrow alone, cannot expiate a Pyrats robberies; hee muſt both leaue his theft, and ſerue his Country, ere his Prince wil receiue him to fauour. 'Tis he that confeſſeth &amp; forſakes his ſinne, that ſhal find mercy: 'tis his leauing his wickedneſſe,

that is as his Colon, and carries him halfe way to heauen. Yet heere alſo is the Clauſe vnperfect, vnles he goes on to the practice of righteouſneſſe, which as a Period knits vp all, and makes the ſentence full. Returne, and penitence is not ſufficient for him, that hath fled from his Soueraignes banner; hee muſt firſt doe ſome valiant act, before by the law of Armes, hee can bee reſtored to his former bearing. I will not content my ſelfe with a Comma; Repentance helps not, when ſinne is renued; nor dare I make my ſtay at a Colon; not

to doe good, is to commit euill, at leaſt by omiſſion of what I ought to doe: before I come to a Period, the conſtant practice of piety, I am ſure, I cannot bee ſure of complete glory. If I did all ſtrictly, I were yet vnprofitable; and if God had not appointed my faith to perfect mee, miſerable. If hee were not full of mercies, how vnhappy a creature were man?
            
            
               LXXXI.
               Euen from naturall reaſon, is the wicked man prou'd to bee ſonne vnto Satan, and heire of hell, and

torments. For not to ſpeake of heauen, (where the bleſſed are happy, and al things beyond apprehenſion excellent,) euen in the Firmament, we ſee how all things are preſerued by a glorions order: the Sun hath his appointed circuit, the Moone her conſtant change, and euery Planet &amp; Starre their proper courſe and place. For as they are called fixed Starres, not becauſe they moue not at all, but becauſe their motion is inſenſible, and their diſtances euer the ſame, by reaſon of the ſlow motiō of the eighth ſphere, in which they are: So they

are not called wandring Planets, for that they moue in an vncertaine irregularitie; but becauſe thoſe ſeuen inferiour Orbes, wherin they are ſet, are diuerſly carried about; which makes them appeare ſometimes in one place, ſomtimes in another, yet euer in the ſettled place of their owne Orbe, whoſe Reuolutions alſo, are in moſt ſtrict, and euer certain times▪ The earth likewiſe hath her vnſtirred Station; the Sea is confin'd in limits; and in his ebbings, &amp; flowings, dances as it were after the influence, and aſpect of the Moone; whereby it is

both kept from putrifaction, and by ſtruggling with it ſelfe, from ouer-flowing the land. In this world, Order is the life of Kingdoms, Honours, Arts: and by the excellency of it, all things flouriſh, and thriue. Onely in hell is confuſion, horrour, and amazing diſorder. From whence the wicked man ſhewes himſelf ſprung, for there is nothing that like him, liues ſo irregular, and out of compaſſe. Diſorder is a bird of the Diuels hatching: I feare leſt thoſe that rent the Church for Ceremonie, haue ſome affinitie with that prince of

miſ-rule: wee oft finde the parents diſpoſition, though not propagated to the child, yet followed by him. I do not cenſure, but doubt. We haue ſeldome knowne him good, that refuſeth to obey good orders. Who can expect a fruitfull crop, when the field is ſomtimes blaſted with Lightning, ſometime drenched with invndations, but neuer cheriſhed with a kindly Sunne? things vncapable of a true forme, are euer mending: yet euer vnperfect: when the rankes are broken, the victory is in hazzard. One bad voice, can put twenty

good ones out of tune. I will firſt order my minde by good reſolution; then keepe it ſo, by a ſtrong conſtancie. Thoſe Souldiers dyed brauely, that where they ſtood to fight, they fell to death.
            
            
               LXXXII.
               In euery man there bee three things that encounter our Conſideration; The Mind, the Behauiour, the Perſon. A groſſe blemiſh in any of which, ſticke ſome diſgrace on the vnhappy owner. If the Mind be vitious, though the carriage bee faire, and Perſon comely; Honeſty eſteemes

not outward parts, where inward Grace is wanting. If his mind be good, &amp; carriage clowniſh, his outward bad demeanour makes his inward worth ridiculous: and admit he hath both deſeruing applauſe; yet a ſurfeited and diſeaſed body, makes al diſregarded; while the approch of his preſence may proue preiudiciall, infectious, noiſome. To remedy the defects of all theſe, I finde three noble Sciences: Diuinity, Philoſophy, Phiſick: Diuinity, for the Soule; to preſerue that vnſtain'd, and; holy; as alſo to indue it with vnderſtanding; for

God with his Graces, inſtils Knowledge: it was the keeping of his Law, made Dauid wiſer then thoſe that taught him. Diuine knowledge is not without humane; when God giues the firſt, in ſome meaſure hee giues both: and therefore we ſeldome finde the ignorant man honeſt; if hee bee mentally, yet hee failes expreſſiuely. Philoſophie, for his manners and demeanour, in the many contingent things of this life; to fit him both with decent Complements, and ſufficicient ſtayednes: neither ſauouring of Curioſity, nor

ruſticity: nor was euer Religion found a foe to good manners; For ſhee ſhines brighteſt in a braue behauiour, ſo it bee ſtill free from affectation, flattery. Philoſophy is the ſalt of life; that can dry vp the crude humors of a nouice, &amp; correct thoſe peſtilent qualities wherewith nature hath infeſted vs: which was ingenuouſly confeſt by Socrates, when Zopyrus by his Phiſiognomy, pronounced him fouly vicious. Phyſicke, to know the ſtate of the body; both to auoyde diſtempers in health, and to recouer health, in wearying

diſeaſes; 'tis the reſtitution of decaying nature: when ſhe is falling, this giues her a hand of ſuſtenance: it puts away our blemiſhes, reſtores our ſtrength, and rids vs of that, which would rid vs of our liues. In all theſe though a man bee not ſo learned, as to teach them to others; yet in all I would know ſo much, as might ſerue to direct mee, in mine owne occaſions. 'Tis commendable to know any thing that may beare the title of Good; but for theſe ſo pleaſing Sciences, I will rather ſtudy with ſome paines, then want experience

in things ſo neceſſary. Thus ſhall I fit my mind for God, my body to my mind, my behauiour to both, and my friends.
            
            
               LXXXIII.
               The diſtempers of theſe times, would make a wiſe man both merry, and mad: merry, to ſee how vice flouriſhes but a while, and being at laſt fruſtrate of all her faire hopes, dyes in a deiected ſcorne; which meetes with nothing in the end, but beggery, baſeneſſe, and contempt. To ſee how the world is miſtaken in opinion, to ſuppoſe thoſe

beſt, that are wealthieſt. To ſee how the world thinkes to appall the minde of nobleneſſe with miſery; while true reſolution laughs at their poore impotency, and ſlights euen the vtmoſt ſpight of tyranny. To ſee how men buy Offices at high rates, which when they haue, prooue gins to catch their ſoules in, and ſnare their eſtates, and reputations. To ſee how fooliſhly men coozen themſelues of their ſoules, while they thinke they gaine, by their cunning defrauding another. To ſee how the proiectors of the world,

like the ſpoke of the Wheele of SESOSTRIS Chariot, are tumbled vp and downe, from beggery, to worſhip; from worſhip, to honour; from honour, to baſeneſſe againe. To ſee what idle complements are currant among ſome that affect the Phantaſticke garbe: as if friendſhip were nothing but an apiſh ſalute, gloſſed ouer with the varniſh of a ſmooth tongue. To ſee a ſtrutting prodigall ouer-looke a region, with his wauing plume; as if he could as eaſily ſhake that, as his feather; yet in priuate creep like a crouching Spaniell,

to his baſe muddy proſtitute. To ſee how pot-valour thunders in a Tauerne, and appoints a Düell, but goes away, and giues mony to haue the quarrell taken vp vnderhand. Mad on the other ſide, to ſee how Vice goes trapperd with rich furniture, while poore Vertue hath nothing but a bridle and ſaddle, which onely ſerue to increaſe her bondage. To ſee Machiauel's tenents held as Oracles; honeſty reputed ſhallowneſſe; Iuſtice bought and ſold; as if the world went about to diſprooue Zorobabel, and

would make him confeſſe, mony to bee ſtronger then Truth. To ſee how flatterie creepes into fauour vvith Greatneſſe, while plaine dealing is thought the enemie of ſtate, and honour. To ſee how the Papiſts (for promotion of their owne Religion) inuent lyes, and print them; that they may not onely cozen the preſent age, but gull poſterity, with forged actions. To ſee how well-meaning ſimplicitie is foot-ball'd. To ſee how Religion is made a Polititians vizor; which hauing help't him to his purpoſe, hee caſts by, like

Sunday apparell, not thought on all the weeke after. And which vvould mad a man more then all, to know all this, yet not know how to helpe it. Theſe would almoſt diſtract a man in himſelfe. But ſince I finde they are incurable; I'le often pray for their amendment in priuate, neuer declaime, but when I am call'd to't. Hee loſeth much of his comfort, that without a iuſt deputation, thruſts himſelfe into danger. Let mee haue that once, and it ſhall neuer grieue mee, to die in a warrantable Warre.
            
            
               
               LXXXIV.
               To reuenge a wrong, is both eaſie, and vſuall; and as the world thinkes, ſauours of ſome nobleneſſe: but Religion ſayes the contrarie, and tels vs 'tis better to neglect it, then requite it. If any man ſhall willingly offer me an iniury, hee ſhall know, I can ſee it; but withall, he ſhall ſee, I ſcorne it: vnleſſe it be ſuch, as the bearing is an offence. What need I doe that, which his owne minde will doe for me? If he hath done ill, my reuenge is within him: if not, I am too blame in ſeeſeeking

it. If vnwillingly he wrongs me, I am as readie to forgiue, as hee to ſubmit: for I know, a good minde will bee more ſorrowfull, then I ſhall be offended: With his own hand hee rebateth his honour, that kills a priſoner humbly yeelding: Who but a Deuill, or a Pope, could trample on a proſtrate Emperour?
            
            
               LXXXV.
               I obſerue none more lyable to the world's falſe cenſure, then the vpright nature, that is honeſt, and free. For many times, while he thinkes no ill, hee

cares not though the world ſees the worſt of his actions; ſuppoſing he ſhall not be iudged worſe, then hee knowes himſelfe: but the world beeing bad it ſelfe, gueſſes at others by his owne: ſo concludes bad, of thoſe that are not. Some haue I knowne thus iniur'd; that out of a minde not acquainted with ill, haue by a free demeanor, had infinite ſcandals caſt vpon them; when I know, the ignorant and ill world is much miſtaken, and coniectures falſe. I will neuer cenſure till I ſee grounds apparant: hee that thinks ill without this,

I dare pawne my ſoule, is either bad, or would be ſo, if opportunitie but ſeru'd him. In things vncertaine, a badde conſtruction muſt needs flow from a badde minde: who could imagine priuate vice which they doe not ſee, by a harmeleſſe carriage, which they doe ſee, vnleſſe either their own ill practice, or deſires, had prompted them? Vice as it is the Diuels iſſue; ſo in part it retaines his qualities; and deſiring others bad, beleeues them ſo. But vertue had a more heauenly breeding: ſhee is wary, leſt ſhee cenſure raſhly:

and had rather ſtraine to ſaue, then erre to condemne. If my life bee free from villany, and baſe deſignes, I know, the good will ſpeake no worſe then they ſee: as for thoſe that are lewd, their blacke tongues can neuer ſpot the faire of vertue: onely I could ſometimes grieue, to ſee how they wrong themſelues, by wronging others.
            
            
               LXXXVI.
               Euery man either is rich, or may bee ſo; though not all in one and the ſame

wealth. Some haue abundance, and reioyce in't: Some a competency, and are content: ſome hauing nothing, haue a minde deſiring nothing. Hee that hath moſt, wants ſomething: hee that hath leaſt, is in ſomething ſuppli'd; wherein the minde, which maketh rich, may well poſſeſſe him with the thought of ſtore. Who whiſtles out more content, then the low-fortun'd Plow-man, or ſings more merrily, then the abiect Coblar, that ſits vnder the ſtall? Content dwels with thoſe, that are out of the eye of the

world, whom ſhe hath neuer train'd with her gawds, her toyes, her lures. Wealth is like learning, wherein our greater knowledge, is onely a larger ſight of our wants. Deſires fulfilled, teach vs to deſire more: ſo wee that at firſt were pleaſed, by remouing from that, are now growne inſatiable. Wiſhes haue neither end; nor End. So in the midd'ſt of affluencie, wee complaine of penurie; which not finding, wee make. For to poſſeſſe the whole world with a grumbling minde, is but a little more ſpecious pouerty. If I

be not outwardly rich, I will labour to bee poore in crauing deſires; but in the vertues of the minde, (the beſt riches) I would not haue a man exceed me. He that hath a minde contentedly good, inioyeth in it boundleſſe poſſeſſions. If I be pleaſ'd in my ſelfe, who can adde to my happineſſe? as no man liues ſo happy, but to ſome his life would be burdenſome: ſo we ſhall finde none ſo miſerable, but wee ſhall heare of another, that would change calamities.
            
            
               
               LXXXVII.
               
                  To haue beene happie, is wretched; to bee happie, momentany; to may bee happy, doubtfull. All that the world yeelds, is either vncertainely good, or certainely ill. Euen his beſt cordials, haue ſome bitter ingredients in them; leſt fooliſh ſenſuality ſhould catch them with too greedie a hand. Wee ſhould ſurfet with their hony, if there were not gall intermingled. The reaſon of defect I finde in the obiect, which beeing earthly, muſt

be brittle, fading, vaine, imperfect: ſo though it may pleaſe, it cannot ſatisfie. Earth can giue vs but a taſte of pleaſure, not fill vs. What ſhee affoords, let me lawfully vſe; truſt to, neuer. He onely, that hath beene, is, and ſhall bee for euer, can make my paſt happineſſe preſent, my future certaine, and my preſent continue, if not as 'tis, better, and then for euer.
            
            
               LXXXVIII.
               A good name is among all externals, both the beſt, and moſt brittle bleſſing.

If it be true, that Difficilia quae pulchra, this is a faire beatitude. 'Tis the hardeſt both to get, and keepe: like a glaſſe of moſt curious workemanſhip, long a making, and broke in a moment. That which is not gained but by a continued habit of many vertues, is by one ſhort vitious action, loſt for euer. Nay, if it could onely vaniſh in this ſort, it would then by many be kept vntainted: If it could not be loſt but vpon certainties; If it were in our owne keeping; or if not in our own, in the hands of the wiſe

and honeſt; how poſſible were it to preſerue it pure? But alas! this is the miſerie, that it reſts vpon probabilities, which as they are hard to diſproue, ſo they are readie to perſwade: That it is in the hands of others, not our ſelues: in the cuſtodie not of the diſcreet, and good onely; but alſo of Fooles, Knaues, Villaines: Who though they cannot make vs worſe to ourſelues; yet how vile may they render vs to others? To vindicate it from the tongues of theſe, there is no remedie but a conſtant carefull diſcretion.

I muſt not onely be good, but not ſeeme ill: Appearance alone, which in good is too little, is in euill too much. He is a wilfull murtherer of his owne fame, that willingly appeares, in the ill action hee did not. 'Tis not enough to bee well liu'd, but well reported. When we know good fame a bleſſing, wee may eaſily in the contrary, diſcerne a curſe: whereof wee are iuſtly ſeized, while wee labour not to auoid it. I will care as well to bee thought honeſt, as to be ſo: my friends know mee by the actions they

ſee, ſtrangers, by the things they heare: the agreement of both, is the confirming my goodneſſe. The one is a good complexion; the other a good countenance: I deny not but they may bee ſeuerall; but they are then moſt gracefull, when both are ſeated together. It had beene well ſpoken of Caeſar, if hee had not put her away, when after tryall, and the crime cleered, hee ſaid, Caeſars wife ſhould not onely bee free from ſinne, but from ſuſpition. An ill name may bee free from diſhoneſtie, but not from ſome folly. Though

ſlanders riſe from others, we our ſelues oft giue the occaſion. The firſt beſt way to a good name, is a good life: the next, is a good behauiour.
            
            
               LXXXIX.
               All earthly delights I finde ſweeter in the expectation, then the inioyment: All ſpirituall pleaſures, more in fruition, then expectation. Thoſe carnall contentments that heere wee ioy in, the Diuell ſhewes vs through a proſpectiue glaſſe; vvhich makes them ſeeme both

greater, and neerer hand: when hee tooke Chriſt to the Mountaine, he ſhewed him all the Kingdomes, and the glory of them; but neuer mentions the troubles, dangers, cares, feares, vigilancies, which are as it were the thornes, wherewith a Crowne is lined. Oh! what mountaines of ioy doe wee caſt vp, while wee thinke on our earthly Canaan? whatſoeuer temporall felicitie wee apprehend, we cull out the pleaſures, and ouerprize them; the perils and moleſtations wee either not ſee, or not thinke of: like the fooliſh

man, that at a deare rate buyes a Monopoly, wherein hee counts the gaines, and ouer-caſts them; but neuer weighs the charges, nor the caſualtie, in making of him lyable both to the hatefull curſe of the people; and the ſeuere cenſure of a Parliament. Herein wee are all fooles, that ſeeing theſe Bladders, wee will blow them beyond their compaſſe. 'Tis Satans craft, to ſhew vs the inticing ſpots of this Panther, concealing the toruitie of her countenance. But when againe wee looke at heauenly things, like a cunning

Iuggler, he turnes the glaſſe; ſo detracts from thoſe faire proportions, the chiefe of their beauty, and worth: thoſe, we beleeue both leſſe, and more remote; as if hee would carrie vs in Winter, to ſee the pleaſures of a Garden. Thus the heart informed by abuſed ſences, is content to ſayle as they ſteere; ſo either tombes her ſelfe in the boſome of the waues; or cuts through the way to her enemies Country; where ſhee is quickly taken, ranſack't, and rifl'd of all. If this were not, how could wee be ſo heartleſſe

in purſuite of celeſtiall prizes, or what could breed ſo ſoone a loathing of that, which moſt we haue coueted, and ſweat to obtaine? If my mind grow enamoured on any ſublunarie happineſſe, I will coole it with this knowledge: and withall tell her, ſhee is happier in apprehending the taſte, without the Lees; then in drinking the Wine, that is yet vnfined. That felicitie which experience findes lame, and halting, Thought and ſuppoſition giue a perfect ſhape. But if the motions of my ſoule wheele toward any diuine

ſweet, my ſtrongeſt arguments ſhall perſwade a proceeding. Heere imaginations dark eye is too dimme, to fix vpon this Sunne. When I come to it, I am ſure I ſhall finde it tranſcending my thoughts: Till then, my faith ſhall bee aboue my reaſon, and perſwade mee to more then I know. Though fruition excludes faith, yet beliefe makes bleſſed. So I will beleeue, what yet I cannot inioy.
            
            
               
               XC.
               Euery mans actions are according to his mind, tedious or delightfull. For be it neuer ſo laborious and painefull, if the minde entertaines it with delight, the body gladly vndergoes the trouble, and is ſo farre at the mindes ſeruice, as not to complaine of the burthen. And though it be neuer ſo ful of pleaſure, that might ſmooth the ſences; yet if the mind diſtaſtes it, the content turnes to vexation, toyle. Deſire is a 
                     •
                  ind that againſt the tyde can

carry vs merrily; with it, make vs fly. How pleaſant would our life be, if we had not croſſe gales to thwart vs, various tydes to checke vs? With theſe, how full of diſtreſſe? yet in them, we often increaſe our ſorrows, by vainely ſtriuing againſt vnconquerable fate; when if we could but perſwade our minde, wee might much eaſe both it, and our body. That which is bad, though neuer ſo pleaſureable, I'le ſtriue to make my minde diſlike; that my body alſo may bee willing to forgoe that, which my mind hates. That which is good, and

ſhould be done, I'le learne to affect, and loue; howſoeuer my body refuſe. As my mind is better then it; ſo my care ſhall bee more to content it: but moſt to make it cōtent with goodnes, otherwiſe I had better croſſe it, then let it ſettle to vnlawfull ſolaces. I prefer this vnquietneſſe, before the other peace. That which is eaſie, Ile eaſily doe; that which is not, my mind ſhall make ſo. My life as it is full enough of trauaile; why ſhould I by my mindes loathing, make it ſeeme more difficult?
            
            
               
               XCI.
               I cannot know God as he is; if I could, I were vnhappy, and he not God. For then muſt that eternall omnipotencie of his be finite, and comprehenſible; elſe, how could the fleet dimenſions of the minde of man containe it? I admire the definition of Empedocles, who ſaid, God was a Sphere, whoſe Center was euery where, and Circumference no where. Though his full light bee inacceſſible, yet from this ignorance ſprings all my happineſſe, and ſtrongeſt

comfort. When I am ſo ingulfed in miſery, as I know no way to eſcape; God, that is ſo infinite aboue mee, can ſend a deliuerance, when I can neither ſee, nor hope it. He needes neuer deſpaire, that knowes he hath a friend, which at all aſſayes, can helpe him.
            
            
               XCII.
               If I were ſo puniſht as to liue here perpetually, I would wiſh to haue alwaies ſuch a mind, as I find after the conqueſt of a ſtrong temptation: then haue I as much happineſſe, as can be

found in this lifes moueables. The tryall firſt bewrayes the danger, then the eſcape vſhers in ſucceeding ioy: and all know, the Sun appeares more luſtrous to a priſoner that comes out of a Dungeon, then to him that dayly beholds his brightneſſe. When is wine ſo pleaſant as after a long thirſt? Beſides, the ſoule withdrawne from GOD, returnes in the end with comfort, and againe ſweetly cloſeth with her Maker; whoſe goodnes ſhe knowes it is, to make her ſo brauely victorious. We are neuer ſo glad of our friends

company, as when he returnes after tedious abſence. All the pleaſures that wee haue, relliſh better when wee come from miſeries; then, what a glory is it to a noble ſpirit, to haue endur'd and conquer'd? there being more ſweetneſſe in a hard victorie, where wee come off faire; then in the neglected pleaſures of a continuall peace. Thoſe Fowles taſte beſt, that we kill our ſelues in birding: what bread eates ſo well, as that which wee earne vvith labour? And indeed 'tis the way to make vs perfect; for as he can neuer

bee a good Souldier, that hath not felt the toyle of a battell: ſo he can neuer be a ſound Chriſtian, that hath not felt temptations buffets. Euery fire refines this gold. If I did finde none, I ſhould feare I were vices too much: or elſe that God ſaw me ſo weake, as I could not hold out the encounter: but ſeeing I do, the pleaſantneſſe of the fruit, ſhall furniſh me with patience, to abide the precedent bitterneſſe; This gone, I ſhall find it a felicity to ſay, I haue beene wretched.
            
            
               
               XCIII.
               Earth hath not any thing more glorious then ancient Nobility, when tis found vvith vertue. What barbarous mind will not reuerence that bloud, which hath vntainted run through ſo large a ſucceſſion of generations? Beſides, vertue addes a new ſplendor, vvhich together vvith the honor of his houſe, challengeth a reſpect from all. But bad greatneſſe, is nothing but the vigor of vice; hauing both minde and meanes to bee vncontrollably

lewd. A debauched ſonne of a Noble Familie, is one of the intollerable burthens of the earth, &amp; as hatefull a thing as hell: for all know, he hath had both example, and precept, flowing in his education; both which, are powerfull enough to obliterate a natiue illneſſe: yet theſe in him, are but auxiliaries to his ſhame, that vvith the brightneſſe of his Anceſtors, make his owne darkneſſe more palpable. Vice in the Sonne of an Ancient Family, is like a clowniſh Actor in a ſtately Play, hee is not onely ridiculous in

himſelfe; but diſgraces both the plot, and the Poet: vvhereas vertue in a man of obſcure Parents, is like an vnpolliſh't Diamond, lying in the way among pebbles; which howſoeuer it bee neglected of the vnciuill vulgar; yet the wiſe Lapidary takes it vp, as a Iewell vnvaluable; it being ſo much the more glorious, by how much the other were baſer. He that is good and great, I would ſell my life to ſerue him nobly; otherwiſe, being good, I loue him better, whoſe father expir'd a Clowne; then he that being vitious,

is in a lineall deſcent from him, that was knighted with Tubal-Cain's fauchion which he made before the Floud.
            
            
               XCIIII.
               I find ſome men extremely paſſionate: and theſe, as they are more taken with a ioy; ſo, they taſte a diſaſter more heauily. Others are free from beeing affected; and as they neuer ioy exceſſiuely; ſo they neuer ſorrow immoderately: but haue together, leſſe mirth, and leſſe mourning: like patient gameſters, winning, and loſing, are one. The

latter I will moſt labour for. I ſhall not loſe more contentment in apprehending ioyes, then I ſhall griefe in finding troubles. For we are more ſenſible of paine, then delight; the one contracting the ſpirits, the other dilating thē. Though it were not ſo, liuing heere, vexations are more ordinary: Ioy is a thing for hereafter. Heauen cannot bee found vpon earth. Many great ioyes are not ſo pleaſant, as one torment proues tedious. The father ſighes more at the death of one ſonne, then he ſmiles at the birth of many.
            
            
               
               XCV.
               In weighty affaires, wee can neuer doe well, vnleſſe we know both our ſelues, and the thing wee intend. Truth falls into hazard, when it finds either a weak Defender, or one that knowes not her worth. How can hee guide a buſineſſe, that needeth a guide for himſelfe? Haue we not knowne many, taking their abilities at too high a pitch, ruſh vpon matters that haue proou'd their ouerthrow? Raſh preſumption is a ladder that will breake our

necks. If wee thinke too well of our ſelues, we ouerſhoot the marke; If not well enough, wee are ſhort of it. And though wee know our ſelues, yet if ignorant in the thing, wee expoſe our ſelues to the ſame miſchiefe. Who is ſo vnwiſe as to wade through the riuer he hath not ſounded, vnleſſe hee can either ſwimme wel, or haue helpe at hand? Hee that takes vpon him what hee cannot doe, rides a horſe which he cannot rule; he can neither ſit in ſafety, nor alight when he would. In whatſoeuer I vndertake, I vvill firſt ſtudy

my ſelfe; next the thing that I goe about: being to ſeeke in the former, I cannot proceede well; vnderſtanding that, I ſhall know the other the better; if not the particulars, I may caſt it in the general; ſomething vnſeene, we muſt leaue to a ſodaine diſcretion, either to order, or auoyde. 'Tis not for man to ſee the euents, further then nature and probabilities of reaſon lead him. Though wee know not what will bee, 'tis good wee prepare for that which may be: we ſhall brooke a checke the eaſier, while wee thought on't,

though wee did not expect it. But if knowing both aright, I find my ſelfe vnable to performe it; I vvill rather deſiſt from beginnings, then run vpon ſhame in the ſequell. I had better keepe my ſelfe and ſhip at home; then carry her to ſea, and not know how to guide her.
            
            
               XCVI.
               What an elated Meteor would man grow to, did proſperitie alwayes caſt ſweetening dewes in his face? Sure he would once more with Ouids Gyants,

fling Mountaines on heaps, to pull downe God from his throne of Maieſty; forgetting all felicity, but that aiery happineſſe hee is blinded with. Nothing feedes pride ſo much, as a proſperous aboundance: 'tis a wonder to ſee a Fauorite ſtudy for ought, but additions to his greatneſſe: If I could bee ſo vncharitable, as to wiſh an enemies ſoule loſt, this were the onely way: Let him liue in the height of the worlds blandiſhments. For how can hee loue a ſecond Miſtreſſe, that neuer ſaw but one beauty, and ſtill continues

deepely enamoured on it? Euery man hath his deſires intending to ſome peculiar thing: GOD ſhould bee the end we aime at; yet we often ſee, nothing carries vs ſo farre from him, as thoſe fauours hee hath imparted vs: tis dangerous to be outwardly bleſſed. If plenty and proſperitie were not hazardous, what a ſhort cut ſhould ſome haue to heauen, ouer others? 'Tis the miſery of the poore, to be neglected of men: 'tis the miſery of the rich, to neglect their God. 'Tis no ſmall abatement to the bitterneſſe of

aduerſities, that they teach vs the way to heauen. Though I would not inhabite Hell, if I could, I would ſometimes ſee it; not out of an itching deſire to behold wonders; but by viewing ſuch horrors, I might value heauen more dearely. Hee that hath experienc't the Seas tumultuous perils, will euer after, commend the Lands ſecurity. Let mee ſwimme a riuer of boyling Brimſtone, to liue eternally happy; rather then dwell in a Paradiſe, to bee damn'd after death.
            
            
               
               XCVII.
               Euery Vice makes the owner odious; but Pride and Cruelty more then any beſide. Pride hath no friend: His thoughts ſet his worth aboue himſelfe, all others vnder it. Hee thinks nothing ſo diſgracefull, as want of reuerence, and familiaritie. There is a kinde of diſdaining ſcorne writ in his brow, and geſture; wherein all may reade, I am too good for thy company. So 'tis iuſt all ſhould deſpiſe him, becauſe hee contemneth all. Hee that hath firſt ouerprized

himſelfe, ſhall after be vnder-valued by others; which his arrogancie thinking vniuſt, ſhall ſwell him to anger, ſo make him more hatefull. Pride is euer diſcontentiue: It both occaſions more then any, and makes more, then it doth occaſion. As Humilitie is the way to get loue and quietneſſe: ſo is Pride the cauſe both of Hatred, and Warre. Hee hath angred others, and others will vex him. No man ſhall heare more ill of himſelfe, then he that thinkes he deſerues moſt good. It was a iuſt quip of that wiſe King, to

that proud Phyſician, who writing thus, Menecrates Iupiter, Regi Ageſilao ſalutem; was anſwered thus, Rex Ageſilaus, Menecrati ſanitatem indeed he might well wiſh his wits to him, that was ſo vnwiſe as to thinke himſelfe God. Ariſtotle, when hee ſaw a youth proudly ſurueying himſelfe, did iuſtly wiſh to be as he thought himſelfe; but to haue his enemies ſuch, as hee was. I dare boldly ſay, neuer proud perſon was well beloued. For as nothing vnites more, then a reciprocall exchange of affection: ſo there is nothing

hinders the knot of friendſhip more, then apparant neglect of courteſies. Cruelty is a Curre of the ſame litter. 'Tis natures good care of her ſelfe, that warnes vs from the denne of this Monſter. Who will euer conuerſe with him, that he hath ſeene deuoure another before him? A Tyrant may rule while hee hath power to compell; but when he hath loſt that, the hatred hee hath got, ſhall ſlay him. Who wonders to heare yong Cato aske his Schoolemaſter, how Silla liu'd ſo long, when hee was ſo hated for

his crueltie? it was a diuelliſh ſpeech, that Caligula borrowed of the Poet, Oderint dum metuant: I am content if they feare mee, that they ſhould hate me. And ſure if any man tooke the courſe for't, hee did; when hee bade his executioners ſo ſtrike, as they might feele that they were a dying. Hee that makes crueltie his delight, ſhall bee ſure to haue hate his beſt recompence. Deteſtation waites vpon vnmercifulneſſe: who would not helpe to kill the Beaſt, that ſucks the bloud of the Fould? What hath made ſome

Nations ſo odious as theſe two; Pride, and Cruelty? The proud man will haue no friend; and the cruell man ſhall haue none. Who are more miſerable then they that want company? I pitie their eſtate, but loue it not. Were I Lord of the whole Globe, and muſt liue alone, I had vnhappineſſe enough to make my cōmands my trouble. The one turn'd Angels out of Heauen; the other, Monarks from their thrones: both, I am ſure, are able to turne vs to hell: it is better being a beaſt, then a dying man, with either vnpardoned.
            
            
               
               XCVIII.
               I know not vvhether is more true, That, likeneſſe is the cauſe of Loue: or, Loue the cauſe of likeneſſe. In agreeing diſpoſitions, the firſt is certaine; in thoſe that are not, the latter is euident. The firſt is the eaſier loue; the other the more worthy. The one hath a lure to draw it; the other without reſpect, is voluntarie. Men loue vs for the ſimilitude we haue with themſelues; GOD, meerely from his goodneſſe, when yet wee are

contrary to him. Since he hath lou'd mee, when I was not like him, I vvill ſtriue to bee like him, becauſe hee hath lou'd mee. I would bee like him being my friend, that lou'd mee, when I was his enemie. Then onely is loue powerfull, when it frames vs to the will of the loued. Lord, though I cannot ſerue thee as I ought, let me loue thee as I ought. Grant this, and I know, I ſhall ſerue thee the better.
            
            
               
               XCIX.
               What wee either deſire, or feare, wee are eaſily drawne to beleeue. Tell the prodigal, his Kinſman's dead ſhould leaue him an eſtate to ſwagger with, hee'le quickly giue credit to 't. The mother of a ſicke infant, if ſhee but heares death whiſper'd, ſhe is confident her childe is gone: either of them tranſport the minde beyond her ſelfe, and leaue her open to inconueniencies. How many haue ſhortened their dayes, by ſudden falſe apprehenſions,

that haue been help'd forward, by one of theſe two; or elſe ſo diſcouered their mindes, as they haue made way for themſelues, to bee wrought vpon by flatterie, by ſeducement? In the one, Nature is couetous for her owne good; ſo dilates her ſelfe, &amp; as it were ſtretcheth out the armes of her ſoule, to embrace that, which ſhee hath an opinion may pleaſure her: and this is in all ſenſitiue creatures; though I know the deſire of onely rationall, and intelligible things, is peculiar to Man: who by vertue of his intellectuall

ſoule, is made deſirous of things incorporeall, and immortall. Thus hee that would bee vvell ſpoken of, beleeues him, that falſely tels him ſo. In the other, Nature is prouident for her owne ſafety; ſo all the ſpirits ſhrinke in to guard the heart, as the moſt noble part: whereby the exteriour parts, beeing left without moiſture, the haire is ſometimes ſuddenly turned gray: the heart thus contracted, and wrought vpon, by it ſelfe; more eaſily then, admits any thing, that is brought her by the outward ſenſes.

Thus if the miſerable Man heares a fire hath beene in the towne where his houſe is, he cryes vndone, though his owne were neuer in danger. In either of theſe, how might perſwaſion worke, and betray vs? What nature hath infuſed, I cannot caſt out; correct I may. If I muſt deſire, and feare, I will doe it ſo moderately, as my iudgement, and reaſon may bee ſtill cleere. If vnawares I be ouertaken, I will yet be carefull to conceale my ſelfe: ſo though my owne paſſions bee ouer-ſtrong; others ſhall not ſee them,

to take mee at aduantages. As many haue been ſpoiled by being ſoothed, in their plauſible deſires: ſo haue many beene abuſed, by being malleated, in their troubleſome feare.
            
            
               C.
               Reſolutions may often change; ſometimes for the better; and the laſt euer ſtands firmeſt. But vowes well made; ſhould know no variance: For the firſt ſhould bee ſure, without alteration. Hee that violates their performance, failes in his duty: and euery breach

is a wound to the ſoule. I will reſolue oft, before I vow once; neuer reſolue to vow, but what I may keep; neuer vow, but what I both can, and will keepe.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
               When thou view'ſt this, mend faults,
               that heere are ſhowne;
               And when thou view'ſt thy ſelfe,
               then mend thine owne.
            
            In the 12. line of the third page to the Reader, for noting, reade, notifying: in line 13. for tels me a fault, read, tels me of a fault, pag. 60. line 5. for I imagine, read, imagine: pag. 294. lin. 16. for mind, reade wind.
         
      
   

