
   
      
         
            A short and profitable treatise, of lavvfull and vnlavvfull recreations and of the right vse and abuse of those that are lavvefull. Written by M. Dudley Fenner, Preacher of the Word of God in Midlebrugh [sic]. 1587.
            Fenner, Dudley, 1558?-1587.
         
         
            
               1590
            
         
         Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00641
            STC 10777
            ESTC S113734
            99848965
            99848965
            14090
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00641)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14090)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1518:06)
         
         
            
               
                  A short and profitable treatise, of lavvfull and vnlavvfull recreations and of the right vse and abuse of those that are lavvefull. Written by M. Dudley Fenner, Preacher of the Word of God in Midlebrugh [sic]. 1587.
                  Fenner, Dudley, 1558?-1587.
               
               [16] p.   
               
                  By Richard Schilders,
                  Imprinted at Midleburgh :
                  1590.
               
               
                  Running title reads: Of lavvfull and vnlavvfull recreations.
                  Signatures: A.
                  A variant; imprint includes date.
                  Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Amusements --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-11
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2005-11
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
               
A SHORTE TREATISE against STAGE-PLAYES
            
            
               
                  Prov. 10. 23.
               
               It is a ſport to a foole to doe miſchief.
            
            
               
                  Prov. 21. 17.
               
               He that loues paſtime ſhall be a poore man.
            
            
               
                  Epheſ. 5. 11.
               
               Haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull works of darkneſſe, but rather reproue them.
            
            
               Printed in the yeere of our Lord 1625.
            
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               AN HVMBLE SVPPLICATION TENDRED to the High and Honourable Houſe OF PARLIAMENT, Aſſembled May xviij. 1625.
            
            
               WHereas Stage-playes are repugnant to the written Word and Will of Almightie God, the onely wiſe Gouernour &amp; righteous Judge of the whole world; dangerous to the eternall ſaluation both of the actours and ſpectatours; breede many inconueniences whereſoeuer they come; procure the judgments of God to the whole kingdome, for ſinne tollerated pourchaſeth Gods wrath to the whole nation, as appeareth Joſhu. 22. 18. and Salomon ſayth Prov. 14. 34. Sinne is a reproach to any people; and haue beene juſtly cenſured and

worthily prohibited by statutes made in the late Raigne of famouſe Queene Elizabeth, and of our Learned and Noble King James: May it therefore pleaſe this High and Honourable Houſe, which is the moſt honourable Court in all Europe, vpon view of this ſhort Treatiſe following, to take once more into conſideration this matter of Stage-playes, and by ſome few words added to the former Statutes, to reſtreyne them for euer hereafter.
         
         
            
            
               A SHORT TREATISE OF STAGE-PLAYES.
            
               The Preface.
               
                  IN all ages the Prophets haue applied their preachings to the preſent occaſions: and the generall concurſſe of many baptiſed Chriſtians to Stage-playes, euery where in theſe times, haue occaſioned the Lords remembrancers, which ſtand continually on their watch-towres, both more diligently to examine the nature of Stage-playes, which haue had much countenance, and ſome defenſe; to trie whether they be warrantable by the word of God or no; and alſo more earneſt prayer to God for his aſſiſtance, and ſerious indeavours to diſſwade Chriſtians from entertayning them. Hence proceede theſe fewe enſuing reaſons, briefly contracted into a narrow roome, that the reader may with facilitie conceaue the force of the arguments, and ſoundly judge of

the trueth of them. And for better direction to the Reader, the whole ſumme is drawne to theſe foure heads.
               
                  Firſt, the originall beginning of Stage-playes is ſhewed: ſect. 2.
               
                  Secondly, the end is pointed out for which they were firſt deviſed. ſect. 3.
               
                  Thirdly, the generall matter or argument acted in them, is opened in few words: ſect. 4.
               
                  Fourthly, the reaſons to proue them vnlawfull are rendred: ſect. 5.
            
            
               I. The originall beginning of Stage-playes.
               2. THe firſt beginning of playes proceeded Heathen invented playes. from thoſe men which were not in the Church of God. When God had appointed man to get his liuing, with his labour Gen. 3. 19. Iuball the ſeauenth of Cain his race invented playing. Gen. 4. 21. on Inſtruments, which (as after) is a lawfull recreation. But the invention of divers ſorts of vnlawfull playes is briefly noted by Plinius Hiſtor. natur. lib. 7. cap. 59. by Euſebius de praepar. euang. lib. 1. cap. 2. and lib. 2. cap. 2. by Arnobius contra gentes lib. 7. by Polydorus Virgilius de rerum invent. lib. 3. cap. 13. by Alexander ab Alexandro genialium dierum. libr. 6. cap. 19. by Caelius Rhodiginus antiq. lib. 8. cap. 7. Whether they grew vp firſt at Lydia in Aſia as ſaith Herodotus lib. 1. or at Athens in Graecia, as Polydorus Virgilius lib. 3. cap. 13. and Volaterranus lib. 29. ca. 11. report, it is not materiall. Pauſanias in Eliacis writeth that Iphitus was admoniſhed by the oracle of

Apollo to reſtore the Olympike games. Ioſephus Scaliger poëtices lib. 1. cap. 22. &amp;c. may ſatiſfie all men that deſire to reade more of this point. About the beginning of the Perſian monarchie, which The ſolemn beginning of playes. was almoſt 500 yeeres afore Chriſt, and about the time of the Iewes returne out of the captivitie of Babylon, this miſcreant author alwayes of ſome hurte, never of any good to Chriſtian or heathen, firſt came abroade with great ſolemnitie, as it may be gathered by Herodotus. Afterwards from thoſe Lydians in Aſia, or from the Grecians at Athens, came playes to Rome in the reigne of Tarquinius Priſcus, as Euſebius noteth in his Chronologie at the yeare of the world 4602. Hermanus Contractus at the yeare of the world 3341 noteth the 
                     Alexander 
                           〈◊〉
                         A
                           ••
                        xand. lib. 5. c. 16. ſame. And Titus Livius lib. 7. Pomponius Laetus in Philippo, Funccius in his worthie Chronologie at the yeare of the world 3512. and Herodianus lib. 3. witnes how the Romans augmented their playes afterwards.
               The firſt authoriſed entrance that any ſuch kinde The entrance of playes into the Church of the Iewes. of playes or heathen exerciſe had into the church of God, ſeemeth to be about 170 yeares before the birth of Chriſt, when that wicked Ieſus affecting heatheniſme, changed his name into Iaſon, and for 150 talents of ſilver purchaſed a commiſſion of Antiochus Epiphanes king of Syria, that he might erect a place for heathen exerciſes at Ieruſalem, and traine up the youth of the Iewes in the cuſtomes of the Gentiles, 1 Maccab. 1. 12. Ioſeph. antiq. lib. 12. cap. 6. but more ſpecially 2 Maccab. 4. 7. &amp;c. Which exerciſe though it was not to play on the ſtage, but for activitie of their bodies, yet it may

here be obſerved as an entrance to other heathen cuſtomes, and as that which maketh way to bring in Stage-playes afterwards. Then Herode the greate increaſed heatheniſh playes and exerciſes greatly in his dayes, building one theater at Ieruſalem; Ioſeph. antiq. lib. 15. cap. 10. or 11. and an other at Caeſarea Stratonis; Ioſeph. antiq. lib. 15. cap. 13. and lib. 16. cap. 9. The horrible ſinnes of the Iewes cutte them off ſhortly after from being the Church of God, and therefore no more can be ſayd of their heatheniſh exerciſes.
               How or when Playes came into the Chriſtian Church, and who firſt gaue them intertainment, Their entrance into the christian church. is more incident to this preſent purpoſe, and fitter teſtimonie to giue evidence hereafter either for them or againſt them. When the Roman Emperours delighted too much in all kind of playes, and when chriſtian religion grew mightily under them in Europe eſpecially, chriſtians imbraceing the Goſpel could not be altogether ignorant of theſe ſtage-playes, but ſometimes ſome chriſtians reſorted to theſe playes, as by the complaints and invectiues of ſome ancient fathers againſt them, it doth appeare. And though ſecretly by ſuch meanes playes through ſatans ſubtilties approached neare to the church doore, yet all this while neither the Emperours power thruſt them upon the Church, nor the reverend Fathers and faithfull Paſtours of thoſe times gaue way to ſuch open wickednes by theire ſilence. But when that great ſcarlet coloured whore of Babylon with her golden cup of abhominations in her hand, which hath a name written in her forehead, a myſterie, great Babilon the mother

of whoredomes, and which reigneth over the kings of the earth, was ſet in Peters chaire at Rome as the Papiſts ſay; then did the king of the Locuſts, called Abaddon and Apollyon, hauing the key of the bottomeles pitt, with full power for ſuch a purpoſe, ſette the church doore wide open for ſundrie ſportes and playes to enter freely into the houſe of God, as Platina reporteth Paulus II. did. And that not onely in their great ſolemnities and feſtivals, which were ſpent commonly in bellie cheare and Playes, as Peucerus writeth of Vrbanus IIII. much after the faſhion of the Iſraelites, ſitting downe to eate and drinke, and riſing up to play: but ſpecially in their rich Iubilies, firſt begunne in the Chriſtian church by Bonifacius VIII. in the yeare of Chriſt 1300. and afterwards continued and haſtened by his ſucceſſors. Of which Sports and Playes Aventinus annal. Bojor. lib. 7. ſpeaking of Clemens VI. and Bale in the life of Iulius III. doe write. And thus much ſhall ſuffice for the beginning of Playes among the Lydians of Aſia; and among the Grecians and Romans in Europe; as alſo for their entrance into the Chriſtian church, firſt ſecretly by the malice of Satan ſtealing ſome Chriſtians affections to ſuch vanities; then openly by the power of that Abaddon of Rome, who beſotted mens ſenſes with ſuch fooleries, that he might robbe their purſes in his rich Iubilies.
            
            
               II. The ende for which Playes were deviſed.
               3. THe finall cauſe or ende for which the Heathen firſt deviſed Playes, was to pacifie their

angrie gods, and ſo remoue ſome preſent calamitie which vexed them. The Lydians ſought by Playes to remedie a greate famine that was among them, as Herodotus witneſſeth in Clio. The Athenians renewed their Playes about the latter ende of the Perſian Monarchie, in the dayes of Euthydemus their governour, thereby thinking to remoue a grievous peſtilence, as ſayth Diodorus Siculus lib. 12. Alſo Livius lib. 7. and Paulus Oroſius libr. 3. cap. 4. write that the heathen Romans ſore afflicted about the ſame time, with peſtilence, by the adviſe of their idoll prieſts, ſet forth their Stage-playes to turne away that affliction, thinking their Playes would pleaſe their gods.
               But Dionyſius Halicarnaſſeus li. 7. Arnobius. lib. 7. contra gentes. Pauſanias in Corinthiacis. Auguſtinus de civitate dei lib. 2. cap. 13. &amp; lib. 3. cap. 18. &amp; lib. 4. cap. 1. &amp; cap. 26. Polydorus Virgil. de inventione rerum lib. 3. cap. 13. and Volaterranus lib. 29. cap. 11. write ſo plainly and fully of this matter, that the reading of any one of them may ſatiſfie the ſober minded, and giue them to underſtand, that as Chriſtians by direction out of Gods word uſe prayer and faſting to turne away the Lords provoked anger: ſo heathens inſtructed by the Divell their maſter thought to remoue their afflictions by Playes. But the Popes of Rome ſolemniſed their Feſtivals and Iubilies with all ſortes of Playes and Sportes for recreation, and to delite the people with ſuch fooleries.
            
            
               
               III. The argument of Stage-playes.
               4. WHereas Stage-playes ordinarily goe under the name either of Tragedies or els of comedies; we are to underſtand that the argument or matter acted in tragedies is murther, treaſon, rebellion, and ſuch like; and in comedies is bauderie, coſenage, and meere knaverie.
               But here ſome men eyther meerly ignorant (as Objection. the moſt religious and learned are ignorant of many things, for we know but in part. 1 Cor. 13. 9.) or 
                     Bucerus de regno Christi lib. 2, ca. 54 els perverſly irreligious, will ſay, that ſometimes the ſacred Scripture is or may be acted by players on the ſtage, and thereby a man may learne more then at a ſermon.
               But for better information of the ignorant, and Anſwer. more forcible confutation of the perverſe and profane, a threefold anſwer may be giuen.
               Firſt, concerning thoſe perſons that ſo greatly 1. anſwer.
                   deſire to learne religion at Stage-playes, let them examine their owne conſciences by their workes which are manifeſt before God and men, and conſider themſelues in theſe fiue points.
               1. They ſeldome come to the Church to learne religion according to Gods ordinance, though God command them ſo to doe, Deut. 12, 5. But ye ſhall ſeeke the place which the Lord your God ſhall chooſe out of all your tribes, to put his name there, and there to dwell, and thither thou ſhalt come, &amp;c. though God intreate them ſo to doe, Prov. 1. 20. Wiſedome cryeth without: ſhee uttereth her voyce in the ſtreets. &amp;c. as alſo

                     〈4 pages missing〉
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
cerning good and neceſſarie matters.
               As for hawking, hunting, fiſhing, fouling, and ſuch like, they are rather to be counted honeſt and lawfull callings, wherein men may get their living with their labour, then recreations, except it be by change of labour, as in other lawfull callings.
               And now to come to confutation of the objection, Confutation. it ſeemeth that Stage-playes cannot be counted in the number of recreations, and that for theſe three reaſons.
               Firſt, they are not worhie to be compared to any of the former lawfull recreations.
               Secondly, they ſerue not the ende of recreations, which is to refreſh the wearie, but not to make men delight in ſinne.
               Thirdly, the moſt perſons that ordinarily reſorte to them, are verie idle perſons, that ſhould rather be ſet to ſome honeſt labour, then ſo unprofitably to miſpend their time to their owne hurte.
               The originall beginning then is ſufficient to perſwade the faythfull to renounce Stage-playes, and ſay unto them, Gette thee hence. Eſai. 30. 22.
            
            
               The ſecond reaſon.
               6. THE ſecond reaſon may be taken from 2 Reaſon.
                   the matter or argument, which is acted upon the Stage, which is eyther murther and miſchief in tragedies, or bauderie and coſonage in comedies, as was obſerved before ſect. 4. And the reaſon may be contrived thus.
               It is not lawfull for Chriſtians to ſporte themſelues eyther with the dreadfull judgments of

God, or with the abhominable ſinnes of men.
               But in Stage-playes there are acted ſometimes the fearefull judgments of God, as in tragedies: and ſometimes the vile and hatefull ſinnes of men, as in comedies.
               And therefore it is full of horrour ſeriouſly to thinke upon them, and much more to be eyther actor to ſhew them, or beholder and hearer to laugh at them, or delite in them.
               Ham derided his Fathers nakednes Gen. 9, 22. but he was accurſed for it. Curſes are denounced in Gods Law againſt all ſinners, Deut. 27, 26. And they that make a ſport of ſinne cannot avoyd Gods curſe, no more then they that feaſted when they ſhould haue faſted, Eſay. 22, 14. Surely this iniquitie ſhall not be purged from you, till ye dye, ſayth the Lord of Hoastes.
               
            
            
               The third reaſon.
               7. THE third reaſon is taken from the Stage-players, and from ſuch their vices as properly 3 Reaſon.
                   belong to them, as they are Stage-players. And four of their vices may perſwade all men that their playes are unlawfull.
               Firſt, they being men, change their apparel, and put on womans apparell, without which exchange 1. they cannot act ſome partes in their Playes, which thing the Lord forbiddeth. Deut. 22. 5. The woman ſhall not weare that which perteyneth to the man, neyther ſhall a man put on womans rayment: for all that do ſo are an abomination to the Lord thy God. For this change of apparell maketh the man effeminate, and the

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
woman maniſh, as ſome can teſtifie if they would, ſome haue confeſſed, and the Heathen know. Cyprianus lib. 2. epiſt. 2. ſpeaking of this change of apparell in Stage-playes, ſayth thus: evirantur mares; men looſe their manhood &amp;c. Charondas made a law to the inhabitants of Thuria (which is a citie in Greece, deſcribed by Pauſanias in Meſſenicis, and by Strabo lib. 8.) that if any man refuſed to goe to warres, or being in the field caſt downe his weapons and ranne away, he ſhould ſtand three dayes in the open market in womans apparell, which argued effeminatenes in him, as if formerly he had uſed it. Diodor. lib. 12.
               Secondly, they never come on the Stage in theire owne name, but ſome in the name and perſon 2. of a divell, others of a foole, others of a bawde, others of a tyrant, others of other men, which beſeemeth not a Chriſtian, neither proceedeth it of God, nor is approved of God, but is contrarie to Chriſtian profeſſion. Tit. 2. 12.
               Thirdly, they ſweare by the living God, which is contrarie to the Law of God, Exod. 20. 7. or by 3. heathen idols, which is forbidden, Exod. 23. 13. or by both, which is reproved Amos 8. 14. Zephan. 1. 5.
               Fourthly, they teach their hearers and beholders much ſinne in the acting of their Playes, as to 4. ſweare, curſe, lye, flatter, coſen, ſteale, to play the bawde and the harlot, with very many ſuch other lewde leſſons.
            
            
               
               The fourth Reaſon.
               8. THE fourth reaſon ariſeth from the conſideration of the hearers and beholders, 4 Reaſon.
                   who being baptiſed into the name of Chriſt, are brought into danger of gods wrath, and their owne condemnation, in as much as they are partakers of the ſinnes of the Players and of the Playes in approving them. And whatſoever brings men into theſe dangers muſt needs be evill. And beſides the approbation, which maketh them guiltie, they learne ſinne: for as ſayth Cyprianus lib. 2. epiſt. 2. adulterium diſcitur, dum videtur, they learne to commit adulterie, when they heare and behold ſuch immodeſt and unchaſte words and geſtures upon the ſtage. And many goe honeſt thither, which returne home diſhoneſt. Iob made a covenant with his eyes, that he would not looke on a maide, Iob 31. 1. David deſired God to turne away his eyes from regarding vanitie, Pſal. 119. 37.
            
            
               The fift Reaſon.
               9. THE fift reaſon may be taken from conſideration of theſe eight fruits or effects 5 Reaſon.
                   which follow Stage-playes:
               Firſt, the Stage-players get their living by an ungodly &amp; unlawfull trade, never approved by God, 1. &amp; when they ſhall ſtand at the barre of Gods judgement, they ſhall be ſpeachles, and caſt into utter darkenes, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, except they repent and forſake their wicked

trade betimes, whiles the Lord granteth ſpace to repentance.
               Secondly, the hearers receaue much hurte by them, as was noted in the fourth reaſon, and if it 2. be true which is reported, whoredome is ſometimes committed at that place, and at that time.
               Thirdly, the better ſort of men which are governours of families, receaue domage, when ſome of 3. their families reſorte to Stage-playes, for ſometimes their goods are ſtollen to mainteine Lewdnes, ſometimes their daughters or maide-ſervants are defiled, or ſtollen away, and maried without their governours conſent or privitie.
               Fourthly, the word of God and the miniſters thereof, are now and then taxed and taunted. 4.
               
               Fiftly, the Lord himſelfe is there blaſpheamed ordinarily. 5.
               
               Sixtly, the poore in the church of Chriſt, are 6. hindred from ſome reliefe, which otherwiſe they might haue. for the prodigalitie laviſhed upon 
                     dist. 86, c. 8 Stage-players, reſtrayneth the liberalitie that might and ought to be beſtowed upon the poore.
               Seauenthly, there is loſſe of pretious time, which ſhould be ſpent in Gods ſervice, by thoſe that are 7. hired to be diligent labourers in his vineyard, and not be wickedly miſpent in ſuch ſinfull ſportes, ſeeing everie one, both young and olde, muſt giue account to God of his labours, and of his time ſpent in this life. The Holy Ghoſt ſayth Epheſ. 5. 16. Redeeme the time, for the dayes are evill; but ſome men ſay, Let us haue paſtime, that is, any ſinfull courſe, whereby we may paſſe away &amp; miſ-ſpend the ſhort time which we haue in this life, that the day of

death, judgment, and condemnation may come ſpeedily upon us before we repent, and before we conſecrate our ſelues wholly to God. Peter ſayth: It is ſufficient for us, that we haue ſpent the time paſt of this life, after the lustes of the Gentiles, walking in wantonnes, lustes, drunkennes, in gluttonie, drinkings, and abominable idolatries. 1 Pet. 4. 3. And if any be otherwiſe minded, the Lord in his time will either convert or confound him.
               Eightly, whereas the life of a Chriſtian effectually called, ſhould be ſpent continually in fighting 8. againſt all kinde of ſinne, in crucifying the old man, and in renewing the inner man dayly, theſe Stage-playes quench the ſpirit, and deſtroy the new man, as alſo on the other part, they foſter, cheriſh, and mainteyne the old man, as all thoſe that haue the ſpirit of Chriſt know and feele. But if any man haue not the ſpirit of Christ, the ſame is not his. Rom. 8. 9.
            
            
               The ſixth Reaſon.
               10. THE ſixt reaſon may be taken from the 6 Reaſon.
                   opinion and judgment of all ſortes and ſtates of men, by whom theſe Stage-playes haue been diſalowed.
               Firſt, all orthodoxall Proteſtants of all ages and 1, Orthodoxal Protestants.
                   times, which maintayned the generall doctrine of the Catholike church, haue cenſured Stage-playes, as unlawfull from age to age hitherto. To reporte and repeate their ſeverall judgements out of their owne writings, or out of hiſtories, is more then I can performe, it would make a greate volume, it

would be tedious to reade, and perhaps not ſo neceſſarie.
               Wherefore it ſeemeth rather convenient to call a greate number of them together out of all the places of their dwellings, and as it were out of all the world, that they all may be heard to ſpeake altogether with one conſent and voyce. But becauſe it would be a verie tedious, and troubleſome thing, for ſo many, ſo reverend, and ſo old aged Fathers to travell ſo farre; it is more convenient and reaſonable to ſpare their labours ſo much as may be, and call them together at three ſeverall times, and in three ſeverall places of their habitations; that is, to call thoſe of Aſia, to meete together in Aſia: thoſe of Africa, in Africa: and thoſe of Europe, in Europe.
               In Aſia, about two and twentie of the moſt reverend Aſia, Fathers of thoſe times, met together in Laodicea, ſomewhat more then 300 yeres after Chriſt, and holding a councill there, decreed cap. 54. that none of the Cleargie ſhould be preſent at Stage-playes. And the Centuriators of Magdeburg haue inſerted this whole Councill in their laborious and worthie hiſtorie Cent. 4. cap. 9. col. 834.
               In Africa more then 400 years after Chriſt there Afrike. were ſome four and fortie of the worthieſt &amp; learnedſt Fathers aſſembled at Carthage in the third councill that was holden there, amongſt whom was that worthie Auguſtinus, and they decreed cap. 11. that the children of miniſters or of others of the Cleargie ſhould not be preſent at Stage-playes, ſeeing none of the Laitie might be there. Semper enim Chriſtianis omnibus hoc interdictum eſt, ut
                  
                  ubi blaſphemi ſunt, non accedant. that is; for all chriſtians haue evermore beene forbidden to come in place, where blaſphemers are. And the ſame religious Fathers then, and there decreed alſo cap. 35. That the church ſhould not tefuſe to receaue the Stage-players into their fellowſhip, if they repented and renounced that their trade of playing. Whereby is evident that Stage-players in thoſe former and purer times, were generally excommunicated, and caſt out of the ſocietie of the ſaintes.
               In Europe divers worthie and graue Fathers of the church, called and ſummoned by Conſtantinus Europe. Magnus, a little after the Nicene Councill, to come together at Arles in France, held two Councils there, the firſt, and ſhortly after the ſecond. In both which they decreed the excommunication of all Stage-players, ſo long as they continued that trade of life. And in the firſt Councill, cap. 5. thus they ſay: De theatricis, &amp; ipſos placuit, quandiu agunt, à communione ſeparari; that is, as touching Stage-players, we thinke it good, that whiles they continue in that trade of life, they be kept from the communion. And in the ſecond Councill held there preſently after, they decree the ſame thing againe, can. 20. and almoſt in the ſame words.
               But yet to giue in more evidence, we may haue all the worthie Fathers of the Churches in Aſia, Africa, and Europa, aſſembled together in the ſixt generall Council, which was held at Conſtantinople, approue that which at Laodicea in Aſia, and at Carthage in Africa, was decreed againſt Stage-players. For when Conſtantinus Pogonatus in the yeare 681 called that ſixt general Councel at Conſtantinople

againſt the Monothelites of thoſe times, as Zonoras, Tomo tertio ſheweth, about fiue yeares after, his ſonne Iuſtinianus II. aſſembled the Fathers there againe, as Gratianus diſt. 16. cap. 7. and the Centuriators of Magdeburgh, Cent. 7. cap. 9. col. 455. doe witneſſe: and can. 20. they approue thoſe two former Councils of Laodicea and of Carthage.
               And thus we haue the judgement of all the orthodoxall and true Catholike Fathers of the churches throughout the whole world, againſt Stage-players, and Stage-playing, with one conſent.
               Secondly, the Papiſts, though they be favourers 2, Papiſts.
                   of Stage-playes, and actors ſometime upon the Stage (as lately at Lions in France) yet they cannot for verie ſhame juſtifie them, but contrariewiſe condemne them in their writings. And in their great Canon booke of Decrees compiled by Gratian, they ratifie the four firſt generall Councils, and all the other Councils made afterwards, and conteyned in that greate booke of Decrees, diſt. 15. cap. 2. &amp; 4. and diſt. 16. cap. 6. &amp;c. they approue by name the three Councils alledged before. More particularly they approue that which was mentioned before of the Council of Laodicea, de conſecratione diſt. 5. cap. 37. and that which was decreed againſt Stage-plaies in the third Councill of Carthage, de conſecrat. diſt. 2. cap. 96. and the canons of the ſixt generall Councill, de conſecratione diſt. 3. cap. 29.
               Thirdly, the Honourable Court of Parliament in this Land, hath juſtly cenſured Stage-players, as 3, Parlement.
                   thoſe that liue not in a lawfull trade to mainteyne

themſelues by. as in the xiiij. yeare of Elizabeth, chap. 5. and in the xxxix yeare of Elizab. chap. 7. and in the ſecond yeare of King Iames, chap. vij.
               Fourthly, the civill law in pointing out thoſe perſons which are of evill note or name, ſayth thus 4, The civil Law.
                   of Stage-players Pandect. lib. 3. tit. 2. Eos enim, qui quaeſtus cauſa in certamina deſcendunt, &amp; omnes propter praemium in ſcenam prodeuntes, famoſos eſſe, Pegaſus &amp; Nerva reſponderunt; that is, Pegaſus and Nerva ſaid, that thoſe were infamous which tryed maſterie for gaine, and all that came upon the Stage for a rewarde. Alſo who liſt, may reade ſomewhat to the ſame purpoſe. Novel. conſt. 51.
               Fiftly, the infidell Heathens, howſoever they firſt deviſed them, and after uſed them very much, 5, Heathens.
                   yet haue they diſalowed them, as Auguſtine de civitate Dei, lib. 2. cap. 13. rehearſing the words of Scipio out of Tullie, ſheweth: Quum artem ludicram ſcenamque totam probro ducerent, genus id hominum non modo honore civium reliquorum carere, ſed etiam tribu moveri notatione cenſoria voluerunt. that is, The Romans accounting thoſe playes, and the whole Stage to be reproachfull, when they valued the goods and enrolled the names of their citizens, gaue not the honour of other citizens to Stage-players, but razed their names out of their wardes or companies. Suetonius taxeth Nero for a favorer of them, and an actor among them. Arnobius lib. 7. contra gentes, appealing to the conſcience of the Heathen, ſheweth that they diſallow them, and ſayth thus of the Stage-players, actores inhoneſtos eſſe jus veſtrum judicavit, that is, your owne law hath adjudged the ſtage-players to be no honeſt men.
               
                  
And theſe judgements of men are ſufficient to condemne Stage-playes as unlawfull, and diſhoneſt alſo, as Cornelius Nepos ſayth in his preface before the deſcription of the noble Emperours.
            
            
               The ſeauenth Reaſon.
               11. THE ſeauenth and laſt reaſon is drawne from 7 Reaſon.
                   the judgments which God hath inflicted upon the Players, and beholders.
               1. Philip king of Macedonia, and father of Alexander the greate, was ſlaine at a play by Pauſanias, as Diodorus Siculus writeth lib. 16.
               Plinius hiſtor. natur. lib. 7. cap. 53. ſpeaking of divers that dyed ſodainly, ſayth, that one M. Ofilius Hilarus a noble player of Comedies, after he had played his part gallantly on the day of his birth, and was vaunting at ſupper of his dayes worke, died ſodainly at the table.
               3. Paulus Oroſius lib. 7. cap. 4. writeth that in the twelft yeare of Tiberius, (which was three yeares before Chriſt beganne to preach the Goſpel publikely) there were twentie thouſand perſons ſlaine by the fall of the Theater at Fidena in Italie.
               4. About thirteene yeares after, Caius Caligula the Emperour was ſlaine at a play. Ioſeph. antiq. lib. 19. cap. 1. Suetonius in Caligula cap. 58.
               5. About 150 yeares after Chriſts nativitie, whiles the Playes were kept at Rome with great ſolemnitie, for the ſpace of three dayes and three nights together, continually and without intermiſſion,

a great parte of the citie was ſette on fire and conſumed. And Phillip the Emperour was ſlayne at Varona, and his ſonne at Rome, as it is reported by Sextus Aurelius, Pomponius Laetus, and Eutropius lib. 9.
               6. Tertullianus in his booke de Spectaculis, ſayth, that a Chriſtian woman going to the playes, was then poſſeſſed of a divell, and when other Chriſtians, intending to caſt the divell out of her, demanded of him, how he durſt preſume to aſſault one that beleeved in Chriſt, the divell anſwered, that he found her in his owne houſe, and therefore had good right to ſeaze upon her. Alſo he writeth in the ſame Booke and place, that an other faythfull woman going alſo to behold the Playes, had eyther a fearefull dreame or a viſion the next night after, wherein ſhee was checked for going to the Playes, was warned of her death, and dyed within fiue dayes after.
               7. Aventinus annal. Bojorum lib. 7. writeth, that about 1200 yeares after Chriſt, three hundred men were ſlaine with hayle and lightning at Piſonium, a cittie of Bavaria, in the confines of Italie, whiles they were there to behold the Playes.
               8. The ſame Author Aventinus annal. Bojor. lib. 7. writeth alſo, that when Pope Nicholaus V. ſolemnized his rich Iubilie, in the yeare 1450, with Stage playes, fiue hundred &amp; threeſcore perſons, comming to Rome to behold the Playes, were partly troden to death, and partly drowned in Tiber.
               
                  
9. At London in the yeare of Chriſt 1583 eight perſons were ſlaine, and more hurte, by the fall of the theater.
               10. At Lions in France in the moneth of Auguſt, in the yeare 1607, whiles the Ieſuites were acting their Playes, to the diſgrace of true religion, and the profeſſors thereof, the Lord from heauen continuing thunder &amp; lightnings, for the ſpace of two houres together, ſlewe twelue perſons preſently, and amaſed all the reſt with great terrour and feare.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

