
   
      
         
            Fennors descriptions, or A true relation of certaine and diuers speeches spoken before the King and Queenes most excellent Maiestie, the Prince his highnesse, and the Lady Elizabeth's Grace. By William Fennor, His Maiesties seruant.
            Fennor, William.
         
         
            
               1616
            
         
         Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00649
            STC 10784
            ESTC S102016
            99837817
            99837817
            2160
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00649)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2160)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:04)
         
         
            
               
                  Fennors descriptions, or A true relation of certaine and diuers speeches spoken before the King and Queenes most excellent Maiestie, the Prince his highnesse, and the Lady Elizabeth's Grace. By William Fennor, His Maiesties seruant.
                  Fennor, William.
               
               [44] p.   
               
                  Printed by Edvvard Griffin, for George Gibbs, and are to bee sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Flower-Deluce,
                  London :
                  1616.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: [A]⁴ B-F⁴ (-[A]1, F4).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-10
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-05
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-05
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               FENNORS Deſcriptions, OR A TRVE RELATION OF CERtaine and diuers ſpeeches, ſpoken before the King and Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, the Prince his highneſſe, and the Lady ELIZABETH's Grace.
            By WILLIAM FENNOR, His Maieſties Seruant.
            LONDON, Printed by EDVVARD GRIFFIN, for GEORGE GIBBS, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Flower-Deluce. 1616.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE WILLIAM, Earle of Pembroke, LORD Chamberlaine of his Maieſties houſhold, Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, &amp;c.
            THis ſilly Infant, borne before the time,
            Got life by reaſon, though begot in ryme
            By hir true father; ſhe is very yong,
            And yet as females quickely finde a tongue,
            So doth this changeling babble for a Patron,
            Forſakes hir Father, and out-runnes hir Matron.
            At length for hir protection ſhe hath found,
            Your honour with a wreath of vertues crown'd,
            To whom hir ſelfe ſhe humbly dedicates
            That knew hir birth, and breeding, let the Fates
            Proue happy to the end of your liues race,
            To crowne your Greatneſſe, with immortall grace.
            
               
                  Your Honors euer bounden in all duties, William Fennor.
            
         
         
            
            To the Gentlemen Readers.
            WOrthy gentlemen, of what degree ſoeuer, I ſuppoſe this Pamphlet will hap into your hands, before a play begin, with the importunate clamour, of Buy a new Booke, by ſome needy companion, that will be glad to furniſh you with worke for a turn'd Teaſter. I reſt well aſſured ſome of you will know mee at the ſight of the infant, to ſuch I commend it for acquaintance ſake; others (I make no queſtion) haue heard of me, to thoſe I ſend it, in hope of better acquaintance; A third ſort (it may be) neuer knew mee, nor I thinke care not whether euer they doe or no: To them I preſent it as careleſly as vnthrifts ſpend their anuities. Laſt to Criticks, I wiſh it may hap as ſeldome into their hands, as Vſurers giue almes, or Lawyers plead pro nihil. If any chance to ſay my inuention runs low, in regard I ſell relations for demonſtrations, to ſuch I anſwere, not like a light huſwife, that will be wonne before ſhe be wooed; but like a chaſte virgin that would be ſcarce wonne with wooing: as for example, it is three yeeres ſince I ſpake ſome of theſe ſpeeches, and ſince that time I haue beene earneſtly intreated by noble perſonages (who haue had priuate copies for their owne vſe) to print it for publike delight, at length I conſented, &amp; ſince I am won, haue amongſt you gallants, let it ſpeed as it will. This is my comfort, how ere it proue in the reading, it was well lik't in the rehearſing, by that Imperiall power; for whoſe proſperous continuance we are all in dutie bound to pray, Farewell.
            
            
               Yours in honeſt mirth, W. F.
            
         
         
            
            In Laudem Authoris.
            WHat Enthouſiaſmos, what celeſtiall ſpirit,
            what ſacred fury doth thy braines inherit?
            When as without the libertie of time,
            with reaſon thou doſt couch thy witty ryme
            So quicke, ſo nimble, and acute that all
            wiſe men, will hold thy wit Canonicall.
            Why ſhouldst thou not then weare a wreath of bayes,
            nay a whole groue of Lawrell to thy praiſe
            On thy ingenious temples, ſeeing no man
            can match thee, our times beſt Ouidian?
            
            Though in this wit-bleſt age ther's many men,
            haue gain'd them endleſſe glory by their penne,
            Yet none of theſe could euer ſay like thee,
            that what they writ, was done extempore.
            
            Therefore were I thy Patrone and poſſeſt
            but halfe that wealth wherewith ſome men are bleſt:
            Thou ſhouldſt for euer in thy life inherite
            meanes, as were correſpondent to thy merit:
            And being dead thy name ſhould liue inroul'd,
            not in courſe parchment, but rich leaues of gold.
            
               Iohn Meltonne.
            
         
         
            
            In Laudem Authoris.
            WHy hath thy penne beene hid in obſcure ſhades,
            or thy lines lockt in the darke wombe of night,
            Which being publiſh't, when thy body fades,
            in earths deepe Cauernes may giue others light?
            Thy Muſe the loue of Noble-men perſwades
            to ſhelter her, by their protecting might,
            Gain'ſt pining enuy, who with ruſty blades,
            ſtands oppoſite againſt good workes to fight;
            With belching hate, who her full gorge vnlades,
            to make wit loathſome in the vulgar ſight
            Of men illiterate, and Mechanicke trades,
            that ſcarce can iudge betwixt the wrong and right,
            Of thy indeauours which the heart inuades
            of worth (to praiſe thee) what though Criticks byte,
            And through the gulfe of baſe diſliking wades,
            ſo farre vntill ſhe drowne her ſelfe in ſpight
            Of all mans ſuccour, other winching iades
            can like of nothing, but all things indight,
            To their owne cenſures; but bright fame ſhall ſpread
            hir leaues, where thou ſhalt liue, when thou art dead.
            
               Tho. Gunſon.
            
         
         
            
            TO HIS FRIEND Mr. FENNOR.
            
               I Prayſe thee not becauſe thou art my friend,
            nor would I hate thee, if thou wert my foe,
            But theſe good parts in thee I muſt commend,
            which Art and Nature did on thee beſtow
            In thy bleſt cradle, but goe forward ſtill,
            Make thy friends ſharers of thy nimble quill.
            
               J. B.
            
         
         
            
            THE CONTENTS of this Booke.
            
               
                  1. THe diſcription of a Poet.
               
                  2. The diſcription of the Palſegraues Countrey, with an addition of the marriage betwixt the Prince, and Princeſſe, &amp;c.
               
                  3. Cupids iourney to Germany with the effects of the ſame.
               
                  4. The originall of the moſt noble order of the Garter.
               
                  5. The deciding of the difference betwixt Oxford and Cambridge, about the Kings entertainement.
               
                  6. The Gowries and Gun-powder Treaſon.
               
                  7. A Parliament of Gods in a paſtorall ſong.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The Deſcription of a Poet.
            A Poets life is moſt vnfortunate,
            Gouern'd by Starres of high malignant fate;
            Yet for his worth thus high my pen ſhall raiſe him,
            The rankled tooth of enuy neuer ſtayes him
            From writing nobly. A true Poet can
            Deſcribe the inſide of an outward man:
            Kill him in's life time, make him liue being dead,
            His lines with Bayes adorne his victors head:
            This is his chiefeſt bleſſing to be good:
            But when his writings are not vnderſtood,
            (O) ti's a plague beyond mans patient thought,
            What he makes good a multitude makes nought.
            A horrid murtherer, or a baſe theefe
            In his foule boſome harbers leſſer griefe,
            Then heauen-bred Poeſye: they ſhall be tryed
            By vpright Iuſtice, and their faults deſcried
            Before a publike Bench, hold vp their hand
            And plead not guiltie, on their iuſt cauſe ſtand,
            Twelue men empannelled to finde this out
            Before the ſentence paſſe, to clee
                  •
               e the doubt,
            Of iudging raſhly. But ſweet Poeſye
            Is oft conuict, condem'd, and iudg'd to die
            Without iuſt triall, by a multitude
            Whoſe iudgements are illiterate, and rude.
            
               Witneſſe Sceianus, whoſe approued worth,
            Sounds from the calme South, to the freezing North.
            And on the perfum'd wings of Zepherus,
            
            In triumph mounts as farre as Aeolus,
            
            With more then humane art it was bedewed,
            Yet to the multitude it nothing ſhewed;
            They ſcrewed their ſcuruy iawes and look't awry,
            Like hiſſing ſnakes adiudging it to die:
            When wits of gentry did applaud the ſame,
            With Siluer ſhouts of high lowd ſounding fame:
            Whil'ſt vnderſtanding grounded men contemn'd it,
            And wanting wit (like fooles to iudge) condemn'd it.
            Clapping, or hiſſing, is the onely meane
            That tries and ſearches out a well writ Sceane.
            So is it thought by Ignoramus crew,
            But that good wits acknowledge's vntrue;
            The ſtinckards oft will hiſſe without a cauſe,
            And for a baudy ieaſt will giue applauſe.
            Let one but aske the reaſon why they roare
            They'l anſwere, cauſe the reſt did ſo before.
            But leauing theſe who for their iuſt reward,
            Shall gape, and gaze, amongſt the fooles in th'yard.
            Now to our Poets; they are much like mothers,
            That loue their owne babes farre aboue all others
            Though harder fauor'd: ſo a Poets quill
            With his owne labours beſt doth pleaſe his will,
            The reaſons this, becauſe he knowes the paines
            He tooke in the Compoſing, from whoſe braines,
            A Poets worth takes birth, at firſt ti's weake
            Till by the life of Action it doth ſpeake,
            
               In a ſquare Theator; yet vnderſtand
            The Actor ſpeakes but at the ſecond hand.
            The Poet ſcans, and knowes, what beſt befits
            His birth whom he adornes with Epethites,
            
            Congruus accents: but I heere ſtrike ſaile
            That haue iuſt cauſe my weakeneſſe to bewaile,
            That am no Poet, rather a poore pleader
            For friendly ſentence from the iudging Reader,
            As you allow the beſt, forgiue whats ill,
            Though harſhly wrote accept of my good will.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A deſcription of the Palſgraues Countrey, as it was deliuered in a ſpeech before the King, the Prince, the Lady ELIZABETH, at White-Hall.
            
            By W. F.
            
            
               THe mornings Bridegroome with his Roſie cheeke
               inuites chaſte Cynthia to a Royall feaſt:
               Long for her welcome preſence did he ſeeke,
               to grace his Princely region in the Eaſt,
               Faire Phebes light he doth eſteeme diuine,
               to make his ſplendor mongſt the Germaines ſhine.
            
            
               High Princely Palſgraue, Proteſtants Protector,
               loud ſounding fames report, Germaines rich treaſure,
               Arch-ſhewer of the Empire, chiefe Elector,
               whoſe yea, or nay, ſets vp, or puts downe Caeſar.
               
               O! let it not in me be thought ambition,
               To ſhew the Countries worth, and Thy condition.
            
            
               On the right ſide of Pals the riuer Rhyne,
               
               runnes ſwimming by the bankes of pleaſant vines,
               Vpon whoſe tops bright Sol ſo warme doth ſhine,
               that from the flintie rockes flow Renniſh wines,
               And on the left ſide glides the gentle maine,
               there are few Lands haue two ſuch flouds againe.
            
            
               
               Theſe riuers meet at Mence and are vnited,
               like Gemeni to ſwim towards Belgicke Seas,
               But vpward theſe ſweet waters are diuided
               for Palſ-Lands comfort and the people eaſe:
               The Rhyne brings boats vnto each South-ward Towne,
               but in the North the maine brings treaſure downe
            
            
               From Brandenburgh and High-borne Saxons Land,
               great Chamberlaine, and Lord high Martiall;
               
                  Mence, Triurs, and Cullen, for the Popes right ſtand,
               if either ſide in choice be partiall,
               
                  Bohemiaes King he is indifferent,
               betwixt the Papiſt and the Proteſtant.
            
            
               Theſe are the ſeuen pillars of the Land,
               on which great Europe Empire ſtandeth faſt
               
                  Pals, Brandenburgh, and Saxony in one hand,
               vnite their ſtrength which makes their powers laſt:
               The Popiſh Prelates at theſe Princes frowne,
               yet theſe three Proteſtants vphold the Crowne.
            
            
               To ſecond them ther's Brund-ſwickes valiant Duke,
               
                  Heſſons great Landſgraue worthy of renowne,
               And for the Popes right ther's the Prince of Luke,
               
               the Citie Cullen and great Ausburge Towne,
               But Franckfords force with Proteſtants doth hold,
               which by the Palſgraues power make Papiſts cold.
            
            
               
               In this faire Franckford Caeſar was inſtal'd,
               this Citie borders on the Palſgraues Land,
               Tis richly furniſht and moſt ſtrongly wal'd,
               well ſtor'd with all prouiſion, ſtoutly man'd.
               But leauing Frankford ſeated on the maine,
               the bridge hath brought me into Pals againe.
            
            
               Betwixt the Riuers that are nam'd before
               the Palſgraues Land ſtands like a Paradice:
               The ground is fruitfull yeelding vine-yards ſtore,
               and mightie woods for hunting exerciſe
               Stand on the hills, inuironing the plaines,
               theſe Forreſts brings the Palſgraue trebble gaines.
            
            
               Firſt they inrich his Countrey (large) with wood,
               ſecondly, they afford him veniſon ſtore,
               Thirdly, for hunting pleaſures they are good,
               to rouze the Stagge, or chaſe the tusked Bore:
               If man on earth would chuſe a place of pleaſure,
               His Country yeelds it in exceeding meaſure.
            
            
               On rocky clifts his ſtately Caſtles ſtand,
               like to mount Sion built of Marble ſtone;
               With turrets out of which he viewes his Land,
               ſuch worthy proſpects heere are few or none.
               Their aire it is ſo wholeſome kinde and ſweet,
               they ſeldome die till death and age doe meete.
            
            
               
               At Bachrade ſtands a Caſtle on a clift,
               and vnderneath a Citty of ſome ſtate,
               Which euer is his eldeſt ſonnes by gift,
               it would ſeeme tedious if I ſhould relate
               Each ſeuerall Caſtle, but let mee report
               the ſtate of Hedelberge his Princely Court.
            
            
               Palace of pleaſure and a houſe of State,
               his winters White-Hall, and his ſummers Hampton,
               
               A Riuer glideth vnderneath the gate,
               which brings him plentie, nothing hath he lack on:
               There ſtands a veſſell which ſhall neare want wine,
               ſo long as earth beares fruit, or ſunne doth ſhine.
            
            
               Braue Knights and Barons on his grace attend,
               His Countries ordered by a Martiall:
               All ſtrangers doe his gouernment commend,
               becauſe in nothing he is partiall,
               But deales withall according to deſert,
               which makes all people honour him in heart.
            
            
               His Court is pleaſant, and his perſon Royall,
               his Councell graue, his Officers care true;
               His Gentry faithfull, and his Commons loyall,
               his lands are fruitfull, what can then enſue?
               Nothing but his Religion, which is grounded
               vpon the Goſpell that hath Rome confounded.
            
            
               
               In him there flowes the beſt of Art and Nature,
               himſelfe like Dauid, and his Court like Sion;
               Of louely viſage and of comely ſtature,
               yet full of maieſty as is a Lion,
               For with ſeueritie his grace is kinde,
               Iuſtice and pittie in his heart are ioyn'd.
            
            
               What may be in a Prince in him their flowes,
               excepting Vice for that he euer hated;
               What ſhould be in a Prince in him their growes:
               for Englands good this good Prince was created,
               His Lawes are iuſt his gouernment is ciuill,
               he doth purſue good and eſcheweth euill.
            
            
               Many braue Caſtles his faire Land doth yeeld,
               and toll houſes vpon the riuer Rhyne,
               
               Which vnderneath his Caſtles he doth build,
               to ſtore his Cofers with all Countrey coyne,
               Each paſſage boate before they paſſe away,
               vnto theſe Toll-houſes muſt cuſtome pay.
            
            
               Fiue Princes in this iron age ſuruiue,
               which makes it ſeeme the ſiluer world againe:
               To match them hardly ſhall we finde out fiue
               yet weell forbeare to ſpeake of France or Spaine,
               
               Fiue heires, fiue youths, fiue kinſmen, and fiue Princes,
               Of one Religion, though in fiue Prouinces.
            
            
               
               Yong Prince of Heſſon is the firſt muſt enter,
               to act his vertues on the worlds Theater;
               Tis hard to finde a yong man on earth's center,
               that is a vertue louer and vice hater,
               Old Landſgraues glaſſe hath many houres to runne,
               whil'ſt all his vertues liueth in his Sonne.
            
            
               Yong Prince of Brundſwicke craues the ſecond place,
               whoſe vertues with him brings a noble ſpirit:
               Hee's milde and courteous, mixt with maieſticke grace,
               his praiſe is not ſo much as he doth merit:
               A Prince, a Schollar, and a Trauailer,
               a peacefull youth and yet a Souldier.
            
            
               Yong Prince of Brandenbergh, Prince abſolute,
               for now thou raigneſt in thy Fathers ſtead;
               Thy eares are open vnto euerr ſuite,
               thy hand is prone to euery worthy deed,
               Many degrees thy vertues doe commence,
               
                  Brandenburgh neuer had a better Prince.
            
            
               Yong Prince of Pals, or Palſgraue of the Rhyne,
               
               were this a Chronicle and the letters gold;
               To regiſter thy vertues moſt diuine,
               to make all Nations wonder to behold,
               Thy grace of all their goodneſſe doth allow,
               But all their graces to thy goodneſſe bowe.
            
            
               
               Yong Prince of England period of my praiſe,
               thy vertues now thou entreſt fils the round,
               Subduing euill and all good to raiſe,
               thy powers ready now my praiſe is crown'd:
               Foure kingdomes comfort, and Great Brittaines ioy,
               miſchiefe befall him that thinkes the annoy.
            
            
               Theſe Princes ſeuerall vertues doe agree,
               and in a true coniunction ſymphathize;
               When Princely fruit ſprings from a royall tree,
               there future branches to the like ſtate riſe:
               Each of theſe are their Countries ioyfull hope,
               friends to the Goſpell, foes toth' Diuell and Pope.
            
            
               Three matchleſſe Virgins in this wanton age,
               vertue doth heere commend for the worlds mirror,
               Their hallowed feete tread on Dyanes ſtage,
               their ſpotleſſe thoughts are free from female error:
               In framing of theſe three, Nature did well,
               but made a fourth that doth her ſelfe excell.
            
            
               
                  Heſſons faire Virgin one of vertues traine,
               Lady of pleaſure, and the Nymph of peace,
               Whoſe face the ſtampe of beauty doth containe,
               which in her liuely image neare ſhall ceaſe;
               A match fit for a Prince, ſweet Saint-like creature,
               wonder of all that gaze on thy faire feature.
            
            
               
               
                  Brunſwicks bright Virgin, Germ
                        •
                     ines louely roſe,
               whoſe veſtall lampe ſhines like the Moone at full,
               Thou art admired by the Dutch-land Froes,
               
                  Saxony vowes thy blowming bud to pull:
               A Prince of vertues and a Princeſſe true
               who can deny, when ſuch for loue doe ſue.
            
            
               
                  Brandingburghs Siſter of an Angels face,
               the top of vertue and the branch of beautie;
               Of humble, modeſt, and maieſticke grace,
               the gods haue ſtroue who firſt ſhould ſhew their duty,
               
                  Dyan and Venus are for hir at ſtrife;
               which choiſe is beſt for hir, a maide or wife.
            
            
               Thus they contend each houre 'boat all three;
               
                  Dyan ſpeakes, Virgins hearken to my voyce,
               Keepe your ſelues ſingle if you would liue free,
               
                  Venus ſayes ſports in bed cauſe maides reioyce.
               But let them chide, I can iudge neither rude,
               till the fourth virgin wife the iarre conclude.
            
            
               
                  Englands faire Phoenix, Europes admiration,
               of matchleſſe beauty, yet of vertue rare;
               A kingdomes comfortable conſolation
               who euer rareſt is, yet ſhe is rarer.
               Now in the Eaſt ſhe lets her ſplendor ſhine▪
               
               all doe confeſſe ſhe is a light diuine.
            
            
               
               She ſeeing Dyan and Loues Queene at odds,
               
                  Dyan made claime, bright Venus ſwore ſhee'd haue hir,
               At laſt the cauſe being heard before the gods;
               
                  Hymen ſtood vp and this ſweet ſentence gaue hir,
               For chaſte virginitie, mates haſt thou none,
               and being wed like thee, ſhall ſcarce be one.
            
            
               Poets leaue writing of the Graecian Queene,
               and of Aeneas, Lady Venus ſonne:
               Two rarer beauties ſhortly ſhall be ſeene
               in Almany, when Englands pride is wonne.
               Make haſt yong Prince, ſwim liuely downe the Rhyne,
               
               to ſtile hir peereleſſe Princeſſe Palatine.
               
            
            
               Lend all your hands to knit this Princely knot,
               all euerlaſting ioy binde ſure the ſame;
               A noble Prince, a Princeſſe without ſpot,
               will fill the trump of euer ſounding fame:
               All Europes bells that ioyfull day ſhall ring,
               
                  Pals hath ioyn'd power, with Englands royall King.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            
               Cupids iourney to Germanie and the effects of the ſame.
            WHen Hymen had his ſentence ended,
            He of the gods was much commended,
            
               Venus was buxome blith and glad
            But Dyans front with frownes look't ſad,
            
               Almaine was fild with loues deſires
            Their heart flam'd Citharean fiers,
            
               Oldenburgs Earle and Heſſons Prince
            Sent preſents from their hearts Prouince:
            Loue in a rich ſhape croſt the maine
            From Courtly France and hauty Spaine,
            
            With hope to gaine this matchleſſe prize.
            But ſtormes of Non-ſuite did ariſe,
            Which fil'd their ſailes with diſcontent,
            And blew them backe incontinent.
            Then Cupid tooke a box of balme,
            And gaue to Neptune for a calme;
            To Aeolus he ſent a ring,
            Intreating him no ſighs to fling:
            In his ſailes forefront thus he went
            To th' Seas imbark't with ſweet content,
            Sweet Zephirus to winne a wreath
            Into loues ſailes goodwill did breath,
            Which ſoone conuey'd him to the Rhyne
            
            Where Bachus quaffes vp Renniſh wine.
            
               There Cupid feaſted in each Court
            And at the length met true report,
            Whoſe newes did cauſe the boy admire,
            Filling his heart with ardent fire.
            And preſently he mounts the skies,
            To craue one of his mothers eyes:
            Shee grants the ſuite and thus ſhe ſpake,
            Ile doe it for the Princes ſake.
            Hir left eye ſhe plac't in his for'head,
            Which made the God of loue adored.
            He tooke his leaue and humbly bends,
            And from hir Deity deſcends;
            The winged youth who vnderſtood,
            His way by's eye through thickeſt wood,
            Where Siluian tooke vp her ſtay,
            And met with Cupid on the way,
            But ſhe from him began to flye,
            When ſhe perceiu'd he had an eye,
            Leaſt he her nakedneſſe ſhould ſee
            She ſhrowdes hir ſelfe behide a tree.
            For Autumne that the field bereaues
            Had left hir nought but withered leaues.
            
               Cupid amaz'd kept ſtill the path
            Which brought him to a priuate bath,
            And cloſe by it a thicket ſtood,
            More like an Arbour then a Wood,
            The willowes twiſted arme in arme,
            To keepe the Bower in winter warme,
            And in the ſummer when the ſunne
            Through the high Meridian runne,
            
               Hee cannot pearce in with bright eyes
            But peepe through hole cut checker wiſe.
            This Arbor fil'd with naked Imphes,
            The thrice three Muſes and their Nymphes.
            
               Dyan with ſundry flowers crown'd
            Begirt abount with Virgins round:
            
               Cupid drew nye and got a ſight,
            Which bred in him no ſmall delight.
            None did deny the ſhamefaſt boy,
            But in him tooke exceeding ioy
            Saue Dyan, whoſe wrath did inuade hir,
            Vntill at length all did perſwade hir
            To ſmiling mirth which ſhee allowes
            And tooke her violl from the bowes,
            Whereon moſt ſweetly ſhe did play
            A well contriued Roundelay.
            
            Which rauiſht ſo the god of Loue,
            That he a queſtion thus did moue.
            You Nymphes and Goddeſſes of grace,
            How doe you call this ſacred place:
            This is (quoth they) the Muſes fountaine,
            Impayl'd with many a craggy mountaine,
            The name of it is Helycon:
            Hence Germaines bounds firſt borders on,
            It parts the lowe Dutch from the high,
            And heere great Caeſars crowne doth lye:
            We know yong Archer thou art ſent,
            To wound a Prince with Loues content;
            Thy ſhaft ſhall not be ſhot in vaine,
            For he a faire Princeſſe ſhall gaine:
            
               Whoſe beauty no Appelles needes,
            Hir vertues all our worths exceeds.
            But haſt thee Cupid, flye away,
            And Hymen crowne their Nuptiall day:
            The one ey'de boy tooke leaue of all,
            And tooke vp's bowe which he lets fall.
            His quiuer on his backe he hung,
            And ſpread both wings and vp he ſprung;
            With matchleſſe ſwiftneſſe to the Rhyne,
            
            Which ſhewes the way to Palatine:
            But being driuen in by ſtormes,
            He was conſtrained to lodge at Wormes.
            
            The Cities worth the God admires,
            And the next day he din'd at Spyres.
            
            But e're the night approached nye,
            He came to the Vniuerſitie;
            Cal'd Hedelberg a famous place,
            Where he beheld the Princes grace
            Well mounted on a ſtately ſteed,
            Which did Bucephalus exceed.
            The day had left the Eaſterne Coaſt,
            And to faire Thetis gallopt poſt;
            Which made the Germaine mountaines darke,
            
               Cupid drew nye to view the marke:
            And at his boſome ſent a ſhaft,
            Which after it a tincture left;
            No ſooner Cupid dedicates
            This ſtroke, but ſtraight he eleuates
            To the gods, where he a lecture redde,
            How loue had metamorphoſed
            
               This Princes heart perplext with paine,
            Which cauſed him to croſſe the maine
            To Brittaines Coaſt, firſt Graue-ſend gaines him,
            And England brauely entertaines him.
            The Court his company deſires,
            
               London the louely Prince admires;
            Such ioy ſprung forth on euery ſide,
            That all the Gods mans mirth enuide:
            Therefore they held a Parliament,
            How they might worke his diſcontent,
            Laſt they agree'd (O! diſmall day)
            To take our chiefeſt hope away.
            Grim viſag'd death preſum'd to ſtrike
            A Prince that neuer had his like;
            For as his vertue all excel'd
            His valour was vnparralel'd
            Heauen tooke his worth, earth knew his want,
            And made a generall complaint;
            Great Brittaine clad in ſable blacke,
            With endleſſe teares lament his lacke.
            This hopefull match begot great gladneſſe,
            But Henries death a ſolemne ſadneſſe.
            And had not theſe two oppoſites
            Met, England ſure had loſt hir wits:
            For had their beene no funerall,
            To ſtay this happy Nuptiall
            This Kingdome being ouerioy'd,
            With mirth her ſelfe might haue deſtroy'd.
            So had their beene no Nuptiall,
            After this driery funerall,
            
               This Iland would her ſelfe confound,
            Of force to drowne with her owne teares
            A heart of cork. Therefore the Scene,
            'Twixt mirth and mourning kept the meane.
            And time which all things doth expell,
            Prouided for this Kingdome wel:
            For though he tooke our hope away,
            He left behinde a ſecond ſtay,
            Whom heauens higheſt hand preſerue
            For he all goodneſſe doth deſerue.
            Thus leauing hearts with ſorrowes clad,
            For him whoſe like earth neuer had;
            Tis fit my pen purſue the carriage,
            Of this ſelected ſacred marriage:
            Twixt theſe two Princes dignity,
            Who were with all ſolemnitie,
            Ioyn'd with the forefront of the ſpring,
            In Nuptiall bands before a King.
            But time that for no King will ſtay,
            Conducts this Virgin bride away;
            T'wards her new confines, bleſt conten
            Attended on her grace in Kent:
            The trees ſtood all in ſuites of greene,
            To guard this Nymph-like natures Queen.
            
            She leaues a Land where ſhe is knowne,
            To ſee a ſtrange Land of her owne.
            The louely Nightingale did ſing,
            Hir ſweete farewell from Englands King.
            
            Thus after many parting ſtories,
            Time brought them to their teritories:
            
               And eare twelue moneths their courſe had run
            Betwixt them they poſſeſt a Sonne.
            This bleſſed newes the Seas ſent poſt,
            To comfort vs for him we loſt;
            From Henry's aſhes, there is ſprung,
            A ſecond Henry, who eare long
            We hope ſhall in this Land arriue,
            The hearts of all men to reuiue:
            And greet his royall Grand-ſires raigne,
            The Queene and's Vncle Charlamayne.
            
            Whom heauen ſtill protect and bleſſe,
            With royall iſſue to poſſeſſe
            This Kingdome, Scepter, and beare ſway,
            Till Sunne and Moone doe paſſe away.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            The Originall and continuance of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, as it was ſpoken before the Kings Maieſtie, on Saint GEORGES day laſt: Anno Dom. 1616.
            
            By W. FENNOR.
            
            
               
                  EDward the third, that truely Potent King,
               whoſe Temples worthily wore Englands Crowne:
               This Noble Order, of whoſe fame I'le ſing,
               inuents for Britaines Trophy of renowne.
               
                  Salſburies Counteſſe, hath all Ladies grac't,
               that looſe their Garter, yet keepe Honour chaſt.
            
            
               From Honor'd chaſtitie the Garter fell,
               and in a moment roſe to royaltie:
               King Edward grac't this Ladies fauour well,
               who humbly bends his kingly Maieſty,
               Catcht vp the ribbon had a leg inbrac't
               that neuer capor'd with a ſtep vnchaſt.
            
            
               The Lady dies her cheekes with tell-tale redde
               which blabs ſhe bluſhes, that her Garters found,
               By him that had aduanc't it to a head,
               which with Imperiall dignity was crown'd:
               The Nobles murmur, and the King by chance
               perceiv'd, ſpoke Hony ſoit quy maly penſe.
               
            
            
               
               Exchanges lawleſſe loue for lawfull Armes,
               buckles on' armour, weell's his warlike ſword,
               Beats his brac't Drums, Trumpets ſounds alarums:
               thus like bold Hector rode he to the field,
               Subdu'd his foes, and for his deeds in fight,
               of the rich Garter was inſtal'd a Knight.
            
            
               Which bred ſuch luſter in each Noble breſt,
               as if new Troy had muſtred vp the Sonnes,
               Of ſtrong back't Priam, and amongſt the reſt,
               the bold blacke Prince toth' field moſt fiercely runs;
               And with his ſword hammor'd in Vulcans forge,
               made the French Dennys kneele to Engliſh George.
               
            
            
               For which he with the Garter was inſtal'd,
               and made a Knight of that moſt Noble Order;
               With many other Nobles that were cal'd
               worthy by fame, that ancient, true Recorder.
               
               The Garter bred ſuch luſter in great hearts,
               each ſtroue for excellence in Armes and Arts.
            
            
               Saint Patricks Croſſe, did to the Garter vayle,
               Saint Iaques Order waxt with anger pale:
               Saint Dauids leeke began to droupe ith tale,
               Saint Dennys he ſate mourning in a dale;
               Saint Andrew look't with cheerefull appetite,
               as though toth' Garter he had future right.
            
            
               
               But Dragon-killing George that ſtill depends
               vpon the Garter ſince third Edwards dayes;
               In this age preſent hath as many friends,
               as well deſeruing high eternall praiſe:
               As any ages euer had before,
               neuer at one time better; neuer more.
            
            
               
                  Hanniball ſtroue for Romes triumphant bayes.
               
                  Scipio for the Carthaginians bough;
               But thankleſſe Senators did dimme the rayes,
               of theſe two worthies, and would not allow,
               Nor wreath, nor branch, they dy'd and left their fame
               vnto the glory of the Garters name.
            
            
               Impartially a royall King beſtowes it,
               vpon ſome Subiect worthy of the wearing;
               His Armes aduanc't within a Church that owes it,
               the oath adminiſtred in publike hearing,
               Which being falſifyed, the Honors croſt,
               by Heraldry, the Armes, and Garter loſt.
            
            
               Say that a man long languiſhing in loue,
               whoſe heart with hope and feare growes cold and warme:
               Admit ſome pitty ſhould his ſweet-heart moue,
               to knit a fauour on his feeble arme;
               All parts would ioyne, to make that one ioynt ſtrong,
               to appoſe any that his loue ſhould wrong.
            
            
               
               The Garter is the fauour of a King
               claſping the leg, on which mans beſt part ſtands;
               A poeſye in t', as in a Nuptiall ring,
               binding the heart, to their liege Lord in bands;
               That whil'ſt the leg hath ſtrength, or the arme power,
               to kill that Serpent would their King deuoure.
            
            
               For which the George is as a Trophy worne,
               and may it long, and long remaine with thoſe,
               Which to that excellent dignitie are borne:
               as oppoſites vnto their Countries foes.
               God keepe our King and them from Romes black pen,
               let all that loue the Garter ſay, Amen.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            The Deciding of the Difference betwixt the two Vniuerſities, Oxford and Cambridge, about the Kings entertainement, ſpoke before his Maieſty at Theobalds,
               the xiij. of Iuly, 1615.
            
            By W. F.
            
            
               PErnaſſus and the fountaine fell at ods,
            Who ſhould giue beſt content vnto the gods:
            The mountaine ſpake, tis not thy fenne can yeeld
            Such learned Arts, nor can thy foggy fiel'd,
            Giue ſuch delightfull taſte to gods or men,
            As my ſweet ſhady groues; Hellicon then
            Returnes this anſwere, though thou that ſtands on high,
            My braines are moiſt when thine are hote and dry.
            But leauing this vpbraiding argument,
            To ſtand to triall dar'ſt thou be content:
            (Dare? quoth Pernaſſus) yes I dare and will,
            Make triall when thou dar'ſt not ſhew thy skill.
            Thus throwing downe their Gauntlets they appeal'd,
            Vnto the Gods who iuſtly with them deal'd:
            
               Ioue ſent his nimble footed Mercury,
            
            With all the Trophyes of high Herauldry,
            
            To ſignifie vnto the learned Mount,
            That kingly Ioue himſelfe made full account
            To viſite him in's progreſſe; ſhe or'ioy'd,
            Hir chiefeſt, choyſeſt, cureſt wits imploy'd;
            
               To giue him welcome, Syluian left the woods,
            Heardſ-men their cattell, Townſ-men from their goods
            Fled with amazement to be hold the ſhew
            Of royall maieſtie. Amongſt this rowe
            Stept in ſome fortie of Helconians race,
            Amongſt the Pernaſitians tooke their place,
            To view in ſecret note the whole euent
            Of his receiuing, welcome, and content,
            And where a word or letter was miſtooke,
            To Brack a gram it in a Table-booke.
            Time turn'd three hower glaſſes, whilſt they ſtood
            Expecting him whoſe ſight ſhould doe them good:
            But on a ſudden all their voyces ſummes,
            A ioyfull generall clamour, yon he comes,
            See, ſee, whoſe that rides with agilitie;
            Peace, peace, that's one of the Nobilitie,
            Who paſſed by in ſtate and due degree;
            And after them his Royall Maieſtie.
            Drawne by the winged Courſers of the ſunne,
            About whoſe Chariot thouſand people runne:
            With ſhouts of ioy the multitude ſtill ſpeakes,
            Welcome dread King, the Students, Viuat Rex:
            
            The Heardſ-men mov'd to teſtifie their loues,
            Beſtow'd on him a paire of hunting gloues.
            So vſhard him vnto Parnaſſus hill,
            And there to welcome him ſhew'd their beſt skill,
            With Masking, reuells, and a Comedy,
            Which was performed very ſolemnly.
            In penning it the Poet paines did take,
            To cauſe Ioue ſleepe, though he himſelfe did wake.
            
               But when their ſports were paſt, great Ioue retyr'd,
            Yet at their learned arts he much admir'd:
            
               Helycons Nymphs returned to their Cell,
            And there the whole diſcourſe of all did tell:
            Which when ſome heard, they laid their heads together,
            And made a Ballad of the Buck-skins leather.
            
               The kings entertainment at Cambridge.
               Now time with ſtealing ſteps doth ſwiftly haſt,
            Imagine ſeauen yeeres compleatly paſt;
            When Ioue remembring the Gods requeſt,
            Hath tane his royall iourney North by Eaſt;
            To viſit the diſtreſſed Helycon,
            
            Whoſe face till now his eye neare look't vpon.
            
               Parnaſſus hearing, that he thither would,
            From frozen Alpes ſent forth a bitter cold;
            Which did congeale the waues of Neptune ſo,
            That all the water in the ayre turn'd ſnow.
            And from the ponderous clouds, fell downe in flakes,
            Couering high mountaines, filling dales and lakes.
            By which the little brookes forſooke their bounds;
            And waters all the paſſages ſo drown'ds,
            That thouſands durſt not venture, yet his Grace
            Held firme his reſolution, ſpight the face
            Of griſled Hyems, or ſtrene Boreas,
            
            
               Aeolus, Auſter, or ſweet Zephirus.
            
            Thither he would to view the learned skill,
            Betwixt the fountaine and Parnaſſus hill.
            
               Minerua hearing this, ſhe cal's the Clownes,
            And ruſticke ſwaines, and ſaide, put on your gownes:
            You firſt ſhall meet his Maieſtie in order,
            By the aduice and wit of your Recorder:
            
            
               Out rode the ruſtickes in their glittering pride,
            And when they had their royall Ioue eſpyed,
            Vpſtart God Pan, who with a ſtudied ſpeech
            His kingly Maieſty he did beſeech;
            That hee'd be pleaſd ſtill to protect his darling,
            Before his Croch came neere by halfe a furlong.
            Moreouer that the Nymphes might beare no ſway,
            Aboue them and their wiues by night or day.
            And furthermore their good wils to vnfold,
            They gaue a ſiluer cup was three yeeres old:
            So gaue him way, he on rides toward's the Towne,
            Met by Minerua in a ſcarlet gowne;
            Who ſpoke a rare ſpeech, of ſuch high deſerning;
            That at the very firſt ſhe ſhew'd her learning.
            Which when Ioue heard he rode vnto the Cell,
            And after was conducted to the well;
            Where he moſt freely of the water taſted,
            And for foure daies this royall paſtime laſted.
            But when Mineruaes maides their wits had ſpent,
            Great Ioue retir'd thence incontinent:
            Yet at his parting graciouſly did ſay,
            He would returne and viſite them in May.
            
            Which promiſe he perform'd, Parnaſſus then
            Wrote ſharpe invectiues from her whipping penne,
            Which ſent to Helicon, were backe retorted,
            Thus theſe two worthies the wide world haue ſported.
            Th' are like two famous Caſtles in one Towne,
            Who for their worth's would put each other downe:
            Or like a iealous husband who breeds ſtrife,
            If he eſpy another lookes on's wife.
            
               Two beautious Virgins cannot well indure,
            One man vnto them both ſhould be made ſure:
            Were there a difference t'wood be no contention,
            But being equals both, breeds this diſcention.
            But to conclude, Parnaſſus is the mountaine,
            Of learned Arts; and Helicon the fountaine,
            And this is all I'le ſay of both, I thinke
            The one giues food to vs, the other drinke:
            Then why ſhould they each others worth controule,
            Since they can both giue Phyſicke for the ſoule?
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A ſpeech concerning the Gowries treaſon, and the Gun-Powder-Plot: ſpoken before the Kings Maieſty, at the Biſhops Palace at Salysbury, Alias Sarum,
               the fifth of Auguſt. 1615.
            
            By W. F.
            
            NO Poets Muſe can better tidings bring
            Then mine: the ſafetie of a royall King;
            Yet I with words cannot deſcribe the faction,
            So well as you, dread King, which try'd the action
            Of baſe deluding Traitours: whoſe inuention
            Proceeded from the authour of diſcention.
            Whoſe blacke plots in the heart all miſchiefe ſowes,
            Which not preuented to ranke Treaſon growes.
            As this day well can witneſſe to all ages,
            The Gowries cruell and inſatiate rages:
            Well may their titles ſtile them goe awry,
            Who in their by-paths led a King to die.
            But th'Almightie for his choſen ſtands,
            And ſtrikes amazement, ſtaies the villaines hands,
            That are lift vp againſt his true Anointed,
            All praiſe be to him, that all diſappointed;
            Nay, gaue vnto your Maieſty ſuch ſtrength,
            To grapple with your Butcher, till at length
            He ſhew'd his power, as once to Abraham,
            
            And in the place of Iſaac ſent a Ram;
            
               Who ruſhing through the midſt of bramble thornes,
            He gor'd the Gowries with his two edg'd hornes;
            Which deed hath rais'd his name eternally,
            And hurl'd them downe to laſting infamy.
            For whoſoeuer ſpeakes of Ramſeyes name,
            Shall found it to the Gowries endleſſe ſhame:
            Or whil'ſt the fifth of Auguſt can giue light,
            Let men giue praiſes to the God of might.
            And let it be as Holy-day obſerued,
            Wherein your grace by wonder was preſerued.
            Or who ſoeuer ſhall that day remember
            Let him record the fifth of cold Nouenber,
            
            Where they the Diuells higheſt plot ſhall read;
            Who ſought not to deſtroy the royall ſeede
            Alone: but with it all poſteritie,
            The Gentry and the States Nobilitie.
            Making this Land a Chaos in an houre,
            After replant in it their forraine power:
            But heauen's iuſt, when he begins to ſpeake,
            And ſent a warning in Mounteagles beake;
            As he by Ioſeph did to Pharaoh tell,
            Of ſcarcitie for th'good of Iſrael.
            
            So in your royall heart he ſent a doubt,
            By which the hight of Treaſon was found out:
            And the baſe Traitours for their workes rewarded,
            Thus a good Prince is by the Angels guarded.
            What Plots were lay'd gainſt Queene Elizabeth,
            
            To cut her off by an vntimely death?
            Yet maugre all their blaſted blacke infection
            She liv'd, till heauen cal'd her by election.
            
               Inioy abounding, and her Princely Throne,
            She left vnto your Maieſty alone:
            Whom God hath placed with a peacefull hand,
            The like hath ſcarce beene heard in any Land;
            To haue ſo many foes, and all turne friends
            By th'which the ſword of warre, toth' Oliue bends.
            I gheſſe the reaſon ſince you entred heere,
            The Lion rampant keepes the reſt in feare:
            The Dragon is diſmiſt, whoſe poyſonous breath;
            Hath oft beene cauſe of many a thouſands death.
            And in the place you haue put the Vnicorne,
            
            T' expell the poyſon with his precious Horne;
            By which each royall ſubiect ſafe may dyne,
            And taſte the propper fruit of his owne vine:
            Then if ingratefull men will this record,
            Can they forget to praiſe or laud the Lord
            For his preſeruing, of you many wayes,
            Giuing them peace in your moſt happy daies.
            Sure who forgets, is an vngratefull gueſt,
            Not worthy to inioy this peacefull feaſt:
            Which God continue many, many yeeres,
            And ſtill preſerue you from all forraine feares:
            Falſe plots at home, euer confounding thoſe,
            Who in their heart profeſſe to be your foes.
            But let good ſubiects Haleluiah ſing
            To God, for the protecting our good King,
            O! let their prayers inuocate agen,
            God long preſerue your grace, Amen, Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A Paſtorall Sonnet containing a Parliament of the Gods.
            
               WAlking of late it was my chance,
               To view Floraes roſy bowers;
               When drowſie Morpheus into a trance,
               Did confine me certaine howres
               Where I might ſpy, very much reſort paſſe to amaine
               And one did come vnto me this meeting to explaine.
               Come, quoth he, prepare thy ſelfe to goe,
               Where thou ſhall attend,
               I to thee the full euent will ſhew
               Whereto and what end:
               Straight me thought I was conuayed away,
               Wherevnto my ſenſe he did diſplay,
               How that this meeting was of all the Gods,
               And that braue Mars and Vulcane falne were at ods:
               
                  Vulcane as plaintiffe did for iuſtice cry,
               Cauſe Mars which was defendant, did with Venus lye.
               And moreouer would diſcouer,
               but (alas) it was, his fate:
               Whil'ſt he's working, they are lurking,
               how they may cornute his pate▪
               
               Straight a diſcention there aroſe,
               Who in iudgement chiefe ſhould ſit,
               
                  Fearing that man would hold them as foes,
               Each of other thought moſt fit.
               At laſt it paſt, that bright Sol as Vmpire needs muſt ſtand,
               For why, his eye vnderneath the Spheares,
               hath chiefe command.
               
                  Phoebus at the laſt did condiſcend,
               Yet with this condition
               
                  Cynthia might ſit as Venus friend,
               Ioyntly in commiſſion:
               Preſently was ſet a chaire of State,
               On which the pale fac't Luna ſate;
               Next Ioue and Iuno, did aſſume their place;
               Then Saturne, Aeolus, and Neptune with his Mace.
               After Appollo with the Muſes nine,
               And blackt fac't Pluto tooke his place by Proſerpine:
               
               And belowe, there ſate a rowe of Shepheards,
               Which adore God Pan;
               
               Each one ſitting, all thing fitting,
               ſtraight a ſilence there began.
            
            
               A ciuill ſilence being proclaimed,
               One there ſtood vp preſently,
               And as I deeme he was Mercury nam'd,
               Which full loud began to cry
               O yes, then he pauſd a while and began againe,
               O yes, ſilence in the Court on further paine.
               Thus O yes, being thrice proclaimed,
               they beginne to plod,
               On the inditements which pertained
               'gainſt this worldly god.
               
                  Straight a Iury of twelue Shepheards Swaines,
               Which with rurall paſtime keepe the plaines;
               Impannel'd were the ſole euents to proue
               'Twixt Noble Mars, and Venus faire, the Queene of loue.
               Without Atturneyes Mars and Vulcane plead,
               And Venus abſent, Cupid ſtood in's mothers ſtead:
               
                  Vulcan ſtill ſwore, Mars did ill,
               in wronging of his marriage bed;
               Which was cauſe 'gainſt reaſon lawes,
               he alwayes wore a Heart-like head.
               
                  Mars in reply was reſolute,
               As he e're in the field did fight,
               And ſoone he did poore Vulcane confute
               Sometime might, may ore'come right.
               Yet he did gree vnto all that Vulcan could report,
               And would withhold, if this age would yeeld him better ſport.
               For, quoth Mars, alas, I am kept ſo long
               From my wonted vſe,
               'Its no maruell though I Vulcan wrong
               With ſo ſmall abuſe.
               Idely I ſleepe in Ladies laps,
               Childiſhly I am dandled on their paps;
               Armour, ſhield, ſword, which oft my foes did chaſe,
               Are into ſilkes and veluets turn'd, O too too baſe,
               I that before my foes in field did iuſt,
               Now in a downe-bed lye, whil'ſt all my Armor doth ruſt,
               Souldiers now, alas muſt bow,
               vnto each ſilken feathered Swaine;
               That before had gold good ſtore,
               beſides the credit they did gaine.
               
                  Thus hauing ended, the Iury reſin'd
               The ſole verdict, which did ſay,
               
                  Mars in no errour at all they could finde,
               But the Fault in Cupid lay:
               Which then began to excuſe himſelfe, but all in vaine,
               And ſwore no more ruſticke clownes,
               henceforth his loue ſhould gaine.
               Crooked Vulcan ſeeing that his ſuit,
               Might no whit preuaile
               On poore Cupid, which alas ſtood mute,
               He began to raile,
               Hud wink't boy, how dareſt thou be ſo bold,
               As let flie thoſe ſhafts whoſe heads were gold;
               It had beene fitter ſhot with them of lead,
               Then Mars had ne're made me to weare a horned head.
               
                  Cupid made anſwere, vrging this diſgrace
               If hornes thou were,
               thou need'ſt not feare to breake thy face;
               
                  Sol ſtood vp &amp; drank a cup of Nectar, to his fellow gods
               Which being done, he thus begun,
               to ſentence this there fore paſt odds.
            
            
               
                  Cupid, quoth Phoebus, hold vp thy hand,
               Heare thy ſentence from my lips;
               Twelue moneths I baniſh thee the Faiery Land,
               Cauſe bright Mars thou doſt eclipſe,
               Thy flight with ſpight, hath bereft ſouldiers thy chiefeſt ioy
               In place of diſgrace, hath tooke vp her ſeat,
               to worke annoy:
               Wel, quoth Cupid, I your wils obey, but il'e match you al;
               
                  And no doubt, ea're long i'le finde a day,
               when to minde i'le call;
               How that you wrong'd the God of loue,
               As the ſtout's of all in time ſhall proue:
               Peace elſe, quoth Ioue, what doſt thou threaten me?
               Yes Ioue, ere long, ſhall finde me ſtrong,
               to o're match the
                     •
                  
                  ▪
               
               The Court being ended, long they did not ſtay
               They to their Manſions, Cupid baniſh't, went away.
               Then came he that firſt led me,
               with charge my viſion to indite▪
               
               'Twixt warres King, and loues bright Queene,
               to relate 
                     〈…〉
                   ſpight▪
               
               He being gone, my eies anone, from ſleepe 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               their ha
                     •
                  ery freng
                     •
                  
                  ▪
               
               Now remaines▪ I take ſome paines▪
               
               in the relating loues reuenge▪
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            Gentle R
                  ••
               der, in Cupids iourney to Germany, there is 
                  〈◊〉
                a line miſplac't, being the ſecond line of the laſt page 
                  〈…〉
               .
            
               Of force to drown'd with hir owne teares, read
            
               With hir owne teares, of force to drown'd.
            
            
         
      
   

