
   
      
         
            The compters common-wealth, or A voiage made to an infernall iland long since discouered by many captaines, seafaring-men, gentlemen, marchants, and other tradesmen but the conditions, natures, and qualities of the people there inhabiting, and of those that trafficke with them, were neuer so truly expressed or liuely set foorth as by William Fennor His Maiesties servant.
            Fennor, William.
         
         
            
               1617
            
         
         Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00646
            STC 10781
            ESTC S102012
            99837813
            99837813
            2156
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00646)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2156)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The compters common-wealth, or A voiage made to an infernall iland long since discouered by many captaines, seafaring-men, gentlemen, marchants, and other tradesmen but the conditions, natures, and qualities of the people there inhabiting, and of those that trafficke with them, were neuer so truly expressed or liuely set foorth as by William Fennor His Maiesties servant.
                  Fennor, William.
               
               [6], 85, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Edward Griffin for George Gibbes and are to be sold at his shoppe in Pauls Churchyard at the signe of the Floure-de-luce,
                  London :
                  1617.
               
               
                  Describes his experience as a prisoner for debt.
                  The words "by William Fennor His Maiesties servant" are bracketed together on the title page.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Debt, Imprisonment for --  England --  Early works to 1800.
               London (England) --  Social life and customs --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-04
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-04
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE COMPTERS COMMON-WEALTH, OR A VOIAGE MADE TO an Infernall ILAND long ſince diſcouered by many Captaines, Seafaringmen, Gentlemen, Marchants, and other Tradeſmen:
            
               BVT THE CONDITIONS, NAtures, and qualities of the people there inhabiting, and of thoſe that trafficke with them, were neuer ſo truly expreſſed or liuely ſet foorth as
            BY WILLIAM FENNOR HIS MAIESTIES SERVANT.
            
            
               LONDON Printed by Edward Griffin for George Gibbes and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe in Pauls Churchyard at the ſigne of the Floure-de-luce. 1617.
         
         
            
            
               Ad Lectorem, Sufficit ſcire locum eſſe in Carcere:
            
            
               It is enough to know, too much to ſee
               That in the Compter there is roome for thee.
            
         
         
            
            TO ALL CASHEERD Captaines, or other their inferiour Officers, heedleſſe and headleſſe young Gentle-men, eſpecially elder brothers, forſaken Seruing-men, Rearing-boyes, Broken-Citizens, Country-Clients, or any other of what art or faſhion ſoeuer, that ſhall by chance, rather miſchance, be vnreſiſtably encountred, and ſo become tenants againſt their wils, within the Territories of this enſuing Common-wealth, greeting and meeting, rather at an Ordinary then here.
            
               Worthy Gentle-men;
            
            
               I Reſt aſſured this ſmall volume (being no Elephantine load of Mogoulian ſtory, compiled by the wandring Pawne-Knight of Troy) will bee bought and read ouer by manie, how it will be cenſured. I know not, or how I ſhall be reputed for publiſhing it, to deale plainly, I care not, ſo it bring future benefit to my Countrey, And ſome preſent benefit to my ſelfe. and content to the iudicious, to whom I commend it for two eſpeciall reaſons. The firſt ſtands grounded on theſe three points▪ a Proſpectiue Glaſſe, an Inſtructiue
               
               Booke, and a Suſpectiue blow. For as Proſpectiue ſet to the ſight of a mans eye, will draw the Obiect ſo neere the ſence, that hee may diſcerne whether his oppoſite be friend or foe, and make haſte too, either to embrace the one, or ſhunne the other, before he come neere him: ſo in this glaſſe, a young Gentleman may plainely perceiue the folly that raignes in others, and ſeeke to eſchew them before they take hold, which will hurry him into theſe inconueniences. It is a booke to inſtruct young heires to keepe out of books and bonds, which oftentimes are the maine cauſe of their ouerthrow, and brings that long ſuſpected blow vpon their ſhoulders, which if it chance to light heere, they may cleerely diſcouer the Keepers large conſcience, and be throwly inſtructed to ſhunne their extortion. My ſecond reaſon is an Apologie, to ſhield mee from thoſe wounding tongues, that may perhaps taxe me for writing ſo harſhly againſt Citizens, Prodigals, Sargeants and other Officers, to ſuch I anſwer, let the gall'd iade winch till he breake his heeles againſt my buckler, which thus I aduance. How much I reuerence and reſpect the Right Worſhipfull Order of this famous City in their iuſt proceedings, let my beſt and vtmoſt ſeruice be a true witneſſe. Neither ſeeme I to carpe at the bounty or large expence of young Gentle-men, whoſe meanes and birth are correſpondent. No, no, I rather encourage and commend their worths, for of ſuch there are too few, and for their ſakes onely, I haue diſcouered what trappes and ſnares are daily ſet by careleſſe Vnthrifts, to winde them into the like ruine they themſelues are in▪ They haue ſtrange deuices, and a certain kinde of longing to caſt their eſtates in a conſumption,

by which their perſons may lie languiſhing vnder that infectious diſeaſe, wherewith they themſelues are poyſoned, by the incurable plague of pouerty. Concerning Sargeants, I hope there are none ſo ſhallow conceited, to thinke my pen ſo full of vineger, to write againſt their meere profeſsion, which in a well-gouern'd State is ſo neceſſary. I rather wiſh they were as free from abuſing their place and office, as I am from diſliking of it, and then a ſhorter chapter would ſerue to diſcouer their ſiniſter deuices &amp; treacherous dealings, which I haue obſerued ſo carefully, that if any of the fraternity of the Mace-mongers chance to fall ſicke at the conceit, let them but diligently view it ouer, and they ſhall finde as comfortable cordials to refreſh the heart, as I did from that colde cawdle when they firſt arreſted me, which I willingly beſtow vpon them in requitall. But me thinkes I heare ſome curious Criticke murmure before he hath read ouer halfe the preamble, becauſe I entitle it a Common-wealth, and begin it ſo ſingly with my ſelfe: to ſuch I anſwer my vnwilling experience and not reports of that they ſhall read hereafter, emboldened mee to write the truth, that I haue tried, which may beget beleefe in thoſe that read, if not, I wiſh it may be their good fortunes to goe the voyage, and let them confute me if they can. If any ſhall obiect what reaſon I haue to diſcourſe of the foure branches, before I come to the maine body of the Commonwealth, and ſtand ſo long on them, deferring their expectations, let them reſt ſatisfied with this anſwer. A building cannot be raiſed without a ground-worke, or a tree will ſeeme naked without branches, and a man wanting limbs to ſupport him, is but a decrepit bodie,

which I conſidering haue adorned this Ocean with compleat Riuers, which are indeede the beſt Benefactours that belong to it. The firſt three chapters ſhew how diſtreſſe and oppreſsion ioyn'd hands to wound my weake and vnprouided eſtate, by which ſingle example, all o her may diſcerne the true vſage they ſhall receiue from the kinde Keepers, if their meanes once faile or their friends for ſake them. The foure chapters following, lay open the foure armes or currents, with their ſeuerall natures, that bring ſupply to this body or maine Ocean, which in the laſt three chapters is liuely anatomized. The cruelty of Keepers and the miſery of Priſoners. For the truth of which I haue quoted an authority in the margent, and for your delight mingled it with many pleaſant diſcourſes, which I freely ſend abroad to all, either to thoſe that haue beene paſſengers through this troubleſome Ocean, and know the danger, or to any that ſhall heereafter, vpon ſpeciall occaſion, before'd to make proofe of this relation. Laſtly, to thoſe that haue no deſire to venture this voyage, but will rather be contented to ſit at home and read the the diſcouery. I commend it with as much loue as Keepers beare to priſoners purſes when they haue money in them, wiſhing it might proue as delightfull to them, as their ill dealings were hatefull to me, and ſo farewell. From the Compter in Woodſtreet. 1616. Octob. 23.
            
               Yours in what he may, thus beſtraited and diſtracted, William Fenner,
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               THE COMPTERS COMMON-WEALTH. OR A voyage made to an infernall Iland, long ſince diſcouered by many Captaines, Sea-faring-men, Gentle-men, Marchants, and other Tradeſmen.
            
            The Penner WILLIAM FENNOR His Maieſties Seruant.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. I. Containing, 1. The manner of my arreſt. 2. The deſcription of a brace of Sergeants. 3. Their counſaile to me, 4. My comming into priſon. 5. The Deſcription of a Iaylor. 6. And my entertainment into the Maſterſide.
               
                  WAlking (not long ſince) in an euening through the city, when the Heauens were muffled vp in clowdes, as many of our moderne Gallants faces are in their cloakes, and being in a fixt meditation with my ſelfe, a Trinobantine Burger (comming in haſte) ranne full but at me with his head, ſo that he had nigh goar'd me into the kennell, (I tooke him to be ſome compleat harneſſed

benchbeleagerer, for hee had a wrought night-cap on his head to keepe the broath of his wit warme, ſatten ſleeues, a taffata ierkin to couer his canuaſſe backe; and a paire of veluet hoſe.) I, for his vnexpected curteſie, not forgetting to giue him the good time of the night, vp with my ſword ſcabbard and all, and tooke him a ſound knock o'rethwart the pate, that if the moſt head-ſtrongſt oxe that euer was ſacrificed in Saint Nicholas Shambles, had receiued but halfe ſuch a blow, it would haue ſtaggered him; but hee like a valiant and prouident Tradeſman, bare it off with his Sinciput and ſhoulders and ranne away.
               I (as glad I was rid of him as he of me) poſted as faſt to my lodging, as a releaſt priſoner (hey ho a priſoner) from the Iayle, for feare he ſhould run to the Compter and enter an action againſt me; but hauing eſcap't the Charybdis of this danger, I inſtantly fell into the Scylla of a more deepe and dreadfull then the firſt, for as I was making homewards, a brace of Bandogs belonging to one of the Compters, moſt cowardly came ſnarling behind me, and faſtened on my ſhoulder, giuing me this ſalutation. Sir we arreſt you in the Kings Maieſties name, and we charge you to obey vs.
               
               Theſe Rauens had no ſooner croak't out this ominous meſſage, but I lookt as blancke as thoſe that ſolde all their eſtate, and ventured it at a lottery and drew blancke, or an olde Vſurer when hee heares of a Priuie ſeale, or a coppy-holder plow-holder when be is ſerued with a Sub poena; but all could not preuaile, I was forc't to obey them for feare of further inconuenience, ſo rendred my weapon into their hands; and my body to the Lawes of my Soueraigne, telling them the thunder I ſo much feared, was now fallen on mine head. Yet the thought of my arreſt did not ſo much affright me as the coūtenances of thoſe peuterbuttond, ſhoulderclapping Catch-poles that ſeazed on my body. The one

had a face ten times worſe then thoſe Iewes that are picturedThe deſcription of a brace 
                        •
                      of Sargeants. in Arras-hangings whipping Chirſt, his blacke haire hung dangling about his eares like Elfelockes, that I cannot be perſwaded, but ſome Succubus begot him on a Witch, his noſe was precious, richly rubified, &amp; ſhined brighter then any Sumners ſnout in Lancaſhire. The other of theſe Pagans had a phiſnomy much reſembling the Sarazens head without Newgate, and a mouth as wide vaulted as that without Biſhopſgate: I was in a great doubt whether he were an Engliſhman or no, for I was certified a Dane begot him on a Switzers wife: and to make him ſhew the more like himſelfe, his ill-fauoured viſage was almoſt eaten through with pock-holes, (the Grand I hope) ſo that halfe a pariſh of children might eaſily haue playd at cherry-pit in his face.
               Theſe Furies had no ſooner faſtened their ſharpe fleſh-hookes on my ſhoulders, but they (as their faſhion is) began to exhort mee to patience, telling mee, I ought not to be incenſt againſt them, for they were but the Miniſters and Executioners of the Law, and that the Mace which they held in their clutches, was put into theirs by the hand of Iuſtice, that they were both for the good of the Common-wealth, and the diſcharge of their owne conſciences, ſworne to execute their office though it were vpon their owne father, that I being ſo gracious in the Court, could not long be detained in the Compter, that after I had beene reſident there but one quarter of a yeere (if it ſhould bee my ill fate to ſtay there ſo long) I would not loſe the rich experience I ſhould learne there for ten times ſo much debt I was arreſted for. And laſtly, ſwore as they were Chriſtians, they would doe me what kindneſſe lay in their power, either perſwading my Creditour to come to a reaſonable compoſition, or prouide me Baile, the Cormorants tolde me true, for they ſwore as they were

Chriſtians they would doe me good, but being contrary to them, playde the Iewes, and falſified their oathes with me, for I neuer ſaw them after I was mewed vp in the Compter. But before I was matriculated in one of theſe city vniuerſities, by perſwaſion they got mee into a Tauerne not farre from (the inchanted Caſtle) the Priſon, and there milk't me out of all my money to ſtuffe their paunches with wine and good cheere: but their guts and garbidge being full-gorg'd, they told me it was time to repaire to the Compter, for if the Sheriffe their maſter ſhould be certified of their detaining a Priſoner ſo long after an arreſt, it would bee a great preiudice to them, and ſmall good to my ſelfe: ſo I diſcharging the reckoning, wiſhing them choak't, and all their fellow varlets, that euer after ſhould taſte of my bounty (when I began to ſent their rogery) came ouer with them, ſo bid them farewell and behang'd.
               But heere is one ſerious point not to be ſlipt ouer, for the Cerberus that turned the key of the Compter-gate, no ſooner ſaw thoſe hell-guides bringing me in, but he ſet the doore as wide open to receiue me, as Weſtminſter Hall is in the terme-time to country Clients, which put me in minde of that odde olde verſe in the Poet,
               Noctes at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   dies pate
                     •
                   atri ianua Ditis.
               I no ſooner was entred into this Infernal Iland (where many men lie winde-bound ſometimes foure or fiue yeeres together) but a fellow (whom at firſt ſight I tooke to bee a Gardiner, becauſe hee had ſomewhat a reddiſh beard and turn'd vp withall) called mee to a booke (no Bible or Diuinity, but rather of Negromancy, for all the Priſoners called it the Blacke-booke) comming to it, hee demanded my name, I tolde him, and then hee ſet it downe as horſes are in Smithfield at the Tole-booth. This ceremonie being ended, hee askt me whether I would go to the Maſterſide, the Knights ward, or any other place of a cheaper rate; I anſwered

the beſt, though it were the deareſt, for I did hope to get my liberty before a weeke was expired: vpon this determination there was one call'd to ſhew me the way to my lodging, who vpon the firſt call made no delay, but inſtantly came wadling downe ſtaires. Hee was aThe deſciption of one of the vnderiaylours. groſſe fellow, one that had a fat body though a leane braine, a face of a ſanguine complection, and an heart correſpondent to the ſame, hee had a motly beard cut round like a rubbing bruſh, ſo that if all the skinne of his body had beene like that of his face, it would haue ſerued excellent well when he had beene dead to make cloakebags of: This lumpe of mans fleſh (that like a fore-man of a Iury could ſpeak nothing ſo well as guilt) conuayed me vp a paire of ſtaires, and ſo to a doore, where another Fury like himſelfe ſate, telling me, that if I meant to haue entrance there, I muſt pay my fees, or elſe I could haue no farther paſſage that way, a ſhilling was his demand, which hee would haue, or elſe I muſt returne the ſame way I came; I (ſeeing nothing but a ſiluer key would open this locke) gaue him his fee, wiſhing the waight of that twelue pence in Aqua fortis or Mercury water in his necke, but hauing ſhot this gulfe, my corpulent conductour brought mee through a little Gallery, which led vs to a ſpacious Roome, and then into a Hall hung round about with the ſtory of the Prodigall childe (a very edifying peece of worke-man-ſhip for the gueſts of that place) being come into this vncouth and ſtrange place, my guide (with a countenance as ſowre as any muſtard-maker in the City) bad mee welcome, and tolde mee that there was a garniſh to be payd: But I that vnderſtood the Hebrew, the Syriake or Caldean language as well as his ſpeech, askt him what that was, hee tolde mee two ſhillings would diſcharge it, I mildely certified him, I was not at that vnhappy preſent ſo well furniſht, beſides I was ignorant whether any ſuch thing were due to him,

or no; at this anſwer hee rouz'd himſelfe vp like an angry maſtiffe, and being in coller, in a curriſh manner barkt out theſe words to me. Sir, if you meane to lie on this ſide, you muſt and ſhall pay mee my fees, or (though you be no Alderman) I will bee ſo bolde as to vncloake you. I ſeeing him ſo reſolute, and my ſelfe Ioath to lie without a bedde, becauſe it was late, put mine arme into my pocket, which was ſo ſoare with the Sargeants griping, that I had much adoe to pull two ſhillings out of it; that being diſcharged, like a baſe violl) he went grumbling vp ſtaires with me, and brought me to my lodging, richly hung with cob-weblawne. So hauing ſhewed me my bed, whereon he clapt a paire of ſheetes, that neuer came nigh Holland by three hundred mile, left mee a peece of candle ſcarce ſo long as his noſe, lockt vp the doore, bidde mee goodnight, went downe gingling his keyes, and left mee to my repoſe.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. II. 1. Mine acquaintance with my fellow-priſoners. 2. Mine entertainment at dinner time the next day. 3. The character of a priſon. 4. The Keepers kindneſſe to me while I had money. 5. Their vnkindneſſe to mee when I had none. 6. Laſtly their transporting me from the Maſterſide to the Knights ward.
               BVt what with change of my lodging, and meditating of mine entertainment, I ſlept not at all, but like a true Male-content, made my brains the minutes to euery clocke I heard, betwixt whoſe ſeuerall ſounds the watch of mine inuention beating vp my panting heart hammered foorth a hundred ſtrange cogitations:

thus lay I longing for day, at whoſe approach, I might deſcerne the manner of my new diſtaſtefull lodging, which lookt ſo confuſed, raſty and ominous, that euery obiect preſented new greefe, and ſtrucke mee into further conſideration of this worſe then wofull purgatory, wherein I lay plunged by the froward will of Fate, dreading the danger I was in, and doubting how long this vnwelcome affliction might continue. In the middeſt of my muſing, my chamber-fellowes awak't, whom I coniectured to bee of the ſame fellowſhip of affliction that I my ſelfe was: I ſaluted them with a Bon-iour, they perceiuing me to be a ſtranger, gratified my good-morrow with a Bien, asking of me whether I came in vpon an arreſt or a command; I anſwered, with a deepe ſigh and ſad voyce, faith Gentle-men I am arreſted to my greefe, God help me, at which words I could ſcarce refraine from teares, which cauſed my kinde chamberfellowes to pitty my preſent ſorrowes, and apply ſome words of comfort to expell them. In the ſame chamber lay an Attourney: who beganne to bee more buſie then the reſt, who perceiuing I was apt to giue eare to any new conceited hope, ſlipt on his blacke ſuit (which was worne bare for want of bruſhing) and comming to my bed ſide, whiſpered in mine eare, and tolde mee if I would riſe he could tell mee ſomething for my good; theſe words poſſeſt each part with more then haſte to heare this vnexpected kindnes, ſo being with ſpeed apparrelled, down the ſtaires poſted I and my Atturney, who taking me by the hand, demanded of me whether I were in vpon action or execution, I anſwered, an action of 100▪ pound, to which he replied he would haue me out preſently, and with an Habeas Corpus remooue my cauſe to the Kings Bench and ſo farewell. I (thinking the dores had beene blowen open already by his breath) ſtood in a maze, conſidering with my ſelfe whether he were mortall or no, yet marking that his crabbed

countenance accorded with his counſell, for which he greedily gaped for ten groates, I began to pauſe with my ſelfe, &amp; askt him what the charge would amount to, he told me for 40. ſhillings he wold vndertake to ſet me free, I told him I would conſider a little of it, &amp; then he ſhould heare my reſolue: &amp; ſo we tranſcended to our former lodging chamber, where we found all our aſſociates vpon their legs, ſome buttoning, ſome truſſing, others taking Tobacco, to expell noiſome ſauors, they all kindly ſaluted me, &amp; ſo from complementing &amp; talking, we fel to drinking (the only remedy to driue away melancholly, and bring ſtrangers acquainted) thus we paſt away the morning while ſeruicetime, which being ſpent in deuotion, the table was couered and vp came our dinner, at which each man ſate downe without reſpecting of perſons, for he that firſt comes is firſt ſeated like thoſe that come to ſee playes; or goe to dinner at an ordinary, but I (being the youngeſt priſoner as their faſhion is) ſat at the vpper end of the table, to which preferment by much entreaty, I was aduanc't, ſhort grace ſerued for ſharp ſtomacks, &amp; ſo to't they fell without circumſtance. But I ſeeing all their teeth laboring ſo hard, thought foule ſhame mine ſhould ſtand idle, began to accompany my quicke ſhauers, but as I was about to put meat into my mouth, one with his mouth halfe full, mumbled out and ill tuned ſpeech of a garniſh, the Vintners boy that waights for ſuch purpoſes, was ready with a pottle of clarret, who filling a boule brimme-full, ſet it on my trencher, and ſo I was entreated to drinke to all the ſociety, and compelled to pay for it when I had done: theſe plagues diued deeper into my pockets then Graueſ-end ſearchers doe into ſhippes, to finde out vncuſtomed commodities. Thus hauing finiſht our feaſt (and waiting for no banquet) we roſe, euery man diſpoſing of himſelfe as he pleaſed, onely my ſelfe guided by the euill Fatewalkt into the

fore-roome, where the fraternity of Keepers and other ſeruants of the houſe were feeding on the fragments that were reſerued from our table, I with a common ſalutation bad much good do them, but when they had emptied their cramd iawes, told me there was a certaine garniſh to bee payd, I now being too well acquainted with that language, tolde them plainely I would pay no more, to which they replied and ſayd, that then I ſhould haue my liberty no more, for all the reſt of my fellow-priſoners had payd it, and except I would bee their imitators and come off roundly, I ſhould bee barred of that priuiledge the reſt of my aſſociates had, I, loath to be pent vp like a Lyon in the Tower, and haue no more liberty then to looke through an iron grate, demanded the ſumme, they told me ſix-pence, to ſend for a quart of clarret wine, which was the laſt teſtor that remained in my peacefull pockets, at laſt, flinging it to them, I walkt vp to my lodging againe, and thereby chance eſpied a ſtandiſh and a ſheet of vndefiled paper, which being fit for my purpoſe, I made bolde with, and in the middeſt of melancholly, writ this character of a priſon.
               It is a Fabricke built of the ſame ſtuffe, the Keepers of it are made of, ſtone and iron: It is an vnwholeſome full-ſtuffed humorous body. which hath an Hole in the poſteriors of it, whence it vents many ſtinking, noyſome and vnſauoury ſmels, which is the onely cauſe there is ſuch a perpetuall ſickneſſe and diſeaſe in it: It is a booke where an honeſt man may learne and read a leſſon of bettering himſelfe, and where a bad man may ſtudy to be ten times worſe: it is a coſtiue creature, that ſurfets almoſt all the yeere long, yet very ſeldome doth purge it ſelfe; and when it doth it leaueth abundance of ill humours behinde; when Epimetheus opened Pandora's box, there did not more miſchiefes and maladies flie out of it into the world, then there is in this curſed

place, for it hath more ſickneſſes predominating in it, then there are in twenty French Hoſpitals, or at the Bathe, in the ſpring or fall of the leafe; It is a Bankrupts banquetting houſe, where he ſits feaſting himſelfe with diſhes borrowed from other mens tables, without any honeſt determination to repay them againe: It is a Prodigals purgatory, and a ſickneſſe that many young Gentle-men, and Citizens ſonnes and heires are incident to be troubled with, at the age of one and twenty or much thereabout, It is a dicing houſe, where much cheating is vſed, for there is little ſquare dealing to be had there, yet a man may haue what baile hee will for his money.
               This being finiſht, I veiwed it ouer, but as I was reading of it, I was called downe to ſpeake with a friend that came to viſit me in my new transformation, and after ſome formall goſſipping diſcourſes, as I am ſorry to ſee you beere, How were you met with all, and what hard hap had you, and ſuch like) lent mee a brace of Angels, the ſight of which two faire creatures, made me couragious, and a companion for the beſt, I then rouz'd▪ my heart vp to a ſtraine of mirth, which caus'd the Gentlemē to delight in my cōpany, the keepers began to wax diligent, I could no ſooner name a bottle of Ale, but it was ready to flie into my face, the Vintners boy was ready at mine elbow, that if I calld but for a quart of ſacke or clarret, would forget his errand by the way, and for his owne profit preſent me with a pottle. In this iouiall vaine I waſted my money and time, neuer deſiring to deale with mine Attourney for my liberty, becauſe I vnderſtood by others, that it was onely a tricke to worme mee out of my money. Many ſuch ſupplies I had to vphold my mirth, but none to diſchage my debts, which began to increaſe, for euery day brought in a new action, till the totall ſumme of my debts had drawen a head, &amp; ioyn'd their forces in the Paper-houſe.
               
               
                  But at the end of the weeke when they vſe to call for their reckoning (which is for diet and lodging) they willingly truſted mee, telling mee there was no ſuch haſte, thus I frolikt out three weeks on the Maſterſide, thinking my credit ſtood built on the firme rocke of their kindneſſe, whereas indeede (as the ſequell ſhall vnfolde) it was ſuncke in the quickeſands of their cruelty. For hauing run my ſelfe into a moneths arrerages, my friends beganne to wax weary of ſupplying my wants, and the keepers (knowing of it) vnwilling to truſt me any farther, thus both my friends and hopes ſhook hands with me, and bad me farewell; to bee briefe, the month being ended, my fat fellow (before mentioned) like a watch-man came with a bill in his hand, to make a priuy ſearch in my purſe, but finding it altogether vnprouided for his purpoſe, returned the bill to the book without any croſſe language, vpon the view of theſe vnſatisfied figures, there aroſe a thunder-clap of conſpiracie againſt mee, for my preſent tranſportation ouer from the Maſterſide to the Knights ward, but I that ſcorned to bee frighted with the firſt flaſh of falſe fire, defended my ſelfe with good words that night, and ſo went to bed, determining with my ſelfe (rather then be offenſiue to them which might more incenſe them againſt me) the next day to goe quietly ouer my ſelfe, and not to diſcredit my ſelfe ſo much, as to bee forced ouer by compulſion; ſo the next morning, as ſoone as I was ready, I tooke my leaue of all my fellowes on that ſide, and inſtantly went ouer, writing theſe few verſes in a little peece of paper, and left them to the peruſing of my kinde Comrades.
               
                  
                  To all my friends that heare this ſingle ſtory,
                  If you to try their kindneſſe haue occaſion,
                  Being poſſeſt i'th' Compters Territory,
                  Whilſt money laſt they'le pleaſe thee with perſwaſion:
                  But being ſpent, they change their firſt euaſion
                  To their owne ſhapes, when they your wealth haue wonne,
                  With you they'le deale, as they with me haue done.
               
               Thus leauing the Maſterſide, I kindely entreat your patience to walke ouer to the Knights ward with mee, and partake of the fruits of my new ſociety, &amp; ſtrange vnexpected entertainment.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. III. 1. Mine entrance into the Knights ward. 2. My rough vſage. 3. The deſcription of a commanding officer in that place. 4. My ſtrange acquaintance with a company of Gentle-men, being all priſoners. 5. The occaſion of this enſuing diſcouery. 6. And laſtly, the entrance into this diſcouery.
               I No ſooner came downe the Maſterſide ſtaires, but a key was turned for me, ſo vp went I into the Knights ſide, but did goe as heauily (howſoeuer I layd a braue and guilded out ſide vpon my heauy and leaden diſcontent) as thoſe poore priſoners that goe vp New-gate ſtaires, after they come condemned from the Seſſions houſe. At firſt I went through a long darke gallery, that repreſented the place it was moſt like, Hell; for it was as gloomy, as if the Rauen-like wings of night did continually couer it, hauing paſt through this Aegyptian fogge, on a ſudden I ſtept into the Hall, where men were walking vp and downe, as thicke as Marchants doe on the Exchange betweene twelue and one in the afternoone, being entered, I began to play my part as well as I could, and thus to ſalute them.
               Gentle men, God ſaue you all, may that you all long for happen vnto you all, Liberty; courteouſly they returned the like to me, and badde me welcome holding me in diſcourſe concerning my forſaking the Maſterſide, but as I was making an Apologeticall defence for

my pouerty, and a true narration of their cruelty that turned me ouer, I was interrupted by a fellow, whoſe character I thus will deſcribe vnto you. Hee was a tall rawboned thing, and might very well at Mid▪ ſummertime, haue ſerued in ſteed of a May-pole, had he been in a coūtry town, for all the hob-nail-wearers in the pariſh to dance about; his face was much like a withered warden, and wrinckled all ouer-like an Apple-Iohn of a yeere olde, he was chapfalne, and lookt like the picture of Famine, the haire that grew vpon his muſſell was ſo blacke, that I thought he had a couple of blacke puddings round about his chaps, beſides all theſe exteriour endowments, his internall vertues were as many, for he was as proud as a new made Conſtable, and would mooue his hat no more to any man that came within his iuriſdiction, then a Lawyer will to a poore client, though he ſtand two houres together bare before him, this compound of ill qualities (I ſay) very roughly came to me, when Heauen knowes I never dream't of ſuch a miſcheefe, and thus accoſted me.
               Sir are you a Priſoner? yea ſir, ſaid I, Fortune and the world haue beene my heauy aduerſaries, who conſpiring together, haue concluded that I muſt lie heere while the Diuine prouidence doth break the Adamantine bond of my dull and Saturnine miſhaps. But ſir, ſayd he, haue you any money? If I haue none (ſayd I) make no doubt but my ſupplies will come in to morrow, and then what is fit to be done, I will ſee ſatisfied: nay (ſaid he) I muſt not be procraſtinated, prorogued or demurred withall, I muſt haue a Garniſh of you, a parcell of eighteene pence, I will not ſpare you if you were my father; I beleeued him, therefore gaue him faire words, deſiring him to bee calmer, and the next money that I was bleſt withall, hee ſhould participate of, at this anſwer hee beganne to looke as ſcuruily on me, as a whore on a conſtable, a begger on a bead
                     ••
                   or

whipping poſt, as a cheater on a Iuſtice; and began to rent out three or foure three-pild, huge Baſiliſco oaths, that would haue torne a Roring-boyes eares in a thouſand ſhatters, telling mee, that the quality of my vſage ſhould bee according to the quantity of my money: which I found true, for when it drew neere bed time, he brought me to a priuy lodging (of indeede a lodging neighbouring nigh the Priuy) for the chamber ſtinkes worſe all the yeere long, then a lakeſ-farmers clothes doth at twelue a clocke at night. But dayes roſiate finger had no ſooner boared out the eyes of night, but I got vp, and beganne in a ſolitary and ſadde manner to mourne and pitty my ſelfe, being more amazed then thoſe that dreamed they ſaw hell, and had felt the tortures thereof, or thoſe that drunke of Circes cups, and felt themſelues turning monſters. Being thus drencht in a boundleſſe ſea of melancholly, for the ſpace of a fortnight or three weekes together, Ireſolued to walke into the yard, to ſee if I could eſpie any of my friends that were in the Maſter-ſide, purpoſing to ſpend the day away in diſcourſe, but I walkt there an houre or more, and ſaw none but ſuch as were as melancholly as my ſelfe, ſo I determined to walke vp againe, but by chance I turned my head aſide, and ſaw the cellar doore ſtanding open, gaping to ſwallow any priſoner that drew neere, ſo hoping to finde ſome of mine olde acquaintance there, I ſtept downe, and being no ſooner deſcended, but I beheld a company of Gentlemen, all priſoners, ſitting at a ſquare table, making themſelues exceeding merry with the muſike the cans made, being as brimfull of beere, at mine heart was of melancholly, or theirs of mirth, ſome hauing the pipes neuer out of their mouthes, who puft more ſmoake out of their noſes, then euer came out of Cole-harbar chimneyes, or any brew-houſe in Saint Katherines: ſome againe ſinging as merrily, as if they had been as free as the mountaine

aire, I ſeeing them in theſe Bacchanaliall rages, faine would haue ſlipt by them, but one that ſat at the vpper end of the table (hauing a Can in one hand and a pipe in the other) deſired me to approach and bee one of their ſociety (proteſting more kindneſſe to me, then a Dutch-man will when he is drunke) ſo proffered mee halfe a can; I tolde him I could not pledge him ſo much, but I would drinke a whole one in conceit; why quoth he, not drinke, Foot, man it is the ſoule of good fellowſhip, the marrow of a Poets Minerua, it makes a man as valiant as Hercules, though he were as cowardly as a French man when he is ſober, beſides I will prooue it neceſſary for a man to be drunke ſometimes, for ſuppoſe you ſhould kill a man when you are drunke, you ſhould neuer be hanged for it while you are ſober, therfore I thinke it is good for you to be alwaies drunk, againe, it is the kindeſt companion and friendlieſt ſin of all the ſeauen, for whereas moſt ſinnes leaue a man (by ſome accident) before his death, this truſty Trojan Drunkenneſſe will neuer forſake him while the breath is out of his body; and laſtly, a full bowle of ſacke or clarret, or a Can of ſtrong beere, will drownd all ſorrowes; indeede ſir, ſayd I, whether it will drownd all ſorrowes or no, I am not greatly experienct in, but I am ſure it will drownd our ſoules, yet ſir, for your kindneſſe I will beſtow the curteſie of the cellar vpon you, and ſo I called for halfe a dozen, and dranke a little to them all; another that was oppoſite againſt mee, askt me if I would drink Tobacco, ſo proffered me the pipe, which I denied, telling him that I would not be conuerſant with that Indian whore, that not onely the Lords and Gentry of the Land had committed adultery with, but alſo euery Tinker, Cobler and Dray-man of the City. Why, ſaid he, it is an excellent purge for the head, true, ſayd I, but it is a vilde purge for the purſe, and that for mine owne part, I had rather haue a peece of

pudding of an inch long for mine owne eating, then twenty yards of pudding Tobacco for my drinking, they ſeeing my fixt and ſollid reſolution, let me alone to haue mine owne humour as they had theirs; ſo that we ſat exceeding merry without any melancholly fit, and at the laſt, I began to giue them a touch of my qualitie, but after we began to bee more familiar together, he that firſt entertained me, whiſpered me in the eare, and tolde mee, if hee thought I would bee ſecret, hee would reueale that to me, which ſhould not onely for euer gaine me a neuer-dying memory, but alſo would be an vnknowen profit to the Common-wealth, I promiſed him to be as ſecret as any Surgeon, then hee called me aſide from the reſt of our company, and tolde me, if I would repaire to him in the morning, he would vnbowell the hugeſt bulke of villany, that euer was burthen ſome to the world, that hee would anatomize vice, and lay the vlcers and ſores of this corrupted age, ſo apparant to the ſight of this Kingdom, that the moſt Oſpray and Owle-eyed ſpectator ſhould not chuſe but confeſſe, there neuer was a more neceſſary and commodious diſcouery reuealed. Why ſir, ſayd I, there is a booke called Greenes Ghoſt haunts Cony-catchers; another called Leger demaine, and The Blacke Dog of Newgate, but the moſt wittieſt, eleganteſt and eloquenteſt Peece (Maſter Dekkers, the true heire of Apollo compoſed) called The Bell-man of London, haue already ſet foorth the vices of the time ſo viuely, that it is vnpoſſible the Anchor of any other mans braine can ſound the ſea of a more deepe and dreadfull miſcheefe. Theſe indeede, ſayd he, haue done (eſpecially the laſt) moſt exquiſitely, both for their owne reputation, and their countreyes good, but I haue that lockt vp in the cloſet of my breſt, that when it is opened and made apparant to you will amaze you. Therefore I admire that the Fabricke of the earth is not continually ſhaken with

earth-quakes, that the Earth it ſelfe (as ſhee is a mother to beare all kinde of fruit) doth not in gender all kinde of murthering and killing creatures, as Harpies, Cockatrices, wolues and Hyenas to deſtroy thoſe that are continually trampling on her teeming wombe; that the aire is not choaked with fogs, and that blacke pitel
                     •
                  y miſts doth not perpetually maſque the face of Heauen, and leaue the world in obſcurity, putting vs in minde of our ſinnes, a thouſand times blacker then that ecclipſe; and laſtly, that the ſea is not turnd all to blood to put vs in minde of the cruelty and vnconſcionable vſage of one man toward another, for there are vices in this ſinne drownd age, that are able to pull the two edged ſword of vengeance on our heads, and plucke fire from the forge of heauen, I admire that we haue not leane-faced Famine, meager mortality, pale ſickneſſe, and grim-faced warre tyrannizing in this Land, as once it did in Ieruſalem, in the time of Titus and Vespaſian▪
                   when the glorious Sanctum Sanctorum was ſet on fire; when the fields were filled with ſlaughtered carkaſſes, and when the mother for want of food, was driuen to kill her owne child, to quench her owne hunger. Hee would haue proceeded farther in his diſcourſe, but that I entreated him to containe himſelfe while the morning, telling him I would rather faile of my liberty, then to meet him to heare this diſcouery, vpon this reſolue we both went to our former ſeats, and fell to our former familiarity, but on a ſudden, the Keepers broke off our mirth, and commanded euery man to his lodging, ſo not daring to diſpleaſe their authority, wee payd the ſhot, in a friendly and kinde manner tooke our leaues one of each other, went vp ſtaires, and euery man to his ſeuerall ward and lodging. But my braines like the wandring ſtars; or clocks on Shroue-Tueſdayes were neuer at quiet, but all night I lay wondring and muſing what diſcouery this ſhould be, therefore

I longed more to ſee the day, then an hungry Courtier will a table groaning vnderneath the waight of well-fill'd diſhes: but the Day-ſtarre no ſooner began to cheriſh the world with his all-reuiuing light, but I ſprung from mine hard couch, made mee ready, and when the dores were open (by much intreaty) got into the yard, where hauing not walked halfe a dozen turns, but I made my repaire into the Cellar, more a thirſt to haue my mindes pallate quencht with his diſcourſe, then my mouth with the beſt liquor in all the barrels, but hauing called for two Cans of beere, I ſent for a quart of ſacke to whet the point of his wit, that it might wound vice the deeper, that being come, I ſent for my friend who lay in the Hole, who was foorth with let out (being an olde priſoner) and being come downe, thus I began to ſalute him.
               Ingenious friend, as well come to me as this faire day is to the world, this night hath ſeemed long, but the burning deſire I had to conferre with you, concerning the diſcouery (you out of your loue promiſed to reueale) made it more tedious, &amp; if you will but diſcloſe the maine body, let me alone to vnmaſque the face, and lay euery member open to the worlds eye. Sir (quoth he) you ſeeme ſo compleat in your quality, that I hope you will publiſh what I ſhall relate, if you ſhould ſmother it, I rather would keepe it to my ſelfe then impart it, but not doubting of your diligence in this matter, I will venture my diſcourſe, and good ſit giue a diligent attention. I (as glad to heare as he to ſpeake) tooke vp a roome in a priuate place, and loth to hold my ſelfe in delayes, firſt of all, ſwept cleane the channell of mine at tention with a cup of ſacke, drunke an health to him, and the liberty of all poore diſtreſſed priſoners that lay labouring vnderneath the burthen of miſery, which being pledg'd in this (or ſuch a) manner, he began.
               As the maine Ocean is nouriſhed by the armes and

riuers, that pay howerly tribute to him with the ſiluer ſtreames, and eſpecially out of our Land, by ſwan-bleſt Thames, ſwift Seuerne, dangerous paſſing Humber, and ſmooth-faced Trent, ſo is this turbulent ſea the Compter by theſe foure eurrents heereafter mentioned: Firſt, Vnconſcionable Citizens: Secondly, Politike Prodigals, alias Ingeneers: Thirdly. Catch-poles: Fourthly and laſtly, Conſtables and their adherents, as the Beadle and his Watch-men, all whoſe abuſes I will ſtrip naked, and ierke with my tongue, till I fetch blood; the firſt of whom haue beene the onely cauſe of my detaining in priſon this foure yeeres, yet let no man thinke that I ſpeake againſt all Citizens. No, as I hope for eternall happineſſe, I reuerence that Worſhipfull, ancient, and fameworthy order, I meane ſuch as maintaine themſelues and their families, I touch not thoſe that care not who looke and pry into their conſciences, becauſe their dealings haue beene ſo ſquare and honeſt: but ſuch as enrich themſelues by fraud, deceipt and ſiniſter meanes, working vpon the infirmity of youth, and greene-witted Gallants, to increaſe their owne ſtore, caring not how much they decreaſe other mens eſtates: ſuch there are in the moſt flouriſhing and religious Commonwealths in the world; In the moſt famous vniuerſities in Chriſtendome there are ſome dunces reſident. that not onely diſgrace themſelues, but alſo their fellow-ſtudents; It is impoſſible, but that in the moſt vertuous Court there will be ſome Paraſites, ſo in the moſt goodly &amp; glorious city vnder Heauens Canopy there are ſome aſpes lurking, that ſting the reputation of their brethren by their poyſonous and corrupt dealings, ſuch as theſe I will portray and limme foorth to you, and firſt of all I will diſcourſe vnto you the extreame abuſe of Gaine-greedy Citizens, and in order will touch the Politike Prodigals, alias Ingeneers, and (I thinke Soule-leſſe
                  
                  Sargeants, and Conſtables and Beadles: but firſt of the firſt.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. IV. Containing 1. The Subtilty of many vnconſcionable CitizensAn vnconſcionable Citizen, the firſt current that paies howerly tribute to the Sea the Compter. that intangle young Gentle-men and lap them into bonds. 2. The craft and cunning of their Confederates (Gentle-men-like Broakers) by whoſe wicked and vnchriſtian like dealing, many elder brothers and braue Gentle-men are vndone.
               I Haue read that Italian Mountebanckes, before they ſpeak in their drug-tongue &amp; Fuſtian language to the auditory of innocent and ignorant people, furniſh out the play, where they ſing their owne Encomians, with viols, painted boxes, and bils of all the famous cures they pretend to haue done in many forraine parts of Chriſtendome, which baſe and vſuall iugglings are onely to enrich themſelues, and defraud the generall rout that flocke about them. Many Mountebancke-Citizens haue we in this moſt ſumptuous (but moſt ſubtill and ſinnefull) City of London, that when they would rauiſh the minde, and take the intuitiue ſence of many profuſe Prodigals, and melting Heires with their Syren-like ſeducings lay open their wares, as ſatten, veluets, gold and ſiluer lace, or any other braided commodities (or rather indeede diſcommodities) which though they ſhew rich, yet are out of faſhion or not ſaleable, theſe are ſpringes to catch young Countrey Woodcockes, or our City Dottrels, that had rather bee out of the world then out of the faſhion, who will bee braue for the preſent time, though their gallantry coſt them all their future fortunes, who with more feruency▪
                  
and proteſtation wooe the Citizen for his traſh and trumpery, then many decayed Knights will rich widdowes to inherit their poſſeſſions; but our tradeſman perceiuing their forwardneſſe and follies, playes the rope-maker and will bee extreame backeward, and will not be brought to truſt them with any of his Bartholomew faire-ſtuffe vpon any condition; bonds hee refuſeth, recognizances he diſdaineth, iudgements hee will not heare off, ſtatutes he ſcorneth, &amp; tels them in a Puritanicall faſhion, that he had rather truſt a Gentle-man on his word, then his bond or oath. For (ſaith he) they that will not haue a care to keepe their words, will not ſticke to haue ſo large a conſcience as to breake their day, and ſlight the payment of their bonds, againe, he tels them the danger he is in of leeſing of his debt: for (ſaith hee) when the bonds come to be due, and payday at hand, may not they ſtraight flie ouer into the Low-countreyes, or take Sanctuary in Milford lane, Duke Humphreyes Ordinary, or get a Protection Royall from the King, and ſo defraud me of my debt, and many ſuch collops as theſe haue beene cut from the body of mine eſtate ſince I haue beene a Tradeſman. Therfore good Gentle-men (ſaith he) I cannot dare truſt any longer, for my kindneſſe hath bred mine owne calamity, then ſet vp your reſolutions and trouble me no more, for I haue giuen you your anſwer.
               Thus are my young nouices ſtrucke to the heart at the firſt venny, and dares come no more for feare of as ſharpe a repulſe.
               Alas, alas, this is but to grinde the blunt apperite of my commodity taker into a ſharper edge, and make them more greedy of their owne ruines, imitating the cunning and deceit of pretty, but petulant and cloſe Curtezans, that are nice when a ſicke-brain'd yoong Gallant importunes them vpon any kindneſſe, onely to make him more fierce vpon his owne confuſion,

holding him off, like a Fencer, at diſtance a moueth or two, becauſe he ſhall come vp the roundlier to her purpoſe: but to the matter.
               But ſome or one of my young Gallants that neuer giues ouer plodding with himſelfe how hee might get into the bookes of ſome Gold-ſmith, Habberdaſher, Silkman, Woollen or Linnen-draper, hath ſome Broker or other comming earely in a morning and certifies him, that if it pleaſed him, he ſhould haue a commodity that lay ready to bee carried away, if hee would enter into bond for it, nominating the ſame man that gaue him the former repulſe. My young heire (whoſe hart knocks againſt his ribs for ioy) kindely bids the Broaker wellcome, ſends for a cup of wine, and drinkes to him with all his heart, reſoluing to entertaine his proffer vpon any condition, proteſting rather then he will let ſuch a bleſt opportunity ſlip, will ſet his hands to more parchment then a whole flocke of ſheepe are able to furniſh a Scriuener with; but my Broaker (before inſtructed by the commodity-letter) tels him that though he heard him ſpeake ſomething doubtfull of him, yet if he would be ruled by him, hee would vndertake to make his credit paſſe as firme as any Farmers or Yeomen in Kent, for (ſaith hee) I am a great friend of this Tradeſmans, and make no doubt but may preuaile as much with him as any man in this Towne, eſpecially if you will bee ruled by me, you muſt not be too importunate, but as ſcornfull as he is diſdainefull, tell him that you are your fathers heire, and that ſuch lands he hath you muſt inherit, and that the entailement cannot be cut off, though he were neuer ſo hainous an enemie of yours, beſides you muſt tell him you are about to marry ſome rich widdow which you know you might win, ſo that you could but haue a hundred pound or two, to put your ſelfe in good cloathes.
               Theſe spels charmes my poore Prodigall, ſo at laſt he

and the Woolfe (that came as Legate from the Tyger) go together, and finde my Citizen buſie in his ſhop, not taking any notice of their comming, but (as to other paſſingers) at firſt askes them what they lack, and what they would buy, but boldly they come into the ſhoppe and after acquaintance taken, the Broaker vnfoldes the matter, and the occaſion of their comming to him, telling him that he came with a friend of his about a commodity, and if hee were a friend, as hee alwaies tooke him to bee, as to condeſcend to the Gentle mans requeſt, and let him haue an hundred pound: for (ſaith he) I know his friends are of faire poſſeſſions, he is his fathers eldeſt ſon, beſides on my conſcience he would not trouble you at this preſent, if he were not to marry with a rich widdow, whom he may loſe for want of ſetting forth, and then no doubt when the match is made vp, but he will haue an honeſt care to pay in your money▪ with a million of thankes for your kindneſſe. Now all the while the Broaker is pleading, mine Innocent doth ſecond him, and will rather then goe without his trinkets, binde whatſoeuer the Broaker ſaith with halfe a ſcore oathes.
               The Citizen begin to hearken after this, and proteſts to my greene goſling, that he would be glad to do any man a pleaſure, but that he hath had ſo many loſſes alreadie, and that he would bee willing to let him haue an hundred pounds worth of commodities, if ſo be he thought it would redound to his good, and that hee might bee ſure at the ſixe moneths end to haue his money paid in, the young Gallant proteſts, the Broaker warrants it, and at laſt, though very loah, the Citizen condeſcends, but how, thus, that if hee could procure as good a man as himſelfe to be bound with him, he ſhould haue what ware he could deſire, for, ſaith he, mans life is fraile and brittle, and you may die a fortnight or a weeke hence, for ought that I know, nay, to

morrow, or ſoone at night, and then where is nine hundred pound, therefore, good Sir, looke out ſome of your moſt eſpeciall and indeered friends, and get one of them to be bound with you, and you ſhall haue the wares at a quarter of an houres warning. The tide now is turn'd, and Signior Unthrift put to his non-plus, and at laſt fals to intreat Maſter Broaker to bee the man, who for two or three daies together, will by no meanes or perſwaſions bee won to enter into bond with him, except hee muſt ſhare halfe. Is not this extreame and almoſt incredible villany? and moſt vnconſcionable dealings, thus to ſnare in the Gentry of the land, and ruine his fortunes but newly in the ſpring, knowing that he will rather let him haue three quarters of the Commodity then goe without it, becauſe, as many others do, hee would goe gallant, haue money in his purſe, and keepe company with ſatten and veluet out-ſides.
               But ſuppoſe the commodities are deliuered, after they haue both ſealed the bonds (you muſt ſuppoſe the Heire alwaies to bee the principall) how muſt theſe Hobby horſes, Reames of browne paper, Iewes-trumps and Bables, Babies and Rattles be ſolde, the Gentle-man is aſhamed to proffer them to ſale himſelfe, no, he truſts the other that ſhares halfe with him, to put them off▪ who muſt be hired to ſell them, and perhaps when they are all ſolde out right, will haue to his owne ſhare three quarters of them, are not theſe dealings worthy of the the ſharpeſt rodde Iuſtice euer did holde in her righteous hands, they are and haue beene ſoundly laſht, and ſeuerely puniſht, by that moſt noble, graue, wiſe and prouident Stateſ-man, the Right Honourable the Lord high Chancellor of England, yet for all this there will ſuch falſe play be acted, though the Sword of Iuſtice continually were hanging ouer their heads: but I will returne to our former ſubiect, let vs now ſuppoſe my young Gallant reuelling in a Tauerne or Ordinary:

you may bee ſure the Broaker is triumphing, that hee pluckt the feathers of this young gull, and meanes ere long to leaue him as bare of meanes as he is of braines. Now my vſurious Citizen dreames of nothing but his day, which he hopes my nouice will breake, which is no ſooner expired, but inſtantly, by ſome ſtratagem or other, gets him within the liberty, then inuites him to ſupper (by giuing him faire words) either to his owne or ſome of his neighbours houſes, and when they haue almoſt made an end, inſteed of a meſſe of fruit, or a peece of Banbury cheeſe to cloſe vp their ſtomackes, a Brace (or more) of Sargeants are not farre from his ſhoulder, and except he preſently pay▪ he muſt preſently to priſon. Are theſe worthy the names of Citizens? no, no, ſuch may be Citizens of London, but neuer of Heauenly Ieruſalem. At this period I began to ſpeake to him, ſaying: Sir, I proteſt you haue reuealed a ſtrange and monſtrous abuſe to the Gentry of this land, if I did not take you to bee (what I thinke you are) an honeſt man, I ſhould ſtand in a great doubt, whether your diſcourſe did taſte of truth or no: but good Sir proceede. Sir, as I hope for ſaluation, ſayd he, (an oath not for a Chriſtian to dally with) I relate no vntruth, but what is as nigh a kin to truth as I am to miſery, for what I haue ſpoken, I finde by mine owne wofull experience to be true, and what hath beene practiſed on my ſelfe by theſe City-Cormorants, theſe trickes haue beene put on me, and for which I haue ſuffered a long impriſonment, and yet they will haue no compaſſion on mee, but rather ſee mee ſtarue then releeue mee, and either haue my carkaſſe or their coyne, yet their conſciences know, what I had from them was nothing but rotten, baſe &amp; moth▪eaten commodities, an hundred pounds worth, of which (according to their rate) I neuer made fifty of, yet they ſticke not to demand an hundred of me, beſide the intereſt and all their charges.
               
                  Againe, marke the policy they haue to keep a poore priſoner in fetters of aduerſity: if they ſuppoſe the priſoner goeth about to ſue out an Audita querela, foorthwith they either put their debt ouer to ſome Alderman, or elſe agree with ſome Officer in the Exchequer, and ſo put their debt ouer to the king, faining they owe him ſo much money, knowing that the Cauncery wil not, or cannot allow any thing, in ſuch a caſe as this, to proceed againſt his Maieſty. This is a ſpeeding tricke, and ſuch a one I am now trounc't with, and many beſides my ſelfe.
               I haue read when Iewes haue bought a red hair'd boy, at firſt they will cloath him in ſilkes and taffaties, rauiſh him with all delights that can bee thought on, neuer haue muſique from his eares or banquets from his taſte, and thus vſe him vntill ſuch time they know he is plump, fat and fit for their purpoſe; but when the poore Chriſtian leaſt thinkes of his imminent ruine, he is taken by a brace of ſlaues, and tied vp by the heels, ſo by degrees beaten to death with cudgels, hauing Mummie made of his braines: Such as theſe are vnconſcionable Citizens, that at firſt will cloath our young Prodigals in ſilkes and veluets, golde and ſiluer lace, inuite him home to dinner, vſe him very courteouſly, but whē his bonds are due, &amp; that he leſt dreams of his misfortunes, a couple or two of Sargeants are ſet vpon him, and hurry him to the Compter, where perhaps he ſhall lie two▪ three, foure or fiue yeere, nay a dozen or twenty yeeres together before hee can get himſelfe releaſed, or if hee chance to preuaile ſo much with his creditors, as to enfranchize him, it muſt be vpon ſome vnreaſonable, vnconſcionable condition, as to giue him fiue hundred pound for an hundred at the death of his father. Vulcan fell from Heauen into the Ile of Lemnos, and by that fall loſt the vſe of one of his feete, let all ſuch vnconſcionable Citizens take heede they fall

not from the earth to Hell, and loſe their ſoules.
               Theſe are the Boares that plow vp whole acres, nay whole fields of Gentlemens lands with their ſnoutes, theſe are ſwine that eate vp whole Orchards, and theſe are they whoſe fiery conſciences drinke vp whole fiſhpooles at a drought; their vſurious dealings make ſo many Cornutos in the City as there are, for when young Gentlemen haue beene beggered by their extortion they haue no other meanes then to fall in with their wiues and ſeek to them for ſupply: It is this that makes Newmarket heath, and Royſton-dounes about Chriſtmaſ time ſo full of high-way men that poore Countrie people cannot paſſe quietly to their Cottages, but ſome Gentleman will borrow all the mony they haue (only indeed they will make them take their bonds) this makes Tiburne and Wapping haue ſo many hangers-on, and this is the cauſe ſo many ſuch Citizens ſonnes are plagued after their fathers deaths as their fathers when they were liuing haue plagued others, for moſt commonly ſome knaue or deboſht fellow lurch the fooles their ſons as cunningly after their fathers diſceaſe as they did others only to make their ſonnes Gentlemen, who at laſt may as miſerably die in the Hole for want of ſuſtenance as ſome of his fathers debtors haue done before him.
               Vpon this I began to interrupt him ſaying, ſir in this ſhort time that I haue beene here I haue ſeen ſome Creditors bring their Debtors both meat, drinke, and mony when they haue beene ſicke, and ill at eaſe.
               Tis true ſir ſaid he, I acknowledge it, but did you neuer heare that when a Lion hath got a pretty bleating lambe or kid in his pawes hee will play and tumble vp and downe with them a little while, but you muſt not thinke it is for any loue hee beares them, but onely to chafe their blood and make them eate more ſweete, and tender: Such are theſe kinde of vnkinde Citizens

that when they haue got young Gentlemen into priſon will (if the ſumme be any thing weighty) relieue him with meate, drinke, and mony, (if they ſee him begin to droope) but do you thinke this is in loue to him? no, if you doe you wander a thouſand leagues from a true conſtruction, hee doth it to keepe him aliue that hee may haue his mony if any meanes ſhould fall to him, and that the world may take notice of his charitie, alas, alas this is but a fained holineſſe, which is a double iniquity: This kindneſſe is but like Alchimy, or Saint Martins rings that are faire to the eye, and haue a rich outſide, but if a man ſhould breake them a ſunder, and looke into them, they are nothing but braſſe, and copper. The Apples of Gomorrha haue glorious rinds but infectious cores.
               It is an extreame miſery for a Priſoner to be indebted to a rich man, or a very poore man; for the firſt (moſt commonly) will haue all or none, for if his debtour chance to die, the loſſe he may well ſpare, but if it is his fortune to liue, and pay him it addes to his eſtate, the other (that is) the poore man will haue no pitty becauſe it may be the debt is all he is worth.
               Thus doe many Gentlemen periſh vnder the hands of cruell Creditours, nay a father that hath brought vp his childe with care and paine, griefe and heart breaking, and thinkes to leaue him ſuch faire poſſeſſions after his deceaſe, that he may liue in his Countrey like a Gentleman (as his aunceſtors haue done before him) either in his life time doth ſee his ſonne lie rotting in priſon, or is not able to ſhew his face out of his fathers gates, or after his deceaſe, his brothers, ſiſters, friends and kinsfolkes ſee his lands extended on, his woods felled downe before his face, thoſe legacies and portions he ſhould pay to his brothers and ſiſters, paide away to ſatisfie his debts (being baſe commodities) and ſo beggers a whole worſhipfull Family, who before that

curſed time had liued a hundred yeares or more in grace and fauour in his Country. Alas, alas, with that the teares fell from his eyes, and hee could ſpeake no more for weeping, yet I deſired him to proceed, but he crau'd my pardon, and tould me that he was at the fartheſt end of that diſcourſe, and thus (quoth he) haue I ſhewed you the nature, property, and quality of this maine arme that hourely paies tribute to the Ocean the Compter, now will I go to the ſecond arme which is concerning Gentlemen-Cheaters.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. V. 1. The true nature and quality of many of our moderneSpent-Callants the ſecond current. ſpent-Gallants. 2. Their tricks to fetch in young Heires to ſet their hands to bonds. 3. And a true narration of their vitious, and lewd courſe of life.
               HOw can thoſe Tyrants flouriſh in their kingdomes, when the foundation of their raigne is built on the Sepulchers of the right and lawfull Heire they haue murthered? And how can thoſe men proſper whoſe raiſings are reared vpon other mens ruines? Many ſuch there are in theſe moſt ſinfull daies who being gulled themſelues when they were ignorant-ſots by knaues, turne knaues themſelues, and ſtudy to cheate, defeate, and coſen young Heires. Is not this a ſtrange Metamorphoſis? It is better to bee a poore foole then a rich Knaue. Many of theſe vnluckie, and ominous Starres wagge, and wander perpetually raigning in the Spheare of this City, that hunt after young Heires as greedily as the Diuell doth after Vſurers ſoules when they be vpon their death beds, for

theſe like Pyrats or Bandites liue onely vpon the ſpoile.
               Theſe Souldiers hauing beene beaten to the world (or indeed beaten by the world) beginne to ſummon vp their ſences, and call their idle braines to a ſtrickt reckoning how to get that vp againe their riot and follies haue ſpent, and thinking there is no way to recouer themſelues but by that they haue ruined themſelues, caſt about-them and beginne to fiſh after this order.
               They prepare their lines, prouide their baites, make ready their hookes which ſhall haue ſuch conſtant and firme batbs, that after they haue ſtrucke a gudgeon in the gills ſhall bee ſure to hold him though they ſuffer him to play a little in the ſtreame: when they haue all theſe things in readineſſe they ſeeke into diuers floods, as the Temple, Inns of Court, Citizens-houſes, as wealthy Marchants, and gold Smiths pry into Ordinaries, and inquire if there be any in that place worthy abaite, if theſe faile then they repaire into Pauls-Church, to Playhouſes, Cockpits, Brothells, and Tauernes, and leaue no place vnſearcht, but like the Aire viſit all parts rather then they will go without their prey, and if they haue found any that is agreeable to their minds, or that they thinke may eaſily bee wrought vpon, in this faſhion they vſe him.
               Like his ſhaddow they will neuer be from his heeles, but dogge him into what place soeuer hee goes, eſpecially if he bee a young country-Gentleman whom his father hath ſent vp to the City to ſee faſhions, and rather then he ſhall go out of towne as raw as he came in they will ſeaſon him, and giue him a little of the City poudring: They will firſt ſeeke what meanes his father doth allow him, then of what nature he is, either merry or melancholly, milde or dogged, and according to the garbe and faſhion he is of, beare themſelues toward him: He ſhall not go into a Tauerne, Ordinarie (or

almoſt any friends houſe) but they will be as nigh his body as his ſinnes are his ſoule, and by ſome ſiniſter way, ſement, and glue themſelues into his familiaritie whatſoeuer it coſt them. This being brought to perfection and themſelues growne ſomething familiar (as in much company keeping a man ſhall ioyne himſelfe to much ſociety) they neuer will bee from his elbow but ſeem to be his boſome friend, his maſculine ſweete heart, and that like Hypocrates Twinnes they muſt liue and die together.
               The golden-leaued marigold neuer opens her leaues while the ſun doth riſe, and neuer cloſeth her ſelfe while he doth ſet; ſo theſe politicke Prodigalls, neuer will be ſtirring while my Heire is riſing, and neuer ſleepe while they ſee him inclining that way: becauſe they would be ſure to haue him in their ſight. But hauing by much induſtry and ſweat apted and fitted him to their humor and purpoſe, and wrought him to ſuch a ſoft and waxen temperature (that they may caſt him into what mould they liſt) bring him to their Rendeuous (an Ordinary) where this decaied Knight ſalutes him, that poore Eſquire doth embrace him, the other beggerly Gentleman kindly entertaines him, and all their ſeruants vaile bonnet to him, none vſe him diſcurteouſly but all moſt louingly, they will haue him to play-houſes, inuite him to a Tauerne to ſupper, and as yet let him not pay a penny, what company ſoeuer he comes in: and if hee chance to borrow forty or fifty ſhillings of them (nay three or foure pound) they will not aske a penny, yet all this while hee runnes but on that vnconſcionable ſcore, which they will make him diſcharge to the laſt farthing before they leaue him.
               This young innocent (ſcarce hauing ſented the Citty aire) all this while thinkes himſelfe in a heauen vpon earth, that he is in Eliſium and ſees more delights then the Turkes Paradiſe affords, thinkes himſelfe much

graced (as to be ſo much beholding to them) as to be entertained among Gallants, that were wrapt vp in ſatten ſuites, cloakes lined with veluet, that ſcorned to weare any other then Beauer hats, and gold bands, rich ſwords and ſcarfes, ſilke ſtockings and gold fring'd garters, or ruſſet bootes and gilt ſpurres, and ſo compleate cape ape that he almoſt dares take his corporall oath the worſt of them is worth (at leaſt) a thouſand a yeere, when Heauen knowes the beſt of them all for a month nay ſometimes a yeere together haue their pockets worſe furniſhed then Chandelors boxes that haue nothing but two-pences, pence, halfepence, and leaden tokens in them, yet he ſtill is confidently perſwaded the Country he was borne in yeelds not ſuch a man as the worſt he hath aſſociated himſelfe with.
               Alas, alas, I truly pittie them, and would as truly relieue them if it lay within my poore power, but when youth is in the height and full vigor of their deſires, neither wholeſome councell, or lamentable examples can giue them ſufficient warning of their future falls. But they hurt themſelues not mee. Why ſir (ſaid I) this diſcourſe tends not to a young Gentlemans hurt, but (as I ſuppoſe) rather to his good.
               Sir ſaid he, you as much erre from the true conceiuing of this buſines as my young Gentleman from a true courſe of life. This is but the Praeludium or Prologue to the play that is to come after, for my Country-nouice being honnied with theſe ſweete and Nectar delights (that theſe falſe brethren ſerue him with) thinks that all the kindneſſe he can returne them is not able to giue them a true and due ſatisfaction, and if at any time theſe practitioners perceiue my freſh-Gallant to droop or languiſh, with theſe (or the like) ſpeeches (which are as wholeſome as a Whore in the Dog-daies) will ſtriue to ſhake off his mellancholly: Why how now my noble ſpirit, what is it that lies within the reach of

our abilities that we can ſupply you with? Speake, you ſhall not want it; it may be you mourne becauſe you are not ſo well accoutred as thoſe you keepe Company with, come our Taylor ſhall furniſh you, we will haue you ſtrip of this Deuonſhire-kerſie ſuite, and put on ſatten, you ſhall caſt off this courſe cloath-cloake, and be furniſh't with one lined with veluet, your foureſhilings dutch felt ſhall be conuerted to a three pound Beuer, your wooſted ſtockings and neatſleather-ſhooes to ruſſet boots and guilt ſpurres: then courage man, is it not better to liue in the City among a braue ſociety of Gallants, then in the Countrey with a heard of gulls? what man is ſo ſtupid and blockiſh as to drinke the running ſtreames when he may quaffe Greek-wines? who will feede on courſe cates when he may hourely taſt of delicates? who will weare poore ſerg D'bois when he may go in ſattens? and who will liue in a ſmoakie Countrycottage, when he may lead his life in a braue Ordinary in the City? You are your Fathers Heire, therefore lay it on while you may, if it ſhould bee your fortune to bee clapt vp, doe you thinke your friends will ſee their only ſonne and Heire (the ſole hopes of their houſe) periſh in a priſon? no, therefore play the Lyon and rouſe your ſelfe vp, and be not ſo Lamblike and ſtill, but freely vnfold your thoughts to vs, and as wee are Gentlemen and your ſworne friends wee will indeuour with our vtmoſt ſtrength and abilitie to redreſſe you, or in any other faſhion to pleaſure you.
               This draught of poyſon (adminiſtred to him in a golden boule) ſwells his heart vp with ſuch hopes that he is ready to burſt, he refuſeth not their proffer'd kindneſſe but takes them as willingly as they trecherouſly meant them, and thinkes that a rich ſuite will immortaliſe him. But yet theſe cloathes are but like the ſhirt Deianira ſent to Hercules which being poiſoned with a Centaures blood wrought his death▪ ſo theſe rich trappings

in ſhort time after either coſt foure or fiue yeeres impriſonment (if his friends are not the more affectionate to him) or pay foure or fiue hundred pound or more to ranſome him out, for after he is thus inueſted it may be he reuells it vp and downe the City with his familiars, drinkes, domineers, and declares in euery company hee comes in how much he is beholding to ſuch Gentlemen, and hauing his braines throughly warmed with wine vowes to doe them any kindneſſe that lies in his power, but marke the ſequell. At laſt as a whole Congregation of theſe Caterpillers (that eate vp ſome of the chiefeſt fruit that growe in the Garden of this Common-wealth) are carrouſing healths to ſome Strumpet or other, there muſt enter (hauing his Cue giuen him) a Scriuener with a bond of fiue or ſix hundred pound ready made for one of theſe Gallants my prodigall doth moſt of all doate on, telling him if he can procure ſome Gentleman either of preſent meanes or future hopes to be bound with him hee might inſtantly vpon the ſealing of the bonds haue ſo much mony he lately ſpake for laide downe to him; my Polititian being in a counterfeit maze, at firſt beginnes to fret, fume, and ſweare, ſaying that his credit was neuer before this time ſo ſlighted as not vpon his owne bond to be truſted for ſo ſmall a matter, then he beginnes to trie his conſorts about him deſiring them to ſtand bound with him, they tell him plainely they will not enter into bonds for their brother, but if hee had neede of a hundred or ſix ſcore pound they would make it vp among them &amp; lend him Pox▪ of it (ſaith he) I am to purchaſe ſuch a Lordſhip of ſuch a Knight and two or three hundred pound will not ſerue my turne, for I haue ſome two thouſand pound ready and if I had this full ſumme the Lordſhippe were mine own; which if I ſhould miſſe I might leeſe three or foure hundred pound which eaſily I may get if I were furniſhed; beſides

if I could ſtay while next Terme I ſhould haue a thouſand pound paide to mee vpon a bond, and then I could eaſily cancel this. At this Simon Sandbox the Scriuener is about to depart, and Signior Shift, chafes, frets, and is ready to teare his haire for grief that he cannot be furniſhed: At laſt hee comes to Corkebraine my Country-nouice deſiring him to ſtand his friend; and ſtand bound with him for that ſumme of money, and that he ſhould ſtand only for a Cipher, and that hee rather would leeſe all his Lands (you may beleeue him) then preiudice him in the leaſt thing the world might taxe him with, Now my young Gallant (that neuer before this time was lapped vp in Lambskinne, and would rather ſet his hand to his owne vndoing then diſpleaſe him) takes it as a kindneſſe that he would intreate him to do him ſuch a curteſie, ſo without any reading ouer the bond (to ſee how the condition runnes) ſeales and deliuers it to Signior Security the Scriuener, neuer dreaming that he is put principall, or of the after-claps that will fall heauy on him about ſixe months after, or that this bond he ſeald to, was for ſome baſe commodities to furniſh his ſuppoſed friend, or laſtly, that it is ſome old debt, that now hee hath ſhifted from himſelfe and laide on the Nouices backe, but ſtill holds him as deare to him as his life blood is to his heart, and ſtill they will reuell together when all this while my Coſen neuer lookes into the enſuing danger becauſe he neuer conſiders of the day or what the penaltie of forfeiting a bond is; ſo to be ſhort, when the time is expired (that the mony ſhould be paide in) the Scriuener and the Cheat plot to arreſt him knowing him the beſt able to pay, and on a ſudden, when they haue him within the Citty with the help of halfe a dozen Puttocks belonging to one of the Compters lay their clawes on him, and ſeldome ſtay (except he bee able to diſcharge the debt) while they haue incarcerated him.
               
                  Thus is this poore Gentlemans fortunes (by his own kindnes and this villaines policie) vtterly ouerthrowne, who neuer comes at him, ſends to him, nay or ſo much as once thinkes on him. Many of theſe moſt deteſtable and diſhoneſt trickes haue I known practiſed on young Gentlemen newly come to the Temple, Inns of Court, and other places that now my heart bleeds to think on. Sir, ſaid I, I haue heard much of thoſe that lie in priuiledged places being in debt daring not ſhew themſelus, but I neuer heard they practiſed ſuch abuſes.
               Sir, ſaid he, if what I ſpeake taſt of vntruth may I neuer inherit eternall happineſſe, what good would it do
                     •
                   mee to wrong them and do my ſelfe no good onely to hold you in a diſcourſe? yet theſe are not halfe the vices that are daily practiſed among them, for let a Gentleman come into their companie you ſhall heare ſome curſing and damning for mony they haue loſt either at cards or dice, others chafing and ſwearing they haue loſt twentie pound when their conſcience knowes they haue wonne as much more, others ſtabbing one another about ſome triuiall word paſſing betweene them, ſo that there will bee ſuch a confuſed Babylonian language of blaſphemy among them that none (but their truchman the Diuell) can interpret it, and when they haue loſt that in a quarter of an houre at cards, dice, tables, or bowles they haue borrowed of ſome rawfreſhman (that lately was admitted into their worſe then leſuiticall Colledge) what will they doe? but ſtart out ſome this way and the reſt another, ſome betake themſelues to their geldings, piſtols, and a good ſword, and not ſticke to bidde a Traueller good morrow, and for that curteſie lighten him of his purſe becauſe he might ride the eaſier, and then returne home againe.
               Others lie in their beds muſing (hauing their Tutor the Deuill not farre from them) where they may finde

out ſome eaſie Gull of whom they muſt borrow ſome mony for a day or two, but whatſoeuer they borrow for one houre is borrowed for one age, for though they binde it with a thouſand Dam-mees (that they will repay it againe within the ſpace of a weeke) you may as well neuer beſtow lippe-labour to demand your mony for you ſhall be ſure neuer to haue it againe.
               Others lie penning baudy letters to Citizens-wiues, inticing them to let them haue mony or wares, but if they will not be inſtructed by their diueliſh doctrine (as to deceiue their husbands to ſupply their wants) what will they doe? but raiſe cauſeleſſe ſcandalls and imputations againſt them and ſo contrary to the will of God go about to part man and wife. Theſe are they that care for no body but themſelues, nay not themſelues, for if they did they would not ſo often hazard their liues in the field vpon the refuſall of ſome drunken health, or in ſpeaking againſt ſome painted, proſtituted Curteſan, and he that kills the moſt men is accounted the braueſt man.
               Theſe are they that like Owles dares not ſhew their faces into the Citty in the day time, but as the Dogges of Aegypt when they come to drinke of the ſtreame of Nilus lappe here and there and dare not ſtay long in one place for feare the Crocodiles (that lie lurking within the bankes) ſhould pull them into the current: ſo theſe, when they chance to skulke out of their dennes to ſome Tauerne to be merry, dare not ſtay long there, but ſtraight ſhift to an other for feare ſome Sergeants that lay watching about the ſtalls ſhould faſten on them and pull them into one of the Compters.
               Theſe are they that go braue by running in debt and neuer care how to pay ſo they haue it: I once read a pretty tale of a Popiniay that againſt the time he ſhould appeare before the Eagle (who had ſummoned all the birds to come before him) borrowed of euery one of

his acquaintance a feather, the Peacocke lent him one of his plumes brauely ſhining with variety of cullors, the Parrot lent him one of his greene fethers, the goldfinch one of his yellow, ſo that as ſoone as he was dreſt and had preſented himſelfe before the Royall and princely Bird, and diſmiſt, he flew vp and downe the woods ſo proudly that euery inferiour Bird) as the Titmouſe, the Hedgſparrow, and Wren) began to adore him: At laſt theſe birds that he had been ſo much beholding to, came to challenge their fethers of him, and (though very loath) he was conſtrained to render them back againe, that when he was bare and naked he lookt ten times worſe then thoſe poore birds that lately did admire him. Such Popiniayes are theſe that borrow of euery Citizen to make them ſhew glorious in the worlds eye, but when the Goldſmiths, Marchants, Silkemen, and Haberdaſhers come to claime their own and get it, they will ſeeme ten times more foule then lately they did faire and glorious. Theſe are the inſtrumentall cauſes that many fathers diſinherit their right Meires (and put in their ſecond ſonnes) who at laſt are forced to marry ſome whore for want of meanes, or flie into the Lowcontries and for halfe a crowne a weeke ſerue in ſome Garriſon towne, for if they are caught (being by their meanes runne into debt) they will be clapt into priſon, and there lie and rot, where in proceſſe of time (when theſe cheating Gallants grow old and their trickes faile) may lie themſelues and fatten a priſon, and end their daies in the Hole, in pouerty, famine, and extreame wretchedneſſe. Thus haue I deſcribed to you the nature of the ſecond arme that continually runnes to the maine Ocean the Compter, now will I haſt to the third which is
               Villanous Sergeants.
            
            
               
               
                  CHAP. VI. Containing 1. The condition of Sergeants. 2. Their nature,The third current, Macemongers. and property. 3. A Paradox in praiſe of them. 4. Their abuſes, their trickes and ſleights in arreſting of men. 5. In what garbe, and faſhion they often-times apparell themſelues, and laſtly their vnſufferable extorting from his Maieſties ſubjects, and their crueltie toward them.
               IN heauen there are many times ingendred Meteors, Exhalations, and fiery Comets: In many Countries there are many Monſters, as in Ruſſia rugged beares, in Germany tusked-Boares, in Clenoma taileſtrong Lyons, in Ireland cruell blood-ſucking backbiting ſixfooted Creepers: but the moſt rauening and cruell Monſters in our Land are the ſhoulder clapping purſebiting mace-bearers. A neceſſarie euill and plaguſorein the body of an infected City, and a diſeaſe that the moſt of the Gentry is ſicke of. For as in the moſt medicinable phiſicke there is moſt infectious poyſon (which elſe would not bee forcible or haue any vertue) ſo in the moſt peacefull, and populous Commonwealth there muſt be ſuch neceſſarie inſtruments or elſe it would not long continue: theſe are they that ſtrike with the axe of Law and luſtice deeper cuts then they haue authority for, ſo that ſometimes they murther a whole family at a blow, and haue no more mercy when they ſtrike then a Spaniſh-army when they are vpon the execution or ſlaughter of their enemy. Yet thus much I will ſay for them when a Gentlemans fortunes begin to be ſicke and craſie, moſt commonly they will apply him with caudles and cordials which only haue

but this fault they taſt ſome thing too much of the Mace, a ſpice more familiar in England then in the Eaſt-Indies: for the moſt baſe ſort of people in the Land are neuer without it in their pockets. But now I thinke on it I will not be inuectiue againſt them becauſe no ſubiect plaies his part to the life ſo well as theſe do, then what kinde of vocation is more neceſſarie in a Commonwealth? I hold them very religious men, for they will continually watch and pray, watch a whole day together to catch young Gentlemen, and after they haue clutcht them pray vpon them: They are very valiant men for they will ſtrike the braueſt ſpirit that walkes in the ſtreete, I haue known many Knights run away at the ſight of them: they are men of great reſpect and reuerence, for I haue ſeene many Gentlemen giue them the wall, and rather then they will iuſtle with them let them haue the whole ſtreete at their command: They are men of good conſciences for they will do nothing without warrant vnleſſe it be now and then for their aduantage: They are very louing creatures for I haue ſeene them come running to a Gentleman and hange about his necke and not leaue him to the death: They are very familiar and as ſociable as any whore, for they will be drunke with any man (ſo it bee not of their owne coſt) And laſtly, very kinde and affable for they will promiſe a young Gentleman more curteſie then a Courtier wil a citizen: Why then ſhould we not thinke well of Sergeants? Sir (ſaid I) I am ſure you ſpeake this Paradox only to make your ſelfe (and mee) merry, for on my conſcience what you now ſpeak is rather in an ironicall kinde of faſhion then ſerious or true, for if you will haue my opinion of them, they are the excrement that proceeds from the body of a Commonwealth, whoſe vilde doings haue beene ſo vnſauorie to mee that (for euer as all the world elſe beſide do) I ſhall hate them worſe then a Butcher doth

Lent, or a Fiſhmonger Chriſtmas or Eaſter weekes, therefore good Sir be not partiall in your proceedings but laſh them at the whipping poſt of Iuſtice and Equitie, while you fetch as much blood from their ribbes as they haue teares from many poore men and womens eyes.
               Faith Sir (ſaid he) indeed to tell you true I am like a kinde mother, that hauing ſeene her child doe ſome wittie vnhappie tricke ſtands in doubt whether ſhee ſhall laugh at him and let him eſcape, or frowne at him and correct him: ſo I hauing ſeene the cleanely and ſmooth practiſes of theſe fellowes know not whether I ſhall ſmile at them, and let them eſcape the ſcourge of my tongue, or grieue at them and correct their enormities, but howſoeuer I haue ſo braue and conſtant a Champion on my ſide as Truth I will go on though all the Sergeants belonging both to Poultry and Woodſtreet Compter were within eareſhot of mee, therefore thus I will charge vpon them with a volley ſhall wound ſome of their conſciences (if it is poſſible for them to haue any.)
               In ancient Rome the Lictores, or Sergeants went alwaies with their ſtaues of Office in their hands, and in ſuch apparell that the whole City knew them, and yet to this day in this forme, and faſhion they continue, or cary about them ſome marke of difference: So in many other Countries they are ſo markeable that they are no ſooner ſeene then knowne: But here in England (where they once went in pide coates and white roddes in their hands as a badge of infamie) they will alter their faſhion of habite oftner then a Whore doth her lodgeing, or a French Count his ſhirts in ſummer-time: Proteus neuer changed ſhapes oftner then theſe fellowes, for ſometime they will go accoutred like a ſcholler, then like a Merchant, ſometime like a Councellor, then a Butcher, Porter, or Countrie-gentleman with

their bootes and ſpurres as durty as if they had rid fiue hundred mile through the deepeſt ſlowy way that euer was trauelled; but this is (moſt commonly) when they go to arreſt ſome Farmer or Yeoman of the Country that is either but newly come into his Inne, or going out of towne, and a hundred more ſuch ſtratagems haue they in their heads when they are well greaſed in the hand; or when the arreſt is ſomething dangerous. Therfore firſt of all I will relate the manner they oftentimes arreſt a man to make you a little merry, and then proceed to the manner of their vſage of a man after they haue arreſted him. A Norwich man being exceedingly indebted to certaine Londoners (who often laide waite to arreſt him) came to the City ſo priuate that they knew not how to come at him, though ſometime they had intelligence where he was; and when (as it was very ſeldome) the Citizens came to parley with him it was out of a window, but he could by no means be drawne nigh their forces for hee was too ſubtile for them, and alwaies left word with the ſeruants in the houſe where he lay, that none ſhould haue acceſſe to him before ſuch time he himſelfe had ſeene them, eſpecially if they were in ſatten doublets, cloakes faced with taffatie, and ruffes of a Marchants ſett; at laſt his Creditors being incenſed againſt him (caring not what coſt they were at ſo they might Incounter him) came to the Compter in Woodſtreete and feed halfe a ſcore Sergeants promiſing them if they could take him they ſhould haue a lacobus a piece beſides, one of theſe ſenting the buſines, ſtraight forged a deuice which was in this manner, hee was certified that this Norwich man had weeekly ſome letters come to him out of Norfolke, and that the Porter that brought them had free acceſſe to him, this Sergeant inſtantly prouided a frocke, a red-cappe, a rope about his ſhoulders (which would haue become his necke better) and with letters in his

hand directed to the ſame party, trudges to his lodging being iuſt on that day the Porter was accuſtomed to come to him; knocking at the doore and being demanded his buſines told them that he had letters out of Norfolke for ſuch a Gentleman, vpon this he was directed vp ſtaires to the Chamber-doore, who no ſooner knockt but the Gentleman did ſtart vp from his bed to the Chamber-doore peeping before through the key-hole, and ſeeing him to be a Porter let him in, as ſoone as hee was entred hee bidde his worſhippe good morrow, vales his bonnet, and deliuers him a letter that ſhould come from a Gentleman of his acquaintance, but as he was opening of it, what doth my Porter doe but pulls his mace out of his pocket (the Gentleman not dreaming of ſuch a breakfaſt) and laide on his ſhoulders, and arreſted him, telling him that he was not what he ſeemed to be (a Porter) but what hee was a Sergeant, and that there was no way with him but either to giue ſatisfaction to his Creditors, or to priſon, therefore make your ſelfe ready, and along. So he ſeeing how hee was betraide and arreſted went quietly with him to the Compter, and died in execution. As pretty a pranke as this the ſame Sergeant plaide by an other Gentleman that ſtood vpon his guard, who hauing his Creditors with him the day before ſeemed to grow to a compoſition with him vpon the ſealing of certaine bonds, promiſing to releaſe him while a farther day, telling him that the next day they would bee with him, and bring a Councellor, and a Scriuener: a Councellor to giue them direction for the managing of the buſines on both ſides, and the Scriuener to make and write what they ſhould determine. The Creditors hauing taken their leaue ſtraight plotted together ouer night how they might arreſt the Gentleman in the morning, and hauing inuented the proiect, forth-with went to the Compter and there did ſee theſe Sergeants

and halfe a dozen more with them to diſpatch this buſines: the Sergeants being well oyled in the hand with Aurum potabile were as hot vpon the exploite as an Italian on a wench of fiueteene, and did long to put their deuice in practiſe, the Sergeant would needes take vpon him to be the Councellor, and his Yeoman the Scriuener, who had attired themſelues ſo quaint that they who had neuer ſeene them before would haue ſworne they had beene the ſame they counterfeited, for the Sergeant had a Barriſters gowne on his backe (that euer after could not chooſe but infect the true Owner with knauery) a double ruffe about his necke, and his beard cut as cloſe as a ſtubble field; his Yeoman (that had as villanous a looke as any Scriuener betweene Charing, croſſe and Pauls) had his inkehorne at his girdle, his pen in his care, and his parchment and waxe in his hand, and away they go with a ſcore more of their Comrades, whom they had appointed not to be farre from them but to come and releiue them when they heard a piſtoll diſcharged (which lay in the Gentlemans window ready charged to guard himſelfe with) the Citizens led the way, and my Councellor and Scriuener trot after vntill they came to the houſe, ſo the folkes ſeeing there was no body but ſuch as had beene there the day before (except a Councellor and a Scriuener) conducted them vp into the Gentlemans chamber (where were halfe a dozen of his men about him for feare of the worſt (ſo the Gentleman and the creditors began to lay open the matter to the Coūcellor who deſired the Gentleman to diſmiſſe his ſeruants for halfe an hower, for it was not fit they ſhould heare any of their proceedings; they were ſo then the Counceller begins to vtter his opinion, wh
                     ••
                  e the Scriuener▪ began to ſneake nigh the window, and when hee ſaw his time, diſcharged the piſtoll▪ and then inſtantly arreſted him, the other Sargeants hearing the watch word giuen,

ſtraight ran vp into the chamber with their ſwords drawen, and layd hold on him, telling him their intent and what they were, ſo the poore Gentle-man ſeeing himſelfe thus caught (rather then goe to priſon) payd the debt, ſo ſent the Sargeants and Citizens away.
               Other ſuch dog-trickes as theſe haue they plaid, as vpon a Marchant, that (either vpon pollicy or-pouerty) broke, and hauing made all his goods ready to goe into the Low-Countryes wanted nothing to diſpatch, but to mend three or foure dry-fats, which he ment to put his goods in, and gaue order to his Maide, to prouide two or three Coopers to mend them, but ſhee (being brib'd by his Creditors) betrayd her maſters purpoſe to them, ſo they prouided halfe a dozen Sargeants, to goe like Coopers the next morning, to mend this Marchants dry-fats, and were let in to diſpatch it, and had direction from the Marchant himſelfe how to finiſh it: but as he was buſie about them, inſteed of hooping the barrels, they hoopt him in their armes, and arreſted him, ſo that before they left him, they made him pay the executions they had to charge him withall, and was glad to giue them a fee beſide, that they ſhould lay no more actions on him.
               An hundred ſuch ſtratagems they haue beene fortunate in, and came off without dread or danger, but now I haue related to you the manner of their arreſting many men, now will I tell you how they vſe many (or moſt) men they haue arreſted. If they perceiue the party whom they haue ceas'd on to be a Country-Gentleman, they will be buſie with him to know whether this were the firſt time he was arreſted, if it bee, they haue the better ſubiect to worke on, and know (as they term it) how to milke them the better. Firſt they will carry him to ſome Tauerne (but it ſhall bee nigh one of the Compters) where they will call for pottle after pottle, and ſuch meat as the houſe affords, holding him in delayes,

while their guts are full, telling him they will do him what pleaſure they can for him, and that they only keepe him there, becauſe they would haue his aduerſaries come to him, and diſpatch him with all expedition, ſwearing to him, that they were ſorry to doe their office vpon him, and that if his creditor had not beene with them, they had rather haue giuen a crowne to another to arreſt him, then take a twenty-ſhilling peece to execute their office. Vpon this, one of them will makes as though hee goes to fetch his Aduerſary, when God knowes, he goes vp and downe Cheap-ſide, and other places of the City, enquiring among the Tradeſmen, whether ſuch a Gentle-man bee indebted to him or no if he bee, then hee will tell them, if hee will giue him a peece of money hee will vndertake to arreſt him, for he by chance had intelligence where hee ſupt, and when he hath his fees, what will hee doe but goe to the Compter, enter an action, takes his warrant out of the office, and comes to the Tauerne againe, telling him, he hath beene with his Aduerſary, and that hee could not poſſible come to him this three or foure hours yet, and that if he would giue them any money, they would ſtay with him, if not, they muſt haue him to the Compter, for they had or her buſineſſes to diſpatch, that they might get fiue pound by, if he offer them an Angell or a Marke for two or three houres waiting with them, account it nothing, and ſcorne to ſtay ſo long for ſo ſmall a matter, knowing the poore Gentle man will rather disburſe the value of twenty ſhillings, then goe to priſon, ſtill expecting his Aduerſaries comming, of whoſe approach there is no more hope, then of the Kings: little thinking of the villanie they are practizing againſt him, yet ſtil he expects his Aduerſary, but when it begins to bee late they call for ſomething to ſupper, and according to the lining of the poore mans purſe will ſauce him, if they ſee he hath good ſtore of crowns,

they will councell him to goe and lie in their houſe a day or two, telling him it is a thouſand to one whether his Aduerſary will come or no, for though he promiſed he would not faile, yet hee ſeem'd very vnwilling, beſides (ſay they) if you feare any other actions, wee can keepe you ſo ſafe in our houſe, that none of them ſhall know where to finde you; whereas if you were in priſon, they would all come thundering vpon you, ſo it may be you may be laid vp for two or three winters: Theſe ſpeeches terrifies my poore Gentle man, and ſtill rather then he would goe to priſon, would giue all the money in his purſe, at laſt, hauing diſcharged all the reckoning at the Tauerne, away he goes with them, and lies in ſome of their houſes a day or two, which is enough (for it will coſt him at leaſt twenty ſhillings day and night) and yet the poore man is farther from his liberty, then when he was firſt arreſted, and when theſe purſe-leeches haue ſuckt him dry, then they bring him to priſon.
               Why Sir (ſaid I) when I was arreſted I neuer ſaw any ſuch abuſes among them, it may be ſo, ſaid he, then they perceiued you had no money, or that you were too wiſe to be cheated, for I haue ſeene diuers Gentle men come into priſon (after they haue laine a fortnight or three weekes at ſome of their houſes, at an exceſſiue rate) without either cloake, ſword or hat which the Sargeants haue got from them, onely bearing them in hand that they will get them baile.
               Againe, if he be a poore ſimple fellow, as ſome Seruing-man, or Countrey Tradeſman, they will carry him to ſome blinde Ale-houſe, and there practize on him, telling him, that if hee goe to priſon, it will coſt him at firſt entrance a marke or fourteene ſhillings, and that he muſt haue irons put on his legs, as ſoone as hee comes in, and put into a place where hee ſhall neither ſee foot or hand, while he hath diſcharged the debt, and

that he would giue them ſo much money, they ought to haue for arreſting him, and ſomething to drinke beſides, they would if it ſhould bee his fortune to go thither ſpeak to the Keepers to vſe him kindly. This trick I haue knowen them ſerue a poore Country fellow, and brought him to priſon with neuer a penny in his purſe: once they ſeru'd a friend of mine ſo, but I think I made them render the money backe againe, and be glad they could be rid ſo quietly of him.
               If I ſhould but repeat but halfe their abuſes, I ſhould fill a reame of paper, I haue ſeene them come dragging in a poore man by the heels, that his head hath knockt againſt the ſtones for a quarter of a mile together, and ſo battered and martyred, that a man could ſcarce know whether he were a man or no. Sometimes when they know a man in feare of arreſting, they will, without warrant from the Creditor, giue him a caſt of their office, onely to get ſome money out of him, and ſo let him goe againe: ſometime when they are feed to arreſt a man, they will ſend the party word to keepe out of their way, hoping to haue a gratitude from him: ſometime when they haue arreſted a man (if the creditours be not by) will not ſticke to take a brace or two of Angels and let him goe, telling his aduerſary the next time he meets him, he cannot ſet eye of him, and whereas a Sargeants fee from the Creditor is no more then one ſhilling for an arreſt, they ſcorne to ſtep from the gate vnder a Crowne, a Noble or an Angell, and whereas there is a ſtatute that none of them ſhall take aboue a groat of him that is arreſted, they will not ſticke to milk him out of all his money, and turne him into priſon without either hat, cloake or ſword,
               They haue other tricks as bad as theſe, as for example, when they haue arreſted any man, either vpō an execution or action, &amp; if any Gentleman or Tradſman, or of what faſhion ſo ere he be, by chance do but iuſtle them

as they are bringing their priſoner to the Compter, for if they call them by their right names, Varlets, they (without warrant or any authority from ſome Superiour power, as Iuſtice or Conſtable, but by the vertue of their owne office) will carry him to priſon, and either lay my Lord Maiors command on him, or clap ſome heauy action on him, that except he haue good friends or a fat purſe to compound with them, he may lie and rot there for all them. *I know a poore man that didOne Atkinſon now dwelling at High gate. but offer to reſcue his friend, was clapt vp by them, and could neuer get free from them while hee was worth a teſter, and if the Iudge, before whom hee was bail'd, had not beene more pitifull then they were conſcionable, he had beene in priſon all his life time.
               If any man they arreſt, in his ſtruggling to make an eſcape from them, chance to hit any of them, either on the legs, face or breſt, ſo that they haue no hurt at all, they will gripe, beat and pinch the poore man ſo miſerably, that hee ſhall not bee able to lift his arme to his head, and then enter an action of battery againſt him, which will more vex and diſturbe him then all the reſt: I my ſelfe haue beene eye-witneſſe of the like, for in the beginning of August, 1616. they arreſted a poore Iohn Rogers. Seruing-man, who had an action entered againſt him by them, becauſe hee offered to make an eſcape from them, and when he had all his other actions withdrawn he could by no meanes get free from them, they were ſo vnreaſonable in compounding with him, that hee tooke a ſtrong conceit, and the nineteenth of the ſame month ended his life.
               Thus haue I portrayed foorth in my freſheſt cullours the abuſes and wrongs his Maieſties ſubiects daily ſuſtaine by theſe Sargeants, for which they can haue little or no remedy, and as well as I could, waded through the third arme that paies tribute to the Maine Ocean the Compter. Now will I proceede to the fourth and laſt.
            
            
               
               
                  CHAP. VII. Containing, 1. The nature of a Conſtables office. 2. An obiection concerning the abnſes his Maieſties ſubiects ſuffer by Beadles and Watch-men that vnderſtand not the vertue of their office. 3. And laſtly, an anſwer in their defence.
               REaſon (the Soule of Law) and Law (the life of a Common-wealth) ſhould ſhine and be tralucent in thoſe that beare the office of a Conſtable, for hee being the Kings Deputy for the night, is the King of the night, therfore being ſo, he ſhould impartially with his ſtaffe which repreſenteth Iuſtice, beate downe diſorder, and defend Equity, Peace and Innocence: but there are many Conſtables in theſe dayes, that through their ownenegligence (not wilfulneſſe) doe contrary to the nature of their office, for very often the Beadle and Watch-men in his abſence, commit that which the Conſtable himſelfe is much blam'd for, who vnder the pretence of ſeeing good order kept, as I haue heard, are the firſt that breed diſorder: but for mine owne part I neuer was eye-witneſſe of any of their miſdemeanours, but onely as I haue heard it reported, therefore I dare nor will goe no further then truth doth guide me. For firſt, I ſhould wrong that worthy office, in relating what I haue no probability for, and ſecondly my ſelfe, in making my ſelfe a diſhoneſt man in print. Why Sir, ſaid I, I haue often heard it reported, that the Beadles and Watch-men are in fee with the Keepers of both the Compters, and that for euery man they commit they receine a groat, and therefore onely for gaine, will (vpon any light or ſlight fault) carry any man that comes in their way to priſon, or if any man fee them, they will

(if he be neuer ſo drunke, vnruly or diſordered) conuay him to his lodging; or otherwiſe, if hee bee vnfurniſht, conuay him to one of the Compters. And to mine owne knowledge I haue knowne a Beadle committed to the Gatehouſe for committing a Noblemans ſeruant (who went vpon ſpeciall buſines for the Lord his Maſter) therefore if he had not firſt wronged this Gentleman, and ſecondly the force, and nature of his Office, why ſhould he being an Officer be committed for his miſdemeanour? Againe I haue ſeene many men come into priſon (ſince I came hither) that haue been extreamly hackt and maimed with their halberds: which in (my opinion) they cannot anſwer, for though they haue authority to commit, they haue none to kill or wound, therefore in my iudgement theſe abuſes are vnſufferable, and onely are vpholden by their Head the Conſtable.
               Sir (ſaid he) you muſt vnderſtand that a Conſtable is but an Iland brooke that paies but ſmall tribute to the Ocean the Compter, he is but cauſa accidentalis, an accidentall cauſe, and by chance fattens the groſſe and vaſt body of it, for after his watch is ſet hee is bound by oath to performe his office both for the diſcharge of his owne conſcience, and the good of his Prince, and Countrey, in which duty euery good ſubiect is bound in duty to aſſiſt him. For a Conſtable is the preſeruer of peace, the attacher of vice, and the Intelligencer of iniuries, and hath as ſtrong and forcible power to commit Offendors in the night as any Iuſtice of peace hath in the day: nay if any Lord, Knight, or Gentleman of what degree, or faſhion ſoeuer he bee, comming in the night-time through the watch in an vnruly faſhion is as ſubiect to his command and authority as the pooreſt ſubiect that walkes the ſtreetes: and if hee ſhould not ſometimes nay many times clappe vp ſuch perſonages, they would be thought very ſlacke in their office and

not worthy of that authoritie, and power the King hath giuen them; for many men though they haue braue outſides may commit or act as great, or more heinous miſchiefe then thoſe that are of a poore ranke, for if the Conſtable ſhould not ſtand Centinell, how many men would beerob'd in the ſpace of one weeke, nay of one night, which by his induſtry and care hee preſerues. But here it is obiected that the Beadle and Watchmen haue for euery man they commit a groat, whether it be true or falſe I neuer could confidently ſpeake of, if they haue, it is fit that for ſo many nights as they ſit vp for the good of the Commonwealth they ſhould haue ſomething allowed, and who is the fitteſt to allow it but ſuch as haue offended and they haue beene troubled with the night before: Againe you ſay they will commit ſuch as haue no mony to giue them, though it be vpon a ſleight occaſion, and let ſuch paſſe though their fault bee neuer ſo heynous ſo they will greaſe them in the fiſt. This obiection I will thus anſwer, if this abuſe is offered it cannot enter into my minde that the Conſtable hath any hand in it, for there are many occaſions that may call him away after his watch is ſet, and he that is his Deputy may commit the offence (knowing not what truely belongs to his office or place) and if ſometimes they let a Drunkard eſcape without going to priſon, it is a thouſand to one but they that conduct him to his lodging will haue the houſe-Keeper, paſſe his word for his comming foorth in the morning to anſwere what ſhall bee laide to his charge before the Iuſtice: and I thinke a 
                     •
                  eſter or a ſhilling is well beſtowed vpon them for ſuch a curteſie: againe if they chance to let any vnruly Gallant paſſe, it is either vpon his ſubmiſſion to the Conſtable or his Deputy, or elſe he muſt alledge ſome firme and conſtant reaſon what the occaſion is of his being ſo late out of his lodging. And though there are many men hurt in the

watch, the fault lies moſt of all in themſelues and not in the Watchmen, for when a company of Gallants come from ſome Tauerne, or worſe place high gon in wine, and will not render an account of their walking at ſuch an vntimely ſeaſon, but draw their ſwords and fall to hacking them, therefore they are bound firſt of all by the Kings lawes to apprehend them, and ſecondly by the law of nature to defend themſelues, and rather offend then to bee offended. Thus haue I anſwered your obiectious deſiring to draw to an end, for this is a ſubiect I haue no firme or ſollid ground to worke on, if Conſtables, Beadles, and Watchmen, are conſcious or guilty of theſe obiections I haue defended, I deſire they may amend and correct them and giue no occaſion to haue any pen buſie it ſelfe in deſcribing the abuſes; thus haue I ſet foorth in order the foure armes that pay tribute to the Ocean the Compter, now will I come to the Compter it ſelfe.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. VIII. Containing 1. Areſemblance betweene the Sea, and the Compter. 2. With the true nature and conditions of ſuch as liue in it.
               NOw I haue croſt the armes of this maine Ocean the Compter I will ſaile in the Ocean it ſelfe; and well may the Compter hold ſimilitude with the Sea, for as the Sea is oftentimes diſturbed with ſtormes, guſts, and tempeſts, ſo is the Compter with continuall ſtormes of griefe; guſts of ſorrow, and tempeſts of tribulation which are continually beating vpon the head and heart of many a poore Priſoner. The Sea as Philoſophers hold is rul'd by the Moone and according to

the nature of her fourequarters, ſhe doth ebbe and flow, riſe or fall, ſo is the Compter maintained by the Law and the foure-Tearmes, and according to their nature and property, it is full and empty. The ſea hath many fearefull and hideous monſters in it, ſo hath the Compter an abundance of Sergeants. In the Sea the great ones eate vp the little ones, ſo in the Compter the Iaylors and Officers feed vpon the poore Priſoners. In the Sea there are many rocks and quickſands, ſo in the Compter is the booke where many poore men pay their fees, and the Paper houſe where he hath his diſcharge: in the Sea there are many ſhippes caſt away by wracks and tempeſts, ſo in the Compter are many men by extortion and cruell Creditors: And laſtly, as in a ſtorme at ſea a braue ſhippe Royall-well man'd that hath ſtore of skilfull Marriners and a good Pilot may ride out the fury and rage of the tempeſt when a poore rotten weatherbeaten Pinke deſtitute of Anchor, ſailes, munition, men and Skilfull Pilots, is ſoone drowned: So in the Compter in the moſt horredſt wracke of affliction, a rich man well friended, well monyed (his chiefeſt Pilot) may make way through the fearefulleſt ſtorme of aduerſity, and come againe to the Port and Hauen of Liberty, while the poore man deſtitute of friends and mony is ſoone caſt away in a ſmall brunt and ſhocke of aduerſitie: but now to the matter.
               In Noahs Arke there were ſome of all ſort of Creatures, ſo in the Compter ſome of all kinde of people, for to ſay the right of it, it is a Commonwealth though very little wealth bee common there. There lies your right-worſhipfull poore Knight, your worſhipfull beggerly Eſquire, your diſtreſſed Gentleman, your Mechanicke Tradſman, your prating Pettifogger, and iuggling (lyers I would ſay) Lawyers, all theſe like ſo many beaſts in a Wilderneſſe deſire to prey one vpon

the other, for I thinke there are as many ſinnes looking through the grates of a Priſon as there are walking through the gates of a City: For though we are all Priſoners yet the cauſes of our reſtraint are diuers, ſome are in for debt, ſome for other more heynous and criminall actions, ſome there are that are in vpon conſtraint, and ſuch are they that come in for debt and can no way ſhunne what they ſuffer, or haue no meanes to giue ſatisfaction to their Creditors: Others there are that are voluntary and ſuch are they that come in of purpoſe, who (if it pleaſe themſelues) may keepe themſelues out, of which I finde foure kinde of people that are good ſubiects to this Commonwealth the Compter, and they are theſe, the firſt your ſubtile Citizen, the ſecond your riotous-Vnthrift, the third your politicke High way-man, and the fourth and laſt your crafty mechanicke.
               The firſt of theſe is the firmeſt legge the body of this Commonwealth doth ſtand vpon, for after hee hath been a Tradſman ſome fiue or ſix yeeres or longer, hauing borne vp his head as high as his neighbours, hath had good credit on the Exchange among the Marchants, and continually paying them at the day appointed, may if it pleaſe him (hauing kept his word ſo faithfully with them) haue what goods he pleaſeth at halfe a yeere or yeeres day of payment: at laſt when he finds his beſt oppo
                     •
                  tunity, what doth he, but gets fiuehundred pounds worth of wares of one marchant, as much more of an other, and ſo runnes ouer all thoſe he hath had doings with, and when hee hath got the quantity of foure, or fiue thouſand pounds worth of goods into his hands, a moneth or ſix weekes before the day of payment, my Citizen in priuate ſells all theſe commodities by whole ſale for ready mony at the beſt rate, and hauing all this caſh in his purſe ſtraight flies into the Countrie among his friends, and lies there perhaps

a ſummer together for his owne pleaſure, and when hee heares of any writs that are out for him returnes againe to the Cittie, and lies cloſe making none acquainted with his lodging but ſome man he knowes will breake before the next quarter, and imploies this partie to go to his Creditors to certifie them of the miſerie he is in, and that by truſting young Gentlemen he hath vndone himſelfe, deſiring them to bee good to him, proteſting that they ſhall haue all that is left among them if they will be content to let him walke the ſtreetes quietly to vſe ſome meanes to raiſe his fortunes once againe: his Creditors perhaps giues his friendes good wordes telling him they will not be rough with him hoping with this baite to catch my cittizen abroad and ſo clappe him vp, which my Bankrupt little cares for, knowing that after he hath laine in priſon a yeere or two they will be glad to take a quarter of their debts and let him out, what cares he for Actions, Executions, Iudgements, Statutes, or any other Writs, hee hath enough to keepe himſelfe in priſon and will make them come to compoſition with him as hee liſt himſelfe, or they get none at all, ſo his Creditors at laſt ſeeing his reſolution ſo fixt and ſetled will (though very loath) take one quarter of their debts rather then looſe all, and it may bee not halfe of that in mony, but young Gentlemens bonds, and deſperate debts that God knowes whether they ſhall euer recouer one penny: thus doe many Banrupts ly in diuers priſons about this Towne inriching themſelues, and by their policie are good for nothing but to defraud his Maieſties ſubiects, and fatten a loathſome priſon, and this is the firſt of theſe voluntary Souldiers.
               The ſecond of theſe are ſuch that will compound with a braſe of Sergeants to arreſt them, and ſuch are many young Gentlemen that want mony to ſupply ſome vitious vſe or other (knowing they haue kinde

friends) will voluntarily haue an action enter'd againſt them and be arreſted, ſo perhaps will lye there a day or two while their friends heare of it, who if it bee but a matter of foure or fiue pound will not ſticke to diſcharge it, which being no ſooner done but ſtraight they go to the party to whom the mony was paide▪ and there giue the Sergeant an Angell, and ſhare the reſt among themſelues, many trickes of this kinde haue I ſeen put in practiſe ſince I came hither; but one thing I will not forget which was this: One of theſe fellowe▪ that had vſed this tricke three or foure ſeuerall times, and beene fetcht out by his friends for ſeuerali ſummes of mony, did once more put it in practiſe, which his friends (at laſt) perceiuing, let him lie there ſome two or three yeeres together, and the moſt part of his impriſonment was in the Hole, and if at laſt he had not got off cleere by his owne induſtry he might haue beene a Priſoner there while this time for all them. How ſay you ſir was not this a pretty tricke? yes faith ſir (ſaid I) I would all ſuch voluntary priſoners might be ſeru'd ſo, but (good ſir) to the third of theſe voluntaries.
               The thirſt ſort of theſe are ſuch that hauing beene in priſon, and lying in the Hole haue beene releaſed by Legacies, but being freed and feeling theſweetneſſe of it, will purpoſely once a yeere (as about Chriſtmas or Eaſter, when they know Legacies come in) get ſome friend of theirs to arreſt them for a matter of thirty or forty ſhillings and then make ſuite to the Marchants (that yearely come and releaſe priſoners if their debts be not aboue that value) which if they get, they haue ſo much mony cleere to bee merry with. Theſe baſe trickes are vſuall though they be not lookt into, or corrected, for it is an extreame wrong firſt to the party that giues it in cheating of him, and ſecondly in defrauding other poore Priſoners that lie in for due debts.
               
                  The fourth and laſt ſort of theſe are young Gallants that now and then will make a ſteppe to Newmarketheath or ſome ſuch place, and after they haue that they long lookt for, come poſting to London, and if the hews and 
                     
                        ••
                     ies come too hotly after them, inſtantly gets themſelues arreſted into one of the Compters, and lie there while the matter cooles, for who will looke into ſuch a place for any ſuch Offenders? Thus haue I laide downe in my beſt methode the nature of theſe voluntary Priſoners that fatten this Common-wealth the Compter Sir (ſaid I) theſe reports ſtrike mee into a maſement: I proteſt I thought there could not haue beene ſuch villany extant in a Realme much leſſe in a priſon: But I hope ſir you are come to treat of the Keepers, I am ſir, ſaid he, and thus began.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. IX. Containing 1. A Character of a Iaylor. 2. Their true nature and dispoſition. 3. Their cruelty, and extortion, And 4. and laſtly ſuch abuſes that haue been diſcouered, liuely diſplaied.
               DAre you write? Why not? my dore is ſhut. They that pinch me ſee not how I pinch them. But, but when your diſcourſe comes out the Keeper will hold you in the faſter. Tuſh my booke muſt helpe me out. I hope to ſee Pauls▪ Churchyard as ſoone as it. If I doe not, the worſt cenſure that can paſſe, will be a Rayler againſt a laylor. Bold Muſe hold on thy pace. If the world is a Body, then I cannot be perſwaded but laylors and Keepers of Priſons are the nailes of it, for they ſcratch exceedingly, and like ſicke men poſſeſt with lunacie ſnatch at any thing: Theſe kinde of fellowes

are as nigh a kinne to Sergeants as Brokers are to Vſurers, both of them are inſeparable purſeleaches, and are men that hauing runne through their trades as they haue their eſtates, at laſt are forced to take vpon them this moſt baſe, and odious kinde of life, which they no ſooner haue obtained but are as proud of it, as a louſie priſoner of a freſh ſute, or a beggerly Rimer of tweluepenny dole when hee oweth ninepence for ale. They are men that haue no quality in them but one, and that is to aske mony, and like Lawyers without their fees will doe nothing. They imitate Rauens, Kites and Crowes that feede vpon the corruption, ſtinking garbige and guts of any carrion lying in the fields, and leaue that part that is moſt wholeſome vntouch't, ſo theſe feed vpon the follies and vices of the age, &amp; haue nothing to doe with any thing that is good. If a Gentleman come into their Confines that hath his purſe well lined with crownes they will haue no more mercy ouer him then a Dog killer hath ouer a diſeaſed Curre in the plague time. Which makes me call to mind that Motto I haue often ſeene and read Homo homini Lupus man is to man a Wolfe. If a man ſhould trauell into the Wilderneſſe or ſome vaſt deſert, and bee deuoured by ſōme Reare, or Boare, or ſuch like ſauage Creature, it were but their kinde to doe ſo being prickt and ſtung with hunger; But for one man like a Canniball to feed vpon the other, what more monſtrous and worſe then crueltie is this which euery day is ſeene in this place. Yet in their crueltie they will vſe deliberation and feed vpon a man while he hath mony, and make as dainty of him as a Spaniard will of a piece of beife or mutton, and make many ſweete meales of him: Or like ſome cruell Surgeons that haue a rich man in cure of ſome dangerous diſeaſe, will not at firſt ſend him to purge in another aire, but let him by lingring, and as they call them with their compounding plaiſters make him

ſmart while they haue got more money from him, and while they haue drawne his life to the laſt thread, and thinke here is no more to be got out of him, ſtraight poſt him to his graue; ſo Iaylors when a mans mony is ſpent turne him into the Hole.
               Sir (ſaid I) I haue ſeene ſome of their doings ſince I came hither, and haue admired they ſhould bee ſo hardened that their hearts cannot bee mollified with the oile of compaſſion, no nor cut with the Diamond of compunction, or that they haue no ſenſe or feeling of their owne inhumanity and hard-heartedneſſe, nor once thinke that God may one day make them in as wretched a plight as thoſe they thus tyrannize ouer. Sir (ſaid he) you ſhall ſeldome ſee a Butchers-dogge that continually lies in the ſhambles without a bloudy mouth, and thoſe Officers that liue in this place hauing once their finger dipt in the blood-boule of crueltie, ſeldome or neuer can be reduced to a milder kinde of vſage: Cuſtome is a ſecond nature with them, and becauſe they daily do it they thinke it is as naturall with them as their meate and drinke.
               But I will leaue their ſtrickt dealing with old Priſoners while an other time, and come to their vſage and behauiour to new-come Priſoners at their firſt entrance.
               At the firſt entrance of any man into this Dedalean Labyrinth, after they haue viewed him and know his name, then according to the faſhion of his cloaths (but moſt eſpecially the weight of his purſe) they beare themſelues towards him, Flies neuer come to painted gallipots for their gay outſides, but their ſweet inſides as ſuckets, ſugars, and other preſerues, ſo theſe rather reſpect the purſe, then the perſon; for they had rather know he hath a ſiluer inſide then ſee him to haue a golden outſide. If they know hee hath good friends that will not ſee him want, or that hee hath meanes of his

owne correſpondent to their expectation, they will fawne and flatter him in euery reſpect more then a funerall ſermon will a dead man; he ſhall want nothing while he wants not money, euery Officer will haue a cappe and a knee for him, euery time they ſee him hee ſhall command all the houſe be Dominus fac totum, what abuſe ſoeuer he offers ſhall be ſmothered ſuffering him to doe any wrong, yet take none, when a poore man for the leaſt offence ſhall be clapt into irons, and caſt into the Hole, and there ſhall remaine while ſuch time he ſubmits himſelfe in all humilitieto Maſter Keeper.
               If they ſee a young Nouice come in, who liberally and freely will pay all the large fees of the houſe without much asking, and ſometimes greaſe their perpetuall dry palmes with a teſter or a ſhilling, he ſhall not only command their hats, but alſo their hearts, a couert paraſite will not be more ſubmiſſe to his beſt Patrone then theſe Compter Spaniells will bee before ſuch profuſe prodigalls. But if a Gentleman of a rectified and ſollid vnderſtanding chance to be arreſted, and being demanded the fees and garniſh ſtand vpon interrogatories with them, asking them what warrant they can ſhew for the taking of ſuch mony (being loath to caſt away his mony) they will inſtantly anſwere it is a cuſtome. A cuſtome! Oh heauens is cuſtome become Law, and muſt it becauſe it is vſuall with them be lawfull for them to grinde the faces of his Maieſties ſubiects, who will not for the moſt part ſtand and capitulate with them but rather condeſcend to them ſo they may get good vſage of them, and when they are diſcharged neuer thinke of their abuſe, but are glad they haue got from them, and will rather leaue their cruelty to be puniſhed by Gods hand then the Lawes.
               I deſire to know the reaſon, why, when a Gentleman comes to the Maſterſide he muſt before hee is ſuffered to come into the dining roome pay twelue pence for

turning the key, which not long ſince was but a groat, by what authoritie or warrant are they now to take two groats more then there due: nay indeede, why ſhould they haue any at all, becauſe I neuer read in any place in the ſtatutes of England that ſuch fees are due, therefore hauing no warrant from thence, I admire they dare venture to take that which may turne to their vndoing, if any Informer ſhould proſecute this extortion againſt them.
               Againe, ſuppoſe a man payes the ſhilling is demanded of him by the porter, why ſhould hee pay for his bed the firſt night two ſhillings (which extortion is diuided betweene the cheefe Keeper and the Chamberlaine his ſeruant) they can yeeld none other reaſon but this, that it is a cuſtome: and if they bee hardly put to it, they will ſay that is the pleaſure of the Sheriffes, on my conſcience they doe be lye their Worſhipfull Maſter, for though they are Maſters of the Houſe where priſoners are, yet they are not Maſters of their purſes: beſides no man can bee ſo ignorant and ſimple, to beleeue that they will deuiſe lawes of themſelues, for which they haue no warrant out of the ſtatutes: beſides the ſtatutes of the Compter were wont fiue yeeres ſince to hang in the yard, that euery man might ſee what wasPriſoners vſed worſe then ſlaues, whoſe price appeareth written on their backes. due to the houſe and euery officer, but now they are cut downe and buried in obliuion, that they may demand what they liſt, which they cannot iuſtifie, for if they could, they would when they are put to it, ſtand to the vertue of their authoritie and office, which not long ſince I ſaw tryed, which euer ſince made mee confidently beleeue, that no ſuch large fees (they vſually take) are due to them.
               For a Gentle-man (they afterward clapt into the Hole, becauſe hee plainely and boldly tolde them of their abuſes) being arreſted came into the Maſter ſide, &amp; being demanded his fees and garniſh, which hee very

well had beene acquainted with, becauſe hee often, by his owne confeſſion, had beene a priſoner, tolde them there was none due and none he would pay, for, ſayd he, howſoeuer you may fetch ouer young guls for their money, I will not be ſo ſoone caught, what I call for, I will make a ſhift to ſee diſcharged, otherwiſe I determine to pay nothing, and ſo reſolue your ſelues.
               The Chamberlaine (the cheefeſt officer on that ſide) be gan to take the repulfe very hainouſly, and thought he would one way or other be euen with him, making no account that hee ſhould loſe his fees by him, earely the next morning before the Gentleman was vp, came into his chamber, where he found him ſleeping, and his cloake (the marke he ſhot at) lying on the table by him, ſo tooke it vp and went downe ſtaires againe, but when the Gentle-man was awake, and began to make himſelfe ready, he found his cloake miſſing, ſo that hee began to enquire of his chamber-fellowes if they ſaw it not, but they denied it, at laſt he had intelligence that the Chamberlaine had got it for his fees, vpon this hee firſt went and demanded his cloake of him, who refuſed to deliuer it, vnleſſe he would pay him his garniſh, for, quoth hee, you haue met with no fooles, no faith, ſaid the Gentle man, I rather think I am come among a crue of cunning knaues, and vnleſſe you redeliuer me my cloake againe, I will make ſome of you appeare ſo before yours and my betters. And ſo foorthwith ſent his letter by a friend of his to the next Iuſtice, demanding his warrant for the apprehending of ſuch a fellow, naming of him, that the ſame night had rob'd him, ſo layd flat fellony to his charge: The Iuſtice hearing the matter could doe none other, ſeeing he purpoſed to ſweare againſt him, and being for the King granted him his warrant for the attaching of the ſame Chamberlain and to bring him before him to be examined, he ſeeing how he was ſeru'd with this warrant, would haue giuen

the Gentle-man his cloake againe, which he refuſed but at laſt by much perſwaſton he was intreated to take it againe, if ſo bee hee might heare no more of the matter, and with all his heart for gaue him all ſuch fees he before demanded of him and was glad he eſcapt ſo well. And that the world may know this is no fiction of mine owne inuention that I haue related, I will tell the name of him that did this, who was one Mr 
                  Venard (that went by the name of Englands Ioy) that afterward died heere in miſery, plagued by the Keepers, being more guilty of his death then his cruell aduerſaries, for after hee began to tell them of that they were loath to heare of, they thruſt him into the Hole, being in winter, where lying without a bedde, hee caught ſuch an extreame cold in his legges, that it was not long before he departed this life.
               Now I would know of them, if their fees had beene due, why did they not ſtand to the maintaining of their due, or if the Sheriffes did appoint ſuch fees to bee taken▪ why did they not appeale to him, and deſire his aide in the matter, and ſince that time why did they not procure of him that the Articles might bee hung vp by the gate, that all priſoners as ſoone as they are brought in vpon an arreſt or command, may read them and not ſtand in contention, but paie what the Right Worſhipfull Sheriffes and Court of Aldermen thinke fit to be paide.
               That the extortion of theſe Iaylors are extreame,23. of his raigne. looke into the ſtatutes of Henry the ſixt, where it was appointed by act of Parliament, that a Iaylour ſhould take of any priſoner committed to ward but a groat, in this iniunction there is not ſet downe any due belonging to the dore-keeper, there is no ſhilling mentioned for him, no two ſhillings for the Chamberlaine, no ſix-pence for the Porter, or large fees for the Bookekeeper, but heere is onely mention made of a groat for

the Iaylor and no more: this is the iniunction after which followes the penaltie, which is this, (mentioned in the ſame Statute) And if any Iaylor ſhall any waies doe contrarie to this aforeſaid ordinance he ſhall looſe to the partie thus endammaged or greiued his treble dammages, and forfeit forty pound at euery time that any of them doe contrary in any point of the ſame, whereof the Queene ſhall haue one halfe to be emploied onely to the vſe of her houſe, and the partie that will ſue the other halfe, only the Warden of the Fleete and of the Queenes-Pallace at Weſtminſter for the time being ſhal not be preiudiced by this Ordinance in the dutie of his office. Thus you haue heard the iniunction and penaltie of this Statute which was made in King Henries the ſixts time, which were in force in Queene Elizabeths time, &amp; which now is of vertue and efficacie in our Soueraigne Iames his time, for theſe Statutes neuer ſince they were firſt made in the Honourable houſe of Parliament were repealed: Therefore I admire they knowing the Statutes wil in danger themſelues ſo much euery day as to infringe this ordinance, by the breaking of which they reape an infinite gaine yearely, for of ſo many thouſands that come into their iuriſdictions they let none ſcape but haue fiue times more then this Statute allowes them, nay ſometimes tenne times, nay twentie times more then they can anſwere; for I haue ſeene ſome men pay ten groates for his fees at booke, ſome ten ſhillings, ſome a marke, ſome twenty ſhillings, nay I haue noted it they haue not beene aſhamed to aske fortie ſhillings for his fees, beſides garniſh, and other charges which will amount to the matter of a noble or ſeuen ſhillings if hee lie heere but one night, let him go the nigheſt way to worke he can. Therefore I haue many times wiſhed a Promooter at ſome of their backes to ſee their vnconſcionable dealing, that hee might ſerue them out of the Exchequor with a sub paena
                  
for their horrible extortion, and make ſome of the worſt of them (if there can be one worſe then another) examples for the reſt, for no Iaylor will ſtand to triall if he be wiſe, but will rather confeſſe it, and plead guilty, which if he do he confeſſeth his extortion; but if he be ſo valiant as to ſtand to a iuſtification, he hath no warrant to exceede his limitation. Therefore whether he pleades guilty, or ſtands to his iuſtification he cannot chuſe but ſhew himſelfe an extorter, as on Carman that
                     Carman and Bud, ſecundo of the King in Michael▪ mas Terme▪ And How and Bud, quarto of the king in Trinity Terme. lay in the Compter of the Poultry two or three yeare had like to prou'd one of his Keepers if hee had ſtood to the triall, but he was glad to compound with him and giue him a piece of mony to let his ſuite fall, which if many other Priſoners would take example by this fellow, and call their good doings in queſtion, it would be a great eaſe to many poore mens purſes. For what extreame extortion is it when a Gentleman is brought in by the watch for ſome miſdemeanour committed, and ſtaies but while the next morning, that muſt pay at leaſt an Angell before he be diſcharged, hee muſt pay tweluepence for turning the key at the maſterſide dore, two ſhillings to the Chamberleine, tweluepence for his garniſh for wine, ten pence for his dinner, whether he ſtay or no, and when he comes to be diſcharged at the Booke it will coſt at leaſt three ſhillings and ſixpence more, beſides ſixpence for the Booke-keepers paines, and ſixpence for the Porter. But this abuſe was once complained on by one that had beene wronged in this nature, and my Lord Maior ſent word and commanded that no man comming in by the watch ſhould be receiued into the maſter-ſide, yet within ſixe or ſeuen weekes after they could not forget their old wont but fell to it againe, imitating the Fox that was commanded by the Lyon for killing many geeſe and hens to go a pilgrimage for his ſinnes, yet he could not chooſe but caſt his eyes on euery flocke of geeſe he ſaw graſing on

euery greene he trauelled through, and at laſt for all the Lyons command caſt off his Pilgrimmes weed before he had gone halfe his iourney, and fell to his olde trade againe. But they haue other trickes as badde as theſe, which are as followeth: when a Gentleman that hath beene long reſident in the maſterſide, and hath paide all their demand there, and chanceth to be turn'd ouer to the Knights-ward for want of meanes he, muſt be forced to pay all the fees ouer againe, or elſe they will either pull his cloake from his backe, or his hat from his head, and the Steward of that ward will ſtand as peremptorily vpon it as if it were confirmed to him by Act of Parliament, or had it vnder all the Priuie Councells hands: And if a Gentleman ſtay there but one night he muſt pay for his garniſh ſixteene pence beſides a groate for his lodging, and ſo much for his ſheetes, and ſtill he that receiues it, ſaies, it is a cuſtome, &amp; that it is toward the buying of ſuch things he wants. why if it be ſo I thinke euery Priſoner is of vnderſtanding ſufficient to buy theſe things himſelfe, and not to truſt his money▪ in other mens hands, and ſtand to their kindneſſe for ſuch things he ſhall want; but theſe are onely trickes to get money, for I haue ſeene them put to their nonplus, and dared by Gentlemen that vnderſtood their dealings to pull their cloakes from their backes, telling them that there was no ſuch exactions due, at which hot repulſe they haue beene as calme as midnight; but if they meete with ſome raw young fellow that will ſwallow and digeſt ſuch wrongs they will triumph ouer him, and not let him paſſe while they haue made him open his purſe and giue them their demand.
               When a Gentleman is vpon his diſcharge, and hath giuen ſatisfaction for his executions they muſt haue fees for irons, three-halfe-pence in the pound, beſides the other fees, ſo that if a man were in a thouſand or

fifteene hundred pound execution, they will if a man is ſo madde haue ſo many three-halfe-pence, but I thinke the Keeper of one of the Compters that tooke ſuch vnlawfull fees was forced to pay backe againe what he had receiued with a thouſand thankes as ſoone as hee perceiued he had a ſubpaena was ſeru'd vpon him out of the Exchequor: Thus if ſome men would but take this order with them, and ierke them with ſuch rods they would learne a better and honeſter leſſon.
               To mine owne knowledge I ſaw a Promooter thatIupus lupum n
                        •
                     uit, &amp; ſurem sur. was arreſted vſed more kindly and reſpectiuely then a Gentleman of fiue hundred pound a yeere, hee had what in reaſon he called for in the Celler, and might haue broath and meate out of the Kitchin at any time whenſoeuer hee would call for it: but will any man thinke that this was in loue to him, no it was in feare for not many yeeres ſince hee had informed againſt them for extortion, therefore this conſidered vnleſſe they knew themſelues guiltie of ſuch faults they did ſuſpect he would ſent out, why ſhould they ſtand ſo much in feare of him, and if they had tooke nothing but their due, they might haue let him gone like an informing Knaue as he was, and ſcorne his worſt of malice, for Truth is a braſen tower and will retort the ſhot of malice into their owne faces that ſhoot them, Vertue is like a bedde of Camomill the more it is trodden on the more it flouriſheth, the more ſhe is depreſt the more ſhe expreſſeth her ſelfe. What a ſtrange thing is it when a man is arreſted &amp; puts▪ himſelfe to the knightſward muſt pay a groat a night for his lodging, and a groate for euery paire of ſheetes heelies in, what conſcience haue they to exact ſo much when the beſt bedde in that ſide is not worth a Seruing-mans yearely wages; but I haue heard their due is but twopence a night if a man lie alone, and a penny a night if he haue a bedfellow, and that in the twopenny-ward where they receiue

fourteene pence a weeke their due is but ſeuenpence, then what exceſſiue gaines is this in a yeare, when I haue heard it credibly reported that within the circuit of one yeare there is committed and diſcharged both vpon command &amp; arreſt at the leaſt fiue thouſand Priſoners, what might this amount to beſides their fees at the booke and their garniſhes, but no more of this, for ifI hope my booke ſhall meet with a Printer that neuer married Iaylours daughter. any keeper ſhould eaſdrop vs, and be witneſſe of what I relate, I perpetually ſhould be lockt vp into the Hole, or neuer haue a good looke of the well-fauouredſt of them all. Therfore my pen ſhall ſleep in ſilence, &amp; reueale no more of their abuſes that lie hid frō moſt mē.
               Sir, ſaid I, I perceiue you are either loath to proceede in your diſcourſe, or elſe you grow weary with diſcourſing, therefore I will giue you ſome expauſion &amp; breathing time, &amp; vnfold vnto you what I heard of others ſince I came in, concerning them, and if in any point I erre in the relation, I deſire you to be my guide and put me into the right way, for I am loath to wrong them, though they wrong moſt men they haue power ouer, but would haue the body of my diſcourſe ſtand vpon the feet of truth.
               I haue heard it reported, when any Legacies come into the houſe, towards the releaſe of the poore people of the Hole, the Keepers ſometimes takes them into their hands, promiſing thoſe that deliuer them, that they ſhall be layd foorth toward the diſcharge of the poore, but contrary to the wil of the Benefactor deceaſed, releeue not only the poore in the loathſome dungeon of the Hole, to whom it was ſoly giuen, but help thoſe out with them that lie in the two-penny ward, becauſe they owe them money for their lodging, and ſo not for any good will to them, helpe them to a Legacie, that they might be payd themſelues out of it, or elſe they might lie there like the reſt of their fellowes. Thus they firſt wrong the charitable Benefactours, that

on their death-beds bequeath their bounty to the poor, and laſtly, the poore themſelues, in depriuing them of that which is due to them, in making them ſtay, it may be two months or a quarter of a yeere before they can be releaſed, expecting other Legacies, when as halfe a ſcore or more of them may die before they come in. Againe, I haue heard ſome murmure at their plots, in keeping men in by pollicy that haue ſtore of money, letting them not goe before ſuch time their money is almoſt ſpent, and when their Creditors come to heare of them, will not ſticke to tell them that they haue money enough in their pockets, &amp; that it was fit they ſhould haue their due before they withdrew their actions: yet when they ſee his coine begin to waſt, will not ſtand out to perſwade their aduerſaries to take pity of them, and come to ſome reaſonable compoſition: for what ſhould they doe with them when they haue no more caſh: dealing with them as ſome dainty Lady will with a Woodcocke, cares not what becomes of the body, when ſhee hath eaten vp his braines, or as Huntſmen doe with foxes, fling the carkaſſe into ſome ditch or on ſome dunghill, after they hane ſtript his skin ouer his eares. Beſides theſe trickes I haue heard that when a young Gentle-man is arreſted, and hath competent allowance from his friends, as weekely his diet and his lodging diſcharged, they continually will certifie his friends or his father of the leaſt miſdemeanour he ſhall commit, nay, rather then faile to relate all, will adde more to it, to make it more hainous, ſo that hee might bee incenſed againſt his childe, and ſtill keepe him in priſon, which policy is onely for this cauſe, that they might ſtill haue ſo good a gueſt as hee is, knowing his friends will ſee ſuch things hee cals for truely diſcharged▪
               
               Theſe things (ſay they) are common with them, and when a Tradeſman is arreſted vpon ſeuerall actions

they will giue (being feed well) intelligence to their Aduerſaries whether they meane to put in baile or no to them, or what they determine to get their releaſe by, caring not what becoms of the poore man, wife and children, ſo they themſelues gaine but twelue-pence. Some, ſay they, will not ſticke to take fees of dead men, and ſcarce let the coffin goe out of their gates, before his friends hath payd his fees, therefore if theſe reports bee true, it is firſt moſt abhominable for them to act, and moſt lamentable to heare. Therefore, good Sir, let me haue your aduiſe and opinion in this matter, and truly without any fallacie or equiuocation, whether theſe things I lately was certified, of are true or no, after a little pauſing he began to reſolue me in this manner.
               Indeede Sir, ſome of theſe deuiſes I haue found practiſed vpon my ſelfe, but for ſome others, that you haue made mention of I will not boldly warrant to bee true, but you haue heard no more reported then I haue heard ſpoken: but this I can iuſtifie to be true, as a true token and ſigne of their wooluiſh diſpoſition and ingluvious appetites, there cannot a diſh of meat come into the gates, but they muſt and will haue a ſhare of it, nay, and thinke that the poore priſoners are much beholding to them, that they are ſo much graced, or haue ſo much fauour as to haue them partake with them: but if any man hating their ſociety will neither giue them entertainment, or inuite them to any peece of meate hee ſhall bee ſure to bee lockt vp all that weeke that Keeper waits, and doe him ſome villanous miſchiefe whenſoeuer he conueniently can contriue it. Or on the contrary, if any young nouice that hath no execution againſt him, bee pliant to their humour, they will vſe him with as great a reſpect as any Noble-mans heire, if they ſee him profuſe and riotous, they will not leaue vrging him to go abroad with them to take ſome compoſition with his creditors, when Heauen knowes, it is

not for any good they purpoſe to him, but themſelues. For they vſe him as Anglers doe the fiſh, giue him a bait, but it is for his bane, ſo theſe are kinde, but it is for ſome benefit they expect from him, for they will neuer goe abroad with any of theſe vnder two ſhillings or halfe a crowne, if they ſtay but an hower with them, beſides in what company ſoeuer they come in, and ſtay at dinner &amp; ſupper, either at an Ordinary or Tauerne, or any friends houſe, they pay not a penny, thus doe they perſwade many abroad with them (that elſe would ſtay at home, I meane in Priſon) firſt that they might furniſh their purſes with money, and their bellies with good cheere, and bring them home at night, as bare of money as a ſheepe is of wooll that all day long hath beene feeding among buſhes and briers.
               But ſuppoſe this man from whom they haue receiued ſo much kindneſſe, as good diet, money and other fauours, fall into want and diſtreſſe, doe you thinke they will releeue him, no they will let him lie and break his heart with his owne ſighes, waſh his couch with his owne teares, grinde his teeth into powder, and make himſelfe bread of it to eat, before they will releeue or helpe him, or if by chance they doe releeue any poore man (as it is very ſeldome) they will in a Phareſaicall oſtentation report it to any friend that comes to viſit him.
               I haue ſeene an Embleme, where the picture of Charity held in one hand loaues of bread, diſtributing it to the poore ſtanding round about her, and in the other, a Trumpet to report to the world her beneuolence. Such are theſe Iaylours, that vpon the leaſt taſte of friendſhip or kindneſſe ſhewed to a man, will bee ſure to haue all the people in the houſe know of it, yet theſe curteſies come as ſeldome from them, as virgins out of Pickthatch, or ſound horſes out of Smith-field.
               
               But for one good qualitie they haue ten badde, and

what iniury or wrong ſoeuer they doe a man hee muſt not complaine, a rugged behauiour towards them preuailes not. If a man ruſh through a quicke-ſet hedge in haſt he cannot chuſe but haue his face ſcratcht▪ wheras if hee temperately did diuide the buſhes with his hands he might go through without any hurt: when a poore man comes nigh a churliſh maſtiffe he muſt not ſpurne at him if he meane to goe quietly by him, but flatter and ſtroake him on the backe, and ſpit in his mouth: So muſt Priſoners if they meane not to bee prickt with a Iaylors thorny diſpoſition muſt vſe him gently, or if he will not bee bitten with his curriſh and dogged vſage let him giue faire words and ſometimes if he be able flinge a ſoppe or two into his gaping and all-deuouring iawes.
               They doe as all the world elſe, more for money then merit, for I haue ſeene a fellow come in with ſcarce a ragge on his backe being ſome Cheate or Decoy that hath beene preferred to the Maſterſide, becauſe the Keepers knew they of his trade would fetch him out ſpeedily, and pay all the fees: when on the contrary, I haue knowne a Gentleman of good reputation whoſe behauiour and outward habiliments ſhewed his deſert, clapt vp into a darke roome without any light among halfe a ſcore men, and if there were no ſpare bedde for him to lie on, let him take vp his lodging on the bourds which he muſt pay for before he and they part. Other mens miſeries makes them merry, and the more Priſoners they haue committed the more is their gaine, for I haue often heard them (when my Lord Maiors officers haue brought in Bakers for making their bread an ounce or two too heauy) whiſper in their eares telling them they haue had but a fewe Priſoners that weeke which is an inſtigation to them, to bring as many as they can poſſible; beſides the Booke-keepers, doe not much ſtand vpon it to giue ſometime a pint or a quart

of wine to a Beadle that hee might not forget him the next night following, but wake the watchmen if they ſhould chance to nodde, 
                     •
                  o by that meanes might looſe a night walker.
               Their cruelty is as great as their policy for I haue heard ſince I haue been Priſoner a poore ſicke man, that not halfe an hower before he died cald about midnight for water to quench his thirſt, yet none of theſehard-hearted Keepers would riſe to releiue him, but were deafe to his lamentable and ſad complaints: ſo that the poore ſoule before day tooke his leaue of the world. But what comes all the durt and droſſe to, they thus ſcrath and ſcrape together? moſt commonly to nothing, for what they are getting in three or foure yeere they may looſe in an after noone, ſo that it is as rare to ſee a rich laylor, as a droue of fat Oxen in Spaine; for ſometimes when they go abroad with Priſoners for tweluepence or eighteene pence gaine, may looſe them before they come in again, &amp; ſo are forced to compound with their Creditors. And that I may recreate your ſpirits (too much dull'd I feare with my tedious diſcourſe) I will tell you three or foure pretty trickes, three or foure ſeuerall Priſoners ſerued thoſe Keepers that went abroad with them.
               A poore man hauing beene two or three Winters in the Hole, and along time froſt bitten with calamitie and want, deſiring to free himſelfe becauſe neither his friends nor his cruell aduerſaries would do ſo much for him, came to a Keeper deſiring him to go abroad with him telling him he had a firme hope to make a finall agreement with all his Creditors: for hee was going to a friend of his to receiue ſo much mony (naming the ſumme to him) as would releaſe him: and if hee would take the paines to go out with him he would before hee ſtept one foote out of the gates giue him content: The Keeper that had as excellent a gift in taking money as

any leaking boate hath in taking water, vouchſafed to receiue his fees, and (to be ſhort) wentabroad with him: the beſt part of the day they ſpent in walking vp and downe the City from friend to friend, yet they could not get ſo much as one ſixpenny piece from any: at laſt to prolong the time, the Priſoner deſired the Keeper but to go with him to one friend more, and there hee made no doubt but to ſpeede: well, away they go together, but they found no more mony there then they did at diuers places they had beene at before, ſo that they were comming home againe as emprie of money as they went out: for the Keeper would not ſtay a minute longer when he ſaw there was non Lariohn to bee had, ſo he haſtens his Charge to go a little faſter that they might be at home betimes, nay faith ſaid the Priſoner ſeeing you haue been ſo good as to ſtay out with me ſo long, I deſire you to doe me that honeſt office as to go into a Barbers ſhoppe and ſtay while I am trim'd which I haue not been this twelue-moneth, and to recompence you for your paines I will giue you your ſhauing; the Keeper not refuſing this curteſie thinking to ſaue a groate or ſixpence in his purſe by the bargaine, went with him into the next Barbers ſhoppe they came to, where the Barber after a finnicall congratulation biddes them welcome, and prouides his chaire and his napkins, his combs, and his Sizers, his balls and his ſpunges, and falls firſt about the Priſoners eares: Who being diſpatcht gaue him a teſter and went to the window to put on his band, the Keeper inſtantly vpon his riſing beganne to fall into his roome, and being ſet fell a talking with the Barber about what newes hee heard in the City, but they had not diſcourſed long, but Cutb
                        •
                     rd ſtopt his mouth with a waſhing ball, deſiring him to ſhut hi lippes for feare the ſuddes ſhould come into his mouth, and to cloſe his eyes for hee was trimming him with a ſtinging ball: the Keeper did ſo, now in this

time the Priſoner had made himſelfe ready, ſlipt out of doores, went quite away, and was neuer heard of again. Now the Barber had no ſooner tooke the baſen from the Keepers chinne, and was carrying it to the window but the Keeper admiring hee could not heare his Priſoners tongue walke all this while, opened his eyes (venturing a ſmarting) to ſee whether the Priſoner were in the ſhoppe or no, whom hee no ſooner miſt, but vp he ſtarts, runnes out of doores bearing the Barber ouer and ouer, that came with his raſor in his hand to ſhaue him, and ran into the ſtreetes with the Barbers cloathes about his ſhoulders, with his choppes all white with the froth and ſuddes that hung about them, ſo that he looked like a Boare that foamed at mouth, or a well trauelling horſe, and in this order runnes he madding vp and downe the ſtreete inquiring for his Priſoner, the Barber followes him for his cloathes, and mony for his trimming, while euery man, woman, and childe that met him gaue him way, thinking hee had newly broke out of Bedlam; but my Barber at laſt ouertooke him, laide holde on him, and got his cloaths, and his mony of him before he would let him go: and ſo my Keeper was forced to turne backe to the Compter without his Priſoner, ſo that when all his fellowes heard the conceit they almoſt laught him out of countenance, beſides the plague he was put to in compounding with the Priſoners Aduerſaries.
               But in my conceit the beſt ieſt was of a fellow who was committed to the Compter (for getting a Wench with childe) by a Iuſtice, who ſent this prouiſo to the Keepers, that they ſhould not permit him to go abroad vntill ſuch time hee had put in ſufficient baile to diſcharge the Pariſh of the burthen: Now the wench was not yet deliuered but looked euery hower, in the mean time this fellow made continuall ſuite to go abroade to ſeeke baile, at laſt one of the Booke keepers let him go

to ſome of his friends hauing for his Keeper one of the Meſſengers belonging to the houſe, now the Priſoner being abroad and ſeeing his time and oportunity, moſt nimbly and like an Iriſhfootman betooke himſelfe to his heeles, and ran quite away, I cannot ſay cleane away, for he was in ſuch a fright that a man might haue ſmelt him a furlong; but to conclude, the Meſſenger went home to the Compter as like an Aſſe as he went out, and brought home the ſadde tidings which was as welcome to the Booke-keeper as a Priſoner that had neuer a penny in his purſe. Well to be ſhort, the Pariſh complained of the Keepers negligence, who laide the fault on the Meſſengers head, at laſt it fortuned ſo, that the Wench was brought abedde, but with what in the name of God? by my troth, with two chopping boyes, which the Iuſtice hearing of, to eaſe the Pariſh of ſuch a charge, ſent for the Booke-keeper and the Meſſenger, and made the Booke-keeper keepe one of them, and the Meſſenger the other, and this was their iuſt and righteous doome.
               Thus with my beſt Arte and induſtrie according to my promiſe I haue compiled in as briefe a method as I could the ſtate of the Compters Commonwealth rehearſingCompendium, imò ſuſpendiū. the beſt and chiefeſt ſubiects belonging to it, as ſubtile Citizens, politicke Prodigalls, villanous Sergeants, and officious Conſtables and Beadles which are the foure maine Pillars that ſupport it: then I diſcourſed to you of the nature of the place it ſelfe and the inhabitants, their extortion, and crueltie: I could now relate to you the villany of the Meſſengers, that are members of the ſame body, who inſteed of going to mens friends with letters (which concernes their liberty or reliefe) will ſit drinking in ſome Alehouſe and neglect their buſines, which it may be is a perpetuall vndoing to the poore man. I could diſplay the abuſes of drunken Tapſters that poyſon poore Priſoners with their ſtinking

ſower beere, which they ſell as deare as if it were as good as euer died any noſe in graine: for the moſt wee haue is as you ſee, ſcarce a wine pint for a penny, and they will not ſuffer vs to ſend for it out of doores where wee may haue farre better, and better meaſure, but will breake ſuch bottles our friends ſend in too for our releife, and wil neither truſt vs when we haue no mony, nor ſuffer vs to ſend for it where we may be truſted, but ſerue vs with drinke that the worſt Iaylor among them will ſcorne to taſt of, but when we are all lockt vp into our Wardes will ſend for better out of doores, and will bee drunke when many a poore ſoule is ſo drie that they are readie to choake. I was intreated to haue a 
                     •••
                  ke at the Paperhouſe, which I could not bee wonne to, becauſe I know nothing in their office worthy of diſplaying, for if I ſhould expreſſe more then I know, both the wrong and diſgrace would redound to my ſelfe, therefore if there be any coruption or double dealing among them I will leaue it to their owne conſciences. And thus will I leaue of this diſcourſe, deſiring you if you meane to put theſe obſeruations in print I haue deliuered, not to nominate me, or reueale from whom you haue had this diſcouery.
               Sir (ſaid I) I will be as cloſe as an Aldermans doore at dinnertime, yet good Sir let it not ſeeme tedious or trouble ſome to you, to acquaint mee with one ſecret more, and I ſhall reſt your friend in the higheſt degree of loue and affection, which is that you (though conciſely) would expreſſe to me the nature of the Hole, what place it is, and what gouernment they haue there, for I haue heard much of the authority among themselues. At this hee beganne to ſmile, telling mee hee was one of the chiefeſt in that place, and if it ſhould be knowne that hee reuealed any of them ſecrets, hee ſhould not onely haue a fine put vpon his head, but alſo ſhould be put out of ſhare. I ſeeing his backewardneſſe

drunke a cuppe of ſacke to him, and at laſt (though very loath) hee beganne to mee once more as followeth.
            
            
               
                  CHAP. X. Containing 1. The miſerie of ſuch as liue in the Hole. 2. A reſemblance betweene Ieruſalem and it. 3. An anſwer to certaine obiections. 4. A reſemblance between the Hole, and a well gouern'd Citty. 5. The authoritie of the Steward and the twelue oldeſt Priſoners. 6. Their manner of ſitting in counſell, And laſtly their Iuſtice, Law, and Equitie.
               HE that would ſee the ſtrange miracles of God, let him take ſome long voiage to ſea, and hee that would ſee the miſeries of man let him come into this place the Hole, that ſtinkes many men to death, and is to all that liue in it, as the Dog daies are to the world, a cauſer of diſeaſes, except a few whom I haue ſeene ſo ſtout and tough (ſtinkeproofe, nay plagueproofe I thinke) that no infection could pierce their hearts. Ieruſalem when it was ſackt had not more calamities feeding vpon her heart then this place, and I thinke it was the true Idea and ſhaddow of this loathſome Dungeon we liue in, for as there as pinching famine in Ierujalem, ſo in this place there are many men that for want of ſuſtenance vtterly periſh. In Ieruſalem there was ſickneſſe, ſo in this place a man ſhall not looke about him but ſome poore ſoule or other lies groaning and labouring vnder the burthen of ſome dangerous diſeaſe, the childe weeping ouer his dying Father, the mother ouer her ſicke childe, one friend ouer an other, who can no ſooner riſe from him, but hee is ready to

ſtumble ouer an other in as miſerable a plight as him he but newly tooke his leaue of, ſo that if a man come thither he at firſt will thinke himſelfe in ſome Churchyard that hath beene fatned with ſome great plague, for they lie together like ſo many graues. In Ieruſalem the warres ruined millions of ſoules, ſo in this place the continuall warre that hard hearted Creditors make againſt the liues of their poore debters deſtroy many wretched and moſt miſerable Creatures: and as in Ieruſalem a mother was forced through hunger to eate her owne childe to ſaue her owne life, ſo in this place one man is ready to prey vpon the other, ſo that they walke vp and downe like ſo many Ghoſts for want of food to relieue them. Laſtly in Ieruſalem were inteſtineAnd fighting againſt vs in our owne clothes. ſeditions, ſo here innumerable aſſaults of our homebred friends deſcended from our owne fleſh. But (Sir ſaid I) I haue heard it reported for truth that there are many liuing in that place that go Gentleman-like, haue money continually in their purſes, eate good meate, liue as merrily as the beſt of the houſe, if this be true it cannot chuſe but hinder them from much charity that elſe would be ſent vnto them, for what neede charitable Benefactors ſend them meanes when ſo many of them go ſo neate and hanſome, for it is not giuen them to lay on their backes but to put into their bellies, for in ſuch a place the courſeſt garments are the beſt: againe (they ſay) there is a certaine company of them that take what they liſt themſelues of what reliefe ſoeuer comes in, and the reſt as the pooreſt, haue their leauings, ſo then this is obiected to bee one of the chiefe cauſes that there is ſuch continuall ſickneſſe, pouerty, and famine there: And laſtly, that what meanes or money ſoeuer comes in to them, in the ſpace of an hower after will either in wine, beere, or Tobacco make themſelues drunke for the preſent time, which is the cauſe they faſt a weeke after, therefore good ſir reſolue

me theſe doubts, and I ſhall ceaſe to trouble you any more: He inſtantly condiſcended and thus began to anſwere me.
               Sir (ſaid he) it is granted that there be ſome in this place that go decent and hanſome, but you muſt not be perſwaded that they get it from ſuch charities as are ſent in to them, their owne indeauours and labours procures it them, and it may be ſome of them as they haue liued like Gentlemen abroad, ſo they would bee glad to ſhew themſelues ſtill though they be in priſon: Beſides, their friends ſometimes furniſh them with ſuch neceſſaries as are fit to keepe them cleane, and hanſome. Againe, whereas you ſay that there are ſome of them haue what they liſt, and leaue what they diſlike to the poore, is not to be credited, for there is nothing that comes in but the youngeſt hath as great a ſhare as the eldeſt (I as Maſter Steward himſelfe) therefore whoſoeuer informed you of this, ſpake it out of enuie towards vs, yet wee confeſſe at Eaſter', or Chriſtmas when any good Legacie comes in, it is fitteſt that thoſe Priſoners that haue beene of fiue or ſixe yeeres ſtanding ſhould haue the profit of it before ſuch as haue beene there but two or three moneths, and this breeds a mutiny many times among them, becauſe the youngeſt hath not that priuiledge the eldeſt ought to haue. And laſtly, whereas you alledge how riotous they liue there when they haue mony, may be very well denied: for they haue no money deliuered into their hands, but into the Stewards diſpoſing, who carefully prouides them ſuch neceſſaries as they want, onely at Chriſtmas and Eaſter or ſuch times when the liberality of the Cittie is more ample then at any other time of the yeere elſe, they (though vnwillingly) may fall into ſome error being kept from a full diet ſo long time as many of them are And now Sir I hope I haue cleered your doubts, therefore now I will proceede to

the gouernment of the place.
               This little Hole is as a little Citty in a Commonwealth, for as in a Citty there are all kinde of Officers trades and vocations, ſo there is in this place, as we may make a pretty reſemblance betweene them. In ſteede of a Lord Maior we haue a Maſter Steward to ouer-ſee and correct all ſuch miſdemeanours as ſhall ariſe, hee is a very vpright man in his dealings though he ſtoope in his body, but the weight of the office he beares is the cauſe he bends, which is a great ſigne of humilitie. And as the Cittie hath twelue Companies that exceede all the reſt for authoritie, antiquitie, and riches; ſo hath this place twelue old Priſoners that helpe the Steward in his proceedings, who by the generall voice of the houſe rule and beare ſway ouer all the reſt; and heere as in a Cittie is Diuine ſeruice ſaid euery euening, and morning; heere as in a Citty is a commanding Conſtable, that vpon any miſdemeanours offered by any man either to the Steward, or the Twelue ſhall bee brauely mounted and haue ten pounds with a purſe, that the print of their iuſtice ſhall ſticke vpon his buttockes foure and twenty howers after. And laſtly as in a Citty there is all kindes of Trades, ſo is there heere, for heere you ſhall ſee a Cobler ſitting mending olde ſhowes, and ſinging as merrily as if hee were vnder a ſtall abroad; not farre from him you ſhall ſee a Taylor ſit croſſe-legged (like a Witch) on his cuſhion, threatning the ruine of our fellow Priſoners the Aegyptian vermine: In an other place you may behold a Sadler empannelling all his wits together how to patch this Scotchpadde hanſomely, or mend the olde Gentlewomans Crooper that was almoſt burſt in pieces: You may haue a Phiſition here that for a pottle of ſack will vndertake to giue you as good a medicine for melancholly as any Doctour will for fiue pound, and make you purge vpward and downeward as well as if you

had taken downe into your guts all the drugges in Lothbury. Beſides if you deſire to bee remoued before a Iudge you ſhall haue a Tinker-like Atturney not farre diſtant from you, that in ſtopping vp one Hole in a broken cauſe will make twenty before hee hath made an end, and at laſt will leaue you in priſon as bare of mony as he himſelfe is of honeſty: Heere is your Cholericke Cooke that will dreſſe our meate when wee can get any as well as any greaſie Scullion in Fleetlane or Pyecorner. And twentie more then theſe there are, which for breuitie ſake I will leaue out, becauſe I would diſcourſe vnto you the maieſtie and ſtate of theſe Officers, when euery Saterday at night they ſit in counſell about their affaires, and thus it is.
               About the time that Bowbell ſummons the toaſt and butter Eaters to ſhut vp their ſhoppes, the Councell beginne to flocke together, and then the youngeſt man of the Twelue prouides a broome and makes the little cockeloft as cleane as any Cittizens wiues chamber in the Towne, then ſpreads a greene carpet on the board not much bigger then a Horſes ſaddle-cloath iuſt before the place the Steward ſits in, and then takes three or foure ſtoopes in his hands and trudges downe to the Cellar, calling for the beſt liquor, telling Froath the Tapſter that it is for Maſter Steward and the reſt of his brethren, who giues them of the beſt becauſe they are his beſt Cuſtomers: when he hath his full load of drink I meane his armes and not his head full, away he goes to the Councell-chamber not forgetting to carry with him halfe a dozen papers of Tobacco: Hauing aſcended the Ladder in a moſt comely order hee places the Canns on the Table, and fills halfe a ſcore pipes of Tobacco, thus hauing all things in readineſſe he requeſts the Steward and the reſt of the Twelue to comevp, who being aſcended beginne to ſucke out the braines of the barrells to adde to their owne, and light the

pipes and let them go merrily round. The reaſon that they drinke ſo much before they determine of any thing, is this, that they may the eaſier caſt vp their reckonings; and why they drinke ſo much Tobacco, is, that if any man be brought before them for any abuſe committed, they might ſmoake him ſoundly. When they haue deuoured all their drinke, and Trinidado, they ſift and boult out what expences they haue beene at that weeke, what pepper, ſalt, vineger, faggots, and candles they haue ſpent, how many dozen of bread, ſheepes gathers, and barrells of foureſhillings beere they haue had brought in that weeke. This buſineſſe of moment diſpatched, the youngeſt of the priuie Councell calls vp all ſuch as haue had wrong done them any time that weeke, and preferres their bills of complaint vp to the whole body of the Councell, or elſe are permitted to relate, but with all modeſty and deliberation, the nature of the offence, and ſo producing their witneſſes, ſhall without all partiality haue the Law paſſe vpon the Offender, who muſt either fine for the fault, or if he be not worth ſo much, will make his poſteriours pay for it. If any man be knowne to be a common Drunkard he ſhall, if he be able, fine for it, or elſe his puniſhment ſhall be to go a dry while he can get mony to quench his thirſt, or elſe muſt either drink water, or choake. If any man ſteale any of his fellowes meate▪ if it be knowne he ſhall fine for it, but if hee be not able, the Twelue will take ſuch order with him that hee gets not a penny loafe three daies after. Whoſoeuer forſweares himſelfe if hee be able, hee ſhall fine for it, if hee be not▪ ſhall go and be damn'd as long as hee ſtayes in the houſe, and neuer haue ſo much credit as runne one penny on the Tapſters ſcore.
               Againe if they chance to fall together by the eares themſelues about any thing they enact, ſo that they beat the Canns about each others eares, they will not

long beare enuie in their hearts, but at the approach of the other halfe doſen quench that fire of debate, drinke a health to ſome of their beſt Benefactours, ſhake hands, be ſworne friends, breake vp Councell for that night, and go to their beddes (if they haue any.)
               Thus haue I beguiled the time, and I feare my ſelfe, in relating to you the true nature of the Hole, the miſerie of it; my defence to the ſlanderous obiections, and the authoritie and iuſtice of the Steward and the Twelue, therefore I will touch one point more and draw to a concluſion. But as hee was going forward in his diſcourſe the Bell of the Maſter-ſide range to dinner, and by this meanes wee were both called vp; ſo I promiſed him ſecreſie as hee intreated mee, made an end of our ſacke, put a ſmall token of my loue into his hand, ſo he went to his Hole, and I to my Ward, but I no ſooner was entered into my chamber, but with all expedition I tooke penne, inke, and paper, writing what I could remember of his diſcourſe, which I haue made bold to publiſh to the world, hoping that thoſe that read it will not thinke a miſſe of mee for ſetting it foorth, for I doubt not but if it be ſeriouſly peruſed, it will giue true content to them. So remembring my beſt loue and ſeruice to all thoſe that affect me, and my willing labours, I reſt theirs to bee commanded, and remaine their poore and then impriſoned friend▪
               
               
                  William Fennor.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

