
   
      
         
            Fuimus Troes Æneid. 2. The true Troianes, being a story of the Britaines valour at the Romanes first inuasion: Publikely represented by the gentlemen students of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford.
            Fisher, Jasper, b. 1591.
         
         
            
               1633
            
         
         Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00760
            STC 10886
            ESTC S102088
            99837888
            99837888
            2235
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00760)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2235)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 797:08)
         
         
            
               
                  Fuimus Troes Æneid. 2. The true Troianes, being a story of the Britaines valour at the Romanes first inuasion: Publikely represented by the gentlemen students of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford.
                  Fisher, Jasper, b. 1591.
               
               [72] p.   
               
                  Printed by I[ohn] L[egatt] for Robert Allot, and are to be sold at the signe of the Beare in Pauls-Churchyard,
                  London :
                  1633.
               
               
                  By Jasper Fisher.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-I⁴.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            FVIMVS TROES Aeneid. 2. THE TRVE TROIANES, Being A Story of the Britaines valour at the Romanes first invasion: Publikely represented by the Gentlemen Students of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford.
            
               Quis Martem tunicâ tectum adamantinâ
               Dignè scripserit?
            
            
               LONDON, Printed by I. L. for Robert Allot, and are to be sold at the signe of the Beare in Pauls-Churchyard, 1633.
         
         
            
            Dramatis Personae.
            
               
                  
                     
                        Livius, lib. 5.
                        
                     
                     Mercurie. 
                     Fur. Camillus. 
                     Brennus. 
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                         Caesar com. de bell. gall. lib. 4. &amp; 5.
                        
                     
                     Iulius Caesar.
                     C. Volusenus. 
                     Q. Laberius, aliàs Labienus. 
                     Q. Atrius.
                     Comius Atrebas. 
                     Cassibellaunus Imperator Britannorum.
                     Mandubratius, princeps Trinobantum. 
                     
                        
                           
                              4. Petty Kings in Kent.
                           Cingetorix. 
                           Carvilius. 
                           Taximagulus. 
                           Segonax.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                        Galfrid. Monu: metensis. lib. 4.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                           Beli maur, his sonnes,
                           
                              
                                 Lud, his sonnes. 
                                  Androgeus. 
                                 Themantius. 
                              
                           
                            Cassibelane. 
                            Nennius. 
                        
                     
                     Belinus, a chiefe Nobleman. 
                     Hirildas, nephew to Cassibelane. 
                     Eulinus, nephew to Androgeus. 
                     Cridous King of Albania. 
                     Britael King of Demetia. 
                     Guerthed, King of Ordouicia. 
                  
               
            
            
               Names fained.
               
                  
                      Two Druids, or Priests.
                     Lantonus.
                     Hulacus. 
                  
               
               
                  
                     Two Ladyes mentioned.
                     Landora. 
                     Cordella.
                  
               
               Rollano, a Belgicke.
               Chorus of fiue Bardes, or Poets laureate.
               Souldiers.
               Shipmen.
               Seruants.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            Mercury, conducting the Ghosts of Brennus and Camillus, in compleate armour, and with swords drawne.
            
               
                  MEr.
               As in the vaults of this big-bellied earth,
               Are dungeons, whips, and flames, for wicked Ghosts;
               So faire Elysian fieldes; where spotlesse soules
               Doe bathe themselues in blisse. Among the rest,
               Two pleasant Groues by two sorts are possest:
               One by true Louers crown'd with myrtle boughes,
               Who hand in hand sing Paeans of their ioy:
               Braue Souldiers hold the second, clad in steele,
               Whose glittering Armes brighten those gloomy shades,
               In lieu of Starry lights. From hence I bring
               A paire of Martiall Impes, By Ioues decree,
               As sticklers in their Nations enmity.
               Furious Camillus, and thou Britaine bold
               Great Brennus, sheath your conquering blades: In vaine
               You threaten death: For Ghosts may not be slaine.
            
            
               Brenn.
               From the vnbounded Ocean, and cold climes,
               Where Charles his wayne circles the Northerne Pole:
               I first lead out great swarmes of shaggy Gaules,
               And big-bon'd Britaines. The white-pated Alpes,
               Where snow and winter dwell, did bow their neckes
               To our victorious feete: Rome, proudest Rome,
               We cloath'd in skarlet of patrician blood,
               And 'bout your Capitoll prauns'd our vaunting steedes,
               Defended more by Geese, than by your gods.
            
            
               Cam.
               But I cut short your fury, and my sword
               Redeem'd the City, making your huge vast trunkes
               To fat our Crowes, and dung our Latian fields:
               I turn'd your Torrent to another Coast:
               And what you quickly woone, you sooner lost.
            
            
               
               Mer.
               Leaue these weake brawlings. Now swift time hath spent
               A Pylian age, and more, since you two breathed,
               Mirrours of Britaine, and of Roman valour.
               Loe, now the blacke Emperiall Bird doth claspe
               Vnder her winges the Continent, and Mars
               Trampling downe nations with his brazen wheeles,
               Fights for his Nephewes, and hath once more made
               Britaines and Romanes meete. To view these deedes
               I Hermes bring you to this vpper skie;
               Where you may wander, and with gastly lookes
               Incite your Country-men, when night and sleepe
               Conquer the eyes, when weary bodyes rest,
               And senses cease: Be Furies in their brest.
               Neuer two Nations better matcht. For Iove
               Loues both alike: whence then these armed Bandes?
               Mavors for Rome, Neptune for Albion stands.
            
            
               Brenn.
               Then let warre ope his iawes, as wide as hell,
               And fright young babes, my Country-folke more sterne
               Can out-looke Gorgon: Let the Fates transpos'd
               Hang beaten Flags vp in the victours land:
               Full dearely will each Pase of ground be sold,
               Which rated is at deerest Blood, not Gold.
               What, are their ruin'd Fanes, demolisht Walles
               So soone forgot? Doth Allia yet runne cleare?
               Or can three hundred Summers slake their feare?
            
            
               Cam.
               Arise thou Iulian Starre, whose angry beames
               Be Heraulds to the North, of warre, and death.
               Let those blacke Calends be reueng'd; Those Ghosts,
               (Whose mangled sheaths depriv'd of Funerall rites,
               Made the Sixe hils promise a Cadmus croppe:)
               Be expiated with a fiery deluge.
               Iove rules the Spheares, Rome all the world beside:
               And shall this little corner be denide?
            
            
               Merc.
               Bandy no more these priuate Frownes; but hast,
               Fly to your parties, and inrage their mindes:
               Till at the period of these Broyles, I call,
               And backe reduce you to grimme Pluto's hall.
            
            Exeunt.
            
               
               
                  Act. 1.
               
                  
                     Scen. 1.
                  Duke Nennius, alone.
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Me thinkes I heare Bellona's dreadfull voyce
                     Redoubled from the concave shoares of Gaule:
                     Me thinkes I heare their neighing Steedes, The groanes
                     Of complementall Soules, taking their leaue:
                     And all the dinne and clamorous route, which soundes
                     When falling Kingdomes cracke in fatall flames.
                     Dye Belgickes, Dye like men. Free mindes need have
                     Nought, but the ground they fight on, for their graue:
                     And we are next. Thinke ye the smoaky mist
                     Of Sunne-boyld Seas can stop the Eagles eye?
                     Or can our watry walles keepe dangers out,
                     Which flye aloft? That thus we snorting lye,
                     Feeding impostum'd humours, to be launch'd
                     By some out-landish Surgion:
                     As they are now: whose flaming townes, like Beacons,
                     Giue vs faire warning, and euen guild our Spyres,
                     Whilst merrily we warme vs at their Fires.
                     Yet we are next: who charm'd with peace and floath,
                     Dreame golden dreames. Goe, warlike Britaine, goe,
                     For Olive bough exchange thy Hazell bow:
                     Hang vp thy rusty Helmet, that the Bee
                     May haue a hive, or Spider find a Loome:
                     In steed of souldiers fare, and lodging hard,
                     (The bare ground being their bed, and table) lye
                     Smother'd in doune, melting in luxury.
                     In steed of bellowing drumme, and chearefull flute,
                     Be lull'd in Ladyes lap with amorous Lute.
                     But as for Nennius, know, I scorne this calme:
                     The ruddy Planet at my birth bore sway,
                     Sanguine adust my humour; and wild fire,
                     My ruling Element. Blood, and rage, and choller,
                     Make vp the Temper of a Captaines valour.
                  
                  Exit.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 1. Scen. 2.
                  Iulius Caesar. Comius. Volusenus. Laberius. Souldiers. with Ensigne, A two-neck'd Eagle displayed sable, Drumme, Ancient, Trumpet. A Florish.
                  
                     Caes.
                     Welcome thus farre, Partners of weale and woe,
                     Welcome braue bloods: Now may our weapons sleep,
                     Since Ariovist in cocke-boate basely flies:
                     Vast Germany stands trembling at our bridge:
                     And Gaule lies bleeding in her mothers lap.
                     Once the Pellaean Duke did Eastward march,
                     To rowse the drowsie Sunne, before he rose
                     Adorn'd with Indian rubyes: But the Mayne
                     Bad him retire. He was my Type. This day,
                     We stand on Natures westerne brinke; Beyond,
                     Nothing but Sea and Skie. Heere is Nil vltra.
                     
                     Democritus make good thy fancy, giue me
                     More worlds to conquer, which may be both seene,
                     And wonne together. But me thinkes I kenne
                     A whitish cloud kissing the waues, or else
                     Some chaulky rockes surmount the barking flood.
                     
                        Comius, your knowledge can correct our eyes.
                  
                  
                     Com.
                     It is the Britaine shoare, which ten leagues hence
                     Displaies her shining clifts vnto your sight.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     I'le hit the white. That Sea-marke for our Shippes,
                     Invites destruction, and giues to our eye
                     A treacherous Becko. Dare but resist: your shoare
                     Shall paint her pale face with red crimson goare.
                  
                  
                     Com.
                     Thus much I know, Great Caesar, that they lent
                     Their secret ayde vnto the neighbour Gaules;
                     Fostering their fugitiues with friendly care:
                     Which made your victory flye with slower wing.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     That's cause enough. They shall not henceforth range
                     Abroad for Warre, Wee'l bring Him to their doores:
                     His vgly Idoll shall displace their gods,
                     Their deare Penates, and in desolate streetes
                     
                        Raise trophees high of barbarous bones, whose stench
                     May poyson all the rest. I long to stride
                     This Hellespont, or bridge it with a Navy,
                     Disclosing to our Empire vnknowne Landes,
                     Vntill the Arcticke Starre for Zenith stands.
                  
                  
                     Laber.
                     Then raise the Campe, and strike a dreadfull March,
                     And vnawares poure vengeance on their heads:
                     Be like the winged Bolt of angry Iove.
                     Or chiding Torrent, whose late-risen streame
                     From mountaines bended toppe runnes raging downe,
                     Deflouring all the virgin dales.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     First let's advise; For soone to ruine come
                     Rash weapons, which lacke counsell graue at home.
                  
                  
                     Laber.
                     What need consulting, where the Cause is plaine?
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     The likeliest Cause without regard proues vaine.
                  
                  
                     Laber.
                     Provide for Battaile, but of Truce of word.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Where peace is first refus'd, should come the sword.
                  
                  
                     Laber.
                     But tis vnlike, their selfe-presuming might
                     Will curbed be with termes of Ciuill Right.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Tis true: yet so, we stop the peoples cry,
                     When we propose, and they doe peace deny.
                     Wee'l therefore wise Embassadours dispatch,
                     Parents of Loue, the Harbingers of Leagues,
                     Men that may speake with mildnesse mixt with courage,
                     Hauing quicke feete, broad eyes, short tongues, long eares;
                     To warne the Brittish Court.
                     And further view the Ports, faddome the Seas,
                     Learne their complotments; where Invasion may
                     Be soonest intertaind. All this shall lye
                     On Volusene, a Legate, and a Spy.
                  
                  
                     Volus.
                     My care and quicknesse shall deserue this kindnesse.
                     Meane time vnite, and range your scattered troupes.
                     Imbarke your Legions at the Iccian shoare,
                     And teach Erynnis swimme, which crawl'd before.
                  
                  Exeunt.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 1. Scen. 3.
                  Cassibelane, Androgeus, Themantius, Belinus, Attendants.
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Although the peoples voyce constraines me hold
                     This Regall staffe, whose massie waight would bruise
                     Your age and pleasures: yet this, Nephewes, know:
                     Your trouble lesse, your honour is the same,
                     As if you wore the Diademe of this Ile.
                     Meane while Androgeus hold vnto your vse
                     Our Lady-City Troynovant, and all
                     The Toll and Tribute of delicious Kent;
                     Of which each Quarter can maintaine a King.
                     Haue you, Themantius, Cornewalles Dukedome large,
                     Both rich and strong, in mettalles and in men.
                     I must to Verulams fenced towne repaire,
                     And as Protectour for the whole take care.
                  
                  
                     Androg.
                     My heart agrees. Henceforth ye Soveraigne cares,
                     State-mysteries, false graces, iealous feares,
                     The Linings of a Crowne, forsake my Braine:
                     These Territories neither are too wide,
                     To trouble my content; nor yet too narrow,
                     To feed a Princely traine.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     All thankes I render: your will shall guide ours,
                     With treble-twisted loue wee'l striue to make
                     One Soule informe three Bodyes, keeping still
                     The same affections both in good and ill.
                     Now am I for a hunting match. You thickets
                     Shelter a Boare, which spoyles the plough-mans hope:
                     Whose iawes with double sword, whose backe is armd
                     With bristled Pykes; whose fume inflames the ayre,
                     And fome be-snowes the trampled Corne. This Beast
                     I long to see come smoaking to a feast.
Exit. Themant.
                     
                  
                  Enter Rollano.
                  
                     Belin.
                     Heere comes my Belgicke friend, Landoraes seruant:
                     What newes, Rollano, that thy feet so striue
                     
                        To haue precedence of each other? Speake,
                     I read disturbed passions on thy brow.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     My trembling hart quauers vpon my tongue,
                     That scarce I can with broken sounds vent forth
                     These sad, strange, sudden, dreary, dismall newes.
                     A Merchants ship arriu'd tells, how the Romane
                     Hauing run Gaule quite through with bloody armes,
                     Prepares for you: His nauy rigg'd in bay,
                     Onely expects a gale: Farther, they say,
                     A pinnace landed, from him brings command,
                     Either to loose your freedome, or your land.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     And dares proud Caesar backe our vn-tam'd surges?
                     Dreads he not our Sea-monsters? whose wild shapes
                     Their Theaters neere yet in Picture saw.
                     Come Sirs, To armes, To armes: Let speedy poasts
                     Summon our petty Kings, and muster vp
                     Our valourous nations from the North, and West.
                     
                        Androgeus hast you to the Scots and Pictes,
                     Two Names, which now Albaniaes kingdome share:
                     Entreat their aide, if not for loue, yet feare:
                     For new foes should imprint swift-equall feare
                     Through all the arteries of our Ile.
                     
                        Belinus, thy authority must rouse
                     The vulgar troopes within my speciall charge,
                     Fire the Beacons, strike alarums loud,
                     Raise all the countrey gainst this common Foe:
                     Wee'l soone confront him in his full careere;
                     This newes more moues my choller, then my feare.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
                  Rollano, alone.
                  
                     Roll.
                     I am by birth a Belgicke, whence I fled
                     To Germany, for feare of Romane Armes:
                     But when their bridge brideled the stately Rhine,
                     I soone returnd, And thought to hide my head
                     In this soft Halcyons neast, this Britaine Ile.
                     But now, behold, Mars is a nursing heere,
                     And gins to speake aloud.
                     
                        Is no nooke safe from Rome? doe they still haunt me?
                     Some peacefull God transport me through the ayre,
                     Beyond cold Thule, or the Sunnes Bed-chamber,
                     Where only Swine or Goates doe liue and raigne.
                     Yet these may fight. Place me, where quiet Peace
                     Hushes all stormes, where sleepe and silence dwell,
                     Where neuer man nor beast did wrong the soyle,
                     Or cropp the First-fruites, Or made so much noyse
                     As with their breath. But foolish thoughts adieu:
                     Now catch I must, or stand, or fall with you.
Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 1. Scen. 4.
                  Eulinus, Hirildas.
                  
                     Eul.
                     The Court a wardrobe is of liuing shapes:
                     And Ladies are the tissue-spangled suites,
                     Which Nature weares on festiuall high dayes.
                     The Court a Spring, each Madame is a Rose.
                     The Court is Heauen, faire Ladies are the Starres.
                  
                  
                     Hiril.
                     I, falling Starres.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     False Eccho, don't blaspheme that glorious sexe,
                     Whose beautious raies can strike rash gazers blind.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Loue should be blind.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Pray, leaue this Cynicke humour, whilst I sigh
                     My Mistresse praise: Her beauty's past compare:
                     O would she were more kind, or not so faire.
                     Her modest smiles both curb and kindle loue:
                     The Court is darke without her; when Shee rises,
                     The morning is her hand-maid, strewing roses
                     About loues Hemispheare: The lampes aboue
                     Eclipse themselues for shame, To see her eies
                     Out-shine their Chrysolites, and more blesse the skies,
                     Than they the Earth —
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Giue me her Name.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Her body is a Chrystall cage, whose pure
                     
                        Transparent mould not of grosse elements
                     Compacted, but the extracted Quintessence
                     Of sweetest formes distill'd: where Graces bright
                     Doe liue immur'd, but not exempt from sight. —
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     I prethee speake her.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Her modell is beyond all Poets braynes,
                     And Painters pencells: All the liuely Nymphes,
                     Syrens, and Dryads, are but kitchin-maydes,
                     If you compare. To frame the like Pandore,
                     The Gods repine, and Nature would grow poore.—
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     By Loue, who ist? hath she no mortall Name?
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     For heere you find great Iunoes stately front,
                     Palla's gray eie, Venus her dimpled chinne,
                     Auroraes rosie fingers, the small wast
                     Of Ceres daughter, and Medusaes haire,
                     Before it hist:—
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     O Loue, as deafe, as thou art blind! Good Eulinus
                     
                     Call home thy soule, and tell thy Mistresse name.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     O strange! what ignorant still? when as so plainely
                     These Attributes describe her: why? She is
                     A Rhapsody of Goddesses. The Elyxar
                     Of all their seuerall perfections. She is
                     (Now blesse your eares) by mortals called Landora.
                     
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     What: Landora the Trinobanticke Lady?
                     How grow your hopes, what mettall is her breast?
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     All steele and adamant. Tis beauties pride, To staine
                     Her lilly white with blood of Louers slaine.
                     Their groanes make musick, and their scalding sighes
                     Raise a perfume, and vulture-like she gnawes
                     Their bleeding hearts. No gifts, no learned flattery,
                     No stratagems can worke Landoraes battery.
                     As a tall Rocke maintaines maiesticke state,
                     Though Boreas gallop on the tottering seas,
                     And tilting split his froath out spurging waues
                     Vpon his surly breast: So she resists:
                     And all my proiects on her cruell hart,
                     Are but retorted to their Authors smart.
                  
                  
                     
                     Hir.
                     Why then, let scorne succeed thy loue, and brauely
                     Conquer thy selfe, If thou wilt conquer her:
                     Stomackes, with kindnesse cloy'd, Disdaine must stirre.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Most impious thoughts! O let me rather perish,
                     And louing die, than liuing cease to loue:
                     And when I faint, let her but heare me cry,
                     Aye me, there's none, which truely loues, but I.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     O ye crosse darts of Cupid! this very Ladie,
                     This Lady-waspe woes me, as thou dost her,
                     With glaunces, iewells, bracelets of her haire,
                     Lasciuious banquets, and most eloquent eies:
                     All which my heart misse-consters as immodest,
                     It being pointed for another Pole.
                     But hence learne courage, Coosse; why stand you dumbe?
                     Women are women, and may be ore-come.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Your words are eare-awigges to my vexed braine
                     Like henn-bane iuice, or Aconite diffus'd
                     They strike me senselesse.
                     My kinsman, and Hirildas to my end:
                     But I'le neere call you Counsellor, or Friend Adieu.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Stay, stay. For now I meane with gentler breath.
                     To waft you to your happy landing place.
                     Seeing this Crocodile pursues me flying,
                     Flyes you pursuing: wee'l catch her by a tricke:
                     With promise fain'd, I'le' point a Cupids stage,
                     But in the night, and secret, and disguizd:
                     Where thou, which art my selfe, shalt act my part;
                     In Venus games, all Coosning goes for Art.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Blest be these meanes, and happy the Successe.
                     Now gin I reare my creast aboue the Moone,
                     And in those guilded bookes read Leactures of
                     The Faeminine Sexe. There moues Cassiope,
                     Whose garments shine with thirteene pretious stones,
                     Types of as many vertues: Then her Daughter,
                     Whose Beauty without Perseus would haue tam'd
                     The monstrous Fish, glides with a Starry Crowne:
                     Then Iust Asttea kembes her golden haire:
                     
                        And my Landora can become the skies,
                     As well as They. Oh, how my ioyes doe swell!
                     He mounted not more proud, whose burning Throne
                     Kindled the Cedar-toppes, and quafft whole fountaines.
                     Flye then, ye winged houres, as swift as thought,
                     Or my desires: Let dayes bright Waggoner
                     Fall headlong, and lye buried in the deepe,
                     And dor-mouse-like Alcides night out-sleep.
                     Good Tethys, quench his Beames, that He nere rise,
                     To scorch the Moores, to sucke vp hony-dewes,
                     Or to betray my person.
                     But prethee tell, What Mistresse you adore?
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     The kind Cordella, Louing, and Belou'd:
                     Onely some iarre of late about a Fauour
                     Made me inueigh gainst women. Come, away,
                     Our plottes desire the night, not babbling day.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     We must giue way: Here come our reuerend Barde
                     To sing in Synode, as their Custome is,
                     With former chance comparing present deedes.
                  
                  Exeunt.
               
               
                  
                     Act. 1. Scen. 5.
                  Chorus of fiue Bardes laureate, foure voyces, and an Harper: Attired.
                  
                     1. Song.
                     
                     
                        1.
                        At the Spring
                        Birdes doe sing:
                        Now with high,
                        Then low cry:
                     
                     
                        Flat, acute;
                        And salute,
                        The Sunne borne,
                        Euery morne.
                     
                     
                        
                           All.
Hees no Bard that cannot sing:
                        The praises of the flowry Spring.
                     
                     
                        2.
                        Flora Queene
                        All in greene,
                        doth delight
                        To paint white,
                     
                     
                        3.
                        Woods renew
                        Hunters hue.
                        Shepheards gray
                        Crownd with bay,
                     
                     
                        
                        And to spred
                        Cruell redd,
                        With a blew,
                        Colour true.
                        
                           All. Hees no bard, &amp;c.
                     
                     
                        With his pipe
                        Care doth wipe,
                        Till he dreame
                        By the streame.
                        
                           All. Hees no bard, &amp;c.
                     
                     
                        4.
                        Faithfull loues,
                        Turtle Doues,
                        Sit and bill,
                        On a bill.
                        Country Swaynes
                        On the plaines,
                        Runne and leape,
                        Turne and skip.
                        
                           All. Hees no bard, &amp;c.
                     
                     
                        5.
                        Pan doth play
                        Care-away.
                        Fayries small
                        Two foote tall,
                        With caps red
                        On their head
                        Daunce around
                        On the ground.
                        
                           All. Hees no bard,
                     
                     
                        6.
                        Phyllis bright
                        Cloath in white,
                        With necke faire,
                        Yellow haire:
                     
                     
                        Rockes doth moue
                        With her loue,
                        And make mild,
                        Tygers wild.
                     
                     
                        
                           All. Hees no bard that cannot sing,
                        The praises of the flowry spring.
                     
                  
                  
                     2. Song.
                     
                     
                        Thus spend we time in laughter,
                        While peace and spring doe smile:
                        But I heare a sound of slaughter,
                        Draw neerer to our Ile.
                     
                     
                        Leaue then your wonted prattle,
                        The Oaten reed forbeare:
                        For I heare a sound of battell,
                        And Trumpets teare the ayre,
                     
                     
                        Let bag-pipes dye for want of wind,
                        Let Crowd and Harpe be dumbe;
                        Let little Taber come behind:
                        For I heare the dreadfull drumme.
                     
                     
                        
                        Let no Birds sing, no Lambkins daunce,
                        No fountaines murmuring goe:
                        Let Shepheards crooke be made a launce:
                        For the martiall hornes doe blow.
Exeunt.
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  Act. 2.
               
                  
                     Scen. 1.
                  Cassibelane, Cridous, Britael, Guerted, Nennius, Belinus, Eulinus. Volusene following.
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Heauens fauour Cridous faire Albaniaes King:
                     And Britael deckt with the Demetian Crowne:
                     The same to famous Guerted, whose command
                     Embraces woody Ordovickes blacke Hilles.
                     Legate, you may your message now declare.
                  
                  
                     Volus.
                     By me great Caesar greetes the Britaine state:
                     This letter speakes the rest.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Then read the rest.
                  
                  
                     Volus.
                     Caesar Proconsul of Gallia to Cassibelane King of Britaine.
                     Since Romulus race by will of Ioue,
                     Haue stretcht their Empire wide:
                     From Danowes bankes by Tygris swift,
                     Vnto mount Atlas side:
                     And Provinces and Nations strong.
                     With homage due obey.
                     We wish that you hid in the Sea,
                     Doe likewise tribute pay.
                     Submitting all vnto our willes,
                     For rashly aiding Gaule:
                     And noble Laddes for hostages
                     Make ready at our call.
                     These graunted may our Friendship gaine:
                     Denied shall worke your woe:
                     Now take your choise, whether you'de find
                     Rome, as a Friend, or Foe.
                  
                  
                     
                     Cassib.
                     Bold mandates are vnwelcome to free Princes.
                     Legate withdraw; you shall be soone dispatch'd.
Exit. Volus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Crid.
                     He writes more like a Victour, than a Foe;
                     Whose greatnesse risen from subdued nations,
                     Is fastned onely with feare's slippery knot.
                     Nor can they fight so feirce, for wealth or fame,
                     As we for natiue liberty. With answer rough
                     Bid him defiance. So thinkes Cridous.
                     
                  
                  
                     Guert.
                     
                        Guerted maintaines the same, and on their flesh
                     I'le write my answer in red Characters.
                  
                  
                     Brit.
                     Thou Rauenous woolfe, Imperious monster Rome,
                     Seuen-headed Hydra; know, we scorne thy threates:
                     We can oppose thy hils with mounts as high;
                     And scourge vsurpers with like cruelty.
                     And thus thinkes Britael.
                     
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Let Caesar come: Our land doth rust with ease,
                     And wants an obiect, whose resisting power
                     May strike out valarous flashes from her veines.
                     So shadowes giue a Picture life. So flames
                     Grow brighter by a fanning blast. Nor thinke,
                     I am a Courtier, and no Warriour borne:
                     Nor Loue-Obiect: For well my Poet saies,
                     
                        Militat omnis Amans, Each Louer is a Souldier;
                     I can ioyne Cupids bow, and Mars his Launce.
                     A pewter-coate fits me, as well as silke.
                     It grieues me see, Our Martiall spirits trace
                     The idle streetes, while weapons by their side
                     Dangle and lash their backes, as t'were to vpbraid
                     Their needlesse vse. Nor is it glory small,
                     They set vpon vs last, when their proud Armes
                     Fadome the Land and Seas, and reach both Poles.
                     On then, So great a Foe, so good a cause,
                     Shall make our name more famous. So thinkes Eulinus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Then Friends and Princes on this Blade take oath:
                     First to your Country, to reuenge her wrongs:
                     And next to me, as Generall, to be lead
                     With vnity and courage.
they kisse the sword.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     All.
                     The gods blesse Britaine, and Cassibelane.
                     
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Now royall friends, the Heires of mighty Brute:
                     You see, what storme hangs houering ore this land,
                     Ready to poure downe cataclysmes of blood;
                     Let antient glory then inflame your hearts:
                     Beyond the craggy hilles of grim-fac'd death,
                     Bright honour keepes triumphant Court, and deedes
                     Of martiall men liue there in marble rolles.
                     Death is but Charon to the Fortunate Iles:
                     Porter to Fame.
                     What though the Romane arm'd with forraine spoyle,
                     Behind him lead the conquered world, and hope
                     To sinke our Iland with his Armies waight:
                     Yet we haue gods, and men, and horse, to fight:
                     And we can brauely die. But our iust cause,
                     Your forward loues, and all our people edg'de
                     With Dardane spirit, and the powerfull name
                     Of Country; Bid vs hope for victory.
                     We haue a world within our selues, whose breast
                     No Forainer hath vn-revenged prest
                     These thousand yeeres. Though Rhine and Rhoane can serue,
                     And enuie Thames his neuer captiue streame:
                     Yet mauger all. If we our selues are true,
                     We may despise, what all the earth can doe.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Lets then dismisse the Legate with a frowne:
                     And draw our forces toward the Sea, to ioyne
                     With the foure Kings of Kent, and so affront
                     His first arriuall. But before all, let
                     Our Priests and Druids in their hallowed groues
                     Propitiate the gods, and scanne events
                     By their mysterious Artes.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 2. Scen. 2.
                  Eulinus. Hirildas. Rollano.
                  
                     Hir.
                     Well, so: your tongue's your own, though drunk or angry.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Vmh.
seales his mouth.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Hir.
                     Speake not a word vpon your life: Be dumbe.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Vmh.
gives him money.
                     
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     I'le winch vp thy estate. Be Harpocrates.
                     
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Vmh.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Thy fortunes shall be double-guilt. Be midnight.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Vmh.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     An excellent instrument to be the Bawd
                     To his deare Lady. — But Rollano, harke:
                     What words, what looks did giue my letter wellcome?
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Vmh.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Nay, now thy silence is ante-dated. Speake.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Vmh.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     I giue thee leaue, I say. Speake, Be not foolish.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Then—with your leaue: She vs'd vpon receipt
                     No words, but silent ioy purpell'd her face,
                     And seeing your Name, strait clapt it to her heart,
                     To print there a New Copy: As shee'd say,
                     The words went by her eyes too long a way.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     You told her my Conditions, and my Oath
                     Of silence, and that only you be vs'd.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     All, Sir.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     And that this night—
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     I, Sir.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     You guard the Doore—
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     I, Sir.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     But I nere meane to come.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     No, Sir? Oh wretch!
                     Shall I deceiue, when Shee remaines so true?
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     No. Thou shalt be true, and She remaine deceiu'd.
                     I'le lye, and yet I will not lye. My Friend
                     
                        Eulinus in my shape, shall clime her Bed.
                     This is the point. You'le promise all your ayd.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Your Seruant to Command, and then Reward.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Wee'll draw thee Meteor-like by our warme fauour
                     Vnto the roofe and feeling of the Court:
                     Wee'll raise thee (hold but fast) on Fortunes ladder.
Exit Roll.
                     
                     This Fellow is a Medley of most lewd
                     And vicious qualities: A braggart, yet a coward,
                     A knave, and yet a slave: True to all villany,
                     But false to Goodnesse. Yet now I loue him,
                     
                        Because he stands iust in the way of loue.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     
                        Coosse, I commend you to the Cyprian Queene;
                     Whil'st I attend Diana in the Forrest,
                     My kinsman Mandubrace, and I must try
                     Our Grey-hounds speed after a light-foot hare.
Exit Hirild.
                     
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     O Loue! whose nerves vnite in aequall bonds
                     This massy frame. Thou Caement of the world:
                     By which the Orbes and Elements agree:
                     By which all Liuing creatures ioy to bee,
                     And dying liue in their Posteritie.
                     Thy holy raptures warme each noble breast,
                     Sweetly inspiring more Soule. Thy delight
                     Surpasses melody, Nectar, and all pleasures
                     Of Tempe, and of Tempe's eldest Sister
                     
                        Elysium: A banquet of all the Senses!
                     By thy Commanding power, Gods into Beasts,
                     And Men to Gods are chang'd, as Poets say:
                     When Sympathy rules, All like what they obey.
                     But Loue triumphes, when Man and Woman meete
                     In full affection: Double vowes then fill
                     His sacred Shrine. Yet, This to mee denied,
                     More whets my Passion: Mutuall Loue growes cold.
                     
                        Venus, be thou Propitious to my wiles;
                     And laugh at Louers periuries and guiles.
Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 2. Scen. 3.
                  Lantonus. Hulacus. Two Druids, in long robes, hats like Pyramids, branches of Mistletoe.
                  
                     Lant.
                     That Soules immortall are, I easily grant:
                     Their future State distinguisht, Ioy, or Paine,
                     According to the merits of this Life.
                     But then I rather thinke, being free from Prison,
                     And bodily contagion, they subsist
                     In places fit for Immateriall Spirits:
                     Are not transfus'd from Men to beasts, from beasts
                     To men againe: wheel'd round about by change.
                  
                  
                     
                     Hul.
                     And were it not more cruell, to turne out
                     Poore naked Soules stript of warme flesh, like Landlords,
                     Bidding them wander: Then (forsooth) imagine
                     Some vnknowne Caue or Coast, whether all the myriads
                     Of soules deceas'd are slipt, and thrust together.
                     Nay, Reason rather sayes: As at one moment,
                     Some dye, and some are borne; so may their Ghosts,
                     Without more cost, serue the succeeding age:
                     For sure they do'nt weare; to be cast aside.
                     But enter strait, lesse, or more noble bodies,
                     According to desert of former deedes.
                     The valiant into Lyons, coward mindes
                     Into weake Hares, Th' ambitious into Eagles
                     Soaring aloft; But the peruerse and peeuish;
                     Are next indenniz'd into wrinkled Apes:
                     Each vice and vertue wearing seemely shapes.
                  
                  
                     Lant.
                     So you debase the gods most liuely image,
                     The humane Soule, and ranke it with meere Brutes,
                     Whose life of reason void, ends with their sense.
                  
                  Enter Belinus.
                  
                     Bel.
                     Hayle to Heauens priuy Counsellors. The King.
                     Desires your iudgement of these troublesome times.
                  
                  
                     Lant.
                     The gods foretold these mischiefes long agoe,
                     In Eldells raigne, The Earth and Sky were fild
                     With prodigies, strange Sights, and hellish shapes.
                     Sometime two Hostes with fiery launces met,
                     Armour and Horse being heard amid the Cloudes:
                     With Streamers red now march these ayrie Warriours,
                     And then a sable hearse-cloath wrappes vp all:
                     And bloody droppes speckled the grasse, as falling
                     From their deepe-wounded limbes:
                     Whilst staring Comets shooke their flaming haire.
                     Thus all our Warres were acted first on high,
                     And we taught what to looke for.
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     Nature tunes step-dame to her brood, and dammes
                     
                        Deny their monstrous issue. Saturne ioyn'd
                     In dismall league with Mars portends some change.
                     Late in a groue by night, a voyce was heard
                     To cry aloud, Take heed, more Troianes come.
                     
                     What may be knowne or done, wee'l search, and helpe,
                     With all religious care.
                  
                  
                     Belin.
                     The King and army doe expect as much:
                     That powers diuine perfum'd with odours sweete,
                     And feasted with the fat of Bulles and Rammes;
                     Be pleas'd to blesse their plots.
                  
                  
                     Lant.
                     All rites and orizons due, shall be perform'd.
                     Chifely Night's Empresse fourefold Honour craues,
                     Mighty in Heauen, and Hell, in Woods, and Waues.
Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 2. Scen. 4.
                  Caesar, Volusene, Laberius. Souldiers.
                  
                     Caes.
                     What land, what people, and what answer; Show.
                  
                  
                     Volus.
                     We saw a Paradise, whose bosome teemes
                     With siluer oare: whose Seas are pau'd with pearle:
                     The Medowes richly spread with Floraes tapistry:
                     The fields euen wonder at their haruest loades.
                     In Christall streames the scaly nations play,
                     Fring'd all along with trembling poplar trees:
                     The Sun in Summer loath to leaue their sight,
                     Forgets to sleepe, and glauncing makes no Night.
                     Then for the men, Their statures tall and bigge,
                     With blue-stain'd skinnes, and long blacke dangling haire
                     Promise a barbarous fiercenesse. They scarce know,
                     And much lesse feare our Empires might; but thus
                     Return'd defiance:
                     Cassibelane King of Britaine to Iulius Caesar Proconsul of Gallia.
                     Seeing your Empire's great. why should it not suffice?
                     To couet more and more, is Tyrants vsuall guize.
                     
                        To loose what Ioue you gaue, you'de thinke it but vniust:
                     You haue your answer then: Defend this Ile we must;
                     Which from the world cut of, and free from her first day,
                     Hath Iron more for swords, than Gold for tributes pay.
                     If amity, and like feare, succour to Gaule impartes:
                     Pardon: For this small brooke could not deuide our hearts.
                     We hope the gods will helpe, and fortune backe our Cause,
                     Who take Armes, but to keepe our liues, our Wiues, and Lawes.
                     As you from Troy, so we; Our pettigree do claime:
                     Why should the branches fight, when as the roote's the same?
                     Despise vs not, because the Sea and North vs cloze▪
                     
                     Who can no further goe, must turne upon their foes.
                     Thus rudely we conclude: Wage warre, or change your will:
                     We hope to vse a launce, far better than a quill.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     I grieue to draw my sword against the stocke
                     Of thrice-renowned Troy: But they are rude,
                     And must be frighted, ere we shall be friends.
                     Then lets aboord, and hoysting sailes conuey
                     Two legions ouer: For I long to view
                     This vnknowne land, and all their fabulous rites;
                     And gather margarites in my brazen cap.
                     Nature, nor Fates can valourous vertue Stop.
                  
                  
                     Laber.
                     Now Caesar speakes like Caesar: stronger and stronger,
                     Rise like a whirlewind, teare the mountaines pride;
                     Shake thy brasse harnesse, whose loud clattering may
                     waken Gradivus, where he sleepes on top
                     Of Haemus, lulld with Boreas roaring Base:
                     And put to flight this Nation with the noyse.
                     A Flie is not an Eagles combatant:
                     Nor may a Pygmee with a Gyant striue.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 2. Scen. 5.
                  Cassibelane. Belinus. Comius following. Attendants.
                  
                     Com.
                     Health and good fortune on Cassibelane tend.
                     My loue to you and Britaine, waft me hither,
                     To make attonement, ere the Romane Leader.
                     
                        Bring fire and spoyle and ruine on your heads.
                     No herbe can euer grow, where once he treads.
                     Nothing withstands his force. Be not too hardie,
                     But buy a friend with kindnesse, least you buy
                     His anger dearely.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     
                        Comius, speake no more: He knowes our mind.
                  
                  
                     Com.
                     O let not rage so blind your iudgement, but
                     Preuent with ease the hazzard of a warre,
                     Of warre, a word compos'd of thousand Iles.
                     O be not cruell to your selues. I'le vndertake
                     Without discredit to appease his wrath,
                     If you'le cas-sheere your souldiers, and receiue
                     Him like a Guest, not like an Enemie.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     False-hearted Gaule, dar'st thou perswade euen me,
                     For to betray my people to the sword?
                     Now know I, thou art sent for to sollicite
                     Our Princes to rebell, to learne our strength.
                     Lay hands on him: A Spy.
                  
                  
                     All.
                     A Spy, a spie, a traytour, and a spie.
they chaine him.
                     
                  
                  
                     Com.
                     Is this the Guerdon of my louing care?
                     You breake the lawes of Nature, Nations, Friends:
                     But looke for due reuenge at Caesars hand.
                  
                  
                     Cassi.
                     Expect in prison thy reuenge. Away with him.
exit. Com.
                     
                     
                        Belinus, haue you mustered vp our Forces?
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     Yes, if it please your Highnesse.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     And what are the particulars?
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     First Cridous leades from the Albanian realme,
                     Where Grampiu's ridge deuides the smiling dales,
                     Fiue thousand horse, and twenty thousand foote,
                     Three thousand Chariots man'd. The Brigants come
                     Deckt with blew-painted shields, twelue thousand strong.
                     Vnder the conduct of Demetiaes Prince,
                     March twice three thousand, arm'd with Pelts and Glaues:
                     Whom the Silures flanke, eight thousand stout,
                     Greedy of fight, borne souldiers the first day,
                     Whose gray-goose-winged shafts neere flew in vaine.
                     Then Guerted mounted on a shag-haire steed,
                     
                        Full fifteene thousand brings, both horse and foote,
                     Of desperate Ordovicians, whose vse is
                     To rush halfe naked on their foes, inrag'd
                     With a rude noyse of pipes.
                     Your Prouince bounded with that boyling streame,
                     Where Sabrine louely Damsell lost her breath,
                     And with curld-pated Humber, Neptunes heire:
                     Affoordes eight thousand Carres, with hookes and sithes,
                     And fiftie thousand expert men of warre:
                     All braue Lhoegrians, arm'd with Pike and Speare:
                     Each nation being distinguisht into troopes,
                     With gawdie pennons flickering in the aire.
                     Beside these, Kent is vp in armes, to blunt
                     The edge of their first furious shocke.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Wee'l now invite them to a martiall Feast,
                     Caruing with Fauchions, and carowsing healths
                     In their liues moysture. Well return'd Androgens:
                        enter Andr.
                     
                     Haue you obtain'd, or is your suite denied?
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     Our message told vnto the Scots, Their King
                     VVith willing sympathy, leauies a Band,
                     Ten thousand footmen, whose strange appetites
                     Murder, and then deuoure; and dare gnaw, and suck
                     Their enemies bones. Conducted thence, we saw
                     The Pictish Court, and friendly intertain'd,
                     Receiue eight thousand, whose most vgly shapes,
                     Painted like Beares, and VVolues, and brinded Tygers,
                     May kill, and stonifie without all weapons.
                     More aide they promise, if more need. These forces.
                     Lead by Cadallan hither march with speed.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Tis well, our Kings consent for common good.
                     VVhen all are ioyn'd, we shall ore-spred the hills,
                     And souldiers thicker than the sand on shoare,
                     Hide all the landing coasts. Ere next day breake,
                     The rockes shall answer, what the drumme doth speake.
                  
                  Exeunt.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 2. Scen. 6.
                  Hulacus. Lantonus. Ministers.
                  
                     Lant.
                     That ceremonious feare, which bendes the heart
                     Of mortall creatures, and displaies it selfe
                     In outward signes of true obedience;
                     As praier, kneeling, sacrifice, and Hymnes:
                     Requires againe helpe from immortall Deities,
                     As promise, not as Debt: we laud their names,
                     They giue vs blessings, and forgiue our blames.
                     Thus gods and men doe barter. What in Pietie
                     Ascends, as much descends againe in pity:
                     A golden chaine reaching from Heauen to Earth.
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     And now's the time, good Brother, of their aide,
                     When dangers, blacke face frownes vpon our state.
                     Away, away, ye hearts and tongues prophane:
                     Without deuotion mysteries are vaine.
                  
                  They kneele, elevate hands thrice.
                  
                     Lant.
                     Draw neere ye heauenly powers,
                     Who dwell in Starry bowers.
                     And ye who in the deep,
                     On mosste pillowes sleep.
                     And ye who keep the center,
                     Where neuer light did enter.
                     And ye whose habitations,
                     Are still among the nations;
                     To see, and heare our doings,
                     Our birthes, our warres, our wooings.
                     Behold our present griefe:
                     Beleefe doth beg reliefe.
                     Both going around say.
                     By the veruaine, and Lunary,
                     By Fernefeed planetary,
                     By the dreadfull Mistletoe,
                     Which doth on holy Oake grow.
                     Draw neere, draw neere, draw neere.
                  
                  
                     
                     Hul.
                     Helpe vs beset with danger,
                     And turne away your anger:
                     Helpe vs begirt with trouble,
                     And now your mercie double:
                     Helpe vs opprest with sorrow,
                     And fight for vs to morrow.
                     Let fire consume the foe-man,
                     Let aire infect the Romane,
                     Let Seas intombe their furie,
                     Let gaping earth them burie:
                     Let fire and aire and water,
                     And earth conspire their slaughter.
                  
                  
                     Both.
                     By the veruaine, &amp;c.
                     Helpe vs, helpe vs, helpe vs.
                  
                  
                     Lant.
                     Wee'l praise then your great power,
                     Each moneth, each day, each hower:
                     And blaze in lasting story,
                     Your honour and your glorie.
                     High altars lost in vapour;
                     Young Heifars free from labour;
                     White Lambes for suck still crying,
                     Shall make your musicke dying.
                     The boies and girles around,
                     VVith honie-suckles crown'd:
                     The Bardes with Harpe and riming,
                     Greene bayes their browes entwyning,
                     Sweet tune, and sweeter dittie,
                     Shall chaunt your gracious pittie.
                  
                  
                     Both.
                     By the vervaine, &amp;c.
                     VVee'l praise, wee'l praise, wee'l praise.
                  
                  The image of the Moone, the Shrine opens.
                  
                     Hul.
                     Fixe, holy Brother, now your praiers on One,
                     Britaines chiefe Patronesse; with humble cry,
                     Let vs inuoke the Moones bright Maiestie.
they kneele.
                     
                  
                  
                     Lant.
                     Thou Queene of Heauen, Commandresse of the Deep,
                     Lady of Lakes, Regent of VVoods and Deere,
                     
                        A Lampe dispelling irksome night: The source
                     Of generable moysture. At whose feete
                     With garments blue, and rushie garlands drest
                     Waite twenty thousand Naiades. Thy Crescent
                     Brute Elephants adore, and man doth feele
                     Thy force run through the Zodiack of his limbes.
                     O thou first guide of Brutus to this Ile,
                     Driue backe these proud vsurpers from this Ile.
                     Whether the name of Cynthiaes siluer globe;
                     Or chaste Diana with a guilded quiuer;
                     Or dread Proserpina, sterne Dis his spouse;
                     Or soft Lucina, call'd in child-bed throwes:
                     Doth thee delight. Rise with a glorious face,
                     Greene droppes of Nereus trickling downe thy cheekes,
                     And with bright hornes, vnited in full orbe,
                     Tosse high the Seas, with billowes beate the bankes,
                     Coniure vp Neptune, and the Aeolian slaues,
                     Contract both Night and Winter in a storme:
                     That Romans loose their way, and sooner land
                     At sad Avernus, than at Albions strand.
                     So maist thou shun the Dragons head and tayle:
                     So may Endymion snort on Latmian bed:
                     So may the faire game fall before thy bow:
                     Shed light on vs, but lightning on our foe.
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     Me thinkes, a gracious luster spreads her brow:
                     And with a nodde she ratifies our suite.
                  
                  Within. Come neere, and take this Oracle.
                  
                     Lant.
                     Behold, an Oracle flies out from her Shrine:
                     Which both the King and State shall see, before
                     We dare vnfold it.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 2. Scen. 7.
                  Brennus Ghost. Nennius, in night robes.
                  
                     Brenn.
                     Follow me.
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Follow? what meanes that word, who art, Thy will?
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     Follow me Nennius.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Nenn.
                     He names mee: Sure it is some friend which speaks.
                     I'le follow thee, though't be through Stygian lakes.
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     Tis Ancient Brennus calles, whose victories
                     Europe and Asia felt, and still record.
                     Deare Nennius, now's the time to steele thy courage.
                     Canst thou behold thy Mother captiue, then
                     Looke backe vpon thy Ancestors enroll'd
                     Among the Worthies, who spread wide her Fame?
                     First let thy Eye-balles powre out poysoned beames,
                     And kill them with Disdaine, who dare but lift
                     Their hand against her. No: no Confull must
                     Boast of her Thraldome, and out-braue our Walles.
                     I wonder that such impudent Owles should gaze
                     Against the splendour of our Britaine clifts:
                     Play thou a second Brennus, Let thy Lance,
                     Like an Herculean clubbe, Two monsters tame,
                     
                        Romes Auarice and Pride; So come Life or Death,
                     Let Honour haue the Incense of thy Breath.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Farewell heroick Soule: Thou shalt not blush,
                     At Nennius deeds. The smallest drop of Fame
                     Is cheape, If death and dangers may it buy.
                     Yet giue thy words new vigour to my spirits,
                     And spurre the Pegasus of my mounting thoughts:
                     I'le follow thee, ore pyles of slaughtered foes,
                     And knocke at Plutoes gate. I come. Come Life or Death,
                     Honour, To thee I consecrate my Breath.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  Caesar. Camillus Ghost following.
                  
                     Cam.
                     
                        Iulius, stay heere: Thy friend Camillus speaks.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     O thou Preseruer of our present Race,
                     Our Cities Second founder! What dire fate
                     Troubles Thy Rest, that thou shouldst trouble Mine?
                  
                  
                     Cam.
                     Only to bid thee fight.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Thou shalt not need.
                  
                  
                     Cam.
                     And bid thee take a full Reuenge on this,
                     This Nation, which did sacke and burne downe Rome,
                     Quenching the coales with blood, and kickt Our ashes,
                     Trampling vpon the ruines of our state.
                     
                        Then led the Gaules in triumph thorow Greece,
                     To fixe their Tents beside Euxinus gulph.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Is this that Northerne route, the Scourge of kingdomes?
                     Whose names till now vnknowne, We iudged Gaules;
                     Their Tongue and Manners not vnlike.
                  
                  
                     Cam.
                     Gaules were indeed the Bulke, but Brennus lead
                     Then Brother to the Britaine King, those armyes,
                     Backt with great troopes of warlike Ilanders.
                     To thee belongs, To render Bad for Ill:
                     O bee my Spirit doubled in thy breast,
                     With all the Courage of three Scipioes,
                     
                     
                        Marius, and Sylla: That this nation fierce
                     In feats of warre, be forc'd to beare our Yoake.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     So mayst thou sweetly rest, as I shall striue
                     To trace your steps: Nor let mee liue, If I
                     Thence disappointed euer seeme to flye,
Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 2. Scen. 8.
                  Chorus.
                  
                     1. Song.
                     
                     
                        Antient Bards haue sung,
                        With lips dropping hony,
                        And a sugred tongue,
                        Of our worthy Knights.
                        How Brute did Gyants tame,
                        And by Isis current,
                        A second Troy did frame;
                        A Center of Delights.
                     
                     
                        Locrinus eldest sonne
                        Did drowne the furious Hunne,
                        But burnt himselfe with Elstrids loue,
                        Leist, Rex Pacificus.
                        Elud, Iudicious,
                        How heauenly Bodies rowle aboue.
                     
                     
                        
                        Wise Bladud founded hath,
                        Both Soule and Bodies Bath:
                        Like Icarus he flew.
                        How first Mulmutius weares
                        A golden crowne: whose heyres
                        More than halfe the World subdue.
                     
                  
                  
                     2. Song.
                     
                     
                        Thou nurse of Champions, O thou Spring
                        Whence Chiualry did flow:
                        Thou Diamond of the worlds great Ring,
                        Thy glorious vertue show:
                        Thou many a Lord hast bred,
                        In Catalogue of Fame read:
                        And still we haue
                        As Captaines Braue,
                        As euer Britaines led.
                        Then dub a dub, dub. The Armies ioyne, Tantara.
                        
                     
                     
                        Cassibelane with armour gay,
                        And strongly couched launce:
                        His courser white turn'd into bay,
                        On carkesses shall praunce.
                        What a crimzon streame, the Blade
                        Of Nennius sword hath made.
                        Blacke Alliaes day,
                        And Cannaes Fray,
                        Haue for a Third long stayd.
                        Then dub a dub, dub. The Armies ioyne, Tantara.
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  Act. 3.
               
                  
                     Scen. 1.
                  Noyse of Ships landing, and the battell within. Caesar. Volusene. Laberius. Atrius. Ensigne, Drums, Flagge.
                  
                     Caes.
                     Our Landing cost vs deerely, many liues
                     Betweene the ships and shoare being sacrific'd.
                     
                        Our men with heauy armour clogg'd, and ignorant
                     Of all the flats, and shallowes, were compell'd
                     To wade and fight, like Tritons halfe aboue,
                     Halfe vnder water. Now we surer tread,
                     Though much diminisht by so many lost.
                     Come on. Come on.
They march, and goe out.
                     
                  
                  Cassibelane. Cridous, Britael, Guerted. The foure Kings of Kent. Nennius. Androgeus. Themantius. Eulinus. Hirildas. Belinus. Rollano. Ensignes. Drumme. A March.
                  
                     Cassib.
                     So, let them land. No matter which they chuse
                     Fishes or Crowes to be Executers:
                     They'le find the Land as dangerous as the Sea.
                     The Nature of our Soyle won't beare a Romane,
                     As Irish earth doth poyson poysonous beasts.
                     On then: charge close, before they gather head.
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Brother, Aduance. On this side, Ile lead vp
                     The new-come Succours of the Scots and Picts.
                  
                  They march, and goe out.
                  
                     Caesar, &amp;c.
                  
                     Caes.
                     What, still fresh Supplyes come thronging from their dens?
                     The nest of Hornets is awake: I thinke
                     Heere's Natures Shop: Heere men are made, not borne,
                     Nor stay nine tedious moneths, But in a trice
                     Sprout vp like mushromes at Warres thunder-clap.
                     We must make out a way.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
                  Rollano, arm'd, cap a pea.
                  
                     Roll.
                     Since I must fight, I am prepar'd to fight:
                     And much inflam'd, with noyse of Trump and Drum:
                     Mee thinks I am turn'd Lyon, and durst meete
                     Ten Caesars. Where are all these Couetous rogues?
                     Who spoyle the rich for gaine, and kill the poore
                     For glory? Blood suckers, and publike Robbers.
                  
                  Laber▪ enters. Rollano retires afraid; but being gone out, goes forward.
                  
                     Roll.
                     Nay stay, and bragge, Rollano did thee kill:
                     Stay, let me flesh my sword, and weare thy spoyles.
                  
                  Laber. re-enters with an Ensigne.
                  
                     
                     Laber.
                     Come. Will ye forsake your Ensigne, and fall off?
                     I call to witnesse all the gods, I heere
                     Performe my duty. Thou canst not scape.
                     Rollano would flye, fights, fals as wounded.
                     Now dye, or yeeld thy selfe.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     I yeeld, I yeeld, Oh saue my life, I yeeld.
                     I am no Britaine, but by chance come hither:
                     I'le neuer more lift weapon in their quarrell.
                  
                  
                     Laber.
                     How may I trust your faith?
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Command me any thing.
                  
                  
                     Lab.
                     Lay downe your neck.
                     Treads on it.
                     Giue vp your sword.
Beates him with it.
                     
                     Base coward liue: Such foes will neere do hurt.
exit. Laber.
                     
                  
                  Enter Eulinus, Androgeus, Belinus, with bloody swords.
                  
                     Eul.
                     
                        Rollano, what at stand? pursue the chase.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     I made their strongest Captaine flie: This hand,
                     This martiall hand, I say, did make him flie.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     Some silly scoute.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     He was a match for Cyclops, at each step
                     The ground daunc'd, and his nostrills blew the dust:
                     Arm'd as the God of Battell pictur'd is.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     What were his lookes?
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     His browes were like a stormy winter night,
                     When Iuno scolding, and Mars male-content
                     Disturbe the aire: At each looke lightning flies,
                     Ioue 'gainst the Gyants needed but his eies.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     How eloquent is feare!
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     So came he stalking with a Beame-like speare,
                     I gaue the onset, then receiu'd his charge,
                     And next blow cleft his morrian: So he flies.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     O brauely done. Here comes a stragling souldier.
ent. Lab.
                     
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Tis he, tis he. I care not for vaine glory:
                     Its sweeter liue, than dead to be a storie,
runs away.
                     
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     O valiant coward, stay. Theres not a sparke
                     Of Britaine Spirit doth enliue thy corps.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen▪
                      2.
                  Nennius, pursuing.
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Fight Britaines, fight. The day is ours. I'me cloy'd
                     And glutted euen with slaughter. There some flie,
                     And flying die, and dying mangled lie.
                     I twise broke through the rankes, yet cannot find
                     That ventrous Captaine Caesar, on whose breast
                     I long to try my blade, and pricke that bladder
                     Puft with ambition, and victorious fight.
                  
                  Caesar enters.
                  
                     Caes.
                     We may confesse, they come of Troiane kind,
                     An hundred valiant Hectors here we find.
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Fairely incountred, let our blades discusse
                     Who hath the iustest cause: And on this combate
                     May victory her equall Ballance hang.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Thou seem'st a worthy Prince, and Caesars match.
                  
                  They fight, wounds Nennius in the head, who staggers, fights, and recouers Caesars sword falne, and puts him to flight.
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Stay, stay. Thou art at home: Heere's Campus Martius.
                     The Britaines sought-for see thy frighted backe:
                     Returne, and take possssion of our Ile,
                     And by thy death be stil'd Britannicus.
                     Leaue not thy blade vnsheath'd: A tyrants heart
                     To his owne sword a scabberd should impart.
                     Ye Senatours, and gaily-gownd Quirites,
                     Open the Capitolls iuory gates, and lead
                     Fat bulles with garlands greene, and guilded hornes:
                     Let supplications last for twice ten daies:
                     
                        Caesar returnes a victour.
                     Prepare the laureate Coach, and snow-white steedes,
                     Embroydered Canopie, and skarlet gownes:
                     Let Altars smoake, and Tholes expect our spoiles:
                     
                        Caesar returnes in Triumph. — Basely flies,
                     And leaues his conquest in weake infancy.
                     
                        For had he won this coast, yet many blowes
                     Must passe, ere he could passe the Thames; And then
                     Ere he touch Humber, many nations must
                     Be tam'd: And then before he Tweed can drinke,
                     And climbe the craggy rocks of Caledon:
                     A Life is spent: yea, many thousand liues.
                     Oh my wound rages, and tormented braine
                     Doth labour of a Fury, not a Pallas.
                     This Blade was steept in poyson: O, I am poyson'd:
                     Well didst thou flye, or I had made thee tast
                     Thine owne provision. Now my wrath and paine,
                     With double force shall flow in purple streames.
                     The three infernall Ladyes with wyar-whips,
                     And speckled snakes, shall lackey close my steps;
                     Whilst that I offer Hecatombes of men
                     The Latian Shepheards brood shall ban those starres,
                     Whose glimmering Sparks lead their audacious Pines,
                     To lye so farre from home in forraine soyle.
                     When Cedars fall, whole woods are crusht: nor dye,
                     Can Nennius priuate without company.
                     Enter Laberius.
                     Thou runst vpon thy death.
                  
                  
                     Lab.
                     A Romane neuer daunted was with lookes;
                     Else had not Sarmatane, and Lybian bug-beares
                     Bin captiue led in chaines.
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     But our lookes kill.
Fight: Laber. falls.
                     
                     Dye Slaue, by Caesars sword. Thou art his friend.
                     Dye, as the Ransome of his greater ghost:
                     And learne as well as I, how venome smarts.
                     Be thou my Post to the Tartarian Prince,
                     And tell him, Nennius comes: But first, I'le send
                     More of you headlong home, a neerer way,
                     Then by the cloudy Alpes.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  A retrait sounded.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen. 3.
                  Cassibelane. Belinus. Lantonus.
                  
                     Cassi.
                     Now hot Alarums dye in fainter notes:
                     Tempestuous night is gone: Victorious ioy,
                     (As when pale Eos cleaues the Easterne fogs,
                     And blushing more and more opes halfe her eye,
                     With holy water sprinkling all the meades,
                     Whose cleere Reflexe serues as her Morning glasse:)
                     Doth paint with gawdy plumes the checkerd sky.
                     The only Name of Victory sounds sweeter,
                     Than all mellifluous Rhetoricke.
                  
                  
                     Lant.
                     Thankes to Andates, whose power kingdomes feele:
                     
                        Andates, greatest goddesse: In whose traine,
                     Feare, red-fac'd anger, and confusions wheele,
                     Murder, and Desolation runne before:
                     But ioyfull shouts, mirth, Olive-budding Peace,
                     And Lawrell-crowned triumph, at her backe,
                     Do pase with stately steps. Thy Temple is,
                     The Earth: where furious Monarches play the Priests:
                     Armies of men imbrue thy Altar stones.
                     Thanks also to the Trident-shakers Mace,
                     Drawne by two ramping Sea-horses: at whose Becke,
                     The waters wrinkled frowne, or smoothly smile.
                     But thou Heauens Diamond, faire Phoebus Sister,
                     Nor Delian Dames, nor the Ephesian Towers,
                     Shall blazon more thy Praise. Thy influence strong
                     Strucke vp the sandy ooes; that madding waues
                     Batterd their ships, and dasht their bended sayles,
                     And with a tempest turn'd them round in skorne.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     But where's the Answer which her Idoll gaue:
                     Can you expound the sense?
                  
                  
                     Lant.
                     Dread Soueraigne, Thus runnes the Oracle▪
                     
                     Loud doth the King of Beasts roare,
                     High doth the Queene of Birds soare:
                     But her wings clipt soone grow out:
                     
                        Both repent they are so stout.
                     Till C. gainst C. strike a round,
                     In a perfect Circle bound.
                     The meaning wrapt vp in crosse doubtfull termes,
                     Lyes yet thus open: That disastrous fate
                     Must be the Prologue to a ioyfull cloze.
                     The rest wee'l search out, if our skill don't faile.
                  
                  
                     Belin.
                     Renown'd Cassibelane, might my counsell speake!
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     I know thy loyall heart, and prudent head,
                     Vpon whose haires Time's child experience hangs
                     A milke-white badge of wisedome: And canst wield
                     Thy tongue in Senate, and thy hands in field.
                     Speake free, Belinus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     We forfeit fame, and smother victory
                     By idle lingering: The Foe discomfited
                     Must needs be much amaz'd: His Ships dismembred
                     Doe peece-meale floate vpon the waues: The Horse,
                     Whose succour he expects, are beaten backe
                     By friendly windes: His Campe contracted is,
                     A tithe of souldiers left, the rest all slaine:
                     His chiefe munition spent, or lost: prouision,
                     An Armies soule, but what we giue, he wants.
                     What then shall hinder to destroy their name?
                     So none againe shall venter, but our Ile
                     Rounded with Nereus girdle may inioy
                     Eternall peace.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     I like thy warning: with vnited stroke
                     Of all our Nations, wee'l his Campe beleaguer,
                     Devouring ships and men. But one mischance,
                     My Brother's wound, his mortall wound I feare,
                     Turnes all to wormewood. Why were ye dumbe ye Idolls!
                     No Sainted Statue did foretell this griefe.
                     Come lets goe visit him. You may, Lord Generall,
                     Set Comius free: We loue not to insult,
                     But render good for ill.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen. 4.
                  Caesar, Volusene, &amp;c.
                  
                     Caes.
                     Heauen, Sea, and Wind, and all the Elements,
                     Conspire to worke vs harme. Our Ships in Gaule
                     Wind-bound, at length put forth, and come in view
                     Are tost, and torne: Our Nauy on the shoare
                     With ciuill discord breake each others plankes.
                     The ayrie Rulers are displeas'd, all day
                     Noyses and nimble flashes mixt with raine
                     Amaze our souldiers.
                     To make griefe full, my Daughters death I heare.
                     When, powerfull Fortune, will thy anger cease?
                     Neuer till now did Caesar fortune feare.
                     Mount Palatine, thou Throne of Ioue, and ye
                     Whose lesser Turrets pinnacle Rome's head:
                     Are all your Deities fled? or was I bold,
                     To out-goe Nature, and our Empire stretch
                     Beyond her limites? Pardon then my fault.
                     Or doe we basely faint? Or is our might
                     Answer'd with like, since Troy gainst Troy doth fight?
                     Nor can I write now, I came ouer, and
                     
                     
                        I ouercame: Such foes deny such hast.
                  
                  
                     Volus.
                     The Ilanders consult, and sure intend
                     Some sudden stratageme. And now the scales
                     Poyze equall day and night, when rougher Seas,
                     And stormy Pleyads may our passage stop.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Then Sirs, to ship: Compell'd I leaue this land:
                     But to returne, if gods doe not withstand,
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen. 5.
                  Cassibelane, Belinus, Lantonus. Nennius in a chaire.
                  
                     Nenn.
                     We wunne the day: and all our foes are fled?
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     Yes noble Nennius, scatter'd on the shoare
                     Thicke lay the Latines, and the glutted streame
                     
                        Spewes vp her dead, whom death hath taught to swimme,
                     Though ignorant aliue: Their flowing blood
                     Made a new Red Sea. But those few we lost,
                     Sweetly repos'd vpon their mothers breast,
                     And wounded all before, kept in their face
                     A warlike frowne.
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Where is false Caesars sword, call'd Crocea Mors,
                     Which neuer hurt, but kill'd: Let it be plac'd
                     Within my tombe.
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     Heere is the fatall Blade.
                  
                  
                     Nenn.
                     Death like a Parthian flies, and flying kils:
                     In midst of Conquest came my deadly wound.
                     Accursed weapon, more accursed man,
                     Who Serpent-like in poyson bathes his sting:
                     Tyber doth breed as venemous beasts as Nile:
                     We skorne such cruell craft. But death drawes neere,
                     A giddy horror seazeth on my braine.
                     Deare Brother, and thou holy Priest of Heauen,
                     Witnesse my words; I leaue my Country free,
                     And dye a victour. Thus, with lighter wing
                     My purified soule mounts to her First-best Cause.
                     I long euen to behold those glorious Cloysters,
                     Where Brutus, great Dunwallo, and his sonnes,
                     Thrice noble Spirits walke.
                     Thou mighty Enginer of this wondrous Globe,
                     Protect this Ile, confound all forraine plots:
                     Graunt Thames and Tyber neuer ioyne thair chanells;
                     But may a naturall hate deriv'd from vs
                     Liue still in our long-trailed progeny.
                     (My eyes doe swimme in death.)
                     Before this land shall weare the Romane yoke;
                     Let first the adamantine axell cracke,
                     Which bindes the Ball terrestriall to her poles,
                     And dash the empty aire; Let Planets drop
                     Their scalding gelly, and all flame being spent,
                     Entombe the world in euerlasting smoake.
                     Come faster, Death: I can behold thy grim,
                     
                        And vgly Iawes with quiet mind: Now, now:
                     I heare sweet musick; and my spirit flies.
he dies.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cassi.
                     His breath is gone: who was his Countries prop,
                     And my right hand. Now onely doth he craue,
                     To see him laid with honour in the graue.
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen. 6.
                  Eulinus, Hirildas.
                  
                     Eul.
                     A mind content, Oh, tis a mind of pearle,
                     A Mint of golden thoughts, A Heauen on Earth!
                     When eager longer meete full-but their scope,
                     And hopes are actuated beyond hope.
                     So Iason ioy'd, the golden Fleet obtain'd:
                     So Hercules ioy'd, the golden fruit being gain'd:
                     So Venus ioy'd, the golden Ball to hold:
                     So Mydas ioy'd, when he turnd all to gold.
                     So, and much more reioyc'd, the Phrygian swaine,
                     When he conuaide the fairest (except mine)
                     Which aire did euer kisse: His brazen keele
                     Proud of her burden, slic'd the capering brine:
                     The Tritons blew their hornes, and Sea-gods daunce,
                     Before, behind, about his Ship they praunce:
                     The meare-Maides skip on high, but to compaire
                     Their dangling tresses with her silken haire.
                     These were but shadowes of my blisse. A robe
                     Of pure beatitude wrapes me round about,
                     Without a specke, or blemish: nor can Invention
                     Wish more vnto me, than I haue, Landora.
                     
                     I'me rich, free, learned, honor'd, all; in this.
                     Who dares conceiue against the Female sexe,
                     But one base thought? Lo heere I stand, their Champion,
                     And will maintaine, He is a beast, a deuill,
                     Begot betweene a Bitch-woolfe, and an Incubus.
                     Women, all good, all perfect, and all gracious,
                     Men-making creatures, Angels clad in flesh;
                     Let me adore your Name.
                  
                  
                     
                     Hiril.
                     — And let me speake.
                     Why: Landora loues not you, but me in you.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     But I in you inioy Landoraes loue.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     But she inioyes not your loue, cause vnknowne.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     No matter; I in you, or you in me:
                     So that I still possesse my Dearest deare.
                     A paultry fancy last night in her bed
                     Turmoyl'd my thoughts, which since I shap't in Rimes. Thus.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Prethee let's heare: I know thou art turn'd Poet.
                     The Dreame.
                     Night having drawne the Curtaine, downe I lye
                     By one, for worse Saturnius left the skie.
                     Slumbring at last: For loue can hardly sleepe:
                     Strait-waies I dream'd: For loue doth Reuelles keep.
                     A Damsell faire, and fashion'd for delight,
                     (Our day-borne obiects doe returne at night)
                     With flowry chaplet, and red veluet gowne,
                     Which from her breast was fastned along downe
                     With rich enamel'd lockes, all which one key,
                     Whose bright gold 'bout her siluer necke did play,
                     Could open and diuorce. A vaile most faire,
                     (Such whitnesse onely Paphian doues doe weare)
                     With false light did her beauteous Front improue;
                     From this Arch Cupid shot his darts of Loue.
                     With gentle straine she tooke me by the hand,
                     (Touches in loue doe more than tongue's command)
                     Then leades me with an amorous smile along:
                     Hee's easily led, whom beauty drawes, more strong▪
                     
                     Than Cable-roapes. An Altar we descry,
                     Where Incense-franke, and Amber fumes did flie,
                     In little rowling curles: A reuerend Priest,
                     With snowy beard wauing vpon his breast,
                     There kneeling did his eies in sorrow steepe:
                     Whose passionate cry made me, though ignorant, weepe.
                     Phlegons hot breath no sooner lickes vp dew,
                     Than ioy had dried those teares: For loe I view
                     A circular roome, all built with marble cleare,
                     
                        The title, Natures Store-house. Most strange heere
                     It seem'd: I know not how we came, nor whence,
                     Nor any passage saw to get from thence.
                     But Oh the rich delight, and glorious fire
                     Which dazeled me: No hart can more desire.
                     Her first my guide op'd her spice-breathing doore,
                     Aske what thou wilt, this is the Arke of store,
                     No vowes are heere repuls'd, she said. But I
                     Surpriz'd with extreame ioy and extasie,
                     By chance a Scorpion's taile behind her spide:
                     Pitty, such beauty such a monster hide.
                     Trembling, yet silent, doubtfull what to craue:
                     Loe, with a stinke and fearefull screech this braue
                     And glorious Dame doth vanish, and a dart,
                     Which still I quake at, strucke me to the heart.
                     But waking I reuiu'd, and found in bed,
                     Such Soueraigne Balme, would cure old Peleus dead.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Ha, ha. Your tedious dreame hath made me drowsie.
                     But harke, we must attend the Funerall pompe.
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen. 7.
                  The Funerall passes ouer the Stage. Nennius Scutcheon, armour Caesars sword borne. Torches, Mourners.
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Set downe that heauie load with heauier hearts.
                     Could vertuous valour, honourable thoughts,
                     A noble skorne of Fortune, pride, and death;
                     Myriads of vowes and prayers sent to heauen,
                     Could Countries Ioue, or Britaines Genius saue
                     A mortall man from sleeping in his graue:
                     Then hadst thou liu'd great Nennius, and out-liu'd
                     The smooth-tongu'd Greeke. But we may more enuy,
                     And lesse bewaile thy losse, since thou didst fall
                     On honours lofty Field-bed, on which Stage
                     Neuer did Worthy act a statelier part.
                     Nor durst pale death approach with Cypresse sad,
                     Till florishing Bay thy conquering temples clad.
                     
                        
                        A Funerall Elegie sung to the Harpe.
                     
                     
                        Turnus may conceale his Name,
                        Nennius had Aeneas fame.
                        Hannibal let Africk smother,
                        Nēnius was great Scipioes brother.
                        Greece forbeare Achilles story,
                        Nennius had braue Hectors glory.
                     
                     
                        Thrush and Nightingale be dumb:
                        Sorrowfull songs befit a Tombe.
                        Turne ye marble stones to water:
                        Isis Nymphes forswear al laughter:
                        Sigh and sob vpon your bed:
                        Belyes noble Sonne is dead.
                     
                  
                  A Banquet seru'd ouer the stage. Rollano with a leg of a Capon, and a tankard of wine.
                  
                     Roll.
                     I like such slaughtering well, of birdes and beasts;
                     Which weare no swordes, nor shake a fatall pike:
                     When hogsheads bleed, and Oxen mangled lye.
                     O what a world of victualls is prepar'd
                     For sacrifice and feasting. Fourty thousand
                     Fat Bullockes: than the Parkes and Forests send
                     Full thirty thousand wild beasts, arm'd with hornes,
                     And dangerous teeth: The maine battaillion
                     Consists of Sheep, an hundred thousand fat:
                     The winges are both supplied with birds, and fowles,
                     Sans number: And some fish for succours serue.
                     A goodly Army. Troynouant doth smoake,
                     And smells all like a kitchin. The King, Princes,
                     And Nobles of the land a Triumph hold.
                     Musicke, and songs, good cheere, and wine; and wine,
                     And songs and Musicke, and good cheere▪ High, braue.
                     No more shall barly broath pollute my throate,
                     But Nectar, Nectar of the grapes sweete blood:
                     Come heauenly Potion, wine: whose gentle warmth
                     Softens the braine, vnlockes the silent tongue,
                     Wits Midwife, and our spirits vestall Priest
                     Keeping aliue the naturall heate. A health,
                     A health (to make short worke) to all the world:
                     So will it sure goe round.
steales behind.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     The Triumphes. Cassibelane. 4 Kings of Kent. 3 Kings, Cridous, Britael, Guerted, Androg. Themant. Hirild. Eulin. Belin. take places.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     
                        Sorrow must doffe her sable sable weedes, and ioy
                        Furbish the Court with fresh and vernant colours:
                        Else should we seeme vngratefull to the gods.
                        Triumphs must thrust out Obsequies: And Tilt
                        With Turny, and our antient sport call'd Troy,
                        
                        Such as Iulus 'bout his Grandsires tombe
                        Did represent. And at each Temples porch
                        Games, songs, and holy murdering of beastes.
they sit downe.
                        
                     
                     A dauncing Maske of sixe enters. Then the Epinicion sung by two Bardes.
                     
                        The Romane Eagle threatning woe,
                        The Sea did shadow with her wing:
                        But our Goose quilles did pricke her so,
                        That from the clouds they downe her bring.
                        
                           Both. Sing then ye Hilles and Dales so so cleare:
                        That Io Paean all may heare.
                     
                     
                        They may vs call Iles Fortunate;
                        They sought for life heere, not for Fame.
                        All, yeeld to them, they to our State:
                        The world knowes but our Double Name.
                        
                           Both. Sing then ye Streames and Woods so so cleare:
                        That Io Paean all may heare.
                     
                  
                  Androgeus, and Themantius, play at foyles. Then Hirildas and Eulinus play.
                  
                     Eul.
                     Twas fowly plaid.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     You lye, twas fairely hit.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     I'le giue a quittance.
                  
                  
                     Hir.
                     Do your worst, vaine braggart.
                     They take swordes. Fight. Hirildas slaine.
                     Oh, I am slaine.
                  
                  
                     
                     Cassi.
                     Hold, hold: my Nephew's slaine before my face.
                     Life shall be paid with Life.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     He shall not dye.
                  
                  
                     Cassi.
                     Shall not? Your King and Vncle sayes, Hee shall.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     No kingly menace, or censorious frowne,
                     Doe I regard. Tanti, for all your power.
                     But the compunction of my guilt doth send
                     A shuddering chillnesse through my veines inflam'd:
                     Why doe ye stare, ye grisly powers of night?
                     There, there, His soule goes: I must follow him.
                  
                  Offers to kill himselfe: is hinderd.
                  
                     Andr.
                     He was prouok'd and did it in defence:
                     And being My kinsman shall be iudg'd by lawes
                     Of Troynovant: Such custome claimes our Court.
                  
                  
                     Cass.
                     No custome shall barre Iustice: I command
                     That he appeare before vs.
                  
                  
                     And.
                     Trials are vaine, when Passion sits as Iudge.
                  
                  
                     Cass.
                     I'le soone rebate this Insolent disdaine.
                     Exeunt Androg. Them. Eul.
                     Let not this dismall chance deface our ioy:
                     Most royall Friends.
                  
                  
                     Crid.
                     Warre being silenc'd, and Enyoes rage
                     In hell fast fetterd: Sound we now retrayte,
                     That souldiers may regreete their houshold gods.
                     Their children cling about their armed thighes.
                  
                  
                     Brit.
                     And place their Trophees 'bout their smoaky halles;
                     There hang a Gauntlet bright, here a stabt Buckler,
                     Pile vp long piles, and in that corner plant
                     A waighty sword, brandisht by some Centuríon.
                     Not he, who neere on snaky perils trod,
                     But happy He, who hath them stoutly past:
                     For danger's sauce giues ioy a better tast.
                  
                  
                     Guert.
                     Great Monarch, if thy Summons call vs backe,
                     We tender here our Seruice, Men, and Armes:
                     As dutie bids, and binds.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Should he returne: Our Province dares him front.
                     So a most kinde adieu vnto all three.
                     Exeunt Crid. Brit. Guert.
                     
                        
                        Cingeterix, Carvilius, Taximagubis, Segonax:
                     
                     I know your faithfull loue, Kents foure-fold Head,
                     Will checke rash Rebels, and as firmely stand
                     As heartie Oakes, who beare off Aeolus blowes,
                     And with a whistle but deride his force.
                     Exeunt foure Kings of Kent.
                     Burst gall, and dye my actions in flame-colour:
                     I saw Hirildas fall, and breath his soule
                     Euen in my face. As though hell watcht a time,
                     To crush our pompe, and glory into sighes.
                     The conduits of his vitall spring being ript,
                     Spurtle'd my robes, solliciting Reuenge. Belinus,
                     
                     Attach the Murderer, and if abettors
                     Deny obedience, then with sword and fire
                     Wast their Dominions. For a Traytors sake,
                     Whole townes shall tremble, and the ground shall quake.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen. 8.
                  Androgeus. Themantius. Mandubrace.
                  
                     Andr.
                     Shall Iustice, and iust Libra neere forsake
                     The imbroydered Belt? No signe of them on earth?
                     Are Gods dim-sighted growne, or doe they sleepe
                     The morning, and carowse the after noone?
                     That mortall motions tumble thus by chance:
                     Cleaue thou blew Marble Seeling, that heavens King
                     With clearer ayme may strike a tyrants crowne,
                     Nor spend his brimstone bullets 'gainst some hill,
                     Or innocent Pine.
                  
                  
                     Mandub.
                     Your iniuries run low; Mine breake all bounds.
                     My Father butcherd at his lawlesse will:
                     I banish'd from my lands, depos'd from rule,
                     Owing my Life to night and flight.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     I doe confesse, You may complaine aloud,
                     And teare the Element with a dolorous note:
                     Call downe Astraea from her chrystall chayre,
                     Or call vp Nemesis from the dyrefull deepe,
                     To expiate your wrongs.
                     
                        Else would the Manes of your father slaine,
                     In a white sheet come sliding to your Bed:
                     And be reveng'd on you. He gaue you life;
                     How can you better spend it, than to wreake
                     His death and slaughter? But our case and Cause,
                     Brother, is not the same: Eulinus slew
                     His innocent friend; And we defend the fact;
                     With hostile noyse drowning Lawe's reuerent voyce:
                     But Murder out-cries Both. Giue me then leaue
                     To be a Neutrall: My young yeeres vnfit
                     For any desperate course, can but complaine:
                     The King our Vncle doth not vse vs well.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     Vsurpers vse this method still: At first
                     Hee as Protector flily got the sterne,
                     During our nonage: Then the Commons voyce,
                     Bought with a fawning brow, and popular grace,
                     Confirmes his Regiment: Wee appointed shares,
                     With emptie titles to beguile our thoughts,
                     Like puppet-Lords, drest vp with crowne and skarfe,
                     Glad that wee liue, and hunt, and raigne ore brutes.
                     Our Vncle is the King. So when he saw,
                     His throne establish'd, and his foes repuls'd,
                     Growne bigge with prosperous fortune, proudly spurnes
                     All feare of God or man.
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     His anger nurst by iealousies must feed
                     On Princes flesh, who loose both state and life,
                     If they but looke awry. A tyrants growth
                     Rear'd vp by Ruines, thence may learne his fall:
                     For whom all feare, Hee iustly feareth all.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     In Antiphones thus tune wee female plaints:
                     But plots and force beseeme vs. Thus. Great Caesar
                     
                     Shall pull him downe below vs. Thou Mandubrace,
                     
                     Sure pledges take of our revolt, and quickly
                     Implore his ayd: blow vp his drooping fire
                     With hopefull termes. But let him stronger come.
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     I flye vnseene, as charmers in a myst.
                     Gratefull Reuenge, whose sharp-sweet rellish fats
                     
                        My apprehensiue Soule. Though all were par'd of,
                     Which doth accrue from Fortune, and a man left
                     As barely poore, as Nature thrust him out:
                     Nay worse, though spirits boyle, rage, anger, care,
                     And griefe like wild-horse teare the affrighted mind:
                     Though wrongs excoriate the heart: yet all is sweetned,
                     If vengeance haue her course. I wreake not how;
                     Let Common-wealth expire, and owles proclaime
                     Sad desolation in our Halls; Let heapes
                     Of dust and rubbage Epitaph our townes;
                     Let fire and water fight, who first shall spoyle
                     This vniuersall frame. From North, or South,
                     Reuenge, th'art wellcome. No sin worse than pitty:
                     A tyrants onely physicke is Phlebotomy.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 3. Scen. 9. Chorus.
                  
                     1. Song.
                     
                     
                        Reioyce O Britanie,
                        Britaine O reioyce:
                        The stormy cloud past ouer,
                        And onely made a noise.
                        A clattering sound was heard;
                        And still we felt no wound:
                        Reioyce; Reioyce:
                        Thou happy Britaine ground.
                     
                     
                        O that sweet plenidh,
                        Eloquent Orone,
                        Were now to chaunt our victories,
                        With a melodious tone:
                        And rowsing Echo from the dales,
                        With harmony to sound:
                        Reioyce; Reioyce:
                        Thou happy Britaine ground.
                     
                  
                  
                     2. Song.
                     
                     
                        Gang ye lads and lasses,
                        Sa wimble and sa wight:
                        Fewle mickle teene betide ye,
                        If ye ligg in this plight.
                        Bee bonny, buxome, iolly.
                        Trip haydegues beliue:
                        And gif night gars the welkin merk
                        Tom piper doe you blive.
                     
                     
                        Hidder, eke and shidder,
                        With spiced sow ycramd;
                        Sa that vnneath thilke borrells
                        May well ne yede, ne stand:
                        As leefe as life doe weete it,
                        When timbarins gin sound;
                        Fore haruest gil prankt vp in lathe,
                        To loute it low around.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  Act. 4.
               
                  
                     Scen. 1.
                  Caesar, Volusene, Attendants.
                  
                     Caes.
                     A Story ist, or fable; That sterne Mars,
                     Thy waight did Romulus sleepy mother presse?
                     Since we thy Brood degenerous, stand at gaze,
                     Charm'd in the circle of a foaming flood,
                     And traile our dastard pikes? Burst Ianus prison,
                     Roare as thou didst at Troy, drowne Stentors voice
                     By many eights, which Pindus may re-beate,
                     Which Caucasus may as a Catch repeate,
                     And Taurus lough the fame: That Pygmees small
                     May squeake, It thunders, and diue into burroughs.
                     Let the foure winds with dreadfull clamour sing
                     Thy anger through the affrighted world.
                     What Lemnian chaine shackles our mounting Eagle?
                     The Moone's round Concaue is too strait a cage
                     For her aduanced Pineons.
                  
                  Enter Mandubrace wounded and bloody, with Androg. young son.
                  
                     Mane.
                     If pitty can haue roome in angry breast,
                     Fauour a Britaine Prince, his Father slaine,
                     His regiment bereft, his dearest blood
                     Drawne by the sword of false Cassibelane.
                     
                     Hauing got Crowne, he then strucke at my head:
                     Nor can I safely sucke my natiue aire.
                     His Coosse Androgeus also, and whole regions
                     In open warre withstand his violence.
                     Lo, Albions aged armes spread wide t'inchaine
                     Thee as her Patrone, in a true-loue knot.
                     Wherefore dread Caesar, let thy mercy strike
                     Reuengefull fire; and be iustly stil'd,
kneeles.
                     
                     Tamer of Tyrants. Then fame blowes aloud,
                     When valour helpes the weake, pulles downe the proud.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Arise vnhappy Prince, our deeds shall show,
                     We grant thy suite.
To Volusene.
                     
                     
                        Fortune repents at last;
                     The Moone is chang'd, the Globe doth to vs turne
                     Her shining cheeke, and woes vs with a smile.
                     But what firme signes of Faith, what faithfull aide,
                     What furtherance can you giue at our arriuall?
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     See here Androgeus heire, whose tender age
                     His Father venters, and makes bold with nature,
                     To pledge his Darling. He and thirtie more
                     Of noble linage shall assure our faith:
                     Besides I pawne my life.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Enough. I'le once more crosse the Seas,
                     For your good, more than mine; That happier skie
                     May blesse your Townes with peace, your fields with plentie;
                     Perpetuall spring in gay perfum'd attire,
                     Sirname your Ile, the Garden of the West.
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     Thanks, gracious Caesar, for this kind acceptance,
                     My knee doth kisse the ground, my lippe your knee.
                     Pardon ye gods, if any haunt our land,
                     Ye Nymphes, and Lares, Fawnes, and Silvanes wild;
                     That thus I bring a stranger on our coasts,
                     Whose forraine shape and language, may affright
                     Our lazie clownes, and on my Countries backe
                     Once tread victorious steps: Be pleas'd to view,
                     Wrongs now redrest, neglected first by you.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Now Volusene:
                     Our glorious state, like the noone-pointed Sunne,
                     When he bestrides the Lyons flaming fleece,
                     Doth North-west rowle his burning brand, whose fire
                     The Oceans blue lake cannot stop, but flies
                     With brighter blaze to thaw the frozen Iles.
                     But how proceedes our preparation?
                  
                  
                     Volus.
                     Many strong Ships are built, fiue Legions arm'd
                     Readie to launch.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Blow gently Africus,
                     Play on our poopes: When Hyperions Sonne
                     Shall couch in West his fome-bedappled iades;
                     Wee'l rise to runne our course.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 4. Scen. 2. Eulinus.
                  
                     Eul.
                     Though Orpheus Harpe, Arions Lute, the Chimes
                     Whose siluer sound did Thebane towers raise:
                     Though sweet Vrania with her ten-string Lyre,
                     Vnto whose stroke the daily-rowling sphaeres
                     Dance their iust measures; Should with tune and tone
                     Tickle my eare-bred ayre: Yet can their notes
                     Those fabulous stones more enter, than my Soule.
                     Lead, poppy, Slumber stupifie my heart:
                     But Bedlame griefe actes gambolles in my braine.
                     The Centaures Wheele, Prometheus Hawke, The Vulture
                     Of Tityus, Sisyphus neuer mossie stone,
                     The tale of Danaids tubbe, and Tantalus gaping,
                     Are but flea-bitings to my Smart: I've slaine
                     A kinsman: more, A friend I dearely lou'd:
                     Nay more, no cause prouoking, but in rash
                     And hellish choller.
                     I had thought my Loue had cannon-proofe bin 'gainst
                     A world of iniuries: when see, all is split
                     By a small wind. Cursed be thou my Sword,
                     The Instrument of Fury: Cursed hand,
                     Which mad'st the thrust: But most accursed Part,
                     Whose ruddy flesh triangular boyld in flame,
                     Like an Aetnean, or Vesuvian Salamander.
                     That Breast, I so could hugge, that faithfull breast,
                     That snowy white, I with darke sanguine stayn'd;
                     And from the wounds red lips, his panting heart
                     Did seeme to speake, Is this a friendly deed?
                     
                     O no, Hirildas: Beares can harmelesse play,
                     Lyons can dally, and sheath vp their clawes:
                     I onely, worst of brutes, kill friends in iest.
                     Why dost Androgeus kindly-cruell keepe
                     Mee from their Sentence? Say, Law bids me dye:
                     If Law should not, Ile make that Law my selfe.
                     Shall Ensignes be display'd, and Nations rage
                     About so vild a wretch? Shall forraine hoofes
                     Kick vp our trembling dust, and must a Caesar
                     
                     
                        Redeeme my folly with a kingdomes fall?
                     First may I stop blacke Cerberus triple iawes.
                     Dye, Dye, thou hast out-liv'd thy selfe. Thou only,
                     Phaenix of females, still dost bind and bound
                     My runnagate spirit in these walles of mudde:
                     From thee, and For thee tis, I breath. Yet how
                     Borrow can I his Shape, or vse mine owne?
                     Odious before, now worse than hell-borne goblin
                     With brand and chaines, to skare this Doue all quaking
                     Twixt wrath and feare. But Time may fauour win:
                     When Hope doth fayle, then Knife or Rope begin.
Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 4. Scen. 3.
                  Cassib. Belin. Rollano.
                  
                     Cass.
                     Wisdome confirme my Sense: what seem'd their number?
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Rising from shore Coniecture might descry
                     A thousand Ships with painted prowes, to pave
                     The briny fields of Neptune, their broad sayles
                     Did Nereus canopy, Titans taper vayle.
                     As nations twenty nine 'gainst Troy built vp
                     A floating Delos of a thousand Ships,
                     To plough the liquid glasse: No frame of Pallas,
                     No crafty Sinon; but Those woodden horse
                     Did Troy dis-Troy: So Troynovant shall feele
                     Her Mothers Fate: Achilles comes againe:
                     And Pergamus againe shall sinke in dust:
                     They threaten.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cass.
                     Wonder! What can their Arsenalles spawne so fast?
                     Last yeere his Barkes and Gallyes were debosht;
                     This spring they sprout againe: Belike their Nauy
                     Like the Lernean adder faster growes,
                     The more tis prun'd. They come their last. Lord Deputy,
                     Lead on the present troopes, and leauy new.
                     Twere best I thinke to lett Him land, least view
                     Of his huge Nauy should our Commons fright:
                     Retire our selues to some place of advantage,
                     Entice him from his ships: So cutt the veines
                     Which nourish both: Enclos'd he cannot scape.
                  
                  
                     
                     Bel.
                     I rather iudge, We should oppose his footing,
                     Vsing the benefit of our naturall mound.
                  
                  
                     Cass.
                     Vncertaine tis, where, when, he makes in-road:
                     To furnish all, vnlikely: to neglect
                     Any, were dangerous, as Pelides heele.
                     Our shores are large, and levell: Then t'attend
                     His time and leasure, would exhaust the state,
                     Weary our souldiers.
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     All places may be strengthned more, or lesse:
                     As by last yeere, Discretion now may guesse.
                     The Clifts themselues are Bullwarkes strong: The Shelves
                     And Flats refuse great ships, the coast so open,
                     That euery stormy blast may rend their cables,
                     Put them from anchor: Suffering double warre,
                     Their men, pitcht battaile; and ships, navall fight.
                     For charges, tis no season to dispute:
                     Spend something, or loose all: Shall he maintaine
                     A fleete to inthrall vs, we detract small costs,
                     When freedome, life, and kingdome lye at stake?
                  
                  
                     Cass.
                     But the Assaylants are the flower of Italy
                     Backt with foure hundred Gallick horse, all tried
                     And gallant troopes, ioyn'd in one martiall body,
                     To giue a fuller stroke; When we Defendants
                     Scatterd along, can weake resistance make:
                     Plainenesse of ground affoording vs no shelter.
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     For what serues Art and Engines, Mounts and Trenches,
                     But to correct the nature of a plaine?
                     A few on firme land may keepe out a million,
                     Weaken'd by sea, false footing, billowes rage,
                     And ponderous rage. When as receiu'd within,
                     He prospers by our spoile; We feed a Viper:
                     And male-contents and rebells haue a refuge.
                     Nor were it safe, to venter all at once:
                     When one fought field being lost, swift ruine runnes
                     And rushing throwes downe all.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     We know our strength, and his: wee'l fight in field.
                     Some dozen miles from sea. An open Theater
                     Giues luster to our prowesse: To keep him out
                     
                        Supposes feare, not manhood. No, let him march,
                     Till he rowse death, and stride his future graue.
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     Your will commands, and mine obeies.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 4. Scen. 4.
                  Caesar, &amp;c. Ensigne, Drumme, Trumpet, Flag, Souldiers, Shipmen. The noyse of landing.
                  
                     Caes.
                     The coast is cleere. Our honour is the Goale.
                     In vaine doth Tagus yellow sand obey,
                     Rhenes horned front, and nimble Tygris running
                     For wager with the wind, which skimmes his top:
                     In vaine from Ganges to Hesperian Gades,
                     The Bounds markt out by Ioues two base-borne Sonnes,
                     Our Ecchoed Name doth sound: If we recoyle
                     From hence againe not victours.
                     Ye Pilotes old, who were begot on mere-Maides,
                     Whose Element is the Sea, bred and brought vp
                     In cradles rockt with stormes, and woodden walles,
                     Feare not to grapple with their seas. Feare not
                     Their bulkes, Brave veteranes: That extended masse
                     Is not of iron, but can bleed, and dye:
                     They were not dipt in Styx: nor are they Gyants,
                     Or wild Poetick Centaures we assayle:
                     Let then this voyage quit our credit lost,
                     And let Rage lash on Courage. Heere's the Game:
                     Life may be lost, but sure weele hold fast Fame.
                  
                  They march about, and goe out. The whole battaile with-in.
                  Cassib. Belin. &amp;c. Souldiers.
                  
                     Gass.
                     Our first attempt doth prosper: They retiring
                     Scudde to the bosome of their Firre-tree vaultes,
                     And vnder hatches hide themselues from death.
                     The Cornish band made havocke of their rankes,
                     Like Scythian wolues midst of a bleating fold:
                     The gingling launces, ratling chariot-wheeles
                     Madded their horse. The Bow men merrily shott.
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     Yet would our tributary Kings had succoured!
                     
                        We are decai'd they much in number growne,
                     And surely will make head againe.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Feare not, thou knowest I can euen with a whistle,
                     Hide Kent with glittering armes: More flaming sparkles
                     Paint not a freezing night: nor speckled Bees
                     Buzze not about sweet Hyblaes bloomy head.
                     But what need millions, when some thousands serue?
                     O did my Brother liue! wee'de clime the Alpes;
                     Like braue Mulmutius sonnes; make Romulus woolfe
                     Howle horrour in their streets, and Rome looke pale,
                     As when the Punicke Captaine eyed her walles.
march out.
                     
                  
                  Caesar. Volusene. &amp;c.
                  
                     Caes.
                     Are ye the Men, who neuer fought in vaine?
                     Who weare Bellonaes fauours, in your skarres:
                     I, ye are They. What then benummes our Spirits?
                     Our Empire from Quirinus narrow Center
                     Doth circling spread, and finds no brinke nor bottome.
                     Titan no later sets, nor earlier wakes,
                     Than he beholds our Provinces, Why, then?
                     What Priviledge hath this place? Haue wee, or They
                     The Phrygian powers? Haue they Palladium got?
                     No, no, Those gods our Capitoll keepe with ioy:
                     These only haue vn-daunted minds from Troy.
                     Enter Q. Atrius.
                     What newes, good Atrius?
                     
                  
                  
                     Atr.
                     No good newes from Atrius.
                     
                     When ominous Earth with shade and cloudy vapours
                     Had darknesse doubled, stormes began to sound,
                     The dabled South, ruffe-footed Aquilo,
                     Came rushing like two Rams, whose steeled hornes
                     Dart fiery sparkes: The clouds crusht breathe out flames:
                     Thunder and Lightning daunt all eares and eyes.
                     The windes and billowes striue, who loudest roare.
                     The skie distill'd in raine: his roome to fill,
                     Ambitious waues would clime the starry hill.
                     Our ships are batterd all, some fortie sunke.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     What diuell-Cacus drags our Fortune backe?
                     Doth Shee mooue retrograde? and hoyst vs vp.
                     That we may fall at heigth? Why doest Camillus
                     
                     
                        Each night torment my sleep, and cry, Reuenge?
                     I striue against the streame.
                  
                  Enter Androgeus, Mandubrace, souldiers.
                  
                     Androg.
                     Thus ioyne we Standards: And resigne the keies
                     Of Troynovant, with all our warlike forces.
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     By me the Trinobants submit, and Cenimagnians,
                     Segontiackes, Ancalites, Bybrockes, and Cassians,
                     Sixe worthy nations doe desire thy guard.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     All, all shall know our loue.
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     The Tyrant lies on Isis flowrie bankes,
                     Where a full Quier sing of white-surplist swannes.
                     The foordes vnleuell belly they haue fenced,
                     With sharpe stakes vnder water.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Nor stakes, lakes, foords, nor swords shall checke our progresse:
                     Those downie swannes shall heare more funerall notes.
                     Their Kings departed, Nennius dead, whose losse
                     Would teares extort euen from Pumicean eies;
                     Had Britaine nurst but such another Champion,
                     They might haue stucke their darts on our barr'd gates,
                     And Latium trembled with contrary fates.
                     In what now lies their hope?
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     Great numbers still remaine: nay worse, they laugh
                     At death, and boldly trust (as Druids preach)
                     Their soules who die in fight shall liue in ioy.
                     Hence count they dangers, benefits: and die
                     With freedome in their mouth, and willfull rage.
                     But let soft mildnes waite on women, Let
                     Thy wrath ring through the woods in dustie noise,
                     To tell thy comming. No man's built so loftie,
                     But his foundation meetes the humble dust:
                     Which vndermin'd, how high he pearc'd the clouds,
                     So deep he sinkes.
                     Hostile and ciuill foes shake top and roote
                     As windes inuade aboue, and Vines below.
                     And so will We.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     No doubt: This blow shall like an earth-quake mooue
                     The rootes and pillars of this sea-clipt Ile.
                     
                        A cloud of vultures shall attend our Campe,
                     And no more shall the fields beare Vert, but Gules:
                     The graine en-graind in purple die shall loose
                     His verdant hue. Bones, marrow, humane limbes
                     Shall putrifying reake, whose vapoured slime
                     Kindled on high may breed long-bearded Starres,
                     To tell more mischiefe, and out-beard Apollo.
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     Let's wast no time, least more vnto him flocke,
                     As humours glide to guard the wounded member.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     
                        Atrius, let our ships be drawne on shoare,
                     New-rigg'd and mended. I must needs confesse him
                     A darling of the gods; vnder whose colours
                     Starres, winter, skie, and tempests serue in pay,
                     And know both march and skirmish by his Drumme.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 4. Scen. 5.
                  Rollano▪ Eulinus hearkning.
                  
                     Roll.
                     O my deare Ladie, hast thou slaine thy selfe?
                     So fairely pure, so kindly chast, so
cries.
                     
                     A Venus and Diana mixt in one.
                     She eat her meate with studdes of Pearle, she kist
                     With Rubies, and she look't with Diamonds bright.
                     Fish seas, and foule the aire, hunt all the earth,
                     For such another bit, and loose your labour.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     O, why dost thou complaine.
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Had she not kill'd her selfe, no cruell Atropos,
                     No fury could for pitty cut her thread.
                     She was the Load-stone of all eies, The whet-stone
                     Of all braines, the touch-stone of all hearts: She was—
cries.
                     
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     O my presaging thoughts in vgly forme
                     Suggest some Tragedy. Speake: yet stay a while:
                     I know thou kill'st with speaking. Be then dumbe:
                     Let sound neere giue those Notions airie roabes.
                     Yet speake, dispatch me: Feare's as bad as death.
                     Oh, could no tongue affirme it! Is she dead?
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     My Mistresse is.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     VVither ye pleasant gardens, where she trod:
                     VVhite lillyes droope, and blasted daysies winke,
                     
                        And weep in pearely dew. Blind Vesper mourne,
                     Hang thy cold teares on euery grassie blade.
                     Groane loud ye woods, and teare your leafie haire:
                     Let wind and hoarie frost kill euery flower:
                     For she is gone, who made continuall May.
                     Let foggie mistes envellop Sunne and Starres:
                     For she is gone, who made perpetuall day.
                     Confounded Nature stand amaz'd, dissolue
                     Thy rowling engines, and vnbrace the Seas:
                     Fling all into their first disordered lumpe.
                     For thy chiefe paragon, thy rich Master-piece,
                     The Iewell, for which thou didst venter all,
                     Is lost, is lost. And can I liue to speake it?
                     How died she?
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     By a poisoned draught.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     The very word (poison) infects my breath.
                     Durst thou presume to passe that corrall portch?
                     Were not her Lippes sufficient Antidote?
                     Durst thou descend through those close winding staires
                     With treacherous intent? How could thy venome
                     Seaze on her, and not sweetned loose his vertue,
                     Or rather vitious qualitie? May toades,
                     Dragons, and mandrakes be thy gally-pottes:
                     This Bodie was a casket for the graces,
                     No caske for poison. With her dies all loue:
                     Cupid may breake his Bow, his arrowes burne,
                     Then quench his Taper in a flood of teares.
                     Is she dead?
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     Or in a long traunce.
                  
                  
                     Eul.
                     She may reuiue:
                     I'le visit her: Art may prolong her daies,
                     Whether she will or no.—
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 4. Scen. 6. Chorus.
                  
                     
                        1.
                        Alecto rising from the lakes
                        Of nights sad Empery:
                        With knotty bunch of curled snakes,
                        Doth lash faire Britany.
                     
                     
                        
                        2.
                        More ghastly monster did not spring,
                        From the Hybernian flood:
                        With which Morindus combating,
                        Of foe became his food.
                     
                     
                        3.
                        Shall no more Shepheards in the shade
                        sit whistling without care?
                        Shall neuer speare be made a spade,
                        And sword a plowing share?
                     
                     
                        4.
                        Grant heauen at last, that Musick loud
                        Of bloudy Mars be still:
                        That Britaine Virgins in a croud,
                        With hymnes the skie may fill.
                     
                  
                  
                     2. Song.
                     
                     
                        Nor is Landoraes losse,
                        The least part of our mournefull muse:
                        Ioue Iuno for to crosse,
                        This Troiane Dame for Bride did chuse.
                        Where Shee doth shine,
                        'Boue Guendoline,
                        The Amazon of her daies:
                        And Mercia wise
                        Law to deuise. O sound Landor. praise.
                     
                     
                        There doth she shine aboue,
                        Cleare as great Deliaes horned bow,
                        Bright as the Queene of Loue,
                        To shoote downe gentle beames below.
                        Sabrina dare
                        Not to compare
                        With her most splendent raies:
                        A ring the skie,
                        A gem her eie: O sound Lando. praise.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  Act. 5.
               
                  
                     Scen. 1.
                  Caesar, Androgeus, Mandubrace, &amp;c. souldiers.
                  
                     Caes.
                     Thus gaine we ground: yet still our foes will fight,
                     
                        Whether they winne or loose. With bloody drops
                     Our path is printed: Thames his maiden-cheekes
                     Blush with vermilion: Nations crave our League
                     On euery side: Yet still Cassibelane braves vs,
                     Nor will submit.
                  
                  
                     Androg.
                     Not farre hence Verolame lies, his chiefest fort,
                     By nature guarded round with woods and fennes,
                     By Art enclosed with a ditch and rampire:
                     From hence we must dislodge the Boare.
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     There are but two wayes to assayle this Towne:
                     Both which I know. Your parted army must
                     Breake thorow both at once, and so distract
                     His doubtfull reskues.
                  
                  Enter Volusene with Hulacus prisoner.
                  
                     Hul.
                     Draw slaves vnwilling, I dare meete my death:
                     And lead my Leader.
                  
                  
                     Vol.
                     You'le repent anon,
                  
                  
                     Hal
                     If I doe ill: But not for suffering ill.
                  
                  
                     Vol.
                     Your stoicall apathy will relent I know.
                     This Priest I caught within a shady grove,
                     Devoutly kneeling at a broad Okes foot.
                     Now He awaites your Doome.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     What god adore you?
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     Him, whom all should serue.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Whats the Moone?
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     Nights Sunne:
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Whats Night?
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     A foyle to glorifie the Day.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     What most compendious way to happinesse?
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     To dye in a good cause.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     What is a man?
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     An Hermaphrodite of soule &amp; body.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     How differ they in nature?
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     The body hath in waight, the soule in length.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     One question more: What dangers shall I passe?
                  
                  
                     Hul.
                     Many by land and sea: As steps to glory▪
                     
                     Throw Palatine on Aesquiline, on both
                     Heape Aventine, to raise one Pyramis: for a
                     Chaire of Estate, where thy aduanced Head
                     Among those Heroes pictur'd in the Starres,
                     Orion, Perseus, Hercules, may consult
                     With Iove himselfe. But shun the Senate house.
                     March round about the Caspian sea; search out
                     
                        'Mong Cedars tall the Arabian Phaenix nest;
                     Run counter to old Nile, till thou discouer
                     His sacred head wrapt vp in cloudy mountaines:
                     And rather than worke fayle, Turne Hellespont
                     Out of his channell; Digge that Isthmus downe,
                     Which tyes great Africk. Shun the Senate house.
                     Be Saturne, and so thou shalt not be Tarquine.
                     A Brutus strong,
                     Repayes in Fine:
                     Thy brutish wrong
                     To Brutus line.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Wee'll talke at leasure more.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 5. Scen. 2.
                  Cassib. Belin. &amp;c.
                  
                     Cass.
                     No rampires keepe him backe: He presses forward,
                     Though euery stampe he treads, seemes to coniure
                     The fates from their infernall center. None
                     But he, durst be so bold.
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     Yes, when Britaines lead, and Mandubrace insulting
                     With naked sword calles on the lagging souldiers:
                     When fearce Androgeus with revolted nations,
                     Vsher his army. No way halfe so quicke
                     To ruinate kingdomes, as by home-bred strife.
                     Thus while we single fight, we perish all.
                  
                  
                     Cass.
                     I, I, those treacherous caitiffes, rebell slaves:
                     O may their countryes heauy curse them sinke
                     Below the nine-fold brazen gates of hell:
                     That princox proud: I, twas a scape in policy,
                     I should haue slaine the whelps with their good Syre.
                     Let Britaines climactericall yeere now runne,
                     The Series breake of seuentie Kings: Nay let
                     One vrne conclude our ashes and the worlds.
                     Befall what will: In midst of horrors noyse,
                     And crackling flames, when all is lost, wee'll dye
                     With weapons in our hands, and victory skorne:
                     There's none that dye so poore, as they are borne.
                     Faithfull Belinus, let a Post command
                     
                        The Kentish Kings to set vpon his fleete:
                     Whilst we heere bid the bace. Foure thousand chariotteers,
                     (Such as did glide vpon the Phrygian Plaines,
                     And wheeling double seruice doe performe,
                     Both horse-mans speed, and foot-mans stable strength)
                     Still doe remaine: With these and flocking voluntaries
                     Wee'll giue him once more battell. Let the Captaines
                     Enter, and heare my charge.
Enter Captaines. He stands on a throne.
                     
                     Subiects and Fellow-souldiers; We must now try
                     For ancient freedome, or perpetuall bondage.
                     There is no third choise. The inraged foe
                     With cruell pride, proud avarice, hath spoyl'd
                     From East to West, hunting for blood and gaine.
                     Your wiues and daughters ravisht, ransackt townes,
                     Great bellyes ript with launces, sprawling babes,
                     The spouse about her husbands necke run through
                     By the same speare. Thinke on these Obiects:
                     Then choose them for your Lords, who spoyle and burne
                     Whole countryes; and call Desolation, Peace.
                     Yeeld, yeeld; That he ennobled by our spoyles,
                     May clime the Capitoll with triumphant carte,
                     You led fast fetterd through the staring streets,
                     For citie Dames to mocke your habite strange,
                     And fill their arras hangings with our story.
                     No: Brennus ghost forbid, who this night stood,
                     Before my eyes, and grimly furious spake:
                     Shall Britaine stoop to Romane Rods and Hatchets,
                     And servile tribute? Will ye so defame
                     Your ancestors, and your successors wrong,
                     Heires but of slauery▪ O, this day make good
                     The glory of so many ages past!
                     I see, you are incens'd, and wish to vse
                     Your weapons, not your eares.
                     All. To armes, to armes, to armes: Wee'll fight, and dye.
                  
                  Exeunt.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Act. 5. Scen. 3.
                  Eulinus, in a nightcap. vnbraced. Violl. Poynado. Playes and sings to the violl.
                  So the Siluer-feathered swan,
                  Both by death and colour wan,
                  Loues to sing before shee dye,
                  Leauing life so willingly.
                  But how can I sing a note?
                  When dead hoarsenesse stops my throat:
                  Or how can I play a stroke?
                  When my heart-strings all are broke.
                  Come guilty night, and with blacke velvet wings
                  Mantle me round; Let melancholike thoughts,
                  Hang all my braine with Blacks: This darkesome grove,
                  My gallery. So, all things suite my mind:
                  Such funerall colours please a gasping heart.
                  I dyed with thee Landora once: Now only
                  Some strugling spirits are behind, to be
                  Laid out with most thrift on thy memory.
                  Where shall I first begin my last complaint,
                  Which must be measur'd by my glasse of life?
                  At thee Hirildas? Slaine in furious moode,
                  By whose helpe only I inioy'd my loue?
                  Or thee Landora? dying for his sake,
                  And in thy death including mine?
                  Or at my Countries wracke? whose surface torne
                  Doth for my vengeance importune the Pole?
                  Or at my selfe? I, there is sorrowes spring.
                  Shall I goe wandring lurke in woods vnknowne,
                  A banisht Hermite, and sigh out my griefes?
                  Teaching the prettie birds to sing my deare,
                  My deare Landora: There to feed on acornes,
                  Drinke the cleare fountaine, and consume with weeping,
                  Were but an easie life, an easie death:
                  My violent passion must haue sudden vent.
                  Refined Soule, whose odoriferous light,
                  The damned hags stare at, and whining elves,
                  
                     Thinking it Heauen in hell: Behold my pangs,
                  Pittie my dying groanes, and be more soft.
                  O may our shadowes mingle; then shall I
                  Enuie no more those Citizens aboue,
                  The ambrosian iuncates of the Olympian hall
                  And all that gorgeous Roofe. But cowards talke.
                  Come thou last refuge of a wearisome life;
Drawes his Poynado.
                  
                  A pasport to the Elysian land, A key
                  To vnlocke my grieued in-mate. Loe I come.
                  O let this riuer from my eyes, this streame
vnbuttons.
                  
                  From my poore breast, beg fauour of thy ghost:
                  O let this luke-warme blood thy Rigour steepe,
stabs.
                  
                  And mollifie thy adamantine heart.
                  Leander-like I swim to thee through blood:
                  Be thy bright eyes my Pharos, and conduct me
                  Through the dull night of gloomy Erebus.
                  Flow, flow, ye liuely drops, and from my veines
                  Run winding to the Ocean of my blisse:
                  Tell her my loue, and if Shee still shall doubt,
                  Sweare that ye came directly from my heart.
                  I stay too long.
stabs agen.
Sweet Lady giue me wellcome.
                  Though I shall passe twelue monsters as the Sunne,
                  Or twelue Herculean labours on a row:
                  Yet one kinde looke makes all my iourney sweet
                  Thou Fayry-Queene of the Tartarian Court,
                  To whom Proserpine may the Apple giue,
                  Worthier than Shee, to warme old Plutoes bed:
                  See thy poore vassall weltering in his goare.
                  I faint, I faint.
                  I dye thy Martyr, as I liu'd thy Priest:
                  Great Goddesse be propitious, Sweet Landora —
                  falles and dyes.
               
               
                  
                     Act. 5. Scen. 4.
                  The foure Kings of Kent march ouer the stage. A Drum strucke vp within. Q. Atrius comes with Cingetorix prisoner. Rollano running. Volusene meetes him.
                  
                     Roll.
                     What shall I doee? How shall I scape?
falls for feare.
                     
                  
                  
                     Vol.
                     I scorne to take aduantage, Rise and Fight.
                  
                  
                     
                     Roll.
                     I had rather be kill'd quickly, quickly.
                  
                  
                     Vol.
                     Then die, as thou destrest.
thrusts at him.
                     
                  
                  
                     Roll.
                     O let me winke first.
bawles aloud.
                     
                     I shall neuer indure it. Oh, oh. I am pepper'd and salted.
                  
                  Exit. Volus. Roll. crawles away.
                  Cassibelane, Belinus, &amp;c.
                  
                     Cassib.
                     O that base Fortune should great spirits damp,
                     And fawne on muddie slaues: That enuious fate
                     Should ripen villany with a Syrian dew,
                     And blast sweet vertue with a Sirian flame.
                     A Catalogue of mischiefes doe concurre
                     Our Britaine Hector, Nennius dead: Our Kings
                     Angry to be refus'd, sit stil at home:
                     And then those traitors with their traine augment
                     His huge and expert Armie: Nothing stops him;
                     Riuers, nor Rampiers, Woods, nor dangerous Bogges;
                     On this side Thames his dismall Ensignes shine:
                     Last, Kents vnhappie rulers are at Sea
                     Ore-throwne, and our men almost spent. Then, Generall,
                     In desperate pride, and valours scornefull rage,
                     Let vs runne head-long through their armed tents,
                     And make their Campe a Shambles: So to raise
                     Our loftie toombes vpon their slaughtered heapes.
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     Nay, rather first lets parley for peace.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Ye Country-gods and Nymphes, who Albion loue,
                     Old Father Neptune, all ye powers diuine,
                     Witnesse my loyall care: If humane strength,
                     Courage, and policy, could a Kingdome saue;
                     We did our best. But discord, child of hell,
                     Numbers of traine-men, and each Captaine pickt
                     Out of a Province, make vs bow or breake.
                     In vaine we striue, when Deities doe frowne:
                     When Destinies push, Atlas himselfe comes downe.
                  
                  Enter Comius.
                  
                     Bel.
                     No mediator is so fit as Comius: And heer's the man.
                  
                  
                     Com.
                     Doe not the dangers which enuiron you,
                     
                        Call for a good conclusion? which I wish
                     As friend to both sides.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     No Comius: There is more behind, than Caesar
                     
                     Hath ouer-runne: Our Chariotters still driue,
                     Our harnesse still is worne: Through woods and lakes
                     Wee'l tire his daintie souldiers: Then set fire
                     On Townes, and sacrifice our selues, our wiues,
                     Our goods, and cattell, in one publike flame:
                     That wind may blow our ashes in his face.
                  
                  
                     Com.
                     So shall dead Elements curse your causelesse fury.
                     Rather conclude some friendly peace.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Thus farre we heare you: If with honoured termes,
                     And royall lookes, he will accept our faith:
                     We will obey, but neuer serue.
                  
                  
                     Com.
                     I'le vndertake as much.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 5. Scen. 5.
                  Androgeus, Themantius.
                  
                     Andr.
                     Thus ciuill warre by me, and factious broyles,
                     Deface this goodly land: I am reueng'd:
                     The cause Eulinus dead, my Anger dies.
                     He is our Vncle, and in danger's mouth;
                     Both claime relenting pitty. Whom peace made
                     A rampant Lyon, warre hath made a Lambe.
                     
                        Caesar shall not proceede, for priuate ends,
                     To captiuate our Ile: whose clamorous curse
                     Doth knock, I know, at Heauens Starre-nailed gates:
                     For that Ioues bird, impt with our plumes, ore-flew
                     The Oceans wall; To seeke her prey in Britaine.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     I, we haue made a Rod for our owne backes:
                     Fetters of gold are fetters. No gap worse
                     To let destruction in by, than to call
                     A forraine aide: who hauing seene our weaknesse,
                     And tasted once the fatnesse of our land,
                     Is not so easily thrust out, as admitted.
                     Such medicine is worse than the maladie,
                     Fretting the bowells of our kingdome.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     I know their hatred iust; and heere resigne
                     
                        All my birth-right to thee, my second selfe:
                     I must forsake my Countries sight, and seeke
                     New fortunes with this Emperour; In hope
                     To be rais'd vp, by his now rising wheele.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     O, doe not so, deare Brother. So to part,
                     Were to diuide one Indiuiduall Soule.
                     Nor thinke me so ambitious: I can liue
                     A priuate life, and see a regall Crowne,
                     With no more entry than I see the Sunne,
                     Glitter aboue me. Let not Lud's two sonnes
                     Be parted by a Sea: I hold your presence,
                     At higher price than a whole kingdomes pomp.
                     Keepe then your right: like those admired twinnes,
                     Let vs reioyce, mourne, liue, and die together.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     You shall a Scepter gaine.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     And loose a Brother.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     Beare you the Soueraigne power of this land.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     A body politicke must on two legges stand:
                     I'le beare a part, so to diminish enuy.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     I must away, and shun the peoples eie.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     If to your selfe vnkind, be kind to me:
                     For my sake stay at home: why will you flie?
                     Thinke you a stepdame soile giues sweeter sappe?
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     I: For trees transplanted do more goodly grow.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     And I'le count men but stockes, when they do so.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     I am resolu'd: All troubles brought a sleepe:
                     To leaue you with a parting kisse.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     And by that kisse
                     May I transfuse my soule, or quite expire?
                     Brothers haue often for a kingdome fought:
                     We striue to loose it. This is holy strife.
                     But heere I vow, if ere that sacred Lace
                     Shall gird my Temples: Rome must keep her boundes,
                     Or fish for Tribute in the dredfull deepe.
                  
               
               
                  
                     Act. 5. Scen. 6.
                  Caesar. Mandubrace.
                  
                     Andr.
                     Let gracious fauour smooth warres rugged brow:
                     
                        Cassibelane will compound: All rage must end:
                     We choose you Vmpire, for a friendly cloze.
                  
                  
                     
                     Caes.
                     It is my glory to end all with peace:
                     And for that cause, I Comius sent in hast,
                     For to conduct him hither.
                  
                  
                     Them.
                     This trump giues warning of the Kings approach.
                  
                  Cassibelane. Comius. Lantonus.
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Fate, and no fault of mine, makes me appeare,
                     To yeeld as far as honour giues me leaue.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Haile valorous prince, disdaine not this ingrafting
                     Into Romes Empire, whose command incloses
                     The whole Leuant, and whose large shadow hides
                     The triple-bounded Earth, and bellowing Seas.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     We shall obserue your will; so you impose
                     A league, no yoake.
They shake hands.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Thus we determine: That Crowne still shall stand;
                     Raigne as the totall Monarch of this Ile:
                     Till death vn-kings you. 'Twere, Androgeus, best
                     You in our traine kept honourable place:
                     And let Themantius weare the royall wreath.
                     You must forgiue the Townes which did reuolt,
                     Nor seeke reuenge on Trinobants, but let
                     Young Mandubrace possesse his Fathers Princedome.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Be all wrongs drencht in Lethe.
                  
                  
                     Andr.
                     Pardon my rash attempts.
Cassib. embraces Androg. and Mand.
                     
                  
                  
                     Mand.
                     Count me your loyall friend.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     In signe of league, you shall vs pledges giue,
                     And yeerely pay three thousand pound of siluer,
                     Vnto our Treasury. So let these decrees
                     Be straight proclaim'd through Troynovant, whose Tower
                     Shall be more fairely built at my charge, as
                     A lasting Monument of our arriuall.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     All shall be done: Renowned Prince, whose worth,
                     Vnparalelld both as a Friend and Foe,
                     We doe admire.
                     Accept this Surcoate, starrified with pearles,
                     And Diamonds, such as our owne shoares breed.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     And you receiue this massie Cup of gold,
                     Loues earnest, and Memoriall of this day:
                     
                        By this, suppose our Senate cals you friend.
                  
                  They sit together.
                  
                     Lant.
                     Now time, best Oracle of Oracles,
                     Father of truth, the true sense doth suggest
                     Of Dians answer;
                     The Lyon and the Eagle doe designe
                     The Britaine and the Romane states, whose armes
                     Were painted with those Animals: Both fierce
                     Weary at last conclude: The Semicircles,
                     First letters of the Leaders names, we see
                     Are ioyn'd in true loues endlesse figure.
                     Both come of Troiane race, both nobly bold,
                     Both matchlesse Captaines, on one Throne behold.
                  
                  
                     Caes.
                     Now the Tarpeyan rocke ore-lookes the world;
                     Her Empire bounded onely by the Ocean;
                     And boundlesse Fame beates on the starry Pole.
                     So Danow crawling from a mountaines side,
                     Wider and deeper growes, and like a Serpent,
                     Or Pyramis reuerst; improues his bignesse,
                     As well as length: Till viewing countries large,
                     And fed with sixty riuers, his wide mouth
                     On the Euxine Sea-nymph gapes, and feare doth stir,
                     Whether he will disgorge, or swallow her.
                  
                  
                     Cassib.
                     Since the great guide of all, Olympus King,
                     Will haue the Romanes his Vice-Royes on earth:
                     Since the red fatall eyes of crow-blacke night,
                     Fling their malignant influence on our state:
                     Since Britaine must submit: It was her fame,
                     None but a Iulius Caesar could her tame.
                  
                  While Trumpets sound: Androgeus and Themantius imbracing take leaue. All depart.
               
               
                  
                     Act. 5. Scen. 7. Chorus.
                  
                  
                     1. Song.
                     
                     
                        Come fellow Bards and sing with cheere;
                        Since dreadfull Alarums we shall no more heare.
                        
                           Come louely peace, our Saint diuine,
                        Oliue and Lawrell doe loue for to twine.
                        The Graces, and Muses, and Nymphes in a round:
                        Let voice beate the aire, and feet beat the ground.
                     
                     
                        So Hells blacke image chas'd away,
                        Eos doth dandle the goldy-lock'd day:
                        So Bruma banisht all forlorne,
                        Cupid and Flora the spring doe adorne.
                        And so the grim fury of Mars laid in graue,
                        A merrier ending doth friendly peace craue.
                     
                  
                  
                     2. Song. A Morisko.
                     
                     The Skie is glad that Starres aboue,
                     Doe giue a brighter splendor:
                     The Starres vnfold their flaming gold,
                     To make the ground more tender:
                     The ground doth send a fragrant smell,
                     That aire may be the sweeter:
                     The aire doth charme the swelling Seas,
                     With pretty chirping meeter:
                     The Sea with rivers water doth
                     The plants and flowers dainty:
                     The plants doe yeeld their fruitfull seed,
                     That beasts may liue in plenty:
                     The Beasts doe giue both food and cloth,
                     That man high Ioue may honour:
                     And so the world runnes merrily round,
                     When peace doth smile vpon her.
                     Oh then, then Oh: Oh then, then Oh:
                     This Iubilee last for euer:
                     That Forraine spight, or Ciuill fight,
                     Our quiet trouble neuer.
                  
                  Exeunt.
                  Mercury reducing the Ghostes of Camillus, and Brennus.
                  
                     Cam.
                     How brauely Caesar past the angry Maine?
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     How brauely was he backe repulst againe?
                  
                  
                     
                     Cam.
                     How did he wheele his sword in Nennius face?
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     How did he loose his sword, and flie apace?
                  
                  
                     Cam.
                     How did againe his Army fill your coast?
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     I, when our Princes did conduct his hoast.
                  
                  
                     Cam.
                     How did they pierce through Isis dangerous flood?
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     But made her swell, and bank-rupt with their blood.
                  
                  
                     Cam.
                     Mirrour of Captaines, Iulius stile hath wonne.
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     But we may iustly brag of two for one.
                  
                  
                     Cam.
                     Confesse, our valorous race hath now repaid
                     The Allian Massacre, and our cities Flame:
                     See how they yeeld, and yeerely Tribute pay.
                  
                  
                     Brenn.
                     No, proud Dictator: Both do weary stand
                     On equall termes: Both wish a peacefull League.
                     But if they shall oppresse; know, Generous spirits
                     Will breake this Compact, like a Spiders webbe.
                  
                  
                     Merc.
                     Ioues will is finisht: And (though Iuno frowne,
                     That no more Troiane blood shall die the stage)
                     The worlds fourth Empire Britaine doth embrace.
                     The Thunder-bearer with a Ianus looke
                     At once viewes ruddie morne, and cloudie West:
                     Her wings displaied ore this Terrestriall egge,
                     Will shortly hatch an Vniuersall peace:
                     For Ioue intends a fauour to the world.
                     It now remaines, That you two martiall wights
                     Cease from your brauing one anothers worth:
                     You must be friends at last. The cloze is sweete,
                     When after tumults, hearts and hands doe meete.
                  
                  Exeunt.
                  
                     Nec Lusisse pudet, sed non incidere Ludum.
                  
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

