
   
      
         
            The copy of a letter describing the wonderful woorke of God in deliuering a mayden within the city of Chester, from an horrible kinde of torment and sicknes 16. of february 1564
            Fisher, John, of Chester.
         
         
            
               1565
            
         
         Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00792
            STC 10910
            ESTC S119671
            99854878
            99854878
            20333
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00792)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20333)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 567:3)
         
         
            
               
                  The copy of a letter describing the wonderful woorke of God in deliuering a mayden within the city of Chester, from an horrible kinde of torment and sicknes 16. of february 1564
                  Fisher, John, of Chester.
               
               [18] p.   
               
                  By Iohn Awdely, dewyllyng [sic] in litle Britayne streete, beyonde Aldersgate,
                  Imprinted at Londo[n] :
                  23. of March 1564 [i.e. 1565]
               
               
                  Dedication signed: I. F. Signed at end: The names of the wytnesses hereof, which also dyd set to their handes. Sir William Caluerley knight, Richard Hurlestone Esquier. Iohn Fisher Gentleman.
                  Title is from leaf A3r.
                  Publication year is according to Lady Day dating.
                  Concerning the exorcism of Anne Milner by John Lane, a minister in the county of Chester.
                  Signatures: A B¹.
                  Imperfect; title page torn, with loss of text.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Milner, Anne.
               Lane, John, d. 1605.
               Exorcism --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2005-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ The Copy of a Letter Describing the wonderful
woorke of God in deliuering a
Mayden within the City of Che
               ster,
from an horrible kinde of
torment and sicknes
16. of February
1564.
            
               O England thou behold a fact most 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Shewed forth by God in this thy natiue land
               
               Sithe by gods woord thou setst so lytle care.
               God. God I say, begyns to stretch his hande.
               As in this booke thou mayest wel vnderstand.
               A Mayd but young, late with great ill 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               But now by God she is agayne re
                     •
                  est.
            
            ¶ Imprinted at Londō by
John Awdely, dewllyng in litle
Britayne streete, beyonde Aldersgate.
23. of March.
1564.
         
         
            
            
            ¶ To his very
friend Maister J. D.
            AFter harty salutacions
letting al other matters
passe, these chiefly are to signifye
vnto you: That here
of late hath hapned a wonderful
cure of a Mayd with
in this Citye, wrought by
Gods power in his faithful
Minister &amp; Preacher of Jesus
Christ, Mayster Lane,
to the auancement of Gods
glory, and to the great marueiling
of all those inhabiting
in these partes. And
least the same should be misreported,
or the wicked suffred

to wrest thinges, to abuse
Gods Preachers, &amp; for
that the thyng is so rare &amp;
notable that it shoulde not
be kept from the posteritye,
I haue therfore sēt you the
whole tru discourse therof,
described with the hande of
Syr Wyllyam Caluerley
knight, Richard Hurleston
Esquire, and myne own. I
could haue had euerye man
here to haue done the lyke,
but cōsidering we haue had
good profe the one with the
other, I thought this shall
suffice, praying you to put
the same in print.
            
               From the City of Chester the .xv. of
March. 1564.
                
               Your friend J. F.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ The copy of a letter describing
the wonderful worke of
God, in deliuering a Maiden within
the City of Chester, from an horrible
kinde of torment and
sickenes, 16. of February.
Anno. 1564.
            
            HAuing receiued your letter, &amp;
therby vnderstanding aswel
what brute hath lately happened
in your partes, concernyng
the deliuery of a womā here within
the City of Chester, from a most
monstrous and horrible kynde of
torment and disease, as also howe
desirous you are to learn the truth
therof: I am contented in gratefieng
this your request, to signifye
herein as is for truth knowen and
accepted. The storye therfore was
thys:
            Anne Mylner a Mayden of the
age of .xviii. yeres, daughter to Rā
               dulphe
Mylner, and broughte vp

in her Fathers house, wythin the
bridge strete of the same City, wēt
the .xviii. daye of October last, to
bring her Fathers Kyne into the
fieldes. And at her returne, comming
in the high way neare to the
City, was sodaynlye taken wyth
great feare, and thoughte that she
saw a whyte thing compassing her
round about, and so amased, came
to her fathers house, &amp; in the nexte
morning felt her selfe greued, &amp; very
sore in al the partes of her body,
which so increased, that thereupon
she was enforced to keepe her bed,
beyng verye sicke. And during the
space of fyue dayes then next ensuing,
did not take anye kynde of bodely
sustenance, as her Parentes
hath sundry tymes declared. She
had her fyt and traunce almost frō
houre to houre, and had neuer aboue
three houres rest in the day &amp;

night. Neyther did eate during the
time of her sycknes, but once in ech
xxiiii. houres, and then most commonly
a litle quantitye of breade
and cheese, which notwithstāding
was done with wonderfull snatching
and rashnes.
            The maner of her disease and
sycknes was suche (as here after,
touching the time of her cure, shall
be more perticularly described) that
vnto her out of al partes of the citye,
repayre of verye manye was
made. Yea, insomuche that after
Maister John Pierce, one of the
Canons of the Cathedrall churche
of Chester, and Reader of the Didinity
Lecture there, with diuers
persons of reputacion had sene the
Mayden, he with his Auditorye in
December last, at the ende of hys
Lecture, kneling vpon their knees
made speciall prayers vnto God,

for her deliuerace.
            After this it chaunced Mayster
John Lane, late fellow of Christs
Colledge in the Uniuersity of Cā
               bridge,
&amp; now a famous and godly
Preacher of the Gospell of Jesus
Christ, within the County of Chester,
preaching at Torperley, at the
request of Raufe Done Esouyer, about
the xxi. of Januarye last, metther
with two men of the sayd City,
the one being a nere neyghbour
to this woful woman: who then among
other talke, demaunded of
Maister Lane, whether ther were
not some possessed wyth spirits as
in times past, and for confirmacion
hereof spake of the sayd Mayden,
&amp; alledged the horryblenes of her
torment to be suche, at the time of
her traunce, that it could argue nothing
els, but that she was possessed
with some spirite. And further

said, that she had remayned in that
miserable plight .xv. or. xvi. wekes,
and (as I suppose, hauing hearde
howe it is well knowen to diuers
credible persons in these partes,
what rare and syngular remedye
god hath wrought by M. Lane, to
some that sustained of late no smal
decay of minde and memory, or els
being of that religion, as in theese
dayes seeke myracles to confirme
Gods woorde) desyred him at his
next comming to the City of Chester,
to see the tormented Mayden,
and they would bring him vnto
her.
            Maister Lane then condecending
to their request, &amp; at his next
repayre vnto the sayd City, lodged
in the house of Syr William Caluerly
Knight, wheron Friday being
the .xvi. of Februarye laste (at
which time the Assise was hloden

in Chester) met agayne by occasion
with the sayd two men: who after
they had put hym in remembrance
of hys promise, &amp; had disclosed the
maner of the Maydens torment to
Syr William Caluerley, syr Wylliam
Sneyd Knightes, and my Ladye
Caluerley, with diuers other
then desirous to see the Mayden,
went al together, and brought maister
Lane vnto the sayd Mylners
house (to see the Mayden, and thē
to hym vnknowen) about two of
the clocke in the after noone of the
same .xvi. day of February, &amp; there
finding the Mayden in her traunce
after her accustomed maner, lying
in a bed within the haule, her eyes
halfe shut, shalfe open, looking as
she had bene agast, neuer mouyng
either eye or eye lyd, her teeth somthing
open, with her toung doublyng
betwene, her face somewhat

red, her head as heauy as leade to
lift at, she lay stil as a stone, and feeling
her pulce, it beat with as good
measure, as if she had bene in perfite
health. And in this sort beholding
her, almost during the fourth
part of an houre, her bellye began
to moue, swelling vp &amp; down, somtime
beneath her chest, sometyme
vp to the throte, in suche vehemenry,
that a man would haue thought
she would haue burst. Then sodenly
she lifteth her self vp in her bed,
bending backwards in such order,
that almost her head and fete met,
falling downe somtime on the one
syde, somtime on the other, but rysyng
againe so sodenly, that the beholders
could not imagine howe if
might bee possible so quicklye shee
coulde without ayde of hande, cast
her selfe (her belly being vpwarde)
into the fourme of a hoope.
            
               
Maister Lane demaunded of
her that kepte this cruell handled
creature, whether shee coulde not
keepe her downe? Who answered
no, and sayd that she had once tryed
it, and then was almost cast into
the fyre. Then desired he that she
woulde permitte him to assay if
hee coulde holde this dolefull woman
downe. Shee aunswered
yea, but yet sayd it woulde not preuaile.
W
                  •
               l said Maister Lane, by
the grace of God it may preuayle.
And therupon after that this pitiful
Maydē had lifted her self. 4. or
v. times in such wonderful maner
as before is noted, hee tooke her in
hād, &amp; with much ado pluckt down
her feete, and wyth more ado kept
them downe, holdinge her handes,
sytting vpon her legs, in whom he
found such strength and vehement
panges, that he was fully perswaded

she was possessed.
            The people present, seing hym
so to continue with her, and her
paines encrease, some thought best
he should let her alone, saying that
it woulde haue the course. Whom
maister Lane desired to be quyet,
and let God woorke, willing them
to pray to God for her, for asmuche
as in him onely consisteth her deliuerance
from that payne, and that
god was as strōg as euer he was.
And when she was in the vehemēt
panges the beholders called vpon
god for her, maister Lane secretly
sayd the fifty Psalm, &amp; oftē desired
God, through the bloud of his sōne
Jesus Christ, to ease the Maiden,
not doubting of his mercye in that
behalfe.
            And when he had thus striued
with her the space of two houres,
that the drope trickled downe hys

face, he had thought to haue commended
her vnto God: but then againe
it came to mynde to tary the
end, and so began a freshe to striue
with her, euer secretly praying &amp; calling
vpō the bloud of Christ, &amp; whē
her belly was pressed downe wt as
much weight &amp; strēgth as could be,
by those yt wer present, she stryued
more thē before, and diuers times
with the vehement swelling of her
bellye, shee was verye like to haue
throwne them ouer, that so helde
downe her body.
            At the last Maister Lane called
for viniger, wherat the stāders
by marueiled, saying, that yt thing
with muche more had bene often
tymes attempted, but to no purpose.
Notwithstanding he ceased
not to call styll for it, saying, that
God might do that then, which he
did not before, and so receiued viniger,

put it into his mouth &amp; blewe
it into the Maydēs nostrels, wherat
she cryed a Lady, Lady. He thē
willed her to cal vpō God, and the
bloud of Christ, &amp; in these doinges
she being astonied▪ he called againe
for more viniger. Wherat she cried:
No, no, no more for Gods sake.
            Thē maister Lane willed her to
speake &amp; say after him, &amp; so he &amp; all
thē present, said the Lords prayer
&amp; Te deum, she saying after them.
            After this her deliueraunce, she
then continually called vpon God,
and by the appointment of maister
Lane, she had her clothes put on, &amp;
meate brought, wherof she did eat
a little. This done, maister Lane
willed to try whether she could go.
Whereunto, albeit that those then
present answered that it was not
possible, for that shee had not gone
in al the time of .xvii. weekes then

last past, yet master Lane affirmed
that the same God which gaue her
speche, could geue her strength also
to go: and so departing the place,
vntill the women had gotten on
her hosen, and then comming in againe,
wyl
                  •
               ed her in the name of
God to come to him, standing in
th
                  •
                other syde of the house, whych
she did. And thereupon after talke
had wyth her of the maner of her
taking, &amp; admonishing her to haue
a stedfast faith in Christ, and to occupy
her selfe in praier, left her.
            My Lady Caluerley, maistres
Erauenor, wyfe to John Erauenor,
with diuers other credible per
so as wer present, during such time
as mayster Lane was wyth the
mayden, and are eye wytnesses to
these his doinges.
            The next day following, mayster
Lane preached at saynt Maries

within the sayde Citye, before
John Chrogmarton Esquier, the
Quenes maiesties high Justice in
the Countye of Chester, at whych
sermon the late recouered Maiden
was present.
            Upon this so wonderful a cure
great talke was had in eche company
within the City, that therupon
the Mayden was not onelye
brought vnto the said Justice, and
maister Lane afterwardes vppon
earnest request by som of hys friendes,
halfe constrayned, dyd wryte
hys whole doinges therin: but also
maister Rogers. Archdeacon of
Chester, in his sermon made in the
Cathedrall Church of Chester, the
iiii of this instāt month of March,
before the Maior of the Citye, the
Bishops of Chester and of Saynt
Assaphats, with a great multitude
of the Citizens besides, hauing occasion

offered by the wordes of the
then present Gospel, touched thys
fact: Alledging that what so euer
was the originall cause of so great
and straūge a disease, yet was the
cure wonderfull, and wrought by
God, either to the great commodity,
or els for the great plague of the
City of Chester, and the countrye
adioyning. The Mayden remayneth
at this presēt (praysed be god)
in perfit good health and lyking.
            Thus truly, and as briefly as I
myght, you haue the effect of your
request. 
            
               Writtē at the City of Chester,the .viii. of March. An. 1564.
                ¶ The names of the wytnesses hereof,
which also dyd set to their
handes.
                  
                     ¶ Sir William Caluerley knight,
                     ¶ Richard Hurlestone Esquier.
                     ¶ John Fisher Gentleman.
                  
               
            
         
      
   

