
   
      
         
            The rules and righte ample documentes, touchinge the vse and practise of the common almanackes, which are named ephemerides A briefe and shorte introduction vpon the iudiciall astrologie, for to prognosticate of thinges to come, by the helpe of the sayde ephemerides. With a treatise added hereunto, touchinge the coniunction of the planets, in euery one of the. 12. signes, and of their prognostications and reuolutions of yeres. The hole faithfully, and clerely translated into Englyshe by Humfrey Baker.
            Canons &amp; documents tresamples, touchant l'usage &amp; practique des communs almanachz, que l'on nomme ephemerides. English
            Fine, Oronce, 1494-1555.
         
         
            
               1558
            
         
         Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00750
            STC 10878.7
            ESTC S107419
            99843120
            99843120
            7830
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00750)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7830)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 469:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The rules and righte ample documentes, touchinge the vse and practise of the common almanackes, which are named ephemerides A briefe and shorte introduction vpon the iudiciall astrologie, for to prognosticate of thinges to come, by the helpe of the sayde ephemerides. With a treatise added hereunto, touchinge the coniunction of the planets, in euery one of the. 12. signes, and of their prognostications and reuolutions of yeres. The hole faithfully, and clerely translated into Englyshe by Humfrey Baker.
                  Canons &amp; documents tresamples, touchant l'usage &amp; practique des communs almanachz, que l'on nomme ephemerides. English
                  Fine, Oronce, 1494-1555.
                  Baker, Humfrey, fl. 1557-1587.
               
               [112] p. : ill.  
               
                  In Fletestrete nere to S. Dunstons church by Thomas Marshe,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  [1558?]]
               
               
                  A translation of: Fine, Oronce.  Les canons &amp; documents tresamples, touchant l'usage &amp; practique des communs almanachz, que l'on nomme ephemerides.
                  Printer's name and address from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.
                  Signatures: A-G.
                  Identified as STC 21449 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Astrology --  Early works to 1800.
               Ephemerides --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2007-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ The Rules and righte ample Documentes, touchinge the vſe and practiſe of the common Almanackes, which are named Ephemerides.
            
            ¶ A briefe and ſhorte Introduction vpon the Iudiciall Aſtrologie, for to prognoſticate of thinges to come, by the helpe of the ſayde Ephemerides.
            
            ¶ With a treatiſe added hereunto, touchinge the Coniunction of the Planets, in euery one of the. 12. ſignes, and of their Prognoſtications and Reuolutions of yeres.
            ¶ The hole faithfully, and clerely tranſlated into Englyſhe by Humfrey Baker.
            
         
         
            
            
            ¶ To the louynge Reader.
            
               
                  IOſephus, the true Hyſtoriographe (gentle reader) hathe wrytten in his firſt boke of the Judaical hyſtories y• the fyrſt inuēters of Aſtronomy, and the inquiſitours of the courſe and celeſtiall mouementes haue bene the ſonnes of Seth who wylling to leaue ſome memory therof vnto their chyldren and poſteritye, dyd ordayne and make two great pillers, the one of earth beyng harde dried, and the other of Copper, in the whyche they dyd graue the prynciples of the ſeuen Artes liberall, and eſpecially that of Aſtrologie. And they wrote the ſame in the ſayd pillers, to thende that if the worlde ſhoulde periſhe by fier, or by water, (as they dyd

vnderſtande of their good father Seth: who had learned the ſame of Adam) that then one of the ſayde pillers ſhoulde abyde whole, and that the Scyence of Aſtronomie ſhoulde not periſhe. Some do affirme that Abraham dyd firſt find it, other ſaye that it was Moyſes, Dyodore Sicilian ſayeth, that the Egiptyans were the firſte Authors, and Herodote wryteth that the Phenicians wer the inuenters, but who ſo euer they were, it lyttle forceth, let vs therefore leaue the inquiſition vnto the curious and praiſe we God the creatoure of his diuine grace, who hath willed to illuminate the vnderſtanding of them whiche haue left vs in writing the art of Aſtronomie, to our great commoditie and profyt. And ſeinge that the people at thys preſente are dayly more intentiue, &amp; enclined alſo to reade &amp;

to haue vnderſtandynge in artes and ſciences, as ſome which do folowe polletycke and cyuell matters, do applie them ſelues to vnderſtād the lawes of Cities, and Regions, and of ſuch thynges as apperteyne vnto the feates of war. Other there be whiche gyue thē ſelues to read the holly ſcriptures according to the vnderſtandynge of holy Church, to thende that thereby they maye be ſtirred and brought to lyue more vertuouſly: and if ther be any which other wiſe do, we ought to pray vnto God that he wold in ſuche wiſe amende theim, that they take not his holy word in vaine: other ther bee whyche are deſirous to reade Hiſtories &amp; Poeſies, and ſome haue affection to read bookes of Aſtrologye, &amp; to haue knowledge of the celeſtiall conſtellacions, &amp; mouements, vnto whom thys preſente

treatiſe of the rules &amp; documents of the comon Almanackes named Ephemerides (tranſlated into engliſhe) ſhal be right expedient &amp; neceſſary, ſeing yt theſe rules are the pathe &amp; way vnto the knowledge of the ſaid Ephemerides, for by thē are foūd the courſe, &amp; mouemēts of the lightes and planets, wyth other neceſſary thinges of Aſtrology wherby to iudge &amp; Prognoſti eate of the whether, and of things to come, as by the table folowing more plainly doth appere. Take therefore in good worthe (louing Reader) theſe few rules, being my firſt traduction, &amp; loke ſhortely if God ſpare me life for other workes apperteining vnto this worthye Arte.
            
               ¶ And this gentle Reader,
               I moſt hartely the require
               To examine well theſe Rules,
               And thou ſhalt haue thie deſire.
            
            Finis.
         
         
            
            ¶ The Table of the Rules and generall thinges conteyned in this volume.
            
               OF the thinges conteined in the beginninge of the Ephemerides.
            
            2 Of the Eclipſes of the ſunne and of the moone
            
            3 For to knowe the quantitie of the Eclipſes.
            4 Of the directions and retrogradations of the. 5. planetes.
            5 Of the true mouementes of the lightes and planetes and other thinges cō
               teined in the ſeconde face of the ſayde Ephemerides.
            
            6 Of the equalitie and vnequalitie of the naturall dayes.
            7 The maner howe to bring the true place and mouement of the moone vnto the true noone ſtede or middaye.
            
               8. To knowe the true place and moue mente of the lightes at euerye hower you liſte, be it before or after middaye.
            9. To bring the true mouement of the moone vnto what meridian ye pleaſe.
            10. Of the latitude of the .v. planetes, Saturne, Iupiter, Mars, Venus, and Mercurye.
            
            11. Of the latitude of the moone.
            
            12. Of the aſpectes of the moone, vnto the ſunne, and planets, and other thinges conteined in the right and ſeconde face of the ſayd Ephemerides.
            
            13. Howe and by what maner ye may bring the newe and full Moone and the Eclipſes vnto what meridian you wyll.
            14. Of the aſpectes of the ſunne vnto the planetes, &amp; of the planets amonge theim ſelues, and of the dragon of the Moone
            
            15. To knowe when the planets be oriental or occidentall.
            16. To knowe the quantitie of the day

and of the nighte, and at what hower the ſunne riſeth and ſetteth.
            17. Of the. 12. houſes of heauen and of their nature accidental accordyng vnto the iudgement of the Aſtrologiās
            
            18. Howe you may erecte or calculate the 12. houſes of heauen accordinge vn to the Ephemerides.
            
            19. Of the diuiſion of the Zodiake, &amp; of the nature of the. 12. ſignes.
            20. Of the nature and complection of the lightes and the. 5. planets.
            21. Of the ſtrength and accidentale nature of the aſpectes.
            22. The declaracion of the table of the fixed ſtarres whiche are in the ſayde Ephemerides.
            
            23. Of the. 28. manſyons or bidynge places of the Moone.
            
            24. A declaracion of the table which is before the Ephemerides, touching the force, dignity, exaltacion, and other termes or boundes of the planets and euery of the. 12. ſignes.
            
               25. General rules &amp; perticulers wher by to iudge of the mutacion &amp; change of the ayre.
            26. Other rules and general doctrines wherby to iudge more ſurely of the varietee of the time and mutacion of the ayre by the coniunctiōs, quadratures, and oppoſitions, of the ſunne &amp; of the moone.
            
            27. Of the aſpectes and conſtellations whiche are to be obſerued and choſen, to beginne and ende happelye all workes and humaine buſineſſe.
            28. Of the elections, which are mete to be obſerued in the Flebotomie or lettinge of bloud.
            29. Of Elections to take medecine.
            30. Of Elections too ſowe and plante trees and vines.
            The ende of the Table general.
            
         
      
      
         
            ¶Hëare after enſueth the Rules of the Ephemerides, moſte amply tranſlated into Englyſhe.
         
            ¶ Of thynges conteyned at the begynnyng and entring of the Ephemerides The firſt Rule, or Canon.
            
               FOR to haue cleare, and eaſye vnderſtandynge of the vſe, and practyſe of the Ephemerides, in leuynge all ſuperfluous thynges &amp; wordes, it is conuenient firſt to note that at the begynnynge: and entrynge of euerye Ephemerides, is wrytten the yeare for the whyche it ſerueth, and apperteyneth, and after there foloweth the common thynges of the eccleſiaſticall compoſt and kalender, that is too ſaye, the circle of the moone, called the golden nombre, the circle of the ſunne, the Dominicall letter, and the Indyction Romane, called in latten Indictio Romana, wyth the monthes and dayes,

vpon the whyche the mouable feaſtes in that yeare maye be celebrated accordyng to their order.
         
         
            Of the Eclipes of the ſunne and mone ſecond Rule.
            COnſequentlye are noted and figured the eclypſes of the ſunne, and of the moone, whyche ſhall appere the ſame yeare, and fyrſte is wrytten the monthe, daye, hower, and mynute, of the mydle time of the ſayde eclypſes, that is to ſaye, when the ſunne or the moone, ſhall come into the moſte obſcuration, or darckenes that maye then happen vnto theym, afterwardes is noted the halfe of the tyme that the ſayed eclipſes ſhall endure, or continewe, that is to ſaye from the begynnynge vnto the greateſt obſcuration aboueſayde, or from that darknes vnto the ende: thirdlye are noted the partes of the ſunne, or of the moone, whych ſhalbe eclypſed, and they are called eclipty
                  ••
               e poyntes, as well in the perticuler eclipſes, as in the vniuerſall, and it is cō
               ueniente to ymagen that the Diametre vyſuall of the ſunne, and of the moone, (that is to ſaye, taken and ymagened according

to the iudgement of the ſight (is deuided into. 12. egall partes, the whych are brought backe into the moone, in retournynge towardes the begynnynge of theym, and they doo make the nombre of. 24.
            And it is to be noted y• the ſunne can neuer be eclipſed vniuerſallye throughe all places of ye earth, nor yet of one like ſort, quātitie, or diſpoſition, by reſon of divers aſpectes of the inhabitāts, and although the ſunne do appeare at ſome times wholy eclipſed, it cānot be ouer al places, nor by any notable ſpace of time, by cauſe the eclipſe of the ſunne dothe come by the interpoſition of the moone, betwene the ſunne and vs, and that the moone is of a more ſodaine and ſwifter mouement thē is the ſunne, and is more nearer vnto vs and alſo leſſer then all the earthe, and the moone, and the earth are both much leſſe then is the ſunne, and for to ſay the truth the ſunne neuer loſeth his light, as doth the moone entringe into the ſhaddow of the earthe, when ſhe is Diametrally oppoſite vnto the ſunne for the ſayde ſhaddowe doth then depriue the moone of her lighte (which ſhe receyueth of the ſunne. By the Interpoſition of the ſayde earthe

whyche is then betwene the moone and the ſunne.
         
         
            For to knowe the quantitie of the ſaid eclipſes. 3. Rule.
            IN the eclipſe then of the moone, if the eclipticke pointes bee leſſe then. 12. the eclipſe ſhalbe particuler (as the ſame of the ſunne) accordynge vnto the proportion of the ſaide pointes vnto. 12., and if the ſayde pointes be preſiſely. 12. the ſayd eclipſe ſhalbe vniuerſall without during that is to ſaye that ſhe ſhall ſodenlye begynne to recouer her lyghte, but if the ſaide pointes bee more then. 12. it betokeneth that the moone ſhall be wholy eclipſed by ſome ſpace of time, and ſoo muche the more, as the ſaide pointes are, or ſhal be in greateſt nombre.
            And to knowe then howe longetyme the moone ſhalbe wholy depreued of her lighte, you ſhall take the ſaide eclipticke pointes, and the mynutes if there be any (for euery pointe is deuided into. 60. minutes) the whiche you ſhall fynde in the Ephemerides, and you ſhall ſeeke theim at the lefte hande of the table entitulid. Tabula more Lune in tenebris, tempore totalis
               
               
                  
                     ••••
                  ſdem defectionis. For at the ryghte hande you ſhall fynde the howers and minutes, or the minutes only, of the ſaid fatall obſcuration. And if you fynde not the mynutes of the ſaide poyntes eclypticke preciſely in the ſaide table, you ſhal then take the moſte neareſt, and it ſhall ſuffice.
            
               Example.
               AS is of the firſte vniuerſall eclipſe of the mone, that came in the yere 1551. you woulde knowe howe longe time the moone was in darcknes depreued totallye of her lyghte, you ſhall take the poyntes ecliptycke of the ſayde eclipſe, whiche are. 14. and. 12. minutes and thoſe ſhall you finde in the aboue named table (in takynge the. 10. minutes for. 12.) and at the ryghte hande ioininge to thoſe. 14. pointes and. 10. minutes, you ſhal ſe one hower and. 
                     •
                  . minutes ſo long tyme was the mone in full darknes.
            
         
         
            Of the directions and retrogradaciōs of the. 5. planets the. 4.
            AFterwardes doth followe vnderneth the ſaide eclipſe, the time pr
                  •
               
               fired of the directions and retro

gradacions of the. 5. planetes, that is to ſaye vpon what daye they do beginne and ende their ſayde Retrogradacions, and conſequentelye howe often tymes Mercury ſhall bee retrograde the ſame yeare, for he by reaſon of the fwyft mouement of his epicicle is more often retrograde then are ye other planets, the which you ſhal finde lykewyſe among the mouementes of the ſayd planets whiche are noted in the lefte face of the ſaid Ephemerides with this ſillable Re. which ſignifyeth the beginning of the retrogradacion and with this ſillable Di. whiche betokeneth the beginninge of the directiō of the ſame planets. And furthermore the proper mouement of the ſayde planets wyll ſhewe it you, for when the mouemente doth go encreaſing from daye to day the planet is directe, &amp; when it doth decreaſe the planete is retrograde. We doo call the planete directe, when the line of his true mouement goeth after the order of the. 12. ſignes of the Zodiake, and retrograde, when the ſayd line goeth agaynſt the ordre of the ſayd ſignes, notwithſtanding the moone hathe no direction, nor retrogradatiō, by reaſō that his epicicle goeth contrarye to the others, and is of

more haſty mouement: But ſhe hath only ſwiftnes, or ſlownes, &amp; is called haſty or ſlowe.
         
         
            ¶ Of the true mouementes of the lightes and the planetes and other thinges conteyned in the lefte face of the ſayde Ephemerides. 5. rule.
            THeſe thinges thus ſet forthe, there foloweth after the. 12. monethes of the yeare deuided in two faces, of the whyche the lefte face conteyneth the name of the moneth, with the noumbre of the daies of the ſame, wherof the Son daye is named by the dominicall letter, which hath courſe for that yeare. And yf there be any ſeſtable daye, it is lykewyſe noted, at the leeſt wiſe accordinge vnto the cōmon vſe of the churche. After there foloweth the true mouementes of the lightes and planetes calculated at nonetide of euery day, which are deuided and ſet in. 8. collōnes or ſpaces, of the which the firſt is of the ſunne, the ſecond of the moone, the thirde of Saturne the fourth of Iupiter the fifthe of mars the ſixte of Venus the ſeuenth of mercury and the eyghte for the interſection or ſeperacion of the circle

of the moone, and of the Zodiake, whiche is called Caput draconis, as the carecters or marks of the ſaid planets and of the ſaid dragon (whiche are aboue the heed of euery colompne do ſhewe) of the which the interpretation foloweth.
            
               
                  The Sunne ☉
                  The moone ☽
                  
                  Saturne ♄
                  Iupiter ♃
                  mars ♂
                  Venus ♀
                  mercury ☿
                  The hed of the dragon ☊
                  The tayle  of the dragon ☋
               
            
            And it is requiſite to note that euerye colompne hathe two orders of noumbers wherof the leſt is of degrees &amp; the righte of the minutes of the ſigne whereof the carecter is nereſt collocated or ſet ouer the head betwene the ſayde degrees and minutes: of which carrecters, here enſueth the interpretacion.
            
               
                  
                     Signes ſeptentrionalls
                     Aries ♈
                     Taurus ♉
                     gemini ♊
                  
                  
                     Cancer ♋
                     Leo ♌
                     virgo ♍
                  
                  
                     Signes meridionales.
                     Libra ♎
                     Scorpio ♏
                     Sagitta. ♐
                  
                  
                     Capri. ♑
                     Aquari. ♒
                     Piſces ♓
                  
               
            
            
               And thus you haue ryghte againſte euery daye, in what ſigne, degree, or mynute, is euery one of the ſayde planettes, and the ſaide ſection of the heade of the Draggon of the moone, vpon the pointe of noone, of the ſame day.
         
         
            Of the equallitie, and vnequallitie of the naturall daies. the. 6.
            BUt it is to bee noted y• the natural daies are ſuppoſed to be equall the one to the other in the ſaide Ephemerides, althoughe they bee not ſo: &amp; that for by cauſe of the obliquitie, or crokednes of the zodiacke, and of the mouement irreguler of the ſunne aboute the centre of the worlde, the tyme then, at the whyche the ſunne departeth from the Merediane (whiche is the true noonetide) and goeth into the occident vnder the earth, retournynge by oriente vnto the ſaide meridiane againe: is the true quantitie of a naturall deye, and the tyme at the whyche all the equinoctiall circle is paſſed and reuoluted or tourned backe vnder the ſayde merediane, wyth. 59. minutes and. 8. ſecondes of a degree more, is the meaſure of a natural daye equall and meaſurable

according vnto whiche are ma
                  •
               e the ſupputations of the meane and reguler mouementes aſtronomicalls. And although that there be difference betwene the true and the meane or equall dayes naturall aboue ſayde, yet notwythſtandynge ther can folow no notable errour for the true place and mouement of the ſonne and of the. 
                  •
               . planettes, whych are of mouement ſlowe ynoughe, but onely of the mone by reaſon of the ſwiftnes of her mouement.
         
         
            The manner too bringe the true place and mouemente of the moone, vnto the true noonetide. The. 7.
            VVhen thou wylte then reduce, or bring the true place and mouemēt of the mone vnto the true vulgare or common noonetide at the whyche the true naturall dayes, do begynne and end that is to ſaye when the ſunne is ryghtely vpon the meridianc: thou ſhalt do thr
                  •
                as foloweth. Take ryghte with the daye propoſed, the true place of the ſunne, 
                  •
               nd of the moone, then entre wyth the ſygn
                  •
                and degree of the ſaide place of the ſunn
                  •
                into the table entituled Tabula motus lun
                     •
                  
                in takynge the ſigne ouer the heade, an
                  •
               
               
the degree at the lefte ſyde of the ſaide table: and you ſhall fynde vnder the ſayde ſigne, righte wythe the ſayde degree, the nombre of minutes, whyche you muſte take awaye, and ſubſtra from the true place of the moone taken in the Ephemerides for to bryng them vnto the true noone tide propoſed. And for by cauſe the degrees which are at the left ſide of the ſaid table do procede from two vnto two you ſhal take the degre which ſhalbe moſt nereſt vnto the ſayd place of the ſunne, not hauyng any regard vnto the minutes, in caſe they paſſe not. 30. &amp; when they paſſe. 30. you maye then adde▪ one degree, with out any errour, for the ſayde mynutes.
         
         
            To know ye true place, &amp; mouemēt of ye lightes &amp; planets, at euery howre that a mā pleaſe: whether it be, afore or after noone. The. 8. Rule.
            ANd if it be cōueniēt to haue ye true place of the ſunne or of the moone or of any planet, at what howre ſo euer it be, either before none or after, you ſhal take his true place &amp; mouement aunſwering vnto the nonetide paſt, and alſo the ſame of ye nonetide folowing, as hath ben ſaid before. After you ſhal ſubſtra the

mouemente from the greateſt: and that whiche doth remayne ſhalbe the mouement of the ſayd plan
                  ••
               e anſwering vnto the ſame natural daye, frō one noone tide to the other, the whyche mouement you ſhall deuide by▪ 24. in reſoluinge the degrees into minutes, and the minutes into ſecondes, if there be nede, then thou ſhalt adde ſo manye times the. 24. parte of the ſayd dayly mouemēt vnto the mouement of the nonetide paſt, as there be howers paſt ſince the ſame nonetide, yf the planet be direct. Or els you ſhal ſubſtra the ſame. 24. parte ſo many times if he be retrograde, &amp; if you haue one quarter, one third, or halfe of an houre more: you maye likewiſe adde or ſubſtraye the fourth, or the thirde, or the halfe of the aboue ſayd. 24. parte of the ſayd dayly mouemēt and by this meane you ſhal haue that which you demaund.
         
         
            ¶ For to bringe the true mouement of the moone vnto what meridiane you pleaſe. 9. rule.
            ANd although that the Ephemerides laſt imprinted, are calculated and reduced vnto the meridiane of a Citie of Almaigne called Tubinge, yet neuertheleſſe

it is no neede to reduce, or brīg the true places &amp; mouemētes of the ſunne and of the. 5. planetes (whiche are ſlowe inoughe of mouement) vnto anye other meridiane what ſo euer it be: except onely the place of the moone, for the ſwiftnes of his mouement. The whiche you ſhall do after this maner. Take the name of your city, or of ye place moſt nereſt to the ſame, in the table which is called Tabula regionum, prouinciarum, et oppidorum inſigniorum Europae. and drawinge toward the right hande, you ſhal finde vnder the charecter of the moone the numbre of minutes, which muſt be added or ſubſtraed from the true mouemente of the ſaid moone, which hath bene calculated by the ſayd Ephemerides: accordinge as the letter. A. or. M. being at the left hand ſhal ſhewe you, for the letter. A. ſignifyeth that ye muſt adde, and the letter. M. that you muſt dimyniſhe or ſubſtra the ſayde minutes, and therewith you ſhall finde al at once at the right hande of the ſayd minutes, in the laſte columpne, the degrees of the latitude, or eleuatiō of the pole Articke of the ſayd citie or region, of the which you may haue to do withal as here after you ſhal ſee.
         
         
            
            Of the latitude of the. 5. planetes. ♄. ♃. ♂. ♀. and. ☿.
            Furthermore vnder euery columpne of the. 5. planetes, are noted their latitudes (that is to ſay, how much th
                  ••
                decline from the eclipticke, calculated onely for the. 1. 10. and. 20. day of euery moneth by the meanes of the which, you may eaſely proportionate the latitudes of thoſe planetes for all the other dayes whiche are betwene both, of the which latitudes the denominations are noted aboue y• head of euery of the ſayd columnes, by the Capital letters which hereafter folowe
            
               
                  
                     S. A.
                     which doth ſignify the planet to be.
                     Septentrional aſcendant
                  
                  
                     S. D.
                     Septentrional deſcendāt
                  
                  
                     M A
                     Meridional Aſcendant
                  
                  
                     M. D
                     Meridional Deſcendant
                  
               
            
            The which dominations whē they do chaūge are likewiſe noted by the chaūge of ye ſayd capital letters put or ſet amōg the noumbers of the true mouementes. As if ouer the head you haue. S. A. and then you mete belowe vnderneth in any of the colomnes, this letter. D. it betokeneth y• the planet which was ſeptentrional

aſcendant is made ſeptentrional deſcendāt, ſo muſt you vnderſtand if it chaunce contrary, and it you haue ouer the head S. A. or S. D. and then you mete. M. that denoteth that the latitude ſeptentrional is conuerted into the meridionall, and contrary wiſe if after. M. there do folow the letter. S. which is a thing righte eaſy to be vnderſtande, we call the planet deſcendant, whan the centre of his epicicle, deſcēdeth from the point of the eccentrike the moſt fartheſt parte of the earth whyche is called Axe tree, towardes hys oppoſite whych is the moſt neareſt and is called aſcendant, when from the ſaid point oppoſyte he mounteth towardes the ſayd poynt moſt fartheſt of the earth.
         
         
            Of the Latytude of the moone. the. 11.
            THe latitude of the moone, is founde in the ſayde Ephemerides by his owne table intituled Tabula latitudiais lunae thus as foloweth. Take the true mouement of the mone, &amp; of the dragons head. ☊ of the ſame, at the day and hower propoſed as hath bene ſaid hereto fore: and reſolue the caracters of the ſygnes of the ſame mouemēts into the nombers of the ſaide ſignes whiche are theſe that folowe.
            
               
               
                  
                     1
                     2
                     3
                     4
                     5
                     6
                     7
                     8
                     9
                     10
                     11
                     12
                  
                  
                     ♈
                     ♉
                     ♊
                     ♋
                     ♌
                     ♍
                     ♎
                     ♏
                     ♐
                     ♑
                     ♒
                     ♓
                  
               
            
            ¶ Then ſubſtra the true mouemente of the head of the dragon of the moone, frō his owne proper and true mouement in adding. 12. ſignes if the ſubſtcaction cā not be otherwiſe made) and that whyche reſteth, ſhal be the true argument of the latitude of the moone, with the which argumente you ſhall enter the table of the latitude of the ſame in taking the noumber of the ſignes of the ſayde argument at the head of the ſayde table, and the de, grees at the lefte ſide, in the line intituled linea numeri, which procede in deſcending from the toppe downeward or els in taking the nomber of the ſignes at the foote of the ſayde table, and the degrees at the right hand in the line which amoū
               teth from beneth vpwarders: for in the place at the which y• lines of the nōbers of the ſayd ſignes &amp; degrees do agree together, you ſhall find the latitude of the moone in degrees &amp; minutes, the which latitude ſhall be called ſeptentrionall, if you haue taken the nombers of the ſygnes at the head of the table, or els meridionall

if the ſaide ſignes haue bene taken at the foote of the table. And further the moone ſhalbe called aſcendant if the nū
               bre of the ſignes of the argument of the latitude be. 0. or. 1. or. 2. in the head, and. 9 or. 10. or. 11. at the foote of the ſaide table And if the ſaide nombre of ſignes aboue ſaide bee in the heade. 3. or. 4. or. 5. and at the foote. 6. 7. or. 8. ſhe ſhall be named deſcendant as the titles and inſcriptions of the ſaid table doth declare, being ſecur y• head &amp; fote of euery colūne of the ſame ¶ And if it happen that your argument haue any nombre of minutes ouer &amp; beſides the degrees, it behoueth to enter the ſayd table two times, &amp; to take firſte the latitude whiche aunſwereth vnto the degrees precedinge immediatlye the ſayd minutes, and then the latitude aunſwering vnto the degrees which next do folowe the ſaid minutes. After it is cōuenient to take the difference of both the latitudes in ſubſtraing the leaſt from the greateſt. That done put. 60. for the firſt nombre, &amp; the nombre of the ſayd minutes for the ſecond, and the ſaid difference for the third: and multiply the third nō
               bre by the ſeconde, and that whiche cometh of the multiplication deuide by the

firſt &amp; you ſhal haue the fourth noumbre proportionall, the whiche you muſt adde vnto the firſt latitude, yf it be leſſe then the ſecond: or els ſubſtra the ſame from the ſayd firſt latitude, if it do ſurmounte the ſecōd latitude for that which cometh or remayneth therof ſhal be the true latitude of the moone anſwering vnto the minutes of the ſayd argument.
            And who that would make ſhorte, there is no daunger if he leaue the ſayd minutes if they be leſſe then. 30, or els to adde one degre vnto the degrees of the ſayde argument, if the ſayde minute do excede or paſſe 30. and then to finde the latitude as aboue hath bene ſayd.
         
         
            Of the aſpectes of the moone vnto the ſunne and planetes, &amp; other thinges conteyned in the righte and ſeconde face of the ſaide Ephemerides the. 12. rule.
            Conſequently in the right and ſecond face of the ſaide Ephemerides, are comprehended the aſpectes of the moone vnto the ſunne, and vnto the. 5. planetes, and from one of the planets vnto the other: as the ſuperſcription of the ſaid face doth ſhewe. And firſte of al is declared the

nombre of the yeare, and the nombre of the monthe and vnderneth the ſame, the nombre of the dayes of the ſayd moneth ioyning vnto the ſayd noumbre, are noted the coniunctions, oppoſitions, quadratures, trines, and the ſextiles aſpect of the moone vnto the ſonne: then frome the moone vnto Saturne, Iupiter, Mars, Venus and Mercury, as it appeareth by the caracters of the ſunne and of the ſaid planets being ſet above the head of the. 6. colompnes and the ſayd aſpectes are noted by their figures and caracters, wher of the interpretacion and diffinicion foloweth.
            ☌ ſignifieth coniunction, that is to ſay when, 2. planettes are vnder one like degree accordinge vnto the lōgitude of the Zodiake.
            ☍ Signifieth oppoſition, that is to ſay, when two planets are diametrallye conſtituted, diſtante. 6. ſignes the one from the other.
            
               □. Signifieth quadrate aſpecte: which is made, when. 2. planets are diſtant the one from the other by. 3. ſignes, whyche make the fourthe parte of the. 12. ſygnes of the Zodiacke
            
               
               △. Sygnyfyeth trine aſpecte: whyche happenethe when two plannettes are diſtante the one from the other by foure ſignes, whyche do make the thirde parte of the ſayde. 12. ſignes of the zodiacke.
            ⚹. Signifieth ſextile aſpecte: whiche is cauſed, by the diſtaunce of two ſygnes betwene two planettes. And it is ſoo named, by cauſe two ſygnes doo make the ſyxte parte of the. 12. ſignes of the ſayde zodiacke, and it is too bee noted, that the nomber ſette after the character of eueri aſpecte ſheweth the howre in the whyche the ſayde aſpecte ſhall happen in reckenyng from the noonetide of the ſame day righ
                  ••
                with the whiche is noted the ſaide aſpecte. Excepte the coniunctions and oppoſitions of the moone and of the ſunne, that is to ſaye the newe and full moones of the whyche not onely the howres, but alſo the mynutes are written for the firſt nombre after the carrecter of the cōiunction or oppoſition of the ſunne and of the moone, do ſignifye the howre: and the ſeconde and ryghte nombre, the mynutes that the ſaid coniunctions, or oppoſitions ſhall fall vpon.
         
         
            Howe the newe and full mones, and eclypſes, maye be reduced vnto what meridiane you will, differynge from the ſame of the Ephemerides▪
                The. 13.
            
               FOr ſo muche that the ſayde new and full moones, and the eclypſes of the ſunne and of the moone, whiche happen in theim, are calculated in the ſayde Ephemerides for the meridiane of the afore named cytie of Tubinge in Almaigne: it is conueniente 
                  ••
                reduce, for the leſte, the tyme of the ſayde coniunctions, oppoſitions, and eclypſes of the ſunne and of the moone vnto your meridiane, wytheoute hauynge care of the other aſpectes the whyche you ſhall eaſelye doo by the table entituled Tabularegionum, prouinciarum, et oppidorum inſigniorū europae thus as followeth.
            Take the name of youre Citye, or of the place moſt neareſt to the ſame, in the table aboue ſayde, &amp; you ſhal fynd at the ryghte ſyde vnder this tittle Tempus, the howers and mynutes, or the mynutes onely, whiche you muſt adde, or ſubſtra 
                  •
               rom the howres and minutes of the ſaid coniunctions, and oppoſitions, and eclipſes of the ſunne and of the moone: as the 
                  •
               ettre A. or M. written at the lefte ſyde of 
                  •
               he ſayde howres and mynutes ſhall

ſhewe you.
         
         
            Of the aſpectes of the ſunne vnto the planettes, and of the planettes amonge theim ſelues, and of the dragon of the moone. The. 14.
            AFterwarde there foloweth vpon the ryghte ſyde of the ſayde face of the Ephemerides, the aſpectes of the ſunne vnto the planettes, and of one planet vnto a nother, whiche are figured as well by the carracters of the ſayde plannettes, as by the characters of the ſayde aſpectes, of the which the interpretation hathe beene heretofore declared. Conſequently amonge the ſaide aſpectes is noted when the moone is in the head or in the tayle of the dragon, whiche are their interſections or diuiſions of his circle and of the Zodiake, as we haue ſaid a
                  •
                fore. When ſhe is in the head, ſhe is thus figured. ☽. ☊. and whē ſhe is in the taile ſhe is figured after this maner. ☽. ☋.
         
         
            ¶ When the planets are oriental or occidental. 15. rule.
            
               FInally is noted ouer the head of euery columpne of the. 5. planets, vnder their propre charecters, when the ſayd planets are orientall or occidentall by theſe ſillables. or. and. oc. and it is to be noted that ſaturne, Iupiter and mars, are orientall whiles the ſunne departeth frō them after the couiunction of him and of the ſayd planets, comminge vnto the oppoſition and occidentall, from the ſaid oppoſition in approchinge him ſelfe nere vnto them, vntill the coniunction nexte enſuing. But Venus and mercury are called orientall, when they do precede▪ the ſunne from the eaſt parte, and are ſeene before the ſunne riſing and occidentall, when they do folowe the ſunne from the weſt parte, and are ſeene after the ſunne is ſette.
         
         
            For to knowe the quantitie of the artificial daye and of the nighte, and at what houre the ſunne ryſethe and ſetteth. 16. rule
            ANd too the ende that all menne maye knowe, if they canne ſee the eclipſes of the ſunne or of the moone which happen nere vnto the horizont

aboute the ſunne ſettinge, or the ſun riſinge, it is neceſſarye to knowe the quā
               titie of the dayes and of the nightes artificiall, and at what howre the ſunne ryſeth and ſetteth. There is than before the table of the Ephemerides, a table intituled Tabula quantitatis dierum, that is to ſaye a table of the quantitye of the dayes: the whyche conteyneth in the hedde the latitudes, or eleuations of the pole of al places vpon the earth, from. 36. degrees, vntill. 55. degrees: and at the left hand there are. 6. ſygnes of the zodiack &amp; other. 6. at the righte hande, whyche are diſtributed from. 3. degrees to. 3. in the middes of the ſayd table are comprehended the houres and mynutes of the halfe of an artificial daye, whyche are from the ſunne riſyng vntyll noonetide, or from noonetide vntyl the ſunne ſettyng, when the ſunne is in the ſignes ſeptrentionalles: or eles the howres &amp; minutes of half of the nyghte whyche are from the ſunne ſettynge vntyll mydnyghte, or from mydnyghte vntyll the ſunne ryſyng, whan the ſōne is in the ſygnes meridionalles, knowe then in what ſigne, and degree the ſunne is, and howe muche the poole is eleuated aboue your horizont, as before hath be
                  •
               
               ſayd.

And take the ſayde ſygne and degre at the ryghte, or lefte ſyde of the aboue ſayde table, and procede ryghtelye in the ſame table, vntyll that you be 
                  •
               uſtelye at the nombre of youre pole: and there you ſhall finde the howers, and minutes of the halfe of the artificiall day if the ſunne be in the ſeptentrionall parte of the zodiacke: or elles of the haife of the nyghte, if he bee in the meridionall parte: what ſygnes are ſeptentrionalles, and what meridionals hath beene declared in the fifte Rule. The whiche is likewiſe euident by the ſayde table, by theſe woordes, Sig▪ Bor. fig. Auſt. Yf you double then, the ſayde howres and minuttes of the halfe of the artificiall daye, you ſhall haue the whole day: and if you do ſubſtra them from. 24. howres, there reſteth the nyghte. Or yf you double the howres and mynutes of the halfe of the nyghte, you ſhall haue the nyghte wholye: and if you ſubſtra them from. 24. howres, there reſtethe the artyfyciall day, and by thys meanes you maye knowe at what howre the Sunne ryſethe, or ſettethe euerye daye in the yeare.
            
               For the daye artificial dureth from the ſunne riſinge to noone, vntill the ſunne ſetting: and the night artificial, from the ſunne ſetting vnto midnight, and ſo vntil the ſunne riſing. And the natural day of. 24. houres dothe comprehend them both.
         
         
            ¶ Of the, 12. houſes of heauen, and of their nature accidentall accordinge vnto the iudgement of the aſtrologians. 17. rule.
            FOr to gather any ſruyt of the thynges aboueſayd according to the habilitie that god hath geuen vnto mē it is conuenient, to treat of the. 12. houſes of heauen, and of their accidentiall nature and how they muſt be diſtingued and erected in all regions. In leauinge then a heape of ſuperfluous and vnprofitable wordes, whiche are in the latine rules of the Ephemerides and the varietis of the opinions of the Aſtrologians touching the ſaid houſes, I wil declare the opinion and maner howe to do them, according vnto the which, the Tables are calculated which are in the Ephemerides, and that all men do commenlye vſe now adayes. To come then vnto the

poynt you muſte note that as the ſunne and the moone and the. 5. planettes, makinge their reuolution by their propre mouementes vnder the Zodiake, doo cauſe diuers effectes and ſenſible mutacions in earthly thinges, according vnto the diuers proiection of their beames and diuers diſpoſitions of natural thinges here belowe, in makinge their peregrinacion from ſigne to ſigne, and according vnto the nature accidentale, of the 12. ſignes of the Zodiake: likewiſe the ſayd lightes and planetes, in tourninge round about the earthe by the firſte and vniuerſal mouement of al the world, frō the orient by the ſouth into the accident, within the time and ſpace of. 24. houres (whiche we cal a natural daye) do cauſe again euery day of the yeare diuers and perticuler effectes, according as they be in the orient or occident, and notably eleuated or depreſſed vnder y• earth, &amp; y• thei haue more ſtronge or weake irradiaciō vppon the ſayde thinges here belowe on earth. For this cauſe the Aſtrologians haue diſtingued all the roundnes of the vniuerſall worlde into. 12. partes (after the nombre of the ſaid. 12. ſignes) whych are called houſes, of the which there are

6. aboue the earth, and. 6. vnderneth parpetually and in all regions, in the maner and forme as foloweth.
            Firſt it is to vnderſtande, that the meridian circle and the Horizont, do deuide them ſelues into 2. halfes, and with right angles towardes the South and North, and they deuide the Equinoctiall into 4. quarters, whereof there be. 2. aboue the earth, and 2. vnderneth: two lykewiſe toward the Eaſt, and 2. toward the Weſt. And euery. 4. porcion contemeth. 90. degrees. You muſt thē imagen euery of the ſaid quarters of the equino. to be deuided into 3 egal parts of 30 degrees, euery one of them &amp; by the pointes of the ſaid deuiſions to paſſe. 4. great circles, proceding frō the foreſaid interſections of the meridian circle, &amp; of y• horizont, by this menes the ſaid 4. circles with y• ſayd meridian &amp; horizont (which do make togither the nū
               bre of. 6.) do deuid the equl. &amp; al the ſphere of the world into. 12. partes, which we cal the. 1
                  •
               . houſes of heauen: the which are or dained &amp; diſtributed accordinge vnto the ſucceſſion of the 12. lines of the zodiacke &amp; of the propre mouement of the lyghtes &amp; planets, cōtrary vnto the firſt mouemēt vniuerſall, as it doeth ſomwhat appeare by this fygure folowinge.
            
               
               
            
            
               MYne opinion notwithſtandinge is, that the ſaide. 4. circles oughte to paſſe by the deuiſyons of the Circle vertycall, whiche doth deuyde the meridian circle with right angles and not by the equinoctial (yf it be not in the right Sphere) for many good cauſes and inuincible reaſons as is noted in the Coſmographie or Sphere of the worlde, publyſſhed by Orentius, and in the. 12. Chapter of the ſeconde boke of the ſame.
            
               ¶ The firſt houſe beginneth then in the orientale parte of the horizont, and endeth in the next halfe circle which is vnder the ſaid horizont, the which houſe is named the angle of orient, or aſcendaunt, and horoſcope: and it is the houſe to iudge of all the beginninges of life, &amp; the beginninges of all workes. For bycauſe the firſt and vniuerſal mouement beginneth at the eaſt parte, and rayſeth the ſterres and planets aboue the earth in ſuch wiſe that from the orient cometh all vertue and the heauenly goodnes.
            The ſecond houſe foloweth after, vnder the ſaid horizont. The which is the houſe of ſubſtaunce as well of neceſſary thynges to the life, as of other goodes, of marchandiſes, of byinges, ſellinges, adminiſtrators, and helpers.
            ¶ The. 3. houſe folowinge endeth at the part of the meridiane, whyche is vnder the earthe, and bath ſignification vppon brothers, and ſiſters, couſynes, neighbours and friendes, and vpon ſmal and ſhort viages.
            ¶ The. 4. houſe beginneth at the ſayde parte of the meridiane, whiche is vnder the earth. The which is called the angle of the point of the earthe, or of midnight

and of ſame the bottome or depth of heauen. And it is the houſe for to iudge of diuiſions and heritages, of treaſors hide and of all thynges vnmouable
            The. 5. houſe foloweth after, the whyche is the houſe of chyldren, of frendſhippe legates and meſſengers.
            The. 6. and folowing houſe, is ended at the occidentall parte of the horizont and hath ſignification vpon ſickeneſſes, lordeſhippes, membres of the body, vpon ſeruauntes, pryſoners, and domeſtycall beaſtes.
            7. The ſeuenth houſe begynneth at the ſaide horizonte occidentall drawynge toward the ſouth, called the angle or point of occident, oppoſite vnto the aſcendant: whiche beginneth to deſcende vnder the horizont. And it is the houſe to iudge of women, mariages, debates and contentions, of the one halfe of the humaine lyfe.
            8. The. 8. houſe foloweth after approching toward the South. The whiche is the houſe of death, and interfection, and of the ende of life.
            9. The. 9. and houſe folowing is ended at the part of the meridiane which is aboue the earthe and hathe ſignification vppon

long vſages, peregrinations, fayth, religion, wiſedom, and dreames.
            10. The tenthe houſe begynneth at the ſaide meridiane verticall aboue the earth the whyche called the angle or poynte of the ſouth, or of the middes of heauen, oppoſite vnto the fourth houſe which is the angle of the earthe, and is the houſe royall, imperiall, of exaltacion, and honoure nobleneſſe, and good renoume.
            11. The eleuenthe houſe, foloweth affer, drawing towardes the Eaſte, the whiche is the houſe for to iudge of hope, cōfidēce and the fortune of man.
            12. The twelfe and laſt houſe, endinge at the oriente is the houſe of ſadnes, enuye, malice, deception and craft.
            And by this maner there be foure angular and principall houſes, that is to ſaye the firſt, the fourth, the ſeuenth, and the tenth. And foure whiche are named ſuccedinge, that is to ſaye. The ſeconde, the fyfthe, the eyght, &amp; the eleuenth, whiche do folowe the other foure aboueſayd.
            The other foure whiche come next after the ſuccedinge houſes, are called falling or coming after, which be theſe. The thirde, the ſixt, the ninth, and the twelfth Of the whiche houſes this is the figurefolowing,

after the iudgemente of our Aſtrologians, and as they are accuſtomed to vſe them and to put them in platfourme.
            
               The Figure of the xii. hovvſes of heauen, after the Iudgementes of the Aſtrologians.
               
                  
                     The fyrſte howſe the Angle of Orient. ♈
                     The ſecond houſe ſuccedinge. ♉
                     The third houſe fallynge. ♊
                     The fourth houſe the Angle of the earth. ♋
                     The fyf
                           •
                        e howſe ſuccedinge. ♌
                     The ſyxte howſe fallynge. ♍
                     The vii. houſe the Angle of the Occident. ♎
                     The viii. howſe ſuccedinge. ♏
                     The ix. howſe fallynge. ♐
                     The x. houſe the Angle of the middes of heuen. ♑
                     The xi. howſe ſuccedinge. ♒
                     The xii. houſe fallynge. ♓
                  
               
            
            
               And it is conueniente finallye, to note that the lyghtes and planettes do reioiſe, and haue certeyne power, and accidentall vertues, in ſome houſes more then in other, as dothe heareafter folowe.
            
               
                  
                     ♄ Saturne
                     
                        doth reioyce in the
                     
                     xii.
                     
                        howſe,
                     
                  
                  
                     ♃ Iupiter
                     xi.
                  
                  
                     ♂ Mars
                     vi.
                  
                  
                     ☉ the ſunne
                     ix
                  
                  
                     ♀ Venus
                     v
                  
                  
                     ☿ Mercury
                     i
                  
                  
                     
                        ☽ the moone
                     iii
                  
               
            
         
         
            ¶ Howe to erecte and diſtyngue the. 12. houſes of heauen, after the order of the ſayd Ephemerides. 18. rule
            TO erect thē or caculate the. 12. houſes of heauen is no other thinge but to finde the pointes of the Zodiacke, which are noted and diſtingued by the ſixe circles aboueſaid: the whiche you ſhall do by the tables of the Ephemerides thus as foloweth. You muſt thē firſt note, y• there are in the ſayde Ephemerides
               
5. tables perticulers, ſufficiente for all Europe, calculated for the latitude or eleuation of the poole of. 42. 45. 48. 51. and. 54. degrees. And althoughe that there be difference of. 2. degrees, betwen euerye of the ſaide eleuations or latitudes: yet can there folowe no notable erroure of the ſame. If for the degrees left out you do vſe of the table whiche is calculated for the next degre. For the table of. 45. degrees ſhal ſerue principally for the ſayde. 45. degrees: and without any notable errour for. 44. and. 46. and the ſame of. 48. ſhall ſerue for. 47. and. 49. degrees and, ſo of the other. Comming then to the effect, you muſt conſydre the time, at the which you will erect he ſaid houſes of heauen, to knowe if it be preciſely at none, eyther before or after.
            
               ¶ The firſte parte or difference, when the time is preciſely at noone
               LEt it be propoſed that you woulde erect the ſayde houſes at the houre of noone, preciſelye, you ſhall then take the true place and mouement of the

ſunne at the ſayd houre of none by your Ephemerides. Then you ſhal take the ſigne in the which is the ſunne aboue the head of the ſayd table of the houſes whiche is made, or may ſerue moſt commodiouſly for your latitude or eleuation of the pole and the degree at the left hād of the ſayd table: in the columne or line of the aboue ſayd tenth houſe, for ye degre is the beginning of the 10 houſe. Right with the whiche degre, in drawing toward the ryght hand, you ſhal finde incontinent the degrees orderly of the. 11. 12. 1. 2. &amp;. 3, houſe at the ſaid houre of noone. The whyche degrees are of the ſignes, whoſe characters are nereſt noted aboue them. And if it happen that the true place &amp; mouemēt of the ſunne haue anye nombre of minutes as moſt often it doth happē then may you leaue thoſe minutes if they be leſſe then. 30. or els adde one degree, if the ſaid nombre of minutes do excede. 30. without any errour, or notable intereſt.
               
                  ¶ The maner how to proportionate the ſayde houſes when the true place of the ſunne hath minutes.
                  ANd if you wil haue the ſayd houſes more curiouſly: you ſhall doo thus. Take righte agaynſte the

whole degrees of the ſunne, whiche are before the minutes, the houſes whiche you ſhal finde at the right hand as I ſaid before. And at the left hande of the ſayde houſes, take the time, that is to ſaye the houres and minutes, whiche you ſhall finde vnder this title Tempus a meridie.
                  
                  Then take the difference of the ſaid time next enſuing (in ſubſtraing the leſſer frō the greater, and note the ſame a part vnder the ſame time, Lykewiſe take the difference of euery of the ſayd houſes alredy noted &amp; of the next houſes folowing, and note euery difference vnder his propre houſe. After this done, entre into the table entituled Tabula proportionū ad 60. minuta celi domicilus fabricandis ſatiſfaciens.
                  
                  And take at the lefte ſide of the ſayde table the minutes of the true place of the ſunne whiche are ouer and beſides the degrees, and at the head of the ſame table take the nombre of the minutes of the ſayd difference of time, and you ſhal finde right with thoſe minutes, the partes proportional of the ſayd difference in ſecondes, or elles in minutes and ſecondes together. The which part proportionall, or the neareſt to the ſame, you ſhall take at the left ſide of the table folowing

the aboueſayd, which is intituled Tabula quatuor minutorum temporis and the difference of euery houſe (the one after the other) at the heade of the ſayde table: and youſhall finde righte againſte the ſayde nombre the minutes, or the degrees and minutes together, the whiche you muſt adde vnto the degrees of the houſe, out of the whiche was taken the ſayde difference, and there as the ſayd houſes haue not the difference, you muſte adde nothinge vnto theym. By this meanes you ſhal haue the preciſe iuſtification of the ſayd houſes more curious then neceſſary. Example. And for to haue of all more eaſier vnderſtanding, I haue here giuen you an example, calculated for the middaye of the laſte of Jnue. 1540. and for the latitude of. 48. degrees, as is the ſame of Paris. At the which tyme I did finde the ſunne to be in the. 17. degres and. 40. minutes of Cancer. And then I did execute and folowe the reſt, as aboue hath bene ſaide, and I haue taken in the ſayd table proportionall at the left hand the. 40. minutes of the true place, &amp; the 4. minutes of the difference of time at the heade of the ſayde table, and right againſt thoſe I found. 
                        •
                     . minutes and. 40

ſecondes: whiche is the parte proporcionall of the ſaid difference of time, whiche was founde of the. 4. minutes, vnder ſuche reaſon as haue the. 40. minutes vnto 60. minutes of one hole houre. Afterwardes I did take in the ſaid table quatuor minutorum temporis, the ſaid. 2. minutes and 40. ſecondes at the right ſyde, and the difference of the howſes (whiche is but of one degree, at the head of the ſaide table: and I did finde right with them. 40. minutes to be added vnto euery houſe aunſwering vnto the 17 degrees of the ſūne: The which 40 minutes haue ſuche reaſon vnto one degree (whiche are worthe 60 minutes) as haue the 2 minutes and 40 ſecondes, vnto the aboue ſayde 4 minutes of the difference of time), and by this meanes you do anoide a multiplication and diuiſion by the ſaide table proportionall, and as muche by the table quatuor minutorum temporis, beſides the reductions whiche ſhoulde be made.
                  The reſte is cleare ynoughe by the diſcours, and ſupputation of the ſaid example propoſed▪ of the which here foloweth the true deſcription.
                  
                     
                     
                        
                           The order of the ſixe houſes orientall.
                        
                        
                           The time frō m today
                           10
                           11
                           12
                           1
                           2
                           3
                        
                        
                           ♋
                           ♌
                           ♍
                           ♎
                           ♏
                           ♐
                        
                        
                           hou.  
                           m.
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           g 
                           m
                           g 
                           m
                           g 
                           m
                           g 
                           m
                           g 
                           m
                           g 
                           m
                        
                        
                           7  
                           14
                           0
                           17 
                           0
                           24 
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           
                              
                                 ••
                               
                           
                           0
                           14 
                           0
                           7 
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           8
                            
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                        
                           The houſes aunſwering vnto 17 degrees.
                        
                        
                            
                           4
                           0
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           0
                           1
                           0
                           1
                           0
                           0
                           0
                           1
                           0
                           0
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                        
                           The differences.
                        
                        
                           7
                           18
                           0
                           8
                           0
                           25
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           22
                           0
                           14
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           0
                           8
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                        
                           The houſes aunſwering vnto 18 degrees.
                        
                        
                            
                           2
                           40
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           40
                           0
                           4
                                 •
                              
                           
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           40
                           0
                           0
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           
                              
                                 ••
                              
                           
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                        
                           The partes proportionals.
                        
                        
                            
                            
                            
                           17
                           4
                                 •
                              
                           
                           24
                           
                              
                                 •
                              0
                           21
                           4
                                 •
                              
                           
                           14
                            
                           7
                           4
                                 •
                              
                           
                           8
                           
                              
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                        
                           The houſes iuſtified.
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            
               ¶ The ſeconde parte or difference, when the time propoſed is after none.
               ANd yf the time propoſed be after none▪ you ſhall take the ſigne and degree that the ſunne is in, by the eight rule, and you ſhall enter into the table of the houſes of your region, as before hath ben ſayde, taking the degree of the ſunne vnder the ſigne in the columne of the tenth houſe, and note apart the houres and minutes of the time, whiche you

ſhall finde at the lefte ſide of the ſayd degre. And if there be minutes beſydes the degrees, you ſhall take the difference of the ſayde time, and of the time next folowinge, and the parte proportional of the ſame difference, by the aboueſaid table, intituled, tabula proportionum ad 60 minut
                        •
                     . &amp;c. with the ſayd difference, and the minutes of the ſunne. The whiche part proportionall you ſhall adde vnto the ſayde time which was taken right againſt the degree of the ſudne. Then afterward vnto y• time ſo iuſtified, you ſhall adde your time which is paſt after none, the minutes with the minutes, &amp; the houres with the houres, in addinge for 60 minutes one houre vnto the ſayd houres, the whiche houres if they do paſſe 24, you muſte ſubſtra them, and note the reſt. Likewiſe as many times as you ſhall haue 6 houres after noone, you ſhall adde vnto the ſaide time one minute, by this meanes you ſhall haue the time iuſti
                     •
                  ied for to fynde youre houſes. Then take the ſayde tyme at the lefte ſyde of the table of the houſes, vnder the title, tempus a meridie, or the mooſt neareſt vnto it (yf you fynd not the ſame preciſely) and you ſhall finde at the right hand of y• ſaid time the 6 houſes

orientalles aboue ſayd, as you may ſe by the example whiche foloweth, calculated for 8 houres after none of the ſaide laſte daye of June 1540, and for the aboue ſaid latitude of 48 degrees, the ſunne beynge then in the 17 degree and 59 minutes of Cancer.
               
                  
                     The houſes aunſweringe to the ſayde time propoſed.
                     
                         
                        hour
                        mi.
                        10
                        11
                        12
                        1
                        2
                        3
                     
                     
                        The time aun
                           
                              •
                           ring vnto the 
                              •
                           e of the ſunne
                        7
                        18
                        ♏
                        ♐
                        ♐
                        ♑
                        ♓
                        ♈
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           e time after 
                              •
                           e
                        8
                        0
                        gr
                        gr
                        gr
                        gr
                        gr
                        gr
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           e time iuſti
                           
                              ••••
                           .
                        15
                        19
                        22
                        9
                        25
                        21
                        11
                        28
                     
                  
               
            
            
               ¶ The thirde parte or difference when the time propoſed is before none.
               IF the time propoſed be before none, there ſhall be no difference or other difficultie to calculate, except that you muſt ſubſtra the time that you do adde when it is after none. Then after that you ſhall haue taken the true place of the ſunne, and haue proportioned the time aunſweringe vnto the degree of the ſunne, as before hath ben ſaid

you ſhall ſubſtra from the ſaide time, the diſtaunce of the time propoſed vntyll none, and as many minutes as the ſayde diſtaunce ſhall haue of times 6 howres, (in puttinge therunto 24 houres, yf the ſayde ſubſtraction cannot otherwiſe be made) and with that whiche ſhall reſte of the ſayde time, you ſhall finde the ſayde houſes by your table in the faſhion and maner as hath bene ſayde before of the time after none. And if you do not preciſely finde the ſayde time, you ſhal then take the moſt nereſt, or elles if ye will be ſo curious that you will haue the extreme certaintie, you ſhall take the houſes whiche are right with the time that is nexte leſſer then yours, and then with the minutes whiche do reſte, and the difference of euerye houſe, you ſhall take the parte proportionall in minutes, or in degrees and minutes, by the aboue ſayde table quatuor minutorum temporis, as it hath ben declared and done of the time of the iuſte none. The whiche partes proportionals you ſhall adde vnto the ſaide houſes, for to haue them more preciſely. And for the more better vnderſtanding, you may examine the example whiche foloweth, calculated for 8 houres in the morninge, which are foure before none of the aboue

ſayde laſt day of June 1540, and for the ſaide latitude of 48 degrees, the ſunne beinge then in the 17 degree and 21 minutes of the ſigne of Cancer.
               
                  
                     
                        hou.
                        mi.
                        The ſixe houſes orientals.
                     
                     
                        The time aunſwering vnto the degrees. of the ſunne.
                     
                     
                        17
                        15
                        10
                        11
                        12
                        1
                        2
                        3
                     
                     
                        The diſtannce of the time propoſed vntyll none.
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        ♓
                        ♈
                        ♊
                        ♋
                        ♌
                        ♌
                     
                     
                        The time iuſtified which reſteth.
                     
                     
                        2
                              •
                           
                        
                        14
                        g
                        m
                        g
                        m
                        g
                        m
                        g
                        m
                        g
                        m
                        g
                        m
                     
                     
                        The leſſer time moſt nereſt.
                     
                     
                        23
                        12
                        17
                        0
                        2
                              •
                           
                        
                        0
                        1
                              •
                           
                        
                        0
                        14
                        0
                        5
                        0
                        23
                        0
                     
                     
                        The difference.
                     
                     
                         
                        2
                        1
                        0
                        2
                        0
                        1
                        0
                        1
                        0
                        1
                        0
                        1
                        0
                     
                     
                        The parte proportionall.
                     
                     
                         
                         
                        0
                        30
                        1
                        0
                        0
                        30
                        0
                        30
                        0
                        30
                        0
                        30
                     
                     
                        The ſixe houſes iuſtified.
                     
                     
                         
                         
                        17
                        30
                        26
                        0
                        13
                        30
                        14
                        30
                        5
                        30
                        23
                        30
                     
                  
               
               
                  ¶ Of the ſixe houſes occidentals, oppoſites, or contrarye vnto the ſixe goinge before.
                  VUhan you haue the ſixe honſes orientals aboue ſaid, by one of the thre rules or differences aforeſayd, you ſhall haue then forthwith the ſixe houſes

occidentalles, by the ſignes and degrees oppoſites, for becauſe that euerye greate circle deuideth in the ſphere all other great circles, into two halues, or equall partes. As if the .x. houſe beginne at the xvii. degree of Piſces, the fourth houſe (whiche is his oppoſite, and deuided by a lyke circle) ſhall beginne at the. xvii, degre of Uirgo, whiche is oppoſite vnto the ſaide ſigne of Piſces, and ſo it is to be vnderſtand of all others, by meanes wher
                        •
                      of no man doth deſcribe in the tables any other but the ſixe houſes orientalles. For it ſuffiſeth to take the partes oppoſites for the ſixe houſes occidentalles, as we haue ſaide here aboue. The houſes and ſignes oppoſites be heare noted to thende you may haue the more eaſye vnderſtanding &amp; vſe of y• thinges aboue ſaid.
                  
                     
                        
                           The ſignes ſeptentrionalles.
                           ♈
                           ♉
                           ♊
                           ♋
                           ♌
                           ♍
                        
                        
                           The ſignes meridionals oppoſ.
                           ♎
                           ♏
                           ♐
                           ♑
                           ♒
                           ♓
                        
                        
                           The ſixe houſes orientales.
                           10
                           11
                           12
                           1
                           2
                           3
                        
                        
                           Sixe houſes occidētals oppoſi.
                           4
                           5
                           6
                           7
                           8
                           9
                        
                     
                  
                  Theſe thinges thus declared, you ſhal make the figure of the. xii houſes at the houre propoſed, and you ſhall put at the beouer

all humayne membres, are ſuch as do here folowe.
                  
                     
                        Triplicite cholerike.
                        
                           
                              Aries
                           
                           Are hoate and drye, of the nature of the fier, maſculines, of the daye; orientalles, and of the humayne members they do rule,
                           the heade
                        
                        
                           
                              Leo
                           
                           the backe and ſydes.
                        
                        
                           
                              Sagittar.
                           
                           the thighes▪
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Triplicite ſanguine.
                        
                           
                              gemini▪
                              
                           
                           Are hote and moyſt, of the nature of the ayre, maſculines, of the daye, and occidentales, and of the humayne members they do rule.
                           The ſhoulders armes &amp; hādes
                        
                        
                           
                              Libra
                           
                           the nauell &amp; lower parte of the belly.
                        
                        
                           
                              Aquar.
                           
                           the legges.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Triplicitie flewmatike.
                        
                           
                              Cancer
                           
                           Are colde moiſte, and watery, femenins, of the night, ſeptentrionales, and of the humayne mēbers they do gouerne.
                           the breſte, ſtomack, &amp; loūgs
                        
                        
                           
                              Scorpio
                           
                           the priuie partes.
                        
                        
                           
                              Piſces
                           
                           the fete.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Triplicite melancholike▪
                        
                        
                           
                              Taurus
                           
                           Are colde and drye, of the earth, femenines, and of the nighte, me ridionals, and of the humayne members they do rule.
                           the necke▪
                           
                        
                        
                           
                              virgo
                           
                           the belly &amp; in ward parts
                        
                        
                           
                              Capricor
                           
                           the knees.
                        
                     
                  
                  Lykewiſe the ſayde ſignes haue other affections, and accidentall natures, ſeruinge to the mutation of the ayre, for
                  
                     
                        
                           Aries, Cancer, Libra, Capricornus
                           
                              are
                           
                           moueable,
                        
                        
                           Taurus, Leo, Scorpius, Aquarius,
                           fyxed,
                        
                        
                           Gemini, Virgo, Sagietarius, Piſces,
                           cômune, or meane,
                        
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            ¶ Of the nature and complexion of the lightes, and of the .v. planetes. The .xx. rule.
            AFter this it is neceſſarye to haue the complexion, vertue, &amp; nature, as well of the ſunne &amp; of the mone as of the .v. planetes: the whiche is ſuch as foldweth here in orde
                  •
               .
            The Sunne is hote and drie, louing, geuynge lyfe, and lyghte vnto all naturall vertues. And of the members humayne he rulethe the brayne,

the marowe, the ſight, the ſyuewes, and generally all the members of the righte parte of the bodye.
            ¶ The mone is colde and moiſt, louyng, of whome the effectes are manifeſte, hauing dominatton ouer the ſtomacke, the bellye, and of the mother of women, and generally ouer the members of the lefte parte of humayne bodye.
            Saturnels colde and drye, enemye of nature, malitious and enuious, deſtroyer of life, and of the bodye he gouerneth the right eare, the milte, and the bladder: and of humors the inclancholye, and parte of the fleume.
            Jupiter is hoate and moiſte, louinge, ſanguine, hauinge regarde ouer the langes, the ſides, the griſtels, and of the ſede or naturall humour of man.
            Mars is hote and drye, cruell: and of the humaine bodye is attributed vnto him the lefte eare, the vaynes, the genetories, and of the humors, the choler, and after the opinion of ſome men, he gouerneth the liuer.
            Uenus is colde and moyſte, louinge, flewma
                  •
               ike, and of the bodye humayne he gouerneth the backe bone, the buttockes: the lower partes of the bellye, the matrice with the mone, and the fa
                  •
               te and

the ſede, with the ſigne of Leo.
            And it is to be noted, that Jupiter and Uenus are called good and fortunate, but Jupiter is the greateſt good fortune and Uenus the leaſte.
            Saturne and Mars are called vnfortunate, or euill fortunes, but Saturne is the greateſt vnfortunate, and Mars the leaſte.
            The Sunne and the Mone are called meanes, or betwene both, that is to ſay, neither fortunate nor vnfortunate, but indifferent.
            Neuertheleſſe, Mercury taketh parte alwayes of the nature of the Planete, with the whiche he is cont
                  •
               yned, or neareſt vnto: for with the good he is good, principally when he beholdeth him with a trine or ſextile aſpecte. And with the euill he is euill likewiſe, when he is oppoſite or comoyned with them, or when he beholdeth him with a quadrate aſpecte.
         
         
            Of the force and accidentall nature of the aſpectes. The. 21. 
                  •
                ule.
            FOr ſomuche that the lightes and planets do chaunge their influence accordinge vnto the varietie of the aſectes, whiche haue ben declared in the

12. rule, it is conuenient to note the goodnes and malice comming of the ſaide aſpectes, in the faſhion and maner as foloweth. Fyrſt as touchinge the coniunction (whiche properlye is no aſpecte) you muſt note that although the coninnctiō be defined to be one, whan the planetes are vnder one like degree of the zodiake, according vnto the longitude of y• ſame, neuertheleſſe in matter of influence, one planete is ſaide to be conioyned with the other, when the one is entred vnder the beames of the other, although that they be not in one like degre, and foreſeynge that the diſtaunce of the one vnto the other be leſſe thē 12 degres. And the mone or planet ſo conioyned wyth the Sunne, is ſayde to be combuſte by the beames of the Sunne, and ſuch coniunction is not proprely a coniunction. And it is to be noted, that when two good planetes are conioyned together, the ſame denoteth manifeſt amitie and good wyl of the one vnto the other, &amp; encreaſemente of their goodnes. And the coniunction of the good with the euill, diminiſheth the malice of the euill planete, and weakeneth ſomewhat the goodnes of the good Planete.
            
               As touchinge the oppoſition, it is an aſpect of manifeſt diſcord and inimitie.
            The quadrate aſpect is hate and vnper fite inimitie.
            The trine aſpect, ſignifieth perfect and manifeſt loue of the Planetes.
            The ſextile aſpecte, is of hidde &amp; ſecrete beneuolence, and vnperfect amitie.
         
         
            ¶ A declaration of the table of the fixed ſterres whiche is in the Ephemerides. The. 22. rule.
            FOr to knowe the aſpectes, not onely of the one planet vnto the other, but alſo of the ſayd planetes &amp; fixed ſterres, you haue before the Ephemerides a table intituled, tabula ſtellarum fyxarum inſigniorum. That is to ſaye, the table of the mooſte notable fixed ſterres, rectified in the yeare. 1499. The whiche conteineth firſt of al at the left ſide the names of the moſt notable fixed ſterres, after the members &amp; dominations of the images &amp; con ſtellatiōs in the which they ar brought. The afterward doth containe their lōgitude. that is to ſay, their true place, &amp; diſtaūce frō the beginning of Aries. After the which longitude, there foloweth the latitude of the ſayde ſterres, which is the deuiatiō &amp; diſtaūce of y• ſame fixed ſters

from the zodiake or Ecliptike li
                  •
               e, or towarde the parte meridionall. Conſequentlye foloweth the declination of the ſayde ſterres from the equinoctial circle, and the difference or denominatiō of the ſaide declination, that is to be knowen if ſhe be ſeptentrionall by this lettre S. or if ſhe be meridionall by this lettre M. Afterwarde foloweth the right aſcention of the ſame ſterres, that is to ſaye, the arche of the Equinoctiall, beginninge at the diuiſion of the ſpringe time, and heade of Aries, aſcending aboue the horizont with the ſaide ſterres in the right ſpheare, and vnder euery merediane. For all m
                  •
               r
                  •
               dianes are euery one as a right horizonte, and euery right horizont, is that whiche paſſeth by the poles of the worlde: finally is noted the greatnes or magnitude, and then the nature of the ſayde ſterres referred vnto the Planetes, as the titles, inſcriptions, and characters of the ſaide table doth ſhewe plainely inough.
         
         
            Of the 28 manſions or abidinge places of the mone. The 23. rule.
            COnſequentlye is to be noted, that euen ſo as the ſunne doth paſſe the 12 ſignes of the zodiake in 365 days

and almoſt 6 houres (whiche maketh the whole yeare) doth cauſe here below vpon the earth diuers effectes, according vnto the nature of the 12 ſignes, the diuers protection of his beames, and the diſpoſition and varietie of inferiour thinges, ſo likewiſe doth the mone, as touchinge his influence, paſſinge the ſaide Zodiake in 27 dayes, and almoſt 8 houres, accordinge vnto the metinge together of her, with the fixed ſterres, whiche are principally in the 12 ſignes of the Zodiake, for ſhe cauſeth diuers alterations, and mutations in the elementall region. By menes of the which, and to diſcerne and knowe the effectes aboueſaide, the aunciente Aſtrologians haue deuided the ſame time of 27 dayes and 8 houres into 28 egall partes, wherof euery one comprehēdeth 2
                  •
                houres and 25 minutes and almooſte 43 ſecondes, and to euerye one of theſe ſayd 28 partes, do aunſwere 12 degrees, 51 minutes and almooſt 26 ſecondes, the whiche are called the 28 manſions of the mone, of the which the diſtinctions, and beginninges iuſtified in oure time, and vnto the ninthſphere, with their natures and properties, ar brought (for more ample eaſe) into the fourme of a table thus, as foloweth.
            
               
               ¶ Heare foloweth the nature and qualitie of the 28 manſions of the mone, with the elections depending of the ſame.
               
                  
                     The 28 manſions of the mone.
                     
                        
                           
                              ••
                           e or
                           
                              •••
                            of ye 
                           
                              ••
                            man
                           
                              ••••
                           s.
                        The nature and qualitie of ye ſaid manſi
                              ••
                           
                        
                        The diſtinction &amp; beginning of euery manſion.
                        ¶ The properties &amp; accidental effectes which the mone cauſeth in euery manſion.
                     
                     
                         
                         
                        S
                        g
                        m
                         
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        temperate
                        ♈
                        19
                        26
                        It is good to iourney to ta
                              ••
                            medicine, to put on newe apparel, and noughte to hier ſeruauntes.
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        temperate
                        ♉
                        2
                        17
                        It is good to ſayle vpon the water, and to bye tame beaſtes.
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        moyſt
                        ♉
                        15
                        9
                        It is good to bye and ſell, to bye tame beaſtes, and not good to make companies.
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        cold, moiſt
                        ♉
                        28
                        0
                        It is good to ſow, to put on new apparell, and noughte to attempte mariages.
                     
                     
                        
                           5
                        drye
                        ♊
                        10
                        52
                        It is good to 
                              〈◊〉
                            medecine, to atte
                              •••
                            mariages, good t
                              •
                            
                           
                              ••
                           
                           tre children in ſco
                              •••
                            &amp; to ceaſe frō tra
                              ••••
                           
                        
                     
                     
                        6
                        temperate
                        ♊
                        23
                        43
                        It is good to m
                              •••
                            warre, nough
                              ••••
                            ſowe, or to begin 
                              〈◊〉
                            good thynge.
                     
                     
                        7
                        moyſt
                        ♋
                        6
                        15
                        It is good to 
                              〈…〉
                            to laboure, to pu
                              •
                            
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            newe apparell, noughte to take 
                              〈…〉
                            neye.
                     
                     
                        8
                        temperate
                        ♋
                        19
                        26
                        It is good to 
                              〈…〉
                            medecine, to ſha
                              •••
                            weare on new a
                              •••
                           
                           rell, and to iour
                              •••
                            by water onely.
                     
                     
                        9
                        drye▪
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        2
                        17
                        It is vnme
                              ••
                            
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            ſowe, tō take a 
                              ••••
                           
                           ney, 
                              •
                           nd to putt
                              •
                            
                           
                              ••
                            newe apparell: 
                              〈◊〉
                            to borow wheat
                              •
                           
                        
                     
                     
                        10
                        moyſt
                        ♌
                        15
                        9
                        It is good to tempte mariage 
                              〈…〉
                            not good to iour
                              •••
                            and to chaunge  
                              ••
                           
                           parell.
                     
                     
                        
                           
                        
                        temperate
                        ♌
                        28
                        0
                        It is good to ſowe, to plant, and not good to releaſe priſoners.
                     
                     
                         
                        moiſt
                        ♍
                        10
                        52
                        It is good to buylde and edifie, to plante, and ſow, and good to make mariages.
                     
                     
                         
                        temperate
                        ♍
                        23
                        43
                        It is good to ſow to laboure, to take iorney, and to make mariages.
                     
                     
                         
                        temperate
                        ♎
                        63
                        5
                        It is good to marrye wiues, to take me decine, to ſowe, and to plante.
                     
                     
                         
                        moyſt
                        ♎
                        19
                        26
                        It is good to delue welles, and ſpringes, and noughte to take iourneye.
                     
                     
                         
                        moyſt
                        ♏
                        2
                        17
                        It is not good to take iourneye, nether to take medicine, ne to bye or ſell, nor to weare new apparell.
                     
                     
                        
                           17
                        moiſt
                        ♏
                        15
                        9
                        It is good to beaſtes, and to 
                              〈…〉
                            them to paſture.
                     
                     
                        8
                        drye
                        ♏
                        28
                        0
                        It is good to 
                              〈…〉
                            landes, to buylde 
                              〈…〉
                            to receiue digni
                              •••
                           
                        
                     
                     
                        19
                        moiſt
                        ♐
                        10
                        52
                        It is good to 
                              〈…〉
                            cauſes, to aſſie 
                              〈…〉
                            ties, to take iou
                              ••••
                            and not good to 
                              〈…〉
                           
                        
                     
                     
                        20
                        moiſt
                        ♐
                        23
                        43
                        It is good to 
                              〈…〉
                            tell, and verye 
                              〈…〉
                            captiues.
                     
                     
                        21
                        temperate
                        ♑
                        6
                        35
                        It is good to 
                              〈…〉
                            edifices, to buy 
                              〈…〉
                            and to ſowe.
                     
                     
                        22
                        moyſte
                        ♑
                        19
                        26
                        It is good to 
                              〈…〉
                            medecine, to ta
                              ••
                            
                           
                              ••••
                           
                           ney, to put on n
                              •••
                            
                           
                              ••
                           
                           parell, and nau
                              ••••
                            attempte maria
                              ••
                           
                        
                     
                     
                        
                           
                        
                        temperate
                        ♒
                        2
                        17
                        It is good to take medecine, to putte on new apparell, to take iourney, and nought to make wagers.
                     
                     
                         
                        temperate
                        ♒
                        15
                        9
                        It is good to take medecine, and to conducte men of warre vnto battayle.
                     
                     
                         
                        drye
                        ♒
                        2
                              •
                           
                        
                        0
                        It is good to make noyſe, debate, &amp; warre and to iourneye towarde the regyon of South.
                     
                     
                         
                        drye
                        ♓
                        10
                        52
                        It is not good to begynne anye thinge whatſoeuer it be.
                     
                     
                         
                        moyſte
                        ♓
                        23
                        43
                        It is good to ſowe, to vſe marchaundiſe, to make mariages, and noughte to laye wagers.
                     
                     
                         
                        temperate
                        ♈
                        6
                        35
                        It is good to vſe marchaundiſe, to ſow to make mariages, and noughte to make wagers.
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶ A declaration of the table whiche is before the Ephemerides, touching the force, dignitie, exaltation, and other termes or boundes of the Planetes in euery of the 12 ſignes. 24 rule.
            FOr ſo muche that the influences as well of the lightes as of the planets, are augmented, when they be in thoſe ſignes, in the whiche they haue their force or dignitie as when they be in their propre houſe, exaltation, triplie
                  •
               
               tie, face, or terme prefixed. There is put in the Ephemerides, after the tables of the 12 houſes, a table of the 12 ſignes, of the dignitie, force, and ſtrengthe of the ſayde planetes in euery ſigne and degree of the Zodiake, of the whiche table, the interpretation is manifeſt and playne ynough by their titles, inſcriptions, and ſubſcriptions of the ſame. For firſt of all ioyning vnto the degrees of euery ſigne, you haue towarde the righte hande, the depe degres called in latin putei. noted by the letter P. then the degrees fortunates by this ſillable For. and the degrees of weakenes and defection of the humaine body, caled Aſemene by this leter A. Then

foloweth the triplicities, faces, &amp; tymes prefixed of the planetes▪ marked by the propre characters of them. Conſequently are noted the degrees maſculines, by this lettre M. and the feminines by this letter F. The darke and cloudye by this lettre T. The brighte and cleare by this lettre L. and the voyde or emptye by this lettre V. and laſte of all at the ende and righte ſide of euery ſigne, are noted the degrees of the dignities, of the lyghtes and planetes by ordre, beginning at Saturne vnto the mone, and vnto the interſections or deuiſions of ☊ and ☋, that is to ſaye, of the heade and of the tayle of the dragon of the ſame, as well by their proper characters, as by the nombre of the ſaid degrees. And vnderneth euerye ſigne, is noted the houſe and the degree of the exaltation &amp; detriment of the ſayde lightes and planetes, which are thinges neceſſary &amp; worthy to be noted of al ſuch as do practiſe the iugemente of the ſters.
         
         
            ¶ Generall and perticuler rules, for to iudge of the mutation and chaunge of the ayre. The 25 rule.
            TO vnderſtand and to knowe more eaſelye how to iudge of the chaungement of the time or wether, and

the mutation of the ayre, it is firſt requiſite to knowe the qualitie and diſpoſition of the foure 
                  •
               artes and ſeaſons of the yeare, whiche are ſuche as foloweth. The ſpringe time is hoat and moiſt, ſanguine, and beginneth when the ſunne entreth into the ſigne of Aries. The ſomer is hoate and drye, cholerike, and beginneth when the Sunne entreth into the ſigne of Cancer. Harueſte is colde and dry, melancholike, and beginneth when the Sunne entreth into the ſigne of Libra. The winter is colde and moyſt, fleuma
                  •
               ike, and beginneth when the Sunne entreth into the ſigne of Capricornus. Afterwardes muſte be knowen and vnderſtande the natures and affections of the 12 ſignes of the Zodiake, here before expreſſed in the ninetenth rule. For y
                  •
                the planettes (yea thoſe that be of a hote nature) doo beholde the one the other, or be conioyned together in hoate and drye ſignes, they ſhall cauſe heate and exceſſe of drougth in Sommer, or elles temperaunce of ayre in Winter. And contrary wiſe, if the ſayde aſpectes and coniunctions of the planetes aboueſayd, do happen in colde and drye ſygnes, they wyll cauſe in wynter great ſnowes and yet, and in ſommer moderation of the 
                  •
               eate,

and in hoate and moiſte ſignes, greate aboundaunce of windes. And if this happen in waterye ſignes, they will cauſe then great haboundaunce of rayne, whiche will make the ayre very intemperate in winter, and of a moderate heate in ſō
               mer. And ſo is to be vnderſtande, and to iudge conformablye of all lyke thinges, accordinge vnto the nature of the planets and ſignes, and the▪ qualitie of their aſpectes. Alſo hauinge regarde with the ſame, vnto the nature of the▪ fixed ſterres likewiſe of them whiche are moſt n
                  ••
               eſt vnto the Zodiake. And that not onely in all elections, but alſo in the mutation of the ayre lykewiſe, as ſhalbe perticulerlye recited hereafter.
            
               ¶ Perticuler rules of the aſpectes of the planetes amonge them ſelues.
               
                  ☌ ♄ ♃FIrſte the coniunction of Saturne with Jupiter diligentlye obſerued in hoate and drye ſignes, cauſe the greate drougth many dayes before, and many dayes after the ſayd coniunction: and in moiſt ſignes, continuall inundation of waters, and perticuler flouds, becauſe they abide longe together, for the ſlowenes of their mouementes.
               
                  Likewiſe the oppoſition, quadrature,♄ ☍□⚹, ♃ or ſextile aſpecte of the ſayde Saturne, with Jupiter, is the cauſe of great mutations in the ayre, and engēdreth raynes, hayles, and windes many dayes before, and many dayes after the ſayd oppoſition or aſpect. Alſo there foloweth greate mutations of wether, at altimes, and as often as ther is ſextile aſpect of Saturne with the Sunne, or of Jupiter with Mercurye, or trine aſpecte of Mars with Uenus, or contrarywiſe, the which aſpects are commonly called of the aſtrologians the openinge of the gates of heauens, for ſo much that they do moue and trouble the ayre, and do cauſe notable chaunge of weather.
               
                  ♄, ☌, □ ☍ wt ♂The coniunction, oppoſition, or quadrature of Saturne with Mars, in moiſt ſignes, engendreth raine, hayle, and thō
                  dre▪ with tempeſtes 
                     •
                   dayes before, and as many dayes after the ſayde coniunction.
               
                  ♄, ☌, □ ☍ wt ☉The coniunction▪ quadrature, or oppoſition of Saturne with the Sunne, cheifly in cold ſignes, engendreth haile, raine darke wether, thunder, and colde dayes, and notable mutaſion of the ayre.
               
                  ♄, ☌, □ ☍ wt ♀The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of Saturne with Uenus in winter

engendreth colde and rayne, principally in watery ſignes. And in ſommer mit
                     •
                  
                  gation of heate.
               
                  ♄, ☌, □ ☍ wt ☿The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of Saturne with Mercury in moiſt ſignes, bringeth rayne, in hote and drye ſignes, cauſeth droughte, and in Somer thonder, lightninges, and tempeſte.
               
                  ♃ ☌, □ ☍ wt ♂The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of Jupiter with Mars, in moyſte ſignes, cauſeth raynes, lightninges, and thunders, in Winter ſhewe and cloudy weather, and in hoate ſignes and dry
                     •
                  
                  ▪ cauſeth exceſſe heate.
               
                  ♃ ☌, □ ☍ wt ☉The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of the ſaid Jupiter with the ſunne▪ cauſeth greate and mooſte vehemente windes, dryuinge away all raynes.
               
                  ♃ ☌, □ ☍ wt ♀The coniunction, quadrature, and oppoſition of Jupiter with Uenus, in moiſt ſignes, caiſeth colde and miſlinges, and that more cer
                     •
                  at
                     ••
                  elye, in caſe there happen any coniunction▪ quadrature, or oppoſition of the mone, but when they be co
                     ••
                  o
                     •
                  ned with other ſignes, cauſeth fair wether and windes.
               
                  ♃ ☌, □ ☍ wt ☿The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of Jupiter with Mercurye, cauſeth great windes, and alteration of wether.
               
                  
                  ♂ ☌, □ ☍ wt ☉The coniunction, quadrature or oppoſition of Mars with the Sunne in fyrye ſignes, cauſeth drougth, in waterye ſignes thonder and rayne.
               
                  ♂ ☌, □ ☍ wt ♀The coniunction, quadrature or oppoſition of Mars with Uenus in moyſte ſignes, cauſeth rayne and tempeſt.
               
                  ☌, □ ☍ wt ☿The coniunction quadrature or oppoſition of Mars with Mercurye in hoate and drye ſignes, cauſeth great heate and drougth, in waterye ſignes rayne, ſome times thonders and lightninges, with ſo dayne fierce windes.
               
                  ☉, ☌, ♀ ☍□ 
                     ☽
                  The coniunction of the ſunne with Uenus in moiſt ſignes by meanes of the oppoſition or quadrature of the moone▪ cauſeth raynes.
               
                  ☉ ☌ ☿The coniunction of the Sunne with Mercury, in moiſt ſignes, cauſeth raine, and in wyndye ſygnes, as are Gemini, Libra, &amp; Aquarius▪ do engender winds▪
               
               
                  ♀ ☌, □ ☍ wt ☿The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of Uenus with Mercury in moiſte ſignes, cauſeth rayne, in caſe they be not 
                     •
                  et by anye other euell planete. And in 
                     •
                  ommer they prouoke tempeſte, the more if they be in watry ſignes. And note that 
                     •
                  ll the Planettes aboue ſayde, haue great force, when the mone is in coniunction, oppoſition, or quadrature wyth

them, and accordinge to the varietie of the nature of the ſignes, and the qualitie of the houſes of the ſaid mone.
               Note alſo what is ſayde of the coniunction, quadrature, and oppoſition, the ſame is ment likewiſe of the ſextile, and trine aſpect, but they are of leſſe ſignification.
            
            
               ¶ Perticuler rules by the aſpectes of the mone with the planetes.
               
                  
                     ☽, ☌, □ ☍ wt ♄THe coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſitiō of the mone with Saturne in moiſt ſignes, bringeth a cloudy daye, and colde ayre, according vnto the nature of the ſigne: And if the Mone do go frome Saturne vnto the Sunne, by coniunction or otherwiſe, harde wether enſueth.
               
                  
                     ☽, ☌, □ ☍ wt ♃The coniunction, quadrature, or opſition of the moone with Jupiter, in the ſignes of Aries and Scorpio, ſheweth fayre wether, with white diſperſed cloudes. And if Mars be diſpoſed to the ſame by anye aſpecte, it cauſeth thunders and lightninges, or elles great windes. After the which coniunction, if the mone come vnto Mercurye, there foloweth greate windes, the whiche are mittigate, and layed by the oppoſition or quadrature of

the ſayde mone with Jupiter, but if the planetes whiche be of ſlowe mouement be not diſpoſed thervnto, the aboueſayde coniunction ſhall bringe fayre weather.
               
                  
                     ☽, ☌, □ ☍ wt ♂The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of the mone with Mars, in watery ſignes, cauſeth rayne, &amp; yf the mone be ſeperate from Mars, and commeth vnto Venus, there foloweth notable chaunge of wether, but in hote ſignes cauſeth diuers coulered cloudes all ouer the elemente, in ſommer often thunder, bringinge with them ſometimes ſmall miſlinges, principally if the planetes be in aſpects diſpoſed thervnto.
               
                  
                     ☽, ☌, □ ☍ wt ☉The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of the moone with the Sunne in moiſt ſignes, bringeth raynye weather, the more if the mone go from the Sunne vnto Saturne.
               
                  
                     ☽, ☌, □ ☍ wt ♀The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of the mone with Venus, cheiflye in moiſt ſignes, rain foloweth: the mone going from Venus vnto Mars by oppoſition, quadrature, or ſextile aſpecte, be to keneth greate varietie of weather.
               
                  
                     ☽, ☌, □ ☍ wt ☿The coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of the mone with mercury in moiſt ſignes, ſheweth great rayne and windes to enſue, the more if ſhe go from Jupiter

and come vnto the ſayde Mercury, or if Saturne and Mars be in oppoſition or quadrate aſpecte duringe the ſayde coniunction.
               Wherefore you muſt note in all coniunctions of the mone with the planets, The coniunctions and quadratures of them, and likewiſe of the fixed ſterres after their nature aboueſayde.
               And when the mone is without any aſpect in moiſte ſignes and manſions, the ſame denoteth rayne, wherefore he that will iudge more perfitely, and more ſurely, it is conuenient in all and euerye of the thinges aboueſayde, that he conſidre diligentlye the nature of the ſignes, and of the manſions of the moone, and the diſpoſition of the foure times and ſeaſons of the yeare at their fyrſte enterynge.
            
            
               ¶ Other rules, and generall doctrines, for to knowe better and more ſurelye to iudge of the varietie of the time and weather, of the alteration of the ayre by the coniunctions, quadratures, &amp; oppoſitions of the ſunne and of the mone.
               
                  FOr as muche as the mutation of the ayre is one of the moſt neceſſaryeſt thinges, as well for the fruits of the earth, as for the health of the humayne body, and beſides that, one of the partes of the iudgement of Aſtrologie, more apparent and likeſt true, I haue ſet here all at ones ouer and beſides the thinges aboueſayd, ſome leſſons and notable rules, for to knowe the better and more ſbrely howe to iudge of the ſaid alteration of the ayre.
               Firſt you muſt diligently note the ſinifications and general rules which we haue declared in the rule goinge before, for ſomuche that the generall ſignifications do chaunge and ſurmount the perticuler vertues, by reaſon that the greateſt vertue draweth vnto him the leſſer, and the leſſer doth obey vnto the greater, and with this, the perticuler vertues are not of ſo great vertue and ſtrength, as be the generall.
               It is then neceſſarye for all men that wyll iudge of particuler thinges, to conſider, and beholde firſt the thinges whiche be vniuerſall and generall. As if you wyll prognoſticate of the qualitie, and diſpoſition of ani day propoſed, you muſt diligently conſider theſtate or diſpoſition

of any day propoſed, you muſt diligently▪ conſider the ſtate or diſpoſition of the time, in the whiche the ſayd daye propoſed ſhall chaunce or happen. Of the whiche eſtate and diſpoſition, you ſhal iudge by the lorde of the coniunction, quadrature▪ or oppoſitiō preceding of the Sunne and ſhe mone, and of the ſigne where ſhe is made. The whiche Lorde of the ſayde coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition, you ſhal knowe by the figure of the auen, that is to ſaye of the twelue houſes, and places of the planetes iuſtlye verefied at the▪ hour of the ſame coniunction, oppoſition, or quadrature. Then when you ſhal haue the figure of heauen well iuſtified for the time aboue ſayde of the coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſitiō of the ſunne and of the mone, you ſhall firſte conſider in whiche of the 12 houſes, and in what ſigne ſhall fal the ſayd coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition, and the ſigne and degree aſcendent, with the ſignes and degrees of the other angles. For the▪ planet whiche ſhal haue in the ſaid places more prerogatiue, force, and domination, ſhalbe principall lorde of the ſaide time and figure, and that whiche ſhall haue leaſte, ſhalbe participant in the ſaid lordeſhip, &amp; dominatiō. And it is to be noted, that the

planet which hath moſt dominatiō vpon the place of the ſaid coniunction, oppoſition, or quadrature, and vpon the ſigne &amp; degree aſcendant, doth ſurmount all the others, and ought to be in this place preferred. Loke then of what nature the planete is which ſhall rule in the ſaid figure For the vniuerſal diſpoſition of the time ſhall holde the qualitie of the ſaid planet. As if at the time of the ſaid coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition, Saturne be founde lorde, the time ſhall be colde and drye. And if it be Uenus, it ſhal be moiſt, and ſo of others, after their nature, and qualitie, excepte the ſunne and the mone: for the beſt aſtrologians, do neuer chuſe the ſunne nor the mone in this place for Lordes nor rulers, for becauſe that they do eſteme the 5 planetes to be the onelye moderatours of the time and weather, that is to ſaye Saturne, Jupiter, Mars, Uenus, and Mereurye. And not wtoute a cauſe, in the coniunctiō they do chuſe the Lord of the place of the ſaid coniunction. And in the oppoſitiō, the lord of the place of the ſame of the lightes which ſhalbe aboue thearth, or in thorient preciſely, for there is in this place moſt greateſt vertu. Likewiſe in iudging almoſt as much by the place of the quadrature of the ſayde lightes, for thei take the place of the ſame

light whiche is aboue the horizont, if the other be vnderneth. And if they be bothe aboue, or both vnderneth the ſaide horizont (as it chaunceth often times) they take then for the place of the ſayde quadrature, the place of the ſame light whiche is founde to haue moſt force and dignitie. As if one of the planeties were in one of the angles, or houſes ſuccedinge. and the other in the houſe fallynge, the ſame whiche is in the ſayde angle, or hooſe ſuccedinge, ſhalbe preferred before the ſame whiche is in the fallinge houſe. The whiche force, dignities, and other witneſſes of the planetes, you ſhall extra out of the table, which is expreſſelye put in the Ephemerides, for the ſame cauſe, the whiche hath ben ſufficiently declared in the 24 rule. Then when you ſhall haue the Lorde and dominatoure at the time of the coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition of the lightes, you ſhall fyrſte note his nature and qualitie. For mooſt often times the diſpoſition of the tyme ſhall reſemble the ſame. Secondlye you ſhall conſidre the ſigne in the whiche is the ſayde lorde and dominatoure, for the time ſhall be diſpoſed vnto the qualitie of the ſayde ſigue. Furthermore, you ſhall haue regarde vnto the ſigne whiche is

then aſcendant, and vnto his nature, and of what manſion of the mone he is, with out forgettinge the lord of the ſayd ſigne aſcendant. Afterward you ſhal take hede and ſe whiche planets are in the angles: for thoſe whiche do occupie the middeſte of heauen, or the aſcendant, ſhall be better and more ſtronger then they whiche ſhall be in the angle of the 7 or 4 houſe. Conſequentlye you ſhall marke, with whiche of the planetes the mone cometh to be conioyned, or in aſpecte after the 
                     ••
                  y
                     •
                  d coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition. Likewiſe you ſhall note with which of 
                     •
                  he planettes, or notable fyxed ſterres, the lord of the ſayd figure i
                     •
                   conioyned, or beheld with any aſpect. Theſe thynges thus cōſidered, you may bringe to effect, and perfectly iudge as foloweth If the ſayd lord of the coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition, be of a moyſt nature, and the places aboue ſayd and planettes being in them likewiſe moyſt: and with this the ſayd lord being conioyned, or in any aſ
                     ••••
                   with any moyſt ſterres or planettes. And if the moone after the ſayd coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition, come to be conioyned, or in aſpect with ſome moiſt planet ioyned therunto that the qualitye of the time be diſpoſed

vnto moyſtnes: if all the thinges aboutſayd or the moſt part of them do tend vnto humiditie, you may gather and iudge that the time ſhall be mayſte, and if they tende vnto drouthe, that it ſhall be drye, and if vnto heate that it ſhalbe hote: and if vnto coldnes, that it ſhal be colde: and if there be as many witneſſes for the one qualitie, as for the other, the time ſhalbe indifferent, hauing then knowen the general diſpoſition of the time (as now preſently hath 
                     •
                  ene ſayd) you ſhal diſcretlye entremingle the applications of the moone vnto the planettes and of the one planet vnto the other, for to indge more certeynly of the perticuler days. And to make an end of this matter, you ſhall yet note theſe .ii. leſſons, wherof the firſte is. that the ſygnyfycation of the tyme thus found as hath bene ſayde aboue, his effect principally ſhall appeare, and come forth, when the moone after the coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition, aboueſayde ſhalbe conioyned or comme vnto ſome ſtronge planet, with the ſygnificatour of the ſayd time.
               ¶ The ſeconde is that when the moone ſhall come vnto the ſigne aſcendant, during the ſayd coniunction, quadrature, or oppoſition, the time ſhalbe diſpoſed vn

to the nature and qualitie of the ſayde ſigne. And this ſuffiſeth for the diſpoſition of the time and chaunge of the weather.
            
         
         
            ¶ Of the aſpectes and conſtellations which muſt be obſerued and choſen for to beginne and ende happelye all workes and humayne buſineſſe. The .xxvii. rule.
            THe dyſpoſition of the heauenly bodyes do grea
                  •
               lye inclyne the inferiour thinges to bee happely done or begonne, and dothe aduaunce theyn: or elles make late theyr comminge to perfection, and their full and hole effecte to comme forthe, for this cauſe are here ſette forthe by order the elections whiche muſt be obſerued or auoyded in theſe places beginninge at Saturne and then at the other planettes in order.
            
               
               
                  
                     
                        Saturne beinge with the moone in
                     
                     
                        Coniunction
                     
                     ¶ Cauſeth an euell vnluckye daye for all matters, and principally it is not good to haue to doo with aged people, ne wt rural folkes nor laborers.
                  
                  
                     
                        ſextile aſpect
                     
                     ¶ It is good to haue to doo with olde folkes and of good counſel, to edefy caſtelles and houſes, and to erecte thinges that are in ruyne, to plowe, to plant, and nought to requyre the loue of women.
                  
                  
                     
                        quadrature▪
                        
                     
                     ¶ You muſt beware and kepe your ſelfe from olde folkes, and from labouring. or planting, it is nought alſo to iourney and leaue to accompliſhe thy deſire eſpeciallye if it bee euel.
                  
                  
                     
                        trine aſpecte
                     
                     It is good to haue to do with aged people, to labour y• earth &amp; vines, to ſowe and to plante trees, to fortfye caſtelles, and to make the foundacion of cityes and townes
                  
                  
                     
                        oppoſition.
                     
                     It is neither good to ſowe nor to plant, nor to beginune any matter what ſo euer it be, &amp; it is requiſite to auoyde y• cōuer ſatiō &amp; meting wt olde folkes.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     
                        Iupiter beinge with the moone in
                     
                     
                        coniunction.
                     
                     ¶ It is good to be conuerſant with noble men, with religyous perſons and lawyars, &amp; to giue ſupplications, and requeſtes, and to demaunde right and iuſtice.
                  
                  
                     
                        Sextile. Aſpect.
                     
                     It is good to ſpeake vnto iudges, and eccleſiaſtical and religious perſons, and to begin all good workes.
                  
                  
                     
                        quadrature▪
                        
                     
                     It is a mete time to ſtudye in philoſophy, to mete with iudges and religious perſons, &amp; to require right and iuſtice.
                  
                  
                     
                        Trine aſpect
                     
                     It is good to beginn all good matters and to haue to doo with lawyars, iudges, religious perſons, and their prelates, and to require of theyn: the thinge which they would obtayne.
                  
                  
                     
                        Oppoſition,
                     
                     It is a mete time to ſtudye in philoſophye and to haue conuerſation with eccleſiaſticall perſons, and with noble men and to go before Judges.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     
                        Mars beinge with the moone in
                     
                     
                        Coniunction
                     
                     It is good to auoyde warriours, and all noiſes, debates, and ſtrife.
                  
                  
                     
                        ſextile aſpect
                     
                     It is good to leade and encourage men of warre vnto the battell, to haue to do with princes and captaines, to buy horſes for the warres, and thinges of redde coloure, and to finiſh all firy workes.
                  
                  
                     
                        quadrature▪
                        
                     
                     It is an vnmete time to mete with gentlemen, and knightes and to worke in firie workes.
                  
                  
                     
                        trine aſpecte
                     
                     It is good to be with warriours, and to deuiſe of things perteininge to the warres, to buy beaſtes, and to make fyer for the alch
                           •
                        mye.
                  
                  
                     
                        oppoſition.
                     
                     It is an vnmete tyme to treate of loue, and frendſhips, to take ſeruauntes, and to beginne any thinge whatſoeuer that it be.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     
                        Sol beinge with the moone in
                     
                     
                        coniunction.
                     
                     It is good to finiſhe hidden matters, and ſecrete counſels, that one would not haue to be knowen, and naught to do any other thinge.
                  
                  
                     
                        Sextile. Aſpect.
                     
                     It is good to haue to do with kinges, princes, wiſe mē and of counſell, and good to require right, offices, and dignities.
                  
                  
                     
                        quadrature▪
                        
                     
                     It is not good to mete with princes, and noble men.
                  
                  
                     
                        Tsine aſpect
                     
                     It is good to mete with kinges, princes, counſellers, people of eſtate, and to require of them right and iuſtice, and that thinge which a man wold obtaine of theim, and to ſeke loue and frendſhip of princes.
                  
                  
                     
                        Oppoſition▪
                        
                     
                     It is a very vnhappye daye for all matters, therefore at tempte nothinge, ne any manner of ſute, neither plant, build nor iourneye.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     
                        Venus be iuge with the moone in
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           oniunction
                     
                     It is good to take a wife, to treate of loue, to haue cohabitation with wemen, and good to take ſeruauntes.
                  
                  
                     
                        ſextile aſpect
                     
                     It is good to attempte mariage, to ſeke the loue of wemen, to put on newe apparel, and to ſpeak vnto noble men.
                  
                  
                     
                        quadrature
                     
                     It is good alſo to take a wife, good to woo and to obtayne ſutes of womenne, to combe the heade, and to putte on newe apparell.
                  
                  
                     
                        trine aſpect.
                     
                     It is lykewiſe good to take a wife, to combe the heade, to ſeke the loue of women, to be conuerſaunte with theym, and to putte on newe apparell.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     
                        Mercurye beynge with the moone in
                     
                     
                        eomunction.
                     
                     It is good and a lucky day to bye and ſell, to iourneye, to geue accomptes, good to entre children in liberall artes, and to demaunde benefices.
                  
                  
                     
                        ſextile aſpect
                     
                     It is good for the verſifier, to pleade cauſes, to geue accomptes, to iourneye, to bye and ſell, to vſe marchaundiſe▪ and good to entre chyldren to learninge.
                  
                  
                     
                        quadrature.
                     
                     It is good to calculate, and to render vp accomptes, to ſend embaſſage, good to haue to do with penne menne and wryters, to bye and ſell, and to iourneye.
                  
                  
                     
                        Oppoſition.
                     
                     It is good to meete with writers, to bye and ſell, to vſe marchaundiſe, to ſend embaſſage and meſſengers, &amp; 
                           •
                        good to ſet children to ſtudye and learninge.
                  
               
            
            
               Likewiſe when the moone after her coniunction with anye fortunate planette ſhal be notably remoued farre from the ſayd planet, the daye ſhal be vnfortunate and when ſhe ſhall be notablye remoued farre from her coniunction with any vnfortunace planet, it is the good to worke in all matters, eſpeciallye the moone being in the ſigne of Cancer, Taurus, Piſces or Sagittarius, or in the houſe of the Sunnne, hauynge Trine or Sextil e aſpect with the ſayd Sunne.
            ¶ Beſides this the moone hath certeyne and propre effectes in euery one of the. xii ſignes, in caſe ſhe bee not then letted by any ſtronge ſignification or conſtellation. The whyche are ſuche as foloweth.
            
               Aries,
               It is good to begin that which a man would haue ſone ended, and nought to beginne anye thinge that a man would haue to be firme and ſtable, and to haue to do with kinges, and riche men, good to bathe, &amp; nought to clippe heare, &amp; to ſcarifye the ſkinne with cuppinge, of ſuche as haue diſeaſe in their necke and eares.
               Tau.
               It is good to beginne ſuche thinges, as you woulde haue to be firme and ſtable, good to ſowe, and to plant trees, to labour the vines, to buylde, to be gladde and merye, to comen with women, and

to bye bulles and beues.
               Gemi
               It is good to begin the thinges whiche ſhoulde be of litle duraunce, good to put children to learninge, and not mete to let bloude.
               Cācer
               It is good to iourney, to make vyages, and to take electuaries.
               Leo.
               It is good to beginne ſuch thinges as ſhall be of longe duraunce, and ſtable, and nought to take medecine by vomite and to ſhape and putte on newe apparell.
               Virgo
               It is good to putte children to be inſtructed in learninge, to ſeke the loue of younge maydens, and not good to marrye.
               Libra
               It is good to begin thinges of ſmall duraunce, te ionrney, to bye and ſell, to haue to do with religious perſons, &amp; not good to haue copulation with women.
               Scorp
               It is an vnlucky day for to begin any matter of goodnes.
               Sagit.
               It is good to learne to ſhote in the bow, to vſe marchaundiſe, to be conuerſaunte with iudges, and men of lawe, and to haue copulation with women.
               Capri.
               It is good to be in company with aged people, to plowe the fieldes, and to decke gardens and vines.
               Aqua.
               It is good to edefie towres and

cities, and to buyld houſes, to plant trees and decke vines.
               Piſces.
               It is good to iourneye and to go a fyſſhinge.
            
            And here you muſt note, that whan the moone is in a moueable ſigne, it is then good to beginne the thinges, where of ye deſire ſone to haue an ende, and in a fixed ſigne, that whiche you deſire to be of lōge duraunce. And in common ſignes, the thinges whiche ye will haue of litle duraunce.
            And whan the mone is cōioyned with the fortunate ſterres, the aſpecte is fortunate, and contrarywiſe vnfortunate.
            Likewiſe whan the mone is in the ſection or diuiſion of the head of the dragon thus figured ☊, ſhe is fortunate, and in the ſection of the taile of the dragon, thus marked ☋ vnfortunate.
         
         
            ¶ Of elections which are to be obſerued in the plylebotomie or lettinge of bloud. The. 28. rule.
            VVHo that will conſequently know whan it is good to lette bloude, he muſt take good hede vnto the aſpectes whiche folowe. Fyrſte, if the mone be in coniunctiō with Jupiter in a mete ſigne, or in trine aſpecte, or in oppoſition

with him, or in in aſpect with Venus: it is good then to be let bloude. The ſignes mete are Aries, and Sagittarius, for the flemmatikes, and the firſte parte of Libra, for the melancolickes, and for the cholerickes Cancer Piſces, and the ſignes diſagreīng vnto the Phebotomy are Leo. the ſeconde part of Libra, &amp; the firſt part of Scorpius. Likewiſe is to be noted that al ye hole courſe of the moone is deuided into foure quarters whyche muſt alſo be be obſerued.
            
               
                  
                     The
                     1
                     is from
                     the new mone
                     vntyll.
                     the fyrſt qu
                           •
                        rter.
                     good for
                     yonge people,
                  
                  
                     2
                     the firſt 
                           •
                        uarter
                     the 
                           •
                        ull mone
                     yonge and myd
                           •
                        e aged
                  
                  
                     3
                     
                        
                           •
                        he full mone
                     the. 
                           •
                        i. quarter.
                     midle aged and olde.
                  
                  
                     4
                     the ſecō quar
                           •
                        er
                     the new mone.
                     olde folkes o
                           •
                        elye.
                  
               
            
            ¶ Likewiſe you muſt cut no vayne, nor touche any membre withany yron 
                  •
               oole what ſo euer it be, the moone beinge in the ſigne which beholdeth, and hath domination vpon the ſayd membre. What membres are ſubiect vnto euerye ſigne hath ben declared in the .xix. rule.
            And on the other part, it is not onelye euel to let bloude, when the moone is in the ſection of the head or of the tayle of the dragon (thus marked. ☊. ☋.) but alſo by 
                  〈1… pages missing〉
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  〈1… pages missing〉
               
               with Mars, Saturne, or Jupiter. And this ſhal ſatiſfy you for me decinal rlections.
         
         
            ¶ Of elections for to ſowe, and to plant trees and vines. The .xxx. rule.
            FInally as towchinge the moſte apte and mete time, for 
                  •
               o ſowe &amp; plante trees, &amp; to dec
                  •
               e vyn
                  ••
               , it behoueth to note that there are▪ v. monthes▪ in the yeare deputed and mooſte 
                  •
               ete for the ſame, that is to ſa
                  ••
               , Marche, Apryll, Maye, Septembre and Octobre▪ But in al times, you muſt take hede of the euill aſpectes of Saturne and of Mars. And to kepe the aſpects &amp; places of the moone which do here folowe
            
               
                  
                     If the mone de behold Saturn wt trine or ſextile aſpect, bein
                           •
                         in the ſigne of
                     Taurus,
                     It i
                           •
                         good
                     to plant trees &amp; vines▪
                     
                  
                  
                     Cancer.
                     to 
                           •
                        ow
                           •
                         generally.
                  
                  
                     Virgo.
                     to ſowe fielde
                           •
                        .
                  
                  
                     Libra.
                     to ſow and to garden.
                  
                  
                     Capricor.
                     to ſowe generally.
                  
                  
                     Aquarius
                     to plant trees &amp; vines.
                  
               
            
            And eſpecially if the moone do beholde Venus or Jupiter (which are the. 
                  ••
               . beſt fortunates) with Trine, Sextile, or quadrate, Aſpect. And it is good to plante trees at the laſt quarter of the moone.
            Concluſion of the Author.
            And this ſuffiſeth for the declaration vſe

and practiſe, of the matters, conteyned aſwel in the Almanackes, or Ephemerides, as in y• Latin rules of the ſame. In the whiche I haue not folowed the letter worde by worde, but onelye the meaninge and doctrine in chaunginge, addinge, and ſubſtrainge that whyche I thought worthy to be chaunged, added, and ſubſtrayed, bycauſe of the more perfect and eaſter erudition, deſyringe my lord god with all my power to ſatiſfye you herein, and all theim whiche be louers of this ſcience.
            Finis.
            
               ¶ Vireſcit vulnere virtus▪
               
            
         
         
            
               ✴ 
               Here folovveth a ſingular treatiſe of Aſtrologie touching the coniunctions of the planettes in euery of the twelue ſignes, and of theyr Prognoſtications in the reuolutions of yeares.
            
               IF you deſire to knowe euerye yeare▪ what thinges ſhalbe deere, and what good cheape, or of a meane price, ſie what ſigne is aſcendant aboue youre horizont, at the hour that the ſunne entreth into the firſte minute of Aries. For the planet whiche ſhall be then in the ſayde ſigne. ſhall be Lorde of the ſaide yeare.
            Let then be made the figure of heuen in the which lette be ordeined the 12 houſes, accordinge vnto the ſaid aſcendent, and let be ordeined the 7 planetes in the ſayde houſes, as by their mouement preciſely iuſtified they ſhalbe founde to be then in heauen. And this done, ſe and cō
               ſider
                  •
               duly the natures of the 12 ſignes▪ &amp; of the ſterres beinge in them. And according as by the induſtry of youre ſpirite you may eſteame and inuente, ſo iudge of thinges to come the ſame yeare, as hereafter I ſhall ſhewe, for you maye iudge to the veritie.
            
               ¶ Of the ſignifications of the planetes in euerye of the ſayde ſignes and houſes.
               FIrſt then if Saturne be in the aſcendant in the firſt houſe or ſigne, or in the 10. Then all wightie and blacke thinges, as azur, yron, leade, and wollen cloth of black 
                     •••
                  er ſhalbe dear the ſame

yeare. And if the ſayd Saturne be in the fourth, ninth, and twelfth houſe, the ſaid thinges ſhalbe ſomewhat deare, and not muche.
               But if he be founde in any of the houſes fallynge, as is the third, ſix
                     •
                  , nynthe, and twelfth, the ſaid thinges ſhalbe neither deare nor yet good cheape, but of a meane price.
               So ſaye we and muſte iudge of other planets and thinges vppon the whiche they haue their ſignification, of the whiche planetes the ſignifications, for to make ſhort, are ſuch as folowe. Jupiter ſignifyeth oyle, cotton, hony, and ſiluer. Mars ſignifieth pepper, targettes, and all other armours. The ſunne ſignifieth gold that is vnforged, and that hath not bene wrought. Venus ſignifieth al greaſes, oyntmentes, ſpices, white odoriferāt wood, perles and the ornamentes of women. Mercury ſignifieth all ſmall graines, all maner of ſilke woorkes, as well tiſſhues as others, nuttes and thinges of like qualitie. And the mone ſignifieth ſwete encence, mylke, cheeſe, and other lyke thinges.
            
            
               Of the ſignification of the coniuntion of the planets in the ſigne of Aries.
               
                  VUhen you ſhall haue thē made the figure, and found Saturne &amp; Jupiter conioyned together in the ſigne of Aries, or the one of them neare vnto the other, they ſignifie ſome newe ſecte to come. But if in the ſaid ſigne of Aries are founde to be Jupiter, Uenus, Mercury, the ſunne, and the mone, or for the leaſt thre of them, there ſhalbe greate plentie of all thinges, people ſhalbe enclined to goodnes, and there ſhall be great raynes, and hayles, writers and ſcriueners ſhall muche profit Cattell ſhall be at a lowe and vyle price. And the freſſhe Riuers and waters ſhall aboundantl
                     •
                  e encreaſe. And if Jupiter and the mone be founde in one like degre of the ſaid ſigne of Aries, in the orientall or eaſte parte, it ſignifieth then that the kinge ſhal do iuſtice and right iugement in his realmes and that his kingedome and lordeſhippe ſhall proſpere. But if Saturne, &amp; Mars, or Mars and Jupiter, or Mars and Mercury, or the ſaide Mars and Uenus be founde in the place aboueſaide, and orientall parte, there ſhal be warre, &amp; great effuſion of bloude amonge the Arabians in theyr countreis, and they ſhall be deſtroyed, &amp; their men of warre taken and ſeperated into diuers countreis.
            
            
               
               Of the ſignification of the coniunction of the planets in the ſigne of Taurus.
               If Uenus and Mars be found conioyned in one like degre of the ſigne of Taurus, then wemen ſhall moue ſeditions againſt men, hopinge to be violated by them, and there ſhalbe a greate death of catel. But if Mars be in the ſigne of Taurus, there ſhall be warre towarde the South parte, and ſuche vehemente windes, that the fruit ſhal fal from the trees and the moſt part ſhal periſhe by drouth. And if Mars, Jupiter, Uenus, and the mone, or three of theim be founde in the place and part aboueſaide, men ſhal lightely make lies, and there ſhall be greate noyſes and tumult among them ſelues, and that yeare ſhall die the moſt beutiful creatures, for Jupiter and Uenus do ſignifie the fayreſt, and Mars ioyned and abidinge with theim in the ſaide ſigne and degree, ſhall ſlea them. And beſides this there ſhall be greate raines, and aboundaunce of waters as wel of the ſea as of the floudes and riuers. And at the ſonth part people ſhall riſe and rebel, deſiringe to ſlaye their Lorde, but they can not do it. And if Saturne, Jupiter, and Mars, be in the ſaid degree of Taurus, then the emperours and kinges▪ ſhal loſ
                     •
                  
                  
their realme, or beinge aſtonied wyth ouermuch feare ſhal die. And the men of religion, as chanons and monkes, ſhall leaue their habites, or els ſhall dye. But if Saturne &amp; Mars be onely in the ſame place▪ and ſigne as aboue, women ſhall haue diſeaſes in their 
                     •
                  eates, in the throte and in the priuie partes, and the men in the generall partes, and in the bladder.
            
            
               ¶ Of the ſignification of the cōiunction of the planetes in Gemini.
               If the Sunne, Uenus, and the moone are conioyned in the ſigne of Gemini, the ſcriueners and writers ſhall gaine but litle that yere, &amp; ſeruaunts ſhal rebel againſt their Lordes and maiſters, but there ſhalbe great aboūdaunce of corne vpon the earth, and the high wayes il aſſured, becauſe of the aboūdaunce of theues and robbers. And if Mars and Saturne, or mars and Jupiter be conioyned in the ſaid ſigne or degre, there ſhalbe greate warres in the lande of Armenia in Aſia, for their enemies ſhal runne vpon them, and the moabites ſhall moue warre, and ſhall ſlea their preiſtes, and they ſhall go into the mountaynes, truſting in the iudgements of their deuines and prophetes. And from the eaſte parte ſhall come a merueilous greate winde.
            
            
               
               ¶ Of the ſignification of the cōiunction of the planetes in Cancer.
               If Jupiter, Mars, the ſunne and the mone, be conioyned in the ſigne of Cancer, then terrour and feare ſhal compaſſe them, who do ſtir vp &amp; prouoke the other by offences, and amonges the men, the one ſhal moleſt and greue the other. And there ſhalbe ſene many ſignes in heauen as comets, and fiers flienge, in the ayre, with earthquakes, the waters ſhal waxe drye, the fruites ſhalbe corrupted &amp; marred, the ſailers ſhal periſhe vpon the ſea, the cities, caſtels, and townes being edified harde or nere to the ſea ſide, ſhall be troubled with great feare, and the north winde called boreas ſhall do muche domage the ſame yeare.
            
            
               Of the coniunctiō of the planets in Leo.
               If Saturne, Jupiter, mars, &amp; the mone be found conioyned in the ſigne of Leo, the people dwellinge east wardes, ſhall make warres within them ſelues, &amp; mē ſhalbe vexed &amp; greued with paines of the bellye, of the ſtomack, &amp; of the priuie partes. But if Jupiter, mars, and the ſunne be in the ſaid ſigne, the merchaunts ſhal feare to haue wronge of their Lorde, the wind ſhalbe great from the eaſte parte, &amp; the Arabians ſhal not be without fear.
            
            
               
               ¶ Of the ſignificatiō of the coniunction of the planets in Uirgo.
               If Jupiter, Mars, and Mercurye, be conioyned in the ſigne of Uirgo, all the fruytes of the earth ſhall periſhe, almoſt all wholy by the greate aboundaunce of Locuſtes and greſhoppers. But if Saturne and the ſunne be there founde conioyned and eclipſed, and the heade of the dragon with Mars be there at the ſame time, or nere therto, then in the lande of the Nubians, and in the South parte, ſhall be engendred ſedicion amonge the poore and riche people. And if Saturne and Jupiter be in the ſaid place, ther ſhal folow great raine, and the wind ſhal procede from the South parte, and all thinges, eſpecially Corne and wine, ſhall be dere the ſame yeare.
            
            
               ¶ Of the ſignification of the coniunctiō of the planets in Libra.
               If Mars and Jupiter be conioyned in the ſigne of Libra, the heuen ſhalbe ſene to be redde, whiche is a ſigne of diſeaſes to come vpon men, &amp; of effuſion of bloud But if the Sunne, Jupiter, &amp; the mone, be in the ſaide place, there ſhall folowe mortalitie of wemen, and great raynes. And if Mars &amp; Saturne be in the ſame place, there ſhall folowe warres, and the

theues and robbers ſhall fall vpon men by the waye to robbe them.
            
            
               ¶ Of the ſignification of the coniunctiō of the planetes in Scorpius.
               If Saturne, Mars, and Uenus be conioyned in the ſigne of Scorpius, they ſignifie that the kinge ſhall die of poiſon, and the Lords ſhall vſe detractions, and ſhal haue enuy the one againſt the other. And if the moone be there, with anye of theſe thre, there ſhalbe ſuch great raine, that it ſhall ſeme that the worlde woulde periſh
                     •
                   by water, as in the time of Deucalion. But if Jupiter and Saturne be in any degree of the ſaid ſigne, then it is conuenient to vnderſtand generallye in al ſortes, that there ſhall come falſe prophetes, bringing in new ſectes.
            
            
               ¶ Of the ſignification of the cōiunction of the planets in Sagittarius.
               If Mars and Jupiter be conioyned in y• ſigne of Sagittary, there ſhalbe made warres alonge the ſea ſide. But if Saturne, Jupiter, mercurye, and the mone be there, the ſea and floudes by the great inundation of waters ſhall ſo encreaſe, that the whole worlde ſhall almooſte periſhe by a deluge. The ſcribes, phiſitions aſtrologians, and preiſtes ſhalbe multiplied and honoured of the people. And yf

Saturne &amp; Mars, be in the ſaid place, the theues ſhal robbe the rural people, &amp; thē of villages, and the pirates ſhall robbe the ſaylers vpon the ſea. But if Mars &amp; Uenus be in the place aboueſayd: y• harlottes and ſtrompetes ſhall rauiſhe their children &amp; doughters, and ſhall by force bring them into captiuity.
            
            
               Of the ſignification of the coniunction of ye planets in the ſigne of capriconus.
               IF the Sunne Mars &amp; Mercury, be in the ſigne of capricornus: manye greate lordes ſhall die, &amp; there ſhalbe greate in firmities &amp; diſeaſes. The mē ſhall burne the houſes &amp; the barnes with corne, and there ſhal reigne mer
                     •
                  eilous great windes, in ſuch wiſe, that ſmal ſtore of corne ſhalbe gathered. And if ſaturne &amp; Mars be in the ſayd place: there ſhall not then folowe ſo much euel, but the warres ſhal be great, and mankinde ſhal much feare god.
            
            
               Of the ſignification of the coniunction of the planets in the ſigne of Aquarius.
               If Saturne, Mars, &amp; the moone be in the ſigne of Aquarius there ſhall be litle rayne, &amp; great drouth, but yet the waters of ſpringes and fountaines: ſhall ſufficientlye abounde: the goers by the wayes ſhall be aſſayled by theues, the

ayre ſhalbe ſore troubled and cloudye, &amp; yet ſhall giue no rayne. And then ſhalbe borne a man of whom the people ſhall much reioyce, and vnto whom manye nations ſhall be ſubiect: The moneſt aries &amp; monkes ſhal greatly abound, and ſhal be men fearing god.
            
            
               Of the ſignification of the coniūction of the planets in the ſigne of Piſces.
               If in the ſigne of Piſces be Jupiter, the religion ſhalbe greatly obſerued amōgs men▪ who then that would giue iudgement of thinges which ſhould come in any yeare it is mete that he do examyne witte
                     •
                  y the coninnctions, conplexions, and ſignifications, of the planets, aswel by the thinges here aboue written as alſo by the ſubtiltie of his vnderſtanding in takinge hede vnto the nature of the ſignes, in the whiche the ſayd planetes ſhal be. And this doing he may giue certayne iudgemente of thinges to come by the wil and grace of god.
            
         
         Finis.
         
            ¶ Vireſcit vulnere virtus,
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London in Fleteſtrete nere to S. Dunſtons church by Thomas Marſhe.
         
      
   

