
   
      
         
            The Spaniards monarchie, and Leaguers olygarchie. Layd open in an aduerisement [sic], written by Signor Vasco Figueiro a gentleman of Portingale to the rebellious French: wherein is discouered the tyrannie of the one ouer the kingdome of Portingale, and the treacherous rebellion of the other in the kingdome of France, with a patheticall persuasion to the French to returne to the obedience of their naturall and legitimate king. Englished by H.O.
            Figueiro, Vasco, gentleman of Portingale.
         
         
            
               1592
            
         
         Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00734
            STC 10865
            ESTC S102056
            99837857
            99837857
            2204
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00734)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2204)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 226:08)
         
         
            
               
                  The Spaniards monarchie, and Leaguers olygarchie. Layd open in an aduerisement [sic], written by Signor Vasco Figueiro a gentleman of Portingale to the rebellious French: wherein is discouered the tyrannie of the one ouer the kingdome of Portingale, and the treacherous rebellion of the other in the kingdome of France, with a patheticall persuasion to the French to returne to the obedience of their naturall and legitimate king. Englished by H.O.
                  Figueiro, Vasco, gentleman of Portingale.
                  H. O., fl. 1592.
               
               [48] p.   
               
                  By Richard Field for Iohn Harison,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1592.
               
               
                  Original title not traced.
                  Signatures: A-F⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sainte Ligue (1576-1593) --  Controversial literature.
               Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
SPANIARDS
MONARCHIE, AND
LEAGVERS OLYGARCHIE.
LAYD OPEN IN AN ADVERISEMENT,
written by Signor VASCO FIGVEIRO a Gentleman of Portingale
to the rebellious French: wherein is diſcouered the tyrannie
of the one ouer the kingdome of Portingale, and the treacherous
rebellion of the other in the kingdome of France,
with a patheticall perſuaſion to the French to returne
to the obedience of their naturall
and legitimate king.
            Engliſhed by H. O.
            Praeiudicium ſaepè tollit omne iudicium.
            Imprinted at London by Richard Field for
Iohn Hariſon. 1592.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE GENTLEMEN
READERS.
            
               COVRTEOVS Gentlemē, to your
cenſures I commit this labour of
mine, ſmall and ſimple, it is the
firſt (I will not ſay) it may be the
laſt. If you accept and applaud it,
I am throughly animated to enter
into ſome matter of more cōſequēce, &amp; ſuch as
I know ſhalbe acceptable. VVhat the vulgar either
imagine or ſpeake, I care not: for with Horace.
            Non ego ventoſae plebis ſuffragia venor.
            It is no feather of fancie, for that I accompt it baſe,
to fetch ſuch light marchandiſe ſo farre as Valentia.
If you expect extraordinarie elegancie, I anſwer,
that a Tranſlator is bound rather to ſearch fit
words, to expreſſe his Authors meaning, then inuent
words running on the letter, to content ouercurious
fancies, which I contemne as dictionarie
method; and thus much can I aſſure you, that albeit
it hath no title fetched from the Bull within
biſhops gate, as a figge for a Spaniard, yet doth

it diſcouer ſo ſuccinctly and briefly, a Spaniſh imitatiō
of Machiauellized axiomes, that what other
volumes at large, this in a leafe doth plainly demonſtrate.
If any obiect, that this treatiſe ſerueth
for french men, and not appertinent to vs. I anſwer,
that their wit reacheth no further then their
owne home. For is not our Iland the marke that
Philips ambitious humour eſpeciaily aimeth at?
hath he not ſent his inuincible Armada, to make a
conqueſt of our vltima inſula? Nay would he not
repute him ſelfe an abſolute Monarch, if he might
but get any intereſt within vs? And haue not we a
viperous brood of puritan Papiſts, and reconciled
Leaguers, that dreame vpon a new inuaſion? with
good foreſight by this treatiſe they may be warned,
and true ſubiects armed. VVhich ſucceſſe
God graunt.
            
               Yours H. O.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A FAITHFVL ADVERTISEMENT
OF SEGNIOR VASCO
FIGVEIRO A GENTLEMAN OF
Portingale unto the rebellious French.
            
               IF the Gréek Achamenides ſhewed himſelf
ſo carefull for the ſafetie of the Troians
his ſworn enemies, that after hauing diſcourſed
of the horrible cruelties, that the
Prince Vlyſſes and his people had receiued
by the hand and tooth of the cruel Antropophage
Poliphemus, he admoniſhed
them to fly with diligence from the Sicilian
ſhore, the repaire of that inhumane Cyclops. It ſéemeth vnto
me, by a more forcible reaſon, as well for the auncient alliance
which our nation hath had with the French, as alſo hauing
bene diſciplined in a better ſchoole, then that of this barbareus
infidell: that I am obliged, by the lawes both diuine and humane,
to demonſtrate vnto you, ſo much as in me lyeth, the good
affection which I beare vnto you. Then (Sirs) being induced by
this example, and many other good reaſons, knowing by experience,
the tyrannicall and barbarous gouernment of Philip king
of Spaine, the vniuſt vſurper of our kingdome of Portingale.
And ſéeing you Frenchmen (I ſpeake to the ignorant, and thoſe
which are gone aſtray) are come like the Troians to the Sicilian
ſhore, to caſt the anchor of your turbulent rebellions, and indiſcréete
affections, ſtill longing for noueltie, in the daungerous
and vnaſſured port of the inexorable ambition of this Philip. My
deſire is to aduertiſe you as a good neighbour &amp; charitable friend,
to weigh your anchors ſpéedily from this port, making ſayle to
the ſhore from whence you haue ſtrayed: that is, to returne to

the dutie of true and naturall Frenchmen, which the impetuous
wind of a temerarie ſedition hath cauſed you to abandon, and ſo
to caſt your ſelues fooliſhly into the hands of a forraine Prince,
which can not tend but to the euident ruine of your libertie. For
this is he (who like that infamous Polyphemus, which acknowledged
no other God but his belly) ſo he may féed his own inſatiable
ambition, careth not with what garbage ſoeuer it be: &amp; therfore
maketh no conſcience wickedly to violate, euen the law of
God it ſelfe. Now as this miſerable Achamenides made vnto the
Troians, a long narration, of the inhumanities of Polyphemus,
before he exhorted them to flie, that he might not ſéeme to amaſe
them, without iuſt occaſion: ſo am not I ignorant, that I ought
by the ſame example, to recount in what maner Philip vſurped
our realme, and with what rigor he hath ſithens managed his tyrannicall
gouernment, leſt I ſhould be thought to build my diſcourſe
vpon the wind, and induce you to auoyd ſhipwracke, without
yéelding example, or pertinent reaſon. I could ſpend the time
in recounting particularities, were it not that they are ſo manifeſt
to the world, that it were but loſt labour to rehearſe them.
Notwithſtanding to ſatiſfie thoſe, which for curſt heart will yet
ſtand in doubt, I will ſpeake a word or two, and ſo away.
            It is knowne vnto all men, that the king Henrie, who before
was Cardinall, the predeceſſor of Don Anthonio our naturall
and legitimate king▪ in the aſſemblie of the eſtates of his realme,
eſtabliſhed fiue gouernors for ye adminiſtration of ye ſaid Realme
after his death, vntill Don Anthonio made manifeſt the right
which he pretended to the crowne: ordaining that the other competitors
ſhould not in the mean time attempt any thing vpon the
ſaid Realme, vpon paine, of repelling their pretenſions. But
while theſe things were in doing, Philip hauing corrupted by
rewards and promiſes, thrée of the ſaid gouernours, and manie
of the nobilitie, directly contrarie to this ordinaunce of the ſayd
Henrie and the ſtates, entred the ſaid Realme by force of armes,
and ſeaſed him ſelfe of ſome eſpeciall places. Which the people
and ſtates perceiuing, without any delay, becauſe periculū erat
in meum, acknowledged incontinently Don Anthonio for their

ſoueraigne, beſéeching and vrgently preſſing him, to take vpon
him, the title and qualitie of king, which after many refuſals, he
condiſcended vnto. In ſuch ſort, that he was eſtabliſhed king,
with all the ſolemnities thereunto required, and ſithens being
aſſiſted by part of his good ſubiects, he came in battell againſt the
ſaid Philip, vnto whom the fortune of warre gaue the victorie:
in ſuch ſort, that our ſaid Don Anthonio was forced (hauing eſcaped
infinite dangers of death, by the ambuſhes which were
layd for him by the tyranny of Philip) to retire him ſelfe into
France, and afterward into England. The ſaid Philip being
come to the top of this tyrannous vſurpation, hath pardoned neither
great nor litle, neither anie ſexe or qualitie, that he knewe
had bene, or might hereafter oppoſe them ſelues to his tyrannie.
The Princes, Lords, Gentlemen, gouernours, captaines, officers,
Ladies: both the ſecular and regular, the prieſts and religious,
partly killed in diuerſe maners, partly detained in perpetuall
priſon, partly baniſhed the Realme, part chained in galleys,
and part vagabonds wandering in the forreſts, and hiding
themſelues in dens, for feare leſt they ſhould fall into the hands
of theſe mercileſſe hangmen, do ſufficiently teſtifie his cruel and
ſanguinarie ambition. I will content my ſelfe with naming of
ſome few hereafter, referring them which would know farther,
to the copie of an Epiſtle written by our king to Pope Gregorie
the thirtéenth, albeit that was but in the beginning of our miſeries
and ſlaughters, which are ſithens ſo multiplied, that the number
is now infinite.
            The Spaniard ſéeing him ſelf enriched with the ſpoiles of our
king, contenting not him ſelf with this pray, imagined it ſhould
ſerue but as a ladder, to mount vp to the top of an abſolute monarchy.
And being drunke with the greatneſſe of this happy ſucceſſe,
he began to plot higher attemps in his ſpirit, as ambition
neuer wanteth matter, propoſing France for the marke of his
other enterpriſes, but knowing well that he might not attempt
openly, and that herein force of armes might turne rather to his
dammage then profite, he reſolued to follow the aduiſe of Liſander,
namely, where the lyons ſkin is not ſtrong enough, to patch

it with a péece of the fores. But then he imagined, that nothing
could more ſecurely, and more ſoone eleuate him to the top of this
greatneſſe, then a forcible ladder of gold, vnderpropped with a
more then Punicke ſubtilty, and maſked with a falſe ſemblance
of integritie.
            Likewiſe ſéeing that he had principally two great obſtacles
in France, namely the late king, and Monſieur his brother:
he deliberated to remooue the leſſer. And to come to the point
of this enterpriſe, knowing the naturall auarice and ambition
of the Dukes of Guiſe and Maine, (who following the trace and
inſtruction of their father, and their vncle the Cardinall, pretended
to enrich their Bonnet, with the thrée floure deluces: and if
not of all three, yet at leaſt of a part) he eaſily corrupted thē with
rewardes and promiſes: in ſo much that ſhortly they accorded
vpon the death of Monſieur, either by poyſon, or otherwiſe, and
that by a Gentleman of his own traine named Salſede, who being
attainted, and conuicted of the ſaid enterpriſe, was drawne
in péeces with horſes in the citie of Paris, hauing firſt diſcouered
and accuſed thoſe which had practiſed with him. But your king,
who ought according to the enormitie, &amp; importance of the cauſe,
to haue made exact ſearch, &amp; iuſtice vpon the culpable, ouer whom
at that time he had ſufficient puiſſance, caried not him ſelfe toward
the truth, with that diligence that the importaunce of the
cauſe did merit. Et haec prima mali labes. For he knowing the humour
of the aboueſaid, he ought infallibly to haue held them ſuſpect
of great miſchiefes in his Realme.
            For all this the Spaniard altered not his enterpriſes, but cō
               trarily
continuing, and more and more augmenting the penſiōs
of his two partakers, practiſed euery day new matters. Finally
a few yeares after he obtained that which he had long expected:
for lo, Monſieur. being made away, not without euident ſuſpitiō
of poiſon, &amp; now ye Spaniſh king not being able any longer to cō
               taine
the heat of his ambition encloſed, or hidden, ſhewed himſelf
ſo amorous of France, that without ceaſſing he cheared &amp; courted
it, ſolliciting continually his partakers to venter: and briefly,
leauing nothing vndone, which he thought might conduct him to

the port of his deſires, which being not able to reach vnto, it hammered
his head, &amp; gnawed his inwards with a tedious torment.
            Suppreſſing his paſſions, as impatient, that his partakers
could not withdraw or diſwade her from her fidelitie: he had recourſe
vnto that remedie which cuſtomablie fooliſh and deſperate
louers vſe, namely ſome fine Dariolette or Magician: and indéed
he ſearched ſo much and ſo curiouſly, that at laſt he recountred
with a miſchieuous and craftie harlot, not ignorant in Magicke,
who had bene engendred, nouriſhed, brought vp and entertained
in the proud and magnificke Pallaces of Rome: whom
hauing furniſhed in abundance, with all that was requiſite for
her affaires, recommending vnto her all the artificialnes of her
craft, but eſpecially to keepe her ſelfe diſguiſed vnder the maſke
of the Catholike religion, he preſently ſends her into France.
And this is that miſchieuous and traiterous harlot, which is called
the holy league: a name truely fatall and pernitious to euerie
well ordered Monarchie and common wealth.
            This ſorcerie and ſubtletie of the League is incontinently
receiued with great applauſe of the partakers, &amp; penſionaries of
Philip king of Spaine, who leaue nothing vndone that they
may make her ſéeme plauſible vnto France. The king himſelfe
maketh ſemblance of a faire countenance in entertaining it
courteouſly, yea making great difficultie to giue credite to his
moſt faithfull ſubiectes, friends and ſeruants, who pertinently
declared that it was not begun for other end, but to withdraw
France from his obedience, and finally to rauiſh her from betweene
his armes. But the good prince is alreadie ſo charmed
by her alluring ſpeaches, that contrarily he ſweareth onely by
her, and acteth whatſoeuer ſhée commandeth, at leaſt giuing outwardly
ſufficient demonſtrations, like to that infortunate Priamus,
who was ſo bewitched with the ſorceries and ſubtleties of
Helena, that inſtéed of giuing credite to the true ſpeaches of his
owne daughter Caſſandra (who propheſied vnto him the miſfortunes
that ſhould in the end fall vpon him and his kingdome by
meanes of this faire Dame) he not onely taunted her as a foole,
but alſo detained her in priſon▪ Alas you Frenchmen, how manie

true Caſſandras hath your king had, which foretold him the
ruine both of him, and you. Notwithſtanding it is manifeſtly
ſéene what ſmall eſtimate, both he and you haue made of their
holy and profitable aduertiſements: nay you haue bin ſo far frō
giuing credit to this infallible Oracle, yt otherwiſe you haue mocked
&amp; ſearched for ye authors, as mē guiltie of ſome capital crime.
And herein you may be compared to the Orithains, who after
they had whooted and hiſſed at Euphraces the Orator, they impriſoned
him as a perturber of the people, for that he aduertiſed thē
to take héed leaſt they ſubmitted themſelues vnder the tyrannie
of Philip king of Macedon, as afterward they found it too true.
            Now this damnable League, this impudent courtiſan, propoſing
her ſelfe to corrupt the fidelitie of France, gained firſt of all
ſecretly thoſe whom ſhe knew gaue moſt credence vnto her, as
manie of the nobilitie, ſome of the officers, as well of the kings
as of the cities, and in a manner all the Eccleſiaſticall perſons:
who (oh horrible ſhame) made no conſcience to ſell for ready money,
their eloquence and knowledge (which they ought to haue
imployed in preaching the goſpel, and inſtructing the ſimple people
in the feare of God and obedience to their king) to corrupt
the conſtancie and fidelitie of France, but Quid non mortalia pectora
cogis auri Sacra fames? Where is the time that the kings of
France, and their Magiſtrates, yea all good Chriſtians, had in
ſuch indignation, thoſe which dared to take either rewards or
penſions of forraine Princes? that if any were noted with this
crime, he was ſure without either grace, or remiſſion, ignominiouſly
to looſe his life: for this iuſtice hath bene one of the firmeſt
pillers, which haue ſo manie ages ſuſtained the excellencie
of this Monarchy. But ſithence that kings and their officers haue
neglected this vertuous obſeruation, it may eaſily be perceiued,
how the ſtate of their Monarchie hath bene more and more ſhaken.
All other kings &amp; princes obſerue inuiolably this maxime,
&amp; he which infringeth it is puniſhed according to the rigor of the
law: for vnder ſhadow of theſe liberalities, ſtrangers take
knowledge of the eſtate of the realme, and ſo ſeduce the ſubiects.
And in this manner Cambyſes eſpied &amp; deceiued the Ethiopians.
            
               
Now the preachers (by meanes of their mercenarie tongues)
forget no art that may ſerue their purpoſe to ſuborne France,
but vſe all meanes poſſible to make the king odious vnto her, in
altering by little and little, by their flattering diſcourſes the ſincere
amitie, and faithfull loyaltie, which ſhe hath alwayes held
entirely towards him: either exalting euerie pettie imperfecti
               
                  ••
               ,
aboue his great perfection: either in blaming, accuſing, or attributing
vnto another, the glorie onely due vnto him: and contrariwiſe
in all things magnifying the greatnes, and vertues of
this amorous Spaniard, whom they paint out accompliſhed
with all the perfections that may be imagined. Briefely, they
omit nothing, wherby they may ſubſtract France from her king:
who ſéeing, vnderſtanding, and knowing all the practiſes that
were managed againſt him, notwithſtanding flattereth himſelf,
or rather is ſo bewitched by this League, that he will neither beléeue,
nor chaſtiſe, ye opprobrious iniuries, which were publikely
attached againſt him, yea euen oftentimes to his face: ſo much,
as it ſéemed, did he feare to diſpleaſe or offend her, which gaue
ſuch audaciouſnes and courage, to theſe naughtie packes, that no
man was accounted of, vnleſſe he ranged himſelfe with the
League, to vomite out a world of iniuries againſt the authoritie
of the king: and he which could gorge out moſt, whether in preaching
or writing, was accounted the moſt honeſt man: yea euen
thoſe who are his owne creatures and fedde at his table, are not
aſhamed to ſet themſelues againſt him, and rent his renowne by
all manner of iniuries &amp; ſlanders. As namely one called Roze,
biſhop of Senlis, the true portrature of ingratitude, who among
manie other iniuries vttered one worthily meriting a corporall
puniſhment: yet this good prince was content onely for his chaſtiſement
to baniſh him the court. Likewiſe an Aduocat of Paris
named Breton, was ſo impudent as to publiſh to the world a
book againſt him repleate with miſchieuous calumniations: notwithſtanding
it was euē againſt his will that iuſtice was executed
vpon him. But for theſe holy preachers did they approue this
act of iuſtice? nothing leſſe, but rather reprooued it, as a tyrannicall
act: ſo that one of them named Boucher, was ſo ſhameles as

to preach, that the cord wherwith the Aduocat Breton was ſtrangled,
was a thouſand times more honorable, then the ſcarlet robe
of the preſident which condemned him. I cannot here forget a
certain Pariſian, inſtructed and prompted by Madame de Mompenſier,
who faigning himſelfe mad, entered ye Louure, vttering
a thouſand deteſtable words againſt the perſon of the king, yet
for his knauerie, he was but ſimplie whipped in one of the o
                  ••…
               
               ces
of that place. Behold how this prince brooketh theſe iniuries
which were diſgorged, and that impudently againſt him and his
authoritie. Behold how careful he is to extinguiſh the fire which
kindleth to borne him, and the eſtate of his realme: ſo that well
may it be ſaid of him, Malum eſt quidem habere imperatorem, ſub
quo nemini licet quicquam facere: ſed multo peius est quando omnia licent
omnibus.
            
            The League hauing now had a long time to practiſe vpon
France, ouer whom ſhe had alreadie gotten this aduantage, that
it eaſily gaue her credite in whatſoeuer, aduiſed with her ſelfe
that it was now high time to let them, which had ſet her a work,
ſée ſome better fruits of her trauell. So that leauing off words &amp;
ſuch like matters, ſhe will now venter vpon practiſe, wherein
the dice chanced ſo well, that her enterpriſe fortuned euen to her
wiſh. And this was when ſhe called the Duke of Guiſe, with his
other partakers into the citie of Paris againſt the will of the
king: who (as well for the more aſſurance of his perſon, as to
ferret out certaine miſcheiuous naughtipackes, lurking priuily
in the ſaid citie, which put in feare the good ſeruants of the king,
whom the League termed by the name of Polliticks) placed the
guards of his body in certain places of the citty: but the League
cauſed him ſoone to know, that ſhée had ſo throughly altered the
will of the people, that they were farre more affectioned to the
ſaid Guyſard, then to him himſelfe: which he then perceiued
when it was too late to remedy. Thus within leſſe then thrée or
foure houres, the Pariſians were ſo animated againſt the kings
guard, by the inſtigation of the Duke of Guiſe, (as himſelf vaunted
and braued in certaine letters directed to the nobility of
France) that they killed &amp; hurt diuers of them: yea ye king himſelfe

was ſcarſely ſpared: for the Barricados were planted within
the gate of his Louure, in ſuch ſort that he thought his ſtay
would be far more perillous then his departure. This is that infortunate
day, which ye preachers haue extolled as the moſt fortunate
day which happened of a thouſand yeares in France, and
which they themſelues in open ſermon, baptiſed by the name of
Barricados: as in truth it hath beene very aduantagious for the
maſter whom they ſerue.
            The king hauing receiued this indignitie of his France, in ye
capitall cittie of his realme, and in the ſight of all the Princes in
Chriſtendome, who were there reſident in the perſon of their
Ambaſſadours or Agents, did he ſhew himſelfe to be mooued or
angrie? not at all: but as if he had too much let looſe the bridle of
his malignant affections, fearing a worſe euent, he is content
to put vp the wrong, and to accuſe himſelfe. So ſeeking to reconcile
himſelfe with her, he made it knowne, that he would aſſemble
the eſtates of his realme, by whoſe aduiſe and counſell he
would hereafter rule all his actions: and that he might ſhew
ſome confirmation of his will, he caſheard in one morning about
33. of his Edicts.
            At the firſt bruit of this declaration, the League ſéemed ſomwhat
male content, fearing that if Fraunce being admoniſhed,
and reprooued by her king, ſhould haue any remorſe of conſcience
for her fault, ſhée would returne to her former duety: yet conſidering
that ſhe had ſo practiſed her neareſt counſailors, that they
would ſpeake nothing but by her mouth (like a good ſcholler that
Fortune had put in her hands, to mount the more eaſily, whether
ſhe aſpired) made ſhew to wiſh nothing more then the conuocation
of the eſtates: meane while letting not ſlippe an houre
vnimployed, either in reſolliciting her old partakers, or purchaſing
new: but eſpecially watching that none might be at this aſſembly,
but thoſe whom ſhe knew to be of her partie, whom ſhée
inſtructed from point to point, what they had to do.
            Whileſt ye Prouinces, were aſſembling to prepare, their Articles,
ſhe ſuffered not the time to paſſe vnprofitably, giuing aduiſe
to her partarkers in thoſe things which were neceſſarie for

their Articles, to ſome to beſiege Boulogne, to others to beleager
and batter Iamets, and to others to poſſeſſe themſelues of the
Marqueſhip of Saluce: yet not forgetting to aduertiſe her Maſter
what ſhe had happely negociated, as alſo the good eſtate of the
affaires which ſhe then managed, requiring him with all ſpéede
to imbarke, that puiſſant army which he had ſo long equipped to
that end: whether to vſurpe England, or to viſite France in
forme of an Ambaſſage, whereby to make proofe of her good affection,
and to encourage her reuolt againſt her king: but either
the one or the other might haue bene preiudiciall to the
French king, if the iſſue had fitted their expectation: but
God by his grace myraculouſly ouerturned it, for this
great Armada, which was termed inuincible was broken,
defeated, and diſſipated, beyonde all humaine expectation, by
the valiauncie and magnanimitie of the fléete, which the
Quéene of England had ſent forth, to defend the coaſtes of her
realme.
            Albeit the defeating of this Armada ſomewhat vexed the
Spanyards, and not without cauſe: for that it clipped the
wings of their other enterpriſes: notwithſtanding the League
was not any whit diſmayed, but purſued more hotly her affaires,
as willing to repaire this ruine, by double diligence.
And indéede ſhée effected ſo farre with the king, that he ſolemnely
ſware and proteſted to vnite himſelfe with her,
and hereafter to be ſolely ordered by her counſell: ſo that the
king was ſo blinded that he ſware the deſtruction of himſelfe,
and the extirpation of his, by an Edict enſuing, named for this
cauſe the Edict of reunion.
            The time being come, where the eſtates ought to aſſēble, their
Deputies ſhowed themſelues at Bloys, where the aſſignation
was giuen. Then was queſtion made in this aſſemblie, that the
king, and his France, or rather the League, ſhould giue vnderſtāding
of their affaires, to thoſe which were called to determine
thereof. For this part of France, had alreadie retired their affection,
from their naturall king, to yéeld it to the king of Spains,
yea from their owne children and heires, to commit it to the ſaid

Spaniards in ſuch manner, did they effect that the kings eſtabliſhed,
a foundamentall law of his kingdom, whereby no heretike,
or fauourer of hereſie might euer come to the Crowne. In this
ſort excluding the king of Nauarre, whom the League held for
an hereticke, and the reſidue of the houſe of Bourbon, his couſins
(except ſome few) from their naturall, and legitimat, right, to
the Crowne of France. Thus the League not onely depriuing
him, but alſo employing all their might, to root them out, by force
of armes. Briefly, the French League, might not abide the ſight
of her owne children, but hated them, with a moſt mortall hate.
So that hauing giuen away her ſoule from her owne king, like
an vniuſt ſtepmother, ſhe diſherited her legitimat children, to inueſt
baſtards, or ſtraungers, in their fathers heritage.
            And which is more, ſhe is not contēted to haue drawen away,
this great corner ſtone from the foundations of the kings eſtate,
(for in ſtéede of adding another good foundation for this vniuſt
law, ſhe haled away one of the beſt, to the end to ouerthrow it) as
may be ſéen, in that ſhe bound his hands in the adminiſtration of
his Realme, yea euen to the taking away of thoſe few which remained
of his moſt faithfull, auncient, and domeſticall ſeruants:
placing in their ſtéed, thoſe whom ſhe thought moſt affectionat towards
her. Thus was this good Prince depriued of his legitimat
ſucceſſours fallen in a manner frō his dignitie, diminiſhed of his
puiſſance, &amp; abandoned of his moſt faithfull, and loyall ſeruants.
            What reſteth now therefore for vnfaithfull France, but to
caſt herſelfe betwéene the armes of her good friend the Spaniard?
the king ſo timerous, that he dare not hinder her, and albeit he
durſt, all his meanes are remoued, hauing not one onely heire,
nor one, or at leaſt few ſeruants, that either would or could aide
him to retaine her.
            Furthermore, ſhe hath bin ſo ſhameleſſe, as to enterpriſe vpon
the life of the king, for that being vtterly impatient, and tranſported
with a fooliſh affection, ſhe ſought all meanes to rid him away:
ſo that treading vnder feete, the feare of God, and ſhame of
men, ſhe reſolued vpon his death, what euer came of it. She néeded
not greatly trouble her ſelfe, to ſéeke one, to execute her miſchieuous

will, a thouſand are readie to enterpriſe it, euen to the
perill of their life. Albeit among ſo great a nūber, ſhe diſcouered
her ſelfe but onely to one, whom ſhe eſpecially loued, &amp; put moſt
affiance in, who was a hundreth times more readie to obey,
then ſhe to commaunde. Yea, ſuch a one as moſt inflamed her to
practiſe vpon the enterpriſe. Behold then this good Prince, ordained
by this French League, to a miſerable death, and who muſt
be the bloudie parricide, but the Duke of Guiſe? onely the execution
thereof remained which had not bin long delayed, had it not
bin for the prouidence &amp; mercy of our God, who as he hath a care,
eſpecially ouer the perſon of kings (Rex venerādus curae eſt Deo,
ſaith the Poet) manifeſted vnto the king this bloudy conſpiracie,
giuing him meanes by the aide of ſome of his faithfull ſeruants,
which yet remained, to preuent the traiterous, murtherer &amp; parricide,
who had vowed to take away his life, or at leaſt his libertie.
And thus was he taken in the nett, which he had ſpread for others:
yea the hand of the Lord, ſtretched euen vpon the Cardinall
his brother a man of the ſame ſtampe. But ſurely they had
the reward, which they had rightly deſerued, wherewith Hermeas
was payed by the king Antiochus. As alſo accuſtomablie it
happeneth, that. Nimium potētes, &amp; regibus ſuis, formidofi proceres,
aut auditi miſerum, &amp; tragicum tādem vitae exitum, ab ipſiſmet
regibus, à quibus ſe formidari, &amp; metui voluerunt, conſequuntur.
If France, at the fall of this man, were meruailouſly
moued, much more, were the League, and Phillip. Hauing
loſt the beſt feather of their wing, and the ſtrongeſt piller, which
ſupported their attempts. Now France ſeing, that her floud, was
diſcouered, knew neither what countenance to make nor what
way to take: whether to entreate pardon of the king, whom ſhe
had ſo deteſtably offended, or following on, with her miſchieuous
reſolution, to perſeuere in the amitie, which ſhe had ſworne to
Phillip. And I verilie beléeue, that ſhe had retained the former
opinion, as moſt ſafe: had not the League, in vſing, more fine and
artificiall ſubtleties, then euer before, by the ſeducing of the vnfaithfull
preachers, induced, perſwaded, yea, and cōſtrained her,
to follow her laſt reſolution, ſetting before her eyes, the enormitie

of all the faults, that ſhe had committed againſt the authoritie
of her king: who would be ſo irreconciliable, and inflamed with
a deſire of reuenge, that he would neuer be induced to open the
gate of his mercie. Thus deſperatlie ſhe reſolueth, that ſeing the
dice was caſt, ſhe would runne fortunes hazard: as alſo the ardēt
affection, that ſhe had to change her naturall Prince, to aſſay the
gouernement of a ſtranger: which ſhe earneſtlie wiſheth for, albeit
to her common dammage, and extreme ruine. The Gaules
(ſaith Caeſar in his Commentaries) loue noueltie, and deſire to
change their Signorie: ſo that there néeded no great labour, to
incite them to a generall rebellion; &amp; yet the ſeditious preachers
adding oile to fier, by their charming Sermōs, and vniuſt declaration,
make proceſſe vpon the bodie, by which proceſſe, the Colledge
of Sorbone, acquited, the people, frō the oth of fidelitie and
obedience to their Prince: and without any ſcruple of conſcience
to take armes againſt him, to extirpat both him, &amp; all thoſe which
ſhall ſuſtaine, or defēd his quarell. As if the Colledge of Sorbone
were aboue the king, to licence his people to violate the moſt
firme, and holie lawes of the Realme: now in ſuch caſe, if often
hapneth (as Caeſar ſaith) that ſome are pricked forward with auarice,
others with deſire of reuenge, or any other light folly, which
ordinarilie aecompanieth the cōmon people. Moreouer the great
ones labour to ſet the vulgar ſort in a tumult, wherein hauing
committed ſome great miſchief, they may be aſhamed to repent,
or craue mercie, others there are, who are drawne by a hope, to
become great men: which (as ſaith Saluſt) maketh men, but of
meane condition to venter their life. Now before this French
League will commit her fortune to the field, ſhe would remoue
all ſuch ſtumbling blockes, as might hinder her actions, or interrupt
the courſe of her vnbridled rage, in ſuch ſort that ſhe captiuated
or baniſhed the Cities, all thoſe whom ſhe neuer ſo litle ſuſpected
to be ſeruants to the kings. And then began France, ſo to
ruffle, that the League, &amp; her preachers had gathered a puiſſāt armie,
whoſe leader muſt be the Duke du Maine, whō you cheriſh
no leſſe, thē his late deceaſed brother: but O France, to what end
doeſt thou march accompanied with ſuch a terrible courage, as

though thou wouldſt affray, and ſubdue the whole world? is it to
maintaine the authoritie of thy king? or to conquer, new lands
planting the borders of thy Monarchie, vpon thy neighbours? or
finally to recouer thoſe, which the aunceſtors of thy Spaniards,
yea, and he himſelfe hath vniuſtly robbed thée of? no, no ſuch matter.
It is to abaſe, and beate downe the greatnes of my king, for
that he hath takē away the life of my Minion, who (might I haue
had my will) ſhould haue taken away his. To this end, do I muſter
ſo many men in field, to ſacrifice their bloud, for the expiatiō
of the offence perpetrated by the king vpon the perſon of my fauorite:
As alſo my fields ſhall be ouerflowen with the bloud of
the French, for an earneſt pennie of my Mariage dower, with
Philip king of Spaine, for that ſo is his pleaſure, and he inſtantlie
requireth it as a token of my affection. Ah miſerable France,
well may it be cried out againſt thée.
            
               Gallia, quis furor? heu: quae tanta licentia ferri.
               Gentibus inuiſis Gallum praebere cruorem?
            
            You long for nothing ſo much as a bloudie warre, and you imagine
thereby to triumph incontinētly ouer your king, to yéeld
your ſelfe afterward to a forraine Prince: but brainſicke as
you are, you conſider not the meſſage, which the great warrier
Metellus ſent vnto king Bocchus. The entrāce into warre (ſaith
he) is eaſie: but the end difficult, neither are the beginning, and
iſſue thereof in the power of one, and the ſame perſon: euery one
euen the verieſt coward in the world, may eaſiely begin it, but
the end thereof is onely at the pleaſure of the conquerour.
            The king perceiuing France, to ruſh with ſuch furie vpō him,
to auoid thoſe inconueniences, whereinto he might fall, iudged
that his beſt remedie, was to abrogate and ſuppreſſe that iniuſt
law, whereby at the inſtant requeſt of the League, he had declared
his legitimat, and indubitat heires, incapable of ſucceſſion to
the Crowne, and to recall them, neare vnto his perſon: together
with all his old, &amp; faithfull ſeruants both to ſuſtaine the aſſaults
of his rebellious ſubiects, as alſo to abate the pride of their ouerraſh
inſolencie: who in the meane while, made a ſodaine aſſault
vpon him, in the ſuburbes of the Citie of Tours, frō whence they

were ſo valiantly repulſed, that they were conſtrained to make a
ſhamefull retraite.
            The king had no ſooner made declaration of the things aboue
ſaid, but he might ſée him ſelfe aſſiſted, with a great and couragious
armie compoſed of the Princes of the bloud, of the moſt faithfull,
and magnagnimous Nobilitie, and of the better ſort of his
people, friends, and confederates, who neuer failed him at néed.
So that all trembled for feare, where his armie paſſed, the towns
which opened not their gates, were ſoone ouerthrowen, nothing
might reſiſt his puiſſance, and brieflie all ſtouped vnder his authoritie.
            Thus hoping to moue France, to acknowledge her offences,
and to demande pardon, which ſhe might eaſilie haue obteined of
his gracious clemencie, he cauſed his armie to approche, euen to
the gates of Paris: then were both France, and the League in
extreme perplexitie, without all hope of ſafetie. France was ſore
vexed and toſſed in ſpirite, manie doubts, and difficulties, trouble
her braine: the worme of her conſcience, doth gnaw, and pricke
vnceſſantlie, and ſo liuely, that ſhe féeleth as it were an vnſupportable
torment. Of the one ſide, ſhe balanceth the enormitie of
her miſchiefs, which plonge her into a mortall diſpaire, and on
the other ſide, the great mercie of the king, which farre ſurpaſſed
the heaps of her miſdéedes, lifting her to an infallible hope of ſome
great good: and I doubt not but that ſhortlie ſhe had returned to
acknowledge her faults, and cordially to cleaue to her king, who
had handled her ſo graciouſly, if God would ſomuch haue fauoured
her, as to take away the vaile from before her eyes, that ſhe
might diſcerne, truth, from falſhood, and euidentlie ſée the errour
whereinto the charming ſorceries, &amp; craftie illuſions of this pernicious
League, had cauſed her to ſtray: and ſo caſt her headlong,
into a bottomleſſe pit, ouerflowing, with all calamities, and miſeries:
but it pleaſed not the diuine goodneſſe of God, to endue her
with ſo fauourable a grace, as one vnworthie for her deteſtable
vices to receiue it: as in truth full well hath ſhe deſerued the
paines that ſhe hath ſuffered, yet (ſo obſtinate is ſhe in her wickednes)
that ſhe ſéekes no amendment.
            
               
The malicious League ſéeing France, in this doubtfull anguiſh,
gathered her ſpirits together, to forge more craftie ſubtelties,
then euer before, to cauſe France, to runne to armes, after
the death of the Duke of Guiſe, and ſo throughlie intrudeth her,
into her former errours, that waxen more fellonious then euer
afore, ſhe reconſpireth the death of her king: and yet holdeth an
other courſe then afore. And therefore bethinketh to enterpriſe it
by treaſon, and by ſuch a one as might do it with leaſt ſuſpition:
ſo that hauing throughly diſcourſed of her affaires, ſhe cōcludeth,
that Religion, ſhould ſerue her as a couert, to commit this damnable
parricide. Then was found out an execrable traitor, a Iacobin
Frier, who driuen by a diabolicall ſpirite, enterpriſeth to
the hazard of his life traiterouſly to murther his naturall Prince.
O deteſtable crime, and ſo horrible, that there is not a name ſo
cruell or obhominable, as may ſufficientlie expreſſe it. Damnable
Monkes, do you read in the holie Scriptures that it is lawful
for any man to murther, I ſay not onely his king, but euen the
baſeſt man on the earth? the law of God expreſlie forbiddeth to
defile, the hands in humaine bloud. God commaundeth (in the
booke of Deuteronomie) to take the homicide frō the aultar, and
to ſlay him: but as for kings, he hath giuen them a particular priuiledge,
as he ſaith by the mouth of the Pſalmiſt. You ſhall not
touch mine annointed, much more you ſhall not kill him. Dauid
alſo forbore to lay violent hands vpon king Saul his enemie: albeit
he had him at aduantage. Did the Apoſtle teach you to commit
this execrable fact, when he ſaid. Obedite praepoſitis veſtris
etiam diſcolis? dare you thē in this manner tread vnder féete the
law of God, whereof in wordes you vaunt your ſelues to be ſo
zealouſlie affectionate, ſhame befall vpon you, miſchieuous, and
traiterous hipocrites, who preach vnto the people, the law of
God yet your ſelues will not follow it.
            Euen the ethnicke Pagans ſhall condemne you in the latter
day: for albeit they were ignoraunt, yet they caried this reſpect
vnto the Princes of their land, as to terme them (in reuerence)
the liuing pourtraitures of the ſupreme diuinitie. Harken what
ſaid one of the Poets. Rex eſt Imago animata Dei. But ſuppoſe

he were ſo wicked as you, and the treacherous Leaguers would
faine him to be, yet ought we to obſerue this good aduertiſement.
Principes boni voto quidem expetendi, qualescun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  ; tamen tolerandi.
But certaine it is, that he was endued with all the perfections
requiſite to make a Prince worthie of the greateſt prayſe,
and the onely imperfection that he had (which was but to great
an imperfection in a Prince) was, that he ſhowed himſelfe ſomwhat
to negligent for the maintenance of his greatnes, and conſeruation
of his eſtate.
            Now, then hath the French League, miſchieuouſly cauſed her
king to be murthered: who féeling the extremitie of death, to approch
neare vpon him, declared in the preſence of all his Princes,
and Lords of his Realme, the king of Nauarre as naturall, and
legitimate ſucceſſour to the Crowne (as in truth he is, and that
moſt apparent) ending with theſe wordes the courſe of his life.
            Incontinently all the Princes, all the Lordes, and all the Officers
of the Crowne following the declaration, and laſt will of
the deceaſed king acknowledged the king of Nauarre, and that
according to all equitie to be king of France, which all the whole
armie likewiſe acknowledged. Now France being left a widow
of her king, &amp; conſequently miſtreſſe of her ſelfe, according to her
owne opinion &amp; will (for it is a ſure maxime, that the king neuer
dyeth in Frāce) let vs accord to her vnreaſonable appetite: what
face ſetteth ſhe vpō it? doth ſhe mourne, or is ſhe ſorrowfully diſcōforted?
Doth ſhe ſhow any ſigne of ſorrow in her widowhead,
which ou
                  •…
                
               
                  •…
               o haue bin drowned in teares? No, but cōtrariwiſe,
ſhe reioyceth ſo extremely, that ſhe ſetteth publickly forth, a thouſand,
and a thouſand ſignes of ioy, as among many others her
bonfires being ſo great, that euen her furtheſt neighbours, were
lightned with the flame thereof, whō notwithſtanding, ſhe thinketh
ſcarcelie aduertiſed by this exteriour ſigne, of her vnmeaſurable
ioy, and therefore will certifie them by expreſſe letters:
poore vnfortunate France, which makeſt vertue of thy vice, and
glorie of thy infamie: poore inchanted France, which reioyceſt
when thou ſhouldeſt ſwimme in teares: but thou wilt not care
to doe otherwiſe, while thou art bewitched by the enchanters of

this diabolicall League.
            But now let vs ſée, what will become of this widow: let vs ſée
to what Prince Frāce deſireth to betroathe her ſelfe: for I thinke
ſhe will yéeld but onely to one, otherwiſe ſhe ſhould doe contrary
to the nature of all other common wealths, who finallie haue
ſubmitted themſelues vnto one onely Monarke, as approuing
the gouernemēt of one to be better then of many: which the Satrapas
of Perſia, alſo approued when as they conſtituted Darius
for their ſouueraine Monarche. The Romane common wealth alſo,
after it had béen a long time furrowed, and toſſed by the ciuill
warres of particular perſons. Maluit parere vni, quam pluribus.
Furthermore in priuate families one commandeth ouer the reſt:
as the head ouer the inferiour members: Yea euen in nombers.
The vnitie (as ſaith Plato is moſt eſtéemed). Philo Iudaeus in his
booke of the creation of a Prince, teacheth that the gouernement
by one onely, was ordained by the commandement of God. Let
vs hearken vnto the iudgement of Homer: Non bonum eſt multorum
principatus, vnus Princeps eſto.
            
            It appeareth then, that there is no ſort of gouernment more
excellent or commendable, then the Monarchie which France is
not ignorant of, and therefore will not be ſubiect to many: but
ſhe will chuſe one to fit her own fancie, as though ſhe were ignorant,
that in a Monarchie, an election is perillous, &amp; that nothing
hath made her ſo redoubted and puiſſant, as an immediat ſucceſſion
of Princes barring the gate to electiō, which all Monarchies
and well ordered kingdomes haue curiouſly obſerued. But if this
poore abuſed France, remaineth ſtill opiniated in her election, yet
the expreſſe commandement of God forbiddeth her to elect a forraine
Prince, as it is written in the 17. of Deuteronomie in theſe
wordes. From among thy brethren ſhalt thou make a king ouer
thée: thou ſhalt not ſet a ſtraunger ouer thée, which is not thy
brother.
            Many examples might be produced to this purpoſe, of common
wealthes and kingdomes, which haue béen deſtroyed, onely for
truſting and ſubiecting thē ſelues too much to ſtrangers. For this
cauſe Bartholomeus Coleon, reprehēded the Venetians (who for

his merites toward their common wealth, had erected his ſtatue
in gold) as hauing to inconſideratly aduentured their common
wealth into the hands of a ſtranger. The Corinthes had not fallen
into a tyrannicall gouernement, if they had not ſubmitted
thēſelues vnder Timophanes a forraine leader. The Brittaines
were chaſed their Realme by the Engliſh Saxons. The Spaniards
by the Moores: and the Gréekes by the Turkes: onely by
crauing ſuccour of them in their warres: yet this Frēch League
paſſeth a degrée further: ſhe not onely calleth in the Spaniard to
aide to deſtroy her owne children: but ſhe will wholy ſubmit her
ſelf vnto him, and make him her ſoueraigne Lord: which becauſe
ſhe might not as yet openly, and abſolutly doe, for ſome conſiderations,
ſhe aduiſeth vpon ſome fit expediēt to couer her miſchieuous
intention: and to the end to cloke her theft, which ſhe ſecretly
deſireth to commit with the ſaid Spaniard, ſhe elected for her
king by forme of acquit Charles Cardinall of Bourbon, a man ouerworne
with age, whom ſhe had purchaſed to no other end, but
to alienate the Crowne, being wel aſſured that he could not hinder,
but rather profit much for the negociatiō betwéene the Spaniard
and her, as before times he had alwayes done, for this
Prince, ſhe had expreſlie reſerued for this affaire.
            But the late king hauing (as it ſéemed) foreſéen this accident,
to hinder him from diſturbing the ſtate any more, had committed
him to a place, where being ſurely guarded, neither his rebels,
nor the Spaniard, might aide him at their deuotion, which meruailouſly
diſquieted them. For Fraunce of her ſelfe could do nothing
to any effect without the authoritie of her beane king, as I
may terme him: whom ſhe onely vſed as a couert for her traiterous
monopolies, and inuentions againſt her legitimate and naturall
king: albeit he had not right, or title to the Crowne, the
king being liuing, whom to be deliuered of, they would euen remoue
heauen and earth, if it were in their power: but ſeeing all
this was to no purpoſe, becauſe the ſaid Cardinall was ſurely
guarded by the good, &amp; faithfull ſeruants of the king, ſhe recourſed
vnto force of armes, and ſetteth a great armie in the field,
which charged vpon the king, being at that time, with a ſmall cō
               panie,

at Deipe, and there abouts: promiſing vnto themſelues,
either to ſlay him, to captiuate his perſon, or at the leaſt to cauſe
him flie the Realme: but God ſo aſſiſted him, by his own proweſſe,
and the valour of his owne ſouldiers, with the ſuccours ſent vnto
him by the Quéene of England, that his enemies had but onely
the wil to hurt him, &amp; the grief, becauſe they were altogether vnable
to hurt him: for the king defeated, and repulſed them valerouſly,
and afterward ſearched them euen at the gates of Paris,
from whence they durſt not appeare, to anſwere him in battaile
which he preſented vnto them.
            The Spaniard for his part continually entertaineth France
with faire wordes, &amp; great hope of new forces, ſufficient enough
aſwell to ſet the fained king at libertie, as to defeate him, which
truely and by good title is called king. And in déede fiue or ſix mouethes
after the charge vpon Deipe, was the Countie Egmond,
ſent with a great troupe. The Pope alſo ſent his Legate, to comfort
&amp; encourage her. In ſuch manner that a puiſſant armie preſented
it ſelfe to the king, who ſodainely ſet him ſelfe in battaile
aray in the plaine of Yury, where God once againe ſo miraculouſly
fauoured him (although his enemies forces were twiſe as
great as his) that he gained ye victorie, hauing ſlaine the greateſt
part of his enemies, amōg whom was the Countie Egmond, and
put the reſt to a ſhamefull flight, which ſore troubled Frāce: and
yet behold another worke of God, who working for his annointed,
about two monethes after tooke the Cardinall to him ſelfe.
            This vnexſpected death of the Cardinall rechargeth her, with
diuers and troubleſome thoughtes. She ſaw that the king had a
puiſſant armie, which ſo encreaſed euery day, that he had conquered
a good part of his kingdome, and which more tormented her,
ſhe ſaw that he had blocked on all ſides the Citie of Paris, which
then ſuffered an extreme defect, both of victuals, and other commodities:
which occaſioned the people to open their eyes, which
ſuperfluitie of eaſe, &amp; the charmes of the League, vntill then, had
ſhut vp and vailed: and ſurely they would willingly haue yéelded
to the king, had not the damnable League by her ſubtelties,
&amp; the force of her partakers, retained thē in their obſtinacie, whether

they would, or no. Thē began France to perceiue the fraude
of the Spaniard, and the illuſions of the League, acknowledging
that being fooliſhly perſwaded, ſhe had committed vnpardonable
faultes againſt her king, and that perſeuering in her follie, ſhe
had raſhly takē armes againſt him, whom ſhe ought to haue cheriſhed
more then any Prince in the world, who notwithſtāding
is ſo mercyfull, that ſhe might haue promiſed her ſelfe, that he
would forget all that was paſſed. So that ſhe fully determined
to ſend to his Maieſtie to entreate of peace, but that ſhe was ſo
watched by the League, and intāgled in her laberinthes that ſhe
might doe nothing, without her knowledge or conſent, who counſelleth
her, to propoſe vnto the king, among other Articles theſe
two following.
            1. That he ſhould change his Religion, into the Romiſh Catholike
Religiō, a thing that ſhe knew well that the king, would
neuer accorde vnto, eſpecially at that time.
            2. That he ſhould pardō all thoſe, which are coulpable of ye death
of the late king, a thing which he neither might, nor ought to do.
            And as touching the changing of his Religiō, albeit he holdeth
it for the moſt true, and holy, notwithſtanding he hath alwayes
proteſted, that he would ſubmit him ſelfe to the decrées of a holy,
&amp; frée Councell, generall or nationall, aſſembled to determine of
the two Religiōs which are profeſſed in his kingdome: to the end
to embrace that, which ſhalbe iudged moſt Chriſtian, &amp; to reiect
the other. But that he is an heretike he denieth, for that no Councell,
hath condemned the Religion, which he profeſſeth to be hereſie.
But put caſe his Religion were hereticall, yet it maketh not
either him, or any other perſon incapable to poſſeſſe thoſe goods,
which naturally and lawfully belong vnto him, and to force his
conſcience in regard of Religion, were a thing vneaſie to doe. If
his Religion be not good they néede not feare, for that he cannot
long vphold or maintaine it in his Realme, ſéeing Ieſus Chriſt
hath ſaid, Euery plant, which my heauenly father hath not planted,
ſhalbe plucked vp by the roote. They may ſée, a faire plea vpon
this queſtion, in the 5. of the Actes, where a Doctour of the
law, named Gamaliell, ſpeaking of the Religion, and doctrine of

the Apoſtles, ſaid vnto the high Prieſt, and to the Iudges. If this
counſell, or worke be of men, it will come to naught: but if it be
of God, ye cānot deſtroy it, leaſt ye be found euē fighters againſt
God. And doe not you, manifeſtly reſiſt the word of God, to ſuſtaine
a Religion by the point of the ſword, and enforce men to
follow it? It is euident God neuer planted his, by the ſword of
Princes. To hope alſo that the French king, will leaue his Religiō,
to the end to enioy peaceably his kingdome is a vaine hope,
and I beléeue he will neuer do it, if the Monarchie of the whole
world were offered vnto him, for that he eſtéemeth it, a great
breache both to his conſcience and honour, if it be not (as I haue
ſaid) firſt condemned by a Councell.
            The League knowing then, that France could not treate a
peace with the king, vpon the conditons before ſaid, and that by
her obſtinacie ſhe reaped ſuch great diſcommodities, that at the
length would bring her to reaſon: ſhe ſolliciteth her more, &amp; more
to perſiſt in her miſcheiuous opinion, and the more the people cry
out with famine, ſo much the more doe the preachers entertaine
them in their rebellion, playing the Orators vnto them, like as
aunciently Critognatus, a Captaine of the Gaules, did vnto the
inhabitants of Lauxois, being beſieged by the Romanes: who
propſed vnto them, that it were farre more honorable, to eate
one an other, then to yéelde them ſelues to the mercy of the Romaines.
But Critognatus was farre different from theſe preachers
more inhumane, then the very Canibals, for that he did it
for feare of comming into bondage: and theſe to the end to yéeld
France, and her poore people, vnder the yoke of a miſerable tyrannie:
he ſhowed him ſelfe truely zealous of his countrey, and
the name of the Gaules, and theſe are thereunto mortall enemies:
for they haue nothing but the French names, whereas in
heart they are Spaniards, aboue foure and twentie carrects.
            Now to the end to comfort the people in their aduerſitie, they
féede them with a hope of ſuccour, which ſhall remooue that long,
and inſupportable ſiege. And ind indéede the Spaniard, after hée
had ſet all his wits awork, cauſed the Prince of Parma to march
into France, againſt the king, who togither with his nobilty,

and other men of warre, preſented him battaile foure or fiue
times, with a magnanimous courage, ſo that the Spaniard for
all his brauadoes, was ſo aſtoniſhed at the ſight of this valorous
armie, that he neuer dared to come to blowes, contenting himſelfe,
to lurke about Paris, to conſume the reſt of that ſmall portion
of victuals, which remained in the countrie and townes
thereabout. The king ſéeing that the Spaniard had taken this
reſolution, licenſed ſome of his nobilitie to depart, and ſeparated
himſelfe a few leagues from Paris, making dayly couragious
aſſaults vpon the enemie, who for all his great brauadoes, and
proud rodomantadies, tooke onely two ſmall Hamlets, not without
the loſſe of a great number of his ſouldiers, which were ſoone
taken againe, and that before his face: and hauing done theſe
two memorable exploits, he thought it beſt to truſſe vp his baggage,
and returne to his lodging, for feare of greater loſſe, to the
vtter abaſing of his reputation: which he did not ſo ſecreatly, but
that the king made him faſten his ſpurres, and leaue part of his
glorious feathers behind him. For he purſued him without cealing,
now in the forefront, now on his wings, and now at his
taile, euen vnto the borders of Flaunders. Thus in briefe behold,
all the ſuccours and aduancement, that France receiued
of her great friend Philip king of Spaine, by the comming of the
Prince of Parma. Behold the people left in greater calamitie,
then euer before, and their affaires ſtill growing from euill to
worſe: the king ſurpriſing to day one towne and to morrow another.
            Poore abuſed France, diſmaſke and pul away the vaile, which
the League hath put before your eyes, turne away your eare,
from her craftie illuſions: breake the bonds wherewith ſhe hath
captiuated you, and purge your braine with ſome good antidote,
againſt her charmes: and then, not till then, ſhall you perceiue,
in what darkenes, in what errour, in what captiuitie you haue
bene detained, whileſt this accurſed League hath gouerned you:
then your ſelfe ſhall be iudge, how much you haue loſt of your
beautie, of your authoritie, of your greatnes, of your fidelitie, of
your libertie, of your wiſedome, and of your forces: which before,

and that from the beginning were redoubted, not onely to
your neighbours, but euen to the moſt renowned nations, ſo that
if you would looke backe vpon your ſelfe, you ſhould ſée, that
your viſage is ſo changed that you could not know it, nay you
would be afraid to behold it. Conſider all your members, and
Organes, apart by themſelues, and you ſhal finde all your members
defeated, beaten downe, féeble, and weak, and your organs
all peruerted and gone aſtray in their offices. Your neighbours
which were wont of late, to feare, and redoubt you, doe now
hiſſe at you, pointing with their finger, and mocking at your deſperate
rage, and miſerable follie, which hath made you more
cruell then Medea, againſt your owne innocent children, whom
you moſt cruelly purſue, and without all humanitie maſſacre, as
if they were your moſt mortall enimies, that had conſpired your
death. Take patience awhile, to hearken vnto one of your moſt
affectionate neighbours, who will ſet downe nothing which ſhalbe
vnreaſonable, but rather wholly to your aduantage and profite.
            Imitate that vertuous Prince Antigonus, who fréely hearkned
vnto a plaine countrey man (whom he met with by chance)
reprehending the vices, wherewith he was attached: and albeit
he felt himſelfe pricked to the quicke, yet he tooke all in ſo good
part, that it returned greatly to his profite: correcting afterwards,
that which the good man had noted to be vicious in him,
and being returned to his court, he ſaid vnto his minions, that
he had learned that of a peaſant, which he neuer knew before,
namely, the truth, which his flatterers had alwayes kept hidden,
and diſguiſed. In like manner (miſerable France) depart but a
little from this fraudulous League, and her traiterous preachers,
to learne, not of one of your domeſticall flatterers, and deluders,
but of a ſimple ſtranger, deſirous for your owne good &amp;
ſafetie, to cauſe you to know the ſincere veritie, which this long
time you haue not heard of, for that you would neuer giue eare
to anie diſcourſes, but thoſe of your deceiuers, depart therefore
but a while out of your court, and I will cauſe you ſincerely to
vnderſtand, what you haue hereafter to do.
            
               
               Demoſthenes perſwading the Athenians to reſiſt Philip of
Macedon, exhorted them not onely to repulſe the vſurper, but
conſequently to chaſe out of their cittie certaine Orators, whom
by rewards he had drawne vnto his faction. In like manner I
aduiſe you, that to auoid the tyrannie of Philip of Spaine, it is
néedfull to betake you to your weapons, and more then high
time, to exile this pernitious League, and her corrupted preachers
if they will not amend, contenting themſelues to preach
the goſpel, as Ieſus Chriſt hath enioyned his Apoſtles, whoſe
imitatours and ſucceſſours they faine themſelues to be. Go (ſaith
Chriſt) throughout the whole world, preaching the goſpel vnto
euery creature: he commandeth them, not to meddle with the
eſtates of Princes, to ſeduce their people, cauſing them to reuolt
againſt thē, nor to cauſe their doctrine, to be obſerued by armes,
committing cruel and bloodie butcheries, vpon all perſons without
any exception, as theſe our venerable maſters haue done for
theſe thirtie yeares, and do yet ſollicite others to do: and herein
muſt I néeds commend the policie of all other kingdomes, which
forbid vpon grieuous penalties, that diuines ſhould in their ſermons
diſpute vpon matters of ſtate. But how dare I take in
hand to beate downe ſo puiſſant a Prince, redoubted to all Europe,
who hath ſo great commaundement ouer me, bieng ſubiected
vnder his puiſſance: your naturall and legitimate king, of
whom it may be well ſaid,

                  Rex quo iuſtior alter
                  Nec pietate fuit, nec bello, maior, &amp; armis.
               
He onely it is that may vaunt, as ſometime that great chieftaine
Abarius vaunted: Sweat, duſt, and ſuch like things are more
delectable vnto vs then the moſt delicate fare. And briefly this is
he, who from his cradle hath followed the counſell, that Plinius
ſecundus giueth to a magnanimous Prince, which deſireth to be
ſkilfull in militarie affaires. Princeps (ſaith he) vt ſit Militaris
debet prius multum, &amp; dium bello periclitatus eſſe: ſic enim diſciplina
militaris ſcientiſſimus erit. This is he which is more then
ſufficient to breake all the attempts and enterpriſes of the Spaniard:
yea euen to purſue him into his owne countrie if neede

were, which he knowing full well, hath for this long time
ſowed diſcention betweene you, and hath enterpriſed: to make
him odious vnto you, fearing that if you ſhould both march vpon
one foote, he ſhould be conſtrained to take héede to himſelfe,
without enterpriſing vpon his neighbours: ſo that he ſhould fal
from this high attempt to become Monarch of the world. It is
méere ſimplicitie in you to redoubt the ſaid Philip, ſéeing his
greatnes is growne onely by the negligence, floath, and malice
of thoſe, ouer whom he hath tyrannically vſurped, as namely
ouer vs Portingales. In like manner would he waxe great by
your ciuill diſſentions, which are vnto him as a bridge to paſſe
ouer vnto your ſoueraintie. For making you beléeue that he wil
(as a friend) ſuccour you againſt him, whom falſly you intitle
your enimie, he will vſe the ſame ſubtletie that this other Philip
of Macidone vſed, who vnder colour of aſſiſting diuers people
of Grecia againſt their neighbours (ſaying that it was the dutie
of a friend, &amp; confederate, to lend ſuccours to others in their vrgent
affaires) eaſily poſſeſſed himſelfe of their common wealths.
            And thinke you, I pray you, that Philip of Spaine, will tell
you by his hyred preachers (for you will not hearken to any other)
that he wil firſt reduce you vnder his gouernment, &amp; afterward
handle you rigorouſly? for my part, I thinke him more
wiſe, neither doubt I that you thinke otherwiſe: but rather to
the end to intrappe you, he promiſeth you more good, then you
dare hope or wiſh for of your legitimate king. But if you haue
any diſcretion, be it neuer ſo little, you will make no receit of
ſuch exceſſiue promiſes, for that they are too much ſuſpect, and too
full of diſtruſt, which in this caſe ought to finde ſome place in
you. Men haue inuented diuers thinges conuenient for the defence
and conſeruation of their citties, as wals, ditches, trenches,
bulwarks, baſtiles, engines, artillerie, and ſuch like,
which haue not bene done without great charges by ingenious
mechanickes and workmen. But ſage diſcretion findeth naturally
in it ſelfe, an inexpugnable rampire, eſpecially in a free people,
againſt the aſſaults and inuaſion of a tyrannous vſurper:
and what rampier is this? a diſtruſtfull foreſéeing, wherewith

if you be thoroughly fortified, no encombrance ſhall annoy you,
but you ſhal conſerue your deare libertie, wherof the Spaniard
is a ſworne enimie, and vſurper.
            Good God: how grieuous would it be vnto you, if after al this,
you make the Spaniard poſſeſſour of you and yours, and that by
your owne meanes: murthering one king, reiecting another,
who is your legitimate king, diſaduowing your owne children,
contemning your nobilitie, diſdaining your moſt faithfull people,
ouer whom you haue made innumerable extorſions. And
briefly after hauing ſuffered all the miſchiefes in the world, on
your members afféebled with trauell. Inſtéede of finding in this
Spaniard all recreation, pleaſure, ſwéetnes, courteſie, reſt, and
tranquilitie, he ſhould cauſe you to enter from a feuer to a frenzie.
For to deliuer you from warre, which you moſt deſire, what
face ſoeuer you ſet vpon it, for that it is grieuous and weariſome
vnto you, he cannot doe it though he would, for that he
hath too ſtrong parties, not to ſpeake of ſtrangers, which thing if
it may go by vſurpation, haue as good right in your kingdome
as he. You haue good example of my ſaying at your doore, euen
Flaunders his patrimonie, which is now a thouſand times leſſe
in peace, then it was in the beginning of their troubles. I aſſure
my ſelfe that the leaſt warres that you haue vpon you, as well
of his part, as by his occaſion, ſhall be more tedious vnto you,
then all thoſe, which for this thirty yeares you haue ſupported,
yea compriſing the laſt (albeit in good earneſt they felt the extraordinarie
rigour of the Spaniard,) which notwithſtanding in
compariſon of theſe future, haue bene but as childes play: albeit
it was long of thoſe which firſt began them, to the great griefe
of the moſt faithfull, who were forced to defend themſelues againſt
the arrogancy of the Guyſards, who would tread them vnder
their féete. And albeit herein they had committed ſome fault,
which cannot be ſaid, for that they did it for their defence, yet
are they neuertheleſſe in ſome ſort excuſable, for that they are
houſhold children. For like as he which is borne in a rich and puiſſant
family, if he happen to do any thing vnfitting, and contrarie
to his duetie, is not to be blamed, or reprehended ſo ſharply as

a ſtranger: but if ſome ſeruant or ſtranger hath loſt, or waſted,
that whereunto he hath not any right, how much more foully
ſhould he fault? and how much more grieuouſly were he to be
reprehended? Now it goeth farre otherwiſe with the Spaniard,
for not onely he is not French, but alſo he hath nothing in him
worthy to be ſimbolized in the leaſt degrée, to the good and laudable
nature, I ſay not of the Princes, but of the meaneſt gentlemen
of France.
            All this notwithſtanding is nothing in regard of the dolourous
heartbreaking, which inceſſantly ſhal torment you, hauing
in ſtéede of the maſter, one of his ſeruaunts to rule and gouerne
you, by the name of a Viceroy. Yea albeit he ſhould giue you
ſome French Lord (but make account he will take héede to that)
he wil not handle you better thē vs Portugales, or the Neapolitans,
and Milannois, and all thoſe which are vnder his ſubiection.
            If the Grecians found it ſtrange to haue Philip of Macedone
abſent from their Pithian games, whereat if he aſſiſted not himſelfe,
he cauſed ſome of his court, to be preſident: will the proud
diſdaine of your Philip, be more tollerable vnto you, when he
will not daigne, I ſay not to honour you certaine moneths
euerie yeare with his preſence, but not to viſite you at all? and
yet ſurely the adminiſtration of ſuch a kingdome, is of farre
more worth, and importance, then the feaſt of I know not what
games, and paſtimes. And yet moreouer, you haue bene always
accuſtomed to talke familiarly with your king, and to remonſtrate
vnto him, whether in priuate or publike all your affaires:
you alwayes ſaw your king preſident in the congregation of
your eſtates. You I ſay are they, eſpecially aboue all other nations,
who deſire nothing more, then to content your eyes, with
the preſence of your Prince.
            But herein in my opinion he ſhal beare himſelfe maruellous
diſcréetely, for that he ought not to entertain himſelfe with you,
but in a tedious manner, by reaſon of the iuſt diſtruſt he may
haue of your fidelitie. For ſéeing you haue falſified your faith to
your legitimate Prince: ſéeing you haue killed your rightfull

king, ſéeing you haue ſhewed your ſelfe a ſtepmother to your
owne children, to adopt ſtrangers, good occaſion may he haue to
hold your loyaltie alwayes in ſuſpect: which you may as eaſily
violate towards him, as you haue done towards your naturall
and legitimate Prince. And be you ſure, that he will ſoone
make you taſt of the frutes of his diſtruſt, by taking away all
thoſe which may any wayes be obſtacles to his enterpriſes. Make
account, that he is not ignorant, that Tyrannidis inducendae, ac
ſtabiliendae prima initia ſunt frequens accuſatio, &amp; in quouis crimine
adiuncta delaeſa maieſtate Principis. Itemque delatorum authoritas.
Which he throughly practiſed in Flanders, cauſing the Counties
Egmond and Horne to be beheaded: beſides diuerſe other, as alſo
the Prince of Orange, whom he cauſed traiterouſly to be murthered.
And as for vs Portingales, hath he ſpared vs? I will
make you partakers of ſome examples of his clemencie towards
our Nobilitie. The Countie de Vimioſe Conſtable of Portingale
being ſlaine in fighting for the libertie of his countrie. The
Spaniard confiſcated all his goods, and ſent his mother with her
ſeuen daughters, priſoners into Caſtile. Diego de Meneſes ſometime
Viceroy of the Eaſt Indies, and gouernour of the towne of
Caſcais, was publikely beheaded, and one of the Captaines of
the ſayd to towne, named Henry Perera, was ignominiouſly hanged,
notwithſtanding his nobilitie. Emanuel Serradas was executed
by the ſword in the Ile of Tercera. And the Countie de Torres
vedras gouernour of the ſayd Ile, was in like manner beheaded.
The ſame end had Peter Alpoen, after that Philip vnderſtood
yt our king Don Anthonio was retired toward France.
Sfortia Vrſino a valorous Captaine, was likewiſe empoyſoned.
Theſe few, which I haue collected from a great number, may
ſuffiſe, becauſe I would not be tedious vnto you. And therefore
by the example of the miſeries of our Realme, take héed in good
time, leaſt that happen vpon yours (if the Spaniard become
maiſter) which Tacitus writeth, Sub tyrannis &amp; iniuſtè imperium
occupantibus, omnia ſunt bellis ciuilibus, proditionibus, mutuis coedibus,
exilijs plena, &amp;c. I take you to be ſo benigne a mother, that you
would féele an extreme gréefe, to ſée your Nobilitie, the honour
and ſtay of your authoritie to be maſſacred or baniſhed. And albeit

it had prouoked you by a thouſand outrages, as the League
hath vndertaken falſely to perſwade you: yet would you impatiently
ſupport this horrible and cruell tyrannie.
            Now then you ſée into what infortunate calamities, this pernicious
League would precipitate you into. You ſée, how ſhe ſéeketh
nothing but to deſtroy you, to enrich Philip with your dammage.
And you ſée that ſhe enforceth her ſelf to charge your neck
with ſuch a waightie tyrannie, that you ſhal cōtinually remaine
courbed vnder the burthen therof, without being able to redreſſe
your ſelfe. But I hope that by this time you haue reculed farre
backe from her, yea euen wholly chaſed her from your eares, and
that returning to your ſelfe, you will be gouerned by reaſon: by
whoſe good counſell you ſhall returne vnto your king, and be appeaſed
with your Nobilitie, who heartely deſire to reuiew you,
more excellent and magnificall then euer before: as full eaſily
you may be, being aſſiſted and maintained by the moſt vertuous
and magnanimous king, that euer ſwayed your crowne. Oh how
comly wold it be, to ſée you reueſted with this faire French robe,
embrodered with the flour deluces. Oh how neat it wold be, ouer
this Spaniſh motley robe, which for a time you haue worne,
which hath made you ſo vgly and deformed, that you are become
the fable of all your neighbours, who take you for ſome fooliſh
ſot, not knowing you being ſo fooliſhly diſguiſed: but take but
once againe your owne habite, and they will both honour and reuerence
you. Theſe faire floure deluces will put them in minde
of your integritie, and vnmoueable conſtancie towardes your
king, which if you kéepe inuiolably, then ſhall you triumph ouer
the arrogancie of the Spaniard, if he ſhould offer hereafter to diſquiet
or diſturbe your felicitie.
            But now I come to you people of France, diuided principally
into two parties, whereof the firſt part, which is the leſſer, hath
continually remained entire and faithfull to their Prince, what
faire language, what ſubtleties, what menaces, what priſons,
what tortures, what cruelties, and what loſſe of goods ſoeuer, that
the League and her partakers had plotted or inuented, to leade
them to their deuotion. The other part being farre greater, hath
not only run at the firſt furie of ye League, to reuolt againſt their

king, but alſo hath taken in hand to intraine &amp; corrupt the ſound
partie: and yet remaineth plunged in their obſtinacie. To theſe
two parties agreeth well the difference, that Demoſthenes put
betwéene thoſe of Athens and Thebes. The Athenians as true
citizens, and men zealous of the common wealth, would fauour
Philip of Macedon no further, then honeſtie and vertue would
permit them: but the Thebans contrariwiſe ſerued him for an
ardent couetouſneſſe of gaine and particular profit, which they
hoped to draw thereby, not apprehending any farther, like men
of baſe vnderſtanding, the rigor of a tedious ſeruitude. Now as
for you ſage Athenians, you faithfull Frenchmen, me thinketh
you néede no aduertiſement, to entertaine you in your dutie, ſéeing
the League, by ſo many and ſo many croſſes, troubles, &amp; perſecutions,
hath not bene able to diuert you: I eſtéeme you ſo conſtant,
that nothing ſhalbe able hereafter to diſtract you: you are
men rather worthie of immortall praiſe, which ſhall neuer fayle
you, then any admonitiō, and therfore I ſhould be but too tedious
to exhort you to conſerue that, which I know you do moſt affect,
namely your libertie &amp; fidelitie. And albeit Demoſthenes played
the orator often to his Athenians, yet were if néedleſſe vnto you,
becauſe you are more vertuous then the Athenians. But it is to
you, that it is more then néedfull, not to ſpeake, but to cry out, O
you ſenſleſſe Thebans, you rebellious Frenchmen, you traiterous
brokers of your goods, your friends, your parents, your
wiues, your children, your ſelues, &amp; your countrey, which ought
to be more deare vnto you, then miſchieuouſly to deliuer ouer to
a cruell tyrannie. But you are runne further then the Thebans
of Graecia, for they being groſſe heads, and without any foreſight,
couetous, and ſuch as only reſpected their profit, enriched them
ſelues by the harmes of their fellow citizens: but you faile not
for want of underſtanding or of ignorance, but rather through
rage, fellonie, and fore determined malice: like certaine Orators
among the Orithains, or like the Olympians among ye Atheniās:
ſo you being once infected by this pernicious League, haue ſtirred
vp by your flattering orations and lying pamphlets, the moſt
ſimple to rebellion, and therein detaine them, as it were by force
and violence. For theſe poore idiots are ſo drunken by your mellified

and ſeducing ſermons, that they ſuffer them ſelues to be led
by the ſnoute like beares and elephants.
            What ſay you now you unfaithful Frenchmen, abuſed by the
Sorbonical ſeducers? becauſe you haue once ſhaken off the yoke
of obedience to your king, will you neuer more receiue it? Well
may you be likened to a ſauage and outragious beaſt, ſéeing you
haue taken ſuch vnbridled libertie: or if you ſubmit your ſelues
to obedience, you will chuſe a head to your owne fancie. And in
déed better it is to obey in what ſort ſoeuer it be, thē euilly to cō
               maund,
and continue ſo long time confuſedly, in a chaos of Anarchie,
which is moſt perillous, Nihil anarchia periculoſius, ſaith
Plato, and herein you follow the aduice of Tacitus, Praeſtat ſub
malo Principe eſſe, quam ſub nullo. I perceiue then, you would acknowledge
a ſuperiour, but not he whom God and nature hath
giuen you, being induced to this reſolutiō by the prattle of your
Preachers. And why? forſooth he is not of the Catholicke religiō,
which it may be he will take away from vs, and conſtraine vs by
violence to embrace his religion, as the Quéene of England hath
done in her Realme: but as for the Spaniard, he is a Catholike,
whom we loue better then our naturall king, aſwell for that reſpect,
as for the promiſe he hath made to gouerue vs with all clemencie,
for that he deſireth not to be our king, but only to maintaine
vs in the Catholike religion. Briefly, nothing leadeth vs
hereinto, but the conſeruation of this religion, he being at this
time the eldeſt ſonne of the Romiſh Church.
            I haue before ſatiſfied you concerning the firſt part of your obiection,
when I declared, that your king will entertaine you in
libertie of conſcience, vntill a Councell haue determined of both
religions, and aſſure your ſelues for certaine, that herein he wil
inuiolably obſerue his faith and promiſe.
            Touching the ſecond obiection, that the example of the Quéene
of England cauſeth you to miſtruſt, yt your king notwithſtanding
his promiſe, will force you to obſerue the religion reformed. I
perceiue that you haue bin miſinformed of the ſtate of England
touching this point: for the Quéene neuer made promiſe vnto her
Catholicke ſubiects to continue their religion: but contrariwiſe
the Eſtates of her Realme cauſed her at her coronation to ſweare

to maintaine the religion reformed: yet for all this, it was neuer
yet found, that ſhe conſtrained the conſcience of one onely Catholicke,
to renounce his religion to liue in the reformed: true it is,
that according to her oth, ſhe hath forbidden the Maſſe to be publikely
ſaid. As for the Catholikes which haue bene executed, they
haue bin condenmed with all the ſolemnities requiſit to the procéeding
of rightfull iuſtice, as being attainted, and conuinced by
their owne confeſſions of high treaſon againſt her Maieſtie: either
for riſing in armes againſt their Soueraigne, or for being ſo
deteſtable, as to dare make attempt vpon her ſacred life. How
much had it auailed your late king, if by this laudable example
he had chaſtiſed the perturbers of his ſtate, who now finally haue
digged his graue? Herein this ſage and vertuous Princeſſe, hath
caried her ſelfe ſo diſcréetly &amp; modeſtly, that ſhe is cheriſhed and
reuerenced by all the Princes of the earth. And ſurely her actiōs
are ſo vertuous and laudable, that all men beléeue vndoubtedly
that the ſpirit of God guideth her alwayes, as it were by ye hand.
Yea I am perſwaded, that ye greateſt Prince in the world, would
eſtéeme him ſelfe happie, if he might ſecond or imitate her in the
adminiſtration of her eſtate. Yet notwithſtanding that impudēt
lyer and ſlanderous deceiuer, who at the entrance of the League,
publiſhed foorth a booke, intituled the Engliſh Catholicke to the
French, was plunged into ſuch impudencie, as falſly to alledge
actes ſo cleane contrary to the procéedings of this famous Quéen,
as I durſt ſweare ſhe neuer once imagined, onely to the end to
cauſe you to feare, &amp; redoubt the gouernment of your legitimate
king, a prince as vertuous as any this day liuing vnder the ſun.
            And leſt any man thinke, that any particular affection hath incited
me to take her cauſe in hand, I proteſt, that nothing but the
plaine and ſincere truth (which hath cauſed her innocencie to be
knowne, againſt theſe calomnious falſhoods, &amp; maketh her praiſeworthie
in all her workes) hath incited me to ſuſtaine the equity
of her cauſe: and albeit that God and nature do otherwiſe ſufficiently
bind me, yet ſhould I be too ingratefull, if I ſhould forget
the royall magnificence, and more then ſiſterlike amitie, which
her benigne clemency hath demonſtrated, and dayly doth demonſtrate
to our king ſecluded from his kingdome: as alſo the gracious

benefits which we his poore exiled countrimen haue receiued,
and yet do receaue of her vnſpeakeable liberalitie.
            The laſt part of your obiection is, that nothing occaſioneth the
Spaniard to be ſo deſirous to command ouer you, but only to cō
               ſerue
among you ye Catholike religion: ah poore ſenſleſſe ſouls: for
gods ſake do but giue eare, to what I ſhal briefly recoūt touching
his actions in this point: &amp; then ſhall you plainly perceiue, whether
the zeale that he beareth towards your religion ſolliciteth
him to be ſo charitable vnto you. Hath this great Catholike king
ſpent the treaſures, or hazarded the life of his ſubiects, only for the
aduauncement of the Chriſtian faith againſt vnchriſtian Princes?
nothing leſſe. To verifie this to be true, Pope Gregore 13.
propoſing him ſelfe to the ayd of certaine Chriſtian Princes, to
make an enterpriſe vpon the Perſian, for the augmentation of
the Church, requeſted this Spaniard to giue them ſome ſuccours:
which he not onely flatly denied, but which is more, would not
lend any of his galleys, albeit the holy ſee offred to fraight them
at her owne charges. Moreouer how dealt he with our late king
Don Sebaſtian, whoſe death all Chriſtendome hath ſufficiēt cauſe
to bewaile: who (deſiring to aſſiſt Mulei Mahumet king of Fez
and Marocco, agaiuſt Mulei Maluco his brother, who had expulſed
him his Realme, a worke ſurely worthy of ſo Chriſtian a
Prince, and aduantagious to the whole Church, for the good conditions
he had compounded with the ſtranger) required the Spaniard
his vncle to ſuccour him in this expedition, who accorded
that he ſhould haue fiftie gallies equipped, &amp; iiij. thouſand fighting
men. Which Mulei Maluco perceiuing, incontinently offred him
certaine townes on the ſea ſide to deſiſt from his promiſe, which
he ſpéedely accepted, not ſhaming to breake his othſworne to his
nephew, to contract alliance with a barbarous infidell: ſo much
did auarice raigne ouer him, as to cauſe him violate the lawes of
God &amp; men: but he was payd with the ſame money that he lent,
for that ſending his Ambaſſadour named Vanegas, to take poſſeſſion
of the town of Rarache and others promiſed vnto him: the
Barbarians mocking at his trecherie, conſtrained the Ambaſſadour
by force of the Canon, to retire ſooner then he was willing.
But it may be you will ſay, he bare him ſelfe politickly in theſe

two actions, to conſerue and maintaine his eſtate: as if humane
pollicie were to be preferred before the law and honour of God.
I, but for all this he hath ſhewed him ſelfe a very zealous Catholike,
&amp; hath caried a particular reſpect toward thoſe which make
ſtrict profeſſion of this religion. Well, let vs ſée if that be true.
After he had inuaded our Realme, and that among infinite other
Ladies, he had baniſhed into Caſtile the wife of the Agent of our
king Don Anthonio, his children and mother in law, he drewe
thrée of his ſiſters, chaſt, and holy religious, out of the monaſtery
of S. Clare at Liſbone, and confined them likewiſe into Caſtile.
But he hath dealt maruellous clemently with them in ſauing
their liues, albeit ſeruile and miſerable. Yea but ſith the women
are thus dealt with, the men muſt be handled more rigorouſly, &amp;
ſurely herein he hath throughly acquitted himſelf, witneſſe a good
religious, named Frier Iohn, of the order of the Iacobins, who
for embracing the libertie of his countrey, was hanged in the Ile
of Madera: another Frier, Hector Pintus of the order of S. Hierome,
was cōmitted to the hands of certaine ſouldiers in Caſtile,
where he was afterward empoiſoned. Frier Iames de Noronba
a Iacobin brother to the Counte de Mire, was ſo cruelly beaten,
and hurt by the ſouldiers, that he ended his life. A Doctor named
Frier Auguſtine, of the order of S. Auguſtine, and Frier Emanuel
Margues a gray Frier, were chained together with rouers and
théeues in a galley, which was afterward taken by the Turkes,
vnder whoſe crueltie, I leaue it to your iudgement to imagine
what torments theſe poore religious haue ſuffred. Frier Gregory
of the order of S. Auguſtine, was alſo captiuated in the gallies.
Frier Lewes Soarez of the order of the Trinitie, hauing bin tortured
with a thouſand torments in priſon, was afterward exiled.
Frier Anthonie Seneuſe was conſtrained to lurke ſecretly in the
forreſts, to auoyd the bloody rage of this Philip king of Spaine.
And briefly a million of others, who haue bene, and are dayly, either
drowned, ſtrangled, empoyſoned, priſoners or fugitiue.
            You might ſée a ſufficient number of them flie for refuge into
France, who yéeld more then ſufficient teſtimonie of his cruell
barbariſme. But for what occaſion or to what end were all theſe
cruelties committed? Theſe good men were faithfull Portugals,

contrary to your Preachers, &amp; therfore he feared, leſt they ſhould
moue the people to recouer their libertie. I ſpeake not of an infinite
number of the heads of our Nobilitie, wherwith the gates of
our townes are ſtuffed, and repaired from day to day. Yea but he
hath throughly gratified all thoſe which were fauouring in the vſurpation
of our Realme: ſurely according to their merits, and
the bountie of the ſayd Spaniard, a people who commonly loue
treaſon but hate the traitors, when their own turnes are ſerued:
he hath made them know when they haue demanded recompence
for their ſeruice, that albeit they haue ſold &amp; betrayed their countrey,
yet he is nothing in their debt, and that a man were ill aduiſed
to buy that which is his owne. Behold the faire reward of
their trecherie, and the payment of their ſale. Chriſtian Var de
Vegua gouernour of the Caſtle of S. Iohn, can beare witneſſe
hereof, who hauing deliuered that place to the Spaniard, for a
good annuall penſion during his life, in ſteed of enioying this promiſe,
he was incontinently baniſhed for ten yeares into Affrica
to make warre againſt ye Moores. And if you deſire to know further
herof, behold the requeſt which theſe traitors preſented vnto
the ſayd Spaniſh king, beſéeching him to kéepe his promiſe: and
the anſwer which he gaue them, you ſhall find it in the end of the
Iuſtification of our king Don Anthonio, touching the war which
he made vpon this Philip: ſo that if he hath left any (hauing chaſed
away the reſt) in their charges, and gouernments, which are
not of any great importance, he holdeth thē ſo ſhort, &amp; ſetteth ſuch
néere eſpials vpō thē, yt they are as it were in a méere captiuitie.
            Conſider now if you run not the ſame race: as for the faithfull
Frenchmen, whether ſecular or regular, albeit throughly Catholikes,
it is alreadie concluded (as it were of neceſſitie) that they
ſhall paſſe through the Spaniſh butcherie. And as for you faithleſſe
traitors, make you no better account, for that your naturall
French humanity (which difficultly can be vtterly extinguiſhed)
cannot long ſuffer the proud &amp; intollerable Spaniſh arrogancie:
which the Spaniard full well knowing, at the leaſt ſuſpition he
may take of your firſt and naturall affection (as by good right he
may alwayes hold your fidelitie in ſuſpect) will not ſpare you any
more then the reſt. The reformed religion, as it ſerueth him

now for a pretext to impaire himſelf of your kingdome, although you
called him not: ſo ſhal it alſo ſerue him as another pretext, to couer his
tyranny with a mantle of iuſtice, whileſt he tormenteth &amp; maſſacreth
thoſe, whom he ſhall perceiue, may giue him the leaſt trouble or impeachment,
making them beléeue, that they are of the religion reformed.
For my part I beléeue that you are not ſo voyd of iudgement, euen
the moſt groſſe among you, that you do not foresée what I haue
rehearſed, whereupon I eſteeme you ſo much the more ſottiſh, miſchieuous,
&amp; diſloyall toward your ſelues, séeing you precipitate your
ſelues, as it were with blinded eyes, from a faſt footing to ſo dangerous
a perill, as is imminent ouer you.
            Are theſe the effects of a king terming him ſelfe ſo great a Catholike?
Is this the reuerence he beareth to the holy Apoſtolicke ſee? Is
this to ſhew himſelf the ſole protector and piller of ye Chriſtian church
as he impudently vaunteth in his titles? Is this to be the true Paſtor
of the people, as Homer writeth of ye prince Agamemnon? Is this to
be like the good houſholder? Is this to vanquiſh his will, to handle
thoſe ſo rigorouſly, whom he hath conquered by force of armes? Surely
it is farre worſe then that pagan Cyrus, who curteouſly intreated
the Caldeans, whom he had vanquiſhed. It were good he went to the
ſchoole of that excellent hiſtoriographer Xenophon, who teacheth this
good leſſon to all vſurpers, Noui populi bello parti, ſunt beneficio afficiendi:
quo lubentius nobis parere velint. Néedleſſe it were to ſet before
your eyes, the dammages and miſeries, which you haue ſupported in
theſe warres for the Spaniards ſake: you doubt not that the rich are
become poore, that the néedie haue ſpoyled other of their goods, to reueſt
and poſſeſſe thē ſelues therof. The poet Theognides yéeldeth the principall
reaſon thereof, when ſpeaking of the like ſedition vnto yours,
he ſaith, Baiuli imperant, mali ſuper bonos.
            
            I néed not to rehearſe the taking of townes, by the armie of your
king of townes (I ſay) wherinto the ſouldier was conſtrained to enter
by aſſault, wheras you the inhabitants haue not only loſt the moſt
part of your goods, but alſo your own honor and the honor of your anceſtors,
who had ſome intereſt therein. And verily vnworthie you are
to receiue any milder chaſtiſement, albeit all be againſt the intentiō,
will, and expreſſe commandement of the king, ſéeing you are so hardned
in your rebellion, that you make all the reſiſtance yt poſſible may

be, vntil ye soldier (hauing firſt eſcaped a thouſand &amp; a thouſand deaths,
which you leuell vpon his head) ſurmount you by violence of armes.
And yet which is more to be deplored, few towns become ſage by the
miſfortune of others: wherin may be noted the iuſt vengeance of God,
which permitteth not long vndelayed the puniſhmēt due to your miſchieuous
offences: yet do I not think, that you would continue ſo obſtinate,
were it not for thoſe treacherous preachers, and others, who
haue Hiſpaniolized harts, like Philiſtides, Menippus, &amp; certaine other
orators, and partakers of Philip of Macedon amōg the Orithains: for
careleſſe are they of all your miſeries, ſo they may ſatiſfie the deſires &amp;
commandements of the Spaniſh king their Maſter, who deſireth nothing
ſo much, as the finall deſtruction of France: which he litle eſtéemeth,
ſo he may poſſeſſe it, and wold ſée it wholy ruinated, ſo he might
looſe nothing of his owne: &amp; the more it ſhalbe diſfurniſhed of power,
and diſabled with men, the more eaſily may he Hiſpaniolize ouer it:
knowing then that he cannot ſubuert it, being vnited and conioyned,
he whetteth his wits to the end to diuide it. Thus could not France
be ſubuerted but by it ſelf, like the common wealth of the Romans, of
whom it is ſaid, Mole ſua ruit. Saluſt hath left written, that the auncient
Romans were accuſtomed to ſay, yt they felt themſelues ſtrōgly
enflamed with vertue, when they beheld the monuments of their anceſtors.
In imitation of theſe noble Romans, behold ye rebellious
Frenchmen, the images of your anceſtors, their vertues, &amp; laudable actiōs,
pourtrayed and grauen in the quiers of your hiſtories, and you
ſhall ſée, that they haue alwayes combated to maintaine the libertie
of France, ſauing in ye raigne of Charls the ſixt, by reaſon of the diſſention
betwéen the Dukes of Orleans &amp; Burgundie: at what time they
made a great breach in their ancient conſtancie, diuiding themſelues,
and permitting the king of England to take déep rooting in the kingdome
of France: which notwithſtanding Charles the 7. ſonne of ye forenamed,
wholy rooted out: and all the French (like men awaked out of
a profound ſléep, which had a long time ſecurely detained them) remē
               bred
them ſelues to be true and naturall Frenchmen, which haue neuer,
at leaſt very ſeldome ſuffred thē ſelues to be gouerned by forrain
Princes. If you be curious to ſearch more anciently, the immouable
conſtancie of the French or Gaules, it is all one, you ſhal ſée it liuely
depainted for more then 1650. yeares ago, in Caeſars commentaries,

who without great trauell &amp; difficultie, could neuer ſubiect them to
the Romane Empire: which maketh me promiſe vnto my ſelfe, that
you ſéeing theſe things, wil bluſh for ſhame, ſo entirely to degenerate
from their braue courage and conſtancie, being rather in euery thing
contrary vnto them. They conſpired, they reuolted, they tooke armes,
they warred without fearing any kind of death. And why? To conſerue
their libertie, their fréedome, &amp; eſpecially not to receiue the garriſons
of the Romane Empire, redoubted, and commanding ouer the
whole world: of whom the greateſt kings held them ſelues happy to
be called the friends and confederats. Briefly, nothing was more odious
vnto them then forraine garriſons: as Ambrorix &amp; the Captains
of Tournay demonſtrated to Titurius and Cicero the Lieutenants of
Caeſar. But contrariwiſe, you league your ſelues, you rebel, you run
to armes, you enter into warre, and expoſe your life to a thouſand
dangers. Againſt whom? Euen againſt your natural and legitimate
king, whole vertue is a thouſand times more cōmended of ſtrangers
then of his owne ſubiects. To what end? To murder him, as you haue
done his predeceſſor, or to chaſe him out of his realme, that you might
ſeruilely ſubiect your ſelues. To whom? To Philip, a Spaniard, odious
for his ambition &amp; tyrannie to the whole world: &amp; after to admit
his garriſons, will you nill you, into your townes, proud garriſons,
arrogant garriſons inſolent garriſons, inſupportable garriſons: and
briefly, garriſons more then barbarous: who wil vſe you, your wiues
your children &amp; goods after their own appetite, you not daring to ſhew
the leaſt ſemblance to take it in euil part. I ſpeake not idlely, neither
do I recount fables or lies: you ſhall not be handled more curteouſly
then your neighbours: the garriſons which ſhal bridle, &amp; triumph ouer
you, ſhall not be compounded of leſſe tyrannous and cruell ſoldiers,
then thoſe whice preſſe vs ſo hardly, yt ſcantly we can take our breath:
nay happy ſhall you be if it be not worſe. Your french ſoldiers, which
haue conuerſed any time in the army of the Prince of Parma wil witneſſe,
if ſo be they will tell truly, that I am not a lier. Yet if you deſire
to haue more ſufficient teſtimony of my ſpéech, informe your ſelues of
the towns of Brittaine, where the Spaniards haue long inough ſoiorned:
yea which is a country, which the ſaid Spaniard wold make you
beléeue were appertaining to him: albeit he hath no more right then to
the other prouinces of France, for yt king Francis the firſt, &amp; ſince that

king Henry his ſonne, vnited this dutchie by the conſent of ye Eſtates
of the countrie, to the Crowne of France: in ſuch ſort, that it is of the
eſſence of that Crowne which neuer falleth vnto the diſtaffe. If you
ſubmit your towns to the tyrannie of Philip, looke hardly to ſée in thē,
by theſe impudēt garriſons, that which we dayly ſée in ours, the churches
profaned by a thouſand filths, villanies, and horrible ſacrileges:
virgins violated, matrons defloured: &amp; briefly the places and ſtréets regorging
wt the blood of poore ſlaughtered innocents. Yea theſe infamous
ſoldiers haue borne ſo litle affection to the Catholike religion, as to fix
publikly vpō the gates of ye Cathedral church of Liſbon, execrable propoſitions
againſt the doctrin of ye Goſpel, &amp; the decrées of holy Coūcels.
            Yea, but if theſe garriſons be ſo rigorous as you ſay, we wil chaſe
them out of our townes, &amp; retire our ſelues from the ſeruitude of the
Spaniard. I pray you was it eaſie or poſſible to your ancient Gauls,
notwithſtanding they enterpriſed it, to deliuer them ſelues from the
ſubiection of the Romans, vntil after many ages, &amp; at ſuch time as the
ſaid Romanes had worke cut out for them in other prouinces of their
Empire? To the Grecians, from that Philip of Macedon, and at this
day from that of the Othomans? To the Brittains, from that of the
Engliſh Saxons? And ſée you not, that we haue not bin able to recouer
our fréedom, whatſoeuer our king might do, either by the ſuccours giuen
him by your late king, or by thoſe giuen him by ye Quéene of England
about ſome 26. months paſt. No no, when you haue once ſuffred
your ſelfe to be troden vnder foot by ſuch a proud &amp; puiſſant vſurper, it
is more then difficult to raiſe vp your ſelues. It is not eaſie to remoue
the bridle when it is once put within the mouth, no more thē for Horaces
horſe, who permitted himſelfe to be bridled, for the deſire he had
to vanquiſh the hart in his courſe: but it fell out otherwiſe then he expected,
for he could neuer ſince affranchiſe him ſelfe from the bridle,
nor ſeruice of man.
            For Gods ſake, ye Frenchmē, after the example of your anceſtors,
be iealous in kéeping your precious liberty, be faithful to your prince,
and baniſh away from you this diſordinate appetite of nouelty, in deſiring
to aſſay the dominion of a ſtranger, what euer he be. For if it be
dangerous (as Saluſt ſaith) to make experience of new ſeruants, it is
without compariſon farre more dangerous to proue a new maiſter,
and principally ſo ſeuere and rigorous, as is the Spaniard. If in the

time paſſed you haue offended, ſtudie to repaire this fault, &amp; you ſhall
ſoone and with facilitie do it, if you rid from your heart this indiſcréet
affection of change, this fooliſh perſuaſiō, that the king wil take away
the Catholike religion: and this peſtilent root of auarice, which hath
wholly waſted and corrupted you, as it hath done many other people.
Do ſo hereafter, that Philip may not ſay of France, as Iugurth ſomtimes
reproched the citie of Rome, where for money he had wrought
all things to his aduantage, and departing from it, oftentimes looking
backe, brake forth into theſe words: O Citie readie to be ſold, and ſodeinly
to periſh, if it find out a marchant. But your auarice hath alreadie
done ſo much, that France is in farre worſe eſtate, for that it
hath found a marchant that hath alreadie gone through with it. Notwithſtanding
thanks be to God, he hath not yet taken poſſeſſiō therof,
and I thinke the earneſt money he hath giuen, will proue a deſperat
debt, for that the ſellers might not warrant the ſale, hauing no right
thereunto, nor repay the money without great difficulty: and albeit
they had ſome right, yet the good counſell that Scipio gaue to Iugurth,
who laboured by rewards, to purchaſe particularly the amitie of the
people of Rome, ought to haue made him more wiſe. It is dangerous
(ſaid Scipio) to buy that of a few perſons, which appertaineth to many.
Take good héed, that this miſchieuous auarice take no further hold
on you, leſt you cauſe your poſteritie and forraine nations to ſay of
this Philip, as of ancient was ſaid of Macedon: Non Philippum, sed
aurum Philippi subegiſſe Graeciam. And of our Philip: Non Philippū
Hiſpanum, ſed eius aurum ſubegiſſe Galliam. I am not ignorant that
many among you know not of what force this money of Philips is, hauing
neuer touched it as his partakers, many Captaines, officers,
preachers, and others, haue throughly done. For theſe are they which
haue miſerably ſold you, and aſſure your ſelues, that you ſhall haue
daily more &amp; more miſchiefs heaped vpon you, till you ſtop the mouth
of theſe faithleſſe preachers, or baniſh them as a mortall peſtilence, if
they will not as I haue aforeſaid, teach onely the pure word of God,
reprehending vices, for that is their vocation and no other. Which if
you do, and withall craue pardon of your king for your raſh rebellion
and offences: I dare promiſe, that he will vſe his accuſtomed clemencie
towards you: and receiue you, not only as a benigne king his faithfull
ſubiectes: but as a charitable father his welbeloued children.
            
               
As for our lamentable and deſolate Realme, the blood of our nobilitie,
and of our beſt citizens, the impriſonment, exile and baniſhment
of others: our loſſes, miſeries, and briefly our hard captiuitie, which
ſo hardly reſtraineth our throte, that ſcantly can we ſpeake, and albeit
we could, yet is it forbidden vs, leaſt we looſe that benefit to cōplaine,
exaggerating and redoubling the paine of our inſupportable martyrdomes,
either by loſſe of life, impriſonment, or at the leaſt exile &amp; baniſhment.
Let all this (I beſéech you) be as a cleare mirrour, to the
end looking therein, you may ſée, may feele, touch and apprehend, that
which you contemplate: and then, I doubt not but it may be ſayd of
you, Poſt infoelicem, rebellionis ſucceſſum, populus facilè inclinari ſolet,
ad vetus obſequium repetendum. Suffer not your ſelues any longer
to be ſeduced by the ſubtleties preſents, nor faire promiſes of this
Spaniard, who herein, as in all other things, is farre more malicious
then the Ciclops Polyphemus, for he vſed no artificiall ſubtletie to
draw men to him, and deuour them: but Philip like an ingenious architect
of all iniquities, inuenteth millions of meanes to deceiue, and
tyrannize ouer you. Sed fugite, ô miſeri, fugite, yea euen ſo ſoone as
poſſible may be, leſt hereafter you be conſtrained to do that which willingly
you would not do. Be mindfull to recouer, and preciouſly to
reſerue that gorgeous title, which you haue alwayes carried, aboue
all other people: namely, inuiolable fidelitie towards your king: retaine
euen with both hands that ineſtimable libertie, which your anceſtors
haue conquered by a million of dangers, and left intailed frō
hand to hand to your poſteritie. Finally let this be engrauen in your
hearts, that you are French men, that is to ſay, moſt affectionatly zealous
of your countrey, king and libertie, yea redoubted to all other
nations, as being iſſued out of the ſtocke of ye ancient warlike Gaules:
who oftentimes by force of armes haue terrified the Romane commō
wealth, being the terrour of all other nations. The Romanes (ſaith
Saluſt) conquered all other nations, but as for the Gaules, with them
they combated for ſafetie and not for honor.
            It would highly content me, might I vnderſtand that ye haue followed
my ſincere and faithfull aduertiſement: beléeue, that I haue
brotherly aduertiſed, and faithfully counſelled you to your great vtilitie
and profit, and that all the rigorous &amp; more then barbarous cruelties
of the Spaniard which you haue heard, are as true, as his tyrā
               nous

iniquities are manifeſt to the whole world. Theſe things haue
I diſcouered vnto you, as an eye witneſſe, hauing remained in Portingale
after the departure of our king, no leſſe miſerable then poore
Achamenides, abandoned of his Prince Vlyſſes in the deſerts of Sicilie.
For I haue alwayes euen to this preſent liued poorely in dens,
moſt often, in forreſts, rockes, and caues, and ſometime in ſome litle
corner of my friends houſe, like a languiſhing priſoner, which hath
continually hanging before his eyes, ye apprehenſion of a cruell death.
Shew not your ſelues leſſe credulous to my true ſpéech, then were
the Troians to that of the Gréeke Achamenides,
               
                  Moſt happie the man which keepeth a care,
                  By other mens harmes to learne to beware.
               
            
            Sirs, I haue declared vnto you how miſchieuouſly you haue bin ſeduced
by the Spaniſh faction, which pretendeth to vſurp your realme,
and captiuate your libertie: for this is the finall end of the plots &amp; Monopolies
which he hath practiſed, and of the diſſentions, which he hath
ingeniouſly ſowed among you. Now therfore my deſire is to aduertiſe
you in few words (but eſpecially thoſe, which may carrie an opinion,
that I haue compiled this diſcourſe, not ſo much for your good, as for
the affection that I haue to ſée your king, to the particular contentatiō
of him and his, peaceably to poſſeſſe his kingdome) that nothing hath
incited me to this admonition, but the brotherly charitie, &amp; the good wil
that I haue to ſée your troubles aſſwaged: to the end that you be not
hereafter tormented by ciuill warrs, &amp; that the Spaniard poſſeſſe not
any more your ſottiſh affections: but rather after ſo many &amp; ſo great
trauels, which willingly you haue heaped vpon your ſelues, you may
enioy a long &amp; peaceable trāquillitie, which all good men ought to wiſh
for, &amp; with hands lifted vp to demand of the diuine goodnes of God: and
not maliciouſly to nouriſh and enkindle warre, which finally heapeth
moſt miſeries vpon thoſe which do moſt ſéeke after it. Behold thē your
caſe, taking all things that I haue ſaid in the worſt ſort, touching the
eſtate of your king, flattering your ſelues, yt without great difficultie
he ſhal neuer become Maſter of his kingdome whileſt you are his aduerſaries,
&amp; fauoriſe the partie of the Spaniard, or any other his enemies,
&amp; that for this occaſion, I haue takē in hand to induce you, to reconcile
your ſelues towards his Maieſty, &amp; require pardō of your follies.
But ye caſe is farre otherwiſe, then either you think, or your preachers

giue you to vnderſtand. He is not (thanks be to God) ſo diſfurniſhed
of courage, of good and faithfull ſubiects, nor of the aſſiſtance of
his affectionat friends, who are puiſſant &amp; many, but that he can both
eaſily &amp; ſpeedily bring you to what reaſon he will, and wholly purge
his realme of this lothſome Spaniolized League, yea, and follow the
Maſter thereof by the trace, were he neuer ſo litle puſhed forward by
ambition. For you know wel, how many townes he hath forced &amp; reduced
to his obedience, and that euen at the firſt ſight. Neither are you
ignorant, that his only clemencie hath retained his puiſſance frō forcing,
ſubuerting &amp; ſaccaging the citie of Paris: herin ſhewing himſelf
rather a father then a king, not willing to do that againſt his people,
which he well might do, &amp; their obſtinat rebellion had iuſtly deſerued.
But me thinketh it is now more thē hie time, not any longer to abuſe
his patient clemēcie, leſt at length it happen to your own great harm,
as ſaith the prouerbe, Patientia nimium laeſa conuertitur in furorem.
The example of many kings, yea of your own kings, who haue chaſtiſed
their people according to their merites, ought long agoe to haue
brought you to this conſideration, amēding your ſelues, rather to day
then to morrow. And indéed there is great apparence that he wil now
betake himſelf to rigor, ſéeing his clemencie cā not vanquiſh your obſtinate
courage, by ye great preparatiōs of war which forrain Princes
addreſſe to aſſiſt him: as the Q of England, who hath already ſent good
auantcurrors: all the Princes of Germanie, many Princes of Italy,
the kings of Scotland, Denmark &amp; Sueueland, &amp; other ſeptentrional
Princes. Yea, if he would require the ſuccors of the great Turk, it is
certain he might be furniſhed. In ſuch ſort that I ſée, that if you do not
ſhortly remedy it, in ſubmitting your ſelues to his Maieſtie, the moſt
terrible ſtorme that euer lighted vpon France, is euen now readie to
light vpon you, to breake a ſunder &amp; ſubuert the very eybrow of your
proud and deteſtable rebellion No no, looke not that the Spaniſh king
with all his double piſtolets, craftie ſubtleties, &amp; arrogant brauados
ſhalbe ſufficient to turne away neuer ſo litle this impetuous &amp; cruell
tempeſt, hanging within two fingers of your head. Recourſe therfore
ſpéedily to your Prince, before he hath exiled his mercie and clemencie.
I verily hope that by this you are become wiſer then you were, &amp;
ſo ſhall your monarchie herafter become more excellent then euer before,
vnder the gouernement of ſo vertuous &amp; magnanimous a king.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

