
   
      
         
            Amends for ladies VVith the humour of roring. A comedie. As it was acted at the Blacke Fryers, both by the Princes seruants, and the Lady Elizabeths. By Nat. Field.
            Field, Nathan, 1587-1620?
         
         
            
               1618
            
         
         Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00723
            STC 10852
            ESTC S105484
            99841212
            99841212
            5776
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00723)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5776)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 773:07)
         
         
            
               
                  Amends for ladies VVith the humour of roring. A comedie. As it was acted at the Blacke Fryers, both by the Princes seruants, and the Lady Elizabeths. By Nat. Field.
                  Field, Nathan, 1587-1620?
               
               [62] p.   
               
                  Printed by G. Eld, for Math. Walbancke, and are to be sold at his shop, at the new gate of Grayes-Inne, or at the old,
                  London :
                  1618.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-H⁴ (-A1, +-A2?).
                  Another state (issue?) of STC 10851. The title page is in substantially the same setting.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-08
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2003-08
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Amends for Ladies.
WITH
THE HVMOVR
OF RORING. A COMEDIE. As it was acted at the Blacke Fryers,
both by the PRINCES Seruants, and
the Lady ELIZABETHS.
            
               By Nat. Field.
            
               LONDON:
Printed by G. Eld, for Math. Walbancke, and are to be
sold at his Shop, at the new Gate of Grayes-Inne,
or at the old. 1618.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            AMENDS FOR
LADIES.
            A COMEDIE.
            Actus primi Scaena prima.
            Enter the Lady HONOR, the Lady PERFECT,
the Lady BRIGHT.
            
            
               Maid.
               
                  A Wife the happiest state? It cannot be.
            
            
               Wife.
               Yes, such a wife as I, that haue a man
               As if my selfe had made him: such a one
               As I may iustly say, I am the rib
               Belonging to his brest. Widow and Maide,
               Your liues compar'd to mine are miserable,
               Though weal
                     ••
                   and beautie meete in each of you.
               Poore virgin, all thy sport is thought of loue,
               And meditation of a man, the time
               And circumstance ere thou canst fixe thy thoughts
               On one thy fancy will approue.
            
            
               Maid.
               That trouble already may be past.
            
            
               Wife.
               Why if it be.
               The doubt, hee will not hold his brittle faith,
               That he is not a competible choise,
               And so your noble friends will crosse the match,
               Doth make your happinesse vncertaine still:
               
                  
Or say you marryed him, what hee would proue.
               Can you compare your state then to a Wife?
            
            
               Maide.
               Nay, all the freedome that a virgin hath
               Is much to be preferr'd. Who would endure
               The humours of so insolent a Thing
               As is a husband? Which of all the Heard
               Runs not possessed with some notorious vice,
               Drinking or whoring, fighting, Iealousie,
               Euen of a Page at twelue, or of a Groome,
               That rubs horse-heeles? Is it not daily seene,
               Men take wiues, but to dresse their meate, to wash
               And starch their linnen: for the other matter
               Of lying with them, that's but when they please:
               And whatsoere the ioy be of the bed,
               The pangs that follow procreation
               Are hideous, or you wiues haue guld your husbands
               With your loud shrikings, and your deathfull throes.
               A Wife or Widow to a Virgins life?
            
            
               Widow.
               Why should the best of you thinke yee inioy
               The rest and rule, that a free widow doth?
               I am mine owne commander, and the blisse
               Of wooers, and of each varietie
               Frequents me, as I were a maide. No Brother
               Haue I to dice my patrimony away, as you
               My maiden Madaine may. No husbands death
               Stand I in doubt on: for thankes be to heauen
               (If mine were good) the grieuous losse of him
               Is not to come; if hee were bad, hee's gone,
               And I no more embrace my iniury.
               But be yours ill, you nightly claspe your hate;
               Or good, why he may dye, or change his vertue.
               And thou (though single) hast a bed
                     •
                  fellow
               As bad as the worst husband, thought of one,
               And what that is, men with their wiues do doe,
               And long expectance till the deed be done.
               " A wife is like a garment vsde and torne:
               " A maide like one made vp, but neuer worne.
            
            
               
               Maide.
               "A widow is a garment worne thred-bare,
               Selling at second hand, like Brokers ware.
               But let vs speake of things the present time
               Make happy to vs, and see what is best.
               I haue a seruant then the crowne of men,
               The fountaine of Humanitie, the prize
               Of euery vertue, Morall and Diuine;
               Young, valiant, learned, well-borne, rich and shap'd
               As if wise Nature when she fashioned him,
               Had meant to giue him nothing but his forme,
               Yet all additions are conferr'd on him,
               That may delight a woman: this same youth
               To me hath sacrific'd his heart, yet I
               Haue checkt his suite, laught at his worthy seruice,
               Made him the exercise of my crueltie,
               Whilst constant as the Sunne, for all these clouds
               His loue goes on.
            
            Enter INGEN.
            
            
               Widow.
               Peace, here's the man you name.
            
            
               Wife.
               
                  Widow. Wee'll stand aside.
            
            
               Ing.
               Good morrow to the glory of our age.
               Meeting the 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               The Lady Perfect, and the Lady Bright,
               
               The vertuous wife and widow: but to you
               The Lady Honor, and my Mistresse,
               The happinesse of your 
                     〈◊〉
                  .
            
            
               Maid.
               By thi
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  ight, I neuer heard one speake so scu
                     ••
                  lly,
               Vtter such s
                     •
                  ale wit, and pronounce so ill.
               But to you,
               My Lady Honor, and my Mistresse,
               The happinesse of your wishes.
            
            
               Ingen.
               Stop your wit,
               You would faine shew these Ladies what a hand
               You hold ouer your seruant. T' shall not neede,
               I will expresse your tyranny well enough.
               I haue lou'd this Lady since I was a childe,
               Since I could construe Am
                        •
                     : now she saies
               I doe not loue her, 'cause I doe not weepe,
               
                  
Lay mine armes ore my heart, and weare no garters,
               Walke with mine eyes in my hat, sigh, and make faces
               For all the Poets in the towne to laugh at,
               Poxe a this howling loue, ti's like a dogg
               Shut out midnight. Must loue needs be poudred,
               Lie steept in brine; or will it not keepe sweet?
               Is it like beefe in sommer?
            
            
               Maid.
               Did you euer
               Heare one talke 
                     •
                  ustian like a Butcher thus?
            
            
               Ingen.
               T'is foolish, this same telling folkes we loue,
               It needs no words, t' will show it selfe in deeds,
               And did I take you for an entertainer,
               A Lady that will wring one by the finger,
               Whil'st on anothers toes shee treads, and cries
               By Gad I loue but one, and you are hee:
               Either of them thinking himselfe the man,
               I'de tell you in your eare, put for the busines,
               Which graunted, or denied, Maddam God b'wee.
            
            
               Maid.
               Come these are daily slaunders that you raise,
               On our infirme and vnresisting Sexe,
               You neuer me
                     •
                   I am sure with such a Lady.
            
            
               Ingen.
               O
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  any by this light, I haue seene a Chamber
               Frequented like an office of the Law,
               Clients succeede at midnight one another:
               Whilst the poore Maddam 
                     〈◊〉
                   be
                     •
                  ne so distrest,
               Which of her Loues to show most 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               That hi
                     •
                   dull Husband ha's perceiu'd her wiles.
            
            
               Maid.
               Nay perhaps taught her, many of those Husbands
               Are base enough
               To liue vpon't.
            
            
               Ingen.
               I haue seene another of 'em
               Cheat by this light at Cardes, and set her women,
               To talke to the Gentlemen that plaid,
               That so distracted they might ouer see.
            
            
               Maid.
               Oh fie vpon yee, I dare sweare you lie.
            
            
               Ingen.
               Doe not faire Mistresse, you will be for sworne.
            
            
               Maid.
               You men are all soule mouth'd, I warrant, you
               
                  
Talke thus of me and other Ladies here,
               Because we keepe the Cittie.
            
            
               Ingen.
               Oh prophance.
               That thought would damne me, will you marrie yet?
            
            
               Maid.
               No I will neuer marry.
            
            
               Ingen.
               Shall we then
               Couple vnlawfully? for indeed this marrying
               Is but proclaming what we meane to doe;
               Which may be done priuatly, in ciuill sort
               And none the wiser, and by this white hand La:
               The wrack, Strapado, or the boiling boote,
               Should neuer force me tell to wrong your honor.
            
            
               Maid.
               May I beleeue this?
            
            
               Ingen.
               Let it bee your Creed.
            
            
               Maid.
               But if you should proue false. Nay ne'er vnhang
               Your sword, except you meane to hang your selfe:
               Why where haue you beene drinking? sfoot you talke
               Like one of these same rambling boies,
               That raigne in Turnebull-street.
            
            
               Ingen.
               How doe you know?
            
            
               Maid.
               Indeed my knowledge, is but speculatiue
               Not practique there, I haue it by Relation,
               From such obseruers as your selfe deare Seruant,
               I must professe, I did thinke well of thee,
               But get thee from my 
                     ••
                  ght, I neuer more
               Will heare or see thee, but will hate thee deadly,
               As a man enemy, or a woman turn'd.
               Enter Widdow,
Wife.
               Ladies come forth, see Sir what Curtesie
               You haue done to mee, a strange praise of you
               Had newly left my lips, iust, as you entred,
               And how you haue deseru'd it, with your carriage?
               Villain, thou hast hurt mine honor to these friends,
               For what can they imagine but some ill▪
               
               Hath past betwixt vs by thy broad discourse?
               Were my case theirs, by Virgin Chastity,
               I should condemne them: hence, depart my sight.
            
            
               Ingen.
               Madam, but here mee, oh that these were men,
               
                  
And durst but say or thinke you ill, for this
               I haue so good a cause vpon my side.
               That I would cut their hearts out of their brests:
               And the thoughts out of them that iniur'd you.
               But I obay your best, and for my pennance,
               Will run a course neuer to see you more,
               And now I loose you, may I loose the light:
               Since in that beauty dwelt my day or night.
               Exit Ingen.
            
            
               Widd.
               Is this the vertuous youth?
            
            
               Wife.
               Your happines?
            
            
               Widd.
               Wherein you thought your seat so far 'boue ours,
            
            
               Maid.
               If one man could be good, this had beene hee.
               
                  Enter SVBTLE, HVSBAND, FEESIMPLE,
WEL-TRID.
               See here comes all your sutors, and your Husband,
               Aud
                     •
                  oome for Laughter, heer's the Lord Feesimple,
               
               What Gentlewoman do's hee bring along?
            
            
               Enter HVSBAND, embracing SVBTLE, the Lord FEESIMPLE,
with young BOVLD like a waiting Gentlewoman▪
               
VVEL-TRID, HVSB: SVBTLE talke with
WIFE.
            
               Fees.
               One and thirty good-morrows to the fairest, wisest,
chastest, richest VViddow that euer conuersation coapt
withall.
            
            
               Widd.
               Three score and two vnto the wisest Lord,
               That euer was train'd in vniuersitie.
            
            
               Feesimp.
               Oh Curteous, bounteous Widow, shee ha's outbid
me 31. Good morrowes at a clap.
            
            
               Welt.
               But my Lord Feesimple you forgot the busines impos'd
on you.
            
            
               Fees.
               Gentlewoman, I crie thee mercie, but ti's 
                     •
                   fault in
all Lords, not in mee only, we doe vse to sweare by our Honors:
and as we are Noble, to dispatch such a businesse for
such a Gentleman and wee are bound, euen by the same
Honors wee sware by, to forget it in a quarter of an houre.

And looke as if wee had neuer seene the Partie, when wee
meete next, especially if none of our Gentlemen haue bin
considered.
            
            
               Welt.
               I, but all your's haue, for you keepe none my Lord:
Besides though it stands with your Honor to forget mens
businesses; yet it stands not with your Honor, if you doe not
doe a womans.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why then Maddam, so it is that I request your Ladiship
to accept into your seruice this Gentlewoman, for
her truth &amp; honestie I will be bound, I haue knowne her too
long to be deceiu'd, this is the second time I haue seene her.
            
            
               Maid.
               Why how now my Lord: a preferrer of Gentlewomen
to seruice like an old knitting woman? where hath
Shee dwelt before.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Shee dwelt with young Boulds sister, hee that is my
Corriuall in your Loue, she requested me to aduance her to
You; for you are a dub'd Lady: so is not shee yet.
            
            
               Welt.
               But now you talk of yong Bould, when did you see
him Lady?
            
            
               Wid.
               Not this month Maister Well-tri'd.
               
               I did coniure him to forbeare my sight:
               Indeed swore if he came Il'd be denied.
               But tis strange you should aske for him, yee two were wont
neuer to be asunder.
            
            
               Welt.
               Faith Maddam we neuer were together but wee
differd on some argument or other,
               And doubting least our discord might at length
               Breed to some quarrell, I forbeare him to.
            
            
               Fees.
               He quarrell? Bould: hang him, if he durst haue quarrel'd,
the world knowes hee's within a mile of an oke ha's
put him too't, and soundly, I neuer car'd for him in my life,
but to see his sister, hee's an asse, pox an arrant asse, for doe
you thinke any but an arrant asse, would offer to come a
wooing, where a Lord atempts? he quarrell: hee dares not
quarrell.
            
            
               Welt.
               But hee dares fight my Lord, vpon my knowledge,
               And raile no more my Lord, behind his back,
               
                  
For if you doe my Lord bloud must insue.
            
            Dr
                  ••••
               .
            
               Fees.
               Oh, oh my honor dies, I am dead.
            
            
               Welt.
               Vd'slight whats the matter, wring him by the nose
            
            
               Wild.
               A paire of riding spurs now were worth gold,
            
            
               Maid.
               Pins are as good, prick him, prick him
            
            
               Feesim.
               Oh, oh.
            
            
               Wife.
               Hee's come againe, lift him vp.
            
            
               Omnes.
               How fa
                     •
                  es your Lordship?
            
            
               Fees.
               Oh friends, you haue wrong'd my spirit to call 
                     〈◊〉
                  
backe, I was 
                     〈◊〉
                   in Elizium at rest.
            
            
               Welt.
               But why sir did you sowne?
            
            
               Feesi.
               Well though I die Maister Wel-tri'd before all these
I doe forgiue you, because you were ignorant of my infirmitie,
oh sir, i'st not vp yet, I die againe, put vp now whil'st
I winke, or I doe winke for euer.
            
            
               Welt.
               Ti's vp my Lord, ope your eies, but I pray tell mee
Is this antipathie twixt bright steele and you naturall, or
how grew it?
            
            
               Feesi.
               Il'e tell you sir, any thing bright and edg'd, works
thus strongly with me, your hil
                     •
                  s now I can handle as boldlie,
looke you else.
            
            
               Knight.
               Nay neuer blame my Lord Maister Well-tri'd, for
I know a great manie will sowne at the sight of a shoulder
of mutton or a quarter of Lambe, my Lord may be excus'd
then, for a naked sword.
            
            
               Welt.
               This Lord, and this knight in dogge-collers would
make a fine brace of beagles.
            
            
               Maid.
               But on my faith 
                     •
                  twas mightily ouerseene of your
father, not to bring you vp to foyles, or if hee had bound
you Prentise to a Cutler or an Ire-monger.
            
            
               Fees.
               I a poxe, hang him old gouty foole, he neuer brought
me vp to any Lordly exercise, as fencing, dancing, rumbling,
and such like: but forsooth I must write and reade, &amp; speake
languages, and such base qualities, fit for none but Gentlemen.
Now sir would I tell him, Father you are a Count, I
am a Lo: a poxe a writing and reading, and languages, let
mee be brought vp as I was borne.
            
            
               
               Subtle.
               But how my Lord came you first not to 
                     〈◊〉
                   the
sight of steele.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why I'l
                     •
                   tell you Sir, when I was a child, an infant,
an Innocent.
            
            
               Maid.
               T'was e'
                     •
                  e now.
            
            
               Fees.
               I being in the kitchin, in my Lo: my fathers house,
the Cooke was making minc'd pyes: so sir, I standing by the
Dresser, there lay a heape of plums. Here was hee mincing;
what did mee I sir, being a notable little witty coxcombe,
but popt my hand iust vnder his chopping knife, to snatch
some Reysins, and so was cut 
                     •
                  re the hand, and neuer 
                     •
                  ince
could I endure the 
                     •
                  ight of any edge-toole.
            
            
               Wid.
               Indeede they are not fit for you my Lord, and now
you are all so well satufied in this matter, pray Ladies how
like you this my Gentlewoman?
            
            
               Maid.
               In troth Maddam exceeding well I, if you be prouided,
pray let me haue her.
            
            
               Wife.
               It should be my request, but that I am full.
            
            
               Wid.
               What can you doe? What's her name my Lord?
            
            
               Fees.
               Her name? I know not. What's her name Mr. Well-try'd?
               
            
            
               Weltr.
               Her name? slid, tell my Lady your name.
            
            
               Bould.
               Mistresse Mary Princox forsooth.
            
            
               Wid.
               Mistresse Mary Princax: she has wit, I perceiue that
alrea
                     •
                  y. Mee thinkes she speakes as if she were a my Lords
brood.
            
            
               Bould
               Brood Maddame, 'tis well knowne I am a Gentlewoman.
My father was a man of 500. per annum, and hee
held something in Capite too.
            
            
               Welt.
               So does my Lord, something.
            
            
               Fees.
               Nay, by my troth, what I hold in capite is worth little
or nothing.
            
            
               Bould.
               I haue had apt breeding, how euer my misfortune
now makes me submit my selfe to seruice: but there is
no ebbe so low, but hath his tyde againe: when our dayes
are at worst, they will mend in spight of the frowning Destinies.
For wee cannot be lower then earth, and the same

blinde Dame that hath cast her bleare eyes hitherto vpon
my occasions, may turne her wheele, and at last winde them
vp with her white hand to some pinnacle that prosperously
may flourish in the Sunne-shine of promotion.
            
            
               Fees.
               Oh mouth, full of agilitie, I would giue 20. Markes
now to any person that could teach mee to conuey my
tongue (sance stumbling) with such dexteritie to such a period.
For her truth and her honesty I am bound before, but
now I haue heard her talke, for her wit I will be bound body
and goods.
            
            
               Wid.
               V'dslight, I will not leaue her for my hood.
I neuer met with one of these eloquent old Gentlewomen
before. What age are you Mistresse Mary Princox?
               
            
            
               Bould.
               I will not lye Maddam, I haue numbred 57. Summers,
and iust so many winters haue I past.
            
            
               Subt.
               But they haue not past you, they lye forzen in your
face.
            
            
               Bould.
               Maddam, if it shall please you to entertaine me, so:
if not, I desire you not to misconstrue my good will, there's
no harme done, the doore's as big as it was, and your Ladiships
owne wishes crowne your beauty with content. As for
these frumping Gallants, let them doe their worst: it is not
in mans power to hurt mee: 'tis well knowne I come not
to be scoff
                     •
                  d. A woman may beare and beare till her backe
burst. I am a poore Gentlewoman, and since vertue has now
a dayes no other companion but pouerty, I set the Hares
head against the Goose giblets, and what I want one way
I hope I shall be inabled to supply the other.
            
            
               Fees.
               A'nt please God, that thou wert not past children;
            
            
               Wid.
               Ist e'ne so my Lord? nay good Princox do not crie,
I doe entertaine you, how doe you occupie? what can you
vse?
            
            
               Bould.
               Any thing fit to be put into the hands of a Gentlewoman.
            
            
               Wid.
               What are your qualities?
            
            
               Bould.
               I can sleepe on a low stoole, if your Lady-ship be
talking in the same roome with any Gentle-man, I can reade

on a booke, sing loue songs, looke vp at the loouer light,
heare and be deafe, see and be blind, be euer dumb to your
secrets, sweare and equiuocate, and whatsoeuer I spie, say
the best.
            
            
               Wid.
               Oh rare Croane? how art thou endu'd? but why did
Master Boulds sister put you away?
            
            
               Bould.
               I beseech you Madame to neglect that desire,
though I know your Lady-ships vnderstanding to be sufficient
to partake or take in the greatest secret; can be imparted:
yet.—
            
            
               Wid.
               Nay prithie tell the cause, come heer's none but
freinds.
            
            
               Bould.
               Faith Madame, heigh ho, I was (to confesse truly)
a little foolish in my last seruice, to beleeue mens oaths, but
I hope my example, though preiudiciall to my selfe, will be
beneficiall to other yong Gentle-women in seruice, my mistresses
brother (the Gentle-man you nam'd e' now, master
Bould) hauing often attempted my honor, but finding it impregnable,
vow'd loue, and marriage to me, at the last I, a
yong thing and raw, being seduced, set my minde vpon him,
but friends contradicting the match, I fell into a greiuous
consumption, and vpon my first recouerie, least the intended
sacred ceremonies of Nuptials should succede, his sister
knowing this, thought it fit in her iudgement, we should be
farther a sunder, and so put me out of her seruice.
            
            
               Omnes.
               Ha, ha, ha.
            
            
               Wid.
               God a mercie for this discouerie ifaith,
               Oh man what art thou? when thy cock is vp? come wil your
lordship walke in? tis dinner time.
            
            Enter hastily M. Seldome with papers on his arme.
            
               Omnes.
               Whose this? whose this?
            
            
               Maid.
               This is our Land-lord, Master Seldome,
               
               An exceeding wise Citizen, a very sufficient vnderstanding
man, and exceeding rich.
            
            
               Om.
               Miracles are not ceasd.
            
            
               Wid.
               Good morrow Land-lord, where haue you beene
sweating?
            
            
               Seld.
               Good morrow to your Honors, thrift is industrious,
your Lady-ship knowes we will not stick to sweat for our

pleasures, how much more ought wee to sweat for our profits?
I am come from master Ingen this morning, who is married
or to be married, and though your Ladyships did not
honor his Nuptials with your presence, he hath by me sent
each of you a paire of gloues, and Grace Seldome my wife is
not forgot.
               Exit.
            
            
               Omnes.
               God giue him ioy, God giue him ioy.
            
            Exeunt.
            
               Maid.
               Let all things most impossible change now.
               Oh periur'd man! oathes are but words I see.
               But wherefore should not we that thinke we loue
               Vpon full merrit, that same worth once ceasing
               Surcea
                     •
                  e our loue to, and finde new desert?
               Alas we cannot, loue's a pit, which, when
               We fall into we ne're get out againe,
               And this same horrid newes which me assaults
               I would forget, loue blanches blackest faults:
               Oh! what path shall I treade for remedie?
               But darkest shades, where loue with death doth lie.
               Exit.
            
            
               Manent HVSBAND, WIFE, SVBTLE.
            
               Wife.
               Sir I haue often heard my husband speake of your
acquaintance.
            
            
               Husb.
               Nay my vertuous wife,
               Had it beene but acquaintance, this his absence
               Had not appear'd so vncouth, but we two
               Were Schoole-fellowes together, borne and nurs'd,
               Brought vp, and liu'd since like the Gemins,
               Had but one suck, the Tauerne or the Ordinarie.
               Ere I was married, that saw one of vs
               Without the other, said we walk't by halfes,
               Where deere, deere friend haue you beene all this while?
            
            
               Subt.
               Oh most sweet friend the World's so vicious,
               That had I with such familiaritie
               Frequented you since you were married,
               Possess'd and vs'd your fortunes as before,
               As in like maner you commanded mine,
               The deprau'd thoughts of men would haue proclaim'd
               Some scandalous rumors from this loue of ours,
               
                  
As saying, mine reflected on your Ladie,
               And what a wound had that beene to our soules?
               When only friend-ship should haue beene the ground
               To hurt her Honor, and your confident peace,
               Spight of mine owne approu'd integritie.
            
            
               Husb.
               Wife, kisse him, bid him welcome poxo'th World,
               Come, come you shall not part from me in hast,
               I doe command thee vse this Gentle-man
               In all things like my selfe, if I should die
               I would be queath him in my will to thee.
            
            
               Wife.
               Sir, you are most welcome, &amp; let scandalous tongues
               No more deterre you, I dare vse you Sir,
               With all the right belonging to a friend,
               And what I dare, I dare let all man see
               My conscience rather, then mens thoughts be free.
            
            
               Husb.
               Will you looke in?
               Wee'le follow you. Now friend
               Exit. Wife.
               What thinke you of this Ladie?
            
            
               Subt.
               Why sweet friend,
               That you are happie in her, shee is faire,
               Wittie and vertuous, and was rich to you,
               Can there be an addition to a wife?
            
            
               Husb.
               Yes, constancie, for t'is not chastitie
               That liues remote from all attempters free,
               But there, ti's strong and pure where all that wooe
               It doth resist, and turnes them vertuous too;
               Therefore deere friend, by this, loues masculine kisse,
               By all our mutuall engagements past,
               By all the hopes of amitie to come,
               Be you the setler of my jealous thoughts,
               And make me kill my fond suspect of her,
               By assurance that shee is loyall, otherwise
               That shee is false, and then, as shee's past cure,
               My soule shall euer after be past care.
               That you are fittest for this enterprize
               You must needs vnderstand, since prooue shee true
               (In this your tryall) you my dearest friend,
               (Whom onely, rather than the World besides
               
                  
I would haue satisfied of her vertue) shall be,
               And best conceale my folly, proue shee weake,
               T'is better you should know't than any man,
               Who can reforme her, and doe me no wrong,
               Chimicall metals, and bright gold it selfe
               By sight are not distinguisht, but by'th test,
               Thought makes good wiues, but triall makes the best:
               To the vnskilfull owners eies, alike
               The Bristow sparkles as the Diamond,
               But by a Lapidarie the truth is found,
               Come you shall not denie me.
            
            
               Subt.
               Doe not wrong
               So 
                     •
                  aire a wife (friend) and so vertuous,
               Whose good name is a theame vnto the World,
               Make not a wound with searching where was none,
               Misfortune still such projects doth pursue,
               He makes a false wife, that suspects a true;
               Yet since you so importune, giue me leaue
               To ruminate a while, and I will straight
               Follow and giue you an answer.
            
            
               Husb.
               You must do it.
               Exit.
            
            
               Subt.
               Assure your selfe deere—Coxcombe, I will do't
               Or strangely be denied, all's as I wisht,
               This was my aime, although I haue seem'd strange.
               I know this fellow now to be an Asse;
               A most vnworthie husband though in view
               He beare himselfe thus faire, shee knowes this too,
               Therefore the stronger are my hopes to gaine her:
               And my deere friend that will haue your wife trid'e,
               I'le trie her first, then thrust her if I can,
               And as you said most wisely I hoped to be
               Both Touch-stone to your wise and Lapidarie.
               Exit.
            
         
         
            Actus secundi Scaena prima.
            Enter SELDOME his WIFE working as in their shop.
            
               Grace.
               HVsband these gloues are not fit for my wearing,
I'le put 'em into the shop and sell 'em, you shall
giue me a plaine paire for them.
            
            
               
               Seld.
               This is wonderfull, wonderfull, this is thy sweet care
and iudgement in all things, this goodnesse is no
                     •
                   vsuall in
our wiues, well Grace Seldome, that thou art faire is nothing,
that thou art well spoken is nothing, that thou art wittie is
nothing, that thou art a Citizens wife is nothing; but Grace,
that thou art faire, that thou art well spoken, that thou art
wittie, that thou art a Citizens wife, and that thou art honest
I say, and let any mun denie it that can, it is something,
it is something, I say, it is Seldomes something, and for all
the Sunne-shine of my joy mine eyes must raine vpon thee.
            
            Enter MALL with a Letter.
            
               Mall.
               By your leaue Master Seldome, haue you done the
hangers I bespake for the Knight?
            
            
               Seld.
               Yes marrie haue I Mistris hic &amp; hac, i'le fetch 'em to
you.
               Exit.
            
            
               Mall.
               Z'oones, does not your husband know my name, if
it had beene some bodie else I would haue cal'd him Cuckoldlie
slaue.
            
            
               Grace.
               If it had been some bodie else perhaps you might.
            
            
               Mall.
               Well I may be euen with him, all's cleere; pritie
rogue I haue long'd to know thee this twelue moneths, and
had no othermeanes but this to speake with thee, there's a
letter to thee from the partie.
            
            
               Grace.
               What partie?
            
            
               Mall.
               The Knight Sir Iohn Lo
                        •
                     all.
               
            
            
               Grace.
               Hence lewd impudent
               I know not what to tearme thee man or woman,
               For nature shaming to acknowledge thee
               For either; hath produc'd thee to the World
               Without a sexe, some say thou art a woman,
               Others a man; and many thou art both
               Woman and man, but I thinke rather neither
               Or man and horse, as the old Centaures were faign'd.
            
            
               Mall.
               Why how now Mistris, what lack yee? are you so
so fine with a poxe? I haue seene a woman looke as modestly
as you, and speake as sinceerely, and follow the Fryars as
zealously, and shee has beene as sound a jumbler as e're paid
for't, t'is true Mris. 
                     •
                  ipenie, I haue sworne to leaue this letter.
            
            
               
               Grace.
               D'ee heare, you sword and target (to speake in
               your owne key) Marie Vmbree, Long-Meg,
               
               Thou that in thy selfe (me think'st) alone
               Look'st like a rogue and a whore vnder a hedge:
               Bawd, take your letter with you and begone,
               When next you come (my Husband's Constable)
               And Bridewe
                     •
                  l is hard by, y
                     •
                  aue a good wit,
               And can co
                     ••
                  eiue.
            
            Enter SELDOME with hangers.
            
               Seld.
               Looke you, heere are the hangers.
            
            
               Mall.
               Let's see them.
               Fie, fie, you haue mistooke me quite,
               They are not for my turne (b'y mistris Seldome)
               Exit.
            
            Enter Lord PROVDLIE.
            
            
               Grace.
               Heere's my Lord Proudlie.
               
            
            
               Lo. Proud.
               My Horse Laquey, is my sister Honor aboue?
            
            
               Seld.
               I thinke her Ladiship, my Lord, is not well, and keeps
her Chamber.
            
            
               Proud.
               Al's one, I must see her, haue the other La. din'd?
            
            
               Grace.
               I thinke not my Lord.
            
            
               Proud.
               Then i'le take a pipe of Tobacco heere in your
shop if it be not offensiue, I would be loath to be thought to
come iust at dinner time. Garsoon; fill, sirrah,
Enter PAGE with a pipe of Tobacco.
What said the Gold-Smith for the money?
            
            
               Seldome hauing fetch a candle, walk's off at th' other end of
the Shop, Lord sits by his wife.
            
               Page.
               He said my Lord he would lend no man money
that he durst not arrest.
            
            
               Proud.
               How got that wit into Cheape-side 'tro, hee is a
Cuckold.
               Saw you my Ladie to day, what saies shee?
            
            Takes Tobacco
            
               Page.
               Marry my Lord, shee said her old husband had a
great payment to make this morning, and had not left her
so much as a jewell.
            
            
               Proud.
               A poxe of her old Cats chops, the teeth shee had,
haue made a transmigration into haire, shee hath a bigger
beard than I by this light.
            
            
               
               Sel.
               This custome in vs Cittizens is good,
               Lo: whispers
to Grace.
               
               Thus walking off when men talk with our wiues,
               It shew's vs curteous, and mannerly,
               Some count it basenesse, hee's a foole that does so,
               It is the highest point of pollicie
               Especiallie when we haue vertuous wiues.
            
            
               Gr.
               Fie, fie, you talke vnciuillie my Lord.
            
            
               Pr.
               Vnciuillie, mew, can a Lord talke vnciuilly? I thinke
you a finicall taffatae pipkin may be proud ile sit so neare it,
vnciuillie mew.
            
            
               Gr.
               Your mothers Cat ha's kitten'd in your mouth sure:
            
            
               Pr.
               Prithee but note yo
                     •
                   Felow, do's he not walke &amp; look
as if hee did desire to be a Cuckold?
            
            
               Gr.
               But you doe not looke as if you could make him one,
now they haue dind my Lord.
            
            Enter Lord Feesimple, Maister Wel-tri'd.
            
               Feesi.
               God saue your Lordship.
            
            
               Pr.
               How dost thou Coze, hast thou got any more wit yet?
            
            
               Feesim.
               No by my troth I haue but litle money with that
little wit I haue, and the more wit euer the lesse money, yet
as litle as I haue of either: I would giue some thing that I
durst but quarrell,
               I would not be abused thus daily as I am.
            
            
               Welt.
               Saue you my Lord.
            
            
               Pr.
               Good Maister Wel-tri'd, you can informe mee, pray
how ended the quarrell betwixt yong Bould, and the other
Gentleman.
            
            
               Welt.
               Why very fairelie my Lord, on honorable tearmes,
               Young Bould was iniur'd and did challenge him,
               Fought in the field, and the other gaue him satisfaction
               Vnder his hand, I was Boulds second, and can shew it heere.
            
            
               Pr.
               T'is strange there was no hurt done, yet I hold
the other Gentleman, farr the better Man.
            
            
               Welt.
               So doe not I.
            
            
               Pr.
               Besides they say the satisfaction that walks in the Ordinaries,
is counter-feit.
            
            
               Welt.
               He lies that saies so, and ile make it good,
               And for I know my frend is out of towne,
               
                  What Man soeuer wrongs him is my foe,
               I say he had full satisfaction,
               Nay that which wee may call submission:
               That the other sought peace first, and who denies this,
               Lord, Knight, or Gentleman, English, French, or Scot,
               I'le fight and proue it on him with my sword.
            
            
               Feesi.
               No sweet Maister Well-tri'd, let's haue no fighting
till (as you haue promis'd) you haue rid me from this foolish
feare, and taught mee to endure to looke vppon a naked
Sword.
            
            
               Welt.
               Well and il'e be as good as my word.
            
            
               Feesi.
               But doe you heare Cozen Proudly? they say my old
Father must marrie your sister Honor, and that hee will disinherit
me, and intaile all his Lordships on her, and the heire
he shall beget on her bodie, i'st true or not?
            
            
               Proudly.
               There is such a report.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why then I pray God he may die an ould Cuckoldlie
               slaue, oh world what art thou? where is Parents loue?
               Can he denie me for his naturall Child,
               Yet see (oh fornicator) ould and stiffe,
               Not where he should be, that's my comfort yet,
               As 
                     •
                  or you my Lord: I will send to you as soone as I dare
fight and looke vppon steele, which Maister Wel-tri'd I pray
let be with all possible speede.
            
            
               Pr.
               What d'ee this afternoone.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Faith I haue a great mind to see long-megg and the
ship at the Fortune.
            
            
               Pr.
               Nay afaith let's vp and haue a rest at Primero.
            
            
               Welt.
               Agreed my Lord, and toward the Euening il'e carrie
you to the Companie.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Well no more words.
            
            Exeunt Lord PROVDLY, Lord FEES. WEL-TR.
            
            
               Grace.
               I wonder Sir you will walke so and let anie bodie

                     •
                  it prating to your wife! were I a man Id'e thrust'em out ot'h
shop by the head and shoulders.
            
            
               Sol.
               There were no pollicie in that wife, so should I loose
their custome, let them talke them selues wearie, and giue
thee loue tokens still, I loose not by it.
               
                  
Thy chastitie's impregnable, I know it,
               Had I a dame whose eies did swallow youth,
               Whose vnchast gulph together did take in
               Masters, and Men, the Foot-bodies and their Lords,
Making a Gally-moferie in her blood,
               I would not walke thus then: but vertuous wife,
               He that in chast eares poores his ribauld talke
               Begets hate to himselfe, and not consent;
               And euen as durt throwne hard against a wall
               Rebounds and sparkles in the throwers eies,
               So ill words vtter'd to a vertuous Dame,
               Turne and defile the speaker with red shame.
            
            Exeunt.
            Enter HVSBAND and WIFE.
            
            
               Hus.
               Z'oones, you are a whore, though I entreat him faire
               Before his face, in complement, or so,
               I not esteeme him truly as this rush,
               Ther's no such thing as friend-ship in the world,
               And he that can not sweare, dissemble, lie,
               Wants knowledge how to liue, and let him die.
            
            
               Wife.
               Sir I did thinke you had esteem'd of him
               As you made shew, therefore I vs'd him well,
               And yet not so but that the strictest eie
               I durst haue made a witnesse of my cariage.
            
            
               Husb.
               Plague a your carriage, why he kist your hand,
               Look't babies in your eies, and wink't and pink't,
               You thought I had esteem'd him, S'blood you whore,
               Doe not I know, that you doe know you lie,
               When did'st thou heare me say and meane one thing?
               Oh I could kick you now, and teare your face
               And eate thy Breasts like vdders.
            
            
               Wife.
               Sir you may, but if I know what hath deseru'd al this
I am no woman, 'cause he kist my hand, vnwillingly.
            
            
               Hurb.
               A little lowder pray.
            
            
               Wife.
               You are a base fellow, an vnworthie man
               As e're poore Gentlewoman match't withall,
               Why should you make such shew of loue to any
               Without the truth, thy beastly minde is like
               Some deca
                     •
                  'd Tradseman that doth make his wife
               
                  
Entertaine thos
                     •
                   for gaine he not endures,
               Pish, swell and burst, I had rather with thy sword
               Be hew'd to peeces, then lead such a life,
               Out with it valiant si
                     •
                  , I hold you for
               A drawer vpon women, not on men,
               I will no more conceale your hollow heart,
               But e'ne report you as you are in truth.
            
            
               Hub.
               This is cal'd marriage, stop your mouth you whore.
            
            
               Wife.
               Thy mother was a whore if I be one.
            
            
               Enter SVBTLE.
            
               Hus.
               You know ther's companie in the house, sweet friend
               What haue you writ your letter?
            
            
               Sub.
               T'is done, deere friend, I haue made you stay too long
               I feare you'll be benighted.
            
            
               Husb.
               Fie, no, no,
               Madame &amp; sweetest wife farewell, God blesse vs,
               Make much of master Subtle heere my friend
               kisse her.
               Till my returne, which may be ee'n as't happens,
               According as my businesse hath successe.
               Exit.
            
            
               Subt.
               How will you passe the time, now fairest Mistresse.
            
            
               Wife.
               In troth I know not, wiues without their husbands
               Me thinks are lowring daies.
            
            
               Subt.
               Indeed some wiues
               Are like dead bodies in their Husbands absence.
            
            
               Wife.
               If any Wife be, I must needs be so
               That haue a Husband farre aboue all men,
               Vntainted with the humors others haue,
               A perfect man, and one that loues you truly,
               You see the charge he left of your good vsage.
            
            
               Subt.
               Push, hee's an Asse, I know him, a starke Asse.
               Of a most barbarous condition,
               False-hearted to his friend, rough vnto you,
               A most desembling and perfideous fellow,
               I care not if he heard me, this I know,
               And will make good vpon him with my sword
               Or any for him, for he will not fight.
            
            
               Wife.
               Fie seruant, you shew small ciuilitie
               And lesse humanitie, d'ee requi
                     •
                  e
               
                  
My husband
                     •
                   loue thus ill, or what 
                     ••
                  ee thinke
               Of mee, that you will vtter to my face
               Such harsh, vnfriendly, slanderous iniuries
               Euen of my Husband? Sir, forbeare I pray
               My eares, or your owne tongue, I am no hous-wife
               To heare my Husbands merrit thus deprau'd.
            
            
               Subt.
               His merrit is a halter by this light,
               You thinke hee's out of Towne now, no such matter
               But gone aside, and hath importun'd me
               To t
                     •
                  ie your chastitie.
            
            
               Wife.
               It cannot be,
               Alas he is as free from jealouzie,
               And euer was as confidence it selfe,
               I know he loues me to, too heartily
               To be suspitious, or to proue my truth.
            
            
               Subt.
               If I doe faine in ought, ne're may I purchase
               The grace I hope for, and faire Misteris
               If you haue any spirit or wit, or sence,
               You will be euen with such a wretched slaue,
               Heauen knowes I loue you, as the ayre I draw,
               Thinke but how finely you may cuckold him,
               And safely too, with me, who will report
               To him, that you are most inuincible,
               Your Chastitie not to be subdu'd by man.
            
            
               Wife.
               When you know, I'm a whore.
            
            
               Subt.
               A whore, fie, no,
               That you haue beene kind, or so, your whore doth liue
               In Pict-hatch, Turnebole-streete.
            
            
               Wife
               Your whore li
                     •
                  es there,
               Well Seruant leaue me to my selfe a while,
               Returne a none, but beare this hope away,
               T
                     •
                  shall be with you, if I at all do
                     •
                   stray.
               Exit. Subtle.
               Why heer's right wordly friendship, ye are well met;
               Oh men! what are you? why is our poore sexe
               Still made the di
                     •
                  grac't subiects, in these plaies?
               For vices, follie, and inconstancie?
               When were men look't into with such criticall eies
               Of obseruation, many would be found
               So full of grosse and base corruption,
               
                  
That none (vnlesse the Diuell himselfe turn'd writer)
               Could faine so badly, to expresse them truely;
               Some wiues that had a husband now like mine,
               Would yeeld their honors vp, to any man,
               Farre be it from my thoughts, oh let me stand,
               Thou God of marriage and chastitie,
               An honor to my sexe, no iniurie,
               Compell the vertue of my breast to yeeld,
               I'ts not reuenge for any wife, to s
                     •
                  aine
               The nuptiall bed, although she be yok't ill,
               Who fals, because her husband so hath done,
               Cures not his wound, but in her selfe makes one.
               Ex. Wife.
            
            Enter INGEN reading a letter, sits downe in a Chaire
and stampes with his foote: to him a Seruant.
            
               Ing.
               Who brought this Letter?
            
            
               Seru.
               A little Irish foot-boy, Sir, he staies without for an
answere.
            
            
               Ing.
               Bid him come in Lord.
               What deepe dissemblers are these females, all,
               How farre vnlike a friend, this Ladie vs'd me,
               And heere, how like one mad in loue, she writes:
               Enter MAID like an Irish foot-boy with a dart, and
gloues in hir pocket, and a handkercher.
               So blesse me Heauen, but thou art the prettiest boy
               That e're ran by a Horse, hast thou dwelt long
               With thy faire Mistris?
            
            
               Maid.
               I came but this morning, Sir.
            
            
               Ing.
               How fares thy Ladie, boy?
            
            
               Maid.
               Like to a turtle, that hath lost her mate,
               Drooping shee sits, her griefe Sir cannot speake,
               Had it a voice articulate, we should know
               How, and for what shee sufters; and perhaps,
               (But t'is vnlikely) giue her Comfort Sir,
               W
                     ••
                  ping shee sits, and all the sound comes from her,
               Is like the murmure of a siluer Brooke,
               Which her teares truely, would make there about her,
               
                  
Sate she in any hollow continent.
            
            
               Ing.
               Beleeue me boy▪ thou hast a passionate tong,
               Liue
                     •
                  y expression, or thy memorie
               Hath carried thy lesson well away,
               But wherefore mournes thy Ladie?
            
            
               Maid.
               Sir, you know,
               And would to God I did not know my selfe.
            
            
               Ing.
               Ah las, it cannot be for loue to me,
               When last I saw her shee reuil'd me (boy)
               With bitter'st words, and wish't me neuer more
               To approch her sight, and for my marriage, now
               I doe sustaine it, as a pennance, due
               To the desert, that made her bannish me.
            
            
               Maid.
               Sir, I dare sweare, she did presume, no words
               Nor dangers, had beene powerfull to restraine
               Your comming to her, when she gaue the charge—
               But are you married truely?
            
            
               Ing.
               Why my Boy?
               Dost think I mock my selfe, I sent her gloues.
            
            
               Maid.
               The gloues she ha's return'd you Sir by me,
               And praies you giue them to some other Ladie
               That you'll deceiue next, and be 
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  iur'd to.
               Sure you haue wrong'd her Sir, she bad me tell you,
               She ne're thought goodnesse dwelt in many men,
               But what there was of goodnesse in the world,
               Shee thought you had it all, but now shee sees
               The jewell she esteem'd is counterfeit
               That, you are but a common man, your selfe,
               A traitor to her, and her vertuous loue;
               That all men are betraiers and their breasts
               As full of dangerous gulphes, as is the S
                     ••
                  ,
               Where any woman thinking to finde Harb
                     •
                  r,
               Shee and her honor are praecipitated,
               And neuer to be brought with safetie off:
               Ahlas my haplesse Ladie, desolate,
               Distrest, forsaken Virgin.
            
            
               Ing.
               Sure this Boy
               Is of an excellent nature, who so newly
               
                  
Tane to her seruice, feeles his Mistresse griefe,
               As he 
                     •
                  nd they were old famili
                     •
                  r fri
                     •
                  nds,
               Why weep'st thou gentle L
                     •
                  d?
            
            
               Maid.
               Who hath one teare,
               And would not sau't from all occasions,
               From Brothers slaughters, and from mothers deaths
               To spend it heere, for my 
                     〈◊〉
                   Ladie;
               But Sir my Ladie did com
                     ••
                  und me begg
               To see your wife, that I may bare to her
               The sad report, what creature could make you
               Vntie the h
                     •
                  nd-fast plighted vnto her.
            
            Enter his Brother like a woman maskt. Ingen kisses her.
            
               Ingen.
               Wife, wife, come forth-now Gentle boy, be iudge
               If such a face as this being paid with scorne
               By her I did adore, had not full power
               To make me marrie.
            
            
               Maid.
               By the God of Loue,
               Shees a faire Creature, but faith should be fairer.
               My Ladie, Gentle Mistresse, one that thought
               Shee had some intrest in this Gentleman,
               (Who now is onelie yours) Commaunded m
                     •
                  
               
               To kisse your white hand, and to figh and weepe,
               And wish you that content she should haue had
               In the fr
                     •
                  ition of her Loue you hold,
               She 
                     •
                  ad me say, God giue you ioy, to both;
               Yet this withall (if ye were married)
               No one, her foot-steps euer more should mee
                     •
                  e,
               Nor see her face, but in a winding sheete.
            
            
               Brother.
               Ahlas poore Ladie, 'saith I pittie her,
               And, but to be i'th same state, could forgoe
               Any thing I possesse, to ease her woe.
            
            
               Maid.
               Loues blessing light vpon thy gentle soule,
               Men raile at women Mistris, bu
                     •
                  t is we
               Are false and cruell, ten times more vnkind,
               You are smoother farre, and of a softer mind:
               Sir, I haue one request more.
            
            
               Ing.
               Gentle Lad, It must be one of a strange-qualitie
               That I denie thee, both thy forme, and minde.
               
                  
Informe me that thy n
                     •
                  rture hath beene better,
               Than to betray thee to this present life.
            
            
               Maid.
               
                  
                     •
                  'is, that you would vouchsafe to entertaine me,
               My fee
                     •
                  e do tremble vnder me, to beare
               My bo
                     •
                  ie back vnto my vncouth Ladie,
               To assure her griefe; what heart so hard, would owe
               A tongue, to tell so sad a tale to her?
               Ahlas, I dare not looke vpon her eies,
               Where wronged loue, 
                     •
                  its like the Basilisque,
               And sure would kill me for my dire report,
               Or rather should not I appeare like death,
               holding vp his dart.
               When euery word I speak shot through her hart,
               More mortallie than his v
                     •
                  sparing dart.
            
            
               Brother.
               Let me speake for the Boy.
            
            
               Ing.
               To what end (loue)
               No, I will sue to him, to follow me,
               Introth I loue thy sweet condition,
               And may liue to i
                     •
                  forme thy Lady of thee;
               Come in drie, drie thine eies, respit thy woe:
               The effects of causes, crowne, or ouerthrow.
            
            
               Enter Lo. PROVD. Lo. 
               
                  •
               EESIM. WEL-TRI'D, Ma.
SELDOME, WIDD. BOVLD pin
                     •
                  ing in
a Ruffe, WIFE.
            
               Proud.
               S'light, what should be become of her, you sweare
she past not forth of do
                     •
                  es, and i'th house she is not?
            
            
               Widd.
               Did you not see her Princox?
               
            
            
               Proud.
               This same Bawd has brought her letters from
some yonger brother, and she is stole away.
            
            
               Bould.
               Bawd, I defie you, indeed your Lordship thinkes,
you may make Bawds of whom you please, i'le take my oath
vpon a booke, since I met her in the necessarie house i'th
morning, I ne're set eye on her.
            
            
               Grace
               Sh
                     •
                  e went not out of dores.
            
            
               P
                     •
                  oud
               Sure shee has an inuisible ring.
            
            
               Feesi
               M
                     •
                  rrie she's the honester woman, for some of their
ring are visible enough, the more shame for them, still say
I, let the pond at Islington be search't: goe to, there's more

haue drown'd themselues for loue this yeare then you are
aware of.
            
            
               Proud.
               Pish, you are a foole.
            
            
               Welt.
               S'hart call him foole againe.
            
            
               Feesi.
               By this light and I will, as soone as euer you haue
shew'd me the Swaggerers.
            
            
               Wife.
               Her clothes are all younder my Lord.
            
            
               Grace.
               And euen those same she had on to day.
            
            
               Proud.
               Madam where is your Husband?
            
            
               Wife.
               Rid into the Countrie.
            
            
               Feesi.
               O' my conscience, rid into France with your sister.
            
            
               Omnes.
               Away, away for shame.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why, I hope she is not the first Ladie that has run
away with other womens husbands.
            
            
               Welt.
               It may be shee's stolne out to see a play.
            
            
               Proud.
               Who should goe with her, man?
            
            
               Wid.
               Vpon my life you'll heare on her at Master Ingens
house, some loue past betwixt them, and we heard that he
was married to day, to another.
            
            
               Proud.
               S'hart, ile go see.
               Exit. Proudly.
            
            
               Welt.
               Come to the Swaggerers.
            
            Exeunt Feesi▪ Welt.
            
               Feesi.
               Mercy vpon me, a man or a—Lord now?
            
            
               Omnes.
               Heere's a quoile, with a Lord and his sister.
            
            
               Wid.
               
                  Princox, hast not thou pin'd in that Ruffe yet, ah!
how thou fumblest.
            
            
               Bou
                     •
                  d.
               Troth Madam, I was ne're brought vp to it, t'is
Chamber-maids work, and I haue euer liu'd Gentlewoman.
And beene vs'd accordingly.
            
            Exeunt.
         
         
            Actus tertius.
            Enter HVSBAND and SVBTLE.
            
            
               Subt.
               SHee's a rare wife beleeue it Sir, were all such,
               Wee neuer should haue false inheritors.
            
            
               Husb.
               Pish friend, there is no woman in the world
               Can hould out in the end, If youth, shape, wit,
               Met in one subiect, doe assault her aptlie,
               
                  
For fayling once, you must not faint but trie
               Another way, the path of womens minds
               Are crooked, and diuerse, they haue by-waies
               To leade you to the Pallace of their pleasures,
               And you must wooe discreetely; first obserue
               The disposition of her you attempt,
               If shee be sprightly, and heroicall,
               Possesse her that you are valiant, and haue spirit,
               Talke nothing but of beating euery man
               That is your hinderance, though you doe not doe it,
               Or dare not, t'is no matter. Be shee free
               And of a liberall soule, giue bounteously
               To all the seruants, let your angels flye
               About the roome, although you borrow'd 'em.
               If shee be wittie, so must your discourse
               Get wi
                     •
                  , what shift
                     •
                  so'ere you make for it,
               Though't cost you all your land, and then a song
               Or two is not amisse, although you buy 'em,
               There's many in the Towne will furnish you.
            
            
               Subt.
               But still I tell you, you must vse her roughly,
               Bea
                     •
                  e her face black and blew, take all her cloth's
               And giue them to some Punke, this will be ground
               For me to worke vpon.
            
            
               Husb.
               All this I haue done.
               I 
                     〈…〉
                   her now, as bare, that should I die,
               Her fo
                     •
                  tune (ô my conscience) would be
               To marrie some Tobacco-man, shee has nothing
               Bu
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   old black-woorke wastco
                     •
                  e, which would serue
               Exceeding wel to 
                     •
                  it i'th shop and light
               Pipes for the lowzie Footmen (and sweete friend)
               First heere's a jewell to present her, then
               Heere is a So
                     •
                  net writ against my selfe,
               Which as thine owne thou shalt accost her with,
               Farew
                     •
                  ll and happie successe attend thee.
               Exit.
            
            
               Subt.
               Ha, ha, ha.
               [he read
                     •
                  .
               Faire
                     •
                  d, still wilt thou be true
               To a man so false to thee?
               Did be le
                     •
                  d a Husbands due,
               
                  
Thou did'st owe him loyalti
                     •
                  ;
               But will curses, wants and blowes
               Breed no change in thy white soule
                     •
                  
               
               Be not a foole to thy first vow
                     •
                  s,
               Since his breach, doth thy faith controle,
               No be
                     •
                  utie else, could be so chast,
               Thinke not thou honour'st women then,
               Since by thy co
                     •
                  science, all disgra
                     •
                  't,
               Are rob'd of the deare loues of men;
               Then grant me my desire that vow to proue
               A reall husband, his adul
                     •
                  erate loue.
               Tooke euer man more paines to be a Cuckold?
               Oh! monstrous age where men themselues we see,
               Studie and pay for their owne infamie.
               Exit.
            
            Enter INGEN, MAID, PROVDLY, BROTHER
like a woman, swords drawen.
            
               Proud.
               Giue me my sister, Ile haue her forth thy heart.
            
            
               Ing.
               No earthly Lord can pull her out of that,
               Till he haue pluckt my heart first out, my Lord
               Wer't not inhospitable, I could wrong you heere
               In mine owne house▪ I am so full of woe,
               For your lost sister that by all my ioyes
               Hop't for in her, my heart weepes teares of bloud,
               A whiter virgine, and a worthier,
               Had ne're creation: L
                        •
                     da's Swan was black
               To her virginitie, and immaculate thoughts.
            
            
               Proud.
               Where hast thou hid her? giue her me againe,
               For by the God of vengeance, be she lost,
               The female hate shall spring betwixt our names,
               Shall neuer die, while one of either house
               Suruiues, our children shall at seuen yeares olde
               Strike kniues in one another.
            
            
               Ing.
               Let Hell gape
               And take me quick, if I know where she is,
               But am so charg'd with sorrow for her losse,
               Being 
                     •
                  ne cause of it (as no doubt I am)
               That I had rather 
                     •
                  al vpon my sword
               [Offering to kill himselfe
               Then breath a minute longer.
            
            
               Broth.
               Oh sir! hold.
            
            
               
               Proud.
               Thou shalt not neede, I haue a sword to b
                     •
                  the
               In thy false blood, inhumane murderer.
            
            
               Maid.
               Good Sir be pacified, i'le goe, i'le run
               Many a mile to finde your sister out;
               Shee neuer was so desperate of grace,
               By violence to rob her selfe of life,
               And so her soule in danger; comfort Sir,
               Shee's but retir'd somewhere on my life.
            
            
               Ing.
               Preethee let me alone—
               [To his Brother.
               Doe I stand to defend that wretched life
               That is in doubt of hers, heere worthy Lord,
               Behold a breast, fram'd of thy sisters loue,
               Hew it, for thou shalt strike but on a stock,
               Since she is gone that was the cause it liu'd.
            
            
               Proud.
               Out false dissembler, are not married?
            
            
               Ing.
               No, behold, it is my yonger brother drest,
               Plucks off his 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               A man, no woman, that hath guld the world,
               Intended for a happier euent
               Than this that follow'd, that she now is gone,
               Oh fond experiments of simple man,
               Foole to thy fate, since all thy project man't
               But mirth, is now conuerted vnto death.
            
            
               Maid.
               Oh doe not burst me joy, that modestie
               aside.
               Would let me show my selfe to finish all.
            
            
               Proud.
               Nay, then thou hast my sister somewhere villain,
               T'is plaine now, thou wilt steale thy marriage,
               Shee is no match for thee, assure thy selfe.
               If all the law in England, or my friends
               Can crosse it, t
                     •
                  shall not be.
            
            
               Ing.
               Would t'were so well,
               And that I knew the Ladie to be safe.
               Giue me no ill words; Sir, this Boy and I
               Will wander like to Pilgrimes, till we finde her:
               If you doe loue her as you talke, doe so:
               The loue or griefe that is exprest in words,
               Is sleight and easie, t'is but shallow woe
               That makes a noise, deep'st waters stillest goe;
               I loue her better then thy parents did,
               
                  
Which is beyond a Brother.
            
            
               Proud.
               Slaue, thou liest.
            
            
               Ing.
               Z'oones.
            
            [about to strike
            
               Broth.
               Kill him.
            
            
               Maid.
               Oh hold; Sir, you dishonour much your brother,
               To counsaile him 'gainst hospitalitie,
               To strike in his owne house.
            
            
               Ing.
               You, Lord insolent, I will fight with you,
               Take this, as a challenge, and set your time.
            
            
               Proud.
               To morrow morning Ingen,
               
               T'is that I couet, and prouoke thee for.
            
            
               Bro.
               Wil you not strike him now?
            
            
               Ing.
               No, my good Boy
               Is both discreete and just in his aduise,
               Thy glories are to last but for a day;
               Giue me thy hand, to morrow morning thou shalt be no Lo.
            
            
               Proud.
               To morrow noone, thou shalt not be at all.
            
            
               Ing.
               Pish, why should you thinke so, haue not I armes▪
               
               A soule as bold as yours, a sword as true:
               I doe not thinke your Honor in the field
               Without your Lordships liueries will haue oddes.
            
            
               Pr.
               Farewell, and lets haue no excuses, pray.
               Exit. Pr.
            
            
               Ing.
               I warrant you, pray say your prayers to night,
               And bring no ink-horne w
                     •
                  ee, to set your hand to
               A satisfactorie recantation.
               Exit.
            
            
               Maid.
               Oh wretched Maid, whose sword can I pray for?
               But by the others losse, I must find death,
               Oh odious brother, if he kill my loue,
               Oh bloodie Loue, if he should kill my brother;
               Dispaire on both sides of my discontent,
               Tel's me no safetie rests but to preuent.
               Exit.
            
            Enter WIDDOVV and BOVLD like Princox.
            
            
               Wid.
               What's a clock Princox?
               
            
            
               Bould.
               Bed-time an't please you Madame.
            
            
               Wild.
               Come, vndresse me, would God had made me a man.
            
            
               Bould.
               Why, Madame?
            
            
               Wid.
               Because I would haue beene in bed as soone as they,
wee are so long vnpinning and vnlacing.
            
            
               Bou.
               Yet many of vs Madame are quickly vndone sometime,
but heerein we haue the aduantage of men, though 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  
they can be a bed sooner than we, i'ts a great while when
they are a bed e're they can get vp.
            
            
               Wid.
               Indeed if they be well laid Princox, one cannot get
them vp againe in hast.
            
            
               Bould.
               Oh God Madame, how meane you that, I hope
you know, ill things taken into a Gentlewomans ea
                     •
                  es, are
the quick corrupters of maiden modestie, I would be loath
to continue in any seruice vnfit for my virgin estate, or where
the world should take any notice of light behauiour in the
Ladie I follow: for Madame, the maine point of chastitie in
a Ladie, is to build the rock of a good opinion amongst the
people by circumstances, and a faire shew she must make, Si,
non caste, tamen ca
                        •
                     te Madame, and though wit be a wanton
Madame: yet I beseech your Lady-ship for your owne credit
and mine, let the bridle of judgement be alwaies in the
chaps of it to giue it head, or restraine it, according as time
and place shall be conuenient.
            
            
               Wid.
               Precise and learned Princox, dost not thou goe to
Black-fryers.
            
            
               Bould.
               Most frequently Madame, vnworthy vessell that
I am to partake or retaine any of the delicious dew, that is
there distilled.
            
            
               Wid.
               But why shouldst thou aske me what I meant e'ne
now, I tell thee there's nothing vtter'd that carries a double
sence, one good, one bad, but if the hearer applie it to the
worst, the fault lies in his or her corrupt vnderstanding, not
in the speaker, for to answere your lattine: prauis omnia pra
                     
                        •
                     a,
beleiue me wench, if ill come into my fancie, I will purge
it by speech▪ the lesse will remaine within: a pox of these
nise mouth'd creatures, I haue seen a norrow paire of lips vtter
as broad a taile, as can be bought for money; Indeed an
ill tale vnutter'd, is like a maggot in a nut, it spoiles the
whitest kernell.
            
            
               Bould.
               You speake most intellegently Madame.
            
            
               Wid.
               Ha'
                     •
                  t not done yet? thou art an old fumbler, I perceiue
me thinkes thou doest not doe things like a woman.
            
            
               Bould.
               Madame, I doe my endeauour, and the best can
doe no more, they that could doe better, it may be would

not, and then t'were all one, but rather then be a burthen
to your Lady-ship, I protest sincerely, I would beg my bre
                     •
                  d,
therefore I beseech you Madame to hold me excus
                     •
                  d, and
let my good will stand for the action.
            
            
               Wid.
               Let thy good will stand for the action? If good will
would doe it, there's many a Ladie in this Land would be
content with her old Lord, and thou canst not be a burthen
to me, without thou lie vpon me, and that were preposterous
in thy sexe; take no exceptions at what I say, remember you
said stand e'ne-now, there was a word for one of your coate
indeede.
            
            
               Bould.
               I sweat Madame, you are verie merrie, God send
you good luck, ha's your Ladyship no waters, that you vse at
bed-time?
            
            
               Wid.
               No introth, Princox.
               
            
            
               Bould.
               No Complexion?
            
            
               Wid.
               None but mine own I sweare, did'st thou euer vse any?
            
            
               Bould.
               No indeede Madame: now and then a peece of
scarlet, or so; a little white and red Cerusse; but in troth Madame,
I haue an excellent receipt for a night masque, as euer
you heard.
            
            
               Wid.
               What is it?
            
            
               Bould.
               Bores grease one ounce, Iordane Almouds blanch't
and ground a quarterne, red Rose-water, halfe a pint,
Mares vrine, newly couer'd, halfe a score drops.
            
            
               Wid.
               Fough, no more of thy medicine, if thou lou'st me,
few of our Knights errant, when they meete a faire Ladie
errant, in a morning, would thinke her face had lien so plaster'd
all night: thou hast had some Apothecarie to thy sweet
heart: but leauing this face physick, for (by my troth) it may
make others haue good ones; but it makes me make a scuruie
one. Which of all the Gallants in the Towne would'st
thou make a husband of, if thou might'st haue him for thy
chusing?
            
            
               Bould.
               In troth Madame, I but you'll say I speake blindly,
but let my loue stand a side.
            
            
               Wid.
               I think it not fit indeede your loue should stand in the
middle.
            
            
               Boul.
               I say Master Bould; oh, do but marke him Madame,

his leg, his hand, his bodie, &amp; all his members standin print.
            
            
               Wid.
               Out vpon thee Princox; no, me thinkes Wel-trid
                        •
                     
                   a
handsome fellow, I like not these starch'
                     •
                   Gallants: masculine
faces, and masculine g
                     •
                  stures please me best.
            
            
               Bould.
               How like you Master P
                        •
                     rt?
               
            
            
               Wid.
               
                  
                     •
                  ie vpon him, when he is in his skarlet clothes, he
lookes like man of waxe, and I had as leue haue a dogge a
waxe, I do not thinke but he lies in a case a nights, he walkes
as if he were made of gyues, as if nature had wrought him in
a frame, I haue seene him sit discontented a whole play, because
one of the purles of his band was fallen (out of his
reach) to order againe.
            
            
               Bould.
               Why? Bould Madame is cleane contrarie.
            
            
               Wid.
               I but that's as ill, each extreame, is a like vi
                     •
                  ious; his
carefull carelesnesse is his stud
                     •
                  e, he spends as much time to
make himselfe sloue
                     •
                  ly, as the other to be spruse, his garters
hang euer on the calues of his legs, his dublet vnbutten'd,
and his points vntrust, his haire in's eyes like a drunkard, and
his hat worne on his hinder part of his head, as if he car'd
more for his memorie, than his wit: makes him looke as if he
were distracted; Princox, I would haue you lie with me, I
doe not loue to lie alone.
            
            
               Bould.
               With all my heart Madame.
            
            
               Wid.
               Are you cleane skind?
            
            
               Bould.
               Cleane skind Madame
                     •
                   there's a question, do you
thinke I haue the itch? I am an English-woman, I protest, I
scorne the motion.
            
            
               Wid.
               Nay prithee Princox be not angrie, it's a signe of honestie
I can tell you.
            
            
               Bould.
               Faith Madam I thinke ti's but simple honestie that
dwels at the signe of me scab.
            
            
               Wid.
               Well, well, come to bed, and wee
                     •
                  le talke further of
all these matters.
               Exit.
            
            
               Bould.
               Fortune, I thanke thee, I will owe thee eies
               For this good turne, now is shee mine indeede,
               Thou hast giuen me that successe my project hop'd
               Of, false disguise that hast beene true to me,
               And now be Bould, that thou ma
                     •
                  'st welcome be.
               Exit.
            
            
               
Enter WHOORE-BANG, BOTS, TEARE-CHOPS,
SPIL-BLOVD, and DRAWER: seuerall
patches on their faces.
            
               Tear.
               Dam-me, we will haue more wine, sirrha, or wee'l
downe into the Seller, and drowne thee in a Burt of Malmesey,
and he wall the Hogs-heads in peeces.
            
            
               Whoore.
               Hang him rogue, shall he die as honorably as the
Duke of Clarence; by this flesh lets haue wine, or I will cut
thy head off, haue it rosted and eaten in Pie-corner next
Bartholmew-tide.
            
            
               Draw.
               Gentlemen, I beseech you consider where you
are, Turne-bole streete, a ciuill place, do not disturbe a number
a poore Gentlewomen, Master Whoore-band, Ms: Bots,
Ma: Teare-chops, and Ma: Spill-bloud the Watch are abroad.
            
            
               Spilb.
               The Watch? why you rogue, are not we Kings of
Turne-bole?
            
            
               Draw.
               Yes marrie are yee, Sir, for my part, if you'l be
quiet, ile haue a signe made of yee, and it shall be cal'd the
foure Kings of Turne bole.
            
            
               Bots.
               Will you fetch vs wine?
            
            
               Whoore.
               And a whoore (sirrah)
            
            
               Draw.
               Why what d'ee thinke of me, am I an Infidell, a
Turke, a Pagan, a Sarazan, I haue beene at Besse Turnups,
and she sweares all the Gentlewomen went to see a Play at
the Fortune, and are not come in yet, and she beleeues they
sup with the Players.
            
            
               Tear.
               Dam-me, we must kill all those rogues, we shall neuer
keepe a whore honest for them.
            
            
               Bots.
               Goe your waies, sirrha, wee'l haue but a gallon a
peice, and an ounce of Tobacco.
            
            
               Draw.
               I beseech you, let it be but pottles.
            
            
               Spilb.
               S'hart you rogne?
            
            Exit. Draw.
            Enter WEL-TRI'D and FEE-SIMPLE.
            
            
               Whoore.
               Master Well-tri'd, welcome as my soule.
            
            Enter DRAWER with Wine, Plate, and Tobacco.
            
               Bots.
               Noble Lad, how do'st thou?
            
            
               Spilb.
               As welcome, as the Tobacco and the Wine Boy.
            
            
               Tear.
               Dam-me thou art.
            
            
               
               Fees.
               Blesse mee (saue you Gent) They haue not one
face among 'em. I could wish my selfe well from them, I
would I had put out something vpon my returne, I had as
leue be at the Barmuthoes.
               
            
            
               Welt.
               Pray welcome this Gentleman.
            
            
               Spilb.
               Is he valiant?
            
            
               Welt.
               Faith hee's a little faulty that way: somewhat of a
bashfull and backward nature, yet I haue brought him
amongst you, because he hath a great desire to be flesh'd.
            
            
               Fees.
               Yes faith Sir, I haue a great desire to be flesh'd:
now Mr. Well-tri'd said, hee would bring mee to the onely
flesh-mongers in the towne.
            
            
               Welt.
               Sir, he cannot endure the sight of steele.
            
            
               Whor.
               Not steele? zoones.
            
            Claps his Sword 
                  •
               re the Table.
            
               Fees.
               Now I am going.
            
            
               Bot.
               Here's to you sir, i'le fetch you again with a cup of sack.
            
            
               Fees.
               I pledge you sir, and begin to you in a cup of Claret:
            
            
               Welt.
               Harke you my Lo: what will you say, if I make you
beate all these out of the roome?
            
            
               Fees.
               What will I say? why I say it is impossible, ti's not is
mortall man.
            
            
               Welt.
               Well drinke apace, if any braue you out braue him,
Ile second you, they are a Companie of cowards beleeue me.
            
            
               Feesi.
               By this light I would they were els, if I thought so, I
would be vpon the Iack of one of 'em instantly, that same
litle Dame me, but Mr. Wel-tri'd if they be not verie valiant
or dare not fight! how come they by such Cuts and gashes,
and such broken faces?
            
            
               Wel.
               Why their whores strike 'em with Cans, and glasses,
and quart pots, if they haue nothing by 'em, they strike
'em with the Poxe, and you know that will lay ones nose as
flat as a basket hilt Dagger.
            
            
               Fee.
               Well let me alone.
            
            
               Tear.
               This bullie dares not drink.
            
            
               Fee.
               Dare I not Sir.
            
            
               Welt.
               Well said, speake to him man.
            
            
               Fee.
               You had best trie me Sir.
            
            
               Spilb.
               Wee fouer will drinke foure healths to foure of the
seauen deadly sines, Pride, Drunkennesse, wrath &amp; Leeherie.
            
            
               Fee.
               I'le pledge 'em, and I thanke you, I know 'em all,
heeres one.
            
            
               
               Wb.
               Which of the sinnes?
            
            
               Fee.
               By my troth e'ne to Pride.
            
            
               Wel.
               Why well said, and in this doe not you only pledge
your Mistris health, but all the womens in the world.
            
            
               Fee.
               So now, this little Cup to Wrath, because he and I
are strangers.
            
            
               Tear.
               Braue boy, Dame me he shall be a Rorer.
            
            
               Fee.
               Dame me, I will be a rorer, or't shall cost me a fall.
            
            
               Botts.
               The next place that falls, pray let him haue it.
            
            
               Fee.
               Well, I haue two of my healths to drinke yet, Lecherie
and Drunkennesse which en'e shall goe together.
            
            
               Welt.
               Why how now my Lord, a Morralist?
            
            
               Botts.
               Dame mee, art thou a Lo: what vertues hast thou?
            
            
               Fee.
               Vertues? enough to keepe ere a Dame me Company
in England, me thinkes you should thinke it vertue enough
to be a Lord.
            
            
               Whore.
               Will not you pledg these healths? wee'le haue no
obseruers.
            
            
               Welt
               Why, Mounser Whore-bang? I am no play maker,
and for pledging your healths, I loue none of the foure,
you drank to so well.
            
            
               Spilb.
               Zoones you shall pledge me this.
            
            
               Welt.
               Shall I?
            
            
               Fee.
               Whats the matter, do'st heere Maister Wel-trid, vse
thine owne discretion, if thou wilt not pledge him, say so?
and let me see, if er'e a Dame me of 'em all, will force thee.
            
            
               Spilb.
               Puffe, will your Lordship take anie Tobacco? you
Lord with the white face?
            
            
               Botts.
               Heart he cannot put it through his nose.
            
            
               Fee.
               Faith you haue neare a nose to put it through, dee heart
blow your face sirra.
            
            
               Tear.
               Youle pledge me Sir?
            
            
               Wilt.
               Indeede I will not.
            
            
               Tear.
               Dame me hee shall not then.
            
            
               Tear.
               Lord, vse your owne words, Dame me is mine,
               I am knowne by it all the towne o're, d'ee heare?
            
            
               Fee.
               It is as free for mee as you, d'ee here Patch?
            
            
               Tear.
               I haue paid more for't.
            
            
               Welt.
               Nay Ile beare him witnesse in 
                     〈◊〉
                   truth, his soule lies
fort my Lord.
            
            
               Spilb.
               
                  Wel-tru'd, you are growne proud since you got

good Clothes, and haue follow'd your Lord.
            
            Strikes, &amp; they scuffle.
            
               Whoore.
               I haue knowne you lowzie, Wel trid,
               
            
            
               Welt.
               Rorer you lie.
            
            Draw and fight, throw pot
                  •
                and stooles.
            
               Dr.
               Oh Iesu.
            
            
               All Sw.
               Zoones cleaue or be cleft: pell mell, sl
                     •
                  sh armes
and legges.
            
            
               Fee.
               Hart let me alone with 'em.
            
            Breake off.
            
               Welt.
               Why now thou art a worthy wight, indeed a Lord
a Lorne.
            
            
               Fee
               I am a mad man, looke is not that one of their heads?
            
            
               Welt.
               Fie no my Lord.
            
            
               Fee.
               Dam me but tis, I would not wish you to crosse me
a purpose, if you haue anie thing to say to me, so, I am readie.
            
            
               Welt.
               Oh braue Lord, manie a rorer thus is made by wine:
come it is one of their heads my Lord.
            
            
               Fee.
               Why so then, I will haue my 
                     •
                  umour, if you loue me,
let's goe breake windowes somewhere.
            
            
               Welt.
               Drawer, take your plate, for the reckoning there's
some of their cloakes: I will be no shot-log to such.
            
            
               Draw.
               Gods blessing o'your heart, for thus ridding the
house of them.
            
            Exeunt.
         
         
            Actus quarti Scaena prima.
            Enter WIDDOVV vndrest, a sword in her hand, and
BOVLD in his sh
                  ••
               t, as started from bed.
            
               Wid.
               VN
                     •
                  iuill man, if I should take thy I 
                     •
                  e,
               It were not to be weigh'd with thy attempt:
               Thou hast for euer lost mee.
            
            
               Bould.
               Maddam▪ why?
               Can loue beget losse? Doe I couet you
               Vnlawfully? Am I an vnfit man.
               To make an husband of? Send for a Priest,
               First consumma
                     •
                  e the match, and then to bed
               Without more trouble.
            
            
               Wid.
               No, I will not doe't.
            
            
               Bould.
               Why you confest to mee as you'r Gentlewoman,
               I was the man your heart 
                     •
                  id most affect:
               That you did doa
                     •
                  e vpon my minde and body.
            
            
               
               Wid.
               So, by the sacred and inuiolate knot
               Of marriage, I doe, but will not wed thee.
            
            
               Bould.
               Why yet inioy me now. Consider Lady,
               That little, but blest time, I was in bed,
               Although I lay as by my sisters side,
               The world is apt to censure otherwise:
               So 'tis necessitie that wee marry now.
            
            
               Wid.
               Pish, I regard not (at a straw) the world:
               Fame from the tongues of men doth iniury
               Oftner then Iustice▪ and as conscience
               Onely makes guilty persons, not report:
               (For shew we cleare as springs vnto the world,
               If our owne knowledge doe not make vs so,
               That is no satisfaction to our selues▪)
               So stand wee ne're so leprous to mens eye,
               It cannot hurt hart-knowne integritie.
               You haue trusted to that fond opinion,
               This is the way to haue a widdow-hood,
               By getting to her bed: Ahlas young man,
               Should'st thou thy selfe tell thy companions
               Thou hadst dishonour'd mee (as you men haue tongues
               Forked and venom'd 'gainst our subiect sexe)
               It should not moue me, that know 'tis not so:
               Therefore depart, Truth be my vertuous shield.
            
            
               Bould.
               Few widdowes would doe thus.
            
            
               Wid.
               All modest, would.
            
            
               Bould.
               To be in bed and in possession
               Euen of the marke I aim'd at, and goe off
               Foild and disgrac't, come, come, you'll laugh at me
               Behind my back, publish I wanted spirit,
               And mock me to the Ladies, call me childe,
               Say you denide me but to trie the heate
               And zeale of my affection toward you,
               Then clap't vp with arime, as for example.
               Hee coldly loues, retires, for one vaine triall,
               For wee are yeelding, when we make deniall.
            
            
               Wid.
               Seruant I make no question, from this time
               You'll hold a more reuerent opinion
               
                  
Of some that weare long coates, and tis my pride,
               To assure you that there are amongst vs good:
               And with this continencie, if you goe away,
               I'le be so farre from thinking it defect,
               That I will hold you worthiest of men.
            
            
               Bould.
               S'hart, I am Tantalus, my long'd for fruit
               Bobs at my lips, yet still it shrinks from me.
               Haue not I that, which men say neuer failes
               To o'recome any? oportunitie?
               Come, come, I am too cold in my assault.
               By all the vertues, that yet euer were
               In man, or woman, I with reuerence
               Doe loue thee Ladie, but will be no foole
               To let occasion slip, her fore-top from me.
            
            
               Wid.
               You will faile this way to, vpon my knees
               I doe desire thee to preserue thy vertues,
               And with my teares my honor; t'is as bad
               To loose our worths to them, or to deceaue
               Who haue held worthy opinions of vs,
               As to betray trust: all this I implore
               For thine owne sake, not mine, as for my selfe,
               If thou bee'st violent, by this stupid night,
               And all the mischiefes her darke wombe hath bred,
               I'le raise the house, I'le crie a rape.
            
            
               Bo.
               I hope you will not hang me, that were murther Ladie,
               A greater sinne, then lying with me sure.
            
            
               Wid.
               Come, flatter not your selfe with argument,
               I will exclaime; the law hangs you, not I,
               Or if I did, I had rather farre confound
               The deerest bodie in the world to me,
               Then that, that bodie, should confound my soule.
            
            
               Bould.
               Your soule, ahlas Mistresse, are you so fond
               To thinke her generall destruction
               Can be procur'd by such a naturall act,
               Which beasts are borne to and haue priuiledge in?
               Fie, fiie, if this could be, farre happier
               Are sensitiue soules in their creation
               Than man the prince of creatures, thinke you Heauen
               
                  
Regards such mortall deeds, or punisheth
               Those acts, for which he hath ordained vs?
            
            
               Wid.
               You argue like an Atheist, man is neuer
               The prince of creatures, as you call him now,
               But in his reason, faile that, he is worse
               Than Horse or Dog, or beasts of wildernesse,
               And tis that reason teacheth vs to doe
               Our actions vnlike them: then that which you
               Termed in them a priuiledge beyond vs,
               The basenesse of their being doth expresse,
               Compar'd to ours, Horses, Buls, and Swine,
               Doe leape their Dams, because man does not so,
               Shall we conclude his making happilesse?
            
            
               Bould.
               You put me downe, yet will not put me downe,
               I am too gentle, some of you I haue heard,
               Loue not these words but force, to haue it done
               As they sing prick-song, e'ne at the first sight.
            
            
               Wid.
               Go too, keep off, by Heauen and Earth, i'le call else.
            
            
               Bould
               How if no bodie heare you?
            
            
               Wid.
               If they doe not,
               I'le kill you with mine owne hand, neuer stare,
               Or failing that fall on this sword my selfe.
            
            
               Bould.
               Oh widdow wonderfull, if thou bee'st not honest.
               Now God forgiue my mother and my sisters.
               Thinke but how finely Madam vndiscouer'd
               For euer you and I, might liue all day your Gentlewoman
               To doe you seruice, but all night your man
               To doe you seruice, newnesse of the trick,
               If nothing else might stirre ye.
            
            
               Wid.
               T'is a stale one
               And was done in the Fleete ten yeares agoe,
               Will you begon? the doore is open for you.
            
            
               Bould.
               Let me but tarrie till the morning Madam,
               To send for clothes, shall I goe naked home.
            
            
               Wid.
               T'is best time now, it is but one a clock,
               And you may goe vnseene, I sweare by Heauen,
               I would spend all the night to sit and talke w'ee,
               If I durst trust you, I doe loue you so,
               
                  
My bloud forsakes my heart now you depart.
            
            
               Bould.
               S'hart, will you marrie me heereafter then?
            
            
               Wid.
               No, you are too yong, and I am much too old;
               I and vnworthy, and the world will say,
               We married not for loue, good morrow seruant.
               Ex. Wid.
            
            
               Bould.
               Why so? these women are the erranst Iuglers in
the World, the wry-leg'd fellow is an Asse to 'em. Well I
Musique.
must haue this wddow, what e're come on't: Faith she has
turn'd me out of her seruice verie barely, harke, whats heere,
musique.
            
            Enter SVBTLE with a paper, and his BOY with a cloake.
            
               Subt.
               Rise Ladie Mistresse, rise:
               The night hath tedious beene,
               No sleepe hath fallen into my eies,
               Nor slumbers made me sinne.
               Is not she a Saint then say,
               Thought of whom keepes sinne away?
               Rise Madame, rise and giue me light,
               Whom darkenesse still will couer.
               And ignorance darker than night,
               Till thou smile on thy louer;
               All want day 
                     〈◊〉
                   thy beautie rise,
               For the grate morne breakes from thine eies.
               Now sing it sirrha.
            
            [The Song sung by the Boy.
            
            
               Subt.
               S'foote, who's this? yong Master Bould? God saue
you, you are an earely stirrer.
            
            
               Bould.
               You say true Master Subtle, I haue beene earely
vp, but as God helpe me, I was neuer the neere.
            
            
               Subt.
               Where haue you beene Sir?
            
            
               Bould.
               What's that to you Sir? at a womans labour.
            
            
               Subt.
               Very good: I neare tooke you for a man Mid-wife
before.
            
            
               Bould.
               The troth is, I haue beene vp all night at dice, &amp;
lost my clothes, good morrow Master Subtle, pray God the
Watch be broke vp: I thanke you for my Musique:
               Exit:
            
            
               Subt:
               Tis palpable by this aire, her husband and being abroad,
Bould has layen with her, and is now con
                     •••
                  'd out of doores.
Is this the Ladie Perfect with a poxe? The truth is, her vertuous

chastitie, began to make me make a myracle of her,
still holding out to me, notwithstanding her husbands most
barbarous vsage of her, but now indeede t'is no maruaile
since another possesses her. Well Madame, Ile go finde out
your Cuckold, ile be reueng'd on you and tell a tale
Shall tickle him, this is a cheate in loue,
Not to be borne, another to beguile
Me of the game, I plaid for all this while.
               Exit.
            
            Enter WELTRI'D, and BOVLD puting on his doublet,
FEE-SIMPLE on a bed, as in Bould's chamber.
            
               Welt.
               You see, we made bould with your lodging, indeed,
I did assure my selfe, you were fast for this night.
            
            
               Bo.
               But how the Deuill came this foole in your companie?
            
            
               Welt.
               S'foote man, I carried him last night among the
Rorers, to flesh him, and by this light he got drunke, and
beate e'm all.
            
            
               Bould.
               Why then he can endure the sight of a drawne
sword now?
            
            
               Welt.
               Oh God Sir, I thinke in my conscience, he will eate
steele shortlie, I know not how his conuersion will hold
after this sleepe, but in an houre or two (last night) he was
growne such a little dam-me, that I protest, I was afraid of
the spirit, that I my selfe had rais'd in him: but this other
matter of your expulsion thus mads me to the heart; Were
you in bed with her?
            
            
               Bould.
               In bed by Heauen.
            
            
               Welt.
               I'le 
                     •
                  e hang'd, if you were not busie to soone, you
should haue let her slept first.
            
            
               Bould.
               Z'oones man, she put her hands to my breasts and
swore I was no maid, now I being eager to proue her words
true, tooke that hint, and would violently haue thrust her
hand lower, when her thought being swifter then my
strength, made her no sooner imagine that she was betrai'd,
but she leapes out of the bed, whips me downe a sword that
hung by, and as, if fortitude and justice had met to assist
her, spight of all argument faire or fowle she forc't me away.
            
            
               Welt.
               But is't possible thou should'st haue no more wit,
would'st thou come away vpon any tearmes, but sure ones,

hauing night, her chamber and her selfe naked in thine
armes? By that light, if I had a sonne of 
                     •
                  4 whom I had
help 't thus farre, that had seru'd me so, I would breech him.
            
            
               Bould.
               S'hart, what would you haue me done?
            
            
               Welt.
               Haue done? done, done twice at least.
            
            
               Bould.
               Haue plaid Tarquin and rauish't her.
            
            
               Welt.
               Pish, Tarquin was a block-head, if he had had any
wit and could haue spoke, Lucr
                        •
                     ce had neuer been rauished,
she would haue yeelded, I warrant thee, &amp; so wil any woman
            
            
               Bould.
               I was such an erronious heretique to loue, and
women, as thou art, till now.
            
            
               Welt.
               God's pretious, it makes me mad, when I thinke
on't: was there euer such an obsur'd trick? now will she abuse
thee horriblie, say thou art a faint-hearted fellow, a
milk-sop and I know not what, as indeede thou art.
            
            
               Bould.
               Z'oones, would you had beene in my place.
            
            
               Welt.
               Z'oones, I would I had, I would haue so jumbl'd her
honestie: would'st thou be held out at staues end with words?
dost not thou know a widdow's a weake vessell, and is easily
cast if you close.
            
            
               Bould.
               
                  Weltri'd, you deale vnfriendly.
            
            
               Welt.
               By this light I shal blush to be seen in thy companie.
            
            
               Bould.
               Pray leaue my chamber.
            
            
               Welt.
               Poxe vpon your chamber,
               I care not for your chamber, nor your selfe
               More than you care for me.
            
            
               Bo.
               S'blood I as little for you.
            
            
               Welt.
               Why fare you well.
            
            
               Bo.
               Why, fare-well you. Weltri'd, I prithee stay,
               Thou know'st I loue thee.
            
            
               Welt.
               S'hart, I loue you as well; but for my spleene, or
choller I thinke, I haue as much as you.
            
            
               Bo.
               Well friend, this is the businesse you must doe for me,
               Repaire vnto the widdow, where giue out,
               To morrow morne, I shall be married,
               Inuite her to the wedding, I haue a trick,
               To put vpon this Lord to, whom I made
               My instrument to preferre me.
            
            
               Welt.
               What shall follow,
               
                  
I will not aske, because I meane to see't.
               The 
                     •
                  ars 'twixt friends, still keeps their friendship sweet.
               Ex.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why Weltri'd, you rogue, whats that a vision?
            
            
               Bould.
               Why how now my Lord? who do you call rogue?
the Gentleman you name is my friend, if you were wise I
should be angrie.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Angrie with me? why dam me Sir, and you be;
               Cut with your sword, it is not with me I tell you
               As it was yesterday, I am flesh
                     •
                  man, I.
               Haue you any thing to say to me?
            
            
               Bould.
               Nothing but this, how many doe you thinke,
you haue slaine last night?
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why fiue, I neuer kill lesse.
            
            
               Bould.
               There was but foure: my Lord, you had best prouide
your selfe and begon, three you haue slaine starke dead.
            
            
               Feesi.
               You jest.
            
            
               Bould.
               T'is most true, Weltri'd is fled.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why let the Rorers meddle with me another time,
as for flying, I scorne it, I kild 'em like a man; when did you
euer see a Lord hang for any thing? we may kill whom we
list, marry my conscience p
                     •
                  icks me; ah plague a this drinke,
what things it makes vs doe, I doe no more remember this
now than a puppie-dogge.
               Oh bloodie Lord that art bedawb'd with gore,
               Vaine world adiew, for I will rore no more.
            
            
               Bould
               Nay stay my Lord, I did but trie the tendernesse
of your conscience, all this is nothing so, but to sweeten the
tale (I haue for you) I foretold you this fain'd mischance.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Is it a tale belonging to the Widdow?
            
            
               Bould.
               I thinke you are a witch.
            
            
               Feesi.
               My grand-mother was suspected.
            
            
               Bould.
               The Widdow has desired you by me to meete her
to morrow morning at Church in some v
                     •
                  knowne disguise,
least any suspect it, for quoth she,
               Long hath he held me fast in his moist hand,
               Therefore I will be his in nuptiall band.
            
            
               Feesi.
               
                  Bould, I haue euer taken you to be my friend, I am
very wise now, and valiant, if this be not true, dam
                     •
                  me Sir,

you are the sonne of a whore, and you lie, and I will make it
good with my sword.
            
            
               Bould.
               I am, what e're you please Sir, If it be not true, I will
goe with you to the Church my selfe, your disguise I haue
thought on; the Widdow is your owne. Come, leaue your
fooling.
            
            
               Feesi.
               If this be true, thou little Boy,
            
            Cant.
            
               Bould.
               So true, as thou tel'st to me,
               To morrow morne when I haue the Widdow,
               My deare friend shalt thou be.
            
            Exeunt.
            Enter MAID like the foote-boy: SELDOME with a
couple of SERIEANTS, PITS, DONNER.
            
            
               Maid.
               Sir, t'is most true and in this shall you be
               vnlike to other Citizens that arrest
               To vndoe Gentlemen: your clemencie heere
               perchance saues two liues, one from the others sword,
               The other from the Lawes; this morne they fight,
               And though your debtor be a Lord, yet should he
               Miscarrie, certainely your debt were lost.
            
            
               Seld.
               Do'st thou serue the Lord Proudly?
               
            
            
               Maid.
               Sir, I do.
            
            
               Seld.
               Well, such a Boy as thou, is worth more money
               Then thy Lord owes me, t'is not for the debt
               I doe arrest him, but to end this strife,
               Which both may loose my money and his life.
            
            Enter Lord PROVDLY with a riding rod.
            
               Pr.
               My Horse there, Z'oones I would not for the world
               He should alight before me in the field,
               My name and henor were for euer lost.
            
            
               Seld.
               Good morrow to your Honor, I doe heare
               Your Lordship this faire morning is to fight,
               And for your honor: Did you neuer see
               The Play, where the fat Knight hight Old-castle,
               
               Did tell you truly what this honor was?
            
            
               Pr.
               Why, how now good man flat-cap, what d'ee lack?
               Who doe you talke to, sirrha?
            
            
               1. Serg.
               We arrest you.
            
            
               Pr.
               Arrest me, rogue? I am a Lord ye curs, a Parliament
man.
            
            
               2. Serg.
               Sir, we arest you though.
            
            
               Pr.
               At whose suit?
            
            
               
               Seld.
               At mine, Sir.
            
            
               Pr.
               Why thou base rogue, did not I set thee vp,
               Hauing no stock, but thy faire shop and wise?
            
            
               Seld.
               Into my house with him.
            
            
               Maid.
               Away with him, away with him.
            
            
               Pr.
               A plot, a trick by Heauen. See Ingens foote-boy, t'is
by his Masters meanes, oh coward, slaue; i'le put in baile, or
pay the debt.
            
            
               Sel.
               I, I, I, wee'll talke with you within—thrust him in.
               Ex.
            
            Enter INGEN looking on his sword and bending it,
his brother like a Man.
            
               Ing.
               If I miscarrie Franck, I prithee see
               All my debts paid, about fiue hundred pounds
               Will fully satisfie all men, and my land
               And what I else possesse, by natures right
               And thy descent, Franck, I make freely thine.
            
            
               Broth.
               I know, you doe not thinke I wish you dead
               For all the benefit: besides, your spirit
               So opposite to counsaile, to auert
               Your resolution, that I saue my breath,
               Which would be lost in vaine, to expire and spend
               Vpon your foe, if you fall vnder him.
            
            
               Ing.
               
                  Franck, I protest you shall doe iniurie
               Vnto my foe, and much disturbance to
               Vnto my soule departing, die I heere
               Fairely, and on my single enemies sword,
               If you should not let him go off vntouch't.
               Now by the Master of thy life and mine,
               I loue thee Boy, beyond any example,
               As well as thou do'st me, but should I goe
               Thy second to the field, as thou dost mine,
               And if thine enemie kild thee like a man,
               I would desire, neuer to see him more,
               But he should beare himselfe off with those wounds
               He had receau'd from thee, for that time safe,
               And without persecution by the Law,
               For what hap is our foes, might be our owne,
               And no mans iudgement, sits in Iustice place,
               
                  
But weighing other mens as his owne case.
            
            
               Broth.
               He has the aduantage of you being a Lord,
               For should you kill him, you are sure to die,
               And by some Lawyer with a golden tongue,
               That cries for right, ten angels on his side;
               Your daring meete him, cal'd presumption:
               But kill he you, hee, and his noble friends
               Haue such a golden snaffle for the jawes
               Of man, deuouring Pithagorean Law,
               Thei'le reyne her stubborne chaps, e'ne to her taile?
               And though she haue yron 
                     •
                  eeth to meaner men,
               So master her, that who displeasd her most,
               She shall lie vnder like a tired jade,
               For small boates on rough seas are quickly lost,
               But ships ride safe, and cut what by they list.
            
            
               Ing.
               Follow what may, I am resolu'd deare Brother,
               This monster vallor, that doth feed on men,
               Groanes in me for my reputation.
               This charge I giue thee to, If I doe die,
               Neuer to part from the yong Boy, which late
               I entertain'd, but loue him for my sake:
               And for my Mistresse the Ladie Honor,
               
               Whom to deceiue, I haue deceiu'd my selfe.
               If she be dead, pray God I may giue vp
               My life a sacrifice on her, brothers sword;
               But if thou liu'st to see her gentle brother,
               If I be slaine, tell her I dy'de because
               I had transgrest against her worthy loue.
               This sword is not well mounted, lets see thine.
            
            Enter MAID like a foote-boy.
            
               Maid.
               Your staying Sir, is in vaine, for my Lord Proudly,
               
               Iust at his taking horse to meete you heere,
               At Seldomes suit the Citizen, was arrested
               Vpon an action of two hundred pounds,
               I saw it Sir, t'is true.
            
            
               Ing.
               Oh, scuruie Lord,
               It had beene a cleanlier shift then this to haue had
               It hinder'd by command, he being a Lord,
               
                  
But I will finde him.
            
            Enter Lord PROVDLY.
            
            
               Proud.
               You see, valiant Sir, I haue got loose
               Pro. stabs his sister.
               For all your stratagem, oh rogue are you there.
            
            
               Ing.
               Most ignoble Lord.
            
            Ingen stabs Proud. in the left arme.
            
               Proud.
               Coward thou did'st this
               That I might be disabled for the fight,
               Or that thou mightst haue some excuse to shun me,
               But t'is my left arme, thou hast lighted on.
               I haue no second; heere are three of you,
               If all doe murther me, your consciences
               Will more then hang you, damn you; come prepare.
            
            
               In.
               Brother walk off, &amp; take the boy away, is he hurt much?
            
            
               Bro.
               Nothing or very little.
            
            Fr. thrusts the Boy out.
            
               Ing.
               I
                     •
                  le bind your wound vp first, your losse of blood
May sooner make you faint.
            
            
               Pr.
               
                  Ingen, thou art a worthy Gentleman, for this curtesie,
               Go-too i'le saue thy life, come on Sir: hay,
               a passe or two.
               I'le cut your codpeice point Sir, with this thrust,
               And then downe goes your breeches.
            
            
               Ing.
               Your Lordships merrie
               passe.
               I had like to haue spoild your cut-worke band.
            
            Enter MAID like a foote-boy running, BROTHER
after him, Maid kneeles betwixt 'em.
            
               Maid.
               Oh Master, hold your hand, my Lord hold yours,
               Or let your swords meete in this wretched breast,
               Yet you are both well, what blood you haue lost
               Giue it as for the iniurie you did, and now be friends,
            
            
               Pr.
               S'hart, t'is a louing rogue.
            
            
               Ing.
               Kind Boy, stand vp, t'is for thy wound he bleeds,
               My wrong is yet vnsatisfied.
            
            
               Pr.
               Hence away it is a Sisters losse, that whets my sword.
            
            
               Mai.
               Oh stay, my Lord, behold your sister heere
               discouers her selfe.
               Bleeding by your hand Seruant see your mistresse
               Turn'd to thy seruant running by thy Horse,
               Whose means it was to haue preuented this, but all in vaine.
            
            
               Broth.
               Oh noble Ladie.
            
            
               Ing.
               Most worthie patterne of all women kind.
            
            
               Proud.
               
                  Ingen, I am satisfied, put vp your sword.
               
                  
Sister, you must with me, I haue a husband
               The Lord Fee-simple
                        •
                     
                   father, old, but rich:
               This Gentleman is no match for you; kneele not,
               That portion of yours, I haue consum'd,
               Thus marrying, you shall neuer come to want.
            
            
               Maid.
               Oh I s
                     •
                  eet my Lord, my brother do not force me,
               To breake my faith or to a loathed bed.
            
            
               Ing.
               Force you, he shall not, brother beare her hence,
               Shee is my wife, and thou shalt finde my cause
               Ten times improu'd now.
            
            
               Pr.
               Oh, haue at you Sir.
            
            
               Ma.
               Hold, hold for heauens sake, was e're wretched Lady
               Put to this hazard? Sir, let me speake
               But one word with him, and i'
                     •
                  e goe with you,
               And vndergoe, what euer you command.
            
            
               Proud.
               Doo't quickly, for I loue no whispering,
               T'is strange to see you Madame with a sword,
               You shou
                     •
                  d haue come hither in your Ladies cloathes.
            
            
               Maid.
               Well, as you please my Lord, you are witnesse,
whatsoe're before
               Hath past betwixt vs: thus I doe vndoe.
               Were not I mad to thinke thou could'st loue me
               That would'st haue slain my Brother?
            
            
               Pr.
               Sai'st true sister.
            
            
               Ing.
               Oh thou faire creature! wilt thou be as false as other
Ladies?
            
            
               Maid.
               Thou art my example,
               Ile kisse thee once, farewell for euer, come my Lord, now
               Match me, with whom you please, a tumbler.
               I must doe this, else had they fought againe.
            
            
               Pr.
               Mine own best Sister, farewel Mr. Ingen.
               
               Ex. Pr. &amp; Ma.
            
            
               Broth.
               Oh antient truth to be denied of no man,
               An Eele by'th taile's held surer than a woman.
            
            Exeunt.
         
         
            Actus quintus.
            Enter SVBTLE with HVSBAND.
            
            
               Subt.
               SHee is not to be cast.
            
            
               Hus.
               It cannot be: had you a wife, and I were in your
               case.
            
            
               
               Husb.
               I would be hang'd euen at the chamber doore
               Where I attempted, but i'le lay her flat.
            
            
               Subt.
               Why tell me truely, would it please you best,
               To haue her remaine chast, or conquered.
            
            
               Husb.
               Oh friend it would do me good at the heart
               To haue her ouer come, shee do's so brag
               And stand vpon her chastitie forsooth.
            
            
               Subt.
               Why then in plaine termes Sir, the fort is mine,
               Your wife has yeelded, vp-tailes is her song,
               The deed is done, come, now, be merrie man.
            
            
               Husb.
               Is the deed done indeed? come, come, you jest,
               Has my wife yeelded? is vptailes her song?
               Faith come, in prose, how got you to the matte
                     •
                   first, ha.
               Pish, you are so bashfull now.
            
            
               Subt.
               Why, by my troth i'le tell you, because you are my
friend, otherwise you must note it is a great hurt to the art
of whooremasterie to discouer, besides the skill was neuer
mine o'th price.
            
            
               Husb.
               Very good, on sir.
            
            
               Subt.
               At the first she was horrible stiffe against me, then
               Sir I tooke her by the hand, which I kiss'd.
            
            
               Husb.
               Good Sir.
            
            
               Subt.
               And I cal'd her pretie Rogue, and I thrust my finger
betwixt her breasts, and I made lips; at last, I pul'd her
by the chin to me, and I kist her.
            
            
               Husb.
               Hum, very good.
            
            
               Subt.
               So at the first, she kist very strangely, close, &amp; vntoward;
then said I to her, thinke b
                     •
                  t vpon the wrongs, the
intollerable wrongs, the rogue your Husband does you.
            
            
               Hus.
               I that was very good, what said she to you then sir?
            
            
               Subt.
               Nay, I went on. First quoth I, thinke how he hath
vs
                     •
                  d you, left you no meanes, giuen all your clothes to his
Punckes, struck you, turn'd your gray eies into black ones,
but yet—
            
            
               Husb.
               A pre
                     •
                  ie conceit.
            
            
               Subt.
               Quoth I, these things are nothing in the Rascoll,
thinke but what a base Whoore-master, the Rascoll is.
            
            
               Husb.
               Did you call me Rascoll so often are you sure.
            
            
               Subt.
               Yes, and oftner, for said I, none comes amisse to

the rogue, I haue knowne him quoth I, doe three lowzie beggars
vnder hedges in the riding of ten mile, and I swore
this to.
            
            
               Hus.
               Twas verie well, but you did lie. On I pray.
            
            
               Sub.
               Pish, one must lie a little, now sir by this time shee
began to kisse some what more openly, and familiarlie, her
resistance began to slacken, and my assault began to stiffen,
the more her Bulwarke decai'd, the more my batterie fortified,
at last sir, a little fumbling being past to make the Conquest
more difficult, shee perceauing my readines mounted,
fals me flat vpon her backe, cries mee out aloud
               Ahlas I yeeld, vse me not roughly friend,
               My fort, that like Troy towne, ten yeares hath stood
               Beseig'd and shot at did remaine vnwon:
               But now tis conquer'd. So the deede was done
                     •
                  
               
            
            
               Hus.
               Then came the hottest seruice. Forward with your tale sir.
            
            
               Sub.
               
                  Nay Caetera, quis nes
                     •
                  t, lassi requienimus ambo▪
               
               Proueniant medii sic mihi sape dies.
            
            
               Hus.
               Which is as much to say: I am a Cuckold, in all Languages,
but sure tis not so, It is impossible my wife should
yeeld.
            
            
               Sub.
               Hoyday, ene now, it was impossible she should hold
out, and now it is impossible she should yeeld, stay you but
heere &amp; be an eare witnes to what followes, Ile fetch your
wife. I know he will not stay.
               Exit.
            
            
               Hus.
               Good faith Sir but he will. I doe suspect some knauerie
in this.
               Exit.
               Here will I hide my selfe, when thought as gone,
               If they doe ought vnfitting I will call
               Witnesse, and straight way sue a diuorce.
            
            Enter WIFE and SVBTILL.
            
            
               Sub.
               I knew hee would not 
                     ••
                  ay. Now noble Mistrisse,
               I claime your promise.
            
            
               Wife.
               What was that good seruan
            
            
               Sub.
               That you would lie with me.
            
            
               Wife.
               If with anie man,
               But prithee first consider with thy selfe
               If I should yeeld to thee, what a load thy Con
                     •
                  cence
               
                  
Would beare about it, for I wish quick thunder
               May strike me, If I yet haue lost the truth,
               Or whitenesse of the hand I gaue in Church,
               And twill not be, thy happinesse (as thou thinkst)
               That thou alone should'st make a woman fall,
               That did resist all else, but to thy soule
               A bitter Corasiue, that thou didst staine,
               Vertue that else had stood immaculate,
               Nor speake I this, as yeelding vnto thee,
               For tis not in thy power, wert thou the sweet'st
               Of natures Children, and the happiest,
               To conquer me, nor in mineowne to yeeld,
               And thus it is with euery pious wife.
               Thy daylie railing at my absent Husband
               Makes me indure thee worse, for let him doe
               The most preposterous ill relishing things
               To me, they seeme good, since my Husband does 'em,
               Nor am I to reuenge or gouerne him,
               And thus it should be with all vertuous Wiues.
            
            
               Sub.
               Poxe a this vertue and this chastetie,
               Doe you know faire Mistresse, a young Gentleman
               About this towne cald Bould, where did he lie
               Last night, sweet Mistris, oh oh, are you catch'd,
               I saw him slip out of the house this morne,
               As naked as this truth, and for this cause
               I haue tould your Husband that you yeelded to me,
               And he I warrant you, will blaze it throughly,
               As good doe now then as bee thought to doe.
            
            
               Wife.
               No, twill not be yet, thou iniurious man,
               How wilt thou right me in my Husbands thoughts,
               That on a false surmise, and spight hast tould,
               A tale to breed vncurable discontent?
               
                  Bould was that ould wench that did serue the Widdow,
               and thinking by this way to gaine her loue
               Mist of his purpose, and was thus cashier'd,
               Nor cares shee to proclame it to the world.
            
            
               Su.
               Zoons, I haue wrong'd you Mistris. On my knees
               kneels
               I aske you pardon, and will neuer more,
               
                  
Attempt your puritie, but neglect all things
               Till that soule wrong I haue bred in your Knight
               I haue expeld, and let your loues aright.
            
            
               Hus.
               Which now is done alreadie Madame wife,
               kneeles
               Vpon my knees, with weeping eies, heau'd hands,
               I aske thy pardon, oh sweet vertuous creature,
               I prithee breake my head.
            
            
               Wife.
               Rise, rise, Sir pray▪
               
               You haue done no wrong to me, at least I thinke so;
               Heauen hath preuented all my iniurie,
               I doe forgiue and marrie you a new.
               Come, we are all inuited to the weddings,
               The Ladie Honor to the old rich Connt.
               
               Yong Bould vnto another Gentlewoman,
               We and the Widdow are inuited thither,
               Embrace and loue, henceforth more really,
               Not so like worldlings.
            
            
               Husb.
               Heere then ends all strife
               Thus false friends are made true, by a true wife.
            
            Exeunt.
         
         
            Actus quinti Scaena prima.
            Enter old COVNT wrapt in furs, the Ladie HONOR drest
like a Bride, the Lord PROVD. WEL-TRI'D, BOVLD,
leading FEE-SIMPLE like a Ladie masqu'd, HVSBAND,
WIFE, SVBTLE with a letter, WIDDOVV, to them
BROTHER, SELDOM, and his wife.
            
               Broth.
               HEalth and all joy vnto this faire assemblie,
               My brother, who last tide is gone for France,
               
               A branch of willow feathering his hat,
               Bad me salute you Ladie, and present you
               With this same letter written in his blood,
               He prayes no man, for his sake euermore
               To credit woman, nor no Ladie euer
               To beleiue man, so either sexe shall rest
               V
                     •
                  niur'd by the other, this is all, and this I haue deliuer'd.
            
            
               Pr.
               I and well, you pronounce rarely did you neuer play?
            
            
               Broth.
               Yes, that I haue, the foole, as some Lords doe.
            
            
               Wel.
               Set forward there.
            
            
               Count.
               Oh, oh, oh, a pox a this cold.
            
            
               
               Welt.
               A cold a this poxe you migt say, I am a feard.
            
            
               Maid.
               How full of ghastly wounds this letter shewes,
oh, oh.
            
            swoones.
            
               Pr.
               Looke to my sister.
            
            
               Bou.
               S'hart the Ladie swoons.
            
            
               Wife.
               Strong-water there.
            
            
               Feesi.
               If strong breath would recouer her, I am for her.
            
            
               Co.
               Ahlas good Ladie, hum, hum, hum. coughs perpetually
               
            
            
               Subt.
               He has fet her againe with coughing.
            
            
               Maid.
               Conuey me to my bed send for a Priest
               And a Physition, your Bride I feare,
               In stead of Epithalamious shall neede
               A Dirge, or Epitaph, oh lead me in,
               My bodie dies for my soules periur'd sinne.
            
            Exit Maid, Grace, Wife, Husb. Subtle.
            
               Bould
               Hymen comes towards vs in a mourning robe.
            
            
               Welt.
               I hope friend, we shall haue the better day.
            
            
               Proud.
               I'le fetch the Parson and Physition
               Ex. Lo. Pr.
            
            
               Broth.
               They are both readie for you.
               Exit. Broth.
            
            
               Welt.
               Madam, this is the Gentlewoman.
               Who something bashfull does desire your pardon, that shee
               Does not vnmasque.
            
            
               Wid.
               Good Master Wel-tri'd, I would not buie her face,
and for her manners if they were worse, they shall not displease
me.
            
            
               Welt.
               I thanke your Ladyship.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Looke, how the old Asse my father stands, he looks
like the Beare in the play, he has kil'd the Ladie with his verie
sight as God helpe me, I haue the most to do to forbeare
vnmasquing me, that I might tell him his owne, as can be.
            
            
               Bould.
               Fie, by no meanes.
               The Widdow comes towards you.
            
            
               Count.
               Oh, oh, oh, oh.
            
            
               Wid.
               Seruant, God giue you joy, and Gentlewoman,
               Or Ladie as full joy, I wish to you,
               Nor doubt that I will hinder you, your loue,
               But heere am come to doe all curtesie
               To your faire selfe, and husband that shall be.
            
            
               Feesi.
               I thank you heartilie.
            
            
               Welt.
               S'hart, speak smaller man.
            
            
               Feesi.
               I thanke you heartilie.
            
            
               
               Coun.
               You're going to this geere to Mr. Bould, vm, vm, vm.
            
            
               Bould.
               Not to your couching geere my Lord, though I
be not so olde, or rich as your Lordship, yet I loue a yong
wench as well.
            
            
               Welt.
               As well, as my Lord, nay by my faith, that you do
not, loue a yong wench as well as he, I wonder you will be
vnmannerly to say so.
            
            
               Count
               Faith Master Wel-tri'd, troth is I loue them well,
but they loue not me, vm, vm, vm, you see, what ill luck, I
haue with them, vmp, vmp, vmp, a poxe a this cold still say I.
            
            
               Welt.
               Where got you this cold my Lord? it can get in no
where that I can see, but at your nostrels, or eies, all the other
parts are so barricado'd with furre.
            
            
               Feesi.
               It got in at his eies, and made that birdlime there
where cupids wings doe hang intangled.
            
            
               Count.
               Is this your wife, that (vm, vm, vm) shall be, Ma.
Bould, i'le be so bould as kisse her.
            
            [Wid. Bould whisper aside.
            
               Count. sits in a chaire and fals a sleepe.
            
               Feesi.
               Sir, forbeare, I haue one bould enough to kisse my

                     〈◊〉
                  , oh olde coxcombe, kisse thine owne naturall sonne, t'is
worse then a Iustices lying with his own daughter, but Mr.
Wel-tri'd when will the Widdow breake this matter to me?
            
            
               Welt.
               Not till the very close of all, she dissembles it yet,
because my Lo
                     ••
                   your Father is heere, and her other suitor
Bould.
               
            
            
               Feesi.
               That's all one, he's o'th plot a my 
                     ••
                  de:
            
            
               Wid.
               T'is needlesse Master Bould, but I will doe
               Any thing you require to satisfie you,
               Why should you doubt, I will forbid the banes,
               For so your friend, heere tould me? I should rather
               Doubt that you will not marrie.
            
            
               Bo.
               Madam by heauen, as fully I am resolu'd to marry now,
               And will to, if you doe not hinder it,
               As euer louer was, only because
               The World has taken notice of some passage
               Twixt you and me, and then to satisfie
               My sweet heart heere, who poore soule is a feard,
               To haue some publike disgrace put vpon her,
               
                  
I doe require some small thing at your hands.
            
            
               Wid.
               Well, I will doe it and th
                     •
                  s professe besides,
               Married, you shall as welcome be to mee
               As mine owne brother, and your selfe faire Ladie,
               Euen as my selfe, both to my boord, and bed.
            
            
               Wel.
               Ah, ah, how like you that?
            
            
               Feesi.
               Now she begins, abundant thanks vnto your widdow-hood.
               Z'oones my Fathers a sleepe on's wedding day,
               I wonder'd where his cough was all this while.
            
            
               Enter INGEN like a Doctor: A PARSON, BROTHER,
PROVDLY, SELDOME, MRIS. SELD. HVSBAND,
WIFE, and SVBTLE.
            
               Ingen.
               I pray forbeare the chamber, noise does hurt her.
               Her sickenesse I ghesse rather of the minde
               Than of her bodie, for her pulse beates well,
               Her vitall functions not decaid a whit,
               But haue their naturall life and operation.
               My Lord, be cheer'd, I haue an ingredient about me,
               Shall make her well I doubt not.
               In Master Parson, it shall be yours I pray,
               The soules Physition should haue still the way.
               [Exit Ingen, Parson shuts the doore.
            
            
               Wid.
               How cheeres she pray?
            
            
               Wife.
               In t
                     •
                  oth exceeding il
                     •
                  
                  ▪
               
            
            
               Ms. Seld.
               A verie weake woman indeed she is, and surely
               I thinke cannot scape it.
            
            
               Husb.
               Did you marke how she ey'de the Physition?
            
            
               Wife.
               Oh God I, she is very loath to die.
            
            
               Ms. Seld.
               I that's n'ere the better signe, I can tell you.
            
            
               Subt.
               And when the Parson came to her, she turn'd away,
               And still let the Physicion hold her by the hand.
            
            
               Proud.
               But see what thought the Bride-groome takes,
my conscience knowes now, this is a most praeposterous
match, yet for the commoditie, we winck at all inconueniencie.
My Lord, my Lord.
            
            
               Count.
               Vmp, vmp, vmp, I beshrow you for waking of me,
now shall I haue such a fit of coughing, hum, hum—
            
            
               Bould.
               Oh haplesse wife, that shall haue thee, that either

must let thee sleepe continually, or be kept waking her selfe
by the cough.
            
            
               Wid
               You haue a proper Gentleman to your sonne, my
               Lord, he were fitter for this yong Ladie than you.
            
            
               Welt.
               D'ee marke that againe?
            
            
               Feesi.
               Oh sweet widdow.
            
            
               Count.
               He a wife, he a fooles head of his owne.
            
            
               Feesi.
               No, of my Fathers.
            
            
               Count.
               What should he doe with a vmp, vmp?
            
            
               Wife.
               What with a cough? why he would spit, and that's
more than you can doe.
            
            
               Proud.
               Your bride my Lord is dead.
            
            
               Count.
               Marrie, e'ne God be with her, griefe will not
helpe it, vmp, vmp, vmp.
            
            
               Broth.
               A most excellent spouse.
            
            
               Pr.
               How fares she Mr. Doctor. Z'oons, whats here
               looks in at the window
               Bould, Widdow, Wel-tri'd, Fee-simple, hoy-day.
               
               Husband, Wife, Seldome, Ms. Seld. Subtle: how now?
               
            
            
               Feesi.
               Looke, looke, the Parson joynes the Doctors hand
&amp; hers; now the Do. kisses her by this light.
            
            [omnes whoop.
            
               Feesi.
               Now goes his gowne off, hoy-day, he has
read breeches on: Z'oones, the Physition is got
Pistols for Bro.
o'th top of her, be like it is the mother she has,
harke the bed c
                     •
                  eakes.
            
            
               Pr.
               S'hart, the doores fast, break 'em open, we are betrai'd.
            
            
               Bro.
               No breaking open doores, he that stirs first
               draws &amp; holds out a pistoll.
               I'le pop a leaden pill into his guts.
               Shall purge him quite away, no hast good friends,
               When they haue done (whats fit) you shall not neede
               To breake the doore, thei'l open it them selues.
            
            A curtaine drawne, a bed disco
                  •
               er'd, Ingen with his sword
in his hand, and a Pistoll, the Ladie in a peticoate,
the Parson.
            
               Pr.
               Thy blood base villain shal answere this
               the Bro. set back to back
               I'le dye thy nuptiall bed in thy hearts go
                     •
                  e.
            
            
               Ing.
               Come, come, my Lord, t'is not so easily done,
               You know it is not. For this my attempt
               Vpon your sister, before God and man
               
                  
She was my wife, and n'ere a bed-rid gowt
               Shall haue my wench, to get diseases on.
            
            
               Pr.
               Well mai'st thou tearme her so that has consented,
               Euen with her will to be dishonor'd.
            
            
               Ing.
               Not so, yet haue I lyen with her.
            
            
               Ma.
               But first (witnesse this Priest) we both were married,
            
            
               Priest.
               True it is Domine.
               Their contract's run into a marriage,
               And that my Lord into a carriage.
            
            
               Pr.
               I will vndoe thee Priest.
            
            
               Priest.
               'Tis to late,
               I'm vndone alreadie, wine and Tobacco, I defie thee
               Thou temporall Lord, perdy thou neuer shalt
               Keepe me in jayle, and hence springs my reason,
               My act is neither Felonie nor Treason.
            
            
               Fee.
               I sir, but you do not know, what kindred she may haue.
            
            
               Omnes.
               Come, come, there is no remedie.
            
            
               Wife.
               And weigh't right in my opinion my honor'd Lord,
               And euery bodies else, this is a match,
               Fitter ten thousand times, than your intent.
            
            
               Omnes.
               Most certaine t'is.
            
            
               Wid.
               Besides, this Gentleman your brother in law well
parted, and faire mean'd, and all this come about (you must
conceiue) by your owne sisters wit as well as his.
            
            
               Ing.
               Come, come, t'is but getting of me knighted my
               Lord, and I shall become your Brother well enough.
            
            
               Pr.
               Brother your hand, Lords may haue projects still,
               But there's a greater Lord, will haue his will.
            
            
               Bo.
               This is dispatcht. Now Madam is the time,
               For I long to be at it, your hand sweet heart.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Now, boyes.
            
            
               Wid.
               My Lord, and Gentlemen, I craue your witnesse
               To what I now shall vtter. 'Twixt this Gentleman
               There has beene some loue passages and my selfe,
               Which heere I free him, and take this Ladie.
            
            
               Welt.
               Law ye, and take this Ladie.
            
            
               Wid.
               Which with a mothers loue, I giue to him,
               And wish all joy may crowne their marriage.
            
            
               
               Bould.
               Nay Madame, yet she is not satisfied.
               Bould giues her a ring, and she puts it on her thumb.
               
            
            
               Wid.
               Further, before yee all I take this ring
               As an assumpsit, by the vertue of which
               I bind my selfe in all my lands and goods,
               That in his choice, i'le be no hinderance:
               Or by forbidding banes, or claiming him
               My selfe for mine, but let the match goe on
               Without my check, which he intendeth now.
               And once againe I say, I bind my selfe.
            
            
               Bo.
               Then once againe, I say, widdow thou'rt mine▪
               
               Priest marrie vs, this match I did intend,
               Yee are all witnesses, if thou hinder it,
               Widdow your lands and goods are forfeit mine.
            
            
               Wid.
               Ha, nay take me to, since there's no remedie,
               Your Widdow (without goods) sels scuruilie.
            
            
               Omnes.
               Whoop, God giue you joy.
            
            
               Count.
               S'light, I am cozend of all sides, I had good hope
of the Widdow my selfe, but now I see euerie bodie leaues
me sauing vm, vm, vm.
            
            
               Bo.
               'Troth my Lord, &amp; that will sticke by you I warrant.
            
            
               Wid.
               But how Sir, shall we salue this Gentlewoman?
            
            
               Bo.
               Hang her whoore.
            
            
               Welt.
               Fie, you are too vnciuill.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Whoore in thy face, I doe defie thy taunts.
            
            
               Bo.
               Nay hold faire Ladie, now I thinke vpon't.
               The old Count has no wife, lets make a match.
            
            
               Omnes.
               If he be so contented.
            
            
               Count.
               With al my heart.
            
            
               Bo.
               Then kisse your Spouse.
            
            
               Count.
               S'foot she has a beard: how now, my sonne?
            
            
               Omnes.
               T'is the Lord Fee-simple.
               
            
            [Feesi vnmasques.
            
               Feesi.
               Father, lend me your sword, you and I are made a
couple of fine fooles, are we not? If I were not valiant now,
and meant to beate 'em all, heere would lie a simple disgrace
vpon vs, a Fee-simple one indeed, marke now what i'le
say to 'em, d'ee heare my Masters, Dam-me, yee are all the
sonne of a whoore, and ye lie, and I will make it good with
my sword, this is cal'd Roaring Father.
            
            
               Subt.
               I'le not meddle with you Sir.
            
            
               
               Pr.
               You are my blood.
            
            
               Welt.
               And I flesht you, you know.
            
            
               Bo.
               And I haue a charge comming, I must not fight now.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Has either of you any thing to say to me?
            
            
               Husb.
               Not we Sir.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Then haue I something to say to you. Haue you
any thing to say to me?
            
            
               Broth.
               Yes marrie haue I Sir.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Then I haue nothing to say to you, for that's the
fashion, Father if you will come away with your cough, doe?
Let me see how many challenges must I get writ: You shall
heere on me beleiue it.
            
            
               Proud.
               Nay, wee'le not now part angrie, stay the Feasts
               That must attend the weddings, you shall stay.
            
            
               Feesi.
               Why, then all friends, I thought you would not
haue had the manners to bid vs stay dinner neither.
            
            
               Husb.
               Then all are friends, and Ladie, wife, I crowne
               Thy vertues with this wreath, that 'tmay be said,
               There's a good wife.
            
            They set Girl
                  •
               nds on their heads.
            
               Bo.
               A Widdow.
            
            
               Ing.
               And a Maid.
            
            
               Wife.
               Yet mine is now approu'd the happiest life,
               Since each of you hath chang'd to be a wife.
            
            Exeunt.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

