
   
      
         
            A short discours of the excellent doctour and knight, maister Leonardo Phiorauanti Bolognese vppon chirurgerie VVith a declaration of many thinges, necessarie to be knowne, neuer written before in this order: whervnto is added a number of notable secretes, found out by the saide author. Translated out of Italyan into English, by Iohn Hester, practicioner in the arte of distillation.
            Cirugia. English
            Fioravanti, Leonardo, 1518-1588.
         
         
            
               1580
            
         
         Approx. 257 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00755
            STC 10881
            ESTC S105601
            99841328
            99841328
            5903
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00755)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5903)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 528:06)
         
         
            
               
                  A short discours of the excellent doctour and knight, maister Leonardo Phiorauanti Bolognese vppon chirurgerie VVith a declaration of many thinges, necessarie to be knowne, neuer written before in this order: whervnto is added a number of notable secretes, found out by the saide author. Translated out of Italyan into English, by Iohn Hester, practicioner in the arte of distillation.
                  Cirugia. English
                  Fioravanti, Leonardo, 1518-1588.
                  Hester, John, d. 1593.
               
               [8], 64 leaves   
               
                  By Thomas East,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1580.
               
               
                  Translation of: La cirugia.
                  Running title reads: Leonardo Phiorauanti, vpon chyrurgerie.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Medicine --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-12
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2009-01
            Megan MarionSampled and proofread
         
            2009-01
            Megan MarionText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A SHORT DISCOƲRS Of the excellent Doctour and Knight, maiſter Leonardo PHIORAVANTI BOLOGNESE vppon Chirurgerie.
            
               With a declaration of many thinges, neceſſarie to be knowne, neuer written before in this order: whervnto is added a number of notable ſecretes, found out by the ſaide Author.
            ¶ Tranſlated out of Italyan into Engliſh, by Iohn Heſter, Practicioner in the arte of Diſtillation.
            
               MIEVLX VAVLT MOVRIR Ē VERTV I QVE VIVRE EN HONCTE
            
            ¶ Jmprinted at London by Thomas Eaſt. 1580.
               
            
            
               Jacobius Boraston me juxe tenet
            
         
         
            
            
               
                  VERO NIHIL VERIVS
               
            
         
         
            
            
               ❧ To the Right Honourable his ſinguler good Lorde and Patrone, EDWARDE DE VERE, Earle of Oxenforde, Viſcount Bulbecke, Lorde of Eſcales and Bladeſmore, and Lord great Chamberlaine of England: Iohn Heſter wiſheth health of bodye, tranquilitie of mynde, with continuall increaſe of moſt godly honour.
            
               TRIE, AND THEN TRVST, ſaith the olde Adage: but I muſt hope for truſt without triall: bicauſe as I can compare you, (Right Honourable) to none more fit, thē to ALEXANDER the Macedon: So muſt I humbly requeſt your good Lordſhip, to imitate that famous worthie: who being ſicke, was aduertiſed by letters, that his Phiſition would empoyſon him. The good Prince notwithſtanding being offered the medicine by the accuſed, firſt tooke it, and dranke it vp, and then gaue the Phiſition the letter of his accuſer to reade: but perceyuing no alteration of countenaunce in the man, he tooke good courage, and by that ſame medecine (although extreame in operation) preſently recouered his former health. In like manner (Right Honourable) hauing tranſlated and gathered together this compēdious &amp; ſhort way of Chirurgerie, as I thought none ſo meete, to whome I might conſecrate theſe fruites of my trauailes: So muſt I moſte humbly deſire your good Lordſhip to peruſe it, and then to make triall of the contentes thereof: which being deuiſed and practiſed by a worthye and famous Capitaine, called Signior LEONARDO PHIORAVANTI of Bolognia, doth ſhewe both the names and natures of eche

wounde, with the order and manner to cure them in halfe the time which is or hath bene vſed heretofore, by either ignoraunt or arrogant Profeſſors and Practicioners of that noble and profounde Science, which as they more eſteeme a great gaine to them-ſelues, then a little eaſe to their pacientes, and a long protracting of the cure for a large payment: So I knowe although I eaſe the rich, relieue the poore, and teach the ignorant: yet are there ſuch, which being more wilfull then skilfull, will beare me a priuate grudge for this publique commodity, and will attempt more then eyther they can or are able to anſwer: the which to auoyde, I moſt humbly craue your Honorable patronage, that according to your name and poeſie, your name and propertie may be to protect the truth: So ſhal both the Tranſlator the leſſe doubt his foes, the Booke benefit more his friendes, and they both moſte reioyce of ſo worthy a Patrone. Whoſe lyfe God prolonge with health and increaſe of honour, and after the courſe of this pilgrimage finiſhed, enſtall you among his choſen, to reigne with him in eternall felicitie.
            
               The moſte affectioned of all thoſe, which owe your L. dutifull ſeruice, Iohn Heſter.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the gentle Reader.
            
               ALthough diuers learned men of no leſſe Iudgement then Practiſe, haue héere before tranſlated and ſet foorth ſundrye bookes, containing the moſt wholeſome and profitable precepts of Phiſicke and Chyrurgerie, where-in they ſeme to haue opened and at large declared al ſuch things as ſéemed neceſſary and expedient to be had &amp; knowne, in this our vulgar Engliſh tongue: yet neuertheleſſe, I callyng to memorye the notable ſentence of Cicero: That euery man is not all onely borne for himſelfe, but chiefly to profite his natiue country, then his parents, afterward his children and friendes, ſéeking a meanes where-by I might profite this my natiue countrey, thought it beſt to tranſlate this lyttle treatiſe vpon Chyrurgerie, gathered out of the workes of the moſt famous Knight &amp; Doctor, both in Phiſicke &amp; Chyrurgerie, Maſter Leonardo Phiorauanti, &amp; haue applyed my whole labor &amp; dilygēce to ſet ye ſame forth as truly and as nigh the Authours minde as I could, notwithſtanding but there doe ſome faultes remayne therein, bicauſe of diuers termes of the Art, the which I am not practiſed in: of the which if inſtructions be giuen, they ſhall the next impreſſion be amended.
            Therefore gentle Reader, take this booke in good part, for there-with thou ſhalt profite more then of any other that hath bene ſet foorth héeretofore, bicauſe it is onely the méere trouth, and pure practiſe approued by experience, and héere-with I make an ende, committing thée and vs all to almightie God, who proſper vs in all our workes.
            Gentle Reader, ye ſhall vnderſtand that if GOD

proſper me in health, I meane to ſet out all the workes of this Authour: which are .24. bookes, comprehended in eight volumes. In the which are conteined the whole art of Phiſicke and Chyrurgery, to the honour of God, &amp; the profit of my countrey.
            
               
                  From my houſe at Paules Wharfe, the. 23. of Iannuary.
                  
               
            
         
         
            The names of the bookes of this Authour.
            
               
                  A diſcourſe vpon Chyrurgerie, beeing this booke.
               
               
                  Caprici medicinalle.
               
               
                  Il compendio dei ſecreti rationalle.
               
               
                  Il ſpechio del ſcientia vniuerſalle.
               
               
                  Il Regimēte de la peſte. béeing ſette foorth already, and is entituled, The ioyful Iuel.
               
               
                  Il Theſoro de la vita humana.
               
               
                  La Chirurgia del Phiorauanti.
               
               
                  La Phiſica del Phiorauanti.
               
            
         
         
            
            
               The Table of the contents of this Booke following.
            
               WHat Chyrurgerie is. fol. 3.
               What wounds are. eod.
               Of Vlcers, and what they are. fol. 4
               Of Impoſtumes and their kindes. eod.
               Of Fiſtoloes and their kindes. eod
               Of all ſorts of ſcabbes. fol. 5.
               Of Formicola and his effects. fol. 6.
               A diſcourſe of woundes and other kindes of inwarde ſores. eod.
               An order to vſe in healing all manner of diſeaſes apperteining vnto the Chyrurgian. fol. 7.
               Of medicines to be vſed in all kinde of wounds outward, with eaſe and breuitie. fol. 8.
               To helpe vlcers of all ſorts. fol. 9.
               The order to be vſed in curing Impoſtumes of diuers ſortes. eod.
               The order to cure all manner of Fiſtoloes. fol. 10.
               To helpe all manner of ſcabbes. fol. 11.
               To helpe Mal di formica. eod.
               Of the Tow which is layd vpon wounds of common Chyrurgians. fol. 12.
               Of the diſgeſtiue with the which they dreſſe wounds after the aforeſayd Towe. eod.
               Of the mundificatiue vnguent, wher-with they dreſſe the woundes after they are digeſted, to mundifie them. fol. 13.
               Of their incarnatiue wher-with they dreſſe the woūd after it is mundified. eod.
               A rare ſecret the which this author did ſend vnto a very friend of his, being the in warres in Africa, the which helpeth all wounds, either by cut thruſt, galling

with arrows, or hargabuſh ſhot, or otherwiſe. 13
               Of thoſe Vnguents that Cicatirze wounds. fol. 14.
               A remedie to help a wounde with great ſpeede of our inuention. eod.
               An excellent ſecret to heale wounds of Gun-ſhot or Arrowes, with-out any danger. eod.
               A diſcourſe vppon olde wounds that are not yet healed and their ſouereigne remedie. eod.
               To diſſolue a brooſe in ſhorte time, when it is newe done. fol. 15.
               To helpe a wound quickly that is in perill of any accident. eod.
               To ſtop the fluxe of bloude in woundes with greate ſpeede. eod.
               An other remedie to ſtay the flux of bloud in woūd. fol. 16.
               Of our Cerote magno, that helpeth againſt all ſortes of ſores and woundes. eod.
               Of our magiſtrall Vnguent that helpeth diuers ſortes of ſores. eod.
               To make Oyle of Frankencenſe. fol. 17.
               Of Oyle of Waxe and his effecte. eod.
               To helpe the tooth ache that is cauſed of rotten teeth, or that commeth of a diſſentiō of the head. fol. 18.
               Againſt a ſtinking breath. eod.
               To helpe thoſe that haue a great cough in the ſtomake. eod.
               To helpe thoſe that can-not hold their water. fol. 19.
               To helpe thoſe that can-not make water. eod.
               To helpe thoſe that haue great burning of their vrine. fol. 20.
               To helpe thoſe that haue great payn of the Gout. eod.
               A remedie againſt the peſtilence, that preſerueth thoſe that vſe it. fol. 21.
               To helpe Pellaria, that is a diſeaſe which cauſeth the haire and beard to fall away. eod.
               
                  To helpe a Carnoſitie in the yarde. eod.
               To helpe a white Scall. fol. 22.
               To helpe thoſe Caruolli that come vppon the yarde, and their cauſes. eod.
               A diſcourſe of thoſe ſores that come of the Pockes, and how to helpe them quickly. fol. 23
               The cure of one that had the Pocks in his head. eod.
               The cure of a wound in the head &amp; the hand. fol. 24.
               A great ſecrete particuler for the Fluxe and Diſſenteria. eod.
               The cure of one that was poyſoned with Arſnick. 25.
               The cure of an vlcerated legge. eod.
               The cure of the Gout on a certeine Gentle-man. 26.
               Of the cauſes of the Scyatica, and how ye may helpe it eod.
               A moſte excellent remedy to helpe the Fluxe of the body, with a certeine diſcourſe there-on 27.
               A diſcourſe as concerning Cornes in the feete or els where, with their remedies. eod.
               Of an Infirmitie of importaunce, that commeth vpon the extremitie of the Toe, vpon the nayle. eod.
               A diſcourſe vppon the Hemerhodes, with the order to cure them with moſte excellent medicines of our inuention. fol. 27.
               A great ſecrete to helpe thoſe that are burſt or haue the Rupture. eod.
               A rare ſecrete and diuine, to helpe thoſe that are troubled with the Spleene. fol. 28
               An other great ſecret to helpe the Spleene with great ſpeede. eod.
               The cure of a certeine Spanyard called, Carabaſull di Cordonet, the whiche was troubled wyth the Pockes. eod.
               The cure of the Stiche in the ſide with retention of vryne. eod.
               
                  A cure of a certayne Spanyard wounded in the head in Naples. 29.
               The cure of a certaine Gtntleman, that had Mal di formica. eod.
               Certeine cures that his Authour did, when he trauailed into Afryca. eod.
               The cure of the Flux, wher-with I holpe the Army of the Emperour in Afryca. fol. 30.
               A goodly remedy found out by me, for wounds in the head. fol. 31.
               The cure of one that had his Noſe cut off, and ſet on againe. eod.
               The cure of an Arme of S. Giordano Vrſino. fol. 33.
               A great chaunce that happened at the aſſault in Afryca. eod.
               The cure of woundes being poyſoned, and of other ſores. eod.
               A remedy found out by me, agaynſt the poyſon of a Fiſh. fol. 34.
               Of the taking of Afrika and his diſtruction. eod.
               The cure of a great wound on tht head. fol. 35.
               A very ſtraunge thing that happened in the afore-ſaid yeare. eod.
               The cure of a Fiſtoloe in the lower partes. eod.
               Of many that I cured in Naples. fol. 36.
               A cure of Vlcera putrida, the whyche was in the Arme. eod.
               The cure of Etheſia in the beginning. fol. 37
               The cure of a certeyne man, wounded in thirteene places. eod.
               Of remedies that helpe many diſeaſes. fol. 38.
               Here beginneth the order to make diuers and ſundry medicines of our inuention, neuer founde out before by anye man. And firſt to make our Petra

Philoſophalla, that helpeth againſt all manner of diſeaſes that happeneth vnto man or woman, or any other animall terreſtryall. eod.
               To make our Balme artificiall, with the order to vſe it, and wherfore it ſerueth fol. 40.
               To make our Aromatico, the which helpeth agaynſt all manner of infirmities, of what quallytie ſo euer they be. fol. 41.
               To make our Electuario Angelico, and the order to vſe it, and in what diſeaſes. eod.
               Of the vigitable Stone, of our inuention, to tranſmute a body of one complection into an other, and to make him ſound for euer. fol. 42.
               Our ſolyble Siroppe with the order to vſe it. fol. 43.
               Our Siropo magiſtrale Leonardo, the which ſerueth againſt an infinite number of diſeaſes, and is a rare medicine. eod.
               Our Syropoe agaynſt the melancholyke humour, and ſpeciallye where there is ventoſity in the ſtomacke. fol. 44.
               Our Potion of Lignum Sanctum, the whyche is myraculous to dyſſolue crud, and malygne humours, with the order to vſe it, in the French Pockes, and ſuch like diſeaſes. eod.
               A moſte meruailous Water and rare, to cauſe a man to auoyde the Grauel in vrine, and to mundifie the raynes. fol. 45.
               To make the water of Lignum ſanctum, moſte wholſome againſte the Pockes, wyth a newe order. fol. 46.
               Our Dyſtillation for the Eteſia, the whyche is of meruaylous vertue, and wyth-out comparyſon, with the order to vſe it. fol. 47.
               
                  Our vigitable Siroppe, the which is miraculous and diuine. fol. 47
               An Electuarye that helpeth the cough, with great ſpeede and eaſe. eod.
               Electuario benedicto Leonardi, the which purgeth the body without any griefe, and is miraculous in his operation. fol. 48.
               An Electuary againſt the euil diſpoſition of the Liuer and Stomacke. eod.
               Our magiſtrall Electuary of Sulfure the which ſerueth againſt diuers fortes of infirmities. fol. 49.
               Our Electuario of Conſolida magore that ſerueth for many diſeaſes inwardly. eod.
               Our imperial Electuary for the Mother. fol. 50.
               Pylles agaynſt poyſon the which are of meruaylous vertue. eod.
               Vnguento magno Leonardo. eod.
               Oyle of Hipericon, the which is moſt miraculous for woundes and bruſes. fol. 51
               To make our Oleum benedictum, the which healeth woundes diuinely. eod.
               A magiſtrall Water, the which preſerueth the ſight a longe tyme, and mundifieth the eyes of all ſpots. fol. 52.
               To make Oyle of Vitrioll compound, the which preſerueth nature in his ſtrength. eod.
               Oleum philoſophorum de termentiua &amp; cera. fol. 53.
               Our magno licore the which is of great vertue. eod.
               Pillole Angelica, the which euacuat the body without any impediment, and are moſt profitable. 54.
               Pillole Aquilone of our inuention. 55.
               Our Quintaeſſentia ſolutiua, the which is of meruailous operation in diuers matters. eod.
               Our Siroppe of Quintaeſſence, the which is of meruailous vertue eod.
               
                  Pillole magiſtrale, the which is good againſt diuers infirmities. fol. 56.
               A compound Aqua vitae, the which ſerueth againſt all colde diſeaſes of the ſtomacke. eod.
               A compound Oyle againſt poyſon, the which is of a meruaylous vertue. eod.
               A meruaylous Sope that helpeth thoſe which can-not ſpit but with great payne. fol. 57.
               To make the Quintaeſſence of Hunny. fol. 58.
               To make our Elixer vitae or Aqua coeleſtis. eod.
               To make Aqua Reale vel Imperiale, the which maketh the teeth white preſentlye, incarnateth the goumes, and cauſeth a good breath. eod.
               A kinde of Pille moſt conuenient for the eyes, and comforteth the ſtomacke. fol. 60.
               A diſcourſe vpon a compoſition that preſerueth a man or woman in health a long time. eod.
               A meruailous Water to bee vſed of all Chirurgians in curing of their pacientes. fol. 61.
               To make our Cauſticke. eod.
               To make oyle of Antimony. eod.
               A precious Licour aboue all other. fol. 62.
               A ſecrete of meruailous vertue. eod.
               Our ſecret of marueilous vertue in act &amp; ſtrēgth. eod.
               To rectifie &amp; preſerue the ſight of thoſe that are weak ſighted. eod.
               Of Lac Virginis, and the order to make it. fol. 63.
               To calcine Tutia, and to bring it into a ſalte. eod.
               To precipitate Mares, and to bring it into a red powder, called Crocus martis, the which ſerueth for diuers purpoſes. eod.
               A ſecret of Turpentine of Ciprus. fol. 64.
            
            FINIS TABVLAE.
         
         
            
            HOW THAT OVR PHISICKE AND Chyrurgerie is better, then that, the which the Auncients haue commonly vſed.
            
               THere is no doubt, but that our newe Phiſicke and Chyrurgerie, is better then that, ye which the Auncients haue vſed: bicauſe it helpeth the ſick with more eaſe and ſpéede, and much more ſafer, and to ſhew the troth, the Aunciēts had neuer knowledge of our Dia Aromatico, nor of Electuario Angellica, nor of our Pillole Aquilone, nor did not make our ſiropo ſolutiuo, nor yet our magno licore, with a number of other medicines found out by me, the which are written in the ende of this booke, with the which I haue done wonderful cures, as thou maiſt read in my Theſoro de la vita humana, and truely moſt neceſſary for all profeſſours of this Arte, bicauſe therein thou ſhalt finde ſo manye goodly experiences, and it would cauſe the world to wonder thereat. But to tourne to our purpoſe, I ſay that the Auncients the which had not knowledge of our remedies, they wanted alſo knowledge of the true Phiſicke, and Chyrurgerie, as by ye experience thou mayſt ſée, I ſay not this to ſpeak euil of thoſe wiſe auncient Doctors, that were inuentours there-off, but I ſay it to ſay the troth, and many ſhall be my teſtimony of this troth. Bicauſe in many countrys, wher our worke that are Imprinted are come, they begin to practiſe after our order. And this order of curinge: I repute it not to my ſcience, but a worke that God would reueale vnto the worlde, thorow my meanes, and to ſhewe the troth, there hath bene none, that hath found the medicines for woundes with ſo much eaſe and breuitie as I haue done.
            
               Who hath euer founde the true Remedie for the Goute, for the Ouartain, for Fluxes, and all ſorts of Feuers, as I haue done? or what is he yt euer brought the whole Art of Phiſicke and Chyrurgerie into .viij. ſmall volumes, as I haue done? What is he that euer writ of the Peſtilence, and of his qualytie and remedies and orders to be vſed in the ſame, as I haue done. And if there be any that doth not credite me, let them make experience of all that I haue ſayde, and I promiſe you and ſweare as I am a true Knight, they ſhall finde more truth then I will write at this time, being as I haue ſaid, a worke giuen of God, for a vniuerſal benefit of all the world, and foraſmuch I exhort euery one of the profeſſors of Phyſick &amp; Chirurgery, to follow this our truthe, bicauſe they are of ſo great experience, yt it ſéemeth miraculous vnto man, as I haue ſéene many yeares agoe, to my great honour, and ſatiſfaction of the people of the world, &amp; thus doing &amp; working, thou ſhalt come to know yt our Phyſick &amp; Chirurgerie is more better &amp; wholeſome, then ye which hath bene vſed of the Auncients vntill this preſent time.
            
               Certeine remedies, for al Capitaines and ſouldiers that trauell eitherby water or lande.
               THere are .3. infirmities, that offend the ſouldiours in the campe aboue al ye reſt, the which are theſe, Feuers, Woundes, &amp; Fluxes of the body, the which thou maiſt help in this order following, wt theſe medicines, that is our Quintaeſſence of wine, our Balſamo, Magno licore, Quintaeſſencia ſolutiua, &amp; Specie Imperiale, &amp; the order to vſe thē is thus. When any hath a feuer or a flux, then preſently when ye diſeaſe beginneth, let him bloud in one of the .2. vaines vnder ye tongue, cutting it ouerthwart, &amp; this thou ſhalt do in ye euening, thē ye next morning, take a doſe of our imperial powder

mixt with wine, and this ye may do with-out any dyet or ſtrayght order, that being done, giue him .3. mornings together, halfe an ounce of our Quintaeſſence ſolutiue with broth. But if it be a flux, and that the Patient is not cured, let him ſtand in a colde bath of ſalt water of the Sea .3. or .4. houres or more, and hée ſhall bée perfectly holpe.
               Then as concerning wounds, as wel cuts as thruſts, and as wel gallings with arrows, as hargabuſh ſhot, and other ſortes, thou ſhalt cure them thus. The firſt thing that ye ſhall doe to them, is to waſh them very cleane with vrine, and then drye them well, then put there-in our Quintaeſſence of wine, &amp; preſently ioyne the parts together, &amp; ſow or ſtitch them cloſe, then put there-vpon 5. or .6. droppes of our Balſamo, and vppon the wound lay a cloth wet in our Magno licore, as hot as he may ſuffer it, and this ye ſhall do the firſt day: Than the next day follow this order: Firſt put theron our Quintaeſſence, and a lyttle of our Balſamo, &amp; then our Magno licore very hot, &amp; neuer change that medicine, and thus doing the wounde ſhall heale with great ſpéed, and in a quarter of the time, that the common Chyrurgians is able to doe it, by the grace of God.
            
         
         
            
            
               ❧ A short diſcourſe of the moſt excellent Doctor &amp; knight, Maſter Leonardo Phiorauanti Bologneſſe, vpon Chirurgerie, with a declaration of many thinges neceſſary to be knowne. Neuer written before in this order, where vnto is added a number of notable ſecrets founde out by the ſaide Author.
            The Proheme.
            
               IT is to be vnderſtoode, that when the Almightie creator had made ye worlde, he alſo created all manner of beaſts, as well on earth as in the water, with other foules, after which ſaith the holy Scripture, hée created man after his owne Image and ſimilytude, and to him gaue power ouer all things created, and with the ſame, grace and reaſon. Through the which he was apte to rule &amp; haue knowledge of all through the ſpirite of God, as to haue knowledge of al things where-vnto he gaue his minde &amp; vnderſtanding, as it is at this preſent to be ſéene among men in the worlde that haue knowledge of dyuers and ſundrie thinges, all neceſſarie for thoſe that will liue in the world with honour: For ſome vnderſtande the art of huſbandry, which was the firſt art vſed in the world, for ſo much as without it we cannot well liue as it is plainely ſéene. There are other that haue knowledge in keping beaſtes of all kinds apt or méete for mans bodie, as Goats, Kyne, Hogges, Hens, Geeſe, Horſe, Mules, and ſuch like. There are other that haue knowledge in Nauigation, without ye which alſo the world would be vnperfet, as it is ſéene by experience. There be other that haue knowledge in Coſmographie, whereby they knowe diuers partes of the

world whether men may trauaile. There be other that haue knowledge in the art of warres, whereby they may helpe to defend their Prince and countries, in executing of iuſtice. There be other that vnderſtand Aſtrologie, by the which they knowe ye courſe of Planets and their effects: Other vnderſtand the Mathematica, whereby they meaſure land and all other thinges: Other ſtudie Muſicke, to accord voyces together, &amp; other vnderſtand Phiſicke to helpe the diſeaſed bodyes of humaine creatures, and alſo annymales of dyuers and ſundrie infirmities. There be other that vnderſtande Chyrurgerie, to helpe al manner of ſores yt happē vnto men: vpon which Chirurgery, we wil write a brief diſcourſe &amp; pleſant reaſō, &amp; will leaue apart the ſcience yt is doubtful, bicauſe ther is no ſcience in the world wherwith a man may do good if there-with be no practiſe or experience, as a man may ſay. The which experience is maſter of all things, as it is plainly ſéene, and therfore we will giue you to vnderſtand which of thoſe partes be beſt or moſt neceſſary in this Chirurgerie, either to helpe thoſe that are hurt, or the ſcience, or experience. And we will ſhewe the méere troth without any diſſimulation or fraude, as I haue alwayes done in my workes which are Printed, and at this preſent doe intend to do, if almightie God giue mée grace, and quicken my ſpirits or wits in writing that which ſhalbe to his honour, and profite to the worlde.
         
         
            
            
               ❧ TO THE Reader.
            
            
               HAuing taken vpon me to write a briefe treatiſe of Chirurgerie, in the which I wil write the meere verity, &amp; that with as much breuitie as may be, bicauſe the troth occupieth but little roome, for the Philoſopher writeth that the troth is ſuch a light as all men doe hide, couering it with diuerſe abuſes, as the Poets many times doe: for when they write one of their tales they goe about to hide it, and thus to our purpoſe. Thoſe that write greate volumes cannot chooſe many times but hide the troth, for in much matter there entreth both good and bad, &amp; therefore I will write no more then is neceſſary, declaring what Chirurgerie is, and in what order it ſhould be vſed with all his accidents, ſhewing what woundes are, with Impoſtumes and vlcers, how they ingender, and when they are ingendred, howe to cure them and diſolue them. A diſcourſe which will pleaſe many bicauſe it is only troth, &amp; of great importance: Let euery one therfore know that ſcience with experience do apeare to be one thing, and at this preſent euery one is certeine thereof, that the experince of Phiſicke as wel as of Chirurgerie, cannot be good without ſcience, or Methode, as a man may terme it. But I ſay that experience is better then Science, in theſe two arts, that is in Phiſicke and Chirurgerie, for ſcience onely ſheweth the vertue the which may be done with practiſe that hath no theorike. Of which I haue written ſufficiently in my Capricy medicinalle, Imprinted at Venice, and that this which I write is troth, I will proue it, for I ſay, that noe can helpe with the onely Methode, but alwayes it is neceſſary that there be ſome experience

or practiſe therefore thoſe that do delight to vnderſtande, let them followe this my ſhort treatiſe, in the which I will intreate of thinges moſt neceſſary to bee knowne, &amp; wil ſhew how eaſie it is to work in that art, declaring al the dificult matters, ſo that euery one may ſee and perceiue it plaine, and afterwards I will ſhewe howe to make many newe medicines, as well for wounds, as for the other ſorts of ſores, which haue not beene vſed neither of old Doctors, nor of new: the which remedies are of ſuch vertue &amp; ſtrength, that the world wil wounder at them for their notable quicke working, and hereafter I will write what Chirurgerie is.
            
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ WHAT CHIRVRgerie is.
            
               
                  CHIRVRGERIE is both Science and practiſe, and to ſay the troth he that wil know the compoſition of mans body, muſt of neceſſitie haue ſome ſcience, and be Anatomiſt, although the ſame Science bée a thing to bée learned by practiſe, for I haue ſéene many times thoſe which wer vnlearned to be expert in the Anatomie of mans body, and thoſe were paynters and drawers, the which was neceſſary for thē to know to frame their figures accordingly: and therefore I take not that for ſcience but practiſe, for ſcience is onely that where-with the cauſes of euery infirmitie is found out, and is of ſmal effect to our purpoſe, bicauſe Chyrurgerie helpeth not only the cauſe, but alſo the effect after it is knowen, and therefore I may ſay that Chyrurgerie is no other then a pure and méere practiſe, and that it is onely neceſſary for the Chyrurgian to know how to ſtich a wound well, to mundifie an vlcer, and to kéepe it frō putrifaction, and kéepe it from alteration, ſo that ther runne no euill humors vnto the place offended, and to know all kinde of Vnguents that are apt to heale al kinde of wounds and vlcers, which thing muſt be knowen by practiſe. And lykewiſe to make all manner of Vnguents neceſſary for Chyrurgerie, &amp; for that cauſe I conclude moſt truely, that our Chyrurgerie is onely practiſe or experience. And that which cauſeth mée to beléeue it, is, that I haue alwayes ſéene the moſt part of Chyrurgians, when they ſhould haue any caſe in Chyrurgerie, they knew not what Vnguent would helpe the ſore, cut many times they proue this, and

that, and ſo continue vntill they haue found one, that is conuenient for the ſore, where-vnto it is applyed, and therefore this is a certeine ſigne, that they knowe not by Science there medicines to helpe the ſore, but with experience they ſearche it. Therefore if it be ſo, it is a ſigne that I haue ſayd the troth, and ſo conclude that Chirurgerie is a practiſe to helpe ſores on mens bodies, and alſo on beaſts, when occaſion ſhall ſerue.
            
               What Woundes are.
               WOundes are thoſe which in Latine is called Vulnus, &amp; of the vulgar Vulnere, and they are of two kindes, that is, ſimple &amp; compoūd. The ſimple are thoſe that are onely in ye fleſh, the compound are thoſe wher are cut ſinewes, veynes, muſcles and bones, and theſe are of diuers and ſundry kindes. And the difference that is among them is, by the varietie of the place where they are wounded, and by the difference of the weapon where-with they wer hurt, for ſome goe right, ſome ouerthwarte, ſome long, ſome broade, ſome are thruſts or ſtocate, that offende diuers partes of the body. The ſimple are of ſmall importaunce, bicauſe if ye kéepe them cleane and cloſe ſhut, nature wil heale thē without any kinde of medicine. But thoſe where veynes are cut, haue néede of ſome Art or practiſe, with the which they may ſtop the bloud, &amp; in any wiſe not to ſuffer ye wound remaine open, but to ſowe it vp verye cloſe, ſo that the veyne may heale. Alſo thoſe where ſinewes are hurt are of great importaunce, and would be healed with great ſpéede, ſo yt the ſinews may ioyne with more eaſe. But thoſe where bones are hurte, are of greater importaunce, for if the bone be ſeperated frō the other, of neceſſitie it muſt be taken 
                     ••
                  rth, before the

wound be healed. So that by this meanes euery one may know what woundes are, and their kindes.
            
            
               Of Vlceres, and what they are.
               VLcers are of diuers and ſundrye kindes, and are ingendred of many cauſes, as hereafter I wil ſhew. But firſt I will write of thoſe kinde of Vlcers that are cauſed of woundes. You ſhall vnderſtande that wounds in what part of the bodie ſoeuer they be, béeing impoſtumated, or cancrenated, they chaunge their names, and are no more called wounds, although the originall was a wound. For when it is cancrenated, it is called Vlcera coraſiua, bicauſe it goeth eating and créeping on the fleſh. But when the woūd is impoſtumated and full of matter, it is called, Vlcera putrida, that is putrified, &amp; it is bicauſe it is filthie &amp; ſtinketh. But when it is neither cancrenated nor yet apoſtumated, but that through ſome euill diſpoſition the wound is cloſed, and that there commeth in it euill qualyties without alteration, then it is called Vlcera ſordida, bicauſe therin is euil qualytie, &amp; it appeareth but a litle, but it is euill to heale. There be other ſorts of vlcers alſo, the which are cauſed of diuers &amp; ſundry kindes of tumors, &amp; the moſt euill &amp; miſcheuous, are thoſe that are of tumors cauſed of the pocks, for vnto thoſe there runneth aboundance of euil humors that augmēt the vlcer, &amp; they be the worſt ſort, for they can not be healed by themſelues, except the body be well purged and euacuated of al the humors that are offenſiue. Ther is another kinde of vlcer the which cometh of an Impoſtume, as well hot as colde, and thoſe are more gentle and eaſie to be helpt, if ye know the medicines that are apt to helpe and diſſolue thoſe kinde of vlcers.
               Theſe are the thrée kinde of Vlcers that commonlye

happen vnto men and women through diuers cauſes, as it is ſayd before, ſo that theſe are the principal cauſes of thoſe maligne vlcers.
            
            
               Of Impoſtumes, and their kindes.
               IMpoſtumes are a certeine kinde of tumor that is called in diuers manners, bicauſe they come in diuers places of ye body, as thoſe ſorts of Impoſtumes that come in the groyne, which in Venice is called Pannoche, in Rome Tencone, in Naples Dragonſelly, in Spayne Incordi, and the Auncient called them Buboni, and ſome with other names. There are other that come in all parts of the bodye, and when they come they cauſe great payne, and then they ripen and breake of themſelues for the moſt parte, and theſe in Naples are called Autrax, and in Rome Chicolini, in Venice Vn naſito, in Lumbardie Vn bungo, and in Spayne Vn nacido mui viliaco. There is an other kinde of Impoſtume, that is ingendered of a contuſion or brooſe, and is properly called Apoſtumato pro Amacatura. In the head there grow certeine kindes of ſores that are called Talpa or Topinare, ye which are of ſmall importaunce, for they maye bée healed in ſhort time, as it is ſéene in childrens heads yt are oftē troubled there-with, and alſo in their throats, and for the moſt part about the eares.
            
            
               Of Fiſtoloes, and their kindes.
               ALl manner of ſores that doe not cicatrize perfectly and haue communication with the inward parts, are called Fiſtoloes, and we terme them in Italian Sofio or Spiraculo, as ye may ſée by experience, and this is perillous when a Fiſtoloe cloſeth, being in the

body and ſpecially thoſe fiſtoloes that are in the fundament, for Nature hir ſelfe doth ingender it for eaſe. But theſe fiſtoloes that come in dyuers parts of the body are troubleſōe, but not perillous, alſo al ſuch ſores as tary long before they be incarnated come to fiſtoloes, &amp; many times it commeth through long curing, by tenting with their tentes, the which are cauſe that nature maketh a Callow &amp; leaueth the ſore ſo hollow, that it will neuer be filled with fleſh, but ſo remaine hollow, as it is ſéene eaſely by experience. There be other ſorts of fiſtoloes in forme of a ſore, and they bée thoſe ſores that moſt commonly come on the legges, the which do purge a long time, and are alſo very hard to heale, bicauſe if ye heale one of them preſently, there wil riſe another hard by it, and that is a kinde of fiſtoloe. There is another kinde of fiſtoloe that is cauſed of thoſe ſores that are vpon the bone, the which by his continuance do breake and conſume the ſkine and the bone, and theſe many times remaine fiſtolated, but who ſo taketh away the cauſe of the ſore, nature it ſelf will preuaile mightely and heale it, as may be ſéene dayly by experience, in thoſe that be ſo troubled. The fiſtoloes that come in the eyes, are called Fiſtola Lacrimoſa, and they haue ſome communication with the inward partes, and are euill to be healed. Bicauſe firſt the cauſe muſt be taken away inwardly, and then nature will heale it by it ſelfe, as I haue ſéene by experience, ſo that theſe are the kind of fiſtoloes moſt knowen vnto all men, and the cauſes of theſe fiſtoloes are two: and for my part I am fully perſwaded it is ſo. The firſt is of woundes euil healed, that remaine Fiſtolated. The ſecond cauſe I find to be of ſores cauſed of the poxe, and to ſhew a troth, yée ſhall cure them of the Poxe, and their fiſtoloes will heale of themſelues without any other helpe, as it is dayly to be ſéene:
               
                  There may be many other cauſes the which as yet I know not, but theſe two are a ſufficient reaſon, and to be conſidered of the profeſſors of this art, if they deſire to come to any excelencie: and therefore I wyll reaſon no more of the matter, bicauſe the ſcience and my experience will reach no farther.
            
            
               Of all ſortes of ſcabbes.
               THere be dyuers kindes of ſcabbes, but I will onelye intreate of thoſe in which I haue had moſt experience, and will ſet them forth as plaine as I can, that euery one thereby may haue profite. The firſt kinde of ſcabbe is that which is cauſed of Riplexione of the body, by eating much meate of great nouriſhment, and then not to digeſt it, ſo in that cauſe nature to eaſe it ſelfe, ſendeth forth that humiditie, and when it ioyneth to the ſkinne it ingroſeth and cauſeth an Impoſtume, and paſſing to the outwarde partes it is alreadie corrupted, and ſo cauſeth the Puſtules, as by experience may be ſéene, and this kinde is a viſcous and fat humour with great humiditie. There is another kinde of ſcabbe that is alwayes drye with readneſſe, and is ſmal, with great heate and itching, and the ſame in my iudgement is cauſed by much heate of the Lyuer and aduſtion of bloud, and may be healed eaſely. There is another kinde of great ſcabbe, that hath a greate drye cruſt on them and they growe bigge, and the ſame is of the french poxe being new taken. There is another kinde like ſerpigo that goeth créeping, and hath a drye cruſt, and hath no matter vnder it: and the ſame is alſo of the french poxe Inueterated. There are alſo dyuers other kindes, the which I wil leaue at this time,

bicauſe they are of ſmall importaunce, and may be helpt with thoſe medicines which are fit for the kindes aforeſaide.
            
            
               Of Formicola and his effects.
               THoſe kinde of vlcers that are commonly called Maldi formica, are ſo called bicauſe they are a kinde of maling Vlcers and coroſiue that goeth creping vppon the fleſh, and maketh many holes that are lifted vp on the ſides and are red, and theſe for the moſt parte are cauſed of the poxe as may be ſéene by experience, and thoſe ſores are euill to be healed, bicauſe therevnto runneth aboundance of humors, the which cannot be reſolued but with inwarde medecines, that is, with exquiſite purgations that purifie the bloud, and that cutteth away the euill humours that runne therevnto, &amp; cauſe great alteration with burning. This kinde of ſore commeth many times in the heade, and when it commeth in that part, it is called Tigna, or the white ſcalle, and to ſhewe that this is the troth, ye may ſée that thoſe medecines which heale Formicola, doth alſo heale the white ſcalle, for this is a kinde of the pox, as by the effects ye may plainly ſée, for if any ſhoulde ſay the contrary, I woulde aunſwere him againe that this may well be, bicauſe the ſame infirmitie may bée taken in the mothers wombe, or as ſoone as the childe is borne it may take it of the Nurſe that giueth it ſucke, if ſhe be infected with that diſeaſe, ſo that I conclude it may be ſo. But there are a number of that kinde of diſeaſe, which I let paſſe bicauſe I haue ſéene no experience of them.
            
            
               
               A diſcourſe of woundes and other kindes of inward ſores.
               WOundes that are within the body, as in the ſtomacke or belly or in Teſtinalles, in the bladder, raines, or guttes: The Milt, Lyuer, Lungs, Heart or other muſkles or Arteres, as there be a number, I confeſſe to know nothing therein, and I will ſhewe you the reaſon, you ſhall vnderſtand that when a wounde doth offende the interior parts, the Phiſition, or Chyrurgion or great Anatomiſt what ſo euer he be, cannot know all thoſe partes offended in the body, for after the weapon is with-in the bodye, it may turne and with the point hurt other parts a farre off the wound, and offend diuers particuler parts one different from the other, &amp; therefore I beſéech you excellent Chyrurgions, when ſuch a caſe commeth, how do you know or diſcerne which parts are hurt, but to ſay yt troth, I beléeue in that caſe they know al alike, but what ſhold I ſay of ye cure of ſuch a wound, if the Chyrurgion know not where it is, nor of what importance, but worketh by imagination, and if that nature doth preuaile, and that the wounde doth heale, it is by the good fortune of the phiſition, ſo yt for wounds inwardly I conclude no other at this time, but will leaue it to thoſe that know more then I, and hereafter I will diſcourſe of vlcers and impoſtumes inwardly what they are and how to cure them with our order: ye ſhall vnderſtand that there are a number of kindes of vlcers and impoſtumes that may ingender inwardly, but it ſéemeth to me ſo hard to vnderſtand, that I can determine nothing that were true, and the cauſe is this, that wée haue ſéene an infinite of Phiſitions and Chyrurgions that haue viſited one Impoſtumated or Vlcerated, and the Phyſition coulde not knowe the place,

and particular of that impoſtume or vlcer, if that the patient do not tell him and ſhew him, and cauſe him to féele with his hande, and this is moſt true, &amp; therefore if one cannot reſolue him of outward things that he may ſée &amp; féele with his hande, how can he reſolue him when one of thoſe accidents is within the bodye, where the patient knowes not himſelfe, which is grieued. Truely I would gladly know what iudgement they would giue of that matter, for bicauſe if ther be any Impoſtume or vlcer in any part of the body, the ſicke ſhall féele great offence and paine, neuertheleſſe he cannot tell wher it is, nor what part is hurte, ſo that I conclude, if that the Patient know not, much leſſe the Phiſition knoweth, and of this I haue made a large diſcourſe in Caprici medicinalle, for as I haue ſayd before, in this caſe I know nothing. Neuertheleſſe when it ſhall come to his place, I will write a diſcourſe of the order to cure the moſt part of Vlcers and Impoſtumes, but touching woundes, I will promiſſe no more thē I haue ſaid before. Alſo I wil write excellent remedies of great experience, with the which all woundes, ſo they be not mortall, may be helpt and healed, and alſo the reaſons conuenient in that matter.
            
            
               An order to vſe in healing all manner of diſeaſes apperteining vnto the Chyrurgian.
               WOundes and all other ſorts of ſores, are of ſundry and diuers kindes, as is aforeſaid, neuertheleſſe the order to helpe them is not much different one from ye other, if we ſhould ſay only the troth without abuſe. For ye ſhal vnderſtand that Nature is the maſter of al things created, &amp; the Phiſitian and Chyrurgian are helpers of that Nature, as the Auntient profeſſors

of the Art haue affirmed. Than ſéeing this is ſo, what néede we to make ſo much adoe, hauing Nature that worketh ſo gently, if it be not hindered by the miniſter, &amp; therefore if we wil ſpeake of woundes, I ſay that the miniſter hath thrée operations to do, and no moe, and the reſt leaue to nature that worketh gently. The thrée operations that the Maſter hath to doe, are theſe: To defend the wound ſo that there runneth no humours to it, and that it putrifie not, and to kéepe it cleane, and when the miniſter hath done that, letto Nature worke that which ſhe will worke well, and if any deſire to ſée if it will be ſo in effect, ye may ſée by a dogge, for if he hath a great wound vpon his bodie, he healeth it without any medicine, onely with dyet &amp; kéeping it cleane with his tongue, and this is moſt true, that thoſe which doe helpe woundes by inchauntment, doe nothing but kéepe the wound cleane, &amp; cauſe the patient kéepe a dyet, &amp; ſo nature worketh as well on man as on a dog, therefore let none maruell of this authoritie of a dogge, although I approue the lyke of a Chriſtian. But for ſo much as it woulde be good to helpe Nature, that it might worke with more ſpéedineſſe, as huſbandmen do and gardeiners, who bicauſe they would haue Nature to worke the better &amp; quicker in their ground, doe caſt there-on diuers ſorts of dounges, &amp;c. The which is done only to helpe Nature to worke the quicker, and to conclude, I ſaye that the Chyrurgian ſhould do the ſame in helping of wounds. But as for vlcers of diuers ſorts, it were neceſſary to finde out the cauſe, bicauſe they come of diuers cauſes, for when ye cauſe is found, it wil bée more eaſie to bée helpt, bicauſe vlcers cannot come but by great diſtemperaunce of nature in our bodyes, as by great heat or colde, or by replexions of ye body. Therfore in this caſe it is neceſſary to purge the body: firſt, to eaſe Nature

which is offended, &amp; to extinguiſh the ſuperfluous heat or colde that is in the body: That being done ye miniſter or helper of Nature hath thrée things to do. The firſt is to mortifie or kil ye ſore, the ſecond to mundifie, &amp; the third to incarnate, &amp; then nature wil cicatrize it, &amp; theſe thrée operations are to be vſed in vlcers. Alſo Impoſtumes are cauſed of diuers accidēts, in the which it is alſo neceſſary to ſeeke out the cauſe, where-by to know what purgations are fit to purge ye body of the ſuperfluous humors, &amp; then the miniſter hath .3. things to do in yt caſe. Firſt to bring it to maturation quickly, then when it is ripe and broke to mundifie it well, and thirdly to incarnate it, &amp; theſe are the .3. operations that are to be done in an impoſtume to help nature to worke wel, and ſo following this order thy worke ſhal proue wel &amp; go ye right way, as héerafter I wil ſhew in his place ye operatiōs to vſe in ye effect with ye order to helpe thē, &amp; alſo to make thy vnguents, ſhewing their qualytie &amp; vertue, &amp; will proue by reaſon thoſe things that are doubtfull, ſo that euery one ſhall be ſatiſfied in that matter.
            
            
               Of medicines to be vſed in all kinde of woundes outward with eaſe and breuitie.
               HAuing declared what outward woundes are, it is alſo neceſſary to ſhew ye order how to cure them, with as much ſpéed &amp; eaſe as it is poſſible, &amp; therfore I wil begin firſt with ſimple wounds yt are only in the fleſh, without offence of veynes, ſinewes, or bones, although theſe néede no helpe, but onely to ioyne ye lyps cloſe together, &amp; if néede be to ſtitch them cloſe, &amp; then let nature worke, ye which in ſhort tyme will heale them, but if thou by Art wilt helpe nature, thou ſhalt anoynt them with oyle of frankencenſe once a daye.

But wounds where veynes are cut, haue néede of preſent helpe, and artificiall meanes and ſufficient remedies to helpe it with as much ſpéede as may be, ſo that the veynes cut may ioyne agayn together, without any great offence of the woūd, &amp; that is done in this order. The firſt thing is to ioyne the parts cloſe together &amp; ſtitch it wel, not as the common Chyrurgians do, but as they doe vſe to ſtitch bagges, and when it is ſtitched cloſe, annoynt it onely vppon the wounde with our Magno licore, and lay there-on a cloth wet in ye ſame Oyle very warme, then take Hipericon with the ſéed, Millefolli, Viticella, Ana, and make theroff a powder, the which thou ſhalt ſtrowe vppon the wound béeing dreſt, and round about it, for this medicine doth aſſuttiliate the matter that runneth vnto the wound, and taketh it forth with great eaſe and without paine of the wound, for this is the moſt ſuffereigne medicine in that caſe, that Nature with Art may make, &amp; hath bene proued a thouſand times by experience in diuers places. But thoſe woundes where bones and ſinewes are hurt, haue néede of great artificie and cunning, bicauſe they be of importaunce. But when the ſinews be onely offended, it were neceſſary to ſtitch them preſently, as I haue ſayd of thoſe where veynes are cut, but not to dreſſe it with Magno licore, but in ſtéede thereoff to take our Oleum benedictum, and Oyle of frankencenſe, of each a lyke, for thoſe Oyles doe excéedingly comfort the ſinewes that are cut, and when it happeneth that a ſinew hath a puncture or is cut halfe way, in yt caſe it wer neceſſary to cut it ouer-thwart, bicauſe it ſhall bring no Spaſmus to the wound, but if ſo be than that the bone be hurt, and that there be any part to come forth: it were neceſſarye to leaue the wound open, vntill the bone commeth forth, and then to incarnate it, and this thou ſhalt doe with our artificiall

balme, for the ſame 
                     〈◊〉
                   for woundes, and lay therevpon the Cerote of Gualtifredo di medi, the which healeth it with ſpéede, and ſo with theſe orders thou maiſt helpe all the aforeſaide ſorts of woundes, and the defenſiue to vſe in theſe woundes is this. Rec. Aqua vitae made of pure wine &amp; that wil burne all away, and put therein Hipericon, Millifollie, Viticella, Betonica, and then wet a cloath in that infuſion and lay it for a defenſiue rounde about the wounde, and ſo thou ſhalt haue thine intent to the great ſatiſfaction of the patient. Wounds in the heade, are helpt as thoſe are, where the ſinowes are offended, there are alſo dyuers other ſorts of wounds which are helpt with the aforeſaide remedies.
            
            
               To helpe vlcers of all ſortes.
               SEing that vlcers are of diuers &amp; ſundrie kindes, it were neceſſarye to knowe of what kinde and quality they are, ſo that thou maiſt help them in forme and order conuenient, and firſt I will write of the coroſiue vlceras of a wound Cancrenated, mal di Formicola, and other ſortes of vlcers that go créeping vppon the fleſh. The cure of theſe kindes of vlcers is to apply quickly our Cauſtike to mortifie the euill, the which thou ſhalt do thus, wette a little bumbaſte in our Cauſtike, and therewith waſh all the ſore, &amp; then leaue it ſo open 24. houres without binding it faſt, &amp; when 24. houres are paſt, waſhe the ſore with ſtrong Vineger &amp; water, of eche a like quantitie, with charge that there remaine none of the Cauſtike in the ſore, then laye theron butter waſhed, with a coleworte leafe vntill the aſker or deade fleſh fall away, then take our Cerote Magiſtrale, with a little Precipitate ſtrawed thereon, and their annoynt it with Magno licore, and

lay it vpon the ſore▪ for this 
                     〈◊〉
                   helpeth al manner of coraliue vlcers without any other helpe, and euerye plaiſter will ſerue thrée or foure dayes, taking them off, euery 24. houres, and make them cleane, and then laye them on againe, and as for the filthy vlcer that I haue ſhewed off in his Chapter, yée ſhall dreſſe them onely with our Vngento magno. The which without any other helpe will heale them quickelye: But yée muſt euery foure dayes touch them with Aqua fortis, drawen from Precipitate, the whiche watter draweth forth the offenſiue matter, and leaueth it purified and cleane, and in all other ſortes of Vlcers, our Balme artificiall, our Magno licore, Oyle of Waxe and Terpentine, the blacke Cerote of Gualtifredo, di medi, our Cerote Magiſtrale with Precipitate, are able to helpe, be they neuer ſo euell.
            
            
               The order to be vſed in curing Impoſtumes of diuers ſortes.
               THere be manye ſundrye kindes of Impoſtumes that commeth to mannes bodye, that are cauſed, of dyuers ſundrye accidentes, and therefore muſt be cured by dyuers orders and with ſundrye medicines according to his kinde, bicauſe ſome Impoſtume is cauſed of a contuſion or bruſed fleſh, ſome are certeine grieues, that Nature woulde diſcharge hir ſelfe off, and ſo ſendeth forth that matter, ſome are cauſed of colde, other of melancholike humours, and other are cauſed of corrupſion of the Pockes, and theſe are the kindes of Impoſtumes that commonly come, and hereafter I will ſhewe the order to cure them, one after another.
               And firſt of thoſe that are cauſed of a contuſion bicauſe it is bruſed fleſh, for euerye contuſion muſt bée

putrified and brought to matter, therefore make a Maturatiue and bring it to ſupperac
                     •••
                  , and when you knowe there is matter, preſently launce them and dreſſe them with this medecine as well within as without, the whiche without any other helpe will heale any great contuſion. But you muſt make the Vnguent freſhe euery day, and with newe Egges, yee ſhall mixe the youlke of an Egge with our Magno licore, and there-with dreſſe them. And as for thoſe Impoſtumes that come by indiſpoſition of Nature, are certeine, Sboryne, a word ſo called in Italian, by the which nature woulde preuaile, it were neceſſarye to let thoſe haue their cures according to Nature, vntill they breake of themſelues, and when they are brooken dreſſe them within with this Vnguent. Rec. Oyle of Roſes, ounc. 6. Litarge of gold in fine powder, ounc. 2. Storax liquida ounc. 1. Terpentine, ounc. 2. yellow Waxe ounc. 3. mixe them and boyle them on the fire vntill it be blacke, and if it be to hard put thereto more oyle of Roſes, &amp; make it in forme of an vnguent, and therewith dreſſe thoſe kindes of Impoſtumes, and lay thereon the Cerote Diapalma, and there-with will be wrought myracles. Alſo for thoſe Impoſtumes cauſed of colde, ye ſhall vſe hot medicines and 
                     •
                  tractiue: the Cerote of Oxicrocij is excellent in thoſe kinde of impoſtumes, our Balme artificial, or the water, &amp; ſuch like thinges as are temperate by Nature. But thoſe Impoſtumes that haue their Originall of the french pockes, are euil &amp; maling, bicauſe their cauſe is 
                     ••
                  a
                     •
                  ing and euell, and therefore their cure is with great purging, &amp; to let the impoſtume ripe of himſelf, &amp; when ye launce it, dreſſe it within, wt our vnguento magno, mixed thus. Rec. vnguēto magno, ounc. 2. magno licore ounc. 1. precipitate ounc. 
                     ſ
                     semis
                  . mixe thē wel together, &amp; therewt dreſſe yt impoſtume, ye which will heale quickly &amp; well,

and lay theron our Cerote Magiſtrale, with this charge that in all the cures aforeſaid yée purge the body wel, ſo that the humours runne not vnto the place offended, and vſe defenſiues according to the kinde of Impoſtume, as Oyle of Frankēſence, of Terpentine, of wax, of hunny, Aqua vitae, al theſe are excelēt defenſiues by themſelues, annoynting them rounde about the Impoſtume.
            
            
               The order to cure all manner of Fiſtoloes.
               FIſtoloes as I haue ſaid before, are of diuers kindes, and cauſed of dyuers accidents, and ſo likewiſe they haue néede of dyuers medicines, and firſt I wil write of thoſe fiſtoloes that come of woundes euill healed, and that haue made a callowe in that order that nature cannot ſcicatriſe and ſo remaine fiſtolated, and ye cure of theſe kind of fiſtoloes is to put therin a Rupture that doth cutte and mortifie the callow, and cauſeth it to fall awaye, and then with incarnating medicines, incarnate them and ſcicatriſe them and this is the true cure of theſe fiſtoloes. But thoſe kinde of fiſtoloes that nature cauſeth, to eaſe hir ſelfe of ſome accident, commonly doe come in the lower partes about the fundament and they be very perillous, and not to be healed as they before were. But they muſt bée with purging the bodye, ſtomacke, and heade, the which is to be done thus. Firſt purge them x. or xij. dayes with our Magiſtral Syrope, then giue them our Aromatico, and drinke thereon a little white Wine, then purge the heade with a perfume made of Mirra, and Cynaber, after theſe thinges bée done yée ſhall rectifie the Lyuer with ſome decoccion fitte for that purpoſe, as of Lignum ſanctum, or Salſa peryllia, or ſuch like,

that worke effecte, for this medicine doth alſo helpe Fiſtola lacrimoſa, that cōmonly come about the eyes, or eares. There be other Fiſtoloes in forme of a ſore, which muſt be helpt with purging, and laye vpon the ſore our Cerote magiſtrale with Precipitate &amp; annoint it with Magno licore, for with this Cerote only may all fiſtolated ſores be healed, for it doth mundifie and afterwardes cicatrize it, there be alſo diuers ſuche lyke matters that are cured eaſely, if ye apply therevnto thoſe medicines that are appropriate.
            
            
               To helpe all manner of ſcabbes.
               THe kindes of ſcabbes be many, and cauſed of diuers cauſes, and their cures are alſo diuers wayes. Thoſe that are cauſed of replection of the body and of groſe bloud, ye which is cauſed by eating aboundance of ſuch meates as are of great nouriſhment, ye which if thou wilt cure them, it were neceſſary to purge them with our Siruppe Solutiuo .x. or .xij. dayes, then giue him or hir one dram of our Aromatico in ye morning faſting, and drinke ther-on a cup of ſwéete wine, then let him ſweat thrée or foure times, and after annoint him with our Vnguento magno two or thrée times, &amp; it will heale him of thoſe kinde of ſcabbes.
               Now to cure that kinde of ſcabbe that is red and ſmall, and cauſeth great itching, you ſhall make a decoction of hearbes that coole the lyuer and purifie the bloud, as Borage, Bugloſſe, Endiue, Mayden-haire, Liuer-wort, Harts-tongue, Agrimony, Citrach, Succory and ſuch lyke hearbs, then purge with Aloes, the iuyce of Elder rootes, Iera pigra ſolutina, and ſuch like as doth coole the liuer and bloud, &amp; then annoint them with Vnguento di Litargirio, &amp; therwt you ſhal helpe

all thoſe kinde of ſcabbes. There be alſo certein great ſcabbes ouer all the body, the which are very thicke, &amp; thoſe are a kinde of the Pockes, the which maye bée helpt with giuing thē our Pillole contra il mal Franceſe, the quātitie is according to the diſcretiō of ye Phiſition, and theſe Pilles ye ſhall take thrée times euery third day, and then annoynt them with our Vnguento magno, and he ſhal be helpt. Ther is an other kinde of ſcabbe that goeth créeping with a dry cruſt like vnto petigine, and thoſe are the méere Pockes inueterated, and the order to cure them is thus, giue them our Sirop againſt the melancholike humour, bicauſe it purgeth the bloud and cooleth the lyuer, and diſſolueth that viſcous humour that ingendereth that cruſt, that being done giue them our Aromatico, &amp; annoint them with our Magno licore, and he ſhall be perfectly helpt in ſhortt ſpace. There are other kinde of ſcabbes that come through great colde, and thoſe are healed onelye with annoynting them with Oyle of Frankenſence thrée or foure times.
            
            
               To helpe Mal di formica.
               THoſe be certein vlcers which go créeping in the vpper parte of the fleſhe and haue manye orifices or mouths, and theſe are cauſed of the Peckes béeing inueterated, the which are cured in that order that the Pockes is; and that is this. Firſt, purge the bodye with▪ our Electuario Angelica, the which purgeth away groſe and maligne humors, and euacuateth the ſtomacke of cholar and fleame, this being done, cauſe the patiēt to ſweat, for that wil a ſubtiliate the humors, and cauſe them to come forth, that being done, take our Cerote magiſtrale and ſtroe there-on Precipitate, and then annoynt it with our Magno licore, and laye it

vppon the ſore, and ther let it lye .24. houres before yée chaunge it, then make it cleane and lay it on againe, for that Plaſter may ſerue foure dayes, making it cleane euery .24. houres, and when the Plaſter will draw no more matter, you ſhall vſe our Vnguento magno, the which wil help it in ſhort time. But if it do happen that this order doe not cure thē, then it would be neceſſary for them to be annoynted with the vnction for ye Porks, and to annoynt them ſo long til the mouth be ſore, and when that ſigne doth appeare, annoynt them no more, for hée will ſpit or vaper at the mouth, for twelue or fiftéene dayes, and as ſoone as he vapoureth, make a Bathe and waſhe him well, and waſh the mouth with wine and with-out all doubte it ſhall helpe him God willyng, nowe héereafter I will write of certeine thinges which are vſed of common Chyrurgians, with a briefe diſcourſe vppon them.
            
            
               Of the Towe which is layd vpon wounds of common Chyrurgians.
               THe pleggits of Tow which is layd vpon woundes when they are firſt ſtitched is made in this order. Rec. The white of an Egge, Salt, and Roſe-water, and beat them together, and when the wound is ſtitched, they lay it ther-on, bicauſe the bloud ſhould ſtint, and the wound remaine ſhut, ſo that it maye be helpt with more eaſe. Now touching this, I will ſhew the reaſon why they vſe it in their firſt cure, ye ſhall vnderſtand that euery like deſireth his like, to ſuccor him or kéepe company with him, and therefore the Auncient, our auncient profeſſors of Arte, willed the white of an Egge to be occupied in woundes, bicauſe it is a

ſubſtaunce of fleſh lyke vnto the other fleſh, and to declare the troth I will proue it by naturall reaſon, for ye ſhall vnderſtand that the white of the Egge is that part which ingendreth the fleſh, the ſkinne, and the fethers of the henne, and the yolke engendreth only the guts and other entrayles of the animall, then ſéeing the white is that which ingendreth the fleſh onely, it is lyke vnto fleſh, as it is ſayd before, then the ſalt is a materiall which preſerueth al things from putrifaction, as is ſéene by experience dayly, and for that conſideration it was put in this cōpoſition to preſerue the fleſh, the Roſe-water by nature is colde and drye, and by his coldneſſe defendeth the inflamation, and by his dryneſſe is repercuſſiue &amp; mitigateth, ſo that theſe are the reaſons why the ſayd Tow is layd vpon wounds, but I would to God that ſuch things were vſed as by their excellent operations would helpe and heale from the beginning to the latter ending, &amp; to leaue of ſuch trifling orders.
            
            
               Of the diſgeſtiue with the which they dreſſe woundes after the aforeſayd Towe.
               AFter that the tow is taken away from the wound they dreſſe it with a compoſition called diſgeſtiue, bicauſe it diſgeſteth ye wound although this medicine be ſom what ſcrupulus &amp; againſt ſcience, &amp; the reaſon is this, ye ſhal vnderſtand that when a man is wounded, the place before was ſownde, and therefore being wounded, our true duetie is to help ye ſame wound and not to diſgeſt or rotte it, as commonlye all Chyrurgians doe, for by rotting of it in that order, it is perillous, and more daungerous to be cured, as is daily ſéene by experience, and this no man can denye.

But nowe I will followe our regiment in ſhewing what this diſgeſtiue is, the which is made thus.
               
                  Rec. The youlke of two Eggs, Terpentine waſhed ounce 1. Oyle of Roſes ounce 
                     ſ
                     semis
                  . mixe them in an Vnguent, and this is the diſgeſtiue wher-with they dreſſe it vntil the ſore haue made quitter or matter ynough, and then they vſe to dreſſe it with medicines much differing from the ſame, but I meruaile much at the diuerſitie of this matter, that this diſgeſtiue being applied to a putrified vlcer, worketh diuers effects, for it healeth it diuinely: and moreouer, ye ſhall vnderſtand that if it be applied vnto when they be incarnated, it will ſcicatriſe them meruailouſly, for truelye theſe are thinges worthy to bee knowen, and he that vnderſtandeth the reaſon I accompt him to bee wiſe, for if this diſgeſtiue be laide on freſh woundes it putrifieth and rotteth them, againe being laide on a filthy ſore it doth mundifie and heale, and then if it be applyed on a wounde incarnated, it Scicatriſeth it and healeth, for this I haue done diuers and ſundry times, the which is to be woundred off.
            
            
               Of the mundification vnguent wherewith they dreſſe the woundes after they are digeſted to mundifie them.
               WHen woundes are come to digeſtion and that they purge, alwayes they chaunge vnguents, and they apply Vnguentes that haue vertue to mundifie the wounde and make it cleane, ſo that it may the better incarnate, and that vnguent is called properly a mundificatiue, the which is made of Barly flower &amp; is the mundificatiue they vſe 8. or 10. dayes to-gether for if the wounde were not well mundified, it woulde

neuer incarnate-well ſo that this vnguent is moſt neceſſary in that operation in reſpect of the ingredience.
            
            
               Of their incarnatiue wherwith they dreſſe the wounde after it is mundified.
               WHen that the wounde is mundified, ſo that, thervnto commeth ſmall quantitie of matter, than it is neceſſary to apply vnguentes that incarnate, ſo that they may cicatrize with more eaſe, and this kinde of incarnatyue is in the moſt vſe among the commō Chirurgions, the which is made of Terpentine, Waxe, and Franckenſcence, and a little Oyle of Roſes mixt of the fire, and this is their incarnatiue.
            
            
               A rare ſecreate, the which this author did ſende vnto a very friende of his, being in the warres in Africa, the which helpeth all woundes, either by cut, thruſt, galling with arrowes, or hargabuſh ſhotte, or otherwiſe.
               THe firſt thing that ye ſhall doe is to waſh the wounde very cleane with vryne and than dry it very well, then put there-in our Quintaeſſence of wine, and preſently ioyne the partes cloſe together, and ſtitch or ſowe them well, but in any wiſe ſowe nothing but the ſkinne, for other-wiſe it woulde cauſe great paine, then put thereon fiue or ſixe droppes of our Balſamo, and vppon the wounde laye a cloth weate in our Magno licore, as hotte as he may ſuffer it, and this do the firſt day, then the next day folow this order, firſt put thereon our Quintaeſſence &amp; a little Balſamo, and then our Magno licore very hot &amp; neuer chaunge this medicine vntill he be whole▪
               
            
            
               
               Of thoſe vnguents that Cicatrize wounds.
               THe vnguents that cicatrize wounds after they are incarnated be of dyuers kindes, although they work one effect in cicatrizing or cauſing a ſkine. The digeſtion that is written off before, being applyed vppon a wounde incarnated, it doth cicatrize it with ſpéede, the like doth Diachilon &amp; vnguentum de tutia. The Cerote called Gratia dei, although theſe be ſundrie compoſitions one differing from another, yet in effect they ſerue all to this cicatrization as ye may ſee by experience, &amp; this they doe bicauſe they be temperate and of good qualities and ſo they helpe nature to work more quielitier, and they are called helpers of nature. But theſe kinde of vnguents that worke by them-ſelues, as Vnguento Apoſtolorum, the Cauſticke, Aegyp
                        ••
                     atum, the rottery &amp; ſuch like vnguents as worke with violence, and ſuppreſſe nature, and do that which nature cannot doe by it ſelfe without helpe, but all thoſe vnguentes that are not violent, neither in heate or colde, are apt to cicatrize woundes, and all ſores, that are mundified and incarnated.
            
            
               A remedie to helpe a wounde with great ſpeede, of our inuention.
               WOundes of diuers and ſundry forts are very perillous of life, but to helpe them quickly bicauſe the patient may take no harme, ye ſhall vſe this ſecret, waſh the wound with our water of balme, and cleanſe it well, and lay theron clothes wet in Oyle of Frankencenſe made by diſtillation, and therwith thou ſhalt heale any great wounde in ſhort time, as I haue proued diuers and ſundry times, in ſundry cauſes.
            
            
               
               An excellent ſecreate to heale woundes of Gunne ſhotte or Arrowes without any daunger.
               IF thou wilt helpe the aforeſaide wounds it were neceſſarye firſt to ioyne the partes cloſe too, and waſh it with our Aqua celeſtis, and laye thereon our Oleum balſami, &amp; there-with thou ſhalt ſaue the liues of many wounded perſons.
            
            
               A diſcourſe vppon olde woundes that are not yet healed and their ſouereigne remedie.
               WHen that woundes are euel healed and that they impoſtumate, and that the arme, or legge, or other partes where they were wounded is indurated and full of paine, thou ſhalt vſe this ſecrete of our inuention neuer knowen before of olde nor newe writers, for it is of greate vertue and many times proued: firſt yée ſhall waſh the wounde well and make it cleane rounde about, then waſh the wounde with our Quintaeſſence, and make it to fume, bicauſe our Quintaeſſence doth open the powers, and aſuttiliateth the matter, and cauſeth the humour to come forth, that being done, annoynt it al ouer we our Magno licore, &amp; thus doing, before thrée dayes ende he ſhal féele great eaſe, and in ſhort time it ſhall bée helpt bicauſe this medecine taketh awaye the hardeneſſe and healeth the wounde, and comforteth the place offended.
            
            
               
               To diſſolue a brooſe in ſhort time, when it is new done.
               THeſe are called contuſions, vnto the which nature ſendeth quickly great quantitie of humiditie, and in that place, it cauſeth Impoſtumation: But if our Chyrurgians would be dilygent and quicke, all contuſions might be helpt with great eaſe in ſhort time, and therefore if thou wilt worke miracles in yt cure, vſe this our meanes, and it will tourne to thy great honour, and the remedy is this.
               
                  Rec. Lyquid Verniſh, pound .3. Yeolow waxe, ounce. 4. Common aſhes, ounce .6. Aqua vitae rectified, poūd. 2. Put al the afore-ſayd matters in a Retort of glaſſe, and diſtill it with a gentle fire vntill al the ſubſtance be come foorth, the which will be Oyle and water, the which ye ſhall ſeperate, and kéepe them, and when occaſion ſerueth, annoynt the brooſe there-with and laye ther-on a cloth wet in ye ſame, for this is a miraculus medicine experimented &amp; proued by reaſon, for an experiment without reaſon is as a man without clothes, and therefore if thou wilt know great &amp; rare ſecrets neuer written before, looke in my Spechio del ſcientia vniuerſalli, and in my Theſoro del vita humana, and there-in thou ſhalt finde ſtraunge things, proued by reaſon and experience, the which bookes God willyng, I meane to ſet foorth in the Englſh tongue to the profite of my Countrey.
            
            
               To helpe a wound quickly that is in perill of any accident.
               WOundes in ſome parts of the body are very daungerous of lyfe, and ſpecially where ſinewes bée

cut or pearced, or veynes or muſcles hurte, or bones broke, and by an infinit of other particulars, which being open or euil healed, the patient may be in daunger of lyfe, bicauſe the winde entereth in, and they cauſe paintes and inflamation, and therefore to auoyde all theſe afore-ſayd matters, ſo that the wound ſhall haue no detriment, vſe this remedie. Firſt ioyne the parts cloſe together, and put ther-in our Quintaeſſence, and lay there-on a cloth wet in our Balme, and binde it falt that the ayre get not in, for it is very hurtfull, ye ſhall vnderſtand that theſe are two of the excellenteſt medicines that maye be found, bicauſe our Quintaeſſence doth aſſuttiliate the bloud, and taketh it foorth, and taketh away the paine, &amp; the Balme doth warme and comfort the place offended, and will not ſuffer any matter to runne ther-vnto by any meanes, for this is moſt true, as I haue proued diuers &amp; ſundry times, and alwayes haue had good ſucceſſe.
            
            
               To ſtop the flux of blood in woundes with great ſpeed.
               VVHen there is any great flux of bloud in wounds by reaſon of ſome 
                     ••
                  eyne that is rut, and that the Chyrurgians would ſhop it, it were neceſſary to ſtitch it well, but not as the common Chyrurgians do with wide ſtitches, but ſtich it very cloſe and hard, and put ther-in our Quintaeſſence, and vpon the wound ſtrew the bloud of a man dryed in powder, and laye vppon the bloud a cloth wet in our Balme artificiaill, verye warme, and vppon that binde the wounde with ligaments very ſtraight, and euerye daye twice, waſh it with our Quintaeſſence, and round about annoynt it with our Balme, and alſo caſt ther-on our ſecret powder for woundes, and that do morning and euening,

euery day without opening of the wound, and in that time the wound wil remayne wel, and the-veynes wil be in a manner healed ſo that they will not bléede, giuing you charge that the wounded man-kéepe no dyet, bicauſe ye vertue being weake, 
                     •
                  elaueth the veynes, and that cauſeth the fluxe of bloud.
            
            
               An other remedie to ſtay the ſlux of blood in a wounde.
               WHen there is a great ſlux of blood in a wounde, the perfecteſt remedie, is to ſtitch it verye cloſe, then take mans bloud being dryed and made in powder, and caſt it vpon the wounde, and binde it ſomewhat ſtraight, and ſo let it remaine .24. houres &amp; when ye vnbinde it, take héede that ye remoue nothing, and caſt on more dryed bloud vppon the wound▪ annoint it rounde about with our Oleum Philoſophorum de Terpentina &amp; Caera, and binde it vp againe other 24. houres, &amp; then binde it gently, and annoynt ye wound with Oyle of Frankenſence, &amp; ſo in ſhorte time it will be whole, giuing, thée great charge that ye putte in no tent or ſuch lyke, and then thou ſhalt ſée miracles.
            
            
               Of our Cerote magno, that helpeth againſt all ſorts of ſores and woundes.
               THis Cerote is of great vertue, and healeth all mā
                  ner of ſores and wounds if it be ſpred on a cloth and layd there-on, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Galbanum. ℥.1. Ammoniacum. ℥.2. Oppoponax. ℥.2. Ariſtolochia longa. ℥.1. New wax. ℥.18. Fiue Mirrha, Olibanum, Verdigreſe, ana. ℥.1. Bedellin. ℥.2. Gum of the Pr
                     •
                  in
                     •
                   trée. ℥.
                     
                        •
                     . Lapichemarites. ℥.2. Terpentine, Frankencenſe, of each. ℥.4. Oyle of wax. ℥.3.
                  
Beath all thoſe that are to be beaten, and ſearce them finely, and kéepe euery one by him-ſelfe, then diſſolue the gummes in diſtilled Vineger, according to Arte, and then vaper away the Vineger againe, &amp; ſtrayne the gummes through a cloth, then take the wax with as much ſwéet oyle and melt them on the fire, &amp; when they are melt, put there-vnto ounce .2. of Litarge of gold finely ſearced, and ſtirre them continually vntill it be boyled, the which ye ſhall know by this token. Put a feather there-in, &amp; if it be boyled inough, it wil burne ſtraight wayes, or els let it boyle vntill it burn it, then take it from the fire and let it coole a lyttle, &amp; than put in the gunns &amp; ſtir them wel together, &amp; ſet it on ye fire again, &amp; it wil riſe with a great noyſe, &amp; therfore let it boyle vntil it do fal down againe, that take it from the fire &amp; put there-vnto all ye afore-ſaid powders, and ſtir it vntill it be colde, and there-with thou ſhalt worke meruaylous cures, if it be made wel, according to Art.
            
            
               Of our magiſtral Vnguent that helpeth diuers ſortes of ſores.
               THis Vnguent is appropriate for manye kinde of ſores bicauſe it comfortech the ſore &amp; taketh awaye the payne and draweth the matter from the lower parts or bottome of yt ſore. The which matter is cauſe of the payne, it kéepeth it alſo from accidents, giuing you charge that it be made artificially, for other-wiſe it will not bée of ſo much vertue, and this is the Vnguent.
               
                  Rec. Litarge of golde, ounce .4. Oyle of Roſes, pound 2. Boyle them in a Copper pan ſo long, as if ye put a feather there-in, it will burne it, then it is ſodde, then put there-to of newe Waxe, ounc. 6. Storax liquida,
                  
ounce 2. common bunny, ounce 3. then let it boyle a while vntil they be wel incorporated, thē take it from ye fire, &amp; put ther-to Olibanum, Mirra, Mercury Precipitate, Oyle of Waxe, Oyle of Terpentine, Oyle of Frankenſence, ana ounce 2. mixe them wel till they be incorporated, then put therto pure rectified Aqua vitae, ounces 4. and mixe them well, and then it is ended: &amp; this is of my inuention, where-with I haue done very ſtraunge cures.
            
            
               To make Oyle of Frankenſence.
               TAke a retort of glaſſe, wel luted, and fill it halfe full of Frankenſence, &amp; for euery pounde of Frankenſence put there-vnto ounces 3. of common Aſhes finely ſerced, then diſtill it in ſande, and the firſt that commeth forth will be water, the which wilbe cleare, then increaſe the fire, and there will come foorth an Oyle of the coulour of a Rubye, the which kéepe cloſe in a glaſſe, the firſt water is of merueilous vertue in diuers operations, but one myraculous experiment I will not leaue to write off, bicauſe it is a thing verye neceſſary, &amp; is this. For thoſe that haue chilblanes, or kibes, or chophes in the handes or féete that commeth through colde, ye ſhall firſt perfume the parts that are ſore ouer the fume of hot water, ſo that they may ſweate, then drie them and waſh them with the aforeſaide water, and put on a paire of gloues, and in ſhort time they ſhall be whole, it helpeth alſo the white ſcall and ſcabbes, and ſuch like thinges. The Oyle ſerueth in many operations, and ſpecially in all colde diſeaſes, if they be inwardly, giue thereof euerye morning one ſcruple to drinke, and if they be outward annoynt. Alſo it helpeth all manner of wounds be they neuer ſo great.
               
                  If ye annoynt them therwith, and kéepe them cloſe from the ayre: And in any wiſe vſe no tenting to kéepe them open but wette a cloth therein, and lay it theron, and in ſhort ſpace they will be healed, alſo it diſſolueth a brooſe in ſhort ſpace if ye annoynt it often therwith, this oyle ſerueth alſo for painters to make verniſh.
            
            
               Of Oyle of Waxe and his effect.
               THis Oyle of Waxe is merueilous excellent, for ſo much as it ſerueth for the moſt part againſt all diſeaſes: which Oyle Raymond Lulli doth approue to be a more heauenly and deuine medecine then humaine, and is moſt rare for woundes, but it is not good for commō Chirurgions bicauſe it helpeth a great wounde in x. or xij. dayes at the moſt, but as for ſmall wounds it healeth them in 3. or 4. dayes annoynting onely the wounde therewith, and lay there on clothes wette in the ſame. Alſo this oyle worketh myracles againſt diuers diſeaſes inwardly, if ye giue theroff one drame wt white wine, &amp; as for thoſe whoſe heaire &amp; heard do fal away it is a rare thing and of great profite, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. A retort of glaſſe well luted and put therein what quantitie of Waxe you will, ſo that it bee not halfe full, and for euery pounde of Waxe put thervnto 4. ounces of ye powder of bricks, then ſet it in a forneyes, and giue it gentle fire vntill all the ſubſtance be come forth, the which oyle will be congealed hard, the which is his perfection, for if you will diſtill it ſo many times that it congeale no more, it will be too hot &amp; ſharpe, and not to be vſed within the body in any wiſe, but the firſt diſtillation you may vſe ſafely inwardlye and make Vncions for any kinde of diſeaſe where néede ſhall require, and alwayes it will be good, and

doe no hurte in any wiſe in any diſeaſe, and therefore this Oyle ought to be had in greate regarde of all men.
            
            
               To helpe the tooth atch, that is cauſed of rotten teeth, or that commeth of a diſſention of the heade.
               THe téeth being rotten or corrupted alwayes cauſeth great paine and many times it commeth of a diſſention from the heade and ſuch like humours as Cattars, Eriſipella, but let it come of what cauſe it will I will ſhewe a remedy of great importance, and it is very ſhort, ye ſhal take our Aqua realle and holde it in your mouth a good white and then ſpit it out againe, and this ye ſhall doe for thrée dayes together euery day once, then afterwarde it were neceſſary to waſh your mouth in the like manner wt our Aqua balſami for the ſpace of a moneth, &amp; ſo the tooth atch ſhalbe taken away with eaſe, for this is our ſecrete and may be vſed in all times of the yeare.
            
            
               Againſt a ſtincking breath.
               THe breath may ſtincke through many cauſes, as by vlcers in the mouth or by corrupt and rotten téeth, and ſometime it commeth of the ſtomacke, and that is euill to be helpt, and therefore if thou wilt helpe theſe thou muſt vſe diuers remedies, and firſt to helpe thoſe that haue their mouthes vlcerated, ye ſhall giue them a quantitie of our Pillole aquilone, and then let them waſh their mouthes with our Aqua realle, and ſo the vlcers ſhalbe helpt, and the mouth ſhal not ſtincke. But when the ſtench commeth of rotten téeth, vſe the aforeſaide remedie or medicine that is written,

for the tooth atche, the which will make the téeth as white as ſnowe, and will acke no more, but when the ſtincke commeth from the ſtomacke, it were neceſſary to purge the body with our Sirope Solutiuo, ſixe or ſeuen dayes, and then to take our Aromatico, that being done, take rectified Aqua vitae &amp; ye water of hunny and Oyle of Terpentine of ech a like, mixe them well together, and euerye morning drinke thereoff, ounce 
                     ſ
                     semis
                  . faſting, for the ſpace of a moneth or there about.
            
            
               To helpe thoſe that haue a great cough in the ſtomacke.
               THe cough doth come of diuers and ſundrye cauſes, but let it come of what cauſe it will, it alwayes offendeth the ſtomacke and the heade, for alwayes when the ſtomacke is offended of neceſſitie the heade is offended, bicauſe it hath communication with the ſtomacke, ſo that the ſtomacke is cauſe of the paynes in the heade, and therefore it is neceſſary to helpe the ſtomacke firſt, &amp; that thou ſhalt do with our Pillole aquilone the which is written in this booke folowing, and if ſo be you cannot take pilles, take our Aromatico, this being done, if there be no feuer, giue him euery morning 1. ounce of our electuary magiſtrale per la toſſe, and euery night annoynt his ſtomacke with Magno licore, and alſo his heade and noſtrelles, but if it happen that the aforeſaide thinges helpe it not, then take bloud of the Lyuer vaine, and purge the bodye with our Sirope againſt the melancholike humor, and ſo by the grace of God they ſhall remaine healed.
            
            
               
               To helpe thoſe that can-not hold their water.
               THis procéedeth of two cauſes principally, the firſt is of ſuperfluous heat of the body, through ye which heat, nature doth aſſuttiliate too much that humid part, and continually doth ſend it downe into the bladder. The ſecond cauſe is, that the powers are too much relaxed or opened, by the which operation the vrine doth paſſe with-out retention, and theſe are the two cauſes why the vrine can-not ſtays, and this commeth commonly to young children, bicauſe they are very hot of complection, and the order to helpe them, is this.
               Giue them our Pillole Aguilone thrée times, the quantitie is from one dram, to one and a halfe: that being done, ye ſhall make them a decoction of Hiſop of the mountaine, and put ther-in ſugar, &amp; this they ſhal vſe .x. or .xij. dayes at the leaſt, for this mundifieth the place offended, and diſpoſeth it to ſolution. Then after this is done, ye ſhall giue him for .x. dayes together halfe a dram of Maſticke with a little Plantaine water, for this is hot and reſtringeth the powers, and ingroſſeth the Vryne, and ſo the Patient ſhall remaine whole of that infirmitie, by the vertue of the afore-ſayd thrée medicines, and it is a verye eaſie cure and ſouereigne for that purpoſe. But ſome-time there happeneth a flux of vryne ſome-what lyke this, and it is not of the afore-ſayd cauſes, but of cauſes much different from them, for this is in men and womē of age, and this I finde to be cauſed of the Pockes that cauſeth the flux, and they voyd certeine threds which ſome call Gonorea, and the remedie there-off is onely with great purging and ſweating, and then to annoint them fiue or ſixe nights with our Vnguento magno, &amp; kéepe

them warme in bedde vntill ye haue ended to annoynt him, and then go to the ſtowe, and he ſhall be helpt of that infirmitie.
            
            
               To helpe thoſe that can-not make water.
               THe vryne is ſtayed through diuers and ſundry cauſes, and the principall are thrée, of the which one is the ſtone that ingēdreth in the bladder, for alwaies it hangeth down in the necke of the bladder, and ſtoppeth the Meat
                        •
                     
                   or powers that the vryne can not paſſe, the which grieueth the patient meruaylouſly. The other is cauſed of grauel or groſe and viſcous humours that cannot paſſe the powers, and ſo cauſe that retention of vryne with great payne. The third is cauſed of an obſtruction or reſtriction of the powers or cunduites, where the vryne doth paſſe, and ſo kéepeth the vryne with-in, with great payne ſo that theſe bée the thrée chiefeſt cauſes of the retention of vryne.
               The cure of the firſt cauſe which is the ſtone, is to purge them well, and then to vſe our moſt ſouereigne remedie that is written in this booke following, the which is of great vertue to breake the ſtone, as I haue proued many times, but whē this medicine is not able to breake it, then it is neceſſary to cut it foorth, &amp; this is all concerning the firſt cauſe.
               To helpe the ſecond cauſe, it were neceſſary to vſe purgations that purge the reynes well, &amp; then to giue them our Aromatico, and then to annoynt the reynes ſixe dayes euery day once with Vnguento magno, and with this medicine thou ſhalt helpe him perfectly.
               To cure the third cauſe it were neceſſary to purge with aperatiue things, &amp; then to annoynt his reynes and vnder the members and belly with our Balme artificiall, and giue him to drinke the powder of Hogge

lyce or Centum pedes, that are founde vnder ſtones, and by the grace of God he ſhall be perfectly whole.
            
            
               To helpe thoſe that haue great burning of their vrine.
               THe burning of the vryne may come of diuers &amp; ſū
                  drye cauſes, but I finde foure principall, of which one is ye ſtone in the bladder being great or ſmal. The ſecond cauſe is a certaine heat ye which corrupteth the place where it paſſeth and caryeth forth as it were certeine long thrids the which cauſeth that burning. The third cauſe is a certein viſcouſneſſe the which holdeth to the botome of the Vrinal, and it wil not wel break, and this is called Gonorea. The fourth cauſe is certein fluxes of Vrine cauſed of ſome kinde of the Pockes, as ye may ſée by thoſe that vſe company with euil women and take harme, for preſently this burning commeth, and therefore this ſhoweth me playnely to bée the Pockes that cauſeth that burning of vryne.
               But if thou wilt helpe the afore-ſaid foure cauſes thou mayſt doe it with eaſe hauing the true Art of a good Phiſition, and the remedie of the firſt cauſe comming of the ſtone, is to take it foorth of the bladder.
               The ſeconde cauſe, is to be helpt with purging with our Siropo ſolutino, &amp; then after that, to vſe our oyle of Vitriole compound taking thereoff euery morning .1. ounce, and ſo they ſhall remaine helpt.
               The third cauſe is helpt with taking euery tenue dayes a quantitie of our Aromatico, and ſo with this onely remedie they ſhall be helpt.
               The fourth cauſe is helpt with medicines appropriate for the Pocks, and to annoynt them with Vnguento magno.
               
            
            
               
               To helpe thoſe that haue great payne of the Goute.
               THe Goute is a corrupt and maligne infirmitie, and properly ingendred of corruption, as it is plainely ſéene in thoſe that are troubled there-with, &amp; to proue it to be true, Nature doth ſhewe it wel, bicauſe you may ſée how great the alteration is of that accident, &amp; ſéeing that humour is cauſed of a windie humour and alteration of the bloud, as is ſéene by experience, I beléeue the ſame diſpoſition hath his original and beginning of the ſtomacke, for ſo much as all thoſe that are troubled with that diſeaſe, the firſt ſigne that appeareth vnto them, is a great payne in the ſtomack .3. or 4. dayes or more before the griefe commeth, and then the payne increaſeth excéedingly, ſo that by the ſayde ſigne, I iudge this accident can-not procéede of other place then the ſtomacke, and to affirme it better, yée ſhall vnderſtand that thoſe which are troubled there-with, can finde no better remedie then to euacuate the ſtomacke from all corruption, and therefore if thou wilt helpe them of that accident, the firſt thing yt yée ſhall doe is to giue them a quantitie of our Aromatico in the morning faſting, and drinke there on a litle white wine, that béeing done, it would be neceſſarye to make a fomentacion with Nettells, that bée well boyled in water, and then to annoynt them with our Balſamo artificiato, and ſo for that time the Gout wil be gone, and will remayne away for a long time.
               But if God permit me lyfe, I will héereafter ſet forth the order to helpe the Gout, that it ſhall neuer come again, with a certein order to be obſerued in the ſame, found out by this Authour, and hath bene proued an infinite number of times in diuers places, &amp; on diuers

noble men as ye may well vnderſtande in his Theſoro della vita humana.
               
            
            
               A remedie againſt the peſtilence, that preſerueth thoſe that vſe it.
               THe peſtilence is a certeine corrupt humour ye which is cauſe of the euill diſpoſition of the ayre that is corrupted, and poyſoned, and it is ſo contagious that in 36. houres it corrupteth the body, &amp; cauſeth them to dye, and therefore if any will defende them from that infection they may do it by the helpe of God and the Phiſition with theſe medicines, the firſt thing is to confeſſe our ſelues vnto almightie God, and to praye hartely vnto him, and then as concerning Phiſical medicines, thrée things are to be vſed, which may ſaue the liues of many. The firſt thing is to euacuate the ſtomacke, the ſecond to ſweate, the thirde vnccion. And touching yt firſt, ye ſhal vſe euery 3. dayes our Pillole aquilone for they euacuate the contagiouſnes and wil not let it corrupt the bodye. For the ſeconde yée ſhall cauſe them to ſweate by artificiall meanes, for that euacuateth a certeine matter very apt to corrupt. And the thirde is to annoynt all the body with our Balme artificiall, for that preſerueth the body, and defendeth it from the contagiouſneſſe, ſo that by theſe 3. meanes men and women may be preſerued from that violent death.
            
            
               To helpe Pellaria, that is a diſeaſe which cauſeth the haire and bearde to fall away.
               THis Pellaria is a certeine kinde of fantaſticall infirmity the which we by practiſe do know ye cauſe,

the which is by vſing company with women corrupted with the pockes, and by the ſame practiſe we ſée that thoſe whoſe haire doth fall awaye, doe fall into great infirmities of the pockes, although not all, yet the moſt part, and therefore if thou wilt helpe that accident, it were neceſſary to purge them with our Siropo Solutiuo, 8. or 10. dayes together, that being done, giue them our Aromatico, and then annoynt the place where the haire is fallen away euery euening with our balme artificiall, ſo that with the vſe of theſe thrée medicines the patient ſhall remaine perfectly whole of that matter, bicauſe the ſirope purgeth the whole bodye vniuerſally, and the Aromatico purgeth the ſtomacke and the heade, and the Balme comforteth and defendeth the place where the haire is fallen, ſo that it ſhall fall no more, for this I haue proued an infinite of times. You ſhall vnderſtande that there be two other kindes of Pellaria the which wil not be helpt in the afore-ſaid order, for the one commeth of a great feare, &amp; the other commeth bicauſe they haue had Mal di maſſuca, and their heads be corrupted by that meanes, and for theſe two I knowe no remedye but to let nature haue hir courſe.
            
            
               To helpe a Carnoſite in the yarde.
               THe Carnoſite that commeth in the yarde hindereth the vryne ſo that it can-not paſſe, and groweth in the mouth of the bladder, and is a kinde of matter ingendred in that place, the which is much like vnto an Emerode that commeth in the necke of the inteſtine about the fundament, and bicauſe it is a groſſe and vlcerated matter the vrine paſſeth with difficultie and great burning, the which is verye painefull,

vnto thoſe that haue it, but if thou wilt helpe that inconuenience it were neceſſary to purge the body wel, and to kéepe a dyet, and to drincke the Decoccion of Hipericon made with hunnye, and vſe to eate drye meates as muche as is poſſible, and then make certeine little Waxe Candles of Waxe and Frankenſence, and then make this vnguent.
               
                  Rec. Reade leade ounce 1. white hunny ounce 1. butter two ounces, white Wine as much as will ſuffiſe to incorporate them in a liquid forme, on a ſoft fixe, and then take tenne quilles that hath bloude in them out of the winge of a young Pigion that is fat, and therwith ſtirre the vnguent when it boyleth, and when one quill is dryed take another, and ſo chaunge them vntill the Wine be conſumed, and then it is made, and when thou wilt occupie it, take one of the ſaide Candles of Waxe and vppon the ende put of this vnguent, and put it into the yarde vntill it touch the Carnoſite, and this thou ſhalt vſe day, by day vntill the Candell paſſe without any impediment, and then the patient ſhalbe helpt, for this is moſt true, and I haue proued it an infinite of times to my great credite and content of the patient.
            
            
               To helpe the white ſcall.
               THis diſeaſe being ſo odious, is a corrupt humour the which is not onely in the heade as many do thinke, but it dependeth of the inwarde partes and hath communication with the heade, and this humour is like vnto the Fume, for continually it vaporeth vp, and when it can aſſend no more bicauſe it is hindered in the ſkinne, then it

ſetleth and ingroſſeth and cauſeth the heade to breake forth in that grieuous order as is ſéene. But I will ſhewe a ſecreate to helpe it, ſo that it ſhall neuer come againe, and the order it thus. You ſhall giue them our Siropo Solutiuo 8. or 10. dayes together, that béeing done giue them our Pillole Aquilone thrée times, the which pilles muſt be taken euery thrée dayes once, that being done, take Sinaber finely beatē, two ounces, Olibanum, Mura, ana one drame, mixe them together, &amp; deuide it into 5. partes &amp; make therof fiue perfumes in fiue mornings, and couer their heades with a cloth ſo that it touch not the heade, then let the pouder bée caſt on by little and little vntil it be ſpent, vpon a chaſing diſh of coles, and ſo let them ſtande couered one houre without mouing, and this do euery one of the times, that being done annoynt the heade for the ſpace of a moneth with Oyle of Waxe and Terpentine, and they ſhalbe helpt, for this is a remedy that cannot faile, for I haue proued it an infinite of times, in Palermo, in Meſina, in Naples, in Rome, and in Venice, and alwayes I haue had good ſucceſſe to my great credit, and profite of the diſeaſed perſon.
            
            
               To helpe thoſe Caruolli that come vppon the yarde, and their cauſes.
               THoſe Caruoli that come vppon the yarde, are of diuerſe kindes, as by reaſon and experience thou maiſt ſée, but ye moſt parte are taken by vſing ye cōpany of lewd &amp; corrupt womē, infected wt the pocks, and thoſe are the worſt kinde, for they are the firſt original of ye pockes, &amp; of thoſe caruolli come Pannochie or botches, &amp; certaine great ſcabbes, Pellaria, aiches, &amp; tumors, &amp; an infinite of other euill effects &amp; theſe are ye
                  
firſt kinde. There are another kinde the which commonly come of their own accord by reaſon of heat, and thoſe are eaſie to be holpe, and are not perillous or paynefull. There is an other kinde, the which is as though it were ſcorched or burnt, the which commeth thorow debilytie of the yarde, &amp; hauing company with women, and theſe are alſo of ſmall importaunce.
               The firſt kinde are certeine Vlcers that come vppon the end, and ſome vppon the proper ſubſtaunce of the yard, &amp; ſome vpon the ſkinne, and the order to cure them is thus. Ye ſhall mortifie them with-in &amp; with-out with our Cauſticke, and when they are mortified, ye ſhall dreſſe them with our Magno licore, and they ſhall be whole quickly.
               But ye ſhal wel note, that many times after they are healed afore .xv. dayes doe paſſe, there will come a certeine alteration in the throate, ſo that they canne ſcarce ſwallow their meat, and this alteration many times endureth viii. or x. dayes, and than it reſolueth by it ſelfe, and that is a certeine ſigne of Pellaria.
               
               And therefore if thou wilt auoyde that inconuenience that the haire fall not off, aſſoone as ye féele any of the a afore-ſayd griefes, then preſently take a quantitie of our Electuario Angelica, and then take our Siropo magiſtrale .4. or .5. dayes, and annoynt thy heade .x. or xij. dayes with our Magno licore, &amp; ſo by theſe meanes thy haire ſhall not fall. Bicauſe our Electuario Angelica doth euacuate the ſtomacke, and clenſeth the head, &amp; dryeth vp the matter, the which is already alterated by that diſeaſes. Alſo our Siropo magiſtrale, doeth euacuate the bodye, and purifie the bloud, and ſlaketh the furye of the diſeaſe. Our Magno licore preſerueth the haire from drying and fallyng.
               There commenth manye times, after thoſe Caruoli are healed certeine Impoſtumes in the groyne, of the

which we will ſpeake off in an other booke particularly. The other kinde of Caruolli that come vppon the yard, are holpe onely by waſhing thē with ſome bath that is reſtrictiue and comfortatiue. The other kinde which is lyke ſcorching or burning, are holpe by kéeping them cleane, and annoynting them with a Liniment of Tutia camphorata.
               
               And thus I make an ende, giuing to vnderſtande to thoſe that practiſe, how that they may auoyde that diſeaſe called Pellaria or falling of the haire or beard, for this is one of my ſecrets, where-off I meane to write a great number if God permit me.
            
            
               A diſcourſe of thoſe ſores that come of the Pockes, and how to helpe them quickly.
               THe Pockes as I haue written of diuers times, being a putrified and corrupt diſeaſe, the ſores comming there-off, of force muſt be of his nature, that is corrupt and ſtinking, therefore if thou wilt help them and take away their paine quickly thou ſhalt vſe thrée operations, the firſt is to giue them our Pillole Aquilone, and then to waſh the ſore with oyle of Sulphur, &amp; then lay ther-on our Cerote magiſtrale, with Precipitate, and annoynt it with Magno licore, and there-with thou ſhalt helpe thē quickly, bicauſe thoſe Pilles are appropriate for that diſeaſe, &amp; the oyle of ſulphur draweth forth the filth from ye ſenter, &amp; the precipitate draweth forth the groſe matter, ſo that of force it muſt heale.
            
            
               The cure of one that had the Pockes in his heade.
               BEing in Naples, among al other that I cured, ther came vnto me a Spaniard called Il ſignor Diego

di Menas, a man of the age of .36. yeares, of complection cholericke aduſte, the which had the Pockes, and in his forheade hée had a certeine tumour the which had periſhed a great part of the ſkull, and was open, and he had bene taken in hand of diuers men, &amp; none could doe him good, I ſéeing that toke him in hande, &amp; gaue him our Siropo ſolutiuo .8. or .9. dayes together, afterward I gaue him our Aromatico, and thē gaue him the rootes of Cina in decoction, and then perfumed him with Olibanum, Maſtick, Mirrha, &amp; Scinaber, and ſo by theſe meanes he was holpe of ye infirmitie, but the bone remained bare, &amp; I layde ther-on our Cerote magiſtrale, and ſo in ſhort time, the bone did ſeperate of his owne accord, and one day I tooke it off altogether, and was ſo great that it couered the fourth part of the heade, than preſently this ſignor Diego went abroade, ſhewing what was taken from his head, as diuers can teſtifie.
            
            
               The cure of a wound in the head and in the hande.
               THere was a certeine Gentleman called Gionan Iacopo Veniciane, the which had a great wound on the heade, and in one of this handes, the which béeing taken in hande of diuers Chyrurgians, was brought to a very euil caſe by reaſon of great alteration in the woundes, and the Phiſition that had hm in hande, was one called Realdo polumbo cremenſe, the which dreſſed his heade with Wine and Oyle, and the hand with Turpentine and Oyle of Roſes. Than I being in company tolde him, yt it were good to chaunge thoſe medicines, bicauſe in woūds of ye head, thoſe medicines were not conuenient, for ye oyle being crud putrifieth,

and the wine is repercuſſiue, and will not ſuffer the putrifaction to come forth, that the oyle ingendereth, and for that reaſon the ſayd medicine woulde not bée vſed.
               And as for the medicine for his hand, I ſay that the Turpentine is not conuenient, for where there is offence of ſkinne, veynes, ſinewes, and bones, Turpentine is not good, bicauſe it is hot and putrifactiue, by meanes of the Oyle, and cauſeth inflamation, and therefore it ought not to be vſed.
               But if thou wilt helpe the head and hande both, ye ſhal vſe a kinde of medicine that comforteth the place offended, and that doth aſſuttiliate the matter and incarnate, to the which the ſayde Realdo aunſwered and ſayd, my reaſon was good, if I coulde finde remedies that will doe that effecte, the which I ſent for to my houſe, and vſed them in this order.
               Firſt, I did put our Quintaeſſence into his wound in the head being colde, and then a lyttle of our Balſamo colde, the which ſéemed ſtraunge to Realdo, and then I layd there-on our Magno licore, and vpon the cloth I layd a lyttle of our ſecret Powder, and the lyke I did to the hande, and ſo in .14. dayes the wounds were whole, to the great meruayle of a number.
            
            
               A great ſecret particular for the flux, and diſſenteria.
               THe fluxes of the body are no other but a diſtemperaunce of Nature, and are of two kindes, the one is cauſed of an euill qualytie and diſtemperaunce of the lyuer, and that is called Fluſſo epatico. The other is cauſed of great heat, Feuer, and diſtemperment of Nature, and this is called Diſenteria, that is, a diſtemperment of the guts, &amp; both theſe ſorts are harde

to be holpe of the auncient doctours, as it is well ſéene by experience, of thoſe that practiſe, for they will helpe them with repreſſion and reſtrictiues, but that is not the way if wée ſhall beléeue Galen, the which writeth, Fluxus Fluxus curat, the which is moſt true, for I haue cured a thouſande of the fluxe with giuing them our Aromatico, and thrée or foure doſſes of our Siropo Solutiuo, therefore Galen ſaith true.
               But the Diſenteria is cured with giuinge them our Electuario, Angelica, and then euery day after dynner ſtande in a bathe of water of the ſea colde, two houres at the leaſte, and ſo in this order thou ſhalt helpe any crud kind of Diſenteria in ſhort time and with greate eaſe, vſe this as a ſecreate.
            
            
               The cure of one that was poyſoned with Arſenycke.
               THere was a certeyne man poyſoned with Arſenycke giuen him in a meſſe of Ryce pottage, in an euyning at ſupper, and as ſoone as it was in his ſtomacke hée beganne to grone and ſweate, and vomyte, in ſuch order as it was ſtraunge to ſée, and it happened that at the ſaide time there was a learned man in the houſe, who ſéeing this man in that caſe ſuſſpected him to bée poyſoned, and ſo ſent for me, and when I came, the poore man was all-moſt deade, then preſentlye I called the wife of the houſe and tolde hir that hir huſbande woulde dye, and that ſhée ſhoulde haue the Lawe for poyſoninge of him, but if that ſhée woulde tell him what poyſon ſhée had giuen him perhappes hée might recouer hym againe, with many wordes more, ſo to conclude ſhée tolde him that ſhée had giuen him two graynes of Arſenycke

in Riſe pottage, then preſentlye I called for a cuppe of Sacke, and cauſed him to drinke, and then he vomyted and went to the ſtoole, and then I annoynted hym wyth our Oyle of Hiperecone, and Scorpiones, all the body ouer, and ſtyll cauſed him to drinke that hée might euacuate that poyſon, but all his mouth and throate remained ſwollen, and he did ſpite greate aboundaunce, and I cauſed him to vſe that vngnent, and euery morning gaue him Theriacle with wine &amp; euery thrée dayes, I gaue him a quantitie of Pillule Aggregatiue, and laſt of all I cauſed him to vſe Aqua vitae compounde, and ſo ere fortie dayes hée was perfectlye whole, and rydde of a terryble diſeaſe the which he had a fore he was poyſoned.
            
            
               The cure of an Vlcerated legge.
               THere was a certaine man of the age of ſixe and thirtie yeares, of complexion cholerike and ſanguine, the which had his lefte legge all vlcerated, in ſuch order that the Phiſitions and Chirurgions of the citie woulde haue cutte it off, but in any wiſe I woulde not conſent there-vnto, but tooke it in hande, and gaue him fyrſt our Magiſtrall Sirope, in the morning eight or nyne dayes together, and in the meane time I waſhed the legge with Wine where-in was boyled Mallowes, Conſolida maiore, Cardus benedictus, and Hunny, and then wette cloathes therein and layed them on twiſe a day, than I cauſed hym to vſe a decoccion of Lignum vitae and the barke with Iua artetica, Cardus benedictus, Pollipodi, Ripontico, Wine, and Sugar, and his common drinke was wine and water boyled on the feſtes

of the ſame, and this he vſed foure and twentie dayes than I perfumed him with Cinaber thrée times, and ere thrée monethes were paſt he was perfect whole, for his diſeaſe came of the Pockes, and thoſe ſores are commonly called Mal di formica.
               
            
            
               The cure of the goute on a certeine Gentle-man.
               IN the aforeſaide yeare, in the moneth of Auguſt I was called to viſite a noble Gentle-man called Ill ſeignor Don Chriſtofalo della roca, a man of fiue and thirtie yeares, of complexion chollerike and ſanguine, the whiche was ſore troubled with the goute, and bicauſe it was in the beginning of Auguſt, our auncyent Doctours haue for bodden to take any ſolibell medicine in that time. In reſpecte of the Caniculare dayes. Neuertheleſſe I called Armellio, and Leonardo Teſta, two excellent Phiſitians, the which gaue their counſaile to take no medicine, neuer the leſſe I proued that the goute was extreame whote, and for that I ordayned a colde Sirope to mittigate the ſuperfluous heate, the whiche was made of Lyuerworte, Hartes tongue, Dates, Rayſons, Figges, Sugar, and Succorye water, and Aromatiſed it with Muſke and Roſe water, of the which hée tooke euerye day foure ounces, and for the alteration of the goute, I waſhed it thrée or foure times a daye with our Aqua del Balſamo, bicauſe it penetrateth and openeth the powers, &amp; a ſuttiliateth and dryeth the humoure offenſiue, alſo I ordeined him breade of Barly, bicauſe it coleth the bloud and is of good diſgeſtion, and cauſed him to refraine from all fat brothes and his drink was

temparate, and to this one of the Doctors did agrée, but the other woulde not, neuer the leſſe the Gentleman was content with my aduiſe, then I beganne to giue him the afore-ſaide decoccion, with our ſolible Quintaeſſence, and there with he had euery day two or thrée ſtooles, and I waſhed the gout thrée or foure times a day with our Aqua Balſami, and the firſt day hée beganne to féele eaſe, and the ſeconde he felte more, ſo that in ſeuen dayes all his paines was taken away, and then I applyed ther-vnto our ſecreate of ſecreats, for that kinde of diſeaſe, the which in thrée dayes delyuered him: then I cauſed him to vſe certeine medicines to defende the goute for comming againe, and ſo he continued whole to his great ſatiſfaction.
            
            
               Of the cauſes of the Scyatica, and how ye may helpe it.
               THe Sciatica is a diſeaſe ſo called, bicauſe it commeth in that place of the body called, Sio, and is cauſed of an euill qualytie and groſſe humores, that are ſtayed in that place, bicauſe they cannot paſſe downe, and this is ſéene by experience dayly, for where that paine is, there is alteration, and the cure thereof is with Gliſters, Vomittes, Purgations, and Vnctions, bicauſe the Gliſter doth euacuate thoſe places next vnto it, and ſo eaſeth the humour, the vomitte cleanſeth the ſtomacke, the purgaciones doe euacuate the bodye downewardes, the vnctions diſſolue the winde, and ſo by theſe meanes thou maiſt helpe the Scyatica, as I haue done many times to my great honour, and ſatiſfaction of the patient.
            
            
               
               A moſt excellent remedie to helpe the flux of the body, with a certeine diſcourſe there-on.
               IF thou wilt helpe the flux of the body, it were neceſſary to know firſt from whence it proceedeth, for he that knoweth not the cauſe, is leſſe to be credited to cure the effect, and therefore I will ſhew thée what the flux is, and from whence it commeth, &amp; then I will ſhew the order to cure it, alſo to make the medicines.
               The fluxe of the bodye is cauſed of a ſuperfluous heate conceiued in the ſtomack, the which make a continuall ſolution inwardelye, as ye maye ſée by experience of thoſe that are troubled there-with, for ſo long as the cauſe is not taken awaye, all their meat dothe tourne into that matter, the which if it bée ſo, that is true which I doe ſaye, that the fluxes are a diſtemperance of the body, cauſed of hot and corrupt humours in the ſtomacke, and therefore if thou wilt cure it, it wer neceſſary to extinguiſh the heat and to take away the corruption, the which thou ſhalt doe with the redneſſe of Marte Militare, written in this booke following, for that is the moſt ſouereigne remedie that can be found. But firſt ye ſhall take twelue graynes of our Petra Philoſophalla, with halfe an ounce of Mel Roſarum, and then take for foure mornings together one ſcruple of ye rednes of Marte, with half an .℥. of ſugar Roſat, &amp; ther-with thou ſhalt work miracles,
            
            
               A diſcourſe as concerning cornes in the feete or els where, with their remedies.
               THis callowes matter, is a certeine hot humour, of the which Nature would diſcharge hir-ſelfe, and

when that humor is driuen forth of Nature, it goeth vnto the lower parts, into the ende of the toes, for in that extreme part of the toes, that ſkinne that is called Epiderma, is hard, and wil not ſuffer it to paſſe or exalare, and there many times it ingendeth a tumor in the ſkinne with great hardneſſe, and many times that tumor doth increaſe and cauſe ſuch paine, that it doth not onely hinder their going, but hindreth them from ſléepe in the night, and this kinde of tumor is called commonly Callo or Cornes in Engliſh, and I thought it good to call them Creſte, bicauſe they are alwayes growing, and is of great importance among the Chyrurgians, for an infinite number of perſons are troubled there-with, &amp; therefore I will ſhew thée our ſecret to helpe them quickly, and with great eaſe, which ſecret was neuer knowen afore of any. Firſt, ye ſhal pare them with a ſharpe knife vntil the bottome, and there ye ſhall finde a certeine thing lyke matter, but if ye finde no matter, ye ſhal pare it vntil ye bloud doth appeare, than touch it once with oyle of ſulphur, and then dreſſe it with our Balſamo artificiato, once a day vntill it be whole. Kéepe this as a ſecret.
            
            
               Of an infirmitie of importaunce that commeth vpon the extremitie of the toe, vppon the nayle.
               THere are manye men that are troubled with a certein infirmitie vnder ye nayle of their great toe, the which ſéemeth as though ye nayle grew in the fleſh, the which is not ſo, but the fleſh groweth ouer the naile, and although this ſéemeth to be a thing of nothing, &amp; that the Auncients haue had ſmall conſideration theroff. Neuertheleſſe it is an infirmitie of great importaunce, and to be conſidered of, bicauſe many are troubled there-with, &amp; ſpecially men of authoritie, &amp; in ſpecially

thoſe that are troubled with the Goute. I cal to remembrance, that in the time that I was in Naples, I cured a great number, &amp; ſpecially thoſe that were of great authoritie, to my great honour and profite. The firſt thing that I did I cut the nayle on yt part which was grieued, and toke it away the which was done eaſely and with little paine, the which thing being done, I touched it with our Cauſtike, and ſo let it remaine thrée dayes together, an than I dreſſed it euery day with our Magno licore vntill it was whole, the which was in ſhort time.
            
            
               A diſcourſe vpon the Hemerhodes, with the order to cure them with moſt excellent medicines of our inuention.
               THe Hemerhodes are a certeine kind of euil tumor, cauſed of the bloud in the veynes Emorodiale, and theſe come alwayes in the extremitie of the Inteſtinals about the fundament, &amp; ſome of them cauſe great paine, &amp; ſome of them do burne exceſſiuely, or do ſcald. The which commeth thorow the qualitie of the good &amp; euil humors. As ye may ſée by experience how yt ſome haue ſuch burning yt they cannot reſt in the night, the other haue ſuch payne that they canot ſit, ye other are ſo ſcalded that they cannot abide it, ye ſhall vnderſtād this infirmitie is more paynefull in one complection than in another, and the cure there-off is difficile. Neuertheleſſe it maye be cured, and the order is this.
               Firſt take our Aromatico, then take our Siropo ſolutiuo thrée or foure dayes, then take our perfume thrée or foure times on the fundament, that being done, annoynt the place with our Balme artificiall, for that dryeth and taketh away the payne altogether, and ſo the Patient ſhall remaine perfect whole.
               
                  There is alſo a great ſecret in the tooth of a Horſefiſh if it be worne on a mans finger, to take away the Hemerhodes, the which tooth I haue known proued at the leaſt .7. or .8. times, for I haue a ring made theroff and haue vſed it.
            
            
               A great ſecret to helpe thoſe that are burſt or haue the Rupture.
               THis is rare ſecret, neuer knowen afore of anye man, and in ſpecially for thoſe that haue not béene burſt long time, &amp; that the Rupture hath not yet made a callow, and the order to cure it, is thus.
               Firſt ye ſhall giue them our Aromatico, euery ten dayes once, and euery morning faſting giue them one ounce of fine Tartar beaten in powder with water or wine to drinke, and lyke-wiſe in the euening two houres afore ſupper giue him as much, and his bread ſhall be Biſket made of Rye, alſo he muſt weare a truſſe made fit for that purpoſe, and vſe this remedie.
               
                  Rec. Rectified Aqua vitae with-out fleame, ounce xij. Roſen of the Pine trée that is drye, Ohbanum, Maſticke, Sarcocolla, ana ounc. ſemis. Mixe them altogether, and with this water waſh the Rupture euery day twice, and then caſt there-on preſently the powder of a hearbe called Biſlingua and Balſamina, ana, and than wet a cloth in the ſayde water, and laye it there-on, and binde the truſſe very hard, and kéepe thy houſe with as much eaſe as thou mayſt and ſtrayne not thy ſelfe in any wiſe, and thus with-in .100. dayes thou ſhalt help any great Rupture, kéeping the aforeſayd order.
            
            
               
               A rare ſecrete and deuine, to helpe thoſe that are troubled with the ſpleene.
               THe Mylte is alterated &amp; commeth harde, by reaſon of a ſuperfluous humidity, the which it receiueth, by the euill diſpoſition of the lyuer and longes, and therefore if thou wilt helpe it, it were neceſſary to vſe medicines abſterſiue and drying, &amp; to giue them our Aromatico once, and then to vſe this electuarye, the which is of meruailous vertue, in that operation.
               
                  Rec. Squamma ferri one ounce, Scolopendria, one ounce, Spignarde, Lapis Laſuly, ana, two ſcruples, Sinamon, ounce halfe, beate them fine and make thereoff an electuary with purified hunny, according to art, &amp; ther-off take euery morning a ſpoonefull, &amp; as much at nyght, two houres before ſupper, &amp; annoynt ye place where the Mylte lyeth, with our Balſamo artificiato, &amp; ſo by the grace of God and meanes of theſe medicines, thou ſhalt be holpen quickely.
            
            
               A nother great ſecreat to helpe the ſpleene with great ſpeede
               THe Mylt as is a foreſaide, is grieued thorowe aboundaunce of humiditie he which it receiueth, and therefore thou muſt onely ſéeke to drye that humiditie, and for that purpoſe, I will ſhewe thée 2. great ſecreates, where-with thou ſhalt worke myracles, and are of great reaſon and experience. The one is to bée let bloude vnder the tongue in one of theſe 2. veynes: that is, on that ſide where the Mylte lyeth, that béeing done, ye ſhall take Muſtarde &amp; myxe it with the vrine of a boye, and laye it betwéene two cloathes, and lay it on the ſore place one nyght, and than if it bée not

well, vſe it ſtill vntil it be holpen, for this I haue proued an infinite of times.
            
            
               The cure of a certeine Spanyard called, Carabaſall di Cordonet the which was troubled with the Pockes.
               THis ſouldiour being of the age ot two and thirtie yeares, was myghtely troubled with the Pockes with extréeme paines and ſores, among the which he had all his thigh ſo eaten away as though he had béene gnawen with dogges, with moſt extréeme payne, and the way that I cured him was thus. I gaue him 12. graynes of our Petra Philoſophalle, with Sugar Roſate, the which cauſed him to vomyte and to euacuate downe-warde, of the which he found great eaſe, that being done, I prepared him our decoction of Lignum ſanctum ſolutiue, the which is written off hereafter, with a certeine drinke made with wine and Lignum vitae, and this he vſed fiue and twentie dayes, and then I annoynted, him with our vnguento Magno, and in the ſpace of fortie dayes he was perfectly holpen to the ſight of all men.
            
            
               The cure of the ſtytch in the ſide with retention of vryne.
               THere was a certaine gentleman called, Marco di Chiuffune of the age of ſixe and thirtie yeares, the which was troubled with a terrible ſtytch in the ſide, and had proued many medicines &amp; none did him pleaſure, the which after, I toke him in hande, I gaue him our Aromatico, and after that the paine ſlacked, than I cauſed him to annoynt all thoſe partes with the

Oyle of Nutmegs, and the Oyle of Egges mixte together, and ſo he remayned quite whole, for in this order I haue cured an infinite of perſones to my greate honour.
            
            
               A cure of a certaine Spanyard wounded in the heade in Naples.
               THere was a certeine Spanyard called Zamora, of the age of foure and thirtie yeares, of complexion cholorike and ſanguine, the which was wounded in the left ſide of the heade, with inſcicion of the bone, alſo ye ſhall vnderſtande, that in Naples the ayre is moſt euill for woundes in the heade, by reaſon that it is ſo ſubtile, and for that cuaſe the doctours did feare the cure, neuertheleſſe I dreſſed him with out Magno licore, and Balſamo, artificiato, kéeping the wounde as cloſe as was poſſible, annoynting it onely vppon the wounde, and ſo in fourtéene dayes he was perfectlye whole, to the great wonder of a number, of Chirurgions of that cytie.
            
            
               The cure of a certeine gentleman that had Mal di formica.
               THere was a certeine Gentleman Neapolitan, the which was called Ill ſignior Giouan Franciſco Gaetauo, of the age of 38. yeares, the which was meruailouſly tormented with a ſore arme and a ſore legge, called Mall di formica, and he was of complexion cholerike and melancholyke, and theſe ſores went créeping vppon the fleſh, healing in one place and breking in another, and in his arme hée had nyne ſores, and in the legge fouretéene, and this Gentleman had ſought helpe the ſpace of 2. yeares &amp; could finde none,

and had twiſe taken the dyet, and yet coulde finde no helpe, the which Gentle-man I tooke in hande, and the firſt thing that I gaue him was this, one ounce of Gerapigra Galenie with twentie graines of our Petra Philoſophalle, the which prouoked both vomitte and ſege dyuers times, that being done, I gaue him our Siropo Solutiuo, xij. morninges together, that being done I gaue him a medicine with our Petra Philoſophalle and Eleborus niger, the which cauſed him alſo to vomite and purge downe-wardes, that being done I cauſed him to make a ſirope of Lignum ſanctum, and the barke, Iua Artetica, and Cardus benedictus, in the which I put ſeuen pounde of wine, and one of Sugar, and then I cauſed him to make a drinke with water, wine, and hunny to drinke continuallye, and that I cauſed him to vſe fiue and twentie dayes, and then I annoynted him with our Vnguento Magno, fiue times without fire, the which vnguent cauſed him to ſpitte a boundance of filthy matter, and at the laſt it cauſed him to ſpitte bloud, then I cauſed him to make a bathe the which is written in our Regiment of the peſtilence, called the ioyful Iewell: I laid on the ſores our Cerote Magiſtralle, and thus with in 38. dayes hée was perfecte whole.
            
            
               Certeine cures that this authour did when he trauailed into Afryca.
               IN the yeare 1550. hée trauailed into Africa, and there he was choſen by Il. S. Don Pietro di Toledo vicere di Napoli, to be Phiſition vnto the campe vnder Don Gracia his ſonne, and ſo in the yeare .1551, in the moneth of May he departed from Naples with all the army of the Emperour, Carolo quinto, D. Auſtria, &amp; ſo hauing a proſperous wind, ariued in Barbary by a

certeine olde citie called Monaſterio, and ther gaue an aſſiege, &amp; tooke it, with-out any remiſſiō or rāſoming, &amp; made ſlaues of all thoſe that were lefte alyue, and it remained vtterlye deſtroyed, but not with-out greate mortalytie of our Chriſtian ſouldiers, and beſide thoſe that were killed, there was a great number wounded the which were brought into the Gallyes, and caryed to the Ile of Sicilia in a certeine citie called Trapano, the which ſay they, was buylded by a great Idolater called Tarpos, and there in the hoſpital thoſe wounded perſons were lefte, with certeine Chyrurgians that were vnder my iuriſdiction, &amp; with certeine medicines of my inuention, and ſo in ſhorte time the moſt parte were holpe, and then the army retourned vnto Naples againe, and refreſhed them with new men and victual. And then on the .15. of Iune, we ſet vp ſayle and ſayled, and when we were in the midſt of the goulfe betwéene Naples &amp; Palermo, there happened a great miſfortune, the which was thus.
               In the Galley of Signor Giordano Captaine generall of the Galleyes of the Duke of Florence, it happened that he being at the table with diuers captaines &amp; gentlemen, &amp; as they were at dinner, a certeine Captaine being grieued with an other, multiplyed words, and tooke a loafe of bread &amp; threw it at his face, without any reuerence or reſpect of the ſayde Generall S. Giordano. That being done, the ſayde Generall ryſe from the table &amp; tooke him by the boſome, &amp; gaue him 5. ſtocados in the breaſt the which pearced within the body, and there he fell for dead, that being done, the ſayd Generall repented him-ſelfe of his raſhneſſe, and preſently ſent for me being in the Gally of Don Gracia, to come and dreſſe him, and ſo my Generall cauſed me to doe with all dilygence, and when I came, this poore Captaine laye as though he had bene dying,

neuertheleſſe I dreſſed him with great dilygence, and the medicines which I vſed were theſe. Firſt I put in to the wounds, of our Quintaeſſence, and vppon the wound I dreſſed it, with ur Balme artificiall, and gaue him a vomite, the which cauſed him to caſt great quantitie of bloud, and then euerye morning I gaue him halfe an ounce of our Aqua Balſami, &amp; thus within two dayes after we ariued at Palermo, the Capitaine was perfecte whole, to the great meruayle of a number. After that we departed from Palermo, and went to the citie of Trapano, wher the reſt of the galleyes were, and there continued .4. dayes, and then on Saint Iohns euen, we went to an Iland called Fanignana, and there kéept the feaſt of Saint Iohn, and then we departed with all the army, and went on the ſide of Africa, and on Saint Peters day we landed in the Gardeins of that citie, and there began to offer battayle, and there remayning about .24. or .25. dayes, the army beganne to be infected with a certeine kinde of fluxe, where-off a great number dyed, euerye daye. My Generalll ſéeing that, called me, and aſked if it were poſſible to finde ſome remedie for that fluxe, vnto the which I aunſwered willyngly, and ſayde, I would deuiſe by the help of God ſome remedie, bicauſe it was my duetie, aſwell as for th health of the ſouldiors of the Emperour, the which thing I did in ſhort time thorow the whole campe: as I wil write héereafter in the next chapter.
            
            
               The cure of the flux, where-with I holpe the Armie of the Emperour in Africa.
               BEing as I haue ſayd afore in ye campe, wher they were meruaylouſly tormented with a flux, &amp; many dyed there-off, and could finde no helpe, although they

had medicines. Than I which had the experience in hand, began to laugh to my ſelfe, &amp; the remedy wherwith I holpe them all, was this. Firſt, I cauſed them to eate wel, &amp; thā on ye morning, I gaue them a vomit, and then euery day after they had eaten, I cauſed thē to goe into the water of the Sea, and there to remaine 4. or .5. houres, and ſo doing with-in .4. or .5. dayes they were holpe, for I ſweare as I am a Knight, that if I had not bene there, the whole army had dyed of that fluxe, for of .14. or .15. thouſande that were there, there was not left, 2. thouſand but they were infected with tha flux or diſtemperaunce of the lyuer, cauſed of ſuperfluous heate, the which heate diſtempereth the ſtomacke, &amp; cauſeth ye continuall flux: ye ſhall vnderſtand that our vomit doth euacuate the ſtomacke of the putrified humor, &amp; the ſalt water cooleth the heat, &amp; reſtraineth the flux, ſo that by theſe meanes they were holpe.
            
            
               A goodly remedy found out by me, for woundes in the head.
               WOundes in the head, were very perillous in that place, ſo that if a .100. wer hurt in the head, it was not poſſible to recouer .x. and that came thorowe two things, the which were much contrary in that region, for the day was ſo hot, yt it burned all things, and the night to the contrary ſo extreame colde, that it was intollerable, &amp; not to be credited, &amp; ſo by this diſtēperance whē 
                  Craneum was vncouered that ye aire might touch it, preſently they dyed without any helpe, than I ſéeing that, beganne to conſider of the matter, deſiring to finde ſome meane to helpe them, &amp; ſo ſtudying, it came in my memory, that the aire was cauſe of their death, as it was in troth.
               Than preſently I commaunded all thoſe Chyrurgians that wer vnder my iuriſdiction, yt they ſhold not

meddle with any wound in the head without my preſence, the which thing was done, &amp; as many as were wounded, the firſt thing yt I did in ſtéede of cutting or launcing or diſcouering, according to the cōmon order, I ioyned the parts &amp; ſowed them cloſe &amp; dreſſed them vpon the wound with our Quintaeſſence, &amp; with Balſamo and Magno licore, and ſo in ſhort time the moſt part were holpe, and there dyed none ſo deſperate as they did afore, and therefore to my Iudgement, this was a good inuention, and neuer vſed of any afore, and this order of curing is very naturall, for Nature doth ſhew it in hearbes, plants, and ſtones, how that they cannot ſtande diſ vnited: then much more our fleſhe cannot ſtande diſ vnited, with-out great torment of the Patient, for vntill it be ioyned together againe, it is vnpoſſible to be holpe, then ſeing that is true, it is moſt natural for the wound to be ioyned together, and to vſe thoſe medicines that wher they be applyed, wil not ſuffer the humor to come there-vnto, nor putrifie the place that is hurte, and ſeing it is ſo, as by experience is ſéene, wée muſt beléeue this to be a naturall and moſt wholſom remedie, ſo that I affirme that the ioyning of the parts of the wounde in the heade and other parts of the body, is moſt ſouereine and of great ſatiſfaction to the ſicke, for they neuer féele payne, nor haue no feuer nor other ſorte of accident, for of thoſe I haue cured a great number with good ſucceſſe.
            
            
               The cure of one that had his noſe cut off, and ſet on agayne.
               IN that time when I was in Africa, there happened a ſtraunge caſe, and that was thus.
               A certeine Gentleman a Spaniard that was called Il Signor Andreas Gutiero, of the age of .xxix. yeares,

vppon a time walked in the fielde, and fell at words with a ſouldiour, and began to drawe his weapon, the ſouldiour ſéeing yt, ſtroke him with the left hande &amp; cut off his noſe, and there fell downe in the ſande, than I hapened to ſtande by, and tooke it vp, and pyſſed thereon to waſh away the ſande, and ſtytched it on againe verye cloſe, &amp; dreſſed it with our Balſamo Artificiato, and bound it vp, and ſo let it remaine viii. dayes, thinking that it woulde haue rome to matter: neuertheleſſe when I did vnbinde it, I founde it faſt conglutinated, &amp; then I dreſſed it onelye once more, &amp; hée was perfectly whole, ſo that all Naples did meruaile there at, as is well knowne, for the ſaide S. Andrea doth liue yet, and can teſtifie the ſame.
            
            
               The cure of an arme of S. Giordano Vrſino.
               AT the ſame time, the ſaide S. Giordano Vrſino, and S. Antamo Sauello Romano, and S. Aſtor Baglione, with diuers other, toke their horſes, &amp; ryd about two myles from the campe, and there perceiued certeine Mores on horſebacke, the which dyd aſſault theſe gentlemen, and one More with his launce, did thruſt thorow the arme from ye elbow through the ſhoulder, then the ſaid S. Giordino returned to the campe with great paine, and preſently I was ſent for, and when I had ſéene it I put therein our Quintaeſſence, and vpon the wounde I laide our Balſamo and Magno licore, and bounde it ſtraite, and ſo left it, and in fiue dayes it was whole and ſound, and than went to the aſſaulte moſt valyantly, as many can teſtifie, bicauſe he was generall of Firenze.
               
            
            
               
               A great chaunce that happened at the aſſault in Africa.
               AT the ſame time, there was a Gentleman Florentine that was with ye ſaid S. Giordano Vrſino, that was called Milllematti, the whiche fought with his ſworde and target, and defended many ſhotte of Calyuers and ſuch like, at the laſt one perſed his targette, and ſtroke him vppon the breaſt, and bruſed him merueilouſly, and yet broke no ſkinne, and there-with all he fell to the ground for dead, and the caryer of deade men or Becamort, as they call them, woulde haue buryed him in a mine, I then being preſent cauſed him to be brought to the tent of S. Aſtor Baglione, and ther I put our Quintaeſſēce into his mouth, and that cauſed the bloude to liquifie and come forth at the mouth, and layd vppon his ſtomacke a plaiſter of Aſhes and Oyle, as hot as he coulde abide, and that I chaunged morning and euening, and alwayes I gaue him of our Quintaeſſence to drinke, ſo that in ſhort time hée was holpe, and yet lyueth in health: and this was one of the moſt ſtraungeſt thinges that euer I ſawe, that a pellet of a Calyuer could not breake the fleſh, and that came by certaine wordes that the ſaide Millematti dyd carry written vppon his breaſt, as he perſwaded me afterwarde for the ſaide. In verbis, &amp; in herbis, &amp; in lapidibus ſunt virtutes, &amp;c.
               
            
            
               The cure of woundes being poyſoned, and of other ſortes.
               WHile that warres dured in Africa, many times the Chriſtians were poyſoned with venomous

Arrowes and ſuch like, for the Mores commonly whē they fight againſt the Chriſtians, they ſtycke the heads of their arrowes in a Squill and poyſon it with the iuyce, and when thoſe arrowe heades or other weapon goeth into the fleſh of a man, it cauſeth ſo greate burning that it bringeth Spaſmus, and ſo in ſhort time they dye. And vntill this time there hath béene no other medicine found, but to cut away all the fleſh that the weapon hath touched, or els to cauteriſe it two or thrée times with a redde hot yron, to exſtinguiſh the venome, but I thorowe the grace of God haue founde the true and perfect way to helpe them quickelye and with great eaſe, and without detriment of the wounded, and the remedy is this, ye ſhall put our Quintaeſſence into the wounde, and laye there-on our Magno licore, the which are two medicines that kill the poyſon of the Squille, and therefore if any wil proue this to be true: To ſée the experiēce, take a péeſe of a Squilla, and ſcratch it with thy nayle, and then put thy finger into thy eare, or ſcrach any other place that yée may touch the fleſh, and preſently thou ſhalt féele a terribell bourning, and to quench it, preſently take of our Quintaeſſence, and waſh the place therewith, and preſentlye the payne will ceaſe, and therefore vſe this as a ſecrete, for there-with I haue cured a great number.
            
            
               A remedie founde out by me againſt the poyſon of a fiſh.
               WHen that I cauſed ſo many ſicke of the fluxe to go into the ſea whereby they were holpe, there was a certeine kinde of fiſh yt as ſoone as they touched

the fleſh of a man, preſentlye it inflamed and the poyſon ſo increaſed, that in two or thrée dayes, it cauſed coroſiue ſores, the which cauſed many to dye, and many were ſtonge with that fiſh the which neuer could finde helpe, I than ſéeing that deſparate caſe, vppon a time viſited a young man being a Romaine, the which was hurte on the coddes and yarde, with ſuch a ſpaſmus that it was wonderfull to behold, and hauing a glaſſe full of my Quintaeſſence in my hande, I opened the ſore and waſhed it therewith, and preſently the paine ceaſed, then afterwarde I dreſſed it with an vnguent made of the fat of the fiſh, &amp; ſo there with he &amp; a great number more were holpe in ſhort time, and theſe are ſecretes of my inuention.
            
            
               Of the taking of Afrika and his diſtruction.
               IN the yeare .1551. the 11. of September about the 19. houre the generall aſault was giuen to the citie of Africa, and in the ſpace of 2. houres it was takē, and deſtroyed by the ſoulders of Carolus Quintus, Emperour, where at was ſlaine a great number of both parts, and there was ſuch a number hurte that it was to bée wondered at, the which were healed with our Magno licore, and Balſamo, and when the citie was taken and all ended, the Galles remayned there all September, and the fourth of October euerye man went to ſerue at their portes appoynted, and ſo we tourned to Naples to paſſe the Winter, but yet we remayned but a while, for there was occaſion to go to Siena, the whych rebelled againſt the Emperour, &amp; ſo we went with Don Pietro da Toledo the which dyed after at Firenza, &amp;c.
               
            
            
               
               The cure of a great wound on the head.
               IN this yeare .1551. in the moneth of Nouember, there came vnto my houſe a Spaniard, the which was called Giouan Ruiz di Zamora, the which had a great wound ouer the eare, on the left ſide that reached halfe ouer the head, with great fracture of the bone, the which I preſently ſtitched with diligence, and put there-in our Quintaeſſence, and vppon the wounde I dreſſed it with Magno licore, and Balſamo, and made a gentle ligature with a péece of ſilke, and ſent him home to his lodging, and commaunded him to come againe the next day about the ſayd houre, &amp; thoſe that were about me, fell a laughing at my words, and ſayd that he woulde dye of that wounde, bicauſe I let him goe foorthe in the ayre, to the which I aunſwered that hée might ſafely goe foorth, and ſo the next day he came agayne, and I tooke off the lygament, bu not the cloth, and ther-on I put of our Quintaeſſence and Balme, and ſo in thrée dayes I touched it not, and then I tooke off the Lygament agayne, and dreſſed it vppon the cloath, and lette it remaine vntill the .8. daye, and then I opened it and tooke away the cloath and found the wound ſo healed that ye could ſcarce perceiue any ſcarre, and many ſaid that it was vnpoſſible to be healed, for it would come to impoſtumation, neuertheleſſe it remayned perfectly whole, for .5.or .6. moneths that he remayned in that citie, in the which time I cured a great number in the ſame order that were wounded in the head, to the great wonder of thoſe that dwelt in Naples, for they count all woundes in the heade to be mortall, bicauſe the ayre is ſo peſtilentiall, for as ſoone as it toucheth the ſcull it corrupteth the wound.
               But vſing our order thou mayſt ſafely helpe them, ſo that the wounde be not mortall, for by kéeping it

cloſe ſhut it is preſerued.
            
            
               A very ſtraunge thing that happened in the afore-ſayd yeare.
               THere was a certeine young Mariner of the age of 26. yeares, the which was called, Franciſco di Giouanni Raguſeo, of the Ile of Mezo, the which being in fight fell downe, and the other that fought with him cut him ouer the ſide and backe a handfull long, inſomuch that a péece of the Milt was cut ouer-thwart, then hée was caryed to a Chyrurgian, and hée ſtitched him vp, than the next day I was called, and ther I foūd the wounde not well ſtitched, the which I ripped vp agayne, and found the belly full of bloud, and when I ſaw that, I cauſed diuers to make water, and there-with I waſhed him, and with takinge foorthe of the bloude, there came a péece of the Milte that was cut, the which I waſhed, and gaue it to a Mariner that ſtoode by, and the Patrone of the ſhip tooke it from him and caryed it away, then I ſtitched him vp againe and left a lyttle hole or orifice beneath, where the matter might come forth, and dreſſed him with our Quintaeſſence, with Balſamo, and Magno licore, and in the ſpace of .22. dayes he was whole perfectly.
            
            
               The cure of a Fiſtoloe in the lower parts.
               IN the yeare .1552. in the moneth of Marche, I was broughte vnto a man of the age of fourtie yeares of complection, cholericke, and melencholicke, the which had a Fiſtoloe in the lower parts, ye which was of this Nature, that it had alterated the coddes, the member, and al the parts ther-about, with .xi. holes infiſtolated▪ at the which .xi. he made water with great burning &amp; intollerable paine, &amp; which are accident of a feuer in manner continual, ye which Patient had ben

taken in hand of diuers &amp; none could do him pleſure. Than the firſt thing that I did, I gaue him our Aromatico, that being done, I gaue him .xij. dayes together our Quintaeſſencia ſolutiuo, that being done, I gane him a quantitie of our Electuario Angelica, a then he vſed one of my ſecrets, the which I will not write in this place, that being done I cauſed him to ſpitte with one of my confections, written héere-after, and ſo by theſe meanes he was perfectly whole.
            
            
               Of many that I cured in Naples.
               IN that time that I remayned in the famous Citie of Naples vntil yt yere .1555. in ye Moneth of Februarie, &amp; then I thought it good to go to Rome where at this time I cure a number of perſons, &amp; haue holpe ſo many by the helpe of God, the which if I ſhould record them it would be ſufficient to fil a great volume, for ther came ſuch a number to my dore, that the people wondred ther-at, &amp; with .4. medicines compounded by me, I holpe in māner all of euery diſeaſe, &amp; the medicines were theſe, one Pil made with our Petra philoſophile, Elbero negro, Olio di ſulpho, Olio dimelle, mixed wt marchpane, &amp; made in pilles. The ſecond remedie was ſoluble pilles, made wt 
                  Aloe hepatico, Colloquintida, Siena, &amp; oyle of vitrioll, made in paſte wt ſugar, &amp; common hunny, The third remedie was a vnction, made wt Sage, Roſemary, Worme-woode, Rew, Mint. Nutmegs, Cloues, Cinamon, Maſtick, Frankē
                  cenſe, Terpentine &amp; waxe with common oyle. The .4. remedie was our Quintaeſſence, &amp; theſe .4. remedies, I gaue vnto thoſe people to help their griefes: &amp; I willed thē yt tooke theſe medicines to eat wel &amp; of good meats, &amp; ſo alwayes they praiſed theſe medicines, the which was not without great reaſon, bicauſe ye pilles firſt euacuate ye ſtomack of al impedimēts, a leaueth nature eaſed, ye ſecond pilles euacuate ye body of the corrupptiō.
               
                  The Vnction comforteth the ſtomacke, and helpeth diſgeſtion, and mitigateth the payne. The Quintaeſſence comforteth the ſtomacke, cauſeth good diſgeſtion, purifieth the bloud, and comforteth the heade, ſo that be theſe aforeſaid reſons, ye may vnderſtand that theſe foure remedies may help againſt al indiſpoſitions inwardly, and for cauſe of thoſe remedies thoſe people honour me lyke a Prophet, and alwayes haue had mée in great reuerence, as longe as I remayned amonge them.
            
            
               A cure of Vlcera putrida, the which was in the arme.
               IN the yeare afore-ſayd &amp; in the month of Auguſt, there came to my hande a certeine Gentleman of the Imbaſſadours of Portingall, that was called, Il ſignor Iari, a man of the age of .32. yeares of complection melancholyke: the which had a putrified vlcer about the lefte ſhoulder, that he had caryed aboue thrée yeares, and was a bigge as a hand, and verye déeps the which could not be healed of the common Chyrurgians, nor yet be eaſed of his payne, than I reaſoning with this Gentleman, tolde him that the cauſe of that ſore, was corrupt and putrified bloude, and by that meanes the 
                     •
                  yuer receiued euill qualyties, and that if he would be holpe, the cauſe muſt bee remoued, the which was hard to bée done, bicauſe the bloude muſt be euacuated a little, and then the ſtomacke muſt bée euacuated of moyſte matter that offendeth it, and hindereth diſgeſtion of the meate, and will not ſuffer good bloud to ingender, than it will alſo be neceſſarye to euacuate the body downwards, that the corruption ſendeth no vp his vapors to the vpper parts of ye body, and hinder the cure of the vlcer, al this being done,

it were neceſſary to euacuate the humor betwéene the ſkinne and the fleſh; by ſweate, ſo that all the partes of the body may remaine purified, and ſo by theſe meanes the vlcer may eaſely mundifie, incarnate, and ſcicatriſe, and ſhalbe a perfect cure, to the which thing the Gentle-man was willing, for hée had as willingly dyed as lyued, and ſo in the name of GOD I tooke him in hande, and the firſt thing that I gaue him was a vomitte that purged the ſtomacke, and tooke away great parte of his paine: then I purged him with our Quintaeſſencia Solutiuo, eight dayes together, that being done I made him a fomentation, that cauſed him to ſweate well, and to ſpitte aboundaunce, than I cauſed him to be let bloud vnder the tongue, and then I annoynted all the vlcer with our Cauſticke, the which mortified all the filthineſſe therein, and then I dreſſed it with Magno licore, and our cerote Magiſtralle, and ſo with theſe remedies in ſhort ſpace the ſaide Gentle-man was cured, to the greate meruaile of the ſaide Ambaſſadour, and all thoſe that ſawe it, by reaſon of that cure came another of the ſame houſe vnto me called Il ſeignor diego Iaimes the which was troubled with a difficultie of vrine, the which troubled him mightely, the which I gaue thrée times our Petra Philoſophalle, and once the iuyce of Elder barkes, and he was holpe: I cured another in the ſame houſe of a feuer with our Oyle of Hunny, and with Balſamo: The Ambaſſadour like wiſe being troubled with the gout, willed me to take him in hande ye which I did, and cured him ſo that in thrée yeares after which I continued in Rome he neuer felt paine, and of theſe cures I holpe an infinite in Spaine, as is wel knowne to the inhabitaunts thereoff.
            
            
               
               The cure of etheſia in the beginning.
               I
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  he yeare 1555. in the moneth of Marche, there came to my handes a young man of Milayne the which was a painter, of the age of fiue and twentye yeares, the which was fallen into a ſpice of etiſie, and did ſpitte much bloude with a continuall feuer, the which I cured in this order.
               Firſt I let him bloude vnder the tongue on the right ſide, and after that I gaue him a quantitie of our Aromatico with Plantaine water, bicauſe the bleding taketh away the ſuperfluous bloude of the breaſt, the which nature ſendeth forth by it ſelfe, and the Aromatico with Plantayne water is colde and dry, which are moſt neceſſarye for that diſeaſe, for they euacuate the ſtomacke, repercute and mittigateth yt alteration, thoſe things being done, I cauſed him to vſe our Quintaeſſence ſolutiue to euacuate the body in reſpect of the putrification alreadye conceiued with-in the inteſtinalles, alſo I cauſed him to vſe the Quintaeſſence of the flower of flowers, and I annoynted his ſtomacke with Magno licore, and alſo he vſed our Electuarie of Althea, and ſo by theſe meanes he was holpe perfectlye.
            
            
               The cure of a certeine man wounded in thirteene places.
               IT happened that a certeine man called Aleſſandro Oreſice, was wounded afore my lodging in 13. places, and there fell for deade, and then by a certeine friende was brought into my lodging, and there I layde him vpon a table and tooke of his clothes, and ſowed all thoſe wonndes which were to be ſowed or

ſtitched, and dreſſed him with our Quintaeſſence, and Balſamo, and Magno licore, and our ſecrete powder, and ſo by thoſe meanes in 15. dayes hée was perfecte whole.
            
            
               Of remedies that helpe many diſeaſes.
               THere are diuerſe and ſundry diſeaſes, and they bée holpe with dyuers and ſundry medicines, therefore I will make a note onely of thoſe the which are moſt vſed.
               And firſt I will write of thoſe remedies that helpe the feuers of all ſortes, the which are theſe, the ſirope of Burrage, Buglos, Endiue, Cicory, Hoppes, Fumitori, Rhabarb, Caſſia, Scamony, Sine, Barlye water, ſirope of Scytrones, and ſuch like.
               The remedies that helpe the pockes are theſe, Aloes, Coloquintida, Turbit, Hermodactilis, Scamony, Precipitate, Oriola, Oliuella, the vnction of Mercurie, Lignum ſanctum, Cina, Salſa perilla, the perfume of Scinaber, a ſtoue of hearbes, our Ceroto Magiſtralle, and ſuch like thinges, thoſe remedies that helpe the cough, are Enula Campane, Garlike, Sulfure, Hunny, Lapaciolle, the Oyle of Sulfure, and ſuch like, thoſe remedies that helpe the ſcabbes are the iuyce of Aureola, Sulfure, Litarge, Aqua Realle, Roch Allome, thoſe that are troubled with paines in the bodye, may vſe Genciane, Nutmegs, Dictamus albus, Euphorbio, thoſe that are wounded ſhall vſe Terpentine, our Balſamo, Magno licore, Aqua Balſamo, Elixer vitae, Ceroto magiſtralle, Oyle of Hiperconie of our inuention, and ſuch like: Thoſe yt prouok vrine, are yt flowers of Mallows, Alcakēgi, Hoggs liſe, Cantarides, &amp; ſuch like, &amp; therfore I will not trouble you further bicauſe I haue written ſufficiently in my other bookes in ſundrye places,

and hereafter I will write of dyuers, and ſundry medicines of our inuention neuer founde out a fore of any man.
            
         
         
            Here beginneth the order to make diuerſe and ſundrie medicines of our inuention, neuer founde out before by any man. And firſt to make our Petra Philoſophalle, that helpeth againſt all manner of diſeaſes that happeneth vnto man or woman, or any other animall tereſtryall.
            THere hath alwayes béene a greate queſtioning among the Philoſophers, whether that one medicine might helpe againſt all diſeaſes or noe. The which I affirme, and wil approue with ſufficient reaſon that the Petra Philoſophalle made of our inuencion, may helpe againſt al the infirmities that commeth vnto mans bodie, and two onely reaſons I will ſhewe thée with breuitie, the firſt of them is this, that all ſortes of infirmities haue their Originall and beginning of the ſtomacke, and to knowe the troth yée may ſée manifeſtlye, that if the body be neuer ſo little infermid the ſtomack is alſo grieued: For yée may ſée how the anymalles tereſtryall, neuer helpe themſelues of other infirmitie than of the ſtomacke, and when they wil helpe themſelues, they eate hearbes, the which cauſeth them to vomitte, and this doth ſignifie that they haue no other infirmitie, than the aforeſaide, ſo by ye experience of ye animalles I approue that the infirmitie is cauſed of the ſtomacke, and this is the firſt reaſon. The ſeconde is, that all the medicines, where in our Petra Philoſophalle is put, as ſoone as they are come into the ſtomacke, it draweth vnto it, all the euil humours of the ſtomacke, and alſo of the whole bodie,

and mixeth with them, and ſo Nature ſendeth them foorth by vomit or by ſege, or both, and ſo the ſtomack ſhall be euacuated of that matter, and the body remain frée from al impediments of infirmities, ſo that by this reaſon I affirme, that our Petra Philoſophalle maye helpe againſt all ſorts of infirmities, and to know the troth, I haue proued it by experience, in all manner of infirmities, and alwayes haue founde it to doe much good vnto al men, and hurt none vnto my knowledge, and the order to make this Petra Philoſophalle, is thus.
            
               Rec. Sal niter, Rock allome, Vitrioll Romayne, of each two pound.
            Firſt dry the Vitrioll in a earthen panne, and then beat it to powder, and mixe it with the other matters, and put there-vnto foure ounces of Sal gemme, then put it in a goord with his head, &amp; a receiuer, well luted, and diſtill it in a winde furnace, ſo that ye maye make fire with woode, and at the firſt make ſmal fire, and ſo increaſe it according to Arte, and alwayes lay wet clothes on the head and receiuer, and that thou ſhalt doe bicauſe the ſpirites of the water ſhall not flye away. Ye ſhall vnderſtande that in the beginning of of your diſtillation, the Receiuer will waxe red lyke bloud, and then tourne white, and at the laſte, when ye giue it ſtrong fire, it will tourne red againe, and thoſe are the pure ſpirites of the Aqua fortis, and then at the ende, the Receiuer will tourne white againe, &amp; then it is ended, then let it wax colde, and then kéepe it in a Glaſſe cloſe ſhutte, to make our Petra Philoſophalle.
            
            Than take Mercury. lib. 1. Quicke lyme, ounces .6. Sope, ounces .4. Common aſhes, ounces .3.
            
            Mixe them together in a morter of ſtone, &amp; then put them into a Retort, and diſtil it with a ſtrong fire

vntil all the Mercury be come foorth into the receiuer▪ then take it foorth, and kéepe it in a glaſſe, to make thy compoſition, the which is made thus.
            
               Rec. The water that thou madeſt firſt, and put it into a goord of glaſſe being well luted, and then put in thy Mercury that thou diddeſt diſtill afore. After that, take Stéele in thinne plates, ounce .1. Iron alſo in thin plates, ounce .2. Fine Golde in leaues, the waight of two French crownes, and put them altogether in the glaſſe, &amp; preſently ſet on the heade, for it will begin to boyle, and cauſe red fumes lyke bloud, the which thou ſhalt receiue in a receiuer, and preſently ſet thy glaſſe in the Furnace and giue it fire vntil all the water be come foorth with the fume. Them let it coole, and kéepe that water cloſe in a glaſſe, then breake ye other glaſſe that ſtoode in the fire, and in the bottome thou ſhalt finde our Petra Philoſophalle, the which thou ſhalt grinde finely, and ſearce it in moſt fine powder, and then waſhe it well with Vineger diſtilled, and drye it againe, and at the laſt waſh it with Roſe-water, and drye it very well, ſtirring it continually ouer the fire, then kéepe it as a precious Iewell cloſe in a Glaſſe.
            For the order to vſe it, I wil write héere-after, in ſundrye places: Ye ſhall vnderſtande that the water the which ye diſtilled away from the ſtone, will ſerue for the ſame purpoſe agayne: But ye muſt take but halfe the quantitie of the afore-ſayde matters, and when yée haue diſtilled it agayne from the ſtone, yée ſhall preſerue it, for an infinite number of purpoſes, as I will ſhew thée héere-after.
            
               
               To make our Balme artificiall, with the order to vſe it, and wherefore it ſerueth.
               THis Balſamum hath all the vertues of the natural Balme, although not in qualytie, yet in vertue, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Venice Turpentine, pound .1. Oyle of Bayes, that is perfect with-out mixture, ounces .4. Galbanū, ounc. 3. Gum Araby, ounc. 4. Olibanum, Mirrha electe, Gum hedera, of each, ounces .3. Lignum Aloes, Galingal, Cloues, Conſolida minore, Cinamon, Nutmegs, Zedoaria, Ginger, Diptamnum album, of each, ounce 1. Muſke of Leuant, Ambergres, of each one dram.
               Beat all thoſe afore-ſayd things together, &amp; put them into a Retort of glaſſe well luted, and put there-to .6. pound of Rectified Aqua vitae with-out fleame, and ſo let it ſtande viij. dayes, and then diſtil it by ſande, and there wil come foorth a white water mixed with oyle, and ſo kéepe thy fire ſmall, vntill there come foorthe a blackiſh Oyle, then chaunge thy receiuer, and ſet therto an other, and increaſe thy fire vntill all the ſpirites be come foorth, than ſeperate the Oyle from the black water, &amp; kéepe them by themſelues, &amp; the lyke ſhall ye do by the firſt water. The firſt water that is white, is called Aqua del Balſamo, and the Oyle ſeperated from that is called, Oleum del Balſamo. The ſecond water that is blacke is called Mater Balſami, and the Oyle ſeperated from that water, is called Balſamo artificiato, the which would be kept as a precious Iewell.
               The firſt water is moſt excellent to cléere and preſerue the ſight of the eyes, alſo the face being waſhed ther-with, it maketh it very faire, &amp; preſerueth it youthfully, it kéepeth backe age, it breaketh the grauell in the reynes, and prouoketh vrine the which is ſtopped

                     〈1 page missing〉
                  
                  
is our Aromatico, bicauſe it euacuateth the ſtomacke by vomitte, and the body downewarde, and his operation is ſuch, that it doth in maner helpe any crude ſort of infirmitie, and the quantitie is from one drame, to two drames, and may be taken in broth, in wine, in water, or mixe it with any pilles, or pocion, giuing you charge, that when yée put it in any pocyon that ye leaue none in the bottome, of the cup where yée drinke it out, bicauſe the Petra Philoſophalle is heauie, and will remaine in the bottome, for if that remaine it wil not worke at all, giuing you alſo charge that the ſaid day that yée giue this medicine, that ye let the patient drink as much crude water as the will, and giue them little meate to eate that day, and this is the order to vſe this medicine.
            
            
               To make our Electuario Angelico, and the order to vſe it, and in what diſeaſes.
               
                  ELectuario, Angelico romano, is ſo called, bicauſe it was compounded of me in the citie of Rome, in the time of the Pope Paulo quarto, and bicauſe this compoſition worketh ſodeinelye, I called it Angelico, and is moſt excellent againſt many diſeaſes, it is good againſt all ſortes of feuers, giuing it Perminoratiuo, and for the ſtitch in the ſide it is moſt rare, bicauſe it taketh away the viſcocitie in the ſtomacke, and openeth the powers, and is good againſt the goute, for if they take it euery thirde day once, in ten dayes they ſhalbe hope, it is alſo good againſt the cough, Cattar, and for the Mylte, and for thoſe that haue ye pocks, or the running gout, and ſuch like influences, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Safran, Lignum alleos, Sinamon, redde Coral ana thrée drames, Elleborus niger, without preparation,

two ounces Electuario de ſucco roſarum, Meſue, that is not too much boyled, vi. ounces, Sugar roſate viii. ounces, Muſke of Leuant one drame, Petraphiloſophalle thrée ounces, our Quintaeſſence, of wine, two ounces, purified hunny as much as wil ſuffiſe to make it in forme of a Lectuary, mixe them on a ſmall fire in an earthen pan, and when it is made, kéepe it in a veſſell of glaſſe, for any other veſſell wil not be good: This Electuary yée may mixe with any ſollible medicine, but ye muſt take it faſting, the quantitie is from two drames to foure drames. Ye ſhall vnderſtand yt this in manner reuiueth the dead by his great vertue, as hath bene ſéene many thouſand times, in Venice, &amp; in Rome, moſt worthy of memory, and therfore if any Phiſition deſire to get fame in the world, let them vſe our Electuario Angellica, the which worketh miracles on the earth.
            
            
               Of the vigitable ſtone, of our Inuention, to tranſemute a body of one complexion into another, and to make him ſounde for euer.
               THe way to make the vigitable ſtone is rare, and his vertues are infinite, and without compariſon, &amp; the cures that are done therewith are ſo myraculous, that the worlde will not beléeue them, although it bée the méere troth, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Tartar of white Wine that is thicke and ſhining, Turpentine that is cleare and pure: The herbe called Alloes that hath leaues as long as an arme, and dented on both ſides, and ſome cal it ſemper viue, take of ech of theſe one pounde, and ſtampe them together, and put them into a vrynal with a heade and receiuer, and diſtyll them in a wyne furnes vntyll all the ſubſtance be come forth, then take the feſſes out of ye glaſſe

and grinde them with the ſaide water, and then diſtill them as thou diddeſt afore, and alwayes at the laſt giue it a ſtronge fire that the feſſes may remaine well burnt, then take out the feſſes againe and grinde them with the water as thou diddeſt firſt, and diſtill it againe, and this thou ſhalt do 15. or twentie times, vntill all that water be conſumed, &amp; yt the feſſes remaine white like ſalte, then lay that feſſes on a ſmoth ſtone in a moyſt place, and it wil turne into water, the which kéepe in a glaſſe cloſe ſhutte, and that is the water of the vigitable ſtone, the which water is of ſo much vertue, that one ſcruppell there-of being put into ij. ounces of Iulepe of Violettes, and giuen to drinke to any that is infirmed or euil complexcionated, in leſſe then foure and twentie dayes he ſhalbe holpe of anye griuous diſcaſe, and this muſt be taken in the morning faſting when the ſtomacke is emptie, for than it worketh better his operation.
               This is alſo an excellent remedy againſt ye worms, giuing it in the a fore-ſaide manner, it mundifieth the Lyuer, and dryeth ye humiditie of yt Mylte, it diſſolueth the cough, and Cattares, it prouoketh vryne where it is lette, with dyuers other vertues, the which I wyll let paſſe vntill another time, for if I ſhoulde write them all, they woulde not be credited, and there-fore we Phiſitians ſhoulde not reſt to practiſe in all things that ſéemeth to vs conuenient, and I promiſe thée truely that hée which ſhall occupie this thing, ſhall worke myracles on the earth, and winne greate fame and honour. Yée ſhal vnderſtande that this is the ſtone that the Philoſophers haue long ſought to fixe their medicine mynerall, ſo that making the proiection they ioyne the medicine with metalling bodyes, and not to go away in ſume, bicauſe this ſtone reſiſteth all great fires with-out conſuming, and ſixeth Sulfure

and Orpiment, ſo that they ſhall abide the fire, &amp; maketh them white, if ye make proiection there-with on Copper, or on Lattine, it will turne it into the whiteneſſe of pure ſiluer, &amp; that I haue ſéene with my eyes, ſo that ye may ſée of what importaunce this vigitable ſtone is, the which worketh ſuch goodly tranſmutations, as well in mettallyng bodyes, as in humain bodyes, and therefore it is to be accounted off, bicauſe it may ſaue the lyfe of manye that vſe it in their medicines.
            
            
               Our ſolyble ſiroppe with the order to vſe it.
               SOlyble ſiropes made in decoction are very wholſome and of great facultie, &amp; ſpecially in the crudite of humours, and the reaſon is this: bicauſe it diſperſeth the matter, and euacuateth it with great eaſe, and without daunger or trouble of the Patient, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Sage, Roſemary, Worme-wood, Cicory, Cardus ſanctus, Nettels, Organy, of each a handfull. Figs, Raiſons, Dates, ſwéet Almonds, Sal gem, ana ounc. 4. Coloquintida, Aloes hepatica, Cinamon, Mirabolani citrini, ana ounc. 2. Common hunny, two pound.
               Stampe them all groſely, and put them to infuſe in eightéene pounds of faire water, then boyle it till halfe be conſumed, then ſtrayne it, and diſtill it by a filter, and aromatiſe it with two caretes of Muſke and a pint of Roſe-water, and then it is made, the which ye ſhall kéepe in a bottell of glaſſe cloſe ſtopte, the quantitie is from foure ounces to ſixe ounces.
               In Winter you ſhall take it very warme. And in the Spring and Autumne, ye ſhall take it but warm. In Summer ye ſhall take it colde, for this purgeth

the groſe humors of the body, and hurteth not the ſtomacke, ye may vſe it in a feuer .4. or 5. dayes together, and it will helpe it. In cruditie of humours, as the French Pockes, Goutes, Cattares, Doglie Artetiche, and ſuch lyke matters, where there is no accident of Feuer, ye may take it .x. or .xv. dayes together, &amp; cannot hurt by any meanes, for it purgeth moſt excellent, it is giuen againſt the Cough, againſt fluxe of the vrine, &amp; paynes in the head, and carnoſitie in the yard, for the Hemerhodes, and in ſumme it is good againſt al diſeaſes cauſed of corrupt humors, for it hath ſuch vertue, that it draweth from al parts, and euacuateth the humours inteſtinall, for of this Siroppe I haue had great experience, in ſuch perſons as were in manner baniſhed and had loſt their taſte, and preſently vſing this, they came to good temperature, and I haue vſed it an infinite number of times, in perſons that were vlcerated, and full of ſores, euil bandeled of Fortune, and of the infirmitie, and finding no meanes to cure them as they ſhould be, I gaue them this Sirop fourtéene or fiftéene dayes, and then they were cured, with a number of other things the which would be too long to write, and therefore I would wiſh euery one to vſe this, not onely in the afore-ſayd matters, but in all other diſeaſes.
            
            
               Our Siropo magiſtrale Leonardo, the which ſarueth againſt an infinite number of diſeaſes, and is a rare medicine.
               THis Sirop is ſolutiue, and very pleaſant to vſe, and can-not hurt in any wiſe, the which is ſeldome ſéene in other medicines, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. The leaues of Sine, ounces .2. Fumitorie, Mayden-haire, Hartes-tongue, lyuer-wort, Epitemū,

Ellemo, Pollipo of the Oke, the floures of Burrage, of Bugloſſe, Lycories, of each ounces .3. Colloquintida, Elleborus niger, Aloes hepatica, Mirabolani Indi, ana ounc. 1. Proynes .14. Sebeſtien .12. Tamiriſe. ℥ .1. Stampe them groſely, and infuſe them in .x. poundes of Fumitorie water, then boyle it vntil the conſumption of the third part, and then ſtraine it, and in that which is ſtrained put theſe things: Sirop of Stecados, pound .1. Saffron, one ſcruple. Mel roſarum, ounc. 6. Rectified Aqua vitae, ounc. 4. Muſke, dram .1. The muſlege of marſh Mallowes, ounces .4. Beniamin, ounce 1. Roſe-water, ounces .3. And then it is made, ye which ye ſhall kéepe in a glaſſe cloſe ſtopt, &amp; kéepe it in a temperate place, and this you muſt take warme, the quantitie is from two ounces to foure ounces, and it is a moſt ſafe medicine to be vſed with-out kéeping of any dyet. It helpeth thoſe much that haue Pellaria, ſcabbes, Hemerhodes, and ſuch like diſeaſes, and may be giuen vnto a woman with childe, with-out any daunger, when ſhe ſhall haue occaſion to vſe any.
            
            
               Our Sirop againſt the melancholike humor, and ſpecially where there is ventoſitie in the ſtomacke.
               IT were neceſſary for thoſe that will make this ſiroppe, to be experte in the Arte, for it woulde be made with great diligence, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Water of Fumitorie, of Hoppes, of Wormwoode, of Mayden haire, of each fiue pounde. Then with this water thou ſhalt make a decoction with theſe things that follow.
               
                  
                  Rec. Pollipodium of the Oake, one pounde, Sine leaues, Epitimum, ana ounc. 4. Cordiall floures, two handfulls. Mayden-haire, one handful. Lycoris, Raiſons, Cinamon, of each ounces .2. The .4. Cole ſeedes, ounces .2. Make thereoff a Decoction acording to Art, and ſtrayne it, then take foure pounde of that Decoction, &amp; put there-to, the iuyce of Burrage, of Bugloſſe, of Hoppes, of each ounces .2. Common Hunny, ounces .6. Then with white Sugar, make a Sirope in good forme, and aromatiſe it with Muſke and Amber, putting there-to, one ounce of Plyris with-out Muſk, and then it is made. The quantitie is from thrée ounces to foure ounces in the morning warme, and faſte there-on, at the leaſt thrée or foure houres, for this purgeth meruaylouſlye the melancholycke humoures and all other groſe humours, and diſſolueth winde, and comforteth the heart, &amp;c.
            
            
               Our Potion of Lignum Sanctum, the which is miraculous to diſſolue crude, and malygne humours, with the order to vſe it, in the French Pockes, and ſuche lyke diſeaſes.
               BIcauſe the Pocks is a diſeaſe contagious, putrified, and corrupt, and worketh many euill effects, as I haue written in my Caprici medicinalle, therefore it were neceſſary to prepare moſt excellent and rare rememdies to diſſolue the ſame, which medicines are infinite.
               But in this Chapter I wil write one, that purgeth the crude and viſcous humoures downe-wards, and doth aſſuttiliate the groſe humors, and dryeth al ſorts of ſubtill humours that offende Nature and ſendeth them foorth by ſweate, it dryeth the melancholick humour,

and diſſolueth choller, and is moſt holeſome for thoſe that are troubled with that diſeaſe, bicauſe it dryeth much and diſſolueth the diſeaſe, with many other good effects, as by experience thou maiſt ſée, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. The barke of Lignum ſanctum groſely beatē pounde .1. and lay it to ſtéepe in xiiij. pounde of faire water 24. houres, then boyle it vntill foure poundes be conſumed, then put there to, Pollypody of the Oke, two ounces, Cicory one handfull, Aloes epatike foure drames, and let them boyle for an houre: Then put therevnto the leaues of Syue, Epitemum, ana, ounce 1. Coloquintida, drame 6. Sugar, ounce 8. thē let it boyle till halfe be boyled away, and that there remain pound 7. then ſtraine it, and put it in a glaſſe with 12. graines of Muſke, and kéepe it very cloſe ſtopt, and this is the ſirope the which ye ſhall take twiſe a day, that is morning and euening, then make this drinke following ye which ſhall be ye common drinke at all times, to your meate.
               
                  Rec. One pounde of Lignum ſanctum, Raſpead, and ſtéepe it in x. pounds of whit wine that is ripe, and let it boile an houre, thē put therto xv. poūd of faire water &amp; let boyle a little more, and then ſtraine it, and kéepe it in a glaſſe bottle, for this is to be vſed all they day time, and the order to vſe theſe is thus. Firſt whan any féeleth himſlefe greued with the pocks or any ſuch like diſeaſe, he muſt kéepe his bedde at the leaſt xx. dayes, and vſe to take of the firſt ſirope or pocyon euery morning a good draft being as warme as he may ſuffer it, than kéeuer him wel with clothes that he may ſweate as much as he can, then take off the clothes by lyttle and lyttle, and drye him with warme clothes, &amp; ſo let him repoſe for two houres, and then let him eat and his meate muſt be drye, as Biſcote, roſt-meate,

Rayſons of the Sun, Almonds, and ſometime a rawe egge, &amp; his drinke at meales,a and al the day beſide ſhal be the laſt made with wine &amp; water, thē at night giue him of the firſt ſirope as ye did in ye morning, &amp; cauſe him to ſweat, &amp; then drye him, and this order thou ſhalt vſe xx. dayes together not comming forth of thy chāber, &amp; by the grace of God thou ſhalt be holpe of anye ſuch griuous infirmity, as I haue ſene ye experiēce therof an infinite of times, to my great honour, for it may be occupied in all complexions, with ſafetie, as by the ingredience thou maiſt ſée.
            
            
               A moſt meruailous water &amp; rare, to cauſe a man to auoyd the grauel in vrine, and to mundifie the raynes.
               THe grauel int he raynes of the backe is cauſed, and ingēdred of great heate, &amp; drynes in thoſe parts, as thou maiſt plainely ſee by thoſe which are troubled therwith, for heir raynes is ſo hot yt they cannot abide any heauie garment to lye there-on, and they alwayes make their water with great paine &amp; burning: therefore if thou wilt helpe that infirmity, it were neceſſary to refrigerate the raynes and moiſten it with good iuyce, &amp; take away that burning of ye vrine, &amp; ſo in that order the patient ſhal be holpe, and this thou maiſt do in ſhort time, and with great eaſe with this remedy.
               
                  Rec. The ſéede of ſmal Lemonds, the ſéede of Oranges, ana one pound, Saxifrage, pound vi. Balme, Scolopendria, Pellitory of the wall, Sparagus, Criſoni, Iſope, Fenel rootes, Parſely roots, ana, ounce 6. ſtampe thē altogether &amp; make thē in forme of aliquid vnguēt wt the iuyce of Lemons, thē diſtil it in a cōmon tyn ſtillytory being luted vntil the matter, remaine dry, thē kéepe yt water in a glaſſe cloſe ſtopt, &amp; whē ye wil occupy this water, ye muſt firſt purge ye body of the crude &amp; viſcous

humors, &amp; likewiſe euacuate the ſtomacke of choller &amp; fleme, that being done thou ſhalt take euery morning &amp; euening vi. ounces warme, &amp; it wold be neceſſary for thoſe yt take it, to vſe a dyet, &amp; to refraine moiſt &amp; cold meats, &amp; vſe only dry things &amp; ſo this water ſhal help thoſe aforeſaid griefs, as I haue proued diuers times.
            
            
               To make the water of Lignum ſanctū, moſt wholſome againſt the pockes with a new order.
               COmmonly they vſe to take the water of Lignum ſanctum, againſt the pockes, the whiche ſurely is moſt wholeſome, but it muſt be taken in good order and fourme, and muſt be made with great diſcretion, and not as they vſe it now adayes, for they giue it ſome 3. or 4. times, &amp; neuer the better, although the wood be ſufficient ynough to helpe themm and therefore I would wiſh euery one yt will vſe this water to take it in ſuch order as it ought to be, the which I wil ſhew thée hereafter.
               
                  Rec. Lignun ſanctum Raſped ſmall, pound 1. ye bark being beaten .℥.3. infuſe them in 12. poundes of fayre water one night, &amp; the next morning put therein li.1. of hunny, the which is put in, bicauſe it is aparatiue &amp; warme, a helpeth to prouoke ſweate, and cauſeth it to haue a good taſt, then boyle it til halfe be conſumed, then put ther-to Cardus ſanctus .℥ .4. ſtrong wine poūd 3. then boyle it vntill a thirde part bee conſumed, and than it is made, that ſtraine it, &amp; take forth the Cardus ſanctus, &amp; put ther-on 20. pounds of faire water, &amp; li.1. of hunny, &amp; let it boyle vntil 4. pounds béeconſumed, and ſtraine it and kéepe it in a glaſſe bottle, for this is ye common drinke to drinke all ye day long, &amp; ye order to take it is thus: firſt afore ye wil take this water it wer neceſſary to take our Siropo Solutiuo .7. or .8. dayes, after ye take of our Electuario Angelica, ℥ 
                     ſ
                     semis
                  . yt being done in ye name of god take this potion of Lignum ſanctum
                  
in this order, take in the morning at the appering of ye day, ounce 8. very warme as ye may ſuffer, &amp; preſently lay clothes on him, and cauſe him to ſweate 2. houres, &amp; then dry him with warme clothes, and ſo let him remaine 2. houres, &amp; thē giue him to eate, &amp; his meate ſhalbe Biſcote, Rayſons, Almonds, &amp; ſometime a litle roſt-meate, and no other: then in the euening about the 22. houre, ye ſhall giue him the ſaid ſirope as ye did in the morning, neither more nor leſſe, and cauſe him to ſweate, and about the 24. houre giue him only Biſcote and Rayſons, and the other common drinke that was made laſt, giuing you warning that ye make this drinke freſh euery thirde day, bicauſe it ſhall not hurt the ſtomacke, and euery wéeke once ye ſhall take a pil of Marte millitare, and that day thou ſhalt eate byrdes fleſh, bicauſe of weakning, alſo ye ſhal take very great héede to one thing, &amp; yt is this, if it happen tha at the beginning of this cure, there commeth a feuer or other accydent vnto the patient, that in any wiſe ye leaue not the cure, but followe the order, for that is a certeine ſigne of helth, for many times I haue giuen this water and vnto ſome in the fourth or 5. daye the feuer came, and taryed many tames, x. or xij. dayes, and thē the feuer went away with the corrupt diſeaſe, and all for company, and ſo in ſhort time they were cured, ſo that as I haue ſaide afore when that ſyne appeareth, &amp; is delyuered it is a certeine ſigne of health: Alſo I will aduiſe thée of another thing, and that is this, if the patient cannot ſweate, yée ſhall annoynt him all ouer wt the Oyle of Quinces, the which will cauſe him to ſweate a pace: For without ſweate the cure will not be perfect, and this order thou ſhalt kéepe at the leaſt fortie dayes together, within the chamber ſo that there come no ayre in, for it will hinder the cure.
            
            
               
               Our diſtillation for the Eteſia, the which is of of meruaylous vertue and with-out compariſon with the order to vſe it.
               SAuing written ſufficiently of the qualytie of the Feuer Etike and his cure, in my Caprici medicinalle, héere I will write of nothing but the order to make this precious Licore, with the order to vſe it, as well for that diſeaſe as for other ſuch lyke, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. A young Hen that hath not yet layd Egges, and pull hir quicke, and then take forth hir guttes, only and ſtampe hir in a ſtone morter, and put there-to as much crum of white bread as the fleſh doth way &amp; ſtampe them together, and putte there-to a handfull of freſh ſcabious, and as many leaues of golde as wayeth a French crowne, than put there-to as much water of Mortella as all the afore-ſayd matter doth waye, &amp; ſo leaue it one night, and then diſtill it in a vrinall of glaſſe, with thrée pound of ſtrong wine, in Balneo Marie, vntil the feſes remaine drye, and then it is ended.
               Then for euery pound of this diſtillation, putte thre-vnto one ounce of the water of Honny made according to our order, and kéepe it in a glaſſe vnſtopte that the ſtrong ſauor may go away, &amp; the order to vſe it in the Feuer Etike I haue written in his chapter, this ſerueth alſofor thoſe inward cauſes the which are moſt troubleſome, a for thoſe yt haue a burning feuer, alſo for women that haue a feuer in their childberth.
            
            
               Our vigitable Siroppe the which is miraculous and diuine.
               THis Sirop is one of my 7. ſecréetes with the which I haue done many myracles many times, in diuers

operations, on many infirmities, and haue ben ſo charie of it, that I ment neuer to ſet it foorthe in my lyfe time, but yet I conſidering what great benefit it might be vnto the world, I thought good to ſet it foorth that euery one might be ſerued according to his pleaſure: and the lyke I will doe of many other ſecrets of great importaunce, the which ſhall be diſpearced among my bookes, and the order to make this Siroppe, is thus.
               
                  Rec. Lignum aloes, Riopontico, Eupatorio, Redde Saunders, of each ounces .2. Beat them &amp; make therof a decoction in good form, &amp; with foure pound of this decoction make a ſirop, &amp; put therto theſe things following, whiles it is hotte, Saffrane, one ſcruple. Ginger, one dram. Muſke .2. Carrets. The ſolucion of our Petra Vigitabile, ounc. 3. Cloues, Nutmegs, of each one ſcruple and a halfe, that kéepe it in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut, and this is our vigitable ſirop, the which worketh miracles in diuers infirmities, for by his nature it purifieth the bloud mundifieth the lyuer, comforteth ye hart, preſerueth ye ſtomack, prouoketh urine diſſolueth grauel in the raines, it helpeth ye cough, &amp; helpeth diſgeſtion, &amp; quieteth al ye humors in the ſick perſon, with diuers other vertues, the which I wil leaue till another time. This may be taken with broth, with diſtilled waters, or with any decoction or medicine faſting, ye quantitie is from one dram, to two drams, and happy ſhall they be the which ſhall vſe it.
            
            
               An Electuary that helpeth the cough, with great ſpeed, and eaſe.
               THe Cough is cauſed of a cattarus humor, and coldneſſe of the ſtomacke, and therefore if ye wil helpe it, it were neceſſary to haue a remedy that doth ripen the cattare, and mollifie the ſtomacke, and the order

to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Enula campana, ounc. 4. Marſh mallowes, xij. ounces. Quinces .xvi. ounces. But if ye can-not get Quinces, ye may take Marmilade ready made, and boyle it in faire water with the ſaide rootes, vntill they be drye then ſtampe them in a morter, &amp; ſtrayne them thorow a ſtrayner, then take for euery pounde of that matter .2. pound of white Honny, and boile them together, but boyle them not to much, then take it from the fire, and put there-vnto for euery pound of the aforeſayd matter, one ſcruple of Saffran, and one dram of Cinamon, and two ounces of ſulphur, and one ſcruple of Lycoris, and then incorporate them well together, and aromatiſe it with Muſke and Roſe water, &amp; this ye ſhall vſe morning and euening, for this is of ſo great vertue that it is to be wondred at, bicauſe the mallowes do moilifie, the Enula campana doth warme, and cauſeth diſgeſtion, &amp; comforteth ye ſtomack, ye quinces are cordiall &amp; warme, the ſulphur is a great dryer, the which deſtroyeth ye euil humors of ye body, ye ſaffran comforteth the heart, ye cinamon is ſtomacall, ye lycoris is mollificatiue, &amp; diſgeſteth ye matter, ſo yt of force this Electuary muſt help any kind of cough, except it come of ye pocks, for then it wil doe ſmal pleaſure, as I haue proued.
            
            
               Electuario benedicto Leonardi, the which purgeth the body without any grief, &amp; is miraculous in his operation.
               THis Electuario benedicto, is compound of our inuē
                  tion many yeares agoe, &amp; is ſo called bicauſe of his meruailous operation, &amp; the order to make it, is thus.
               
                  Rec. Of a certeine kinde of frute called of ſome, Spina merula, of other Spini ceruino, with his bery they make a kinde of ſap gréene, take of theſe berries when they be ripe, and ſtampe them, and take there-off, the

Iuice and ſtraine it by a fylter, and for euery pound of the afore ſayde Iuice ye ſhall put therin theſe thinges, Sinamond, Safarne, Cloues, Nutmeges, Ginger, ana dram 1. Sena, alloes, ana dram .3. mixe thē well together and ſet it in the ſunne till it be dryed like a paſte, and than make it liquid againe with theſe following.
               
                  Rec. Roſe water, our Quintaeſſence, ana ounces 2. for a pound. Muſke 2. carretes for a pound, Mirrha dramme .1. for a pounde. Incorporate all the aforeſayde thinges together, and ſet it in the ſunne vntill it be thorowe drye and may be made in powder, of the which yée ſhall take what quantitie yée will, and mixe it with as much honnie purified, and that is our Electuario benedicto, the which purgeth the body without paine, and preſerueth the ſtomacke, purgeth the head, and helpeth putrified feuers, with diuers other things the which I will not write at this time. Ye may kéepe this Mixture 6. monethes after it is mixt with honny: the doſe is from halfe an ounce to a whole ounce. Yée may take them in Pilles in broth, in a Lectuarie, or in Wine, or how yée will, and alwayes they ſhall make his effect well.
            
            
               An Electuarie againſt the euill diſpoſition of the Liuer and Stomacke.
               THe Liuer is troubled with diuers and ſundry cauſes: but for the moſte parte it is of heate: For the heate ſhoweth ſome out-warde ſigne as is ſéene by experience, for their Face and Noſe are red, they haue heate in their Legs, chops in the palme of their hand, and féete. It ingendreth Fluxes in the body, burning of Vrine, running of the Raines, and ſuch like effects. And the order to cure them is thus.
               
                  Rec. Citraca, Scolopendria, Epatica, Eupatorio, ana 3.
                  
ounces, beate them in fine pouder, Lignum aloes thrée drames, Safrane 2. ſcrupules, Cinamon, two drames, white crude hunny one pound and a halfe mixe them and incorporate them together without fire, then take thereof morning and euening 1. ounce at a time, but afore ye begin to take this electuary, ye ſhall take a quantitie of our Electuario Angelica, and then in ſhort time they ſhall be holpe as thou maiſt well ſée by the ingredience that goeth into this compoſition.
            
            
               Our magiſtrall Electuary of Sulfure the which ſerueth againſt diuers ſortes of infirmities.
               AS the fire hath vertue to heate and drye materyall things, ſo hath the Sulfure vertue to warme, and to drye the humiditie and coldneſſe of our bodyes, for I haue occupied it diuers &amp; sundry times, and all wayes haue ſéene diuers and ſundry good effects, but for the better commoditie, and more eaſe to vſe it, I haue compounded this Electuary, the whiche thou maiſt vſe with eaſe and benifite vnto a number, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Very fine Sulfure that is without earth, and make it in fine powder, one pound, Cinamon halfe an ounce, Safran one ſcruple, Ginger 2. drames. Muſke diſſolued in roſe water .2. Carretts, white hunny crude as much as will ſuffice to make it in a lectuary with out fire, then kéepe it in a dry place: and this ye ſhall vſe in the morning faſting, and his quantitie is from foure drames to ſeuen. This dryeth vp ſcabbes, proueth vryne, breaketh the ſtone in the raynes, it helpeth ye cough, dryeth vp ye watering of the eyes, cauſeth

a good appetite, with dyuers other thinges the which I will leaue to the experimentors.
            
            
               Our Electuario of Conſolida magore that ſerueth for many diſeaſes inwardly.
               THis Conſolida magore, is a herbe ſo called, bicauſe of his effecte that it doth in healing of woundes, and other places of the fleſh ſeparated, for if ye eate thereof it will helpe the rupture, and all ſortes of woundes penetrating and vlcers of the longes, it dryeth the milte and ſuch like effectes, but bicauſe thou maiſt vſe it more commodious, I haue compounded an Electuary the which is excellēt and rare, and is made thus.
               
                  Rec. The roote of Conſolida magore, one pounde, &amp; boyle it in water vntill it bee conſumed, then ſtampe them in a morter and paſſe them thorowe a ſtrayner, then put there-to as much white hunny as the matter wayeth and boyle them on a ſmall fire vntill it bée come to the forme of a Lectuary, and when it is boyled put thereto theſe thinges.
               
                  Rec. The ſhelles of Pomgarnades in fine powder, one ounce, Lignum aloes, vi. drames, Mirra, Maſtike, Sarcocolla, Sanguis dragonis in graine, ana two drams Sinamon, one drame, Muſke of Leuant diſſolued in Roſe water, one Carret, then incorporate them well whiles it be warme: Ye ſhall note that the body muſt firſt be well purged are yée take this Electuarye, and ye muſt alſo kéepe a dyet that the medicine may worke the better, for this helpeth all the afore-ſaide diſeaſes inwardlye as is ſaide afore: yée may vſe it implaiſter wiſe vppon woundes, and on broken bones, and vſe it inwardlye, and ſo the pacyent ſhall remaine holpe. With this I haue ſene man of great age

holpe, that were burſt belowe, and wounded from one parte to the other, and alſo broken bones and bruſes, the whiche if I ſhoulde write them, it woulde not bee credyted.
            
            
               Our imperyall Electuary for the Mother.
               THis Electuary for the Mother, is by Nature temparate whot, and by his heate prouoketh Menſtrua, &amp; comforteth the Matrixe, and all other weake partes of what cauſes ſo euer it be, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Cinamon elect, one ounce, Nutmegs, Maces, Cloues, ginger .ana, one drame, Calsie ligne, drame vj. Marmilad .12. ounces Lignum aloes, 4. drames, redde Sanders, 2. drames, Aqua vitae well rectified 3. ounces, fine Muſke two Carrets, purified hunny 2. pound, then make thereof a Lectuary according to arte, the which is moſt excellent againſt the indiſpoſition of the mother: But firſt ere ye begin to take this medicine, it were neceſſary to take a quantitie of our Pillole Aquilone, and then to take this Electuary in the morning faſting thereon, 4. or fine houres, the quantitie is from halfe an ounce to an ounce, alſo that time that ye eate this Electuary, ye ſhal eate no euil meates, as hoggs fleſh, fryed meats, or baked meats or ſuch like as might hinder the operation of the Electuary: This Electuary ye ſhal vſe at ye leaſt 40. dayes together, &amp; ſo thou ſhalt ſee merueilous effects theof, as I haue done a thouſand times in Cicilia, in Naples, and in Rome, and alſo in Venice, and al wayes it fel out in one order, and yet the regions are much different one from another, &amp; the inhabitance are cōtrary of complexion, neuertheles this medicine wrught alwayes one effect in operatiō, as wel in one place, as in another, &amp; therfore

I approue it to be a moſt bleſſed medicine and of great experience.
            
            
               Pilles againſt poyſon the which are of meruailous vertue.
               THeſe pilles are of ſuch experience againſt poyſon, as is not to be beléeued, and the order to make them is thus.
               
                  Rec. Imperatrice, Biſtorta Tormentilla, Valeryana, Dittamo bianco, Carlina, Ariſtologia rotunda, Gencyana, Agarico electo, Salgem, of ech a like quantitie, beate them in fine pouder, then take the iuyce of garlike, and of onyons as much as wil make it into a paſte, alſo put into the iuyce one drame of Safrane, then let the ſaide paſte being mixt dry in the ſhadowe, and then beate it into powder againe, &amp; mixe it with the afore-ſaide iuyce in good forme, and kéepe it in a veſſell of leade vntill thou haſt néede, and when thou wilt occupie it, take thereof 4. drames and make ther of pilles with Siropo Acetoſo, in good forme, the which thou ſhalt giue vnto him that is poyſoned and in ſhort time thou ſhalt ſée miracles of that medicine: for all the aforeſaid ſimples in manner a lone is ſufficient to deliuer one that were poyſoned, but being mixed together it worketh greater effecte.
            
            
               Vnguento magno Leonardo.
               THis Vnguento magno is ſo called by reaſon of his great vertue &amp; operation, for it worketh ſo ſtraung in ſome diſeaſes, yt it in manner reuiueth the pacient, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Otnegra ouiu. 6. ounces, Oximel ſquilliticum half an ounce, mix thē together in a earthen diſh vntill

the Otnegra ouiu. be become lyke aſhes, then it is deifitrom, then put there-on two ounces of vineger, and waſh it well, vntill it remaine pure and cléere, then take, Olibanum, halfe an ounce. Ceruſae, ounc. 1.
               
               Beat them fine, and mixe it in a ſtone morter with as much Magno licore, as will ſerue to incorporate them well, thē put ther-to the Otnegra ouiu. &amp; mixe thē very well together, that being done, put ther-to Auxungia porcina, ounc. 8. And mixe them all together, and then it is made, the which kéepe in a veſſell well glaſed, for it will kéepe a long time with-out corruption, and is apt to helpe thoſe that are lame, full of paynes, and ſores and ſwellings, paines of the eyes, the ſtone in the raynes, and ſuch lyke matters, it helpeth al manner of French Pockes, if ye annoynt them there-with vntill their gumbes be ſore, and then leaue. But ye ſhal note that ye body muſt firſt be well purged afore ye annoint them. This vnguent cooleth al coroſiue vlcers, and helpeth them in ſhorte time, it helpeth all paynes in the eyes, if ye put it there-in, &amp; taketh away all burning wth ſpéede, and to be ſhort, it helpeth thoſe diſeaſes in moſt ſhort time, ſo that it is to be woundred at.
            
            
               Oyle of Hipericon, the which is moſt miraculous for woundes and bruſes.
               THis oyle of Hipericon cōpounded by vs, is of great vertue, in diuers and ſundry accidents and ſpecially in woundes, for it helpeth them with-out any pain, although the veynes ſinewes, or bones were hurte or cut, and that in verye ſhorte time, it preſerueth the wound from corruption, and taketh away the paine, &amp; incarnateth &amp; cicatrizeth, as by experience thou maiſt playnely ſée. It diſſolueth contuſions, and is moſt meruaylous agaynſt poyſon.
               
                  It helpeth againſt any crude ſort of venemous feuer, if ye annoynt al the body ther-with, leauing no parte, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. The flowers, leaues and ſéede of Saint Iohns wort, as many as ye will and ſtampe them together, and put them in a glaſſe, with as much ſtrong white wine as will keuer it well then ſet it in the ſunne, x. dayes together, then put there-to as much pure ſallet Oyle, as the hearbes and the wine doth way, then let if ſtande in the Sunne other .x. dayes, giuing you warning that ye way your oyle before ye mixe them, that being done put there-vnto for euery pound of Oyle .2. ounces of Turpentine, and one dram of Saffrane. Of Nutmegges, Cloues, Mirrha electe, of each halfe an ounce. Frankencenſe, ounce .1. Viticella, ounc. 2. for euery pound.
               Stampe them altogether, and put them into a great glaſſe, and ſet it to boyle in Balneo Mariae, with a head and Receiuer cloſe ſhut, and to know when it is boyled inough, is that there will aſcend no more vapours into the head, and that will be within .24. houres or there-about, then take foorth the glaſſe being yet hot, and ſtrayne it, and kéepe it in a glaſſe cloſe ſhutte as a precious Iewel, ye ſhal note that this Oyle muſt alwayes be occupied very warme and in any wiſe tent no wound but wet clothes ther-in and lay it thereon, &amp; thy cure ſhall proſper well, for this I haue proued a thouſand times in diuers places.
            
            
               To make our Oleum benedictum the which healeth wounds deuinely.
               THis Oleum benedictum ſerueth chiefly for wounds in al parts of the body, and in ſpecially for wounds

the head, if there were fracture of bone, and offences of the Pannicle, and in other places where ſinewes wer hurt, or muſcles or veynes, or in any other noble place of the body, with this Oleum benedictum, &amp; with our vigitable Quintaeſſence thou mayſt helpe them eaſely and in ſhort time, with-out any daunger or detriment of the wounded perſon, as is ſaid afore, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. The whites of Egges being hard ſodde in water, ounces .12. Cléere Turpentine, ounces .14. Pure Mirrhe, ounces .3. Mixe them and put it into a Retort of glaſſe and giue it gentle fire at the firſt, and then increaſe it according to Art, vntil all the ſubſtaunce be come foorth of the Retort, the which will be both water and Oyle, the which ſeperate, and kéepe the oyle by it ſelfe in a glaſſe as a precions Iewell, for this worketh miracles in wounds of what ſort ſoeuer they be, more-ouer it cauſeth haire to grow on ye head or beard, the which were falne away, and that it doth in ſhorte time by onely annoynting the place there-with, alſo if any haue a ſtitch in his ſide, and retention of vrine, let him take a Gliſter, where-in he ſhall put a lyttle of this Oyle and he ſhall be holpe, and this effecte it doth bicauſe it dryeth mightely, that alteration made in the ſecret parts of the raynes inwardlye, where no locall medicine can be applyed.
            
            
               A magiſtrall water, the which preſerueth the ſight a long time, and mundifieth the eyes of all ſpots.
               IF thou wilt make a water that ſhal haue vertue to preſerue the ſight long, and to mundifie the

eyes from all ſpots, that are therein, it were neceſſary that therein were ſimples that are preſeruatiue, and mundificatiue, as I will ſhew thée héere-after.
               
                  Rec. The beſt and ſtrongeſt white wine that thou canſt finde, pounds .12. New bread well riſen, pounds 4. Celandine, Fenell, Cipolla ſquilla, ana ounc. 4.
               
               Cloues, halfe an ounce. Stampe them and then diſtil them altogether in a goord in Balneo Mariae, vntil yée haue receiued v. pound, the which kéepe by it ſelfe, for that is moſt excellent againſt paine in the eyes.
               Alſo if any drinke euery morning for a moneth, the quantitie of one ounce, it will helpe him of any grieuous Infirmitie. Alſo I neuer applyed this Water to any thing, but alwayes it did great pleaſure.
            
            
               To make Oyle of Vitriol compound, the which preſerueth nature in his ſtrength.
               THe order to make this compoſition is thus.
               
                  Rec. Foure pound of fine Sugar. Riopontico, lib. 1. Rhabarbaro, ounc. 1. The flowers of Mercury, one pound.
               Stampe them altogether, &amp; make there-off a paſte, that being done, take pure rectified Aqua vitae with-out fleame, foure pounde. And put them altogether in a Retort of glaſſe cloſe ſtopped, then ſette it in warme horſe dounge ſixe dayes, then take it foorth, and diſtil it in Balneo Mariae, vntill there will come forth no more ſubſtaunce, than take forth the feſſes in the Retorte, and put it in a canuas, and preſſe it foorth very harde. Than take Bugloſſe water, Fumitorie water, Scabious water, of each ſixe ounces. And with the ſayde waters waſh well the feſſes and preſſe it foorth againe as hard as ye can. Then caſt them away, and diſtill

that water by a filter, vntill it be cleare, then mixe it with the firſt that was diſtilled by Balneo, then take the beſt Oyle of Vitryoll that ye can get, and for euery pounde of the ſaide matter, put there vnto halfe a ſcruple of the ſaide Oyle of Vitryoll, and kéepe it in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut. This compoſition I haue cauſed to be vſed in the ſummer time, and yet continually doe vſe it, whereof I haue ſéene great experience, it prouoketh a good appetite vnto thoſe that haue loſt or ſpoyled it, it helpeth the Milte, It diſſolueth the paynes of the heade and téeth, with many other vertues the which I will not write at this time, it preſerueth olde men in their ſtrength and luſtines, ſo that it hath bene a thing do be woundred at, and the order to take it is thus. Ye ſhall take halfe an ounce in the morning faſting as it is, and faſt there on 4. houres at the leaſt, and that day eate but lyttle meate but let it be of good noriſhment, and who ſoeuer foloweth this order long, ſhall liue in perfect health of body, as I haue ſéene diuers and ſundry times.
            
            
               Oleum philoſophorum de termentiua &amp; cera.
               THis Oyle of Turpentine and waxe, is a moſt pretious Balme, and his vertues are infinite, bicauſe it is made of ſimples in manner vncorruptible, and is moſt miraculous for thoſe that are corrupted or ſtroken with the peſtilence, bicauſe it is moſt penetratiue, and of nature drying, and comforteth al weake partes in mans body of what infirmitie they be, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Newe yellow Wax. ℥.12. cleare Turpentine, ℥.18. Bengimine .℥.2. Fine rectified Aqua vitae, ℥.30. common Aſhes, ℥.6. mix them &amp; put them into a retort of glaſſe wel luted, and then diſtil it in a wind fornes,

vntill all the ſubſtance be come forth, &amp; in the receiuer thou ſhalt finde 3. things, the firſt is ye water, ye ſeconde oyle, the third fleame, yt which thou ſhalt ſeparate one from another, &amp; kéepe them cloſe ſtopt in a glaſſe, the which is moſt excellent in time of ye peſtilence, as well for vnctyon, as for to helpe ye ſores, for if ye put it in a ſore or botch that is broke, preſently it taketh awaye the paine, &amp; being mixed with other of our medicines as I haue ſhewed in my regiment of the peſtilence, it helpeth them with great ſpeade. If any annoynt al his body with this Oyle twiſe a moneth, it will preſerue him youthfull and in health a long time, it preſerueth alſo deade fleſh or fiſh that is put therin from corruption, alſo if any be wounded in any parte of the body, let him annoynt it with this Oyle 4. or 5. times, and it ſhalbe whole: Alſo if any cannot make water, giue him 2. drames of this Oyle to drinke, and preſently he ſhall make water, it is alſo good againſt ye ſtitch in the ſide and plureſſe, and wormes, and ye cough &amp; cattar, &amp; againſt the peſtillent feuer, &amp; ſuch like in diſpoſition, if ye drinke a little thereof, it hath a number of other vertues the which I will leaue vnto the experimentors.
            
            
               Our magno licore the which is of great vertue.
               THis is of my inuention, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. ſwéete ſallet Oyle, xx. pound, white wine, 2.li. boyle them together vntill the wine be conſumed, thē put it in a veſſell of ſtone, and put there vnto theſe thinges following.
               
                  Rec. The flowers of Roſemary, 3.li. Lignum aloes, ℥.6. Olibanum, Bedellinum, ana. ℥.x. then ſtope it verye cloſe, &amp; bury it in ye ground, 4. foote déepe, &amp; this woulde be buryed in ye beginning of Auguſt, &amp; ther remain vntill

ye moneth of March, thē take it forth of ye ground, &amp; ſet it in ye Sun, &amp; put therto theſe matters following. Sage, Roſemary, Rew, Betony, Millyfolly, Comfery rootes, Tamaro, Viticella, ana, one handful, Gallingall, Cloues, Nutmegs, Spignard, Saffarne, ana, ℥.1. Sarcocolla, Sanguis Dragonis in grain, Maſtike, ana ℥.2. aloes epatike, Raſa di pino, ana, ℥.8. yellowe Wax, Auxungia, ana, ℥.18. colophonie, 1.li. Hipercone wt the ſeade &amp; all, 2.li. Muſke 1. drame. Mixe theſe all well together, &amp; boyle thē in Ballneo vntill the herbes become drye &amp; haue no more ſubſtance, then it is boyled, then take it forth and ſtraine it, &amp; put there vnto for euery pound, 6. drames of our Balme artificiall, &amp; when ye moneth of September commeth, put thervnto 2.li. of ye fruite of the herbe ralled Balſamina, the which are red, &amp; then it is ended, ye which thou ſhalt kéepe in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut, for the older it is the better it is, &amp; is of ſuch vertue, yt it helpeth the Etici, &amp; Hidropſie, if ye giue them euerye morning 4. drams, with 1.℥. of ſirope of Roſes warme the ſpace of 40. dayes, as I haue proued: And this is ye true &amp; perfects vnction, yt helpeth the Petocchie, a diſeaſe ſo called in the Italian: If any were wounded &amp; had cut vaines, ſinowes, &amp; bones, let him ioyne ye parts cloſe together, and dreſſe it with this Oyle very hot vpon the vpper parts, &amp; in ſhort time it ſhalbe whole, with out any alteration, it helpeth alſo the white ſcal if ye annoynt it therewith: It helpeth coldneſſe in the head &amp; Cattares, if ye annoynt it within the noſtrilles at neight when yée go to bedde, if yée annoynt the ſtomacke therewith it cauſeth perfecte diſgeſtion of the meate, it prouoketh vrine where it is let thorow carnoſitie or Gonorea, or ſuch like matter, it cauſeth haire to grow, it preſerueth ye heard blacke, &amp; is good againſt worms, &amp; al theſe experimēts are true, &amp; proued of me diuers &amp; sundry times in yt aforeſaid infirmities,

and alſo in dyuers other the which I leaue vntill another time: Ye ſhal note that if ye anoynt any all ouer that is grieued with the pocks with this Oyle, it will increaſe his paine, &amp; ſo by that meanes ye may know whether he be infected or no.
            
            
               Pillole Angelica, the which euacuate the body without any impediment, and are moſt profitable.
               IT is moſt neceſſary yt all kinde of Piltes, ſhould be wel prepared &amp; artificially hādled, bicauſe they ſhall make no alteration in ye ſtomacke of thoſe yt take them, and therfore I will write a kinde of pill of our inuention, and are called Pillole Angelica, Leonardo, the which may be vſed in any kinde of infirmitie, and may be giuen to a woman with childe without daunger, for they diſſolue the bodye with-out trouble, they purge choller and fleame, and purge partibus alonge, &amp; are good againſt all paines, they drye vp vlcers in all partes of the body, it diſſolueth the Cattarrus humore and in manner all feuers, and the order to make them is thus. Rec. Coloquintida, ℥. 4. &amp; put it in 1. pound of pure rectified Aqua vitae without fleame, &amp; ther let it remaine 3. dayes, thē ſtraine it hard into a cleane veſſell, and put therein Aloes epatike, Mirra, Eleborus niger, ana. ℥.1. Beate in fine pouder, and mixe them lyke a paſte, then ſet it in the Sunne vntill it be almoſt dryed: Than put thereto Saffarne, Cinamon, yellow Sulfure, ana, 4. drames, &amp; mix them wel together, and let them drye altogether, then make it into a paſte wt white crude hunny, &amp; kéepe it in a veſſell of leade, for that is beſt, the quantitie is from one drame to two drams, for theſe are Pillole preparate, yt may be takē wt out kéeping of dyet, &amp; they do purge al humors hāging in the body, &amp; preſerueth the body from putrifaction as I haue ſéene the experience thereof dyuers times.
            
            
               
               Pillole Aquilono of our inuention.
               THeſe Pilles are aboue all other in operation, as the Eagle is aboue all other bides, and therfore I thought good to cal them Pillole Aquilone, and the order to make them is thus.
               
                  Rec. conſerue of Damaſke Roſes made with Honny, ounces .3. Lignum alos, dra. 1. Oyle of Vitryoll .12. graines. Cinamond elect, two ſcruples. Petra Philoſophalle of our inuention, halfe an ounce. Sugar candie, ounces. 2.
               
               Mixe them and make there-off a paſte with Siropo acetoſo, and kéepe them in a Glaſſe. The vertue of theſe Pilles I will not write at this time, but onelye I ſay they help againſt all ſorts of infirmities, &amp; hurteth none in any wiſe, the quantitie is from one dram to two drams in the morning faſting, but ye may not guild them in anye wiſe, but drincke after-them a cup of water or wine, to cary them downe, then ſléepe there-on, and that day eate lyttle meate, and lyght of diſgeſtion.
            
            
               Our Quintaeſſencia ſolutiua, the which is of meruaylous operation in diuers matters.
               THis Quintaeſſentia ſolutiua euacuateth the body wt great eaſe &amp; without any detriment, &amp; it purgeth al partes of the body, that are troubled with groſe &amp; viſcous humours, it reſolueth ſwellongs &amp; taketh awaye the paines, it preſerueth the ſight, and killeth wormes, and cauſeth a good appatite, with many other good qualyties, the which I will leaue at this time, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Lignum aloes, Cinamon, Turbite, Aloes hepatica,

ana ounc. 1. Colloquintida, ounc. 2. Cloues, Saffran, of each thrée lcruples. Muſke of Leuant one dram. Iulep of Vyolets, one pound.
               Mixe al the afore-ſaid matters together in a glaſſe, and put there-on two pound of our Quintaeſſence, &amp; ſo let it ſtande .12. dayes and then ſtrayne it, and put it into a veſſell of glaſſe cloſe ſhut, this may be taken with broth, wine, or with what ſirop or potion ye wil, the quantitie is from two drams to foure drams in the morning faſting with-out kéeping of any dyet at all, and it ſhall worke well with-out trouble at all.
            
            
               Our Sirope of Quintaeſſence, the which is of merualous vertue.
               THis ſirop is of meruaylous vertue as is ſéene daylye by experience, and the order to make it, is thus.
               
                  Rec. Of that pure rectified Aqua vitae where-off we make our Quintaeſſence, ounces .12. Oyle of Sulphur, Oyle of Vitriol, of each one dram. Oyle of Tartare perfect ounces .2. Iulep of Roſes, pounds .4.
               
               Muſke, carretes .2. Saffran one ſcruple, Cinamon, one dram.
               Mixe them together, and kéepe them in a glaſſe, for his vertues are innumerable and in manner reuiueth thoſe that are halfe dead. It helpeth the feuer in ſhort time, if ye vſe it. This ſirop may be mixed with any kinde of potion that is giuen to the ſicke, and may be giuen alone in broth, wine, or water, or in what ſort ye will, the quantitie is from two drams to foure drams, and héere-with I haue done miracles, as thou mayſt read in my Theſauro dela vita humana.
               
            
            
               
               Pillole magiſtrale, the which is good againſt diuers infirmities.
               THeſe Pils are of great vertue, and ſpecially againſt al kind of paines comming of corrupt humours, for they purge the putrified humours, and preſerue the body from corruption, and the order to make them, is thus.
               
                  Rec. Olibanum, Maſticke, Mirrha. Sarcocolla, Aloes hepatica, Elleborus niger, Saffran, Turbit, Colloquintida, ana q.v.
               
               Stampe them finely, and for euerye ounce of the afore-ſaid matters, put ther-vnto .2. carretes of muſke, and than incorporate it with honny of Roſes, and Aqua vitae of each alyke, and this paſte thou maiſt kéepe for .6. moneths, in a veſſel of lead, the quantitie is from 2. drams to .3. drams, in the morning faſting, &amp; drinke there-on a little wine. Theſe Pilles are moſt excellent to take away the paynes of the Gout, and to preſerue a man from it, they are alſo good for thoſe that haue the French Pockes, bicauſe they euacuate the groſe and viſcous humors, &amp; mainteine the bodye in good temperature, &amp; vſing them in thoſe diſeaſes, it preſerueth the body in good temperature. They are alſo good for women that are troubled with paines of the Mother, and retention of their termes, for theſe are aperatiue &amp; prouoke them, and purgeth the matrice of al impediments contained ther-in, they ſerue againſt the Megram &amp; al paynes of ye head, &amp; alſo againſt al kinde of putrified feuers, as I haue ſéene ye experiēce theroff ſundry times.
            
            
               A compound Aqua vitae the which ſerueth againſt all colde diſeaſes of the ſtomacke.
               THis Aqua vitae, aromatiſed with ſimples of Leuant, is of moſte excelletn vertue, and by the

ingredience thou maiſt perceiue, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Rutmegs, Cloues, Gallingal, Cardamonum, Cubebes, Maces Cinamon, Ginger, Saffran, Ohbanū, ana. ounc. 1. Beat then finely and put them in a goord of glaſſe, and put there-on ſire pound of pure rectified Aqua, vitae, and ſo let it ſtande ſixe dayes, then diſtill it by ſande, and there will come foorth a red water, the which is moſt precious againſt all infirmities cauſed of colde, it mundiſteth all ſorts of ſores, and helpeth al woundes with-out payne. It cauſeth a good memory, it helpeth the cough, and maketh the hart merye, with diuers other vertues, yt which I leaue to ye experimenter.
            
            
               A compounds Oyle againſt poyſon, the which is of a meruaylous vertue.
               IF thou wilt helpe thoſe that are poyſoned, it wer neceſſary to haue remedies of ſuch vertue, that are apt to the ſolution of the poyſon, for the poyſon worketh thoſe thrée effects, as is ſayde afore, in the Chapter of the effectes of poyſon, where-in it is written, how that it is neceſſary to kéepe the bloud lyquid, ſo that it congeale not in the veynes, and lyke-wiſe to let or ſtay that water which commeth to the ſtomack, and to let that alteration or inflamation, as wée may terme it. And all theſe operations, are neceſſary to be done with moſt excellent Remedies, in the which ther entereth part of poyſon, for the Prouerbe ſayth, that one poyſon killeth an other, and that I will approue in this Chapter, and the order to make this compoſition is thus.
               
                  Rec. The oldeſt Oyle that thou canſt finde, pound one. Aloes hepatica, 
                        •
                     liabarbaro, Spico nardo, Mirrha, Tormentillae, Dictanum album, Gentiana, Biſtorta.

Conſolida magore, Rubia di tintory, ana, ℥. halfe. Theriaca, Methridato, ana, thrée drams, quicke Scorpions to the number of 60. Firſt put the quicke Scorpions into the Oyle, &amp; let it boyle in Balneo, Marie 4. houres than put thervnto the other matters, &amp; let them boyle altogether other foure houres, then ſtrayne it &amp; kéepe it in a veſſel of glaſſe cloſe ſhut, for truely this is a deuine Oyle for that accident, in the which ye ſée entereth Scorpions, the which are venomous, and yet hys poyſon is wholeſome for thoſe that are poyſoned.
               The like ye may ſée by thoſe that are burnte with fire, for ye beſt medicine that they can finde is to burne that place againe: Alſo yée may ſée that when greate quantitie of bloude commeth forth of a wounde, the Chirurgian preſentlye letteth him bloude in another place to turne ye ſame. Séeing thē yt theſe are true, it is alſo true, yt one poyſon doth kil another poyſon. And by this reaſon I approue, yt if yée exſtinguſh the poyſon it were neceſſary to be done with his kinde, neuer-theleſſe it muſt be prepared ſo that the matter be not altered, and become hurtful vnto the poyſoned perſon, &amp; the order to vſe this Oyle againſt poyſon is thus.
               When that a man is poyſoned preſently annoynt all his body with this Oyle, and giue him thereof to drinke two drames with white wine Vinigar, morning and euening, and God willing thou ſhalt helpe any poyſon be it neuer ſo ſtronge: It he bée poyſoned with Subblimate, or a Diamond, this remedy will not be good bicauſe they are not poyſons, but are deadlye mineralled, the which by no meanes can be diſgeſted or their euill effect mitigated. Therefore when one is poyſoned with Subblimate, his remedy is no otherwiſe, but to make him bathes of Viniger, and let him drinke milke ynough, and eate butter, and drink Siero.
               
               For this is the true remedy, as for an example whē
                  
that a ſore is mortified with a rottorye made of Subblimate, or Arſenicke, preſently it cauſeth great altealteration, for the which there is no excellenter remedies than Vineger, Butter, and Milke: Than ſéeing yt theſe remedyes are ſo profitable to be vſed outwardly there is no doubt but that they will doe the ſame effect inwardly: Alſo it woulde be neceſſarye to cauſe them to vomit euery day once at the leaſt, to kéepe the ſtomacke euacuated of that matter, ſo that it come not to choke the infected perſon, or infect the ſinowes, ſo that the partie remain not lame, for a long time after as is dayly ſéene in diuers places.
            
            
               A meruailous Sope that helpeth thoſe which cannot ſpyt but with great paine.
               THis compoſition is called Saponea noſtra, bicauſe it is made of Sope, but not of that Sope the whiche is in the Apothicaries ſhopes in Venice, but this is a confection, the which being eat euery morning a little quantitie, it helpeth thoſe that ſpit with paine, it openeth the ſtomacke, and breaketh that euil matter conteyned therein, and caſteth it forth at the mouth with the ſpyttle, and ſo leaueth the pacient wel diſpoſed and merry, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. White Venice Sope, and beate it in powder, ℥.1. pure Maiſticke 2. drams, Sinamon, Licores, ana, one drame, fine Sugar as much as wil ſuffiſe to make it in tables according to art, yt which are moſt ſtrange, neuertheleſſe meruaile not there at for I will ſhewe the reaſon, ſo that euery one ſhalbe ſatiſfied.
               Yée ſhal vnderſtande that the firſt ingredience being the Sope, is made with the Lye of Soda and Calkes, the which thinges doe drye and mundifie al ſorts of Vlcere Sordide, and cooleth them: Alſo there in is

Oyle Olyfe, the which is one of the moſt excellenteſt licours in the worlde, for this of it ſelfe is able to cut that matter from the ſtomacke, and to mundifie it, than in this compounde there is Maſticke, the whiche is moſt excellent for the ſtomacke, and draweth downe from the head, than the lycoures, and Sinamon are aparatiue &amp; comforteth the ſtomacke, ſo that all theſe being mixed together, of force it muſt helpe againſt theſe infirmities of the breaſt, and the quantitie therof is from .2. drams to halfe ounce.
            
            
               To make the Quintaeſſence of Hunny.
               THis Quintaeſſence hath all the vertues of the Quintaeſſence of wine, and is made in this order, &amp; is rather to be counted a diuine remedy than humaine.
               
                  Rec. The pureſt Hunny that ye can gette, the which is not mixt with any thing 2. pound, and put it into a gowrd of glaſſe, with his head and receuer cloſe luted, and giue it firſt a gentle fire vntill there appeare certeine white feumes in the heade, the which will turne into a red water, by laying of clothes wet in cold water, vppon the head and receiuer, than kéepe in thy fire according vnto art vntil al the ſubſtance be come forth the which thou ſhalt keepe in a glaſſe cloſe ſhutte, and in ſhort time it wil turne into the cooler of a Rubyne, than diſtill it vii. times in Balneo marye, and it will léeſe his red couler, and be of a very pleſant ſmell, and remaine in the cooler of golde, and this Quintaeſſence diſſolueth golde &amp; maketh it potable, and alſo all manner of Iewels that is put therein, alſo if yée giue two or 3. drams to any that lye a dying, preſently it will recouer him againe, as the Quintaeſſence of Wyne doth: If yée waſh any wound or ſore therwith it will

heale it quickly: It is good againſt the cough, cattar, and paynes of the Mylt, and many other ſortes of diſeaſes the which I wil not write at this time, for few or none will beléeue his great aparation or vertue. If ye diſtill it 20. times with fine Siluer, it will reſtore the ſight vnto thoſe that are almoſt blinde. Moreouer I haue giuen this 46. dayes vnto one that had the Palſie and he was holpe quickly.
               It helpeth alſo the falling ſickneſſe, and preſerueth the body from putrifaction, ſo that by theſe meanes we may ſée that it is a celeſtial remedy giuen vnto vs by the almyghtie God, and therefore I woulde wyſh ſome vertuous men to take a little paynes in making of this precious liquore, and they ſhall ſée ſuch wonders thereof that the worlde will meruaile there at, as I haue proued many times, to my great honour and profite of the pacient. For many times I haue giuen it the ſicke that no man dyd ſée me, and preſently they thought I had wrought by inchantment by reaſon of his great vertue, and therefore all men that profeſſe Phiſicke and Chirurgery, ought to be prouided of this licour and ſuch like for their commoditie, and profite of the patient.
            
            
               To make our Elixer vitae, or Aqua Caeliſtis.
               THis Elixer vitae is a medicine of ſuch vertue and ſtrength yt it helpeth in manner againſt all diſeaſes that commeth to mans body, for thoſe that are hot it coleth, and thoſe that are cold it warmeth, and that it doth by his proper qualitie and vertue, for this I haue proued a thouſand times, and haue vſed it againſt ſundry diſeaſes, and alwayes haue had good ſucceſſe, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  
                  Rec. Ginger, Zedoaria, Gallingal, Long Pepper, round Pepper, Iunipyr berries, Citron péeles, Orāge péeles, Sage, Baſill, Roſe-mary, Minte, Margerome, Bay berries, Penyrial, Gentian, Callamint, the flowers of Elders, red Roſes and white, Spica nardi, Cubebe, Lignum aloes, Cardamomū, Cinamon, Calamus aromaticus, Germāder, Sticados, Camepitcos, Meligette, Mace, Olibanum, Aloes hepatica, the ſéede of Mugwort of each two drams, Figs, Rayſons, Dates, Almonds, Graynes of the Pine, of each .6. ounces. Pure white Honny, pound .1. Muſke of Leuant, one dram. Fine ſugar, pound .4.
               
               Mixe them altogether, and infuſe them in fiue pound of pure Aqua vitae with-out fleame, and ſo let it ſtand .8. dayes, than diſtil it in Balneo Mariae, vntil the feſſes remaine dry, then take that, and ſercolate it in a Pellicane, in horſe dounge .40. dayes, thē take the glaſſe with the feſſes, and diſtill it in ſande, vntill all the ſubſtaunce become foorth, the which will bée red lyke bloud, and ſtinketh of the fire, and is thicke, the which muſt bée ſercolated as the firſt, and this is the firie part, the which is of meruaylous vertue, inſomuch that it reuiueth thoſe that are at the poynt of death, &amp; therefore I will write of ſome of his vertues, yt which I haue proued.
               The firſt water diſtilled by Balneo, béeing taken euery third day one dram, preſerueth the body in proſperous ſtate, and defendeth from many ſorts of diſeaſes. It helpeth all ſorts of wounds, if ye waſh them therewith .3. or .4. times, and is moſt excellent againſt all impediments in the eyes, if ye put there-in one droppe and preſerueth the ſight a long time, ſo that ye ſhal not néede to weare ſpectacles. If a young woman doeth waſh hir face there-with oftentimes, it preſerueth hir a long time in that ſtate. If ye vſe to drinke this Elixer
                  
it prouoketh Venerous ades, and diſpoſeth women to be delyued with diuers other vertues, yt which I leaue to the experimenter.
               The laſt water the which is red, is excellent good againſt the paines of the mother if it be dronke. It diſſolueth alſo the Pluriſſie, if ye giue ther-off two drams and annoynt the parts grieued there-with. It helpeth the paynes of the Collyke, and hardneſſe of the Milte.
               It is alſo good againſt paynes in the téethe and ſtinking breath, and many ſuch lyke things. It helpeth all manner of Feuers, and the reaſon is, bicauſe it dryeth vp all the euil humours that offendeth Nature as well with-in as with-out, ſo by this reaſon it is apt to helpe all ſort of diſeaſes. If any were ſicke &amp; could not ſpeake, let him take one dram of this, with one dram of the firſt, and preſently he ſhall ſpeake moſt miraculous to ſée, for this I haue proued a thouſād times to my great honour and content of the Patient, and therefore I would wiſh all thoſe that profeſſe Phiſicke or Chyrurgery to be prepared of this liquor, and ſuch lyke, for their owne profite, and health of their neighbour.
            
            
               To make Aqua Reale vel Imperiale, the which maketh the teeth white preſentlye, incarnateth the goumbes, and cauſeth a good breath.
               THe téeth being blacke ruſtie and ful of filth, and the goumes putrified or corrupte, are the w
                     〈…〉
                   things that may be ſéene in man or woman, and ar
                     〈…〉
                   very vnwholeſome, and the remedie to make the téeth white and to helpe the goumes, is thus. Make this water, and vſe it in the order as I will ſhew thée.
               
                  Rec. Sal gemma, Roch allom, Brumſtone, of each .2.
                  
pound. Borax, ounces. 10. Pearle beat fine, Corall, ana ounces. 2. Pure diſtiſtilled Vineger, ounces. 4. Put al the afore-ſayd matters in a goord with his head and receiuer and giue it fire according to Art, &amp; and at the laſt there will come foorth a white water lyke Milke the which after it hath ſtoode a while, wil waxe cléere. Ye ſhal vnderſtād yt this water is aboue al other waters in ye world to helpe vlcers in ye mouth, &amp; to incarnate ye goumes, &amp; to make ye téeth white, &amp; cauſeth a good breath in thoſe which are troubled with the afore-ſaid matters. For of this water I haue made great quantitie: &amp; hath ben caryed into Spayne, into Almany, into Poland, into Conſtantinople, &amp; in diuers other countryes, as though it had bene a diuine thing, and not materiall.
               For truely his experience doth cauſe the worlde to wonder at it, the vſe héere-off I haue written in this booke, and héere-after I will write it agayne in ſome of my-bookes wher occaſiō ſhall ſerue to vſe it in cures.
            
            
               A kinde of Pille moſt conuenient for the eyes and comforteth the ſtomacke.
               THoſe Pilles which comfort the ſtomacke, by force muſt helpe the ſight, for when the ſtomacke is filled with maligne humours, it diſtempereth thoſe partes that are about it, and the fumes that aſcende vp to the head, moyſteneth Nerui optici of the eyes, and by this cauſe the eyes are offended, therefore it were neceſſary for thoſe Pilles that helpe the eyes alſo to comfort the ſtomack, the which muſt be done by, euacuating the matter hanging by vomit, and the order to make theſe Pilles, is thus.
               
                  Rec. Marchpane made with ſugar &amp; almonds, dram .1. Petra Philoſophalle grain. 10. Elleborus niger. grain. 6.

Diagridij .3. graynes, Mixe them well in a morter in forme of a paſte, and make there-off .5. Pilles, and thoſe thou ſhalt take in the morning faſting, for they are of ſo much force and ſtrength that they helpe not onely the eyes and ſtomacke, but in manner all diſeaſes, bicauſe they cleanſe the ſtomacke, and euacuate the bodye, the which two things are moſt neceſſary in all diſeaſes.
            
            
               A diſcourſe vpon a compoſition that preſerueth a man or woman in health a long time.
               IF thou wilt make a paſſe that ſhall haue vertue to preſerue whole bodyes, and to helpe the ſicke, it were neceſſary to looke out ſimples that haue vertue to doe it, and when thou haſt found out thoſe drugs that haue vertue to preſeue, thou maiſt put thy truſt in them: the which I diſcourſing by the way of reaſon, and conferring it by experience, haue found out a nūber of drugs that are friends vnto our nature, and preſerueth it, of the which I will ſhew thée ſome that are of great importaunce, the which may be approued of reſon and experience, and are theſe.
               
                  Rec. Aloes hepatica, Olibanum, Mirrha, ana ounc. 2. Beat them in fine powder, and make them into a paſte lyke a ſalue with rectified Aqua vitae, then drye it in the Sunne, then beat it into powder agayne, and make it into a paſt with our Oleo del balſamo, &amp; than thou ſhalt haue a paſt of moſt meruaylous vertue, for if ye take ther-off euery morning one dram, it wil preſerue him long in health, it is moſt excellent for thoſe that be wounded or haue any ſore vppon them, bicauſe it kéepeth the ſore from putrifaction as by the ingredience thou maiſt perceiue.
            
            
               
               A meruailous Water to be vſed of all Chirurgians in cureing of their pacientes.
               IT is neceſſary for the Chirurgion in the cure of woundes and ſores, to helpe the body, aſwell inwardly as outwardly, to take away the euill quallities and corruption of the humours, and to preſerue it from putrifaction, and then the ſore will heale with little helpe, and in ſhort time, and that thou maiſt do with this Water, the which is vncorriptible and of great experience, and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Of that Aqua vitae where-of we make our Quintaeſſence, pound x. and put there-in theſe things following. Sinamond, Lignum alloes, red Sanders, Cardus benedictus, ana 3. ounces, Cloues, long Pepper, Callomus aromaticus, Saffrane, ana 2. ounces, Almondes, Graines of the Pine, Dates, ana 4. ounces. Melegette ounce 1. fine Sugar, pound 4. Muſke 4. carrets: let all theſe ſtand in a long necked glaſſe, cloſe ſtopped, 8. or 9. dayes, and then diſtill it in Balneo vntill ye haue receiued 5. poundes, the which keepe cloſe ſtopped in a glaſſe, as a precious Iewell: than diſtill the reſt in ſand, vntill the feſſes be drye, and that will be a red Water, and will ſtinke ſome-what of the fire or ſmoke, the which alſo kéepe in a glaſſe: for in time it will léeſe his ſtinking ſmell, and be moſt precious. The firſt Water is of ſuch vertue, that it helpeth al putrified vlcers, if yóe dreſſe them therwith. The ſecond is alſo perfect, that if any man drinke euery morning 2. drames, it will ſo preſerue him, that it were vnpoſſible he ſhould haue any infirmitie. For of this Water I haue made great experience in many kinde of diſeaſes, and ſpecially in the plurifie and petechie. &amp;c.
            
            
               
               To make our Cauſticke.
               ALthough I haue written this Cauſticke in my Regimēt of ye peſtilēce, called now in engliſh, A Ioyful Iewell. Imprinted by William Wright, dwelling vnder ſaint Mildredes Church. Neuertheleſſe, I thought good to write it in this place, bicauſe euerye one hath not both theſe bookes: and the order to make it is thus.
               
                  Rec. Arſnike criſtalline, Sal armoniack, Sublimate, ana, boile them being finely ground in as much ſtrong vinegar as the matter wayeth, vntill two thirde partes be conſumed, and that there remayne a thirde: then kéepe it in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut vnto thy vſe. As I will ſhowe thée in diuers places when occaſion ſhal ſerue.
            
            
               To make oyle of Antimony.
               
                  Rec. Antimoni and calcine it vntill it will ſmoke no more, and that it be of a grayiſh colour, and alwayes as it cluttereth, ſtampe it agayne: then take as much common aſſhes as the Antimoni, finely ſearced, and put them in-to a Retorte well luted, and giue it fire according vnto arte, till all the fumes or ſpirites be come forth: giuing you charge that your Receiuer be very great, leaſt all breake. This Oyle is of merueilous vertue againſt Vlcers: if yée giue ther-of 4. graynes with any ſirop, it helpeth the feuer preſently. It helpeth Phiſtolowes: and to be ſhort, it is moſte wholſome in diuers thinges. But it were neceſſarie for the Chirurgion to be expert in the vſe thereof, and to mixe it according to his work. And therfore he that cannot vſe it wel, it were better to let it alone: bicauſe it is a perilous thing vnto the vnſkilfull, and precious

vnto thoſe that knowe how to vſe it.
            
            
               A precious Licoure aboue all other.
               THis is the moſt precious Water that may be made in ye world, and his vertues are ſuch, and ſo manye, that they cauſe the worlde to meruaile at them. The Mirra and Aloe with Verniſh and with as much of our Quintaeſſence, being myxed, the which without fire aſſhes and coales, cannot be ſeperated, and when the Ayre, the Water, and Eearth, are ſeperated, ech of them ſhall be apte to mittigate paynes, diſſolue humoures, helpe woundes, diſſolue paines with-in the body, and ſuch like matters. This Water I haue vſed diuers tymes, and cauſed the worlde to wonder of his operations, and ſo ſhall euery one do that deſireth to follow the right way, and that will be a childe of arte. Thou ſhalt vnderſtand that I would haue written this playner, but that I write it to thoſe that haue iudgement bothe of the quantities and vertues: bicauſe pearles are not for ſwine.
            
            
               A ſecrete of meruailous vertue.
               
                  Rec. A new bricke forthe of the kill, and breake it in ſmal péeces like a Nut, then lay them in the fire vntill they be red hot: then take them forth and quench them in ſwéete ſallet Oyle, then take them forth againe, and lay them in the fire vntill they be red hot: then quench them againe, and this yée ſhall do at the leaſt fiue times, and at the laſt tyme take them forth, and put them in-to a glaſſe with Aloes, Frankenſence, and Mirrha, and diſtill it according to arte: then ſeperate ech lycoure by him ſelfe, and ther-with thou ſhalt worke wonderfull cures, if thou knoweſt howe to vſe it and where-vnto.
            
            
               
               Our ſecrete of marueilous vertue in act and ſtrength.
               THis Vnguent is of meruailous vertue, and was neuer made by any a-fore, neyther auncientes nor of our time, the which vnguent helpeth putrified Vlcers in the legges, ſo that it is to be wondred at: for it worketh diuers operations, it mortifieth the euill, mundifieth, incarnateth and cicatriſeth, the whiche thinges to the profeſſors of the arte ſéemeth hard: Neuertheleſſe, it is true, as I haue proued and infinite of tymes: and bicauſe the worlde ſhould haue it, I haue written here the receite.
               
                  Rec. Of our Magno licore, and oyle of Maſtike made at the Apothecaries, and put them into a veſſell of copper, with as much Litarge as yée ſhall thinke good, and ſo let it ſtand a good while on the fire, and put there-to of our Cerote magiſtrale, and incorporate them wel together, and ſo of yellow, it ſhall become blacke: then take it from the fire, and put ther-in Mercurie precipitate, and ſtirre them well vntill it be colde, and here-with thou ſhalt work wonders. It would be neceſſary for him that will make this receite, to conſider well of the ingrediences of the compoſitions, the which are written in this booke.
            
            
               To rectifie and preſerue the ſight of thoſe that are weake ſighted.
               IF thou wilt rectifie and preſerue the ſight in thoſe that are weake ſighted, of what cauſe ſo-euer it be: thou ſhalt make this Water, and vſe it according to this receite.
               
                  Rec. Fenell ſéede, the flowers of Roſemary Rew, Celendine, Cardus benedictus, Staueſeager, Eufrage,

Eufrage, of each a handfull, Cinomon, Nutmegges, ſwéet Almonds, of each one ounce.
               Stampe all theſe groſely, and infuſe them in .xxx. pound of pure white wine, then let it ſtande .4. dayes, and then diſtill it in Balneo, vntil-ye haue receiued .4. pound, the which kéepe cloſe by it ſelfe, and when thou wilt occupy it, put there-off one droppe into the eye, when ye goe to bed, and in the morning when ye riſe. And thus vſing it, it will preſerue the ſight a longe time.
            
            
               Of Lac Virginis, and the order to make it.
               THis Lac Virginis, is a ſolution of Satorne and Sal gemma, the which is a thing moſt neceſſary, for the Chyrurgion to vſe, and the order ot make it, is thus.
               
                  Rec. Lytarge of golde as much as ye thinke good, &amp; beat it in fine powder, then put there-on ſtrong diſtilled Vineger, and ſo let it remaine two or thrée dayes, ſtirring it euery day, then boyle it vntill halfe be conſumed, then let it repoſe two or thrée houres, and the vineger will be cléere and of the coulour of gold, then poure it foorth into a glaſſe, and kéepe it, then take Sal gemma and rayne water, ana, and diſſolue it on warm aſhes, and when it is diſſolued, kéepe it in a glaſſe, and when thou wilt make Lac Virginis, take of eache of theſe ſolutions alike, and mixe them together, and thou ſhalt ſée a ſtraunge thing. For as ſoone as they are mixed together, they will tourne to a white Vnguent like Ceruſe or white lead, the which ſerueth in diuers cauſes according to the intention of the Chyrurgian. The ſolution of Lytarge by him-ſelfe, with as much Oyle of Roſes béeing mixed together, maketh a delycate Vnguent, an refriſcatiue the which cicatrizeth vlcers with great ſpéede.
            
            
               
               To calcine Tutia, and to bring it into a ſalte.
               THou ſhalt diſſolue thy Tutia in this water following.
               
                  Rec. Sal niter, Roch allome, Vitrioll, Scinaber, ana lib. 1. Beat them together, and diſtill them according to Arte. Then take that water, and put there-in thy Tutia, and let it diſſolue vppon the warme aſhes, and when it is diſſolued, vapor away the water vntil it remaine dry, the which take foorth, &amp; put it into an earthen panne vnglaſed and calcine it with a ſtrong fire. Then diſſolue it in diſtilled vineger, and whē it is diſſolued, vapor away the vineger, &amp; the ſalt wil remain in the bottome, the which ſerueth much for Tinture, &amp; to make a Liniment for the eyes, the which is moſt precious and rare, for if ye mixe a lyttle ther-off with Hogges greaſe and Camphir, and then put it into the eye, it helpeth them with ſuch ſpéede, that it is to bée wondred at, and not with-out cauſe. For his Nature is to giue light and to heale things imperfect. The Tutia mixt with Borax and with our Verniſh that wée guylde leather with, and giuen in proiection vpon Venus molte, it cauſeth it to be in colour not much differing from Sol, of the wich thou mayſt make ſtraunge things, for he that knew the vertue and qualitie of Tutia, aswell in Alchimi, as in infirmities, were to bée counted a wiſe man.
            
            
               To precipitate Mares, and to bring it in to a red powder, called Crocus martis, the which ſerueth for diuers purpoſes.
               
                  REc. Sal niter refined, Roch Allom, Vitriol Romain, ana, and there-off make a water according to Art,

with all his ſpirites, and in that water diſſolue thinne plates of Iron or ſtéele, and when it is diſſolued, vapor away the water, vntill it remaine drye in a red powder, then take it foorth, and calciue it in a Furnaice of reuerberation .24. houres. Then kéepe it to thy vſe, vntill thou knoweſt more there-off, for it is wounderfull in his operation, as I will ſhew thée héere after.
            
            
               A ſecret of Turpentine of Ciprus.
               THe Turpentine of Ciprus is a kinde more finer then our Turpentine, and with-out compariſon, &amp; of more vertue then ours is, and this the Doctors ſay, doth diſſolue paynes and preſerueth the body, if it bée taken inwardly: bicauſe they ſaye, that Turpentine is an vncorruptible Gumme, the which is moſt true. But in that Gumme there is one part thicke &amp; groſe that hindereth his operation, and he that can ſeperate this groſe parte from the noble partes, ſhall doe great wonders there-with: It is néedefull then with the fire and the meanes of our Quintaeſſence, to make the ſeperation of the Elements, the which are .4. Water, Oyle, Lyquor, and Earth. The Water is profitable, the Oyle is perfect, the Lyquor is noble, and the Earth that remaineth is ſpoyled &amp; of no ſubſtaunce, &amp; with thoſe things thou mayſt do high and great cures, whē they are applyed according as they ought to be, bicauſe many good and profitable things thorow the want of perfect applycation in time and place many times do hurt, and to ſhew the troth I will ſhew thée an example of wine the which is a precious lyquor, the which being dronke in the morning is hurtefull to many, to eate meate betwixte meales is not good, and manye ſuch lyke things, yt when they be not done with order

doe hurt, and therefore it is neceſſary for thoſe that wil vnderſtand that matter to be of a good intellygence, as well in making it, as in vſing or applying it to the ſicke.
            
         
      
      
         
            
               IF any be diſpoſed to haue any of theſe afore-ſayd compoſitions redy made, for the moſt part he may haue them at Paules Wharfe, by one Iohn Heſter practiſioner in the Arte of diſtilliations, at the ſigne of the Furnaiſes.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
               
                  blazon or coat of arms
                  MIEVL X. VAVLT. MOVRIR-EN. VERTV. QVE. VIVRE. EN. HONCTE.
               
            
            ¶Jmprinted at London by Thomas Eaſt. 1580.
            
         
      
   

