
   
      
         
            A spirituall consolation, written by Iohn Fyssher Bishoppe of Rochester, to hys sister Elizabeth, at suche tyme as hee was prisoner in the Tower of London. Uery necessary, and commodious for all those that mynde to leade a vertuous lyfe: also to admonishe them, to be at all tymes prepared to dye, and seemeth to bee spoken in the person of one that was sodainly preue[n]ted by death
            Fisher, John, Saint, 1469-1535.
         
         
            
               1578
            
         
         Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00776
            STC 10899
            ESTC S109711
            99845357
            99845357
            10251
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00776)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10251)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 40:11)
         
         
            
               
                  A spirituall consolation, written by Iohn Fyssher Bishoppe of Rochester, to hys sister Elizabeth, at suche tyme as hee was prisoner in the Tower of London. Uery necessary, and commodious for all those that mynde to leade a vertuous lyfe: also to admonishe them, to be at all tymes prepared to dye, and seemeth to bee spoken in the person of one that was sodainly preue[n]ted by death
                  Fisher, John, Saint, 1469-1535.
               
               [138] p.   
               
                  [W. Carter,
                  [London :
                  1578?]]
               
               
                  Imprint conjectured by STC.
                  Includes, with caption title: A sermon verie fruitfull, godly, and learned, vpon thys se[n]te[n]ce of the prophet Ezeckiell, .. .
                  Signatures: A-H I⁶ (I6 blank).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Prisoners' writings, English --  Early works to 1800.
               Theology --  Early works to 1800.
               Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-05
            Melanie SandersSampled and proofread
         
            2005-05
            Melanie SandersText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ A spirituall consolation, written by Iohn Fyssher Bishoppe of Rochester, to hys sister Elizabeth, at suche tyme as hée was prisoner in the Tower of London. Uery necessary, and commodious for all those that mynde to leade a vertuous lyfe: Also to admonishe them, to be at all tymes prepared to dye, and séemeth to bée spoken in the person of one that was sodainly preuē
               ted by death.
            
               2. Corinthians. vj.
               Beholde now is the acceptable tyme▪ now is the day of saluation.
               Mathew. xxiiij.
               VVatch therefore, for ye knowe not what houre your Lorde doeth come.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ¶ A spirituall consolacyon vvritten by Iohn Fyssher Bishop of Rochester, to his sister Elizabeth.
            
               SIster Elizabeth, nothing doth more help effectuallye to get a good and a vertuous lyfe. Then if a soule when it is dull and vnlustie without deuotion, neyther disposed to prayer, nor to any other good worke, may be sturred or quickened agayne by fruiteful meditacion. I haue therfore deuised vnto you this meditation that followeth. Praying you for my sake and for the weale of your owne soule, to reade it at suche tymes as you shall feele your selfe most heauie and slouthfull to doe any good worke. It is a maner of lamentacion and sorowfull complaynyng made in the person of one that was hastily preuented by death, (as I assure you euery creature may be) none other suretie we haue, liuing in this

worlde héere. But if you will haue any profite by reading of it, thrée things you must do in any wise. First when you shall reade this meditation, deuise in your mynde as nigh as you can, all the conditions of a man or woman sodaynlye taken and rauyshed by death: and thynke
                  •
                wyth your selfe that yée were in the same condition so hastily taken, and that incontinent you must néedes dye, and your soule depart hence, &amp; leaue your mortall bodie, neuer to returne again for to make any amendes, or to doe any release to your soule after this houre.
            Seconly, that yée neuer reade thys meditation but alone by your selfe in secrete maner, where you maye be most attentyue therevnto. And when ye haue the best leasure without any let of other thoughtes or buzinesse. For if you otherwyse behaue your selfe in the reading of it, it shall anon lose the vertue and quicknesse in stirring and mouing of your soule when you woulde ratherest haue it sturred.
            
               Thirdly, that when you intende to read it, you must afore lifte vp your minde to almightie God, and beséech him that by the helpe and succour of his grace the readyng thereof may fruitfully worke in your soule a good and vertuous life, according to hys pleasure and say, Deus in adiutorium meum intende, Domine adiuvandum me festina. Gloria patri. &amp;c. Laus tibi domine rex eternae glorie. Amen.
            
            Alas, alas, I am vnworthily takē, all sodaynly death hath assayled me, the paynes of his stroake be so sore and gréeuous that I may not longe endure thē, my last home I perceiue well is come. I must now leaue thys mortall bodie, I must nowe departe hence out of this world neuer to returne againe into it. But whether I shall goe, or where I shall become, or what lodgyng I shall haue thys night, or in what company I shal fal, or in what countrey I shall be receiued, or in what maner I shall be entreated, God knoweth for I knowe not. What if I shall be dampned in the perpetuall prysō of hell, where be

paynes endelesse and without number. Gréeuous it shall be to them that be dampned for euer, for they shall be as men in moste extreame paynes of death, euer wishing and desiryng death, and yet neuer shall they dye. It should be nowe vnto mée muche wearie, one yeare continually to lye vpon a bed were it neuer so soft, how weary then shall it be to lye in the most painefull fyre so many thousād of yeares without number? And to be in that most horrible company of diuils most terrible to beholde, full of malice and crueltie. O wretched and miserable creature yt I am, I might so haue liued and so ordered my lyfe by the helpe and grace of my Lorde Christ Iesu, yt this houre might haue bene vnto mée much ioyous &amp; greatly desired. Many blessed &amp; holy Sayncts were full ioyous and desirous of this houre, for they knewe well that by death their soules shuld be trāslated into a new life: To the life of all ioye and endlesse pleasure, frō ye streightes and bōdage of this corruptible body, into a very libertie and true fréedom

mong the company of heauen, frō the miseries &amp; gréeuāces of this wretched world, to be aboue with God in comfort inestimable yt can not be spoken ne thought. They were assured of ye promises of almightie god which had so promised to all them that bée hys faithfull seruauntes. And sure I am that if I had truly &amp; faithfully serued him vnto thys houre, my soule had bene partner of these promises. But vnhappie &amp; vngracious creature that I am, I haue bene negligent in hys seruice, and therefore now my harte doeth waste in sorowes séeing ye nighnesse of death, and considering my great slouth &amp; negligence. I thought full little thus sodainly to haue bene trapped: But (alas) now death hath preuented me, and hath vnwarily attached mée, &amp; sodainly oppressed mée with his mightie power, so that I know not whither I may turne mee for succour, nor where I may séeke now for helpe, ne what thing I may doe to get any remedy: If I myght haue leasure and space to repent mée and amende my lyfe, not compelled

with this sodayne stroake but of my owne frée will and libertie, and partly for the loue of God, putting asyde all slouth &amp; negligence. I might then safely dye wtout any dread, I might then be glad to departe hence and leaue my manifold miseries &amp; encombraūces of this world. But how may I think that my repentance or mine amendement commeth now of myne own frée will, sith I was before thys stroake so colde and dull in the seruice of my Lord God. Or howe may I thinke that I doe this more rather for his loue, then for feare of his punyshement, when if I had truelye loued hym, I should more quickely and more diligently haue serued him héeretofore? Mée séemeth now that I caste away my slouth and neglygence compelled by force. Euen as a Merchaunt that is compelled by a greate tempest in the sea to cast his merchandice out of the Shippe, it is not to bée supposed that hée would cast away his ryches of hys owne frée will, not compelled by the storme? And euen so lykewyse doe I if thys tempeste of death were

not now raysed vppon mée, it is full like that I would not haue cast from me my slouth and negligence. O woulde to God that I might nowe haue some farther respet, and some longer tyme to amend my self of my frée will and libertie. O if I might entreat death to spare me for a season, but that will not bée, death in no wise will be entreated, delay he will none take, respet he will none giue, if I would giue him all the ryches of this worlde, no if all my louers and friends would fall vppon their knées and pray him for mée. No if I &amp; they would wéepe (if it wer so possible) as many teares as there be in the seas droppes of water, no pietie may restraine him. (Alas) when oportunitie of tyme was, I would not vse it well, which if I had done, it would nowe bée vnto mée more precyous then all the treasures of a Realme. For then my soule as nowe should haue béene cloathed wyth good workes innumerable, the which shuld make mée not to be ashamed when I should come to the presence of my

Lorde God, where now I shall appeare loaden with sinne myserably, to my confusion &amp; shame. But (alas) to negligently haue I letted passe frō me my tyme not regardyng howe precious it was, ne yet howe muche spirituall riches I might haue gottē therein, if I would haue put my diligence and studie thervnto. For assuredly no déede that is be it neuer so little, but it shall be rewarded of almightie God. One draught of water giuen for the loue of God, shal not be vnrewarded: And what is more easie to be giuen thē water. But not onely déedes, but also the least wordes and thoughtes shall be in likewise. O how many good thoughtes, déeds, and workes might one thinke, speak, and doe, in one day? But how many more in one whole yere. O (alas) my great negligence, O (alas) my foule blindnesse, O (alas) my sinfull madnesse that knew this well, and would not put it in effectuall executiō. O if now all ye people of this world were present héere to sée &amp; know the perillous condition that I am in, &amp; howe I am

preuented by the stroake of death, I would exhort to take me as an example to them all, &amp; while they haue leasure and time to order their liues and caste from them slouth and idlenesse, &amp; to repent them of their misbehauior towardes God, and to bewayle their offences, to multiplye good workes, and to let no tyme passe by them vnfruitfully. For if it shall please my Lorde God that I might any longer liue, I would otherwyse exercise my self then I haue done before. Now I wishe that I may haue time and space, but rightuously I am denyed. For when I might haue had it I would not well vse it: And therfore now when I would well vse it, I shall not haue it. O ye therefore that haue and may vse this precyous tyme in your libertie, imploy it wel, and be not to wastfull thereof, least peraduenture when you would haue it, it shall be denyed you likewise, as now it is to mée. But now I repent me full sore of my great negligence, and right much I sorow that so little I regarded the wealth &amp; profit of my

soule, but rather tooke héede to the vayne comfortes and pleasures of my wretched bodie. O corruptible bodie, O stinking carion, O rotten earth to whom I haue serued, whose appetites I haue followed, whose desire I haue procured, now doest thou appeare what thou arte in thy own likenesse. That brightnesse of thy eyes, that quicknesse in hearing, that lyuelinesse in thy other sences by naturall warmenesse, thy swiftnesse and nimblenesse, thy fayrenesse and bewtie. All these thou hast not of thy self, they were but lent vnto thée for a season, euen as a wall of earth that is fayre painted without for a season with freshe and goodly colours, and also gylted with golde, it appeareth goodly for the tyme to suche as consider no déeper then the outward crafte thereof. But when at the last the colour faileth, and the gilting falleth away, then appeareth it in hys owne lykenesse. For then the earth playnely sheweth it selfe. In lykewise my wretched bodie for the time of youth it appeareth fresh and lustie,

and I was deceyued with the outwarde bewtie thereof, little considering what naughtinesse was couered vnderneath: but now it sheweth it selfe. Now my wretched bodye, thy bewtie is faded, thy fayrenesse is gonne, thy lust, thy strength, thy lyuelinesse all is gonne, all is fayled: Nowe arte thou then returned to thyne owne earthly coolour: Now arte thou blacke, colde, &amp; heauie, lyke a lumpe of earth: Thy sight is darkened, thy hearyng is dulled, thy tongue flaltereth in thy mouth, and corruption issueth out of euery parte of thée: Corruption was thy beginnyng in the wombe of thy mother, and corruption is thy continuaunce. All thyng that euer thou receyuest, were it neuer so precyous, thou turnest into corruption, and naught came from thée at any tyme but corruption, and now to corruptiō thy selfe returnest: altogyther ryght vile &amp; lothly art yu becom, wher in apparāce before yu wast goodly, but ye good lines was nothīg els but as a paintīg or a gilting vppō an earthē wal, vnder

it was couered with stinking &amp; filthy matter. But I looked not so déepe, I contented my self with the outward painting, &amp; in yt I tooke great plesure: For all my studie &amp; care was aboute thée, either to apparel thée with some cloathes of diuers colours, eyther to satisfie thy desire in pleasaūt sightes, in delectable hearinges, in goodlye smelles, in sundrie maner of tastings &amp; touchings, either els to get thée ease and rest aswel in sléepe as otherwise. And prouided therfore pleasaunt and delectable lodgings, and to eschue tediousnesse in all these, not onely lodgings but also in apparell, meates and drinkes procured many and dyuers chaunges, that when thou wast weary of one, then mightest thou cō
               tēt thy self with some other. O (alas) this was my vaine and naughtie studie whervnto my wit was ready applied, in those things I spent the most part of my dayes. And yet was I neuer content long, but murmuring or grudging euery hour for one thing or other. And what am I now ye better for all this? what reward may I loke

for of all my long seruice? Or what great benifites shall I receiue for all my great studie, care, and diligence? Nothing better am I but muche the worse, much corruption and filth my soule thereby hath gathered, so that now it is made full horrible &amp; lothely to beholde. Rewarde get I none other then punishment, either in Hell euerlasting, or at the least in Purgatorie, if I may so easily escape. The benifites of my labour are the great cares and sorowes which I now am wrapped in: May not I thinke my wit to haue ben well occupied in this lewde and vnfruitful buzinesse? haue not I wel bestowed my labour about this seruice of my wretched bodye? hath not my tyme bene well imploy
               
                  ••
                
               
                  〈…〉
                miserable studies, wherof now no comfort remayneth, but onely sorow &amp; repentance. (Alas) I heard full often that such as shuld be dampned, should gréeuouslye repent them selues, and take more displeasure of their misbehauior then euer they had pleasure before. And yet that repentance then should stande them in no

stéede, where a full little repentance takē in tyme might haue eased them of all their paines. This I heard and read full often, but full little héede or regarde I gaue thervnto, I well perceyued it in my selfe, but all to late I dread me. I woulde that nowe by the example of me all other might beware, and avoyde by the gracious helpe of God these daungers that I now am in, and prepare them selues against the houre of death better thē I haue prepared me. (Alas) what auayleth mee nowe anye delicacie of meates and drinkes which my wretched bodie insaciabl
                  •
                dyd deuoure? What auayleth my vanitie or pryde that I had in my selfe eyther of apparel or of any other thing 
                  〈…〉
                vnto me? what auayleth 
                  〈…〉
                and vncleane delightes and lustes of the stincking flesh, wherein was appearance of much pleasure, but in very déede none other then the Sowe hath, waultering hir self in ye myerie puddle. Now these pleasures be gon my body is nothing better, my soule is much the worse, and nothyng remayneth

but sorow and displeasure and yt a thousand fold more thē euer I had any pleasure before. O lewde bodie &amp; naughtie which hast brought me to this vtter discomfort, O dyrtie corruption, O sachell full of dunge, now must I goe to make answere for thy lewdenesse, thy lewdenesse I say for it all commeth of thée. My soule had nothing néede of such things as was thy desire, what néede my soule that is immortall, eyther cloathyng or meate or drink? what néede it any corruptible gold or siluer? what néed it any houses or beddes, or any other things yt appertayneth to these. For thée O corruptible body which lyke a rotten wall dayly néedeth reprati
               
                  •
               ns and botching vp with meate and drinke, and defence of cloathyng against colde and heate was all thys studie and diligence taken, and yet now wilte thou forsake mée at my most néede, when accompt and reckoning of all our misdéedes must be gyuen before the throne of the Iudge most terrible. Now thou wilt refuse me and leaue mée to the ieoperdie of

all this matter. O (alas) many yeares of deliberation suffice not before so great a Iudge to make answer which shall examyne me of euerie idle word that euer passed my mouth. O then howe many idle wordes, how many euill thoughtes, howe many déedes haue I to make answere for, &amp; such as we set but at lyght, full greatlye shall be weyed in the presence of hys most high maiestie. O (alas) what may I doe to get some helpe at thys most daungerous houre? Wher may I séeke for succour? Where may I resorte for any comforte? My body forsaketh me, my pleasures be vanyshed away as the smoke, my goods will not goe wyth mée. All these worldly things I must leaue behinde mée: if any comforte shall be, either it muste bee in the prayers of my friendes, or in myne own good déeds that I haue done before. But as for my good déedes that shoulde be auayleable in the sight of God: (alas) they bée fewe or none that I can thynke to bee auayleable, they must bee donne pryncipallye and purely

for his loue. But my déedes when of their kynde they were good, yet did I linger them by my folly. For eyther I did them for the pleasure of men, or to auoyde the shame of the world, or els for my owne affection, or els for dreade of punishment. So that seldome I dyd any good déed in that puritie and streaightnesse that it ought of ryght to haue bene done. And my misdéedes, my lewde déedes that be shamefull and abhominable be without number, not one day of all my lyfe, no not one houre I trow was so truely expended to the pleasure of God, but many déeds, words, and thoughtes, miscaped me in my lyfe. (Alas) little trust then may I haue vppon my déedes. And as for the prayers of my friendes suche as I shall leaue behynde mée, of them manye peraduenture bée in the same néede that I am in. So that where theyr owne prayers myght profytte them selues, they can not so profitte an other. And many of them will bee full neglygente, and some forgetfull of mée. And

no meruaile, for who shoulde haue béene more friendly vnto mée then myne owne selfe. Therefore I that was most bounden to haue done for my selfe, forget my owne weale in my lyfe tyme, no meruaile therefore if other doo forget me after my departing hence. Other friendes there be by whose prayers soules may be holpen, as by the blessed and holy saincts aboue in heauen, which verely will be myndfulll of such as in earth here haue deuoutly honored them before. But (alas) I had special deuotion but to a fewe, &amp; yet them I haue so faintly honored, and to them so coldly sued for fauour, that I am ashamed to aske ayde or helpe of them. At thys tyme in déede, I had more effectually ment to haue honored them, &amp; more diligently to haue commended my wretched soule vnto their prayers, and so to haue made them my special friendes: but nowe death hath preuented me so, that no other hope remayneth but onely in the mercye of my Lord God, to whose mercy I doe now offer my self, beséeching him not

to looke vppon my desertes, but vppō his infinite goodnesse and abundaunt pietie. (Alas) my dutie had bene much better to haue remembred this terrible houre, I should haue had this daū
               ger euer before my eyes, I shoulde haue prouided therefore, so that now I might haue bene in a more readynesse against the comming of death, which I knew assuredly would come at the last, albeit I knew not when, where, or by what maner, but well I knewe euery houre and moment, was to him indifferent, and in his libertie. And yet my madnesse euer to be sorowed. Notwithstanding thys vncertaintie of his comming, and the vncertaintie of the tyme thereof, I made no certayne nor sure prouision against this houre. Full often I tooke great studie and care to prouyde for litle daūgers, only bicause I thought they might hap, and yet happed they neuer a deale. And but tryfles they were in comparisō of this, how much rather should I haue taken study and care for this so great a daūger which I knew wel must necessarily fall vnto

mée once. For thys can not be eschued in no wyse, and vppon thys I ought to haue made good prouision: For in this hangeth all our wealth, for if a man dye well, he shall after his death nothing want yt he would desire, but his appetite shall be saciate in euerie poynte at the full. And if he dye amisse, no prouysion shall auayle him that euer he made before. This prouision therefore is most effectually to bée studied, sithens this alone may profit without other, and without thys none can auayle. O yée that haue tyme and space to make your prouisiō agaynst the houre of death, defarre not from day to day lyke as I haue done. For I often did thinke and purpose with my self that at some leasure I would haue prouided, neuerthelesse for euery tryfelous buzinesse I put it aside, and delayed thys prouysion alway to an other tyme, and promysed with my selfe that at suche a tyme I would not fayle but doe it, but when that came an other buzinesse arose,

and so I deferred it agayne vnto an other tyme. And so (alas) from time to tyme, that now death in the mean tyme hath preuented mée, my purpose was good, but it lacked execution: My will was strayghte, but it was not effectuall, my mynde well intended, but no fruite came therof. All for bicause I delayed so often and neuer put it in effect, that, that I had purposed. And therefore delay it not as I haue done, but before all other buzinesse put this first in suertie, which oughte to bée chiéefe and princypall buzinesse. Neyther buildyng of Colleges, nor makyng of Sermons, nor giuing of almes, neyther yet anye other manner of buzynesse shall helpe you without this.
            Therefore first and before all things prepare for thys, delaye not in any wyse, for if you doe, you shall be deceyued as I am now. I read of manye, I haue hearde of manye, I haue knowne many that were disappoynted as I am nowe. And euer I thought and sayde, &amp; intended, that

I would make sure and not be deceiued by the sodayn comming of death. Yet neuerthelesse I am now deceyued, and am taken sléeping, vnprepared, and that when I least wéened of his comming, and euen when I reckoned my selfe to be in most healthe, and when I was most buzie, and in the middest of my matters. Therfore delaye not you any farther, nor put your trust ouer much in your friends: Trust your selfe while ye haue space and libertie, and doe for your self now while you may. I would aduyse you to doe that thing that I by the grace of my Lord God would put in execution if his pleasure were to sende me longer lyfe. Recounte your selfe as dead, &amp; thinke that your soules were in pryson of Purgatorie, &amp; that there they must abyde till that the Raunsom for them be truly payde, eyther by long sufferance of payne there, or els by suffrages done héere in earth by some of your speciall friendes. Be y
                  •
               u your owne friend, doe you these suffrages for your owne soule, whether they be praiers or almes déedes,

or any other penitentiall paynefulnesse. If you will not effectually and hartely doe these thinges for your own soule, looke you neuer that other will doe them for you, and in dooyng them in your own persons, they shal be more auayleable to you a thousād folde then if they were done by any other: If you followe this counsayle and doe thereafter, you be gracious and blessed, and if you doe not, you shall doubtlesse repent your follyes, but to late.
         
         
            
            ¶The wayes to perfcet Religion made by Iohn Fyssher, Byshop of Rochester, being Prysoner in the Tower of London.
            
               SIster Elizabeth gladlye I would wryte vnto you some thing that myght be to the health of your soule and furtheraunce of it in holye Relygion. But well I knowe that without some feruor in the loue of Christ, Relygion can not bée to you sauerie, nor anye worke of goodnesse can bée delectable, but euerie vertuous déede shall séeme laboryous and paynefull. For loue maketh euerie worke appeare easie and pleasaunt, though it bée ryghte displeasaunt of if selfe. And contrariwyse ryght easie labour appeareth gréeuous and paynefull, when the soule of the person that doeth the déede, hath no desyre ne loue in doing of it. This thing may wel appear by the lyfe of hunters, ye which out of doubt is more laborious and painfull

then is the lyfe of relygious persons, and yet nothing sustayneth them in theyr labour and paynes, but the earnest loue and hartie desire to fynde theyr game. Regard no lesse my writing, good sister, though to my purpose I vse the example of hunters, for all true christian soules be called Hunters, and their office and duetie is to séeke and hunt for to fynde Christ Iesu. And therefore scripture in many places exhorteth vs to séeke after him, &amp; assureth that he will be found of them that dyligently séeke after him. Inuenietur ab hijs qui querunt eum. That is to say, he will be founde of them that séeke hym, well happy are all those that can fynde him, or can haue any sent of him in this life here. For that sent (as Saint Paule saith) is the sent of the verie lyfe. And the deuout soules where they féele thys sent, they runne after hym a pace. Curremus in odorem vnguentorum tuorū. That is to say, we shall runne after the sent of thy swéete oyntmentes. Séeyng then all deuoute soules maye bée called Hunters, I will

farther prosecute ye comparysō made before betwéene the lyfe of ye Hunters and the lyfe of the relygious persons after this maner.
            
               A comparison betvveene the lyfe of Hunters, and the lyfe of religious persons.
               WHat lyfe is more paynefull and laborious of it self then is the life of Hunters which most early in the mornyng breake their sléepe and ryse when other doe take their rest and ease, and in his labour he may vse no playne high wayes and the softe grasse, but he must treade vppon the fallowes, runne ouer the hedges, &amp; créepe thorowe the thicke bushes, and crye all the long day vppon his dogges, and so continue without meate or drinke vntill ye verie night dryue him home, these labours be vnto him pleasaunt and ioyous, for the desire &amp; loue that he hath to sée the poore Hare chased with dogges. Uerely, verely, if hée were compelled to take vppon hym

such labours, and not for thys cause he would soone be wearie of thē, thinking them full tedious vnto him: neither would he ryse out of his bed so soone, ne faste so longe, ne endure these other labours vnlesse he had a verie loue therin For the earnest desire of his mynd is so fixed vppon his game, that all these payns be thought to him but verie pleasures▪ And therfore I may well say that loue is the principall thyng that maketh anye worke easie, though the worke bée right painfull of it selfe, &amp; that without loue no labour can be comfortable to ye dooer. The loue of this game deliteth him so muche that he careth for no worldlye honour, but is content with full simple and homely aray. Also the goodes of the world hée séeketh not for, nor studieth howe to attayne them. For the loue and desire of his game so greatly occupyeth his mynde and harte. The pleasures also of his flesh he forgetteth by wearinesse and wasting of hys bodie in earnest labour. All his mynde, all his soule, is buzied to knowe where the

poore Hare may be founde. Of that is his thought, and of that is his communication, and all his delight is to heare and speake of that matter, euerie other matter but this, is tedious for him to giue eare vnto, in all other things he is dull and vnlustie, in this onely quicke and sturryng, for thys also to be done, there is no office so humble, ne so vyle, that he refuseth not to serue hys owne dogges hym selfe, to bathe theyr féete, and to annoynte them where they be sore, yea and to clense their stinkyng Cannell where they shall lye and rest them. Surely if religious persōs had so earnest a mynde and desire to the seruice of Christ, as haue these Hunters to sée a corse at a Hare, their lyfe should be vnto them a verie ioye and pleasure. For what other be the paynes of religiō but these yt I haue spokē of. That is to say, much fasting, crying, and comming to ye quire, forsakyng of worldly honours, worldly riches, and fleshly pleasures, and communication of the world, humble seruice, &amp; obedyence to his soueraigne, &amp; charytable

dealyng to his sister, which payns in euerie pointe, the Hunter taketh and sustayneth more largely for the loue that he hath to his game, then doeth many religious persons for the loue of Christ. For albeit, the relygious person ryseth at mydnight, which is painefull to hyr in verie déede, yet shée went before that to hyr bedde at a conuenyent houre, and also commeth after to hyr bedde agayne. But the Hunter ryseth early, and so continueth foorth all the long day, no more returning to his bed vntill the verie night, and yet peraduenture he was late vp the night before, and full oftē vp all the long nightes. And though the religious woman fall vntill it be noone, the which must be to hir paynfull, the Hūter yet taketh more payn which fasteth vntill the verye night, forgetting both meate and drink for the pleasure of his game. The religious woman singeth all ye forenoone in the quier, and yt also is laborious vnto hir, but yet ye hunter singeth not, but he cryeth, halloweth, &amp; shooteh all the long day, &amp; hath more greater pains.

The religious woman taketh much labour in comming to the quyer and sitting there so long a season, but yet no doubt of it more labour taketh the Hunter in running ouer the fallow and leaping ouer ye hedges, &amp; créeping thorow the bushes then that can bée. And would to God yt in other thyngs that is to say, touching worldly honours, worldly ryches, worldly pleasures, would to God that the relygious persōs many of them might profite as much in myndfulnesse in séeking of Christ, as the Hunter doeth in séeking of his game, &amp; yet all theyr comforte were to common and speak of Christ, as the Hunters hath all their ioye to speake of the poore Hare, and of their huntyng. And furthermore, would to God ye religious persons would content them selues with the humble seruice done to their soueraigne, and with charitable behauiour vnto their sisters, and with as good a harte and mynde as the Hunters acquit thē to serue their heūds. I wisse it is a thing much more reasonable to loue and serue reasonable

creatures made to the Image of almightie God, rather then to loue and serue dogges which be vnreasonable creatures. And rather our dutie were to speake of Christ, and of things belonging to his honour, then of the vaine worldly matters which be but very trifles in déede. And also wyth more attentyue mynde we shoulde séeke after our sauiour Christ Iesu, to knowe our very comforte in him, wherein resteth the great merite of our soules. Then the Hunters should séeke after the Hare, which whē they haue gottē, they haue no great gaines thereby. But as I sayde the cause why that so many religious persons so diligently pursue not the wayes of religion as doe the hunters, is the want of ye obseruation of their game which is nothing els but the lack of loue. For verely as I thinke the earnest loue and hartie desire of game maketh all labours and paynes pleasaunte and ioyous vnto the Hunter. And if there were in religious persons as great fauour and loue to the seruice of God, as be in Hunters to

their game all their lyfe should bée a verie Paradise and heauenly ioye in this worlde. And contrariwise without this feruor of loue it can not bée but painfull, wearie, and tedious to them. My purpose therefore deare sister is to minister vnto you some cō
                  mon considerations which if you wil often resorte vnto by due remembraunce, &amp; so by diligent prayer call vppon almightie God for hys loue, you shall now by his grace attain it.
            
            
               The first consideration.
               THe first consideration may be this: First consider by your owne mynde and reason, that almightie God of his owne singular goodnesse &amp; frée will dyd create you and make you of naught, whervnto he was not bounde by any necessitie, nor drawen by any commoditie that might ryse vppon him by your creation. No other thing moued him but his verie goodnesse and speciall fauor yt he bare vnto you, long or euer he did make you. This good sister take for a very truth &amp; firmly beleue it, for so it

is in verye déede innumerable creatures more then euer were made or euer shall be made, hee myght haue made if it had bene so pleasing vnto him. For how many suppose you maryed men and maryed weomen haue bene and shall be héereafter in thys world, that neuer had ne neuer shall haue any children, yet they full gladly would haue had, and by possibilitie of nature might haue had many, if it had so pleased almightie God to haue made and to haue giuen vnto them children. But all those be lefte vnmade, and amongest them he myght haue lefte you also vnmade, and neuer haue put his hande to the making of you, if he had so would. Neuerthelesse as I sayde it pleased his goodnes herein to prefer you of his special fauour yt he bear vnto you, leauing vnmade other moe innumerable, electing you, &amp; appointing you to be made refusing &amp; setting apart all thē which wold peraduēture haue cōsidered his speciall grace &amp; fauour more louingly thē you hitherto haue don. And wold haue studied more for his plesure and

seruice then euer you did, and you occupie the roome and place that some of them might haue occupyed by lyke fauour, as almightie God hath shewed vnto you. Ah deare sister howe much should this one consideration moue you to the earnest loue of thys our so gracyous a Lorde, that thus hath appoynted and chosen you to bée his creature, before so many other where hée might haue, taken any of them at his pleasure, &amp; repelled you, and left you as naught, without any maner of being.
            
            
               The second consideration.
               THe second consideration is this, where there is manye maner of beings, some creatures haue a goodly béeyng, some haue an vngoodly being. It is a more goodly beinge Margarite of a precious stone, then of a peble stone, of the fayre bright golde, then of rustie yron, of a goodly Fesaund then of a venemous Serpent, of a prettie Faune then of a foule Toade, of a

reasonable soule, then of an vnreasonable beast. And it is not to be doubted but almightie God might haue giuen to any of them, what being so euer he woulde, &amp; might haue transformed eche of those into the nature and kynde of any of the other at hys pleasure and will. For of the stones he might make men, as in the gospel our sauiour doeth affyrme, potens est deus de lapidibus istis suscitare filios Abrahe. Almightie God is of power to make of these stones the children of Abraham. And contrariwise he might of men haue made stones as the wife of Loth was turned into a salt stone. And in likewise me or you or any other man or woman, he might haue made a stone, or a Serpēt, or a Toad, for his pleasure. There is no creature so foule, so horrible, or so vngoodlie, but he might put you in the same cō
                  dition that the most loathly of them be put in, and them, in contrariwise he might haue put in the same condition that you be in. Consider now by your reasō, that if you had bene made in the lykenesse of an Owle, or of an

Ape, or of a Toade, howe deformed you shoulde haue bene, and in howe wretched &amp; myserable condition. And thank your Lord God yt hath giuē you a more excelēt nature, yea, such a nature as excelleth in noblenesse, in dignitie, all other bodilie natures: For it is made to the verie lykenesse and Image of almightie God: wherevnto none other bodily creature doth reach néere. Metalles ne stones be they neuer so precious, neyther herbes nor Trées, neither Fysshes, ne foules, neyther any maner of beast be they neuer so noble in their kinde, doeth attayne to this high poynte of noblenesse to haue in them the Image and lykenesse of almightie God, but onely man. For as much thē as our lord God, might haue giuen this excelent dignitie to other innumerable creatures, as to beastes, to Foules, to fishes, to trées, to herbes, to mettalles, to stones. And hathe not so done but before all those hath elected and chosen you to beare hys Image &amp; lykenesse, &amp; to bée indued wt a reasonable soul, how much shuld his louing dealing

moue you to enfore your selfe wt all ye strength and power of your harte &amp; mynde, to loue him therfore agayne.
            
            
               The third consideration.
               THe third cōsideration is this, that where notwithstanding this great and excelent gyft you neuerthelesse by the reason of originall sinne wherewith you were born of your mother into this world, had lost the great inheritaūce aboue in heauen, and purchased euerlasting imprisonment in hell, he of his great and singular goodnesse had prouyded you to be borne within the precinctes of Christendeome, where you haue bene instructed in the doctrine of hys fayth, and receyued the holy Sacrament of baptisme, and haue béene made a christian woman, whereby you dyd receyue againe your inherytaunce before lost, and haue etcaped yt most horrible daūger of euerlasting dampnation. Howe manye suppose you in all the worlde that bée not instructed in this lawe and fayth

of Christ, ne haue not receyued the holy Sacrament of Baptisme, both noble men &amp; women, both Knightes and Princes, which haue great wisdome and reason, and many suche as peraduenture if they were taught it, woulde more readilye applye their myndes to Christes fayth then you doe, and more hartily serue him, honour and loue hym, thē euer you did. And yet loe thus graciously hath hée prouyded for you before all them, and hath appointed you to be a Christian woman, &amp; to be partaker of all those graces and benifites that belong vnto the christian people, which bée so many and so great, that it passeth the wittes of men, not onely to number, but also to think? And héere good sister doe déepely consider in your soule, howe much this louing preferment of our Lorde God should sturre you to loue him agayn, when he suffereth so innumerable a multitude of men and women to perishe &amp; to be lost for euer, amongest whom many do passe you in all naturall vertues, both of bodie and soule, and also would farfarther

passe you in profiting in the lawe of Christ, if they were receyued therevnto, and yet I say he suffereth them to perish euerlastingly and perpetuallie to be dampned to: And for your safegarde hath prouided of hys singular goodnesse &amp; mercy towardes you, for the whiche sithens it is not possible of your parte to recompence, whie shall you not with all your power enforce your selfe to loue hys most gracious goodnesse againe, and after your possibilitie to gyue vnto him most humble thankes therfore.
            
            
               The fourth Consideration.
               THe fourth cōsideration is this, that where sithens that tyme of your baptisme and that you were made a christian woman, you haue many tymes vnkindely faulne into deadly sinne, and broken hys lawes and commaundemēts, setting at naught all these benifites which he before had giuē to you following your wretched pleasures, to the great dyspleasure and contempt of his moste

highe maiestie. And yet he furthermore did not strike you, ne yet reuēge him selfe vppon you rigoriously, punishing the transgressors &amp; breakers of his lawe, as he might and shoulde by his rightuousnesse haue done. But contrariwyse he did long spare you by his excelēt mercy, and mercifully he did abyde your returne to hym againe by sorowfull repentaunce, and askyng of him mercy for your abhominable offences. And where you so dyd with good hartie mynde at anye tyme, he receyued you to his grace, and by the Sacrament of pennaunce you were takē into his fauour again, and so yet escape the horrible paynes of Hell due for your outragious vnkindnesse: No reason may iudge the cōtrarie but yt you of good ryght haue deserued them for your foule presūption, in breaking of ye lawes of your Lord God: and preferring your wretched appetites before hys pleasure, and following your owne wilfull desires before his most high commaundements. (Alas) what miserable cō
                  dition should you now haue bene in, if he so incōtinent after your offēces had strikē you by death, &amp; had sēt you

to ye horrible payns of hell, where you shuld not onely for a time haue biddē but for euer, &amp; wtout all remedy. No praiers of your frinds, no alms déeds, ne such other good works shuld haue releued you. Ah, sister imprint déepely in your soule this inestimable mercy of your Lorde God shewed vnto you through his most gracious &amp; merciful abidīg for your return to him by true repētāce &amp; asking of his mercy. For inumerable soules of men &amp; weomen for lesse offēces then you haue done, lye now in ye prisō of hel, &amp; shal there cōtinu wtout end: which if they might haue had as great sufferance as you haue had, &amp; so long leasure to repent them, they woulde haue taken more sorowfull repentance then euer you tooke, &amp; doe now more sorowfully repent them thē euer you did, but yt as now cā not profit thē, for yt sorow &amp; repētāce is now to late. But to my purpose, how may you thīk yt this louing sufferāce &amp; gracious abidīg of your amēdmēt &amp; merciful accepting of your sorows &amp; repētāce, for your great sins cōmeth not of a singular loue shewed vnto you by your lord god, before all them.

And shall not this cōsideration pearce your harte, and moue you muche to loue him againe.
            
            
               The fifth consideration.
               THe fifth consideration is this: Peraduenture after that thus by your repentance &amp; askyng mercy, you were taken to this grace of your God, yet far more gréeuously, and farre more vnkindly you fell againe to sinnne, and kepte not ye purpose and promyse that before you did make, but more without shame and dread of hys hyghnesse, tooke your libertie in your sinfull wayes, abusing his gentlenes, &amp; presuming vppō hys mercie, not regarding any benifite or kindenesse shewed by his most excelent goodnesse vnto you before, so defiling your soule by innumerable wayes, and makyng it filthie &amp; more vngoodly then is the Sowe that waltereth hir self in the foule myrie puddle, and more pestilently stinketh in the sight of God, then is the stinking carion of a dead dogge, being rotten

and lying in a ditch, yet neuertheles for all these misbehauiors, your Lord God of his farre passing goodnes hath called you agayne from your sinfull life, and hath graciously stirred your soule to forsake your sin, &amp; to leue this wretched worlde, &amp; to enter the holy relygion. Wherby after the sentence of holy doctors, your soule is made as cleane as it was at your baptisme, and restored agayne to the puritie and cleanenesse of your first innocencie: And not onely that, but also hée hath appointed you to be of the number of them, that be assigned for hys best beloued spouses. And what hygh point of singular fauour is this? How many weomen farre better then you, be lefte behinde in this worlde not called to this high dignitie, nor admitted to thys most speciall grace? When the noble Kinge Asuerus as it is written in the scripture commaunded many fayre yong maydens to be chosen out, and to be séene vnto with all things yt might make them fayr
                     •
                   and beautifull and pleasaunt to his sight, to the intent that they at

all tymes when it should like him to appoynte any of them to come to his presence and to be his spouse, they might be ye more readie. This thing no doubt of it, was to them yt were thus chosē a comfort, that they were preferred before other, and also euerie one of them might lyue in hope to come to ye kings presēce, &amp; haue some likelihood to be accepted for his spouse in so much yt all other but they were excluded. In like maner it is with religious women. All they by the gracious calling of the great king of heuen be gathered into Gods religion and disseuered from thother seculer women that be of the world, there a season to abide, vntill they be sufficiently prepared by the holy sacraments, and the holy obseruacions of religiō to come to his gracious highnesse presence, and to be brought into his secret chamber aboue in heauen, there to abide with him in endles ioy and blisse. Blessed is that religious woman, that so doth prepare her selfe for this litle time that héere she shal tarry by prayer, by meditation

by contemplatiō by teares of devocion, by harty loue &amp; burning desyre yt after this transitory life she may be admitted to the most excellēt honor &amp; not with shame &amp; rebuke be repelled therfro, whē ye day shal com.
            
            
               The sixt consideration.
               THe sixt consideration that you call wel to your remembrāce, who it is yt doth thus exhorte you for to loue, verely he is ye person that if eyther you wil fréely giue your loue, or els sell your loue, he is most worthie to haue it aboue all other. First if ye were of that mynd to giue your loue frée, it were good yet there to bestow it, that you shoulde choose suche a one, as both in goodlinesse of person, as also in prowesse &amp; wisdom and good gentil maners may be worthie your loue. For if there be any deformitie in him whō you would loue, it is an impediment and great let for to loue hym: But in our sauiour Christ the sonne of God is no deformitie, for hee is all goodlye and surmounteth all other in goodlynesse: And therefore of hym the Prophet

Dauid affyrmeth in thys maner. Speciosus forma pre filijs hominum: that is to say, he is goodly before the chyldren of men. And of truth much goodlie must he néedes be that hath made so many goodly creatures. Behold the Rose, the Lillie, the Uyolet, beholde the Pecockes, the Feasaunt, the Popingaye: Behold all the other creatures of this world: All these were of his making, all there beautie and goodlinesse of hym they receyued it. Wherfore this goodlinesse discribeth that he him self must néedes of necessitie be verie goodly &amp; beautifull. And for that in the booke of Canticles the Spouse discribeth his goodlinesse saying: Dilectus meus candidus et rubicūdus, electus ex millibus. That is to saye, hée that I loue is whyte and redde, chosen out amōgest thousands. And this beautie and goodlines is not mortal, it can not fade ne perish as doeth the goodlinesse of other men, which lyke a flower to day is fresh and lustie, and to morrowe with a little sicknesse is withered and vanisheth away. And yet it is sensible to the goodlinesse of

mans nature, for the which also he is more naturallie to bée beloued of many. For lykenesse is the grounde of loue, lyke alway doeth couet like: and the néerer in lykenesse that any person bée, the sooner they may bée knit togither in loue. The same lykenes he hath &amp; you haue, like body and lyke soule, touching his māhood, your soule is also like vnto him in his godhead: For after ye Image &amp; similitude of it, your soule is made. Furthermore of his might and power you may bée likewise a certayne season. He made this world by the onely commaundement of his mouth, and gaue to the herbes and all other creatures their vertue, &amp; might that they haue. And may also by his power saue &amp; dampne creatures eyther to lifte them vp in bodie and soule into heauen aboue, or els to throw them downe into euer during payns of hell. If ye doubt of his wisdom behold all this world, and cōsider how euery creature is set with an other, and euery of them by him selfe, how the heauens are apparelled with starres, the ayre with

Foules, ye water with Fishes, ye earth with herbes, trées &amp; beastes, how the starres be clad with light, the Foules with feathers, ye fish with scales, the beastes wt heare, herbes &amp; trées with leaues, and flower with sent, wherin doth wel appear a great &amp; merueilous wisdō of him yt made thē. Finally his good &amp; gentil maner is all full of pleasure &amp; cōfort so kinde, so friendly, so liberall &amp; beneficious, so pittious and mercifull, so readie in all oportunities, so mindfull &amp; circumspect, so dulcet &amp; swéet in communicatiō. For as scripture saith. Non licet amaritudinem conuersatio vel tedium cōuetas illius, Sed letitiam et gaudeum. That is to say, hys maners be so swéet &amp; pleasaūt, yt the cōuersaciō of him hath no bitternes, yea, his cōpany hath no loathsomnes, ne wearines in it, but all gladnes and ioye. Here peraduenture you wil say vnto me, how may I loue yt I sée not, if I might sée him with all ye cōditiōs ye speak of, I could wt al my hart loue him. Ah good sister yt time is not come yet, you must as I said now for ye time prepare your self in cleannesse of bodie

and soule, against ye tyme, so that when that tyme commeth, you may be able and worthie to sée him, or els you shall be excluded from him with the vnwise virgins of whom ye gospel telleth yt they were shut out from his presence with great shame &amp; cōfusiō, bicause they had not suffitiently prepared thēselues. Therfore good sister for this time be not negligent to prepare your selfe with all good workes, that thē you may be admitted to com vnto his presence, from ye which to be excluded, it shall be a more gréeuous payne, thē any paine of hell. For as Chrisostome sayth. Si decem mille gehē
                     nas quis duerit nihil tale est quale ab illa beata visione exadere, that is to saye, if 
                     •
                  ne would rehearse vnto mée tenne thousand hels, yet all yt should not be so great paines as it is to be excluded from the blessed sighte of the face of Christ.
            
            
               The seuenth consideration.
               THe seuēth cōsideratiō is this: wher now it appeareth vnto you, that if you will giue your loue fréelie there is non so worthy to haue it as Iesu ye
                  
sonne of the virgin Mary. I will further shewe vnto you that if you will not fréely giue it, but you will looke peraduenture to haue some thing agayne, yet there is none so well worthie to haue it as he is, for if an other will giue more for it then he, I will not be agaynst it, take your aduantage. But sure I am there is none other to whome your loue is so deare, and of so greate price as it is vnto him, nor any that will come nigh vnto that, yt he hath giuen or wil giue. If his benifits and kyndnesse shewed towardes you, wherof I speak somewhat before, were by you well pondered, they be no small benifites, and especially ye loue of so great a prince, and that he would thus loue you, an
                     •
                   preferre you before so many innumerable creatures of his, and that when there was in you no loue, and when you could not skill of loue: yea, and that, that more is, when you were enimie vnto him yet he loued you, and so wonderfully that for your loue and to washe you from sin, and to deliuer your soule from the extreame perrill

he shead his most precious bloud, an
                     •
                   suffered the most shamefull, the most cruel, and the most painefull death of the crosse, his head to be perced with thornes, his handes and féete to bée thorough holed with nayles, his side to be launced with a speare, and all his most tender bodie to be torne and rent with whippes &amp; scourges. Beléeue this for a very truth good sister, that for your sake he suffered all, as if there had bene no moe in all the world but onely your selfe, which I will declare more largely vnto you in the next consideration following. Beléeue it in the meane tyme certainely, for so it is in déede, and if you belieue it not, you doe a great iniurie and shewe a full vnkindenesse vnto him that thus muche hath done for you. And if this beliefe truly settle in your harte, it is to me a meruaile if you can content your heart without the loue of him, of him I say, yt thus déerely hath loued you, and doeth loue you still. For what other louer will 
                     ••
                  e thus much for your loue? What creature in all the world will die for

                  
                     •
                  our sake? what one person wil depart with one drop of his hart bloud for your sake? whē thē the son of God, the prince of heauē, ye Lord of Angels hath done this for your sake, which thing no other creature wil do, what frost could haue vngeled your harte, that it may not relēt against so great an heat of loue? if he so excelēt in all noblenesse should haue giuen you but one fauourable countenance from the heauens aboue, it had bene a more precious benifit then euer you could recompence by your loue againe. It were impossible for your loue to recompence that one thing. But nowe much rather when he hath descended into this wretched worlde for your sake, and here hath become man, and hath endured all miserie pertaining vnto man, saue onely sinne and ignoraunce, and finally hath suffered this great horrible death for your loue, how shall you euer now recompence this by any loue or seruice to be done for your pittie? And he hath not onely don al this for your sake, but also hath prepared for you after this transitory

lyfe a rewarde aboue in heauen, so great that neuer mortal eye saw the lyke, nor any tonge can expresse, nor yet any hart can think. Ah sister whē your wretched soule shall hence departe, which can not be verie longe héere, who shall giue you refreshing the space of one hour. Good therfore it is that you looke vnto your selfe, &amp; vppon him bestow your loue, yt which hitherto hath done most for you, &amp; best hath deserued it beyond all other, and yet after this life he wil giue for it a rewarde so inestimable that it shall neuer fayle you.
            
            
               The eight consideration.
               THe eight cōsideration is this: yt albeit, there are many other which also are beloued of christ Iesu, yet ye loue yt he sheweth to them, nothing minisheth his loue towards you, as if there were no moe beloued of him in all ye kinde of mā. This may euidently be shewed vnto you by this exāple folowing. If before any Image of our sauior were disposed &amp; set in a

long rowe many glasses, some great and some litlle, some high and some lowe, a conuenient distance from the Image, so that euerie of them myght receiue a presentmēt of the Image, it is no doubt but in euerie of these glasses should appeare the verie likenesse of the same Image I will not say but this lykenesse should be longer in the great glasses then in the lesse, and clearer in the better clensed glasses, and in them that were nigh vnto the Image, then in the other that were not so well clensed, &amp; much farther of. But as to the likenesse it selfe it shall be as full and as whole in euerie one glasse as though there were but one. Now to my purpose, if you consider lykewise that all ye good soules that be scourged from deadly sinne, be in the maner of glasses set in an order to receiue the loue of our sauiour Christ Iesu. Such soules as by true pennaunce doing, by sighing, by wéeping, by praying, by watching by fasting, &amp; by other lyke, be ye better scoured and clensed from the spottes and mallice of deadly sinne, they bée

the brighter glasses and more cléerly receyue this loue, &amp; such also be néere vnto our Sauior, for nothing putteth vs farre from him but onely sinne. And therefore they that haue more diligently scoured their soules from the rust of sinne, be néerer vnto him, then the other that so haue not done. Such soules also as of their parte enforce them selues to a great loue and to a more ample feruor, they doe inlarge the capacitie of their soules, to receyue a more large abundaunce of loue agayne, those that lesse enforce them, haue a lesse capacitie in receyuing, and therfore so much the lesse they receyue of this loue. Euen as a man that openeth his bosome wyde and enlargeth it, is more able to receiue a greater thing into it, then hée that doeth not. But yet as I haue sayde before of the glasses, euery one of the soules receyue as full and as whole a loue of Iesu Christ, as though there were no moe soules in all the world but that one alone, for the loue of Christ Iesus infinite. And therfore whē innumerable of soules

haue euerie one of them receyued as much the loue of Christ Iesu, as to euerie one of them is possible, yet hath he still in him self loue suffitiēt for infinite moe, &amp; this his loue therby is not in any point diminished nor lessened, though it be deuided vnto many be ye number of them neuer so great. None of them yt be beloued receiue ye lesse bicause of the multitude of his fellowes, nor if he had no moe but him selfe he shoulde not thereby haue any more abundance of loue to his parte, but according to the clēsing and capacitie of his soule &amp; nighnesse vnto Christ, his parte in loue shall be the lesse or more. Wherefore good sister I pray you bée you dylygent to scoure your soule cleane, and to enforce your soule on your parte feruently to loue your spouse Christ Iesu, and drawe nygh vnto hym with entiere deuotion, &amp; then vndoubtedly you shall be partener to ye more plentuous aboundaunce of his loue, notwtstāding any other multitude which beside is beloued of him, for he neuerthelesse is as studious of you, and as

mindfull, &amp; as feruēly careth for your weale, as though ther wer no mo beloued of him but you alone in all thys world.
            
            
               The ninth Consideration.
               THe ninth cōsideratiō is this, wher peraduenture you would obiect to me again &amp; say, Brother if it bée thus as you say, that my Lord Iesu loueth me so much, and is so mindfull of me, and so feruently entēdeth my weale, what néede me to care whatsoeuer I doe, he will not cast me away, he wil not forsake me nor suffer mée to perish. Good sister without doubt as I haue said, our sauior Christ Iesu is in loue towards you, &amp; he is myndfull &amp; more louing towards you then I can expresse. And sure you may be, yt hée will neuer cast you away, ne forsake you, if you before cast not your selfe away, ne forsake your selfe. But if you giue any place to sinne in your soule, and suffer it to enter vpon you, verely then you forsake your self and cast your selfe awaye, and willinglie destroye your selfe, that is your déede &amp; not hys: for he neuer forsaketh

any creature vnlesse they before haue forsakē them selues. And if they will forsake them selues were they neuer in so great fauour with hym before, they then incontinently lose his fauour, the which thing well appeareth in his first spirituall creatures the noble Angelles Lucifer and hys comp
                     •
                  nie, which were created in excelent brightnesse, and were muche in the fauour of almightie God, they presumptuously offēded him in pride for the which not onely, they lost hys fauour, but also their merueylous brightnesse became incōtinently horrible, foule, and were expelled out of the glorious kingdom of heauen that they were in, and throwen into perpetuall darkenesse into the pryson of hell. The first man Adam also who was created in singular honour, and was put into Paradise a place full of gladnesse, there to liue in comfort of all pleasure, the which was done to him for a singular loue yt almightie God had towardes him, yet anon as h
                     •
                   fell to sinne he was in lyke maner expelled out from that pleasure, and

sent into this miserable world to endure miserie and payne. If those noble creatures which were lift vp into so great fauour with almightie God, so lightly by their misdemeanor in sin, lost his gracious fauour, let none other creature thinke but if they admit any sinne to their soule, they shal be likewyse excluded out of his fauor. For sinne is so odible vnto almightie God, that not the dearest friends that euer he had in all the worlde, but if there were founde in their soules any deadly sin after death, they should neuer be receiued into the ioy of heauen. Not the blessed Mary Magdalen for all hir loue towardes him, nor yet his owne blessed mother that bare him into this world, if one deadly sin were foūd in their soules, they shuld incontinent be throwen into ye darke dungeon of hell. Wherfore good sister say not, if his loue be so muche vppon you, and he so desirouslie entendeth your profite, that you may doe what you list, you néed not to care what you doe. But contrariwise the more that he loueth you, the more you shoulde

take héede vnto your self and beware that you offend him not, for so did the blessed Mary Magdalen of whome I spake before. Shée notwithstandyng the great loue that both our sauiour had to hir, and shée vnto him agayne for the which also hyr sinnes were forgiuen hyr, yet after his death shée fled from the companie of men, &amp; lyued in the wildernesse farre from any worldly comforte, in great wayling, fasting, and prayer, &amp; such other painefulnesse of hir body, &amp; was nothing ye lesse diligent to kéepe hir selfe warely from sinne, for the great loue that our lord &amp; sauiour had to hir, but for yt the more studiously she did auoid &amp; eschu euery thing wherby she might run into any displeasure against him.
            
            
               The tenth consideration.
               THe tenth consideration is this: it were wel done and much it shuld farther this cause if you truly esteme of how little value your loue is, how vaine, how light, &amp; howe triflelous a thing it is, &amp; how few ther be yt would much regarde it, or set muche pryce

thereby, for fewe there be or none to whom it may doe any profit or auail. Contrariwise you should consider the loue of your spouse ye swéet Iesu, how excelēt it is, how sure, how fast, howe constantly abiding, how many haue much specially regarded it, Martirs innumerable both men and women for his loue haue shead theyr bloud, and haue endured euery kind of martirdom were it neuer so cruell, were it neuer so terrible. No paine, no tormentrie, might compell them to forsake his loue: so desirous were they of his loue, yt rather then they would forgo it, they gaue no force of ye losse of all this world beside, &amp; theyr owne life also. So deare and precious was that loue to them, that all ye honors, pleasures, and possessions of this life, they recompted as verie trifles in comparisō of that. And what be you in comparison of thē, but naughty, wretched, and miserable? where then they which be now glorious saincts aboue in heauen, so much haue valued and so greatly estéemed this most excelēt loue, and you may haue the same loue

for yours, that is so naughtie and so little worth, what should you doe of your parte? howe muche should you enfore your selfe not onely to obtayn this loue, but studiouslie to kéepe it, sithens that you haue it once, and for nothing to departe therefro. He of his goodnesse doeth not repell any creature from hys loue, but permitteth them assuredly that if any draw nigh vnto him by loue, he will loue them agayne, and giue his most precyous loue for theirs, he sayeth, Ego diligentes me diligo: That is to say, I loue them that loue mée. And in an other place. En qui venit ad me nō equam foras: That is to say, what person so euer commeth vnto me, I wil not cast him away. Sister if you consider this déeply, it should moue you to fall downe vpon your knées, &amp; with all your hart and mynde say vnto your Spouse in this maner. O my blessed Sauiour Lord Iesu thou askest my loue, thou desirest to haue my harte, and for my loue thou wilt giue me thy loue agayne. O my swéete Lorde, what is this for thée to desire, which arte so

excelent, if my poore harte were of so much value as all the hartes of men and weomen that euer were, if they were put togither in one, &amp; if it were as precious &amp; noble as there is price and noblenesse in all ye orders of Angels, if furthermore it did contayne in it all bodelie and spirituall treasure that is within the compasse of heauen or without, yet it were but a little gift to giue vnto so great a lord, for his most delicate &amp; precious loue to be had of him againe: much rather my loue and hart as it is now naughtie, wretched, and miserable, so is it but a small gift and of little value. Neuerthelesse such as it is, sithens it is thy pleasure to haue it, &amp; thy goodnesse doeth aske it of mée saying, Prebe mihi cor tuum, That is to say, giue me thy harte, I fréely gyue it vnto thée, and I most humbly beséech thy goodnesse and mercy to accept it, and so to order me by thy grace, that I may receiue into it the loue of nothing contrarie to thy pleasure, but that I alwayes may kéepe the fyre of thy loue auoyding from it all other

contrarie loue that may in anie wyse displease thée.
            
            
               The finall conclusion of all.
               
                  NOw thē good Sister, I trust that these considerations, if you oftē read them with good deliberation, and truelie imprint them in your remembraunce, they will somewhat inflame your harte with the loue of Christ Iesu, and that loue once established in you, all ye other points and ceremonies of your religion shall bée easie vnto you, and no whit painefull, you shall then comfortriblie doe euerie thing that to good religion appertayneth, without any great wearynesse. Neuerthelesse if it so fortune that you at any tyme begin to féele any dulnesse of mynde quicken it again by the meditatiō of death, which I send you here before, or els by some effectuall prayer, earnestly calling for helpe &amp; succour vpon the most swéete Iesu, thinking as it is in deed, that is

your necessitie, &amp; that no where els you can haue any helpe but of him. And if you will vse these short prayers following, for euerie day in the wéeke one, I thinke it shall be vnto you profitable. For thus you may in your hart shortly pray what companie so euer you be amongest.
            
            
               The Prayers be these.
               O blessed Iesu make me to loue thée intierlie.
               O blessed Iesu I would fayne, but without thy helpe I can not.
               O blessed Iesu let me déeply consider the greatnesse of thy loue towards mée.
               O blessed Iesu giue vnto mée grace hartilie to thanke thée for thy benifites.
               O blessed Iesu giue me good will to serue thée, and to suffer.
               O swéete Iesu giue me a natural remembraunce of thy passion.
               O swéete Iesu possesse my hart, holde and kéepe it onelie to thée.
               
                  THese short praiers if you wil often saye, and with all the power of your soule &amp; harte, they shall merueylouslie kindle in you this loue, so that it shal be alway
                     •
                   feruent and quicke, ye which is my especiall desire to knowe in you. For nothyng may be to my comfort more then to heare of your furtheraunce and profiting in God &amp; in good religion, the which our blessed Lorde graunte you for hys great mercie. Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            ¶ A Sermon verie fruitfull, godly, and learned, vpon thvs sētēce of the Prophet Ezechiell, Lamentationes, Carmen, et vae, very aptely applyed vnto the passion of Christ: Preached vpon a good Friday, by the same Iohn Fissher, Bishop of Rochester.
            
               THe Prophet Ezechyell telleth yt hée sawe a booke spread before him,
                  Ize. 2. the which was written both within and without, &amp; there was written also in it, Lamentationes, Carmen, et vae, that is to say, lamentation, songe, &amp; woe. This was a wonderfull booke, and much to be merueiled vpon. Much comfortable knowledge and swéetnesse this Prophette gate by this booke, (as he saith in the Chapter next ensuing,
                  Eze. 3. 
               factum est in ore meo sicut mell dulce, thys booke was in my mouthe as swéete as honye. This booke to our purpose may bée taken vnto vs, the Crucifixe, ye which

doubtlesse is a merueylous booke, as wée shall shewe héereafter. In the which if wée doe exercise our admiration, wée shall come to wonderfull knowledge. Meruayling was the cause, why that the Philosophers came to so greate knowledge, as they had. They behelde and sawe many wonderfull thynges, and effectes in thys worlde, as the marueylous earthquakes, Thūders, lightnings, Snow, Rayne, &amp; Frostes, blasinng Starres, the Eclipses of the Sunne and of the Moone, and suche other effectes. And those marueylous wonders moued them to search for the causes of the same. And so by dyligent searche and inquisition, they came to great knowledge and cunning, which cunnyng men call Philosophie naturall. But there is an other higher Philosophie which is aboue nature, which is also gottē with marueyling. And this is the verye Philosophie of Christian people. And doubtlesse amongest all other things concerning a christian man, it is a thyng muche marueylous, and most

wonderfull, that the sonne of God, for the loue that he had vnto ye soule of man, woulde suffer hym selfe to bée crucified, and so to take vpon him that most vyllanous death vpon the Crosse.
                  Abac. 1. Act. 13. Of thys the Prophet Abacuck sayeth. Admiramini et obstupescite, quia opus factum est in diebus vestris, quod nemo credet quum narrabitur, marueyle, and wonder you, for a worke is done in your dayes, which when it shall bée shewed, no man will beléeue.
            Is it not a wonderfull thyng, that he whych is most to bée dreade and feared, would be in so muche feare, that for verie feare and dreade of payne hée had to suffer, he swet water and bloud.
            Is it not a wonderfull thing, that he yt was most inestimable in price, and moste precyous, woulde suffer hys bodie to bée solde for so little a pryce, as for the value of thyrtye pence?
            Is it not a wonderfull thyng, that hée that is the Lorde of heauen and earth, and all other creatures,

would suffer him selfe to be bound of those vyllaynes wyth ropes lyke a théefe?
            Is it not a wonderfull thing that he that hath so great might and power, would suffer him selfe to be taken of his cruell &amp; mortall enimyes, and so led vnto all these paynes?
            Is it not a wonderfull thyng, that hée that is the Iudge of all the worlde, woulde thus wrongfullye be iudged?
            Is it not a wonderfull thing, that hée yt had in hymall wisedome, would thus bée mocked and reputed as a foole?
            Is it not a wonderfull thing, that he that is so strong &amp; mightie, would be made so weake, and féeble, that he fell vnder the wayght and burthen of the Crosse?
            Is it not a wonderfull thing, that hée that is the Lord of Angels, would be spytted and bobbed of a sorte of Lorrelles in that moste dispytefull maner?
            Is it not a wonderfull thyng, that he that is the Kyng of euerlastyng

glorie would suffer his head in mockerie to be crowned with thornes?
            Is it not a wonderfull thyng, that he that giueth lyfe to euery creature, would suffer this most shamefull, sorowfull, and so painfull death?
            Is it not a wonderfull thing, that he yt is the Lord, and Aucthor of all libertie, woulde thus be bounde with ropes, and nayled hand and foote vnto the Crosse?
            Thus who that list with a méeke harte, and a true fayth, to muse and to maruayle of this most wonderfull booke (I say of the Crucifixe) hée shall come to more fruitefull knowledge, then many other which dayly studie vpon their cōmon bookes. This booke may suffice for ye studie of a true christian man, all ye dayes of his life. In this boke he may finde all things that be necessarie to ye health of his soule. Sainct Fraunces coulde passe hys time wt this booke, &amp; was neuer wery thereof, and his great studie was in the compasse of a fewe wordes. Quis tu, et quis ego domine. That is to say, who arte thou Lord, and who an
                  〈…〉
               .

Thys thought alway dyd run from hym selfe to Christ: And agayne, from Christ vnto hym selfe. And so euer he meruayled of the most excelent noblenesse of Christ, and compared it with hys owne naughtynesse, alwayes meruaylynge that Christ being of so incomparable worthynesse, woulde suffer that moste paynefull death for so vnworthye sinners, which lesson is so playne, and so common, that euerie man (be he neuer so simple,) may somewhat profite in it. And agayne, it is so hygh, that fewe can attayne to reach to the specyall fruite of it. This holie Sainct Fraūces so profited in this lesson, that it caused in hys hearte such a feruent loue, such a deuotion, suche an affection to Christ, that the capitall woundes which he behelde in the handes and féete, and syde of Christ, ware by myracle imprinted in hys owne handes and féete. This thing the B. of R. Innocent and hys Cardinalles dyd sée, and had verye proofe thereof.
            The meditation and imagination

of this booke was so earnest, and so continuall, that the token of the fiue woundes of Christ, were imprinted and ingraued in thys holy Saynctes bodye. But to this hygh fruite (as I sayde) fewe or none besides him doth attayne. It is a singular gyfte of almightie God, and not common to bée looked for of other persons. Neuerthelesse, who that will exercise this lesson, though he come not to this hygh poynte of perfection, he shall neuerthelesse greatly profite in ye same, and come to a great knowledge both of Christ &amp; of him selfe. A man may easily say &amp; thinke with him selfe (beholding in his hart the Image of ye Crucifixe, who arte thou, and who am I. Thus euerie person both ryche and poore▪ may thinke, not onely in the church here, but in euery other place, and in hys businesse where about hée goeth. Thus the poore laborer maye thinke, when he is at plough earyng hys grounde, and when hée goeth to hys pastures to sée hys Cattayle, or when hée is sittyng at home by hys fire side, or els when he lyeth in hys

bed waking and can not sléepe. Likewyse the rich man may do in his businesse that concerneth him. And the poore women also in theyr businesse, whē they be spinning of their rocks, or seruing of their pullen. The ryche weomen also in euerie lawfull occupation that they haue to doe. It is an easie thyng for any man or woman to make these two questions wyth them selfe. O my Lorde that wouldest dye for me vpō a Crosse, how noble and excelent arte thou? &amp; agayne, how wretched and myserable am I? Doubtlesse O thou christian soule, he that hunge for thy sake on ye Crosse, was verelie the sonne of God, as the noble Centurio sayde, when at the death of Christ he sawe so many wonderfull tokens. He saw ye sunne withdrawe his lyght, and the ayre in darkenesse, and felte all the earth tremble and quake, and the stones brake a sunder, then he sayde, vere filius dei erat iste.
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     at. 27. That is to say, verely thys person was the sonne of God. Thinke wt thy self, O christan soule, how great a person he is that is the

sonne of God? And thinke againe how vilaynous and how wretched thou art, in cōparison of him. What art thou but asshes, ciuis es,
               
                  Gene. 3. and vnto ashes thou shalt returne, et in cinera reuerteris. Abraham which was a man of high perfectiō, yet when he should speake vnto almightie God he sayde, quū sum puluis et ciuis loquar ad dominū,
               
                  Gene. 18. that is to say, I am but dust and asshes, and yet I must speake vnto my Lorde. Dauid also sayth,
                  Psal. 38. 
               vniuersa vanitas omnis homo viuens, that is to saye, man contayneth in him all vanitie. Furthermore Iob speaketh of man saying in this maner,
                  Iob. 14. 
               Qui puasi flos egreditur, et cōteritur, et fugit velut vmbra. Man is lyke a flower, he dooth issue foorth into the worlde, and soone after he is troden downe, and so finally hée passeth lyke a shadowe. Man is but earth and asshes, &amp; shall passe away lyke a shadow, and lyke a méere vanitie.
            Contrarywyse Christe, was, is, and euer shalbe, the prince of heauen, the Lorde of Angells, and the creator of all creatures,
                  Act. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               Qui fecit coelum et terram

et omnia que in eis sunt,
               
                  Psal. 145. He made heauē and earth &amp; all that is in them. His power is infinit, &amp; most to be dreade, Omnipotens rex, et metuendus nimis. His wisedome is incomprehensible. O altitudo diuitiarum sapientiae et scientiae dei.
               
                  Rom. 11. His greatnesse passeth all measure,
                  Psal. 47. Psal. 144. 
               Magnus dominus et laudabilis nimis, et magnitudinis eius non est finis. Shortly to saye, when a man hathe spoken or thought all that can be to the prayse of his excellencie, yet he dooth farre passe and surmount all that, as the Scripture sayth,
                  Excle. 43. 
               Glorificantes dominū, quantum cūque poteritis super valebit ad huc et admirabilis magnificentia illius. Now then, O thou sinfull creature, maruell at his excellent worthines, that was thus crucified. And maruell also at thy naughtinesse, for whose loue he was thus crucified. Thus I say dyd the holy sainct Francis, Quis es tu et quis sum ego domine, Who arte thou my Lord so excellent, and who am I, for whome thou wouldest endure all this payne.
            O Christen soule often beholde this booke, and saye with this holy man,

               Quis es tu et quis sum ego. Marueyle that his inestimable goodnesse would thus dye for so myserable a vanitie. And so maruelinge, thou shalt profyt in a gracious knowledge of Christ, and thy heart shall taste maruelous swéetenesse, and be replenished with a deuoute sauour of his most excelent goodnesse. But you maruell peraduenture why I call ye crucifix a booke? I will now tell you the consideracion why? A booke hath boardes, leaues, lynes, wrytinges, letters booth small and great. Fyrst I saye that a booke hath two boardes: the two boardes of this booke is the two partes of the crosse, for when the booke is opened &amp; spread, the leaues be cowched vpon the boardes. And so the blessed body of Christ was spred vpon the crosse. The leaues of this booke be ye armes, the handes, legges, and féete, with the other members of his most precious and blessed body.
            Neuer anye Parchement skynne was more strayghtlye stratched by strength vpon the tentors then was

this blessed body vpon ye crosse. These lorells that crucifyed him, drewe by vyolence his moste precious armes, with ropes vnto either braunche of the crosse, that the sinowes burst in sonder, and so nayled his handes fast with spykinge nayles of yron, vnto the crosse. After they stretched his féete lykewyse vnto an other hole beneath in the crosse, and there nayled them with the third nayle thorough bothe his féete. And so they reared vp this body a loft against the sunne, euen as a parchment skinne is sette foorth before the heat of the Sun for to drye. It was set vp a loft to the entent that all the worlde might looke vpon this booke.
            This booke was written with in and without. Fyrst within was wrytten but one worde: neuerthelesse this one word compryseth in it, as sayth saint Paule, the whole treasure of al cunning and wisdome partayning vnto God, In quo sunt omnes thesauri sapientiae dei,
               
                  Col. 2. in whome are all the treasure of the wisedome of god. Of this worde Saint Iohn speaketh,
                  Iohn. 1. saying,

               In principio erat verbum, the word was in ye begynning before all creatures, thys worde is the second person in the godhead, the sonne of God which by the holie Ghost was written in the inward syde of thys parchment. For the Godheade of Christe was couered and hidde vnder the lykenesse of man. The holy Ghost was the penne of almyghtie God the father, He set hys most mightie word vnto the body of Christ, within the wombe of the Uyrgine Marye, and so this booke was written within. For as Sainct Paule sayeth,1. Cor. 2
                     •
                  
                
               si cognouissent nunquam dominum gloriae crucifixissent, That is to saye, if they had knowne the sonne of God, whiche was and is the Lorde of euerlasting glorie, they woulde neuer haue crucified hym. They sawe his manhood which was in outwarde sight, but they sawe not hys Godheade whych was couered within the same. The Godhead was the inward syde, and the manhoode was the outwarde syde. Furthermore when a booke is spread, you sée that in the leaues

are many lynes drawen. And many letters, some read, some blacke, and some blewe, so in this booke, (the moste blessed bodie of Christ) was drawne many lynes, for it was all to scourged with whippes, so yt euery where ye print of ye cordes of ye scourges, was left behynd, &amp; that in euery place, from ye necke downward vnto the soles of his féete, so yt there was no margent lefte in all thys booke, there was no voyd place, but euery where it was eyther drawne with lynes, or els wryttē with letters, for these scourges fylled not onely his moste precyous bodie with lynes drawne euerie where, but also left many small Letters, some blacke, some blewe, some reade. For the bloud by the vyolence of the schourges sprunge out in euery place. And for bycause no parte of thys booke shoulde bée vnwritten, hys head also was pearsed with sharpe thornes. These cruell Iewes put vpon hys heade a Crowne of thornes, and pressed it downe vpon the same,

as harde as they myght presse it by vyolence, beatyng it downe with a strong Réede.
                  Mat. 2
                     •
                  
                
               Et Arundine percuciebant caput eius. And hys blessed heade so Crowned, they dyd beate it downe with a gadde, or a harde Réede. Thus you perceyue that this booke was full of lynes and small Letters, whyche were of dyuers coulers, (as I sayde) some black, some blewe, some reade, some blewyshe, that is to saye, full of stroakes, and lasshes, where by the skynne was toarne, and rente in a thousande places. Besides these small letters, yet was there also greate Capytall Letters precyouslie illumyned with Roset colour: Roset is a reade colour lyke vnto the coulour of a Rose, which colour that most precyous bloude, whiche issued out of his hands and féete, doeth represent vnto vs, with this most precious blud was illumined the fyue great Capital letters in this wonderful booke. I mean by these capital letters ye great woūds of his body, in his handes, and in hys féete, and in his side.
            
               These fyue great woundes were ingraued with sharpe &amp; vyolēt pennes, that is to say, the sharpe nayles, and the speare. And they doe represent vnto vs the fyue capytall Letters of thys booke. Thus then you maye perceyue what bée the boardes of this booke, and what be the leaues, howe it is written within, and without, howe it is lyned and leathered, and what bée the Letters, as well the small as the great. Now wée shall heare what maner of wryting is contayned in thys booke. But first héere, let vs make our prayer for grace, beséechyng almyghtie God, to gyue vnto our hartes the gracyous lyght of his beames, whereby wée may the more clearely perceiue the writings of this booke, and that they may bring foorth some good fruite to our soules health.
            Now you shall heare what wrytings be contayned in thys booke, in the booke which Ezechiel did sée, was written thrée maner of things. Lamē
                  tationes, Carmen, et vae, which is to say, Lamentations, songes, and woe.

And the same thrée things, in lyke maner be wrytten in thys booke of the Crucifixe. Fyrst is lamentation, and this verie conuenientlye is written in thys booke of the Crucyfixe. For whosoeuer will ioye wyth Christ, must fyrst sorow with him. And by sorowe and lamentation hée may come vnto ioye: But hée that will not sorrowe and lament wyth Christ héere in thys lyfe, hée shall come fynallye to the place where is euerlastyng woe, I saye woe that shall neuer haue ende. Héere therfore is written all these thrée, lamentation, songe, and woe.
            Fyrste then wée will speake of lamentation.
            Lamentation aryseth of foure affections, eyther of a great feare, or dreade, or of a great shame, or of some sorrowe, or els of some hatred. When Holophernes with a mightie power was entred into ye countrey of Iurie, &amp; terribly threatned to distroy all before hym, the people were in a greate feare and dreade to be oppressed, and so fell downe before

almyghtie God, and with great lamentation, dyd call for hys helpe, omnius populus cetidit in faciē,
               
                  Iudith. 4. 
               adorantes dominum cum lamentatione et fletu, all the people fell on theyr faces, worshyppyng our Lorde with wéepyng and lamentation.
            The cause of this lamentation, was the great dreade whych they were in. Héere first then let vs learne to dread, and doubtlesse thou Christian soule, thou mayest héere learne greater matter of dread, then the Iewes then were in. For the Iewes then were onelye in perill of temporall death, thou arte in perill of euerlastyng death.
            Consider man how gréeuouslie thou hast sinned: And also behold how gréeuously sinne was reuenged, and punished in the blessed bodye of Christ. And thou shalt anon fynde here great cause and matter of dread. The storyes telleth of Cambises the King of Persia, yt where one of hys Iudges had giuen a false and a wrong iudgement, he depriued him of hys offyce, and made an other in his place their

Iudge after him. Furthermore bicause of hys falsehoode he caused him to be slayne, and his skinne to be hanged vp before the place of the commen iudgement, to the entent that this newe Iudge beholdyng ye gréeuous punishment of his predecessor, might beware of falshood, and alway dread to giue any wrong iudgement. In like maner ye Image of the Crucifix is hunge vp in euery Church, to the entent that we may sée how gréeuouslie sinne was punyshed in that moste blessed bodye of our Sauyour Christ Iesu, not for him self, nor for hys owne sinne, but for ours was he thus cruellye intreated, wée were the cause, wée committed the sinne. But yet neuerthelesse he bare the paynes, and burthens of our sinnes vpon his backe.
            As wryteth Sainct Peter, Peccata nostra ipse pertulit in corpore suo super ligium crucis.
               1. Peter. 2▪
                And therefore when we behold the Image of the Crucifixe in anye place set vp, we should thynke howe gréeuously sinne was punyshed in the body of our sauiour Christ.
            
               And there by learne to dreade the gréeuous punishment of sinne. (Alas) man thynkest thou not, that thys was matter of dreade. This I say, that the verie sonne of God, was for thy sinne put vnto thys cruell death of the Crosse: If thou beléeue not thys, thou arte worse then the dyuylles▪ For as Sainct Iames sayeth, demones credunt et contremiscunt,
               
                  
                     
                        ••
                     cob. 2. the diuilles doe beléeue, and tremble. And if thou verely beléeue it, thou mayest thereby thynke and learne howe muche our sauyour and hys father both doeth hate sinne. For sith almightie God the father woulde gyue hys moste dearely beloued sonne vnto suche an horrible death, onely for to quenche and to extincte sinne, thou mayest bée sure that he hateth sinne very much.
            Our Sauyour also must néedes hate sinne when hée rather would suffer thys moste vyllanous death, then that sinne shoulde haue domynion vpon our soules, séeyng then that thou knowest that bothe they hate sinne? Howe shouldest thou dreade

to receue any sinne into thy soule. If sinne were so displeasant to almighty God the father, that rather then hée would suffer it, he would giue his owne sonne vnto death for the expulsion of it. How much rather now doth it displease him, when his sonne hath suffered death therfore, and yet sinne rayneth neuerthelesse, and more generally then euer it dyd before. Furthermore, if sinne was so greuously punished in him that neuer did sinne, how bytterly shall it be punished in thée O sinfull creature, the which haste done so many great outragious sinnes. Surely wher he hath one nayle in his handes &amp; féete, thou sinfull creature hast deserued one hū
               dreth. And for euery one thorne, that he suffred in his head, thou hast deserued a thousande. And for euery one lash that he felt of the scourges, thou art worthy to haue innumerable. Who yt déepely considerith this that I haue sayde, and with an earnest study resorteth often to looke vppon this booke I maruell if he doo not fynde here in, great cause and earnest matter

of dread.
            Here also may euery sinner quicken his sinne, if any be within hist breast, for it is maruell that a sinner can wt out shame beholde this blessed Image? If a sinner call to remembrance his great vnkyndnesse, &amp; repute the same vnkyndenes any maner of vice, I trow that he wylbe much ashamed of his moste vnkynde and vngentle dealing against so louing a Lorde. Say to me thou sinful creature, wilt thou not looke that other men, when thou haste béene vnto them in anye thinge beneficiall, I saye, wylt thou not looke that they shall be kynde and louing vnto thée againe? And if any person be vnkynde vnto thée, wylt thou not rebuke him fully, and lay it vnto his reproofe to make him ashamed thereof? I am suer that thou wylt. Now then let me sée, wher is thy shame? beholde and vew euery part of this blessed body, what payne it endured for thy sake?
            Séest thou not his eyes, how they bée fylled with blood and bytter teares?

Séest thou not his eares, how they be filled with blasphemous rebukes, and obprobrious words?
            His chéeke &amp; necke with buffets, his shoulders with ye burthen of ye crosse? Séest thou not his mouth, how in his dryghnesse they would haue filled it with Asell and Gaule?
            Séest thou not, how his backe is payned against the hard Crosse?
            Séest thou not his sydes, how they were skourged with sharpe whyps? Séest thou not his armes, how they were strayned by the violence of the ropes?
            
               
                  〈◊〉
                thou not his handes, how they be nailed iust vnto ye crosse? Séest thou not his legges, how they be wearyed with labour?
            Séest thou not his féete, how paynefully they stay and bere vp the wight of his whole body?
            O moste vnkinde sinner, all this he suffred for thy sake. No greater kyndes euer was, or could be shewed to thée by any creature, then this which swéete Iesus dyd shewe for thée and for thy sake, &amp; wher is now

thy kindenes againe?
            No kyndnesse thou canst shewe, but much vnkyndnesse thou haste often shewed vnto him, and yet thou art not ashamed. Alas man where is thy shame? Thincke with thy selfe how many abhominable sinnes thou hast done against his pleasure. I doo a certayne thée that the least of them stryketh him more paynefully vnto the hart then any vnkyndnesse that euer was done vnto thée in all thy lyfe. For as Sainct Barnerd sayth in the person of Christ, when he hath rehersed all ye gréeuous paynes of his passion, he putteth vnto these wordes, Extat interius plauctus pregrauior, quum te ingratum experior, that is to say, but inwardly mourning is much more greuous bicause I perceue thou arte to me so much vnkynd. So many sinnes so much vnkyndnesse. And the more haynous, and the more accustomable that they bée, the more abhominable is thyne vnkyndenesse.
            If the least of many of thy sinnes had come to lyght, and to the knowledge of men, thou wouldest haue béene

sore ashamed of them, Christ knoweth them, and saw thée doo them, for Omnia vnda et aperta sunt oculis eius,
               
                  Heb. 4▪
                All thinges be naked and open before his eyes: and yet thou art not ashamed of all thy vnkinddes.
            Alas man, heare what the King and Prophet sayth,
                  Psal. 43. 
               Tota die verecundia mea cōtra me est, et confusio faciei meae cooperuit me, All the day long my shame is before mée, and my face is couered with confusion. Thus sayd this holy Kinge, when our sauiour as yet had not suffered his passion for him. This high poynte of kindenesse was not as yet shewed vnto this man by our sauiour Christ, and he neuerthelesse was ashamed of his sinne. Thou hast peraduenture done much more outragious sinne, and hast béen much more vnkynde after this his moste wonderfull passion suffered for thy sake, then euer that king was, &amp; that also maketh thy sinne much more horryble. Thou hast after thy promise made vnto him, falsified the same promise and vntruely broken it, by multiplying of many foule and abhominable

sinz, &amp; by oftē renewing of ye same Thou dyddest promise once at the sacramēt of baptisme to kéepe thy fayth &amp; trueth vnto thy sauiour, &amp; to forsake the diuel &amp; all his works? An honest man, or an honest woman would be much ashamed to brek their promise, &amp; specially to theyr friend? Albeit the worlde is now full of such lorrells, yt doo no more regard to break their promise, thē for to drīk whē they be drye. How often hast thou broken thy promise? Alas man learn to be ashamed and saye with the Prophet Esdras, Deus meus, cōfundor et erubesco leuare faciem meam quoniam iniquitates nostrae leuatae sunt super caput nostrum,
               
                  
                     •
                  . Esdr
                        •
                     ea. 8 that is to say, O my god I am confounden and ashamed to lyft vp my face vnto thée, for our sinnes be rysen far aboue our heads. Ye women when there is any black spot in your faces, or any moole in your kerchiues, or any myer vpon your clothes, be you not ashamed? yes forsooth syr? But I shall tell you, where of you ought to be ashamed. Surely if your sowls haue any spots of deadly sinne in them, for when our

sauiour so dearely with his most precious bloud, &amp; with all these gréeuous paynes dyd wash and wype, &amp; clense our soules from euery spot of deadly sinne, ye should be much ashamed to defyle them againe? If you be ashamed for a foule myrie shoo, and not of a foule stincking soule, ye make more dearer your shooes, then your soules. If ye be ashamed of a spot in your clothes &amp; haue no shame for many great blots in your soules. What shal I say but Frons meretricis facta est tibi,
               
                  Iere. 3. 
               noluiste erubescere, that is to say, thou hast takē vpon thée the face of a brothell, thou wylt not be ashamed. If yu then depely consider how many shameful blots of sinne be in thy soule, before ye eyes of almightie God, &amp; all the glorious court of heauen, &amp; how by them thou hast vtterly broken thy promise vnto god, &amp; cōmitted so great vnkindnes against this moste louing charitie, that was shewed vnto thée for thy loue &amp; for thy sake by our sauiour on ye crosse I suppose thou shalt fynde matter, &amp; cause of great shame, if any sparkle of honesty be yet left in thy soule?

Thirdly thou maist here take matter inough of sorrow, for here your sauiour pitiously cryeth &amp; complayneth of his great sorrowes, saying, O vos omnes qui transitis per viam attendite et videte si est dolor similis sicut dolor meus.
               
                  Lamen. Hier. ca. 1. All ye that passe foorth by, take héede &amp; sée whether any sorrow was euer lyke vnto myne. Alas to sée so noble a man, so gentle, &amp; so innocent, so cruelly intreated in euery parte of his most delicate body. And to here him so pitiously complayninge, who shall not be sory? surely none, except hys hart be harder then any flynte stone or Adamant stone. These same foure poynts alone may suffice to styrre any gentle hart to sorrowe. I say his excelent noblenesse, his innocēcie, the crueltie that he dyd suffer, and his pitious complayning.
            If thou saw (O Christiā man) thyne enimie thus mangled and wounded, it might styrre thée to take compassiō vpon him? If thou sawe any Iew or Sarazin thus tormented, it mighte moue thée to pittie? But much rather to sée thy Lord, thy sauiour, and for

thy sake thus cruelly entreated, thus with out any pittie crucified, and payned, hanging on a crosse, should moue thée to compassion. For say to me, for whome supposest thou that our sauyour Christe Iesus suffered all those gréeuous paines? surely for thy sinne, Pro impijs Christus mortuus est.
               
                  Rom. 
                  
                     ••
                  
                For sinners Christ Iesus died, there was no cause but sinne. Thy sinne was the cause of his death. Thy sinne gaue him his deathes wound. O sinful creature, how much cause hast thou for to be sory. For thy sinne was the roote &amp; foūtayne of all his sorrow, &amp; yet thou ceasest not dayly by thy sin to encrese his sorrow. O what floud of teares dyd the blessed Magdalene shed, remembring hir gréeuous sinne. She firste conceiued a great dread in hir soule for hir sinne. Secondly, she was greatly ashamed of hir abhominacyons, with in hir soule, for she regarded much more the inward shame of hir conscience, then ye outward shame of the world. And therfore she let not in the presence of many persons to come to the féete of our sauiour, &amp; to

shewe hyr selfe a sinner. And there tooke great sorrow, and wept ful bitterly for hyr sinne. Thus after dread and shame followed hyr sorrow. And when had shée this dread, shame, and sorrow? truely before that our sauiour hung on the crosse? yet she knew not that hir sin was cause &amp; occasion of his most cruell death.
            But when shée sawe him hange so painfully on the Crosse, and considered that for hir sin he suffered all the paynes, hir harte was then so full of sorrow that for very payne it myght haue brast.
            O thou sinfull creature? If thou can not sorrow, come learne of thys blessed woman, to sorrow for thy sin. Thinke that thy sinne was the cause and occasion of all this payne and sorrow, that thy Lorde and sauiour dyd suffer on the Crosse.
            And not onely she giueth ye example of sorrowe, but his blessed mother abundantly thē sorowed at his death. Sainct Iohn sorrowed, Sainct Peter sorrowed and wepte bitterly.
                  Luke. 2. All the Apostles were in sorrow.
            
               But wherevnto speake I of reasonable creatures, the vnreasonable, and the vnsensible creatures shewes a maner of sorrowe. The earth quaked.
                  Math. 27 The mighty stones brast in sunder. The monuments opened, ye dead courses issued out of theyr monuments.
            All these were moued with compassion. And onely thou wretched sinner, for whose cause he suffred all this paine and gréeuance, hast no pitie nor compassion vpon him.
            (Alas) howe great is thy hardnesse? Howe obstinate is thy harte, that will suffer no pittie to enter in to it? Uerely, thou arte more harder then are the stones? for they were moued by his passyon, so myghtely that they brake in sunder.
            
               Petrae scissae sunt.
               
                  Math. 27. When then the harde stones, and all the other vnreasonable creatures were thus moued, and stirred to take some compassyon of the paynfull death of Christ, and yet felt no profite by his death.
            
               Thou much rather shouldest be moued, for whose loue he dyd endure all this gréeuous pains. Looke thou therfore vpō this booke, &amp; thou shalt here fynde great cause &amp; matter of sorrow. Fourthly, if thou canst not sorrowe, yet thou maiest here learne to hate. Thou maiste learne to hate sinne, which was cause of all this trouble. It is not for nought that ye scripture sayth,21. 
               Quasi a facie colubri fuge peccatū, dentes leonis, dentes eius interficientis animas hominum. Flée from sinne euen as thou wouldest flée from the face of an Adder, for as the téeth of the Lion deuoureth ye body of man, so death doth sleay their soules. Sinne is so odious, and so great an iniury to god, that it was necessary for the recompence of this iniury, yt the sonne of god should suffer this most paineful death of the crosse. Sinne so prouoked almightie god ye father so déeply to displeasure, &amp; wrath, &amp; to take vengance vpon sinners that without the sacrifice of his owne sonne in ye gybbet of the crosse, he wold not be appeased, ne recōciled vnto sinners againe. Sinne so deadly

wounded &amp; blotted the soule of man, that with out shedding of ye most precious bloud of our sauiour Christ Iesu, no lyfe could be restored vnto sinners, nor the soules might be washed from the fowle abhominable corruption of sinne.
            Sinne so debarreth and shutteth frō sinners ye gates of heauen, that they might not haue béene opened, but only by the merit of this moste bytter passion, &amp; suffering this most painfull torments on the crosse. Sinne set the gates of hell so wyde open, &amp; brought all this world into that daunger, and thraldome of the diuell, that all we should haue béene deuowred of the pyt of hell, vnlesse we had béene raū
               somed with this most precious treasure, that was shed for vs on ye crosse-O sinful creature hast thou not great cause to hate sinne, that hath brought thée into that miserable cōdicion, that by thy sinne thou hast done, and committed high iniurie against almighty god, and hast prouoked him to vengeaunce. That by thy sinne, thou hast thus mortally wounded thyne owne

soule. That by sin, thou haste brought thy selfe into the daunger of the dyuill, and be dampned in hell perpetually. That by thy sinne thou hast shut the gates of heauē against thy selfe. (Alas) man where canst thou fynde greater occasion of hatred.
            If thy neyghbour doe vnto thée but a lyght iniurie, thou canst anon hate him, yea, and so hate him, that thou wilt say thou mayest not finde in thy harte to loue him.
            Sinne hathe done vnto thée, all these great iniuries, and yet thou loueste sinne and canste not hate it?
            (Alas) what madnesse is this? Ioab sayde vnto Kyng Dauid,
                  
                     •
                  . Reg. 19. 
               dilegis odientes te, et odio habes diligentis te.
            
            Thou loueste them that hate thée, and thou hatest them that loue thée. The same worde may well be sayde vnto euery sinner that followeth the course of sinne. And lykewyse vyce doeth procure the dystruction of sinners, and yet the sinners doe follow after them.
            
               Our sauiour with all grace &amp; vertue procureth ye saluation of sinners, but him they will not heare, nor take any wayes after his counsayle. And this is nothing els but an extreame madnesse, for they should contrarywyse loue our sauiour, that so louingly for theyr weale indured the gréeuous paynes of the Crosse, and hate the diuill and sinne which was the very cause of death.
            By thys then you may perceyue that in this booke ye may fynde matter inough of lamentation, sith you may read in this booke so much cause of dread, of shame, of sorrow, and of hatred. And this is the first wryting wherof we promised for to speake.
            The secōd writing that I said was also writtē in this booke, was Carmē, that is to say, Songe. Surely if eyther loue or hope, or ioye, or comfort, wil make a soule to sing, here he may take great occasion to sing.
            Fyrst here is great matter of loue, and so great, that if any person will eyther gyue hys loue fréely, or els for some certayne pryce sell it, hée

that died on the crosse, is best worthy to haue it. If thou search in heauen, &amp; in earth one person vpon whom thou maist best bestowe thy loue. Thou shalt fynde none comparable vnto Christ Iesus, so wyse, so myghty, so gentle, so kynde, so amyable, far passing all other, and there to he is much desirous of thy loue, for when Moyses had rehearsed the great benifites which almightie God had giuen vnto man,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   10. he sayth, Et nunc audi quid dominus deus tuus requirat a te, nisi vt diligas eū. Now here what thy Lord God dooth require of thy parte, truely but that thou loue him.
            So now if thou wylt fréely giue thy loue thou canst not more wysely, nor better bestow it then vpon him which is so excelent and hath all the condicions aboue saide, and there to also is so desirous to haue thy loue.
            And if thou wylt sel thy loue, I trow there is none that wyl giue vnto thée more liberally for the same than he hath done. Where shalt thou finde him that wyll shedde one droppe

of bloud out of his harte for thy sake. Where shalte thou finde hym that will giue hys owne soule and lyfe for thy loue. There can no more bée asked of any man then that,
                  Iohn. 1
                     •
                  . 
               Maiorem charitatem nemo habet nisi vt animam suam ponat quis pro amicis suis. No man can shewe greater charitie, then for to put hys owne life in ieopardie for his friendes.
            But thou peraduenture wilt say, Syr if he had done this for me alone, I had béene bounde then to haue gyuen him my loue whollye agayne?
            Why man arte thou so enuyous, that thou wouldest haue no parteners, of this moste precious deathe with thée, but thine owne selfe? This were a very malicious desire to exclude all other, &amp; specially when thy profite and merite shall not be mynished.
            Albeit, there bée neuer so manye besides, that take commoditie there by. I say vnto thée O man, and I assure thée that as fruitefully hée dyed for thée (if thou wilt dispose thy selfe to be partener of this death) as if there

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
had beene no more, but thy selfe in all thys world. Truth it is, there bée many moe besides thée, that bée parteners of this death. But all they, yea, &amp; if there were a thousand thousande tymes innumerable moe then there be. All that multitude shall nothyng mynish any one crum of merit of this most blessed death belongyng vnto thée. And agayne, if thou take much more fruite thereof, then any one of them, yet shall they take no impayrement, or receyue the lesse bicause thou hast so much.
            Wilte thou sée by some example that thys is trueth that I nowe say?
            When thou séest a torch lyght in an house where many persons bée, doeth not that torche gyue as muche light to them all, as if there were but one person there? Euery person after the quicknesse of theyr sight, taketh more or lesse profitte of that lyght, then doeth an other, but yet he that taketh more, hyndereth hys fellowes nothyng in so takyng, nor he yt taketh lesse giueth thereby anye

occasion for his fellowes to take any more. And if it be thus of the light of a torche, muche rather it is so of the merite of this most gracyous death, and of this most precious blud, which by the reason of the godhead abundauntly suffyseth for the redemption of innumerable soules, were theyr sinnes neuer so many, neuer so horrible, neuer so abhominable. Surely as Sainct Iohn sayth, ipse est propitiatio pro peccatis nostris,
               1. Iohn. 2
                     •
                  
                
               non pro nostris tantum sed et totius mundi. Hée was and is a sacrifice abundantly sufficyent, for the sinnes of all this world.
            When then for thy sake, &amp; for thy loue, he suffered thys most horryble death, which was so painfull that the onely remembraunce of it made him to sweate bloudy sweate, and that in so great aboundance that it trickled downe by hys syde vnto the ground. If the onely thinking of thys death was so painfull, howe paynefull was the suffring of ye same in déede. Howe might he more euidētly expresse vnto thée, ye loue of his harte, then by thys means. Or what might he more haue

done for thy loue, as he saith himself, quid vltra facere debui, et non faci, what myght I further haue done, whiche I did not for thy loue.
            Thou mayest then fynde héere in this booke great matter of loue.
            Héere is also great matter of hope, &amp; specially to sinners &amp; will vtterly forsake their sinne, and amend theyr liues for Christ Iesu sake. Doubtles for such he suffered this moste bitter death.
                  Rom. 5. 
               Pro impijs Christus mortuus est, for wicked sinners Iesus Christ dyed. And in an other place, ye same s. Paul sayth.2. Tim. 1. 
               Christus Iesus venit in hunc mundū saluos facere peccatores. Christe Iesus came into this world for to saue sinners that will amend theyr lyues.
            O christian soule take thou vpon thée, the crosse of pennaunce, and bée crucyfied with him, &amp; then without doubt thou shalt be partener of the the merit of his crucifying, and of his most fruitfull passion.
            What shall exclude thée from hys merite?
                  Rom. 8. Almightie God the father? Nay, qui proprio filio suo non peporcit, sed pro nobis omnibus tradidit illum, quomodo

non cum illo nobis omnia donauit. He that dyd not spare his own sonne, but gaue him vnto the death for vs all, what shall hée denye vs? what greater euidence canst thou aske? that almightie God the father wil forgiue thy sin, then thys that he would not forsake to giue vnto the death hys own sonne, I say his own most dearly beloued sonne of whom hée sayde, Hic est filius meus dilectus in quo mihi cō
                  placui.
               2. Pet. 
                  
                     •
                  . This is my welbeloued sonne in whom is all my pleasure. What greater euydence and proofe mayest thou desire, that he will forgyue thy sinne, then yt he would put this most inestimable Iuell into such a daunger for thy sake, and sende it vnto thys most painfull and shamefull, and sorrowfull death of the Crosse.
            But peraduenture thou thynkest that our sauiour bycause thou haste bin so vnkynde vnto him, will not receyue thée vnto his mercy? I say therfore forsake thy sinne, and accuse thy vnkyndnesse, and be sory for it. And doubt not but he will forgiue &amp; forget thyne vnkyndnesse, and receyue

thée agayne vnto hys great mercy.
            And therfore he sayth by his Prophet Hieremie, when a woman (saith he) is gone from hyr husbande, and hath accompanyed hyr bodye with an other man, will hyr husband receiue hir againe? As who say, that it is not verie lyke, but yet heare what comforte he giueth to a sinner,
                  Hiere. 3. 
               tu autem fornicata es cum amatoribus multis tamen reuertere ad me et ego suscipiam te. Neuerthelesse (he sayeth to the soule of a sinner.) Albeit, thou hast forsaken me and playde the brothell with manye other, yet returne thou agayne vnto mée, and I shall receyue thée. But here, thou sinfull soule deceyue not thy selfe. Thou mayest dissemble a returning, and be not in déede returned. And if thou set not thy backe toward all sinne, and turne thy harte fully vnto thy sauiour, thou arte not returned. But bée thou truly returned and doubt not.
            Beholde earnestly the maner how thy sauiour Iesu hanged on ye Crosse, and thou shalt sée great cause of hope of his mercy if thou thus returne.

Sainct Barnerd sayth. Quis non rapiatur ad 
                     •
                  pem, impetrandique fiduciam, quā do considerat corporis cius dispositionem, caput inclinatum ad osculum, brachia extenta ad amplexandum, manus proforatas ad largiendum, latus opertum ad diligendū pedum confixionem ad manendum nobiscum corporis extensionem ad se nobis totaliter impendendum. Who may not bée rauished to hope and confidence, if he consider ye order of his body, his head bowing downe to offer a kisse, hys armes spreade to embrace vs, hys handes bored thorow to make lyberall giftes, his side opened to shewe vnto vs the loue of his harte, his féete fastened with nayles, that hée shall not starte away but abyde with vs. And all his bodie stretched, forcesing him selfe to giue it wholly vnto vs. Surely O man, he that would thus and after this maner exhibite his bodie vnto thée on the Crosse, (if thou wilt indeuer thée vpon thy parte, hée will not refuse thée, but take thée vnto his mercy.
            This most precious bloud yt he shed on the Crosse, cryeth alwayes mercye for sinners, that doe thus rereturne.

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
And therefore Sainct Paule sayeth.
                  Hebr. 12. 
               Accessistis ad sanguinem melius loquentem quam Abel. Ye become, and haue returned you vnto the bloude, that speaketh more graciously, then did the bloude of Abell. The bloud of Abell cryed vengeaunce before almightie God. As almightie God sayd vnto Caine in the booke of Genesis, Sanguis Abell fratris tui clamat ad me vindictam de terra.
               
                  Gen. 4. The bloude of thy brother Abell crieth vengeaunce in mine eares from the grounde where it is shead.
            But the moste precious bloude of our sauiour Iesu Christ cryeth mercy for all sinners that doeth repent. And our sauiour now before ye face of hys father sheweth his woundes, &amp; sheweth his most precious bloud, &amp; ceaseth not to procure mercy for them.
            This plainly doeth affyrme ye blessed Apostle Saint Iohn saying in this maner,
                  
                     •
                  . Iohn. 2. 
               filioli hec scribo vobis vt non peccatis, sed et si quis peccauerit aduocatū habemus apud patrem Iesu Christum iustum et ipse, est propitiatio pro peccatis nostris. That is to say, Childrē I write these

things vnto you, to the intent that you should not sinne. Neuerthelesse if it fortune any man to sinne, wée haue an aduocate for vs Christ Iesus, before ye face of his father. And he is rightuous, and without sinne, &amp; a verye satisfaction for al our sinnes. Who thē attentiuely doth beholde this Crucifix, &amp; verely beleueth that on the Crosse was payd the raūsom of all sinners, how may he not fully trust that if he aske mercy for his sinnes, they shall be forgiuen him. So that here euery sinner may finde great matter and occasion of hope. In the Crosse is also matter of ioy. Héere is occasion of such excessiue ioy, that a soule which verely tasteth it, can not but highly reioyce in the same. And therfore Sainct Paule did say Mihi autem absit gloriari nisi in cruce domini Iesu Christi,
               
                  Gala. 
                  
                     •
                  . God forbid that I reioyce in any other thing then in the Crosse of our Lorde Iesu Christ. Here doubtlesse is great cause for euerye true Christian man to reioyce, and specially for thrée poyntes.
            The first is that by the death of our sauiour on the Crosse, and sheding of his moste precious bloude on the Crosse we be fully reconciled to almighty God,

as often as we doe true repentaunce, with a fast purpose of amendement. Thus Saint Paule sayth, ad Col Complacuit per eum reconciliari omnia in ipsum per sanguinem cruicis. It hath pleased God the father, that by his sonne and by his bloud shed on the Crosse all should be reconciled.
            But you will aske me what meaneth this word reconciled? It is as much to sai, as to be made attone with almighty God and to be at friendship with hym. As two men when they haue bene at variaunce to be made louers together againe. So the displeasure which he had against vs for our sinne, is taken away. And his great wrath against vs is fully pacified. And where we were by sin the children of the diuell, now we haue recouered to be made againe the children of God, and consequentlye the inheritours of heauen.
            O thou Christian man is not here great cause to reioyce.
            If thou haue a ritche man to thy father which had loued thée much, and he for thy misdemaner had caste thée out from his fauour, and so thou werte in

ieopardie to lose thy enherytaunce, if by meanes of a brother of thine thou mightest be brought into his fauour againe, and be taken for his sonne as thou waste before and restored thereby to thine enheritance, haddeste thou not great cause to be ioyous and reioyce, that by this means, thou hast recouered againe thy fathers loue, with all the commodities belonging vnto the same? In like manner it is of euery sinner, for he by his lewde demainer and by his sinful dealing hath so displeased his father, that he is cast out from the fauour of his father, and is in perrill to lose his inherytaunce, which his most louing father had prouided for hym.
            Neuerthelesse his onelye begotten sonne by his inestimable goodnesse and charitie suffering the most painful death of the Crosse, and shedding his most precyous bloude for amendes and recompence of our vngracious dealinge, hath reconcyled vs agayne, and made vs at one with his father, and set vs at a perfecte peace, concorde, and vnytie. And thys is concernynge the fyrste poynte.
            
               The second by the vertue of the crosse, and of his most blessed passyon, ye power of our enymies be much broken, for on the Crosse our sauyour by his death gatt the victory vpō thē, for the which Sainct Paule saide, expolians principatus et potestates traduxit confidenter, triumphans cos in seme tipso.
               
                  Col. 2
                     •
                  
                Christ Iesus spoiling ye mighty power of the diuill, hath openly detected theyr frauds, and gotten a very triumph of them in his owne person. And therfore nothing is yet more tirrible vnto them, then is the signe of the Crosse. A blessed virgine sainct Christian had suche a confidence in the token of the Crosse, that when shée féelt hyr selfe tempted with hyr ghostly enimy, shée marked hyr selfe with the same token, and at euery temptation shée gatte the better of the diuils. And by this holy token chased thē away, &amp; put euer to flight. Thirdli by the vertue of the crosse, &amp; of this most fruitful death, our hand wryting the which made most against vs, was clerly put out. Whē where was it written? In the booke of our owne conscience, there is no maner of sinne that we doe, but it is written in the booke of our consciēce. And if we repent vs not of the same, &amp; be hartily sory

for it before our death, thys booke of our conscience shal be shewed against vs in ye dreadfull day of iudgement. Neuerthelesse if we repent vs and confesse vs, and doe true repentance therfore, then by the vertue of this passion it shall be scraped out of the booke of our conscience. Therfore Sainct Paule calleth sinne our own hand writing,
                  Col. 2. 
               Deleuit quod aduersū nos erat chirographum decreti quod erat contrarium nobis, et ipsū tulit de medio affigens illud cruci. Christ Iesus (he saith) put out the hande writing of ye decrée whiche was against vs, and so withdrewe it fastning it vnto the Crosse. When thou perceiuest (O sinfull creature) that by the Crosse of Christ, and by that most precious bloud which was shed on the crosse thou art reconciled and made at one with God, and that the power of thine enimies be greatly represt. And fynallly that thy sin which was most against thée was crucified on the same Crosse, so that thou maist clearely sée that héere is great matter of excessiue ioy and to reioyce in the most blessed Crucifix.
            Finally in the Crosse is also matter of great comfort, when a person hath deserued a great open shame, &amp; is broght

euen to the plunge of the matter, and yet by the meanes of helpe he is deliuered from the same, is not this his deliuerance from this open shame, a comforte vnto hym? yes doubtlesse?
            The noble woman Susanna, as the Prophet Daniell telleth,
                  Daniel. 17. all be it she was giltlesse, yet for because she woulde not assent to the wretched desyre of two lewde priestes, she was by them wrongfully accused, and put to great shame, for they wrongfully slaundered hir, that she had taken an other man besides hir husband, and that she had committed adulterye. Neuerthelesse, when the matter was tryed by the goodnes of almightye God, and she was clearelye discharged from this terrible occasion, and clearely deliuered frō this shame, it was a great comfort vnto hir.
            
               
                  Luke. 7.The blessed Magdalen which by hir wretched liuing had deserud great shāe, yet when she came to our sauiour Christ and wept at his féete, and so by his great mercy was excused of hir shame, hir hart was set at a great rest, &amp; in great cōforte. The woman of whom the gospel telleth, yt was taken in aduoutery by hir enimies &amp; so brought before our sauiour Christ,
                  Psal. 21 &amp;

there in his presence, &amp; before al his people, hir shamfull dealing was published, who may think but yt she was sore accō
               bred with that open shame, but yet whē our souiour had confounded hir enimies and deliuered hir from yt shame, she was restored to much ease and comfort of hyr hart. Why tel I this? Truly to the intent that we may sée great matter of cō
               fort in the Crosse, for we sinners haue deserued great shame for our abhominable sinne, surelye so great that if we verely knew the greatnes of the shame, that we haue deserued, we might neuer sustaine the remembraunce therof. And yet that moste inestimable goodnesse of Christ by that horyble shame that he suffered on the Crosse, deliuered vs from euerlasting shame. He toke ther vpon hys back all the burthen of our sinne. There wanted no circumstances of horryble shame, for then the death of the Crosse was the most shamefull maner of death, that was put to any villaine. It was thē the most vilanous death to be hāged on ye gebbit of the Crosse. And this was done in no secret place, but high vppon an open mountaine, that all the people might behoulde and looke vppon hym.

And he was hāged ther naked &amp; betwéen two théeues as though he were a prince and captaine of misdoers. And against ye feast of Easter, when the most number of people did assemble vnto ye temple of ye Iewes,
                  Ezech. 16. nigh vnto the Citie of Ierusalem, that all the people might commodiouslye resort to gase vppon this cruell spectacle. This thing was done also in the open day, for from the midst of the day he thus did hang aliue on the Crosse by the space of thrée howres and more. And al the strangers as they passed foreby did wonder vpon him. The souldiers opprobryously rebuked him. The priests with wordes of derision and mockerye assaulted him. The théeues that honge besides him blasphemed him. Finally al his enimes reioyced in their victorye against him. Alas what creature mighte be more shamefully intreated, then was our sauiour christ Iesus hanging thus on the Crosse. A troth it is, now the Crosse is made honorable by his death, but then as I said,
                  Psalm. 31. it was more shameful then anie gibbet or gallows, or any other instrument of death. And moreouer, and besides that he was hanged on the same with the most dispight and villany th
                  ••
               
               
could be thought or deuised for any creature to be put vnto. O thou christian soule, Christ Iesus the sonne of God tooke vpon him al this shame, for thy loue, to ye entent that if thou wilt amend thy life, and forsake thy sin and do true penance, thou shalt by his shame be deliuered frō al shame. His shame shall hide thy sins. Hée was there naked and spoyled of all his cloathes, to the intent yt thou shouldest be couered vnder his mantle fro thy shame. And therfore by the prophet Ezechiell he saith, Expādi amittum meum super 
                     〈◊〉
                  , et operui ignominiam tuam. I did spred my mantle vpon thée, and so couered thée from shame. Let euery persō héere think wt them selues what déedes they haue done worthie of great shame, which if they had come to light and bene openlye knowne, thei should haue bene blotted wt opē infamye here in this lyfe, and with out the special mercy of god in the day of iudgement they shoulde thereof haue an open shame before all the world, and fyfally in hell an euerlasting shame. But from al those shames by ye gracious mantle of Christ many bée couered. Hée hath mercifully spred his mantle ouer them, and kept them from those importable

shames. Of this couering also the Prophet Dauid sayth, Beati quorum tecta sunt peccata. Blessed are those whose sinnes be couered. O thou sinfull creature, if thou mightst see what shame thou hast deserued for thy sinne, thou shouldest recken this a singular comfort. But thou séest not the abhominacion of thy sin, and therfore thou perceyuest not what shame thou hast deserued. Why doeth a common brothel take no shame of hir abhomination? what is the cause, why that shée regardeth hyr infamye no more? Truely as far as I can iudge, the cause is for that al the light of honestie is quē
               ched in hyr, shée is so blynded with hyr wretched pleasure that shée is paste all shame, and hath not left in hir one sparke of ye light of honestye, where by shée may value &amp; estéeme ye horriblenesse of hir offences. Shée reputeth more a litle spote in hir kyrchefe, or in hir face, thē a thousād blots of deadly sin in hir soule. But if she had any honesty wtin hir hart to think how foule &amp; abhominable hir lif were, surely she wold be much ashamd of hir self.
            Thamar the daughter of King Dauid, whē hir brother Amon wold haue oprest hir,2 Reg▪
                   13. she sayde. Noli facere hanc stulticiam, ego

enim ferre non potero opprobrium meum. O my brother saide she, doe not this folly, for this reproch that ye inforce to do vnto me is greater then I may suffer. This woman had some light of honestye, within her brest, whereby she was moued to resist, and to withstande this shamefull déede batwéene hir and hir brother.
            A Romane woman also, whose name was Lucretia, whom by force &amp; againste hir wil in the absence of hir husband, one mā called Sextus Tarquinius, had abused hir, albeit the thinge was 
                  〈◊〉
               , yet she was there of so muche as
                  •
               amed in hir owne mind that she might not beare the shame. But when hir husband came home, she tooke a knife and in his presēce slew hir selfe. This noble woman had the light of honesty in hir soule, she sawe how abhominable a thing it was to commit adultery. But a brothell hath in hir no spark of honesty wherby she can take any shame, nor she doth not consider the foule abhomynacion of, hir wretched life, and therefore she is shamles. And in like maner euery sinner, yt lacketh ye light of faith, neither considereth ye greatnes of his sinne, nor the presence of almightye God, which looketh vpon the same.

He regardeth nothing the blessed Angels the which doth behold the
                  •
                abhominable conscience, to their great discomfort, nor the deuilles his mortal enimies which be ful ioyous of his shameful demainer. If the sinner clearely considered al these thinges, (as they be matter in very déed) he would be doubtlesse greatly ashamed of him selfe, and in a great discomforte. Neuerthelesse a penitent soule, yt is sore prest and wrong with vtter shame, lyke as was the womē of whō I spake before I meane Susanna and Mary Magdalen, &amp; the woman that was apprehended in aduoutry. I say such a soule being holdē in such distresse of shame, and cōsidering that by the approbrious and shamefull death, which our sauiour did suffer on ye Crosse. He that deliuered all true penitēt sinners, from the shame which he deserued for their sinne, and that he there by tooke all their sinne in hys owne necke, hath great cause (as me séemeth) to take a wonderful comforte in the most blessed Crosse. So yt here also (as I said) is great matter &amp; cause of very comfort, &amp; of solace incomparable. Wherefore to conclude my tale as touching this second writing, if eyther loue, or hope, or ioy, or comfort

wil make vs sing. Here in thys booke of the Crucifixe is great occasion of song. If thou first truly lament with Christ, thou shalt after ioyfully sing with him, and eche of these shal induce other, hatred of sinne shall bring into thy harte the loue of Christ, dreade shall bring in hope, sorow shal bring in ioy. And shame here taken for thy sin, shal bringe into thy soule perpetuall comfort. And thus much I haue sayde for the second writing.
            The thyrde wrytinge that is written in this booke, I sayde is ve, that is to say wo, ve betokeneth in scriptures euerlasting dampnation. And doubtlesse this woe may such sinners here reade, that neither wil lament, nor sing with Christ on the Crosse, as hée said vnto the Iews Cecinimus vobis et non saltastis, lamentauimus vobis et non planxistis, that is to saye,
                  Mat. 
                  
                     ••
                  . we sunge vnto you, and you sorrowed not. And soone after the Gospell telleth, that he reprochfully spake vnto ye cities, to ye whiche he had shewed many great myracles. And they for all that did no maner of pennaunce for theyr sinne, to such there he tirribly threatneth saying, Vae tibi Corozaine, Vae tibi Bethsaida,
               
                  Mat. 11. wo shal

be to thée Bethsaida, by thys we maye learne that such whiche will not stir in them selues these affections aboue rehearsed, whereby they may lament, or els singe with Christ on the Crosse they shall come to euerlasting woe.
            I say who that will not stir in theyr hartes, dreade, shame, sorrowe, and hatred, of theyr sinne, and so truely lament with Iesu, eyther els quicken in theyr hartes loue, hope, reioysing, and comfort and so singe with Iesu, doubtlesse they shall come to the wo of euerlasting dampnation, which woe is the thirde writinge that as we sayde before is written on the Crosse.
            Behold O thou christian soule ye extreme paines, yt our sauiour suffered on ye crosse, for thy sinne. And if thou wilte not by such aflictions, as I now haue rehearsed enforce thy selfe to be made parteiner of ye same paines in this lyfe, thou shalte in the life to come endure like manner of paines and that euerlastingly where he suffered them on the Crosse for a time. Let vs therefore déepely consider what paines he did endure &amp; suffer on ye crosse. The first, when he was crucified he was spoyled and made naked of al his clothes.

And so violently throwne downe vppon the hard tymber, and his handes &amp; féete cruelly digged in with nailes, as he sayeth in the 21. Psalme. Foderunt manus meas et pedes meos,
               
                  Io. 
                  
                     •
                  . they haue digged my handes and my féete, this he suffered for thy sinne O sinfull creature, and if thou wilt not amend thy life be times, thou shalt be spoyled of all thy clothes, and so cast downe into hell, vpon a more painefull couch, then was the Crosse. The Prophet Esay saith vnto such a sinner. Subtus te seruatur timea et opera mentum tuum verinis.
               
                  Esay. 14. The mothes that shall teare and gnaw thy body, shall lie vnder thée acd the burninge wormes and serpents shal sprale aboue thée &amp; dig away part of thy body. O think what an horrible paine it were for to lye in a bed full of snakes, adders, and todes, créepinge and sprawling, and byting, and pinching thée on euery parte.
            The seconde, when our sauiour was reared vp aloft on the Crosse, that same hanging there was very paynefull vnto him, O what payne was it vnto that most delicate and tender bodye of hys to hange so longe in that tormentrye. But where he did hange here but for a

time, if yu amende not thy life, thou sh
                  •••
                hang in the gibbet of hell for euermore. For be thou well assured that if thou shalt suffer for thine owne sinne in hell, thou shalte suffer a more gréeuous tormentry then he dyd, &amp; that without seasing. For as it is sayd in the Apocalipses, fumus tormentorum ascendet in secula seculorum,
               
                  Apoca. 14. the smoke of the tormentries of that place shall ascende by innumerable worlds, that is to say without ende. The tormentes which he suffered on the Crosse, was the nayles, the thornes, the rops, the schourges, the speare. But ye torments that thou shalt suffer, shal a thousande folde passe them. Looke howe far the mallice and wit of the diuils passeth the mallice and witte of the Iewes, so farre excéede the engynes which the diuilles haue cōceiued and forged for the dampned soules to be tormented. Aboue them that ye Iewes maliciously deuysed agaynst our sauiour Christ. The thyrd, our sauiour endured an extreme heate, &amp; feruour, when he for the great afflictiō &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                agony whiche he did suffer, was cō
               strained for yt gréeuous anguish to sweat water &amp; blud. But this heat is nothing to ye heat of the burnyng fyre of hell which

neuer shall be quenched, Ignis ille non extinguetur, As the gospell sayth, that fyre shall neuer be quenched. The Prophet Esay sayeth, Quis ex vobis poterit habitare cum ardoribus sempiternis which of you may continually inhabite with the heates that neuer shal cease.
            O sinfull creature thinke with thy self ye largenes of these two wordes. Euer and neuer, thinke with thy self howe paynefull it shall be euer to be in that brenning fyre, and neuer to be released of thy payne.
            If thou shouldest be compelled to lye but one sennight vpon a softe featherbed, I suppose thou wouldest be weary thereof. But how weary shalt thou be euer to lye stewing and brenning without ceasing.
            The fourth, our sauiour Christ endured also colde not onely for his nakednesse, but also when his naturall heate by death, lefte his bodye. But the dampned sinner shal endure in hell a more excessyue colde. Iob sayth of such, transibunt ab aquis niuis ad calorem nimirem, they shall be shyfred

out of ye colde snow brought into the outragious heates. O Iesus, a tender hand wherin ye froste and snowe it hath bene made extreme colde and sodenly is brought into the heate of the fier, it féeleth a greater payne, but nothynge comparable vnto that shyfting from that colde into that heate whych is in hell.
            The fift, our sauior in his crosse hard blasphemous &amp; opprobrious words, and much insultinge of his enimies against him, which doubtles was very paynefull vnto him. But the damned sinners shall in hel heare nothīg els but continual outcryes, opprobrious insulting, blasphemes of the diuells and other that be dampned. Blasphemabunt deum caeli doloribus, they shall blaspheme the god of heauen for continuall paine and sorrowes. And they shall sée before their faces continually the most horrible and ireful countenaūce of their immortal enimies the diuells.
            The vi. our sauiour wept on ye crosse for ye sinnes of other, as s. Paul saith, cū clamore et lachimis,
               
                  Heb. 5. with crying &amp; teres

but the damned sinners that would not here wepe wt Christ, such teares as might washe theyr sinnes, shall wepe in hell for theyr owne sinnes, such teares as shall skalde theyr bodies, and yet they shalbe neuer the better. Ibi erit flectus et stridor dentium, Ther shal be wéeping &amp; gnashing of teeth,
                  Math. 22. the smoke of ye Fyer shal make them for to wéepe, &amp; the coldenesse of the snow shal make their téeth for to gnashe, &amp; chytter in theyr heades. Yea and that is more merueilous, neither the colde shall attemper the heate, nor contrarywyse, the heate shall attemper the colde, but eyther of them shall encrease the violence of the other. Euen as in the forge of a Smith, the colde water when it is cast into the Fyer, causeth the Fyer to be much more fearse and violent. The seuēth, our sauiour on the crosse had extrem drighnes, for ye which he cōplained &amp; said, Scitio, I am dry, And no maruell though he wer dry, after so much payne and trauayle, after so much bléeding &amp; sweting, wherby no moisture almost was left in his bodi.

But howe vnmeasurable drighnesse shall ye dampned soules endure in the fyre of hell? The rich glutton yt was buried in hel teacheth vs what drighnesse is there, for he would haue gyuen all this worlde to haue had one drop of water or lycour to haue refreshed his tongue, that was made so drye with the flame of that fyre.
            The eight, our sauiour on ye crosse had much sorrow and heauinesse. If he for the onely remembrance of the paine for to come was in so great an agony that he sweat water &amp; bloud, who can expresse or think what sorrow and heauinesse he suffred when all the paynes were present, &amp; presently did oppresse hym. Neuerthelesse euery dampned person, by the reason of their continuall and euerlasting paynes shall haue muche more sorrow and heauinesse, for the which it is writtē in the booke of Sapience, penitentiam Agentes et pretristitia spiritus gementes, they verely lamentably repent them selues, and for extreame heauinesse of spirite mourne and sorrowe, thinking, for howe briefe and

transitory pleasures, they loste the ioyes euerlasting, and gate ye paynes that euer shall endure.
            The ninth, our sauiour on ye crosse did suffer muche infamy and shame. And specially to deliuer (as I said all sinners that would amēd thē selues, and forsake their sinne,) from euerlasting shame. But such as will not, shall suffer theyr owne shame, as they haue deserued. The true penytent soule shall bée sacyate with perpetuall glory, But he that will not repent him selfe shall haue perpetuall shame and infamy.
            Almightie God sayeth, to suche by his Prophet Naum, Reuelabo pudenda tua in facie tua. I wil make open all thy shamefulnesse and euill dealyng in thine owne face. And the Prophet Hieremy sayeth, saturabitur opprobrijs
               ▪ he shall bée sacyate with opprobryous shame.
            The tenth, aboue all other paynes that our sauyour dyd suffer on the Crosse, was to be desolate of all comforte, yea of his father, and to bée as a person forsaken of almightie God,

and destitute of all help and succour, for the which hée sore complayneth on his Crosse, crying vnto his father Deus meus Deus meus, vt quid dereliquistī me, O my God, O my God, why hast thou forsakē me. But this forsaking was but for a season, for within a short time after, he was raised again to immortall glory. But the dampned sinners which shall be punished for their owne sinnes in hell, shall euer be forsaken, and fully be depryued, not onely from all ioye &amp; comforte, but from that moste glorious sighte of the face of almighty God, wherein standeth all blessednesse and consummation of all comforte. And this shall more pinche the dampned soules, then all the other tormentes of hell besides. For the which Chrisostome sayth. Ego autem multo grauiores cruciatus duco, quam gehenuam, remoueri et ab duci ab illa gloria. I think (saith he) that to be remoued and cast out from that euerlastyng glory, is more gréeuous torments then all the other paynes of hell.
            
               Fynally, our sauiour on the crosse, suffered the paynes of death for our sinnes, whereby wée had deserued death. And therfore he suffered death to deliuer vs from the death of sinne. Neuerthelesse he remayned no long tyme in the bondes of death. But the dampned sinner that must paye his owne debtes in hell, shal suffer euerlasting death, not so that the sinners shal haue no lyfe nor féeling in them, but bycause that they shall be euer as though they were in the extreme paynes of death, and yet they shall haue no perfecte sense of the paynes, and neuer dye. The paynes shall be to them so vyolent, that they shall perish a thousand tymes, and desire cō
               tinually for to dye, but death shal flie away from them, desiderabunt mori et mors fugie ab eis, they shal desire death, and death shall fly from them. O Iesu in what myserie shall they be in, that euer shall couet death, and neuer may fully dye.
            The Prophet Dauid speaking of their payne sayeth. Mors depascet eos,
               
which words may haue thrée senses, one is that death shall bée their pastour and heardman, hée shall order them, and leade them to theyr pastures. In hell is two pastures, the one is all full of snow, the other full of fyre, for the whiche Iobe sayeth, Ad calorem nimium transient ab aquis niuium, they shal walke from the snow vnto the fyre. And agayne from the fyre vnto the snow, this may be one sense, an other may be this, they shal be the continuall meate of death, as ye sée in the pastures, where ye shéepe féede. They croppe the grasse euer as it ryseth and kéepeth it lowe, and so the grasse is euer in eatyng, and neuer full eaten.
            In lyke maner death shall continually croppe the dampned persons in hell. And he shall euer be gnawyng and eating vpon them, and yet they shall neuer be fully consumed. The third sense may be this, death shall be theyr continuall meate, for they shall euer long and desire for to dye, they shal euer aboue all other things couet to haue death, and their desire

shall alway be a lyke freshe and feruent. An other comforte and refresshing besides this, they shall haue none, but whatsoeuer the sense of these wordes be, thou mayest well perceyue by them. O thou christian soule) that if thou shalt come to that place to pay thy debtes of thine own sinnes, it shall bée to gréeuous and to importable for thée to sustayne, for as I sayde, looke any maner of paine that our sauiour Christ suffered on the crosse for all our sinnes. If wée be not before our death by such affections (as I before did rehearse) made perteyners of his sufferyng, we shall suffer all the same paynes in hel perpetually.
            And therefore it is a troth, we may read in the booke of the Crucifix great matter of woe, whiche is the thyrde wryting that we had to speake off. Now thou sinful creature, haue oftē before thyne eyes thys wonderfull booke which as I sayde is wrytten within and with out. In the which also thou mayest reade thrée maner of wrytings, that is to say, lamentation,

song, and wo. If thou wilt begin to lament with Iesu, thou shalt therby come to sing with him. And therby thou shalt be made so fully parteiner of his passion, that the debtes of thy sinnes shall be throughly payde, and that thou shalt escape euerlasting woe. But if thou doe refuse this remedy, and follow the desires of thys world, and of the fleshe, be thou well assured that then thou shalt pay thine owne debtes amongest the diuils in hell, with euerlasting woe. From the which he defend vs, that for our loue as this day suffered on the Crosse, his most paynfull and sorrowfull death, our sauiour Christ Iesus. Amen.
            Per Iohannem Fyssher Episcopum Rofensem.
            
               Memoria crucifixi: vitia crucifigit. Grego Quecumque momorderit astucia sathanae aspiciat Christum inligno pendentē August
            
            
         
      
   

