
   
      
         
            A learned sermon preached before the King at VVhitehall, on Friday the 16 of March: by M. Doctor Field: Chaplaine to his Maiestie
            Learned sermon preached before the King at Whitehall, on Friday the 16 of March.
            Field, Richard, 1561-1616.
         
         
            
               1604
            
         
         Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00726
            STC 10855
            ESTC S115098
            99850317
            99850317
            15508
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00726)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15508)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 795:06)
         
         
            
               
                  A learned sermon preached before the King at VVhitehall, on Friday the 16 of March: by M. Doctor Field: Chaplaine to his Maiestie
                  Learned sermon preached before the King at Whitehall, on Friday the 16 of March.
                  Field, Richard, 1561-1616.
               
               [44] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iames Roberts, for Ieffry Chorlton,
                  At London :
                  1604.
               
               
                  First leaf blank?.
                  Signatures: A-B C⁶.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-09
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2004-09
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A Learned Sermon preached before the King at VVhitehall, on Friday the 16 of March: by M. Doctor Field: Chaplaine to his Maiestie.
            At London, Printed by Iames Roberts, for Ieffry Chorlton. 1604.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               Iude. verse. 3.
                ¶ Beloued, when I gaue all diligence, to write vnto you of the common saluation, it was necessarie for me to write vnto you, to exhort you, that you should earnestly contend for the maintenance of the Faith, vvhich was once deliuered vnto the Saints.
            
            THE blessed Apostle Saint Iude, finding that many in his time began well, and ended ill, who beeing seduced by wicked miscreants made shipwracke of the fayth, forsooke their first loue, departed away from the liuing GOD, and embraced this present world: writeth this his Epistle generall to the Christians of those times, to strengthen the vveake, confirme the doubtfull, and stay such as were ready to fall.
            The argument whereof is contained in these words, which I haue now read in

your hearing; wherein three thinges are to be obserued. First, he maketh knowne vnto them his loue: in that he calleth them his beloued. Secondly, his carefull and diligent study and endeuour, not onely by word being present, but also by writing beeing absent, to procure their euerlasting good, and to direct them to the attayning of eternall saluation, in that he professeth, he gaue all diligence to write vnto them of the common saluation: Thirdlie he sheweth, what it was, that in those his carefull deliberations (how he might most happily worke their eternall good) he found most necessary to write vnto them of. It was necessary for me to write vnto you to exhort you to contende &amp;c. Of these thinges in order, as they lie in the words of the Apostle, &amp; first of the first, which is his loue.
            
            Many and great are the things Almightie God requireth of them, whom he appointeth Rulers and Gouernours ouer his people. For as he communicateth vnto them part of his owne honour, giueth them his owne tytles, setteth them vpon his owne seate, committeth

the care of his people vnto them, and trusteth them with the execution of his owne iustice and iudgement, so he requireth of them, and putteth in them a spirit of more, then ordinary wisedom, courage, and magnanimitie, fit to sustaine and beare the weight of so great a burthen. But aboue all he requireth of them a tender and louing affection towards his people, of whom they take the charge, that they seeke not their owne priuate pleasure, profit, or content, but the good of them ouer whom they are set.
            And as this is required generally of all Rulers, so most principally of them, to vvhom the Word of reconciliation, the dispensation of the Diuine mysteries, and the power of the keyes of the kingdome of heauen is committed. This our Sauiour shewed by his manner of proceeding, and the course he tooke, when hauing accomplished the worke of redemption, and being ready to returne back to him, that sent him, he resolued to send out his Apostles with most ample Commission for the gathering

of the Saints, the worke of the Ministerie, and the conuersion of such, as he had bought &amp; purchased with his most precious blood. For though he had made choyce of such men for that imployment, as had beene conuersant with him in the dayes of his flesh, seene his miracles and workes of wonder, and heard the words of his heauenly wisedome, and were most fit to be witnesses of all the things he did and suffered, and to publish the ioyfull tydings of saluation to the people of the world, yet would 
                  ••
                giue them no Commission, till he vvere assured of their loue. And therefore, though he had promised to builde his Church on Peters fayth and ministerie,Math. 16. and to giue vnto him the keyes of the kingdome of Heauen, yet before he performed this promise, and said vnto him,Iohn, 21. 
               Feed my lambes, feede my sheepe, he demaunded thrice of him concerning his loue. Neither doth he aske him of his loue towards them, he was to take charge of, but of his loue towards himselfe, thereby the more to enforce it, and raise it to a higher degree, as if he had

thus said: If I haue de
                  •
               erued any thing of thee, if my death and bitter sufferings deserue thy loue, if thou owest any thing vnto me for the benefits of the heauenly calling, the knowledge of that truth, which flesh and blood could not reueale vnto thee, and the dignitie of an Apostle, wherewith I haue honoured thee, as (I say vn
                  •
               to thee) thou owest more then thy selfe: turne the course of thy loue vpon the people of my purchase: for they are the inheritance my Father gaue me, vvhen I came into the worlde, the reward of my labours, the recompence of my trauailes, and the price of my blood: for their sakes I left my throne in Heauen, put off my robe of Maiestie, and put vppon me the habite of a seruaunt, they are my Temple, in which I am worshipped, my Church, in the middest wherof my Name is called vppon, my spouse, whom my soule loueth, and my body, with out which I am not complete and full.
            An example of this loue, which God requireth of vs, himselfe gaue vs, when he loued vs, and gaue his Sonne for vs,

whiles we were yet his enemies. An e
                  •
               
               ample hereof Christ shewed vs, when he poured forth his soule in bitter passions, to redeeme his people from theyr sinnes. An imitation of these examples in the highest degree, that euer was founde amongst mortall men, we haue in Moses, that desired to haue his name blotted out of the booke of life, rather then GOD should be dishonoured, or his people destroyed: and in Pa
                     •
                  ule, who wished to be Anathema from the Lord Iesus, for the Iewes his brethren and kinsmen according to the flesh. A portion, degree, and measure of this loue, resteth vpon all the true seruaunts of God, whence it commeth that so often, when they speake vnto the people of God, they call them beloued. So much of the Apostles loue. His diligence follovveth.
            
               Diligence or studie, is an intentiue fixing of the minde on some one thing much esteemed, and respected. The diligence of the Apostles, and Apostolike men in the worke of the Ministry, the gathering of the Saints, and procuring the euerlasting good, and eternall saluation

of Gods people appeareth in three thinges; the multiplicitie of the thinges, they do for the working of this intended good: the sedulitie in doing them: and the diuers manner of doing of them.
            Touching the first: who can expresse the varietie of the things, they do for the good of them, whom GOD hath committed to theyr charge? They teach the ignorant, convince them that erre, seeke them that are lost, bring backe them that are ou
                  •
                of the way, heale the sicke, binde vp the broken harted, comfort the heauy, &amp; such as are deiected with sorrow, they strengthen the weake, confirme the doubtful, stay them that are ready to fall, and raise vp them that are fallen.
            This multiplicity of endeuours, to procure the good of Gods people, we shall find in the blessed Apostle Saint Paule more, then in all the rest: who though he vvere the last, and esteemed himselfe the least, and not woorthy to be named an Apostle; yet laboured he more, then all they, who sometimes disputeth, sometimes exhorteth, sometimes commaundeth, sometimes entreateth, sometimes

counselleth, sometimes threatneth, sometimes promiseth, sometimes terrifyeth, &amp; sometimes comforteth; sometimes commeth in the Spirit of meeknes, &amp; sometimes with a rodde in his hand, calleth backe some, as beeing out of the way, encourageth others, &amp; maketh himselfe one of their companie, as beeing in a good way: some he calleth his ioy, his crowne &amp; glorie, and to some he obiects folly &amp; madnes; to some he giueth milk, to some strong meat: sometimes he proscribeth and banisheth from the Church, sometimes he confirmeth his loue towards the same againe. These are the diuers &amp; different things the Apostles and Apostolike men doe for the good of Gods people.
            Now as theyr diligence appeareth in this varietie, and multiplicitie of things they do, so likewise in theyr sedulitie in doing them, in that they doe them in season, and out of season; and in the different manner of doing them, in that they perfome them by vvord being present, and by Letters being absent. The Apostle Saint Iude, desiring to benefite

the vvhole Christian Church, (vvith all the parts whereof it was not possible for him to be present) sheweth his diligence in vvryting: It was necessarie for me to vvrite vnto you. VVhere we are occasioned to speake first of vrryting in generall: and secondly of sacred vvryting, &amp; and the obiect of it.
            Great and inestimable is the benefit of writing, for by it all the treasures of wisedome, pietie, vertue, and learning, that euer God poured forth vpon the sonnes of men, are communicated to posterities. By it we may commune withall the Patriarches, Prophets, Apostles, Martyrs, Confessors, Fathers of the Church (the lights and wonders of the world) that euer were; and whensoeuer any doubt ariseth and troubleth our mindes, we may call a greater &amp; more generall Councell, then either Constantine, Theodosi
                     •
                  s, or any of the Romane Emperours either did, or could doe.
            The benefit of writing will appeare to be the greater, if we compare them, who (being renow
                  •
               ed for wisdome and learning) neuer wrote any thing, (as Pythagoras

Socrates and others, of whom very few things remaine) with Plato, Aristotle, and the like, that committed the treasures of their learning, and wisedome to writing, who, being dead long since, yet liue, and are the great Maisters of the world euen vnto this day. Hence it is that no treasure was anciently, nor is presently esteemed greater, then the holy library of the church; in which respect the Romanistes deserue exceeding ill, that did formerly, &amp; doe presently adulterate the monuments of antiquitie, and leaue nothing sincere, and vncorrupt, as their manifold forgeries in former times, their Index expurgatorius and other like practises of these times make it too plaine
            This beeing noted in generall touching the benefit of writing, let vs come to the more especiall consideration of sacred writing and the obiect of it. In the Apostles times men admired their writings, but despised their words, and personall presence, as not being accompanied with that greatnes, they looked for. His letters say they (speaking of the blessed Apostle Saint Paule that trumpet of

the Gospell, and 
                  ••
               ood of Christian elo
               
                  •
               uence) are peremptory, and full of au
               
                  •
               horitie and power, but his wordes, and 
                  •
               ersonall presence weake, vile, and con
               
                  •
               emptible.
            But now contrariwise the Romanistes 
               
                  •
               egarde not their writings, but magnifie 
                  •
               heir words, deliuered by tradition, char
               
                  •
               ing their writings with obscuritie, insuf
               
                  ••
               ciency, and imperfection, comparing 
                  •
               hem to a shipmans hose, a nose of wax. Lesbian rule; affirming that but fewe 
                  •
               hings were written, non vt praeessent, sed v
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  bessent fidei nostrae, not to commaund &amp; 
                  •
               uer-rule our faith, but to be ouer-ruled 
                  •
               y it; that the Apostles receaued a com
               
                  •
               andement to preach, but none to writ; 
                  •
               hat they meant not to compose a perfect worke, containing the rule of our faith, but wrote onely occasionally, as they 
                  •
               ere entreated, or as the particular ne
               
                  ••
               ssities of the Churches did require.
            This their censure of the diuine Scrip
               
                  ••
               res is iniurious, in that they thinke them 
                  ••
                be so obscure, and the sence, and mea
               
                  •
               ing of them so vncertaine, and doub
                  •
               
               
               
                  •
               ull, that wicked men may wrest and abuse

them, according to their owne pleasures, &amp; no man be able to repro
                  •
               e and conuince them by the euidence and for
                  ••
                of the Scriptures themselues: Impious
                     •••
                  
                that they thinke they proceeded from the priuate motions of the Apostles and Euangelists, without the immediate and special instinct, motion, &amp; commaund o
                  •
                the spirit of truth: Inconsiderate in tha
                  •
                they thinke the men of God entende
                  •
                not to compose a perfect work.
            The absurditie of which conceipt wi
                  ••
                appeare, if they will but take a view 
                  ••
                the bookes themselues, they haue le
                  •
                vnto vs. For the writings of the Euangelists containe a perfect history of the things Christ did, and suffered from the time of his birth, till the time he w
                  ••
                assumed into Heauen. The Actes 
               
                  ••
                the Apostles, the comming of the holy Ghost, &amp; the planting of the Churche
                  •
                after Christes ascension. The Epistles, t
                  ••
                clearing of the questions, and doub
                  ••
                which troubled the Churches of thos
                  •
                times. And the Reuelation, a prophes
                  ••
                of the future state of things, to the e
                  ••
                of the world.
            
               The obiect of these sacred writings is Saluation. Three things are deliuered vnto vs in the bookes of God, the creation, the fall, &amp; the restauration &amp; saluation of man. Saluation is the preseruation from those dangers &amp; deliuerance from those eternall euils we were subiect vnto by the fall. This is the greatest benefit that euer God bestowed on men, and the principall matter and obiect of the diuine Scriptures. For we might with Iob curse the day of our birth, wish the knees had neuer receaued vs, the armes neuer embraced vs, nor the pappes giuen vs suck, that the wombe had bin ourgraue, and that we had bin like the vntimely fruite, 
                  •
               hat neuer sawe the Sunne; that the Mountaines would fall vppon vs, the Rockes cleaue in sunder, and the de
               
                  •
               ouring Gulfes swallow vs vp; that we might cease to be, and bee as if we had 
                  •
               euer beene, if wee had no part in the saluation mentioned in this place.
            Behold sayth Gregorie Nazianzen magnifying this benefit of saluation) in 
                  •
               he creation God gaue vs the best things 
                  •
               e had, when as yet we had nothing, but

in the restauration hee maketh an exchange with vs, he taketh the worst we haue, and giueth vs the best he hath▪ he taketh our nature, and giueth vs his grace, he taketh our sinne and giueth vs his righteousnes, he taketh our curse and giueth vs his blessing, he taketh our misery and giueth vs his happines, he taketh our death and giueth vs his life, he humbleth himselfe and exalteth vs.
            This Saluation is sayd to bee common, not as if all men of how vile condition and wicked conuersation soeuer should be partakers of it. For the Apostle Saint Paule protesteth against this frensie, saying. Knowe you not that the vnrighteous shall not inherit the Kingdome of God? And againe, bee not deceaued, neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor wantons, nor couetous persons, nor extortioners shall inherit the Kingdome of God.
            
            Touching this matter there were foure dangerous errors in the primitiue, Church: the first of Origen who thought that all (euen the deuils themselues) after certaine reuolutions of times shall 
                  〈◊〉
                saued: the second of them, who not daring

               
                  •
               ing to proceed so farre as Origen did, 
                  •
               et thought, that all men shall in the end be saued, as by fire. The third, that not 
                  •
               ll men, but all Christian men, notwith
               
                  •
               tanding whatsoeuer wickednes, Schis
               
                  •
               e or Heresie shall in the end bee saued. The fourth, that not all Christians, but 
                  •
               ll Catholique, Or
                  •
               hodoxe, and right 
                  •
               eleuing Christians shall in the end bee 
                  •
               ued, as by fire, holding the foundati
               
                  •
               n of a right profession. This last error 
                  •
               any of the fathers fell into, as appeareth 
                  •
               y very pregnant places in Hierome, and 
                  •
               hers tending to that purpose, and by 
                  
                     •
                  ustines owne confession, where hee 
                  •
               riteth against it, calling it a mercifull 
                  •
               ror of some Catholique diuine.
            Against this error Austine opposeth himselfe,August: de ciuitat: dei de fid: et oper: In enchir: ad Laur: but very fearfully; professing, 
                  〈◊〉
                he will not peremptorilie denie, but at a mitigation or suspension of the 
                  ••
               nishments of the wicked may be ob
               
                  ••
               ned after they are departed out of this 
                  ••
               rld, so that their punishments bee 
                  •
               nfessed to be eternall. And if this will 
                  ••
                satisfie them, from whom he is vn
               
                  •
               ling to dissent, he sayth that though

men professing the faith, being wholy wicked and voyde of loue, cannot bee saued, as by fire, but must perish eternally, yet hee dareth not deny but that men, that doe beleiue aright, and haue loue (though mingled with much imperfection) may bee saued by a kinde 
                  ••
                purging fire after this life, which whether it be so, or not he cannot tell.
            Thus wee see in what sort Austine was driuen vpon the opinion of purgatory, and how doubtfully he speaketh 
                  ••
                it, yet was he the first that euer spake 
                  ••
                this kinde of purgatorie in the Churc
                  •
                of God. So doubtfull a beginning ha
                  ••
                this article of the Romanistes faith, wh
                  ••
                yet rest not in the iudgment of this f
                  •
               
               ther, that only some lighter sinnes a
                  •
                wasted, and consumed away in this pu
                  •
               
               ging fire, but imagine that the iusticed God in it is satisfied, and the punishme
                  ••
                of mortall sinnes suffered (the faul
                  •
               , an
                  •
                not the punishment being remitted 
                  〈◊〉
                this life) which things Austine ne
                  •
                dream
                  •
                of.
            But to returne to the wordes of the Apostle; Saluation is sayde to be comm
                     ••
                  
               
               
               
                  •
                absolute vnto all, but vnto them that 
                  •
               re called, and sanctified of GOD, and 
                  •
               serued in Christ Iesus.
            As in nature the best things, &amp; things 
                  •
               f necessitie, are eyther absolutely and 
                  •
               qually, or at least in some mediocritie 
                  •
               mmon vnto all, but thinges of orna
               
                  •
               ent &amp; delight, are proper to some few
                  •
                
               
                  •
                is it in the matter of fayth, and saluati
               
                  ••
               . Among the things of nature, vvhat better, then ayre, fire, water, earth, 
                  •
               owers of raine, the fruites of the fielde, 
                  •
               uses to dwell in, garments to put on, 
                  •
               alth and strength of bodie, length of 
                  •
               yes, comely proportion, and statu
                  •
               e body, quicknes of sence, sharpnes of 
                  ••
               , and faithfulnes of memory, the vse 
                  ••
               d benefit of these is in some sort com
               
                  •
               on vnto all, and the poore man often 
                  •
               oyeth them with more contentment, 
                  •
               n the rich: neyther is there any man 
                  •
               nd to be so great a Tyrant, as to de
               
                  •
                to enioy these common benefits a
               
                  ••
               : but gold, pearles, precious stones, 
                  •
               t aray, and thinges of that kinde, are 
                  〈◊〉
                peculiar lot, &amp; portion of some few. likewise in the matter of fayth, and

grace, the Law, the Prophets, the couenaunts of Grace, the sufferings of Ch
                  •
               ist, regeneration, the Gospell, the giuing of the Spirit, Faith, Hope, Loue, and eternall Saluation are common vnto all, that are called, and sanctified of GOD, no
                  •
                as Manna in a certaine measure, but euery one taketh as much of them as he
                  •
                will: the gyfts of tongues, myracles, prophecie, the degrees of ministerie, &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                like, are proper to some few.
            VVhen the Law was giuen vppo
                  •
                Mount Sina, Moses, &amp; the Elders on
                  •
               
               ly went vp, the people (though prep
                  •
               
               red and sanctified to meete the Lorde had boundes set vnto them, and mig
                  ••
                not so much as touch the Mountaine Moses only entred into the clowde, co
                  •
               
               muned with GOD, and receiued fro
                  •
                him the tables of the Law; but vvh
                  •
                
               Moses came downe from God, the La
                  •
                the Couenaunts, the Sacrifices, cerem
                  •
               
               nies, and all that Moses learned of Go
                  •
                was imparted and communicated to 
                  〈◊〉
                the people.
            Thus much of the Apostles diligen
                  ••
                in writing. The matter whereof he w
                  ••
               
               teth,

followeth, It was necessary, for me to writ vnto you to exhort you to contend. &amp;c. In the matter, whereunto the Apostle exhorteth them, three things are to be obserued. For first they must contend, secondly they must contend earnestly, thirdly they must contend for the maintenance of the faith. It may seeme a thing very needles to exhort men to contend. For the world is and euer was to full of contentions. The contentions of Christians haue scandalized many, they haue beene the cause of the ouerthrow of many famous Churches; and the remouing of those golden Candlestickes, in the midst whereof the Sonne of God some
               
                  •
               ime walked. So that all good men disswade from contentions, and seeke to extinguish the flames of that fire, which hath alreadie wasted, and burnt downe so many, &amp; so worthy parts of the house of God.
            
               Austine vnderstanding of the bitter invectiues,Epist. 15. that Hierome and Ruffinus had published one against another, breaketh forth into these words, expressing the sorrow of his hart: Hei mihi, qui vos

                  
                     •
                  licubi simul inuenire non possum: fortè 
                     •
                   nunc moueor, vt doleo, vt tim
                     ••
                  , pr
                     •
                  cid
                     •
                  
                  rem ad pedes vestros, flerem quantum v
                     •
                  
                  l
                     •
                  rem, rogarem quantum amarem, 
                     〈◊〉
                   vnumquen
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   vestrum pro seipso, nunc vtrum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   pro alterutro, et pro alijs, et m
                     •
                  ximè infirmis, pro quibus Christus mort
                     ••
                  s est, qui vos tanquam in theatro huius v
                     •
                  ta
                     •
                   cum magno suo periculo spectant, ne de vobis ea scribendo spargatis, quae quando
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   concordes delere non poteritis. Woe is me (saith he) that I can no where meet with you two togeather for if I could, as now I stand affected, as I sorrowe for these beginnings, and feare what will be the issues of things so ill begunne, I would fall at 
                     •
                  our feete and weepe till I had dryed vp the Fountaine of teares, I would entreate you so long, as the affection of loue, that raigneth in me, could suggest vnto me one word of entreatie, no
                     •
                   entreating and beseeching each of you for himselfe, now either of you for other, and for others, most of all the weake, for whom Christ dyed, which not without great peri
                     ••
                   behold you in these your contentions, brought vpon the stage of this world to be gazed on, I would entreate you, not to publish those

                  
                     •
                  hings in writing one of another, which hereafter wh
                     •
                  n happily you may be friends, it will 
                     •
                  ot be possible for you to blot out againe.
            
            That we may therefore see, in vvhat sence the Apostle exhorteth to contend, we must obserue, that the thinges, for which men contend, are of three sorts; the first are things indifferent. Such vvas 
                  •
               he contention in the Primitiue Church about fasting on the Saterday, in vvhich obseruation the Church of Rome, and some other Westerne Churches, differed 
                  •
               rom the Churches of the East, vvhich fasted not on that day. Some condemned the Church of Rome in this behalfe, 
                  •
               ut Austine thinketh the matter to be indifferent,Epistle to Cassulanus. and sheweth, that when his Mother Monica came to Milan (where Ambrose was Bishop) where the Saterdayes fast was not kept, and was doubtfull what to doe, Ambrose being consul
               
                  •
               ed, aunswered, she should do as he did. She thinking she must not fast, because 
                  •
               e did not, he replyed, he meant not so: 
                  •
               ut that she should comforme her selfe 
                  •
               o the manner of that Church, where she 
                  •
               hould happen to be, as he in such cases

vsed to do. And Austine addeth, that if in the same. Churches there be different customes, men should follow the example of the principall Pastors.
            This iudgement we take to be much better, then that of the Fathers of the sixt Councell in Trullo, who condemned the Church of Rome (as violating the Apostolike, and auncient custome) in that it fasted on the Saturday. Of this nature was the difference between the East, and West Churches, about consecrating in leauened, or vnleauened bread, dipping, or sprinkling the baptized
                  •
                thrice, o
                  •
                once; and such haue been the contentions of some in our Church, about round and square, white &amp; blacke, sitting, standing, and kneeling. In which thinges if any man list to be contentious, vve say with the Apostle, We haue no such c
                     •
                  
                  stome, neither the Churches of God.
            
            The second kind of things, for which men contend, are things mistaken. An excellent example in this kinde we hau
                  •
                in the Oration of Gregory Nazianzen, in the praise of Athanasius, where he 
                  ••
               
               porteth, that when the Bishop of Ro
                     ••
                  
               
               
and the Bishops of the West Church affirmed, that there is one essence of God, and three persons, and the Easterne Bishops, one essence, and three hypostases, or subsistences, the contention grew so ho
                  •
               e▪ that the whole Christian world was in danger, to be rent in peeces vpon the difference of these syllables. Hierome liuing in the East parts, and being required to acknowledge three hypostases, or subsistences in God, writet
                  •
                to Damasus, intreateth and beseecheth him, per crucifixam mundi salutem, per 
                     •
                  omousion trinitatem, vt sibi 
                     ••
                   Epistolis suis, siue tacendarum, siue dicendarum hypostaseon detur a
                     •
                  
                  thoritas, and protesteth he greatly feareth, least sathan hath transfigured himselfe into an Angell of light. The Grecians iudged the Latines, to be Sabellians, and the Latines the Greekes to be Arrians. Athanasius (that worthy of the vvorld, in whose lappe our wearied Mother the Church did often repose, and lay her head, seeking rest from her forsaken children) in gentle and louing manner interposed himselfe, and examining eyther party, found they meant one &amp; the same

thing. Thus was this diuision composed more easily by friendly mediation, then it would haue beene by writing or disputing, which often rather increase contentions, then end them.
            Of this nature doubtlesse are the differences betweene the Diuines of Germany, Denmarke, Sweden, and other parts embracing the confession of Auspurg
                     •
                  , and the Churches of Heluetia, Fraunce, and other, touching the vbiquitarie presence of Christ, and his presence in the Sacrament, touching the losing, or not losing of grace once had, and touching predestination; in all which I am verili
                  •
                perswaded, if the meaning of each part were fully knowne to other, there would be no difference amongst them.
            For the diuisions of our own Church, our hope is, that by the goodness of God, and the godly care of our gratious Soueraigne, they are now at an end: so that whosoeuer heereafter shall blow the coales, and kindle the fire of that dissention any more, he shall for euer be branded with the note and marke of a turbulen
                  •
               , vnquiet, and factious spirit. Let not

our aduersaries therefore insult vppon vs in respect of our diuisions. For I dare vndertake to proue, there are more reall, &amp; materiall differences amongst them in some one poynt of Christian religion, then amongst all the reformed Churches in all.
            The third sort of things for which men contend, are such as we ought to contend for; to wit, matters of fayth, no part whereof we must betray, how deere so euer the defence of it cost vs. For these things we must contend earnestly. Indifferencie in matters of fayth and religion displeaseth God. If God be God, let vs follow him; if Baall be God let vs follow him. There is no communion betweene light and darknes, righteousnes, and vnrighteousnes, Christ and Beliall, the temple of God, &amp; Idols, and what part hath the beleeuer with the infidell? But it will euer be true, which Christ obserued in his time; the children of this world are wiser in theyr generation, then the children of light. The Pharisees then, the Iesuits and others of that sort now, omit no opportunitie, take all occasions, &amp; compasse

sea &amp; land, to make one Proselyte, to make one of theyr profession, though they make him the childe of hell seauen-fold more, then themselues. But the Orthodoxe and right beleeuing Christians are negligent, and are so farre from gayning, that they lose the aduantages they haue.
            It is obserued, that in the time of the Arrian heresie, at the first the Catholiques had all aduantages on their side, the determination of the Nicen Councell called &amp; confirmed by the royall authoritie of Constantine was for them, and Constantine resolute to suppresse that heresie, and to send into banishment the maintainers of it. The Arrians seeing into what straites they were brought, rested not till they had insin
                  •
               ated themselues into Constantines fauour, and peruerted Constantius the next succeding Emperour, a man the Catholiques might easily haue possessed. There vvere two thinges (as Nazianzen reporteth) tha
                  •
                much disquieted and afflicted his minde at the time of his death, the one, that h
                  ••
                had followed new and strange opinions

in matters of fayth, the other, that he should leaue Iulian a wicked miscreant to succeede him in the Empire.
            But what followed vppon this carefull diligence of the one sort, and securitie &amp; negligence of the other? by the meanes of Constantius the Arrains so preuailed, that in the Councels of Arimmum &amp; Seleucia, the synceritie of the Christian profession (agreed on in the Nicen Councel) was betrayed, all the Bishoppes of the world, (Athanasius, Eusebius, Hilarius, &amp; some very few more, if yet there were any more, excepted) were drawne away and abused by the Arrians. Ingemuit totu
                     ••
                  rbis et miratus est, sefactum esse Arria
                  
                     •
                  um.
            
            In our times, they of the Romish faction by fayre promises, and sweet and sugred words, draw vnto them the choysest wits they find amongst vs, they obserue wherin each man is most likely to excell, and imploy him accordingly, some in writing, some in reading, some in preaching, some in disputing, they haue some for Schoole diuinitie, some for positiue, 
                  •
               ome for the studie of the Fathers, and

courses of antiquitie. But with vs all the
                  •
                things are neglected, and therefore 
                  〈◊〉
                goe before vs, not in the goodnes of 
                  〈◊〉
                cause, but in the good and wise managing of an euill cause. For I dare vndertake that if a choyce be made, and me
                  •
                may haue those helps &amp; encouragemen
                  •
                that are fit for men so imployed, this nationall Church will yeeld men more th
                  ••
                matchable with the greatest of the aduerse faction, in all those courses of learning, wherein they seeme most to excell.
            But to returne to the words of the Apostle, we must contend, not for thinge
                  •
                indifferent, not mistaking one another▪ but for the maintenaunce of the fayth. A
                  ••
                the name of hope, sometimes signifieth the things we hope for, (as when the Apostle saith, If we had hope onely in this life we were of all men the most miserable) sometime the desire and expectation of the same thinges: so the name of fayt
                  •
                sometimes signifieth the act or habite of beleeuing, sometimes that sum of Christian doctrine, the conclusions wherea
                  •
                are not demonstrable by reason, but 
                  〈◊〉
               
               
he belieued by faith. This doctrine of fayth (least we mistake it) is described by two circumstances. It was once deliuered, and it was deliuered to the Saints. It is said to haue been once deliuered, to expresse the difference betweene the manner of the diuine reuelation formely, and since Christ appeared. For before, the heauenly truth was reuealed, not all at once, but in diuers sorts, and degrees, according as the time wherein the reuelation vvas made, was neerer, or more remote from the appearing of Christ, but in the last times God spake by his owne sonne, and b
                  •
                him at once deliuered all that, that shal be knowne concerning himselfe, till the ends of the world. So that we which are Christians must be
                  ••
               eue nothing but that which was deliuered at the first beginning of Christianitie.
            So that the error of the Montanists is to be reiected, which imagined, that Christ reuealed not all the mysteries of his kingdome to Peter, on whom he promised to build his Church, to Iohn, the disciple he 
                  •
               o deerely loued, which leaned on his breast at the mysticall supper, and to the

rest of that blessed company, but reserued many things till the spirit descended vppon Montanus, and his prophetesses: as also the phrensie of those heretickes in Fraunce, which affirmed, that as the Father was author of the old Testament, &amp; the Sonne of the New, so the holy Ghost in the last times must be the author of a third, which is a law of loue, which because it is the last, to continue for euer, &amp; to haue none after it, may (as they suppose) be rightly termed the eternall Gospell, so abusing the place of the reuelations of Saint Iohn.
            
            But passing by these errors of phanaticall and vaine men: in that the faith is said to haue beene once deliuered, we obserue two things; the f
                  •
               rst, that that onelie is true which was deliuered at the first. For howsoeuer many things be more fullie, distinctly, and expresly knowne in latter times then they were formerly, yet they were deliuered at the first infolded in generalities, out of which they are afterwards more distinctly, and expresly deduced, euen as a child, when it is first borne, hath all those parts of body, that

euer after it hath, though not expressed and enlarged as afterwards they are, as Vincentius Lerinensis most aptly noteth.
            Secondly we may obserue, that vvhatsoeuer may be proued to be most auncient, is vndoubtedly true, as being immediatly inspired from the spirit of truth. Quod primum, verissimum: the truth is before the counterfeite, the thing before the imitation of the thing, the habite before priuation, and good before euill: the good seede was first sowed, and then the enuious man came, et superseminauit zizania, and sowed tares, where the good seede was before.
            We deny not therefore, but most willingly graunt vnto our aduersaries, that Antiquitie is a note of the true Church; not as if that Church were alwaies purest, and most vncorrupt, which first re
               
                  •
               eiued the fayth, and hath longest conti
               
                  •
               ued in the profession of it: for then the Aethiopian and Asian Churches, would proue themselues as pure or purer, then 
                  •
               ny Churches in the world: but because 
                  •
               hat is the truest and purest Church, which holdeth that doctrine, and discipline

that was first deliuered.
            The Romanists are wont to stand much vppon this note of Antiquitie, but hovv wil they proue, they haue the faith which was first deliuered. They proue it, because they once had it, and it cannot be shewed, when they departed from it. For aunswer wherevnto we say, that in many things we can shew, when the alteration beganne.Georg▪ Cassa. in praefa. ordi
                  
                     •
                  : Roma: For who knoweth not, that Charles the Emperour with threates, and punishments, forced all the Clergie in the Prouinces subiect vnto him, to forsake the ancient formes of diuine seruice, &amp; publique administration, they had formerly vsed, and to receiue the Romane order; and that the Spanyards (as beeing most stiffe in all theyr courses) held their owne rites, till in the time of Gregory the seauenth, they were forced by Alphonsus the sixt, to leaue them, which they did not without great sorrow expressed with teares.
            And though we could not preciselie note the time, when theyr errors &amp; abuses entered into the Church, yet the consequent were not good, that therefore

they haue not departed from the first and originall puritie. For there are and haue beene many errors in the Church, not onely so iudged by vs, but confessed to be so by them, the precise time of the beginning whereof is not knowne. The opinion of the necessitie of giuing the Sacrament of the Lords body vnto infants,August. d
                     •
                   peccat: rem: and the practice of the same continued in the Latine Church, (as Maldonatus confesseth) sixe hundred yeeres, and is retained in all the Orientall Churches to this day. This was an error, and yet neyther the time when it began, nor the author of it knowne. The opinion, that none shall see GOD, nor enter into heauen till the resurrection, was the error of many of the auncient, yet the author of it, &amp; the time, when it beganne is vnknowne. The opinion of two resurrections the one of the iust, the other of the wicked, (there beeing betweene the one and the other aboue a thousand yeres) was an error amongst the auncient, the Author of 
                  •
               t, and the time when it beganne, is not 
                  •
               nowne.
            To leaue these things that were auncient,

and to come to the things now priuayling in the Church of Rome; it vvas the old custome, that the Sacrament of the Lords body and blood, was giuen to all that were present, at the time of the mysticall blessing, consecration, and operation: all the Catech
                     •
                  meni, poenitents, &amp; not communicants missis, et exclusis, being sent away and excluded: whence the whole mysticall action is called Miss
                     •
                  . This custome continued till the time of Gregory the first, in whose time the Deacon after the reading of the Gospell pronounced those solemne words, si quis non communicat, exeat. This doth Cassander proue at large in his preface before the booke called Ordo Romanus, shevving that many doubted, whether the wordes of the Canon of the Mas
                  •
               e, which imply a communion of the people, may be vsed in priuate Masses. By degrees they fe
                  ••
                from the publique, and solemne communion of the people, &amp; the Clergie alone communicated with the priest. Afterwards, they also (though present) abst
                  ••
               
               ned, and communicated not. VVhe
                  •
                these priuate Masses began, it is no
                  •
               
               
knowne.
            The custome was to giue the sacrament in both kindes to the people (as Lindan proueth) and it was thought necessary, as the booke called Ordo Romanus sheweth: And all the Churches of the east retaine this custome vnto this day. When the halfe communion began it is not knowne. In the time, that Luther began, almost all beleeued and taught, that Mary was conceaued without sinne, and thought it a matter of pietie to be of that iudgement.In 3 sent: dist: 3. quaest: 2. 
               Bonauentura in his time 
                  •
               ime professeth, that he neuer saw the writings of any one, that was of that opinion nor neuer could meet with any one that so thought. Who was the first that 
                  •
               roached this opinion &amp; published it in writing vnto the world, it is hard to 
                  •
               inde.
            Besides all Romish religion standeth of contradictory assertions, as that the Pope may erre, and that he cannot erre, 
                  •
               hat he may depose Princes, and that he may not, that one body may be in many 
                  •
               laces, and that it cannot be in many 
                  •
               laces, the one sort of them denying,

that the other affirmeth: yet is not 
                  〈◊〉
                first author of any of th
                  •
               se contradictory opinions knowne. Thus we see how weakly the Romanistes proue the antiquitie of their faith and religion, whereof they so insolently glory and boast. But le
                  •
                vs leaue them &amp; returne to the words of the Apostle.
            The second circumstance, whereby the doctrine of faith, for which we must contend is noted and described, vnto vs least we should mistake it, is that as it was once deliuered, so it was deliuered to the Saints. So that if we desire to finde the vndoubted truth of Heauenly doctrine we must seeke it, non in confusione paganorum, non in purgamentis haereticorum, non in languore schismaticorum, non in coecitate Iud
                     •
                  orum, not in the confusions of pagan Infidels, not among out cast and forsaken Heretiques, not in the con
                  •
               enticles of Schismatiques, not among the blinde &amp; hard harted Iewes, but amongst those Disciples of Christ Iesus, which cannot be iustly challenged either for innouation, or diuision. According to that in the Canticles, where Christ is inquired

after. Show thou mee O thou whom my soule loueth, where thou 
                     •
                  eedest, and where thou lyest a
                     •
                   noone. For why should I be, as shee that turneth aside to the flockes of thy companions? and immediately he sheweth how he may be found. If thou knowest not O thou the fairest among women, get thee forth by the steps of the flockes, and feed thy kids by the tentes of the shepherdes. In which words we are directed to seeke our Sauiour Christ in the troupes, and companions of Christian people and pastors, which are named Saints in this place by the Apostle, because they are called to sanctification, &amp; haue the happie meanes of it. In these companies we shalbe sure to finde our Sauiour Christ and the doctrine of faith 
                  •
               e left vnto vs, if we haue an eye to them, vppon whom no note of innouation or 
                  •
               iuision may iustly be fastened. So that 
                  •
               f those societies in which we liue haue 
                  •
               orrupted their wayes, and left theyr first 
                  •
               uritie, we must (as Vincentius L
                     •
                  rine
                     •
                  sis 
               
                  •
               irecteth vs) looke to other Churches, &amp; 
                  ••
               st our eyes vp higher, to the times that 
                  •
               ere before vs. For example, in the daies

of our Fathers, they had priuate Ma
                  ••
                halfe communions, and sundry others abuses, the most of the guides of God people taught men to put trust in papall indulgences, and such like lying vanities. Who soeuer doubted and made question of any of these thinges, if they did but cast their eyes vpon the Eastern
                  •
                Churches that then presently were, or the Churches in former times, they might easily find, that in them there was no such thing.
            Thus then in the Church we haue certaine direction to find out the truth, neyther are any other to hope to find it, but such as reuerence her iudgement, &amp; se
                  ••
                it in her communion. Whereupon Ter
                  
                     •
                  ullian pronounceth, that none but such as are so affected, are to be admitted 
                  ••
                any question or dispute of the Scriptures, and matters of fayth: and bringeth in the Church speaking vnto her
                  ••
                tickes, and praescribing against them i
                  •
                this sort: quid agitis in meo, non mei? what do you medling with my things, you that are none of mine? By what right do
                  •
                thou Marcion cut downe my wood

               
                  •
               ho gaue thee leaue Valentinus, to turne 
                  •
               he course of my Fou
                  •
               taines? By vvhat 
                  •
               uthoritie doest thou Apelles remoue 
                  ••
               y auncient bounds? It is my possession, 
                  •
               hat do you here the rest of you, sowing 
                  •
               nd feeding at your owne pleasures? It is 
                  ••
               y possession, I possessed it of old, I 
                  •
               ossessed it before you, I haue the cer
               
                  •
               ine originall of it from them, whose the 
                  •
               hing was, I am the heyre of the Apostles, as they disposed by their last vvill &amp; testament, as they committed it vnto my 
                  ••
               ust, as they adiured me, so I keepe it; 
                  •
               ou they know not, you they disclaimed 
                  •
               nd reiected, as strangers, as enemies.
            This true and Orthodoxe church, which is the onely mistresse of Heauenly truth, maketh vse of them, that erre, to her owne good, and their bettering and correction, if they refuse not her instruc
               
                  •
               ions. Vtitur Gentibus ad materiam ope
                  
                     •
                  ationis suae, haereticis ad probationem doc
                  
                     ••
                  inae suae, schismaticis ad documentum sta
                  
                     ••
                  ilitatis suae, I
                     •
                  daeis ad comparationem pul
                  
                     •
                  hritudimis suae; altos inuitat, alios exclu
                  
                     •
                  it, alios relinquit, alios antecedit: omnibus 
                     •
                  ratiae dei participandae dat potestatē, siue 
                     •
                  lli

informandi, siue reformandi, siue reco
                     ••••
                   di, siue admittendi sunt. Infidels are th
                  •
                matter of her diuine worke of con
                  •
               e
                  ••
               ion. Heretiques serue for the tryall, prouing, and approuing of her doctrine, Scismatiques to shew her constancy, th
                  •
                Iewes imperfection to shew her perfection and beauty; some she inuiteth, some she excludeth, some she forsaketh, and some she goeth before in diui
                  ••
                perfections; to all she offereth the participation of diuine grace, whether they be to be informed, or reformed or r
                  •
               
               conciled, or to be admitted to a hig
                  ••
                degree of knowledge, and a more perfect estate. Thus haue we heard the exhortation of the Apostle, mouing vs to con
                  
                     •
                  end earnestly for the maintenaunce of th
                     •
                   fayth, and describing it to vs, by the Antiquitie of it, and that company of me
                  •
                amongst whom it is to be sought: Let u
                  •
                beseech almighty God to enlighten or vnderstandings, that we may know it, 
                  〈◊〉
                frame our harts to the loue of it, and 
                  〈◊〉
                make vs euer constant in the defence o
                  •
                it. Amen.
            
         
      
   

