
   
      
         
            A learned astronomical discourse, of the iudgement of natiuities Deuided into three bookes, and dedicated first to Katherin the French Queene, by Oger Ferrier her physition. Translated by Thomas Kelway Gentleman.
            Jugemens astronomiques sur les nativités. English
            Ferrier, Auger, 1513-1588.
         
         
            
               1593
            
         
         Approx. 254 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00700
            STC 10833
            ESTC S102052
            99837853
            99837853
            2200
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00700)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2200)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 226:01)
         
         
            
               
                  A learned astronomical discourse, of the iudgement of natiuities Deuided into three bookes, and dedicated first to Katherin the French Queene, by Oger Ferrier her physition. Translated by Thomas Kelway Gentleman.
                  Jugemens astronomiques sur les nativités. English
                  Ferrier, Auger, 1513-1588.
                  Kelway, Thomas.
               
               [4], 59, [1] leaves   
               
                  Printed at the widdow Charlewoods house, for Richard Watkins,
                  At London :
                  Anno. 1593.
               
               
                  Translation by Thomas Kelway of: Jugemens astronomiques sur les nativités.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Astrology --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-12
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2006-12
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  
                     A Learned Aſtronomical diſcourſe, of the iudgement of Natiuities. Deuided into three Bookes, and dedicated first to Katherin the French Queene, by Oger Ferrier her Phyſition.
                  ¶ Tranſlated by Thomas Kelway Gentleman.
                  Publiſhed by Authoritie.
                  
                     Pſalm. 147. 4. He counteth the number of the ſtarres, &amp; calleth them all by their names.
                  
                     AT LONDON, Printed at the widdow Charlewoods houſe, for Richard Watkins. Anno. 1593.
               
            
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, VERTVOVS, AND LEARNED LORD HENRY, Earle of Northumberland: (*) Lorde Percie, Lucie, Brian, Fitzpaine and Poynings: Lord of the Honors of Cockermouth and Petworth &amp;c. Knight of the moſt honorable order of the GARTER. All true felicitie both in thys life and in the worlde to come moſt hartily wiſhed.
            
               IF that ſaying of Plato (right noble Lorde) be true, that our Countrey challengeth an eſpeciall intereſt in our very vttermoſt abilitie, which any way may tend to profit &amp; benefite the ſame: then will it ſufficiently countenaunce the poore receiued Talent of myne, in that being ſo ſtrictly charged by ſo great and graue a Phyloſopher, I ought not to burie in obliuion my knowledge whatſoeuer, but rather as freely beſtow mine endeuour on her, as ſhee did franckly impart the light thereof to me.
            For though it be a common phraſe in the mouthes of men altogether ignorant in the precious value and profite of Sciences: That the ſtudie of Letters is a bottomleſſe Gulfe, and ſo long and ſo vneaſie a iourney, that they which raſhly thinke to finiſh it, oftentimes are drowned in the midway, and ſo vnder this pretence, account it better not to know much, yea, nothing at all: Againſt ſuch ſlothful ſuggeſters of men in a deadly obſcuritie while they lyue, let mee auouch that ſaying of Aristotle, Man (ſayth he) was created to vnderstande and to doe, for knowledge begetteth iudgement, and by iudgement men execute all good and vertuous actions.
            
            
               O Science (ſayth Plato) howe would men loue thee, if they did but knowe thee? for euen as health is the conſeruation of the body, ſo is knowledge the ſure and onely ſafe-garder of the ſoule. And Cicero beeing of the ſame opinion, ſayth: O knowledge, the guide of our life, the onely cauſe of vertue, and enemie to vice: What is the life of man without thee?
            
            If then (right learned Lord) ſuch a maine &amp; current ſtreame of vnconquerable reaſon, waſheth to nothing the emptie and confuſed wits, of ſuch as are enemies to the excellencie of Arte, and maketh moſt fertile (like the ouer-flowings of Nylus) the iudgements of thē that are gouerned thereby: (though farre from me be the thought of arrogating the very leaſt tytle of Arte to my ſelfe, yet as one that deſires

to receiue the breath of life from her ſacred dwelling, and holdes with the learned in all ages, that man is as a bruite beaſt without her:) then let me thus farre preſume vnder your noble fauour, to ſhewe that I haue not altogether trewanted in my life time, but howe I haue beſtowed thoſe permitted howers of exerciſe, that more waighty affaires in the world affoorded me, both to declare my reuerende zeale to ſo high a miſterie, and vnfeyned affection. I beare to your honor.
            The worke was firſt written in French, by an excellent Scholler, Oger Ferrier, a Phyſition, borne in Tolouze, &amp; dedicated to Queene Katherine of Fraunce, mother to the King that laſt deceaſſed. And beeing now by me changed into an Engliſh habite, that it might receiue no indignitie by dedication, I haue ſtampt your noble name in the fore-head thereof, that it may bee ſayde (in deſpight of the proudeſt carper or controller,) Thys is the God-chylde of a peereleſſe God-father.
            And as I doubt not of your honourable acceptauce, ſo I am likewiſe perſwaded, that what hath wanted on my behalfe in tranſlation, or any other imperfection beſide, ſhall be as nobly cenſured: in which reſolution I humbly kiſſe your hand, and continue as forward in affection, as any to your Honours welfare.
            
               Thomas Kelway.
One of her Highneſſe Trumpets in ordinarie.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE COVRTEVS Reader.
            
               I Am to requeſt (gentle Reader) one fauour at thy hande, that if this worke of the iudgement of Natiuities ſeeme harſh and vnpleaſant to thee, thou wouldeſt not therefore wound the ſame with iniurious words, to charge thy ſelfe with more follie then needes: but if thou finde it aboue thy knowledge or capacitie, ſaie as honeſt minded Chion ſaid: Let my betters iudge of theſe matters. For I muſt and do confeſſe, that it is not a Booke for euerie mans reading, and hee that reades with deriſion, becauſe he vnderſtands not, muſt blame his owne inſufficiencie, and not the booke: for if hee could learne as much in an hower, as coſt a learned man many yeeres to compaſſe, then would his humor be pleaſed, and the worke not reproched. But let ſuch loyterers vnderſtand, that knowledge requires the whole circuit of a mans life, and liue he neuer ſo long, yet may he learne: but if it might be attained in a Sommers daie, a number would be excellent, that through default thereof remaineth vtterly ignorant.
            To vſe many words, I account needleſſe, knowing that the reproofe of the vnlearned, is rather the badge of their owne weake braine, then any blemiſh to a worke of worth: Therefore let them cenſure as they pleaſe, the learned (I know) will iudge like themſelues, of whom I had rather be deſeruedly controlled, then by the other be ignorantly commended.
            
               Thomas Kelway.
            
         
         
            
            
               ❧ The Table of the matters in this preſent Treatiſe.
            
               The first Booke.
               OF the Celeſtiall figure of a Natiuitie. Fol. 1.
               Of the verification of the houre of the Natiuitie. fol. 1.
               The manner to ſette downe the ſaide figure verified. fol. 3.
               Of the parts of Natiuities. fol. 3.
               Of the latitudes and aſpects of the Planets. 6.
               Of the fortunes and infortunes of Plannets, and parts of heauen. fol. 6.
               If the Child ſhall lyue or no. fol. 8.
               Of the gyuer of life, called of the Arabians Hyleg. fol. 9.
               Of the gyuer of yeeres, called of the Arabians Alcocoden. fol, 10.
               Of them that augment and diminiſh the number of the ſayd yeeres. fol. 11.
               Of the Lord of the natiuity. fol. 12.
               Of the vnderſtanding and maners of the man. 13.
               Of riches and pouerty. fol, 15.
               By what meanes riches and pouerty come. fol, 16.
               Of the time that the riches &amp; damages ſhall come. folio. 17.
               Of Bretheren. fol, 18
               Of Father and Mother. fol, 18
               Of heritages and goods of the earth. fol, 19.
               Of Chyldren. fol, 19.
               Of Seruaunts. fol, 20.
               Of Diſeaſes. fol, 21.
               
                  
Of marriage. fol. 22.
               Of Dowery and other goods by the meanes of marriage. fol. 23.
               Of the death. fol. 23.
               Of voyages by Land and by Sea. fol, 25
               Of the conſtancie in his religion. fol. 25
               Of the action and profeſsion. fol, 26.
               Of dignities, offices and honours. fol. 26.
               Of companions and friends. fol, 27.
               Of ſutes and enemies. fol, 28.
               Of impriſonments and captiuities. fol, 28.
               Of Horſes, Muttons and other beaſtes. 29
            
            
               The ſecond Booke.
               Of the ſignifications of the Planets. fol. 29.
               Of the ſignifications of the twelue ſignes. fol. 32.
               Of that which the Plannets ſignifie in the ſayde ſignes. fol. 34
               Of the aſpects of the Planets between them. 36.
               Of the ſignifications of the twelue houſes. fol. 40.
               Of the Lords of the Tryplicities of the ſaide houſes. fol. 41
               VVhat the Plannets ſignifie in the twelue houſes. folio. 42.
               The ſignifications of the Lords of the houſes, by all the places of the figure. fol. 48.
            
            
               The third Booke.
               Of Directions. fol. 52.
               Of the Seperator or Burner, called of the Arabians Algebuthar. fol. 53.
               
                  
Of the Lords of the Tryplicities. fol. 54.
               Of Reuolutions. fol, 54.
               Of the iudgements vpon the Reuolutions. fol. 54
               Of the yeeres gouerned by the Planets, called of the Arabians Fridarie. fol. 55.
               Of Profections. fol. 57
               The Lord of the circulation, from the Lorde of the hower of the natiuity. fol. 58
               Of the circulation of the Lorde of the aſcendant, and of the Planets which be in the aſcendant. fol. 58.
               Of the Eclipſes and great coniunctions appertayning to the Reuolutions of natiuities. fol. 58.
               Of the particuler meetings of all the yeere. fol. 58.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            OF THE IVDGEMENTS ASTRONOMICALL VPON NATIVITIES. The firſt Booke.
            
               CHAP. I. Of the Celeſtiall figure of a Natiuitie.
               
                  FOR to iudge of Aſcendants and Natiuities, after the traditions of the auncient and learned Aſtrologians, it is conuenient firſt to explaine the Celeſtiall figure, and in the ſame, to applie the ſeauen Planets, with the head and tayle of the Dragon Lunaire, together with the part of Fortune, and the part of the ſpirite and others, more appertaining to the high &amp; notable ſignifications of the ſtarres; Then, to ſette downe plainly the Celeſtiall figure, you muſt in the firſt place, note the yere, the day, &amp; the houre, with the moſt neereſt minute of time of the natiuitie that you haue vndertaken. The number of the howers and mynutes, you muſt ſette them downe after the manner of the numbring of the Aſtrologians, within theyr tables: alwaies ſette downe the hower's after-noone, as well by day as by night, and neuer ſay, one hower, two howers, three howers after midnight, but number xiij. hovvers, xiiij. howers, xv. after noone. This done, ſearch in the Ephemerides in the table of the yeere of your natiuitie, in the right month &amp; day propoſed, the degree of the ſigne

wherein the Sunne is: looke afterwarde in the Table of houſes, which ſerue for the latitude of your Country, and ſearch there the ſaid degree of the Sunne vnder the lyne of the tenth houſe. And hauing founde in the ſame place the ſame degree of the Sunne, you ſhall find directly vppon the left hand of the ſame Table, a number of howers and minutes, the which write apart. To which number, you muſt adde the howers and mynutes that hath beene giuen you of the ſame natiuity, and that which reſteth by your addition, you muſt ſeeke in the table of houſes: and there where you find the ſame number of howers &amp; mynutes comming of the ſame addition, you muſt take to a right lyne the poynts and beginnings of the ſixe houſes, which you ſhall finde marked: the which you ſhall direct vpon your figure, beginning at the poynt of the tenth, and continuing towards the left hand.
               The beginning of the other ſixe houſes, you muſt take the oppoſite ſignes; and if it happen that the number of houſes and mynutes, come to more then twentiefoure howers, it is then conuenient to ſubſtract twentiefoure howers of the ſame tyme, and the reſidue ſeeke out as we haue aforeſaid. If the hower of the ſame natiuitie, be vpon the poynt of twelue howers of noone, you muſt take the houſes in a right line of the degree of the ſunne, in the table of your latitude, without making any other addition, or ſubſtraction, and that when in the figure eſtimatiue: within the which, it is needfull by all meanes to apply the moouing of the Moone exactly calculated, according to the vulgare cannons of the Ephemerides, for to verifie afterwarde your natiuitie by the hower of the conception. As followeth.
            
            
               CHAP. II. Of the verification of the bower of the natiuity.
               LEauing the Animodar of Ptolome and the meetings of Schoner, and all other vncertaine waies (although they haue theyr Authors) to verifie the howers of

natiuities, I will preſently follow the method of Hermes, approoued by long experience, and confirmed by Ptolome in his Centiloque, and by Abraham Aueneſrus, by Alphonce Leopolde, Haly, and other moſt expert Aſtrologians. Hermes ſaith, that the aſcendant of a natiuitie, hath beene the place of the Moone at the tyme of the cō
                  ception; and that the aſcendant of the conception, is the place of the Moone at the hower of the natiuitie. Who would be moore neere certified of the hower &amp; mynute of a natiuitie, and of the true aſcendant, it is conuenient that you follow the doctrine of Hermes by the method folowing. Firſt of all that you looke into the figure eſtimatiue, whether the Moone be aboue the Horrizon or beneath. If ſhe be aboue the Horrizon, count the diſtance that is betweene the poynt of the ſeauenth houſe and the Moone: if ſhe be beneath the Horrizon, count the diſtance which is from the firſt houſe vnto the Moone, which diſtance of ſignes and degrees, you muſt ſearch in the table that followeth, vnder the title of the Moone, aboue the Horrizon or beneath, as truely you haue found in the ſaid figure. In a right lyne of the ſaid diſtance, you ſhall find the time that the infant hath remained within the wombe of his Mother, in a certaine number of dayes, the which you muſt reckon from the day of your natiuitie backward; and there where the number endeth, you muſt marke the day of the conception, if the Moone be found in the ſigne of the aſcendant eſtimatiue. If you find her not in the ſame place, goe backwarde or forward certaine dayes of your account, vntill you haue founde the Moone within the ſaid ſigne, not farre from the degree aſcendant in the ſaid figure. The day conſidered, and in what hower, goe forwarde to the Eaſt poynt, the place where you haue ſounde the Moone in the figure eſtimatiue, and at that hower you muſt calculate the moouing of the Moone. For this degree and mynute in the which you found her, you muſt place it in the aſcendant of your natiuitie.
               
                  
And to know the hower in the which the place of the Moone of the natiuity, roſe to the Eaſt poynt at the time of the conception, take firſt the ouerthwart aſcention of the ſaid place of the Moone, within the table of the directions of your country, in the booke of Iohn de Regiomonte, of the ſame aſcention take away 90. degrees, (&amp; ad to the whole circle which is of 360. degrees, when the ſubſtraction cannot be otherwiſe made) the reſidue ſhall be the right aſcention of the height of the poynt of the Merydian circle: take afterward the right aſcention of the Sun, and take out by the ſubſtraction of the right aſcention of the ſayd poynt of the Merydian, and adde 360. degrees if it be neceſſary, &amp; turne that which is left into howers and minutes, in gyuing to 30. degrees two howers, to fifteene degrees one hower, to one degree 4. minutes of an houre, to fifteene minutes one minute of an hower; by thys meanes you ſhall exactly come to the hower of the conception, to the which you muſt calculate the place of the Moone, and the ſame well calculated, put it to the poynt of the firſt houſe, in the figure of the natiuitie.
               Diuers for this verefication doe dreſſe and garniſh the motions of the Planets foure figures. One of that hower eſtimatiue of the natiuitie, the other, of the precedent coniunction or oppoſition of the brightnes: the third, of the verification by the Animodar: the fourth, of the conception. The which beſides the vnprofitable and ſuperfluous labour, erre greatly, thinking to find out the tyme of the conception by the Animodar of Ptolome, the which experience from day to day ſheweth to be falſe, and that it hath no auncient Author to maintaine it, or hath made mention of thys newe doctrine, being full of contention and diſproued veritie.
               
                  
                  
                     ¶ The Table of the time that the Childe dooth remaine within the wombe of his Mother.
                     
                        The Moone beeing vnder the Horrizon, reckon from the Aſcendaunt.
                        The Moone being aboue the Horrizon, reckon from the ſeauenth.
                         
                     
                     
                        ſig
                        degr
                        dayes
                         
                         
                         
                     
                     
                        0
                        0
                        273
                        Indifferent abiding.
                        258
                        Little abiding.
                     
                     
                        0
                        12
                        274
                         
                        259
                         
                     
                     
                        0
                        24
                        275
                         
                        260
                         
                     
                     
                        1
                        6
                        276
                         
                        261
                         
                     
                     
                        1
                        18
                        277
                         
                        262
                         
                     
                     
                        2
                        0
                        278
                         
                        263
                         
                     
                     
                        2
                        12
                        279
                         
                        264
                         
                     
                     
                        2
                        24
                        280
                         
                        265
                         
                     
                     
                        3
                        6
                        281
                         
                        266
                         
                     
                     
                        3
                        18
                        282
                         
                        267
                         
                     
                     
                        4
                        0
                        283
                         
                        268
                         
                     
                     
                        4
                        12
                        284
                         
                        269
                         
                     
                     
                        4
                        24
                        285
                         
                        270
                         
                     
                     
                        5
                        6
                        286
                         
                        271
                         
                     
                     
                        5
                        18
                        287
                         
                        272
                         
                     
                     
                        5
                        29
                        288
                        Long abiding.
                        273
                         
                     
                  
               
            
            
               CHAP. III. The manner to ſette downe perfectlie the ſaid figure verified.
               HAuing put to the poynt of the firſt houſe, the degree &amp; minutes of the Moone of the time of the conception, take the ouerthwart aſcentions of the ſaid degrees and minutes: take out afterward 90. degrees of the ſayd aſcentions, and adde thereto 360. degrees, if otherwiſe the ſubſtraction cannot be made: that which remaineth, ſhalbe the right aſcentions of the higheſt poynt of the circle Meridian, the which ſearch in the

table of the right aſcentions, in the booke of Alphonce, or of Iohn de Regiomonte, &amp;c. and put to the poynt of the tenth houſe, the degrees &amp; minutes of the ſigne you find, aunſwering to the right number of the ſaid right aſcentions. The poynt of the fourth is alwaies againſt the ſigne and degree of the tenth: likewiſe the poynt of the ſeauenth, to the poynt of the firſt. The other houſes ſufficed, take the Ephemerides, becauſe they doe not deſire exact calculation, ſeeing that the moſt part of the Aſtrologians, deſire more to take of the equall portion of the Eclipſe then of the horizontall ſect.
               For to know the exact hower of the ſaid figure, verifie firſt the ſayd right aſcentions of the Meridian, and take from them the right aſcentions of the Sunne, that which remaineth turne into howers and minutes, gyuing to xv. degrees one hower, to euery degree foure minutes of an hower. &amp;c. as we haue ſayde before. At thys hower you muſt newly count the moouing of the Moone, and of the Sunne, &amp; of the other Planets: and vpon thys figure you muſt ground the parts and iudgements Aſtronomicall.
            
            
               CHAP. IIII. Of the partes of Natiuities.
               AFter you haue well ſought the Planets in the ſayd figure verified, you muſt conſider their aboue certaine proportions of the Planets and partes of the heauen, taken of theyr diſtances, as followeth.
               
                  The parts concerning the ſignifications of the firſt Houſe.
                  The part of the qualitie of the lyfe, is taken by the diſtance of Iupiter from Saturne, counting as much ſpace from the aſcendant, as when the natiuity is by day: for when it is by night, they take it to the cōtrary, the diſtance of Saturne vnto Iupiter, folowing the natural order of the ſignes, counting likewiſe as much ſpace ſince the aſcendant.
                  
                     
The part of lyfe by day and by night, is taken of the degree of the precedent coniunction, or oppoſition of the lights vnto the Moone, counting from the aſcendant.
                  The part of the Spirite (many do call the part of earthly things and ſecrets, the other, the part of things to come, the others, the part of the Sun) in the day frō the Mooue vnto the Sunne, from the aſcendant, in the night to the contrary.
                  The part of the vnderſtanding, by the day, is frō Mercurie vnto Mars, from the aſcendant, at night to the contrarie.
               
               
                  Of the ſecond Houſe.
                  The part of Fortune by the day, is from the Sunne vnto the Moone, from the aſcendant, at night to the contrarie. Ptolome doth take it as much by day as by night, from the Sunne vnto the Moone.
                  The part of the goods aſwell by day as by night, is from the Lord of the ſecond houſe, vnto the ſaid ſecond houſe, taken vpon the quality of the Eclipſe, frō the aſcendant.
               
               
                  Of the third.
                  The part of brothers, by the day, is from Saturne vnto Iupiter, from the aſcendant, at night to the contrary.
                  The part of the loue of bretheren, by the day, is from the Sunne vnto Saturne, from the aſcendant, at night to the contrary. If Saturne bee vnder the beames of the Sunne, take Iupiter in his place.
               
               
                  Of the fourth.
                  The part of father, by the day, is from the Sun vnto Saturne, from the aſcendant, at night to the contrary. Thys ſame is like the loue of bretheren: then if Saturne be vnderneath the beames of the Sun, in his place take Iupiter.
                  The part of inheritances and poſseſsions, by day and by night, is from Saturne to the Moone, from the aſcendant.
                  The part of fortune in tillage and ſowing, by day and by night, is from Venus vnto Saturne, from the aſcendant.
               
               
                  
                  Of the fift.
                  The part of Infants, is as the part of the qualitie of the lyfe.
                  The part of male chyldren by day and by night, is from the Moone vnto Iupiter, and is numbred from the aſcendant.
                  The part of daughters, by day and by night, is from the Moone vnto Venus, and is taken from the aſcendant.
               
               
                  Of the ſixt.
                  The part of diſeaſes inſeperable, in the day, is the diſtaunce of Saturne vnto Mars, and it is caſt from the degree aſcendant, and in the night from Mars, which is contrary.
                  The part of ſeruaunts, by day and by night, from Mercurie vnto the Moone, is from the aſcendant.
                  The part of pryſon and captiuity by day, from the lord of the place of the Sunne, vnto the Sunne, and is reckoned from the aſcendant. By night, from the Lorde of the place of the Moone, vnto the Moone.
                  If the Sunne by day, or the Moone by night, be in theyr proper houſes or exaltations, they ſhall be ſignifiers of thys part.
               
               
                  Of the ſeauenth.
                  The part of the marriage of men, by day and by night, from the Sunne vnto Venus, is from the aſcendant.
                  The part of the marriage of women, by day &amp; by night, from Venus to Saturne, is from the aſcendant.
                  The part of marriage common to men &amp; to women, by day and by night, is from Venus vnto the poynt of the ſeauenth houſe, accounting from the aſcendant.
                  The part of kindred, by day and by night, from Saturne vnto Venus, is from the aſcendant.
                  The part of diſcord &amp; agreement, by day, is from Mars to Iupiter from the aſcendant: by night to the contrary.
               
               
                  
                  Of the eight.
                  The part of death, by day and by night, from the Moone vnto the degree of the eyght houſe, taken vpon the equalitie of the Eclipſe accounting from the place o
                        •
                      Saturne.
                  The part of the mortall Planet by day is from the Lord of the aſcendant, vnto the Moone, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
                  The part of the perrillous yeere of death, or pouerty, or of any other miſ-fortune by day, and by night, is from Saturne vnto the Lord of the fore-ſaid coniunction or oppoſition of the light, from the aſcendant.
                  The part of all enuies, by day, is from Saturne vnto Mars, by night to the contrary, accounting frō the place of Mercurie.
               
               
                  Of the ninth.
                  The part of fayth and of religion by day, is from the Moone vnto Mercurie, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
                  The part of waies by land by day and by night, is from the Lord of the ninth vnto the ninth, taken vpon the equalitie of the Eclipſe, from the aſcendant.
                  The part of trauaile by water by day, is from Saturne vnto the fifteenth degree of Cancer, from the aſcendant, at night to the contrary.
                  If Saturne doe meete in the ſayde fifteenth degree of Cancer, he ſhall be ſignifier of this part, with the aſcendant.
               
               
                  Of the tenth.
                  The part of nobilitie by day, is from the Sunne vnto the nineteenth degree of Aries, accounting from the aſcendant, by night, from the Moone vnto the third degree of Taurus. If the Moone by night be in the ſaid degree of Taurus, or the Sunne by day, in the ſaid degree of Aries,

they ſhall be ſignifiers of the ſaid part.
                  The part of gouernment by day, is from Mars vnto the Moone from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
                  The part of Magiſtrates, as the part of the vnderſtanding, written vpon the firſt houſe.
                  The part of conqueſt &amp; victorie, as the parte of father.
                  The part of ſuddaine aduauncement, by day, is from Saturne vnto the part of Fortune, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary; If Saturne be burned, take in hys place Iupiter.
                  The part of eſtimation, by day and by night; is from Mercurie vnto the Sunne, accounting from the aſcendant.
                  The part of gouernments and ſeates of warre, by day, is from Mars vnto Saturne; from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
                  The part of the profeſsion and action, by day and by night, is from Saturne vnto the Moone frō the aſcendant.
                  The part of honour proceeding of the profeſsion, by day and by night, is from the degree of the Sunne, vnto the degree of the tenth houſe, from the aſcendant.
                  The part of the induſtry of the hands, by day, is from Mercurie to Venus, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
                  The part of the feare of Merchandize, by day, is from the part of the ſpirite, vnto the part of Fortune, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
                  The part of felicitie, and profit, by day, is from the part of Fortune vnto Iupiter, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
                  The part of the mother, by day, is from Venus vnto the Moone, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
               
               
                  Of the eleuenth.
                  The part of friendes, by day and by night, is from Mercurie to the Moone, from the aſcendant.
                  The part of praiſe, by day, is from Iupiter vnto Venus from the aſcendant, by night to the contrarie.
                  
                     
The part of honourable companies, by day, is from the part of Fortune vnto the Sunne, from the aſcendant, by night to the contrary.
               
               
                  Of the twelfth.
                  The part of enemies, by day &amp; by night, is from the lord of the xij. houſe vnto the ſaid xij. taken vpon the equalitie of the Eclipſe, from the aſcendant.
                  The ſecond part of enemies, as the part of diſeaſes inſeperable, written in the ſixt houſe.
                  The part of paine, trauaile and affliction, by day and by night, is frō the part of the ſpirite, vnto the part of fortune.
               
            
            
               CHAP. V. Of the latitudes and aſpects of the Planets.
               HAuing applyed the Planets in the ſaide figure, and ordained as we haue ſaid in the former chapter, the parts proceeding of the proportions of the ſaid Planets, you muſt conſequently draw out of the Ephemerides theyr latitudes, &amp; put apart all the aſpects which is among them, and towardes the ſaid parts and xij. houſes; alſo the radiations, after the laſt propoſition of the booke of Directions of Iohn de Regiomonte: vpon the which note, that the aſpects oppoſites, haue alwaies diuers latitudes to them of their Planets, although they keepe the ſame number. As if Saturne had two degrees of latitude ſeptentrionall, his oppoſition hath two degrees of latitudes meridionall. The quadrant aſpect hath no latitude, for it falleth alwaies vpon the Eclipſe.
               The Trine aſpect, retaineth the halfe of the number of the latitude, in contrary part: for if a Planet haue one degree of latitude meridionall, his trine ſhall haue thirtie minutes of latitude ſeptentrionall. The Sextile retaineth the ſame ſide, with the halfe of the number. You muſt alſo note, that theſe aſpects of Saturne and of Iupiter, doe not extend but vnto nine degrees, or for the moſt longeſt

vnto twelue; thoſe of Mars vnto eyght, or for the moſt part to tenne. The Sunne extendeth his beames to xv. degrees, Venus and Mercurie almoſt to eyght. The Moone vnto twelue, the head &amp; taile of the Dragon, likewiſe extend their forces vnto twelue degrees.
               Moreouer, it is to be noted, that the oppoſition is a plaine aſpect and perfect enmity: the Quadrate of leſſe enmity: the Trine of perfect loue: the Sextile of imperfect loue. That which alwaies receiueth exception in Iupiter and Venus, (of the which oppoſites and quadrate aſpects) profit the Sunne &amp; the Moone with reception, or without reception, and to others alſo with reception.
            
            
               CHAP. VI. Of the fortunes and infortunes of the Planets, and parts of Heauen.
               AFter this, you muſt conſider the forces &amp; weakeneſſe of the Planets, parts and Houſes, and conferring the ones ſignifications with the other, you muſt collect the fortunes and infortunes of euerie place, as followeth.
               
                  Heere followeth the infortunes.
                  The Planets and other places of the Heauen, be called vnfortunate, when they be burned vnder the beames of the Sunne. Burnings are called Saturne and Iupiter, when betweene them &amp; the Sunne they haue leſſe then twelue degrees. Mars when he is burned of the Sunne, hath at the leaſt xj. degrees and a halfe. Venus and Mercurie, when they be neere the Sunne, xj. degrees. The Moone when ſhe is not burned, by xiij. And yet you find other termes, when you will take a Planet for to giue the yeeres. Then the three ſuperiours are eſteemed burnt, becauſe they are neere the Sunne by xv. degrees, and if they be occidental. For when they be orientall vnto tenne degrees, they are burnt from the tenne vnto xv. vnder the beames. Venus

and Mercurie occidentall neere to the Sunne by ſeauen degrees, or orientall by fiue, be burned, from thence vnto twelue vnder the beames. The Moone neere by twelue degrees is burnt, from thence vnto xv. vnder the beames. And you muſt note, that the ſaide accidents are not hurtfull when they fall in the ſignes of Aries, and of the Lyon.
                  Vnfortunate alſo are the Planets, when they goe backwarde, and when they bee ioyned with Saturne or with Mars: or when they receiue euill aſpects of them.
                  When they are ioyned with any fixed ſtarre of violent nature.
                  When they are in their detriments or fallings, (that is to ſay) in places oppoſite to their houſes or exaltations.
                  When they are in their declining houſes.
                  When they are firſt ſtanders, (that is to ſay) when they be in the degree and minute wherein incontinently they beginne to goe backward.
                  When they are in the way of burning, which beginne at the 19. degree of Libra, and end in the third degree of Scorpio.
                  When they be with the tayle of the Dragon.
                  When they are ioyned with a backward Planet, or otherwiſe vnfortunate.
                  When they are Peregrines, without beeing receiued. They are called Peregrins, when they haue no dignitie or place where they be. Of the reception we will ſpeake afterwards.
                  When they be meridionall deſcendents.
                  When any of the three ſuperiours are occidentall, or Venus &amp; Mercurie orientall, when they be in euil aſpects of the Sunne.
                  When they doe not regard any other Planet.
                  When they be oppoſits to the Lord of the ſigne where they be.
                  When they be ſette, (that is to ſay) betweene two euill Planets, although they haue 30. degrees of diſtance.
                  When they be in euill houſes or termes.
                  
                     
When they be in the twelfth ſigne of theyr principall houſes.
                  When they be vnder the Horrizon in the day, or aboue the Horrizon in the night: if they be Diurnes, as Saturne, Iupiter, and the Sunne.
                  When they be aboue the Horrizon in the day, and beneath at night. If they be Nocturnes, as Mars, Venus, Mercurie, and the Moone.
                  When they be in ſignes and degrees feminine, they be maſculines, or in ſignes and degrees maſculine, they bee feminines. Feminines are Venus and the Moone, Mercurie and Androgine, the others are maſculines.
                  When they be in degrees which are called Azemenae, or in degrees ſtincking, darke, or ſmokie. That which is marked in the Ephemerides, in the table of the dignities of the Planets.
               
               
                  Infortunes particuler to the Moone.
                  When ſhe decreaſeth.
                  When ſhe is within the eyght Houſe, out of her principall dignities.
                  When ſhe is within the ſeauenth, and that as to the life. And as for any other ſignifications ſhe is not infortunate in the ſeauenth.
                  When ſhe is in the xix. degree of a ſigne.
                  When ſhe is ſlack in her courſe, (that is to vnderſtand) when ſhee goes in twenty-foure howers, leſſe then thyrteene degrees and xi. minutes.
               
               
                  The fortunes of the Planets.
                  Fortunate be the Planets, and other places of Heauen, when they be in angles, or at the leaſt in houſes ſucceeding.
                  When they be in a good aſpect of Iupiter, or of Venus, or at the leaſt in euill, with reception.
                  
                     
When they bee ioyned to the Sunne within ſixteene mynutes.
                  When they be in a good aſpect of the Sunne, of the Moone, or of Mercurie fortunate.
                  When they be ioyned with any fixed ſtarre of a louing nature.
                  When they be directs, or at the leaſt, in the ſecond ſtation, (that is to vnderſtand) when they be in degree and minute, in the which beginneth incontinently the direction.
                  When they be within theyr proper houſes or exaltations.
                  When they be in theyr triplicities and termes together, or triplicity and face together.
                  When they be in houſes, wherein they naturally take pleaſure, as Mercurie in the aſcendant, the Moone in the third, Venus in the fift, Mars in the ſixt, the Sunne in the ninth, Iupiter in the eleuenth, and Saturne in the twelfth.
                  When they be in any of theyr dignities, or if they be peregrines, when they be receiued. Receiued; that is, the Planets, which receiue aſpect of him, which in their place hath at the leaſt foure dignities, the which reception is fortunate, when ſhee is made of a good aſpect.
                  At all times the receptions of Iupiter and Venus be alwaies fauourable, although they be not made of good aſpects.
                  When they mount to the higheſt part of their Circles.
                  When they be ſeptentrionals, principally aſcendants.
                  When any of the three Superiours is orientall, or Venus and Mercurie occidentall.
                  When they beginne to goe from the beames of the Sunne.
                  When they be in Houſes or termes of fauourable Planets.
                  When they be aboue the Horrizon in the day, or vnder the Horrizon in the night, if they be Diurnes.
                  
                     
When they be vnder the Horrizon in the day, or aboue the Horrizon in the night. If they be nocturnes.
                  When they are in ſignes and degrees maſculine, they be maſculine, or in ſignes and degrees feminines, they be feminines.
                  When they be in degrees fortunate &amp; cleere degrees, which are called Lucides.
               
               
                  Particuler fortunes of the Moone.
                  When ſhee increaſeth.
                  When ſhe is within the houſe or exaltation of the Sun.
                  When ſhe is very ſwift in her courſe, (that is to vnderſtand) when ſhee goes more then thirteene degrees &amp; 11. minutes in 24. howers.
               
            
            
               CHAP. VII. If the child ſhall lyue or no.
               ALL thys aboue conſidered, you muſt firſt looke, whether he that is borne, is for life in this worlde or no. That which principally will ſhewe vs the light of the time, (that is to ſay, the Sun by day, and the Moone by night) are the Lords of the triplicity of him, and the aſcendant with his Dominator.
               When the Dominator of the aſcendant, ſhal be vnfortunate by the Lord of the eyght houſe, the Childe cannot liue: and leſſe, if the Lordes of the triplicitie of the temporall light be vnfortunate.
               When within the firſt houſe ſhall be any fixed ſtarre of violent nature, or any ill fortune, (that is to ſay, Saturne or Mars) without hauing at the leaſt foure dignities, and the temporall light ſhall be vnfortunate, the childe ſhall die quicklie. If you find not any fixed ſtarre of amiable nature, or if Iupiter and Venus, or the Sunne or the Moone, doe not communicate vnto him their beames. For and if the aſpect be of loue, or of enmitie with reception, the chyld ſhall liue.
               
                  
If the Dominator of the aſcendant be burnde, the child ſhall dye before 9. daies be acompliſhed, and more ſooner if he be burned within the eight houſe, or in this eſtate, if he be ioyned with the Lorde of the eygth. Except when he is burned in his owne houſe or exaltation, or within the houſe or exaltation of the Sunne.
               When the Moone, being the temporall light, ſhall bee vnfortunate within the firſt houſe, without any aſpect of the fortunes, &amp; without the coniunction of any fixed ſtars of amiable nature, the hope of lyfe ſhall not be great.
               When the Moone ſhal be vnfortunat within the fourth houſe, and he that hath the misfortune ſhall be alſo vnfortunate, &amp; out of his principall dignities, the Infant cannot liue, &amp; the mother ſhall be in great daunger of death at her deliuerance, and principally if the aſcendant be the houſe or exaltation of the Moone.
               When the infortunes are conioyned within the eighth houſe, it ſignifieth very ſhort life: except when Mars and Saturne be in Capricorne.
               Many ioynt Plannets within the firſt houſe, bring not good teſtimonie of life, although they be all fortunate.
               When the Domynator of the aſcendant, and the temporall light, and the Lords of their triplicities be not altogether vnfortunate, the childe may eaſily liue.
            
            
               CHAP. VIII. Of the Giuer of life, named of the Arabians Hyleg.
               
               THe giuer of life is taken out of the principal places of the Figure (that is to ſay) of the Sunne, of the Moone, and of the Aſcendant, of the part of Fortune, &amp; of the degree of the laſt coniunction or oppoſition of lights; the which hauing wel noted, we cōſider firſt, if the natiuitie be diurnal or nocturnal? For if ſhe be diurne wee beginne at the Sunne, the which within the firſt, tenth, or eleuenth houſe, in a maſculine or feminine ſigne, ſhall be fitte to giue life, if it haue any giuer

of tyme that doth regard it: If it be in the nynth, eygth, or ſeuenth houſe, it may alſo be the giuer of life, if it be in a Maſculine ſigne, and not in a Feminine: in other places it cannot be the giuer of life, but by conſtraint. It is alwaies neceſſarie for ſuch an acte, that the giuer of time regard the giuer of life, otherwiſe, the ſayd giuer of life ſhall be as perſon that hath good will to doo his friend good &amp; hath not wherewithall; And ſo when the Sunne ſhall be without aſpect of any giuer of time, you muſt leaue it there, &amp; goe to the Moone, which may giue the life within the firſt houſe, in the ſigne Maſculine or Feminine, and within the tenth, eleuenth, ſeuenth, fourth, fifth, ſecond and third houſe, in ſignes Feminines and not Maſculines, receiuing aſpect of any giuer of time. If the Moone haue not all the ſayde conditions, you muſt come to the degree aſcendant, if the natiuitie be coniunctionall (Coniunctionall is ſayed the natiuitie, before the which laſtly the lights haue beene conioyned) and if the ſayde degree receiue aſpect of his gyuer of time, he ſhall be gyuer of life: otherwiſe not. Wherefore you muſt examine the part of Fortune, the which ſhall giue life in the Angles and houſes ſucceeding, with the aſpect of the giuer of time, otherwiſe you muſt come to the degree, to the which laſtly the lights haue beene conioyned: the which within the Angles or houſes ſucceeding ſhall be giuer of life, if hee receiue aſpect of his giuer of tyme.
               It is heere neceſſary that the giuer of time haue dignitie of houſe, or of exaltation in places of the part of Fortune, and of the ſayd degree coniunctionall. By this order you muſt ſeeke the gyuer of life, when the natiuitie is coniunctionall. When ſhe is preuentionall, (Preuentionall is ſayed, afore the which laſtly the lights haue beene oppoſites) after you haue conſidered the Sunne and the Moone, you muſt conſequentlie contemplate the place of Fortune, more than the degree aſcendant, and laſtly the degree of the oppoſitions of the lights, &amp; ſee that it haue 2. degrees in the oppoſition, one of them of the Sunne, and

the other of the Moone. The Aſtrologians commaund to conſider it, that at the time of the oppoſition it hath beene in the firſt houſe, or elswhere aboue the Horizon.
               When the Natiuitie is nocturniall, we followe the ſame order, (except that firſt we conſider the Moone, ſecondly the Sunne, &amp;c.) This gyuer of life, when either by direction, or by profection, or by other way, meete any euill aſpect of the infortunes, or of the ſtarres fixed of vyolent nature, or any of the notable coniunctions, or Eclipſes of the lightes, it cauſeth then ſome ſickneſſe, and very ſuddaynly bringeth death, when the Fortunes doo not intermingle the fauourable beames.
            
            
               CHAP. IX. Of the giuer of yeeres, called of the Arabians Alcocoden.
               
               THE gyuer of time or giuer of yeeres, is the ſame that hath dignitie of houſe, exaltation, triplicitie, or tearme in the place where is the giuer of life. As if the Sunne were in the xj. in the ſigne of Sagitarius, (there where he may be gyuer of life,) and Iupiter were in the ſigne of Aquarius, he ſhall regarde the Sunne of the Sextile aſpect, and looke that he haue dignitie of the houſe in the ſigne of the Sunne, he ſhalbe giuer of yeeres. It is then neceſſary, that theſe two thinges concurre together, to the end that one Plannet be giuer of yeeres, that is to ſay, that he hath dignitie neuertheles of tearme (for the dignitie of face is not ſufficient enough for one ſo great effect) in ſigne and degree, in the which ſhall be the giuer of life, and that he regarde the ſayd giuer of life, of one aſpect or other.
               This gyuer of time, well lodged vpon the point of Angles, gyueth him olde yeeres, in points of the houſes ſucceeding: is meanes, is Cadants, is ſmalneſſe, and for as much as he ſhall be long from the beginnings of the ſaid houſes, ſo much the more or leſſe hee muſt diminiſh the number of his olde yeeres, meanes, and ſmalnes, after

the difference taken of the next houſes with the difference of yeeres. And firſt of all if it be within any angle of heauen, not alwayes to the firſt poynt, you muſt proceede alſo, and take in the firſt place the diſtance of the ſayd angle, and of the next houſe ſucceeding. Note afterwarde, how many degrees the ſaid giuer of yeeres is frō the point of the angle. Then take the difference of his olde yeeres and meanes, multiply this difference by the number of the ſayd elongment, and part it by the diſtance of the ſayd angle, &amp; of the houſe ſucceeding: that which reſteth, take for the exact number of the yeres of life, promiſed by the ſaide giuer of yeeres. If hee be within any houſe, ſucceeding out of the points and beginnings of the ſame, you muſt firſt take the diſtance of the houſe ſucceeding, and of the next Cadant: then note how many degrees the ſaid giuer of yeeres ſhall be elonged from the point of the ſaid houſe ſucceeding; afterward take the difference of yeres, meanes and ſmalnes, the which multiply by the ſecond number, and part it by the firſt: the reſidue ſhall be the time of life which was promiſed by the ſaid giuer of yeres. If it bee in Cadant houſes it ſhall be vppon the points of them, or after, he giueth but onely ſmall yeeres: Except when he is within 5. degrees neere to the point of the ſaid angles, &amp; then you muſt reckon as it followeth. Take the difference of the olde yeeres, and ſmalnes of the Plannets that giueth the yeres, and deuide them into 5. parts; afterward looke in which of the ſaid 5. degrees ſhal be the ſaid Plannet. For if it be in the firſt and moſt neere the poynt of the angle, (that is to ſay) if he be elonged from the ſaid angle one degree onely, then is it conuenient to take out of his old yeeres, one of the ſayd 5. parts: if he be elonged by 2. degrees, you muſt take out 2. parts: if he be elonged 3. degrees, you muſt ſubſtract 3. parts, &amp;c. You muſt note that the Moone in the viij. giues but ſmall yeeres. And that the Sunne within the 9. and Iupiter in the 11. and Venus in the 5. and Mercury by the whole aſcendant, and the Moone in the 3. giue their olde yeeres as perfectly, as

if they were vpon the points of the angles: For they be places wherein principally they doo reioyce. Iupiter, Venus, and Mercury within the 9. giue theyr yeeres indifferent: and the Moone in the 11. giues them old. Mars in the 6. and Saturne in the 12. they are indifferent, becauſe in the ſaide places they greatly delight themſelues: wherefore if they were not euill, they woulde there giue olde yeeres.
               Vppon this propoſe it is conuenient alſo to note, that one burnt Plannet cannot bee a giuer of yeeres: and the Moone in the prime of the beames of the Sunne, cannot giue life nor time. If a Plannet, which otherwiſe may be a giuer yeeres, bee burnt in his proper houſe or exaltation, receiuing there the Sunne, cauſeth the Sunne to take the charge to be the giuer of yeeres. If it come to paſſe that the Sunne or the Moone be in their proper houſes or exaltations, they may be giuers of life &amp; time together, with out neede to deſire aſpect of any other Plannet. If one place being ſignificator of life, haue many giuers of yeres, wee will take him that hath moſt dignities in the ſame place, and if they be equall in dignities wee will take hym that hath his aſpect moſt whole, and his beames moſt neereſt the ſayd giuer of life. If they finde two or three or many giuers of life, that haue their giuers of yeres, they muſt alwayes conſider and direct, as the firſt and principall, following the yeeres of the Plannets.
               
                  
                     
                        Olde yeeres.
                        Meane yeeres.
                        Small yeeres.
                        Of
                     
                     
                        57
                        43
                        30
                        Saturne.
                        ♄
                     
                     
                        79
                        45
                        12
                        Iupiter.
                        ♃
                     
                     
                        66
                        40
                        15
                        Mars.
                        ♂
                     
                     
                        120
                        69
                        19
                        Sol
                        ☉
                     
                     
                        82
                        45
                        8
                        
                           Ʋenus.
                        ♀
                     
                     
                        76
                        48
                        20
                        Mercury.
                        ☿
                     
                     
                        108
                        66
                        25
                        Luna.
                        
                           ☽
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. X. Of them that augment and diminiſh the number of the ſayd yeeres.
               THey which augment the number of the ſayd yeres, are Iupiter, Venus, the Sunne, the Moone, &amp; Mercurie fortified; the which fortunatly regarding the gyuer of yeeres, with an amiable aſpect adding to their ſmall yeeres, (that is to vnderſtand) the Sunne x. and ix. Venus viij. the Moone xxv. &amp;c. Likewiſe If the gyuer of time be conioyned with any fixed ſtarre of amiable nature, it taketh of the ſaid ſtarre the number of the ſmall yeeres of the Plannet, of the which the ſaid ſtarre holdeth his nature. If the ſaid Plannets regard the giuer of time with an euill aſpect with reception, they adde as before, which they doo not when they haue no reception: Except Iupiter and Venus, that in euery ſort of aſpects, with reception or without reception, alwayes adding to theyr ſmall yeeres, for to ſee that the gyuer of tyme be not Saturne or Mars, towards the which the reception is neceſſary, if the aſpect be of enmitie.
               The ſayd Plannets euill placed and infortunate, in the place of the whole ſmall yeeres, in adding the halfe, or the third, or fourth part, or certaine number of monethes, of weekes, or of dayes, according to the greatneſſe or ſmalneſſe of theyr infelicitie. The amiable aſpects of ill fortunes, with reception, giue theyr yeeres ſmall: without reception, they doo neither good nor euill. If the giuer of yeeres be retrogarde or meridionall deſcending, or in hys fall or detryment, or in the way burned, that taketh from it the fift part of that which hee had giuen beeing otherwiſe diſpoſed. That which happened alſo to the 3. ſuperiour Planets, when they be occidentall, &amp; to the Moone when ſhe decreaſeth, and when ſhee is in the xx. and ix. degree of a ſigne, and when ſhe is ſlack in her courſe. The Sunne regarding the Moone with the aſpects of enmitie without reception diminiſhed. Saturne, Mars, or Mercurie

depriued, looking to the euill aſpect of the giuer of light they take away the number of their ſmall yeeres: Except they recouer; For then by oppoſition they doe but halfe the euill: By quadrate aſpect, they diminiſh but the fourth part. The tayle of the Dragon taken from the Moone xij. yeeres, I haue found it often by experience, that the fortunes (that is to vnderſtand, Iupiter &amp; Venus) or the Sunne and the Moone, and Mercurie fortunate in the firſt houſe, or neere to the giuer of life, adding to their ſmall yeeres, although they doe not regarde the giuer of time: and to the contrarie, that the infortunes in the ſayd places, take away the ſmall yeeres, without regarding the ſaide giuer of time. Except when they were well honoured in the ſayd places, or when they were Lordes of the Natiuities.
            
            
               CHAP. XI. Of the Lordes of the Natiuitie.
               YOu muſt take the Lord of the Natiuitie, out of the places of the which we haue taken the giuer of life, (that is to vnderſtand) of the place of the Sunne and of the Moone, of the degree aſcendant of the part of Fortune, and of the degrees of the precedent coniunction or oppoſition of lightes. Of all theſe places likewiſe it is to be conſidered, what Plannet hath moſt dignities, for he ſhall be Lord of the Natiuitie, that which the giuer of yeeres ſhall ſignifie the tyme of our life, according to the ſcituation &amp; felicitie or infelicitie, as we haue before ſayd of the giuer of yeeres. And if the one giue more than the other, you muſt take the difference of both, and the halfe ad or diminiſh: according as ſhall be neceſſarie.
               
                  
                  
                     
                         The Signes.
                        5 The houſe of the Planettes.
                        Exaltation.
                        3 The triplicitie of the Planettes.
                        2 The termes of the Planettes.
                        1 The faces of the Planettes.
                        Perigren.
                        The hurtes.
                        The falls.
                     
                     
                        S
                         
                         
                         
                        D
                        N
                        P
                         
                        G
                         
                        G
                         
                        G
                         
                        G
                         
                        G
                         
                        G
                         
                        G
                         
                        G
                         
                         
                         
                     
                     
                        ♈
                        ♂
                        D
                        ☉
                        ☉
                        ♃
                        ♂
                        ♃
                        6
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        12
                        ☿
                        10
                        ♂
                        25
                        ♄
                        30
                        ♂
                        10
                        ☉
                        20
                        ♀
                        30
                        When the Planettes naue no dignities.
                        ♀
                        ♄
                     
                     
                        ♉
                        ♀
                        N
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♀
                        ♄
                        ♀
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        ☿
                        14
                        ♃
                        22
                        ♄
                        2
                              •
                           
                        
                        ♂
                        30
                        ☿
                        0
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        20
                        ♄
                        30
                        ♂
                         
                     
                     
                        ♊
                        ☿
                        D
                        ♃
                        ♄
                        ☿
                        ♃
                        ☿
                         
                        ♃
                        
                           
                              •
                           2
                        ♀
                        17
                        ♂
                        24
                        ♄
                        30
                        ♃
                        10
                        ♂
                        20
                        ☉
                        
                           
                              •
                           0
                        ♃
                         
                     
                     
                        ♋
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        
                           DN
                        
                         
                        ♀
                        ♂
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♂
                        7
                        ♀
                        13
                        ☿
                        
                           
                              •
                           9
                        ♃
                        26
                        ♄
                        30
                        ♀
                        10
                        ☿
                        20
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        30
                        ♄
                        ♂
                     
                     
                        ♌
                        ☉
                        
                           DN
                        
                         
                        ☉
                        ♃
                        ♂
                        ♃
                        6
                        ♀
                        11
                        ♄
                        18
                        ☿
                        24
                        ♂
                        30
                        ♄
                        10
                        ♃
                        20
                        ♂
                        30
                        ♄
                         
                     
                     
                        ♍
                        ☿
                        N
                        ☿
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♀
                        ♄
                        ☿
                        7
                        ☿
                        17
                        ♃
                        21
                        ♂
                        28
                        ♄
                        30
                        ☉
                        10
                        ♀
                        20
                        ☿
                        30
                        ♃
                        ♀
                     
                     
                        ♎
                        ♀
                         
                        ♄
                        ♄
                        ☿
                        ♃
                        ♄
                        
                           
                              •
                           
                        
                        ☿
                        14
                        ♃
                        2
                              •
                           
                        
                        ♀
                        28
                        ♂
                        30
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           0
                        ♄
                        20
                        ♃
                        30
                        ♂
                        ☉
                     
                     
                        ♏
                        ♂
                        N
                         
                        ♀
                        ♂
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♂
                        7
                        ♀
                        11
                        ☿
                        
                           
                              •
                           9
                        ♃
                        24
                        ♄
                        
                           
                              •
                           0
                        ♂
                        10
                        ☉
                        20
                        ♀
                        30
                        ♀
                        
                           ☽
                        
                     
                     
                        ♐
                        ♃
                        D
                         
                        ☉
                        ♃
                        ♂
                        ♃
                        12
                        ♀
                        
                           
                              •
                           7
                        ☿
                        21
                        ♄
                        26
                        ♂
                        30
                        ☿
                        
                           
                              •
                           0
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           0
                        ♄
                        30
                        ☿
                        ♃
                     
                     
                        ♑
                        ♄
                        N
                        ♂
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♀
                        ♄
                        ☿
                        7
                        ♃
                        14
                        ♀
                        22
                        ♄
                        26
                        ♂
                        30
                        ♃
                        10
                        ♂
                        20
                        ☉
                        30
                        
                           ☽
                        
                         
                     
                     
                        ♒
                        ♄
                        D
                         
                        ♄
                        ☿
                        ♃
                        ☿
                        7
                        ♀
                        13
                        ♃
                        20
                        ♂
                        25
                        ♄
                        30
                        ♀
                        10
                        ☿
                        20
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        30
                        ☉
                         
                     
                     
                        ♓
                        ♃
                        N
                        ♀
                        ♀
                        ♂
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♀
                        12
                        ♃
                        16
                        ☿
                        19
                        ♂
                        28
                        ♄
                        30
                        ♄
                        10
                        ♃
                        20
                        ♂
                        30
                        ♀
                        ☿
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. XII. Of the vnderſtanding and manners of a Man.
               HOW to knowe the felicitie or infelicitie of the Spirite, &amp; the nature of the ſame, you muſt looke in the place of Mercurie and of the Moone, the Planet that in theſe two places hath moſt dignities, ſhall be ſignifier of the ſpirite. The which if it be Saturne well diſpoſed, ſhall ſignifie the man of a great and profound knowledge, of good counſell, and of good grauitie or a ſtrong opinion: cloſe, ſecrete, ſolitarie, diſſembling his good and euill, a louer of iuſt men, and of good age: reioycing vpon the treaſures, heritages and labourings; holding diſcourſe of antiquities and of great affayres, admirator of buildings. Sometimes a little merrie, incontinent ſadde: ſometymes laughing or murmuring by himſelfe alone, a lyttle ſlothfull, a little enuious, and not alwaies keeping hys promiſe. If he be vnfortunate, he ſhall be noted enuious, ſadde, ſolitarie, fearefull, mellancholie, faint-harted, a raylor, iealous, a malefactor, euill, a blaſphemer, a lyer &amp; deceiuer, a Vſurer, &amp; holder of opinions: reiecting the counſell of others: fearing that all the world doth deceiue hym: vnciuill, a villaine, a ſlouine, diſhoneſt, flying the company of men vnleſſe it be to deceiue them, and to draw any profite, hauing no other friend but his villainous gayne, vſing ſomtimes ſorcery.
               Iupiter ſignifier of the ſpirite, well diſpoſed, ſhewes the man ſweete, curteous, honeſt, gracious, amiable, faithfull, pittifull, liberall, of good behauior, of good hart &amp; good loue: following nobleneſſe and all honeſty: louing God, abounding in friendes, dreaming alwaies vpon ſome vertuous thing, and withdrawes himſelfe ſometimes ſolitary, to thinke vpon ſome goodnes: vſing in all and by all hys affayres, a great equitie, prudence and modeſtie, hauing great courage to accompliſh. If hee be vnfortunate of himſelfe, and not to meete with other ſtarres, in the place

of good loue, hee will giue ſometimes fooliſhnes in the place of honeſty, pryde in the place of liberalitie, prodigalitie in the place of louing good will, doth yeeld hym an hypocrite, ſeeming to follow nobleneſſe, when indeed he will diſpraiſe all the world: in the place of honeſtie, it wyll make hym dreame of tyranny.
               If the ſaid Iupiter be vnfortunate of other Planets and not of hymſelfe, he taketh all theyr vices, and couereth them with his ſayde vertues in manner of an euill hypocrite. If Mars well fortunate be the ſaid ſignificator, hee ſhall cauſe the man to be of a high courage, hardy, irefull, furious, a hazarder, a conducter of warres, &amp; the firſt in buſineſſe, and onely in deedes and cogitations gyuen to armes: ſtrong, ſtubberne and mightie, truſting too much to his owne puiſſaunce, not fearing any perrill, and bleſſed in all hys deedes. If he be vnfortunate, it maketh the man tymerous, a theefe, a lyer, blaſphemer, mutenous, cruell, a murtherer, hardy, proude, arrogant, not to be borne withall, deſpyſing hys owne proper goods, and the goods of other, vſing force and violence againſt hys Parents, and againſt all the worlde: a diuiliſh man, without ſhame, without counſell, without vertue, without loue, without any feare or reuerence of God, furious, ſeditious, gyuen and prompt to all miſchiefe.
               If the Sunne be ſignificator in his good diſpoſition, it makes the man mannerly, wiſe, prudent, of good counſell, a louer of noblenes, following glory and honour, gyuen to iuſtice and gouernments of Townes and Citties, louing hunting, worthy, and of great eſtimation. If it be vnfortunate, it ſheweth great pride, exceſsiue ambition, and tyrannie, and doth nouriſh the thought.
               If Venus ſignifie the qualitie of the ſpirite in good diſpoſition, it maketh the man pleaſant, merry, dauncing, laughing, content, amiable, gracious, of good conuerſation, and a little ielous. If vnfortunate, it maketh the man frowning, and too merry, of euill maintenaunce, vſing diſhoneſt words, giuen to voluptuouſnes, and ielous of

that which belongeth not vnto him.
               If Mercurie bee fortunate, it gyues good vnderſtanding, good memorie, great perſeuerance, great ſubtiltie of ſpyrite, good diſcourſe of reaſon, full of wit, very apt to know the Mathematicals, and the ſecretes of nature; it makes the man a Poet, an Orator, well ſpoken, writing well, and a great trader. If it be euill diſpoſed, it makes him preſumpteous, of little knowledge, with great eſtimation of his perſon, inconſtant, a lyer, a mocker, a deceiuer ordinarily, fine, fantaſticall, and vicious.
               If it be the Moone that is fortunate, ſhee maketh him that is borne, pacified, modeſt, of good hart, or good will, and eaſie to endure any thing that one will doe. Vnfortunate doth ſhew inconſtancie, lightnes of ſpyrite, faint-harted, prodigall, faythleſſe. If the ſayde ſignifiers, are not greatly fortunate or vnfortunate, it is conuenient to rebate the ſayde ſignifications good and vicious, after the qualitie of theyr good and euill diſpoſitions.
               If any Planet be participant in the ſignification of the manners, or if it haue great communication of aſpect with the principall ſignificator, then conſidering the vices and vertues of him, that (according to his good or euill diſpoſition) wee doe ioyne them to him which gyueth the principall. As if Saturne well diſpoſed, be principal ſignificator, and Mars infortunate be participant, or regarde Saturne of one whole aſpect with reception, then it is conuenient to mingle ſome little of the nature of Mars vnfortunate, with the ſignifications of Saturue fortunate.
               The Aſtrologians doe aduertiſe vs, that if the Lord of the aſcendant be well placed, and the ſaide ſignificator of manners euill diſpoſed, you muſt more conſider vppon that which the Lord of the aſcendant ſignifieth, then vppon that which the ſaid ſignificator doth promiſe. Moreouer, they conſider more particulerly, the place of Mercurie and of the Moone, and the aſpect which they receiue. If Mercurie be in the aſcendant, it maketh the Man ingenious, and of great and profounde knowledge,

a great Phyloſopher, a Mathematician, an Orator, a Poet, a Diuine; principally whē he is in the place in the which Saturne hath at the leaſt 4. dignities, or when he receiues aſpect of Saturne.
               Mercury in the twelfth, receiuing aſpect of the Moone, hath very neere as great force for to giue wit and knowledge, as if he were in the firſt. And where that Mercurie is, if he regard the Moone, and both two, or the one or the other, regard the aſcendant or the Lord of the aſcendant, thys is ſigne of a good and ſubtile ſpyrite. And if Saturne, Iupiter and Mars, or other Planets, do communicate to him theyr fauorable beames, if they mingle theyr good vertues, if they regarde the euill aſpect, they intermingle theyr vices: except Iupiter and Venus, which of euill aſpect doe neuer anoy them, and leſſe when he hath reception.
               If the Sunne be temporall light, it may ſignifie the quality of the ſpyrite with the Moone and Mercurie in the forme aboue ſayd. If Mercurie be occidentall within the houſe or exaltation of the Sunne, hauing aſpect of the Moone, or of the aſcendant, or of his Lord, it is the ſoueraigne ſigne of good and high ſpirits, of men of al knowledge, gyuen to great enterpriſes and vertues, as Poets, Orators, Mathematicians, Counſellers, Adminiſtrators of Common-weales, and Gouernours of Realmes: principally when hee is fortunate in euery angle of Heauen.
               Mercurie within the ſeauenth houſe fortunate, giueth good vnderſtanding, and ripe iudgement: it maketh the man ſubtile, watchfull, and of good counſell, with great craft to gouerne his affayres. Mercurie in the ninth or third houſe, giueth knowledge and contemplation. The part of the vnderſtanding of the ſpyrite with theyr Lords fortunate, ſignifieth good ſpirits and good manners.
               Mercurie in the ſigne of Piſces, doth not any way loue learning: the contrary happeneth, when he is in the ſigne of Virgo and of Gemini, by all the places of the figure of Heauen. Saturne within the houſes of Mercurie, is alwaies

contemplatiue: Mars, a lyttle deceiuer. Mercurie within the houſes of Saturne fortunate, is alwaies ſtudious, within thoſe of Mars, he is full of euill words, and often falſe.
               When the lyghts and ſignificators of manners ſhall be oppreſſed with ill fortune, the chylde ſhall be of a verie ſtrange and peruerſe nature. The Moone oppoſite to the Sunne, makes hym hate all men. If the Sunne and the Moone with the aſcendant and his Lorde, be all in feminine ſignes, the manners of hym ſhall be feminine, and he ſhal be a man of little hart. If they be in ſignes maſculine at the natiuitie of a woman, her deedes ſhal be manly, and ſhe ſhall be a woman of great enterpriſe.
               If Venus be in the ſigne of the Lyon, or vnder the beames of the Sunne, or in coniunction or other aſpect of Mars, ſhe maketh that the man ſhal be ſuddainly ſtriken in loue. And if in that eſtate ſhee be within the firſt or tenth houſe, without any aſpect of Iupiter, hee ſhall be voluptuous without hauing ſhame; and when ſhe ſhalbe in the ſigne of Scorpio, the aſpect of Iupiter towards Venus, gyueth alwaies chaſtitie, and loue of vertue.
            
            
               CHAP. XIII. Of riches and pouertie.
               FOR the riches and pouertie, it is conuenient firſt that you looke to the ſeconde houſe, for if ſhee and her Lord be fortunate, we ſay that the chyld ſhall be rich, and if they be vnfortunate, he ſhall be poore on that ſide. Then afterward you muſt conſider the part of Fortune, the which with hys Lorde well diſpoſed, promiſeth great ſtore of goods, without other witnes. If they be euill diſpoſed, you muſt come to the parte of goods the which with his Lord fortunate enricheth, vnfortunate gyueth nothing. Likewiſe you muſt iudge of the part of felicity and of his Lord. And that thing which the other places ſignifie, you muſt alwaies haue recourſe to the naturall

ſignificator of riches, which is Iupiter, the which well placed and fortunate, gyueth goods in aboundance: principally if he be Lord of the natiuity, or Lorde of the hower, or of the aſcendant, or of the ſeconde houſe, or of the part of Fortune, or of the part of goods, or of the part of felicitie, or of temporall light, or of the tenth houſe, otherwiſe he gyueth nothing.
               When the aboue-ſayde Significators ſhall be vnfortunate, the chylde cannot be rich, if the tenth houſe (of the which wee will ſpeake heereafter) doe not promiſe hym ſome good lucke. Men finde alſo often by experience, that when a Planet is within his own houſe or exaltation, or in hys ioy, (without beeing vnfortunate, or els where enuironed with the fortunes or theyr beames) that hee gyueth goods, although he be not Significator of riches. If in the fourth houſe be hys lord or other fortunate Planet, he promiſeth inheritaunces. If any fixed ſtarre of the firſt or ſecond greatnes be ioyned to the temporall lyght, or to the degree aſcendant, or to the poynts of the other angles, or to other Planets in the ſayd places placed, ſhe dooth rayſe the man of baſe eſtate, to great authority and honour: and if he be of the race of Princes, it will make hym a puiſſant Lord and King.
               When a lyke Planet ſhall be Lord of the aſcendant, &amp; of the ſecond houſe, the chylde ſhall be couetous of money &amp; gayne, as that which happeneth when Capricorne is aſcendant. When the Lord of the ſecond houſe ſhal be within the firſt, the goods come without laboure. Likewiſe when the Lord of the ſecond houſe giueth ſtrength to the Lord of the aſcendant. When the Lorde of the aſcendant ſhall be in the ſecond, the goods ſhall not come without trauayle: nor whē the lord of the aſcendant ſhall gyue ſtrength to the Lord of the ſecond. Saturne, Mars, Mercurie depraued, the Sunne and the tayle of the Dragon lunarie, within the ſecond, deſtroy the man, and diſperſe his goods; except when they haue at the leaſt foure dignities, or when they be receiued. When the

Lord of the aſcendant ſhall regarde with euill aſpect the ſecond houſe, or the part of goods and of fortune, or their Lords, the chyld of hys owne proper will ſhall diſperſe his goods. If the Lord of the aſcendant be vnfortunate in the ſecond houſe, the chyld ſhall be too large a giuer, and prodigall. If any miſ-fortune haue domination vpon the aſcendant, and in the ſecond, the chylde ſhall be deſtroyed by others, which ſhall deſtroy hys goods and robbe hym. When the ſayde Significators of goods ſhall be vnfortunate, the chyld ſhall be all hys lyfe in payne and trauaile, without any aduauncement or profite.
               
                  Abraham Aueneſre ſaith, that if the Lord of the ſecond be burnt, and Iupiter euill diſpoſed, that the chyld ſhalbe Foure Planets in their fals or detrymēts, do ſhewe great miſeries, as it was in the natiuite of Iohn Duke of Saxony, who was takē priſoner of Charles the 5. Thys good Duke had 3. Planets in their detryments, and one Perigren. alwayes poore. And Hermes ſayth: when the Lord of the profeſsion (of the which we ſhall ſpeak in the 27. chap.) ſhall be burnt, or retrogard, or in the ſixt or xij. houſe, and not any Planet regarding the Moone, the chyld ſhall ſeeke hys lyuing from doore to doore like a begger. Iupiter, Venus, and the head of the Dragon in the ſecond, alwaies enrich. Venus in the fift promiſeth ſome good. The Sunne in the nynth fortunate, gyueth benefices, or other goods of the ſide of the men of the Church. Mars in the ſixt well diſpoſed, gyueth good or nouriſhment to Beaſtes, and exerciſe of Phiſicke. The Sunne in the ſigne of Leo, will neuer ſuffer the child to be poore.
            
            
               CHAP. XIIII. By what meanes riches and pouerty commeth.
               HAuing well noted the places which promiſe and bring riches, in regarding the ſituation of the ſaid ſignificators, we wyll know by what means ought to come the good and the euill. For if the ſignificator be in the firſt houſe receiued and fortunate, it eaſily inricheth the perſon by hys induſtry and proper labour: and if he be in the ſayd place vnfortunate, it is that his induſtry and labour doth profit hym nothing; and the ſooner from thence to loſſe and damage.
               
                  
If he be in the ſecond houſe well diſpoſed, it profiteth to talke with Merchants, and lend merchandize &amp; money, and of them make gaine. And if he be there euil diſpoſed, the ſayd buſines bringeth great damages. If he be within the thirde houſe fortunate, it bringeth the goods from the ſide of Brothers and Siſters, and Coſins &amp; alyes, or frō the ſide of the men of the Church in taking charge of theyr affayres: or to traffique heere and there about his Country. If he be in the 4. wel placed, he is inriched of inheritances &amp; goods of our fathers &amp; predeceſſors, of laborings &amp; tilling of ground, of houſes, &amp; oftentimes doth meete with treaſure. If it be within the fift, it profits to be a good Dauncer, a good Player, to bee braue, gracious, pleaſant and delightfull, and ſometimes to be voluptuous: alwayes well, becauſe of God-fathers and God-mothers, and of theyr proper chyldren; or becauſe of gyfts, or to make ſome voyage and doe ſome embaſſage. Thoſe things that come appertaining to brauery and volupteouſneſſe, and making ready delicates, odours &amp; perfumes, of thys houſe they very ſuddainly draw theyr profite. If the ſayd ſignificator be in the ſixt well placed, hee ſhall make his profite in nouriſhing, and buying and ſelling of Sheepe, muttons, and other ſmall beaſtes, or ſhall become rich by the diligence and faithfulneſſe of his ſeruaunts, or ſhall gaine by the exerciſe of Phiſicke. The Gaylors and others which haue the charge of pryſons, drawe oftentimes theyr profit from thys houſe.
               If the ſignificator be in the ſeauenth fortunate, it promiſeth great good of the ſide of women, by marriages or like agreements: and oftentimes to haue pleaded &amp; gayned his ſute in the law, or hauing beene in the warres and pilled the enemies. If it be in the eyght well diſpoſed, it gyueth great dowrie and great good, becauſe of women, and ſometimes heritages, of the which he ſhall not greatlie thinke of. If it be in the ninth fortunate, hee ſhalbe enriched of the goods of the church, or by traffique &amp; traueling in ſtrange Countries.
               
                  
If it be well in the tenth, he ſhall haue his profit of the ſide of Kings, Princes, and Lordes, and be made of them Gouernours of Townes, and honourable Officers; or be enriched by their owne vocation and profeſſion.
               If it be within the eleuenth in good diſpoſition, he profiteth by reaſon of friendes, and by fauour of men in authoritie.
               If it be in the twelueth, fortunate, it giueth gayne by nouriſhing and ſelling of Horſes, Mares, Oxen, Kyne, Cammells, and other great beaſtes: or to haue charge of pryſonners: or of the perſecution of enemies, with profitable victorie in the end; As oftentimes it happeneth to ſome, which accuſing others, and cannot prooue the crymes intended be condemned to make a good amendes to the partie: after all which perſecution, the partie doth finde himſelfe content.
               Saturne by himſelfe, enricheth by heritages &amp; labours, nouriſhing of all Cattell, and with trading with auncient men, or with Countrey-men, Marriners, &amp; other vilde men: in Corne, Wines, Oyles, Fyſh, Oade, Roſen, Allum, Leather, Tyles, Stones, Plaiſter, Chalke, Lyme, and ſuch merchandize.
               Iupiter, by Offices, benefices, and buſines of men of the Church, and all gaynes that are made without deceit. Except when he is infortunate, for then vnder the ſhaddow of vertue, he dooth his affaires craftilie.
               Mars, by warres, ſutes, or thefts, or by ſlaughter, and ſelling of Cattell: or if it be in aſpect of Venus, by phyſicke.
               The Sunne, by honourable offices, dignities &amp; Lordſhips, by great credit, by charges to keepe and gather the money of Princes and Common-weales.
               Venus, by muſique, pleaſure, grace and vertue, by brauery, by play, and ſometimes by voluptuouſnes, and ſomtime to ſerue ſome great Ladie.
               Mercury, to ſpeake well and write well, and to be very skilfull, to be a Secretarie, a Regiſter, a Poet, an Oratour,

and a good aduocate, to be a Geometrician, Arethmetrician, Aſtrologian, and a good trader. The moone for voyages, nauigation, wandring, and trading in far Countries, to haue the chardge of ſmall affaieres of the common wealth.
               If the ſaid Significator be vnfortunat in the ſame places, they bring dammage and intereſtes, and if they be within the houſes of Saturne, Iupiter or other planets, wee iudge the profit &amp; intereſt after the nature of Saturne, Iupiter, and other planets which ſhalbe lords of the ſame places.
            
            
               CHAP. XV. Of the time when the riches and dammages ſhall come.
               THe ſayde riches ſhall come, when the Significators of goodes ſhall meete by direction, in body or in aſpects of amitie. As if Venus in ſome natiuitie promiſe goodes, they ſhall come when Venus by direction shall touche the place of Iupiter, or the degree of the ſecond houſe, or the part of fortune, or their good aſpects: Likewiſe you muſt iudge of damages in goodes. For when a ſignificator of damages and intereſtes doth meete by directiō a ſignificator of goods, or his aſpects of enmitie, then certainly comes the loſſe and damage. As when Saturne or Mars meete Iupiter in the parte of fortune, the parte of goodes and other places which ſignifie riches, the which alſo you muſt direct to the ſayd ill fortunes, or to their euill aſpect ſygnifying alwayes ſome loſſe.
               By the reuolutions alſo you may know the time of good and euill fortune. For when Iupiter in the natiuitie shalbe in the ſigne Libra well diſpoſed, alwayes and as many times, as you shall find him in the reuolution in the signe, in the ſame fortune certainlie he shall then bring the goodes that he promiſed, at the houre of the Natiuitie.
               To the contrarie, if hee be vnfortunate by Saturne or

Mars in the Natiuitie, alwayes and as many times as he shall be in the reuolution ouer againſt the ſayd vnfortunators, then the ſayd damage ſhall come in the ſort and manner as was ſignified in the natiuitie.
               If the Significator of goodes be Orientall, the goodes come in youth, if it be Occidentall, in age. If it be in the firſt houſe hee ſhall be rich in his firſt age, if it be betweene the firſt and the tenth, vppon the time of twenty and ſeuen yeares. If it be in the tenth, betweene thirtye and fiue and thirtie. If it be betweene the tenth and ſeuenth, about fortie and fortie eight. If it be in the ſeuenth he ſhalbe rich in his old age. You muſt alſo looke to the three Lords of the triplicitie, and to euery Significator of goodes. For the firſt lord ſignifieth the firſt age, the ſecond of the time of thirtie or fortie yeares, the third the laſt age. Wherefore if the firſt lord of the triplicitie of one ſignificator of riches be fortunate, the ſayd goodes ſignified shall come at the firſt time: or if hee be vnfortunate, the damage then shall ſticke, by this meanes you may applie the other lordes, to the ages following, and according to the good or euill diſpoſition you muſt iudge of the fortune of euery one.
            
            
               CHAP. XVI. Of Bretheren.
               MArs and Saturne within the thirde houſe out of their principall dignities and not receiued, signifieth that the childe shall haue no brother nor Siſter. And if they be in their principall dignities, or if they be fortunatly receiued, they may then giue ſome bretheren, but by reaſon of the which hee shall alwayes be in ſorrowe, ſtrife, and contentions. The taile of the Dragon or lunaris, maketh him ſee the death of his bretheren, when ſhee is in the thirde houſe. That doth the Lord of the ſayde houſe alſo, when hee is in the tenth or eight, and when he is burned or otherwiſe euilly diſpoſed.
               
                  
If in the ix. be any Plannet well dignified, and the Lord of the third houſe be vnfortunate, his bretheren ſhall dye before him, if he doo not finde in the ſame houſe ſome fauourable Plannet, or if the Lord of the ſaide houſe be not amiably regarded of fortunes.
               Iupiter, the Sunne, Venus, the head of the Dragon, the Moone, and Mercury, fortunate in the thirde houſe, doo giue many bretheren, happy, pacified and fortunate. Mars, regarding the ſaid houſe, or his Lord of euill aſpect, ſignifieth ſtrife and debate among the bretheren. That which ſignifieth alſo the Lord of the ſaid houſe, in the vij. and xij. And Mars oppoſite to the aſcendant, or to the Lord of the aſcendant, and to the temporall light, and when a like Plannet is Lord of the iij. and vij. or xij. houſe. The part of the amitie of bretheren with his Lord fortunate, ſignifieth concorde: vnfortunate, diſcorde among bretheren. The part of bretheren, and the third houſe, with their Lords in watry ſignes, denoteth many brethren and ſiſters: and if they be fortunate, they ſignifie concorde and good loue together: vnfortunate, denoteth the contrarie.
            
            
               CHAP. XVII. Of the Father and the Mother.
               THe Lords of the fourth, and of the part of the Father, burnt out of their proper houſes and exaltations, ſignifie that the Father cannot long liue; The ill fortunes within the 4. ſignifie that the father ſhall dye preſently after, if within the ſaid houſe they bee not dignified, or if the fortunes doo not enterlace their fauourable beames: Likewiſe you muſt iudge of the mother, when the ſayd Conſtellations ſhall be in the 10. The fortunes in the 4. ſignifie long life to the Father, and happie fortune: &amp; likewiſe of the mother, when they be within the x. The Sunne vnfortunate within the iiij. or viii. houſe, teſtifieth that the Father ſhall not liue long: likewiſe you muſt iudge of the mother when the Moone ſhal

bee ſo diſpoſed. If the Lord of the 4. be in the 11. the childe ſhall ſee the death of his Father. If the Lord of the x. be in the 5. he ſhall ſee the death of his mother. Venus or the Moone in the 4. vnfortunate, giueth perrill to the mother at her deliuerance. The Lord of the 4. in the 7. or 12. houſe, or in euill aſpects of ill fortunes, ſignifieth ſtrife and quarrells betweene the Father and the Sonne. Likewiſe you muſt iudge of the mother, when the Lord of the 10. ſhall be in the ſame diſpoſition. The part of the Father fortunate, denoteth long and happy life to the Father: vnfortunate, he ſhall dye very quickly. The part of the mother, ſignifieth as much of the mother, after her good or euill diſpoſition.
               Commonly the Aſtrologians haue regard to the Sunne and to Saturne for the Father, and to Venus and the Moone for the mother; If the natiuitie bee by day, they take the Sun for ſignificator of the father: if it by be night they take Saturne, if the Sunne be not in any angle of heauen: For if it be in the 1. or 4. they preferre him alwayes to Saturne. If the Sunne be in the 1. in the natiuitie of the 1. childe, the figure of the natiuitie of the Father and of the Sonne ſhall be both one. The ſignificator of the Father, ioyned to the Fortunes, or receiuing their amiable aſpects, denote good fortune and long life to the Father: the contrary you muſt vnderſtand when they be vnfortunate.
               If the Lorde of the aſcendant, and the Lorde of the 4. doo looke with an euill aſpect; the Sonne and the Father ſhall be in diſcorde, principally if Mars intermeddle with his pernicious beames. For the mother you muſt looke principally to Venus, if the natiuitie be by day: or to the Moone if it be by night; And after their good and euill diſpoſitions, you muſt iudge the good or contrary fortune of the mother.
            
            
               
               CHAP. XVIII. Of inheritances and earthly goods.
               THE Fortunes, or other Plannets fortunate, within the fourth or eight houſe, denoteth inheritances and poſſeſſions: the ill fortunes doe deny or diſpiſe them. Saturne, naturall ſignificator of heritages, landes and poſſeſſions, well diſpoſed, dooth giue great goods and landes, and maketh the man happie in labouring and tyllage; That alſo ſignifieth the ſignificators of ryches, when they bee well diſpoſed within the houſes of Saturne. And the part of heritages, and the part of fortune in ſowers &amp; tyllers whē they be fortunate, with their Lords. If the ſayde ſignificator be vnfortunate, you muſt iudge the contrary.
               When one ſelfe Plannet is lorde of the firſt and fourth houſe, the childe ſhall haue inheritances which ſhall enrich him, if the ſayd lorde be fortunate: and if he ſell and diſpearſe them, he is vnfortunate. The lorde of the aſcendant, or the Moone within the fourth fortunate, and amiably by Iupiter or Venus regarded, denote that he ſhal finde ſome great ſumme of money vnder the earth, principally, if Saturne caſt his Trynes or Sextil beames: or that of Mines of golde and ſiluer he ſhall be made rich.
               The tayle of the Dragon in the ſouth, maketh him to ſell &amp; diſpearſe his goods. That doth alſo the head of the Dragon, when ſhe is in a ſigne earthly or watriſh: In ayrie ſignes or fiery, ſhe giueth great goods and landes.
            
            
               CHAP. XIX. Of Infantes.
               THe Fortunes in the fift, giue the children: the vnfortunes denyes them. Except when they be in their proper houſe or exaltations, for then they giue euill children; that which they doo alſo, when regarding the ſaide houſe, or the lord of the ſame, with eeuill

aſpects. If the Lord of the firſt be burned, he giueth the children abortiues, or which preſently after their birth, dye. If the ſayde lorde be in the xij he ſhall ſee the death of his children. If he bee in the vij. or xii. or if a like Plannet bee Lorde of the v. vij. or xij. hee ſhall haue ſutes and queſtions with his children. The lorde of the aſcendant, in euill aſpect of the lorde of the v. denoteth as much. Before you giue iudgement of the Children, you muſt conſider the x. and the vii. houſe, and the parts of children with their lordes. The ſignificators of the children in Maſculine ſignes, ſignifieth Male children. in feminines, denote daughters: Likewiſe you muſt iudge when they bee coupled with plannets, maſculines, or feminines.
            
            
               CHAP. XX. Of Seruaunts.
               THe ſignifications of ſeruaunts muſt be taken of the place of Mars &amp; Mercurie, of the ſixt houſe of the part of ſeruaunts, and of their lordes. The which fortunate giueth faythfull ſeruauntes, vnfortunate giue them euill. When the lord of the aſcendant &amp; the lord of the ſyxt ſhalbe in good aſpect together to the ſygnificators of riches, the child ſhalbe come rich by the induſtrie and faythfulneſſe of his ſeruants. Likewiſe when the fortunes be within the ſyxt houſe: to the contrarie, when the Significator of riches ſhalbe vnfortunate in the ſyxt houſe, he ſhall be vndone by his ſeruants. Likewiſe when the ill fortunes ſhalbe in the ſaid houſe. If the lord of the vi. be in the x. he ſhall yeelde his ſeruaunts more greater maiſters then himſelfe. If the lord of the vi. houſe be in the ſigne of a humane figure, his ſeruauntes ſhall beare him reuerence and be at his commaundement.
               
                  
                  What kind of conditions euerie Planet dooth yeelde.
                  
                     ♄ Fortunate.
                     Sadde &amp; of a deepe cogitation. Secrete. Solitarie. Labourſome. Painful. A heaper of goods. Patient. Sparing. Carefull of hys owne preferment.
                  
                  
                     ♄ Vnfortunate.
                     An abiect. A fugitiue. Baſe minded. A vile man. Negligent. Fearefull. Sadde or penſiue. Couetous. Enuious. A Witch. Stubberne. A Roge. Suſpicious. Superſtitious. A Deceiuer.
                  
                  
                     ♃ Fortunate.
                     A louer of GOD. Religious. Honeſt and vertuous. Stoute. Couragious. Iuſt. Vpright. Authoritie. Modeſtie. Bountifull.
                  
                  
                     ♃ Unfortunate.
                     A louer of hymſelfe. High-minded. Proude. Superſtitious. feareful. faint-harted. Careles or negligent. Prodigall. Nothing ſo good as when he is fortunate.
                  
                  
                     ♂ Fortunate.
                     Gentle. Manly-minded. Full of courage, Stoute. Irefull. Earneſt. Fearing no danger. Patient. Delighting in warres and manly exerciſes.
                  
                  
                     ♂ Vnfortunate.
                     Quarrelſome. Cruell. Angry. Tyranical. Vniuſt. Vnfaithfull. A blood-ſhedder. Theeuiſh. A make-bate. Haſtie, or raſhe. A boaſter. Very proude.
                  
                  
                     ♀ Fortunate.
                     Pleaſant Merry. Fayre. Gentle of ſpeech. Of comlie ieſture. Good. Mercifull. Gyuen to pleaſure both of bodie and minde. A louer of dianty and delicate thinges.
                  
                  
                     ♀ Unfortunate.
                     Womaniſh. Fearefull. Weake of nature. Slothful. Lecherus. A ſlaunderer. Not caring for his good name, Giuen to filthy luſt. Sodomiticall.
                  
                  
                     
                     ☿ Fortunate.
                     Of an excellent wit, Studious. Of a quicke capaſitie. Of a good and ſounde iudgement in euery thing. Poeticall. Gramatical. Mathematical. Finding out many things vntaught.
                  
                  
                     ☿ Unfortunate.
                     Vnſtable. Malicious. A lyer, chiefely if he be with the Dragons tayle. Priuily ſowing deceite. A ſlaunderer. Forgetful. Fooliſh. Full of wicked counſell and malice.
                     Thus may you gather the naturall diſpoſition of anie man, eyther preſent or abſent: according to the nature of the Planets as is aboue ſpecified. As for the lyghtes, the ☽ from her ☌ to her ☍ dooth make theyr manners moſt apparant, from her ☍ to her ☌ more obſcure.
                  
               
            
            
               CHAP. XXI. Of Diſeaſes.
               YOV muſt firſt of all conſider the places of Saturne and of Mars, and of the Lord of the ſixt houſe. And according to the ſigne in the which they bee, you muſt iudge the ſickneſſe to bee in the place marked by the ſayd ſigne. As if Saturne were in the ſigne of Libra, it denoteth that the ſicknes is in the reynes of the nature of Saturne: becauſe that Libra is the ſigne that hath gouernment ouer the reynes, as ſhall be declared in the ſeconde Booke. Likewiſe you muſt iudge of other Significators, after the gouernment of the ſigne in the which they be.
               The ſicknes and accidents comming by Saturne, Mars and other Planets, ſhalbe explaned in the ſecond booke. Mars in the aſcendant, gyueth alwaies ſome notable hurt vpon the face, or vpon the head, and often neere the eyes, when hee is neere the lights. Saturne in the firſt houſe, yeeldeth the man to be very ſadde, and melancholie, and vexeth the minde, cauſing horrible ill and fearefull imaginations.

The tayle of the Dragon in the firſt, darkeneth much the ſight and often yeeldes the men blind, when the Luminaries or the fortunes, doe not intermingle their fauourable beames. Saturne and Mars in the tenth, ſignifie ſicknes in the necke, in the ſeauenth, in the buttockes: as Fiſtuloes, Emrods, Vlcers, and hurts &amp;c. In the ſixt, diſeaſes in the feete: in the twelfith, hurts and grieſes in the legges, as I haue often tryed. Saturne infortunate, ſignifieth diſeaſes in the parts appertaining to Saturne. Iupiter and the other, ſignifie as much when they be euill diſpoſed. Of the partes which belong to the Planets wee will ſpeake of in the ſecond Booke.
               They which haue the Lumynaries, or any of the principall places in the figure vnfortunate in the figne of Scorpio, are ſubject to the French-pocks. The ill fortunes in the ſigne of Gemini, gyue alwaies ſome great and violent blowes vpon the ſhoulders, legges &amp; armes. The Moone vnfortunate in the ſigne of Aries, ſignifieth great paine in the head. Saturne and Mars ioyned to the Lumynaries, or to the Lord of the aſcendant, trouble the ſight, and ſpoyle the eyes with ſome blowe. The Sunne in the natiuities Diurnes, ſignifyeth the right eye, the Moone the left: in the Nocturnes, to the contrary. If the degrees of the firſt houſe, or the Lumynaries be ioyned with any troubleſome ſtarre, the eyes ſhall be darke, and the ſight troubled; lykewiſe if they be in the ſignes which the Aſtrologers call Azemena and filthy dregges. &amp;c.
               Saturne in the ſixt houſe burned in a warry ſigne, denoteth ſome forme of leproſie. Saturne in the aſcendant, maketh ſome notable deformitie in the face, when hee is neere the Moone. The ill fortunes, and the Moone and Venus in warry ſignes, ſignifie leproſie, vlcers &amp; cankers on the body, and villainous ſpots in the face. Saturne in the ninth, and the Moone in the eyght vnfortunate, denote trouble of minde and ſolly. Venus ioyned to Mercurie vnfortunate by Saturne or Mars, without aſpect of Iupiter or of the Sun, ſignifie notable griefe in the partes

of generation. If Venus &amp; Mercury be vnder the beames of the Sunne, they ſignifie as much. Saturne wyth the Moone burned, cauſeth Palſies and Impoſtumes. Mercurie vnfortunate, gyueth alwaies ſome impediment in the tongue: and ſo doth Saturne alſo when he is vnfortunate in the temporall lights. The Sunne vnfortunate, denoteth weakenes of the hart: principally when he is lord of the ſixt houſe, or Lord of the part of ſickneſles. The ill fortunes with the tayle of the Dragon, cauſe looſeneſſe and the flixe of the bellie. They that haue the Sunne or Mars in the ſignes of Aries or Gemini, be ſubiect to the Stone. The retrogradation and burning of Saturne and Iupiter, ſpoyle the hearing, and the teeth.
               When the Moone &amp; Mercury doe not looke between them, and doe not regard the aſcendant, nor the Lord of the aſcendant, the chylde ſhall be troubled in his vnderſtanding. The retrogradation of all the fiue Planets, ſignifyeth the falling ſicknes. The ill fortunes ioyned in the aſcendant in euill aſpects of the Moone or the Lorde of the aſcendant, denote entire folly. The part of ſickneſſes with hys Lord fortunate, preſerueth from ſicknes, vnfortunate, gyue many euils.
            
            
               CHAP. XXII. Of Marriage.
               FOR the marriage, you muſt looke the vij. houſe and hys Lord, the places of Venus and the Moone in the natiuities of men, and in the places of the Sunne and of Mars in natiuities of women: and the parts of marriage, and the place of Iupiter. If the ſayde Significators be fortunate, the marriage ſhall be happie, if they be vnfortunate, it ſhall be full of enuies, reproches and euils. If ſome be fortunate, and ſome vnfortunate by certaine tymes, now happy, and then vnhappy, it ſhall be manifeſt. Many Planets in the ſeauenth houſe, giue many women: likewiſe when many Planets regard the ſayd

houſe or his Lord. If Venus, &amp; the Lord of the ſeauenth houſe be burned, or otherwiſe of Saturne oppreſſed, the chylde ſhall neuer marry. Iupiter and Venus within the 6. or 8. ſignifyeth that he ſhall marry a widdow. Iupiter burned, ſignifieth as much. Otherwiſe, if Iupiter behold Venus, and the other ſignificators of marriage, it promiſeth maydes and virgins. If Venus or Iupiter, or the Lord of the ſeauenth houſe be ioyned to Saturne, or if Saturne be within the ſeauenth houſe, the woman ſhall haue ſome note of infamie; (that is to vnderſtande) ſhee ſhall be of a ſtrange religion, or ſhall be a baſtard, or ſhall be of the race of Lepors, or of ſome other, by whom the Parents haue receiued ſome ſhame, or ſhe ſhal be deformed, and her Parents ſhall be of a very weake condition. Mars in the ſayd houſe, or beholding with euil aſpect the Significators of marriage, intermingle ſtrife and contentions betweene the man and the wife: the ſame doth alſo Venus in the ſeauenth or twelfth houſe.
               Mars in the ninth, aſmuch in the natiuities of women as of men, denoteth ſome manner of ſeparation of marriage. And Venus in the ninth, ſignifieth that the man ſhal hate his wife, not ſo much for the vice which he ſhal find in her, but of a deſire to be ſolitary. The Significators of marriage vnfortunate, or within the houſes Cadents, ſignifieth the woman to be of a ſimple race, or the husbande in the natiuities of women.
               If Venus and the Lorde of the ſeauenth houſe, ioyne with the Significators of riches, beholding the Lord of the aſcendant with an amiable aſpect, ſhe giues much goods by reaſon of women. The Significators of mariage within the thyrd or ninth, or elſe where Peregrines, ſignifie that he ſhall marry out of hys Country. The fortunes within the ſeauenth houſe, denoteth happy marriage, the ill fortunes vnhappy. The Lorde of the ſeauenth within the ſeconde, denoteth that hee ſhall ſee the death of hys wife. The Significators of marriage occidentall, witneſſe that he ſhall marry late, or in his youth take a wife older

then himſelfe. Orientall, denoteth that he ſhall marrie in hys youth, or in hys age marry a young wife. Likewiſe you muſt iudge of husbands in the natiuities of women.
            
            
               CHAP. XXIII. Of a dowery and other goods by the meanes of marriage.
               BEcauſe the eyght houſe is ſucceeding to the ſeauenth, by good reaſon it ſignifieth the profit of the ſignifications of the ſeauenth, (that is to ſay) of marriage. If then in the eyght there bee any fortunate Planet, or any part fortunate, the chyld ſhall haue great dowrie by his wife, and of that ſide ſhall meet with great inheritaunces &amp; great goods. To the contrary, if Saturne and Mars be vnfortunate in the ſaid houſe, hee ſhall haue ſmall dowery, and the ſame ſhall neuer be fully payd.
               When the fortunes be in the ſayd houſe vnfortunate, he hath hope of great goods the which in the end he ſhal not enioy. The Lord of the ſaid place vnfortunate, denoteth as much: and if hee be fortunate and coupled with the Significators of riches, it denoteth great goods and great profite on that ſide. It happeneth well ſometimes when the ſeauenth houſe is fortunate, and the eyght vnfortunate. As that which ſignifieth a little dowery &amp; deſperation of other goods towards his wife, &amp; that alwaies he ſhall be inriched by the diligence, induſtry, and faithfulneſſe of his wife.
            
            
               CHAP. XXIIII. Of the Death.
               YOV muſt firſt conſider if there bee any Planet in the eyght houſe, for it is conuenient to take it for Significator of the death. If within the ſayde houſe there be neuer a Planet, take them for Significators that be in the ſeauenth, preferring him alwaies that is beſt dignifyed. If within the ſeauenth you finde none, drawe

the Sgnifycator of the death from theſe places which followe.
               Of the aſcendant and of his Lord.
               Of the eyght houſe and of his Lord.
               Of the part of Death and of his Lord.
               Of the eyght Signe, from the place of the Sunne &amp; of hys Lorde.
               Of the eyght Signe, from the Moone and of his Lord.
               Of the place of the firſt Lorde of the triplicitie of the fourth angle.
               Of the place of the Planet which hath dignity of terme, to the degree of the ſeauenth houſe.
               The Planet which in all theſe places ſhall be moſt dignifyed, ſhall be principall Sgnificator of death.
               If Saturne beeing in the eyght or ſeauenth houſe, or otherwiſe more dignified in the aboue ſaide poynts of the figure, he is principall ſignificator of the death. If hee be well diſpoſed, it witneſſeth, that the ſame partie ſhall dye of the Dropſy, of ſome great ſtopping of the lyuer, and of the Spleene, or of a quarterne Feuer, of the flixe of the belly, of Pthiſick, or of ſome burning Feuer, and of Impoſtumations of the eares. &amp;c. If it be greatly vnfortunate, and together with the Lord of the aſcendant, and the luminaries temporally be euill diſpoſed, it denoteth violent death by Impoſtumes, Palſies, falling downe of humors, ſuffocations, ouer-flowen with water. When it is in watry Signes, by ſome fall or ruine: when it is in earthlie Signes, by great blowes: for to be hanged when it is in ayerie Signes.
               If Iupiter be Significator of the death, it denoteth that he ſhall die of a Plureſie, of a Squinance, or of ſome hote appoſtumations of the lyuer, or of the lunges, or of other ſickneſſes comming of wind or of blood; and that if he be fortunate. For when he is euill diſpoſed and vnfortunate, it maketh hym die by the hand of iuſtice, by the commandement of the Prince, by ſentence of the Iudge or of the Marſhall, by ouer-flowing in waters, to be whypped and

ſcourged, by long impriſonment.
               If it be Mars well diſpoſed, by continuall tertian Feuers, by flixe of blood, by Carbuncles and peſtilences, by Impoſtumes comming of chollerick matters, burnings by too much vſing of women. If he be very euil diſpoſed, it maketh him to be hanged and ſtrangled, or ſmothered, or otherwiſe killed in his bedde, or on hys horſe. When he is an ayrie ſigne or partaker within the water, when he is a watry ſigne or fallen frō on high, or of ſome ruinous murtherer. When he is a terreſtiall, or burned: when he is a fierie Signe: principally if the Lord of the aſcendant and the luminaries temporally be vnfortunate by Mars. If it be the Sunne well diſpoſed, hee ſhall die of ſome hote diſeaſe. If it be vnfortunate, by the commaundement of the Prince, or by ſentence of the Iudge, or hee ſhall dye among a great company of men, ſubiect to death, or in priſon, or in a Dungeon, or in ſome other ſtincking and filthy place. If it be Venus wel diſpoſed, he ſhal die of too much eating fruites, or with too much continuing his voluptuouſnes, or of ſome Fiſtula or Impoſtume. If ſhe be vnfortunate, it denoteth death by venim, principallie when ſhe is burned, or ioyned to Saturne, or of too much burning affection of loue, or of great griefes of the French pockes. If it be Mercurie fortunate, it maketh him dye by ſadneſſe, by great apprehenſions, by the Yellowe iaunders, by pthiſickes, by the burning Feuer, or by too much watching. If he be greatly vnfortunate, it ſignifieth that he ſhall die by madneſſe, the Falling-ſicknes, by violent Coughes, with breaking in ſunder the veynes, by fooliſh mellancholie, by Ielouſie.
               If it be the Moone well diſpoſed, with too much eating moyſt meates, by drinking water, by too much continuing his pleaſure; If ſhe be vnfortunate, you muſt conſider the nature of him which is vnfortunate. For if it be Mars hee ſhall dye by fire, or by hurt: or by abortiſment if it be a woman. If it bee Saturne, by ruines, falles, peſtilences, and like accidents.
               
                  
Before concluding of what death the partie ſhall dye, you muſt conſider the diſpoſition of the Lorde of the aſcendant, and of the luminaries temporall: For if they be well diſpoſed, the death ſhal not be vyolent, although the principall ſignificator bee greatly vnfortunate. If the ſayd ſignificator be vnfortunate, together with the luminaries temporall, or the Lord of the aſcendant euill diſpoſed, we eſteeme certainly that the death ſhall be vyolent, if Iupiter or Venus doo not intermingle theyr fauourable beames, and then the ſayd perſon ſhall fall in great daunger of the ſaid violent death, &amp; from the which he ſhall alwayes eſcape myraculouſly.
               If one of the ill fortunes be in the ſigne of Cancer, and the other in the ſigne of the Lyon, the death ſhall be vyolent; Likewiſe, if any of the ſayde ill fortunes be in the ſigne of the Lyon, and the luminaries temporall, or the Lord of the aſcendant be vnfortunate, and one of the ill fortunes be in the firſt houſe, and the other in the ſeuenth or fourth, or one of them in the tenth and the other in the fourth.
               The Sunne, or the Moone, or the Lord of the aſcendant, ioyned with Mars, haue right in one fixed ſtarre, which the Aſtrologers cal the head of Meduſe, or otherwiſe the head of the diuel, maketh him by the hand of the Executioner to leeſe his head.
               When the Sunne, and the Moone, and Saturne, and Mars, occupie the 4. angles of heauen, or at the leaſt 3. the perſonne ſhall dye a horrible death: for he ſhall leeſe his head, or be cut in foure quarters, or be drawen with foure horſes: principally, if in the ſayde angles be the ſignes of Gemini, Piſces and Aquarius. Mars in the ninth or eyght in the ſigne of Aquarius or of Gemini, oppoſite to the Moone, or the Lorde of the aſcendant, without good aſpect of fortunes, maketh hym perriſh by Sulpher or fire from heauen. Saturne in the twelfth, ſixt, eyght, or fourth houſe vnfortunate, the lord of the ſayde houſes maketh hym dye in pryſon, or els where in great payne

and trauaile: principally when the luminaries temporall, or the Lord of the aſcendant be vnfortunate in any of the ſayd houſes.
               The tayle of the Dragon beeing ioyned to the Significators of death, denote poyſons, venims, and violent medicines, or ill applyed, and flixe of the belly. Mars within the fourth, eyght, twelfth, or ſixt vnfortunate, theyr lords and the luminaries temporall, or the Lorde of the aſcendant, witneſſe violent death, by the ſhedding of blood or otherwiſe.
               The Significators of death within the ninth or thyrd houſe, ſignifie that the perſon ſhall die by the way, or in a ſtrange Country: except they be in theyr owne proper houſes or exaltations, for then he ſhall die in his houſe, &amp; bring his euill from the high waies. The ſaid Significators in their proper houſes or exaltations, make him die in his houſe, if they be Peregrines, they make him dye out of his houſe.
               The Moone ioyned to a fixed ſtarre, named the Claire of the ballance meridionall, denoteth violent death. That dooth ſhe alſo when ſhe is ioyned with other ſtarres that haue the nature of the luminaries. Mars in the viij. houſe with the head of the Dragon, maketh him to bee hanged and ſtrangled. Many Planets within the ſeauenth houſe, make him dye of ſome ſtrange and terrible kind of death. Saturne, Mars, and the heade of the Dragon in the firſt, Venus and Mercurie with the taile in the ſeauenth, make the body in a thouſand peeces.
               If the principall Significator bee burned in his owne proper houſe or exaltation, without being otherwiſe vnfortunate, it maketh him dye ſuddainly of ſome feeblenes, or other ſuddaine and ſecrete accident, without other violence. The fortunes well diſpoſed in the eyght houſe, preſerue him alwaies from violent death.
            
            
               
               CHAP. XXV. Of voyages by Land and by Sea.
               IVpiter, Venus, the Sunne and Mercurie fortunate in the ninth houſe, denote that he ſhall be happy in viages by Land and by Sea. Saturne and Mars ſignifie to the contrary; and principally Saturne doth hinder the viages by water, and Mars the waies by Lande. If within the ninth houſe there be neuer a Planet, you muſt conſider the Moone, and the Lord of the ninth, and the parts of the waies and viages by land and by water, with their Lordes, the which fortunate, giueth profitable nauigations: vnfortunate, denote the contrary. Likewiſe you muſt iudge of the third houſe and of his lord, when they be well or euill diſpoſed. The head of the Dragon in the ninth, fauoureth greatlie to the fortune of viages, and the tayle to the contrary.
            
            
               CHAP. XXVI. Of the conſtancie in his Religion.
               ALſo as the head of the Dragon, the luminaries, and Mercurie in the ninth houſe well diſpoſed, denote entire fayth and conſtancie in hys Religion, Saturne, Mars, and the tayle of the Dragon do hynder it. Saturne of his nature is moſt enclined to the Law of the Iewes: and Mars to the law of the Turkes &amp; Mahometiſts; the tayle of the Dragon, cauſeth him alwaies to erre from the truth of the law. The lord of the nynth, and the part of the fayth, with hys Dominator fortunate, yeeldeth a man conſtant in his faith: vnfortunate maketh him variable.
               If the part of the ſpirite be in the ſigne of the Lyon at the byrth of a Chriſtian, hee ſhall be very conſtant in hys religion, if the Sunne be fortunate: if he be vnfortunate by Saturne, to goe from his fayth, and to addreſſe it to that of the Iewes. If he be vnfortunate by Mars, it maketh

him more to encline to the lawe of the Turkes and Mahometiſts. If the ſaid part be in the houſes of Saturne at the natiuitie of a Iewe, or in the houſes of Mars at the natiuitie of a Turke, they ſhall denie theyr lawe: if the ſayd lords of the ſayd part be retrogrades, or otherwiſe ill diſpoſed. Saturne in the nynth at the natiuitie of a Iewe, doth nothing diminiſh his faith. Saturne in the ſaid houſe when he is fortunate, ſignifieth Dreames to be true. Mars and the tayle of the Dragon ſignifie them vaine and falſe. The other ſignificators doe aſlure them to be true.
            
            
               CHAP. XXVII. Of the action and profeſsion.
               HOW to knowe of what profeſsion the childe ſhall be, you muſt chiefely conſider if any Planet be in the tenth houſe, for he ſhal be Significator of the profeſsion: otherwiſe, you muſt come to the part of Fortune, and to his lord, to the part of the profeſſion, and to his lord, to the tenth houſe, and to his lord, and to the places of Mars, Mercurie and Venus.
               The Planet that vpon theſe places ſhal haue the moſt dignities, ſhalbe Significator of the profeſſion. The which if it be Saturne, it ſhall ſignifie a Husbandman, a good houſe-keeper, a Receiuer of rents, and many times a Gouernour of Townes, when he is in angles fortunate. Iupiter denoteth the officers, Iudges, Benefices, Prelates, Byſhops, Gouernours of the goods of the Church. Mars ſignifieth Captaines, men of warre, Coyners, Forgeours, and other that vſe to worke with fire and yron: and Phiſitions when he is in the aſpect of Venus.
               Sol repreſenteth Princes, Lords, Magiſtrates, Hunters, Treaſurers and Archers. Venus Players, Dauncers, Perfumers, Appothecaries, and in aſpect of Mars, Phiſitions. Mercurie, Aduocates, Notaries, Regiſters, Poets, Rymers, Phyloſophers, Mathematicians, Diuiners, wryters, Meſſengers and traders.
               
                  
The Moone, Embaſſadors, Counſellers, Conſuls, Rulers of Common wealth, Trauailers, Hunters. If there be many Significators, or if the principall bee coupled with many Planets, you muſt mingle the ſignifications of the one and of the other, and of the ſaid mixture, gather together the profeſsion comming of the concurrence of the ſtarres. You muſt alſo conſider in what houſe the ſayde Significators be, if they be within the ſecond, the profeſſion ſhall be of feates of merchandize and traffiques: if within the third or ninth, of feates of religion, or gathering the goods of the Church. If in angles, of Dominations &amp; gouernments. If in the fift of Embaſſages, legations, and other things of pleaſure. If in the ſixt, of feates of diſeaſes, of ſeruaunts and of Cattell. &amp;c. If the part of the honour comming of the profeſſion, be with his Lord fortunate, the Infant ſhall obtayne great credite and honour becauſe of his profeſsion. If they be vnfortunate, if hee doe neuer ſo well, he ſhall neuer gayne to himſelfe honor in the feates of his profeſsion.
            
            
               CHAP. XXVIII. Of dignities, offices, and honours.
               FOR the dignities, offices, charges and honors, you muſt haue reſpect to the tenth houſe, to the luminaries temporall, to the part of noblenes, to the part of gouernment, to the part of Magiſtrates, &amp; others appertaining to the tenth houſe, with theyr Lordes. The Planet that in the ſayde places ſhall haue moſt dignities, ſhall be Significator of the ſayd conſiderations in good or euill, according to his good or euill diſpoſition: particulerly alſo you muſt follow the ſayde places one after another to know of what ſide principally the ſayde dignities, offices and honours ought to come.
               Saturne in the tenth houſe, or in the aſcendant in natiuities by day, ſignifieth great aduauncement and honour after thirty yeeres, when he is not euill diſpoſed: in natiuities

by night, it denoteth continuall feare, to receiue damage of Princes and Kings. Mars in the ſayde places in natiuities by night, ſignifieth alſo great aduauncement, &amp; by day more then Saturne.
               The part of gouernment and his Lorde within any of the angles, witnes great fauour of Kings. Likewiſe you muſt iudge of the other part that we haue deducted vpon the tenth houſe. Mercurie in the tenth well diſpoſed and fortunate, promiſeth dignities, offices and honours, by reaſon of knowledge. Venus and the Moone becauſe of women. Iupiter for hys vertue. The Sunne and the head of the Dragon in the ſame houſe, denoteth as much. The two luminaries in theyr houſes or exaltations placed in the figure of Heauen, doe denote great aduauncement &amp; honour.
               That which Iupiter dooth alſo when hee receiueth the vertue of all the other Planets, &amp; communicateth hys owne to Saturne and the Sunne; and the fortunes and the luminaries when they be in the angles of Heauen. Manie Planets in the fourth houſe, denoteth great honour after death. If in the poynts of the angles be any fixed ſtarre of the firſt or ſecond greatnes, or other hauing the nature of lumynaries, it is a great ſigne of incredible aduancement. That which happeneth alſo when the ſayd ſtarres be ioyned to the lumynaries temporall, or to the parte of Fortune, or to his Lord, or to the Planets and parts that bee in the angles.
               They which haue Saturne in the tenth burnt, or the Lord of the tenth burnt, or be by Saturne oppreſſed, or that haue the tayle of the Dragon in the tenth, receiue commonly ſome forme of diſhonour, and often be depriued of theyr eſtate, vvhen the Fortunes doe not intermingle theyr fauourable beames: except when they be alſo vnfortunate in theyr proper houſes or exaltations, or in the ſignes of Aries and the Lyon.
               You muſt note that Saturne &amp; Mars, hinder greatly the good fortunes, vntil that the man hath paſſed the number

of yeres corriſpondent to the number of the ſmal yeres of the ſaid Planets: and if they hinder any more time, it ſhal bee vntill that the man ſhall accompliſh the number of yeeres aunſwering to the number of degrees, of the ouerthwart aſcentions of the Signe, in the which they ſhall be at the natiuity.
            
            
               CHAP. XXIX. Of companions and Friendes.
               YOV muſt for the Companions and Friendes, haue reſpect to Iupiter, the eleuenth houſe, the parte of friendes, the part of honourable companions. The Planet hauing moſt dignities in the ſaid places, ſhal be principall Significator of friends: the which after hys good or euill diſpoſition, ſhall denote honourable, faythfull, and profitable friendes: or vnprofitable, diſloyal, and of baſe condition. Iupiter and the Sunne in the ſaid houſe, ſignifie honourable companies and profitable: ſo dooth Venus, the Moone and Mercurie alſo in the ſaide place. Saturne in the eleuenth fortunat, witneſſeth graue friends, auncient and honourable. Mars, men of warre, Captaines and Lords.
               Saturne or Mars in the eleuenth out of their principal dignities, depriued of the beames of the fauourable Planets, ſignifie ſome great ſute againſt hys friendes, or ſome great euill by reaſon of them: as it happeneth commonly to the Aunſwerers and Suerties. The parts of honorable companions and of praiſe, with theyr Lords fortunate, ſignifyeth profite and honour on the ſide of friendes: vnfortunate denoteth the contrary. The part of friendes denoteth as much.
               The heade of the Dragon in the eleuenth houſe, gyueth fauour of friendes: the tayle denoteth a thouſande miſchiefes by reaſon of them.
            
            
               
               CHAP. XXX. Of ſutes and Enemies.
               THE fortunes in the ſeauenth and twelfth houſe, gyue victories againſt enemies, when they bee in good aſpect to the lord of the aſcendant. And cō
                  monly thoſe which haue theſe 2. houſes with theyr Lordes fortunate, be happy in theyr ſutes: the contrarie you muſt iudge, when they with theyr Lordes be vnfortunate. The ill fortunes in the ſayde places, ſignifie much ſtrifes and enemies. That doth alſo the parts of enemies, and of diſcord and accord, when they and theyr Lords be euill diſpoſed.
               The Lord of the twelfth houſe fortunate, it denoteth little puiſſaunce of enemies: vnfortunate denoteth the contrary. If one of the two ill fortunes be in the twelfe, and the other in the ſixt, in euill aſpect of the lumynaries temporall, or of the Lord of the aſcendant, the chylde ſhall be killed by his enemies. They which haue Saturne, or Mars, or the Moone oppoſite to the Sun in the Signe of Cancer, be commonly contrary to all the world. Mars in any of the foure angles, ingendereth naturally ſtryfe, ſutes, debates, and enmities againſt all the world: except when he is in a good aſpect of Iupiter and Venus. For then he doth expell hys ire and anger againſt the vices, &amp; of great zeale maintaineth the right of euery one.
               The Lorde of the aſcendant, or the Moone, or the Sunne vnfortunate in the twelfe houſe, denoteth great perſecutions and calamities of the enemies. The Lord of the aſcendant by the lord of the twelfe oppreſſed, teſtifieth that he ſhall die by the hand of his enemies.
               The Lord of the twelfe, and the Planets that be in the ſeauenth &amp; twelfe houſe, ſignifie the qualitie of enimies, (that is to vnderſtand) the Sunne ſignifieth the Princes &amp; great Lords, the Moone all the world, and Mars the men of warre. &amp;c.
            
            
               
               CHAP. XXXI. Of impriſonments and c
                     •
                  ptiuities.
               THE Lord of the aſcendant, or the Moone or the Sunne greatlie vnfortunate in the 12. 6. 8. and 4. houſe, doe ſignifie impriſonments, and death within the pryſons, or in captiuitie: principally when they be burned out of theyr principall dignities, and out of the ſignes of Aries and the Lyon, and when they bee oppreſſed by Saturne lorde of one of the ſayd houſes. Saturne and Mars in the angles of Heauen, ſignifie alwaies ſome impriſonment: and principally Saturne. Mercurie in the angles vnder the beames of the Sunne, receiuing an euill aſpect of ill fortunes, ſignifieth as much. If Mercurie or the lorde of the aſcendant gyue his vertue to Saturne, beeing in the eyght houſe, it ſignifieth that the chylde ſhall dwell long in priſon and captiuity.
               If the lord of the aſcendant bee in the twelfe in a ſigne of a humane figure, without aſpects of fortunes or of luminaries, hee ſhall be captiue and a ſlaue in his youth. If the lorde of the nynth be burned in any of the angles of Heauen, he ſhall be taken by the high-waies, and put in pryſon.
               The parts of priſon, and of paine, trauayle and affliction with theyr lords burnt, or otherwiſe vnfortunate, ſignifieth impriſonment and captiuitie. That dooth alſo the vnfortunes when they bee well dignified in the ſayde places.
               The partes of all enuies, and of the perrillous yeere doth ſignifie as much, when they with theyr Lordes bee greatly vnfortunate.
               The ſayde parts with theyr Lords fortunate, preſerueth from priſon, and from captiuitie.
            
            
               
               CHAP. XXXII. Of Horſes, Sheepe, and other beaſtes.
               THE fortunes and Planets fortunate within the 6. and twelfe houſe, yeelde the men happy in horſes and nouriſhing of beaſtes. The lords of the ſayde houſes fortunate, and coupled with the Significators of riches, ſignifie as much. Naturally the ſixt houſe denoteth Sheepe, and Goates, and other ſmall beaſtes, the 12. Horſes, Oxen, Kine, Camels, &amp; other great beaſtes. The ill fortunes within the ſayd houſes, or the lordes of the ſayd houſes vnfortunate, ſignifie loſſe and damage of the ſaid beaſtes.
               Saturne and Mars in the twelfe, maketh the horſes to fall with notable loſſe. The which they doe alſo whē they be elſwhere in the Signe of Sagitarius. The lorde of the natiuitie in the twelfe houſe in euill aſpect of the Lord of the twelfe, maketh hym fall from his horſe in great perrill of death, when the fortunes &amp; luminaries do not yeeld theyr amiable aſpects.
               If the twelfe be of Sagittarius or the Lyon, &amp; the lord of the aſcendant, or the Sunne, or the Moone be vnfortunate, hee ſhall fall from hys horſe and dye, if the fortunes within the eyght houſe doe not hinder the euill.
            
            The end of the firſt Booke.
         
         
            
            Of the Aſtronomical iudgements vpon the Natiuities, contayning particuler conſiderations. The ſecond Booke.
            
               CHAP. I. Of the ſignifications of the Planets.
               SAturne, hauing regard ouer the right part of Septentrion, ouer the earth and the water, ouer the melancholie, and ſometimes ouer the phlegme, groſſe humors, ouer the eares, the ſpleene, the bladder, the mawe, the ſinowes, and the bones. And ſignifieth pale men, or black, leane, penſiue, ſolitarie, fearefull, raylers, graue, contemplators, labourers, Maſons, buyers of rents, Vſurers, Carpenters, Fiſhers, Merchants of oyles, Leather, Fiſh, tyles, ſtone, allome. &amp;c. Of diſeaſes it ſignifieth leperouſnes, cankers, rottennes, quarterne-feuers, opilations, dropſies, flixe of the belly, collicke, burſtneſſe in the coddes, miſconception of women, the gowte in the legs, gowte in the wriſtes, Sciatiqua, deafenes, the falling ſicknes, fooliſh melancholy, very difficult in fetching breath, &amp; others, ingendered of groſſe humors or of wind, which endure long. Of ages, oldnes: of partes of the yeere Autumne: of colours the black, cleer, tawny, dark: of ſauors, the ſharpe and abſtringent, pricking with ſharpnes: of dayes, the Saturday: of Regions, Bauieres, Saxony, Romanie, Conſtance, and the firſt Clymate. Of particuler places, Caues, Lakes, Pondes, cloſe places, olde &amp; ruinous houſes, ſolitary places, obſcure deſerts &amp; ſtinking places.
               
                  
Iupiter regarding the occident, the ayre, the blood with the vitall ſpyrits, the lunges, the ſides, the lyuer and the veynes: and ſignifieth men of good ſtature, and ful faced, bald, curled, white with a pleaſant redneſſe intermingled, hauing the eyes indifferent great, the noſtrils reaſonable ſhort, the fore-teeth reaſonable great, honeſt men, gratious, bleſſed, religious, Abbots, Byſhops, Prelates, Officers, Iudges, Magiſtrates. With copulation of Saturne, it ſignifieth Nigromancers, Enchaunters, Sorcerers. With Mars, Phiſitions. With the Sunne, appeaſors of quarrels, controuerſies and diſputations. With Venus, Muſitions. With Mercurie, Mathematicians. With the Moone, Geometricians, Geographers, &amp; Hidrografers. Of Diſeaſes, it ſignifieth burning Feuers, Quincies, Plurifies, ſwellings, Impoſtumes, phlegmes, and other, comming of bloode. Of ages, betweene age and youth. Of the partes of the yeere, the Spring-time.
               Of colours, as cleere as a Saphire, as yellowe as a Citterne, greene, and a lyttle drawing vpon the redde. Of ſauours ſweete and amiable. Of dayes, the Thurſday. Of Countries, Babylon, Perſia, Hungarie, Spayne, and the ſecond Clymate. Of particuler places, churches, pallaces, priuiledged places, cleane, honeſt, and religious.
               Mars looking towards the South, the fire, chollericke humors, the reynes, the payne in the noſtrils, the gaule, the genitories. He denoteth men with red faces, and the skinne redde, the face round, the eyes yellow, horrible to behold, furious men, cruell, deſperate, proude, ſedicious, ſouldiers, Captaines, Smythes, Colliers, Bakers, Alcumiſtes, Armourers, Furniſhers, Butchers, Chirurgions, Barbers, Sargiants and Hangmen, according as they ſhal be well or euill diſpoſed.
               With Saturne, commonly it ſignifieth Chirurgions. With Iupiter, Naturall Philoſophers &amp; Phyſitions. With the Sunne, healers of eyes. VVith Venus, Barbers and Sheremen. With Mercury, men of skil to let blood. With the Moone, Tooth-drawers, and clenſers of the eares. Of

diſeaſes, it denoteth tertian Feuers, and continuall impediments, peſtilences, megrams of the head, carbunckles, ring-wormes, bliſters, chollericks and burnings, madnes, phrenſies, iſſues of blood, vomiting of blood, chollericke paſsions, the yellow Iaunders, the bloody-flixe, &amp; others, comming of chollericke humors and burnings. Of ages, the flower of youth. Of the parts of the yeere, the Sommer.
               Of colours, red, flame-colour, ſanguine, and drawing to an yron colour. Of ſauours, the bitter and ſharpe. Of Of the dayes, Tueſday. Of Regions, Getulie, Lombardie, and the third Clymate. Of places particuler, houſes of Smythes, Coyners of money, ſlaughters, furnices, all places dedicated to fyer, yron and blood.
               The Sunne hauing domination ouer the Eaſt &amp; South, ouer the fire, ouer the pure blood, and ouer the vital ſpyrites, ouer the eyes, ouer the brayne, ouer the hart. And it ſignifieth wiſemen, prudent, dyſcreete, couetous of glorie and of honour: of an indifferent ſtature, browne of colour, great bearded, yellow eyed, the face marked, a great voyce, and very ill fauoured. Honourable men, Officers, Magiſtrates, Lords, Princes, Kings and Gouernours of Countries and great hunters. And with Saturne, denoteth principall Meaters, Renters, and labourers honourable. With Iupiter, Beneficed men, Pryors, Abbots, and Prelates, or Iudges and Officers of iuſtice. With Mars, Captaines and Conductors of warres. With Venus, Gouernours of the goods of Princes, and officers of the ſame. With Mercurie, Counſellers, Secretaries, Chauncellors. With the Moone, Legates, Embaſſadours, and honourable meſſengers.
               Of diſeaſes, hote rumes vpon the face, and vppon the eyes, rednes of the face, tympanies, palpitation of the hart, dolor of the heade comming of too much bloode, or with tarrying long in the beames of the Sunne. Of ages, youth. The parts of the yeere, the beginning of Sommer. Of colours the yellow, the cleere redde, colour of golde.
               
                  
Of ſauours, ſowernes and ſweetneſſe agreeably intermingled. Of dayes, Sunday. Of Countries, Italy, Cicillia, Bohemia, and the fourth Clymate. Of particuler places, houſes of Princes, Pallaces, Theaters, and other large places, excellent and cleere.
               Venus Dominatrix ouer the right parte of the Eaſt, vpon the ayre and water, vppon the mixtion of phlegme, blood and ſpyrits, and ſeede of generation. Vppon the reynes, belly, nauill, lyuer, backe, and other partes dedicated to generation. And ſignifieth white men or browne, with ſome redneſſe intermingled: fayre faced, pleaſant lookes, hawke-noſed, full of hayre, ioyfull, laughter, liberall, pleaſers, dauncers, entertayners of women, players, perfumers, muſitions, meſſengers of loue. With Saturne, it ſignifieth Preachers, and others that ſing and ioyfullie aſſiſt at deceaſes and burials. With Iupiter, muſitians and others, which ſing the prayſe of God in ſolemne hymnes. With Mars, trumpeters and dromſlades in warre. Wyth Mercurie, ſingers of rymes &amp; poetry. With the Moone, ſingers of common ſongs. Of diſeaſes, impoſtumes, and of moyſt matters, fyſtuloes, imbecility of the ſtomach, of the reynes, and of the part of generation, folly comming by too much loue, the French-pockes with his ſupporters, and other, comming of cold and moyſt matter, and of venims.
               Of ages, young yeeres: of parts of the yeere, the beginning of the Spring-time: of colours, the white, greene, redde, and a little yellow; of ſauours, the ſweete, delectable, and ſauourlieſt. Of dayes, Friday: of Regions, Arabia, Auſtria, Sweecherland, and the fift Clymate. Of particuler places, neere gardens, fountaynes, Chambers well decked, halles hanged with Tapeſtry, beds wel adorned, and others, dedicated to playes, dauncies, ſongs and al voluptuouſneſſe.
               Mercurie beeing chiefe ouer the Septentrion ouer the water and earth, and of the ſpyrits of beaſtes, and ouer the confuſion of humors. Ouer the hands, feete, armes, ſhoulders,

tongue, mouth and teeth. And ſignifieth men neyther white nor blacke: leane: of ſmal ſtature: long fingered: long faced: high fore-headed: the noſe ſtraight and long: little beard: full of hayre: the eyes little &amp; quicke: ſubtile men: ingenious: vnconſtant: Rymers: Poets: Aduocates: Orators: Phyloſophers: Sooth-ſayers: Arithmeticians: Merchants: and buſie fellowes.
               With Saturne, Geomitricians: Architects: With Iupiter, Lawyers: Cannons: and thoſe that keepe the Regiſters of the benefits of Churches and ſutes. With Mars, Sargiants of the bande, Archers of the Garde. &amp;c. With the Sunne, Maiſters of the houſes of Princes and great Lords: and theyr Secretaries &amp; Stewards. With Venus, Muſitions: Apothicaries and Perfumers. The Moone, trauailers, meſſengers &amp; traffiquers. Of diſeaſes, vertigo or turning of the head: lightnes of the braine: like to follie: fooliſh imaginations: lets of the tongue: pthiſickes: iſſues in the legges, feete and hands: and other, that haue cauſes hydden, and that come by certaine times. Of ages, the time betweene ſeauen and fourteene yeeres: Of the parts of the yeere, Autumne. Of colours, the ſtrangeſt, diuerſt and mixtious. Of ſauours, the ſtrangeſt &amp; of newe taſt. Of dayes, Wedneſday. Of Countries, Egipt, Greece, England, Flaunders: Paris: and the 6. Clymate. Of particuler places, ſhops: fayers: cōmon-markets: ſchooles: halles of Lawyers.
               The Moone doth gouerne ouer the right part of the Weſt: ouer the water: ouer the phlegme: ſweatinges: monthly flowers: and like ſuperfluities. Ouer the ſtomacke: the belly: the brayne: the lunges: the breſt and the eyes. And ſignifieth men of fayre ſtature, white, and the face round and ſpotted: the eyes a little blacke, and a little lowring: long bearded: hys eye-browes knit together: amiable men, peaceable: Trauailers: Pilgrims: Hunters: Embaſſadors: Legates: Conſuls: Atturneyes: Benchers: Gouernours of Townes: principall in deedes of pollicie.
               
                  
With Saturne, it ſignifieth Carters and vile Workers. With Iupiter, Geomitricians and Geographers. Wyth Mars, Drawers of teeth: Alcumiſts and Blowers. With the Sunne, honourable meſſengers. With Venus, carriers of packs. With Mercury, Poets, Rymers, meſſengers, trauailers and traffiquers. Of diſeaſes, gowtes of the feete &amp; wriſtes: ſciatiqua: dropſies: lyttargy: palſies: rumes: ſhaking of the members: drowſie ſickneſſes: flixe of the bellie: vomitings: fiſtuloes: wormes: and other cauſes of cold and moyſtnes. Of ages, the infancie: of the partes of the yeere, Winter: of colours, white: yellow: greene: of ſauours, the ſaltiſh: freſh: or without fauour: of daies, Monday. Of Countries, Flaunders: Affrick: and the ſeauenth Clymate. Of particuler places, fieldes: fountaines: mountaines: Hauens of the Sea: woods: high-waies and deſert places.
            
            
               CHAP. II. ¶ Of the ſignifications of the twelue Signes.
               ARies doth gouerne ouer the hart of the Orient, ouer the fire, ouer the chollerique humors &amp; hote: ouer the beginning of the Spring: ouer the head: the noſe, the face, the eares and the eyes. And ſignifieth leane men, redde coloured, flat noſed, chollericke, ſtrong, and right men of warre: Captaines: ſouldiours: Alcumiſtes, and other martialiſts. Of diſeaſes, it denoteth lytargy: madneſſe: iſſues of bloode: rednes of the face: filthineſſe: falles: hurts: and all ſickneſſes violent and continuall.
               Of colours, redde: yellowe: and ſanguine colour: Of ſauours, the ſweete. Of Countries, Brittany: Almanie: Inde: Iuda: England: Naples: Florence: Fauence: Imole: Capne: Ferrara: Venice: Verone: Pauie: Craconie: Marſelle: Saragoſſe: and the third Clymate.
               
                  
Of particular places, feildes, paſtures, houſes of Forgiours of money, and places of blood, and iuſtice.
               Taurus gouerneth ouer the left parte of the meridies, ouer the earth, ouer the melancholy humours, ouer the middle of the ſpringe, ouer the necke, and throate. And ſignifieth little men, well fleſhed with great ſhoulders, great eyes, large bellyed, paynefull men, liberall, truſtie, voluptuous, meſſengers of loue, dauncers, players. Of ſickneſſes, the kings euill, Caterches, Squinacies, and other ſickneſſes of the necke. Of Coloure, the greene and white. Of ſauours, the ſweete with adſtriction. Of Countreys the Sea coaſtes of Aſia the leſſer, Cyprus, Media, Perſia, Campanie, Rhetia, Sweathland, Lorraine, Bolongne, Sene, Montorie, Tarrante, Parme, Panorme, Capne, Salerne, Verone, and the vi. Climate. Of particuler places, Feildes, Tillages, Vines very neere greene, Gardens, and other pleaſant and odoriferous places.
               Gemini gouerneth ouer the right parte of Occident, ouer the ayre, ouer the blood, and other end of the ſpring time, ouer the ſhoulders, armes, and handes. And ſignifieth men of middle ſtature, fayre faced, and bodyed, ſtore of haire, little eyes, labouring men, ſubtile, ingenious, prudent teachers, fraudulent, Arethmetricians, Geometricians, Aſtrologians, Orators, Poets, Aduocates, Witches, Southſayers, Buſie fellowes, Weauers. Of ſickneſſes, Phleames, Foroncles, and others comming of blood in the ſayd parte. Of Colours, the mixtures. Of Sauors, the ſweete. Of Countreyes, Hircanye, Armenie, Montiane, Syrenian
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , Marmari
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , Lowe Egipte, England, Sordigne, Brabant, Flaunders, Lombardie, Viterbie, Vercel, Norremberge, Louayne, Magonce, Brudges, London, Paris, Cordube. Of particular places, Fayres, Schooles, Shoppes, places of high mountaines, places of hunting of birdes, places garniſhed within with inſtruments of muſique.
               Cancer gouerneth the heart of the Septentrion, ouer the water, ouer the hollow humours, and Phlegmatiques,

ouer the breſt, ſides, and lunges, and ouer the dugges and ſtomacke. And ſignifieth amiable men, peaceable, modeſt, white, full faced, the noſe indifferent long, lardge ſhoulders, little bearded, ſlowthfull, vnconſtant, and effeminate, Nauigators, Strangers, Conſulls, Attournies, &amp;c. Of diſeaſes, Litargy, Leprouſie, darkeneſſe of the ſight, galling of the skinne, and euill ſickneſſes, of the face and bodie. Of Colours, the white and yellow. Of ſauours, the ſalt, and his contrary freſhnes. Of Countries, Bythinie, Phrigia, Affrica, Carthage, Scotland, the kingdome of Grenade, the Countie of Burgony, Pruſie, Holland, Zelande, Conſtantinople, Thunis, Venis, Millayne, Genes, Luques, Piſe, Treues, Madebourge, Berne: Of particular places: pondes, lakes, riuers, the ſea, and portes of the ſea.
               Leo, gouerneth the left parte of Orient, ouer the fire, ouer the choller, ouer the heart, ſtomacke, liuer and backe. And ſignifieth fayre men, ſtraight, the noſe broade and little, great eares, with a little ſtrong looke, the face browne, the body reddiſh, hairy, couragious and of great heart, Princes, Officers, Magiſtrates, Gouernours Kings. Of diſeaſes, ſhaking of the heart, ſwoundings. Of Colours the yellow and redde as golde. Of ſauors, the bitter, and the ſtrong. Of Countries, Italie, Fraunce, Apulie, Sicillia, Chaldea, Bohemia, Rome, Rauenna, Prage, Vlme, Mantoue, Cremone, Syracuſa: Of particular places, noble landes, Lordſhips, Caſtels Townes, Pallaces, and Royall buildings.
               Virgo gouerneth ouer the right part of the Meridies, ouer the earth, ouer the malancholly, ouer the gutts, belly and diaphragme: And ſignifieth men of indifferent greatnes, the bodie ſtraight, the face ſayre, good voyce, ſhining haire, little eyes, prudent, learned, ingenious, couetous of glorie and honour, Scriueners, Arithmeticians, Geometricians, Boate men. Of diſeaſes, the collique, (the diſeaſe which cauſeth the patient to vomit his excremēts at his mouth called Iliaque) &amp;c. Of Colours, the white

&amp; purple: of ſauours, the aſtringēt: of Countries, Greece, Achaia, Creet, Meſopotania, Aſſiria, Cicilia, Athēs, Rodes, Alexandria, Hieruſalē, Corinth, Tarrante, Beneuent, Farrare, Pauia, Baſle, Paris, Lyons, Tholoſe. Of particular places, faires: ſhops: ſchooles: and arrable grounds.
               Libra gouerneth ouer the hart of the Occident, ouer the aire, ouer the blood, ouer the beginning of Autume, &amp; ouer the reynes: and denoteth ſimple mē, honorable, faire faced with whitnes ouer al the body, the eyes a little troubled or ſpoyled, plaiers, dauncers, muſitiās, hunters, iudges. Of diſeaſes, ſuppreſſiō of the vrine, iſſue of blood in the lower parts, ſtones in the reynes, &amp; darknes of the eyes. Of colours, the greene: of ſauours, ſweete: of Regions Bactriane, Caſpie, Thebes, Trogloditi
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , Ethiopia, Tuſcia, Auſtria, Sauoy, Danphina, Gaiete, Plaiſance, Argenton, Vienna in Auſtria, Franckford, Spire, Auguſte, Arles, Liſbone. Of particular places, where ſuites be iudged vppon, all high places and mountaynes bearing corne, grapes, or other fruites.
               Scorpio gouerneth ouer the left part of the Septentrion: ouer the water: ouer the phlegmati
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   humours and aquoſits, ouer the parts dedicated to generation. And ſignifieth men very deformed: broad breſted: the head deformed: great ſpeakers: bablers: mockers: lyers: gluttons: voluptuous: traytors: ſpyes: poyſonnours. Of diſeaſes, darkneſſe of the eyes: ſcabbes: ſcurffes: kanckers: leoprouſneſſe: falling off the hayre: and deformed diſeaſes in the face: and all the bodie impoyſoned by violence of medicines, &amp;c. Of colours, the redde and tawnie. Of ſauours, ſalt and freſh. Of Regions, Syria, Cappadocia: the lande of the Moores: Catalongne: Bauaires: Trapezonce: Saxonie: Padua: Vrbin: Brixie: Valence in Spaine: Vienna in Danphinna. Of particular places, vineyardes: and gardens euill trimmed, deſert places: ſtincking: infected: abounding in woormes: ſnakes: and ſcorpions, &amp;c.
               Sagitarius gouerneth ouer the right parte of the Orient:

ouer the fire: ouer choller: ouer the end of Autumme: ouer the thighes: and all ſuperfluous partes: as a ſixth part of the finger &amp;c. And repreſenteth men of right and high ſtature: the face yellowe or reddiſh, the breſt large: Cattes eyes: iuſt men and pittifull: &amp; ceremonious: iudges: magiſtrates: prelats: beneficed men marchants, hunters. Of diſeaſes, darknes of the eyes, falles from high places: hurts by horſes: Agues &amp; woundes. Of colours: cleere: yellow. Of ſauours: ſtrong &amp; ſharp with ſome ſweetnes intermingled: of Countries, Tuſcan, Spayne: Arabia the happye: Portugale: Hungarie: Slauonia: Volterre: Mutine: Bude: Caſchonia: Narbona: Auignon: Tolete. Of particular places, Gardens: Wayes: Mountaynes: or where menne keepe horſes.
               Capricorne gouerneth ouer the heart of the meridies, ouer the earth: melanchollie: the knees: ouer the beginning of the Winter. And ſignifieth little ſtature, a little rounde head: the face browne: faire noſe: fayre eyes: chollerique and ſadde: ſubtle: ſecrete: prudent: paynefull: ſheepheards: fiſhers: marryners: carpenters: buyers of Rentes. Of diſeaſes, ſcabbes: gaules: infirmyties of the skinne: hinderaunces of the hearing: of the voyce: of the eyes: iſſues of blood in the lower parts. Of colours blacke and earthly. Of ſauours, the bitter and aſtringent. Of Regions, Macedonia, Thracia, Indea, Brandebourge: Anchone: Fauence: Tortonne: Auſburge, Conſtans, Gand, Malnies. Of particular places, Gardens, Fountaynes, Riuers, Fields tilled, Land plowed, Priſoners, Caues, Obſcure places, deepes; and full of fewmes and vapours.
               Aquarius gouerneth ouer the left parte of the Occident, ouer the ayre, ouer the blood, ouer the legges, ouer the middle of Winter. And ſignifieth fayre men, fayer &amp; ſomwhat long faced, &amp; the face ſomwhat red, the breſt or the elbowes marked, and men Curteous, Scotiable, Couetous, Prudent, giuen to the actes of Saturnins.

Of diſeaſes, quarterne feuers, the blacke iaunders, &amp;c. Of Colours, the greene and darke yellow. Sauours, ſweete. Of Countries, Arabia, Ethiopia, Sarinatia, Oxione, Tartaria, Denmarke, Picmount, Mountferrat, Piſaure. Of particular places, Lakes, Pondes, Cloſe places, Caues, Sepulchers and infamous houſes.
               Piſces gouerneth ouer the right part of the Septentrion ouer the water, phlegme, aquiſits, and ouer the feete, and ouer the end of winter. And ſignifieth men of whitiſh colour, delicate, faire foreheaded, fayre breaſted, faire bearded, the eyes open and indifferent great, and indifferent ſickly: Fiſhers, and Nauigators. Of diſeaſes, gaules vppon the skinne, vlcers and deformed ſpottes vppon the skinne payne in the feete. Of Colours, the greene, white &amp; mixtures. Of ſauors ſalt and freſh Of Regions, Lydia, Lycia, Cicilia, Pamphilia, Calabria, Normandie: Rattisbone: Roane: Compoſtella, Of particular places: port of the Sea: heades of Riuers, Pondes and watriſh places.
            
            
               CHAP. III. Of that which the Plannets ſignifie in the ſayde Signes.
               SAturne in his ſignes of Capricorne and Aquarius in Natiuities by day giueth knowledge and loue of noble men: and of credit and great riches principally in the Aſcendant: with the part of Fortune: and maketh the man graue, prudent: proude and mellanchollie: and firſt of all his bretheren, or moſt aduaunced. In Natiuities by night giueth great payne and trauayle and many diſeaſes. Iupiter in the ſayd ſigne, maketh the man of little courage, vnfortunate in the goodes of the Church, otherwiſe of ſmall riches, or alwayes poore.
               Mars maketh him bolde, a great enterpriſer of matters, and not in vayne, and maketh him ſee the death of his bretheren.
               The Sunne in the natiuities by day ſignifieth that hee ſhall be perfect and happie in all his enterpriſes. In natiuities

by night that he ſhall haue vnconſtant fortune.
               Venus maketh him an Adulterer and effeminate, and denoteth that his wiues ſhall not liue long.
               Mercurie cauſeth him to haue impeachment in his tongue, and maketh the man euill ſpoken otherwiſe, and which haunteth the companie of men of knowledge and of Religion.
               The Moone maketh the man too ſlowthfull, and one of euill eſtimation: and his mother alſo, and ſignifieth imbicillitie of the eyes and great coughes.
               
                  In the houſes of Iupiter. ♐ ♓
                  Saturne in the houſes of Iupiter, which bee Sagitarius &amp; Piſces maketh the man fayer, rich, mighty and faithfull in natiuities by day: In natiuities by night, ſtrife againſt men of authoritie, and neere the death of his Father.
                  Iupiter ſignifieth riches, honour, great creditte and offices.
                  Mars yeeldeth the men noble, gouernours in warres &amp; friendes of Princes.
                  The Sunne maketh them beneficed men, prelats, officers and more aduaunced then any of their familie, they ſhalbe alwayes greatly couetous.
                  Venus giueth them goodes of the Church, or of the ſide of women; and maketh them diſcreet, honeſt, among the which they ſhall haue great ſtrife againſt theyr parents, famylies and friendes.
                  Mercurie maketh them iuſt, men of good eſtimation, which by their proper vertue ſhall come to the knowledge &amp; loue of great Lordes and Kings.
                  The Moone yeeldeth them chiefe and moſt honored among their friendes: maketh them alſo couetous, ſound and of long life.
               
               
                  In the houſe of Mars. ♈ ♏
                  Saturne giueth great anger and cruell malice.
                  Iupiter maketh the man happie, and afriende of great

Lordes, and a Conductor of warres, principall in the ſigne of Aries.
                  Mars within his houſes ſignifieth Captaines, Gouernours in warres, and great Lordes.
                  The Sunne, hote diſeaſes, in the ſigne of Scorpio: in the ſigne of Aries great aduauncement.
                  Venus denoteth luxurie and all voluptuous villanie, but againſt nature, and euill dealing to women. Alwayes in the ſigne of Aries ſhe maketh him hate women, principally if the moone be in the ſame ſigne, and if the ſunne be in a maſculine signe.
                  Mercurie, maketh the man a lyer, an euill perſon, a deceiuer, a babler and a demaunder of vniuſt thinges: otherwiſe eloquent, ſubtle in his affayres, diligent, ſuſpicious, a nigromancer, a little falſe or a theefe.
                  The moone denoteth euill companions, in perill of being drowned: and short end by the ſea.
               
               
                  In the houſes of the Sunne. ♌
                  Saturne in the signe of Leo: being a houſe of the Sunne: ſygnifieth good Fortune and long life to the father.
                  Iupiter maketh the man wiſe: of good ſpirite: of good nature: amiable: which by vertue shall come to the knoweledge and loue of great Kinges and princes.
                  Mars denoteth violent death, great ſickneſſes, loſſe of goodes, infirmyties of the eyes. and of the Stomacke.
                  The Sunne in his ſayde houſe ſignifieth great and incredible aduauncement, in Angles or Houſes ſuccedant, when the Natiuitie is by daye: VVhen it is by night ſygnifieth Sadneſſe, Enuies, and a ſhort ende of the Father.
                  Venus, great loue, great couetouſnes, and impudent life, when Iupiter dooth not regard her.
                  Mercurie: good writers, men of knowledge, good memorie, and of great councell.
                  
                     
The moone, honourable companions, and viuacitie of the ſpirite.
               
               
                  In the houſes of Venus. ♉ ♎
                  Saturne denoteth impudent life, loue of maydes &amp; women of ſmall diſcretion, diſeaſes by reaſon of leacherie.
                  Iupiter honourable companions, loue of great lordes, profit by the ſide of women, or Eccleſiaſticall goodes, or comming by the men of the Church.
                  Mars, furious men, raueſhers of women, ſhameleſſe in their leacherie, vnto the conſtraynings of their parents &amp; friendes.
                  In the ſigne of Taurus, maketh the man, falſe and trayterous.
                  In the ſigne of Libra denoteth ſome hurt by irō or fire.
                  The Sunne maketh him contēplatiue, iuſt, interperter of dreames, curious in the ſecreets of nature, and a louer of pilgrimages.
                  Venus ſignifieth ioyfulnes, great proſperity, happy in effecting his entepriſes, but he ſhal loue womē reprehended Mercurie giueth many good &amp; profitable friendes: and yeeldeth the man pleaſant, ioyfull, and a muſitian.
                  The moone giueth profit by women.
               
               
                  In the houſes of Mercurie. ♊ ♍
                  Saturne, maketh the man verye skilfull, wiſe, and of great iudgement: which hath enuious menne purſuing him, an impediment in his ſpeach, his anger violent.
                  Iupiter maketh him alſo skilfull, or a marchant, a man of good fayth, and more rich then his parents.
                  Mars, ſlowthfull, prudent, ſubtile, men of warre.
                  Sagitarius buſie fellowes, counterfeytors of letters and forgers.
                  The ſunne giueth aboundance of knowledge aſwell in matters of iudgements as in mathematickes.
                  Venus companies &amp; loue of men of the Church, otherwiſe ſhe doth yeelde them very leacherous.
                  
                     
Mercurie in his proper houſes ſignifieth men of all knowledge, philoſophers, mathematicians: Orators, Aduocates, Poets, Rimers Southſayers, &amp; skilfull in knauery.
                  The Moone good life and long, great vnderſtanding in the affayers which he taketh in hande good fortune in merchandizes and in loue of young maydens.
               
               
                  In the houſe of the Moone. ♋
                  Saturne greate ſickneſſe loſſe of goodes: hurt in the eyes, voyages from the which hee ſhall neuer returne, or very late with great payne.
                  Iupiter: loue of honourable men good renowne and good fortune.
                  Mars: ſwiftneſſe of ſpirit, raſh, bold enterpriſers, blindnes of the eyes, loſſe of goodes by his mother.
                  The Sunne, good renowne, and if he be ioyned to the tayle of the Dragon, or to Saturne or Mars, blindneſſe of eyes, perill of drowning, frequenting voiages.
                  Venus ſignifieth, inconſtancy, &amp; ſhamleſſe lecherie.
                  Mercurie good will, chaſtitie, fidelitie, and happie fortune in deedes of marchandiſe.
                  The Moone, hooly, and profitable in voiagaes, Traffiques and marchandize when ſhe is fortunate: or when ſhe is vnfortunate, continuall ſickneſſes, hurts in the eyes, perill of death by land and water.
               
            
            
               CHAP. IIII. Of the aſpects of the Plannets betweene them.
               
                  ☌THE Coniunctiō of Saturne &amp; Iupiter giueth faire poſſeſſions, farmes rents, houſes, &amp; charges of the  affaires of the king, profitable if Mars do not behold them.
               The coniunction of Saturne &amp; Mars, ſignifieth that the child ſhalbe truſted: but he ſhal not accompliſh his enterpriſes without great difficulty, &amp; ſhall die ſooner then his father &amp; mother, &amp; yet his brethren ſhall die before him.
               
                  
The coniunction of Saturne and of the Sunne, loſſe of patrimony, great trauaile to gette goods, and moſt in the natiuities by night.
               The coniunction of Saturne and Venus, denote that the man ſhal haue no male chyldren, that he ſhal eſpouſe ſome old woman, or ſome widdowe, or ſome of euil condition, or a baſtard: or other ſtaine of hys honour, or by the which his parents haue had ſome diſcredite.
               The coniunction of Saturne and Mercury, doth yeelde him a poore vagabonde, needy, of no miſtery, the which hath an impediment in hys ſpeech.
               The coniunction of Saturne and Luna, weakenes of bodie, loſſe by the ſide of his Parents.
               The coniunction of Iupiter &amp; Mars, ſignifieth, riches, rule and gouernment of warres, and of good renowne.
               The coniunction of Iupiter and the Sunne, pouerty &amp; neede if it be not Orientall, for then it promiſeth good fortune to the father, to hym, and to his children.
               The coniunction of Iupiter and Venus, good inſtitution, amity of honourable men, and profit of them, and of the wife and chyldren.
               The coniunction of Iupiter and Mercury, ſignifieth Lawyers, Secretaries and Chauncellers.
               The coniunction of Iupiter &amp; the Moone, great riches.
               The coniunction of Mars and the Sunne, loſſe of patrimony, damage of goods, and ſhort lyfe to the father, and great perrill of the child to be burnt.
               The coniunction of Mars and Venus, ſutes, ſtrifes, debates by reaſon of women, adulterers with women of infamous condition.
               The coniunction of Mars &amp; Mercury, lyers, deceiuers, eloquent, dilligent, and bablers.
               The coniunction of Mars and the Moone, ſhorte lyfe, woundes, blowes, danger of violent death by yron or by fier, or by falles and ruines.
               The coniunction of Sol &amp; Venus, praiſe, good renown, fauour of the common people, eſpecially of women.
               
                  
The coniunction of Sol &amp; Mercurie, wiſdom, ſcience, great aduauncement, and eſtimation to be very skilfull.
               The coniunction of the Sunne &amp; of the Moone, ſhort lyfe, gouernment, and honourable company.
               The coniunction of Venus and Mercury, maketh the man pleaſant, ioyfull, a player, a dauncer, muſitian, well furniſhed, and bringeth hym damage by the ſide of women. If they be conioyned vnder the beames of the Sun, they make great hinderance in the parts of generation.
               The comunction of Venus &amp; the Moone, maketh the man fayre, pleaſant, proude, an adulterer: and of whom his wife is an adultreſſe, if Mars do caſt his beames without aſpect of Iupiter.
               The coniunction of Mercury &amp; Luna, denoteeh good renowne, ſcience, &amp; vnconſtancy of maners &amp; of fortune.
               The tryne aſpect of Saturne and Iupiter, ſignifieth inheritaunces, 
                     △
                   poſseſsions, faire houſes, riches, meetings with treaſures, great gaynes: whē they be infortuate places of the figure.
               The tryne of Saturne and Mars, great aduauncement, dignities, great credite, rule and gouernment of townes &amp; Countries, and death of brethren.
               The tryne of Saturne and the Sunne, rule, offices, dignities, great renowne, in natiuities by day: in the night it maketh the diſperſing of patrimony goods, &amp; afterwards by his deedes and vertue ſhall recouer and obtaine more greater.
               The tryne of Saturne &amp; Venus, maketh the man truſtie, milde, honeſt, ſhame-faced, of good conuerſation, of good renowne, the which by men of baſe condition ſhall be purſued with enuie, and ſhall marry late.
               The tryne of Saturne and Mercurie, maketh the man prudent, ſubtile in all his affayres, a man of good &amp; great knowledge, ingenious, induſtrious, an Arithmetrician, Geomitrician, Aſtrologian, and a Geographer, Preſident in matters of accounts and calculations: Chauncellors, Secretaries and Regiſters.
               
                  
The tryne of Saturne &amp; of the Moone, fauour of great Lords and Kings, glory, honour and gouernment.
               The tryne of Iupiter and Mars, ſignifieth audacity, honour, victory, fauour of Kings, gouernment of townes &amp; great credite.
               The tryne of Iupiter and Sol being greatly fauourable, to glory, honour, gouernment, credite, and giueth great riches, fayre poſseſsions, and fayre chyldren.
               The tryne of Iupiter &amp; Venus, denoteth beauty, grace, faithfulnes, honeſty, and profit of wiues and friends, dignities and inheritaunces by theyr meanes.
               The tryne of Iupiter and Mercurie, maketh the man ingenious, ſubtile, forward, of good iudgement &amp; aduiſe, happy in his enterpriſes, a Iudge, Officer, great Lord, Secretary, well vnderſtanding the ſecretes of nature and Aſtrologie.
               The tryne of Iupiter with the Moone, ſignifieth nobleneſſe, honour, glory, good renowne, loue of vertue, fidelity, principality and gouernment.
               The tryne of Mars with the Sunne, great aduancement, great credite, dignities, gouernments adminiſtrations of Common-wealthes, and Conductors of warres.
               The tryne of Mars with Venus, gayne, riches, goods of women, proude, arrogant, braue and lecherous.
               The tryne of Mars and Mercurie, prudent, crafty, ſubtile of ſpyrite, and maketh the man to ſtudie ſecretly: a good Aduocate, Preſident in matters of account, &amp; rich.
               The tryne of Mars with Luna, maketh him happy in all his affaires: Preſident in matters of account, an honorable officer, &amp; a great Lord, with great renowne.
               The trine of the Sunne with Venus, ſignifieth the ſame that the tryne of Mars and Venus ſignifieth, with great honour of the ſaid ſignifications.
               The tryne of the Sun with Mercury and Luna, likewiſe as of Mars, with great honour and profit.
               The tryne of Venus with Mercurie, braue, pleaſant, graue, beauty, and happy enterpriſes with profit.
               
                  
The tryne of Venus &amp; the Moone, beauty, grace, brauerie, pride, and adultery.
               The tryne of Mercury with the Moone, maketh the man greatly eſteemed in hys profeſsion: be it in muſicke, paynting, or other pleaſant induſtry: or in al knowledge, or in merchandiſe or office.
               The Sextiles aſpects, make the ſame effects which the trynes make; except that the Sextiles bee not of ſo perfect vertue.
               The Quadrate aſpect of Saturne and Iupiter, ſignifieth loſſe of patrimoniall goods, great aduerſities, hinderaunces 
                     □
                   in all enterpriſes: vaine cogitations, principally when Saturne is eleuated ouer Iupiter, without receiuing hym.
               The quadrate of Saturne and Mars, ſignifieth aſmuch, and further maketh knowne the death of brethren.
               The quadrate of Saturne and the Sunne out of the ſayd ſignifications, bringeth great damage to the honour, and ſpoyleth the body with cold diſeaſes and contractions of the ſinowes; and maketh the father die before the mother, and yeeldeth the chyld not agreeable to his father.
               The quadrate of Saturne with Venus, denoteth loſſe of goods, pouertie, myſerable fortune to women, vnciuility, when Saturne holdeth the right part of the aſpect. For when Venus holdeth it, the chyld ſhall be ſhame faced and of good manners, and hys wiues ſhall loue hym effectually, although they diſſemble theyr loue and wyll gouerne in the houſe.
               The quadrate of Saturne &amp; Mercury, maketh the man laborous, a ſeruaunt, of poore councell, deafe or of ill hearing, ſtutting or euill ſpoken, purſued of enuie.
               The quadrate of Saturne and of the Moone, maketh the man ſlothfull, ſickly, euill graced, full of care, without friendes, a diſperſer of the goods of hys mother and of his wiues.
               The quadrate of Iupiter and Mars, if Iupiter be mightieſt, it ſignifieth that the chyld ſhall be eſteemed, praiſed and honoured of Princes &amp; Kings, and that he ſhall haue

perſeueraunce in all hys enterpriſes with profit; alwayes he ſhal loſe and dyſperſe his inheritances and poſſeſsions, and ſhall ſee the death or deſtruction of his children. If Mars be moſt eleuate, he ſignifieth ſutes, debates and loſſes, by meanes of great Lords, and a troubleſome lyfe.
               The quadrate of Iupiter with the Sunne, if Iupiter bee the Superior, honour, profit, and good fortune to the Father. If the Sunne be Superior, the child ſhal diſperſe his goods, and ſhall not be beloued of hys neighbours; and ſhall goe out of his Country.
               The quadrate of Iupiter and Venus, profit by women, faithfulnes, honeſty, ciuility, when Iupiter is moſt higheſt. When he is inferiour, luſt, deceite by women, inconſtancie, ioy incontinently turned into ſadnes, when Venus is not receiued by Iupiter.
               The quadrate of Iupiter and Mercury, ſignifieth the man skilfull, a Mathematician, a Sorcerer, Sooth-ſayer, abounding in ſeruaunts, very faythfull and very rich, principally when Mercurie is receyued by Iupiter.
               The quadrate of Iupiter and the Moone, of good renowne, great honours, in knowledge and loue of great Lords, with a little vnconſtant of Fortune and of maners.
               The quadrate of Mars with the Sunne, ſignifieth many euils, loſſe of goods, darknes of the eyes, and in great daunger of violent death, or publique.
               The quadrate of Mars with Venus, great troubles &amp; tribulations by reaſon of women of baſe condition, or impudent, &amp; ſomewaies defamed, when Mars is in a moueble ſigne.
               The quadrate of Mars with Mercurie, weakenes of all the body, pryſons, purſutes, accuſations, falſe nature of the chyld, wyth malice and iniquitie.
               The quadrate of Mars and the Moone, ſignifieth the mother to be weake, and of a very ſhort lyfe, and the child an euill boy, prodigall, vnconſtant, poore, and which ſhal die myſerably: and of the which, the wiues ſhalbe proud, arrogant, and terrible.
               
                  
The quadrate of the Sunne and Venus, ſignifieth that which the quadrate of Iupiter and Venus ſignifieth.
               The quadrate of Sol &amp; Mercury, ſignifieth that which the quadrate of Iupiter and Mercury ſignifieth.
               The quadrate of the Sunne with the Moone, augmenteth the dignities and the honors, &amp; giueth enuiouſnes.
               The quadrate of Venus and Mercury, maketh the man diligent &amp; induſtrious in his office, &amp; well renowned, but he ſhal receiue ſome infamy by reaſon of women.
               The quadrate of Venus and Luna maketh him verie rich, and happy in his profeſsion, eloquent, gracious, very happy in wiues &amp; chyldren: but hee ſhal haue ſome loſſe of good and honour by reaſon of women.
               The quadrate of Mercury with Luna, maketh him skilfull, ingenious, vnconſtant of manners and of fortunes, which in a common ſedition ſhall be taken, or ſhal be accuſed by many of his conſpirators.
               
                  ☍The Oppoſition of Saturne &amp; Iupiter, ſignifieth great troubles, a thouſande miſchiefes and tribulations, depriued  of chyldren. If Saturne be in the aſcendant, and Iupiter in the ſeauenth houſe, the beginning of hys life ſhall bee with paynes, trybulations and torments, and the ende with repoſe, profite and honour.
               The oppoſition of Saturne and Mars without aſpect of Iupiter and Venus, denote great troubles, common ſeditions and conſpyrations againſt the ſayd man: many dyſeaſes intollerable, ruines, falles, perrils by water, violent death, or peſtilence, and a miſerable father.
               The oppoſition of Saturne and Sol without aſpect of Iupiter, maketh the man ſickly, ſad, full of thoughts, full of tribulations, with great loſſe of goods, and daunger of violent death.
               The oppoſition of Saturne and Venus, maketh hym euill diſpoſed, depriued of beauty and of vertue, lecherous, infamous by reaſon of women.
               The oppoſition of Saturne and Mercury, an imperfect ſpeech, ſeperation of brethren, knowledge and ſcience.
               
                  
The oppoſition of Saturne and Luna, diſpertion of hys mothers goods, gryefes happening to the mother, troubles and tribulations, with great danger of violent death, according to the nature of the ſigne wherein Luna is.
               The oppoſition of Iupiter and Mars, raſhnes, diſpertion of goods, enemy to them which haue beene friendes, vnconſtant fortune.
               The oppoſition of Iupiter &amp; Sol, maketh him diſperſe his fathers goods, &amp; ſell his offices and his honor.
               The oppoſition of Iupiter and Venus, ſignifieth vnconſtant friendes, vngratitude of them where hee hath doone good: otherwiſe ſufficient fortune.
               The oppoſition of Iupiter and Mercurie, common ſeditions, enuies, conſpirations, ſtrifes, ſutes, enmitie of brethren, of the which he ſhall ſee the death.
               The oppoſition of Iupiter with Luna, ſufficient fortune after long trauaile.
               The oppoſition of Mars and of the Sunne, ſpoyle of the eyes, maketh him to be killed, or fal from on high, maketh him diſperſe his patrimony, &amp; his father die quickly.
               The oppoſition of Mars and Venus, yeeldeth the man voluptuous, an a little vicious, weak, vnconſtant, and maketh his wife and children to die in ſignes tropiques, maketh him marry wiues of baſe condition, or otherwiſe defamed.
               The oppoſition of Mars and Mercury, without aſpect of Iupiter, maketh the man a falſefyer, of euill conſcience, accompanied with euil chyldren, accuſed of many crimes, for the which hee ſhall be a fugitiue or baniſhed: principally if Mercury be in the houſes of Saturne.
               The oppoſition of Mars and the Moone, ſignifieth ſpoyle of the eyes and the body, by blowes and hurts and other ſickneſſes, and gyueth great aduerſities, maketh him hate marriage, and cauſeth violent death, and often Canon: principally when the Moone increaſeth in the angles; wyth ſufficient aſpect of fortunes.
               The oppoſition of the Sun, of Venus and of Mercurie,

ſignifie that which we haue ſayd of Iupiter.
               The oppoſition of the Sunne and of the Moone, changeth the fortunes of goods and honour, pouertie after riches, diſhonour after honour, weakenes of bodie after health; mutation of good to euill, and great vnconſtancie of manners.
               The oppoſition of Venus and Mercury, enuies, quarrels, enmities by reaſon of women; otherwiſe graue eloquence, beauty and brauery.
               The oppoſition of Venus with the Moone, vnfortunate marriage, iniuries by women, depryuation of chyldren.
               The oppoſition of Mercury and of the Moone, conſpyrations againſt hym, enuies, treaſons, feare and lecherous.
               Likewiſe you muſt regarde the parte of Fortune, the part of the Spyrite, and of theyr aſpects with the ſayde Planets; you muſt iudge as of the aſpects of the Planets with the Sunne and the Moone. For if the parte of fortune be part of the Moone, and part of the Spirit &amp; part of the Sunne, which would conſider the aſpects towards the other parts and houſes of heauen, he may iudge as of the Planets of the which the proiections of the ſayd parts ſhall be made. &amp;c.
            
            
               CHAP. V. Of the ſignifications of the twelue houſes.
               THE firſt houſe ſignifieth the life, nouriſhment, and diſpoſition of the body of the ſpirit, and complexion, and repreſenteth the head, face, brayne, eares, and noſe, and is called, Horyſcope angle, adorning and aſcending.
               The ſecond houſe ſignifieth goods, traffique, ryches, gayne, companies to gette profite &amp; gayne men that help to gayne. It ſignifyeth alſo gold and ſiluer, and al moueable goods, and is called, The houſe ſuccedant to the aſcendant, and beneath the earth; &amp; raigneth ouer the neck.
               
                  
The thyrd houſe denoteth the brethren, ſiſters, Coſins and allies, and little voyages, and the lyuer, and diuinations of dreames, and is called, The houſe cadant of the aſcendant, otherwiſe goodnes: and hath gouernment ouer the ſhoulders, legges and armes.
               The fourth houſe ſignifieth the Fathers and Parents poſseſsions, inheritaunces, houſes, fieldes, Orchards, vineyardes labouring, woode, and other goods &amp; moueables, treaſures and goods hydden, and mynerall matters, pryſons and obſcure places, and in the end all things; &amp; that which commeth after death, as the graue and good reporte. &amp;c. and is called, The angle of the earth, and the depth thereof: and raigneth ouer the breſt and lunges.
               The fift houſe ſignifieth infancie and Daughters, Nepheues, gyfts, preſents, pleaſures, voluptuouſnes, ornanaments, brauerie, dauncing, playes, banquetting, meſſages, gold and ſiluer, and the riches of the Father, the profite of inheritaunces, poſſeſſions, tyllage, and is called, The houſe ſuccedant to the fourth, and otherwiſe good fortune: and raigneth ouer the hart and ſtomack.
               The ſixt houſe denoteth ſeruaunts, ſicknes, wild beaſts, ryding, hunting of and by dogges: ſheepe and muttons, Goates and Pulleine, and hath ſome ſignification ouer pryſons, vniuſtice, and falſe accuſations, and is called, The houſe cadant of the fourth, and otherwiſe euil fortune, and hath gouernment ouer the belly and bowels.
               The ſeauenth houſe, denoteth marriage, wiues, ſutes, quarrels, ſtryfe, debate, knowne enmity, and men appertayning to gayne and profite, and ſignifieth agedneſſe, and ſtrange places, &amp; is called, The angle of the occident, and raigneth ouer the reynes.
               The eyght houſe ſignifieth ſadnes, enuie, long torments, the quality of death: dowery with wiues, inheritance and other benefit, prouided by Parents, and thoſe that belong to gayne, riches of the which one hath not greatly thought, and is called, The houſe ſuccedant, to the angle occidentall, and otherwiſe is entred on high, and

gouerneth the parts of generation.
               The nynth, long viages: long pilgrimages and nauigations: fayth: religion: ſacrifices: cerimonies: ſcience: wiſedome: diuination of dreames: prodigious interpretations: new ſects: paradoxes: ſignes of heauen: diuine puniſhment: and is called, The houſe Cadant of the angle occidentall, and otherwiſe the houſe of God, and gouerneth the buttocks.
               The tenth, ſignifieth honour: dignities: offices: Magiſtrates: adminiſtrations: gouernment: Rulers: Conductors: good renowne: eſtimation: profeſſion: action: and the mother: and is called, The middle and heart of heauen: the Merydian poynt and angle Merydian. It gardeth and gouerneth the knees.
               The eleuenth houſe, ſignifieth friendes: companions: hope: confidence: fauour: helpe: ſuccour: prayſe: eſtimation and renowne: counſell of friends: and is called, The houſe ſuccedant to the angle Meridional, and otherwiſe called the good angle: and gouerneth the legges.
               The twelfe houſe ſignifieth hidden enemies: pryſon: captiuitie: bondage: ſadnes: torment: complaynt: lamentation: teares and hate; treaſons: villanies: horſes and great beaſtes of lyke and iuſt proportion: and is called, The houſe cadant of the angle Meridional, &amp; otherwiſe an euill ſpyrite: and gouerneth the feete.
            
            
               CHAP. VI. Of the Lords of the Triplicities of the ſaid Houſes.
               THE firſt Lorde of the tryplicitie of the firſt angle, denoteth the nature and life of the chylde, and hys cogitations and will: that which he loueth and hateth, and that which is to come, health or ſickneſſe: good or euill entertainment, perrill of his life in the firſt age. The ſecond, Lord of the tryplicitie of the ſaide angle, ſignifieth force and ſtrength of the body, &amp; the midſt of the lyfe.
               
                  
The thyrd, the end of the lyfe.
               The firſt Lord of the tryplicitie of the ſeconde houſe, betokeneth riches, the ſecond the manner of the ſame riches, the third the intent and confidence in getting.
               The firſt Lord of the tryplicitie of the thyrd houſe, denoteth the moſt auncient and fyrſt brethren, the ſeconde the middle, the third the leaſt.
               The firſt Lord of the fourth, denoteth the Parents, the ſecond lands poſseſsions and houſes, the thyrd impriſonment and end of things.
               The firſt Lord of the fyft, denoteth chyldren, the ſecond loue, pleaſure, grace and brauery, the third, meſſages and embaſſages.
               The firſt Lorde of the ſixt houſe, denoteth ſickneſſe, trouble, the ſecond, ſeruaunts, the thyrd, Cattell, pryſon, and the profite of the ſignifications of the ſaid houſe.
               The fyrſt of the ſeauenth houſe, women, the ſeconde ſtrife and ſute, the thyrd diuiſion.
               The fyrſt Lord of the eyght houſe, death, the ſeconde, antiquity, the thyrd, inheritaunce.
               The fyrſt Lord of the ninth houſe, denoteth pilgrimages, long viages, nauigations: the ſecond, fayth, religion, and deuotion: the thyrd, ſcience, deuination, dreames, prophecies, ſortes of croſſe and prodigall ſects.
               The fyrſt of the tenth, denoteth profeſsion, honor, dignitie and aduauncements: the ſecond, audacitie, and the meanes to work in his profeſsion: &amp; the third, preſeruation in ſuch fortune.
               The fyrſt of the eleuenth houſe, denoteth conſtancie, hope, the ſecond, friendes: the thyrde, the profite of the eleuenth houſe.
               The fyrſt of the twelfe houſe, denoteth enemies: the ſecond, payne and trauaile: the thyrd, beaſtes of like proportion: and other that be appoynted to charge and labour.
            
            
               
               CHAP. VII. What the Plannets ſignifie in the twelue Houſes.
               IN the firſt houſe, Saturne out of his principall dignities, ſignifieth that the chyld ſhall haue ſhort life, vnfortunate, deformed, euill-fauoured: and ſhall dye becauſe of other lands and poſseſſions: neuertheleſſe, he ſhall be firſt of his bretheren.
               Iupiter in the ſayd houſe ſignifieth long life, good fortune, beauty, honeſty, loue of vertue, feare of God, honour, and fauour, and makes hym the firſt of hys Bretheren.
               Mars in the ſayde place, ſignifieth hurt alwaies in the heade or face, and maketh hym diſpende a parte of hys goods, and maketh him intermeddle in many dyſcordes and contentions: if he be in his houſe or exaltation, it maketh him a mighty and valiant man, hardy, fortunate in armes. out of his principall dignities, it dooth yeelde hym euill, miſchieuous, furious, ſeditious, mutinous and quarrelſome: principally when the fortunes do not intermingle theyr beames.
               The Sunne gyueth honour and prayſe, and eſtimation, credite and great aduauncement: fauour of great Lords, riches by the meanes of Princes, and maketh the chylde firſt borne, or moſt aduaunced of all his bretheren.
               Venus gyueth hym grace, beauty, brauery, ciuility, loue of women, healthfull and proſperous: and yeeldeth the man lecherous, ioyous, louing muſick, dauncing, &amp; ſomething vnconſtant.
               Mercurie, maketh hym ingenious, skilfull, dilligent, Apprentice, of good iudgement, of good memory, a good Reader a good Wryter, a great Mathematician; and apt to all knowledge.
               The Moone yeeldeth 
                     〈…〉
                   conſtant, vagabond, which taketh diuers affayres, and 
                     〈…〉
                   to many viages, a man healthfull, fortunate, fayre, 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                  mething ſpotted in the

face, and ſhall be numbred among great Lords.
               The head of the Dragon lunarie, honour, dignity and fauour of great Lords &amp; Prelates. The tayle of the Dragon, loſſe of goods and honour, deformity, obſcurenes of eyes, and great danger of the loſſe of lyfe.
               In the ſecond houſe Saturne out of his principall dignities, deſtroyeth the man, and maketh him ſpende and ſcatter his goods, and yeeldeth him poore and vnprouided of ſuccour. And in his houſe or exaltation, maketh him rich, proude, and with all his goods miſerable.
               Iupiter gyueth great riches by honeſt meanes.
               Mars maketh hym ſpend his goods, &amp; in the end doth yeeld him poore many waies.
               Sol maketh hym honourable, a great man, liberal, braue, which in his magnificence ſhall ſpend his goods.
               Venus giueth ayde and ſuccour, and greatly enricheth by women and men of the Church.
               Mercurie, profit in merchandize, and in Scripture, and very induſtrious in the Mathematiques, and a thouſande meanes to become rich.
               Luna, riches, aduauncement by embaſſages, meſſages, and imployments when ſhe is fortunate; vnfortunate, ſignifyeth paines and trauailes for the goods of the worlde, without going forward, and hynderaunce in whatſoeuer he doth.
               The head of the Dragon, riches, great gaines, profit, inheritaunce, or goods of the Church.
               The tayle of the Dragon, deſtruction, prodigalitie, follie, diſpence in playing, and falling from on high, without expectation.
               In the third houſe, Saturne deſtroyeth bretheren, and maketh them ſee theyr death, and intermedleth ſtryfes &amp; ſutes among bretheren. Yeeldeth a man vnfortunate in ſmall viages, an hypocrite, ſuperſticious, raſh, fearefull aſtonied at prodigious dreames.
               Iupiter ſignifieth peace &amp; concord amongſt bretheren, not without profite, maketh a man prudent, happy in

viages neere hand, and that his dreames ſhall be true.
               Mars ſignifieth great iniuries, ſtrifes, and ſutes among bretheren, and cauſeth the bretheren to die quickly: and yeeldeth the man a terrible blaſphemer, forſworne, a deceiuer, not fearing GOD, which ſhall be vnfortunate in all his waies, and after in danger of Theeues and Robbers, and ſhall be tormented in many terrible and vaine dreames.
               Sol, honour, dignities, offices, out of his Country, long pilgrimages, honourable bretheren, and true dreames.
               Venus, loue among bretheren, happy viages, feare of God, and true dreames.
               Mercurie, profite in traffique and viages, in fayre markets, and giueth good fortune at all times and places, concerning the good of the Church.
               In the ſigne of Gemini or Libra, it maketh the man a good Muſitian, and a ſounder of muſicall Inſtruments, principally in coniunction or good aſpect of Venus.
               The Moone maketh hym giuen to goe heere and there on pylgrimages, ſo that hee reſteth not long in a place: neuertheleſſe, in his deedes hee ſhall be honoured and prayſed, and meete with good fortune, and friendes, and great Lords, that ſhall employ him in embaſſages, in meſſages and other voyages: and hee ſhall be loued and prayſed of his bretheren.
               The head of the Dragon ſignifieth, that his bretheren ſhall be of greater eſtate and authority then hee: neuertheleſſe, it denoteth ſome Eccleſiaſticall goods.
               The tayle of the Dragon deſtroyeth the bretheren, &amp; maketh them die quickly.
               In the fourth houſe, Saturne out of his principall dignities, maketh him ſcatter his patrimony, and yeeldeth the man poore and vnfortunate in vnmooueable goods, as in houſes, lands and poſseſſions, plowing and ſowing: and ſignifieth that the mother ſhalbe of an infamous condition, and ſhall not lyue long.
               If hee be within his houſe or exaltation, hee gyueth inheritaunce,

houſes, lands, poſſeſsions, and ſignifieth the mother honorable, &amp; of long life.
               Iupiter, yeeldeth him happy in vnmooueable goods, &amp; gyueth him great ſtore of inheritaunce, &amp; ſometime cauſeth him meere with treaſure and goods, of the which he neuer greatly thought. And ſignifieth the Father of long life and happy: and ſignifieth hys chylde ſhall be eſteemed after hys death: and hee ſhall be honourably layd in his graue.
               Mars, loſſe of goods by fier and wind, and houſes, lands and poſseſsions, deſtruction of trees, diſpending of hys goods, euill end by wounds: effuſion of bloode, euill renowne after death, and ſhort life of the Father.
               The Sunne denoteth faire poſseſsions, lordſhips, gouernment, inheritaunce and fayre houſes, prayſe, honor and good fortune in hys olde yeeres, and good renowne after death, an honorable ſepulchre, and maketh him gyuen to diuination, and to preuent things to come.
               Venus denoteth the ſame that Iupiter doth.
               Mercury fortunate, yeeldeth the man induſtrious, prouiding and foreſeeing things to come: a buyer of rentes, houſes, and poſſeſſions, a planter of trees, and curious in Husbandry aſſayres: inclined to gather golde and ſiluer.
               If it be vnfortunate, it yeeldeth hym quarrelſome, ſtryuing, and hated of his neighbors, alwaies angry and ful of diſpites, and little eſteemed.
               Luna ſignifieth that which is ſaid of Mercurie, except that ſhee is gyuen to Mylles, Pondes and watry places, and yeeldeth the man in the beginning vnfortunate, and in the ende happie, principallie when the natiuitie is by day.
               And when the heade of the Dragon is in ayrie and fyerie Signes, it ſignifyeth that which Iupiter dooth, and in earthly and watrie, that which the tayle of the Dragon dooth.
               The tayle of the Dragon maketh the Father die quicklie, and ſcatter his goods vnmoueable.
               
                  
In the fift houſe, Saturne ſignifyeth ſadneſſe, neceſſitie, rudenes, vnciuill, euill-faced, euill entertainement, depriuation of death of chyldren vnnaturally, going in euil and filthy clothing.
               Iupiter, gyueth grace, honeſty, prudence, ciuility, brauerie, riches, profite in meſſages and embaſſages, aboundance of fayre chyldren, well nurtured, &amp; well inſtructed and beloued, good fortune by Churchmen, gyfts, and a dealer for gold, iewels, precious ſtones, ſweet and precious ſauours.
               Mars deſtroyeth and maketh the chyldren die, or wholie depriueth them of chyldren: maketh a man happie in all ſignifications of the fift houſe, when hee is out of hys principall dignities; Within his houſe or exaltation, he yeeldeth hym very lecherous and impudent, timerous, a ſcoffer, abounding in baſtards and euill chyldren.
               The Sunne, denoteth fayre chyldren, honorable companies, good renowne, meſſages, gyftes of great Lordes, and a dealer with Iewels and precious ſtones, and ſweete perfumes and ſauours.
               Venus maketh a man pleaſant, delectable, ioyful, dauncing, vaunting, playing and laughing, Gentleman-like, a Muſitian, happy in children, lecherous and iealous.
               Mercury maketh hym a merry ieſter, a mocker, braue, to write well, a good Painter, induſtrious with his handes, ingenious, a Muſitian, voluptuous, not caring greatly for his affayres or tribulations, indifferent happy in chyldren, and giuen to embaſſages and meſſages, and to goe on viages.
               Luna maketh him an Atturney and of Councel, a Bencher, a Legate, an Embaſſador by election of the people, and had in great account with the people, abounding in banquetting, and happy in chyldren.
               The head of the Dragon ſignifieth as Iupiter doth.
               The tayle ſignifieth what Mars and Saturne ſignifie for chyldren.
               In the ſixt houſe, Saturne ſignifieth payne of the belly

and teeth, much ſicknes, an ill ſeruaunt, vnlucky to ſheep and like beaſtes.
               Iupiter, good ſeruaunts, health of the body, good Fortune in bringing vp beaſtes.
               Mars within his houſe or exaltation, good ſeruitours in warres, profeſſion of phiſicke. Out of the ſame places, hote ſickneſſes, peſtilence, euill impediments, and euill ſeruaunts to be rebells, and theeues.
               Sol, ſickneſſe of the heart, imbecillytie of the bodye, hurtes by his ſeruants.
               Venus, imbicillytie of the Reynes and partes of generation, otherwiſe ſoundnes of body, good and faythfull ſeruaunts, good fortune in nouriſhing beaſtes, &amp; commonlye impudent loue of maydes, and in natiuities of women maketh him loue ſeruaunts, and ſignifieth perill of death in childe bearing.
               Mercurie ſignifieth him to be a deceiuer of women, &amp; to be deceyued by them and his ſeruauutes, and yeeldeth him a deceyuer, a diſſembler, a deteſter, of euill memorye. If hee be with Saturne or Mars, hee threatneth death by pryſon, a conſpiracie of ſeruants or in pryſon.
               Luna denoteth weaknes in the eyes and brayne, great and feruent, ſicknes, ſtrife againſt parents, enmytie of women, a company of men il condicioned, when ſhe is infortunate. When ſhe is fortunate, giueth health and profit in nouriſhing young beaſtes and good ſeruants.
               The head of the Dragon preſerueth from ſicknes, giueth good ſeruants, and good lucke in keeping beaſtes.
               The tayle vnfaythfull ſeruauntes, loſſe of cattell.
               The ſeauenth, Saturne out of his principall dignities ſignifieth marriage of an euill wife, blotted with ſome infamie, proper to himſelfe or parents, ruine of enemyes, &amp; perill of euill death. In watrie ſignes it denoteth Emrods, Phiſtyloes, Conſtitution of the ſinewes, and diſeaſes of the backe.
               In his houſe or exaltation, hee ſignifieth the woman to be rich, and enemies mightie.
               
                  
Iupiter, happy marriage, the woman honeſt, ſhamfaſte, vertuous, fayre, rich, victorie againſt enemies, &amp; fortunate in age.
               Mars in his houſe or exaltation, or out of his dignities alwayes ſignifieth myghty and terrible Aduerſaries, bruite of women, or husbandes in Natiuities of women, impudencye of the man, timerous, leacherous, in danger to be killed, to haue blowes on the feete &amp; handes.
               Sol, mighty enemie, rich, wiſe, well brought vp, and honourable age.
               Mercurie, leachearous, ſtrife &amp; debate betweene man and wife, euill by reaſon of impudent deſire, crafty knowledge in numbring, loue of vertue. If he be with Saturne or Mars hee ſhall kill his wife, and ſhall bee killed or put in pryſon, and put in exile, or condemned to dye by ſentence of a Iudge.
               Luna, profit of wines, thouſand ſtrifes and ſuites, deſire of change of Countryes. If ſhee be fortunate, ſhe ſignifieth all well in all ſignifications of the ſayd houſe, and vnfortunate the contrary.
               The head of the Dragon ſignifieth as Iupiter.
               The tayle maketh the woman dye quickly &amp; deſtroyeth the enemies.
               In the eyght, Saturne out of his principall dignities, ſygnifieth ſtraunge Death, Sorrowes, Complaints, Lamentations, long Torments, Sadneſſe, Anguiſh &amp; Pouertie in his houſe or exaltation, inheritaunce &amp; goodes vnlooked for, death by flyxe or plague, or of ſome colde or long ſicknes.
               Iupiter, long life to 72. yeares, inheritaunce, goodes by women, happy death.
               Mars, out of his principall dignine, ſignifieth haſtye death, peſtilence, impediment, ſlaughter, and other ſorts of violent death.
               If he be with the head of the Dragō, he ſhalbe hanged, if in his houſe or exaltation he giueth goods not without great ſtriefes and ſuites.
               
                  
Sol, cauſeth death preſently after honor, ſhort life to the father, inheritaunce to the childe, loſſe of goodes by vyolence of great men, except when he is oppreſſed with euill fortune, for then in an ayrie ſigne it ſignifieth ſtrangling by force, burned in fire, &amp; kild, &amp; buried in the earth, death by a fall, ruyne, drowning in water. Except in Scorpio, where it often cauſeth death by poyſon, mad doggs, or of venimous beaſtes.
               Venus, good death, inheritaunce, riches, long life, ſhorte life of mother and Nurſe, and his wife more ancient then himſelfe.
               Mercurie, enmytie of neighbours, vaine hope of inheritaunce, death by ouer ſtudy of his affaires &amp; busineſſe.
               Luna, inheritaunce, riches by women, long life if ſhe be fortunate, ſhort life, impryſonment, ſlaunder by falſe witnes, ſtrife, ſuites, quarrells, &amp; vexation of ſpirit, as madde or diſtraught of wittes.
               The head of the Dragon, inheritaunce, riches, honor liberallitie, prodigallitie, and good death.
               The tayle, horrible death, ſmall indeuour, no goodnes in the ſignification of this houſe.
               In the ninth, Saturne betokeneth horrible dreames, terrible viſions, hypocriſie and ſuperſtition, ceremonies, preachers, Fryers, men of Religion, and a thouſande troubles, by the way and perturbation of ſpirit.
               Iupiter, giueth faith, conſtancy in his religion, profitable iorneys, feare &amp; loue of God, and knowledge of diuine miſteries, interpretations of dreames, reuelation and profit in the ſtate Ecclesiaſticall.
               Mars, out of his princypall dignitie, daunger by the waye, vnfaythfulneſſe, ſhaking of the Fayth, and terrible Opinions and more then an Herytique, Timerous, Violent, Impudent: horrible Dreames, and falſe dexteritie in Armes and Valyantneſſe, when he is otherwiſe fortunate in his houſe or exaltation, it maketh the man very terrible, a Nigromancer, happy in his iorney or pilgrimages, hardy, ventrous, and of great courage.
               
                  
Sol, Benefices, Abbeyes, Biſhoprickes, Eccleſiaſticall dignities, Cardinalls, Popes, Legates, principaly in a maſculine ſigne, good fayth, conſtant, religious, a reuerencer of holy things, a louer of God and vertue, true dreames, profitable iorneys, and honor in his profeſſion.
               Venus, true dreames, except in the imagination of women, eccleſiaſticall dignities, conſtant Religion, loue and reuerence of God, long pilgrimage by the Worlde, profitable iorneys, honor in profeſſion which taketh awaye the deſire of marriage.
               Mercurie, goodes Ecclesiaſticall, high knowledge, diuine myſteries, admyration of iuſtice and prouidence of God, cogitation of God &amp; Angells, and of Spirits, profitable iorneys, great knowledge in diuinitie, Aſtrologie, &amp; in all other philoſophie, interpretation of Dreames, Oracles, and ſtraunge things, profit in trafique, in farre Countryes good renowne.
               Luna, long pilgrimage, peruerſe cogitations, vnconſtant in manners, and fortune, true dreames, knowledg of ſtarres: When the ix houſe is the houſe of Mercurie, or of other things anſwerable to the nature of the Lord of the ix. houſe.
               The head of the Dragon, variable dreames, honour and profit in trauayle, Ecclesiaſticall goods.
               The tayle, lacke of Fayth, terrible Dreames, perillous iorneys, and full of enuie, and little honour in his profeſſion.
               In the tenth houſe, Saturne out of his principall dignities ſignifieth ſhort life of the mother, manye ill fortunes, Sighes, Playnts, &amp; impryſonments. If the tenth houſe be in the ſigne of Leo, and any of the Lumynaries bee with Saturne, hee ſhall die in pryſon. If Saturne be with Iupiter in the houſes of Iupiter, hee ſhall be condempned of wronge: If hee be with Mars in the houſes of Mars, hee ſhalbe condemned according to his crime. If hee be with Mercurie hee ſhall dye a verye ſhamefull death by falſe witneſſes: If with Venus and Mars he ſhalbe whipped &amp;

racked, &amp; condemned to dye. Saturne in his houſe or exaltation in the tenth houſe, dooth licence dignities, preheminence, and gouernment.
               Iupiter great honor in his profeſſion, ecclesiaſticall dignities, and great renowne.
               Mars out of his principall dignities, maketh a man terrible, cruell, ſeditious, quarelſome, arrogant, a deſpiſer of his goodes, vſurper of the goodes of other, hated of Father, mother, bretheren, and other, and many tymes to be impryſoned and puniſhed by iuſtice. In his houſe or exaltation it maketh him valyant, hardie, couragious in feats of armes. In the houſes of Iupiter well diſpoſed, and regard of Fortunes, maketh him a Preſedent, Councellor, or ſoueraigne Iudge.
               Sol giueth honour, offices, dignities, preheminences, rules, gouernments, great credit and fauour of many great Lords, in eſtimation of the common people, honour in profeſſion, with riches and great goodes, principally if he be in fierie Signes, and if the child be poore and of baſe condicion, hee lifteth him vp to honour and great dignities.
               Venus honour in his profeſſion, goodes of Princes, and great Lordes, great credit, &amp; long life of the mother, with proſperitie and honour.
               Mercurie maketh him a Chauncellor, Secretary, Councellor, Preſident put in great dignities, skilfull in Arithmaticke, Geometrie, and, Aſtrologie well renowned, rich and abounding in goodes. If hee be vnfortunate by Mars, hee ſhall come to an euill ende, for hauing taken too much vppon him, or for taking quarrells againſt his betters.
               Luna ſignifieth prayſe and honor of great Lordes, &amp; ſhall be happy in all enterpriſes, and eſteemed in all the Worlde.
               The head of the Dragon ſignifieth as Iupiter.
               The tayle maketh him receiue diſhonour and loſſe of his calling, and falling from an highe, and denoteth the

ſhorte life of the Mother.
               In the eleauenth houſe, Saturne out of his principall dignities betokneth acquaintance, and to be a companion with men defamed and of baſe condicion, miſchieuous: ſadneſſe of friendes: vaine hope to come to things vndertaken: difficultie in affayres: loſſe of frindes, if hee bee in his houſe or exaltation, he giueth loue of Saturnityes as by great &amp; ancient Lords.
               Iupiter maketh him happy in all his deuoyres: giueth fauour of great Lordes: great creditte: aboundaunce of friendes: aduancement by friendes: riches &amp; fayre children: of the which the firſt ſhalbe a Maior.
               Mars in his houſe or exaltation, loue by men of warre &amp; fortunate in feats of armes, &amp; out of thoſe places ſignifieth diſpayre, vnhappy enterpriſes, loſſe of friendes, &amp; enmitie with his friends, he ſhall not be loyall to his lords &amp; friendes: by which ſhall enſue great damage.
               Sol, happy enterpriſes, goods, honor, dignities by meanes of friends which ſhalbe men of authority &amp; great lordes.
               Venus giueth good friends which ſhall bee honorable men: and of good authoritie: &amp; of good will ſignifying good fortune: happy enterpriſes: &amp; many children.
               Mercurie knowledge: and company: &amp; loue of men of knowledge and vertue: and good renowne amonge friends: happy enterpriſes.
               Luna giueth good riches, honor, good renowne: good friends which ſhalbe great lordes: &amp; happy enterpriſes.
               The head of the Dragon, that which Iupiter ſignifieth.
               The tayle, that which Saturne &amp; Mars ſignifieth.
               In the twelfth Saturne out of his principall dignities maketh vnhappye in Horſes and other great Beaſtes, from the which hee ſhall fall and receaue hurte and ſignifieth feare of iuſtice, impryſonment or exile. In his Houſe or Exaltation, victorye agaynſt his enemies, good Fortune in Horſes and other Beaſtes, fitte for burthen and labour.
               Iupiter out of his principall dignities, mighty enemies

and Aduerſaries of men in authoritie, impryſonment, exile, condemnation, pouertie, well dignified hee ſignifieth the contrary.
               Mars the fall from Horſes, hurte or other damage by beaſtes, aboundance of enemies, impriſonment, ſlaunders, &amp; a thouſand perſecutions, great euill in leggs &amp; feete.
               Sol, good fortune in Horſes and other great Beaſtes, great perſecution by enemyes, greate Lordes, &amp; mighty confiſcation and loſſe of goodes, impryſonment, exile, ſlaunder, falſe witnes, euill reporte, condemned to a great fine, depriuation of his eſtate, by peruerted trayterous and how ſhould ſeruants.
               Venus, giueth good Fortune to Horſe, ſtrife and enmytie to Women, diſprayſe in marriage, miſchieuous and euill renowne becauſe of Women: principallye if they bee euill condicioned and defamed, an impudent Louer of Women defamed, for the which he ſhalbe impryſoned: and ſuffer great diſhonour. If ſhee be in the ſigne of Virgo or Capricorne, or of Aquarius, ioyned with the Sunne and Saturne, or to Mars ſignifieth great perill of death by loue.
               Mercurie giueth great knowledge, principally in ſciences that ſhall bring ſmall profit, maketh a man a philoſopher, mathematician, &amp; ready in al knowledge, a litle fooliſh by reaſon of the lightnes of the ſpirite, hauing manie enemies, giuen to voluptuouſneſſe, euill fortune: hated by men of knowledge, likely to be ſlaundered and impriſoned. If Saturne be well diſpoſed he giueth good fortune in horſes and other beaſtes.
               Luna giueth many enemies which dayly ſhall grow &amp; increaſe, if ſhe be vnfortunate ſignifieth impriſonment &amp; exile, if ſhe be burnt &amp; ioyned with Saturne or Mars, the child shalbe euer miſerable and of a short life, which shall receiue hurt by beaſtes of like proportion: and dyeth by plague, to be killed or drowned: If shee be fortunate it betokeneth eſcape from all theſe euills.
               The head of the Dragō betokeneth that which Iupiter.
               
                  
The tayle, damage by beaſtes of like proportion and ruine by enemies.
               And generally when a Planet is well dignified or otherwiſe well diſpoſed and regarded of fortunes within the ſayd houſes, it ſignifieth good lucke in all ſignifications of the ſayd houſes, but when it is vnfortunate, it yeeldeth miſchiefe in all the ſayde ſignifications.
            
            
               CHAP. VIII. The ſignifications of the Lordes of the houſes by the places of the figure.
               THE Lord of the firſt houſe within the firſt Fortune, betokneth long life, health of bodye, goodes, and riches by his owne proper meanes, honour of his parents. In the ſecond, riches: In the third, often voiages, agreement and concorde with his bretheren. In the iiij. inheritaunces houſes and goodes vnmouable. And it noteth that he ſhalbe a great builder, a planter of vines and trees, a medler with mines of golde and ſiluer, and other thinges according to the nature of the ſayde planet: In the v. betokeneth many children which hee ſhall loue greatly, to be giuen to banquets, playes; dauncing, brauerie and to all voluptuouſnes and pleaſure, and ſhall haue many friendes to enrich him. In the vi. a buyer of ſmall cattell, abounding in ſeruaunts the which he ſhall teach and make dilligent, hee ſhalbe ſickly: In the ſeauenth, quarrelſome, giuen to ſtrife and ſuites in matters of marriage, vnfortunate in all his actes. In the viij. ſadde, fearefull and of ſhorte life. In the ix. an interpreter of Dreames, of Oracles, ſecreate things and viſions, giuen to knowe diuine myſteries, to trauayle, and to abide in ſtraunge Countreys. In the x. goodes, riches, dignities, and honor by the meanes of Princes and great Lords, good fortune in his profeſſion. In the xi. happie enterpriſes, good friendes, honourable companies, proſperitie, fewe children. In the xii. euill manners, peruerſe nature; great enmitie, good fortune in cattell. If hee bee vnfortunate

in the firſt, the childe ſhall not liue long, if in the ſeconde, hee ſhall be deſtroyed and poore. If in the third, he ſhall receiue great euill by his bretheren. If in the fourth, he ſhalbe vnhappy in landes, inheritaunces, labor, and poſſeſſions, and die in priſon. In the fifth, it denoteth ſadneſſe and tribulation, be cauſe of children, &amp; of meſſages and gifts, &amp; ſhall many times die by too much drinke, or by too much pleaſure. In the ſixth, ſignifieth great ſicknes and piteous death. In the ſeauenth, by meanes of the wife by poyſon, if he be in the ſigne of Capricorne, by fire, if he be in a fierie ſigne, by fall from on high, if in an earthly. In the eyght, ſhorte life, daunger of death in trauayle. In the ninth, in perill to be ſlayne by theeues. In the tenth, impriſonment, wracke, condemnation, &amp; death by meanes of princes. In the eleuenth, a thouſande euills, and miſchiefes for friendes. In the twelfth, death in pryſon. The lord of the ſeconde in the firſt houſe ſignifieth much gaine and to be rich; In the ſecond, that hee ſhall haue much goodes and bee verye rich and auaricious. In the third, loſſe by bretheren, &amp; profit in ſmall voiages. In the fourth, innumerable inheritaunces, augmentation of patrimonie. In the fifth, profit in all things of pleaſure and magnificence, children to come to honour, and ſhalbe rich giuers. In the ſixth, profit by meanes of ſeruauntes, and of keeping beaſtes. In the ſeauenth, goodes of women; and by ſuites. In the eight, great dowries: ſome inheritaunces, otherwiſe ſcattering of goodes. In the ninth, goodes of the Church, fortunate in long pilgrimage. In the tenth profit, profit in his profeſſion, goodes by greate Lordes, and offices, and dignities. In the eleuenth, goods, riches and honour by friendes. In the twelfth, profitte in horſes and beaſtes, otherwiſe loſſe and iniuſtice by the meanes of gayning. The lorde of the thirde houſe in the firſt ſignifieth greater riches and prayſe then his bretheren, that he ſhall make many voyages. In the ſeconde, hee ſhall haue ſuit with his bretheren for goodes. In third, he ſhall often goe abroad for pleaſure, and his bretheren and

friends accompany him. In the iiii. he ſhall goe ofte to viſite his lands and poſſeſſions, and his bretheren ſhall leaue him, and with-holde parte of his right. In the v. his bretheren ſhall bee braue, pleaſant, and gracious, and giuen to voluptuouſneſſe, and make agreement with his Children. In the vi. that hee ſhall holde queſtion of iniuries with his bretheren and that they ſhall not anſwer him. In the vii. ſuite againſt bretheren and friends, a voyage to be married. In the viii. ſhorte life to bretheren flying for feare of plague or murther. In the ix. pilgrimage of friends, and voyages to obteyne pardons. In the x. voyages by reaſon of profeſſion, and for dignities &amp; death of brethren and friendes. In the xi. good friendſhip among brethren, voyages to meete with good fortune. In the xii. enmities of bretheren, &amp; voyages becauſe of enemies.
               The Lorde of the fourth in the firſt houſe, ſignifieth good diſpoſition and honour, richer then other of his kyndred, a great man in buylding &amp; poſſeſſions, and ſhall builde houſes, plante vines, trees, and a diligent husband in his grounds. In the ſecond a good Traffiquer-in corne Oyle, Wine, and Fruits, a deare ſeller and a good cheape buyer, and a buyer and ſeller of Landes and Houſes. In the thirde, hee ſhall haue the goodes and inheritaunce of his Bretheren: in the fourth, hee ſhall haue greate Fortune in goodes, Landes, Houſes and laboures, and happen vppon Treaſure. In the fifte, the riches of the Father, Children happie in theyr inheritaunce. In the ſixt, ſignifieth no great eſtimation of the Father, but phiſicke, Surgerie and gouernment of ſicke Folkes, and a Nouriſher of Beaſtes: in the ſeauenth, inheritaunce by Women, enmitie betweene the Father and Children, a good huſwife of his wife: in the eight, the father of ſhorte life, inheritaunce, death out of his Countrie: in the ninth, lands, &amp; poſſeſſions ioyned to the Church or in ſubiectiō to the Church-men, and the father a ſtraunger: in tenth, the father to be knowne of great Lords, by the which ſhall come greate profitte to the Childe, and ſhall haue lordſhips,

Landes, and poſſeſſions by meanes of great Lords. In the eleuenth, ſhorte life to the Father, inheritaunce by friends: in the 12. the father a ſtranger &amp; of baſe condiciō, &amp; ſhall hate his ſonne, &amp; shall haue ſome mouable goods of his enemies, not without long ſuite &amp; great difficultie.
               The Lorde of the fift, in the firſt houſe ſignifieth feaſting, bankquetting, dauncing, voluptuouſnes, &amp; faire children. In the ſecond rich children &amp; ioy of their gayning. In the third, voyages for pleaſure: in the iiii. goodes of parents and alies: in the v. feaſtes, bankets, playes, brauerie, daunces, pleaſure and faire children: in the vi. witnes that he shalbe a peace-maker and not greatly giuen to pleaſure: but in ſeruants &amp; keeping cattell: in the vii. the children shall hate the father, &amp; shall haue ſuites one againſt the other, yet alwayes contentment by his wife &amp; reioyce in her. In the viii ioyfull, becauſe of vnlooked for inheritaunce, and short life to children. In the ix. ioy in pilgrimages, vowes, holy religion, good children that feare and loue God. In the x. pleaſure in honour. In the xi. pleaſure in freinds and many children. In the xii. shorte life of children, enmitie betweene the father and the children, pleaſure in horſes.
               The Lord of the ſixt in the firſt ſignifieth many ſickneſſes of the ſayd Lorde, and that his ſeruantes, and beaſtes shall dye quickly. In the ſecond that he ſhall be rich by keepinge of cattell. In the thirde, ſickneſſe and going heere and there from home, a poore kindred. In the iiii. that his Father ſhall bee of verye baſe condicion. In the fith, Sickneſſe by ouer much pleaſure, Children of more baſe condicion then their father In the vi. health if the Lorde of the Aſcendant doe not regarde him, otherwiſe ſickneſſe by ouer-labour. In the ſeauenth, ſickneſſe by Women, of ſtrifes, and ſuites and ſtrife betweene his ſeruauntes and him. In the eight, death by reaſon of ſeruauntes. In the ninth, ſicke out of his Countrey by trauayle. In the tenth, ſickneſſe by ouer-trauayle in his Profeſſion, or by ouer-labouringe for honour.
               
                  
In the xi. acquayntaunce of men vnknown; and ſicknes by meanes of friends. In the xii. ſickneſſe by meanes of enemies and of impriſonment, and enemies of his owne Seruaunts.
               The lorde of the vii. in the firſt ſignifieth gavne by traffique, peace and agreement, by exerciſe of phiſicke &amp; Aſtrologie, and that he ſhalbe well loued of his wife, and haue goodes with her: but hee ſhalbe quarrelſome and haue ſuites. In the ii. ſhort life of his wife, ſuites for her goodes &amp; riches: in the iij. ſtrife &amp; ſuites againſt friends, kinsfolkes: and they ſhall loue his wife impudently. In the iiij. inheritaunce by women, ſuites againſt parents. In the v. a young Wife, honeſt and vertuous, beloued of her husband, and ſuite againſt his children. In the vi. ſtrife for cattell and ſeruaunts, marriage with ſome woman of baſe condition, or noted of ſome infamy proper to himſelfe and parents. In the vij. ſuits for women, houſholdeſtrife, profit, and to agree and communicate his goodes. In the viij, ſtrife for inheritaunce, great goodes by women. In the ix. ſtrife and accuſations for matters of fayth, marriage with a ſtraunge woman: In the x. trouble for offices and honour, an honourable wife, and dignitie by the wiues frindes. In the xi. ſuites againſt friends, or by their meanes, and ſhalbe married by his friends. In the xii. controuerſie againſt enemies, marriage with women of baſe condicion, and not long loue together.
               The Lord of the eight in the firſt ſignifieth ire, ſadnes, angrie for that he cannot bring to paſſe, and ſhall not bee of long life. In the ii inheritaunce: in the iij. death of bretheren: in the iiij. death in his houſe, and ſhall ſee the death of his parents, and ſhall haue inheritaunces: in the v. death of children: in the vi. death of his familie before him, and ſhall be vnfortunate in cattell: in the vij. death of wife by whome he shall haue iuheritaunce, and thereby become rich: in the viij. that hee ſhall thinke ſodenly to die, and yet ſounde of bodie, trouble in ſpirite, and ſhall haue dower by his wife &amp; inheritaunce, and other goods.

In the ix. that hee shall haue euill courage, and ſhall dye out of his Countrie: in the x. honorable death, or othertherwiſe by the meanes of great Lordes, and of iudges, or becauſe of his honour: in the xi. death amongeſt his friends: in the xii. death amongſt his enemies, or by reaſon of themſelues.
               The Lord of the ninth in the firſt ſignifieth prudence, religious, vertuous, deuine, a louer of Church-men, and ſhall make many voyages: in the ii. that hee shall make many voyages, by the which he shall become rich: in the iij. marriage out of his Countrie, or take a ſtraunger, and shall make iourneys becauſe of his bretheren: in the iiii. death from home, pilgrimage by perſwaſion of parents. In the v. haue childrē from home out of his Countrie &amp; shall make iourneys for them: in the vi. marriage of a mayde or woman of baſe condicion, ſickneſſe from home, and ſhall trauell for his ſeruauntes &amp; cattell: In the vii. voyages and ſuites by reaſon of women and their goodes, and ſignifieth the woman to be deuout, moderate, &amp; well mānered: In the viii. deſire of riches, trauell for his wiues goodes: In the ix. good vnderſtanding, a louer of vertue, fearing God, knowledge in deuine myſteries, oracles, ſecrete thinges, and true dreames, trauell for deuotion: In the x. trauell for profeſſion &amp; honour: In the xi. good friendes from home: In the xii. euill courage, &amp; enemies out of his Countrie, trauell by reaſon of enemies.
               The Lord of the tenth in the firſt ſignifieth that by his induſtrie hee shall come to great honor, and shall haue dignitie, offices, and gouernments. In the ſecond honour for his wealth: In the iii. honour by his bretheren, or by trauell: In the iiii. vnmouable goods, ſumptuous houſes. In the v. honour by his children: In the vi. little honour, except of his houſhould and ſeruants, or in gouerning of the ſicke. In the vii. honourable marriage: In the eight goodes by marriage, inheritaunce, and perill of death to the mother at the time of her trauell and delyuetie. In the ix. Eccleſiaſticall dignitie, honour in ſtraunge Countries,

and eſtimation by his trauell. In the x. dignities, offices, and great honour by his owne meanes, and fauour of Princes. In the xi. proſperitie, honour, and fauour of friendes. In the xii. honour by his enemies, honour and eſtimation of men of euill condicion.
               The Lord of the eleauenth, in the firſt ſignifieth good fortune, happy enterpriſes, good friendes, and many children. In the ſecond, goodes, and riches by friends. In the third, amitie of bretheren, iorneys &amp; trauayles for friends. In the fourth, good fortune in vnmouable goods. In the fift, aboundance of children, bankquets, ioy and good fortune. In the ſixte, fortune in good husbandrie. In the ſeauenth, rich and fortunate marriage, and good friendes, ſtrifes and debates againſt friendes, and that he ſhall bee poore in his youth, and rich in his age. In the eight, inheritaunce, death of friendes. In the ninth, profitable iorneyes, friendes out of his Countrye, and good fortune in ſtraunge places. In the tenth, goodes and honour by meanes of men of authoritie, and dignitie in youth. In the eleauenth, aboundance of friends, &amp; children, great goods and honour, &amp; fauour of men in authoritie, good renown and proſperitie. In the twelfth, ſmall friendes, few goods, and debate with his friends.
               The Lord of the twelfth, in the firſt ſignifieth pouertie in youth, ſadneſſe, long trauell, enmytie and conſpiration againſt him. In the ſeconde euill manners, quarrells for goodes. In the third, quarrells with friendes and kyndred. In the fourth, ſtrife and ſuites for inheritaunce and mouable goodes, and diſcorde with the father. In the fift, rebellious children to the father, and ſtrife amonge themſelues. In the ſixt, ſtrife and anger amonge the familie. In the ſeauenth, that hee ſhall take wiues of baſe condicion, and not loue them long, and by theyr meanes ſhall haue great paine and trauell, and ſhall bee in griefe for them, and his friendes ſhall conſpire againſt him, and his enemies ſhall take away part of his goodes, and in the ende of his dayes bee poore and miſerable. In the eight,

hatred and treaſon for lyuelyhood and goodes of women, death of enemies. In the ninth, quarrell with Church-men and miſchiefes by the way. In the tenth, quarrell with great Lordes, perſecution by reaſon of his profeſſion, of his offices and honour. The eleauenth, ſignifieth that his friendes ſhalbe his enemies, and ſhall haue great miſchiefe for his friendes. In the twelfth, many enuies and enemies that ſhall imagine many miſchiefes againſt him.
               Likewiſe, you muſt iudge of all the partes of the xii. houſes, as the part of fortune in the firſt ſignifieth: that he ſhalbe rich and fortunate by his induſtrie. In the ſecond, that he ſhalbe come rich in all that is ſignified by the ſecond houſe, &amp;c.
               All theſe bee the foundations and rootes of the iudgements Aſtronomical, from the which you may not ſwarue or depart: Except in aſmuch as be mittigated, prohibyted, or augmented by the Concurrences and aſpects of the Planets, and coniunction of the fixed ſtarres.
            
            The end of the ſecond booke.
         
         
            
            Of Iudgementes Aſtronomycall vppon Natiuities, contayning the directions and reuolutions. The third Booke.
            
               CHAP. I. Of Directions.
               THE art of Directions ſo dilygently entreated vpon by John de Regiomount, that their is no more place fitly to ſpeake of the ſame. Except that with the ayde of God we haue purpoſed to tranſlate into French his problemes and documents appertayning to the ſayde matter. Neuertheleſſe we will here touch the the principall poynte. To direct (which tearme I vſe being being moſt commonly vſed and of long time receyued, although it bee not proper) it is no other thing then to ſtay the meeting of one place of the heauens with another conſequently following, acording to the naturall order of the ſignes, &amp; that the mouing of the firſt mobile. The firſt place is named the ſignificator, the ſeconde the promittor: as if the aſcendant were in the xx. degree of Sagittarius &amp; Saturne in thex of Capricorne, one might direct the aſcendant to Saturne &amp; the aſcendant ſhall bee ſignificator of life, &amp; Saturne promittor of death or ſicknes, &amp; thē the iudgement ſhalbe danger of death, there is another form of directiō attributed to the parts &amp; planets retrogrades, which do make following the naturall courſe of thei
                     •
                   mobile, to the contrary of the conſequence of the ſignes, of the which the craft is like to the 1. &amp; there is no

difference but that wee haue called Significator, which is here promittor, and the Promittor is heere Significator.
               The poynt meridionall of the tenth houſe, you muſt direct by the right aſcentions. The poynt of the aſcendant, by the aſcentions obliques, founde in the Table of the latitude of your Region. The poynts and ſtarres that ſhall be betweene the Merydian and the Horrizon, by the oblique aſcentions vnder the circle in the which they be, the which you call, The cyrcle of Poſition, the which for to finde, and likewiſe to haue the aſcentions of euery place hauing latitude or no, you muſt follow the methode following.
               Firſt, you muſt take the longitudes of Plannets, fixed ſtarres, and other places that you would direct (that is to ſay) the ſigne, degree, and mynute that they 
                     •
                  olde in the Zodiack and in the Ephemerides, or other tables Aſtronomicall. &amp;c.
               Secondly, you muſt calculate their latitudes, in degrees and mynutes placed in the Ephemerides.
               Thirdly, theyr declination by the firſt probleame of the booke of directions of Regiomont.
               Then, theyr right aſcentions by the third probleame of the ſayde houſe.
               Then againe, the diſtances of the circle Meridional by the nineteenth probleame.
               Incontinent, the circles of their poſitions, by the twentith probleame, conſequently the dyfferences aſcentional by the Table expreſſed.
               And finally the oblique aſcentions by the tenth Canon, if the ſayd ſtarres be betweene the poynt meridionall of the tenth houſe, and the poynt of the fourth, or the diſcentions of obliques by the eleuenth probleame, if they be betweene the poynt of the fourth and the tenth.
               Thys done, take out the number of the oblique aſcentions of the Significator, of the number of the oblique aſcentions of the Promittor, take to the Table of the poſition of the Significator, or the contrary, if you direct the

parts and Planets retrogrades; that which reſteth of degrees &amp; minutes, turne into yeres, monthes &amp; dayes: and by this meanes, you ſhall haue exactly the time of good or euill that ſhall happen vnto you by direction, intending that one degree is heere ſignified a yeere, fiue mynutes a month, one minute 6. dayes &amp; ſome od howers, he that would helpe the ſeconds hee ſhall touch the ende more perfectly.
               For to know the ſickneſſes and daunger of death, you muſt direct the fiue vital places that we haue conſidered, ſearching the gyuer of lyfe, in fixed ſtarres of violent nature in the poynt of the fourth, ſixt, ſeauenth and eyght, and the tayle of the Dragon, to the ill fortunes and theyr euill aſpects in the partes of death, and by and by to the Sunne, and to the head of the Dragon. Likewiſe for the ſame conſideration, you muſt direct the ſaide pernicious places to the fiue vitall places. And they meeting, they iudge that the man is in great danger of death, when the Fortunes doe not ſhewe foorth theyr fauourable beames.
               For the goods, honour, dignities, friendſhips, and other conſiderations, you muſt direct the one ſignificator of goods with the other, and the one ſignificator of honour with the others, of the which wee haue made mention in the firſt Booke, following the particuler iudgements of the natiuities.
            
            
               CHAP. II Of the Seperator or Burner, called of the Arabians, Algebuthar.
               
               THE Seperator or Burner, is the Planet which hath dignitie of tearme &amp; degree, to the which the yeere is aunſwerable, mutiplied with the aſcentions of one Significator.
               For to finde the Seperator of the like, you muſt take the Oblique aſcentions of the aſcendant, and adde vnto the ſame the yeeres of your age, and ſearch it all in the

Table of the latitude of your Region, to looke to which ſigne and degree the ſaide number aunſwereth, for vnto that poynt ſhall come the perfection of your life. Looke afterwarde which is the Plannet which hath dignitie of tearme in the ſaid degree, for of the ſelfe ſame ſhall be the Seperator of the life.
               By the ſame meanes you may ſeeke the Seperators of the honour, goods, gaynes, friendes, and of other lyke, vpon the circles of theyr poſitions. The which is conuenient to ſeeke following the afore-ſaid methode of directions.
            
            
               CHAP. III. Of the Lords of the Triplicities.
               YOV muſt alſo note all the Lordes of the Triplicities, in places which ſignifie good and euill, as well in ſignifications of lyfe, as of goods, friendes, honor, marriages, pylgrimages &amp;c. If they be wel diſpoſed in the reuolution, they ſhall ſignifie well, touching the ſignification of the place of the which they be Lordes. If they be vnfortunate, they ſignifie euill. That is to vnderſtand, the Lords of the tryplicities of vitall places, wil ſignifie of the life: of the places of fortune, riches &amp; profit: of places of honour, of the honour, good or euill, according as they be fortunate or vnfortunate at the hower, of the reuolution.
            
            
               CHAP. IIII. Of Reuolutions.
               THE Sunne returning to the ſame poynt in the which he was at the hower of the natiuity, maketh the reuolution euery yeere. He therfore that wold know the hower and mynute of the reuolution, he muſt looke in the Ephemerides, at what hower and mynute the Sunne beganne to enter into the degree minute and ſecond, in which he was at the hower of the natiuity.
               
                  
If the Ephemerides doe not ſuffiſe you for thys matter, goe to a Table made for the ſame purpoſe, by Peter Pitat, in the beginning of the ſame Ephemerides, by him corrected and augmented. Jerom Cardin vſeth another, which I finde very exact: the which hee hath written in his booke. Of the reſtitution of times and celeſtiall motions, in the fyft Chapter.
            
            
               CHAP. V. Of the iudgements vpon the reuolutions.
               FIrſt looke howe the Seperator of lyfe is diſpoſed in the figure of the reuolution: for if hee be vnfortunate, he denoteth ſicknes and other daungerous accidents; If he be fortunate, he holdeth him healthfull and glad all the yeere. So likewiſe you muſt iudge of the Seperator of goods, friends, dignities &amp; other effects. It is to vnderſtand, that they giue good fortune in the ſaid ſignifications, if they be well diſpoſed: or els loſſe &amp; euill fortune if they be vnfortunate.
               In the ſecond place, looke if the Lords of the Tryplicities of the vitall places be well diſpoſed: and of places which ſignifie riches, honour, trauailes, bretheren, Parents, wiues and children, doe ſo much. For in the ſame ſignifications the man ſhall be happy or vnhappy, according as the ſayd Lords ſhall be wel or euil diſpoſed. And principally you muſt conſider the Lord that ſhall raigne ouer your age: for the firſt Lord of one tryplicity gouerneth the firſt age; the ſecond, the middeſt of the life; the third, the latter yeere.
               Thirdly, you muſt conſider which is the Planet which gouerneth ouer the yeere of your age, that which the Arabians call Fridate.
               
               Fourthly, the Lorde of the Signe in which ſhall come the ſame yeere of perfection.
               In the fift place, the Lord of the circulation, accounting by the Lord of the houre of the natiuity.
               Then the Lord of the circulation, accounting by the

Lord of the aſcendant of the natiuitie.
               And if in the aſcendant of the natiuitie there be anie Planet, you muſt likewiſe make circulation.
               Furthermore, you muſt looke if any Planet returne to the ſame ſigne and houſe, in the which it was at the natiuitie; for then it intendeth the ſame effect which it hath ſignifyed in the natiuity, principally when it returneth to the ſame ſigne. You muſt alſo haue regard to the aſpects which are made in the reuolution, if they be like to them of the natiuity: for that ſhal be a renuing of the effects of the ſaid aſpects.
               And you muſt not forget the chaunging of the places. For if a happy Plannet bee in the reuolution in the place where an euill Planet was in the natiuity, the euill ſignified by the ſayd euill Planet in the natiuitie, ſhall be deferred that yeere by the preſence of the happy Planet. To the contrary, if a Planet promiſe any good fortune in the natiuitie, and in hys place in the reuolution be any vnfortunate Planet, the ſame good ſignifyed in the natiuitie, ſhalbe diminiſhed in the reuolutiō, or loſt by reaſon of the ſaid ill fortune. The miſ-fortune in the places of miſ-fortune augmenteth the euill, the good fortunes in the places of good fortune, augmenteth the good fortune.
               For to iudge of the ſaid conſiderations, you muſt haue recourſe to that which we haue ſayde in the two former Bookes of generall and particuler ſignifications of the Houſes, Signes, Planets, aſpects, &amp; particuler ſituations of the Planets in ſignes and houſes: hauing alwaies before your eyes, the diſpoſition of ſtarres in the figure of the natiuitie. For if a Planet be in the natiuity greatly vnfortunate, and in the reuolution well diſpoſed, it cannot much profite becauſe of the firſt infelicity.
               Likewiſe you muſt iudge of thoſe which bee fortunate in natiuities, which being vnfortunate in reuolucions, do no great damage. There be ſome that contemplate herevpon, many other things, the which by experience I haue often found vnprofitable, falſe, and ſuperfluous.
            
            
               
               CHAP. VI. Of the yeeres gouerned by the Planets, called of the Arabians Fridarie.
               
               IF the natiuite be by day, then the Sunne gouerneth the fyrſt tenne yeeres, Venus eyght yeres following, Mercurie thirteene yeeres after that: then the Moone, the nine following. Saturne eleuen yeeres, Iupiter twelue, Mars ſeauen, the head of the Dragon three, the tayle of the Dragon two. When it is by night, you muſt beginne at the Moone, the which gouerneth the firſt nine yeeres, then Saturne, Iupiter, Mars, Sol, Venus, Mercurie, the head of the Dragon, and the tayle, the numbers by order as we haue ſayd before.
               Many by great curioſitie, haue added to this companie other Planets to euery gouernment, the which I finde by good reaſon to be reprehended by the Chaldeans. For experience hath often taught mee and other very expert in this Science, that this ſubtiltie is too curious, vaine and ſuperfluous.
               
                  
                  
                     The Table of the Fridaries by Daie.
                     
                         
                         
                        Yeeres.
                        Monthes.
                        Dayes.
                     
                     
                        ☉
                         
                        1
                        5
                        5
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♀
                        2
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ☿
                        4
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        5
                        8
                        17
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♄
                        7
                        2
                        22
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♃
                        8
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♂
                        10
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♀
                         
                        11
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ☿
                        12
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        13
                        5
                        4
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ♄
                        14
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ♃
                        15
                        8
                        17
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ♂
                        16
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ☉
                        18
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☿
                         
                        19
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        21
                        8
                        17
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♄
                        23
                        6
                        2
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♃
                        25
                        5
                        14
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♂
                        27
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ☉
                        29
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♀
                        30
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                         
                        32
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♄
                        33
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♃
                        34
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♂
                        36
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ☉
                        37
                        5
                        5
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♀
                        38
                        8
                        17
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ☿
                        40
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♄
                         
                        41
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ♃
                        43
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ♂
                        44
                        8
                        18
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ☉
                        46
                        3
                        14
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ♀
                        47
                        10
                        16
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ☿
                        49
                        5
                        6
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        50
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♃
                         
                        52
                        8
                        17
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ♂
                        54
                        5
                        4
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ☉
                        56
                        1
                        21
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ♀
                        57
                        10
                        8
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ☿
                        59
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        61
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ♄
                        63
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                         
                        64
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ☉
                        65
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ♀
                        66
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ☿
                        67
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        68
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ♄
                        69
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ♃
                        70
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☊
                         
                        73
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☋
                         
                        75
                        0
                        0
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     The Table of the Fridaries by Night.
                     
                         
                         
                        Yeeres.
                        Monthes.
                        Dayes.
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                         
                        1
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♄
                        2
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♃
                        3
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♂
                        5
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ☉
                        6
                        5
                        5
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♀
                        7
                        8
                        18
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ☿
                        9
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♄
                         
                        10
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ♃
                        12
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ♂
                        13
                        8
                        18
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ☉
                        15
                        3
                        14
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ♀
                        16
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        ☿
                        18
                        5
                        6
                     
                     
                        ♄
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        20
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♃
                         
                        21
                        8
                        17
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ♂
                        23
                        5
                        4
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ☉
                        25
                        1
                        21
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ♀
                        26
                        10
                        8
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ☿
                        28
                        6
                        25
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        30
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        ♃
                        ♄
                        32
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                         
                        33
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ☉
                        34
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ♀
                        35
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ☿
                        36
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        37
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ♄
                        38
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♂
                        ♃
                        39
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☉
                         
                        40
                        5
                        50
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♀
                        42
                        10
                        10
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ☿
                        43
                        3
                        15
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        44
                        8
                        20
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♄
                        46
                        1
                        25
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♃
                        47
                        7
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☉
                        ♂
                        49
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ♀
                         
                        50
                        1
                        2
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ☿
                        51
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        52
                        5
                        6
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ♄
                        53
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ♃
                        54
                        8
                        20
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ♂
                        55
                        10
                        8
                     
                     
                        ♀
                        ☉
                        57
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☿
                         
                        58
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        60
                        8
                        17
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♄
                        62
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♃
                        64
                        5
                        4
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♂
                        66
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ☉
                        68
                        1
                        21
                     
                     
                        ☿
                        ♀
                        70
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☊
                         
                        73
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        ☋
                         
                        75
                        0
                        0
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                         
                        76
                        3
                        13
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♄
                        77
                        6
                        26
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♃
                        78
                        10
                        9
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ♂
                        80
                        1
                        22
                     
                     
                        
                           ☽
                        
                        ☉
                        81
                        5
                        5
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. VII. Of profections.
               FOR the profections you muſt reſolue the twelue houſes of your natiuity in equall partes vppon the Eclipſe, ſo farre as the aſcendant is in the firſt degree of any Signe: the ſeconde houſe ſhall be in the fyrſt degree of a ſigne following, and the thirde, in the firſt degree of a thirde ſigne: and to conclude, that euery houſe beginne by the fyrſt degree, as the firſt houſe.
               Alſo, euery houſe will containe thirtie degrees, &amp; the firſt thirty degrees of the firſt houſe, ſhall appertaine to the fyrſt yeere wherein the infant is borne; the thirtie of the ſecond, to the ſecond yeere: the thirty of the thirde to the third yeere, &amp; ſo conſequently vntill twelue. Twelue yeeres paſſed, you muſt begin againe at the firſt, and then come to the ſecond, third, fourth &amp;c. and ſo from twelue to twelue you muſt renue the ſame circuite.
               If you finde the reuolution within the thirtie degrees ſeruing to your yeere, it ſignifieth ſome good or euil, according to his nature or good or euill diſpoſition, &amp; ſignification of the place, of which ſhall be the ſayd profection; that is to ſay, of the places of lyfe, ſicknes, death, or good health; of the places of goods, riches, loſſe, or pouertie. &amp;c. Commonly they ſeeke the profection of fyue places of one natiuitie, that is to ſay, of the place of the Sunne for honour; of the place of the Moone for the qualities of the ſpyrit, towardes the body and externall goods; of the place of the parte of Fortune, for gaine and profite; of the tenth houſe for the actions; of the aſcendant for the lyfe.
               If the Sunne be gyuer of lyfe, it muſt be conſidered as gyuer of lyfe and giuer of honor likewiſe, the which you muſt doe alſo in other places, when they import manie ſignifications. If then you finde any Plannet within the thirtie degrees of your profection, and would know what

moneth or day the accident by him ſignifyed ſhal happen.
               Looke what diſtance you haue betweene the firſt point of your profection, and the ſaid Plannet, if there be xv. degrees betweene them, the ſaide accident ſhall happen out in the ende of ſixe moneths: if there be twentie-fiue degrees, at the end of tenne monethes, for heere two degrees and a halfe, value one moneth, one degree valueth twelue dayes and foure houers, thirty min
                     ••
                  es value ſixe daies, fiue minutes one day.
               Of this there is a verie exact table among the documents of Peter Pytat vpon the Ephemerides. Example of the profections. Suppoſe that the aſcendant of a natiuitie was the fifteene degree of Scorpius, I would know where the profection ſhall light of the aſcendant at the ende of tenne yeeres after the childborne. I account tenne ſignes from the aſcendant, after that, I finde the fifteene degree of Virgo ſeruing after tenne yeeres, accompliſhed to xj. current. I ſay then that in the ſaid time, the profection of the aſcendant is come in the fifteene degree of Virgo; &amp; ſhall end that yeere in the fifteene degree of Libra: and alſo ſhal containe thirty whole degrees, within the which if any Planet be founde, it ſhall ſignifie good or euill of the life, according to the nature &amp; diſpoſition as if in the ſaid time.
               Mars beeing to the fift degree of Libra, I woulde ſay that the infant ſhould be troubled that yeere at the end of eyght moneths, becauſe that Mars was in the place profectionall of life, diſtant from the firſt poynt twentie dedrees. We haue ſhewed before that two degrees and a halfe value one month, fiue degrees two monthes, and fifteene degrees ſixe monthes, and by courſe twenty degrees eyght monethes. You muſt note, that the profections ought to fitte to the yeeres currant or complete. It is to be vnderſtoode the tenth ſigne, as for incontinent after nine yeeres complete, which is tenne yeeres currant, &amp;c.
            
            
               
               CHAP. VIII. The Lords of the circulations from the howers of the Natiuities.
               THE Babilonians hold for a great ſecrete, the Circulation of the Lord of the hower of the natiuitie? It is to be vnderſtood, that the Lord of the ſaid houre ſignifieth of the life as the aſcendant, and the Lord of the hower following, of goods as of the ſecond houſe: and the Lord of the third hower of bretheren as the third houſe, and ſo conſequently of others.
               In Reuolutions, they giue the Lorde of the hower of the natiuitie to the firſt yeere, the Plannet following to the ſecond, and ſo conſequently following the natural order of the Planets. As if one were borne in the hower of Venus, that Planet ſhould raigne the firſt yeere, the ſecond yeere, Mercurie, the third, the Moone, the fourth, Saturne, the fift, Iupiter, the ſixt, Mars, the ſeauenth Sol, the eyght, Venus, the ninth, Mercurie, and ſo by order. And you muſt note, that wee take heere the yeeres currant, and not complete, for to fit the ſayde circulation of the Planets.
            
            
               CHAP. IX. Of the circulation of the Lord of the Aſcendant, and the Planets which are in the Aſcendant.
               THE circulation of the Lord of the Aſcendant, and the Planets and parts which be in the Aſcendant, they be euen as we haue ſaide of the Lorde of the houre of the natiuitie, and by the ſame order you muſt place them. The yeeres of the age of the Chyld, by iudgement, we haue made mention and proofe of Reuolutions.
            
            
               
               CHAP. X. Of Eclipſes and great coniunctions appertaining to Reuolutions of Natiuities.
               THE Eclipſe of the Sunne, and the coniunctions of the Superiour Planets, cauſeth commonly many euils, after the congruence of the ſtarres, and nature of the ſignes and Plannets raigning in the ſaide places, to men cauſeth ſickneſſes, when they be within the fiue next degrees of the Aſcendant, or to the gyuer of lyfe: if they touch the other parts, Plannets or houſes, they pronounce euill fortune, appertaining to the ſignifications of the ſame places; principally, if in the ſame time of the natiuitie, any ſuch conſtellations were in force. If they touch the places perfectionals, they doe almoſt the ſame effect as in natiuities.
            
            
               CHAP. XI. Of the particuler meetings of the whole yeere.
               COncerning the particuler meetings of all the yere, Ptolomeus, Iohn de Regiomonte, Ganrique, and manie others, doe reſt harde vppon the Profections, Menſturnes and Diurnes, of the which you haue a perfect Table in the Booke of Directions of John de Regiomonte, hauing more ſubtiltie &amp; curiouſnes then trueth, as I haue often found by experience. It aunſwereth better my opinion Schonor, which euerie day conſidered, if any Planet touch the places of the Planets, parts &amp; houſes, of the natiuitie or their good or euill aſpect, that I doe apply to the places profectionall. As for example, let the aſcendant of a natiuitie, or the place of his profection bee the twelfe degree of Libra, the Sunne in the fifteenth of Gemini, Mars in the fifteenth of Leo: alwaies, and as often as the Sunne or the Moone doe paſſe ouer the xv. degree of Leo, the man ſhall bee mooued by angry accidents, as of diſpleaſure, of ſome alteration, payne of the

head, Feauer, hote Impoſtumes, Tetters. &amp;c. Likewiſe when it toucheth the fyft degree of Scorpius, or of Taurus, there where the quadrate aſpects be within the place of Mars, or the fift of Aquarius, which is the place oppoſite to Mars. If any Planet touch the fift degree of Libra, or of Gemini (there where the Sextile aſpects be) or the fift of Sagitarius and of Aries, (which make the Tryne aſpects of the ſaide Mars) it ſhall ſignifie ſome fauourable meetings of Captaines and men of warre.
               If the ill fortunes touch not the ſaide twelfe degree of Libra, as we haue ſaid in the Aſcendant, that ſhalbe ſigne of ſome euill meeting, as well to life as to the body. Likewiſe you muſt iudge of other attouchments, according to the nature of the aſpects, by vs explained in the ſeconde Booke. You muſt contemplate the places profectionals. For I doe apply euerie degree and minute to the dayes in the which their ſignification fall, and regard the good &amp; euill aſpects of the Planets euery day, if they touch the degree profectionall. As for example, of the ſaid natiuitie in the which was the Aſcendant Libra, ſuppoſe that the profection was come to the twelfe degree of Cancer, in the ninth yeere complete and the tenth currant. The thirteenth degree of Cancer, ſerueth to the twelfe day after the proper day of the reuolution.
               Wherefore I conſider then the aſpects of the Planets towards the ſaide thirteenth degree. Likewiſe ſo I do of other degrees and minutes, fitted to thoſe daies in the which they gouerne. And ſo much for Reuolutions.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

