
   
      
         
            A catalogue of diuers visible professors of the Catholike faith Which sheweth, that the Roman Church hath byn (as the true Church must be) continually visible, in all ages since Christ. Taken out of the appendix to the Reply of A.D. vnto M. Ant. Wotton, and M. Ioh. White ministers.
            Reply made unto Mr. Anthony Wotton and Mr. John White ministers. Selections
            Fisher, John, 1569-1641.
         
         
            
               1614
            
         
         Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00794
            STC 10912
            ESTC S102114
            99837914
            99837914
            2261
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00794)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2261)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 798:01)
         
         
            
               
                  A catalogue of diuers visible professors of the Catholike faith Which sheweth, that the Roman Church hath byn (as the true Church must be) continually visible, in all ages since Christ. Taken out of the appendix to the Reply of A.D. vnto M. Ant. Wotton, and M. Ioh. White ministers.
                  Reply made unto Mr. Anthony Wotton and Mr. John White ministers. Selections
                  Fisher, John, 1569-1641.
               
               15, [1] leaves   
               
                  English College Press] Permissu superiorum,
                  [Saint-Omer :
                  M.DC.XIV. [1614]
               
               
                  An excerpt from "A reply made unto Mr. Anthony Wotton and Mr. John White ministers" by John Fisher.
                  Place of publication and identification of printer from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.
               Catholics --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-04
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2005-04
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A CATALOGVE OF DIVERS VISIBLE PROFESSORS OF the Catholike Faith. Which sheweth, that the Roman Church hath byn (as the true Church must be) continually Visible, in all Ages since Christ. Taken out of the Appendix to the Reply of A. D. vnto M. Ant. Wotton, and M. Ioh. White Ministers.
            
               Deut. 4. &amp; 32.
               Inquire of ancient tymes before you: remember the old dayes of your Fore-fathers: consider of euery age as they haue passed: aske your Father and he will tell you: demaund of your Ancestours, and they will declare vnto you.
            
            Permissu Superiorum. M. DC. XIV.
         
         
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
            TO THE READER.
            
               GENTLE Reader, This ensuing Catalogue, hath byn greatly desyred by diuers friends to be printed alone, to the end, that when any Aduersarie of the Roman Church shall demaund (as the vse of many is to do now adayes) a visible succession of Professours of the Catholike Faith, throughout euery Age, all agreeing in one, &amp; the self same vnity of Faith and Beliefe, from Christ his time vnto ours; thou maist easily, &amp; without further seeking of other Authours, shew the same vnto him for his satisfactiō in this behalfe. And if he cannot shew vnto thee a like succession of Professors of his Church &amp; Faith (as infallibly he will neuer be able to do) all agreeing in the profession of one and the same Faith and beliefe from the beginning; then hast thou good reason not only not to credit, or harken vnto him, or his Church, but vnto the Catholike, one of whose speciall Markes, is this of visible Succession, which of how great importance the same is, and euer hath byn in the cōtrouersy of Catholik and Protestant beliefe, I leaue to thy prudent Consideration.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
                  
                     An. Dom.
                     Chiefe Pastours.
                     Gen. Councells.
                  
                  
                     30. From the yeare 30.
                  
                  
                     30
                     Iesus Christ.
                     
                        The Hierosolymitan Councell. Act. 15.
                  
                  
                     34
                     S. Peter Apost.
                  
                  
                     69
                     Linus.
                  
                  
                     80
                     Cletus.
                  
                  
                     93
                     Clemens.
                  
                  
                     100. From the yeare 100.
                  
                  
                     103
                     Anacletus.
                      
                  
                  
                     112
                     Euaristus.
                  
                  
                     121
                     Alexander.
                  
                  
                     132
                     Sixtus I.
                  
                  
                     142
                     Telesphorus.
                  
                  
                     154
                     Higinius.
                  
                  
                     158
                     Pius I.
                  
                  
                     165
                     Anicetus.
                  
                  
                     175
                     Soter.
                  
                  
                     179
                     
                        
                           •
                        leutherius.
                  
                  
                     194
                     Victor I.
                  
                  
                     
                        200 From the yeare 200.
                  
                  
                     204
                     Zephyrinus.
                      
                  
                  
                     221
                     Calixtus I.
                  
                  
                     227
                     Vrbanus I.
                  
                  
                     233
                     Pontianus.
                  
                  
                     238
                     Anterus.
                  
                  
                     239
                     Fabianus.
                  
                  
                     254
                     Cornelius.
                  
                  
                     255
                     Lucius.
                  
                  
                     257
                     Stephanus I.
                  
                  
                     260
                     Sixtus II.
                  
                  
                     261
                     Dionysius I.
                  
                  
                     273
                     Felix I.
                  
                  
                     275
                     Eutychianus.
                  
                  
                     284
                     Caius.
                  
                  
                     296
                     Marcellinus.
                  
                  
                     From the yeare 300.
                  
                  
                     304
                     Marcellus.
                     
                        The first Nicene Councell, hauing in it 318. Fathers vnder Pope Siluester against Arius the Heretike.
                     
                  
                  
                     309
                     Eusebius.
                  
                  
                     312
                     Melchiades.
                  
                  
                     314
                     Syluester I.
                  
                  
                     
                        336
                     Marcus.
                  
                  
                     337
                     Iulius.
                     
                        The first Constantinopolitan Coū
                           cell, hauing in it 150. Fathers vnder Damasus Pope, against Macedonius the Heretike.
                     
                  
                  
                     352
                     Liberius. Liberius vvas first before Felix, and secondly after Felix.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        58
                     Felix II. Liberius vvas first before Felix, and secondly after Felix.
                  
                  
                     367
                     Damasus.
                  
                  
                     385
                     Siricius.
                  
                  
                     398
                     Anastasius I.
                  
                  
                     400 From the yeare 400.
                  
                  
                     402
                     Innocentius I.
                     
                        The Ephesine Councell hauing in it 200. Fathers vnder Celestine Pope, against Nestorius the Heretike.
                     
                  
                  
                     417
                     Sozimus.
                  
                  
                     419
                     Bonifacius I.
                  
                  
                     424
                     Celestinus I.
                  
                  
                     432
                     Sixtus III.
                  
                  
                     440
                     Leo Magnus.
                  
                  
                     461
                     Hilarius.
                  
                  
                     
                        468
                     Simplicius.
                     
                        The Calcedon Councell hauing in it 630. Fathers, vnder Leo Pope, against Eutiches the Heretike.
                     
                  
                  
                     483
                     Felix III.
                  
                  
                     492
                     Gelasius I.
                  
                  
                     497
                     Anastasius II.
                  
                  
                     499
                     Symmachus.
                  
                  
                     500 From the yeare 500.
                  
                  
                     514
                     Hormisda.
                     
                        The second Constantinopolitane Councell, hauing in it 165▪ 
                        Fathers, vnder Pope Vigilius, against Anthimus &amp; Theodorus.
                     
                  
                  
                     524
                     Ioannes I.
                  
                  
                     526
                     Felix IIII.
                  
                  
                     530
                     Bonifacius II.
                  
                  
                     532
                     Ioannes II.
                  
                  
                     535
                     Agapetus.
                  
                  
                     537
                     Si
                           ••
                        erius.
                  
                  
                     540
                     Vigilius.
                  
                  
                     556
                     Pelagius I.
                  
                  
                     
                        560
                     Ioannes III.
                  
                  
                     573
                     Benedictus I.
                  
                  
                     578
                     Pelagius II.
                  
                  
                     590
                     Gregorius Magnus.
                  
                  
                     600 From the yeare 600.
                  
                  
                     605
                     Sabinianus.
                     
                        The third Constantinopolitane Councell, hauing in it 290. Fathers vnder Pope Agatho against the Me
                           
                              •
                           othelites.
                     
                  
                  
                     606
                     Bonifacius III.
                  
                  
                     615
                     Deus-dedit.
                  
                  
                     618
                     Bonifacius. IV.
                  
                  
                     626
                     Honorius.
                  
                  
                     639
                     Seuerinus.
                  
                  
                     640
                     Ioannes IV.
                  
                  
                     642
                     Theodorus. I.
                  
                  
                     649
                     Martinus I.
                  
                  
                     654
                     Fugenius.
                  
                  
                     655
                     Vitalianus.
                  
                  
                     669
                     Adeodatus.
                  
                  
                     676
                     Domnus I.
                  
                  
                     678
                     Agatho.
                  
                  
                     683
                     Leo II.
                  
                  
                     684
                     Benedictus II.
                  
                  
                     
                        685
                     Ioannes V.
                  
                  
                     686
                     Conon.
                  
                  
                     688
                     Sergius.
                  
                  
                     700 From the yeare 700.
                  
                  
                     702
                     Ioannes VI.
                     
                        The second Nicene Councell, hauing in it 350. Fathers, vnder Pope Adrian, against Imagebreakers.
                     
                  
                  
                     705
                     Ioannes VII.
                  
                  
                     708
                     
                        
                           Sisimus.
                           Constantinus.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     714
                     Gregorius II.
                  
                  
                     731
                     Gregorius III.
                  
                  
                     742
                     Zacharias.
                  
                  
                     752
                     
                        
                           Stephanus II.
                           Stephanus III.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     757
                     Paulus. I.
                  
                  
                     768
                     Stephanus IIII.
                  
                  
                     772
                     Adrianus.
                  
                  
                     796
                     Leo III.
                  
                  
                     
                        800 From the yeare 800.
                  
                  
                     816
                     Stephanus V.
                     
                        The fourth Constantinopolitane Councell, hauing in it 300. Fathers, vnder Adrian the second Pope, against Photius.
                     
                  
                  
                     817
                     Paschalis I.
                  
                  
                     824
                     Eugenius II.
                  
                  
                     827
                     Valentinus.
                  
                  
                     828
                     Gregorius IV.
                  
                  
                     844
                     Sergius II.
                  
                  
                     847
                     Leo IV.
                  
                  
                     855
                     Benedictus III.
                  
                  
                     858
                     Nicolaus I.
                  
                  
                     868
                     Adrianus II.
                  
                  
                     873
                     Ioannes VIII.
                  
                  
                     883
                     Martinus II.
                  
                  
                     884
                     Adrianus III.
                  
                  
                     885
                     Stephanus VI.
                  
                  
                     891
                     Formosus.
                  
                  
                     897
                     
                        
                           Bonifacius VI.
                           Stephanus VII.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     900
                     Romanus.
                  
                  
                     900 From the yeare 900.
                  
                  
                     901
                     
                        
                           Theodorus II.
                           Ioannes IX.
                        
                     
                      
                  
                  
                     905
                     Benedictus IV.
                  
                  
                     907
                     Leo V.
                  
                  
                     
                        908
                     
                        
                           Christophorus.
                           Sergius III.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     910
                     Anastasius II.
                  
                  
                     912
                     
                        
                           Lando.
                           Ioannes IX.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     928
                     Leo VI.
                  
                  
                     929
                     Stephanus VIII.
                  
                  
                     931
                     Ioannes XI.
                  
                  
                     936
                     Leo VII.
                  
                  
                     940
                     Stephanus IX.
                  
                  
                     943
                     Martinus III.
                  
                  
                     946
                     Agapetus II.
                  
                  
                     956
                     Ioannes XII.
                  
                  
                     965
                     Benedictus V.
                  
                  
                     966
                     Ioannes XIII.
                  
                  
                     972
                     Domnus II.
                  
                  
                     973
                     Benedictus VI.
                  
                  
                     975
                     Benedictus VII.
                  
                  
                     984
                     Ioannes XIIII.
                  
                  
                     985
                     Ioannes XV.
                  
                  
                     995
                     Ioannes XVI.
                  
                  
                     996
                     Gregorius V.
                  
                  
                     999
                     Siluester II.
                  
                  
                     1000 From the yeare 1000.
                  
                  
                     1003
                     
                        
                           Ioannes XVII.
                           Ioannes XVIII.
                        
                     
                     
                        The Laterane Councell, hauing in it 113. Fathers, vnder Nicolas the second Pope, in which Berengarius the Heretike (who denyed the Reall presence of Christs body in the B. Sacrament) being conuicted, did abiure that Heresy.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        1009
                     Sergius IV.
                  
                  
                     1012
                     Benedictus VIII.
                  
                  
                     1024
                     Ioannes XIX.
                  
                  
                     1034
                     Benedictus IX.
                  
                  
                     1044
                     Gregorius VI.
                  
                  
                     1047
                     Clemens II.
                  
                  
                     1048
                     Damasus II.
                  
                  
                     1049
                     Leo IX.
                  
                  
                     1055
                     Victor II.
                  
                  
                     1058
                     Stephanus X.
                  
                  
                     1059
                     Nicolaus II.
                  
                  
                     1061
                     Alexander II.
                  
                  
                     1073
                     Gregorius VII.
                  
                  
                     1086
                     Victor III.
                  
                  
                     1088
                     Vrbanus II.
                  
                  
                     1100
                     Paschalis II.
                  
                  
                     1100 From the yeare 1100.
                  
                  
                     1118
                     Gelasius II.
                     
                        The Laterane Councell, hauing in it 1285. Fathers, vnder Pope Innocentius the III. against diuers Heresies.
                     
                  
                  
                     1119
                     Calixtus II.
                  
                  
                     1125
                     Honorius II.
                  
                  
                     1130
                     Innocentius II.
                  
                  
                     1143
                     Celestinus II.
                  
                  
                     1144
                     Lucius II.
                  
                  
                     
                        1145
                     Eugenius III.
                  
                  
                     1154
                     Anastasius IV.
                  
                  
                     1155
                     Adrianus IV.
                  
                  
                     1160
                     Alexander III.
                  
                  
                     1182
                     Lucius III.
                  
                  
                     1185
                     Vrbanus III.
                  
                  
                     1187
                     Gregorius VIII.
                  
                  
                     1188
                     Clemens III.
                  
                  
                     1191
                     Celestinus III.
                  
                  
                     1198
                     Innocentius III.
                  
                  
                     1200 From the yeare 1200.
                  
                  
                     121
                           •
                        
                     
                     Honorius III.
                     
                        The Councell of Lyons hauing in it almost 1000. Fathers, vnder Pope Gregory the tenth, against the errour of the Greekes.
                     
                  
                  
                     1222
                     Gregorius IX.
                  
                  
                     1241
                     Celestinus IV.
                  
                  
                     1242
                     Innocentius IV.
                  
                  
                     1254
                     Alexander IV.
                  
                  
                     1261
                     Vrbanus IV.
                  
                  
                     1265
                     Clemens IV.
                  
                  
                     127
                           •
                        
                     
                     Gregorius X.
                  
                  
                     1276
                     
                        
                           Innocentius V.
                           Adrianus V.
                           Ioannes XX.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     1277
                     Nicolaus III.
                  
                  
                     1281
                     Martinus IV.
                  
                  
                     1285
                     Honorius IV.
                  
                  
                     1288
                     Nicolaus IV.
                  
                  
                     1294
                     Celestinus V.
                  
                  
                     1295
                     Bonifacins VIII.
                  
                  
                     1300 From the yeare 1300.
                  
                  
                     1303
                     Benedictus IX.
                     
                        The Councell of Vienna▪ hauing in it 300. Fathers vnder Pope Clement the fifth, against divers Heresies.
                     
                  
                  
                     1305
                     Clemens V.
                  
                  
                     1316
                     Ioannes XXI.
                  
                  
                     1334
                     Benedictus X.
                  
                  
                     1342
                     Clemens VI.
                  
                  
                     1352
                     Innocentius VI.
                  
                  
                     1362
                     Vrbanus▪ V.
                  
                  
                     1371
                     Gregorius XI.
                  
                  
                     1278
                     Vrbanus VI.
                  
                  
                     1389
                     Bonifacius IX.
                  
                  
                     
                        1400 From the yeare 1400.
                  
                  
                     1404
                     Innocentius VII.
                     
                        The Councel of Florence, vnder Pope Eugenius the fourth.
                     
                  
                  
                     1406
                     Gregorius XII.
                  
                  
                     1409
                     Alexander V.
                  
                  
                     1410
                     Ioannes XXII.
                  
                  
                     1417
                     Martinus V.
                  
                  
                     1430
                     Eugenius IV.
                  
                  
                     1447
                     Nicolaus V.
                  
                  
                     1455
                     Calixtus III.
                  
                  
                     1458
                     Pius II.
                  
                  
                     1464
                     Paulus II.
                  
                  
                     1471
                     Sixtus IV.
                  
                  
                     1484
                     Innocentius VIII.
                  
                  
                     1492
                     Alexander VI.
                  
                  
                     1500 From the yeare 1500.
                  
                  
                     1503
                     
                        
                           Pius III.
                           Iulius II.
                        
                     
                     
                        The Councell of Trent, vnder Paul the third, and Pius the fourth Popes, against the Lutherans.
                     
                  
                  
                     1513
                     Leo X.
                  
                  
                     1522
                     Adrianus VI.
                  
                  
                     1523
                     Clemens VII.
                  
                  
                     1534
                     Paulus III.
                  
                  
                     1550
                     Iulius III.
                  
                  
                     
                        1555
                     
                        
                           Marcellus II.
                           Paulus IV.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     1560
                     Pius IV.
                  
                  
                     1566
                     Pius V.
                  
                  
                     1572
                     Gregorius XIII.
                  
                  
                     1585
                     Sixtus V.
                  
                  
                     1590
                     
                        
                           Vrbanus VII.
                           Gregorius XIV.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     1591
                     Innocentius IX.
                  
                  
                     1592
                     Clemens VIII.
                  
                  
                     1605
                     
                        
                           Leo XI.
                           Paulus V.
                        
                     
                  
               








            
         
         
            
            Catholike Professours.
            
               Vnto the yeare 100.
               The Blessed Virgin Marie.
               S. Iohn Baptist. S. Iohn Apostle &amp; Euangelist, with the other Apostles and Euangelists. Martha. Mary Magdalene. S. Paul Apostle. Stephen the first Martyr. Timothy. Barnabas. Tecla. Dionysius Areopagita. Martialis. Andothers.
               
               
                  Romans, Corinthians, Galathians, Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians, Thessalvnians, Hebrewes, and others dispersed through all Countreys where the Apostles and Apostolike men preached, to wit, in Italy, Spaine, France, England &amp;c.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 200.
               Ignatius. Eustachius. Hermes. Getulius. Polycarpus. Concordius. Iustinus. Eusebius. Vincentius. Pantenus. Irenaeus. Potentianus. Narcissus. Potamiena. Sophia. Spes. Fides. Charitas. Felicitas with her seauen children. Dionysius Corinth. Peregrinus. Lucius King of England. Andochius▪ Agrippinus, and innumerable others.
               
               
                  Many Indians conuerted by Pantenus. See Baronius his Annales, and Martyrologe.
               
            
            
               
               Vnto the yeare 300.
               Simplicius. Calepodius. Abdon. Sennen. Pamachius. Tiburtius. Valerianus. Verianus. Marcellinus. Dorotheus. Gordianus. Polieuctus. Potentiana. Triphon. Blasius. Maximianus. Clemens. Barbara. Agatha. Apollonia. Cyprianus. Hippolitus. Gregorius. Thaumaturg. Pontius. Laurentius. Thyrsus. Caecilia. Victorius. Polychronius. Nemesius. Olympius. Crispinus. Crispinianus. Adrianus. Eubolus. Georgius. Irene. Chronia. Pantaleon. Agnes. Iulitta. Gordius. Barlaam. Gereon with his companions. Cosmas. Damianus. Mauritius with the Thebean Legion. and others without number.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 400.
               Domnus with 2000. Martyrs. Lucianus. Theodorus. Paulus the first Eremite. Milles. Iacobus Nisibitanus. Spiridion. Macarius. Nicolaus. Helene mother to Constantine. Constantine Emperour, by whose meanes Christian Religion did wonderfully flourish. Marcus Arethusius. Nicetas. Theodorus. Antonius. Hilarion. Artenus. Athanasius. Martyrius. Paulus Constantinop. Hilarius. Martianus.

Pachomius. Gregorius Nazianz. Ephreem. Didimus. Macarius. Nicetius. Basilius. Pacianus. Mutius. Prudentius. Ambrosius. Hieronymus. Epiphanius. Brixius. Cyrillus Hierosolym. Euphrasia. Blesilla. Amphilochius.
               
                  The conuerted Dacians, Getes, Bess
                        ••
                     es, and Scythians, Morins, and Neruians, of whome Paulinus writeth. The Armenians, and Huns, and those troupes of Monkes of India, Persia, Aethiopia, of which S. Hierome writeth, and infinite others.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 500.
               Seuerinus. Tigrius. Exuperius. Eutropius. Ioannes Chrysostom. Paulinus. Mauritius. Augustinus. Maximus. Sisimus. Vincentius Lyrin. Iacobus Persa. Alexius. Cyrillus Alexandrinus. Vrsula with 11000. Virgins. Prosper. Honoratus. Rusticus. Palladius. Germanus. Bonifacius. Euthymius. Simeon Stelites. Chrysologus. Patricius. G
                     •
                  minianus. Proclus. Remigius. Vedastus. Albinus. Eugenius. Vigilius. Fulgentius. Boetius Epiphanius Ticinensis. Nilus. Seuerinus. Theodosius Abbas.
               
                  
                  The Scots conuerted by Palladius. The French conuerted by Remigius and Vedastus. 4979. Martyres and Confessors of Africa, and many others.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 600.
               Gerardus. Genouefa. Columbus. Oportuna. Germanus Parisiensis. Maria Aegyptiaca. Brigitta. Simeon Salus. Leander. Benedictus Institutor of the Order of Benedictine Monkes. Rupertus. Maurus. Placidus. Arnulphus. Launomarus. Radegundis. Leonardus. Hospitius. Gallus. Columbanus. Ioannes Clymacus. Goar. Ermingildus. Isaac. Felix. Quiriacus. Fortunatus. Tetricus. Agricola. Auitus. Bonifacius. Cassius. Victor. Cerbo
                     •
                  ius. Crotildis. Dacius. Eleutherius. 
                     •
                  irminus. Lantus. Nicetius. Praetextatus. Quintianus. Euphronius. Eusychius. Gregorius Turonensis. Medardus. Dalmatius. Paternus

Mellitus. Sabbas, and others.
               
               Augustine the Monke who sent by Pope Gregory conuerted England. The Northern Picts, the Gothes, the Bauarians, Barbaricians, and Burgundians were conuerted in this age.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 700.
               Anastasius Persa. Walburga. Attala. Eustasius. Ioannes E
                     •
                  eemosynarius. Isidorus. Claudius Bizunt. Theodorus. Arnulphus. Aldegund. Eligius. Seuerus. Caesarius. Bauo. Maximus. Trudo. Oswaldus. Audoenus. Lambertus. Gaugericus. Anhelmus. Betulphus. Berta. Cunibertus. Aidanus. Cuthbertus. 
                     •
                  ulranus. Marinus. Bercarins. Eugenius. The two Ewaldies. Andonius. Damianus Tiemensis. Kilianns. Ioannes Bergomensis. Willebrordus. Aldagisus. Ceadda. Maxellendis. Proiectus. Paulinus. Wikfridus. Edilburga. Leodigarius. Suibertus. Walericus Nicetius. Vltanus, and others
               
               
                  The Flemings conuerted by Eligius. The VVestphalians conuerted by the two Ewaldies. The people of
                  
                  Franconia concuerted by Kilianus. Multitudes of Spaniards conuerted by Andonius. The Frizians conuerted by VVillebrord.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 800.
               Venerable Bede. Bonitus. Grimoaldus. Guthlacus. Ioannes Damascenus. Germanus. W
                     •
                  nocus. Hermingildis. Bonifacins. Sebaldus. Piectu
                     •
                  dis. Wandergilsus. Lioba. Iodocus. Pirminus. Odilia. Gertrudis. Hubertus. A
                     •
                  gilolphus. Lullus. Butchardus. Rigobertus. Gangulphus. Gudula &amp; others.
               
               
                  The Hassus, Thuringians, Erphordians, and Cattians conuerted by Boniface the English Monke. The Lombards conuerted by Sebaldus. The Iewes of the 
                        〈◊〉
                      Berithum being conuerted by the bleeding of a Crucifix which was 
                        〈◊〉
                      by them contumeliously, the bloud whereof cured al
                        •
                       diseases, a Crantzius testifieth in Metropol l. 
                  
                     •
                   
                  c. 9▪ 
                  The two Saxon Dukes, 
                        〈◊〉
                      and Albion conuerted by a miraculous sight seene by VVi
                        •
                     k
                        •
                     ndu
                        •
                     , to 
                        •
                     it, a faire child descending from the Priests hands into the mouth of them that receiued the holy Sacrament.
               
            
            
               
               Vnto the yeare 900.
               Sabinus. Ansgratius. Ludgerus. Gerfridus. Geroldus. Ioannicius. Ida. Nicetas. Monolphus. Withgungus. Adelradus. Meruardus. Rumoldus. Ansgarus. Rembertus. Swithinus. Atalphus. Se
                     •
                  inandus, and others.
               
               
                  The Danes and Swethens conuerted by Ansgratius. The Bulgarians conuerted by Ioannicius. The Rugians conuerted by the Monkes of Corbeia. The Morauians conuerted by VVithgungus. The Russites conuerted by a Priest sent by the Emperour Basilius.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 1000.
               Odo Cluniacensis. Wenceslaus. Adalricus. Bruno Coloniensis. Guibertus Maiolus.

Dunstanus. Romoaldus. Elphegus. Adelheides. Wolfgangus. Poppo. Berualdus. Adelbertus. Aegidius Tusculanus, and others.
               
               
                  The Polonians conuerted by Aegidius Tusculanus sent by Pope Iohn the XIII. The Sclauonians conuerted by Adelbert. The Hungarians conuerted by another Adelbert.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 1100.
               Odilo Cluniacensis.. Henricus II. the Emperour. Kunegundis. Colomanus. Petrus

Damianus. Oddas. Simeon the Eremite. Brado. Dominicus Loricatus. Gothardus. Edouardus. Wigbertus. Lantfrancus. Gerardus Gandauens. Anselmus. Stanislaus. Aswerus. Godfridus Ambianens. Arnulphus Suesson. Iuo. Bruno Carthusian. Hugo Cluniacensis. Hugo Grationopol. and others.
               
               
                  The Vindicians, and multitudes of Prussians conuerted in this age.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 1200.
               Agnes Romana. Noribertus. Malachias. Bernardus Abb. Gulielmus Duke, and after Eremite. Gerardus. Hildegardis.

Thomas Cantuariensis. Hugo Lincolniensis, and others.
               
               
                  The Pomeranians and Noruegians conuerted by Nicolas the English Monke, who after was made Pope, called Adrian the fourth.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 1300.
               Dominicus Institutour of the Order of Dominican Fryars. Franciscus Institutour of the Order of the Franciscan  Fryars. Maria de Oegne. Christina Mirabilis. Engelbertus Coloniensis. Petrus Mediolan. Luitgardis. Elizabeth Lan
                     •
                  grau. Antonius Paduan. Gulielmus Bononiensis. Hiacynthus. Alexander de Hales. Thomas Aquinas. Bonauentura. Nicolaus Nouesiensis. Heduigis. Medardes. Nicolaus Tolentinas. Irmgardis. Mechtildis. Gertrudis. Angela de Fulgineo, and others.
               
               
                  The Liuonians conuerted by Medardes. The Lituanians conuerted by the Knights of S. Mary. The
                  
                  Emperour Cassanes, with innumerable Tartarians conuerted in this age.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 1400.
               Iuo Iurisconsultus. Rochus. Christina Sumlensis. Venturinus Bergomensis. Gertrudis ab Oesten. Godfridus Eptingensis. Henricus Suso. Catharina Senensis. Albertus Allobrog. Andreas Fesulanus. Gerardus Groet, and others.
               
               
                  Azatines Emperour of the Turkes, the Iles of Canaries, the reuolted Lituanians, the Cunians, the Bosnians, the Lipnensians, the Patrinians, and other Sclauonian Nations conuerted by meanes of Pope Clement the sixt, and Lewis King of Hungary.
               
            
            
               
               Vnto the yeare 1500.
               Colecta. Vincentius Valentinus. Bernardinus Senensis. Ioannes Capistranus. Laurentius Iustinianus. Antoninus Florentinus. Didacus ab Ascala. Andreas Chias. Maria Toletan
                     •
                  . Dominicus Pisciensis. Margarita Rauenatensis. Nicolaus the Bremite. Iacobus Picenus. Iacobus Alemannus. Columba Reatin. Ioāna Roderignsia. Osanna Mantuana, and others.
               
               
                  The Gamogetians. The people of the Kingdomes of Betonine, Guinaea, Angola, and Congo conuerted in this age.
               
            
            
               Vnto the yeare 1600.
               Catharina Genuensis. Franciscus à Paula. Andreas ex Olmo. Franciscus Ximenaeus. Gentilis Rauenatensis. Martinus Valentinus. Stephanus Soncinas. Ignatius Loyola Institutour of the Society of Iesus. Franciscus Xauerius. Felix Capucinus. Stanislaus Kostka. Ioannes de S. Francisco.

Carolus Boromaeus. Antonius Pestana. Alexander Capocchius. Nicolaus Fictor. Aloysius Bertrandus. Edmundus Campianus. Philippus Nereus. Antonia Romana. Aloysius Gonzaga. Caesar Baronius. Gulielmus Alanus. Gregorius de Valentia. Thomas Stapletonus. Robertus Bellarminus, Robertus Personius, and infinite others.
               
               
                  As in Italy, France, England, Spaine, Germany, Polonia, and other Christian Countryes: besides innumerable people in the Indies, Iaponta, China, Brasilia, and other places lately conuerted to the Faith, by Religious men of the Roman Faith.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            AN ADVERTISEMENT concerning the former Catalogue.
            I Would haue thee aduertised (Gentle Reader) that in this Catalogue, I haue set downe the Names of all the chiefe Pastours, as being the principall members of the visible Militant Church, with obseruation of the yeare or time, and such order of succession, as I could find in those Authors, which I had at hand.
            Likewise I haue set downe, the names of some few other Professours, liuing in, or neere those seuerall ages, in which I haue placed them: but in this I haue not byn so curious, either to name all which are knowne, or which my selfe know to haue bene; or to set downe any precise yeare, or orderly succession of their being; but haue contented my self to name only a few in euery age, and this without specifying the particuler yeare, in which they flourished, or obseruing any exact order, in which they succeeded one another.
            Thirdly, I haue set downe some principall Councells, or Assemblies of the Pastors,

and Doctours of the Church, leauing out many others, which I might haue set downe. The reason why on the one side, I haue set downe these particulers, is, that it may euidently appeare, that the Catholike Roman Church hath bene continually Visible, in euery Age, as the true Church must, and ought to be.
            On the other side, the reason why I haue omitted so many other particulers, is, partly that I may not be too tedious to my Reader; and partly that I may not seeme to exact vnreasonable paynes to be taken by our Aduersaryes, when a like Catalogue shal be required of thē, of the names of like visible Professours of their Protestāt Church &amp; beliefe throughout euery age: which whiles they do not (as indeed they cannot) I may boldly say with old Irenaeus, 
               Iren. l. 1. c. 3.
            
            
               That by only bringing forth that Tradition and Religion, which the greatest, and most ancient, and to all men manifest, I say, the Church of Rome, founded and erected by the two most glorious Apostles S. Peter &amp; S. Paul, receiued of them, and by succession of Bishops, hath brought vnto our time; we do counfound all those, which howsoeuer, either by vaine pleasing of themselues, or vaine glory, or by blindnes and peruerse iudgment, do make erroneous decoctions.
            
            And this I may the better vrge, because

(as the same Irenaeus affirmeth)
            
                there is in the Roman Church a more powerfull principality, by reason wherof, it is necessary for euery Church, that is, for all Christians throughout the whole world, to haue recourse vnto it &amp;c.
            
             If any be desyrous to see more of this matter, let him peruse the Reply it selfe (out of which this Catalogue is taken) and the Treatise of Faith, newly set forth by the same Author.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

