
   
      
         
            On wings of feare, Finch flies away One paire of legges is worth two paire of hands: whirre. Alas poore Will, hee's forc'd to stay. Ide try the conclusion, were I out of these bands. Heigh-ho.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00749
            STC 10877
            Wing O330A
            ESTC S115037
            99850256
            99850256
            15445
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00749)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15445)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 797:06)
         
         
            
               
                  On wings of feare, Finch flies away One paire of legges is worth two paire of hands: whirre. Alas poore Will, hee's forc'd to stay. Ide try the conclusion, were I out of these bands. Heigh-ho.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  
               
                  S.n.,
                  [London? :
                  1640 or 1641]
               
               
                  Caption title. Place of publication suggested both by STC and Wing.
                  There are two settings; stanza 1, line 1 has: (a) "choose" (L, 1 HD) or (b) "chuse" (1 HD). Of the sixteen stanzas all but the last five are about Laud. Since Finch arrived in Holland on 31 December 1640, it is possible that one or both settings were printed in 1641; also entered as Wing O330A--STC.
                  STC suggests a publication date of 1640 while Wing suggests 1641.
                  Verse - "Reader, I know thou canst not choose but smile".
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Finch of Fordwich, John Finch, --  Baron, 1584-1660.
               Laud, William, 1573-1645.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-09
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-09
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ON
WINGS
OF
FEARE,
Finch
Flies away.
                  
                     
                        One paire of legges
                        is worth two paire of hands:
                        
                           Whirre:
                        
                     
                  
               
               ALAS
Poore Will,
Hee's forc'd
to ſtay.

                     
                        Ide try the concluſion,
                        were I out of theſe bands.
                        
                           Heigh-ho.
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            
               1.
               REader, I know thou canſt not chooſe but ſmile,
               To ſee a Biſhop tide thus to a ring?
               Yea, ſuch a Princely prelate, that ere-while,
               Could three at once in Limbo patrum fling;
               Suſpend by hundreds where his worſhip pleaſ'd,
               And them that preach'd too oft; by ſilence eaſ'd.
            
            
               2.
               Made Lawes and Canons, like a King (at leaſt)
               Deviſ'd new oaths; forc'd men to ſweare to lies?
               Advanc'd his Lordly power 'bove all the reſt;
               And then our Lazie Prieſts began to riſe?
               But painfull Miniſters, which plide their place
               With diligence; went downe the wind apace.
            
            
               3.
               Our honeſt round-heads to, then went to racke,
               The holy ſiſters into corners fled;
               Coblers and Weavers preacht in Tubs; for lacke
               Of better Pulpits; with a Sack inſtead
               Of Pulpit-cloth, hung round in decent wiſe,
               All which the ſpirit did for their good deviſe.
            
            
               4.
               Barnes, Cellers, Cole-holes, were their meeting-places,
               So ſorely were theſe babes of Chriſt abus'd,
               Where he that moſt Church-government diſgraces
               Is moſt eſteem'd, and with moſt rev
                     •
                  rence us'd.
               It being their ſole intent religiouſly
               To raile againſt the Biſhops dignity.
            
            
               5.
               Brother, ſaies one, what doe you thinke, I pray
               Of theſe proud Prelates, which ſo lofty are?
               Truly, ſaies he, meere Antichriſts are they.
               Thus as they par
                     •
                  e, before they be aware,
               Perhaps a Purſivant ſlips in behind,
               And makes 'em runne like hares before the wind,
            
            
               6.
               Downe tumbles parſon prick-eares, chaire and all,
               Making a noiſe, which frightens all the reſt.
               Here two or three ſtand quivering cloſe to th'wall.
               There halfe a ſcore lie cram'd up in a cheſt,
               And though the Candles all extinguiſh'd were,
               A blind man eaſily might have ſmelt their feare,
            
            
               7.
               Thus ſtill the Biſhop kept the Browniſts ſhort,
               And oftentimes was catcht beyond his bounds;
               But if he were what man durſt tax him for't?
               His very breath the ſilly wretch confounds:
               He quel'd 'em all; to no man hee'd ſhew favour;
               But now hee's bound (yee ſee) to's good behaviour.
            
            
               8.
               A yeere a gone 'tad beene a hanging matter;
               T'avewrit (nay ſpoke) a word 'gainſt little WILL;
               But now the times are chang'd, men ſcorne to flatter:
               So much the worſe for CANTVRBVRY ſtill,
               For if that truth once come to rule the roaſt,
               No mar'le to ſee him tide up to a poſt.
            
            
               9.
               His high-Commiſſion kept us once in awe;
               There men paid fees before they knew for what.
               Honeſt Lambe and Ducke could make it good by law,
               To ſqueeſe mens purſes, when they look't too fat.
               But now your Maſter's catch't, run Lamb fly Duck;
               
               See, ſee, his Court's pul'd down, and hee's chain'd up.
            
            
               10.
               By wicked counſels, faine he would have ſet
               The Scots and us together by the eares;
               A Patriarks place, the Levite long'd to get,
               To ſit bith' Pope, in one of Peters chaires.
               A
                     •
                  d having dranke ſo deepe of Babels cup,
               Was it not time d'ee thinke to chaine him up?
            
            
               11.
               'Twas time, 'twas time; this is the generall cry;
               And who alas can ſwim againſt the ſtreame?
               His corner Cap, me thinkes ſtands all awry;
               His ſleeves have loſt both whiteneſſe and eſteeme:
               All's former honour's vaniſh'd, he diſplac'd.
               Thus is his grace, for want of grace, diſgrac'd.
            
            
               12.
               But ſtay what Bird's that, flies away ſo faſt?
               O, tis a Goldfinch; let him goe I pray,
               Something has frighted him, he makes ſuch haſt,
               Perhaps ſome ſnare was layd, to take away
               His life; if ſo, wiſely he did to flie
               On wings of ſafety, danger being ſo nigh.
            
            
               13.
               'Tis thought he was a good Aſtronomer;
               And did a ſtorme faſt comming on foreſee?
               Which made him, when the clouds began to appeare?
               Into another place for ſhelter flee.
               O ſubtill Finch, 'tis well he ſcaped is,
               His ſinging elſe had beene quite ſpoild ere this.
            
            
               14.
               But here's the ſpight; one ſheep breaks thorow th'hedge
               And makes a gap, to let out all the reſt:
               
                  Finch flowne, our other birds grew quickly fledge;
               And all that could flie, thought that way the beſt.
               The Finch indeed loſt more then all that fled,
               But who'd not part with's purſe, to ſave his head.
            
            
               15.
               Oh, had the Biſhop beene as wiſe as he,
               He might have found a way to cure his care.
               Now ſure he vexes, frets, and fumes to ſee
               How like a wretch he lies in ſorrowes ſnare.
               And how his running friends eſchew'd the danger.
               Whilſt he ſtands tide up like an Aſſe toth' manger.
            
            
               16.
               In this fine Finch my Lord tooke great delight,
               Ere now they've ſung harmonious notes together.
               But 
                     •
                  un ſhine daies are clouded oft ere night
               So theirs; and now none cares a pin for either:
               Thus I conclude and pity 'tis I ſay,
               Though one be tyed that th' others flowne away.
            
            
               No maſ
                     •
                  
no maſſ will we allow.
               To keepe it downe, w'ave ropes enow.
               He that in England thus deſires to doe, 
               
               Muſt ſwing-am, ſwang-am, thus, a turne or two. 
               
            
            
               And if that cure not his ambitious hope,
               Let me be next that capers in a rope.
               Be warn'd by him who thus hath crackt his credit,
Tis true,M
               
                  Qui antea non caveat poſt dolebit.
               
            
         
         
            I. C. V. B. poore CANTVRBVRY
in a tottering ſtate;
            A. P. O. P. you ſought to be, now tis too late.
            R. V. Y. Y. before their eyes
that are among you:
            V. R. A. K. if that you ſay
that they will wrong you.
            S. C. O. T. ſome ſay was he
which brought all this to light.
            I. C. V. R. in ſome great feare
your Lawne ſleeves are not white,
            G. R. E. G. ſweares certainely
that he ſhall have the Miter.
            H. E. A. D. and all for me,
but you will fall the lighter.
         
         FINIS.
      
   

