
   
      
         
            True relations of sundry conferences had between certaine Protestant doctours and a Iesuite called M. Fisher (then prisoner in London for the Catholique fayth:) togeather with defences of the same. In which is shewed, that there hath alwayes beene, since Christ, a visible church, and in it a visible succession of doctours &amp; pastours, teaching the vnchanged doctrine of fayth, left by Christ and his apostles, in all points necessary to saluation and that not Protestants, but only Roman Catholiques haue had, and can shew such a visible church, and in it such a succesion of pastours and doctours, of whome men may securely learne what pointe of fayth are necessary to saluation. / By A.C.
            A. C.
         
         
            
               1626
            
         
         Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00797
            STC 10916.5
            ESTC S118355
            99853562
            99853562
            27141
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00797)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27141)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 885:16, 1815:27)
         
         
            
               
                  True relations of sundry conferences had between certaine Protestant doctours and a Iesuite called M. Fisher (then prisoner in London for the Catholique fayth:) togeather with defences of the same. In which is shewed, that there hath alwayes beene, since Christ, a visible church, and in it a visible succession of doctours &amp; pastours, teaching the vnchanged doctrine of fayth, left by Christ and his apostles, in all points necessary to saluation and that not Protestants, but only Roman Catholiques haue had, and can shew such a visible church, and in it such a succesion of pastours and doctours, of whome men may securely learne what pointe of fayth are necessary to saluation. / By A.C.
                  A. C.
                  Sweet, John, 1570-1632, attributed name.
                  Floyd, John, 1572-1649, attributed name.
                  Fisher, John, 1569-1641, attributed name.
               
               [16], 74, [4], 72, [16], 178 p.   
               
                  English College Press],
                  [Saint-Omer :
                  Permissu superiorum M. DC. XXVI. [1626]
               
               
                  Sometimes attributed to John Sweet, to John Floyd, and to John Fisher.
                  Imprint from STC.
                  A reply to STC 25382: White, Francis.  A replie to jesuit Fishers answere to certain questions propounded by king James. Also a reply to STC 10378: Featley, Daniel.  The Romish Fisher caught and held in his owne net.
                  In three parts. Part 2, "An answer to a pamphlet, intituled: The Fisher catched in his owne net", (with publication date 1623) is a reissue of STC 10910.4 with added (leaves L-M⁴): "An appendix containing an answere to .. D. White, and D. Fealty". Part 3 is subdivided into two parts (both with publication date 1625): 1) "Reply to D. VVhite and D. Fealty .. The first part" and 2) "A reply to D. VVhite, and Doctour Featly. The second part"; but register and pagination are continuous.
                  Formerly STC 23530; part 3 formerly 10915.
                  Part 3 identified as STC 10915 on UMI microfilm reel 885.
                  Imperfect: part 1 title page stained, affecting text. Imperfect as filmed; part 2 not filmed; reel 885 contains only part 3; reel 1815 contains only part 1.
                  Reproductions of the originals in the Harvard University. Library (all three parts) and in the Cambridge University Library (part 3 only).
                  Appears at UMI microfilm reels 885 (Cambridge University Library copy) and 1815 (Harvard University copy).
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               White, Francis, 1564?-1638. --  Replie to jesuit Fishers answere to certain questions propounded by king James.
               Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645. --  Romish Fisher caught and held in his owne net.
               Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.
               Catholics --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            TRVE RELATIONS OF SVNDRY Confwerences had betweencertaine Protest
                  〈…〉
                and a IESVIT called 
                  〈…〉
               
               soner in Lond
                     ••
                  
                for the Cathol
                  〈…〉
                Fayt
                  〈…〉
                togeath
                  〈…〉
                Defences of the 
                  〈…〉
                IN WHICH Is shewed, that there hath alwayes beene, sinc
                  〈…〉
                
               Church, and in it a Visible Successio
                     〈…〉
                  
                Doctours 
                  〈…〉
                Pastours, Teaching the vnchan
                  •••
                Doctrine of 
                  ••
               yth, left 
                  〈◊〉
                Christ and his Apostles, in 
                  〈◊〉
                paines necessary to Sal
                  ••
               tio
                  •
                AND THAT Not Protestants, b
                  ••
                only Roman Catholiques have had and 
                  〈…〉
                
               Church and in it such 
                  〈…〉
                and Doctours, of 
                  〈…〉
                men may 
                  〈…〉
                what poi
                  〈…〉
                Fayth are necessary to Salvation.
            By A. C.
            
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               Rom. 16.v.
                     ••
                  
               
            
            Permissu Superiorum M. DC. XXVI.
         
         
            
            
            The Preface of the Publisher of
these Relations.
            
               
                  GENTLE READER,
            
            I haue thought good to present
to thy view these Relations,
together with the defē
               ces
of them; not doubting but
if thou peruse and ponder them well, they will
turne to thy benefit more wayes then one. First,
supposing thou neuer heardst any thing of these
conferences but in general, or perhaps hast heard
particulers falsly related by some who are partially
affected, or misinformed; thou mayest by
this my labour be certified of the truth, and heerby
enabled to do a worke of Charity, in freeing
others from ignorance and errour, and contradicting
such false rumours as thou mayst chance
to vnderstand to haue bene spread abroad, whether
in speach, or in print, about this matter.
            Secondly, if thou be not thy selfe already resolued
a right in matter of Faith necessary to saluation,
thou mayest gaine no small help towards

a sound setling of thy mynd; first, in the
true knowledge &amp; belief of that One Holy, Catholique
and Apostolique Church which is mē
               tioned
in the Apostles, and the Nicene Creed; &amp;
by meanes of it, in euery other article, &amp; point
of that true Catholique Fayth, which S. Athanasius
in his Creed signifyeth to be so necessary to
saluatiō, that whosoeuer doth not hold it entire
(that is, in all points) and inuiolate, (that is, in
the true, vnchanged, and incorrupted sense, in
which Christ, &amp; his Apostles left it, as a sacred
Depositum, to be kept alwayes in the Church)
without doubt he shall perish euerlastingly.
            Thirdly, if thou be already rightly resolued,
thou mayst receaue confirmation in thy Faith,
and consolation, in considering how plainly it is
proued, that there is no other Church, nor consequently
Fayth, which can (with any probable
colour) be pretended to be truly Christian
&amp; Catholique, besides that which alwayes was,
&amp; yet is, the Roman, or vnited with the Roman
Church, and Fayth.
            Lastly, hauing once thy mind thus setled, and
confirmed in the right Roman, Christian Catholique
Fayth, and thereby freed from wauering
in vncertainty and doubtfulnes about any
particuler point of Fayth, thou needst not spend
tyme in endlesse Disputes about Controuersies
of Fayth, nor be alwayes reading, and learning

(as many curious people be now adayes, &amp; neuer
cōming to setled, &amp; well-grounded knowledg,
or beliefe of all points of Fayth) but mayst
bestow thy tyme,2. Pet. 1. as S. Peter coūselleth those who
be faythfull Christiās, when he sayth: Imploying
all care, minister yee in your Fayth, Vertue (by which
you may liue conformably to that Fayth) and
in Vertue, Knowledge (by which you may discerne
practically good from ill) and in Knowledge, Abstinence
(from all that is ill) &amp; in Abstinence, Patiēce
(in regard there will not want some paine to be
suffered, whiles you labour to abstaine from ill)
and in Patience, Piety (or Deuotion, out of which
will spring spirituall comfort, inabling yow to
endure patiently all kind of paine) and in Piety,
Loue of the fraternity (or brotherhood, &amp; vnity of
the whole Church, not suffering your selues
with a preposterous piety of priuate feeling deuotion,
to hate, or separate from the cōmon Doctrine,
Sacrifice, Sacraments, Seruice, Rites or
Ceremonies of the Catholique Church) and in
Loue of the fraternity, Charity (or loue of God;
which charity of it be well grounded, &amp; rooted
in your hart, it will doubtlesse mooue you to labour,
as the same S. Peter further aduiseth) by
good Workes (and not by only Fayth,Ibid. or apprehē
               sion
that your sins be forgiuen; or that yow be
iust, or the children of God, or of the number of
the Elect) to make sure your Vocation and Election,

which doing, yow shall not (as the same Apostle promiseth)
sinne at any tyme;
               Ibid. 
               and there shalbe ministred
vnto you aboundantly, an entrance into the euerlasting
kingdome of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus-Christ.
            
            Some may perhaps meruaile, Why these Relations
come out so late, it being now long since
the Aduersaries haue giuen out false Reports,
both in speaches, and print? For answere herof,
it must be considered, that besides the ordinary
difficulties which Catholiques in England haue,
eyther to write for want of conuenient place,
tyme, commodity of bookes, and conferring
which others, or to print; there haue bene some
speciall extraordinary impediments which haue
hindred the same. As namely, that M. Fisher
was straightly charged, vpon his Allegiance,
from his Maiesty, that then was liuing, not to
set out, or publish what passed in some of these
Conferences, vntill he gaue Licence; which
made both M. Fisher, &amp; his friends to forbeare,
hoping (as was promised by him who deliuered
his maiesties message) that D. Whyte and others
were not to publish any thing,L. K. vntill they meeting
with M. Fisher, should treate, and agree, &amp;
vnder their hands confirme what was sayd on
both sides; which his Maiesty perusing, would
grant licence to publish. The which meeting
M. Fisher expected a long while, &amp; once went
to D. Whytes House, to know what he would say

about the Relation which he had set out; but
found him vnwilling to make any such treaty &amp;
agrement, nor would himself set out in print, or
writing, what he thought to be the true Relatiō,
as knowing by likelihood that he could not set
out the truth, without disaduantage of his cause,
or not without impayring, or at least not aduancing
his owne credit so much, as he desired.
            If any meruayle, why in these Relations so litle
is sayd of the secōd Dayes Conference with Doctour
Whyte, the reason is, because in a manner all
the speach of that meeting, was betweene his
Maiesty, and M. Fisher, who beareth that dutifull
respect to his Soueraigne, that he will not permit
any thing sayd by him, to be published now
after his death, which he had so specially forbidden
to be published in the tyme of his life. For
if this cause had not bene, it had bene also now
published as wel as the rest; there being nothing
in it, which M. Fisher should be ashamed off,
or by which any preiudice might come to the
Catholique Cause: for if there had bene any such
matter, D. White (who in generall tearmes doth
in his Preface seeke to disgrace M. Fisher, saying,
he vanished away with disgrace) would not haue omitted
to set downe in particuler some, at least
one, blame-worthy Argument, or Answere. But
of this, as also of D. Featlyes indeauouring to disgrace
M. Fisher, by obiecting falsly-supposed

Vntruthes, Contradictions &amp;c. more is to be
sayd in another place; and therfore not being
willing to hold thee, Gentle Reader, any longer
from the consideration of the first Occasion of
all this busines, I commit thee to the Protection
of Almighty God.
            
               Thy hearty Wellwisher, and seruant
in Christ. W. I.
            
         
         
            
            THE TABLE
Of the principall Contents, and Chapters of
the ensuing Relations.
            
               THE Occasion of a certaine Conference 
had betweene D. Francis White, and M.
Iohn Fisher. pag. 1.
               A Relation of what passed betweene D. Whyte,
                  
and M. Fisher, about a certaine Paper, giuen
by the sayd M. Fisher to an Honourable Lady,
wherein was proued the Catholique Roman
Church and Fayth to be the right. pag. 13.
               A Relation of the Conference betweene a certaine 
Bishop, and M. Fisher; defended against
the sayd B. his Chaplaine. pag. 37. &amp; 41.
               An Answere to a Pamphlet, intituled, The Fisher 
catched in his owne Net. In which is shewed
that the Protestant Church was not so visible
in all Ages, as the true Church ought to be;
and consequently is not the true church, of
which men may learne Infallible Fayth, necessary
to Saluation.
               CHAP. 1. About the first occasion of the Conference;
in which is shewed that M. Fisher did

not seeke it, nor prouoke his Aduersaries by
any challenge vnto it, nor did intend to haue
it so publicke, as by his Aduersaries fault it
proued. pag. 1.
               A Copy of the first Paper, which M. Fisher wrote
and deliuered to an old Gentleman, before
the meeting. pag. 7.
               A copy of the second Paper, writen by M. Fisher
before the sayd meeting. pag. 10.
               CHAP. II. About that which passed in the
conference it selfe. pag. 12.
               CHAP. III. Of the issue of the conference. pag. 43.
               CHAP. IIII. conteyning a Reuiew, and Reflexion
vpon the Premisses. Togeather with diuers
Obseruations cōcerning the Occasion,
Meaning, Methode, &amp; Manner of proceeding
in the forsayd conference. pag. 46. &amp; seqq.
               
               
                   An Appendix vnto the former Answere, refuting
diuers Vntruthes obiected by D. Whyte
and D. Featly, against M. Fishers Relations, &amp;
writings. pag. 73.
               
                   A Reply to D. Whyte, and D. Featly, who haue
vndertaken to shew a visible Protestāt Church
in all Ages, by naming, prouing, &amp; defending
visible Protestāts in all Ages out of good
Authors. The first Part. In which is shewed,
that neyther they, nor any other haue performed
this vndertaken Taske, in such methode

and manner, as M. Fishers Question
(proposed vnto the sayd Doctours in
a former Conference) required: And much
lesse haue they, or can they, or any other shew
such a visible Protestant Church in all Ages
and Nations, as Christs true Church is (in
the Prophesies, and Promises of holy Scripture)
described. Whence it followeth, that
the Protestant Church is not the true Church
of Christ. pag. 1.
               CHAP. I. About the vtility of M. Fishers Question
(requiring Names of visible Protestants
in all Ages out of good Authours) for finding
out the true Church, and by it, the true
Fayth. pag. 9.
               CHAP. II. In which M. Fishers Question is
explicated, and D. Whytes and D. Featly Answere
giuen in the Conference, is shewed to
haue byn very deficient. pag. 13.
               CHAP. III. In which is shewed, how many
Ministers, after the Conference aforesayd,
haue endeauoured to make Answere: And
that none haue sufficiently answered M. Fishers
Question. pag. 17.
               CHAP. IIII. About M. Bernards Answere,
intituled, Looke beyond Luther. pag. 19.
               CHAP. V. Concerning M. Rogers his Answere
to M. Fishers fiue Propositions. pag. 22.
               A true Copy of M. Fishers fiue propositions aforesaid. pag. 24.
               
                  
CHAP. VI. Concerning W. C. his idle Dialogue. pag. 36.
               An Argument prouing, that he that denyeth the
Authority of the Church in any one point,
taketh away infallible Certainty. pag. 39.
               CHAP. VII. About a certaine Treatise of the
Visibility of the true Church. pag. 51.
               CHAP. VIII. About a Booke intituled, Luthers
Predecessours, set forth by a Namelesse Author. pag. 61.
               CHAP. IX. Concernining D. Whytes Answere. pag. 65.
               CHAP. X. A Reply to D. Featly his Answere
to M. Fishers Question. pag. 71.
               Certaine shifts, and Tergiuersations vsed by D.
Featly. pag. 79.
               CHAP. XI. About D. Vshers Sermon preached
before his Maiesty 
                     •
                  0. of Iune, 1624. pag. 123.
               CHAP. XII. Contayning a Confutation of
the Pamphlet, called, The Protestant Kalendar. pag. 136.
               
                   The second Part of the Reply to D. Whyte, and
D. Featly. In which is shewed, that the Catholique
Roman Church can name, proue, &amp;
defend visible Professours of her Fayth in all
Ages. And that she only, and such as agree in
Fayth with her, is the True visible Catholique
Church, out of which there is no saluation. pag. 143.
               
                  
CHAP. I. In which is shewed, that the Roman
Church hath had visible Professours,
whose Names may be shewed in all Ages. pag. 145.
               CHAP. II. In which is shewed, that out of the
Catholique Roman Church, there is no saluation. pag. 152.
               A Discourse wherin is demōstrated by Reasons 
drawne out of Scriptures &amp; ancient Fathers,
that out of the Vnity of the Roman Church,
there is no Saluation. pag. 153.
               The first Argument therof. pag. 157.
               The second Argument. pag. 158.
            
         
         
            
            Faultes escaped in the printing.
            
               
                  In the Relations of the Conferences.
                  
                     Page,
                     Line,
                     Fault,
                     Correction.
                  
                  
                     24
                     31
                     whome when
                     
                        dele whome
                  
                  
                     26
                     5
                     be true
                     to be true
                  
                  
                     33
                     7
                     being a diuine
                     cōming frō a diuine
                  
                  
                     Ibid
                     11
                     this definition
                     so this definition
                  
                  
                     44
                     24
                     of fayth
                     of points of fayth
                  
                  
                     45
                     23
                     to be firme
                     be firme
                  
                  
                     49
                     4
                     it not
                     is not
                  
                  
                     51
                     1 &amp; 2
                     so rudely
                     formerly
                  
                  
                     Ibid.
                     13
                     knowne
                     foreknowne
                  
                  
                     56
                     15
                     for contra
                     
                     for if contra
                     
                  
                  
                     Ibid.
                     18
                     What then? Is it
                     What then is it?
                  
                  
                     57
                     2
                     to Rome
                     to come
                  
                  
                     61
                     14
                     do iustify
                     do not like
                  
                  
                     64
                     vlt.
                     argument
                     against
                  
                  
                     66
                     15
                     out opposite
                     but opposite
                  
                  
                     70
                     12
                     vnion
                     vnanime
                  
               
            
            
               
                  In the Answere to the Fisher catched. &amp;c.
                  
                     4
                     17
                     questions
                     question
                  
                  
                     8
                     vlt.
                     solloweth
                     followeth
                  
                  
                     16
                     12
                     repotteth
                     reporteth
                  
                  
                     23
                     11
                     sense: Wherof
                     sense wherof
                  
                  
                     39
                     18
                     defired
                     desired
                  
                  
                     59
                     16
                     heahen
                     heathen
                  
                  
                     60
                     28
                     with
                     which
                  
                  
                     67
                     26
                     pre-present
                     present
                  
                  
                     71
                     6
                     Prostant
                     Protestant.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  In the Reply to D. Whyte, and D. Featly.
                  
                     1
                     17
                     offeringes
                     ofspringes
                  
                  
                     4
                     18
                     pages
                     ages
                  
                  
                     6
                     6
                     denyed not
                     confessed not
                  
                  
                     8
                     11
                     different
                     deficient
                  
                  
                     11
                     5
                     pretended
                     produced
                  
                  
                     14
                     31
                     or defend
                     and defend
                  
                  
                     15
                     8
                     The Proofes
                     Moreouer the Proofes
                  
                  
                     21
                     18
                     first
                     fifth
                  
                  
                     28
                     4
                     is of
                     are of
                  
                  
                     32
                     12
                     of the argument
                     against the argument
                  
                  
                     Ibid.
                     31
                     possessours
                     professours
                  
                  
                     33
                     2
                     the M.
                     the same M.
                  
                  
                     36
                     7
                     pretenteth
                     pretendeth
                  
                  
                     41
                     21
                     to mooue
                     doth mooue
                  
                  
                     45
                     22
                     (especially obstinatly) dele vlt. parenthesim
and read (especially obstinately against the knowne
fayth of the Church) any one &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     68
                     26
                     precept of positiue &amp;c. read, positiue and
negatiue precept of profession &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     69
                     18
                     infer
                     answere
                  
                  
                     74
                     20
                     Maior
                     Minor
                  
                  
                     84
                     vlt.
                     to be good
                     not to be good
                  
                  
                     96
                     9
                     do not denominate. read, do not (as the
Name Protestant doth) denominate &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     67
                     vlt.
                     euery piously disposed. read, euery intelligent,
and piously disposed &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     108
                     21
                     points, to take
                     points. To take &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     109
                     29
                     but say
                     and say
                  
                  
                     117
                     32
                     it seemeth
                     It seemeth
                  
                  
                     118
                     1
                     notable
                     not able
                  
                  
                     119
                     9
                     hunreds
                     hundreds
                  
                  
                     131
                     29
                     found in
                     sound in
                  
                  
                  
                     140
                     27
                     be nameth
                     he nameth
                  
                  
                     146
                     3
                     Fayh
                     Fayth
                  
                  
                     147
                     19
                     Traditions. The
                     Traditions; the
                  
                  
                     151
                     19
                     defined
                     defined
                  
                  
                     153
                     13
                     had,)
                     dele parenthesim.
                  
                  
                     163
                     31
                     vncharitable
                     vncharitably
                  
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE
OCCASION
OF A
Certaine Conference had betvveene
D. Francis White, and
M. Iohn Fisher.
            
               THE Occasion of this Conference,
was a certaine writtē
Paper, giuen by M Fisher
to an Honble Lady, who desired
somthing to be briefly
writtē to proue the Catholique Roman
Church, &amp; Faith, to be the only right.
            
               The Copie of this Paper is as followeth.
               FIRST, It is certaine,Ephes. 4. Heb. 11. that there is
one, and but one, true, diuine, infallible

Faith, without which none can
please God, or attayne Saluation.
               2. This one, true, diuine, infallible
Faith, is wholy grounded vpon the authority
of Gods word; and in this it differeth
not only from all humane sciences
bred by a cleere sight, or euident demonstration,
and from humane opinion
proceeding from probable arguments
or coniectures, &amp; from humane
Faith built vpon the authority of Pithagoras
his Ipse dixit, or the word of any
other man; but also from all other diuine
knowledge, had, either by cleere
vision of the diuine Essence, which
Saints haue in heauen, or by cleere reuelation
of diuine Mysteries, which
some principall persons, to wit, Patriarkes,
and Prophers, and Apostles had
on earth; and also from that Theologicall
discursiue knowledge, which learned
men attaine vnto, by the vse of
their naturall wit, in deducing Conclusions,

partly out of the foundations of
supernaturall Faith, partly out of principles
of naturall reason: From all these
kindes of knowledge (I say) that one
true, diuine, and infallible Faith differeth,
in that it is grounded wholly vpon
the authority of the VVord of God, as humane
fallible Faith is grounded vpon
the authority of the VVord of Man.
               
               3. This VVord of God, vpon which diuine
infallible faith is grounded, is not
only the word of God Increate, or the
prime Verity, but also the word Created,
or Reuelation proceeding from that
prime Verity, by which the truth of
Christian mysteries, by Christ (who is
true God) was first made manifest to
the Apostles, and other his Disciples;
partly by the exteriour preaching of
his owne mouth, but chiefly by the inward
reuelation of his eternall heauenly
Father, and by the inspiration of the
holy Ghost. Secōdly, It was made knowne

to others liuing in those dayes, partly by
owtward preaching, partly by the writinges
of the aforesaid Apostles, and
Disciples, to whome Christ gaue lawfull
mission &amp; commission to teach, saying
Teach all nations,
                  Matth. 28.. promising that himselfe
would be with them all dayes,Ioan. 16. vnto the
end of the world;Luc. 10. and that his holy Spirit
should assist them, and teach them,
(and consequently make them able to
teach others) all Truth, in such sort, as
whosoeuer should heare them, should
heare Christ himself, and so should be
made docibles Dei, and as the Prophet
foretould, docti à Domino, and as S. Paul
speaketh of some, Epistola Christi, the
epistle of Christ, written not with inke,
but with the spirit of God. Whence appeareth,
that not only the Word Increate,
but also the Word Created, may
be truly sayd to be the Foundation of
our Faith; and not only that Word
which was immediatly inspired by the

heauenly Father, or by the holy Ghost,
in the hartes of the Apostles, and other
Disciples, who liued in our Sauiours
dayes; but also the Word, as well preached,
as written by the Apostles, and
also that Word, which by the preaching
and writing of the Apostles, was by the
holy Ghost imprinted in the hartes of
the immediate hearers, who were therupon
said to be the Epistles of Christ,
as I haue already noted.
               4. This Word of God (which I call
Created, to distinguish it from the word
Increate) being partly preached, partly
written, partly inspired or imprinted in
manner aforesaid) was not to cease at
the death of the Apostles and Disciples
and their immediate hearers,1. Tim. 2. but by the
appointment of God (who would haue
all men to be saued, and come to the
knowledge of the Truth,) was to be deriued
to posterity; not by new immediate
reuelations, or Enthusiasmes, nor by

sending Angells to all particuler men,
but by a continuated succession of Visible
Doctours, and Pastors, and lawfully-sent
Preachers in all ages, who partly by
Transcripts of what was written first by
the Apostles; but cheifly by Vocall preaching
of the same doctrine, without
change, which the Pastors of euery age
successiuely one from another receaued
of their predecessors, as they who liued
in the age next to the Apostles dayes,
receaued it from the Apostles, as a sacred
Depositum, to be kept and preserued
in the Church, maugre all the assaultes
of Helly gates, which according to
Christs promise, shall neuer preua-le
against the Church Whence followeth,
that not only for 400. or 500. or 600.
yeares, but in al ages since Christ, there
was, is, and shalbe the true Word of God
preached by visible Doctours, Pastors, and
lawfully sent Preachers, so guided by
Christ and his holy spirit, that by them

people of euery Age were, are, and
shalbe sufficiently instructed in true,
diuine, infallible Faith, in all thinges
necessary to Saluation; to the intent,
that they may not be little ones, wauering,Ephes. 4.
nor carried about with euery winde
of new doctrine; which being contrary to
the ould and first receaued, must needs
be false.
               5. Wheras by this which is already
said (which if need be, may be morefully
proued) it apeareth first, that there is
one, true, diuine, infallible Faith, necessary
to saluation. Secōdly, that this Faith
is wholy grounded vpon the word of
God. Thirdly, that this word of God, is
not only the word Increate, but also the
word Created, either inwardly inspired, or
outwardly preached, or written, &amp; continued,
without change in one, or other
continued succession of Visible Pastors,
Doctours, and lawfully-sent Preachers,
rightly teaching, by the direction of

Christ, and his holy spirit, the said word
of God wheras (I say) all this doth most
euidently appeare by this which is already
sayd.
               That I may proue the Romā Church
only, and those who consent and agree
in doctrine of Faith with it, to haue
that one, true, diuine, infallible Faith,
which is necessarie to saluation,
               
                  Thus I dispute.
                  
If it be needfull, that there should
be one, or other continuall succession
of Visible Pastors, in which, and by which
the vnchanged word of God, vpon
which true, diuine, infallible Faith is
grounded, is preserued and preached;
and no other succession besides that of
the Roman Church, and others, which
agree in Faith with it, can be shewed (as
if any such were, may be shewed) out
of approued Histories, or other ancient
monuments; Then without doubt, the
Roman Church only, and such as agree

with it in Faith, haue that true, diuine,
infallible Faith, which is necessary to
saluation.
               But there must be one, or other such
succession of Visible Pastors; and no other
can be shewed out of approued Histories
or ancient monumēts, besides that
of the Roman Church only, and such
others as agree with it in Faith. Ergo.
               
               The Roman Church only, and such
others as agree with it in Faith, hath
true, diuine, infallible Faith, necessarie
to saluation.
               The Consequence of the Maior cannot
with reason be denied, and if it be,
it shalbe proued.
               The Minor hath two partes. The
first wherof is plaine, by that which is
already said, and if need be it shalbe
more fully proued out of holy Scriptures.
               The second part, may be made manifest,
first out of Histories, secondly

out of the confession of Protestants.
            
            
               The second Argument.
               If the Roman Church had the right
Faith, and neuer changed any substantiall
part of Faith: Then it followeth,
that it hath now that one true, diuine,
infallible Faith, which is necessary to
saluation.
               But the Roman Church once had the
right Faith, and neuer changed any
substantiall part of Faith. Ergo.
               
               The Roman Church now hath the
right Faith; and consequently Protestants,
so far as they disagree with it,
haue not the right soule-sauing Faith.
               The Maior is euident.
               The Minor hath two partes. The
first is cleere out of S. Paul, Rom. 1. and
is confessed by Protestants.
               
                  The second part, I proue thus:
                  
Yf the Roman Church changed any
substantiall part of Faith, then there
may be shewed the point changed, the

person which was the Authour of
that change, the time when, and place
where the change was made; &amp; others
may be named, who persisting in the
ancient Faith, continued opposition
against the innouation and change, as
may be shewed in other like, and lesse
changes, and namely in Luthers, and
Caluins change.
               But these circumstances cannot be
shewed. Ergo. No change.
               If my Aduersaries name any point,
which they affirme to haue beene changed.
1. This wil not suffice, vnlesse they
name the other circumstances of the
Author, time, place, and who persisting
in the former vnchanged Faith, opposed
and continued oppositiō against
it, as against a Nouelty, and Heresie;
as we can do in other changes, and namely
in that which was by Luther and
Caluin.
               
               2. These points, which they say

were changed after the first 600. yeares,
may be shewed them to haue beene
held, by more ancient approued Authors,
in the same sense, in which they
are held by the Roman Church; which
doth argue, that there was no such
change made.
            
         
         
            
            A briefe Relation of what passed betweene D.
White, and M. Fisher, about the
foresaid written Paper.
            
               THIS forsaid paper passing from one
to another, came to some hāds, who
gaue it to D. Francis Whyte to answere,
and to prepare himselfe to
oppugne it in a Conferēce with M.
Fisher: who whē he wrot it, &amp; gaue
it to the Lady, did not thinke, or suspect
that any such great matter should haue bene made
of it, as after proued, M. D. Whyte hauing (as he cōfessed
after to M. Fisher) had this paper about ten dayes in his
handes, studying what to say to it, came as he was appoynted
to the place of meeting, and M. Fisher being
then a Prisoner, was also sent for. At the houre and
place prefixed, both the one, and the other (as they
were bidden) sate downe before a few, but very Honorable
Persons, whose names I will onely (as M.
Fisher first did) expresse in these ensuing letters. L.
K.  L. M. B.  L. B. &amp; M. B. Then D. Whyte drew
out a copie of the aforesaid written paper, and asked
M. Fisher whether he wrote it. Vnto which M. Fisher
answered, I wrote such a thing, &amp; if it be a true copy,
I will defend it.
            
               
Then D. Whyte read the first point of the said paper,
in which was said: This is one, and has one, was, diuine
Faith &amp;c. This saith D. Whyte, is true, if Faith be
vnderstood explicite, or implicite. Which to be the true
sense M. Fisher assented.
            Then D. White read the second point, in which
was said, That this true, diuine Faith, was wholy prouided vpon
the word of God &amp;c. This also D. White yielded to be
true.
            Then D. White read the third point, in which was
said, That this word of God, vpon which Faith was grounded, is
not only the Word increate, but also the Word Created, to wit,
the diuine reuelation made manifest, partly by Christes 
                     〈◊〉
                  
preaching, partly by the holy Ghosts inward inspiration in 
                     〈◊〉
                  
hartes of the Apostles &amp;c.
            
            This point also D. White allowed, but knowing
what followed in the fourth point, he asked M. Fisher,
whether he thought that the holy Ghost was equally
in others, as in the Apostles? M. Fisher said, that the inspiratiō
of the holy Ghost was promised, &amp; giuen both
to the Apostles, &amp; others, yet not in the same degree,
nor in the samefull measure; but the Apostles, as being
after Christ the prime foundations of the Church, had
the holy Ghost in such high degree, and full measure,
that they could, and did write Canonicall Scriptures.
Others that were Pastours and Doctours, had it in an
inferiour degree, yet so, as by it they were enabled to
teach infallibly, and without change, the substance of
all pointes needfull to saluation, especially when in a
generall Councell, after discussion of the matter, they
did conclude as the Apostles and Seniours did, Visum
est spiritui sancto &amp; nis. It seemeth good to the holy
Ghost, and vs. The people also had a measure of the
same spirit, sufficient to enable thē to conceiue rightly

and to belieue stedfastly the teaching of their Pastours.
            
               D. Whyte did not disallow the substance of this
answere, but only made a verball Obiection, saying:
The Apostles had inspiration, Pastours and People onely illumination.
            
            
               M. Fisher answered, that both Apostles &amp; Pastours
had inspiration and illumination, in regard the motion
of the holy Ghost, as receiued in the vnderstanding,
is called Illumination, and as receiued in the will,
it is called Inspiration.
            
            L. K. bad them leaue that verball controuersy, and
proceed in the matter. D. Whyte excepted against
that part of the paper, wherin was said, That the word
of God was partly written, partly vnwritten, and
would haue nothing to be the word of God, but what
is written in Scripture.
            
               M. Fisher to iustifie that part of the paper, first alledged
that Text of S. Paul, Hold the traditions which you
haue learned, whether by our Word, or Epistle. 2. He made
these two ensuing arguments (to proue that more
is to be belieued by diuine Faith then is written in
Scripture.)
            It is necessarie to belieue, by diuine Faith, that Genesis,
Exodus, and other particuler Books are Canonicall,
and diuine Scripture.
            But this to be so, is not assuredly knowen by the
only Word written. Ergo &amp;c.
            Moreouer Protestants hould, and belieue this proposition:
Nothing is to be belieued by Christian Faith,
but what is contayned in Scripture:
            But this Proposition, is not contayned in the word
written. Ergo. Somthing is belieued euen by Protestants
which is not contayned in the written Word,
and therefore they must admit for a ground of Faith

some Word of God not written.
            
               D. Whyte answered: Although at that time when S.
Paul wrote the text alledged, some part of Gods word
was not written, yet afterwards all needfull to be belieued,
was written. This D. Whyte said, but did not,
not cannot proue, especially out of any parte of the
written Word.
            
               D. Woyte alledged this text, Omnis scriptura diuinit
                     〈…〉
                  
inspirata, vtilis est&amp;c. But (as M. Fisher then tould him)
this Text doth not proue the point which is to be proued.
For this text doth not say, that all which is diuinely
inspired, was written, or that Genesis, Exodus,
and other particuler books, are diuinely inspired, or
that nothing is to be belieued which is not contayned
in scripture; but only saith, That all, or euery Scripture diuinely
inspired, is profitable.
            
            
               D. Whyte said: Scripture is not onely said simply to
be profitable, but to be profitable, to argue, to teach, to
correct, to instruct, that the man of God may be perfect:
and therfore being profitable to all these offices, it
may be said to be sufficient.
            
               M. Fisher replyed: Although wood be profitable to
make the substance of the house, to make wainscot, to
make tables and stooles, and other furniture, yet hence
doth not follow, that wood alone is sufficient to
build and furnish a house. I will notsay, that heere
D. White was at a Nonplus, because I vnderstand that
word Nonplus, doth not please him; but the truth is
that to this D. Whyte did make no answere. And for my
part I professe, I do not see what answere he could
haue made to the purpose, and worthy of that Honorable,
and vnderstanding Audience.
            
               D. Whyte therefore without saying any thing to
this instance, seemed to be weary, and giving the paper

to M. Fisher, had him read on.
            
               M. Fisher taking the paper, read the fourth Point, in
which was sayd, That at the word of God manifested to the Apostles,
and by them to their immediate hearers, was not to cease
at their death, but was to be continued and propagated without
change, in, and by one, or other companie of visible Pastours, Doctours,
and lawfully-sent preachers successiuely in all ages &amp;c.
All which to be true being at last graunted, or not denyed
by D. Whyte, M. Fisher proposed the first of the
two arguments set downe in the aforesaid Paper. viz.
            If there must be in all ages one, or other continuall
succession of visible Pastours, Doctours, and lawfully-sent
Preachers by whom the vnchanged word of
God, vpon which Faith is grounded, was preserued &amp;c
preached in all ages since Christ; and no other is visible,
or can be shewed, besides those of the Roman
Church, and such as agree in Faith with them; Then
none, but the Pastours of the Romane Church, and
such as agree in Faith with them, haue that one, infallible,
diuine, vnchanged Faith which is necessarie to
saluation.
            But there must be such a visible succession, &amp; none
such can be shewed different in Faith from the Pastours
of the Roman Church. Ergo.
            
            Onely the Pastours of the Romane Church;
and such as agree in Faith with them, preserue and
teach that one, infallible, diuine, vnchaunged Faith
which is necessarie to saluation.
            
               D. Whyte answered, That it was sufficient to shew
a succession of visible Pastours, teaching vnchanged
doctrine in all points fundamentall, although not in
points not fundamentall.
            
               M. Fisher replyed saying: First, that if time permitted,
he could proue all pointes of diuine Faith, to be

fundamentall (supposing they were points generally
held, or defined by full authority of the Church; (to
which purpose he did recite the beginning of this sentence
of S. Augustine: Ferendus est disputator errans in
alijs quaestionibus non diligenter digestis, nondum plena authoritate
Ecclesia firmatis, ibi ferendus est error; non tantùm progredi
debet, vt ipsum fundamentum quatere moliatur. In
which S. Auston insinuateth, that to erre in any questions
defined by full authority of the Church, is to
shake the foundation of Faith, or to erre in points fundamentall.
But M. Fisher not hauing the booke at hand
(and fearing to be tedious in arguing vpon a text
which he had not ready to shew) passed on: and secondly
required D. Whyte to giue him a Catalogue of
all points fundamentall, or a definition or description
(well proued out of Scripture, and in which all Protestants
will agree) by which one may discerne which
be, and which be not points fundamentall.
            
               D. Whyte reiected this demaund, as thinking it vnreasonable
to require of him a Catalogue, or definition,
or description of Points fundamentall, out of
Scripture, in which all Protestants will agree. But
(considering in what sense D. Whyte did understand
this distinction of points fundamentall, and not fundamentall
(to wit, that none could be saued who did
not belieue all pointes fundamentall rightly; and that
none should be damned for not belieuing other
pointes, vnles he did wilfully against his conscience
deny, or not belieue them;) M. Fishers demand was
both reasonable and most necessary; for sith all Protestants
agree in houlding it necessarie to be certaine
of their saluation; and that none can be saued, who
do not belieue all points fundamentall; and that
in these pointes, one must not content himselfe with

implicite Faith, but must expressely know them; it is
most necessary, that all Protestants should out of
Scripture) which they pretend to be their onely Rule
of Faith) find, and conclude with vnanimous consent
certainly, what is, and what is not a fundamentall
point of Faith, necessary to saluation. For whiles
some hould more, some lesse to be fundamentall, and
none of them giueth (out of Scripture) a sufficient rule
by which it may be discerned, which is, and which is
not fundamentall; how can ech particuler Protestant
rest assured, that he belieueth expresly all points fundamentall,
or so much as is necessary, and sufficient to
make him assured of saluation. But to returne to the
Relation. D. Whyte, hauing reiected M. Fishers demand,
requiring a Catalogue, definition or description out of
Scripture (in which all Protestants will agree) said:
That all those points were fundamentall, which were
contained in the Creed of the Apostles.
            
               M. Fisher might haue asked him diuers questions
vpon this answere. 1. What text of scripture taught
him, that all the points contained in the Apostles
Creed were fundamentall in the sense aforesaid? Or,
That this Creed was composed by the Apostles, as a
summary of Faith, contayning points needfull (at least
necessitate Praecepti) to be expresly belieued by all men?
The Church indeed so teacheth, but the Scripture hath
not any text which doth expressly say so, or whence
by necessarie consequence so much may be gathered;
and therefore according to Protestant principles (permitting
nothing to be belieued but Onely Scripture)
the Apostles Creed ought not to be beleiued, as a rule
of any point of Faith, and much lesse a rule containing
all principall and fundamentall points of Faith.
            2. M. Fisher might haue asked, Whether Onely
               
the words of the Creed are needfull to be held, as a sufficient
foundation of Fayth, or the Catholique senses.
If onely the wordes; then the Arrians, and other condemned
Heretikes may be sayd to haue held all the
fundamentall points sufficient to Saluation; which is
contrary to the iudgement of Antiquity, and is most
absurd. If the Catholique sense; then the question
must be, who must be iudge to determine which is the
catholique sense? and whether it be not most reasonable,
and necessary, that the Catholique Church it
selfe, rather then any particuler man, or Sect of men,
should teach the true sense? When especially,Ioan. 14. &amp; 16. the holy
Ghost was promised to the catholique church (and
not to any particuler man, or Sect of men, differing in
doctrine from it) to teach it all Truth.
            3. M. Fisher might haue asked, whether all points
fundamentall were expressed in the creed, or not? If
they be not, by what other rule shall one know, what
is a point fundamentall? If all which is fundamentall
be expressed in the creed, then to belieue only Scripture,
or to belieue that there is any Scripture at
all, is not fundamentall, or necessary to Saluation;
but to belieue the catholique church (and consequently
the truth of all such doctrines of Fayth,
which she generally teacheth, or defineth in her generall
councells) is fundamentall. So as, we may say
with S. Athanasius, Whosoeuer will be saued, must belieue
the catholique Fayth (that is, the Fayth taught
by the catholique church) and this not only in part
or in a corrupt sense, but in all points, and in catholique
sense. For as the same S. Athanasius saith, vnles one
belieue the said Catholique faith (integram inuiolatam▪)
entiere and inuiolate, without doubt he shall perish
euerlastingly. All these questions M. Fisher might

haue asked, but he at that present only asked, Whether
all articles of the Creed, were held by D. Whyte to be
fundamentall?
            To which Question D. Whyte answered, That
all was fundamentall.
            
               M. Fisher asked, Whether the article of christs
descending into hell, were fundamentall?
            
               D. Whyte said, Yes.
            Why then (said M. Fisher) did M. Rogers affirme,
That the Church of England is not yet resolued,
               Rogers in his doctrine of the Church of England, Art. 3. 
               what is
the right sense of that Article?
            
            It was answered, that M. Rogers was a priuate
man. M. Fisher replyed: That his Booke in the title
professeth to be set out by publique authority. To
which M. Fisher might haue added. That the Booke
so set out by publique authority, beareth title of the
Catholique, or Vniuersall doctrine of the church of
England; by which addition is shewed a difference
betwixt this book of M. Rogers, and some others,
which were obiected to be set out by licence of the
catholique side: for these our books are only licenced
to come out in the name of such, or such a priuate
author, and as books declaring his priuate opinions:
but this of M. Rogers was authorized, and graced
with the title of the Catholique doctrine of the church
of England, and therfore ought by Protestants to be
more respected, then other priuate mens books.
            
               M. Fisher not thinking it necessary to presse this
difference, returned againe to D. Whytes first answere
to the maine argument, in which he hauing said,
That it was sufficient to shew a visible succession of
such as held points fundamentall, did implicitely
graunt it necessary, that a succession should be shewed
of such visible Pastours as did hold all points, which

at least himself held to be fundamentall, or necessary
to saluation. Whereupon M. Fisher bad D. Whyte
name a continuall companie, or succession of visible
Protestants (different from the Romane Church
which they call Papists) holding all points which
he accounted fundamentall.
            
               D. Whyte expresly graunted, That he could not
shew such a visible succession of Pastours and Doctours
(differing in doctrine from the Romane
church) who held all points which he accounted
fundamentall. Which his ingenuous confession, I
desire the Reader to note, applying it to the argument
which M. Fisher proposed, shewing that Onely
the Roman church hath had such a succession. For
if, as the argument vrgeth, one such succession hath
bene, and none differing in doctrine from the Roman
can be shewed by D. Whyte (being accounted
a prime Protestant Controuersist, who may teach such
as D. Featly, as was lately professed by D. Featly himself)
we may absolutely conclude, that no such visible
succession was of Protestants, so farre as they differ in
doctrine from the Roman church, and consequently
till they assigne some other (which they can neuer do)
they must acknowledge the Romane to be the only
church, or at least a church which hath had a visible
succession, teaching the vnchanged Faith of christ
in all ages, in all points, at least fundamentall: which
being acknowledged, worthily might M. Fisher aske
(as he did aske) D. Whyte, Why Protestants made a
schisme from the Romane church? and why Protestants
did persecute Romane catholiques, contrary
to the custome of the ancient Fathers, who still kept
vnity with other churches, although in their opinion
holding errours; (vntill the catholique church by

full authority defined them to be errours in Faith)
and that after such definition of the church (which
was yet neuer made against the Romane church)
they would still obstinatly persist in errour; as
appeareth in S. Cyprians case. To these demaunds
made by M. Fisher, D. Whyte answered; We do not
persecute you for Religion. About which answere
I desire the gentle Reader to obserue, that M. Fisher
asked two Questions. 1. Why Protestants made a
schisme from the Romane church? 2. Why Protestants
did persecute Romane catholiques?
            To the first of these questions being about Schisme,
D. Whyte answered not a word, and yet this was
the most important Question, sufficient to shew Protestants
to be in a damnable state, vnles they repent
and returne to vnity with the Roman church. For on
the one side, it cannot be denyed, but that schisme
or separation of ones selfe from church-Vnity, is a
most damnable sinne, which cannot be made lawfull
for any cause, nor cannot without repentāce, &amp; returning
to Vnity, be washed away, euen with martyrdome
it selfe, as the ancient Fathers confesse: And on
the other side it is euident (&amp; euen confessed by some
Protestants) that Protestants did separate themselues
from the Romane Church, which is confessed to be
the mother Church, and which cannot be shewed
to haue separated it selfe from a former church yet
extant, as the true church of christ must alwayes be
visibly extant; Neither can there be shewed any other
reason, why Protestants did make, and continue this
their separation, then were, or might haue bene alledged
by Heretiques, and Scismatiques of ancient
times, separating themselues from the catholique Roman
church: For setting asyde all temporall respects,

which doubtles were (but were very insufficient
and vnworthy) causes why some did first, and
do yet continue this separation; there cannot be
imagined any pretended cause which may not be reduced
to these two heads: to wit, corruption of
Manners, or corruption of Doctrine. Corruption of
manners, is not a just cause to make one leaue the
Faith, Sacraments, and rites of the church, our
Sauiour hauing sufficiently forewarned what is to
be done in this case,Matth. 21. when he said; Vpon the chaire
of Moyses the Scribes and Pharisees have sitten; all therefore
that they say vnto you, obserue, and do, but according
to their works do not. For by this is shewed
that the separation which in other places of Scripture
is commanded, is not meant so, as if it were
to be made by neglecting or contradicting the doctrine
of lawfully authorized Pastours, or by corporally
absenting ones selfe from communicating
with them in necessary Sacraments, and church
Rites, but only spiritually to departe from the imitation
of their ill manners. The second, to wit, corruption
of Doctrine, pertayning to the common
Faith of the catholique Church, neither did, nor can
happen to the whole visible church; christ hauing
promised, that the holy Ghost shalbe alwaies with
it, to teach it all Truth; and that Hell-gates shall
neuer so preuaile against it, as to ouerthrow in it
the fundation of all goodnes, to wit, true Faith. And
for other errours in such questions as are not determined
by full authority of the said catholique church,
S. Austens rule is to be obserued,Aug. de verb. apost. Ser. 14. whom when he
saith, Ferendus est disputator errans: neither must one
for the errour of a few, leaue the society and communion
of all; neither must one or a few, presuming

vpon their owne priuate reading, and interpreting
of scripture, or their priuate spirit (which is
or may be the comō pretext of all Heretiques) censure
&amp; condemne the doctrine, or practise of the vniuersall
Catholique Church to be erroneous: which to doe, is
by S. Bernards sentence, Intollerable Pride, and in S. Austans
iudgment, Insolent madnes.
            
            The beginning therefore and continuance of the
Schisme, and separation of the Protestants from the
Catholique Romane Church (in which euen, as
Caluin confesseth,Caluin l. Ep. epist. 141. there was made a discession &amp; departure
from the whole world) is very damnable,
and altogether inexcusable. Which perhaps was the
cause why D. Whyte passed ouer that part of the Question
(touching this Schysme) with silence, and onely
answered, as is aboue said, to the other parte saying:
We do not persecute you for Religion.
            
            To which answere M. Fisher replyed, saying: You
do vs wrong, for my self being a prisoner was never
taxed with any state matter, but do suffer for Religion.
L. M. B. made another answere, saying:
You of your side, did first persecute Protestants.
            
            
               M. Fisher answered, that we Catholiques hold all
points, in which Protestants differ from vs in doctrine
of faith to be fundamentall, and necessary to
be belieued, or at least not denyed, and so may haue
cause to punish them who deny, or contradict. But
Protestants, who believe catholiques to hold right
in all points which themselues esteeme fundamentall,
have no reason to persecute vs, for supposed errours
in points not fundamentall, which Protestants
do not account damnable. For better cleering wherof
M. Fisher, asked D. White, whether he thought errour
in a point not fundamentall to be damnable?
            
               
               D. White, said, No, vnles one hold it against his
conscience.
            
               M. Fisher asked, How one could hould an errour
against his conscience? meaning that one could not inwardly
in his conscience believe that be true, which he
knew in his conscience to be an errour.
            
               D. White answered, That by peruersity of will he
might hould an errour against the knowne truth.
Which answere is true, if he meane, that one who
knoweth the truth at this instant, may after by peruersity
of Will, incline the Vnderstanding to hold
the contrary errour. But that, at the same instant, he
should know the truth actually, and yet actually
hold, in the same instant, the contrary errour in his
conscience, or inward knowledg, is more then I think
any Philosopher can explicat. For this were to know,
and not know, and to belieue two contraries, Truth,
and Errour, about the same obiect in the same subiect,
the inward conscience at one, and the same instant,
which is impossible.
            M. B. meruayling at D. Whites answere asked,
him againe the same question, saying: May one be
saued that holdeth errour in points of Faith, not fundamentall,
supposing he hould not against his conscience?
            
               D. White sayd; Yes.
            Those (faith M. B.) who suffering for conscience
hould errour in Faith against their conscience, are
worthy to be damned.
            M. Fisher hauing obserued, that D. White had insinuated,
that one might be damned for holding errour
in points of Faith not fundamenall, in case he
hould them against his conscience, said; If it be damnable
to hold errours in points not fundamentall, in

case one hold them willfully against his conscience:
à fortiori, it is damnable to hold the like errours wilfully
and obstinatly, against the known iudgment,
and conscience of the Church. For as S. Bernard saith:
Qua major superbia,
               Bern. serm. 5. de resurrect. 
               quàm vt vnus homo iudicium suum praeferattoti
Congregationi? What greater pride, then that
one man should preferre his iudgment (or conscience)
before the iudgment (and conscience) of the whole
Church?
            
               D. Whyte said, he remembred that sentence of S.
Bernard: but it is not remembred that he gaue any good
answere, either to that sentence, or to the argument
confirmed by it. Neither indeed can he giue any good
answere, in regard it is certaine, that the iudgment &amp;
conscience of the whole Church (or Congregation
of so many faithfull, wise, learned, and vertuous men,
assisted by the promised Spirit of truth) is incomparably
more to be respected, and preferred before the
iudgment, and conscience of any priuate man; as appeareth
by that of Christ our Sauiour, who (without
excepting any who pretendeth to follow his conscience,
and without distinguishing the matter in
which he pretendeth to follow it, into points fundamentall,
&amp; not fundamentall) absolutely affirmeth,Matt. 1
                     •
                  .
               He that will not heare (that is, belieue and obey) the Church,
let him be to thee as an Heathen &amp; Publican.
            Hence Protestants (who preferre their priuate Iudgment
and Conscience before the iudgment and
conscience of the Catholique Church, in interpreting
Scriptures, or otherwise) may learne, in what state
they remaine, so long as they do thus, being by the
Censure of S. Bernard, extremely Proud, and in the
indgement of S. Austen insolently madde, and by the
sentence of Christ himselfe, to be accounted no better

then Heathens and Publicans.
            
            It seemeth that D. Whyte did not deeply ponder
this point, or els was willing to passe ouer it (as a
Cat ouer hote coales) and so he betooke himselfe to
oppugne another part of M. Fishers paper, in which is
sayd, that; No company of visible Pastours deliuering vnchanged
doctrine, could be shewed in all ages, besydes those of the
Romane Church.
            
            
               D. Whyte denyed this to be true, and (notwithstanding
he had before said that he could not shew
any companie differing in doctrine from the Roman
Church, holding in all ages all fundamentall points)
said, that both the Greeke Church, and the Protestant
Church had such a succession of visible Pastours:
which two sayings, how D. Whyte will reconcile,
pertayneth to him to declare.
            
               M. Fisher replyed, and tould him that the Greeke
Church changed, and erred in a point of Faith, to
wit, about the holy Ghost. A like, or greater change he
might, and in likelyhood would, haue tould him to
hauc bene in many points held by the Protestant
Church, if he had not bin interrupted by L. K. who
asked, Whether notwithstanding that errour of the Greeke
Church, Ignorant man might not be saued?
            
            
               M. Fisher answered to L. K. his question, saying:
Some ignorant men may be excused from actuall
sinne, in holding that errour, as, through inuincible
ignorance, one holding some errour against the holy
Trinity it self, may be excused. Yet for other actuall
sinnes, they might be damned for want of meanes necessary
for remission of them. This answere was
meant by M. Fisher of such ignorant men, who (although
by inuincible ignorance excused from the
actuall sinne of positiue Infidelity, Heresy &amp; Scisme)

wanted true supernaturall Faith, Hope and Charity,
out of which an act of true Contrition springeth; or
wanted the true, and lawfull vse of the Sacrament of
Pennance, &amp; Priestly Absolution; which being needfull
to obtaine pardon of sinne, may easily be wanting
to such people as commit other sinnes against the light
of nature, or against those good motions of Grace,
which now and then Almighty God giueth to all
sorts, who consequently (through this their owne
fault) are not illuminated with true supernaturall
Faith, but are permitted still to remaine in Infidelity,
or Heresy, or Schisme, or in a negatiue disposition of
want of all Faith, deuotion, and desire of vnion with
God, and such good men who truly serve god in his
true Church: of which sort of ignorant people, it is to
be doubted there be but to many in all (especially Infidel,
Hereticall, or Schismaticall) Countries. But
hence doth not follow, neither did M. Fisher euer
meane to affitme, that all ignorant Graecians, Protestants,
or of any other sort of Schismatiques, Heretiques,
or Infidels are damned; for if on the one side
this their ignorance be inuincible, so as to excuse them
from the actuall sinne of their Schisme, Heresy, and
Infidelity; and on the other syde, they by Almighty
Gods speciall grace, be preserued from other actuall
mortall sinne, and by the same grace be excited extraordinarily
to Faith, Hope, Charity, and to true
Contrition for all finne, they may be saued: But
this being extraordinary, no man ought ordinarily
presume, or rely on it, especially so, as to neglect the
ordinary meanes, knowne to be in the vnity of the
Catholique Roman Church.
            After this D. White excepted against another point
of M. Fishers paper, in which was sayd: That the Roman

Church had still held vnhanged doctrime of Fayth in all points
&amp;c. And for instances of change made, he obiected
Transubstantiation, Images, Communion vnder one kind, Sacrament
of pennance &amp;c. These points he slieghtly began
to touch, but did not (as the paper required) name
when, and by whome the change was made in these
points, but sayd; It was not needful to shew these circumstances.
As for example (sayth he) the Pharisies
held errour, in saying, that the gold of the Altar was
more holy then the Altar, which was a change in doctrine,
&amp; yet you cannot shew when, and by whome
this change was made.
            To this M. Fisher answered, that although he could
not on the suddaine tell when, and by whome this
Change was made; yet he did not doubt but that with
study he might find it out. And so indeed, he might
haue named the Author of the Sect of Pharisies, who
first brought in that error, and the time when that Sect
began, which is inough. For we do not presse Protestants
to tell the very day, or houre in which euery
one of our supposed Errors were brought in; but to
name the first Author of any erroneous doctrine, or
of any Sect of men who were specially noted for
teaching such a peculiar doctrine, and about what
yeare, or Age that Sect of men, first began; and
who they were, who then noted them to teach such
doctrine, contrary so the formerly receaued Fayth of
the vniuersall Church; as must be, and is vsually noted,
when especially any such notorious matters as
those which D. White obiected, were by any man,
or any sect of men, taught contrary to the formerly
receaued Faith of the vniuersall church.
            Sith therfore, the aforesaid circumstances are
vlually noted in other such kind of changes, and that

it is morally impossible, that such great changes and
so vniuersally spread ouer the world, should be made
ether in an instant, or in succession of time, and that
not one, or other writer would haue made mention
of the change, and when, where, and by whome it
was made, as they do of all other such matters; D.
White (who obiected such great changes of doctrine
to haue beene made in the Roman church, accusing
hereby greuiously her, which consessedly was once
the true Mother church,) is obliged and bound, not
only to proue this his accusation, by shewing the forsayd
circumstances, in good Authors, if he will not be
accounted an vnnaturall and false calumniator of
his true Mother-church: but he must also shew another
continually visible church, which neuer did admit any
any such change in doctrine of Faith, if he will
not impiously deny the truth of the Prophesyes and
Promises of Scripture, wherby we learne, that Hell
gates shall not preuaile against the church: And that
christ himself, and his holy spirit will alwaies be with
the church teaching it, and consequently enabling it
to teach vs all truth, and making it the pillar and
ground of truth, and consequently free from all error
in matters of Fayth.
            But D. White can neuer proue his accusation by
shewing out of good Authors the aforesayd circumstances
of the change of the Roman church, in doctrine
of Fayth, nor can shew any other continually
visible church, which did not admit change in doctrine
of Fayth. Let him therfore consider, whether
it be not better to recall his false vnnaturall accusation
of his Mother the Roman church, being sorry
for it, with purpose here after humbly to heare, belieue,
obey, and follo wher doctrine and direction,

rather then to incurre, not only the foresayd censure
of men, but also of christ himselfe, who sayth; He that
will not heare the Church, let him be to thee as an heathen &amp;
Publican: that is, cast out of the fauour of God, and all
good men, both in this present life, and also, if he do
not in time repent, in the future eternall life.
            These be the chiefe points which I haue gathered
out M. Fishers first Relation, which he shewed to D.
Whyte with an intēt that he should put him in mind
if any thing were not remembred, or misremembred:
But the Doctour at that time did not, nor could truly
say, that any thing was safely related; only he sayd, 1.
That himselfe did not remember a point or two, which
both M. Fisher and M. B. did perfectly remember to
haue bene so as is here related. 2. He sayd, that something
more was sayd then is related, which M. Fisher
did not deny, but was willing to add any thing, that
D. Whyte could put him in mind of, or that himselfe
should after remember: and so being put in remembrance
made by D. Whyte, to wit, Whereas M. Fisher
vpon some occasion or other, had sayd, That although
a generall Councell might erre in the premisses, yet not in
the Conclusion, D. Whyte obiected, saying: That in all
sciēces the conclusiō is no more certayne, thē the Premisses,
&amp; therfore if the premisses in a general councell
be fallible, the conclusion cannot be infallible. To
which M. Fisher answered, saying; Although in
sciences which depend only vpon the light of Nature,
the conclusion cannot be more certaine then the
premisses; yet in a generall councell, assisted by the
holy Ghost, in the finall conclusion, or definitiue
sentence, the conclusion is alwayes infallible, although
sometimes the premisses be fallible.
            And M. Fisher had great reason to answere in

this manner. Indeed if to define a matter of Fayth
were to conclude the same by way of discourse out of
Principles, as the Argument doth suppose; then if
Councels might erre in the Promisses they might likewise
erre in their Conclusion, and d
                  •
               finitiue sentence.
But this supposition is false, Infallibility in defining,
being a diuine Assistance, not to inferre one
thing out of another by way of connexion and consequence,
but to decree and declare what is conform
                  〈…〉
               
to the word of God, by way of authority, binding
the Church so to believe. And this definition is euer
infallible, though all the arguments the Councell
bringes by way of discourse in proofe of the definition
eyther before or after the same is made, be not still
demonstratiue.
            Another obiection M. Fisher hath since that time
remembred (to wit) that D. White alleaged something
out of Abulensis in Matt. 7. 19. which M. Fisher differred
to make answere vnto, vntil he might see the Author
himself, hauing had experience inough, how falsely
many Ministers the Authors, and how false their
Note-Bookes be. Now M. Fisher, hath seene the
booke, and findeth the words cited by D. White to
contayne two parts; one, as contrary to D. White as the
other seemeth contrary to M. Fisher, &amp; that the whole
discourse of Abulensis in that place, sheweth that euen
that part which seemeth contrary to M. Fisher, doth
nothing preudice M. Fishers cause, as will appeare
to any that will duly ponder all that is there sayd of
the Authority of the Church, in defining what bookes
be, and what be not Canonicall. For Abulensis expressly
declareth, that all, and only those bookes are to be accounted
Canonicall. which the church doth define to
be canonicall: and the reason why he did (in his priuate

opinion) thinke one, or two Bookes not to be
canonicall, which we do now hold for canonicall, is,
for that the Church had not then so cleerely defined
them to be Canonicall, as it hath done since A
                  〈…〉
               sts
wrot that passage as there are diuers other Bookes held
for Canonicall, euen by Protestants, which haue not
beene so esteemed by some of the Ancient Fathers, in
regard the church had not then so clearely defined
them to be canonicall, as is hath done in after times.
            A third obiection was made by D. White about the
worship of Images, which D. White would needs affirme
to be an Innouation, and gross
                     •
                   Error of Papists:
Which M. Fisher denied, and sayd, that the worship
(meaning the same worship which is due to the Prototypon)
is not giuen by vs to the Image it selfe.
This obiection D. White vrged no further the first
day; but the next day of meeting, he vrged those words
of Bellarmine, Datur veneratio ipsi imagini. M. Fisher anwered,
that Bellarmine did not meane that the same
worship, which was due to the Prototypon, was giuen
to the Image it selfe, but an inferior degree of worship,
and that also for the Prototypons sake.
            Then D. White betooke himselfe to Suares, saying:
That Suares did hold, that the same worship which
was giuen to the Prototypon, was giuen to the Image.
M. Fisher answering, sayd: You do not vnderstand our
Authors: For, sayd M. Fisher, they that seeme to giue
most, giue the least to Images; for those that say that
one and the same worship is giuen to the Image, and
that which is represented by it, hold the Image to be
incapable of any part of worship, and so the whole to
pertayne to the thing: Wheras others who distinguish
one honour to be due to the thing, and another farre
inferior to be giuen to the Image, giue something, as

               M. Fisher explicated in the example of the respect one
beareth to the picture of his friend, which although it
be not capable of that friendly respect, and affection
which by looking vpon it, he exciteth in himselfe
towards his friend represented by it; yet is it capable
of an inferiour degree of respect, as to be set in a more
worthy and eminent place &amp;c. then it should be, if
it were the picture of some other, who were not ones
friend.
            These be the chiefe Passages of this Conference
between D. White, and M. Fisher, so far as hath come
to my notice, who haue vsed so much diligence in inquiring
the truth of this matter, as I haue no doubt,
but for substance I haue not omitted any thing that
may much import, considering what the occasion, and
subiect of the Conference was; to wit, that Paper
written by M. Fisher, in which he proued the Roman
Church, and those who agree in Fayth with it, to be
that Company, of whome euery one must learne what
is the truth, in all points and questions of Fayth necessary
to saluation: which paper not being substantially
confuted, as it was not, by any thing sayd by D.
White, or any other at that time or after, D. Whyte is yet
obliged to make a better answere, if he meane to giue
satisfaction either to Catholiques or Protestants in this
most important point of a perpetually visible church,
of which all forts must learne true, diuine, infallible
Faith, necessary to Saluation.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            
            A
RELATION
OF THE
Conference between a certain B. &amp; M. Fisher,
defended against the said B. his Chaplayne.
            
               The Preface.
               
                  GENTLE Reader, I think
it needful to let thee vnderstand,
that whereas
the Chaplaine of a certayne
B. sayth: (in
the Preface of his Answere to a Relation
of what passed betweene the said
B. and M. Fisher,) That the Iesuite spread
abroad papers of this Conference, which were
full of partiality to his cause, more full of calumney
against the B. the truth is, that the
Iesuite did not at all, so much as in

speach, &amp; much lesse in papers publish
this, or either of the other two Conferences,
which he had with D. White,
vntill he was forced vnto it, by false
Reports giuen out about them, to his
priuate disgrace, and to the preiudice of
the Catholique Cause. Neither then
did he spread papers abroad, but only
deliuered a very few Copies to speciall
friends; and this not with intent to calumniate
either the B. or the Doctor,
or to make the papers common, but to
enable his friends to answere and countermaund
such false Reportes, as they
had heard, or might heare. Which being
so, I do not see, how the Chaplaine can
free himself from the faults of partiality
and Calumny, wherof he doth accuse
the Iesuite, vnles he do (by some other
proofs better then his owne, or his Maisters
bare affirmation) proue, that the
Iesuite spread such papers; shewing also
particulerly wherein he did relate partially

to his cause, and calumnlously against
the B. I say relate, in regard I do
not at this present promise to examine
exactly all doctrines insinuated in the
Iesuits Relation, and impugned by the
Chaplaine (as neither hauing sufficient
leysure, nor commodity of Bookes requisite
for such a worke;) but the Relation
to haue bene sincere and true, free
from partiality, more free from calumny,
I vndertake to defend. For which
purpose I thinke best to set downe the
Iesuits Relation (for the most part as I
find it in the Chaplains printed Copie)
in greater letters, and in a lesser letter
the Chaplains chiefest exceptions, and
my answere vnto them.
               I think the Iesuite himself for his
owne particuler respect, could be content
to let passe this partiall and calumnious
Censure of his Relation, suffering
it patiently as one of the ordinary persecutions,
which he, and others at this

day endure for the Catholique Faith,
and for that peculiar order of life which
he professeth, vnder the name of the
Society of IESVS; comforting himself
with the exāple of Christ his Apostles,Act. 5. 41.
                  who reioyced that they were thoughts worthy
to suffer Contumely, for the name of Iesus.
In this respect I say, I suppose the Iesuite
himself could be content, that nothing
were said to the Chaplaines Censure:
But considering the hurt which may
come to the common cause by his vniust
disgrace, I haue thought it necessary
to defend the sincerity and truth of his
Relation, and some of the chief heads of
doctrine conteined in it, to the intent
that hereby men may be moued better
to trust what he hath written heretofore,
or may write hereafter, in defence
of the Catholique Faith &amp; Church; &amp;
lesse trust his Aduersaries, who without
iust cause do so much endeauour to calumniate
his person, or writinges.
            
         
         
            
            M. Fishers Relation of the Conference,
betvveene a certaine B.
and himselfe.
            
               THE occasion of this Conference
was, for that it was
obserued, that in a second
Conferēce with D. VVhite,
all the speach was about
particuler matters, &amp; little or nothing
about a Continuall, Infallible, Visible
Church, which was the chief and onely
point in which a certaine Lady required
satisfaction, as hauing formerly
setled in her mind, that it was not for
her, or other vnlearned persons to take
vpon them toTo wit absolutly &amp; to rely vpō their priuate iudgment, so, as to aduenture Saluation vpō it alone, or chiefly. iudge of particulers,
without depending vpon the Iudgment
of the true Church.
            
               
This La. therefore hauing heard it
graunted in the first Conference, that
there must be a continual, visible Company
euer since Christ, teaching vnchanged
doctrine, in all points Fundamentall,
that is, in all points necessary
to Saluation, desired to heare this confirmed,
and proofe brought to shew
which was that Continuall,The Chaplaine noting the word, Infallible, to be sometimes put in, somtimes left out, taxeth M. Fisher of speaking distractedly But I note herein, that M. Fisher spake most aduisedly, and with precise care of pūctuall Truth: for when he speaketh of what was obserued, or desired by the La. he putteth in the word Infallible, because he knew it was an infallible Church which she sought to rely vpon. But when he speaketh of what D. Whyte or L. K. graunted, he leaueth it out, because they did not mention the word Infallible, but onely granted a visible Church in all ages teaching vnchanged doctrine, in all matters necessary to Saluation. Infallible,
Visible Church, in which one
may, and out of which one cannot, attaine
Saluation. And therefore hauing
appointed a time of meeting betwixt a
certaine B. and my selfe, and thereupon
hauing sent for the B and me, before
the B. came, the La. &amp; a friend of hers
came first to the roome where I was, &amp;
debated before me the aforesaid Question,
and not doubting of the first part,

to wit, That there must be a Continuall
Visible Church as they had heard grā
               ted
by D. VVhite, L. K. &amp;c. The Question
was, which was that Church? The
La. friend would needs defend, that not
only the Romane, but also the Greeke
Church was right. I told him, that the
Greeke Church had plainely changed,
and taught false in a point of doctrine
concerning the Holy Ghost, and that
I had heard say, that euen his Maiesty
should say, The Greeke Church hauing
erred against the Holy Ghost, had lost the
Holy Ghost. The La. friend not knowing
what to answere, called in the Bishop;
who sitting downe firstThe Chaplaine taxeth the Iesuite, as if in this parcell he did insult: and saith it was the B. his modesty to vse this excuse, and to say there were a hundred schollars better then he. But I do not see any Insultation, but a simple &amp; true narration of what was sayd: Neyther do I see lesse modesty in the Iesuits preferring a thousand before himself, then in the B. his preferring a hundred before himself. excused himself
as one vnprouided, and not much
studied in Controuersies, and desiring
that in case he should faile, yet the
Protestant Cause might not be thought
ill of, it hauing a hundred better Schollers
to maintaine it then he. To which
I said, there were a thousand better

schollers then I, to maintaine
the Catholique cause.
            Then the Question about the
Greek Church beingThe Chaplaine telleth, that the Iesuite sayd, that what the B. would not acknowledge in this, he would wring &amp; extort from him: But these words, of wringing &amp; extorting the Iesuite neuer vseth, euē to his meanest Aduersaries, &amp; therfore not likely to haue vsed thē to the B. but at most, that he would euince, by argument, or such like. proposed,
I said as before, that it had
erred. The B. said, that the errour
was not in a point
                  The Chaplaine faith, the B. was not so peremptory: his speach was, that diuers learned men, &amp; some of your owne are of opinion (as the Greeks expressed themselues) it was a question not simply fundamentall.
                  
                  But the Iesuite cannot remēber the B. to haue said these words; yet if he did, the Iesuite did not much misse of the chiefe point of the B. his meaning, which was by the distinction of Faith fundamentall and not fundamentall, to defend the error of the Graecians not to be such (although held against the knowen definitiue sentence of the Church) as doth hinder saluation, or exclude them from being members of the true Church. About which see more hereafter.
                Fundamentall.
            Wherupon I was forced to
repeate, what I had formerly
brought against D. VVhyte concerning
points fundamentall,
firstThe Chaplains corrupt Copie hath righting, inst
                     •
                  ed of reading the sentence of S. Austen. The whole sentence is set downe by the Chaplaine thus: This is a thing founded: An erring Disputer is to be borne with all in other questions not diligently digested, not yet made firme by full auauthority of the Church; there errour is to be borne with. But it ought not to goe so far that it should labour to shake the foundation it selfe of the Church: S. August. Ser. 14. de verbis Apost. cap. 12.
                reading the sentence of

               S. Augustine;
Ferēdus est disputator
errans &amp;c. Out of
which isOut of this place we may gather, that all points defined are fundamental. All points defined are (as S. Austen speaketh) made firme by full authority of the Church. But all points made firme by full authority of the Church are fundamentall, in such sense as the Iesuite taketh the word fundamentall, that is (in S. Austens language) such as cannot be denyed, or doubtfully disputed against, without shaking the foundation of the Church. For denying or doubtfully disputing against any one, why not against another, &amp; another, and so against all; sith all are made firme to vs by one and the same diuine reuelation, sufficiently applyed by one and the same full authority of the Church: which being weakened in any one, cannot be to firme in any other. proued that
all pointes defined by the
Church areBy the word Fundamentall, is vnderstood not only those Primae Credibilia, or prime Principles, which do not depend vpon any former grounds, for then all the Articles of the Creed were not (as both the B. and D. White say they are) fundamentall points; but all which do so pertaine to supernaturall, diuine, infallible, Christian faith (by which Faith Christ the only prime foundation of the Church, doth dwell in our hearts, (1. Cor. 3. 11.) &amp; which Fayth is to the Church the substance, basis, and foundation of all good things which are to be hoped for, Heb. 11.) as that (they being once confirmed, or made firme by full authority of the Church) if they are wittingly, willingly and especially obstinately denyed or questioned, al the whole frame and in a sort the foundation it self of all supernaturall diuine Christian Faith is shaken. fundamē
               tall.
            Secondly, I required to
knowe, what points the
Bishop woulde account

               The Chaplaine granteth, that there are quaedam prima Credibilia, or some prime Principles, in the bosome whereof, all other Articles lay wrapped and folded vp; So as euery point of the Creed is not a prime Foundation, and therefore the B. himself did not vnderstād the word fundamentall so strictly, as if that which in one respect is a foundation, may not in another respect (to wit, as included in, and depending vpō a more prime Principle) be accoūted a superstructure.
                fundamētall? He said;
All the points in theIf the B. meane, that Onely those points are fundamentall, which are expressed in the Creed of the Apostles; I meruayle how he can afterwards account Scriptures, wherof no expresse mention is made in the Creed, to be the foundation of their Faith. But if he meane, that not only those are fundamentall which are expressed, but also all that is infolded in the Articles of the Creed; Then not Scriptures onely, but some at least of Church-Traditions vnwritten may be accounted fundamentall, to wit, all those that are inwrapped in these two Articles, I belieue in the holy Ghost, The holy Catholique Church: as all those are, which being first reuealed by the holy Ghost vnto the Apostles, haue byn by successiue Tradition of the Church (assisted by the same holy Ghost) deliuered vnto vs; one of which is, That the Bookes of Scriptures themselues be diuine, and infallible in euery part: which is a foundation so necessary, as if it be doubtfully questioned, all the Faith built vpon Scripture falleth to the ground. And therefore I meruayle how the B. can say, as he doth afterwards in the Relation, That Scriptures Onely, and not any vnwritten Tradition, was the foundation of their Faith.
               
Creed were such.
            I asked, how then it
happened that M. Rogers
sayth, that the English
Church is not yet resolued
what is the right sense
of the Article of Christ his

descending into Hell? The
B. sayd, that M. Rogers
was but a priuate man.
But (said I,) ifThe reason why the Iesuite did specially vrge M. Rogers booke, was for that it was both set out by publique authority, and beareth the Title of the Catholique doctrine of the Church of England. Our priuate Authors are not allowed (for ought I know) in such a like sort, to take vpon them to expresse our Cath. doctrine in any matter subiect to question. 
               M. Rogers,
writing as he did by
publique authority be accounted
onely a priuate
man, in what Booke may
we find theBy Protestants publick doctrine in this place, the Iesuite meant, as he vnderstood the B. to meane, onely of English Protestants; for the words going before making mention only of the English Church, do limit the generall word, Protestants, to this limited sense. Protestāts
publique Doctrine?
            The B. answered; That
to the Booke of Articles

                  This Answer hath reference to that sense which the question had of Onely English Protestantes, and not of all English Protestants, out of such as the B. and others are, who by office are teachers of Protestant doctrine, who do either sweare to the booke of Articles, or by subscribing oblige themselues to teach that, and no contrary doctrine. But if the Chaplain (to discredit the Relation) will needs inforce a larger extent of the sense, contrary to the meaning of him that made the answere, and him that asked the Question, who vnderstood one another in that sense which I haue declared; he must know, that although none do sweare or subscribe besides the English clergy to the Book of Articles, yet all who wilbe accounted members of, or to haue communion with one and the same English Protestant church, are bound eyther to hold all those Articles, or at least not to hold contrary to any one of them, in regard the English Protestant church doth exclude euery one from their church by Excommunication ipso facto, as appeareth in their book of Canons. Can. 5. Who shall hold any thing contrary to any part of the said Articles.
                  
                  So as, in this respect I do not see, why any one who pretendeth to be of one and the same Protestant communion with the church of England, can be sayd not to be obliged to hold one, and the same doctrine which is in the book of Articles, not onely as the chaplaine sayth, in chiefest doctrines (which like a cheuerell point may be enlarged to more by those who agree in more, and straitned to fewer by those who agree in fewer points) but absolutly in all points, and not to hold contrary to any one, or any the least part of any one of them. Such a shrew (as it seemes) is the church of England become, (no lesse then the chaplaine saith, the church of Rome to haue bene) in denying her blessing, and denouncing Anathema against all that dissent (although most peaceably) in some particulers, remote inough from the foundation, in the Iudgment of the purer sort, both of forraine and home-bred Protestants.
                  
                they were all sworne:

and theThe Chaplaine saith, The Church of England grounded her positiue Articles vpon Scripture &amp;c. True; if themselues in their owne cause may be admitted for competent Iudges; in which sort some other Nouellist will say, that he groundeth his positiue Articles vpon scriptures; and his Negatiue refuse not only our Catholique, but also Protestant doctrines. As for example, Baptizing of Infants, vpon this Negatiue ground, it not expressely (at least euidently) affirmed in Scriptures, nor directly (at least not demonstratiuely) concluded out of it. In which case I would gladly know, what the Chaplaine would answere, to defend this doctrine to be a point of Faith, necessary (for the saluation of poore Infants) necessitate medij, as all Catholique Deuines hold? I answere with S. Austen, Aug. l. 1. contra Cresc. c. 31. Scripturarum à nobis tenetur veritas, cùm id facimus quòd vniuersae placet Ecclesiae, quam earundem scripturerum commend at authoritas: We hold the verity of Scriptures, when we do that which pleaseth the whole Church, which the authority of the same scriptures doth commend. But what answere the chaplaine can make, I cannot easily guesse, vnles with vs he acknowledg authority of church-tradition to be necessary in this case. Scriptures only,
not any vnwrittē Tradition
was the foundation
of their Fayth.
            
               
I asked, howThe Iesuite did not aske this question as doubting of the diuine authority of Scripture, but to make it seene, that beside scripture, which the B. sayd was the Onely foundation of Faith, there must be admitted some other foundation, to wit, Vnwritten Tradition, and this of infallible authority, to assure vs infallibly that these Bookes are diuine; which to be diuine is one point infallibly belieued by diuine, Faith, and yet cannot be infallibly proued out of Onely Scripture; therefore Onely Scripture cannot be sayd (as the B. said) to be the Onely foundation of Fayth, or of euery point belieued by Faith. I hope the Chaplaine (who is so carefull to auoyd all suspition of being familiar with impiety, as he would haue no question moued about this point vpon any termes or pretence) will not be so impious as to say, That to belieue these bookes to be diuine scripture, is not a point of diuine Faith; or that this point (being so important as it is, to be most firmely belieued) is belieued by diuine Faith, without any ground or foundation; or without a sufficiēt infallible, &amp; diuine foundatiō of Gods word, written or vnwritten. Sith therfore this is a point of Faith, &amp; hath a foundation, yea an infallible foundation; it is not against either art, or equity, or piety (for confutation of Error, and confirmation of Truth) to enquire what particuler foundation of Gods word, written or vnwritten, doth assure vs infallibly, that these particuler bookes containe the sole, and whole truth of God, belieued by christian Fayth. Neyther need any be troubled, or endangered by this question, but such as not finding any sufficient foundation in gods word written, do pertinaciously resolue, not to belieue any thing to be Gods word which is not written. Those that belieue that there is a word of God, partly written and partly vnwritten (according to that of S. Paul (2. Thess. 2.) Hold the Traditions whether by our word or Epistle) do easily, without too much turning in a wheele, or circle, answere the question. See the Reply to M. Wotton &amp; M. White in the Introduction (of which mention is made in the Relation,) where this, and diuers other important matters pertayning to the drift of this Conference, are handled at large. he knew
Scripture to be Scripture,
and in particuler Genesis,
Exodus &amp;c. These are belieued
to be Scripture, yet
not proued out of any
place of Scripture. The
B. said, That the Bookes
of Scripture are principles

to be supposed, and
needed not to be proued.
Against this I read what
I had formerly written
in my Reply to M. Iohn
White; wherin I plainly
in shewed, that this
                  The Chaplaine saith, that some body tould him, that the B. vntied the knot; But why doth not the Chaplaine tell how he did vntie the knot? It seemeth the knot was not well vntied, when the Iesuite had a Reply so ready, as is insinuated, by his only going againe and reading in the Book which he had so rudely writen. Although a Praecognitum in faith need not be so cleerly knowne as a praecognitum in science; yet there must be this proportion, that as primum praecognitum, the first thing foreknowne in a science, must be primò cognitum, first knowne, &amp; must not need another thing pertayning to that science to be priùs cognitum, knowne before it: So if in Faith, the Scriptures be the first and only foundation, and consequently the first thing knowne, primùm praecognitum, it must be in Faith primò cognitum, first knowne, and must not need any other thing pertayning to Faith to be priùs cognitum, knowne before it; &amp; so Church-Tradition, which is one thing pertayning to Fayth, could not (as the Chaplain saith it is, and as indeed it is) be knowne first, and be an Introduction to the knowledge of Scripture. Moreouer like as sciences which suppose a principle proued in a higher science, cannot haue certainty of that principle, but either by hauing seene that principle euidently proued by other principles borrowed of that higher science, or by giuing credit to some that haue seene, or haue by succession receiued it from others that haue seene it euidently so proued▪ So Faith cannot haue certainty of her first principles, but either by seeing proof from the knowledg of the Blessed, which ordinarily no mā now seeth, or by giuing credit immediatly to some who haue seene, as to Christ who cleerly saw, or to the Apostles to whom cleere reuelation (I say cleere in attestante) was made; or by giuing credit to others who by succession haue had it from the first seers. In which last case the certainty of these principles can be no greater then is the authority of that succession. If it be meerely humane and fallible, the science and Faith is humane and fallible. Neither can either science or Faith be diuine and infallible, vnlesse the authority of that succession be at least in some sort diuine and infallible.
                  The chaplain therefore, who (as it seemeth) will not admit church-Tradition to be in any sort diuine and infallible, while it doth introduce the beliefe of scriptures to be diuine bookes, cannot sufficiently defend the Faith introduced of that point to be infallible, vnles he admit an infallible impulsion of the priuate spirit ex parte subiecti, without any infallible sufficiently applied reason ex parte obiecti, which he seemeth not, not hath reason to doe 
                        〈◊〉
                      this were to open the gap to Enthusiasms of all vpstart Anabaptists, and would take away due proportion of Obiect and Subiect, and the sweet order of things which diuine prouidence hath appointed. It may be, that if he would but consider the Tradition of the Church, not only as of a Company of fallible men, in with sort the authority of it is but humaine and fallible, but also as it is the Tradition of a Company; which (by it owne light) sheweth it self to be assisted by Christ and his holy Spirit, farre more cleerely then Scripture (by it owne light) doth shew it selfe to be the infallible word of God; he would find no difficulty in that respect to account the authority of Church-Tradition to be infallible, and consequently not only able to be an Introduction, but also an infallible motiue reason or at least condition ex Parte obiecti, to make both it self, and the bookes of Scripture appeare (infallibly, though obscurely) to our soule disposed and illuminated by Gods spirit, to haue in them diuine and infallible authority, and to be worthy of diuine and infallible credit, sufficient to breed in vs diuine and infallible Fayth.
                  Neither do I see why the Chaplain may not consider the Tradition of the present Church these two waies, as well as the present scriptures printed and approued by men of this age. For if the scriptures printed and approued by men of this age must be considered, not onely as printed or approued by men, in regard the credit giuen to them thus considered can be no more then humane; but also as printed, and by authority of men assisted by Gods spirit approued to be true copies of that which was first written by the Holy Ghosts Pen-men, before we can giue infallible credit vnto them; I see no reason, why the like twofold consideration of the Tradition of the present church may not be admitted, especially when as the promise of Christ and his holy Spirits continuall presence and assistance (Luc. 10. 16. Math. 28. 19. 20. Ioan. 14. 16.) was made no lesse (but rather more) expressly to the Apostles and their successours, the lawfully-sent Pastours and Doctours of the Church in all ages, in their teaching by word of mouth; then in writing, or reading, or printing, or approuing copies of what was formerly written by the Apostles.
                  Perhaps the Chaplaine will aske mee, how I know that any church or company of men of this age, or any age since the Apostles, haue promise of christ and his holy spirits assistance? I answer that I know it both by Tradition and Scripture (considered in the twofold manner aforesaid) both which without any vitious circle, mutually confirme the authority of ech other (as a Kings Embassadors word of mouth, and his Kings letter beare mutuall witnesse of ech other); And I do not want other both outward and inward arguments or motiues of Credibility, which are sufficient not only to confirme the Fayth of belieuers, but also to perswade well disposed Infidells, that both the one and the other were sent from God, and that one is the infallible word of God, speaking in and by his Legats, the lawfully-sent preachers, of the Church; The other, the infallible word of God speaking in and by his letters the holy scriptures, which he hath appointed his said legats to deliuer and expound vnto vs, and which among other things do warrant that we may heare and giue credit to these Legats of Christ, as to Christ the King himself.
                Answere

were was not good; and
that no other Answere
could be made but by admitting
some Word of
God vnwritten, to assure
vs of this point.
            
               
               
From this the La. called
vs, &amp; desiring to heare,
                  The Chaplain saith: As it is true, that this question was asked, 
                           〈◊〉
                         it is false, that it was asked in this forme, or so answered. I answer that the Iesuite doth not say that the La. asked this question in this, or any other precise forme of words, but onely saith, she was desirous to heare, whether the B. would graunt the Roman Church to be the Right Church: which to haue ben her desi
                        •
                     e the Iesuit is sure, as hauing particulerly spoken with her before, and wished her to insist vpon this point.
                  Secondly, he is sure, that she did not propound the question in that precise forme insinuated by the Chaplayne, vz. whether the Romane Church be a true Church; as if she meant to be satisfied with hearing the B. say, that the Rom. church is a true church, and the Greek church another, and the Protestant another. This, I say, could not be her Question, for that she was persuaded that all these were not true and right, and that there was but One Holy Catholique church; and her desire was to heare, whether the B. would graunt the Rom. church, (not only that which is in the Citty or Diocesse of Rome, but all that agreed with it) to be it?
                  Thirdly, what precise forme of words the La. did vse, the Iesuite did not remember perfectly, and therefore did not aduenture to set downe; but by the B. his Answer which he perfectly remenbred, &amp; so set downe in these words (It was) he thinketh that her question was, whether the Roman church was not the right church? (vz. once, or in tyme past, before Luther and others made a breach from it?) To which question so vttered, or so vnderstood (as it seemes by the Answere, and the ensuing discourse made by the B. it was vnderstood) the B. might truely (&amp; certainly did) answere, as is related (to wit) not, It is; but, It was: vz. once, or in tyme past the right Church; for so the Chaplaine doth heere confesse pag. 37. The time was &amp;c. that you and we were all of one belief. Out of which answere it may be the B. suspected that the La. would inferre: If once it were the right, what hindereth it now to be? sith it did not depart from the Protestant Church, but the Protest. Church departed from it. And therefore (as in the Text) he was willing to graunt, that the Protestants made a Rent or diuision from it &amp;c.
               
whether the B. would
grant the Roman Church

               
to be the right Church?
The B. graunted, That it
was. Further he
                  The Chaplaine (hauing told vs that the B. could be hartily angry,) saith: The B. neuer said nor thought, that Protestants made this rent. The cause of the schisme is yours &amp;c. I answere, that the Iesuite is sure, that whatsoeuer the B. thought (which may be was as the Chaplain now expresseth, to wit, that we had giuen cause to the Protestants to do as they did;) yet he did say (either ijsdem or aequipollentibus verbis) iust as is in the Relation. For the Iesuite did in fresh memory take speciall notice of this passage, in regard it concerned a most important point, which being vrged by him in the first Conference against D. White in these words, Why did you make a schisme from vs? Why doe you persecute vs? the Doctour slipped ouer that of the schisme without denying it to haue ben made by them, or laying the cause to vs, and only answered to the other, saying. We do not persecute you for Religion. The Iesuite therefore, say, did, as he had reason, take speciall notice in fresh memory, and is sure he related at least in sense, iust as was vttered by the B.
                  And I aske the Chaplain, what reason the B. had to discourse so long as he did, endeauoring to shew what reason Protestants had to make that rent or diuision, or (if he like not these words) that discession, (to vse Caluins phrase) or departure, not only from the church of Rome, but also (as Caluis, lib. Epist. ep. 141.) confesseth, à toto mundo, from the whole world; if he had not (as the Iesuite related) confessed that Protestants, being once members of the Roman Church, separated themselues from it, as the world knowes they did, when they got the name of Protestants, for protesting against it. Now for the Chaplains ascribing the Cause of the schisme to vs, in that by excommunication we thrust them from vs; he must remember, that befo
                        •
                     e this, they had diuided themselues by obstinate holding and teaching opinions contrary to the Roman Fayth, and practise of the Church, which in S. Bernards iudgment (serm. de resur.) is most great pride. Quae maior superbia &amp;c. What greater pride, then that one man (Luther for example) should prefer his Iudgment, not only before a thousand Austens, and Cyprians, and King Harry-Churches; but before the whole Congregation of all christian churches in the world? which in S. Austen his Iudgment is most insolent madnes; for, contra id disputare &amp;c. to dispute against that which the vniuersall church doth practise, is, saith S. Austen, most insolent madnes.
                  What then? Is it, not onely by way of doubtfull disputation, but by solemne and publick &amp; protestation, to condemne the generall practise of the church as superstitious, and the doctrine as erroneous in Fayth, yea as hereticall and euen Antichristian? All this considered, the B. hath no cause to be hartily angry, either with the Iesuite for relating, or with himself for granting Protestants to haue made a rent or diuision from the Rom. church; but might with a safe conscience yet further grant, as one did (was it not He?) to an Honorable person, That it was ill done of those, who did first make the s
                           •
                        paration, Which is most true, both in regard there can be no iust cause to make a schisme and diusion from the whole Church (for the whole Church cannot vniuersally erre in doctrine of Fayth, and other iust cause there is none) and also for that those who first made the separation (Luther and his Associates) gaue the first cause in manner aforesayd to the Rom. church to excommunicate them, as by our Sauiours warrant she might, when they would not heare the church, which did both at first seeke to recall them from their nouel
                        •
                      opinions, and after their breach did permit, yea inuite them publikely with safe conduct to Rome to a Generall Councell, and freely to speake what they could for themselues. And I make no doubt, (so farre is the Rom. Church from being cause of continuance of the schismes, or hinderance of Re-union) that it would yet (if any hope may be giuen that Protestantes will sincerely seeke nothing but truth and peace) giue them a free hearing, with most ampie &amp; safe conduct; which is more then euer we English catholiques could obtayne, although we haue made offers diuers times to come to publique Dispute, first in Queene Elizabeth her dayes, and also in his Maiesties that now is; only requiring the Princes word for our safe
                        •
                     y and equality of Conditions of the dispute. Vnto which offer our Aduersaries neuer did, nor euer will giue good Answere: As one saith; Honestum responsum nullum dabunt praeter vnum, quod numquam dabunt; Regina (Rex) spondet, Aduola. Camp. inrat, Acad. red.
                  
                granted,
that Protestants made a
Rent or Diuision from it.
            Moreouer he said, he
would ingenuously acknowledge,
that Corruption
of māners was not a
sufficient Cause to iustifie
their departing from it.
            But (said he) besides
Corruption of manners,
there were Errours in doctrine,
which whē the Generall
Church would not
reforme, it was lawfull for
particuler churches to reforme
themselues.
            
               
               
I
                  This question the Iesuite made chiefly against that part of the B. his last speach, in which he said, There were errours in doctrine; for if the B. meant (as the Iesuite vnderstood him to meane) that there were errours of doctrine of Fayth in the Generall Church, neuer did any lawfull &amp; competent Iudge so censure, neither can it so be. No power in Earth or Hell it self can so far preuayle against the Generall Church of Christ, built vpon a Rock, as to make it, or the pastours thereof erre generally in any one point of diuine truth. Christs promises stand (Matth, 16. &amp; 28. Luc. 22. Ioan. 14. &amp; 16.) and will neuer permit this, no not in Antichrists dayes. Particuler Pastors &amp;
and Churches may fall into Heresy or Apostasy, but the whole Church cannot. It may sometyme not expresly teach, or know all diuine truthes, which afterwards it may learne by study of Scriptures and otherwayes; but it neuer did, nor can vniuersally, by its full authority teach any thing to be diuine truth, which is not; and much lesse, any thing to be a matter of Fayth which is contrary to diuine truth, either expressed, or inuolued in Scriptures rightly vnderstood. So as no reformation of Fayth can be needfull in the Generall Church, but only in particuler Churches; in which case also when the need is onely questionable, particuler Pastours or Churches must not take vpon them to iudge, and condemne others of errour in Fayth, but as S. Irenaus intimateth, must haue recourse to that Church which hath more powerfull Principality, the Church of Rome, and to her Bishop being Cheife Pastour of the whole Church, as being Successour to S. Peter: To whom Christ promised the Keyes, (Math. 16.) For whom Christ prayed, that his Fayth might not faile: (Luc. 22.) and whom he charged to confirme his brethren; and to feed and gouerne the whole flock, lambes and sheep (loan. 21.) people and Pastours, subiects and superiours; which he shall neuer refuse to do in such sort, as that this neglect shall be a iust Cause for any particuler man or Church to make a schisime or separation of himself and others, from the whole Generall Church, vnder pretence of Reformation either of manners, or of Fayth.
                  Protestants therefore did ill in first deuiding themselues from the Generall Church, and do still ill in continuing deuided from it. Neither can those Protestants be excused from intolerable pride &amp; insolent madnes, who presume to be Accusers, Witnesses, Iudges, &amp; Executioners of the sentence pronounced by themselues against the Church in Generall, and against the principall and Mother Church, and the B. of Rome, which is, and ought to be their Iudge in this case. For although it be against equity that Subiects and Children should be accusers, witnesses, iudges and executioners against their Prince and Mother in any case; yet it is not absurd that in some case the Prince or Mother may accuse, witnesse, iudge, and (if need be)
execute Iustice against vniust or rebellious subeuects, or euill children.
                asked; Quo Iudice,
did this appeare to be so?
Which question I asked,
as not thinking it equity
that Protestants in their
owne Cause should be Accuers, Witnesses, and
Iudges of the Romane
Church.
            
               
               
I also asked; Who ought
to iudge in this case? The
B. sayd:
                  It is true, when the Question is about the Generall Fayth of the church, the matter may be made most firme, if the church in a Generall Coū
                     cell with the full authority of her cheif Pastour, and all other Pastours (whome all people must obey (Rom. 13. Hebr. 13.) decree, what is to be held for diuine truth, by Visum est spiritui sancto &amp; nobis (Act. 15.) and by adding Anathema to such as resist this Truth. For if this be not firme and infallible, what can be so firme and well founded in the church, which vnder pretext of seeming euidēt Scripture or demonstration, may not be shaken, and called in question by an erring disputer? For if all Pastours being gathered togeather in the name of christ, praying vnanimiter for the promised Assistance of the Holy Ghost, making great and diligent search and examination of the Scriptures, and other grounds of Fayth, and hearing ech Pastour declare what hath been the ancient Tradition of his church, shall in fine conclude and decree in manner aforesaid, what is to be held for diuine truth: If (I say) the Councell in this decree may erre, and may be controlled by euery particuler, or any particuler vnlearned, or learned man, or church, pretending euident text of Scripture or cleere demonstration (supple, Teste &amp; Iudice seipsis;) what can remaine firme or certaine vpon Earth, which may not by a like pretence be cōtrolled, or at least (by one or other) called in question?
                  A Generall councell therefore being lawfully called, continued and confirmed, is doubtles a most competent iudge of all controuersies of Fayth. But what is to be done, when a Generall councell cannot be called, as many times it cannot by reason of manifold impedimēts, or if being called, all will not be of one mind; (As among Protestants and others, who admit no Infallible meanes, rule, or iudge beside Onely Scripture, which ech man will interprete as seemeth best to his seuerall priuate Iudgment or spirit, it is scarse to be hoped that all, or the maior part will euer so agree, as to remaine constant in one and the same mind:) Hath christ our Lord in this case prouided no meanes, no rule, no iudge, which may Infallibly determine and end controuersyes, &amp; procure vnity and certainty of belief being so necessary for the honor of God, and the good of his church? Must people for want of such a iudge, rule or meanes, continue not only moneths and yeares, but whole Ages in vncertainty and disiunity of Fayth, and in perpetuall Iarres about euen maine matters of diuine truth? There is no earthly Kingdome that (in case matters cannot be composed by Parlament, which cannot be called vpon all occasions, and at all tymes) hath not beside the law-bookes, some liuing Magistrates and iudges, and aboue all one visible King, the highest Magistrate and Iudge, who hath authority sufficient to end controuersies, and procure peace and vnity, and certainty of Iudgments, about all temporall affayres: And shall we thinke that christ the wisest King hath prouided in his kingdome, which is the church, onely the Law-bookes of Holy Scriptures, and no liuing visible Magistrats and Iudges, and aboue all One cheife Magistrate, and iudge, so assisted with his spirit and prouidence, as may suffice to end controuersies, and breed vnity and certainty of Fayth, which neuer can be while euery man may interprete Holy Scripture, the Law-booke as he list?
                A Generall
Councell.
            I told him, that a Generall
Councell (to wit of
Trent) had already iudged,
not the Roman Church,
but the Protestant, to

hold Errour. That
said the B. was not
a
                  The chaplain saith, that the B. said not only so, but that, it was no Generall Councell. I answere, that if the B. said so, it was onely for want of memory that the Iesuite did not relate it so: for the Exceptions which the B. did or can make against the lawfulnesse or generallnesse of the Councell of Trent, may be made by Arrians against the councell of Nice. It is not necessary to the lawfulnesse and generallnesse of a Councell that all Bishops of the world be actually present, and actually subscribe or yield assent; but that such promulgation be made as is morally sufficient to giue notice that such a Councell is called, and that all may come if they will, and that a competent number, at least the maior part, of those which be present, yield assent to the decree.
                lawfull Councell,
So, sayd I, would

               As Protestants do thinke that the councell of Trent is not lawfull, for hauing (in their Iudgment) departed from the letter &amp; sense of Scripture: so did the Arians thinke of the councell of Nice. And as Protestants do iustifie that some were sent from the Pope to Trēt, and that the Pope was President: So doubtlesse did the Arians mislike, that at Nice the Pope had Legats, who did carry his messages, and one of them in his place sate as President. the Arrians say of
the Coūcell of Nice.
The B would not
admit the case to be
like, pretending that
the Pope made Bishops
of
                  The Chaplain saith, that the B. did not say, that the Pope made Bishops of purpose &amp;c. I answere, that the Iesuite doth not say that the B. expresly said to; but that (by insinuation) he did pretend so much, which in effect the chaplaine seemeth to graunt, when he saith (pag. 40.) the B. said, the Pope made himself a strōg partie in it. For although these words may be taken in another sense, yet they may also be taken in that sense which the Iesuite by the circumstances of the B. his speach) did then vnderstand, and expresse in his Relation: for that a great number of Italian Bishops, which the Chaplain saith the B. alledged as a proof, may very well import, that the B. cōceiued the Pope to haue made more Italian Bishops then of other Countryes, of purpose to haue a strong faction. But this proof was so weake, as the
Iesuite might well say, it was no proofe, nor worthy of answere, or of looking into the book for it; it being only a surmise of Aduersaries, who are apt to interprete euery thing to the worst. Italian Bishops might be more, as being neerer, (as in Greeke Councells more Grecians were present) without any factious Combination with the Pope, in any other sort then all the Cath. Bishops in the world, who are as much vnited with the Pope for matters of Fayth, defined in the Councell, as any Italian Bishop.
                  Neither can the B. proue, that any Catholique French, or Spanish, or of any other Country, or the schismaticall Greekes did agree with Protestants in those points which were defined in the Councell, especially, after it was confirmed by the Pope. For they all, euen Grecians, did, &amp; do at this day vnanimously oppose Protestāts, as appeareth by the Censure of Hieremias the Grecian Patriarch. So as if such a free Councell as the B. and others wished, were gathered out of East and West, Protestants (doubtles) would be condemned for Heretiques, and their negatiue refutes and denialls of ancient Articles, for Heresies, by more then the double maior Part compared to those who would take their part. For although (as all Heretiques vse to do.) Protestants perswade themselues, Scriptures to be euident for their opinions, and that with euident demon̄trations they should be able to conuince all the world, that they teach truth, and nothing but truth; yet they would find innumerable others as learned (to say no more,) and as well studyed in Scripture, and skilfull in making demonstrations, who are of another mind.
                purpose
for his side: but this
the B. proued not.
            
               
In fine, The B. wished,
that a lawfullI meruaile, in what sort the B. will describe such a Generall Councell; and how it should be gathered; and what Rules are in it to be obserued, which are morally likely so to be obserued as to make an end of cōtrouersies, better then our catholique Generall councels. Generall.
Councell were called to
end Controuersies. The
persons present said, The

King was enclined therunto,
and therefore we
Catholiques might do
well to concurre.
            I asked the B. whether
he thought, a Generall
Councell might erre? He
said, it might. If a Generall
Councell may erre, what
neerer are we then (sayd
I) to Vnity after a Councell
hath determined? yes
(said he) although it may
erre yet we shall be bound
toThe Chaplaine saith, that the B. added a Caution (which the Iesuit omitteth) saying: The determination of a Generall coūcell erring, was to stand in force, and haue externall obedience at least yielded to it, till euidence of Scripture, or a demonstration to the contrary made the errour appeare, and vntill thereuppon another Councell of equall Authority did reuerse it. I answere, that added Caution (which eyther was not then added, or not remembred by the Iesuite) maketh the B. his Answere far worse, then as the Iesuit did relate. For whereas the Iesuite relateth onely thus, Although it may erre; this caution maketh the case to be, that it doth actually erre. And whereas the Iesuite relateth, That we (not knowing whether it do erre or not, but only that it may erre,) are bound to hold it till another come to reuerse it; this caution doth put the case so, as if the determination of a Generall Coūcell actually erring, were (not ipso iure inualide, but) such as is to stand in force, &amp; to haue externall obedience at least yielded vnto it, till (not onely morall certainty, but) euidence of Scripture, or a demonstration to the contrary make the errour appeare; and after the errour appeareth, yet we must continue this yeilding of obedience: And how long? Vntill thereupon a
Councell (and not euery Councell, but) of equall authority do reuerse
it, which perhaps will not be found in a whole Age. Verily
I can not belieue, that the B. vpon better aduisement will allow
this Caution, or giue any thankes to his Chaplain for setting it
downe, but will commend the lesuite for relating his speach more
truely, and at least lesse disgracefully. hold it, till another
come to reuerse it.
            After this, we all rising,
The La. asked the B. whether
she might be saued in
the Roman Fayth? he answered,

Shee
                  Heere againe the Chaplain
taxeth the Iesuite saying,
That the B. did not answer thus in
particuler. But the Iesuite is sure
he did; and it appeareth to be
so by the Iesuits wordes who
said to the La. Marke that. Vnto
which the B. replied saying, She may be better saued in it then you; which
Reply sheweth that the B. had said, that she in particuler might be
saued in the Roman Fayth. Otherwise, if his first Answere had ben
as the chaplaine would now make, the B. should haue said, The ignorant
may be saued in it, but neither you, nor she. But the Iesuite is sure
that this Answere of the B. and Reply of the Iesuite (Marke that) was
iust as he related, without any such addition, as now the chaplain
doth relate; and that if such a Caueat were added, it was after the
end of the conference, and not in the Iesuits presence.
                  Out of this last passage the Chaplain obserueth that Catholiques
take aduantage, and make vse of the argument drawne from Protestants
granting, That one liuing and dying a Rom. Catholique may be saued;
accounting it secure so to liue and die, euen by confession of Aduersaries.
The force of which argument he endeauoureth to weaken by
saying, that although Protestants grant it to be possible, yet they say
withall that it is not secure, but hard &amp;c. But he must remember,
that when Protestants graunt, that in the Rom. Fayth and Church
there is ground sufficient, and consequently possibility of saluation;
this is a free confession of the Aduersaries argument themselues, and
therefore is of force against them, and is to be thought to be extorted
from them by the force of truth it self. But when Protestants do say▪
that saluation is more securely and easily had in Protestant Fayth &amp;
Church, then in the Romane; this onely is their partiall priuate
opinion in their owne behalf, which is of no weight, especially
when Romane Catholiques farre more in number, and farre more
spread in place, and of much longer continuance in tyme, and for
vertue and learning at least equall, or rather much exceeding Protestants,
do confidently, and vnanimously, and with authority and
reason proue, that (according to the ordinary Course of Gods prouidence)
Out of the Cath. Romane Church, there is no possibility of saluation.
And therefore, who will not thinke it safer to adhere to the Cath. Romane
Fayth and Church, in which all both Catholiques and
best learned Protestants do promise possibility of saluation without
doubt, then to the Protestant Church, sith all Roman Catholiques
do threaten damnation to all who obstinately adhere vnto it; and
dye in it? The which threat, doth not proceede out of malice, or
want of Charity, but is grounded in Charity; as are the like threats
of Christ our Sauiour, and Holy Fathers, who knowing that there
is but One True Fayth, and One True Church, out of which there is no
saluation, do out of their Charitable care of our soules good, so
commend to vs the beliefe of that Fayth, and the cleauing to that
Church, as they pronounce, He that shall not belieue, shall be condemned.
(Mar. 16.) and, He that will not heare the Church, and haue it for his Mother,
is to be accounted as a Heathen and Publican (Matth. 18.) and cannot
haue God to be his Father; accounting it more charity to fore warne
vs by these threats, of our perill, that we may feare and auoide it,
then to put vs in a false security, and so to let vs runne into danger,
for want of foresight of it.
                  Those examples which the Chaplaine giues of the Donatists giuing
true Baptisme in the opinion of all, and Protestants holding a
kind of Reall Presence not denied by any, are nothing like our case.
For in these cases there are annexed other reasons of certainly
knowne perill of damnable schisme and heresie, which we should
incurre by cōsenting to the Donatists deniall of true Baptisme to be
among Catholiques; and to the Protestants denyall, or doubting of
the true substantiall presence of Christ in the Eucharist. But in our
case there is confessedly no such perill of any damnable Heresy,
schisme, or any other sinne, in resoluing to liue and die in the Catholique
Rom. Church: and in case some Protestants should say, that
there is perill of damnation in liuing and dying Roman Catholiques;
the authority of them that say there is perill, being so few (in
comparison of those who say there is none,) and so passionate and
partially affected men, who are in this their saying contradicted by
their owne more learned brethren, ought not to be respected more
then a Scarre-crowe. But the authority of those who allow saluation to such as do liue and die Roman Catholiques, being so many,
so ancient, so vertuous, so learned, and some no way partially affected,
out opposite to the Romā Church, ought to be accoūted of exceeding
great weight, &amp; may worthily perswade any wise man that
it is most secure to liue and dye a Roman Catholique, and consequently
that in so important a matter this most secure course of liuing
and dying in the Roman Church, ought in all reason to be
chosen, and that so pretious a Iewell as the Soule is, ought not to
be left to the hazard of loosing heauen, and falling into hell, by relying
vpon ones ownes opinion, or the opinion of those few new
Protestant Doctours, who acknowledg that their whole congregatiō
may erre: &amp; much more therfore may they thinke that ech member
therof may be deceiued, in following his owne, or any other
mans opinion.
                might.
I bad her mark that. She
(sayd the B.) may be better
saued in it, then you.

               
D. White
                  
                     Heere the Chaplain taxeth
the Iesuite for falsly relating
D. Whites Answer, and saith he
hath spoken with D. White,
who auowes this, &amp; no other
Answere: He was asked in the
Conference, whether Papists errours
were fundamentall? To this he gaue
answere by a distinction of persons, which held and professed the errours; Namely,
that the errours were fundamentall reductiuè, by a reducent, if they
who imbraced them did pertinaciously adhere vnto them, hauing sufficient
meanes to be better informed: Nay further, that they were materially in the
kind and nature of them▪ leauen, drosse, haye, and stubble; yet he thought withall,
that such as were misled by education, or long Custome, or ouer-valuing
the soueraigntie of the Romane Church, and did in simplicity of heart imbrace
them, might by their generall Repentance, &amp; faith in the merits of Christ▪
attended with Charity and other vertues, finde mercy at Gods hands. But that
he should say, signanter &amp; expressè, that none of yours or your fellowes errours
were damnable, so long as you hold them not against your Conscience, that
he vtterly disauowes &amp;c.
                  To this the Iesuite answereth; first, that he did not in this his Relation
say, that D. White did signanter, and expresly say these precise
words, None of yours, or your fellowes errours are damnable. Secondly, he
saith, that D. White did not signanter, and expresly make this precise
Answere which now he maketh, nor scarse any part of it; as appeareth
by the Relation of the first Conference made by the Iesuite
in fresh memory, and conferred with D. White himself, who did
not at that time contradict it in this point.
                  Thirdly, the reason which moued the Iesuite to say, that D. White
had secured him, as is said in this Relation, was for that D. White in
the said first Conference graunted, that there must be one or other
church, continually visible, which had in all ages taught the vnchanged
Fayth of Christ in all points fundamentall; and being vrged
to assigne such a church, D. Whyte expressely graunted that he
could not assigne and shew any church different from the Roman,
which held in all ages all points fundamentall. Whence the Iesuite
gathered his opinion to be, that the Roman church held and taught
in all ages vnchanged Fayth in all fundamentall points, and did
not in any age erre in any point fundamentall. Whereupon the Iesuite
asked, whether errours in points not fundamentall were damnable?
D. White answered, they were not, so long as one did not
hold them against his conscience; which Answere he repeated
againe to M. B. asking the same question. Out of all which, the
Iesuite did collect, that D. Whites opinion was, that the Roman
church held all points fundamentall, and only erred in points not
fundamentall, which he accounted not damnable, so long as one
did not hold them against his conscience: and thereuppon the Iesuit
might well say, that D. White had giuen security to him, who
holdeth no Faith different from the Roman, nor contrary to his
owne conscience.
                  As for D. Whites saying he could discerne but small loue of truth,
and few signes of grace in the Iesuite, I will let it passe as the censure
of an Aduersary, looking vpon the Iesuite with eyes of dislyke,
which is not to be regarded further then to returne vpon him (not a
like censure, but) a charitable wish, that he may haue no lesse loue
of truth, nor fewer signes of grace, then the Iesuite is thought to
haue, by those who know him better then D. White doth.
               ,
said I, hath
secured me, that none of
our errours are damnable,
so long as we hold them
not against our Cōscience,

               
and I hold none against
my Cōscience. The Lady
asked, Whether she might
be saued in the Protestant
Fayth? Vpon my
                  The Chaplain noteth, that
the B. was confident, and had
reason of his confidence. For
sayth he, To belieue the Scripture
and Creed in the sense of the Ancient
Primitiue Church; to receiue
the first fowre Generall Councells
so much magnified by Antiquity: To
belieue all points of doctrine generally receiued, as fundamentall, in the
Church of Christ, is a Fayth, in which to liue and dye, cannot but giue saluation.
And I would fayne see, sayth the chaplain, any one point
maintained by the church of England, that can be proued to depart
from the foundation.
                  To which I answer, first, that if to say thus be a sufficient cause of
confidence, I meruayle why the chaplain maketh such difficulty to
be confident of the saluation of Rom. Catholiques, who belieue all
this in a farre better maner then Protestants do: neyther can they be
proued to depart from the foundation so much as Protestants do,
who denying infallible authority to all the Pastours of the cath.
church assembled in a Generall councell, do in effect deny Infallibility
to the whole catholique church, which is bound to heare &amp;
belieue what is defined, and to practise what is prescribed by her Pastours
in a generall councell, and ordinarily doth so belieue and
practise.
                  Secondly I aske, how Protestants, who admit no certaine and
infallible meanes and rule of Fayth, beside onely Scripture, can be
infallibly sure that they belieue the same entier scripture and creed,
and the foure first Generall councels &amp;c. in the same vncorrupted
sense which the Primitiue Church belieued? What text of scripture
doth tell, that Protestants who now liue, do belieue all this, or that
all this is expressed in those particuler Bibles, or in the writings of
the Fathers or Councells which now are in the Protestants handes,
or that Protestants do rightly vnderstand the sense of all which is
expressed in their bookes according to that which was vnderstood
by the Primitiue Church, and the Fathers which were present at the
foure first Generall Councells? Or that all, and onely those points
which Protestants do account to be fundamentall and necessary to
be expresly knowne by all, were so accounted by the Primitiue
Church? I suppose, neither the B. nor the Chaplain can produce
any text of scripture sufficient to assure one of all this: And therefore
he had need to seeke some other Infallible rule and meanes, by
which he may know these things infallibly, or els he hath no reason
to be so confident, as to aduenture his soule, that one may be saued
liuing and dying in the Protestant Fayth.
                soule

(said the B.) you may.
Vpon my
                  Heere I note, that the Iesuite
was as confident for his
part, as the B. for his; but
with this difference, that the
B. had not sufficient reason
of his Confidence as I haue
declared; But the Iesuite had
so much reason both out of
expresse scriptures and Fathers, and the infallible authority of the
Church, that the B. himself then did not, nor his Chaplaine now
doth not, taxe the Iesuit of any rashnes: but the Chaplain expresly
graunteth that, There is but one sauing Faith, and the B. did (as was
related) graunt that the La. might be saued in the Rom. Fayth;
which is as much as the Iesuite did take vpon his soule. Onely the
chaplain saith, without any proofe, that we haue many dangerous
errours: but he neither tels vs which they be, nor why he thinketh
them dangerous, but leaueth vs to look to our owne soules, and so
we do, and haue no cause to doubt; because we do not hold any
new deuise of our owne, or any other man, or any thing contrary,
but all most conformable to scriptures interpreted by Vnion, consent
of Fathers, and definitions of Councells.
                  Which being so, the B. and his chaplaine had need to looke to
their soules, for if there be but one sauing Fayth, as the Chaplain
graunteth, (and he hath reason, because S. Paul sayth (Ephes. 4.) Vna
fides, One Fayth: and S. Leo, (serm. de Natiuit.) Nisi vna est fides, non est,
vnlesse it be One, it is not Fayth) and this One Fayth was once the
Roman, which also yet is (as the B. graunteth) a sauing Fayth; (or
else he ought not to haue granted, that one may be saued liuing &amp;
dying in it:) I see not how they can haue their soules saued without
they entirely imbrace this Fayth, being the Cath. Fayth, which as
S. Athanasius (in Symb.) affirmeth, vnles one hold entiere (that is euery
point of it,) and inuiolate, (that is, belieuing all in right sense, and
for the true formall reason of diuine reuelation sufficiently applied
to our vnderstāding by the Infallible authority of the Cath. Church
proposing to vs by her Pastours this reuelation) without doubt he
shall perish for euer. In which sort if the B. and his chaplain did
belieue any one Article, they (finding the same formall reason in
all, and applyed sufficiently by the same meanes to all) would easily
belieue all. But so long as they do not belieue all in this sort, but
will, as all Heretiques do, make choyse of what they will, and
what they will not belieue, without relying vpō the Infallible authority
of the Cath. Church, they cannot haue that One Soule-sauing
Fayth, which all good Catholique Christians haue, in any one article
of Fayth. For although they belieue the same truth, which other
good Catholiques do in some Articles, yet not belieuing them for
the same formall reason of diuine reuelation, sufficiently applyed
by Infallible Church-authority, but either for some other formall
reason, or at least not for this reason sufficiently applyed, they cannot
be sayd to haue one and the same Infallible diuine Fayth which
other good catholique christians haue, who do belieue those Articles,
not for any other formall reason beside the diuine reuelation
applyed sufficiently and made knowne to them (not by their owne
fancie, or the fallible authority of humaine deductions,) but by the
infallible authority of the church of God, that is of men infallibly
assisted by the Spirit of God, as all lawfully called, continued, and
confirmed Generall councells are assisted.
                  Whence I gather, that although euery thing defined to be a diuine
truth in Generall councells, is not absolutly necessary to be expresly
knowne and actually belieued (as some other truthes are)
by all sorts; yet no man may (after knowledge that they are thus
defined) doubt deliberatly, and much lesse obstinatly deny the
truth of any thing so defined. For, euery such doubt and denyall is a
breach from that one sauing Fayth, which other good christians
haue, in regard it taketh away infallible credit from the church; and
so the diuine reuelation being not by it sufficiently applyed, it cannot
according to the ordinary course of Gods prouidence breed infallible
belief in vs; for as S. Paul Rom. 10. saith, How shall they belieue
vnles they heare, how shall they heare without a Preacher, how shall they preach
(to wit infallibly) vnles they be sent, to wit, from God, and infallibly
assisted by his spirit? And if a whole Generall councell defining
what is diuine truth be not belieued to be sent, and assisted by gods
spirit, and consequently of Infallible credit, what man in the world
can be said to be of infallible credit? or if such a Councell lawfully
called, continued, and confirmed may erre, in defining any one
diuine truth, how can we be Infallibly certaine of any other truth
defined by it? for if it may erre in one, why not in another and another,
and so in all? or how can we (according to the ordinary course)
be infallibly assured, that it erreth in one, and not in another, when
it equally, by one and the same authority, defineth both to be diuine
truthes? for if we leaue this to be examined by any priuate man, this
examination not being infallible had need to be examined by another,
and this by another, without end, or euer coming to infallible
Certainty, necessarily required in that One Fayth which is necessary
to saluation, and to that peace and Vnity which ought to be in
the Church? It is not therefore (as the Chaplain would perswade)
the fault of councells definitions (but the pride of such as will preferr,
and not submit their priuate Iudgments) that lost, &amp; continueth
the losse of peace and vnity of the Church, and the want of certainty
in that one aforesaid soule-sauing Fayth: the which how far
it doth extend is indeed (as the Chaplain pag. 73. confesseth) no
work for his penne, but is to be learned of that one Holy Catholique,
Apostolique, alwayes Visible, and Infallible Roman Church,
of which the La. once doubting, resteth now fully satisfied, that in it
she may learne all truth necessary to saluation, and that out of it
there is no ordinary meanes sufficient to teach her the right way of
saluation. And therefore the Iesuit might well say, as he did in the
Relation, that the La. was by this &amp; a former conference, satisfied of
the truth of Roman Religion.
                my Soule,
sayd I, There is but one
sauing Fayth, and that is
the Roman.
            
               
               
               
Vpon this, and the precedent Conference,
the Lady rested fully satisfied
in her Iudgment (as she tould a
friend) of the truth of the Roman
Churches Fayth: Yet vpon frailty, &amp;
feare to offend the King▪ she yielded
to goe to
                  The Chaplain
vpon this
last clause saith,
that he is sure
she wilbe better
able to answer
for her coming
to church
thē for her leauing
the church
of England, &amp; following
the superstitions and Errours of the Church of Rome▪ But
he neither proueth, nor can proue that it is lawfull for one (perswaded
especially as the Lady is) to goe to the Protestant Church,
which were to halt on both sides, to serue two Maisters, to dissemble
with God and the world, to professe outwardly a Religion
in conscience knowne to be false; neyther doth he, or can he proue
any superstition or errour to be in Romane Religion; but by presuming
with intolerable pride to make himself, or some of his fellowes
iudge of Controuersies, and by taking authority to censure
all to be superstition and errour, which suteth not with his fancy,
although it be generally held or practised by the vniuersall church,
which in S. Augustins Iudgment, is most insolent madnes.
                  
                Church; for which
she was after very sorie, as some of
her friends can testifie.
            
               
I beseech sweet Iesus, to giue grace to euery one
that offendeth in this sort, to see, repent, and get
pardon of their faults past, and light of true Fayth
in tyme to come; for obtayning whereof they
had need to pray to God for it, and with a great
desire to seeke after it, and with humility to submit
their will and Iudgment to those whom God
hath appointed to teach it; To wit, such Doctours
and Pastours as by a visible continuall succession,
haue without change brought it from christ
and his Apostles, euen vntill these our dayes; and
shall by a like succession carry it along, euen vntill
the end of world. The which succession not being
found in any other church, differing in doctrine from
the Romā Church, I wish the Chaplain &amp; his Lord,
and euery other man carefully to consider; whether
it be not more Christian and lesse brainsick, to thinke
that the Pope, being S. Peters successour, with a Generall
Councell should be Iudg of Controuersies, &amp;
that the Pastorall Iudgment of him (vpon whom as
vpon a firme rock Christ did build his Church,Ephes. 4. 11. and

for whose Fayth Christ prayed,Matt. 16. 1
                     •
                  . enioyning him to
confirme his brethren,Luc. 
                     •
                  2. 3
                     •
                  . and to whose care and gouernent
Christ committed his whole flock of lambes,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  0. 18.
and sheep) should be accounted Infallible, rather
then to make euery man that can read Scripture
Interpreter of Scriptures, Decider of Controuersies,
Controller of Generall Councels, and Iudge of his
Iudges: Or to haue no Iudge of Controuersies of
Fayth, to permit euery man to belieue as he list, as if
there were no Infallible certainty of Fayth to be expected
on earth; The which were to induce insteed
of One sauing Fayth, a Babylonicall Confusion of so many
Fayths as phantasies, or no true christian Fayth at
all. From which euills sweet IESVS deliuer vs.
Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

