
   
      
         
            [3 dialogues in verse, between Gelasimus and Spudaeus, Eda and Agna, and Wisdom and Wyll]
            Fisher, John, student in Oxford.
         
         
            
               1558
            
         
         Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00799
            STC 10917
            ESTC S112327
            99847582
            99847582
            12621
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00799)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12621)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 226:11)
         
         
            
               
                  [3 dialogues in verse, between Gelasimus and Spudaeus, Eda and Agna, and Wisdom and Wyll]
                  Fisher, John, student in Oxford.
               
               [52] p.   
               
                  In Smithfyeld at the signe of the mytre, by Ihon Tisdale for William Pickeryng dwellyng at saynt Magnus corner,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  In the yeare of our Lord God M. D. L. VIII. The .v. daye of Marche [1558]
               
               
                  Title from STC.
                  In verse.
                  At end of G1 verso: Compiled by Ihon Fysher student in Oxforde.
                  Signatures: A-F⁴ G² .
                  Imperfect; lacks title page.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Dialogues, English --  Early works to 1800.
               English poetry --  Early modern, 1500-1700 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               Spudeus.
               
                  EUer pla
                     ••
                  ng Gelasmie:
               Lorde, when wyll you be wise &amp; sad.
               In scholers shoulde be modestie:
               But you playe euer the wanton lad.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶Is this your first salutation?
               You appeare some quarrels to picke,
               In few wordes make relation,
               Wherfore with me you are so quicke?
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶I must in few wordes shew my mynde
               Whersoeuer I chaunce to come,
               Idle and vayne I doo you fynde
               Lo, here I haue tolde you the some:
               And I knowe well that your parentes
               To learne vertew, putte you to schole:
               You defraude them of their ententes
               For daily you playe the wanton foole.
               Also sittyng at schole amonge vs
               What doo you els but playe and toye
               So that of you, all scholers saye thus:
               Gelasimus is a wanton boye.
               
                  Tu leuior foliis, tunc cum siue pondere succi,
               
               To you I may this verse apply
               You are lighter then leaues without sap
               For good exercise you let go by
               
                  And your owne selfe in Idlenesse wrap.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶Of you God sende your frendes moch ioy,
               I thynke you wyll proue a sage Solon
               O God saue you and sweete saynt Loy
               You are lyke to be a wyse man anon,
               Se you not lo, a good body
               When dyd my frendes to you complayne?
               Medle you with your owne study
               I doo not your maners disdayne.
               
                  Multa facere ect, vbi
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      putridum:
               
               About many thynges busy to be
               In euery place (qd he) doth stynke.
               Curiouse you are in checkyng me
               But of your selfe you doo not thynke.
               Now syr, because you doo thus reporte.
               When dyd you me so Idely fynde?
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶Euery houre full of play and sporte
               And as light as fethers in the wynde.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶If I play, I am not Idle in deede
               As you your selfe haue testified:
            
            
               Spudeus·
               ¶Idle as he, as sayth saynt Beede
               Which is neuer well occupied.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               
                  
                  ¶Interpone tuis, interdum gaudia curis:
               
               Somtyme, sayth the wyse man Cato:
               Interlace myrth amonge thy cares.
               Wherfore doo sobre men vnto playes go
               But to ease their myndes in great affayres▪
               
               What sayth the wyse man Tully?
               Gamnyng and pastyme we may vse
               As sleepe and other rest truly
               Which no honest persone wyll accuse.
               
                  Dum fata sinunt, viuite lati▪
                  
               
               Dooth not Seneca this verse write,
               While fortune suffereth, be mery.
               And so wyll I for all your spyte
               Play and syng, hay dery dery.
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     era nimis vita est crastina, viue hodie,
               
               Yesterdayes life is very late,
               Liue to day. Asmoch to say:
               Be mery and play with thy mate,
               Yea forsoth and that euery day.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶As your memory I doo commende
               In that you can Authours reherse
               So I must needes you reprehende
               Because you abuse a good verse,
               I meane the verse of wyse Cato
               
                  
                     •
                  hich you dyd english competently
               But the sentence of Cicero
               
                  You passed ouer negligently.
               We may right well vse play and game
               As we vse sleepe and other rest
               But for what cause may we do the same?
               In that place, it is manyfest.
               Than (saieth hee) whan we haue satisfied
               Other maters both weightie and graue
               Also whan we haue rectified
               Euylles, wont publique weales to depraue
               For hee sayeth in his offices
               That nature hath not brought vs forthe
               To vse playes, games and fantasies
               Whiche are maters nothinge worthe.
               But rather to seueritie
               And to more weighty studies
               Meete for men in authoritie
               And health for soules and bodies.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶What speake you of senators
               In whose handes cōmon weales did depende
               They were great learned orators
               Whose wisdome we can not comprehende
               
                  Quod medicorum est▪
                  
               
               
                  Promittunt medici, tractant fabrilla fabri
               
               That longeth to Phisicians
               Thereof they promise and talke largely
               Carpenters for their furtherans
               
                  Talke and treate of Carpentry:
               We are laddes, Scholers and Studentes
               Let vs talke, as to laddes is semely:
               So shall we please God and our parentes
               And men shall iudge well of vs truly.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶Well, of Idlenesse we beganne to speake
               Wherto you are moche geuen I doo see
               From that I coueyte you to breake
               That more studeouse you might be
               A fewe sentences you haue caught
               Which plainly you doo moche abuse
               You apply them not as the Authours taught
               But your owne Idlenesse to excuse.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶You talke here lyke a great deuine
               And altogither of Idlenesse
               I pray you vouchsafe the same to define
               Because it is so great wickednesse.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶In the Tusculane questions
               Of Idlenesse, thus sayth Tully,
               As touchyng all honest actions
               Idlenesse is an ignary vncomly
               Also an ircksomnesse of the mynde
               When any good matier is begonne.
               And therfore seeketh some other kynde
               
                  Wherabout vainly it may ronne
               As thus you are set to schole now
               To learne both vertew and science
               This is a good thyng begonne in you
               Godly is parentes wyll and pretence
               But a none ircksomnesse of harte
               And lothsomnesse of well dooyng
               Cause you to take another parte
               And to geue your selfe to plaiyng.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶A certayne wyse man geueth warnyng
               Not ouer moche in study to stande
               For to some body Arte and learnyng
               Are as a sworde in a mad mans hande
               
                  Doctrina scelesti, ect gladio in sani similis.
               
            
            
               Spudeus.
               Truthe, a wicked persone without dout
               To whom no honest thyng is good
               Mischeuously vttereth learnyng out
               As one dooth a weapon that is wood:
               But I woulde haue you to note two thynges
               First: The goodly sequels of studentes
               Some haue ben counsellours to Kynges
               Yea, though thei haue come of poore parentes
               What were the cheife counsels of Rome
               I meane when vertew flourished,
               Learned and graue in iudgement and dome.
               
                  Who their Comunaltie most nourished.
               A thousande I coulde reherse by name
               Of whom I reade in diuers stories
               Which through learnyng haue come to fame▪
               
               And attayned vnto high glories.
               
                  Qui probus atque idem doctus diademate talem
               
               
                  Quis dignum neget? hic aliis precellit vt aurum
               
               
                  Est oricalcho nobilius vitroque pyropus.
               
               He that is good and learned withall
               Who wyll denie suchone worthy
               To enioy an honour royall
               Which we call a diademe truly
               For such one dooth other excell
               As farre as golde dooth the copper passe
               And as precious stone or Birrall
               Excelleth counterfaites or glasse
               Yet must learned men come of poore lignage
               Example of Marke Tully by name
               Uertue is a most sure heritage
               For that enhaunceth to honour and fame.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶Truly your wordes make me to smile
               You speake not of the endes of the same
               Either they were driuen to exile
               Or els suffred death with shame.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶Impute that to ingratitude
               
                  Marke this: Suche is euer the rewarde
               Of the ignoraunt multitude
               Whiche dyd neuer vertue regarde
               Suffred with shame say you? forsoth no:
               Happy are they which for vertues sake
               Suffre death, or into exile go
               So that paciently they doo it take
               Also I wyll tell you as I thynke
               He that is endued with doctrine
               Shall neuer want mony, meate nor drinke
               So that to vertue he doo incline
               But the fallible chaunces of fate
               He shalbe hable to withstande
               And if he be deposed from his state
               Learnyng preserueth him in any lande.
               
                  Ipse tamen vidi nunquam, &amp; vix credere possunt
               
               
                  Vel perijsse fame, vel mendicasse disertum,
               
               I dyd yet neuer see, the poete dooth say,
               And scarsely beleue it I can
               That for honger any shall decay
               That is in deede a learned man.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               Frende Spudeus I wyll be playne
               To obtayne glory, I bende not my hope
               They that coueyte honour to attayne
               At noone dayes for the way doo grope.
               
                  Ergo honor &amp; fama▪ &amp; myrtalis gloria laus▪
                  
               
               
                  
                  Somnia sunt prorsus nil conducentia,
               
               Honor, fame worldly, glory and prayse
               Are but dreames, for nothyng profitable
               Therfore I am bent nothyng that wayes
               For I looke not to be honourable.
            
            
               Spudeus,
               ¶Lo this is your commune fascion
               To truncate and destroy the verse
               Styll for your owne excusacion
               And wyll not the whole sentence reherse.
               
                  Somnia sunt prorsus nil conducentia, quando
               
               
                  Sorte magis quam virtute acquiruntur,
               
               They are dreames nothyng profitable
               But whan? whan by chaūce thei are acquired
               Rather than by vertue honourable.
               who so dooth not desyre honour
               The same dooth no vertue regarde
               For honour in good men euer more
               For vertue is a iust rewarde.
            
            
               Gelasimus,
               ¶Ha ha ha, to laugh you compell me
               In the faute wherin you dyd me charge
               Most euedently in you I see
               As I shall declare more at large.
               
                  Turpe est doctori cum culpa redarguit ipsum▪
                  
               
               It is a foule thyng to a teacher
               When the same faute in him is fownde
               
                  Whiche he rebuketh in other
               Himselfe first to teache he is bownde
               I dyd truncate a verse you say
               Your later verse now doo you scande
               And whether I say true, proue you may,
               Or whether as a vexse it may stande.
            
            
               Spudeus,
               
                  ¶Serte magis quam virtute acquiruntur, at esto?
               
            
            
               Gelasimus,
               ¶At esto? Haue you founde, at esto?
               In your first rehersall that dyd lacke
               You talke so moche de honesto
               
               That you cast rectum at your backe.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶That (at esto) beginneth a new sentence,
               Which had ben prolixe to reherse.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶I perceyue your cautelouse pretence
               That sentence woulde your wordes requite
               Because you woulde appeare fautlesse
               Takyng vpon you other to blame
               What foloweth I wyll expresse
               Earnestly without mocke or game:
               
                  At esto,
               
               
                  Quod tantum dignis tribuantur, dic mihi nunquid
               
               
                  Corporibus prosint? certe nil. Animis ne?
               
               
                  Tantundem hos inflant potius tumidos
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      leues
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Nec non solicitos reddunt: se sub dere multis,
               
               
                  Et seruire solet multis, Ambire praecari,
               
               
                  Munera largiri quisquis festatur honores.
               
               My formour wordes I must agayne reherse:
               For honour (I say) I doo not moche care
               Hereto tendeth my formour verse
               Now these in english I wyll declare.
               Be it so, that honour and fame
               Are geuen only to the worthy
               What profite haue men by the same?
               They profite nothyng their body
               What commoditie are they to the myndes
               Euen asmoch: they fyll them full of pride
               And make them as light as the wyndes
               And fill them with care on euery syde
               Many must one serue and many flatter
               Pray, speake fayre, and mony pay
               Stoutly he must beare out the matter
               That wyll haue honour at this day.
               Lo, who so hunteth for honour
               This disquietnesse he shall fynde
               To the body a longe dolour
               And a continuall sore to the mynde.
               
                  O bona paupertas, o non dum cognita diuum
               
               
                  Munera, virtutum custos &amp; amica pudori.
               
               ¶O Good pouertie, o Gods good gifte,
               Unknowne is thy cōmoditie
               
                  Keper of vertue throughe thy shyft
               And a very frende to honestie.
               A meane state is surest of all
               Daungerouse it is highe to clyme
               The mightye Okes haue greatest fall
               Whan the lowe shrubbes grow out their time
            
            
               Spudeus.
               Your wordes be good, but you digresse
               And declyne muche fro my purpose
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               Go to hardely: your minde expresse
               Spare not your learnyng to disclose
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶I counsailed you lightnes to leaue
               And to giue your selfe to study
               To vertue I wolde haue you to cleaue
               Commodiouse to soule and body.
               By examples auncient and olde
               Stearyng vp your hope as I thought
               But with sentences stoute and bolde
               You haue sett my counsell at nought.
               As I coulde haue tolde you by name
               Of suche as study in youth haue loued
               Whiche haue attayned honour and fame
               And worthy men haue bene proued.
               Likewyse of innumerable
               I can tell you also by name
               
                  Whiche of byrth haue bene honourable
               And yet their endes haue bene shame.
               Wherfore? this is the cause for a truth
               Their tyme full Idely they dyd spende
               And would not study in their youthe
               Therfore shame &amp; dishonour was their ende.
               Let all youth of Idlenes beware
               For it is the steppedame of vertue
               If you be caught ones in her snare
               All myschefes besyde wyll soone ensue.
               
                  Otia enim fomes Vitiorum est otia mentem
               
               
                  Ad mala multa trahunt, oti comes ipsa libido est.
               
               It is the prouoking of wickednes
               To many myschefes it draweth the mynde
               Unclennes accompanyeth Idelnes
               No greater enemy to mankinde.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               You may perceiue well by my wordes
               That I haue not bene ydle alway
               Though somtime I set pytfalles for byrdes
               I am not ydle, as perceiue you may.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               Your goodly wyt I do commende
               And to prayse god you haue great cause
               But I haue sene that doth mee offende
               As I sayed in my former clause.
               
                  Emollit otium Vires sicut rubigo ferrum.
               
               
                  ¶Idlenesse weakeneth the strength
               Like as rust dooth the yrone freate
               Quicke wyttes it dulled at lengthe
               And bredeth infirmities great
               Haue you not hearde men of grauitie
               Wishe that they had learned in youthe
               And haue bewayled their vanitie
               Cursyng themselfes with their owne mouth
               
                  Vidi iam iuuenem praemeret, cum ferior aetas
               
               
                  Moerentem tardos praeterijsse dies.
               
               ¶I haue sene (sayth Quid) a yonge man
               When with more age pressed he was
               Mournyng in himselfe now and than
               That idely he dyd let the dayes passe.
               Idlenesse bryngeth in voluptuousnesse
               Whom good sayntes call the deuils bayte
               In voluptuousnes is all wickednesse
               Wherin youth to catche, the deuyll doth wayt
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶An olde prouerbe: Yonge saint olde deuyll
               Whiche to you I may well apply.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶Thus rather he that in youth is a dreuyll
               Is most like a deuyll to dye
               He that in youthe no vertue wyll vse
               As the commune prouerbe dooth say
               In age all goodnesse wyll him refuse:
               
                  Whiche to hell is the pathe waye
               As no fruite is founde in that tree
               Wheron no flowre dyd before appeare
               Som age he can come to no degree
               Whiche in youthe wyll vse no vertue cleare.
               
                  Iuuenis existens multa bona disce:
               
               While thou arte yonge, sayth Menander,
               Many good thynges study and learne.
               About foly let not your mynde wander
               Geue eare to wyse men which doo you warne
               Well may you be named Gelasimus
               Whiche scornfull dooth signify
               For whatsoeuer good men discusse
               You tourne it to a scorne vtterly.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶And Spudeus may well be your name
               Whiche signifieth studious
               You study to gette honour and fame
               So that you wyll be come furious.
            
            
               Spudeus,
               ¶Not so, I trust there is a meane,
               I haue learned to vse modestie
               Not so wyll I to study leane
               That I shall forgette honestie.
               I study not vertue to acquire
               Fame and honour therby to attayne
               Uertue for her owne sake I desyre
               
                  In whom alone honour dooth remayne.
               
                  Propter se virtus petitur non propter honorem.
               
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶I pray you let all this reasonyng passe
               And tell me this: may I not somtyme play?
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶You remembre what our talke was?
               As sleepe and other rest Tully dooth say.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶I am glad of that by this light
               I wish that my maister so wolde say.
               Men vse to rest and sleepe euery night
               Than so might I play euery day.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶Whether you may or no, you doo
               Yea truly, and that without measure
               And suche wantonnesse you adde therto
               That none other in your play haue pleasure.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶In good fayth I play not other to please
               I vse to play for myne owne solace.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶But in your play you doo other disease
               And in so dooyng you doo trespace:
               
                  Est modus in rebus sunt certi den
                        •
                     
                     
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      f
                        •
                     n
                        •
                     s
               
               
                  Quos vltra citra
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      nequit consistere rectum.
               
               ¶There is a comly meane in all thynges
               
                  Therbe also certayne limites pyght
               Beyonde the which if you passe the strynges,
               Nothyng that you doo, can be doone right
               In your play, and in all your affayres
               Learne you honest maners to vse
               Let not idlenesse catche you in her snares
               And euyll company doo you refuse
               
                  Corrumpunt etiam Sanctos commercia praua,
               
               Euyll company dooth corrupte alway
               Euen those that be well disposed
               Conceale no falshed night nor day
               But of you let it be disclosed
               Serue God daily before any thyng
               Feare him, beware his lawes to offende
               Honour, loue, and truly serue the kyng
               And where fautes be, learne to amende:
               Your Father, Mother and Maister
               Loue, feare, serue, and gentely obay:
               Of their goodes be ye no waster
               With truthe helpe to gette that you may.
               Of ton
                     ••
                   and hande be you euer true,
               
                  
                     •
                   oathes to sweare,
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   doo you rewe:
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   beare.
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
               
                  And you shall neuer go out of the way.
            
            
               Gelasimus,
               ¶I haue not so litle wyt, good frynde,
               But that I perceyue your intent
               I thanke you both with hearte and mynde
               Your counsell is honest and prudent
               This one thyng of you I woulde desyre
               Daily that we may togither talke
               At suche a tyme as you shall requyre
               When you are best disposed to walke.
            
            
               Spudeus.
               ¶I shalbe content with all my harte:
               Fare ye well, God haue you in his kepyng.
            
            
               Gelasimus.
               ¶Seyng that you wyll hence departe
               God preserue you wakyng and flepyng.
            
            Finis.
         
         
            ¶Here after 
                  〈…〉
                the Dialogue 
                  〈…〉
                liuyng of 
                  〈…〉
                which 
                  〈…〉
               
            
            
               
               Eda.
               GOd for me this day (I trust) hath wrought
               For yonder cōmeth she, whō I haue sought
               I am glad that I haue mette with you Agna.
            
            
               Agna.
               And I as glad to see you mery Eda
               It ts a straunge thinge to see you here alone.
            
            
               Eda.
               My syster is but euen now fro me gone
               And in dede we should haue gone togyther
               But that I did see you comming hyther
               To speake with you is my tarying here
               I thought to salute you since you were so nere.
            
            
               Agna.
               I thanke you gentle Eda for your good will
               Tell me dwell you with your Father still.
            
            
               Eda.
               Yea I thanke god, and stil I purpose to doo
               For I haue none so good a frende to go too
               I see wherto this wretched worlde is bent
               Therfore I minde not other houses to frequent
               In our last talke you did to me disclose
               A goodly sentence of holy saint Ambrose
               Whiche while I lyue I shall beare in minde
               For great vertue forsothe therin I fynde.
            
            
               Agna.
               Good lord do you those wordes so long remembre
            
            
               
               Eda.
               If I should forget them, my wyt were slender.
            
            
               Agna.
               As I dyd recyte them, can you say them again?
            
            
               Eda.
               To here me say them, wyl you take the payne
            
            
               Agna.
               Yea truly that I wyll, yeuen with all my harte
               And helpe you, yf you mysse in any parte.
            
            
               Eda.
               That virgin whiche for Christ doth enquire
               To be amonge rude people, ought not to desyre.
               Seldom sene without cause in the market place
               Neuer alone in the streetes to shewe her face.
               It is not virgin like to be high in voyce
               Neither in vyle wordes or songes to reioyce
               Mayden like without nycenes in her pace
               No token of wantonnes in her eies or face.
               Lo Sister Agna these be the wordes I suppose
               Whiche you taught me out of Saint Ambrose.
            
            
               Agna.
               Saint Ambrose wrote this of the virgin Mary
               From whose sentence you do not muche vary
               Let her humilitie and fourme of vertue
               Be examples for you all your life to ensue.
               Who so doth the rewarde of Mary requyre
               Must folowe Maries vertue, with humble desire
               
                  Howe meke, how pure how holy she was in dede
               You know, so yt more to declare we shal not nede.
               To know good thinges is right commendable
               But to folowe them is most profitable.
               I prayse greatly your goodly memory
               Yet I must warne you to beware of vaynglory
               That is a vice of so craftie a vilany
               That it seketh euen vertue to accompany.
               Therfore a certaine Doctor doth monishe
               All persons whiche in vertue do floryshe
               Of vainglory aboue all thinges to beware
               For he calleth it a crafty gyuue or snare
               Wherby Satan wayteth to catche the vertuose
               And to frustrate them of their godly purpose.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶I thanke you truly, for your godly councell
               Your wordes I finde as true as the Gospell
               God to wytnesse, I haue a purpose sure
               To kepe both body and minde cleane and pure
               So that neither consent worde nor countenance
               Shall appere vayne, by goddes help &amp; gouernance
               Yet I haue had a delight to be commended
               And therin I wotte well, I haue offended
               For though I do thinges neuer so commendable
               Yet am I but a seruaunt vnprofytable.
               I do but that whiche is commended to mee
               Neither all that, as in the Gospell I do see.
            
            
               
               Agna.
               ¶Because you remēbre so well Christes doctrine
               I wyl teach you a lesson of holy saynt Austine:
               Uainglory of this worlde is great vanitie
               And not els but a fallible suauitie
               An vnfruitfull labour, a perpetuall feare
               A sublimitie perelesse for any to beare
               A beginnyng without good prouidence
               And an ende with vnprofitable penitence.
               Lo good Eda, this is a vertuouse lesson
               Ponder it with earnest discrecion
               And with your chaste mynde and puritie
               Pray to God to geue you humilitie
               For somoche the more to God you are preciouse
               How moch in your own eyes, you ar conteintuos
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶I trust in God also this lesson to beare away,
               And to folow it, I wyll do that I may:
               But gentle Agna, doo you not yet departe
               For to you I wolde shew the secretes of my hart
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶Your request standeth with so good reason
               That I must nedes tary with you a season.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶Truly one thyng maketh me moch to lament
               And that is, somtime for myne owne document
               I wold keepe company with Maides very fayne
               
                  And I fynde the most of them raumpysh &amp; vaine
               And like as many of them are past all shame
               So feare they not God, neither honour his name▪
               
               If I chaunce with any of them to walke,
               Of beauty, or of gay raiment is their talke
               Elles of mar
                     •
                  age, or of yonge bachelers
               To speake shortly: they are vayne claterers.
               Speake to them of God, and of obedience
               They fare as persons without intelligence
               So that in their company kepyng in deede
               Of .ii. perilles, it is expedient to take heede:
               One is, (if I be not like to them) obloquie,
               The other is (if I be lyke the company)
               Lewde condition, by talke vncomly:
               Whiche thynges are a great greefe to me truly.
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶Children and seruauntes are representations
               Of their parentes and maisters abhominations
               Like as many parents ar without the fere of god
               So from their maners the children be seldome od
               My coūsell is suche Maydes company to forsake,
               What they talke of you, no mater it dooth make
               So that a pure conscience beareth you recorde
               That faithfully you serue Iesus christ our lorde
               Neuer be you without some vertuous booke
               Wheron at voyde times you mai diligently looke
               
                  ¶In good bookes truly is all my solace
               For in them I learne thynges wysely to compace
               First how I shal feare god our lorde omnipotent
               To my Prince and parentes to be obedient
               To loue my familiers, to honour my betters
               To pitye the needye, and to forgeue my detters.
            
            
               Agna.
               As I wyll you to vse bokes well, if you haue any
               So I counsell you not to vse very many
               For so many heades, so many wyttes they say
               Amonge the whiche all take not the right way.
               For some haue written asmoche for affection
               As for any good zeale or instruction
               And as virginitie is nothyng without humilitie
               So neither of thē is ought worth without veritie
               Uertuous in good persons are so lynked togither
               That one can not auayle without the other:
               What is virginitie worth, ioyned with errour
               Nothyng but payne takyng for infernal terrour.
               That mynde can neuer be scincere and pure
               Which in the fayth of Christ standeth not sure.
               In Christes Testament be stable eruditions
               Therafter frame your lyfe and conditions.
               Saynt Ambrose wrote the lyfe of saynt Cecily
               Wherin are notable examples verely.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶Sauyng your tale, I haue read the same story
               
                  Wher I find many thīgs sounding to gods glory
               And cheefly this I noted in saynt Cecily
               That the Gospell she bare in her hert secretly
               And as a Bee busely goeth from flame to flame,
               So she in all thynges serued God day and houre▪
               
               And whē other dyd syng &amp; with instrumēts play
               Unto our Lorde in her mynde she dyd thus pray
               O Lorde let my hart be pure and immaculate
               That I be not confounded with the reprobate
               She was no vayne babler of the holy Gospell
               But framed her lyfe accordyng to Christes coūsel
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶O well noted good syster Eda in deede,
               God graūt you in knowledge forward to procede
               As you say, bablers there are to many
               The floures they haue, but thei tast not the hony
               Saynt Cecily kepte the Gospell in her brest
               But in the mouthe nowe only it dooth rest.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶Better it had ben neuer it to haue knowne
               Then so vily in the stretes to haue it throwne.
               Sayntes in tyme past studyed the Gospell
               To thentent that in good lyfe they myght excell,
               As it is to see very well in theyr lyues,
               Yea both of men &amp; women, maydes and wyues▪
               
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶Haue you red the lyfe of saynt Agnes?
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
            
            
               
               Eda.
               ¶I readde it ones in Englysh doutlesse
               If it be truly translated as it was
               All other Uirgins of that age she dyd passe
               Thirtene yeres of age, lytle past infancye
               Marterdome she suffred with great constancye.
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶Saynt Ambrose, as it is thought by the stile
               Dyd her lyfe in latine eligantly compile
               At .xiii. yeares of age (saith he) death she lost
               And founde eternall lyfe, though her lyfe it cost,
               Full well loued she the floure of Uirginitie
               That woulde die rather then spotte her integrite
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶What I am hable to doo, I doo not fynde
               But without doute I am of the same mynde
               Uirginitie? oh can there be any greater pleasure,
               Into this world we brought none other treasure
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶It is euen so: whan into this world we came,
               Moch misery we brought as the childrē of Adam
               Yet with vs we brought this commoditie
               In thought, worde and deede, pure virginitie.
               Nothyng in mankynde God loueth more
               Nothyng so moche aduaunceth his honour
               Therfore scripture compareth virginitie to Bisse
               The finest lynnen cloth that euer was or is,
               
                  Wryters therof whiche do the nature knowe
               Say that it is a cloath as white as snowe
               As Bysse doth all one lynen passe in puritie
               So aboue all vertues god loueth virginitie
               It ouer passeth mans nature Doctors do say
               And make men like vnto Aungels alway
               Greater (saye they) is virgyns victory
               Than the triumphe of Aungels in glory.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶Where as you speake of that kinde of vesture
               Bysse is a precious cloth, that is most sure.
               But yere it come vnto the perfection
               It requireth great labour and correction
               For before to the whytenes they can it bring
               They vse to beate it oft, and oft it to wryng▪
               
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶You say truthe, yeuen so virginitie
               Must eftsones be beate with humilitie
               It must be wronge with abstinence and prayer
               Before it be perfight, pure, cleane and fayer
               It must be rubbed with the soape of penaunce
               And bleached in the hote sunne of sufferaunce
               Here to must we adde perseuerance to the ende
               Whiche is our lyfe in defence therof to spende
               Thus shall we make a fayer garment of Bysse
               And therwith entre, before the kynge of blysse.
            
            
               Eda▪
               
               
                  Lord why haue not the christen maids this talke
               When they meete, or togither doo walke
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶I told you before that the parentes negligence
               Causeth most this, and like inconuenience
               The filthy perswations of suche as be olde
               Kyndle moche euyll and make maides euer bold.
               Agayne, the bringyng vp of them in idlenes
               Is thoccasion of moche vnthriftenes
               They haue no respecte also vnto the company
               Which to virginitie is a great vilany
               Whosoeuer toucheth pitche shalbe defiled
               So by euyll company many one is begiled.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶Where as you talke of suche as be aged
               I knowe that some haue to filthely raged
               Hauyng no respecte theyr vile mouthes to open
               Shewyng therwith many an vnchast token
               Yea forsothe, &amp; that before yonge girles &amp; boyes,
               Wherby they learne to practise wicked toyes.
               Auncient women &amp; wyues assemblyng togither.
               Many times do not their talke honestly consider,
               Neither what thei speke, where, nor before whom
               No truly lytle wisdome without, &amp; lesse at home.
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶O lytle regarde they the terrible sentences
               Of Christ our Lord for suche great offences.
               Better were it for suche a corrupte persone
               
                  Aboute his necke to haue hanged a mylstone
               And so in the myddest of the sea drowned to be
               Than to offend any lytle one that beleueth in me
               Also for euery ydle worde spoken in vayne
               They shall render a strayte compte agayne
               For they doo not only themselues condempne
               But they cause other Gods lawe to contempne.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶Uerely syster Agna, my mynde doth me geue
               That the worde of God suche men do not beleue,
               I wolde they heard what God speaketh by Esay
               A boye of an hundreth yere olde shall dye
               Namely whē he laketh maners to age corespōdēt
               That is grauitie, discretion, and a mynde sapient
               Understande me not here in any wyse
               That I go about aged persons to dispyse.
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶No I dare saye, for you are taught otherwyse
               Before the honorable and aged, dooe thou aryse
               The order of nature where as is intelligence
               Teacheth vs age in all men to reuerence
               But where as euyll maners in aged men be
               As from the face of a serpent we ought to flie
               Thre thynges saith Syrach my soule dooth hate
               Wherwith I am greued and at great debate:
               A poore man proude, a ryche man a lyer
               An olde man a foole, and full of fleshly desyer.
            
            
               
               Eda.
               ¶I flee the company bothe of olde and yonge
               Whyche be not honest in gesture dede and tonge
               With the holy, thou shalt learne to be holy
               Amonge fooles we shall learne but foly
               Wherfore yf I see any bent to inhumanytie.
               I auoyde his foly and lewde vanitie.
               Wyth non do I vse to common or dispute
               But wyth such, by whom I may haue sum fruit.
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶For so doyng God be thanked for his grace
               A token that you intende vertue to enbrace.
               I redde in a booke of virginitie lately
               Where one compareth it vnto a Lyly.
               Whiche if it be towched, as he doth expresse
               A none it wyl lose all the fayre whytenes.
               So yf virginitie be touched a lytle
               Eyther with vncleane thoughtes or wordes ydle
               It wyll lose the purytie therof anone
               Yea and the sauour pleasing god wyl be gone.
               Wherfore hedge we in our garden with faith sure
               That our Lily from touching may be kept pure.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶I haue redde in a sermon of good authorytie
               That abstynence is a frende to virgynitie
               Contrarywyse, a full bely is an enemye
               Unto all maydes that wyl lyue honestly
               
                  I haue hearde my father talke of that mater
               He sayd that maides wold fast with bred &amp; water
               And dyd labour asmoch, &amp; toke paynes as great
               As any day that they eate their meales and meat
               But as fastyng is tourned into surfaityng
               So is worke tourned into idle leuteryng.
               This I see in all states now for a surety
               The most parte are geuen to fleshly libertye
               As sum withold ye truth of god in vnrightousnes
               So of his word thei make a cloke of maliciousnes
               Yea yong &amp; olde, maydes, widowes men &amp; wiues
               As it doth appeare to playnly by their lyues.
               To the good towne they must go to drinke wyne
               Though they come agayne as dronke as swyne.
            
            
               Agna.
               Amōg the Romayns no greater offēce ther was
               Then for womē at Tauernes their tymes to pas
               A lawe ther was, that they might no wine drinke
               Whiche was no euyl truly I do thynke.
               But whan yonge gyrles wyll be wyne bybbars
               It foloweth, that they intende to be euyl lyuers
               Wine sayeth Hierom, youth and lustines
               Is a doble kyndeling vnto voluptuousnes.
               Madnes it is to adde oyle vnto a fyre
               But more madnes to giue youth their desyre.
               There is better pathe to lyfe euerlasting
               Than (is being in the fayth) prayer and fasting.
            
            
               
               Eda.
               ¶May you tary no longer here trowe you?
            
            
               Agna.
               The time draweth nere that I must depart now.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶Let vs talke .iii. or .iiii. sentences mo
               And than in goddes name you shall go.
               Me thinke that there is a great falte in parentes
               Concernyng their doughters attyre &amp; garmentes
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶As all things are cleane to them that be cleane
               So in all thynges there is an honest meane
               I doo not moche passe of the outwarde vesture
               So the mynde be morned with christen or nature
               Asmoche mekenes may be vnder a veluet gowne
               As in one that wereth the worst coat in the toune
               &amp; asmoch pride in him that wereth a patched coat
               As in him that weareth golde about his throate,
               Superfluous disguisyng is very euyll
               But paintyng of the hearre cometh of the deuyll.
               o womā saith Ambrose, yu blottestout gods pictur
               When thou with paintyng alterest nature.
               I can not prayse these new founde disguisynges
               Through pride they were of Satans dyuysinges
               A holy man sayeth, that externall superfluitie
               Is a sygne of an internall vanytie
               Whersoeuer sayeth hee, nyce garmentes ye finde
               
                  You may be sure ther to haue the nicenes of mind
               Wolde to god in garmentes there were more modestie
               I alow clenlines in apparel wt honestie.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶As of vertuouse maters here we do talke
               So in our lyuyng, God gyue vs grace to walke.
               Howe say you by singing and dauncing
               To synne I iudge them a great aduauncing
               My father wil haue me to play at the Lute
               Also at the Uirginalles wherin is small fruite.
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶As in godly maters you are very wyse
               So in thinges indifferent be not to nyce.
               The best giftes of God may bee abused
               The giftes therfore maye not be accused,
               But they whiche abuse goddes good giftes
               As all they do whiche are carnall vnthriftes
               To can singe truly is right commendable
               Yf the cyrcumstances be alowable.
               As the songe to be good, sunge with good intent
               The persone the time the place honest and decent.
               In like maner at instrumentes to playe
               A goodly gift of God it is truly I saye.
               But abused, they may be through vaine pride
               
                  And whan better thinges for them are laide aside
               In holy scripture we finde that yonge damsels
               Sang Psalmes, songes, &amp; played at Tymbrels
               Suche Instrumentes as they vsed than
               Whiche haue not ben rebuked of any wise man.
               But those thinges were euer done in time
               To the honour of god, wherin was no crime.
               I tell you in this thing my poore aduisement
               But leane you to a wyse bodies Iudgement.
               Nowe as for dauncing, I wot not what to say
               Holy men haue spoken against it til this day.
               And though kyng Dauid daūced before the Arke
               I wot not what to say for I am no clarke.
               But this is the sentence of some that be wyse
               Dauncing can be scacely vsed without vice
               For by their owne iudgement you can not daunce finely
               Without a great pride and secrete enuy.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶God saue me then from learnyng that arte
               Herodias doughter played a wicked parte
               For through her daūsyng, most holy saynt Ihon
               By Herodes commaundment was beheded anon
               Pride and enuy are synnes which I detest,
               To avoyde thoccasion of them I thynke it best
               When I see that any vertue therby dooth chaūce
               Then diligently wyll I learne to daunce,
               God graunt me grace to learne him to please
               
                  To my minde that shalbe the greatest ease.
            
            
               Agna.
               ¶I must byd you fare well tyl to morowe
               Thā to talke wt you more, a time I wil I borow
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶I thanke you hartely for your great payne
               I shal thinke longe tyl I speake with you again▪
               
               I desyre you, this night in your meditation
               Deuise in your minde against our next cōmunication
               How I may serue god as he doth require
               Let this be our next talke I do you desyre.
            
            
               Agna
               ¶With a good wyl you shal knowe my harte
               God haue you in his keping I must departe.
            
            
               Eda.
               ¶God be with vs in farewel and greeting
               And send vs againe a mery meeting. Amen.
            
            Finis.
         
         
            
               ❧Here after foloweth A Dialogue concernyng wysdom and Wyll. Who reason togither thus.
            
               TO spende the time honestly a season
            I thinke this to be a talke conuenient
            Of Wyll and Wisdom a while to reason
            And who maye iustly be called sapient
            I thinke it meete therfore Wysdom to defyne
            Tully calleth it a knowledge or science
            Of maters aswell heauenly and diuyne
            As of humane thinges, in thordre of prudence.
            So that perfightely to knowe goddes wyll
            That is, what of man, god doth requyre
            And the same in worde and dede to fulfyll
            Is the highest wisdom wherto man can aspyre.
            Also what percayneth to cumly ordre
            Amonge men at all times to be vsed
            And to kepe the same in euery bordre
            Is wysdom, of none to be refused.
            According hereto a Christian Poete
            Certaine pleasant versis in Latin doth wryte
            Whiche if a whyle you wyl be quyete
            As well as I can, I wyll recyte.
            
               Sed fortasse aliquis quaerit sapientia quid sit:
            
            
               Nil aliud certe est nisi prima scientia, per quam
            
            
               Mens pura &amp; nulla mortali pondere praessa
            
            
               Libera terrenis affectibus atria coeli
            
            
               Scandit, &amp; aethera cum dijs versatur in aulae,
            
            Sum perchaunce wyll aske, what is sapience
            Nothing elles but a science principall
            
               Wherby (a minde spotted with no vncongruence
            Neither pressed with any synne capitall
            But free from affections terrestriall)
            Unto the heauenly palaces doth ascende
            And is conuersaunt with spirites celestiall
            In heauen I meane, wher god is without ende.
            Many noble sentences be in that place
            Right worthy to be talked of in dede
            But because they requyre more time and space
            I leaue them and wyl to other thinges procede
            As in fewe persons is this Sapience
            So in all men lyuing is there a wyll
            Whiche through stoborne disobedience
            Many one, both soule and body doth spyll.
            
               Wylle.
               ¶Somwhat of Wyll here by your pacience
               I must saye accordyng to learnyng
               And as you haue praysed sapience
               So of Wyll, let me say my meanyng.
            
            
               Wisdome.
               ¶Wyll playeth the wanton boy now and than.
               Whan Wyll without wyt, reuelleth alone
               He vndoeth many a wylfull man
               Who wolde repent whan the time is gone
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶Wyll is an appetite gyuen to goodnes
               According to prudent Aristotles mynde
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
                  In the fyrst boke of Rethorickes he doth expresse
               The same sentence, or moche of that kynde
               And the same Poete which you dyd reherse
               (A Poete? no forsoth. rather a Deuine)
               Ryght nobly speaketh of Wylle in a verse
               As though Wylle, doth not to euyll encline.
               
                  Sunt
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      voluntatis bona plura &amp; quatuor horum
               
               
                  Praecipua existunt, prudencia▪ iustitia atque
               
               
                  Grandia quae aggreditur fortis discrimina virtus,
               
               
                  Net non quae frenis nos temperat at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      modestos,
               
               
                  Efficit. &amp;c.
               
               There be many good thynges longyng to Wylle
               And cheefly .iiii. Prudence, and Iustice,
               Strength, that noble vertue gret thīges to fulfyl
               Temperance, who restrayneth sensuall vice.
               These .iiii. be called vertues Cardinall:
               For of them all other vertues depende
               Of the which vertues, Wylle is thoriginall
               Wherfore, Wylle I may iustly commende.
            
            
               Wisdome.
               ¶I say styll, that Witte is a crafty boye,
               Fayne he wolde his wilfull foly excuse,
               He hathe played euen nowe a subtle toye.
               For a learned sentence he dyd abuse
               Aristotle in the place of you aledged
               Whereas you say, he dooth Wylle define,
               Is of you triuicated and abredged
               Contrary to the Philosophers doctrine,
               
                  Wyll is an appetite of goodnes sayeth he
               Coniuncte or rather subiecte to reason
               I saye whan Wyll to reason doth agree
               Than all thinges be done well, and in season
               But I speake onely of that sturdy Wyll
               Whiche to obay reason doth proudly disdayne
               Than both it selfe, it doth destroy and spyll
               And putteth many another to payne.
               In that Wyll, whyche to reason doth consent
               Is all kynde of good vertues conteyned
               Than it doth nothing wherof it should repent
               For all vyces therby are restreyned.
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶Me thynke you make lytle difference
               Betwyxt Wyll and sensualytie
               Wyll is equall with sapience
               Yea and hygher in authorytie.
               For what could sapience or reason do
               Or any other power of the minde
               Except Wyll, wolde consent therto
               Who hath power both to loase and to bynde.
               Only in Wyll is free lybertie
               Whan Wysdom and reason haue deuysed
               Wyll hath this power for a suertie
               To let all that they haue practysed.
               Example. Reason and Wisdom do teache
               
                  Performe this they can not whiche they preache
               Except Wyll therto shall lybertie gyue.
            
            
               Wisdome.
               The pride of this stoborne Wyll, breaketh out
               And by lytle and lytle dooth the selfe declare
               Wyll is proude, Wyll is sturdy and stout
               And yet miserable, beyng lefte bare
               Euery mā through Wyl alone is made a wretche
               But the more wretched as Austen dooth publish
               When the same Wyll dooth it selfe stretche,
               So farre that he may his desyre accomplish
               And also it foloweth, that through euyll Wyll
               Not euery man a wretche is made
               But also the more wretched when he may fulfyll
               That euyll wherto euyll wyll doth perswade,
               Thus he meaneth, the more power Wyll hathe
               To doo euyll, the more wretched it is,
               The more power Wyll hathe reason to scathe,
               The more bonde, and the more dooth a mis.
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶You haue talked of euyll wyll a long season
               I praye you what doo you call the same euyll wil
            
            
               Wysdome.
               ¶That Wyll which is not subiecte to reason
               But seketh his sensuall rage to fulfyll
               
                  Now to make answere to your comparison.
               Where you preferre Wyll before reason,
               In dede, Wyll, and his wylfull garison
               Compare with God from whō all goodnes come
               But in this poynt, wisdome doth wyll excell
               Wisdome is alway good, and Wyll somtime euyl
               Wisdome obaieth God, Wyll somtime doth rebel
               Wisdom, of God is led, Wyl somtime of the deuyl
               And let not wyll reioyce in his wicked power
               For the more power he hath to commit euyll
               The more seruile, the more vile day and hower,
               And the more draweth he vnto the deuyll.
            
            
               Wylle.
               ¶To your sentence I can not moche disagre
               In few words you haue shewed ye bōdage of wyl
               Now I praye you declare how it may be free
               And I wyll humbly harke vnto your skyll.
            
            
               Wysdome.
               Whan Wyll to Wisdome wyllyngly doth encline
               (Now what Wysdome is I declared before)
               Than Wyll, not of merytes, but of grace diuyne
               Is enfrenchesed, and made free euermore
               
                  Recte igitur quidam, liber solus sapiens est
               
               
                  Dixere, Hic etenim solus ratione Magistra
               
               
                  Castigat motus animi sensum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      rebellem.
               
               Certayne learned men forsoth sayed ryghtly
               
                  A wyse man onely hath a free wyll
               For a wyse man through lady reason aptely
               Chastiseth euyl lustes, &amp; the flesshe rebelling stil.
               Reke this ordre. And than the wyll is free
               With Salomon aske of God his sapience
               Than to reasons rule alway agree
               And holde sensualitie in obedience
               He that can obserue purely these .iiii. lynes
               Not only a vertuouse man I do hym call
               But also I compare hym to a diuines
               And to the highest learned of them all.
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶I haue Ministred communication
               Sumwhat contrary to verytie
               That by your wyttie declaration
               I might be brought out of ambyguitie.
               For by reasonyng and argument
               Maters of contr
                     •
                  uersy and in doubt
               Are opened, made playne and euydent
               And the veritie searched and boulted out.
               Now to God humble thankes let vs rendre
               For his wonderful worke in mankynde
               Who our misery so greatly dyd tender
               That he sent his sonne his lost shepe to fynde.
            
            
               Wysdome.
               ¶Say this before dyner or supper:
               
                  Glory, honour and prayse to God the father
               For all his benefites geuen vnto vs
               Who by his spirite vouchsafe vs to gather
               Into the true fayth of his sonne Christ Iesus,
               We beseche that one God in Trinitie
               To blesse his creatures for vs prepared,
               Rendre we thankes with all humilitie
               For his kyndnesse to vs in all thynges declared
               He graunte vs his giftes so meanly to take
               That our bodyes may be in subiection
               Wherwith, suche a lyuely sacrifice we may make
               As before him may be in acception.
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶He keepe our tongues from talke of vanitie
               From backbityng, sclaunderyng or liyng
               At our table let there be suche humanitie
               As becometh his people bothe liuyng and diyng.
               In Gods name now take your refection
               We haue ended our talke for this season
               After your meale I must make an obiection
               Concernyng the highest parre called Reason.
               After dyner or supper say this
            
            
               Wisdome.
               ¶Approche my frynde I pray you &amp; come neare
               Go to nowe, propugne your obiection
               
                  And in the truth, shewe you a direction.
            
            
               Will.
               ¶You sayed before that Wyll is than free
               Whan it is subiecte to reason and sapience
               This sentence to reason doth not agree
               There is no fredom where as is obedience.
            
            
               Wisdom.
               ¶If Wyll hath any lybertie at all
               The most is reason and Wysdome to obay
               The freedom of Wyll, of it selfe is but small.
               Whan it refuseth reason to be his stay.
               To haue lycence to do euyll is no lybertie
               But the most vyle bondage that euer was
               Now reason through grace hath this propertie
               To cause Wyll in the way of truth to passe.
               He that doth synne, is seruaunt vnto synne
               O what seruitude is lyke vnto this
               Non other aduauntage therby do they wynne
               But hell, where Satan the Deuyll dampned is.
               Contrary wyse, there is no lybertie
               Lyke the subiection vnto vertue
               For that erecteth the soule into felycitie
               Yf vnto the ende we do it ensue.
               Beholde, here obedience is lybertye
               And lybertie (yf I may it so name)
               Is vyle bondage and vtter seruylitie
               
                  Whiche bringeth many a man to shame.
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶You haue well satisfyed my mynde
               But where as you talked sumwhat of reason
               I wolde knowe what reason is in kynde
               Whom you saye, Wyll must obay in season.
            
            
               Wysdome.
               
                  Est autem ratio lumen quoddam at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      animi Vis
               
               
                  Qua curuum a recto secernimus, at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ab honesto
               
               
                  Turpe. Oculus
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      solet mentis quando
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Vocari▪
                  
               
               Reasson is a certayn lyght &amp; strength of the mind
               Wherby we discerne the croked from the right
               The fylthy from the honest therby we do fynde
               Therfore of the mynde it is named the light.
               Lo here is this great Clearkes dyffinition
               Wherby what reason is you may learne
               Also reason is a perfecte erudition
               By the Whyche good from euyll we discerne.
               Now reason, as the phylosopher sayeth
               Euer more approcheth vnto the beest
               A directry of lyfe an handmayd of fayeth
               Whiche loueth vertue, and doth vice detest.
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶Than I see yf Wyll foloweth reason
               It shall consent to all that is honest
               But sensualytie worketh moche treason
               
                  And doth both reason and Wyll greatly molest
               But where as in your diffinicion aforesayd
               Of the mynde also you made mencion
               This terme (mynde) ought to be wayed
               Therin let vs also knowe your intencion.
            
            
               Wysdome.
               
                  Mens igitur sol est animae, sunt sidera sensus.
               
               The mynde to the soule is a sunne bryght
               Whiche illumineth the same with her clere shine
               By the minde the soule seeth to go right
               And nedeth not out of the way to declyne.
               As for the senses are as the dyuine starres
               Whiche giue a shyne, but not to worke by
               Yea against reason they be obstacles and barres
               The motions of reason to stoppe or denie.
               Senses alonely do the brute beastes beutyfie
               But reason and senses both do enorne mankinde
               Yet reason excelleth senses verely
               As a man a lyue excelleth a man dead and blind.
               Reason is the more noble parte in dede
               For to heauenly thinges the minde it doth cary
               Senses holde man downe, on the earth to feede
               And therby man from beastes do not much vary.
            
            
               Wylle.
               ¶You put me in memory of a sentence
               Whiche the great clarke Lactantius doth write
               
                  Wolde to God I had the wyt and science
               As he ment it, the same purely to recyte.
               That high artyficer God our parent dere
               Hath giuen to man, sense, reason and sapience
               That man to be made of him it might appere
               For God is sense, reason, Wisdom &amp; intelligence
               Of all the creatures that euer God did make
               In man he shewed most his omnipotencye
               Alas why dyd Adam his precept forsake
               For through synne he lost his innocencye
               Wysdom, Wyll, reason, mynde be here declared
               If you wyll speake a worde or .ii. of sence
               Whiche God in man hathe also prepared
               I wyll no more trouble you, but depart hence.
            
            
               Wisdome.
               Sum learned men call sense a powre passyue
               That is suffering obiectes variable
               Sensualytie is an appetite sensityue
               To the outwarde felyng very delectable.
               But senses are deuyded of phylosophers
               Into senses externall and internall
               Auicenna, Thomas, and their folowers
               Speake also of senses Intellectuall.
               Touching the senses externall ther be fyue
               That is, seyng, hearyng, smellyng, tasting, feling
               Bothe men and beastes as many as be alyue
               
                  Haue these fyue commonly, without differyng
               These are as wyndowes to intelligence
               For by them all things enter into vnderstanding
               Of the whiche thinges, reason and sapience
               Apoynt an ordre after their determining.
               We myght minister hereof more mater
               Than to the auditors should be profitable
               Of many thinges to vtter muche clater
               Is losse of tyme, and nothing laudable.
            
            
               Wyll.
               ¶There is not a worde spoken this season
               But therof some fruite I haue gathered.
               The knowledge I haue not farther to reason
               Whiche I trust is right well considered.
               To God yf it wyll please you thankes to giue
               Whiche wyth hys benefytes doth vs feede
               We shall do but our deutye, and I beleue
               That in all our actes, the better we shal speede.
            
            
               Wysdome.
               ¶Thankes to the o father our creator
               Thankes to the Iesus Christ the way &amp; veritie
               Thankes to the o spirite our consolator
               Thankes to the one blessed God in Trynitie.
            
            Amen.
            Finis.
            
               Compiled by Ihon Fysher student in Oxforde.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               ❧Imprinted at London in Smithfyeld at the signe of the Mytre, by Ihon Tisdale for William Pickeryng dwellyng at saynt Magnus corner.
            In the yeare of our Lord God M.D.L.UIII.
            The .v. daye of Marche.
         
      
   

