
   
      
         
            Fidelitas. A distinct declaratio[n] of the requiring of the Lorde and of the godlie testimonies of the holie spirit of the loue of Iesu Christ. Set-fourth by Fidelitas, a fellowe-elder with HN, in the famelie of the loue. Translated out of Base-almayne
            Fidelitas. A distinct declaration of the requiring of the Lorde and of the godlie testimonies of the holie spirit of the love of Jesu Christ.
            Fidelitas.
         
         
            
               1574
            
         
         Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00712
            STC 10843
            ESTC S117554
            99852767
            99852767
            18110
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00712)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18110)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 507:06)
         
         
            
               
                  Fidelitas. A distinct declaratio[n] of the requiring of the Lorde and of the godlie testimonies of the holie spirit of the loue of Iesu Christ. Set-fourth by Fidelitas, a fellowe-elder with HN, in the famelie of the loue. Translated out of Base-almayne
                  Fidelitas. A distinct declaration of the requiring of the Lorde and of the godlie testimonies of the holie spirit of the love of Jesu Christ.
                  Fidelitas.
                  Vitell, Christopher, fl. 1555-1579.
                  Niclaes, Hendrik, 1502?-1580?
               
               [46] p. : ill.  
               
                  Printed by N. Bohmberg,
                  [Cologne :
                  1574?]
               
               
                  Fidelitas is a pseudonym.
                  A translation by Christopher Vitell.
                  Imprint from STC.
                  HN = Hendrik Niclaes.
                  Signatures: A-C (-C8).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Familists --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-07
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-08
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-09
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2003-09
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
            
            
               Our Heart, is th
                     •…
                   Minde of God most-
                     •…
                  ie.
               Our Beeinge a
                     •…
                  able, as the sweete Lillie.
               Our Faithfulnes / Loue / and Trueth vpright,
               Is Gods Light / Life / and Cleernes bright.
            
         
         
            
            
               FIDELITAS. A Distinct Declaratiō of the Requiring of the Lorde and of the godlie Testimonies of the holie Spirit of the Loue of Iesu Christ.
            
            Set-fourth by Fidelitas, a Fellowe-elder with HN, in the Famelie of the Loue.
            
               Translated out of Base-almayne.
            
            
            
               Beholde, I set before your Eyes this-daye, the Blessinge &amp; the Curssinge. The Blessinge, 
                     〈◊〉
                   yee obey the Commaundementes of ye Lord your God, which I cōmaund or giue you this-daye. The Curssing, if yee obey not the Commaundementes of the Lorde your God, but 
                     •…
                  rne you out of ye Waye which I this-day will 
                     •…
                  ou vnto or set-fourth before you.
               Deu. 11. 30.
            
         
         
            
            
               Now goeth the Iudgment ouer the World: Now becometh the Prince of this World cast-out.
               Iohn. 12.
            
            
               
            
            
               Now is the Saluation / the Power / and the Kingdom, becom our Gods: and the Might his Christes.
               Apoca. 12.
            
         
         
            
            THE PREFACE.
            VNto the Louers of the Trueth and of the vpright Righteousnes, and vnto all which shall reade or heare this distinct Declaration of the Requiringe of the Lorde, Health and Saluation.
            2. This-daye through our faithfull Elder FIDELITAS ⁏a Fellowe-elder with HN, in ye Famelie of the Loue of Iesu Christ; ther becō
               eth ⁏out of God-his Grace; distinctlie expressed and declared vnto you all ⁏O yee Louers of the Trueth; with thissame Declaration of the Requiringe of the Lorde, what the Will and Requiringe of the Lorde is, and how yee all should enter, rightlie and accordinge to the Trueth, into the Pro. 4. b. Iere. 6. b. Wayes of the Lorde &amp; his Requiringe, for to liue vprightlie in God-his true Luk. 1. g. Eph. 1. a. Righteousnes, and to inherit Math. 2
                     •…
                  . d. the eternall Life, according to the Promises of God ye Father and his Christ.
            3. Ther is likewise expressed and declared vnto you in the same, from whence the wicked Thing proceedeth, wher-through the whole Worlde is 1. Iohn. 5. 
                     •…
                  . so full of Falshod: and how that ye Man is lett or hindered by the same, that hee doth not rightlie vnderstand nor obey the Requiring of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde: and wherthrough also the same wicked Thing and his Lett or Hinderinge, may be remoued and depressed or vtterlie brought-to-nothing: with other-moe groundlie Instructions, to the Mans Preseruation in the Godlines, &amp; euident

or distinct Admonitions, for the auoydinge of his Destruction.
            4. With which Declaration of the Requiringe of the Lorde, the Lorde likewise calleth and biddeth ⁏through the fore-named Elder FIDELITAS; all People, to ye 
               Esa. 16. 
                     •…
                  . Heb. 5. a. Gratious-stoole of his Loue: and that they should all willingly applie them, vnto the 1. Pet. 1. c. Obedience of the Requiring of his gratious Woord and Seruice of Loue.
            5. To the Preseruation of them all in hys Godlynes, and to an Admonitiō for the auoyding of their Destruction, in the Gen. 3. b. Esa. 59. b. Estraunging or Seperation from his godlie Beeing and true God seruice vnder the Obedience of his Loue.
            6. Therfore ⁏O yee Louers of the Trueth; when yee now this-daye, heare this Voyce &amp; proffered Grace to the Entraunce of your Saluatiō, Psal. 95. b. Heb. 3. b. so hardē not ⁏in any-case; your Heartes, as to be disobedient vnto ye Requiringe of this Declaration, To thende that yee remaine not with-out the Rest of the Childrē of God, which God now in the last time, declareth-fourth out of ye Famelie of his Loue, &amp; wher-vnto Hee also calleth and biddeth all People.
            Take it to heart.
         
      
      
         
            
            A distinct Declaration of the Requiring of the Lorde / which the Lorde ؛the liuinge God of Heauen
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                hath declared out of his holie Sion and heauenlie Ierusalem · and set-fourth through the Elder Fidelitas.
            
            The First Chapiter.
            
               IN the Two-and-seuentith  Yeare of the Elderdom of HN (In y• time when-as Certen ⁏beinge turned-in vnto themselues; tooke-on a Conceit or Meaninge, that they could vnpre
               
                  •…
               ared and vnregenerated · and with-out the Tes
               
                  •…
               amentes of God · and with-out the Ministra
               
                  •…
               ion of those-same through HN, be the People of God in whom Hee is wel-pleased / and vncircum
               
                  •…
               sed on the Foreskinne of their Heartes, enter into 
                  •…
               he Sanctuarie of God: and that then coulde euen
               
                  •…
               , in the Turning-in and Loue vnto themselues · 
                  〈◊〉
                the Disobedience vnto the Requiring of the gra
               
                  •…
               ous Woorde of the Lorde and his Seruice of 
                  •…
               oue · and in the Seperation from the Doctrine of 
                  
                     •…
                  N in the true Testamentes of God, liue vpright 
                  •…
               d free / and also followe-after and fulfill the Lord
               
                  •…
               s Will / which they distincted not from out of 
                  •…
               eir owne Will) hath the God of Heauē distinctlie

declared vnto Mee Fidelitas, a Fellowe-elder in the Famelie of Loue ⁏with cleere Declaration, out Psal. 50. a. Esa. 2. a. Mich. 4. a. of his holie Sion and heauenlie Ierusalem; the right Requiring of his Woord and Will: and also the right Waye or Passe-ouer which leadeth to the vpright Life of the Righteous · to God-his true Sanctuarie · and to the right Esa. 32. c. Sap. 3. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Rest and Freedom of the Children of God: and the Woorde of the Lorde came vnto Mee / and saide:
            2. GO-fourth and shewe thyself among the Children of Men which trouble or busye them about my Trueth · and about my Woorde and Righteousnes / speciallie among them, that are turned-in vnto themselues and their owne Loue / and meane or suppose euenso, that they in the Loue of themselues · and in their taken-on Knowledge of the godlie Thinges, haue my Trueth and Righteousnes: and saye vnto them ⁏to their Preseruation; all these Woordes which I speake vnto thee / Ier
                     •…
                  . 31. c. and geeue thee in thy Heart and Mouth / or write thesame in a Letter / and endeuour the
                  •…
                diligentlie, that thesame be heald-fourth before thei
                  •…
                Eyes · and hearde in their Eares. First ⁏or befor
                  •…
                all; amonge those which reade and heare the god
                  •…
               lie Testimonies of my gratious Woorde ⁏set-fourth by my chosen Minister HN; or which haue rea
                  •…
                and hearde or allowed thosesame and yet not ap
                  •…
               plyed them with all their Heart, to perfourme th
                  •…
                Requiringe therof: and witnes and declare vnt
                  •…
                them all which geeue-eare thervnto, That whic
                  •…
                I require through my gratious Woorde: Ezech. 3. b. an
                  •…
                warne them all of the Desiruction that shall fa
                  •…
                vpon the wicked Worlde · vpon all Vnbeleeuers

Disobedientones / and Resisters of the Requiringe of my Woorde · and vpon all Offallers or Declyners from the Requiringe of thesame.
            3. And in all thissame, infourme and instruct them likewise, what it is that letteth or hindereth them, that they vnderstand not rightlie the Requiringe of my gratious Woorde and Seruice of Loue / nor-yet are obedient ⁏from the Requiringe of the Math 3. 
                     〈◊〉
                   Luk. 3. b. Heb. 6. a. first Entraunce to the true christian Life, till vnto the Perfection therof; in anye right maner to thesame / nor bestowe their diligence aright ther vnto: and how that they for-that-cause, cannot perseuer firmlie therin · nor com to the true Heb. 3. b. 4. a. Freedom of the Children of God. But call or bidde them first, to the Conuertion and Math. 18. a. Iohn. 3. a. Turningeabout to the right Childshipp of the new Birth / and that they let their Vnderstandinges be renewed therto, vnder the Obedience of my Loue / and saye vnto them:
            4. TVrne you about to the Math. 18. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Mark. 10. b. childish Singlemindednes, O yee Children of Men: Depart from the Heathenshipp of your Vncircumcision / and com-in heather to the Couenaunt of the Lorde and his Circumcised: and humble you obedientlie, to the Requiringe of the seruiceable Outflowinge of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde / shewing-fourth vpright Math. 3. a. Act. 2. c. 3. c. Frutes of Repentaunce. For That is the Requiringe of the Lorde: And ther-to ⁏to-weet, to the Entraunce of thatsame, wherof ther is spoken; let your Vnderstandinges becom renewed, vnder the Obedience of the Loue / and yourselues Act. 3 
                     〈◊〉
                  . brought-to-right againe: and euenso in your Conuertion, becom first in the right

Feare Pro. 1. a. 9. b. Eccli. 1. b. of God ؛the true Forefrunt of ye Entraunce to the Sanctuarie of God
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                circumcised on the Foreskinne Deu
                     •…
                  . 10. b. Iere. 4. a. of your Heartes, to the Col. 2. b. 1. Pet. 2. a. Laying-away of the Sinne in the Fleash: and shewe-fourth goodwillinge Obedience therin.
            5. For thatsame and to shewe-fourth Obedience therin, is the Lord-his right Couenaunt of Circumcision / Rom. 2. c. Col. 2. b. which the right Seede of Abraham beareth in his Fleash / and that maketh the right Difference, betwixt the Lord-his People / and the vncircumcised Heathen: And it is the right Couenaunt of the Lorde / which the Lorde ⁏er-euer Hee maketh the Iere. 31. c. Heb. 8. b. 10. a new Couenaunt with his People; ordaineth Gen. 17. b. first by his People / and which also in the Ministration and Obedience of his Requyringe, hath the Fore-going by them, to the Esa. 52. a. Ezech. 44. a. Ioel. 3. b. Entraunce of the true Sanctuarie of God and of his vpright Godseruice / where no Vncircumcised may enter-in.
            6. And when yee now ⁏to a right Entraunce of the true Sanctuarie of God; are entred into this Couenaunt of the Lorde / and of the Circumcising of his People / and that his Requiringe is accomplished by you, with the People of the Lorde, the Communialtie or Famelie of the Loue / so enter than likewise into the Rom. 10. b. Beleef of Iesu Christ 
               ؛the true Holie of God-his Sanctuarie
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                wherin the Accomplishing Heb. 9. b. c. of the true Offeringe &amp; Godseruice of the Circumcised of the Lorde · the right Baptisme ether Washinge of the Beleeuers, Ezech. 36. c. with the pure Water and pretious Bloud of Iesu Christ · and the true Forgeeuenes of Sinnes / Heb. 9. b. c. and the vpright Purginge or Safe-makinge from thesame, comethto-passe

or is wrought: and where-out the right Renewinge Rom. 12. a. Ephe. 4. b. of the Heart and Minde proceedeth.
            7. And in thesame true Beleef and Baptisme of Iesu Christ, becom implanted into Christ, 
               Rom. 6. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Phil. 3. a. with his like Death: and let yourselues euenso ⁏in the Death of Iesu Christ; be prepared to an vpright People of the Lorde / Deut. 4. a. d 10. b. Ephe. 1. a. in whom Hee hath a goodpleasure / and that are meete to enter into his Rest · and to the Rest and Freedom of the Children of God. And in thesame true Beleef or Holie / and in the Requiringe of thesame and his Ministration, shew-fourth Deu. 6. 30. a. goodwillinge Obedience / and Mat. 10. 24. b bide stedfast therin, vntill that it all which the Lorde requireth of you and in you, be fulfilled / and that Christ 
               Rom. 8. a. Gal. 2. c. 4. b. after the Spirit · and the true Apo. 21. c. Kingdom of Heauens and his vpright Righteousnes, be com vnto you.
            8. For euenso in the Fulfillinge or Perfourmaunce  of the Requiringe of the Seruice of the true Beleef · and in the Cominge of Christ with the Apo. 21. a. Kingdom of Heauens and his spirituall and heauenlie Goods, the Lorde Ier. 31. d. Heb. 8. a. 10. a erecteth with his People, his new Couenaunt of Perfection / wherin it becometh then all fulfilled and accomplished, that is writen in the Luk. 24. g. Lawe of Moyses. that God hath required through his Propheates. and that is euangelized of Christ and of his Kingdom.
            9. And thatsame new Couenaunt, is the true new Couenaunt which the Lorde hath promised, to mate or erect with his People: and which also in the Fulfilling of his former Couenaunt, Hee maketh or erecteth with his People / and remembreth not Ier. 31. d. Heb. 8. 10. a. their Sinnes anymore. For euenso, in their

Purginge or Safe-makinge through Iesus Christ in the Beleef · and in the Accomplishinge of thesame Seruice in the Holie, becometh Math. 27. d. 2. Cor. 3. b. the Vayle ⁏which is the Heb. 10. b. Fleash of Christ; don-away from the Mostholie of the true Sanctuarie of God / and the Lorde vncouereth then by his People, his mostholie Sanctuarie Apo. 21. a. full of all sumpteous Garnishinge of pure Bewtie / and full of all spirituall and heauenlie Goods and Riches of God and Christ: and they becom euenso glorified, from the 2. Cor. 3. b. vncouered Face of God and Christ, with the true Beeinge of the vpright Perfection. serued with the spirituall Heb. 8. a. and heauenlie Goods. and repleanished with the holie Iohn. 14. b. Act. 2. a. Spirit of the Loue of God and Christ.
            
            10. And euenso in the Fulfillinge of thesame, They are Rom. 8. b. the true Children of the new Testament in Iesu Christ, and the vpright Elders and Fathers in the Famelie of the Loue of Iesu Christ, which geeue or set not fourth their Testimonies, out of the Knowledge of many godlie Thinges: but which bring-fourth, out of the Accomplishinge of the fore-goinge Seruice · and out of the spirituall and heauenlie Treasure of the godlie Beeing of their Heart, Math. 13. f. the Newe and the Olde / that is, the True and the Figuratiue.
            11. And all they that are in such-sort, out of the Accomplishinge of the fore-goinge Seruice, entred into Ier. 31. d. the true Sanctuarie of God and Christ, Those knowe and perceaue that the Lorde is euenso the true Lorde, Deut. 4. a. amonge his People: and they haue then obtayned the vpright Ephe. 4. b. Knowledge of the perfect Righteousnes and Godlines · the vpright

               Esa. 32. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Iohn. 8. c. Freedom of the Children of God · and the true Appeasement of the Conscience, in Iesu Christ.
            
            12. But to remaine in the Sinne vnrepentant ·  and without the Seruice of the Loue of Iesu Christ, vnregenerated (wherin yee seduce and destroye one-another of you ⁏O yee Children of Men; with the Knowledge) and that yee then euenso at the last ⁏when-as the Destruction hath bewrapped you; shall see and perceaue therin, that yee haue accounted yourselues wyse, before the time appointed · taken-on the Sap. 2. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Freedom in your Vnregeneration · and Pro. 1. c. refused the proffered Grace of the Lorde / and the Obedience of the Requiring of his gratious Woorde and Seruice of Loue: and that yee likewise in all your Fourth-goinge, haue not ⁏accordinge to the Requiringe of the vpright Righteousnes which God esteemeth; don ne brought-fourth any vpright Frutes of Repentaunce / and must be fayne to beare the Rom. 2. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Iudgment of God, with the wicked Worlde · and with the euell Thinges, wherin shee and her Adherentes do liue: and that yee then knowe or perceaue therin, that the Lorde ؛the true God of Loue
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                is not any God of the Vnrepentant and of the Disobedient: but is their God, Iohn. 9. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Act. 10. f. which loue the Righteousnes and the Fulfillinge of the Requiringe of his Woorde / and hate all Vnrighteousnes and Resistaunce of the Requiringe of his Woorde / So shall then all thatsame ⁏in thesame Iudgment of God; be a great Sap. 5. a. Accusation vnto you of your Sinnes, to your Condemnation.
            13. Therfore, be now warned heer-withall / and feare not ouer-much, to forgoe or leese your owne

Will and Corruption or Consumeablenes that hangeth so fast on / Math. 16. e. that yee forsake not therthrough the euer-lastinge vpright Righteousnes · and the Ministration to thesame appertayninge: But feare rather, for the Frindshippe of ye Worlde / and for your owne Self-seekinges cause, to becom the Iam. 4. a. Enemies of God · and Disobedient to the Requiringe of his Woorde / and so then to leese the Apo. 21. a. eternall Perfection of the pure Bewtie of the euer-lastinge Kingdom: and perpetuallie to misse ⁏or be depriued-of; the eternall immutable Riches of the spirituall and heauenlie Goods: and to byde seperated for-euer, 2. Tess. 1. a. from the louelie Beholdinge of the vncouered Face of God and Christ, and from the perfect Esa. 35. 51. b Ioye of the eternall Life. Yea, therof be you all afraide.
            14. BVt if now ther be not any Feare with  you touching this Matier / or that yee beleeue not the Woorde of the Lorde and his Requiringe heerin / nor haue any force therof, O yee Children of Men / and euenso meane ether coniecture out of your owne Wisedom, that yee being vnprepared · and without the Obedience of the Requiringe of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde · and without the Perfourmaunce of the Requiring of the forementioned Seruice in the Holie, can inherit and bring-fourth the vpright Frutes of the godlie Life / Trulie, that Supposell of yours, will vtterlie disappoint you / and your owne Wisdome will deceaue, seduce, and begile you all: and also estraunge you from the Ioye of the Childship of the holie Sion. from the Ephe. 2. b. Citizenship of the heauenlie Ierusalem. from the Inheritaunce of the

Testamentes of God and Israel. and from the Freedom of the Children of God: and yee shall euenso be forced, to remaine captiue in the Heathenship · and in the Abhomination of Desolatiō of the Kingdom of Babel, and obtaine therin a terrible Ende.
            15. THerfore heare the Woorde of the Lorde, to Obedience of his Requiringe / and let Pro. 2. 4. 
                     •…
                  . thesame sincke into your Heartes / and turne not backe in any-case: nether suffer yourselues to be drawen-away from That which is set-fourth before you, out of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde and his Seruice of Loue / nor-yet lead therfrom, by any Mans Woordes that is against thesame. For if you haue bestowed your diligence to heare the Witnessinges of the gratious Woord of the Lorde, set-fourth through the holie Spirit of the Loue of Iesu Christ: and that yee haue yealded your Voyce or consented therin, with our Fellowe-elder HN: and that yee haue ⁏moreouer; enterprised or begon your Fourth-goinge therin / So looke well then heerto, that yee seeke not to finish thesame Beginninge, in the Witnessinges of Men that are against thesame / and in their Malice and Offenciuenes, execute or iudge a false Iudgment ouer vs and our Ministration.
            16. But fixe or bende alwayes all your Sight  and Consideration on Mee ؛
               FAITHFVLNES
               
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                / and consider, how that the Lorde hath chosen Mee ⁏euen from my very Psal. 71. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Ier. 1. a. Birth out of my Mothers Wombe; to the Obedience of the Requiringe of his Woorde / for that I with you / and yee also with mee ⁏according to the Requiringe of ye Testimonics

of his gratious Woorde; should becom vnited therin / and so wee to growe of one vniformebeeinge with each-other, in thesame / To thende that yee mought euenso ⁏according to the Requiringe of thesame; haue a right Course or Passaige for to com-in, Deut. 10. a. Math. 22. d. to the true Loue of your God · to the vpright Loue of your Neighbour · 2. Pet. 1. b. to the vpright Loue of brotherlie Familiaritie · and to the right common Loue towardes all Men: and then likewise mought Math. 10. c. 24. b. perseuer firmlie therin.
            17. BVT ⁏alas; for that I ؛
               FAITHFVLNES
               
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                am so small / and that my faithfull Obedience, is ⁏euery-wheare; so little regarded among the Children of Men / So cannot therfore many of you, consider well on Mee nor on my Obedience / for to becom of one Heart and Minde therwith.
            18. Therfore heare now the Woorde of the Lorde, O yee Children of Men: Turne-away the Sight of your Eyes, Psal. 131. a. Pro. 6. b. from the Highest / and turne thesame to ye Lowest or Humblest: and notewell theare in the Lowest, the faithfull Obedience. first-of-all, in the little or childish Singlemindednes / and how that Faithfulnes, with the Goodwillingones · and the Goodwillingones with Faithfulnes, do Ephe. 4. b. growe-vpp obedientlie, from out of the childish Singlemindednes, to the manlie Olde-aige of the Man Iesu Christ.
            
            19. For-that-cause / humble you euen-so / for to set yourselues ⁏first-of-all; with vs, in the lowestNOTA or nethermost Luc. 14. b. Place of all the Humble and Obedientones / so shall yee then also right-well perceaue, that the lowlie Humbleones / and faithfull

Obedientones ⁏euen in the manlie Olde-aige of Iesu Christ; do in such-sort rightlie inherit with God and his Sainctes, the Highest of the Glorie of God and the Lambe. and the true Freedom of the Children of God and of all the Holyones of Christ, and therto the euerlastinge Life.
            20. But yet many of you haue not ben able to  perceaue thesame: For yee are lett or hindred therin, through the Gen. 3. b. Seede of the olde Serpent, Ezech. 8. a. that greeuous &amp; horrible Beast of the Bottomles-pit / which with his Knowledge, contrarie to the Requiring of the Lorde · and with his Stoole of Disobedience, hath set himself on the North, 2. Tess. 2. a. in the Temple of ye Lorde / wheare the gratious Woorde of the Lorde and his Requiringe, is now ⁏through our Fellowe-elder HN; administred vnto Manye.
            21. Which horrible Beast, hath marred and corrupted all the Vnderstandinge of Man, in the Knowledge / and hath euenso alwayes ben a Lett to the Children of Men, in their corrupt Vnderstandinge / and with his Knowledge ⁏contrary to the Requiringe of the Woorde of ye Lorde; hindred them for entring-in to the right Entraunce of the true Life / and for turning-againe aright vnto the God of their Saluation.
            22. And thatsame horrible Beast ؛
               Gen. 3. b. Ezech. 8. a. the Seede of the olde Serpent
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                is now also in the last tyme, most-dammaigefull &amp; pernitious vnto you all ⁏O yee Children of Men; in your Sight / Hearinge / and Vnderstanding, for to com to the Obedience of the Requiringe of the Woorde: and that also theefliest turneth you out of the Waye that leadeth to the true Life / and bringeth you into a 2. Tess. 2. b. secreat

Errour, which yee ⁏through the Lett of that mostgreeuous and detestable Beast; cannot well perceaue / for that thesame is ouer-all, most-chieflie esteemed amonge the Children of Men / and hath ⁏in all their Wayes; plucked or 2. Cor. 11. a. drawen them into a contrarye Minde / wherin they notwithstanding suppose that they are in the right.
         
         
            The Seconde Chap.
            ANd albeit now that many Men perswade  themselues, that they turne them onlie to God and his Woorde / and walke in the Waye to the Life / yet turne not they themselues to the true God and his Woorde of Life, in any right-maner / nether haue they also founde 4. Esd. 7. a. the Waye to the true Life: For they turneaway themselues from the gratious Woorde of the Lorde, which in his Seruice of Loue, doth seruiceablie set-fourth and expresse vnto them ⁏in their Esa. 59. a. Seperation or Disiunction from God and his vpright Beeinge; the first Entraunce of the right Waye to the Life / to thend that they should euenso becom turned-about therin, to the Math. 18. a. childish Singlemindednes · and plucked to the true Obedience of the Requiringe of the Woorde of ye Lorde: and that they mought then euenso ⁏rightlie and accordinge to the Trueth; com-againe to their God · and inherit the true Life of God · and the vpright Beeinge of the Loue of Iesu Christ. But many refuse thissame / and turning them vnto themselues, they applie them to geeue-eare vnto that Ezech. 8. a. horrible and mischeuous Beast, which inhabiteth

with them / and hath set himself in them ⁏with his Stoole of Disobedience; on the North, in the Temple of the Lorde · and euenso broughtin and placed his Woorde of Knowledge, against the Woorde of Life of the true liuinge God, by and amonge them / and they let themselues becom veryshamefullie seduced through thesame.
            2. Verelie / thissame Beast ؛the seducinge Seede of the olde Serpent
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                is a terrible Beast, before the Eyes of all the Holyones / inasmuch as that hee is risen-vpp out of the Apo. 17. b. Bottomles-pitt [that is, out of the Seperation from God-his Beeinge]: and is the Esa. 5. b. 59. b false Light of the Knowledge itself / which in all his Nature and Disposition, is very false and deceitfull / and bringeth-vnto ether heriteth the disobedient Man, with the Iere. 17. b. most-wilie and mischeuous Heart.
            3. And forasmuch as that thesame Beast is so exceeding false · and so hindersom or dammaigefull vnto all Men, concerning the right Entraunce to the Life / and planteth so great Falshod in them / So ought all Men therfore, to take good-heede of thesame / and to staye or Deut. 4. a. Pro. 3. a. 6. b. holde themselues somuch the faster and faithfuller on the gratious Woorde of the Lorde and his Requiringe / and to passe-fourth therin obedientlie / vntill that thesame false and deceaueable Seede of the olde Serpent / together with his disobedient Knowledge, be damned and buryed Apo. 17. b. 19. d. in the Bottomles-pitt, wherout it came-fourth.
            4. For / so-longe as it sitteth in the Man with  his Dominion, on his Stoole of Disobedience / and is had chiefliest in estimation of the Children of

Men / So doth thesame appeere or glinse so mightilie ⁏with his false Light of the Knowledge; before the Eyes of Men / that they Pro. 3. a. 
                     •…
                  sa. 5. b. 59. a. suppose thesame to be the true Light of the Wisdome of God. also it bloweth his Knowledge ⁏to the Tourning-in o
                  •…
                Men vnto Phil. 2. 
                     •…
                  . their Self-seekinge; so forciblie into their Eares, that they conceaue it to be the very Woord of the Lorde (For they applie them gladlie accordinge to the Requyringe of thesame Knowledge). It taketh likewise their Vnderstandinges captiue so mightelie therin, that they suppose thesame Captiuitie to be their Freedom: And for-that-cause also ⁏so-longe as they heare and beleeue thesame; they cannot by anye-meanes see / heare / nor beleeue the true Obedience and Faithfulnes / nor the Forsakinge of their Selfseekinge ⁏the which is required out of the Math. 16. c. Luk. 9. c. 14. 
                     •…
                  
                Woord of the Lorde and his Seruice of Loue; to an Entraunce into the Doctrine or Discipline of Iesu Christ ·  nether-yet go-fourth nor perseuer constantlie therin.
            5. Also they cannot rightlie vnderstand, how they ought ⁏according to the Requiringe of the Woorde of the Lorde and of his Seruice of Loue; to let themselues be prepared Luk. 1. 
                     •…
                  . to an vpright People of the Lorde / vnlest they vtterlie Math. 16. c. Luk. 9. 14. c. forsake and leaue the venemous Seede of the olde Serpent and his Requiring of Disobedience · and also their Selfnes☞ which they seeke therin: and euenso turne them about to the Math. 18. a. childish Singlemindednes / and not respect or waye the Perrell of the Fleashes Dammaige: but turne them whollie and altogether, to the Inwarde-beholdinge of the Math. 10. c. 16. c. Luk. 1
                     •…
                  . 
                     •…
                  . Hinderaunce of

the Soule and of the vpright Righteousnes / and to the Inspection of the Preseruation of thesame, to a Remnaunt in the euerlastinge Immortalitie / for to accomplish euenso the Lord-his Will. to enter-in to the Obedience of the Requiringe of the Woorde of the Lorde. and to fulfill Math. 
                     •…
                  . 
                     •…
                  . all Righteousnes obedientlie: and not let themselues lust after anye other thinge.
            6. Yea / so should they then ⁏out of the Obedience of the Requiringe of the gratious Woorde and Seruice of Loue; learne to perceaue, the vpright Consubstantiation Iohn. 6. e. 17. 
                     •…
                  
                or Vnifourme-vnitinge, which the Man ought to haue with God and his vpright Beeinge / and also what-maner of Loue hee ought to beare towardes an other: and that thesame forementioned greeuous Beast, is Ezech. 8 a. Apo. 17. b. the wicked and horrible Beast, whose Generation hath ⁏thorough thatsame Wickedone; killed or Act. 17. e. murdered y•
               NOTA Witnesses of God and Christ · and the holie Zacharias the 2. Para. 24. c. Math. 23. e. Sonne of Barachias, betwixt the Temple and the Aulter [that is: betwixt the Entraunce into the Sanctuarie / and the Fulfillinge of the Offeringe ether Godseruice in thesame]. also caused the Dan. 8. b. daylie Offeringe ether Godseruice to ceasse. and brought the whole Howse of the Lorde, which Hee had chosen vnto himself for his Dwelling, in vtter desolatiō 
               4. Reg. 25. 
                     •…
                  . Psal. 74. 79. a. Esa. 64. d. with Abhominatiōs.
            7. Also they should well perceaue, that the Reuendgment of all giltlesse Bloud ⁏which from the Beginninge til-vnto this present Daye of the Manifestation of the Iudgment of God, is shead vpon the Earth; shall com Math. 23. d. Apo. 6. 
                     •…
                  . 16. 
                     •…
                  
                ouer thatsame wicked Generation, to his vtter Rooting-out and Condemnation:

and also how and wher-through, that the mischeuous Beast and his Generation, hath euen hetherto, ben a very mightie Lett vnto all Men, for to assemble them to God-his Witnesses: and doth yeat also presentlie now in the last time, hinder very many, for to go-in ⁏vnder the Obedience of the Loue; to the Entraunce of the vpright Godlines.
            8. BEholde / how cleere and apparant all  thissame is set-fourth before you all ⁏O yee Children of Men; which heare vs / and how distinctlie, both the Deut. 11. 30. b Eccli. 15. c. Destruction and also the Preseruation, becometh ⁏out of God-his Grace; prefigured vnto you. For-that-cause / learne now once to consider and marke, that yee all erre / and haue wicked Eyes · and much Euel-surmisinge among you: as also that your Eyes are 
                  
                     •…
                  en. 3. 
                     •…
                  . opened through that greuous &amp; horrible Beast ؛the false Light of y•
               ☞ Knowledge
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                / and hee hath geuē you to vnderstand, that yee ⁏in your Vnregeneration; should take-on the Freedom, for to be disobedient to the Requiringe of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde. Pro. 1. 
                     •…
                  . Esa. 5. 
                     •…
                  . to contemne and resist the Lord-his proffered Grace and the Minister of his Woorde. and to turneaway yourselues therfrom.
            9. For-that-cause, withdrawe now your Eyes from thesame wicked Sight / and turne you about hether, to the Life of the Trueth / and becom counselled in-time, to turne the Sight of your Eyes vnto the Lust to accomplish the Will of the Lorde / &amp; to be obedient vnto ye Requiring of his Woorde / So shall yee then perceaue and knowe, that the Sentence-of-iudgment and the Doctrine set-fourth

by HN, is proceeded from out of the liuinge God: and that the Obedience to the Requiring of thesame, trayneth and leadeth men into the true Life, which God accepteth / &amp; is the Mans Saluation.
            10. Yee shall then also right-well insee and vnderstand, that thesame Obedience, is the Iohn. 
                     •…
                  . 
                     •…
                  . vpright Freedom of the Children of God: and that the true Life, wher-vnto thesame Obedience bringeth-men, is the vpright and Iohn. 1. 
                     •…
                  . true Light of Men: and that all other Lightes and Freedomes which are without thesame, cannot bide-standinge before God nor his Holyones.
            11. Moreouer / yee shall insee and perceaue or vnderstand, that the Disobedience is not any Freedom. but is the Subiection or 2. Pet. 2. c. Bondaige to the Sinne · to the Self-will of Man · and to ye Might of the Deuell / of the Hell / and of the Fleash (toweet, that those-same haue the Dominion ouer and in the Disobedience) and that thesame Disobedience beareth alwaies a Care or resteth mindfull, of all what concerneth the Fleash / but is verie-little carefull of that which concerneth the Soule and the vpright Beeinge of God: and that also therfore, all the Esa. 59. a. Lightes and 2. Pet. 2. a. Freedomes of the vnrepentant and vnregenerated Men, are false and deceitfull / and bringe-in or stirre-vp Breach / Dissention / and Offenciuenes, among the Children of Men / and euenso turne-away the Children of Men from the Mercifulnes Mich. 6. a. Math. 1
                     •…
                  . c. 
                     •…
                  
                and Forgeeuinge of Sinnes which they owe one towardes an-other: as also from the peaceable Concorde of the vpright brotherlie Loue / and from the vpright Beeing of God &amp; his Christ.
            
            12. Also that all vnregenerated Men, which 
               
haue regarde and geeue-eare vnto these false Lightes and Freedomes, becom therwithall very shamefullie seduced / and that those-same are also very hindersom vnto them, for to com to y• humble and obedient Singlemindednes of Iesu Christ and his Loue: For they all leade-men away from thesame / as also from the Waye which reacheth thervnto.
            13. FOr-that-cause ⁏O yee Children of Men; holde you Eccli. 2. a. Heb. 12. a. stedfastlie on the Woorde of the Lorde and his Requiring / and on the Loue and Mercifulnes, Rom. 13. a. which yee are deptours to keepe and shew-fourth towardes euery-one: and suffer not yourselues to be withdrawen at any time, from the safe-makinge Testimonies of God and his holie Spirit of Loue / which haue ben ⁏out of entire Loue; to all your Preseruation, healde-fourth by our Fellow-elder HN, before you / and which are also yeat dailie borne before you: For out of those-same, yee may readelie conceaue the true and vpright Beeing of the regenerated Men · and their true Freedom with the Children of God: as also vnderstand, wherto yee are created · and called or bidden, through the Seruice of the Loue: And yee shall euenso well perceaue, the pernitious Seducinge of the Sap. 2. a. 14. b. Rom. 1. c. 2. Pet. 2. b. false Freedom of all vnregenerated Men, wherof yee are presentlie warned.
            14. Thus beware that yee eate not Act. 15. 
                     •…
                  . of ThatNOTA which is strangled in the Bloud. go not to the Aulters of the Heathen or Vncircumcised / for to offer-vp your willing Guiftes theron to the Lorde. haue not any Lust for to eate 1. Cor. 10. c of that which is offered to their Idole. mu
                  •…
               e not yourselues familier

               1. Cor. 5. b. with their Vncleannes. go not in also to their Howse-of-laughter / inasmuch as thesame ⁏assuredlie; lieth altogether desolate. nether reioyce you with the Vnrepentant: but turne you therfrom / Eccle. 7. a. and go much-rather into the Howse-of-lamentation ⁏or Mourning-howse; Esa. 66. a. wheare the Littleones and Poore are / wheare y• Goodwillinge and Obedientones are / and wheare the Humble and Lowlie · the Mercifull and Meeke-minded · and the Math. 5. a. Hungrie and Thirstie after the Righteousnes, are: and wheare-as also ther is Sorrowe borne and Repentaunce shewed for the Sinne: and ther-out let your Ioye / Freedom / and Peace · and all your Familiaritie or Common-heartednes / Loue / and Wisdome, haue his proceeding / and be brought-fourth / So shall yee then vnderstand aright, that I haue writen and administred the Trueth vnto you: and that this Counsell of the Wisdome, is not of Man · but of God.
            15. Therfore take now in-tyme, the Counsell  of the Wisdome ⁏albeit that thesame is dispised of many; and thissame distinct or cleere Instruction, effectuallie Pro. 2. 4. 
                     •…
                  . to heart / and assemble you all vnto vs / and to our Seruice of Loue: and in thesame Seruice, let all your Vnderstanding becom renewed / to a right Inspection of the vpright Beeing, wherin the Man 
                  •…
               ught ⁏concordablie; to stande comprehended: To thende that ther mought be founde among vs all that loue the Righteousnes, one concordable Minde, Rom. 12. 15. 1. Cor. 1. a. to the Vnitie of Heart · one vpright Dealinge · and one mutuall brotherlie Walkinge, euenlike as it is meete and · right.
            16. Heer-vnto let vs becom Phil. 2. 
                     •…
                  . like minded / and

passe-fourth concordablie ⁏with goodwilling Heartes; after thesame: and not looke how Certen ⁏in times-passed; haue walked and spokē / for to retaine any Matier against anyone to the worst or to his reproch: Math. 18. d. Ephe. 4. c. Col. 3. b. but laye it all downe &amp; not thinke theron anymore: and let vs euēso turne our whole Sight, for to beholde wher-vnto wee were created and chosen / and what a Loue and Mercie wee Rom. 13. b. are deptours to extēd or shewe one towardes another: and ther-vnto let vs loue and be seruiceable one towardes another: and euenso enter into the true Life / and then speake or talke therof.
         
         
            The Thirde Chap.
            HEare now therfore the Woorde of  the Lorde and his Requiringe, O yee Children of Men: forasmuch as that the false Esa. 5. b. 59. a Math. 6. c. Light of y• deceitfull Knowledg, hath euery-wheare brought-in and placed his Stoole of Disobedience, amōg all vnrepentant vnregenerated Men: and that now in this Daye, y• Manifestation or Declaringe of all Thinges that are in Heauē and vpon Earth ⁏both of the Perfect and also of the Vnperfect; becometh ⁏through the seruiceable Testimonies of the holie Spirit of Loue; administred and declared, so cleere and expreslie vnto 
                  〈◊〉
                / So let vs now then respect-well this 2. Cor. 6. a. Gal. 6. 
                     •…
                  . gratious Time / and diligentlie applye vs with each-other ⁏concordablie; in thesame / that the wel-prepared Esa. 16. c. Stoole of Obedience of the true Light of Life (which presentlie in thissame Daye of the Loue ⁏to an euerlasting Stoole-of-grace; is com vnto vs from Heauen,

vpon the Earth / and wheron also the Faithfulnes doth sitt, Esa. 16. 
                     •…
                  . 32. a. with Iudgment and Mercie) mought now be erected euery-wheare ⁏by all vs which loue the Righteousnes in Iesu Christ; against the Stoole of the Disobedience of the false Light of the Knowledge (which it hath broughtfourth and lifted-vpp out of the Bottomles-pitt, to a Stoole of Indignation ⁏on the North; in the Temple of the Lorde: and wheron the Vnfaithfulnes, with his vnmercifull Iudgment hath sett himself): and that euenso thesame Stoole of Obedience, mought be planted ⁏Iam. 1. c. with Meckmindednes; into all Louers of the vpright Righteousnes.
            2. For through the Erectinge of thesame / and in that wee all which loue the vpright Righteousnes, consent and geeue-ouer ourselues ⁏according to the Requiring of the gratious Woorde and his Seruice of Loue; ther-vnto, wee shall rightlie and according to the Trueth, be brought to the true freedom Iohn. 8. c. of the Children of God · Math. 13. f. taught to the Kingdom of Heauens · and Iohn. 15. a. 17. c. implanted to the vpright Beeing of Iesu Christ.
            
            3. Yea in such-wise ⁏in the Consentinge and  Geeuinge-ouer of our Heartes, to the Obedience of the Requiringe of the gratious Woord and of his Seruice of Loue; shall the stoole of Disobedience of the fal
                  •…
                
               
                  •…
               ight of the Knowledge, in vs and in all Beleeuers and Obedientones, be ouer-throwen · and so then Rom. 16. c. trodden vnder feete &amp; vtterlie broughtto-nothing, by vs and by all Beleeuers and Obedientones: and it shall euenso appeere, that wee ⁏in our Faith and Obedience; are the vpright Disciples Luk. 14. c. Iohn. 8. c. or Schollers of the gratious Woord of the

Lorde / and Math. 10. c. 
                     •…
                  4. b. perseuer firme therin obedientlie.
            4. It shall also right-well appeere, that wee the Perseueraunce in the Discipline of the gratio
                  •…
                Woorde, do knowe the Trueth, in the Truet
                  •…
                and that wee also are rightlie made-free, not thorough the Knowledge. Iohn. 8. c. but of the Trueth · an
                  •…
                through the Inheritinge of her vpright Beeinge.
            5. Therfore, followe not now ye 
               Deu. 12. a. Esa. 5. b. Goodthinkin
                  •…
                of your Heartes: but ensue the Requiringe of the Testimonies of the Trueth. For in this Daye of the Trueth, which wee presentlie declare / it shall all whatsoeuer is Trueth / and of the Trueth / and also all Act. 3. 
                     •…
                  . that which God hath spoken through his Propheates, from the Beginninge of the Worlde, becom now restored · Agg. 2. a. b. Apoc. 2
                     •…
                  . a. and erected in his pure Bewtie or Excellentie and Perfection, vnder the Obedience of the Loue: and many People shall be ashamed of their ignorant Knowledg / and that they haue so vncomlie leaned Eccli. 41. c. with their Elbowe on the Bread · not esteemed thesame according to the V
                  •…
               
               lue therof · and eaten so 1. Cor. 11. c. vnworthelie of thesame.
            6. HAue therfore now a good Consideration  heeron / and note how that presentlie, through the Lion of the Tribe of Iuda 
               ؛the Roote of Dauid
               
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                
               Apoc. 5. a. the Booke of ye Priuie-misterie of God ⁏which is full of Writing both within and without; becometh opened vnto you Apo. 14. 
                     •…
                  . and the 
                  •…
               ighteous Iudgment of God and Christ, declared out of thesame: and how that fardermore, the greeuous and horrible Beast of the Bottomles-deapth and his Stoole, shall ⁏through thesame Iudgment; be cast into his owne Apoc. 17. b. 19. 
                     •…
                  . 20. b. Bottomles-pitt · and remaine therin damned for euermore.
            
               
               
                  •…
               . When now therfore all this is accomplished · 
                  •…
               d the fore-mentioned greeuous Beast ؛the false 
                  •…
               ght of the Knowledge
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                and his Stoole of Diso
               
                  •…
               dience ؛the 4. Esd. 4. c. d. Place wheare the Euell is sowen
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                
               
                  •…
               st-downe and ouerthrowen · and with his Adhe
               
                  •…
               ntes, damned in the Bottomles-pitt: and that 
                  •…
               e vpright Beeinge of the Loue ؛the true Light o
                  •…
                
               
                  •…
               ife
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                and his Stoole of Obedience ؛ye Place where 
                  •…
               e Good is sowen
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                is set-vpp againe / and hath got
               
                  •…
               n the Preheminence / Then shall ⁏verelie; the 
                  •…
               cripture becom fulfilled / Apo. 11. 11. b. and the Kingdom and 
                  •…
               ominion, be the Lordes / and the Might, his Christes.
            
            
               
                  •…
               . And all Men which repent them of their 
                  •…
               innes, Psal. 98. a. Esa. 52. b. shall obtaine the Godlines / and inherit 
                  •…
               e true Iohn. 8. c. Freedom with the Children of God / like 
                  •…
               s the Lorde hath promised them / and wher-vnto 
                  •…
               ee hath also loued and chosen them, euen from the 
                  •…
               eginning: and shall fardermore vnderstand / that 
                  •…
               e Iudgment, which the God of Heauen hath de
               
                  •…
               ared through HN, vpō the Earth · and set-fourth 
                  •…
               hrough thesame his Minister, is very-true: and 
                  •…
               hat also thesame Iudgment, pronounceth and de
               
                  •…
               areth the right Forme or State, of all what is in 
                  •…
               eauen and vpon Earth and beneath the Earth · of 
                  •…
               ll what is Gods and Mans · Spirituall &amp; Hea
               
                  •…
               enlie · and 
                  〈◊〉
                all what is Naturall, right, and re
               
                  •…
               nable: and that no such Iohn. 1. a. 10. d. 15. c. Wonderful-woorkes 
                  •…
               oulde be wrought nor brought-fourth by anye Man, vnlest God were with him.
            
               
                  •…
               . They shall also vnderstand, that the Reuea
               
                  •…
               inge  or Declaring of thesame Iudgment of God, 
                  〈◊〉
                God-his great Loue &amp; Mercie / which Hee now

in the last tyme, is extending ouer all Men on th
                  •…
                Earth, to their Preseruation in the Godlines / to thend that they all, which are captiued wt Sinnes and estraunged from their vpright State / and from the good Beeing of God, should be warned (ereuer the Iudgment of God fall vpon them) o
                  •…
                the terrible Miserie and Condemnation, Math. 24. c. Luk. 21. c. Rom. 2. a. Iudae. 1. b. which shall fall vpon the Vngodlie / and vpon all them that would not shewe-fourth any Repentaunce / but dispise the proffered Grace of the Lorde: and that they all should euenso ⁏to their Preseruation in the Godlines; turne them to the God of Life / and to his gratious Woorde and Seruice of Loue · repent Act. 2. f. 3. c. 17. d. them of their Sinnes · and so becom prepared to an vpright People of the Lorde / and that the Scripture mought euenso becom fulfilled ⁏vnto good; ouer them.
            10. O Yee Children of Men, dispise not ⁏in anye-case; thissame Pro. 1. c. proffered Grace. nether let your Eyes be wicked in their Sight / Math. 6. c. Luk. 11. d. lest your whole Bodie becom darke: but let them be single / and so becom turned, for to looke into the good Beeing / wher-vnto yee were created of God · and chosen through Iesus Christ, and wher-vnto yee are presentlie loued and inuited or courteousliebidden by the Famelie of Loue: and euenso in thesame single Sight, let your Vnderstandinges becom renewed vnder the Obedience of the Loue / To thende that yee be not deceaued, with any peruerse Sight Math. 18. a. 
                     •…
                  0. b. nor Wicked-conceauinge ouer yt Woorke and Woorde of the Lorde (according to the peruerse Sight &amp; Wicked-conceauing ouer yt Woorke and Woorde of the Lorde from the Beginninge

wherwithall the Man was begiled, Gen. 
                     •…
                   
                  
                     •…
                  . through the 
                  •…
               olde Serpent; nor-yet after the maner of the per
               
                  •…
               erse Sight and Wicked-conceauinge, ouer the Woorke and Woorde of the Lorde / wherwithall now also in the last tyme, the false Light of the Knowledge ؛the Seede of the olde Serpent
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                deceaueth the vnrepentant Men): but that yee may haue all Math. 6. c. Luk. 11. d. single-minded Sight / and all good Cogitations, ouer thesame · and be thankfull to the Lorde for his great Grace, that Hee so meeteth you all / and reacheth you the Hande ⁏now in the last tyme; Iohn. 7. 
                     •…
                  . with the Outflowinge of his gratious Woorde / and with the Seruice of his Loue / for to pluck you againe vnto Him: to purge you from all wicked Beeing: and euenso to sett you vpp againe, in your vpright Ephe. 1. a. Forme or State, whervnto Hee created the Man, in the Beginninge / and sett him therin: and whervnto Hee hath bidden all Men to com, through his Christ: as also whervnto Hee presentlie ⁏through the holie Spirit and Seruice of the Loue of his Christ; loueth vs all / To thende that wee should all euenso, through thesame Seruice of Loue and Assistaunce or Hand-reachinge, becom washed and cleansed / and so enter Iohn. 13. b. with cleane-washed Feete · with Eyes of singleminded Sight · and with cleere or pure Bodies, Esa. 52. a. Ezech. 44. b. into the true Sanctuarie of the spirituall and heauenlie Bewtiful-excellentie.
            11. YEa, ther-vnto let all the Sight of your  Eyes becom opened / and then looke into the Matier, what great Loue and Mercie of God · and what great Diligence and Feruentie, ther is bestowed on you / for to bring you all againe ⁏thorough

the seruiceable Testimonies of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde; to your vpright Godlynes / To thende that yee mought ⁏without faile; be safetie-kept, from the Seductinge of the false Light of the Knowledg / which now1. Tim. 4. a. 2. Tim. 3. a. 2. Pet. 2. a. in the last time, breateth-in forciblie, among many vnrepentant vnregenerated Men / and that yee should not refuse That, whervnto yee are loued by God-his Grace. nether-yet also turne you away, from your Godlynes · nor from vs and our Documentes, which are seruiceable ⁏therin; vnto you.
            12. And if now it were so ⁏yee Deerlie-beloued; that som of you had benPro. 6. 14. a. negligent or sluggish, in that which the gratious Woorde of the Lorde and his Seruice of Loue requireth · and turned you away from the Doctrine of the Woorde and Seruice of Loue / and from Vs ؛the Lordes and your Ministers
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                yet remaine not therfore seperated from vs / nor from our Doctrine of your Godlynes: but turne you againe to thesame / and assemble you euenso againe ⁏with goodwilling Heartes; to the Gratious-stooleHeb. 5. a. of the Remission of all Sinnes, for the which Sorrowe or Contrition is shewed / and Repentaunce don: and haue euenso out of Loue, your communion ⁏or mutual-societie; againe with vs / wherby yee mought then also with vs, haue your communiō
               1. Iohn. 1. a. with God the Father / with his Sonne ؛the Lorde Iesus Christ
               
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                / and with all Holyones / in all Loue: and receaue or imploy all ye Seruiceablenes which wee shewe and bestowe on you out of Loue, vnto your Reformation / and not in any-case vntoMath. 1
                     •…
                  . 
                     •…
                  . Offenciuenes or Displeasure / that yee may euenso cōtinuallie, be founde humblieminded

toward the good Beeing / and to the Loue of your Neighbour.
            13. For beholde / to that effect / and to all your  Amendement and Preseruation in the Godlynes, do I witnes thissame ⁏out of the Woorde of the Lorde; vnto you: and out of entire Loue, I do heere set-fourth the Trueth, both of the Preseruation of Men / and also of theSap. 1. 
                     •…
                  . 5. 
                     •…
                  
                Errour tending to their Destruction, before all your Eyes and Eares / To thende that yee should rightlie and according to the Trueth, looke-into / vnderstād / and beleeue the forementioned godlie Testimonies of our Writinges ؛the wonderfull Woorkes of God
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                which also declare-fourth ⁏with full Instruction; thesame Preseruation of Men and their Destruction · and applie you rightlie, according to the Requiringe of thesame · Iohn. 20. c. and so becom saued.
            14. But heerin (to-weet, in this Declaration) I haue no respect of persons, nether of great nor small: but call you all, to the Renewinge in your Vnderstandinge · Esa. 40. 
                     •…
                  . Math. 3. 
                     •…
                  . to the vpright Repentaunce for the Sinne · and to theMath. 18. 
                     •…
                  . childish Singlemindednes and Obedience,1. Pet. 1. c. which the gratious Woorde of the Lorde requireth, in his Seruice of Loue / to thende that yee all mought euenso, becom turnedabout to thesame childish Singlemindednes and Obedience · instructed to theIohn. 
                     •…
                   
                  
                     •…
                  . newe Birth in Iesu Christ, and to the Passe-ouer of thesame · taught to theMath. 13 
                     •…
                  . Kingdom of Heauens · and lead-in to the trueEsa. 32. Sap. 3. 5. a. Rest and Freedom of the Children of God / andRom. 6. c. inherit the eternall Life: and that the Woorde which the Lorde IesusIohn. 19. c. spake / in the Ende of his Passion [Consummatum est] It is finished,

mought also be then rightlie and according to th
                  •…
                Trueth, spoken by you all.
            15. For when-as all that which the Lorde requireth through his Woorde and through the Seruice of his Loue, is fulfilled, with vs all / and in vs all / so is then also verelie with vs all [namelie / by those, with whom thesame is fulfilled] the
                  
                     •…
                  . Cor. 15. 
                     •…
                  . f Oze. 13. 
                     •…
                  . Ende of the Sinne · and the Death of thesame, com-to-pas or attayned-vnto: and thatsame Ende of the Sinne and her Death,4. Esd. 7. e. is the Beginninge of the eternall Immortalitie: and is also the vprightIohn. 8. 
                     •…
                  . Freedom in Iesu Christ, wher-vnto all Men ؛Iewes and Greekes / Circumcised and Vncircumcised / Wyse and Vnwyse. &amp;c
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                are called an
                  •…
                bidden, by the Grace of God.
         
         
            The IIII. Chap.
            THerfore looke now all well vnto it, that yee deceaue not yourselues / nor-yet becom begyled of Others, which make-vp themselues against vs and our godlie Doctrine / or dispise thesame / and resist vs therin / for to plucke you to the Minde of their Opinions, which they set-fourth and maintaine against vs and our godlie Seruice of Loue. For-that-cause / keepeMath. 24. b. alwayes a good watch, toward all those that com vnto you with subtill Woordes and manlie Prudence, for to seduce you from the godlie Doctrine of the Seruice of Loue / Rom. 16. c. and seperate yourselues from Such / for they make Breach / and bringe-in Offence / and not any Concorde to the Vnitie of heart, in the Loue: but indeuour you for

to com and go-in, whervnto yee are now in the last tyme ⁏out of the Grace of God; called through the Ministration of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde, vnder the Obedience of the Loue.
            2. Howbeit, yee are not called to the Hardeheartednes of y• vnmercifull Man ouer his Frinde: nor-yet to com to theExo. 19. 
                     •…
                  . 
                     •…
                  
                Hill which is terrible / or which is heald-fourth as terrible before you, by vs / nether-yet to the Hill, which yee / beinge vnprepared or vnsanctified, may touch: but yee are called to the holieHeb. 12. c. Hill of Sion. to the peaceable Citie of the liuinge God. and to the heauenlie Ierusalem: to the Multitude of many Thowsandes of Angels or Sainctes. to the Communialtie of the Firstborne that are writen in Heauen. and to God the true Iudge ouer All: to the Spirites of the perfect Righteousnes. to Iesus, the true Mediatour of the newe Testament. and to the Sprincklinge of Bloud, which speaketh more or greater then the Bloud of Abel.
            
            3. Which pure and singuler Bewtifulnesses of  the heauenlie Beeinge (which were preached in times-passed in the Worlde, to anMark. 16. b. Luk. 24. f. Act. 1. b. 
               Euangelie or Ioyful-message / and which is also com vnto vs, now in the last time ⁏to a peaceable Kingdom and Gratious-stoole of the perfect Glorie of God and Triumphing of Iesu Christ, with all the Multitudes of manye Thowsandes of Sainctes; according to the Scriptures) wee do also presentlie in thissame Daye, publish or spread-abrode,Math. 24. b. Apoc. 14. 
                     •…
                  . to an Euāgelie or Ioyful-message of thesame. Kingdom · NOTA and to an eternall Glorie of the Goodnes of God and of his gratious Dominion ouer all Repentantones,

in the vniuersall Worlde / Math. 24. b. to a Testimonie towarde all People,Ezec. 7. a. b. c that the Ende cometh / namelie, the Fulfillinge of all that which is writen of the Iudgment and Righteousnes of God · of the Saluation and Preseruation of the Man · and of his Iniquitie / Destruction / and Condemnation.
            4. Therfore yee haue now toHeb. 12. 
                     •…
                  . looke-well heervnto / that yee refuse not thatsame whervnto yee are called and requyred for to com, by Hym which speaketh vnto you / that the Destruction bewrappe you not to your Perditiō. For if They escaped not the Destruction, which refused Him in tymes-past, when-as Hee spake vnto them on the Earth / muchlesse then shall yee escape the Destruction, if yee refuse That whervnto yee are called, by Him which speaketh vnto you out of Heauen. whose Voyce in tymes-past, n
                  •…
               ooued or shooke the Earth.
            5. And now ⁏verelie; speaketh Hee and sayeth: YetA
                     •…
                  . 2. 
                     •…
                  . Heb. 12. c. once-more will I mooue, not onlie the Earth. but also the Heauen / To thende that It which is becom moueable, may be chaunged / and be then vnmoueable, likeas it was made: and that God-his Kingdom of perfect Bewtie and Peaceablenes, mought then euenso be and remaine vnmoueable alwayes and for-euer vpon y• Earth, as in Heauē. Which Kingdom wee now inherit in theIohn. 
                     •…
                  . a. Tit. 3. b. seconde Birth, that cometh-to-passe in Iesu Christ, and is the euerlastingeSap. 1. b. Immortalitie: and which also bydeth fast-standinge before God, for euermore / and inheriteth in itself, all that which is euerlasting and immortall.
            6. And thesame seconde Birth in Iesu Christ, isMath. 19. d. verelie the true Birth, which standeth-fast

perpetuallie vnremoueable, in the Iudgment of God · and in the Communialtie of the Righteous: and wherin wee also serue and please the God of Heauen, rightlie and accordinge to the Trueth.
            7. FOr-that-cause,Rom. 13. b. awake now all out of your Dreame / and turne the Sight of your Eyes, to the true Light of Life: and discerne or distinct thesame, from out-of the false Light of the Knowledge: and beholde then euenso the perditionable Ende of thesame false Light / and how that the wicked Worlde and all Vnrepentantones ⁏which admit or take vnto them the false Light; shall not be able to escape thesame perditionable Ende / but must needes beare a likeMath. 25. d. Rom. 2. a. 2. Tess. 1. a. Sentence of Condemnation with thesame. Yea, looke well into thesame / and consider aduisedlie theron / that yee may be defended from thesame perditionable Ende · and preserued in the Godlines of the true Light of Life, which is required out of the Ministration of the gratious Woorde and his Seruice of Loue.
            8. For seeinge that the Dominion of the false Light,4. Esdr. 14. b. Math. 24. b. raigneth now so mightelie in the wicked Worlde and in her Adherentes, with al-maner of Falshod and Malitious-subtiltie: and that likewise many Adherentes of the wicked Worlde, haue a Lust and stand-inclined thervnto / So is now also the Destruction of the wicked Worlde and her Adherentes, com harde-at-hande / accordinge to the Scriptures: For theEzech. 7. 
                     •…
                  . Math. 24. b. c Ende of the wicked Worlde cometh vpon all the fower Corners of the Lande. Yea, euen-now ⁏in the Iudgment4. Esd. 13. d. Iudae. 
                     •…
                  . b. of God with all his Holyones; cometh the Ende ouer her: For nowEzech. 7. a. will the Lorde send-fourth his Indignation · 

and Apoc. 6. c. the Lambe his Wrath, ouer her / and iudge her, according as shee hath deserued: and let all that com vpon her, which appertaineth to her Abhominations for to receaue.
            9. Thus becom heer-withall admonished / and make not yourselues ⁏in any-wise; familier nor ofone-beeinge with any-thinge that cleaueth vnto the wicked Worlde / that yee perrish not therwith: For the Ezech. 7. a. Eye of the Lorde shall not spare the wicked Worlde · nor anye of all those which cleaue vnto her / nether-yet also looke vpon her, to her Excusation. 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . Esdr. 13. c. Apoc. 18. b. c. but will let com vpon her and her Ministers, like as they haue deserued.
            10. For-that-cause / haue now a right regard, vpō all the Abhominations of the wicked Worlde / that yee may keepe yourselues seperated from thesame: But not from vs nor our Documentes, which loue and are seruiceable vnto you, to your Preseruation in the Godlines: Ezech. 3. 
                     •…
                  . and warne you of the Abhominations of the wicked Worlde and her Destruction / to thende that yee should not perrish with her. For I fore-tell you assuredlie, that the Abhominations of y• wicked Worlde (haue therfore a circumspect consideration heeron, O yee Children of Men) shall breake-in among you / and yee shall likewise be vehementlie assaulted therwith.
            11. Neuerthelesse / if yee holde you firmlie to the Requiring of the gratious Woorde and his Seruice of Loue / yee shall then be deliuered from the wicked 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 2. a. Ephe. 6. c. Heb. 12. a. Assaultinges which com against you, out of the Abhominations of the wicked Worlde · and out of the Falshod of our Resisters / and inherit the Crowne Sap. 3. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 2. Tim. 4. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . of the eternall Life / and the true Annointinge

               Psal. 45. b. 1. Iohn. 2. c. of the Ioyful-oyle of the holie Spirit of the Loue of Iesu Christ: and euenso finde-by-experience, that our God of Loue, is the true Lorde / and that Wee ؛his obedient Communialtie of the Loue
                  
                     
                  
                  punctel
                are his acceptable People: and that also they all, which bide estraunged from thesame God. as also remaine with-out vs and our Communialtie · and with-out the Requiringe of the gratious Woorde and his Seruice of Loue / or withdrawe themselues therfrom, haue no liuing God nor-yet true Godseruice: Ephe. 2. b. but are without God and without Godseruice, in this Worlde. For our God 1. Iohn. 4. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . of Loue, is the true liuing God / and Esa. 43. 44. 2. besides Him, ther is no God more. and his Godseruice of Loue ⁏which wee minister vnder the Obedience of his Loue; is the true safe-making Godseruice / and besides thesame, ther is not any Godseruice more, nether in Heauen nor-yet vpon Earth.
            12. Therfore is our God, a God and Life of his vpright Beeinge / and a God &amp; Life of his People, which loue his vpright Beeinge / and haue a Psal. 4
                     •…
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Lust to accomplish his Will, vnder the Obedience of his Loue: and thesame our God, is also an Enemie and Death vnto all false Beeinge of y• peruerse World / and an Enemie &amp; Death vnto all Vngodlie which hate his vpright Beeinge / and resist his Will · and the Obedience of the Requiringe of his Woorde. And therfore our God of Loue, is 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 1
                     •…
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                  . a God that soueth the true Righteousnes / and hateth all vngodlie Beeing: and in such-like-sort wee also with Him, euen with all Inclination to doo his Will.
            13. Therfore goeth now also Esa. 2. 8. Mic
                     •…
                  . 4. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . the Woord of the  Lorde out of Ierusalem ⁏ouer the peruerse World,

to her Destruction: but ouer all Beleeuers and Obedientones of the gratious Woorde, to their Preseruation in the Godlines; and warneth vs all / together with all those which clea
                  •…
               e with vs vnto the Requiringe of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde and his Seruice of Loue, of the terrible Esa. 13. a Mal. 4. a. Destruction that is for to com vpon the wicked Worlde and her Abhominations · and vpon all those that bide without vs and our Seruice of Loue / and resist our God and his gratious Woord of Life / and speaketh euen-thus:
            14. O Yee Children of Men / Math. 2. c. attende or watch now all on the Destructiō which is for to com. Ezech. 7. a. For so / the one Infelicitie cometh vpon another: The one Woe goeth before / and the other Woe followeth thervpon much-more rigorous: And albeit that the one Night passeth-ouer by many / and that they then suppose, that it is becom Daye with them, in their Vnregeneration / and that the Infelicitie hath not com-nye or lighted-on them in the fore-goinge Night / yet are they not therfore escaped the Infelicitie / nether shall the other Nightes bide-backe or not com vpon them: but they shall all followe vpon y• fore-going Night / and euerye sondrie Night shall make-manifest and bringe with him, his owne Infelicitie and Destruction ouer them / vntill that the last most-horrible Night be com vpon them, in vnmeasurable and vnqueanchable Destruction.
            15. OH! what an vnmeasurable Woe, cometh-ther  ouer the wicked Worlde: and also ouer all them that cleaue vnto her / and shewefourth Rom. 2. a. no Repentaunce / nor will assemble them,

wher-vnto they are called and bidden through the gratious Woord and his Seruice of Loue, to their Preseruation in the Godlines.
            16. For-that-cause seperate you now all 4. Esd. 2. d. from the wicked World / and shew-fourth Repentaunce / and saue or ridde your Soule and Bodie from the Destruction / and forsake Math. 16. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Luk. 9. 14. d. all what is your owne / and bring vnto the Lorde that 2. Para. 30. which is His: For the Ende cometh. Beholde, Ezech. 7. b. it cometh swiftlie on / and beginneth alredie to make his Entraunce / and breaketh-thorowe verye stowtlie ouer the Inhabitantes of the Lande.
            17. The Time of Destruction cometh / and the great terrible Miserie is harde-at-hande. Ezech. 7. b. Therfore, mourne not now ouer that which yee haue solde / reioyce not also ouer that which yee haue bought / but let him that mourneth, mourne for that the Iniquitie 4. Esd. 14. b. Math. 24. b. raigneth so mightesie / and let him that reioyceth, reioyce in the Intelligence of the true godlie Beeinge / and in the Hope of the tocoming Peace: For the Time of Destruction bringeth not els-what with it, but an Inspection of great Affliction / Dolour / and Miserie: Ezech. 7. b. and ther shall not be any Singinge heard therin, to the Ioyfulnes of Life. but all Bewayling and Rufulnes / and Seekinge of Death: For such an Endinge, will the Lorde now shortlie bring vpon the wicked World / and powre-fourth his Indignatiō, vpon them that are so full of Falshod: and will euenso fullie accomplish his Wrath ouer them.
         
         
            The V. Chap.
            
               BEholde / now commeth the Daye: Lo / Ezech. 7. c. theare commeth hee / and breakethfourth / and shall not deferre him. For the Rodde doth blossom / the Prowde waxeth greene / and Tirannie hath made-vpp itself, to a Punnishment ouer the Vngodlie: in such-wise / that none of them nor of ye Multitude of their Heapes, shall haue anye staye of Comfort ether Hope: For the Indignation of the Lorde passeth-fourth ouer all the Multitude of their Heapes: Ezech. 7. b. Yea, the Sworde raingeth-abrode in their Streates / and the Pestilence and Hunger is in their Howses.
            2. They shall ⁏euen out of great Miserie; castfourth their Esa. 2. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 30. c. 31. c. Ezech. 7. b. 4. Esdr. 16. c. Siluer on the Streates / and esteeme their Golde and Bragginge-iewels or Riches, as Filthynes or Dirte. Soph. 1. c. Eccli. 5. b. For all this shall not deliuer them, in the Daye of the Wrath of the Lorde: nether shall they also suffise their Sowles therwith / nor fill their Bellie therwith all: for all thatsame hath not wrought in them anye Reformation nor Righteousnes / but rather Offenciuenes and Malice, to the ingendringe of Misdooinge: and they haue euenso vsed their Iewels or Riches, vnto Pryde / and made thesame to an Abhomination before the Lorde.
            3. OH! How full ofEzech. 7. c. Bloud-giltines are the Landes / and how full of Malitiousgrudginge are the Cities: and how full of Variaunce and Resistaunce of the Loue, are their Inhabitantes. Therfore hath the Lorde also deuysed to bringe vpō them, the most-wicked among the Heathē or Vncircumcised / that they might seduce them to the very-worst / and counsell them to liue free, in

their sinfull Birth · in their Vnrepentaunce · and in their Vnregeneration: and then will the Lorde also take his occasion therout, to make-an-ende ofEzech. 7. c. the Pryde of the Presumpteous · and of the Tirannie of the Violent-oppressours / and to disclose the ProphanatingeThe Prophanatinge of their Assemblies, are the Feastifuldayes of the V
                     •…
                   godly
                     •…
                  . or Vnhallowinge of their Assemblies: and will euenso reiect both them and also their Elders or Wise (which they haue set-vpp / admitted / and chosen from amonge them-selues ⁏without the Loue and her Seruice; to be Elders or Wise · as also healde and esteemed them for Such) from the Presence of his Face.
            4. Then shall manye of them, Ezech. 7. c. seeke after the  Peace which they now misse or haue lost / but it shall not be any-wheare to be founde amonge them. For Vexation and Trouble shall fall vpon them whereuer they becom. and one euell Brute shall com ouer them after another. Then shall they diligentlie go vnto their Propheates, to seeke the Insight or Vision of the Peace / and make-inquisition amonge their Elders, after the Wisdome and after the Ordinaunce of the Lorde, to their Concorde.
            5. But Ezech. 7. c. ther shall nether Wisdom / Ordinaunce of the Lorde / nor Vision of Peace · nether-yet any Counsell to Concord nor to Preseruation, be found by their Elders. Their Kinges or Gouernours shall then also be afflicted with great Heauynes · and their Princes clothed with Mourning-weede. For their Might and Dominion shall not be feared / and the Ezech. 7. b. Handes of the People in the Lande, shall finde themselues vnmightie · and their Heartes discomforted.
            6. Yea / euen-then will the Lorde himself Esa. 
                     •…
                  2. b. with

his Arme / and with the Armes of his Holyones, be the true Iudge vpon the Earth / and cleanse the vniuersall Earth, Math. 3. b. Luk. 3. b. from all the Vnrighteousnes &amp; Falshod that the Children of Men ⁏in their Vnrepentaunce and Contemning of the Saluation; haue practised and erected on the Earth: and they shall euēso perceaue-in-experience, that our God of Loue, is the true Lorde / and that Hee hath neuer willed the Ezech. 18. d 1. Tim. 2. a. 2. Pet. 3. a. Destructiō of Men: but alwayes called them to Repentaunce / and to their Preseruation in the Godlynes / and warned them of the Destruction: euen-like as his Loue and Mercie doth also yeat presentlie in the last Daye, shew-fourth thesame.
            7. O Yee Childrē of Men, consider and note  aduisedlie, the great Loue and Goodnes that becometh yeat presentlie in the last Daye extended on you / to your Preseruation in the Godlines: and how that yee are with this distinct Declaratiō of the Deut. 11. c. Eccli. 15. c. Life and of the Death, visited out of entire Loue · required to com to the Psal. 45. b. Esa. 16. c. Heb. 1. b. 5. a. Gratious-stoole of the godlie Maiestie, which is com vnto vs on the Earth · and loued ⁏in Iesu Christ; for to haue one vniforme Heart and Minde with vs / To thende that yee mought haue your communion with vs / whilst ⁏surelie; our communion is 1. Ioan. 1. 
                     •…
                  . with God the Father. with the Lorde Iesus Christ. and with the true Beeinge of the Holie-gost.
            
               Take it to heart.
            
            8. WIth this distinct Declaration, ther is ⁏euen out of Loue; required o
                  •…
                you all ⁏O yee Children of Men; which heare thesame / or to whom it becometh administred / that eueryone;

vnto Concorde and Rom. 15. 
                     •…
                  . 1. Cor. 1. 
                     •…
                  . 2. Cor. 
                     •…
                  3. b. Vnitie-of-minde to the Loue; do open or make-manifest his Heart by vs, euenlike as wee do heare by him / &amp; geeue Testimonie,☜ whether that hee be of one Minde and Meaning heerin with vs / or-els whether that hee ⁏as repugnant vnto vs; desireth not to geeue his consent heerin.
            9. For, inasmuch as that the vpright Goodwillingnes to God Math. 22. d. Eph. 1. 2. 4. b. and his synceere Righteousnes · and the true Common-heartednes of the Rom. 12. b. 1. Pet. 1. c. 3. b brotherlie Loue and Conuersatiō, is so nakedlie and expresslie set-fourth heerwith before you / So can yee also somuch-the-easelier feele &amp; perceaue in your Heartes, whether that yee be goodwillinge with vs Littleones and Lowlyones, to seeke-after the vpright Righteousnes · and after the true Familiaritie of brotherlie Loue: and whether that yee also desire ⁏in this Math. 24. b. 1. Tim. 4. a. 2. Tim. 3. a. 2. Pet. 2. 
                     •…
                  . perrelous Time; our willinge Seruice, ther-vnto / and to your Preseruation in the Godlines: or that yee as repugnant vnto vs, are vnwilling thervnto: as also whether that yee ⁏with your Knowledge 1. Tim. 6. 
                     •…
                  .; desyre to holde you backe and as Straungers, from thesame and from Vs / and not to haue your soscietie with vs / nor-yet do require any Seruice of Loue ⁏ther-vnto; at our handes.
            10. Therfore let euerye-one now, freelie geeue  Testimonie heerof / and do yee yourselues, examine your owne-selues / whether that yee be Fellowe-beleeuers with vs Littleones and Lowlyones, to the Beleef of the vpright Righteousnes and Ephe. 4. b. true Life of Iesu Christ: and euenso desire to go-out-from &amp; forsake with vs ⁏vnder the Obedience of the Loue of Iesu Christ; all the Worldes Falshod / and all

that which ought not to be by the vpright Beleeuers of Iesu Christ, and so to be the Seruauntes of God, in his vpright Rom. 6. b. Righteousnes: or whether that yee both against Vs / and also against the true Faith to the vpright Righteousnes, do rest vnbeleeuinge / and desire not, for God-his vpright Righteousnes cause ⁏or for to be the Seruauntes of God therin; to forsake the Loue of the Worlde · and all that which is worldlie and vnright / together with your owne Self-seekinge / nether-yet to consent or stand-willinge to thesame, whervnto yee are presentlie loued of vs.
            11. Whosoeuer now then is 1. Cor. 1. a. 2. Cor. 13. b. concordablie-minded with vs to the good Life and vpright Beeinge (whervnto wee haue ⁏according to the Requiring of the gratious Woorde of the Lorde; whollie geuen-ouer our-selues / and all our Heart / Minde 
                  •…
                and Soule, to a Esa. 10. c. Remnant in the Perrishinge o
                  •…
                the wicked Worlde) and yealdeth his Voyce therin with vs / let him also expresse then therwith, hi
                  •…
                Inclinable-affect to thesame good Life and vprigh
                  •…
               
               ☞ Beeinge / and that hee consenteth therin / and hat
                  •…
                an Heartie-lust and Desire to the Furtheraunce o
                  •…
                the Seruice pertayninge to thesame.
            12. Ouer Whom [namelie they that haue 
                  •…
                Lust with vs to accomplish the Will of the Lorde and that receaue our Warninge for the auoyding of the Destruction · and our Doctrine to their Preseruation in the Godlines, in Thankes-geeuinge t
                  •…
                the Lorde / and applie them diligentlie thervnto] w
                  •…
                will also continuallie ⁏to their Preseruation in t
                  •…
                Godlines; shew-fourth our good Care: For to
                  •…
               
               ardes such Goodwillingones / and humble Go
                  •…
               
               
fearingones, wee 
                  〈◊〉
                not spare oursel
                  •…
                uiceable vnto them ⁏both Night and Daye; in this perrelous Time / inasmuch as they with vs, haue adioyned themselues ⁏with whole Heart; to the onlie liuing God and the Requiringe of his gratious Woorde / and also loue Him / and haue a Psal. 40. 
                     •…
                  . Lust to keepe his Commaundementes / and to fulfill Math. 3. c. all Righteousnes.
            13. But those which refuse to conuersate them  with vs, accordinge to the Requiringe of the Loue and her Seruice / and beleeue Abac. 1. 
                     •…
                  . Act. 13. c. not Gods Wonderful-woorkes and his Testimonies, set-fourth or brought-to-light by vs. but contemne / deride / and resist those-same and our Seruice, layed on vs by God: and also backbite and defame vs with much Falshod / ouer Those, wee will shewe-fourth Pacience and all Goodnes and 2. Cor. 4. a. Tit. 3. a. Discrectnes.
            14. Neuerthelesse, therin wee Act. 20. c. excuse and cleere ourselues before them, as touchinge their Destruction: as also of all that which shall com vpon them and their Children, by the Euell / wherof wee haue warned them / and they would in no-wise heare vs. And keepe euenso our Heartes and Conscience pure and vnspotted, from their Vnbeleef &amp; Vnwillingnes: Act. 13. turninge vs to the Beleeuers and Goodwillingones · and to the humble Godfearingones, which haue a Lust to walke in the Wayes of the Lorde / and to doo his Will / for to be alwaies seruiceable vnto Them, to the good Life / and for to bringe vnto them, the Declaration of the heauenlie Treasures · and of the louelie Beeinge of the 2. Cor. 3. b. vncouered Face of God and Christ ·  as also of the Misterie Math. 13. a. Col. 2. 
                     •…
                  . of the Kingdom of Heauens / all which

gones ⁏in their Vnbeleef; do vtterlie 
                  〈◊〉
               .
            15. Let eueryone take this effectuallie to heart / and let noman refuse the good Beeinge, whervnto God hath created the Man · and called him thorough Iesus Christ and his Holyones / and whervnto hee is also presentlie loued, by the Communialtie of the Loue of Iesu Christ.
            
            16. Also let noman be ashamed, to be adioyned vnto the Goodnes of God and the Requiringe of his gratious Woorde / and to confesse thesame / nether let him also refuse to assemble him vnto vs / and to geeue Testimonie, that hee desireth to endeuour himself accordinge to the Requiringe heerof / and consenteth or agreeth therin with vs: and so to let his inclined Goodwillingnes appeere, that hee intendeth or meaneth with Heart, the Seruice of Loue · and the Ministration to thesame that is healde-fourth before him: like-as ther is also 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 42. d. c. Reue. 
                     •…
                  9. d. 
                     •…
                  . requyred ether desired in the Euangelie of the Kingdom, set-fourth by God-his chosen Minister HN.
            
            17. Take it to heart: and let eueryone respect-well thissame proffered Grace / and let noman harden his Heart ther-against.
            CHARITAS EXTORSIT PER FIDELITAS.
            
         
      
   

