
   
      
         
            Here after foloweth a mornynge remembrau[n]ce had at the moneth mynde of the noble prynces Margarete countesse of Rychemonde [et] Darbye moder vnto kynge Henry the. vii. [et] grandame to oure souerayne lorde that nowe is, vppon whose soule almyghty god haue mercy
            Mornynge remembraunce
            Fisher, John, Saint, 1469-1535.
         
         
            
               1509
            
         
         Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00766
            STC 10891
            ESTC S105603
            99841330
            99841330
            5905
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00766)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5905)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 40:07)
         
         
            
               
                  Here after foloweth a mornynge remembrau[n]ce had at the moneth mynde of the noble prynces Margarete countesse of Rychemonde [et] Darbye moder vnto kynge Henry the. vii. [et] grandame to oure souerayne lorde that nowe is, vppon whose soule almyghty god haue mercy
                  Mornynge remembraunce
                  Fisher, John, Saint, 1469-1535.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  In Flete strete at the sygne of the sonne by Wynkyn de Worde,
                  [Enprynted at London :
                  [1509]]
               
               
                  Running title reads: Compyled by ye reuerent fader in god. Iohan Fyssher bysshop of Rochestre.
                  With a title-page woodcut.
                  Place of publication and printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.
                  Signatures: A-B⁶.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Beaufort, Margaret, --  Countess of Richmond and Derby, 1443-1509.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-04
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-04
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶Hereafter foloweth a mornynge remembraū
               ce
had at the moneth mynde of the noble prynces
Margarete countesse of Rychemonde &amp; Darbye
moder vnto kynge Henry the .vii. &amp; grandame to
oure souerayne lorde that nowe is vppon whose
soule almyghty god haue mercy.
            
               
            
            
            
            ¶Dixit Martha ad Ihesum.
            
               THis holy gospell late red / conteyneth
in it a dyalogue that is to saye a comynycacyon
betwyxt the woman of
blessyd memory called Martha and
our sauyour Ihesu / whiche dyalogue
I wolde applye vnto this noble
prȳces late deceased / in whose remē
               braunce
this offyce &amp; obseruaūces be done at this tyme.
And thre thynges by ye leue of god I wyll entende
Fyrst to shewe wherin this noble prynces may wel be
lykened &amp; compared vnto ye blessyd woman Martha.
Seconde how she may complayne vnto our sauyour
Ihesu for ye paynfull dethe of her body / lyke as Martha
dyde for ye dethe of her broder Lazarus. Thyrde ye
confortable answer of our sauyour Ihesu vnto her agayne.
In the fyrst shall stonde her prayse &amp; cōmendacyon.
In ye seconde our mornyng for ye losse of her. In
the .iij. our confort agayne. Fyrst I saye yt the comparyson
of them two may be made in .iiij. thȳges. In noblenes
of persone / in dyscyplyne of theyr bodyes / in or
deryng of theyr soules to god / in hospytalites kepȳge
&amp; charitable dealing to their neybours. In whiche .iiii
the noble woman Martha (as say ye doctours entreatynge
this gospell / &amp; her lyfe) was syngulerly to be cō
               mended
&amp; praysed / wherfore let vs consyder lyke wise
whether in this noble coūtesse may ony thyng lyke be
foūde. Fyrst ye blessyd Martha was a woman of noble
blode to whom by enheritaūce belonged ye castel of bethany / 
&amp; this noblenes of blode they haue which descē
               ded
of noble lygnage. Besyde this there is a noblenes

of maners / withouten whiche the noblenes of bloode
is moche defaced / for as Boecius sayth. Yf oughte be
good in the noblenes of bloode it is for that therby the
noble men and women sholde be ashamed to go out of
kynde from the vertuous maners of theyr auncetrye
before. Yet also there is another noblenes / whiche aryseth
in euery persone by the goodnes of nature / wherby
full often suche as come of ryght pore and vunoble
fader and moder / haue grete abletees of nature / to noble
dedes. Aboue all these same there is a foure maner
of noblenes / whiche may be called an encreased noblenes / 
as by maryage and affynyte of more noble persones
suche as were of lesse condycyon maye encrease
in hyer degre of noblenes. In euery of these I suppose
this coutesse was noble. Fyrst she came of noble blode
lyneally descendynge of kynge Edwarde the .iij. wt
in the .iiij. degre of the same. Her fader was Johan duke
of Somerset her moder was called Margarete ryghte
noble as well in maneres as in bloode. To whome
she was a veray doughter in all noble maners / for
she was bounteous &amp; lyberall to euery persone of her
knowlege or aquayntaunce. Auaryce and couetyse she
moost hated. And sorowed it ful moche in al persones
But specyally in ony yt belonged vnto her. She was
also of synguler casynes to be spoken vnto / &amp; full curtayse
answere she wolde make to all yt came vnto her / 
Of meruayllous gentylnesse she was vnto all folkes / 
but specyally vnto her owne / whom she trusted and loued
ryghte tenderly. Unkynde she wolde not be vnto
no creature / ne forgetefull of ony kyndnes or seruyce
done to her before / whiche is no lytel parte of veray noblenes.
She was not vengeable / ne cruell / but redy anone

to forgete and to forgyue iniuries done vnto her
at ye leest desyre or mocyon made vnto her for ye same.
Mercyfull also &amp; pyteous she was vnto suche as was
greuyd &amp; wrongfully troubled And to them yt were in
pouerty or sekenes or ony other myserye. To god &amp; to
the chirche full obedyent &amp; tractable serchynge his honoure
&amp; pleasure full besyly. A warenes of herself she
had alwaye to eschewe euery thynge yt myght dyshonest
ony noble woman / or dystayne her honour in ony
condycyon. Tryfelous thynges yt were lytell to be regarded
she wolde let passe by / but the other yt were of
weyght &amp; substaūce wherin she myghte prouffyte she
wolde not let for ony payne or laboure to take vppon
hande. These &amp; many other suche noble condycyons
lefte vnto her by her auncetres she kepte &amp; encreased
them with a grete dylygens. The thyrde noblenes also
she wanted not whiche I sayd was ye noblenes of
Nature / she had in maner all yt was praysable in a woman
eyther in soule or in body. Fyrst she was of singuler
wysedome ferre passynge ye comyn rate of women
she was good in remembraūce &amp; of holdyng memorye
A redy wytte she had also to conceyue all thynges. Albeit
they were ryght derke / right studyous she was in
bokes whiche she hadde in grete nombre bothe in Englysshe
&amp; in Frensshe / &amp; for her exercyse &amp; for ye prouffyte
of other she dyde translate dyuers maters of deuocyon
out of Frensshe in to Englysshe. Ful often she
complayned yt in her youthe she had not gyuen her to
ye vnderstondynge of latyn wherin she had a lytell perceyuynge
specyally of ye rubrysshe of ye ordynall for ye
sayeng of her seruyce whiche she dyde wel vnderstande.
Here vnto in fauour / in wordes / in gesture / in euery

demeanour of herself so grete noblenes dyde appere / 
yt what she spake or dyde it meruayllously became
her. The .iiii. noblenes whiche we named a noblenes
goten or encreased she had also. For albeit she of her lynage
were ryght noble / yet neuertheles by maryage / 
&amp; adioynyng of other blode it toke some encreasement
For in her tendre aege she beynge endued wt so grete
towardnes of nature / &amp; lyklyhode of enherytaūce many
sued to haue had her to maryage. The duke of suth
folke whiche thā was a man of grete experyēce moost
dylygently procured to haue had her for his sone and
heyre. Of ye contrary parte kinge Henry ye .vi. dyd make
meanes for Edmonde his broder then therle of Rychemōde.
She whiche as then was not fully .ix. yeres
olde / doutfull in her mynde what she were best to do
asked counsayll of an olde gentylwoman whome she
moche loued &amp; trusted / whiche dyde aduyse her to cō
               mende
herselfe to saynt Nycholas ye patron &amp; helper
of al true maydens / &amp; to beseche him to put in her mȳ
               de
what she were best to do. This coūsayl she folowed
&amp; made her prayer so full often / but specyally yt nyght
whan she sholde ye morowe after make answer of her
mynde determynatly. A meruaylous thing yt same nyghte
as I haue herde her tell many a tyme / as she lay
in prayer callynge vpon saynt Nicholas / whether slepynge
or wakyng she coude not assure / but aboute .iiii
of ye clocke in yt mornȳge one appered vnto her arayed
like a bisshop / &amp; naming vnto her Edmonde had take
hȳ vnto her husbande. And so by this meane she dyde
enclyne her mynde vnto Edmonde ye kinges broder &amp;
erle of Rychemonde. By whom she was made moder
of ye kinge yt deed is / whose soule god ꝑdon / &amp; grandame

to our souerayne lorde kyng Henry ye .viii. whiche
now by ye grace of god gouerneth ye realme. So what
by lygnage what by affinite she had .xxx. kinges &amp; quenes
within ye .iiii. degre of maryage vnto her. Besyde
erles / markyses / dukes / and princes. And thus moche
we haue spoken of her noblenes.
            SEconde ye blessyd Martha is praysed in chastysynge
her body by crysten dyscyplyne / as in abstynence / 
fastyng / sharpe clothes werynge / chastite wt
other. Whiche thing albeit necessary to euery crysten
persone wyllynge to be saued / yet it is moche more to
be praysed in the nobles / hauyng this worldy lyberte
As it was in this noble prynces late deceased whome
my purpose is not vaynly to extol or to magnyfye aboue
her merytes / but to ye edefyenge of other by thexā
               ple
of her. I wold reherce somwhat of her demeanȳg
in this behalue / her sobre temperaūce in metes &amp; drynkes
was knowen to al them yt were conuersaūt wt her
wherin she lay in as grete wayte of herself as ony ꝑsone
myght / kepinge alway her strayte mesure / &amp; offendyng
as lytel as ony creature myght. Eschewȳge bankettes / 
reresoupers / ioncryes betwyxe meales. As for
fastynge for aege &amp; feblenes albeit she were not boūde
yet tho dayes yt by ye chirche were appoynted she kept
them diligently &amp; sereously / &amp; in especyall ye holy lent
thrugh out yt she restrayned her appetyte tyl one mele
&amp; tyl one fysshe on ye day / besyde her other peculer fastes
of deuocion / as saint Anthony / mary Maudeleyn
saynt Katheryn wt other. And thorowe out al ye yere ye
fryday &amp; saterday she full truely obserued. As to harde
clothes wering she had her shertes &amp; gyrdyls of heere / 
whiche whā she was in helth eueri weke she fayled

not certayne dayes to weare somtyme yt one / somtyme
yt other / yt full often her skynne as I herde her say
was perced therwith. As for chastyte thoughe she alway
contynued not in her vyrgynte yet in her husbā
               des
dayes longe tyme before that he deyede she opteyned
of hym lycence &amp; promysed to lyue chast / in the
handes of the reuerende fader my lorde of London / 
whiche promyse she renewed after her husbandes dethe
in to my handes agayne / wherby it may appere ye
dyscyplyne of her body.
            THyrdly ye blessyd Martha is cōmended in orderynge
of her soule to god / by often knelynges / 
by sorowfull wepynges / &amp; by contynual prayers &amp; medytacyons
wherin this noble prynces somwhat toke
her part. Fyrst in prayer euery daye at her vprysynge
whiche comynly was not longe after .v. of ye clock she
began certayne deuocyons / &amp; so after theym wt one of
her gentylwomen ye matynes of our lady / whiche kepte
her to then she came in to her closet / where then wt
her chapelayne she sayd also matyns of ye daye. And after
yt dayly herde .iiij. or .v. masses vpon her knees / soo
contynuynge in her prayers &amp; deuocions vnto ye hour
of dyner / whiche of ye etynge daye was .x. of ye clocke / &amp;
vpon ye fastynge day .xj. After dyner ful truely she wolde
go her stacyons to thre aulters dayly. Dayly her dyryges
&amp; cōmendacyons she wolde saye. And her euensonges
before souper bothe of ye daye &amp; of our lady / besyde
many other prayers &amp; psalters of Dauyd thrugh
out ye yere. And at nyght before she wente to bedde she
faylled not to resorte vnto her chapell / &amp; there a large
quart of an hour to occupye her in deuocyōs. No meruayl
though al this long tyme her knelȳge was to her

paynfull / and so paynfull that many tymes it caused
in her backe payne and dysease. And yet neuertheles
dayly whan she was in helth she faylled not to say the
crowne of our lady whiche after the manere of Rome
conteyneth .lx. and thre aues / and at euery aue to make
a knelynge. As for medytacyon she had dyuers bokes
in Frensshe wherwith she wolde occupy herselfe
whan she was wery of prayer. Wherfore dyuers she
dyde translate oute of Frensshe in to Englysshe. Her
meruayllous wepynge they can bere wytnes of whiche
here before haue herde her confessyon whiche be
dyuers and many / &amp; at many seasons in ye yere lyghtly
euery thyrde daye / can also recorde the same tho ye
were present at ony tyme / whā she was housylde whiche
was ful nye a dosen tymes euery yere: what flodes
of teeres there yssued forth of her eyes / she myght wel
saye. Exitus aquarum deduxerūt oculi mei.
And more ouer to thentente all her werkes myght be
more acceptable and of gretter meryte in the syght of
god suche godly thynges she wolde take by obedyence
whiche obedyence she promysed to the fore named fader
my lorde of London for the tyme of his beynge wt
her. And afterwarde in lyke wyse vnto me whereby it
if may appere the dylygent ordre of her soule to god.
            FOurthe the holy Martha is magnyfyed for her
godly hospytalyte and charytable dealynge to
her neyghbours. Moche besynes there is in kepynge
hospytalyte. And therfore oure lorde sayd vnto her.
Martha martha solicita es &amp; tbarꝭ erga plri.
The housholde seruaūtes muste be put in some good

ordre. The straungers of honeste whiche of theyr curtesy
resorteth for to vysyte the souerayne must be consydered.
And the suters / also whiche cometh compelled
by necessyte to seche helpe &amp; socoure in theyr cause
muste be herde. And the poore &amp; nedy / specyally wold
be releued &amp; conforted. Fyrst her owne houshold with
meruayllous dylygence &amp; wysdome this noble prynces
ordred prouydynge reasonable statutes &amp; ordynaū
               ces
for them / whiche by her offycers she cōmaūded to
be redde .iiij. tymes a yere. And oftentymes by herself
she wolde soo louyngly courage euery of them to doo
well. And somtyme by other meane persones. Yf ony
faccyons or bendes were made secretely amongest her
hede offycers / she wt grete polycye dyde boulte it oute
and lyke wyse yf ony stryfe or contreuersy / she wolde
wt grete dyscrecyon study the reformacyon therof.
            ¶For the straungers / o meruayllous god what payn
what labour she of her veray gentylnes wolde take wt
them to bere them maner and company / &amp; intrete euery
persone. And entertean them accordynge to theyr
degre and hauour / &amp; prouyde by her owne cōmaundement
that nothynge sholde lacke yt myght be conuenyent
for them / wherin she had a wonderfull redy remē
               braūce
&amp; perfyte knowlege.
            ¶For the suters / it is not vnknowen how studyously
she procured Justyce to be admynystred by a long season
so longe as she was suffred. And of her owne charges
prouyded men lerned for the same purpose euenly
&amp; indyfferently to here all causes / and admynystre
ryght and Justyce to euery party / whiche were in no
small nombre. And yet mete and drynke was denyed
to none of them.
            
               
¶For the poore creatures / albeit she dyd not receyue
in to her house our sauyour in his owne persone as ye
blessyd Martha dyde / she neuertheles receyued theim
that dothe represent his persone. Of whome he sayth
hymselfe Quod vni ex minimis meis fecistis
michi fecistis. Poore folkes to ye nombre of .xij. she
dayly and nyghtly kepte in her house / gyuynge them
lodgyng / mete &amp; drynke &amp; clothynge / vysytyng them
as often as she conuenyently myght. And in theyr sykenes
vysytynge them &amp; confortynge them / &amp; mynystrynge
vnto them with her owne handes. And whan
it pleased god to call ony of them out of this wretched
worlde she wolde be presente to se theym departe and
to lerne to deye. And lyke wyse brynge them vnto the
erthe / whiche as Bonauēture affermeth is of gretter
meryte than yf she had done all this to the selfe persone
of our sauyour Ihesu. And ye other seruaūtes and
mynystres of our lorde. Whom she herde were of ony
deuocyon &amp; vertue ful glad she was at al tymes whan
she myght gete theym to whome she wolde lyke wyse
shewe the comforte yt she coude. Suppose not ye that
yf she myghte haue goten our sauyoure Ihesu in his
owne persone / but she wolde as desyrously and as feruently
haue mynystred vnto hym as euer dyde Martha / 
whan thus moche she dyde vntyll his seruaūtes
for his sake.
            ¶Thus it maye appere some comparison of ye blessid
Martha &amp; of this noble prynces whiche was the fyrst
promysed.
            FOr the seconde that is to saye for the complaynynge
&amp; lamentacyon yt the soule of this noble
prynces myghte make for the dethe of her only body.

It is to be consydered that oftentymes in scrypture ye
vertuous and holy faders maketh lamentable exclamacyons
agaynste almyghty god / for that he semeth
to be more indulgent and fauourable vnto ye wycked
persone then vnto the good lyuer. The prophete Dauyd
sayth in this maner. zelaui super iniquos: pa
cem pctō
               
                  
                     
                  
                  rum
                videns. Quia non est respectus
morti eorum nec firmamentū ī plaga eorū.
That is to saye it perceth my stomacke to se the rest &amp;
case that synners often haue It is not loked for ye deth
of them / nor none abydynge stroke or punysshemente
falleth vpon them. The prophete Iheremy sayth also
complaynynge vpon god. Quare via impiorum
prosperatur bene est oībus qui preuaricātur
et inique agunt. Why dothe the wycked persones
prospere in theyr way. wele it is with al them that breke
the lawes / and do wyckedly. The prophet Abacuc
sayth lyke wyse cryenge vpon god. Quare respitis
contemptores et taces conculante nupio iustiorem 
se. why lokest thou fauourably vpon them yt
dyspyse the. And suffrest a synner to bere downe him
that is more ryghtwyse than he is. And the holy-man
Job. Quare ergo īpii viuūt subleuati sūt confortati
qm diuitiis. why then be the wycked persones
suffered for to lyue. They be set alofte / and they be
comforted with rychesse.
            ¶The reason that moueth them thus to murmure &amp;
complayne may be this. There is in almyghty god .ij.
vertues specyally commended &amp; magnyfyed thorowe
out al scrypture. That is to say mercy &amp; ryghtwysnes

And bothe these sholde moue hym rather to be fauourable
vnto the good than vnto ye badde. Fyrst his mercy
sholde moue him therto haue pyte and compassyon
where is the gretter cause of pyte but the greuaunce
trouble and vexacyon of the good persone hath gretter
cause of pyte and is moche more pyteous than of
the euyll persone. wherfore it may be thought that almyghty
god whiche of his owne proprety is mercyful
and redy to gyue mercy. Deus cui proprium est
misereri. He sholde rather shewe his mercy vpon ye
good than vpon the badde. And here vnto his ryghtwysnes
also sholde enclyne hym / for of his ryghtwysnes
he sholde gyue vnto euery persone accordynge to
his deserte. But the good deserueth rather by theyr
goodnes to haue fauoure shewed vnto them then the
badde. Wherfore the holy faders seynge in this world
the wycked in prosperyte And the good in trouble &amp;
aduersite make these complayntes and exclamacions
aboue rehersed agaynst almyghty god and some crye
vpon hym as though he were a slepe. Exurge qua
re obdormis domine. Some other threpe yt he hathe
forgoten theym. Quare obliuisseris in opie
nostre / &amp; tribulationis nostre. Some thȳke there
is noo god at all. Dixit incipiens in corde suo
non est deus. Some weneth at ye leest he is absente
&amp; asketh where he is. Ubi est deustuus. In thys
condycion was ye blessyd woman Martha. She knew
that our sauyour Ihesu was so good and mercyfull / 
And shewed his goodnes generally to al persones / she
byleued faythfully that yf he had be present at ye dethe

of Lazarus her brother whom for his goodnes he loued
so moche he wolde not haue suffred hym to deye.
And therfore she sayd vnto hȳ. Domine si fuisses
hic frater meus nō fuisset mortuus. That is
to saye Syr yf thou had ben presente my brother had
not ben deed. And in lyke maner ye soule of this noble
prȳces whiche had ye body adioyned vnto it in fauour
&amp; loue as syster &amp; brother it myght complayne for the
dethe of ye body / syth euery parte of yt same body had
ben so occupyed in the seruyce of god before. Her eyes
in wepynges &amp; teares somtyme of deuocion somtyme
of repentaunce / hereares herynge the worde of god &amp;
the dyuyne seruyce whiche dayly was kept in her chapell
wt grete nombre of preestes / clerkes and chyldren
to her grete charge &amp; cost / her tongue occupyed in prayer
moche parte of the daye / her legges and fete in vysytynge
the aulters and other holy places goynge her
stacyons customably whan she were not let / her handes
in gyuynge almes vnto the poore and nedye / and
dressynge them also whan they were syke and mynystrynge
vnto them mete and drynke. These mercyfull
and lyberall handes to endure the moost paynful crā
               pes
soo greuously vexynge her and compellynge her
to crye. O blessyd Ihesu helpe me. O blessyd lady socoure
me. It was a mater of grete pyte / lyke a spere it
perced ye hertes of all her true seruaūtes yt was aboute
her &amp; made theym crye also of Ihesu for helpe &amp; socoure
wt grete haboundaūce of teares. But specyally
whan they sawe ye dethe so hast vpon her and that she
must nedes departe from them / and they sholde forgo
so gentyll a maystrts / so tender a lady then wept they

meruayllously / wepte her ladyes and kynnes women
to whom she was full kynde / wepte her poore gentylwomen
whom she had loued so tenderly before / wept
her chamberers to whome she was full deare / wepte
her chapelaynes and preestes / wepte her other true &amp;
faythfull seruauntes. And who wolde not haue wept
that there had ben presente. All Englonde for her dethe
had cause of wepynge. The poore creatures yt were
wonte to receyue her almes / to whome she was alwaye
pyteous and mercyfull. The studyentes of bothe
the vnyuersytees to whome she was as a moder.
All the lerned men of Englonde to whome she was a
veray patronesse. All the vertuous and deuoute persones
to whō she was as a louȳge syster / all ye good relygyous
men and women whom she so often was wont
to vysyte and comforte. All good preestes and clerkes
to whome she was a true defenderesse. All the noble
men and women to whome she was a myrroure and
exampler of honoure. All ye comyn people of this realme
for whom she was in theyr causes a comyn mediatryce / and toke ryght grete dyspleasure for them / and
generally the hole realme hathe cause to complayne &amp;
to morne her dethe. And all we consyderynge her gracyous
and charytable mynde. So vnyuersally &amp; consyderynge
the redynes of mercy and pyte in our sauyour
Ihesu may saye by lamentable complaynt of our
vnwysdome vnto him. Ah domine si fuisses hic
Ah my lorde yf thou hadde ben present and had herde
this sorowfull cryes of her thy seruaunte with the other
lamentable mornȳges of her frendes &amp; seruaūtes
thou for thy goodnes wold not haue suffred her to dye

But thou wolde haue take pyte and compassyon vpō
her. It foloweth in the gospell by the mouthe of Martha.
Sed et nunc scio quia quecū
               
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                poposceris
a deo dabit tibi deus. That is to saye what so
euer thou wylt aske of god thy fader I knowe wel he
wyll graunte it vnto the. who may doubte but ye sone
of god of whome saynt Poule sayth. In diebus
carnis sue preces et supplicationes / offerens
exauditus est pro sua reuerētia. That is to saye
in the dayes of his mortalite whan he was mortall here
in erthe yet neuertheles he was herde of almyghtye
god in his prayer and askynge / his fader for his reuerente
behauoure. Who may doubte but moche rather
now he shall be herde whan he is in soo gloryous maner
aboue in heuen. And there presente before the face
of his fader for our cause as sayeth saynt Paule. In
troiuit ipse celum vt appareat vultui dei ꝓ
nobis. He hathe entred the heuen to appere before ye
vysage of his fader for vs / to shewe the woundes whiche
he dyde suffre for the delyueraunce of vs from syn
Yf in his mortall body he prayed &amp; asked forgyuenes
for his enmyes that crucefyed him and cruelly put hȳ
vnto the dethe. And yet neuertheles he opteyned hys
petycyon for them. Moche rather it is to suppose that
he shal opteyne his askynge her that had so often compassyon
of his blessyd passyon / and dyd bere it so often
in her remembraunce as dyd this noble prynces. Thā
for his mortal enmyes whiche were many and but vylaynes / 
he prayed vndesyred of only / he let not so to do
by ye greuous paynes of dethe whiche he there suffred
Nowe therfore he beyng in so grete glorye aboue and

at all lyberte. Yf all we call &amp; crye vpon hym prayer
for this one soule of this moost noble prynces whiche
was his faythfull &amp; true seruaunt. Who maye thynke
but yt he for his infynyte goodnes wyll haue mercye
there vpon. We wyll not craue vpon him yt he shal restore
the body agayne to lyfe / as he dyde the body of lazarus / 
we muste be contente wt the dethe of it / &amp; lerne
therby to prepayre our owne bodyes to ye same poynt
within shorte tyme. But we shall wt moost entyer mindes
beseche hym to accepte yt swete soule to his grete
mercy to be parteyner of yt euerlastynge lyfe wt hym &amp;
wt his blessyd sayntes aboue in heuen / whiche I pray
you al nowe affectually to praye / &amp; for her now at this
tyme moost deuoutly to say one Pater noster.
            FYrst ye haue herde ye goodly condicyons of this
noble prynces whome we dyde resemble vnto
the blessyd woman Martha. Ye haue herde also in the
ij. place a pyteous complaynt of the parte of her soule
for the dethe of her body made vnto our sauyour Ihū
Nowe wyll I rememembre ye comfortable answer of
our mercyfull sauyoure agayne vnto her wherof we
all may be gretely comforted &amp; take cause &amp; matere of
grete reioysynge. It foloweth in the gospell. Dixit
ei iesus resurget frater tuus. That is to saye in
Englysshe. Ihesu sayd vnto her / thy broder shal ryse
agayne. I said before that consyderynge the loue and
amyte that is betwyxe the soule &amp; the body they maye
be thought to be as broder and syster. A trouthe it is
the soules that be hens departed out of theyr bodyes / 

haue neuertheles a natural desyre and appetyte to be
knytte &amp; ioyned wt them agayne / whiche thinge not onely
the theologyens wytnesse / but ye phylosophers also.
A grete comforte then it is vnto the soule yt hath so
longynge desyre vnto the body to here yt the body shal
ryse agayne. And specyally in yt maner &amp; forme of rysynge / 
wherof saynt Poule speketh in this wyse. Se
minat in corruptione: surget in incorruptione.
Seīatur in ignobilitate: surget in gloria.
Seīatur ī infirmitate: surget in vtute. Seīa
tur corpus aīale surget corpus spūale. Foure
condycyons ye body hathe whan it dyeth &amp; is put in to
the groūde. Fyrst it anone begynneth to putrefye &amp; resolue
in to foule corrupcyon. The ayre dothe alter it:
the grounde dothe moyste it / the wormes dothe brede
of it &amp; fede also. Seconde it is vyle &amp; lothely to behold
&amp; ryght vngoodly to ye syght. Thyrde it is vnweldy / &amp;
not of power to styre itself or to be conuayed from place
to place. Fourth it is so grosse yt it occupyeth a row
me &amp; kepeth a place &amp; letteth other bodyes to be presēt
in ye same place. Agaynst these four ye bodyes of them
yt shall be saued shall take at theyr rysynge agayne .iiij
other excellent gyftes. Agaynst ye fyrste it shall be in yt
condicion yt neyther ye ayre / ne ye water / ne fyre / ne knife / 
nor wepen nor stroke / nor sekenes shall anoye it.
            Agaynst ye .ij. it shall ryse bryght &amp; gloryous and in ye
moost goodly &amp; beauteous manere. Agaynst ye thyrde
it shall be more nymble &amp; more redy to be conuayed to
ony place where ye soule wolde haue it then is ony swalowe.
Agaynst the .iiij. it shall be subtyle yt it shall perce
thorowe the stone walles without ony anoyaūce of

them. This shall be a farre dyfference &amp; a grete dyuersyte
of her body as she had it before / and as she shall in
conclusyon receyue it agayne. But yet me thinke I se
what the soule of this noble pryncesse may answere agayne somwhat to lesse &amp; to mynysshe this dysconfort
after the same maner that Martha dyde answere vnto
our sauyour Ihesu. Scio ꝙ resurget in resurrectione
in nouissimo die. That is to say I knowe
well yt it shall ryse agayne in the laste daye of ye general
resurreccyon / but yt is farre hens / that is long to
come. Et spes que diffentur affligit animam.
And the hope of a thynge delayed tormenteth ye soule
in the meane tyme. Therfore our sauyour more comfortable
answereth to her agayne &amp; sayth in this maner.
Ego sum resurrectio &amp; vita. That is. I am
sayth he the veray cause of raysynge of the body. And
I am also the veraye cause of lyfe vnto the soule. As
who saye tho the rysynge of the body be delayed for a
season / the soule neuertheles shal for the meane tyme
haue a pleasaunt &amp; a swete lyfe. A lyfe full of comfort
a lyfe full of ioye &amp; pleasure / a lyfe voyde of all sorow
&amp; encombraūce / a lyf not lyke vnto ye lyfe of this wretched
world whiche is alway entermelled wt moche bitternes / 
eyther with sorowes / eyther wt dredes or elles
with perylles. In hoc mundo non dolere nō timere
non periclitari impossibile est. Sayeth
saynt Austyn. It is impossyble to lyue in this worlde
&amp; not to sorowe / not to drede / not to be in peryl. This
same noble prynces yf she had contynued in this worlde
she sholde dayly haue herde &amp; sene mater &amp; cause of
sorowe as well in herselfe as in her frendes parauenture.

Her body dayly sholde haue waxen more unweldy / 
her syght sholde haue be derked / and her herynge
sholde haue dulled more and more / her legges sholde
haue faylled her by &amp; by. And all the other partyes of
her body waxe more crased euery daye / whiche thynges
sholde haue ben mater to her of grete dyscomforte
And albeit these thinges had not fallen vnto her forth
with / yet she sholde haue lyued alwaye in a drede and
a fere of them. Dare I say of her she neuer yet was in
that prosperyte but the gretter it was ye more alwaye
she dredde the aduersyte. For whan the kynge her sone
was crowned in all yt grete tryumphe &amp; glorye / she
wepte meruayllously. And lyke wyse at the grete tryumphe
of the maryage of prynce Arthur. And at the
laste coronacyon wherin she had full grete Joye / she
let not to saye yt some aduersyte wolde folowe / so that
eyther she was in sorowe by reason of the present aduersytes / 
or elles whan she was in prosperite she was
in drede of ye aduersyte for to come. I passe ouer ye perylles
&amp; daungers innumerable whiche dayly &amp; hourly
myght haue happed vnto her wherof this lyf is ful
And therfore saynt Gregory sayth. Uita hec terrena
eterne vite comparata mors est potius di cenda
quam vita. And for that cause who yt ones
hathe tasted the pleasures of yt lyfe / this is vnto them
a veray dethe for euer after. Example of Lazarꝰ whiche
after yt he was restored to ye myseryes of this lyfe
agayne / he neuer lough but was in contynuall heuynes
and pensyfnesse. Now therfore wolde I aske you
this one questyon. Were it not suppose ye al this considerd
a meetly thȳg for vs to desyre to haue this noble
princes here amōgest vs agayn to forgo ye ioyous lyfe

aboue to wante ye presence of ye gloryous trynyte whō
she so longe hathe sought &amp; honoured to leue yt moost
noble kyngdome to be absent frome the moost blessyd
company of sayntes &amp; sayntesses &amp; hether to come agayn
to be wrapped &amp; endaūgered with ye mysteres of
this wretched worlde / wt the paynfull dyseases of her
aege / wt the other encomberaunces yt dayly happethe
in this myserable lyfe. Were this a reasonable request
of oure partye / were this a kynde desyre / were this a
gentyl wysshel yt where she hathe ben so kinde &amp; louȳg
a maystresse vnto vs / all we sholde more regarde our
owne prouffytes then her more synguler wele &amp; comforte.
The moder yt hathe so grete affeccyon vnto her
sone yt she wyll not suffre hym to departe from her to
his promocyon &amp; furtheraūce but alway kepe hym at
home / more regardynge her owne pleasure than hys
wele / were not she an vnkinde &amp; vngentyl moder / yes
verayly / let vs therfore thȳke our moost louyng maystres
is gone hens for her promocyon / for her grete furtheraunce / 
for her moost wele &amp; prouffyte. And herin
comforte vs / herin reioyse ourselfe &amp; thanke almyghty
god whiche of his infynyte mercy so gracyously hathe
dysposed for her. But ye wyll say vnto me. Syr yf
yf We were sure of this we wolde not be sory / but be
ryght hertly glad &amp; ioyous therfor As for suerte veray
suerte can not be had but only by ye reuelacyon of god
almighty. Neuertheles as farre as by scrypture / this
thȳge can be assured in thende of this gospel folowingly
iz made by our sauyour a stronge argument almost
demōstratyue of this same thynge / ye argumēt is this.
Euery persone yt putteth theyr full truste in cryst Ihū
               
Albeit they be deed in theyr bodyes yet shall they neuertheles
haue lyfe in theyr soules / &amp; that lyf yt neuer
shall haue ende. But this noble prynces she put her ful
truste in cryste▪ Ihesu verayly byleuynge that he was
the sone of god &amp; came in to this worlde for ye redempcyon
of synners / wherfore it must necessaryly folowe
yt albeit her body be deed her soule is in yt ioyous lyfe
yt neuer shall cease. The fyrste parte of this argument
foloweth in ye gospell. Qui credit in me etiam simortuus
fuerit viuet. That is to say who yt fully
trusteth in cryst Ihū / albeit they be deed in theyr bodies / 
they neuertheles shal lyue in theyr soules. But yet
we wante a lytell I sayd more than this. I saw yt lyfe
shall neuer haue ende / &amp; for this also it foloweth. Et
oēs 
                  
                     
                  
                  qui
                viuit &amp; credit ī me nō 
               moriet ineternū.
That is to saye euery persone yt hathe this lyfe &amp; this
full trust in Ihesu shall neuer dye. So here appereth
well yt fyrst parte of our argument. For ye .ij. part now
yt this noble prynces had full fayth in Ihesu cryste it
may appere yf ony wyll demaūde this questyon of her
yt our sauyour demaūded of Martha / he sayd to her / 
Credis hoc. Byleuist yu this? what is yt / that this gē
               tylwoman
wolde not byleue / she yt ordeyned .ij. contynual
reders in bothe ye vnyuersytes to teche ye holy dyuynyte
of Ihesu / she yt ordeyned prechers perpetuall
to publysshe yt doctryne &amp; fayth of cryste Ihesu / she yt
buylded a college royall to ye honour of ye name of crist
Ihesu / &amp; lefte tyll her executours another tobe buylded
to mayntayn his fayth &amp; doctryne. Besyde al this
foūded in ye monastery of westmynster where her body
lyeth thre prestes to praye for her perpetually. She

whom I haue many tymes herde saye yt yf ye crysten
prynces wolde haue warred vpon the enmyes of his
faith she wold be glad yet to go folowe ye hoost &amp; helpe
to wasshe theyr clothes for ye loue of Ihū / she yt openly
dyde wytnesse this same thynge at ye houre of her dethe / 
whiche saynge dyuers here presente can recorde
how hertly she answered whan ye holy sacrament contaynȳge
ye blessid Ihū in it was holden before her / &amp; ye
questyon made vntyl her whether she byleued yt there
was verayly ye sone of god yt suffred his blessyd passyō
for her &amp; for all mankynde vpon ye crosse. Many here
can bere recorde how wt all her herte &amp; soule she raysed
her body to make answere there vnto / &amp; confessed assuredly
yt in yt sacrament was conteyned cryst Ihesu
ye sone of god yt dyed for wretched sȳners vpon ye crosse
in whom holly she put her truste &amp; confydence / these
same wordes almoost yt Martha confessed in the ende
of this gospell. Ego credidi quia tu es christus
filius dei qui ī mūdū venisti. That is to saye I
haue byleued yt thou art cryst ye sone of gad whiche came
in to this worlde. And so sone after yt she was aneled
she departed &amp; yelded vp her spyryte in to ye handes
of our lorde / who may not nowe take euydent lyklyhode
&amp; coniecture vpon this yt the soule of this noble woman
whiche so studyously in her lyf was occupyed in
good werkes / &amp; with a faste fayth of cryst / &amp; the sacramentes
of his chirche was defended in yt houre of departynge
out from ye body was borne vp in to ye countre
aboue wt ye blessyd aūgelles deputed &amp; ordeyned to
yt holy mystery. For yf ye herty prayer of many ꝑsones
Yf her owne contynuall prayer in her lyf tyme. yf ye sacramētes
of ye chirche orderly taken. yf indulgences &amp;

pardons graūted by diuers popes / yf true repentaūce
&amp; teeres / yf fayth &amp; deuocyon in criste Ihesu / yf charyte
to her neyghbours / yf pyte vpon ye poore / yf forgyuenes
of iniuries / or yf good werkes be auaylable / as
doubtles they be / grete lyklyhode &amp; almoost certayne
coniecture we may take by them / &amp; all these yt soo it is
in dede. Therfore put we asyde all wepynge &amp; teeres / 
&amp; be not sad ne heuy as men withouten hope / but rather
be we gladde &amp; ioyous / &amp; eche of vs herin con
                  •
               ort
other. Alwaye praysynge &amp; magnyfyenge the name of
oure lorde / to whome be laude and honoure endlesly
Amen.
         
      
      
         
            ¶Thus endeth this lamentable mornynge. Enprynted
at London in Flete strete at the sygne of the sonne
by Wynkyn de Worde.
            
               W
                     〈☐☐☐☐〉
                  C
            
            wynkyn .de. worde.
            
         
      
   

