
   
      
         
            Here begynneth a ryght frutefull mater: and hath to name the boke of surueyeng and improume[n]tes
            Book of surveying
            Fitzherbert, John, d. 1531.
         
         
            
               1523
            
         
         Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00895
            STC 11005
            ESTC S112253
            99847511
            99847511
            12548
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00895)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12548)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 42:10)
         
         
            
               
                  Here begynneth a ryght frutefull mater: and hath to name the boke of surueyeng and improume[n]tes
                  Book of surveying
                  Fitzherbert, John, d. 1531.
                  Fitzherbert, Anthony, Sir, 1470-1538.
                  Berthelet, Thomas. aut
               
               [7], lvi, [1] leaves : ill.  
               
                  In fletestrete by Rycharde Pynson, printer to the kynges noble grace,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  The yere of our lorde god. M.D.xxiii. the. xv. day of Iuly. [1523]]
               
               
                  By John Fitzherbert. Sometimes also attributed to Sir Anthony Fitzherbert.
                  Place of publication and printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.
                  Woodcut illustrations on title page and m3v.
                  Running title reads: Extenta manerii.
                  Editions with this title include commendatory verses by Thomas Berthelet.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Agriculture --  England --  Early works to 1800.
               Landlord and tenant --  England --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-08
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-11
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-11
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶Here begynneth a ryght frutefull mater: and hath to name the boke of ſurueyeng and improumētes.
            
               
            
         
         
            
            
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶Hereafter foloweth the table of this preſent treatyſe / and the chapiters of an olde ſtatute called Extenta manerii.
            
               
                  
                     FIrſt the prologue of the authour / for the declaracyon of this preſent treatyſe. ¶Of caſtelles and other buyldynges / what the walles / the tymbre / the ſtonne / the leed / the ſclate / the tyle / or other of couerynges is worthe by the yere / aſwell within ye walles as without. And alſo of gardeyns / curtylages / dofehouſes / and all other profytes be worthe by the yere. Capitulo primo.
                  ¶Howe many feldes are of the demayns / and howe many acres are in euery Felde / and what an acre is worthe by the yere. Cap. ſecundo.
                  ¶Howe many acres of medowe are of the demeyns and howe moche euery acre is worthe / and to what maner of catell it is mooſt neceſſary vnto / and howe many beeſtes it wyll fynde / and what the paſture of a beeſt is worthe by the yere. Cap. tertio.
                  ¶Of forrayne paſtures that be cōmen / howe many and of what maner of catell the lorde may haue in the ſame / and what the paſture of a beeſt is worthe by the yere. &amp;c. Capitulo quarto.
                  ¶Of parkes and demayne woodes / the whiche the lorde maye aſſarte and to do his profyte / and howe many acres they cōtayne / and what the veſture of an

acre is worthe / &amp; what the grounde is worthe whan the veſture is fallen. Cap. v.
                  ¶Of forren woodes where other men haue cōmen / wheder the lorde maye improwe himſelfe therof and of howe many acres / and what the veſtur of an acre is worthe / and what the grounde is worthe whan the woode is fallen / and howe many acres they cōtayne and what an acre is worthe by the yere. Cap. vi.
                  ¶Wheder the lorde maye gyue or ſell the reſydue of his forreyne woodes / and what ſuche gyfte or ſale is worthe. &amp;c. Cap. vii.
                  ¶Of panage and herbage of the towne / and of all other profytes of pooles / meyres / and rynnynge waters: of moores / heythes / and waſtes / what they be worthe by the yere. Cap. viii.
                  ¶Of mylnes / ſeuerall fyſſhinges / &amp; cōmen fyſſhinges / what they be worthe by the yere. Cap. ix.
                  ¶Of free tenauntes / the whiche dwell without as well as within. &amp;c. Cap. x.
                  ¶Who be free tenauntes and what landes and tenementes &amp; what fees they holde and by what ſeruyce / wheder by ſoccage or by knight ſeruyce or other maner / and what rent of Aſſiſe they gyue by the yere / &amp; who holdeth by chartoure and who by Auncyent demeyne / and who by newe feoffement. Cap. xi.
                  ¶Of ſurrenders / and dyuers maners of makynge of copyes. &amp;c. Fo. xiiii.
                  ¶The othes of all maner of officers gen̄ally. fo. xx.
                  ¶Of dyuers maner of rentes. &amp;c. Fo. xxi.
                  ¶Of thoſe free tenaūtes that ſewe in the court of the

countie and who ſeweth nat / and howe moche falleth to the lorde after ye deceſſe of ſuche tenaūtes. cap. xii.
                  ¶Howe many cuſtomary tenaūtes there be &amp; howe moche euery of them holdeth / and what werkes and cuſtomes they do / and what the werkes and ye cuſtomes of euery tenaunt is worthe by the yere / &amp; howe moche rent euery of them payeth / ouer the cuſtomes and werkes. &amp;c. Cap. xiii.
                  ¶Of cotyers / what Cotages and curtylages they holde and by what ſeruyce / and howe moche rente they paye by the yere. Cap. xiiii.
                  ¶Of perqueſytes or profytes of counties / of courtes / and of foreſtes / what they be worthe. Cap. xv.
                  ¶Of churches that belong to the gyfte of the lorde / howe many there be and where they be / and what euery churche is worthe. Cap. xvi.
                  ¶What the herryottes be worthe / the feyres / exchetes / cuſtomes / ſeruyces / and forreyne warkes: The plees and perqueſytes of the courtes / fynes / relefes / and all other thynges that maye falle to the lorde by the yere. Cap. xvii.
               
               ¶Explicit capitula ſtatuti.
            
            
               
                  
                     OF dyuers maners of takyng and doyng of homage and fealtie. Cap. xviii.
                  ¶What a ſurueyour ſhulde do. Cap. xix.
                  ¶Howe a manne ſhulde viewe / butte and bounde / the manere and the townſhyppes. Cap. xx.
                  ¶Howe to but and bounde the feldes. Cap. xxi.
                  ¶Howe to but &amp; bounde the medowes. Cap. xxii.
                  
                     ¶Howe to butte and bounde paſtures. Cap. xxiii.
                  ¶Howe to amende errable lande. Cap. xxiiii.
                  ¶Howe a man ſhulde mēde his medowes. ca. xxv.
                  ¶Howe to amende and make better dyuers maner of paſtures / and firſt of lowe grounde lyke medowe grounde. Cap. xxvi.
                  ¶Howe to amende ley grounde that hath ben errable lande of late. Cap. xxvii.
                  ¶Howe to amende buſſhy groūde and moſſye / that hath ben errable of olde tyme. Cap. xxviii.
                  ¶Howe to amende buſſhy grounde that was neuer errable lande. Cap. xxix.
                  ¶Howe to amende woode grounde / that lyeth in ſeuerall paſture. Cap. xxx.
                  ¶Howe to amende gorſty grounde that hath ben errable lande. Cap. xxxi.
                  ¶Howe to amende gorſty grounde that was neuer errable lande. Cap. xxxii.
                  ¶Howe to amende brome grounde. Cap. xxxiii.
                  ¶Howe to amende heyth grounde. Cap. xxxiiii.
                  ¶Howe to amende marres grounde. Cap. xxxv.
                  ¶Howe to amēde bromy groūde &amp; ferny. ca. xxxvi.
                  ¶Of chylturne grounde / flyntie grounde / &amp; chalke grounde. cap. xxxvii.
                  ¶Of lyme ſtonne grounde. Cap. xxxviii.
                  ¶What profites may come or growe to the lorde by reaſon of his waters. cap. xxxix.
                  ¶Of dyuers maner of mylnes. cap. xl.
                  ¶Howe to make a towneſhippe that is worthe .xx. marke a yere worthe twentie pounde. cap. xli.
               
            
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            
            
               
¶Tho. Berthelet to the reders of this lytell boke.
            
               
                  REde this boke / with the other of huſbandry
               And ye ſhall fynde them very profytable
               Good / behouefull / and moche neceſſary
               To my mynde they be right commendable
               It is nat a ieſt / a tale / nor a fable:
               It is ſuche mater (ye may beleue me)
               As noble clerkes wrote / in olde antiquyte.
            
            
               
               ¶The worthy Caton / that excellent romayne
               Columella / Varro / and Vergilius
               Of huſbandrie to write / had in no diſdayne
               Nor many other / eloquent and famous
               Thought it nat a thynge inglorious
               Suche mater to write / wherby they might auaūce
               The cōmon welthe. And theyr countre enhaunce.
            
            
               ¶But in our dayes / ſome are blynded ſo withfolly
               That they count huſbandrie / but a thing right vyle
               Some had leauer write of loue. ye of baudry
               Than to ſo good a mater tourne their ſtyle
               Fonde pleaſure and pride do them ſo begyle
               That ſlouthe wandreth about in euery way
               And good buſyneſſe is fallyng in decay.
            
            
               ¶yet neuertheleſſe / good labour to call agayne
               In welthy buſyneſſe / men to exercyſe
               This worthy man / nobly hath done his payne
               I meane hym / that theſe ſayde bokes dyd deuyſe
               He ſheweth to huſbandes / in right frutefulwyſe
               The manyfolde good thynges / in brefe ſentence
               Whiche he hath well proued / by long experyence.
            
            
               ¶And this I leaue hym / in his good wyll &amp; mynde
               That he beareth / vnto the publyke weale
               Wolde god noble men / coude in their hertes fynde
               After ſuche forme / for the cōmons helth to deale
               It is a true token / of hyghe loue and zeale
               Whan he ſo delyteth / and taketh pleaſure
               By his buſy labour / mens welth to procure.
            
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            
            ¶The prologue of the authour / for the declaracyon of this preſent treatyſe.
            
               SAlomon ſapientie Primo. Omnis ſapientia virtus / honor / dignitas / et que
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſcientia a dn̄o deoſunt. That is to ſay: all wyſdome vertue / honoure / dignyte / and cunnyng / are of our lorde god. Than ſithe almighty god our redemer &amp; creatour / by high wyſdome / goodneſſe / lyberalite / and prouydence / in this tranſitorie worlde and myſerable lyfe: Hath ordayned dyuers eſtates and degrees in his people &amp; creatures / and ſome of them: aſwell hath endowed with gooſtly and heuēly wiſdome and diſtynke graces / as with great honour / poſſeſſyons / and rycheſſe with great gyftes &amp; graces / aſwell ſpirytuall as temporall. His highe cōmaundement / chargeth euery ꝑſon that is ꝑtaker of the ſayd gyftes or graces / charritably and diſcretely / the ſame to diſtrybute and deuyde among his poore creatures / That euery poore perſone that is wyllynge to laboure duely for his lyuyng / may haue therby conuenyent helpe and ſuſteynaunce. And in as moche as the great eſtates / rulers and gouernours of this realme / whom our ſauyour hath ſo largely and bountuouſly rewarded / with all ſuche gyftes / poſſeſſyons / and rycheſſe: haue accordyng to his pleaſure and cōmaundement / demyſed / 

diſtrybute / and graūted to the creatures of god. and to their fermours and tenauntes / their ſeuerall poſſeſſyons and inherytaunces / reſeruynge to them for the ſame certayne rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / to ſuſtayne and vpholde their honours and eſtates / as to them apertayneth / acordyng to their highe gyftes and graces / wherwith they be ſo largety endowed. And for the great zele / loue / and confort that I beare to the ſayd fermours and tenauntes / and to all other goddes creatures: that they may more ſurely / eaſely and profitably encreaſe and ſuſtayne their pore houſholde / wyues / and chyldren: and alſo truely to paye their rentes cuſtomes / and ſeruyces vnto their lordꝭ and the honoures of their fermes and tenauntryce. Of late by experyence / I contryued / compyled / and made a treatiſe for the ſame poore fermers and tenā
               tes / and called it the boke of Huſbandrie: the whiche me ſemed was very neceſſary for huſbande men that vſe tyllage / &amp; for many other of dyuers degrees and occupacyons. And where as in the prologue of the ſayd boke I demaunded and aſked a queſtyon / and that was this. Whervnto is euery man ordayned as playnely it dothe appere in the prologue of the ſame In lyke maner in the prologue of this treatiſe / ye whiche I entende by the ſuffraūce and helpe of our lorde Ieſu / to contryue / compyle / and make to the profyte of all noble men and women bothe ſpyrituall &amp; temporall / I demaunde another queſtyon / and that is this. Howe &amp; by what maner / do all theſe great eſtates and noblemen and women lyue and maynteyne

their honour and degre? and in myne opinyon / their honour and degre is vpholden and maynteyned / by reaſon of their rentes / iſſues / reuenewes / and profytes that come of their maners / lordſhippes / landes &amp; tenementes to them belongyng. Than it is neceſſarye to be knowen / howe all theſe maners / lordſhips / landes / &amp; tenementꝭ ſhulde be extēded / ſurueyed / butted / boūded / and valued in euery parte: that the ſaid eſtates ſhulde nat be diſceyued / defrauded / nor diſhe ryted of their poſſeſſyons / rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / the whiche they haue to thē reſerued / for mayn teynaunce of their eſtates and degrees. And yt there be no parcell therof loſt nor imbeſelde / and than may the lorde of ye ſayd maners / lordſhippes / landes / and tenementes / haue parfyte knowledge where the landelyeth. What euery parcell is worthe / and who is his freholders / copyeholders / cuſtomarye tenaunte / or tenaunt at his wyll. And what rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruice he ought to haue of them / with many moartycles / as here after ſhalbe declared. Wherefore it is neceſſary that euery great eſtate / bothe men &amp; women of worſhip / that haue great poſſeſſyons of landes and tenementes / ſhulde haue a Surueyour that can extende / but / and bounde / and value them. And therof to make a boke in parchement / bearyng a certayne date / after the maner &amp; forme as I ſhall make an intytulynge / and to amende it where he ſemethe conuenyent. Quia facilius eſt addere quam de nouo facere. That is for to ſaye / It is lighter to adde / refourme / or correcte / thanne for to make newe and

perfyte. And the Surueyour to leaue the ſayd boke made by hym with his lorde in maner of a regyſter / whervnto the ſame Surueyour or another offycer / maye alway haue reſort / whan nede ſhall requyre to loke vpon. And that boke ſo truely made / maye be a regyſter and ſure euydence: that the lorde / his freholders / copye holders / nor tenauntes / ſhall neuer loſe landes nor rentes / cuſtomes / nor ſeruyces: but euery man that redeth the boke / ſhall ꝑfitely knowe where the lādes lye / whoſe it was at the day of the makyng of the ſayd boke / and whoſe it is. Than if the owner make a true pee / degre / or cōueyaunce / by diſcente or by purchace vnto the ſaid landes or lordſhippes. and ſpecially if the names of the lordes and tenaūtes that occupy / might be renewed ones ī fourtie or threſcore yeres. for than it wolde be as a perpetuall and ſure euydēce for euer / to put away all ſtrife and varyaūce bytwene lorde and lorde / lorde and tenaunt / tenaunt and tenaunt / in good quyetneſſe &amp; peace. But of one thyng I pronounce and declare / and take god to my recorde: that I make this boke all onely / to thentent that the lordes / the freholders nor their heyres ſhuld
nat be diſheryt / nor haue their landes loſt nor imbeſelde nor encroched by one from another / and to non other entent. And for that I aduertyſe and exorte on goddes behalfe / all maner of perſons as well lordes as other. That whan the lordꝭ or freholders / knowe where their landes lye and what euery paſture or ꝑcell is worthe by the yere. That the lordes nor the owners therof do nat heyghten their rentes of their tenauntes

/ or to cauſe them to pay more rent or a gretter fyne / than they haue ben acuſtomed to do in tyme paſt. For as me ſemeth / a gretter charyte nor almes dede a man may nat well do / than vpon his owne tenauntes. And alſo to the contrarie / a gretter bribery nor extorcyon a man can nat do / than vpon his owne tenaūtes / for they dare nat ſay nay nor yet cōplayne / and therfore on their ſoules go it that ſo do and nat on myne. Parauēture the lorde wyll ſay it is nat his dede it was his Surueyours / but that can nat be ſo for ſaynt Auguſtyne ſaythe. Qui ꝑ alium facit per ſeipſum facere videtur. That is to ſay: he that commaūdeth another man to do a thyng he dothe it hym ſelfe. And there be two princypals in one acte doyng and alſo he ſaythe. Conſenſcientes et agētes pari pena puniantur. That is to ſay / the conſentours and the doers ſhall be lyke punyſſhed. at grammer ſcole I lerned a vers and that is this. Dum poteris quid vis poſſis cognoſcere quid ſis. That is to ſay / whan thou mayſt do what thou wylte / thou mayſt knowe what thou arte. that is to wytte / good or yuell. But for a grounde of this treatyſe the whiche I do note / and calle it the boke of Surueyng and of improuementes / I do take an olde ſtatute named Extenta manerii / as a principall groūde therof: as herafter enſueth.
            ¶Explicit.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶Of caſtels and other byldinges / what the walles / tymbre / ſtone / leed / ſclate / tyle / or other of couerynges is worthe: aſwell within the walles as without. And alſo of gardens / curtylages / douehouſes / &amp; all other profytes be worthe by the yere. &amp;c. Capitulo primo.
            
               
                  INquirend eſt de caſtris et etiam aliis edificiis foſſatꝭ circū
               datis quātum muri et edificia ligna et lapidia / plumbo / &amp; alio modo cooꝑta valent et pro quāto appreciari poterunt ſcdm verum valorem eorūdem murorum et edificia. et quātum edificis extra foſſatis appreciari poſſunt / et quantū valeant vna cū gardinis / curtilagiis columbar / et omnibus aliis exitibus cur per annū. This is to ſay in Englyſſhe. It is to be enquered of caſtels / and alſo of other buyldinges dyched about. What the walles / the byldinges / tymbre / ſtone / leed / and other maner of couerynge is worthe. And howe they maye be ſolde / after the very value of the ſame walles and bylding. And howe moche the bildinges without the dyche maye beſolde for / &amp; what they be worthe / with the gardens / curtylages / douehouſes / and all other iſſues of the courte by the yere. To the declaracyon and conſtructyon of this ſtatute / me ſemeth there ought to be made a diſtynction / for ye ſtatute

gothe generally. De caſtris et aliis edificiis foſſatis et circundatis et extra foſſatis. Theſe wordes go aſwell to thoſe caſtelles and other byldinges that be well vpholden and inhabyted / as well as of thoſe that be fallen in dekay and nat inhabyted / &amp; to thoſe that be inhabyted. It is nat neceſſarie to be extēded nor valewed in any parcell / For lette a man make a caſtell / towre / or any maner of newe buyldinges and finyſſhe it clerely / if he ſhulde go take it downe / and ſelle euery thyng by it ſelfe agayne / he ſhulde loſe the more halfe of his money. And therfore in myne opynion / this ſtatute was made ſoone after the barones war / the whiche ended at the bataile of Eueſſham or ſoone after / in the tyme of kynge Henry the thirde / where as many noble men of blode were ſlayne and many fledde / that afterwarde were attaynted for the treaſon they dyde to the kyng. and by reaſon therof / their caſtelles and maners were ſeaſed in to the kynges handes. And ſo for want of reparacyons / the caſtels and the maners fell to ruyne and in dekay. And whanne the kyng and his counſayle ſawe that / they thought it was better to extende them and make the mooſt profyte that they coulde of them / than to lette them to fall to the grounde / and come to no mannes helpe and profyte. Wherfore kyng Edwarde the firſt ordayned this ſtatute to be made the fourthe yere of his raygne / wherin is cōtayned many &amp; dyuers chapiters and artycles / the whiche at that tyme was but inſtructyons / howe &amp; what they ſhulde do / that were commyſſioners or ſurueyours in the ſame.
            
               ¶Firſt it is moſte neceſſary &amp; conuenient to retayle and to ſell euery thyng by it ſelfe / and nat all in groſe ſome to one man &amp; ſome to another. For that that is good for one man is nat good for another: and euery thing to be prayſed and ſolde by it ſelfe / that is to ſay The ſtone wall of one houſe by it ſelfe / the tymbre of the ſame houſe by it ſelfe / the coueryng by it ſelfe / the tyle / ſclate / or leed by it ſelfe / the glaſſe by it ſelfe. the yron ware / as barres / bandes / hokes / boltes / ſtaples or latches / and all ſuche other by themſelfe: doores / wyndowes / boordes / and all other thynges by them ſelfe / and to go fro houſe to houſe &amp; ſell euery thynge by it ſelfe / and than ſhall the trewe value be beſt knowen. And it is conuenyent that theſe thynges be offred to be ſolde to dyuers men and to ſe who wyll gyue moſt / and ſpecially to ſell whan men deſyre to bye. Alſo to value what the graſſe of the gardens / curtylages / courtes / and houſe places / that be within the dycheſſe or without be worth by the yere. A curtylage is a lytell croft or court / or place of eaſment to put in catell for a tyme / or to ley in woode / cole / or tymbre / or ſuche other thynges neceſſary for houſholde. Alſo to value the profyte of the douehouſe if any be there / yf it be replenyſſhed with doues.
         
         
            ¶Howe many feldes are of the demeynes / and howe many acres are in euery felde / and what an acre is worthe by the yere. &amp;c. Cap. ſecundo.
            
               
               ITem inquirend eſt quot campiſunt in dn̄ico &amp; quot acre ſunt in campo et quā
               tū valet q̄libet acra ꝑ ſe per annū. It is to be inquered / how many feldes are of the demeyns and howe many acres are in euery felde / and what euery acre is worthe by the yere. This is a lyght letter and nedeth but lytell declaracyon / for by theſe wordes / quot campi ſunt in dn̄ico. It muſt nedes be taken of feldes that be in tyllage or plowyng / but it wolde be vnderſtande / wheder the demeyne landes lye in the commyn feldes among other mennes landes / or in the feldes by them ſelfe. And if they lye in the commyn feldes / it is conuenyent that they be plowen and ſowen / and than is nat an acre ſo moche worthe as &amp; it were in ſeueralty incloſed or in ſeuerall paſture. For &amp; the felde be incloſed about / than it is at the lordes pleaſure wheder they ſhall lye to paſture or to tyllage / and thoughe it lye in tyllage / yet hath the lorde the Edyſſhe and the aftermathe hym ſelfe / for his owne catell. And therfore an acre is at the more value / and yf it lye in paſture the paſture may be ſuche / that it is at double or treble the value of the errable lande. Wherfore the acres are to be prayſed accordynge / and if they lye by great flattes or furlonges in the commyn feldes / it is at the lordes pleaſure to encloſe them and kepe them in tyllage or paſture / ſo that no nother man haue cō
               myn therin.
         
         
            
            ¶Howe many acres of medowe ar of demeyns and howe moche euery acre is worthe / and to what maner of catell it is mooſt neceſſary vnto and howe many beaſtes it wyll fynde / and what the paſture of a beaſt is worthe by the yere. Cap. iii.
            ITem inquirendū eſt quot acre parti ſunt in dn̄ico et quantū quelibet acr valet ad locādū per ſe per annū et adcuiuſmodi beſtias et aīa lia paſtur illa fuerit magis neceſſaria &amp; quot et quales poſſit ſuſtinere / et quantum valet paſtura cuiuſlibet beſtie et aīalis ad locandum per annum. It is to be enquered / how many acres of medowe ar
of the demeyns and how moche euery acre is worthe to ſet by the yere / and to what maner of beeſtes or catell it is moſt neceſſary vnto / and howe many it wyll fynde and of what maner / and what ye paſture of one beeſt is worthe by the yere. And in myne opinyon / it wolde be vnderſtande whether the medowes or paſtures lye in the cōmen medowes or cōmen paſture / at large / or in ſeueraltie: For and it lye at large in the cōmen medowes / an acre is no better worthe than the graſſe that ye hey is made of is worthe / for after / it is cōmen and of lytell value. And if it lye in ſeueraltie / it is worthe halfe as moche againe as the graſſe was worthe. And that highe grounde and drie / is mooſt conuenyent for ſhepe / wode grounde and buſſhe for beeſtes and ſpecially in wynter tyme. Lowe groū
               des / medowe groundes / and marſſhe groundes for hey &amp; after for fat catell / and in wynter for horſes and

mares / and meane groundes that is bothe hylly and dalye as leyſe and lowe groūdes / is good for all maner of catell if the graſſe be good and fyne / and ſpecially for fat catell or fatte ſhepe / horſes / mares / and yonge coltes / for that graſſe that one maner of catell wyll nat eate another wyll. And therfore it is good to haue a large cloſe / ye dyuers maner of catell maye go togyder in it / and to knowe what a beeſtes graſſe is worthe by the yere / that is as the paſture is that he gothe in is worthe / and nat ouer charged with catell and the fyneneſſe of the graſſe and the goodneſſe of an acre. For ſome acre of groūde is nat worthe a penny by the yere / and ſome acre is worthe .xl. pens / and ſo a beeſtes graſſe may be dere ynoughe twelfe pens in the yere / and it may be worthe .xl. pens or fyue ſhillynges / and a horſe graſſe or a mare graſſe maye be dere ynoughe twelfe pens or twentie pens by ye yere / and it maye be worthe fyue ſhillynges or a noble / accordyng to the goodneſſe of the paſtures. But howe theſe maners / landes / medowes / and paſtures / ſhall be viewed / butted / bounded / and valewed / ſhall be reherſed after the ſtatute be ones declared.
         
         
            ¶Of forren paſtures that be commen / howe many and of what maner of catell the lorde maye haue in the ſame / and what the paſture of a beeſt is worthe by the yere. Cap. iiii.
            
               
               ITem inquirend eſt de paſturis for inficis que eſt cōmunis quot &amp; quas beſtias aīalia dominus habere poſſit in eadem et quantū valet paſtura per annum et locand. It is to be inquered of forren paſtures that is cō
               myn / how many and what beeſtes and catell / &amp; what the lorde may haue in the ſame / and what the paſtur
of a beeſt is worthe by the yere to ſet. This is a derke letter to be well vnderſtande without a better declaracyon / for where he ſaythe / De paſturis forinficis que eſt cōmunis. That may be vnderſtande thre wayes: for there is in many townes / where as their cloſes and paſtures lye in ſeueraltie. There is commonly a cōmyn cloſe taken in / out of the cōmen or feldes by tenauntes of the ſame towne / for their oxen or kyen or other catell / in the whiche cloſe euery man is ſtynted and ſette to a certayntie / howe many beeſtes he ſhall haue in the ſame / &amp; of what maner of beeſtes they ſhalbe. And if ye lorde ſhall haue any catell therin he ſhulde be put to a certayntie and of what maner of catell / and this paſture may be well valewed / And alſo the beeſtes graſſe what it is worthe therin. But than it ought to be ſhewed howe many acres be contayned in the ſayd paſture / and what euery acre is worthe one with another. Another maner of commyn paſture / is mooſt cōmenly in playne champyon countreis: where their catell gothe daylye before the herdeman / and lyeth nighe adioynīg to their cōmyn feldes / and it may lye in two or thre places or mo. &amp; in theſe it is alſo conuenyent that euery man be ſtynted

to a certentie / outher by yerdes / landes / oxgāges rentes / or ſuche other cuſtomes as the tenaūtes vſe / and the lorde in lyke maner. Theſe cōmen paſtures may be extended how many acres be in euery parcell by it ſelfe / and what an acre is worthe by it ſelfe / but it can nat be ſo well knowen what a beeſtes graſſe is worthe yerely / for they lye mooſt cōmenly with the falowe feldes / &amp; ſome falowe feldes is better than ſome and ſo a beeſtes graſſe may be better or worſe. The thirde maner of cōmen paſture / is in ye lordes out wodes that lye cōmen to his tenauntes / as commen mores or hethes / the whiche were neuer errable landes. In theſe maner of cōmens / me ſemeth the lorde ſhulde nat be ſtynted nor ſette at no certentie / but put his catell vpon ſuche maner of cōmen paſture at his pleaſure / bycauſe all the whole commen is his owne / and his tenauntes haue no certayne parcell therof layde to their holdyngꝭ / but all onely bytte of mouthe with their catell / and it were agayne reaſon to a bridge a man of his owne right. But his tenauntes and euery mannes tenauntes / me ſemeth ought of ryght to be ſtynted what euery manne ought to haue goynge vpon all maner of commens / for elles wolde the ryche men in the begynnynge of Somer byeſhepe and other maner of catell and eate vp the commens / and ſelle them againe at wynter / or putte them in their paſtures that they haue ſparedde all the Somerr / and ſo ouerpreſſe the poore men that haue no money to bye nor able to reyre.
         
         
            
            ¶Of parkes and demeyne woodes / the whiche the lorde maye aſſarte and to do his profyte / &amp; howe many acres they cōteyne and what the veſture of an acre is worthe / and what the groūde is worthe whan the veſture is fallen. &amp;c. Cap. v.
            
               ITem inquirendum eſt / de parcis et dn̄i cis boſcis / que ad volūtatem ſuam poſſunt aſſertare / et excolere et quot acre in ſe continētur. Et quantum veſtura cuiuſtibet acre poſſit app̄ciari / et quantū fuudus in ſe contineat et valeat quando proſtratus fuerit / et quantum valeat quelibet acra per ſe per annum. It is to be enquered / of ꝑkes and of demeyne woode / the whiche at the lordes wyll may be aſſerted and plucked vp or fallen downe / And howe many acres are conteyned in them / and for howe moche the veſture of euery acre may be ſolde / and howe moche the grounde in hym ſelfe conteyneth whan the wode is fallen / and howe moche euery acre is worthe by it ſelfe by the yere. This is to be vnderſtande / of parkes and demeyne woode that be inſeueraltie / wherof
the lorde at his pleaſure / may aſſert / ſtocke vp by the rootes or falle by the erthe / plowe and ſowe to his mooſt profyte as he wyll / And howe many acres of woode are conteyned in the ſame. For in a parke or woode may be two hundred acres and more / and yet nat paſt a hundred acres therof woode / lytell more or lytell laſſe / and what the veſture / that is to ſay / the woode of euery acre is worthe by hym ſelfe / for one

acre maye be worthe .xx.s. or .xl.s. and another acre dere ynoughe .ii.s.vi.s. or .x.s. and howe moche the whole grounde conteyneth whan the wode is fallen / And that is to be vnderſtāde / all the grounde within pale or hedge / aſwell the laūde groūde as of the wode grounde where the woode growed / and what euery acre is worthe by the yere / as well of the one maner as of the other.
         
         
            ¶Of forren woodes where other men haue cōmen / where the lorde may improwe himſelfe therof and of howe many acres / and what the veſture of an acre is worthe / &amp; what the groūde is worthe whan the woode is fallen / and howe many acres they cō
               tayne / and what an acre is worthe. Cap. vi.
            
               ITem inquirendum eſt de boſcis forinſicis vbi alii cōicant / quid de eiſdem boſcis dominus ſe poſſit approiare / et de quot acris et pro quanto veſtura cuiuſlibet acre cōmuniter poſſit appreciari / et quantum fundus valet poſt
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                proſtratus fuerit boſcus / &amp; quot acre iſte cōtineant / &amp; quantū quelibet acra valet ꝑ annū. It is to be inquered of forren wodes / wher they &amp; other cō
               men togyder / &amp; what of thoſe wodes the lorde maye improwe him ſelfe &amp; of howe many acres / &amp; for howe moche the veſture / yt is to ſay / the wode of euery acre maye be ſolde / &amp; howe moche the grounde is worthe after the woode be fallen downe / &amp; howe many acres it conteyneth / &amp; what euery acre is worth by the yere.

The declaracyon of this ſtatute is doutfull / bycauſe of the none certentie therof / what is ſufficyent commen. for it is clerely ordayned by ye ſtatute of Moreton / and after confyrmed by the ſtatute of Weſtmynſter ſeconde. That the lorde ſhall improue hym ſelfe of their waſtes / wherby is vnderſtāde of their cōmen mores / hethes / and waſt groundes / as well as of wodes. Thoughe the ſtatute ſpeke but of woodes onely leauyng their tenauntes ſufficient commen / the whiche in myne opinyon be thoſe tenauntes that haue cō
               men appendaunt / and holde their landes of hym. It is neceſſarie to be knowen what is ſufficient of commen / and that me ſemeth by reaſon ſhulde be thus. To ſe howe moche catell the hey and the ſtray that a huſbande getteth vpon his owne tenement / wyll fynde ſufficyently in wynter / if they lye in houſe and be kept therwith all the wynter ſeaſon / for ſo moche catell ſhulde he haue cōmen in Somer / and that is ſuffycient. ye ſhall vnderſtande that there be foure maner of commens / that is to wytte: cōmen appendant commen appurtenaunt / commen in groſe / and commen per cauſe vicynage .s. neyghbourſhepe. Commen appendaunt / is where a lorde of olde tyme hath graunted to a man a meſeplace / and certayne landes medowes / and paſtures with their appurtenaunces to holde of hym. To this meſeplace / landes / and medowes belongeth commen / and that is called cōmen appendaunt. But and a man graunt to another certayne landes or paſtures / the whiche lye in ſeueraltie encloſed with the appurtenaūce in fee / to holde of the

chefe lordes. To theſe landes me ſemeth belōgeth no cōmen / without he haue ſuche ſpeciall wordes in his dede. Commen appendaūt / is where a man hath had cōmen to a certayne nombre of beeſtes or without nō
               bre belongyng to his meſeplace in the lordes waſtes / this is commen appurtenaunte by preſcripcyon / bycauſe of the vſe out of tyme of mynde. Commen ingroſe / is where the lordes haue graunted by their dedes / commen of paſture to a ſtraunger that holdeth no landes of hym / nor ought to haue any cōmen / but by reaſon of that graunt by dede. Nowe the lordes maye nat improue hym ſelfe of any parcell / for it is contrarie to his graunt / thoughe there be ſufficyent of commen. And in lyke caſe / if the lorde graunt commen to a man by dede / and to lymitte him a certayne nombre of beeſtes. Se what was commen at that tyme and of that the lorde ſhall nat improue hym ſelfe / for and he ſhulde / the goodneſſe of the cōmen to that certayne nombre ſhulde be abridged that they ſhulde nat fare ſo well / and euery mānes dede ſhall be taken ſtrōgeſt agaynſt hym ſelfe. And in lyke maner / if the lorde graunt a man commen with his catell / within certayne meyres / lymittes / &amp; boundes / the lorde ſhall nat improue hym ſelfe / within thoſe meyres and boū
               des. Cōmen per cauſe de vicynage / is wher the waſt grounde of two towneſhippes lye toguyder / and nother hedge nor pale bytwene to kepe their catell a ſonder / ſo that the catell of one towneſhyppe gothe ouer his meyre or bounde in to the waſte grounde of the other towne / and lykewiſe the catell of the other townſhyppe

to them. And alſo if their commen feldes lye toguyder vncloſed / in opyn tyme whan harueſt is in their catell wyll go out of the one felde in to the other felde / and this is called commens / bycauſe of neyghbourſhyp / and is nat vſed nor laufull to pynne their catell ſo goyng / but in good maner to driue and chace beſyde ſuche cōmen. And as for that maner of commens / me ſemeth the lorde may improwe him ſelfe of their waſt groundes / leauyng their owne tenauntes ſufficyent cōmen / hauyng no regarde to the tenauntes of the other towneſhyp. But as for all errable landes / medowes / leyſe / and paſtures / the lordes maye improwe them ſelfe by courſe of the cōmen lawe / for the ſtatute ſpeketh nothynge but of waſt groundes. And ye ſhall vnderſtande / that howbe it that a lorde maye nat improwe him ſelfe of his waſt groundes / yet may he laufully fall and ſelle all the wode / brome / gorſe / fyrs / braken / ferne / buſſhes / thornes / and ſuche other / as fre ſtonne / lyme ſtone / chalke / turues / claye / ſande / leed / ore / or tynne / to his owne vſe: for the tenā
               tes may haue nothyng by reaſon of commen / but all onely bytte of mouthe with their catell. And ye ſhall knowe / that ſwyne and Geeſe haue no commen / but by ſuffraunce / without ſpeciall wordes in their charter. Alſo the lorde ſhall haue his free warren / for all maner beeſtes &amp; foules of warren in his waſt groundes / as well as in his ſeuerall groundes. and as long as the beeſtes or foules of warren be vpon the lordes grounde / they be the lordes yf he haue warren / and the lorde maye haue an actyon of Treſpace agaynſt

any man that chaceth or kylleth any of theym in his commen / as well as in his ſeuerall. And if they go or flye out of the lordes warren / than is the proꝑtie chā
               ged / and the lorde hath loſt his actyon for takynge of them whan they be oute of his warren / without they come in to his warren agayne. there is no man hath warren but by ſpeciall graunt of the kynge by charter / except it haue ben vſed tyme out of mynde / and alowed before iuſtyce in heyre. And as for the articles contayned in this preſent chapiter the letter therof is playne ynoughe / and alſo touched before.
         
         
            ¶Whether the lorde may gyue or ſelle the reſydue of his forren woodes / and what ſuche gyfte or ſale is worthe by the yere. &amp;c. Cap. vii.
            
               ITem inquirendum eſt / vtrum dominus de reſiduo boſcorum predictorum / forinſicorū dare poſſit / et quantum valet huius donationis et venditionis per annum. It is alſo to be enquered / wheder the lorde maye gyue or ſell the reſydue of his forren woodes aforeſayd and what ſuche gyfte or ſale is worthe by the yere. This letter is playne ynoughe / and as me ſemethe no doubte / but that the Lorde maye gyue or ſelle the reſydewe of the ſayde woodes or waſtes / Excepte that a manne haue commen of Eſtouers / But what

that gyft or ſale is worthe. it is to be vnderſtāde and knowen and as me ſemeth the donee or the byoure / ſhalbe in lyke cauſe as the lorde ſhulde haue ben if he had nat gyuen it nor ſolde it. Than the lorde hath ī
               proued hym ſelfe of as moche wodes and waſtes as he can laufully and whan he hath gyuen or ſolde the reſydue of that he canne nat improue hym ſelfe of. in lyke maner the donee nor the byour can nat improue them ſelfe of any parte therof / For they canne nat be in no better caſe / than he of whome they had it. howe be it that they that of right ought to haue their commens be nat their tenauntes / but their tytell and intereſt grewe by enherytaunce / longe tyme before the gyfte or ſale made by the lorde. And it foloweth by reſon / that the gyfte or ſale of a ſtraunger ſhall nat hurt another mannes enherytaunce. But this donee or this purchaſoure / ſhall take to their profyte all the veſture ſtandyng vpon / or beyng with in the ſayd groūde / as woodes and ſuche other: as is ſayde before in the next chapiter.
         
         
            ¶Of panage and herbage of the towne / and of all other profytes of pooles / meyres / and rynnynge waters / of moores / heythes / and waſtes / what they be worthe by the yere. &amp;c. Cap. viii.
            
               
               ITem inquirendū eſt de panagio herbagio ville / et omnibus aliis exitibus viuariorū morarum bruerum et vaſtorum quantum valent per annum. Alſo it is to be inquered / of panage herbage of the ſame towne / and of all other profytes of polles / meyres / and rynnyng waters / of mores / hethe and waſtes / what they be worthe by the yere. And where this Statute ſpeketh / de panagio / that is to be vnderſtande. Whan̄e there is any maſt growyng in ye lordes wodes / wherby mēnes ſwyne may be fedde and releued / what profyte that may be to the lorde. For ther is no man that can clayme of right / to haue the maſt the whiche is a frute / but the lorde: except his free tenaunt haue it by ſpeciall wordes in his dede. Quod ſit quietus de panagio. And the lorde ſhall haue it in his forren out wodes / as well as in his parkes or ſeuerall wodes / &amp; as the quantite of the maſt is / ſo the lordes baylye of right ought to ley mēnes ſwyne thervnto from Myhelmas to Martylmas / and to make a true accompt therof at the lordes audyte / what he taketh for euery ſwyne. And in many places the tenauntes go fro panage in the forren wodes by cuſtome / &amp; that is mooſt commenly where as the tenauntes pay tacke ſwyne by cuſtome / if he haue to a certayne nombre / or els to pay yerely at Myghelmas .i.d. or an halfpeny for euery ſwyne / as the cuſtome is vſed. The ſtatute ſpeketh / De herbagio ville. That is to be vnderſtande of the commen paſture that belongeth to the towne / whervpon the herdman kepeth the tenauntes catell / 

It may be ſo good that the tenauntes nede nat to haue any ſeuerall paſture / but that their cōmen paſture ſhulde be able to fynde all their catell / bothe horſes / mares / beeſtes / and ſhepe / and ſo it was of olde tyme that all the landes / medowes / and paſtures / lay open and vncloſed. And than was their tenemētes moche better chepe than they be nowe / for the mooſt parte of the lordes haue encloſed their demeyne landes &amp; medowes / and kepe them in ſeueraltie / ſo that their tenauntes haue no cōmyn with them therin. And alſo the lordes haue encloſed a great parte of their waſte groundes and ſtreytened their tenauntes of their cō
               myns therin. and alſo haue gyuen lycence to dyuers of their tenauntes to encloſe parte of their errable lā
               des / and to take in newe intackes or cloſes out of the cōmens / payeng to their lordes more rent therfore ſo that the cōmen paſtures waxen laſſe / and the rentes of the tenauntes waxen more and more. And that is bycauſe the tenauntes waxen more polytike in wyſedome to improue their tenementes / holdynges / and fermes: and at thende of the ferme / another man that made no coſt of the ſayd improuement / offereth the lorde certayne money for a fyne to haue it or to heghten the rent of the ſame / ſo that he that made the coſte or his children ſhall nat haue the ſayd ferme / without he wyll gyue aſmoche or more as is offred to ye lorde / and ſo thorowe the enuy of his neighbour &amp; the couytouſneſſe of the lorde and his offycers / the pore tenāt hath a great loſſe or els vtterly vndone / god amende it. And the lordes haue a gretter loſſe than they wene

for their tenātes ſe howe their neyghburs yt haue bylded their houſes / improued their landes &amp; be put out except he make a fyne or pay more rent. Cauſeth thē nother to bylde nor otherwyſe to improue their holdī
               ges / to the lordes great loſſe at length. And where ye ſtatute ſayth / de oībus aliis exitibus viuariorū morarū bruerū et vaſto
                  
                     
                  
                  rum
               . &amp; of all profytes that ſhall cōe of the lordes ſtādyng waters / mores / hethe &amp; waſtes. viuariū is a pole or a meyre that fiſſhe encreaſeth &amp; lyueth in. Some rynnīg waters be as fre &amp; ſeuerall to the lordes / as their pooles / meyres / or ſtandyng waters. And as they be ſtored with fyſſhe / ſo dothe ye profyte ryſe to the lordes / wheder they go by way of improuement or ſet to ferme: wherof the bayly ſhall make accompte. Moores / hethe / and waſtes / go in lyke maner as the herbage of the townes / for the lordes tenauntes haue commen in all ſuche out groūdes with their catell / but they ſhall haue no wode / thornes / turues / gorſe / ferne / and ſuche other / but by cuſtome or els ſpeciall wordes in his chartour. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Of mylnes / ſeuerall fyſſhinges / and commen fyſſhyng / what they be 
                  •
               orthe in the yere. Cap. ix.
            
               I Item de molēdinis / piſcariis ſeperalibus / et cōibus quantū valent. Alſo of mylnes / ſeuerall fyſſhinges / &amp; cōmen fyſſhingꝭ / what they be worthe. In this ſhort artycle many thingꝭ ar to be remēbred / for wher he ſayth de molēdinis / ye whiche is in the plurell nōbre / it is to

be vnderſtande / that ther be many maner of mylnes as cornemylnes / wyndmylnes / horſemylnes / &amp; quernes that go with hande. Fullyngmylnes / ſythe mylnes / cutlerſmylnes / ſmethymylnes / &amp; all ſuche other as the whele gothe by drifte of water to blowe the bales or to dray any water lyke a pompe / as there be in Cornwall and dyuers other places. Though they be no mylnes properly to grynde corne / yet it is a ꝓfyte to be lorde / the whiche a ſurueyour may nat forget to put in his boke and to but and bounde them as they lye / and who be the fermours and what rentes they pay. And to the cornemilnes to the mooſt parte of thē belongeth Socone / that is to ſaye / cuſtome of the tenauntes to grynde their corne at the lordes mylne / &amp; that is as me ſemeth / all ſuch corne as groweth vpon the lordes grounde that he ſpēdeth in his houſe. But and he bye his corne in the market or other places / he is than at lybertie to grynde wher he may be beſt ſerued / that maner of grynding is called loue Socone / and the lordes tenauntes be called bonde ſocon. And if they grynde nat their corne at the lordes mylne / ye lorde maye a merce thē in his court / or els he may ſue them at the commen lawe. De ſecta molendim facienda. But whan he ſhall make his declaracyon in ye debet and whan in the ſolet / I remytte that to men of lawe that haue experience therof. It is alſo to be knowen howe the tole ſhulde be taken / but there be ſo many dyuers graūtes made by the lord / ſome men to be groūden to the twentie parte / and ſome to the .xxiiii. parte / tenaūt at wyll to the .xvi. parte / and bondmen

to the .xii. parte / ſome men to be tole free / and ſome to be hopper fre / that is to wytte: that his corne ſhalbe put into the hopper and groūde next to the corne that is in the hopper / at the tyme of his comynge. And in ſome place to take the tole after the ſtrength of the water / that foloweth by reaſon. for that mylne that hath a bygge water and maye driue a great brode ſtonne / the whiche wyll make moche more meyle / than that mylne that gothe with a lytell ſtone / he is moche better worthy to haue the more tole / and yet ſhall the honer of the corne haue the more profyte. And ſo there be ſo many dyuerſities of takyng of tole / that I wyll nat take vpon me to tell howe / but alſo to remytte it to men of lawe to ſhewe the dyuerſities. But dout ye nat / the mylners wyll be no loſers / &amp; of mylnes ther
ſhall more be ſpoken of in the chapiter of waters / among the improwmentes / De piſcariis ſeperalibus that is to be vnderſtande / in the lordes ſtandyng waters / as pooles and meyres: and alſo rynninge waters that be ſeuerall / as be very many in dyuers coū
               treis / ſette to ferme from one place of the ryuer to another for certayne rent / and if any man fyſſhe in the lordes pooles or meyres / the lorde maye haue his accyon vpon the ſtatute of Weſtmynſter prim̄. And yf he fyſſhe in the rynning and ſeuerall waters / the lorde may haue his actyon at the cōmen lawe / &amp; in lykewyſe the lordes tenaunt / if any man fyſſhe in his ferme holde / be it ſtandynge waters and rynninge waters: And where he ſaythe / de omnibus / of commen fyſſhynges / that is lytell profyte to ye lorde but to his

tenaūtes / except he dwell nighe the ſee / and wyll cauſe his ſeruant to fyſſhe there for hym / for yt is the beſt cōmen water yt any man can fiſſhe in. And ſomerynning waters be cōmen / as lytell brokes / and ſytches / and in ſome rinnyng waters / the lordes tenaūtes haue lybertie by cuſtōe to fyſſhe with ſhouenettꝭ / trodenettes / ſmall pytches / and ſuche other.
         
         
            ¶Of fre tenauntes / the whiche dwell without as well as within. &amp;c. Cap. x.
            
               ITem inquirendum eſt de libere tenentibus quibuſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                forinſecis et extrīſcicis. Alſo it is to be enquered of fre holders / the whiche dwell without aſwell as wt
               in. By this letter it is to be vnderſtan
               
                  •
               e / that a free holder maye dwell out of the precyncte of the lordes manere / and yet holde his lande of the ſaid manere▪ For one manere maye ſtretche in to dyuers ſhyres / as the honer of Tutebury / Walyngeforde / Pountfrette / Tyckell / and ſuche other: And in that cauſe the lorde of the honer or manere / may take a diſtreſſe for his rentes / homages / relifes / cuſtomes and ſeruyces / and to bringe the ſame dyſtreſſe out of that ſhyre where it was taken / in to that ſhyre where the manere is / of whom theſe ſayd landes be holden. And if the tenaūt wyll ſewe repleuy / the ſherife wher
the catell is ſhall make and ſerue the repleuy / and nat the ſherife where the goodes or the catell was taken / nor returne vpon his repleuy / qd aueria elongata ſūt

And the lorde may haue a fre holder that holdeth his lande of hym / &amp; payeth hym chefe rētes and other ſeruyce / and nat by the reaſon of any manere. As thus / a man purches a parcell of lande before the makyng of the ſtatute / quia emtores terrarum. And gyue the ſame landes agayne to a ſtranger before ye makyng of the ſayd ſtatute / to holde of hym by certayne rent and ſeruyce. This may be called a forren fre holder / for it is no parcell of any manere / and it is no maner
it ſelfe▪ For to euery manere belongeth two thynges / that is to ſay
                  •
                parcell in demeyne &amp; parcell in ſeruice. That is landes in demyne belongyng to the maner
and ſeruyce / cuſtomes / or rētes / &amp; this free holder / I ſpake of before hath demeyne / but he hath no ſeruice. Alſo a man maye haue bothe rent and ſeruyce of a freholder / and yet he holdeth nat his landes of him that he payeth his chefe rent vnto. As and a man purches lādes ſythe the makyng of the ſayd ſtatute / and gyue it to a ſtraūger / reſeruyng fealtie and certayne rent: this free holder holdeth his landes of the chefe lorde next aboue. and yet ſhall he paye his rentes and ſeruices reſerued to him that gaue it to hym / &amp; if the gyfte were in the tayle and no remaynder in fe euer / nowe the reuercyon reſteth ſtyll in ye donor. I coude ſpeke more of the gyftes &amp; remaynders / but I remyt thē to men of lawe that be lerned / for it is nat the mater that I entende to ſpeke of. How be it / it is very neceſſarie for euery Surueyoure to haue inſyght and experyence of the cōmen lawe / or els at ſome ſeaſon he ſhall diſceyue his lorde or his tenant / &amp; ſpecially his owne

ſoule / for ſaynt Iſodorus ſaythe. Qd ignorātia craſſa vel affectata non excuſat peccatū. That is to ſaye / ignorance of connynge or of the facultie in hym yt taketh vpon him as a mayſter or techer of the ſcience or cōnyng / excuſeth nat a mannes offēce. for euery man that god gath ſende wytte and reaſon vnto / is bounden to knowe / wheder he do well or yuell. And therfore it is neceſſarie / that euery man lerne and do his dilygence / to knowe what he oughte to do / or he take vpon hym / any ſuche offyce or rowme.
         
         
            ¶Who be fre tenauntes and what landes and tenementes and what fees they holde and by what ſeruyce / wheder by ſocage or by knyght ſeruyce or other / and what rent of aſſyſe they gyue by the yere and who holdeth by charter and who by Aūcyent demeyne / and who by newe feoffement. Cap. xi.
            
               ITem inquirendum eſt qui ſunt liberi tenentes / et qui et quas terras et tenementa / et que feoda teneant / et per quod ſeruicium / vtrum per ſoccagium / vel per ſeruiciū militare / vel alio modo / et quantum reddant per annum de redditu Aſſiſe / et qui tenent per cartam / et qui non / et qui per antiquam tenuram et qui per nouum feoffamentum. Alſo it is to be enquered / who be fre tenauntes and what maner landes and tenementes / and what fees they holde and by what ſeruice / and wheder it be by ſocage or by knight ſeruyce or of any other maner and what they yelde by the yere of rent of Aſſiſe / and

who holdeth by charter and who nat / and who by the olde tenur / and who by the newe feoffement. It apereth by this artycle / yt there be many maner of fre holdes / and holde their landes and tenemētes in diuers maner / and by many maner of rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / as tenauntes in fee ſymple / tenātes in tayle tenantꝭ by copye of court role / tenauntes by the curteſy / tenauntes in dower / and tenauntes for terme of lyfe by ſpeciall graūt / and many other. And all theſe tenauntes maye holde their landes by dyuers tenures / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces: as by homage / fealtie / eſcuage / ſocage / knight ſeruyce / graunt ſergentie / petyte ſergentie / franke almoyne / homage / auncetrell / burgage / tenures / and tenure in vyllenage. But to declare the dyuerſytie of all the tenures / it wolde be to longe a proceſſe / &amp; therfore I remytte it to the firſt boke of the cōmen lawe / called the tenures. But ye diuerſytie of theſe tenures / what rentes / fees / cuſtomes and ſeruices / the lorde ought to haue of his tenaūtes can nat be knowen but by the lordes euydence / court rolles / rentayles / and ſuche other preſydētes / and ſpecially by the originall dedes of their tenauntes. And ye ſhall knowe / yt the lordes maye nat diſtreyne their tenauntes nor ceaſe their landes in to their handes / to cauſe their tenantes to ſhewe their euydence / wherby they holde their landes. But and the lorde haue any euydence / rentayles / or court rolles / or any maner of rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyce that he hath nat and can proue a poſſeſſyon of the ſame in his aunceſters / ſythe the lymitacyon expreſſed in the ſtatute of Weſtmynſter

ſeconde in the ſecōde chapiter / than he maye laufully diſtrayne for the ſame. And than muſt the tenaunt ſhewe a diſcharge by ſuffycient writyng / and nat by wordes / or elles to paye the ſame: for mater in writyng / may nat be diſcharged by a newe de paroll .s. bare wordes. The ſtatute ſpeketh / qui tenent per cartam / et qui non. The tenauntes in fee ſymple and the tenauntes in tayle / that haue euidence and dedes made &amp; ſealed / and poſſeſſyon delyuered of their lordes or by their attourney / from one to another / they holde their lādes by charter / be it newe made or olde. And alſo there be tenauntes in fee ſymple / and tenaū
               tes in tayle / that holde by no charter / and thoſe be tenauntes by copye of courte role. As and a lorde haue a manere / and within the ſayd manere there is a cuſtome that hath ben vſed tyme out of mynde / that certayne tenauntes within the ſayd maner haue vſed to haue their landes and tenementes / to holde to them and to their heyres / in fee ſymple / fee tayle / or for tme
of lyfe at the wyll of the lorde / after the cuſtome of the manere. &amp; ſuche a tenant maye nat gyue nor ſelle his lande by dede / for and he do / the lorde maye entre as in landes forfayte to hym. For if ſuche a tenant wyll gyue or ſell ſuche maner of lādes to another / he muſt ſurrēdre the ſame landes in the lordes court in to the lordes handes / vnto the vſe of hym that ſhulde haue it: or in fee ſymple / fee tayle / or for terme of lyfe. And he that ſhall haue the lande / muſt come into the court and take it of the lorde / as here after foloweth.
            
               AD hanc curiam venit I.B. et ſurſum reddidit / in eadem curia vnum meſſuagium. &amp;c. in manus domini ad vſum A. D. et hered ſuorū vel hered de corpore ſuo exiſtētium / vel pro termino vite ſue. Et ſuper hoc venit predictus A. D. et cepit de domino in eadem curia predictum meſſuagium. &amp;c. habendum et tenend ſibi et heredibus ſuis / vel ſibi &amp; hered de corpore ſuo exiſtētibus / vel ſibi ad terminū vite ſue ad voluntatem dn̄i ſecundum cōſuetudinem manerii / faciēdo et reddendo inde reddit ſeruicia cō
               ſuetudīes inde prius debita et cōſueta / et dat dn̄o de fine. &amp;c. et fecit dn̄o fidelitatē / et ad miſſus eſt inde tenēs. And theſe maner of tenantes ſhall nat plede nor be impleded of their tenemētes by the kynges writte but and they wyll implede eche other for their ten̄tes they ſhall haue their pleynt made in the lordes court / after this forme or this effect. A de B. querit verſus C de D. de placito terre vcꝪ de vno meſſuagio decē acris tre tri
                  
                     
                  
                  bus
                acris ꝑti. &amp;c. cū ꝑtin̄. &amp; ſhall make ꝓteſtacion to ſue his pleynt 
                  〈◊◊〉
                nature of the kynges writ / of formdowne in dec
                  〈…〉
               t the cōmen lawe / or of the kynges writ of aſſiſe of nouell diſſeſon / or of aſſiſe of mortaūceter / or of any other writ at the cōmen lawe. Plegii de proſequend GF. et GH. but howe the declaracion / the anſwere / replicacion / &amp; reioyndre ſhulde be made: and alſo in actiōs of dette / detinue / c
                  •
               uenauntes / treſpas / &amp; ſuche other / I remyt yt to men of lawe yt haue expeience therof. but one thyng wotte I well / yt many an erronious proceſſe the ſtewardꝭ make in their court rolles. Wherfore men of honour and

of worſhyppe / and abbottes / priours / and ſuche other ſhulde make men of lawe their ſtewardes / &amp; to cauſe them to exercyſe the offyce hym ſelfe with his clerke / ſufficiently inſtructed by his maiſter / that there may be made due proues without fauoure / bribery / or extorcyon / on payne of forfeyture of his offyce. But it is a cōmen vſe in ſome countreis: that lordes / knightes / eſquyers / and gentylmen / that knowe but lytell of the lawe be made ſtewardes / and they come to the court or ſende their clerkes / that can as lytell lawe as their mayſter or laſſe: but that he vnderſtandeth a lytell laten. And if there be a fyne to make for a tenement / houſe / or cloſe / that is to be ſette: the ſtewarde ſhall haue a rewarde for his good wyll / that he may haue it before another man / and the clerke muſt haue another rewarde for to entreat his mayſter to the ſame / ſo that the lordes fyne muſt nedes be the laſſe / or els the poore man ſhalbe at a great charge. Wherof ſpeketh Salomon / prouerbiorum .xvii. Melius eſt parum cum iuſtitia / 
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                multi fructus cum iniquitate. It is better to haue a lytell rightwiſely / than to haue moche ꝓfyte wickedly. But nowe to my mater that I ſpake of before / there maye be in one manere or lordſhyp bothe charter lande and copyelande / and eche of thē well knowen from other / &amp; one man maye haue and holde them bothe. Alſo there be other tenā
               tes by copy of court role / and is called tenauntes perle virge .s. by the yerde. And they be called ſo / bycauſe whan they wolde ſurrendre their tenementes in to the lordes hādes to the vſe of another / they ſhall haue

a lytell yerde in his hande by cuſtome of the courte / &amp; that he ſhall delyuer vnto the ſtewarde / if he be there preſent / or to the bayly or reue / or to other two honeſt men of the lordeſhyp. And at the next court he yt ſhall haue the ſaid landes ſhall take it in the court / and his takyng ſhalbe entred in the role / and the ſtewarde or bayly as the cuſtomes is vſed / ſhall delyuer to hym yt ſhall haue the lande the ſame yerde / or another in the name of ſeaſon / &amp; hath non other euydēce but ye copy of ye court role &amp; it maye be made in fee ſymple for fee tayle or for terme of lyfe / And all maner of cuſtomes that be nat agayne reaſon may be admytted and a lowed for a cuſtome. And how be it that theſe maner of copye holders haue an eſtate of enherytaunce / after the cuſtome of the maner / yet haue they no franke tenement bycauſe of the cōmen lawe / and therfore they be called tenantes of baſe tenur. Meſemeth it were neceſſary and cōuenyent / to ſhewe dyuers dyuerſites howe copyes ſhulde be made / for fere leſt euery man that taketh vpon hym to kepe a court / hath nat ꝑfitelye thexperyence therof / as herafter enſeweth.
            
               ¶Firſt of ſurrenders of landes holden by the yerde.
               HE ſhall take a yerde in his hande by thende / and delyuer the ſtewarde the other ende in his hande / and ſay to the ſtewarde. Here I A.B. do yelde vp or ſurrendre my landes that called D. the whiche I holde of this lordeſhyp at the lordes

wyll / after the cuſtome of this manere / to the behoue of Iohan Browne and his heyres.
            
            
               ¶Howe the ſtewarde ſhall delyuer ſeaſon.
               ¶The ſtewarde ſhall delyuer hym an ende of the yarde in his hande that ſhall haue this lande / and he ſhall ſaye thus to hym. My lorde graunteth you ſeaſon of this lande that was A. B. the whiche ye haue take here in the courte to you and to youre heyres / to holde at my lordes wyll / after the cuſtome of this manere / and than he ſhall be ſworne. &amp;c.
            
            
               ¶The maner of the othe of the tenaunt.
               ¶I ſhall beare faythe &amp; trouthe to my lorde of this manere / as for the landes and tenementes that I haue taken of hym / and truely do and pay the ſutes / cuſtomes / rentes / and ſeruyces that longeth therto / as for ye terme that I ſhall ocupy it / ſo helpe me god. &amp;c. and kyſſe the boke &amp; ley downe .i.d. as the cuſtōe is.
            
            
               ¶Howe the copy ſhulde be made of landes holden by the yarde.
               ¶Ad hanc cur dn̄s conceſſit extra manus ſuas ꝑ I. F. capitalem ſen̄ ſuum TD. &amp; M. vxori eius vnum meſſ. et ſex acr terre cū pertin̄ 
                  iacent apud B. qui
                     
                        
                     
                     bus
                   dn̄s perſeneſcallū ſuum conceſſit ſeiſinā 
                  habend ſibi et heredibus ſuis de dn̄o per virgam ad voluntatem dn̄i ſecundum conſuetudinem manerii / et dant pro

fine pro ingreſſu inde habendū prout patet in capite et fecit dn̄o fidelitatem / et admiſſus eſt inde tenens.
            
            
               ¶Another forme for certayne rent / for all maner of ſeruyce.
               ¶Ad hanc cur dn̄s conceſſit per I.F. ſeneſcallū ſuū TB et M. vxori ſue vnum meſſ. ſex acr terre .ii. acr
prati / et vnam acram boſci cū pertin̄ prefatꝭ T &amp; M. hered / et aſſignatis ſuis ad voluntatem dūi ſecundū conſuetudinem manerii / redd inde annuatim dn̄o / et hered ſuis / vel ſucceſſoribus ſuis / ſi dn̄s ſit religio ſus .v.s.vi.d. pro omni
                     
                        
                     
                     bus
                   et ſingulis ſeruiciis ad duos anni terminos videlicet. &amp;c. equis portionibus / et dant dn̄o define. &amp;c. et fecit fidelit. The cōmen courſe is nat to put in certayntie all their rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / in their copyes. And that is in auncyent demeyne / and in all places where their tenaūtes haue their landes by copye to them and their heyres / after the cuſtome of the manere. for there they haue or ought to haue a cuſtomarie role / wherin is euery mannes lande contayned / and what rent / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces euery man ought to pay and do / and in many places / their lawes and their cuſtomes be put in writyng / and remeyn in their owne kepyng to put thē in a redyneſſe / whā nede ſhall require. but &amp; there ſhalbe made any new incrochmētes or intackis incloſed or taken in out of the cōmens / or any myne newe foūde / as leed / ore / tyn / cole / yrcuſton or ſuche other / if a copy ſhalbe made therof / it is thā neceſſary &amp; conuenyent

the rente therof to be put in the copye / for it is a newe thyng that hath nat gone by cuſtome / and alſo it wolde be put in the cuſtomarye role / for this newe approumēt maye fortune to encreſe of rent or decreſe in rent / and therfore the rentes muſt alway be expreſſed. Alſo wher a man hath a lordſhyp / wherin be many tenantes that holde their landes of their lorde by copy of court role for terme of yeres or for tme of life where they haue no ſtate of inherytaunce. In all ſuche copyes / it is conuenyent that the rentes be expreſſed in the ſame copyes / cauſa patet.
            
            
               ¶A recogniſcyon of a tenaunt what he holdeth of the lorde.
               ¶Ad hanc cur venit R. T. coram S. E. ſeneſcallo huius manerii / &amp; cognouitſe tener de domino vnum meſſuagtū / decem acras terre / tres acras prati cum pertin̄ in L. voc. C. libere per cartam in ſocagio per redditum .xii.d. vel vnam libram piperis / et ſectam cur bis per annum. Et etiam dictus RT. cognouit ſe tenere de domino alium meſſuagium cū crofto ad iacente / et ſex acras tre / et. ii acras prati cum pertifi / ad voluntatem domini ſecūdum conſuetudinem manerii / et per redd duorum ſolidorum / et fecit fidelitatem / et admiſſus eſt tenens.
            
            
               ¶The forme of a copye in auncyent demeyne where the proclamacyons ſhulde be hadde.
               
                  ¶Ad hanc cur 
                  tent ibidem tali die et anno. &amp;c. venit A.B. filius et heres I.B. et ſurſum redd in manus dn̄i vnum meſſuagium .x. acr 
                  terr / tres acr prati cū vno crofto in D. infra iuriſdictionem huius cur ad opus EF hered / et aſſign̄ ſuo
                     
                        
                     
                     rum
                   imꝑpetuum virtute barganie ī eos fact. Et ſuꝑ hoc publica ꝓclamatio in ead 
                  cur fact fuit ꝙ ſi quis aliqd ius in ſeu ad eūdem meſſuag. terr 
                  prat et crofto / vel in aliqua eo
                     
                        
                     
                     rum
                   parcella pretēdere voluit / vel haberet veniret et audiretur / et nullus venit ad hāc cur / per qd 
                  ſcdm conſuetudinē manerii / meſſu. predict terras prata et croft 
                  predict
remanerent in manus dn̄i / vſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ad tertiā 
                  proclamac
ſuꝑ eo
                     •
                  dem fact / et ſuꝑ hoc dies dat eſt ꝑtibus predictis eſſendi ad ꝓximam cur manerii p̄dicti / ad audi end ſuꝑ inde iuditiū ſuū ſuꝑ premiſſis / et ad hāc cur
                  tent ibidē tali die. &amp;c. tam p̄dictꝰ AB 
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   
                  predict EF venere / et ſuꝑ hocſcda proclamcio fact fuit ſuꝑ p̄miſſis / ꝙ ſi aliquis aliqd ius vel titulū ad predict meſſ. terr prata. &amp;c. haberet aut pretēderet veniret et audi. ret. Et nullus venit et ſuꝑ hoc dies dat eſt ꝑtibus predictis eſſēdi ad ꝓximam cur manerii predicti et aue diendi inde iuditium ſuum. Et ad hanc cur 
                  tent ibidem tali die. &amp;c. tam predictus AB 
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   predictꝰ EF. vener / &amp; ſuper hoc tertia proclamatio facta fuit ſuper premiſſis ꝙ ſi aliquis aliquod ius / vel titulum ad predict
meſſuagium terr 
                  prat et croft / vel in aliqua eorum parcella haberet / vel pretenderet / veniret / et audiretur: et nullus adhuc venit. Et ſuꝑ hoc dominus per IG. ſeneſcallum ſuum conceſſit ſeiſinam de predict
meſſuagio terras prat / et croft cum eorum pertinenc
                  
prefato E. F. tenend ſibi hered / et aſſign̄ ſuis ſecundum conſuetudinem manerii predict / et dat domino de fine ad ingreſſū. &amp;c. et admiſſus eſt inde tenens et fecit fidelitatem.
            
            
               ¶The forme of a copye in auncient demeyne wher the wyfe ſhalbe examyned.
               Dale. ¶Ad cur 
                  tent ibidem tli die anno. &amp;c. TB. de N et M. vxor eius hic in plena cur ſola examinata et confeſſ. ſurſum reddiderūt in manus dn̄i vnum meſſuagium et dīam bonatam terr / ac vnam quatro nam terre cum ſuis pertin̄ in N. predicta voc D. ad opus WC de O. vnde accidit dn̄o vnū equū de herriotto. et ſuper hoc venit dictus WC. &amp; cepit de dn̄o dict meſſ. &amp;c. cum ſuis pertiū 
                  habend et tenend ſibi &amp; anne vxor ſue et her et aſſign̄ ipſius W. imꝑpetuum ſecundum conſuetudinem manerii / per redd conſuetudinem et ſeruic inde prius debit et conſuet / et dant dn̄o de fine pro ingreſſu habend 
                  dict meſſ. et ceteris premiſſis. &amp;c. et data eſt eis ſeiſinā et fecerūt fidelit.
            
            
               ¶Another forme for terme of lyfe.
               ¶Ad hanc cur. &amp;c. venit ID et I. vxor eius ipſa ſola examinata coram ſeneſcallo / et ſurſum reddiderūt in manus dn̄i vnum ten̄tum cum ꝑtin̄ in A. iac inter tenement IB. ex parte orrient et ten̄tum CD. ex ꝑte occident et abuttat ſuper altam viam ex parte auſtrali et ſuper gardinū EF. ex parte boriali ad opus GH et I. vxoris eius ad terminum vite eorum et alterius

eorum diutius viuentis ſecūdum conſuetudinem manerii / &amp; dant dn̄o de fine. &amp;c. et fecerūt fidelit.
            
            
               ¶Another forme vpon condycion.
               ¶Ad hanc cur. &amp;c. venit IC. et ſurſum redd in manus dn̄i vnum cotagium iacent. &amp;c. ad opus ID. &amp;c tenend ſibi et hered ſuis de domino ad voluntatem domini ſecundum. &amp;c. ſub conditionibus ſubſequentibus: vicꝪ ſi predictꝰ ID. ſoluat aut ſolui faciat prefat
IC. xl.s. ad feſt vicꝪ. &amp;c. proximo futuro poſt data huius curie ꝙ tunc preſens ſurſum redd ſit in ſuo robore et effectu / et ſi ipſe defecerit in ſolutiōe ſolutio nū 
                  p̄dict in ꝑte vel in to / ꝙ ex tunc bene licebit prefat
IC. et aſſign̄ ſuis reintrare et rehabere predictum cotagium iſta ſurſum reddic non obſtante in aliquo et dat domino de fine / et cetera. et fecit fidelitatem. et cetera. et admiſſus eſt et cetera.
            
            
               ¶Another maner of ſurrendre made to the baylye out of the court.
               ¶Ad hanc cur. &amp;c. compertum eſt ꝙ TC. extra cur
ſurſum reddidit in manus I. D. balliui in preſenc. DR. et aliorum tenentium domini huius manerii / hoc teſtante vnam acram terre in G. quond WB. et opus X.z. cui dominus inde cōceſſit ſeiſinam tenend
ſibi et hered et cetera / de ſeruic. &amp;c / et dat. &amp;c.
            
            
               ¶Another forme / wher the lorde graunteth a copye of his ſpecyall graunt.
               
                  ¶Ad cur apud D. tent ibidem tali die et anno. &amp;c. preceptū fuit balliuo ſeiſir in manu dn̄i / vnum tenementū ſiue meſſuagium cum pertiū IB. voc. E. eo ꝙ ipſe alienauerit / et vendidit dictum ten̄tum cuidā IT 
                     •
                  ine licentia dn̄i et inde reſpondebit domino de exitibus quouſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  . &amp;c. et ꝙ in iſta eadem cur dominus / ex ſua gratia ſpeciali conceſſit dictū tenemētum cum pertin̄ prefato IB. cui dominus inde conceſſit ſeiſinam habend ſibi et hered. &amp;c. de domino ad voluntatem ſecundum. &amp;c. et dat. &amp;c. et fecit et cetera.
            
            
               ¶Another maner for terme of yeres / where the lorde ſhall kepe reparacyon.
               ¶Ad hanc cur dominus per IF ſeneſcallum ſuum conceſſit IE. vnum meſſuagium cum domibus ſuperaſtantibus et aduerſas terras prata paſcuas &amp; paſturas cum ſepibus foſſatis / et omnibus aliis ſuis ꝑtin̄ 
                  voc A. habend et tenend ſibi &amp; aſſign̄ ſuis a feſto ſancti Michaelis archangeli proxīo futuro poſt dat
huius cur vſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ad finem et terminum quadraginta annorum / ex tunc proximo ſequentium et plenarie cō plendorum redd inde annuatim .xx.s. ad duos anni terminos vicꝪ. &amp;c. ꝑ equales portiōes. Prouiſo ſemꝑ ꝙ durante termino predicto predictus dn̄s inueniet meremiū totiens quotiens neceſſarium fuerit dicto tenemento ad emendandum reperandum et ſuſtinē
                  dum / et dat domino define. &amp;c. et fecit fidelit. &amp;c.
            
            
               ¶Another maner / where a man pretendeth a tytle / and after releſeth in the court.
               
                  ¶Ad hanc cur 
                  tent. &amp;c. compertum eſt ꝙ cum dominus per IF. ſeneſcallum ſuum / ad cur 
                  tent apud C. tali die et anno. &amp;c. conceſſit extra manus domini. AB. et hered ſuis vnam peciam terre continentem circa tres acras terre ſiue plus ſiue minus habeatur quond TC in A. iacentem inter terram PQ ex ꝑte auſtrali et terram RS. &amp;c. habend &amp;c. ad voluntatē domini ſecundum. &amp;c. et poſtea venit quedam Alicia Bate coram prefato IF ſeneſcallo domini / et pretendit habere titulum in predicta pecia terre / et hic preſens in cur remiſit relaxauit et imꝑpetuum quietum clamauit prefato AB. et hered ſuis per licentiam domini totum ius ſuum et clamium / que habet vel habuit vel in futur habere poterit in predicta pecia terre / et in qualibet inde ꝑcella. Ita vicꝪ ꝙ ipſa Alicia nec hered ſui / nec aliquis alius nomine eorum aliqd
ius / vel clameum in predicta pecia terre de cetero exigere / vel vendicare poterit / 
                     
                        
                     
                     sed
                   ab omne actione iuris vel clamei ſint excluſi ꝑ preſentes / et dat domino. &amp;c. et fecit. et cetera.
            
            
               ¶Another forme / where the heyre is admytted to his lande / after the dethe of his father.
               ¶Ad hanc cur 
                  tent. &amp;c. compertum eſt ꝙ IB. obiit ſeiſitus poſt vltimam curiam / qui de domino tenuit ſibi et hered fuis vnā placeā 
                  terr 
                  voc C. &amp; inde obiit ſeiſitus et dicūt qd RB. filius eius eſt proximus heres / et plene etatis / vel infra etatem vicꝪ .xii. annorū et in cuſtodia. TW vel SB. frater eius / vel cōſanguineus

eius eſt proximus heres eiuſdem IB et plene etatis / et preſens hic in cur petit admitti et admiſſus eſt inde tenens / tenend ſibi et hered ſuis de dn̄o ad voluntatem ſcdm 
                  conſuet. &amp;c. et dat. &amp;c. &amp; fecit. &amp;c.
            
            
               ¶Another forme of landes tayled with a remayndre ouer.
               ¶Ad hanc cur compertum eſt qd RB de A. ad cur
                  tent apud E tali die et anno. &amp;c. ſurrum redd in manus domini vnū tenementum et tres acras terre voc
C ad opus RC filius eiuſdem R et A vxor eius quibus dn̄s conceſſit ſeiſinam. Tenend ſibi et hered de corporibus eorum legittime procreat. Et ſi predictꝰ R et A vxor eius ſine her de corporibus eorum legit time procreat obierint / ꝙ tunc predit terras et ten̄ta cum ſuis pertin̄ remaneant rect 
                  her ipſius RB. Et modo curia iſta informaretur per totum homagium qd predictus R et A. obierunt ſine herede inter eos procreat et predictus RB. ſilit / et ſuper hoc venit IB. fratr et heres predict RB. et petit admitti et admiſſus eſt tenens. &amp;c. et per licentiam domini prefatus IB. conceſſit predictum tenementum et terras / que ei remaneant poſt mortem predictorum RB. et RC et A. vxor eius / Remaneret WC et hered
ſuis cui dominus inde conceſſit ſeiſinam tenend ad volūtatem domini ſecundum. et cetera / et dat. &amp;c. et fecit. &amp;c.
            
            
               
               ¶Another maner for terme of lyfe with dyuers remaynders ouer.
               ¶Ad hanc cur venit RB et ſurſū reddit in mani
                     
                        
                     
                     bus
                   dn̄i vnū meſſuagium / et octo acras terr 
                  cuſtomar
                  voc A. vt dominus faciet inde voluntatem ſuam / et dominus inde habetur ſeiſinam. Et ex gratia ſua ſpeciali reconceſſit predictum meſſuagium et terr prefato RB et I vxori eius durante vita reorum ita qd
poſt eorum deceſſū dictum tenementum et terras remaneāt B vxor A / durante vita ſua et poſt deceſſum ipſius B. predict terras &amp; tenementa remaneant rectis hered ipſius R.B imperpetuum tenend eiſdem RB et I vxori eius durante tota vita corum per virgam ad voluntatem domini ſecundum. et cetera / in forma predicta ſaluo iur cuiuſlibet / et cetera / et predictus R. et I. dant domino de fine / et cetera / et fecerunt fidelitatem / et cetera.
            
            
               ¶A ſurrendre out of the court / and a remayndre with a cōdycion.
               ¶Ad hanc cur compertum eſt qd RF. languens in extremis ſurſum redd in manibus B. R. extra cur
per manus IH in preſentia A. C. et B. D. tenentes huius manerii / hoc teſtante vnum meſſuagium cum pertin̄. &amp;c. ad opus A vxor 
                  predict R. F. tenend ſibi per ſeruic inde debit ſecundum conſuetudinem manerii / pro termino vite ſue ita ꝙ poſt mortem dicte A predict meſſ. remaneat I filio predict R. et A. ether
de coꝑe ſuo legittīe procreat. Et ſi cōtingat I obier
                  
ſiue hered de corpore ſuo legittime procreat / qd tunc predict meſſuagiū remanere R. filio p̄dict R et A. &amp; hered de corpore ſuo legittime procreat. Et ſi cōtingat predict R. obiere. &amp;c. qd tūc predictū meſſuagiū per executores vtrum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   eorum diutius viuent 
                  vendantur. et denerios inde recept et prouenient pro aīabus parent eorum et ſuorum in piis vſibus / et operibus caritatiuis in miſſis celebrādis et elemoſinis diſtribuendis / pro vt melius eis viderint expedir pro aīabus anteceſſorum et predeceſſorum ſuo
                     
                        
                     
                     rum
                   / quibus dn̄s inde conceſſit ſeiſinam / tenend in forma predict
ad voluntatem dn̄i ſecundū 
                  conſuet manerii / et dant dn̄o de fine. &amp;c. et fecit fidelit. Et nota ꝙ ſi vnus eo
                     
                        
                     
                     rum
                   obiit &amp; heres eius ſit infra etatem fidelitas reſpectuatur quouſque ad etatem veniat.
            
            
               ¶A ſupplycacion to be exempt from all maner inqueſtes and iuryes within the lordſhyppe.
               ¶Ad hanc cur venit RC. inſtant ſupplicando ꝓ vt ipſe per plurima tempora tranſacta ſupplicauit. Et profert domino finem annualem nomine exēptionis nis vt ipſe ex ſua gratia ſpeciali et fauore ob cauſam ſenectutis infirmitatis et debilitatisſue poſſit exono rare de cetero / ab omnibus et ſingulis inquiſitionibus iuramentis &amp; offic quorumcunque: tam in hac villa 
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   alibi infra dominium domini ſibi obiciend / &amp; aſſignād / quapropter aſpecta vero ſenectute / vna cum infirmitate / et debilitate ſua ſub fine ānuali nomine exemptionis inde prolate ac ſuggeſtione eius / 

per tenentes et viſus 
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   ipſum veracit congrua teſtificata in premiſſis. Modo dn̄s conceſſit in iſta curia per IF ſeneſcal. ſuum prefato RC huiuſmodi licēt
fauorem et exemptionem ad terminum vite ſue duratur
/ et predict RC dat domino de annuali redd ꝑ ſoluendum annuatim .iiii.d. ad terminos vſuales. ¶Ad hanc cur venit IS / et dat domino de fine pro ſecta cur 
                  reſpectuand per .i. annum / vt patet. ¶Ad hanc curiā venit IS / natiuus domini huius manerii / et petit licenc ad maritand filiam ſuam infra dominium iſtud / vel extra / &amp; dominus per W. C. ſeneſcallum ſuum conceſſit licenc et dat. &amp;c.
               MEmorandum that there is no maner of eſtatꝭ made of free lande by polle dede or dede indē
                  ted / but lyke eſtates may be made by copye of copye landes / if they be well made and entred in the courte rolles. And the ſtewarde is bounde by lawe and conſcyence to be an indyfferent iudge bytwene the lorde and his tenauntes / and to entre their copyes truely in the lordes court rolles / the whiche is a regeſter to the lorde to knowe his preſydentes / cuſtomes / &amp; ſeruyces / and alſo a great ſuretie to the tenantes / that if their copies were loſt / they may vouche and reſort to the lordes court rolles / and the ſtewarde maye make them newe copyes / accordynge to the olde preſydent in the lordes court role / lyke as at the commen lawe / whan a mater in varyaūce bytwene two men is paſt by verdyt / and iudgement gyuen therof / and entred in the kynges recordes / ther it reſteth of recorde. and

alſo yf a dede or a patent be inrolled / there it remeyneth of recorde in lyke maner. ſo yt if any partie wyll haue any copye therof / they maye ſue to the iudges &amp; the offycers of the place where the recorde lyeth / and haue a copye therof exemplyfied vnder the ſeale of offyce of the ſame place / where ſuche recorde lyeth / and maye plede the ſame recorde in euery court the kyng hathe / and the lordes ſtewarde maye do in lyke maner. &amp;c.
            
            
               ¶The othe of all maner of offycers generally.
               ¶To whome the ſtewarde ſhall ſaye / ley thy hande vpon the boke and ſaye after me / I ſhall true conſtable be / trewe thridborowe / trewe reue / trewe frankelege / trewe tythingman / true ale taſter / trewe wodewarde / and trewe pynder / with ſuche other offycers that be vſed to be ſworne in ye lordes courte / and true preſētment make / and truely and duely do and kepe all thynges that belongeth to myne offyce to do / ſo helpe me god and my holydome / and kyſſe the boke.
            
            
               ¶The othe of a denyſen.
               ¶I ſhall true liegeman be / and true faythe beare to kyng Henry that nowe is / and to his heyres / and no trayſon do / nor thervnto aſſent / nor no thefte do / nor no theues felowe be / nor any of them to knowe / But that I ſhall enforme and do to witte them that be the

kynges offycers therof that haue ye lawe to gouerne. and I ſhall be buxome and obeydient to iuſtyces / cō
                  myſſioners / ſheriffes / exchetours / baylyes / and conſtables / and to all other offycers of the kynges in all thynges that they commaunde me to do laufully / ſo helpe me god and halydome. &amp;c.
            
            
               ¶The othe of afferoure.
               ¶I ſhall truely affere this court / and highe no man for no hate / ne lowe no man for no loue / but to ſette euery man truely after the quantite of his treſpace to my knowledge / ſauyng to a gentylman his counteynaunce and his houſeholde / a machaunt his marchā
                  dyſe / a huſbande his tenure and his werke beeſtes to his ploughe / ſo helpe me god and my holydome.
               This artycle gothe farther. Et quantum reddant per annum de redditu aſſiſe. And howe moche they yelde by the yere of rente of aſſiſe. And firſt ye ſhall knowe / that there be thre maner of rentes / that is to ſaye: rent ſeruyce / rent charge / and rent ſeeke. Rent ſeruyce / is wher a man holdeth his lādes of his lorde by fealtie &amp; certayne rent / or by homage / fealtie &amp; certayne rent / or by any other ſeruice and certayne rent. This is a rēt ſeruyce / &amp; if the rent be behynde at any day yt it ought to be payed at / the lord may diſtreyne for that rent of cōmen right / and if the lorde purchaſe parcell of the ſayd lande that the rent gothe out of / ye rent ſhalbe apporcyoned: except it be an entter rent / 

as a ſperhauke / or a horſe / or ſuche other that can nat be ſeuered / for than the rent is extinct and gone for euer. &amp;c. Rent charge / is where a man is ſeaſed of landes in fee and graunt by poole dede or by dede indented▪ Annuell rent goyng out of the ſame landes in fee or in fee tayle or for terme of lyfe / with a clauſe of dyſtreſſe that is a rent charge / and the graūtee maye diſtreyne for the ſame rent / bycauſe of the clauſe of dyſtreſſe. But if the graunte purchaſe parcell of ye ſayd landes / wherof the ſayd rent gothe out / the hole rent charge is extynct and gone for euer. For ſuche a rent charge maye nat be apporcioned / bycauſe the landes come to his owne poſſeſſion by his owne acte or dede Rent ſeeke / is wher a man is ſeaſed of landes in fee graunt / a rent goyng out of the ſame without a clauſe of diſtreſſe / that is a rent ſeeke and it is called a rēt ſeeke / bycauſe there is no diſtreſſe inſedent nor belō
                  gyng to the ſame. Alſo if a man by dede indēted make a feoffement in fee or in fee tayle / the remayndre ouer in fee or for terme of lyfe remeyner ouer in fee / reſeruyng to hym certayne rente without any clauſe of diſtreſſe in the ſame. That is a rent ſeeke / and if the graunte were neuer ſeaſed of the ſaid rent / he is with out remayndre by courſe of the cōmen lawe. Ther is another maner of rent: that is nother rente ſeruyce / rent charge / nor rent ſeeke / and that is called rent annuell. And that is / where as a man graunteth by his dede / an annuitie of .xx.s. be it more or laſſe / and chargeth no lande with the payment of the ſame. That is a rent annuell / and it chargeth the perſon that graunteth

the ſayd rent by a writte of annuite / and in ſome cauſe a rent charge / may become an annuell rent. as and a man graunt a rente charge out of his lande wt a clauſe of dyſtreſſe / the graunte is at lybertie / wheder he wyll diſtreyne for the rent / or ſewe a writ of an nuyte agaynſt the graunter. And if he ſewe his writ of annuyte / the lande is dyſcharged of any diſtreſſe. and therfore the grauntour maye make a prouycion in his graunt .s. prouiſo ſemper / ꝙ preſens ſcriptum nec aliquid in eo ſpecificatum non aliqualiter ſe extendat ad onorandū perſonam meam per breue / vel actionem de annuite. ſed tantūmodo ad onorandū terras / et tenementa predicta de annuali redditu predicto. And this prouyſe had / the landes be charged and the perſon diſcharged.
            
         
         
            ¶Of thoſe free tenauntes that ſewe to the courte of the countie / and who ſeweth nat / and howe moche falleth to the lorde after the deceſſe of ſuche tenaū
               tes. Cap. xii.
            
               ITem inquirendum eſt de predictis libere tenentibus et qui ſecuntur / ad cur ad com̄ in cōmitatu / et qui non / &amp; quantum accidit domīo poſt mortem taliū liberorum tenentium. It is to be enquered of the foreſayd free tenauntes / whiche of them ſhall folowe the court of the countie and whiche nat / &amp; what ſhall fall vnto the lorde / after the dethe of ſuche free tenauntes. Me ſemeth that all maner ſuche tenaūtes

that holde their lande by ſuche ſeruyce hauyng charter lande / ought to folowe the court of the countie / if he be ſomoned to appere / excepte he haue a ſpecyall graunt by chartour / of the kyng to the contrary. and to be ſworne in inquyries before the iuſtyce of peace / iuſtyce of aſſiſe / excheters / coroners / and all other cō
               miſſyoners of the kynges / &amp; bitwene partie and ꝑtie as the lawe hath ordayned it. howbeit in ſome caſe he ſhall diſpende &amp; haue more landes than in ſome caſe. that is to ſay / if the domage in plee ꝑſonell: as dette treſpas / detynue / and ſuche other / be declared vnder the value of .xl. markes. Than a freholder that hath any charter lande / be it more or leſſe / maye paſſe bytwene partie and partie. And alſo he is ſufficyent to enquere for the kyng in euery byll of indytement / of felony / and ſo is euery conſtable and freman / though he haue no lande. But ther ſhall no conſtable nor fre holder enquere of ryot nor forcyble entrees / without he maye diſpende .xl.s. clerely. and therfore ſe the ſtatute of kyng Richarde the .ii. &amp; kyng Henry the .vii. and alſo wher the domages in plee ꝑſonell de declared .xl. markes. or aboue / the freholder muſt haue lā
               des to ye clere value of .xl.s. And euery man that ſhall paſſe of lyfe and dethe and for tytell of lande be it neuer ſo lytell / he muāſt haue ldes to the value of .xl.s. clerely aboue all charges. And in atteynt / if the thing in demaunde and verdyte vpon that gyuen / extende to ye value of .xl.li. or aboue. Than euery man of the graunt iury / muſt haue landes to the value of .xx.li.
of freholde / out of auncient demeyne. and of landes

in Gauelkynde .xx.li. and yf it be vnder the value of xl.li. than .xl.s. of freholde is ſuffycient. The ſtatute reherſeth further. Quid et quantum accidit dn̄o poſt mortem talium libere tenentium. What and howe moche falleth to the lorde / after the dethe of ſuche fre tenauntes / That is and maye be / dyuers maners of rentes / cuſtomes / &amp; ſeruyces / As and a tenaunt holde of ye lorde by knight ſeruyce deceſſe / his heyre beyng of full age / the lorde ſhall haue for euery knightes fee that the tenaūt holdeth of the lorde. C. s. of his heyre in the name of relefe. For the whiche the lorde maye diſtreyne in euery ꝑcell of that lande that is ſo holden of hym for the ſame / of cōmen ryght. And if it be vnder a hole knyghtes fee / as halfe a kynghtes fee / the thirde parte / the fourthe parte / or the .xx. parte more or laſſe / the relefe ſhalbe apporcyonate / accordyng to the ſame / &amp; ſhall paye his chefe rentꝭ if any be neuertheleſſe. And yf the tenaunt deceſſe / his heyre beyng within age of .xxi. yeres / the lorde ſhall haue ye warde and the kepyng of the body duryng his nonage / and if he be vnmaryed / than his maryage to gyue or ſell to whome he wyll without diſpargement / and whan he cometh of full age / he ſhall pay no relefe. and if he be maryed and vnder the age of .xiiii. yeres / he may refuſe and diſagre / but howe the garden or his commytte or graūte ſhall tende / and offre mariage to the warde / and if the warde refuſe the offre / or if the warde be rauyſſhed and of wardes bycauſe of wardes / and of diſpargementes of wardes / and diſagrementes after maryage / and of waſt done by the garden / 

or his cōmytte or graunte / with mo artycles parteynyng to the ſame. I remytte all thoſe poyntꝭ to men of lawe that haue knowlege &amp; experience therof / for it toucheth nat my mater that I treat of. &amp; if the tenant haue yſſue female / aboue the age of .xiiii. yere / be ſhe maryed or nat maryed / the lorde ſhall nat haue the warde ne the maryage / bycauſe the lawe entendeth yt ſhe hath a huſbande or maye haue a huſbande at that age / able to do ſuche ſeruyce. But &amp; the heyre female be vnder the age of .xiiii. yeres vnmaryed / the lorde ſhall haue bothe the landes holden of him and ye maryage / tyll ſhe come to the age of .xiiii. yeres / and two yeres further to tende her mariage in / if ſhe be vnmaryed. and at the two yeres ende / ſhe may entre in to her landes and put out her garden / and to marry her ſelfe at her pleaſure. but and ſhe be maryed before the age of .xiiii. yeres in the lyfe of her aūceſtr / and than her aunceſtr dye / the lorde ſhall haue ye warde of the lande to the age of .xiiii. yeres / and than her huſbāde and ſhe maye entre and putte out the lorde / and if the tenaūt holde of two lordes by knyght ſeruyce / of one by priorite and of another by poſteryorite and dye / the lorde that the tenaunt holdeth of by priorite / ſhall haue the warde of the body / be it heyre male or heyre female / thoughe there be thre or foure doughters / for all they are but one heyre to the landes that beholden of hym. And the other lorde of whome the landes be holden of by poſteryorite / ſhall haue thoſe landes holden of hym ſelfe / and nothyng els. And if the tenaūt holde landes of one lorde by knyght ſeruyce / and alſo

holde landes of another lorde by ſoccage and dye / his heyres beyng within age / the lorde of whome the landes be holden of by knyght ſeruyce / ſhall haue the warde and maryage of the heyre and the landes holden of hym / but he ſhall nat haue the landes holden in ſocage / nor the lorde of whome they be holden of / nother / For thoſe landes holden in ſocage durynge the nonage / ſhall go to the next of the blode / to whom the enherytaunce may nat diſcende / wherof he ſhall make acompt vnto the heyre whan he cometh of full age &amp;c. And if the heyre be of full age at the deceſſe of his aunceſtre / he ſhall paye a relefe to euery lorde that he holdeth any lande of / yf relefe be due to be payed / by reaſon of his tenure. But in caſe that a tenant holde dyuers manours of dyuers lordes by knight ſeruyce and haue but one parcell of lande holden of the kyng in capite / the kyng ſhall haue all the hole landes holden of euery lorde / duryng the nonage: and the mariage of ye heyre if he be vnmaryed. and if the heyre be vnder the age of .xiiii. yere &amp; wyll dyſagre to the maryage / than the kyng ſhall haue the maryage of hym or her / or the value therof. and the kyng ſhall paye no chiefe rent duryng the nonage / except it be foūde due to be payed in the offyce of therchetour. and many other thynges maye fall to the lordes as herryottes &amp; other cuſtomes / accordyng to their origynall dedes / and vſe of the maner. And ye ſhall vnderſtande / that there be two maner of herryottes: that is to wyt / herryot ſeruyce and herryot cuſtome. Herryot ſeruyce / is where a man hath gyuen landes and tenemētes to

another man and to his heyres / to holde of hym and of his heyres / as before the makynge of the ſtatute / Quia emptores terrarum / or ſythe ye makyng of the ſayd ſtatute to holde of ye chefe lorde of the fee / by the ſeruyce therof due &amp; of right accuſtomed / reſeruyng to hym certayne rentes / herryottes / or any other cuſtome. This is rent ſeruyce and herryot ſeruyce / bycauſe it is expreſſed in his origynall dede. Herryotte cuſtome is wher a man hath a lordſhip / wherin hath ben vſed tyme out of mynde / that euery tenaunt that holdeth any meſe place of ye lorde / ſhall gyue his beſt quycke good in the name of a herryotte to the lorde / and he that hath no quicke good / ſhall gyue his beſt deed good. And in ſome place the tenaunt ſhall gyue for euery meſe place yt he holdeth a herryot / thoughe the houſes were lette downe an hundred yere before / the whiche me ſemeth ſhulde be a great bribery and extorcyon / as I ſayd in the prologue of this treatyſe. And therfore it is wiſdome for euery man to take his houſe by indenture or by copye / wherin maye be expreſſed: what rentes / herryottes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces the tenaunt ſhall paye and do / for a lorde maye abridge and make leſſe his cuſtome by writyng. but thoughe he make writyng and ſpecifye what rent he ſhall paye / he muſt ſaye further / for all maner rentes / herryottes / cuſtomes / &amp; ſeruyces. And in ſome lordeſhyppe / euery man that dyeth within the ſame / be he the lordes tenaunt or nat / ſhall paye an herryotte. In ſo moche that if a ſtraunge man ryde or go by ye way

and dye within ſuche a lordſhyppe / he ſhall paye an herryot / the whiche is playne extorcyon and agaynſt the commen ryght / For bytwene the lorde and hym that dyed / ther was no maner of priuyte of bargayn or couynaūt. And in ſome lordſhyppe / the lorde ſhall take his herryotte before the perſon / or the vycare his mortuarye / &amp; in ſome places the churche before / And that is / as it hath ben accuſtomed and vſed tyme out of mynde. But for the mooſt parte / the lorde taketh before: bicauſe the lorde maketh couynaunt with his tenaunt in his lyfe / that he ſhall haue his beſt quycke good at his deceſſe / and the mortuary is nat due tyll he be deed / and the herryotte was couynaunted and graunted before in his lyfe / and the firſte bargayne muſt be obſerued and kepte. And alſo in ſome places it is parted bytwene the churche &amp; the lorde / and that is / where he that is deed hath no moore quycke good / but one horſe or one beeſt / and thā he that hath be vſed to choſe firſt / ſhall haue ye better parte by one penny / but of deed good / eyther partie ſhall haue one But there ſhall nother of them take any deed good / as longe as there is any quycke goodes / and in many lordſhyppes / it is vſed / that and the tenaunt leaue his houſe by his owne wyll / without any diſcharge of the lorde / ye tenaunt ſhall pay his beſt quicke good to the lorde in the name of an herryot. &amp; in ſome lordſhippes it is acuſtomed / that &amp; the tenant deꝑte fro ye lordſhyp by his owne wyll / he ſhall make a fyne with the lorde for his deꝑtyng / &amp; mooſt cōmenly it is .ii.s.

and it is called a farefee or a farewell. And ſuche a tenaunt that gothe at his owne wyll ſhall make all maner of reparacyons / and that tenaunt that is dyſcharged by the lorde or by his offycers / ſhall make no reparacions / except he be diſcharged for nat doyng reperacions. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe many cuſtomary tenantes there be / &amp; howe moche landes euery of thē holdeth / and what werkes and cuſtomes they do / &amp; what the werkes and the cuſtomes of euery tenaunt is worthe by ye yere and howe moche euery of thē payeth / ouer the cuſtomes and werkes. &amp;c. Cap. xiii.
            
               ITem inquirend eſt de cuſtumariis videlicet quot ſunt cuſtumarii / et quant rerre qui libet cuſtumarius teneat / quas operatiōes quas conſuetudines facit / et quantū valent opera et conſuetudines cuiuſlibet cuſtumarii / per ſe per annum et quantum redditum de redditu aſſiſe per annum preter opera &amp; conſuetudines / et qui poſſunt talliari ad voluntatem dn̄i / et qui non. It is to be enquered of cuſtomarye tenauntes / that is to wytte / howe many there be &amp; howe moche lande euery tenaunt holdeth / and what werkes and cuſtomes he dothe / and what the werkes and cuſtomes be worthe of euery tenaunt by it ſelfe / and howe moche rente by the yere / aboue his werkes and cuſtomes he dothe paye / and whiche of them maye taxe their landes at the wyll of the lorde / and whiche nat. Cuſtomary

tenauntes / are thoſe that holde their landes of their lorde by copye of courte role / after the cuſtome of the maner. And ther may be many tenaūtes with in the ſame manere yt haue no copyes / and yet holde be lyke cuſtome and ſeruyce at the wyll of the lorde. and in myne opinyon / it began ſoone after the conqueſt / whan Wyllyam Conquerour had conquered this realme / he rewarded all thoſe that cāe with hym in his voyage royall / accordyng to their degre. And to honourable men he gaue / lordſhippes / maners / lā
               des / and tenementes / withall the inhabytaūtes / men and women dwellyng in the ſame / to do with thē at their pleaſure. And thoſe honourable men thought yt they muſt nedes haue ſeruauntes and tenaūtes / and their landes occupyed with tyllage. Wherfore they ꝑdoned the inhabytauntes of their lyues / and cauſed them to do all maner of ſeruyce that was to be done / were it neuer ſo vyle / and cauſed thē to occupye their landes and tenementes in tyllage / and toke of them ſuche rētes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / as it pleaſed thē to haue. And alſo / toke all their goodes &amp; catell at all tymes at their pleaſure / and called them their bonde men. and ſythe that tyme / many noble men bothe ſpirytuall and temporall of their godly diſpoſycion / haue made to dyuers of the ſayd bonde men manumiſſions / and graunted them fredome and lybertie. and ſet to them their landes and tenemētes to occupy / after dyuers maners of rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces the whiche is vſed in dyuers places vnto this daye. how be it in ſome places the bonde men contynue as

yet / the whiche me ſemeth is the gretteſt inconuenyēt that nowe is ſuffred by the lawe. That is to haue any chriſten man bonden to another / and to haue the rule of his body / landes &amp; goodes / that his wife chyldren and ſeruauntes / haue laboured for all their lyfe tyme / to be ſo taken / lyke as and it were extorcion or bribery. And many tymes by colour therof / there be many fre men taken as bonde men / and their landes and goodes taken fro them / ſo that they ſhall nat be able to ſue for remedy / to proue them ſelfe fre of blode And that is mooſt commenly / where the fre men haue the ſame name as the bonde men haue / or that his aunceſters of whome he is comen / was manumiſed before his byrthe. In ſuche cauſe there can nat be to great a punyſſhement. for as me ſemeth / there ſhulde no man be bonde but to god / and to his king &amp; prince ouer hym. Quia deus non facit exceptionem perſonarum. For god maketh no excepcyon of any perſon Wherfore it were a charytable dede / to euery noble man bothe ſpūall and temporall / to do as they wolde be done by / &amp; that is to manumiſe them that be bonde and to make them free of body and blode / reſeruyng to them their rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / of olde tyme due and accuſtomed / wherin they may geat the prayers of the partie and remiſſyon of their offēces / as in the hoſpell. Eadem menſura qua menſi fueritis remiſictur vobis. The ſame meaſure that ye do mete to other men / ſhall be metton to you. In many lordſhyppes / there is a cuſtomary roole bytwene the lordes and their tenauntes / and it ought to be indented

/ one parte to remayne in the lordes kepynge / the other parte with the tenauntes / and dyuers true copyes to be made of the ſame / that the rentes and cuſtomes ronne nat out of remēbraunce. And alſo a ſuyte rooll / to calle all thoſe by name that oweth any ſuyte to the lordes court / and than ſhall there be no counſelment of the ſutours / but that ye ſtewarde may knowe who is nat there. &amp; if any ſuctour deceſſe / the name of his next heyre wolde be entred in to the ſame roole / &amp; an inquery made and preſented what he helde of the lorde / and by what tentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyce of euery parcell by itſelfe / &amp; who is his nexte heyre and of what age he is of. and this truely done and entred in to the role / it wolde be a conueyaunce of diſcent in maner of a pee degre / and profytable to the lordes / and alſo to the tenauntes / cauſa patet. The name of euery tenaunt muſt be put in the roole / and his meſe place to be butted &amp; bonded / as it lyeth in length and brede / and bytwene whom. And alſo / his landes / medowes / leys and paſtures / lykewiſe butted and bonded / that it maye be knowen many yeres after who dwelled there: and what landes / medowes / and paſtures / laye to the ſame at that tyme. And what warkes and cuſtomes the tenaunte dothe for euery parcell / and what the werkes and cuſtomes be worthe in a yere / and howe moche rent ye tenant dothe paye for euery parcell beſyde the cuſtomes and werkes / to the entent that if any parcell of lande / medowe or paſtur
be aliend / ſolde / or chaūged / or put from one tenaunt

to another. The lorde &amp; his baylye may knowe what rentes / cuſtomes / and werkes / he ſhall aſke and haue of the occupyer for euery parcell. And it is the mooſt ſpeciall poynt that longeth to a ſurueyour / to but and bounde truely euery parcell by it ſelfe / and to knowe what rentes / werkes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / gothe out of the ſame / for than maye he make a true rentall or cuſtomarye roole / and putte all thynges in a certentie.
         
         
            ¶Of cotyers what cotages and curtilages they holde and by what ſeruyce / and howe moche rent they paye by the yere. &amp;c. Cap. xiiii.
            
               ITem inquirendū eſt de cotorellis / que cotagia &amp; curtilagia teneant / et ꝑ quod ſeruic / et quantū reddant per annum / pro predict cotagiis et curtilagiis. Alſo it is to be enquered of Cotagers / what cotages and curtylages they holde / &amp; by what ſeruyce: and what they yelde by the yere for the foreſayd cotages and curtylages. This chapiter and the next preſent be bothe of one effecte / but that it is to p̄
               ſume / that ther is nat ſo moche rentes / herryottes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces to be payed &amp; done for a cotage as there is for a meſe place or a better tenement / but it maye be lyke cuſtome and ſeruyce.
         
         
            
            ¶Of perqueſytes or profytes of counties / of courtes / and of foreſtes / what they be worthe by the yere. &amp;c. Cap. xv.
            
               ITem inquirend eſt de perqueſitis com mitatuū 
               cur foreſtariorum cum expeditamentis canum &amp; quantum valent per annum in oībus exitibus. Alſo it is to be enquered / of the perqueſytes and profytes of the coūties / of the courtes and of the foreſtes with the cuttynge of of the dogges cleyſe / and howe moche they be worthe by the yere in all the iſſues and profytes. This chapiter toucheth nat the offyce of a ſurueyour but lytell / for ye yſſues and profytes of the coūties / ſeſſyons / and aſſiſes / are mooſt cōmenly the kynges / and they be kept and ordayned by the ſhiryf and the iuſtyces of peace / that be ordayned and put in cōmyſſion by the kyng and his counſayle / and the iſſues and profytes of them are eſtreyted by the ſayd iuſtices / and returned in to the kynges eſcheker / and ther they reſt of recorde / the whiche afterwarde is eſtreyted agayne / and ſende downe to the ſhiryffes of euery countie to leuy and gader vp the ſame / &amp; therof to make an accōpte in the ſayd eſcheker / and it is called grene waxe. And the courtes of the foreſtes be ordayned and kepte by the iuſtyces of the foreſtes and their deputies / and the iſſues and profites therof / the whiche cometh mooſt cōmenly by fynes and mercymentes are nat eſtreyted in to the eſcheker / but made out by the ſtewarde to the baylyes and other officers

of them that oweth the forreſt. And there me ſemeth / the Surueyour maye ſytte with the iuſtyces of the forreſtes to one thyng ſpecially / and that is this. that no townſhyppe nor hamell entre comen within the foreſtes / chaſes / waſtes / heythes / moores / and ſuche other great cōmens / but all onely ſuche that of ryght ought to haue commen within the ſame. Wherfore it wolde be ordayned / that euery towneſhyppe and hamell that ought to haue any ſuche commen in any foreſtes / chaſes / waſtes / moores / heythes / and ſuche other great cōmens: where dyuers townſhyppes and hamels entre cōmen toguyder. Euery townſhyppe and hamell ought to haue a dyuers brennynge yron and euery beeſt / horſe / mare / &amp; colte that is put vpon the cōmen / ought to be brenned in ſome parte of his body with the ſayde yron / and than ſhall euery beeſt be knowen of what townſhippe he is / And that were a great redyneſſe to the kepers / and alſo a great ſauegarde for ſtealyng of the catell. And than may the kepars / regarders / goyſters / and other offycers of ſuche foreſt and chaſes / haue parfyte knowledge what townſhyppe the catell is of. And if any of theſe ſayde officers fynde any maner of catell hauynge no ſuche brenne / they maye attache theym and ceaſe theym as ſtreyes / and put them in ſauegarde to the lordes vſe / tyll they be yered and deyd. And they ought to aſke them thre ſondayes in thre or four next paryſſhe churches / and alſo crye them thre tymes in thre the nexte market townes. And if no man come within the yere and the day / and to make ſuffycient proue that the catell

is his / than it is forfayte to the lorde as a ſtrey. &amp; in lyke maner the ſwyne and ſhepe of euery townſhip and hamell / ought to be pytched with the ſayd brennyng yron / or ſuche another lyke the ſame. but as for all other poyntes and artycles touchyng the foreſtes the Surueyour hath lytell to do. Wherfore I remyt all other artycles to the iuſtyces of the foreſtes and to their deputies to execute their office. &amp; ye ſhall knowe that no man ſhall haue a foreſt of right but the kyng / except he or his aunceſt
                  •
               rs haue had a ſpecyall graūt therof by charter / of the kyng and his progenytours in tymes paſt / and ſo vſed. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Of churches that belong to the gyfte of the lorde / howe many there be / and wher they be / &amp; what euery churche is worthe. &amp;c. Cap. xvi.
            
               ITem inquirend eſt de eccleſiis / que pertinent ad donationem dn̄i / quot ſunt / et vbi / &amp; quantū valent / et quātum quelibet ecclia valet per ſe per annum / ſcdm verā eſtimationem illius It is to be enquered of all ye churches that belong to the lordes gyft / how many ther be &amp; where they be / &amp; what they be worthe / &amp; what euery church is worthe by it ſelfe by the yere / after the true eſtimacyon of the ſame. The letter of this chapiter is very playne &amp; nedeth nat moch declaracion further than is ſpoken of / but alonely in one thyng / &amp; that is thus. oft tymes he yt hath right to preſent to a churche at one tyme / hath nat right to preſent to ye ſaid church at the next tyme.

And that is where any ſole patrone of a churche hath iſſue / two / thre / or four doughters and deceſſe / ſo that the right of patronage of the ſayd churche diſcēdeth to all the ſayd doughters. Whan ye churche is voyde they ſhall preſent by tourne / the eldeſt doughter firſt: than the ſeconde at the next auoydaunce / than the .iii. and ſo forthe / tyll they haue preſented ones ouer. and than to begyn agayne at the eldeſt doughter / excepte they make any other perticyon among them ſelfe by agrement. And than muſt euery one of them preſent by their tourne / accordyng to their petycion / as it cometh about. And ſo muſt the Surueyour make his boke accordyng to the ryght of the preſentacyon / as euery tyme / ſecōde tyme / thirde tyme / or fourth tyme and ſo forthe. Alſo what lordes or Gentylmen haue their tourneyſe with them in the ſame benifyce / and whiche of thē preſented laſt / and who ſhall haue next / and who than / tyll they haue gone aboute. &amp; in what towne it is / and in what ſhyre and dyociſe it is / and what euery benifyce is worthe by it ſelfe by the yere / as it canne be eſtymate.
         
         
            ¶What the herryottes be worthe / the feyres / exchetes / cuſtomes / ſeruyces / and forreyne warkes: the plees and perqueſites of the courtes / fynes / relefes / &amp; all other thynges that may fall to the lorde by the yere. &amp;c. Cap. xvii.
            
               
               INquirendum eſt quantum valent herriotta / nūdine / eſcaeta / conſuetudines / et ſeruic
et operationes forinſie / et quantum valent placita / et perqueſita fines / et reliuia / et omnia alia que accidere poſſunt per annum in omnibus. It is to be enquered / what be the value of herryottes / feyres / exchetes / cuſtomes / ſeruyces / &amp; forreyne warkes: and what the plees be worthe / and the perqueſytes or profites of the courtes / fynes / relefes / and all other thynges maye fall by the yere in all. This chapiter gothe in a generalytie and is lyke / as whan an audytour hath caſt all the myniſtr and partyculer accomptes of euery baylye or reue and other accomptance / and hath made his boke parfyte of all the partyculer / whervpon the whole charge reſteth. Than whan the lorde wolde knowe what thertent is of all his hole landes / and alſo of euery ꝑtyculer parcell by it ſelfe / it were to long a proceſſe to ſhewe hym all the ſayde minyſtr and partyculer accomptes / and thoughe he dyde / he ſhulde nat knowe the groſe ſommes of his rentes / fynes / herryottes / exchetes / ꝑqueſytes &amp; ſuche other / euery of them by hym ſelfe. Wherfore he wyll cauſe his audytoure to make a value in maner of a bridgement of all the ſayd minyſtre accō
               ptes / and firſt to knowe the hole charge of all the partyculers / what they be at the firſt ſyght / in the ſōmes totall. Than to deuyde the ſōmes totall in dyuers ꝑcels / as the chefe rentes of the freholders by thēſelfe / the rentes of cuſtomary tenaūtes by thēſelfe / tenauntes by indēture / or tenaūtes at the lordes wyll by thē
               
ſelfe  ſo that he may make a groſe ſōme of euery maner of rent▪ ſo that one rēt may be knowen from another. But than muſt the audytour haue good &amp; parfyte informacion / or els he can nat do it. and that informacion muſt come by the ſurueyour &amp; the baylyes for they ought to knowe one maner of rent from another / and therfore their rentalles wolde be made a cordyng / alſo the perqueſytes of the courtes by thēſelfe. And thoſe muſt be in lyke maner deuyded / as ye plees by them ſelfe / the mercementes for cōmen treſpace by them ſelfe / fynes by them ſelfe / herryottes by thēſelfe exchetes by them ſelfe / and ſo of relefes / feyres / markettes / and all other caſualties / euery of thē by them ſelfe and ought to be preſented in the court by them ſelfe. And therof to be made an eſtreyt to the bayly or reue to gader by / &amp; brought in to the accompte to the audytour / the whiche he may deuyde in makynge of his value / if the accōptance bring hym perfyte rētals and court roles and nat els. but if they do it nat at the firſt tyme / he muſt teche and enforme thē howe they ſhulde make them perfyte. Alſo cuſtomes / ſeruyces / and warkes be ofte tyme done by bodely ſeruice and warkes / and than they be nat to be acompted for / but yet mencyon wolde be made in the accompte therof. And many tymes ſuche maner of cuſtomes / ſeruyces and warkes be tourned in to money: And than it cō
               menly gothe with the rentes / and the bayly or reue is charged therwith. And this chapiter reherſeth further / Et omnia alia que accider poſſit per annum in omnibus. And of all other thynges that maye fall to

the lorde / what they be worthe by the yere. and thoſe may be taken as mynes of tynne / leed / ore / cole / yron ſtonne / freſton / mylne ſtones / gryndell ſtones / lymeſtonne / chalke / furlers / erthe / Sande / cley / grauell / brome / gorſe or fyrs / marle / turues / thornes / woode / buſſhes / heyth / Ferne or braken / and ſuche other / yf there be any newe founde: and ought to be putte in a rentall to a certentie / or els to be putte in accompte by waye of approwment. And than thauditour may deuyde the caſualties from the certenties / and to make a groſe ſomme of them all. And yet maye the value of euery thyng appere and be knowen / howe moche it is by it ſelfe. And than muſt there be deduct out of the ſayd groſe ſomme all maner of out rentes and ordynary charges: as baylyes fees / reparacyon and ſuche other / and than̄e to make a clere groſe ſomme of euery yere by hym ſelfe / And bycauſe ofte tymes more caſualties falle or come to the lorde more in one yere than in another. Therfore it is conuenyent that the clere groſe ſommes of fyue or ſixe yeres or mo / wolde be caſt togider in one groſe ſomme / and to deuyde that ſomme in as many partes as ther was yeres caſt togyder / and than the clere value of one yere wyll be cōmenly about that ſomme ſo deuyded. And thus endeth the brefe declaracyon of this ſtatute Extenta manerii.
            ¶Explicit.
         
         
            
            ¶Of dyuers maners of takyng and doyng of homage &amp; fealtie. Cap. xviii.
            
               IN ſo moche I haue ſhewed dyuers dyuerſites of tenures / &amp; alſo dyuers maners of makyng of copyes / and the othes of the officers of the court / though they be nat expreſſed in the ſtatute. Me ſemeth alſo it were conuenyent to ſhewe the dyuerſytes &amp; maner of takyng and doyng of homage and fealtie. And ye ſhall vnderſtande / that homage is the mooſt honorable ſeruyce &amp; the mooſt hū
               ble ſeruyce of reuerēce / that a free man may do to his lorde. For whan the tenaunt ſhall do homage to his chefe lorde / of whōe he holdeth his chefe maner or mā
               cyon place / by knight ſeruyce and priorite. He ſhalbe vngirde and his heed vncouered / and the lorde ſhall ſyt &amp; the tenaunt ſhall knele before hym on bothe his knees / and ſhall holde his handes ſtretched out togyder bytwene the lordes handes / and ſhall ſaye thus. I become your man from this day forwarde of lyfe and of membre / and of worldely honour. And to you ſhall be faythfull and lowly and ſhall beare faythe to you / for the landes and tenemētes the which I holde of you / ſauyng the faythe that I owe to our ſoueraygne lorde the kyng and my other lordꝭ. And the lorde ſo ſytting ſhall kyſſe his tenaūt / the which is a ſygne

of perfyte loue. And why ſaythe the tenaun of lyfe &amp; of membre / and of all worldely honour? Bycauſe he holdeth his landes of his lorde by knight ſeruice and alſo by priorite. for and he holde other landes of a nother lorde by knight ſeruice and poſteriorite / he ſhall nat ſaye to hym of lyfe and of membre / for though he be bounde to hym by reaſon of his tenures of knyght ſeruyce / to go to batayle with his lorde / and to putte his life and membres in ieopardy with his lorde: yet can he nat go with them bothe. And therfore ſhall he go to batayle with that lorde that he holdeth his landes of by priorite. And bycauſe therof / if any ſuche tenāt dye / his heyre beyng within age / the lorde ſhall haue the kepyng of his body / and the profyte of thoſe landes that be holden of hym / duryng the nonage / &amp; alſo the maryage of hym. Wherfore it is to be preſuppoſed / that the lorde wyll be more louyng and kynde to hym / than any other of his frendes wolde be. Seyng / that whan he cometh of full age / he ſhall put his lyfe in ieopardy for his lorde / the whiche byndeth the lorde by reaſon the rather to do for hym / whan he is nat able to helpe hym ſelfe. Where as his frendꝭ may fortune cared nat for hym / and hadde leuer / another had the lande than he.
            ¶And yf an abbot or a priour / or any other man or woman of relygion ſhulde do homage / they ſhall ſay I become your man. &amp;c. bycauſe they be all onely ꝓfeſſed to god to be his men and women / and to none other. And therfore they ſhall knele and holde their

handes as the other dyde / and ſay thus. I do to you homage and to you ſhall be faythfull and lowly / for the landes and tenemētes the whiche I holde of you / ſauyng the faythe that I owe to our ſouerayne lorde the kyng. &amp;c.
            ¶And yf a woman ſole ſhulde do homage / ſhe ſhall nat ſaye / I become your woman: for it is nat conuenyent that a woman ſhulde become woman / to any other man than to her huſbāde / whan ſhe is maryed. And therfore ſhe ſhall ſaye as the relygious men and women dothe. I do to you homage. &amp;c.
            ¶And if a woman couert with baron ſhall do homage / they ſhall knele before the lorde bothe / &amp; the lorde ſhall take bothe their handes bytwene his handes / &amp; the huſbande ſhall ſpeke all the wordes / as thus. We to you do homage / and faythe to you we ſhall beare for the landes that we holde of you / ſauyng the fayth that we owe to our ſouerayne lorde the kyng his heyres / and to our other lordes: &amp; they bothe ſhall kyſſe the lorde. &amp;c.
            ¶And in caſe a man ſhulde do homage to his lorde / and the lorde graunt his homage and ſeruyce to a nother man. Nowe ſhall the tenaunt do his homage &amp; ſeruyce to the grauntee / after this maner. I become your man fro this day forthe / and to you ſhalbe faithfull and lowly / for the landes and tenementes that I helde of A. B. your grauntour / in the townes of C.

D. the whiche to you he hath graunted my homage and ſeruyce in the ſayde townes / ſauynge the faythe that I owe to our ſoueraigne lorde the kyng and my other lordes. &amp;c.
            ¶And knowe you / that one lorde may haue done to hym dyuers homages of dyuers tenauntes / for one maner of lande. But one tenaūt ſhall do but ones homage for one maner of lande / for thoughe the lorde dye / his heyre or his aſſigne / if he ſell it or graunt it a way / they do repreſent the lordes eſtate. But and the tenaunt haue done his homage to his lorde / and after the maner / wherof the tenaūt holdeth his landes is recouered agaynſt the lorde. Nowe ſhall the tenāt do his homage agayne to him that recouered the manere / for he cometh nat in by the lorde / but by force of the recouere / the whiche proueth the firſt homage to be voyde / for it was done to hym that had no ryght to take it. &amp;c.
            ¶Alſo ye ſhall knowe / that a man maye diſtreyne his tenauntes catell for homage by courſe of the commen lawe / and alſo for relefe. And though a man haue payed his relefe / yet he ſhall do homage and feaultie. alſo ye ſhall vnderſtande / that no man ſhall do homage / but he that hath a ſtate of enherytaunce in fee ſymple or in fee tayle / in his owne right or in his wyues / for tenauntes for terme of lyfe / tenauntes by the courteſye / nor tenaunt in dower / ſhall do no homage nor take no homage. &amp;c.
            
               ¶And if a man holde landes of the kyng in chiefe / &amp; haue yſſue thre or four doughters &amp; dye / all ye doughters ſhall do homage to the kynge. and if the landes be holden of another lorde / the eldeſt doughter ſhall do homage for all / and alſo ye ſeruyces. and the other doughters ſhall be contrybutories / and beare euery one of them their porcyon of the ſame.
            ¶And whan a fre man ſhall do feaultie to his lorde / he ſhall ley his hande vpon the booke / and ſhall ſaye thus. Here you my lorde that I W.O.D.E. fro this day forthe / to you ſhalbe faythfull and lowly / &amp; fayth to you ſhall beare for the landes and tenemētes / that I clayme to holde of you / and loyally ſhall do &amp; paye the rentes / cuſtomes / and ſeruyces / that I ought to do at the termes aſſygned / as god me helpe &amp; all ſayntes / and than kyſſe the boke.
            ¶Whan a villayne ſhall do feaultie to his lorde / he ſhall ley his hande vpon the boke and ſay thus. Here you my lorde R. that IW. de C. fro thus day forthe to you ſhalbe faythfull and lowly / and to you ſhall do all the cuſtomes and ſeruyces that I ought to do to you / for the landes that I holde of you in vyllenage / and I ſhall be iuſtifyable of body and of goodes / as god me helpe and his ſayntes / and than kyſſe. &amp;c.
            ¶Whan a villayne that holdeth no landes of ye lorde ſhall do feaultie / he ſhall ley his hande vpon the boke and ſaye thus. Here you my lorde S. that IW.B.

fro this day forthe to you ſhalbe faythfull and lowly and I ſhalbe iuſtifyable to you of body and of goodꝭ as god me helpe and his ſayntes / &amp; kyſſe the boke. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶What a ſurueyour ſhulde do. Cap. xix.
            
               NOwe this ſtatute is breuely declared / it wolde be vnderſtande / howe a lordſhyp or a maner ſhu de be ſurueyed &amp; vewed butted and bounded on euery ꝑte / that it maye be knowen for euer / whoſe euery parcell therof was / at the makyng of this boke. &amp; it may ſerue as well to ſaue the inherytaūce of the lordes / as of euery fre holder by charter / copye holder / &amp; cuſtomary holder / and to knowe euery mānes lande as it lyeth to his houſe one frō another. ſo that it may be knowen an hūdred yeres after and for euer / what maner of landes / and howe many acres euery man had to his houſe at that tyme / and where they lyeth. The name of a ſurueyour is a frenche name / and is as moche to ſay in Englyſſhe as an ouerſeer. Than it wolde be knowen / howe a ſurueyour ſhulde ouerſe 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               uruey a towne or a lordſhyppe / as and the cytie of London ſhulde be ſurueyed. The ſurueyour may nat ſtande at Hygate / nor at Shoterſhyll / nor yet at the Blackheth nor ſuche other places / and ouer loke the cytie on euery ſyde. For and he do / he ſhall nat ſe the goodly ſtretes / the fayre buyldinges / nor ye great ſubſtaunce of richeſſe conteyned in them / for than he

maye be called a diſceyuer &amp; nat a ſurueyer. &amp; in lyke wiſe if a man ſhall vieu a cloſe or a paſture / he maye nat loke ouer the hedge &amp; go his way / but he muſt outher ryde or go ouer / &amp; ſe euery parcell therof. and to knowe howe many acres it cōteyneth / &amp; howe moche therof was medowe grounde / howe moche paſture groūde / howe moche wode grounde or buſſhe groū
               de / heythe / lyng / or ſuche other. &amp; what an acre of medowe groūde is worthe / and what an acre of paſture and what an acre of the woode grounde or buſſhe / &amp; ſuche other be worthe. And what maner of catell it is beſt for / and howe many catell it wyll graſſe or fynde by the yere / and what a beaſtes graſſe is worthe by the yere in ſuche a paſture / or els he can nat ſet a true value what it is worthe. And therfore a Surueyour muſt be dilygēt and laborous and nat ſlouthfull and recheleſſe / for and he be / he is nat worthy to haue his fee or wages / and may fortune to make an vnperfite boke / And if he ſo do / it is to his ſhame &amp; rebuke / and great ieopardy to his ſoule to make a falſe preſydent Wherfore it is conuenyent to remembre the ſayenge of the wyſe philoſofer. Abhibe curam. that is to ſaye take hede to thy charge. &amp; ſo if he ſhulde vieu a cytie or a towne / he muſt begyn at a certayne place / as and it were at the drawe bridge of London bridge on the Eeſt ſyde / and there to make his tytelynge where he begīneth and to ſhewe who is lorde of the houſe next vnto the ſayd bridge / and who is tenaunt. And if he be a free holder / what chefe rent it payeth to the lorde cuſtomes or other ſeruyces. and if it be no free holde / 

than the rent nedeth nat to be ſpoken of but at his pleſure / for it maye ryſe and fall / and howe many fote in brede and howe many en length. Than to the ſecōde houſe on the ſame Eeſt ſyde in lyke maner / and ſo to peruſe from houſe to houſe / tyll he come to ſaynt Magnus church. And than retourne agayne to the ſayd drawe bridge on the Weſt ſyde / and ther begynne at the houſe next to the ſayd bridge / and ſo to peruſe fro houſe to houſe / tyll he come to the corner next Tēmes ſtrete. and than he may choſe wheder he wyll folowe the ſouthe ſyde of the ſayd Tēmes ſtrete Weſtwarde and Eeſtwarde / tyll he haue peruſed the hole pariſſh And if there be any maner of gardens / entres / or aleys / or other dwellyng places withīforthe / they may nat be ouerſkipped / forgoten / nor laft out / but taken by the way: Howe moche euery garden is / howe longe euery aley and entre is / and how many dwellyng places be therin / and whoſe they be / and howe many cellars or tauernes there be / and howe many footes euery one of them be in length and brede. And ſo to go from paryſſhe to paryſſhe / tyll he had viewed the cytie / and euery ſtrete and lane wolde be remembred what length &amp; brede they be of. And alſo / euery churche and churche yarde &amp; other voyde places / the whiche wolde aſke a great leyſar / but yet it is poſſyble to be done.
         
         
            ¶Howe a man ſhulde vieu / but and bounde / the maner and the towneſhyppe. Cap. xx.
            
               
               ¶The towne of Dale.
               
                  THe vieu of the maner of Dale taken the tenth day of May / the .xiiii. yere of the raygne of kyng Henry the .viii. by AB generall Surueyour to the ryght honorable lorde C. D. lorde of the ſame &amp; by his cōmaūdement / &amp; alſo by the othes of EF. GH. &amp; many other tenātes of the ſame / as herafter enſueth.
               ¶The cytie of the maner of Dale / ſtandeth &amp; lyeth bytwene the kynges hyway leadyng from the towne of A. vnto the towne of B. on the ſouthe parte / &amp; the churche yarde of the ſame towne of Dale on the Eeſt ſyde / and the cōmen felde of the ſame towne called the northe felde on the northe parte. And the tenement or meſe place of Iohn̄ Coke on the Weſt parte / and conteyneth .xx. perches in brede &amp; .xxx. ꝑches &amp; four fote in length / euery perche .xvi. fote &amp; a halfe. Whervpon is ſet the maner place ſufficiently buylded / with two croſſe chābres of ſtonne / of bricke / or tymbre: withall maner of houſes of offyce within forthe / &amp; two barnes and an oxe houſe / a hey houſe and a ſtable / a garden &amp; an orcharde. And if it be moted about / expreſſe howe moche houſyng ſtandeth with in the mote / and howe moche without / and with what maner of coueryng the houſes be couered. The which maner with the demeanes / landes / medowes / leyſe / &amp; paſtures be nowe in the holdyng and occupacion of T. S. and payeth by the yere / at four termes or two tymes ther vſed .s. &amp;c. by euyn porcions .vi.li.xiii.s.iiii.

¶The cytie of the perſonage ſtandeth and lyeth bytwene the ſayd hyway on the ſouthe parte / &amp; the ſayd churche on the Weſt parte / and the ſayd northe felde on the northe parte / and the tenementes of I. C. on the Eeſt parte. And the ſayd perſon hath a crofte lyeng bytwene the ſayd northe felde and the ſayd churche yarde on the ſouthe parte. and the ſayd cytie and crofte cōteyneth .x. perches on the ſouthe ſyde / &amp; .xiiii. perches on the northe ſyde / and .xxx. perches in lēgth on the Eeſt ſyde / and .xvi. perches and a halfe on the Weſt ſyde. And the mancyon place &amp; the houſes ther vnto belongyng / be nowe ruynous / and one ſir S. B. is nowe perſon there / and had it of the gyfte of the lorde / to whom the gyft belongeth euery thirde tyme and to y. F. the next tyme / and C. D. the thirde turne and ſo as ofte as it falleth. And the ſayd. S. B. occupyeth the ſayd perſonage him ſelfe / withall the glebe landes / medowes / tythes / and all other frutes / and is worthe by the yere .xx.li. And in lyke maner of a vycarage / and than muſt ye ſhewe who is ꝑſone / the whiche mooſt cōmenly is a ſpirytuall man.
               ¶I. B. holdeth a meſe place frely of ye lorde by charter / with dyuers landes / medowes / and paſtures be longynge to the ſame. The whiche meſe place lyeth bytwene the ſayd hywaye and the ſayde northe felde (as before ſayd) and the ſayd perſonage on the Weſt ſyde / and the tenement or meſe place of F. G. on the Eeſt parte / and conteyneth .xii. perches on the ſouthe ende in brede / &amp; .xxii. perches and four fote in length

and .xvi. perches in brede on the northe ende. And he holdeth the ſayd meſe withall that longeth therto / of the ſayd lorde by homage / fealtie / and .ii.s. by ye yere and halfe a poūde of peper / &amp; ſuite of court from thre wekes to thre wekes / and to the two great letes. And this he may expreſſe the ſeruyce of the rent / if he may haue ꝑfyte knowledge by the lordes preſydens or by origynall dedes.
               ¶FG. holdeth a meſe place with the appurtenaūce of the ſayd lorde at his wyll / or by indenture or copye and it lyeth bytwene the ſayd hiwaye. and the northe felde and the foreſayd meſe place of IC. on the Weſt ſyde / and the felde called Eeſt felde on the Eeſt ſyde / cōteyneth .xi. perches and ſixe fote in brede / and .xviii perches &amp; ten fote in lēgth / And payeth vnto the lord
at the termes their vſuels / ſixtene ſhillynges / ſuite of courte / two hennes / and an herryot at his deceſſe. &amp;c.
               ¶GH. holdeth a cotage of the lorde by copye / &amp; ſtandeth bitwene the ſayd hiwaye on the northe ſyde / and the townfelde called the ſouthe felde on the ſouthe ꝑte and the ſayd Eeſt felde on the Eeſt ſyde / And a meſe place of the priour of B. on the weſt ſyde / &amp; it conteyneth by the hiway ſixe perches / and at the ſouth ende ſeuyn perches and eight fote / and on eyther ſyde .xii. perches / and payeth by the yere at the ſayde termes twentie pens / ſuyte of courte and one henne.
               ¶The priour &amp; the couent of B. holdeth a meſe place

and a croft with the appurtenance of the lorde frelye in pure almes / and it lyeth bytwene the ſayde cotage in the buyldinge of G H. on the Eeſt ſyde / and a meſe place of the lordes / in the holdyng of TS. on the weſt / and buttes vpon the ſayd hiway on the ſaid ſouthe felde / and conteyneth in brede by the ſayd hyway ſixtene perches / and in length twentie perches / and at the ſouthe ende twelfe Perches in brede / and payeth to the lorde halfe a poūde of peper for all maner of ſeruyce. &amp;c.
               ¶TS. holdeth a meſe place of the lorde by indenture / and it lyeth bytwene ye ſayd tenement of the priours on the Eeſt ſyde / and another hiwaye that leydeth or gothe fro the forſayd churche or ꝑſonage / vnto the towne of .z. on the Weſt ſyde / and bytwene the foreſayd hiwaye on the northe ſyde / and the tenemēt of the lordes in the holdyng of H. L. on the Southe ſyde / and it cōteyneth .x. perches euery way / &amp; payeth by the yere. &amp;c. ſuyte of courte and herryot. Alſo the ſayd ST holdeth of the lorde an horſe mylne / nexte adioyning to his ſayd meſe and the tenement of HL and is cōteyned bothe in length and brede within the ſayd .x. perches. Wherof the lorde ſhall fynde all the great tymbre and bring it to the mylne / and the mylner ſhall make all the coſt / bothe of the houſe and the goyng geyre. And alſo he ſhall bothe thacke &amp; daube at his owne coſt and charge / and payeth for the ſame at the ſaid termes ſixe ſhillynges / two hennes at chriſtenmas / and two capons at Paſche.
               
                  ¶H.L. holdeth a tenement of the lorde / and it lyeth bytwene the ſayd horſe myle on the northe ſyde / &amp; the ſayd ſouthe felde on the ſouthe ſyde / and buttes vpon the ſayd hiwaye yt leadeth to .z. on the Weſt / and the croft of the ſayd priours on the Eeſt / and conteyneth xii. perches and .x. fote in brede by the hywaye / and ix. perches in length to the ſayd crofte / and payeth at the termes aforeſayd .x.s. two hennes at Chriſtmas and ſuyte. &amp;c.
               ¶P.Q. holdeth a cotage of the lorde at his wyll / &amp; it lyeth bytwene the ſayde way that leadeth to .z. on the Eeſt ſyde / and a crofte of RX on the Weſt ſyde / and a felde called ſouthe felde on the ſouth ſyde / and the tenement of RX of the northe / and it cōteyneth in brede by the hiway four perchez / and in length ſixe perches and a halfe / and payeth. &amp;c.
               ¶RX. holdeth a tenement &amp; a crofte called the ſwan frely by charter / &amp; they lye vpon the corner bytwene the ſayd two hywayes / on the northe and Eeſt / and a tenement of the lordes / in the holdyng of WC. and a medowe called Weſt medowe on the Weſt ſyde / and a cotage in the holdynge of PQ. and ſouthe felde on the ſouthe ſyde. And it conteyneth in it ſelfe .viii. perches ſquare / and the crofte conteyneth .xii. perches in length and ſixe in brede / wherin be fyue buttes / of the whiche one but is the ſaid priour of B. that is to ſay next vnto the hedge on the Weſt ſyde except one. and he holdeth the ſayd tenement of the lorde by homage / feaultie / and aſperhauke for all maner of ſeruyce.

¶WC. holdeth a tenement of ye lorde / lyeng bytwne the ſaid tenement of RX on the Eeſt ſyde / and the medowe called weſt medowe on the Weſt and Southe / and the ſayd way that leadeth from A vnto B on the north ſyde / &amp; cōteyneth .xiiii. perches in brede / &amp; .xvii in length / and payeth. &amp;c. ſuite of court &amp; herryot. &amp;c.
               ¶IC. holdeth a tenement of the lorde / and it lyeth bytwene the ſayd maner place on the Eeſt ſyde / &amp; the Weſt medowe on the Weſt ſyde / &amp; the northe felde on the north ſyde / and the ſayd way that leadeth frō A to B. on the ſouthe ſyde / &amp; conteyneth by the way ſeuyn ꝑches and in lēgth .x. perches and payeth at the termes acuſtomed .xii.s.vi.d two hēnes at Chriſtmas ſuyte of court / and herryot at his deceſſe. &amp;c.
               ¶He that ſhall vieu / but and bounde landes or tenemētes / by Eeſt Weſt Northe and Southe. It is neceſſarie that he haue a Dyall with hym / for els &amp; the ſonne ſhyne nat / he ſhall nat haue perfyte knowlege / whiche is Eeſt Weſt Northe and Southe. For many tymes / the landes or medowes do nat lye alwaye euyn Eeſt or Weſt northe or ſouthe / but ſōtyme more of one parte than of another. As ſouthe Eſt or ſouthe Weſt / northe Eeſt or northe Weſt / and ſome two partes of the one and but the thirde parte of the other. as northe northe Eeſt / northe northe Weſt / Eeſt northe Eſt / and Eeſt ſouthe Eſt / ſouthe ſouthe eeſt / &amp; ſouthe ſouthe Weſt / and Weſt ſouthe Weſt / and Weſt northe weſt. But it nedeth nat to a ſurueyour to take ſo narowe

a dyuerſite / but to but it vpon the mooſt ꝑte as it lyeth. &amp; than muſt the dyall gyue hym ꝑfite knowlege howe it lyeth / and ſo muſt he tytell it in his boke. as ſhall appere herafter / &amp; he muſt ſtande in the myddes of the flatte whan he ſhall butte truely.
            
         
         
            ¶Howe a man ſhulde butte and bounde the feldes. Cap. xxi.
            
               ¶The northe felde vpon Dale furlong.
               
                  THe northe felde lyeth on the northe ſyde of the towne / and beginneth at the croſſe at a furlong called Dale furlong / ye whiche furlong conteyneth .xxx. landes and two heed landes / and they but on northe and ſouthe. wherof the ſouthe endes butteth vpon the hall orcharde &amp; vpon the crofte of IC. &amp; the northe endes but vpon ryhyll. Than to begyn on the Eſt ſyde next to the hiwaye that leadeth to A. the perſon hath two landes / the lorde thre landes. I. B. one lande. F. G. two landes / the lorde four landes / the priour two landes / the perſon one lande. R. X▪ two landes. W. C. one lande. H. L. one lande. T. S. two lādes / the priour thre landes / the lorde two landes. G. H. one lāde the perſon one lande / the lorde two landes next to the Weſt ſyde / and the heed lāde next to the hall orcharde and the other heed lande is the perſons next ryehyll. and if the huſbandes haue perfyte knowledge which is a rodde &amp; whiche is an halfe acre. than it were better to ſaye the lorde hath an acre / conteyning thre landes

are made in four or fyue landes / and I. C. halfe acre made in two landes / &amp; T S a rodde in one lāde and if it be laſſe than a rodde / than call it a but. howebeit a man may ꝑceyue and knowe if any man make two landes of one lande / or of one lande make two lā
                  des / bycauſe of the certayne nombre of euery flatte.
               ¶Ban furlong lyeth next to the ſame / and cōteyneth xxiii. landes / and one hadlāde at the ouerendes / and they lye Eeſt and Weſt / and but vpon Dale furlong / at the neder endes / and on the ſouthe ſyde next the ꝑſons crofte. The perſon hath thre landes / the priour one lande. I. C. two landes the lorde four landes. I B. two landes. T. S. two landes. H. L. one lande G. H. one lande. F. G. one lande. R. X. thre landes / ye prioure two landes. P. Q. one lande / the lorde hath the hadlandes.
               ¶Whethyll furlong / lyeth next to the ſame hadlādes and it cōteyneth .xxxvi. landes / &amp; thre gores fother or pyke / and they be all one thing. &amp; be called ſo / bycauſe they be brode in the one ende &amp; a ſharke pyke in the other ende / &amp; they be alway ſhorter than the other landes / and they but vpon the ſayd hadlande of ye lande at the weſt ende / &amp; vpon depeſyche at the Eeſt ende. &amp; to begyn at the northe weſt ſyde of the ſayd flate HL two landes. TS two lādes. GH one lande / ye lorde ſixe landes. IC two landes / the ꝑſon thre landes. WC two landes &amp; one pyke / the priour two landes and one pyke / FG two landes &amp; one pyke / the lorde four

landes / RX thre landes / TS two landes / GH two landes &amp; the lorde thre lādes next to the ſoutheſt ſyde.
               ¶Than tourne agayne to rye hyll / that conteyneth xxxvi. landes and two pikes / and but vpon Dale fur long on the ſouthe endes / &amp; vpon long medowe vpon the northe weſt endes. Than on the ſouthe Eeſt ſyde next to the way that leadeth to A. the priour hath two landes G.H. one lande / the perſon two landes I.B. two landes. F.G. two landes / ye lorde thre lādes two pikes. W.C. two landes / RX thre landes / TS two landes / PQ two landes / HL two landes / the lorde thre landes next to the balke that the wyndmylne ſtā
                  deth vpon. &amp;c.
               ¶PQ the whiche holdeth a cotage of the lorde / holdeth alſo this ſayd wyndmylne / whervnto all the lordes tenauntes are bounde to grynde all their corne and malte that they occupy of their owne / at the ſayd mylne / as well free tenauntes as other. and the lorde ſhall fynde all maner of tymbre &amp; yron worke / borde and nayles. And bring thē to the mylne / and the mylner ſhall neyle vp the bordes / make his ſhafte and the ſayle yardes / vpholde and reparell the ſpindell &amp; the rynde / the mylne pykes and the ſayle clothes / cogge and ronge / at his owne proper coſt and charge. And ſhall pay by the y
                     •
                  re .xx.s. at the termes there vſuell / and to grynde the lordes corne and maulte tole free / and to grynde it firſt / nexte to the corne that is in the hopper / if any be. &amp;c.
               
                  ¶On the other ſyde of the wynde mylne balke lyeth a flatte called Peyſe hyll / and it conteyneth .liii. landes and four pykes and one hadlande / of the whiche landes there be ſixe of them / that breke or cutte in the myddes of the landes / as ſhall appere by the boundyng. And the ſayd flatte lyeth bitwene the commen paſture / called the balke on the ſouthe Eeſt / and the foreſayd medowe called the longe medowe vpon the northe Weſt / and next vnto the foreſayd balke / I.C. hath thre landes / the lorde ſixe landes and a pyke / the perſon foure landes and a pyke / IB four landes / FG two landes and a pyke / WC thre landes / RX two landes / at the vpper ende next to the hadlande / PQ the nether endes of the landes nexte to the longe medowe / TS four landes / HL thre lādes at the heed and IC the nether endes of the ſame / the priour .v. landes / the lorde eyght landes / IB thre lādes / GH two landes and a pyke / FG one lande at the heed / HL two lādes / buttyng vpon the ſame one lande / and vpon the medowe / the perſon thre landes nexte to the northe Eeſt ſyde / and the prioure hath the hadlande at the heed. And this me ſemeth ſhulde be ſuffycient inſtructyon for buttyng and boundyng of all the feldes one after another. &amp;c.
            
         
         
            ¶Howe a man ſhulde butte and bounde the medowes. Cap. xxii.
            
               
               ¶The long medowe belongyng to the townſhyppe of Dale.
               THe longe medowe lyeth vpon the northe ſyde of the northe felde / bytwene the ſaid felde and the broke / that departeth the townſhyp of Dale and the townſhippe of Sale. and the Weſt endes butteth vpon the way that leadeth to A. and the Eeſt ende of the ſame medowe vpon a cloſe of the ſayd lordes / called ye parke cloſe / &amp; conteyneth. C. xxii. acres. this medowe lyeth in dyuers ſhotes of length / ſōtyme in two ſhotes of length / ſomtyme in one / &amp; ſomtyme in thre. Than to begyn at the weſt ſyde next to the waye that gothe to A. on the ouer ſhot / the lorde hath four acres IC two acres and a halfe / the perſone thre acres. IB two acres and a halfe. FG thre acres / the prioure foure acres / the lorde .viii. acres. And on the nether ſhot next vnto the broke next to the ſayd hiwaye / FG two acres / the priour foure acres / GH halfe an acre / WC two acres and a halfe / RX ſixe acres / the lorde vii. acres. Than to the long dolez yt butte fro the ſaid northe felde to the ſaid broke. TS four acres / the ꝑſone thre acres / IC an acre and a halfe / IB an acre and a halfe / the lorde ſixe acres / PQ thre acres / HL thre acres. And at the nether ende of the ſayde thre acres / IK lorde of ſale hath attached his weyre of his mylne of Sale / for the whiche attachement the ſayd IK payeth to the lorde of Dale and to his heyres euery yere .ii.s. at the feeſt of ſaynt Mighell tharchā
                  gell / for all maner of ſeruyce. &amp;c. Than to the ouer ſhotte nexte the ſayd felde / GH an acre and a rodde / 

WC thre roddes / RX an halfe acre / the lorde two acres / the perſon halfe an acre / PQ halfe an acre / the priour two acres and a halfe / IC two acres / the lord
four acres / TS two acres nexte to the parke cloſe. Than to the myddell ſhotte next to the longe dolez / FG an acre / the perſon thre acres / IB two acres / the lorde four acres / HL two acres / ye priour four acres next to the ſayd parke cloſe. Than to the nethermaſt ſhotte next the broke on the ſyde next to the longe doles / the ꝑſon two acres / RX thre acres / the lorde four acres and a halfe / GH dī acre / the priour two acr / WC two acres and a dī / IC dī acre / TS two acres / IB two acres in the corner next to ye ſaid parke cloſe and butteth vpon the ſayd broke. And if there be any mo medowes / than but them and boūde them in lyke maner / for the mo medowes there be and the fewer ſhottes / the better they may be boūded. for medowes go mooſt cōmenly by acres / halfe acres / and roddes / and they ought to be well ſtaked bytwene euery mannes dole / and ſpecially well ſtoned with great ſtones bytwene / &amp; ſet on a great heyght that they ſynke nat farre in to the erthe / for the propertie of a ſtonne is to dyſcende downewarde / and the propertie of erthe to aſcēde vpwarde. Therfore they wolde be taken hede vnto be tyme / and amended whan nede is. And this me ſemeth ſuffycient. &amp;c.
            
         
         
            ¶Howe a man ſhulde butte and bounde his paſtures. Cap. xxiii.
            
               
               ¶The paſtures belongyng to the ſame towne.
               THe lorde hath a cloſe called parke cloſe / and it cōteyneth .xxx. acres / and it lyeth bytwene the ſayd medowe called long medowe on the Weſt parte and a cloſe of the ꝑſons called Oxhey on the Eſt ꝑte / and the ſaid broke on the northe parte / and a felde called Eeſt felde on the ſouthe parte / and it is worthe by the yere twentie ſhillynges. &amp;c.
               ¶The perſon hath a cloſe next to the ſame called ox / hey and it conteyneth .x. acres / and lyeth bytwene the parke cloſe on the Weſt parte / and a cloſe of I.B. on the Eeſt ſyde / and the ſayd broke on the north eſt ꝑte and a felde called Eeſt felde on the Weſt parte. I do nat value it / bycauſe it is nat the lordes / the quantite of the acres therin is ſuffycient. &amp;c.
               ¶The ſayd IB holdeth a lytell crofte frely / belongyng to the tenement called rye croft / and cōteyneth two acres / and lyeth bytwene the ſayd perſons cloſe on the weſt ſyde / and the lane that gothe towarde R. on the ſouthe Eſt ſyde / &amp; butteth vpon the hiway that cometh from S. to the ſayde towne of Sale on the northe eſt ſyde / and the ſayd Eſt felde on the weſt ꝑte I ſet it at no value / bicauſe he is a freholder / and ronneth in the chefe rentes of his houſe / but and it be gyuen to the freholder by another dede / than muſt ye ſurueyour expreſſe the chefe rent therof by it ſelfe. And it is the mooſt ſpeciall poynt to a ſurueyour / firſt to a

viewe / butte / and bounde / bothe the towne and the hole lordeſhyppe / or euer he deſyre to ſe or loke vpon any euydence of any freholders. For this firſt done / the Surueyour maye than parfitely knowe wheder the freholder ſhewe his euydence for all his lande or nat / and let the ſurueyour haue good remembraūce / what parcelles of landes be conteyned in the ſayd euydence. And than may he well parceyue wheder he ſhewe for all or nat. And if the dedes be ſhewed firſt / the tenaūt maye ſay there is for all his lande / and the ſurueyour can nat controle hym nor ſaye nay. &amp;c.
               ¶FG holdeth a crofte of the lorde / lyeng next on the otherſyde of the ſayd lane called Goſe crofte / and cō
                  teyneth two acres and a halfe / and butteth vpon the ſayd hiwaye on the northe eſt ſyde / and the ſayd Eeſt felde on the weſt parte. &amp;c. And thus ye may paruſe / butte and bounde all the croftes / cloſes / and paſtures about the towne and within the lordſhippe / whoſe ſo euer they be. And to expreſſe euery hiwaye or croſſe / cōmen / balke / or marle pytte / where they lye / the whiche ſhall be a great redyneſſe many yeres hereafter. And if there be any commen paſtures where heerdmen kepe their catell / or any commen wodes / mores / heythes / or ſuche other / they maye nat be forgoten to be butted and bounded as they lye. &amp;c.
            
         
         
            ¶Howe a man ſhulde a mende errable lande. Cap. xxiiii.
            
               
               IT is conuenyent that a huſbande kepe his errable lande lyenge rounde / that it be nat to highe in the rygge / nor to lowe in the myddes of ye ſides / nor to hye a lytell fro the rayne: for than wyll ye water ſtande in the ſydes of the landes &amp; drowne ye corne. &amp; though there be no corne / yet it wereth the grounde &amp; maketh it lene / for ſtādyng water diſtroyeth graſſe / and therfore it muſt nedes diſtroye corne / the whiche is moche more tendrer than the graſſe. And if it ſo be / than take thy ploughe and begyn to plowe a forowe in the myddes of the ſyde of the lande / &amp; caſt it downe as and thou ſhulde falowe it / and ſo ꝑuſe bothe ſydes tyll the rigge be caſt downe. &amp; than take thy ploughe agayne and begyn to plowe wher thou dydeſt plowe firſte / and rygge all the remynaunt vpwarde / and ſo ſhalt thou bothe caſt thy landes and rigge it / and all at one plowyng. And this wyll make the lande to lye roūde / the which is good bothe for corne &amp; graſſe. &amp;c.
            ¶Another maner of mēdyng of errable lande / is to mucke it / marle it / lyme it / or dong it / with ye carte or wayne. and as I ſayde in the boke of huſbandrie / to ſette thy dong vpon the firſt ſturryng whan it is rygged / for that is beſt for many cauſes. and if thou lay it vpon the falowyng / than ſet thy mucke hepe in the reyne of the lande and than ſprede it / and all that falleth in the rygge caſt it out agayne / for elles it dothe but lytell good / for it wyll be couered with erthe and ſyldome ſene agayne. &amp;c.
            
               ¶Another maner of mendynge of errable lande / is to ſette thy ſhepe folde vpon it / and to flytte it euery daye / and it is better vpon the ſturrynge than vpon the falowe / and the ſhepe folde is better vpon the rye grounde than vpon the whete grounde. &amp;c.
            ¶Another maner / whan a huſbande hath moche errable lande / and hath no donge nor ſhepe to compoſt nor donge his lande with all. Than let the huſbande take his plough / and caſt all ſuche landes thre or four tymes togyder / and make the rigge there as ye reyne was before. And if the landes be to brode whan it is ſo caſt downe / than rygge eyther ſyde by it ſelfe / and ſo make two landes of one lande / or thre landes of .ii landes. And ſo ſhall he fynde newe moolde that was nat ſene in a hūdred yeres before / the whiche muſt nedes gyue more corne than the other dyde before. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe a man ſhulde amende his medowes. Cap. xxv.
            
               SE that there be no moldy warpes caſtige in the medowes / and yf there be / in Aprill lette them be ſpradd and beaten ſmall. And this is ye beſt way to ſprede them and make them ſmall. To take a great boughe of a tree / and to plaſſ he the bowes abrode and lay them lowe / and if they lye nat brode ynoughe / than take other ſmalle bowes and bynde

them faſte to the ſame / and to ley a tree or two ouerthwarte the bowes / to holde them downe flatte to the erthe / and to bynde the trees or the bowes that it fall nat of. And than to boore an hole with an nauger in the great boughes ende / or els to tye a rope faſt to all the boughes endes toguyder / and to faſt the teym to the ſame / and with oxen or horſes to drawe the ſayde boughes / bothe vp and downe and ouerthwarte the ſayde moldy warpe hylles / the whiche ſhall ſpredde them better / than any mannes handes can do. &amp; that ſhall refreſſhe the graſſe and make the medowes moche better.
            ¶Another maner of mendynge of medowes / is yf t
                  •
               ere be any rynning water or lande flode / that may be ſette or brought to ronne ouer the medowes / from the tyme that they be mowen vnto the begynning of May / and they wyll be moche the better. and it ſhall kylle / drowne / &amp; driue awaye the moldywarpes / and fyll vp the lowe places with ſande &amp; make the groūde euyn and good to mowe. All maner of waters be good / ſo that they ſtande nat ſtyll vpon the grounde. But ſpecially that water that cometh out of a towne from euery mānes mydding or donghyll is beſt / and wyll make the medowes mooſt rankeſt. And fro the begynning of May tyll ye medowes be mowen and the hay goten in / the waters wolde be ſet by and ron another way / for dyuers conſideracyons. &amp;c.
            
               
               ¶To amende and make better / dyuers maners of paſtures.
               
                  IT is vndouted / but there be dyuers maners of paſtures / as lowe grounde lyke medowe grounde / ley groūde / the whiche hath ben errable groūde of late / buſſhie grounde the whiche ſomtyme hath ben errable groūde / buſſhye groūde the whiche was neuer errable grounde / gorſtye grounde / the whiche hath ben errable grounde / gorſtie grounde / the whiche was neuer errable. Brome groūde / heyth grounde / marrys grounde / chalke grounde flyntie groū
                  de / chylturne grounde / and lymeſtonne grounde.
            
            
               ¶To amende lowe grounde lyke medowe grounde.
               ¶ye ſhall do by it as I haue ſhewed you in the next chapiter before of your medowes / and if any water ſtande ſtyll and wyll nat voyde / make a dyche / two or thre / as nede ſhall requyre / and opyn the ſydes of the dyche that the water maye come in to it. Conuey the water away / and with a ploughe make dyuers ſorowes from the ſaid dyche vp in to the paſtur / where the water ſtandeth / and with a Carte / a wayne / or a ſleyde / cary awaye therthe that the ploughe tourneth vp / or els it wyll ſtoppe the water on the one ſyde. &amp; if the ploughe forowe be to lytell / thanne make dyuers ſmall dycheſſe and open them on bothe ſydes / ſo that

thou leaue no water ſtandyng in the paſtur no tyme of the yere. And melche kye / draught oxen / laboring horſes and mares / be mooſt conuenyent to go togyder in ſuche paſtures. &amp;c.
            
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende ley grounde / the whiche hath ben errable lande of late. Cap. xxvii.
            
               YE muſt take hede howe the leyſe lye / and ſpecially that they lye nat to hyghe / for &amp; they do / it is more profite to ye huſbande to caſte it downe agayne / &amp; ſowe it with otes / one yere / two / or thre / and to ley it lower and rounde in good temper. and ſe that no water ſtande at the landes endes / buttyng on the heed lā
               des. and if it ſo do / than with a ploughe caſt a forowe towarde the heed landes / and than the water wyll folowe that forowe and make the landes drie. But that forowe wyll nat ſerue paſte one or two yeres / but it muſt be renewed / And yf it waxe moſſye in wynter / than wolde it be plowed agayne and ſowen with dyuers cornes / as the grounde requyreth. And at the firſt plowynge it wolde be plowed a ſquare forowe / as depe as it is brode / and layde flatte &amp; ſowen with otes / that the moſſe maye rote / and than to lye falowe one yere / &amp; than to be ſowen with wheat / rye / or barlye / as the huſbande thynketh mooſt cōuenyent. And if it ſhulde lye falowe the firſt yere the moſſe wyll nat rote / and at wynter it wyll be weate / and drowne all

the wheat and rye that it toucheth. And if a man haue plentie of ſuche paſture that wyll be moſſye euery thirde yere / let hym breke vp a newe peſe of grounde and plowe it and ſowe it (as I haue ſaid before) and he ſhall haue plentie of corne with lytell dongynge. &amp; ſowe it no lengar than it wyll beare plentie of corne without dong / and it wyll beare moche better graſſe ten or .xii. yere after. And if the leyſe be to brode / than make two lādes of one lande (as I haue ſaid before) And ſhepe are the mooſt conuenyent catell that may go on ſuche paſture / and beſt they wyll amende the graſſe. and to take good hede that ye ſuffre nouther breres nor blacke thornes / nor none other maner of buſſhes to growe in your paſtures / and ſpecially by the hedges. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende buſſhy grounde &amp; moſſy / that hath ben errable lande of olde tyme. Cap. xxviii.
            THere is none other remedy / but to ſtocke and gette vp the buſſhes by the rotes / and the landes plowed and ſowen (as I haue ſayd before) the reyſt grounde if it be drie wyll bringe moche corne / for the moſſe wyll rote / and the moole hyllockes wyll amende the grounde well. And yf there be any marle pyttes / that haue be made of olde tyme within the ſame cloyſe / than̄e whan the landes begynne to weare / if he haue nat ſufficiēt

of ſuche buſſhye and moſſye groūde to breke vp and ſowe. than there wolde be newe marle pyttes made &amp; the landes newe marled / the whiche is moche better than outher / donge / mucke / or lyme / for it wyll laſte twentie yeres togyder / if it be well done / and ſhall be the better whyle it is lande. And I marueyle greatly that in the cōmen feldes / where of olde tyme hath ben made many great marlepytes / the whiche hath done moche good to the lādes / that nowe a dayes no man dothe occupy thēne make none other. &amp; they nede nat to doute / but ther is marle nowe aſwell as was than but as me ſemeth ther be two cauſes why
               ▪ one is / the tenauntes be ſo doutefull of their lande lordes / that if they ſhulde marle and make their holdynges moche better / they feare leeſt they ſhulde be putte out or make a great fyne / or els to paye more rent. And if a lorde ſo do / me ſemeth he is vnreſonable / ſeyng that it was done all at the coſtes of his tenaunte / and nat at his. The ſeconde cauſe is / that men be diſpoſed to ydelneſſe and wyll nat laboure as they haue done in tymes paſte / but paſſe forthe the tyme as his father dyd before hym. but yet me ſemeth a freholder ſhuld
nat be of that cōdycion / for he is in a ſuretie / his chefe lorde can nat put hym out doyng his duetie. And he knoweth well / he ſhall take ye profite whyle he lyueth and his heyres after hym / and thus ſhulde gyue him a corage to improwe his owne / the which is as good as &amp; he had purchaſed as moche as the improwment cometh to. And one man this doyng / wolde gyue other men a corage and a good example to folowe the

ſame. And all other countreis may take enſample at Cheſterſhyre and Lancaſterſhyre / for many of them that haue ſo doone / haue made the improwmente as good as the lande was before. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe a man ſhulde amende b
                  •••
               hye grounde that was neuer errable lande. Cap. xxix.
            
               YE muſt conſyder what the groūde is diſpoſed vnto / &amp; wheder it be drie or wete / or be diſpoſed to beare woode / graſſe or corne. If it be drie and full of grauell it is better to bere wode / than outher corne or graſſe. If it be weate grounde / it is nat good for corne: but it wyll beare bothe wode and graſſe. But and it be a blacke erthe and drie / it is good for corne / and it wyll quyte the coſt to ſtocke it vp by the rotes / and to ſowe it with corne. And yf it be whyte cley / it is mooſt commenly a weate grounde / and than it is nat good for corne / but it wyll beare bothe wode and graſſe: and an acre of wode is as good as an acre of corne groūde / or of graſſe / and in ſome places moche better. And if ye wyll encreaſe the ſayd buſſhy groū
               de and to make more wode: than bytwene Myghelmas and Martylmas / ye muſt gader many akehornes and put them in erthen pottes / for thoſe will kepe them moyſt / and in February and Marche ſette the ſayd akehornes in the ſayde buſſhes / as thycke as ye

wyll / &amp; vndouted they wyll growe. And alſo ye may gette the keys of aſſhes / nuttes / and ſuche other / and ſet them in lyke maner / and to kepe all maner of catell that wyll eate any wode out of the ſame grounde tyll it be paſt daūger of catell. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende wode grounde that lyeth in ſeuerall paſture. Cap. xxx.
            
               IF they be great olde trees / if ye felle thē by the erthe / there wyll neuer come any ſpringe of them vp agayne / except they haue many ſmalle pumples and ſpringes about the rotes. And therfore ſuche olde trees wolde be but lopped and cropped / to beare more wode ſtyll / and if it be a good grounde to beare corne &amp; be but a fewe trees / than it were beſt to ſtocke thē vp by the rotes / and to plowe it and ſowe it. And if it be but yong wode / ye may choſe wheder ye wyll ſhrede it / loppe it / or croppe it / or felle it by the erthe. And if ye fell it by the erthe and kepe the ſpringe well ye ſhall haue for euery tree two or thre trees / ſo that it be felde at a due ſeaſon of the yere / and that is bytwene Candelmas and Maye / wherof I haue ſpoken ſufficiently ynoughe in the boke of huſbandrie.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende gorſty grounde that hath been errable lande. Cap. xxxi.
            
               yE ſhall vnderſtande that there be two maner of gorſe / and ſome men calle them fyrſe. One maner wyll growe on drie grounde / &amp; that maner wyll growe as hyghe as a man / and haue a great ſtalke as moche as a walkyng ſtaffe. and if ye wyll ſuffre them to growe and fell them nat / by proceſſe of tyme whan beeſtes go amonge them / and ſpecially in wynter tyme for colde / and in ſomer for ſhade that wyll cauſe them to dye. And many tymes and longe contynuall froſt in wynter wyll kyll theſe maner of gorſe: and whan they be deed / if ye plowe the lāde agayne and ſowe it with corne whan it lyeth ley agayne / the gorſe wyll growe agayne. And the beſt remedy for growynge agayne / is to putte vpon ſuche maner of paſture many ſhepe to eate it bare / but in many places they ſette great ſtore by thoſe maner of gorſe / and ſpeciallye for their fewell: &amp; wolde nat gyue an acre of gorſty lande for two acres of errable lande. And on that maner of gorſty lande wolde growe good corne with lytell donge / &amp; it is more profyte to plowe it and ſowe it / than to lye ley / except he kepe it for his fewell▪ and they growe mooſt commenly vpon drie grounde / ſomwhat ſandye or grauell / and Shepe is the mooſt conuenyent catell that maye go vpon ſuche paſture.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende gorſtye lande that was neuer errable lande. Cap. xxxii.
            
               
               IF the grounde be drie and growe full of ſuche maner of gorſe with the great ſtalkes / ye be at your lybertie to do as I haue ſayde / and yf it be of the other maner of gorſe or fyrſe / the whiche growe lowe by the erthe and haue but lytell ſmall ſtalkes. that maner of gorſe groweth alwaye on welſpring grounde ſomwhat moyſt and weate / and it wyll neuer beare good corne / but hewe it vp to bake and brewe withall / for it wyll nat lightlye be diſtroyed / for yf it be brēde it wyll growe agayne. But and there be marle vnderneth in the grounde within the ſame cloſe / if ye make coſt / than bren the gorſe at Marche / and with a bygge and many oxen / plowe it and make ſmall lā
               des / and than marle them and ſowe them with otes / for that corne wyll growe beſt on ſuche groūde. And if this wyll nat ſerue it is paſt remedy / for marle mē
               deth all maner of grounde but it is coſtely. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende bromy grounde Cap. xxxiii.
            BRome groweth alwaye vpon drie and ſandy grounde / and it wyll beare good rye and otes but it wyll nat endure to beare corne longe / without it be donged with the carte or with the ſhepe folde / or bothe. And if ye let it lye ley &amp; plowe it nat / ye brome wyll come agayn. and ſhepe is the beſt catell to holde it vnder / but neuertheleſſe it wyll growe. Whan it is growen of a yarde of heyght or more / than it is good

to bake and brewe with / and ſpecially whan a houſe is thacked / to take the brome and make it ī quarters of a yarde long / or there about / and to pricke them in to the thacke by and by / and couer the thacke clene ouer / and it ſhall bothe kepe out weate and alſo ſaue it from pullynge downe with crowes / pyes / dawes / or choughes: And if ye wolde diſtroy it whan it is growen thre or four fote of height / than about ſaynt Iames day fell it a fote aboue therthe or more / and than the ſtalke wyll dye for a good ſeaſon / but yf it be plowed agayne / it wyll growe as faſte as euer it dyde / whan he leaueth plowyng.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende heythy groūde. Cap. xxxiiii.
            ye ſhall vnderſtande that there be four maners of heyth groūde .s. heyth growyng vpon grauell / and heyth growyng vpon ſande. theſe two maner of heth groundes wyll beare no corne without moche donge or mucke / for ſeldome is there any marle vnder that maner of heyth / And in many countreis where plentie of lyme ſtonne is / the huſbandes do bren the lyme ſtonne with wode and ſecole / and make lyme therof: and do ſet it vpon their landes as they do their dong and do ſprede it in lyke maner / the whiche they calle moche better than dong / for lyme is hote of hym ſelfe The other two maners of heyth / is heyth growyng vpon white cley grounde / and heyth growyng vpon blacke erthe / that lyeth lowe lyke marrys grounde / &amp;

vnderneth theſe two maner of heyth groundes / ther
lyeth mooſt cōmenly marle. Than brenne the heyth and ſerche for the marle / and dygge it vp and ley it thycke vpon the grounde &amp; ſprede it / and than plowe it and ſowe it. and it is moche better thā outher lyme mucke / or any maner of dong / and lengar it wyll laſt and ſe that there be no water ſtandyng vpon the ſaid grounde. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende marres grounde. Cap. xxxv.
            
               THere is none other remedy / but firſte to dreyne the water clene awaye. And this is a good meyne to dreyne ye water clene away. Firſt in the loweſt cloſe wher the water maye be beſte auoyded: Make a great dyche and a depe / that the water may auoyde. And if all the water wyll nat come to that great diche but ſtande ſtyll in dyuers places / thaūe make many ſmalle dyches one in to another / from the ſayd ſtandyng waters / ſo that all theſe ſtandyng waters may come in to the great dyche / and that by reaſon ſhulde dreyne the water clene. And in a drie ſomer ye maye make many brode and depe diches and ſeuer ye marres in dyuers paſtures / and make bridges ouer the dyches in to euery cloſe / and dyuers lanes made lyke a cauſey to conuey the catell in to the paſtures / ſo that one cauſey or lane / maye ſerue the cloſes or paſtures on bothe ſydes. And in the loweſt place of euery cloſe

or paſture / make a trenche or a lytell dyche in to the great dyche that gothe about. And this ſhall ye make by proceſſe good paſtures of marres groūde / and euer the lengar the better paſtures: and ſpecially if ye put in moche catell / it ſhall make the better graſſe and the fyner. And melche kye / draught oxen / and labourynge horſes / is the beſt catell to make good paſture on marres grounde / and ſhepe on drie groūde / for they wyll eate the grounde mooſt bareſt / and that cauſeth the graſſe to be good &amp; fyne. And if this maner of dichynge wyll nat make the marres grounde drie / than muſt you make a ſough vnderneth therthe as men do to gette cole / yron / ſtonne / leed / ore / or tyn And if that wyll nat ſerue / than kepe out your catell for feare of drownyng. &amp;c.
         
         
            ¶Howe to amende bromy grounde and ferny grounde. Cap. xxxvi.
            
               BRomye grounde and fernye grounde be moch of one nature / for they growe on ſā
               dye and drie groūde: And they wyll bere good rye / barley / bygge / or beyre / and otes / if they be donged with ſhepe / carte or wayne: For ſuche lyght grounde wyll ſoone weare and waſſhe with water / yf it be nat donged. And yf they lye vnplowed / they wyll growe full of brōe and ferne / and if ye wyll diſtroy the brome whan it is growen thre or foure fote hye / In Mydſomer mo
                  •
               ne or

ſoone after whan it is full blomed / with a hedgynge byll cutte the ſtalkes halfe a yarde aboue the erthe / ſo that ye leaue no grene ſtalke growyng vpon the rote and that wyll cauſe it to dye. But and ye plowe it agayne and after let it lye / it wyll growe agayne. and if ye mowe ferne whan it is yonge / ſo that it be mowen before Mydſomer / by vſe of ſuche mowynge it wyll weare away.
         
         
            ¶Of chylturne grounde / flyntie grounde / and chalke grounde. Cap. xxxvii.
            
               CHylturne grounde and flyntie groūde be lyght groundes and drie / and full of ſmall ſtones / and chalke groūde is moche of the ſame nature / and they wyll weare &amp; waſſhe awaye with water. And therfore they wolde be donged / as the bromye and fernye groundes be / for marle is ſeldome founde in theſe maner of groundes. And therfore / if ye want ſhepe and dong / they wolde lye ley and reſt thē that they maye mende with lyeng.
         
         
            ¶Of lyme ſtonne grounde. Cap. xxxviii.
            LIme ſtonne grounde is very good / bothe for corne and graſſe / and yet in ſome places there wyll moche heyth growe vpon lyme ſtone grounde / 

and that is longe of yll huſbandrie. For &amp; that heyth were brēned / plowed / &amp; ſowed ye firſt yere with otes / and than falowed and ſowed with whete / rye / &amp; barley / and after with beanes or pees / it wyll beare moche corne with lytell donge / and ſhall beare alway after the better graſſe. And ſhepe is the beſt catell that can go vpon any of theſe ſixe maner of groūdes / and beſt they wyll amende the graſſe / and kepe them ſelfe from rotyng. And he that hath lymeſtone / maye bren it with coole and wode and make lyme / wherwith he may lyme his grounde &amp; that wyll bring good corne / or he maye ſell his lyme at his pleaſure.
         
         
            ¶What profytes maye come or growe to the lorde by reaſon of his waters. Cap. xxxix.
            
               FIrſt ye ſhall vnderſtande / that there be dyuers maners of waters: that is to ſay ſtādyng waters / as poles / meyres / mottes / and stewes. And alſo ronnyng waters / as great ryuers / ſmale ryuers / brokes / ſucches / welſpringes / and pyttes: than what ꝓfyte may come to the lorde of them. The lorde maye ſette the fyſſhinges of all theſe ſayd waters to his tenaūtes for certayne rent / and he maye reſerue to him ſelfe certayne fyſſhe / or to fyſſhe certayne tymes / or at any tyme at his pleaſure.
         
         
            
            ¶The maner to make dyuers maner of mylnes. Cap. xl.
            
               ALſo vpon theſe waters / the lorde maye ſette dyuers maner of mylnes / the whiche maye be to the lordes great eaſe and profite. As vpon the great riuers / corne mylnes that be called grounde mylnes / and they be called groūde mylnes / bycauſe the ouerſyde of the heed ſylle lyeth euyn leuell with the ouerſyde of the grounde / in the bottom of the water. And alſo fullyng mylnes / otherwyſe called walk mylnes / may be made in like maner / and ſtande alſo vpon the great ryuers. And thā one whele is able to driue two ſtockes / that is to ſay / bothe a potyer and a faller / the faller bothe to ſcoure and herely / and the potyere to thicke the clothe. And commenly theſe mylnes be nat ſet vpon the great ſtremes of theſe great ryuers / but a great parte of the water is cōueyed out of the great ſtreme by a mylne fleme made with mānes hande to a certayne place / where wyſemen thynke the mylne mooſt cōuenyent to be ſet / &amp; the ſayd water to be holden vp and brought to the ſaid mylne / by reaſon and ſettyng of a weyre ouerthwart the ſayd ſtreme / made of trouſe / tymbre / or ſtonne / or of bothe. And whan it is palte the mylne with a ſuffycient fall of the water / that the mylne ſtande nat in backe water / to retourne in to the ryuer agayne. and in many places / the ſaid

mylnes be ſet on the one ſyde of the great ryuer / and a weyre made of tymbre and ſtone to holde vp the water to the mylne / the whiche is a great coſt / and many tymes it wyll ſtande in lacke of water that it may nat well go at a great ſtode / except the groūde warke be made very hie. But they be ꝓfitable bothe in grin dynge of corne and fullyng of clothe / and in takynge of moche fyſſhe. And in lyke maner theſe ſayde two maner of mylnes maye be ſette vpon ſmale ryuers / without any fleme caſtyng / but all onely his weyre to holde vp the water / and his flode gates to let it go at a flode / whan nede ſhall requyre. Alſo there be other two maner of corne mylnes / that is to ſaye: a breſte mylne and an ouerſhotte mylne / and thoſe two maner of mylnes be ſette and go mooſt commenly vpon ſmale brokes / and vpon great poles &amp; meyres. And they haue alway abrode bowe a fote brode and more and the ladelles be alwaye ſhrowded with compaſt bordes on bothe ſides to holde in the water / and than they be called bokettes. And they muſte be ſet moche nerer toguyder than the ladelles be / and moche more a ſloope downewarde / to holde moche water that it fall nat out / for it driueth the whele as well with the weyght of the water as with ye ſtrength. And the mylner muſt drawe his water acordyng to his bokettes / that they maye be alway full and no more / for the lenger that they holde the water the better they be. Alſo another maner of fullyng mylnes / maye be ſette and go vpon the ſayde ſmale brokes / pooles / or meyres.

and thoſe be called fallers / for a faller by hymſelfe requyreth nat ſo great ſtrength of water as the potyer dothe / bycauſe the water cometh moſt cōmenly ouer the whele / and the braces do butte heue vp the two fete that fall in to the ſtocke vpon the clothe / the whiche cauſeth the clothe to thicke and tourne. Alſo theſe mylnes that be ſette and go on ſmall waters / may go and ron with a gogyn of yron vpon bulder ſtones or vpon braſſe as a bell dothe / for yt wyll go mooſt lighteſt. But theſe mylnes that go vpon theſe great ryuers / that be brode / heuy / and weighty / muſt nedes haue two great thycke hoopes of yron foure inches brode / and an inche thycke: and eight or nyne inches bytwene the ſydes / ſette on bothe endes of the ſhafte / for the gogyn of yron wyll nat beare them / and ſpecially the fullynge mylne. And that mylne that gothe with a gogyn / yet muſt it haue on eyther ende of the ſhafte a hoope of yron and bulders vnder / and if the gogyn feyle or waxe loſe / but it ſhall nat touche them bothe attones. And lette the mylner take good hede bothe to the gogyns and hoopes that they be nat loſe for than wyll the ſhafte endes brenne of. For than he hurteth his lorde / his mayſter / or hymſelfe / for mylne ſhaftes be coſtely. But in ſo moche as there is great profyte to the lordes in makyng of theſe mylnes / and the mooſt rente is reyſed vpon ſo lytell grounde / and ofte tymes for want of the ſede of diſcrecyon and experyence of good makynge / there be many defautes made in them / and ſpecially in makyng of the mylne

troughe / wher the mylne whele gothe / for ofte tymes they make it to holowe and depe vnder ye whele / that the water ſtandeth therin whan the mylne gothe nat / for the tayle ſyll wolde lye bare &amp; drie whan the myln gothe nat. And the tayle ſylle wolde lye twētie inches or .xxiiii. vnder the heed ſylle / and the troughe wolde nat paſſe thre inches holowe at the mooſt / and as longe as it maye receyue thre ladelles / the fourthe ladell entrynge the water / and the fyfte ladell leauynge the water. And the ſtrake ſylles bothe aboue and vnder wolde be of a good length / ſo that the whele come nat nighe vnto the draught gate be two fote or more / for the further fro the gate the bygger and the ſwyfter is the ſtreme. And the lengar that the ladell is the better it is / ſo yt it haue ſufficyent water. And than the mylner nedeth nat to drawe vp his gate ſo highe / as and the ladell be ſhorte / for the ebber the water is the ſwifter it is. And a double bowed whele is moche better than a ſyngle bowed whele / for many cauſes / if there be ſufficient water / and better it wyll kepe the ladels from loſynge. The ladell mooſt commenly of a double bowed whele / wolde be thre fote longe and a fote brode / and to drawe vp his draught gate nyne or ten inches is ſuffycient: And than ſhall nat the bowe of the whele be hydde nor couered in ye water / and than it gothe ſwyftly. And vpon the great ryuers the ladelles maye be an elne longe / but for the weyght and drawynge vp of the draught gate. &amp;c. The greatter compaſſe the whele is / the laſſe water wyll driue it:

but it wyll nat go ſo ofte about as a lytell whele wyll do. But the cogge whele in a corne mylne / is a great helper if it be well pycked / well cogged / and well rō
               ged / ſixe ronges &amp; .xlviii. cogges / are beſt for a great ryuer. For than the mylne ſtonne gothe eyght tymes about and the water whele but ones / and euery rong kepeth his owne cogge / et econtra. &amp; changeth nat on any ſyde. And for a meane water ſixe rōges and .xlii. cogges is beſt. And for the ouer ſhotte mylne ſixe rō
               ges and .xxxvi. cogges is beſt / For the cogge whele maye nat be of ſo great a compaſe as the other cogge wheles be / And in all theſe pyckes / euery cogge kepeth his owne ronge. And if ye putte in any whele a cogge or two cogges / mo or laſſe: thanne as I haue ſayd. Than ſhall euery cogge chaunge his ronge at all tymes / ſo that and it be nat very truely pycked it wyll nat go well / and if it fortune to breke a cogge as it is lyke to do / it wyll than breke many of them / excepte he ſhote downe his draught gate ſhortely / and lykewiſe a wyndmylne. howbe it a wyndmylne hath neuer vnder .xlviii. cogges or .liiii. &amp;c. but they muſt be ſo pycked / that euery cogge kepe his owne ronge / and ſeuyn ronges are nat profytable for they go latte lye. Of horſe mylnes I do nat ſpeke of the makyng / for I haue nat thexperience of them as I haue of water mylnes.
            ¶Alſo the lordes and their tenauntes haue another maner of profyte by reaſon of theſe waters / ouer and

beſyde theſe maner of mylnes or fyſſhingꝭ / and that is by reaſon of the watrynge of their catell and beeſtes bothe wynter and ſomer / and ſpecially of the rynnynge waters / as ryuers / brokes / ſucches / and welſpringes / for they done ſyldome freſe or neuer / &amp; they wyll be colde in ſomer and warme in wynter / and yf a cloſe want water it hath a great meame and is moche the worſe.
            ¶Furthermore it is cōuenyent for a ſurueyour that whan he hath ſurueyed his Lordes landes / and ſene what profytes and approwmentes maye ryſe and be made within the ſame / that he ſhewe his lorde therof and aduyſe hym to do it / and to make the coſt. For it is vndouted / that a man can nat make no ſurer purchaſe of any maner of lande / better tytell / nor lighter coſte / nor more aduauntage to hym ſelfe / than to improwe / amende / and make better / his owne olde enherytaunce. I meane nat by the heyghtnynge / reyſyng / or increaſyng of the rentes of their tenauntes / but all onely in mendyng and makyng better his errable landes / medowes leyſe / &amp; paſtures / and in makyng of water mylnes / wyndmylnes / horſe mylnes / fullyng mylnes / ſythe mylnes / cutteler mylnes / be it by water or draught of horſes / ſmethy mylnes / or ſuche other. And alſo of gettynge of all maner of profytes / as well vnder the erthe as aboue (as before is remembred) in the ſixt chapiter.
            And by the reaſon of theſe improwmētes / me ſemeth

a man myght make euery townſhyppe that ſtandeth in the playne champyon countre and occupyed in tyllage / halfe as good agayne in all maner of profytes to the tenauntes as it was before. If the lordes therof / &amp; their tenaūtes can agre of the coſtes that ſhulde be made therof. And neuer a houſe nor cottage to be decayed nor lette downe / and to haue as moche lande in tyllage and plowing as ther was before / and their corne and graſſe ſhulde be better ſaued and kepte frō diſtroyeng.
         
         
            ¶Howe to make a townſhippe that is worthe twentie marke a yere worthe .xx.li. a yere. Cap. xli.
            
               IT is vndouted that euery townſhyppe that ſtādeth in tyllage in the playne coū
               trey / there be errable landes to plowe &amp; ſowe / and leyſe to tye or tedder their horſes and mares vpon / and commen paſture to kepe and paſture their catell / beeſtes / &amp; ſhepe vpon. And alſo they haue medowe grounde to gette their hey vpon. Than lette it be knowen howe many acres of errable landes euery man hath in tyllage / &amp; of the ſame acres in euery felde to chaunge with his neyghbours / and to ley them toguyder and to make hym one ſeuerall cloſe in euery felde / for his errable landes and his leyſe in euery felde to ley them toguyder in one felde / and to make one ſeuerall cloſe for thē
               
all. And alſo another ſeuerall cloſe for his porcyon of his commen paſture / and alſo his porcyon of his medowe in a ſeuerall cloſe by it ſelfe / and all kepte in ſeuerall bothe in wynter and ſomer / and euery cottage ſhall haue his porcion aſſigned hym acordyng to his rent. and than ſhall nat the ryche man ouerpreſſe the poore man with his catell / and euery man maye eate his owne cloſe at his pleaſure. And vndouted / yt hay and ſtrawe that will fynde one beeſt in the houſe wyll fynde two beeſtes in the cloſe / &amp; better they ſhall lyke For thoſe beeſtes in the houſe haue ſhorte heer &amp; thyn and towarde Marche they wyll pyll &amp; be bare. And therfore they maye nat abyde in the felde before the heerdman in wynter tyme for colde. And thoſe that lye in a cloſe vnder a hedge haue longe heer &amp; thycke / and they wyll neuer pyll nor be bare. and by this reaſon the huſbande may kepe twyſe ſo many catell as he dyde before.
            ¶This is the cauſe of this approument. Nowe euery huſbande hath ſixe ſeuerall cloſes / wherof thre be for corne / the fourthe for his leyſe / the fyfte for his cō
               men paſtures / and the ſixte for his hay: and in wynter tyme there is but one occupyed with corne. &amp; than hath the huſbāde other fyue to occupy tyll lent come / and than he hath his falowe felde / his ley felde / &amp; his paſture felde all ſomer. And whā he hath mowen his medowe than he hath his medowe grounde / ſo that &amp; he haue any weyke catell that wolde be amended / or

dyuers maner of catell / he may put thē in any cloſe he wyll / the whiche is a great aduaūtage. &amp; if all ſhulde lye cōmen / than wolde the edyſſhe of the corne feldes &amp; the aftermath of all the medowes be eaten in ten or xii. dayes. And the riche men that hath moche catell / wolde haue the aduauntage / and the poore man can haue no helpe nor relefe in wynter / whā he hath moſt nede. And if an acre of lande be worthe ſixe pens or it be encloſed / it wyll be worthe eyght pens whan it is encloſed / by reaſon of the compoſtyng and dongyng of the catell / that ſhall go and lye vpon it bothe day and night. And if any of his thre cloſes that he hath for his corne be worne or waxe bare / than he may breke and plowe vp his cloſe that he had for his leyſe / or the cloſe that he had for his commen paſture / or bothe and ſowe them with corne / and lette the other lye for a tyme / and ſo ſhall he haue alway reiſt grounde / the whiche will beare moche corne with lytell dong. and alſo he ſhall haue great profite of the wode in the hedges whan it is growen. &amp; nat all onely theſe profytes and aduauntages beforeſayd / but he ſhall ſaue moche more than all theſe: for by reaſon of theſe cloſes / he ſhall ſaue meate / drinke / &amp; wages of aſhepeheerd the wages of the heerdman / &amp; the wages of the ſwynheerd / the whiche maye fortune to be as chargeable as all his hole rente / and alſo his corne ſhall be better ſaued fro eatyng or diſtroyeng with catell. For dout ye nat / but heerdmen with their catell / ſhepeheerdes with their ſhepe / and tyeng of horſes and mares / diſtroyeth

moche corne / the whiche the hedges wolde ſaue. Paraduenture ſome men wolde ſaye / that this ſhulde be agaynſt the cōmen weale / bycauſe the ſhepheerdes / heerdmen / and ſwyneheerdes / ſhulde than be putte out of wages. To that it maye be anſwered / thoughe thoſe occupacyons be nat vſed / there be as many newe occupacyons that were nat vſed before. As gettyng of quyckeſettes / dyching / hedgyng / and plaſſhyng / the whiche the ſame men may vſe and occupy. Alſo it maye fortune men wyll ſay / that and all ſhulde be encloſed / that ther wolde be many foule lanes as there be in Eſſexe: but for that there may be a prouycion / and that is thus. Where the kynges hye way is / if it be drie grounde / ſtony groūde / or ſandy grounde / in all ſuche places may be lanes made of a conuenyent brede / for the kynges people to paſſe thorowe with all maner of cariage. And where it is ſoft grounde lyeng leuell / that the waters maye nat well paſſe by the dicheſſe / at euery hedge that gothe ouerthwart the hywaye there to make a gate / and ſtonne it or grauell it in that place. And thā hath euery man the hole cloſe to ryde / cary / or go in / as they hadde before / Lykewiſe as they do at the wynde gates a this ſyde Chorley in Lancaſhyre / and lykewiſe bytwene towne &amp; towne / and as to their owne drifte lanes to their cloſes / let them make them for their owne eaſe as they wyll haue thē. &amp;c.
            
               
               THe mooſt indyfferenteſt meane to make theſe approumētes / as me ſemeth is this All the lordes of one towne be there neuer ſo many / ſhulde be all of one aſſente / that their tenauntes ſhulde exchaunge their landes one with another / &amp; the ſayd exchaunge to ſtande and endure for euer / for doute them nat but they knowe it beſte, and euery tenaunt for his owne aduauntage wyll do it indifferently / and the curate of the ſame paryſſhe for his parte. and euery lordes bayly to be indyfferent to ſe theſe cloſes lotted and aſſigned to euery mannes eaſe / ſo that euery man may haue one lytell crofte or cloſe next to his owne houſe / if it maye be / thoughe he haue no lande of his owne. This done / lette euery lorde by his copy of court role or by indenture / to make a ſuffycient leaſe to euery of their tenauntes / to haue to hym and to his wyfe and to his chyldren / ſo that it paſſe nat thre lyues / than beyng a lyue and named. yeldyng and payeng to their lordes and to their heyres / the olde rentes and ſeruyces before due and accuſtomed / duryng thoſe thre lyues / vpon this cōdycion. That they ſhall do or cauſe to be done duryng their lyues / ſufficyently to quicke ſette / dyche / hedge / and plaſſhe whan nede is / all the ſayd cloſes / &amp; ſo kepe thē duryng their lyues / the whiche wyll be a great charge to the tenauntes. But yet me ſemeth they may well do it if they entēde to thrife and ſpecially do remembre the profytes that may cōe to them afterwarde. There is an olde ſayeng / quod

leuis eſt labor cum lucro / that is to ſay. That labour is light where winnyng foloweth. and moche of this labour may be done by hym ſelfe &amp; his ſeruantes at a cōuenyent tyme / ſo yt he let nat his huſbādrie. It is to moche to be done in one yere two or thre / but and they may do it in ſixe or nyne yeres / as the feldes go about they hye them well / for it is to coſtely for huſbandes to hyre it to be done. And the lordes / me ſemeth canne do no laſſe / than to graūt them theſe thre lyues of the olde rente / remembring what profytes they may haue at the ende of their termes / they knowe nat howe ſoone. For vndouted on ſette day cometh at laſt / and thoughe the aduaūtage of the lordes come nat anone it wyll come at length. And therfore ſaythe the philoſopher / Quod dffertur non aufertur / that thyng that is dyfferred is nat taken awaye / and in the meane tyme the lordes haue no maner of loſſe / nor yet make no coſtes but at their pleaſure.
            ¶Ibi finis.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
¶The authour.
            
               GO thou lytell queare / with due reuerence
            And with an humble hert / recōmende me
            To all thoſe / that of their beniuolence
            This lytell treatyſe / dothe rede / here / or ſe
            Wherwith I pray them / contented to be
            And to amende it / in places behouable
            Where as I haue fauted / or be culpable.
            
               ¶For herde it is / a man to attayne
            To make a thyng perfyte / at the firſt ſyght
            But whan it is reed / and well ouer ſeyne
            Fautes maye be founde / that neuer came to lyght
            Thoughe the maker haue do / his dilygence &amp; might
            Prayeng them to take it / as I haue entended
            And to forgyue me / if that I haue offended.
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            ¶Thus endeth this lytell treatyſe / named the boke of Surueyeng and of improumentes. Imprinted at London in fleteſtrete by Rycharde Pynſon / printer to the kynges noble grace. The yere of our lorde god .M.D.xxiii. the .xv. day of Iuly. Cum priuilegio a rege indulto.
         
         
            
            
               
            
            
         
      
   

