
   
      
         
            In this booke is contayned the offices of shyriffes, bayliffes of lybertyes, escheatours, constables, and coroners and shewed what euerye one of them may doe by vertue of their offices, drawen out of bookes of the common lawe and of the statutes.
            Office et auctoryte des iustyces de peas. English. Selections
            Fitzherbert, Anthony, Sir, 1470-1538.
         
         
            
               1579
            
         
         Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00880
            STC 10993.9
            ESTC S4009
            34382733
            ocm 34382733
            29068
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00880)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29068)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1896:2)
         
         
            
               
                  In this booke is contayned the offices of shyriffes, bayliffes of lybertyes, escheatours, constables, and coroners and shewed what euerye one of them may doe by vertue of their offices, drawen out of bookes of the common lawe and of the statutes.
                  Office et auctoryte des iustyces de peas. English. Selections
                  Fitzherbert, Anthony, Sir, 1470-1538.
                  Harvey, Gabriel, 1550?-1631.
               
               [111] p.   
               
                  By Thomas Marshe,
                  Imprynted at London :
                  [not after 1579]
               
               
                  Extracted from the author's The newe boke of iustices of the peas.
                  Title page contains Gabriel Harvey's autograph and date, 1579.
                  Place and publisher from colophon.
                  Contains ms. notes 1 p. preceding and 1 p. following printed text.
                  Imperfect: cropped.
                  Signatures: A-G⁸.
                  Reproduction of original in: Library of Congress.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sheriffs --  Great Britain.
               Bailiffs --  Great Britain.
               Constables --  Great Britain.
               Coroners --  Great Britain.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-07
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2002-07
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-08
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            In this booke
is contayned the Offyces of Shyriffes,
Bayliffes of lybertyes, Escheatours,
Constables, and Coroners;
and shewed what euerye
one of them may doe by vertue of
their offices; drawen out of bookes
of the common Lawe and
of the Statutes.
            gabvielharuey. 1579.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            The office of Shiriffes.
            
               WHat the Offyce of a shyriffe is
heereafter shall more playnely
appeare, but in a generality,
his office is righteously, &amp;
duely to returne all writs and
precepts to hym directed, and truely to execute
the same accordinge as hee shall bee
commaunded in the same Wryts and prece
                  •
               ts.
And that bee take nothyng of any
person for doing his offyce, but the due, &amp;
accustomable fees to hym belonging. And
that hee duely holde and keepe hys Countyes,
Courtes, and turnes, according to the
our course of the Lawe. Upon these three
poynetes dependeth the whole charge and
effect of hys offyce.
            The offyce of the Shyriffe is to returne
good sufficient and reasonable issues, and
vpon such persons as haue sufficient goods
or lands, according to the statute of Westminster.
An. ij. capitulo .xxxix. and Edwardi
tertij capitulo quinto
            The Shiriffe ought to take the inditements
foūo before him in his turne by Indenture,
and so shall Bayliffs of fraunchises,
one parte whereof shall remayne with
the Indytours. An. secundo Edwardi tertij.
Capitulo .17.
            
               
The Shiriffe may arrest men ryding or
going armed, and commit them to pryson,
there to remayne at the Kings pleasure
.2. Ed. 3. cap. 5. at Northampton.
            Shiriffes and vnder Shiriffes shall receyue

                  •
               rits in euery place within y• county
without taking ought, &amp; shal make a vil,
whych i
                  •
                they reful
                  •
                other that hee present
shall pu
                  •
                to their Seales. And if they returne
not the same writs: they shall be punished
and shall re
                  •
               der damages to y• party
.2. Ed. 3. cap. 5. at Northampton.
            Shyriffes, and Iaylours shall receyue
Theeues indited, or taken wyth the maner
without taking any thynge for the receypt
.4. Ed. 3. cap. 10.
            Shyriffes shall lease theyr hundredes, &amp;
Wapentakes after the olde fearme, &amp; not
aboue. An. 4. Ed. 3. cap. 25. and An. 14.
Ed. 3. cap. 8.
            Shiriffs ought to arrest persons suspect
of felony going by night, or by day, whych
be of euill fame .11. Ed. 3. cap. 14.
            The shiriff i
                  •
                one coūty shall haue no moe
Bayliffes errant but one .14. Ed. 3. cap. 9.
            Shyriffes ought to keepe their turnes
euery yeare within a moneth after Easter,
and wythin a moneth after Mychaelmas,

xiii &amp; .xxxi Edwardi tertij. cap. xiiii.
            Shyriffes that leuy issues, fines and amerciamentes
in the County, ought to haue the
extreates ensealed with the seale of the Eschequer,
so that as much as is payd may

                  •
               oe blotted. And if any shiriffe or Mynister
doe the contrary, he shall render to the party
tryple damages, and shall make 
                  〈◊〉
                to
the King, and the sute hereof may be aswell
before Iustices of peace as before other Iustices
.xxiiii. Edward. ter. cap. ix.
            The Shyriffes shall aray the panneis of
Assises foure dayes before the session
                  •
                at the
least vppon payne of .xx. li. And Bayliffes of
liberties, shall make returne to Shyriffes
sixe dayes before the sessions, vpon the same
paine
                  •
                
               
                  〈…〉
                .3. cap. ix.
            T
                  •
                
               
                  〈…〉
                ought to examyne Loyterers

                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               agarantes, and compel them to
finde 
                  ••
               rety of theyr good behauior 
                  •
               y sufficient
mainpryse of such as bee distrey
                  •
               able,
if any defaulte bee found in such vagarantes.
And if they cannot finde such surety:
then to commaund them to the next Iayle,
there to remayne vntill the comming of the
Iustices of Iayle deliuery, they to doe with
such vagarants as they shal thinke best .vii.
Richardi .ii. cap. vii.
            
               
The Shiriffe shall bee bounden foure
tymes in the yere to make Proclamation
of the Statute of Wynchester, in euery hū
               dreth
of his Bayliwicke.
            The Shiriffe ought to take swords, Daggers
and hangers, from Seruauntes labourers,
and Seruaunts of craftes men, and
vitaylers that weare them, vnlesse it be in
time of Warre or when they labour in the
countrey with theyr maysters or vpon theyr
busines. And the Shiriffe shall keepe y
                  •
                same
weapons, which they shall present vnto the
Iusticers of the peace at their sessions with
the names of them that bare them .xii. Richardi
ii. cap. vi.
            Shiriffes ought to receiue Labourers,
Seruaunts, Beggers and Uagabonds, and
them detaine in Pryson wythout bayle or
mainpryse and wythout fee or taking any
thing at their entre or going out of Prisō vpon
payn to forfayt a C.li. to the King .xi. R.
ii cap. ix.
            Shiriffes and other ministers of the
Kyng so soone as they haue knowledge of
assembles and roiots, with outragiōs nūber
of people, ought with the power of the shyre
to goe and make resistaunce agaynste such
malite wyth all theyr strength, and shall

                  〈…〉
                and keepe them in

prison vntill the due punishment of the law
be executed vppon them. And all manner of
Lordes, and other the kings true lyege mē
ought to bee assistent with all their power &amp;
strēgth to ayde the Shiriffes and other ministers
therein. 17. Ric. 2. cap. 8.
            Shiriffes ought to be personally dwelling
in their Bayliwickes for the tyme, and
they shall not let thē to farme 4. H. 4. ca. 5.
            Shiriffes ought to see and prouyde, that
neyther their vnder Shiriffes, Bapliffes
Clarkes, nor receyuers shal bee atturneis
in the Kinges Courts for the tyme of their
office .i. H. 5. cap 4.
            Shiriffes ought to let to mainpryse persons
ind
                  •
               ted of heresy and Iollardes which
are in their keeping within x. dayes vnder
good suretyes, so that they appeare before
the end of the sayd .x. dayes. 2. Hen. 5. ca. 7.
Shiriffes shal cause the Statute of prirueiours
to bee proclaymed foure tymes in the
yere, vpon paine of C-li. for euery time that
hee fayleth so to do. And vppon lyke payne
shall deliuer the same to his successours to
be proclaymed .
                  •
                Hen. 6. cap. 2.
            Shiriffes muste make due election of the
Knightes of the Parliament ix. H. 6. ca. 40
            
               
Shiriffes must returne such persons,
Knightes of the Parliament which be chosen
by the greatter number of the freeholders
dwellyng in the county which may expend
xl.s. yerely aboue all charges.
            And that those Knightes 
                  •
               ee dwellinge
within the same county. And that he examine
euery freholder at such elections vppon
a booke how much he may expend. And
if any Shiriffe returne other knightes: hee
shall forfayte an hundred li. to the king and
shall haue one yeares imprisoment without
bayle or maynpryse.
            Shiriffes vpon a precept made vnto thē
by Iustices of the peace to inquire for forcible
entre, shall returne vppon euery of the
i
                  •
               rours .xx.s. in fynes at the first day.
            And Iustices of the peace shall heare and determine
such defaultes of Shiriffes by Bill
of the suite of the party or 
                  •
               y inditement.
            And they shal loose xx. li. for euery defaulte.
And hee yt will sue shall haue the one halfe
13. Hen. 6. cap. 9.
            To anoyd robberyes and spoyles vppon
the riuer of Seuerue, &amp; by y• coastes of the
Forrestes of Deane, &amp; the hūdreds of Blo
               
                  •
               essom,
&amp; Westbury in the county of Glocester,
the Shiriffes of Glocester or the
            
               
Bayliffes of the towne of Glocester after
notification made to any of them of such inturyes
and damages, by the partyes greued,
within foure dayes after the notificatiō
made, shal make proclamation at the town
of Glocester that such offenders within .15.
dayes after such proclamation, shall restore
vnto y• party endamaged their goods
so taken, or the vaine with a reasonable amendes.
The sayd Shiriffes &amp; Bailiffes to
forfayte xx. li. if they fayle so to do. 9. Hen. 6,
cap 28.
            The Shiriffe of Herforde, neyther in his
turne or in any other place after the turne
ended, shall take any inquiry or inquest of
office which ought not to be taken there.
            Neyther shall hee take any fyne or amerciament
for thinges not appertayning to his
office or turne vppon payne to forfayte x. li.
x. Hen 6. cap 8.
            Shiriffes ought to returne in attaynt in
plea of land, men of the yerely value of xl.s
or in an action of deedes concerning lands
of such value, and in actions of the summe of
forty pound. And moreouer, those persons
dwellyng within their Bayliwicke, which
may expende twenty poundes yerely aboue
all charges for terme of lyfe at the leaste,

out of auncient demeane Gau all kinde and
the 5 portes. And at the first distresse xl.s. &amp;
at the second v.li. and the double value of
euery other distresse agaynst the iu
                  •
               oors,
vpon payne of x. pound, to the King and as
much to the partye. And if there bee not
sufficient persons dwellyng within the coū
               ty
which may expēde twenty pound, yerely
then shall they impanell other persons of y•
most sufficient possessions of yerely value of
landes and tenementes, within the value of
twenty pound vpon payne to forfayte ten
pound to the king and to the party, as much
as the fourme afore sayd, decimo quinto .H
6. cap. 5.
            The Shiriffe or vnder shiriffe of Herford
must arrest such persons of Wales, or the
Marches therof which be outlawed of treason
of felony, whō the sayde Shiriffe knoweth
or seeth to bee in any place within the
sayd county, and co bryng to the Iayle. And
if any such person beyng indyted do dysobey
of flee away: the said Shiriffe shal leuy hue
and crye, and pursue him vppon payne to
make fyne and raunsome to the kinge .23.
Hen. 6. cap 5.
            The Shriffe shall not occupy his office

aboue one yeare, and if he so doe: then to forfayt.
xx ii. and euery pardon for such offēces
shalbe voyd, any words put in such Letters
Patents notwithstanding. Also he that presumeth
to occupy the same office aboue one
yere by force of such letters patents, shall be
disabled to be Shiriffe in any other shyre afterward
.xxiii. Hē vi. cap. viii.
            No Shiriffe shall let to fearme his county,
nor any of his Bayliwickes. Hundreds
Wapentakes. No Shiriffe, Bayliffe of frā
               chyse,
ne other officer shall returne in any
panell any of his Bayliffes, officers or their
Seruauntes.
            No Shiriffe nor any other to any vse shal
take ought of any person to be arrested attached,
nor to successe of any arest or attachmēt
to be made to the body.
            Nor shall take ought of any person arested
or attached, for fine, see, sute of prison, mainpryse,
letting to baile, or for shewing any fauour
or ease to any person being so arrested,
except it be as here followeth, that is to wit
to the shiriff .xx.d. to the Bayliffe that reade
the arrest .iiii.d. and to the Iaylour if the
Prisoner be committed to ward, foure pēce.
            The Shyriffe him selfe, nor any to his

vse shall not take any thinge for the makyng
of any returne or panel, but for the coppy of
the panel .iiii.d. How be it they vse to take ii.
shillyngs for the returne of a panell but that
seemeth to be extortion.
            Shiriffes out to let out of Pryson al persons,
beeing in theyr ward by force of any
wryt, byll, or warraunt, in any action personall
or indytement of Trespasse vppon a
reasonable surety beeing sufficient in the
County to keepe theyr dayes in the places,
as the sayd Billes wryttes, or Warraunts
requyre, except such as be condempued outlawed,
excommunycated or for suretye of
the peace, or by the commaundement of any
Iustice, and vagabounds which refuse to
serue.
            Also Shiriffes ought not to take any obligations
for any thynge aboue mencioned
or by colour of theyr offyce. But onely to
them selues, nor of any Person beeynge in
theyr Ward but by the name of their offyce
as by the name of ye shirife in the Obligatiō
vppon condition that the party shall appeare
at the Dayes contayned in the Wryttes,
in such places as the Billes Wryttes or
warraunts requyre. And if any Obligation
bee taken of any Person by colour of theyr

office in any other fourme, it shalbe voyde.
            Shiriffes shal not take for any obligatiō
warrant, or precept by them to be made any
more then foure pence.
            Shiriffes must make their deputyes yerely
in the kings courtes, that is to wit in the
chauncery, the bench, and the Escheker of
recorde before they returne any writte.
            Shiriffes that do contrary to this ordinaunce
in any poynt, shall loose to the party
g
                  •
               ieued triple damages, and shall forfiate
xl.li. foreuery time that they shal so offende
the one halfe to the Kinge, and the other
to him that will sue .23. Hen. 7. cap. x.
            Shiriffes when writtes be directed vnto
them to leauie the expences of Knightes of
the Parliament, must make proclama
                  •
               ion
at the next county after the deliueraunce of
the same writtes, that the Coroners, Cō
               stables,
and Bayliffes of hundreds shall be
there to assesse their wages vppon poyne
of fourty shillinges. What tyme they shal
assesse euery hundred at a certayne summe
by it selfe, and after they shall assesse euery
village within the same hundred at a certaine
summe by it selfe, and if they be otherwise
assessed, for euerye default they shall
forfaite twenty poūds, the one halfe wherof

shalbe to the party that wyll sue. And the
Shiriff shall leuy the same duely and shall
pay it to the Knights of the Parlyament,
vpon payne of xx. pound. And the party that
wil sue shall haue his action by Scire facias,
and shall haue ten poundes aboue the
twenty pounds wyth triple damages .xxiij.
Henrici sexti capitulo vicesimo secundo.
            The Shiriffe after the deliuery of any
writ to make election for the Knyghtes of
the Parliament, must make a sufficiente
precept vnder hys Seale to euery Mayor,
and Bayliffe of Cyties, and Boroughes,
within the County, commaunding them
to elect Citizens, and Burgesses, to come
vnto the Parliament And the sayde Maior
and Bayliffe shall truely returne the same
precept to the Shiriffe by Indenture beetwene
them for the election, and names of
them that are chosen. And the Shyriffe is
bounden to make a good, and true returne
of euery such writ &amp; of euery returne made
to him by the Mayor, and Bayliffes.
            And for euery tyme that the Shyriffe
shall doe contrary to thys or any other Estatute
made for the elections of Shyriffs,
to come vnto the Parliament, hee shall encur
                  •
               e
the paine of one C. pound to the king,

and a yeres imprysonment without bayle.
            And more ouer shall pay vnto the person
so beyng chosen Knyght, Citizen or burgesse
and not duely returne: or to any other person
whych in default of such Knyght, Burgesse
or Citizen, wil sue therefore, one hundreth
pound to be recouered by Action of debt.
            And the Shiriffe ought to make such elections
in the full County betwene the houres
of viii. and 
                  •
               yne before none, and to make
a good and true returne of such elections, vpon
payne to forfaite one hundred pound to
the Kyng, and asmuch to the party that wyll
sue therefore against the Shiriffes, their executours
or administratours .xxiiii. Henrici
vii. capitulo .xv.
            Shyriffes in theyr turnes ought to enquyre,
heare and determine, if any Mynister
of the Wardeyne of the Courte in the
Marches of Scotlande: or if any other arreste
any person by hys Bodye or Attach
hym by his goodes out of the Counties of
Northumberland, and Cumberlande, and
Westmerland, and the Towne of Newecastell,
to answere in any of the sayd courtes:
or else by Colour or cause of any pro
               
                  ••••
               
in the sayd courts: for in such arrestes it

shall be lawfull for euery man to make resistaunce.
And the party grieued shall haue
an Action of false imprisonment or trespasse
and shall recouer triple damages therefore
and the defendaunt shall haue two yeres imprysonment.
And the shiriffe shall haue power
to proceede thereuppon as well as vppon a
presentment made in his turne .xxxi. Henrici
sexti. Capit. ii.
            Where as some men by dissimulation
and other meanes fayne them selues to bee
louers to Women namaryed or Maydens
or Wydowes, hauyng greate possessions
and substaunce of goods, and get some Women
into theyr possession, and conuey them
into such places, from whence they wyll
not suffer them to goe at their Liberty, except
they will make to them Oblygations
of great summes to bee payed vnto them,
or cause them to bee bounden in a Statute
Marchant, or sometime will compell them
to bee maryed at their pleasure which if
they refuse, to leuy vppon them the summes
contained in the same obligations and Statutes:
it is ordayned that the partie grieued
shall haue a writ out of the Chauncery
comprysing the whole matter of theyr
vnreasonable intreatyng, directed to the

Shyriffe commaundinge him to make pro
               
                  •
               lamation
at the nexte county after the receipt
of the writ that the offendour shal appeare
at a certayne day, &amp; place, prefixed in

                  •
               he writ before the Chaunceller or the Iuticers
of assise of the shyre where such offences
shall 
                  •
               ap to be done, or before some
other person assigned by the chaunceller.
            And the Shiriffe to whom such a wry
                  ••
               
shalbe directed, shall execute the same according
to the tenour thereof, vpon payne
of iii. C. li. the one halfe to the kyng, the other
to him y• will sue therefore by writ of
debt, wherein no wager of Law, protectiō
nor former plea (to cause the matter to bee
tryed in another Countye then where the
writ is brought) shalbe allowed .xxxi Henrici
quarti, capitulo quarto.
            Upon euery Inditemente, or Presentement
taken before Shiriffes or other ministers
in their turnes, or lawdayes. They
shall deliuer the same Indytementes, and
presentments to the Iusticers of the peace
at their next Sessions vpon payne of .xl.li.
And the Iustices of the peace shall awarde
Processe vppon the same aswell as if they
had bene taken before themselues and shal
arrayue those that be so indited of 
                  •
               elony, &amp;

shall set fines vppon such as bee indyted of
trespasse, the extreates of which fines shall
bee enrolled by Indenture, and deliuered
vnto the same Shiriffes, or mynisters.
            And if any Shiriffes, or their ministers
arrest or attache any person by colour of any
such inditement, or presentment in their
turnes, or lawe dayes, or els take any fine,
or amerc
                  •
               ament before they haue processe
from the Iustycers of the peace, or afore y•
excreats out of the Indytementes shall bee
delyuered, they shall forfayte a C. 
                  •
               . the
moyty whereof shall be to the party suing
therefore by wryt of debt, in whych no wager
of law nor protection shalbe allowed.
            Anno primo Edwardi .4. cap. vitimo.
            Upon an information made to Iusticers
of peace, or other Iusticers against any person
for retayning or geuing of liueries, or
agaynst any that is retayned or taketh lyuery,
y• Iusticers shall make processe there,
as vpon a recouery of debt or trespas. And
if the Shiriffe in any suite graunted therevpon
agaynst any person being sufficiente,
returne any lesse Issues then xx.s. at the
first day of the distresse, and at the seconde
day .xxx.s. &amp; at the thyrd day .xl.s. and so at
euery day after more by .x.s. in issues for euery

such returne hee shall forfayte .xx. s.

                  •
               . Edwardi .4. cap 2.
            The olde Shyriffe shall haue power to
returne Writs, and execute hys offyce during
the terme of S. Michaell, and Hilary
after the yeare of the sayd office expired vnlesse
he be lawfully discharged, thereof before
.15. Edwardi. 4 cap. II.
            No shiriffe nor other officer shall sease,
or take the goods of any person beinge arrested
or emprysoned for Felony vntyll the
same person be duly cōuict or attayneed of
the same Felony by course of the common
lawes or except the same goods bee otherwyse
lawfully forfayte, vpon payne to forfayte
the double value of the goods so tak
                  •
               
to the party grieued suing therefore by Action
of debt, wherein no wager of lawe essoyne
nor protection shall be allowed i. Richard.
3. capitulo. 3.
            No bayliff or other officer in any panell
within any county of this realme shall returne
any person to bee put in or vppon any
Inquiry, in the turnes of shiriffes, but such
as be of good name &amp; fame hauing freehold
to the yerely value of .xx.s. or copyholde to
the yerely value of .xxvi.s.viij.v. at the least
aboue al charges vpō pain to lese for euery

person not being sufficient, at euery tyme
that they shall so offend .xl.s. and the Shiriffe
other .xl.s. whereof y• one moyty shalbe
to the party suinge therefore by
                  •
                Action of
debt, in which suite no protection or essoyne
shalbe alowed. But wager of lawe is not
expressed. And for that cause is behooueth
to wake information thereof to the Eschequer.
primo. Richardi .iii. cap. iiii.
            Shiriffes or other, hauyng the custody
of Iayles shall certifie the names of euery
pris
                  •
               ner being in theyr custody and of them
committed for felony, vnto the Iusticers
at the next generall Iayle deliuery to bee
kalendred, vpon paine to forfayte for euery
tyme that they make defaulte in so doinge
a hundred shillinges. iii. H. 7. cap. 5.
            Also the Shyriffe nor any other person in
his name or by his commaundement
                  •
                shall
entre no playntes into their Bookes in no
mans name vnlesse the playntiffe bee there
in his proper person or els by sufficient atturney
or Deputy that is knowne of good
name, &amp; the playntiffe shall finde pledges,
persons y• bee knowne in that County, is
pursue hys playnt, and the playntiffe shall
haue but one playnt for one trespasse or one
contract. And if the shiriffe or any other his

officers cause to bee entred anye moe playntes
then the playntiffe suppposeth that hee
hath cause of Action agaynst the defendaūt
then the Shiriffe or hys Clarke that both
cause to bee entred any such playntes contrary
to this acte shal forfayt for euerye default
xl.s. the one halfe to him that wil sue,
and proue the same matter by action of deb
                  •
               
or information.
            Also the Shiriffe shal make sufficiēt precepte
after such playntes entred agaynste
the defendant directed to the Baylife of
the hundred to attach or warne the defendante-
                  •
               
appeare and aunswere to the sayd
playntes, and there be any defaulte in the
sayd Bayliffe or the hūdred in warninge or
executing of their offices, then to forfayte,
xl.s. shillinges, and to be conuict therof by
examinations of the Iustices of the peace or
any of them.
            The same Shiriffes nor their deputyes,
shall make none estates to leuye the Shyriffes
amercements til the two Iusticers of
the peace, whereof one to bee of Quorum,
haue the syghte of their Bookes, and the estreates
to be indented betwene the Iusticers
of peace &amp; the Shiriffe &amp; vndershiriffe,
sealed with their seales, the one part to remayn

with the sayde Iusticers, and the other
part with the Shiriffe.
            And those persōs that shall be gatherers
of the sayd amerciaments shalbe sworne by
the sayde Iusticers that they take no more
money then is forfayte and contained in the
estreates sealed with the seale of the Iusticers
to the same, vppon the same payne of
forfayture as is aboue rehearsed, the same
gatherers to be conuict by examination of
the same Iustices or one of them. And the
same Iusticers of peace shall be appoynted
at the sessions holden at Michelmas by him
that is custos rotu
                  •
               orum, or in his absence
by the eldest of the quorum to haue the controlement
of the sayd Shiriffes, vnder shiriffes,
shyre Clarkes &amp; other of the sayd officers,
and of the sayd shirifs amerciaments
And the said Iusticers of peace vppon suggestion
shal
                  •
                make Processe agaynst th
                  •
               
Shiriffe, vndershiriffe, shyre Clarkes, o
                  •
               
other officers to appeare before them to answere
to such suggestion or information as
is vsed in action of trespas. An. secundo. H.
6. cap. 15.
            And euery Shiriffe shall cause to bee taken
all vagabondes, idle people and suspecte
persons, and set them in the Stocke

there to remayne at the first takinge by one
day and one night, and at the second time to
be in the Stockes by 3. dayes &amp; 3. nightes
with bread and water.
            And if anye Shiriffe execute not these
premisses of euerye vagabond, bermit or
beger able to labour, or Clarkes, pilgrims,
or shipmen, as often as anye such commeth
in sight, or that he hath therfore any knowledge
within the towne or place where hee
hath authority, that as oft as any such misdoer
abydeth there aboue the space of one
day and one night and depart vnexamined &amp;
vnpunished: for euery misdoer so departed
the Shiriffe to loose three shillinges, and
foure pence, and the Shirif in his turne
hath authority to enquire of all yt defaults
of Maiors, Bailifs, high Constables, pety
Constables and all other gouernours and
officers of Cities, townes &amp; villages with
in their turne, &amp; to haue 
                  •
                s.4.d. for euerye
defaulte found in his turne. Au, 15. Hen. 7.
cap 12.
            Also euery Shirife vpon a precept directed
vnto him by the Iusticers of peace to returne
a panell to enquire of any royot or vnlawful
assemble committed, shall returne
xxiiii. persons dwelling in the shire, euerye

               
                  〈…〉
               
viii.d. of copyhold or of both ouer all charges
&amp; to returne in issues euery person. xx.s
at the first day, and at the second day .xl.s.
and if the default be in the Shiriffe for returning
of persons not being of that sufficiency
or for no returning of Issues in forme
beforesayd, he to forfait .xx li. An. xvi. Henrici
vii. capitulo. xv.
            Also if any royot 
                  •
               r assemble of people be
made in any parte of this Realme agaynste
the law, the Iusticers of the peace or two
of them of the least, and the Shiriffe or vnder
Shiriffe may come with the power of
the County (if neede bee,) to arreste and
brynge them before the same Iusticers o
                  •
               
the peace. And the Shiriffes or vnder Shiriffes
haue power to recorde that, that the
shall finde in their presence done contrary
to the Lawe, and the offendour shal
be conuicte by such recorde. And if they v
                  •
               
departed before the comming of the said I
                  •
               
               sticers
Shiriffe or vndershiriffe, then shal
                  •
               
the same Iustices or two of them within on
                  •
               
moneth after such royot enquire diligently
where they assemble was made. And if the
trueth cannot be found, then the same Iust
                  •
               cers,
or two of them and the Shiriff, or vnder

               
                  〈…〉
                within a Moneth
next following: shall certifye before the K.
and his counsaile the whole deede with all
the circumstaunces thereof, which certificate
shalbe as stronge to put the partyes to
answere thereuppon as in an inditemente
found by xi. men, 13. Hen. 4, rapi. vltimo.
            And if the sayd ryot or vnlawfull assemble
be not found by reason of any imbracery
or maintenaunce of the sayd Iury, then the
sayde Iusticers of peace, the Shiriffes ouer
and aboue such Certificate, that they
must make according to the sayde Statute
made. Anno xiii. Henrici. quarti, shal in the
same Certifycate certifye the names of the
sayde maintainers and imbrasours in that
behalfe (if any bee) with their misdemeanours
that they know, vpon paine of euery
of the said Iusticers and Shiriffes, or vnder
shiriffes xr. li. if they haue no reasonable
excuse for not certifying of the same, whych
certificate so made shal bee an inditement in
the law and euery person duely proued to
be maintayner or embrasour shal forfait, 
                  •
               x.
li. and to be committed to ward there to remayne
by discretion of the Iusticers. An xix.
Hen. vii cap xiii.
            Also that no Shiriffe vppon wryts and

preceptes directed to him do returne before
Escheatours or commissioners any person
to inquire of any landes or tenementes, except
euery of the same Iury haue landes &amp;
tenements of the yerely value of xl.s. aboue
all charges in the same Shyre vppon paine
of forfayture for euery person so returned a
C.s. Anno. 3. Henric
                  •
                oc
                  •
               aui, capitulo secū
               do.
            Also all panels put in by the Shiriff before
any Iusticers of Iayle deliuerye or before
Iusticers of peace (whereof one to bee
of the Quorum) in their open Sessions to
inquire, for the King shall bee reformed by
puting to, and taking out of the name so impanelled
dy discretion of the same Iusticers
            And that the same Iusticers or Iusticer
shall commaund euery Shiriffe and their
ministers in their absēces to put other persons
in the same panell so reformed by the
Iusticers to be good. And if any Shiriffe do
not returne the same panell so reformed,
then euery Shiriffe so offending, for euery
such offence shal forfayte xx. li. halfe to him
that wil sue by actiō of debt, bill of cōplaint
where such fall or be, and no wager of law
essoyne, nor protection shalbe allowed.
            Also vpon euery exigent (where writtes

of proclamation are to be awarded) y• same
wrytte of proclamation to haue the same
day of returne that the exigene hath, and
to be deliuery
                  •
                of recorde, and the Shiriffe
to make proclamation three seuerall dayes
in hys playne county, whereof one of the
proclamations to bee made at the generall
Sessions in those partes where the party is
supposed to be dwelling, that hee yeeld him
selfe to the shiriffe of the forrayne Shyre yt
ye shirife may haue the bodye at the day of ye
exigent, returnable to answere to ye plaints
&amp; that the Shiriffe of the sayd County that
hath such wryts of proclamation: duely execute
the same, &amp; therof make due returne
at the day appoynted in the wrytte, vppon
payne to forfayte such amerciament as by
the Iustices shalbe assessed.
            Shiriffes, Bayliffes Constables and all
other head officers and euery of them, findyng
or knowing any person vsyng or exercising
any vnlawfull game contrarye to the
Statute, haue full power to commit euery
such offender to Ward there to remayne
without bayle or maynpryse, till such time
as they so offending be bound by obligatiō
to the kinges vse in such summes of money
as by discretiō of the sayd Shiriffs or other

officers shall bee thought reasonable yt they
from henceforth shall not vse any vnlawfull
game .6. Hen. octa. capi secundo.
            If any impotent person beg within anye
other place, then within such limittes, as
hee shall bee assygned, the Shiriffe and all
other the kinges officers shall by their discretion
punish such persons b
                  •
                imprisonmēt
in the Stockes, by the space of two Dayes
and two Nightes, geuinge them Breade
and Water onely, and after that, cause thē
to be sworne to returne againe to the place
where they be licensed to beg. Anno. 32 Hē.
8. capi. duodecimo.
            The Iusticers of peace vppon informatiō
or presentment made against any township
for none executyng of this acte, shall make
proces by distresse against the inhabitaūtes
of the Towne, and thereby the shiriffe shal
distrayne the goods of one or two of the inhabitaūtes
of the Towne as he maye know
for negligēt in the Towne, and retaine the
distresse til they find surety to apeare at the
Sessions before the Iusticer.
            And vppon the returne of the Shiriffe
of the distresse if the person appeare not, thē
euery such person to loose xl.d. the first distresse,
&amp; at the second distresse. vi.s.viii.d.

on hys defaulte, and so to bee doubled at euery
distresse tyll appearaunce bee had.
            Shyriffes that haue custody of Iayles shal
make seales to bee grauen wyth the name
of the Castle that hee keepeth for
                  •
               to geeu
                  •
               
and seale Wryts to prysoners acquited, to
beg for their fees within y• bun
                  •
               reth where
he is delyuered by syxe weekes nexte after
hys deliuerye and then to goe to the Hundreth
where hee last dwelled by three yeare
or where he was borne. The shiriff shal not
suffer any such prysoner to beg for hys fees
nor to departe but to doo
                  •
                seruice and laboure
tyll that hee delyuer such Letter and
the Clarke of the peace to make the bryefe
within one daye after the Sessyons vppon
payne of .xii.d. to the Kynge. An. 22 Henri.
8. capitulo .12.
            For distroyinge of Crowes, Rooks, and
Choughes, it is ordayned that euery persō
hauing any Manours, lands, &amp; tenemēts,
in theyr manurance, shall do as much as in
him is reasonable to kyl &amp; destroy the same
Crowes and Choughs, and Rookes breeding
or abiding vpon his Landes, or Tenementes
vpon payne of a grieuous amerciament
to bee set. And if the offence be within
the limmits of Leetes, or Courte barōs

then to be set by the Steward wyth two of
the presentours by the Steward and presē
               tours
to bee named vpon the presentmente
found and presented, and to bee reasonably
assessed after the quality of the offence. And
the amerciament to be to the Lord of ye law
day, and if any person be Lord of such Manours,
or inhabyte there (wherevnto any
such Laweday or Rape is belonging) then
vpon a presentment had before the shyriffe
in his turne with two of the presentours to
be chosen by the presentours shal ceasse the
sayd amerciament by their discretion to the
vse of the Kynge, and leuyed by distresse.
An. 24. H. 8. cap. 10.
            And the Shyriffes in their turnes shall
geue in charge to the tenauntes and Inhabytaunts
appearing before them that they
shall duely enquire and put in execution the
effect of thys Acte.
            Shiriffs shall holde their Courtes from
moneth to moneth: and where greater time
is wont to be, greater shal be. Magna Carta.
cap. 33.
            The Kinge cōmaundeth that Shiriffes,
and their officers which receiue hys debts
shall acquite lawfully the debtours at the
next accomptes after that they haue receaued

the debt, and then it shall be allowed at
the Eschequer, so y• it shall not come in the
sommons after. And if the shiriff do otherwyse
and be attaynted thereof, he shal render
three tymes so much as hee hath receaued
and shall make fine at the kinges will.
            And if another do it for whose hande hee
is aunswerable at the Eschequer, hee shall
render the triple thereof to the playntiffe &amp;
shall make fine in the same. And the shiriffe
shall make tayles to all thē that haue payd
hym the Kings debts. Westminster primo
Capituli no
                  •
               o.
            Concerning Shyriffes and other which
haue leuyed the Kings debt, &amp; make ray
                  •
               es
or other acqui
                  •
               taunce to the debtour, and
discharge him not, it is agreed that when
the shiriff is impleaded therefore in the E
                  •
               
               che
                  •
               er
by the debter, if he come not at ye distres,
then shall another distres be awarded
returnable at a certayn day wherein it shal
be commaunded yt proclamatiō be made in
the full county, y• the defendaūt shall come
in by a certayne day to acquite the debtour
of the sūme, for which hee made hym y• acquitaūce
or tayle, at whych if hee come not
in, &amp; the wryt bee returned and the proclamation
certified, hee shalbe holden conuict

and the debt shall bee leuied of him, in lyke
maner as debt recouered agaynst hym in
the kinges courte &amp; damages shalbe awarded
to the playntif according to the discreation
of the Barons. 14. Ed. 2. In the Statute
of Attayntes in the last chap.
            The Kinge commaundeth that all hys
Shiriffes and Baylifes whych haue receaued
hys debts, of the somons of the Eschequers
which acquite not the debtours vpon
the next accompte shall be punyshed accordyng
to the estatute made. Distresses of y•
Eschequer. Capitulo quinto.
            It is ordayned that execution of Wryts
whych come to the Shiriffe be made by the
hundreders knowne and sworn
                  •
                and in the
full County and not by others if it bee not
for great scarcity of hundreders. For then
it shalbe done by other persons conueniēt &amp;
sworne. The statute of Lincolne ye last capi.
            Shiriffes shall not be charged with the
leauinge of any issues, nor shall leuy
                  •
                any
before they come out of y• Eschequer by the
extreats there to be leuyed. And if percase
any Shiriff returne issues vpon any recognitor
pledg or manucaptor by hym assessed,
and returned into our courte whych to the
payment of the same Issues or Amerciaments

at the time of the returne was insufficient,
y• same shyriffe shalbe charged there
wyth at the Eschequer, &amp; shal make tayles
to any person of all maner thynges by hym
receyued, and shall not returne any where
the names of Manucaptors, Iutours or
other, except it be according to the tenour
of y• Wryts to them dyrected, nor shall returne
the names of pledges of freemen any
where vnles they haue manyfestly confessed
themselues pleadges. The statute of
fines. cap. 2.
            No shyriff, Coroner, or other the kyngs
mynisters shall take no rewarde for doing
his offyce, and if he do, he shall pay the double,
and shalbe punished at the kynges will
but shall be payd of that which they take of
the kyng. West. i. cap. 26.
            Shiriffes shall not suffer any barretour
or mayntayners of matters within his coū
               ty,
neyther stewards of great Lordes, other
(which bee not atturneyes to their Lordes
to do their suites) nor to sit vpon the iudgementes
of the County, nor to pronounce
them, except hee bee thereto required of all
the Suters &amp; atturneys that shall be there
at the same io
                  •
               rney. And if he doe the contrary,
the kyng shall take it gr
                  •
               euously to

the Shiriffe, and the offendour. Westminster
prime capitulo. 31.
            It shalbe lawfull for euery Shiriff, Iusticer
of peace, and Escheator to sease to y•
Kinges vse all such goods and cattels that
such persons as come withing thys Realme
(that 
                  •
               e called Egyptians haue) &amp; thereof
to make account to the Kyng in his Eschequer,
&amp; to retayne &amp; keepe y• moyty thereof
to his owne vse, &amp; account for the residue, &amp;
to pay no fees for the accoūt nor for his discharge
thereof.
            In these Statutes it appeareth what
thing the shirif ought to do by reason of his
office, and that hee ought not to take any
thinge for doing his offyce, but onely that
which is appoynted to him by the same statute.
And if hee do or take any thyng otherwise:
it is extor
                  •
               ion, which ought to be enquired
vppon by the Iustices of the peace, &amp;
the Shiriffe shalbe punished therefore.
            And if any shiriffe doe any extortion to ye
people, and 
                  •
               ee duely attaynted thereof hee
shall straytely be punished therefore, at the
pleasure of the Kyng. Anno primo. H. 4.
captulo. 9.
            Shyriffes may, and are bound to enquire
of cōmon annoysances done to all maner of

the Kynges Subiects, but not of assaultes
made vppon any priuate person for that is
but a particuler offence, by Martin. 4. Henrici
sexti.
            The shiriffe must keepe his turne wythin
a moneth after Easter, and wythin a moneth
after the feaste of S. Michael. And if
be keepe it at any tyme after the moneth of
the sayd feasts: it is voyde by the statute of
An. 31. E. 3. cap. 19. And all inditements &amp;
presentmentes there taken after the same
tyme be voyde.
            Bloudshed shalbe enquired of in ye Shyriffes
turne, because it is an article that is
to be inquired of in a Leete. All Leetes be
deriued &amp; taken out of the Shiriffs turnes
in so much that for defaulte of enquiry in
leetes of things enquirable there, the same
thinges there omitted ought to be inquired
of in the turnes of shiriffes. 8. E. 4.
            And all the Iusticers sayde that the shyriffe
in his turne hath aucthority to inquire
of all things that be trespasse, or felony by
the cōmon law (except the death of a man)
but of trespasse, or felony made by Statute
the Shiriffe in his turne hath no power to
enquire of M. 28. Edwardi. 3.
            And if the Shiriffe in his turne inquire

of Nusances, that shoulde bee inquired of
in the Leete of an other &amp; the same be foūd,
yet may hee not distreyne for the amerciament
of such a presentment. For if he doe:
he is trespassour. But if there were a default
in the Lord of y• Leete that he would
not inquire or finde ye sūme when he ought
to haue inquired thereof, in thys case it seemeth
that y• Shyriffe in hys turne may enquire
of it in default of the Lord .M.xxviij.E.3.
And if one haue a fayre or market by
graūt or prescription, &amp; keepe not his fayre,
or market as he ought: the shiriff ought to
inquire thereof in his turne. 22 Hen. 6.
            Uppon presentment of Nusance in the
shiriffes turne, the party shall bee ame
                  ••
               ed
there by the shiryffe, which may distrayne
for the amerciament. And if propre stare be
presented there the Shiriffe may abate the
same, and refourme it. P. 26. E. 3.
            Also it appeareth by the booke of Br
                  •
               tō
that vnto the turne of the shiryffe ought to
come all the freeholders of the hūdred and
other land tenaunts (Clarkes, men of Religion
and Women onely excepted) where
at the shiriffe shal cause .3. of the most sage
and sufficient persons of the hundred to bee
sworne. And then shall all the residue bee

sworne by dosins and by the townes, which
shall make their presentment to the first xii.
Iurours, vppon the article wherewith they
shalbe charged. And it seemeth that the
Shiriffe ought to holde his turne in euery
hundred within the county.
            
               VVhat thinges be enquireable
in the Shiriffes turne.
               FIrst they shal enquire if there be any misdoer
in the hūdred of whom any standeth
in doubt of Lyfe or Lym, and what is his
name.
               Also they shall enquire of all mortall enemyes
to the King, y• Queene, their children
and councellours, of counterfaytyng ye
Kings seale or his money, of ma
                     •
                  stears and
murderers, burners of others corne or house

                     •
                   feloniously, of Burglours of robbers,
of theeues, of outlawes, of those that haue
abiured the Realme and come agayne, of
Sorcerers and witches, of miscreances, heretykes,
of traytours, and of poysoners, of

                     •
                  utters of purses, of Usurers, of bittailers
buying and felling wittyngly stolne flesh,
of them that wittinglye make whyte the
Skinnes of Beast
                     •
                  s stolne, of redubbours
that witingly 
                     ••
                  ye stolen clothes, &amp; dresse
them into an other fashion, of treasure hyd

in the grounde, hues and cryes wrongfully
or rightfully leuyed &amp; not pursued, or waters
stopped straightned or turned, of
boundes pulled vp or wrongfullye chaunged,
of Walles, houses, Gates, marle pits
Ditches, or other disturbaunces made or
le
                     ••
                  d vppon any common waye to the annoyance:
or pety bribours that sheare sheepe
to haue the wolle, of such as take the boote,
and of those that haue made a prisō of their
owne house or houshold, of pounde breach,
of trespassours in parke &amp; pondes, of takers
of other mens Dooues, of the assise of bread
and ale broken, of them that buy and sell by
measure agaynst the assise, of chaunce medleyes,
of contectours, of bloodshed, watches
vnkept, of the kinges high wayes not
enlarged, of those yt haue kept appeachers
in any other prison thē the kings or any other
felon aboue a day and a night, of newe
libertyes, customes or iurisdictions vsurped
since the last turne, on water or on land,
of weffes or wreckes of the sea, founde and
kent away, of brydges and causies broken,
and who ought to repaire them and of thos
                     •
                  
that clayme fraunchises, or iudgemente
                     •
                  
reall, and of all those of the age of twel
                     •
                  
yeares 
                     •
                  one out of the hundred which 
                     •
                  e

not come into their turne (except Clarkes,
Knightes, their Children and wiues which
bee not in do sins) of vagabondes by the
countrey which are of no mans retinue, of
whom there is an euill suspicion of lewde
demeanour.
               And when the townes haue geuen their
verdite to the first Iurours, then immediately
shal the first Iurours goe and geue vp
their presentment, such as they will abyde
by. And the presentmēt of felons they shall
shew priuily. and the other openly. Breton.
lib. 
                     •
                  . fol. 38.
               Nowe must yee inquire further if Bayliffes
of libertyes and fraūchises, haue duely
done their office, which resteth in three
pointes, which is, that they truely execute
the preceptes which be directed vnto them
according to the tenours of the same; and
that they make due answere and returne
to the Shiriffe of the same preceptes; and
that he take nothing for doing his office but
onely the fees to hym due, and appoynted
by the course of the law. And what fees they
shall take, and what thyng they ought
to doe by reason of theyr office
shal appeare more plainly
here folowing.
            
         
         
            
            The office of Bayliffes of
libertyes.
            VPpon a precept made by the Shiriffe to
a Bailiffe of libertye vppon a writte of
distresse directed to y• Shiriffe to distraine
the refendant, or the Iurours in any inquest
the Bayliffe must returne good and sufficient
issues vppon the defendaūt, or vpon the
Iurous if they haue sufficient goodes or
landes within hys Bayliweeke, and if h
                  •
               e
do not, the plaintiffe in the action shal haue
an auerment that hee might haue returned
greatter issues, if the defendaūt make defait
or the Iurours by the statute of 
                  •
               . Ed. 3.
ca. 5. And the Iusticers of t
                  •
               e peace must
inquire if the Bayliffes haue done theyr office
in that poynt.
            Also they must inquire if Bayliffes of libertyes
which bee keepers of any Iayle enforce
any of their prisoners to be appealers
to the intent to haue a fine of the partyes appealed
for daubt of imprisonment, 
                  •
               . Ed. 4.
cap vii.
            Bayliffes of lybertyes which take inditementes
in their turnes, or other where
ought to take them by Indenture, whereof
the one part shall remayne with the I
                  •
               ditours,

and the other with the Bailiffe. 2. Ed
wardi 3. Cap. 17.
            Non
                  •
                shalbe made Bayliffe of liberties
cxcept he haue sufficient landes in the place
where he is minister, to make aunswere to
the king and his people, 4. Ed. 3. cap. 9.
            Bayliffes of libertyes which be Ioilours
and haue the kepinge of prisons oughte to
receyue and safely keepe all the eues deliuered
to them by the Cōstables of the townes
being indited, taken with the maner or appealed
of felony without taking ought. 4.
Ed. 3. cap. 19.
            Bayliffes of libertyes must receyue such
persons as be arrested in their fraunthise by
the Constables, for suspicion of felony that
walke in the Country by night or be of euill
name, and shall keepe them in Prison
vntill the comming of the Iustices of Iaile
deliuery, &amp; in the meane tyme the bailiffes
must inquire of thē. 5. E 3 cap. 14.
            Bailiffes of libertyes, Constables &amp; other
officers of townes where 
                  •
               oyterers and bagabonds
resort, haue power to examine thē
diligently, &amp; compell them to find surety by
sufficient mainpernours being distreinable
of their good behauyour.
            And if any default be founden in the same

               
                  •
               oyterers and bagabonds, and cannot finde
suerty, they shalbe sent to the next Iaile,
there to remayne vntil the comminge of the
Iusticers of Iaile deliuerye, which may do
with them, as they shall thinke best by the
course of the law. 7. R. 2. cap. 5.
            No seruaunt or labourer at the ende of
his terme shall depart out of the hundred or
Rape where hee is dwellinge to dwell any
other where, vnlesse hee bryng a letter patent
contayning the cause of his going vnder
the kinges sea
                  •
               e thereto assigned. And
if any seruant labourer be found vagarant
without such letter, hee shalbe taken forth
by the Shirifs, Maiors, Bailifes, or other
officers: and put in stoekes till hee fynde suerty
of returne to the towne to serue, from
whence he came, vntil he haue such a letter
to depart for cause reasonable. 12 R. 2. ca. 3.
bailifs of libertyes haue power to arest seruantes
&amp; labourers y• wear daggers swordes
&amp; knyfes: and them to sease and keepe
vntill the sessions of the peace and the weapons
to present to ye Iustices there with the
names of them that bare them, and the weapons
shalbe forfayte, except they bee trauailing
in the countrey with their maister, or
theyr landes or busynesse. 12. R. 2. cap. 6.
            
               
Shyriffes &amp; Bayliffes o
                  •
                libertyes in theyr
libertyes are bound to receiue seruauntes
and labourers begging and vagarant, and
them to detayne in Prison without baile,
without taking anye fee or other thing of
them at theyr entring or departing by them
selues or by their deputies vppon paine of a
C.s. to the king xii. R. ii. cap. 9.
            Bayliffes of libertyes to whom the keeping
of the assyse of breade and ale, and the
correction of the same belongeth, shall take
no amerciament nor fyne for no default touching
the sayd assise for which the offendour
ought by the lawe to haue corporall penaunce,
but they shall iudge theym to the
same penaunce. And Baylifes of liberties
and ail other that haue the keepinge and
ouersyght of vittayles shall put in due execution
the statute made in the 23. yere of Et
the .3. which beginneth, quia maior pars populi.
&amp;c. 13. R. 2. cap 8.
            Butchers, Fishers, Hostelers, Bruers,
Bakers, Pulters, and all other sellers of
vittayles, are bounden to sell such maner
of Uittailes at a reasonable price hauing
regard to the price wherat such vittails are
solde in other places neare so that they
may haue a competent gaine and not excessiue

according as by the distance of the
places from whence the vittailes are carted
they shall thinke reasonably to be required.
And if any sell vittailes in any other maner
and thereof be conuict: he shall pay the double
of that he hath receiued to the party indamaged,
or in his default to any other that
will sue therfore. And maiors and Bailiffes
of townes &amp;c. haue power to enquire of all
such as offend agaynst this ordinaunce in any
poynt, and in case that the same Maiors,
and Bailiffes be negligent in doyng execution
of the premisses and thereuppon bee
conuicted by the Iusticers assygned by vs,
they shalbe cōpelled by the same Iusticers
to restore the triple value of the thing solde
to the party greeued, or to any other that in
his defalt wil sue, and neuerthelesse shal be
greeuously punished against vs. 24. Ed. 3.
capi 6.
            No Steward, Bayliffe, nor other minister
of Lordes of fraunchise which haue returne
of writtes shalbe atturney to any person
in any matter within the same fraunchise
or Bayliwicke where hee is officer at
any maner tyme 4. H. 4. cap xix.
            If any haynous roiot 
                  •
               e made, the Iusticers
of the peace, &amp; the Shiriffe or vnder-Shyriffe

ought to do their office according
to the statute made. 13. H. 4. And if they
doe not, at the suite of the party grieued 
                  •
               
cōmission shall goe forth to inquire thereof
and of the default of y• Iusticers &amp; the Shiriffe,
and y• Coroner shall serue the processe
and he must returne persons y• haue Lande
to the yerely value of x.li. and shall returne
also .xx.s. in Issues at the first day and .xl.s.
at the seconde, and at the thirde a C. shillings,
and so double it at euery day after.
And if default be in the Coroner in returning
the Issues or of persons of such lande
bee shall leese .xl. pounde. And if the olde
Shiriff be discharged, the new shiriff shall
serue the processe, and not the Coroner vppon
payne of xl.
                  〈◊〉
               . if the default he found in
him, touching the returne of other persons
by him impanelled whych haue not landes
to the yearely value of .x.li. or to returne
such Issues as the Coroners bee charged
with. And Bayliffs of libertyes are bound
for to impaneli sufficient persons, as aboue
is sayd vpon payne to leefe .xl
                  •
               l. in case that
such persons may be found within his bayliwicke.
2. Hen. 5. Capitulo. 8.
            Bayliffs of fraunchises ought to make
their returnes and aūswers vnto y• shiriffe

vpon hys precept made vnto them in a speciall
wryt of assise .6. dayes before the daye
of the sessions vppon payne to forfayte .xl.li.
for euery tyme that they shall doe the contrary
.vi. Hen. 6. cap. 2.
            Where a Precept is made to the Shyriffe
by Iusticers of the peace, to returne a
panell to inquire of forcible entre, and hee
sendeth his precept to the bayliff of y• liberty
to returne the panell because y• ry
                  ••
                was
done within the Liberty, nowe is the Baylyff
boūden to make due returne and execution
of the Precepts to hym dyrected vpon
payne of .xx.l
                  •
               . for euery defaulte. And the
statute wyll that the Shyriffe shall returne
xx s. in issues vpō euery Iurour at the first
day, &amp; that euery Iurour whych shall passe
in y• inquiry shall spend .xl.
                  •
               . yearely where
by it seemeth that bayliffs of lyberties are
bounden to doe lykewise, if so many of the
sayd Iurours be within hys liberty for els
he is not. 8. Hen. 6. cap. 9.
            Bayliffs of lyberties in attayntes vppon
plea of land of the yearely value of .xi.s. or
more nor in attaynts for deedes cōcerninge
lands of lyke value, nor in attayntes vppon
personal actiōs wherein the recouery extē
               deth
vnto .xl.l
                  •
               . or more shall not returne,

or impanell any person in such inquests but
those that be dwelling wythin hys Baylywicke,
and that haue Estate to theyr owne
vse in landes or tenemēts for terme of Lyfe
to the yerely value of xx.l
                  •
               . or more, within
his Bailywick out of aūcient deme
                  •
               ne, &amp;
the five portes. And at the first day of y• dystresse
returned shall returne no lesse issue
in such actions of attayn
                  •
               e then .xl.s. and y•
second distresse .C.s. and the double of euery
other distresse vpon the persons so impanelled
and returned And if he doe the contrary
he shall pay .x.li. to the Kinge and as
much to the party. 15 Henri
                  •
               l. 6. capitulo
quinto.
            Bayliffs and other the Kynges officers
may arrest those Souldiers that come frō
the Sea, &amp; shew not letters Testimonialls
from their captayns that they haue lycēsed
them. And they shal keepe the
                  •
                vntill they
haue inquired whether that they had licēce,
or not, and if they haue no such Lycence
thē shal they be punished as 
                  •
               e
                  •
               ons. 28. H. 6.
capi. 19.
            No Bayliffe of a liberty vpon any precepte
to him directed to returne the panell
of any enquest shall in the same returne any
bayliffes, officers or seruants to any Officer

aboue sayde, nor shall take any thynge
by them selues, or by other, of any persō by
them arrested or attached to their owne vse
or auayle nor it any other person for any
arrest or attachmēt by y• body made by thē
or that is arrested by vertue of their office
for fine, fee, suite of person, maynprise, letting
to bayle, of shewing of any case or fauour
to any person so being arrested for
their rewarde or profit, but as is heere lymitted,
yt is to wit, for the Shiriffe .xx.d. the
Bayliffe yt maketh the arrest .iiii.d. &amp; to the
Iaylour if the prisoner be cōmitted to hym
iiij.d. And no Bayliffe of any Liberty, nor
Coroner by him selfe nor by other, by colour
of his office shall take any thing for the
making of returne, or panell, &amp; for the copy
of a panell, but .4.d. And bayliffes of libertyes
shall let out of pryson all prisoners by
them arrested, or beinge in their keepinge
by force of any bill, writ, or warrant in any
action personall, or by force of any inditement
of trespasse, vppon reasonable surety
hauinge sufficient wythin the Bayliwicke
where they bee let to bayle, to keepe their
daies in ye same places as ye same bill, writ,
or warrant shall require, those onely excepted,
which be in warde vppon condemnation

or bee excommunycate or outlawed
or arrested, vpon suretye of the peace,
and vagarantes that refuse to serue. And
that the sayde Bayliffes shall not take any
Obligation of any person nor by any person
beyng in theyr Warde by course of the
Lawe, for any the causes aboue rehearsed
but in the name of their Office, and vppon,
the condition that the same Persons shall
appeare at the dayes contained in the sayde
writtes Billes, or Warraūtes and in such
places as they requyre. And if any Bayliffe
take any Obligation in any other fourme,
by colour of hys Office it shall be voyde,
and that he shall take no more for the making
of any such Obligation, UUarraūt or
precept by them to be made but .iiii d. And
if they doe contrary to this ordinaunce in any
poynte for so doyng they shall render to
the party grieued his damages treble, and
shall forfaite for euery tyme that they dothe
contrary .xl.li. the one half whereof shal be to
him that wil sue in any of the kings courtes
therefore. &amp;c. xxiii. H. vi. cap x.
            Bayliffes of liberties ought not to seale
the goods of any person arrested or imprisoned
for felony before that they shall bee conuice
or attaynted of the same Felony according

to the law or els that the same goodes
be otherwise forfaited, vppon payn to forfait
the double value of the goods so taken vnto
the parties endamaged suing therefore by
action of debt, wherein no wager of Law, essoyne,
nor protection shall in any wise be allowed
to the defendaunt .i. Richardi ii. capitulo
.iii.
            Bayliffes of Liberties that be Iailers &amp;
haue the keeping of Iailes shall certifye the
names of euery prisoner in his Iayle that is
there for felony at the next generall Iayle
deliuery in euery County or franchyse
where such Iayle is to bee kalendred before
the Iusticers of the same Iayle delyuery,
vppon pain to forfait for euery default
there recorded .v.l.iii. Hen viii. cap. iii.
            Al Bayliffes and other head officers and
euery of them findyng or knowyng any person
vsing or exercising any vnlawful games
contrary to the statutes haue power to commit
euery such offender to ward and there to
remaine in prisō, without baile or mainprise,
till such time as he be bound by obligation
in such summe as by discretion of hym that
taketh the bonde seemeth reasonable to the
kings vse that he shal play no more. An. vi. H
viii. cap. ii.
            
               
All statutes made agaynst Siriffes, vnder
Shiriffes, Baylifs or other Ministers
for making &amp; returnyng of pannels or Iuries
or for due execution of seruing of Writs
or other processe, or for takyng of fees or for
the reformation of extortions, or for any other
thinge concernyng their office and all
paynes contayned in euery such Statute
shal be extended to all stewards, bayliffes &amp;
other ministers and officers of Liberties and
franchises hauing returne of writs and execution
thereof in like maner as they extende
to Shiriffes, theyr vndershiriffes, bayliffes,
or other ministers, sauing that the bayliffes
and officers of liberties may ocupy their offices
for as longe time as they shalbe geuē vnto
them An. xxvii. Henrici octaui capitulo
.xxiii.
         
         
            ¶The office of Escheators.
            YE shall inquire of Escheators, if they
haue duely executed theyr Office and if
they haue taken any more for doing thereof
then they ought or if they haue committed &amp;
done any extortion or oppressiō vnto yt kings
people by colour of their office.
            And therefore yee shall vnderstand that

no Escheator oughte to meddle or inquyre
for the Kynge, but in case where the Kyng
of right ought to bee intituled and haue the
Land or thinge that is found for him by the
inquest, for if one hold of the Kyng as of hys
Duchy of Lancaster by knights seruice and
dye, his heyre being wythin age, the Kynge
to haue the ward of the heyre and the Land.
And yet in case that if the Escheator finde
it by Office hee shall haue nothyng for the
findyng thereof, because the Tenaunt helde
not of the Kynge in chief as of his Crowne.
And therefore the King may enter and sease
the Land and the Heyre wythout office and
may graunt it. In like manner if the Eschetor
finde by Office that one died seased and
helde of other Lordes and not of the Kynge
by Knightes seruice and that he is deade and
his heyre wythin age, the Escheator shall
demaunde nothing of ryghte for findyng
of such an Office. And so if he finde an office
that one dyed seased of such a manner in fee
and helde of the Kynge as of such an honor
or Castell by knights seruice, and his Heyre
within age yet oughte not the Escheatour
to haue any fee or duety for the findyng of
that office, and if 
                  •
               e take any thynge therefore
it is extortion which is well proued

by the writ of diem clausit extremum the
wordes whereof bee these. Quia Georgius
Per. qui de nobis tenuit in capite die quo
obijt diem clausit extremum vt accepimus,
ideo tibi precepimus. &amp;. Whereby it
appeareth if one holde not of the Kynge in
chiefe, the Escheator ought not to haue the
fee of xl.s. for fynding of the Office. And
if he take it in that behalfe it is extortion.
            And in assise if the defendant say that
the Landes are seased into the Kings hands
by the Escheator, and the Escheator being
there present and examined by the Iusticers
thereuppon doth confesse that he hath seased
the Lands into the kinges handes where indeede
he hath not so done: in this case the escheator
doth wronge to the plaintif whych
may haue an action vpon his case agaynst the
Escheator for his faished, and for that delay
that he hath sustained through that confession
by suing to the Kinge for a Procedendo.
            
            None shalbe subescheator vnlesse hee haue
sufficient la
                  •
               d in those places where he is officer
to aunswere to the king and his people
in case that any will complaine against thē.
Anno quarto. Edwardi tertij. cap ix. Anno. v
tiusoem. cap. iiii.
            
               
The Escheators shall bee chosen euery
yere as the Shiriffes shall bee &amp; by the same
persons that chose the Shiriffes.
            And that no Escheator shall abyde in hys
office aboue one yere. An. xiii. Edwardi tertij
capitulo .vii.
            The Escheators shall not doe waste in
Bishoprickes and other places during the
vacation of them, neither shall sell vnder
woods, nor chase in parke or warraunts nor
fish in Pondes, or free fishings, nor may take
no fines of any tenements free nor bound, but
shall cause them to be kept and saued without
doing damage or any maner of oppressiō.
An. xxiiii. E. iii. cap. iiii.
            So by this statute it appeareth that it
appertayneth to the office of an Escheator
to sease the temporalities of Archbishoprickes,
Byshoprickes, and Abayes of the
kings foundation, during the vacation of ye
same, and take the profites and to accompte
for them to the Kynge in the Escheker how
be it there is an other statute made in the
same yeare in the effecte whereof is, that if
the Deane and Chap. Prior or supprior wil
take temporalities to Fearme, paying the
value according to the remembraūces in the
Eschecker, that they shall haue them before

any other. And by an other statute made
the same yeare, cap. quinto, the Chauncelour,
Treasurer of the Eschecker, taking
to them such other of the counsaile as they
shall thinke good, shall lease the vacations
of Archbishoprickes, Bishoprickes, Abbeis
Prioryes and other Houses of religion the
auoydance whereof belonge to the king the
Deane and Chap. Prior or Supprior, Prioresse
or Supprioresse, Couent at a certaine
rent to pay by the yeare, quarter or Moneth
during the vacations, as they shall thynke
best, without makyng fine. And neither the
Escheator nor any other officer shall seeke
cause or matter to enter or to meddle, or do
any thynge in a preiudice of the Churche.
Sauing to the King and his heyres, knights
fees, aduousons, Escheates, wardes, Mariages,
reliefes and seruices to the said fees belonging,
In witnes whereof the kynge caused
his letters Patentes to bee made, thereof
dated at West. the viii. day of Apryll. The
yeare aboue mencioned whereby it appereth
that the authority aforesayd to make Leases
was geuen to the Chaunceller &amp; the Treasurer
by the kings letters patents. &amp;c. Anno
.xiiii. E. iii. cap. vi.
            The escheators &amp; other the kings ministers

must make accompte in the Eschecker after
this manner that is of Lands and tenemēts
whereof profit ariseth from tyme to tyme,
throughout the yeare as of Milles, Harbages
to
                  •
               pleas, profites of cources, or such other
issues and profites, they shal be bounden
to aunswere the king for the rate &amp; value
of the tyme accordyng to the old course
of the Escheker. And touchyng auncyent
fearmes and rentes that are to be payde at
certayn tearmes as rent seeke, and rent seruice,
whereof no profit ariseth vntil the daye
of paiment, such rents and fearmes shal bee
paid vnto them that haue liuery thereof out
of the Kings hand at the termes of paiment
of the said fearmes and rents next folowyng
such liuery made, as wel for the tymes paste
as the time to come .xxviii. Ed. iii. cap. iiii.
            The Kinge and his Progenitors haue
bene seased at forfaitours of Warres, tyme
out of mynde that is aswell of Landes and
possessions as of goodes and cattels. And by
colour thereof the Escheators by their office
haue seased many landes and tenemētes,
as forfaytes to the Kynge surmising treason
in some persons beyng dead at the tyme
of the seaser, whych neuer were attaynted
in theyr liues, the Kyng hath ordayned touching

such forfaytures that fell in the tyme
of his Graūdfather and before that so soone
as an inquest thereof shall be returned into
the Chauncery by any Escheator or other
that hath power to enquyre thereof the Tenaunt
shall not hee put out of possession but
shall bee warned by a Scire facias, to appeare
at a certaine day for to answere vnto
the same if he will, &amp; if no such forfaiture
be sound the kinges hand shall bee closed so
that in all other cases of forfaitures of treason
by persons deceased nor attaynted, nor
iudged in theyr Lyues their heyres nor lād
Tenauntes shall not bee chalenged nor impeached
of any other Forfaytures but of
those onely that haue bene iudged in tyme
paste afore the death of certayne persons by
presentment in Eire in the Kings Bench, as
of felons of the king &amp; other. And therefore
it seemeth that if one moue warre agaynste
the King in his realme and is slayne in the
same: then the Escheator may sease the lands
&amp; tenements as forfaitour of Warre without
any other inquiry to be made thereof.
            Euery Escheatour muste take his inquestes
of office of good and lawfull men,
sufficient of inheritance and of good fame &amp;
of the same county where the inquiry shall

be made. And the inquestes shalbe indented
betwene the escheators and the iurours, &amp;
if it be otherwise done: they shall bee voyd,
and they shal be taken in good townes openly
Trauerse may be taken to the escheators
office, whereby any alienation or dying seased
or that the heire is within age, and the
land holden of the Kyng in chiefe is found.
            Lands seased into the kyngs Handes by
reason of ward shal be kept without waste.
And the escheators shall haue no fee of venison,
fish, nor other thing, but shall answere
the Kinge of the issues and yearely profites
arising of the sayd lands without wast. And
if he do otherwise, then to make fine at the
Kings will, and to pay treble damages at
the sute of the heyre, as well within age, as
of full age.
            And if he be within age hys Freendes
shall haue the sute for him, answeryng to
the heyre of that, that shall bee so recouered
of him. Concerning other landes seased into
the Kynges handes by inquest of office by
the escheators this foresayd ordinaūce, and
punishment shall holde place agaynste the
escheator. And if any make claime to lands
so beeing seased: the Escheator shall returne
an in inquest into the Chauncery with

in one moneth after such seaser, so that a
writ he deliuered to him to certifie the cause
of the seaser, and there shall the party bee
harde to trauerse the Office, or otherwise
to shew his ryght, And the Chauncellour
vppon his owne discretion (if hee see cause
may sease the Lands to the Tenaunt paying
to the king the value, if it belong to the king
so that he findes surety, that he shall doe no
wast until it be adiudged.
            And the Escheators shall take theyr inquestes
in good townes, and by honest Men
openly by Indenture to be made betweene
the Escheator and them of the inquest. And
if he doe contrary to this ordinaunce: then
to haue two yeares imprysonment, and further
to make fine at the Kinges pleasure.
Anno. xxxvi. Ed. iii. cap. xxii.
            None shall bee Escheator if he haue not
xx. li. Land at the least or more in fee and that
they execute their office in proper persō. And
if he be otherwise then to be put out, whereby
it appeareth that the Subescheator can
not inquyre nor fynd offyce. An. xli. Edwardi
iii. capitulo v.
            Escheators nor Commissioners, shal not
take inquest, but by those that be impannelled
and returned to the shiriffe, and if they

doe other wyse and bee conuicte by examination
or otherwyse at the sute of the party
or of the Kinge or any other person that
will sue, they shall incurrethe payne of .xl.li.
the moitye to him at whose sute they shall
be counict. And that no landes seased into
the kings handes shal be let to fearme by ye
Chauncellour, vntill the inqueste and vervits
bee returned into the Chauncery, and
by one moneth after the same returne except
it bee to the party grieued which was
put out of those lands by the inquestes and
will offer to trauerse them, and shewe good
euydence and and finde sufficient suretie to
sue his trauerse with effect, and to pay to ye
king the yearely value of the lands
                  •
                If it happen
to be discussed for the kinge. And if any
Letters patentes of any lands or tenements
to the contrary be made to any other persō
then to him that offereth to trauerse, or hee
let to fearme with in a moneth nexte to the
sayd moneth of returne: they shal be voyd
and holden for none, A viii. H. vi. cap. xix.
            Escheators, and Commissioners, shall
returne the inquestes taken before them into
the chauncery or in the Eschecker with
in one moneth next after the takyng of the
same vppon payne of xx. l. the one moitye to

the King, the other to him that wil sue, An.
viii. Hen. vi. cap xix.
            And if any Escheator take any office before
him and do not returne the same into the
Chauncery or the eschecker within the moneth
next after the taking thereof he shal incurre
the pain of forty poūd forfait by the statute
made. Anno. viii. Heurici .vi. and further
shal be bounden to pay to the King as much
as he is indamaged by the not returnyng of
the same. And yt the Chaūcellour of Englād
callyng to hym the Treasurer of England
may lease such Fearmes, for the due execution
of the sayd Statute. Neuerthelesse it appeareth
that the same statute giueth but xx.
pound of forfait against the Escheator or cō
               missioner.
Therefore search for the true record
of both the statutes. An xviii. Hen. vi. capitulo
.vii.
            Escheators must take their inqueste of
office by vertue of the writs of diem clausit
extremum, and other Writtes wythin one
moneth after the receipte of the same. And
that such inquestes be taken in good townes
and open places. And that none of them
priuily nor openly by him selfe or by other,
take any thynge for the execution of such

wryts in one county aboue the summe of vis.
viii.d. or xiii. 
                  •
               . iiii.d. or vnder, wyth hys
labour and his costs so that the same that he
hath taken altogither exceede not aboue xi.
s. for the execution of any such wryt, in one
county. And if he do contrary to the premisses
thē to forfait the sūme of .xl.l. the moytie
to him that wyll sue for the kyng and hymself.
An. xxiii. Hen. vi. cap. xvii.
            None shall be Escheators if hee haue
not Landes or Tenements to the value of .xx
Pounde wythin the Countye, for terme of
Lyfe nor in the Countye where hee is Escheator.
Nor no Escheator shal let hys office
to fearme nor make deputy other then hee
wyll at his peryll answere for, whose name
he must certify by hys Letters patentes to
the Treasurer and Barons of the Escheker
for the tyme beyng wythin .xx. dayes after
such deputation made, And that no such
deputy take vppon hym to occupy in the said
office vnlesse the Escheator haue Lands tenementes
or Rentes to the yerely value of
xx.l. as before is sayde. And if any Person
do contrary to the premisses or any of them
then to forfayte for euery defaulte .xl.li. the
one moitye to hym that wyll sue and the other
to the vse of the Kyngs house by action

of debt, where no wager of law essoine or
protection shal lye .22. E. 4: cap ix.
            No Shiriffe, Escheator nor other persō
shall sease or take the goodes of any person
arrested or imprisoned, for felony before the
same person so arrested or imprisoned, bee
conuicte or attaynted of the same felony, accordyng
to the law of England, or that the
same goods shall be otherwyse forfayted vpon
payne to forfayte the double value of ye
goods taken to the party damaged, suinge
therfore by action of debt, where no wager
of law, essoyne nor protection shal lye. An.
1. R. cap. 3
            If any Escheator or commissioner put in
to any of the kinges courtes any inquisition
or office concerning landes or tenementes,
or other hereditamentes not found nor presented
by the oathes of 12. men, and indēted
&amp; by them sealed, then to forfayte for euerye
such offēce returned and put vnto any of the
kinges courtes on .C.ii. to the party grieued
A. iii. Hen vii. cap. ii.
            No Escheator nor other Commissioner
shall sit by vertue of any commission to inquire
of landes or tenementes except hee
haue landes or tenementes or hereditamēts
to the yerely value of fourty markes, ouer

all charges vpon payne of xx. pound.
            The Escheators, and Commissioners
shall be discharged by theyr othes that they
may not dispend xl. Marke ouer all Charges
and that vppon proces made agaynste
them out of the Eschecker. The Escheators,
and Commissioners shal sit in opē places &amp;
shall suffer euery person to giue euidence openly
in theyr presence to the inquest taken
before them vpon paine of .xx.l.
            The Iary shal receiue the Counterpayne
of the Indenture that shalbe presented, indē
               tēd
and sealed by the Escheator, Commissioners
and to rest in the possessiō of the first
man that was sworne in the same Iury vpon
paine of euery person that shal be sworne .xx.
shillings.
            And euery Escheator and Commissioner
after the Iury is sworne, and ready to gyue
theyr verdit, and offer to present the same yt
the same Escheators or Commissioners or
part of them shal receiue the same verdit wt
               out
further delay vpon paine of a C li. &amp; deliuer
the counterpaine of the same Indenture
to the Iury in fourme before sayd vppon the
same paine.
            And if the Clarke of the pety Bagge, or
his deputye will not receiue such Offices,

and put it into the Fyles to remayne of recorde
wythin three dayes after it be receaued
or offered to be receaued, he to forfayte
for euery such default .xl.l
                  •
               . And y• cōmissiner
&amp; Escheator to be discharged of the penalty
of .xl.li. lymitted by the Statute for
none returning of the same offyces, or inquisition
wythin one moneth.
            The like lawe &amp; penalty to bee agaynst
the officers in the kings Eschequer which
ought to receiue such inquisition, for refusing
so to receiue them. And the Commissioners,
and Escheators to bee discharged of
the penalty for not returninge of the same
inquisition, so made by the sayde Escheators,
or Commissioners at any tyme after
the moneth of such office, before thē founde
or before any of them wythin an other moneth
then next ensuing, returned the sayde
office into the Chaūcery, or Eschequer, as
the case shall require. And the clark of the
Pety bag to certify the transcript of euery
such offyce taken before any commissioner,
or Escheator, into the Eschequer the nexte
tearme following the receipt thereof, vpon
payne of 
                  •
               .C.s. for euery default.
            And no man be compelled to occupy the
office of Escheator by any patent ouer one

whole yeare, &amp; hee that is once Escheator
shall not be Escheator agayne wythin .iij.
yeres next after yt sayd whole yere ended.
            If any Escheator exercise his offyce by
reason of any Patent ouer the tyme of one
whole yeare ended, or bee made Escheator
within .iij. yeres after: then after the sayd
whole yeare ended hys patent so made to
be voyd &amp; the party grieued shall haue his
recouery of euery of the sayd forfaytoures
of one .C.li. by action of debt, where no wager
of law, essoyn nor protection be allowed.
There hee dyuers prouisions made for
dyuers Escheators in Cities, &amp; Boroughs
and in diuers counties.
            And if the Lands, or tenementes of any
man be seased in the kynges hande by vertue
of any office founde before the Escheator
or Cōmissioner, or by reason of any other
recorde foūde in the Chauncery or the
Escheker, &amp; be y• is so put out of his landes
by reason of such recorde or offyce so found
come and trauerse that Recorde, or Office
and it is found for hym wherevpon he hath
his iudgement, that the Kyngs hands bee
closed &amp; amoued: nowe if so bee that there
bee an other recorde, or office found remayning
amongest the Kyngs recordes, which

is not trauersed nor tryed, yet shall not the
Escheator sease the lands agayne into the
kings handes by the reason of the recorde
b
                  •
               ing founde not trauersed. And if he doe;
then both hee wronge and exto
                  •
               cion, and
the party that is put out shall haue assyse against
him, and shall recouer double damages
agaynst hym. But in this case the king
must sue a Scire facias agaynst hym that
hath the lands out of his hands vpon thys
other record or office, that was not trauersed
before. This is giuē by the Statute of
Lincolne, calles the statute of Escheators.
Anno 20. Edwardi .2.
            And if the Escheator by colour of his offyce
wythout warrant, or authority of the
law that belongeth to his office, dissease any
man of hys Landes or tenementes, the
party that is disseased shall haue an assyse
of Nouel disseison, and shal recouer double
damages agaynste the Escheator, Westmin.
1. capi. 26.
            The Escheator hath no power to amearce
any man that appeareth before hym, and
misdemeaneth him selfe, or if the Iurours
that 
                  •
               ee 
                  •
               ōmoned appeare before doe make
default, he shall recorde such things in his
Role, and shall not amearce the Iurours,

but hee shall sende the same recorde to the
Iustycers in Eire, or to the Iustycers of
assyse when they come into the countrey.
It shalbe lawfull to the Shiriffe, Iusticer
of peace, &amp; Escheators to sease to the kings
vse all such Goods, and Cattels that such
persons as come within this Realme, that
bee called Egyptians haue, and thereof to
make accompt to ye king in his Eschequer,
and to retayne and keepe the moity thereof
to his owne vse, and accompt for yt residue,
and to paye no fees for the accompt nor for
hys discharge thereof.
         
         
            The Offyce of Constables.
            FOr asmuch as the offyce of a Constable
was an office at the common Lawe
of long cōtinuance, &amp; was firste ordayned
for the cōseruation of the kinges peace
to be had and kept in euery towne amonge
the kings Subiects there dwelling, somewhat
shal be spoken. And howe farre forth
their power doth extend, and what penalties
are prouided agaynst them, for not executing
theyr Offyces.
            Who were conseruatours of the peace
at the common lawe.
            
               
IT is now seene for the conseruation of the
peace, what persons by the common lawe
had authority therein, before the making of
the Statutes whereby the Iusticers of the
peace are ordayned.
            And it seemeth that by the common lawe
dyuers persons were conseruatours of
the peace, for at the common law there was
one persō which is called thiefe Iustice of
England, to whō the king cōmitted his authority
in ye ministratiō of iustice for things
touching his crowne, &amp; for the conseruation
of hys peace among his subiectes through
out al his realme, And that is proued by the
writ which the K. sēdeth to him, yt he should
hold his place in the ministratiō of Iustice
to his subiectes in the forme aboue saide,
throughout all his realme, wherby it doth
appeare that the same chiefe Iustice is high
conseruatour of the peace throughout all
the countyes of England, and in euery part
of the Realme where he goeth. Also there
be other persons conseruators of the peace
throughout the Realme, as the steward of
England, the Marshall, and the Constable
of England. Also the Constable of euerye
towne were and bee keepers of the peace
by the common law: likewyse the high Constables

of hundreds, wapentakes, lathes,
or tithinges were and bee conseruatours of
the peace by the common lawe within the
townes or hundreds, and within their limittes.
And before the making of the Statutes
whereby Iusticers of the peace are
ordayned, the king by his commission made
conseruatours of the peace in those coūties
&amp; places (where hym thought best) to keepe
his peace, and the authority which conseruatours
of the peace, had by the common
law, is the same authority that a Constable
of a towne or wapentake hath at this day,
which I shall partly touch.
            If one make assault vppon the Cōstable,
the Constable may defend hym and maye
take him, and commit him to the Iaile, vntill
he haue found surety to keepe the peace,
though that the assaulte were made vppon
him selfe. As it appeareth Micha. v. Henrici.
vii. in the tytle Bar. Much more then if
a Constable see one making assult vppon
a straunge person, he may take hym and cō
               mit
him to prison, or to the Iaile, vntill he
haue found surety to keepe the peace.
            And if one man threate another wherevpon
hee that is threatned commeth to the
Constable, and sheweth his matter, &amp; prayeth

hym to compell hym that so threatned
him to find surety: in this case the Cōstable
and the party that is threatned may goe and
compell him that so did make such threatning
to fynd surety to keepe the peace, and
yf he wil not: they may commit him toward
vntill hee haue founde such suretye as you
may see Mich. 44. Edwardi 3. in the tytle of
Bar.
            And if one be stricken in perill of death, it
is the office of the Constable of the Towne
to arrest the offender, and to keepe hym in
prison vntill it be knowen whether the party
so stricken shall liue or dye vntill that hee
haue found suretie to appear before the Iusticers
of Iayle deliuery, or at such tyme as
he shalbe called vppon to appeare before y•
Iusticers at their discretion.
            And if one flee for felony it is the office of
the Cōstable of the town to sease his goods
and to keepe them, and if they hap to be impayred
in his keeping, he shall answere for
them to the King 2. E 3. in the Shyre of
Northampton, but by the statute ma
                  •
               e. 1. R
3. capit. 3. that is chaunged. And if felons
or murderers he in the town, &amp; the Constable
haue knowledge thereof, it is hys office
and duety to assemble people for to take thē
            
            
               
And yf one take a felon in the Towne &amp;
bryng hym to the Constable to bee cōueyed
to the Iayle, the Constables office is to cary
hym thither, and to cause other of the
towne to ayde and assist hym in so doyng.
            And note that the constables were ordained
for two intentes, yt is to wit, to keepe
the peace, and also to represse felons, to take
surety by obligation of such persons as they
shall fynde making of frayes.
            It apperatyneth to the office of the chiefe
Constable of England to haue co
                  ••
               sance of
deedes of armes any contractes touchinge
deedes of armes &amp; of war out of the realme
and in lyke manner of thynges touchinge
armes within the realme; which cannot
bee determined by the common lawe, as it
appeareth clearly by the Statute made the
13. yere of Ri. 2. cap. 2.
            Also it appeareth by the Statute made. anno
primo. H. 4. cap. 13. that all appeales to
to bee made of thinges done out of y• realme
of England shalbe tried and determined before
the Constable &amp; Marshall of England
for the tyme beyng.
            Also when battaile is ioyned in a writte
of ryght or in appeale, that shalbe de
                  •
               ayned
before the Constable &amp; Marshall; how be it

the Iusticers must see the battayle done because
y• they be properly Iudges thereof, &amp;
not the Constable nor the Marshall.
            And the Constables haue manye other
authorityes as wel by the common law, as
by statutes made, y• which you may see there
            Anno 7. Ed. 4. It is sayd the gardiners
of the peace at the common lawe may inquire
of congregations, &amp; vnlawfull assemblyes,
and of disseyson with force, but not of
entre with force. But now by the statute
yf anye entre with force, or do disseason
with force, or entre peaceablye, and kept
passession with force; the Iustices of peace
may make restitution to the party and put
hym in possessiō by theyr writ directed to the
Shiriffe, Constables in the townes where
they beare office may arest men y• go or ride
armed in fayres, or markettes, by day or
by night and take their armour as forfait to
the kinge, imprison them at the Kings pleasure.
An. 2. Ed. 3. at Northampton.
            The Kinges purueyours ought to make
theyr purueyaunce for the Kinges house,
by the Constable, and 4 honest men of the
townes, where such purueiaunce shall bee
made without threatning. And in presence
of y• Cōstable, tayles shall be made &amp; sealed

with the seales of the takers, betweene the
sayd takers &amp; the partyes of whō the goods
be taken, And if any taker make his prise otherwyse:
it shalbe done with him as with a
theefe. An. 12 Ed. 
                  •
                cap. 
                  •
               ,
            Constables of townes must arrest such
as passe by night, of whom suspicion is had,
and deliuer them to the Shiriffe, there to
remayne in ward vntill they bee duely deliuered.
Also they must arrest such as be called
robberdes men. wasters, and draw la
                  •
               
               ches
(if suspicion he had of any such) be it by
night or day, &amp; deliuer them to the Shiriffe
vntil the comming of the Iusticers of Iaile
deliuery. 5 E. 3. cap. 13.
            It is ordayned that none shall take for
threshing a quarter of wheat or corne aboue
2.d. ob. &amp; for a quarter of Barley, Beanes,
Peas &amp; O
                  •
               es. 1, d. ob. if so much haue ben vsed
to bee geuen, and in the countrey where
they vse to reape by the sheffe, and thresh by
the bushell, they shall take no more or otherwyse.
And that such labourers and other
seruauntes shall make an oth two tymes in
the yere before Lordes, Stewardes, Bayliffes
and Constables of euery towne, to do
&amp; keepe this ordinaunce, &amp; that none of thē
shal go out of ye town wher they dwelled in

winter for to serue in sommer (if hee can
haue seruice in the same Towne) sauyng to
the folke of the countyes of Stafford, Darby,
Lancaster, Crauen, and the marches of
wales, theyr free liberty to labour in other
countryes in the tyme of August. And
they that refuse to make such othe, or to perfourme
the thing that they haue sworne &amp;
taken vppon them shalbe put in the stockes,
by the sayd Stewardes, Bayliffes, Cōstables
of townes by the space of three dayes,
or more, and shalbe sent after to the nexte
Iayle, &amp; there to remayne vntil they wil be
ordered, and yt there bee Stockes in euerye
towne for the same intente. And the Stewards,
bailifs, &amp; Constables shal make oth
before the iusticers assigned to enquire diligently
of al thē that offēd against this ordinaunce
&amp; to certify their names before the
same Iustices when they shal come into the
coūtry, to kepe their sessiōs, vpō which certificate
made, the same Iustices shall cause
them to be attached by their bodyes to appeare
before the same Iustices to answere
vnto such contempts; so that if they bee attaynted:
they shall make fine and raunsome
and further to be commaunded to prison vntill
they haue found surety to serue in maner

aboue sayde. And the Iustices at euerye
tyme that they shall come into the countrye
shall inquire of Stewardes, Bayliffes and
Constables, whether they haue made good
and lawfull certificate, or haue concealed
ought for any gyfte, procurement, or affinity,
&amp; shall punish them by fine and raunsome
if they be found guilty. 25. Ed. 3. Capit. 2.
and 8.
            Constables of townes whereas faytours
or vagabondes resort, haue power to examine
them diligently, &amp; cōpel them to finde
surety of their good behauiour, by sufficient
may
                  •
               pernours dist
                  •
               einable in case that
any default bee found in such feytures and
vagabondes. And if they can finde no such
surety: then to be sent vnto the next Iayle,
there to remayne vnto the comming of the
Iustices of Iayles deliuery, which haue
authority to do with such faytors and vagabondes
as they shall thinke best to bee done
by the law. Anno 1. Ri. 2. cap. 5.
            Constables of townes may arrest any
Seruant labourer comming to the Towne
from any place vagarant, vnlesse hee haue
a letter contayning the cause of hys goynge
&amp; the time of his returne, vnder the kinges

seale that thereto shalbe assigned &amp; delyuered
to the custody of some honest man of the
hundred, Wapentake, City, or Boroughe,
according to the discretion of the Iustices
of peace. And y• Constables may put hym
in stocks, &amp; keepe him vntill he haue found
surety to returne to his seruice, or to serue
in the towne from whence he came vntil he
haue a letter to departe vppon cause reasonable.
An. 12. Ri. secundi. cap. 3.
            Constables haue power to arrest Sernaūts,
&amp; labourers that beare about them
Hanger, Dagger, or knife, and to sease the
sayd weapōs as forfayt &amp; them to keepe vntill
the sessions of the Iustices of peace before
whom they shall present such weapons
with the names of them yt bare them, except
that they trauell in the coūtrey in their masters
message 14. Ri. 2. cap. 6.
            Shiriffs and other the kyngs mynisters
may take the power of the countrey to represse
assemblies and royots in outragions
number, &amp; to commit them to pryson. An.
17. Ri. 2. cap. 8. It seemeth by these words
(the Kinges mynisters) that Constables of
townes, haue power to do so by thys act aswell
as the shiriffes.
            Constables may at rest seruaūtes labourers,

and imprison them by the space of sixe
dayes, which vse not Bowes, and arrowes
vpon So
                  •
               dayes &amp; such other festiual daies,
which will not leaue vtterly all playing at
the Ba
                  ••
                aswell with hand as with Foote,
and other games called coyts, dice, casting
of the stones, ke
                  •
               les, &amp; all other like importunate
games .xi. Hen. 4. cap. 4.
            Constables and all the kings liege people
that are able to trauaile wtin the county
must be assisting, &amp; aydoing to the Iusticers
of peace, and the Shiriffe to represse great riots,
and vnlawfull assembles vpon payne
of imprysonment, and to make fine &amp; raunsome.
Anno secundo. Hen. 5. cap 8.
            Constables shall be made in euery parte
of y• marches of Wales &amp; market townes
to inquire, searche and arrest such persons
that cary victayle, or armour to any parte
of Wales, wtout the kinges licence whych
Constables shall haue the 6. part of the forfayte
for their trauayle .4. H. 4. cap. 16.
            Constables of port townes (where souldiours
that haue bene retayned in Wages
to serue in warre beyond Sea or vpō the
Sea, &amp; depart from their Captaynes, and
turne backe &amp; arryue in any porte of Englend
wtout licence of their Captayne vnder

hys seale, may arrest such souldiers &amp; keepe
them vntil inquiry be made of them: and if
it may be prooued by inquiry before Iustycers
of the peace, and prooues yt they haue
mustred of recorde, &amp; departed from theyr
captaine (as before is sayd) without licēce:
then they to be punished as felons. Anno. 18
Hen. 6. cap. 19.
            The Constables, Tythingmen, &amp; chiefe
pledges of euery towne, must assist &amp; ayde
the owners &amp; sellers of any goods (where
the kings purueiou
                  •
               s will make their purueyaunce,
or bargayne of any goods to the
value of .x
                  •
               .s. or vnder) of any person and
will not pay prest paimēt in hand: in which
case it shall be lawfull for euery one of the
Kings lieges: to retayne them, and to resist
such purueyours and not to suffer them
to make any such purueyaunce. And if the
Constable, tythingman, or chiefe pledge be
required to ayde and assist any Man in making
such resistaunce, and hee refuse it, bee
shall pay to the party grieued the value of
the thinge so taken, by action of debt, wyth
the damages to the double. An. 20. Hen. 6.
capitulo. 14.
            Constables may arrest purueyors or buiers
for any Lorde or other person (excepte

purueyors for the King &amp; Queene) whych
take any vitayle or cariage against the wyll
of the owners, &amp; to cōmit them to the next
prison of the kings there to remayne wtout
bayle or maynprise vntill they haue deliuered
al the sayd victayles or cariages, and other
thinges so takē. And if the Constables
do otherwise when they be required: they
shall forfayte twenty pound. The moyty to
be to the party from whom the goods were
taken, to bee recouered by Action of debt,
wherein the defendant shall not wage hys
lawe. An. 23. Hen. 6. cap. 13.
            Clothiers shall pay to carders, spinners
and other Labourers lawefull Money for
their wages, &amp; carders, fullers, and other
labourers shall doe the or duety vpon paine
of double damages. And the Constables
of the hundred or Constable may heare and
determyne the complaintes of e
                  •
               ery such
clothier, and labou
                  •
               er, as well for no payment
of the sayd wages of labourers, as of
the sayde forfaytures and damages by due
examination of the parties in that behalfe,
and further for none payment of the sayde
duties, forfaytures and damages, to cōmit
the trespassor to the next Iayle in the same
county, vntill the sayd duties, forfaitures, &amp;

damages, to commit the trespasso
                  •
               res to
the next Iayle in the same county, vntil the
sayd duties forfaytures, and damages bee
duely payed 
                  •
               ato the sayd labourers or clothiers.
4. Ed. 4. cap. 1.
            Euery highe Constable or pety Constable
shall take or cause to bee taken all va
               
                  •
               abounds,
idle people and suspect persons
liuing suspiciously &amp; set them in the stockes
and there to remayne by one day, and one
night, and to haue none other sustenaunce
but bread and water, and then to auoyd the
towne where they were taken, into such
place or hundred where they were borne, or
where they last dwelled by the space of .iij.
yeares. And if eftsoones they bee taken in
such default, then they to be set lykewise in
the stocks by three dayes and three nightees
wyth like dyet .xix. Hen. 7. cap. 12.
            Constables and other head officers, and
euery of them findinge, or knowinge any
person vsing or exercisinge any vnlawfull
games, as Tenis play, bowles, clashe, and
all other vnlawefull games prohibited by
many Statutes, shall haue full power to
commit euery such offendour to ward there
to remayne without bayle, or Maynepryse,
till such tyme hie or they so offendinge bee

bound by obligation to the Kynges vse, in
such sūme as by the discretion of the same
officer shalbe thought reasonable that thei
from thence forth shall not vse any vnlawfull
games. 6. Hen. 8. cap. 2.
            For wages for water men and for theyr
barges or boates, or for a Barge from Lō
               don
to Graues end .iij.s. or els euery person
and his male .ij.d. From London to
Eryth, Gr
                  ••
               nwhich, Grastorock, or Parfler
.xij.d. or 
                  •
               ls for euery person, and hys
fardle. 1.d. so it passe not .vij.d. From London
to Wulwich .xiij.d. for a boate or whery
that is y• tide boate, or els for euery person.
ob. From London to Greenwhich .iij.
d. or els, 
                  〈◊〉
               . for euery person and hys fardle.
From London bridge, Sainct Mary
Oueries, or Paules wharfe, to Westminster,
iij d. or els euery person. ob. From
the Blacke Friers, Bridewell, &amp; the Temple,
to Westminster, or Lambeth .ij.d.
with their males or els euery person .ob. so
that it amount to .ij.d. From Westminster
to Lambeth or stayngate. ob. for a boate.
From London to Mortlake .xij.d. or els euery
person .ij.d. with hys male. And from
those places about named, to London for
a boate or barge like sūmes to be paid. And

these articles to bee kept vpon paine to forfait
treble the fare; and Bailiffes Constables
and other the Kinges officers next adioyning
to the series vpon complaynt to thē
made or to any of them, by them that be grieued
in that behalfe, may arrest them, and cō
               mit
them to warde for theyr misdemeanour
&amp; to make fine for the same .vi. H. viii.ca.vi
                  •
               .
            By the statute made. An. xxii. Hen. viii.
how impotente persons shall bee ordered to
begge and haue their liuing. It is ordained
that if any impotente Person auctorysed to
begge do beg in any other place then within
the limits to him assigned: then the constables
and all other the kings officers shall
by their discretion punish all such Persons
by imprisonment in the stockes by the space
of two dayes and ii. Nyghts, geuyng them
but onely Breade and Water. And after
that to cause euery such person to be sworde
to returne agayne wythout delaye, to the
hundreth, R
                  •
               pe, City, Borough, Towne parish
or franchise wherein they be auctorysed
to beg in.
            And if any impotente Person bee vagarant,
and goe a begging &amp; ha
                  •
               e no such, letter
vnder seale as is specified by this statute
then the Constables and all other inhabytauntes

wythin such Cownes or parish shal
cause euery such Begger to bee taken and
broughte to the next Iusticer of peace or
high constable of the hundred. And thereuppon
the sayd Iusticers of peace or hygh
constable shal, commaund the said Cōstables
and inhabitantes of the Towne or Parish,
which shall bryng before hym any such begger
that they shall s
                  •
               ryp hym naked from
the middle vpward, and cause him to be whipped
wythin the Towne or where he was taken
or where the same iusticers of peace or
hygh Constable shall appoynte. And if
not: then to commaund such begger to bee
set in the stockes in the same towne or parysh
where he was takē by the space of thre daies
and three Nyghtes, to haue onely Breade
and Water and thereuppon the sayd Iusticers
or hygh Constable shall limit a place
to the same Begger to begge in. And to
giue hym a Letter vnder seale in fourme
before limytted &amp; to sweare hym to repaire
thyther immediatly after his punishment executed.
            And all other Persons beeing whole &amp;
mighty in Body that doe begge, the Constable
of the hundred Rape, or Wapentakē
wherein such Persons shall bee taken, and

               
                  •
               he Iusticers of peace or high Constable
before whom they shalbe brought by theyr
discretion shall cause them to be brought to
such places as they thinke conuenient, and
there to bee whipped naked through the
towne or market, and then to bee sworne
to returne to the place where he was borne
or where he last dwelled by the space of 3.
yeres, and to haue a letter vnder the seale
witnessing that he hath bene punished.
            Also all persons that a biure to sainctuary
within 
                  •
               his realme shalbe cōueyed thervnto
by the Constables of euerye towneship
that is from Towne to Towne till that
hee come vnto that same Sainctuary wher
vnto he is abiured in lyke maner &amp; fourme
as persons that had abiured this 
                  •
               ealme
should haue bene conueied to the next port
of the sea from that place where they be abiured
vnto the same pore by course of the cō
               mon
law before the making of this Statute
22 H. 8. cap. 13.
            Euery farmer or owner of landes, tenemente
or hereditamentes, whereof y• yerely
value or rent amounteth to fiue poundes
                  •
               
which manureth, the same shall pay to euery
person, which by his diligence and laboure
at hys owne costes taketh any old
                  •
               
               
Crows, Rookes or Choughs vpon the same
Landes Tenements, or hereditamentes of
the yerely value aforesayd .ii. pence for euery
xli. old Crows, Rookes, or Choughes and
a penye for 
                  〈◊〉
               , and a halfe peny for .iii. olde
Crowes, Rookes, or Choughes. And any
Farmer or owner refuse to pay the sayde
money accordyng as is aforesayd, then vpon
a complaynt and proofe made thereof to any
Iusticer of peace, or high Constable the
same Iusticer, or byghe Constable shall
cause the samemoney to be leuied by distresse
of the goods and cattels of euery such Farmer
or occupyer of the same lands and tenements.
Anno xiiii Henrici .vii
                  •
               . cap. x.
            Where it is ordayned by a Statute
made in the vii. yeare of Richard the Second
.cap ix. that he whych espyeth and proueth
defaultes in any Clothes, put to saie
contrary to the assise thereof, ordayned touchyng
Clothes and contrary to the sayd statutes
should haue the thyrde parte of euery
such cloth beeing defectiue for hys Labour
by the deliuery of the Shiriffes if they
bee present or els of the Lordes of Fayres
and Markets or of Stewards Bayliffes or
Constables of townes, where such defectiue

clothes shalbe found by Indēture betwene
them to be made the which shalbe deliuered
euery yere in the escheker at the feast of S.
Michaell by them that shal make such deliuery,
to the intēt to charge the Annagours
and toilours, by whom such manner of defaultes
ought to be searched and amended.
An. 7. Ri. 2. cap. 9.
            If any person, shippe, marchaundise of
Staple, be in place suspect adioyning to the
Costes of the Water, and maketh no Indentures
thereof betweene him &amp; the maior
or Constable of the towne, they shalbe forfayte,
and the king shal haue the moytye.
And it is lawful for euery person to searche
in these causes. An. 
                  •
                4. Hen. 6 cap. 5.
            It is ordayned that a Horseman shall
pay for passage at Douer 3. s. and a footeman
6. d.. And the Constable of Douer to
punish them that do contrarye at the suite
of the party that will complayne and shall
do him right in that behalfe. Anno. 4. Ed.
3 cap. viii.
         
         
            The office of Coroners.
            
               
FOr to declare playnely the Offyce of a
Coroner, it appeareth by the Statute
of Magna carta in the xv. capi. that no
Coroner ought to holde any pleas of ye Corone.
But Breton declareth ye offyce of a
Coroner in forme following.
            First that in euery county Coroners shall
be the principall conseruators of the peace
to beare record of al the pleas of the crown
of abiurations, vtlagaries, &amp; such like, and
the Coroners shall make an othe before the
Shiriffes in the full county, that they shall
make their inquests, inrollementes, and all
that to the coroners office apertaineth, lawfully
or wythout askinge allowance. And
if any felony chaunce, or treasure be found
or any Woman ra
                  •
               yshed, or Pryson broke,
or any man wounded nighe vnto death, the
coroner so soone as hee shall knowe thereof
shal send to the Shiriffes and Bayliffs of ye
places where such aduenture shall happen
to cause to come before hym, at a certayne
day at the place where such chaunce befell,
foure of the nexte towneships, and other if
neede be by whom hee shall inquire the verity
&amp; shall compel the townships to sweare
vpon the Saints to shew the truth of those
articles yt he shal demaunde of them. Then

shall the Coroner and the Iurours viewe
the body, the Woundes, and the stroakes,
and immedyately after such view had, the
Body shall bee buryed, And if the Coroner
finde the body buried before the commyng
hee shall recorde the same: neuerthelesse
he shall not omit to digge vp the Body and
make it to be viewed openly of the Townes.
And those Iurours which haue bene sommoned
and come not to the inquyries of coroners
shall bee amerced at the commyng
of the Iusticers at the first assises in those
counties so that such defaultes be entred in
Coroners rolle: so that the Coroner shall
haue no power to amerce no man for any default.
And when the inquest is sworne, the
Coroner muste inquyre if the person were
slayne by felony were done within a House
or without, and all the circumstaunce. And
after it shall be inquyred who were present
at that deede and who be culpable of the said
force, commaundement, consent or receipte
of such felonies wittyngly. And if the Coroner
haue any suspection of the first inqueste
for concealemēt of the truth or if it bee needeful
to inquyre better by other, then shal hee
inquyre diuers times &amp; al such as therof shal

hap to be indited the shiriffe shal take in all
the hast if they may be found, and if not the
Coroner shall inquire who they be and who
hath withdrawen thēselues for that occasiō
and the Shiriffe shal forthwith cause their
lands to be seased, &amp; afterwardes, all their
goods, and cause them to be praised by lawfull
inquest and the goodes with the prises
shalbe inrolled in the Coroners rolle and
shal bee deliuered to the township for to bee
answereable therfore vnto the K. in case the
party so indited flee, &amp; wil not stād to right.
            And after they shall inquire if hee that is
indyted did euer fynde surety to keepe the
kings peace &amp; the names of hys may
                  •
               pernours,
which he shall enter into his rolle.
            And if the playntiffe will sue apeale within
the yere and the day, then shall hee fynd
two sufficient pledges to the Shiriffe of ye
county distreinable within the same to sue
his appeale according to the lawe of ye land.
And thē shal the Coroner cause the appeale
to be entered, with the names of the pledges
and after it shalbe commaunded vnto
the sergeant of the county where such felony
is done which as mee seemeth, is the
Shiriffe or his bayliffe errant that he hath
the bodye at the next county. And if the

Sergeant returne at the second county that
he cannot fynd them, then shall it be awarded
that the pryncipall beyng appealed of
the deede shal be solempnely called to stād to
right touching the same felony and so shalbe
called from coūty to county vntil they come
or bee outlawed, and if the plaintiffe make
default at any countie then shall the exigent
passe vntill the comming of the Iusticers
of the Kynges benche or the Iusticers
in Eire in the county. And if the pryncipall
be outlawed the exigents shall goe forth immediatly
agaynst accessaries. And when
they shall be outlawed wythdrawen or suspected
                  •
               
the Coroner shall inquyre at whose
finding such a fugitiue hath bene and accordyng
vnto the verdit hee shall inrolle it and
then inquyre of the Landes and goods of y•
fugitiue. And if they appeare before outlawry
they shalbe repleuiable, aud if the felony
were done out of a House: the Coroner shall
inquyre who found the body fyrst and he shal
be taken and let go vnder sureties. And that
no Iurour be remoued by chalenge of any
party. Neyther shall any Coroner take any
thinge by him selfe or by other, nor suffer
to bee taken by his Clarke for doing his
office, And if it be found that any is deade by

misaduenture then shall it bee inquired
what misaduenture as if it be found that he
fell from a Mill, it shalbe inquired what
thinges were then mouing there, and how
much they bee worth, and so if he fell out of
a carte, &amp; if one fall out of a shippe nothing
shalbe iudged the cause of his death but the
shippe and the thinges that mooue therin, &amp;
not the marchaundise lying therin.
            And the Coroners ought to receiue the
confession of felons made by proouers in
in presence of y• shiriffe who shal be his controller
in all his office, and such confession
he shall cause to bee inrolled; and when any
person fleeth to a Church so sone as the Coroner
shall haue knowledge therof he shal
send to the Bailiffe of the place, that he shal
cause to come before hym by a certaine day
the neighbours, &amp; foure of the next townships
adioyning to the Church, and in their
presence shall receiue the confession of the

                  •
               elon. And if the fugityue pray to abiure the
realme: the Coroner shal do that the which
to his office belongeth.
            Also he shall inquire of rape and all the
circumstaunce, the appeales, whereof
with all other Appeals of robbery, felony
and such like hee shall cause to bee entred

in his rolle.
            And they shall inquyre of treasure foundē
               
                  •
               
of wreckes of the Sea and of Sturgions &amp;
of Whales taken, and who were takers,
whose names they shall inroll and let them
go by mainpryse. And such thynges as shall
happen to be founden they shal safely keepe
to the kyngs vse. And the Shiriffs &amp; Bayliffes
shal be alwayes attendant vpon them,
and at theyr commaundements.
            It is ordayned that throughout all the
Counties of England there be chosen sufficient
Coroners of the moste sage and lawfull
Knyghtes that may best to the same office
intende whych lawfullye shall attache
and present peales of Corone as well of appeales
as of thynges to the same Office belongyng.
And that no Coroner demaunde
or take any thynge for doyng his office, vppon
paine of a griuous forfaiture to the king
i. West .cap. xii. But now by the Stat
                  •
               te
made. Anno. i. Hen .viii. cap. i. the Coroner
shall haue xiii .s.iiii.d. of the goodes of the
murderer and if the murder bee committed
in the day time and the murderer escape the
coroner shall haue xiii .s.iiii.d. for the escape
vpon the towneship, also it appeareth by 
                  •
               
Statute made in the xiii. yere of E. the fyrste

whych is called the statute of Excerer, vnder
what order inquisition shal be made of
the defaults of Coroners bee they alyue, or
dead; where he shall see the charge that shal
be geeuen to the inquests y• shal be charged
to inquire of Coroners, in whych charge it
appeareth further what the Coroner ought
to do by his office; which charge heere insueth.
            
               ¶The forme of the charge to inquire of
the defaults of the Coroners according
to the statute of Exceter.
               FIrst they shall inquire if the Coroner,
go in proper person to doe his offyce or
not, whereby it appeareth that he cannot
make a deputy.
               2. Also if hee haue sente any other to doe
his offyce what hee was, and howe often &amp;
about what aduentures.
               3. Also if hee came at euery tyme of hys
owne good wyll without delay, or that hee
or his Clarke haue taken any thing for the
more speedy executing of their office. 
               4. Also
if hee tary or delay to the intent to haue
any rewarde after yt hee hath knowledge of
the truth, &amp; after y• he is sent vnto, how oftē,
and in what place, and vnder what maner.
               5. Also if the Goods of Felons taken by

him be deliuered to the townes to keepe by
a lawfull inquest as they ought to be &amp; inrolled
in his recorde or not.
               6. Also if the Coroner take any thing of
any person for to take a false inquest for to
destroy the right of any or to prayse y• goods
for lesse then they be worthe.
               7. Also if he enter any thing in hys rolles
otherwise than it was geuen by the inquest
and what thing he or his clerke tooke therefore
&amp; how often, and for what thinge hee,
or his Clerk tooke such things. 
               8
                     •
                   Also if he
or his Clerke tooke of the goods that were
prysed, and prysed them at lesse, then they
entred them in their rolles. 
               9. Also if y• prises
were not assessed by the inquest.
               10. Also if y• township were falsely charged
and of what thing. 
               11. Also if any appeales
were falsely inrolles or imbeaseled out of ye
rolles after that they were entered. 
               12. Also
if be refuse to take any playnt of appeales
for pouerty, hate or other lyke cause, &amp;
what hee tooke for that occasion &amp; of whom
and how much. 
               13. Also if hee or his Clerk
haue taken ought of the goods of the party
that is dead vpon whose body he tooke view
what thinge it was and howe ofter hee so
did. 
               14. Also if hee haue entered all the attachments

belonginge to hys offyce in due
maner, or if he haue made any attachment
for to grieue any person or to haue of hys
owne, and enter it into his rolle. 
               15. Also if
hee haue not done his offyce at all tymes at
hys owne costes, wythout takynge oughte
therefore. 
               16. Also if hee haue concealed
ought in any Coūty or procured to be murdred
to the grieuaunce of any person and if
he so did than to inquire how often and for
what rewarde, and for whom, and in what
case he so old. 
               17. Also all the attachments,
hanging, and lawfully receiuing be pursued
by him as he ought to doe for the kynge
or for the party, or cause to be pursued.
               18. Also if the goods of such as haue fled the
townes where they dwell for suspection of
felony, were attached by hym, and praysed
by inquest, and inrolled accordinge therevnto
and deliuered vnto the townes where
those goods were found to keepe safely vntill
the comming of the Iusticers in Eire.
               19. Also if he suffer appeals or other plaints
to hym made to be cōueyed away imbeaseled,
or caried out of the roiles, and if he take
ought for such falshed, of whom, how much,
and how many tymes.
               
                  
20. And if there were any treasure found in
the tyme of the sayd Coroner in what, and
what maner of treasure, and howe much,
and in whose handes it resteth, &amp; by whose
deliueraunce.
            
            This is the whole charge that Iustices in
Eire must geue for inquiry of Coroners, &amp;
of their defaults. Furthermore Iusticers
in Eire may impanell other Inquestes of
24. persons of the body of the county to inquire
of the cōcealement of y• first inquests,
whych dyd inquire of the defaultes of the
Coroners.
            When Coroners haue any knowledge
from the Kings Bayliffes, or other honest
men of the countrey for to go vnto such as
be slayne, or sodenly deade, or wounded, or
breakers of houses, or to any
                  •
                place where
treasure is sayd to be founde they must goe
forthwith, &amp; commaund foure, fiue, or sixe,
of the next Towneships, that they be afore
them at such a day &amp; place, and when they
shall come, thē the Coroner must make inquiry
thereof in forme following.
            First if the person were slayne in house,
or in the field, in bed or at the Tauerne. &amp;c.
and who be guilty thereof, eyther of y• déede
or cōsent
                  •
                &amp;c. And if any be in y• court which

were there, so y• they can speake or haue any
discretion, and they that be found guilty
by inquest shall be taken and delyuered to y•
Shyriffe. And such as were present, and be
not guilty shall be attached vntill the comming
of the Iusticers &amp; their names shall
be written in the Coroners Rolle.
            If any be sodaynely flayne in fields or in
Woodes, it is first to bee seene whether he
were slayne there or not, and if he were not
slayne there, then as neere as they can they
shall followe the steps of hym that brought
the body thither with horse or carte, if it be
possible in case the murderer be knowen: &amp;
if he be a straūger; then shall they inquyre
where he was lodged the night before: and
touching such as shalbe founde
                  •
                guilty the
Coroner shal go immediately to their houses
and inquire what goods &amp; Landes they
haue and how much they bee worthe by the
yere. But by the statute of King Rychard
the third it is ordayned that the lands and
goods of such persons shall not bee seased
vntill they bee attaynted or otherwyse conuict
by course of the law. And these things
thus being inquired: the bodyes shall bee
buryed incontinent.
            Moreouer they must inquire of such as

bee drowned or deade sodaynely, and whether
they were drowned, strāgled, or slaine,
and they must enquire who were the fynders,
and they may bee attached, also they
must view the length, breadth, and deepnes
of all woundes, &amp; must inquyre wyth what
weapons and in what place of the body: and
if the wound be mortall: the offendour shal
bee kept vntill it bee knowen whether the
party may be whole. And if the wound be
great then hee shalbe let goe vnder foure,
or sixe pleadges, &amp; if it be but little then. 2.
pleadges shall suffyce. Also they must inquire
of horses, Cartes, and other thynges
whereby any was slayne, that they may be
praysed, and deliuered. 
                  〈◊〉
                .s.
            Also they shall inquire of wrecks of the
Sea, and if any lay hand vpon it, he shal be
attached by good pleadges, and the wreck
shall bee prysed and delyuered to the nexte
towneships. Further more Hue, and Cry
shall bee leuyed vppon all Manslaughters,
Burglaries, as when any is slaine or in perill
of death if it may be. And all shall followe
such hue and cry if they bee able, and
they that doe not, shall bee attached to appeare
before the Iusticers. &amp;c.
            Also if any person flee vnto the Church

or other halowed place, for Murder, Felony
or such lyke offence, the Coroner vppon
knowledge thereof shall come thyther and
take hys confession; and if hee will abiure
the Realme, the Coroner shall receiue hys
abiuration, which he shall say in this forme.
            
               The fourme of abiuration.
               HEare you this Syr Coroner, that I
A. B. am a Theefe of one horse or other
like thing, or a mans
                     •
                  ear of one
man or mo, and a felon of our Soueraigne
Lord kynge Henry the viij. And for asmuch
as I haue committed many eu'll deedes,
and felonyes in thys Realme, I heere abiure
hys Lande for euer, and shall make as
much hast as I cā to yt Ha
                     •
                  en of. O. which
you haue assygned mee and I shall not depart
out of the high way, &amp; if I do: I will y•
I be taken as theefe and felon of the king.
Aud further I shall diligētly seeke my passage
at the place aboue lymitted, &amp; I shall
not abyde there any longer then one Eb, &amp;
one Floud if I may haue passage. And if I
can haue no Passage in so much space, I
shall goe euery day into the Sea, vp to my

                     〈◊〉
                  , and assay if I can get ouer. And if
I cannot so do wythin xl. dayes continuing

I shall yeeld my 
                     •
                  elfe againe to the Church
as the kinges theefe and felon. So helpe me
God and holydome.
               Neuertheles it seemeth that when any
person shal abiure him, it behoneth to shew
the place the day and yere, and in what coū
                  ty
he did the felony or murder; which confession
shalbe as an inditement in effect; notwithstandyng
if hee do it not, but onely as
before is expressed, it is good inough, because
he is attayned before by hys abiuration.
How beit, this maner of abiuration
is put out of the statute of Henry the eight
made the xii yere of his raygne, whereby it
is ordayned that such as will abiure, shall
make their abiuration from all their liberty
vnto some sanctuary within this realme,
there to remayne ouryng their lyues, and
shalbe burned in the ryght hand with thys
letter A. And if such person afterward bee
taken out of Sanctuary, hee shalbe ordered
in lyke maner as one that had bene abiured
the Realme before the said statute. And the
same person y• so taketh ye church shal make
hys abiuration, and shall take hys passage
from thence at such a day and tyme as the
Coroner shall appoynt, and shalbe marked
vppon the braune of his thumb on the right

hand with a burning Iron, and shalbe 
                     •••
                  
                  ueyed
to the Sainctuary, wherunto he is
abiured by the Maiors, Bayliffes and Constables,
in such fashion as they haue bene
which heretofore had abiured the realme.
               And if any felō refuse to abiure before the
Coroner he shalbe taken out of the sanctuary
and shall loose the priuiledge thereof, &amp;
that is by the Statute. 22. H. 8. cap 2.
               Also it is ordayned that none shall be chosen
Coroner if he haue not lande sufficient
within the same county for to answere all
persons. An 4. Ed. 3. cap. 2.
               And it is further ordayned that all Coroners
shall bee chosen in the full County, by
the commons of the said county of the most
conuenient and able persons. Anno. 28. Ed.
3. cap 6.
               The Coroner shall inquire vppon the view
of the body if he were slayne by day, if the
murderer bee taken. And if the murderer
escape the township to bee amerced. And
the Coroner shall inquire of that escape,
when hee inquireth of the death vpon view
of the body. And Coroner shall haue for his
see 13 s.4.d. of the goods of the murderer
               And if hee haue no goodes then to haue
hys fee of such amerciamente as shall bee

set vppon the township for the escape. And
after the murderer found: the Coroner shal
certify his inquisition afore the Iusticers of
the next generall Iayle deliuerye in tha
                     •
                  
same county. And if the Coroner be remisse
to make his inquisition vppon the viewe of
the body, and certify not according as is afore
sayd: thē the Coroner for euery default
to forfayt one hundred. s. An. 3. H. 7. cap. 1.
               It is ordayned that vppon request of the
Coroner, to come and inquire of anye persō
drowned or slayne by misaduenture: the Coroner
shall diligently do his office without
taking any thing therefore vppon payne of
euery Coroner y• wil not indeuour him to
do his office, or that taketh anye thinge for
doing hys office vpon anye person dead by
misaduenture forty shillings. An. 1. Hen. 8.
cap. 7.
               In case of mans death within the vierge
it shalbe commaunded to the Coroner of yt
countrey that hee together with the Coroner
of the kinges house, do make the inquiry
and inroll it. And that which cannot
bee determined before the steward because
the felons bee not attached or for other like
cause: shall remayne at the common lawe

so that the exigentes, vtlagaryes, and presentmentes
therof to be made in Eire by y•
Coroner of the coūtrey, as of other felonies
done out of the vierge. Articles vppon the
Charters cap. 2.
               No Coroner, Shiriffe, nor other officer,
shall take ought for his office, &amp; if be do, he
shall restore twyse so much. West. 1. cap 20
But the statute of H. 7. giueth to the Coroner
a marke for euery murder.
               Also it was sayd by the Iusticers. M 6.
R. 2. that the Coroner hath no power to inquire
of a mans death, but onely vpon view
of the body, and if he do, it is frustrate, and
boyde. And if one Coroner inquire vppon
the view of the body, aud after another Coroner
will come and inquire therof agayne
the second inquiry is boyde, for the first inquiry
is onely of recorde.
               If one become a proouer before the Coroner
he shal not afterward be admitted to say
that he did committe the acte by duresse of
imprisonment: for the record of the Coroner
shall esto
                     •
                   him to pleade that.
               If any will sue appeale of robbery of 
                     •
                  arcency,
he must come into the full Countye
within the yere and the day after the felony
done, and must finde two pledges for to

follow hys suite, and the Coroner shal entre
hys impa
                     •
                  ell immediately in his roll, &amp; the
names of the pleadges. And then shall it be
commaunded to the Bayliffes of the place,
where &amp;c. that he haue the body at the next
county. And if hee returne at the secōd coū
                  ty
non est inuentus, then shall the appeale
be called from county to county, vntill he be
outlawed; and if the playntife make default
at any coūty, then shal the exigent cease vntill
the Eire of the Iusticers in the same
county, and the playntife shall loose his action
after appearaunce for euer; whereby it
appeareth that after the yere and day a man
shall not haue appeale of felony. And to this
poynt agreeth Breton in his first booke.
               The Coroner must recorde hys view, abiuration,
appeals, and accusatiōs of theeues
made before hym, and so must hee do of all
things that belōg vnto his office to be done,
and the nonsuites of plaintifes in appea
                     •
                  es
hee must recorde, with al things done in the
County which belong vnto his office.
               Also yee shall note that appeales shall be
made in the court of any Lord y• hath fraunchise
of infangtheefe, in presence of the Coroner.
&amp;c.
               A presentment was sent into the Kinges

bench by a Coroner comprysing how a c
                     •
                  
                  tayne
person taken for felony was conueied
vnto the Church by certaine Fryers. &amp;c.
And because the Coroner had no power to
take such an inditement a writ was directed
to the same Coroner to certify whether hee
had any other presentment or not. An. 27. E.
3. libro assisarum.
               An aduenture of the death of a man was
presented before the Iustices in Eire and because
the same was not found, in the Coroners:
rolle: the Coroner was awarded to
prison. The Coroners fee in Eire is to haue
i.d. of euery venue when they shall come.
               Note that a presentmēt made before Iusticers
in Eire of a thing which is contrary
to that that is entred in the Coroners rolle
shalbe taken vayd, &amp; the Coroners roll shall
be taken for the record.
               The Coroner shall inquire of the death
of men slayne or drowned in the armes or
creekes of the Sea, where they land maye
bee seene of eyther syde.
               But now by the Statute made. An. 13.
R. 2. cap. 5. and confyrmed. An, 2. He. 4 cap
11. the Admiral hath no iurisdictiō but onely
vppon the high sea. Whereby it appeareth
that the Coroner hath iurisdiction

there to inquyre of mens death.
               A Coroner may take an appeale of felony
made by an approuer in any Countye of
England and so may he do of an abiuration
in case that he confesse the felony to bee done
in any other county. And the Coroner may
abiure him as well vppon that as if the felony
had bene done within the same County.
But he cannot take any appeale of robbery
or felony, vnlesse it bee within the same
county where the robbery or felonye was
committed, and where he is Coroner; for by
the confession or appeachment he is attainted,
and so he is not in the other case.
               One that becommeth a prouer, before
Iusticers, shall not haue a Coroner, excepte
he will confesse the felony before them, and
pray a Coroner. An. xxvi. Ed. iii.
               And if one become a proouer, and appeale
other of diuers felonies done in other
counties, in this case the Coroner shall not
make processe thereuppon into any forrayne
County, but hee shal enter it in hys rolle,
and shall send the same presentment before
the Iusticers of Iayle deliuery and the Iusticers
of Iaile deliuery shall award proces
to the Shiriffe of the forraine county for, to
take him that is so appealed.
               
                  
Thus 
                     •
                  e must vnderstand, that if any Shiriffes,
Bayliffes, Escheators, Constables,
or Coroners take ought for doing their offices
otherwyse then to them is limitted by
the statutes before declared: that then such
taking is extortion; which is punishable at
the kings pleasure, as appeareth before, &amp;c.
in the statute made 1. H. 4. cap. 11. Wherby
it appeareth, that Shiriffes, and other
ministers; Bailifs &amp; their ministers; Esche
a
                     •
                  ors and their ministers; Coroners and
their ministers, are bound to serue all preceptes
to them directed from the Iustices
of peace, without taking ought of
                     •
                   any party
And if a precept bee directed to the Shiriffe
or any other the kinges officer, to compel any
to appeare before the Iustices, to fynde
surety of peace, if the party agaynst whom
any such precepte is dyrected bee ready to
come before the said Iusticers to find surety
of peace they shall take nothing of him.
               And in like maner must they serue all processes
that come to them, directed out of the
Kinges bench, the cōmon place, the Escheker,
or the Chaūcery, without taking ought
therfore, but onely the fees expressed in the
statutes before written. And if they take
any other fees it is playne extortion.
            
         
         
            
            A briefe declaration concerning the
extortions of Ordinaries; Parsons,
Vicars and Curats.
            AS concerning Ordinaries, yee shall
vnderstand that it is ordayned by a
statute made in the xxi. yere of king
Henry y• eyght, that no Ordinary shal take
any thinge for the probate of the testament
of such a person, whose goods amounte not
aboue the sūme of a hundreth shi
                  •
               lings, except
to the scribe .vj.d. onely. And of goods
aboue the value of a C.s. vnto .xi. pounde,
iij.s.vj.d: And the Scribe to haue .xij.d. of
the summe. And for the probate of a Testament
of goods aboue the value of .xl.l'.v.s:
whereof the Scribe to haue .ij.s.vj.d. or
for euery lyne beinge. 10. Inches in length
one peny. And such summes for Letters of
administration, where such persons die intestate,
&amp; the Testament to bee registered, &amp;
delyuered to the party wythout delay; and
letters of administration to bee graunted
to the wyfe or next of the bloude of the party
deceassed or to bothe: And for the probate
of a Testament, or letter of administration
of goods, vnder the summe of a hundreth .s.
the Ordinary shall take nothing. Moreouer

it is the office of the Ordinary to deface the
seale of the testatour wherewyth the testament
was sealed and to deliuer it agayne
to the party. And if the Ordinary take any
more then afore is limitted, hee shall forfayte
so much as hee taketh, and ten pound
more besides that, whereof the moyty shall
bee to the party greeued.
            If the Ordinary cite any person to appeare
in the Spirituall courte to depose in
any matter there, as a witnesse: that is extortion
aud wronge to the party.
            If any Ordinary; Person, or Uicar take
any mortuary after the death of any person
whych had not goods to the value of .x.
Markes, that is extortion. And lykewise it
is, where they take a mortuary in such places
where it hath not bene accustomed to
pay mortuaries. And euen so it is where
a Person, or Uicar taketh more then .iij.s.
iiij.d. in the name of a mortuary. If y• goods
amoūt aboue .x. markes, and vnder the value
of .xxx.li. for that is extortion.
            Also if hee take more then .vj.s.viij.d. for
a mortuary where the goods bee aboue the
value of .xxx.li. and vnder the summe of .xl.
pound the debts payd, that is extortion.
            And if they take of them whose goods amount

to .xl.li. aboue the debts, payd more
then .x.s. for a mortuary: that is extortion.
            And if they take any mortuary for a woman
maryed, or one that is wythin age, or
for a man that keepeth no house, it is extortion.
And if any mortuary bee taken in
Wales it is extortion, except Bishops that
shall take mortuaries thereof priestes and
Curates, and the Archdeacon of Chester
shall take mortuaryes of Priestes within
the county of Chester.
            And whosoeuer taketh for a Mortuarye
more then hee ought, shall forfayte asmuch
in value as hee taketh, and .rl.s. besides
that
                  •
                the party grieued. Anno. xxi. Henri
                  ••
               .
octaui. capitulo sexto. And thus haue
I thought sufficient to declare vnto
you concerning extortions
in Ordynaries; Parsons,
Uicars, and
Curates.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            ¶Imprynted at London, by
Thomas Marshe.
         
      
   

