
   
      
         
            Satyres: and satyricall epigrams with certaine obseruations at Black-Fryers? By H:F: of Lincolnes-Inne gent
            Fitzgeffrey, Henry.
         
         
            
               1617
            
         
         Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00826
            STC 10945
            ESTC S113885
            99849114
            99849114
            14249
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00826)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14249)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 709:04)
         
         
            
               
                  Satyres: and satyricall epigrams with certaine obseruations at Black-Fryers? By H:F: of Lincolnes-Inne gent
                  Fitzgeffrey, Henry.
               
               [110] p.   
               
                  Printed by Edw[ard]: All-de, for Miles Patrich, and are to be sold at his shop neare S. Dnnstons-Church [sic] in Fleet-street,
                  London :
                  1617.
               
               
                  H:F: = Henry Fitzgeffrey.
                  In three books, each with separate title page; register continuous.
                  Errata on G7r, final printed leaf.
                  Signatures: A-G (-A1, blank?).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Epigrams, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-10
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2008-10
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  
                     SATYRES: AND SATYRICALL EPIGRAM'S: With Certaine Obſeruations at Black-Fryers? By H: F: Of LINCOLNES-INNE Gent:
                  
                     Horat: Serm: Lib. 1.
                     —Nil mî officit vnquam 
                     Ditior hic aut eſt quia Doctior: eſt Locus vnicui
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         ſuus:—
                     It neuer vexeth me a whit
                     That this man hath more welth or wit:
                     Euery one hath where he may ſit.
                  
                  LONDON Printed by Edw: All-de, for Miles Patrich, and are to be ſold at his ſhop neare St. Dnnſtons-Church in Fleet-ſtreet. 1617.
               
               
                  
                  
                  The Author in praiſe of his owne BOOKE.
                  COmmend my Selfe? No! But my Booke I may!
                  And boldly (blameleſſe) 'tis Praiſe-worthy fay.
                  How ſo? The ſenceleſſe Subſtance well may plead
                  My Selfe I was not, when the Booke I made.
               
               
                  
                  Of his deare Friend the Author, H. F.
                  
                  
                     OF what is heere thou'lt not haue any write
                     
                        Prayſes: that willing, would: and iuſtly might,
                  
                  
                     
                        Permit me then! For Ile Praiſe what I ſee
                     
                        Deficient heere (thy name FITZ-IEOFFERY,)
                  
                  
                     Where Engliſh FITZ aright, and I ha' done
                     So rightly art thou called IEOFFERYES-Sonne.
                  
                  
                     Then adde time Age but to thy induſtry,
                     In thee againe will liue Old-IEOFFERY.
                     NATH: GVRLYN.
                  
               
               
                  
                  The Author's Anſwer.
                  
                     OF what is Heere I forbid any Write
                     
                     
                        Praiſes. Why? Nothing Heere can merite it:
                  
                  
                     Yet Ile Permit thee. Thoul't but Praiſe my Name.
                     
                     And that's Deficient. Then Praiſe not for ſhame
                  
                  
                     Where do (FITZ) right: Write, place it to 
                           •
                         minde:
                     Stil rightly muſt (FITZ) IEOFFERYES come behind wrought:
                     
                        French muſt turne Engliſh firſt, (ſtrange wonders)
                     
                        (Olde) be a new Borne: The (Sonne) brought to nought.
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     HORAT: De Arte Poeti.
                  
                     NVnc ſatis eſt dixiſſe, Ego mira poemata pango:
                     Occupet extremum ſcabies!
                  
                  Anglicè ſic
                  
                     NOw 'tis inough to ſpeake,
                     I wondrous Poemes make:
                     Then, Diuell the hindmoſt take.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Satyra prima.
                  
                     LIB: 1.
                     
                        VVHo'd not at venture Write? So many waies
                        A man may proue a Poet now a daies?
                     
                     
                        Does Nature witt afford to breake a Ieſt?
                        This is a Poet: and his friends proteſt
                        He is to blame he Writes not: when (indeed,)
                        Th' Illiterate Gull can neither write nor read.
                        
                     
                     
                        Let Nature faile! Takes he but ſo much Paine,
                        
                        To write obſcurely: adding ſo much Braine.
                        
                        As end his crabbed ſenceleſſe verſe in Rime:
                        
                        This might a Poet beene in Perſeus time.
                        
                           
And more! (Though Horace in his book reherſes)
                        (Nature and Arte are both requir'd in Ʋerſes.)
                        There are thoſe, of their Poetry will vaunt,
                        Which do (God wote) both Wit &amp; Learning want:
                        I know them! Such as they at Table ſit
                        Each Ieſt you ſpeake, will to a Metre fit.
                        And thus your Witt's ſell for their priuate gaine
                        And bee accouted Poets for their paine.
                     
                     
                        Others there are, that Others workes ſuruay,
                        And muſt from all thinges ſome thing filtch away.
                        Who if to weaker Braines they can vnfolde
                        A Learned Author: nick a Phraſe thats olde:
                        Or change but one word in a line or two:
                        Straight all's their owne, they write, who doubts it ſo?
                        When I wood ſcarce beleeu't, though they, in fine,
                        To euery Verſe ſubſcribe: By Ioue 'tis mine.
                        
                        Nor is't inough they this in priuate ſhow,
                        But theſe are Poets, all the world muſt know.
                        
                           
'Tis ſtrange to ſee what ſtretching is of Wit
                                 •
                              ,
                        
                        What ſpare of ſpeech this plentious Preſſe begets.
                        Some (if you keepe them company) you'l finde
                        As choiſe to breake a Ieſt as to bteake winde.
                        And what's the reaſon thinke ye? Onely this:
                        All they can ſpeak's too little for the Preſſe.
                        
                        Where 'tis not loſſe of Friend, Life, Libertie,
                        
                        Shall cauſe them keepe a Ieſt in ſecrecy.
                     
                     
                        Others haue helpes: when their Inuention faile,
                        Straight they begin abuſiuely to raile.
                        Then out comes Whelps of the olde Dog: for ſport:
                        Shall barke at Great ones: bite the meanet ſort:
                        When the On-ſetters (after all their paine:
                        For feare, woo'd gladly call them in againe.
                        And theſe will Poets bee accounted too:
                        Becauſe they Dare doe more then others doe.
                        Though they their Verſes write, (a man may ſay:)
                        As Clown's get Baſtards, and ſtraight runne away.
                     
                     
                        
                        
                           Montanus needes will bee a Poet! why?
                        Becauſe the Muſes on a Mountaine hy
                        Inhabited. Peto for that his Name
                        
                        Denotes him Poet in the Anagrame:
                        And Quaint Caſtilio: (ſince his Father dy'd!)
                        Who many Volumes publiſh't: and beſide
                        Diuers neglected, Left vnto his Son:
                        Which dubbes him Poet, by praeſcription.
                        True! And Caſtilio will approued bee,
                        Or he will Print his Fathers Legacy.
                        
                     
                     
                        And marke Criſippo, but what ſhifts he'l finde,
                        Ere he'l bee counted once to come behinde,
                        In euery Booke he will beſpeake afore:
                        The comming out, roome for halfe a ſcore
                        Or a dozen Verſes, which he'l hugely puffe
                        With commendations of the Authors ſtuffe.
                        And in Hyperbolyes his Name extoll
                        
                           Yond Homer, Virgill, Ouide, Iuuenall.
                        
                           
Vouching no better Volume, ere was Writ,
                        
                        And that himſelfe hath had a Hand in it.
                     
                     
                        Oh this vaine-Praiſe-Affecting Poetry
                        
                        Is a bewitching-itching Leoproſie:
                        
                        That makes men Rub, ſcrub, rouz and touz their Braine,
                        
                        Pump their Pates dry for Ieſts: and all to gaine
                        So much Report: might ſerue to make them vaunt,
                        They are Applauded (though of Ignorant.)
                        
                        They'l ſnatch, and ſcratch, and ſcrape (though nere ſo ill)
                        And rather ſmart then holde their fingers ſtill:
                     
                     
                        Be there a Citty ſhow: or ſight at Court:
                        Of Acts Heroicke: or of Princely ſport:
                        
                           
                              •
                           which right to write of, or in Type to tell:
                        Might taxe a Daniels or a Spencers quill.)
                        Marke how theſe hungerbit Inuentions ſcud
                        To eye! to ſpy! All for no other good
                        Then onely this! poore this! But to obtaine:
                        
                           
                              •
                           ome fodder for their needy greedy ſtraine.
                     
                     
                        
                        See then how (Enuy) gin's her eyes to 
                              •
                           at
                        On dainties plenty, and repines thereat:
                        How muttering Momus (that knowes not to bite,)
                        Grumbles and mumbles mouthfuls out of ſpite.
                        How curriſh (Critticks) moſt ſeuerely harke:
                        Ready at each ſound of applauſe to barke.
                        How all together, and how each a part
                        Stretch, retch, faine, ſtrain, Inuention, Iudgement Art,
                        Raile, Lybell: what not? Rather then labour looſe
                        Ieſt on your Geſture: or be-lye your cloathes.
                        A ſubiect fitter for a Beadles fiſt
                        Then the tart lines of a ſmart Satyriſt.
                     
                     
                        Let Natures cauſes (which are too profound
                        For euery blockiſh ſottiſh Pate to ſound.)
                        Produce ſome monſter: ſome rare ſpectacle:
                        
                        Some ſeauen yeares Wonder: Ages miracle:
                        
                        Bee it a worke of nere ſo ſleight a waight,
                        It is recorded vp in Metre ſtraight,
                        
                           
And counted purchaſe of no ſmall renowne,
                        To heare the Praiſe ſung in a Market-towne.
                     
                     
                        How many Volumes lye neglected thruſt
                        In euery Bench-hole? euery heape of duſt?
                        Which from ſome Gowries practiſe, Powder plot,
                        Or Tiburne Lectur's, all their ſubſtance got:
                        Yet to
                              •
                           ſe our Time-ſtalles youll admire the rout
                        Of careleſſe feareleſſe Pamphlets flye about.
                     
                     
                        Bookes, made of Ballades: Workes: of Playes,
                        
                           Sightes, to be Read: of my Lo: Maiors day's:
                        
                           Poſt's, lately ſet forth: Bearing (their Backe at)
                        
                           Letters, of all ſorts: An intollerable Packet.
                        
                           Villains diſcouery, by Lanthorn and Candle-light:
                        (ſtrange if the author ſhould not ſee it to hādle right)
                        
                           A Queſt of Inquirie: (Iacke a Douer's)
                        The Ieſts of Scoggin: and diuers others
                        (which no man Better the Stationer knowes)
                        Wonderfull Writers; Poets in Proſe.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        What poſte pin'd Poets that on each baſe Theame,
                        
                        With Inuocations vexe Apollo's name.
                     
                     
                        Springes for Woodcockes: Doctor Merriman:
                        Rub and a good Caſt: Taylor the Ferriman.
                        Fennor, with his Vniſounding E'are word;
                        The vnreaſonable Epigramatiſt of Hereford:
                        
                        
                           Rowland with his Knaues a murninall;
                        No
                              •
                            worth the calling for, a ſire burne em all:
                     
                     
                        And number numberleſſe that march (vutolde)
                        Mongſt Almanacks and Pippins, to be ſolde.
                     
                  
                  
                     Apologie.
                     
                        THeſe Ill which berter Dare thē know to wrig
                        
                        Makes thoſe (I know) not dare w
                              •
                            better mig
                              •
                           
                        
                        For who iſt now attempts to Print, but knowes,
                        He muſt be one or cenſured on, of Thoſe!
                        
                        
                           
For my part (Gallants) it was nere my hap,
                        On high Pernaſſus Top, to take a nap:
                        Or the Diuine Nine ſiſters Fount to ſee:
                        Whence I might ſteale a ſip of Poetry.
                        
                        Theſe Idle Ʋerſes (which I Idle made)
                        None but the Idle I requeſt to read:
                        Then what Applauſe looke I for, all may gueſſe,
                        When none may looke for Praiſe from Idlenes.
                        
                     
                     Finis Saty: Primae.
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                  Satyra Secunda.
                  A MORALL SATYRE.
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              
                                  
                                 Sunt
                                  
                                 Videntur.
                              
                              
                                 Q Vidam
                                  
                                 &amp; non
                                  
                              
                              
                                  
                                 Videntur
                                  
                                 Sunt
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                  A Morall Satyre.
                  
                     Proaemium.
                     
                        I Taxe no Times, I beare no Furyes ſcourge:
                        I bring no powerfull Fountaine ſpringes to purge
                        This vicefull Lerna, this Augean ſtye,
                        From long neglected noyſome filthery.
                     
                     
                        
                           Vaunt Varlots then: Grizely Tartarian curres:
                        Vice-Pack-horſes: Swaines of inchanting pleaſures:
                        Wallow in Lake of Leaudneſſe: racket: yell
                        And all the world with thundring vproare fill,
                        Till angry Ioue his Chaos drench agen
                        And a new nature of milde molde begin.
                     
                     
                        Yet knowe (Earths Of-ſcums) I haue force, and woo'd
                        Vncaſe, vnlaſe, your Leaudnes: make ye ſcud:
                        Laſh at Lines length: and inſtrike ſuch a print,
                        Shu'd make ye ſtartle, had ye hartes of flint,
                        Coo'd I finde Patrons to maintaine me in't.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Satyra.
                     
                        BVt range my Muſe! find out ſome freſher Game,
                        
                        Some Mayden matter, ſome vnchaſed Theam
                                 •
                              .
                        
                        Beat through the throwes of theſe diſordered times.
                        
                        The thorny thickets of contagious crimes,
                        And rouz from ſquat, purſue with aeger cry,
                        The lurking Leaudneſſe, ſtrong ſcent villany,
                        Of thoſe cloſe Foxes, who (in milder skins)
                        Inuey, and gueſſe inuectiuely at Sinnes:
                        Bite with ſharpe cenſure: and ſeuerely ſcan
                        The inward Vertues, by the outward man.
                     
                     
                        Beſhrow mee (Sirs) if I dare ſtrout in 
                              •
                           treet,
                        Winke at a Window: A God-dam-me greet:
                        Vſher a Lady: but ſalute her Gloue:
                        
                        Or Kiſſe a Maide for manners more then Loue:
                        
                        Cringe to a S
                                 •
                              riuener: be conuerſing ſeene
                        In Ludgate, with a broken Citizen:
                        
                        
                           
Turne oft in Pauls: call for a ſtoole o'th Stage:
                        
                        Or walke atended with my Hackney Page:
                        
                           Pace Turnball, Shorditch, Long-lane: or Pickt-hatch,
                        Leaſt I be taken by this heedfull watch.
                        Theſe pickthanke Peſants; that with Lynceus eye,
                        Inſpect mans Actions too Iniuriouſly.
                     
                     
                        Firſt to yon Maſſe of man: yon loade of Guts,
                        
                        That all he handles in his belly puts:
                        Who euery meales meate makes a Maſſecry,
                        
                           Of Shambles, Poultry, Sea variety.
                        How on the Table he his Panch doth reſt,
                        And ſtuffes it as a Wallet of the beſt▪
                        
                        Yet cloſe his Buttockes rammes vp as in Pound
                        For feare o'th worſt, to'th' good-behauiour bound.
                        Snorts at mid-day: yet ſtartles at the ſturre,
                        Of a betraying Boote, or tel-tale Spurre:
                        Cryes out of Faſhions, as of Faſting-dayes,
                        
                        Rebukes Exceſſe: gainſt Vanityes inueyes:
                        
                           
Hates Vice as Hunger: and abhorres to ſtand
                        
                        In ſight of a (Sir reuerence) Saffron-band.
                        
                     
                     
                        Tell him his Worſhip is ſo ſtrictly wiſe:
                        His cloſeſt Trounces, full as full of vice.
                        As wide from Vertues meane as Largeſt ſize.
                     
                     
                        Next to yon Preſter Iohn, that Learned Clarke:
                        
                        Who after all my cloſeſt acts doth harke.
                        A man, that for a Wiſe one ſure woo'd paſſe,
                        Shu'd there but 6. bee, as there 7. was:
                        Hee heretofore (out of his Loue exceeding)
                        Woo'd euer bee examining my Reading:
                        Now (more Officious) euer Checking is:
                        A ſtrickt Remembrancer of all amiſſe.
                     
                     
                        Bid him bee leſſe in Office: more in Loue:
                        
                        Leaſt he ere long Iacke out of Office proue.
                     
                     
                        Laugh, Laugh, Demorritus! who can hold to hear
                              •
                           
                        
                        
                           Socraticke Doctors, Catoes moſt auſteer.
                        
                           
Roule vp the Records of Antiquity,
                        
                        To frame Abridgements for youth's Liberty.
                        
                        Accuſe Wits folly. Times ſtrange alterations:
                        The vaine expence of cloth conſuming faſhions,
                        When their allowance was (themſelues can tell)
                        At leaſt vnto a Codpiſſe halfe an Ell.
                     
                     
                        Lend me Athenian but a while thy light:
                        To ſcowre the ſcoutes, the Lurking holes of Spite,
                        
                        And execrable Enuy: ſee the rout
                        Of Raſcals: venome Vermin, I'le finde out:
                        Cankermouth'd Catchpoles, that in Ambuſh lye,
                        To wreck, to ſeck Vertues aeternitie:
                        With poyſnous blaſt of miſcreant Infamy.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                           (Iuſtmian) is too Fortunate to beare
                        The name of Iuſt: (Flora) too Curtious farre
                        To harbour Honeſty: (Varro) held to bee
                        
                           Vaine, for his skilfull vaine in Poetry.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        
                           (Fantaſticke) cannot with his Flaunders feete
                        Lock'd in his foure-wheele-casket vex the ſtreet:
                        Knocke in a Tauerne, but his Father heares,
                        Some 20 Leagues off. Luxurio feares
                        Retaine a ſeruant fairer then his wife:
                        Nor will Lorella in deſpaire of Life
                        Tell of her ſide-ſtitch or the Belly-ake,
                        Leaſt ſhe bee ſaid Lucinas ayde to lacke.
                     
                     
                        Who is from ſcourge of Cenſure can ſcape free,
                        Yea (Temperate Nature) men will jerke at thee!
                        How ſuffer ſome but for a Sanguin Noſe?
                        
                        A Scarlet ſcone? when each Logitian knowes
                        'Tis Vertues colour. How enuy ſome at
                              •
                           
                        
                        A Stirrill Chin? Or a top naked Pate?
                        
                        Emblem of Truth, and Graces. What reproofe
                        Goes with a Limping Leg? Or Vulcan Hoofe?
                        
                        Yea ſome ſo farre preſume, as to define
                        
                           Knaues, by their Bunch-back's, and their Goggle-eyne
                        
                        
                           
When Accidents (affirmes the Stagerite)
                        
                        Not Naturall cauſe no note but in Spirit.
                     
                     
                        Peace then Melampus, peace Albertus, Cocles:
                        
                        Ptoloemie, Rafis, and Auerroes.
                        
                           Gallon, Palemon: hence be ſilent all,
                        Or proue the cunning Huperphiſicall.
                        
                        And all leſſe learn'd in Rules of Phiſnomy:
                        
                        That Natures notes, holde markes of Infamy.
                        
                     
                     
                        Elſe (mincing Madam's) why doe we (alas!)
                        
                        Pine at your Pencill and conſpiring Glaſſe?
                        
                        Your Curles, Purles, Perriwigs, your Whal eb on
                              •
                            wheels▪
                        
                        That ſhelter all defects from head to heeles.
                        Making but Good what theſe count Vicious:
                        
                        Yet not iniuſtly termed odious.
                     
                     
                        To ſtrout in Purple or rich Scarlet dye
                        With ſiluer barres begarded thriftily:
                        To ſet in print the Haire: Character the Face:
                        
                        Or dye in graine the Ruffe for Viſage grace.
                        
                           
To clog the Eare with plummets: clag the wreſts
                        
                           With Busk-points, Ribbons, or Rebato-Twiſts:
                        From Barbors tyranny to ſaue a locke,
                        His Miſtris wanton fingers to prouoke:
                        Such Trifles, Toyes: in theſe ſharpe Crittitks view,
                        Throwes vs in number of the damued Crue.
                        
                     
                     
                        As if a Frounced, pounced, Pate coo'd not,
                        As much Braine couer, as a Stoike cut.
                        Or practicke Vertue, might not lodge as ſoone
                        Vnder a Silken, as a Cynicke gowne.
                        Fond fond Philoſophers: who e're definde
                        
                           Vertue a Habite of the Cloathes but minde?
                        
                     
                     
                        Tell me (preciſely) what auailes it ware,
                        A Bongraco Bonnet, Eye-brow ſhorter Haire?
                        A Circumcized Ruffe? Conuerting Eye?
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            Sadneſſe? Yes Indeed? Yea Verily?
                        To beare a Bible euery Edifying day
                        Of an Armefull, (beſide the Apochriphay?)
                        
                        
                           
To carry no more cloath then skin: to ſho
                              •
                           
                        
                        The Stockens worne at Knees, the Shooes at Toe?
                        If thou but nod at Fryers, Or be tane
                        Cloaſly conuerting an impure Queane?
                        Found in a Morgage, not a minute ſpare?
                        Or turne Informer for a demyſhare.
                     
                     
                        Who Vertue holdes a bare apparant Good,
                        
                        Makes nothing 
                              Ʋice, that may aſſume a hood,
                        A vaile of Well, pure honeſty no more
                        Then flat Hypo
                                 •
                              riſie: a painted Whore.
                        Countes nothing more (when indeed nothing leſſe
                        Then others mens Opinions Happines.
                        
                        And Vertue (rare!) All thinges to be at End:
                        
                        When euery action needs to Good muſt tend.
                     
                     
                        Giue me a Genius: a well tempred minde
                        which no Feare vrge: no Syren note can winde
                        From way of Right: that doth all Good approue
                        For no Good elſe, but for bare Vertues Loue.
                        
                           
Whome not Cymerian darknes, more then day:
                        Nor Gyges Ring could corrupt any way.
                     
                     
                        A Minde well mounted, that will ſcoffe at Hate,
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           rample on Fortune, feircel Incounter Fate,
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           purne at the ſound of Vulgar praiſe as baſe:
                        
                           
                              •
                           pit a defiance in proud Enuyes face:
                        An armed Conſcience that dares grapple with
                        A mu
                              •
                           ter of Opinions, in the teeth:
                        Who though a Theater ſhould ſtriue bring out
                        
                           
                              •
                           is cloſeſt groſeſt Faults, and all about
                        
                           
                              •
                           et on to barke: durſt boldly ſtand it out.
                     
                     
                        Who thinks to trauerſe ſo vpright the Stage
                        (Free from 
                              〈◊〉
                            of this C
                                 •
                              nſorious Age:
                        
                        Or aimes in Action at the Vulgar grace,
                        
                        Of Hydra-He
                                 ••••
                              
                            multitude, Appl
                                 •
                              uſe;
                        
                        Need frame him ſelfe a Nature that will brooke
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            many shapes as euer Proteus tooke.
                     
                     
                        To crye God 
                                 〈◊〉
                               you with a Courtly grace,
                        
                           
                           To Kiſſe the Hand, to-lay at Foote the Face:
                        To act the Croſ-point Longey ſleightly:
                        
                           Is held Affecting Proud Humility.
                        To Vaile the Bonnet: ſtiffe as Elephant,
                        
                        A Furlong off to caſt a Complement:
                        
                        To titch the Brimmes: or ſcarceto ſpeake at all:
                        Wee ſtately, ſcornefull, hatefull Geſture call.
                        And careleſſe carriage argues, Loues neglect:
                        In beſt endeauours Critticks finde defect.
                     
                     
                        Let me no oftner then Apollo appeare
                        To Laugh, to skip 
                              〈◊〉
                            
                           Phaebus) once a yeare,
                        To goe more formall then my won
                              •
                           ed faſhion,
                        Corrected in my Taylours laſt Edi
                              •
                           ion▪
                        
                        To rectifie my Fore-top: or aſſume,
                        For one nights Reuel▪ a 3. ſtory P
                              ••
                           me:
                        (Though ſome will Laſes weare, and Leekes as of
                        And with a more (p
                              •
                           rchance) Ambitious thought
                        Straight 'tis ſurmiſed, rumord r
                              •••
                           d about
                        
                           
I roare, I ſcore, I lauiſh, laſh it out.
                        Trifle Times Treaſure: And keepe open port,
                        To all Companions of licentious ſort▪
                        
                        When in a day or two, being found alone,
                        Hemmed in the hopefull habite of a G
                                 •
                              rne.
                        
                        By me a Plowdon or a Littleton.
                        
                        Lord! what a new bred fame gins hence to paſſe,
                        How I am changed from the man I was?
                     
                     
                        Thus I can expectation 
                              •
                           alſify:
                        Weary out Cenſure in vncertainty:
                        Redeeme Time as I liſt: proue Want of Wit
                        
                        In thoſe that moſt inue
                              •
                           tiue jerke at it:
                        And moſt precize, of greateſt vice condemne.
                        Making my Faults theirs: by Belying them.
                     
                     
                        Know I can Frolique be with (Fr
                                 •
                              gio)
                        
                        Court it in Compteſt phraſe with (Curio.)
                        
                        Come deepe the Caſter: and Carouce it free▪
                        
                        (As farre as Vertues limites Licence mee.)
                        
                           
In as rich Grograns, Sattins, Tiſſues, goe
                        As Florence, Carles, Tartary can ſhowe.
                        Meet, and crye farwell, to thoſe ſpirits bolde
                        By Piſtolltenure that their Liuings holde,
                        Confer with Crop-eard knights ath'poſt; heare tell
                        Of Stangate prizes, and of Shooters Hill,
                        Of Brothells, Stewes, of vil
                              •
                           ſt villanies,
                        
                        And learne out Vertue by her contraries.
                     
                     
                        Fond Affectation, to be counted Great,
                        
                        To be The man held: to be pointed at.
                        I e're neglected. Singularitye
                        
                        May ſometimes vertue b
                              •
                           : nere Poli
                              •
                           ye.
                        Who is a man of Note (note this from me)
                        Is ſure ne're to offend in ſecrecie:
                        
                        To liue in Bondage in Fa
                                 •
                              es Iealoſie.
                        
                     
                     
                        Tis not the mouthfull of mans breath I care,
                        Nor ſeuere Cenſure of ſtrict Critick
                                 •
                              
                            feare
                        In ſpite of Enuy, Hate 'twas neuer known:
                        
                           
                           But euer Fame will Vertue waite vpon;
                        And now, when Vertue Vice is held: whome is't
                        We may not Praiſe or Diſpraiſe as wee liſt?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        THen (Snarling curres) turne to this gally ſlyme.
                        Feed on the putrid ſubſtance of my Ryme,
                        
                        Heer's Hotch-pot: Soſſe: prouided filling ſtuffe
                        Shall finde your greedy Cenſures worke inough.
                        Where if I finde ye! Or but ſpie a traine:
                        A freſh haue at yee (Varlots) once againe.
                     
                     FINIS.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  To his worthy Friend vpon theſe Satyres.
                  
                  
                     
                        SAtyres in Engliſh? I pray God your fate,
                     Send's you not into the world too late
                     To proue there may be ſuch: For there ha's bin
                     So much deceit in Satyres, 'tis a Sin
                     
                     (Almoſt) to hope for good ones: They who beſt
                     Haue done, haue onely Dar'd: and more expreſt
                     Their Paſſions, then a Poem. Nay eeuen all
                     Doe but conuert their little Braines to gall:
                     And bee it bitter once they care not then
                     How venomous it be. Which errors when
                     I ſee, and ſee how well approu'd they are,
                     'Tis more then miracle, Your's be ſo farre
                     Diſtinguiſhed. And that you ſuruiue to Write,
                     
                     More out of true diſcerning then of Spite.
                     
                  
                  I. STEPHENS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  THE SECOND BOOKE: OF Satyricall Epigram's.
                  
               
               
                  
                  To his True Friend Tho: Fletcher of LINCOLN'S-INNE Gent:
                  
                     TOM!) 'twas thy Speeches did me firſt poſſeſſe
                     Theſe ſcattered Epigramm's deſeru'd the Preſſe.
                     
                     VVhoſe Learned Iudgement, and Loue, I knew ſuch,
                     Might wel Commend, and Command, twice as much.
                     If (Reader) then heer's ought may breed delight,
                     Giue halfe the thankes to him it brought to light.
                     Nor bluſh not (Tom!) nor blame not! that I ſeeme,
                     Thee the halfe-parent of my Booke to deeme.
                     Heer's nought but Good (if nothing they miſ-ſcan!)
                     
                     Let Critticks, Momus, All, ſay what they can!
                     Th'are Good: who doubts it? not, for ought I know:
                     Yet Good Ile ſweare: becauſe Thou ſaiſt th'are ſo.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Satyricall Epigrammes.
                  
                     
                        Ad Emptorem. Epig: 2.
                     
                        THeſe Epigrams thou ſee'ſt whoſe are they? mine?
                        No! The Book-binders: buy thē, they are thine.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Thraſonem. Epig: 2.
                     
                        SInce (Thraſo) met one ſtoutly in the field,
                        He cracks his Spirit knowes not how to yeeld.
                        Looks big! Sweares! ſtroutes with ſet-ſide armes the
                        Yet gently yeelds the wall to all he meets. (ſtreets:
                        And to his Friend that askes the reaſon why
                        
                           His Anſwer's this: my ſelfe I grace thereby.
                        For euery one, the common Prouerbe knowes:
                        
                           That All-wayes to the Wall the weakeſt goes.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Of a Rayling Clyent.
                     Epig. 3.
                     
                        I Call'd one Knaue: who anſwered: (Sir) not ſo!
                        
                           The Knaue doth all-way's with the Lawyer goe.
                        How could I well but well approue his ſpeech?
                        Each Lawyer walkes, his Clyent at his breech.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Of Debt. Epig. 4.
                     
                        TO bee Indebted is a ſhame (men ſay!)
                        Then 'tis Confeſſing of a ſhame, to Pay.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Medicum. Epig. 5.
                     
                        WHen (Mingo) cries How do you ſir! tis thought
                        He Patients wanteth? &amp; his practic's nought.
                        Wherefore of late now euery one he meeteth,
                        
                           
                           With Sir I'm glad to ſee you well hee greeteth.
                        
                        But who'l beleeue him now, when all can tell
                        The world goes Ill with him when all are Well?
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Againſt the Accademicks of their abuſiue * Ignoramus. Epig. 6.
                     
                     
                        THe Law is in our Hands! How dare ye then
                        Abuſiue bee? Cauſe ye are Law-leſſe men:
                        
                        Your fault was great! but wee neglect the ſame,
                        For ye excuſe your Error in the * Name.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Cornutum. Epig. 7.
                     
                        ONe tolde his wife a Harts-head he had bought
                        To hang his Hat vpon: and home it brought,
                        To whome his frugall Wife: what needs this care?
                        I hope (ſweete Hart) your Head your hat can bear
                              •
                           .
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     No-lawes Reformation.
                     Epig: 8.
                     
                        SInce (No-law's) Father did him Counſaile giue
                        And ſaid▪ hee onely by his Booke muſt liue.
                        Ha's bought the Law: and vowes his life to mend,
                        And moſt on's time will in his Studdy ſpend.
                        And (doubtleſſe) ſo he meanes, for wot ye why?
                        Has cha ng'd his Bed, and doth in's Studdy lye:
                        How like ye (No-law) now? Is hee not wiſe?
                        Thus he is certaine by 
                              •
                           he Law to Riſe.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Lucus and his long Haire.
                     Epig: 9.
                     
                        
                           LVcus) long locks down to his ſhoulders weares:
                        And why? He dares not cut them for his Eares.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Franciſco's Trauels. Epig: 10.
                     
                        TEn monthes (I take it) are not fully gone,
                        Sinee bolde (Franciſco) croſt the Seas alone.
                        VVho late returned (one woo'd thinke it much)
                        A compleat Linguiſt: skilfull in the Dutch.
                        
                        And more (if you knew all) for wot yee what?
                        In the Low-cuntry's hee the French hath got.
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Braggado and his Valour.
                     Epig: 11.
                     
                        GIue one bad word out comes Braggadoes ſword,
                        And ſweares (in rage) to ſheath it in your guts.
                        But draw and ſtifly ſtand vnto your word,
                        
                           
                              •
                           nd gently vp againe his blade he puts.
                        
                           
                              •
                           raues your acquaintance▪ vowes he loues all ſuch
                        
                           
                              •
                           s on their Reputation ſtand ſo much.
                        
                           
But bee he One that can his wroth containe,
                        He Scornes to ſtrike him! Hee'l not ſtrike againe.
                        When will Braggado then his manhood proue?
                        When he
                              •
                            meets one he doth not ſcorne, or Loue.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Duke and his Impriſonment.
                     Epig. 12.
                     
                        
                           DVke) lyes for Debt, yet nothing owes he'l ſweare
                        Beleeu't, 'tis falſe, as ſure as hee Lyes there.
                     
                  
                  
                     Againe: Of Duke and the Debt.
                     Epig. 13.
                     
                        
                           DVke's not in debt: yee doe him wrong to ſay it:
                        The Debt is—God knowes whoſe. His that w
                              •
                            pay i
                              •
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     (Guido's) Bounty.
                     
                     Epig. 14.
                     
                        GIft-gobling Guido alwayes, as he takes,
                        Vnto his Friend this hopefull anſwere makes.
                        I thanke you kindely: You haue beene at coſt:
                        But (if I liue) you ſhall not finde it loſt.
                        Then can I euer hope to liue and finde
                        Cloſe-fiſted Guido in the Giuing minde?
                        Nor can I thinke guifts loſt, though Guido dye?
                        
                        For who can looſe that he doth Giue away?
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Of Lawyers. Epig. 15.
                     
                        SOme, Lawyers praiſe: &amp; ſome their ſect defame:
                        The firſt I cann't: the laſt I will not blame.
                        Nor yet eſteeme Thoſe leſſe Praiſe-worthy, when
                        All loue not Vertue: No not moſt of men.
                        
                           
VVhome All men Praiſe I praiſe him not at all,
                        But rather him a Temporizer call.
                        When Two contend for, what but One muſt haue,
                        Who can doe Right and eithers fauours ſaue?
                        When one mans Loſſe anothers Game doth make,
                        And Looſers muſt, and will haue leaue to ſpeake.
                        Then Ge
                                 •
                              tle Lawyers,) thinke it more then well,
                        If the ha
                              ••
                           e part of men your Praiſes tell.
                     
                  
                  
                     To his Fellow Students.
                     Epig. 16.
                     
                        TO Riſe by Law, a Life wee couet all.
                        Why? 'Tis Death to vs, by the Law to Fall.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Him ſelfe. Epig. 17.
                     
                     
                        A Friend of mine, (and yet no friend to mee,)
                        Comes oft and craues my Epigram's to ſee.
                        
                           
He waighes each word, &amp; highly doth cōmend 'em
                        And much intreats me to the Preſſe to ſend 'em.
                        Thus (Foole!) my Labour's I let him pertake,
                        That Labour's mee a Foole imprint to make.
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Phantaſmo a Miſtris Boaſter.
                     Epig. 18.
                     
                        FY! fie (Phantaſmo!) ceaſe to raiſe
                        Such Trophaeis in thy Miſtris Praiſe.
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           hee's Faire! what then? The houſe moſt white
                        
                           
                              •
                           eeme Venus Birds moſt to inuite.
                        And Trees that faireſt Fruite doe beare
                        VVith Stones aſſaulted oftneſt are.
                        
                           
                              
                                 •
                              hee's Pretty! Witty! cruell Wit,
                        
                           
                              •
                           f not Wiſdome, Ioyn'd with it!
                        
                           
                              •
                           hee's Kinde! 'Tis true! what better knowne?
                        
                           
                              •
                           Vhat worſe? when Kinde to more then one.
                        
                           
Wrong not then my Pureſt Faire,
                        
                        With this meane this skin compare.
                        Rather by thy Sonnets, ſeeke,
                        To make her Praiſes Venus like.
                        How ere ſhe Propper: Faire her Feature:
                        
                        Beleeu't ſhee's but a Common creature.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Sextum. Epig. 19.
                     
                        
                           SExtus) 6. Pockets weares: 2. for his Vſes:
                        
                        The other 4. to Pocket vp Abuſes.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Epig. 20.
                     
                        
                           KIt) I commend thy care of all I know,
                        That p
                              •
                           un'dſt thy Cuſhion for a Pipe of To—
                        Now thou art like (though not to ſtuddy more!)
                        Yet ten-times Harder then thou didſt before.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Cynna's Theft. Epig. 21.
                     
                        STolne Fruite is ſweete: So cannot Cynna ſay,
                        
                        That Stole a Wench, and had her tooke away.
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Luce and her 4. Husbands, 3. of them thus Named, Small, Forman, Middleton. Epig. 22.
                     
                     
                        
                           LVce) late is left a Wealthy widdow:
                        
                        (How can it other bee then ſo?)
                        
                           
                              •
                           oure Husbands ſhe hath buryed,
                        Yet would not ſtick againe to wed,
                        Which on her Hand ſhe thus doth caſt:
                        
                           
                              •
                           mall, Forman, Middleton: And my Laſt.
                        Counting for euery finger One)
                        
                        Which all (God wot) are dead and gone.
                        Then (Luce) beware a Fift to take,
                        
                           
                              
                                 •
                              eaſt ſo a Hand of all you make.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     More-dew's Payment.
                     Epig. 23.
                     
                        
                           MOre-dew) the Mercer (with a kinde ſalute)
                        Woo'd needs intreat my Cuſtome for a Sute
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                        He'r Sir (quoth hee) for Sattins, Vel
                                 •
                              ets, call:
                        
                           VVhat ere you pleaſe, Ile take your word for all.
                        I thank't! Tooke! Gaue my word! (ſay than?)
                        Am I at all indebted to this man?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Clyms Account. Epig. 24.
                     
                        
                           CLym calls his Wife and reckoning all his neighbor
                        Iuſt Halfe of them are Cuckolds he auer's.
                        Nay fie (quoth ſhe!) I would they heard you ſpeak
                        You of your ſelfe it ſeemes no Reckoning make.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Of Sim, and his ſpeedy Marriage.
                     Epig. 25.
                     
                        SIx months (quoth Sim) a Sutor and not ſped?
                        I in a Sennet did both Woe and Bed.
                        
                        : Who greene Fruit Loues muſt take long paines to ſhake.
                        Thine was ſome Downe-fall I dare vndertake.
                     
                  
                  
                     A Manly Woman the beſt Wife.
                     Epig. 26.
                     
                        
                           FAire! manly! Wiſe! Imagine which of theſe
                        In Wedlock choiſe would beſt my fancy pleaſe?
                        Of all: giue me the Woman halfe a Man:
                        
                        So I ſhall (happy) haue but halfe a Woman.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     The Womans Anſwer. Epig. 27.
                     
                     
                        IF Halfe a woman beſt your Humour fit:
                        'Twere beſt to marry an Hermophrodite.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Tom's good Fortune in being Rob'd.
                     Epig. 28.
                     
                        
                           TOm) tels hee's Rob'd, and counting all his loſſes,
                        
                        
                           Concludes: All's gone the world is full of Croſſes.
                        If all be gone (Tom) take this comfort then,
                        Th'art certaine neuer to haue Croſſe agen.
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Lawyers and Poets.
                     Epig. 29.
                     
                        NO mar'le that Lawyers, rich: Poets, poore liue,
                        One giues to take, the other, takes to Giue.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Ignotum. Epig. 30.
                     
                        VVHat bred a Seholler: borne a Gentleman,
                        
                        Of 5. yeares ſtanding an Oxonian.
                        
                        
                           
Of perſon Proper: of a comely Feature:
                        
                        And ſhall I baſely now turne Seruing-Creature?
                        
                        
                           (Foole!) hug thy fortune. S'fut 't may be thy making
                        A Ladyes proffered Seruice not worth taking?
                        Who her ſerues (ſure) ſhall be well Borne: (and
                        
                           One knowne ſufficient for the Turne before. (more)
                        The more thy Standing, greater (Foole) thy Grace.
                        
                        And thou farre fitter to ſupply the place.
                        For men in ſeruing Ladyes much may get,
                        
                        Then men of Beſt-parts ſooneſt they'l admit.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Spruſam. Epig. 31.
                     
                        WHen men ſpeake Baudy knoweſt thou what's the matter.
                        
                           (Sprufa) ſo often ſpitteth? (not to flatter!)
                        The cauſe (I take't) is this: Her teeth doe water.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Of the Riming Sculler.
                     Epig. 32.
                     
                        
                           HOrace the Poet, in his Booke reherſes,
                        
                           That Water-drinkers neuer make good Verſes.
                        Yet I a Poet know, And (in his Praiſe!)
                        
                        Hee's one has liu'd by Water all his day's.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sues Slip. Epig. 33.
                     
                        
                           SVe ſwore ſhe Lou'd mee: and vow'd faithfully
                        Neuer to match with any but with mee.
                        Now ſhe hath chang'd her minde: and of All men
                        Will none of mee. Hath ſhe not match't mee then?
                     
                     
                        Tell her ſhe Trifles. Aske but to what end
                        
                           She ſwore ſhee Lou'd? She meant but as a Friend.
                        
                           
Aske why Loue tokens ſhe did priuate ſend?
                        
                           Still ſhee replyes: She meant but as a Friend.
                     
                     
                        Aske why ſh' Inuited mee to walke alone
                        where ſhe her thoughts more fully did make known
                        Binding with Oathes, Deliuering Hand on that,
                        
                        
                           Sealing with Lippes, In Wttneſſe I know what:
                        Caſting her ſelfe downe by mee: where I could
                        And might haue tooke, what Suerty I would.
                        
                           Still blameleſſe, ſhameleſſe, Shee will all defend,
                        
                           Saying in all: Shee meant but as a Friend.
                     
                     
                        Then bee Su
                                 •
                              
                            ſuch to all her Friends, as mee,
                        I'ad rather ſhee my Friend then Wife ſhu'd bee.
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Win and her Sutors.
                     Epig: 34.
                     
                        
                           WIn is much wooed to, but not wonne of any:
                        The troth on't is: She doth admit too many.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Tym's Studioſity. Epig. 35.
                     
                        MArke ye how ſtudious (Tym) is turnd of late?
                        How he breakes Company to meditate?
                        Does hee but thus continue, certainly,
                        Hee'l bee (at leaſt) a Sargeant, ere hee dye.
                        Hee may doe (doubtleſſe) much! yet I can tell,
                        Hee'l not come neere a Sargeant, by his will.
                     
                  
                  
                     Aenigma.
                     
                        A Begger once exceeding poore
                        A penny pray'd mee giue him:
                        And deeply vow'd n'ere to aske more:
                        
                        And I, nere more, to giue Him.
                        
                        
                           Next day he Begg'd againe, I gaue,
                        
                        Yet Both of vs onr Oathes did ſaue.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Of an Egregious Whoore.
                     Epig. 36.
                     
                        THy Belly is thy God. I well may ſay!
                        
                        All thy care is to ſerue it Night and Day.
                        
                        
                           Feare then thy God: leaſt (whil'ſt thou worſhip ſo!)
                        
                           He Riſe, and Helliſh torments put the to.
                     
                  
                  
                     Of Felo and his Poetry.
                     Epig. 37.
                     
                        
                           FElo) that lately kiſt the Gaole, hath got
                        A ſmacke of Poetry! yea more then that!
                        Hee will maintaine none can bee truely ſaid
                        A Poet, that was neere Impriſoned.
                        
                        : No Bird ſings ſweet
                              •
                           r then the Bird in Cage.
                        : And Satyriſts (like Dogs) ty'd, fierceſt rage.
                        
                           
Thus will fond (Felo) proue by Diſputation,
                        That New-gate is the Muſes habitation.
                        
                        But how ſo? when ſome there cannot reherſe,
                        In a month's Learning, for their Liues a Verſe.
                     
                  
                  
                     To his Vnconſtant Miſtris.
                     Epig. 38.
                     
                        I Dare not much ſay when I thee commend,
                        Leaſt Thou bee changed ere my Praiſes end.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Woman (quaſi) Woe-man.
                     Epig. 39.
                     
                        HAd I not felt it miſery to W
                                 •
                              e,
                        
                        I had beene marryed (certaine) long agoe.
                        Had I Not marryed, ſtraight (Moroco) ſayes,
                        I had not once felt Woe in all my dayes.
                        
                           
If after Woman as before comes Woe,
                        
                        
                           Woe worth the Man with Woman hath to doe.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        For Lawyers. Epig. 40.
                     
                        I Muſe that Lawyers feare no more to marry
                        
                        That from their Wiues muſt all the Terme-time tarry.
                        O Sir! If Termely abſence breeds the Feare,
                        
                        How many Frights each Lawyer, in a yeare?
                     
                  
                  
                     Speudall's Pollici
                           •
                        .
                     Epig. 41.
                     
                        NOuerint Vniuerſi per prae—Thus began
                        
                        
                           (Notario) read, ere hee'd his Coyne forgoe.
                        Holde (cryes young Spendall:) S'fut you marre all man!
                        By any meanes my Father muſt not know.
                        
                           For any money I'de not haue it ſo.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Of Liber too wary to Thriue.
                     Epig. 42.
                     
                        
                           LIber) is late ſet vp, and wanteth Cuſtome.
                        
                        Yet great reſort hath got: but hee'l not Truſt 'em.
                        
                        Is not his Loue vnto his Friend the greater?
                        Hee'l want himſelfe, ere hee'l ſee him a Debtor.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     In Lesbiam, ingratam.
                     Epig. 43.
                     
                        WHy I ſhould Loue thee I no Reaſon ſee:
                        
                           Then Out of Reaſon (Lesbia) I Loue thee.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Sir Hughes miſtake. Epig. 44.
                     
                        IN Marriage, Woman promiſe makes:
                        To ſerue her Husband all her Life.
                        
                           
                           
                              •
                           ence comes it that Sir Hugh miſtakes:
                        
                           
                              •
                           hat vſes Seruants as his Wife.
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           nd further yet the ſence doth wreſt,
                        
                           
                              •
                           ouing Her moſt that ſerues him beſt.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Pontum. Epig. 45.
                     
                        
                           
                              
                                 •
                              Ontus comes Poſting almoſt euery day,
                        And cryes How doe you Sir? Come, what's th
                              •
                            play?
                        Who doubts but much his labour hee hath loſt,
                        nere coo'd tell, no more then coo'd the Poſt.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        In Milonem. Epig: 46.
                     
                        
                           MIlo) much blames mee, that in all my 
                              Ʋerſe,
                        
                        I nothing in my Miſtris Praiſe reherſe.
                        
                           
                              •
                           now I haue Volumes, and wou'd (I confeſſe.)
                        ut can not get conſent of Her to Preſſe.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Of Wine. Epig. 47.
                     
                        
                           PHyſitians) Wine at Spring-Time poyſon call;
                        I hold! It neuer hurteth but ith' Fall.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     In Preſbiterum.
                     Epig. 48.
                     
                        
                           PResbyter) that of late his Pariſh croſt,
                        By his looſe Liuing, hath his Liuing loſt.
                        And will turne Begger: hoping by his Wittes,
                        
                        To raiſe a Benefice from Benefitts
                        
                        Foole! Studdy better, better meanes to liue.
                        To Learned Beggers, rare, or ne're men giue.
                        Where Art and Pouerty together dwell,
                        'Tis ſhrowdly to bee fear'd all is not well.
                        Men doe by Beggiug Liuings get (we ſee!)
                        Yet few get Liuings by their Beggery.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        In Ignotum. Epig. 49.
                     
                        A Corniſh Citizen came to his Wife,
                        
                        Swore he had beene in danger of his life.
                        How man (quoth ſhee!) Faith pointing but at One
                        
                        Counted the arrant'ſt Cuckold in the Towne.
                        
                           
                              •
                           ay Lord (quoth ſhee!) what meant you Man to ſay it?
                        
                           
                              
                                 •
                              ye you forget your Selfe too bad, be quiet.
                     
                  
                  
                     The Iealous Man.
                     
                        
                           Care: I Feare: I Vexe full ſore:
                        To Know of what would Vexe mee more.
                     
                  
                  
                     The Wittall.
                     
                        
                           Know my Fate, and that muſt beare,
                        And ſince I Know I need not Feare.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Epig. 50.
                     
                        HOw can (Sir Amorous) in his ſute ſpeede ill,
                        
                        That hath his Miſtris, euery where at Will.
                        
                        Then worke thy Will of her, for know, of Olde,
                        
                        
                           Tayle Tenure hath been held the ſureſt holde.
                     
                  
                  
                     Incerti Authoris Of a Bald-man. Epig. 51.
                     
                     
                        THy Haires, and ſinnes, no man may aequall cal
                        For as thy Sinnes increaſe thy Haires doe Fall
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     An Anſwer to the ſame.
                     Epig. 52.
                     
                        YEs: If thy Haires fall, as thy Sinnes increaſe,
                        
                        Both will ere long proue aequall, Numberleſſe.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        In Philippum. Epig: 53.
                     
                        CAll Phillip, Flat-noſe, ſtraight hee frets thereat!
                        And yet this Phillip hath a Noſe, that's Flat.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     To his Ingenious Friend Will: Goddard of his Booke intituled: Waſpes▪
                        
                     
                     Epig. 54.
                     
                        TRue Epigrams moſt fitly likned are
                        To Waſpes, that in their taile a ſting muſt beare.
                        
                           
                              •
                           hine being Waſpes. I ſay, (who'ſt will repine!)
                        
                           
                              •
                           hey are not Epigrams are not like Thine.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Amor ex viſu.
                     Of a Blind-man, Louing.
                     
                        Epig. 55.
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           F Loue comes but by Sight: (as 
                              •
                           rue we finde.)
                        Then needs muſt (Caec
                                 •
                              ) ſee: for he is Blinde.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Maxima amicitia inter aequales.
                     The Younger Brother to the Elder.
                     
                     Epig. 56.
                     
                        
                           IF Amongst aequals greateſt Friendſhip bee,
                        Our Loue was Beſt in our minoritie.
                        When as this mutuall Leſſon wee were taught,
                        To bee as Equall branches from One graft.
                        Then did wee Goe and Grow alike, as One,
                        
                        No Difference had in Education.
                        So our Affections Sympathiz'd in all,
                        That no euent could come but mutuall.
                        
                        So Neare ſo Deare, we both did Loue and Liue,
                        
                        That each ones Breath to each might Being giue,
                        What more? So Life, and Loue, in all did linke vs,
                        That One that knew vs both, both one wou'd think v
                     
                     
                        Which in our Father br
                                 •
                              d this foule miſtake,
                        Who gaue One all, and ſo did Difference make.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Vaitas non eſt numerus.
                     Epig. 57.
                     
                        ROme for (Reuerſio:) there's but One, Ile ſwear
                              •
                           
                        
                        Betwixt him and 5. hundred a Yeare.
                        
                        O happy, thrice (Reuerſio) if that One,
                        
                        (As none a Number) thou coo'dſt number none!
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Againe: Vnus Homo nullus homo.
                     Epig. 58.
                     
                        
                           ONe Man is no man: Proue that if you can,
                        
                           (Re
                                 •
                              erſio) you for euer make a Man.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Natura nihil agit fruſtra.
                     Againſt Painted Women.
                     Epig. 59.
                     
                        MOſt are of minde that Women are leſſe Fair
                                 •
                              ,
                        
                        And more Deformed: then of Olde they were.
                        
                           
                           True! elſe In vai
                              •
                           e woo'd Nature labour take,
                        To giue them Beauty, that can Beauty make.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     To his Hearts conciled Honor.
                     
                        THen Thee, the Goddeſſe did Diuinely frame,
                        For her Art's glory, and the
                              •
                           e Artiſts ſhame.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     In Amicam dotem quaerentem.
                     Epig. 60.
                     
                        (—) Loues me, and woo'd wed, but wot ye what?
                        Vnleſſe I make her Ioynture ſhee will not.
                        
                           And whats this Ioynture. A future Eſtate
                        : Purchaſt by Prouidence, poſſeſt by Fate.
                        Whereon to Hopes vnkindneſſe, griefe t'inioy,
                        A Sin, to wiſh for, in it ſelfe a toy.
                        
                        
                           
A meerly neerl' Inuention, onely fit
                        To part falſe hearts, and not to Ioyne on it.
                        Then (—) on Ioynture doe not ſo much ſtand,
                        : All faithfull Louers are not borne to Land.
                        It breeds Diſtruſt: Inferres ſuſpition
                        
                        Of other diſlikes, to diſlike thee on.
                        For was thy Loue, ſo firme as mine! with me
                        Thou'dſt thinke no other but to liue and die.
                     
                     
                        Yet bee't as 'twill! ere Ile my Loue forgoe,
                        For want of what I need not: this Ile doe,
                        Take mee! Ile play th' Good-husband, and I will
                        Both Day and Night bee getting for thee ſtill.
                        And what I get (and I will get for Life,)
                        
                        Dying Ile wholly leaue vppon my Wife.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           f this contents not! marke then what Ile ſay.
                        Dues muſt not bee demaunded till the Day.
                        
                        
                           
Let (—) then Iuſtly Ioyne me to her now,
                        And then aske Ioynture when it ſhall grow Due.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Of a Lawyer and a Phyſitian, which the Better man.
                     Epig. 61.
                     
                        A Quaint Phyſitian that had tooke Degree,
                        Like in his Habite: aequall in his Fe
                                 •
                              .
                        
                        Being a man of Vniuerſall grace,
                        
                        Contended with a Lawyer for the place:
                        Sir (quoth 'Phyſitian) I am One you know
                        That before Lords and Ladyes vſe to goe.
                        My Life ſecure, voide of ſeditious ſtrife.
                        Not one dares once moleſt me, for his Life.
                        
                        I oft am ſent for, Lawyer then (bee ſe'd)
                        And haue to doe, with Ladyes in their bed.
                     
                     
                        Lawyer.
                        
                           Be Patient (Doctor,) And take this from mee,
                           Tis not your Grace: like Habite: aequall Fee:
                           
                           
                              
Nor Priuiledges all: (ſay what you can)
                           May make you bee, or ſeeme the better man:
                           I (as Apollo) am the God, to whome.
                           All Countryes croutching doe for Counſaile come.
                           Iudge then my ſtate! how Honored I liue:
                           How Liberall: Counſaile vnto all I Giue:
                           
                           How Honeſt, That am ſought too: free from Hate
                           
                           When men will truſt mee with their whole eſtate.
                           No not the ſtatelyeſt Lady in the Land,
                           Will ſticke to put her Caſe into my hand:
                           Goe to our Practiſe! (for my Countries care)
                           I moſt am ſtirring where Contentions are.
                           You in Infections, and Diſeaſes raining,
                           Make out of Others loſſe and Hurt, your gaining.
                           I to ſuppreſſe Deceit, Truth's Cauſes vrge:
                           
                              You, Humours to exhale, with Gliſters purge.
                           Miſtake not Doctor then, and you ſhall finde.
                           It is your Office for to come behinde.
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Of 2. Painters contending for Praeeminence in their Ar
                           •
                        . Epig. 62.
                     
                     
                        TWo Painters on a time at variance fell,
                        Which might each other in his Art excell.
                        One thinking ſtraight to end ſo vaine a ſtrife,
                        Pluckes forth the curious Picture of his Wife,
                        
                        Swearing if ought of his could this ſurpaſſe,
                        Hee, of the Two the better Artiſt was:
                        The other more Learned in Philoſophie.
                        
                        
                           Saves All compares muſt amongſt ae
                              •
                           ua
                              •
                           ts bee.
                        Now then (if this mu
                              ••
                            the Contention end)
                        You of neceſſity your Wife muſt lend.
                        Then let me preſently her with me take,
                        And I hee Image ſhall more Liuely make.
                        Let no ſuſpition cauſe you to deny her,
                        Ile make it ſpeedily: And ſend it by her.
                        This done! The Artiſt cuuningly did bid her,
                        Before him ſtand, as when her Husband did her,
                        
                        
                           
Who ſpeedily his Percill forth did plucke,
                        And cloſe him
                              •
                           elfe vnto his worke betooke.
                        So Iuſtly Her hee fitted euery where,
                        She ſwore her Husband could not him come neere.
                        : No better Iudge then, can I haue, nor Will,
                        
                        : Goe home and tell thy Husband of my Skill.
                        
                        At whoſe returne the Good-man (fond to know)
                        Askt her the Enſigne of his Art to ſhow.
                        (Quoth ſhe) this time the Ground he onely laide,
                        It ſhall in time bee perfected (hee ſaide.)
                        Oft was he vrgent, (and woo'd Anſwer none,)
                        From day to day hee'd aske (What ha's h
                                 ••
                               done?)
                        
                        It chanced ſo that in ſome 10. Months after,
                        Shee was deliuered of a goodly Daughter.
                        
                        So like in all, to th' Mother was this Elfe,
                        
                        That none could thought bee mother but herſelfe.
                        
                        Which Born
                                 •
                              , ſhe tooke, and to her Man did ſend it
                        
                           Loe heere my Picture: Trie if you can mend it.
                     
                     FINIS.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  To the worthy Author vpon theſe Epigrams.
                  
                     LEt me not whilſt I praiſe an Epigram,
                     
                     Deſerue a Satyre: Let not me who am
                     As nice in praiſing as diſpraiſiug ſtill,
                     Commend your worke as trading Poets will:
                     For then I might praiſe Bookes I neuer read,
                     Bookes ſenceleſſe, at leaſt not Interpreted,
                     And ſweare I know them good. Thus many doe
                     Commend and yet maintaine, their credits too:
                     Which, my poore Innocence hath much admir'd,
                     Till I perceiu'd theſe Poets who are hir'd,
                     In all reſpects are Shop-keepers: And they
                     Grow Bankroupts, if forſworne but once a day:
                     So theſe in wit grow beggerly whoſe ſloath
                     Hath nothing but a Wager, or an Oath
                     To proue their owne or other mens deſert:
                     
                        
And did not my per-vſall now conuert
                     My Iudgement to conſider what I praiſe:
                     I might (as they) approue, and many wayes
                     Recant hereafter: But I giue them leaue
                     To Write vpon me, when they ſhall perceiue
                     Such ſcorn'd Inconſtancie; and if they pleaſe
                     To doo't in Epigrams, Let them firſt learne Theſe.
                     
                     Which if they can learne, they may truely boaſt▪
                     
                     They haue aduantage gotten with the moſt.
                  
                  IO: STEPHENS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  THE Third Booke of Humours: Intituled Notes from BLACK-FRYERS.
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
               
               
                  
                  Epigram.
                  To his Lou: Chamber-Fellow, and neareſt Friend NAT: GVRLIN Of Lincolnes-Inne Gent.
                  
                     
                        NAT) Counſaile me! (faith!) what wod'ſt hau
                           •
                         me doe
                     My priuate Notes produce in publique view?
                     
                     Tuſh! mooue me not: yet (doubtles) tis rare ſtuff
                     And may Take, why not? if ſo! Good inough.
                     How ere (Nat) Patronize it, thou canſt tell,
                     (If ought miſlike:) I meant, and wiſh all well.
                     
                     Then, Good: or Bad heer (Sirs!) on liking take it
                     If Good, 'tis I: If Bad: 'tis you that make it.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                     Notes from Black-Fryers.
                  
                     WHat (friend Philemo) let me thy corpes Imbrace!
                     So jumpe met in this vnfrequented place?
                     Then, faith! 'lets Frolique't: pre'thee whats the Play?
                     
                     (The firſt I viſited this twelue monthes day.)
                     
                        (They ſay) A new Inuented Toy of Purle
                     
                  
                  
                     That ieoparded his Necke, to ſteale a Girle
                     Of 12: And (lying faſt impounded for't)
                     Hath 
                           •
                        ither ſent his Beard, to Act his part.
                     Againſt all thoſe in open Malice bent,
                     That would not freely to the Theft conſent.
                     Faines all to's wiſh, and in the Epilogue,
                     Goes out applauded for a famous—)
                  
                  
                     
                     Now hang me if I did not looke at firſt,
                     For ſome ſuch ſtuffe by the fond peoples thruſt.
                     Then ſtay! Ile ſe
                           •
                        't, and ſit it out (what ere)
                     Had I at comming forth tooke a Gliſter:
                     
                     Had Fate fore-read me in a Croude to dye:
                     To bee made Adder-deafe with Pippin-crye.
                     Come▪ let's bethink our ſelue
                           •
                         what may be found
                     To deceiue Time with, till the ſecond ſound:
                     Out with theſe matches fore-runners of Smoake,
                     This Indian paſtime I could neuer brooke.
                  
                  
                     SEe (Captaine Martin) he ith' Renounce me Band▪
                     
                     That in the middle Region doth ſtand
                     Woth' reputation ſteele! Faith! lets remoue,
                     Into his Ranke, (if ſuch diſcourſe you Loue)
                     Hee'l tell of Baſilisks, Trenches, Retires:
                     
                     
                        Of Pallizadoes, Parepets, Frontires:
                     
                        
Of Cnluerins, and Baricadoes too:
                     What to bee Harquebazerd: to lye in Perdue:
                     
                     How many men a Souldier ought to ſlay
                     For a Lieutenant-ſhip: or Twelue month Pay.
                     
                     Hee'l read a Lecture (by his skill exceeding)
                     O
                           •
                         
                        Reputation: when▪ it lyes a Bleeding:
                     
                     
                        When Tutcht: when Ingaged: when quite Dead,
                     
                        
                           •
                         How none may euer Fight once Baffled.
                     
                        What ſatisfaction for the Lye: and when
                     
                     Quarrels are mortall: when Sec
                           •
                        nds may come in▪
                     
                     Then of the Nether-lands! what Paſſes there:
                     What ſtout Performances: wherein hee'l ſweare
                     As many weekely fall but for the Lye,
                     
                     As did in ho
                           •
                        teſt time of Si
                              •
                           kneſſe dye.
                     Laſt for his Manhood: how in furie (cro
                           •
                        t)
                     For a falſe reckoning once he ſlew his Host.
                     
                     And late in England, (ſince his comming o're)
                     
                        
                           •
                        nto the Channell flung an Oyſter-whoore.
                     
                        
For taking th'wall of him: ſeeme but to doubt
                     (The leaſt) of theſe: ſtraight he will plucke ye out
                     Handfuls of Reputation: gain'd of thoſe
                     That dared not his Valour counterpoſe.
                     But wronging him: and call'd to account for't
                     
                        In Satisfaction from their Hands woo'd part.
                     Which he puts vp, and gloriouſly puts forth
                     In Ordinaries to proclaime his worth,
                     
                     Thinking to get (what common ſence denyes)
                     Credit: by Pocketting vp Iniuryes.
                     Then Learne of him, he'l teach you how yee might
                     Be counted Valiant, and neuer Fight.
                     
                  
                  
                     LOok next to him to, One we both know well,
                     (Sir I
                              •
                           and Hunt) a Trauailer that will tell
                     Of ſtranger Things then Tatterd Tom ere li't of,
                     Then Pliny, or Heroditus e're writ of:
                     How he a remnant lately brought with him
                     
                        
                        Of Iacobs Ladder from Ieruſalem:
                     At the Barmodies bow the Fiſhes fly.
                     Of Lands inriched by a Lottery.
                     
                     Of Affricke, Aegypt: with ſtrange Monſters fil
                           •
                        
                        ▪
                     
                     Such as nere Noahs Arke: nere 
                           
                              •
                           den held.
                     And rarer Rarities, then all of theſe:
                     Iuſt now to bee diſcouered (if yee pleaſe!)
                     Such as woo'd make a Blind-man fond to ſee:
                     Conuicted Gallants looſe their hopes and flie,
                     Moſt younger Brothers ſell their Lands to buy,
                     
                        Guyantan Plumes: like Icarus to fly.
                  
                  
                     BVt ſtay! ſee heere (but newly Entred,)
                     A Cheapſide Dame, by th' Tittle on her head!
                     Plot (Villain!) plot! Let's lay our heads together▪
                     
                     We may deuiſe perchance to get her hither.
                     (If wee to-gether cunniningly compact)
                     Shee'l holde vs dooing till the Latter Act.
                     
                     
                        
And (on my life) Inuite vs Supper home,
                     Wee'l thruſt hard for it▪ but wee'l finde her rome,
                     Heer Mis—(pox ont! ſhe's paſt, ſh
                           •
                        'l not come ore,
                     Sure ſhee's beſpoken for a box before.
                  
                  
                     KNoweſt thou yon world of faſhions now comes in
                     In Turkie colours carued to the skin.
                     Mounted Pelonianly vntill hee reeles,
                     That ſcornes (ſo much) plaine dealing at his heeles.
                     His Boote ſpeakes Span
                              •
                           ſh to his Scottiſh Spurres,
                     His Sute cut Frenchly, round beſiucke with Burres.
                     Pure Holland is his Shirt, which proudly faire,
                     Seemes to out-face his Doublet euery where,
                     His Haire like to your Mo
                              •
                           r's or Iriſh Lockes,
                     His chiefeſt Dy
                           •
                        t, Indian minced Dockes.
                     What Countrey may-game might wee this ſuppoſe,
                     Sure one woo'd thinke a Roman by his Noſe.
                     
                     
                        
                        
                           •
                        o! In his Habite better vnderſtand,
                     ee is of England by his Yellow Band.
                     
                  
                  
                     NOw Mars defend vs! ſeeſt thou who comes yonder?
                     Monſtrous! A Woman of the Maſculine Gender.
                     
                     
                        
                           •
                        oke! thou mayſt well deſcry her by her groath,
                     
                        
                           •
                        t, point not man! Leaſt wee be beaten both.
                     e her a little, marke but where ſhee'l goe,
                     ow (by this hand) into the Gallants Roe.
                     
                        
                           •
                        ther her alone! What ere ſhe giues to ſtand,
                     ee'l make her ſelfe a gayner, By the Hand.
                     
                  
                  
                     VHat think'ſt thou of yon plumed Dandebrat,
                     
                     
                        Yon Ladyes Shit
                           •
                        le-cocke, Egyptian Rat:
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           n Musk-ball, Milke-ſop: yon French Sincopac
                           •
                        :
                     at Vſhers in, with a Coranto graco.
                     
                        
                        Yon Gilded March-pane: yon All Verdingall,
                     This is the Puppet, which the Ladyes all
                     Send for of purpoſe and ſolicite ſo
                     
                        To daunce with them. Pray (Sir) a ſtep or two.
                     A Galliard or a Iigg: Pox ont! cryes hee,
                     That ere I knew this Toyling faculty.
                     
                     Yet marke! No ſooner ſhall the Cornets blow,
                     But ye ſhall haue him skipping too and fro.
                  
                  
                     A Stoole and Cuſhion! Enter Tiſſue ſlop!
                     
                     Vengeance! I know him well, did he not dr
                           •
                        
                     
                     Out of the Tyring-houſe? Then how (the duſe)
                     Comes the miſhapen Prodigall ſo ſpruſe,
                     His year's Reue
                              •
                           ewes (I dare ſtand vnto't,)
                     Is not of worth to purchaſe ſuch a Sute.
                     
                     Tuſh! is it now to queſtion Gallantry,
                     
                     When No-land for a rich Gratuity,
                     
                     
                        
May Seale as deepe as can Auare's Heire,
                     That may diſpend fiue hundred a yeare?
                     When Tradeſmen take by whole ſale all they can,
                     Venting it out, on day, to any Man.
                     And then themſelues for Twelu-pence in the pound,
                     Will in the payment of the Debt be bound
                     And eſcape free by Breaking. This an age
                     To feare preferment? When a Raſcall Page
                     
                     An Abiect outſide ſhall preſume to Woe
                     Rich bruted (Caſhia:) and hope better too,
                     Then hee that of the Of-ſcums of his Braine,
                     
                     Can a man better then the (Vice) maintaine.
                     (Tut! 'tis the Mothers plot! Now ſhe ſhall ſee
                     The Court ſometimes! Oh Carnall Pollicy!)
                     
                  
                  
                     Then who in Studdy woo'd ſpend Time in vaine
                           •
                        
                     
                     Omit youth's pleaſures for a fruitleſſe paine?
                     Or for an Ayrie puffe of Enuy'd Praiſe,
                     
                     Liue bound to th' Good-behauiour all his dayes.
                     
                        
Hang't! Let's be Iouiall! Braue it whilft we can!
                     Whats Coyne ordain'd for, but the vſe of Man?
                     
                     To Borrow is a Vertue, when to Lend,
                     Is to beget an euerlaſting freind:
                     And may a man haue more ſaid in his grace,
                     Then to bee Credited in euery place?
                     Hee's not a Gentleman I dare maintaine,
                     Whoſe Word runnes nor as Current as his Coyne.
                     
                     A Pipe heere (Sirra) no Sophiſtocate.
                     
                     (Villain) the beſt: what ere you prize it at.
                     Tell yonder Lady, with the Yellow fan,
                     
                     I ſhall be proude to Vſher her anon:
                     My Coach ſtands ready. Lord how me thinkes I long!
                     To carue the inſide of a dry'd Neats-tong.
                     
                     
                        England cannot afford a kinder reliſh,
                     For Backragg, Deale, or your more pleaſing Re
                              •
                           iſh
                     
                     When ſhall we make a pleaſant cut to Douer,
                     
                     In a mad merry Humor? And ſend ouer?
                     
                        
A Laugh ſhall rouz the Hage: ſhake Leſbou walls:
                     
                     And raiſe in Armes the fearfull Portugalls.
                     
                     Say Gallants (faith) ſhall's neuer ſee the day,
                     When wee ſhall Fiſh-ſtreet once againe ſuruey.
                     A butterd Crab or Lobſters leg to get,
                     
                        O Venus! How a Life I ſauour it?
                     Who woo'd not all his Land ſpend had hee more,
                     Then in a day a Kite could hoouer ore.
                     T'inioy the pleaſant Harmony that wee
                     Finde in this Microcoſme, Man's ſocietie.
                     When all is gone, tis weakneſſe to diſpaire,
                     Are there not wealthy Widdowes eu'ry where.
                     Ambitious Sick, woo'd part from all their Good;
                     
                     To crowne their latter dayes with a French-hood?
                     
                     Are there not Pates, in ſtrange diſcoueries teaching
                     Wh
                           •
                        re mountains are of Gold? s'fut, tis but fetching!
                     Twenty ſuch Fe
                              •
                           ches hath the (Shar
                           •
                        e) to moue 
                           〈◊〉
                        
                     
                     Gallants of the firſt Head, but to approue
                     
                        
His ſwaggering Humor▪
                         vowes that all he ſpends,
                     He getteth brauely by his 
                           
                              •
                           ingers ends.
                     
                     There's not a Cheapſide Mercer (if he looke)
                     That will not ſweare to▪t deeply on his booke.
                     No note
                           •
                         
                        No ary in Cornwell row,
                     But is ſubſcribed Witneſſe there too.
                     Silkmen. Haberdaſhers▪ Tradeſm
                           •
                        n all:
                     
                     Inamor'd on him, for his Cuſtome call,
                     And he takes all of them But woe to him
                     If he bee taken but by one of Them.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        :W' Ant it for Women w
                           •
                        e ſhu'd all be men.
                     I cannot preſent better inſtance, then
                     In you Spruſe Coxcombe, yon Affecting Aſſe,
                     
                     That neuer walkes without his Looking-glaſſe,
                     
                     In a Tobacco box, or Diall ſet,
                     That he may priuately conferre with it.
                     
                        
How his Band jumpeth with his Peccadilly,
                     
                     Whether his Band ſtrings ballance equally:
                     Which way his Feather wagg's: And (to ſay truth)
                     What wordes in vtterance beſt become his mouth.
                     Oh! Hadſt thou yeſterday beheld the Valour
                     
                     I ſaw him exerciſing on his Taylour▪
                        
                     
                     How, out of meaſure, hee the R
                           •
                        ſcall beat,
                     Not fitting to his minde his Doublet.
                     Lord! how I laught to ſee the witleſſe Noddy,
                     Durſt not reply, he meant it to his Body.
                     
                     See Villain, Rogue! (And in he ſhrinks his breſt)
                     Oh Heauens! Too wide a handfull at the leaſt,
                     Straight it is Cut! And then proues (being try'd)
                     As much too little on the other ſide.
                     But what skil't! Hee'l haue an attractiue Lace,
                     
                     And Whalebone-bodyes, for the better grace.
                     Ad nit ſpare dyet, on no ſuſtnance feed,
                     But Oatmeale, Milke, and crums of Barly-bread.
                     
                     
                        
Vſe Exerciſe vntill at l
                           •
                        ſt hee fit:
                     (With much adoe) his Body vnto it.
                  
                  
                     Hee'l not approach a Tauerne, no nor drinke ye
                     To ſaue his life Hot-water, (wherefore thinke ye,)
                     For heating's Liuer! Which ſome may ſuppoſe
                     Scalding hote, by the Bubbles on his Noſe.
                     
                     Hee'l put vp any publique foule diſgrace,
                     Rather then hazzard cutting of his Face.
                     
                     If in his Element you'd haue the (F
                              •
                           ole!)
                     
                     Aske him when he came from the Dauncing-ſchool
                     
                     Whereas much Leather he doth dayly waſte
                     In the French Cringe, which Ieremy brought laſt.
                     And more, then C
                              ••
                           iat (I dare maintaine)
                     In going to the Alp
                              ••
                           
                         and backe againe.
                     Whereof, that all the world may notice take,
                     See! euery ſtep an H
                              •••
                           r hee doth make
                     That Ladyes, may denote him with their Fa
                              •
                           ,
                     
                     As he goes by, with a Lo: Hee's the man.
                     
                     
                        
IS't not a thing to bee admired at
                     That any man ſhould Sing himſelfe in debt.
                     Then who'd not giue as willingly a groate,
                     To heare (Fantaſticks) admirable note?
                     As ſee a Mandrake, or a Sea-monſter:
                     
                     Edwards blade: with the Tombes at Weſtminſter.
                     The Eagle at the Tower: St. Iames's Rarityes:
                     
                     The Eſtrich, or Beauer, that woo'd worrey Trees?
                     (Amorous Fantaſticke) that did neuer ayme at
                     A ſmaller Riſe, then Ela in the Gamat.
                     
                     That ne're conuerſed but with men of Note,
                     
                     Your Crotchet Pate, and your Organick Throat.
                     
                     Neuer Ambitious more then to be able,
                     But to attaine vnto a Chamber Treble.
                     
                     Wondrous proficient! See how the Gentlewomen
                     Throng to his Chamber doore, but dare not come in,
                     Why? leaſt he rauiſh them! Tuſh! Laugh ye not,
                     H'as done (I woſſe) as great exploites as that.
                     
                        
(Or elſe he cracks) the ſweetneſſe of his voyce
                     Ore-heard of Ladyes, hath procur'd him choyſe
                     Of Matches: Noble, Rich: but hee'l not meddle,
                     And why (I pray?) for cracking of his Treble.
                     
                     No! hee'l with better induſtry make tryall,
                     If hee can Match his Treble to the 
                           Ʋioll.
                     
                     Gainſt when, hee hath proclaim'd throughout the Citty,
                     To All your Witts, an Angell for a Ditty:
                     Faith! was he heere wee'd bargain for a Rime,
                     
                     And heere he comes. So truely he keepes Time.
                  
                  
                     BVt h'ſt! with him Crabbed (Webſterio)
                     
                     The Play-wright, Cart-wright: whether? either! ho-
                     No further. Looke as yee'd bee look't into:
                     Sit as ye woo'd be Read: Lord! who woo'd know him?
                     Was euer man ſo mangl'd with a Poem?
                     
                     See how he drawes his mouth awry of late,
                     
                        
How he ſcrubs: wrings his wreſts: ſcratches his Pate.
                     A Midwife! helpe! By his Braines coitus,
                     
                     Some Centaure ſtrange: ſome huge Bucephalus,
                     
                     Or Pallas (ſure) ingendred in his Braine,
                     
                     Strike Vulcan with thy hammer once againe.
                  
                  
                     This is the Crittick that (of all the reſt)
                     I'de not haue view mee, yet I feare him leaſt,
                     Heer's not a word curſiuely I haue Writ,
                     
                     But hee'l Induſtriouſly examine it.
                     And in ſome 12. monthes hence (or there about)
                     
                     Set in a ſhamefull ſheete, my errors out.
                     
                     But what care I it will be ſo obſcure,
                     That none ſhall vnderſtand him (I am ſure.)
                  
                  
                     Others may chance (that know me not a right,)
                     Report (iniuriouſly) all my delight,
                     And ſtrength of ſtuddy I doe wholly bend
                     
                        
To this Loſſe-labour and no other end.
                     To theſe I wiſh my ſcanda
                           •
                        d Muſe reply
                     In as plaine tearmes as may bee 'Tis a lye.
                     
                     
                        Heer's but Pate-paſtime: Play-houſe Obſeruation,
                     
                        Fruits of the vacants howers of a Vacation.
                     
                     Then (ſay all what they can) I am ſure of this,
                     That for Play-time it is not ſpent amiſſe.
                  
                  
                     
                        Semel inſaniuimus omnes.
                     
                     
                        Once wee haue all
                        Beene Iouiall.
                     
                  
                  FINIS
               
            
            
               
                  
                  To his worthy Friend, H. F. vpon his Notes from BLACK-FRYERS.
                  
                  
                     HAd the Black-Fryers beene ſtill vn-ſuppreſſd,
                     I cannot thinke their Cloyſters had bin bleſſd
                     With better contemplations: Seeing now
                     
                        
                           •
                        eſſe may be gleand from Puritanes then you
                     Haue gathered from the Play-houſe. And I muſt
                     (Though't bee a Players vice to be vniuſt,
                     To Verſe not yeelding coyne) let Players know
                     They cannot recompence your labour: Though
                     They grace you with a Chayre vpon the Stage,
                     And take no money of you nor your Page.
                     
                        
                           •
                        or now the Humours which oppreſſe Playes moſt,
                     
                        
                           •
                        hall (if the owners can feele ſhame) be loſt:
                     And when they ſo conuerted doe allow,
                     What they diſlik'd once, Players muſt thanke you,
                     
                        
And Poets too: for both of them will ſaue
                     Much in true Verſe, which hiſſes might depraue:
                     Since you haue ſo refin'd their Audience,
                     That now good Playes will neuer neede defence.
                  
                  IO: STEPHENS
               
               
                  
                  Epilogue.
                  The Author for Himſelfe.
                  
                     
                        J Am no Poet! (yet I doe not know
                     Why I ſhould not: or why I ſhould be ſo.)
                     I can (I muſt confeſſe) a Metre ſcan:
                     And Iudge of Verſes as an other man.
                     I haue been Trayn'd vp'mongſt the Muſes: (more!)
                     The ſacred Name of Phaebus I adore.
                     
                        
Yet I no Poet am! (I'de haue ye know)
                     
                        I am no Poet (as the world goes now.)
                     : My Muſe cannot a Note ſo poorly frame,
                     : As Inuocate a Penny-Patrons name.
                     : I cannot ſpeake and vnſpeake (as I liſt:)
                     : Exchange a ſound friend for a broken Ieſt:
                     : Conferre with Fountaines: or conuerſe with Tree▪
                        
                     
                     : Admit in my diſcourſe Hyperbolyes.
                     
                     
                        
I cannot highly praiſe Thoſe higheſt are
                     Becauſe they ſit in Honours l
                           ••
                        ty chayre.
                     
                        
                           •
                        or make their States in S
                              ••••
                           ts happy knowne,
                     Being (perchan
                           •
                        e) leſſe happy then mine owne.
                     I cannot ſing my Miſtris ſhee is Faire:
                     
                     T
                           •
                        ll her of her Lilly Hand▪
                         her golden 
                           〈◊〉
                        ,
                     Fetch a Compariſon (beyond the Mo
                              •••
                           ,)
                     
                     To proue her conſtant in A
                              •••
                           ction.
                     
                     
                        
: I dare not Her ſo much as Louely call:
                     : Or ſay I haue a Mistris at all.
                     : Why? Ere too morrow, ſhe will changed bee:
                     : And leaue me laught at for my Poetry.
                     
                     Had I of Scoggins Crowes writ: or ſet out
                     In Womans Praiſes what I was about.
                     I am perſwaded (yet I cannot tell)
                     I had a Poet prou'd againſt my will.
                     
                        
                        
                           •
                        et (ye vnproued good) blame not becauſe
                     yet as (doubtfull on your merits) pauſe.
                     will produce and Patronize it too:
                     
                        
                           •
                        inde I but one amongſt ſo many true.
                     
                        
                           •
                        ut Faine I cannot, heere is not a word,
                     Which I dare not maintaine true with my ſword.
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           oets men Lyers call. If ſo! Then (know it)
                     
                        
                           •
                        ee is a Poet, doth mee call a Poet.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                  Poſt-ſcript to his Book-binder.
                  
                     
                        STationer) A Good turn
                              •
                           
                         to thee I owe:
                     Heere! I will pay thee no
                           •
                         in Folio.
                     
                     But ſtay! Not ſoe: that I woo'd haue thee put
                     Mee in the Folio: or the Q
                              •
                           art
                              •
                            e
                              •
                           t.
                     
                     Rather con
                           •
                        riue mee to the Smalleſt 
                              〈◊〉
                           ,
                     
                     Lea
                           ••
                         I bee eaten vnder Pippin-pyes.
                     
                     Or in th' Apothicaryes ſhop bee ſeen
                           •
                        
                     
                     To wrap Drugg's: or to dry Tobacco in.
                     Firſt (might I chu
                           •
                        e) I would be bound to w
                           •
                        pe▪
                     
                     Where he diſcharged laſt his Gliſter-pipe.
                     
                     
                        
The Character I care not, Great, or Small,
                     
                     So I bee plainly vnderſtood of all.
                     Onely preſerue mee from the ſight of Thoſe,
                     
                     That cannot but muſt Read me in the Noſe.
                     
                     Then care to caſt mee: not ith' Learned Roe,
                     
                     Leaſt I the Learned c
                           •
                        nſure vndergoe.
                     Not lay me with ſcald Poets leaſt I titch,
                     And ſo become infected with Their itch.
                     Let not each Peſant, each Mecannick Aſſe,
                     
                     That neer knew further then his Horn-booke croſſe.
                     Each rauin-Ruſtick
                              •
                           : each illiterate Gull:
                     
                     Buy of my Poeſie, by pocket full.
                     Booke-like made-D
                              •
                           ſhes may for Daintyes goe,
                     Yet will not euery pall
                              •••
                           
                         taſte 'em ſo:
                     
                        
Then were it good, I ſhould inioyne the Sell.
                     
                     Mee vnto none but thoſe that loue me well.
                  
                  
                     If any Puff-paſte, Bumbaſte Iobernole,
                     
                     Wrapt in the Hangings of a Brokers-ſtall.
                     
                     A halfe-Noſe: or a Carbonado'd face:
                     Of a ſuſpitious ſubtill Serpents pace.
                     Truſt to a Basket-hilt: chances to drop.
                     But for a Reſting-roome into thy ſhop.
                     And catches in his fatall hand my Rime.
                     
                     To lurke in it, vntill hee ſee his Time.
                     
                     Thruſt him out head-long, for (beleiue him not)
                     Now (by the Mace) itis a Counter-plot.
                  
                  
                     If thou behold a Courtca
                           •
                        t Satten-ſhow,
                     Fallen from the Fa
                           •
                        hion a Degree or two.
                     
                        
                        One as goes purueying vp and downe for Tales,
                     
                     To Ieſt 
                           •
                        is 
                           •
                        ungry ſtomacke into meales.
                     
                     That with a m
                           •
                        rry pocket▪ 
                        Pamp
                              •
                           let will,
                     For a weeke after Laugh his Be
                              ••
                           y full.
                     
                     Send him to Sojourne with Duke Humfrey,
                     
                     Let him ſtarue ere hee g
                           ••
                         a bit
                           •
                         of mee▪
                     
                     Leaſt lying (Read) neglected in his Slop▪
                        
                     
                     I bee conueyed vnto the Brokers-ſhop.
                     Or by his theeui
                           •
                        h Page diſcouered:
                     Quickly conuerred into Gi
                              •
                           g
                              •
                           r-bread▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     If any Younger Brother▪
                         that noe more
                     Hath then a Daggle▪tayl'd She
                              •
                           p-skin kept in ſtore▪
                     
                     Whoſe An
                           ••
                        all 
                           •
                        leec
                           •
                         will but bare me
                           •
                        nes afford,
                     And with the Echer of 
                           •
                        i
                           •
                         Brothers bord.
                     
                        
That ſits a Ledger at his Fathers Table:
                     My Booke woo'
                           •
                         
                        
                           •
                        oudly purchaſe: (hardly able,)
                     To win, the preſence by the 
                           ••
                        ers ſide,
                     Of Mrs. Sis, or Sue the Dary-maide.
                     Or chooke the Ruſticke Leather-lobs with laughter▪
                     
                     Bid him goe ſtuddy how to liue hereafter:
                     Read where mor
                           •
                         
                        
                           •
                        ollid ſubſtance hee may get
                     To Liue vpon, or learne to goe in Debt.
                     
                  
                  
                     Ye, ye, Braue Gallants: Patrons of liuely mirth:
                     Ye, the young hopefull Land-Lords of the Earth:
                     The youth of youth! That read moſt libe
                           •
                        ally,
                     More out of 
                           〈◊〉
                         then nec
                              ••••
                           ty.
                     
                     Y
                           •
                        e worthy Worthyes! Non
                           •
                         elſs (
                           •
                        ight I chuſ
                           •
                        )
                     Doe I deſire my 
                           〈◊〉
                         p
                           •
                        ruſe▪
                     
                     
                        
For to ſaue charges: ere the Playes begin:
                     Or when the Lord of Libertie comes in.
                     And if a Booke muſt needs a Patron haue,
                     Yours is the onely Patronage I craue.
                     Others I wiſh the Stationer fore-warne▪
                     
                     
                        With a Hand's off: It is not for your turne▪
                     
                  
                  FINIS.
               
               
                  
                  Errors in the Printing.
                  
                     
                        
                           Ye pro your, Folio 2.
                           
                              Saty: 1.
                        
                        
                           Rome for halfe, pro Rome for ſome halfe:
                        
                        
                           Eare-word, pro Er'e-word.
                        
                        
                           Non pro not.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           Demoritus pro Democritus▪
                           
                           
                              Saty: 2.
                        
                        
                           So pro too.
                        
                        
                           Scoue pro Sconce.
                        
                        
                           Longey pro Congey.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Whoſ't pro whoſe. Ep
                              •
                           g. 54.
                     
                        L
                              •
                           ec
                              •
                           
                         pro C
                              •
                           ec
                              •
                           . in aliquibus. Ep
                              •
                           g. 55.
                  
                  
                     Puts pro Pull's. Lib: 3. page 6.
                     Yee pro you.
                  
               
            
         
      
   

