
   
      
         
            A godly sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 31. day of October 1591. By VVilliam Fisher, Master and keeper of the hospitall of Ilford in Essex. ... Seene and allowed
            Fisher, William, student of diuinitie.
         
         
            
               1592
            
         
         Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00800
            STC 10919
            ESTC S117556
            99852769
            99852769
            18112
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00800)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18112)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 507:09)
         
         
            
               
                  A godly sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 31. day of October 1591. By VVilliam Fisher, Master and keeper of the hospitall of Ilford in Essex. ... Seene and allowed
                  Fisher, William, student of diuinitie.
               
               [64] p.   
               
                  By Edward Allde for Edward Aggas,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1592.
               
               
                  A sermon. On Mal. iii. 16-17.
                  Signatures: A-D.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-05
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2007-05
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            A GODLY SERMON preached at Paules Croſſe the 31. day of October 1591.
            By VVilliam Fisher, Maſter and Keeper of the Hoſpitall of Ilford in Eſsex.
            
            
               Prouerbs. 22. verſe. 3.
A wiſe man foreſeeth the plague, and hideth him ſelfe: But the fooliſh runne on ſtill, and are puniſhed.
            Seene and allowed.
            
            ¶ Imprinted at London 
                  〈◊〉
                
               Edward Allde, for Edward Agg
                     •…
                   
                  
                     ••
                  92.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               Malachi 3. verſe 16, 17.
               16 Then ſpake they that feared the Lord, euery one to his Neighbour, and the Lord hearkned and heard it, and a booke of Remembrance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord, and thought vpon his name.
               17 And they ſhall be to me ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in that day that I ſhal do this, for a flock, and I will ſpare them, as a man ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerueth him.
            
            
               THis Scripture was denounced by that Prophet whome the Lord ſent to giue a farewell to his people, for Malachi was the laſt Prophet in Iſraell, and after him there was noe moe, vntill Iohn Baptiſte came. It is thought of ſome, that the Lord in his wrath, and in a iuſte Judgement againſt Iſraell, would not vouchſafe them any moe Prophetes after Malachi, either to 
                  〈…〉
               
               
forte them in their diſtreſſes, or to call vppon them for the amendment of their liues. But of other ſome, it is ſuppoſed, that there was not ſo great a miſery ment againſt them, as a miſterye for their good, which was this, that they ſhould the more inſtantly and feruentlye looke for &amp; longe after the King of Prophetes, Jeſus Chriſt him ſelf. But howſoeuer it was, of this I am well aſſured, Malachi performed his function, ſo fully and ſo faithfully, that he was reputed generallye to haue béene an Angell ſent downe from Heauen, rather then a man borne and bred vpon the earth. Not ſo muche becauſe Malachi doth ſignifie an Angel, as that his doctrine did ſhowe an Angellike ſpirite, and did woork an Angellike effect.
            
               Gregorye 1. being Biſhop of Rome, when he ſawe certaine Engliſh children brought thether to be ſolde, aſked of what countrey they were, it was anſwered Angli. Engliſhe children, where vpon the alluded thus, Immo Angeli qui vultu nitent vt Angeli, Nay rather they are Angelles, for that in countenaunee they ſhine, and ſhew them ſelues to be Angels.
            So we may ſay of Malachi he was no queſtion a mā, and his name being Malachi, &amp; not Malach doth importe no leſſe by the termination therof. And Epiphanius by good proofe, 
                  ••
               es warrantiſe thereof: yet looke we vpon

the perfourmance of his office &amp; function, and then we ſhall finde that non ſolum vultu▪ ſedctiam ſpiritu nitet vt Angelus, not onely in countenaunce, but alſo in ſpirite, he doth ſhine lyke an Angell. For therein he bewrayed an Angellike parte, farre paſſing humane operation. otherwiſe he would neuer haue wrought ſuch a ſudden and ſtraunge conuerſion in ſuche a ſenſeles and generall corruption, wherin both Prieſt and Prophet were far from all ſignes of grace, and not neare any hope of remorſe. But ſicut populus ſic Sacerdos, Imo ſicut populus, ſic Sacerdos, as the people were, ſo were the prieſts.
            For the prieſt, they diſpiſed the name of the Lord, and yet they ſaid wherein haue we deſpiſed thy name. ver. 6. Chap. 1. They offered vncleane bread vpō the Alter of the Lord, and yet they ſaid, wherein haue we polluted it? Verſe. 7. Chapter. 1. they ſacrificed the corrupt, the blinde, the lame, the ſick, ſuch as they durſt not preſent to a mortall Prince, yet they thoght thē good enough for the Lord of Hoſtes who is a great King. ver. 14. chap. 1. They were out of the way, they cauſed many to fall by the lawe, they brake the couenant of Leui, ver. 8. chap. 2. They defiled the holynes of the Lord, and maried the daughters of a ſtraunge God, ver. 11. chap. 2. To be ſhorte they ſaid

that euerye one that dooth euill, is good in the ſight of the Lord, and he deliteth in them. ver. 17. chap. 2.
            
            And nowe for the people, did not the Lorde himſelfe charge &amp; accuſe them, that they were ſoothſayers, adulterers, falſe ſwearers, detainers of the hirelings wages, oppreſſours of the widowes and the fatherles, ver. 5. chap. 3. ſuch Atheiſts that they ſaid, it is in vaine to ſerue God. ver. 14. chap. 3. Such Mammoniſtes that they would néeds know what profit they ſhould haue by kéeping his Commandements ver. 14. ibi. And ſuch rakehels, that they counted the proude, bleſſed: and the tempters of God worthy to be aduaunced. ver. 15. chap. 3.
            
            In which ripenes and outragiouſnes of their ſins, Malachi was preſentlye ſent to denounce Gods heauy Judgements, and Indignation againſt them, which hee ſo throughlye executed, that thereby he not only ripped vp &amp; ranſackt their cōſciences, but alſo perſed their ſoules, and deuided their ſpirites, with the two edged ſworde, which came out of his mouth, in ſomuch that they ſpake &amp;c.
            Now in this ſcripture we haue chéefelye to note two points.
            1 A bleſſed conference, and mutual prouocation of the people, for the amendement of their lyues. Then ſpake they. &amp;c.
            
            
               Secondly, a thréefolde comforte and encouragement which the Lorde gaue them, to procede in their Repentance. 1. Becauſe he hearkened and heard them. 2. For that he cauſed a booke of Remebrance to be writen &amp;c.
            3. Becauſe hee gaue them the promiſe of his merciſull protection, And they ſhall be to me in the day &amp;c.
            
            
               1. Pars.
               
                  THen ſpake they which feared the Lorde, &amp;c. So mightie and effectuall were the Prophets woords, in the heartes of as manye as feared the Lord, that by and by thereupon, they conferred about the reformation of their lyues, and ſpoke euery one to his Neighbour, (as by the circumſtance we gather) to this effect. Deare Neighbours we haue often and deſperatly prouoked the Lords wrath againſt vs, and needes muſt wée grant our ſelues guilty of all the crimes whereof Malachi doth accuſe vs. What ſhall we doo then? We are now called to repentance. both by the voice of Gods vengeance, ſaying, I will come now to you in Iudgement, and I wil be a iuſt witnes againſt you. ver. 5. chap. 3. and alſo by the voice of his mercy: ſaying, Returne to me, and I will returne to you. ver. 7. chap. 3. All this notwithſtanding

ſhall wee ſtill runne on with remorſe? Why then the wrathe of God, muſt néedes come vpon the children of diſobedience. Therefore let vs humble our ſelues vpon the loweſt pauement of vnfained repentaunce, that it may repent him of his purpoſed vengeaunce. To this end and in this ſenſe, they ſpake euerye one to another.
               Whereby (right Honorable, and dearelye beloued) wee may ſ
                     •
                  e and obſerue, not onelye that the feare of the Lord is a wel-ſpring of life, to auoid the ſnares of death, for ſo ſaith the wiſe man, Pro. 14. But alſo that y• word of God is ſharper then any two edged ſwoorde, and pearceth, &amp; cutteth, whereſoeuer it commeth, euen to the hard bones and marrow, for ſo ſaith the Apoſtle Hebrewes. 4. And therfore ſo it preuailed with this people, that it wrought in them a reſolute conference for their conuerſion, and bettering of their conuerſations.
               And ſo it preuailed with Ioſias and his people: for at the reading of the booke of the law by Shaphan, there was renting of cloathes, and melting of harts, and ſhedding of teares, in all humility, 2. King. 22.
               
               And ſo it preuailed with the King of Niniuie, and his People, for at the preaching of Ionas, there was proclaming of faſtes, and putting

on of ſackcloath, and ſitting downe in aſhes, and crying mightilye vnto God, from the greateſt to the leaſt: Iohn. 3. And ſo it preuailed with the Iſraelites, at the preaching of Eſay, for they letted not to inuite one another ſaying: Come ye houſe of Iacob, let vs walk in the light of the Lord, Eſay. 2. And ſo it preuailed with the people which heard Peters heauenly ſermon: for they were thereby euen pricked in their hartes▪ and ſaid, men and brethren what ſhall we do? Act. 2.
               
               But I do not ſée beloued in the Lorde, that it hath ſo preuailed with vs, and yet how mightilythe Lord hath called vpon vs, both Judgelike, &amp; Fatherlike in puniſhing, and in fauours, I knowe &amp; you can not be ignorant.
               Haue not the mountaines trembled, &amp; the foundatiōs of ye earth béen ſhakē in your daies Haue not bloodthirſtye conſpirators ſwarmed like graſhoppers, here at home in our own boſomes? Haue not the furious executioners of Gods vengeance couered our ſeas, with their ſhips, and attempted to inuade vs? Haue not the meſſengers of the Lord: lyke ſo many trū
                  pets ſounded daily in your eares, that tribulation &amp; anguiſh, wéeping &amp; gnaſhing of téeth, vnquenchable fire, vtter darknes, the worme y• neuer dieth, euen the portion of hypocrites, is prepared for all hard harted &amp; ſtifnecked ſinners:

ſurely euē theſe wer the voices of Gods vengeance, and in euerye one of them hee hath ſaid, I will come nere to England in Judgement, and will be a ſwift witnes againſt you.
               And on the otherſide, wherhence is it, that we haue receiued ſuch gratious gouernment, for ſuch bloudy tyrannies: ſuch ſunſhine of the Goſpell, for ſuch darkenes of Idolatrie: ſuch dayly preaching for ſuche damnable Maſſing: ſuch plenty for ſuch ſcarſety, ſuch peace for ſuch warre: ſuch health for ſuch ſicknes, ſuch fatherly bleſſings, for ſuch Pharaolik perſecutiōs, as is meruellous in our eyes, &amp; manifeſt to al the worlde: As this is the Lords doings, and in euery one of theſe, his good graces he hath engrauen the voice of his mercy: ſaying Returne to me, and I will returne to you?
               
               But I knowe not how, we make no more account thereof, then of a blaſt of winde, naye as there was neuer that good or grace wroght to reclame theſe Iſraelites, but the Lord hath vouchſafed the like or greater to vs. So what euill was there committed by them in Malachies time, but it is doubled and tripled by vs in theſe daies? and that in ſuch meaſure, both in Prieſt and People, beginne where you will, that it can not but irk our harts to think of it, alas then why ſhould it not vrdge our tongues to ſpeake againſt it, as the Iſraelites
                  
did, euery man to his Neighbour?
               For firſt, as their Prieſtes polluted the Altar of the Lord in manye a foule abuſe, ſo doo we, I may not conceale it, cure it as I maye. For ſome of vs are idle bellies, &amp; do the worke of the Lord negligentlye, for wee labour not, but loyter in the Lordes Vineyard: &amp; what is this, but with the Prieſtes of Iſraell to offer vncleane bread, and to preſent our worſt gifts and to ſacrifice the halt and maimed vnto him who is a great King.
               Some of vs are men pleaſers, and ſuch placebos, that we laye pillowes vnder the eares, and cuſhins vnder the elbowes of ſinners, and what is this, but to ſay with the Prieſtes of 
                     
                        •
                     uda, that euery one that doth euill, is good in the ſight of the Lord? Some of vs are brainſicke and fantaſticall, and euen like Narciſſus, are not only in loue with our owne ſhadows, but wedded to our owne peſtilent conceits? ſo that no reaſon can perſwade vs, or aſwage them: and what is this but with the tribe of Leui, to marry with y• daughters of a ſtrange God.
               Some of vs are bitter &amp; contentious, making ruptures in the Church, our tender mother, like ſo many vipers, deuouring one another, more like wolues then ſhéepherdes: and deuiding the vnſemed coate of Chriſtian vnity,

not vnlyke arrant théeues, &amp; what is this, but the miſerye whereof Baſile complaineth, Hoc omnium miſeratione, vel maxime dignum eſt, cum ea pars quae ſana viſa eſt, in ſe deuiſa eſt: This is a moſt lamentable thing, when that parte which ſéemeth to be ſound, is deuided in it ſelfe. And the miſery whereof Lactantius complaineth, Gladium quiſque habet, quo hoſtem feriat, ſed nemo clypeum, quo ſedefendat, euery one hath a ſwoorde whereby he may ſtrike his enemie, but no man hath a ſhéelde whereby he may defend him ſelfe. And the miſery whereof Barnard complaineth, Omnes amici, &amp; omnes inimici: omnes neceſsarij, &amp; omnes aduerſarii: omnes domeſtici, &amp; nulli pacifici: All are friendes▪ and all are enemyes: all are neighbours, and all are aduerſaries: all are home-dwellers, and none are peace-makers.
               Now then (beloued in the Lord) is it poſſible for vs of the miniſterie to finde and know theſe euils in our ſelues, and yet to bée mute and ſilent? ſurely theſe outrages are able to make him ſpeake that is not wilfully tonguefyed. Atys, Craeſus ſonne was dumbe, &amp; neuer ſpake in al his life (as Herodotus reports) &amp; yet when he ſaw Cyrus about to cutte his fathers throat, he burſt out into theſe ſpéeches, &amp; ſaide, O homo ne interficias patrem, O man kill not my father.
                   Wee ſee what wée ſée, and I do not ſee,

how wee can ſay leſſe to them which intreate our ſpirituall and Ghoſtly Fathers as they doe, that is, euen cut the throate of their honorable reputation through ſpitefull ſlaunder, of their goodlye reuenewes through priuate lucre, and of their lawfull authoritie through proud inſolencie: I doe not ſee I ſay how wee can ſay leſſe than this: O homo ne interficias patrem, O man kill not my father.
                  
               
               Thus then is the Altar of the Lord at this day in the Church of England polluted in many a foule abuſe by vs of the miniſterie, and therefore great cauſe there is to lay our heads and hearts together, and to lay aſide all bitterneſſe and curſed ſpeaking one agaynſt another, and to ſpeake euery man vnto his neighbour, as Iſrael did, for repentance, and againſt ſinne.
               But now let vs leaue the Altar of the Lord, &amp; come Ad Atria where the people vſe to ſtand: Alas if ſuch iniquitie dwell in the middeſt of the Sanctuarie, and amongſt the Prieſts, what maruaile is it, if it be farre worſe in the ſtreetes, and among the people? Surely beloued in the Lord, you haue not done wel, &amp; your ſin lyeth before the doore, as well as ours: you haue plowed wickednes, and how ſhoulde you but reape the rewarde of iniquitie? For what curſed thing is there, but you haue reached

your hands vnto it, and delighted your hearts in it, as wel, nay ill as Iſrael? Is it ſorcerie? Is it adulterie? Is it falſeſwearing? Alas if ther were no other ſorcerie, but the ſubtill inchaunting of their circumuenting tongues, it were too much: for thereby as with the ſin of witchcraft, you abuſe the wiſe, and defraud the ſimple, yea thereby you reape as much profite as by patrimony or frée-land: &amp; the bread of ſuch deceit is the ſweeteſt morſel that commeth into ſome of your mealy mouthes. And then for Adulterie, it is the diſeaſe that cleaueth faſt to your bones, and lyeth feſtring in your bowels, and hath rooted it ſelfe betwéene your breſtes: inſomuch that the father defloureth a woman, and to make her amendes marrieth her to hys owne ſonne, Amos. 2. 7. And ſo may I ſay of periury: For affection, malice, feare, and lucre, doe at wil ſuppreſſe and ſmother all truth, and ſupplye and ſuggeſte all falſhoode, when you come to ſpeake vppon your oathe. And I doe not ſee, to what end there ſhould be anie, either admiſſion or tolleration of them whom you call knights of the Poſt, and ſurely not amiſſe, for it is thought they haue no more conſcience what they ſweare many times, than a verye poſte, and I pray God that ſuche Poſts 
                     ••
                   poſt to pleaſure men with their falſe oathes haue not firebrands another day in hell: for

burning, is a fit end for all ſuch rotten blaſphemous Poſtes.
               And the damnable wretchednes of our time wherein is it not ſutable with the wickednes of Iſraell? Neuer pride more diſdainfull, neuer ambition more preſumpteous, neuer couetouſnes more inſatiable.
               For there are ſome ſuche merciles oppreſſours among you, that build fair houſes, with the bloody ſobs and ſighs of their poore neighbours, whoſe liuinges they haue taken ouer their heads, and whoſe liuelyhoode, they haue wringed out of their hands.
               There are ſome ſuche deuouring Vſurers among you, that purchaſe ſtatelye manners, and ſell the poore for olde ſhooes, to make vppe their ſommes, and euē ſtrip the ſkinnes of the needy ouer head &amp; eares, to fit their purpoſes.
               There are ſome ſuche pilling extorſioners, that if it were poſſible they could finde in their hartes with Flauius Veſpaſianus, vectigall ex vrina capere.
               
               There are ſome ſuch infatiable and intollerable Church leaches, or rather ſponges, that ſuck and ſoaken vp, both the bloode of the Mother, and the milke of the children, yea with Achilles, they can finde in their heartes, to ſet on ſale the dead bodye of Hector, 
                  
                     •
                  ay rather the deare bought ſoules of Gods ſaints. They

are not aſhamed with Cirus in hope of gaine to dig vp the very graues of the dead▪ nor with Dioniſius to deface the moſt auncient▪ &amp; goodly monumentes that are, nor with Iulian to ranſacke churches, colleges, hoſpitall &amp; hoſpitals? yea hoſpitality, to the vtter ruine, and wrack of all Religion, learning, and chriſtian reléefe.
               To be ſhorte, there are ſome, and the moſt parte of you al grown to ſuch curſed Atheiſme and infidelity with theſe Iſraelites, that no Religion hath any reliſh in your heartes, but that which ſauoureth of gaine to your purſes.
               And albeit your tongues be mute &amp; ſilent for very ſhame, yet your deeds ſpeak without ſound of woorde, &amp; ſay with this People, It is in vaine to ſerue God▪ &amp; what profit is it, that we haue kept his commandement, &amp; that we haue walked humblie before the Lord of Hoſtes.
               
               O ſtrange infidelity, the roote and branches of all miſery, alas how hath this helliſh bramble ouergrowne and ouerſpread the Lordes vyneyarde here in England? O the plague of all plagues, our vnbeleeuing hartes, this makes you that ye will not be warned, but do as you do, or rather that you care not what you do, this hath made you more incredulus then the diuils in hell, Qui credunt et contremiſcun
                        •
                     , which beleue and tremble. And by reaſon

hereof, are you not at this point? If a méere ſtranger, or a common lier, or a ſtarke Idiote, ſhould but bring you tydings that you and all other magiſtrates, you and all other lawyers, you and al other marchants, you and al other riche men, you and all other Artificers, you and all other Huſbandmē, are what? in a flat praemunire, you woulde then looke about you, and lay your heads together, and ſpeake euery one to his Neighbour, and finding it true, would neuer eat meat that ſhould do you good nor take any good nights reſt, vntill you had found meanes to obtaine your pardon, and were quite out of daunger,
               Heereby then maye you meaſure the miſthiefe of infidelitye, for all our preaching &amp; teaching (as verye fooles and Idiotes as you accompt vs) is to no other end, but to tell you, and giue you notice of a dangerous and a moſt dānable praemunire whereinto you are fallen, all the ſorte of you, yea euery mothers ſonne▪ thorowe your deſperate and rebellious ſinnes againſt the almighty, and yet you do not once offer to ſue for your pardon, or to ſéeke for mercye at his hands, whoſe Maieſtye you haue ſo highly offended.
               Now then beloued in the Lord (al this conſidered) is it not hye tyme, or rather more then time for vs to growe to ſuch a gratious conference

as Iſraell did, for the amendement of all that is amiſſe? The wiſe man ſeing the plague comming, hideth him ſelfe: but the foole goeth on forward, and is ſnared, Pro. 22. Let vs be wiſe now at the length, and learne to hyde our ſelues in tyme vnder the ſackcloath, and in the aſhes of repentaunce. Let vs diſcharge that duety which the Apoſtle requireth Heb. 3 which is to exhorte one another, and to edifie one another, whiles it is called to day. Let vs be aduiſed by Saint Iude, euen to edifie our ſelues in our moſte holy faith, knowing this, for an aſſured trueth, that they which turne many to righteouſnes, ſhall ſhine as the ſtars for euer. Daniel. 12. 3. And that he that conuerteth a ſinner from going aſtray, ſhall ſaué a ſoule from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſinnes. Iames. 5. ver. 20. This duety therefore as we owe one to another, and euery mā to his Neighbour, ſo the Lord make vs carefull to performe it, that we may be partakers with Iſraell, of ſuch grace and fauour as doeth belong vnto it.
            
            
               Pars. 2.
               
                  ANd the Lord hearkned and heard it &amp;
                        •
                     . Here you are to conſider, of a thréefolde

comforte and encouragement, which they receiued from the Lord. Whereof this is the firſt, becauſe he vouchſafed to heare them. A maruellous grace, they no ſooner began to repent, but the Lord gaue eare and heard them: Who would not frame him ſelfe to the lyke conference, and penitent conformity? No no, dearely beloued, our God is not like to Baall, he can heare you be ſure, for as Hillary ſayeth, Qui naturam audiendi humano generi impertit, ipſe extra auditus non poteſt eſſe naturam. He that made the eare, can heare, and he can anſweare you aſwel by fire from Heauen, as euer he did Firſt, by ſending down the holy Ghoſt to comfort you. There is not the ſofteſt miſereri which you breath out of your mouthes, nor the leaſt penitent thought in your heartes, but it is in his eares like the ſhirleſt noiſe of a trumpet.
               For he is non vocis, ſed cordis auditor, not the hearer of the voice onelye, but of the heart to. And he can heare before men ſpeak, for he ſaid to Moyſes, quid clamas ad me?
                   why cryeſt thou to mée? And yet he ſpake not a worde, only he ſighed and groned. Exod. 14. No more did Anna, when the tears came down her chéeks, and her lippes were ſéene to moue, her voyce was not heard. 1. Sam. 1. Loquebatur non voce, ſed corde: praece occulta, ſed manifeſt a fide,
                   ſaith Ciprian.
               
               
                  Shée ſpake not with her voice, but with her harte: her prayer was hid, but her faith was manifeſt: heereby then ye may be bolde that the Lord is neare to all them that call vppon him, I meane faithfully.
               There is one kinde of voice which the Lord will not heare: But there are thrée kinde of voices, which he is moſt forward to hear, and I beſéech you let vs conſider of it, &amp; you which are the Gods of the earth, I meane Judges, and Maieſtrats, haue regarde and care to ſeaſon and temper your eares thereafter, for hee is the beſt Juſticer, and you can not better his preſident.
               That one voice, which the Lord will not heare, is theirs which contemne his word and deſpiſe their owne ſaluation, as al wilfull and malicious ſinners. And this very Judgement is laid downe expreſlye againſt them, by the Prophet, though they cry vnto me, yet I wil not heare them, Ier. 11. and the Iſraelites felt the miſery of it. Deut. 1. and ſo did Dauids enemies, for they cryed out for aide, and were not heard, 2. Sam. 22. and it was ment of ſuch miſcreants, where it is ſaid, that God heareth not ſinners. I0. 9. Therefore iudge you what a meruellous peuiſhnes it is, yea worſe then madnes it ſelfe, to deſire to wax oulde in ſinne, and to cary it to the graues, and to ſay

you will repent at your laſt end: for it is a memorandum to man, that ſin wil bring the Lord ſo farre out of conceit with you, that hee will not heare you.
               And now the thrée voices which the Lord, will heare, and that both willingly &amp; ſpéedely, are theſe. Firſt the voice of innocent blood, and he doeth ſo hear it, that it is alwayes to their coſt which ſhed it: for ſtill it beggeth vengeance at Gods hands, and is therein ſo importunate, as that ſame poore widowe which followed the vnrighteous Judge, &amp; woulde haue no naye, but ſtill cryed Reuenge me on my aduerſary, Luke. 18. or it is lyke that ſame ſorrowfull womā of Canaan which followed our Sauiour Chriſte, crauing the health of her daughter ſo inſtantly, that the diſciples ſaid, Demitte eā quia clamat poſt nos, Diſmiſſe her for ſhe crieth after vs, Mat. 15. Did not the Lord tell Caine, that the voice of his brothers bloode cryed vnto him from the earth? and what a fearefull Judgement had he? Gen. 4. And the bloode of all the Prieſts whome Saul ſlew ſo butcherlike for affecting Dauid, neuer ceaſt crying out for due vengeance, vntill Saul with his owne hands, ſheathed his owne ſworde in his owne bowels, 1. Sam. 31. And what an outcrye made▪ the innocent bloode of Naboth, ſhedde by the practiſe of Iezabel, and was not

her rewarde thereafter? when her pride had a fall, her necke was broken, and the dogges deuoured her fleſh &amp; gnawed her bones. 2. Kin. 9. The innocencie of Zachary the preiſt (murthered by Ioas King of Iuda) cryed ſo loud for vengeance, that the Lord brought the Kings own blood vpon his owne head, and ſuffred his own ſeruauntes to cutte him off in his neſte, 2. Kings▪ 12.
               
               And heere-hence it is, that you ſhall neuer lightly ſée a murtherer proſper or thriue vpon the earth: no, albeit the parties be agréed withall, albeit the Princes pardon be obtained, and euery thing be thorowlye ſalued: and why? becauſe the Lord heareth the voice and reuengeth the villanye of innocent bloodſhedding.
               Beware then you deſperate ympes, how ye ſéeke by blood to reuenge your drunken quarrelles: and take héede yée cunning deep wittes how with falſe accuſation and ſubtill packing, you ly in waite to eaſe your dogged ſtomacks, by ſhedding your neighbours blood. And you (right Honourable) which are deputies and ſubſtitutes to our dread Soueraigne, Gods Leiuetenant here in England, be wiſe, and let no interceſſion of fréendes, no corruptions of bribes, no affection of parties, ſtop your eares or make you deafe, when the cauſes of blood

are in queſtion before you, for the crye thereof will then be as lowde againſt you for acceſſaries, as againſt the very actors, for principalls: and all the water in Pilats Baſon ſhall not waſhe away Gods vengeaunce from you and yours.
               An other voice which the Lord will heare and that very quickely, is the crye of the poore or oppreſſed, be they widowes or fatherles, be they fréendles or ſuccourles: And this is apparant by his owne promiſe. Exod. 22. If thou vexe or trouble any ſuch, that is, widowe or fatherles childe, and ſo he call and cry vnto me, I wil ſurely heare his cry. ſo ſaieth Eccle. 38. he heareth the prayer of the opreſſed. And marke it when you will, the teares of the widowe runne not ſo faſt downe her chéekes, but they ariſe vp as faſt into Heauen: and the Lord which heareth them, in due time pittieth them.
               So that our mercifull God is not like thoſe Lacedemonian Ephori, certaine retchleſſe magiſtrates, which heard mens peticions they cared not how, belike with their harueſt eares. Nor to that careleſſe Emperour Adrianus, who, hauing receiued into his handes many billes of ſupplicacion: in the very ſight of the ſuters them ſelues, threwe them all into the water. But he is like himſelfe, id eſt, is full of

compaſſion, and tender in affection towarde the diſtreſſed, to whome all good Magiſſtrats and Juſtices ought in this reſpect to be lyke.
               You may read in Xenophon, what authority and fauour, the Perſian Kinges obtained, by ſuffering the people to haue eaſie acceſſe vnto them, when they came with complaints for redreſſe of their wrongs: and you may read in Samuell how ſtrangelye Abſalon ſtale away the hearts of the men of Iſraell from Dauid his Father, by complaint that there was none to heare them, and by promiſe of ſpéedye diſpatch, if he him ſelfe might rule the roſt. I grant you Ad penitentiā properat, qui cito Iudicat. He haſteneth to Repentaunce, which maketh haſte to giue Judgemēt. But it is ment of him qui preiudicat, which giueth raſh Judgement. For otherwiſe, as nothing els brought Philippe to his deaths wound, but becauſe he wold not hear the cōplaint of Pauſanias. And as nothing wrought that maine confuſion vpon the Lacedemonian eſtate, that neuer could be recouered, but onlye their ſlacknes in hearing poore mens cauſes. So indeed nothing more fretteth the hartes or aſtraungeth the minds of poore mē, then delaying of their cauſes from hearing.
               Which is doubtleſſe a great faulte in our

Courts in England, both eccleſiaſtical &amp; ciuil, that it is ſo long before poore mens cauſes can come to hearing. Indeed ſome times (I know) they are the longer, by meanes of their careles and couetous Lawyers, careles of their cauſe and couetous of their money: for they can tell, how to ſpin or rather to ſpill a cauſe, &amp; to draw it out like a thréede, from tearme, to tearme, vntill their clyents coats be thréed bare, and their purſes money bare. And therefore to be plaine, I lyke not this ſame Ad idem in proximum, which is ſo much vſed among the Ciuilians, nor theſe ſame néedeles and trifling Demurrars, which are ſo ordinary, among the cō
                  mon Lawyers: for both theſe proue many tymes to be the very bane and murrain of many a good mans right.
               But let a mans cauſe runne thorow all the delaies and pikes, that the cunning of any drawlatch can deuiſe, yet vnleſſe he make earneſt and great meanes to haue it heard, it ſhal neuer be hearde, vntill doomeſday. Be wiſe then ye Judges of the earth, and learne to be forewarde &amp; ready to heare of him, which one day ſhall Judge you all, and ſuffer not good mē to be diſcouraged, or poore men to be eaten out of all they haue, thorow your delayes. If you doe, you ſhall finde that the Grand Judge him ſelfe will make no delay, to rewarde you therafter,

&amp; to meaſure his vengeance accordingly.
               Laſtly, the Lord heareth the voice of the penitent, nay, the very breath and the leaſt thought in his heart, tending to repentance. And therfore it is ſaid: If any man be a woorſhipper of God and doth his will, him doth he heare. Ioh. 9. Now this is his will, euen your holynes. 1. Theſ. 4. And he willeth not the death of a ſinner, but that he ſhould be conuerted and liue. And beſides, this very thing is warranted vnto vs in this Scripture, why, they did no ſoner wiſh wel in there harts but the Lord heard it. We cannot ſo ſay of any mortall Prince, his ſubiectes may ſpeake and cry and call long inough, and yet if they be not, within his hearing they are neuer y• nere. And therfore this is a flat daſh to that peeuiſh reaſon of the papiſts which tell vs that as a mortall Prince muſt be laboured vnto by meanes and mediatours, ſo muſt the Lord our God be ſolicited by Saints and Angells: Alas there is no proporcion in this compariſon: for God only is himſelf Scrutator Cordis the ſearcher of our harts: &amp; we cannot do it but by meanes: And what iniury or rather villāy is it to make him in his hearing of no more capaſity or excellency then a mortal creature? And ſo let this ſuffice, for our firſt encouragement to drawe vs on to repentāce, for that the Lord vouchſafeth

to hearken and hear all them, which haue but any motion of ſo happy a purpoſe.
            
            
               Of the ſecond Comforte.
               
                  ANd a booke of remembrance was writtē before him. &amp;c. Let vs now in theſe words conſider of that which was a ſecond cō
                  fort &amp; encouragemēt for this people to procede in their repentance. That it was acceptable to the Lord, we perceiue by his attentiue fauour in hearing them. But now you ſhall vnderſtand that it was very honorable beſides. And y• he doth vouchſafe them the rareſt welcome home to his mercye and grace, that euer was heard of, for he cauſed a booke of remembrance. &amp;c. And to what end? Surely that it might for euer be remembred, how much he deliteth in al penitent ſinners, which aſſone as euer they forſake ſin, he will embrace &amp; honor in his bottomles and abundant mercy. Alſo that it might neuer be forgotten, that howe great and how generall ſoeuer the corruption was, yet they were the people which became penitent, and turned vnto the Lord, at the preching of Malachi, &amp; therefore ſome cauſe why all poſterity ſhould be encouraged, not only to follow their example, but alſo to haue them in Admiration. It ſhall be expedient, that here we conſider firſt, what is ment by the booke of remēbrance, &amp; then to whom it doth apertaine. For this book of remēbrance it is very ſtrange
               
                  We read of certaine ſtones of remembrāce, which being ingrauen with the names of the children of Iſraell, and ſet in golde, Aron was to weare that he might remember them to Godwards.
               And we finde that there was a ſacrifice of Remembrance, made by fire, for a ſweete ſauour vnto the Lord, to ſignifie that God will not forget him that offereth it, Leuit. 2. And we vnderſtand of a Saboth of Remembrance to be obſerued, and celebrated, for a memorial of the blowing of Trumpets, and of the Jubile. Leuit. 23.
               
               And who can be ignorant of Abſalons piller of remembrance, which he erected, becauſe he had no ſonne to kepe his name in memorie? But what this booke of Remembrance ſhould importe, that wee doe not ſo eaſelye perceiue. Surely ſome learned wryters are of opinion that hereby we are to vnderſtand, this booke of Malachies prophecy. Which becauſe it was writtē at the Lords appointment, was doutles written before his face: and becauſe it can not be red openly in the congregation, without recitall of this their conferrence, therefore it may be termed iuſtly a booke of remēbrance. Euen as the goſpell it ſelfe, is a booke of Remē
                  brance, in reſpect of that which Marie Magdalen did to our Sauiour Chriſt: for whereſoeuer

this goſpell ſhall be preached, through out all the world, there ſhal this alſo that ſhe hath done bee ſpoaken of, for a memoriall of her, ſaith Chriſt Jeſus himſelfe. Math. 26. And in this ſence it doeth maruelouſlye approue and confirme the authority of this booke of Malachies Prophecy, as beeing written in his preſence, and at his appointment.
               But by the cenſure, and in the Judgement of the moſt learned and godly writers that I haue red; there is another meaning to be vnderſtoode, by the booke of remembrance. For thereby is ſignified the booke of lyfe, wherein the righteous are written, and whereof we read. Exod. 32. Pſal. 69. Apoc. 3. And it is ment, that therein the Lorde did write their names preſently vpon their repentance, for a memoriall thereof.
               And that you may ſée in what ſtéed it wil ſtād you, to be writen in the booke of the Lordes Remembraunce, and to be remembred in the booke of lyfe, conſider firſt of that which is ſet downe Daniell. 12. ver. 1.
               
               And thereby may you perſeiue that albeit there fall out ſuch a tyme of trouble, as neuer was ſince the worlde beganne, yet euerye one that ſhalbe found written in the booke of lyfe ſhall be delyuered, and to the ſame effect it is, that this booke was ordained for this people▪
                  
to be as it were their Paſſeouer, to auoid and eſcape the dayes of miſerye, which the Lorde did threaten, to bring vpon them. Prouide that the doore poſtes of your conſciences maye be ſprinckled with the bloode of the Lambe, or that your repentaunce maye bee recorded in the booke of lyfe, and you are ſure of an euerlaſting Paſſeouer to eſcape Gods moſt dreadfull vengeance.
               But if you wll ſée that prerogatiue, which is, Inſtar omnium: in ſtéede of all other. Then conſider againe and againe, of that which is written, in 20. Apoc. ver, 12. Wherin the glorious maieſty of our Sauiour Jeſus Chriſt, is moſte truely deſcribed, euen as he ſhall come to Judge the quick and the dead, for it is ſaid, And I ſaw the dead both great and ſmall ſtād before God: and the bookes were opened, &amp; another book was opened, which is the book of lyfe, &amp; the dead wer iudged of thoſe things which were written in the bookes, acording to their workes.
               
               But now what are theſe bookes that ſhall be opened before the booke of lyfe be opened? doubtles theſe thrée, the booke of the Lawe, the booke of the Goſpell, and the booke of Conſcience.
               Firſt the booke of the Law ſhal be opened, and laid before vs, that it maye appeare what

duetye we ought to haue done towardes God and man through loue. And euen as Moyſes commāded the Leuites to put this booke in the ſide of the Arke, that it might be for a witnes againſt them, when they diſobeyed the ſame. Deu. 31. So ſhall all the workers of iniquity in the fearefull day of the Lord, find this booke a ſwift witnes againſt them. And if Ioſias rent his cloathes and wept for wo, when he heard the law red, and thereby ſawe how much duety was required, and how little he had performed: what ſorrow and heauines ſhall compas vs about, and if it were poſſible, diſſolue our teares, and turne them into drops of blood?
               When in the preſence of this our ſeuere Judge we ſhall both heare and ſée, not onelye what we haue left vndone, in that book commanded, but alſo what we haue done therein forbidden. In the meane time therefore, let vs not onelye be hearers of the Law, but dooers alſo, leſt then we finde Gods fauour vnrecouerable, and our repentance vnprofitable.
               Secondly the booke of the Goſpell ſhal be opened, that thereby it may appear what mercy, what grace, what frée pardon, what remiſſion of ſinne, what imputation of righteouſnes, and what aſſuraunce of lyfe and Saluation, you might haue had in Chriſt Jeſus.
               
                  If you had bene ſo happye to haue ſought it by repentance, and to haue laid holde vppon it by faith.
               At the opening of this booke, ſhall you ſée before your eyes all the ſwéete promiſes, and tender inuitations which our Sauiour Chriſt offred vnto you through preaching of the goſpell, to haue drawne you to repentance, Then ſhall all the benefites of his bitter paſſion be laid open before your eyes, and you ſhall ſée that he was debaſed himſelfe, to haue brought you to honour: that he was wounded himſelf to haue healed your wounds of ſinne: and that he died himſelfe, to haue ſaued his enemies from death, and to haue purchaſed eternal life to all penitent ſinners. And as the booke of the lawe ſhall ſhewe what wee ought to haue done, ſo the booke of the Goſpell ſhall ſhewe, what we ought to haue beleeued: and both to one end (Chriſt knoweth) that ſo much more Juſt and dreadfull may be our Judgement.
               O ye proude contemners of the worde of trueth, conſider of this; you which thinke the Goſpell to baſe for your déepe wittes haue regarde vnto it, leſt the time come that you repent it, and féele the ſmart of it. And as the ritch man begde of Abraham, that poore Lazarus might dip but the tippe of his finger in water, to coole his tormented tongue, ſo the day

may come, that you will be glad
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  e in your harts, that the 
                     〈…〉
                   raſcall a
                     •
                  d ab
                     ••
                  ct miniſter among vs all (as you 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                   vs) might be ſuffered to bring y
                     •
                  u euen the leaſt all drop of the water of lyfe, ye a the leaſt comfort of the Goſpell to refreſh your 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  les, but it will be to late, to late.
               Thirdlye the booke of Conſcience ſhall be opened, and ſhewe what abhominable ſinnes we haue done and committed▪ 
                  Conſcientia Codex eſt; in quo quotidiana conſcrib
                        〈…〉
                     r peccata▪
                   
                  
                     •
                  aith Chriſoſt. in Pſa. 50. The conſcience is a booke where in a mans dayly ſins are written. Therfore keepe this boke well &amp; cleare frō the blots and blemiſhes of ſinne, and then the reward thereof will be ſo ſtrong and ſubſtantiall on thy ſide, y• it is called mille teſtes, a thouſand witneſſes: Sillogiſmus practicus, a concluſion of Experience: Cordis ſcientia, the knoweledge of a mans owne hart: It is murus Aeneus; as Horace ſaith a braſen wall, It is maxima conſolatio rerum incōmodarum. The greateſt cōfort in aduerſity; ſaith Tully, nay it is▪ 
                  ger Benedictionis, the field of bleſſing, Hort is delitiarum. The garden of pleaſures. Gaudium An
                     
                        〈…〉
                     m, The ioy of Angels. Habit 
                        〈…〉
                     m Spiritus ſancti, The habitation of the holy Ghoſt, ſaith Hugo de Anima▪ Lib. 2. Cap. 9.
                  
               
               But ſuffer this booke to be 
                     〈…〉
                   and 
                     ••
                  lluted

with ſinne: and what is it then? It is formidinis mater, ſaith Chriſoſtome, the Mother of all feare. It is confuſionis tabula. ſaith Auguſt. It is the table of confuſion. And of all other bookes in the world, you can not abyde to look into the book of your guilty conſciences.
               This made the Father (I meane Adam) a cr
                     •
                  ep
                     •
                  iſh in Paradice, and this made him ſay Abſcondi me, Gen. 3.
                   This made, the ſonne I meane, Caine a runnagate, and ſo reſtleſſe that hee durſt abide noe where, for feare his throat ſhould be cut,▪ 
                  Gen. 4. This made Ionas conuey him ſelfe into the bottome of the ſhippe, thinking there to hyde him ſelfe from the booke of his owne Gauled conſcience.
               This made Iudas betake himſelfe to the halter, becauſe he coulde not abide to ſee the abhominable treacherye hee had committed againſt the innocent bloode of Jeſus.
               This made Ecebolus that turne cote heretike to caſt him ſelfe downe before the Church and to deteſt him ſelfe, ſaying Calcate me in ſipidum ſalem, Trample vpon me vnſauorye ſalt that I am.
                  
               
               Now then if it be ſuch a feareful &amp; horrible thing to looke into the booke of a guilty conſcience in this life, what ſhame and confuſion ſhal ouerwhelme vs, in the lyfe to come? when

nothing ſhall be concealed, when all pleates and wrinckles ſhall be vnfolded, when al coū
                  ſels and ſecrets ſhal be diſcouered, when there is not an idle word of our tongues, or a wicked thought of our herts, that ſhall eſcape our accompt, and when all our falts ſhall appeare vppon record againſt vs, euen in the bookes which we our ſelues haue caried in our owne boſomes: Alas, alas who ſhall endure it, and not deſire that the déep may ſwallow him vp, or that the mountaines maye couer him, or that the hilles may fall vpon him? Haue a 
                     •
                  are then good people, and an eye to your boſome booke, I meane the conſcience, the verye regiſter of all your ſecrets.
               Now all theſe bookes being opened, the booke of the Law, to ſhow what wee ought to haue done: The booke of the Goſpell, to ſhewe what we ought to haue beleeued: and the book of our owne conſciences, to ſhew what abominable ſins we haue committed: &amp; that we haue neither by loue ſatiſfied the Law, nor thorow faith relyed vpon the goſpell: what followeth? Then ſhal the booke of lyfe, which is here called the booke of Remembraunce be opened, wherein the Lord, hath ſet downe vpon record whatſoeuer good thing we haue done, for the obtaining of the crowne of lyfe, and the auoiding of the ſnares of death, and namely theſe

foure things.
               Firſt, the Names of all Gods Saints and ſeruants, and this is apparant by the wordes of Moyſes, Exod. 32. 32. If thou wilt not forgiue thē, I pray thee race my name out of the booke of lyfe, which thou haſt written. And Daniell praieth, that the wicked may be raced out of the boke of lyfe, and that they may not be written with the righteous. Pſal. 69. So that as Aſſuerus had his booke of rememberaunce, wherein the names of ſuch, as had don him hye ſeruice at any time, wer vſually written, and as he finding that Mardocheus had diſcouered two traitours which ſought to laye violent hands vpon the King, cauſed him to be honored, by putting on his owne rich apparel, and by wearing his royall crowne vpon his head, Eſter. 6. In lyke maner our heauenlye King, ſéeing the good that we haue done, for the ſupplanting and ſubuerting of the enemies of his trueth will he not recorde our names in his book? will he not giue vs the rich robes of his innocencie? and the royall crowne of his euerlaſting glorye? Read you the 2. of the Re▪ and you ſhall ſee, that the Lord doeth profeſſe this fauour: Very notably he tolde the Church of Epheſus that heknew her workes, her labor and her patience &amp;c. And ſo he tolde the church of Smirna, the Church of Pergamus, and the

Church of Thyatyra, that he knew not onely what yet they had done, but alſo did remember and recite in particuler their good, reckoning with them for the one, and promiſſing to rewarde them for the other.
               Secondly in this booke of Remembraunce we ſhall finde written the teares of our affliction, and therefore Dauid ſaith: Thou haſte counted my wandrings, &amp; put my teares into thy bottle, are they not in thy regiſter? Pſ. 56. 8. Can there, be a greater comfort then this when wee are brought to the ſtake to bee burnt, or to the ſworde to be cut as fleſh to the potte, or to the wilde horſſes to be torne in a thouſand peeces? Let the butcherlike tirants glut their hartes by making aſhes of our bodies, or foules meat, or dogs meat of our fleſh, what care wee? They can not ſcrape our teares out of the booke of Remembrance, nor race our bloode out of the regiſter of lyfe.
               Thirdly, In this booke of Remēbrance we ſhall finde written the works of our compaſſion, for ſo much doth the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt importe, Math. 25. Who ſhall ſay to them on the right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Father inherite ye the kingdome prepared for you frō the foūdation of the world, for I was an hungred &amp; ye gaue me meat▪ &amp;c. Then ſhall the righteous aunſwer him, and

ſay, Lord When ſawe we thee anhongred, &amp;c. Then ſhall he anſwer and ſay, Verely, in aſmuche as you haue done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren, ye haue done it vnto me.
               
               And ſo much doth the woordes of Iob import, Cap. 31. ver. 35. Where he ſaith, that the Almighty will witnes his pitty towardes the poore, albeit his enemy ſhould write a booke againſt him. And ſo will he doe for vs: If wee giue but a cuppe of colde water for his names ſake, we ſhal not loſe our rewarde.
               We ſee that Princes haue their bookes of Subſidies, of Beneuolence, of priuye Seales, wherein they ſet down whatſoeuer good they receiue at the hands of their Subiects, by free gift or vpō lone or lending. And ſo it is with our heauenly potentat: I warrant you, if you releeue the poore, he ſets it down in his book for a ſubſidy, or a beneuolēce don to him: &amp; if you lend to the poore &amp; needy, he ſets it downe for a priuy ſeale lent to him: &amp; he will become your debter, and ſée it diſcharged to the vttermoſt.
               Therefore ye rich men, out with your ſubſidie, extend your beneuolences, and ſend abroad your priuye ſeale money, the Lord will not forget it, he will not faile but ſet it downe in his booke of Remembrance.
               And heere, right Honorable, and beloued in the Lord, I cannot but put you in minde of

a neceſſary Beneuolence, and a Chriſtian ſubſidy, to be ſupplyed in reſpect of the Godly preachers, called, and appointed for this place: which as you know is vſually and beſt furniſhed with learned men, from both the vniuerſities: But how hardlye, and vnwillinglye they ar drawen hither, it is but to wel known. And why? becauſe they are faine to come at their owne great coſte and charge, which can not ſtand with their poore and ſmall abilitye: For I ſpeake not for my ſelfe, and other
                     •
                   my brethren, which thankes be to God are prouided for ſufficiently to do any ſeruice appliable to our calling, without beeing chargeable to you: But for fellowes in Colleges, and other poore ſtudents in the vniuerſities, men of rare knowledge and ſinguler guifts, which being enioyned to ſupply this place, are not more often ſent for, then commonlye they refuſe to come: And for my parte, I cannot greatlye blame them: for why ſhould they labour and haue no hyre? Or tread out your corne with the Oxe, and haue their mouthes muſted? No man is hound proprijs ſtipendiis militare to make warre at his owne charge. Why ſhould not he that preacheth the Goſpell, liue of the goſpel? Or why ſhould not they which ſowe ſpirituall things, reape your temporall things?
               Might it therfore pleaſe you, the right honorable

the Lord Maior▪ and the read
                     •
                   the right wor
                     ••
                   
                  
                     ••
                  full your brethren, and Maie
                     ••
                  
                  trats of th
                     •
                   famous cittie of London, 
                     ••
                   impar
                     ••
                   
                  
                     •
                  ou
                     〈…〉
                  berality and ye
                     •
                  rly contribution, in 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪ I know
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  e learned 
                     〈…〉
                   godly B
                     •
                  ſhop, which in my hearing▪ hath not onely promiſed before▪ 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪ but 
                     〈…〉
                  ed before God to giue a good portion for
                     ••
                  er towardes thi
                     •
                   ſo good a purpoſe▪ 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   I am ſure it will bee a
                     •
                   freelye and thorowlye performed▪ make triall when you pleaſe▪
               
               And albeit perhaps you will not pre
                     •
                  ent him yet the cauſe being ſo reaſonable and important, I hope God will ſtirre vp your harts, not to be long or much behinde him▪
               
               And in trueth I 
                     ••
                   
                  
                     ••
                  der that this noble Cittie of London hath not heretofore▪ looked into this want, and had 
                     •
                  are to ſupply it, 
                     〈…〉
                   in there is no charitable w
                     ••
                  ke almoſt vndo
                     ••
                   or at the leaſt vnprouided for.
               You haue ſundry not able fr
                     •
                  e ſchooles founded in this Cittye, where by you giue 
                     •
                  u
                     •
                  ture to the rude, and learning to the ignorant▪ You haue many goodly hoſpitals endewed, wherein yo
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  e me and allowe Phiſick to the 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪ 
                  
                     ••
                  rger
                     •
                   to the ſore, meate to the hungry, drink to the thirſty, cloaths to the naked houſeroom for the h
                     〈…〉
                  ourles▪ and good and godly education to Orphanes and infants. And you haue

ſtore of faire and ſweete Conduits, wherebye you ſpare not for any coſte, to conuey water into euery place almoſt of this populus citty: Yea there cannot be a fountaine heard of, or a deuiſe thought of, to yeelde ſtore of water, but lyke good and careful gouernours, your hands are in your purſes to laye out what ſo euer it will coſt. And will you beſtow nothing vppon the bleſſed Pypes, and ſugred Conduites which bring you the water of lyfe? You cannot bring water a quarter of a myle, to the Cittie, without your own great charges. And doo you thinke it reaſon that the water of life ſhould be brought you, 40▪ or 50. myles at other mens charges? Conſider but of the excellency thereof, and thinke but of the happines of theſe our daies, wherein wee may haue it either for loue or money.
               The waters of Sylaris in Lucania▪
                   maketh ſoft things hard as a wand laid in it all night, wil be as hard as a ſtone by the morning: But the water of lyfe will make hard thinges ſoft, as your hard ſtonye heartes it will turne into tender fleſhy hartes.
               The water of Sinneſana in Campania, maketh mad men wiſe and ſober, and ſo this water chaungeth worldly folly into Heauenly wiſedome.
               The water of Clytumnus, if O
                     •
                  enor ſhéep

being neuer ſo blacke, vſe to drinke of it, it wil make them as white as the driuen ſnowe: So this water albeit ſinne hath made you as blak in ſoule as any Ethiopian is in bodye, yet it will waſh you, and purge you, and make you cleane and white.
               And as the water of Betheſda when it was moued by the Angell, cured them which ſtept into it, whatſoeuer diſeaſe they had: So this water will cure and recouer al the infirmities of your ſicke ſoules, if ye ſtep into it, and embrace it, when Gods miniſters moue it, and poure it out before you.
               To be ſhorte, as Varro writeth of Zame, a fountaine in Affrica, that it runneth with ſuch ſweete ſinging noiſe, that thereby bothe men and beaſts are allured to drinke of it: So the waters of lyfe, running and falling in this publik and famous place, through ſuch learned pipes, and gratious Conduites as comes from the Vniuerſities▪ are moſte pleaſant and of maruellous force, to allure all men, bothe cleane and vncleane, to taſte of them, and to hath their ſinfull ſoules in them.
               Wherefore the vertue and excellencie of this water, being ſo ſinguler, and ſoueraigne as you haue heard▪ I hope it will not grudge you with all ſpéede to prouide that it maye haue moſte frée and plentifull paſſage to this

Cittie, thorow your Chriſtian relief and lyberalitye.
               I am not the firſt that hathe moued this ſute, but you may be the firſt that euer tendered it, or prouided for it: two and fifty poundes a yere, would bountifully performe it, a good parte whereof (as I haue toulde you) a Reuerend and moſte learned Biſhoppe meaneth to yeld: And if you would vouchafe to ioyne with him, and to lay out the reſt, and ſo make vppe the ſomme, out of your common treaſurye for the cittie, you ſhould not onely be thankfully remembred in this place vnto the worlds end, but alſo this good woorke of your compaſſion ſhall be recorded in the booke of the Lords Remembrance, and at the laſt day, you ſhall reap the frute of your well doing, &amp; finde that with ſuch ſacrifice God is highlye pleaſed,
               Laſtly in this booke of Remembrance ſhall be written the ſorrow and remorſe▪ of our penitent and broken harts. And hereof what better teſtimony, then this preſent Scripture, The Lord cauſed a booke of Remembraunce to be written, &amp;c. It is doubtles a great and gratious fauour when the Lord ſayeth, At what time ſoeuer a ſinner ſhall repent, I will blot his wickednes out of my Remembrance, Ezech. 18.
               
               But this paſſeth and is with out all compariſon,

that he will make a memoriall of it, and write a booke of Remembrance of our repentaunce, and recorde it in the booke of lyfe, So that with Iſrael, we ſhal not onelye eſcape all euill, or the greateſt euill in this lyfe, but alſo at the laſt and moſt de
                     •
                  adfull time, be tide what ſhall, come the day of the Lord neuer ſo glowmingly, ſound the trumpet neuer ſo fear fully, arriſe the dead neuer ſo ſinfully, approch the deuils neuer ſo fiearſly ſmoake the mountaines melt the hilles, tremble the earth, vaniſhe the ſea, flaſh and flame the whole vn
                     •
                  
                  uerſall worlde, neuer ſo furiouſly, yet this ſhal be our comfort and refuge▪ that we haue repented vs of our ſinnes, and that our Repentance is of record, and written in the booke of the Judges remembrance▪
               
               And ſo to come to the next obſeruation in this comfort: Seing the Prophet in plaine termes ſaith that this booke was written for them that feared the Lord, and thought vpon his name, let all the woorkers of Iniquitye which forget God, and put farre from the
                     •
                   the euill day, which ſaith in their hartes▪ tuſh▪ God hath forgotten, hee wil not ſée it, which are at their leagues with death, and at their bargaines with hell, let them all ſtand backe and know, that there is no place for their names in this booke: And why? the Lord himſelf

yeelds the reaſon, Whoſoeuer ſinneth againſt me, I will put his name out of my booke. Ex. 32. And againe. I will make their rememberance to ceaſe from among men: No, No, Ieremie telleth them plaine enough where they ſhal be writen, euen in the duſt or in the earth Ier. 17. and why? becauſe they haue forſaken the Lord, the fountaine of liuing waters.
               Therefore let them write their names vpon their owne ſtately houſes, and vpon their ſumpteous tombes and Sepulchers, no man will controll them. But it is their Judgemēt to be ſcattred lyke the chaffe before the wind: Pſal. 1. To be withered lyke graſſe before the Sonne. Pſal. 37. and to melt or conſume lyke waxe before the fire. Pſal. 68. that is: to be forgotten, and to be raked vppe and buried in the forlorne aſhes of all obſcuritye and obliuion.
               And yet their puniſhment ſhall not be forgotten, I warrant you: for that is written and ſet downe in another kinde of booke then we haue yet ſpoken off, I meane the blacke booke of Gods moſt bitter vengeance, wherof Ezechel ſpeaketh Chap. 2. Which indeede is written within and without, and there is nothing written in it, but lamentation, &amp; mourning, and woe. For alas howe ſhould they lament and mourne and bewaile their curſed

condition, when becauſe they are not founde written in the booke of lyfe, therefore their owne conſciences ſhall accuſe them: all creatures ſhall be ſuffred to exclame vpon them: The Judge himſelfe ſhall condemne them to be caſt into the lake of fyre: the bleſſed Angels ſhall thruſte them out of Gods preſence: and the vgly deuils ſhall thereupon arreſt thē, for firebrands of hell.
               And ſo to conclude this point I can ſay no more but onely wiſh with Iob. cap. 19. That my words were written in a booke, and Ingrauen with an Iron pen in lead or in ſtone, for euer, id eſt, in the harts and minds of you all, ſo many as are here preſent, whether they be like vnto a booke, id eſt, learned and wiſe, and well able to inſtruct others: or like vnto lead, id eſt, dui through groſſe ignoraunce, or like vnto ſtone, id eſt, obdurat, and hard, euen through ſinne and wickednes: yet the Lord graunt that the Iron penne of his ingrauing Spirite, may imprint depe in your harts, and ſoules, the ſomme and effect of all that I haue ſpoken touching the booke of Remembraunce, and that you maye eſteeme with your ſelues, how fearefull a thing it will be to fall into the handes of the Lorde at the laſt daye, becauſe your Repentaunce is not of Recorde, nor written in the booke of his gratious Remembraunce.
            
            
               
               Of the third Comforte.
               
                  ANd they ſhall be vnto me ſaith the Lorde for a flocke. &amp;c. In theſe words the Iſraelites are mightely encouraged to procede in their repentaunce, with a mercifull promiſe of the Lords protection, wherein moſt gratiouſlye he giues thē warrantiſe of two things.
               Firſt that they ſhalbe to him for a flock, &amp;c.
               Who woulde not repent, and bee obedient to the voice of the meſſengers of the Lord, that might thereby become ſo happy, as to be his flocke▪ yea or a ſhéepe of his flocke? A rare encouragement exceding farre the royaltye of all Princes, and the Maieſtye of all Emperours. For as the Lord hath freelye choſen to him ſelfe of all the trées in the woode one Vine: of all the flowrs in the garden one Lyllie: of all the depthes of the ſea, one Riuer: of all the buildinges on the earth, one Syon: of all the foules of the aire, one Doue: of all the cattell of the earth, one ſhéepe: and of all the Nations of the world, one people: So this people is his flocke: and this flocke is his church, and this Church is not Synagoga, id eſt, qualiſcunque Congregatio, any kinde of aſſemblye, yea common riffe r
                     •
                  ffe, or diſordred: but it is

more properly and worthily tearmed E
                        ••
                     le
                        〈…〉
                      
                     id eſt, Coetus ordinatus, a Goodly aſſembly.
               
                  Ab 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  euocare, for the manner of the Athenians was, when they woulde haue the people aſſembled to heare the ſentence of the Senate, to ſend foorth a cryer to call vpon thē and ſo to 
                     •
                  u
                     •
                  l them out from the raſcal ſorte of the people: And here vpon the Apoſtle tranſlated the word to their purpoſe, and gaue the Church it ſelfe that tearme: becauſe it is Caetus Dei praeconio verbi a regno ſa
                        •
                     hanae ad gratiam &amp; ſalutem in Chriſto Ieſu e
                        •
                     ocatus. An aſſemblye or flocke of God with the voice of his woorde called or c
                     •
                  lled from the kingdome of ſath
                     〈…〉
                   to grace and Saluation in Chriſt Jeſus. This is the way then, beloued in the Lord▪ 
                  
                     ••
                   become ye ſhepe of Chriſt his flock, &amp; ſo to be reputed and taken: to do as Iſraell did, id▪ eſt, obey his voice, and heare his worde. My ſhepe know my voice, Ioh. 10. And Moyſes had incharge to tel the Iſraelites thus much from the Lord, that if they wold here his voyce in deed, &amp; kéep his couenāt, then they ſhould be his flock or chief treſure aboue al people, Ex. 19. let this then ſtand 
                     •
                  or one of the moſt happieſt prerogatiues of the flock of Chriſt, that it is &amp; will be aſſembled at the ſounde of his heauenlye worde, from the raſcall hearde of goates.
               The voice of Gods worde makes his people

flocke and throug together; lyke ſhéepe to the folde.
               Another prerogatiue of this flock is, that as it is cōuented and aſſembled by the call of the worde, ſo it is continued and kept together thorow vnity and chriſtian loue, which is the bond of perfection▪ This is like the folde that coopes vp the ſhepe together, and keepes them from wandring and ſtragling▪ It is lyke the band that preſerues the ſheſe or faggot from ſhattering Vnus Paſtor, vnum Ouile. There is one ſheepehearde and one flocke or ſheepefolde.
               And therefore in the behalf of Jeſus Chriſt our head ſhepehearde, I beſéeche you, and for your owne ſaluations ſake, I require you and charge you al to take heed how by ſciſmes and ſects ye ſeeke to ſcatter the flocke of Chriſt, leſt you bring it from Ouile to Hedile, and from Hedile to Canile, from a ſhepefolde to a hearde of Goates, and from a heard of Goates, to a kē
                  nell of dogges.
               Alas, alas, it was not lawfull to break a bone of Chriſtes naturall bodye, but hée that breaketh the peace of the Church, breaketh the verye backebone of his miſticall body.
               And it was as vnlawfull to part or deuide ſo muche as his vnſeamed cote: But they which practiſe to deuide the Church, what do

they elſe, but teare his cote off his backe? and rent in ſonder his tender harte? Wherefore as nature forced the right mother to abhorre the deuiding of her owne childe. 1. King. 3. So the Lord graunt, that grace may make vs all forbear to deuide the ſweete Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, the common mother of vs al: Nature I ſay made the mother to abhorre to deuide the child, and can not grace make the childe aborre to deuide the mother?
               A third prerogatiue of the Lords flocke is, that it is ſuſtained and foſtered after the beſt manner that may be poſſible. For Dauid ſaith The Lord is my ſhepheard, therfore I ſhal wāt nothing. Pſal. 23. And againe, He ſhall feede me in a greene paſture, and lead me beſids the waters of comforte. By the greene paſture we are to vnderſtand, the woorde of trueth, Quod manet in aeternum: Eſay. 40.
                   For this alwayes flouriſheth, and neither the heat of Sommer can ſcorch it, nor the colde of winter freeſe it. And by the waters of comforte, he meaneth the graces of the holye Ghoſt according to that which is written. Io. 7. Hee that beleueth in me, out of his belly ſhal flow riuers of the water of lyfe.
               
               Fourthlye, this flocke is ſure to be guided, and directed by the Lordes owne hand, Hee ſhall lead mee in the pathes of righteouſnes,
                  
ſaith Dauid. Pſa, 23. And againe, Thou art with me: thy rod and thy ſtaffe comforte me.
               
               By his rod he meaneth ſuch correction as it ſhall pleaſe him to giue the ſhéepe of his paſture: And by his ſtaffe, he vnderſtandeth 
                     •
                  he ſtrength and power whereby hee will dryue backe his enemies.
               And to this very end was the miniſtery of the Angels ordained, to guarde the flocke of Chriſt in all ſafety. The Angell of the Lord pitcheth round about them that feare him, &amp; delyuereth them. Pſal. 34. And againe, He ſhall giue his Angelles charge ouer thee, to kepe thee in all thy waies: They ſhall beare thee in their handes, that thou daſhe not thy foote againſt a ſtone. Pſal. 91. And haue not the Patriarkes, and the Prophets, &amp; the people of Iſraell, and the Apoſtles, and the Saints of God founde it ſo in their diſireſſes?
               Was not Iacob comforted againſt Eſau, by an hoſt of Angels? Gen. 32. Was not Elizeus ſauegarded by an army of Angels from the Aſſirians? 2. King. 6. Was not our bleſſed Sauiour Chriſte himſelfe miniſtred vnto by Angels? Math. 4.
               
               Moſte wonderfull is the protection, and moſt tender is the care which the Lord hath ouer his flocke.
               It were a great fauour to allow vnto his

flocke a garde of men, and to allowe it a band of Princes, were exceading and ſurpaſſing and incredible loue: But to make the Angels garde vs, and to pitch round about vs for our ſafetye, what an vnſpeakeable prerogatiue is it of his incomparable mercye and bottomles compaſſion towardes the ſhéepe of his paſture?
               And laſtly, this flocke ſhall eſcape and goe ſcotfree in the day of vengeance. In the day that I ſhall do this. But what is it the nere, or wherein are wee the better? when in the meane time our Sauiour Chriſt telleth his diſciples, that their eſtate in this lyfe ſhall be Tanquam Oues in medio Luporum, As ſhepe in the middeſt of Wolues, Math. 10.
                   Is this all the care he hath of his flock? to leaue it in ſuch a caſe in the middes of Wolues? Tuſh, take we no care, for the Lordes care ouer his: For as the very heare of our heades are numbred, and not one of them ſhall miſcary: So right deare in the ſight of the Lorde, is the death of his Saints. And if they be but in daunger once, he will doe as that ſame good ſhepheard did, whereof we read in the Goſpell. Luk. 15. Who hauing but 100. ſheepe in all his flocke, when one of them went aſtraye, left the reſt in the wildernes, and ſought it out, and brought it home into ſafetye.
               
                  But what if the Lordes flock be left in the middes of Wolues, id eſt, Heretickes, or tytantes? yet the Lorde hathe noe ſuche purpoſe rhere to leaue them, becauſe they ſhould be deuoured of them, but a contrary drift there is, which you woulde lyttle thinke. That is, that this flocke ſhould ouercome and deuoure the Wolues themſelues. And ſo much Chriſoſtome ſaith, Plurimos morſus ab us accipientes non ſolum non conſumuntur, ſed et illos conuertunt, receiuing many bytings of them, they are not only not deuoured, but they euē conuert thē.
                  
               
               And this is ſurely miraculous. It were ſtrange to ſee a ſhéepe ouercome or kil a wolfe But it is not ſtraunge to ſée one of Chriſtes ſheepe ouercome or kill one of Sathans Wolues.
               It were a wonder to heare that a ſheepe ſhould turne a Wolfe into a ſheepe (I warrant you that Ouid in all his Metamorphoſis hathe none ſuche) But it is not vnlikelye nor vnpoſſible that one of the Lordes ſheepe may of an Heretike make a good Chriſtian, and of a tyrant a good Magiſtrat, which is al one in effect. And therefore Chriſoſtome ſaith, multo mirabilius eſt et maius, tranſmutare mentes eorum, quam interficere eos. It is a thing much more wonderfull &amp; greater, to chaunge the minds of Heretikes &amp; tyrants then to kill

them.
               Taking theſe Wolues for Heretikes, you ſhall finde that the ſheepe of the Lords flocke haue conuerted them, and turned them into ſhéepe.
               The Apoſtle Andrewe reclaiming Maximilla from Idolatrie to Chriſtianity, notwithſtanding the diſpleaſure and furye of her Huſband Ageas, did he not turne a Woulfe into a ſhéepe?
               The Apoſtle Iames by his wonderfull conſtancy, wrought a wounderfull feate, that is ouercame and rauiſhed the wretch that accuſed him before the magiſtrates▪ into ſo muche that he knew no better waye to make him amendes, but to confeſſe that he himſelfe was a Chriſtian as well as the Apoſtle, and aſked him forgiuenes for his treatcherye, and was willing to drinke of the ſame cup of torments with him Now what was this but to turne a woulfe into a ſheepe?
               But taking wolues for tyrants, you may ſée and conſider how the Lordes flocke hath ouercome them.
               In that S. Steuen prayed for them that ſtoned him to death.
               In that 
                     •
                  . Andrew beeing faſtned to the Croſſe, reioyſed t
                     •
                  ereat, and tould Ageas the tyraunt to his teeth Sicrucem horruiſſem, maieſtatem
                  
                  et gloriam crucis Chriſti nunquam predicaſſem. Had I feared the Croſſe, I would neuer haue preached the Maieſtie and glorye of the Croſſe of Chriſte.
               In that S. Laurence being broyled vpon a gridirone tooke it in ſo good part, that he could finde in his hart to ſay to Decius the tyraunt, Aſſum eſt ſatis, verſa, et manduca: One ſide is broyled enough, turne it and then eat part.
               And in that Ignatius beeing caſte to wilde beaſts to be deuoured, ſpake no worſe words then theſe to Traiane the tyraunt, Frumentum Dei ſum, et per dentes beſtiarum commolor▪ vt mundus panis inueniar, I am become Gods Wheat, and I am to bee ground in the teeth of theſe wilde beaſtes, that I may proue clean bread.
               In that I ſay in all theſe bloody perſecutions, the patience of Gods ſaints and ſeruants was ſo inuincible, howe intollerable ſo euer were their torments. Who had the victorye the woolues or the ſhéepe?
               The lyke conqueſt had our Engliſhe martires in Quéene Maries dayes ouer Bonner, Gardener, and Storye, the bloudethirſty wolues of Antichriſte, for they did not let to confeſſe that they thought the Heretykes (meaning the Martyres) tooke great pleaſure in

burning, they went to it ſo willingly: they endured it ſo conſtantly: and they yéelded themſelues weary with tormenting them. The Wolues were weary with deuouring: But the Lambes were not weary with ſuffering, a foile, a foile.
               No maruaile then if Hillary ſaid, Hoc Eccleſiae proprium eſt, dum perſequitur, floret, dum opprimitur creſcit; dum contemnitur, proficit: dum leditur vincit, dum arguitur intelligit, tunc ſtat cum ſuperari videtur▪ de Trinitat. Lib. 4. This is the manner of the Church, when it is perſecuted it floriſheth: when it is oppreſſed, it groweth: when it is contemned, it profiteth: when it is hurt it vanquiſheth: when it is reproued it vnderſtandeth: and then it ſtandeth when it ſeemeth to be ouercome.
               No maruaile if Auguſtine ſaid, Occidebantu
                        •
                     , v
                        •
                     ebantur, 
                        •
                     orquebantur, Cruciebantur, et multiplicaban
                        •
                     ur, Gods Prophets were ſlaine, burned, tormented, crucified, and yet they were multiplied.
               And no maruaile if the Churche it ſelfe be compared to a Palme trée, pſal. 92. Which for all the froſte of Winter, and ſcorching of Sommer, and bluſtering of windes, and preſſing downe of waightes, yet it will ſtill bee greene, and floriſhe, and riſe vp againſt and aboue the burtheng, and therfore was giuen to

Conquerors in token of victorye.
               If you would knowe the reaſon hereof, go no further thēto the firſt promiſe, The ſedè of the woman ſhall bruſe the Serpents head: This is done by vertue of that ſeede. Or go no further then the wordes of Elizeus: They that are with vs, be moe then they that be againſt vs, 2. Reg. 6. And becauſe Michaell and his Angels haue beene, bee, and ſhallbe to good for the Dragon and his Angelles for euer. Appo. 12. Therefore it ſuffiſeth to reſolue vs that it ſhall be ſo.
               And heere as I haue ſpoken of the eſtate and condition of the Lordes flocke as it is in this lyfe preſent: So if the time did not exclude me, I had thought to haue laid before you the bleſſed prerogatiues thereof▪ which it ſhall haue in the lyfe to come. As firſt that it ſhall bee ſeparated from all the noyſome goates of this worlde. Secondlye, that it ſhal be ſcituate on the right hand of the Judge. Thirdly that it ſhall be leaſed, and poſſeſſed of that kingdome which was prepared for them before the foundations of the world. Math. 25.
               
               But I come to the other thing, which is gratiouſly warranted in this promiſe of the Lords protection, which is ſpecified in theſe wordes.
               
                  
                  And I will ſpare them, &amp;c. The like promiſe is made generally to all them that feare God. Pſal. 103. Euen as a Father hath pittie on his children: So hath the Lord compaſſion on them that feare him.
               
               Indéed many Fathers haue béene vnkinde &amp; vnnatural to their children. Saule made an odlawe, &amp; when Ionathas his ſonne was within the lurtch of it, hee would haue cut him off, had not the people ſtoode him in ſtead and reſcued him. 1. Sam. 14. Herode hauing but onlie two ſonnes, Alexander and Ariſtobolus, vppon a falſe ſurmiſe ſtrangled them both. Whereupon Auguſtus ſaid, Melius eſt Herodis eſſe porcum, quam filium: It is better to bee Herodes hogge, than his ſonne,
               
                  Plutarch ſaith, that in Rome rich men vſed to carry whelps and yong apes vp and downe the ſtréets in their armes: which when Caeſar ſawe, he would néeds know, Ecquid apud ipſos mulieres liberos non parerent? Whether women did not bring forth children with them?
               But to let theſe monſters go, which either praeter &amp; contra naturam, haue thus rebelled &amp; repined againſt their own bowels: do you but meaſure the tender affectiō of parents toward their children by olde Elie, who hearing of the death of Hofni &amp; Phinehas his ſons, with very wo fell downe backward &amp; brake his necke. 1

                  Sam. 4. Or by Dauid, who at the death of that one ſonne which was begotten in adulterie: and after the death of that other ſonne, which letted not to cōmit adultery with his fathers concubines, I meane Abſolon: did ſo take on, that very ſorrow had almoſt broken his very heart inſunder. 2. Sa. 12. 2. Sam. 18. 33. And to read in hiſtories, that Gordianus whē he heard of the death of his ſonne, ſtrangled him ſelfe. Or that Orodes king of Parthia, hearing that his ſonne Pacorus was ſlaine in war, through extreame ſorrowe fell madde. Or that Pythias king of Bithinia, when Xerxes had ſlaine his ſonne, left his kingdome to his wife, and went to his ſonnes graue, and there ended his life with mourning. Or that A
                        •
                     geus ſurmiſing that Theſeus his ſonne had béene ſlayne of Minotaurus, leapt into the ſea &amp; drownd himſelf. To read of all theſe, &amp; infinit other the like examples, how doth it demonſtrate the deare and tender affection of fathers towards their ſons: therefore in that the Lorde promiſeth to fill, and to poure out his compaſſion after this rate and meaſure, what a comforte is this?
               But indéede our heauenly Father doth ſo entirely tender his children, that there is no ende or compariſon thereof to bee made. And therfore as Eſay ſaith, he is our Father. cap. 63.
               
               
                  And as Ieremy ſaith, He will be called our Father. Ier. 3. So whye our Sauiour Chriſt ſhould forbid vs to call any other by the name of Father here in earth, ſaying For one is your Father in heauen, Math. 23. I knowe no reaſon but this, for that no father on earth doeth ſo tenderlye loue his owne children, as our heauenlye Father doeth affect and like of vs, being but his adopted children.
               He ſpareth vs in three reſpectes, in two of them much lyke a naturall Father, but in the third there is no compariſon, I am ſure, and ſo you will ſay.
               Firſt, as a naturall Father will not Kill or deſtroye his childe when he is ſicke, and feeble, and cannot eat his meat, or aborreth ſuch things thorow infirmity, as ſhould be a mean to recouer his health: So our heauenly Father will ſpare vs, and not cōdemne vs, or confound vs for euer, although we be ſicke in ſpirite, and weake in faith, &amp; do euen loath often times his heauenly woord, which is the health and ſaluation of our ſoules.
               Secondly, like a natural father he ſpareth vs in reſpect of our wilfull prodigalities, and waſtinges of his bleſſinges and graces: not vnlike that ſame louing Father in the goſpell who forgaue his ſonne, which had ſo leudlye conſumed his fathers ſubſtance, and his owne

portion.
               Our race we haue as wilfully runne. Our tyme we haue as vainely ſpent. His fauours we haue as ilfau
                     ••
                  rdly beſtowed, and his diſpleaſure we haue as deſperatly incurred. But yet come home to his mercy by repentaunce, and ſay, father we haue ſinned againſt thee▪ &amp;c. and then you ſhall finde that he wil ſpare you, and embrace you in the armes of his mercifull compaſſion. &amp;c.
               But now to ſpeake of that reſpect of the Lords gratious fauour which is without compariſon. What naturall Father euer did as he hath done▪ to ſpare vs which were but his adopted children, hee hath not ſpared his onelie begotten Sonne Chriſt Jeſus. So that to vs ward he was woorth his promiſe heere made, but hee hath laide it vppon his naturall ſonne with a witneſſe 
                     〈◊〉
                   our ſakes. He was faine to reſigne a royall kingdome to come to an Aſſes cribbe: to relinquiſh the ſweete ſocietie of Angels, to liue among malitious rakehels, the Scribes and Phariſees: to ſurrender a throne of glory, for a curſed croſſe of wood: to yéelde vp a crowne of bliſſe, for a crowne of thornes: to looſe the fauour of his heauenly father, to pleaſure his deadly foes: and to ſuffer death, that miſerable wretches might be ſpared and ſaued aliue. O kind and tender Sauiuiour,

to ſpare and to ſaue vs, thou haſt ſuffered thy ſelfe to become a very ſpoile for the malice of Sathan.
               I graunt you Fabius Maximus was verie deſirous to ſpare and ſaue the Romane Captiues, when hee ſolde all his patrimony to redéeme them. But our Sauiour Chriſt hath ſuffered himſelfe to be ſolde, to redéeme vs his very enemies in reſpect.
               
                  Mithridates was wondred at for his tender affection toward Leonicus his deere frend, becauſe hee gaue all the Rhodian captiues to redeeme him: but yet he gaue his enemies to redéeme his friend. But Chriſt Jeſus our bleſſed Sauiour, hath giuen himſelfe to redeeme his enemies.
               To bee ſhort, when there was in Rome a ſodaine gaping gulph which they could by no meanes fill vp, and the Oracle had ſignified, that except the chiefeſt thing, and that which the commons loued beſt, were caſt into it, it could not be ſtopped: Curtius vnderſtanding that he himſelfe was their onely Jewel, without any more adoe threw himſelfe into it, and ſo it was fild vp preſently. Yet this was done for his country, that loued him ſo well, that they accounted nothing better or more worthy thē hée. But when ye gaping gulph of Gods moſt dreadfull vengeance was to bee ſtopped,

our bleſſed ſauiour caſt himſelfe into the middeſt of it, and died a moſt bitter death, &amp; this he did for the people, which thought they had nothing worſe or more vile than hee, no not Barrabas that arrant cutthroat.
               What ſhall I ſay then of this ſo rare, ſo royall, ſo vnſpeakeable, and ſo incomparable loue of his towards vs? I can ſay no leſſe than Barnard ſaid, Opus ſine exemplo, gratia ſine merito, charitas ſine modo: Such a worke as hath no example, a fauour without deſert, and loue without meaſure.
               The Lord therefore graunt that ſuch bottomles compaſſion in him may preſently work ſome thankfull compunction in you. And that as the vaile of the temple rent in ſunder from the toppe to the bottome, when theſe thinges were performed: So the conſideration of the extreame miſerie which hée endured, that hée might ſpare and ſaue our forlorne ſoules, may ranſacke euery vaine in our hearts in all due remorſe. And y• as the very earth did quake in horrour of ſo great violence wrongfully offered to him, and méekely ſuffered for you: So our heartes and conſciences may quake and tremble, conſidered that an innocent perſon hath endured the ſame to ſpare our guilty and damned ſoules.
               To him therefore, which hath ſo entirely

oued vs, that he hath not ſpared his onely begotten Sonne to ſaue vs: and to him which hath ſo dearely bought vs, that hee hath layde downe his life to redeeme vs: and to him that hath ſo wonderfully purged and ſanctified vs through the Lauer of regeneratiō, that hee hath thereby ſealed vs vntill the day of Redemption: id eſt, to God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt three diſtict perſons and one euerlaſting God, bee al praiſe, power and dominion, world without end.
               Amen.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

