
   
      
         
            Sir Francis Drake his honorable lifes commendation, and his tragicall deathes lamentation.
            Fitz-Geffry, Charles, 1575?-1638.
         
         
            
               1596
            
         
         Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00823
            STC 10943
            ESTC S105617
            99841344
            99841344
            5920
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00823)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5920)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 226:15)
         
         
            
               
                  Sir Francis Drake his honorable lifes commendation, and his tragicall deathes lamentation.
                  Fitz-Geffry, Charles, 1575?-1638.
               
               [104] p.   
               
                  Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to bee solde in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Bible,
                  At Oxford :
                  1596.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Charles Fitz-Geffrey.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A⁴ B-G.
                  The poems on A3r,v are signed "R.R." and "F.R.". Variant 1: poems signed "Richard Rous" and "Francis Rous". Variant 2: with an additional leaf following A4, with a Latin poem by T. Michelborne.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Drake, Francis, --  Sir, 1540?-1596 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-02
            Celeste NgSampled and proofread
         
            2007-02
            Celeste NgText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            SIR
FRANCIS DRAKE,
His
Honorable lifes commendation,
and his
Tragicall Deathes
lamentation.
*⁎*
            
            Conamur tenues grandia.
            
               AT OXFORD,
Printed by Ioſeph Barnes,
and are to bee ſolde in
Pauls Church-yard
at the ſigne of
the Bible.
1596.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE BEAVTEOVS, AND
vertuous Lady ELIZABETH, late
wife unto the highlie renowmed
SIR FRANCIS DRAKE
deceaſed.
            
            DIvorc'd by Death, but wedded ſtill by love,
            (For love by Death can never be divorced)
            Loe Englands Dragon, thy true turtle Dove,
            To ſeeke her make is now againe enforced.
            Like as the Sparrow from the Caſtrels ire
            Made his Aſylum in the wiſe-mans fiſt:
            So he, and I his tongueſ-man, doe require
            Thy ſanctuarie, Envie to reſiſt.
            So may heroique DRAKE, whoſe worth gave wings
            Vnto my Muſe that nere before could flie,
            And taught her tune theſe harſh diſcordant ſtrings,
            A note above her rurall minſtralſie,
            Live in himſelfe, and I in him may live,
            Thine eies to both vitalitie ſhall give.
            
               Your Ladiſhips vertues devoted,
CHARLES FITZ-GEFFREY,
            
         
         
            
            
            To the Authour.
            
               ONce dead, and twiſe alive, thriſe worthie DRAKE,
               And worthie thou by whome he lives againe:
               O would that thou who him alive doſt make,
               A life unto thy ſelfe by him might'ſt gaine!
               But if thou canſt not get this for thy paine,
               Yet will I offer heart and pen to thee,
               And if one faile, the other thine ſhalbe.
            
            
               Sure one will faile; the other thine ſhalbe,
               Admitting thee into her chiefeſt part;
               Wiſhing that art with nature would agree,
               To ioine an able pen with loving hart,
               That to the world ſhee might her minde impart:
               So hart imagine ſhould, and art indite,
               And art and hart ſhould both thy praiſes write.
            
            
               But now let DRAKE, unto whoſe ſhrine thou ſingeſt
               Theſe lamentable accents on his tombe,
               Retribute part to thee of that thou bringeſt,
               And make thee famous, though himſelfe be dumbe;
               So by thy praiſing, ſhall thy prayſes come:
               Then let thy ſwan-ſweet verſe ſing to a DRAKE,
               And that which makes him, ſhall thee famous make.
            
            
               R. R.
            
         
         
            
            To C. F.
            VVHen to the bankes of ſweete Elyſium
            
            Came worthy DRAKE, to get his paſſage there▪
            
            The ferriman denied his ghoſt to come,
            Before his exequies ſolemniz'd were:
            But none t' adorne his funerall hearſe did prove:
            And long he ſate vpon the hopleſſe ſhoare.
            Vntill thy Muſe (whome pittie ſtill did move)
            Helpt thee to riſe, and him to reſt no more:
            And ſent her mournefull teares unto his ghoſt,
            And ſweete (though ſad) complaintes as exequies,
            Paſſing him to thoſe fields which long he loſt,
            And won his ſoule the ioy, thy pen the priſe:
            So ſtill thy funeralles ſhall adorne his name,
            And 
                  ••
               ll his funeralles ſhall enlarge thy fame.
            
               F. R.
            
         
         
            
            To the Authour.
            
               
                  ENglands Vlyſses, ſlaine by mortall fates,
               His bodie Tethys caught within her armes,
               
                  Jove plac'd his ſoule amid the heavenlie ſtates,
               Setting him free from fortune-toſſing harmes,
               From Scylla's gulfes, and Circes deadlie charmes:
               And both did chuſe a place to keepe his pray,
               
                  Tethys her lap, but Jove the Milke-white Waye.
            
            
               Yet ſhall his fame, his worth▪ his worthy deedes,
               Eterniz'd by thy verſe, amonge us dwell,
               And whatſoever after-age ſucceedes,
               Vnto poſteritie the ſame ſhall tell,
               And make thy prayſes with his owne excell:
               Time that doth all things elſe in time devoure,
               Shall never have thy name within her power.
            
            
               Old GEFFREY CHAVCER, Englands auncient Muſe,
               And mirrour of the times that did enſue,
               Yeelded to death, that nere admits excuſe;
               But now in thee he ſeemes to live a newe,
               (If grave Pythagoras ſage ſawes be true:)
               Then ſith old GEFFREY's ſpirite lives in thee,
               Rightlie thou named art FITZ-GEFFERY.
            
            
               D. W.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            SIR FRANCIS DRAKE
HIS HONORABLE LIFES
commendation, and his
tragicall deathes lamentation.
*⁎*
            
            
               DARKE night, the ſov'raigne of Cymmerian black,
               Th' inhabitant of pitchie Acheron,
               
               Mounted upon Alaſtors ſnaky backe,
               From Taenarus (her blacke pavilion)
               Rides through the world in ſad progreſſion;
               Dew-dropping miſts, and darkeneſſe duſkie bloome
               Attende, as Heraulds, to proclaime her roome.
            
            
               Blinde Veſperugo, cloath'd in ſable ſhade
               (Night's cloudie harbinger, colde Heſperus)
               
               Runs on before to ſee that way be made;
               And being authorized her Prodromus,
               Rides on the Vulture-bearing Caucaſus,
               
               Vailing the golden tapers of the light,
               And bids Olympus entertaine the night.
            
            
               
               Shee briſtling up her leaden-plated creſt
               Of feathers, broader then the dragons wings,
               Whoſe ſpace disioines the Lycaonian beaſt
               From Cynoſure, whoſe praiſe the ſea-man ſings,
               That ſhee as patroneſſe directs his rings;
               Enclaſpeth with her winged eminence
               The worlds orbicular circumference.
            
            
               Now only is ſhee earth's high Monarcheſſe,
               And tirannizeth ore this maſſie rounde;
               For hee, whoſe puiſſance quel'd her monſtrouſneſſe,
               Enchaining her beneath the waightie grounde,
               By deaths fierce Heben trident hath his wounde,
               Repaying unto greedie deſtinie,
               The int'reſt of his life-lent uſurie.
            
            
               Drownd is the day-ſtar in th' Heſperian deepes,
               The radiant Eos of white Albion:
               
               
                  Tithonus love-laſſe, faire Aurora, weepes,
               And day-reducing Phoſphorus doth mone,
               That he unto the other world is gone;
               Denying them the traffique of his ſight,
               From whoſe faire luſtre they deriv'd their light.
            
            
               
               See how Apollo taſks his wearied teames
               Vnto the Occidentall Ax
                     •
                  ltree,
               Making th' Horizon maſke in ſable ſeames,
               Abandoning the earth from mirth and glee,
               Swearing it never more his lamps ſhall ſee,
               But meanes (except the fates his wrath appeaſe)
               To live immur'd amonge th' Antipodes.
               
            
            
               As when he left th' Olympique ſtarrie rocks,
               Living an exile long in Theſsalie;
               
               And neere Amphryſus fed Admetus flocks,
               Onlie accompaned with Mercurie:
               
               Or when for Phäetons ſad tragedie,
               Enrag'd with paſſionate woe he fell at ods
               With thundring Jove, and all the minor-Gods.
            
            
               But now nor Clymenes audacious boy
               Torne by the morning-breathing horſes rage;
               Nor Amyclaean Hyacinth's annoy
               Cauſe this his griefe, impatient of aſſwage;
               Theſe woes long ſince gave place to time and age:
               The paines that now exagitate his ſoule,
               Time cannot tame, nor ſwan-white age controule.
            
            
               
               He, from whoſe ſunne the ſunne deriv'd his ſhine,
               (As doth his ſiſter-planet from his light)
               Whilome than criſtall far more criſtalline,
               Now is oppreſt with deaths eternall night,
               Exempt from intercourſe of Phoebus ſight;
               Who wailes his loſſe, but ſollaced in this,
               That his immortall ſoule ſurvives in bliſſe.
            
            
               The Gods Pandora, heavens bright firmament,
               Faire Albions bulwarke, caſtle of defence,
               The worldes rare wonder, th' earths rich ornament,
               Harts adamant, mindes ſacred excellence,
               Wiſedomes grave Delphos, vertues quinteſſence,
               Right perfect workmanſhip of ſkilfull nature,
               Some ſemi-God, more then a mortall creature.
            
            
               Great God of proweſſe, thunderbolt of war,
               
                  Belionae's darling, Mars of chivalrie,
               Bloudy Enyo's champion, foe-mens feare,
               Fames ſtately Pharus, map of dignitie,
               
                  Joves pearle, pearls pride, prides foe, foes enemie:
               
                  Spaine-ſhaking feaver, regent of wars thunder,
               Vndaunted DRAKE, a name importing wonder.
            
            
               
               All this, yea thriſe a thouſand times and more
               Than this untold, though Angels eloquence,
               Though all the ſoules of Poets heretofore,
               And moderne Muſes made their reſidence
               In mortall mould to pen his excellence;
               More then all arts Arithmetique can ſumme,
               Ay me! are now enclos'd in DRAKES rich tombe.
            
            
               Tombe? ah no tombe, but Neptunes froathing waves:
               Waves? ah no waves, but billow-rouling ſeas:
               Seas? ah no ſeas, but honour's hallowed graves:
               Graves? ah no graves, but bones eternall eaſe:
               Eaſe? ah no eaſe, but reſt borne to diſpleaſe:
               What ere it be where worthy DRAKE doth lie,
               That ſacred ſhrine entombes a Deitie.
            
            
               If Deitie in earth can be enrold,
               Or maie participate with brickle claie,
               Or can be compas'd with ſo fraile a mould,
               Or be inveſted in ſo baſe aray.
               As tranſitorie fleſh borne to decay;
               Then whereſoere it be that DRAKE doth lie,
               That ſacred ſhrine entombes a Deitie.
            
            
               
               If Deitie maie be a thing created,
               The quainteſt workemanſhip of skilfull nature;
               Or by a parliament of Gods enacted,
               Or be appropriated to a creature,
               Omnipotent Joves richeſt architecture:
               Then whereſoere it be that DRAKE doth lie,
               That ſacred ſhrine entombes a Deitie.
            
            
               But if mans ſoule his Deitie define;
               Which is an eſſence metaphyſicall,
               Immortall, heaven-infuſed, and divine;
               And fleſh be but a priſon temporall,
               That for a ſeaſon holdes the ſoule in thrall:
               Then in DRAKES tombe doth this his priſon lie,
               But heavens bright ſhrine containes his Deitie.
            
            
               O who will leade me to that two top't mountaine,
               The Heliconian Muſes laureat hill?
               Who will conduct me to that ſacred fountaine,
               Whence ſoule-infuſing Nectar doth diſtill,
               That Poets ſp'rites with winged furies fill:
               Where naked Graces uſe to bathe and ſwim,
               While Nymphs and Fairies daunce about the brim?
            
            
               
               Where no Actaeon ſtragling through the fields
               Defiles thoſe Dian's with polluted eyes;
               No Pyrenëus this chaſt forreſt yelds,
               Whoſe ſugred words and ſoothing flatteries
               Ioyn'd with conſtraint would cauſe them wantonize:
               No ſuch polluted peſſaunts haunt theſe places;
               For luſt is ſacriledge unto the Graces.
               
            
            
               Phoebus faire wel-ſprings, fountaines criſtall bright,
               Oile of invention, Poets paradiſe,
               Impreſſures of conceite, ſap of delight,
               Soules ſweete Emplaſtrum, unguent of the eies,
               Drops, making men with Gods to ſympathize,
               Baths of the Muſes, Hebes ſugred wine,
               Pure Helicon, the very name divine.
            
            
               Mount me, faire ofſpring of Mnemoſyne,
               
               Vpon Bellerophon's winde-winged ſteede;
               Lift up my leaden ſp'rite, Euphroſyne,
               
               Above the pitch of paſtors rurall reede:
               For he that ſings of matchleſſe DRAKE, had neede
               To have all Helicon within his braine,
               Who in his hart did all heavens worth containe.
            
            
               
               No common theame is ſubiect of my verſe,
               One Muſe cannot ſuffice to pen this ſtorie:
               He that intends DRAKES merites to rehearſe▪
               
               And pen the proceſſe of his famous glorie,
               Should in his hart all Muſes ſpirites carrie:
               Yet all inferiour to his worthines,
               Whoſe ſoule did all the Worthies ſp'rites poſſeſſe.
            
            
               Audacious infant, proud preſumpteous boye,
               That dares preſume to name with faltring tongue,
               And voice vntaught to tune an humble laye,
               A name which thundring Zephyrus hath ſonge,
               And thouſand Echo's through the world have tonge▪
               
               With fames triumphant trumpet often ſpred,
               From th' Artique to th' Antartique famoſed.
            
            
               None but old Atlas heauen-up-holding armes▪
               
               Or greate Alcides adamantine breſt,
               To whoſe exploites all Poets ſinge alarmes,
               Should under-prop the Axel of the weſt,
               And wield the heavē that DRAKES name hath addreſt,
               Whoſe waight will bruiſe the ſhoulders of the weake;
               Let children ceaſe of ſuch exploites to ſpeake.
            
            
               
               Yet may we weepe, although we cannot ſinge,
               And with ſad paſſions volley forth our feares;
               While others accentes in the aire doe ringe,
               Our Anthems may detaine the vulgar eares,
               And what we want in words, ſupplie in teares▪
               
               While Philomela tunes ſweete melodie,
               
                  Progne may weepe her diſmall tragedie,
            
            
               Then you, ſweete-ſinging Sirens of theſe times,
               Deere darlings of the Delian Deitie,
               That with your Angels-ſoule inchauntinge times
               Tranſport Pernaſsus into Britanie,
               
               With learnings garland crowninge Poeſie;
               Sdaine not that our harſh plaints ſhoulde beate your cares:
               Arts want may ſtop our tongues, but not our teares.
            
            
               SPENSER, whoſe hart inharbours Homers ſoule,
               If Samian Axioms be autenticall:
               DANIEL, who well mayſt Maro's text controule
               With proud Plus ultra true note marginall:
               And golden-mouthed DRAYTON muſicall,
               Into whoſe ſoule ſweete SIDNEY did infuſe
               The eſſence of his Phoenix-feather'd Muſe:
            
            
               
               Types of true honour, Phoebus Tripodes,
               
               Hell-charminge Orphêi, Syrens of the ſence,
               Wits ſubſtance, Joves braine-borne Pallades,
               
               Soules Manna, heavens Ambroſian influence,
               True centers of renownes circumference,
               The gracefull Graces faire triplicitie,
               Of moderne Poets rareſt trinarie.
            
            
               Imbath your Angel-feathers loftie quill
               In fluent amber-dropping Caſtalie.
               
               That liquid gold may from your pen diſtill,
               Encarving characters of memorie,
               In braſen-leav'd bookes of eternitie:
               Be DRAKES worth royalized by your wits,
               That DRAKES high name may coronize your writs.
            
            
               Let famous RED CROSSE yeld to famous DRAKE,
               And good Sir GVION give to him his launce;
               Let all the MORTIMERS ſurrender make
               To one that higher did his fame advance;
               Ceaſe LANCASTERS, &amp; YORKES iars to enhaunce;
               Sing all, and all to few to ſing DRAKES fame;
               Your Poems neede no laurell ſave his name.
            
            
               
               Had he beene borne in Agamemnons age,
               Whē ſtout Achilles launce ſcourg'd Troies proud towres:
               When men gainſt mē, and Gods gainſt Gods did rage,
               Aenaeas, Achilles, nor Vliſſes powres,
               
               Had beene ſo famous in this age of ours:
               All Poets would have written in his praiſe
               
                  Their Aeneads, Iliads, and Odyſses.
            
            
               But now (o ſhame!) the vertuous are forgotten,
               Th' Heröes are contemn'd and Neroes told:
               The auncient orders all are dead and rotten;
               Gone is the puritie of Poets old,
               And now eternitie is bought and ſold:
               Free Poeſie is made a marchandize,
               Onlie to flatter is to Poetize.
            
            
               Wel-worth Auguſtus laurel crowned times,
               Pure Halcion houres, Saturnus golden dayes,
               When worthies patronized Poets times,
               And Poets times did onlie worthies praiſe,
               Sdaining baſe Plutus groomes with fame to raiſe:
               When now, ſave mercenaryes, few do write,
               And be a Poet is be a Paraſite.
            
            
               
               But you (ſweete ſoules) the Graces trinarie,
               Straine up your tunes with notes angelicall;
               From heavens faire houſe (ô Fames Trium-viri)
               Fetch Orpheus harpe with ſtrings harmonicall;
               And muſicke from the Spheares melodicall;
               And with ſweete quires of Swans, and Nightingals,
               Sing dolefull ditties at DRAKES funerals.
            
            
               My Muſe all mantled in death's livorie gowne
               Shall mourne before his hearſe in ſad araie,
               With ſable Cypariſſus hanging downe
               Her mornefull breſt, whole boughes ſhall fan awaie
               
                  Titans bright beames, bedarkning all the daie:
               And while with teares you ſit melodying,
               Shee ſhall weepe with you, though ſhee cannot ſing.
            
            
               Even as the Larke, when winters waſt drawes neere,
               Mounteth her baſinetted head on high,
               And through the aire doth tune her trebles cleere
               Quav'ring full quaintlie forth her Tireli,
               Beyond the ken of any piercing eie;
               While as the Red-breſt on an humble thorne,
               With weeping notes the ſummers loſt doth mourne.
            
            
               
               Yee that attend on Cytherea's traine,
               And feede her ſilver-feathered turtle-doves,
               Which in their golden-wired cage remaine,
               Whether at Paphos ſhrine or Cnydus groves;
               Whoſe livet-laps do ſwell with full-vain'd loves,
               While damoſell Ladies doe imparadize
               Your thoughts within the Eden of their eies.
            
            
               Whoſe Muſe is ſo inraviſh'd with the lookes
               Which from your Miſtreſſe ivorie browes do fall.
               As makes you fill the largeſt volum'd bookes
               With ſoule-perſwaſive ſongs patheticall,
               And minde-alluring ſpeech methodicall;
               Taſking your pens to pen a womans praiſe,
               And ſhee the actreſſe of your owne diſeaſe.
            
            
               O let your Muſe make an Apoſtrophe
               From Venus courts unto Bellona's camps;
               Give but a glance on DRAKES high dignitie,
               Impreſt with magnanimities true ſtampes:
               And when your ſence is lightned with theſe lamps,
               Solemnize to the world his funerals,
               In all your ſonnets and your Madrigals.
            
            
               
               Ceaſe (fondlings) henceforth to idolatrize
               With Venus, your Carpathean-ſea-borne Queene;
               And to heroique DRAKE do ſacrifice
               Of expiation for your former ſinne,
               Erect his ſtatue whereas hers hath beene;
               Make DRAKE your Saint, and make the ſhrine, his hearſe;
               Your ſelves the Prieſts, the ſacrifice your verſe.
            
            
               O you the quaint tragedians of our times,
               Whoſe ſtatelie ſhanks embuskind by the Muſes,
               Draw all the world to wonder at your rimes;
               Whoſe ſad Melpomene robs Euripides,
               
               And wins the palme and price from Sophocles:
               
               While Poe and Seine are ſick to thinke upon▪
               
               How Thames doth ebbe and flowe pure Helicon.
               
            
            
               Who at your pleaſures drawe, or elſe let downe
               The floud-hatches of all ſpectators eies;
               Whoſe ful-braind temples deck't with laurell crowne,
               Ore worlds of harts with words do tirannize;
               To whome all Theaters ſing Plaudities:
               While you with golden chaines of wel-tun'd ſonges.
               Linke all mens eares and teares unto your tongues.
            
            
               
               Ceaſe to eternize in your marble verſe
               The fals of fortune-toſſed Veneriſts;
               And ſtraine your tragicke Muſes to rehearſe
               The high exploites of Iove- borne Martialiſts,
               Where ſmoakie gun-ſhot clouds the aire with miſts;
               Where groves of ſpeares pitch'd ready for to fight,
               Dampe up the element from Eagles flight.
            
            
               What neede you ſummon from the ſilent hell
               The ſoules of Hector and of Priamus,
               
               And thouſand others that beneath us dwell,
               Wafted long ſince through Styx to Erebus,
               
               Or to th' Elyſian Tempe glorious?
               Whoſe acts by auncients often have beene told,
               And all love novels, few like that is old.
            
            
               Loe heere a moderne ſubiect for your wits,
               But loftier than anie heeretofore
               Eternized by former Poets writs;
               Whoſe worth their ſacred Muſes did adore,
               And he ſcarſe entred yet th' Elyſian dore;
               Whom dead, yet all mens thoughts alive doe make:
               For who wold think that death could cōquere Drake▪
                  
               
            
            
               
               Heere Poets, ſpend your wits chiefe quinteſſence,
               And bandie verſes with the God of verſe,
               Imbalme him with your wits beſt influence,
               All intellectual powres his praiſe rehearſe,
               And with your poems bewtiſie his hearſe:
               Feare neither Theons tooth, nor Critique lookes,
               DRAKES onlie name ſhall patronize your bookes▪
               
            
            
               Be DRAKES heroique deedes the argument,
               His name the prologue of your tragedie,
               The acts and ſcenes, his acts all excellent,
               Himſelfe chiefe actor of Spaines miſery,
               His launce the Scorpion-ſcourge of Heſperie;
               
               Fettring with golden chaines their principates,
               And leading captive Spaines chiefe potentates.
            
            
               The Muſes hill ſhalbe the Theatre,
               And all the world ſpectators of the ſhowes,
               A quire of Angels ſhall the Chorus beare,
               The maſſacre ſhalbe of Englandes foes,
               And ſuch as thinke to worke Eliza's woes:
               And when DRAKES death ends the Cataſtrophe,
               Heaven ſhall clap handes, and give the Plaudite.
            
            
               
               But ah! our daies are ſtampt in envi's mint,
               And this our age caſt in the yron mould,
               Our hearts are hew'd out of Caucaſean flint,
               And two-leav'd plates of braſſe our breaſts enfold;
               Hate waxeth yong, the world thus waxing old:
               And beſt wee like them that doe love us leaſt,
               And leaſt we love them whome we ſhould like beſt.
            
            
               Impietie of times, vertues cheefe hater,
               The dying worlds twiſe-infant-waxen dotage,
               Worth's cankar-worme, deſert's ingrate abater,
               Hard yron-ages death-declining ſottage,
               Foule ſerpent-eating envi's loathſome cottage:
               Poyſon-tooth'd viper, impiouſly that bites
               The wombe of thoſe who are her favorites.
            
            
               Falſe touch-ſtone, not diſcerning gold from braſſe,
               Falſe ſooth-ſayer, divining alway lies,
               Falſe clocke, not telling how the day doth paſſe,
               Falſe friend, forſaking in adverſities,
               Falſe pilot, leading through extremities,
               Falſe in election, falſe in amitie,
               And only true in infidelitie.
            
            
               
               Such is the worlde, as one that dotes with yeares,
               Loathinge things preſent, though of greater price,
               Liking that which is paſt and not appeares,
               And ſaies, the elder age was far more wiſe,
               Of higher worth, and of more ſound adviſe:
               All that it ſees, it think's not worth the ſight,
               But what it wants, it craves with maine and might,
            
            
               Bleare-eyed elde, not ſeeinge dark from day,
               Blinde with affection, ignorant of truthe,
               Vnwain'd from ſelfe-love, never at a ſtaye,
               Leaning upon the crabbed ſtaffe of ruthe;
               Vntoward to forecaſt for that enſueth,
               Iniurious to thoſe that moſt befriend it,
               Obſequious to thoſe that moſt offend it.
            
            
               The auncient nobles are moſt noble deem'd,
               And in Fames calender Saints regiſtred,
               While preſent worthies vaſſals are eſteem'd,
               Though worthier to be canonized
               Than thoſe that are in Legendaries red:
               Nor Hercules, nor Mars were Gods accounted,
               Before they died, and unto heaven were mounted.
            
            
               
               What marvell then though ſome baſe humoriſts,
               Foule whelps of fierce Hyrcanean tygars ſeedes,
               Extenuate the worth of lovialiſts,
               And ſuch as merite heaven by famous deedes,
               Returning baſe diſdaine for worthy meedes:
               Oule-ſighted eies, that dazled are with light,
               But ſee acutelie in the darkeſome night.
            
            
               Some ſuch there are, (ô ſhame! too great a ſumme!)
               Who would impeach the worth of worthy DRAKE,
               With wrongfull obloquies ſiniſter doome,
               And eagerly their ſerpent-tongues they ſhake,
               And ſith they cannot ſting, a hiſſing make:
               But he, who made all Spaine quake with his fame,
               Shall quell ſuch muſh-rumps onlie with his name.
            
            
               Monſters of nature, Nile-bred Crocodiles,
               Sight-ſlaying Baſilisks, poyſon-ſwolne toades,
               Fame-fretting cankers, ſhames infectious biles,
               Earth-gaping Chaſma's, that miſhap aboades,
               Preſumpteous gyants, waging war with Gods:
               Aire-putrifying Harpyes loathſome broode,
               
                  Echidna's ofſpring, ſworne foes to the good.
            
            
               
               Theſe ſerpents mouths with tongues &amp; teeth are filled,
               With tongues they ſting, with teeth they fiercely bite;
               By ſtinging, mindes; by biting, hearts are killed;
               The mindes with griefe, the hearts with deadly ſpighte:
               This ſpighte kils ioie, this griefe doth ſlay delight.
               O what fierce hell begot this monſtrous kinde,
               Whoſe toūg, whoſe teeth, kils, ſlaies, the hart, the mind?
            
            
               Their breſt, the harbour of an envious hart;
               Their heart, the ſtore-houſe of a pois'ned hate;
               Their hate, the quiver holding ſlanders dart;
               That dart they ſhoote at men of higheſt ſtate;
               That ſtate, that ſoone is ſubiect to debate:
               And that debate breeding diſſention,
               Procures all common-wealth's deſtruction.
            
            
               Their heades lay complots, ſtrife how to procure:
               Their hands do practiſe what their heades deſire:
               Their hearts approove what hands have put in ure:
               Their mindes in miſchiefe with their harts conſpire:
               Their ſoules conſent to that their mindes require:
               Who will not ſaie they are ſpronge from the devill.
               Whoſe heads, hands, harts, whoſe minds, whoſe ſoules
are evill?
            
            
               
               Celeſtiall Goddeſſe, eviternall Fame
               
                  Minerva's daughter by faire Maia's ſonne,
               Of all th' inhabitants of heavens faire frame
               Moſt highlie honord ſince the world begonne,
               And ſhalbe, till the fatall Glaſſe be runne;
               Soules ſweete receipt, the health's reſtorative,
               Hearts cordiall, the mindes preſervative:
            
            
               Goddeſſe of thoughts, Muſe animating ſpirite,
               Aulter of honour, temple of renowne,
               Shrine of devotion yeelding art her merite,
               Lifes richeſt treaſure, vertues gorgeous gowne,
               Heavens beſt habilement, Ariadne's crowne;
               The Cynoſura of the pureſt thought,
               Faire Helice, by whom the heart is taught:
            
            
               Send honour downe (ô chiefe of Goddeſſes,)
               Honour thy royall perſons meſſenger,
               To raviſh DRAKE from earth's unworthines,
               (As Jupiter once ſent his armour-bearer
               To tranſport Ganimed from Ida thither:)
               And as that boy was honoured of Jove,
               
               So honour DRAKE, and let him be thy love.
            
            
               
               Daughter of time, ſincere Poſteritie,
               Alwaie new borne, yet no man knowes thy birth,
               The arbitreſſe of pure ſinceritie,
               Yet changeable (like Proteus) on the earth,
               Sometime in plentie, ſometime ioyn'd with dearth:
               Alwaie to come, yet alwaie preſent heere,
               Whom all runne after, none come ever neere:
            
            
               Vnpartiall Iudge of all, ſave preſent ſtate,
               Truth's Idioma of the things are paſt,
               But ſtill purſuing preſent things with hate,
               And more iniurious at the firſt than laſt,
               Preſerving others, while thine owne doe waſt:
               True treaſurer of all antiquitie,
               Whom all deſire, yet never one could ſee:
            
            
               Be thou religious to renowned DRAKE,
               And place him in thy catalogue of ſaints;
               In ſteede of Neptune, God of ſea him make,
               Either to looſe, or binde the windes reſtraints;
               Let ſea-men offer him their vowes and plaintes:
               Envie lives with us, while our ſelves ſurvive,
               But when we die, it is no more alive.
            
            
               
               And you, eternall Joves high progenie,
               Whom at your birth the Gods, your parents, bleſt,
               To conſecrate unto eternitie
               In never-dying regiſters of reſt
               Your ſelves, and others that deſerve it beſt;
               To whom they ſeal'd this chartar at your birth,
               Your ſouls ſhould live in heaven, your fames on earth:
            
            
               
                  Joves deereſt darlings, Gods beſt favorites,
               Saints paragons, of pureſt earth refinde,
               Scorn'd of the world, becauſe heavens chiefe delightes,
               Inheritours of Paradiſe by kinde,
               Which was to you before your birth aſſign'd:
               The golden rings where honours iewels ſhines,
               Whoſe ſun is Fame, heaven Zodiake, you the Signes:
            
            
               Imbathe your Phoenix quils in Nectar ſtreames
               Of milken ſhowrs, that Juno's breaſts did raine,
               Let DRAKES high excellence be all your theames,
               Whereon to ſpend the chiefeſt of your braine,
               His worth in honours pureſt dye engraine;
               That after-ages maie him deifie
               In holie heavens celeſtiall Hierarchie.
            
            
               
               GRINVIL, a name that made Iberia tremble,
               Whom Jove would make the Atlas of the weſt,
               (So well he did his Hercules reſemble)
               Had not a waightier charge his minde poſſeſt;
               For having plac'd him in Elyſian reſt,
               In heavens ſtar-chamber held a Parliament,
               And made him Prorex of his regiment.
            
            
               Well hath his Poet royaliz'd his acts,
               And curiouſlie deſcrib'd his tragedie;
               Quaintlie he hath eternized his facts
               In laſting regiſters of memorie,
               Even coëternall with eternitie:
               So that the world envies his happie ſtate,
               That he ſhould live when it is ruinate.
            
            
               Some fierie Muſe with heavenly heate enflam'd,
               Mount DRAKE likewiſe above the azur'd skie;
               Be not the Eagle Joves thunder-bearer nam'd,
               Let DRAKE poſſeſſe that glorious dignitie,
               Or rather let himſelfe the thund'rer bee,
               And make the world his maieſtie to wonder:
               For who more fit then DRAKE to rule the thunder?
            
            
               
               Hee rul'd earth's thunder while he did ſurvive,
               Which, when he liſt, could make great Neptune quake,
               Angrie with Jove that anie man alive
               Should terrifie, and make his kingdome ſhake;
               But when he heard it was renowned DRAKE,
               He gave to him his trident, and his mace,
               As one more fit to rule that ſtormy place.
            
            
               
                  Spaine trembled at the thunder of his name,
               And when thoſe Gyants proudlie did rebell,
               No thunder-bolt had needed but his fame,
               Their hawtie-minded forces for to quell,
               And ſend them by whole Myriads unto hell;
               That Charon curs'd their comming on ſo faſt,
               And knew not how ſo many could be paſt.
            
            
               The proud Tarteſſian Caligula feares,
               And hides his doating head for very horrour,
               If but DRAKES name doe thunder in his eares:
               And lies aſtoniſh'd with an uncouth terrour,
               Exhaling forth his gaſping breath with dolour,
               While DRAKE (our new Alcides) vanquiſhed
               This Spaniſh Hydra's ever-growing head.
            
            
               
               The Pyrenean cloudie-topped mountaines,
               At his approach, with miſts their faces vail'd,
               The hills ſhed teares, and made encreaſe of fountaines,
               Still fleeting downe the clifts, and never fail'd,
               When through the Ocean waves his navie ſail'd:
               And if cleere waters in the fleete were ſcant,
               He made his foe-mens teares ſupplye the want.
            
            
               Oft did the ſourges, plow'd vp by his ſhip,
               Seeme to ore-whelme the Caſſiterides;
               
               While the Cantabrian-Ocean ſea-nymphs ſkip,
               Together with the faire Nerëides,
               
               And all the lovelie Oceanitides,
               
               Dauncing about to have a ſight of DRAKE,
               Or of his ſhip a lovelie kiſſe to take.
            
            
               As oft as neere the Gades both he ſail'd,
               And by Cape-Sacers ſky-top'd promontory,
               Their heades (like dappers) under waves they vail'd,
               Th' Herculean maine it ſelfe ſeem'd to be ſorry
               Grieving it ſhould ſuch pondrous forces carrie;
               For though it could beare him who bare the ſkye,
               It could not DRAKE, for DRAKE was more thē he.
            
            
               
               The Baleares wiſht them-ſelves unknowne
               Or ioyn'd in league unto the Brittiſh maine,
               Dreading they ſhould by DRAKE be overthrowne,
               And raviſh'd from their neighbour-bordring Spaine,
               
               Whoſe weakned powrs it ſelfe could not maintaine:
               They wiſht ſome God would metamorphoſe them
               To ſea-nymphs, that they might be ſafe from him.
            
            
               
                  Toledo's towres, and Compoſtella's Saint
               Kept not Heſperia ſecure from dreade;
               The towres declind, the Saint with feare was faint,
               Faint Saint, for feare that durſt not ſhew his heade,
               Dreading leaſt greater dangers followed:
               Alas! what could ſuch fearefull Saints prevaile,
               Where ſuch great Joves, as DRAKE, meant to aſſaile?
            
            
               Iberus river in Cantabria
               Oft wiſht he had ſtill kept him under grounde;
               His head-ſpring neere to Juliobrica
               
               Thriſe hid himſelfe, and could no where be founde,
               Thriſe overwhelming, all the land was drown'd,
               For hearing that the conqu'ring DRAKE came by,
               Poore coward river knew not where to flie.
            
            
               
               What profited th' Herculean Calpe now,
               That Titan in the Occidentall line
               Trav'ling unto th' Antipodes belowe.
               Daynes to ſalute him with his radiant ſhine,
               As to the other world he doth decline?
               One meanes to diſpoſſeſſe him of his might,
               Who diſpoſſeſſed Titan of his light.
            
            
               
                  Tagus, thy gold could not redeeme thy feare,
               Nor all thy ſands thy griefe could countervaile;
               DRAKE comes, and leades with him the Gods to war,
               With victorie diſplaied on his ſayle:
               What can thy gold and water now availe?
               Thy precious water ſhall his thirſt alaie,
               Thy gold ſhall ſerve to give his ſouldiers pay.
            
            
               
                  Spaine annuallie prepar'd a royall fleete,
               To ſweepe the ſeas unto the Indian coaſt.
               That comming home they might our Dragon meete,
               And pay him tribute at their proper coſt;
               
                  England, thou had'ſt the gaine, and Spaine the loſt:
               Had he ſurviv'd, Tempe had beene our land,
               And Thames had ſtream'd with Tagus golden ſand.
            
            
               
               Such as the Hyperborean Dragon, was,
               That bare th' inchaunting daughter of the ſunne
               On ſcaled creſt of triple-plated braſſe,
               When through Campania's coaſt he us'd to runne,
               And ceas'd not ranging till his courſe were done;
               But with irrefragable force and might
               Made obſtant lets give waie unto his flight.
            
            
               Such was our Dragon when he liſt to ſoare
               And circuit Amphitrite's watrie bowre:
               The rampant lyon, and the tuſked boare,
               The ravenous tigar borne ſtill to devoure,
               To barre him paſſage never had the powre:
               Whole heards and hoaſts could never make him ſtay,
               His onlie ſight ſuffic'd to make him way.
            
            
               Forth of his noſtrils burning flakes of fire
               (As from an ovens gaping mouth) did flame,
               Wherewith he waſted in his raging ire
               All that oppos'd themſelves againſt the ſame;
               All the ſea-monſters trembled at his name:
               And when it pleas'd him progreſſe through the ſea,
               His fame was herauld to proclaime him way.
            
            
               
               O what an heavenly ſight it were to view,
               And with the eie ſurvey him on the maine,
               Incountring with a prowd Tarteſſian crew,
               The choyſeſt Martialiſts of war-like Spaine,
               
               And ſwarthy Moores, and Indian ſlaviſh traine,
               Mantling all Tethys with their Argoſ eies
               With high-topt maſts included in the skies.
            
            
               Their gallies fraughted full with men of war,
               Whoſe oares plow'd furrowes in the ſwelling waves
               Than towred whales, or dolphins, larger far,
               Of ſiſe ſufficient to be gyants graves,
               Row'd with an hundred Indian captive ſlaves;
               Made glaucie Nereûs groane, and ſeeme to ſhrinke,
               Who often wiſht to ſee their navie ſinke.
            
            
               Sea-caſtles, which they Galeazos nam'd,
               Garded (like bul-warks) all the mightie fleete,
               Whoſe maſts of ſeaven conioyned oakes were fram'd
               By skilfull architecture made to meete,
               Whoſe tops might ſeeme the element to greete:
               Hoyſed aloft their ſailes diſplay'd on high,
               As though they ment to vaile the ſhining skie.
            
            
               
               Who ſo beholding from the bordring ſhoare,
               Had view'd their navie floating on the maine,
               Would ſweare they were no ſhips, that Neptune bore,
               But woods of cedars growing on a plaine,
               Whoſe tops above the region of the raine,
               Were damp'd with circumfuſed clouds from ſight,
               Which no tranſpiercinge eye could ken aright.
            
            
               
                  Neptune encircled in his watry armes
               His ſilver-ſhining darling Albion,
               
               And in his boſome ſhielded her from harmes,
               That might endanger his chiefe paragon,
               Fearing of nothing ſave his louelie one:
               
                  And like as Perſeus kept Andromeda,
               So kept he her from monſters of the ſea.
            
            
               Now had our Dragon rouſ'd him from his cave,
               Againſt his foe-men bending forth his flight:
               All the ſea-ſourges paſſage to him gave,
               Vntill he had his enemies in ſight,
               Gainſt whome he bended all his force and might:
               And in approch the adverſarie deem'd
               That all heavens hoaſt to march againſt them ſeem'd.
            
            
               
               Who ſo had ever ſeene in Arcadye
               
               The Molorchean Lion, through the feilde
               Whole heards of beaſts purſuing eagerlie,
               That none eſcape but ſuch as meeklye yeld,
               Vntill deſire of praie be largely fild:
               He might have iudged how our Dragon rag'd,
               Till full reveng his thirſt had quite aſſwag'd.
            
            
               On ſome he breath'd a fatall-burning fire,
               That blew them up in aſhes to the ſkye:
               Others agaſt, dreadinge his wrathfull ire,
               Duck'd downe their fearefull heades immediatlie
               Vnder the waves to ſave themſelves thereby:
               So that their fleete invincible by fame,
               Chriſtninge anew he gave an other name.
            
            
               As on Vliſſes Circe did beſtowe
               A blather, where the windes imboweld were,
               That at his pleaſure he might let them blowe,
               Or keepe them in when danger did appeare:
               So DRAKE about him ſtill the windes did beare:
               And if miſfortune forc'd ſome ſhips to fall
               
                  Jove into ſea-nimphs did tranſforme them all.
            
            
               
               If fates had fram'd him in the Gyants age,
               When 
                     
                        •
                     erra's highe diſcent made heaven to tremble,
               And Titans broode againſt the Gods did rage,
               Whoſe trumpets (that did thunders noyſe reſemble)
               Whole myriads of monſters did aſſemble;
               Whoſe coale-black enſignes in the ſky diſplayed,
               Out-bearded Jove, and made the Gods diſmayed.
            
            
               When Phloegra's feilds and proud Pellene's coaſt
               Swarmed with troupes of gaſtlie Gyants bands;
               Where ſturdie Typhon generall of the hoaſt,
               Summon'd his kinſmen with the hundred hands
               To come and fight with Jupiter for lands,
               Vnder the conducte of great Briareûs,
               
               
                  With Gya
                     •
                  , Caeus, and Halcyoneûs.
            
            
               Their pondrous waight did make their mother grone,
               Dreading ſhe ſhould be preſſed downe to hell▪
               
               Their father Titan ſeemd him-ſelfe to mone,
               As oft as from their mouths and noſtrels fell
               (Broade, like Abyſsus gulfe where divels doe dwell)
               Forth iſſued mightie clouds of miſtye ſmoake,
               Whoſe duſkie fogs his fierie beames did choake.
            
            
               
               
                  Oſſa they preſſed downe with Pelions waight,
               And on them both impoſ'd Olympus hill;
               Vpon whoſe crooked top (by ſtrength made ſtraite)
               Black pitch'd pavilions all the ſpace did ſpill,
               The which before the ſubtile ayre did fill:
               Which beinge exiled from his proper place,
               Wandred, and could not finde a vacant ſpace.
            
            
               
                  Porphyrio, Crius, and Enceladus,
               
               With Ephialtes, and Polybotes,
               
               
                  Pallas, Lapetus, Clytius, Euritus,
               
               
                  Gration, Agrius, and Argyropes,
               
               With millians moe as big and large as theſe;
               Followed the colours of Typhoeus bands,
               Swearing to batter heaven with their hands.
            
            
               They wore no harneſſe to defend their breſt,
               But marched naked gainſt their foe-mens face;
               They thought their ſkin was armour of the beſt,
               To ſhield them woundleſſe in the eager chaſe:
               Such was the proofe thereof in everie place,
               As ſcarce a thunder-bolt could enter in
               But was rebated with the verye ſkin.
            
            
               
               
                  Typhon, whoſe ribs reſembled cedar trees,
               A quiver full of mountaines by his ſide
               In-ſteede of darts did beare, and at his knees
               Two dragons heads in knotted ioyntes were ti'd,
               Which in their mouths two fierie tongues did hide:
               Againſt whoſe ſting no plaiſter could prevaile,
               Nor Moly, nor Dictamnum once could heale.
            
            
               In ſteede of trumpet, Briareûs did roare,
               And ſtraind his high-reſounding voice aloude;
               Whoſe ougly note a baſe ſo gaſtly bore,
               As when amid the aire ſome uncouth cloude
               Meetes with an other, and together croude
               With ſuch a deadlie-ſounding fearefull voice,
               As heaven and earth doe tremble at the noiſe▪
               
            
            
               Heaven hid his heade, and ſeem'd to flye for feare,
               The daſtard Gods betooke themſelves to flight,
               And vnto Aegypt forth-with made repaire,
               Not daring to encounter them by might,
               But truſting more to flight than vnto fight:
               Neere unto Nilus (hoping ſo to ſcape)
               Each one of them reſum'd a divers ſhape.
            
            
               
               Iove (like a ram) did weare both hornes &amp; wooll,
               (A livorie which of late he gave to manye)
               Hence Ammon yet doth beare a horned ſcull:
               
                  Juno became a cow unknowen to anye,
               To ſave her from the Gyants tirany:
               Men to themſelves their wives enioyned now,
               While he did playe the ſheepe, and ſhe the cow.
            
            
               Swift-footed Mercurye his talars chaunged
               Into the ſerpent-ſlayeinge Ibis winge:
               
                  Venus (turn'd to a fiſh) the ſeaes now raunged,
               Suppoſing that, which firſt her life did bringe,
               Should ſave her life againe from periſhing:
               
                  Phoebe did play the cat, Phoebus the crowe,
               
                  Bacchus diſguiſed like a goate did goe.
            
            
               O had victorious DRAKE among them then
               In heaven (as now he is) beene deifi'd,
               They needed not have dreaded mortall men,
               Nor for a world of Gyants have deni'd,
               Their God-heads, and, like cowards, in caves abide.
               DRAKE ſhold have pierc'd thē with his burning darts,
               Though all their thunder could not wound their harts.
            
            
               
               Not to a fearefull ramme, or feeble cow,
               But to a dragon DRAKE himſelfe ſhould turne;
               From whoſe fierce noſtrils flakes of fire ſhould flow,
               That in a moment all their tents ſhould burne,
               And headlong from their mountaines overturne
               Their big bon'd carcaſſes to Orcus evils,
               And bid them there wage battaile with the devils.
            
            
               O where is now that cunning Tarentine
               
               
                  Archytas, far renowned for his skill,
               That could Arts pureſt quinteſſence refine,
               And in faire Practiques limbecke at his will
               The pureſt iuyce of Theoriques flowrs diſtill;
               And by proportion Geometrical,
               Make wodden doves to flie, and not to fall?
            
            
               Where is that cunning man of Syracuſe,
               
               The firſt inventour of our Globes and Spheares,
               So deepelie skild in Mathematiques uſe,
               As that whole armies onlie one man feares,
               Whoſe skilfull ſtratagems their might impaires;
               And what a thouſand could not doe by fight,
               One could atchive by arts celeſtiall might?
            
            
               
               Such as were they, ſuch was our worthy DRAKE,
               Whoſe head a ſtore-houſe was of pollicies,
               That (like his valour) forc'd his foes to quake,
               Making their hulkes to caper in the skies,
               And quaver in the aire their Argoſ-eies:
               So by a proper ſleight he knew full well,
               To ſend their ſhips to heaven, their ſoules to hell.
            
            
               Sometime, when number vertue did ſurpriſe,
               (As vertue ſometime is ſurpris'd by number)
               His pollicie could ſoone a waie deviſe,
               To flie their forces that might bring him under;
               And how he could eſcape, it made them wonder:
               For of their Indian gold he made him wings,
               And (like a Phoenix) ſafelie from them flings.
            
            
               Thinke howe the Eagle, armourer to Jove,
               
               Eſpying Ganimede on Ida's plaines,
               Intended to convey him to his love;
               Which being noted by the Phrygian traines,
               And other ſturdie rutters, Troian ſwaines:
               They flocke togither with confuſed cries,
               To reſcue from the bird his lovelie prize:
            
            
               
               An hundred yron-pointed darts they fling,
               An hundred ſtones flie whiſtling by his eares,
               An hundred deadlie-dinted ſtaves they bring,
               Yet neither darts, nor ſtones, nor ſtaves he feares;
               But through the aire his plumed creſt he reares:
               And in deriſion ſafelie ſcapes awaie,
               Preſenting unto Jove his long-lov'd praie.
            
            
               So DRAKE (divine ELISA's champion)
               Ceazing upon a praie of Indian gold,
               Meaning to ſhip it home to Albion,
               
               Ballaſts his barke with treaſures manifold;
               Which when the griev'd Iberians doe behold,
               They ſwarme in troupes to take his prize awaie,
               And to diſrob him of his gained praie:
            
            
               A thouſand hel-mouth'd canons deadly ſhot,
               A thouſand ratling muskets hayle-ſtones flie,
               Yet thouſand deadlie canons hurt him not,
               Nor thouſand ratling muskets reckneth he,
               But ſtill rebeates them all as eagerlie;
               And, maugre all their beards, brings home the ſpoile,
               Ritching ELISA, and ELISA's ſoile.
            
            
               
               Thoſe peereles Peeres, that through the world have ſpred
               Their predeceſſours vertues, and their owne,
               And both with honour have enobeled;
               Who to nobilities chiefe point are growne,
               The ſage attendants on ELISA's crowne;
               Deſir'd to venture on the foe with DRAKE,
               And with his fortunes good or ill partake.
            
            
               When forth they march'd againſt their eager foe,
               HOPE, and REVENGE did beare them out to war;
               Garded with NON-PERILLE did they goe,
               While BONADVENTVRE ſtill their enſigne bare,
               And cowardiſe by DREAD-NOVGHT bandon'd far:
               SWIFT-SVRE their race, though ſwift, yet alway ſure▪
               
               And good FORE-SIGHT to HOPE-WEL did allure.
            
            
               Watchfull ADVISE did march in equipage
               Togither with her ſiſter PROVIDENCE;
               RELIEFE with AYDE, and AYDE with high Courage,
               Courage was guided with Experience,
               And both did guide and garde their high pretence:
               Where all ſuch worthie vertues captaines were,
               What coward would not be a conquerer?
            
            
               
               The ſouldiers followed eager for the fight,
               Knowne to the foe by face, not by the backe▪
               
               Skilfull in fight, but ignorant in flight,
               Swift in aſſault, but in retiring ſlacke;
               Never returning but with foe-mens wracke:
               Who would not be a ſouldier in that band,
               Which, ere it fought, held VICTORIE in hand?
            
            
               Art-tamed TYGARS made waie with their pawes,
               The VNICORN's ſharpe horne the foe did goare,
               The ravenous BEARE with blood imbru'd his iawes,
               The LYONS with their tailes did hurt them ſoare,
               And cut them ſhort for comming once a ſhoare:
               And he that went out WHITE againſt his foe,
               Returnes home RED, for blood imbrued him ſo.
            
            
               A ſilver GRAYHOVND led a GOLDEN-HINDE,
               Now reconciled to his utter foe:
               A ROE-BVCKE that did beare a lions minde,
               Togither with DIANA ſtill did goe,
               And dreaded not her darts and murth'ring bowe:
               The PHOENIX in his fleete her neſt did make,
               And HERCVLES himſelfe attended DRAKE.
            
            
               
               GODS-GIFT he had, and God his gift did SPEEDE,
               No miſadventure cros'd, where God did guide,
               Where GOD did SAVE, none other ſalve did neede,
               He ſped the iournie, he did give the tide,
               He ſav'd the fleete from foes inſulting pride:
               How could the enterpriſe ill iſſue have,
               Where GOD himſelfe did guide, did Speed, did Save?
            
            
               FORTVNE her ſelfe was preſent in the fleete▪
               
               But ſtoode not on her fickle-rowling wheele;
               Conſtant ſtabilitie ballaſſed her feete,
               And being conſtant knew not how to reele,
               But rul'd the rudder and direct'd the keele:
               How could miſchance unto that ſhip betide,
               Where FORTVNE was the pilot, and the guide?
            
            
               Garded with theſe aſſociats royall traine,
               Forth marched valiant DRAKE to martiall armes,
               And makes an earth-quake through the coaſts of Spaine,
               
               When as his thundring drumme reſoundes alarmes,
               And roaring trumpets vollie forth their harmes:
               HOPE and REVENGE to warre conducted DRAKE,
               And VICTORIE &amp; TRIVMPH brought him backe.
            
            
               
               Such were magnanimous DRAKES accomplices
               Not of the vulgar, baſe, inglorious ſort,
               But ſuch did follow warres as rul'd in peace,
               Whoſe very names their fortunes did import:
               Such rare adherents did to DRAKE reſort,
               As he that but their ominous names once heard,
               Did either vanquiſht yeeld, or flie affeard.
            
            
               Neither in wars his worth was only knowne,
               (Although his worth was chieflie knowne in warres)
               But all as well at home in peace was ſhowne,
               In moderating publique wealth's affaires,
               As quieting his foes tumultuous iars:
               And as the Lawrell crown'd him conquerour,
               So did the Olive ſhew him counſelour.
            
            
               Like as abroade with unreſiſted armes
               He tam'd his foes prowde inſultations;
               Even ſo at home with lenitie he charmes
               His iarring friendes diſcordant paſſions,
               Reſcu'ing the poore from prowd vexations:
               So all his life he made a warfare longe,
               Abroade gainſt enimies, at home gainſt wronge.
            
            
               
               In warre he ſtrove (and ſtriving ſtill did gaine)
               To vanquiſh all with never daunted might:
               In peace he ſought (and ſeeking did obtaine)
               All to excell in equity and right:
               A iuſticer in peace, in warre a knight:
               Though hard it were for him that might take eaſe,
               
                  Scipio to be in war, Cato in peace.
            
            
               The mighty ſonne of more than mightie Jove,
               
               Heaven-bearing Hercules, moſt famoſed
               For twelve atchivements, and diſaſter love
               Of Deianira being captived,
               After ſo many monſters vanquiſhed,
               Having ſubdu'd all monſters ſaving one,
               (Woman) ordain'd to maſter him alone.
            
            
               Heaven-honor'd Poets in eternall verſe,
               Among his many brave atchivements done,
               As not the laſt, nor leaſt acte do rehearſe
               His faire fame (though by filthy ſervice wonne)
               Making th' Augaean Oxe-ſtall ſhine as ſunne;
               (Which more then thirty yeares vnclenſ'd had bin)
               By forcing of Alpheus river in.
            
            
               
               Equall with Hercules in al, ſave vice,
               DRAKE of his country hath deſerved grace,
               Who by his induſtrie and quaint deviſe
               Enforc'd a river leave his former place,
               Teaching his ſtreames to runne an uncouth race:
               How could a ſimple current him withſtand,
               Who all the mightie Ocean did command?
            
            
               Now Plymmouth (great in nothing, ſave renowne,
               And therein greater far, becauſe of DRAKE)
               Seemes to diſdaine the title of a towne,
               And lookes that men for cittie ſhould her take;
               So prowd her patrons favour doth her make:
               As thoſe, whom princes patronage extold,
               Forget themſelves, and what they were of old.
            
            
               Her now-bright face, once loathſomly defilde.
               He purg'd and clenſed with a wholeſome river:
               Her, whom her ſiſter-citties late revilde,
               Vp-brayding her with her unſavory ſavor,
               DRAKE of this opproby doth now deliver:
               That if all Poets pens conceald his name,
               The waters glide ſhould ſtill record the ſame.
            
            
               
               Now Fame, the Queene of immortalitie,
               Sommons my Muſe from home-atchieved praiſe,
               (Abandoning all partialitie,
               A fatall ſinne to Poets now adaies)
               Her leaden-winged creſt aloft to raiſe,
               And ſoare, in famous DRAKES memoriall,
               About the compaſſe of this earthly ball.
            
            
               Honour enmoves her to attempt the flight,
               And wave her feathers (unneath taught to flie)
               But faint deſpaire doth urge her feeble might
               (That durſt not yet her home-bred neſt out-prie)
               About the world to ſoare audaciouſlie:
               Honour replies, that if ſhee chance to faile,
               The brave attempt the ſhame ſhall countervaile.
            
            
               Bound on an high adventure ſhee intends
               To tell the world that all the world can tell,
               How all the triple earth's unbounded ends,
               And landes where no inhabitants do dwell,
               Where darke obſcuritie ſtill keepes his cell,
               Whereas the ſunne dares ſcarce appearance make,
               Have heard, and ſeene the fame of famous DRAKE.
            
            
               
               Whoſe heaven-affecting thoughts could not remaine
               Confin'd within the confines of the earth,
               But ſtill contended higher to attaine,
               Since that the ſtars portended at his birth,
               His praiſes plentie neu'r ſhould feele a dearth,
               But growe to that high exaltation
               Of all the worlds peregrination.
            
            
               A GOLDEN-HYNDE, led by his art and might,
               Bare him about the earth's ſea-walled round,
               With un-reſiſted Roe-out-running flight,
               While Fame (the harbinger) a trumpe did ſound,
               That heaven and earth with echo's did abound;
               Echo's of DRAKES high praiſe, praiſe of his name,
               Name royalis'd by worth, worth rais'd by fame.
            
            
               Heart-ſtealing Homer, marrow of the Muſes,
               Chiefe grace of Greece, beſt pearle of poetrie.
               Drowner of ſoules with arts ore-whelming ſluces,
               Embelliſhed with Phoebes lunary,
               Deck't with the Graces rich embroyderie,
               Sweete hony-ſuckle, whence all Poets ſp'rites,
               Sucke the ſweete honie of divine delightes:
            
            
               
               Ceaſe to ſolemnize Anticleas ſon,
               That famous Ithacenſian roavers praiſe,
               (Who greate Achilles armes from Aiax won)
               His hard adventures, and his weary waies,
               His wandring pilgrimages through the ſeas:
               His dangerous travels, and his ten yeeres toyles,
               Diſcovering new-found lands, and vncoth ſoyles.
            
            
               Firſt, how he bare himſelfe ten yeeres at Troie,
               
               And ſlew by ſkill the two Dardanian ſpyes;
               How from his foes he raviſhed with ioy
               Their tall Palladium by quaint pollicies,
               (Where Priams hart, and hope, and helpe relyes:)
               Then, how he ſpent ten other yeeres at ſea,
               Before to Ithaca he found the waie.
            
            
               Raſe forth his name out of the Odyſſes,
               
               Be hee no more the ſubiect of thy verſe;
               But let thy Muſe record DRAKES worthines,
               And in Vlyſſes lieu his fame rehearſe,
               That far beyond Vlyſses fame did pearſe:
               Searching the confines of this earthy round,
               And provinces, that carſt were never found.
            
            
               
               Tell how he bare the round world in a ſhip,
               A ſhip, which round about the world he bare,
               Whoſe ſaile did winged Eurus flight out-ſtrip,
               Scorning tempeſtuous Bore as ſtormy dare,
               Diſcrying uncouth coaſts, and countries rare:
               And people, which no eie had ever ſeene,
               Save Daies faire goldē Eie, &amp; Nights bright Queene.
            
            
               Tell how he hath eſcaped warilie
               Loud-barking Sylla's ever-howling dogs,
               And ſeal'd his eares, and lips up charilie
               Gaynſt Syrens ſongs, and Circes poiſned drugs,
               That metamorphoſe men to uglie hogs:
               Nor Syrens ſongs, nor Circes drugs he feares,
               Vertue had lock'd his lips, art ſeal'd his eares.
            
            
               Tell how he paſs'd Charybdis whirle-poole waves,
               Whereas two mightie roaring chanels meere,
               To ſwallow ſhips, and make their wombe their graves,
               And cauſe their high-top't maſts the gravell greete;
               Tell how Caphareûs could not hurt his fleete:
               Neither the ſtraights, nor quick-ſands him amated,
               Nor waves, nor windes his valour once abated.
            
            
               
               
                  Homer tell how; but ah, how canſt thou tell
               
                  Homer, how DRAKE to purchaſe glorye wonted,
               Since that ſweete ſp'rite that in thy ſoule did dwell,
               And that ſweete ſoule, ſweete above all ſoules counted,
               Longe ſince to ſoules ſweete paradiſe is mounted;
               Wher thou with DRAKE to ſaints doſt ſing DRAKES praiſe,
               Heere we bewaile his loſſe, our deepe diſeaſe.
            
            
               O thou ſo high renowned for thy art,
               In memorizinge baſe atchivements don
               By one that bare a fearefull hares faint hart,
               While ſubtle foxes heade his credit won;
               O had thy Muſe once ſhin'd with DRAKES bright ſun,
               Or had thy golden verſe his praiſe recounted,
               
                  Homer himſelfe had Homer far ſurmounted.
            
            
               Thy glorie, DRAKE would more have glorified,
               His travell eaſed thee, that eaſed it,
               In him thy ſelfe thou hadſt hiſtorified,
               His fame would raiſe thy Muſe, that raiſed it,
               His name would praiſe thy verſe, that praiſed it,
               That after-ages ſhould a queſtion make,
               Wheth'r DRAKE grac'd Homer more, or Homer DRAKE.
            
            
               
               Marke how a civet-ſmellinge damaſke roſe,
               In laurel-leaved garland quaintlie placed,
               Yelds bewtie to the baie, where beſt it ſhoes,
               And nether by the other is defaced,
               But graceth that wherewith it ſelfe is graced:
               So each the other ſhould more famous make,
               DRAKE Homer ſhould adorne, and Homer DRAKE.
            
            
               The fierie-ſparkling precious Chryſolite,
               Spangled with gold, doth moſt tranſplendent ſhine:
               The pearle grac'd by the ring, the ring by it,
               The one the others bewtie doth refine,
               And both together bewties both combine,
               The iewell decks the golden haire that weares it.
               Honour decks learning that with honour rears it.
            
            
               Valour, and art are both the ſonnes of Jove,
               
               Both brethren by the father, not the mother,
               Both peeres without compare, both like in love,
               But art doth ſeeme to be the elder brother,
               Becauſe he firſt gave life unto the other:
               Who afterward gave life to him againe,
               Thus each by other doth his life retaine.
            
            
               
               Art is nobilities true regiſter,
               Nobilitie arts champion ſtill is ſayde;
               Learning is fortitudes right calender,
               And fortitude is learnings Saint &amp; ayde:
               Thus if the ballances twixt both be way'd,
               Honour ſhields learning from all iniurie,
               And learning honour from blacke infamy.
            
            
               Why ſhould Vlyſſes be oppoſ'd to DRAKE?
               DRAKE, that Vlyſses worth exceld ſo farre,
               As Hyperion's golden chariots ſlacke
               Surmounts his ſilver ſiſters two-wheel'd carre;
               Or as her planet doth the ſmalleſt ſtarre:
               DRAKE did Vlyſſes worth exceede ſo farre,
               As ſun exceedes the moone, the moone each ſtarre▪
               
            
            
               
                  Vlyſses was conſtrain'd to go to Troye,
               
               DRAKE unconſtrain'd, except conſtrain'd by fame:
               
                  Vlyſses fayning fury fayne would ſtaye,
               A heavenly fury DRAKES minde did inflame,
               To purchaſe glory to Elyſa's name:
               He mad among his friends, milde with his foes;
               But DRAKE was mild to them, and mad with thoſe.
            
            
               
               Both left their ladyes, fayre, &amp; chaſt: (a wonder:)
               O who could leave a ladye chaſt and fayre!
               But fortune for a while their loves did ſunder;
               That ſundred love could never love impayre:
               
                  Vlyſses left a ladie with an heyre:
               DRAKE left a ladie bounteous, fayre, and wiſe,
               For whoſe ſweete love the Gods would leave the ſkies.
            
            
               
                  Vlyſses did the innocent betraye,
               And in extreames forſooke his aged frinde;
               No ſuch defaults did ever DRAKE bewraye:
               This difference betweene them both I finde,
               Wherein greate DRAKE Vlyſses came behinde;
               
                  Vlyſſes Homer had to pen his ſtorie,
               DRAKE hath no Homer to emblaze his glorie.
            
            
               Envie her ſelfe is forc'd to ſay the truth,
               (And yet the truth doth envie ſeldome ſay)
               Since Brute train'd hither firſt the Troian youth,
               (If ever Brute train'd hither youth of Troye)
               
               The ſmall remaynder of the Greekes deſtroye,
               Noblye diſcended from a vertuous line:
               Noble diſcents make vertue more divine.
            
            
               
               How ſtill the ſilver rockes of Albion,
               
               Lightned tranſlucent luſtre from the ſhoare,
               (Like to the carbuncles that ſhine upon
               The faire ſunnes golden pallace ivorie dore)
               Whoſe radiant ſplendour, and whoſe beauties lore,
               Vpon the world's extreameſt wals reflect,
               Dazling the eies that gaze on ſuch aſpect.
            
            
               How that their loftie mindes could not be bounded
               Within the cancels, that the world doe bound;
               How that the deepeſt ſeas they ſearch'd, and ſounded,
               Beyonde all landes that ever have beene found,
               Making the farmoſt ſeas our praiſe reſounde:
               And nations, which not Fame her ſelfe had ſeene,
               To carrol Englands fame, and fames rare Queene.
            
            
               How they have travers'd ſundrie forraine lands,
               Lands, all inviron'd with the ſwelling ſeas,
               Seas, ignorant of endes, devoide of bands,
               Bands, that might yeelde ſome harbour to their eaſe,
               Eaſe, to refreſh them in their wearie waies:
               Lands, bands, ſeas, waies their mindes amated not,
               By lands, bands, ſeas, and waies they honour got.
            
            
               
               Vnto the confines of Aſſyria
               
               Honour led princely EDWARD, (HENRIES ſonne,
               The third that did the Engliſh ſcepter ſway)
               Whoſe brave atchievements both in Acra donne,
               And Galile, when Nazareth was wonne,
               Inroles in ancient recordes of renowne,
               The tributorie fame to Englands crowne.
            
            
               Rich hart of Lyon, RICHARD Lyon-hart,
               
               Twiſe match'd by name, but never in renowne:
               Two more in RICHARDS title bare a part,
               But none ſave hee (that wore the Engliſh crowne)
               The name of Lyon-hart claim'd as his owne:
               His hart was richeſt, that a lyons was,
               Save her rich hart, whoſe hart all harts doth paſſe.
            
            
               
                  Tancred can tell, and all Sicilia,
               
               But moſt Meſſana his great victories,
               The coaſtes of Paleſtine and Syria,
               
               And Cyprus captivated Emprour's eies,
               Sawe him attir'd in triumphs iollities:
               And on the Pagans, in defence of Syon,
               
               His launce bare witnes, that he was a Lyon.
            
            
               
               
                  Clio her ſelfe (I feare) would be offended,
               And whip me downe with laurell from her mount,
               If WILLIAM Peregrine be not commended,
               If I ſhould not that pilgrims praiſe recount
               In verſe, who did in verſe ſo far ſurmount:
               Since thou wert that I am not, but would bee,
               How can I not (ſweete Poet) write of thee?
            
            
               Brave LONG-SWORD in the coaſtes of Aſia,
               
               Diſplai'd the enſigne of the Engliſh fame;
               And neere Nile-bord'ring Alexandria,
               
               Engrav'd with ſteeled ſword faire Albions name
               In characters, which valours art did frame;
               Where gainſt the Saracens (who Chriſt defied)
               He boldly dying fought, and fighting died.
            
            
               Renowned MADOCKE, Princes ſonne of Wales,
               
               Brave Cambro-britton uncontrol'd by might,
               Blowne by ſucceſſfull fortunes proſperous gales,
               In diſcontentment (moſt victorious knight)
               Left his rich Princedome, left to him by right,
               Betweene his brethren in diſſention:
               A crowne twixt brethren breedes contention.
            
            
               
               Before COLVMBVS ere ſet foote in Inde,
               
               He did diſcover Nov' Hiſpania;
               
               Before VESPVCIVS liv'd, did MADOCKE finde
               The world, cald after him America;
               
               He ſaw the famous Terra Florida:
               
               Little regarding all their gaine and ſtore,
               Honour he gain'd, and MADOCKE ſought no more.
            
            
               What coaſt or countrie knowes not MANDEVIL,
               His pilgrimage of three and thirtie yeeres,
               A vowed votarie to honour ſtill,
               Vnequaliz'd by valours chiefeſt peeres?
               Whoſe travels legend whoſoever heares,
               May doubt (if men for merites ſainted bee)
               Which ſhould be Albons ſaint, ALBANE or hee.
            
            
               Couragious CABOT, brave Venetian borne,
               Foſtred with honour-breathing Engliſh aire,
               Victorious, HENRIES name the more t'adorne,
               And to emblazon Troynovant the faire,
               Vnto the farmoſt climates made repaire;
               And by the Southern and Septentrion,
               Meaſur'd the fame of famous Albion.
               
            
            
               
               Light-leſſe and name-leſſe Prima-viſta laie,
               Till from his eies it borrowed name and light;
               
                  Flora did never Florida aray,
               Roſes, nor lillyes ſhew'd their ſhining ſp'rite,
               Till it was ros'd and lilied with his ſight:
               Thriſe happy ſight that verdant ſpring compoſes,
               By ſtrewing lands with lillyes, and with roſes.
            
            
               By Labradars high Promontorie Cape,
               Beyond the Iles of Cuba, CABOT ſayl'd,
               Diſcovering Baccalaos uncouth ſhape;
               The mightie Silver-river not conceal'd,
               His tributorie ſandes to him reveal'd;
               Nor ſdained it to be a tributour,
               Vnto the Oceans mightie Emperour.
            
            
               Honour of England, brave SEBASTIAN,
               Mirrour of Brittan magnanimitie,
               Although by birth a right Venetian,
               
               Yet for thy valour, art, and conſtancie,
               Due unto England from thy infancie:
               
                  Venice, thou claim'dſt his birth, England his art,
               Now iudge thy ſelfe which hath the better part.
            
            
               
               WYNDAM, although thy raſh temeritie,
               Haſtning to rendleſſe gaine, gain'd haſtned end;
               And though improvident celeritie,
               Too ſoone accelerated death did ſend:
               Yet ſince ſo far thy valour did extend,
               And death for raſhnes made full ſatiſfaction,
               Why ſhould not fame advance thy valorous action?
            
            
               When valours fire enflam'd young Iſadas,
               
               Raſhlie to venture battaile unregarded;
               His raſhnes by a mulct corrected was,
               But with a crowne his valour was rewarded,
               Becauſe his proweſſe had the Spartans guarded:
               For if by raſhneſſe valour have got honour,
               We blame the raſhnes, but rewarde the valour.
            
            
               Then WYNDAM, though thy high-reſolved thought,
               A hare-brain'd hardiment had ill prevented;
               Yet ſince ſo deere thou haſt this raſhnes bought,
               Which at the fatall rate of death was rented,
               Let envie with miſfortune be contented:
               Had'ſt thou Vlyſſes head to Hectors hart,
               The world a braver peere could not impart.
            
            
               
               With like miſfortune (though unlike adviſe)
               Did fame-enobled WILLOVGHBY intend
               A famous actions hapleſſe enterpriſe;
               
                  Arzina ſaw his lamentable end,
               Which her eternal-winters froſt did ſend:
               Though freezing cold benum'd his vitall flame,
               Heate ſhall not hurt, nor cold conſume his Fame.
            
            
               Fortune not alwaie good, nor alwaie ill,
               Willing to ſhew her mercie with her powre,
               Feaſted on others falles (as ſeem'd) her fill,
               Smil'd with a mild aſpect on CHAVNCELOVR,
               Making herſelfe his dailie oratour:
               Heereby (quoth ſhee) the world ſhall know my powrs,
               How Fortune ſometime laughes, as well as lowres.
            
            
               Forth-with for him a barke her ſelfe ſhee fram'd,
               Inchaunting it with an almightie charme;
               Which ſhee the bliſ-full Bon-adventure nam'd,
               Which winde, nor wave, nor heat, nor cold could harme,
               While her omnipotence the ſame did arme,
               Guiding it ſafelie to Moſcovia,
               
               Safelie reducing it from Ruſſia.
               
            
            
               
               Bold with ſucceſſe, and prowd on fortunes favour,
               Againe his loftie ſailes he doth advaunce,
               Allur'd by ſilvers ſoule-attractive ſavour:
               But fortune (like the moone in change and chaunce,
               That never twiſe doth ſhew like countenaunce)
               At Pettiſlego drench'd him in the ſeaes:
               Thus moſt ſhe hurts, when moſt ſhe ſeemes to pleaſe.
            
            
               O tempt not Fortune, ſhee will not be tempted,
               Her thunder followes, when her lightning's donne;
               Her dangers are fore-ſeene, but not prevented;
               When ſhee doth frowne, thinke ſhee will ſmile anone;
               And when ſhee ſmiles, thinke not her frownes are gone:
               What doth her laughter but her lowr's importune?
               Miſfortune followes him that tempteth fortune.
            
            
               Aske the Wingandicoa ſavages
               They can relate of GRINVILE, and his deedes▪
               
               The Iles of Flores, and Azores, theſe
               Extol his valour and victorious meedes;
               While Spaines grip't hart freſh ſtreams of anguiſh bleeds:
               His worth withall the world his praiſe made even,
               But he ſcorn'd earth, and therefore went to heaven.
            
            
               
               What time out-ſliding thought ſo far could flie,
               As did heroique CAVENDISH drive his ſailes?
               The great Magores kingdome did he ſee,
               Where freezing Boreas rings his northern peales,
               Gainſt whoſe benumming blaſt no heate availes:
               His proweſſe hath beene knowne to Mallaca,
               
               And to her neighbour-bord'ring Bengala.
               
            
            
               Knighted by honour in deſerts faire field,
               Death-ſcorning GILBERT, chronicled by fame,
               To Englands Monarcheſſe did force to yeeld
               The ſavage lande (that New-found now we name)
               Making wilde people milde, ſubmiſſe, and tame.
               O were mens lives unto their praiſes tied!
               Then, noble GILBERT, never hadſt thou died.
            
            
               But curſed fates did croſſe brave CHIDLIES thought,
               (O that brave thoughts by fates ſtill croſs'd ſhould be!)
               Nothing but worth his hungrie humour ſought,
               Nothing but honours Nectar thirſted hee,
               When death untimely did exact his fee:
               But CHIDLIE, that which death took frō thy daies,
               Honour ſhall adde to thine immortall praiſe.
            
            
               
               If ſearching labyrinths inextricable,
               By hard adventures, and ambiguous waies,
               To purchaſe glorie, and renowne be able,
               And meritorious of eternall praiſe;
               Then FROBISHER out-lives the Sybils daies:
               What death tooke from his life, this gives his name:
               Death hath no dart to ſlaie deſerved fame.
            
            
               Out of the concave cavern's of the earth,
               Her golden-oared entrals he deſcri'd,
               Exiling famine, povertie, and dearth,
               Theſe precious bowels having once eſpi'd,
               Where maſſie gold ingorged did abide:
               He recompenſed natures iniurie,
               That gives earth gold, and leaves men povertie.
            
            
               Rich China, and faire Met' Incognita,
               
               Admir'd his valour, and extold his fame,
               
                  Cathaia, and the great America,
               
               The dangerous ſtraights that yet doe bear his name,
               Are monumentall annals of the ſame;
               Annals, wherein poſteritie ſhall reade,
               How fame the living ſalves, revives the dead.
            
            
               
               Now drop my pen in inke of drery teares,
               A name of late of laughter, and of ioye;
               But now (ô death, the agent of our feares!)
               A name of dolour and of dire annoye,
               The ſad memoriall of the fates deſtroye;
               HAVVKINS (ô now my hart cleave thou a ſunder!)
               In naming him (me ſeemes) I name a wonder.
            
            
               Epitome of Gods, heavens conterfaire,
               Fames Pyramis, honours imagerye,
               Highe throne, wherein all vertues made their ſeate,
               True proſpective of immortalitie,
               Faire mirrour of celeſtiall maieſtie:
               White palme, whoſe ſilver boughes inharbour'd reſt,
               Snowe-feath'red ſwan, the Neſtor of the Weſt.
            
            
               
                  Neſtor in wiſedome, art, and pollicie,
               
                  Neſtor in knowledge, ſkyll and prudencie;
               
                  Neſtor in counſell, and in gravitie,
               
                  Neſtor in wit, fore-ſight, and modeſtie,
               
                  Neſtor in might, and magnanimitie:
               O would he had (as he had Neſtors haires)
               Enioyed Neſtors age, and Neſtors yeares!
            
            
               
               A mortall man more then a man of late,
               (If mortall man more then a man maie be)
               Since his lifes calender is out of date,
               And deaths new-yeare exactes his cuſtom'd fee,
               No more a man, nor mortall now is hee:
               No more a man, becauſe of breath bereaven,
               Mortall no more, becauſe a ſaint in heaven.
            
            
               CLIFFORD, a name that ſtill was ominous,
               Prefiguring an high-reſolved minde,
               Victorious, vent'rous, vertuous, valorous,
               Eternall adiunctes to that noble kinde,
               By natures ſecret influence aſſign'd;
               Who can denie that names are ominous?
               For CLIFFORDS name hath ſtill beene valorous.
            
            
               O had he periſh'd in his enterpriſe,
               (As did th' inventour of that braſen beaſt)
               Who firſt that fatall engin did deviſe
               The diſmall Gunne, the actour of unreſt,
               Whoſe thunder-bolts do pearce the ſtrongeſt breſt:
               O had he periſh'd in his mothers wombe,
               And that which gave him life, had beene his tombe!
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
               
               Now is the conſummation of your griefe,
               The fates have ſet full period to your paine▪
               
               He, who on earth was all your hearts reliefe,
               Whoſe abſence you in heaven it ſelfe did plaine,
               (If plaints attach them that in heaven remaine)
               In heaven is now aſſociate of your ioie,
               Your glad, our griefe; your pleaſure, our annoie.
            
            
               You, whoſe exploites the world it ſelfe admired,
               Admire the ſtrange exploites of peereles DRAKE;
               And you whom nether lands nor ſea's have tired,
               Have tir'd your tongues when they rehearſall make
               What hard adventures he did undertake;
               Then if that ſuch Atlantes are too weake,
               What marvell, if this waight our ſhoulders breake?
            
            
               O you once matchleſſe monarches of the ſeas,
               But now advanced to an higher place,
               Inveſted Vice-roy's and high Satrapes,
               In that faire palace neere the milken race;
               O thinke not that his praiſe doth yours deface:
               If he be iuſtlie prais'd, you iuſtlie graced,
               Your graces by his praiſe are not defaced.
            
            
               
               What though his worth above yours is extold?
               Yet thereby is not yours extenuated:
               What though your neighbours iewels dearer ſold,
               Than for the price whereat your gemme is rated;
               What thereby is your Diamond abated?
               Wherefore to give both him and you your due▪
               
               I ſaie he was the beſt, the next were you.
            
            
               Like as ſome travel-tired paſſenger,
               By ſilent-ſliding Thames roſe-ſhadow'd ſide
               (Poore care-accloyed pilgrime traveler,)
               Sits downe to view the ſight-reviving ſlide,
               The wanton-bubling waters gentle glide;
               Smiling to ſee the rivers quav'ring flankes,
               Dallie upon the dayſie-diap'red bankes.
            
            
               Thus while he feaſteth both his eies and eares
               With native muſicke ſweeter then a mans,
               (Like to a ſhowre of ſilver ſnowe) appeares
               A flight of alabaſter-feath'red ſwans;
               Whoſe number while his ſence amaſing ſcans,
               Forth-with an other flight his minde doth comber,
               And thus doth number bring him out of number.
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
               
               So in the May-tide of his ſommer age.
               Valour enmov'd the minde of ventious DRAKE,
               To lay his life with winds and waves in gage,
               And bold and hard adventures t' undertake,
               Leaving his countrie for his countr
                     •
                  's ſake;
               Loathinge the life that cowardiſe doth ſtaine,
               Preferting death, if death might honour gaine.
            
            
               At Cuba ſilver, at Coquimbo gold,
               At China cloth and precious ſilkes he found,
               Pearle at the Pearled Iles he did behold;
               Rich Couchanelo hoarded did abound,
               Imboſom'd in Tichamachalco's ground:
               Thus his induſtrious labour ſtill did raiſe
               The publique profite, and his private praiſe.
            
            
               As Nilus with his inundation
               Vpon all Aegypt fertile fat leſſe ſhowrs;
               Or as Euphrates on the Chaldee nation
               An over-flowing floud of plentie powrs,
               And graceth all the continent with flowrs:
               So DRAKE his countrie fil'd with ſtore &amp; plentie,
               And filling it, himſelfe was almoſt emptie.
            
            
               
               Whereas the night can never finde a place
               The ſuns eternall ſhining to aſſwage;
               Whereas the ſun durſt never ſhew his face,
               For feare of icye winters choaking rage;
               Nations unknown unto the antique age:
               There hath he bene, and made eternall light,
               Where, but for him, had bene eternall night.
            
            
               Plung'd in the Ocean of perplexities,
               With waves of death, and windes of black deſpaire,
               Amid the Scyllas of uncertainties,
               With ſourges of ſad death and drery feare,
               Which to the skies their billowes oft did reare:
               Scorne-fortune DRAKE by fortunes rage was borne,
               The more ſhe rag'd, the more he did her ſcorne.
            
            
               Where diſmall dread, and agonizinge deathe
               Hovers about them with their helliſh wings,
               Still threatning to intoxicate their breath,
               And ſtop the conduicts of the vitall ſprings,
               That nutrimentall ſpirites to them brings;
               Even in the laws of death did valor beare him,
               That death himſelf might know DRAKE did not fear him.
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
               
               O heavens, why take you that which late you gave?
               O ſeas, why hold you him that once held you?
               O earth, how haſt thou miſs'd that thou did'ſt crave?
               O England, how art thou bereft thy due?
               O unto whom wilt thou for comfort ſue?
               To earth? why that's partaker of thy mone:
               To heavens? ah they with-hold that is thine owne?
            
            
               O now deſcend my ever-mourning Muſe
               Downe from the by-cliffe of thy ſiſters mount;
               Forſake Cytheron, nor frequent the uſe
               Of th' amber weeping Pegaſe-hoofe-made fount,
               Now prune thy wings, aloft thou maiſt not mount:
               Sighe forth the humble modell of thy woe;
               For ioie aſcends, but ſorrow ſings below.
            
            
               Now chaunge thy winter-ſcorning lawrell boughes,
               That made thy temples ſwell with mounting braine:
               And with ſad cypreſſe all begirt thy browes,
               The drerie enſignes of enſuing paine,
               Sad preſentations of a tragicke vaine;
               In whoſe broade leaves ſpectatours cies maie ſee,
               The deepe-grav'd characters of extaſie.
            
            
               
               Now leave Pernaſſus heaven-aſpiring mountaine,
               For ſad Avernus hel-depreſſed plaines:
               Leave Aganippes hony-bubling fountaine,
               Whereby the Muſes Chorus ſtill remaines,
               And to the waters warble forth their ſtraines:
               Leave Aganippe for the Stygian lake,
               And for the fiendes the Muſes ſongs forſake.
            
            
               In ſteede of Helicons greene-varniſht grove
               Walke in the ſilent ſhade of Erebus:
               
               In ſteede of Ida (where the ladies ſtrove,
               Before the braine-ſicke ſonne of Priamus)
               
               Frequent the bloomy walkes of Taenarus:
               
               Weare ſable Heben for the ſpringing bay,
               Chaunge ioies aucoutrements for griefes aray.
            
            
               Sorrow be thou my Muſe, ſadneſſe my ſong,
               And death the ſubiect that I verſifie:
               The deſtinies deſpight, and fortunes wronge,
               Is that which now I muſt hiſtorifie,
               In ſilent cell of ſad Melancholie:
               My Heben pen ſhall poure out ynkie teares,
               That he maie weepe that reades, he ſigh that heares.
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page〉
            
            
               
               But that which Jove and deſtinie hath don,
               Men may lament, but never diſanull:
               And they that checke me for preſumption,
               (When love conſtrain'd me write, though I were dull)
               Blaming preſumption, muſt praiſe love at full:
               And eaſilie the fault may be redreſſed,
               Where love and dutie only have tranſgreſſed.
            
            
               Now was the mon'the that olde Sextilis name
               Chaung'd by the Roman Senates ſage decree:
               And gloryinge ſo to innovate the ſame,
               To have himſelfe new-chriſt'ned did agree,
               Proud, that Auguſtus god-father ſhould bee:
               While Ceres clad him in a mantle fayre
               Of bearded corne ſtill quavering with the ayre:
            
            
               When as a royall fleete, with ioyfull mindes,
               (O how miſhap is neereſt ſtill to ioy!)
               Daringe their hopes, and lives to ſea, and windes,
               (Two truſtleſſe treaſurers, full of annoye)
               Did toward the weſterne Indes their courſe imploy:
               Whoſe guide to DRAKE, &amp; HAWKINS was aſſign'd,
               When they went forth, ô who would ſtay behinde?
            
            
               
               Whether to win from Spaine that was not Spaines,
               
               Or to acquite us of ſuſtained wronge,
               Or intercept their Indian hoped gaines,
               Thereby to weaken them, and make us ſtronge;
               Heere to diſcuſſe, to me doth not belong:
               Yet if griefe maie ſaie truth by natures lawes,
               Ill was th' effect, how good ſo-ere the cauſe.
            
            
               Now are they on the ſeas, reſolv'd to proove
               The mercie of a mercie-wanting wave:
               
                  England behinde them lies, there lies their love;
               Before them, and about them aire they have,
               And ſometime foggie miſts their ſight bereave:
               Beneath them, ſeas; above them, skies they finde:
               Seas full of waves, skies threatning ſtormes &amp; winde.
            
            
               O Neptune, never like thy ſelfe in ſhew,
               Inconſtant, variable, mutable,
               How doſt thou Proteus-like thy forme renew?
               O whereto is thy change imputable?
               O whereunto art thou beſt ſuteable?
               Rightly the moone predominateth thee,
               For thou art all as changeable as ſhee.
            
            
               
               Thus ſtill ambiguous twixt feare and hope,
               Feare in the ſtormes, and hope in calmer tide;
               Paſſing ſaint Michaels promontorie toppe,
               At length the bay of Portingale they ſpi'de,
               Where not determining long time t' abide,
               Againe they venter on their daungers ſource,
               And to the Grand Canaries bend their courſe.
            
            
               Now paſſe in ſilence, ô my drouping pen,
               So manie famous townes and ports paſt by.
               Some tooke, ſome burnt, ſome unaſſaulted then,
               As that Port Rico, place of miſerie,
               Where (ô!) great HAWKINS, &amp; brave CLIFFORD lie;
               The taking of the citty Hatch conceale,
               Nor many other brave attempts reveale:
            
            
               Only two baſe ignoble places tell,
               Famous for nothing, but for death and dreade:
               Where (ô!) that, which my Muſe lamentes, befell,
               The ſtages where our tragedie was plaide,
               Th' one Scudo, th' other Portabella ſaide:
               Both to be raſed out of memorie,
               But for memoriall of this tragedie.
            
            
               
               O wherefore ſhould ſo manie famous places,
               Worthie eternall memorie and fame,
               Be heere conceal'd, unworthy ſuch diſgraces,
               And theſe two ſhould be regiſtred by name,
               Though meritorious of eternall blame?
               But ſome are ſometime named to their ſhames,
               And therefore muſt I tell theſe places names.
            
            
               Whether of both was in the greateſt fault,
               I know not, nor I care not much to knowe:
               (Far deeper paſſions now my minde aſſault:)
               Thus much I know (ô that I knew not ſo!)
               Both iointlie ioin'd to aggravate our woe;
               Since he on whom his countries hope relied,
               At Scudo ſickned, at Portbella died.
            
            
               Accurſed Ile, whoſe life-impoys'ning aire,
               Intoxicates his ſanctified breath!
               But moſt accurſed port that did impaire
               That fleſh, compacted of the pureſt earth,
               And made the ſame a ſacrifice to death!
               O let them languiſh in eternall night,
               That did extinguiſh earths faire-ſhining light!
            
            
               
               O let theſe places be earth's diſmall hell,
               Th' inhabitants eternall-tortur'd ghoſts,
               The ſnaky-hayred Furies loathſome cell,
               Swarming with fiends and damned ſpirites hoaſts,
               And palpable thick fogs infect the coaſts:
               And bee this never-ending purgatorie
               A place of pennance for DRAKES wofull ſtory.
            
            
               O ſoule, exhale out of thy deepeſt center
               The ſorrow-ſobbing ſighes of extaſie;
               O let thy voice heavens territories enter,
               Breathe forth into the aires concavitie
               The diſmall accents of thy tragedie:
               Call heaven and earth to witneſſe of thy woe,
               How that thy griefe doth heaven and earth oreflowe.
            
            
               O let our clamours to the skies repaire;
               O let our ſmoake-exhalinge breaths enfold
               A mightie cloud of ſighes amid the aire,
               Like vapours in the element enrold
               By Sol's attractive powre expellinge cold;
               Till being diſſolv'd, they ſhal on earth againe
               Powre downe a deluge of teare-ſhowring raine.
            
            
               
               Now duſky clouds have overcaſt the ſunne,
               That latelie bright tranſlucent ſplendour ſhed
               In radiant rayes, that from his beames did runne
               Into earth's eyes, with darkneſſe dazeled,
               Since firſt theſe clouds his face incurtained:
               A darke eclipſe obſcures his ſhining light,
               That latelie made cleare day in darkeſt night.
            
            
               Behold the loftie Cedars ſtatelie toppe,
               Whilome attir'd in ſummers riche aray,
               That in the ſkies his prowd heade did enwrap,
               Now are his greene-ſilke leaves gon to decay,
               His tufted boughes, and braunches falne awaie:
               And ſince his nutrimentall ſap is periſht,
               He falling breakes the trees he latelie cheriſht.
            
            
               He, that the braveſt Champion was accounted
               Boldlie t' incounter with the proudeſt foe;
               Now from his ſtatelie courſer is diſmounted,
               And hath by death receiv'd an overthrowe,
               Vnto the worlds inconſolable woe:
               The tournament turn'd to lamenting feares,
               And all the triumphs into ruthfull teares.
            
            
               
               A ſacred Temple edifi'd to Fame,
               Where honour annuallie did ſacrifice
               An holy Hecatombe to her name,
               Now, level'd with the earth, everted lies:
               This onlie comfort have the votaries;
               That though the temple thus be over-blowne,
               The ſacred ſaint ſhall nere be overthrowne.
            
            
               The vulture anguiſh 
                     •
                  ireth on my mawe,
               Sorrow hath ceazed on my grieved hart:
               There doth he without intermiſſion gnawe,
               From hence the other never can depart,
               But ſtill begins, and never endes my ſmart:
               And thus poore I, twixt ſorrow and twixt anguiſh,
               Doe neither live nor die, but alwaie languiſh.
            
            
               Ay me! what ſhall I doe this griefe t' alaie?
               Shall I with fained ſmiles my ſmart conceale?
               Ah no! like fire, it will it ſelfe bewraie:
               Or ſhall I ſue to heaven his backe repeale?
               Ah no! ſuch ſutes with heaven can nere prevaile:
               What therefore ſhall I doe this griefe t' alaie?
               Still grieve, till Death take griefe and life awaie.
            
            
               
               O Death inhouſ'd in hells profundities,
               Now excerciſe on mee thy tyranie:
               Anatomize me into atomies,
               Set period to my full falne extaſie,
               Prolong no longer this long tragedie:
               O Death ſome eaſe unto my ſorrow ſend:
               For Death, they ſay, doth griefe and ſorrow end.
            
            
               What ſay they? Death doth griefe and ſorrow end?
               O how they are deceav'd in ſaying ſo!
               Death onlie did this griefe and ſorrow ſend:
               Death was the onlie agent of our woe,
               Death was our drerie and our diſmall foe:
               For had not Death himſelfe ſubdued DRAKE.
               The world beſide could not him captive make.
            
            
               This onelie comfort is unto us left,
               (O ſimple comfort in ſo great diſtreſſe!)
               That no prowd Spaniard hath his life bereft,
               No man may boaſt he cauſ'd our wretchedneſſe,
               Nor triumph he ſubdued earths worthineſſe:
               But onlie Death our treaſure hath bereaven,
               And that was due to earth, he gave to heaven.
            
            
               
               To heaven? ah why is heaven covetous?
               Why are the Gods (ô pardon griefe) ſo greedie,
               To raviſh from the earth, the precious,
               And leave to us th' unworthie, baſe, and needie?
               O heavens, what can our harmes and loſſes ſteed yee?
               Ah Jove! if thou beeſt rightly term'd a giver,
               Why doſt thou take from earth that ſhoulde relieve her?
            
            
               An high diſdaine enrag'd the Macedon,
               
               And gall did grate againſt his eager breſt,
               Dreading, his father all the world had won,
               And meaſur'd with his ſword from eaſt to weſt,
               And he ſhould languiſh in ignoble reſt:
               Wherefore he often wiſht, two worldes had bin,
               One for his father, one for him to win.
            
            
               As great as Alexander in renowne,
               In vertue greater farre then ever hee,
               Great DRAKE on nature ſometime ſeem'd to frowne,
               That but one world, and that all knowne ſhould be;
               Wherefore he ſought ſome other world to ſee:
               Vntill at length so heaven he did attaine,
               And finding heaven ſcorn'd to returne againe.
            
            
               
               As one, that vowes a ſolemne pilgrimage
               To ſome canoniz'd Saints religious ſhrine,
               Doth leave his ſolitarie hermitage,
               And with a new-incenſed zeale divine,
               Vnto devotion doth his minde incline:
               Paſſing the way and day in meditation,
               Beguiling both with holy contemplation:
            
            
               At length with often-tired tedious race,
               Alwaie invoking Saints ſucceſſive aide,
               Arriveth at the ſanctified place,
               Where after all his oriſons are ſaide,
               And due oblations to his Saint are paide;
               Raviſht in ſpirite with devoted zeale,
               Becomes a Prieſt, and will not home repeale.
            
            
               So DRAKE, the pilgrime of the world, intending
               A vowed voyage unto Honours ſhrine,
               At length his pilgrimage in heaven had ending,
               Where raviſht with the ioies more than divine,
               That in the temple of the Gods doe ſhine:
               There did a never-dying life renew,
               Bidding baſe earth, and all the world, adewe.
            
            
               
               Intending for to worke his countries pleaſure.
               O cruell chance! he wrought his countries paine:
               And minding to augment faire Englands treaſure,
               (Alaſſe!) he drowned in the Ocean maine
               The richeſt treaſure England did containe,
               Save one rare iewell, whoſe rich price is ſuch,
               As none can either prize, or praiſe too much.
            
            
               What treaſure was it then that DRAKE hath loſt?
               It was not ſilver, ſilver yeeldes to gold:
               It was not gold, pearle is of greater coſt:
               Nor pearle, for precious ſtones are dearer ſold:
               Yet precious ſtones this treaſure did not hold:
               O no! it was himſelfe, more worth alone
               Then ſilver, gold, or pearle, or precious ſtone.
            
            
               O dire miſchance! ô lamentable loſſe!
               Impov'riſhing the riches of our Ile,
               O wherefore ſhould ſiniſter deſt'nie croſſe,
               And with her frowne incurtaine fortunes ſmile?
               O now I ſee ſhe ſmiles but to beguile!
               O Fortune alwaie to deſerts unkinde!
               That England loſt, not all the world can finde.
            
            
               
               O let us looſe our ſight with ſhedding teares,
               And with eternall weeping looſe our eies,
               Looſe breath with ſighes, looſe minde with drerie feares,
               Looſe ſence with terror, and looſe voice with cries,
               Still meditating on our miſeries:
               Since we have found his loſſe, he loſt his breath,
               Since we haue loſt his helpe, he found his death.
            
            
               But oh! why doe we breake our hearts with griefe,
               And to the ſenceleſſe aire ſigh forth our grones?
               Sith all in vaine, heavens ſend us no reliefe,
               But ſtop their eares againſt our piteous mones;
               Our ſighes as ſoone maie penetrate the ſtones,
               As heavens hard eares: ô therefore doe we plaine,
               And therefore weepe, becauſe we weepe in vaine.
            
            
               We weepe in vaine, becauſe for him we weepe,
               Since he with ſaints in thought-ſurmounting ioie▪
               
               At Joves great feſtivall doth revell keepe,
               Where neither ſcarſitie doth him annoie,
               Nor loath'd ſatietie his minde accloy:
               O ſince that he from us is gone to bliſſe,
               We doe lament our owne miſhap, not his.
            
            
               
               The faireſt plot in all th' Eliſian field,
               By Joves commaund, is unto him aſſign'd;
               And heavens eternall Summer-houſe doth yeeld,
               A paradiſe unto his ſoule refin'd,
               For ſacred contemplation of the minde:
               And as of men to Gods he was the neereſt,
               So now to Jove of Gods he is the deereſt.
            
            
               And if his death be rightfully reſpected,
               Some ioie it hath to mitigate our woe;
               For that which for our country is effected,
               Is good, though death with theſe effectes doth goe,
               And well he dies, that dies gainſt countries foe:
               Therefore though death unto him did betide,
               (O ioyfull end!) DRAKE for his countrie di'd.
            
            
               DRAKE for his country di'd, ô ioyfull end!
               This ioyfull ende beganne his countries woe:
               His glorious death his country did defend,
               And yet his death did grieve his country ſo,
               As flouds of ſorrow doe her overflowe:
               Well did he die, that for his country died,
               Had not his countries death to his beene tied.
            
            
               
               This end began our woe, ended our pleaſure,
               This end did end our weale, began our paine,
               This end began our loſſe, ended our treaſure,
               This end did end our mirth, began our plaine,
               This end began our griefe, ended our gaine,
               This end did end reliefe, began annoy;
               O then no ioyfull end, but end of ioy!
            
            
               
                  Spaine, clap thy hands, while we our hands do wringe,
               And while wee weepe, laughe thou at our diſtreſſe,
               While wee doe ſob and ſighe, ſit thou and ſinge,
               Smile thou, while wee lament with heavineſſe,
               While wee our griefe, do thou thy ioy expreſſe:
               Since hee, who made us triumph, and thee quake,
               Hath ceaſ'd to live; ô moſt victorious DRAKE.
            
            
               Proud Spaine, although our Dragon be bereft vs,
               Wee rampant Lions have enowe for thee:
               Magnanimous ESSEX (heav'ns delight) is left vs,
               And ô long may the heavens let him be!
               Greate COMBERLAND and HOWARD yet have we;
               And ô long may wee have them, and enioy
               Theſe worthies to our wealth, and thine annoy.
            
            
               
               Theſe yet ſurvive (o may they ſo for ever!)
               To make eternall thunder in thine eares
               With their hart-daunting names, and (like a fever)
               To make thee tremble all diſtraught with feares,
               When thou th' alarume of their trumpets heares:
               ELISA lives, and while ELISA raignes
               One England neede not feare an hundred Spaines.
               
            
            
               And that deare bodie held in Neptunes wombe,
               By Jove ſhalbe tranſlated to the ſkie:
               The ſea no more, heaven then ſhall be his tombe,
               Where he a new-made ſtar eternallie
               Shall ſhine, tranſparent to ſpectatours eie:
               A fearefull comet in the ſight of Spaine,
               
               But ſhall to us a radiant light remaine.
            
            
               He, who alive to them a Dragon was,
               Shalbe a Dragon unto them againe,
               For with his death his terrour ſhall not paſſe,
               But ſtill amid the aire he ſhall remaine
               A dreadfull Meteor in the eie of Spaine:
               
               And as a fierie Dragon, ſhall portend
               
                  Englandes ſucceſſe, and Spaines diſaſter end.
            
            
               
               Knowne to the heavens by honour long before,
               Now by the preſence of th'immortall ſoule,
               O new-made ſaint, (for now a man no more)
               Admit my tender infant Muſe t' inroule
               Thy name in honours everlaſting ſcroule:
               What though thy prayſes cannot live by me?
               Yet may I hope to live by prayſing thee.
            
            
               And may thy prayſes live a while by me,
               Though prayſing thus I doe but ſtaine thy praiſe:
               And I awhile may live by prayſing thee:
               Vntill ſome heavenlie Muſe begin to rayſe
               Thy fame from grave to live eternall dayes:
               If ominous birds beguile not with their ſong,
               I augurize, this ſhall be done ere long.
            
            
               Phoebus himſelfe ſhall chronicle thy fame,
               And of a radiant ſunne-beame make the pen;
               The inke, the milke whence Via Lactea came;
               Th' empyrean he aven, the volume ſhalbe then;
               To regiſter this miracle of men:
               The ſunne and moone, the letters capitall;
               The ſtars, the commas and the periods all.
            
            
               
               
                  Joves ſilver foote-ſtoole ſhall be librarie
               That ſhall theſe Actes and Monuments containe;
               Which that they maie to after ages tarie,
               And as a true memoriall ſtill remaine,
               Eternitie is th' adamantine chaine:
               And that the heavēs ſtil on DRAKES praiſe may look,
               The Gods ſhall reade, and Saintes peruſe the booke.
            
            Quis Martem tunica tectum adamantina
Dignè ſcripſerit?
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

