
   
      
         
            The curse of corne-horders with the blessing of seasonable selling. In three sermons, on Pro. II.26. Begun at the general sessions for the county of Cornwall, held at Bodmyn, and continued at Fowy. By Charles Fitz-Geffrie.
            Fitz-Geffry, Charles, 1575?-1638.
         
         
            
               1631
            
         
         Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00818
            STC 10939
            ESTC S115075
            99850294
            99850294
            15485
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00818)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15485)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 798:12)
         
         
            
               
                  The curse of corne-horders with the blessing of seasonable selling. In three sermons, on Pro. II.26. Begun at the general sessions for the county of Cornwall, held at Bodmyn, and continued at Fowy. By Charles Fitz-Geffrie.
                  Fitz-Geffry, Charles, 1575?-1638.
               
               [12], 56 p.   
               
                  By I[ohn] B[eale] for Edward Dight dwelling in Excester,
                  Printed at London :
                  1631.
               
               
                  A variant of the edition with M. Sparke in the imprint.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Food supply --  Great Britain --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-07
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-07
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            The Curſe of Corne-horders:
WITH
The Bleſsing of ſeaſonable Selling.
In three Sermons, on PRO. 11. 26.
Begun at the general Seſsions for the County of Cornwall,
held at Bodmyn, and continued at Fowy.
By CHARLES FITZ-GEFFRIE.
            D. Cyprianus ad Demetrian. §. 8.
            Miraris in poenas generis humani iram Dei creſcere, cum creſcat quotidiè quod
puniatur.—De ſterilitate aut fame quereris, quaſi famem maiorem ſiccitas quàm
rapacitas faciat, quaſi non de captatis annonarum incrementis &amp; pretiorum cumulis
flagrantior inopiae ardor excreſcat. Quereris cludi imbribus coelum, cum ſic
horrea cludantur in terris.
            
            Printed at London by I. B. for Edward Dight dwelling in Exceſter. 1631.
         
         
            
            
            To the truly ennobled and rightly
honored, Sir REGINALD MOHVNE,
Knight and Baronet:
Grace, Mercy, and Peace
be multiplied.
            
               SIR,
            
            
               THE end of Gods
puniſhments is to
bring ſinful man
vnto Repentance.
In afflicting vs he
intends not our
affliction, but our
reformation. Hee
who delights not in the death of ſinners,
takes no pleaſure in their ſufferings,
but in compaſsion cauſeth ſometimes
temporall ſuffering to preuent eternall
aking; according to that of the
Apoſtle,1 Cor. 11. 32. 
               We are chaſtened of the Lord, that
we may not be condemned with the world. If

he attaine not this end by one rod, he
vſeth another. If the Peſtilence preuaile
not, he ſends the ſword; if that workes
not, he inflicteth Famine, and like a
good Phyſitian, by diuers medicines he
tendeth to the ſame cure. If the ſame
croſſe haue not effected the end for
which it was ſent, he ſends it the ſecond
time, as a man doth his ſeruant who
hath not fully done his errand at firſt.
Thus doth he with particular perſons,
thus doth hee with whole Nations,
whoſe good he intendeth. He viſited
our ſinnes with the Peſtilence, this
wrought not a ſound recouery; he lanced
vs with the Sword, there yet remained
many peccant humours, thoſe hee
ſought to cure by Famine,Veteres omnes morbos inediâ curabant. as the ancient
Phyſitians vſed to cure all diſeaſes
by Abſtinence. We ſeemed to be on
the mending hand, but we relapſed, and
God was faine to go to work with vs again;
as we renewed our old ſins, ſo did he
his old iudgements. He ſent the Plague

the ſecond time, threatned it the third. About
ſeuen yeeres ſithence the creature ſuffered and
we by it, for our abuſe of it, and for our vnthankefulneſſe
to the Creator. The ſame puniſhment
hee hath inflicted this yeere on ſundry
places of the land. Thus is God enforced
to re-aſſume his rods, when we renew our ſins;
and as wee vſe to take from our children their
Bread when they doe wanton with it; ſo by
want he correcteth our former wantonneſſe,
taking from vs that which wee abuſe, thereby
teaching vs to vſe it better when wee haue it,
that by want we may know how to vſe abundance.
Theſe two yeeres of dearth (in ſome diſtance)
called from mee theſe three Sermons.
That which in the firſt was ſummarily deliuered
in one, vnto the eares of that Bench on
which you haue ſate ſundry yeeres as chiefe, is
vpon this yeeres occaſion enlarged into three,
and now ſent abroad into publike, for the benefit
of many, is firſt preſented vnto your eies.
In this Dedication I craue not patronage, but
onely acceptance. The Kings command, my
calling, the neceſſity of the times are ſufficient

to patronize it. Neither haue I cauſe to doubt
of your acceptance; your care for your Countries
good, and your endeuour in this particular
doe aſſure me that you will approue his labours,
who, according to his calling, addeth
the beſt aduancement hee may vnto yours▪
Whereunto hee will not ceaſe to adioyne his
continued prayers to the fountaine of Grace,
for all gracious bleſſings on your perſon, on
your publike imployments, on your noble
Family; who is, and will be (while he is)
            
               Your worſhips in all Christian
dutie and ſeruice moſt ready,
Charles Fitz-Geffry.
            
         
         
            
            A briefe view of the enſuing
Sermons.
            
               Concio prima.
               
                  THe occaſion of the choyce of this
Text. page 1
               The diuiſion thereof into two
parts. In the former part are
conſidered, 1. The ſinne, 2. The
ſequel. p. 3
               1ma. me. The ſinne, with-holding Corne. ibid.
               
               All conſeruation of Corne, not vnlawfull. What is
vnlawfull herein. ibid.
               
               Vnder the word Corne, euery publike commodity
comprehended. p. 4
               
                  Doct. 1. It is a grieuous ſiune to procure or further
famine, by ſeeking to raiſe the price of Corn. ibid.
               
               
                  Reaſons. 1. It is odious vnto God. The detaining
of other commodities not ſo neceſſary for the life
of man, as Corne, forbidden by God. Much more
of this, without which, the life of man can hardly,
yea, not at all be ſuſtained. The neceſsity of
bread vnto mans life. p. 5, 6
               2. It is oppoſite to Nature, vnto which Cornehorders
are traytors. For, 1. That which Nature

moſt deſireth, they doe moſt deteſt, that is, plenty.
p. 7, 8
               2. And that which Nature moſt deteſteth, they
moſt deſire, namely, Dearth and ſcarcity. ibid.
               
               3. Condemned by the Lawes of Nations. p. 9
               
                  Application. Three ſorts of people guilty herein.
p. 11
               1 The greedy Farmer, who ſometimes with-holdeth
Corne, euen in ſelling it. ibid.
               
               2 The couetous Merchant. p. 13
               3 The Huckſters, or Badgers of Corne. p. 14
            
            
               Concio ſecunda.
               
                  SEcunda primae, The ſequell; The curſes of the
People. p. 17
               A Common ſinne drawes on a common curſe. p. 18
               
                  Doct. 2. The peoples curſe, iuſtly procured, is a fearfull
iudgement. p. 19
               The peoples curſe twofold, 1. Cauſeleſſe or vniuſt;
this not to be feared nor regarded. ibid.
               
               Exhortation to Magiſtrates and Officers to doe
their duties, though the people doe cauſeleſly curſe
them. For ſuch curſes God will bleſſe them. ibid.
               
               2 The iuſtly cauſed curſe of the poore and oppreſſed,
this curſe very fearefull. p. 20
               
                  Vſe. Terror to all kinde of Oppreſſors. p. 21
               Eſpecially to Corne-horders. p. 22
               That theſe curſes are not effectleſſe in this life, ſhewed
by examples. A ſtory out of Matthew Paris
                  
of Walter Grey, Archbiſhop of Yorke, a couetous
Corne-horder, Anno Dom. 1234. p. 23
               Another of a German Biſhop deuoured by Rats, An.
930. p. 24
               The effect of theſe curſes, in latter times, wherein
ſome of theſe Nabals haue hanged themſelues,
when the price of Corne hath fallen. ibid.
               
               The greateſt curſe of all at the day of iudgement.
p. 25
               Obiections anſwered. 1. May I not doe with mine
owne what I liſt? p. 26
               
                  Anſwer. Chriſt onely may both ſay and doe ſo:
Man cannot (without limitation) who can caſt
nothing his owne properly, but his ſinne. ibid.
               
               Men may not vſe their owne, to the hurt of others.
ibid.
               
               It is damnable to with-hold our owne, when our
brethren are ready to periſh for want of that which
we may well ſpare. p. 27
               Two other Obiections, Ioſeph and Gedeon, their
examples anſwered. p. 30, 31
               Famine, a grieuous puniſhment. p. 31
               It is proper to God alone to puniſh a ſinfull Nation
with famine, or any other iudgement. p. 32
               We haue deſerued to be thus ſcourged. But this famine
is not inflicted immediately by the hand of
God, but enforced by the cruell couetouſneſſe of
men. p. 33
               An inuectiue againſt couetouſneſſe. p. 35
               Theſe Corne-horders worſe than Vſurers. ibid.
               
               The pittifull eſtate of poore labouring-men in theſe

times, deplored. p. 36
            
            
               Concio tertia:
               THe ſecond part of the Text, wherein is conſidered;
1. The duty to be performed; Selling.
p. 39
               2. The recompence, Bleſsing. p. 40
               
                  Doct. 3. There is a charity ſometimes in ſelling, as
well as in giuing. ibid.
               
               
                  Vſe 1. To teach vs to acknowledge Gods goodneſſe
in accepting any ſeruice done at his command,
though for our owne aduantage. p. 41
               God ſometimes accepteth ſelling, where there is ability
of giuing. ibid.
               
               
                  Vſe 2. To incite thoſe who are of ability, to this
duty of ſelling. p. 42
               Foure things required in charitable ſelling. p. 43
               1 To ſell that which is good for quality, conuenient
graine, ibid.
               
               2 To ſell for conuenient gaine, at a reaſonable price.
ibid.
               
               3 To ſell in conuenient ſeaſon. p. 44
               4 With meaſure conuenient. p. 45
               
                  2da. 2de. The recompence, Bleſsing. ibid.
               
               
                  Obſeruat. The reward more emphatically layd
downe, than the iudgement threatned. p 46
               
                  Doct. 4. God will bleſſe him who ſelleth charitably
in time of extremity, though men bee vnthankfull.
ibid.
               
               
                  
Two ſinnes of the poore: 1 Murmuring, 2 Vnthankfulneſſe.
ibid.
               
               Neither of theſe ſhould diſcourage vs from charitable
actions, for though men be vngratefull, yet
God is not forgetfull. p. 47
               
                  Application. 1. Vnto Magiſtrates, exhorting
them to doe their duties in this behalfe, according
to his Maieſties Orders. ibid.
               
               And to draw on others by their examples. p. 48
               Dehortation from with-holding iuſtice, and from
ſelling it. p. 50
               2. To Miniſters, to be carefull and and faithfull in
diſtributing ſpirituall Corne for the bread of life,
eſpecially in theſe dangerous dayes. ibid.
               
               3. To the poore. Here is no warrant for them to reuenge
their wrongs with curſings, as commonly
they doe. p. 51
               But rather to accuſe their owne ſinnes, the cauſes of
all their calamities. p. 52
               4. Encouragement and comfort to charitable ſellers.
p. 54
               God ſhall crowne them with bleſsings, Externall,
Internall, Eternall. p. 55, 56.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE CVRSE
OF
Corn-Horders.
            
               The firſt Sermon.
               
                  PROV. 11. 26.
                  Hee that with-holdeth Corne, the people ſhall curſe
him: But bleſsing ſhall be vpon the head of him
who ſelleth it.
               
               
                  THe extremity of the times
do euen extort from me this
Text,The occaſion of the choice of this Text. together with the Explication
and Application
thereof, as God ſhall enable
me. Our gracious Soueraigne,
like a prouident Ioſeph,
hath endeuoured to preuent
the famine, or to pro
                     •
                  ide
remedies againſt it. To this end he hath ſent

                     •
                  orth his Proclamations, and hath authorized his
Hands in theſe remote places, the Iuſtices of Peace,
to draw forth the poore impriſoned graine out of

priuate Barnes, and to afford it the freedome of the
Markets. The Iuſtices haue done their endeuours,
and the beſt of them doe continue ſo doing. But couetouſneſſe
careth for no Lawes, being like the lawleſſe
Iudge,
                  Luk. 18. 2. 
                  Who neither feared God, nor regarded
Man. Hence it is that Lawes are eluded, the Kings
edicts not regarded, the Magiſtrates endeuours
fruſtrated, and the hopes of the poore diſappointed.
The deafe Adder will not bee charmed; the
greedy Farmer will not enfranchize his Corne,
though the Country doe curſe him, and thoſe curſes
be ratified in heauen. But let not vs ceaſe to doe
our duties though others doe not theirs. Let Aaren
and Hur ſupport the hands of Moſes;
                  Miniſters. let Miniſters
(as his Maieſty commandeth) ioyne their forces
with the Magiſtrates againſt this monſter,Et quae non proſunt ſingula, iuncta iuuant. 
                  Auarice.
The good effect which the one cannot produce alone,
may (by Gods bleſſing) enſue vpon the religious
endeuours of both together. I come therefore
to publiſh a Proclamation from the King of
heauen, penned by the wiſeſt King on earth, againſt
all ingroſſers of the fruits of the earth, the terour
whereof is this,
               Hee that with-holdeth Corne, the people ſhall curſe
him, but bleſſing ſhall be on the head of him who ſelleth
it.
               Moſt of Salomons Prouerbs are a Commentary
vpon that one ſentence of his Father Dauid,
                  Pſal. 37. 27. 
                  Iſ
                     
                        •
                     hew
euill, and doe good; and commonly they are
bipartite, one part diſſwading from ſome euill, the
other exhorting to the contrary vertue. His Arguments
are thoſe which are moſt powerfull, Puniſhment,
and Reward; dehorting from ſome ſinn
by puniſhment threatned, exhorting to Vertue by
ſome reward propoſed: Such is this ſentence, reſembling
the two Hils,Deut. 11. 29. 27. 13. the one of Curſes, the other

of Bleſſings:
                  Ioſh. 18. 33. 
                  Hee that with-holdeth Corne, the
people ſhall curſe him;
                  Diuiſion of the Text into two parts. there is Ebal, the Mountaine
of curſing: But bleſſing ſhall be on the head of him
that ſelleth it; there is Gerizin, the Mountaine of
bleſſing.
               In the former wee are to conſider,In the former part conſider, 1. The ſinne, 2. The ſequel. 1. The ſinne,
2. The ſequel. The ſinne, hiding or with-holding
Corne; the ſequel, the curſes of the people. In the
latter, we haue, 1. the duty, 2. the benefit or reward:
The duty, ſelling; the benefit, bleſſing: But bleſſing
ſhall be on the head of him that ſelleth it. Of theſe
(God willing) in their order; and firſt of the firſt
part,
                     Prima primae. The ſin withholding Corne. and firſt branch thereof; namely, the ſinne
condemned, which is, with-holding of Corne.
               He that with-holdeth Corne.
               All conſeruation or keeping vp of Corne,All keeping of Corne not vnlawfull. is not alwaies
vnlawfull. Ioſeph, in the ſeuen yeers of plenty,
gathered and kept Corne againſt the ſeuen yeeres of
ſcarcity. Sundry Cities haue their Magazins, wherein
they prouidently doe ſtore vp Corne and other
prouiſion, the better to endure the extremity of an
aſſiege or famine.Paruula na
                        •
                      exemplo eſt magni formica laboris, Ore trahit quod cun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      poteſt, acque addit aceruo quem ſtruit, haud igna
                        •
                     a e
                        •
                      non incauta futuri Horat. Hyemis memores tect
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      repenunt Virgil. 4. Aenid. Parcum genus eſt patienſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      laboris. Ouid Metam. 7. Videatur Plinius. lib. 11. cap. 30. et Ambroſ. Hexam. l. 6. c. 4. item Aelian. de var. hiſtor. l. 1. Indè dictum Granigerum agmen, Nature hath taught the ſilley
Ant this leſſon of husbanding her prouiſion,a See Pro. 6. 6, 7, 8. and
ſhe by her example readeth the ſame Lecture vnto
man, by the mouth of Salomon.
               
               
                  What is vnlawfull herein. But then to with-hold Corne when publike
neceſſity doth call for the venting it, vpon hope to
enhance the price, thereby to make a prey of the
poore, who haue then moſt need to bee releeued,
this is a crying ſinne, cauſing the people with bitter
cries to complaine to God againſt ſuch deteſtable
couetouſneſſe, and to purſue the ſame with
bitter curſes.
               
                  
The ancient latine reading doth well expreſſe the
meaning; Captans pretia frumenti, (ſoAmbr. Offic. l. 3. c. 6. Saint Ambroſe
alleageth the place.) Hee that catcheth at all
aduantages by the price of Corne, and endeuours
to raiſe it higher, being more greedy of his priuate
gaine, than affected with the publike good, euery
one that doth ſo, commeth within the compaſſe of
this curſe. So that not onely hiding or hording, but
ſelling and buying too, in ſome caſes, are here forbidden;
when they are ſo done in priuate, as that the
price is thereby enhanced in publike: whereof we
ſhall haue occaſion to ſay more (God willing) in
proſecution of this Text.
               
                  Vnder the word, Corne euery publike commodity is comprehended.
I doubt not but that vnder this one word,
Corne, is comprehended any other Commodity,
vſefull for the Countrey; but the Times doe confine
my intendements to that particular which my
Text doth here aſſigne; namely, againſt all auaritious
horders or huckſters, who pinch the guts of
the poore, to fill and extend their owne purſes; taking
aduantage by the dearth of Corne, to make it
more deare: on which ground I may ſafely lay
downe this doctrinall Poſition.Doctr. 1.
               
               It is a grieuous ſinne to procure a Dearth, or further
a Famine,A grieuous ſin to procure or further famine by raiſing the price of Corne. by ſeeking to raiſe the price of Corne.
               When publike neceſſity doth require, and our
owne ability doth permit vs to ſend abroad our
Corne by reaſonable and ſeaſonable ſelling, then to
with-hold it in hope of greater Dearth, this is a
great ſinne: For it is odious vnto God, oppoſite
vnto Nature, iniurious vnto mankinde, and therefore
condemned by the Lawes of Grace, of Nature,
and of Nations.Reaſons.
               
               Firſt,1. It is odious vnto God. it is odious vnto God, as being directly a

breach of his Law, a rebellion againſt his Ordinance.
Otherwiſe hee would neuer haue inueighed
againſt theſe Corne-horders ſo bitterly as he doth,
by his Prophet Amos, ſaying,Amos 
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     , 5, 6 
                  Heare ye this, ô yee
that ſwallow the poore, and make the needy of the Land
to faile, ſaying, When will the new Moone be gone, that
we may ſell Corne; and the Sabbath, that wee may ſet
forth Wheat; and make the Epha ſmall, and the Shekel
great; and buy the poore for ſiluer, and the needy for
ſhoes, and ſell the refuſe of the Wheat? If any doe except
and ſay, What is this againſt horders? this is rather
againſt ſellers of Corne: I intimated at firſt,
that there may be as great a ſinne, in ſome kinde of
ſelling, as in keeping: and thoſe Iewes who ſold at
laſt, they did hord vp Corne at firſt, to this purpoſe:
that when the time ſerued their turne, they
might ſell it at their owne pleaſure and price:Dod ad Text. and
now the time is come, they muſt ſell it in all haſte,
leſt the price ſhould fall againe: They were now
ſo eager after ſelling, that they thought the dayes of
Gods Seruice too tedious till they were at it. They
kept it in while it was good, and ſold it when it
was worſe, they abated the meaſure and augmented
the price; they made the people pay for the
beſt, when they ſold but the refuſe; and ſo inſtead
of ſelling to the poore, they enforced the poore to
ſell themſelues at a vile rate for neceſſary ſuſtenance,
and ſo to become their ſlaues.verſ. 8. The Lord threatneth
a fearefull iudgement on the whole Nation,
for this inhumane cruelty of ſome particular perſons
towards their poore brethren.The detaining of other commodities not ſo neceſſary for the life of man a Corn, forbidden by God.
               
               Leſſer ſinnes than this in compariſon, the ingroſſing
of commodities not ſo neceſſary for the life of
man as Corne is, are threatned with heauy iudgements
in the word of God. The impriſoning of
coyne in Coffers, when it ſhould bee diſperſed

abroad vnto pious and charitable vſes, is condemned
by the holy Ghoſt, who ſaith by Saint Iames
                  Iam. 5. 1, 2, 3.,
that The very ruſt thereof ſhall be a witneſſe againſt the
keepers, and that the canker of their ſiluer ſhall eat vp
their fleſh as fire. The like iudgement is denounced
in the ſame place againſt thoſe who keep their garments
cloſe in their ward-robes to clothe the
Moaths,Much more of bread-Corne, without, which the life of man can hardly, yea, not at all, be ſuſtained. rather than they will produce them to
clothe Chriſt his naked members. What then
ſhall become of them who are kinder to Rats and
Mice, than to their Chriſtian brethren, being contented
that vile vermine ſhall deuoure that for nothing,
which poore Chriſtians cannot get of them
for money.The neceſſity of bread vnto mans life. Bread is called in Scripture theIſa. 3. 1. Leuit. 26. 26. Ezech. 4. 16. 5. 16. 14. 13. 
                  ſtay
and ſtaffe of life, becauſe life is thereby ſuſtained as
by a Staffe: and when God doth threaten one of
his heauieſt puniſhments on a Land for ſinne, hee
doth threaten to breake the ſtaffe of Bread; So neceſſary
it is for this life, that all neceſſaries are comprized
vnder this one, Giue vs, this day, our daily
bread. Chriſt calleth himſelfe the bread which
came downe from heauen: his Word is called the
bread of life. All which doe ſhew how neceſſary
bread is for the vſe of man: ſo neceſſary, that neither
body nor ſoule can well bee fed without it;
not the body without common bread, nor the
ſoule (in thoſe of diſcretion) without Sacramentall
bread: ſo neceſſary, that although a man haue diuers
varieties of meats, and doe want bread, the
beſt is failing, becauſe the binder of all the reſt is
wanting: other meats, without bread, are but beeſomes
without a band, they cannot ſweepe away
hunger from nature;Satis eſt homini fluuius
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Ceres
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     . but if a man haue onely bread
and water, ſufficient for quantity, and conuenient
for quality, hee may liue and doe well: ſo that to
with-hold Corne, and thereby to breake the ſtaffe

of bread, is not onely ſinfull, but ſauage; not onely
againſt the Law of God and grace, but againſt the
Law of Nature.
               Nature teacheth men to ſeeke good and ſhunne euill,
to pray and ſtriue to auert thoſe publike puniſhments,2. It is oppoſite to nature.
                  Sword, Peſtilence, and Famine. Nature
teacheth vs that wee are not borne onely for our
ſelues, and that publike vtility is to be preferred before
priuate commodity. This could Cicero ſay out
of Plato, one heathen out of another. It was the
praiſe of Cato
                  Hi mores, haec duri immota Catonis ſecta f
                        •
                     it, ſcr
                        •
                     are modum, finemque tenere, Naturamque ſequi patriaeque impendere vitam. Nec ſibi, ſed toti genitum ſe credere mundo. Lucan l. 2. that he was, In Commune bonus, good
for the Commonalty, being reſolued, that hee was
borne, not for himſelfe, but for all mankinde.
               But theſe Antipodes to Nature as well as vnto
Grace, theſe Man-haters, oppoſite to the Common
good, as if the world were made onely for them,
would appropriate the earth, and the fruits thereof,
wholly to themſelues, thinking that they can neuer
haue enough, vnleſſe they haue all; and that while
others haue any thing, they themſelues haue
nothing. Wherefore as Quailes grow fat with
Hem locke, which is poiſon to other creatures,
ſo theſe grow full by Dearth, which is the famiſhing
of others. Their whole ſtudy and endeuour is
to trouble the pure ſtreames of publike plenty, that
they may haue the better angling for their priuate
commodity.Eccle. 5. 9. 
                  The profite of the earth is for all (ſaith
Salomon) and the King himſelfe is ſerued by the field.
But theſe, as if the earth, and the profits thereof,
were proper to them alone, as if they were the
Kings of the field, and the whole tribute thereof
were to be payed into their inſatiable Exchequer,,
doe ſtudy how they may dry vp the publike fountaine,
or draw the whole ſtreame thereof into their
owne Ciſterne.Corn-horders traitours to nature. Traitors they are vnto Nature;
for thatThat which Nature moſt deſireth, they deteſt; that is, Plenty. which Nature moſt deſireth, they deteſt;

and that which Nature teacheth moſt to deteſt, that
doe theſe moſt deſire: Plenty is deſired by euery
well minded man, naturally, and Grace doth allow
ſuch deſire; for Plenty is a ſweet effect of
Gods goodneſſe and fauour, therefore called by
Dauid, the Crowne of the yeere:
                  Pſal. 65. 11. 
                  Thou crowneſt the
yeere with thy goodneſſe, and thy ſteps drop fatneſſe. But
theſe deſire to pull the Crowne of Plenty from
the head of the yeare, and inſtead thereof, would
put thereon a crowne of thornes, as the miſcreant
Iewes did on the head of Chriſt. Plenty is one
of Gods chiefeſt earthly bleſſings; but theſe enuious
children doe thinke that their poore brethren
haue too much of their heauenly Fathers bleſſing.
Againe,And that which nature teacheth moſt to deteſt, they doe moſt deſire, namely, Dearth and Scarcity. that which Nature teacheth moſt to deteſt,
they doe moſt deſire; namely, Dearth and Scarcity:
that which Nature teacheth to preuent, they
endeuour to procure; they pray for that which all
men elſe doe pray againſt; angry, in their mindes,
at our Leiturgie for hauing prayers againſt Dearth
and Famine, and thanksgiuings for ſeaſonable weather,
which they cannot endure ſaue in their owne
fields; ready to chide God becauſe he is ſo prodigall
of his temporall fauours, as to cauſeMat. 5. 45. 
                  his Sunne to
ariſe on the euill as well as on the good, and his raine to
fall on the iuſt and on the vniuſt; whereas theſe, by
their wils, would haue the Sunne to warme, and
the raine to moiſten no fields nor gardens, but of
the euill and vniuſt, that is, their owne. What
then can we thinke of them but as enemies both to
God and man, oppoſite both to Grace and Nature?
Salomon at the conſecration of the Temple1 King. 8. 38. making
way for the peoples prayers by his owne, for
the remouing of common calamities, ſetteth Famine
in the fore-front of them, as the firſt and worſt
of all. What ſhall we thinke of them who pray for

tht which Salomon prayed againſt, eſteeming that
a benefit to them, which is one of the greateſt
curſes that can fall on a Nation? When God threatneth
foure heauy iudgements on a Land, wherein if
theſe three Worthies, Noah, Iob, and Daniel were,
Ezech. 14. 13, 14. they ſhould deliuer none but their owne ſoules,
he giueth the precedence vnto Famine. What then
ſhall wee thinke of thoſe who care not though Iob,
Noah, and Daniel, and all the righteous men in the
Country ſtarued, ſo they may be filled? When
God by his Prophet makes a briefe Catalogue of
the crying ſinnes of Sodome, this comes in at laſt, not
as the leaſt of them,Ezec. 16. 49. 
                  Manum pauperis &amp; egentis non
confirmauit; Shee did not ſtrengthen the hands of the
poore and needy: It is not not ſaid that ſhee weakned,
but that ſhe did not ſtrengthen; &amp; that not the heart,
but the hand of the poore and needy; and yet God
rained hell out of Heauen, fire and brimſtone on
her to conſume her. What then ſhall become of
them who doe not ſtrengthen, but enfeeble, not the
hands, but the hearts of their poore brethren, by
with-holding from them that which is the ſtaffe of
their hands, and (vnder God) the ſtrength and life
of their hearts?
               And that theſe Cormorants are ſuch enemies to
the publike good,3. Condemned by the Lawes of Nations. all wiſe men who deſired to procure
it, haue perceiued. Therefore this curſed practice
of impriſoning the Countries prouiſion, hath
euer beene condemned by the Lawes of Nations.
Theſe Cankars of the Common-wealth were by
the ancients branded with odious appellations,
commonly called by the old Romans, Dardanarians,
vexers, ſcourgers, torturers, of the ſtore of the
yeare.Annonam vexare et tentare vel maximè Dardanarii ſolent, quorum auaritia itum eſt tam mandatis quàm coſtitutionibus. Vlpian. in leg. Annon. D. de extraordinar. criminio. Theſe Dardanarians (ſaith Vlpian their great
Ciuilian) are they who chiefly doe vex and perſecute
the annuall prouiſion, againſt whoſe Auarice

Princes and States haue alway oppoſed the barres
of edicts and conſtitutions.
               
                  There is extantan Epiſtle or Edict of Apollonius,
an ancient Gouernour, againſt thoſe ſcourgers of
the Country, by enforced Dearth and ſcarcity; the
beginning whereof, in effect is this;
                  Terra communis omnium mater eſt, propterea iuſta; vos autem iniuſti, qui eam duntaxat veſtram matrem eſſe voluiſtis; quod niſi ab huiuſmodi incepto deſtiteritis, diutiùs vos in ea permanere non ſinam. Epiſtol Apolloniꝭ ad a
                        •
                     nona vex
                        •
                     tores in princip. The Earth
(ſaith hee) is the common mother of all, and therefore
iuſt, but you are vniuſt who would ingroſſe her wholly to
your ſelues, and make a monopoly of the Common mother,
as if ſhee were bound to be a mother onely to you, and a
ſtep-mother to all her children beſides: but if you deſiſt
not from your doings, I will take order that ſhe ſhall not
long be a mother vnto you, but I will root you out of her,
as being vnworthy to be a burthen vnto her.
               I ſpeake nothing of our Nationall Lawes, becauſe
I ſpeake before them, who can better informe mee
herein, than I can others. The laſt Proclamation,
together with the booke, publiſhed by authority,
for fuller declaration of his Maieſties minde and
purpoſe, for preuenting the Dearth by puniſhing
theſe Dardanarians, hath breathed ſome life into
the poore Countrey, from whom theſe doe labour
to take away life, by with-holding the ſtay thereof.
God put it into the hearts of Gouernours to act,
as well as to enact; to performe, as well as to proclaime;
that the Proclamation againſt theſe horders
and huckſters be not like that Senatus conſultum
againſt the Mathematicians in Rome,De Mathemalicis Italia pelend is factum Senatus conſultum atrox et irritum. Tacit. Annal. l. 12. c. 52. 
                  Atrox at irritum,
fierce, but effectleſſe: and that theſe may not
be among vs,Genus hominum quod in Ciuitate noſtra &amp; vetabitur ſemper &amp; retinebitur. Tacit. hiſt. l c. 22. as the Hiſtorian complained, the others
were among them, a kinde of people alway condemned,
but euer repriued, if not acquitted. Affliction
is euer fearefull, and miſery ſtill miſtruſteth the
worſt: No maruell then if the poore people doe
miſdoubt, becauſe there ſeemeth a doore left open
to theſe their oppreſſors, that they ſhall not carry

their life from them without licenſe: wherefore
finding after ſo much thunder by edicts, little lightning
by effects, no lightening of their afflictions:
they feare that they haue cauſe to complaine, We are
all the worſe for licenſes. Theſe feares would ſoone
be remoued, and peraduenture theſe afflictions too,
if but one or two of the offenders in a Country were
puniſhed for terror to the reſt,Tacit, Annal. l. 2. c. 31. as Pituanius and
P. Martius were, when all the Mathematicians and
Magicians were baniſhed out of Italy.
               Three ſorts of people are found among vs,Application. Three ſorts of people guilty of this ſinne. guilty
of this ſinne, and conſequently lyable to the enſuing
Curſe: 1. the greedy Farmar: 2. The couetous
Marchant: 3. The cunning Huckſter, or Badger,
as they are called. I adde theſe Epithites to diſtinguiſh
between the guilty and the guiltleſſe in euery
profeſſion.
               The greedy Farmar ſometimes with-holds Corne
by ſelling it;1. The greedy Farmer, who ſometimes with-holds Corne euen in ſelling in. with-holding it from thoſe who need
it, to ſell it to thoſe who will make greater profit
by it; ſo that the needy ſhall more need it: For
who ſo ſelleth at a price too high for the poore, hee
with-holds it from the poore, as he doth meat from
a childe, who ſets it on a ſhelfe whereto hee cannot
reach. Now what is this, but Captare pretia frumenti,
to make the price too heauie, when either hee
will not ſend it to the Market, or if hee ſend, will
not ſell but at his owne price?
               Thou ſayeſt, I threſh out my Corne as faſt as I
can, and doe fell it, and therefore I am not guilty, I
am no with-holder of Corne. Thou ſelleſt, but to
whom? to the poore? No, vnleſſe as the Iewes did,
of whom Amos complained, that they ſold the refuſe
of the Wheat, and yet at the price of the beſt,
as if thou wouldeſt adde to the badneſſe of the
graine, and want of meaſure, the greatneſſe of the

price, to make a ſorry ſatisfaction. Thou ſelleſt it,
but to whom? to them who helpe thee to ſell the
reſt the deerer, to the Merchant or Badger, who by
exporting or tranſporting it farther, doe cauſe it to
be ſcarſer and deerer at home. Thou ſelleſt it, but
where? at home, in priuate, and ſo cauſeſt the Markets
to be vnfurniſhed. For how canſt thou haue
time to threſh for the Market, when all is too little
to threſh for the Merchant, whom thou haſt promiſed
to furniſh with ſo many ſcores of buſhels by
ſuch a day. The Markets are the Commons of the
common people, and of many who vſe good hoſpitality;
let them be incloſed, ſoone will theſe grow
leane: The Markets are their Magazines; if the
poore buyers be not there prouided, how ſhall their
wants be ſupplied? The Markets are their Wels,
if the couetous Farmers dry vp theſe, as the enuious
Philiſtims did the Wels of Iſaac, theſe poore ſheepe
muſt needs periſh. Thou ſelleſt, but in what manner?
In groſſe, or by ſuch quantities as the poore
cannot accompliſh; whereas if thou wilt ſhunne
the curſe threatned, and obtaine the bleſſing promiſed,
thou muſt doe as the Word importeth in
the ſecond part of my Text, Perfringere frumenta,
breake it out from the heape by ſmall parcels,
as the poore doe need for the preſent and are
able to compaſſe. Breake thy Bread to the hungry; ſo
breake thy Corne by halfe buſhels, by peckes, by
gallons to the needy, as their ability meeteth with
their neceſſity. To ſet a whole loafe before a childe
who hath neither ſtrength to breake, nor knife to
cut, is not to feed him, but to famiſh him.
               I am not vancquainted with ſome of their Apologies:
I haue made a Purchaſe, or taken a Leaſe,
or bought ſo much at a ſuruey to be paid on ſuch a
day, and I muſt ſell many Buſhels together to make
vp a good ſumme of money, I cannot tarry the leaſure

of theſe lingring Markets. All this while I
heare no arguments but drawne from the common
place of thine owne profit; and thou maieſt remember
that the buying of a Farme, and a yoke of Oxen
excluded the vnworthy gueſts from the great marriage
Feaſt; theſe excuſes are worſe. Thou haſt
made a purchaſe, and the calamity of the Countrey
muſt pay for it: thou haſt bought a bargaine, and
thy poore brethren, their wiues and children muſt
pinch for it. A bad bargaine (bare-gaine it may
well be called) to buy the curſes of God and man.
Say not that I condemne purchaſing, becauſe I am
no purchaſer, God grant I neuer bee in ſuch
manner. Buy Farmes, take Leaſes, make bargaines
for Oxen, Cattell, Corne, or what you will, as long
as you wrong not your own ſoules, which you cannot
chuſe but doe, if you wrong or pinch the poore
members of the Sauiour of ſoules.
               The couetous Marchant is alſo free of the company
of theſe Corne-catchers.2. The couetous Marchant. Hee with-holds
Corn from the poore, by drawing it from Markets,
to export it, or tranſport it into other parts or places
whether neerer or more remote; eſpecially out
of the Land, and that without regard of Religion, or
charity, or any thing elſe, ſaue his owne gaine,
which to him is godlineſſe. Tros, Tyrius
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     , Proteſtant,
Papiſt, Mahumetan, Engliſh, French, Spaniſh,
Barbarian, all are alike to him, ſo hee may gaine by
them. The ſauour of lucre is ſweet to him, though
raked out of the puddle of the moſt filthy profeſſion
in Europe, or in all the world. Miſtake me not,
I traduce not the calling, not onely lawfull, but laudible,
I may adde, honourable, the ſecond ſupporter
of the Kingdome. Not the Lyon and the 
                     Ʋnicorue,
but the Plough and the Ship, vnder God, are the
ſupporters of the Crowne. The Marchants by their

trauels and aduentures ioyne together forraigne Nations
which the Sea hath ſet farre aſunder; they
make remote Countries to bee ours vpon the matter,
cauſing their commodities to bee ours; caſting
with their Ships ſuch a Bridge ouer the Ocean, that
the chiefeſt, profits of both the Indies doe come
home to our houſes. I haue often yearned that they
haue beene no better conſidered of, but ſuffered to
be a prey to Dunkers abroad, and to as bad at home.
I know that it is lawfull to tranſport our commodities,
particularly our Corne into other Nations,
vpon ſome conditions, as other Nations doe make
vs partakers of their profits: yea, this ſometimes
may be done to thoſe who are of another, that is,
of an euill Religion. Nature teacheth this: The
Aegyptians releeued the Iſraelites in the Famine,
Gen. 43. 32. though it were an abomination to the Aegyptians,
in their peeuiſh ſuperſtition, to eat bread with the
Hebrewes, yet they would, in common humanity,
afford them bread to eat by themſelues. But this I
affirme; to famiſh Engliſh, and to feed French or
Spaniſh; to ſtarue brethren, and to nouriſh enemies;
to pinch the members of Chriſt, to preſerue the
limbs of Antichriſt; to thriue by the death of Saints,
and life of reprobates; this cannot poſſibly eſcape a
curſe; and all Marchants that vſe ſuch courſes, I can
ſay no better of them, than a bleſſed Saint ſaid at
leaſt three hundred yeares ſithence,Baſil. They are all
Mercatores humanarum calamitatum
                        •…
                     
                   Merchants of
mens calamities.
               The third ſort are theſe whom we call Badgers
of Corne,3. Huckſters, or Badgers of Corne. who were not to be condemned for conueying
Corne from thoſe places where it may well
be ſpared, to other places within the Countrey
where there is more want, if they did not procure
want in thoſe places where it doth abound, nor

foreſtall the Markets, but would take that which
the Markets doe leaue, nor raiſe the price to make
the poore to ſmart for it.
               Sufficient hath beene ſaid (I hope) to ſhew the
impietie, the inhumanity, the iniuſtice of this ſin
of procuring a Dearth by with-holding Corne; and
that it is a lawleſſe rebell againſt the laws of Grace,
of Nature,The ſinne of with-holding Corne, more hamous in our land, than in others. of Nations. Let this be farther added
and conſidered, that this oppreſſion is the more cruell,
and this cruelty the more heauy in our Land,
where Corne ſerueth both for Bread and Drinke;
whereas other Countries by the benefits of the ſoile
doe abound with wine; or becauſe of the heate of
the Climate, are contented with water. But among
vs theſe with-holders of Corne doe doubly plague
the poore people, ſtaruing them with hunger, and
choaking them with thirſt; depriuing them of that
which they ſhould both eat and drinke. Our children
doe not ſay vnto their mothers,Lament. 2, 12, 
                  Where is Corne
and Wine? Keepe you the Wine, giue vnto their
Mothers Corne, and they will finde in it both bread
and drinke that ſhall content them as well as wine.
But denie them Corne, you take from them bread,
drinke, life and all. Wherefore the curſes of theſe
Corn-mungers are likely to be doubled; for that is
the recompence they muſt expect for their curſed
couetouſneſſe, namely, curſes: and as the miſchiefe
is common, ſo it is iuſtly purſued with a common
curſe, the curſes of the Commons,
The People ſhall curſe him.
               
            
            
               
               
               THE SECOND
SERMON.
               
                  PRO. 11. 26.
                  The People ſhall curſe him.
               
               
                  THE ſinne and the odiouſneſſe
thereof to God and Man, hath
beene (in part) diſcouered, that it
may be ſhunned; and ſhunned it
will be the ſooner, if the iudgement
threatned be ſeriouſly conſidered;
which iudgement is expreſſed
in theſe words:
The People ſhall curſe him.
               
               
                  Populares] So Iunius with ſome others,The ſequell. The curſes of the people. doe render
the word, the Commons; or Popul
                        ••…
                     , as moſt
doe reade, the People, implying a collectiue curſe;
as if there were a gathering of curſes ouer the
whole Countrey, and none (ſaue ſuch as himſelfe)
refuſed to contribute curſes towards him. Not one
man, not a few, but the whole Countrey (as with
Hue-and-Cry) ſhall purſue him with curſes. Execrabuntur,
ſhall curſe and banne him; or Maledicent,
                  
ſhall ſay all euill of him, and pray that euill may befall
him. The Originall word is very Emphaticall,
Perſodient, they ſhall digge, or ſtab, or runne him
thorow with curſes. A Metaphor borrowed from
digging or ſtabbing; as who ſhould ſay, the people
with their curſes ſhall digge on him, as with Mattockes,
or runne him thorow, as with Rapiers.
               A common crime ſtill drawes on a common curſe.A common ſinne drawes on a common curſe.
God, in iuſtice doth vſe to proportion the puniſhment
to the offence. Who ſo hurteth or oppreſſeth
many, muſt looke to bee cried out againſt, and
to be curſed by many. The wings of their puniſhment
ſhall ſpread as farre as the tallands of their oppreſſion,
their iudgement ſhall be of equall dimenſions
with their tranſgreſſions. Our Dearth-mongers,
as they are procurers of a common calamitie, muſt
looke to be purſued with a common out-cry, the
whole Country ſhal ſtab them with curſings, as they
ſeeke to ſtab it with ſtaruing.
               But is this ſuch a puniſhment to be hunted with
the clamours and curſes of the people? Doubtleſſe
it is, when thoſe curſes are iuſtly cauſed by wrongs
done vnto the people. In ſuch caſes we may ſafely
lay downe this aſſertion,Doct. 2. that
The Peoples curſe, iustly procured, is a fearefull
iudgement.
               
               Hardly can there be a greater plague,A fearefull thing to be iuſtly curſed by the people. then to be
purſued by the clamours and curſes of the people
for oppreſſing them. Here we muſt diſtinguiſh, that
we may the more ſafely teach: The peoples curſe
is two-fold,The peoples curſe two-fold. either cauſed, or cauſeleſſe; iuſt, or
vniuſt; either iuſtly procured by ſome reall wrong
inſticted on them;1. Cauſleſſe or vniuſt, this not to be feared or regarded. or vniuſtly vented out of error or
malice, where no iuſt cauſe hath been giuen. Salomon
himſelfe affordeth vs this diſtinction, ſaying,Pro. 6▪2. 
                  As
the Bird by wandring, and the Swallow by flying, doe eſcape,

ſo the cauſeleſſe curſe ſhal not come to paſſe.
                  Sciendum eſt quòd ſcriptura ſacra duobus modis maledictum memorat, aliud videlicet quod approbat, aliud quod damnat. Aliud enim maledictum profortur iudicio iuſtitiae, aliud liuore vindictae Greg. Moral. l. 4. c. 5. Where
he ſheweth, that there is a cauſeleſſe curſe, which is
not to be feared: when people out of ſpleene, or
becauſe their corrupt humors are not ſatisfied, doe
flye to the fooles Aſylum, or ſhelter of execrations
or curſes. Such are the curſes of ſome impudent
and inſatiable beggars: ſuch are the curſes of ſome
deſperate malefactors againſt the Iudges, when they
are ſentenced according to Lawes and their
deſeruings: ſuch are the curſes of Roarers, ſonnes
of Belial, againſt zealous Miniſters, for diſcharging
their duties. Hence Ieremy complained, that hee
was cauſeleſly curſed;Ier. 15. 10. 
                  I haue not lent on vſury, neither
haue men lent to mee on vſury, yet euery one doth
curſe mee.
               
               
                  Exhortation to Magiſtrates and Officers to doe their duties though the people do cauſleſly curſe them. And it is not vnprobable that ſome of you (worthy
Magiſtrates) for diligence in doing your duties,
and for your laudable endeuours to furniſh the
Markets by drawing forth the Corne out of the
bands of horders, and the hands of huckſters, ſhall
carry away ſome curſes from the mouches or in the
mindes, of theſe mizars. 'Tis not vnlikely, but that
ſome of them (ſuch is their charity) will reward
you with curſes, euen for this your care to preuent
the curſes of the people vpon them. But be not diſcouraged,
Salomon hath ſecured you againſt ſuch
airie execrations. Theſe breath-bullets ſhall not
pierce you; theſe Speares of Reed, and Swords of
Bull-ruſhes ſhall not ſo much as pricke your reputations,
much leſſe your conſciences.Such curſes ſhall not hurt their credits or conſciences, but rebound on thoſe who do vſe them. The bubbles of
ſuch curſes ſhall fall into the faces and eyes of thoſe
who blow them vp: like mad-men they runne at
you with the hilt, but the point of the ſword runneth
into their owne breſt. Let that bee your refuge
which was Dauids in the like caſe, euen flying
vnto the Lord,Pſa. 109. 28. 
                  Let them curſe, but bleſſe thou. Say

you by them as he did by Shimei, when hee curſed
him,2 Sam 16. 12. For ſuch curſes God will bleſſe them. 
                  God will requite good for ſuch curſing. If for
doing Iuſtice, you bee vniuſtly purſued with virulent
tongues, the ſame promiſe appertaineth vnto
you, which the fountaine of bleſſedneſſe hath made
vnto vs:Mat. 5. 11. 12 
                  Bleſſed are yee when men reuile you, and
ſay all manner of euill againſt you falſely. Reioyce and be
glad, for great is your reward in heauen. Their curſes
are but like the Popes Bruta fulmina, his banning
Buls, which the more lowdly they bellowed againſt
Queene Elizabeth, of bleſſed memory, the better
ſhe proſpered, the more ſhe was bleſſedBeati ſuper quos talis maledictio cadit. Vtinam vt ſuper nos iſta maledictio veniat. Euſeb. Emiſ. ſeu. ſer. 4. poſt. 4, Domini.
               
               Therefore,I
                        •
                     ai 51. 7. 
                  Feare not the reproach of men, neither
be afraid of their reuilings; but,lſai 8. 13. 
                  Sanctifie the Lord of
Hoaſts himſelfe, let him be your feare, let him bee your
dread. Reſt in the bleſſing of the Lord,Ephe. 1. 3. 
                  Who hath
bleſſed vs with all Spirituall bleſſings in heauenly things
in Chriſt. Let theſe cauſeleſſe curſes be ſo farre from
hindering or diſheartning you in your lawfull courſes,
as that you doe rather reioyce in them, and
binde them as crownes to your heads; and be you
aſſured that the promiſe God made to Abraham,
belongeth to euery childe of his, continuing in his
faith and obedience, and ſo particularly vnto you,
Gen. 12. 3. 
                  I will bleſſe them that bleſſe thee, and will curſe him that
curſeth thee.
               
               Contrariwiſe, formidable is that curſe which is
extorted by oppreſſion,3. The iuſtly cauſed curſe of the poore &amp; oppreſſed, this is very fearefull. and vented forth from a
breſt ſurcharged with vexation. No Iron Bullet,
driuen by the ſtrongeſt powder, from the mouth of
a Cannon, is more terrible and tearing. Such a
curſe being ſhot from earth, mounteth vp to heauen;
and being ſent vp from man, is ſealed by God.
It is true, that the common people doe commonly
erre and offend herein; their curſes, many times
are their fooles-bolts, ſhot without ayme, and falling

without hurt, ſaue to themſelues. But many
times they are enforced, by grieuous preſſures, to
ſhoot theſe arrowes againſt their oppreſſors; and
then they hit ſurely, and wound deepely. In this
caſe the people haue a legatiue power like the Paſtors,
What they binde on earth, is bound in heauen.
Here the voyce of the people, eſpecially of the
poore, the people of God, is the voyce of the God
of the people. Therefore wee finde in Scripture,
that the curſe of the people, and a woe from God,
are all one vpon the reckoning. Our Wiſe man
ſaith, in this booke,Prou. 24. 24. See Pro. 17. 15 
                  Hee that ſaith vnto the wicked,
thou art righteous, the people ſhall curſe him. The Prophet
Iſay, inueighing againſt the ſame ſinne, ſaith,
Iſai 5. 30. 23 
                  VVoe to him that iuſtifieth the wicked for a reward.
Here you ſee that God addeth a woe to that ſinne
whereon the people doe affix a curſe: a curſe extorted
from them is ſealed with a woe denounced by
Him; p whoſe curſes, as they are neuer diſcharged
without iuſt cauſe, ſo they neuer returne without
effect.
               Heare and tremble all ye Nimrods,
                  Vſe. all you roughhanded
Eſawes,
                  Terrour to all oppreſſors of the poore. grinders of the poore, oppreſſors
of the people. Thinke not to fillip off theſe curſes
which your cruelties haue ſqueiſed from them,Vt quidam memoratur Athenis ſordidus &amp; diues vulgi cont
                        •
                     mnere voces Sic ſolitus, Populus me ſibilat ac mihi plaudo Ipſe domi quoties nummos contemplor in arca. with
Tuſh, what care I what the people ſay? The Fox, the
more he is curſed, the better he fares.
                  Maledictio diuina ſicut nunquam temerè emittitur ita nunquam re infecta reuertitur. Cartw
                        •
                      ad Text. Let them curſe
and ſpare not, as long as ſuch curſes doe fill my
Coffers. Know you, that the curſe of the people,
iuſtly cauſed, is a vapor exhaled from earth; or rather
indeed a thunder, which cauſeth a thunder-bolt to
be caſt downe from heauen. Let the oppreſſor poſte
from it as faſt as he can, it ſhall ouertake him (r as
the arrow of Iehu did Iehoram) and ſmite him betweene
his armes,Horat. l 1. ſat. 1 
                        •
                      2 King. 9. 24 and runne thorow his heart; let
him fence himſelfe with the beſt amunition that

hee may, it ſhall pierce him thorow. No coate of
male ſhall rebate the edge, no armour of proofe
ſhall beare off the ſtroke of the peoples curſe, when
it is edged with iuſtly conceiued paſſion and backed
by the Almighties approbation. Wiſe men
therefore will hearken vnto the counſell of wiſe
Syrachides;
                  Ecel 4 2, 3, 5, 6. 
                  Make not an hungry ſoule ſorrowfull, neither
prouoke a man that is in diſtres. Adde not more trouble
to an heart that is vexed, defer not to giue to him that
is in need. Turne not thine eyes from the needy, and
giue him no occaſion to curſe thee; for if he curſe thee in
the bitterneſſe of his ſoule, his prayer ſhall be heard of him
that made him.
               
               And among all grinders of the poore,Eſpecially to Corne horders. tremble
you who with-hold from them that which they
ſhould grinde for the neceſſary ſuſtenance of life,
and ſo grinde them the more, becauſe you keepe
them from grinding. You rurall Tyrants, who, by
with-holding your Corne, doe enforce the miſerable
people to flie to their for lorne hope of ringing
a peale of curſes, againſt your couetouſneſſe, in the
eares of the Almighty. IfIam. 5. 4. 
                  the hire of the labourers,
who haue reaped downe your fields, being by fraud kept
backe, cryeth, and thoſe cries doe enter into the eares of
the Lord of Sabboth: then doubtleſſe, the deſerued
curſes of thoſe who are ready to periſh, becauſe
you will not ſo much as fell vnto them that which
they laboured to reape, and to ſaue for you, and
which without the ſweat of their browes, and galling
of their hands, you could not haue ſaued, doe
ſound like a volley of ſhot in the eares of the God
of mercies, and will awake him to take vengeance
on your curſed cruelties.Exod. 2
                        •
                     . 22, 23, 24. 
                  If any widdow or fatherleſſe
childe be afflicted by thee (ſaith the Lord) and in their
affliction doe at all cry vnto me, I will ſurely heare their
cry, and my wrath ſhall wax hot, and I will kill you with

the Sword, and your wiues ſhall bee widdowes, and your
children fatherleſſe. Will God heare the cry of one
widdow, of one fatherleſſe childe, being afflicted,
and can his eares be ſhut at the generall cry of the
whole multitude, among whom are ſo many widdowes,
ſo many Orphans, and ſome of them (doubtleſſe)
his owne children, the ſonnes and daughters
of his deare Saints, the linely members of his onely
begotten ſonne Chriſt Ieſus?
               And that theſe enforced curſes are not alwayes
effectleſſe in this life,That theſe curſes are not effectleſſe in this life, ſhewed by examples. witneſſe the fearefull iudgements
which God hath inflicted on ſome Nabals
for terror vnto others. I could tell you old Chronicle-ſtories
out of Matthew Paris, and others, of
terrible examples in our owne Land, vpon offenders
in this kinde.A ſtory out of Matthew Paris, of Walter Grey, Archbiſhop of Yorke, a couetous Corn-horder. As that of Walter Grey, an Archbiſhop
of Yorke, in the yeare of grace, 1234.
Who hauing fiue yeares Corne vnder-hand, would
not threſh it out for the releefe of the poore in
three yeeres famine, hoping ſtill that the price
would encreaſe. Being aduertiſed by his Officers
that it was greatly to be feared, leſt the Corne were
conſumed by Mice,An. Dom. 1234. he willed them to deliuer it to
the Husband-men, who dwelt in his Mannor, vpon
condition that they ſhould pay him as much
new Wheat for it after Harueſt. They attempting
to take downe a great mow of Corne which hee
had at Rippon, ſaw the heads of many Snakes, and
Toads, and other venemous creatures peering out
at the end of the ſheaues. This being related to the
Archbiſhop, hee ſent his Steward with diuers of
good credite to enquire the truth thereof, who ſeeing
what others had ſeene, enforced, not withſtanding,
certaine poore men to goe vp to the top with
ladders. They were ſcarcely vp, when they ſaw a
great ſmoake ariſing out of the corne, and felt withall

a loathſome ſtinke, which compelled them with
all haſte poſſible to hye them downe againe: Moreouer,
they heard an vnknowne voyce ſaying vnto
them, Let the Corne alone, for the Archbiſhop and all
that he hath, belongeth to the Diuell. In fine (ſaith the
Story) they were faine to build a wall about the
corne, and then to ſet it on fire, fearing leſt ſuch an
huge number of venemous creatures ſhould empoiſon,
at leaſt annoy the whole Country. I could tell
you out of forraine Authors, of aAnother of a German Biſhop deuoured by Rats. Anno 930. 
                  German Biſhop,
who in time of dearth kept in his Corne, and called
the poore which came about him begging reliefe,
the Rats and Mice which deuoured his Corne. But
God retorted his malicious ſcomme vpon his owne
head;Hatto Epiſcopus Moguntinenſis.—Nomineq idem Epiſcopus et Paſtor, ſed reipſa Lupus. Scribunt quidam quòd mures quo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      
                     
                        •
                     o men eius detentes a parietibus et tapetibus aebraſerint.—Inde &amp; in hodiernum diem turris ipſa, turris muri
                        •
                     m vocatu. Iob Fincel. Andr. Houſdorphius. Phil. Laui
                        •
                     er. in theat. hiſtor. Theod. Zuinger. in Theat. vit. human. l. 18. Rauiſius Textor. for he himſelfe was ſoone after deuoured aliue
by Rats and Mice, notwithſtanding that he immured
himſelfe in a ſtrong Tower, which is reported
to be yet ſtanding, and in the name it beareth to
retaine a memoriall of the ſtrange Iudgement.
               I had rather preferre to your conſideration the
pious action ofB. Godwin. Catalogue of Engliſh Biſhops. 
                  Ethelwald, a Biſhop of Winchester,
before the Conqueſt, who in a great Dearth, did
breake vp all the Plate belonging to his Church,
and gaue it to the poore, ſaying, that the Church in
good time might be prouided of neceſſary ornaments, but
the poore that periſhed for want of food, could not be recouered.
               
               But theſe examples of ancient times doe leſſe affect,
and may be held fabulous.The effect of theſe curſes in latter times, wherein ſome of theſe Nabals haue hanged themſelues, when the price of Corne hath fallen. That God hath
made the curſes of the poore effectuall vpon ſuch
couetous Corne-horders, euen in recent remembrance,
may appeare by this, that ſome of this curſed

crue haue become their owne executioners, and
in kindneſſe haue ſaued the Hang-man a labour by
haltering themſelues, when contrary to their expectation,
the price of corne hath ſodainly fallen: and
this both in other Countries, and among vs, asLauater, Cartwright ad Text. Diuines
of good reputation haue deliuered vpon their
owne knowledge.
               But worſt of all will be,The greateſt curſe of all, at the day of Iudgement. when Chriſt at the great
and terrible day of his comming ſhall adde vnto all
theſe the inſupportable weight of his heauie and intolerable
curſe, when he ſhall ſay vnto theſe, as vnto
others (in ſome reſpects more excuſable then theſe)
Mat. 25. 41, 42. 
                  Depart ye curſed into euerlasting fire, prepared for the
Diuell and his Angels; for I was hungry, and yee gaue
me no meate, I was thirstie, and you gaue mee no drinke:
nay, you would not ſo much as ſell mee meate and
drinke for ready money, and at a deere rate, when
by relieuing mee you might haue enriched your
ſelues; by feeding me, you might haue filled your
owne purſes. Oh what ſhall be ſaid to them who
will not ſell for money, when Depart from me ye curſed,
is the mildeſt word that Chriſt ſhall afford
them, who would not giue freely? What Hell ſhall
be hot enough for thoſe that will not ſell, when
Hell fire is prepared for thoſe who would not
giue?
               Shall I ſpeake now vnto the deafe Adder, who
will not heare the voyce of the Charmer? ſhall I
looſe my ſweet words by ſpending them on ſtones
or ſtony hearts, who regard not the Law of God,
the command of the King, the cry of the Country,
the curſes of the people, the teares diſtilling downe
the widdowes cheekes, the ſighes exhaled from
Orphants fainting tongues, the ruthfull ſpectacles of
hunger-ſtarued ſcellitons, whoſe very ſight-might
diſſolue eyes of adamant into teares? they who are

not moued by any of theſe, by all of theſe, what hope
is there that they will be mollified by my weake
words? But a neceſſity is laid vpon vs, and wee
muſt ſpeake; for if wee ſhould be ſilent, the ſtones
would euen cry out againſt theſe, whoſe hearts are
harder then the nether Milſtone. If they will not
heare vs, let them yet tremble at this determinate
ſpeech of God himſelfe by Salomon, Captans pretia
frumenti maledictus eſt in plebe: Hee is curſed by the
people who catcheth at aduantages by the price of
Corne. The ſentence is peremptory (Definita eſt ſententia, nihil diſputationi relinquens. Ambros. Offic. l. 3. c. 6. ſaith a Saint)
leauing no place for diſputation. If thou doeſt ſo,
pretend what thou wilt, fill thy mouth with arguments,
caſt the beſt colour on the matter that thou
canſt, all thy fig-leaued Apologies will not fence
thee from the curſe.
               Thou wilt ſay peraduenture,Obiections anſwered. I do no man wrong,
I keepe but mine owne, I may ſell mine owne when
I pleaſe; Is it not lawfull for me to doe with mine
owne what I liſt?1. May I not do with mine owne as I liſt?
               
               But know, firſt, that thou abuſeſt the words of
Chriſt,
                  Anſw. He onely (becauſe he is Lord of all) may doe
with his own what pleaſeth him.Chriſt onely may doe with his owne as he liſt. Man cānot, becauſe
he is not abſolute owner of any thing; for what
hath he that he hath not receiued: He muſt therefore
doe with his owne, that which pleaſeth the
Supreme owner of all things.Man cannot, who can call properly nothing his own ſaue his ſin. Againe, call it thine
owne; it is not lawfull for thee to doe with thine
owne what thou wilt, vnleſſe thou wilt doe that
which is lawfull and right. Thou mayſt not vſe
thine owne to the hurt of another man.Men may not vſe their own to the hurt of others. Thou
mayeſt not murther with thine owne ſword, nor
make men drunke with thine owne drinke, nor
burne thy neighbours houſe with thine owne fire.
God, who is the owner of the earth, telleth thee
that thou mayeſt not with-hold his (which thou vnproperly

calleſt thy) Corne, thereby to famiſh and
impoueriſh thy brethren.It is damnable to withhold our own when others are ready to periſh for want of that which we may well ſpare. The purple Glutton fries
in hell fire for with-holding his owne bread from
poore Lazarus, lying at his gate. It coſt Nabals life,
for denying his owne bread and victuals to Dauid
and his followers, when he kindely craued it in his
need. What canſt thou expect then, who wilt rather
be curſed by the poore, than ſell thine own to them
at a reaſonable rate in their neceſſity? Know this
therfore, that this Corne is not thine own, but it belongeth
rather to the poore when they need it, and
thou canſt well afford it. Thou takeſt from them
that which is theirs, by with-holding from them
that which thou calleſt thine. Thou doeſt wrong enough,
in not doing right; thou exerciſeſt cruelty,
in not ſhewing mercy; thou killeſt all, from whom
thou keepeſt that which ſhould keepe them aliue.
Is he a theefe that takes from a man his owne, and
makes him to be in want? What is hee leſſe, that
will not ſell a poore man his owne when hee is in
want? It is the worſt kinde of couetouſneſſe (ſaith
aVideatur D. Baſilius ſer. 1. in Auaros. Saint) not to giue to thoſe who are ready to periſh,
that which otherwiſe will periſh; what is it
then not to ſell it vnto them? Thou ſayeſt (ſaith
the ſame) To whom doe I wrong, if I keepe mine
owne? I demand of thee againe (in the words of
that bleſſed man) What are thoſe things thou calleſt
thine owne? Thou anſwereſt, why? my Coine,
my Clothes, my Corne. But how came theſe things
to be thine owne? Didſt thou bring them with
thee into the world? Didſt thou not come naked
out of thy mothers wombe? Shalt thou not returne
naked againe? Whence then haſt thou theſe
things? If thou ſayeſt, I got them by chance, or it
is my good fortune that I haue them; thou doeſt
not acknowledge the author and diſpoſer of all

things, thou art vnthankefull, thou art no better
than an Atheiſt. If thou confeſſeſt thou haſt them
from God, that he gaue them vnto thee; then tell
me, why did God giue them vnto thee rather than
vnto another? For God is not vniuſt, or one that
knoweth not how to diuide his owne gifts in equall
proportions. Why then hath God giuen thee ſo
much, and him ſo little? Why art thou rich, and
hee poore? Certainely for no other cauſe, but that
thy fulneſſe might ſupply his want, and that both
might, doing their duties, obtaine of him a reward;
thou of faithfull diſtributing, and hee of
his patient enduring. If all were rich, what praiſe
were there of patience? If all were poore, who
ſhould be able to ſhew charity? If there were, in
this kinde, an equality, two pretious vertues would
be vile or not at all, Charity and Patience. Therefore
the moſt prudent diſpoſer of all things, hath
moſt prouidently ordained this inequality, that as
the patience of the poore is exerciſed in wanting,
ſo the charity of the rich may be ſhewed in releeuing.
But thou, griping all in the tallands of thine
inſatiable Auarice, and thereby depriuing ſo many
of their portions, ſaiſt thou keepeſt but thine owne,
and thou wrongeſt no man. Thou doeſt herein
(ſaith the ſame bleſſed Biſhop) as if entring into a
Theatre, thou keepe, or driue out all other ſpectators,
as though thoſe ſhewes, which were prouided
for all, were proper to thee alone: or, as if inuited
to a feaſt by a great friend, together with many
other gueſts as good, or better than thy ſelfe,
thou ſhouldeſt ſit downe at the table, and keepe all
the diſhes to thy ſelfe, excluding the reſt, as if the
whole dinner were prouided for thee alone. Yet
ſtill thou ſayeſt, I keepe but mine owne, I doe no
man wrong. But tell mee ſadly, Who is a couetous

man? Hee who is not contented with that which
is ſufficient, but ſtill craueth more. Tell mee againe,
who is a theefe? Hee who takes away that
which is another mans. Art not thou then couetous,
who art not contented with that which is
too much, and which would well content an hundred
men, as good, and as dearely bought by Chriſt,
as thou art? Art not thou a theefe, who keepeſt
that to thy ſelfe which thou haſt receiued of thy
Lord and Maſter to diſtribute and diuide among
thy fellow-ſeruants, thine owne portion (and that
double, treble, yea ſeuen to one of theirs) being
allowed thee? Shall hee who takes away a mans
garment from him, be called a robber, and ſhall not
he who will not clothe the naked, if hee bee able,
be alſo a ſpoiler? Shall hee who kils a man with a
ſword, be called a murtherer, and ſhall hee bee any
better that with-holdeth from him that whereof
the want will ſhortly kill him? Doth not hee put
out the Lampe that powreth not oyle into it, as
well as he that blowes it out? Doth not he put out
the fire that puts not on wood, as well as hee that
throwes on water? What's the oddes, but that
which the murtherer doth ſuddenly, thou doeſt it
leaſurely and lingringly, and ſo art the more cruell
murtherer of the two; becauſe thou doeſt not
quickly diſpatch, but doubleſtTriſtior eſt laetho, laethi mora. Death by delaying,
andProb ſaeuior enſe Parcendi rabies conceſſa
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      vit
                        •
                      dolori. Claudian. extendeſt life onely for greater torment;
not ſo mercifull as a courteous hangman, that leaps
on the ſhoulders, or puls by the heeles, to put out of
paine; but rather as cruell as thatLutum ſanguine. maceratum. Caligula
                        •
                     
                   Tyrant, who was
ſaid to be nothing but morter made of bloud, not
contented to put innocents vnto deathIta ferivt ſentiant ſe meri, Sueton. vnleſſe the
Executioner did ſo ſtrike them, that they might
be ſenſible of their dying. Neuer ſay then that thou
keepeſt but thine owne. It is the bread of the hungry

which thou detaineſt; it is the garment of the
naked which thou ſuffereſt to lye Moath-eaten in
thy preſſe; It is the gold and ſiluer of the needy,
which ruſteth in thy Coffer: It is the Corne of the
poore, ready to dye with hunger, which thou ſuffereſt
to moulder in thy Mow or Barne. Neuer
ſay, thou doeſt no man wrong. Thou wrongeſt ſo
many as thou doeſt not releeue, being able. Calleſt
thou thy ſelfe a Chriſtian, and argueſt thou
thus, quite contrary to the rules of Chriſtianity?
Anſwer once an Heathen who neuer knew Chriſt
and his Goſpell, vnto his ſhort queſtion:
Cur eget indignus quiſquam te diuite?Horat.
                  
               
               Why ſeeſt thou any one to want; who is vnworthy,
while thou doeſt abound? Art thou not vnnaturall,
who ſuffereſt that which nature cannot
endure, vacuity? Art thou worthy to breathe the
ayre, who wilt not endeuour to doe as the ayre
doth, ſhift ſome of it ſelfe from places that are oner-full,
to others that are empty? How canſt thou
call thy ſelfe a Chriſtian, when the members of
Chriſt doe quiuer with cold for want of that
which doth clothe the Moaths in thy preſſe? Or
to want neceſſaries, for lacke of that which the
ruſt conſumes in thy bagges, or ſtarue for need of
of that which releeueth Rats and Mice in thy
Barnes? Hee is a bad ſeruant who will flaunt it in
ſilks himſelfe, gotten by his maſters goods, and
glut himſelfe with the choiceſt food, and ſee his
Maſters children, (yea the Maſter himſelfe in them)
goe naked, or ready to ſtarue for want of bread.
               But did not religious Ioſeph in the yeares of
plenty,Obiect. 2. gather and keepe vp Corne, which he ſold
afterward in the yeares of famine?
                     Ioſephs example anſwered. He did ſo, and
that lawfully; for you haue beene told that there is
a lawfull ſtoring vp of Corne, when it is done, as

                  Ioſeph did, not to procure a Dearth, but to preuent
it, or to be the better prouided againſt it.Fortaſſe dicet. Et Ioſeph in abundantia frum
                        •
                     nta collegit, in caritate vendidit. Ioſeph ſanctus omnibus aperuit horrea, non clauſit, nec pretia captauit annonae, ſed perenne ſubſidium collecauit, nihil ſibi acquiſiuit, ſed quemadmodum fames etiam in poſterum vinceretur prouida ordinatione diſpoſuit. Ambr. Offic. l. 3 c. 6. Godly
Ioſeph opened his Garners in the yeares of famine
he did not ſhut them; his intent was not to raiſe
the price, but to prouide a ſupply againſt the time
of want. He gathered and kept not for himſelfe, but
for others, euen for ſtrangers: thou with-holdeſt
it from neighbours, and wilt ſuffer vile vermin
to feed on it, rather than thy brethren. Shameſt
thou not to alleage the example of Ioſeph, whoſe
care for the common good ſo directly condemneth
thy couetouſneſſe, who careſt for none but for thy
ſelfe.
               
                  Obiect. 3. Gedeons example. Iudg. 6. 11. Anſwered, B. o
                           •
                        
                      Exon. Contemplat. vol. 3. l. 9. Gedeons calling.
                   But doe wee not read that Gedeon threſhed out
his Corne, not to ſell it, but to hide it, and yet is not
blamed for ſo doing?
               He did. But when did hee hide his Corne? in
time of inuaſion by the enemy. His Garner might
be cloſer and ſafer than his Barne. And from whom
did he hide it? not from his neighbours, but from
his and their enemies, the Midianites. Thy courſe is
quite contrary. Then the Iſraelites threſhed out
their corne to hide it from the Midianites: but our
Midianites will not threſh out theirs, or if they
doe, it is to hide it from the Iſraelites. The Sword
of the Lord and of Gedeon (the godly Magiſtrate) bee
againſt ſuch mercileſſe Midianites.
               
               
                  Famine, agrieuous iudgement. Dearth and Famine is one of the moſt grieuous
Iudgements which God inflicteth on a ſinfull Nation.
Ezech. 6. 11 
                  Thou ſhalt fall by the Sword, by Famine, and by
the Peſtilence. Theſe are the three rods wherewith
God vſeth to ſcourge a wanton and wicked people.
I know that ſome graueB. Cowper on Rom. 8. 35. Diuines doe affirme Famine
to bee the eaſieſt of the three, becauſe God,
who beſt knowes the waight of his owne rods,
accounteth three daies Peſtilence, and three months

of the ſword, equall with ſeuen yeeres famine. But
this to me ſeemeth no ſufficient reaſon: ſure I am,
that Dauid, in his hard choice, preferred peſtilence
before it;2 Sam. 24. 14, 15. and it is not probable, that hee would
chooſe the heauieſt puniſhment. Beſides, the Prophet
Ieremie ſaith,
                     Lamen. 4. 9. Dira fames ſemper magnorum prima malorum 1ſt comes
                        ••
                      Lucand
                        •
                     . 
                  They that be ſlaine by the ſword,
are better then they that be ſtaine by hunger. Moreouer,
this ſcourge of famine is the worſe and the more
intolerable for the miſeries and miſchiefes that doe
commonly attend it. Peſtilence often is the companion
of it, robberies, rebellions, outrages and other
enormities are the Pages that doe wait vpon
it. Dire famine! thou haſt taught tender-hearted
Mothers to turne Cannibals, and to become Butchers,
cookes, caruers, eaters of their owne children:
Thou haſt taught men to exceed Cannibals, and for
want of other food to deuoure their owne fleſh, and
as much as they might, to eat vp themſelues. For
this Ieremie moſt lamenteth, as for the moſt lamentable
iudgement,Lam 2. 11, 12 
                  Mine eye doth faile with teares, my
bowels are troubled, my liuer is powred vpon the earth,
for the deſtruction of the daughter of my people; becauſe
the children and ſucklings doe ſwowne in the ſtreets of the
Catie. They ſay vnto their Mothers, where is corne and
wine? They ſwowned as the wounded in the ſtreets of the
Citty, their ſoule is powred out into their Mothers boſome.
That which followes is moſt patheticall;
Lam. 2. 20. 
                  Shall the women eat their owne fruit, and their children
of aſpan long?
               
               Now it is proper to the Lord alone to puniſh a
ſinfull Nation.It▪ is proper to God alone to puniſh a ſinfull Nation with famine or any other iudgement. He knowes when it is fitteſt to whip
a people with famine, and he hath wayes enough to
bring ſuch a calamitie on a Country whenſoeuer it
pleaſeth him:Pſal 107. 34. 
                  A fruitfull land he turneth into barrenneſſe,
for the wickedneſſe of the people that dwell therein.
SometimesLeu. 26. 29. 
                  he makes the heauens aboue as braſſe,

and the earth beneath as iron: ſo that albeit men doe
labour and ſowe, yet they receiue no increaſe. Sometimes
againe,Deut. 11. 14. 
                  he giueth the former and the later raine
in due ſeaſon, ſo that the earth yeeldeth abundance;
but the Lord ſending blaſts, ruſts, Mel-dewes, Caterpillars,
Canker-wormes, doth cauſe the hope of
the yeere to faile: as if ſuch worthleſſe creatures
were more worthy to enioy the fruits of the earth,
then ſinfull and vnthankfull man: ſometimes euen
when the Corne is not yet reaped, but expecteth
the hooke, or while it ſtandeth in the field awaiting
to be houſed in the Barne, God ſends airie threſhers,
violent windes, to beat it out of the eare; the
furrowes of the field doe become the threſhing-floore;
the Wheat is ſowed where it grew, and
that without the helpe of hand, plow or harrow:
thus harueſt, threſhing, and ſeed-time doe vntimely
meet together, as they did ſome few yeers ſince.
Our crying ſinnes,We haue deſerued to be thus ſcourged particularly the vile abuſe of the
creature by Drunkenneſſe and riot, haue called for
vengeance, and we haue deſerued to be ſcourged,
not only with famine, but with the other two rods,
with ſword alſo and with peſtilence.
               But this Dearth is not inflicted immediately by
the hand of God,But this Famine is not inflicted immediately by God, but enforced by the cruell couetouſneſſe of Men. but enforced by wicked mens
cruell couetouſneſſe. God hath not broken the ſtaffe
of bread, but churliſh Nabals haue gotten it into
their owne fiſts, and with-hold it from the people
who ſhould be ſupported by it. We cannot complaine,
Ioel 1. 10. 
                  The field is wasted, and yet the Land mourneth;
the Corne is not waſted, but with-held. God
hath not ſent want of bread, but couetouſneſſe hath
cauſed cleanneſſe of teeth. God hath not ſmitten
vs with blaſting, nor ſent Caterpillers, nor Cankerwormes,
but the Diuell hath raiſed vp Caterpillers
and Locuſts, thoſeFrumentarii pretii captatores, Amb Offic. 
                        •
                     . 3. c. 6. Catchers at the Dearth of Corn

(as the Father ſtileth them) and theſe doe make a
priuate gaine of a publike detriment, improuing
that as a profit to themſelues, which God ordained
as a plague for ſinners;Hoſ. 2. 21, 22 
                  The Lord hath heard the
heauens, and the heauens haue heard the earth, and the
earth hath heard the corne; but thoſe earth-wormes
will not heare the voice of the Lord, nor the crying
complaints of the poore. The earth hath anſwered
the expectation of the ſower, but cannot anſwer the
vnſatiable greedineſſe of the ſeller. Many Mens
Barnes are full of Corne, but their breſts are empty
of compaſſion: their Garners are ſtuffed and ſtored;
two yeeres graine vnder hand in many mens
keeping, yet they ſtill gape for a greater dearth, and
doe their beſt, or rather worſt to procure it. They
ſuffer their Mow-hayes to ſtand laden with corne
neere the high-wayes, in the open view of the
poore, the more to anger their hunger. Thus they
bring vpon their brethren on earth a torment, much
like that which Poets deuiſed for Tantalus in Hell,
to haue faire apples at his lips, and yet to pine with
hunger; and in the midſt of faire water vp to the
chinne, to periſh with thirſt.Ezech. 5. 16. 
                  Theſe arrowes of famine
that haue wounded our ſides, had leſſe afflicted
vs, had they beene ſhot directly from the iuſt hand
of God; him wee could haue entreated with our
prayers, mollified with our teares, pacified with
our repentance; But nothing can preuaile with impenitrable
Auarice:Sam. 24. 14 
                  O let vs fall into the hands of
God (for his mercies are great) but let vs not fall into the
hands of mercileſſe men. If our ſinnes muſt needs be
ſcourged, let not greater ſinners be the Beadles:
Who hath giuen you commiſſion to be the Countries
hangmen? where is your warrant to thruſt
your ſelues into the ſeat of Gods iuſtice; or to take
his quiuer and to ſhoot againſt his children thoſe

arrowes which hee keepeth againſt his enemies?
You may indeed, for a while, be the rods of Gods
wrath (as Aſhur was to Iſrael) but vpon our true repentance,
God will turne his wrath from vs, vpon
you: and the childe being humbred, the rod ſhall be
caſt into the fire.
               O inſatiable Auarice!An inuectiue againſt couetouſneſſe. Doth not the earth yeeld
thee ſufficient encreaſe? what meaneſt thou to plow
and harrow the very guts of thy poore brother for
greater gaine? Now it is farre worſe then they
ſaid it was in the beginning of the iron-age; for
then CouetouſneſſeItum eſt in viſcera terrae. went but into the bowels of
the earth; but now menItum eſt in viſcera fratrum digge into the bowels
of their brethren, yea,Itum eſt in viſcera Chriſti. they delue into the bowels
of Chriſt himſelfe for coyne.
               Call ye me this 
                     Ʋſurie, or rather Fellonie?
                  
                     Theſe Corn-horders worſe then Vſurers. Latrocinium hoc an foenus appellem? Captantur tanquā latrociniꝭ tempora quibus in viſ
                        •
                     era hominum clarus inſidiator obrepas Ambr▪ vbi ſupr. Vſury
it ſelfe is charitable in reſpect of this. Vſury yet
ſends abroad money for money; this rurall ſacriledge
will not ſell corne for coyne. Vſury indeed
biteth, but this killeth by keeping away that which
ſhould ſuſtaine life. Vſury by money ſtealeth money
out of mens purſes (as one by powring a little
water into a dry Pumpe, forceth out a great deale
more) but this Burglary breaketh into mens bowels,
and robbeth them of that which ſhould maintaine
them. Is not this gaine more odious, more
baſe then that of the Emperour, who extracted gold
out of Vrine? I perceiue, that among our Pagan-Chriſtians,
it holds as currant as it did among the
Pagans;Lucri bonus eſt odor ex re Qualibet—Iuuenal 
                  Sweet is the ſcent of Siluer, out of what
ſinke ſoeuer it be raked: ſeeing to theſe Horſe-leeches
gaine is ſweet, though ſucked out of the bowels of
their brethren.
               Oh, if you haue any bowels your ſelues, or haue
not drunke vp that obdurate riuer,Flumen habent Cicones quod potum ſaxea reddit Ʋiſcera, quod tactis inducit marmora rebus Ouid. M
                        •
                     tam. which is reported
to turne the bowels of the drinker into

hard marble; looke once ouer the threſhold of your
poore neighbour, ſome poore coater, ſome daily
labourer, for his groat or three pence a day, groning
vnder the burthen of an heauy houſe-rent,
with a houſe full of ſmall children on the bargaine;
and if you will not enter in, yet ſtand without a
while, and become officious Eueſ-droppers, liſten
to the pittious complaints that are among them.
There may you ſee,The pittifull eſtate of poore labourers in theſe hard times, deplored. or heare the wofull mother,
with her eldeſt daughter, the one carding or knitting,
the other ſpinning a ſorry threed, and ſinging
to her turne an heauy tune of ſome ſorrowfull
Pſalme; as, O Lord conſider my diſtreſſe; or, O Lord
how are my foes increaſt; or, Helpe Lord, for good and
godly men doe periſh and decay: Then awakes the poore
ſucking Infant, and crying, interrupts both worke
and muſicke: The mother takes it vp, and giues it
ſucke with teares, for with milke ſhe cannot. Alas!
how can the infant draw milke from the breaſt,
when the Nurſe cannot get meat for the belly: Mother,
ſaith another childe, when ſhall we eat? Mother,
ſaith another, where is bread? O mother,
ſaith another, I am ſo hungry I know not what to
doe. Thus the feeble children doe call vpon the
wofull mother, ſhee complaines to the ſad father,
he anſwers her with pittious complaints againſt
the pittileſſe neighbours; Alas! What ſhall I doe?
I haue beene at goodman—ſuch a ones houſe;
from him I went to goodman—ſuch a one (good
men with a miſchiefe, that haue not a mite of goodneſſe
in them, becauſe no compaſſion on their miſerable
fellow-members,) I haue beene ouer the Pariſh,
I haue beene out of the Pariſh, with money in
my hand, and cannot get a pecke of Barley: they
haue it, but they ſay they cannot ſpare it. O miſerable
condition! the poore man is put to a double

labour; firſt, to get a little money for Corne, and
then to get a little Corne for money, and this laſt
is the hardeſt labour: he might haue earned almoſt
halfe a Buſhell, while hee ruunes about begging to
buy halfe a pecke. Thus doe our Country-Pharaohs
make their brethren bondſlaues, enforcing them to
make Bricke, and denying them Straw; crying,
Hang them, hang them if they ſteale, yet not ſetting
them on worke, nor releeuing them when
they haue wrought, and ſo enforcing them either to
ſteale or to ſtarue.
               Remember, O ye Palmer-wormes remember,
your predeceſſour, the rich foole in the Goſpell.

                     Luk. 12. 16. Quid faciam? Nonne haec pauperis vox eſt, non habentis ſubſidia viuendi?—Quid faciam (inquit) quòd non habeo? Clamat ſediues non habere; Paupertatis hic Sermo eſt, de inopia queritur abundans fructibus.—Et dixit, Hoc faciam, horrea mea deſtruam. Diceret potius, Aperiam horrea mea, ingrediantur qui tolerare famem non queunt, veniant inopes, intrent pauperes, repleant ſinus ſuos. Deſiruantur parietes qui excludunt eſarientes. Vt quid ego abſcondam cui Deus facit ab indare quod l
                        •
                     rgior? Ambros. l de Nabuth c 6. Id. ibid. c. 7. Dam incrementa pretiorum aucupor, amiſi vſum beneficiorum. Quantas anni ſuperioris frumento animas pauperum reſeruare poſſem? Haec me magis delectarent pretia, quae non nummo aeſtimantur ſed gratia:—Tu verò non h
                        •
                     c ditis, ſed ais. De ruam horrea mea Recte deſtiues ea quibus nullus pauper onuſtus reuertitur, &amp;c. 
                  The ground of a certaine rich man brought forth plenteouſly.
And hee thought with himſelfe, What ſhall I
doe, becauſe I haue no roome to beſtow my fruits? What
ſhalt thou doe, man? Haſt thou ſo much that thou
knoweſt not what to do with thy goods? I will tell
thee what thou ſhalt doe: Giue to the poore out
of thine abundance; if thou wilt not doe ſo, yet ſell
to them at a reaſonable price. What ſhalt thou
doe? why? make the guts of the poore thy Garnors;
their bowels, thy Barnes; their empty
mawes, thy Mow-hayes; ſo ſhalt thou bee ſure
that both thy ſubſtance and thy ſoule ſhall bee ſafe.
How? no, I'le none of that. Why? what wilt
thou doe then? I know what I will doe: I will pull
downe my Barnes, and build greater. Nay, ſoft and
faire, thou mayeſt ſaue charges and labour; for, O
foole, this might ſhall they take away thy ſoule from thee.
                  
So let thine enemies periſh, O Lord, euen all theſe
who are enemies to thoſe whom thou moſt befriendeſt,
the poore and indigent: vnleſſe it rather
pleaſe thee (which wee moſt deſire) to giue them
grace to turne mercifull, that ſo thou mayeſt haue
mercy vpon them: and vnleſſe it pleaſe thee to
giue them wiſdome from aboue, to flye from the
curſe, by forſaking the curſed ſinne which procureth
it, and to buy a bleſſing at ſo cheap an hand, as
by ſelling the ſuperfluity of their Corne, hauing reſerued
ſufficient for their owne prouiſion: For,
Bleſſings ſhall be on the head of him who ſelleth it.
               
            
            
               
               THE THIRD
SERMON.
               
                  PRO. 11. 26.
                  But bleſsing ſhall be vpon the head of him who
ſelleth it.
               
               
                  I Haue almoſt beene tired on Mount
Ebal,
                  The ſecond part of the Text, wherin it is to be conſidered. the Mountaine of Curſing;
Whereunto the firſt part of my
Text neceſſarily tasked mee. I doe
therefore (after ſome pauſe) the
more willingly climbe the Mount
Gerizim, the Mountaine of bleſſing,
whereunto the ſecond part doth lead me; and glad
I am to follow, becauſe the aſcent is eaſie, and the
top excellent. The aſcent I call the Duty, which is
ſelling, than which, what more eaſie? By the top I
vnderſtand the recompence, which is no leſſe than
Bleſſing; than which, what more excellent?
               But bleſſing ſhall bee on the head of him who ſelleth
it.
               Conſider wee firſt,1 The Duty to be performed▪ Selling. the duty, which is ſelling of
Corne, oppoſite to the ſinne of with-holding it.
               
                  
                  That ſelleth.]
                  Perfringentis Metaphora à rebus fractis▪ Cartwright ad locum. The Originall word importeth breaking,
or diuiding. The meaning is, that Corne
muſt be broken from the heape, and by ſmall portions
diſtributed abroad among many, according
to the neceſſity and ability of the buyer; that they
who cannot reach a Buſhell, may haue a Pecke, or
halfe a Pecke, for their money. The like phraſes
are frequent in Scripture: Breake thy bread vnto the
hungry.—Giue a portion vnto ſeauen—As a loafe of
bread is broken and diuided among many, that euery
one may haue ſome, and not one all; ſo Corne
is to be broken from the heape, and not to bee ſold
by the heape to ingroſſers, and to ſuch as will make
a commodity by retailing it at a dearer rate, but in
ſmaller portions to bee diuided and ſubdiuided to
the poorer ſort of people who doe buy for neceſſity.
Thus to ſell (eſpecially in ſuch ſeaſons as theſe)
is a worke of charity, and ſhall not want a reward;
for it ſhall receiue a bleſſing. So that
There is a Charity ſometimes in ſelling.Doct. 3.
                  
               
               There are three principall deeds of Charity:There is a charity in ſelling, as well as in giuing.
1. Giuing, 2. Lending, 3. Selling. Giuing is the
chiefeſt and moſt noble; It is more bleſſed to giue, than
to receiue; and therein man doth moſt reſemble
God,1 Tim. 6. 17. 
                  Who giueth vs abundantly all things to enioy.
Lending is next, if it be free lending;Pſalm. 
                  A good man
is mercifull and lendeth, ſaith the Pſalmiſt. Selling is
the laſt, yet this alſo (rightly performed) wanteth
not a bleſſing. The holy Ghoſt in Scripture preſcribeth
rules for ſelling, giuing a charge, that1 Theſ. 4. 6. 
                  No
man doe circumuent or defraud another in bargaining.
                  Act. 16. 14. 
                  Lydia, a ſeller of purple, is praiſed, and ſaid alſo to
be a worſhipper of God. In the laſt Chapter of this
booke, the godly Matron is commended, not onely

(though chiefly) for her bounty in giuing,Prou. 31. 20 
                  Pro. 31.
20. She ſtretcheth forth her hands to the poore, yea, ſhee
ſpreadeth them out to the needy; but alſo for her ſelling;
Shee maketh fine wooll,
                  Verſ. 24. 
                  and ſelleth it, and deliuereth
girdles to the Merchants.
               
               Behold herein,Vſe 1. and acknowledge the gratious indulgence
and great kindeneſſe of our heauenly Father,To teach vs to acknowledge Gods goodneſſe in accepting any Seruice done at his command, though for our owne profit.
and Maſter to vs his poore children and ſeruants.
He impoſeth no hard taske vpon vs. Chriſt
may well ſay,Mat. 11. 30. 
                  My yoke is eaſie, and my burthen
light: If there bee any hardneſſe in any of his precepts,
it is mollified againe with ſome milde qualification.
Chryſoſt. ad pop. Antioch. hom. 65. Canſt thou not (ſaith a Saint) keepe virginity?
God giues thee leaue to marry: Canſt thou
not faſt? God giues thee leaue to eat: Haſt thou
a great charge, many of thine owne to be prouided
for, ſo that it is not for thine eaſe to giue? Behold,
God giueth thee leaue to ſell, yea, promiſeth a bleſſing
where thou makeſt a benefit.
               
                  Luk. 12. 33. 
                  Sell that you haue, and giue almes, ſaith our Sauiour:
Is that ſomewhat hard to ſell and giue all?
Why, then ſell ſome, and giue almes of a part, yea,
giue almes euen by ſelling ſome part of that which
you may well ſpare to your poore brethren; that
2 Cor. 8. 14. 
                  now at this time your abundance may ſupply their want,
that [at another time] their abandance may ſupply
your want, that there may be an equality. Yea, where
there is ability of giuing,God accepteth ſometimes ſelling, euen where there is ability of giuing. there God accepteth ſelling
at ſome times, ſuch times as theſe. Hee who
ſelleth to preuent a Dearth, doth a good worke, as
well as hee who giueth in the time of Dearth. A
few Buſhels ſent to the Market, and ſold indifferently
to the needy, doe pleaſe God, as well as mony
or bread giuen at the doore: by this, one or a
few are, for the time, refreſhed; by the other, many
are weekely releeued; by giuing at the doore,

many times, idle bellies, looſe lozels, lewd loyteterers
are pampered, whoſe backes had more need
to be puniſhed; but by reaſonable and ſeaſonable
ſelling, many poore painefull families are maintained,
which hauing laboured hard all the weeke,
muſt not onely pray, but faſt the Sunday, if they
caunot buy a little Corne the Satterday. So that the
way to heauen is not ſo narrow, nor the gate ſo
ſtrait, but that a courteous Farmer, with his Cartload
of Corne may enter into it, who is ready to releeue
the Countrey by charitable ſelling.Vſe 2. Behold
how God eſteemes that mercy to others,To incite thoſe who are of ability, to this duty of ſelling. which
brings a commodity to our ſelues; and ſaith, in effect,
to you that are of ability, in theſe extremities;
Thy neighbour hath need, yea, I my ſelfe, in him,
doe ſuffer want, now enrich thy ſelfe. At other
times (and ſo now too eſpecially)Prou. 19. 17. 
                  Hee that giueth
to the poore, lendeth vnto the Lord; at this time, Hee
that ſelleth vnto the poore, giueth vnto the Lord,
and the Lord will repay him with a bleſſing on the
bargaine. Doth Dauid ſay of him,Pſal. 112. 9. 2 Cor. 9. 9. 
                  Who hath diſperſed
and giuen to the poore, that his righteouſneſſe remaineth
for euer? Behold, his righteouſneſſe alſo remaineth,
and a bleſſing is layd vp for him who diſperſeth
and ſelleth to the poore. Did that bleſſed
Saint ſay truly in one ſenſe,Nemo dicat, Non habeo; Charitas de ſacculo non erogatur. Auguſtin. in Pſal. 103. 
                  Charitas de ſacculo non
erogatur, Charity is not drawne out of a Sacke: we
may as truly (in this ſenſe) affirme the contrary,
Charity is drawne out of a Sacke. When a man openeth
the Sacke and ſelleth as he ought, he dealeth
charitably. To ſell, in Latine, is,Vendere quaſi venum dare. To giue to ſale;
ſo that to ſell to him that needeth, is a kinde of gift.
The charitable ſeller ſhall haue his reward, as well
as the charitable giuer.
               
                  Not euery one who ſelleth, but hee who ſelleth charitably, hath the recompence. I ſay, The charitable ſeller: for, Not euery one
that ſelleth, nor that ſelleth at euery time, muſt expect

the bleſſing. Euen thoſe whom the people doe
curſe for not ſelling at this time, doe meane to ſell
at another time. But he who will ſo ſell as that hee
may buy a bleſſing, muſt ſell charitably. How is
that? He muſt ſell,
               
                  Fourethings required in charitable ſelling. 1. Conuenient graine, 2. For conuenient gaine,
3. In ſeaſon conuenient, and 4. Meaſure conuenient.
               
                  To ſell that which is good for quality, conuenient graine. Firſt, hee muſt ſhew charity in ſelling, in regard
of the matter; he muſt ſell that which is good
for quality. He muſt not ſell the refuſe of the wheat,
leſt inſtead of a bleſſing, hee come within compaſſe
of the curſe denounced by Amos
                  Amos 8. 6., againſt ſuch ſellers.
Some will ſell indeed, but it ſhall bee the orts
and fragments of Rats and Mice.Plerum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     , hoc homines nequeunt quod vendere donant. Faern in fab. Many will giue
that which they cannot ſell.Haec hodie porcis comedenda relinques. Horat. But many are worſe
than the Calabrian hoſt, who, if his gueſts would
not accept his profered Peares, hee would tell them
that the ſwine ſhould eat them. Many will not ſell
to their brethren but that which is almoſt too bad
to be caſt vnto the ſwine.
               
                  For conuenient gaine. Secondly, conuenient graine muſt bee ſold for
conuenient gaine, otherwiſe there is no charity, but
iniury and oppreſſion in ſelling. Gold may bee
bought too deare, and ſo may graine. Wherefore,
as Saint Iohn Baptiſt counſelled the Publicans, ſo doe
we the popular Publicans, the Farmars,Luk. 3. 13. 
                  Exact no
more than is appointed. Men ſay that light gaine makes
heauy purſes; ſome ſhall finde that their light ware
and heauy price wil make guilty conſciences, &amp; heauy
hearts at the laſt. Too many doe catch their poore
neighbour, the buyer, as, they ſay, men doe vſe to
catch the Panther, by placing the prey on a Tree in
his ſight, ſo farre aboue his reach, that hee breakes
his heart-ſtrings in leaping at it: ſo, many doe bring
into the Market good Corne, but as a bait in the

ſight of the buyer; for they pitch ſuch an high
price on it, that the poore Coater, though hee
ſtretch his purſe-ſtrings till they breake againe, is
not able to reach vnto it. And if they cannot haue
their owne price, home it muſt againe, or bee houſed
vntill the next Market; and if the price doe fall
in the meane time, they are ready to hang themſelues,
becauſe they neglected their firſt aduantage.
               Thirdly, ſelling (eſpecially in this) cannot bee
charitable,3 In conuenient ſeaſon. vnleſſe it bee alſo ſeaſonable. God
giueth euery thing food in due ſeaſon; ſo will the
godly afford their poore brethren that which muſt
feed them in the fitteſt ſeaſon. Tempeſtiuity in
doing, addeth weight and worth to euery good
deed. What is a pardon worth, that commeth after
execution? As much as the Cardinals Cap which
the Pope ſent to B. Fiſher, when the head was off
that ſhould haue worne it. Farmers will ſell (forſooth)
but not yet, not in haſte, the price is not yet
high enough for their purpoſe. They haue learn'd
the language of the Iewes in Haggaies times, and doe
ſay, by releeuing the ſpiritual Temples of the Lord,
as they did by repairing his materiall Temple.Haggai 1. 2. 
                  The
time is not yet come, the time that the Lords houſe ſhould
be built. The time is not yet come that wee ſhould
ſell; it will bee dearer a great deale, and that ere
long. What is this but to delay a bleſſing, vntill it
turne to a curſe; like the reprieuing of a good diſh
of meat till it be moulded, and full of worms? You
who deſire a bleſſing vpon your ſelling, remember
that of the Apoſtle, and take it as ſpoken to you in
this particular,
                     
                        •
                      Cor. 6. 2. 
                  Now is the acceptable time, now is
the day of ſaluation. Now is the time (you who haue
Corne to ſell) now is your time to ſell it; now that
Corne is deare, now bring it forth, furniſh the Markets,

bring downe the price; now take your time,
that you may bring a bleſſing on your ſoules.
               Laſtly, as the matter muſt be good, ſo the meaſure
muſt be iuſt;4 Conuenient meaſure. there muſt bee a conueniency as
well in regard of quantity as of quality, otherwiſe,
charity and a bleſſing will be abſent from your ſelling.
Prou. 11. 1. 
                  Falſe ballances are abhomination vnto the Lord;
and are not falſe Buſhels and falſe Peckes alſo?
Leuit. 19. 36 Deut. 25. 15. Ezech. 45. 10. 
                  Iuſt Ballances, iuſt weights, a iust Ephah, and a iuſt
Hin ſhalt thou haue.
                  Amos 8. 
                  To make the Ephah ſmall, and the
Shekel great, and to ſell the refuſe of the Corne: bad
ware, and as bad meaſure, this is not to ſell vnto
the poore, but to ſell the poore, or to buy them
for ſo baſe a price as a paire of ſhooes, ſaith the
Prophet. Such Merchants are ſome of our mizars,
who bring good graine and great meaſure to the
Market, onely to fetch vp the price, and doe ſell
worſe Corne and leſſe meaſure to their poore
neighbours at home at the ſame price, ſwearing
that they ſold it for ſo much at the Market, and ſo
by a mentall reſeruation, reſerue their ſoules (without
repentance) for the Diuell. What can this bee,
but a manifeſt breach of that ſtrict iniunction,
Deut. 25. 13, 14. 
                  Thou ſhalt not haue in thy bagge diuers waights, thou
ſhalt not haue in thine houſe diuers meaſures, a great and
a ſmall;
                  Verſ. 16. and marke what followes, and tremble all
yee that practiſe ſuch craft, All that doe ſuch things,
and all that doe vnrighteouſly, are an abhomination to
the Lord. And how can abhominable ſelling expect
a bleſſing? It is the charitable ſeller, for whoſe
head this Crowne is prepared, as a reward, not of
merit, but of mercy; which that it may the more
feruently affect vs, let it be a little more punctually
conſidered by vs,
Bleſſing ſhall bee on the head of him who ſelleth
it.2da, 2de.
                  
               
               
                  
Here it is obſeruable,Obſeruat. that the reward promiſed, is
larger and more emphatically laid downe,The reward more emphatically layd downe, than the iudgment threatned. than the
puniſhment threatned. For whereas the Antitheſis
requires that it ſhould be ſaid, The people ſhall bleſſe
him, as it was of the cōtrary, The people ſhal curſe him,
it is not ſo ſaid, but, Bleſſing ſhal be on his head, which
is more emphaticall. For hereby it is ſignified, that
God taketh on him to be the beſtower of the bleſſing,
he will not entruſt the multitude therewith, he
will doe it himſelfe to preuent failing. In naming
the head, (the ſublimeſt and nobleſt part of the
whole body) he intimateth that God, who is the
fountaine of bleſſedneſſe, will ſtreame downe bleſſings
vpon him plentifully and comfortably. That
which is powred downe vpon the head, muſt needs
proceed from ſomething that is aboue the head.
Now there is none higher than the head of man,
that can conferre a bleſſing on man, but God alone.
Hence therefore it muſt needs follow,Doct. 4. that
God will crowne with bleſſings that man who charitably
ſelleth his Corne in times of extremity,God wilbleſſe him who ſelleth charitably in time of extremity. thereby
to mitigate or abate the Dearth.
               
               Theſe are two ſinnes eſpecially reigning among
the poorer ſort of people;Two ſinnes of the poore. 1. Murmuring, and 2. Vnthankfulneſſe:
If they want, and be not preſently ſatisfied,1 Murmuring
they murmure againſt God and man;2 Vnthankfulneſſe. they
cry out on the hardneſſe of the times and of mens
hearts. This Dauid, long ſithence, obſerued in ſome
of that kinde;Pſal. 59. 15. 
                  They wander vp and downe for meat,
and grudge if they be not ſatisfied. And yet being ſatiſfied,
commonly they are vnthankefull both to God
and man. They haue mouthes full of curſing againſt
them who with-hold Corne; but not a breath of
bleſſing (too many of them) for thoſe who releeue

them, either by giuing, lending, or ſelling. This
makes mens hearts to bee harder than they would
be; and this cauſeth God to puniſh ſuch murmuring,
ſuch vnthankfulneſſe, by encreaſing their
wants,Neither of theſe ſhould diſcourage vs from charitable actions. and remouing the ſupplies. But let neither
of theſe diſcourage good Chriſtians from doing
their duties; let no man bee diſheartned from charitable
beneficence by the peoples vnthankfulneſſe:
For though man be vngratefull,For though men bee vngratefull, yet God is not forgetfull. yet God is not forgetfull.
Good men in doing good, doe looke vp
chiefly to the fountaine of goodneſſe, to God and
his glory. Be ye aſſured therefore, that though men
doe neglect their duty, yet God can as ſoone forget
himſelfe as his mercy. If the people, who are ready
to curſe when they want, be not as ready to bleſſe
when their wants are ſupplied, yet God, who hath
powred charity into your hearts, will powre down
bleſſings vpon your heads, and ſo crowne in you his
owne gifts.
               I muſt reſerue ſome time for Application,Application. and ſo
much the more, becauſe my Text (rightly applied)
ſurroundeth the whole Temple, and beſpeaketh all
Auditors here preſent, of whatſoeuer condition, euen
from the Chancell to the Church-doore, as well
for application as attention.
               And becauſe Salomon ſaith, Bleſſing ſhall be vpon
                  the head,
                  1 To the Magiſtrates, exhorting them to carefulnes in doing their duties in this behalfe, according to his Maieſties orders. let me firſt beginne with the head of this
aſſembly, and prepare them to receiue the bleſſing,
which afterward (like Aarons ointment) may from
the head diſtill vnto the beard, and thence runne
downe to the hem of the garment.
               To you (right Worſhipfull) doth Salomon ſpeake
in this Proclamation, as Proclamations are firſt addreſſed
to the chiefe Officers, that by them they
may be publiſhed to the People. If you be failing in
doing your duties, if you diſcharge not that truſt

which God hath impoſed and his annointed hath
repoſed on you, how will you anſwer it? how will
you eſcape the curſe of God and man. But (praiſed be
God) the Country doth witneſſe, and we thankfully
acknowledge, that hitherto (ſome of you eſpecially)
haue not beene failing. Proceed in the name
of God; all the praiſe and recompence is paid vnto
perſeuerance: feare not, faint not, be reſolute, be
couragious; you haue God, the King, the Cleargie,
the Country on your ſides: onely a few ſcarabees,
whoſe element is dongue, may aſſay to ſcare you
from your commendable courſes. But let not their
buzzing out-braue your worthy proceedings: let
not the murmurings nor reproaches of a few, worthier
to be puniſhed then regarded, daunt you in
the ſeruice of God and your Country. I haue heard
ſtrange language from ſome of their lips; The Markets
are worſe furniſhed, and the price of Corne more riſen
ſince the Iustices haue beene ſo industrious. Strange
inferences! iuſt like Teuterton Steeple the cauſe of
Goodwin ſands. As if Iudges were the cauſe of ſo
many fellonies, as Phyſitians (in ſome places) are of
ſo many funerals, and Attornies of ſo many Lawſutes.
Theſe are but bubbles blowne vp by malice
or couetouſneſſe; let them not be Lyons to ſtop you
from going on couragiouſly in the way of Iuſtice.
Though the people do ſometimes curſe where they
ſhould bleſſe, yet God will ſurely bleſſe, where he
findeth obedience. As bleſſing ſhall be on the head
of them who ſell their Corne willingly, ſo ſhall it
be on your heads, who cauſe them, or compell them
to ſell, who are vnwilling. The bleſſing that might
haue beene on their heads, if they had ſold willingly,
ſhall bee taken from theirs,And to draw on the people by their example. and placed on your
heads, for enforcing them to doe their duty. And
doubtleſſe, this bleſſing ſhal be doubled, if you draw

them on by example, as well as by authority. If
bleſſing ſhall be on the head of the ſeller, how many
bleſſings ſhall bee on the bountifull giuer and releeuer
of the poore? If it be more bleſſed to giue than
to receiue, then, doubtleſſe, it is more bleſſed to giue
than to ſell. Let me incite you (Worthies) to an holy
ambition, a godly enuy, or (to auoyd the odiouſneſſe
of the terme, ſtile it rather) zeale. Diſdaine,
diſdaine that your Tenants ſhould carry away from
your heads, ſuch a Crowne by ſelling, when you may
anticipate the bleſſing by bountifull giuing. Or let
thoſe Earth-wormes be ſo baſe, that they will not
buy heauen by ſelling, be ye more generous (Noble
Bereans) buy it you by giuing.O quae ſtultitia eſt! Deus emit ſanguine ſeruos, Mercari paruo nos piget aere Deum. 
                  Chriſt was contented
to be ſold himſelfe at a vile price, that he might buy
vs at ſo deare a price as his owne blood. How can
we call our ſelues Chriſtians, if wee will not buy
Christ for a little ſiluer, or a morſell of bread? Hoſpitality
at all times commendable, in theſe hard times
is Royall. Learne of Noble Nehemias, to make your
houſes Hoſpitals for the poore. Away with that
mock-chimney, or rather poyſon of Hoſpitality, entertaining
of Nimrods, Eſaus, Iſmaels, and thoſe deuouring
Dromedaries, their followers. If euer, now,
now follow your Sauiours counſell of inuiting and
entertaining your poore neighbours at your tables;
if not at your tables, yet in your houſes; if
not in your houſes, yet at your doores; or if you will
not haue them come to your owne houſes, yet ſend
ſometimes to ſee how they are prouided at their
owne. Your Ouer-ſeers for the poore, in many Pariſhes,
are poore Ouer-ſeers: It is a worthy worke
for a Iuſtice of Peace, in his Pariſh, to ouer-ſee them,
and if need be, to be a Deacon in miniſtring and diſtributing
to the neceſſities of the brethren. Chriſt
hath deſcended to baſer ſeruices for vs. If any ſay, I

talke of coſt and charges; I will ſoone ſhew how
that may be ſaued, at leaſt quitted. Stop ſomewhat
of the ſtreame in your Butteries and Sellars, and open
it rather at your doores. Reſcue your Wine and
your Beere from the tyranny of Rorers, and turne it
into bread for the neceſſary releefe of your hungry
neighbours. Plucke your drinke from the throats of
them that waſte it, that you may the better beſtow
your morſels on thoſe who want it. How many a
hungry family might feaſt it a week, on the healths
that are waſted in ſome Gentlemens houſes in a
night?
               One word more,Dehortation from withholding Iuſtice, &amp; from ſelling it. I pray you, at parting: you haue
myſticall Corne, as well as materiall. Iuſtice and Equity
is your Corne; if you with-hold this, the people
will curſe you, and God will adde the weight of
a woe to their curſes. Onely, this Corne of Iuſtice is
not for the Market; it muſt not be ſold, take heed
of that, it muſt be equally diuided, and diſtributed
freely. Iuſtice muſt not be ſold by the basket, as Corn
is by the Buſhell. Though in Cities, commonly,
Merchants be Iuſtices, yet neither in City nor Country
muſt Iuſtices be merchants, eſpecially of Iuſtice.
The ſellers of this kinde of Corne, are liable to a
curſe, equall with the with-holders of the other.
Bleſſing ſhall be on the head of them who vprightly
doe adminiſter it, and freely doe diſtribute it.
               I ſee here are Miniſters preſent,2 To Miniſters. To be careful and faithfull in diſtributing ſpirituall Corne for the bread of life. as well as Magiſtrates,
and ſhall I diſmiſſe my brethren without a
bleſſing? Were this a Viſitation (as in ſome kinde
it is) here were a Text for a Concio ad clerum, Hee
that with-holdeth corne, the people ſhall curſe him. As
for materiall Corne, our neighbours will exempt vs
from the curſe by keeping our Corne from vs, not
allowing vs (by their wil
                     •
                  ) ſufficient to ſerue our
owne turnes, much leſſe to be ſellers. But (bleſſed

and beloued Brethren) let vs remember that we are
Gods Husbandmen,Hieronym. Hugo Cardinal. et aly. and Ioſephs (as I may ſay) for
ſpirituall Corne: ſome of the ancients doe take this
Text in a myſticall ſenſe, and by Corne doe here vnderſtand
the Preaching of the Goſpell. O let vs not
be hiders and with-holders, but ſtewards and dſpoſers
of that graine whereof is made the bread of
life. Neuer had wee more need to be bountifull in
breaking it to the People, then in theſe dangerous
dayes: ſee we not how the ſeeds-men of ſathan, the
Diuels farmers and Proctors, Ieſuites and ſecret Sectaries
doe beſtirre themſelues? They are not ſparing
in threſhing out their tares: they ſell, yea, they
giue abroad their Romiſh graine, they impoſe it on
the people, and doe preſſe them to take it: Shall we
be with-holders and hiders of Gods graine, when
ſo many are ready to periſh for want of knowledg?
It may be the common people, who care not much
for this myſticall corne, will not curſe vs, though
we keepe it from them: but though they doe not,
God will; for if he be curſed who with-holds corporall
bread, how ſhall he eſcape who with-holds
the bread of the foule? And if bleſſing ſhall be on
his head who in a needfull time produceth his corn,
that the people may haue the food which periſheth,
how bleſſed ſhall he be who in ſo needfull times as
theſe, is bountifull in beſtowing on them the food
that endureth to euerlaſting life?
               Let mee now ſpeake to them,3 To the poore. Here is no warrant for them to reuenge their wrongs with curſings, as commonly they doe. for whom I haue
ſpoken all this while; namely, the poorer ſort of
people, who are therefore the poorer and more miſerable,
becauſe they care ſo little to repaire to the
Temple, and to heare what God ſaith vnto them.
Though the peoples curſe be the curſe of Corn-horders,
yet this is no warrant for you, O ye Poore, to
be impatient, &amp; to reuenge your wrongs with execrations

and curſes. Vengeance is mine, and I will recompence,
ſaith the Lord. When Saint Iames had bitterly
inueighed againſt couetous rich men for keeping
in their coyne, and their cloathing, and for
detaining from the labourer his hire, though hee
ſaid thatIam. 5. 
                  The ruſt of their ſiluer ſhould bee a witneſſe againſt
them, and that the moaths of their garments ſhould
at their fleſh as fire, and that the cries of the laborers entred
into the eares of the Lord; yet hee doth not counſell
the labourers to cry, much leſſe to curſe, but exhorting
them to patience, aduiſeth them to commit
their caſe to the Supreme Iudge, ſaying,Verſ. 7, 8, 9. 
                  Be patient
therefore, brethren, till the comming of the Lord.—Grudge
not one againſt another, brethren, leſt yee be condemned.
Behold the Iudge ſtandeth before the doore.
               
               
                  But rather to accuſe and curſe their owne ſins, the cauſe of that ſufferings. Malorum omnium n
                           ••
                        orum caſa eſt pecc
                           •
                        um. Nihil imputerus aſtris; ſacrilegio annus Exaruit. Symmach.
                   Rather, looke into your ſelues, accuſe your
ſelues, and if you will needs curſe, banne and abandon
your owne ſinnes, for they are the cauſes of all
your calamities. Your grudging, your murmuring,
your vnthankefulneſſe, theſe, and the like, haue cauſed
God to harden the hearts of men againſt you.
Sinne, ſin is the procurer of Dearth, and of all other
diſaſters beſides.
                     Pſal. 107. 
                  God turneth a fruitfull land into barrenneſſe:
why doth he ſo? For the wickedneſſe of the
people that dwell therein. Onely for ſinne, Bethleem,
which was an houſe of Bread, became an houſe of
famine; and that land, which abounded with milke
and honey, was abandoned to Dearth and ſcarcity.
In the Caldean languageLingua patria Caldaei nuncuparunt Sodomam et Gomorram coecitatem et ſterilitatem. Ambrſo. l. de Noe et Arca. c. 19. (ſaith bleſſed Ambroſe) Sodome
and Gomorra doe ſignifie blindneſſe and barrenneſſe.
                  Particularly that common ſinne of the vulgar, who are more carefull for materiall bread than for the word, the bread of their ſoules. Conſider with your ſelues, whether among
your other ſinnes, your affected blindneſſe be not a
cauſe of this inflicted barrenneſſe. Alas! you doe
not feele your greateſt famine: miſerable is your
ignorance: I haue knowne ſome of you that haue
not knowne whether Chriſt were a man or a woman.

How ſollicitous are you for corporall, how
careleſſe of Spiritual ſuſtenance? crying out that you
are ready to dye for want of a cruſt, and not perceiuing
that you doe daily periſh for want of knowledge?
Pſal. 59. 15. 
                  You wander vp and downe for meat, and grudge
if you be not ſatisfied; you may bee fed at home with
the food that endureth to euerlaſting life, and will
not come to receiue it. If your neighbour deny you
Wheat or Barley, you complaine, you cry, you are
ready to curſe him. But if God doe ſend a famine,
not of bread, but of (that which is much more pretious)
the word of God, or if the bread of life be withholden
from you, by thoſe who ſhould breake it vnto
you, you are nothing grieued thereat, you neuer
complaine of that want. Theſe, and the like, your peculiar
ſins haue cauſed vnto you this Dearth. Accuſe
not ſo much the couetouſnes of others, as your own
corruptions: not the conſtellations or courſes of the
heauens, but euill men, euill minds, euill manners, do
make the times euill.Mala tempora facit nobis contemptus Dei, temporum curſus non facit. Chryſologus. De orat. et 
                        •
                     eiunio ſer 43. Amend them, and theſe will
ſoone be amended. And amend, if not for loue of
God and godlineſſe, yet for feare of iudgements. Repent,
if not inuited thereunto by goodthings, yet
enforced by theſe things which you account euill,
What you haue loſt by ſin and negligence, redeeme,
recouer by true repentance. Learne you once to ſeek
firſt the kingdome of God and his righteouſnes, and
then you haue a moſt ſure word of promiſe, thatMat. 6. 33. all
theſe things ſhall be added vnto you God will turn
ſtones into bread, make the moſt ſtony-hearted
Mammoniſt relent and yeeld you bread, or he will
raine downe bread from heauen, or cauſe the Rauens
to feed you, or worke any miracle rather than
you ſhall periſh. Or if it pleaſe God to correct you
with this rod, and to exerciſe you with this affliction,
yet deſpaire not; for euen theſe publike calamities

are ſanctified to Gods children. To them, this
very ſcourge of famine (as well as other curſes) haue
their natures altered, as the bitter waters of Mara,
were turned into ſweetneſſe, and a ſtinging ſerpent
changed into a flouriſhing rod. No extremity of famine
(no more then any other temptation) can
turne the loue of God from his children; as is
cleere by that bold challenge of the Apoſtle to all
afflictions and croſſes, and to this as well as to any
of the reſt,Rom. 8. 35. 
                  Who ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt?
ſhall tribulation, or distreſſe, or perſecution, or FAMINE?
No, for in all theſe things wee are more then conquerors,
through him that loued vs.
               
               Can I quit the Mountaine of bleſſing, without bequeathing
a bleſſing? I cannot; and to whom ſhould
I bequeath it,4 Encouragement and comfort vnto ſellers. rather then vnto them on whom my
Text doth beſtow it, the Sellers? We who are the
Preachers of Peace, may, and ought ſometimes encourage
men vnto contention, ſo it be againſt ſinne,
and the courſes of ſinners. Contend you therefore
(charitable breaſts) againſt theſe hard-hearted horders:
Be you as couetous for your ſoules, as they are
for periſhing ſubſtance: While they heape vp curſes
on themſelues by with-holding, ſtriue you for
bleſſings by charitable ſelling. Now is your harueſt,
take aduantage of theſe hard times to ſtore your
ſelues with the beſt riches; ſee how God makes many
to want, that you may abound, and ſuffers others
to be miſerable, that you may be bleſſed by relieuing
them. Neglect not this opportunity, but now by
ſeaſonable ſelling buy vnto your ſelues an aſſured
bleſſing; you ſee with what a faire offer God preſents
you, to get heauen without looſing any thing
on earth. That bleſſing which others attaine vnto
by free giuing, you may get by profitable ſelling.
               Bleſſed ſhall you be in your outward eſtate, you

ſhall neuer be the poorer at the yeeres end;God ſhall crowne them with bleſſings Externall. you ſhal
finde as much coine in your purſes, as the greedy
cormorant that ſharketh after all aduantages. God
will blow on his ſtore, and boare holes in his bags,
while yours ſhall hold, and be encreaſed: A little
that the righteous hath, is more then all the riches of the
wicked. Bleſſed ſhall you be in your names and reputations;
you ſhall be praiſed and well reported
of by all men (all good men) and by the truth it
ſelfe: the precious ointment of a good name ſhall
perfume the places of your aboad: The righteous ſhall
be had in euerlasting remembrance.
               
               Bleſſed ſhall you be in the loue of the people. The
daily labourer ſhall daily pray for you; and Magiſtrates
ſhall praiſe you; godly Miniſters ſhall reioyce
&amp; take comfort in you; widdowes &amp; orphanes
in their hearty prayers ſhall ſend letters of commendation
in your behalfe vnto heauen, to the King of
heauen, their ſpeciall protector and aſſured friend
to all that doe befriend them.
               Bleſſed ſhall you be in your husbandry, and in
your fields; this yeeres ſelling ſhall be the next
yeeres ſowing and reaping: the earth which was
curſed for Adams ſinne, ſhall be bleſſed vnto you:
No worthing, no marle, no manuring ſhall procure
you more plenty of Corne, then this your ſelling of
Corne; yea, a bleſſing ſhall be on your children, and
on your poſterity after you, as is promiſed vnto the
faithfull.
               God ſhall crowne you with ſpirituall bleſſings:Internall.
                  Pſal. 4. 7. 
                  He ſhall put gladneſſe into your hearts, more then they
haue, when their corne and their wine is increaſed, and
the prices with them: you ſhall haue peace of conſcience,
ioy in the holy Ghoſt, greater treaſures then
all full coffers and barnes can afford.
               You ſhall be bleſſed in your ſickneſſe. God himſelfe

ſhal be your Phyſitian, your keeper,Pſal. 41. 3. your attender:
The Lord will ſtrengthen you vpon the bed of languiſhing,
he himſelfe will burne all your bed in your ſicknes.
You ſhall be bleſſed in that houre wherein others
are moſt diſtreſſed, in your Death; with old Simeon
you ſhall depart in peace, your eyes before-hand
ſeeing your ſaluation.
               But moſt bleſſed ſhall you be after Death,
                     
                        〈◊…〉
                     all. when
God ſhall crowne you with euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe
in heauen; then ſhall the head of bleſſings be on your
head, when you ſhall be moſt neerely and eternally
ioyned vnto your head Chriſt Ieſus, who is bleſſedneſſe
it ſelfe, Who is God bleſſed for euer. O how ioyfull
ſhall you be at that day, when others ſhall be
moſt ſorrowfull: how bleſſed, when theſe Corn-holders
ſhall be curſed▪ for when they ſhall be ſent
away with the Goates on the left hand, with that
wofull word, Depart ye curſed into euerlaſting fire, prepared
for the Diuel and his Angels: then ſhal you ſtanding
among the ſheepe on the right hand heare that
happy call, Come ye bleſſed
                  Mat. 25. 34. 
                  of my father, inherit the
Kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the
world.
               
               To which Kingdome he bring vs who hath prepared
it for vs, and to him one God in three perſons,
bleſſed for euer, be aſcribed all praiſe,
power, might, maieſty, glory, and
Dominion, now and for
euer. Amen.
               
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

