
   
      
         
            Hierothelamium. Or, The heauenly nuptialls of our blessed Sauiour vvith a pious soule. Written by Richard Flecknoe.
            Flecknoe, Richard, d. 1678?
         
         
            
               1626
            
         
         Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00927
            STC 11033
            ESTC S120850
            99856043
            99856043
            21559
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00927)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21559)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 644:06)
         
         
            
               
                  Hierothelamium. Or, The heauenly nuptialls of our blessed Sauiour vvith a pious soule. Written by Richard Flecknoe.
                  Flecknoe, Richard, d. 1678?
               
               [76] p.   
               
                  English College Press],
                  [Saint-Omer :
                  Anno M. DC. XXVI. [1626]
               
               
                  Place of publication and press from Folger Shakespeare Library catalog.
                  In verse.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
                  Signatures: A-D E⁶.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-09
            Daniel HaigSampled and proofread
         
            2003-09
            Daniel HaigText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            HIEROTHALAMIVM.
OR,
THE HEAVENLY
Nuptialls of our Blessed
Sauiour, vvith a
pious Soule.
            
            
               WRITTEN
By Richard Flecknoe.
            Omne tulit punctum, qui miscuit vtile dulci.
            —Horat.
            Anno M.DC.XXVI.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE
GREAT EXAMPLE
of Vertue and Nobility,
the Lady Katherine
Abergauenny.
            
               
                  MADAME,
THIS small
POEME, (a late
Birth of myne, and
so meanly clad, as
poore Art it selfe is euen asham'd of
it) I should scarce haue ventured to
present vnto your Ladishippe, had I

not more then hop't, that the Excellency
of the Subiect, would (in
your iust Esteeme) haue kept at
least in equall Ballance, my wants
in writing it.
            I am to professe (Madame)
so many extraordinary fauours, by
which your vnwearyed Goodnes
hath euer pleas'd (aboue my deserts)
to honour me, as I am forc't to seeke
out some more then ordinary way, to
shew my selfe in Will, theyr gratefull
debtour, in Ability I cannot
hope. Therefore Madame, remayning
still your debtour in the Principall,
all I am able, and intend to
do, is to call as many others as I can,
into the Interest of the Debt with
me; by letting all know (who from

the reading of this little VVorke,
may receaue eyther Profit or Delight,
that they owe it wholly to
your Ladyship.
            By this means perceauing, that I
was like to draw your Name, as
Party, into the Reputation of this
VVorke, I thought it would best become
my Care, as it did my Duty,
(who otherwise as you will see, haue
affected nothing in the writing it)
so to prouide, as none might receaue
offence, or harme by reading it. Of
which happines (though somewhat
rare in these Tymes, and more in
such Workes) being secure in its
Innocency, and my Well-Meaning
it, it dares with the more
Confidence, and cheerfulnes approach

vnto your Ladyshippe, to
leaue in your fayre Hands, a perpetuall
testimony of his Respect, and
Duty, whome your Great Vertues,
&amp; many Deserts haue wonne
to be
            
               Theyr euer Seruant,
&amp; Faithfull Honourer.
Rich. Flecknoe.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The First Canto.
            
               ARGVMENT.
               The Bridegroomes State,
               And grace, in setting forth,
               His Courtiers order,
               And his Mothers worth.
            
            
               
               1.
               MID-night silence, all be dumbe,
               Rise, &amp; see the Bridgroome come.
               But beware that none come neare,
               Only those, whose breasts are cleare
               From all crime, or sinne, so foule,
               That may wound, or kill the soule.
               These are Mysteries, and Rites
               To be seene by chaster Sights,
               
               To be mark't, and vnderstood
               Only by the pure, and good,
               
               Vertue, (as t'is most agreeing)
               Only's fit for Vertu's seeing.
            
            
               
               2.
               Looke, the Heauens transparent gate
               Open's wide, and out there at
               First a flight of Angells come,
               Some do play, and other some
               With the flickr'ing of theyr wings
               Keep the time, whilst others sings.
               Others strew the way with flowr's
               Gather'd fresh from Eden's bowr's
               Such for sight, &amp; curious smell,
               
               As they knew would most excell,
               All in gen'rall, Ioy do share,
               To themselues, peculiar care.
            
            
               
               3.
               Those the Ancient Prophet's were,
               who that wondrous Banner beare,
               Whose true Colour none can know:
               They appeare the lesse in show,
               'Cause about theyr heads there flyes,
               Such a cloud of Mysteries,
               
               As vnto our Sense they leaue
               Scarcely ought we may perceaue.
               But those soul's to whome ti's giuen
               For to know them all in Heauen,
               
               There are few, or none, do say,
               Make a fayrer shew then they.
            
            
               
               4.
               Those more open to our sight,
               Next in ranke, with Garments bright,
               Whose deare Pouerty doth waue,
               In that Ensigne which they haue,
               (Glose of which will neuer fade
               Though in water-colours layd,)
               Were Apostles. Those are they
               
               Who from fishing in the Sea,
               
               Came to take more soul's on Land
               
               Then the shoars haue graynes of sand,
               With no other Netts, or Hookes
               
               Then theyr Tongues, and holy Bookes.
               
            
            
               
               5.
               Those who fayre Vermilion beare
               
                  With greene Laurell, Martyrs were,
               
               Marke how through their shining red,
               Bee't in body, heart, or head,
               All the Wounds were giu'n them heere,
               Brighter then the Sunne appeere.
               
                  Soares, are chang'd to pretious Gemmes,
               
               Grieuous stripes, to glorious beames,
               Drops of bloud, to Rubyes red,
               
                  Scarres, to Crownes vpon theyr head,
               
                  Teares, to Pearles, and euery payne
               Hath it's proper Ioy, and gayne.
               
            
            
               
               6.
               Those whose Colours fayrely spred
               Shew pure white, bestreak't with red,
               Were Confessours, such as heere
               Arm'd by Vertue agaynst Feare,
               
               Durst confesse theyr Fayth, in time
               When t'was thought the greatest crime,
               
               
                  These are they, who did reduce
               Thousand soules, from sinnes abuse:
               Who Hells gates (in manner) brake
               With the force of Truth they spake:
               For the which theyr tongues now shine.
               (As you see) with light diuine.
               
            
            
               
               7.
               Those that next do take your eye,
               Are the Glory's of the sky,
               Whose white Streamers do declare,
               That they euer Virgins were.
               In whose sight, is vnderstood
               All that's perfect, rare, and good.
               
                  Look's as simple, as the Doues,
               
                  Fayre, as twenty thousand Loues,
               
                  Sweeter, then the breath of May,
               
                  Fresher, then the new borne Day,
               With theyr Vertue yet, compare
               All these parts, they nothing are.
            
            
               
               8.
               But in mid'st of these doth come
               Graces, and Perfections summe.
               Queen of Heauen, &amp; Mother deare
               To the Glorious Bridegroome there,
               
                  As the Rose, the Three-leau'd grasse
               Both for sweet, &amp; fayre, doth passe,
               
                  As the Day out-shines the Nights,
               
                  As the Moone the lesser lights:
               
                  Blessed She, so farre, and more,
               Passes all that went before.
               At whose prayse no Angells tounge
               Offer's, but it must do wrong.
            
            
               
               9.
               But now marke, how all thing cheers,
               When the Bridgroome first appeers;
               How his Face doth glory's flame.
               Know you whence theyr brightnes came?
               In cold mornings we perceaue
               Words, behind a mist to leaue:
               So ech word, which He doth say,
               Turn's into a sunne-shine ray:
               Which besid's we may presume,
               Vapours all this rare perfume,
               That doth make the gentle ayre
               Amber-sweet, as Ro-sy fayre.
            
            
               
               10.
               Purple is his marriage weed,
               Which the star's, do thicker seed
               Then a frosty winters night,
               When the Moone shines fayre &amp; bright.
               
                  Phosphorus like a pretious stone,
               
                  
                     •
                  ast before, doth keep it on,
               And behind it loosly flow's,
               Proud at euery step he go's
               For to kisse his Blessed feet;
               Whence it doth returne more sweet,
               
                  
                     •
                  hen the flowers which May conceyu's
               
                  
                     •
                  om the ayre that Zeph'rus breaths.
            
            
               
               11.
               That tongue were of God-like worth
               Which could euery grace set forth,
               And whoeuer pen them will,
               Doth deserue an Angells quill,
               
               And for Inke, were only good,
               Virgins teares, and Martyrs bloud,
               
                  Mixt with sinners contrite galls,
               For theyr much repented falls,
               Written on the Milky Way;
               
               All we write, and all we say,
               All we comprehend by sence,
               Reacheth not his Excellence.
            
            
               
               12.
               
                  Virgins hence, and close your eyes,
               Least his Loue your myndes surprise:
               Th' are to tender, He to fayre,
               
               Euery Looke will be a snare,
               For to take the waryest heart:
               
               Therfore go, in time depart.
               Y'aue inough already spyed,
               To be enuious of the Bride.
               
               Yet stay, wretch what haue I done?
               T'is his will that all should come.
               Stay, harke, He himselfe doth call,
               He hath Loue inough for all.
            
            
               
               13.
               Neyther feare her Iealousy,
               
                  She doth loue, as well as he,
               
               That you freely looke vpon him.
               Till y'ar all enamour'd on him,
               Feed your eyes, and take in flame,
               Keep your blushes, hide your shame,
               It becomes those Virgins most,
               Who the ardent'st loue, can boast
               Vnto him, who all loue merits,
               And all Virgins loue inherits,
               Feare not, ioyne you by his side,
               And with vs, go see the Bride.
            
            
               
               The Allegory.
               IN the great Procession of the Celestiall Court
is vnderstood, the Generall Ioye, of all the
Saints in Heauē, when any one on Earth is foūd
worthy to receaue theyr maker in the most B. Sacrament.
The Bridegroomes attyre is purple,
for to signify, that ioyntly with the Ioy of the receauing
him, we are to call to mynd the bitternes
of his passion. That it is adorn'd with starres, is to
shew, that the reward of sufferance on Earth, is
Glory in Heauen. Phosphorus, or the morning
starre, on his Garment before, declares, that
his presence in comming, brings light vnto our
soules, and that we should take his Grace betimes
when it first appeares, since when it is once past,
we may expect it's returne, but cannot call it
backe.
            
         
         
            
            The Second Canto.
            
               ARGVMENT.
               The Brides Attyre,
               Her meeting with her Louer,
               The guifts he giues,
               The ioy she doth discouer.
            
            
               
               1.
               THAT is she, who kneeling there,
               Seemes to haue no hope, nor feare
               Out of heauen, wherin her eyes
               Fix't (as if the cleerer skyes
               Were her mirrour) seeke to find
               Graces fitting to her mynd.
               
                  Her hands foulded ech in one,
               As if only they alone,
               (Earth not owing any such)
               Did deserue ech others touch.
               Beg of Heau'n by ardent pray'r,
               
                  Her deare louers quicke repayre.
            
            
               
               2.
               
                  She, no other Iewell wears
               Then her owne congealed tears,
               
               Which, on simple Goodnes set,
               Make a pretious Carcanet.
               Her attyre is strange to gold,
               And as farre from rich, as old,
               Which receaues no other staynes
               Then it's natiue, but remaynes
               White as is the Sheep that bears it,
               Pure as is the Soule that wears it.
               
                  Sandalls do conceale her feet,
               On her head, are Flowers sweet.
            
            
               
               3.
               
                  Beauty there (whoeuer seeks)
               Sits inthron'd vpon her cheeks,
               In a colour, red as Roses,
               Or when first the morne discloses,
               
                  White, as mountayns when it snows,
               Or the yielding downe, that grows
               On the breasts of Swans, and Doues,
               
               Spread with hayre, that when it moues
               Casts amazment on our sight,
               T'is so excellently bright.
               One may seeke the world, to find
               Such a forme, with such a mynd.
            
            
               
               4.
               Now the Bridall pompe draw's neere,
               And the noyse hath reach't her Eare,
               
               
                  Eares, her Heart informe of all,
               
                  Heart leapes vp, and Loue doth call,
               
                  Loue, sends Curiosity
               Vp in hast, vnto the Eye,
               
               
                  Eyes, looke out, and Ioy appeares:
               Poore Ioy, almost drown'd in teares,
               Running to the heart in hast,
               Sowing rumours as he past,
               Puts her in Alarum so,
               Where she is, she doth not know.
            
            
               
               5.
               Her swift eyes, that highly moue,
               Mounted on the wings of Loue,
               Or'looke all, but no where bide,
               Till theyr prey they haue espyed,
               When she enuying of her eyes,
               Straight to his imbraces flyes,
               Where she now remayns intwin'd,
               Hands in hands, as hearts are ioyn'd
               Sugred words, with sighings mixt,
               Eyes vpon his beauty fixt,
               All, her loue and ioy declare,
               For to see her Bridegroome there.
            
            
               
               6.
               Vnto some it strange may be,
               That so great a King as he,
               
               Would so farre from State descend,
               To make choyce of such a frend,
               Who, her birth can neyther boast,
               Nor (what takes our liking most)
               Doth in richer cloathing go,
               To affect the outward show.
               Beauty without wealth, some few,
               Yet can be content to view:
               But if Vertue want them eyther,
               She's prefer'd by none to neyther.
            
            
               
               7.
               Let such know, her Innocence
               
               
                  He esteemes, full competence
               For to match the highest State,
               As was euer enuyed at.
               Others (though th'are poore respects
               Which her noble mynd neglects,
               And disdaynes to Court,) yet He
               
               Of meere loue, and care (that She
               
               May not suffer disesteeme,
               In those wants, the world doth deeme
               So essentiall,) for her Honour,
               Will bestow them all vpon her.
            
            
               
               8.
               And with Riches, which is first
               After our accompt (though worst)
               He in such a sort indews her,
               As it takes, who euer views her
               With a iust esteeme, and wonder
               How much earthly wealth comes vnder.
               
                  She herselfe is all a Mine,
               
               And in euery act doth shine,
               So much true, and perfect wealth,
               As euen Auarice it's selfe,
               Such a Treasure to behould
               Would despise it's baser gould.
               
            
            
               
               9.
               This, the Priuiledge hath giuen
               To en-title her to Heauen,
               
               
                  Co-heyre with those Blessed sprit's,
               Who are drown'd with all delights
               In that Sea of ioy, &amp; blisse,
               Where no end, no measure is.
               This is True Nobility,
               
                  This is that, with cannot dy,
               
                  This is it, which doth not clayme,
               Others Worth, to guild it's shame;
               But it selfe, it's selfe commends
               
                  Vnto Honour, Fame, and Frends.
            
            
               
               10.
               Now the heauenly Quires do presse
               To bestow theyr Kisse of Peace
               
               On this happy Soule, they see
               In such heyght of Dignity.
               Now the Bridegroome doth conduct her,
               Whilst his Mother doth instruct her,
               To the Temple, as behou's,
               To confirme theyr Blessed loues,
               By the wishes wayted on
               Of all present ioyn'd in one;
               That no cause be giuen euer
               This theyr Heauenly match to seuer.
            
            
               
               The Allegory.
               IN the Prayer of the Bride, is to be noted that
we should be as carefull, in regard of Gods
greatnes, to receaue him worthily, as desirous
in respect of our owne wants, to receaue him often.
By the playnnes and simplicity of the Brides
attyre, is signifyed that innocency &amp; purity, which
is required in those soules, whome he doth please to
visit with his gratious presence. The Iewell of
her Teares, doth shew that Sorrow for our offences,
by which we should duly prepare our selues,
vnto the receauing of him. Her Sandalls the Humility,
and Flowers, the gratefull odour of our
workes, and merits.
               
               What is sayd of Beauty, both heere, or in
any other place, is meant and to be vnderstood only
of the Soule, whose inuisible Fayrenes can no ways
be rendred perceptible to sense, but by Examples
of visible Excellency. That she hath not any riches
of her owne, but what are bestow'd vpon
her by the Bridgroome, doth shew, that God
giues not Vertue to any, in respect of wealth,
but wealth oftentimes, in regard of theyr Vertue;
and that we are not further to care for them,
then it is his pleasure we should inioy them.
            
         
         
            
            The third Canto.
            
               ARGVMENT.
               The Marriage in the Church,
               The Rites expres't,
               Her Reuerence, and
               Inuiting him her guest.
            
            
               
               1.
               NOW with due becomming state
               They haue entred all, the Gate
               Of the Temple, arch't with gould,
               Rich and shining to behould,
               Rew'd with Iaspar pillars, set
               On fayre bases all of Iet,
               Marble which the sight doth vary
               On the pauement (as in Quarry)
               All one piece doth seeme to be,
               It was ioyn'd so curiously.
               With cleare lights, the Iles are taper'd
               With perfumes the Vaults are vapour'd.
            
            
               
               2.
               They, not farre had led the Bride,
               
               When before her she espyed
               
                  A fayre Picture, did of right
               Challenge euery Virgin-sight.
               
                  Twa's the Kingdome of the Blessed,
               By so liuely skill expressed,
               As it made her nigher draw,
               Thinking all was true, she saw;
               And deceau'd, with listning eare,
               To assay, if she could heare
               
                  Musicke, which the Angells made,
               Whilst they sung, and whilst they play'd.
               
            
            
               
               3.
               Twa's an Omen lik't her well,
               Wherfore she did longer dwell
               On the sight therof, and tooke
               More delight from euery looke.
               There she saw the Virgin Quires,
               
               Shining bright with Holy-fyers,
               
               Following of the Lambe along,
               Seeming for to sing a song,
               Which (a Scedule there did say)
               None in Heauen could sing but they.
               Much she had conceyu'd before,
               But, this sight did adde much more,
            
            
               
               4.
               Longer she would fayne haue stayd,
               But her stay, she was affrayd
               Might to some seeme to discouer
               A neglecting of her Louer.
               
               And (who knows) perhaps, withall
               Some her indiscreet might call,
               Who in fay'nd things could delight,
               Whilst the true on's were in sight.
               Therfore wisely she went on,
               Though resolu'd, when she was gone,
               Deepe in heart away to beare
               All imprest, she had seen there.
            
            
               
               5.
               Now they nigh the Altar come,
               And in order fill the roome,
               All prepare to be imply'd;
               
                  Virgins to attend the Bride,
               
               
                  Priests to Celebrate the Rites,
               
               
                  Angells to assist with Lights,
               
               
                  Musicke, and Perfume: ther's none
               Whose imployment is not knowne;
               Euery one doth take some care,
               And if any Idle were,
               They with wishes do assist
               
                  The Bride, the Bridgroome, and the Priest.
            
            
               
               6.
               Tw'as to all the Saints a sight,
               Did beget them much delight,
               To obserue the trembling Bride,
               
               Kneeling by her Louers side,
               How her well composed eye
               Neuer cast a looke awry,
               For to catch at Thoughts, which might
               
               Bring distraction with the sight:
               But did reu'rently regard
               All she saw, and all she heard,
               Whilst the Priest set all things forth,
               With state, equall to theyr worth.
            
            
               
               7.
               Though she wish't the time were come.
               That might ioyne them both in one,
               And (to thinke too long) had cause
               Euery little stay, or pause:
               Yet as euery Rite did passe,
               So attent, and glad she was,
               As if ech, the reason were
               Only of her comming there.
               Whē 
                  to Heau'n forKyrie eleison. help they call,
               She her voyce doth ioyne with all.
               To the like her mynd they moue
               When they glorify
                  Gloria in excelsis her Loue.
            
            
               
               8.
               When theySanctus▪
                   
                  Holy do proclayme him
               
                  She with much delightDominus Deus. doth name him.
               When theyEleuatiō. 
                  shew him vnto all,
               There is none doth lower fall,
               With more humblenes before him,
               For to reuerence, and adore him.
               When they call to myndAgnus dei. 
                  his Crosse
               
               Who can more resent his losse?
               When they do professe,Domine on sum dinus. 
                  ther's none
               
               
                  Worthy of him, She alone
               Thinks ther's none, her eyes can see
               But is worthier farre then she.
               
            
            
               
               9.
               But at last when she's inuited
               By due prayers, and Tapers lighted,
               To draw neare, and takeCommunion. 
                  her Louer,
               
               O what Ioye doth she discouer?
               
                  Teares her eyes had ouerflow'd
               
                  Sighs burst forth, and playnly shew'd,
               Though Ioy, would not let her speake▪
               
               
                  They must vent, or she must breake.
               
                  He as much Loue did expresse,
               As she Ioy, and tendernes,
               When thus solemnly they both,
               Ech to other plight theyr troth.
            
            
               
               10.
               The Brides declaration of
her Loue.
               
                  1.
                  The World shall sooner want the sunns faire light.
                  The Moone extinguisht be, and put out quite,
                  The starres in darknes leaue the heau'ns aboue.
               
               
                  2.
                  The spring shall sooner cause the dayes grow short,
                  And fading Autumne, make them longer for't,
                  Shippes, on the land shall sayle about, &amp; moue.
               
               
                  3.
                  Cartes shall be drawne the liquid waters o're,
                  Fishes i'th woods shall liue, i'th sea the boare
                  Shall sooner find his food, and where to tread.
               
               
                  4.
                  Then I shall cease to loue thee, euer deere,
                  Whether I breath the life which I haue heere,
                  Or el's am numbred with the gastly dead.
               
            
            
               
               11.
               The Bridgroomes to her.
               
                  1.
                  Nature may proue a Stepdame to the Earth,
                  Spring may refuse to giue her Flowers birth,
                  And tender Mothers hate theyr first borne child.
               
               
                  2.
                  Fayre Vertue from her Goodnes may depart,
                  And Vice may raigne without the conscience smart,
                  All loue from gentle Breasts may be exild.
               
               
                  3.
                  The Sunne may leaue the day, the Moone the night,
                  Prosperity her Ioy, and Enuy spight,
                  The auaricious may despise his Gould.
               
               
                  4.
                  But I, deare soule, can neuer change from thee,
                  Whilst Loue and Vertue which haue taken me,
                  Keep in thy heart that place which now they hould.
               
            
            
               
               12.
               Then whilst Angells sweetly sing,
               On her hand he puts a Ring;
               
               
                  Ring, which had such vertuous might,
               To expell with only sight,
               All Temptations Sinne doth breed
               
               In the thought, the word, or deed;
               
               In the mynd a luster setting
               By pure thoughts of it's begetting.
               Thus the Ceremonyes done,
               All preparing to be gone,
               
                  She her Spouse, that day her guest,
               
               Lead's vnto the Marriage feast
               
            
            
               
               The Allegory.
               BY the picture, vpon which the Bride so liberally
bestowed her eyes, at her Entrance
into the Temple, is signifyed, those good
Thoughts and Cogitations, which the holines of
such places doth often suggest vnto vs. By her withdrawing
her sight from it, assoone as she remembred
she had other more necessary things to do; is shewed
that we should neuer so dwell on the delectation of
any one good worke, as therby to neglect a greater.
               In her Deuotion and Attention during the
Celebration of the holy mysteries, we are taught,
how we are to concur with the Action and Intention
of him who Celebrates.
               By her Ring, may be vnderstood the memory of
our B. Sauiour, on which if we but often &amp; seriously
reflect, it is impossible we should be so vngratefull
to him, and trayterous to our selues, as to
betray the Fort of our Innocency (by the Intelligence
eyther of thought, word, or act) vnto
any Vice, or Imperfection.
               
            
         
         
            
            The fourth Canto.
            
               ARGVMENT.
               The Nuptiall Feast, wherin
               Is much commended,
               Her Drinke, &amp; Fare; but
               In excesse she ended.
            
            
               
               1.
               HENCE exulting Ioy, begone,
               Els thou'lt kill the Bride anone.
               She doth feed with soules delight,
               
               And, as if her Bridgroomes sight
               
                  Her, like him, did heauenly make,
               Hath forgot all food to take.
               How her eyes are fixt on his,
               Scarse belieuing her owne blisse,
               That so poore a Soule, as she
               Should be Loue, to such as he,
               And when most assur'd t'is true,
               Then, she most doth wonder new.
            
            
               
               2.
               
                  Melting snow, that hills doth crowne,
               Toucht with sunshine, runs not downe
               Swifter, nor more currents seeks
               Then the teares vpon her cheeks.
               
               Much I feare they'l ne're haue done!
               Now to see his face, they runne
               Trickling downe, and now as fast
               When she finds, that they haue cast
               Such a mist her eyes before,
               She can scarcely see him more:
               So betwixt her Ioyes and Feares,
               
               
                  Teares, are only cause of Teares.
               
            
            
               
               3.
               In the mid'st of all our noyse
               Singing loude theyr Nuptiall Ioyes,
               
               
                  She her silence breaks no more,
               Then the fishe when seas do roare,
               Least perhaps to gayne discourse,
               
                  She, herselfe doth wisely force
               For to lend a word to lone
               
               Of a thousand words for one:
               But the whilst, as they are payd,
               
                  Blessed Heauen, how she's affrayd
               Least ech one should be the last,
               So too soone her gayne be past.
            
            
               
               4.
               Why is all this Musicke heere?
               See, it neuer takes her eare.
               
                  Angells, though you play, and sing
               Till the Ayre with Eccho ring,
               Though t'is sweet, and rare, yet she
               Is so farre from thanking yee,
               As sh' admirs how you can do
               Any thing, but hearken to
               
                  Those his hony-flowing Words
               Which into her Eare affoards
               
                  Sounds more sweet, more pleasing farre,
               Then your Quiers, or Consorts are.
            
            
               
               5.
               Why d'ye lauish, and consume
               So much rich, and choyce perfume?
               
               She alone might well suffice,
               For to sweeten all the skyes,
               With those sighs, which she doth spend
               Without measure, without end.
               
                  Griefe, before I euer knew
               
                  Ioy, could weepe as well as you,
               
                  Swoune, and suffer, all speach bar'd,
               But such sigh's I neuer heard
               Soft, I see therin doth lye
               Yet some deeper mystery.
            
            
               
               6.
               
                  Marke her, she doth vse to frame
               Of her breath, her Louers Name,
               Tasting which, her mouth receaues
               All the gust, that hony leaues.
               Oh Repast deuine, and rare!
               By that Food we nourisht' are
               Which we take, and in receaue;
               
                  She, by that, which she doth leaue:
               
               Yet th' effect is far more strange,
               Foode in vs to Earth doth change,
               
                  Hers, in Him, to Heauen; so breath
               Wisely hath beguiled death.
            
            
               
               7.
               But some Epicure will say,
               
                  She consumes herselfe this way,
               Not supplying Natures needs,
               But doth languish as she feeds.
               
               Peace, thou Earthly mynd, thy food
               Changeth first to flesh and bloud,
               
               
                  Sicknes doth thereon awayt,
               That brings death, her dyet straight
               Turnes to life, and better spirit,
               
               Fills her full with glorious Merit,
               
               Doth her soule at last commend
               Vnto Life, can neuer end.
            
            
               
               8.
               Now, when she doth list to drinke,
               
               Oh what humane thought can thinke
               On the sweetnes, which she tasts,
               Whilst her draught delicious lasts!
               Yet, deare soule, how ere you fayne,
               I do see, it brings you payne,
               Whilst you drinke out of a wound,
               
               Not alone, for Loue you sound,
               
               Bee't in feet, in hands, or side,
               
               In conceipt it opens wide,
               Euen as deepe a wound in you,
               
               As those pretious ones you view.
            
            
               
               9.
               Drinke not, thirsty soule, so deepe,
               Temp'rance bids a measure keepe.
               Scandall doth arise from such,
               Who vnwary, drinke too much.
               
                  She all counsayle doth despise,
               Stops her Eares, and firmes her Eyes,
               
               Euery daught begets a thirst,
               Hoat and fiercer then the first.
               O how great the daunger is,
               Least some harme. do follow this!
               And now see, She leanes her head
               
               In her Louers armes, as dead.
            
            
               
               10.
               
                  Angells beare her forth, I feare
               Much the cause; she's stifled here:
               
               Ther's no doubt her health's impayre
               May be help't with better ayre.
               
               But himselfe alone sustaynes
               All the burthen, all the paynes,
               Thinking nothing throughly done,
               'Lesse his Blessed selfe be one,
               Rubbe her Temples, bow her head
               
               Beare her to the Mariage Bed:
               
               Feare not, she'le reuiue anone,
               When her Extasy is gone.
            
            
               
               The Allegory.
               IN all this Feast is nothing els to be vnderstood,
then only the tender and pious affections
which are incited, and stired vp, in high Contemplatiue
Soules, by the receauing of the
B. Sacrament, as namely their Deuout
Colloquies, seasoned in tears, &amp; mixt with
sighes, to giue the more delicate tast &amp; relish to
theyr high-fed Soules, and also the strict
watch they keep on theyr Attentions, to barre
the entrance of any thoughts may bring distraction
with them. By her swoning, is signifyed
the sweet force of the Diuine Loue, which (as if
it had changed dartes with Death) doth oftentimes
leaue the Bodies vnto the Graue, by enticing
from them the Soules, vnto the loyes of
Heauen. Lastly, by the Angells Care, and
Bridgroomes diligence, in bearing of her forth
out of that close Chamber where she was (the
world) into Heauen, her Bridall Chamber, is
shewen, that God is neuer wanting to assist
them at theyr Deaths, whose Vertues whilst
they liue on Earth, do labour a sure and perfect
Friendship, betwixt them and Heauen.
               
            
         
         
            
            The fifth Canto.
            
               ARGVMENT.
               The Chamber of the Bride,
               Her' maze, it's stayres.
               Theyr Ioy, the rest, the
               Angells song declares.
            
            
               
               1.
               NOW, they vp a wondrous stayre,
               
               Farre aboue all noysome ayre,
               T'wards her chamber beare the Bride,
               
               When not able to abide
               Such a brightnesse, such a height,
               Leaden Death, with his owne weight,
               
               Fell to ground, from of her eyes,
               In▪ a graue, where now he lyes.
               Then they straight vnclos'd, and gaz'd
               At her being so amaz'd,
               As tw'as long ere she could giue
               
                  Her selfe credit, she did liue.
            
            
               
               2.
               And who could refuse to wonder,
               For to see Earth lye vnder
               Such vnmeasur'd way below
               As t'was almost lost to shew.
               For to see the waters stand
               Like a wall about the Land,
               And without so surely fenc't
               With the moyster ayre condens't,
               For to see the humble fyer
               
               Neyther burne, nor mount vp higher!
               None of these but might amaze
               One who far more bouldnes ha's.
            
            
               
               3.
               Yet this wonder did not last,
               For her eye aside she cast
               And in it, lost all her feare,
               When she saw her Bridgroome there.
               That which made her wonder cease,
               May perhaps make ours increase.
               She of all strange things that were
               By one glaunce on him, more cleere
               Did the hidden Causes see,
               Then within a Mirrour, we
               Our owne faces, when we looke,
               Studying most that flat'ring booke.
            
            
               
               4.
               So all Wonder turn'd to Loue,
               
               
                  Loue in her, a Heauen did proue,
               
                  Heauen, as they did go, was there,
               
                  Heauen they came to eu'ry where.
               
                  Heauen within her, and without,
               
                  Heauen aboue, and round about:
               
                  Heauen is in her Eyes, and Eares,
               
               Nothing now but Heauen appeares,
               In ech sense, in euery part,
               In her mouth, her louing heart,
               
               And these Heauens are all, alone
               In her Bridgroome, ioyn'd in one.
            
            
               
               5.
               She without all payne doth goe,
               (That vn'wares she left below
               On the vnder floore of clay,
               
               Whilst in deadly trance she lay,
               For some faynt, and worldly mind
               Dares not higher go, to find.)
               And they now arriued are
               On the highest Christall stayre,
               Ioyning to a porche of gould,
               (Eyes did ne're the like behould)
               That directly in doth guide
               To the Chamber of the Bride.
               
            
            
               
               6.
               See▪ the dores do open stand,
               And the Bridgroome by the hand▪
               
               (Whilst the Saints his prayses sing)
               His fayre crowned Spouse leads in,
               All the Soules that heauen had euer,
               There stand ready to receaue her,
               For her glory, euery one
               Far more glad then for theyr owne:
               Yet ther's none hath more exprest,
               Of a glad, and ioyfull breast,
               Nor of Loue more pledges giuen,
               Then the sacred Queene of Heauen.
               
            
            
               
               7.
               Those whose Ioyes, are at the height,
               Thinke th'are happyer in her sight,
               
               And who know th'are loued most,
               Such a Riuall soonest boast,
               They so hast her in to beare,
               As our Night begins, I feare,
               And those Glory's which we see
               Too to soone, will vanish't be.
               
                  Darknesse winnes vpon the skies,
               
               Now they lessen in our eyes,
               To a Starre, which was a Sunne,
               
               Now a sparke, and now th'are gone,
            
            
               
               8.
               What a darke, and vgly sight,
               After so much Glorious Light,
               
               This blacke Clod of Earth Appeares.
               But, what Musicke strikes our Eares?
               Sure, t'is that the Angells make,
               For the Bride, and Bridgroomes sake:
               Which whilst Eccho brings to ground,
               
                  Trauayle doth enrich the sound.
               Let vs hearken what they say,
               Somewhat may be learn't this way▪
               
               
                  Hearing that, we cannot see
               
               Is of Ioy the next degree.
            
         
         
            
            HIEROTHALAMIVM.
            
               I.
               
                  SING Io Hymen, chastest Hymen all,
               
               And with loude voyce the Brides great Ioyes repeate,
               So Eccho tost, as not a word let fall.
               May make them seem lesse soūding then th'are great.
               But in this heyght th'are at,
               May they for euer be▪
               
               That euen the Saints, when as they see,
               And haue her Blessings knowne,
               May thinke ther's somwhat wāting of theyr owne.
               Yet Ioy with her, and wish her more beside,
               And ioyne with vs, in hon'ring of the Bride.
               
            
            
               
               II.
               Now world farwell, she thinks on thee no more,
               Or if she doth, it is but to compare
               With much disdayne, thy wants, with her great store.
               
               
                  Thy course
                     •
                   feeding, with her daynty fare,
               
                  Thy mynds perpetuall care,
               With her Soules lasting peace,
               
               Thy Barrennes, with her Increase;
               
               Thy want of sense to choose
               Such things, for wealth, which her doth them refuse
               Make only rich; Thy thousand woes beside,
               With the perpetuall blessings of the Bride.
               
            
            
               
               III.
               You need not boast your Issue, nor be glad,
               T'is but a wreched shift, that Nature finds
               For to repayre the Spoyles, that Death hath made,
               The Sower of all Cares in Parēts mynds,
               Which she who well declines,
               Doth soone find, what a blest
               And happy change sh'as made, by rest
               She feels with in her soule,
               
               When no vnquiet thought, doth there controule,
               Or vrge those Cares, which Ease doth not abide,
               Happy are such, thrice happy is the Bride.
               
            
            
               
               IIII.
               It is theyr Ioy, who grieue that they are old,
               
               To haue some Issue they may leaue behind,
               And in theyr sight, theyr passed youths behold,
               Ioy, is but Ease of Griefe in humane kind.
               Who want's doth seeke to find,
               Who hunger's, food doth loue:
               But happy soules, who are aboue
               The need, and lacke of these!
               
                  Heere, are delights which neuer know decrease,
               
                  Heere, youth is lasting, life doth euer bide,
               
                  Ioy wayt's on it, They all, vpon the Bride.
               
            
            
               
               V.
               No Ielou'sy her quiet heart molest's,
               No feare, of too vntimely losse of life,
               
               No heauy care, that presseth maryed breasts,
               
               No cause of grudging, or contentious strife
               
               The woe of man, &amp; wife.
               
               No Lothing, but the same
               
                  Fyer, which now burnes with holy flame,
               To light theyr Loues to day,
               Will euer last, &amp; neuer can decay;
               For he hath chose, who cānot chāge abide
               To haue her euer for his Spouse and Bride.
            
            
               
               The Allegory.
or Conclusion.
               
                  TOVCHING the Allegory in this
last Canto, little is to be sayd. The
Stayres by which the Bride was borne vp vnto
her Bridall Chamber, do allude vnto the
Elements and Planets, which (according to
the Astrologers) do fill vp by their orderly distances,
the space betwixt Heauen and Earth,
wherin I make the Caeum Cristallinum (following
the Generall opinion) the highest steppe of
this stayre, and next adioyning to the Caelum
Empyreum, or habitation of the Blessed.
               
               ¶It may to some perhaps, seeme some want
of good manners in Art▪ to bring the Bride only to
the Entrance of her Bridall Chamber, and there
abruptly to leaue her &amp; follow her no further: But
if the Paynter Timant, was thought worthy of
prayse, for paynting Agamemnon (present
when his daughter Iphigenia was to be sacrificed,)
with his face couered, signifying that his
Griefe was greater, then could be seene in his

countenance; I see no reason, why I should be blamed,
for passing those Ioyes in silence, which are
greater then can be comprehended by humayne
sense, or Imagination. Besides, that breuity which
I haue studyed from the beginning, loath now to
loose it's Palme at the later end, did hasten me
away from more prolixity, by affoarding me this
reason: That it was euery way auaylable vnto this
worke, and me; that those who were delighted
with it, should be sory it is so short, and those
who were not, should be glad it is no longer.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
            
            
         
      
   

