
   
      
         
            Sicelides a piscatory, as it hath beene acted in Kings Colledge, in Cambridge.
            Fletcher, Phineas, 1582-1650.
         
         
            
               1631
            
         
         Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00979
            STC 11083
            ESTC S102382
            99838167
            99838167
            2530
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00979)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2530)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 836:18)
         
         
            
               
                  Sicelides a piscatory, as it hath beene acted in Kings Colledge, in Cambridge.
                  Fletcher, Phineas, 1582-1650.
               
               [84] p.   
               
                  Printed by I[ohn] N[orton] for VVilliam Sheares, and are to be sold at his shoppe, at the great south doore of St. Pauls Church,
                  London :
                  1631.
               
               
                  By Phineas Fletcher.
                  Partly in verse.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A²  B-L⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2002-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-04
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-05
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            SICELIDES A PISCATORY,
            
               As it hath beene Acted in Kings Colledge, in Cambridge.
            
               LONDON, Printed by I. N. for VVilliam Sheares, and are to be sold at his shoppe, at the great South doore of St. Pauls Church. 1631.
         
         
            
            
            Dramatis Personae.
            
               
                  Perindus, A Fisher, sonne to Tyrinthus, in loue with Gaucilla.
               
               
                  Armillus, A Shepheard, and acquainted with Peri
                        •
                     dus.
               
               
                  Thalander, A Fisher, sonne to Glaucus, in loue with Olinda, disguised and called Atyches.
               
               
                  Alcippus, A Fisher.
               
                  Pas, A Fisher, in loue with Cosma.
               
               
                  Fredocaldo, An old Fisher, in loue with Cosma.
               
               
                  Olinda, Sister to Perindus.
               
               
                  Glaucilla, Sister to Thalander.
               
               
                  Cosma, A light Nymph of Messena.
               
               
                  Cancrone, Two foolish Fishers, seruants to old Tyrinthus.
               
               
                  Scrocca, Two foolish Fishers, seruants to old Tyrinthus.
               
               
                  Tyrinthus, Father to Perindus and Olinda.
               
               
                  Conchylio, Cosmaes page.
               
                  Rymbombo, Cyclops.
               
               
                  Dicaus. Neptunes chiefe Priest.
               
                  Nomicus, An inferior Priest.
               
                  Glaucus, Muti.
               
               
                  Circe, Muti.
               
               
                  Gryphus, Tyrinthus his man.
               
                  Cuma, Perindus his boy.
               Executioners.
               
                  Chorus, of Priests.
               
                  Chorus, of Fishers.
            
         
         
            
            PROLOGVS CHAMVS.
            BEgin, thou royall Muse, Enuie nere vses,
            
               
                  •
               o dwell in gentle Courts, or sacred Muses:
            To begge of them that common courtesie
            Must grant; were to condemne both them, and thee:
            Thy Came assures thee, they will all agree,
            Gently to beare their Actors infancy;
            Infants oft please; the choycest Poet song,
            Breeds lesse delight then th' infants prattling tongue.
            Then let me here intreate your minds to see,
            In this our England, fruitfull Sicely,
            
            Their two twinne Iles; so like in soyle and frame,
            That as two twinnes they'r but another same.
            But this they begge, which you may graunt with ease:
            That all these paines to pleasure you, may please.
         
      
      
         
            
            SICELIDES,
            
               Act. 1.
               
                  Scen. 1.
                  
                     Enter PERINDVS, ARMILLVS, CVMA.
                  
                     Perindus.
                     
                        
                           CVma! beare home our spoyles, and conquering weapons,
                     And trusse them on a wreath as our iust trophie:
                     And when Can
                              •
                           rone returnes, returne to mee.
Exit Cuma
                     
                     Thus: if but thus: yet thus my state is better,
                     While lesser cares do laugh aud mocke the greater;
                     This change is best when changing I frequent,
                     Euen now that moyst, now this drie element,
                     When with this scepter, setting on the Land,
                     The scalie footlesse people I command:
                     When riding on my wooden horse, I see
                     The Earth that neuer mooues, remooue from me.
                     A
                           •
                        d why my friend doth not this guise beseeme me?
                     In this I
                           •
                         am not wretchlesse as you deeme me
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Not that I censure, but demande the cause,
                     Why being borne, and bred, in shepheards lawes;
                     You haue our Hills, and Downes, and Gro
                           •
                        es forsaken,
                     And to these Sands, and Waues your selfe betaken.
                  
                  
                     
                     Per
                     Sh
                           •
                        pheard or fisher, I am still the same,
                     I am a sea guest not for gaine, but game.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     A gamesome life? thus with vnarmed armes
                     To fight gainst windes, and winters sharpe alarmes,
                     And paddle in chill Neptuns Icie lappe?
                     But if in fishing any plesaure be,
                     In Shepheards life there is much more say we.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Yet Fishers life with me doth most consort,
                     This sporting serues to moralize my sport:
                     Viewing the stormes, and troublesome waues; I finde
                     Some thing in nature rest-lesse as my minde:
                     Each captiue fish tels met that in deaths snare,
                     My heart is not the onely prisoner.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Walke along the shore—
                     Oft there he walkes
                     Oft there with me or with the waues hee talkes.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     There in the tide I see fleete fortunes changing,
                     And state of man, weake state: that's neuer standing:
                     But rises still, or fals all as the maine,
                     That ebs to flow, or flowes to ebbe againe.
                     Yet fortune I accuse thee not for raging,
                     Let others plaine, I neuer felt the changing,
                     Bud wast thou at the first, and so art still,
                     Before I knew what's good I knew the ill:
                     And since of all my goods thou first bereau'st me,
                     I neere expected good, thou neere deceiud'st me;
                     Therefore although Oracle from whence
                     I late ariu'd, would feede vaine confidence;
                     Yet since so sure assurance thou doest giue mee,
                     Still of the two fortune I must beleeue thee.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Vaine feare when th' Oracle doth promise good;
                     The heauens decrees by chance weere neere withstood.
                     You feare without a cause, oft cause-lesse fright,
                     Is th' onely cause that makes that on vs light
                     Which most wee feare, euer a iealous eye
                     Makes enemies by fearing emnity.
                  
                  
                     
                     Per.
                     What fearefull tempest doe the waues foretell,
                     When seas without a storme to mountaynes swell.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Ill is inuited when it is suspected
                     And griefe already come where he's expected.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     The greatest euills oft are where thee shew not.
                     I feare the more, because my feare I know not.
                     Musicke! how sad it sounds; my damped heart
                     Tells me in these sad straines I beare a part:
                     I wrong thee fate, or else thou now doest straine thee
                     Which some vnused weleomet' entertaine me.
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 2.
                  
                     Enter Dicaeus Neptunes Priest following Olinda, led by two Nymphes Cosma and Glaucilla, before and after a Chorus of Fishers and Priests singing.
                  
                  
                     Song.
                     Go go thy countries ioy and iewell,
                     The seas and rockes were euer cruell;
                     Men then may pitty thee in vaine,
                     But not helpe nor ease thy payne.
                     Take then these tnares they la
                           •
                        est due,
                     For euer now alasse adiew.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     
                        Glaucus; to thee I frendlesse maide,
                     In these last gifts my vowes haue payd:
                     These once Olindas, now are thine,
                     This net, and hooke, this rod, and line:
                     Thou knowst, why here my sports I giue thee,
                     Hence came my ioyes, and here they leaue me.
                  
                  
                     Gla.
                     
                        Olinda, if that smiles were proofes of sorrow,
                     Sure I should thinke thee full of woe, and sadnesse,
                     but in so heaped griefe, when euery eye
                     
                        Yeilds tribute to so great a misery.
                     Thou only smilst, why euery teare thou seest, is paid to thee—
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     The lesse I need to pay:
                     
                        Gladucilla I cannot mourne, when I am married.
                  
                  
                     Gla.
                     Married? now heauen defend me, if this be marriage
                           •
                        
                     
                     So to be gript in pawes of such a monster,
                     And bedded in his bowells—
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     
                        Olinda I should weepe,
                     And spend the short'nd breath that fate affords me,
                     In cursing fate which makes my breath so short.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Peace peace my Cosma, thou wouldst
                     Haue me mad with reason!
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     No: reason is neuer sencelesse.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Thinkst thou me sence lesse friend?
                  
                  
                     Gla.
                     Dost not thou proue it?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Why my Glaucilla I see thy drowned eyes,
                     I feele thy kinde imbracements, and which thou seest not,
                     Nor feelst, I feele and see, more mirth and ioy
                     Spring in my heart; then if I now were leading
                     To the best bed that Sicely affords me.
                     
                        Glaucilla if there were but fit occasion
                     That I might shew thee this tormented heart
                           •
                        
                     
                     It would affright thee friend to heare me tell
                     How many deaths liue in so narrow Hell.
                  
                  
                     Decae.
                     We stay too long; goe on these idle teares
                     Quench not her griefe, but adde new kindled feares.
                  
                  
                     Olen.
                     
                        Decaeus; no feare within this brest is lying.
                     Who liuing dies, feares not to liue by dying.
                  
                  Exeunt ad rupem rufam manent reliqui.
               
               
                  Scen. 3.
                  Enter Perindus, Armillus.
                  
                     Ar.
                     Saw you the troope which past along here?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Yes.
                  
                  
                     
                     Ar.
                     Who is it ledde with such a mournfull show?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     My sister.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Who the faire Olinda?
                     
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Yes:
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     And doe you know the end and purpose?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     No:
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Nothing but no and yes? fie fie Perindus
                     
                     Your too much passion, shewes you want affection;
                     Your sister in such sort conuey'd, and you
                     So carelesse of her griefe? it much misseemes you
                     Why learne you not the cause?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Thou counsailst well,
                     Griefe weary of it selfe, all sence depriuing.
                     Felt neyther sence, nor griefe, by ouergrieuing:
Enter Atyches.
                     
                     But see my Atyches: what different passions
                     Striue in his doubtfull face, pitty would weepe,
                     And danger faine would rocke high thoughts a sleepe,
                     Whiles resolution chides the daring feare,
                     And courage makes poore feare afrade to feare.
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Thou God that rulst the sunnes bright flaming cart
                     If thou my grand-sire art, as sure thou art
                     For in my breast I feele thy powers diuine,
                     Firing my soule, which tels mee I am thine:
                     Direct my hand and guide this poynted dart,
                     That it may peirce, and riue the monsters heart.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Atyches.
                     
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Ah Perindus this lucklesse howre
                     Bids thee vnwelcome, fly and neuer more,
                     Neuer approach to view this deadly shore.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Why whats the newes?
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Thy sister the fayre Olinda must die.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     So must we all.
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     But none of all as she.
                  
                  
                     
                        Per
                              •
                           
                        
                     
                     Canst tell the cause and manner?
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     yes; and till the sunne
                     Twixt noone and night his middle race shall runne,
                     
                        The rites will not be finisht; 'tis briefly thus.
                     Thou knowst by Neptunes temple close their growes
                     A sacred garden, where euery flowers blowe
                           •
                        
                     
                     Here blushing roses, there the Lillies white,
                     He
                           •
                        e Hya
                           •
                        inth, and there Narcissus bright
                           •
                        
                     
                     And vnderneath, the creeping violets show:
                     That sweetnes o
                           •
                        t delights to dwell below:
                     Vaulted aboue with thousand fragrant trees,
                     And vnder pa'ud with shamefast Strawberies,
                     Which creeping lowe doe sweetely blushing tell,
                     That fairest pleasantst fruits, doe humblest dwell.
                     Breifly a little Heauen on Earth it seemes:
                     where euery sweete and pleasure fully streames.
                  
                  
                     Ar:
                     Fisher thou now describ'st some paradice,
                     Can any ill from so much good arise?
                  
                  
                     Atych:
                     Henbane and roses in our garden growe,
                     Ah that from fruits so sweete, such gall should flowe!
                     Here faire Olinda, with her Mymphs arriues,
                     And time away, time to fast posting driues,
                     While Nago that deformed enchanter, ranging
                     Along these trees, his shape and habit changing
                     Seem'd then Glaucilla, such his statelike eyes,
                     Such haire, such lipps, such cheekes, such rosie dies,
                     So like Glaucillas selfe that had shee spide him,
                     More would shee doubt her selfe, the more shee eyd him
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Can art forge nature with so true a lie?
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     The falsest coine is fairest to the eie,
                     Singling thy sister forth, they chance to see,
                     The sacred graft of that Herperian tree,
                     Whose golden apples much the eye delighting,
                     Would tempt the hands: the longing tast inuiting:
                     And now the subtill witch spies fit occasion,
                     Aud with fitte speech and oaths, and soft perswation,
                     So words hee mind; that shee (ha little guessing,
                     What monster lay vnder that faind dressing,
                     Puls of th' vnhappie fruit straight downe shee falls,
                     
                        And thrice a thundring voice Dieaeus calls;
                     The preist knew what the fearefull voice portended,
                     And faire Olinda halfe dead apprehended:
                     And to the temple beares her, there reseruing
                     Till the third day with death payes her deseruing
                     So Neptune, bids, that who shall touch the tree.
                     With hands profane, shall by Malorcha die;
                     
                        Malorcha bread in seas, yet seas do dread him,
                     As much more monstrous then the seas that bred him
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Ah my Olinda who can pitty thee
                     That wouldst not pitty th' excellent Thalander.
                     'Tis iust yee seas well doth impartiall fate
                     With monstrous death pnni
                           •
                        h thy monstrous hate.
                     And whither art thou now thus armed going.
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Downe to the fatall rocke I goe to see
                     And act a part in this foule Tragedy.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Why canst thou hope such losses to repayre?
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Who nothing hopes yet nothing ought despaire.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     What 'tis impossible? ah cease to proue?
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     What euer was impossib
                           •
                        e to loue?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     'Tis certaine thou adst thy death to hers
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Vnworthy loue that life for loue prefers
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     What good canst do when thou canst not restore her.
                  
                  
                     Atych
                     to liue with her or else to die before her.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     'Tis fate that in this monster bids engraue her.
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     And 'tis my fate to die with her or saue her.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     In vaine to fight against all conquering Ioue:
                  
                  
                     Atyoh.
                     But in my hand shall fight Ioue conquering loue.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Atych
                              •
                           s why shouldst thou thus betray thy selfe?
                     She was my sister, and as deare to me
                     As euer was a sister to a brother:
                     Had fate felt any hope, my willing hand
                     Should be as Prest to giue her ayd as any.
                     Were not the fight gainst heauen I might aduenture,
                     But here I needs must leaue her, though a brother
                     She neuer loued mee.
                  
                  
                     
                     Atych.
                     I lou'd her euer.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     More shouldest thou hate her now:
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Can Seas or Riuers stand can Rocks remooue?
                     Could they? yet could I neuer cease to loue:
                     
                        Perindus, if now I see thee last, farewell:
                     Within thy breast all ioyes and quiet dwell.
                     Adiew: Olinda now to thee I flye
                     For thee I liu'd, for thee i'le gladly die,
                  
                  Exit Atyches.
                  
                     Per.
                     Goe choycest spirit: the heauenly loue regard thee,
                     And for thy loue, with life, and loue reward thee.
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 4.
                  Enter Perindus, Armillus.
                  
                     Ar.
                     
                        Perindus thou knowst how late was my arriuall,
                     And short abode in this your Sicely,
                     
                     And how delighted with these accidents
                     So strange and rare, I haue decreed to make
                     Some longer stay, but since I saw this Atyches
                     
                     His loue more strong then death, a resolution
                     Beyond humanity I much desir'd
                     To know him, what he is, and what his country
                     That breeds such minds: let me intreate you then
                     At large to giue me all this story
                     Somewhat t'will east your griefe, iust are his paines
                     That sorrow with more sorrow entertaines.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     It will be tedious, and my heauy minde
                     Fit words for such a tale can neuer finde:
                     Yet I'le vnfold it all, that you may see
                     How beautious loue showes in inconstancy:
                     Who hath not heard of Glaucus loue? haplesse
                     Whilst fairest Seylla baths him, loue inspires
                     At once herselfe she cooles and him she fires.
                     
                        A sea god burnt in flames, and flames most please him
                     Glaucus findes neither waues nor hearbes to ease him
                     Cold were his eyes more cold her coy disdaine:
                     Yet none of boeth could quench loues schorching flame:
                     Till Circe whom scornd loue to madnes moues
                     Quenches at once her beautie and his loues.
                     There stands shee now a proofe of iealous spite
                     As full of horror now as then delight:
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     The fruite of iealousie is euer curst,
                     But when tis grafted in a crab tis worst.
                     Bad in a man, but monstrous in a woman,
                     And which the greater monster hard to know
                     Then ielous Circe, or loath'd Scylla now
                     After when time had easd his greife for Scylla,
                     
                     Circe with charmes, and prayers and gifts had wone him
                     Her lou
                           •
                         shee reapt in that high rocky frame,
                     Which euer since hath borne faire Circes name:
                     The Moone her fainting light 10 times had fed,
                     And 10 times more her globe had emptied:
                     When two fayre twins she brought, whose beauteous shine,
                     Did plainly proue their parents were diuine.
                     The male Thalander, the female calld Glaucilla,
                     
                     And now to youth arriu'd so faire they are
                     That with them but themselues who may compare,
                     All else excelling; each as faire as other
                     Thus best compard the sister with the brother.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     So liuely to the eare thy speeches show them,
                     That I must halfe affect before I know them.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Vaine words that thinke to blase so great perfection,
                     Their perfectnes more proues words imperfection.
                     But if these words some little sparkle moue,
                     How would their sight inflame thy soule with loue?
                     Scarce did his haire betray his blooming yeares,
                     When with his budding youth his loue appeares,
                     My selfe and sister equally he loues,
                     
                        And as on those two poles heauen euer moues
                     So on vs two his soule still fixt, still louing
                     Was euer constant, by his constant mouing:
                     Yet neuer knew wee which was most respected,
                     Both equally and both he most affected.
                     In mee his worthy loue with iust reflexion,
                     Kindled an equall and a like affection,
                     But shee my sister most vngratefull maide,
                     With hate, ah hatefull vice, his loue repaide
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Ar:
                     Cea'st he not then to loue? this sure wee hold
                     That loue not backe reflected soone grows cold.
                  
                  
                     Per:
                     No though all spite within her bosome sweld,
                     Spite of her spite his loue her hate exceld;
                     At length to shew how much he was neglected,
                     His riuall vgly riuall shee affected:
                     Such riuall could I wish whose foule distortion,
                     Would make seeme excellent a meane proportion,
                     For Mago, thus his hated riuall's nam'd)
                     All blacke and foule, most strang and vgly fram'd
                     Begot by Saturne, on a sea-borne witch,
                     Resembling both, his haires like threeds of pitch
                     Distorted feete, and eyes suncke in his head:
                     His face dead pale, and seem'd but moouing lead
                     Yet worse within, for in his heart to dwell
                     His mothers furies haue their darkest hell.
                     Yet when Thalander woo'd her, shee neglects him,
                     And when this monster flatterd shee respects him.
                  
                  
                     Ar:
                     I'
                           •
                        t possible. troth Sir but that I feare mee,
                     If I should speake some women should ore: heare me
                           •
                        :
                     Meet thinks I now could raile on all their kinds,
                     But who can sound the depth of womens minds?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Shortly to come to'th' height of all their wrong,
                     So could this Mago fill his smoothe
                           •
                        t tongue,
                     That shee 
                           
                              •
                           halander banisht from her sight,
                     Neuer to see her more his sole delight:
                     And he to none his hidden greife in parted,
                     
                        But full of louing duty straight departed
                     Leauing our groues in woods he grows a ranger
                     To all but beasts and sencelesse trees a stranger.
                     Thus in a desert like his loue forsaken
                     Wh
                           •
                        n no
                           •
                        hing but cold death his flames could slacken
                     
                        Atyches spyed him
                           •
                         but so griefe had pin'd him.
                     That when he saw him plaine, he could not find him.
                     And so had sorrow all his graces re
                           •
                        t
                     That in him, of him no
                           •
                        hing now was left
                     Onely his loue; with which his latest brea
                           •
                        h
                     H
                           •
                         power'd into his eares, so slept i
                           •
                         death.
                     The rest when better leisu
                           •
                        e time affo
                           •
                        ds
                     This 
                           •
                        uck
                           •
                        ess
                           •
                         day askes rather teares 
                           •
                        hen words.
                  
                  Exeunt,
                  
                     CHORVS.
                     Who neere saw death, may death commend,
                     Call it 
                           •
                        oyes Prologue troubles end:
                     The pleasing s
                           •
                        eepe that quiet rockes him,
                     Where neither care; nor fancy mockes him.
                     But who in neerer space doth eye him
                     Next to hell, as he
                           •
                        l defye him:
                     No state
                           •
                         no age, no sexe can moue him,
                     No beggars prey, no Kings reprooue him
                           •
                        
                     
                     In mid'st of mirth, and loues alarmes,
                     He puls the Bride from Bride groomes arms
                     The beautous Virgin he contemn
                           •
                        s,
                     The guilty with the iust condemns.
                     All weare his cloth and no
                           •
                        e denyes.
                     Dres't in fresh colour'd liueries.
                     Kings lewe as beggars lie in graues,
                     Nobles as base, the free as slaues,
                     Bles't who on vertues life relying,
                     Dies to vice, thus liues by dying.
                     
                        But fond that making life thy treasure,
                     Surfetst in ioy, art drunke in pleasure.
                     Sweetes do make the sower more tart.
                     And pleasure sharp's deaths keenest dart.
                     Deaths thought is death to those that liue,
                     In liuing ioyes, and neuer grieue.
                     Happelesse that happie art and knowst no teares
                     Who euer liues in pleasure, liues in feares
                  
                  Exit.
                  Finis Actus Primi.
               
            
            
               Act. 2.
               
                  Scen. 1.
                  Enter Conchylio solus.
                  I Haue bene studying, what bold hardie foole
                  Inuented fishers art, th
                        •
                     t tir'd with safety,
                  Would needs go play with waues, winds, death and hell,
                  The summe of fishers life is quickly found,
                  To sweate, freeze, watch, fast toyle be starud or drownd
                        •
                     
                  
                  Well had my Mistris found no better trade,
                  I would ere this haue left these dabling deities,
                  But she while other fishers fish on the seas,
                  Sends me a fishing on the Land for flesh:
                  No, game arriue's amisse vnto her net,
                  For shees not borne among the cliffs, and rockes
                  But from Messena comes to sport herselfe
                  And fish for fooles along these craggie shores,
                  I tooke her for a Nymph, but shees a woman
                  A very woman loueth all she sees,
                  This for his sprightly wit, and that for Musicke,
                  Him cause hee's faire, another for his blacknesse
                  Some for their bashfulnes, more for their boldnesse,
                  The wiseman for his silence, the foole for his bibble babble;
                  And now she longs in haste for another fat cods-head,
                  
                     A good fat sow, and I must snare one for her
                  She has (let me see I haue the tallie)
                  Some hundred louers, yet still desires another
                  The first that passeth all the rest in loue
                  Is called Pas: Hah know you your cue so well?
Enter Pas.
                  
                  He is a malum collum, alas poore foole;
                  He would engrosse my Mistris to himselfe
                  He would haue her all alone, let her alone for that
                  And for that it will not be, he raues and sweares
                  And chides and fights, but what neede I describe him
                  Hee'l doe't himselfe, come, begin begin.
               
               
                  Scen. 2.
                  Pas Conchylio.
                  
                     Pas.
                     Who sowes 
                           •
                        he seas, or plowes the easy shore?
                     Yet I, fond I more fond, and sencelesse more:
                     Who striues in nets to prison in the winde?
                     Yet I in loue a woman thought to bind:
                     Fond, too fond thoughts, that thought in loue to tie,
                     One more inconstant then inconstancy:
                     Looke as it is with some true Aprill day,
                     The sunne his glorious beames doth fayre display,
                     And straight a clowd breakes into fluent showres,
                     Then shines and raines, and cleares and straight it lowres:
                     And twenty changinges in one houre do proue,
                     So, and more changing is a womans loue.
                     Fond then my thoughts, that thought a thing so vaine,
                     Fond loue, to loue what could not loue againe.
                     Fond hopes, that ancho
                           •
                         on so false a ground,
                     Fond thoughts that fir'd with loue, in hope thus drownd:
                     Fond thoughts, fond hope, fond heart, but fondest I,
                     To graspe the winde, and loue inconstancy.
                     Ah Cosma, Cosma.
                     
                  
                  Exit
                  
                     
                     Con.
                     Ah Pas, asse passing asse; hah, ha, he:
                     Fond thoughts, fond hope, fond heart, but fondest I,
                     To graspe the winde, and loue inconstancy; ha, ha, he,
                     This foole would haue I know not what, the sea
                     To stand still like a pond, the Moone neuer to change,
                     A woman true to one hee knowes not what:
                     She that to one all her af
                           •
                        ections brings
                     Cages herselfe and pinions Cupids wings.
                     Le
                           •
                        's see whose the second; O the second
                     Is an old dotard who though now foure
                           •
                        score
                     Yet nature hauing left him some few hot embers
                     Rack't vp in cold ashes, thinkes himselfe a
                           •
                        l fire and flame
                     And the
                           •
                        efore like the dwarfes
                     Who though neere so old, 
                           •
                        et still consort with boyes
                     So he among the freshest, you
                           •
                        h in dancing
                     In songs and sporting spends his fadish time.
                     Whe
                           •
                         snow on's head, showes in his eye
                     With winter lookes giues summer words the lye
                     His name is Fredocaldo; he knowes his name

                           E
                                 •
                              ter Fredocaldo.
                        
                     
                     No sooner cald but comes
                           •
                         what i'st he reads?
                     Vpon my life some sonnet, Ile stand and heare.
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 3.
                  Fredocaldo Conhilio.
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           re.
                     
                     I, I am siluer white so is thy checke
                     Yet who for whitenes will co
                           •
                        demne it?
                     If wrinkled, of thy forehead is not flecke
                     Yet who for frowning dare contemne it.
                     Boys full of folly youth of rage
                     Both but a iourney to old age
                     I am not yet fayre Nymph to old to loue
                     And yet woemen loue old louers
                     Nor yet to wauing light, as false to prou
                           •
                        
                     
                     youth a foule in
                           •
                        ide fairely co
                           •
                        ers.
                     
                        Yet when my light is in the waine
                     Thy sunnes renew my spring againe.
                     Pretty very pretty, why yet I see
                     My braine is still as fresh as in my youth.
                     And quicke inuention springs as currantly
                     As in the greenest head: this little disti
                           •
                        ke
                     I made this morne, to 
                           •
                        end vnto my lou
                           •
                        .
                     See, here's a legge how full, how little waining,
                     My limbs are s
                           •
                        il accompanied
                     With their kind fellow heate, no shaking palsie
                     Nor cramp has tane possession, my swift bloud streames
                     Runs quicke and speedie, through their burning channells
                     Pi'sh I am young, he is not antient
                     That hath a 
                           •
                        iluer b
                           •
                        dge of hoarie haires
                     But he that in sweete loue is dead and cold
                     So old men oft are young, and young men old
                     I'le take my farewell of this prettie verse
                     It is a prettie verse, I'le reade it againe

                           Conchyli
                                 •
                               throws downe his spectacles.
                        
                     
                     If I am siluer white and. O ho my spectacles.
                     Ah naughtie boy alas my spectacles
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Ha ha he your eyes Fredocaldo take vp your eyes hah, ha, he.
                  
                  
                     Fre.
                     Ah naughtie boy alas my spectacles
                     Whether is he gone? O if I finde him
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Find mee without eyes? hah, ha, he.
                  
                  
                     Fre.
                     O my ve
                           •
                        ses my verses,
Snatches his verses.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     A verie prettie verse: how fresh a braine that made it
                     If I am siluer white and. nay if you'l trie your limbs come on.
                     Exit Fredocaldo. Enter Perindus.
                     Farewell f
                           •
                        ost: how? Perind
                              ••
                           
                        ? oh how fitly
                     After warme winter comes a chill could summer
                     This youth in all things is that old mans contrarie
                     This a cold May, that a hot Ianuarie
                     All my art cannot blowe vp one sparkle
                     If I should stay hee'd blast mee, adue sol in Pises
                     
                     Farewell good Caldofredo, I must after Fredocaldo
                     
                  
                  Exit.
               
               
                  
                  Scen. 4
                  Enter Perindus Allcippus.
                  
                     Per.
                     Bles't is that fisher swane that sancke i'th flood
                     Hee's food for them whom he would make his food.
                     But I most wretched, who so many yeares
                     Liue safe in waters to be drownd in feares.
                     In fire and sorrow like Titius is my life
                     A couerd table furnisht still for griefe.
                     Hell loue your paines, for all poore soules can p
                           •
                        oue
                     Is felt and spoke but thus carelesse I loue.
                  
                  Enter Alcipyus.
                  
                     Alcip.
                     
                        Phaebus write thou this glorious victory
                     And graue it on thy shining axel-tree
                     That all may see a fisher hath done more
                     Then any age hereafter or before.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Alcippus what newes? me thinks I plaine descry
                     Ioy mixt with wonder in thy doubtfull eye.
                  
                  
                     Alcip.
                     
                        Perindus most happy haue I found thee here
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Is'st good ah tell me, yet my grounded feare
                     Pleads hope impossible.
                  
                  
                     Alcip.
                     Were you away
                     To the Ecco I had told it, as griefe, so ioy
                     Prest downe is burthensome, for now I see
                     Ioy is no ioy i
                           •
                         bard from company
                     
                        Olinda by the Priests enchained-fast
                     Vnto the fatall rocke downe to the wast
                     Was naked left, which thus was better drea
                           •
                        t
                     Beauty when most vncloth'd is clothed best:
                     And now the Priest all rites had finished
                     And those last words and hidden verses sayd
                     Then thus he loud proclaimes, who dare aduenture
                     
                        Against this monstrous beast, now let him enter
                     And if he conquer by his bold 
                           •
                        ndeauour
                     This goodly maid shall bee his prize foreuer
                     Straight was the monster loos'd, whose vgly sight
                     Strooke euery trembling heart with cold affright
                     Some sweate, some freeze, some shreike, some silent weare
                     The eye durst neyther winke nor see for feare:
                     Heauen hid his light, the fearefull sunne did shrow'd
                     His glorious eye vnder a iet
                           •
                        y cloud.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Saw'st thou the Orke?
                  
                  
                     Alcip.
                     Yes, and my panting heart
                     To thinke I saw it in my brest doth start.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Can'
                           •
                        t thou describe it?
                  
                  
                     Alcip.
                     Neuer tongue can tell
                     What to it selfe no thought can pourtray well.
                     More bigge then monstrous Python, whom men faine
                     By Phaebus first was bred, by Phaebus slaine.
                     His teeth thicke rankt in many a double band
                     Like to an armed battell ready stand
                     His eyes sunke in's head, more fearefull stood
                     Like bloodie flame or like to flaming blood
                     Not any eare vpon his head appeares,
                     No plaint nor prayer, no threat nor charme he feares
                           •
                        
                     
                     In sea and land he liues and takes from both
                     Each monsters part which most we feare and loath,
                     Soone as he felt him loose, he shakes his crest
                     And hungry posteth to his ready feast
                     And as through seas his oares a passage teare
                     The thronging waues fly fast, and roare for feare.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Me thinks I see him and th' vnhappy louer
                     Strook through with fright.
                  
                  
                     Alcip.
                     In all their shreiks he smiles
                     Stretching his armes, to fight himselfe composes
                     And nothing fear'd his body enterposes
                     Shaking a dart the monster he defies
                     Who scorning such a foe to's banquet flyes
                     
                        But he with certaine aime his Iauelin driues
                     Which as the sender bad at's eye arriues.
                     And fixt in's hollow sight, deepe drenched stood
                     Quenching the bloody fire with fiery blood
                     The wounded monster lowdly gins to yell
                     If Hell doe speake such is the voyce of Hell,
                     And to reuenge his hurt he flies apace
                     The other dart met him i'th middle race
                     And as along he blindly fast doth post
                     His way and t'ther eye together lost
                     Thus blinde he quickly dies, and being dead
                     Leaues to his foe his spoiles, his pawes his head.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Hercules thy twelue works with this one conferd
                     This one before thy twelue might be preferd.
                  
                  
                     Alcip.
                     
                        Perindus then mightst thou haue seene how loue
                     Is not more bold then fearefull, he that stroue
                     And conquered such a monster with a dart
                     To her faire eyes yeelds vp his heart
                     Ah hadst thou seene how fearefull modestie
                     Ioynd with chast loue did chide the hungry eye
                     Which hauing long abstaind and long time fasted
                     Some of those dainties now would faine haue 
                           •
                        asted
                     Ah hast thou seene which such fit time he got
                     How loue to much remembring loue forgot
                     How th' eye which such a monster did outface
                     Durst not looke vp vpon her eie to gaze
                     How th' hand which such a bould fight vndertooke
                     When her it toucht as with a palsie shooke.
                     As all that saw it thou wouldst soone haue sayd
                     That neuer liu'd so fortunate a maid.
                     Most happy such a danger to recouer
                     More happy farre by hauing such a louer.
                     And harke the Fishers home the victor bringing
                     Chant lowd his conquest, his due praises singing.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scen. 5.
                  
                     Enter in triumph with Chorus of Fis
                           ••
                        rs a
                           •
                        d Pri
                           •
                        s
                           •
                        s s
                           •
                        nging Atyches crow
                           •
                        d leading Olinda following Glaucil
                           •
                        a and Cos
                           •
                        a.
                  
                  
                     Song
                     Olinda if thou yeeld not now
                     The Orke lesse monstrous wa
                           •
                         the
                           •
                         thou
                     No monster to the eye more hatefull
                     Then beauty to desert vngratefull
                     Yeeld then thy heart and hand
                     And sing along this sand
                     Loue rule heauen, sea, and land.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Atyches how farest thou? O let these armes inlace thee
                     Me thinks I hold halfe heauen when I imbrace thee.
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     Will Perindu
                              •
                           
                         goe with vs to the temple?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Most willingly and when thou once art there
                     Then 'tis a temple 
                           •
                         may iustly sweare.
                  
                  Exeunt omnes.
               
               
                  Scen. 6.
                  Enter Cancrone and Scrocca with their boate from fishing.
                  
                     Scr.
                     Yet more larboord! hol vp against that waue now starboord!
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I thin
                           •
                        e we are vpon the shallow
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Hold in Cancrone I 
                           •
                        mell the shore

                           Cancrone fals in
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay by your leaue 'twas I that smelt it, for I am sure my nose kist it.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Take hold of the stretcher, and then fasten the rope.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     A rope stretch al
                           •
                         such bo
                           •
                        tle-head botemen, had it been

my lot to haue bene Master at sea as 'tis yours, wee had neere taken such a iourney in 
                           •
                        uch a fly-boate, such a sows-eare, such an egge-shell.
                  
                  
                     Scro.
                     Come helpe to laue her.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Its a true she
                           •
                         boote I warrant shee leakes brackish all the yeare long.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Will you come Sir you are yet in my iurisdiction on the water.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Will you scale the fish sir, will you bring forth the nets sir, will you spread them vpon the rocks sir you are at my demand Sir vpon the land, wee'l be knowne in our place (Scrocca drinks) is that your lauing.
                  
                  
                     Scro.
                     Ah ha this is something fresher then Neptuns salt potion, seest not what a pickle I amin, but O those Scyllaes bandogs (bough wough) our boate bepist her selfe for feare.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I and thou thy selfe for companie; faith wee were almost in Thetis powdring tub, but now Scrocca
                        
                           •
                         lets off with our liquor: Sirrah halfe to this blew-beard Neptune, but he gets not one drop on't.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     I and withall remember the roaring boy B
                              •
                           reas (puff puff) hold: you beare your poope too high Cancrone, y'ad neede goe pumpe.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     So mee thinks my braine is somewhat warmer now my wirt gear's on.

                           Let Neptune rage and roare and fome
                           For now Concrone's safe at home.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     How now Cancrone! what? poefied?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Why Scrocca is it such a matter for a waterman to be a poet now a daies?
                  
                  
                     Sco.
                     I but I wonder that in all thy Poems thou neuer madst an Epitaph for thy grandsire that was eaten vp by the Cyclops.
                  
                  
                     Can,
                     Ah Scrocca I prethee doe not ming my grand-sire, thou'lt spoile my poetry presently; those hungry side slops; they eate him vp crust and crum, and then kild him too and

that which grieues me most: hee neuer sent mee word who it was that bit of's head, yet fayth, one draught more and haue at him.
                  
                  Hee drinkes.
                  
                     Scr.
                     Nay if one draught will serue, he shall neuer starue for an Epitaph.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     So: it's comming I haue it Scrocca.
                     
                     Here lies Cancrones grandsire, who sans boate.
                     
                     Sands winde, sans seas saild downe the Cyclops throate.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Here lies? Why will you graue an Epitaph on the Cyclops belly?
                     I
                           •
                        me sure hee lies yonder.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Masse thou sayst true, but all our late writers begin so.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Well sir will you walke home and warme your poeticall vaine at the kitchin fire.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Yes I care not if I doe, for I shall nere be well till I haue got the chimney corner ouer my head.

                           Farewell ye rockes and seas, I thinke yee'l sh
                                 •
                              w it
                           That Sicelie affords a water-Poet
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 7.
                  Enter Conchylio solus.
                  Hah, ha, he; I haue laught my selfe weary: i'st possible?
                  That fire and frost should thus keepe house together,
                  Sure age did much mistake him, when it set
                  His snowie badge on his blew riueld chin.
                  Were not his faces furrowes fild with snow
                  His hams vnstrung his head so straightly bound
                  His eyes so rainy, and his skinne so drie
                  He were a pretty youth.
               
               
                  
                  Scen. 8.
                  Enter Cancrone and Scrocca.
                  
                     Con.
                     What old acqaintance? lie by Mistris a little
                     I'le fish a while, I may chaunce to catch
                     A Cods-head; Ile stand and heare them.
                  
                  
                     Sor.
                     Did not I tell you we were wrong? sir.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Me thought, we were at land vile soone.
                  
                  
                     Sor.
                     I prethee on which hand was the cape of Peloro,
                     When wee left Syllaes bandogs.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     That did belong to thy water o
                           •
                        fice to marke,
                     But sure it stood straight before a little o'th' on side,
                     Right vpon the left, and then it left, the right,
                     And turned west by East, and then stood still North, North, By South.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Well bould woodcocke
                     Wi
                           •
                        hout a bias.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Come looke about you to your land office.
                     I'le hold a ped of oysters the rocke stands on yonder side;
                     Looke this way: I prethee is not this Circe's 
                           •
                        ocke,
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I like thy reasons wondrous well it is her rocke and her distaffe too.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I'
                           •
                        e spin
                           •
                         some thred out of this distaffe.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Then I sweare by Circes iugling box wee come in o' th' wrong side.
                  
                  
                     Can
                     Looke into my poll, canst thou not perceiue by the colour of my braines that I haue vnlac't her knaue
                           •
                        y? thou knowst Ci
                           •
                        ces is a plaguie wi
                           •
                        ch.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     I she did translate a good father of mine into an hogge.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     She with her 
                           •
                        hisking white wand, has giuen this rocke a box ō the ear
                           •
                        , &amp; set it one the other side of the country
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     I care not where Circes dwells, but I am sure we dwell on this side, and wee haue pusht in the cleane contrary way, and wat you what, wee haue leapt through Hell-mouth: O

strange how—
he falls downe and cries.
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     O the Orke the huge huntie, puntie.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Vp cancrone I tell thee wee haue scap't him.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I tell thee Sirocca wee haue not scap't him, he has eate vs vp
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     These fi
                           •
                        hers are new returnd from fishing, and know not that Atyches has slaine the Orke, I'le Orke them.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Ah Sirocca I would this O
                           •
                        rke were in Neptunes bellie, that will suffer such a worme to liue in his dominions, I am a very macherell if the very name be not worse to mee then, three nights cold fishing.
                  
                  
                     
                        S
                              •
                           r.
                     
                     Mee thinks I am colder too then I was before.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Let mee strike then before the iron be key cold
                     What hardie fishers dare approch this shore
                     Vntrod by men this twenty years and mo
                           •
                        e.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Good now Conchyli
                              •
                           
                         doe not the Norke
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        S
                              •
                           r.
                     
                     Wee did eate the go
                           •
                        den apples; wee.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     What old Cancr
                              •
                           ne? I am 
                           •
                        orrie for your chance The best that I aduise you is 
                           •
                        hat you r
                           •
                        turne round about the Cape presently before the O
                           •
                        ke smell you (if he were within twelue score he might wind them) foh.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay I shall be deuourd.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     P
                           •
                        ucke out a good heart man.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     If I could doe so I might saue the Orke a labour, that Will be done to my hand I know I shall be deuourd.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Why man.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Why my grandsire was deflourd, and they say deflouring goes in a blood.
                  
                  
                     
                        Co
                              •
                           .
                     
                     If I ridde you both of this feare will you worship m
                           •
                        e.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     O wo
                           •
                        shipfull water-wight.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     O Neptunes father.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     O Glaucus Mother.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Why then thus; my deities oracle giues you answer thus
                     When 2 famous fishers fall vpon this sand
                     Let them for feare of m
                           •
                        ghtie Orke, leaue seas saile home by land
                     I haue not pincht 
                           •
                        hem for measure
                     I haue giuen them Oracle vp to 
                           •
                        he elbowes.
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Ca
                              •
                           .
                     
                     Saile ther's your office Scrocca, you must goe:
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     By land, there's your office goe you.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     What can you not expound.
                     Dragge vp your bote and home-ward cr
                           •••
                        e this shore
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     W
                           •
                        e are all made, I vnde
                           •
                        stood you sir, but I did not know your meaning.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Pull you the b
                           •
                        te at nose 
                           •
                        'le lift at the arse.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Manners lacke this is a land voyage, I am master.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     
                        Hoh; roh; droh;, Horka, Corka, Suga ponto; the monster coms downe vnder the boate turne it ouer Ile helpe:
they couer themselues ouer with their beates for feare of the Orke &amp; creept ouer the stage.
                     
                     Retire thou sacred monster (cre
                           •
                        pe on)
                     These sweet soules a
                           •
                        e no f
                           ••
                        d fo
                           •
                         thee (on on)
                     'Tis time these soules were spent they begin
                     To stink, retire thou great god Neptunes sc
                           •
                        urg
                           •
                        
                     
                     
                        Retire I say while this twinne tortoise passes
                     
                     
                        And dare not on
                              •
                           e to touch these fi
                              •
                           h flesh asses.
                     
                     Hah, ha, he, farewell good tortoise, what good foutch? Haddocke 
                           •
                        are and C
                           •
                        d? you shall walke with me Ile be your O
                           •
                        ke: yet ile carry the Cod to my mistris Cosma. I know she loues it well: let Conchilio be turn'd into an Oyster if hee would not play the O
                           •
                        ke euery day for such sport, it shall go hard but 
                           •
                        le with my friend 
                           
                              •
                           ancr
                              •
                           ne yet once againe.
                  
                  Exit.
                  
                     CHORVS.
                     Happy happie Fishers swaine
                     If that yee knew your happines
                     Your sport tasts sweeter by your pai
                           •
                        es,
                     Sure hope your labour relishes
                     Your net your liuing, when you eate
                     Labour finds appetite and meat.
                  
                  
                     
                     When the seas and tempest roare
                     You eyther sleepe or pipe or play
                     And dance along the golden shore
                     Thus you spend the night an
                           •
                         day
                     Shrill windes a pipe, hoarse seas a taber
                     To fit your sports or ease your labour.
                  
                  
                     First ah first the holy Muse
                     Rap't my soules most happy eyes
                     Who in those holy groues d
                           •
                        e vse
                     A
                           •
                        d learne those sacred misteries
                     The yeares and months, old age and birth
                     The palsies of the trembling earth.
                  
                  
                     The flowing of the sea and Moone
                     And ebbe of both, 
                           •
                        nd how the tides
                     Sinke in themselues and backward run.
                     How palled Cynthia closely slides
                     Stealing her brother from our sight
                     So robs herselfe and him of light.
                  
                  
                     But if cold natures frozen parts
                     My dull slow heart and cloudie brain
                           •
                        
                     
                     Cannot reach those heauenly nets
                     Next happie is the fishers paine
                     Whose loue roofes peace doe safely 
                           •
                        ide
                     And shut out fortune, want and pride.
                  
                  
                     There shall I quiet fearelesse raigne
                     My boyes my subiects taught submission
                     About my court my sonnes my traine
                     Nets my pu
                           •
                        naiors of prouision,
                     The steere my septer, pip
                           •
                         musition
                     Labour my Phisicke, no Phisitian.
                  
                  
                     So shall I laugh the angry seas and skie
                     Thus singing may I li
                           •
                        e, and singing di
                           •
                        .
                  
               
            
            
               
               Act. 3.
               
                  Scen. 1.
                  Enter Perindus.
                  VVHen Attyches with better sight I eye,
                  Some powre me thinks beyond humanity,
                  Some heauenly power within his bosome lyes
                  And plainely looks through th' windowes of his eyes.
                  
                     Thalander, if that soules departed rest
                  In other men, thou liuest in his brest,
                  He is more then he seemes, or else— but see.
Enter Glaucilla.
                  
                  My loue, my hate, my ioy, my miserie.
                  
                     Glau.
                     
                        Perindu
                              •
                           , whither turnst t
                           ••
                        u? if thy wandring loue
                     My loue eschew, yet nothing canst thou see
                     Why thou shouldst flye me, I am no monster, friend,
                     That seekes thy spoyle, looke on me, I am shee
                     To whom th' hast vowd all fayth and loyalty,
                     Whom thou with vowes and prayers and oathes hast ply'd
                     And praying wept
                           •
                         and weeping beene deny'd,
                     And dy'd in the denyall, I am she
                     Whom by my brothers importunity
                     
                        Thalanders meanes thou want'st, who still perseuer,
                     Though thou art chang'd, I louing loue for euer.
                     Tell me am I altered in minde or bodies frame?
                     What then I was am I not still the same?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Yes, yes, thou art the same both then and now
                     As faire, more faire then heauens clearest brow.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     What haue I now deserued?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     In heauen to dwell:
                     The purest starre deserues not heauen so well.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     
                        Perindus, I am the same, ah I am she
                     I was at first, but thou, thou art not hee
                     Which once thou wast.
                  
                  
                     
                     Per.
                     True, ah too true:
                     Then was I happy being so distressed,
                     And now most miserable by being blessed.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Tell me what thus hath chang'd thy former loue,
                     Which once thou sworst nor heauen nor hell could moue:
                     How hath this scorne and hate stolne in thy heart
                     And on a Commick stage, hast learnt the art
                     To play a tyrant, and a foule deceiuer?
                     To promise mercy, and performe it neuer?
                     To looke more sweete, maskt in thy lookes disguise,
                     Then mercies selfe, or pitties gracious eyes.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Fa, la, la, fa, la, la, lah.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Ah me most miserable.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Ah me most miserable
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Wretched Glaucilla, where hast thou set thy loue!
                     Thy plaints his ioy, thy teares his laughter moue,
                     Sencelesse of these he sings at thy lamenting,
                     And laughs at thy h
                           •
                        arts tormenting.
                     Wretched Glaucilla.
                     
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     More wretched Perindus,
                     
                     Where by refusing life, thou diest, for whom
                     Thou liuest, in whom thou drawst thy ioy and breath,
                     And to accept, thy life is more then death.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Perindus.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Fa, la, la, fa, la, la, lah.
                  
                  Exit Perindus.
               
               
                  Scen. 2.
                  
                     Glaucilla sola.
                     Haplesse and fond, too fond and haplesse maide,
                     Whose hate with loue, whose loue with hate is payd.
                     Or learne to hate where thou hast hatred prou'd,
                     Or learne to loue againe, where thou art lou'd,
                     Thy loue gets scorne: doe not so dearely earne it,
                     At least learne by forgetting to vnlearne it.
                     
                        Ah fond and haplesse maide, but much more fond
                     Canst thou vnlearne the lesson thou has cond?
                     Since then thy fixed loue will leaue thee neuer
                     He hates thy loue, leaue thou his hate foreuer,
                     And though his yce might quench thy loues desiring
                     Liue in his loue and die in his admiring
                           •
                        
                     
                     
                        Olinda so late abroad?
Enter Olinda,
                     
                     The sunne is now at rest, heauens winking eyes
                     All drowsie seeme, loue onely rest denies:
                     But thou art free as aire, what is the reason?
                     What glasse is this?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Prethee Glaucilla
                     
                     Doe not thus search my soules deepe ranckling wound
                     Which thou canst neuer helpe when thou hast found.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Thy soule was wont to lodge within mine eare
                     And euer, was it safely harboured there
                     My eare is not accquainted with my tongue
                     That eyther tongue or ear
                           •
                         should doe thee wrong
                     Yet doe not tell me, I'le thee
                           •
                         I spie
                     Thy burning feauer is thy teltale eye.
                     Thou loust deny it not, thou loust Olinda
                     
                     In vaine a chest to lo
                           •
                        ke vp flames we seeke
                     Which now with purple fires thy blushing cheekes
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Th'art such a mistris in thy louing art
                     That all in vaine I hide my 
                           •
                        oue sicke heart
                     And yet as vaine to open't now tis hid.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Why so loues hee another?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     I would he did.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Strange wi
                           •
                        h in loue, much rather had I die,
                     Is he then perisht?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Yes and with him I.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     I prethee tell me all doe not conceale it,
                     Ile mourne with thee if that I cannot heale it.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Heare then and who so ere maiyst be a bride
                           •
                        
                     
                     Learne this of me to hate thy maiden pride.
                     
                        Atyches tho
                           •
                         knowest?
                  
                  
                     
                     Glau.
                     Thy champion?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     The same
                     Almost a yeare since he came to this towne
                     When finding mee fishing along the shore
                     Silent he angles by mee, till at length
                     Seeing mee take a sta
                           •
                        fish, and fling't away
                     He straight demands why I refus'd that pray
                     The cause I said was hate, he thus replied
                     Alas poore fish how wretch'ed is your fate
                     When you are kild for loue sau'd but for hate;
                     Yet then that fish much worse the fisher swaine
                     Who for his loue by hate is causeles slaine,
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Yet happier he that's slaine by loues defying
                     Then she in fate that liues yet euer dying
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     But soone as loue he nam'd, I straight was parting
                           •
                        
                     
                     He holding mee thus speaks; stay Nymph and heare
                     I bring thee newes which well deserues thine eare
                     He which most loues thee and thou hatest most
                     
                        Thalander (at his name my guiltie heart
                     Ashamed of it selfe did in me start)
                     He thus went on: Thalander's dead and dying
                     By oath and all his loue swo
                           •
                        e me to see thee
                     With these few words: Thalander quite forsaken
                     Would send to thee what thou from him hast taken
                     All life and health, and ne're his loue re
                           •
                        oouing
                     Wishes thee a freind more happie and as louing
                     And with this prayer these legacies he sends thee
                     This pipe his mother Cir
                              •
                           es gift, to bind
                     With this soft whistle the loud whistling wind
                     And with this pipe he left this precious ring
                     Whose vertues cuers a venemous tooth or sting
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Thalander were wee nothing like the other
                     Only thy loue would proue thou art my brother.
                     Did not this moue thee.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     
                        Glaucilla why should I lie
                     I tooke them as spoiles from a slaine enemio,
                     
                        And 
                           •
                        or these gifts (sayes he) his last demand
                     Was thi
                           •
                        , that I might kisse thy hand:
                     The last, the only gift thou canst impart
                     To such, so louing, and now dying heart
                           •
                        
                     
                     I grant; be gone, vpon the Ring 
                           •
                         spie
                     A Rubie cut most artificially,
                     Wherein was fram'd a youth in fire consuming,
                     And 
                           •
                        ound within it as the Ring I turne,
                     I found these words, Aliue or dead, I burne.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     These words well fitt his heart, so you, so I
                     
                        Thalander liuing loues, and louing dies.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     But oh those fained flames, such strange desires,
                     Such true, such lasting, neuer-quenched fires
                     Haue kindled in my brest, that all the Art
                     Of Triphons selfe cannot allay my smart:
                     Ah Glaucilla, tha scornefull proud Olinda;
                     Which at so sweete a loue a mockery made,
                     Who scornd the true Thalander, loues his shade,
                     Whose thousand graces liuing could not turne mee,
                     His ashes now hee's dead to ashes, burne mee.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     If thus you loue him, how can
                           •
                        t thou allow
                     Thy loue to Atyches! late didst thou vowe
                     In Neptunes temple to be his for euer.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     My hand he married there, my heart ah neuer.
                     
                        Glaucilla, I loue him for his loue to mee,
                     For such his venture, for such his victorie,
                     But most, because in loue he is my riuall,
                     Because hee's like and loue, my Loue Thalander.
                     
                     Ah, if my life will please him, let him take it,
                     He gaue it mee and I would faine forsake it.
                     Had it beene mine to giue, my wretched heart,
                     Not worth his dangerous fight, I would impart
                     But that is thine, Thalander thine for euer
                     With mee tis buried and arise shall neuer.
                     And wherefore serues this glasse?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     This is a dessamour Cosma lately gaue mee.
                  
                  
                     
                     Glau.
                     
                        Olinda, knowst not yet the treachery
                     Of Cosma, she thy greatest enemy?
                     Prethee let me see't: shouldst thou this liquor proue,
                     I tell thee, friend, 'twill quench thy life and loue.
                     But so Ile temper't, it shall better please thee,
                     And after few spent houres shall euer ease thee.
                  
                  
                     Olin,
                     Tis beyond art, who there can giue reliefe.
                     Where patients hate the cure, more then the griefe?
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Yes, by my art, before th'art 12 houres older,
                     Ile ease thy heart, though neuer make it colder.
                  
                  Exeunt.
               
               
                  Scen. 3.
                  Enter Conchilio.
                  
                     Con.
                     
                        Glaucilla and Olinda? I marle what mettle
                           •
                        
                     
                     What leaden earth and water nature put
                     Into these Nymphes, as cold, as dull, as frozen
                     As the hard rockes they dwell on! But my Mistris
                     Shee's all quicksiluer, neuer still, still mouing,
                     Now is she with some shepheard or some fisher,
                     And here she sets me to entertaine all commers:
                     This is the houre her Louers vse to muster.
                     But who should this be? ist you, old boy?
Enter Fredocaldo.
                     
                     Old ten i'th hundred, are you the captaine? boh,
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     Beshrew your heart, you are a very naughty boy,
                     I shake euery ioynt of me.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     No shaking palsey, nor cr
                           •
                        mpe has tane possession
                     Of your nimble limbes
                           •
                         ha, ha, he.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     Boy, where's thy Mistris?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Where she would bee.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     Where's that?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Where you would bee,
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     What, in her bed?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Ah old goate
                           •
                         doe I smell you? yet in her bed?
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     May not I speake a word or two with her
                  
                  
                     
                     Con.
                     what a foole tis? thou hast spoken twice a allreadie
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     I But I would speake them in her eare.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I know your errand but I preethee tell mee Fredocaldoe
                     
                     How ist possible that all the bellowes in loues fathers shoppe
                     Should kindle any fire in 
                           •
                        uch a frost?
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     
                        
                           •
                        hou knowst not what is loue, I tell thee boy
                     I loue faire Cosma more then a
                           •
                        l her louers.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     N
                           •
                        w in my conscience he says true, this old wood
                     Makes a b
                           •
                        ighter fire then the greenest euer:
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     Conchylio th'art deceiud, hast not seene
                     That of the May the lust of all the yeare
                     Nipt with the hoarie f
                           •
                        ost grows cold and chare?
                     And oft October tho
                           •
                        gh the yeares declining
                     With many daintie flowers is fairely shining
                     For as the flaming sunne puts out the fire
                     So may the heate of loue quench loues desires.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Cou
                           •
                        d this dotard doe as well as speake, he might—
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     I 
                           •
                        ell thee boy, when I was young—
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     That was at the siedge of Troy
                     
                     Now shall wee hau
                           •
                        , more tales then euer poets made
                     But w
                           •
                        at will you giue mee Fredocaldoe
                     
                     If I helpe thee in the rockie caue, neere to the mirtle groue
                     To sp
                           •
                        ake with Cosma all alone.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     If thou'l doe it, Ile giue thee as faire an otter tamd for fishing as euer was i
                           •
                         
                        Sicely.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Your hand on 
                           •
                        hat: Ah old Saturne cold and dry we'l Ile doe't
                  
                  
                     Fred
                     But when Conchylio when?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Within this houre expect 
                           •
                        er.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     Wilt thou besure.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Why did I euer deceiue you?
                  
                  
                     Fred:
                     neuer neuer:
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     b
                           •
                        eleeue mee Fredocaldoe I say beleeue mee then.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     Farewell; I'le keepe my promise.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Faile not within this houre:
Exit Fredocaldoe.
                     
                     I know not what this old man's like, vnlesse
                     O
                           •
                        r hill of Sicely the flaming AEtna:
                     Whose parches bowells still in fire consuming
                     
                        Fils all the valley with flame and pitchy fuming.
                     Yet on his top congealed snow doth lye
                     As if there were not fire nor Phoebus nie.
                     Why should we count this strange? when euen so
                     This old mans heart's all fire, his head all snow?
                     But what fresh souldier's this?

                           Enter Armillus
                                 •
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     My pretty wagge?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Sure you doe mistake me, sir, I am anothers.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Thou dost mistake mee, boy, I know well whose tho
                           •
                         art.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I doubt you doe not.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Th'art faire Cosmaes boy.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     My mother told me so.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Th'art a very wagge, take thi
                           •
                        , my boy.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     True sir, now I am yours indeede; what! yellow? yours to command: what would you with me?
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Seest thou!
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Yes I see very well.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Thou art too: quicke I prethee let me see thy Mistris.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Troth, sir, you cannot, shee's taken vp with other busines, or rather taken downe, yet i'le trie sir.
Exit,
                     
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Oft haue I maruaild how the erring eye,
                     Which of his proper obiect cannot lye,
                     In other subiect, failes so in his duty
                     When hee's to iudge of's chiefest obiect beauty.
                     None takes the night for day, the day for night.
                     The Lillies seeme alike to euery sight:
                     Yet when we partiall iudge of beauties graces,
                     Which are but colours plac'
                           •
                         in womens faces,,
                     The eye seemes neuer sure the selfesame show
                     And face, this thinkes a swanne, and that a crow.
                     But sure our minds with strong affections tainted,
                     Looke through our eyes as through a glasse that's painted.
                     So when we view our loues, we neuer see
                     What th'are, but what we faine would haue them be.
                     Thus Atyches. Perindus thus affecting
                     
                        These Nymphs, make them seem worthiest their respecting,
                     And thus to louo their beauties neuer moue them:
                     But therefore beautious seeme because they loue them.
                     Me thinks this Cosma farre them both excels,
                     In whose high forehead loue commanding dwels.
                     I like not this same too much modestie,
                     Commend the Senate for their grauity.
                     The wanton Nymph doth more delight me farre,
                     The modest Nymphs doe more seeme chaste then are,
                     Women are all alike, the difference this,
                     That seemes and is not, that both seemes and is.
                     Or if some are not, as they call it, ill,

                           E
                                 •
                              ter Conchylo.
                        
                     
                     They want the power and meanes, but not the will.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     My Mistris as yet is so ouerlayd with sport or busines, she cannot speake with you: may not I know your errand?
                  
                  
                     
                        Ar
                              •
                           
                        
                     
                     My errand boy is loue.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Loue (um) tis light enough, I shall carry it away: 'tis so short I shall remember it; but troth sir, another golden star this starlesse night dropt in my hand, may chance to giue light to make my Mistris shine in your armes.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Hold thee boy, hold thee: will that content thee?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Sir doe you know the myrtle groue?
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Yes well.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Your star will conduct you thither straight, within this houre shee'l meete you there.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     How canst thou assure it?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Trust mee I'le procure it;
                     Else neuer more let me see golden stars.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     I'le try thee boy, 'tis but one mis-spent houre,
                     If thou performe thy promise good Conchylio,
                     
                     Many such glittering nights shall shine on thee.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     If? make no question sir.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Farewell.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Adiew.
Exit.
                     
                     This strange new bird, this goose with golden eggs
                     
                        Must with some graine of hope bee cherished,
                     And yet not fedde too fat; now for my Crab,
                     Here's his twin, if heauens signes are right.
Enter Scrocca.
                     
                     Next to the crab, the twin must come in sight,
                     I'le out and seeke him.
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 4.
                  Scroeca, Cancrone.
                  
                     Scr.
                     Saile home by land quotha? well, I'le haue that saddle boate hung vp for a monument in the temple of Odoxcom, hard by the euerlasting shooes, and now to see the ill lucke on't neuer mo
                           •
                        e neede of 
                           •
                        ish, a bounsing feast toward, vmber of guests, not a whiting, not a haddock, not a cod-mop in the house: and in stead of catching fish, wee must goe fish for our nets, Cancrone, come along, along, along: the Orke's dead and buried, the Orke's dead and buried.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I but does not his ghost walke thereabout?
within.
                     
                     On afo
                           •
                        e, I'le follow hintly fintly, by the hobnailes of Neptun
                              •
                           
                         horse-shooes—
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Nay if you sweare, we shall catch no fish, what Can
                              •
                           rone, sneake you still? whoop, we shall fish fairely if your searmore be off:

                           Enter Cancro
                                 •
                              e bu
                                 •
                              ning his coate.
                        
                     
                     How now, what all in white?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Seest not I am busified? doest thou thinke a man can button his coate and talke all at once?
                  
                  
                     
                        S
                              •
                           r.
                     
                     My prettie sea-cob, why I preethee why in thy white?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Ino triumph I Ino triumph 
                           •
                         tell thee this is my triumphing sute, did not wee vanquish the Orke?
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     I hope so: 
                           •
                        oo but all our fellow fishers say t'was Aty
                           
                              •
                           hes.
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Thus Atyches kild him aliue, and wee kild him dead.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     I preethee on with thy gaberdine againe.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     My old s
                           •
                        aly slimie gaberdine? why, if I should fish in that, euery finne would smell mee.
                  
                  
                     
                     Scr.
                     Well, our nets are not aboue ground, what shall wee doe?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Why then Sir, you must goe seeke them vnder ground.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Well Sir, you'l follow.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Muddie Scrocca, canst thou not perceiue Cancrones inside by his new out-side? my old Orke apparell, my pitch patch poledauies had no good perfume for a sweete louer, as I now must be: but why a louer? because I meane to kill the next Orke hand to hand; for my masters sisters sweetheart Ataches, because a louer, therefore an Orkekiller.
                     
                  
                  Enter Conchylio.
                  
                     Con.
                     What? old crab tortoise? has the Orke made you cast your shell?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Fish mee no fishing: I'me all for flesh.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Thy lob hath learnt that fishers keepe no lent.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Therfore thou blue-beard Neptune, and thou trumphing Triton, and thou watchet iacket Gl
                              •
                           ucus, Dau
                              •
                           us, Maucus, and all the rest of the salt fish gods, I denounce you all, and for your formable farewell, I doe here reach forth to your dropping driueling deities my loue warme hand to kisse.
                     So, haue you done? Fie flapmouth.

                           Conchylio spits ins hand.
                     
                     
                        Triton, thou beslauerest mee.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     O doutie loues! heres more game for my mistresses net, or rather for mine.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nothing but Venus smocke or Cupids wing shall wipe it dry; surmount thy wagging wanton wing to mee, god Cupid.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Are you there? I Orkt you once, and now Ile fit you for a Cupid.
                        Exit. Conchyl.
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Mee thinks I am growne very eloquent alreadie; thanks sweete loue; O now for my master Perindus, he has a fine crosse cut with's armes, and yet that Orke-catcher Ataches has a pesslence carriage on's pate: the Nymphs beleare him partly: so, so, so.

                           Now Cupid doe I come to thee,
                           To thee, vpon my bare-head knee:
                           Knee neuer bare-head yet before,
                           Before it begged at thy doore.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Enter Scrocca. with his nets.
                  
                     Scr.
                     What? deuout Cancrone knocking at Cupids doore?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Ah Scrocca, thou hast corrupted the goodest verse! I was making my supplantation to Trustie Triton for good lucke, and see if he haue not heard mee: our nets are returnd.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     He might well heare thee for this once: for thou doest not trouble him often. But if I had not lookt to them better then he had, wee might haue gone whistle for them: come Cancrone, will you goe?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Yes I warrant you, I'le peraduenture my person in a Cocke-boate.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Why then wee'l take the gallie foist.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Goe foist if you will, the burnt child dreads the water, and good men are scantie, make much of one, Cancrone.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Well, if you come, you shall haue vs at the red roche.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Yes, I'le fish on land for mermaids.
Exit.
                     
                     This dog-fish had almost put mee out of my l
                           •
                        ue-lesson.
                     Now to thee againe, courteous Cupid.
                     
                     
                        All sunke and soust i
                              •
                            soppy loue,
                     
                     
                        Cupid for thy mothers doue
                     
                     
                        Helpe.
                        
                           Enter Con
                                 •
                              hylio in Cupids habitt.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     All haile, Cancrone, according to thy wish I here am present great King of hearts, Duke of desires, Lord of loue, whom mortals gentle Cupid doe ycleape.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Beest thou Cupid? thou art vile like our Conchylio.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     True, Cancrone, and lest the beames of my bright deitie should with their lustre wound those infant eyes, I haue vo
                           •
                        chsaf't in this forme to appeare, lo, thy Conchylio and thy Cupid here, what wouldst thou with mee?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I haue a suite to your godship.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     So it be not your Orke-suite I embrace it: say on, my darling.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I am in loue as they say, but I cannot tell whom to be in loue withall.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Here are Nymphs enow, Vrina, Olinda, Lilla, Glaucilla, Bobadilla,
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Can.
                     Mee thinks that Boberdil sounds like a fine play-fellow for mee.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     No, I'le tell thee one, her name shall make thy mouth water.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Make water in my mouth? thats Vrina, I'le none of her, shee's too high colourd.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     No, tis Cosma, the fishers flame, the shepheards hope, whose beautie Pas admires.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I, but will you throw forth a good word for mee?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I tell thee I'le make her all to beloue thee, shee shall not rest til
                           •
                         
                        
                           •
                        hee meete thee here; but first I must arme thee with some magicke charmes.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     What be they? my chops would faine be champing them.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     First you must anagramatize her name, then sympathize your owne.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Tize, zize, thize. I shall ne're hit that.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     For an anagram I'le fit you: Cosma a smocke.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Prettie.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     For the sympathie of your owne name but thus, your name Cancrone bids you counterfeite the counter-creeping crab; and goe backward to her.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Doe I looke like a crab? I had rather goe forward to a Nymph.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Thirdly, because euery fisher is borne vnder Pisces, therefore the signe is in the foote with you: you must come therefore with one foote bare.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I but shall I not catch cold and cough and spoile my part?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     It mu
                           •
                        t be the right foote: and then see
                           •
                        t thou this mirtle tree? all my arrowes are made of the wood of it, thou must in her sight get vp and gather the highest bough of it.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I but what shall I doe with the bough?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     O the bough? why, setting thus 
                           •
                         prettie while, you must wrappe a cockle garland about it, and then when the poore lasse melts and consumes with thy loue—
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Then I'le throw it at her, &amp; come downe to her, shall I not
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Excellent well, I see thou art inspir'd.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay I 
                           •
                        an take it, if you put it to mee.
                  
                  
                     
                     Con.
                     But the iust nicke when thou must throw it is, when she says I die, I cry, I lie.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I die, I cry, I lye. I would haue her lie, but not die, but will you make her come indeede?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I and in her best clothes too.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay 'tis no such matter for clothes, but what must I say? I had almost forgot it.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Nothing but a short charme, which I'le teach you as we goe on afore, I'le follow you.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Let me see: backward?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Blockhead.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Barelegge?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Beetlepate.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Cockleshell?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Coxecombe.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Boughs?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Bussard.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     The towne's ours. I no triumph
                           •
                         I no triumph
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I'le coole my hot louer, he shall sit on a perch for a stale, now must I be vncupidate, &amp; shortly appeare here Cosmafied, it shall be hard but with the same limetwig I'le catch a bigger bird then this.

                           First I will serue my selfe, my mistris after;
                           My baite is seeming loue, my prey true laughter.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 5.
                  Enter Pas solus.
                  What art, strength, wit can tame a fish or flye?
                  The least of creatures vs'd to liberty,
                  With losse of life shake off base captiue chaines,
                  And with restraint all life disdaines.
                  But I, ah foole, yeld vp my selfe a slaue,
                  And what they shunne, by death doe basely craue:
                  My griefe more then my folly, who deplore
                  That which all others vse to wish before:
                  My loue loues too too much too many,
                  For while she liketh all, she loues not any.
                  
                     Loue, let my prayers yet thus farre onely moue thee,
                  Let me her falsly, or 
                        •
                     he truely loue me.
Enter Cosma.
                  
                  See where she comes; and that so bright a sunne
                  Should haue no spheare, no certaine race to runne:
                  I'le stand and ouer-heare her.
                  
                     Cos.
                     I can but smile to thinke how foolish wise
                     Those women are, that chuse their loues for wisedome.
                     Wisedome in men's a golden chaine to tie
                     Poore women in a glorious slauery.
                  
                  
                     
                        P
                              •
                           s.
                     
                     Hark Heauens! O monstrous! harke. O women, women.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Fond men, that blame the loue that euer ranges
                     To foule and sluttish loue, that neuer changes.
                     The Muses loue by course, to change their meeter,
                     Loue is like linnen often chang'd, the sweeter.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Thus these neate creatures, dead with loue and all,
                     By shunning beastlines, make it beastiall.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Our beauty is our good, the cause of loue:
                     Fond that their good toth' best will not improue;
                     What Husbandman neglects his time of sowing?
                     What fisher loseth winds, now fairely blowing?
                     Beauty our good: ah good, ah short and bri
                           •
                        tle,
                     A little little good, for time as little,
                     How easie doest thou slide, and passe away?
                     Vnborne, full growne, and buried in a day.
                     Thy spring is short, and if thou now refuse it,
                     Tis gone, when faine thou wouldst, thou shalt not vse it.
                     The time and euery minute daily spends thee.
                     Spend thou the time, while time fit leisure lends thee.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Does she not blush? hark, women, heres your preacher,
                     Maids, you want a Mistris; heres a teacher.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Now since Conchylio spake of this Armillus,
                     
                     My new found louer, I halfe long to try him:
                     Too cruell she that makes her hearts contenting,
                     To see a heart languish in loues tormenting.
                     What though i't
                           •
                        ' night we liue most wantonly?
                     I' th' morne with clothes we put on modestie.
                     
                        Thus though we sport, and wanton all the night
                     Next su
                           •
                        ne ile act a part of feare and fright.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Modestie? marry guipp: these are your modest creatures.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Long haue I hated Olinda, and Glaucilla,
                     
                     And one of them by this hath drunke her la
                           ••
                        ,
                     The next shall follow ere the next day's past.
                     The ginne is layd, and if it hit aright,
                     This is her last, this her eternall night.
                     
                        Perindu
                              •
                           
                         long I haue long lou'd, who euer scorn'd mee,
                     Because he loues Glaucilla; I know hee'l grieue:
                     But when the tempest once is ouerblowne,
                     Hoyst vp all sailes; the prize is sure mine owne.
                     Ill for a woman is that woman plac't,
                     Who like old Ianus, is not double fac't.
                     Now to Armillus who sure expects me.
                     How darke the night? more fit for Louers play.
                     The darkest night is louers brightest day.
Exit Cosma.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Well M
                           •
                        stris Iana with your double face,
                     I thinke I shall outface you by and by.
                     Ile fit you for a face i'fayth, I could be mad now.
                     Well, since you are sportiue, i'le make one i'th play;
                     You haue a foole already, i'le act a Deuill;
                     And since you needes must to a new consort,
                     Ile beare a part, and make or marre the sport.
                  
                  Enter Perindus.
               
               
                  Scen. 6.
                  
                     Perindus
                           •
                         Pas.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Atyches?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     No: Pas.
                     
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     If thou seest Atyches, send him hither friend;

                           Exi
                                 •
                               Pas.
                        
                     
                     Of all the plagues that torture soules in h
                           •
                        ll,
                     
                        Tant
                              •
                           le, thy punishment doth most excell.
                     For present goods, thy euill most expresse,
                     Making thee vnhappy in thy happinesse.
                     
                        Such are my paines: my blessednes torments mee,
                     I see, and may enioy what more torments me.
                     My life then loue, I rather would forsake,
                     Yet for my life, my loue I dare not take.
                     
                        Glaucilla, couldst thou see this wretched brest,
                     What torments in it neuer resting rest,
                     Whom now thou thinkst the cause of all thy greeuing,
                     Then thou wouldst iudge the wretchedst creature liuing.
                     She's here.
Enter Glaucilla.
                     
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     
                        Perindus, whither goest thou? the day's enough
                     To shew thy scorne, the night was made for rest.
                     For shame if not for loue, let night relieue me:
                     Take not that from mee, which thou wilt not giue me.
                     Knowst thou this place? euen here thou first didst vow,
                     Which I beleeue, and still me thinkes euen now
                     Cannot vnbeleeu't, that when thy constant heart,
                     From his first onely vowed loue should start,
                     These wauing seas should stand, whose rocks remoue
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Fa, la, la, fa, la, la, lah.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     O dancing leuity, you steady rocks,
                     Still stand you still? his fayth he lightly mocks.
                     Yee 
                           •
                        leeting waues, why doe you neuer stand?
                     His words, his loue, his oathes, are writ in sand.
                     In rocks and seas I finde more sense and louing,
                     The rocke lesse hard then he, the sea lesse mouing.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Didst neuer see the rockes in sayling moue?
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Not moue, but so
                           •
                         me to mou
                           •
                        .
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     My picture right.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     What says Perindus?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Ha, ha, he, how scuruily griefe laughs!
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     
                        Perindus, by all the vowes I here coniure thee
                           •
                        
                     
                     The vow that on thy soule thou didst assure me,
                     Tell me why thus my loue thou false refusest?
                     Why me thy fayth thy selfe thou thus deceiuest?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Ay me.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     How fares my loue?
                  
                  
                     
                     Per.
                     Ah Glaucilla.
                     
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     I know thou can
                           •
                        t not hate me.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     I cannot hate, but laugh, and dance and sport,
                     This is not hate, Glaucilla, 'tis not hate.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Canst thou Perindus thus delude me?
                     I'ue liu'd enough, farewell: thou laft hast viewd mee.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Glaucilla?
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     How canst thou speake that hated name?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Stay:
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     To be mockt?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Stay, i'le tell thee all.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Me thinks this forced mirth does not beseeme thee:
                     Sure 'tis not thine, it comes not from thy heart.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Glaucilla, call backe thy wish, seeke not to know
                     Thine or my death, thou winst thine ouerthrow.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Thy griefe is common, I haue my part in thine:
                     Take not that from me which is iustly mine.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     if I had any ioy, it were thine owne,
                     But grant me to be wretched all alone.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Now all thy griefe is mine, but it vnhiding,
                     Halfe thou wilt take away, by halfe diuiding.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Thou seekst my loue, it is my loue to hide it,
                     And I shall shew more hate, when I diuide it.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Thy loue thus hid, to me much hatred proues,
                     Vnhide thy hate, this hate will shew it loues:
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Glaucilla, while my griefes vntouched rest,
                     My better part seemes quiet in thy brest.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     So thou art well, but still my better part,
                     
                        Perindus, sinkes all loaden with his smart:
                     So thou my finger cut'st, and woundst my heart.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Since then thou wilt not giue me leaue to hide it,
                     Briefely 'tis thus: when thou thy loue hadst vowd me
                     Most sure, but yet no certaine time allowd me;
                     My marriage day as all my good desiring,
                     To Prote
                              •
                           s Cell I went, the time enquiring,
                     There heard these words, the cause of all my sadnes,
                     
                        The ca
                           •
                        se of all my seeming hate and gladnesse.
                     Thus went th' Oracle.
                     The day, that thou with griefe so long forbearest,
                     Shall bring thee what thou wishest most and fearest.
                     Thy sisters graue shall bee her marriage bed,
                     In one selfe day twice dying, and once dead.
                     Thy friend, whom thou didst euer dearest choose,
                     In loosing thou shalt finde, in finding loose.
                     And briefly to conclude the worst at last,
                     Thou, or thy Loue shall from a rocke be cast.
                     
                        Glaucilla, had thy loue but with my life beene priz'd,
                     My life t'enioy thy loue I had despis'd.
                     But since it may be thine, thy life destroying,
                     Shall nere bee giuen for my loues enioying:
                     Much rather, let me liue in fires tormenting,
                     Then with such purchase buy my hearts contenting.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Then loue's the cause of all thy seeming hate,
                     What hast thou seene in me, that I should seeme,
                     My life more then thy loue, or mine esteeme?
                     
                        Perindus thy hat
                           •
                         hath cost me often dying,
                     So hast th
                           •
                        u giuen mee death, by death denying:
                     For th' Oracle, with death I am contented,
                     And will not feare, what cannot be preuented.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Yet though such mischiefe Proteus did diuine,
                     Much better sped I at my fathers shrine:
                     Comming to Delphos, where the Pythian maid
                     Told me my wis
                           •
                        es should be fully paid
                     And that within few
                           •
                         dayes I should arriue
                     Through many bitter stormes, into the hiue.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Why doubtst thou then? ad
                           •
                        ew loue till to morrow,
                     Next rising sunne shall to thee ease thy sorrow.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Maist thou proue true, or if heauen bad decree
                     The good be thine, light all the bad on me.
                  
                  
                     Glau.
                     Farewell.
Exit.
                     
                     Thou giuest Glaucilla what thou wishest good rest.
                     This victory my minde hath whole possest,
                     
                        And from my eyes shuts out all sleepe and rest:
                     If I but slumber, streight my fancie d
                           •
                        eames,
                     This Atyches is much more then he seemes:
                     Comming to his couch, I found his emptie bed
                     As yet vntoucht, himselfe from sleepe is fled.
                     But soft, whom haue wee here?
Enter Atyches.
                     
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     The Oxe now feeles no yoke, all labour sleepes,
                     The soule vnbent, this as her play-time keepes,
                     And sports it selfe in fancies winding streames,
                     Bathing his thoughts in thousand winged dreames.
                     The fisher tyr'd with labour, snorteth fast,
                     And neuer thinks of paines to come or past,
                     Only loue waking rest and sleepe despises,
                     Sets later then the sunne, and sooner rises.
                     With him the day as night, the night as day,
                     All car
                           •
                        , no rest, all worke, no holy-day
                           •
                        
                     
                     How different from loue is louers guise!
                     He neuer opes, they neuer shut their eyes.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Ha: this is he, I'le stand and ouerheare him.
                  
                  
                     Atych.
                     So: I am alone, ther's none but I,
                     My griefe, my loue, my wonted compa
                           •
                        y,
                     And which best fits a grieued louers sprite,
                     The silent stars and solitarie night.
                     Tell mee heauens sentinels that compasse round
                     This ball of earth, on earth was neuer found
                     A loue like mine, 
                           •
                        o long, so truly ser
                           •
                        'd,
                     Whose wage is hate, haue all my paines deseru'd
                     Contempt? mine and her; for shee deare affected:
                     The more I lou'd, the more I was neglected.
                     Since thou canst loue where thou hast hatred prou'd,
                     
                        Olinda, how canst thou hate where thou art lou'd?
                     Thy body is mine by conquest, but I find,
                     Thy bodie is not alwayes with thy mind.
                     Giue both o
                           •
                         none, or if but one, o'th'two
                     Giue mee thy mind, and let thy bodie goe.
                     If this without thy minde I only haue
                           •
                        
                     
                     
                        What giu'st thou more to me then to thy graue?
                     Prooue mee, my deare, what canst thou hate in mee?
                     Vnlesse my loue, my loue still bent on thee?
                     My name's Thalander, perhaps it doth displease thee,
                     I will refuse my name, if that may ease thee.
                     
                        Thalander to exile wee'l still confine,
                     And 
                           •
                        'le be Atyches, so I bee thine.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Thalander? i'st possible? I oft suspected
                     How he is altered! not himselfe! i'st possible?
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Yet what thou hat'st, thy brother loues as well.
                     Tell me, my dearest loue, what haue I done?
                     What has Thalander done? ah tell mee.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     More
                     Then thousand such as she can nere re
                           •
                        tore,
                     
                        Thalander; start not; how haue my eyes deceiu'd me?
                     Ah, let me blesse my armes with thy embraces.
                     My deare, Thalander, my only life, my heart,
                     My soule, O of my soule the better part.
                     Ist thee I hold; I scarce dare trust mine eyes,
                     Which thus deceiu'd mee by their former lies.
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Thou welcomst miserie while thine armes infold mee
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     I am the blessedst man that liues to hold thee.
                     My heart doth dance to finde thee.
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Ah Perindus,
                     
                     When least thou thinkst, thou art deceiued most,
                     My selfe, my loue, my labour I haue lost,
                     When I haue lost my selfe, to finde my loue.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     In losing of thy fame, th'ast found
                     She loues thee friend most dearely,
                     And though she thought thy loue would be her death
                           •
                        
                     
                     Yet for and in thy loue, shee'd lose her breath,
                     And nothing else should grieue her in the end
                     She had one life for such a loue to spend.
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Doe not deceiue me.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Why shouldst thou mistrust me?
                  
                  
                     
                     Aty.
                     
                        Perindus, my ioy, by too much ioy enioying,
                     I feele not halfe my ioy, by ouer-ioying.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Her selfe 
                           •
                        hall speake it. Come, let's goe.
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     'Tis night!
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Shee'l thinke it day, when thou art in her sight.
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Lead me, for yet my mind, too much affected
                     To haue it so, makes truth it selfe suspected.
                  
                  Exeunt,
                  
                     CHORVS.
                     Loue is the fire, damme, nurse, and seede
                     Of all that aire, earth, waters breede.
                     All these earth, water, aire, fire,
                     Though contraries, in loue conspire.
                     Fond painters: loue is not a lad,
                     With b
                           •
                        w, and hafts, and feathers clad;
                     As he is faucied in the braine
                     Of some loose louing idle swaine,
                     Much sooner is he felt then seene,
                     His substance subtile, slight and thinne,
                     Oft leapes hee from the glancing eyes,
                     Oft in some smooth mount he lyes,
                     Soonest he winnes, the fastest flyes:
                     Oft lurkes h
                           •
                         twixt the ruddy lips,
                     Thence while the heart his Nectar sips,
                     Downe to the soule the poyson slips,
                     Oft in a voyce creeps downe the eare,
                     Oft hides his darts in golden haire,
                     Oft blushing cheeks do light his fire,
                     Oft in a smooth soft kinne retires,
                     Often in smiles, often in teares;
                     His flaming heate in water beares,
                     When nothing else kindles desire,
                     Eu
                           •
                        n v
                           •
                        rtues selfe shall blow the fire:
                     Loue with thousand darts abounds,
                     
                        Surest and deepest vertue wounds,
                     Oft himselfe becomes a dart,
                     And loue with loue, doth loue impart.
                     Thou painfull pleasure, pleasing paine,
                     Thou gainefull life, thou losing gaine:
                     Thou bitter sweete, easing disease,
                     How doest thou by displeasing please?
                     How doest thou thus bewitch the heart?
                     To loue in hate, to ioy in smart.
                     To thinke it selfe most bound, when free,
                     And freest in his slauery.
                     Euery creature is thy debter,
                     None but loues, some worse, some better:
                     Onely in lou
                           •
                        , they happy prooue,
                     Who loue what most deserues their loue.
                  
               
            
            
               Act. 4.
               
                  Scen. 1.
                  Enter Perindus and Thalander.
                  
                     Per.
                     BE patient.
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Yes, I am patient,
                     And suffer all, while all heauens ills are spent.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     You giue your selfe to griefe
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Sencelesse and mad.
                     Who in much griefe, is not extremely sad?
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Alas sir, she was mortall, and must die.
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     True, true, and could the fates no time 
                           •
                        spie
                     But this? to me she neuer liu'd till now,
                     And now Perindus? now! oh—
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     She was my sister!
                  
                  
                     Aty.
                     Alas, thy sister!
                     She was my life, my soule, she was my love,
                     She was—words know not what she was to me:
                     She was—thou most accursed word of was
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Per.
                     Be comforted.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     
                        Perindus, the very name of comfort, is most comfortlesse
                     Comfort, ioy, hope, liu'd in her cheerfull smiling,
                     And now must die, or liue in far ex
                           ••
                        ing.
                     Comfort, ioy, hope, for euer I deny you,
                     And would not name you now but to defie you.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     Sir, with more patience you haue often borne
                     Far greater euils.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     
                        Perindus, doe not say so,
                     If thou yet loue me, prethee doe not say so:
                     Was euer ill as this? hels breniary
                           •
                        
                     
                     All torment in this narrow space is layd,
                     The wo
                           •
                        st of all, in these two words are sayd:
                     
                        Olinda dead? dead! whither doest thou lead mee?
                     Why, I can goe alone, alone can finde
                     The way I seeke, I see it best when blinde.
                     I prethee leaue me.
                  
                  
                     Per.
                     
                        Thalander, I'le not leaue thee,
                     Should heauen with thunder strike these arms that claspe thee,
                     My dying hands should but more firmely graspe thee.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Thou violat'st thy loue in thy mistaking,
                     And cleane forsak'st thy friend, in not forsaking
                     
                        Olinda: I cannot come, they heere enc
                           •
                        aine me.
                     But neyther can, nor shall they here detaine me.
                     I'th' meane time, all the honour I can giue thee,
                     Is but a graue, that sacred rocke, the place
                     Of my conception, and my buriall:
                     Since Hymen will not, death shall make thee mine,
                     If not my marriage, my death-bed shall be thine.
                     Exeunt.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Sc
                        •
                     n. 2.
                  Enter Rimbombo.
                  Farewell yee mountaines, and thou burning AEt
                           •
                        a,
                  
                  If yet I doe not beare thee in my brest,
                  And am my selfe, a liuing walking AEtna,
                  
                  The Nymphs that on you dwell, are too coy,
                  Too coy and proud, more fierce then robbed tygre
                  More deafe then seas, and more inflexible
                  Then a growne Orke, false, flattering, cruell, craftie,
                  And which most grieues me, when I would embrace them,
                  Swifter then c
                        •
                     ased Deere, or dogs that chase them,
                  You heauens, what haue we poore men deserued,
                  That you should frame a woman, I and make her
                  So comely and so needefull? why should you cloath them
                  With so fine a shape? why should you place
                  Gold in their haire, allurement in their face?
                  And that which most may vex vs, you impart
                  Fire into their burning eyes, y
                        •
                     e to their heart.
                  Why sweeten you their tongues with sugred charmes
                  And force men loue, and need their greatest harmes?
                  And most of all, why doe you make them fleete?
                  Minds as the windes, and wings vpon their feete?
                  Of hundred women that I know,
                  But one deserues to be a woman:
                  Whom better heauens haue not made more faire,
                  Then courteous, louing, kinde, and debonaire:
                  She, when she vsd our Mountaines, oft would stay,
                  And heare me speake, and vow, and sweare, and pray.
                  Here I haue learnt, she haunts along these shores:
                  Within these rockie clifts i'le hide my selfe,
                  Till fit occasion, if shee haue chang'd her minde,
                  Then safely may I curse all women. kinde.
Exit.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scen. 3.
                  
                     Enter Armillu
                           •
                        .
                  
                  Loue, without thee, all life is tedious,
                  Without thee, there's no sweete, no ioy, no life;
                  Thou first gau'st life, and still with new succession,
                  Continuest what thou gau'st, with sweet inticements,
                  Taming the strongst rebellion, thy weapons women,
                  Whom thou so fram'st, that proudest men are glad,
                  Beaten with them, gently to kisse the rod.
                  Eyther my weighty passions pull too fast
                  The wheele of time, or else the houre is past:
                  But this is she, or I mistake it.
                  Enter Cosma.
                  
                     Cos.
                     Women that to one man their passions bind,
                     As this man alters, so alters still their mind:
                     Thus euer change they, as those changing faires,
                     And with their louers still their loue impaires:
                     But I, when once my louers change their graces,
                     Affect the same, though now in other faces:
                     Thus now my mind is firme, and constant prou'd,
                     Seeing I euer loue, what first I lou'd.
                     Who blames the speedy heauen, for euer ranging?
                     Loue's fiery, winged, light, and therfore changing.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     True, fairest Nymph, Loue is a fire still burning,
                     And if not slak't, the heart to ashes turning.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     If I could scold, sir you might be chidden,
                     For comming to my thoughts before y'are bidden.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Blame me not (Sweet) thy words do fanne thy fires,
                     And coole the flames which thy faire eye inspires.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     The fire so lately applied, so lately fram'd?
                     Me thinks, greene wood should not be yet inflam'd.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Loues flame is not like earths, but heauens fire,
                     Like lightning, with a flash it lights desire.
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           os.
                     
                     I loue not lightning: lightning loue that flashes
                     Before't be all on fire, will be all ashes.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Gather the fruite then while 'tis yet vnblas
                           •
                        ed.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Ist worth the gathering? is it pleasing tasted?
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     Take say 
                           •
                        f this.
kisses her.
                     
                     Monster?
                  
                  Enter Pas offering to kisse on the other side, disguised like a fury.
                  
                     Cos.
                     Helpe ho.
                  
                  
                     Exeunt Armil. Cos. seuerall waie
                           •
                        .
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 4.
                  Pas. Fredocaldo.
                  
                     Pas.
                     The Doe was almost strooke, 'twas time I came,
                     For once I'le be a keeper of the game.
                     I see 'tis Owle-light, Mineruaes waggoner,
Enter Fred.
                     
                     My old riuall, who this twenty yeeres
                     Saw nothing but what shin'd through gla
                           •
                        se windowes,
                     What comes he for? I'le stay a while and watch him.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     Most happy age that shall be crownd with loue
                     Of thy loue, Cosma: I am not as I seeme,
                     Farewell old age, I now am young againe
                     And feele not ages, but a louers paine,
                     In loue I dare aduenture with the best,
                     Old beaten souldiers are the worthiest:
                     If all my riualls heard I could dare them,
                     If 
                           •
                        uries should out-front me, I'de out-stare them.
Pas runs vpon him, hee falls and lyes.
                     
                  
                  Exit. Pas.
                  
                     Enter Con
                           •
                        hylio in his Mistresses apparell.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     How well my Mistris Cosmaes clothes do fit me?
                     What pitty 'twas, I was not made a woman?
                     I thinke 
                           •
                         should haue made a pretty Nymph: ha?
                     I could haue beene a pittifull creature,
                     
                        And yet perhaps, a good vnhappy wench.
                     
                        Cosma by this hath met with her Armillus
                        
                           •
                        
                     
                     And sports her selfe: could I meete Fredocaldo,
                     
                     I should haue sport enough:
She stumbles at Fred.
                     
                     What Fredocaldo dead? cou
                           •
                        age, man.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     I had a fearefull dreame and scarce am waken.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Come shake off dreames, sleepe is not fit for louers,
                     Wee'l to the rocky caue.
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     My sunne? my fire?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     But Fredocaldo, can you thinke that fire
                     Can loue cold water, the sunne can frost desire?
                  
                  
                     Fred.
                     I tell thee fairest Cosma, those faire eyes
                     Bring backe my spring:
                     Wrong not thy selfe, deare loue, so faire a day
                     Cannot but make mid-winter turne to May.
                     Cold rhewms I feele not, no frost's lockt in this chest
                           •
                        
                     
                     Thy loue begets a summer in my brest.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Fie Fredocaldo:
                     Not in the open aire.
                  
                  
                     Ex
                           •
                        unt
                           •
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 5.
                  Armillus. Cosma
                  
                     Ar.
                     Wha
                           •
                         furies haunt this groue? is not this Cosma?
                     Yes: here again she comes
                           •
                         most blessed heauens,
Enter Cosma
                     
                     I see that yee are more gracious then Hell's spightfull.
                     Cosma?
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Armillus.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     My loue.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Sure thou hast done some cruell murder,
                     And the vnexplate ghost thus haunts thee.
                  
                  
                     Ar.
                     I neuer thought it, Cosma: rather some power of these woods,
                     Too enuious of my good hap, and iea
                           •
                        ous of thy fauor,
                     Thus crosses our desires
                           •
                         but if againe
                     He chance to interpose his horrid face,
                     
                        I'le rather dye, then leaue thy wisht embrace.

                           Enter Pa
                                 •
                               disguised.
                        
                     
                     All hell and furies haunt vs.

                           Exit A
                                 •
                              .
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Pa
                              •
                           .
                     
                     Well ouertaken, Nimph, start not, you are sure,
                     S
                           •
                        e I am your familiar.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Beshrew your heart for thus affrighting me.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Doe you not blush to cast your loue vpon a man,
                     Whose loue is as himselfe an alien? to thine owne
                     Thou mak'st thee strange, familiar to vnknowne.
                  
                  
                     Cos
                     P
                           •
                        sh, thou art foolish, did I euer binde thee to me
                     Only? why shouldst thou then confine me
                     To thy sole passion? so oft before
                     You men haue chang'd, that you can change no more:
                     From bad to worse, from worse, to worst of all:
                     There lie you now, and can no lower fall:
                     And as you wisht that we should neuer roue,
                     We pray as fast, that you at length could moue.
                     Cease then for shame to raile at womens ranging:
                     When men begin, women will leaue their changing.
                     Farewell.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Nay soft, I am dog well bitten,
                     And will not part so easily with my prey,
                     I haue not tasted venison many a day.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     I cannot well deny thee, 'tis thy right:
                     Thou well hast purchast it, this be thy right.
                  
                  
                     Exe
                           ••
                        t.
                  
               
               
                  Scen
                        •
                      6.
                  Conchilio.
                  
                     Con.
                     Ha, ha, he: this old dry stubble, how it crackes i'th' burning! alas poore saplesse oake: 'tis time 'twere down, I stayd till he was ready, all vnready, but when he 'gan to put on his spectacles, away slipt I: hee'l doe my mistris little hurt. Spectacles! hah, ha, he! now for my louing Lobster, this is his time; and if the Cyclops too doe keepe his promise, O what rare compound of mirth
                           •
                         I'le make, while the one with sha'me, the other with feare I'le take!
                     
                        The fish comes alreadie to the net.
Enter Cancrone, going backeward vpon her. He lookes ouer his shoulders.
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     To all I speake, but I tell no man,
                     Whether I loue Nymph or woman.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Tell not mee, but tell the rocks,
                     Not words must disciple you but knocks.
                     I am out of your debt for a rime.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I thinke shee knew my cue,
                     The charme begins to worke already.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I know not how this fishers hooke hath caught mee,
                     I euer for his rudenesse loue him: 'tis the badge of innocencie.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Somewhat rude if you will, but innocent in your face.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     O those glearing eyes that dart the beames,
                     The beames that drownd my heart with fierie streames.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Now to Cupids arrowe tree, and she sinks downe-right condoling; Cosma, I haue pitty on thee, but it beseemes a man of my confession, to haue a negligent care of his good reparation abroad in the world and else-where; I would be loth to be seene in my loue-worke, i'le mount the tree and scry the coast.
He goes vp the tree.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Stay not, but come againe thy selfe, sweete heart, to receiue me.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     O ho, here's bundance of people, bundance a lookers on, I dare not loue thee before them all, wee'l into the myrtle groue present.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Quickly returne, my loue, returne Cancrone my dearest.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Stand forth Cosma, and say on till thou come to that, I cry, I dye, I lye.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I spie him now approaching,
Enter Rimbombo.
What though he be all ragges in his limbs? what though his gesture taste of violence? we Nymphes, they say, like not such wooers worst.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Thou speakest of thy Rimbombo, that myrtle groues which loue the winding shores, deserue to bee to Venus consecrate, as faster friend
                           •
                         to louers, then the woods and caues of all the Mounts of Sicily, whose Nymph
                           •
                         do coyly shunne and mocke our troopes,
                  
                  
                     
                     Con.
                     you come somewhat before your time, Rimbombo,
                     
                     And Yet in loue preuention is no crime:
                     Louers may come before, not out of time.
                     And truly I wish, y'had come a little sooner.
                     
                        
                           •
                        uen now a mong
                           •
                        ell crabbed fisher swaine
                     Laid siege to this vnconquered fort.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     What wight of brauest blood by sea and land dares share with mee in Cosmaes loue? by Polypheme my sea-bred fire I vow, the sand on which he treads, is not so small, as shall this pestell make his pounded bones.
                  
                  
                     Con,
                     Nay now he treadeth not vpon these sands, but is fled vp to the hills, and shortly thence will of himselfe come tumbling downe to mee.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     I would he durst: I neuer yet but once did tast of fishers blood, tis iollie sweete: come fisher, this way or that way I am for you at both weapons, club or teeth: let's to the groue, see, euery mirtle tree bids warre to fishers peace, and ioy to mee. Why weepes my Cosma? Sweete, feare not that which thou desirest.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Sweete Cyclops, meanst thou to rauish mee?
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     O heauens thine owne appointed time and place, thine, owne sweete Cyclops, and can rauishment?—
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Why this know; wee Nymphs that long liue chast, and weare our girdle of virginity — but lo, Diana stops my tongue, shee bends her deadly bow, I dare not.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Speake on, here's none but trees, and thy tru
                           •
                        tie true Rimbombo.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     By that bright flame which like one only sunne giues day to'th spheare of thy maiesticke face, I thee adiure, that thou disclose to none this sacred mysterie.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Not: to my mother: no not in my dreame: say on
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Wee neither yeeld, nor take in loue delight,
                     Vntill our girdle fi
                           •
                        st be once vnplight
                     By louers hands, and then about his wast,
                     By our owne hands the same be tied fast.
                     Now all is out.
                  
                  
                     
                     Rim.
                     A pretty piece of work, my hands do their office nimbly
                     I haue vnfettered thee, come put this sweete yoke on mee.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Nay turne about, it must be tied contrarie to other girdles, iust behind. Stand neerer to mee, yet neere.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     As close as thou wilt, Cosma; I would your filthy fisher saw vs now, 't would make his teeth water.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Hang him stinking Lobster, he da
                           •
                        res not look vpon any of thy kinne: his haddocke eyes would start out of his head, if he should see but one haire of Rimbomboes head.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     How long wilt thou be tying mee?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     The more knots I tie, the faster will my loue be to you: but you'l be prating of this secret, when you come home among yo
                           •
                        r mounting Nymphs.
                     
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     If I doe, then ge
                           •
                        d mee: hast thou done?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I haue but three knots to tie: they are all true knots.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     When thou hast done, preethee come kisse me, Cosma,
                        Conchylio steales away, leauing him bound to the tree where Cancrone is.
I see thou art a pure virgin, thou neuer didst this office before, thou art no quicker at it. What Cosma? what? no Cosma! what a wooden wench? here's a true loue knot with a witnes. O faithlesse Cosma! O witlesse Rimbombo! O Nymph! O fishers! O shepheards! O Satyrs! O Cyclops!
                  
                  Enter Conchylio againe.
                  
                     Con.
                     Ha, ha ha: O loue! O wit! O tree! O girdle! O platterface!
                     O oyster eyes!
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Thou bitch, thou witch, thou spawne of a mermaid.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Thou AEtna, thou Chaos, thou Hell: nay tugge and tugge, my virginitie is tough and strong enough: O for, some Nymphs fishers or shepheards to baite this Orke. I'le out and call in some bandog: so ho, so ho, ho, ho.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     The knots are so many, the girdle so strong, and the tree stands so fast. O anger! O shame! here shee'll bring in all the country to laugh mee to death, hide yet thy face with some of these lower boughs.
                  
                  Enter Conchylio.
                  
                     Con.
                     So ho, so ho: O dogged fortune! not one Nymph to be found not one feate fisher! not one: but that feating fisher that

is readie to wing his sea token net on the Cyclops blockhead.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Away thou monstrous woman, oh, oh
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Away thou monstrous mans ah ha hey.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     How now! what's that? what, haue I another witnes of my folly? what gobbet of mans flesh grows
                           •
                         vpon this tree?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Ile haue a graft of this mi
                           •
                        tle tree, it beares fine loue wormes, on the s
                           •
                        ocke, a maggot wou'd vp in a Cobweb, on the bough a barnacle, which ere long will fall and turne to a goose: now Cupids gosling, now on your bare-head knee, goe begge at Cupids doore.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Ah cursed Cupid
                        
                           •
                         i'le no more of thy seruice, I had rather fight with nine Orkes, ha, hei, au.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Come downe thou fished bit; my mouth shall catch thee. Gentle C
                              •
                           sma, i'le forgiue thee all, &amp; loue thee yet, if thou wilt helpe to reach my walking sticke; i'le make my young Orke-ketcher beleeue he shall bee his grandsires heire.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Your staffe? marry and shalt, it's a pretty pole to bang those boughes withall, and when thou doest it, doe but gape, and that rotten plumme will fall into thy mouth.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay, I know of old I should be deuoured.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Thy staffe, Rimbombo, is not for a weak Nymph to lift.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Yet a little more to this hand: Oh oh, my shoulder's thunderstrook!
                           While Rimbombo reaches for his staffe, Cancrone leapes on's backe, and lies on the ground.
                         O coward Ioue, to strike me on the backe, bu
                           •
                         wast our fisher lubber? is he escap't our hands?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     VVhy Cancrone, rise, i'le helpe thee.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Good Charon carry me ouer gently, my bones are sore, and your boate side so hard.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Giue me thy hand, i'le waft thee.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I tell thee Charon, I haue nothing to giue thee for ferriage, i'le helpe to row, I haue beene a poore fisher while I liu'd
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     I would I were there too, but that I should sinke Charons boate with a tree at my backe.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     VVhy valorous Cancron
                              •
                           , view thy selfe and mee thy captiue Cosma, we are conquerours, behold our enemies in fetters fast bound.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Am I aliue indeede? me thought this legge hung out

of Charons boate i'th' water, did I tie the Ork
                           •
                         there; Cancro
                              ••
                           
                         Come captain, let's goe triumphing to the temple.
rises vp.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Nay, the Ork's dead and buried, this is the second fatall for the Cyclops.
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Is he safe? i'le make side-slops on him. I lay studying how to deale with him vpon equall tearmes: come if thou darest, thou sea-bred brat of Polyphemes sine, you that would licke your lips at sweete fishers blood! sweete fishers blood! marke that Cosma: I hope you thinke so too.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Sweete fisher, I will turne thy net maker if thou wilt vndoe me.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     No, it shall nere be said that I was the vndoing of any man by net-making, and besides, I haue forsworne the mudd
                           •
                        e trade.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     
                        Cancrone
                              •
                           
                         wher's thy spirit? this is that pocketted vp thy grandsire in his wide intrailes.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Me thought, when I was on the tree
                           •
                         his breath smel
                           •
                         of fish, my stomacke euen foam'd at him. Now then, sir Bompelo, as that Orke mouth of thine did crumme thy por
                           •
                        idge with my grandsires braines, and then gaue him his deaths wound too, so will I first mince out thy scald-pate bones, and giue thy flesh to a fishers boy for haddocks meate, &amp; then, O th
                           •
                        n I will ge
                           •
                        d thee, that thou neuer shalt run rutting after the Nymphs. How lik'st thou this
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     Shame and scorne make me silent.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Nay, I will tell thee fitter vengeanc
                           •
                        , vse him, as sage Vlysses did his father Polypheme.
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     That same Fool
                              •
                           shes had 
                           •
                         pole-cat
                           •
                         head, I 
                           ••
                        eane to mitigate him: he was something, as it wa
                           •
                        e about branding a huge stone in a caue, in a goate skinne with Polypheme
                        
                           •
                         when the fire-brand was asleepe.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I, I, in the caue 
                           •
                        e br
                           •
                        ded ou
                           •
                         
                        Polyph
                              •
                           mes eye, when he was asleepe, and you must imitate him 
                           •
                        here 
                           〈◊〉
                         his owne staffe, and make it an ex
                           ••
                        guisher fo
                           •
                         that 
                           〈◊〉
                         la
                           •
                        pe.
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     This sport I like worst of all: helpe, gods of the woods.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I'le blow the coale while you take your 
                           〈◊〉
                        , but will your farginity hold him fast?
                  
                  
                     
                     Con.
                     I warrant you it has been tried, come be thou my rest, i'le tilt on thy shoulders.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Raunt tara, raunt taunt: &amp;
Cancrone fals, and his dagger from him in the Cyclops reach.
I shall make you stumble, let me Come hindermost.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     O your Whineyeard, the enemy hath seazd on't.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     'Tis no matter, hee'l hardly make it fly out of the Eel
                           •
                        
                        skinne, it hath seene no sunne this fiue quarters of a yeere I am sure.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     I hope the salt breath of the sea hath seald it vp.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     O Cosma, 'tis out, let vs out too.
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     O Cancrone, loe thy Cosma, Cupid, and Co
                              •
                           chilio. Cyclops, blame not this my supposed sexe, no Nymph, but lad hath caught thee in this snare.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     Rim.
                     The greater shame, and fouler scorne to me.
                     Vp to the hill, Rimbombo flye this shore,
                     And neuer deale with fisher-Nymph-lad more.
Exit.
                     
                  
                  
                     CHORVS,
                     This his wiues quicke 
                           •
                        ate lamenting,
                     Orp
                           •
                        hus sate his soule tormenting:
                     While the speedy wood came running,
                     And riuers stood to heare his cunning
                           •
                        
                     
                     The hares ran with the dogs along,
                     Not from the dogs, but to his song:
                     But when all his verses turning,
                     Onely fram'd his poore hearts burning:
                     Of the higher powers complaining,
                     Downe he went to hell disdaining:
                     There his siluer Lute-strings hitting,
                     And his potent verses fitting:
                     All the sweets that ere 
                           •
                        e tooke
                     From his sacred mothers brooke:
                     What his double sorrow giues him
                           •
                        
                     
                     
                        And loue that doubly double grieues him:
                     There he spends to mooue deafe hell,
                     Ch
                           •
                        rming Deuils with his spell:
                     And 
                           •
                        ith sweetest asking leau
                           •
                        
                     
                     Does the Lord of ghosts deceaue.
                     Caron amaz'd his boate foreslowes,
                     While the boate, the sculler rowes,
                     And of it selfe to'th' shoare d
                           •
                        th floate,
                     
                        
                           ••
                        ipping on the dancing moate.
                     The t
                           •
                        reeheaded Porter preast to heare,
                     Prickt vp his thrice double 
                           •
                        are,
                     The Furies, plague
                           •
                         for Guilt vp-heaping,
                     Now as guilty, fell a weeping:
                     Ixion, though his wheele stood still,
                     Still was wrapt with Musickes skill.
                     Tantale might haue eaten now,
                     The fruite as still as was the bough,
                     But he foole no longer fearing,
                     Staru'd his tast to feede his hearing.
                     Thus since loue hath wonne the field,
                     Heauen and Hell, to Earth must yeeld,
                     Blest soule that dyest in loues sweete sound,
                     That l
                           •
                        st in loue in loue art found.
                     If but a true-loues ioy thou once doe proue,
                     Thou wilt not loue to liue, vnlesse thou liue to lou
                           •
                        .
                  
               
            
            
               Act. 5.
               
                  Scen. 1.
                  Enter Alcippus and Thalander with a torch.
                  
                     Tha.
                     TEll me, Al
                              •
                           ipp
                              ••
                           , is it day or night?
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     The light you beare, shews you there is no light.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     This is none
                           •
                         light was light in her eyes,
                     In them it liu'd, put out with them it dies.
                     The sunne is quench't.
                  
                  
                     
                     Al.
                     Yet soone will shine againe.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Not possible! heauens light will euer plaine.
                     When her two liuing stars can sinke and die,
                     How can the sunne dreame immortality?
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     Sir, if your to mee, or mine to you, might giue me priuiledge, I faine would tell you, that this too fixed loue seemes ra
                           •
                        her do
                           •
                        ing.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     
                        Alcippus, didst thou euer loue?
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     I thinke sir neuer.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     I thinke so too, nor canst know what loue is.
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     Yet this I know, loue still is of the fairest,
                     Fond then the loue, that loues the withered,
                     But madnesse seemes to dote vpon the dead.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     True, true, Alcippus, loue is of the fairest,
                     And therefore neuer tyed vnto the body:
                     Which if compared vnto the mindes faire graces,
                     Seemes like the blocke that Lunaes face defaces.
                     But grounded on the mind, whose vertuous parts.
                     And liuing beauties are loues surest darts,
                     Which makes me now as freely loue as euer
                           •
                        
                     
                     Her vertue and my loue decayeth neuer.
                     Seest thou this rocke, Alcippus? tis a temple,
                     
                        Olindaes temple! 'tis a sacred shrine,
                     Where vertue, beauty, and what ere diuine,
                     Are to be worshipt, prethee friend now leaue me,
                     Here is an Altar, I must sacrifice.
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     If you will leaue your griefe.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     I will, I will:
                     Indeede I will; leaue me: griefs ebbe growes lowe,
                     When priuate heart
                           •
                         th' eye-bankes ouerflow.
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     I will retire, not leaue him: well, I feare,
                     When two such flood-streams meet, loue and despaire.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Thou blessed Altar, take these worthlesse offring
                           •
                        ,
                     The corral's once more drown'd in brine of sorrow,
                     These pearly shells, which dayly shall bee fild
                     VVith my hearts water, through my eyes distild.
                     
                        You corralls, whose fresh beauti
                           •
                        s are a shadow
                     O
                           •
                         her sweete blushes, 
                           •
                        ell her liuing graces,
                     Though now as you pluckt from their natiue places,
                     Are yet as you from your first seate remou'd,
                     He
                           •
                        e fresher shining then when first I lou'd.
                     Thou rocke, that in thy blest armes doest infold her,
                     Witnes my heart as firme as you do hold her.
                     And now goodnight thou set sunne beauties, neuer,
                     Neuer more to be seene, goodnight for euer,
                     Thou siluer forehead and thou golden haire,
                     My best, my onely treasure when you were,
                     You snowy plaines, and you faire modest dies,
                     You liuing stars, but now two quenched lights,
                     Whose fall, heauens stars with feared ruine frights.
                     You eyebrowes, which like Rainbowes two appeare;
                     A miracle, Rainebowes on skie so cleare.
                     And all you vnseene beauties sof
                           •
                        ly rest,
                     Sleepe, quiet sleepe you in this stony chest,
                     I cannot long; I will not long be from you,
                     Shortly i'le come and in this rockie bed
                     Slumber with my Olinda, with Olinda
                     
                     I'le sleepe my fil
                           ••
                        meane time as neere as may be,
                     Here rest mine eyes, rest close by your Olinda.
                     
                     He lies downe by the rocke.
                     Harke, harke; Arion, thou choice Musician,
                     
                     Sing mee a note that may awake pale death,
                     Such as may moue deafe Hell
                           •
                         and Stygian Io
                              •
                           e,
                     
                     Such as once Orpheus —O I am idle, idle:
                     Sleep, sleep, mine eyes, this short releasement take you,
                     Sleepe, sleepe for euer; neuer more awake you.
                     Her face your obiect neuer more shall be,
                     Sleepe then, vaine eyes, why should you wish to see?
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scen. 2.
                  
                     The Rocke opens: Enter Olinda led by Glaucus and Cir
                           •
                        e: they retire leauing Olinda.
                  
                  Song.
                  
                     Olin.
                     Thou worthie
                           •
                        t daughter of the greatest light,
                     Most powerfull Circe, and thon honour'd Glaucus,
                     
                     What dutie a poore fisher maid may giue you,
                     In thankes, and vowes, and holy offerings,
                     Shall still be ready at your sacred altars.
                     
                        Thalander, now to thee, what sacrifice?
                     What offerings may appease thy wronged loue?
                     What haue I but my selfe? ah worthlesse prize
                     Of such, so tryed, and so vnmou'd a faith.
                     Ah, could I spend my body, weare my soule,
                     And then resume another soule and body,
                     And then consume that soule and body for thee,
                     All would not pay the vse of halfe my debt.
                     How pale he lookes, how strangely alter'd!
                     Is he not dead? no, no, his pulse is quicke,
                     His heart is strong, and rising, in his heate,
                     Threatens with strokes, my churlish hand to beate:
                     Nature, how couldst in one so firmely tie
                     Perpetuall motion to fixt constancy?
                     How can this wonder fall in Notion,
                     A heart vnmou'd, yet still in motion!
                     Alas he weepes, I hope his griefe and feares
                     Swimme fast away in those sad streaming teares.
                     Th'ast mourn'd enough, more iustly may I weepe,
                     Leaue me thy teares, rest thou and sweetely sleepe.
                  
                  Thalander starts vp.
                  
                     Tha.
                     
                        Morpheus, one more such dreame shall buy me.
                     
                        Where, where art, Olinda? whither, whither flyest thou?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Nay whither flies Thalander? here's Olinda:
                     Tell mee why wak'd the substance thou eschewest
                           •
                        
                     
                     Whose shadowe in a dreame thou gladly viewest.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Thou fairest shadow of a Nymph more faire,
                     
                        
                           •
                        eath yet I see cannot thy light impaire.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Thou dreamest still Thalander!
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Ah too too true;
                     For such a sight wake shall I neuer viewe.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     I liue.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Would I were dead on that condition.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     So would not I: beleeue me friend, I liue.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Could I beleeue it, I were happie.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     If mee thou wilt not, trust thy sence, thy eyes.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     They saw thee dead, how shall I trust my eie,
                     Which either now or then did vowch a lie?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Credit thy touch.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Then like a dreame thou'lt flie,
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Thou flyest, thou art the shadow loue not I:
                     
                        Thalander, take this, tis thine for euer,
                     Nothing but death, nor death this knot shall seuer.
                  
                  Enter Alcippus.
                  
                     Al.
                     How is this! haue you learnt, haue you learnt your mother Circes art to raise the dead? wonder? thinke shee liues.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     What says Thalander? does he yet beleeue mee?
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     If thou art dead, faire hand, how doest reuiue mee?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     
                        Thalander, heart and hand had now beene cold but for, Glaucilla, she preuenting Cosma, temperd the poysonous viall, changing death for sleepe, so gaue mee life, thee loue.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     
                        Alcippus, art thou there? thou art my freind I prethee tell mee true, true Alcippus! doest thou not see Olinda?
                     
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     I see her in your hand.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Art sure tis she? tell me, are wee aliue?
                     Art sure we wake? are we not both mistaken?
                     If now I sleepe, O let me neuer waken.
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     If you would surely know, trie if shee breathe,
                  
                  
                     
                     Tha.
                     Thy hand liues: doe thy lips liue too Olinda!
                     
                        Alcippus, shee liues and breathes, Al
                              •
                           ippus:
                     And with that sugred bread my heart both fir'd,
                     And life and loue with thousand ioyes inspir'd.
                     Ah my Olinda.
                     
                  
                  
                     Olind.
                     My deare, my deare Thalander.
                     
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Ist possible thou liu'st? ist sure I hold thee?
                     These happy armes shall neuer more vnfold thee.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     Tell mee, my loue, canst thou such wrongs forgiue mee?
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     My ioy, my soule.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     I neuer more will grieue you.
                     Canst thou forget my hate, my former blindnes?
                     If not, boldly reuenge my rash vnkindnes.
                     Pierce this vile heart my soules vngratefull center,
                     Pierce with thy dart where loues dart could not enter.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     For thy defence my hand shall still attend thee,
                     My hand and heart, but neuer to offend thee:
                     The only penance that I enioyne thee euer,
                     Is that wee liue and loue and ioy together.
                     Thinke not my hand will sacriledge commit,
                     To breake this temple where all Graces sit.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     True, true my loue, tis vow'd a temple now,
                     Where euer shall be worshipt loue and thou.
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     You happie paire, since Cosma's spight's defeated,
                     And Magoe's charmes
                           •
                         and death by loue is cheated,
                     Why stand you here? tis time from hence to moue:
                     This was the bedde of death, and not of loue.
                     Death hath his part of night, loue challengeth
                     The rest, loue claimes the night as well as death.
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     What sayes my loue?
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     What my Thalander, euer
                     With thee to life or death, but from thee neuer.
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     This halfe perswades mee to become a louer.

                           Exe
                                 •
                              nt.
                        
                     
                     Where better could her loue then here haue neasted?
                     Or he his thoughts more daintily haue feasted?
                  
                  Manet Alcippus.
               
               
                  
                  Scen. 3.
                  Enter Tyrinthus and Gryphus.
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Knowst thou Perindus sister, or Olinda?
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     I know them both sir.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Liue they yet and breathe?
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     They liue and now most happy.
Exit Alcippus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Thou mak'st me happy, in thy happy newes.
                     All thankes yee heauenly powers, when I forget
                     Your goodnesse in my childrens life and safety,
                     Let heauen forget both me and mine for euer.
                     
                        Gryphus, backe to our shippe, and fetch mee thence
                     The vestments vowd to Neptune, and the chest,
                     Wherein I lockt my other offerings.
Exit Gryphus.
                     
                     This rocke my heart prefers before a palace.
                     Fond men that haue enough yet seeke for more,
                     I thought by traffique to encrease my store,
                     And striuing to augment this carefull pelfe,
                     I lost my goods, my liberty, my selfe:
                     Taken by Persians on the Graecian seas,
                     So I my captaine and the King did please,
                     Soone was I loosed from my slauish band,
                     And straight preferd to haue a large command,
                     There haue I now consum'd these thrice 
                           •
                        iue summers,
                     There might I haue liu'd long in wealth and honour,
                     But ah thou little home, how in thy want
                     The world so spacious, yet seemes too too scant
                           •
                        
                     
                     At my departure hence I left two infants,
                     
                        Perindus and Olinda, the boy some eyght,
                     The girle but two yeeres old, t
                           •
                        eir mother dead,
                     Who giuing life to'th'girle, so tooke her death,
                     And left her owne, to giue h
                           ••
                         in
                           •
                        ant b
                           ••
                        ath.
                     Great Ioue and Neptune, I will keepe my vowes,
                     Seeing my Children liue, two chosen bulls,
                     
                        With mirtle crownd, and Oake leaues laid with gold,
                     Shall fall vpon your altars.
                  
                  Enter Pas.
                  
                     Pas.
                     You sacred vertues, truth and spotlesse fayth,
                     Where will you liue, if not in such a Nymph?
                     Whose brest will you now seeke? what mansion?
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     My trembling heart doth some great ill diuine,
                     And tels me, euery griefe and feare is mine.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     VVhere now can vnsuspected friendship rest?
                     If treachery possesse so faire a brest.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Fishers what newes?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Sir, little as concernes you.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Pray heauens it doe not.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Your habit speakes a stranger,
                     And yet me thinkes, I somewhat else haue 
                           •
                        eene,
                     Some lineaments of that face: are you Tyrinthus?
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     The same.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     O cruell heauens I could you finde
                     No other time, to giue him backe his country?
                     If thus you giue, happy whom you deny,
                     The greater good, the greater iniury:
                     Thy onely daughter
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Is dead.
Tyrinthus falls.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     I should haue sayd so. Alas, he falls.
                     
                        Tyrinthus, what, one blow thus strike thee vnder fortunes feete?
                     How loth his life returnes!
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     How well I had forgot my griefe,
                     And found my rest, with losse of restlesse life!
                     Thou much hast wrong'd me, fisher, 'tis no loue,
                     Death from his iust possession to remoue:
                     Heauens, ye haue thankes for both, yet one you slue,
                     Giue backe halfe of thy thankes, take but your due:
                     I owe you nothing for Olinda, nothing.
                     Ah poore Olinda
                              •
                           
                         I shall neuer more,
                     Neuer more see thee: thy father must lament thee,
                     
                        Thy father, wh
                           •
                         in death should long preuent thee,
                     How long since died shee?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     With the last sunne she fell.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Sure heauens, ye mocke me: alas, what victo
                           •
                        y?
                     What triumph in an old mans misery?
                     VVhen you haue wonne, what conquest, that you slue
                     A wretch that hated his life as much as you?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Sir, you forget your selfe: to warre with heauen,
                     Is no lesse fond, then dangerous
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Tell me fisher, haue you a child?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     No sir.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     No maruell then
                     Thou blam'st my griefe, of which thou hast no 
                           •
                        ence:
                     First lose a child, then blame my patience.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     If thou be grieu'd, this is no way to ease it,
                     Sooner we anger heauen, then thus appease it.
                  
                  
                     
                        T
                              •
                           y.
                     
                     But when the heart such weight of sorrow beares,
                     It speakes from what it feeles, and what it feares.
                     Died she by a naturall, or by violent meanes?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Nature refuses an office so vnnaturall.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Hard fate, most fitly were you women made:
                     Since fate vnmercifull, vnmoued stands,
                     VVell was lifes distaffe put in womens hands.
                     Kild by a man?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     No man was so vnnaturall.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     A woman!
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Yes.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Fit instrument of women: what was the weapon?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     The cowards weapon, poyson.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Canst tell the murderers name?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Her name Glaucilla:
                     A Nymph thought absolute, though now infected,
                     That heauen it selfe might sooner bee suspected.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Tell me the circumstance.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     'Twill but more grieue you.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     True, but 'tis pitty in vnhelpt distresse,
                     
                        Condemned soules with all the weight to presse.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     
                        Olinda this last night complain'd to Cosma,
                     
                     (A Nymph which lately came from faire Messena)
                     That this Glaucillaes powerfull charmes had fir'd her,
                     And with Thalanders loue now dead, inspir'd her
                     With such a feeling griefe, her griefe lamenting,
                     That she, to helpe so desperate loue consenting,
                     Gaue her a water which she oft did proue,
                     Wo
                           •
                        ld eyther quench or ease the paines of loue,
                     Which Cosma swore, the other nere denyed.
                     
                        Glaucilla chang'd, Olinda dranke a
                           •
                        d dyed.
                     
                        Dicaeus hearing this —
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Liues then Dicaeus?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     As well and iust as euer.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     His life doth somewhat mend
                     My childs sad death, after a child, a friend.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     
                        Dicaeus by this euidence condemnes her
                     By 'th' law, from that high rocke to fall, and she
                     With smiling welcom'd death, and quietly
                     Steal'd to the rocke from whence shee must be cast.
                     Wonder so heauie guilt should flye so fast!
                     She led her leaders to that deepe descending,
                     The guilty drawes the guiltlesse to their ending:
                     And thus I left them, and with her iust Dicaeus,
                     
                     To see her execution, who goes not from her,
                     Till from the rocke, in seas she leaue her breath,
                     Die must she as she kild, water her crime and death.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Ah my poore Olinda! had I seene thee yet
                     And clos'd thine eyes, alas my poore Olinda!
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     This griefe is vaine and can no more reuiue her, you lose your teares.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     When that I hold most deare is euer lost, poore losse to lose a teare.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Your sonne striues, the good which heau'n bereaues you,
                     You quickly see, but see not what it leaues you.
                  
                  
                     
                     Tyr.
                     Art sure he liues?
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     Two houres since, sad I left him,
                     But safe.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     What chances happen in an houre?
                     By this he may be dead and buried.
                     But yet Perindus, if thou liuing be,
                     My halfe ioy liues, my halfe ioy dies in thee.
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 2.
                  
                     Enter Cancrone and Scrocca bound: Nomicus 
                           •
                        he Priest.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Ah Scrocca, thou hast often heard me say, it would be my lucke to be deuoured; and to tell thee true, I euer fear'd those Cyclops most; I neuer had any minde to them.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Why Cancrone, this is the slauery on't, had wee beene Master fishers, we should neuer haue beene troubled to climbe vp these Mountaines, wee should neuer haue beene cast to our old acquaintance the fish.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Fisher, knowst thou these men?
                  
                  
                     Pas
                     I know the men, but not their meaning.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     That would neuer haue angred me, thou knowst wee haue fed vpon fish this many yeere, and for vs to haue made them one merry meale, had beene but the signe of a thankefull na
                           •
                        ure, but ah those C
                              •
                           clops, clops, clops. Scro
                              •
                           ca, I cannot digest them.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     I feare they will 
                           •
                        gest vs well enough.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     And yet I care not much if I were sure to bee eaten vp by that Cyclops that ate vp my grandsire, for then I might haue some hope to see the good old man once againe before I die.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     I care not whose hands I fall into, I'me sure hee shall haue no sweete bitte of mee now; nothing grieues mee, but that hauing done but one good deede in all my life, I must die for that.
                  
                  
                     
                     Nom.
                     Thou foolish fisher, thinkst it good to stop
                     The course of iustice, and breake her sword, the Law?
                     By Law thou li
                           •
                        'st: hee iustly death deserues,
                     VVho that destroyes, which him and his preserues.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Are not these my old men, Scrocca and Cancrone?
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     VVell sir, you may say what you will, but if wee liue by the Law, how commeth it to passe, that we must die by the Law?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Mee thinks I see how busie Rimronce will bee about me: he surely will be vpon my backe, for my being vpon his, a while a goe.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Nay Cancrone, thou diest for sauing thy master too.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Ay me, my sonne?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I haue no minde to climbe these Mountaines, I begin to bee short-winded already, I shall neuer hold out; had I thought it would haue come to this, I would haue bene vilely tempted to ha let my Master drowne quickly.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     What, man? thou could'st neuer haue done thy Master better seruice then to dye for him, nay, if Perindus liue, I care not.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     
                        Perindus? I can hold no longer, friend, who is thy Master? why art thou manacled?
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     Mantled hither! marry this Priest hath mantled vs for sauing our Master Perindus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Ay me, my sonne.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Vds fish, old Master, where haue you beene this 20 yeeres and more;
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     
                        Tyrinthus! at such a time! sir, your arriuall is eyther 
                           •
                        ery happy, or else most haplesse, eyther to see, or else preuent a danger.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Priest, how is my Perindus?
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Doom'd to die.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     What is the cause?
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     His will.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     Who could perswade him?
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     She who most stroue to hinder and disswade him.
                  
                  
                     
                     Tyr.
                     What had he done?
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     That which deserues all li
                           •
                        e and loue.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     How fine the heauens powers can sorrowe
                           •
                         frame!
                     The fates will play, and make my woe their g
                           •
                        me.
                     VVhere is he?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Safe enough I warrant you, get's leaue of the Priest, master, and wee'l goe fetch him.
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     We caught him out of the water.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     O, he had supt a bundance of 
                           •
                        ait porri
                           •
                        ge!
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     And brought him to the shippe where the mariners keepe him.
                  
                  
                     Tyr.
                     VVhy stand I idle here! O to the shore i'le fly,
                     And eyther with him liue, or for him die.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Master, master, master.
Exit Tyrinchus.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Pa
                              •
                           .
                     
                     Ile follow him: nature can doe no lesse
                     Then eyther helpe, or pitty such distresse.

                           Exit Pa
                                 •
                              .
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay if you goe too, then farewell all,
                     Farewell ye rockes, farewell to thee O loue,
                     You louely rockes, you hard and rocky loue.
                     Nay I shall turne swaine presently and sing my finall song.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     I maruell what it is that stayes Dicaus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     Marry let him stay till I send for him, the Cyclops shall want their breakefast this month.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Here I must stay for him.
                  
               
               
                  Scen. 5.
                  Enter Cosma.
                  
                     Cos.
                     Faine would I know how my gin
                           •
                        e thriues and prospers. Ol
                              •
                           nda is fast, and by my disamour hath quencht her loue with death: if now Glaucilla bee taken in that snare, then am I cunning: well may I proue a fisher, who haue tooke too maides so soone with one selfe baite and hooke. Is not that Nomicus? I shall learne of him. Nomicus?
                  
                  
                     
                     Nom.
                     Who Cosm
                              •
                           
                        ?
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Why are these fishers bound?
                  
                  
                     Con.
                     For you.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     For mee?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I for you, had not you cus'd Glaucilla, shee had not bene condemnd: if shee had not beene condemnd, Perindus would not haue died for her: if he would not haue died for her, he had not fallen from the rocke: had he not fallen from the rocke, we had not sau'd him: if wee had not sau'd him, wee had not beene bound: were wee not bound, wee would showe a faire payre of heeles,
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     What talks this foole? Perindus falne from the rocke!
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Hast thou not heard then of Perindus faith and fal
                           •
                        ?
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     No, not a word; but faine would heare.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     And shalt: my tongue is as ready as thy eare; Meane while leade these away, soone as Dicaeus returnes, I'le ouertake you.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I prethee Mr Priest, let mee craue one fauour; that I may ha
                           •
                        e an Epitaph for mee in Neptunes church porch, Ile neuer goe farther.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Heres no time for Epitaphs, away.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay, tis soone done, Ile trouble neuer a poet of them all,
I haue it already.

                           Cancrone valorous and kind, where art thou?
                           Cancrone too kind and valorous to liue,
                           Ingulft in Cyclops guts. Readers, why start you?
                           His life for his master he did freely giue.
                        
                     
                     Vngratefull Sicelie that want'st his bones,
                     Instead of members keeping his memorie in stones.
                     Short and sweete, Mr 
                        Priest.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scr.
                     
                        Cancrone, this is a land voyage, you must leade the way.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     But when wee saile downe the Cyclops throat, Ile giu
                           •
                         you the preeminence.
Exeunt.
                     
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     After that haplesse Nymph had heard her doome,
                     As shee was led to'th' rocke, i'th' middle way,
                     
                        Perindus flying fast, calls out, Stay:
                     And for he thought his feete too slowly bore him,
                     
                        Before he came, he sent his voyce before.
                     Stay, stay, Dicaeus, th'art a man, I see,
                     And well mayst erre heauens not more pure then she.
                     Yet since the doome i
                           •
                         past i'le, pawne my breath,
                     And make your fact 
                           ••
                        sse hanious by my death:
                     I'le lose he
                           •
                         life in me, and she shall spend
                     My life in her, so both shall better 
                           •
                        nd.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     This was no ill newes to the Nymph.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Yes, yes: then first she thought her selfe condemnd,
                     Death in him shee fear'd and in her 
                           •
                        elfe contemnd.
                     That law it selfe (says shee) should suffer death,
                     Which one condemnes, another punnisheth.
                     True, sayes Perindus, my life, my all's in thee,
                     When thou offendst, why shouldst thou punish me?
                     But briefe to giue their words in short contracted,
                     VVas neuer part of loue more louely acted:
                     Both loath to liue, and both contend to die,
                     VVhere onely death stroue for the victory.
                     Meane time I could but weepe, nor I alone,
                     That two such loues should die, not liue in one.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Their spotlesse fayth's a cristall, where I see
                     Too late my cancred ha
                           •
                        es deformity.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     At length the law it selfe decides the strife,
                     That he with losse of his might buy her life.
                     Then and but then 
                           •
                        he, wept, and to preuent him,
                     Downe fell shee with a deadly looke and eye,
                     Acting the prologue of his tragedy,
                     And wak'd againe, she 'gan to chide and raue,
                     And vowes to liue no further then his graue;
                     VVhile he with cheerfull steps the rockes asce
                           •
                        ding:
                     Fearelesse beholds his death, that steepe descending,
                     And boldly standing on the vtmost b
                           •
                        owe,
                     Thus sp
                           •
                        ke:
                     Poore life, I neuer knew thy worth till now,
                     How thou art oue
                           •
                         valewed to pay
                     Her life with thine, gold with base alcumy.
                  
                  
                     
                     Cos.
                     Iust, iust, you heauens, I haue set a gin
                     For them, and now my selfe the first am in.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Then turning to his loue, thus spake his last:
                     Farewell Glaucilla, liue and in thy brest
                     As in a heauen my loue and life shall rest:
                     Seeke not by death thy selfe from griefe to free,
                     Remember now Perindus liues in thee.
                     Cherish my hear
                           •
                        , which in thy heart doth lye,
                     For whilst thou liu'st, Perindus cannot dye:
                     So leapt he lightly from the cloudy rocke.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Is hee then dead?
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     No: for the guilty 
                           •
                        ea
                     With soft embraces wrapt his limbes;
                     It seemes the waues moou'd with Sympathy,
                     Would teach vnhumane men humanity.
                     Though they could not preuent, would ease his fall;
                     And not consenting to his pious death,
                     Restor'd him vp againe to aire and breath:
                     Briefly, those two his seruants not regarding,
                     
                        Dicaeus threatning voyce, and iust awarding,
                     With him tooke vp his guilt, and to a shippe
                     That rides in the hauen safe conuayd him, there
                     They left him now reuiu'd, themselues were taken
                     And as the law commands, were doom'd to suffer
                     The death of sla
                           •
                        es: both to be strongly bound,
                     And in those hils left to the greedy Cyclops:
                     And now the stay is onely in Dicaeus,
                     
                     At whose returne they suffer, iust they dye,
                     Who loue their master more then equity.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     O lawlesse loue! this soule offence,
                     Which when it prosperd, pleasd my rauish't sence:
                     With what a drie aspect, what horrid sight,
                     Now done, 
                           •
                        t fils my 
                           •
                        oule with guilty fright,
                     Who ere thou art, if in t
                           •
                        y spotlesse brest,
                     Thy vndefiled thoughts doe quiet rest:
                     
                        Wake them not, and let no blood-hound with thee dwell,
                     These murthering thoughts are like the mouth of hell,
                     Into whose yawning 'tis more easie neuer
                     To fall, then falne, to cease from falling euer.
                  
                  Enter Pas.
                  
                     Pas.
                     
                        Nomicus, thou now mayst let thy prisoners free,
                     
                        Thalander to Olinda now reuiu'd,
                     
                        Perindus to Glaucilla are to be married,
                     And all are brought along with singing,
                     
                        Hymen the shores, Hymen the ecchoes ringing.
                     
                        Nomicus, seest thou this Nymph? ah couldst thou thinke
                     That treason, enuy, murder, spight and hell,
                     All hell it selfe in such a heauen could dwell?
                     This is the knot of all these sorrowes; Cosma,
                     
                     If not for shame, why yet for spight or fashion,
                     For womans fashion let some teares bee spilt:
                     A sea of weeping will not wash thy guilt.
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Great nature, that hast made a stone descry
                     Twixt mean
                           •
                        r natures, checking baser metalls,
                     Which proudly counterfeit the purer gold,
                     Why hast thou left the soule of man no touch-stone,
                     To iudge dissemblance, and descry proud vice,
                     Which with false colours seemes more vertuous
                     Then vertues selfe? like to some cunning workeman,
                     Who frames a shape in such a forme of stature,
                     That oft he excells by imitating nature.
                     He that should looke vpon this Nymphs sweete ey
                           ••
                        
                     
                     Would vow't a temple sworne to purity.
                  
                  
                     Pas.
                     If murder rest in such a louely grace,
                     Here do I vow neuer to trust a face.
                     Shall I call backe your Prisoners?
                  
                  
                     Nom.
                     Prethee doe
                           •
                        
                     
                     Our nets, boates, oares, and hookes shall now goe play,
                     For heauen hath sworne to make this holy day.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scen. 6.
                  Enter Dicaeus, Tyrinthus, Thalander, Olinda, Perindus, Glaucillae, Alcippus, Chorus.
                  
                     Song.
                     Hymen, Hymen, come safe on, Hymen.
                     That I loue for euer constant stands,
                     Where hearts are tied before the hands,
                     Where faire vertue marries beauty,
                     And affection pleads for duty:
                     Hymen, Hymen, come safe on Hymen.
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     You honourd paire of fishers, see where your loue,
                     So full of constant triall now hath brought you,
                     Se
                           •
                        , blessed soules, through so many teares,
                     Turnings, despaires, impossibilities,
                     Your loue is now most safe arriu'd: Thalander,
                     
                     Is this the Nymph, whom heauen and angry hell,
                     Her cold desires, and colder death it selfe
                     Would haue deuoured from thy deseruing loue?
                     
                        Thalander, these hands are thine, that heauenly face,
                     Those starrie eyes, those roses and that grace,
                     Those corrall lips, and that vnknowne brest,
                     And all the hidden riches of the rest:
                     They all are thine, thine is the faire Olinda.
                     
                     Yet thou, as thou wast wont, all sad and heauy
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Tha.
                     Blame me not, friend: for yet I seeme forsaken
                     And doubt I sleepe, and feare still to be waken.
                  
                  Enter Pas, with Cancrone and Scrocca.
                  
                     Cos.
                     Now is the time of pardon. Ye happie maids,
                     Your loue in spight of all tempestuous seas,
                     Is safe arriu'd, and harbors in his ease,
                     
                        And all those stormes haue got but this at last,
                     To sweeten present ioyes with sorrowes past.
                     Blessed Olinda, thou hast got a loue
                     Equall to heauen, and next to highest Ioue.
                     
                     
                        Glaucilla, thy losse thou now dost full recouer.
                     Ah you haue found (too seldome found) a louer.
                     Then doe not her too rigorously reproue,
                     For louing those whom you yet better loue.
                  
                  
                     Olin.
                     For vs, we iudge not of your hard intent,
                     But reckon your ioyes fatall instrument.
                  
                  
                     Dicae.
                     Yet this her penance: Cosma, marke thy censure,
                     Whom most tho
                           •
                         shouldest loue, thou shalt loue neuer
                     Dote thou on dotards, they shall hold thee euer:
                     The best and wisest neuer shall respect thee,
                     Thon onely fooles, fooles onely shall affect thee.
                     Loose now those prisoners; so forward to the temple.
                  
                  Exit Chorus.
                  
                     Can.
                     Ha braue Iudge, now Mistris mine, I must confesse.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     This charme begins to worke already,
                     I loue this foole, and doate vpon him more,
                     Then euer vpon any man before:
                     Well, I must be content thus to be curst
                     And yet of louers, fooles are not the worst.
                     For howsoeuer boyes doe hoote and flout them,
                     The best and wisest oft haue fooles about them.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     I and many a fooles bable too, I warrant the
                           •
                        .
                     Sweete heart, shall we goe to bedde?
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     What, in the morning?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Morning? tis night.
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Thou art a foole indeede, seest not the sunne?
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Why that's a candle or the moone, I prethee let's goe to bed
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Cos.
                     Content; no time vnfit for play,
                     Loue knowes no difference twixt night and day.
                  
                  
                     Can.
                     Nay, all the play's done, gentles, you may goe
                           •
                        
                     
                     I haue another play within to doe.
                     
                        Riddle me, Riddle me, what's that?
                     My play is worke enough; my w
                           •
                        rke is play,
                     I see to worke i'th' night, and rest 'ith' day:
                     Since then my play and worke is all but one,
                     Well may my play begin, now yours is done.
                  
                  Exeunt.
               
            
         
         
            EPILOGVS.
            
               AS in a Feast, so in a Comedy,
            Two se
                  •
               ces must be pleasd in both the eye,
            In feasts, the eye and taste must be inuited,
            In Comedies, the ey
                  •
                and 
                  •
               are delighted:
            And he that onely seekes to please but eyther,
            While both he doth not please, he pleaseth neyther.
            What euer feast could euery guest content,
            When a
                  •
                t'ea
                  •
               h man each taste is different?
            But lesse a Scene, where nought but as 'tis newer,
            Can please, where guests are more, and dishes fewer:
            Yet in this thought, this thought the Author easd,
            Who once made all, all rules, all neuer pleasd.
            Fain
                  •
                would we please the best, if not the many,
            And sooner will the best be pleasd then any:
            Our rest we set in pleasing of the best,
            So wi
                  •
               h we you, what you may giue vs: Rest.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

