
   
      
         
            A discourse of that which happened in the battell fought betweene the two navies of Spaine and Portugall, at the Ilands of the Azores. Anno Dom. 1582
            Bazan, Álvaro de, marquês de Santa Cruz, 1526-1588.
         
         
            
               1583
            
         
         Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00924
            STC 1103
            ESTC S120245
            99855444
            99855444
            20938
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00924)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20938)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 409:19)
         
         
            
               
                  A discourse of that which happened in the battell fought betweene the two navies of Spaine and Portugall, at the Ilands of the Azores. Anno Dom. 1582
                  Bazan, Álvaro de, marquês de Santa Cruz, 1526-1588.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  By Thomas Purfoote, and are to be sould at his shop ouer-against Saint Sepulchers Church without Newgate,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1583?]
               
               
                  Suggested publication date from STC.
                  At end: this relation was sent by the Lord Marquis de Sainta-cruse vnto his Maiestie .. .
                  Signatures: A-C⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Spain --  History --  Philip II, 1556-1598 --  Early works to 1800.
               Spain --  Foreign Relations --  Portugal --  Early works to 1800.
               Portugal --  Foreign Relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.
               Portugal --  History --  Spanish dynasty, 1580-1640 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-05
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-06
            Jason ColmanSampled and proofread
         
            2006-06
            Jason ColmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               A Diſcourſe of that which happened in the battell fought betweene the two Nauies of Spaine and Portugall, at the Ilands of Azores.
            
            Anno Dom. 1582.
            
            ¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas Purfoote, and are to be ſould at his ſhop ouer-againſt Saint Sepulchers Church without Newgate.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               The ſucceſſe which did happen vnto the Nauie of the king of Spaine, whereof was generall Captaine the Marquis of Santa Cruſe, in the battell which was fought with the Nauie that Don Antonie brought to the Ilands of Aſores.
            
            
               The Lord Marqueſſe went out of the riuer of Liſhborne, the tenth daye of Julie 1582▪ with 28. ſhippes, and with fiue ſmall pinneſſes, (for that other three ſhippes which ſhould haue gone with him, could not come foorth till the next day,) bicauſe he had order from his Maieſtie, to depart with the ſaid Nauie, without tarying for the 19 ſhippes, 2. galians, 12▪ gallies, and 2. pineſſes, which were prepared in And
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  zia. And following his voiage, had three dayes of ill weather, at the ende whereof he found him-ſelfe 55▪ leagues from Liſhborne, about the height of the Cape of Saint Vincent, 50. leagues from him. And ſo the foule weather was the cauſe that he fell from the height of his pretended courſe. From whence returned one ſhip being an Aragoze, in the which were three companies of old ſouldiers of Flanders, and the Phiſitians, Surgians, and other officers

of the Hoſpitall, with their prouiſion of all things neceſſarie for that purpoſe: which ſhip returned without anie order, they alledging that ſhe was in a leeke. In the 13. day it pleaſed God to ſend faire weather, by meanes whereof they got in one day &amp; night that which they had before loſt. And being in it, and the fayre weather continuing ſtill, he did follow his voiage, till the 21. at which time they had the ſight of the Ile of S. Michaeel. And the 22. day being Sunday, they approched neere vnto 
                  Ʋilla Franca, which is a towne of the ſaid Iland, containing about 500. houſholds.
            The day before they ariued at the Iland, the Marquis diſpatched two Pineſſes, vnder the charge of Capteine Aguirrei, who was capteine ouer the fiue aforeſaid, and did ſend in euery one ſixe ſouldiers with Caleuers, giuing them warning to go warilie, and if they ſhould chance to meete with their enemies Nauie, that they ſhould not come abord anie of their ſhippes▪ neither ſuffer any of them to come aborde of their pineſſes. And by the ſaid Capteine the Marquis did write vnto Ambroſe Aguier gouernour of the ſaid Iland, certifying him how his Maieſties Nauie which he brought was verie ſtrong, conteining 5500. ſouldiers, in which number

was Don Lopus de Figueroa, with a 1800 of them of Flanders, ouer and aboue 200. Gentlemen and perticular perſons entertained with their aduantages, who came to ſerue his Maieſtie. And that the Nauie which was made readie in Calis, (for the which they did looke euery houre) was of the number and quantitie aforeſaid, with other 5000. ſouldiers, wherof was fiue enſignes of old Terſua of Flaunders. And the Marquis did deſire the ſaid Ambroſio de Aguier to ſend him ſuch newes as he had of the French Nauie, &amp; whether they had paſſed by that waies or not, and the number of their ſhips: becauſe he was determined to go ſeeke them, and fight with them. And that he ſhould ſay vnto Peter Piſhoto, if he ſhoulde chaunce to bee there, that he ſhould make himſelfe readie to follow him with the ſhippes of his charge.
            Whiles the Marquis was at an anker in the road of Villa Franca, there did ariue vnto the Admirals ſhip, one Caruaile of the three which were left in Liſhborne, for to bring the horſes, who gaue them to vnderſtand, that the day before were ariued to the ſaide 
                  Ʋilla Franca, the three ſhippes which were left in Liſhborne, who departed from thence the next day after the Marquis, in companie with the ſaide three Carnailes. They reported

likewiſe, that the three ſhips, after they had fallen with 
                  Ʋilla Franca, were forced backe againe to the ſea, and that the two carueils were taken by the enemie, the other with the horſes belonging to the generall of the field, and others, went to the ſea, beeing chaſed by a French ſhip.
            The Marquis did ſend ſome perticular men to vnderſtand ſomewhat of them of the Iland, who would not ſuffer them to come aland, but diſcharged their peeces at them. And there was a Preiſt that tolde them that the Iland was for his Maieſtie, and that he knewe nothing of the french Armie, others willed them to goe to the Citie. The Marqueſſe vnderſtanding what had paſſed, and perceiuing by one of the two Pineſſes which hee had ſent with Captain Aguirre, that the other Pinaſſe with Captain Aguirre was taken priſoner by a French Shippe and other Barks that came from the land, hee did then ſuſpect that the Iland had rebelled, and hauing ſent for Don Lopo de Figueroa Generall of the Feeld, to conferre with him about the landing of ſome quantitie of men to haue ſpech with them of Villa Franca, and likewiſe to take freſhe water, and hauing ſent to the Captains Michel de Oquendo and Rodrigo de Vargas, to take notice in what place they

were beſt to anker: in the meane time they that were in the top of the Admirall Gallion eſpied certain ſhips neere vnto Ponta Delgaaa, about which place is the principall place of the Iland and the Caſtle: and ſeeming to the Marques that thoſe ſhippes ſhould be of the enemies, he altered his determination and went ſtraightway neere vnto Ponta Delgada, and by &amp; by they diſcouered 
                  •
               o ſhips, &amp; then they perceiued that it was the armie of Don Anthonio. So our armie approching vnto the enimie, and hauing now certaine knowledge of them, for that they prepared them ſelues towards the ſea, and perceiuing them to be aboue 60. ſhips of ſmal and great, the Marquis called a councell, and with the aduice of Don Pedro de Tolledo, the Maſter generall of the Campe, the Marquis de la Fauora, Don Pedro de Taſsis generall Comptroler, Don Franciſco de Bouadilla maſter of the Campe, and other Capteins &amp; Knights beeing called therevnto, they determined to preſent the battell, and to fight with the enimie: who did the like, and put themſelues in order, and ſo they diſcharged a peece of ordinance towards vs in token of battaile. With that the Marquis commanded to put foorth a baner of defiance, and ſhot off one peece of ordinance, and ſent Capteine Maroline,
               
and capteine Rodrigo de Vergas, to aduertiſe the whole armie to ſet them ſelues in order of battaile, which was done in this maner: In the forefront was a rowe of ſhips and galions, and of the right hand of the Admirall was placed the galion Saint Mattheo, wherein was the maſter Generall of the field, and the generall Comptroller: and of the left hand was the ſhip, wherein went Don Franciſco de Bouadilla great maſter of the field, and foure ſhips more to be aſſiſtants: the ten Biſcains, with the other ſhips, wherein was the capteines Michel de Ouando, and Vilia Viſioſa, were placed in the rereward. And by reaſon the ſhip wherin Don Chriſtopher de Eraſſo went, had ſtrained the head of hir maine maſt, by meanes whereof ſhe could not beare hir top ſaile, ſhe was forced to ſtaie behind, and could not therefore take hir place accordinglie. Which was a great greefe to the Marquis, to want the companie of Don Chriſtopher in ſuch a time of occaſion. The Marquis him ſelfe went in the galian Saint Marten, whiche was Admerall of the ſame Nauie. He gaue this order for the battell, that in the uppermoſt ſight vpon the poope ſhould be 20. gentlemen and piſtolets, &amp; 20. caleuers: and belowe the Portiugal gentlemen (except Syr Iames de
               
               Caſtro, which was vpon the poope) and 20. piſtolets, and 6. caliuers: and loweſt of all ſhould be for helpe and ſuccour Syr Anthonie Peſſoua, Syr Lewes Oſorio, Syr Goſton Ronkelio, the coronell Mondonario, captaine Queſſatha, and other foure piſtolets: and vpon the hatches of the galion 40. piſtolets vpon either ſide, vnder the charge of captaine Gamboa: neere to the chamber of the poope, was the body of the gard, with 40. ſouldiers, moſt of them particuler men, which had bene in office before, vnder the charge of capteine Auguſtin Deherrara, for to helpe and ſuccor where ſhould be moſt need. In the ſtarne of the ſhip was Iohn Baptiſt Sauffone gentleman of Milan, with the ſerieants of the capteines Auguſtine Deherrera, and Gamboa, with 15. piſtolets, and 10. caliuers: in the great top was the ſerieant Syr Frances Galeio with 8. caliuers, and in the top of the Trinket ſixe, beſides thoſe that were in the ſmall tops. Vnder the hatches where the great ordinance dooth lie, were the capteins Syr Chriſtopher Deaccouia, and Scouetho, and Iohn Alter, and the ſerieant Tauſte, and Eſquiuel, and with euerie peece of ordinance one gunner, and ſix men to helpe him. And euerie one had an inſtrument called hanſpiks. With the munition

which was vpon the hatches, was Marcelus Carraceolus: and like ſeruice was vnderneath. And in keeping of the gunne powder was capteine Grimaldo, with foure mariners. He commanded alſo, that there ſhould ſtand hard by the ſterne of the galion, the great bote called the Salua, and foure ſmall ones, for to carrie directions, and fill tubbes of water and hogſheads in diuers places of the ſaid galion, and deuide in their places diuers pikes, and that the Mariners ſhould be in the ſhips apparell, and the capteines Marolin and Roger Deuargas (as ſeamen and of great experience) ſhould attend vnto the ordinance and other neceſſaries. All this was executed verie ſhortlie, and with a great good will. For all this was prouided before they approched vnto the Iland.
            This beeing doone, with great noiſe of wifflers and drums, and their baners open, went our nauie for to inuade the enimies: the which made the like in good order. But bicauſe the wind was calme, they could not fight that day, but went ſeaward. And yet the Marquis could not vnderſtand of the ſtate of the Iland. Afterward foure owers within night ariued vnto the admirall Galion, in a Pineſſe, wherin was Domingo de Adurriaga, maſter of a ſhip called the Cateline,
               
with other fiue mariners Biſcaines, and brought a letter from Don Iohn de Caſtilio, conteining as followeth.
            In the army of Don Anthonio there is 58. ſhips, wherof 28. be great ſhips, and the reſt ſmall, and in them is 6000. Frenchmen. If our armie be not ſtrong enough to fight with them, then it may drawe nigh the Caſtle, which is for the king. And I would wiſh you to haue a great regarde to it, for if you ſhould looſe the victory, great inconuenience would enſue. Furthermore the Maiſter and his company declared, that Don Anthonio with his armie came to the Iland of S. Michael the 15. day of Julie, and the 16. he ſet 3000. men a land, with whome Don Lorenco Noguera with iiii. enſigens of footmen did meete, being in number about 500. men, and with 150. Harquebuſhiers taken out of the Byskaine ſhippes, who a litle from the citie did ſkirmiſh with the french armie, but being ouerpreſſed with nomber, were forced to retire to the Caſtle to Peter Piſoto, with the loſſe of 10. Caſtellions, and 12. Byſcaynes, Don Lorenco
                being hurt, wherof after he dyed: and in the Caſtle with Peter Piſoto is the ſonne of the gouernour Ambroſio de Aguiar, and the Biſhop, the Corigedor, and other two or three Gentlemen, and all

the reſt went out of the citie, calling ſome of Don Anthonio, and the ſouldiours of the Frenche armie ſacked the Citie: and that Don Anthonio ſent to the Captaine Don Iohn de Caſtillio, willing him to yeeld vnto him the caſtle, knowing it to be his, and that he would giue him free paſſage for him and his company: the which thing if he refuſed, that then he would bring aland 7. peeces of Ordinance from the ſhips, and would batter the Caſtle: &amp; moreouer he gaue him to vnderſtand that the armie of Spaine woulde not come this yeere. To whom Don Iohn, the gouernours ſonne, the Biſhop, and the Corigedor made anſwere, that the Caſtle was the king of Spaines, and that they woulde not yeeld it to him. The Marquis did likewiſe vnderſtande by the ſaide Maiſter, that the Frenche men the next daye (hauing knowledge of the approching of our armie) did imbarke themſelues in all haſt, and that the 2. Gallions and 3. great Caruelles of Peter Piſoto, were ouerthrowne neere vnto the Caſtle, and the 4. Byskaine ſhips the French men tooke, after that the men were gone aland and withdrawen themſelues into the Caſtle. The Marquis being informed of all things, wrote vnto the Captaine and Gouernour, &amp; others in the Caſtle, by the ſaid Maiſter,

incouraging them, and certifying them of the force of the kings army, not doubting but the next day to giue battell, and to haue the victorye, and that therewith they ſhould holde them ſelues contented, as he him ſelfe was much ioyful of the ſeruice which they had alredy done to the king, which he knew ſhould not remain vnrecompenſed. And with this anſwere they returned with the Pinaſſe to the Iland.
            The next day being Munday, &amp; the 23. of Julie, ye two Armies came to preſent battel: the french Armie hauing both the vantage of the wind and alſo of the Sun, came to aſſalt our Armie being deuided in three quadrons, and made three ſeuerall attempts, and yet could put nothing in execution. And toward night the Spaniſh Army making towardes the ſea, the french Armie placed ten ſhippes alongſt the Iland, thinking that night to haue got the winde of vs: but by reaſon it was calme, they could not preuaile.
            The 24. day of July the Marquis returned, approching nerer the French army, who hauing the vantage of the winde, gaue two ſeuerall attempts, and yet put neither in execution. Then the Marquis perceiuing that the courſe towardes the land was not conuenient for him, he cauſed the armie to take the

courſe towardes the Sea, thinking with himſelfe that whiles his ſhippes were trimming of their ſayles, that the enemie woulde aſſault him hauing the winde for their purpoſe: which fell out accordingly. For one of the Frenche Captaines with 7. Galleons came to aſſault the Captaine of the Spaniardes, and the Galleon Saint Matteo, but approching neere vnto them, did not board them, but diſcharged great quantitiae of Ordinance againſt them, and likewiſe did the reſt of the ſhips againſt ours: of whom they were receiued accordingly, in ſo much that our Captaine did ſhoote of at them aboue 40. peeces, and alſo the Galleon Saint Matteo ſhotte of many peeces, alſo the ſhippe of Don Chriſtopher de Eraſſo (who was now ioyned with the armie) and alſo the ſhippe of Don Franciſco de Bouadilla, and Myguell de Oquendo, and others, which was a pleaſaunt ſight to beholde what Ordenance was ſhotte off, they did hit our Captaine with 4. ſhotte, one in the foreſaile, another in the ſhrouds, another vpon an Anker, and the fourth in the ſhippes ſide, without doing any harme: they hit the Galleon Saint Matteo with 3 ſhotte, without doing any harme, no more did many their peeces which did hit many of our ſhips. And in the Galleons of the Frenchmen wee

might perceiue many ſhot to light, but ſpecially 4. out of our Captaine, which made them to retire, whereby it appeared they receiued ſome harme.
            There came in the Frenche armie two Captaines &amp; two Admirals, and there was a ſmall Galleon like a Patacha, being excellent good of ſayle, wherein it ſhoulde ſeeme Don Anthonio was, carying a ſtandarde in the Poope, which did not approch the fight, but kept a farre off to beholde what paſſed. There came to the number of 40, gret ſhips, and amongſt them ſome very fine Galleons, the reſt were ſmall ſhippes, but fit for the armie in reſpect of the lightnes, and there came diuers other ſmall Pineſſes all about the armie about 2. or 3. leagues of to diſcouer and vnderſtand of all things, and alſo 2. Saities of Mercelles, very good ſhippes of ſayle, and many other light Boates with owres, wherwith they did put in order the battaile, and direct things as time ſerued. The ſame day at night the two armies did ſeparate themſelues. The Marquis determined that at the going downe of the Moone to procure to get the wind of the French armie, and in the morning to aſſault them againe, which hee did, ſo that the 25. day of July he found him ſelfe to windward of the enemy, &amp; ſo ſought

to board them, but bicauſe his ſhippes were great and heauie of ſaile, he could not put in effect that which he purpoſed, but was forced to returne to the reſcue of Don Chriſtopher de Eraſſo, who was in ſome diſtreſſe in following the enemie, and by defaulte of his maine maſt, gaue him a toe with his Captaine. This day there was diſcried a great ſhippe of the enemies which wanted her foremaſt, and other 2. ſhips which did helpe her, and they being not able to helpe her, ſhe was forced to ſinke: it is iudged ſhee had ſome harme with ſome ſhot the day before.
            Of the 10. Hulkes of the Spaniſh armie there did want two which caryed Almaines, and there wanted likewiſe the three ſhippes that departed from Liſhborne after the army departed, ſo that ye Marques had in his Nauie no more but 25. ſhippes with the two gallions.
            The 26 of Julie the Frenche armie came againe to aſſault the Spaniſh armie, in very good order and with a fauourable wind. The Marques did cauſe his ſhips to be placed in order, although the galleon Saint Matteo was ſomewhat aſterne, which was ſome greefe to the Marquis, doubting that the enimy might board hir, before ſhe could conueniently be reſcued: and ſo it fell out, for ſhe was borded

by two galleons, a captaine and an admirall, againſt whom ſhe did defend her ſelf very valiantly, being likewiſe aſſalted by other two ſhippes, who after they had diſcharged certaine ordinance at her, paſſed forwards. At the ſame time came other two French ſhips vppon the Captaine, who beginning to fight with her, ſhe gaue them two ſuch welcomes with her ordinance and arquebuſhe ſhotte, that the one of them was euill to paſſe and almoſt ſonke: and ſo they retyred, hauing ſhot many peeces at the Captaine, and the Captaine at them. At which time came the ſhip of Don Franciſco de Bouadilla, who was nere the Capteine, who did likewiſe annoie the Frenchmen greatlie with hir ſhot.
            All this while did the Admirall, and the Viceadmirall of the French army fight with the galion Saint Mattheo, who did defend hir ſelfe, and offend the others valiantlie: the generall maſter of the Campe, Don Lopo de Figueroa, Don Pedro de Taſsis ouerſeer generall, with the reſt of the gentlemen and ſouldiers that were in hir, valiantlie ſhooting at the enimies bath with great ſhot, arquebuſhot, and muſket ſhot. The Marquis perceiuing that the Spaniſh nauie was to the windward of the French nauie, &amp; ſeeing the diſtreſſe that the galleon S. Mattheo was

in by reaſon of the two French men, he commaunded the Captaine to turne towards the enemie, &amp; ſo did Don Chriſtopher de Eraſſo, and the reſt of the ſhippes of the Spaniſh armie: and the ſhippes of Michael de Oquendo, Vilia Vicioſa, and another Biskain, which were before the ſternemoſt, by changing the wind were then the foremoſt, who came and borded the Admirall of the French nauie, who fought with the galeon Saint Mattheo, and afterward came the ſhip, wherein went Michael de Veneſa, who fought with the capteine of France like a good Capteine, and ſo in like ſort did the ſouldiers that were with him, and bicauſe his ſhip was betwene, the Marquis could not at that time board the Capteine of France, but paſſed forward. In this meane time the Admirall of France was in ſight with the galeon Saint Mattheo, and three ſhips more, who borded hir, Villia Vicioſa being one of the three, and hauing borded the French Admirall at the prowe, was ſlaine, with manie of his companie, as ſhall be declared. The ſhip of Oquendo did board hir aſterne, and did enter his men into hir, and began to ſacke, and tooke foure priſoners and the enſignes. The battell began now to encreaſe: with that came two other French ſhips to reſkew their Capitaine, and

putting aboard hir aboue 300. freſh men, ſhe got from them.
            In this meane while the Marquis gaue an other aſſault vpon the enimie with much ſhot, and at the laſt borded with the French Capteine prowe to prowe, and ſo grapened togither, where was a cruell fight of both ſides, ſhooting the one at the other both with great ſhot and ſmal, for the ſpace of an houre, till ſhe yeelded, where was beheaded aboue 300. Frenchmen, and the Gentlemen and ſouldiers that were in the two fights, did defend them ſelues valiantlie: ſo likewiſe did the two capteins Auguſtine Deherrara, and Gamboa, and their Lieuetenants. The Marquis like a generall went through the fights, encouraging the people to the aſſaulting of the enimie, foreſeeing and ordering all things needfull to be doone. The artilterie both belowe and aloft did great good, through the great diligence of thoſe capteins that had charge thereof. The battell betweene the other ſhips did proceede, giuing and receiuing great chargings one vpon an other. The battell continued fiue houres, and at the laſt the enimie fled.
            
               Don Anthonio was departed in a ſmall Pineſſe, with another ſhip the night before the battell. Some ſhips were ſonke, &amp; ſome

ſpoiled, hauing beheaded the men that were found in them, and ſome fled to other ſhips. And for that we could not toe their ſhips, the Marquis commanded that we ſhould burne them, and ſinke ſuch as we could, as we had begun to doo. The Caruaile with the horſes which they had taken, was recouered.
            It is thought that there is of the enimies aboue 1200. ſlaine, drowned, and beheaded, beſides manie that be hurt, of them that eſcaped in the ſhips which fled. There might haue bene taken manie of their ſhips more, if we had had time and mariners ſufficient for to haue towed them, but they were ſuffered to depart without men and ſpoiled: and it is certaine, that the Admirall which was left for halfe drowned, and other foure or ſiue ſhips more, were ouerthrowne in the Ile of Saint Michael, and it it thought others haue done the like in other places.
            The number of thoſe that were ſlaine in the Nauie of the Spaniards, was 224 men: and of thoſe that were hurt 553. which is in all 777. Beſides ſome that were ſcalded with artificiall fire, amongſt whom was the generall Comptroller Syr Peter de Taſsis in the face.
            
               
               ¶The names of the principall men that came with Don Anthonio, of whom ſome were priſoners, ſome died, and ſome did runne awaie.
               
                  Philip Strozzi Capteine generall was priſoner, and hurt with a ſhot of an harquebuſh, of the which ſhot he died ſo ſoone as he came in the preſence of the Marquis.
               The Earle Devimioſo was priſoner, and hurt with an harquebuſh, and a thruſt with a ſword, wherof he died in the generals ſhippe the day after the battell.
               The Countie Briſak liefetenant, ſome ſaie that he eſcaped in a boat of his ſhip: others ſaie, that he was ſlaine with a ſhot, the truth is not knowne.
               
                  Mounſir de Piamount generall maſter of the Campe, was ſlaine in the battell.
               Of the eight principal capteins of the eight regiments that came in the armie, which was 6800 ſouldiers, accounting the aduenterers, ſome were ſlaine, &amp; ſome fled away.
            
            
               The Lords of Townes and Caſtles, that were taken aliue.
               
                  
                     Mounſir de Bocamaior Lord of Rouſola.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Iohn Delatus Lord of Heria.
                  
                  
                     William de Sanclear Lord of Sanclear.
                  
                  
                     
                     Lewes de Clen Lord of Bronnes.
                  
                  
                     Peter de Oube Lord of Quenes.
                  
                  
                     Gilbert de Louel Lord of 
                        Ʋuell.
                  
                  
                     Peter de Bean.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir de Gal Lord de Gal.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir de Gifford Lord of Giffordel.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir de la Onet eldeſt ſonne vnto the Lord of Greſoul.
                  
                  
                     Edward de Langert Lord of Piel.
                  
                  
                     Fabio Ganſete ſonne to the lord of Ganſete.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir de Vda Lord of Vda.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Franſoius Lord of Montilla.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Laquesbai eldeſt ſonne of the Lord of Biapolis.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Robert Debella eldeſt ſonne of the Lord of Veoſola.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Guillam Maſon lord of Falla.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Bigart de Piloart lord of Manterie.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Beltram de Amigat lord of Stituias.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Petro Iailato lord of Sans.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Philip Mentado lord of Sabruſſa.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Iohn de Bocamaior lord of Roſilla.
                  
                  
                     Claudio de Pomoline Lord of Popalin.
                  
                  
                     Iacobo Laſerean Lord of Laſſerian.
                  
                  
                     Mounſir Demondoc Lord of Mondoc.
                  
               
               The Gentlemen priſoners which were no Lords of Townes nor Caſtles, were in number 51. And of Mariners and common ſouldiers 303.
               
                  The Marquis ſeeing that there was peace and amitie betweene the king his Maſter, and the French king, and knowing that theſe aduenturers came onlie in the fauour of Don Anthonio Prior de Crato, and with mind to robbe and ſpoile his Maieſties Fleet of both his Indians, and to make them ſelues lords of his Ilands and dominions, as they had begun in the Ile of Saint Michael, and that their meaning was to make other ſpoils and piracies: In puniſhing of their fault, and the common offence committed by them againſt the publike peace, ſworne, mainteined, and kept betweene theſe two Crownes, and their ſubiects, did declare all the priſoners to be enemies of the quietnes and common good, troublers of the intercourſes, fauorers of his Maieſties rebels: and as to ſuch ones, and publike theeues, rouers and pyrats, the cheefe Juſtice of the Fleete did ordeine, that for the puniſhment of thoſe, and enſample to others in like caſes, that the noble men ſhould be beheaded, and that the reſt ſhould be hanged from 17. yeeres vpwards.
               And this ſentence being giuen, it was put in execution the firſt day of Auguſt, of this preſent yeere 1582.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            This relation was ſent by the Lord Marquis de Sainta-cruſe vnto his Maieſtie, by Syr Peter Poncei of Lyon, his nephew: who departed from 
                  Ʋilla Franca which is in the Ile of Saint Michael, the fourth day of the moneth of Auguſt, and ariued at Liſhborne the 24. day of the ſame, being S. Bartholmews day, in the morning.
            
         
      
   

