
   
      
         
            [The fleur de luce.]
            Collection Fleur de lys.
         
         
            
               1593
            
         
         Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00983
            STC 11088
            ESTC S116011
            99851228
            99851228
            16496
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00983)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16496)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 508:07)
         
         
            
               
                  [The fleur de luce.]
                  Collection Fleur de lys.
                  Forget, Pierre, 1544-1610, attributed name. aut
                  Arnauld, Antoine, 1560-1619, attributed name. aut
               
               [28] p.   
               
                  J. Wolfe,
                  [London :
                  1593]
               
               
                  Title and imprint from STC.
                  A translation of:  La fleur de lys.
                  Caption title on A2 recto has: The flower de luce. Which conteyneth the discourse of a Frenchman deteyned in Paris, vppon the impieties and counterfeatings conteyned in the manifest of Spayne, published in the month of Ianuary. 1593.
                  Variously attributed to: Arnauld, Antoine and also to: Forget, Pierre.
                  Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .
                  Imperfect; lacks title page.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Spain --  Foreign relations --  France --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-02
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-02
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-02
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE FLOWER DE LVCE.
            Which conteyneth the diſcourſe of a Frenchman deteyned
in Paris, vppon the impieties and counterfeatings
conteyned in the manifeſt of Spayne, publiſhed in the
month of Ianuary. 1593.
            
            
               HEtherto did I alwayes hope that
ſhortly we ſhould ſo open our eyes as
we ſhould neede no farther prouocation
to ſtirre vppe our iuſt diſpleaſure
againſt the auncient and captiall ennemies
of the Flower de Luce, vntill
being reaſſembled together vnder the French bāner,
we ſhould paſſe ouer the Pirinean mountaines for the
deliuery of the poore Nauarrean ſlaues out of captiuity,
who doe ſtretch foorth their armes to that mightye
prince to whōe God hath vouchſafed theſe two goodly
crownes, the one by diſcent from his father, the other
from his mother. But ſith that after ſo many vaine
hopes one in an others neck whereinto we haue beene
forced in this towne of Paris, for the lulling a ſleepe of
our ſences and the deceiuing of our extreame miſery,
we ſtill in the end doe ſee that they from whome wee
expected our felicity (as ſometimes it hath fallen out,
that ſuch as haue bene authors of great miſchiefes,
haue alſo bene miniſters of great remedies) ſith I ſay
that in liew of acknowledging their lawfull king, they
haue paſſed the pikes: and plunged themſelues headlong
in the horrible goulfe of Spaniſh bondage, I can
no lenger keepe this long ſilence, for ſo long as we reteyne
any ſparke of the humor of our auncient French

liberty, we cannot but ſend forth ſome ſpeeches, ſome
ſighes the teſtimonies of our intent. Before we giue
vppe the ghoſt we muſt euen with our bloud write this
our laſt teſtament for our poſterity, to the ende they
may know that their aunceſters were no ſuch traytors
to their Princes, that voluntarily would ſuffer themſelues
to be chayned vppe vnder the locks of this cruell
and moſt barbarous nation.
            O Innocent poſterity, who in ſecret ſhall read theſe
laſt lamentations of your dying mother, euer-more remember
that your ſelues are diſcended of the race of
thoſe who time out of minde, haue made other nations
of the earth to tremble, who haue paſſed the Alpes, and
the Pirinean mountaines, who haue ſayled ouer euery
ſea, to make their weapons to gliſter in the bowels of
forren empires: who neuer fered any thing except that
the sky ſhould fall vpon them, as being aſſured to conquer
and tame whatſoeuer vpon the face of the earth
durſt medle with them. This onely remembrance
will ſo inflame your mindes with ſpite and rage, that
in time you ſhall gather ſtrength, yea albeit all weapons
ſhould fayle you, euen with your handes to ſtifle
theſe ſerpents who hauing once wrethed you within
their traines will ſucke forth the very marow out of
your bones.
            Neuer thinke deere children that thoſe ſhamefull
couenants whereinto your parents are entered did
proceede of their voluntary good will, neither meaſure
the intent of a great nation according to the notable
wickedneſſe of a number of mutinous not frenchmen,
but baſtards heere ingendred by Spanyardes: No it
is not to be thought that any ſo infamous or wretched

cogitation could euer penetrate the harte of any man
diſcended of a perfect french race. I will not heere
bring into conſideration the horrible cruelties that
haue diſpeopled the Indians, in putting to death more
then remaineth vpon the reſt of the face of the earth:
neither will I ſet before you the inſatiable couetize
that hath dried vp the minds of Peru, and baniſhed the
welthieſt houſes in Portugall and the Low countryes,
all this beſeemeth thoſe that ſeeke to haue a ſtranger
to their maiſter, yet will they haue one that is tollerable.
France hath no skill in ſuch a choyce: France
acknowledgeth none but her owne children, thoſe
whome ſhe hath ſuckled, nourſed and brought vp in
her boſome, ouer whome ſhee commandeth, her king
onely excepted, whome God hath made to be borne
the eldeſt of the moſt ancient, greateſt and moſt floriſhing
famely in the world, that hath ſwaied the french
ſcepter ſo many yeares. France giueth eare to that only
child whome ſhe cheriſheth, and loueth moſt tenderly,
to whome ſhe beareth an extraordinary affection,
as accompting nothing difficult or dangerous that
may tende to the exalting of him aboue all other Princes
of the earth. In him hath ſhe ſhewed all her contentation:
her glory and maieſtie are ſhadowed and
doe wholy gliſter in her eldeſt ſonne, whoſe enterpriſes
may for a while ſo long as his mother ſleepeth be ſomewhat
ſlacked, but in the ende if ſhe waken and that
the potion which by her enemies hath bene miniſtred
to lull her on ſleepe, hath loſt all force: when ſhe returneth
to the knowledge of her ſelfe and beginnes to
ſtirre her benummed armes, in how ſhort ſpace ſhall
we ſee all theſe ſpaniſh forces cut in pieces? all theſe

garriſons of moores died in their owne bloud, the woful
countenance of France changed into ioy and mirth,
and all theſe ſtormes driuen away by the beautifull
beames of the ſonne which ſhall reſtore vnto vs the
light-ſome day of contentation and perfect liberty?
our churches ſhall not (as they ſeeke to perſwade) be
deſolate, but contrariwiſe they ſhall bee repleniſhed
with that ancient multitude which vſually we haue
ſeene among vs. We all together ſhall render praiſe
to God for the felicity vnto vs graunted, when round
about vs we ſhall behould not the ſpaniſh inſolencie
full of pompe and vanity, but the ſweetneſſe of our parents
and the delightſome company of thoſe that haue
bene borne in the ſame towne with vs. Oh happy
day, moſt proſperous and ſo long deſired of all good
men in this poore towne, who groane vnder the burden
of forrein dominion with whom we may without
feare bewayle our paſſed calamities, reioyce our preſent
felicity, and ſtill hope for a more full accompliſhment
thereof.
            Albeit our goods be waſted, and that we inioy but
euen halfe a life euell compacted in a weake body, fallen
away with extreame famine, yet may we at the
leaſt ſpeake bouldier: Our miſery ſhall be at an ende:
and the affliction of things paſſed ſhall neuer be agmented
with feare of ſuch as are to come. We ſhall no
longer ſee this proud Rodomontes preſidents of the
counſails of the baſtards of France: our eares ſhall not
be filled with their proud threates, &amp; vaine bragges of
their mighty armies that ſhould driue the warres a
hundred leagues from vs, winne ſo many fieldes and
cary our king into the Baſtille.
            
               
Neuertheleſſe ſith this day ſhall be ſo fortunate vnto
vs, why doe not we endeuour to haſten it, euen with
the haſard of our liues: muſt the feare of death make
vs ſhamefully and cowardly die for hunger, when otherwiſe
we might with weapon be r
                  •
               u
                  •
               nged of thoſe
that draw vs into theſe extremities, by making vs ſo
obſtinately to with-ſtand our countery and king? and
yet doth the ſuperfluity of their expenſes euidently
declare vnto vs, that with them this time is as eaſily
ouerpaſſed, as to vs it is hard and intollerable. The
great pentions that they daily receiue from their good
maiſter, cauſeth them to acknowledge him, and to
terme him The mightie king: the vniuerſall king: the Catholicke
king: the king of kings: the great Monarck, victorious
both by ſea and by land, and whatſoeuer other flattery may
be inuented, they will heape vppon him in exchange of
his duckats. What more aſſured teſtimony cā we craue
to proue that ſuch people are no frenchmen? The Achayans
bring already entered into acknowledgement of
the Romane empire Ariſtaenetus the Megapolitain a
man of great credit amongſt them, on a time in open
connſaile ſaid that it were good to honour the Romans
and not to ſhew any ingratitude toward them, whervpon
Philopoemen, a man who iuſtly was by the hiſtorygraphers
termed the laſt Grecian, hearing this ſpeech,
a while held his peace, but in the end ſo preſſed with
impacience and choller that he could no longer keepe
ſilence ſaid. Ariſtaenetus, why makeſt thou ſuch haſt to ſee the
wretched deſtiny of Greece. For thefe thirty yeares haue
there bene among vs a geuerall complaint proſecuted
not only by the nobility, but euen by al men of courage,
for yt the king of Spaine hath preſumed to thinke to

cauſe his Embaſſadors to take the precedence from
ours. What frenchman hath not with iuſt indignation
complained hereof? and yet now euen at once he that
intituleth himſelfe the pretector and liutenant of the
crowne, of the mightieneſſe and maieſtie of France,
hath ſhewed himſelfe ſuch a coward, or rather ſuch a
traytor, to terme the king of Spaine the great king, and
in what compariſon; but that the king of France muſt
be little
            Why Charles of Lorraine, canſt thou find any example
that by letters patents ſealed with the Flower
de Luce the title of Great was euer attributed to any
forreine kings, nay but contrariwiſe many times haue
the fields flowed with blood for the preſeruation of the
title of Auguſtus to the kings of France, the firſt, the
ancienteſt and the moſt mighty princes in Chriſtiandome,
who doe inioy the crowne of liberty and glory
aboue all other kings, yet now aloud publiquely in letters
patents ſealed with the Flower de Luce by thee
falſified, thou calleſt the Spanyard, the great king, a title
which in our fathers dayes would alone haue coſt
thee thy life. Why Duke of Mayenne, art thou in ſuch haſt to
aduance the wretched deſtinies of France. He haſt, ſayſt thou,
ſuccoured our Catholicke religion: nay, ſay, thy ambitious
and the practizes of thy family againſt this eſtate.
To the ende to vndermine a crowne of many
yeares ſtanding, and to lay hould againe vppon the
ſundrie vaine pretences euer ſince Charlemagne, by hiſtories
conuicted of falſhood, as ſhewing that it is not
paſt ſixe ſcore yeares ſince the race of Vaudemont entered
into the houſe of Lorraine, which in leſſe then 460.
yeares haue fallen into ſeauen ſeuerall families: To

ſtrike, I ſay ſo great a ſtroke, to extinguiſh the blood
royall, and to ſtepe into their place, it is requiſite to haue
great ſupport and a woonderfull plauſible pretence:
this fortereſſe is not to be aſſaulted with weake battery,
conſidering that in ſuch actions the leſt errors are
ſo perilous. The ſupport hath bene the king of Spaine,
the ancient enemie to France, and one who by inheritance
purpoſeth to become Monarck ouer all Chriſtiandome.
The onely pretence any way to be taken,
was for religion, all others being farre to weake. Vpon
this ground haue they long ſince hired thoſe whoſe
tounges haue bene ſaleable in the pulpits dedicated to
the truth, by whoſe meanes they haue caſt vppon the
people al thoſe charmes that haue brought this eſtate
ſo neere to diſtruction. Herevppon likewiſe haue they
long ſince ſent the Ieſwiſtes, very Spaniſh Colonies,
who haue ſhed forth the poyſon of their conſperacy vnder
the ſhadow of holineſſe, and vnder the colour of
confeſſion (O woonderfull policie:) haue abuſed the
deuotion of the French nation, whom by ſeceret othes
they haue bound to their league. Who alſo in liew of
inſtructing our people in the Catholike religion, are
become trumpets of warre, firebrands of ſedition, protectors
and defenders of murther and robbery, to be
briefe, who are waxen forein leuine to ſower the dowe
of our France and to alter the fedility into trechery and
rebellion, ſo cunningly conducting their maſters affaires
that they haue filled this realme, before flouriſhing,
with fire and blood, and euen with the French
ſwords murthered ſo much braue and valiant nobility
as had bene of force and power ſufficient to reconquer
Naples and Millan which this Gothicke race hath ſtollen

from our fordfathers.
            Theſe curſed policies did long lie hidden, but at ye laſt
the war begun with all extremity about the yeare 85.
againſt a moſt Catholicke king, and ſo acknowledged
by thoſe that moſt hated him, againſt a king yet in the
flower of his age, together with the deteſtable murder
committed vppon his perſon fower yeares after,
haue too euidently declared this pretence of religion to
be vtterly falſe and of no apparance. This cruell and
horrible murder of their king hauing brought them
into execration with all courageous perſons, now to
couer their ſubtilties vſed in the compaſſing thereof,
they doe in their declarations giue out this impreſſion
to the people, that the kings death was a blow from
heauen. Oh abhominable impiety? Oh mightie king,
whome all the ſubtilties of thy enemies, who abuſing
thy authority and too much lenity were become maſters
of thy beſt townes, could neuer ſtop from incloſing
them in the capitall city of thy realme, where they
found themſelues brought into ſuch extreamity, that
without that knife forged in hell, the had bene already
chaſtized for all their notable treazons, Oh mightie
king, who couldeſt not haue any fuller confeſſion of
the victory, euen at thy enemies hands then the kinde
of thy death, is it poſſible that thy ſubiectes, euen thy
children who yet do ſpeake the french language ſhould
endure this cruell parricide, the like whereof was neuer
ſeene, neither any thing ſo deteſtable? which hath
repleniſhed all men with ſorrow and teares, to bee
termed a blow from heauen? O God who neuer without
puniſhment, ſuffereſt thy holy name to be abuſed in
ſuch and ſo horrible tranſgraſſions, canſt thou permit

the inuention, euen a blow of the diuel who tormenteth
mankind to be attributed vnto thee, and that thou
who art protector of kings ſhouldeſt be proclaimed
their murderer? Suffer not O Lord ſuch blaſphemies,
but with a ſtripe of thy mightie arme, euen a blow indeede
from heauen, breake the curſed head of theſe
traytors to their king, of theſe bloody paricides who
ſeeke to couer their deteſtable coniuration and conſpiracie
vnder the vayle of thy holy name.
            What an indignity is this, O ye french nation, that
they, who impudent and ſhameleſſe dare yet, though
falſey, cauſe themſelues to be called as you, ſhould bewayle
the death of the Duke of Parma whome they
intitle of happy memorie, a title neuer publickely attributed
to other but kings, and contrariwiſe wiſh vs to beleeue
our deceaſed king to haue bene ſuch a one: that
God who is all good, yea the fountaine of all goodnes
hath cauſed the throat of his annointed to be cut, euen
his who vpon his head did beare the chiefe crowne of
all the nations that are baptized in his name. So that
a petty forrein Prince, the vſurper of Saint Peters patrimony,
is not onely compared with the king of
France, with the king of the Flower de Luce, but is
alſo magnified by the ſame tongue that blaſphemeth
againſt the memory of our deceaſed king. Yet were
this tongue ſpaniſh in ſound as it is in affection, it
were the more tollerable, but a french tongue to be
polluted with ſuch impure ſpeaches. Oh what an indignity?
what a ſorrow.
            The reaſon of theſe ſo contrarie ſpeaches is very
apparant. The death of this Farneſe who ſigned no otherwiſe
but Alexander, haue giuen a great blow at

the affaires of this warre, as finding no ſucceſſor that
can approch to his reputation, ſo that for want of all
others Don Philip hath bene conſtrained to ſet in ſuch
a Captaine as is not otherwiſe knowne but onely that
he hath bene the chiefe executioner of the poore Indians,
by him murdred without reſiſtance, whome alſo
the inhabitants of the country will not receiue as fearing
his extreame cruelty. On the other ſide the Guyſardes
imagined that the death of the late king ſhould
haue brought them to the royalty, and that by their
pollicies they ſhould ſoone diſunite vs each from other,
making vs to beleeue that no man can be a good Catholicke
vnleſſe he be a ſpanyard or a Lorraine, vnleſſe
he weare the red croſſe or the duble croſſe. They haue
aboue two yeares deteyned the people in Paris vpon
an opinion that there was no maſſe ſaid at Tours and
haue drowned thoſe that durſt teſtefy ye contrary. But
ſith all their purpoſes are grounded vpō falſhood, they
be to be excuſed for the cruell puniſhmēt by them inflicted
vpon thoſe that teſtifie the trueth, their capitall ennemy.
            Many who ſince the death of our late king neuer
liued in this city of Paris, may perhaps geue credite to
this declaration by them publiſhed, namely that they
haue labored to bring his Maieſty now raigning into
the boſome of the Church: But we who for theſe foure
yeares haue continually heard their Sermons doe
know the contrary, alſo that they neuer preached vnto
vs any thing ſo much, as that albeit hee ſhould become
as good a Catholike as S. Lewes (theſe bee their very
woordes) the Curate of S. Bennets ſaide in S. Mederickes,
as good a Catholicke as I take him to be,
                yet is hee by no

meanes to be receiued, as being a Relaps and impenitent.
Such as would ſeeme the mildeſt, ſaid. that hee
might be admitted into the Church, but it was requiſite,
for pennance of his fault, that he ſhould reſigne his
crowne to thoſe that had reclaimed him. That hee
might bee a Catholicke, but no king. Thirty thouſand
perſons not onely haue heard but do daily heare theſe
ſpeeches from the mouthes of Boucher and Comolet the
Ieſwiſtes, and yet would they faine perſwade the reſt
of all France yt they haue endeuoured to conuert him.
O ye hipocrites as you are, know you not in your conſciences
that you neuer deſired his conuerſion, but his
eſtate, that you care not whether he haue a crowne in
heauen, ſo you may get yt which he hath vpon earth? do
not your conſciences beare you witneſſe that you could
wiſh that tumulteouſly at his returne from ſome warlike
exploit, he ſhould enter into our church, to the end
for euer hereafter he might be though an Atheiſt, vſing
religion as a cloake to play his perſonage in, and ſo
loſe his credit with all Chriſtian people. In your conſciences
doe you not know that of all things in this
world, you muſt feare leaſt in ſome lawfull counſell by
the working of the holy ghoſt, his errors ſhould be laid
open before him? If you ſtand not in wonderfull feare
therof, why do you ſo ſhrinke away? why had you rather
ſee all France on a flame and ſhortly brought into
combuſtion, and ſo many miſerable perſons ouerwhelmed
with the intollerable burden of theſe tedious
warres, and brought into ſuch pouerty, that
their miſery hath farre ſurmounted the miſery of their
frendes deceaſed? why I ſay had you not rather trie
this remedie which only is proper, and hath bene practiſed

by the ancient fathers in the cure of ſuch diſeazes.
A remedy often times reiterated for one ſelfe error, for
the truth which is alwaies like it ſelfe in all places, and
at all times, is neuer tyed to one onely counſell: A remedy
that might ſerue not him onely, but all other of
his religion. Why I ſay had you not rather vſe this
gentle and holeſome medecine, then fire and ſworde
whereto mans conſcience is no way ſubiect, weapons
doe neuer breed any conuerts, but rather deniers of
their faith. To bodely vlcers bodely matters, and to the
wounds of the ſpirite, ſpirituall remedies doe agree.
To ſeeke by maine force to plucke vp error in religion,
is to ſeeke to cure the ſoule by the body, nay rather to
kil then to cure: by darkeneſſe to ſhew light, and by
cruelty to teach clemency. If yee liſt to deſtroy error, it
is requiſite you ſhould inſtruct the man, and the way
to inſtruct is in a free counſell to heare his reaſons, and
to let him vnderſtand yours.
            Yet if God by the ſucceſſe of your armies, would declare
ye ſame to be acceptable in his ſight: If he would
graunt you great aduantages ouer our king, and miniſter
hope to force ſo many mightie townes, which do
daily encreaſe and fortefie with the ruine and ſpoyles
of our poore Paris, your heat to proſecute your warres
might ſome way be excuſable. But hauing vtterly
loſt a great and notable battaile, euen when yee were
aſſiſted with the power of Spaine, Germany, Switzerland
Lorraine, yea &amp; the ſelfe ſame day as it were miraculoſly
hauing alſo loſt a ſecond battaile in Anuergne. Againe
this laſt yeare the Duke of Ioieuſe one of the principall
pillers of the Spaniſh faction, beeing defeated and
ſlaine in a pitched field with the loſſe of three thouſand

men, either drowned or left dead in the field, among
whome were found all the Capteines of the rebells
throughout the whole country, wherevpon they were
forced to vncoule frier Angell, who in the end ſhall receiue
like recompence for breaking his vowe ſolemnly
made vnto God, as his brother had for violating his
faith to his king, who had ſo highly cheriſhed and exalted
his ingratefull famely. Likewiſe in the ſame
moneth of October the generall of the armie of Lorraine,
hauing loſt both his owne life and his maſters
armie, who were ouercome by a handfull of men, who
for 10000 accompted the Duke of Bouillon for their
head, of whoſe good fortune and aduancement, I
meruel not though the Duke of Lorraine his neighbour
maketh ſo many complaints, conſidering that in ſo
ſhort ſpace he hath already defeated him of two ſtrong
townes &amp; cut in peeces the flower of his men of war,
who now might haue ſtood him in ſome ſteed for the
defence of other his ſtrong holds againſt 12000 men,
and 20 canons that doe lay ſore to them. After I ſay
ſo many great loſſes, and all your great townes ſo
ſtraightly beſeeged, what hope can there remaine, eſpecially
this Alexander of Parma being no longer a
worlds man? True it is that hereafter we may peraduenture
haue ſome ſuccour from the Sauoyan, who
will bring his great forces to aſſiſt his cunning to bee
crowned in our citie of Paris: for he hath maryed one
of the daughters of Spaine: and ſith that by the aduice
of the Doctors of Millan, the Salicke law ought to ſurceaſe,
he hath no doubt a part in the ſucceſſion: for at
Paris there is no prerogatiue of Elderſhip amonge the
daughters, and therefore the towne may well enough

be deuided. Let the eldeſt choſe either the Loure or the
Pallace, the one ſhall hold for Sauoy, the other for Spaine.
But I doubt he hath other matters to thinke vppon,
he ſeeth already the french ancients ſo forward toward
the mideſt of Piedmont, that thirty thouſand canon ſhot
will hardly roote them out, and yet before he come to
that, he muſt winne the field againſt thoſe that haue
profered him battaile any time theſe ſix monethes,
whome he dare not encounter in the plaine field with
al his owne power and the power of his father in law.
This is a very Scipios policie. Our king hath procured
the warre to be tranſported into Affrica, and the
firebrand thereof into the dominions of the Spanyard
and of his ſonne in law, who already intituled himſelfe
Earle of Prouence, from whence he hath found one
of the heires of Gaſton of Foix &amp; of the valeant Nogaret,
that ſhall not onely expell him but alſo proceed further,
&amp; euidently giue him notice of the old prouerbe which
ſaith. That France was neuer ſo weake but a man
might ſtill find ſome cauſe of earneſt fight, and that
either ſoone or late ſhe will giue him to wit that it is
dangerous dealing with her.
            Oh Ingratefull Sauoyan, among all earthly people
the moſt vnthankfull. France reſtored to thy mother,
that which with the ſwordes point and vppon good
cauſe ſhe had taken from thy grandfather, and thou in
liew of acknowledging this magnificence, and in all
manner of good duety, reuerencing the maieſtie of the
french empire, doſt by notable treaſons endeuour to
rent and diſmember the ſame, ſtill conſpiring with
her Capitall enemies. Remember that I doe prognoſticate
vnto thee, that a Spaniſh wife ſhall procure to

thee the loſſe of that which a French wife brought to
thy father, nothing can defend thee. All the cunning
ſpeech of the Archbiſhop of Lions together with the abſtract
of all the ſeditious libells and orations, ſpued out
againſt our kings, &amp; by theſe pentioners of Caſtile, publiſhed
vnder the title of a declaration, can no whit preuaile
with this valeant nobility, whoſe eares and harts
are ſtopped againſt ſuch Mermaids as ſeeke to plonge
them in the goulfe of all miſery. All theſe latter policyes
they take as aſſured arguments that the ſtrength
of this deteſtable conſpiracy draweth to decay. Your
ſelues doe now know that this buſy and ſeditious communalty
is not able to vanquiſh the French nobility,
cannot beare the firſt puſh of their horſes, neither may
any way abide the glims of their gliſtering armour.
What will yee then doe, ſeeke ſome meanes by faire
words to deuide theſe gallant gētlemen among themſelues,
and in a pitcht field procure them to cut each others
throats. Oh what a happy day would that be
vnto you, wherein there ſhould be neuer a blow ſtroken
in vaine: where the loſſe either of the one or the other
ſhould be an equall gaine, and like aduancement
of your drifts, which can haue no ſucceſſe ſo long as
there be any gentlemen in France. They are borne to
liberty, to glory: They can brooke no forrein dominion
or commandement. Any ſpeeches of the king of Spaine,
of the Sauoyan, or of the Lorraines, they cannot heare but
that needes they muſt enter into choller, into indignation,
into threats, yea and into armes to the end to
exalt the name and honour of France aboue all things
in the world. They cānot abide to heare any king but
their owne, intituled the great king, without ouerrunning

of thoſe that dare giue out ſuch ſeruile, Infamous
and baſe ſpeeches. They are not acquainted
with this tytle Vniuerſall king, in whatſoeuer language
it be diſguized: They knowe not that ould tirant
otherwiſe then by the name of kinge of Spaine,
which no man dare now pronounce in their preſence
for feare leaſt at that onely worde they ſhould call to
mind that it is the name of their capitall enemie, the
ſworne enemie to their fathers, the ſame who wrongfully
deteyneth from France the one halfe of her prouinces:
who procured the death of his owne ſonne, and
of his wife the daughter of king Henry the ſecond, and
ſince holpe forward the deathes of his two brother in
lawes, the late Monſieur and our laſt king. Likewiſe
to the end yee may the better know him, he was ſon
to Charles the fift, the poyſoner of the french Dolphine:
who by treaſons ſtole ye greateſt riches of this realme:
who layd the foundations of his tiranny on the citie of
Rome which his ſonne hath ſince perfectly eſtabliſhed &amp;
layd faſt, purchaſing with coyne the voyce of the conſiſtorie
and ſo bringing into the holy ſea his nurcelings
and pentioners, according to the degrees of their affection
to Spayne. Doe you then meruell that their bulles
forged in Madrlt which tooke only their edge at Rome,
wherwith they indeuor to make France through her
diuiſion, tributarie to them, haue beene condemned by
this imperial and ſacred Senate of our king. A ſenate
gouerned by a Cato, repleniſhed with Phocions, and euermore
accuſtomed to reuenge the iniuries of the crowne.
            The french nobility hath ſent ye 
               Marquize of Pizani, to
be aſſured of the truth. If it appeare that Rome is as
ſurely tyed to the Spaniard as Siuill, and that their declarations

can not be well enterteyned, they will well
enough prouide remedies neceſſarie. This is not the
firſt time that the holy ſea hath beene tranſferred to
this ſide of the mountes, albeit I be very well aſſured
there ſhall be no ſuch neceſſitie: For the French ſworde
is ſtrong enough yet once againe to deliuer Rome out
of the hands of this Gothik and Sarrazin ſtocke. Neither
doe we beleeue that all that is beyond the Alpes doth
loue this vniuerſal king, but that contrariwiſe the clearer
that their ſight is naturally, the more they doe apprehend
the effectes of his inſupportable dominion and
the execution of the hereditarie purpoſes of his father
Charles. This French Cath. Nobilitie is of force ſufficiēt
to preſerue both the Eſtate and their Religion, neither
neede they the helpe of theſe ſoueraignes of Spaine, of
Sauoy, or of Lorraine ſo often mētioned in your declaration,
who vnder pretence of ſuccour do ſeeke to driue
them out of the inheritance purchaſed with their anceſters
bloud, ye like whereof haue happened almoſt to all
the natiōs in the world, as hiſtories do teſtifie. Our holy
Cath. Romiſh Religiō is not otherwiſe aſſaulted but
by your wretched League, which withall breedeth Atheiſme,
defloratiō of ſacred virgins, murder of prieſts,
ſacking of Churches in all parts of the Realme: ſo farre
is our king from bringing any alteration whatſoeuer,
or from contrarying his oath euen in the leaſt title, that
contrariwiſe he is carefull of all that cōcerneth our Religion
&amp; the celebratiō of ye holy miſteries as our ſelues.
Witneſſe all the townes that he hath ſubdued vnder
his obedience, in the which it can not be found that he
hath diminiſhed the leaſt relick, or one onely ſacred veſſel.
(yet the moſt part of yours is either moulten, or trāſported

into Arthois) Neither is there any one Religious
perſon or Prieſt, that cōtained him ſelfe within his
habit and his profeſſion, that was euer moleſted, euen
with the leaſt word: whereas yours are either dead for
hunger, or withdrawne into ſuch townes as reſt in his
Maieſties obedience, where they haue bene receaued,
ſuſteined &amp; found acknowledging thoſe things which
they could neuer haue imagined, and which your
falſhoodes and ſlanders continually preached forth did
debarre them the ſight of. Vpon what occaſion, ween
you hath God ſent you theſe great afflictions, this wāt
of all things, eſpecially of ſiluer, but euē to the end that
the people being by litle and litle ſlipped from you and
retired into ſuch townes as reſt in their kings obedience,
ſhould confeſſe their fault and ſimplicitie in that
they haue ſo long ſuffered them ſelues to be abuſed by
theſe enchantments, which made them ſee the things
that neuer were, that made them beleeue that all the
Princes, all the Officers of the Crown, ſo many braue
Lordes and Gentlemen were no longer Catholickes,
becauſe they would not ſtoope to the commandements
of this great Catholicke king, and the letters patents
of Charles of Lorrayne. Is it not for this crime of hereſie
that ye haue robbed and ſpoiled the houſe of Neuers, and
geuen the Dutchie of Rethelois to a Spartaque, whom ye
haue procured to take the title of Duke of Rethelois &amp; Peer
of France? or haue ye ſo euill entreated this Duke of Neuers
at the expreſſe cōmandemēt of the king of Spaine,
who hateth him as much as any Prince vpō the earth,
becauſe that hauing more deeply penetrated and more
manifeſtly reuealed to all France his pernicious practiſes,
to the end to ſtoppe and cōfound them vnder the

protection of our king, he dayly encreaſeth in affection
bringing of valour, couradge, diligence and militarie
diſcretion ſo much as may be deſired. And beſides the
matter which I accoumpt to fulneſſe of all his commē
               dations
is this, yt he bringeth vp his onely ſonne, his
Maieſties coſin germain in extreame diſlike and hatred
of this Spaniſh League.
            Muſt we not alſo as heretickes condemne, excommunicate
and proſcribe Veniſe, Florence, Mantua, Soleure,
Fribourg and other Catholickes our faithfull confederates,
who are ſo preſumptuous as to dare to vndertake
to ſtoppe the encreaſe of your great kings Monarchie,
who alſo will be partakers in the glorious reuendge
of the murder of the firſt Prince of Chriſtendome,
whereto all Europe ſtandeth bound? Beleeue me
this beautifull and gliſtering cloake of Religiō, wherewith
your ambitiō hath bene ſo long ſhadowed is now
threed bare, full of holes, we may ſee through it and euidētly
diſcerne your wretched and pernitious purpoſes.
Now that the incredible felicitie that had guided you
euen to the marke, ſo as ye were ready to mount vnto
the flower Royall, hath forſaken you, whom thinke you
to perſwade to enter into your ſhip halfe broken, when
it is vpon the point of ſhipwracke? Whom wee
                  •
                you to
perſwade to come ſtarue for hunger amōg your ſixtene
robbers, who after the Spaniſh manner hung vp their
chief Iuſtice in the view of all Paris, in the middeſt of
the cōfederates of the conſpiracie of the haulter, whoſe
dagger is at ye throats of all thoſe in whoſe harts there
reſteth any ſparcke of humanitie or clemencie? to be
brief, among ſo many fearefull tokens of Gods wrath,
cruelties, diuiſions, ruines, all ſortes of deſolations,

yea and diſeaſes vtterly new and vnknowen to the
Frēch, of whom you are no longer. How I ſay do you
now thincke to make ſuch poiſons to worke, conſidering
that in Auguſt and September 89. when ye ſeemed
to haue atchieued your affaires, hauing murdered
our king, and with an armie of 30000. men encloſed
his ſucceſſor in Dieppe, after you had publiſhed like
pardons, like abolitions, yet could you not in all finde
aboue three or foure remiſſionaries, and among them
but one onely Gentleman, whoſe name will remaine
infamous among all poſteritie, vnleſſe by ſome notable
ſeruice he waſh away ſo ſhamefull a blot of treaſon cō
               mitted
immediatly after the ſlaughter of his king, his
good maiſter and one who had ſo highly fauored him.
Is it poſſible, Vitry that the tall, pale, and fearefull image
of this great king, ſhould not continually appeare
in thy ſight or follow thee whereſoeuer thou
goeſt? doeſt thou not ſee him with one hand houlding
his bloudie wound, and with the other the red gore
knife, continually following thee to be reuendged of
thy notable trecherie? Is it poſſible that thou canſt
without trēbling and ſighing heare him with a fearefull
voyce obiect vnto thee thy treſpas in theſe wordes?
Oh traitor, while I liued thou diddeſt honor me, but
the next day after my death thou haſt worſhipped my
murderers: thou haſt bowed thy knee in thoſe places
where they deified that monſter more cruell then the
Tygers: thou haſt accompanied thoſe that triumphed
and publickly reioyced in my death? yet doe I more
maruell how our Lieutenant general of the Spaniſh
crowne in France, who ſeeth that in liew of ſo many
Gentlemen that haue habandoned his rebellion and

ranged them ſelues vnder the flower de Luce, he could
not winne paſt two or three in foure yeares, how I ſay
he is now perſwaded that he may deuide the Princes
of the bloud of France, and draw them to his partie. O
ambitious Lorraine, haſt thou dared to thincke that
thou ſhouldeſt haue ſuch ſubiectes to ſtoope to thy commandementes,
or to obey to thy letters patentes, as neceſſarily
they muſt, if they had taken thy ſide? or wilt
thou habandon to them thy Lieutenancie, and ſubmit
thy ſelfe vnder the lawes and Magiſtrats, ouer whom
thou now doeſt ſo proudly commaund in thoſe townes
whcih thy tyrānie doth poſſeſſe? If thou wilt why haſt
thou not ſpoken the word? why haſt thou not ſaid that
thou wert ready to lay away all thy power and to eſtabliſh
them aboue thy ſelfe, and aboue all thy ſtocke of
Lorraine? Thou haſt bene warie inough for proceeding
ſo farre, not that thou art not aſſured that they all are
too magnanimous &amp; too vertuous Princes to League
them ſelues with thoſe that are yet beſprinckeled with
the bloud of the ſlaughter of the eldeſt of their familie
Royall, who loued them as his children: whoſe cruell
and barbarous death all lawes of God and man doe
binde them to reuendge, ſo long as their valiant ſoules
ſhall be encloſed within their bodies: but by ſuch offers,
though fained, thou diddeſt feare to prouoke the ould
tyraunt of Spaine, who abhorreth the whole name of
Bourbon. And indeede what apparance is there of
diuiſion among perſons ſo well vnited? you Lorrains
haue long time directed the heades of your ſpeares againſt
the whole race of Bourbon, and with fire and
ſword doe proſecute ye rooting out of their familie Royall:
When fortune moſt ſmiled vpon you &amp; that you ſeemed

to be vpon the higheſt ſteppe to climbe to the Royaltie,
then did they togither reſiſt you: And now that
all true Frenchmen vpon the opening of their eyes doe
manifeſtly diſcerne in your dri
                  •
               tes with ſuch dexteritie
conducted that whereas your grandfather came into
France weake in goodes, poore in honor, naked in dignitie,
who in the yeare 1522. following the warres
in Picardie vnder the Duke of Vandoſme commanded
onely ouer one companie of men of armes, you in our
adge finde your ſelues among you ſeazed of the moſt
important gouernments of this Eſtate, yea and had it
not bene for the 23. of December 1588. had gone away
with the rule of all France, vnder the commandements
of your maiſter the king of Spaine. Now I ſay
that euery one that is of any calling or courage thoroughout
this Realme, is gathered to his Maieſtie to
chaſtiſe your ambition, the cauſe of ſo many miſeries,
what ground can ye take, to imagine that the Princes
of the bloud ſhould deuide them ſelues, and purchaſe
the ruine and death each of other, to the end to leaue
their roome to the vpſtartes of Lorraine? Well if you
cannot thruſt in the ſpirite of diuiſion into Bourbon,
yet at the leaſt ye will draw vnto you thoſe mighty mē
who within theſe foure yeares, haue ſo often put you ſo
ſhamefully to flight. I thincke the Duke of Aumale
looketh by meanes of this declaration, that this braue
and couragious Lōgueuille, who with leſſe then 1200.
Frenchmen, who ſtanding not vpon th
                  •
               ir number, but
vpon their valour in a pitcht field, ouerthrew him and
all his armie conſiſting of 8000. men and 10. canons
and purſued him euen to S. Denis, ſhall one of theſe
dayes ſend to offer him his ſeruice, deſiring pardon for

his former faultes and craue to be reconciled with his
high and mightie coſin, Lieutenant generall to this
great king the Monarcke of Spaine, France and Italie.
Oh miſerable Leaguers, into what frenſie are
ye entred, when ye thinke with your goodly figures of
Rhetoricke to perſwade thoſe, who in one moneth doe
heare more Maſſes then you do in a yeare: who vnder
the kings auctoritie next to the Princes of his bloud
are the very pillers of the ſtate and of our Religion: to
perſwade them I ſay, that they all are heretickes, and
that none but you onely, who are conſpired with theſe
new Chriſtiās, as yet for the moſt part in hart Iewes
and Sarazins, are true Catholiques: to the end yt therfore
they may yeeld themſelues bound into your hāds,
ſo that without labour ye may in ſhort time roote out
all theſe great and noble houſes, all theſe families fatal
for expulſion of ſtrangers out of France. No, no, if your
Spaniſh remembrances import no other matter, I do
well ſee that this ould dotard is at an end with all his
ſleights, ſith yt to ſubdue France to him ſelfe he craueth
the helpe of the French Gentlemē, who altogither vnder
one ſelfe banner ſeamed of Flower de Luces, haue
ſo often chaſed his Spaniſh troupes, and who as brethren
of one belly, crowned with like garlands atchieued
in ſo many battailes, ſhall for euer be vnited to
maintaine their liberties, franchiſes and preeminences,
which with ſuch woundes and ſo many hazards their
predeceſſors haue left vnto them inſeperably conioyned
with the preſeruation of the crowne vpon the head of
the lawfull heire.
            Courage therfore oh Frenchmē, the victory is yours,
Parma is dead, Ioyeuſe and all his power are layd along,

the Lorraine &amp; the Sauoyan ſhut vp in their capital towns
in liew of giuing doe craue ſuccour at the Leaguers in
France. The horrible conſpiracy againſt Rennes is diſcouered,
the traitors are puniſhed, &amp; the duckats of ſuch
purchaſe of townes are conuerted to our vſe. Behold
Montmorencie marching with a braue army &amp; the ſword
of Frāce in his hād: let vs ſet on wt like courage, a power
deuided yeeldeth no fruict: let euery man endeuour
him ſelfe: cōmon intereſt craueth it &amp; calleth you therto:
your coūtrey inuiteth you: all the vaines of Paris are
ſtopped, it muſt dry vp, vnleſſe our ſelues will noriſh the
rebellion, that is, kindle the fire which conſumeth this
Eſtate. Let ye king remember ye throughout the whole
triumph of Silla the fortunate, there was nothing made
ſo goodly a ſhew as the traine of yt moſt noble and rich
of the Citie of Rome, returning through his victory frō
exile whether ye dregs of ye people had driuen thē, &amp; them
crowned with garlands of flowers did accompany his
triūphāt chariot, calling him their father &amp; ſauiour, becauſe
that by his meanes they returned into their coū
               trey
and recouered their goods, their wiues &amp; their childrē.
The ioy of ſo many good Frēchmē, who ſhall reenter
into Paris will be no leſſe and ye honor infinite times
greater, made firme and aſſured to a lawfull king.
            Let thē all the publicke treaſure be employed to this
effect: let euery one particularly let him ſelfe bloud to
cure this burning feuer: let all theſe Ieſuiſtes ſpeeches,
the onely procurers of a milliō of Frēchmē to ſlay each
other, be ſtopped: let all thoſe that build their particular
purpoſes vpō the publicke calamities (which they hope
for hereafter) be raſed frō among the number of Frēchmen:
let all thoſe, who hauing no feeling of the grief of ye
               
body, do not helpe to relieue it be cut of as rottē mēbers
&amp; the great goods that they enioy with expreſſe charge
to ſuccour ye ſtate in ſuch &amp; ſo vrgēt neceſſities (a charge
by ſolēne oath renewed at euery change) be taken from
them &amp; thēſelues declared vnworthy of nobilitie, &amp; thoſe
goodly inheritāces giuē to thoſe braue Gentlemē, who
for theſe foure yeares haue continually had the cuyrace
on their backes, without whoſe helpe togither with ye
conduct of this great king, ye true French Alexander, we
all ſhould be moſt miſerable bondinē to the Spaniard,
&amp; this we muſt confeſſe: their names ought to be writtē
in goldē letters &amp; ſo conſecrate to the poſteritie, and the
names of ye others withered with perpetual ignominie
to them &amp; all their poſteritie. You Magiſtrates who in
your hands do hold the Iuſtice of Frāce, come in with
ſuch vertue, with ſuch courage, acknowledging ye affectionate
&amp; ſeuerely chaſtiſing the traitors &amp; trechours
to their countrey, yt you may participate in the honor of
the reſtauratiō of the Eſtate. Armies can not be but in
certaine places, neither doe they terrifie any but thoſe
whom they draw neare vnto: the force of Iuſtice at one
ſelfe time penetrateth into all places, yea euen into the
moſt inacceſſible: her ſcarres &amp; woundes are farre more
ſharpe &amp; of longer continuance then thoſe of Bellona. To
be brief, at this time let all thoſe that liſt to liue and dye
Frenchmen, ſet their hands earneſtly to this worke, ſo
excellent, &amp; ſo neceſſarie for the reeſtabliſhment of this
great crown in her firſt eminencie &amp; ancient glory. Let
vs no longer flatter the diſeaſe, &amp; we ſhall ſoone ſee the
wound purged &amp; cured, we ſhal ſpeedely ſee ye end of all
theſe rebelles. We ſhall behold the chariot with the body
of our late king brought frō 
               Compiegne euen into Paris
               
by theſe rebelles euen in their ſhyrtes to the wonderfull
conſolation of all good men. You Syr whoſe memorie
we moiſten with our teares, appeaſe your iuſt
wrath againſt this poore people, againſt your Citie of
Paris, ſometime of you ſo welbeloued, ſo fauored and ſo
enritched: ſhe hath committed the moſt notable ingratitude
&amp; trecherie that euer was or ſhalbe in the world,
but already ſhe hath felt ſuch a puniſhment that the
ſcarres will remaine for euer: caſt the reſt of your indignation,
of your iuſt vengeance vpon the guiltie, pardon
the innocent: Cōfort your ſelfe in yt God hath giuen
you ſuch a ſucceſſor as after your deceaſe will make you
to be acknowledged euen of all thoſe, who in your life
time did diſauow you: who in your Louure will reſtore
your defaced armes and garlands that were pulled
downe, and will exalte your memorie into the higheſt
degree of honor and glorie. Helpe vs alſo by your
prayers to obteine for him at Gods hand ſo
long life, that after the ending of his
owne he may accompliſh the courſe
of your yeares that were cut of.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

