
   
      
         
            Relation of the expongnable attempt and conquest of the yland of Tercera, and all the ylands thereto adioyning: don by Don Albaro de Bacan, Marques of Santa crnz [sic], the cheefe comme[n]dador of Leon, and captayne generall of his Maiestie. And of all the enemies that were in the sayd ylande, and of the bulwarkes, artilerie, and munitions of the citie of Angra, and townes and vilages thereto belonging: and of the dwellers therin, and of all the punishment that was done vpon them. Done in An. 1583
            Bazan, Álvaro de, marquês de Santa Cruz, 1526-1588.
         
         
            
               1583
            
         
         Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00933
            STC 1104
            ESTC S115832
            99851049
            99851049
            16302
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00933)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16302)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 911:04)
         
         
            
               
                  Relation of the expongnable attempt and conquest of the yland of Tercera, and all the ylands thereto adioyning: don by Don Albaro de Bacan, Marques of Santa crnz [sic], the cheefe comme[n]dador of Leon, and captayne generall of his Maiestie. And of all the enemies that were in the sayd ylande, and of the bulwarkes, artilerie, and munitions of the citie of Angra, and townes and vilages thereto belonging: and of the dwellers therin, and of all the punishment that was done vpon them. Done in An. 1583
                  Bazan, Álvaro de, marquês de Santa Cruz, 1526-1588.
               
               [60] p.   
               
                  Printed by Thomas Purfoote,
                  At London :
                  [1583?]
               
               
                  Last leaf blank?.
                  Signatures: A-C D⁴ E² .
                  Reproduction of the original at the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Terceira (Azores) --  History --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-08
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2006-08
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Relation of the expongnable
attempt and conqueſt of the Ylande of
Tercera, and all the Ylands thereto adioyning:
don by Don Albaro de Baçan, Marques
of Santa cruz, the cheefe Commēdador
of Leon, and Captayne generall of his
Maiestie. And of all the enemies that were
in the ſayd Ylande, and of the Bulwarkes,
Artilerie, and Munitions of the Citie of
Angra, and Townes and Vilages thereto
belonging: and of the dwellers therin, and
of all the puniſhment that was done vpon
them.
            Done in An. 1583.
            
               AT LONDON,
Printed by Thomas
Purfoote.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               THurſeday the 23 day of Iune, in
the yeare of our Lord 1583, vpon
the euen of the glorious S. Iohn
Baptiſt, the Marques Santa-cruz
departed out of the riuer of the Citie of Liſburne,
with fyue great ſhippes called Gallions,
and two Galiazes, twelue Gallayes,
30 bigge ſhips, 12 Pataxes, and 15 Zabras,
14 Caruels of Portugall, and ſeuen flat bottomed
barkes to land people: and in all theſe
ſhippes were 8976 ſouldiers, Spaniardes,
Almaynes, and Italions of the companye of
the mayſters of the field, Dō Lope de Figueroa,
Don Françiſco de Bobadilla, &amp; Don Iuan
de Sandouall: And hee that was Coronell of
the Almaynes, was the Earle Geronimo de
Lodron: And the Italions vpon the charge
of Luſio Pinatelo: &amp; ouer a company of Portugals,
was Captaine Don Felix de Aragon.
And there were of Mariners 3823: ſo that
there was in all 12799. and 50 particuler
Gentlemen, and 86 others retayned amongſt
them, and they had ſixe monthes vittayles.
And at ſuch time as this armie did ſet ſayle,
and was going foorth to the Sea, the ſippe
called Santa Maria del Socorro, did ſtrike vpon
the catchippes againſt caſt Calles: in the
which ſhippe was the companye of Don Miguell

de Cordona, &amp; were conſtrayned thereby
to returne agayne into their Port. And
Sonday being the 26, for that the tyme and
weather did ſeeme to be pleaſant and calme,
the Marques was fully reſolued, and did determine
to ſend the twelue Galies before, in
the charge and gouernment of the Captayne
Diego de Mediano. And Monday being the
27 daye, the Vdder of the ſhippe called Santa
Maria de Acoſta, did fall from her, for that it
was not well ſet: and ſtraighte waye they
tooke out of her all the people ſhe had, &amp; put
them into the Pataxes &amp; caried them aſhore:
and ſo all the army did follow their vyage,
with very ſcaſe windes, all vpon the Bowlyne,
till it was Wedneſday the 17 of Iuly,
that they did diſcouer the Iland of S. Mighel.
And vppon the Thurſeday Don Iorge Manrique,
he that was generall ouerſeer of al the
hoſt and armye, went before in a ſmall Pynniſe
for to view the company of the Mayſter
of the field Auguſtin Inigues, and to ordayne
his imbarking in the twelue Gallies which
ariued there the fift day of the ſame moneth,
at the citie of Punta Delgada. And to ordain
all the Artillery and Moiles for to draw and
cary them, with munitions and other neceſſaries
belonging: and likewiſe to make in a

readineſſe the barkes and other thinges fitte
for the vyage. All the whole Nauie was turning
at ſea with calmes &amp; windes that came
of the Ilande, and could not by anye meanes
come to an anker, in which time the Viſeadmirall
did gather togeather al the reſt of the
Nauie, till the thirteenth of the month, at
whithe time they came to an Anker at the
towne of 
                  Ʋillafranca, and citie of Punta Delgada,
in ſight and diſtaunce the one from the
other foure leagues. And from thence the
Marques did paſſe in one of the Gallies vnto
Punta delgada, to vnderſtande the ſtate of
the Ilande, as well as the imbarking of the
2300 Souldiers, whiche they founde in the
muſter of the companye of Auguſtin Iniguez.
And becauſe that the winde was contrarye,
he ſtayde his going till it was thurſeday the
22 of Iulye, and came thither with all the
whole Nauy together on the Saturday, being
the 24 of the ſayd moneth, at nine a clock
of the day: and came to an anker in the play
of the Towne of Sanſebaſtian of the Ilande of
Tercera, nigh vnto the Artilery of the Forts,
who did ſhoote many Canons at the Galyon
wherein the Marques was, and likewiſe at
the reſt of the Nauye as they entred in, for
that the Ilande was fortifyed rounde aboute

with Fortes and Trenches, and very much
people to defend them. And ſtraighte waye
the Marques did ſende a particuler ſouldier
with a Trumpet, to offer vnto the Frenchemen
&amp; Naturalles the pardon and grace that
he would giue them of their liues and goods
as captayne generall: And to giue vnto the
ſtrangers ſhipping and leaue for to departe
with their Enſigns, Armour, Drumme, and
Flute: and he caryed with him the pattents
and pardons in writing, the tenour &amp; fourme
whereof is as followeth.
            
               DOn Albaro de Baçan, Marques of Santacruz,
Commendador, Mayor of Leon,
Captayne generall of the Nauy and armye
for the King Don Philip our Lord, To al thē
that be dwellers, inhabitants, and abiders in
the Iland of Tercera, and in all other places
thereto adioyning, as well ſtrangers as naturalles:
It is well knowne to all, that his
catholick Maieſtie, that being, and as he is,
naturall ſucceſſor of the Kingdomes of Portugall,
the Indies, Orientalles, and of all the Ilands
and other partes comprehended in the
Crowne: and ſo he ought to be acknowledged
and obeyed, for to be Soueraigne King
and Lorde, of all the naturals of theſe kingdomes:

but forgetting their duetye herein,
and farre from this acknowledging, there be
ſome of theſe ſayd Ilandes that hath admitted
into their company, people whiche doeth
not only differ from them in nature, but alſo
in cuſtomes and religion, and hath conſpyred
agaynſt his royall Maieſtie, and hath fallen
into the daunger of Crimen laeſae maiestatis, diuine
and humayne, worthy of exemplar puniſhment:
yet for all this, his catholick Maieſtie
being moued with a chriſtian zeale, and
vſing his accuſtomed clemēcy in the ſeruice
of God our Lord, and in all that in him lyeth
to auoyde effuſion of blood, conſidering that
dayly increaſeth obſtinacie and diſorder, beſides
the offence that they doe vnto God, by
the greate inſolence of the Rebels, and diſobedience
vnto his Maieſtie, &amp; vnto his highe
name. And for that it is a thing whiche toucheth
the ryall conſcience, the breuitie to put
remedy herein, and to take awaye before our
eyes this liuely example of diſobedience, for
that he hath procured by all meanes poſſible
to put remedye therein: and nowe laſt of all
vſing all benignitie, his Maieſtie doeth giue
and graunt grace vnto all the dwellers and
inhabitants in the ſayd Iland of Tercera and
vnto all the reſt hee doeth giue generall pardon,

and ioyntly graunteth with their liues,
ſecuritie of all their goods and Cattles, and
aſſuring more beſides this, that they ſhall
not bee ſacked nor ſpoyled in no kinde of maner,
but rather ſhall be defended in all their
doinges with great quietneffe, vpon condition
that without making any reſiſtance, they
will reduce themſelues, and be ſubiecte and
obedient vnto him, as vnto their naturall
Lord and King, ſuffering and permitting to
diſimbarke alande all the people that doeth
cowe in this ryall Nauy, or ſo many of them
as I ſhal thinke beſt. And moreouer and beſides
all this, in the name of his Maieſtye I
doe offer vnto all Frenchemen, and vnto all
other ſtrangers, of what ſtate and condition
ſoeuer he be, that will depart out of this Ilande,
and goe to his owne countrey, or whether
ſoeuer his pleaſure is, I wil let him depart
liberally and clerely with al his goods
and armour and apparell, and likewiſe I wil
giue them ſhipping if that of their own proproper
will, they wil yield and ſurrender vp
al the fortes that is in their power &amp; charge,
wholy diſmamparing the ſaid Iland. And I
the ſayd Captayne generall, in the name of
his Maieſtie, and by his ryall word, doe promiſe
to perfourme and keepe this publique

pardon, in all, and for all, for that it is the determined
will of the king our Lorde that it
ſhould be ſo obſerued and kept. And here I
do make proteſtatiō, that if you do not keepe
fulfill, and obey all that is herein contained,
but doe perſeuer in your obſtinacie, and forcing
to go forwards with your deſperate intents,
your fault will be the greater, for that
it doth proceede of his owne good will, and
not by any force or conſtraining done herein,
neyther by feare or anye other thing that
might diſturbe him, but your ill purpoſe agaynſt
your naturall king. And I vſing the
power which his Maieſtie in this caſe hath
graunted vnto me, from this time I doe pronounce
thē to be enemies and rebels againſt
their king, and Traytors ſubiecte vnto the
payne whiche they ſhall ſuffer: and here I
doe proteſt, that all publique harmes, chaſtiſmentes
of blood, fyres, deaths, deſtructions,
and deuastaciones yt ſhall be done vpon all thē
that doeth not come to acknowledge their obedience
vnto his Maieſtie, but perſeuer in
their obſtinacie, that it bee not imputed vnto
his ryall Maieſtie nor vnto my charge, but
imputed vnto the default of thoſe that be the
rebels: And for the iuſtifying hereof, and
confuſion of their euill and perpetuall diſhonour,

I do make them this commandement,
for that they may remayne and liue with the
time to ſee a great demonſtration of mercye
and Iuſtice.
            Made in the Gallion the Admirall of this
Nauie, called San Martin, being at the Tercera
the 23 of Iuly 1583.
            
               Don Albaro de Baçan, At the commaundement
of his Lordſhip. Andres de Morales.
            
            The which pardon they would not admit,
but anſwered them with very much ſhotte of
Cannons and harcabuziers. And the better
for to iuſtifie them in this caſe, they ſent vnto
them two Portugals, which they had taken
in the Iland of San Mighel, of thē which
was ſent to ſpye out the Fleete, by Manuel
de Silua in a ſmall barke, by theſe they ſente
the ſecuritie, and neuer hearde anye more of
them. In this tyme the Marques in perſon
did go and view all the Ilande, and had with
him other particuler perſons ſuche as were
ingenious: and in the meane time the Maiſters
of the field, captaynes, and Enſign bearers,
did in diuers partes ſound to armour in
the night, with the Galies and other veſſels
that went with owers procuring for to diſquiet
them. In the end after that they had

taken the iudgementes of thoſe whiche had
ſeene the view, and being fully reſolued, they
entered into counſell, and concluded to giue
the aſſault and enterpriſe in a narrow gut or
creeke which was eaten with water like vnto
a hauen, and was called of the Milles, almoſt
a league from the place where we were
at an anker, and two leagues from the citye
of Angra, and a league from the village of
the Playe: ſo that on tueſday the 26 of Iuly
at 3 of the clocke in the morning, the Marques
did depart with the Galies, carying
forwardes as well as hee coulde, the greate
barkes, Crares and Pyniſes, who by reaſon
that they had ſo much people in them, they
could not profit thēſelues of their owers, for
they caried at their firſt diſimbarking 4500
ſouldiors, of the company of Don Lope de figueroa,
and of theſe captaynes, Auguſtin de
Herrera, Lazaro de Iſla, Pedro Roſado, who
was wounded with a Harquebuz ſhot, and
dyed in the Citie of Angra, Miguel Ferrer,
Diego Coloma, Don Iuan de cordoua, Miguel
de Beneſa, Don Bernardino de çunniga, Sancho
de solis, Don Iuan de Viuero and his Enſigne
bearer, Alonſo de Xeres, (whiche was
one of the two Standard bearers, that did
place the Enſignes vppon their Fortes and

Trenches) and Pedro de Santiſteuan, who
had a Harouebuz ſhot in his legge, in whoſe
company went theſe particuler Gentlemen:
Don Hugo de monçada, Don Godofre de
Mendoça, Don Pedro Henriquez, Don Luyz
Venegas, Don Aluaro de Beneuides Baçan,
Don Iuan de Granada, Mercelo Caracheolo,
Don Geronimo çapata, Don Bernardino de
Mendoça, Don Diego de baça and the Maiſter
of the field, Don Franciſco de Bobadilla:
with the Captaynes Don Antonio de Paſos,
who was the firſt that went vpon the Trenches
and Fortes: Captayne Caſtellani, Iuan
de Texeda, who did vſe the office of the high
Sergeante in all the companies: Diego de
Cardinas, Soto Maior, Buſtamante de Herrera,
Iuan Fernandis de Luna, Diego de Ouiedo:
And with them went theſe Gentlemē. Don
Philip de Cordona, with the mayſter of the
field Don Franciſco de Bobadilla, with them
that went firſt: and Don Alonſo de Rosas, Dō
Gonſalo de Gueuara, Don Frāciſco de Benauides,
Don Antonio de Solis, Don Fernando
de Toledo, Don Franciſco de Guzman, Don
Geronimo de Virues, Dō Iuan de Butrō, Don
Iuan de Piſa, Don Franciſco de Aronda, Don
Pedro Enriquez, the Captayne Melchior de
Eſparça, and the Maiſter of the field Auguſtin

Inigues de çerate: with the Captaynes
Diego Xuarez de ſalazar, Don Chriſtoual de
Açunna, Don Iuan de Caſtillio, Don Fernando
de Viuanco, Antonio Flores, Pedro Ximenez
de Eredia, Chriſtoual de Paz, Franciſco
Calderon, Hernando Pacho, Pedro de Angulo,
and the Enſigne bearer Xaramillo, who
was one of the firſt that put vp their Enſign
in their Trenche: And Gentlemen, Don
Garcia de Cotes, and Don Iuan de Sandoual,
vnder whoſe charge are the ſixteene companies
of Portugalles with their Captaynes,
Geronimo Françes, Manuel de Vega, who receyued
an Harquebuz ſhot in the Trenches,
Antonio Serrano, who alſo had a harquebuz
ſhot &amp; a pricke in his thigh, Diego Valiente,
Don Iuan de Mendoça, Don Iuan de Medrano,
Sancho de Bullon, Don Iuan de Lanuça,
Don Sancho de Eſcobar, Don Eſteuan del Aguila,
Iuan de la rea, Franciſco de la Rocha,
Martin de Herrera, and with them theſe Gentlemen:
Don Pedro Ponce de Leon, Dō Iuan
de caſtelui, Don Franciſco de Borja, Nofre de
Bernegal, (who was the firſt that was ſlayn)
Don Bartolome de Maya, and the Earle Geronimo
de Lodron, with theſe Captaynes:
The Earle Nicolo de Lodron, the captayne
Carlos, the captayne and cheefe Sergeante

               Curcio: and aduenturers, Don Franciſco Perenot,
comēdador de Sparragoſa, of the order
of Alcantara, Mos de la Mota: And Lucio Pinatelo,
with the Italions, and the Captayne
Fray Vicencio of Afflicto, both of them were
wounded with Harquebuziers: and aduenturers,
Miguel Caxa, a Gentleman of Naples,
who being in a barke, hee was wounded
with a Harquebuz ſhot vpō one of his armes,
and Don Felix de Aragon with the company
of Portugals, who was wounded with two
Harquebuz ſhot, one on his ſhoulder, and an
other on his thigh, and they ſlew his Enſign
bearer, and woūded his Sergeant, and Don
Criſtoual Nieto, who was wounded likewiſe
with two Harquebuz ſhot, And at foure a
clock in the morning at the breake of the day
the Marques did enter with his Gallye and
had with him Don Pedro de Tolledo, Marques
of Villa Franca, and Duke of Fernandina,
Don Lope de Figueroa, Don Pedro de Padilla,
Don Iorge Maurique general ouerſeer:
Don Criſtobal de Eraſſo, Dō Iuan Manrique,
Don Luys de Sandoual, Don Alonſo de idiaquez,
Don Luys de Boria, Don Pedro Ponce
de Leon Brothers ſonne vnto the ſayd Marques,
Don Antonio Enriques, Diego de mirā
                  da,
Iuan de Vrbina, Iuan Martines de Recalde,

Don Antonio de Portugal in the ſame, in the
ſight of the Mill to giue aſſault againſt the
forts and trenches, and put themſelues with
the whole bodie of the Galley, where as they
did receiue much ſhotte both of cannons and
muſkets which they did ſhoote from the bulwarks,
then ſtraightway the Galley began
to batter and ouerthrowe the Artillerie of
the enemie, and all the reſt of the Gallies as
they did draw nigh did giue the batterie, ſo
that with the batterie of the Admrial Gally,
&amp; of al the reſt, the other Barks went a ſhore
and did lande people vppon the ſides of the
fortes, and ouerthwart the trenches, although
it was done with great difficultnes
and labour, and the ſoudiours did get vp in
partes and places that was very aſpar and
receiued great repulſe of hargabuſſes and
muſkets: but in the end they did get both the
fortes and trenches which the french Souldiers
had vpon their charge, with their captayne
Borgonion, a perſon of whome they had
a great opinion amongeſt thē. And ſtraighte
waye the Marques wente foorth in a ſmall
barke, and in an other ſmal barke went forth
the Gentlemen that were with him in his
Gallye, and making an ende of the firſt diſimbarking
a Land, they tooke the moūtains

and hilles of all partes, and did ordaine Don
Lope de Figuereo general maiſter of the field
that he ſhould frame the campes with their
wings, with Hargubuziers and Muſkets, ſo
that our people of the maine ward did get vpon
the enemie. And thoſe which were in the
formoſt winges, was Don Pedro de Toledo, &amp;
Don Pedro de Padilla with other Gentlemen
and Captains that were of the company of yt
firſt diſimbarking, ſo that becwixt them they
began to charge many ſkirmeges till ſuche
time as they put themſelues three quarters
of a leage from the Sea ſide, wheras was the
whole force and ſtrength of their Armie, alwaies
ſkirmeſhing very valiantly, charging
and receyuing, ſo that our people did winne
and loſe a place whiche they had for their ſecuritie,
in ſuch ſort, that it was needeful that
the Marques, who was in the face of his armye,
to put himſelfe forward two times for to
courage &amp; animate the harquebuziers. And
at this time the ſecond diſimbarking did ioin
with the firſt, at the which Don Iorge Manrique
ouerſeer generall, returned &amp; made them
to come forewardes, with ſixe Peeces of ordinance
with the which they ſhot at their eenimies,
likewiſe al the reſt of munitions vittals
&amp; water for to refreſh al the people that
was ſkirmiſhing, for that in thoſe parts there

was none to be had but muſt bring it from
the ſhippes, by which diſimbarking they
were ſtrenghthened with theſe Captaines,
Rodrigo de Vargas, Miguel de Oquendo, Marolin
and Carlos, So that they were continually
fighting in the face of the Armies,
and the enemie had eyght peeces of Artillery
with the which they did ſhoote at our people,
making there aſſault in ſtrange maner,
with much ſhrikes and ſhowtes as though
they would ioyne togeather: So in the euening
they did gather togeather to the number
of a thouſand kine or cattell wherewith
they did procure to breake our araye and order,
and the Marques did commaunde the
ſargentes Mayors to giue order vnto the
wi
                  •
               ges of ye Hargubuſſers that they ſhoulde
noe ſhoote of a peece at the cattell, but that
they ſhould make them way without putting
themſelues out of order, and after that they
were paſſed by they ſhould trim them ſelues
againe as before. There was hurt of our
parte in this ſkirmiſh to the number of three
hundred, and ſlaine threeſcore and ten, and
by one Portugall on horſebacke which did
paſſe into our Campe, they did vnderſtande
that amongſt their enemies there were very
many ſlaine and hurte, amougſt whom was

the Liefeteuaunt of Manuel de Silua, his brothers
ſonne and certayne frenche captaynes,
ſo that they as well as the Portugals, were
with a gallante reſolution for to fighte one
power to an other, and would not harken vnto
the pardon and grace which the Maques
did grauntr vnto them, and was preſented vnto
Manuel de Silua by the two men which the
Marques did ſende vnto them, as before is
ſayd
                  •
                ſo that it were euill with them in theſe
ſkyrmeges and other attemptes, although
there was entred to fuccour them a thouſ and
fyue hundred frenchmen, and was generall
ouer them the Commendador Mounsieur de
Chatres, confine vnto the duke of 
                  〈◊〉
                and
brother in law vnto the moſte chriſtian king
of Fraunce, beſides more thē a thouſand that
were there before, ſo that with them, and the
Naturall of the countre, they were nyne Thouſ
ande fighting men, and they were all
very well incamped, and in good order lyke
ſouldiers, and that night our armye was in
good aray, and had well fortifyed the wings
of our Harquebuziers and muſke
                  •
               s, 
                  〈◊〉
               
founde to armoure: ſo in the morning at the
breake of the day, they retourned 
                  〈◊〉
                their
ſkyrmiſhing, and our enemies did diſcharge
their artilerie, and our armye did ſtill gette

more and more, and the winges were ſtill
ſkyrmiſhing, in ſuch ſorte that they did take
away the water from the enemies, &amp; ſtraight
wayes they did win their Artilerie, and the
village of San Sebaſtian, whiche was mayntayned
and kept by their armie, and they fled
away vnto the mountaynes, and when our
hoſte had broken their cāpe, they tooke their
way to the citie of Angra And the Marques
did ſend the galies, that they ſhould aſſaulte
the Nauie of Frenchmen and Portugalles
that was within the Porte: and to the whole
campe did enter into the ſayd citie withoute
any reſiſtaunce, and he did graunte them the
ſpoyle for three dayes, and they did open the
Priſons, and tooke oute of them all ſuche as
were there for bearing fauour vnto his Maieſtie,
and are theſe that followeth.
            
               All ſuch Spanyardes as were Priſoners.
               
                  IVan Auguſtin de Auila was taken Priſoner
a yēre paſt, comming for Factor to S.
Mighell.
               
                  Domingo de inſauraga, which came a yere
paſte from the fyrme lande in the Shippe of
aduiſe.
               
                  
                  Iuan de iada, one that came in the ſame ſhip.
Diego Garcia whome they tooke comming
in aduiſe to Don Pedro de Valdes. The Enſigne
bearer Carrion. The captayne Iuan de
Aguirre, the ſergeant Gutierrez, Iuan Lopez.
Catalina &amp; Eluira Gutierrez, her Daughter
with three ſonnes, that came from Florida in
the ſhip of inſauraga, and to the number of
thirty Spaniards which they made to work
in the Fortes.
            
            
               Portugals that were in priſon.
               
                  The captayne Antonio Rebelo, Pedro Yā
                  nez
Curado, Antonio Mendez, Domingo Ralon,
Iuan Aluarez, Antonio Gonçalez, Luyz
Gonçalez, Franciſco de Roche, Benito Mulato,
Pedro de Las Vinnias, Iuan Domingues,
Conſtantino Machado, Bras Noguera, Gaſpar
Delos Reyes, Diego Perez, Antonio Correa
Piſanso, Diego Aluarez, El Licenciado Iuan
Luys homo, Iuan Yannez, and Frutuoſo, ſanchez
of S. George.
               
               So likewiſe the Galies entered into the
Port of the Citie of Angra, and did take all
theſe ſhippes following.
            
         
         
            
            Relation of the Ships and
other Veſſelles whiche they tooke of the
French army which brought ſuccour to thē
of the iland of Tercera, who was Captaine
generall ouer them all the Commendador
Monſieur de Chattes: and alſo of the Nauy
that Don Antonio had, who was captaine
generall ouer them, Manuuel Serradas a
Portugall and natural of the Yland of Madera:
and was the ſame that did ſack Cabo
Ʋerde and Arguin.
            THere were in the port of the Citie of Angra,
12 french ſhips great and ſmall of al
ſorts. 2 Engliſh ſhips &amp; 1 Hulk. Ther were
of Don Antonio his ſhips to the nūber of 16
ſmall and great, Caruels and others, which
were at Cabo Verde: captayne generall ouer
them, Manuell Serradas, Portugall, all theſe
ſhippes doeth amount to the number of 31,
and had amongeſt them 91 peeces of Artilerye,
of caſt yron and braſſe. This being done
they ſent vnto the caſtell of the citie, and vnto
their houſes of munition, and vnto all the
Fortes round about the Iland, &amp; they found
in them all this ordinaunce and munition as
followeth.
            
               
               In the Caſtell called Sanſebastian.
               One Cannot of batterye, of braſſe: one
Culuerin of braſſe of 21 palmes or ſpannes:
two demy Culuerins of braſſe: two Sacars
of braſſe with their Chambers: one demye
Cannon of braſſe: fiue Peeces of yron, &amp; one
little peece: one Cannon of braſſe broken in
the breeche. All theſe ſayde Peeces were in
the cariage, and had al things in a readineſſe
belonging vnto them.
               Three hoſheads of cannon poulder: 18 bals
of wild fire: 270 ſhot of yron: foure and thirtie
pellet of ſtone. One yron barre: 5 Pikes:
a cariage with his wheeles without a peece:
more, 15 ſtone balles: ſeuenteene charge of
ſtones.
            
            
               ¶Relation of the Fortes which were from the
citie of Angra vnto the Forte called the
poynt of San Mateo, and of al the
Ordinance that were in
them.
               THere was found in the Fort adioining to
the citie, in the ſkirte of Braſill called San
Benito, one great murderer of braſſe to ſhoote
ſtones, in his cariage, and had the Armes of
Portugal on it: one peece of caſt yron, which

wayed 12 kyntals, in his cariage: one other
peece of caſt yron of the ſame bigneſſe without
cariage: one baſe of braſſe with ye armes
of Portugall, of ſeuen kyntals, with chambers:
one demye Cannon of braſſe for-ſtones,
with the Portugall armes: one peece of caſt
yron, of 11 kynt in his cariage: two &amp; twentie
balles of ſtone for the Cannons, and twentie
of yron.
            
            
               ¶What was found in a trenche adioyning vnto
the ſame Forte.
               A peece of caſt yron of 7 kynt. and 24 pound
in his cariage.
            
            
               ¶In the Fort called San Antonio, which is vpon
the poynt of the Braſill.
               One demye Culuering of draſſe, with the
armes of Fraunce, full of flower Delyſes, of
36 kincals, and 22 pound: one peece of braſſe
to ſhoote ſtone, with the armes of Portugall
in his cariage: one Sacar eyght ſquare with
the armes of Fraunce of 19 kyntals: one demye
Sacar of braſſe of 10 kyntals 64 poūd,
in his cariage: one demye Sacar of braſſe of
10 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  li. in his cariage: 1 peece of caſt
yron of 15 kintals in his cariage: two other
peeces of caſt yron of 13 kint. a peece in their
cariages: two Baſes of braſſe verye bigge,
with the their chambers: threeſcore ſhot of yron:

twenty clouen ſhot of lead, ten chains, twenty
great balles of ſtone, two halfe cerſes of
pouder, other ſix horſe load of ſacks of pouder.
            
            
               In an other fort called the çimbrero.
               One Sacar of 15 kintals 48 pound, full
of flower deluſes, three peeces of caſt yron of
the ſame bigneſſe with their carriages, one
falconet of bras in his cariage with two chā
                  bers,
one hundreth and threeſcore baltes of
yron and ſixe charges.
            
            
               In an other fort called the Fanaes.
               One peece of caſte yron of fiue kintals in
his carriage, an other peece of caſt yron of 7
kintals 20 pounde in his carriage, one other
peece of caſt yron of 13 kintals.
            
            
               In an other fort called O alcaide.
               One Sacar of bras eyght ſquare full of
flower deluſes of 18 kintall with a newe cariage:
two peeces of caſt yron ye one of 18 kintals
&amp; the other of 17 kint. with new cariage
and their chargers: eight &amp; thirty ſhot in all.
            
            
               In an other fort called the Ladeoua
de Pero gonçalez.
               Two peeces of caſt yron of 10 kintals a
peece with their newe cariages.
            
            
               In a ſmal fort called La huerta del
Bachilor Rubio.
               Two peeces of caſt yron of 7 kintal a peece

in their cariage: one baſe of caſt yron with
his Chambers: certaine balles, with their
chargers and ſkowrers.
            
            
               In a trenche called Pombado.
               One peece of caſt yron of 10 kintals: his
cariage.
            
            
               In an other for caled the Prayna.
               Three peeces of caſt yron of 10 kintals &amp;
30 pound a peece in their cariages: two double
baſes with their chambers: fiftie balles
of caſt yron, and 10 clouen ſhotte.
            
            
               In a trenche which is harde by the
other forte.
               One peece of caſt yron of ten kintals with
ten balles, with his chargers.
            
            
               In an other fort called the Azogue.
               Two peeces of caſt yron of 10 kint. 30 P. a
peece in their cariage: one other peece of caſt
yron of 9 kint. 20 l, in his cariage: two baſes
of braſſe of 149 Pi. a peece, with crownes and
halfe moones vpon them: 115. ſhot of caſt yron:
100 leade ſhot for the baſes: 10 clouen
ſhot: 12 balles of wilde ſire.
            
            
               In the laſt fort that was viſited
called San Matheo.
               Two Falcons of braſſe with their chambers:
three peeces of caſt yron in their cariages:
two peeces of easie yrnou broken:

two hundreth, ſhot little more or leſſe.
            
            
               In the Frenches about this forte.
               One Peece of caſt yron of a 11 kintals in
his cariage: one other Peece of 7 kintals in
his cariage: one baſe of braſſe, with the arms
of Portugall: one other Peece of caſt yron of
a 11 kint. in his cariage: twenty yron ſhot.
            
            
               Relation of the fortes that is betwixt the Citie
of Angra, vnto the point of the Village
of the Plaie and all the
Artillerie founde
in them.
               In a Trench that is right againſt the Ylandes.
               TWo Peeces of caſt yron in the cariages,
and with their chargers.
            
            
               In a fort called San Antonio de Porto Judio.
               TWo Peeces of braſſe, the one of 25 kint.
43 ll. with the armes of the Turke, and of
Fraunce and the other eight ſquare with the
ſame armes. in their cariages: one Peece of
caſt yron of 10 kintals in his carriage: one other
Peece of caſt yron of 8 kintals 75 ll: one
other Peece of caſt yron of 11 kintals in his
cariage: one hundreth ſhotte.
            
            
               In the fort called El Pico de Saluador Coello.
               One Peece of caſt yron of 18 kintals: one

other Peece of caſt yron of a 11 kintalles in
his cariage without powder or chargers.
            
            
               In the fort called, El Porto de Caſa Salga where
as Don Pedro de Valdes was loſt.
               One Peece of braſſe eyght ſquare with ye
Armes of Fraunce of 18 kintalles 83 ll. in
his cariage: one Falcon with the Armes of
Portugall of 7 kintals: two Peeces of caſt
yron of 15 kintals a Peece in their carriage:
other two Peeces of caſt yron of 13 kintals
a peece in the carriages: one other Peece of
caſt yron of 10 kintalles in his cariage: two
hundreth and thirtie ſhot for them all: a cariage
without any thing.
            
            
               In the fort of the Muelas.
               One Peece of caſt yron in his cariage with
twelue ſhotte: two greate Faulcones with
the Portugall Armes of 6 kintalles a peece:
three Peeces of caſt yron in the cariages:
fiftie ſhot without chargers.
               In the forte right ouer againſt San Sebaſtian,
there was no Artillerie for that they
had caried it away vnto the mountains, that
day the people came a ſhore.
            
            
               In the greate and olde forte of San Sebaſtian
and nowe called
Porto Nouo.
               Six Peeces of caſt yron of 20 kint a peece:

fiue other peeces of caſt yron of 8 kint. a peece
in their cariages. Two hundred ſhot for thē
all: three Baſes: three cariages, and verye
much wood, but no chargers nor poulder.
            
            
               In an other Fort which is at the poynt of the
Ribera Seca.
               One Peece of caſt yron, of 11 kynt. 75 li.
One other Peece of caſt yron, of 7 kyntals.
            
            
               In the Fort of the Perezoſas.
               One demye Culuerin with the armes of
Portugall: one great turkiſh Falcon of 14
kyntals: two Peeces of caſt yron, the one of
11 kyntals, and the other of 7 kyntals, in
their cariages.
            
            
               In the Forte of Porto Martin.
               One Peece of caſt yron of 20 kyntals in his
Cariage: one other Peece of caſt yron of 18
kyntals: three peeces of yron, of 12 kyntals
a peece in their cariages: two baſes of braſſe
with the armes of Portugall. Two hundred
and fiftie ſhot, and three barrels of poulder,
with their chargers.
            
            
               In certaine trenches which were againſt
the Forte.
               Two Falcons for ſtones, with the armes of
Portugall, and their chambers: three peeces
of caſt yron in their cariages: 42 ſhot.
            
            
               In the Fort of Santa Catalina.
               
               One demye Culuer in with the armes of
Fraunce of 35 kyntals in his cariage: One
Falcon of braſſe of 6 kintals with the armes
of Portugall: One Baſe of braſſe with the
ſame armes: Foure peeces of caſt yron of 12
kyntals a peece, in their cariages. 300 ſhot
for all theſe peeces, and their chargers.
            
            
               In the Caſtle called Dopao.
               One demy Culuering with the armes of
Portugall in his cariage. Two greate Pot
gunnes, with all that belougeth vnto them.
            
            
               In the Fort of Medio Faul whiche is
before this.
               Foure peeces of caſt yron, in their cariages:
foure ſcore ſhotte, and their chargers.
            
            
               In the Fort called San Anton.
               Two demye Culuerings of braſſe in their
cariages: one Baſe of braſſe: three Baſes of
braſſe: fiue peeces of caſt yron. Three hundred
ſhot with their chargers.
            
            
               ¶In a Bulwarke which is nigh vnto the Play.
               One peece of caſt yron in his cariage: two
baſes of caſt yron. Sixe and twentie ſhotte
with their chargers.
            
            
               In the Forte called the Chagas.
               One demye Culuerin, eyght ſquare, with
the armes of Fraunce, of 18 kynt. 95 pound
in his cariage: foure peeces of caſt yron of 12

kintals a peece, in their cariages: two great
pot gunnes of yron: 100 ſhot for them all, &amp;
their chambers.
            
            
               In a Fort that is in the Playe called San
Franciſco.
               One peece of caſt yron of 15 kynt. in his
cariage: one other Peece of caſt yron of 14
kint. one other peece of caſte yron of 8 kint.
one other peece of caſt yron of 12 kintals: one
other of caſt yron of 8 kint. all theſe in their
cariages. One barrell of poulder. One hundred
ſhot and chargers for them all.
            
            
               In the Fort called Nueſtra ſennora
de la 
                     ••
                  uz.
               One demy Culuering with the armes of
Portugall, of 28 kyntals in his cariage: one
Baſe of braſſe with the ſame armes, and his
chambers three peeces of caſt yron, of ſixteene
kintalles a peece, in their cariages; 90
balles for all, and their chargers.
            
            
               In the Fort called San Pedro.
               One demye Cannon for ſtones, with the
armes of Portugall, of 13 kintals in his cariage:
one Faulcon of braſſe, with the ſame
armes, and three of Yron: Two Baſes of
braſſe, with their Chambers: two peeces of
caſt yron of fiue kintals a peece in their cariages,
fiftie and foure ſhotte, with all their

chargers.
            
            
               In the Forte called Sauta cruz.
               One cannon of battery of 35 kyntals, 64 l.
with the Turkes armes, and three flower deluſes,
in his Cariage: one other Cannon
for ſtones with the armes of Portugall: one
demy cannō for ſtones, with the ſame arms:
three peeces of caſt yron of 11 kynt, a peece:
two baſes of braſſe with their chābers: two
barrels of poulder. One hundred and eyghte
ſhotte for them all, and all in their cariages,
and with chargers and ſcourers.
            
            
               In the Fort called the Conception.
               Two Cannons of Batterye with the Portugall
armes, in his Carriage: one Baſe of
braſſe in his cariage: two peeces of caſt yron
of 10 kint. a peece in their cariages. Three
ſkore and foure ſhot for them all, with their
chargers.
            
            
               In a trenche which is betwixt the
two fortes.
               Three Baſes of braſſe, and one peece of
caſt yron in his cariage.
            
            
               In a Platforme which is vppon the Poynt, and
thereto they haue viſited.
               One Culuering of braſſe in his Cariage:
One peece of caſt yron in his cariage.
               
                  
In a houſe whiche is in the Village of the
Play, of munition there was more then 600
ſhot of yron, ſmall and great.
               Somewhat afore that there is another fort
called Porto de caſa das alga, which hath foure
peeces, two of braſſe and two of yron. There
is an other Fort before this, called Porto de
cruz, which hath foure Peeces, two of braſſe,
and two of caſt yron. And from one Fort vnto
an other, of al theſe aforeſaid that haue their
Trenches with their trauerſes that doth defend
and keepe them.
            
            
               ¶Relation of the munition that they found in
the high church of the Citie of Angra, and
in the College of the Teatinos.
               THre and twentye hogſheads, the greateſt
full, faſt, and well conditioned, which ſeemed
to be of poulder, nineteene of them were
great, and foure ſmall.
               In the houſe of the Fathers of the company
of Ieſus (which Don Antonio had taken,
and ſome of them he had baniſhed and ſente
into England, for that they were in parte of
his Maieſtie) was founde: two and twentye
hogſheds little and great, full of poulder, 12
of them were faſt ſhut, and al the reſt were open

and ſome of them begon, there was alſo a
ſacke full: foure and thirty balles of wild fire
artificially couered with matches hanging
at them: A cheſt full of braunches of yron for
to make clouen ſhot: Certaine clouen ſhot of
leade of foure and 5 ll. waighte: a ſmall chiſt
of chargers made of white plate: foureſcore &amp;
ten horſe mens ſpeares with their heads, and
ſounde: ten pickes of yron: manie peeces of
corſelets very euill intreated, and ſome olde
hargabuziers: certaine rols of hempen cords
and other bottomes of cotten and of eache a
little: foure Faulcones of braſſe, one greate,
and 3 little ones in the cariages: two greate
chambers of yron: a cloſe wagon for to carrye
poulder: a carriage for a Falcon. Certain
balles of lead for harcabuziers, muſkets, and
Baſes.
            
            
               Relation of that which was founde in the cuſtome
houſe of the Citie of Angra.
               Foure greate hogſheads full of poulder:
Foure hogſheads full of ſalt peter, for to refine
withall, and they ſaye that it is of the Iland
Gracioſa: three hogſheads full of match
for Harcabuziers: certayne balles of yron,
and chaynes, and old ropes endes of hempe:
ſeuen barels of tarre: ſixe cheſtes full of roſin:
two grapels: ſixe kyntals of ſmall tarred

ropes newe: fiue and twentye Oares for
barkes: ſayles for ſhips great and ſmall, as
it ſeemed for ten ſhips: tarred ropes olde and
other neceſſaries for the ſayd ſayies: a great
beame of timber with chaynes, &amp; their ſkuls
whiche belonged vnto the cuſtome houſe: a
little Bell of braſſe broken: an other Bell
whole and ſounde of a meane bigneſſe: two
cheaſtes of wood full of Papers: to the quā
                  titie
of fortie kintals of Biſket, that was nothing
worth: two old Copper Rettles for to
heate tarre in: One Hogſhead with Copperas
one hog ſhead of Allum: one hogſheade
of Rats bane.
            
            
               In a Warehouſe ouer agaynſte the Cuſtome
houſe.
               A great heape of Cannon ſhot of caſt yron
of 1000 ſhot: an other heape of demy cannon
ſhot, and other leſſer ſhotte to the number of
more then foure thouſand: one hundred ſhot
of ſtone and Cannon: one hundred Pickares
of yron with their helues: fyue and twentie
Oares for a Gallie: one hundred and fiftye
wicker baſkets with their gyrts.
            
            
               In an other Ware-houſe was founde as
followeth.
               Two Baſes of yron: old Ropes with pullyes,
and other neceſſaries for ſhippes.
            
            
               
               At the gate towardes the Sea on the left
hande.
               One demye Cannon of braſſe for ſtones
in his Cariage: one Demye Cannon of yron
in his Cariage: one Demye Sacar of
Fraunce, of braſſe, eyght ſquare in his cariage.
So that there was taken and founde in
all the ſhippes, Forts, and in other places as
is ſayd 301 peeces of Artilerie.
               And after that they had taken the citie, Caſtles,
Fortes, artilerie, and munitions, and
giuen to the ſouldiers the ſpoyle for 3 dayes,
as it is ſaid. The Marques did ordain that al
the dwellers &amp; naturals of the Ilande ſhould
returne vnto their houſes, &amp; that they ſhould
vnderſtand in the labour of the field, &amp; tilling
of the ſame, who ſtraight way began to come
together, although but a fewe, and the generall
Auditor did proceede agaynſte thoſe that
were culpable, and did apprehend manye, as
hereafter ſhall bee made mention. In this
time the frenchmen were three leagues from
the citie of Angra, in a ſtrong cituation, the
which they had trenched &amp; made ſtrōg, where
they had water &amp; other commodities &amp; were
treating, with Don Pedro de Padilla, that he
wold let thē depart wt their enſigns &amp; armor,
and to carrye with them ſuch Portugals as

they thought beſt, and all the artilirie which
they broughte out of Fraunce, whiche was
more then one hūdred peeces, and their ſhips
and baſtements, ſaying: that they woulde
ſhow pattents of the king of Fraunce, and of
his mother. To which the Marques woulde
not giue any eare, nor to any thing that was
aſked, but went forth with his campe for to
deſtroy them, but yet after great holde and
keepe, the Marques did reſolue himſelfe at
the inſtance and requeſt of Don Pedro de Toledo,
Don Lope de Figuereo, and of the earle
Geronimo de Lodron, Don Pedro de Padilla,
Don Iorge Manrique, Don Franciſco de Bobadilla,
Don Iuan de Sandouall, Don Criſtoball
de Eraſſo, Iuan de Vrbina, who doeth remayne
for Gouernoure and Mayſter of the
fielde of all the Iland, and of Iuan Martines
de Recalde, that the Frenchmen ſurrendring
and yielding their Enſtgnes, and Armoure,
and to let remayne ſtill in the Galies for to
bee puniſhed, the two hundred whiche before
they had taken, and all the reſt to bee caryed
to the coaſt of Spayne ioyntly with our Nauie,
and from thēce to be caried to their own
countrey, in thoſe ſhippes that the Marques
ſhal think beſt. And ſo wedneſday the thyrde
of Auguſt, Don Pedro de Padilla, &amp; Dō Iorge

Manrique, with the Marques order, wente
vnto their campe, a league from ours, where
when they were come, they brought them vnto
a Fort which was at the waters ſide, nigh
vnto the citie of Angra, whereas they did ſurrender
and yield vp eyghteene Enſignes, the
moſt parte of them of the moſt auntientſte of
Fraunce, and many drums and Flutes, and
they were vnarmed one by one of their Harquebuziers
&amp; muſkets, halberds and Pikes,
and being diſarmed they did paſſe by our armies,
and withoute the Citie they did lodge
them, and gaue them all that was neceſſary:
and the Commendador Monſieur de Chattes,
with the Mayſters of the field, captains, and
cheefe Sargeants as ſhalbe expreſſed, wente
and kiſſed the handes of the Marques.
               
                  Monſieur de Chattes, Generall: Linguadoça
Commendador of San Iuan: Monſieur de carauaques
a Gaſcoyne, mayſter of the fielde.
Baptiſta Serichi, an Italion and chiefe Sergeant.
Captayne Vaſito a Gaſcoyne. Captayne
Hernan, of the Prouince. Captayne
Luys an Italyon. Captain Lauaral a gaſcoin.
Captaine Campani, an Italion. Captain Linerola
a Norman. Capt. Brebito of the Prouince.
Capt. Laſta a Frenchman. Capt. Companion
a frenchman. Capt. Camipit a french

man. Capt. Labarra, a Frenchman. Captayn
Perminet a Frenchman. Captayn Iabino, a
frenchman. Captayn Lagraua a Frenchman.
               In theſe are not counted the captayns that
were ſlayn, nor the Enſigne bearers, for that
there was ſlayne threeſcore &amp; tenne, &amp; wounded
&amp; Priſoners more then 400, beſides the
Portugals, who likewiſe did yeelde and ſurrender
their Enſignes and armes: and it is
a thing neuer the lyke ſeene, ſo great an armye
agaynſte ours, fighting with ſo muche
brauery in their owne countrie &amp; houſes, &amp;
with ſo manye Fortes, &amp; in them more then
300 Peeces of Ordinaunce to come to yeeld
themſelues, certaynly it was a great ſpectakle
to behold. In this time the Marques was
very vigilant &amp; carefull to apprehend Manuel
de Silua, who did titulate himſelfe Earle of
Torres Vedras, Gouernoure &amp; Captayne Generall
of this Ilande, and the principall and
Originall of all theſe Rebellions amongſte
them, and of many robberies and inſolencies
whiche was done with the ſhippes that they
had in the Porte, and Frenchmen &amp; Engliſhe
men whiche came vnto them, and they did
accept and retayne them. So they ſente captaynes
&amp; other ſouldiers vnto diuers parts to
run ouer the hilles and mountaynes, and it

happened thurſeday the fourth of Auguſte, a
captayne of the Fielde of the Mayſter of the
fielde, Don Franciſdo de Bobadilla, did apprehend
him; &amp; did deliuer him vnto the captayn
Lazaro de Iſla, who went alſo to ſeeke him,
and he brought him vnto the citie of Angra,
wheras Don Pedro de Padilla did carry him
abo
                     •
                  rd the Admirall, and did deliuer him to
Iuan Ruyz de Velaſco Captayne of the ſayde
Galiaza, whereas be had likewiſe other captaynes.
Priſoners liefetenants, and ſuche as
were culpable of the rebellion, as ſhalbe declared
vnto you in the puniſhment done vpon
them. And likewiſe certayne Fryers which
went in vndecent habits amongſt them was
Fryer Simon, of the profeſſion of the order of
Saynte Dominicke, Sacerdote, and Preacher,
who did declare that whiche hereafter
followeth.
               How that he went for Fraunce, &amp; did aſke
and &amp; ſuccour of the Queene Mother for this
Iland, and how ſhe did graunt it vnto them,
by the interceſſion of the Duke of Joyoſa, and
of Mos de Rochileu, the Abbot of Guadanni,
the Duke of Prenon, the Earle of Briſac,
Mos de Serlebus, Gouernour of Abre de gracia,
all the which doth ayde, helpe, an ſtrengthen
the cauſes of Dō Antonio. So ye Queene

mother did ſende a thouſande fiue hundreth
frenchmen beſides thoſe that were before in
the Iland with Monſiur de chattres a knight
of the order of Saint Iohn and gouernour of
Deepe, and coſin vnto the Duke of Joyoſa, &amp;
brother lawe vnto the king of Fraunce. And
for maiſter of the fielde, Monſiur de Garabaques,
and Monſiur de Campes, and other principall
men, all which did ariue at this Iland
the two and twenty day of Iune, in this yere
of 1583 with pattents of ye king of Fraunce,
for that the intention of the king and particulerly
of his mother was to haue theſe Ilands
in their powers, and to ſtrengthen them with
men and ſhips, for to diſturbe and take away
the trafficke and commercio of the Indies,
and how that the principals which doth ayde
&amp; helpe Don Antonio are in great hope that
by this meanes they ſhall reape great profite
and intereſt, and nowe ſeeing the diſtruction
and loſſe of victory of the french men, he ſhall
not find any other that will helpe him.
               So likewiſe he was in England, and Antonio
de Vega dwelling in Liſhboorne, who
hath his wife in Caparica, and the Queene
woulde not giue nor graunte vnto them anie
aide or ſuccour, but all onely did conſent that
for his mony he might buy Artilery and munitions

paying for them. Alſo he ſayde that
the twentye of Maye Don Antonio was in
Deepe, and that hee was woonte to goe vnto
Parris in diſembling wiſe with two or three
ſeruants, and did lodge in the houſe of the abbot
of Guadani who is priuat with ye Queene
mother, and for the vittailes for himſelfe and
others which trauails in his ſeruice, they are
merueilous indebted in their lodginges and
Innes, and how that al there remedie did depende
vppon theſe Ilandes, although as it is
ſaide the Queene mother would haue had the
power thereof, and that in ſubſtaunce it was
the voyce of Iacob, and the hands of Eſau, al
ſuch as are in the ſeruice of Don antonio, are
theſe perſons following, and how that in portugall
there are fewe that are coreſpondente
vnto them, for that all in general did abide to
ſee the end &amp; the ſucceſſion herein, in ye which
did depend the quietnes of al chriſtendome.
               Don Antonio de menes, of Liſhborne: Ciprian
de figueredo, of Traſcoſo: Iuan Corea de
Soſa, of Liſhborne: Iuan Rodrigez de vejae, of
Ebora: Thomas Cachero, of Liſhborne: Diego
Rodriguez, of Setubal: Rodrigo de ſantaren, of
Santaren: Diego Botello, of Liſhborn: Manuel
Fernandiz, of Liſhborn: Gaſpar Diaz, chanon
of Ebora: Baltazar Limpo, Deane of Braga: dwelling in 
                     
Guimarans: Simon Alſonſo d
                        •
                     
caruallo of Guimarans: Manuel de brito, of liſh
borne: Conſtantino de brito, of Ebora: Geronimo
de Silua of Viana: Antonio dibrio Pimē
                  tel
of Golagan.
               
               AT ſuch time as they were entred into the
Citie of Angra, wedneſdaye the 7 and 20
of Iuly, as aforeſaide, the Marques of Santa
Cruz did ſend Don Pedro de Toledo, Marques
of Villa franca, Duke of Fernandina, vnto
the Ilande of Fayall, whiche was thirtie
leagues 
                     〈◊〉
                  , wheras was fiue hundred
Frenchmen in gariſon, with twelue Gallies

                     〈◊〉
                   Patares ſixteene Piniſes, and certaine
ſmall Barkes, and in them two thouſand and
fiue hundred ſoldiers of different companies
with the 
                     〈◊〉
                   of the fielde, Auguſtin Iniquez
de çarate, and Captaines, Iuan de ſalazar,
Miguel ferrer, Don Chriſtoval de Açuna,
Don Eſteuan del Aguila, Buſt
                        ••
                     ante de Herrera,
Miguel de benſa, Sancho de ſolis, Don Iuan
de 
                        ••
                     nuza, Sancho de bullon, Luys de guerara,
Pedro pardo de aguiar, Martin de herera
and the Captaine Carlos with one hundred &amp;
fiftie Almains and gentlemen ſuche as were
venturers, Don Vgo de mon çada, Don Iuan
manrique, Don phillippe de cordoua, Don bernardido de mēdoça, Don pedro Enriques, Dō
                     
Gonſalo de Gueuara, Don Hieronimo çapata
Don Pedro Ponza de Leon, Don Iuan de Açunna,
Don Antonio Enriques, Don Gonzaio
Ronquillo, who broughte the newes that the
ſayd Fayal was taken, &amp; Iuan Fernandez Galindo,
Diego de Miranda. And for that was requiſite
at the Sea, theſe captaynes, Miguell
de Oquendo, Rodrigo de Vargas Y Marolin,
Don Antonio de Mēdoça, who in this vyage
had the charge of the pataxes &amp; pyniſes. And
paſſing by the Iland of S George, &amp; the Picke,
reducing them to the ſeruice of his Maieſtie,
they ariued at the ſayd Iland of Fayal, Sonday
being the laſt of the ſayd Moneth, &amp; ſent
them word by a Portugall that they ſhoulde
ſurrender &amp; yeeld themſelues, whō they ſlue.
Vpon the monday they went and viewed the
place where they ſhould diſimbark thēſelues.
So tueſday the 2 of Aug. they put the ſouldiers
aland, &amp; the frenchmē &amp; Portugals did
reſiſt thē, til ſuch time as Don Pedro de Toledo
did ſtrengthē thē that did ſkirmiſh with
200 muſkets, and 100 Pykes, they gaue thē
the repulſe with loſſe of one hundred frenchmen,
and the reſte did retyre and putte themſelues
into the Caſtell, whereas they had 17
great peeces of Ordinaunce, and great ſtore
of poulder and munition, beſides other fortie

Peeces that were in other Fortes there about
them, all the whiche the frenchmen did
ſurrēder and yield vp to ſaue their liues, and
loſte all this, and foure ſhippes that was in
the port, and did yield vp their Enſignes and
arme, And did put into the galies all ſuche
Portugalles as didde enter into the Caſtell
with them, and did hang vp Antonio de Guides,
a portugall, and gouernour of the ſayde
Ilande, a man prodigall and cruell, and lefte
for gouernour thereof for his Maieſtie, Don
Antonio de Portugall, with two hundred ſoldiers,
and vittayles for foure monthes.
               And when they had conquered the Ilands
of S. George, and the Picke, and Fayal,
Don Pedro de Toledo did retourne with the
Galies, ſhippes, and ſuch people as he
caried with him. Mondaye the
eyght of Auguſt
1583.
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                     
                        
                        ¶The Commiſsion giuen
vnto the Licentiado Mosquera, Generall
Auditor of the Nauie and Armie for to puniſh
the Rebels.
                        
                           FOr ſo much as by the commaundemente
of his Maieſtie, I am
come hether with this Nauy and
armye vpon the Iland of Tercera,
and that here they did withſtande mee, and
made reſiſtaunce whereas I ſhould come vnto
an anker with very much artilerie, and not
acknowledging their duetie, but with great
diſobedience and inſolence. I did ſende and
require them with proteſtation for to ſurrender
and yielde vnto me the ylande, and to ſuffer
me to lande in the Ilande, and to pardon
them all the diſobedience paſt, and vnto the
naturals their liues and goods, and likewiſe
vnto the ſtraungers that were come thether
in their ayde and ſuccour, to giue them ſhipping
that they might depart, as doth appeare
by the proteſtes and other writinges whiche
I do cōmaund to bee put adioining vnto this
commiſſion. And for that neyther the one nor
the other would harken vnto this grace and

mercye whiche was offered vnto them, but
rather at ſuche time as I woulde diſimbarke
my army being reweſday the fix and twentie
of this preſent being ſaint Annes day, they
did make defence againſt me, and did reſiſt me
with muche artillery and force of men, and al
that were in the ſaid Iland as well naturals
as ſtraungers did put themſelues in the field
and with their armies in good order, did giue
ye atempt againſt thoſe of his maieſtie which
I had vppon my charge, maintaining themſelues
one whole daye with ſkirmiſhing and
repreſenting of battaile till ſuch time as the
next daye following, being ouercome by the
force of our ſoldiours, they ranne a waye and
put themſelues into the Mountaines. And
for that ſuche lyke diſobedience, rebellion
&amp; tyranny, which vnto this day they haue vſed
with &amp; vnto them whiche hath bene in deuoſion
vnto his Maieſtie, and many other inſolenſies
and roberies which they haue committed
and doone, ſhall not remaine without
liuelye enſample of chaſtiſement. By this
preſente I doe giue power and facultye, as
Captaine generall of his Maieſtie in this
Nauie and Armie vnto Lecenciado Moſquera
de Figueroa, generall auditor of this happie

Armie and Nauie, for that hauing taken
information of the aforeſaide in generall and
in particuler, of all ſuche perſones as bee
founde culpable in the ſame, and the
partyes to be called and heard, and according
vnto the right, to doe Iuſtice vppon their
perſons goodes and Cattelles, for all, and in
all, of defaultes paſte and nowe preſente depending.
I doe giue vnto you power and
facultie in as ample manner as I haue it
of his Maieſtye. And the better to performe
and accompliſh and execute the ſame, I doe
ordayne the cheefe Mayſter of the fielde and
Coronel of the Almaynes, and all the reſte
of the Maiſters of the fielde: Captaynes &amp;
ſoldiours, and of the Gallies, that they doe
giue &amp; deliuer vnto you the priſoners which
they haue, and from this daye forewardes
ſhal haue, &amp; all the ayd and fauoure that you
ſhall demaunde of them. And ſo likewiſe
I doe giue vnto you the ſayde power and facultie
to proceede againſte what ſo euer perſone
or perſones that ſhall withſtande or
diſturbe anye parte or parſell of all that
is aforeſayde, in the whiche GOD and
his Maieſtye ſhall bee ſerued▪ Made
and written in the Ylande of Terçera,
                           
in the citie of Angra, the eyght and twenty of
Iulye, in the yeare of our Lord, 1583.
                        
                           Albaro de Baçan.
At the commaundement of his Lordſhip.
Bartolome de Aguilar.
                     
                  
               
            
            ANd by vertue of this Commiſſion, the
Licenciado Mosquera de Figueroa, did
proceede agaynſt the ſayd Ilands, and particulers
of the ſame, pronounſing theſe ſentences
following.
            In the plyte which in the office of Inſtice
hath ben followed in the abſence of rebellion,
agaynſt the Iland of Tercera, Fayal, the Pick,
and S. George, the Gracioſa, and the Cueruo,
and agaynſt all the dwellers and abiders in
the Iland of the Açores. The proces of the
cauſe being ſeene, and how that the ſayde Ilandes
hath denyed their obedience to their
King Don Philip our Lorde, being their legitime
and natural King, and in proſecuting
hereof, haue admitted into their companye,
people of diuers Nations, Robbers and Pyrats,
and haue conſpyred agaynſt his Maieſtie

Ryall, and made reſiſtaunce agaynſt his
mightye power, and hath defended with armour
and blood, the entrie into theſe Ilands
which is of his crowne of Portugall. The
proſes and caſe, and all thinges requiſite being
ſeene: I do finde, and I ought to declare,
and do declare and pronoūce the ſayd Ilands,
and euery one of them for Rebels, and partakers
of this delyte, in conſequence or confideration
of the which, I oughte to condemne
and doe condemne them in loſſe of all their liberties
which hath bene giuen and graunted
by the kinges predeceſſors, of his maieſtie, of
the kingdome of Portugall, likewiſe of their
proper landes and goods: and other priuileges
of the which they mighte aduaunce and
profite themſelues, if they had not committed
this offence of Rebellion and diſobedience.
And theſe the ſayd Antonio Xuares who was
Factor for the king Don Sebaſtian, &amp; at this
preſent was Iudge of the Mony houſe, Baltazar
Aluarez, Ramires, diſimbargar, and Domingos
Pinnero, and Iuan Gonçales Cottea,
diſimbargar: and all the reſt that bee founde
culpable in this ſayd offence. I do condemne
them, and whēſoeuer and in what place they
ſhal be taken, to be priſoners, and broughte
vnto the common priſon of this citie of Angra,
               
whereas I doe commaunde that they bee
brought forth with ropes about their necks,
with the voyce of a cryer, for to make manifeſt
their faulte, and ſo to bee caryed into the
publique and open place of this citie, whereas
they ſhall be hanged til ſuch time as they
doe naturally die, and ſtraighte waye to bee
quartered, and their quarters to be put in the
high wayes toward this citie. Alſo I do condemne
the aforeſayde in the loſſe of all their
goods, applying them as confiſcate vnto the
chamber of his Maieſtie, and that their ſons
nor Neuewes ſhall not enioy anye Ryall office.
And I doe commaund that all ſuche money
that hath the name of Don Antonio Prior
of Ocrato, with the armes ryall, as falſe euill
and vſurped, to be burned in the publick
place of this citie, and not to bee currante in
theſe Ilandes, and that no perſon doe vſe the
ſame vpon payne of death. (And in the performaunce
of the ſame, they did burne the
ſayd mony publique) And by this my laſt ſē
               tence
difinitiue, I do pronounce &amp; commaund
with coſtes. El Liçenciado Mosquera, de
Figueroa.
            
         
         
            
            Relation of all ſuch as were
put to execution in the Citie of Angra, in
the publique place, the 8 daye of Auguſt,
Anno. 1583.
            
               
                  MAnuel de Silua earle of Torres
Ʋedras, gouernour and
captayne generall of all the
Ilandes of the Acores, for a
tyrannous manſtear, and an
occaſioner of alteratiō in the
Ilands, a robber and receyuer of Heretikes,
was condemned his throte to bee cut, and his
head to be put in the publique place whereas
he commaunded to be put the head of Melchior
Alfonſo, Portugall, for that hee ſayd King
Philip was his natural Lord and king.
            
               Domingos Vguel, an Ordinarye Iuſtice of
this Citie, it was prooued agaynſte him, that
publiquely he did ſhew himſelfe to be againſt
his Maieſtie, and did execute many for ſuſpition

that he found in them to be faythfull and
loyall, in eſpecial vpon Iuan de Betancor, and
of Melchior Alfonſo, who commaunded their
heads to be cut off, which was proued, and he
confeſſed the ſame: hee was hanged, and all
his goods conſiſcate to the chamber, leauing
his ſonnes vnable for any office Ryall.
            
               Pedro Co
                     •
                  e, a Captayne of Don Antonio,
a publique Rebell, who had vpon his charge
a trenche, he was hanged, and his goods con
fiſcate according vnto the other.
            
               Bernardo de Tauora, who was ſometimes
captayn of a galie, and now captaine of footemen,
who had the charge to fortifie the trenches,
and to puniſh &amp; plague thē that woulde
not labour and trauayle, hee was condemned
and hanged.
            
               Anton Fernandez Barroſa, a common maker
of tumultes, and one that publiquelye did
intyſe and prouoke others to take Armes agayn
his maieſty, for the defence of the Ilād,
and ſayd that he did not know him for theyre
naturall king, but Don Antonio, he was cō
               demned
as the reſt.
            
               Arias de Porras, captayne ouer a company,
one of the principal rebellers, &amp; one of the laſt
that did leaue the Campe, was condemned in
the ſame.
            
               
               Manuel Serradas, one that was in Fraunce,
and came in the Fleete with Philip Storcye,
the yeare paſt, and afterward went foorth for
captayne generall in the Fleete that went to
Cabo Ʋerde, and tooke the ſpoyle vnto the ornaments,
challeſes, and croſſes of the church,
his head was cut off.
            
               Gonçalo de Pita, captayne ouer a company,
and liefetenaunt of the fortes of San Sebaſtian,
a publicke perſecuter of them that were
on the kings behalfe, he was hanged.
            
               Mathias Diaz Pilatos, who publiquely with
a loude voyce did perſwade all men to follow
Don Antonio, and at ſuch time as Don Pedro
de Valdes came vnto this Iland, this Mathias
did enter into this citie with a Spaniards
head, and it is publiquely known that he did
eate the liuers of Spaniards, he was hanged
and quartred, and condemned in the loſſe, as
all the reſt.
            
               Baltazar Mulato, the common cryer, he who
did execute the cruel iuſtice which was commanded
to be done by Manuel de Silua, and other
Iudges, did in his proclayminges and
cryes, adde wordes of greate diſobedience againſt
his Maieſtie, was hanged &amp; quartred.
            
               Domingo de Toledo, a captayne of one of
the forts of Porto Nouo, a publique Rebeller,

who alwaies ſaide, Liue the King Don Antonio,
               
and did alwaies beare Manuel de Silua
company, he was hanged.
            
               Gaſpar aluarez chichero, a Mariner who
euer ſince that theſe Ilandes did rebell, hee
went and came from fraunce with the aduiſes
and iudgements of Don Antonio, and caried
priſoners into Fraunce, two perſons yt
came from Liſhborne with Letters from the
Councell for that they ſhould reduce and returne
being a ſedicious perſon, he was hanged.
            
               Amador Biera who came with title of Embaſitor
from his maieſty and fained himſelfe
to be faithfull and lyall, did diſcouer all ſuche
as were currant in all theſe Ilandes, and did
denounce vppon them that they mighte haue
Iuſtice done one them, this had his head cut
off for a traitor, and loſſe of all his goods, and
his ſonnes and neuewes for infamus.
            
               Gaſpar de Gamboa Iuſtice of the Citie of
Angra for that he had condemned to dye in
conformitie with all the reſt of the Iudges,
and apeared that he did fyrme vnto the executions
that were done vpon the Portugalles
that were in part and behalfe of his Maieſty.
And for that he did ſoliſet all their war matters,
hee was condemned to bee hanged, and

loſſe of goods.
            
               Antonio Alaſela chiefe Aunctiente beater
of this Citie and head ſercher, a great rebel,
and a perſecutor of all ſuch as was in his maieſties
behalfe as doth appeare in the proſſes
and bookes, was condemned to bee hanged,
and loſſe of goods.
            
               Anton. Gomez merino ſomtimes of the cuſtome
houſe, ſoliciter and purueier to ordaine
the armour, a rebel, &amp; was condemned in two
hundreth whips and ten yeres to rowe in the
Gallies, and the loſſe of his goods.
            
               Thomas Gomez who publikelye did ſaye
that king Phillip was not his king, but Don
Antonio who had the charche to prouide the
Campe with water in the Armie of our Enemies,
he was condēned in two hundred whips
and ten yeares in the Gallies, and loſſe of his
goods.
            
               Manuel de Acoſta who ſerued Don Antonio,
and went in the publike ſtreets ſpeaking
foule wordes and without reuerence, two hū
               dred
whips and ſixe yeres in the Gallies.
            
               Biaſio de viualdo for ſpeaking of foule
wordes againſt his Maieſtie, and lent monie
to maintaine the warres and was made purueier
of the Army, and cauſed the mony to be
rayſed, was condemned vnto publike ſhame,

and eyght yeares to the Gallies.
            
               Coſme de abreu who was ſeruant vnto the
earle of Bimioſo and nowe was ſeruant vnto
Manuel de Silua, there was prooued againſte
him the generalitie, he was condemned to be
baniſhed out of all the Ilandes and other damages
by mony.
            Many other perſons naturalles of this Iland
for that it was conuenient for the ſeruis
of his Maieſtie and quietneſſe of all the reſte,
were caried vnto the Gallies.
            And of the Frenchmē there were ſome
hanged from ſeuenteene yeares vpwardes, &amp;
put to rowe in the Gallies more then one hū
               dreth
of them that were taken before that the
generall of Fraunce did yield himſelfe with
his company.
            In the meane time that this execuſion
was done, there was great beneuolence ſhowed
vnto certaine widdowes with the goods
of the Rebbels to thoſe that there huſbandes
were put to death in the ſeruice of his Maieſtie,
in the priſons of theſe Ilands, and other
ſome were hanged, and other ſome baniſhed
into England and Fraunce, and tooke away
all their goods and pulled downe their
houſes, ſome of them dyed in the baniſhment.
And likewiſe it was commaunded that there

ſhould reſtitution bee made of the houſe vnto
the fathers of ye cōpany of Ieſus. The which
was pilled and polled by Don Antonio.
            
            So after that they had made this happie
enterpriſe with great reputation of valiantneſſe:
for that there ſhould be no time loſt, the
Marques of Santa Cruz did ſende the twelue
Gallies vnto liſhborn which were the whole
ſubſtance of this enterpriſe. And he remained
gathering together his Nauie, and to ſet in
order the ſtate of this Iland and the reſt, and
placed in them two thouſande ſouldiers, and
for gouernoure ouer them Iuan de Vrbina, a
knight of the order of Santiago. The whiche
and all the reſt of the Ilandes of Açores, was
broughte vnder the ſubiection and obedience
of his Maieſtie, by force of armes, &amp; amongſt
them the citie of Angra, whiche hath more thē
three thouſand houſholders, and a cathedrall
Church, and great traffick with the Indies,
Orientals, and Occidentals, for that it was
the harborow and Port for all their armies.
            So likewiſe they got many other townes
and Vilages, and amongeſt them more then
fiftie fortes, which had in them well nigh to
the number of foure hundred peeces of Artillerye
and other munitions, and fiue and thirtye
ſhippes, ſmall and greate, and ſurrendred

and yeelded vnto them more then three ſcore
Enſigns, which did fight agaynſt them in the
fielde, likewiſe all the armour of the ſtraungers
and naturals. So that al the whole valour
of the Ilands and iuriſdiccion, are condemned
vnto the courteſie, whether his Maieſtie
will ordain or put them, as of the goods
of the rebbles, for that all is iudged and condemned
vnto his crowne all the whiche is of
great value. Made in the Citie of Angra,
in the Ilande of Terçera the
11 day of Auguſt, a thouſand
fiue hundred
eyghtie and
three.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

