
   
      
         
            A divine herball together with a forrest of thornes In five sermons. ... By Tho. Adams.
            Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.
         
         
            
               1616
            
         
         Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00993
            STC 111
            ESTC S100387
            99836229
            99836229
            487
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00993)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 487)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 731:2)
         
         
            
               
                  A divine herball together with a forrest of thornes In five sermons. ... By Tho. Adams.
                  Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.
               
               [8], 157, [3] p.   
               
                  Printed by George Purslowe, for Iohn Budge, and are to be solde at his shop, at the great south-dore of Pauls, and at Brittaines Burse,
                  London :
                  1616.
               
               
                  The first leaf and last leaf are blank.
                  "A divine herball, or, the prayse of fertility. The second sermon"; "The garden or, a contemplation of the herbes. The third sermon"; "The forrest of thornes. The fourth sermon"; "The end of thornes. The fift sermon" each has separatley dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.
                  Reproduction of the original in Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-07
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2003-07
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-08
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A DIVINE
HERBALL
Together with
A Forrest of THORNES. In FIVE SERMONS. 
                  1. The Garden of Graces.
                  2. The prayse of Fertilitie.
                  3. The Contemplation of the Herbes.
                  4. The Forrest of Thornes.
                  5. The end of Thornes.
               
            
            
               By THO. ADAMS.
            
               ESAY 55. 11.
               My word, sayth the Lord, shall not returne
to me void, but shall prosper in the thing wherto I sent it.
            
            
               AVGVST. de benedict. IACO. &amp; ESAV.
               Simul pluit Dominus super segetes, &amp; super spinas: sed segeti pluit
ad horreum, spinis ad ignem: &amp; tamen vna est pluvia.
            
            LONDON,
Printed by George Purslowe, for Iohn Budge, and are to be
solde at his shop, at the great South-dore of Pauls,
and at Brittaines Burse. 1616.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT
Honourable, WILLIAM Earle of
Pembroke, Lord Chamberlaine of his Maiesties household,
and one of his Maiesties most honourable Priuie
Councel, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter:
The most noble embracer, and encourager
of GOODNESSE.
            
               Right Honourable,
            
            
               I Am bolde to present to your Honour a
short contemplation of those Herbes, (cut
in rough pieces) which grow really and
plentifully in your owne Garden: and
giue so good nourishment to your vertues,
delightfull taste to the Church, and odoriferous
sauour to all; that, like the Vine
in Iothams Parable, they cheare the heart of both God &amp; man.
Your Honour, I 
                  •
               now, cannot dislike that in sight, which you
so preserue in sense, and (for a happy reward) doth and shall
preserue you. You are zealously honour'd of all those that know
goodnesse; and haue dayly as many prayers, as the earth
Saints. Into this number I haue (hop
                  •
               fully presuming) thrust
myselfe; as loth to bee hindmost in that acknowledgement,
which is so nobly deserued, and so ioyfully rendred of al tongues:
dedicating to your Honour some publicke deuotions, that can

neuer forget you in my priuate. I will not thinke of adding
one Herbe to your store: I onely desire to remember your Honour
what hand planted them, what dew waters them, what
influence conserues, and enspheares a sweet prouident ayre about
them: and when gay weedes, that shoote vp like Ionas
gourd in a night, shall wither in an houre, (for moriuntur,
quomodo oriuntur) Your Herbe of Grace shall flourish &amp;
be prays'd, both ob eminentiam, and permanentiam; and
at last bee transported into that heauenly Paradise, whence it
receiues the originary roote and being. Your Honour will excuse
mee for coupling to a Diuine Herball, a Forrest of
Thornes; by a true obseruation in both materiall and mystical
Gardens, though a Poet records it.
            Terra salutiferas herbas, eadernque nocentes
            Nutrit, et vrticae proxima soepe rosa est.
            Your Honour will loue the light better, because the darke
night followes so neare it, That your Sunne may neuer set,
your noble Garden neuer wither; that your honours may bee
still multiplied with our most Royall and Religious King on
earth, and with the King of Kings in heauen; is faithfully
prayed for by
            
               Your Honours humbly
deuoted,
THO. ADAMS.
            
         
         
            
               
               To my worthy friend Tho. Adams on his
HERBALL.
               
                  THe Herbes which these dead leaues now bring,
                  Thy liuing voice did sweetly sing.
                  That thy transported Hearers thought
                  A PARADISE before them brought.
                  As if their inward eyes had seene
                  Another EDEN fresh and greene.
                  How they will smell, or taste, thus sent,
                  Will be perceiu'd in the euent.
                  I stay no censures; for my part,
                  May they grow greene still in my hart.
               
               
                  VV. B.
               
            
            
               R. S. His good-speede to the Herball.
               
                  TRuely thou dost the world disclose,
which growes,
                  Promiscuous; here a Thorne, &amp; there a Rose.
                  So shall blacke vices vgly face
adde grace,
                  Vnto the vertue, which shines next in place.
                  So when a stinging Thorne shall wound,
is found,
                  An Herbe to heale the Soule, and make it sound.
               
            
            
               To the diuine Author of the diuine Herball, his
true friend dedicateth this small Encomium of that
which his pen dispaires to prayse.
               
                  HAd ADAM liu'd till this decayed age,
                  And seene an HERBALL so Diuine, and Sage,
                  
                  He would haue sayd, that no succeeding man
                  Might doe for Adam that which Adams can.
                  For while he till'd his Garden, his darke mind
                  In all that compasse no Herbe-Grace could find.
                  This man hath found it; and herein is blest:
                  
                     Adam was good, my Adam's still is best.
               
               
                  W. R. D. of Physicke.
               
            
            
               
               To the prayse of the Herball.
               
                  THe Ground Gods Image, &amp; his word the Raine:
                  
                  His Christ the Sunne, neuer ecclips'd againe:
                  The Cloudes his Ministeriall instruments:
                  His Mercy the all-working influence.
                  From these a Garden of sweete Herbes doth grow,
                  With such a Spring, as shall no Autumne know.
               
               
                  I. STOKES.
               
            
            
               
                  GReat Persons loue a GARDEN for delight;
                  To please their nosthrils, or content their sight.
                  The poore mans state likes it to feast withall.
                  Physicians for the vertues medicinall.
                  For Odour, Ornament, and med'cinal worth,
                  A sweeter HERBALL neuer yet came forth.
               
               
                  
                     Cecinit The. Parny.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
               
                  
                  A
DIVINE
HERBALL
OR
GARDEN
Of
GRACES.
                  
                     HEB. Chap. 6. Vers. 7. 8.
                     
                        For the earth which drinketh in the raine that commeth oft
vpon it, and bringeth forth herbes meet for them by whom
it is dressed, receiueth blessing from God.
                        But that which beareth thornes and bryars, is reiected, and
is nigh vnto cursing, whose end is to be burned.
                     
                  
                  
                     I Presume, heere is no Atheist to
heare and denie;Rom. 1. 16. 
                     The Gospell is
the power of God to saluation. I
hope here is no Libertine; if
there be, let him heare also: It is
the power of God to confusion.

It is a double-edged Sword,
                     Heb. 4. 12. and giues, vel vitam,
vel vindi
                           •
                        tam, either instruction, or destruction.
It is Fire, that doth melt waxe to repentance,
and harden clay to vengeance. It is here a Raine
or Deaw falling on the ground of mans heart;
causing one soyle to bee fertile in good workes,
another to abound with weedes of impiety: For
it returneth not backe to him that sent it, in vaine.
That it conuayes grace to vs, and returnes our
fruitfull gratitude to God, is a high and happy
mercy. That it offers grace to the wicked and by
their corrupt natures occasions greater impietie,
is a heauy but holy iudgement.
                  Not to trauell farre for Diuision, heere lyes
Earth before vs. And as I haue seene in some
places of this Iland, one hedge parts a fruitfull
medow, and a barren heath: so of this Earth,
Man; the same substance for natures constitution,
clay of the same heape in the creating hand of
the Potter; for matter, masse, and stuffe, none
made de meliore luto; though in respect of Eternities
Ordination, some vessels of honour, of disshonour
others; here be two kindes, a good and
a bad soyle: the one a Garden, the other a desart:
the former an inclosure of sweet herbes, excellent
graces: the latter a wild and sauage Forrest
of Bryars and thornes, scratching and wounding
offences.
                  For the better ground we wil consider. 1. The
operatiue meanes, or working cause of the fertility;
the raine that commeth often vpon it. 2. The

thankefull returning of expected fruite; it bringeth
forth herbes meete for them, by whom it is dressed.
3. The reward of mercy; it receiueth blessing
from God.
                  
                  All is an Allegory. The Earth is Man: the
Raine, Gods Word: the herbes are Graces: and the
Blessing, is a sweet retribution and accumulation
of mercie.
                  
                     The Earth
                     IS the best ground that lyes betwixt heauen and
earth, Man: the noblest part of this world:
the worthiest creature, that hath earth for the
pauement, and heauen for the seeling: the Creators
Image; and as some read, his Shadow; which
moues as the body doth, whose it is. When the
body puts forth an arme, the shadow shewes an
arme, &amp;c: so man in his actions and courses depends
vpon the disposition of God, as his allpowerfull
Maker and Mouer. The blessed Deity
(which hath in it a Trinity of most equall and eternall
Persons) is the first and best of all beings:
the holy Angels next: &amp; a Ioue tertius Aiax, man
next them.
                     
                        Ardens conceateth vpon Marke 16.Marke 16. 15. in the Apostles
commission, Goe ye into all the World, and
preach the Gospell to euery Creature; that by this Euery
Creature, is meant Man. For to liuelesse,
senselesse, or reason-lesse things, God neuer enioyned
to preach the Gospell. But man is called

                        Euery creature, because hee hath a participation
of the best in all creatures.
                        * Stones haue a being,
not life: plants haue a being and life, not
sense: beasts haue a being, life, and sense, but
not vnderstanding: Angels haue both being,
life, sense, and vnderstanding. Man participates
with all these in their best. He hath a being with
stones, life with plants, sense with beasts, vnderstanding
with Angels: a sweet abstract or compendium
of all creatures perfections.
                     Let not all this make man proud. Euen this
word Earth, though here vsed in a spiritual sense,
puts him in minde that this excellent man is a
mortall creature. Earth, must bee earth: hot
earth to colde earth: that earth which hath now
a life in it,Iere. 22. 29. to that earth which hath no life in it.
Therefore I will say from the Prophet. O earth,
earth, earth, heare the word of the Lord. Bestow
not too much paines in adorning this perishable
earth, thy flesh: the earth thou must be careful of,
and which God here waters from heauen with
his holy deawes, is thy heart, thy conscience.
                     I could willingly steppe out a little to chide
those, that neglecting Gods Earth, the Soule;
fall to trimming with a curious superstition the
Earths earth, clay and lome: a body of corruption
painted, til it shine like a Lilly (like it in whitenesse,
not in humility,Cant. 2. 1. the candor of beautie; for
the Lilly growes lowe; Lilium conuallium, a flower
of the vallies and bottomes) a little slime done
ouer with a past-boord; rottennesse hidde vnder

golden leaues; stench lapp'd vp in a bundle of
silkes: and by reason of poison suck'd from sinne
and hell, worthy of no better attribute then glorious
damnation. Is there no sicknesse? is there
no disgrace? is there no old age? is there no
death? that you make so much of this earth. Or
doe you desperately resolue to dote on it liuing,
as if you neuer hoped to finde it againe being
dead? Feare not, you shall meet with it againe;
perhaps when you would not. God hath struck
as gallant, as you can make or thinke your selues,
with sodaine, sore, and sure iudgements. Beleeue
it, his hand is his owne. His arme was neuer
yet broken, luxate, or manacled.
                     Woe worth them that haue put Pride and
Couetousnesse fellow-commoners among vs:
for they out-eate vs all, and sta
                           •
                        ue the whole
house of our Land. Couetise would be charitable,
but there is that other summe to make vp.
Pride would giue, or at least forbeare to extort,
but there is a ruffe of the new fashion to bee
bought.* Dignity, a caroch, or strange apparell
is to be purchas'd; and who but the poore tenants
must pay for it! vpon whom they (once so
accoutred) afterward looke betwixt scorne and
anger: and goe as if they were shut vp in wainscote.
                     
                        Sed vitate viros cultum formas
                              
                                 
                              
                              que
                            professos.
                        Quique suas ponunt in statione comas.
                     
                     Such a one will not giue, lest his white hand

should touch the poore beggars: who perhaps
hath a hand cleaner then his; I meane, from aspersions
of bloud, rapine, iniury, briberie, lust
and filthinesse. He cannot intend to pray; for
he is called to dinner iust when his last locke is
hung to his minde. O the monstrous curiositie
of tricking vp this earth of earth! yet from the
Courtier to the Carter, from the Lady to the
Inkle-beggar,* there is this excesse and going beyond
their calling.
                     But I haue strayed out of my way, to cut off
a lappe of Prides garment: I conclude this Earth
with this caution. Respice, aspice, prospice. Looke
back what thou wast: behold what thou art: consider
what thou must be.BERNARD 
                        Recole primordia, attende
media, pr
                              ••
                           uideto nouissima. Haec pudorem adducunt,
illa dolorem ingerunt, ista timorem incutiunt.
Call to mind former things, see the present, foresee
the last. The first will breede in thee shame,
the other griefe, these feare. Remember thou
wert taken out of the earth: behold thy strength
of life subiect to diseases; manifold, manifest,
sensible ones: foresee that thou must dye; this
earth must to earth againe.
                     But the Earth here meant is a diuine, spirituall,
immortall nature; called Earth by a Metaphor,
incapable of suffering terrene fragilitie. This is
Gods Earth, and that in a high and mysticall
sense, though proper enough. Indeed Domini
terra, the earth is the Lords and the fulnes
                              •
                           e thereof,
sayth the Psalmist. But he hath not such respect

to the Earth he made, as to this Earth for whom
he made it. This is Terra sigillata, earth that he
hath sealed and sanctified for himselfe, by setting
his stampe and impression vpon it. Now the
good mans heart is compared to Earth for diuerse
reasons.
                     1. For humilitie. Humus, quasi humilis. The
Earth is the lowest of all elements, and the center
of the world. The godly heart is not so low
in situation; but so lowly in it owne estimation.
God is sayd to hang the earth vpon nothing. Io
                              •
                           .
26.Iob. 26. 7. 
                        He stretcheth out the North ouer the empty place,
and hangeth the Earth vpon nothing: that it might
wholly depend on himselfe. So a true Christian
heart, in regard of it selfe, is founded vpon nothing;
(hath an humble vilipending and disprising
of it owne worth) that it may (ex toto, &amp; ex
tuto)
wholly and safely rely on God. O man of
earth, why exaltest thou thy selfe? this is the way
to preuent and frustrate the exaltation of God.
Keepe thy selfe lowly as the Earth; reiect all opinion
of thy owne worth, and thou shalt one
day ouer-top the cloudes. The Earth is thy mother,
that brought thee forth when thou wert
not: a stage that carries thee whiles thou art: a
tombe that receiues thee when thou art not. It
giues thee originall, harbour, sepulchre. Like a
kind mother, shee beares her off-spring on her
backe; and her brood is her perpetuall burden,
till she receiue them again into the same womb,
from whence she deliuered them. She shall bee

yet more kinde to thee, if her basenesse can teach
thee humility; and keepe thee from being more
proud of other things, then thou canst (with any
reason) be of thy Parentage. Few are proud of
their soules; and none but fooles can bee proud
of their bodies: seeing here is all the difference
betwixt him that walkes, and his floore he walkes
on: Liuing Earth treads vpon dead earth, and
shall at last bee as dead as his pauement. Many
are the fauours that the earth doth vs; yet amongst
them all there is none greater, then the
schooling vs to humility; and working in vs a true
acknowledgement of our owne vilenesse, and so
directing vs to heauen, to find that aboue which
she cannot giue vs below.
                     2. For Patience. The Earth is called Terra,
quia teritur: and this is the naturall earth. For
they distinguish it into 3. sorts. Terra quam terimus:
terra quam gerimus: terra quam quaerimus;
which is the glorious land of Promise. That earth
is cut and wounded with culters and shares; yet
is patient to suffer it, and returnes fruits to those
that ploughed it. The good heart is thus rent
with vexations, and broken with sorrowes; yet
offers the other cheeke to the smiter, endureth all
with a magnanimous patience; assured of that
victory, which comes by suffering, Vincit qui
patitur. Neither is this all: it returns mercy for iniury,
prayers for persecutions, and blesseth them
that cursed it.Psal. 129. 3. 
                        The Plowers plowed vpon my backe:
they made long their furrowes.
                        Psal. 35. 12. 13. 
                        They rewarded mee

euill for good, to the spoyling of my soule. Yet when
they were sicke, my cloathing was sackecloth, I humbled
my soule with fasting: I was heauy, as one
that mourned for his friend or brother; and my
prayer returned into mine owne bosome. When the
heart of our Sauiour was thus ploughed vp with a
speare, it ran streames of mercie, reall mercie;
which his vocall tongue interpreted, Father forgiue
them: they know not what they doe. His bloud
Heb. 12.Heb. 12. 24. had a voice, a mercifull voice, and spake
better things then the bloud of Abel. That cryed
from the cauerns of the earth for reuenge; this
from the Crosse in the sweet tune of compassion
and forgiuenesse. It is a strong argument of a
heart rich in grace, to wrappe and embrace his
iniurer in the armes of loue; as the earth quietly
receiues those dead to buriall, who liuing tore vp
her bowels.
                     3. For faithful Constancie. The Earth is called
Solum; because it stands alone, depending on nothing
but the Makers hand.Eccle. 1. 4. 
                        One generation passeth
away, and another generation commeth; but the
earth abideth for euer. Shee often changeth her
burden, without any sensible mutation of her
selfe.Psa. 119. 90. 
                        Thy faithfulnesse is to all generations: thou
h
                              •
                           st established the Earth, and it standeth. The Hebrew
is, To generation and generation: inferring
that times, and men, and the sonnes of men,
posterity after posterity passe away, but the Earth
whereon, and whereout they passe, abideth. The
parts thereof haue been altered; and violent

Earth-quakes begot in the owne bowels, haue
totterd it.Psal. 104. 5. But God hath layd the foundations of the
earth, (the Originall is, founded it vpon her bases)
that it should not be remoued for euer: the body of
it is immoueable. Such a constant soliditie is in
the faithfull heart; that should it thunder Buls
from Rome, and bolts from heauen, Impau
                              •
                           dum ferient
ruinae. 
                        
                           •
                         Indeede God hath sometimes bent
an angry brow against his owne deare ones; and
then no maruell, if they shudder: if the bones of
Dauid tremble, and the teeth of Hezekiah chatter.
But God will not be long angry with his: and the
balances, at first putting in of the euenest weights,
may be a little swayed, not without some shew of
inequality: which yet after a little motion, settle
themselues in a iust poyse. So the first terrour
hath moued the godly, not remoued them: they
return to themselues, and rest in a resolued peace.
Lord, doe what thou wilt: if thou kill mee, I will
trust in thee. Let vs heare it from him, that had
it from the Lord. Psal. 112.Psal. 112. 6. 
                        Surely he shall not be
moued for euer: the righteous shall bee in euerlasting
remembrance. He shall not be afraide of euill tydings:
his heart is fixed, trusting in the Lord. His heart is
established, &amp;c. Oh sweet description of a constant
soule!
                     
                     They giue diuerse causes of Earth-quakes:
Aristotle among the rest, admits the ecclipse of
the Sun for one; the interposition of the Moones
body hindring some places from his heate. I
know not how certaine this is in Philosophie: 
                           •
                        n

Diuinity it is most true, that onely the ecclipse of
our Sunne, IESVS CHRIST, raiseth Earth-quakes
in our hearts: when that inconstant and
euer-changing body of (the Moone) the world
steppes betwixt our Sunne and vs, and keepes
vs from the kindly vitall heate of his fauour:
then, O then, the earth of our heart quakes; and
we feele a terrour in our bones and bowels, as if
the busie hand of death were searching them.
But no ecclipse lasts long: especially not this:
our Sunne will shine on vs againe: we shall stand
sure,Psal. 129. 1. euen as mount Sion, which cannot be remoued,
but abideth for euer.
                     
                     4. For Charitie. The Earth brings forth food
for all creatures that liue on it. Greene herbe for
the cattell: oyle and wine for man: The vallyes
stand thicke with corne: the Mower filleth his sythe,
and the binder vp of sheaues his bosome. A good
man is so full of charitie: he releeues all without
improuidence to himselfe. He giues plentifully
that all may haue some: not indiscreetly, that
some haue all. On the Earth stand many glorious
Cities, and goodly buildings; faire monuments
of her beauty and adornation. The sanctified
soule, in an happy respondencie, hath manifold
workes of charitie, manifest deedes of piety;
that sweetly become the Faith which he professeth.
                     5. For Riches. The Earth is but poore without:
the surface of it, especially when squalid
winter hath bemired it, seemes poore and barren:

but within, it is full of rich mines, ores of gold,
and quarries of precious minerals. For medals
and mettals, it is abundantly wealthy. The sanctified
heart may seeme poore to the worlds eye,
which only beholds and iudgeth the rinde and
huske, and thinkes there is no treasure in the Cabinet,
because it is couered with leather. But
within hee is full of golden mines, and rich ores;
the inuisible graces of faith, feare, loue, hope,
patience, holinesse: sweeter then the spices of
the East Indies, and richer then the gold of the
West.Psal. 45. 13. 
                        Omnis decor filiae Sion ab intus. The Kings
Daughter is all glorious within. It is not the superficiall
skinne, but the internall beautie, that
moues the King of heauen to bee enamoured of
vs;Cant. 4. 7. and to say, Thou art all faire my Loue: there is
no spot in thee.
                     
                     6. Lastly, for Fertilitie. The Earth is fruitfull:
when the ayre hath giuen influence, the
Clouds showred downe seasonable deawes, and
the Sunne bestowed his kindly heate; loe, the
thankfull earth returnes fruites, and that in abundance.
The Christian soule, hauing receiued
such holy operations, inspirations, and sanctifying
motions from aboue, is neuer found without
a gratefull fertility. Yea, as the Earth to man, so
man to God, returnes a blessed vsurie; tenne for
one; nay sometimes 30. sometimes 60. sometimes
an hundred fold.
                     But the succeeding doctrine will challenge
this demonstration. I haue been somewhat copious

in the first word; the breuity of the rest
shall recompence it. The operatiue cause, that
worketh the good earth to this fruitfulnesse, is a
heauenly Raine that falls oft vpon it: and the earth
doth drinke it vp. Wherein is obseruable, that
the raine doth come, that it is welcome. God
sends it plenteously, and man entertaines it louingly.
It comes oft, and he drinkes it vp. Gods
loue to man is declared in the comming: in the
welcomming, mans loue to God. In the former, we
will consider, 1. The matter. 2. The manner. The
matter that commeth, is Raine. The manner consists
in 3▪ respects. 1. There is mercy, It commeth. It
is not constrained, deserued, pulled downe from
heauen; It commeth. 2. Frequencie, it commeth often:
there is no scanting of this mercy: it flowes
abundantly, as if the windowes of heauen were
opened: Often. 3. Direction of it right, vpon this
earth. It falls not neere it, nor besides it, but vpon
it. To begin with the
                  
                  
                     Raine.
                     GOds Word is often compared to Raine or
Deaw.
                        Deut. 32. 2. 
                        Moses beginnes his Song with My
doctrine shall drop as the raine, my speech shal
distill as the deaw; as the small raine vpon the tender
herbe, and as the showers vpon the grasse. Therfore
in the first verse, he calls to the earth to heare
his voice. Man is the Earth, and his Doctrine the

                        Raine. Mica. 2.Mica. 2. 6. 
                        Prophecie yee not: the originall
word is Drop ye not, &amp;c. Amos 7. 16.Amos 7. 16. 
                        Thou sayest,
Prophecy not against Israel, drop not thy word against
the house of Isaac. Ezek. 21.Ezek. 21. 2. 
                        Sonne of man set thy
face toward Ierusalem, and drop thy word toward the
holy places. The Metaphore is vsuall: wherein
stands the comparison? In 6. concurrences.
                     1. It is the property of Raine to coole heate▪
Experience tels vs, that a sweltring feruour of the
ayre, which almost fryes vs, is allayed by a moderate
shower sent from the clouds. The burning
heate of sinne in vs, and of Gods anger for
sinne against vs, is quenched by the Gospell. It
cooles our intemperate heate of malice, anger,
ambition, auarice, lust; which are burning sins.
                     2. Another effect of Raine, is Thirst quenched.
The drie earth parched with heate, opens
it selfe in refts and cranies, as if it would deuoure
the cloudes for moisture. The Christian soule
thirsts after righteousnesse; is drie at heart till he
can haue the Gospell: a showre of this mercy from
heauen quencheth his thirst: he is satisfied. Whosoeuer
drinketh of the water that I shal giue him, shal
neuer thirst:
                        Ioh. 4. 14. 
                        but it shall bee in him a well of water,
springing vp into euerlasting life.
                     
                     3. Raine doth allay the windes. When the
ayre is in an vprore, and the stoutest Cedars
crouch to the ground before a violent blast; euen
Towers and Cities tremble; a showre of
raine sent from the cloudes mitigates this fury.
When the Potentates of the world, Tyrants, little

better then Diuels, Gog and Magog, Moab and
Ammon, Turkey, Rome, Hell, storme against vs;
God quiets all our feares, secures vs from al their
terrours by a gracious raine, droppes of mercie
in the neuer-fayling promises of the Gospell.
                     4. Raine hath a powerfull efficacy to cleanse
the ayre. When infectious fogges, and contagious
vapours haue filled it full of corruption, the
distilling showres wash away the noysome putrifaction.
We know, that too often filthy fumes
of errors and heresies surge vp in a land, that the
soule of faith is almost stifled, and the vncleannesse
of corrupt doctrine gets a predominant
place: the Lord then droppes his word from heauen:
the pure Raine of his holy Gospell cleanseth
away this putrifaction, and giues new life to the
almost smothered truth. Wo to them then that
would depriue mens soules of the Gospell, and
with-hold the Truth in vnrighteousnesse. When
they locke vp the gates of grace (as Christ reproued
the Lawyers) and labour to make the heauens
brasse, they must needes also make the Earth iron.
How should the earth of mans heart bring forth
fruits, when the raine is with-held from it? No
maruell, if their ayre be poyson'd.
                     5. Raine hath yet another working; to mollifie
a hard matter. The parched and heat-hardned
earth is made soft by the deawes of heauen.
O how hard and obdurate is the heart of man, till
this raine
                              •
                           falls on it. Is the heart couetous? no
teares from distressed eyes can melt a peny out of

it. Is it malicious? no supplications can begge
forbearance of the least wrong. Is it giuen to
drunkennesse? you may melt his body into a
dropsie; before his heart into sobrietie. Is it ambitious?
you may as well treat with Lucifer about
humiliation. Is it factious? a Quire of Angels
cannot sing him into peace. No means on earth
can soften the heart; whether you annoint it with
the supple balmes of entreaties, or thunder against
it the bolts of menaces, or beate it with the
hammer of mortall blowes. Behold! GOD
showres this raine of the Gospell from heauen,
and it is sodainely softned. One Sermon may
pricke him at the heart; one droppe of a Sauiours
bloud distilled on it by the Spirit, in the
preaching of the Word, melts him like waxe.
The Drunkard is made sober, the Adulterer
chaste, Zaccheus mercifull, and raging Paul as
tame as a Lambe.
                     They that haue erst serued the Diuell with an
eager appetite, and were hurried by him with a
voluntary precipitation; haue all their chaines
eaten off by this Aqua fortis: one droppe of this
raine hath broken their fetters; and now all the
powers of hell cannot preuaile against them.
There is a Legend, (I had as good say, a tale) of
an Hermite, that heard (as he imagin'd) all the
Diuels of hell on the other side of the wall, lifting,
and blowing, and groning, as if they were
a remouing the world. The Hermite desires to
see them: admitted, behold, they were all lifting

at a feather, and could not stirre it. The application
may serue; yeeld the fable idle. Satan
and his Armies, Spirits, Lusts, Vanities, Sinnes,
that erst could tosse and blow a man vp and
downe like a feather; and did not sooner present
a wickednesse to his sight, but he was more ready
for action, then they for instigation; now they
cannot stirre him: they may sooner remoue the
world from the pillars, then him from the grace
and mercy of God. The deaw of heauen hath
watred him, and made him grow; and the power
of hell shall not supplant him. The raine of
mercie hath softned his heart, and the heat of
sinne shall neuer harden it.
                     6 Lastly, Raine is one principall subordinate
cause, that all things fructifie. This holy deaw is
the operatiue meanes and working cause, next
vnder the grace of God in our Lord Iesus Christ,
that the soules of Christians should bring forth
the fruits of faith and obedience. I know, God
can saue without it: we dispute not of his power,
but of his worke; of ordinary, not extraordinary
operations. God vsually worketh this in our
hearts by his word. Thus for the matter: the
manner is:

                           1. It commeth.
                           2. Often.
                           3. Vpon it.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        It commeth:
                        IT is not forc'd, nor fetch'd, but comes of his
owne meere mercy, whose it is. Iam. 1.Iames 1. 17. So
sayth the Apostle: Euery good gift, and euery
perfect gift is from aboue, and commeth downe from
the Father of lights. They that want it, haue no
merit of congruity to draw it to them: they that
haue it, haue no merite of condignitie to keepe
it with them. It is the mercy and gratuitall fauour
of God, that this Gospell commeth to vs.
For, if ipsum minus be munus, how highly is this
great gift to be praysed! What deserue we more
then other Nations? They haue as pregnant
wittes, as proportionable bodies, as strong sinewes
as we: and perhaps would bring forth better
fruits. Yet they want it: with vs it is. Wee
need not trauell from Coast to coast, nor iourney
to it; it is come to vs. Venit ad limina virtus:
will you steppe ouer your thresholds, and gather
Manna? When the Gospell was farre off from
our Fathers, yet in them Studium audiendi superabat
taedium accedendi: the desire of hearing it beguiled
the length of the way. But we will scarce
put forth our hand to take this bread: and, as in
some ignorant countrey townes, be more eager
to catch the raine, that falls from the out-side of
the Church in their buckets, then this raine of

grace preached in it, in their hearts. Oh you
wrong vs; wee are fond of it; we call for preaching:
yes, as your forefathers of the blind times
would call apace for holy water; yet when the
Sexton cast it on thē, they would turn away their
faces, and let it fall on their backes. Let God sow
as thicke as he will, you wil come vp thinne. You
will admit frequencie of preaching, but you haue
taken an order with your selues of rare practising.
You are content this Raine should come, as the
next circumstance giues it,
                     
                     
                        Often.
                        GOD hath respect to our infirmities, and
sends vs a plentiful raine. One showre will
not make vs fruitful; it must come oft vpon
us. Gutta cauat lapidem, non vi, sed saepe cadendo.
The raine dints the hard stone, not by violence,
but by oft-falling droppes. Line must be added
to line: here a little and there a little. God could
powre a whole floud on vs at once: but mans
vnderstanding

                              Is like a viall, narrow at the toppe:
                              Not capable of more, then drop by droppe,
                           
Sayes the Poet. If much were powred at once, a
great deale would fall besides, and be spilt. Like
children, wee must bee fed by spoonfulls, according
to the capacity of our weake natures. It is

not an abundant raine falling at once, that makes
the plants grow; but kindly and frequent showers.
One sermon in a yeare contents some throughly;
and God is highly beholding to thē, if they wil sit
out that waking. You desire your fields, your gardens,
your plants to be often watred; your soules
will grow well enough with one raining. How
happy would man be, if hee were as wise for his
soule, as he is for his body! Some there are, that
would heare often, may be too often; til edification
turne to tedification; and get themselues a
multitude of Teachers; but they wil doe nothing.
You shall haue them run ten miles to a Sermon;
but not steppe to their owne dores with a morsell
of bread to a poore brother. They wish wel to the
cause of Christ, but they will doe nothing for it
worth God-a-mercie. The world is full of good
wishes: but heauen only full of good workes. Others
would haue this Raine fall often, so it be such
as they desire it. Such a cloud must giue it, and it
must be begotten in thunder; faction and innouation.Hier. in Ep. ad Galat.
Till Euangelium Christi fit euangelium hominis;
aut quod peius est, Diaboli. Till the Gospell of
Christ be made mans Gospell, or which is worse,
the deuills, If the raine, as it falls, doe not smell
of Nouelty, it shal fall besides them. They regard
not so much heauen whence it comes, as who
brings it. I haue read of two, that meeting at a
Tauem,Manl. fel a tossing their religion about as m
                              •
                           
                           rily
as their cuppes: and much drunken discourse
was of their profession. One protested himself of

Doctor Martins Religion: the other swore, hee
was of Doctor Luthers Religion: whereas Martin
and Luther was one man. No raine shall water
them, but such a mans: otherwise be it neuer so
wholesome, they spew it vp againe. As if their
consciēce were so nice &amp; delicate as that ground
at Coleine,
                           Baron. where some of St. Vrsula's eleuen thousand
Virgins were buried; which will cast vp againe
in the night, any that haue bene interred
there in the day: except of that company, though
it were a child newly baptised. For our selues, the
limits of sobriety being kept, desire wee to heare
the Gospell often; and let our due succeding obedience
iustifie the goodnesse of our thirst. When
Christ spake of the bread of life, the transported
Disciples beseech him, Lord, euermore giue us this
bread.
                           Ioh. 6. 34. So pray wee, Lord euermore showre
down vpon vs this raine.
                        
                     
                     
                        Vpon it.
                        GOd so directs this deaw of his Word, that
it shall fall on our hearts, not besides. The
Raine of the Gospell, like the raine of the
clouds, hath sometimes gone by coasts. Amos 4.Amos 4. 7.
                           I haue with-holden the raine from you, and I haue
caused it to raine vpon one Citie, and caused it not to
raine vpon another Citie: one piece was rained vpon,
and the piece whereupon it rayned not withered.
But I haue wetted your fields, moysten'd your

hearts, with the deawes of heauen, giuen you my
statutes and ordinances,
                           Psa. 147. 20. sayth the Lord: I haue not
dealt so with euery people; there be some that haue
not the knowledge of my lawes. The Sunne shines
on many nations, where this spirituall raine falls
not. This is not all; but as at the last day, two in
one bed shall be diuorced; so euen now one seat
in the Church may holde two, vpon one whereof
this sauing raine may fall, not on the other. The
Spirit blowes where hee pleaseth: and though the
sound of the raine be to all open eares alike, yet
the spirituall deaw drops only into the open hart.
Many come to Iacobs well, but bring no pitchers
with them; wherewith to drawe the water. A
good showre may come on the earth, yet if a man
house himselfe, or bee shrouded vnder a thicke
bush, or borough'd in the ground, hee will be
drie still. God sends downe his raine; one houseth
himselfe in the darkenesse of securitie: hee is
too drowsie to be told in with the bells: Another
sits dallying with the delights of lust vnder
a green bush, a third is borough'd in the ground,
mining and intrenching himselfe in the quest of
riches. Alas, how should the deaw of grace fall
vpon these! Thou wouldst not shelter thy ground
from the clouds, lest it grow barren: oh then keep
not thy soule from the raine of heauen.
                        You haue heard how the raine is come; now
heare how it is made welcome. The good groūd
drinkes it, nay drinkes it in. Imbibit. The comparison
stands thus. The thirsty Land drinkes

vp the raine greedily, which the cloudes poure
vpon it. You would wonder what becomes of it:
you may finde it in your fruites. When your
Vines hang full of clusters, your Gardens stand
thicke with flowers, your Medowes with grasse,
your fields with corne; you will say, the earth
hath been beholden to the heauen. That hath
rained moisture, this hath drunke it in; we see it
in our fruits.Hos. 2. 21. 
                           The Lord sayth, I will heare the heauens,
and they shall heare the earth, and the earth
shall heare the corne, and the wine, and the oyle, and
they shall heare Iezreel. The fruits of corne, wine,
oyle, witnesse that the earth hath heard them, that
heauen hath heard the earth, and that the Lord
hath heard the heauen. The heauens giue influence
to the ground, the ground sappe to the
plants, the plants nourishment to vs, the Lord a
blessing to all. The Lord watereth the hills from
the chambers:
                           Psa. 104. 13 
                           the earth is satisfied with the fruit of
the workes. Hee causeth the grasse to growe for the
cattell, and herbe for the seruice of man: Wine to
make glad his heart, and oyle to make his face shine;
and bread to strengthen mans heart, &amp;c. With such
thirsty appetite, and no lesse happy successe, doth
the good soule swallow the dew of grace. If you
perceiue not when the faithfull take it; you may
see they haue it: for their fruits testifie it. It is a
most euident demonstration, that they haue bin
beholding to the Gospell; they haue a sanctified
life. Drinkes it in.
                        
                        There bee very many great Drinkers in the

world. The maine drunkennesse, that giues denomination
to all the rest, is that throte-drunkennesse:
whereof the Prophet, Vae fortibus ad potandum.
These are they, that will not drinke this
mysticall wine in the Church, so willingly as bee
drunk in the tap-house. Wine-worshippers, that
are at it on their knees, protesting from the bottomes
of their hearts to the bottome of the cups;
if the health be not pledged, actum est de amicitia:
farewell friendship. I haue read of a streete in
Rome, called vicus sobrius, sober street. Find such
a street in any Citie or populous towne in England,
and some good man wil put it in the Chronicle.
                        It hath beene sayd, that the Germanes are
great drinkers; and therefore to Carowse is giuen
to be deriued from them; the word being originally
to Gar-rowse, which is to drinke off all:
Gar signifying totum: so the Germanes are called
by themselues Germanni, quasi toti homines; as if a
Germane were All-man; according to another
denomination of their Country, Allmanie. And
so wee are growne to thinke him, that can tipple
soundly, a tall man, nay all-man from top to toe.
But if England plyes her liquor so fast as shee begins,
Germany is like to loose her Charter. I
haue heard how the Iesuits out-stripp'd the Franciscans.
Indeed Saint Francis at the first meeting
sawe sixe thousand Fryers. Ignatius, because he
could not begin his order with so many, made
vp the number in Diuels. The Germanes had of

vs both priority and number for drunkards. Our
English beggars first got the fashion: but because
their number was short, and it was like that the
Nation would be disgrac'd, it was agreed to make
it vp in Gallants.
                        No maruell, if the Lord for this threaten vs
with the rod of famine, and to scourge vs with
that most smarting string of his whippe. God
hath layd himselfe faire in his bow already, and
is ready to draw this arrow vp to the head, and
send it singing into our bosomes. Ferro saeuior
fames: it is one of Gods sorest iudgements.
Beasts and Sword kill quickly; and the Plague
is not long in dispatching vs: but Dearth is a lingring
death. Lament. 4.Lament. 4. 9 
                           They that be slaine with the
sword, are better then they that be slaine with hunger:
for these pine away, stricken through for want
of the fruits of the field. We see how our seasons
are changed, because we can finde no season to
repentance. Our Springs haue bin graues, rather
then cradles: our Summers haue not shot vp, but
withered our grasse: our Autumnes haue taken
away the flockes of our sheepe. And for our latest
Haruest, wee haue had cause to inuert the
words of our Sauiour, Luke 10.Luke 10. 2. Hee sayth, the
Haruest is great, but the Labourers are few: pray ye
therefore the Lord to send forth more Labourers into
his haruest. But wee might haue sayd: the Labourers
are many, and the haruest is small: pray ye therfore
the Lord to send a greater haruest for the Labourers.
God hath thus, as it were, pulled the Cup

from the Drunkards lippes; and since hee will
know no measure, the Lord wil stint him. If there
will bee no voluntary, there shall be an enforced
fast. Wee haue other great drinkers besides.
                        What say you to those that Drinke vp whole
townes, vnpeople countreys, depopulate villages,
inclose fields? that Pharise-like, swallow vp poore
mens houses, drink their goods, though mingled
with teares of damme and young ones, mother
&amp; children? Are not these horrible drinkers? Sure
God will one day hold the Cup of vengeance to
their lippes, and bid them drinke their fils.
                        The Proud-man is a great drinker. It is not
his belly, but his back, that is the drunkard. He
pincheth the poore, rackes out the other fine,
enhanceth the rent, spends his owne meanes,
and what he can finger besides, vpon clothes. If
his rent-day make euen with his Silkeman, Mercer,
Taylor, he is well. And his white Madam
drinkes deeper then he. The walls of the Citie
are kept in reparation with easier cost, then a Ladies
face, and the appurtenances to her head.
                        The Ambitious is a deepe-drinker: O hee
hath a dry thirst vpon him. He loues the wine of
promotion extremely. Put a whole monopoly
into the cup, and he will carouse it off. There is
a time when other drunkards giue ouer for asleeping-while:
this drinker hath neuer enough.
                        Your grimme Vsurer is a monstrous drinker:
you shall seldome see him drunke at's owne cost:
yet he hath vow'd, not to be sober til his Doomesdaye.

His braines, and his gowne are lin'd with
foxe; hee is euer afoxing. It may be some infernall
spirit hath put loue-pouder in his drinke; for
hee dotes vpon the deuill extremely. Let him
take heed; hee shall one day drinke his owne obligations
and they wil choke him.
                        The Rob-altar is a huge drinker. Hee loues,
like Belshazzar, to drinke only in the goblets of
the Temple. Wo vnto him, he carowses the wine
he neuer swet for, and keeps the poore Minister
thirsty. The tenth sheafe is his dyet: the tenth
fleece (O 'tis a golden fleece he thinkes) is his
drinke: but the wooll shall choke him. Some
drinke downe whole Churches and steeples; but
the bells shall ring in their bellies.
                        Euery couetous worldling is a great drinker: he
swallowes aurum potabil
                                 •
                              
                            as his dyet-drinke. And
like an absolute, dissolute drunkard, the more he
drinks, the dryer he is; for he hath neuer enough.
It may be said of him, as it was of Bonosus, whom
the Emperour Aurelian set to drinke with the
German Embassador; not a man, but a rundlet
fill'd with wine.
                        And my fine precise Artizan, that shunnes a
Tauerne, as the Diuell doth a Crosse, is often as
drunke as the rankest. His language doth not sauour
of the pot; he sweares not, but indeed: but
trust him, and indeed hee will cozen you to your
face. The loue of mony hath made him drunk.
And though the Prouerbe be, In vino veritas;
yet as drunke as he is, you shall neuer haue truth
break out of his lips.
                        
                           
And the vnconscionable Lawyer, that takes
fees on both hands, as if he could not drinke but
with two cuppes at once, is not hee a great drinker?
If what is wanting in the goodnesse of the
cause, be supplied in the greatnes of the fees, O
these
Foecundi calices, quem non fecere disertum?
                        
                        Let all thinke these ebrieties must be accounted
for. How fearefull were it, if a mans latter
end should take him drunke!Luke 21. 34 
                           Take heed to your
selues, lest at any time your hearts bee ouercharged
with surfeting and drunkennesse, and so that day
come vpon you vnawares. In corporall ebriety the
soule leaues a drunken body: in spirituall, the body
leaues a drunken soule; both desperately
fearefull.
                        There is yet a last, and those a blest sort of
Drinkers: which drinke in this sweete raine of
grace and mercie. They doe not onely taste it:
so do the wicked. Verse 4. They haue tasted of the
heauenly gift: they haue tasted of the good word of
God, and of the powers of the world to come. 2. Nor
drinke it onely to their throat, as if they did gargarize
the word; as carnall Politicians, and formall
Professors doe. They must attend, they
must admit, but no further then their throates:
they will but gargarize the Gospell. It shall neuer
come into their stomakes, neuer neere their
hearts. But these drinke it in, digest it in their

consciences; take liberall draughts of it, and do
indeede drinke Healths thereof. Common
health-maintainers drinke their sicknesse. Therefore
sayes the moderne Poet honestly,
Vne salus sanis nullam potare salutem.
                        
                        But this is a sauing health: such as our Sauiour
began to vs; when hee dranke to vs in his owne
bloud, a sauing Health to all Nations. And wee
are bound to pledge him in our owne faith and
thankfulnesse; as Dauid, I will take the cup of saluation,
and blesse the name of the Lord. This is a
hearty draught of the waters of life; the deeper
the sweeter. Blessed he is that drinkes soundly
of it, and with a thirsty appetite. There is, as Diuines
say,Ardens. 
                           sancta ebrietas: such as fell on the blessed
Apostles on Whitsunday. Acts 2. They were
drunke (not with new wine, but) with the holy
Ghost. This holy plenitude doth (as it were) inebriate
the soules of the Saints.Psal. 36. 8. 
                           They shall be abundantly
satisfied with the fatnesse of thy house: and
thou shalt make them drinke of the riuer of thy pleasures.
The Spouse sings of her Sauiours kindnes,
He brought me to the banqueting house,
                           Cant. 2. 4. 5. 
                           and his banner
ouer me, was loue. Stay mee with flagons, and
comfort me with apples, for I am sicke of loue. In the
originall it is called, House of wine. Christ hath
broached to his Church the sweet wines of the
Gospell, and our hearts are cheared with it; our
soules made merry with flagons of mercie

Come to this wine,Cant. 5. 1. 
                           bibite &amp; inebriamini: eate
O friends, drinke, yea drinke abundantly, O beloued:
drinke and be drunke with it. God will be pleased
with this (and no other but this) Drunkennes.
                        
                        The vessell of our heart being once thus filled
with grace, shall hereafter be replenished
with glorie.
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  A DIVINE
Herball,
Or,
THE PRAYSE OF
FERTILITY. The SECOND SERMON.
                  
                     MATH. 25. 29.
                     Vnto euerie one that hath shall be giuen, and he shall haue
abundance.
                  
                  
                     AVGVST.
                     Magnae Virtutis est, cum foelicitate luctari:
                     Magnae foelicitatis est, à foelicitate non vinci.
                  
                  LONDON,
Printed by George Purslowe, for Iohn Budge, and are to be
solde at his shop, at the great South-dore of Pauls,
and at Brittaines Burse. 1616.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                  A
DIVINE
HERBALL,
OR
The prayse of Fertillitie.
                  THE
SECOND SERMON.
                  
                     HEB. Chap. 6. Vers. 7.
                     For the earth which drinketh in the raine that commeth oft
vpon it, and bringeth forth herbes meet for them by whom
it is dressed, receiueth blessing from God.
                  
                  
                     THAT difference which the
Philosophers put betweene
learning and mettals, wee
may truly find betweene humane
writings and Gods
Scriptures conferred. They
that digge in the one, finde
Paruum in magno, a little gold in a great deale of

ore. They that digge in this rich field (which
the wise Merchant solde all hee had to purchase)
finde Magnum in pa
                           •
                         no, much treasure in a few
words.
                  Wee haue heard how the good earth is beholding
to God for his holy Raine: the next
circumstance obiects to our meditation this
earths thankfull fertility. It bringeth forth herbes
meete for them by whom it is dressed. Euery word
transcends the other; and as it excludes some vicious
defect, so demonstrates it also some graduall
vertue.
                  1. It brings forth. It is not barren like a dead
ground that yeelds neither herbes nor weedes.
This is no idle heart, that doth neither good nor
harme; that like a meere spectator of the world,
sits by with a silent contemplation for whom
was made that Epitaph:

                        Here lyes he, was borne and cryed,
                        Liu'd threescore yeares, fell sicke and dyed.
                     
                  
                  Doing neither profit nor preiudice to the Countrey
hee liued in. Heere is no such stupid neutralitie,
nor infructuous deadnesse. It brings
forth.
                  
                  2. They are not weedes it produceth, but
herbes. A man had as good do nothing, as doe
naughty things. It is lesse euill to sit still, then to
runne swift by in the pursuite of wickednes. They
that forbeare Idlenesse, and fall to lewdnesse,

mend the matter, as the Diuell (in the tale) mended
his dames legge; when he should haue put
it in ioynt, he broke it quite in pieces. It is not
enough that this ground brings forth, but that it
yeelds herbes. Of the two, the barren earth is
not so euill as the wicked earth: that men pittie,
this they curse. It brings forth herbes.
                  
                  3. Neither is it a paucity of herbes this ground
affordeth, but an abundance: not one herbe, but
herbes; a plurall and plentifull number. There
is neyther barrennesse nor barenesse in this
ground; not no fruites, not few fruits, but many
herbes.
                  
                  4. Lastly, they are such herbes, as are meet for
the dresser: such as God expects of the garden,
who planted it: such as hee will accept, not in
strict iustice for their owne worth, but in great
mercy for Iesus Christ. Meet for them by whom it
is dressed.
                  
                  We haue now opened the mine, let vs digg
                        •
                     
for the treasure. Foure demonstrations commend
this good Ground.
                     
                        1. It is fruitfull.
                        2. It is fruitfull in good.
                        3. It is fruitfull in much good.
                        4. It is fruitfull in such good, as the Dresser
lookes for.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     1. Fertillitie. It brings forth.
                     BArrennesse hath euer beene helde a curse,
a shame, a reproch. So the mother of
Iohn Baptist insinuated, Luke 1.Luke 1. 25. 
                        Thus
hath the Lord dealt with me in the dayes wherein he
looked on mee, to take away my reproach among men.
When God will bring the Gospell, and with it
saluation to the Gentiles, he is sayd to take away
their barrennesse. So was it prophecied, Esay, 54.
1. So was it accomplished, Galat. 4. 27. Reioyce
thou barren that bearest not, breake forth and crye
(with ioy) thou that trauellest not: for the desolate
hath many moe children, then she that hath an husband.
The primordial praise of this good ground
is, that it is not barren. This Fertillitie in the
Christian heart, doth 1. conclude thankfulnesse.
2. exclude idlenesse.
                     1. For the former; GOD hath giuen him
Raine for this purpose, that he should bring forth
fruite: if hee should take the raine, and not answere
the senders hopes, he were vnthankful. The
good man considers the end why he receiued any
blessing, and examines what God meant in
conferring on him such a benefite. Hath God
giuen him wisedome? Salomen hath taught him
to Let his fountaines be dispersed abroad,
                        Pro
                              •
                           . 5. 16. 
                        and his riuers
of waters in the streets. Whether thy knowledge

be great in diuine things, tanquam luminare
maius; or in humane, tanquam luminare minus;
remember our Sauiours lesson Math.
                        Mat. 5. 15. 5▪ Put not
your light vnder a bushell, but vpon a candlesticke;
that it may giue light to all that are in the 
                              〈◊〉
                           . Let
your light shine before men, &amp;c. They that are
Gods lights, must waste themselues to giue light
to others.Aug. Conf. lib. 12. cap. 25. 
                        Non licct habere priuatā, ne priue
                              •
                           ur 
                              •
                           a.
To keep it priuate is the way to be depriued of it.
So the old verse. Scire tuum nihil est, nisi te scire hoc
sciat alter. As we must not be wise in our selues,
so nor onely wise to ourselues. Hee that conceales
his knowledge, cancels it, and shall at last
turne foole. Doe not inclose that for seuerall,
which God hath meant common. The not imploying
will be the impayring of Gods giftes.
                     This is the fruite, which the good ground must
send forth for all the feeds of grace sowne in it.
Neither doth this instruction bound it selfe with
our spirituall; but extend also to our temporall
gifts. Hast thou riches? when God scattered
those blessings vpon thee, in the seed-time of his
bountie, he intended thou shouldst returne him
a good croppe at the haruest. Be thankfull then,
in doing that with them for which God gaue
them. Custos es tuarum, non dominus, facultatum.
Thou art a deputed Steward, not an independant
Lord of thy wealth. God ment them to promoue,
and helpe forward thy iourney to heauen;
let them not retard thy course, or put thee quite
out of the way. Thou art a thankfull ground, if

thou suffer thy riches to bring forth those fruites,
which the hand of God lookes to gather from
them. 
                           〈◊〉
                         mercifull; be charitable; be helpfull.
Stips pauperum, the saurus diuitum. The rich mans
treasure is the poore mans stocke. The distressed
soule asks but his owne. Christ may say to thee
in the Beggars person; Pay (not giue) me a penny
thou owest me. Da mihi ex eo quod tibi dedi:
de meo quaero,
                        Chrys. 
                        non de tuo: da &amp; redde: Giue mee
of that which I gaue thee: I demaund some of
my owne, not of thine: it is more properly a restoring
then a gift. Petimus
                              
                                 
                              
                              que
                            damus
                              
                                 
                              
                              que
                            vicissim.
Thou askest the Lord, and he giueth thee: but
on this condition, that thou giue him some of it
backe againe. Thou art more truly the beggar:
and God but a demaunder of a iust and easie retribution.
This is not all.
                     God did also meane, that thy selfe should take
comfort in these things. It is a part of that Blessednesse,
                        Psal. 128. 2.
which the Psalmist promiseth to him that
feareth the Lord. Thou shalt eate the labour of thine
hands: happy shalt thou be, and it shall bee well with
thee. For God gaue wine (for this purpose) to
make glad the heart of man,
                        Psal. 104. 15 
                        and oyle to make his face
shine, and bread to strengthen his heart. How doth
man diuert Gods goodnesse, when he turnes his
blessing into a curse, and puts his good creatures
from their intended vses! The Lambes are for thy
cloathing,
                        Prou. 27. 25. 
                        and the Goates are the price of thy field,
sayth the Wise-man. Thou must weare the
wooll, and drinke the milke of thy owne flocke.

Neither be so sparing, as to starue thy selfe in the
middest of thine owne plenty. As the couetous
wretch, that dares not eate an egge, lest he should
loose a chicken. Nor so profuse to thy own lusts,
that thou shouldst giue all, vel veneri, vel ventri:
not that surfets or wine should sluce out thy estate
into thy belly. Not that with vnnecessary
quarrels of lawe, thou shouldst afflict and weary
thy neighbours. O madnesse! that to put out
both thy brothers eies, thou shouldst put out one
of thine owne: nay, both thine owne for one of
his. Ingratefull men for Gods great mercy; that
what they get by peace with forraines, vainly
spend it in ciuill warres: where the Lawyers set
them together, as men clappe on vnwilling Mastiues!
Most commonly they fight at the long
weapon, a tedious, wearying, weather-beaten
sute. Sometimes they fight close; Poniard and
Pistoll, killing quarrells: laying traynes for one
another, till both be blowne vp. Can the backe
of charitie beare no loade? Are the sinewes of
loue growne so feeble? Alas fooles! you get
both nothing but the blowes; the Lawyer goes
away with the victory. He fills his purse, and you
come home both well beaten.
                     Well, the good ground knowes no such end
for Gods blessings. He sees with the eye of faith,
another intentionall and internall meaning for
such bountie. He doth not say of his riches, as
the Atheists of their tongues. Psal. 12.Psal. 12. 4. 
                        They are
our owne. What hath Magistrate on the bench,

or Preacher in the pulpit, or friend in priuate, to
do with it? I waste none of theirs: let me doe
with my owne, as I lift. But sayth the Apostle.
Foole, what hast thou, that thou hast not receiued?
And wherefore hast thou receiued them? To satiate
thy owne lusts? or to bring forth fruit mee
                              •
                           
for them, by whom thou art dressed? There is nothing,
that a man can properly and in district
termes call his owne, but his sinnes. His impieties,
weaknesses, ignoranc
                           •
                        s, vices, lusts; these
are his owne. All good things are Gods giftes,
Iames 1. 17. Bee thankfull then, and after the
raine of mercy, bring forth the herbes of obedience.
You see what this Fertillitie concludes; Thankfulnesse.
Heare now what it excludes.
                     2. Idlenesse. This good ground lyes not dead
and barren: nor returnes all heauens raine with
a naked and neutrall acceptation: it brings forth.
You read, Luke 19.Luke 19. of a Seruant, to whom when
his Lord had intrusted a Talent, he hidde it in the
ground, as an Vsurer his money, to keepe it safe.
And at his Lords returne, Domine ecce tuum: hee
answered his account with, Lord behold thine own.
I knew that thou wert seuerus Magister, a hard
Master: therfore I thought it my securest course,
to make good thine owne againe. But the Lord
replyed, Ex ore tuo: Oh euill seruant, out of thy
owne mouth I condemne thee. Thou shouldst then
haue answered my austeritie, with thy laborious
care of my aduantage. Therefore heare his
doome.Mat. 25. 30. 
                        Cast ye the vnprofitable seruant into outer

darknesse: there shall bee weeping and gnashing of
teeth. Hee did not euill with his talent: no, it
was enough to condemne him, he did nothing.
There is abundance of this dead ground in the
world, which brings forth nothing. Idle wretches,
that sleepe out time and admonition: but
their damnation sleepeth not.
                        2. Pet. 2. 3. It was neuer sayd,
Samson hath lost his strength, till hee slept in the
lappe of Dalila. Idlenesse doth neither get nor
saue: there is nothing more emptie of good
fruits, nor more abundantly pregnant with euill.
That man doth ill, that doth nothing; and he looseth,
whiles hee gaines not. Many beholding
with cowardly and carnall eyes, what a long and
t
                           •
                        oublesome iourney it is to heauen, sit them
downe and fall fast asleepe. O barren grounds!
will ye bring forth nothing? Is difficulty made
your hindrance, that should bee a spurre to your
more eager contention? Know you not, that the
violent shall get the kingdome of heauen? Some
can follow their dogges all day in the fielde: others
hunt Mammon dry-foote in their shoppes
yeare after yeare, and neuer complaine of wearinesse.
Only an houre or two in the Church puts
an ach into our bones; as if nothing wearyed vs
so soone as well-doing. Is it feare of too much labour,
that keepes you from God? why doth not
the same reason deterre you from seruing the diuell?
His lawes are true burdens, and his seruice
drudgerie.Mat. 11. 30. But Christs yoke is easie, and his burden
light.
                     
                     
                        
I'may boldly affirme it: your couetous man
takes more paines to goe to hell, then the godly
ordinarily to get to heauen. He riseth early, and
resteth late, and eates the course bread of sorrow:
and after tedious and odious miserie, goes to the
Diuell for his labour. Shall we refuse easier pains,
for a farre better recompence? It is but Satans
subtiltie, that makes men beleeue the passage to
life so extremely difficult, that it is impossible.
Herein the Diuell doth like the inhospitable Sauages
of some countries, that make strange fires,
and a shew of dismall terrors vpon the shores, to
keepe passengers from landing. The Sluggard,
sayes Salomon, doth but faine Beares and Lyons,
(as the superstitious doth bugges) in the way; as
apologies of idlenesse, that he may sit still and be
at ease. The slothfull person is the Diuels shop,
wherein he worketh engines of destruction. He
is most busie in the lazie.Eccles. 9. 10. 
                        But whatsoeuer thy hand
findeth to doe, doe it with thy might: for there is no
worke nor knowledge, nor deuice, nor wisedome in the
graue whither thou goest. If thy soule be watred
with the deaw of heauen, thou must needes bring
forth. What?
                  
                  
                     2. Herbes. There is Fertilitie in Goodnes.
                     THe eldest daughter of Idlenesse is to doe
nothing: the next borne to doe something
to no purpose. But the good man

is not onely doing, but well doing, Math. 24.Mat. 24. 46
                        Blessed is that seruant, whom his Lord when he commeth,
shall finde so doing. This so consists in doing
Bonum, and Bene. As the former verse may seeme
to intimate. He giues them meate, there he doth
good: in due season, there he doth it well. The forbearance
of wickednesse is not enough to acquit
the soule, but the performance of righteousnesse.
The rich Glutton is tormented in hell, not because
he did hurt, but because he did not helpe
Lazarus. Non quod abstulerit aliena, sed quod non
donarit sua,
                        August. sayth S. Chrysost. Not for taking away
another mans, but for not giuing his owne.
He would not giue the poore the crummes that
fell from his boord; and so facere damna lucrum,
make a gaine of his losses: for they were lost that
fell from his libertine table, and yet would haue
refreshed the hungry and famished soule. But
Diues would not giue a crumme, to get a crowne.
He wore fine linnen; but it was his owne. Hee
was cloathed in rich purple; but it was his owne.
Hee fared sumptuously euery day, but hee did
eate his owne meate: he tooke none of all this
from Lazarus. Yet hee went to hell. God condemned
him, because hee did not giue some of
this to Lazarus. Thus it is not only the commission
of lewdnesse, that sinkes men to hell, but euen
also the omission of goodnesse. Dost thou
heare, O Earth; vnlesse thou bring forth herbes,
thou shalt be condemned. The Fig-tree had no
bad fruit on it, yet was it cursed, because it had

none at all. The axe that is layd to the roote, shall
hew downe euen that tree,
                        Mat. 3. 10. 
                        which brings not forth
good fruite: though it bring forth no euill. Fire
shall take the barren, as well as the vveedie
ground.
                     
                        Except your righteousnesse shall exceede the righ
                           
                              ••
                           ousnesse
of the Scribes and Pharises,
                        Mat. 5. 20. 
                        ye shall not enter
into the kingdome of heauen. Wherein (me
thinks) our Sauiour implyeth a three-fold gradation
to heauen. First there must be Iustitia, Righteousnesse;
an habituall practise of godlinesse; an
vncorrupt life, which shall only be entertain'd to
Gods Hill.
                        Psa. 15. 2 But the ground must be made good,
before it can produce good herbes: for the person
must bee accepted before the worke. And
this worke must be good both quoad fontem, and
quoad finem: wee must deriue it from an honest
heart, and driue it to a right ende. In the
next place, this Righteousnesse must bee a mans
owne. Nisi iustitia vestra. Heere, that ground
which brings forth herbes receiueth blessing; not
that borrowes them of another. For so, as stony
and barren an heart as Cheapside, may be a far
richer garden then some of those, where those
herbes (brought thither) naturally grew. The
Pope hath a huge harden of these herbes; wherewith
hee can store as many, as will pay for them.
Iohn Baptist fasted more then hee was commanded:
and Mary liued more strictly then God required.
Now the Church of Rome keepes an
Herball of these superabundant workes; and money

may haue store of them. But heauen and
Rome stand a great way asunder. And as God
neuer gaue the Pope authority to make such bargains,
so he neuer means to stand to them. It is
not onely spoken, but commanded to be written
of the dying Saints, that their workes follow them.
Their owne workes,
                        Reu. 14. 13. not the workes of others. No
righteousnes of friend liuing, or of Saint dead,
shall doe thee good, but the herbes of thy owne
Garden shall bee accepted of God. Lastly, this
Righteousnesse must excell, nisi abundauerit. If it
come short of those that come short of heauen,
what hope haue you? It must exceed innocence,
and come to reall goodnesse.
                     We haue not sufficiently discharged our duties
in being painfull, vnlesse wee be profitable.
Some will take no paines, vnlesse the Diuell set
them on worke. They must be their owne caruers
in their imployment, or they will sit idle. But
so a man may worke and haue no thankes for his
labour. It is not then simply and onely bringing
forth, commends a ground, but bringing forth
herbes.
                     
                     The fruit of Peters repentance is not to deny
his Master no more; but to stand to him to the
death. We thinke, if wee forbeare our wonted
notorious sinnes, wee are on the sodaine excellent
Christians. As if God were beholden to vs,
for not wounding his name with oathes; for
not playing out Sabaoths; for not rayling on his
Gospell; for not oppressing his poore members:

when we neither reliue the poore, nor obey the
Gospell, nor hallow his Saboths, nor honor his
name. Perhaps an Vsurer when he hath gotten
enough will cease that damned trade: now he is
sure of heauen in a trice. Alas! how repents Zaccheus,
if he restores not? Shall I goe a step higher?
If he giue not liberally, and shew compassion
to the afflicted Saints? Perhaps an old Adulterer
when his sappe is growne to cinders, breaks
off his vncleannesse. When the enuious looseth
his obiect, he may suspend his malice. But where
are the returned fruits of penitence, manifest and
visible obedience? Say the weedes are gone,
where be the herbes? To roote vp the weedes, is
but the first step to heauen: and some are fortie,
threescore yeares taking this steppe. How long
will it be ere their garden be set with good growing
herbes?
                        Iudg. 5. 23. But Curse ye Meroz, sayd the Angell of
the Lord, curse ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof:
because they came not to the helpe of the Lord, (and
that it might fully appeare, that this curse came
not on them, for taking part with Gods enemies
and fighting against him; but onely for deniall
of succour, the song doubles it) to the helpe of the
Lord against the mighty.
                        Mat. 18. 28. The offended Lord deliuered
that Seruant to the tormentors, that (did not
extort from his fellow that hee had no right to,
nor wrest away an others goods; but) did onely
say, Pay me that thou owest; and in a harsh manner,
or vnmercifull measure, required his owne due.
It is the forme of the last doome,Mat. 25. 42. 
                        I was hungry,

and ye gaue me no meate: though you tooke not away
mine, yet for not giuing your owne, Goe yee
cursed.
                     
                     But if that ground be neere vnto cursing, that
brings not forth herbes; what shall we say to that,
which brings forth weeds? What hell, and how
many torments are prouided for oppressing Diues,
when Diues that but denyed his owne shall be
tortur'd in endlesse flames! If he were bound to
an euerlasting prison, that rigorously prosecuted
his owne right, chaleng'd his owne debt: whither
shall they bee cast, that vniustly vexe their
neighbours, quarrell for that which is none of
theirs, and lay title to another mans proprietie?
If hee that giues not his coate to the naked, shall
lye naked to the vengeance of God; then he that
takes away the poore mans coate, shall bee clad
with burning confusion. If hee that giues not,
wring his hands; hee that takes away shall rend
his heart. The old world did but eate and drink,
build and plant, marry and be merry; and were
swept away with the beesome of an vniuersal deluge;
which things were in themselues lawfull:
what shall become of lyars swearers, adulterers,
idolaters, malicious, monstrous, scandalous sinners;
whose workes are in themselues simply vnlawful.
There are 3. sorts of ground mentioned,
Marke 4. and the very worst of them receiues the
seed, yet all damned: whither shall the tempest
of Gods wrath driue them, that would neuer giue
the Gospell a religious eare? O beloued! waigh
it.
                     
                        
Our Idle words must come to iudgement:
what shall be our answere for vnlawfull deedes:
If omission of good works be whipp'd with rods,
commission of impieties shall be scourged with
Scorpions. If they that stand in a luke-warme
neutralitie, shall be spewed vp; sure the palpable
and notorious offender shall bee troden vnder
foote of a prouoked Iustice. Indifferency shall
not scape: and shall extreme presumption be spared?
that like dogges, sup vp the dregges they
haue vomited. I haue read of a Popish Saint,
Henry the Dane, that in a mad and hare-brain'd
deuotion, when wormes crawled out of a corrupt
vlcer in his knee, did put them in againe. There
are such franticke wretches, that when the word
hath squeased some poyson out of their consciences,
and driuen forth lusts, like crawling worms;
they in a voluntary madnesse put them in againe.
As the Tode casts ont per poison, when she goes
to the water to drinke; when shee hath drunke,
sups it vp againe. Adam lost himselfe, and all his
posterity by one transgression; and do we think,
can we hope that our infinite shall scape iudgement?
Or doe we extenuate our iniquities with
such selfe-flattering mitigations, that if they bee
not innumerable, they are pardonable; and that
a few shall bring no man to iudgement? And
what call wee this paucitie? As the Glosse deales
with a piece of Gratians Decretum. The Text
sayes, Meretrix est, quae multorum libidin
                              •
                            patet.
Shee is a whore, who serues many mens turnes.
                     
                        
Now the Glosse brings this indefinite number
to a certaine, and giues Multorum a reasonable
latitude; saying, the name of Whore should
not be giuen her, til she hath lyen with three and
twenty thousand men. So till we haue doubled,
iterated, and multiplyed our lyes, oa
                           •
                        hes, oppressions,
lusts, vnto thousands, and thousands,
we do not thinke that we merite the names of lyers,
swearers, oppressors, or luxurious persons.
Beloued, these things must be reckoned for: and
if nescience be beaten with stripes, wilfull impiety
shal be burned with fire. Blessed ground then,
that brings forth herbes; and that not in scarsitie,
but in
                  
                  
                     3. Plenty. Many herbes.
                     THe good ground is plentifull in fruits. It
beares fruit, good fruit, much good fruit.
Multiplicitie of grace is requisite, though
not perfection. What Garden is only planted
with one singular kinde of herbe? The Christian
hath need of many graces; because he is to meet
with many defects, to answere many tentations,
to fight with many enemies. Therefore, 2. Pet. 1.2. Pet. 1. 5.
                        Ioyne with your faith vertue, and with vertue knowledge,
                        Cant. 4.
                        and with knowledge temperance, &amp;c. One
Iewell will not serue: Christs Spouse must haue
diuerse to adorne her. One piece of armour wil
not secure vs; we know not which way the blow

will come,Eph. 6. 11. nor where it will light. Therefore, Put
on the whole armour of God, that yee may bee able to
stand against all the wyles of the diuell. The loins,
the brest, the head, the feete; all parts must bee
armed. The fruite of the Spirit (those happy
fruits which the Spirit of God worketh in vs, and
bringeth out of vs) is manifold. Galat. 5.Gal. 5. 22. 
                        Loue,
ioy, peace, long-suffering, gentlenesse, goodnesse, faith,
meeknesse, &amp;c. The Apostle chargeth vs to bee
rich in good workes. 1. Tim. 6.1. Tim. 6. 18 And for this cause
bowes his knees vnto the Father of our Lord Iesus
Christ,
                        Eph. 3. 14. 16 that according to the riches of his glorie wee
might be filled with all the fulnesse of God. The reason
is giuen by Christ. To whom much is giuen, of
them shall much be required. And it was his commendation
of Mary Magd
                              •
                           l
                              •
                           n, that because shee
had much forgiuen her, therefore she loued much.
                     
                     Happie then is that ground, which abounds
with good herbes; the fruits of faith, patience,
content, charitie. Not our riches, but our wor
                              •
                           s
shall follow vs. Goodnesse shall only giue Pulchrum
sepulchrum: and as we vse to sticke dead
bodies with herbes; so these herbes our fruitfull
good workes shall adorne and beautifie our memorialls,
when the name of the wicked shall 
                              •
                           ot. I
know England, inueigh the Papists till their galls
burst, is full of pious and charitable workes. It is
a Garden full of good herbes. Not to vs, but to
God bee the prayse; who hath moued such instruments
to workes of his glory. Yet Que
                              •
                           on fecimus
ipsi, vix ca nostra voce: let 
                           •
                        uery man quiet his

owne conscience, with the good herbes his owne
garden produceth.
                     The rich man growes easily richer, so the
good man easily better. It is the custom of most
men to be pleased with a very little religion. For
the world, wee are enraged and transported with
such a hunger, that the graue is sooner satisfied:
but a very little godlinesse contents vs. But if we
would not bee barren nor vnfruitfull in the knowledge
of our Lord Iesus Christ,
                        2. Pet. 1. 8. we must, sayth the
Apostle, abound with these herbes. And then for
a proportionate reward, An entrance shall be ministred
vnto vs abundantly,
                        Verse 11. 
                        into the euerlasting
kingdome of our Sauiour Christ. Blessed is he that
brings forth herbes, many herbes, and lastly such
as are
                  
                  
                     4. Meet for them by whom he is dressed.
                     THe word By whom, may as well be translated
For whom: 
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Two instructions
are here necessarily offered vs.

                           1. By whom this goodnesse comes.
                           2. For whom it must be intended.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        1. By whom it is dressed.
                        GOD is the Husbandman that dresseth this
ground, and causeth in it Fertillitie. It was
the Pelagian errour. A Deo habemus qu
                                 •
                              d
homines sumus, a nobis ipsis autem quod iusti sumus.
We are beholding to God that we are men,Aug. Tract. 81. in Ioh. to
our selues that we are good men. But the contrary
is here euident. God doth not onely make
the ground, but hee makes the ground fruitfull:
he raines vpon it, hee dresseth it, hee blesseth it.
Christ sayd not,Ioh. 15. 5. 
                           Sine me parum potestis facere, sed
sine me nihil. Without me ye can doe nothing, sayth
our Sauiour, and to the best men, euen the Apostles:
not a little, but nothing. If God had onely
made thee a man, and thou made thy selfe a
good man, then is thy worke greater then Gods
worke.August. For, Mel us est iustum esse, quam te hom
                                 •
                              
                              n
                                 •
                              m
esse. Our meere being is not so happie, as
our better being. No, this Text conuinceth that
lye. For, according to that distinction of grace.
1. Here is Gratia operans, God begins the worke;
he makes the ground good. sanctifies the person.
2. Here is Gratia cooperans, God that begins, performes
the worke; he raineth vpon, he dresseth the
heart, and so causeth it to produce herbes. 3. Here
is Gratia saluans, whereby hee crowneth our will
and worke in the day of our Lord IESVS. It receiueth
blessing from God. So

                              
Qui viret in foliis, venit a radicibus humor.
                        
                        The sappe of grace which appeares greene
and flourishing in the branches and fruit, comes
from the root. Now in all this Deus non necessitat,
sed factl
                                 •
                              tat: God induceth the good to good by
alacritie, not enforceth against their wills. Quoniam
probitate coacta,
                           Prud. 
                           Gloria nulla venit. For God
doth not worke vpon vs, as vpon blockes and
stones, in all and euery respect passiue: but conuerts
our wils to will our owne conuersion.August. 
                           Qui
fecit te sine te, non iustificabit te sine te. Fecit nesc
                                 •
                              
                              entem,
Iustificat volentem. Hee that made thee
without thy selfe, will not iustifie thee without
thy selfe. (without thy merite indeed, not without
thine act). He created thee when thou knewest
it not, he doth iustifie thee with the consent of
thy owne will. Let this consideration lay vs all
prostrate before the foot-stoole of God, kissing
the feete of his mercy,Heb. 5. 23: who is the Beginner and
finisher of our faith. Who hath made the ground
good, and encreased the number of herbes with
his holy dewes from heauen; dressed it with his
graces, and promised to reward it with his blessings.
Thus By whom: now For whom.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        Meete for them who dressed it.
                        AND is it possible, that man should produce
herbes meete for the acceptation of
God? Hath he not pure eyes, which see
vncleannesse and imperfection in all our workes?
Is there any man so happy, as to bee iustified in
his sight? No; but it pleaseth him to looke vpon
our workes in the Crystall glasse, Christ; and because
they are the effects of a true faith in him,
to esteeme them meete. S. Peter sayth,1. Pet. 2. 19. 
                           This is
thanke-worthy, if a man for conscience toward God
endure griefe, suffering wrongfully. Doe euen our
sufferings then merite? 
                              〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                            euen this is
grace. To you it is giuen not only to beleeue in him,
but euen to suffer for his sake. This was none of
yours, but giuen you. And when you haue suffered,Rom. 8. 18.
yet you must truely with Paul reckon, that
the afflictions of this present world are not worthy of
that high inestimable waight of glory. There are no
workes acceptable (Quae praecedunt instificandum,
sed quae sequuntur iustificatum) which goe before
Iustification, but these that follow it. All of vs,
as Luther was wont to say, haue naturally a Pope
bred in our bellies; a Mountebanke-opinion of
our owne worth. Narcissus-like, wee dote vpon
our owne shadowes; and thinke our workes acceptable
enough to God. If wee haue prayed,

releeued, beleeued the history of the Gospell, or
attentiuely heard the word, these are works meete
for God. The Monke had but one hole in his
Cell, and though it was in the toppe, vpward to
heauen, yet the Diuell made a shift to creepe in
there. The Serpent thrusts in his head often in
some cracke of our good workes. Luther paradoxically.

                              
                                 〈◊〉
                               
                              
                                 •
                              niustitiarum 
                                 •
                              ere sola causa

                                 〈◊〉
                              . Almost the only cause of all vnrighteousnesse,
is (a too-well conceited) righteousnesse.
We are easily induced to thinke our selues euery
one,Act▪ 8. 9. as Simon Magas, some great man. There
must bee a deiection of this thought, an annihilation
of our owne worth; that we can doe nothing
meete for God, or worthy his iust acceptance.
For Serdet in distincti
                                 ••
                              e Iudicis, quod fulget
in opinione operantis. That is often foule in the sentence
of the Iudge, which shines in the imagination
of him that doth it.
                        But as Physitians say, no man dyes of an ague,
or without it: so seldome any soule dyes of pride,
or without pride; not meerly of pride, for (though
that sicknesse were enough to kill it, yet) it is euer
accompanied with som other disease and vicious
wickednes; nor without it, for it is so inherent vnto
mans nature, that pride, if it doth not prouoke
yet at lest holds the dore, whiles any iniquitie is
doing. Hence flow so many errors, and factions,
and singularities.
                        For as in the body, a raw stomach makes a rhumatick
head, &amp; a rhumatick head a raw stomach.

So in the soule, an indigested conceit of some
good thing in vs, makes the head rume of some
rheumaticke opinion, or madde factious singularitie:
and this petulant rheume in the braine,
keeps the conscience raw stil; that the physicke of
repentance, or good diet of peaceable obedience
cannot helpe it. Let vs correct these exorbitant
and superfluous conceits, which are like proude
flesh vpon vs; and knowe, wee are able to doe
nothing of our selues, but God is faine to put
euen good thoughts in vs. And if wee doe good
from him, how good soeuer it be as from him,
yet running through vs it gets some pollution.
                        Neither let vs run into the contrary errour, as
if in a stupid willfullnesse, what good soeuer wee
did, we could not hope that God in Iesus Christ
would accept it. There is a thresholde of despaire
below to stumble at, as wel as a post of high
presumption to breake our heads at. There is a
base deiection, a sordid humility. Bar
                                 •
                              ena the
Iesuite told another of his order; that when the
deuill appeared to him one night, out of his profound
humility hee rose vp to meete him, and
prayed him to sitte downe in his chaire; for hee
was more worthy to sitte there then he. This did
appeare a strange kind of deiectednes. Surely
I thinke, a man should by Gods word and warrant,
take comfort in his wel doing, and be cheared
in the testimonie which a good conscience,
on good cause beareth to him. So Dauid hartned
himselfe against all the malicious slanders of his

his enemies; O Lord thou knowest mine innocence.
Good workes are the necessary and inseparable
effects of a true faith. We are by nature all dead
in sinne, and by sinne concluded vnder death.
Our Sauiour bore for vs this death, and by his
passion freed vs from eternal damnation. It was
not enough to scape hell, how shall wee get to
heauen? Loe, we are cloathed with the garment
of his righteousnesse, hung with the Iewels of his
merits. So not onely hell is escaped by his sufferings,
but heauen got by his doings. Why
should wee then worke? what need our gardens
stand so full of herbes? Good reason. Shall
God do so much for vs, and shall we do nothing
for him, for our selues? If the Lord of a Forrest
giues me a Tree, it is fit I should be at the cost to
cut it downe, and bring it home, if I will haue it.
I cannot say that I deserued the tree; it was anothers
gift: but my labours must lead me to enioy
that, which was freely giuen me. Neither,
can the conscience haue assurance of eternal life,
so frankly bestowed in Christ, without a good
conuersation. Faith doth iustifie, and workes do
testifie that we are iustified. In a clocke, the finger
of the dyall makes not the clocke to goe, but
the clocke it: yet the finger without shewes how
the clocke goes within. Our external obedience
is caused by our inward faith; but that doth manifest
how truly the clocke of our faith goes. As
a mans corporall actions of sleeping, eating, digesting,
walking, declare his recouery from sicknesse,

and present health. So his life witnesseth
by infallible Symptomes, that the disease and
death of sinne is mortified in him, and that he
hath taken certaine hold of eternall life. It is
meet then that we should doe good workes: but
all our works are made meete and worthy in him
that bought vs. I will conclude then with that
Antheme, made by a sweet singer in our Israel.
Pendemus ate, credimus in te, tendimus, ad te,
non nisi per te, Optime Christe.
                        
                        AMEN.
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  THE
GARDEN
Or,
A Contemplation
of the HERBES. The THIRD SERMON.
                  
                     
                        The Song of Salomon. Chap. 6. Ver. 2. 
                     My Beloued is gone downe into his Garden, to the beds of spices; to
feede in the gardens, and to gather Lillies.
                  
                  
                     AMB. super LVC.
                     Non Virtus est non posse peccare, sed nolle.
                  
                  LONDON,
Printed by George Purslowe, for Iohn Budge, and are to be
solde at his shop, at the great South-dore of Pauls,
and at Brittaines Burse. 1616.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                  THE
GARDEN
OR
A Contemplation of the
Herbes.
                  THE
THIRD SERMON.
                  
                     HEB. Chap. 6. Vers. 7.
                     For the earth which drinketh in the raine that commeth oft
vpon it, and bringeth forth Herbs meet for them by whom
it is dressed, receiueth blessing from God.
                  
                  
                     THat the Herbes of our graces
may be meete for the dresser;
contentful to GOD, who
hath planted, watred, husbanded
the Garden of our
hearts; wee will require in
them foure vertues: Odour,
Taste, Ornament, Medicinall Vertue.
                  
                     
1. That they haue a good odour. God is delighted
with the smell of our graces. My Beloued
is gone downe into his Garden,
                     Cant. 6. 2. 
                     to the beds of spices,
to feed in the gardens, and to gather Lillies. The
vertues of Christ are thus principally pleasant;
and all our herbes onely smell sweetly in his Garden.
Because of the sauour of thy good ointment,
                     Cant. 1. 3. 
                     thy
name is as ointment powred forth, therefore doe the
Virgins loue thee. This sauour is sweetly acceptable
in the nostrils of God. All thy garments smel
of Myrrhe,
                     Psa. 45. 8. 
                     Aloes, and Cassia: It is his righteousnesse,
that giues all our herbes a good odour: and
in him it pleaseth God to iudge our works sweet.
When Noah had built an Altar,
                     Gen. 8. 21. and sacrificed
burnt offerings on it, the Lord smelled a sweet sauour
and sayd, I will not againe curse the ground any more
for mans sake.
                     Mat. 2. 
                     Myrrhe and Prankincense were two
of the oblations, which the Wise-men offered to
CHRIST being an Infant.
                  
                     Tres Reges, regum Regitria dona tulerunt:
                     Myrrham homini, vncto aurū, thura dedere Deo.
                     Tutriafac itidem dones pia munera Christo,
                     Muneribus gratus si cupis esse tuis.
                     Pro myrrha lacrymas, pro auro cor porrige purum,
                     Pro thure, ex humili pectore funde preces.
                  
                  
                     Three kings to the great King three offerings bring,
                     Incense for God, Myrrhe for man, gold for king.
                     Thy Incense be the hands a white soule reares.
                     For gold giue a pure hart, for myrrhe drop tears.
                  
                  
                     
The way to make our herbes smell sweetly, is
first to purge our garden of weedes. For if sinne
be fostered in our hearts, all our workes will bee
abominated. God heareth not the prayers of
the wicked.Leuit. 26. 31. 
                     If yee will walke contrary to mee, saith
the Lord, I will bring your sanctuaries vnto desolation,
and I will not smell the sauour of your sweete odours.
But being adopted by grace in Christ,
and sanctified to holinesse, our good works smell
sweetly, Phil. 4.Phil. 4. 18. 
                     I haue receiued of Epaphroditus the
things which were sent from you, an odour of a sweet
smell, a sacrifice acceptable, well pleasing to God. It
seemes, GOD highly esteemes the herbe Charitie
in our gardens. Hee that serueth the Lord,
shall smell as Lebanon:
                     Hos. 14. 6. 7. 
                     hee shall growe as the
Vine, and his sent shall bee as the wine of Lebanon.
                  
                  Man is naturally delighted with pleasant sauours,
and abhorres noysome and stinking smels.
But our God hath purer nosthrils, and cannot abide
the polluted heapes of iniquities. The Idle
man is a standing pitte; and hath an ill-sauour'd
smell, an ill-fauour'd sight. The drunkard is like
a bogge, a fogge, a fenne of euill vapours: God
cannot abide him. Your couetous wretch is like
a dunghill; there is nothing but rottennesse and
infection in him. Omnis malitia eructat fumum.
All wickednesse belcheth forth an euill sauour.
Wonder you, if God refuse to dwell with the Vsurer,
Swearer, Idolater, Adulterer? There is a

poyson of lust, a leprosie of putrefaction in them:
no carryon is so odious to man, as mans impieties
are to God. Yea the very oblations of defiled
hands stinke in his presence.Esa. 66. 3. 
                     Hee that sacrificeth
a Lambe, is as if hee cut off a dogges necke, &amp;c.
As if Ass a foetida was the only supply of their gardens.
But good herbes giue a double sauour: one
outward to man, another inward to God. The
sweete smoke of a holy sacrifice, like a subtil ayre,
riseth vp to heauen; and is with God before man
sees or smels it. It also cheares the hearts of Christians,
to behold Christian workes. Reuerence
to the Word, hallowing the Sabaoths, releeuing
the poore, deeds of mercie, pittie, piety, giue a
delightful sent: solacing the soules of the Saints,
and pleasing him that made them both men and
Saints. Therefore Hearken vnto me, ye holy children,
                     Eccl. 39. 13.
                     and budde forth as a Rose growing by the brook
of the fielde. Giue ye a sweet sauour, as frankincense,
and flourish as a Lilly, send forth a smell, sing a song
of prayse, and blesse the Lord in all his workes.
                  
                  2. That they taste well. Many a flower hath
a sweet smell, but not so wholsome a taste. Your
Pharisaicall prayers and almes smelt sweetly in
the vulgar nosthrils: taste them, and they were
but rue, or rather worme-wood. When the
Pharise sawe the Publican in the lower part of
the Temple, standing as it were in the Belfrey;
he could cry, Foh this Publican: but when they
were both tasted, by his palate that could iudge,
the Publican hath an herbe in his bosome, and

the Pharise but a gay, gorgeous, stinking weede.
The herbes, that the Passeouer were eaten with,
were sowre: yet they were enioined with sweet
bread. Sowre they might be, but they were wholsome.
Herbes haue not onely their sauour, but
their nutriment. He causeth the grasse to growe for
the cattell,
                     Psa. 104. 14 
                     and herbe for the seruice of man: that he
may bring food out of the earth. Herbs thē are food,
and haue an alimentall vertue. So we may both
with the herbes of charitie feed mens bodies, and
with the herbes of piety feede their soules. A
good life is a good sallet: and in the second place
to precepts, are vsefully necessary good exāples.
The bloud of Martyrs is sayd to haue nourished
the Church. The patience of the Saints, in the
hottest extremity of their afflictions, euen when
the flames of death hath clipped them in their
armes; hath been no lesse then a kindly nourishment
to many mens faith. It is expounded by an
vniuersall consent of Diuines, that one of those 3.
feedings, which Christ imposed on Peter, is Pasce
exemplo; let thy life feed them. Blessed Gardens
that yeeld herbes, like Iothams vine, that cheare the
heart of both God and man.
                     Iudg. 9
                           •
                         13. The Poets fain'd, that
Nectar &amp; Ambrosia were the food of their Gods.
Iupiter Ambrosia satur est, est Nectare plenus. But
the true Gods dyet, is the vertues of his Saints,
wherwith he promiseth to suppe, when he comes
into their hearts. Faith,Reu. 3. 20. loue, patience, meeknes,
honestie; these dishes are his dainties.
                  If thou wouldest make Christ good cheare in

the parlour of thy conscience, bring him the
herbes of obedience. Doe not say, I would haue
beene as kinde and liberall to my Sauiour as the
best, had I liued in those dayes, when he blessed
the world with his bodily presence. But now I
may say with Mary Magdalen: They haue taken
away the Lord,
                     Ioh. 20. 2. 
                     and I know not where to finde him.
Damne not thy selfe with excuses. Wheresoeuer
his Church is, there is he; exercise thy piety.
Wheresoeuer his members are, there is he; exercise
thy charity. Thou art very niggardly, if thou
wilt not afford him a sallet, a dinner of herbes.
Yet, sayth Salomon, A dinner of greene herbes with
loue, is better then a fatte Oxe with hatred.
                  
                  3. That they be fitte to adorne. Herbes and flowers
haue not only their vse in pleasing the nostrills,
and the palate, but the eye also. They giue
delight to all those three senses. Good workes
are the beauty of a house, and a better sight then
fresh herbes strew'd in the windores. The Chamber,
where Christ would eate his Passouer, was
trimmed: and the Palace of our Princely Salomon
is paued With Loue of the daughters of Ierusalem.
                     Cant. 3. 10.
                  
                  There is no ornature in the World like good
deeds: no hanging of Tapestry, or Arrase, comes
neere it. A stately building where an Idolater
dwells, is but a gawdy coate to a Sodome-apple.
When you see an Oppressour raising a great
house from the ruines of many lesse; depopulating
a Countrey to make vp one Family; building
his Parlours with extortion, and cimenting

his walls with the morter of bloud: you say,
there is a foule Minotaure in a faire Labyrinth.
Be a man dead, it is a foolish hope to reare immortalitie
with a few senselesse stones. Perhaps
the Passenger wil be hereby occasioned, to comment
vpon his bad life; and to discourse to his
company the long enumeration of such a mans
vices. So a perpetuall succession of infamie answeres
his gay sepulchre: and it had bin better for
him, to haue been vtterly inglorious, then inexcusably
infamous. The best report, that can be
drawne from him, is but this. Here lyes a faire
Tombe, and a foule carcase in it.
                  These things doe neither honest a man liuing,
nor honour him dead. Good works are the best
ornaments, the most lasting monuments. They
become the house wherein thy soule dwelleth,
whiles it dwels there: and blesse thy memorie,
when those two are parted. A good life is mans
best monument: and that Epitaph shall last, as if
it were written with a pen of iron, and claw of a
Diamond; which is made vp of vertuous actions.
Good herbes beautifie more then dead
stones. Wheresoeuer thou shalt be buried, obscurity
shall not swallow thee. Euery good heart
that knew thee is thy Tombe; and euery tongue
writes happy Epitaphes on thy memoriall. Thus
height vp your soules with a treasure of good
works. Let your herbes smel sweetly, let them tast
chearfully; let them adorne beautiously. So
Gods palate, his nosthrils, his sight shall be well
pleased.
                  
                     
4. That they be medicinable; and serue not
onely as Antidotes to preuent, but as medicaments
to cure the soules infirmities. The poore
mans physicke lyes in his Garden: the good
soule can fetch an herbe from his heart (of Gods
planting there) that can helpe him. Plinie writes
of a certaine herbe, which he calls Thelygonum;
we in English, The grace of God. A happy herbe,
and worthy to stand in the first place, as chiefe of
the garden. For it is the principal, and (as it were)
the Genus of al the rest. We may say of it, as some
write of the Carduus benedictus, or Holy-thistle; that
it is herba omnimorbia; an herbe of such vertue,
that it can cure all diseases. This may heale a
man, who is otherwise nullis medicabilis herbis.
Wretched men, that are without this herbe, The
grace of God, in their gardens.
                  
                     Hysope and Humilitie.
                     IS a man tempted to pride? and that is a sawcie
sinne, euer busie among good workes, like
a Iudas among the Apostles: let him looke
into this Garden for Hysop, Humility of Spirit. Of
which herbe it is written.
                     Est humilis, petrae
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         suis radicibus haeret.
                     Let him be taught by this herbe, to annihilate

his owne worth, and to cleaue to the Rocke,
whereout he growes, and whereof hee is vpholden,
IESVS CHRIST. Or let him produce the
Camomill, which smels the sweeter, the more it
is trodden on. Humility is a gracious herbe, and
allayes the wrath of God; whereas pride prouokes
it. It is recorded of an english king, Edward
the first, that being exceeding angry with a seruant
of his, in the sport of hawking, he threatned
him sharply. The gentleman answered, it was
well there was a riuer betweene them. Hereat
the King more incensed, spurr'd his horse into
the depth of the Riuer, not without extreame
danger of his life; the water being deep, and the
banks too steep and high for his ascending. Yet at
last recouering land, with his sword drawne, he
pursues the seruant; who rode as fast from him.
But finding himself too ill-hors'd, to out-ride the
angry King; he reyned, lighted, and on his knees
exposed his neck to the blow of the kings sword.
The King no sooner saw this, but he put vp his
sword, and would not touch him. A dangerous
water could not with-hold him from violence;
yet his seruants submission did soon pacifie him.
Whiles man flyes stubbornely from God, hee
that rides vpon the wings of the winde, postes after
him with the sword of vengeance drawne. But
when dust and ashes humbles himselfe, and
stands to his mercie, the wrath of God is soone
appeased.
                     This Camomill or Hysop growes very lowe:

                        Humblenesse roots downeward, yet no herbe hath
so high branches. We say, that proud men haue
high mindes: they haue not. For their mindes
only aspire to some earthly honours, which are
but low shrubbes indeed. The humble man aspires
to heauen, and to bee great in the eternall
Kings fauour; and this is the true, but good
height of minde. His desires haue a high ayme,
though their dwelling bee in the vale of an humble
heart. There are engines, that raise water to
fall, that it may rise the higher. A lowly heart, by
abasing it selfe in the sight of God and men, doth
mount al the other graces of the soule as high as
heauen; and the eye of mercie accepts them.
Pride is a stinking weede; and though it be gay
and garish, is but like the Horse-flower. In the
field it is of glorious shew: croppe it, and you
cannot endure the sauour. At the best, the proud
man is but like the bird of Paradise, or the Estridge;
his feathers are more worth then his body.
Let not thy Garden be without this herbe Humilitie.
It may be least respected with men; and
among other herbs ouerlooked; but most acceptable
to God. Respexit humilitatem ancillae suae,
sings the Virgin MARY. He had regard to the lowlinesse
of his hand-maiden. It shall not want a good
remembrance, a good recompence. For the last,
the least, and the lowest may come to be the first,
the greatest, and the highest. This is a necessary
herbe.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Bulapathum. The herbe Patience.
                     IS a man, through multitude of troubles, almost
wrought to impatience; and to repine at
the prouidence of GOD; that disposeth no
more ease? Let him fetch an herbe out of the
Garden to cure this maladie; Bulapathum, the
herbe Patience. The Adamant serues not for all
seas; but Patience is good for all estates. Gods
purpose cannot be eluded with impatience: and
man vnder his hand, is like a bird in a nette; the
more he struggles, the faster he is. Impatience
regards not the highest but secondary causes:
and so bites the stone in stead of the thrower. If
our inferiour strike vs, we trebble reuenge. If an
equall, we requite it. If a superior, we repine not:
or if wee mutter, yet not vtter our discontent.
Thinke whose hand strikes: it is Gods. Whether
by a Pleurisie, or a Feuer, or a Sword, or
what euer other instrument. The blow was his,
whatsoeuer vvas the weapon. And this wound
will not bee cured, vnlesse by applying the herbe
Patience.
                     
                     The good man hath such a hand ouer fortune;
knowing who guides and disposeth all euents;
that no miseries, though they bee sodaine as well
as sharpe, can vn-heart him. If he must dye, he
goes breast to breast with vertue. If his life must

tarry a further succession of miseries, hee makes
absent ioyes present, wants plenitudes; a
                           •
                        d beguiles
calamity, as good company does the way,
by Patience.
                        1. King. 22. 34. 
                        A certaine man drew a bowe at a venture,
and smote the King of Israel betweene the ioynts
of the harnesse. The man shot at random, or as
the Hebrew hath it, in his simplicitie; but God directed
the arrow to strike Ahab.
                        2. Sam. 16. 11. So Dauid spake
of Shimei. Let him alone, and let him curse; for
the Lord hath bidden him. It may be that the Lord
will looke on mine affliction, and that the Lord wil requite
good for his cursing this day. Consider wee
not so much, how vniust man is that giueth the
wrong; as how iust God is that guideth it. Non
venit sine merito, quia Deus est iustus: nec erit sine
commodo, quia Deus est bonus. It comes not without
our desert, for God is iust: nor shall be without
our profite, for God is mercifull. God hath
an herbe, which he often puts into his childrens
sallet; that is Rue: and mans herbe wherewith
he eates it, must be Lapathum, Patience.
                     
                     This Rue is affliction; which hath a profitable
effect in those that qnietly digest it. Of all the
herbes in the garden, onely Rue is the herbe of
grace. How much vertue is wrought in the soule
by this bitter plant! It is held by some a sicknes:
it is rather Physick: a sharpe and short medicine,
that bringeth with it much and long health. This,
if they wil needs haue it a sicknesse, may be compared
to the Ague. The Ague shakes a man
worse then another disease, that is mortall. At

last it giues 
                           〈◊〉
                         a kinde farewell, and sayes, I haue
purged thy choler, and made thee healthfull; by
consuming and spending out that humor, which
would haue endangered thy life. Affliction in
the taste is often more bitter, then a iudgement
that kills outright: but at last it tells the soule, I
haue purged away thy foulenesse, wrought out
thy Iustes, and left there a sound man. So
the good Physician procureth to his Patient a
gentle Ague, that hee may cure him of a more
dangerous disease. Vt curet spasmum, procurat febrim.
Christ our best Physician deales a little
roughly with vs, that hee may set vs straight.
And howsoeuer the Feuer of affliction disquiet
vs a while, we shall sing in the conclusion with
the Psalmist.
                        Psal. 119. 71. 
                        It is good for me that I haue been afflicted;
that I might learne thy statutes.
                     
                     
                        Saepe facit Deus opus quod non est summ; vt faciat
opus quod est suum. GOD by a worke that is
none of his, effecteth a work in vs that is his. He
molests vs with some vexations, as hee did Iob;
which is Satans worke immediately, not his; that
thereby hee might bring vs to patience and obedience,
which is his work immediatly and wholly,1. Cor. 
                              •
                           1. 30
not Satans. So wee are chastned of the Lord,
that wee might not bee condemned with the world.
                     
                     Bees are drown'd in honey, but liue in vineger,
and good men grow the better affected, the
more they are afflicted. The poore man for his
ague, goes to his garden, and plucks vp thyme.
The remedy for this spirituall seuer, is true, but

sensible pâtience. Men should feele Gods strokes,
and so beare them. It is dispraiseable, either to
be senselesse or fenselesse. Not to know wee are
stricken, or not to take the blowes on the target
of Patience.
                     
                     Many can lament the effectes, but not the
cause: and sorrow that God grieues them, not
that they grieue God. They are angry with heauen,
for being angry with them. They with heauen
for iustice, that is angry with them for iniustice.
But Maereamus, quod mereamur paenam.
Let not the punishment, but the cause of it, make
thy soule sorrowfull. Know thou art whipp'd for
thy faults; and apply to the prints the herbe Patience.
                     
                  
                  
                     Hearts-case, and spirituall ioy.
                     DOth sorrow and anguish cast downe a
mans hart, and may he complain, that his
soule is disquieted within him?
                        Psal. 42. Let him
fetch an herbe out of this Garden, called Heartsease;
an inward ioy which the holy Ghost worketh
in him. Though all the dayes of the afflicted
be euill,
                        Pro. 15. 15. 
                        yet a merry heart is a continuall feast. This
is Heauen vpon earth. Rom. 14.Rom. 14. 17. 
                        Peace of conscience,
and ioy of the holy Ghost. His conscience is assured
of peace with God, of reconciliation in the

bloud of IESVS; and that his soule is wrapp'd
vp in the bundle of life.
                     This may be well called Hearts-ease: it is a holy,
a happy herbe to comfort the spirits. When
worldly ioyes, either (like Rahels children) are
not, or (like Eli's) are rebellious, there is Heartsease
in this Garden, that shall cheare him against
all sorrowes, certainty of Gods fauo
                           •
                        r. Let the
world frowne, and all things in it runne crosse to
the graine of our mindes; yet with thee, O Lord,
is mereie and plentifull redemption. And, if no body
els,Psal. 73. 1. yet God will be stil good to Israel, euen to those
that are of a pure heart. Those which we call penal
euils, are either past, present, or to come: and
they cause in the soule, sorrow, paine, feare. Euils
past sorrow, present paine, future feare. Here
is Hearts-ease for all these. Miseries past are solaced,
because God hath turned them to our good;
and we are made the better, by once being worse.
Miseries present finde mitigation: and the infinite
comfort that is with vs, within vs, sweetens
the finite bitternesse that is without vs. Miseries
future are to vs contingent: they are vncertaine,
but our strength is certaine; God. Noui in quem
credidi: I know whom I haue trusted. Heere is aabundant
ease to the heart.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Balsamum, or Faith.
                     HAth the heart got a greene wound, by
comitting some offense against God? for
actuall iniquity makes a gash in the soule.
The good man runnes for Balsamum, and stancheth
the bloud: Faith in the promises of Iesus
Christ. He knowes there is Balme at Gilead, and
there are Physicians there:
                        Ier. 8. 22. 
                        and therefore the health
of his soule may easily be recouered. He is sure,
that if the bloud of Christ bee applyed, it will
soone stanch the bloud of his conscience, and
keepe him from bleeding to death: and that
the wounds of his Sauiour will cure the wounds
of his soule. And though this virtuall healing
herbe be in Gods owne Garden, yet he hath a key
to open it, prayer: and a hand to take it out, and
to lay it on his sores, faith. This is a soueraigne
herbe; and indeed so soueraigne, that there is no
herbe good to vs, without it. It may bee called
Panaces; which Physicians say is an herbe for
all manner of diseases: and is indeede the principall
herbe of grace; for it adornes the soule
with all the merits and righteousnes of IESVS
CHRIST.
                  
                  
                     
                     Saint Iohns-wort, or Charitie.
                     DOth the world, through sweetnesse of
gaine, that comes a little too fast vpon a
man, begin to carry away his heart to couetousnesse?
Let him look in this Garden for the
herbe, called Saint-Iohns-wort, Charity, and brotherly
loue. It is called S. Iohns. herbe not vnproperly:
for hee spent a whole Epistle in commending
to vs this grace; and often inculcated; Little
children, loue one another. And he further teacheth,
that this loue must be actuall. For he that
hath this worlds goods,
                        1. Ioh. 3. 17. 
                        and seeth his brother hath
need, and shutteth vp his cowels of compassion from
him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him? He hath
no such herbe, as Saint-Iohns-wort in his garden.
The good Christian considers, that he hath the
goods of this world, to doe good in this world.
And that his riches are called Bona,
                        August. Goods; Non
quod faciant bonum, sed vnde faciat bonum; not
that they make him a good man, but giue him
meanes to doe good to others.
                     He learns a Maxime of Christ from the world;
which the world teacheth, but followeth not;
that is, to make sure as much wealth as he can: as
if it were madnes, to leaue those goodes behind
him, which he may cary with him. This policie
we all confesse good; but faile in the consecution.
The world thinkes, that this assurance is got by

purchasing great reuenews, or by locking vp gold
in a coffer. The Christian likes well to saue what
he can; but hee thinks this is not the waie to do it.
He considers, that the richest hoorder leaues all
behind him; and carries nothing but a windingsheet
to his graue. But he finds out this policy in
the Scripturs;Psal. 73. as Dauid was resolued of his doubt
in the Sanctuary: that what hee charitably giues
aliue, hee shall carry with him dead; and so resolues
to giue much, that hee may keepe much.
Therfore what hee must loose by keeping, he will
keepe by loosing: and so proues richer vnder
ground, then ere hee was aboue it. The poore
mans hand he sees, to be Christs treasurie: there
hee hoords vp; knowing it shall be surely kept,
and safely returned him. His Garden shall stand
ful with Saint-Iohns-wort; and Charity is his herbe,
to cure all the sores of couetousnes.
                  
                  
                     Peny-royall, and Content,
                     DOth pouerty fasten her sharpe teeth in a
mans sides and cannot all his good industry
keepe want from his familie? Let him
come to this Garden for a little Peny-royall, Content.
This will teach him to thinke, that God
who feedes the Rauens, and clothes the Lillies,
will not suffer him to lacke foode and rayment.
The birds of the ayre neither plow nor sow, yet
hee neuer sees them lye dead in his way for want

of prouision. They sleepe, and sing, and fly, and
play, and lacke not. He gathers hence infallibly,
that God will blesse his honest endeuours: and
whiles he is sure of Gods benediction, he thinks
his Peny royall, his poore estate rich. No man is
so happy as to haue all things; and none so miserable
as not to haue some. He knowes hee hath
some; and that of the best riches: therfore resolueth
to enioy them, and to want the rest with
Content. He that hath this herbe in his garden,
Peny-royall, contentation of heart; bee he neuer
so poore, is very rich.
                  
                  
                     Agnus castus, and Continence.
                     DOth the rebellious flesh, vpon a little indulgence,
grow wanton; and would concupiscence
enkindle the fire of lust? The
good soule hath in this Garden, an herbe called,
Agnus castus, the chaste herbe; and good store of
Lettuce: which Physicians say, coole this natural
intemperate heat. His Agnus castus &amp; Lettuce,
are Prayer and Fasting. He knowes, that if this
kind of diuel get possession of the hart, it goes not
out but by Prayer and fasting. It is fasting spettle,
that must kill that Serpent. Mistris Venus dwels
at the signe of the Iuy-bush: and where the
belly is made a barrell, stuffed with delicious
meates, and heating drinkes, the concupiscence
will be luxurious of turpitudes. Sine Cerere
&amp; Baccho friget Venus. Venerie will freese,

if wine and iunkets doe not make her a fire. Lust
will starue, if flesh-pampering shall not get her a
stomach. Where there is thin diet, and cleane
teeth, there will follow Chastitie.
                     
                  
                  
                     Barly-water, or Coole-anger.
                     DOth the heate of anger boyle in a mans
heart; and enrageth him to some violent
and precipitate courses? Let him extract
from this garden the iuyce of many cooling
herbes; and among the rest a drinke of Barly-water;
a Tysan of Meekenesse, to coole this fire. He
that hath proceeded to anger, is a man: he that
hath not proceeded to sinfull, harmefull anger, is
a Christian, Iras
                              •
                           i hominis, i
                              •
                           iurtam non facere
Christiani.
                        Ierem. The most louing man will chide his
friend sweetly; and he that doth not, hates him in
his heart. Sic vigelit tolerantia, vt non dormiat
disciplina.
                        August. But hee will not be transported with
anger, to the losse of his friends, of himselfe. He
considers, that God is prouoked euery day, yet is
long suffering, &amp; of great goodnes. He heares that
others speake ill of him: he iudgeth not without
certaine knowledge. Knowing, hee suffers not
himselfe abused. It were sillinesse to beleeue all;
sullennesse to beleeue none. The wrong done to
God and a good conscience must moue him.
                     
                        
Non patitur ludum fama, fides, oculus.
                     A mans name, his faith, and his eye must not
be iested withall. Yet when he is most angry, he
recollects himselfe, and clappes vpon his heate
a Tysan of meekenesse.
                     
                  
                  
                     Parsley, or Frugalitie.
                     DEclines a mans estate in this world, as if
his hand had scattered too lauishly?
There is an herbe in this Garden; let him
for a while feed on it: Parsley, Parsimonie. Hereon
he wil abridge himselfe of some superfluities:
and remember, that moderate fare is better then
a whole Colledge of Physicians. He will weare
good cloathes, and neuer better; knowing there
is no degree beyond decency. It was for Pompey
to weare as rich a scarfe about his legge, as other
Princes wore on their heads. But the frugall man
can clothe himselfe all ouer decently, with halfe
the cost, that one of our gallant Pompeyes caseth
his legge. He that would not want long, let him
practise to want somewhat, before he extreamely
needs.Martyrol. pag. 1872. I haue read of an English Martyr, that
being put into a prison at Canterbury, tryed
(when shee had liberty of better fare) to liue on a
spare dyet; as preparing and prearming herselfe
with ability to brooke it, when necessity should

put her to it. Frugality puts but three fingers into
the purse at once: Prodigality scatters it by
heapes and handfuls. It is reported, that Caesars
host liued a long time at Dyrrhachium with Coleworts:
whereof arose the Prouerbe, Lapsana viuere,
to liue sparingly. That stocke lasts, that is neither
hoorded miserably, nor dealt out indiscreetly.
We sow the furrow, not by the sacke, but by
the handfull. The wise man knowes, it is better
looking through a poore lattice-window, then
through an iron grate. And though hee will
lend what hee may, hee will not borrow till hee
must neede.
                  
                  
                     Liuer-wort, or Peaceable loue.
                     IS a man sick in his liuer, by accession of some
distemperature? Doth his charity and loue to
some neighbours, for their malignancie against
him, faile and faint in his heart? For they
say, Cogit amare Iecur. I stand not here on the
distinction betwixt Amare and Diligere. Then
let him steppe to this Garden, for some Iecuraria;
we call it Liuer-wort. Hee askes of his heart for
his olde loue, his wonted amity: if his reason answere,
that the persecutions of such and such calumnies
haue fled her into another countrey; he
is not at quiet, till affection fetch it home again.

He thinkes, that night hee sleepes without Charitie
in his bosome, his pillow is harder then Iacobs
was at Bethel. If carnall respects can draw
him to loue his friend for his profite,Gen. 28. or his kinsman
for bloud: he will much more loue a Christian
for his Fathers sake, for his owne sake.
                     There is a story (nothing worth but for the
morall) of a great King, that married his daughter
to a poore Gentleman, that loued her But his
grant had a condition annexed to it, that whensoeuer
the Gentlemans left side looked blacke,
or hee lost his wedding ring, hee should not
onely loose his Wife, but his life. One day
pursuing his sports, he fell into a quarrell; where
(at once) he receiued a bruise on his left breast,
and lost his ring in the scuffing. The tumult ouer,
hee perceiued the danger, whereinto his
owne heedlesnesse had brought him; and in bitternesse
of soule shedde many teares. In his sorrow,
he spied a booke, which opening, he found
therein his ring againe; and the first words hee
read, were a medicine for a bruised side. It directed
him three herbes, whereof a playster applyed
should not faile to heale him. Hee did so;
was cured; was secured.
                     The application is this. The great King of
heauen marries to man, poore man, his owne
daughter, Mercie, and euerlasting kindnesse: But
threatens him, that his side must not looke black;
his heart must not bee polluted with spirituall adulteries:
nor must he loose his wedding ring,

loue to God and his Saints: l
                           •••
                         hee forset both
Gods mercy, and his owne saluation. Man in
the pursiue of worldly affaires, quarrels with his
neighbours, and sc
                           •
                        ffles with cotention. So
his heart takes a bruise, and looks blacke with hatred.
And Charity his wedding ring is lost, in
these wilfull turbulencies and vexations. What
should hee doe but mourne? Loe, God in his
goodnesse, directs him to a book, the holy Gospell.
There the Spirit helpes him to his ring againe,
his former loue; and to heale his bruise,
prescribes him three herbes.
                     First Rue, or herbe of grace, which is repentance
this teacheth him to sorrow for his strife
and emulation; and purgeth away the bruised
bloud.
                     The second is the 
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            deluce, Thankfulnes:
he considers how infinitly God hath loued him;
therefore he must needes loue God, and in him
his. Beatus qui amat te, &amp; amicum in te, &amp; inimicum
propter te. Hee 
                           〈◊〉
                         it impossible, to
loue him he hath not seene, and to hate his Image,
which he hath seene.
                     
                     The third, 
                           
                              〈◊〉
                           , which will grow the faster
for iniuries. Many wrongs hereafter shal not
put him out of charitie. A good plaister of these
herbes will draw his bosome white againe. And
when it is so, let him vse Iecurarta, L
                              ••
                           er-wort; a
continuall application of loue to his heart: that
he keeping his ring of faith sure from loosing;
and his brest from the selfe-procured blowes of

contention; hee may hold also his wife for euer;
that beautifull daughter of the King, Gods eternall
mercy.
                  
                  
                     Lilly, or Purenesse of heart.
                     DOth a man perceiue his heart a little beguiled
with o
                           •
                        tentation, and desires hee
to seeme better then he is? And how easily
is man wonne, to answere his commenders
speculation? Let him fetch the Lillie, purenesse of
heart; which is an herbe of grace, growing in
the humble valley of a meeke spirit; yet is
white, and louely. He knowes, God can vnmask
the vizarded face, and turne the inside outward.
If a man be a Herod within, and a Iohn without: a
wicked Polititian in a ruffe of Precisian-set; God
can distinguish him. There are too many of
these, that stand vp in the fabricke like Pyramides:
it were better for vs, for themselues, if they
were but good honest pillars. Plaine-dealing, is a
good plaine song, and makes better musicke,
then a forc'd squeaking trebble, that troubles vs
all with 
                           •
                        ouelties. Shallow honesty is more commendable,
then the profound quicke-sands of
subtiltie: and one leafe of the Plane-tree, is better
then many handfuls of the pricking Holly.
They search out iniquities, they accomplish a diligent
search:
                        Psal. 64. 6. 
                        both the inward thought of euery one of them,
and the heart is deepe. But when God shal wound

them with his arrowe, They shall make their
tongue fall vpon themselues. Such a mans owne
witte shall snare him; and hee shall sing, or rather
sigh, Ingenio perii. They are glad of Christs
Crosse; not to suffer for it, but to enioy plenitude
of riches by it: And so, like many in great Funerals,
reioice to bee mour
                           •
                        ers; that they may get
some of the blackes. Put them to no charges,
and they'l make you beleeue, they are strongly,
strangely religious. But, 2. Sam. 24.2. Sam. 24. 24. Shall wee
offer burnt sacrifices to the Lord our GOD of that
which cost vs nothing? Christ compares this man
to a painted sepulcher. Sepulchrum quasi semi-pulchrum,
sayth one. Extra nitidum, intus foetidum.
But let them be the men they seeme; and not nettles
in the midst of a rose-cake. The good great
man, though hee bee able securely to doe much
mischiefe; regards more the sins indignitie, then
his owne indemnity.
                  
                  
                     Enula campa
                           •
                        a, or Obedience.
                     PErhaps euill example hath suddenly, and,
without prouided consideration, led a man
into euill. Let him runne to this Garden for
Enulaeampana. This herbe is that Christ enioined
vs. Search the Scriptures; adhere to the word
of the Lord. This shal giue decision of al doubts:
and teach thee what path to flye, what way to
take. It is giuen of this herbe. Enula campana

reddit praecordia sana. It is true of our constant
cleauing to the word; that it shall purge the hart
of what corruption soeuer bad precedents haue
put into it. Of all the herbes in thy Garden loose
not this. Forgoe not the Sword of the Spirit: it is
thy best weapon.
                  
                  
                     Heart-wort, or Affiance in Gods promises.
                     IT may be, sorrow of heart for sinnes hath cast
a man downe; and he is swallowed vp of too
much heauinesse. There is an herbe to comfort
him, called, Heart-wort; affiance in the mercifull
promises of God: past to him by Word,
Oath, Seale, Scriptures, Sacraments,: and therfore
infallible. At what time soeuer what sinner
soeuer repents of what sinne soeuer, God wil put all
his wickednesse out of his remembrance. Hee will
not let that promise fall to the ground, but meets
it with peace and ioy. Blessed are they that mourn,
for they shal be comforted.
                        Mat. 5. 4. He beleeues that his wet
seed time shall haue a glad haruest:Psal. 126. 5. 
                        for they that
sowe in teares, shall reape in ioy. Hee perswades
himselfe, that the dayes of mourning will passe
ouer, as the winde blowes ouer the raine; and
then God will wipe away al teares from his eyes,
                        Ren. 7. 17. with
the hand of mercie. This confidence, in the
midst of all sorrowes, is his Heart-wort.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Hyaeinth, or Following Christ.
                     SAy that the Christian hath met with some
guilded pill of corruption; some poysonous
doctrine, yet plausible to flesh and
bloud. Let him search this Garden for Hyacinth,
or So
                              •
                           sequium, Tornesol: an herbe, that duely and
obediently followes the Sunne. Doe thou follow
the Sunne of righteousnesse:
                        Mal. 4. 2. and let his bright
beames guide thy course: who hath promised to
teach all those, that with an humble heart, and
earnest prayer seeke it at his hands. Follow the
Sunne, and he wil bring thee where he is, to heauen,
at the right hand of his Father. Let no
wandring Planet erre thee; but adhere to the
Sunne with a faithfull imitation.
                  
                  
                     Care-
                           •
                        way.
                     IF worldly troubles come too fast vpon a man;
hee hath an herbe called Careaway. Not that
hee bequeathes himselfe to a supine negligence,
as if God would fill his house with prouision,
while he sits and sings care away. But as he
is free from idlenesse, so also from distrust. Hee
considers the Rauens and Lillies; and knowes,
that the Lord is the Preseruer of men, as well as
of Fowles and flowers: that hee respects man aboue

those, and his owne aboue other men.
Therefore hee throwes all his cares vpon God;
as if they were too heauy a lode for himselfe.
Sollicitous thoughtfulnes can giue him no hurt,
but this herbe Careaway shall easily cure it.
                  
                  
                     Holy Thi
                           •
                        tle, or good Resolution.
                     YEeld that hee is pressed with iniuries; as
who will liue godly in Christ, and shall not
suffer persecution! He is oppressed by force
or fraud, might or subtilty; and cannot helpe
himselfe. He hath a good herbe in this Garden,
called Carduus Benedictus, Holy thistle: a godly
resolution, that through many miseries he must
enter heauen. He rests himselfe on God; and
rather wisheth his harmelesnesse should suffer,
then himselfe not to giue passiue and patient obedience
to lawfull authority. Our God whom we
serue is able to deliuer vs from the burning fiery furnace,
                        Dan. 3. 17.
                        and hee will deliuer vs out of thine hand, O
King. But if not; be it knowne to thee, O King, that,
wee will not serue thy gods, nor worship thy golden
Image.
                     
                     There are many other herbes in this garden:
as if hee be to deale with craftie aduersaries, let
him fetch some Sage, honest policie; and such
as may stand with an vntouched conscience. For

Christ gaue vs this prohibition, to bee wise as
Serpents; though withall a cohibition, that we be
harmelesse as Doues.
                        Mat. 10. 16. If he be tempted to ebriety,
he hath in this Garden, Coleworts; moderate abstinence.
Matthiolus on the preface of Dioscorides
notes such a naturall enmitie betwixt this
herbe and drunkennesse: that if you plant Colewort
neere to the rootes of the Vine, of it selfe it
flyeth from them. But I excuse my selfe.
                     Non ego cunct a meis amplecti versibus opto.
                     I would not leaue nothing vnsayd. Thus I
haue walked you through a sacred Garden of
many gracious herbes: happy soules thus planted.
I will stay you no longer, then to heare
your blessing.
                  
                  
                     It receiueth blessing from God.
                     THe Reward giues a happy conclusion to
this good ground. So it pleaseth the Lord
to accept our labours, that he will reward
them; not after our owne merit, for that is not an
atome; but after his owne mercy, which exceedes
heauen and earth. Receiue this blessing
with a thankfull heart; thou hast not earn'd it. It
is obiected, that here it is sayd, their workes are
meet for God, therefore deserue this blessing. And
Wisd. 3.Wisd. 3. 5. 
                        God proued them, and found them meete for
himselfe; as if they could stand Gods tryall. And

                        Paul exhorts vs to walke worthie of the vocation,
                        Eph. 4. 1.
                        wherewith we are called. I answere, Deus coronat
don
                              •
                            sua, non merit a nostra.
                        Aug. God rewards his owne
workes, not our worth. It is giuen, Non meritis
operantis, sed miseratione donantis: not for the deserts
of the doer, but for the mercie of the giuer.
Datur operatoribus, non pro operibus. Luke chap.
12. Verse 32.Luke 12. 32. 
                        It is my Fathers will to giue you a
kingdome.
                     
                     Do wee good? from whom is it? doth not
God worke in vs to will and to doe? Thou hast
done well: be comforted; be not proud. It was
Gods worke,Bern. not thine. Omnia merita Dei dona
sunt: &amp; it a homo propter ipsa magis Deo debitor est,
quam Deus homini. All our good workes are
Gods giftes: and therefore man is more beholding
to God for them, then God to man. If in
this Garden any good herbe spring ouer the wall,
and sawcily challenge to i
                           •
                         selfe a prerogatiue of
merite; deale with it, as the Gardiner with supersluous
branches; prune it off. Or as Tor quatus
with his ouer-venturous sonne; cut it short
with the sword of the Spirit, for daring beyond
the Commission. Our Aduersaries oppose this
truth very violently, both in the Schooles, and
in the Pulpits: but come they to their deathbeds,
to argue it between God and their owne
soules; then grace and grace alone; mercy
and onely mercie; IESVS and none but IESVS.
                     And this euen their great Bell-weather is forced

to acknowledge.Bellar. de Iustif. lib. 5. cap. 7. 
                        Propter incert it udinem propriae
iustitiae, &amp; periculum inanis gloriae, tutissimum
est fiduciam totam in sola Dei misericordia &amp;
benignitate repo
                              •
                           ere. I will translate his words
truly. By reason of the vncertainty of our owne righteousnesse,
and the danger of vaine glorie; the sa
                           
                              •
                           est
course is to put our whole trust and confidence in
in the onely fauour and mercie of God. But perhaps
Bellarmine spoke this as a meere Iesuite; and now
made Papable, hee bee willing to recant and
vnsay it.
                     This blessing then comes not for the Grounds
merite, but for the Dressers mercie. It is sayd,
Gen. 6.Gen. 6. 5. tht God would destroy the World with
a floud, Because the imaginations of mans heart
were onely euill continually. And Gen. 8.Gen. 8. 21. it is sayd,
that GOD will no more curse and destroy the
ground for mans sake; because the imaginations of
his heart are onely euill from his youth. The same
reason that is alleaged, why God will not spare
the world, is also alleaged why God will spare
the world.
                     It serues plentifully to demonstrate, that not
for mans merite, but for Gods mercie, confusion
is withholden.Mal. 3. 6. 
                        I am the Lord, I change not.
Therefore ye sonnes of Iacob are not consumed.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     It receiueth.
                     SVch is the immense goodnesse of God, that
he will adde grace to grace, aud when hee
hath showne mercy, hee will shew more
mercy. As if he expected no other argument
of future bounty, but his former bounty. Whom
he did predestinate, them also he called: and whom he
called,
                        Rom. 8. 30. 
                        them also hee iustified: and whom he iustified,
them he also glorified. Man is to be considered in
a foure-fold estate. Confectionis, Infectionis, Refectionis,
Perfectionis. First, God made him happy,
without misery, without iniquity. God hath
made man vpright: but they haue sought out manie
inuentions.
                        Eccl. 7. 29. If a glorious heauen aboue him, a
fruitfull earth vnder him, feruiceable creatures
about him, could giue him solace and folicity,
hee was not scanted. Heere is mans first
draught of Gods bountie; his originall state.
2. Then man fell from holinesse, and so from
happinesse; and lost the fauour of the Creator,
with the good of the creature: that a generall
curse fell on the earth for his sake. Loe, now hee
lyes weltring in his gore, who shall heale him,
who shall reuiue him? God promised him a Sauiour,
and kept his word. Looke on his owne
only Sonne hanging, bleeding, dying on an accursed
Crosse. 3. A Redeemer is come; what
is man the better for it, that hath no power to
beleeue on him? Faith hee hath none, but what

God must put into him. Againe, Lord helpe:
let vs receiue yet a third mercie: make vs beleeuers,
or we are neuer the better. We had as good
haue no Sauiour, as not to haue him our Sauiour:
and ours hee cannot be, vnlesse the Lord
make vs his. 4. Lastly the Lord giues vs Faith:
and so we shall receiue a happines by this beleeued
Sauiour, better then euer our first creation
gaue vs: a kingdome; a kingdome of life; an
eternall kingdome of life; that can neuer be taken
from vs. Thus wee are still receiuers, and
God is the giuer. Wee receiue blessing from God.
                     
                  
                  
                     Blessing.
                     THis word is of a great latitude. What
good is there, which will not be brought
within this compasse? This blessing hath
a double extent. There is Beatitudo viae, and Beatitudo
Patriae. A blessing of the way, and a blessing
of the Countrey: one of grace, the other of
glory. The former is either outward, or inward.
                     1 Outward, Psal. 132.Ps. 132. 15. 
                        I will abundantly blesse
her proutsion: I will satisfie her poore with bread.
Deut. 28.Deut. 28. 4. Blessed in the field, blessed in the citie.
The fruits of thy body, of thy ground, of thy cattell
shall be blessed. Thy basket, thy store; thy going
out, and comming in shall be blessed. Which
things doe often come to the godly euen on
earth, and that in abundance. For as all haue
not riches, that exceedingly loue them: so many
haue them, that doe not much care for them.

Wealth is like a woman; the more courted, the
further off.
                     
                     2 Inward. The godly on earth is (as it were)
in the suburbs of heauen;Rom. 14. 17. whose kingdome consists,
not in meate and drinke, but righteousnesse, peace of
conscience, and ioy of the holy Ghost. Could his
life bee as full of sorrowes, as euer Lazarus was
full of sores, yet he is blessed. The Sunne-shine
of mercie is still vpon him; and the blessing of
GOD makes him rich. Let the ayre thunder,
and the earth quake, and hell roare; yet He that
walketh vprightly,
                        Pro. 10. 9. 
                        walketh surely. Qui vadit plane,
vadit sane. I haue read it storied of a young Virgin,
that at a great Princes hands had the choise
of three vessels. One whereof should be freely
giuen her, euen that she should chuse. The first
was a vessell of gold, richly wrought, and set
with precious stones; and on it written. Who
chooseth me shall haue what he deserueth. The
second was of siluer. superscribed thus. Who
chuseth me shall haue what nature desireth. The
third was of lead; whose motto was this. Who
chuseth me, shall haue what God hath disposed.
The former pleased her eye well, but not her vnderstanding.
It offred what she deserued. She
knew, that was iust nothing: therefore refused
it. The second considered, offred what
Nature desires. Shee thought that could
bee no solide good; for Nature desires
such things as please the carnall lust. This shee
also refused. The third had a course outside, but

the sentence pleased her wel; offering what God
had disposed. So she faithfully put her selfe vpon
Gods ordinance, and chose that. This Virginis
mans soule. The golden vessell is the worlds riches;
contentf
                           •
                        ll to an auarous eye. Too many
chuse this: but being open'd, it was full of dead
mens bones, and a fooles bable. To testifie
them fooles, which cleaue to the world: and at
last all their hopes shall bee rewarded with a bable.
Neither is this all. Though their inward
thought be, that their houses shall continue for euer;
yet they shal be layd in the graue like sheep,
                        Psal. 49. 11. 14. 
                        and death
shall feed on them. The siluer-vessell is the lusts of
the flesh; those fond and vaine delights, which
concupiscence seeks. So saith the Motto: It giues
what nature desireth: but corrupt nature affects
nothing, but what giues cōplacency to the flesh.
This vessell open'd was full of wild fire, and an iron
whip. God shall scourge the lustfull here
with the whip of iudgements, diseases of body,
infamy of name, ouerthrow of estate, vexation of
conscience. And Satan shall hereafter burne
them in wild fire, such flames as can neuer bee
quenched. The leaden vessell is, as the sense &amp;
sentence declares it, the blessing of God. The chuser
of it shall haue what God hath disposed for
him. Blessed soule that makes this election: for
opened, it was found full of gold and most precious
iewels; euery one more worth then a world,
the immortall graces of Gods Spirit.
                     The Virgin chose this, and she was married

to the Kings sonne. Chuse this vessell, O my
soule; and Iesus Christ the king of heauen shall
marry thee. No matter though it seeme lead
without; glister not with earthly vanities: it is
rich within; the wealth thereof cannot be valued,
though all the Arithmeticians of the world
goe about to summe it.Psal. 4. 6. 
                        There bee many that say,
who will shewe vs anie good? Lord lift thou vp the
light of thy countenance vpon vs.
                     
                     This blessing hath yet a further extent, to the
blessednesse of our Countrey: when wee shall
heare it: Come yee blessed of my Father, inherit the
kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of
the world.
                        Mat. 25. 34. For, si sic bonus es sequentibus te, qualis
futurus es consequentibus! If thou Lord,Bern. Serm. 47. in Cant. be so
good to those that follow thee, what wilt thou
be to those that finde thee! If there be such blessing
in this world, what shall that be in the life to
come! If the first fruites of our inheritance, and
the earnest of the spirit bee so graciously sweete
here: surely when that infinite masse of glory
shall be broken vp, and communicated to vs, we
shall be wonderfully rauished. When that which
is perfect is come,
                        1. Cor. 13. 10. 
                        then that which is in part shall bee
done away. This is, beat a vita in fonte, sayth Aug.
a blessed life indeed. Aeterna sine successione, distributa
sine diminutione, communis sine inuidia,
sufficiens sine indigentia, iucunda sine tristitia, beata
sine omni miseria. Thou wilt shewe mee the path
of life: in thy presence is the fulnesse of ioy,
                        Psal. 16. 11. 
                        at thy
right hand there are pleasures for euermore.
                     
                     
                        
No tongue can declare this blessing; happy
heart that shall feele it: whose glorified eye shall
one day behold all: and ten thousand times more
then we haue spoken. Who shall say, as it is in
the Psalme: Sicut 
                              〈◊〉
                           , it a &amp; vidimus;
as we haue heard, so wee haue seene in the Citie of our
God. As we haue heard it preached on earth, we
now finde it true in heauen: though the Citie we
enioy farre excell the mappe we sawe.
                     Well this is Gods blessing, and he will giue
it to the good ground. Labour we then to bee
fruitfull Gardens; and to abound with gracious
herbes; that God may in this world showre vpon
vs, the deawes of his mercie: and after this
life transplant vs to his heauenly Paradise. Let
not the pleasures of sinne; the lusts of the wanton
flesh, the riches, snares, cares of the world, nor
all those transient delights, whose taste is only in
the sense, the operation in the conscience; that
tickle men for an houre, and wound them for euer:
nor all those vaine desires of carnall complacency,
which shall one day bee layd vpon
Gods cold earth; intercept vs to the priuation
of this blessing.
                     Let vs not be hunting after sports, as Esau for
venison, and loose our blessing: lest wee cry,
howle, rore, when it is too late to recouer it
Thinke, oh thinke: there is a heauen, a GOD,
a IESVS, a kingdome of glory, society of
Angels, communion of Saints, ioy, peace, happinesse,
and eternity of all these; which it will

bee a fearefull thing to loose, for the base pleasures
and short delights of this world.
                     O great God of all, and sweete Father of thy
chosen, poure vpon vs thy holy deawes of grace:
make our soules to stand thicke with sanctified
herbes; that we may receiue thy blessing. That
honouring thee in the day of Grace, we may bee
hononoured by thee in the day of Glory. Grant
this for thy loued Sonne, and our louing
Sauiour, euen, IESVS CHRIST
his sake. Amen.
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  THE
FORREST
Of
Thornes.
                  
                     THE
FOVRTH SERMON.
                  EZEK. 28. 24.
                  There shal be no more a pricking Bryar vnto the house of Israel, nor
any grieuing Thorne of all that are round about them.
                  
                     Terra salutifferas herbas, eadem que nocentes
Nutrit; &amp; vrticae proxima saepe rosa est.
                  
                  LONDON,
Printed by George Purslowe, for Iohn Budge, and are to be
solde at his shop, at the great South-dore of Pauls,
and at Brittaines Burse. 1616.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                  THE
FORREST
Of
THORNES.
                  THE
FOVRTH SERMON.
                  
                     HEB. Chap. 6. Vers. 8.
                     But that which beareth thornes and bryers, is reiected, and
is nigh vnto cursing, whose end is to be burned.
                  
                  
                     THis verse begins with a word
of Dsiunction; But. The
Raine of grace falls vpon the
good ground: it returneth
berbes; it receiueth blessing.
But that which beareth thorns
and bryers, is reiected, and is
nigh vnto cursing. &amp;c. It is vndeniably true, that
S. Paul
                     Act. 20. 27. knew no Purgatory: otherwise, he that
shunned not to declare to men all the counsell of God,
                     
would not in a voluntary silence haue omitted
this mysterie. He deliuers two sorts of Grounds,
the good and the bad; the one blessed, the other
neere vnto cursing. Hee knew no meane, either
betwixt good and euill men, or betwixt reward
and punishment, blessing and cursing. It seemes
that Christ him
                        •
                     elfe was ignorant of that point,
which the Papists know so soundly, and beleeue
so roundly.Mat. 13. 24. For he sayes, In Gods Field, whatsoeuer
growes is either corne or cockle: for the
one whereof a Barne is prouided; for the other,
vnquenchable Fire. A third sort, betweene
herbes and weedes, had either the Master or the
Seruant knowne, they would haue acknowledged.
                  This first word of the Text, But, is a strong
engine set to the wals of Purgatory, to ouer-turne
them, and ouer-burne them with the fire of hell.
For they are imaginary pales, that diuide hell
and Purgatorie: take away your conceit, and
they are both one: all is hell. For surely hell
was raked, when Purgatory was found; and it is
nothing els but a larder to the Popes Kitchin.
What fancie soeuer founded it, their wittes are
foundred, that labour to maintaine it. For they
cannot tell vs, vel quid sit, vel vbi: what it is, nor
where it is. They cauill with vs for want of vnity
and consent in iudgement.De Purgat. lib. 2. cap. 6. Yet Bellarmine recites
eight seuerall opinions amongst them, about
the place: And concludes at last, that it
must remaine among those secrets, Quae suo

tempore aperientur nobis; which shall bee vnfolded
to vs in their times. Some thinke the
torments of it to consist in fire, others in water:
some that the afflicters are Angels, other that
they are Deuils. So they teach omni modo, that
which is nullo modo: and because it is vbique, is
therefore nullibi. Howsoeuer, it being the Popes
peculiar; and in his power to command the Angels
to fetch out whom hee list; mee thinks the
Popes are strangely vnmercifull, that in all this
time none of them hath made a generall Gaole-deliuerie.
But our Purgatorie is the blood of
Iesus Christ,
                     1. Ioh. 1. which clenseth vs from sinne. And
they that haue no portion in this blood shall be
reiected, are nigh vnto cursing, and their end is to
be burned.
                  
                  The barren, or rather euil-fruited ground is
the ground of my discourse: and according to
the common distinction of Euill, here is a double
euill in the Text. Vnum quod malus facit, alterum
quod malus patitur. An euill which the wicked
man doth; and an euill which he suffers: an
euill that is sinne, and an euill that is punishment
for sinne. In the former the wicked are agents;
in the latter, patients. The one euill is done by
them, the other vpon them. They offend Gods
iustice, and GOD in his iustice offends them.
They haue loued cursing, and cursing shall be vnto
them: they desired not blessing, and it is farre from
them. They produce Thornes, and the end of
thornes is to bee burned. The first and worst euill

(for the other, though euill to them, is good in
Gods good Iustice) is sinne. Herein 1. the wicked
are compared to bad ground. 2. their iniquities
to thornes and bryers. 3. and the manner
how so ill weeds arise from this ground, is said to
be bearing. The earth that beareth thornes, &amp;c.
Here first obserue,
                  1 The different word the Apostle vseth. For
the good earth, hee sayes, it is 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                     bringing forth herbes. For the euill, it is 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     ,
bearing, not bringing forth. As if good workes
were brought forth like children, not without
paine and trauell: euill workes but cast out like
froth or skimme; as easily vented, as inuented.
Therefore the earth is said ebullire, to bubble or
boile out such things, as meere excretions. Our
prouerbe sayes, An ill weed growes apace. Herbes
grow not without preparing the ground, planting
and watring them by seasonable deawes and diligence.
Weeds are common: it is hard to set
the foote besides them. The basest things are euer
most plentifull. Plurima, pessima. I haue read
of a kind of mouse, that breeds sixe score young
ones in one nest. Whereas the off-spring of the
Lyonesse or Elephant is but single. You shall
find your furrowes full of Cockle and da
                        ••
                     ell,
though you neuer sew them. The earth, sayth
the Philosopher, is now an own mother to weeds,
and naturally breeds and feeds them: but a stepmother
to good herbes. Man by a procliuitie
of his own naturall inclination, is apt to produce

                     thornes and bryers: but ere hee can bring forth
herbes, Graces, God must take paines with him.
No husbandman so labours his ground, as God
our hearts. Happy earth, that yeelds him an expected
haruest. But that which beareth Thornes is
neere to be cursed and burned.
                  
                  2 Obserue, that a wicked man is compared
to bad earth, and that fitly in 5. respects.
                  1 For basenesse. The earth is the heauiest of
all Elements, and doth naturally sinke downewards;
as if it had no rest, but in the center; which
it selfe is. A wicked man is base-minded, and
sinkes with a dull and ponderous declination; not
regarding the things aboue, but these below. He
hath commune with men sursum os, but with
beasts, deorsum cor. All his affections haue a low
obiect, not out of humilitie, but base deiection.
His hope, desire, loue, ioy, are set on these inferiour
things: and like a Mole, he digs still downewards,
till he come to his Center, his owne place,
Hell.Acts. 1. 
                     Telluris inutile pondus.
                  
                  2 For coldnesse. Experience teacheth that the
earth is cold; &amp; coldnes is a natural quality pertinent
to it, though accidentally there be bred in it
fierie vapours. The wicked man hath a cold heart,
frozen vp in the dregs of iniquitie; though there
be an vnnaturall heat sometimes flaming in him;
the fire of lust and malice tormenting his bowels:
but this is no kindly heate to warme his conscience.
That is deriued from the fire of the
Temple, that neuer goes out, and only giuen by

                     Iesus Christ, that baptizeth with the holy Ghost, and
with fire.
                  
                  3 For foulenesse. The squalid earth (for we
speake not heere of any good ground) is called
Lutulenta terra; miery and noysome: yet is it
neate and cleane in comparison of a sinne-contaminated
soule. The body was taken from the
earth; not the Soule: the body shall resolue to
the earth; not the soule: yet the polluted soule is
more sordid, then either a leprous body, or a
muddy earth. In the eye of GOD, there is
no beautie so acceptable, no foulenesse so detestable,
as the soules. The Doue carried the
prayse of beautie from the Peacocke, by the Eagles
iudgement: that though the Peacocke liuing
had the fayrer plumes, yet dead he hath but
a blacke liuer. Gods iudgement of all mens
fairenesse, is by the liuer, the cleanesse of the heart
in his eye-sight.
                  
                  4 For obscuritie and darkenesse; the earth is
called a place of blacke darkenesse, the land of forgetfulnesse.
So Iob and Dauid tearme it. The wicked
Soule is full of darkenesse, thicknesse of sight,
caecitie of vnderstanding; not seeing the glorious
libertie of the Sonnes of God. Our Gospell is hid
to those that are lost.
                     1. Cor. 4. 4▪
                      
                     Whose minds the god of this
world hath blinded.
                     
                        
                           •
                        ugo. There is in them Hebetudo
mentis, which is acutae rationis obtusio, carnalis intemperantiae
crassis sensibus inducta. They are so
vtterly ignorant of heauen, that (as it is in the
Prouerbe) ne pictum quidem viderunt: they haue

not seene it, so much as in the mappe or picture.
As to men shut vp in the low cauernes of the
earth, not so much as the sunne, and starres, and
the lights of heauens lower parts haue appeared.
Tolerabilior est poena, viuere non posse, quam nescire.
Ignorance is a heauier punishment then death;
sayth the Philosopher.Se
                           •
                        . Darkenes is their desire,
because their deeds are euill. Perhaps at last, after
a long dotage on their darke delight, earth; they
come to heare of a better &amp; richer countrey: and
then take onely with them the Lanterne of Nature
to find it. But so erepto lumine can delabrum
querunt. Hauing lost the light, they grope for
the Candlesticke. A man that comes into his
house at midnight, sees nothing amisse: in the
day-light he finds many things misplac'd. Nature
is but a darke Lanterne, when by it we endeuour
to ransacke the conscience. Onely the light of
grace can demonstrate all the sluttish and incurious
misorders in our soules.
                  5 The maine resemblance betweene an euill
ground and worse man, consists in the ill fruites,
that they both produce: bryers and thornes; and
such (not onely vnhelpefull, but) hurtfull vices.
This is the principal analogie, which our Apostle
intends; the pith and marow of this reference.
But before we come to a particular anatomizing
of this Subiect, some obseruable doctrines fall
profitably to our instruction. Obserue therfore.
                  1 The word of God will worke some way. It
fals not vpon any ground in vaine; but will produce

                     herbes or weeds. It is such Physicke, as will
either cure or kill. It mollifies one, makes another
more hard.Acts. 2. Some hearts it pricks, others it
terrifies, though conuerts not, as it made Foelix
tremble. None euer heard it, but they are either
better or worse by it.1. Cor. 1. 23. 
                     We preach Christ crucified,
vnto the Iewes a stumbling blocke, vnto the Gentiles
foolishnesse. But vnto them which are called, both
of Iewes and Greeks, the power of GOD,
                     Heb. 4. 12. 
                     and the
wisedome of God. In this Epistle it is called a double-edged
sword, &amp;c. It is either a conuerting or
conuincing power; sealing receiuers to redemption,
contemners to reiection. The word which
I haue preached, shall iudge you in the latter day.
                  
                  If this doctrine were considerately digested
in hearers hearts, what a zealous preparation
would it worke in their soules! It would bring
vs to these seats with other minds, if we remembred,
that wee returne not backe to our owne
doores the very same wee came out; but either
somewhat better,Act. 13. 7. 8. or much worse. Sergius Paulus
was turned, Elimas obdurated at one Sermon.
After our Sauiours heauenly Sermon. Iohn 6.
Some went backe,
                     Ioh. 6. 66. 
                     and walked no more with him; that
Christ bespake his Apostles, Will ye also goe away?
Others stucke more close.Verse 68. 
                     Lord, to whom shall we
goe? Thou hast the words of eternall life. The
Prophet Esay speakes fully to this purpose. As
the raine commeth downe,
                     Esay. 55. 10. 
                     and returneth not
backe, but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring
forth and bud, that it may giue seede to the sower,

and bread to the eater. So shall my word be that goeth
forth out of my mouth: it shall not returne vnto
mee voyd; but it shall accomplish that which I please,
and it shall prosper in the thing whereto I sent it.
                  
                  The word that we haue preached, shall either
saue you, or iudge you. It shall be either a copy
of your pardon, or a bill of your inditement at
the last day. Iohn Baptist cals the Gospell a Fan,
that will distinguish betweene true and false children,
betweene Wheate and Chaffe. It will make
knowne the faithfulnesse of those,Mat. 3. 12. that with honest
harts embrace it; and scatter hypocrites like
chaffe, by reason of their insolid leuity. Simeon so
prophecied to Mary the Virgin of her Son, That
he should be the fall and the rising, the reparation
and ruine of many:Luke. 2. 34. and whiles he is set for a signe
Which shall bee spoken against, by this meanes the
thoughts of many hearts shall be reuealed. The
word is like fire, that hath a double operation vpon
the seuerall subiects it works; stubble or gold.
It fires the one, and fines the other. Some hearts
it enflames with zeale to it: other it sets on fire
to quench, impugne, persecute it. It is to conuersion,
if beleeued; to confusion if despised. Lo,
Christ, himselfe preaching, some faithfully entertaine,
others reiect;Mat. 8. as the Gergesens, that had rather
haue their hogges saued then their soules.
                  2. That thornes are produced, the fault is not
in the good Raine, but the ill ground. What could
I,
                     Esa. 4. 5. sayth God, haue done more to my Vineyard? I
haue done inough to make it beare good grapes.

                     Wherefore then, or from what cause brings it forth
wild grapes? The earth desires the influence of
heauen, and showres from the cloudes, to make
it fruitfull. It is granted: the Sunne shines, the
dewes fall. The Garden hereupon brings forth
herbes, the desart thornes. If these blessings of
heauen were the proper cause of the weeds; why
hath not then the good ground such cursed effects?
The euerlasting lampe of heauen sends
forth his sauing rayes: and the sacred deawes of
the Gospell fall on the pure and vncleane heart.
There it is requited with a fertile obedience:
here with an impious ingratitude. Let not the
mercy of God be blamed for this mans miserie.
Perditio ex se: God hath done enough to saue
him. S. Augustine directly to this purpose. Simul
pluit Dominus super segetes,
                     De benedict. Esauet Iacob. 
                     &amp; super spinas. Sed
segeti pluit ad horreum, spinis ad ignem: &amp; tamen
vna est pl
                           •
                        uia. GOD at once raines vpon the
herbes and the thornes. Vpon the herbs or good
seed, to shoot it vp for his barne, for himselfe; vpon
the thornes to fit them for the fire: yet is it
one and the same raine.
                  This shall couer the faces of Libertines with

                        •
                     uerlasting confusion; who are euermore rubbing
their owne filthinesse on Gods puritie; and
charging him as the authour of their sinnes. If
the Diuels in hell should speake, what could they
say more? wee haue falne from our happinesse,
and God caused it. Reprobate thoughts! Men
haue spilt bloud, defiled forbidden beds, strucke

at Princes with treasons, ruin'd countries with
depopulations, filled the earth with rapes, and
shot at heauen with blasphemies; and lay their
damnation on their Maker: deriuing from his
purpose excuses of their wickednesse. The ineuitable
decree of Gods counsell is charged: the
thought of that hath made them carelesse: so
with good food they poison themselues. Willing
fooles, racke not your beleefe with impossibilities.
Behold! God is so farre from authorizing
your sinnes and falls; that he raines on yo
                        •
                     
the holy deawes of his word to mollifie your
hearts. Iustifying himselfe by this proffered
meanes of your saluation, that he would not the
death of a sinner. O but his hidden will is to
damne vs. Mad men, that forsake that signed
will, written in tables, published with trumpets,
commanded with blessings, cursings, promises,
menaces, to which euery soule stands bound!
and fall to prying into those vnsearchable mysteries,
couered with a curtaine of holy secrecy,
not to be drawne aside till the day comes, wherein
we shall know as we are knowne.
                  Cease aspiring man to roote thy wickdnesse
in heauen; and to draw in God as an accessary
to thy profanenesse. God would haue thee saued,
but thou wilt beare thorns and briars, though
thou endangerest thy selfe to cursing. Is this the
requitall for his mercy? Are all his kindnesses
to thee thus taken? That when he hath done so
much to bring thee to heauen, thou wilt taxe him

for casting thee to hel? when he hath so laboured
to make thee good, thou wilt lay to his charge
thy owne voluntary badnesse. No: iustifie God,
and magnifie his mercie. Accuse thine owne
corrupt heart, that turnes so good and alimentall
food into offensiue crudities. Say, Heauen
is good, but thy ground is naught. Fatnesse and
iuyce hath been bestowed on thee, but thou hast
yeelded pestilent and noysome fruits. Lay not
the fault on heauen, but on the natiue corruption
of thy owne heart, that hath decocted the
goodnesse of God into venome.
                  3. This obseruation shall make way (and
giue place) to another. That the ground is very
vnthankfull, which answeres the kindnes of heauen
in rayning on it, with bryars and thornes.
Wretched man, that receiues so blessed deawes
from the fountaine of mercie, and returnes an
vngratefull wickednesse. Vnthankefull it is; as
failing in both these essentiall parts of Gratitude;
acknowledging, and requiting a benefite: and so
guilty both of falshood and iniustice. Say the
wicked did confesse Gods mercies, yet where's
their obedience? True thankfulnesse is called
Gratiarum actio, non dictio. Whiles for holy
deawes they render vnholy weedes, this disobedience
is the greatest Ingratitude. The silence of
our tongues; the not opening our lippes, to let our
mouth shew forth his prayse, is a grieuous vnthankfulnesse.
He is of an euill disposition, that conceales
or dissembles a benefite. This is one

branch of Ingratitude: but our speech hitherto
keepes but lowe water; let vs rise vp to view the
mountenous billows of that ingratitude here taxed;
a reall, actual, sensuall, senselesse vnthankfulnesse:
if it bee not a degree beyond it, and vnthankfulnesse
too poore a word to expresse it.
Meere ingratitude returnes nothing for good;
but this sinne returnes euill for good. Silence in
acknowledging is too short: we must thinke of a
contumacious and contumelious retribution.
God, after his mercifull raine lookes for some
herbs of Grace, when he walks down into his Garden,
to see whether the Vine flourished,
                     Cant. 6. 11. 
                     and the Pomegranates
budded. And behold weedes, stinking
weedes, stinging weedes; thornes and bryars!
Here is Ingratitude in ful proportion, wiith all the
dimensions of his vgly stigmaiticke forme. This
is that wickednes, which brings the ground here
to reiection, malediction, combustion. Obserue
further that
                  4. Wicked men proue commonly so much the
worse, as they might haue been better: and diuert
the means of their conuersion to their confusion.
The more raine of the Gospell they receiue, the
more abundantly they thrust forth the thornes of
iniquities. The rootes of these bryars are surely
earthed in their hearts, and do boyle out at the
warme deaws of the Word. It fares with them, as
with a man of a surfeted stomach: the more good
meate he eates, the more hee increaseth his corruption.
The former crudities vndigested, vnegested,

hauing the greater force, turne the good
nutriment into themselues. There is such an antipathie
betwixt the good word of God, and the
heart of a reprobate; that the more it wrastles to
bring him to heauen, the more he wrastles against
it, that hee might be damned. Tully mentions a
Countrey, wherein a great drought and heat maketh
abundance of mire and dirt; but store of
raine causeth dust. It is here experimentally true:
the plentifull raine of Gods blessed word is answered
with the dusty and sandy barrennesse of
mens euill liues. So the Sunne, shining vpon vncleane
dung-hils, is said to cause a greater stench:
yet no wise man blames the beames of the Sunne,
but the filthinesse of those putrified heapes, for
such offence. The Sunne of righteousnesse hath
sent downe the glorious rayes of his Gospell among
vs
                        •
                      the wicked hereupon steame out the
more noysome and stenchfull fruites. Vpon
whom shal the accusation light; Gods comfortable
heate of mercie, or our putrid and ranke iniquities?
Sometimes the Sunnes heat working vpon
a muddy and baneful obiect, breeds horrid serpents.
No wonder then, if this raine of the Gospel
ingender in reprobate minds, weeds, and prickles.
The Cicones haue a riuer, that doth harden
the bowels,Ouid. and make the entrals stony: a strange
operation in them that drink it. But if the water of
life do harden the hearts of Pharaohs, and exasperate
the mischiefes of a malicious Elimas, let the
imputation of fault light where it is deserued.

It was a strange protestatiō, that God had against
Israel. I haue nourished and brought vp children, and
they haue rebelled against me.
                     Esa. 1. 2. I haue brought them
vp in my house, and taught them my precepts, and
yet (as if my instructions and fauours had made
them worse) they haue rebelled against me. Thus
when the Sunne is hottest, the springs are coldest:
and the more feruent the loue of God is to vs, the
more cold is our charity to him, and to others for
him. As if the sweet dews of Hermon had made
the hill of Syon more barren.
                  It is written of the Thraeian flint, that it burnes
with water, and is quenched with oyle: a fit Embleme
of those wicked soules, that are the worse
for Gods endeuour to better them. But such contrary
effects hath the Gospell in contrary natures.
As by the heat of the Sunne waxe is softned, and
yet clay is hardned: so by the preaching of the
word, the hearts of such as shal be saued, are mollified;
but the hearts of the lost are further obdurate.
God in his wis
                        •
                      iustice wil be euen with men:
since they will not bee the better for his fauours,
they shal be the worse. Seeing they wil not bring
forth herbes, they shall cast forth weeds: and he
that might not in their saluation, will be glorified
in their subuersion. For application.
                  This Raine hath falne vpon vs all: how haue
wee entertained it? where bee our herbes? It is
obiected against vs, that our forefathers who wanted
this raine, brought forth more herbs, then we
that haue it. That they in the daies of ignorāce did

more then they knew; that we in the light of the
Gospel know more then we do. Apollonius among
other wonders writes one most wonderfull: that
there was a people, which could see nothing in
the day, but all in the night. What, hath the
Sunne blinded vs? Cannot wee see to serue God
so well in the light, as they did in the darke?
                  It was once said, Ignoti nulla cupido: but now it
may be inuerted; Noti nullus amor: we little esteeme
the Gospel, because it is frequent amongst
vs. The long enioying it hath dulled our estimation.
Full children are weary of their bread, and
play with it. Like the Indians, that haue such
store of gold and precious stones, that they truck
them away for glasses and rattles. Perhaps the
cold legs of custome will bring vs to Church:
and we are content to heare the Preacher taxing
our frauds, vsuries, oathes, oppressions. May be
for some shew of deuotion, wee will aske counsell
at his lips: but say what he will, wee will not part
with our sinnes.
                  The Princes of Israel came to Ieremie, and intreat
him to inquire of the Lord fot them:Ier. 42. promising,
that whatsoeuer direction the Lord should
send they would obey. The Prophet accordingly
presents their supplication to God. God answers
You shall not goe into Egypt,
                     Ier. 43. 
                     lest you be destroyed: but
abide still in Iudah, and you shall be safe. When
they heard this Oracle, because it was not their
humours, they replied, We will goe into Egypt. This
was their purpose from the beginning, (though

they dissembled a will to know Gods mind) which
if Gods command crosseth, they will crosse his
command: they will goe into Egypt. So people
will be content to heare what God sayth to them
by his Ministers: but if hee speake not what pleaseth
them, they will follow their owne affections.
Wee are such nice and froward pieces, that the
more God wooes vs, we are the further off. As
it is with some shallow professors of Musicke,
sayth the Poet.
                  
                     Omnibus hoc vitium cantoribus,Hor. lib. 1. inter amicos,
                     Vt nunquam inducant animum cantare rogati.Sat. 3.
                     
                  
                  When they are most earnestly intreated, they
make most daintie to sing or play. So the more
the Lord cals for our praises, the more hoarse are
our voices, the more harsh our notes; or perhaps
we will not sing at all. But if God hath giuen vs
musicke, and we will not dance; as Christ reproued
the Iewes; wee shall mourne in sadnesse for
our obstinate refusall of profered mirth. You
haue heard Herodotus tale of the Piper. He came
to the water-side, and piped to the fishes: they
would not dance. Hee tooke his net and caught
some of them; and being throwne vpon drie land
they began to leape and skip vp. Nay, quoth the
Piper, I offered you musicke before, and you
would none: now you shal dance without a pipe.
Men commonly regard the Songs of Sion, as they
doe musicke heard late at night in the streets,
whiles they are in bed. Perhaps they will step to
the windore, and listen to it a while; and presently

to bed againe. So men step from the couch
of their lusts and sinnes to, Church, heare the
Sermon; and then to bed againe; lulling themselues
in their former securitie.
                  There are some, that care for hearing it no
more: but sit downe with a conceit of their owne
sufficiencie. They know as much as all the Preachers
can tell them: let the youth go to be Catechized.
So the sluggish and irreligious Master
sits at home, whiles hee sends his seruants to
Church. There is an old tale, idle in it selfe; the
vse may be good. A certaine man that would
neuer go to Church, when hee heard the Saintsbell,
would say to his wife. Goe thou to Church
and pray for thee and me. One night he dream't,
that both he and his wife were dead, and that they
knocked together at Heauen-gate for entrance. S.
Peter (by the Legend) is Porter, and suffred the
wife to enter in, but kept the husband out: answering
him, Illa intrauit pro se ette: She is gone in
both for her selfe and thee. As thy wife went to
Church for thee, so shee must goe to heauen for
thee. The Morall instructs euery one to haue a
personality of Faith, and a proprietie of deuotion:
that himselfe seruing GOD, himselfe may bee
blessed of God.
                  It now remaines, to examine more narrowly
the nature of the sinnes these vngodly hearts produce.Lib. 21. cap. 16.
They are called Thornes and Bryers. Plinie
sayth that the Thorne is more soft then a Tree, and
more hard then an Herbe: as if it were some vnkindly

thing; and but an vnperfect excrement of
the earth. For the Philosopher sayth, It is not the
intent of kind, that Trees should be sharpe with
prickles and thornes: but he would haue it caused
by the insoliditie and vnfastnes of the tree. By
which meanes the cold humour is drawne out by
the pores ere it bee concocted: whereupon for
scarcitie of matter, it is hardned by the sunne; and

                        •
                     o shaped and sharpned into a thorne.
                  
                  But it is vnquestionable truth, that God created
the thornes and bryers on the earth. Some
thinke, because it is sayd, Gen. 3.G
                           •
                        n. 3. 18. in mans punishment,
Maledict
                           •
                         esto terra propter te: Cursed be the
earth for thy sake. Thornes and Thistles shall it
bring forth to thee: that therefore if mankind had
not sinned, the ground should haue produced no
such thing. But the most receiued opinion, and
consonant to truth is; that these Thornes and bryers
should haue been, though man had neuer faln:
but they should not haue been noxious and hurtfull
to him. Now let vs consider what resemblances
may be found, betwixt those naturall, and
these allegoricall thornes and bryers.
                  
                  1 Where is abundance of thornes, there is
most commonly a barren ground. For they hinder
the happy influence of the heauens, the kindly
heat of the sunne, the deawes of the clouds, and
all those working causes of fertillity. God prearmes
Ezekiel, that he should not wonder at the
barrennesse of Israel,
                     Ezek. 2. 6. 
                     for bryers and thornes shall
be with thee. Let no man maruell at our vnprofitable

times; we haue too many Bryers and thorns
among vs: which do what they can to hinder the
goodnes of heauen to vs, or our goodnes to heauen.
That which is sowne nigh or among thorns
seldome prospers. Our Sauiour saith, that the
Seede sowne in some hearers, brought forth no
fruite;Mat. 13. 
                     for the Thornes choked it. The very company
of the wicked is harmful, for they are as thorns
to stifle any goodnes. The companion of fooles shal
be afflicted, saith Salomon. He dwels among thorns,
that shall wound him. To lay no more affliction
vpon him then Salamon there meant; as appeares
by the opposite member of the verse: he shall endure
a priuation of what good soeuer he had; and
a position of their lewdnesse. A good man with
ill company, is like a liuing man bound to a dead
corps: that will sooner suffocate him, then hee
can reuiue that. The Soule that liues among
thornes shall hardly thriue. Therefore saith the
Lord of the vineyard concerning the barren tree.
Cut it downe,
                     Luke. 13. 7. 
                     why troubles it the ground?
                  
                  2 Thornes and bryers grow most commonly
on heapes, and seldome are found single, or destitute
of company of their owne kinde, And
though they be troublesomely harmefull to other
trees, yet they fold and embrace one another,
without hurt. It is so vsually seene, that wicked
men hold together, and sinnes grow in vnited
clusters. There is a combination of the vngodly;
euen so farre as to the very participation of their
estates.Pro. 1. 14. 
                     Cast in thy lot with vs; wee will haue all

one purse. They are intangled in mutuall amity,
like beds of Eeles; nothing but thunder can break
their knots.Mat. 5. 46. Is it much, sayth Christ, that you purpose
diligere diligentes, to loue them that loue you?
Why, bryars and thornes do it, euen Publicans doe
the same. Yea, I would to God, their vnity did not
shame ours. We see here, that one of the Papists
chiefe marks of their church is not infallible; their
cōsent or vnity: when bryers &amp; thorns haue it. The
Pharises, Saduces, Herodians conspire against
Christ: may be, they with the rest. Sins grow in
heaps, like thornes in bushes: where are some, are
many. The Apostle brings them in by couples &amp;
companies. Gluttonie &amp; Drunkennes, Chambering
and wantonnesse,
                     Rom. 13. 13. 
                     strife and enuying. Me thinkes
Gluttonie &amp; Drunkennes come in like an Englishman,
and a Dutchman. Chambering &amp; Wantonnes
like an Italian and a Venetian. Strife &amp; Enuie like
a Spaniard and a Frenchman. These sins being
so Nationall, and naturall to the countreys: to ouer-drinke
in Germanie; to ouer-eate in England;
to wantonize in Italie and Venice; to quarrel in
Fraunce, and to be enuious in Spaine; Enuie being
euer the bosome-companion of Pride.
                  3 Thornes and bryers, by reason of their thicknes
and sharpnes, are refuges for Serpents, Snakes,
Addars, and such other venemous beasts. Where
the vngodly haue a strong part, oppression, rapine,
robberie, murder, and all those fatall and deathstriking
serpents are fostered. God, when he told
Ezekiel. Ezek. 2. That bryers and thornes should

be with him; addes in the very next words, And
thou shalt dwell among Scorpions. Therefore in
Latine, Rubetum is a place of bryars and brambles;
and Rubeta is a toad, and that land-toad, the
most venemous of the kinde. It is dangerous sleeping
neere such places. He that liues among the
wicked, hath no neede of security, but to haue
cleere and circumspect eyes; lest either the thorns
pricke him, or the Serpents vnder the thorns sting
him. Woe is me, sayth the Psalmist, that I must remaine
in Mesheck, and dwell in the tents of Kedar.
                  
                  4. Neither doe the wicked, onely with their
thorns and bryars, hinder others passage, but euen
their owne. No maruell, if it be so difficult for an
vngodly man to get to heauen; for hee hedgeth
vp his owne way. Men multiply their transgressions
to infinite, and cast vp innumerable thornes,
yet hope well to be saued. But in vaine he purposeth
to trauell to Ierusa
                           •
                        em, that hedgeth vp his
owne passage.Pro. 22. 5. 
                     Thornes and snares are in the way
of the froward: not of Gods setting, but of their
owne planting. For (the next words testifie) hee
that keepeth his soule, shall be farre from them. There
are hindrances enough to heauen, though the
wicked make none themselues. The diuell will
looke, that the way shall not bee easie. Neither
hath God set saluation vpon such termes, that we
may play and get it. The kingdome of heauen is got
by violence: and they must striue, that wil passe the
narrow gate. Satan hath so many plots and tricks
to deceiue them; so many tentations, and corruptions

to oppose them; that they haue no cause
to fense vp the way themselues, against themselues,
with a hedge of their owne thornes. Heauen-gates
will not fall downe before men, as the
iron-gates of the Citie to Peter, of their owne accord.
Nay,Acts. 12. 10. 
                     If the Righteous s
                           •
                        arcely be saued, where
shall the vngodly and the sinner appeare?
                     1. Pet. 4. 18.
                  
                  5. Sinnes are fitly compared to thornes and
bryars, for their wounding, pricking, and such
harmefull offenses. Therefore they are called tribuli,
a tribulando; from their vexing, oppression,
and tribulation they giue those that touch them.
The wicked are such Calthrops to the Countrey,
boring and bloudying her sides. Either pricking
the flesh, or tearing of the fleece; as bryars and
bushes that robbe the sheep of their cotes, which
come to them for shelter. A great man wicked
is like Abimelech, whom Iotham calls a Bramble in
his Parable.Iudg. 9. 8. The Oliue would not leaue his fatnesse,
nor the Figge-tree his sweetnesse, nor the
Vine his goodnesse, to bee promoted ouer the trees.
But the aspiring Bramble vsurpes it: and (as if he
were some great Cedar) he calls the Trees to trust
vnder his shadow. But when poore men come to
this Bramble for refuge, here they loose a locke
and there a locke, til they are left naked, Yea, the
clothes are not onely rent from their backes; but
like the sonnes of Sceua exorcising the euill spirits,
they depart not away naked onely,Acts 19. 16. 
                     but wounded.
Their garments satisfie not these bryars, scarce
their bloud aud liues.
                  
                     
These Bryers and Thornes haue such pricking
and wounding effects, in regard of three obiects,
whom they strike. For sins are like Thorns. 1. To
men. 2. To Christ. 3. To the owne consciences of
the committers. First to men. Plinie mentioneth
three sorts of Bryers.
                     Lib. 21. cap. 16.
                  
                  1. The moorish Bryer, that onely growes in
ranke and fen
                        •
                     e places, &amp; is nourished with rotten
mud, and such squalid putrefaction. There is a
generatiō of men like these bryars, giuen to drunkennesse,
whose affections are fed only with the
moisture of the pot. They cannot liue but in fenny
and moorish places. Pliny saith, that addars &amp;
toads loue and eat the fruits of these bryars; and it
is the food of serpents. The effects of drunkennes
(in like sort) is a condiment for the diuell. Augustine
somewhat neare our purpose, when he compares
drunken places to the fens; where are bred
snakes and serpents, and such vile noxious things,
which euery yeare must be burned. It were a good
turne, if these morish brambles were stocked vp by
the roots. If you ask how you should rid them; I
will not point you to the Fen-men, who to make
quick dispatch of their anoiances, set fire on their
fens: but I wil giue you another precedent. When
a king asked how he might be rid of certain noisome
fowles, which came abundantly flying into
his land; one answered him. Nidos eorum vbi
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         destruendos:
that the only means was to destroy their
nests in euery place. So if you would be shut of
these morish bryers, the course is to destroy their

nests; their haunts, and rendeuous, as they terme
them; the common quagmires of all filthinesse.
The ale houses are their nests &amp; cages, where they
exhaust and lauish out their goods, and lay plots
and deuises how to get more. Hence they fal either
to robbing, or cheating; open courses of violence,
or secret mischiefs: till at last the Iayle prepares
thē for the gibbet. For lightly they sing thorough
a red lattice, before they cry through an irō
grate. And when those bryars are hamperd, &amp; put
into prisons; it is said, that those places teach them
more villanie then they knew before. That when
a lewd fellow comes out of prison, he is furnished
with such a pack of mischiefs, that he now sets vp
schoole, and teacheth others. It is wonderfull,
that places ordained for reformation, should bee
instructions of worse lewdnes. I speak not against
mercy: but experience &amp; truth witnesseth that the
mercy of some times is crueltie. And the pittie to
a notorious malefactor argues vs of a hard heart,
&amp; of vnmercifulnes to the common-wealth. The
sparing of rapes, robberies, whoredomes, cheatings,
frauds, vniust measures, false balances, occasioneth,
yea encourageth the like. If thou be a
Magistrate, deputed to iudge it, and sparest a man
that hath shed bloud; the next bloud he sheddes
thou art guilty of. Thou consentest to the second
robbery of a thief, that hast remitted him the first.
A Father brings in a notorious malefactor arraigning
at the bar before the Iudge. When the mother
coms, miserādavlulatione, with bitter weeping
desiring mercy for her son.
                  
                     
The wife Lachrimabili voce, with mournefull
speech, imploring mercie for her husband. The
little children plorantibus ocellis, with crying eyes,
beseeching mercy for their Father. The people
wishing he may be spared for the goodlinesse of
his person. Yet sayth the Iudge, Non misereor modo:
I pitie, but must not spare. Pereat vnus, potius
quam vnitas. Better one perish, then all.
Weed vp the implacable thornes, for they will
keepe the ground barren. It hath beene sayd,
Beare one iniurie and prouoke more: but here in
case of iustice, forgiue one publick iniury, I mean
a fact of horrid nature as I formerly taxed, and
you prouoke and encourage many. The Marriners
would faine saue Ionas; but when there is no
remedy, they will rather loose one Ionas, then all
themselues.
                  2. Plinies next sort of Bryers are Tribuli agrestes,
Field-bryers; which are (sayth he) shrewd enemies
to tillage, and the fruits of the earth. This
Iland of ours, within these late dayes, hath bred a
great number of these field-bryars: which vnnaturally
turne their mother into barrennesse. Oppressors,
Inclosers, Depopulators, Deportators,
Deprauators; that runne the land to ruine for a
priuate benefite: and work out a particular gaine
from a publicke and generall losse.
                  Gaine said I? Where is it? Did you euer know
Inclosers prosper? I will speake boldly. I neuer
knew great man grow greater by his depopulations:
and I hope no man will say, he hath growne

better by them. Corne-fields are turned to sheepwalkes;
once-inhabited townes feede Oxen;
and Churches are made Shepheards Cottages:
and yet the doers of all this neuer the richer.
They keepe lesse Hospitality; for a few roomes
in London serue their turnes: they extort sorer
rents, and yet they haue neuer the more money.
It cannot bee denyed, but the maine end of these
courses was profite, and euhansing their estates:
and loe, in this very end GOD crosseth-them.
Speake what you will of their pride, of turning
the alms they should giue to the poore into feasts
for the rich, of their infrugall courses: I say confidently,
hic digitus Dei: here is the very hand of
God striking them. Man, though hee hath authority,
will not looke to these Field-bryars; but
let them waste and forrage, and play the Abimelechs;
but God will. But if wee doe not looke to
it, let me say to you, as Iotham to the Shechemites
of that aspiring Bramble, Iudg. 9.Iudg. 9. 20. 
                     If fire come not
out of Shechem to deuoure Abimelech; fire will come
from Abimelech to deuoure Shechem. If you vndoe
not the oppressions of the Field-bryers, their oppressions
will vndoe vs all.
                  3 There is the Town-bryar too, which groweth
in our mounds and fenses, and about the closing
of townes. You in the City haue no great
plenty of these bryers; yet you are troubled (in a
metaphoricall sense) with Towne-bryers, and City-brambles:
which would not a little vexe you,
if you were not those your selues.
                  
                     
1. What say you to the Vsurer? Is hee not a
Thorne amongst you? If you were not Vsurers
your selues, you would confesse it. But they say, the
most horrible vsurie in the world is here practised,
to 40. in the hundred: nay, to doubling of the
principall in one yeare. A landed Gentleman
wants money, he shall haue it; but in commodities:
which some compacted Broker buyes of
him, for halfe the rate they cost him, in ready
money. Are these Christians? dare they shew
their faces in the Temple? But I know, you haue
been often told of these things. In a word, euen
the gentles
                        •
                      vsury is a most sharpe thorne, and
pricks the side of the Countrey till the bloud followes.
An Vsurer with his money, is like a man
that hath no worke of his owne, yet keepes a seruant
to let out: and takes not onely hire of others
for his dayes labour; but chargeth him to steale
somewhat besides, and neuer to returne home
emptie. You vnderstand me: I neede not further
apply it.
                  These are vile winding and wounding bryers,
that fetch away clothes, and skinne, and flesh
too. Now the mercie of God ridde vs of these
thornes. And let vs know it is for our sinnes, that
God suffers Vsurers among vs. It may be he permits
them, as he did the Cananites for a while in
Israel, lest the wilde beasts should break in vpon
them. Lest pride, and haughtinesse, and vncleannesse
should spill mens soules by a full estate of
wealth. God suffers Vsurers like Horse-leeches

to suck and soke them: thereby (possibly) to humble
them. Yet in meane time, I may say of them,
as Iosuah did of those Cananites;Iosh. 23. 13. that they are
pricks in our sides, and thornes in our eyes.
                  
                  2 What doe you thinke of Adulterie? Is it
not a Thorne, yes, a sharpe thorne, wounding the
purse, enuenoming the body, condemning the
Soule. The ground that beares it is lust: the sappe
that feeds it, is fulnesse of bread and Idlenesse: the
heate that makes it glow, grow, and shoote, is
lewd and wanton speech, and effeminate gestures:
infamie is the budde; pollution the fruite; and
the end Hell-fire. And as Caietan and Theophilact
obserues on 1. Thes. 4.Thess. 4. 4. that the Apostle hauing
bid men possesse their vessell in holinesse, he addes;
And let no man goe beyond or defraud his brother in
any matter: that this circumuention may be applied
to Adulterie, when a man is deceiued of his
bosome-spouse; who is hired to the subornation
of bastards. So that lightly, concupiscence and
cousenage goe together. As that wickednesse, of
all others, neuer goes but by couples. For Adulterers
non possunt ire soli ad diabolum.
                     Ierom. An Adulterer
cannot goe alone to the Deuill.
                  3 Corrupt and consciensce-les Lawyers you will
confesse to bee sharpe and wounding brambles,
and exceedingly hurtfull. A poore Client among
them, is as a blind sheepe in a thicket of thornes:
there is no hope of his fleece, it is well if he carry
away his flesh whole on his backe. A motion
this terme, an order next; instantly al cross'd: scarce

the twentith order sometimes stands: execution is
suspended, a writ of errour puts all out of course.
Oh the vncertaine euents of suits! I hope, sayes
the poore bloud-drawne wretch, I shall haue an
end of my suite next terme; nay, nor the next
terme, nor the next yeare. Foole! thou art gotten
into a suite of durance; almost an immortall suit.
And when the vpshot comes, perhaps the mispleading
of a word shall forfet all. It is a lamentable
vncertaintie, and one politicke addition of
ficklenesse to the goods of this world, that no man
might set his heart vpon them: that an estate
bought, truly payd for, and inherited, shall bee
gone vpon a word; sometimes vpon a sillable; vpon
a very bare letter, omitted or mis-written by
the Scriuener. These are scratching bryers. If
what is wanting in the goodnes of the cause, be
supplyed by the greatnes of the fees, their tongs
shall excuse their tongs for their contra-conscient
pleadings. The Italians haue a shrewd prouerbe
against them. The Deuill makes his Christmassepyes
of Lawyers tongs and Clerks fingers.
This prouerbe I leaue with them; and come to
their kinsmen.
                  4 Corrupted Officers, who are also sharpe and
sharking brambles. Their office is a bush of thorns
at their backes, and they all to rent the countrey,
with briberie and extortion. These men seeke after
authority, and commanding-places, not with
any intent of good to the common-wealth, but to
fill their owne purses, to satisfie their owne lusts.

As some loue to bee poring in the fire, not that
they care to mend it, but onely to warme their
owne fingers.
                  5 We haue Papists amongst vs; looke to them,
they are rankling thornes, and renting bryers. False
Gibeonites they are; and howsoeuer they pretend
their old shooes, the antiquitie of their Church, we
haue euer found them thornes; ready to put out
our eyes, and (if they could) the eye of the Gospell.
They exclaime against vs for persecution;
and cry themselues (lowder then oyster-women
in the streets) for patient Catholicks, Saints, Martyrs.
But match the peace they enioy vnder vs,
with the tyrannie they exercised ouer vs; the burning
our Fathers at stakes, the butchering our
Princes, their conspiracie against our whole
Realme, their continuall bending their weapons
against Soueraignes and subiects throtes; and
you will say, they are thornes. I haue read of a bird,
that when men are deuout at their sacrifice, takes
fire from the Altar, and burnes their houses. All
their blacke treasons, and bloudy intendments,
they deriue from the Altar; and pleade the warrant
of Religion, to set our whole Land in combustion.
O that these brambles were stock'd vp:
that Ishmael were cast out of dores, that Sara and
her sonne Isaac might liue in quiet.
                  6 There are furious male contents among vs:
a contemptible generation of thorns; that (because
their hands are pinion'd) pricke onely with their
tongs. They are euer whining, and vpon the

least cause filling the world with importunate
complaints. These are sauage &amp; popular humors,
that cannot suffer eminency to passe vnreproched.
But they must vellicate goodnes, and gird greatnesse;
that neither the liuing can walke, nor the
dead sleepe, in quiet. Affecters of innouation,
that are euer finding fault with the present times:
any thing pleaseth them but what is. Euen the
best blessings of God scape not their cēsures: neither
do they esteem by iudgement, or pronounce
by reason: they find fault with things, they know
not wherefore, but because they do not like them.
Beware these thornes: they are like the wheeles of
some cunningly wrought fire-workes; that flie
out on all sides; and offering to singe others,
burne themselues. Laudant veteres, &amp;c. as if no
times were so miserable as ours. As if the ciuill
wars of France, or the bloudy Inquisitiō of Spain,
or the Turkish crueltie in Natolia, where hee
breeds his souldiers; or at home, the time of the
Barons war; or yet later, the persecution of a Boner;
were none of them so cruell, as these dayes,
when euery man sits and sings vnder his owne
figge-tree. Sure if they had once tasted the bitternesse
of war, they would better esteem of their
peace. These are pestilent thornes: nothing but
feare keeps them from conspiracie. Nay, so they
might set the whole land on fire, they would not
grudge their owne ashes.
                  7. There are bryers too growing neere the
Church; too neare it. They haue raised Church-liuings

to foure and fiue yeares purchase: and it
is to be feared, they will shortly racke vp presentatiue
liuings, to as high a rate, as they did their
impropriations, when they would sell them. For
they say, few will giue aboue sixteene yeares purchase
for an impropriate Parsonage; and I haue
heard some rate the donation of a benefice they
must giue, at ten yeares: what with the present
money they must haue, and with referuation of
tythes, and such vnconscionable trickes; as if
there was no God in heauen, to see or punish it.
Perhaps, some wil not take so much: but most will
take some; enough to impouerish the Church, to
enrich their owne purses, to damne their soules.
                  One would thinke, it was sacriledge enough
to robbe God of his maine tythes: must they also
nimme away the shreddes? must they needes
shrinke the whole cloth, (enough to apparell the
Church) as the cheating Taylor did, to a dozen
of buttons? Hauing full gorged themselues with
the parsonages, must they picke the bones of the
Vicaredges too? Well sayth S. August. Multi in
hac vita manducant, quod postea apud inferos digerunt.
Many deuoure that in this life, which they
shall digest in hell.
                  These are the Church-briers; which (let alone)
wil at last bring as famous a Church, as any Christendome
hath, to beggerie. Politicke men, begin
a pace alreadie to with-hold their children
from Schooles and Vniuersities. Any profession
els better likes them; as knowing, they may liue

well in whatsoeuer calling, saue in the ministery.
The time was, that Christ threw the buyers
and sellers out of the Temple; but now the buyers
and sellers haue throwne him out of the Temple.
Yea, they wil throw the church out of the church
if they bee not stayed. But some may say to me,
as one aduised Luther, when he began to preach
against the Popes vsurpation and tyrannie, You
had as good hold your peace. This wickednesse is so
powerfull, that you will neuer preuaile against it. Get
you to your study, and say, Lord haue mercy on vs, and
procure your selfe no ill will. But be it good will, or
be it ill will, we come hither to speake the truth in
our consciences. And if these Church-thornes will
continue their wickednesse, bee it vnto them as
they haue deserued. If they will needs go to hell,
let them go: we cannot helpe it, let them perish.
I had purposed the discouery of more Brambles,
but the time forbids it. I would to God, we
were well freed from those I
haue taxed.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  THE END
Of
Thornes. THE
FIFT SERMON.
                  
                     ESA. 9. 18.
                     Wickednesse burneth as the fire: it shall deuoure the Bryers
and Thornes, and shall kindle in the thickets of the Forrest,
and they shal mount vp like the lifting vp of smoke.
                  
                  
                     GREG. lib. 4. Dialog.
                     Ad magnam iudicantis iustitiam pertinet, vt nunquam
mortui careant supplicio, qui nunquam viui voluerunt
carere peccato.
                  
                  LONDON,
Printed by George Purslowe, for Iohn Budge, and are to be
solde at his shop, at the great South-dore of Pauls,
and at Brittaines Burse. 1616.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                  THE END
Of
THORNES.
                  THE
FIFT SERMON.
                  
                     HEB. Chap. 6. Vers. 8.
                     But that which beareth thornes and bryers, is reiected, and
is nigh vnto cursing, whose end is to be burned.
                  
                  
                     OVr sinnes are thornes to others;
some wounding with their direct
blowes, others with their wipes,
all with their examples. Man only
hath not felt their blowes; our
Sauior also so found them: when
hee was faine for our sakes to set his naked breast,
his naked heart, his naked soule against them.
They say, the Nightingale sleepes with her breast

against a thorne, to auoide the Serpent. Christ
was content to bee wounded, euen to sleepe to
death with thornes, that hee might deliuer vs
from that deuouring serpent, the great infernall
Dragon. His head was not onely raked and
harrowed with materiall thornes:
                     Bern. 
                     Caput Angelicis
spiritibus tremebundum coronatur spinis That
head which the Angelical spirits adore and tremble
at, was crowned with thornes. But these mys
                        •
                     call
thornes, our iniquities, with fiercer blowes
drew bloud of his soule. They doe in a sort still.
Heb. 6. 6.Heb. 6. 6. 
                     They crucifie to themselues the Sonne of
God a fresh, and put him to an open shame. Not in
himselfe, for they cannot: but can them no
thankes; they would, if they could: and to themselues
they doe it. Wretched men, will you not
yet let Iesus Christ alone, and be at rest? will you
still offer violence to your blessed Sauiour; and
labour to pull him downe from his throne to
his Crosse; from his peaceful glorie at the right
hand of his Father, to more sufferings? You condemne
the mercilesse Souldiers, that platted a
crowne of thornes,
                     Mat. 27. 29. and put it on his innocent head.
Sinfull wretch, condemne thy selfe. Thy sinnes
were those thornes, and farre sharper. Thy oppressions,
wrongings, and wringings, of his poore
brethren, offer him the violence of new wounds:
thy oathes, thy fraudes, thy pride scratch him
like bryers. Heare him complaining from heauen,
Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou mee? These
Thornes grow on earth, yet they pricke Iesus Christ
                     
in heauen. Oh wee little know the price of a sin,
that thus play the executioners with the Lord of
life. Thinke, thinke; Christ felt your sinnes as
sharpe thornes.
                  
                  Lastly, you finde them thornes your selues, if
Christ did not for you. When God shall enliuen
and make quicke the sense of your nummed
consciences, you shall confesse your owne sinnes

                        •
                     ruell thornes to your soules, 2. Cor. 12.2. Cor. 12. 7. 
                     A thorne
in your flesh, that shall buffet you with terror. For
a while men are insensible of their iniquities.
Christ, Math. 13. 22.Mat. 13. 22. calls the riches of this world
thornes, which choke the good seede of the Gospell.
                  The common opinion of the world is, that
they are goodly, fine and smooth things; furres
to keepe them warme, oyle to cheare their faces,
and wine to their hearts; of a silken softnesse to
their affections. But Christ saith, they are thorns;
stinging and choking thornes. And the couetous
conscience shall one day perceiue in them, Triplicem
puncturam,
                     Ludolph. a threefold pricking. Laboris
in acquisitione; they are gotten with trouble. Timoris
in possessione; they are kept vvith feare.
Doloris in amissione; they are lost with griefe.
                  Men commonly deale with their sinnes, as
hedgers do, when they go to plash thorny bushes:
they put on tyning gloues, that the Thornes may
not pricke them. So these harden their hearts,
that their owne thornes may giue them no compunction.
But all vanities are but like the fooles

laughter,
                     Eccl. 7. 6. which Salomon compares to the crackling
of thornes vnder a p
                           •
                        t: they make a noise, and suddenly
go out. But sinne neuer parts with the wicked,
without leauing a sting behind it.In. Galat. cap. 1. ver. 3. 
                     Luther saith,
there are two fiends, that torment men in this
world: and they are sinne, and a bad conscience.
The latter followes the former: or if you will, the
former wounds the latter: for sinne is the thorne,
and the conscience the subiect it strikes. This
thorne often pricks deepe; to the very heart. Acts 2.
to the very bones, Psal. 38.Psal. 38. 3. 
                     There is no rest in my
bones because of my sinne.
                     I sid. lib. 2. Soliloquiorum. mens enim malae conscientiae proprijs agitatur stimulis. 
                     Vis nunquam esse tristis?
bene viue. Nunquam securus est reus animus.
Wouldest thou neuer be sorrowfull? liue well.
A guilty mind cannot be securely quiet. An euill
mind is haunted and vexed with the thornes of his
owne conscience. Sinne to the affections, whiles it
is doing, is oleum vngens, supple oyle. Sinne to
the conscience when it is done, is tribulus pungens,
a pricking thorne. What extreame contraries
doe often wicked conceits runne into? In their
time of securitie they cannot be brought, to think
sinne to be sinne. At last desperately, they thinke
it such a sinne, that it cannot be forgiuen. At first
they are delighted with the sense and smel of their
iniquitie, as of a sweet rose: but the rose of their
delight withers, and there is a thorne vnder it, that
pricks the hart. Hereupon Salomon couples pleasāt
vanitie, and troublesome vexation together. If that
tickles the flesh, this shall wound the spirit. You
shall heare an Vsurer in the madnes of presumption

expostulating, what? may I not make benefit
of my money? Obserue him, and in the end
you shall heare him in the madnes of despaire, cry
out of his owne damnation for it. At first
they make question whether it be a sinne: at last
they know it such a sinne, that they make question
whether God will forgiue it. So men will looke to
sin either too superficially, or too superstitiously.
There was no danger saith the Drunkard, when
he is asked how he seap'd such a passage: bring
him backe in the sober moming to see, and hee
falls downe dead in astonishment.
                  I need not further amplifie this point. Christ
giues a vae ridentibus; Woe to them that laugh, for
they shall weepe: and euery smile of sinne shall be
turned to a grone of sorrow. They that exhibite
their liues as sacrifices risuiet lubentiae; shall one
day feele pricks, and goads, and thornes; scratching
and peircing their hearts: when (like the
strucken deare, with the arrowhead rankling in his
side) they shall not bee able to shift or change
paines with places. Let this reach to our soules
two instructions.
                  1 That we labour our hearts betimes to a sensiblenesse
of these thornes. A Thorne swallowed
into the flesh, if it be not look'd to, rankles. Sinne
without repentance, will fester in the soule; and is
so much more perilous, as it is lesse felt. Oh the
number of thornes that lie in many conscience,
who complaine no more, then if they ayld nothing.

The pricke of a thorne is not so painefull
at first, while the bloud is hote, as after a cold
pause. Euerie man hath his complaints; &amp; who
liueth out of the reach of discontent? You shall
heare tradesmen complaining of few or false
customers. Labourers, of little worke, and lesse
wages. Beggars complaine the want of Charity:
and rich men the want of money. Merchants of
rockes and Pyrats: Lawyers of short fees; and
Clyents of long suits. But no man complaines
of the thornes in his owne bosome. He nourisheth
bryers there that wound him: and the heart is as
dedolent,Ephe. 4. 19. as if it were past feeling. But where there
is no discouerie of the disease, the recouery of the
health is in vaine hoped for.
                  2 After sense of the smart will follow a desire
of remedy. The throbbing conscience would
be at ease, and freed from the Thorne that vexeth
it. Dauid rores out for the very disquietnesse of his
heart. The aking heart will make a crying tong,
and wet eyes. Loe the mercie of GOD! A
remedy is not sooner desired, then offred. The
sacred Gospell directs vs to a medicine, that shall
supple the heart, and draw out these thornes;
though they stucke as thicke in it, as euer the arrowes
did in Sebastian. They speake of the herbe
Dictamnum, call'd of some Ditanie, that it hath a
secret vertue to draw out any thing fastened in the
body.Lib. 26. cap. 14. 
                     Plinie sayth, that this herbe drunke, Sagittas
pellit. Experience telleth, that it is soueraigne

to exhale a thorne out of the flesh. Our onely
Dictamnum is the precious bloud of our merciful
Sauiour IESVS CHRIST. A plaister of that is
truely vertuall, to draw out all thornes from our
consciences, Saucia 
                           •
                        nimis, which is nulla medicabilis
herbis, is thus cured. Our sinnes drew bloud
of him; that his bloud might saue vs. He was
crowned with Thornes, that we might not be killed
with thornes. He was wounded for vs, that
we might not perish for our selues.
                  Take we heed, that we despise not this medicine.
The law was so farre from drawing out
these thornes, that it would driue them in further,
and cause them to rankle in the heart, without any
hope of ease. It did but exasperate their
stings, and giue them a deeper continuance of
pricking. The mollifying and healing Gospell
extracts their venome, and sucks out their poyson.
Let vs not dare then to vilipend this cordiall
and soueraigne medicine.
                  You perceiue that our sinnes are Thornes; and
what is their onely remedy. Know now, that if
they be not drawne out in this world, they shall
be found thornes hereafter; when the owners
shall heare Christs sentence, Goe yee cursed, &amp;c.
for the end of them is to be burned. So I come to
the punishment: but I will soone haue done with
that, which shall neuer haue done with those
that must vndergoe it.
                  There is a threefold gradation in the Penalty,
Reiection, malediction, combustion. Is reiected, is

nigh vnto cursing, and the end thereof is to be burned.
And it seems to haue relation to a threefold
distinction of time. 1. For the present, it is reiected.
2. For instance or appropinquation, it is
nigh vnto cursing. 3. For future certainty, the
end of it is to be burned. As men commonly
deale with thornes: first they cut them vp with
bils and mattocks: then they lay them by to wither:
and lastly burne them in the furnace.
                  1 Reiection. This which we here translate (is
reiected) is in the originall (
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     ) which
may signifie Reprobios, or reprobatus: so Beza
hath it; is reproued, or disallowed of God. This
ground shall haue no ground in heauen, no part
in God inheritance. It is reprobate siluer, not
current with the Lord. No man desires to purchase
Land, that will bring forth nothing but
weedes: he will not cast away his siluer vpon it.
And shall GOD buy so base ground, that will
be no better, at so inestimable a price, as the incorruptible
bloud of his owne Sonne? It despiseth
the Lords goodnesse, and the LORDS
goodnesse shall despise it. It is reiected. If any
man sayth, this is Durus Sermo, let him consider
of whom the Apostle speaketh, verse. 4. against
whom hee concludes ab impossibili. It is impossible,
&amp;c.
A hard saying to vnderstand, but more,
most heard to vndergoe. If God be driuen to
loose all his paines and cost vpon an ingratefull
heart, he will at last renounce it, and giue it ouer

a desperate nature. As he in the Comedy, Abeat,
pereat, profundat, perdat. If it will be filthy, let it
be filthy still. If nothing will bring it to goodnesse,
it shall be reiected.
                  
                  2. The second degree of the Punishment is
cursing: and this may seeme to exceed the former.
Gods curse is a fearefull thing. If you
would view (though but in part) the latitude
and extension of it, I refer you to the 28. of Deuteronomy.
But I purpose not to bee curiously
punctuall, in the demonstration of these particular
degrees of the Punishment. That which I wil
obserue, is this.
                  That God is more propense and inclined to
blessing, then to cursing: more prone to shewe
mercy, then to inflict iudgement. It is sayd in
the former Verse, the good ground receiues blessing
of God: receiues it presently, receiues it at once.
But here of the euill ground; it is nigh vnto cursing:
it is not presently cursed, but nigh vnto it.
There is some pawse and delay: some lucida
interualla misericordiae. The whole viall of wrath
is not poured on at once. But first there is a despising
or reiection; to let the wicked see, how
hatefull their vices are in Gods sight. If this
serue not, they are not sodainely cursed; but
there is a breathing time, and a mercifull space
betweene that and cursing; and betweene cursing
and burning. So slowly doth GOD proceed
to iudgement, so little haste he makes to the execution

of his vengeance. Hee is speedy to deliuer,
to saue, to giue his blessing; but hee hath
leaden feet when he comes to strike.
                  The vse of this to our selues is, that the patient
forbearance of God may leade vs to repentance,
Romans the second and the fourth.Rom. 2. 4. The
Prophet Ioel bids vs Rent our hearts,
                     Ioel. 2. 13. and fall to
weeping and mourning; Because the Lord is
mercifull and slow to anger. Gods long-suffering
is as a hand reached out, that points vs to repentance.
Such is his goodnesse, that when all
his terrors and menace; are set in their places,
yet hee makes roome for Repentance, whensoeuer
it comes. And though they bee as ready to
strike, as Abrahams hand was to Isaacs sacrifice;
yet Repentance, tanquam vox Angeli, shall stay
them. O blessed Repentance, how sweet and amiable
art thou! yet how few loue thee!
                  The great man, that thinkes he may securely
be wicked, because he is honourably great; and
dares affront the Pulpit, though the greatest Bishop
in the land were preaching in it; cares not
for repentance. The wealthy Gentleman, that
can bung vp Hospitality into a Diogenes tubbe;
nestle himselfe warme in a City-chamber, whiles
Owles and Dawes parlour themselues in his
countrey-manors: that (as it is storied of that
Iew for the vse of his money) takes his rent in
bloud; the heart-bloud of his racked Tenants;
cares not for Repentance.
                  
                  The countrey Nabal, that hoords his graine,

and with it lockes vp his soule in a Garner, that
the Sunne of Gods blessing may not come at
it: that starues the poore, his family, himselfe;
cares not for Repentance. The auarous Citizens,
whom the glad Diuell can neuer find without
a false measure in one hand, and a cozening
waight in the other; that haue trickes in their
sconces to ouer-reach the diuell himselfe; but
that (like a cunning Fenser) he that taught them
all their trickes, kept one to himselfe, to cheate
them of their soules; care not for repentance. The
muffled Lawyer, that hath no sense left aliue but
his feeling, and waighs all causes by the poyse
of gold; that talkes against others right and his
owne conscience; that leades Iurie into pe
                        •
                     iury,
with his fraudulent circumuentions; cares not
for repentance.
                  
                  The sharking Officer,Zosun. lib. 2. (that like Menelaus,
an Armenian Archer in the wars betwixt Constantius
and Magnentius) can shoot three arrowes
at once, at one loose; wherewith hee
wounds not one, but three at the least: the
Prince whom hee serues, the person whom hee
drawes bloud of, and the body of the Common-wealth;
cares not for repentance. I neede
not speake of the Church-robber, the Vsurer,
the Drunkard, the Proud, the vncleane adulterer:
no man can think, that they care for repentance.
O but they all purpose to repent. Spare
them a while; they are but new set into the Ouen;
not yet fully baked in their hot vanities:

let them foke a little in their pleasures, and at last
they will returne.Hos. 7. 4. 
                     They are as an Ouen heated by
the Baker. Repentance is an ascent of foure steps:
many get vp three of them, but climbe not to
the fourth and best.
                  1. Some there are that purpose to amend
their liues. But purpose without performance is
like a Cloud without raine; not vnlike Hercules
Clubbe in the Tragedy, of a great bulke, but the
stuffing is mosse and rubbish. If the tree bee
fairely blossom'd, and naked of fruite, it may
speed as the Figge-tree in the Gospell. be curseo:
or at least (it is as the euill ground here) nigh
vnto cursing. Many that purposed to repent, are
now in hell, as the fiue foolish Virgins, that intended
to goe in with the Bridegroome; but before
the time their lights dropp'd out.
                  One sayd, that hell is like to bee full of good
purposes, but heauen of good workes. If a bare
Intention would serue, Gods Church on earth
would bee fuller of Saints, and his Court in heauen
fuller of soules. Ignorance and Sloth adulterating,
bring forth this lanke brood, this abortiue
embrion, Purpose. Such a man is like an ill
debtor, who will not pay God his due of deuotion
till hee is old: and then hee cannot pay for
want of (time &amp; mony) space and grace to repent.
We make (in these daies) our purposes like our
Eeues, and our performances like the holy-daies:
seruants work hard vpō the Eeues, that they may

haue the more liberty to play vpon the Holydayes:
so we are earnest, and labour hard on our
purposes; but are idle and play vpon our performances.
But Resolution without action, is a golden
couch to a leaden Iewell.
                  2. The second round of this Ladder is
Preparation. Some there are that will prepare,
&amp; almost set themselues in a readinesse for their
iourney to heauen; yet neuer set one steppe forward.
Preparation is indeed as necessary, as the
dore is to the house: but as idle, if there be no
house to the dore. It may (as Iohn the Baptist
did for Christ) prepare the way of the Lord into
our hearts: and it may be as vaite, as the Apothecaries
Beast,
                     Testia Pharmacopolae. which hee promised his Patient
would helpe him of all diseases; but before morning
it had eaten vp it selfe. Preparation is a necessary
antecedent to all great workes, Amos 4.Am. 4. 12.
                     Prepare to meet thy God, O Israel. But a man may
prepare meate, and not feede: prepare meate,
and not eate. Prepaeration does well, if reparation
followes. A man may climbe both these
rounds, and yet fall short of the true height of
Repentance.
                  
                  3. The third stairre is a Beginning to abstaine
from some horrid iniquities; and as it were, an
entring into a new path; but not going one step
in it, without a voluntary reuolting. But Beginning
is nothing to perfection. Some begin in

the spirit, and end in the flesh: that s
                           •
                        lute Christ
in the market place; take acquaintance of him
in the street, but neuer bid him home to their
houses. It is (vox praetereuntium derisoria) the
speech of them that passe by. This man began
to build. A house but begun is not fit to dwell in:
and shall wee thinke that Gods Spirit will dwell
in an inchoate habitacle, and not likely to be finished?
The Apostle sayth,2. Pet. 2. 21. 
                     It had been better
for them not to haue knowne the way of righteousness,
then after they haue knowne it, to turne from the holy
commandement deliuered vnto them.
                  
                  4 The fourth Round onely pleaseth God, and
is good for our Soules, Repentance; without
which the euill ground is neere to cursing; as it
were at next dore by; and it shall come on him
with a speedy visitation nisi interueniente poenitentia.
This is the Bulwarke to defend vs from the
shot of Gods thunder from heauen: this hedgeth
vs in from his iudgements on earth. Woe
to sinfull man without this: for he is neere to cursing;
and his end is to be burned. Blessed Soule
that hath it. Wheresoeuer it dwels, mercie
dwels by it. If England hath it, it shall ease her
of her thornes, Ezek. 28.Ezek. 20. 14. 
                     There shall be no more
a pricking bryar vnto the house of Israel, nor any
grieuing Thorne of all that are round about them.
                  
                  3 The last and forest degree of the Punishment,
is Burning. I will not discourse, whether

the fire of that euerlastingly-hote furnace be materiall
or spirituall. Surely, it is strangely terrible;
and wee are blessed, if wee neither vnderstand
it nor vndergoe it. The miserie of the damned
is vsually distinguished into the Paine of losse,
and the paine of sense. Both implied in this verse,
and expressed, Thessalonians the second, Chap. 1.
Verse 8, 9.2. The. 1. 8. 9. Christ shall take vengeance on such as
know not God, and obey not the Gospell of Iesus Christ,
there is paine of Sense. They shall be punished with
euerlasting destruction from the presence of the Lord,
and from the glory of his power, there is paine of
losse.
                  
                  1. This Poena damni, or priuation of blessednesse,
may seeme to be implyed in the first
degree here mentioned, Reiection. The reprobate
are cast away of God. Much like that forme
of the last sentence, Math. 25. 41.Mat. 25. 41. 
                     Depart from
me, yee cursed: a fearefull sentence, a terrible separation.
From Me, sayth Christ; that made my
selfe man for your sakes, that offered my bloud
for your redemption, &amp; receiued these &amp; these
wounds for your remedie. From Me, that would
haue healed, would haue helped, would haue saued
you. From Me, that inuited you to mercy,
and you would not accept it. From Me, that purchased
a kindgome of glory, for such as beleeued
on me; and will wrappe their heads with
crownes of eternall ioy: Depart from Me. This
is a fearefull Reiection, My friendship, my fellowship,

my Paradise, my presence, my heauen,
where is fulnesse of ioy, and pleasure for euermore,
                     Psal. 16. vlt. are
none of yours. They might haue been; they are
lost. Neither shall they onely loose Christ, but
all the companie with Christ: the Quire of glorious
Angels, the society of his blessed Mother,
the Prophets, Apostles, Martyrs, all the happy
and holy Saints, with the whole host of heauen.
They shall fret, and vexe, and bee ready to eate
their owne galls, to see those triumphing in glory,
whom they on earth persecuted, martyred,
tortured. They could here exercise their sauage
tyranny ouer them; not onely denying their
owne bread, but taking away theirs: they could
despise, beate, maligne, vndoe, burne them at
stakes: now the estate of both is changed: as Abraham
told Diues. They are comforted,
                     Luke 16. 25. 
                     and thou
art tormented.
                  
                  2. This is not all. The priuation of blessed
ioyes is not enough: there must follow the position
of cursed torments. For their Punishment is
proportioned to their sinne, Ier. 2.Ier. 2. 13. 
                     They haue
committed two euils. They haue forsaken the Lord,
the fountaine of liuing waters, and hewed them out
cisternes, broken cisternes that can hold no water.
As they turned from their Maker, so their Maker
turnes from them: there is Poenadamni. As
they fastned their delights on the creatures, so
the creatures shall be their tortures: there is Poena
sensus. They reiected God, and hee reiects
                     
them; they adhered to wickednesse, and it shall
adhere to their bones for euer, and bring them
to burning.
                  
                  Their torments which are here expressed by
Fire, haue two fearefull conditions, vniuersality,
and eternitie.
                  1. They are vniuersall, vexing euery part of
the body, and power of the soule. It is terrible
in this life, to be pained in euery part of the body
at one time. To haue ache in the teeth, gowt in
the feete, collick in the reines, &amp;c. and to lye (as
it were) vpon a racke, for innumerable diseases,
like so many executioners, to torture him, is intollerable.
But the largest shadowe of these torments
to their substance, is not so much as a little
bone-fire to the combustion of the whole
world.
                  2. They are eternall. If it had but as many
ages to burne, as there be trees standing on the
earth, there would bee some, though a tedious
hope of their end. But it is such a Fire, as shall
neuer be quenched. This word Neuer is fearefull.
Though they raine floudes of teares vpon
it, they shall bee but like oyle to encrease the
flame: for the worme neuer dyes, the fire neuer
goes out. You see the end of Thornes. Wickednes
burneth as the fire:
                     Esa. 9. 18. 
                     it shall deuoure the bryers and
thornes, and shall kindle in the thickest of the Forrest,
and they shall mount vp like the lifting vp of
sm
                           •
                        k
                           •
                        .
                  
                  
                     
I resolued against prolixity. The generall
and summary doctrine is this. That since the
wicked ground, which beareth thornes and bryers,
is neere vnto cursing, and the end thereof is eternall
fire: it followes necessarily, that all they
which lay the foundation of vngodlinesse, must
needs build vpon condemnation. Let no man deceiue
you:
                     I. Ioh. 3. 8. 
                     He that committeth sinne is of the Diuell.
If the course of a mans life be wicked, couetous,
vncleane, malicious, idolatrous, adulterous, drunken;
hee layes the ground-worke of his owne
destruction; and precipitates himselfe to the
malediction of God. Hee that layes the foundation
in fire-work, must looke to be blowne vp.
Perhaps this meditation, though it bee of vnquenchable
Fire, may yet worke coldly in our
hearts; and leaue no impression behinde it; yet
you cannot deny this to be true. He that would
denie it must deny my Text, must turne Atheist,
and reiect the holy word of God. Nay, he must
thinke there is no God, no reuenge of wickednesse,
no diuell, no hell. And he vndertakes a
very hard taske, that goes about to settle this
perswasion in his mind. No, no. Let no man deceiue
you with vaine words:
                     Eph. 5. 6. 
                     for because of these
things cometh the wrath of God vpon the children
of disobedience. And in this passage I must value
all men alike: of what stuffe, or of what fashion
soeuer his coate be: if his life be full of bryers
and thornes, his end is to be burned. What shall
we then doe vnto thee, O thou preseruer of men, that

wee may escape it? what,Mark. 1. 15. but Repent, and beleeue
the Gospell!
                  
                  Let the commination of hell instruct vs to
preuent it: as the message of Niniuehs ouerthrow
effected their safetie. 1. Let vs flie by a
true faith into the armes of our Redeemer, that
God reiect vs not. 2. Let vs poure forth flouds
of repentant teares, that wee bee not nigh vnto
cursing. 3. And let vs bring forth no more bryars
and thornes, that our end may not be, to bee
burned. Faith, Repentance, Obedience; this
same golden rule of three, will teach vs to worke
vp our owne saluation. This done, wee shall not
be reiected, but knowne to bee elected: we shall
be so farre from cursing. that we shal presently receiue
the blessing. And our End shall be, not fire,
but glorie and peace.Psal. 37. 37. 
                     Marke the perfect
man, and behold the vpright: for
the end of that man is
PEACE.
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

