
   
      
         
            The nine English worthies: or, Famous and worthy princes of England being all of one name; beginning with King Henrie the first, and concluding with Prince Henry, eldest sonne to our Soueraigne Lord the King.
            Fletcher, Robert, purveyor of carriages to Queen Elizabeth.
         
         
            
               1606
            
         
         Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00982
            STC 11087
            ESTC S118024
            99853233
            99853233
            18602
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00982)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18602)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 837:01)
         
         
            
               
                  The nine English worthies: or, Famous and worthy princes of England being all of one name; beginning with King Henrie the first, and concluding with Prince Henry, eldest sonne to our Soueraigne Lord the King.
                  Fletcher, Robert, purveyor of carriages to Queen Elizabeth.
               
               [20], 52 p. : ill.  
               
                  Imprinted by H. L[ownes] for Iohn Harrison the yonger: and are to be sold at his shop in Pater-noster rowe, at the signe of the blue Anchor,
                  At London :
                  1606.
               
               
                  Partly in verse.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Jason ColmanSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Jason ColmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
THE NINE ENGLISH WORTHIES: Or, Famous and Worthy Princes of England, being all of one name; Beginning with King HENRIE the first, and Concluding with Prince HENRY, eldeſt Sonne to our Soueraigne Lord the King.
            
            AT LONDON Imprinted by H. L. for John Harriſon the yonger: and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pater-noſter, rowe, at the ſigne of the blue Anchor.
            1606.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE HENRY, Eldeſt Sonne to our Souereigne, the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie.
            
               RIght High, Right Excellent, and gracious ſweete Prince, (in all humilitie) I beſeech your Highneſſe to pardon me, in that (being one of the meaneſt among the King your Fathers ſeruants) I haue preſumed to Dedicate this ſimple ſmall Treatiſe to your Excellencie: the Subiect whereof is notwithſtanding ſuch and ſo great, as may ſeeme vnmeete to bee tearmed a Subiect. For, it treateth onely of Kings and Princes; all excellent Worthies: a matter (I confeſſe) much vnbefitting my ſlender capacity, and leſſe learning, to deale with. In which regard, I cannot but acknowledge, the true Prouerbe moſt fitte to bee applied

againſt me, Blinde Bayard is the boldest horſe in the Cart. Notwithſtanding, that, which hath ſpurred me forward to commit the fault, may (I hope) in ſome meaſure, qualifie and excuſe it; to weet, my ſeruent loue and zealous heart: which cānot endure, your Grace ſhould paſſe by me, without ſome little teſtimony of my great ioy, zeale, and bounden duety: howſoeuer, in the maner of expreſſing it, my diſcretion may perhaps be worthily taxed, and my inſufficiencie layed open to the world. But to proceede on: The Worthies, here recorded, are nine in number; all Henries, al mighty Potentates: eight of which haue already been Souereigne Kings of this renowmed Nation; ſeuen of them excelling in Martiall valour and conqueſt, one of them (namely, King Henry the ſixt) in vertue and pietie, (the conqueſt of ſinne and himſelfe) and none of them much inferiour to ſome of the ancient nine Worthies. Now, your Highneſſe being of the ſame name with them, and Heire apparant to the ſame Dominions, which thoſe eight Worthies (your glorious Anceſtors) ſometime held, and the bleſſed ſonne of a mighty Monarch; the eye of the World is

vpon you, and lookes for a tranſparent paſſage of their vertues into you, and a reflexion from you: the ioy and comfort of this famous Realme of Great Britaine (aſwell in Church as Common wealth) is ſet and ſettled in and vpon you, next to our King and preſent ſauing Gouernour. And their hopefull expectation hath already inſtalled you the ninth Worthy; as being likely (in time) I ſay not, to equall the eight, but euen to ſurmount and exceed them. For, as the ages, ſince theirs, haue been illuſtrated with more learning, Religion, and diuine wiſedom: ſo, beſides your gifts of Nature (who, in perfections, hath not been niggardly towards you) your Highneſſe taking alſo your princely and happie education in a time of peace, and that vnder the wings and eyes of the moſt learned King your father, vertuous Queene mother, and ſuch a Councel of ſettled and deep wiſedom, as not the like in Europe; your Highneſſe, I ſay, hath (herein) meanes, examples, and leaſure to heare, learne, behold, and obſerue the ſingular goodneſſe of God, in that, which hereafter ſhall be your owne greatneſſe and happineſſe. And here I may not forget your

chiefeſt honour, nobilitie, and worthineſſe; that you are deſcended of the eldeſt and higheſt houſe, of the blood royall of Heauen, the child and ſonne of God, and conſequently coheire with Chriſt (our great Lord) to the immortall Crowne. Now, the ſame God, your heauenly Father, who hitherto (in rich mercie) hath ſhowred downe abundantly his graces vpon you, vouchſafe to continue and increaſe them in you; guiding al your princely affections and actions, to the glorie of his name, the benefit of the Church, the good of this whole Monarchie, the vnſpeakeable ioy of your royall Parents; and bleſſe both them and you, as with much health, long life, and glory here, ſo with eternall happineſſe hereafter. July the 4.
            
               Your GRACES moſt humbly deuoted,
ROBERT FLETCHER.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE RIGHT HOnorable, my very good Lords, the Earles of Oxenford, and Eſſex, with my Lord Vicount Cranborne, and the other yong Lords, Knights and Gentlemen attending the Princes Highneſſe; health, honour, and happineſſe.
            
               NObles and Gentlemen: Pleaſe yee to peruſe the Chronicles of this Realme, you may therein reade of many your famous and worthy Progenitors, who (ſome of them by Valour; the reſt, by Wiſedome and their other vertues) haue growen great in Souereignes fauour, been preferred to high Place in Common wealth, liued and died in much glorie; leauing an ouer-plus of honour and dignitie (by many deſcents) to you their children. The conſideration hereof may, and (I doubt not) wil, incite and egge you on (who are already well entred the way) to tread the ſame ſteps of honour, by imitating thoſe your worthy Anceſtors in their vertuous actions. For, your tender yeeres are

not ignorant, that The readieſt way to get (and ſureſt to hold) true honour, is to deſerue it; and (conſequently) that Vertue onely, which firſt began Nobilitie, must ſtill maintaine it: whereas, contrariwiſe, by degenerate and baſe conditions, many forfeit their Nability, ere they come at it. For, who knowes not, that Nobilitie, without Ʋertue, is but apocryphate Gentry? and that, therefore, as it began in vertuous Anceſtors; ſo it endeth in their wicked progenie. We ſee, The ſtrongeſt wine becomes the ſharpeſt vineger: and, The moſt Noble, by nature, are made moſt vile by negligence. Of which Ranke and ſort, are chiefly ſuch as hold learning in ſcorne, and the attaining of knowledge not worth the while. In reproofe of whom, truely and eloquently was it (long ſince) written by M. Aſcham; The fault is in your ſelues, ye Noble-mens ſonnes (and therefore ye deſerue the greater blame) that commonly the meaner mens children come to be the wiſeſt Counſailors, &amp; greateſt dooers in the weighty affaires of this Realme: and why? For, God will haue it ſo by his prouidence; becauſe yee will haue it no otherwiſe by your negligence. And againe, It grieueth me to ſay (but it helpeth not to hide) what euery

man ſees; Tis ſeldome ſeene, that the ſonne of an excellent man prooues excellent. I graunt, that in excellent men, Nature muſt frame the chiefest parts: but learning addeth a further ornament, groundeth a deeper iudgement, and formeth perfection, and excellencie, in ſhorter time. The beſt learned are beſt aduiſed. And, No man is deceiued, but in thoſe things whereof he is ignorant. In a word: What ſoeuer may bee ſaydin dispraiſe of Ignorance, is the praiſe of Learning and Knowledge. Wherefore, I trust, your Honours, and the reſt, wil thinke it as great ſhame (which alſo are M. Aſchams words) to be valiant and Courtly without Learning, as to be ſtudious and bookiſh without Valour. My ſeruent prayers, to almighty God, ſhall be ſo to direct your generous hearts to the ſtudie of good literature, with the loue of vertue and true valour, that you alwayes (not onely in time of this your tender youth) may be found meete Gentlemen to attend ſo worthy a Prince. Remember, I beſeech you, the Poeſies borne in ſome of your honourable Enſignes; Vero nihil verius. Virtutis comes Inuidia. Serò, ſed ſeriò: And neuer forget the most worthy ſaying of that thrice honourable late Senatour; Corvnum, via

vna. Theſe Mottoes, well imprinted in youth, will bring honour to olde age. Which the God of heauen and earth make you all partakers of in the preſent, and poſseſſors in the future; and the ſame, after many yeeres, to be permanent in the heauens, for euer.
            
               Your Honours in all humility, euer to be commanded,
ROBERT FLETCHER.
            
         
         
            
            To his friend M. Ro. Fletcher, vpon his Subiect of the nine Worthies.
            
            
               WHo dreads the fume of euery froathy ſpirit,
               And begs th'applauſe of ech fantaſtick braine,
               Frighting with cauſeleſſe feares induſtrious merit,
               Too much deiects exalted Poeſies ſtraine.
               Let blind diſtruſt inſinuate approbation:
               A princely Subiect ſcornes baſe deprecation.
               
                  Vino vendibili, non opus eſt ſuspenſa bedera.
               
               
                  φιλαρετὴ, R. Fenne.
               
            
         
         
            
            
               Thomas, Lord Windſor, his humble congratulation of the ninth Worthy.
            
               WHo-euer ſhall a vertuous mind imbrace,
               Preſent renowne, and glory ſhall him grace
               Long after life: as in theſe Worthies nine
               It doth appeare. For they long ſince are dead;
               Their Vertues liue, in Chronicles they ſhine,
               Their Corps conſum'd to duſt: yea euen the Lead,
               That cloſ'd their earthly bodies in the graue,
               Can not be ſeene; no ſigne thereof we haue.
               Their names, nor fames, their deeds will neuer die:
               Their Acts (their Monuments) their worthy praiſe;
               Theſe regiſtred, doe liue perpetually:
               There is no end or period of their dayes.
               Liue ſo, Great Britaines Prince, as they haue donne,
               Ninth Worthy, hopeful HENRY, great Kings Sonne.
            
         
         
            
            Sir William Whorewood, Knight, in honour of the ninth Worthy.
            
               WHen Siluius Poſt-humus did ſeeke this ſoile,
               And therin thought to raigne, to rule, to reſt,
               Trauailes he found, and ſtormes, with bitter broile:
               But little ſpace in quiet he poſſeſt.
               Since when, what alterations, and what change,
               By Conqueſt, and by Tyrants bloody hand,
               To write at large, it would be true; but ſtrange
               To count the troubles of now happy land.
               Yet, by eight HENRIES, ſettled in it ſelfe;
               Laſtly, vnited to one Kingdome more,
               What needeth it to care for Indian pelſe?
               Gold, Plate, and Pearle it now poſſeſſeth ſtore;
               And, more then all, a King, a Queene, a Plant,
               A Royall Iſſue, Parents chiefeſt ioy,
               A Captaine that in time will thoſe ſupplant
               That dare attempt Great Britains leaſt annoy.
               Ninth Worthy, worthieſt next our Soueraigne be.
               God grant, long Raigne of both may Britaine ſee.
            
         
         
            
            
               Iohn Widevp (the elder) Gent. vpon the Worthies; but with moſt humble dueties to the Worthieſt of them all.
            
            
               NIne Worthies were deſcribed long agone,
               And as forgotten are intumbed dead:
               No Monument remaines of any one,
               Though they were Shrined better then in Lead:
               But Ioſua, Dauid, Macchabeus be
               In Bible booked for firſt Worthies three.
               Next in that Ranke (and ſo the number nine)
               Were Iulius, Alexander Macedon,
               
               
                  Hector of Troy, and Godfrey-de-Boloigne,
               
               
                  Arthur of Britaine, Charles King Pepins ſonne.
               In other bookes their Stories written are;
               With whom eight HENRIES welnigh may cōpare.
               The ninth, in hope more worthy then the eight:
               Vpon whoſe ſhoulders wiſeſt heads haue hurld
               Of future honour a farre greater weight,
               Applauded of Europa, and the World.
               Beſides all theſe, one Worthy more I ſing;
               The worthieſt of Worthies, IAMES our King.
            
         
         
            
            Jo: Guilliams Gent. vpon the ancient nine Worthies.
            
               THe drift and ſcope of princely Subiect this
               Is bent to very perfect honeſt end.
               The Writer thought, he could not write amiſſe,
               In writing that which formerly was pend.
               Nine former Worthies Stories theirs extend
               Some of them vp to heauen, with endleſſe praiſe:
               All of them liv'd moſt worthy in their dayes.
               But all were not of one, nor oneſelfe ſort:
               Three excellents, of God ordaind before:
               Three other valiant, famous by report.
               The firſt three Kings, one Prophet, valour ſtore:
               All three commended heauenly vertues lore.
               Three other were profane, but valiant men:
               Three Chriſtian Kings, that vſed pike for pen.
            
         
         
            
            
               Paul Peart, Gent. vpon the later nine Worthies.
            
            
               TO make thoſe Worthies liue againe.
               Which long agoe were lapt in Lead,
               Is worthy praiſe for taken paine,
               To him that raiſeth from the dead
               Such Princes as in time poſſeſt
               The Regal Scepter, Crowne and Globe,
               And in their Tumbs haue taken reſt,
               That once did weare a kingly Robe,
               Now to appeare on princely Stage,
               And to reſigne a princely power,
               Vnto a Prince whoſe tender age
               IEHOVA bleſſe, and grant each hower
               Him to attend the royall heſt,
               And follow after true renowne.
               He then from heauen ſhall be bleſt,
               Nor dare proud Fortune euer frowne
               On him that vertuouſly doth liue,
               To whom eight HENRIES honour giue.
            
         
         
            
            Iohn Widevp (the yonger) Gent. of the nine Worthies.
            
               THe primier Worthies, which we Worthies cal,
               Were worthy, three for godly exhortation
               
                  (Ioſua, Dauid, Macchabeus): and all
               The other ſixe for valours imitation.
               Nine worthies more behold; eight Kings, a Prince,
               Yong, Tender, Sweete, Great Britaines hopefull Ioy:
               Who will in time his fathers Foes conuince,
               And worthy prooue, as Hector was of Troy.
               
               Then eighteen Worthies, with the Prince of Britain,
               
               This booke doth note: Loe here their ſtories written.
            
         
         
            
               Thomas Webber (ſeruant to the Kings Maieſtie) vpon the ſixt Worthy, King HENRY the ſixt.
            
            
               THe King was left an infant, moſt vnfit
               To Raigne, by age: but not to rule, till when
               He ſhould attaine in time to riper wit,
               Thereby to iudge the differences of men:
               Yet, Crownd in Paris King of mighty France,
               
               In tender yeeres almoſt an infant ſtill,
               His vncles and his Nobles did aduance
               
                  
His Regal power, as did his father will
               They ſhould. But yet this King, a tender childe,
               Was rul'd and ouer-rul'd by Tutors head.
               For de-la-Poole his nonage then beguil'd
               And brought King Rayners daughter to his bed:
               Yet during nonage, or his kingly youth,
               The valiant Dukes of Bedford, Gloceſter thoe
               
                  Salisbury, Shrewsbury Earles, theſe bent their truth
               T'vphold him King of France in ſpite of foe.
               In whoſe time, Talbot was a terror great
               To all the French. For, as his dubbing drums
               With armed ſouldiers did their walles downe beat:
               So women fear'd their children, TALBOT comes.
               
               Thus whil'ſt theſe Nobles liv'd, this Worthy thriues:
               They being dead, then all was loſt againe.
               
                  Salisbury, Talbot both did loſe their liues,
               
                  Bedford likewiſe. Now both theſe valiants ſlaine,
               This King at home drencht in domeſticke ſtrife,
               Fierce factions ſet his Nobles at debate:
               Some followed him, and ſome his head-ſtrong wife,
               Till Richard Duke of Yorke diſturbd their State,
               Who claimd the Crowne; yet neuer could attaine
               The ſame: but Edward fourth his valiant ſonne
               Roſe into Armes, though firſt his father ſlaine
               At Wakefield, where the Queene a battell wonne.
               With theſe and thouſands moe, this worthy King
               Toſt and turmoyled, ſpent his Mortall time
               Till Tyrant Gloſter in the Tower did bring
               To death this worthy Prince deuoide of crime:
               In all his life who euer ſhunned euill,
               Conquering Sinne, the World, the Fleſh, the Deuill.
            
         
         
            
            
               Thomas Binwin, Gent. vpon his worthy yong Maſter, the ninth Worthy.
            
            
               I Fall the Worthies ſhould on earth appeare,
               The ancient Worthies nine in Ranke and place
               (Three from Iudaea, three from other where,
               And Chriſtians three) our Britaines hopefull Grace,
               Our ſweet yong Prince, thereby could take ſmal ſtaine
               Though they from graues were raiſed vp againe.
               Now for thoſe Kings, which HENRY had to name,
               May they compare with HENRY Britaines Prince?
               Theſe Worthies (though of farre renoumed fame)
               Haue ſought and fought long time agoe, and ſince,
               In vaine for to conioyne their neighbour land
               To this their owne; continuing warre and ſtrife,
               Vntill it pleaſ'd Iehouas mighty hand
               From hence to giue King IAMES the fourth a wife,
               HENRY ſeuenths, ſiſter, Lady Margaret faire;
               Of whom deſcends our Liege and gracious King,
               And braue Prince HENRY, his thrice worthy heire.
               Magnifie God and Nature, for this thing.
               Which ſole ſucceſſion hath brought ſuch accord,
               That he of both may once reſt Soueraigne Lord.
               This then may make our Worthy principall
               Of later nine; His future power and ſtrength:
               Yea more, herein exceeding Worthies all;
               They being dead are now entumbd at length:
               This Worthy liues. God graunt him long to liue:
               Graunt long (good Lord) the King, his father, reigne
               (And to his princely ſonne thy graces giue,
               Great God) that both may Britains wealth maintaine.
            
         
         
            
            The Authors excuſe of an Eſcape, in the Title following.
            
               NExt Title ſome ſmall error may containe;
               Which doth auerre HENRIES, nine Engliſh Kings:
               
               Yet, to my Booke, why ſhould it ſeeme a ſtaine?
               Sith, to Great Britaine, it great comfort brings.
            
            
               The hopefull Prince and Heire apparant, He
               With the eight Kings well may conſorted be.
               Twice ſcap't (by Pen, and Preſſe) I fear'd to raze
               His future Stile, at whom euen Kings may gaze.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The nine English Worthies, or famous and worthie Kings of England; being all of one name, beginning with King HENRY the firſt, and concluding with HENRY now Prince of Great Britaine.
            
            
               King Henry the Firſt.
               
                  
               
               
                  KIng Henry the firſt was the ſonne of William the Brother to William Rufus, that was immediately before King of England: which worthy King for his wiſdom, learning, iudgement, and honourable policy was ſurnamed Henry Beuclarke, or the faire Writer and good Scholler. He

began his raigne the fift day of Auguſt, Anno Domini 1100. He was crowned at Weſtminſter, raigned 35. yeares, and 4. moneths, lacking 4. dayes: he was ſtrong of body, comely of ſtature, blacke haired, large and faire eyes, a Princely and a pleaſant countenance, excelling in thrée vertues moſt commendable and comfortable to the ſubiects of his time, viz, Wiſedome, Eloquence, and Ualour.
               
                  His Epitaphe.
                  
                     HENRY the firſt, a King, a Princes ſonne,
                     Excellent wiſe, well learn'd, of valiant minde,
                     His gouernement recorded this hath wonne,
                     For euerlaſting praiſe to him aſsign'd,
                     Firſt worthy. Then take place, O mighty Prince,
                     That with theſe vertues didſt thy foes conuince.
                  
               
            
            
               
               King Henry, the Second of that name.
               
               
                  
               
               
                  HE was a Frenchman borne, the ſecond ſonne of Ieffrey Plantaginet, Earle of Aniow, begotten of Mawde the Empreſſe, daughter to King Henry the firſt; he began his raigne ouer this noble Kealme of England the 25, day of October, in the yeare after the incarnation of our Sauiour Chriſt 1154. and departed this life in An. 1189. in the 61. yeare of his age, after he had raigned 34. yeares, 9. moneths, and two dayes. And heere may be thought (ſayth the Hiſtoriographer) that the raigne of the Frenchmen, and the names tooke an end, after they had borne ſway 122. yeares, after the comming in of King William the Conqueror. For, thoſe Kings which raigned after this Henry the ſecond, may rightly be called

Engliſhmen, becauſe they were borne in England and vſed the Engliſh tongue, cuſtome, and manners, according to the nature and quality of the Country. His body was buried at Fountverand, which is an Abby ſituate not far from the Eagle, within the Dutchy of Almucon.
               
               
                  His Deſcription.
                  HE was a man of good ſtature and very wel formed, of comely conntenance, partly red hayred, grey eyes, of wit quicke, and perfect good memory, ſo that he could remember long al things of any moment, which he had eyther heard or ſéene; of body ſomewhat fleſhy, and ſtrong, and could abide very patiently the diſpleaſures both of colde and heate, he had a large head, a broad breaſt, and very ſpare of dyet, the rather becauſe he would not be too fat, therefore when he was at leaſure and free from warres, his exerciſe was hunting, and progreſſe trauels.
                  He was a Prince of ſtout ſtomacke and inuincible courage, more reſolute and conſtant in time of aduerſitie, then in proſperitie: liberall to all men, but chiefely vnto ſouldiers. Pittifull to the poore (an excellent vertue and nature in a Prince). For proofe whereof in a time of dearth which happened in Aniow and Mayne, hee did at his owne coſt and Princely pitty: feede ten thouſand poore people euery day with good victuals, from the firſt of Aprill till the laſt of Iuly, An. Dom. 1176. And aboue his Princely and moſt magnificent houſe-keeping he ſtored garners, cellars, and ſtore-howſes, religious perſons and their howſes. Tributes and Taxes he tooke verie ſeldome, and thoſe not great. Hee was very expect in feates of warre, and no leſſe fortunate therin. He would praiſe his Captaines and men of warre after their deaths to encourage thoſe that liued; hee was well learned as

thoſe Princes aforeſayde, and excéeding wiſe. His care to haue Iuſtice duly adminiſtred in his Realme was excéeding great, in ſo much that finding that the Sheriffs in his time were rather inclined to ſeek their owne gaine, then to deale vprightly with his ſubiects, hee appointed Sapraniſors ouer them to ouer ſée their doings, as if they had béen Controllers, ſo as an awfull regard made them circumſpect, and wary in their doings. He ordained alſo puniſhment for Hunters in Forreſtes and groundes of warren, either by fines or byimpriſonment. He ordained that murtherers ſhould be hanged, other offences he puniſhed with loſſe of limmes, and otherwiſe as the qualitie of the offence required. Moſt carefull hee was to haue iuſtice adminiſtred without corruption. He tryed men of ſundry ſorts to execute iuſtice with iuſtice, but in fine hee referred it to the Biſhops and Clergy men, hoping in that profeſſion to finde the moſt integritie: and yet he little regarded the Biſhop of Rome or feared his cenſures, as is manifeſt by the hiſtory of Thomas Becket in this Kings time, and ſundry others.
               
               
                  I find two Latine Epitaphes tranſlated into rude Engliſh by the Writer of this whole Historie, the effect wherof ſomewhat reformed is, as followeth.
                  
                     KIng Henry was of late my famous name,
                     A Conqueror of many a Princely land:
                     Small Epitaph ſhall need to aduance my fame,
                     What done by me was done by powerfull hand,
                     
                        
And in my dayes I paſſed not a pin,
                     For Pope of Rome, he nought of me could win:
                     Warre, Lawe, and Iuſtice as a princes word,
                     I held them alwaies of the great'ſt regard:
                     Where peace would not preuaile I drew my ſword:
                     Vnto my ſelfe and ſouldiers, full reward
                     I gaue, and with ſmall bloudſhed as I could,
                     I tam'd my foes and quailed princes bolde.
                     As ſecond Worthy, I do claime the place,
                     Amongſt the nine, and more. For in my time,
                     All Chriſtian Princes ſought to me for grace,
                     For without me they could not liue ſans cryme.
                     My peeres and princes I maintain'd with right,
                     And in the field dubd many a worthy Knight.
                  
               
            
            
               
               King Henry the third.
               
                  
               
               
                  KIng Henry, the third of that name was the eldeſt ſon of King Iohn, the yongeſt ſon of king Henry the ſecond: being a childe of the age of nine yeares he began his raigne ouer the realme of England the 19. day of October, in the yeare of our Lord 1216. he was crowned at Glocester by the hand of two Biſhops: viz. VVinchester and Bathe, by the honorable meanes of William Marſhall then Earle of Pembroke. He was a Prince of great wiſdome, power, and policy, by whoſe eloquent oration this young king was crowned as is here mentioned: he departed this life at VVestminster the 16. day of Nouember, Nota. in the yeare of our Lord 1272. after he had liued 65. years and raigned King of this Realme 56. yeares &amp; 28. dayes:

hee was buried at VVestminster, lefte a Princely and a very honourable iſſue, as Edward Prince of VVales, who ſucceeded him by the name of King Edward the firſt. He had one Sonne more and three daughters, he was of body well caſt (to vſe the former writers owne words) being ſtrong and of a good ſtature, well fauoured, and of a be wtifull face, only blemiſhed a little in the lid of one of his eyes, of nature very curteous, and of ſtomacke both noble and ſtoute, as may appeare by his many battailes and victories, a deuaut Prince toward his God, and bountifull in works of reliefe, and comforts towards the poore and néedie: therefore a Worthy, and worthy of th'enſuing Epitaph.
               
                  His Epitaphe.
                  
                     
                        HEnry the third began his raigne in peace,
                     And likewiſe brought a mighty peace to paſſe:
                     Beginning his forc't factious French ſurceaſe,
                     And landed Lewis in France where firſt he was:
                     Elſe noble England had been thruſt in thralls,
                     By Lodowicke and his luſty gallants then:
                     But Engliſh Britaines baniſhed the Galles;
                     So ſhewing that they were true Engliſh men.
                     King Henry then of Worthies was the chiefe,
                     That for his ſubiects wrought ſo greatreliefe.
                  
               
            
            
               
               King Henry the fourth.
               
                  
               
               
                  WHen king Richard the ſecod had reſigned the crown, as in his hiſtory it appeareth he did, Henry Plantaginet borne at Bollingbroke in the county of Lincolne, Duke of Lancaster, Earle of Hertford, Lecester and Lincolne, was with the general conſent both of the Lords and commons of the Realm publiſhed, proclaimed, and declared king of England, France, and Lord of Ireland: he was crowned at VVestminſter in An. 1399. with great and kingly Maieſtie, all Officers of eſtate and of princely ſeruice doing their homages, and attending vpon the ſame. He departed this life the 20. day of March 1413. and in the yeare of his age

46. when he had raigned 13. yeares fiue moneths and od dayes.
               
                  The manner of his death.
                  THis king was indued with magnanimity, and did purpoſe a voiage againſt the infidels, and to haue with his force and might redéemed Palestina, or the holy land then ſo called, from the Infidels. Hauing an army and all honourable prouiſions for ſuch a iourney ready, and beeing the time of his high court of Parliament, hee fell ſodainely and extreamely ſicke, as he was then (though vainly) praying before Saint Edwards ſhrine: from whence being remoued into a chamber of the Abbots of VVestminster called Ieruſalem, he departed as is aboue ſayd. But during the time of his ſickneſſe, ſay ſome Writers, he cauſed his crowne to be ſet vpon a pillowe at his beddes head: and ſodainely the pangs of death hauing power ouer him he ſeemed dead, and the gentlemen Attendants couered his face with a vaile. That valiant Prince his ſonne being aduertiſed thereof, entred into the chamber, tooke away the Crowne and departed. The King his father reuiued quickly, and did perceiue the lacke of his crowne, and hauing knowledge that the Prince his ſonne had taken it away, he cauſed him to appeare before his preſence, demanding of him how he durſt preſume to ſuch an act. Who made vnto the king an humble and princely anſwere: but the king anſwered with a powerful Maieſtie, ſaying with a great ſigh; Wel fayre Sonne, what right I had to it God knoweth, yet I commit all to God, and wiſh vnto you all good graces from him worthy of ſo high and mighty a calling; ſo yelding vp the ghoſt in the Abbot of VVestminsters chamber called Ieruſalem as is aforeſayd. And himſelfe being tolde that the ſame chamber was ſo called hee tooke comfort

there at and much reioiced therin: for, determining a moſt honourable iourney towardes Ieruſalem, hee did end his dayes in Ieruſalem.
                  
               
               
                  His Deſcription.
                  THis King was of a mean ſtature, well proportioned and formally compact, quick, prompt and ready of wit, of a ſtoute courage, and in his latter dayes hee ſhewed himſelf ſo gentle that he obtained more loue amongſt the Nobles and people of this Roalme, then he had purchaſed enuie concerning his right to the Crowne mentioned to the Prince his ſonne: he was buried at Canterburie, the King his ſonne being preſent at his funeralles.
               
               
                  His Epitaphe.
                  
                     
                        HEnry the fourth (though Richard ſecond ſhould
                     Haue dyed our king) he dyed our King indeed.
                     Which act by dint ofſword was ſo control'd
                     That many Engliſh hearts it made to bleed:
                     
                        Shrewſburie field doth ſtill the matter ſcan:
                     Where Percies pearc't the heart of many a man,
                     Themſelues were pearc't and periſht in the field:
                     This mighty King could not be conquered ſo,
                     Lord Henry hotſpurre could not make him yield,
                     
                        Northumberland Earle, Worcester, thouſands moe,
                     
                        
The Prince of VVales, a leader young but bould,
                     Fought for his Father like a Lyon olde.
                     Like an olde Lyon rampant open iawes,
                     Deuouring beaſts, ſo fought this peereleſſe Prince;
                     Yet was he, wounded in the face God knowes,
                     Prayd to take Tent: he ſayd I will conuince
                     Thoſe foes that dare beholde my Fathers face,
                     Within his land and worke him this diſgrace.
                     The braue Earle Dowglas ſtrake the King on helme,
                     And feld him flat vpon the trampled plaine,
                     Slew Walter Blunt and like to ouerwhelme
                     The King, the prince, and all their valiant traine,
                     Till Kingly valour forced Dowglas flight
                     And with his hand ſlew thirtie ſixe outright.
                     
                        Dowglas was taken priſoner in the place,
                     So was the Earle of Wore'ſter worthy paine,
                     And ſo he was beheaded wanting grace:
                     But Dowglas was receav'd to grace againe,
                     And freely ranſom'd by that worthy King
                     Gainſt whom he fought and many foes did bring.
                     More of this King, if more ye liſt to heare,
                     Then read his ſtory and more ſhall you finde,
                     That from his prime vnto his perfect'ſt yeare
                     Great honour and great fortunes were aſsign'd
                     Vnto this King; but more vnto his ſonne
                     Who had no peere ſince Chriſtian World begun. Counterfait kings.
                     
                     Counterfaite Kings in Kingly armors clad
                     Were beaten downe by the Earle Dowglas hand,
                     To ſee them fall it ſeem'd his heart to glad
                     To riſe againe, he ſayd ô powerfull land
                     That valiant harts withſtanding fortunes checke
                     Three Kings to riſe each one in others necke.
                  
               
            
            
               
               King Henry the fift.
               
               
                  THe Prince of Wales ſon and heire to king Henry the fourth was born at Mounmouth in Wales vpon the riuer of Wy: after his Father was departed this life, he tooke on him the regiment of the Realme of England the 20. day of March: and beeing proclaimed King by the name of Henry the fift, the yeare of our Lord 1413, ſuch great hope &amp; good expectation was had of this kings fortunate ſucceſſe to follow, that within ſowre dayes after his Fathers departure, diuers Noble men and honourable perſonages did to him homage, and ſware to him due obedience: which had not béen ſéen done to any his predeceſſors

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
kings of this Realme, till they had been poſſeſſed of the Crowne.
               Hee was crowned the ninth day of Aprill beeing Palme-ſonday: and béeing a very fierce and cruell day for variety of fowle weather, men diuined and déemed diuerſely what might inſue of ſuch a beginning.
               But whatſoeuer mens fantaſies might or did coniecture, yet this was the King, that according to the prouerbe did ſhewe and declare indéede how trewe and new honor ought to make exchange of old and euill manners. For no ſooner was he inueſted king and had receiued the Crowne, but hee did put vpon him the ſhape of a newe man, turning inſolency and wildeneſſe, into grauity and ſoberneſſe: and whereas hee had paſſed his youth with wanton and diſſolute wild yong gentlemen who had led him into all exceſſe of ryot, in ſo much as one of his youthfull traine beeing committed by the Lord chiefe Iuſtice for miſdemeanour, the youthfull Prince did ſtrike the Lord chiefe Iuſtice vpon the face, who alſo preſently committed the Prince to ſtraite and cloſe priſon. The King his Father mainetained the Lorde chiefe Iuſtice; baniſhed the Prince from his preſence and Courte, did remoue him from the Counſell Table, and woulde not readmit him into fauour, vntill with ſubmiſſion extraordinary hee obtained the ſame. But as before beeing placed in the ſeate Royall, hee called theſe Gallants before him, toulde them of his and their owne faultes, baniſhed them from his preſence, not vnrewarded nor yet vnpreferred, inhibiting them vpon a great payne, not once to approach, lodge, or ſoiourne within ten myles of his Courte or Manſions. And then hee made choiſe of graue, wiſe, and politicke Counſellors: by whoſe high wiſdomes, and prudent aduertiſements

he might at all times rule to his honour, and gouerne to his profit. And conſidering with himſelf what charge hee had in hand, and what appertained to his duty and office, he truſted not too much to his owne wiſedome, Iudgement, and directions: but as is aforeſayde he called to his Counſell ſuch honourable perſonages as might aſſiſt him in the gouernmēt of ſo weighty a charge to inſtruct him with ſuch good reaſons and fruitefull perſwaſions, as that thereby he might ſhewe himſelfe to his ſubiects, a Mirror of vertue, and an example of iuſt and vpright dealing. And hauing firſt laid the foundations of his gouernment ſure, he did prouidently forecaſt and conſider in his Princely minde, that euery good gifte and euery perfect gifte commeth downe from the Father of lightes. He determined withall to begin with ſomething moſt acceptable to his diuine Maieſtie. And therfore cō
                  manded the Clergy ſincerely &amp; truly to preach the Word of God and liue accordingly; that they might be as they ought to be, and their profeſſion required, lanternes of light to the temporaltie. The Lay men he commanded to ſerue God and obey their Prince, prohibiting them aboue all things the breach of matrimony, the fowle abuſe of ſwearing, chiefely of wilfull periury: and to that end he ordained good &amp; holeſome lawes, and preſently ſummoned a Parliament, in the which in honor of ye moſt noble order of ye garter, he ordained the day of S. George euer after to be kept with a double feaſt: in this his firſt parliament, he propounded matters of queſtiō touching the hierarchy of Churchgouernment, that time; but was anſwered with the iuſt and lawful title which he had to the kingdome of France. Which when he had conceiued to purſue, the Dolphin of France a valiant yong prince, ſent vnto his Maieſty a barrel of tennis bals, as if he would haue ſayd, theſe are fit inſtruments for ſuch a young gentleman to play withall as you the King of England is, &amp; not at theſe

years to forecaſt the conqueſt or rather a Reconqueſt of the noble and renowned kingdome of France, which the King my Father, and I the Dolphin doe and will poſſeſſe mauger the power of England.
               
               But this redoubted king, magnanimous, wiſe, graue, and ſettled to all kingly reſolutions, ſendeth the Dolphin this mild and ſober anſwere. Go tell that gallant yong gentleman your Maſter, that I doe thanke him for his preſent, and will with all ſpeed prepare to ſend him in requitall ſuch ſtore of London bals, as ſhall batter the ſtrongeſt holdes, make ſtoops the moſt bewtifull Towers, and make flat the chimnies, and roufes of houſes, about his and his Fathers eares, that are contained in the realme &amp; confines of France. For I will make the higheſt crowne to ſtoop, and the proudeſt miter to kneele down; yea and that before one yeare doe paſſe me, by the power of God. Which thing to make good he ſlacked no time, omitted no occaſiō, loſt no opportunitie, but made preparation both by ſea and land to execute the full of his intended purpoſes.
               Being furniſhed for the expedition of the fleet, ready for his Maieſtie and Armies to ſaile forth for the intire conqueſt of all France, behold a conſpiracy was practized againſt this immaculate king, by the Earle of Cambridge and others at Sowthhampton, vpon whom he commanded (though ſore againſt his wil, as ſome Authors do affirme) execution to be done vpon his going to ſhipborde, making it knowen by a moſt louing and princely Oration how vnwilling hee was to haue taken life away, or to haue left the noble Earle of Camebridge deade and ſequeſtred from his then victorious voyage.
               Yet had he ſeene or foreſéene at that time to haue ſhewed the like vpon the Earle of March: Richard Duke of Yorke had not claimed afterward as he did, nor confounded the ſtate and gouernement of this kings onely

ſonne, nor wrought his owne end at Wakefield as he did: but the Almighty is and euer wil be all in all.
               This his firſt and honourable voyage into France, his warlike proceedings there, his conqueſt of many particulars, his battaile or moſt famous victorie at Agincourt, where hee ſlewe and ſubiected to himſelfe, as priſoners and captiues, al the flower and chiualry of France, his returne againe into England, his ſecond voyage backe againe, his ſecond conqueſt of all France, the Homages of Philip duke of Burgundy with other eſtates of France, his mariage with Katherin the French Kings daughter, his triumphant ſtay there in Paris, his Princely or rather Emperiall howſekéeping there, his returne againe into England, his laſt returne into France, his ſettling of the eſtate there, his Coronation at Paris, the moſt Propheticall cenſure of Prince Henry his Sonne borne at VVindſor, and afterward King of England crowned alſo in Paris King of France, his vntimely or moſt lamentable death, his returne into England in mournefull funeralls, are extant in his hiſtories, and the beſt worthy of reading, in regard of his owne Princely Perſon, valour, vertues, and moſt excellent actes, of all the other Chronicles of the Engliſh Nation. And yet to obſerue the order and decorum of my poore endeuour in abſtracting the beginnings and endings of eight moſt worthy Kings, and all Henries, I will conclude this moſt worthy king, with the manner of his death, and deſcription, vſing the Hyſtoriegraphers owne words, phraſe, and manner; as not to be amended by any.
               The King fell ſicke, and ſo was brought to Boyes de Vincens, and thither came to viſit his Maieſtie (with heauy hearts) the Dukes of Bedford &amp; Gloceſter: the Earles of Saliſoury, and VVarwicke; whom the King right louingly welcomed, and ſhewed himſelfe to be no leſſe glad of their preſence: but when he did ſee them penſiue for his

ſicknes, and danger wherein he lay, with many graue pithy and courteous words recomforted them the beſt hes could, and there with he exhorted them to be truſty and faithfull vnto his ſonne, to ſée that he might be vertuouſly educated, and brought vp: concerning the rule and gonernance of his Realmes, during the minority and yong yeares of his ſayde ſonne, he willed them to ioyne together in all friendly loue, and concord, kéeping continuall peace and amity with the Duke of Burgundy and neuer to make treaty with Charles, who calleth himſelf Dolphin of Vyenne, by the which any part of the crown of France, or of the Dutchy of Normandy and Gwyene might be leſſened and diminiſhed. And further that the Duke of Orleance, and the other Princes ſhould remaine priſoners till his ſonne came to lawfull age, leaſt by returning they might kindle more fire in one day, then could well be quenched againe in thrée. He further aduertized them, that if they thought it neceſſary, then it ſhould be good to haue his brother the Duke of Glocester to be Protector of England during the minority of his ſonne: And his brother the Duke of Bedford with the help of the Duke of Burgundy to be Regent of France.
               
               Commanding him with fire and ſword to perſecute the Dolphin, vntil hee had either brought him to reaſon and obeiſance, or elſe to driue and expell him out of the Realme of France. And herewith he proteſted vnto them that neither ambitious deſire to inlarge his Dominions neither to purchaſe vaine renowue and worldly fame, nor any ſuch conſideration had mooued him to take that war in hand, but onely that in proſecuting his iuſt Title, hee might in the ende attaine to perfect peace, and come to enioy thoſe peeces of his inheritāces which to him of right belonged: and that before the beginning of the ſame wars he was fully perſwaded by men both wiſe and holy of life, he might and ought vpon ſuch inteut, both begin

the ſame warres and follow them til he had brought them to an end, iuſtly and rightly; and that without all danger of the Almighties diſpleaſure, or perill of ſowle.
               The Noble men preſent promiſed to obſerue his precepts and performe his deſires: but their hearts were ſo penſiue, and repleniſhed with ſorrow, that one could not for wéeping behoulde an other. Then hee receaued the Sacrament and fell to deuout prayer: and in ſaying of certaine Pſalmes méet for the preſent time, hee ended the dayes of this life, the laſt day of Auguſt, Anno 1422.
               
                  His Deſcription.
                  THis Henry was a king whoſe life was immaculate, and his liuing without ſpot, this king was a prince whom all men loued, and was of none enuied, this prince was a Captaine againſt whom fortune neuer frowned, nor miſchance once ſpurned: this Captaine was a Shepheard, whom his flocke both loued and obeyed. This Shepheard was ſuch a Iuſtitiary, that he left no offence vnpuniſhed, nor good deſert vnrecompenced &amp; fully rewarded. This Iuſtitiary was ſo feared, that all rebellion was baniſhed, and Sedition ſuppreſſed. His vertues were no more notable then his other qualities were worthy of prayſe. In ſtrength, and nimbleneſſe of body, from his youth fewe or none were to him comparable. In wreſtling, leaping, and running, no man (almoſt) durſt with him preſume. In caſting of great iron bars, &amp; heauie ſtones, he excelled commonly al men: cold weather neuer made him ſiothful, nor hot cauſed him to ſhrink, &amp; whē he moſt labored his head was vncouered:

he was no more weary of his armor, then of a light cloak. Hunger and thirſt to him were neuer noyſome, he was neuer afraide of a wounde, nor would ſhrink for the paine in dreſſing, he neither turned his noſe from ill ſauoures, nor from ſmoake and duſt would cloſe his eyes, no man could be found more temperate in eating and drinking, whoſe dyet was not too delicate, but rather more méete for men of warre, then for dainty and delicate perſons: euery honeſt perſon was permitted to come to him euen ſitting at meales, and either ſecretly or openly to declare their minds, and intent: high and waighty cauſes as wel betwéen men of warre, as other he would gladly heare, and either determine them himſelfe, or commit them to other to giue ſentence. He ſlept very little, and that was mooued either by bodily labour, or vnquietneſſe of minde: but béeing in ſléepe no ſmall noiſe could awake him; inſomuch as when his ſouldiers did ſing, or minſtrels play in the campe that it ſounded withall, then hee ſlept moſt ſoundly. His courage was inuincible and his heart ſo immutable that fear was baniſhed from him. If an Alarum chanced to be raiſed by his enemies he was the firſt in armor, and the firſt that would ſet forward: in the time of warres he would not only get knowledge what his enemies did, but what they ſayd, and intended to do; ſo that all things to him, were knowne aforehand. And of his deuiſes, fewe perſons before the execution of his purpoſed intent ſhould be made priuie: he had knowledge in the ordering and guiding of an army, and ſuch a rare gifte to encourage his men to fight, that the Frenchmen ſayde it was impoſſible for him to be vanquiſhed in battaile: he had ſuch wit, ſuch prudence, and ſuch policy, that he neuer enterpriſed any thing before he had fully debated it, and foreſéen al the maine chances that might happen: and when the end was once concluded, he with all diligence and courage ſet his purpoſe forward. What policy hée

had in finding ſodaine remedies, from preſent and dangerous miſchiefes, and what practiſe he vſed in ſauing himſelfe and his people in ſodain diſtreſſes, except by his acts they did plainely appeare, it would ſéeme incredible to be tolde; and no leſſe admirable how hee did abſtaine from laſciuious liuing, and auaritious deſires in ſuch time and eſtate of riches and prouoking youth. In the time of loſſe he was no more ſad then in the times of victory, which cō
                     ſtancy fewe Princes haue euer vſed. To ſpeake of his bounty and liberality, no man could be more free, gentle and liberall in beſtowing rewardes vpon all perſons according to their deſerts: ſauing that hee did not regarde money to kéepe, but to giue away, and to ſpend. What may beſayd? he was the Myrror of al Chriſtendome, and the glory of his Country, the flower of Kings paſſed, and the glaſſe of all ſuccéeding Maieſtie. No Prince had leſſe of his ſubiects, no king conquered more: whoſe fame by his death liuely floriſhed, as his acts in his life were ſéene and remembred. The loſſe of ſuch a Prince could not bée ſufficiently lamented of his ſubiectes: blaming fortune for taking away ſo precious a iewel, ſo noble an ornament ſo ſure a defence: for no doubt ſo much hope as was taken away from the Engliſhmen (the aſſured conqueſt of all France) by his ſodaine death, ſo much truſt was increaſed in the French nations ſtomackes to recouer their late loſſes againe; as not many yeares after they did indéed: Peeter Baſſet Eſquier, and one of his chamber, affirmed that he dyed of a Pleuriſy, there were others that did aſtirme otherwiſe, but the moſt likely was a Pleuriſy indeed; the nature of that diſeaſe being then vnknowen to Phiſicians, or to the world in thoſe dayes eſpecially.
                  This King raigned nine yeares, fiue moneths and three and twenty dayes: and liued not full thirty eight yeares: he was of ſtature higher then the common ſort, of body leane, ſingularly proportioned and ſtrongly made,

of face bewtifull, ſomething long necked, blacke haired, ſtoute of ſtomacke, eloquent of tongue, in Martiall affaires a perfect maiſter, and of chiualry the very peragon: His body inbalmed and lapped in lead was layd in a chariot royall, richly apparelled in cloth of golde: vpon his corps was layde a repreſentation of his perſon, adorned with robes, diademe, ſcepter, and ball, like a king: the which chariot was drawen with ſixe horſes richly trapped with ſeuerall armes; the firſt with the armes of S. George, the ſecond with the armes of Normandy, the third with the armes of king Arthur: the fourth with the armes of S. Edward, the fift with the armes of France, the ſixt with the armes of England and France. On this Chariot gaue attendance Iames King of Scotland principall Mourner, his Unkle Thomas duke of Exceter, Richard Earle of Warwicke, Edmond Earle of March, Humfrey Earle of Stafford, Edmond Earle of Mortaine. The Nota. Lord Fitz Hugh, Hugh L. Beufort, Walt. L. Hungerford Sir Lewis Robſert, Lord Bourchier, Sir Iohn Cornwall, Lord Fanhope, and the Lord Cromwell were the mourners. The Lord Louell, the Lord Audley, the Lord Zouch, bare the banners of Saints: the Baron of Dublin bare the ſtandard, The Earle of Longvile bare the banner. The Hatchments were borne onely by Captaines to the number of twelue, and round about the Chariot rode fiue hundred men at Armes all in black armour, and their horſes barbd with black, carrying the but end of their ſpears vpwards. The conuoy of this dolorous funerall was committed to Sir William Philips Treaſurer of his houſehould, &amp; to Sir William Porter his chiefe caruer and other mourners: on each ſide the chariot were 300. men bearing long torches, and Lords bearing banners, baueroles and penons. Nota. With this funerall pompe he was conuaied from Bois De Ʋincens to Paris; and ſo to Roan, to Abuill, to Calis, to Douer, and ſo through London to Westminster,
                     
where he was buried with ſuch ſolemnities as to ſuch a Prince appertained; eſpecially ſuch lamenting of the Lords, and ſuch mourning of the Commons, asn euer before thoſe daies were ſeene in the Realme of England.
               
               
                  There is as I doe thinke an Epitaph fixed vpon his Tumbe, at Weſtminſter: but I held it my dutie to continue my courſe in writing a ſimple one of my owne, in honour of him, &amp;c. His Epitaphe.
                  
                     OHad I Homers pen, and Virgills wit,
                     With Tullies Eloquence to prayſe this Prince,
                     And would the Muſes come and by me ſit;
                     Yet pen and paper would my Muſe conuince.
                     For who can write of this moſt famous King,
                     And ſhall not erre in many a worthy thing?
                     His life immaculate, what doth that meane?
                     But that he conquered ſinne, the world, the fleſh,
                     Vnſpotted ſure: O heart and body cleane!
                     Almoſt two hundred yeares agoe, yet freſh
                     The memorie of thee O King remaines.
                     Thy Tumbe like Cryſtall ſhines deuoyd of ſtaines.
                     Proſe be thy prayſe, which Holinſhed hathpend:
                     And prayſed be thy name O King for euer.
                     Thy owne pure prayſe no mortall man can mend,
                     Thy name cannot forgotten be, no neuer.
                     
                        
                        England and France ring forth thy famous praiſe.
                     Though thou raigne with the Ancient of all dayes,
                     Yet as a mirror, or a looking glaſſe
                     Thou mai'ſt remaine ô King amongſt vs ſtill.
                     Succeeding princes will not let thee paſſe
                     To Heauen without adminiſtring thy Will.
                     Such teſtaments grant all thy heires to proue:
                     Then Englands glory neuer ſhall remoue.
                     Reſt then ô Rex, and riſe vp with renowne,
                     
                        VVestmonastery doth thy tombe poſſeſſe,
                     Succeeding Soueraigne doth enioy thy Crowne
                     And Kingdomes all, one more; for whome we bleſſe
                     Thy name great God, who long prolong his dayes
                     To Englands comfort and ay-laſting praiſe.
                  
               
            
            
               
               King Henry the ſixt.
               
               
                  AFter yt death had bereft the World of that noble Prince King Henry the fift, his only ſonne Prince Henry béeing of the age of nine moneths or thereabout with the ſownde of Trumpets was openly proclaimed King of England and of France, the thirtéenth day of Auguſt Anno. 1422. by the name of King Henry the ſixt. The cuſtody of this young Prince was committed to the Duke of Exceter, and to Henry Beuford Biſhop of Winchester. In the eight yeare of his raigne &amp; the ſame of his age, he was with all ſolemnity crowned king at Westminster: not long after which time he tooke the ſea at Douer, landed at Calis, from thence to Roan, and ſo to Paris, whither attended

on him his Uncle the Cardinall of VVinchester, the Cardinall and Archbiſhop of Yorke, the Dukes of Bedford, Yorke and Norfolke, the Earles of Warwicke, Saliſbury, Oxford, Huntington, Ormond, Mortaine, and Suffolk: of Gaskoines, there were the Earles of Longvoile and March, beſides many Noble men of England, Gwyen, and Normandy: and the chiefe of the French Nation, were the Dukes of Burgundy, Lewis of Luxenburgh Cardinall and Chauncelor of France for King Henry, the Biſhops of Bauiors and Noyom, both Péeres of France; the Biſhop of Paris and diuers other Biſhops: the Earle of 
                     Ʋandemont, with a great number of other Noble-men, ſuperfluous to be named. And hee had a Guarde about his perſon of thrée hundred choyſe Archers, ſome on horſebacke, and parte on foote. With what tryumphes, pageants, riche and ſumptuous ſhewes hee was receaued into Paris, woulde bee too tedious to repeate. On the ſeauenth day of December, he was crowned King of France in our Lady Church (ſo called) in Paris, by the Cardinal of Wincheſter; the biſhop of Paris not being contented that the Cardinall ſhould execute ſuch an high office in his Church and Iuriſdiction. After all ceremonies finiſhed, the king returned to the palace, hauing one crowne on his head, and another borne before him, one ſcepter in his hand and another borne before him: A triumphant feaſt and great reioyſing, but mingled with diſtaſte by means of the proud Cardinall of Wincheſter; who, preferring his owne wil before the weale publike, controlled that mighty Prince and valiant Captaine, the Duke of Bedford Protector of France: which malice moued, and heart-burning broched by the Cardinall, was remembred and reuenged by the Nobility. But my only purpoſe being to ſelect forth the name of Henry, and but to note their beginnings &amp; endings, by way of abſtract I will leaue this worthy yong prince yet a while, and tell

the vntimely death of Iohn Duke of Bedford, a tale worthy of note and memory, and this is it: viz.
               
               This yeare the fourtéenth day of September 1436. dyed Iohn Duke of Bedford and Regent of France, a man moſt politicke in peace, and no leſſe hardy in warre, and yet no more valiant then mercifull when he had the victory: whoſe body was with al funeral pomp and ſolemne obſequies buried in the cathedrall Church of Roan in the North ſide of the quier vnder a ſumptuous &amp; coſtly monument &amp;c. Which Tumbe when King Lewis the 11. knew to be his, and was incited by certaine indiſcréet Frenchmen to deface the ſame, he anſwered; What honour ſhall it be to vs, or to you, to break this monument, and to pull forth of the ground the dead body of him, whom in his life time, neither my father nor your progenitors with all their puiſſance and friendes were not once able to make flee one foote backward; but by his ſtrength wiſedome and policy, he kept them all out of the principall Dominions of the realme of France, and alſo out of this Noble and famous Dutchy of Normandy: wherefore I ſay firſt, as God hath his ſoule, ſo ſhall his body now ly in reſt, who when hee was aliue would haue diſquieted the proudeſt of vs all. And as for the Tombe, I doe aſſure you it is not ſo decent nor conuenient, as his honour and actes deſerued, no although it were more riche and more bewtifull then it is.
               But to returne according to the occaſion, and by the way to touch this worthy Prince. His misfortune in his minority, was the cauſe of his Nobles diſſention: and that the cauſe of an vnméete and vnfortunate mariage; ſo that the Prince in his yong yeares ſpent all the honour power and pleaſures of this mighty and worthy King, whoſe life was immaculate like his Fathers, whoſe patience ouercame all his perplexities. Once depoſed from his regal ſtate, and dignity, and once

againe reſtored (in which interim was his propheticall ſpeach to thoſe Princes and Nobles about him, touching the young Earle of Richmond a child of tenne yeares old, Beholde (ſayth he) ſtedfaſtly beholding the young Earle: This is hee, whome wée and all our Aduerſaries muſt giue place vnto, when all is done) He was againe depoſed, committed to the Tower of London, his onely ſon ſlaine, his Quéene tooke ſanctuary, his Nobles, beſt ſubiects, and all his partakers ſlaine in ſundry battailes: himſelfe laſtly murthered in priſon; and yet his patience, integrity, godly life and good workes were no leſſe commendable, then the acts of his father were famous, and honorable. He reigned 38. yeares, 6. moneths and odde dayes; and other 6. moneths after his readeption of the crowne. Heliued 52. yeares.
               To cenſure him, ye God puniſhed him for his grandfathers &amp; fathers faultes, or that miracles were wrought by him, I neither will belieue, nor write, as the writer of his hiſtorie doth, nor of King Henry the ſeauenths purpoſe to haue him canonized for a Saint: but yet the loue of that moſt mighty King, that in the zeale of this Kings immaculate life would haue had him remembred for ſuch holines, doth commend my purpoſe (which is) to commend him for the ſixt worthy (and in ranke alſo) aboue all other his princely deedes. The kings colledge in Camebridge, and Eaton Colledge neere VVindſor, are both very excellent monuments of his princely liberality: and my ſelfe haue obſerued forty yeares together that God bleſſed both thoſe houſes, the one for education, and the other for bringing forth very excellent ſchollers.
               
                  
                  His Deſcription.
                  HE was of a ſeemely ſtature, of body ſlender; to which proportion all his parts were anſwerable. His face was very bewtifull: wherin was euer reſident a ſweet reſeblance of bountie, wherwith his Royall heart was naturally indewed, and euer thereunto inclined. He abhorred all vices both of the body and of the ſoule. His patience was ſuch, that of iniuries done to him (which were innumerable) he did neuer ſeeke vengeance; thinking and ſaying, that for ſuch aduerſities as befell him, his ſinnes ſhould be forgotten and forgiuen: what loſſes ſoeuer did happen vnto him, he neuer eſtéemed nor made account thereof: but if any thing were done which ſéemed to offend the Almighty, that hee lamented with ſorrowfull repentance.
               
               
                  His Epitaphe.
                  
                     
                        HEnry the ſixt, a Prince, a Saint, a King,
                     Faire Englands ſoueraigne eight and thirty yeare:
                     Which time with more, his wofull end did bring,
                     As in his ſtory doth too plaine appeare:
                     
                        
O had his Vncles liv'd and well agreed,
                     His death had not ſo vilely been decreed.
                     Had Dela Poole been dead ere he was borne
                     King Raynars Daughter had not been thy wife.
                     If innocency thou hadſt held in skorne
                     And reacht thy hand to warre, debate and ſtrife,
                     And Parent like hadſt proued Mars his ſonne,
                     
                        Glocester had not thy fatall thred vnſpon.
                     Had Richard (Warwicke) wonne at Barnet field,
                     Braue Mountacute, or many Nobles moe,
                     That fled, or dy'd, or were inforc't to yield
                     (But power diuine had not ordained ſo)
                     He had not gone backe priſoner to the Tower
                     And there detain'd vntill his lateſt hower.
                     
                        Tewkeſbury field had like or worſe ſucceſſe;
                     Duke Somerſet, the Earle of Deuon, eke
                     The Marqueſſe Dorſet taken in the preſſe
                     The poore young Prince was found, whom Crofts did ſeeke
                     And brought before the King by armed Band;
                     Whom Richard Glocester murthered out of hand.
                     Did patient Iob indure more paine then this
                     Moſt Mighty Prince. Who hearing all this ill
                     Yet neuer murmur'd or once thought amiſſe,
                     More then a man, remaining patient ſtill,
                     A King indeed a conqueror of the mind.
                     In all the ſtories we no ſuch doe finde
                     (Diuine, profane, or morall, as I yet
                     Did euer read) ſuch magnanimitie
                     To reſt in man where humain hart was ſet,
                     Or who had feeling of extremity.
                     Reſt now ô King in heauens moſt happie ſhrine,
                     Preſeru'd from foesb all the powers diuine.
                     Let VVindſor be his monument of ſtate,
                     Becauſe he was both borne and buried there,
                     
                        
Knight of the Garter, mightie Potentate. Nota.
                     
                     Though to his Fathers ſenſe it did appeare
                     That Henry borne at Windſor ſhould not be
                     Like Henry borne at Mounmouth, which was he:
                     Yet Henry borne at Windſor worthy fame
                     Was and ſtill is and ſhall be to the end:
                     His Colledges continue will his name
                     Whil'ſt Worlds indure: it is in marble pend.
                     Then worthy King, Sixt Worthy liue, and be.
                     For many Worthies were not like to thee.
                  
               
            
            
               
               King Henry the ſeauenth.
               
               
                  THat moſt valorous, vertuous, and politicke Prince, King Henry the ſeauenth, needeth not any preamble for his birth and education: onely he was the true &amp; vndoubted heire of the houſe of Lancaster, and came to the Crowne by the conqueſt of his enemy Richard Plantaginet late Duke of Glocester; but later a moſt horrible murtherer, regiſtred Homicide, Tyrant, and Uſurper of the crowne of England: of whom I will make no further mention, but that this mighty Prince conquered him, and his people in foughten field. At Boſworth in the county of Leceſter 22. day of Auguſt 1485. the conflicte and conqueſt was determined.
               
                  
So preuailed King Henry the ſeauenth, the day and yeare aboue ſayd, to the great glory of God, and the continued comfort (euer ſince) of all trew and faithfull Engliſh hearts. Now this King being by conqueſt abſolute, by power able, by birth heir Apparant; yet to ſettle and make ſtedfaſt his raigne and ſucceſſion, he maried Elizabeth, the daughter of king Edward the fourth, next heire of the houſe of Yorke: and ſo reunited both thoſe howſes (moſt honorable in themſelues) into one intire monarchie, into one vnity, into one body, into one (I ſay) and that a moſt happie one, into one bed; and bleſſed be that bedde, and the ſéed for euer, that ſprang and ſtill ſpringeth of that generation. This vnion, or knitting of theſe two famous howſes both together, was the end of long continued ciuill warres, the death of nobilitie, deſtruction of the comminalty, the griete of foraine Princes, the lamentation of Citties, the outcry of the people. The State, before this vnion, was ſo rent and torne, that it was thought a thing impoſſible euer to haue béene reconciled againe: therefore this gracious beginning doth prognoſticate a happie continuance and neuer to haue ending.
               Yet the Dutches of Burgundy, a Princeſſe of ſtate and ſtomacke, being Aunt to Elizabeth the Quéene, did ſo much maligne this great and excellent good, that ſhe ſet vp many mawmentes and apyſh toyes of purpoſe to diſtemper the peace of this vnion: as rearing vp Perkin Warbecke, a baſe dutch vaſſall, to vſurpe the name of Richard Duke of Yorke, the ſecond ſonne of king Edward the fourth; who with his tender yong brother king Edward the fift, had by their vnnaturall Uncle béen both murdered in the Tower. Many vaine and ſurmiled images ſhe aduanced to diſtemper the ſtate, vntill time and ſucceſſion made an end of her malice: which alſo by a lingring ſickneſſe tooke this worthy an excellent king forth of this World. But, before his death, hee married the

Lady Margaret (his eldeſt Daughter) to King Iames the fourth King of Scotland: which mariage I thought good to inſert, as it is recorded in the courſe of his hiſtory; viz.
               
               
                  Iames the fourth king of Scotland, a mighty and a valiant Prince, hauing had ſundry fewdes, and garboyles wich the Engliſh Nation, and that in the interim of truce, and abſtinence of warre, eſpecially about Norham caſtle; the Biſhop of Durham Richard Foxe owner of that caſtle in the right of the Biſhopricke wrote diuers letters of ſubmiſſion to the ſayd K. and the K. againe to the Biſhop, &amp; one letter in concluſion of many things, that the biſhop of Durham ſhould come into Scotland to him about weighty affaires.
               The Biſhop certifying the King his Soueraigne of the premiſſes, The King commanded the Biſhop by his letters to ſatiſfie the Scottiſh Kings deſires, which he tooke to be both reaſonable and honorable: and of which meſſage the Biſhop was verie glad.
               So going into Scotland the king himſelf moſt gratiouſly &amp; curteouſly receaued this Biſhop at the Abby of Melroſe, and after ſome expoſtulation with the Biſhop touching ſome ſlaughter done vpon his Subiects at Norham Caſtle, and the Biſhops ſubmiſſe and gentle anſwers thereunto, the King gaue the ſame moſt like a King the hearing. And afterward called the Biſhop into a ſecret place garden or gallery, where no witneſſes were admitted but only the King and the Biſhop, and then he declared vnto him what iuſt cauſes had mooued him in times paſt to ſéeke amitie with the king of England which now he deſired to haue confirmed, and to hold inuiolable for euer, if the ſayd King would vouchſafe to conioyne in matrimony with him the faire and bountifull Princeſſe L. Margaret the K. eldeſt daughter. In the behalf whereof we were purpoſed to ſend our Embaſſadors to the K. your maſter.

But we thought good firſt to proue your loue, good liking and forwardnes towards vs and our good liking to your king, his daughter, his ſubiects and dominions.
               The Biſhop anſwered but fewe words: only he ſayde that when he was returned to the King his maſter, hee would in ſo great and waighty a cauſe doe the beſt offices that hee coulde. When the Biſhop was returned into England and came before the king, hee declared to his Maieſtie all the communication which had paſſed betwéene king Iames of Scotland, and him, from point to point in order.
               The king liked excéeding well of the motion, as he to whom peace was euer a ſoueraigne ſalue.
               But hauing then a mariage in nuptiall celebration almoſt, betwéen Arthur Prince of Wales, and Katherine the Infant of Spaine, the mariage with Scotland being haſtened by both the kings: in the very triumphs of the former mariage, king Iames ſendeth an Earle, a Biſhop &amp; diuers noble perſonages, who were receaued into London for the conſummation of his mariage with the aforenamed Lady Margaret: which Earle by proxey, in the name of king Iames his maſter affied and contracted the ſaid lady. The which affiance was publiſhed at Pauls croſſe the day of the conuerſion of S, Paul being the 25. day of Januarie ſuppoſed. In the reioicing wherof Te Deum was ſung, &amp; great bonefiers made throughout the Citty of London.
               
               All theſe things being accompliſhed, the Imbaſſadors both of Scotland and Spayne tooke their leaue of the king and departed, not without great rewards to both the Embaſſadors.
               Not long after, the Lady Margaret affyed as aforeſaid was ſent towards the king her husband: the conueiance of which princeſſe was committed to the Earls of Northumberland &amp; Surrey, the Earle of Northumberland being L. Warden of the Marches, and was commanded to deliuer

her at the very confines of both the realmes. And thereupon ſhe was remoued from Barwicke to Lamberton Kyok in Scotland; where the kings Maieſtie met her, and with him all the flower of Scotland of Noblemen and Gentlemen; and where the Earle of Northumberland according to his commiſſion deliuered her vnto the king of Scotland. The Earle of Northumberland that day was ſo richly apparrelled in garments garniſhed with goldſmithes worke, ſtone and pearle, his Hexemen alſo and the barbes and trappings of his horſes, beſides 400. tall med well mounted &amp; apparelled in his liuery &amp; colours, that he ſeemed more like a king then an Earle.
               From Lamberton the foreſaid Lady was conuaied to Edenborough; and there, the day after, king Iames eſpouſed her in the preſence of all the Nobilitie of Scotland, and of thoſe Engliſh that attended her, with great feaſtings banketings, iuſtes, and Princely paſtimes: and after all things finiſhed to ſuch a ſolemnity appertaining, the Earle of Surry beeing chiefe in commiſſion, with the Earle of Northumberland, and all the other Engliſh Lords and Ladies returned into their Countrey againe.
               But as al earthly creatures and things tranſitory haue their end and period, ſo had this Mighty prince K. Henry the ſeauenth. For his ſickneſſe increaſing daily more and more, he well perceaued that his end drew néere: therefore meaning to doe ſome comfort to his people, hee did grant them of his owne free motion a generall pardon for all men, and for all offences committed againſt any his Lawes and Statutes: Thieues, Murtherers, and certaine others were excepted: he alſo payde the fées of all priſoners in and about the gaoles of London abiding there onely for that dutie: Hee payde alſo the debts of all ſuch perſons as lay in the Counters or Ludgate for forty ſhillings, and vnder, and ſome he relieued that were condemned in ten pounds. Generall prayer being made to God

for the reſtitution of his health, neuertheleſſe hee was ſo waſted with his long Malady, that nature could no longer ſuſtaine his life, and ſo he departed this life the 22, of Aprill, 1509 at his palace at Richmond: his corps was conuaied to Weſtminster with all funerall pompe, and there buried by the good Quéen his wife in a ſumptuous Chappell, which he not long before had cauſed to be builded. And as the greateſt Trauellers haue reported it is one of the moſt bewtiful and moſt curious peeces of work in the World.
               
                  His Iſſue.
                  HE raigned twentie thrée yéeres, ſeauen moneths &amp; od dayes and liued fifty two yéeres: he had by his Quéene fowre ſonnes, and fower Daughters, of the which number there remained aliue behinde him, Henry his ſecond ſon, prince of Wales, which after him was king: Margaret Queene of Scotland, and Marie promiſed to Charles king of Castile.
                  
               
               
                  His Deſcription.
                  HE was of body but leane and ſpare, yet mighty and ſtrong therewith, of perſonage and ſtature ſomewhat higher then the common ſorte of men: of a wonderfull bewtie and faire complexion, of countenance merry and ſmiling, eſpecially in his communication: his eyes gray, his téeth ſingle, and haire thinne, of Nota, wit in all things quicke and prompt, of a princely ſtomake, and hauty courage; in great perils, doubtfull affaires and matters of importance ſupernaturall and as it were diuine: for he ordered all his dooings aduiſedly and with great deliberation.
                  
                     
He was ſober, modeſt, moderate, honeſt, curteous, bountious; ſo much abhorring pride, and arrogancy, that he was euer ſharpe and quicke to all about him noted with that fault, he was alſo an vpright Iuſtice: by the which one propertie he wan to him the heartes of many people. He left to that luſtie valiant and gallant young Prince his ſonne and heyre many excellent good partes and properties of a Prince, as alſo Coffers full ſtuffed with coyne, iewells and treaſure. To conclude, he had in him as many good giftes both of body and minde, and fortune as it was poſſible for any King to haue: his politicke wiſedome in gouernance was ūngular, his wiſedome alwayes aſſured, reaſons pithy and ſubſtantiall, his memorie freſh and holding, his experience notable, his counſels fortunate and taken by wiſe deliberation, his ſpeeches grations in diuers languages: leagues and confederations he had with all Princes Chriſtian, his mighty power was dread euery where both within his owne Realme and without, all his people were to him in humble ſubiection as euer they were to King: his land many a day in peace and tranquilitie, his proſperitie in battayle againſt his enemies was maruellous: his dealing in time of perils and dangers was cold and ſober, with great hardineſſe. If any treaſon were conſpired againſt him it was miraculouſly diſcouered: his buildings moſt ſumptuous, and goodly, all of the neweſt forme and faſhion and caſt all of pleaſure. So this king liued all his time in fortunes fauour, in high honour, wealth, and glory, and all which wrought his fame in this world, and the ſame euerlaſting in the world which ſhall neuer haue end.
               
               
                  
                  His Epitaphe.
                  
                     MOſt prouident, moſt politicke, moſt wiſe,
                     Moſt ſumptuous builder, moſt profound in all
                     The things that wealth and wiſdom can deuiſe,
                     The things that Art to memorie can call,
                     All things that God and nature did decree,
                     Thoſe with this worthie king concluded be.
                     Not any other with this mightie King
                     May be receiued nor intertainment haue.
                     That which doth peace and plentie to him bring
                     That which his Realmes and ſubiects liues can ſaue,
                     Thoſe he receaues that bleſsing brings from God,
                     Thoſe he reiects which threaten ſcourge and Rod.
                     Thriſe bleſsings in his mariages he made:
                     Firſt was his owne, Queene El'zabeth his wife;
                     Before the which was many a bloudy blade
                     Bath'd in the bowels of continued ſtrife.
                     The houſe of Lancaſter, with Yorke did ſtriue,
                     To leaue of Prince nor Subiect one aliue.
                     This Worthy brought into his nuptiall bed,
                     The bride whoſe bewtie did the World excell,
                     This Worthy ioyn'd the white Roſe with the red,
                     This bed doth now in Windſor wardrobe dwell:
                     This manage wrought that perfect Vnitie,
                     By which this day all Britaines happie be.
                     The ſecond was his eldeſt Virgin pure,
                     The Lady Margret. Vnto Iames the King,
                     Biſhop of Durham did that match procure:
                     
                        
Earle of Northumberland the bride did bring
                     Home into Scotland. Iames the fourth did wed.
                     
                        Britaine moſt happy by that nuptiall bed.
                     Onely theſe two, though more this worthy made,
                     May now and ſhall ſuffice, for all the reſt.
                     No Actor he of Hymenaeus trade.
                     We in theſe two moſt happie now are bleſt,
                     And bleſt in heauen are the authors all
                     As we thereby redeemed are from thrall.
                     
                        Henry the ſeauenth ſeauen Sciences imbrac't,
                     All liberall, all princely all of power,
                     All enemies he from his kingdomes chac't
                     And left a Sonne of Chivalry the flower,
                     Succeeding Henry and the eight to be
                     Worthy, but now a worthyer is then hee.
                  
               
            
            
               
               King Henry the eight.
               
               
                  KIng Henry the eight was borne at Greenwich the 22. of Iune, Anno. 1492. He began his raign the 22. day of Aprill. 1509. he raigned, 37 yeares, 9. moneths and od dayes, being 18. yeares olde when he began to raignè. And although this worthy king was in years young, in perſon ſtrong, bewtifull and valiant, in treaſure rich paſſing any his predeceſſors, mighty and worthy in power and in action: yet being adorned and bewtified with learning to his Princely magnanimity, he ordained his Councell by the aduice of his gracious grandmother the

Counteſſe of Richmond and Darby, ſuch as he knew to be prudent indéed, and the kings his father moſt deare and familiar friends: ſome of whoſe names I thought good to inſert, for the eſpeciall and ſingular effects which inſued of their moſt honourable and graue counſels: viz.
               
               
                  Thomas Lord Haward Earle of Surrey and Treaſurer of England, George Lord Talbot Earle of Shrewſebury and Steward of the kings houſeholde: Charles L. Somerſet Lord Chamberlaine, after Earle of Worceſter, and others: which wiſe and graue Counſellers, ſéeing what aboundance of wealth this young king was now poſſeſſed of, leaſt it might incline his young yeares vnto riotouſneſſe, and forgetting of himſelfe (for not to any King before him was left the like riches in ready coyne, iewels, and plate, and excellent moueables, as to him by his famous father King Henry the ſeauenth) therefore thoſe moſt honourable Counſellers did labour to attaine his Princely preſence, in their ſecret méetings, and moſt honourable priuie counſels; that by degrées they might win him to ſuruay at leaſt the affaires of a kingly office, and Princely gouernment.
               Which alſo he ſlacked not to do: for within leſſe then 5. yeares after, to wit, the 20. of Iuly in the fift yeare of his reigne, he entred into France with a puiſſant power; and mighty army, wan the ſtrong Townes of Torney▪
                   and Turwin, had in pay (as ſouldiers mercenary) that moſt famous Emperour Charles the fift, and alſo the Palſgraue of the Rhene, which wore Saint Georges croſſe: in which time alſo was fought that famous battaile of Branxſtone or Floden-field, where the King and the flower of all his chiualry was conquered by the valiant hands, of Norfolke, and Hawardes.
               
               In the ſixt yeare of his raigne the Pope did ſend him a cappe of maintenance, in thoſe dayes the higheſt degrée of honour: and the ſame Pope was mediatour to him

for peace, in the French Kings behalfe, and for the confirmation thereof the French king married the kings yonger ſiſter Mary, and dyed ſhortly after.
               In the twelfth yeare, the king made a moſt famous, pleaſant, and princely voyage into France, with atriumphant traine of Nobles, Ladies, &amp;c. for an interuew betwéene him &amp; his Quéene and States on the one party, which was performed in the valley of Andrean, with many varieties of princely ſhowes, as the hiſtory thereof at large deſcribeth that voyage;
               And that in his way the Emperor Charles met his Maieſtie at Canterburie kéeping Whitſontide there, with the king.
               In the fouretéenth yeare of his raigne, he was by a Bull from Rome, ordained or intitled the defender of the Chriſtian faith, which title was then giuen to him and his ſucceſſors for euer.
               The ſame yeare alſo he receaued into his Realme the forenamed Charles the fift Emperour againe into the Cittie of London, with Great triumphes, &amp;c. inuoſted him with the Garter, and habit of that moſt honourable order, ſware league and amity during both their liues.
               In the 18. yeare he contracted league with the french K. to hold both thoſe kings liues, and one yeare after; hee was alſo inueſted, with the coller and order of S. Michael, and the French king with the Garter and order of S. George.
               
               The twentie three yeare hee (or the lawe for him) did confiſcate Cardinall Wolſey a proude and wealthy Prelate in the ſtatute of premunire, had great treaſure therby, as alſo great fines of all the Clergie, for defence of the Cardinals power Legatine: and about the ſame time, he took vpō him the title Supream head of the church &amp;c. For the which &amp; for the ſuppreſſiō of Abbeies immediatly after;

howſoeuer the Pope and his ſucceſſors ſince haue preſumed to curſe him and his bleſſed ſucceſſion (his Daughter Mary only excepted):
               Yet the Almighty hath bleſſed both him, and them, Edward and Elizabeth ſince, and long O Lord vouchſafe to bleſſe the trewe and lineall deſcent of noble King Henry the ſeauenth.
               But ſure it was a wonderfull Kingly Maieſtie in that valiant King: who poſſeſſed but a part of great Britaine, nor hauing faſt friendſhip with the other part, but many domeſtick and ciuill garboiles at home: all or the maior parts of Chriſtendome, holding then Rome and her religion for Catholicke and vniuerſall: all which notwithſtanding, this moſt famous and mighty king did aboliſh and abandon, to his euer immortall praiſe and wonder of the world. How did God after this bleſſe his ſonne, although but with young yeares and ſhort raigne, yet with miraculous might: and his ſecond ſiſter raigning almoſt forty and fiue yeares, with immaculate happineſſe.
               And after this alſo he warred againſt the French king, wonne the Tower of Bulloyne and many other partes on that ſide, forced that Nation to compoſition, brought home peace, honor, wealth; and in the excéeding loue of his people, he ended his life, at his palace at White-hall, the eight and twentieth day of January, Anno 1546. when he had reigned thirty and ſeuen yeares, nine moneths, and odde dayes, triumphantly, and in great felicitie, leauing the Iſſue before mentioned, Edward, Mary, and Elizabeth. His body, according to his Will in that behalf, was interred at Windſor, with all funeral Pompe, in the Chappel, and Colledge of S. George, Patron of the Garter; whereof almoſt 38. yeeres hee had béene ſole Souereigne.
               
                  
                  His Deſcription.
                  THis worthy Prince was right fortunate in all his doing
                        •
                     
                     ▪ ſo that (except onely in his mariages) all other his attempts had good ſucceſſe as wel in matters of peace, as of wars. Of perſonage he was tall and mightie, yet excéeding comely: but towards his latter end groſſe and (as wee tearme it) bourly: in wit and memory very perfect, of great Maieſtie; yet ſo tempered with gracious humanitie as beſt became ſo high an eſtate: a great fauourer of Learning &amp; learned men, and of himſelf not ignorant of diuine Learning, nor morall literature: and for his great magnificence and bountious liberality his renowne was ſpred throughout the World.
               
               
                  His Epitaphe.
                  
                     EIght Worthies now are nominated here,
                     Eight Kings, eight Britaines, eight braue Engliſh men:
                     Eight, ſuch as in their times had no compeere:
                     Eight, ſuch as cannot be expreſt with pen:
                     Eight, ſuch as neuer liu'd in time together,
                     King Dauids Worthies might not match them euer.
                     For Dauids Worthies were not crowned Kings:
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        Dauid was once anointed of the Lord, 
                           
                              〈…〉
                           uid.
                     
                     His Pſalmes great comfort to our conſcience brings,
                     His vertues were according to the word
                     Of God, for all his treatiſes are true
                     Prefiguring Chriſt, he Beare and Lyon ſlew.
                  
                  
                     Prince Ioſua Captaine of that mightie hoſte,
                     Six hundred thouſand did his campe containe, 
                           
                              〈…〉
                           ua.
                     
                     His prayer ſtayed the Sunne amid the Coaſt
                     Till he the Kings of Canaan had ſlaine:
                     He Iſrael their foes did all confound
                     And raz'd proud Iericho downe to the ground.
                  
                  
                     Braue Iudas Machabeus with the beſt 
                           
                              〈…〉
                           as acha
                           
                              〈…〉
                           us.
                     
                     Of valure his thus bouldly may he boaſt:
                     The Iewes redeeming them with foes oppreſt
                     And that with ſmall and verie ſober hoaſt:
                     A Worthie therefore of the Iewiſh Race,
                     Arm'd with that God, diſpoſer of all grace,
                  
                  
                     Great Alexander Macedonian Prince,
                     Whom the earths continent could not content: Alex
                           
                              〈…〉
                           der.
                     
                     
                        Philippe his father Nations did conuince,
                     For which his ſonne with teares did ſorelament,
                     Saying with ſighes his fathers Captaines to,
                     My father will leaue nothing me to doo.
                  
                  
                     
                        Hector of Troy a valiant Champion tri'd
                     Gainſt factious foes did oft r'enforce the field, 
                           
                              〈…〉
                           ector.
                     
                     Enforcing them their faces elſe to hide
                     Or plead for mercy and like ſuppliants yeeld,
                     Not any of our Henries wanted power,
                     To haue ſubdued him in his ſterneſt ſtower,
                  
                  
                     If Iulius Caeſar could haue beene a King 
                           
                              〈…〉
                           lius 
                              〈…〉
                           ſar.
                     
                     With conqueſt which his Romaine Legions made,
                     By blody bodkins he ſhould not the ſting
                     Haue felt of death in powrefull Senates ſhade.
                     
                        Brutus his ſonne nor Caſſius had conſpir'd
                     His death, had he not kingly ſtate requir'd.
                  
                  
                     
                        Arthur of Britaine moſt renowned king, 
                           
                              〈…〉
                           rthur.
                     
                     
                        
Sixe of the nine were not his equall peeres,
                     Full thirty king domes he to his did bring,
                     Yet was his life not many moe in yeares.
                     Braue Britaine then take place among the beſt,
                     And midſt our worthie Henries take thy reſt.
                  
                  
                     Next Charlemaine of France, a Monarch great, Charlemaine.
                     
                     So called great, and Emperour he was.
                     French Chronicles his actions all do treat,
                     He for a Chriſtian Worthy wel may paſſe.
                     Yet Henry ours the eight as good as he,
                     Shall for a Chriſtian King compared be.
                  
                  
                     
                        Godfrey de Bulleigne was a Prince of fame,
                     He wore vpon his helme a crowne of thorne, Godfrey
                     
                     Hefreed all Chriſtian captiues where he came:
                     And not forſooke them, till in peeces torne
                     He left their foes laid groueling on the ground,
                     That durſt attempt a Chriſtian to confound.
                  
                  
                     See then nine Worthies in their ranke and place,
                     Three of which number gouerned the Iewes,
                     Great Ioſua is formoſt of that race:
                     But, for king Dauid brought vs better newes,
                     I place him firſt, and do withall compare
                     
                        Henry the eight a worthie King moſt rare.
                     
                        Henry the eight gaue vs our primier taſte
                     Of milke which is moſt meete for infants foode:
                     
                        Edw. and Eliza. ſtronger meates imbrac't,
                     And fed vs till we better vnderſtood
                     The word of God, which Rome had vs bereft:
                     This grace to England gracious Henry left.
                     Three more of Worthies by their names to call,
                     Great Aloxander was the Graeciaus ioye:
                     And Iulius Caeſar mighty Romane ſhall
                     Be ſecond here, then Hector ſtout of Troy:
                     
                     Threee mighty Princes, peereleſſe in their dayes,
                     Whoſe worthy valour won them endleſſe praiſe.
                     Three Worthies more of Chriſtians beare the name,
                     
                        
                        Arthur of Britaine, Charlemaine of France,
                     
                     And he that freed all Chriſtians where he came
                     Wearing a crowne of thorne the name t'aduance,
                     
                        Godfrey de Bulloyne worthie Chriſtians three.
                     Nine no leſſe worthie follow in degree.
                     
                        Henry the firſt, Henry the ſecond eke,
                     
                        Henry the third, Henry the fourth and fiue:
                     
                        Henry the ſixt, whoſe match is farre to ſeeke.
                     Except King Iames do match him, none aliue
                     With that ſweet King may well compared be,
                     For trew and perfect magnanimity.
                     
                        Henry the ſeuenth a prudent worthy Prince,
                     Whoſe wiſedome ioyn'd with perfect policy,
                     With red Roſe and with white, he did conuince
                     Domeſtike foes, and foraine that durſt try
                     For title, ſtate, preheminence or place.
                     Eld'ſt Daughter his is now great Britaines grace.
                     
                        Henry the eight, eight Worthies more hath made:
                     The ninth remaines in Henry Prince of Wales.
                     
                     The eight do reſt in freſh Elyſian ſhade,
                     The ninth need feare no blaſte of winter gales,
                     So long as worthieſt of all Worthies liues,
                     King Iames, to whome all Eighteen Worthies giues
                     Their Scepters, Crownes, their Diadems and power,
                     Their places and preheminence likewiſe.
                     Th'Almighty hold his mighty hand each hower,
                     Vpon his head; that cauſed him to riſe
                     Like Phoebus when our Cynthia lately ſet, Cynthia.
                     
                     Paying to God and nature all her debt.
                     This Epitaph in Henry eight ſhall end,
                     And Henry Prince of Wales may here beginne,
                     To imitate, for that he doth deſcend,
                     Such Worthies eight, ſuch honour may he winne,
                     Long life, good health, all graces from aboue,
                     With Subiects praiſe and kingly Fathers loue.
                  
               
               FINIS.
            
            
               
               
                  Henrie the ninth, Prince of Great Britaine.
               
               
                  
               
               
                  The Author, in honour of the laſt ninth Worthie.
                  EIght famous Kings precedents to a Prince,
                  Whoſe valiant acts are regiſtred with fame:
                  Eight Henries, and all thoſe the conqueſt ſince,
                  As Worthies all haue iuſtified their name:
                  Eight ſuch as all the King domes of the earth
                  Cannot exceed, for Title, State, and Birth.
                  What makes men Noble? Birth and parentage,
                  Adornd with gifts, and beautified with grace.
                  
                     
Then Britaine boaſt, that neuer any age
                  Brought the like Prince, a thouſand yeares in ſpace:
                  For birth, for vertue, and for expectation,
                  Prince of Great Britaine ouerpeer's each Nation.
                  Ninth Worthie then, O Prince, poſſeſſe in peace
                  That worthy Title, beſt befitting fame:
                  Let prudence, fortitude, and all increaſe
                  That vertue addes, and doth adorne your name.
                  Let Princes all, and ſpite it ſelfe confeſſe,
                  In forraine Lands Prince Henry is peereleſſe.
                  Of all the World our mirror then of might,
                  Our Paragon, moſt rare and worthie praiſe,
                  Our Comet, and our riſing Starre moſt bright,
                  Grant mightie Ioue, that long and happie dayes
                  He may enioy, and we reioyce and ſing
                  For this Ninth Worthie, firſt for Iames our King,
                  Your famous father, and Great Britaines Ioy,
                  Your glorie alſo, guyder of your youth;
                  Whoſe carefull, Counſell to preuent annoy,
                  Moſt like a King, he pend in perfect truth,
                  You to direct: and all young Gentlemen
                  (Your followers) are aduiſ'd, by Kingly Pen.
               
            
            
               
               
                  The Prince his Bien-venue, or welcome to all the famous Worthies of the World.
               
                  BRaue Britaines beautie, and faire Englands Ioy,
                  
                     Cambers Commander, Irelands lamp of light,
                  
                     Cornwales faire Duke, and Cheſter from annoy
                  
                     Count Palatine, for to defend with might,
                  Whole Europes Comet and Saint Georges Knight,
                  Grant Lord, the George and Garter long he weare
                  To King and Countries comfort, as true heire.
                  Welcome ſweet Prince, into our company,
                  Which we from heauen with cheerefulneſſe behold.
                  We had our times, our period was to die;
                  But yours to liue, and regiſtred in gould:
                  Whoſe powerful parent cannot be contrould,
                  Becauſe he knowes and feares the Lord aboue,
                  Liues in his Lawes, and hath his peoples loue.
                  But had your praiſe beene limd with learned pen,
                  Of Princely Surrey, once a Poet ſweet,
                  Sir Thomas Wyat, or like gentlemen,
                  They on this Theame diſcourſers had beene meet:
                  But this (alas) hath earthen hands and feet:
                  And yet, for that we in our Tumbes do reſt,
                  Let's be content to ſee and and ſay the beſt.
                  This poore beginning may much better proue:
                  The faireſt tops and architectures ſtand
                  On lowe laide morter: beautie ſhines aboue.
                  
                     
Foundations, firſt, are laied, with mirie hand:
                  Timber, glaſſe, ſtone, lead, iron, gould on ſand
                  Are ſeated, and more ſubiect to decay
                  Then that beneath, whereon their State doth ſtay.
                  From hence may happe ſome Builders take a frame,
                  And reare with Beautie ſumptuous ſtately Towers:
                  The worthie Poets, Daniell by name,
                  
                     Sylueſter, Drayton, can build ſumptuous Bowers:
                  And many moe bedewd with heauenly ſhowers.
               
               
                  And though who now this taske doth vndertake,
                  Did neuer to the Muſes homage make
                  (The more vnfit to fawne vpon them then,
                  In crauing of their aide without deſart,
                  And to inuite them with a ruſticke pen,
                  Fetching his cunning onely from the Cart)
                  Yet, yet, giue leaue to euerie loyall hart.
                  For all are not indewed with learnings skill:
                  And he writes wel of States, that writes no ill.
                  Then take, in gree, all what proceedes of loue,
                  Of dutie, and of true obedience.
                  And whoſoere he be doth faithfull proue
                  In ſeruices, and ſhall (without offenſe)
                  Whiſtle or pipe, ſans hope of recompenſe,
                  And onely to expreſſe a ioyfull heart
                  At Princes good; O, let him Act his part.
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

