
   
      
         
            Sermo die lune in ebdomada Pasche
            Fitzjames, Richard, d. 1522.
         
         
            
               1495
            
         
         Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00918
            STC 11024
            ESTC S118732
            99853939
            99853939
            19342
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00918)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19342)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1065:01)
         
         
            
               
                  Sermo die lune in ebdomada Pasche
                  Fitzjames, Richard, d. 1522.
               
               [80] p.   
               
                  By Wynkyn de Word,
                  [Enprynted at Westmestre :
                  [1495?]]
               
               
                  Place of publication and printer from colophon; suggested publication date from STC.
                  Text is in English.
                  On Luke xxiv. 15. --STC.
                  Signatures: a-e⁶ f⁴ g⁶.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons --  15th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-04
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  Sermo die lune in ebdomada
Pasche
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Ipse Ihūs apropinquans ibat
cū illis.
            
               Thyse Wordes ben conteyned in the
xxiiij. chapytre of Luke▪ and rad in
the holy gospel of this day. To say
in englyssh tonge The same Ihūs
nyghynge walkyd with mankynde
/ This Ioyous trouth conteyneth
in itselfe two partyes / In whoos declaracyon wyth
our lordys mercy &amp; your suffraūce. shall stonde the
sōme of this poore collacōn. The fyrste is this / that
the same Ihūs nyghed to mankynde. The second
is. that the same Ihūs hath wallryd wt mankynde
/ Of whyche two pryncyples foloweth as a conclusyon
the entent o
                  •
                his nyghyng and walkynge.
That the same Ihūs hath broughte mankynd to
the euerlastynge reste of heuen / For sure it is. y• this
same Ih
                  ••
                of whyche I purp
                  ••
                to treate. neuer put
man to labour / but to the entent. that he sholde after
his labour haue full reste, ye &amp; for thorte labour
haue eternall reste / as after shall appere. Yet or I
descende to the declaracōn of thise two partyes / for
as moche as I saye. that the same Ihūs nyghynge
walkyd with mankynd / I shall shewe you of whiche
Ihūs I meane. whyche it was that nyghed to
man that walkyd wyth man. &amp; that fynally broughte
man to euerlastynge reste in heuen. Where ye

shall vnderstonde. that of dyuers we rede in holy
scrypture whiche were namyd Ihūs. of thre in especyall
/ al men of noble memory. &amp; of grete praysyng
And but figures &amp; seruauntes of the same Ihūs of
whom wyth his mercy. I purpoos pryncypally to
trete. The first was) Ihūs filiꝰ Naue (The seconde
was (Ihūs filiꝰ Iosedec
                  •
               ) And the thyrde was
(Ihūs filiꝰ) the sone of Sirach / All thyse thre. and
eche of this. was for his tyme y• fygure of the fourthe
Ihūs / callyd (Ihūs filius dei) Iesus the sone of
god / The same Ihesus whyche nyghynge. walkyd
wyth mankynde / ¶To whose declaracōn ye
shall vnderstonde. that Ihūs by interpretacōn. is to
saye (saluator) a sauyour or helper / Now soth it is
that eche of thyse thre rehercyd. was in his tyme an
helper or sauer of the people / And yet but in fygure
of Ihūs Cryste. Wherof folowyth / that they
were not the same Ihūs of whom I purpoos talke
For he bothe was &amp; is (saluator mūdi) the sauyour
of the worlde. ¶How eche of thyse thre Ihūs rehercyd
dyde helpe. &amp; saue y• people in his tyme / I shall
shewe you. The fyrst Ihūs the sone of Naue. sauyd
the people (ꝑ potenciā) The seconde (ꝑ obedienciā)
And the thyrd (ꝑ sapienciā) The fyrste saued
the people by myght &amp; power. The seconde by pe
                  •
               
               fyte
obedyence. The thyrde by his grete wysdom.
¶The fyrste of them callyd Ihūs Naue. at hebreees
namyd Iosue Benun after saynt Ierom i
                  •
               
his prologe (cū Iosue) the fyrste ruler of y• chyldren

of Israel after the deth of Moyses the seruaunt of
god / as it appereth in the fyrste chapytre of Iusue.
was conuenyently namyd Ihūs / For by the grete
myghte &amp; power geuen vnto hym of very Ihūs. he
notably sauyd the people of god / as in the story of
Iosue playnly doth appere. acordynge vnto y• promyse
of god made vnto him in the fyrste chapytre
of the same boke / as foloweth (My seruaunt Moyses
sayd god vnto Iosue is deed &amp; from this world
departid. Arise thou &amp; passe ouer the water of Iordan.
thou. &amp; all my people wyth the. in to the londe
of repromyssion. whiche I shal geue to y• chyld
                  •
               n
of Israel. what so euer grounde ye shal set on your
fete. I shal geue it to you. as I promysid to Moyses
my seruaunt. It folowyth soone after / Noo man
shall mow resyst thy power in all thy lyfe. be thou
herof comfortid. &amp; take strengthe vnto the. ¶Now
how this myghty prynce executyd the hyghe cōmaundement
of god in helpynge the people &amp; sauyng
y• same by the grete power geuen vnto hym of god
y• sayd story of Iosue playnly doth declare ¶Shortly
rehercyd. eccliastic. the .xlvi. chapit
                  •
               e (Ihūs naue
sayth he successour vnto Moyses strong in were &amp;
bataylle. was a man of grete name / but of grettest
name was he in helpynge of the people of god. to
distroye his enmyes. where by he myght atteyne to
the people of god promysid / whiche glory and renō
               mee
of name he obsteyned in lyftyng his hondes &amp;
scute. in shetynge of sharpe &amp; fy
                  •
               y arowes ayenst y•
               
cyte of hay. &amp;c
                  •
                / This myghty prynce dilygently
executynge the hyghe cōmaundement of Ihū cryst
of whom. &amp; to whom. he was bothe fygure &amp; seruaunt.
through the grete myghte &amp; power to hym
gracyously geuen. so lad. so guyded. so sauyd y• people
to his rule cōmyttid. that he brought them in y•
lond. to Abraham. Ysaac. &amp; Iacob. repromysid / thef
vaynquisshyd &amp; distroyed the enmyes of god / dyuydid
the londe among goddis seruauntes. &amp; fynally
sette them in reste &amp; peasyble possession of the same
As bryefly declareth saynt Ierom in his epistle (ad
pa
                  •
               linū) ¶Ihūs sayth he y• sone of Naue. beryng
the fygure of Ihū Crist. as well in name as in dedes.
passid the water of Io
                  •
               dan. distroyed the reames
of Crystis enmyes. diuyded the londe to goddis
seruauntes / And by euery cytee. towne. village.
by hylles: fluddes &amp; ryuers. dyscryued in fygure the
spirytuall regaly of Crystis heuenly chirche &amp; Ierusalem
/ ¶Thenne apperyth y• this noble prynce
Ihūs Naue was in his tyme a man of laudable
memory / now callyd in all the worlde one of y• .ix.
worthyes for dyuers causes / For by his grete myghte
and power he sauyd the people to him cōmytted
from enmyes &amp; from peryll. He distoryed the aduersaryes
of Cryste. and sette his people in reste &amp; peas
/ Ye but amonge all his praysynges: his memory
is specyally laudable / For what cōmaundid him
to do. that gladly fulfylled he wythoute grutche o
                  ••
               
ieluctacōn. leuynge example vnto all pryncis &amp; rulers

of the people vnder god to doo the same. Our
lorde cōmaundyd hym. as in the fyrste chapytre of
Iosue doth appere this wyse. ¶Be thou sayth god
vnto this valyaunt knyghte stronge &amp; hertely com
for
                  •
               id. se ye thou obserue &amp; kepe al my lawes cōmaundyd
vnto the by my seruaunt Moyses. Declyne
thou neuer fro them ne in to y• ryght honde. ne yet
in to the lyfte honde / that is to saye. ne in prosperyte.
ne yet in aduersyte / so y• vnderstondynge of my
lawes be thy leder. Lete in no wyse the boke of my
lawe departe from thy mouth: 
                  •
               ut sette therin thy
meditacōn bothe nyghte &amp; day / so y• thou may truly
obserue al thynges there wythin wryten &amp; commaūdyd
/ This cōmaundement of god he gladly
fulfylled as it appereth in the .xi. chapytre of ye same
boke. in this worde (As our lorde commaunded
vnto Moyses: so Moyses cōmaunded vnto Iosue)
And he gladly accomplysshed all goddis preceptes
There escapyd hym not one worde of goddis preceptes
/ but to the extremytee he fulfyllyd them all.
Loke &amp; this well beholde ye Iuges of this worlde.
lerne the lawes of god / and se ye theim obseruyd &amp;
kept
                  •
               leest ye perysshe from the ryght waye of god / 
For &amp; ye be one in prosperyte. a nother in aduersyte
One for affeccōn. a nother for money. one for loue.
a nother for hate: thenne
                  •
               er
                  •
               e ye fro the ryght way
of Ihūs. ¶Of y• seconde Ihūs namyd Ihūs
of laudable memory in the scrypture of god. was
Ihūs y• sone of Iosedech. the grete preest of y• lawe

&amp; one of the .lxx. Interpretours of the Bible / This
grete preest of the lawe at the highe cōmaūdement
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                of god in y• mouth of Cu. 9. kyng &amp; fyrst Monarke
of Perse. whom our lorde had wt his grace inspyred
/ as in y• fyrste chapytre of the fyrst boke of Esdre
doth appere. to release the captiuyte of the Iuys
Whyche for theyr synnes hadr ben in thraldom in
Babylon by the space of .lxx. yere after the distruccōn
of Ihrlm. &amp; subuersion of the temple of god in
the same. by Nabugodonosor. &amp; Nabuzardan hys
capytayne / This grete preest I saye Ihūs the sone
of Iosedech. was in his tyme conuenyently named
Ihūs. y• helper &amp; sauer of the people of god (per sacram
obedienciā. by holy obedience / as Ihūs Nau
                  •
               
was Ihūs. sauer and helper of the people (ꝑ magnificā
potenciā) by his grete &amp; myghty power geuyn
vnto hym of god. To shewe you this. ye must vnderstonde
/ that for the synnes of the Iewes it pleysyd
god. to haue them punysshed / so were they acordyng
to the propheci of Ieremye. the .xxvij. chapytre.
Theyr cyte. theyr temple of grete honour was
dystroyed.
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                Sediche theyr laste kynge was exoculate
&amp; made blynde. brought wyth all his noblesse in
to Babilo
                  •
               e by Nabugodonosor. &amp; there kepte in
streyte captiuyte by the space of .lxx. yere. And here
was an ende of kynges in the genelogy of Crist as
by the processe of the Byble playnly dooth appere.
For soth it is y• after the tyme of this transmigracōn
vnto Cristis natiuyte. where regalyte &amp; preesthode

were Ioyned in one in our sauyour Ihū Crist
The Iewes beyng in ther lyberte or captiuyte. had
neuer moo kynges / but oonly prestes &amp; dukes. bysshops
&amp; pryncis / But thenne were bysshops rulers
of the people. &amp; p
                  •
               yncis helpers &amp; coad
                  •
               utours / So
yt the lyne of kynges after this transmigracōn sessyd
as in rule. not in successyon / And thenne began
the lyne of bysshops in rulynge of the people. whiche
contynuelly enduryd vnto Cristis tēporall natiuyte
/ This declaryth the Mayster of the storyes
who so lyste to se it. ¶Now the fyrste of thyse grete
preestis or Bysshops hauynge rule of the people.
was this Ihūs the sone of Iosedech A man of grete
zele. &amp; deuowte obedyence vnto god / so yt he was
conuenyently namyd Ihūs. helper or sauer of ye peple
by deuowte obedyence. leuynge example to alle
preestys. prelates in especyall to beere deuowte obedience
vnto almyghty god. &amp; teche other the same
For whan it pleysid our lorde to haue his people releuyd
from theyr captiuyte. &amp; his temple in Ihrl
                  •
               m
to be reedifyed to his honour &amp; praysyng: he cōmittid
therof the rule vnto Zorobabel sone to Salat
                  •
               
               ell.
&amp; to this Ihū the sone of Iosedech / as in ye prophecy
of Agge playnly dooth appere. Declarid at
large in the fyrste boke of 
                  •
               ldre. the fyrste. thirde.
&amp; syxte chapytours. ¶And full conuenyently was
this besynes cōmyttid vnto thise two men of auctoryte
&amp; honour / For of y• one. that is of Zorobabel
our Ihūs. our sauyour descendyd by his temporall

natiuyte. as it apereth in the fyrst chapitre of Mathewe.
¶The other. that is Ihūs Iosedech preparyd
the people by due obedyence. truly to serue god
in this materyall Temple whyche they thenne to
goddis honoure reedifyed / but more v
                  •
               rely to serue
god in the temple of Crystis holy body whyche he
toke of Zorobabell. and was in it togyder god and
man in one persone / Of whiche holy temple of his
body. hymselfe sayd. the seconde chapytre of Iohn / 
¶Dissolue ye this temple. &amp; wythin thre dayes I
shall reyse it agayn. &amp; soone after foloweth. Thyse
wordes sayd our sauyour Ihū Cryst of the temple
of his holy body. Of whiche holy temple of cristis
body was spirytually vnderstonde the prophecy
of Agge. in the seconde chapytre. ¶Ferre gretter
sayth this prophete. shall be the glory of this seconde
temple. than was of the fyrste buylded by Salomon
/ Spyrytually I saye For the letter full harde
it is. to expowne of this temple reedifyed bi Ihū Iosedech.
Zorobabell &amp; other Iewes. Sy
                  •
                this second
temple was neuer half so gloryous as was that fyrste
buylyed by Salomon. ne in buyldyng ne 
                  •
               et in
aparell as Iosephus declareth / For in y• fyrst temple
was conteyned the arke of the olde testament.
in it concernyng the tables of the lawe. Manna &amp;
the rodde of Aaron. whiche flourisshid &amp; fructifyed
by myracle. The appostle this declareth to the Hebreos
the .ix. chapytre. Many also precyous Iewels
&amp; tresours were in that temple born awaye by Nabugodonosor.

and Nabuzardan his capytayn / as it
apereth in the fourth boke of the kynges. the finall
&amp; finall but on̄ chapitours. whiche wer neuer fully
restored ayen in the reedifycacōn of ye same temple
able it. that Cirus &amp; Darius many grete thynges
restoryd to the seconde reedifycacyon as it is declaryd
the fyrste boke of Esdre the fyrste &amp; syxte chapytours
/ So y• this seconde temple was no thynge
lyke vnto the fyrste ne in buyldynge ne in garnysshyng:
Wherfore holy cristen doctours as saynt Ierom
&amp; Bede expowne this prophecye to the letter / 
That gretter shall be the seconde glory of this seconde
hous than of fyrste / ¶For as moche as Criste
god &amp; man. Many wyses thys seconde temples
with his holy presence dyde dedicate &amp; inourne / For
in to this Temple by his holy vyrgyn &amp; moder at
her purifycacōn he was offryd vnto god / In this
Temple his holy moder fonde hym in myddes of
doctours. From this temple he droue oute byars &amp;
sellers / In this temple he often prayed. prechyd. &amp;
many myracles shewed. grete thenne was y• glory
of this holy hous. &amp; ferre gretter than euer was the
glory of Salomons temple. sy
                  •
                our sauyour Crist
Ihūs this second temple so many wayes made holy
&amp; gloryous / ¶Thenne to my purpoos I saye y•
this grete preest &amp; bysshop Ihūs Iosedech was full
conuenyently namyd Ihūs an helper or sauer of y•
people by his holy &amp; zelose obedyence / For whe: as
the people of god longe tyme in captiuyte of Babylon.

confusyon by interpretacōn. were after their
custome falle in to ydolatry. worshipyng fals ydoles.
&amp; mawmettes: and so had lost theyr due obedience
vnto almyghty god: Folowynge the wyckyd
lawes of Gentiles. This grete preest &amp; bysshop acordynge
to his offyce &amp; duety. with helpe of Zorobabell
the true prynce &amp; seruaunt of god. as tymely
as they had lycence of Cirꝰ &amp; Dariꝰ to retorne home.
and to reedifye. the temple of god: what obedience
was in this holy bysshop. ye &amp; wyth dylygence
also to brynge the people to the true &amp; faste obedyence
of god. the fyrste boke of Esdre playnly dooth
declare / ¶So y• hymselfe was fully obedyent vnto
almgyghty goddys wyl. and taughte al the people
to the same / As it doth appere as well of the spedy
buyldynge of the temple / as of ympnes. oblacyon
                  •
               
sacrifyces. with other praysynges of god / whiche he
&amp; the Leuites at his cōmaundement. shewed &amp; made
vnto goddis worshyppe &amp; praysynge. Fyrste in
settynge the fundacyon of the sayd temple. as it is
declaryd the fyrste boke of Esdre the thyrde chapytre.
¶Zorobabell sayth he the sone of Salatiel. &amp;
Ihūs the sone of Iosedech. &amp; other of ther brethern
preestes &amp; Leuites and all the resydue of Iewes delyuerde
from captyuyte ordeynyd Leuites from .xx
yeres age &amp; aboue. to suruey the artifycers gadered
to the newe buyldynge of this temple. that they dyde
not neclygently theyr labour. Iosue also. whiche
was Ih
                  •
               s Iosedech. wyth his chyld
                  •
               n &amp; bredern.

as one man of one mynde &amp; herte dyde all theyr dilygence
to spede this holy werke. What Ioye what
gladnesse was there made bi this holy Ih
                  •
               s. &amp; other
the seruauntes of god by his example &amp; techynge.
at the settynge of the fundacōn of this seconde tē
               ple.
there forthwt appereth. ¶All the people sayth
Esdras there gadryd. cryed wyth grete voys to goddys
prasynge / for as moche as the fundacōn of the
temple was sette. Many also of y• olde faders whiche
had seen the temple of Salomon stondynge. &amp;
this temple now begyn. wepte wyth an hyghe voys
/ And many there present lyfte theyr voyces in
Ioye &amp; gladnes. Suche agmixcōn was there of crie
amonge the people to goddys praysynge / that noo
man myght discerne the voyces of wepers. from y•
voyces of Ioyfull people. so y• all enioyed in god.
Of this appereth morally. that one vertuous prelate
dooth moche good in crystis chyrche / as well for
his owne vertue &amp; zelose obedyence vnto the lawe
of god: as in ledynge other men 
                  •
               o do the same by
his holy doctryne and vertuous example. ¶Agayn
where this buyldynge of the temple was interruptid
in ye tyme of Cambises sone vnto Cirꝰ. whom
some callyd Assuerꝰ. some Arthazarses / But in the
tyme of Cambises was it. yt the werke of god. this
buyldynge went not forwarde / but lettyd was it by
fals accusars / whyche neuer cesse in the chyrche of
Cryste to lette the werkes of god / as dayly experyence
dooth shewe: Whan Darius kynge of Babibilon

inspyred by god the seconde yere of his reyne
gaue lycence vnto the Iewes to perfourme the temple
of god begon. And foundid at the lycence &amp; cō
               maundement
of Cirus / what obedyence / what dylygence
/ what zele. this Ihūs Iosedech. wyth ye prestys.
Leuites &amp; all the people had. to perfourme this
holy temple to goddys worshyp &amp; praysynge. Ye &amp;
what Ioye &amp; loouyng was geuen to god in dedicacōn
of the same temple: in the syxte chapytre of the
fyrste boke of Esdre playnly dooth appere. ¶Some
men here present. ye &amp; not a fewe. woll perauenture
muse / why &amp; to what entent I brynge in thys
longe story of Ihūs Iosedech. the grete preest of ye
olde lawe / Surely this is my cause / For syth al holy
scripture is wryten for our erudicōn after y• apost
                  •
               e
the .xv. chapytre to the Romayns / That we to
whom trouthe is made open by Ihū Cryste. as techeth
saynt Iohn in the fyrste chapytre. sholde lern
obedience. lerne zele &amp; dilygence to the lawe of god
of thyse faders passyd in fygure. And agayn to take
grete sham̄ &amp; conscyence whan we rede them to
haue doon so zelously in goddys cause. And beholde
ourself. how neclygent we ben in the same / For
cursyd is he whyche dooth the werkes of god fraudelently.
after Ieremye. the .xlviij. chapytre. They
buylded. we distroye. they gadryd. we disperge. they
curyd. we kylle. They made. we marre. I woll no
man accuse / but loke on our dedes. and behold theyrs.
and ye shall fynde that there is noo comparyson

bytwene lyghte and derkenesse. ¶Thenne haue
we here of two namyd by thys name. Ihūs of
laudable memory in the scrypture of god. The fyrsste
was Ihūs Naue. helper and sauer of the people
by myghte &amp; power. The seconde was Ihūs Iosedech.
sauer of the seruauntes of god by deuowte
obedyence / as now hath be declared / The thyrde
of laudable memory of the same name was Ihūs
filius Sirach. the sone of Sirach. sonnys sone vnto
Ihū Iosedech / as hymself rehercyth in his Prologe
of the boke namyd by hym Ecclesiasticus.
¶And full conuenyently was thys fader namyd
Ihūs. an helper or sauer of the people (ꝑ sapienciā
by his grete wysdom geuen vnto hym of god. and
by hym taughte to the people. vnto the worldes ende.
by reason of his laudable wysdom left behynde
hym in wrytyng in the boke of wysdom callyd Ecclesiasticus.
whyche boke. hymself fyrste made and
wrote in Hebrewe tonge. and after translatyd the
same in to Grekes tonge / As. Ysodorus declaryth
and sheweth in the syxte boke of his Ethemologyse
/ ¶For the declaracōn and expownynge of thys
trouthe. expedient &amp; ryght necessary it is to knowe
and vnderstonde. what helpe and saluacōn. wysdome
doth vnto man. Where ye shall vnderstonde &amp;
marke in your mynde That oonly man of creatures
vnder heuen dyrectyth &amp; ordereth his actes and
dedes by hys vnderstondynge to hys ende naturall
or supernaturall / Thus I saye. to the entent. it is / 

or thus it sholde be. Now for as moche as mannes
vnderstondyng is radically corrupte by synne. and
so by ignoraunce. whiche is the moder of errour a
                  •
               
               ter
saynt Iohn Crisostom the .xxv. Omelye of hys
Imperfyte werke on Mathu. expedyent it is therfore.
y• man erre not from his ende. naturally. or supernaturally
intendyd: that his vnderstondyng be
dyrected by some redy lyghte / This lyghte at philosophers
is comynly namyd the lyght of wysdom
And therfor naturally men desyre cūnynge &amp; wisdom.
as sayth Aristotle in the begynnynge of hys
Metaphisyke That euery man naturally desireth
to knowe / for the more y• 
               
                  •
               ny man hath of of wisdome
the better shall he dyrecte all his dedes to a due
ende. the lesse he hath of wysdom. the worse he shal
directe his dedes: but comynly erre. And very wyse
men comynly ordre wel al theyr dedes &amp; neuer erre
And for this cause. that men wolde not erre from
theyr ende. ye naturally entendyd. what zele &amp; besynesse
olde faders had to atteyne wisdom / wonder
it is to rede. as at large declareth saynt Ierom in
his epistle (ad paulinū) the prologe of the Byble it
is / ¶We rede sayth saynt Ierom in old storyes. many
men haue soughte ferre countrees. straunge nacyns.
&amp; passid ryght peryllous sees / that they myghte
speke famyliarly with suche philosophers. whose
werkes thei befor tyme had rad. to lerne of them
wysdom / This dyde bothe Pictagoras &amp; Plato. of
whom sayth saynt Ierom in the same place (Suche

zele had Plato to wysdom and cunnynge. that
he folowyd scyence in al the worlde / as though scyence
had fledde from him. And on a tyme was he
taken bi pirates in the see. &amp; solde to Denyse y• grete
tyraunt / yet for as moche as he was a philosofer
a louer of cūnynge &amp; wysdom. he was more of pryce
than the tyraunt that boughte hym. syth by reason
of his cūnynge. he cowde more temperatly bere
hymself in all aduersyte than hys mayster &amp; souerayne
hym hauynge in seruytude) There shewyth
forth saynt Ierom of Titus Liuiꝰ. of Appoloniꝰ.
&amp; other wise men of the worlde in grete &amp; profounde
wysdom &amp; lernyng. How theyr fame of cū
               nyng
&amp; wysdom. droue men from the ferthest party
of the worlde. to here them. to lerne of them wysdome.
wherby they myghte surely ordre theyr actes
&amp; dedes to a perfyte ende. and not erre from the same
/ This labour &amp; besynesse sayth saynt Ierom. 
                  •
               oke
gentyl phylosophers oonly lenyng vnto ye lyghte
of reason. and wyth fayth no thynge Indowed / 
¶And of this wysdom to be atteyned by mannes
Inquisicōn. Aristotle one of the grete enserchers. of
the same: sayd there were two kyndes or parties. in
the syxte boke of his Ethikis. That one is callyd
Prudence. the other Sapyence. ¶Prudence▪ after
him is a wisdom to lede man that he erre not from
his resonable ende intendid in worldly occupacōn &amp;
besynesse. ¶And Sapyence after hym stondeth in
speculacōn of highe &amp; presume causes. so that sapience

is a wysdome to lede man y• he erre not from
his ende naturally after Aristotle / but in very dede
supernaturally ententyd / And in this sapyence after
him restyth mannys felycyte. In so moche y• he
myghte atteyne to sapyence. at his opynyon was
(felix) blessyd or happy. For he sholde not erre from
truthes necessary to his blysse &amp; perfyte ende. ¶&amp;
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                able it thise philosofers dide moche to atteyne ther
entent &amp; purpose. not to erre from the ende: yet fayled
they ofte tymes therof. whyche appereth as wel
of theyr errours abowte the laste &amp; perfyte ende. as
of theyr errours abowte meanes ledynge to the same
ende / as declareth Aristotle in the fyrste boke of
his Ethikis / Where he sheweth that some put ther
fynall ende in ryches. some in cōcupiscence. som̄ 
               
                  〈◊〉
               
honour. &amp; other transytory pleysures. whyche may
not endure: but must nedes faylle / Yet were thyse
callyd &amp; acount
                  •
               d wyse men in the worlde / And 
                  •
               uche
wyse men. that for theyr wysdom. they ben of
Immortall fame amonge worldly men. &amp; callyd
Sapientes. wyse men. se
                  •
               in by excellence. yet fayllyd
they &amp; erryd from the 
                  ••
               outhe / For neyther by
theyr prudence. ne yet theyr 
                  •
               apyence. ladde they or
themself. or theyr folowers to the ryghte &amp; perfyte
ende naturall. or supernaturall ¶Then̄e was none
of this Ihūs) ꝑ sapienciā) the helper or sauer of
man to lede hȳ by wysdom to his right ende. The
second cause of this errour declareth y• apostle Poule
in y• fyrste chapytre to the Romayns / This philosofers

erred sayth saynt Poul / ¶For whan they
knewe god: they worshypt not hy as theyr. god / but
wanysshid in theyr proude reasons. &amp; callyng them
self wyse men. were foolys in dede / But a q
                  •
               estion
is this / How knewe thyse philosofers god: the apostle
ansuereth in the same place. The Inuisible misteryes
of god sayth he be knowe of man. ye cheif creature
of this worlde. by other smaller &amp; lower creatures
of the same / But how vanysshid thyse philosofers.
how erred they: For sothe for they gaue not
due thankes to god theyr maker &amp; geuer of ther benefytes.
Sayth saynt Austin on this letter / ¶Thyse
philosofers sawe the ende of all creatures: knewe
there was one god by the lyghte of reason / but vnkynde
vnto ther maker y• gaue to them this knowlege:
ascribed to themself proudly ther knowlege &amp;
wysdom / &amp; for theyr pryde: lost ther true knowlege
&amp; made both blynde &amp; errynge from trouth. accordyng
vnto y• prophe
                  •
               ye of Ab
                  •
               y. y• fyrste chapytre.
rehercyd by the apostle ye fyrst epistle. &amp; fyrst chapitre
vnto the Corinthees. I shall sayth god by hys
prophete. distroye &amp; brynge to nought y• sapience of
sapient men: &amp; I shall reproue &amp; brynge in confusyon
the prudence of prudent men of this worlde. In
whyche wordes god Ioyneth 
                  •
               ogyders sapience &amp;
prudence of this world. shewyng yt they ne yet ony
of them. ledeth or helpeth man to hys perfyte ende
And forwt sheweth thapostle in y• same place. what
sapience. &amp; what prudence it is. y• redily ledeth man

to his perfyte ende. yt he ne erre abowte the ende. ne
yet in meanes to y• same. ¶It plesyd god sayth the
apostle. by prechyng of his holy gospell &amp; wysdom
ther wt in conteyned 
                  •
               at the worlde acoūtyd folyssnes.
euerlastyngly to saue all tho. whiche therunto
geue fast &amp; stronge fayth. accordyng vnto the wordes
of our sauyour. in y• laste chapytre of Marke.
Preche ye sayde Cryste to his discyples my gospell
to all men &amp; wȳmen. say ye vnto them / y• he whiche
truly bileuyth &amp; is baptized. shalbe euerlastyngly
saued / ¶So yt in the scrypture of god is wryten
true wysdom conteynyng perfyte prudence. &amp; perfyte
sapience Prudence to directe euery man in this
worlde lyuynge. y• he erre not in worldly actes &amp; besinesse.
Sapience / y• he erre not in his finall ende. &amp;
truthes to the same required. Fulgens in his sermon
of Confessours this shewyth at large ¶In holy
scrypture is conteyned both mylke for yonge chyldn.
&amp; substancyall meete for men / yt is to saye (easy
lernyng for begȳners: &amp; profoūde wisdom for men
of cūnynge) It folowyth. there is doctryne conuenyent.
for eueri aege. for euery state. for eueri condicōn
&amp;
                  •
               
               ̄ / This holy &amp; ghostly wisdom was it. yt good fads
euer desyred to haue. yt they with lyghte. myghte
passe thrugh this worlde in suche astates as the
                  •
               
stode on. wythoute errour or offence to god. and fynally
theyr supernaturall ende. to whyche ende. y•
wysdome of the worlde myghte neuer lede the hauer
/ ¶ As of Salomon▪ we rede in the thyrde

boke and thyrde chapytre of the kynges. whyche cō
               maūded
by god to aske him what petycōns he wol
de &amp; it sholde be grauntyd. askyd of god on̄ly wysdom
to ordre hymself &amp; his people to goddis pleysure
god gaue hym wysdom aboue all mortall men / 
as appereth in the fourth chapitre of the same boke.
¶Almyȝty god sayth he gaue vnto Salomon
plenteuous abundance of sapience &amp; prudence. And
wyth this wysdom. came generally all other profitable
goodes. ¶The wysdome of this prynce was
so grete. that the people of ferre countrees came to
seke hym. &amp; lerne of hym wysdom: Some in Iugementes
Some to ordre well theyr reames or housholdes.
some to ordre themselfe to goddis pleysure / 
In somoche that (regina Saba) the noble pryncesse
heryng the merueyllous wysdom of Salomon. came
out of ferre countrees. to here &amp; lerne of his wysdom
/ as it is open the thyrde boke of the kynges ye
x. chapytre / ¶Of whyche apperyth that this ghostly
&amp; godly wysdom of olde tyme was gretly desyrid
of grete men. of meane men. of eueri astate / For
by this wysdom they myghte ordre all theyr lyues
to goddis pleysure. knowe theyr ende. atteyne theyr
ende. not be ignoraunt ne yet erre abowte theyr ende.
ne meanes to the same / This worlde is goon &amp;
in effecte tornyd vp &amp; downe / For where somtyme
men 
                  •
               oughte for ghostly wysdom to saue theyr soules.
Now laboureth eueri man in effecte for worldly
wysdom / For now from the hyghest to the lowest.

euery man studyeth in auarice. and from ye prophete
to the preeste euery man dooth gyle &amp; sleyght
Ieremy. the. vi. chapytre. yf they labour for wysoo
me of cūnynge &amp; knowlege as dyde Phylosophres
of whom I spake aboue. of whom sayth the apostle
the fyrste chapytre of the fyrste epistle to ye Corinthees
¶Iewes aske sygnes &amp; Grekes wysdom
somwhat were it. ye &amp; somwhat cōmendable were
it. For after Aristotles cūnynge &amp; wysdom is. acoū
               tid
amonge goodes honourable / But this wysdom
is goon. also. Men force neyher of ghostly wysdom
ne yet of seculare wysdom. callyd scyence &amp; cūnynge
/ But on̄ly wyse men ben acounted in this worlde.
whiche can fynde subtyll &amp; crafty meanes to gete
goodes. playne falsnesse in englysshe / ¶Whoos
ende is euerlastynge dethe. and god is glorifyed in
theyr confusyon whyche sauour alle of the worlde.
wryten to the Philipenses the thyrde chapytre / 
¶Now to my purpoos. I saye this man Ihūs filius
Sirach of laudable memory. was conuenyently
callyd Ihūs. an helper or sauer of the people by
his grete wysdom. whyche wysdom / what worldly
nay ghostly. He fyrst taughte. &amp; thenne left in wrytyng.
wherby man may duely ordre his lyfe to hys
ende naturall &amp; supernaturall. &amp; neyther to be ignoraunt
ne erre abowte the same. or ony of the same.
as in the processe of the boke namyd Ecclesiasticꝰ
of his wrytynge and translacion as I sayd aaboue
playnly dooth appere. In whyche boke sayth

saynt Ierom. this holy fader ledyth and persuadyth
men in this mortall lyfe to the zele and loue
of wysdom / as wysdom conteyneth all vertues / 
Soo that in the techynge and declarynge of wysdom.
he taughte all vertues / and how man sholde
euery maner wyse lyue vertuously / wherby he myghte
redily and surely atteyne his ende. and therof
erre ne fayle.
            Now is there here shewed you from the begynnynge
of thre men of laudable memory conuenyently
namyd by this name Ihūs / for eche of them in his
tyme. was an helper or sauer of the people. The
tyrste by power. The seconde by obedyence. And y•
thyrde by wysdom / as it hath now be declaryd: yet
was ther none of y• thre (
                  •
               p̄e thūs qui a
                  •
               pinquās
that ꝓū illis) The same Ihūs whyche nyghynge.
walkyd with mankynde / but rather fygures or ser
               
                  •
               aūtes
of the same Ihūs. of the essenciall Ihūs. of
the very true Ihūs / whyche is the sone of god and
man / ¶And that I shewe this / For where as eche
of theym was conuenyently namyd Ihūs. that is
to say
                  •
               . an helper or sauer of the people by vertues
perticulare / as that one was by power. that other
by obedyence / and the thyrde by wysdom / Yet was
there not one of thyse thre. whyche had alle thyse
vertues / neyther ony of theym plenarily / but by partycipacyon
of oure Ihūs Cryste / ¶Of whoos fulnesse
and abundaunce we all haue receyued dyuers
vertues and manyfolde gracyous yeftes. the fyrste

chapytre. of Iohn. Ihūs Naue had power: but (al
mensurā) at a melure. Ihūs Iosedech had obedyence:
but (and mensurā) So had Ihūs Sirach wisdom
(ad mensuram) in a mesure as god gaue vnto
hym / Būt Ihūs Cryste was (plenus g
                  •
               e &amp; veritatis)
the fyrst chapytre of Iohn. almyghty of power
perfyte of obedyence. And full. ye infenyte of wysdom.
So that y• same our Ihūs gaue power is Iosue.
obedyence to Ihūs Iosedech. And ghostly wysdom
to Ihūs Sirach / ¶For at his hyghe worde al
thynges were made: He cōmaūdid. &amp; all creatures
were create &amp; brought forth of nought. the. C. xlviij
psalme / Thenne of this▪ Ihūs our sauyour Cryste
purpoos I to talke wyth his mercy (Om̄ ip̄e 
                  •
               hūs
aꝓpinquans that cū illis) The same Ihūs nyghyng
walkyd wyth mankynde. ¶In whyche wordes
I sayd there be two partyes to be declaryd. conteynynge
two notable truthes. The fyrste is. y• the
same Ihūs hath nyghed to mankynde. The seconde
is. that the same Ihūs hath walkid with mankynde
/ And of thyse two. foloweth as a corelary. y•
thirde trouth. that the same Ihūs hath fynally brought
mankynde to euerlastyng reste in heuen. and
in this hath shewed himself to be very Ihūs. y• perfyte
sauyour of mankynde. ¶He nyghed I saye to
mankynde (ꝑ potenciā) by his almyghty power. He
walkyd wt man (ꝑ obediēciā) by perfyte obedyence
And fynally broughte man to reste &amp; blysse (ꝑ sapienciā)
by his Infinyte wysdom. Fyrste I say our

sauiour Ihūs hath nyghed to mankynde by his almyghty
power thre wayes (creando. nascendo. mi
                  •
               
               nistrando)
by his acte of creacōn. by his acte of Incarnacōn.
&amp; by his holy mynystracōn. whyche thre
wt our lordis mercy I shal shewe you in this fyrst
party. And wyth all. how mankynde hath euer &amp;
contynually be way warde. &amp; goo from god. ¶Of
whiche wyl appere the goodnesse of god. &amp; the vnkyndnesse
of man. ¶Fyrst I say our sauyour Cryste
nyghed vnto man by his almyghty power in y•
acte of creacōn / To whoos declaracōn I shal shew
you thre conclusyons. Fyrste wherin stondeth y• acte
of creacion. Seconde yt Ihūs Crys
                  •
               e the eternall
sone of god the fader. excersyced &amp; shewed this acte
as well on man. as on al other creatures. And, thyrde
how in executynge of this acte. he nyghed vnto
man. ¶Fyrste in this party. ye shall vnderstonde / 
that (c
                  •
               eare est ex nichilo aliꝙ facere) after the mayster
of the sentence in the begynnyng of the seconde
boke. The acte of creacyon is to brynge forth a
substaunce of noughte. that is to say. of no thynge
forgoynge. ne matere. ne fourme. / This is callyd
properly the acte of creacōn after the mayster. all be
it largely taken Creacōn maye be where as is matere
forgoynge in makynge a newe fourme of noughte
/ As the resonable soule of man is dayly create
of god. And ryseth not ony power of the matere
syth by creacōn she is infoundyd from god in
to the body of man. and in her infusion she is create

of god / ¶This acte of creacōn oonly apperteyneth
vnto almyghty power. or power of itself infinyte
/ Soo that no lymyte ne determynate power.
maye ony wyse in this acte of creacyon / that is to
brynge forthe oughte ofnoughte. Sayde therfore
gentyll philosofers oonly consyderynge determynate
&amp; lymyte powers / That of noo thynge. can noo
thynge be made. ne euery thynge: of euery thynge / 
but of determynate thyng
                  •
               s: maye other determynate
thynges be broughte forth / so that they denyed
creacōn. and put oonly naturall produccōn. And
no wond though they this wyse erryd / for they neyther
consydred ne yet graunted ony almyȝty powwer.
ne actually Infinyte / For after theyr oppynyons.
there is no thynge actually infinyte / But surely
they vanysshyd &amp; erryd in theyr thouhtes. they
were amasyd in theyr myndes not knowyng their
almyghty maker whiche made al creatures of noughte.
/ It is not that thynge that I woll dyspute
wyth them / ¶But to vs all of crystis relygyon &amp;
holy fayth: ynough it is to confesse that there is an
acte of creacōn / whyche is to brynge forth a substaunce
of no matere fore goynge. and that immedyatly
/ Whyche acte is the acte of all myghty power
oonly to god belongyng. The mayster of the sentence
the fyrste distynccōn of the seconde boke this
declareth. puttynge there dyuersyte atwyxe Creare
&amp; Facere. creacōn &amp; faccōn. ¶Creatour sayth he is
whyche of noo thynge makyth somwhat. so yt this

act of creacōn properly is to make ought of nought
Facere. y• is to make. it is not oonly to make ony
thynge of nought: but of some fore goynge matere.
So y• bothe angell &amp; man ben namyd Factours / 
but not creatours / For this name of creacōn is on̄ly
to god belongynge. whiche makyth some thynges
of nought: And som̄ thynges he makyth of ought
yt is to saye of a matere forgoyng. all be it in holy

                  •
               crypture. thyse names ben often take. the one for y•
other. as the creatour for the factour. ye &amp; many tymes
the factour for the creatour. ¶Thenne haue
we fyrste in this party. wherin stondeth the acte of
creacōn: I saye in the acte of almyghty power. whiche
is to bryng forth ought of nought. on̄ly to god
belongynge. ¶The seconde conclusyon is in this
party to be declaryd. yt our eternall Ihūs. the sone
naturall of god the fader euerlastynge. excersyced
this acte or dede of creacōn / This trouthe declaryd
Moyses the grete prophete of god. Gen. prio. ye firste
chapitre of Gen) (In principio inqd creauit deꝰ
celū &amp; terrā) Almyghty god sayth he. fader. sone. &amp;
holy ghost. thre persones. &amp; one god at the begynȳ
               ge
made heuen &amp; erth of nought ¶Of whiche wordes
apereth. yt the outwarde ac
                  •
                or dedes of y• holy
trynyte be indiuisible. &amp; therfor is this act of creacyon.
rather sayd her of a terme essēcial than ꝑsonal
as whan Moyses sayth. god create &amp; not ye 
               fad. son̄
&amp; holy ghost And yet the fader dyde create. so dyde
the sone. &amp; so dyde the holy ghost. And yet not thre

creatours / 
                  •
               t on̄e creatour. as not thre almyghte
                  ••
               
but one almyghty. ne thre goddis / but one god. ¶y•
and on
                  •
                man doubte where thys acte of creacōn: be
to the sone of god Ihū Criste apperteynynge &amp; belongynge
/ as to true crysten men is no doubte: goo
to the gospell of Iohn. &amp; there ye shall fynde it playnly
expressyd. Fyrste by his secretary saynt Iohn.
&amp; after by hymself / Saynt Iohn purposyng to declare
of Crystys holy diuynyte. begynneth in thys
wyse (In principio erat verbū. et ve
                  •
               bū erat apud
deū. &amp; deus erat verbū) The sone of god sayth he
was euerlastyngly in the fader. with the fader. and
one god with the fader. To stonde moche in declaracōn
of this letter. I truste it nedyth not / For euery
good crysten man here vnderstondeth. y• verbū)
is Ihūs Cryste the eternall sone of god. of whom
folowyngly in the same chapitre sayth saynt Iohn
(Ex verbū caro factū est &amp; habitauit in nob, The
sone of god eternall is become man sayth he &amp; hathe
gracyously made his habitacōn wt vs. / Whan
saynt Iohn had sayd. deꝰ erat verbū) The sone of
god was euerlastyngly god. it folowith (hoc erat in
principio apud deū) Vppon whyche wordes sayth
Hillarius the holy bysshop / as though saynt Iohn
sholde saye / This essenciall worde or sone of god y•
fader. was neuer from god the fader separate ne diuyded
/ Thenne to shewe his almyȝty power egall
wyth the fader: he addyth forthwyth Oia ꝑ ip̄m
facta (sūt) Alle creatures sayth he were create by the

sone of god. The apostle callyth hym therfore in y•
fyrste chapytre to the Hebrees. the bryghtnes &amp; glory
of the fader. bi whom the fader creatyd all creatures.
¶Oour sauyour Cryste hymself declareth y•
same. the fy
                  •
               the chapytre of Iohn. My fader sayth
he werketh vnto now. and I werke vnto now. Here
sayth saynt Austyn. as though Cryst sholde say.
By me all thynges be made. The fader of heuen
made lyghte: but he sayenge made it / yf he sayd &amp;
made lyghte: thenne folowyth that bi his worde he
made it. And I am his eternall worde. thenne by
me he made lyghte / My fader thenne wroughte &amp;
made whan he create the worlde. &amp; vnto now werkyth
in guydynge the worlde / Thenne foloweth yt
by me he made whan he made. and by me he guydith
whan he guydeth. ¶Thenne haue we here in
this party fyrste wherin stondeth the acte of creacion.
where is shewed In om̄ipotencia) in almyghty
power. to brynge forth a substaunce of no thyng
ought of nought. ¶Seconde in this party is shewed.
that this acte of almyghty power. Ihūs Cryste
wyth the fader. &amp; the holy ghost one god. shewed &amp;
put in execucōn in y• formacōn &amp; fyrste makyng of
all creatures. ¶Now folowyngly &amp; thyrde in thys
party. shal I shewe you / &amp; this processe is specyally
to be notyd. how by thys acte of creacōn &amp; almyghty
power: our Sauyour Cryste nyghed vnto mankynde
/ Where ye shall vnderstonde That by thys
acte of creacōn. he nyghed vnto mankynde dyuersly.

That is to saye bothe generally and specyally / 
Ge
                  •
               erally / for as he lefte in alle creatures (vestigium)
a sygne or a 
                  •
               oken of hys hondwerke. So left
he in mankynde a sygne of his handwerke. as in
famylyar ensample / Yf a man steppe in snowe or
sonde. after his departyng remayneth a steppe. So
after the act of creac
                  •
               n remayneth behynde y• hond
werke of god in the creature. Sygnefyenge that
god is therof the dooer / This is a generall nyghinge
of god to all creatures / For in all creatures app
                  •
               
               ryth
his handwerke. that they ben of god create &amp;
made / ¶But in this acte of creacōn of man. apperyth
how specyally god hath nyghed vnto man bi
his almyghty power. For where as in all creatures
he lefte destigium) a generall sygne or token. In
man he lefte ouer thys (ymaginem &amp; similitudin
                  •
               
suam his propre ymage &amp; symylitude. The fyrste
chapytre of Genes. sayd god the fader vnto the sone
&amp; the holy ghost. ¶Make we man to our ym age
&amp; symplytude. And it folowyth Almyghty god
create man vnto his ymage and symylitude. A g
                  ••
               
               te
dignyte is this / yf it were dylygently consydryd
Wherin this ymage and symplitude stondeth D
                  •
               
               dareth
the mayster of the sentence the .xvi. dy
                  ••
               y
                  •
               ccōn
of the seconde boke. ¶Man sayth he was made
to the ymage and symylytude of god in his soule.
wherin he excellyth alle vnresonable creatures / 
But to the ymage of god was he made by reason
of his memory. vnderstondynge. and wyll. To the

symylitude of god. by reason of Innocency. Iustyce
and other vertues morall. in whiche man was made
and created by the alle myghty power of god. in
his soule. of goddys goodnesse. not of or fore ony
mannys decerte or merytes / Thenne here appereth
That by this act of creacōn. god gretly nyghed vnto
man bothe generally &amp; specyally. ¶Ye and ouer
this. god dyuerse wayes nyghed vnto man by thys
sayde acte of creacion. as that god thenne beganne
fyrste to be lorde vnto man. and man seruaunt vn
to god / As declareth saynt Iohn Crisostom in a sermon
begynnynge. ¶The dygnyte of mannes condycyon
is soone knowen. dylygently consydred the
sublymyte and heyghte of god his maker. &amp;
                  •
               .
            ¶Ouer this god nyghed vnto mankynde 
                  •
               per illapsum
gracie specialis▪ bi his inspyred grace. to al
men generally in geuynge vnto them the lawe of
kynde / wryten in enery mannys herte. and stondinge
in thyse pryncyples / that is to saye▪ Do vnto thi
neyghbour as thou woldest be doon vnto / And doo
to noo man that thynge whyche thou woldest not
it were doon vnto the / ¶Ye but to some men god
gaaf specyall grace / as to that Iust and ryghtwysman
Abel. the fyrste cheyf &amp; pryncypal membre of
his cytee in erthe. and to other faders. his electe and
chosen predestynate seruauntes. whyche alle stode
in his specyall grace. and acceptable fauoure. For
they yeldid vnto hym theyr creatour kyndnesse for
kyndnesse / ¶Who so lust well and studyously consydre

the ordre of holy scrypture vnto the Incarnacion
of our sauyour Cryste Ihesu / where I shal declare
how he nyghed vnto man by the acte of hys
Incarnacion: shall moost plenteuously fynde. how
from the fyrste of the creacyon of man. oure moost
mercyfull lorde Ihūs Cryste our sauyour / as the tyme
passyd from the fyrste creacyon of the worlde.
euer more &amp; more nyghed vnto mankynde. leuyng
wyth hym certeyn remembraunce and tokens that
his mercyful lorde god had ben with man. vysyted
man. and wyth his manyfolde graces nyghed vnto
man / For by cause man sholde agayn▪ nyght vnto
hym. and yelde vnto hym kyndnesse for kyndnesse
/ ¶ As to Abrahaam he gaaf Circumsicion
signaculum fidei) A very and perfyghte token of
true fayth whyche man sholde beere vnto hrs lorde
god. The seuententh chapitre of Genes. god wonderly
and kyndly nyghed vnto man by this mystery
/ For this was a very sacrament takynge awaye
orygynall synne. As now dooth the sacrament of
of Baptysme. exceptynge that Circūmsicion dyde
not open the gates of heuen / For as atte that tyme
the pryce was not payed of our sauiour Crist-Ihūs
moost precyous blood and dethe / ¶This declareth
and shewyth the mayster of the sentence. the fyrste
dystynccyon of the fourth boke.
            ¶God also gaue after this by his holy prophete
Moyses a lawe wryten to makynde as playnly
dooth appere in the Penteteuch. In the whyche

lawe he nyghed vnto man very gretly / For in this
he taughte man what he shold leue / what he shold
take / what he sholde refuce / what he sholde folow.
&amp; what he sholde fle. How man-sholde please god
wyth sacrifyces acceptable / whan̄e he were vnclene
or had offended / as y• bokes of Leuiticꝰ &amp; Numeri
doth shewe. Ye. &amp; in this nyghynge of god to man
he nygheth 
                  〈◊〉
                men specyally / as to Moyses.
to whom our 
                  〈◊〉
                spake very famyliarly / as frende
to frende. Whyche after holy doctours exposycōn
was in some hyghe creatur. the. xxxiiii. chapytre of
Exodꝰ / And from this tyme forwarde towarde his
holy Incarnacōn. god euer nighed vnto mankynde
more &amp; more. leuynge in dyuerse hys seruauntes
specyall tokens. that he had be wyth them / whyche
tokens remayne vnto this day / &amp; shal vnto y• worldes
ende / As the hyghe lyght of prophecy. &amp; certen
knowlege of thynges to come. In especyall the mistery
of his Incarnacōn with sequeles of the same.
¶Here is now declaryd how oure sauyour Cryste
Ihūs hath nyghed to mankynde by his almyghty
power in the acte of creacion. as well of man as of
all other creatures. &amp; soo vnto the tyme of his holy
Incarnacōn. how he nyghed to man more &amp; more.
leuyng contynually with man tokens that he had
be wyth hym. vysyted hym. &amp; doon a
                  •
               es helpynge
to the saluacōn of man / Of whyche well appere
                  •
               h
y• grete kyndnes of god shewed vnto man. ¶Now
in the other syde. god was neuer so towardly. ne so

nyghynge vnto man fro the begynnyng: but man
hath euer ben as vntowardly to god. &amp; weywarde
from him. and that shewe I this. God I sayd nyghed
to man by the acte of creacōn. syth he lefte in
mankynde (vestigium) as four me or effecte of hys
hond werke: but allo he left in man his propre. ymage
&amp; symylitude as I shewed aboue / by whythe ymage
&amp; symylitude. man myght suffyciently ordre
hymself to god. yeldyng to hym kyndnesse for kȳd
nesse / But forth with man was vnkynde. &amp; alway
warde from god: and loste his symylitude bi synne
Et in ymagīe ꝑtransit homo) the. xxxviij. psalme
Man now passeth thrugh this worlde in the ymage
of god: but his symylytude hath he loste. Vppon
whyche wordes y• prophete sayth Cassiodor / (Man
passith in this worlde) And true it is: syth in thys
worlde we haue noo dwellynge cyte / But where in
passyth man: surely in the ymage of god / And where
is yt holy symylitude of god to whyche man was
create: Where ben the vertues: where is grace: wher
ben other holy gyftes whyche lede man to euerlastyng
lyf: surely the wretchyd man by his synne lost
all this. whan he fell in to y• hondes of theues: whiche
robbyd man: woūdyd man. &amp; left hym but halfe
a lyue. Man was robbyd from his gyftes of grace:
&amp; sore woundyd in his naturall gyftes. in som
                  •
               
               che
that fro the fote vnto the heed was in man no
helthe / And yet that lytyll that was of ony vertue
or perfeccion. in the ymage it was vnderstondyng

memory. and wyll remayne soryly and full of affeccōns.
as we se in dayly experyence / But Innocency
Iustice. &amp; vertue be goon by synne. whyche causeth
suche abundace of wyckydnesse. as in thys worlde
cōtinually reyneth / but as man is remedy (in aqua
&amp; sp̄usancto) in ye water of baptym. &amp; the holy ghoste
in the same receyued. ¶Agayn I sayd that god
nyghed to man. geuyng hym for a token of the same.
the lawe of kynde. To loue thy neyghbour as
thyself. Caym wolde none of this token: but wronge
from god. slewe his innocent brother Abel. And
where he sholde haue nyghed vnto god agayne: he
fled from the face of god. as it is open the fourth
chapytre of Gen: and thenne dwellyd he in ye londe
callyd Nayde. by Interpretacion callyd fluctuacōn.
or vnstablynesse. And full conuenyently sayth
saynt Ierom in his epistle to Damasus. of y•. vij.
vengaūces of Caym / For he so departe &amp; go from
god sayth he: Anone his fete ben mouyd. that is to
saye. his affeccōns. and in al
                  •
               his wayes is made vnstable
/ ¶Of this folowyth a corelary or a mo
                  •
               all
erudycōn and lernynge. Whyche is so saye. y• synners
departyd from god: be very Inconstaunt and
ryghte chaungeable of theyr condycyons and maners.
But and yf that this be true. it sholde seme
That many one are separate and departyd from
god in this mortall worlde. And sholde seme that
there ben many synners / For moche Inconstaunce
is there in mennys condycyons and maners. and

moche chaunge in theyr clothynge. The one fol
                  •
               
               wyth
of the other comynly / For where as mennes
myndes ben inconstaunt to god or man. to y• prynce
or the comyn weele: there is neuer certente ne fastenesse.
Take this as ye lyst: but sure it is. y• synne
&amp; departyng from god is euer full of vnstablinesse
Thenne where so euer is moche vnstablynesse. sygne
it is. y• men ben fled from god &amp; woll not nyghe
vnto hym. as he doth to them. so they yelde vnkyndenesse
for kyndnesse. ¶I sayd ouer this. that god
nyghed vnto man geuyng hym a law
                  •••
               ryten bi
Moyses. willynge to be knowen for his god. for his
lorde 
                  •
                for his maker. sayenge vnto man / Thou
shalt geue adoracōn vnto thy lorde god. and wyth
this seruyce. serue hym oonly. Ye shall not make
vnto you goddis of god. ne of syluer / For I am on̄
               ly
god. the. xix. chapytre of Exodꝰ / ¶Came Ieroboham
the sone of Nabath. &amp; sayd playnly that god
was strange vnto him in this cōmaundement / and
was not so famylyare wyth man. ne so nyghe vnto
hym as he sholde be / And fyndynge a newe fals
way. made two calfes of golde. the. xij. chapytre of
the thyrde boke of kynges. And sayd vnto the children
of Israel (Ascende ye no more in to Ier
                  •
               m.) y•
glose) there to. do. worshyp vnto god For in Ierlm
was the temple of Salomon / in whiche almyghty
god was solempnely honoured. Thenne folowyth
in the same place the wordes of Ieroboham vnto
the people▪ Beholde Israel. thyse ben thy goddys

whyche delyuerde the from the seruytude of Egypte.
&amp;
                  •
               ) By this meane he broughte the poore foles
to ydolatry / And where as they sholde haue geuen
vnto god (cultū late) honour oonly due vnto god / 
they chaungid sayth Dauid the prophete the glory
of god in to the symylitude of a calfe etynge haye.
¶This was not the fyrste vnkyndnes &amp; way warnes
of ydolatry that I rede in scrypture. by whyche
god nyghynge to man was vnkyndely caste from
hym / For I fynde that bothe Abraham &amp; Tha
                  •
               e.
Moyses &amp; Aaron wyth many other holy faders.
were wyth this wretchydnesse of ydolatry greuously
trowblyd / But of Ieroboham I brynge this in
especyall / For he mayntenyd &amp; bare out the mater
&amp; sayd playnly That thyse were the grete Ioddys
that had doon to them all theyr grete benefytes / yt
brought them out of seruitute. &amp; put them in to liberte.
And in remembraunce herof. he sett
                  •
                one of
thyse ydolles in Bethel. &amp; a nother in Dan. whyche
after Rabi Salomon ben two hylles distyncte.
The one in the south party. &amp; the other in the northe
party. where the. x. tribus dwellyd / that from y•
mydyll partyes of the same. the people myghte att
theyr pleysure vysyte that. or y• ydoll / ¶Thys was
tuyn a meane to drawe (mobile wlgus) the Inconstaunt
people. to be vnkynde to god their maker. &amp;
lene vnto the deuyll theyr distroyer: And to brynge
his purpoos abowte: somwhat more dyde he / as folowith
in the letter
                  •
                
               
                  •
               m̄ fecit sacerdotes de extremis

pp
                  •
               i qui' non erat de filij
                  •
                leui) He made sayth
the glose preestes of euery trybe indifferently / For so
it was The tribe of Leui wold not consente to his
ydolatry / wherfore he sayd vnto the people That
it neded not take preestis oonly of the tribe of Leui
But it was suffycyent: That who so euer cowde
offre a solempne sacrifyce as Aaron dide in his cō
               secracōn.
that suche one myghte be preest wel ynough.
she forsyd not what prest he toke to make his
sacrifyce. were he good. were he bad. of whatso euer
kynne or condicōn he was. cūnynge or no cūnynge
al was one wyth him. And in sygne of this I sayd
he toke (sacerdotes de extremis ppli) I trowe y• bes
                  •
               e
englysshe here to He toke his preestes of y• worste
of the people. ¶God cōmaundyd. there sholde be
no preest in his lawe. ne mynystre his sacrifyce: but
he were of the tribe of Leui. The. v
                  •
               ij. chapytre of
Numeri. leui by Interpretacōn is asmoche to saye / 
as Assūptus / electe or chosen of god / So there shold
no man presume to take the dygnyte of preesthode
but he were callyd &amp; chosen of god. Thapostle this
commaundeth the. v. chapytre to the Hebrees (Noo
man sayth he presume to take on hym the honour
of preesthode but he y• is callyd of god as was Aaton
/ ¶ That and this were true in the olde lawe
where was offrid oonly blood of bestes That ther
sholde noo man take on hym the offyce of preesthode
but he were chosin and callyd by god / as was
Aaron and the Leuites / How moche more in oure

newe lawe. where is dayly off
                  •
               yd vnto god for synners.
the very flesshe and blode of our sauyour Criste
Ihesu. sholde noo man presume the offyce of
preesthode / but he were elected and chosen by god to
that ryght excellent offyce and dygnyte / For as the
sacryfyce of y• newe lawe Incomperably excedyth
all the sacryfyce of the olde lawe: Soo sholde the
mynystre in holynesse. excede the mynystre of the olde.
lawe. ¶I sayd. that Ieroboham in takynge
preestys (de extremis populi) of the worste of the
people contrari to the cōmaundement of god: broughte
by theyr meanes the people to declyne and
torne from god. whyche ryght often had nyghed
vnto them by his manyfolde graces and benefytes
as playnly declar
                  •
               th Moyses (in exodo) and so forwarde
/ And not oonly by thyse euyll preestys were
the people tornyd from almyghty god: But ouer
this. tornyd were they to fals goddys: geuynge vnto
them (actum latrie 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               ur whiche oonly belongyth
vnto god. contra
                  ••
                dyrectly to the grete commaundement
of god / as it is aboue manyfestid / &amp;
in many places of the olde lawe playnly doth apere
/ ¶That in somoche and thyse euyl preestys not
chosen electe thenne of god: but by byenge and sellynge.
and dyuers &amp; many 
                  〈…〉
                meanes / 
causid in this manere wyse the 
                  〈◊〉
                erre from
almyȝty god theyr maker by ydola
                  •••
                Moche more
I thynke. that our euyll prestys in ye newe lawe.
not chose. ne assūpte of god / yf ony suche be, brynge

the people in to scisme &amp; heresy. as well bi theyr ignoraunce:
as by theyr euyll condycōns. I truste the
                  •
               
ben not many-suche / of some I fere me. Criste had
but .xij. apostles: &amp; yet one of theirn was the chylde
of perdicō
               
                  •
                / And therfore no wōder is it: though in
suche a multytude as we ben. there ben some chyldren
of the deuyll. &amp; of perdicō
               
                  •
               . God amende all.
I woll accuse no man ¶I sayd ouer this. y• oure
Ihūs Cryste ayenst the tyme of his holy, Incarnacōn
nyghed vnto mankynde gretly: leuynge wyth
hym a notable token of the same / whyche was the
lyghte &amp; spyryte of prophecy: wherby holy faders
knewe the suretee of Crustis comyng in to our kȳ
               de.
¶Amonge many prophetes Ysay in especyall / 
¶There shall goo forth sayth he a rodde of y• rote,
of Iesse: &amp; a precyous floure shall ascende of that
rote: the .xi. chapytre of Ysai. But for this was som
what derkly spoken &amp; in an allegory. he more playnly
by the lyghte of prophecy in him inspyred: expressyd
the same comynge of Criste in to our kynde
/ sheynge how he sholde be borne of a vyrgyn / 
¶Beholde sayth Ysai. a vyrgyn shall conceyu
                  •
                &amp;
beere a sone / whoos name shalbe callyd (god is to
vs) the .vij. chapytre. Daniel the prophete by his to
ken lefte wyth hym: shewed in the. xij. chapytre of
his boke / whan our sauyour Cryste sholde come.
¶After sayth he tyme: &amp; tymes and halfe a tyme / 
all thyse trouthes of Cryste forsay
                  •
                shall be acomplysshid.
Baruch the the thyrde chapytour of this

bo
                  •
               e declared the condycōns of Ihū Cryste in our
nature. thenne to come / as though he had be come
in dede ¶After this sayth Baruch Crist was seen
in this erthe. and conuersaunt was he wyth man / 
And so forth of other prophetes. Eueryman spake
of Crystis comynge / after the lyghte &amp; token lefte
wyth hym by god / So that in genynge this lighte
of prophecye: and certen knowlege of his mysteries
to come: god nyghed wonderly to man. ¶The deuyll
seenge this: enuyed the mate
                  •
               e. and besyed h
                  •
               
               self
to torne away man from god / that man shold
not yelde kyndnesse for kyndnesse. ne 
                  •
               orne to god.
&amp; nyghe vnto hym / as was his duc
                  •
               y. / And what
dyde trowe ye the deuyll to brynge hys purpoos abowte
I shall goo sayth he. &amp; I woll be a lyenge
spiryte in the mouth of all my prophete
                  •
               ) the. xxij.
chapytre in the thyrde boke of kynges / And where
as almyghty god lyghted his holy prophetes wyth
trouth: The deuyll inpressyd in his prophetes lyes
and falshede to flatere. and to disceyue the people / 
This openly aperyth in the same chapytre 
                  •
               yng
Achab sayd of Miche ye prophete of god (that Miche
neuer prophecyed. or foresayd good vnto hym)
He tolde Achab the trouth. that &amp; he. werred in Ramoth
Galaade. he. sholde be slayne. &amp; neuer retorne
agayn. ¶Yf euer sayd Miche to Achab thou re
               
                  •
               orn
home in peas: god hath not spoken in me. Four
hundrid prophetes of the deuylles were th
                  ••
               e w
                  •
               
Achab. whiche lyed vnto him. and sayd ¶Ascende

in to Ramoth Galaad. fyghte with them / for god
shall geue Ramoth in to thy hondes. Accordynge
vnto their flaterynge he went vnto the werre / And
accordynge vnto the sayenge of Miche. there was
he slayne wyth an arowe / ¶From suche false prophetes.
Flatterers in englysshe. our lorde saue oure
prynce. his londe. and vs all. Moche myscheyf haue
they doon in tymes passyd / and yet doo they no
good / For suche woll saye That all is well whan
they knowe the contrary. Worthy lytyll thankes is
suche one / For he entendyth to disceyue / For after
Ysai in the thirde chapytre. The people whiche cō
               mende
the dysceyue the) ¶Here is now declaryd
vnto you. how that our sauyour Ihūs Crist hath
nyghed vnto mankynde bi his almyghty power in
the acte of creacion / where I haue shewed you. that
he hath contynually lefte tokens wyth mankynde
of his nyghynge vnto hym / As fyrste his ymage &amp;
symylytude / Thenne the lawe of kynde, and other
specyall graces. After that Circūsicion. Thenne y•
lawe wryten / And fynally the lyghte of prophecye
And all thyse wayes he nyghed to man. to the entent
that man sholde agayn nyghe vnto hym. loue
hym. And yelde vnto him kyndnesse for kyndnesse
That is it. that god in especyall desyreth of man / 
For of our goodes he hath no nede. the. xv. psalme.
Now how waye warde man hathe be vnto god for
alle his kyndnesse. And for eche of the same somwhat
haue I shewed you.
            
               
¶Seconde in this party of the nyghynge of god
to man by his almyghty power. I sayde was by
his ryght hyghe and myghty acte of his holy and
most blessyd Incarnacion / whanne the sone of god
became man and dwellyd wyth vs in oure kynde.
The fyrste chapytre of Iohn. ¶To talke moche
of this matere of Crystis Incarnacōn. is to al synners
bothe peryllous and moche dredefull / In as
moche as saynt Iohn Baptist. the frende of the
spowse durste not this presume / As it is open of his
owne wordes in the fyrste chapytre of Iohn in thise
wordes. ¶After me sayth saynt Iohn comyth
by temporall natyuytee Ihūs Cryste god &amp; man / 
whyche was byfore me in excellence of euerlastynge
dygnytee / whoos shoo I am vnworthy to lose / 
Vppon the whyche wordes sayth saynt Gregory (Iohn Baptist the humble and meke seruaūt. and
true frende vnto Cryste. consyderynge hys hyghe
and excellent dygnytee. sayth of hym in this wyse)
¶Saynt Iohn Baptist was vnworthy to lose y•
welte of Crystis shoo / For he was Insuffysaunt to
Inuestigate the mysterye of his Incarnacion / As
though he sholde playnly saye (What wonder is it
though Ihūs Cryste be to me preferryd in dignyte
/ whom I knowe well bi temporall natyuyte bo
                  •
               
ne after me. syth I can not attayne the secretes of
his Incarnacion) ¶Thenne in so moche as thys
holy frende of god. the grettest man in vertue and
holynesse that euer was borne bytwyxe man and

woman. durste not presume to treate in this hyghe
mystery of Cryste Ihūs blessyd Incarnacion: Moche
lesse sholde all synners presume the same. ¶I
shall therfore in thys matere noo thynge talke by
waye of determynacōn / But wyth all reuerence &amp;
honoure. shewe and declare vnto you thre truthes
after my lytyll lernynge. ¶Fyrst wherin stondeth
this hyghe acte of Lryst Ihūs Incarnacōn. ¶Seconde
that this acte. is an acte of the almyghty power
of god ¶And thyrde. how in this acte. our sauyour
Cryste Ihūs nyghed vnto mankynde. / As
to y• fyrste. wherin slondeth this acte of Lrys
                  •
               ts In
carnacōn: ye shall vnderstonde / ¶That whan the
full abundaūce of the tyme of grace was come. acordynge
to the hyghe counsell of the holy trynyte.
From for euer determyned. The holy trynyte sent
downe the seconde persone of the same / And toke
our nature in the wombe of the gloryouse vyrgyn
our lady saynt Mary in to the vnyte of hys persone.
w
                  •
                out consent of man. without spotte of wēme
of synne. Accordyng to the wordes of holy Gabriel
in y• fyrst chapitre of Luke (The holy ghost sayd
tharchangel Gabriel to y• blessid virgyn. shal descende
on the bi y• plenteuous abūdance of his grace
And the vertue of god shall shadowe the from all
synne) ¶So that this acte of Crystis Incarnacōn
stondeth herin. y• by thanctorite of the hoole trinyte
y• seconde persone of the same. hath take our nature
in to
                  •
                
               
                  •
               hunite of his ꝑsone. bileue ye this truthe. it is

ynough. it nedith not dispute the matere. ¶Seconde
I say / this acte was an acte or dede of the almyghty
power of god / For as in creacōn of the worlde
all thynges were made at goddis o
                  •
               nly worde and
cōmaundement / Soo this acte of Incarnacōn was
accomplysshed at hys worde. The angell sayenge
vnto our lady (Hayle ful of grace. our lord is wyth
the) For at goddys power: is no worde impossyble.
the fyrste chapytre of Iohn / All be it in this acte of
Incarnacōn was had consent of the holy vyrgin / 
sayeug to Gabriell Beholde me the hondmayde
of god: I am contented. Be thy worde in me fulfil
lyd. In sygne that this acte was partly preiudic
                  •
               
               all
to nature. syth it was don by the almyghty power
of god: vsyd she the worde of creacōn. sayenge / 
Fiat / partly naturall. &amp; of her owne consent / And
therfore sayd she (Ecce ancilla dm̄) cōmyttynge her
wyll fully vnto the wyll of god / So that this holy
chylde. Ihūs Cryste in his temporall byrth. was create
by god: &amp; yet the naturall sone of the holy vyrgyn
Mary. And she is naturall moder. god supple
ed the offyce of the naturall fader / not by mynystracōn
of the sede of man: but rather excercysynge the
almyghty power of god the creatour. She dide the
offyce of a naturall moder. after saynt Iohn Damascene.
in mynystrynge the purest dropes of her
holy blood. ¶Thyrde is here to be shewed. how
in this acte of Incarnacōn. our Ihūs our sauyour.
nyghed vnto mankynde / Where ye shal vn
                  •
               stonde

That in this acte. our sauyour more Intrinsecally
or more in wardly. ye and more thankfully nyghed
vnto mankynde / than euer he dyde before his Incarnacyon
/ For where as is aboue shewed That in
all his nyghynge vnto man before his Incarnacōn
he lefte contynually tokens in man. that he had be
wyth him / as his ymage. his symylytude. and many
other &amp; dyuers tokens / as Circūcision. the lawe
wryten. the lyght of prophecy. and many other graces
to drawe man vnto hym as is aboue shewed / &amp;
yet hath man contynually be waywarde vnto god
and declyned from hym. So it is that in this acte
of Incarnacōn. he lefte hymself for a token wyth
man / For in takynge our nature in to the vnyte of
his persone: he vouchydsauf to Ioyne hymselfe to
man. and man to him. that for euer after it sholde
be true. that god is man. and man is god / For as sa
yth, Iohn Damascene That god ones assumid of
man in to the vnyte of his persone. he neuer after
lefte or forsoke. / ¶How kynde and thankfull was
this nyȝynge of god to man. to assume &amp; take man
in to the vnyte of▪ the seconde persone. Shewyth saynt
Austin (de verb dn̄i) the. xxxvij. sermon. in treatynge
thyse wordes conteyned in the. x. chapytre of
Luke. of the meke Samaritane. whyche nyghyng
curyd the plages of the myserable man. whyche
hadr fallen in the hondes of theues. where sayth
saynt Austyn in this wyse. / What thyng was there
euer. soo ferre from other / as god from man.

Immortall from mortall. Ryghtuouse from synner
                  •
               .
Gracyouse from wyckyd / Not ferre by dystaunce
of place: but more rather by dyssymylytude
of condycyons. whan therfore our mercyfull lorde
Cryste Ihūs our sauyour had in hymself two grete
goodes. Iustyce. and Immortalyte / And we of
mankynde had in vs two grete maladies or euyls
Wyckydnesse. and Mortalyte / Yf Cryste Ihūs sholde
haue taken on hym both our euylles and maladies.
he hadr ben but egall wyth vs. And sholde haue
nedyd a Redemer as we nedyd / Thenne to the
entent that he wold delyuer vs from our mysery &amp;
wretchydnesse. he wolde be nyghe vs of condycyōns:
but not to take all our condycyons / He wolde
not therfor be a synner as we ben: but he wolde become
mortall as we ben / Soo that in takynge our
payne of mortalyte: and not takynge our synne: he
delyuerde vs bothe from payne and from synne.
            ¶Thenne is there here shewed. how our sauyour
Ihesus Cryste hathe nyghed vnto mankynde by
his almyghty power in the moost highe acte of his
Incarnacion / where it is shewyd That he is come
by this sayd acte so nyghe man. That god is man
And man is god. The moost excellent &amp; hyghest
dede of grace and kyndnesse was this after saynt
Austin. y• euer was doon of tyme / For by this gate
had man his fyrst entre to heuen. whiche so many
thousand yeres was closid out / &amp; yet was man euer
froward &amp; vnkȳde to his sauyour. as at his tēporall

Incarnacōn &amp; Natyuyte playnly dyde appere / For
where as angels songe. kynges honouryd. sheperdes
enjoyed. vertuous men praysed god for his me
he comynge in to our kynde. Herode was trowblid
&amp; all Ierl̄m wt hym. the seconde chapytre of Mathu
/ wheryn sayth saynt Gregory in his Omely (The kynge of heuen borne: the erthly prynce. was
trowblyd) and noo wonder / For surely Temporall
dignyte is sore confoundyd / whan the dygnyte of
heuen doth appere. Herode feeryd Crystis comynge
Suspectid his regaly. &amp; without cause Inquyred or

                  •
               rouyde. soughte to distroye hym. He fledr in to Egyte.
There was all y• worlde full of ydolatry directe
contrary to the due honour of god. He cam̄ home
agayn. Archelaus layed watche to spylle hym / 
And as he grewe ferder in to aege: moche contradiccōn
had he accordyng to the prophecy of holy Symeon
in the seconde chapytre of Luke / Thys is a
sygne sayd he of Cryste / whyche in his tyme shall
haue moche contradiccōn / So that herof dooth ape

                  •
               . that god was euer to wardes mankynde. &amp; man
was contynually waywarde from god.
¶Thyrde &amp; pryncypally in this fyrste party I sayd
our sauyour Ihūs nyghed vnto mankynde (ministrando)
by his holy mynystracōn in, this worlde / 
And all be it soo. that the perfeccōns of god renne
contynually t
                  ••
               der. syth they ben in hym Infinyte.
&amp; really one / as his power. his wysdom. his godenes.
and so of other his perfeccōns. Yet ascribe I

thys acte of (apꝓximacion) or nyghynge of god to
man. vnto the power of god / For his power hathe
in this acte be gretly shewed / So hath his wysdom
so hath his goodnesse / All be it not so playnly to y•
syghte of man / ¶Thenne to my purpose. I layd
our sauyour Ihūs Cryste hath nyghed vnto mankynde
by the acte of mynystracōn. accordyng vnto
his owne wordes writen. the. xx. chapitre of Ma
                  •
               hu
¶The sone of man sayth criste comyth in to this
worlde not be serued / but rather to be a mynystre &amp;
serue / And to geue his lyf for the redempcōn of moche
people. He sayd not for al: but for many / for his
holy dethe toke not in all effecte / &amp; yet was yet for
all the worlde suffycient. ¶Thre wayes our sauyour
Cryste in oure kynde. &amp; now Incarnate hathe
nyghed to man by his admynistracyon / But what
shall I saye: Bodily or ghostly. / For soth to saye y•
trouth: bothe bodyly &amp; ghostly. all be it. more ghostly
thanne bodyly / And all hath he doon. that man
sholde nyghe vnto hym agayn. &amp; be made one spyryte
wyth god. He hath nyghed vnto man I saye
thre wayes by thacte of mynystracōn / that is to say
(in mynystrynge lyghte. In mynystrynge cure. and
in mynystryng his holy sacramentes) ¶For whose
declaracōn ye must vnderstonde That at our sauyours
comynge in to this worlde. mankynde had
many defawtes / Thre in especyall. whyche lettyd
hym to come vnto god non pedibꝰ: 
                  s
                  sed
                
               
                  morib
                  moribus
               ) not
wyth his fete: but wyth his condicōns. he was blȳ
               de

and myghte not se. Syke. and myghte not goo
So vnwyldy &amp; Impotent in euery party. yt he cowde
in no wyse nyghe. &amp; come vnto god. Now thys
defawte our sauyour dyde helpe bi his admynystracōn / 
¶Fyrst I saye where man was blynde / what
bodyly: Naye rather ghostly by ygnoraunce. mynistryng
his holy worde: he lyȝtned gretly the soule of
man. thrugh prechynge of his holy worde. he toke
fro mankynd ignoraūce / And lyghtnyd hym with
the assurid lyȝte of fayth / whiche after saynt. Iohn
Crisostom is the very lyghte of mannys soule.
            ¶To shewe this: I lete you wyte. that man was
Create of god. very god: hauynge knowlege necessary
of god. of hymselfe. &amp; of other creatures abowte
hym / as declareth the mayster the. xx
                  •
               ij. distynccōn
of the seconde. Now so it was as is aboue rehercyd
Mankynde fell in to the hondes of theues. whyche
robbed hym. woundyd hym. and lefte hym but halfe
alyue. He fell in to the deuylles hondes &amp; power
by consent to synne / They dispoyllyd hym of hys
yeftes of grace. and sore woundyd hym in his naturall
yeftes / whan he lost the symylytude of god his
maker / and in this worlde passid forth in his ymage
/ In whyche ymage man was sore woundyd / 
For he had loste Ignoraunce in his vnderstonding
Oblyuyon in his memory / And in his wyll dyffyculte
to doo well. ¶Where my sayeng be true / nay
I reporte me to yourself. / Whyche is he amonge vs
all whyche can excuse hym of Ignoraunce / whyche

can remembre hym of alle his dewetyes and not to
forgete ony of them / Whiche hath no dyffyculte ne
payne to do well: I deme verily not many in this
audieuce. and also I am well assuryd. noo man.
            ¶Now by this ignoraunce in to whiche man was
fallen by synne: He felle in to many other grete inconuenyencts
/ As in to ydolatrye agaynst the due
honour of god. In to rebellyon agaynst his souereynes
and prynces. In to myscheyf and murthur bytwene
man and man / In to a thousande Inconuenyences
moo than I can reherce or shewe / For after
saynt Iohn Crisostom. the. xxv. Omely of his
werke Imperfecte on Mathu Ignoraunce is the
mo
                  •
               er of errour: And euyll wyll the fader) Then̄e
Ioyne thyse two togyders Ignoraunce of trouthe
And euyll wyll. to knowe the same / And by al ma
nere lyklyhode. errour comyth soone after. A sory
kynredr And a ryght wyckyd genelogy. ¶This
Ignoraunce. In especyall of thynges necessary to
mannys saluacyon. somtyme in scrypture is callyd
derkenesse / Somtyme it is callyd. the shadowe of
dethe. Also somtyme the ymage of dethe / And som
tyme the payn of. synne / So y• Ignoraunce I saye
of thȳges necessary to m
                  •
               nys saluacōn. hath euer
Ioyned wt hym. s
                  •
               ne. derknes &amp; deth. ¶Cryst comyng
in to our hȳde. fonde y• worlde in derknes &amp;
y• shadow of deth. &amp; in ignoraunce. &amp; he mynystryd
light / For after y• wo
                  •
               de of Symeon: he was y• very
lyȝte to releue all Gentils beyng blynde by synne.

Thenne I saye our san your Cryste gaue lyghte.:
What was that: Sothly he declarid his holy fayth
to the worlde / whyche as I sayd aboue is the very
lyghte of mannys soule. ¶And in sygne that all y•
worlde sholde be releuyd by the lyghte of his fayth
At his temporall byrth. he apperyd. wyth grete lyghte
/ as declareth saynt Luke in the seconde chapy
               
                  ••
               e
(At the tyme sayth he of Crystis holy byrth. she
peherdes were there in that regyon obseruynge the
nyghte watche on theyr flockes. And sodenly y• angell
of god was amonge them. and the grete clerenesse
of god bryghty dyde beshyne them all abowte)
Vppon whyche wordes sayth saynt Gregory (y•
where in holy scrypture we ofte rede that angelles
haue aperyd to holy faders: we neuer rede that thei
appered wyth suche lyghte as dyde this holy angel
at Crystis byrthe) For full conuenyently sayth saynt.
Gregory was this priuylege reseruyd vnto cristys
natiuyte / whan was bome very lyghte to men
syttynge in the derknesse of Ignoraunce &amp; synne / 
¶So that as our sauyour came wyth grete lyght
in to this roorlde: So by his power in mynystryng
his holy worde to the people. he lyghtned mennys
soules gretly wyth his fayth. accordynge to the wordes
of Dauid the prophete in the. xxiiij. psalme (Nyghe
ye vnto god sayth the prophete: &amp; ye shalbe
lyghtnyd wyth his fayth / For he nyghed vnto you
by mynystracōn of the same lyghte) Thenne thou
heretyk how cannest thou excuse thyself. lete se. god

offreth to the his lyghte of fayth. conteyned in holy
scrypture sayenge (Blessyd be those whyche here
deuowtly the worde of god. and it obserueth the
xi. chapytre of Luke. He nyghed to the wyth necessary
lyghte. thou sparest thy derke &amp; ignoraunt soule.
&amp; wolt not come to god / what wonder thenne yf
thou erre from trouth. &amp; falle in to the derke pytte
of euerlastynge dampnacōn. / This is the way war
denes of all grete synners / As of grete extorcioners
grete vsurers. grete oppressers of the people. Offre
to them lyghte / Shewe to them the peryll of theyr
grete synnes. They sparre theyr soules. Shytte out
the lyghte. And delite to dwelle in ignoraunce. lay
               
                  •
               ng
holy scrypture for them. the. xij. chapytre of Luke.
A seruaunt knowynge his soueraynes wyll / &amp;
it not perfourmynge: shall be greuously punysshyd
And therfore had they moche leuer contynually lyue
in
                  •
               gnoraunce. than to knowe the trouth / But he
that is ignoraunt of trouthes necessary. shall be of
god vnknowen. that is to saye (vnalowed at y• grete
Iugement. ¶Saynt Austyn sayth (y• one thynge
is euyll Not to knowe. &amp; a nother Not to wyll
knowe. The wyll of them is at god reprouyd / Of
whom sayth the prophete Dauid (They woll not
knowe to do wel ¶Seconde in this party. I sayd
our sauuour nyghed vnto man mynystryng vnto
hym cure both ghostly &amp; bodyly. Ishewe it this
At his comynge in to this worlde. Alle the worlde
of men was syke. All ghostly / And many bodyly / 

Alle were ghostly syke by synne / For all were synners.
as sheweth the apostle to the Romayns the
thirde chapytre / how this syknesse of synne entryd
in to all the worlde. the same apostle declareth to y•
Romayns the fyfth chapitre. ¶As by one man laych
the apuostle. synne entred in to all the worlde / &amp;
by synne. deth. So by 
                  •
               o man. deth passyd in to al
men / In whyche o
                  •
                man: alle men haue offendyd
god by synne. ¶Now for this ghostly syknesse of
synne: many haue fallen / &amp; yet falle in bodyly syknesse
/ As declareth saynt Iohn Crisostom vppon
thyse wordes of Crist vnto the palsey man by him
curyd / whyche laye. xxxviij. yeres sore sike in his siknesse
(Goo thy way sayd Cryste vnto hym. and se
thou synne noo more leest if chaunce the worse) the
vi. chapytre of Iohn. ¶Here lerne we sayth saynt
Iohn Crisostom. that this mannys syknesse came
vnto hym for his synne / For so it is. that almyghty
god often punyssheth the body for synnes of the
soule. And it foloweth (though it be so. that al men
ben not in this lyf punysshid bodyly for theyr synnes.
lete vs not theron truste. ne be to prowde / For
assurydly a synner to passe this lyf wythout aduersyte:
sygne it is of grete punysshment &amp; dampnacy
on in hell) After the wordes of Iob the. xxi. chapytre
(grete sȳners sayth he passyth this world ful of
ten in moche prosperite and at a soden poynt they
descende in to hell. ¶Thenne some there be whyche
be here punysshid bodyly for ther ghostly sȳnes

&amp; yet not alle hauynge bodyly syknesse. haue it for
their synnes: but somtyme of naturall causes: Many
tymes of surfeyte. ye &amp; somtyme for god woll
shewe his grete power. &amp; be glorifyed on wretchyd
persones / As Cryste playnly shewed in the. ix. chapytre
of Iohn: where his discyples askyd hym of y•
blynde man of natyuyte. / ¶Who offendyd: thys
man or his frendes. that he was borne blynde: Criste
answerde &amp; sayd. that neyther he ne yet his t
                  •
               endes:
but that the glory of god sholde be made open
on hym. Wherupon sayth saynt Austin Hadr this
man not originall synne. ne yet actuall in progresse
of his lyfe. that Cryste sayd of him. he had not offendyd:
yes lurely sayth sayne Austin / both he and
his frendes had dyuers wayes synned / And yet for

                  •
               heyr synnes. was not this man born blynde: but y•
cause was. that god wold shewe his almyghty power
&amp; be glorifyed in hym) ¶So theme at our sauyours
comyng in to this world. al were syke ghostly.
&amp; many bodyly. Now he lyke a grete physicyen
b
                  •
                his almyȝty po
                  •
               er. mynystrid cure vnto them
He nyghed vnto them that were synners. and like
both ghostly &amp; bodyly. He disdayned not theyr cō
               pany.
etc &amp; dranke wyth them famylyarly / This
meke acte of cryst. displeysid the proude Scribes &amp;
Pharisees. &amp; sayd to his disciples (Whi ete
                  •
               h &amp; dryketh
your mayster wyth grete &amp; open synners) the
v. chapytre of Luke. Cryste was thenne in y• house
of Leui or Mathu. whiche made him a gre
                  •
               e fest

wherunto came many Publicans. grete sȳners. vsurers
I deme many of them. Cr
                  •
               ste I say ete &amp; dranke
wyth them. to cure them. not to folowe them. to
drawe them to hym. not him to them▪ y• they shold
folowe his steppes. not he theyrs. He nyghed vnto
theym by grace. y• they sholde nyghe vnto hym by
penaunce / Wherfore he answerde forth wyth to the
acusacōn of the Scribes &amp; Pharisees this wyse Sike
men nedeth a physicyen. &amp; not hoole men▪ Wher
vpon sayth saynt Iohn Crisostom in thyse wordes
¶Cryste remembred them of the comyn Infyrmy

                  •
               e of synne. shewynge them to be of the nombre of
synners. And hymself to be a perfyte physicyen / &amp;
therfore addeth forth wt (I cam not in to this worlde.
to calle ryghtwysmen: but rather synners to penaunce
As though he sholde saye I disdayne not
synners. syth oonly for synners loue I came in to
thys worlde / not y• they shold remayne synners: but
rather to be conuerted &amp; lyue euerlastyngly) Then̄
I say our sauyour Ihūs Cryst dispysed not the cō
               pany
of syke men. gostly. ne bodyly / but of his infinyte
goodnes bi his grete power cured them all. all
y• wolde come. nyghe. or cleue vnto hym. &amp; forsake
hȳ not / For y• vertue of him yede forth. &amp; curyd all
men. y•. vi. chapitre of Luke ¶We neuer rede y• crist
euer caste ony sȳner or syke man fro hym y• sued to
hȳ for mercy &amp; grace. Al be it. we fynde. y• some cast
away themself. &amp; wold not come at his callyng: but
were alle waywarde. &amp; wrange from hym / As the

ryche man of whom we rede the. xviij. chapytre of
Luke. after moche comunycacōn atwyxe them. criste
sayd vnto hym Goo thy waye. selle all thy godes.
geue them to poore men. Come &amp; folowe me / &amp;
thou shalt haue a tresour in heuen) It folowyth / 
This ryche man departyd heuyly &amp; soryly fro Criste
/ for he had grete possessions. Cryste lokynge abowte
/ &amp; knowyng this man departyd. sayd to his
discyples (Full harde it is a ryche man to entre the
kyngdom of heuen) &amp;
                  •
               . ¶Taketh good hede here
vnto ye ryche men of this worlde: Full harde it is
to you. to nyghe vnto god: but ye wyth Leui caste
from you your burdon. &amp; folowe Cryste. We rede
also in the. viij. chapytre of Iohn That many refusyd
&amp; caste Cryste from theym / whan they went
backe from hym. walkyd no more wyth hym: but
folowed the deuyll / This was it of the. ix. leprous
men of whom we rede in the. xvij. chapytre of Luke
/ This was it of Iudas the traytour to Cryste. &amp;
of fewe other we rede that raste Cryste from them
sayenge in a parable the. xix. chapytre of Luke We
wol not this man to regne on vs) But we neuer rede
that Cryst caste ony seke man from hym ghost
ly. or bodyly / whyche wolde come vnto hym &amp; be curyd.
In token of this. he sayd hymself in the. xi. chapytre
of Mathu (Come ye vnto me. all y• ben chargyd
wyth the burdon of synne / &amp; I shall cure you)
¶Ye but thou as
                  •
               ryst me here a questyon:. Curyd
Cryste his pa
                  •
               yentes. / Ye surely: Neuer physicyen

lyke vnto hym / For he made all the man hoole. the
vij. chapitre of Iohn: He neuer curyd man in his body
/ but he fyrste curyd hym in his soule. And ful resonably
/ For a perfyte physicyen sholde fyrste cure
that thynge in his pacyent whyche is of grete peryll.
&amp; of grettest pryce / Now is there incomparably
grettest peryll in syknesse of the soule than of y• body
/ For the syknesse of the soule foloweth comynly
euerlastynge dethe / whyche is euerlastynge dampnacōn
in hell / And the syknesse of the body foloweth
but temporall dethe: the departyng of the body
&amp; the soule / whyche Cryste accountyd for no grete
thynge / as it is open in the. x. chapytre of Mathu (Drede
ye not sayth Cryste to his seruauntes. thē.
whyche whan they haue slayne the body can hurte
you no ferther / But drede ye hym whyche hath ful
power to cōmytte bothe body &amp; soule to euerlastynge
payne of hell. Ye sayth Cryste. hym drede ye)
¶Thenne syth there is so grete peryll in syknesse
&amp; dethe of the soule aboue the syknesse &amp; deth of y•
body: our sauyour Lryst curyd alway the soule firste.
and folowyngly the bodyes / of whom was lesse
charge ¶Ye but ye must vnderstond. all his phisyk
was heuenly. not erthly. all from aboue. not fro by
neth / For after saynt Austyn He. whyche wyth his
oonly worde made all thynge of nought: he with y•
sam̄ his oonly worde: repayred his creatures at his
pleysur) He mynistred al his cures both gostly &amp; bodily.
by his almyghty power. sayeng to one blynde

man respice
                  •
                beholde &amp; se. To a nother that was
longe wt the Palsey contracte (Ryse vp. take wyth
the thi bedr &amp; walke) To a nother (Be it vnto the
after thy fayth) And to Lazare foure dayes in hys
graue veni foras / come forth &amp; lyue) Cryste neuer
vsyd emplastre. pocion. bayne ne oyntment / but it
wer ones / whan wt his holy spotell medled wt clay
he enoynted the eyen of hym that was borne blynde
/ Whyche after saynt Iohn Crisostom was mo
                  •
               
for mystery than for the matere / ¶Of this apereth
how our sauiour by mynystracōn of his grete cures
on the soules &amp; bodies of syke men. nyghed to man
kynde by his grete &amp; almyghty power. shewynge
hymself a meke seruaūt. to cause mankynde to nighe
vnto him by hertly loue. his grete benefites duly
consydred. ¶Thyrde and fynally in thys party
I sayd our sauyour Crist nyghed vnto man my
nystrynge vnto him his holy sacramentes. leuynge
in his holy chyrche wyth man for euer. auctoryte &amp;
power to doo the same / This dyde our sauyour of
his grete goodnes: but bi his power &amp; auctorite / For
as hȳself sayd in ye. xxviij. chapytre of Mathu All
power in heuen &amp; erth is yeuen vnto our Ihū Crist
¶For the declaracōn of this trouth. how crist hath
nyghed vnto mankynde by his sacrament I shall
shortly shewe you thre truthes / Fyrst whi criste instituted
y• holy sacrament
                  •
                in his chirche. second what
sacramen
                  •
               
               ▪ he instituted / &amp; thyrd how he nyghed to
man in y• same ¶Fyrst whi our sauyour instytutde

holy sac
                  •
               amentes in his chyrche: declareth the mayster
of the sentence in the fyrste dis
                  •
               ynccion of the
fourth. For thre causes / For mannes hum
                  •
               lyacion / 
for his e
                  •
               udycōn / &amp; for his exercytacō
               
                  •
                ¶Thise holy
sacramentes were Instytute ones / for man shold
meke hymself: whyche had offendid by pryde. &amp; seke
helpe euerlastynge in thynges sensyble / not of
themself: but of god in them. &amp; by them. ¶Agayn
thyse sacramentes were Institute. for mannys ghostly
erudycōn / That man whyche by his synne had
loste the syghte &amp; perfyghte knowlege of god had
in the state of Innocency: myghte by vysyble sygnes.
&amp; outward tokens. come to the knowlege of secrete
mysteryes &amp; graces of god. in thyse vysyble to
kens sygnyfyed &amp; conteyned / ¶For ye must vnderstonde.
that (sacramentū) a sacrament after y• mayster
in the same place. is a token. or a sygne of an
holy thynge (That is true sayth mayster Dwns)
on the same / but that it is a practik &amp; effectuous sigge.
not fayllynge. ne vncertayn of his sygnyfycacy
on / For it putteth in effecte. and vnder god in a manere
is cause of that thynge. whyche is therby sygnyfyed.
for the thynge surely. And vndowtidly folowyth
/ yf there be no defawte on him whiche sholde
receyue the sacrament. ¶Thyrde I saye the holy
sacramentes were Institute for mannys excercytacōn.
that man sholde be contynually ocupyed in
the seruyce of god / &amp; not geue hymself to vayn ydilnesse
/ For as sayth saynt Austyn / ¶That man is

not l
                  •
               ghtly wonne bi the deuylles temptacōn. whiche
geuyth hymself to good occupacōn. Exhortyth
therfore saynt Ierom (Be thou man euer more besyed
in some vertuous labour. that the deuyll fynde
not the ydyll) ¶Thenne here appereth the fyrst
why our sauyour dyde mstitute sacramentes in his
holy chyrche. I saye for our humylyacōn. erudicōn.
&amp; excercytacōn / but fynally for our saluacōn / as in
the seconde trouth of this party shall appere / whyche
I sayd to be this / ¶What sacramentes our sauyour
dyde ordeyne. &amp; institute in his chyrche (Vij.
I saye) as the mayster declareth at large in the .
                  •
               ij.
whyche all ben effectuous sygnes of grace. to eche
man. whyche them. or ony of them. worthyly doth
receyue / And so be meanes of mannes fynall saluacōn
/ ¶To talke of all thyse sacramentes to y• purpoos:
tyme woll not permitt I wote / I shall therfore
talke of thre of them. shewynge how kyndly our
sauyour Cryste Ihūs nyghed vnto man in eche of
them / For that is my purpoos to shewe. The fyrst
is the sacrament of baptym / The seconde of penaunce.
The thyrde the holy sacrament of the awter
The fyrst is of necessite simplic
                  ••
                to man. The seconde
is of necessyte condicional. The thyrde is of
necessyte conuenient. The fyrste that is the sacrament
of baptym. is of necessyte simplic
                  ••
                / For baptym
is that fyrste gate by the whyche euery man
must passe of necessite that purposeth entre in to heuen.
Cryste this affermed in the thyrde chapytre of

Iohn. ¶Maye no man sayd Cryste vnto Nichodeme
entre in to heuen / but he be regenerate &amp; redemyd
in water. &amp; the holy ghost ¶I call this sacrament
of necessite simplici
                  •
                / for syth all men be borne
sȳners as is aboue declared: al men must be clensyd
of ther synnes or they entre into heuen / for therne
comyth. ne yet abydeth syth ony synne. or sȳner
                  •
               
Thenne our sauyour Ihūs Criste of his grete godenes
ordenyd &amp; Instituted the sacrament of baptym
as a necessary gate to entree by towardes heuen.
Here is none excepcōn: but yonge &amp; olde. cristen
mānys chylde &amp; hethens. Iewe or gentile: what soeuer
state he be of: by this holy sacrament must he
passe. wythout the baptym of blood / as holy martyrdom.
it lette or preuent / And for this sacrament
is so necessary. Cryste prechyd &amp; declaryd this specyally
/ as testifieth both Marke &amp; Ma
                  ••
               u. a lytyll
before his Ascencyon. he cōmaundyd his dyscyples
this wyse (Go ye forth sayd Cryste in to all y• worlde.
teche ye all people. 
                  •
               aptisynge them / in the name
of the fader. &amp; the sone. &amp; the holy ghost / Who
so euer haue true fayth. &amp; is baptysed. he shal be sauyd)
¶Seconde. I saye the sacrament of penaunce
is of necessite condicionall. That declare I thus
For as baptym wassheth awaye origynall synne &amp;
actuall where it is. So doth y• sacrament of penaū
               ce.
take awaye synne. or synnes actuall after baptym
cōmytted. In wytnesse of this. Cryst geuyng
auctorytee to preesthode for euer to geue remyssyo
                  •
               
               
of synnes. 
                  •
               nsufflate and gracyously brethyd in his
discyples. sayeng. ¶Receyue ye the holy ghost / who
so euer synnes ye forgeue. forgeuen be they at god / 
And whose synnes ye retayne retayned be they att
god. the. xx. chapitre of Iohn / Now for as moche as
euery man is a sȳner in this lyf comynly as saynt
Iohn shewyth the fyrste chapytre of hys fyrst epistle
in thyse wordes / ¶Yf we saye y• we be no synners:
we disceyue ourself. &amp; trouth is not in vs / And
not oonly in one synne we offende god: but in many
synnes: as declareth saynt Iamys in his epystle
the fyrste chapytre (We all sayth he offende god in
many offences &amp; 
                  •
               respasses. is therfor y• sacrament
of penaūce. necessary to man condicionally) That
is to say (yf man offēde / as we do all cominly: then̄
is y• sacrament of penaūce necessary to y• releyf of
mānys synne. to put hȳ in surete of remyssion) For
(penitēcia habitꝰ) thabite of penaūce is not of suche
surete as declareth mayster Dwns in the .iiij. /
Then̄ syth this sacrament is of necessyte requyred
to all sȳners. Crist sayeng in y• .xiij. chapytre of Luke
(Wythout ye do penaunce. all shall ye perysshe)
Caste not awaye this holy sacrament. ne the grace
therof. Dyspyse it not / But amende we ourself
in to better lyfe. takynge penaunce for oure offences
by ygnoraunce commytted. leest we sodaynly
prcuente wyth deth. seke for penaunce. and can not

                  •
               henne fynde it. ⸫ ¶Thyrde I sayde the
holy Sacrament of the aweer is of, necessytee

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
conuenyent / whyche. I declare thus lyke as bodyly
meete &amp; drynke is necessaryly requyred to the bodyly
sustenaunce of man in this erthly lyf: So is this
holy sacrament requyred as ghostly sustinaunce for
mannys spyrytuall lyfe) As declareth saynt Austyn
on thyse wordes of Criste in the .vi. chapit
                  •
               e of
Iohn (My flesshe sayth he is veri meete. &amp; my blode
is very drynke) ¶Syth men sayth saynt astyn
desyre by meete &amp; drynke to satisfye their hungre &amp;
thy
                  •
               ste. this oonly dooth that holy meete &amp; drynke
whyche maketh the deuowte receyuers therof Immortall
&amp; Incorruptyble. the blessyd sacrament of
the awter. ¶Thenne syth this holy sacrament is
ghostly mete &amp; ghostly drynke: necessary is this mete
&amp; this drynke for the contynuaūce of the ghostly
lyf of man / as in the same chapytre of Iohn declareth
our sauyour Cryste at large (But ye ete sayth
he the flesshe of the sone of man. &amp; drynke his blode.
ye shall haue noo ghostly lyfe in you / And who
so euer ete this meete &amp; drynke this drynke worthily.
shal therbi lyue euerlastyngly) ¶And maysters
all
                  •
                I beseche our lordes mercy of one thynge. that
alle we here present. whyche at this blessyd feest of
Ester haue receyued this holy sacrament. sac
                  •
               amē
               tally.
haue also receyued the same spyrytually. that
is to saye (the grace by thys holy sacrament sygnefyed
&amp; geuen) In haste we shal knowe of lyklyhode
/ For as ye knowe the tree by the fruyte: so shall
ye knowe the man by his condicōns. He that retorneth

hastely to his olde synnes ayen: of lyklyhode
neuer receyued this holy sacrament spirytually. Of
lyklyhode I say. I dare no ferder presume to Iuge.
¶The thyrde trouthe in this party I sayd to be
this. how our sauyour in thyse thre sacramentes in
especyall. &amp; in alle in generall. nyghed. and dayly
nygheth vnto man / Where ye shall vnderstonde. y•
our sauyour Cryste hath promysed so to assiste his
holy sacramentes wyth his grace. whan he ascended
vnto the fad of heuen. sayeng to his discyples / 
&amp; to all good crysten men vnto y• worldes ende for
euer in the laste chapytre of Mathu (Remembre ye
well what I saye I am wt you for euer vnto the
worldes ende) That who so receyue worthyly ony
of his sacramentes. receyueth by specyall condiscen
dyng in to his soule. almyghty god. &amp; his specyall
grace / Wherby he stondith in the specyall g
                  •
               ace &amp; fauour
of god. Alle his actes ben in the syghte of god
specyaly acceptyd &amp; alowed. &amp; ordred to euerlastynge
rewarde in heuen. In wytnesse herof sayth saynt
Iohn in the fourch chapitre of his fyrste epistle
God is charyte. &amp; he that dwelleth in charyte.
dwelleth in god. and god in hym
                  •
               
            
            ¶Thenne by vertu of his holy sacramentes. Criste
merueylously nyghed to man / for he dwe
                  •
               leth in
man. &amp; maketh man his holy temple. &amp; place of his
gracious habytacyon / ¶But amonge all his holy
sac
                  •
               amentes. he nyȝeth syngulerly to man in thyse
thre. in baptym. penaunce. &amp; the holy. sacrament of

the awter / ¶For where man is ferre from god by
synne as is aboue sayd: by baptym he wasshith. hȳ.
clensyth hym. entreth in to his soule. dwellyth wt
hym / and makyth hym one of his famyliare housholde.
¶Bi the sacrament of penaunce where the
synner is fallen from god &amp; his grace. fast bounde
in the prison of synne. and oblisshid to euerlastyng
dampnacōn: god of hys Infinyte goodnes nygheth
vnto hym geuyth hym water of contrycion. losyth
him. taketh him in to his housholde agayn. admit
teth hym in to his fauonr / And dysposeth for hym
euerlastynge saluacōn in heuen. hymself sayeng bi
his prophete. ¶In what so euer hour the synner
truly repent: he shall be saut. &amp; his synnes forgeuen
¶By holy sacrament of the aw
                  •
               er. moost syn
gulerly. and moost gracyously. he nygheth vnto euery
man it worthyly receyuynge / For by this blessyd
sacrament. he fedyth man. he comforteth man.
And strengtheth hym ayenst all his enmyes. hymself
is the feder. hymself is the fode. hymself is the
geuer. hymselfe is the gyfte. hymself is the prayser
hymself is the pryce / So y• by this holy sacrament
he nygheth so vnto man. y• he Incorporateth man
in to his mystycall body. And maketh hym one of
his precyous mēbres / For whom by his grete power
he fyghteth. &amp; ayenst al his enmyes he myȝtily defendeth
/ Of whom was Ihūs Naue but a fygure.
for he neuer sauyd y• people to him cōmitted: but bi
y• grace geuen vnto hym by our Ihūs Cryst. Syn

there is no power but of god after the appostle to y•
Romayns the .xiij. chapytre. Ihūs Naue by the power
of god geuen to hym. slewe &amp; distroyed the bodyly
enmyes of his people. Our Ihūs by his owne
almyghty power. distroyeth the ghostly enmyes of
his seruauntes / For after thapostle y• .xvi. chapit
                  •
               e
to the Romayns (almyghty god by his power shal
spedely trede &amp; distroye the deuyll vnder our fete. &amp;
ouer this geuyth power to all his seruauntes to do
the same ¶Behold &amp; take good hede sayth Crist
to his seruaūtes: I haue geuen power to you to trede
serpentes &amp; scorpions vnder your fete. and none
enmye shal mow noye you. the .x. chapytre of Cuke
¶Ihūs Naue agayn broughte the people to hym
cōmytted in to the londe of repromission by y• power
of god. Ye but this londe was alle erthly bryngyng
forth of brymbles and thornes / But our Ihesus
hath sauyd all his people. not one of them perysshyd.
exceptynge the chyldren of perdycōn / And
hath broughte all hys seruauntes in y• to londe of
euerlastynge lyfe. And there hath dystrybuted vnto
euery one of hys seruauntes. glory in abundaunce
Where his seruauntes shal neuer hungre ne thryste
Ne neuer be trowblyd ne noyed nother wyth hete
ne wyth colde. ¶Here is now declaryd &amp; shewed
y• fyrste party &amp; pryncypall conclusyon of this
poore sermon (thus manere fourme) That the same
Ihesus Cryste whyche dyde ayde. and in alle
his werkes dyde assyste vnto forsayd Ihesu Naue

hath nyghed vnto mankynd by his almyghty power
in thre wyse creando. nascendo. ministrando)
bi his actes of creacōn. of Incarnacōn. &amp; of mynys
tracōn / What shall I thenne saye vnto all cristen
men but this (Be not vnkynde vnto hym. Be not
frowarde. be not wayward) ¶For there was neuer
nacōn in this worlde so grete. y• euer had their goddis
nyghyng vnto them as our lorde god nygheth
vnto vs: The fourth chapytre of Deutronomij.
Thenne I exhorte you all to nyghe vnto god wt
the acte of adoracōn / y• is to saye wyth perfyte loue
&amp; seruyce oonly due to god) For he nygheth by his
manyfold graces. to all those. whyche humbly. &amp; of
a
                  ••
                
               
                  ••
               eyr hertes do seke hym.:
            ¶Seconde &amp; pryncypally in 
                  •
               his collacōn. I sayde
me to shewe &amp; declare to you. how the same Ihūs
hath walkyd wyth mankynde by holy obedyence
                  •
               
Yf y• axe me. whyche same Ihūs: I saye the same
Ihūs. the sone of god. &amp; of y• virgyn our lady. whyche
nyghed to mankynde. &amp; assisted to Ihūs Naue
by his almyghty power: The same Ihūs it was y•
walked wt Ihū Iosedech. &amp; so hath sauyd mankȳ
               de
by his holy obedience / To whose short declaracion.
ye shall vnderstonde. y• our sauyour Cryst hath
walkid wyth man thre wyse by holy obedience: but
this must ye vnderstonde of Ihū Criste Incarnate
&amp; lyuyng in our mortall nature / &amp; all for we shold
folowe his holy steppes for our profyte / as aft shal
appere. ¶Fyrste he was obedyent to hys frendes &amp;

prela
                  •
               es. Seconde he was obedyent to the precep
                  •
               
&amp; lawes. Third he was obedyent to passions &amp; de
               
                  •
               he.
¶Fyrst I say he was obedient to his fader putatiue
Ioseph. &amp; to his holy moder. &amp; other potestates
of the worlde. In y• second chapitre of Luke we
rede. y• Ihūs descendid from Ierlm in to Nazareth
&amp; was obedyent vnto Mary &amp; Ioseph (the story is
there declared at large) but to myn entent. this appereth
of the same. That our sauyour Cryste shewed
grete obedyence vnto Ioseph &amp; his holy moder

                  •
               m̄ erat subditus illis) he was to them obedyent.
They cōmaundyd. he obeyed. Vpon whyche wordes
sayth saynt Bede. ¶In this mystery sayth he
is geuen of our sauyour to all 
                  •
               ortall men a grete
example of mekenesse. god was subdued to man.
euerlastyng to tēporall. the gretter to the lesse. y• hyer
to the lower (To the entent y• we sholde lerne &amp;
folow the steppes of mekenesse) whyche purpose to
attayne y• hye glory of god ¶Of whiche foloweth
a notable corelari or morall lesson thys (y• who soo
euer purposeth to walke wyth Cryst in to y• heyth
of heuen: he must fyrst folowe hym in this worlde
by meke obedyence vnto all his heedes &amp; rulers. bothe
spirytuall &amp; temporall. fader &amp; moder / though
he be better &amp; gretter than they in merites &amp; vertu
                  •
               
This sheweth the apostle to the Romayns in the
xiij. chapytre by a longe processe. ¶Euery man sayth
he ought to obeye to hyghe auctoryte &amp; power.
his cause is this / For there is no power but of god.

wherupon sayth saynt Austin (An euyll wyll &amp; desyre
to noye. maye be of man hymself. &amp; of his owne
crokydnesse) But power to noye maye no man
haue: but oonly of god / As it apereth of the deuyls
wordes vnto god in the fyrste chapytre of Ioh. wyllyng
to enoye thys holy man (Put forth thy honde
sayth the deuyll to god. towche &amp; stryke all his go
                  •
               
               des
&amp;c) That is sayth saynt Austyn as though he
sholde say (geue power) He wolde haue enoyed the
holy man: but of hymself he myghte not / wherfore
he askyd power to noye. ¶Then̄e syth there is no
power but of almyghty god: euery man sholde be
gladly obedyent vnto power / For euery thyng geue
&amp; ordeyned by god. is duely ordryd. Now who so resyst
the ordynaunce of god. purchasyth to hymself
euerlastyng dampnacōn. Thou sayst (syre my hede.
my ruler is cruell. Impacyent. a grete wrong doer
or extorcioner) What thenne sayth saynt Peter / 
Be ye obedyent vnto euery man in auctorytee For
goddys commaundement. To the kynge or prynce.
as cheyf by excellence vnd god. to dukes &amp; other
grete asta
                  •
               es / as his hye mynistres &amp; officers / what
to good &amp; badde thou sayst: ye syre / so sayth saynt
Peter (ye seruaūtes be ye obedient vnto your lordes
in all drede. not oonly to good &amp; moderate of condycyons:
but also to wylde &amp; lewde of theyr disposycyon)
¶Saynt Austin de natura &amp; gracia (entreatynge
this matere sayth (Our sauyour cōmaū
               dyth
chyldren to obeye theyr faders &amp; moders. He

commaundeth also subgettes to obeye theyr hedes
and prelates. He dyde as he taughte. Fulfylled y• he
warnyd / For he descendynge wyth our lady &amp; Ioseph.
was to them obedyent / And as a pupill was
guyded vnder power in his tendre a
                  •
               ge. all be it he
was lorde of all the worlde. He hath geuen vnto y•
example of mekenesse. he hath goon before. exhorteth
the to folowe hym. Thou refusest to be of the
body of Cryste: yf thou wolt not wyth hym be vnder
an heed / But y• sayst (I loue power / for it is of
god: but I drede my prelate my heed / for ofte he is
an euyl man) Here thou me sayth saynt Austyn: yf
thy ruler or prelate be good &amp; vertuous: then̄e is he
to the a nouryssher. yf he be euyll: thenne is he thin
attemptour
                  •
                Wherfore take y• gladly thy nouryssher.
And in temptacōn be y• pacyent. And prouyde
the folower of Cryst / whyche sayd vnto all his seruauntes
in the fourth chapytre of Mathu (Folowe
me. I goo before you by perfyte▪ obedyence. takyth
of me ensample. and doo ye▪ the same) ¶Of this
appereth y• our sauyour Cryste walkyd wyth man
by holy obedyence. to his frendes. and other hauynge
power and auctorytee in this worlde. Sayde he
in testimonye &amp; wytnesse of thys vnto Pilate bostynge
hys power / Thou sholdest sayde Cryste
haue no power on me / but it were geuen the from
aboue the chapytre of Iohn / ¶And in this hys
obedyence. he lefte and shewed vs ensample

to folowe the same. ¶Now how the multytude to
low our sauyour in his grete mekenesse &amp; obedience.
god knoweth / full euyll I fere. Cryst sayd honour
thy fader &amp; moder. that y• may lyue longe on erthe)
We saye (what so almes. or good dedys we do
thy party fader or moder is therin. &amp; it shal stonde
you in stede. so leuyng them many tymes in necessyte
&amp; dystresse. the .xv. chapytre of Ma
                  •
               hu. originally
groūded the .xx. chapytre of Exodꝰ / ¶And yet I
trowe veryly the defaw
                  •
               e herof moche in the frendes.
whiche sholde lerne the chyldn. &amp; in theyr yonge
aege brynge them vp (in timore dn̄i) in y• drede
of god. to lerne them to knowe god. to drede god &amp;
theyr frendes. Example herof in especiall was holy
Thoby / whyche taughte his sone from his yonge
aege to drede god. &amp; absteyne from all synne. y•
fyrste chapytre of Thoby. accordynge to the wyse
mannys counsell in the .vij. chapitre of Ecclesiasti
¶God hath geuen to the chyldren sayth the wyseman.
teche them the lawe of god / For sure it is. y•
for lacke of obedyence. &amp; good erudicōn. the chyldn
ofte ryse by vyolence ayenst y• faders: And putteth
them to grete peryll. &amp; many tymes vnto dethe. y•
xiij. chapytre of Mathu. ¶Yf I shold here speke of
our chyldn of the cyte. I reporte me. how well they
thryue. comynly none worse / Why trowe ye: playnly
they lacke erudicōn in youth. wyth due chas
                  •
               ysement
/ So dyde Offny &amp; Phinees the sones of Hely.
They fell to ryotte as it appereth in the 
                  •
               yrste

chapytre of y• fyrst boke of the kynges. The cōclusion
of ther foly was (ther fad Hely brake hys necke
for his necligence. Both his sones were slayne in a
day bi the Philistees. And tharche of god. y• true fygure
of his holy chyrche was taken in to y• hondes
&amp; power of synners &amp; thenmyes of god) The .iiij.
chapytre of the fyrste boke of kynges. ¶A comyn
prouerbe it is &amp; a wyse (y• better is a chylde vnborn
than vntaught) Teche ye therfor your chyldren to
walke wyth Ihū Cryste. by true obedyence to god▪
to their frendes. ye &amp; to their prynce. &amp; other hedes.
This ben they boūde vnder y• payne of euerlastynge
dampnacōn as is aboue shewed. For there is no
power but of god. ¶The cause whi comynly men

                  ••
               bell ayenst theyr heedys &amp; souereynes. is pryde &amp;
highe mynde. Now our sauyour taught mekenesse
Lerne ye of me sayth he to al his folowers. y• I am
meke &amp; humble of spyryte. the .xi. chapytre of Mathu.
Mekenes ledyth to obedyence. &amp; obedyence to
pacyence. Then where lackyth mekenes lackyth
both obedience &amp; pacience: Then foloweth rebelly
on. &amp; wher men be vnable to rebell▪ oft they distroy
thēselfe for malyce. as of Cato Vticense declareth
saynt Austyn y• .xxiij. chapytre of y• fyrst boke of y•
cyte of god. whyche thrugh his pryde was so impacyent
&amp; inobedient. y• he wold rather distroy hȳself
than to lyue vnder the dominion of Iulius Cesar.
This dyde he. distroyed hȳself. &amp; here was thende
of his pride / For sure it is of Crystis sayeng (That

who exalte hymself: shall be mekyd. the .xiiij. chapy
               
                  •
               re
of Luke. ¶Seconde is sayde in this party. that
our sauyour Ihūs was obedyent. accomplysshyd &amp;
fulfylled the lawe. and preceptes of the same / whyche
oughte no duety to the lawe / And that I shall
shewe by this reason (The lawe was made for to
punysshe trangressours. the thyrde chapytre to the
Galathees / Now our sauyour Cryste dyde neuer
synne. ne yet gyle was ony tyme foūde in his mouthe.
the seconde chapytre of the fyrste epystle of saynt
Peter) Thenne folowyth that he was no thȳ
               ge
bounde to the lawe: And yet of his perfyte me
kenesse. for our meryte &amp; ensample: fulfylled he the
lawe as detter to the same. bothe in his circumcision.
in his oblacōn at the temple. in obseruynge 
                  •
               he
Pasche daye in Ierlm whan̄e he was of the aege
of .xij. yeres. alle conteyned in the seconde chapytre
of Luke / Of whyche holy and deuowte obedyence
of Ihū Cryste. sayth the blessyd bysshop Cirillus
the discyple of saynt Ierom this wyse. ¶O high
                  •
               
profundite of the grete wysdom &amp; scyence of god.
Cryste in our kynde was circumscided / whyche by
the auctorite of his godheed dayly circumcideth the
synnes in mennes hertes. He offrid ooutes to god / 
whiche in euery oblacōn made vnto god: is honou
               
                  •
               yd
egally wyth his fader. The lorde of Pasche
daye. mekely as a seruaunt obseruyth the pasche.
Tronthe obserueth the fygures of the lawe. The
maker of the
                  •
                lawe as god: kepyth y• same as man.

And ouer this. in obseruynge and kepynge of the
lawe: What dylygence. and what obedyence oure
sauyour Cryste Ihū dyde. apperyth in the, v. chapytre
of Mathu / Where he sayd vnto al his folowers.
¶Thynke ye not. that I am come in to this
worlde to dyssolue or breke the lawe. or the prophetes
/ I came not to breke them: but rather to complysshe
them. Wherupon sayth saynt Iohn Cri
               
                  •
               ostom
in his Omely (Cryste fulfyllyd the prophetes
in accomplysshynge alle the tronthes wryten of
hym by them) He fulfylled the lawes two wayes / 
Fyrste noo thynge trangressyng or brekynge. commaunded
in the lawe. seconde in iustifyenge synners
by fayth and charyte. that the lawe by the letter
myghte neuer doo. And soo prescice was he in
his obedience. and obseruaunce of the lawe. that he
sayde forth wythin the same chapytre (That the
leest Iote. or leest precepte of the lawe sholde not
passe hym vnobseruyd &amp; kepte) signyfyeng. That
he wolde kepe the lawe to euery poynt. and vttermoost
precept commaunded in the same. ¶I saye
commaunded in the lawe. Not in the / Talmodyke
tradicōns of the Iewes / whyche were besydes
And out of the lawe. Many in nombre. And grete
of charge. To whoos obseruaunce. the Iewes toke
gretter kepe. Ye &amp; gaue gretter obedyence. than̄e
to the lawe / As to ete theyr meete wyth wasshen. &amp;
clene hondes. The discyples of Cryste toke no hede
to this cerimony. The Iewes therfore blamyd

Cryste And sayd to hym / ¶Why breke thy dyscyples
the tradicions of our olde faders: They wasshe
not theyr hondes whan̄e they ete brede. Cryste
preterrynge obedience of the lawe to theyr tradicions:
Answeryd / Why breke ye ypocrytes the commanndementes
of god For ony of your tradicions
As who sayth (Ye sholde not soo doo: But compare
to gadre the lawe of god. And the tradicions
of man: ye sholde awaye be obedyent vnto the
lawe of god For ony tradicion of man) I fere me
we ben in the Iewes caas: We take more dylygence.
and ben more obedyent to mannys tradicion.
thanne to the lawe of god. Stomblynge atte a
strawe And lepynge ouer a blocke. Oure sauyour
sayde (That we oughte of duety obserue and kepe
the lawe / And not to leue the other vnkepte)
¶Lete therfore euery man doo his duety and folowe
Cryste in the waye of his cōmaundementes.
That he may truely synge &amp; say wyth Dauid the
prophete (good lorde I haue renne the waye of thy
cōmaundementes) He went before. he gaue vs ensā
               ple.
he callyd vs wyth him in obedyence to y• lawe.
to whyche he was not boūde / but for his mekenes.
and our example. as it is open in the .xiij. chapytre
of Iohn. where of his grete mekenes he wasshyd y•
fete of his discyples. sayenge vnto them. ¶I hauelgeuen
to you ensample. As I haue doon: so do
ye. For there is noo seruaunt gretter. 
                  •
               e better than
his lord and mayster. Signyfyeng that al Cristys

true seruauntes sholde walke wyth hym by meke
obedience. in obseruyng &amp; keping the lawes of god
¶Thyrde I say this party. y• our Ihū Cryste. our
lauyour was obedient to passyons &amp; deth. To passyons
as to hungre. thryste. colde. werynesse. to persecucōns
&amp; aduersyte. to blasphemye. &amp; detraccyon.
to thornes. scourges. naylles. to aysell &amp; galle. &amp; fynally
to deth) And to what deth trowe ye: playn to
then̄ the moost shamfull deth in the worlde. to the
deth of the crosse. the seconde chapitre to the Pphilipen
                  •
               .
¶Our sauyour Cryst sayth there the apostle
mekyd hymself. made obedyent vnto deth. ye &amp;
vnto the dethe of the crosse. / Why walkyd Cryste
trow ye thys streyte path of obedyence whyche ledeth
to deth / for hymself: naye. he nedyd not / syth
he neuer was the detter of deth / For as I sayd aboue.
he neuer dyde sȳne. ne gyle or dilceyte was ony
tyme foūde in his mouth. Then was it al for our
sake. whyche were synners
                  •
                &amp; of duty the dettours
of deth / As she with saynt Peter in the seconde chapytre
of his fyrst epistle (Cryst he sayth suffryd for
our synnes. leuyng you &amp; vs al example to folowe
his holy steppes) Then haue we here declaryd of
our Ihūs Cryst. y• the same whiche nighed to man
hȳ sauyng by his grete power. shewed in the actes
of creacōn. Incarnacōn. &amp; mynystracōn / whose fygure
was Ihūs Naue. The same Ihūs hath walkyd
 wt man in our kynde. hym sauyng by perfyte
obedience. to his frendes &amp; other astates. to y• lawes

&amp; cōmaundementes. to passyons &amp; deth of y• crosse / 
Whose fygure was Ihūs Iosedech: ¶Of whyche
two pryncypall partyes. doth folowe a corelari
That the same Ihūs whyche nyghed to mankynde.
whyche walkyd wyth mankynde. hath fynally
bi his wysdom broughte mankynde to euerlastyng
reste in heuen / whose fygure was (Ihūs fili
                     •
                  
               
sirach (whyche by his. wysdom hath gretly holpen
&amp; sauyd the people of god / But neuer lyke to
our Ihūs Cryste / For as Ihūs Naue was but a fygure
of power &amp; strengthe. Ihūs Iosedech a fygure
of holy obedyence / So was Ihūs Sirach but a fygure
of the wysdom of Cryste / whyche is the eternall.
&amp; substancyall wysdom of god y• fader (attaynyng
strongly from ende to ende. &amp; delectably allethynges
disposyng. The .viij. chapytre of sapien
                  •
                /
To whose power. no creature may resiste. ¶Syth
all creatures be at his cōmaundement. &amp; to him obedyent.
y• .xiij. chapytre of Hes
                  •
                / For whose meke
&amp; holy obedyence. god the fader hath hym exaltid / 
&amp; geuen to hym a name aboue all the names in y•
worlde. Syth to the holy name of Ihūs: all creatures
of duty do bowe &amp; obeye bothe of heuen. erthe.
&amp; hell. The seconde chapitre to the Philipen? / By
whose infinyte wysdom all y• worlde is sauyd. hȳ
               selfe
sayenge in the .xij. chapytre of Iohn (Whan I
am lyfte vp in the crosse there deyenge for man. I
shall drawe all the worlde vnto me Wherupon sayth
saynt Austin / as thouh our sauyour shold say

(after my deth. &amp; my resurreccōn. I shall ascende to
my fader in heuen. &amp; drawe my chosen seruauntes
vnto me) Syth by stedfast fayth. of duty. the membres
must folowe the heed: yet I saye he wysli hath
disposyd. y• all his seruauntes &amp; membres shold be
obedient: &amp; suffre in this worlde pressure: &amp; passions
as hymselfe dyde. ¶In this worlde sayd he to all
his seruauntes. ye shall haue pressure &amp; persecucōn
the .xvi. chapytre of Iohn. And saynt Poule in the
thyrde chapitre of the seconde epystle vnto Timothe
(All those whyche in this worlde woll lyue the
meke seruauntes of god: must nedes suffre perse
                  •
               ncōn
&amp; aduersyte) For whyche lytyll labour &amp; shorte
trowble in this lyf: all his true seruauntes shall haue
euerlastyng rewarde &amp; rest in henen. hȳself thys
promysed whyche may not erre ne faylle (Ye shall
sayth our sauyour. receyue an hundryd folde more
than ye paye or geue. &amp; wyth all ye shall haue full
possessyon of euerlastynge lyfe. the .xix. chapytre of
Mathu / whiche graunt vnto vs. the same our sauy
our Ihūs Cryste. AMEN
            ¶Per reuerendū doctorē 
               Ric fitz Iames
         
      
      
         
            ¶Enprynted at Westmestre by Wynkyn de Word
         
         
            
            
               
            
            
         
      
   

