
   
      
         
            A Batchelers resolution, or, Have among you now, widowes or maydes ... to the tune of The blazing torch.
         
         
            
               1629
            
         
         Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A00942
            STC 1105.5
            ESTC S3096
            33142627
            ocm 33142627
            28155
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A00942)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28155)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1862:40)
         
         
            
               
                  A Batchelers resolution, or, Have among you now, widowes or maydes ... to the tune of The blazing torch.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  
               
                  A. Mathewes?
                  [S.l. :
                  1629?]
               
               
                  Publisher and date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).
                  Contains three illustrations.
                  Right half of sheet contains "The second part. To the same tune."
                  Imperfect: stained, creased and torn, with loss of print. Best copy available for photographing.
                  Reproduction of original in: Pepys Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Ballads, English --  17th century.
               Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-12
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2003-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            A Batchelers Resolution. OR
            
               Haue among you now, Widowes or Maydes,
               For I come a woing as Fancie perswades.
               I must haue a Wife, be she Older or Younger,
               For I cannot, nor will not lye alone any longer.
            
            To the tune of, The Blazing Torch.
            
               
            
            
               
                  A Batchelour I haue béene long,
               and had no minde to marry,
               But now I finde it did me wrong
               that I so long did tarry,
               Therefore I will a wooing ride,
               there's many married younger,
               Where shall I goe to s
                     •
                  ke a Bride?
               
                  Ile lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               So many sinnes are incident
               vnto a single life,
               That I all danger to pr
                     •
                  uent
               with spéede will seeke a Wife;
               If I with Women chance to drinke
               I'me call'd a 
                     •
                  utton-monger,
               But now Ile stop their mouthes I thinke
               
                  And lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               O Fate send me a handsome Lasse
               that I can fancy well,
               For Portion Ile not greatly passe,
               though Money heares the bell▪
               
               Loue now adayes with Gold is bought
               but I'me no Money-monger.
               Giue mee a Wife, though shee's worth nought
               
                  Ile lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               Yet if she chance to prooue a Slut,
               a Scold, or else a Whore,
               That could not chuse but be a cut,
               and 
                     〈◊〉
                   me very sore,
               A Slut would make me loath my meate
               were I halfe dead with hunger,
               But I must leaue this fond conceate,
               
                  And lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               What if she should a Wanton be,
               a
                     〈…〉
                  ake my forehead ake?
               Oh that would be a griefe to me,
               such wrongs few men will take,
               For iealousie is of such force,
               no passion can be stronger,
               But be she better, be she worse,
               
                  Ile lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               If iealous she shall be of me,
               that were as great a spight,
               Then should we seldome quiet be,
               but quarrell day and night,
               She'd thinke my loue from her did range
               though I nere meant to wrong her,
               Yet this shall not my humour change,
               
                  Ile lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               What shall I doe to chuse a wife
               in euery thing compleate?
               Should I in searching spend my life,
               i'would prooue a taske to great,
               No Man can finde a Woman so,
               the older nor the younger,
               Ile take my chance as others doe,
               
                  And lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               Yet will I chuse the best I can,
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     oue send me luck in chusing,
               And craue the counsell of some man
               whose counsels worth the vsing:
               If she prooue good I shall be glad,
               and vow Ile neuer wrong her,
               Yet am resolued good or bad
               
                  To lye alone no longer.
               
            
            
               
               The second Part. To the same tune.
               
                  
               
               
                  I
                        •
                     e be contented with my lot,
                  How euer it befall,
                  Yet if she prooue a drunken sot,
                  
                     
                        •••
                     ill grieue me worst of all,
                  Then I my selfe must drinke small-béere,
                  and she must drinke the stronger,
                  Though't cost me twenty pounds a yeare,
                  
                     Ile lye alone no longer.
                  
               
               
                  This is the onely time I know,
                  for Young-men to get Wiues,
                  Thou say that Maides and Widowes now
                  fo
                        •
                      Husbands daily striues,
                  The
                        •••
                     ore I shall be quickly sped,
                  sith both for Husbands hunger,
                  with any man th
                        •
                     yle quickly wed,
                  
                     Theyle lye alone no longer.
                  
               
               
                  Be shee a widdow or a Maiyde,
                  I doe not greatly passe,
                  A withered Crone whose bla
                        •
                     d's decayde,
                  or a young li
                        •
                     ely Lasse:
                  One that is rich or one that's poore,
                  a feeble, or a stronger:
                  An honest woman or a whore,
                  
                     Ile lye alone no longer.
                  
               
               
                  But ye
                        •
                      if I 
                        〈◊〉
                      choice may haue
                  a Mayde  
                        •
                     ould b
                        •
                      my wife,
                  I would not be a Widowes slaue,
                  Ide rather loose my life:
                  If I should wed a Widow old,
                  I 
                        •
                     ad better take a younger,
                  For Widowes will not be contrould,
                  
                     Yet I can stay no longer.
                  
               
               
                  If she should haue a stinking breath
                  I neuer should abide her,
                  For tha
                        •
                      to me is worse then death,
                  I had rather touch a Spider:
                  But thats a fault may soone be smelt,
                  s
                        •
                     e Aiax smels no stronger:
                  
                     
                        •
                     efore I
                        •
                     e take one with such fault,
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         lye alone yet longer
                  
               
               
                  If shée chance to prooue a Scould,
                  her tongue will bréede my strife,
                  Then I must looke to be contrould,
                  and curbed by my Wife:
                  A Scould of women is the worst,
                  shele force a man to wrong her:
                  Therefore Ile try all humors first,
                  
                     And lye alone no longer.
                  
               
               
                  Some men perhaps may wonder, why
                  my minde runnes so on Marriage,
                  To him that askes me, I reply,
                  'tis for my honest carriage:
                  For liue a young man nere so chaste,
                  he's counted a Whoremonger:
                  Therefore Ile get a Wife in haste,
                  
                     And lye alone no longer.
                  
               
               
                  Although my Wife be none oth best,
                  yet I must be content:
                  I shall as well speede as the rest,
                  whith 'bout this action went:
                  I am not first that matched ill,
                  therefore it is no wonder:
                  Ile keepe my resolution still,
                  
                     And lye alone no longer.
                  
               
               
                  I trust I shall with one be sped,
                  that doth deserue my loue:
                  If I with such a Woman wed,
                  I sweare by mighty loue,
                  
                  That ere she any thing should 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  Ile suffer colde and hunger:
                  Though she had scant cloathes
                  
                     Ide lye alone no longer.
                  
               
               
                  You that my resolution hear
                  iudge whether I deserue
                  To haue a Wife that loue
                  and would my will obser
                        •
                     
                  
                  Were she a Widdow or a 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  an Elder, or a Younger
                  My Wedding should not be
                  
                     
                        〈1 line〉
                     
                  
               
            
         
      
   

