
   
      
         
            The bitter vvaters of Babylon, or The miserable estate of the citizens of Sion considered by the confusion of all things in this world.
            Forsyth, James, fl. 1615-1619.
         
         
            
               1615
            
         
         Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01077
            STC 11191
            ESTC S121939
            99857095
            99857095
            22767
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01077)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22767)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:13)
         
         
            
               
                  The bitter vvaters of Babylon, or The miserable estate of the citizens of Sion considered by the confusion of all things in this world.
                  Forsyth, James, fl. 1615-1619.
               
               [8], 32 p.   
               
                  Printed by Edw. Griffin for Ralph Mab, and are to bee sold in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Grey-hound,
                  London :
                  1615.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Iames Forsyth.
                  A sermon.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-10
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2008-10
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE BITTER WATERS OF BABYLON, OR THE MISERABLE Eſtate of the Citizens of SION: Conſidered by the confuſion of all things in this world.
            
            
               PROV. 22. 3.
               
                  A prudent man ſeeth the plague, and hideth himſelfe: but the fooliſh goe on ſtill, and are puniſhed.
               
            
            
               HIERON: in lib. de hom. perfecto.
               
                  Omnes ſumus in minimis cauti, in maximis negligentes; hoc ita
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      fit, quia vbi vera vita ſit ignor amus.
               
            
            LONDON, Printed by Edw. Griffin for Ralph Mab, and are to bee ſold in Pauls Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Grey-hound, 1615.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, RIGHT Vertuous, and truely Religious, IOHN, Lord RAMSEY, 
                  Ʋicount Hadington; and to the true Noble, and very Induſtrious Ladie, ELIZABETH, the Vicounteſſe, his moſt louing Wife: All true happines in this life, and eternall glorie in the life to come.
            
            
               Right Honourable:
            
            
               I Need not be in doubt (as many men be) to chuſe a fit Perſonage to patronize this mine Embrio, or my firſt Crude, and vndigeſted meditations;

ſeeing that (vnder God) I haue from your Honours my preſent earthly being: and therefore may iuſtly challenge as much intereſt in mee as Paul did in Philémon, both my ſelfe and all my labours: for it hath beene the gracious ſplendor of your Honourable kinde fauours, that hath ſo bountifully ſhined vpon ſo baſe an obiect, (not through any deſerts of mine obtained) Alaſſe, I am too priuy vnto mine owne wants, qui rudis &amp; iners: not worthy to bee named the ſame day with learned men: but that the bright Rayes of your Honourable kinde fauour in this, are like vnto the Royall Sun beames, that ſhine as bright in the poore mans cottage, as in the Kings pallace. Your worthineſſe in your

               Honorable attempts in promoting learning &amp; religion, is an euident proofe of your godly &amp; religious diſpoſition: without flattery, theſe I profeſſe, which haue had a more particular experience of your gracious fauors: (For they need not falſe praiſes that abound with true,) And I appeale vnto al thoſe that haue had a triall of your Honorable fauours: which freely haue beene found amongſt a great number both of inborne &amp; forreiners: wherby your honorable names may be well regiſtred amongſt the worthies in this age, which no doubt, will remaine in all ages, &amp; neuer be blotted out in your honourable poſterity. And leſt that I ſhould incur the cenſure of ingratitude, (which is a monſter by nature) for all kindneſſes receiued:

I haue caſt this ſmal mite into your treaſury: that as I walke vnder the the ſafegard of your honorable roofe I may goe in ſafety heerein vnder your Honors tuition: beſeeching your Honors to accept of it as our Sauiour Chriſt did the poore widdowes gift, becauſe I giue all that I haue, hoping that you will not regard the meanneſſe of the gift, ſo much as the minde of the giuer, which if I louingly find in your gracious acceptance, I ſhall thinke my ſelfe moſt happy in all mine eſſaies: &amp; ſhall daily pray (as by duty obliged) vnto the God of mercy, for your Honors happineſſe in this life, and euerlaſting happineſſe in the life to come.
            
               Your Honours moſt humble and dutifull
Chaplaine and ſeruant in the Lord
JAMES FORSYTH.
            
         
         
            
            To the Chriſtian Reader.
            
               MAruell not (gentle Reader) that I haue diuulged theſe my mean meditations; being preched in that Place from whence daily doth drop moſt ſweet honny of diuine eloquence: ſince that moſt of the learned that repaire thither, are vnwilling to publiſh their workes; by reaſon of the multiplicity of printed ſermons, that proceed from thence. There be two reaſons that induce me heereunto: The one is, the encouragement I had by the Audience, that day whereon it was deliuered: And ſecondly, the vrgent entreaty of many of my eſpeciall friends; vnto whom I owe my ſelfe and all ſeruice. Looke not for eloquence, according to thine expectation; proceeding from ſuch an eminent place: For I came not with eloquence of words; but euidence of the ſpirit: to perſwade men and women to lament their lewd-led-life, that by their vnfain dcontrition; they may preuent Gods viſitation in Iuſtice, for their tranſgreſsions, by the example of theſe Iſraelites beeing captiuated for their offences. If any thing heerein contained, in thy iudgement, bee too tart and bitter: Conſider with what weapons, I, and all Gods faithfull Ministers, do
                  •
                come into the field to fight againſt Gods enemies; the two-edged ſword of Gods Spirit doth diuide betweene the Carnall and Spirituall man: the ſtone that Dauid tooke

vp againſt Goliah did ſinke ſuddenly into his temples. The diſeaſes of theſe times wherein we liue, require ſuch corraſiues and bitter potions: for we are like vnto Babel that will not be cured. When thou readeſt thoſe things; gadde not abroad, nor aime thou not at other men: deſcend into thine owne Conſcience, and feeling thy ſelfe wounded, apply theſe warily vnto thine own ſoule: and ſo ſhalt thou be healed of thine infirmity. That this conſideration may work ſome zeale of Gods glory in thee; and that thou mayſt daily encreaſe more &amp; more in the knowledge of his waies, I ſhall (as by duty bound, vnto all faithfull Chriſtians) daily pray for thy happineſſe in this life, and eternall glory in the life to come with Ieſus Chriſt, and his holy Angels. Amen.
            
               Thine in the Lord
IAMES FORSYTH.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               IT hath been the manner of moſt of the Anncient, in former time; and at this day is retained in the Church, as a forme, amongſt the beſt D
                     •
                  anes; to chuſe a text fitted for the time: and to ſpeake out of the Scripture appointed for the day. Which order if I had obſerued, my text ſhould haue entreated, of mirth and melodie, both in reſpect of the ſeaſon of the yeare; and occaſion of the feaſt; for of all ſeaſons, this is moſt ſweete, pleaſant, and deliciouſe, Iam floridu aeſtas, quae ſpicea ſerta 
               Ouid. 2. Meta▪
                
               gerit, Now it is floriſhing ſummer, which brings foorth the fragrant flowers: Nay this the merry moneth of May: if the occaſion of the feaſt had ledde me to my text, the matter had been me odious, for by the reuolution of this time euery yeare, is ſpecified vnto vs; the comfort which we receiue by that ſweete Comforter, ſent downe by Ieſus Act. 2. 1. 2. Chriſt vpon the Apoſtles in viſible ſignes, wherefore the Auncient in their Lythargie did tearme it a glorious time: 
               In Miſſa pr
                     •
                   a
                     •
                  e. 
               glorioſum hunc feciſts diem, was their Antheme; And wee obſeruing the ſame in our Church pray the Lord to grant that we may reioice in his holy comfort, in the Collect for Collect vpon W
                     •…
                  
                  mu
                     •
                  day. the day: either of which, if I had regarded, then my ſong had been ſolacious, or a ſong of degrees. But, I conſidering the iniquities of the time, and knowing that m
                     •
                  nare readie to enlarge their hearts too much with worldly mirth, and eſpecially about this time of the year, wherfore I haue changed my note into an Elegiacall tune, which ſounds nothing but weeping, mourning, and lamentation for worldly mirth is like vnto pure wine, which not being mingled with ſome other 
                  •
               cour, will draw drunkenneſſe vpon the receiuer, in like manner earthly melody not being tempered

with a meditation of death, or a conſideration of a better life, it will drowne the affecter with a greedie deſire thereafter, and ouerwhelme him with an obliuion of his Creator: wherefore our Sauiour tooke vp a mournfull ſong in the midſt of the peoples melodie, in his iourney to Ieruſalem; and herefore, it is, that I haue choſen a dolefull Luke. 19. 41. ditty, which I am (by Gods aſſiſtance) to read vnto your godly audience, which may reſtraine our too much pleaſure in worldly vanity.
         
         
            
               PSALME 137. 1.
               
                  By the riuers of Babylon we ſate, and wept: when we remembred Syon.
               
            
            
               
                  ABrahams ſeruant receiuing a meſſage Gen. 24. 15. from his Maſter, to go into his fathers houſe, and chuſe a wife of his owne kindred for his ſonne Iſaacke: did walke along diligently, and ſta
                  •
               ed no where, vntill he came vnto the Well, whereout the women came to draw water, and there taken vp his reſt, found in that place his iourney proſperous; to his Maſters great comfort, and Iſaac
                     ••
                  
                great profit as afterward did appeare. Euen ſo I receiuing a commiſſion, from the Dioceſan of this Sea, to come to this place: did paſſe along by the ſweete waters of holy write, willing to finde out a fit place to bathe your ſoules in, tooke vp my reſt no where, vntill I came to the bitter waters of Babylon, and there finding the children of God mourning vnder captiuitie for a remembrance of their former happineſſe; I haue addreſſed my ſelfe to finde out the cauſe of their great miſerie, in their mournefull behauiour, that thereout, I may draw ſome matter for our great comfort,

and conſolation. Nunquid fily ſponſi lugerepoſſunt, quamdiueſt 
               M
                     ••
                  h. 9. 15. 
               cum illis ſponſus, ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt in an other caſe, can the children of the bride chamber mourne as long as the bride-groome is with them; how can this text fit theſe times wherein we liue, (may ſome ſay) ſeeing we haue peace within our borders there is no leading into captiuitie, nor no complaining in our ſtrectes, can this text ſet forth Pſal 144. 14. the iniquities of the time, wherein ſinne doth abound euery where? yes, verely: and that very fitly: for although now we haue peace and tranquillitie, yet it was the counſell of wiſe Ioſeph vnto the King of Aegypt, that in time of Gen. 41. 
                     •
                  6. plentie, he ſhould prouide for the famine to come: wee read of the Syrens that in faire weather they weepe, and in ſtorme they reioice, thinking that after faire weather there wilbe a turbulent tempeſt, but after a full ſtorme, a ſtill caline, ſic ut turgidum tran quillum mare, ſic pacem bellum ſequitur, as a boiſterous ſea followeth a ſmooth water, ſo warre commonly ſucceedeth a long peace, wherefore the 1 Cor. 10 12. Apoſtle Saint Peter warneth euery one that ſtands to take heede, leaſt he fall, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                And it is I 
                     •…
                  ain locum &amp; Ag
                     •…
                  . the opinion of ſome diuines that the Prophet Dauid doth write this Pſalme many yeares before their captiuitie, to giue them a ſight of their future miſerie; Propheta enimres futuras, &amp; praeteritas ſaepiſſime tanquam preſentes narrat, for a Prophet many times doth ſhew thinges paſt, and to come, as though they were preſent. Againe wickedneſſe being the cauſe of their wretchedneſſe, and ſinae an occaſion of their captiuity the conſideration whereof, will moue no doubt euery Chriſtian mans heart with a Remorſe for his former lewde led life: leaſt his impious and wicked behauiour draw vpon him a greater miſerie. And laſtly if we will beleeue the auncient writers, and ſome of the Moderne there is more myſtically meant, then is literally vnderſtood, 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   Treſſer. 3. 
               Frange osliterae, &amp; inuenies medullam intelligent
                     ••
                  , break the bone of the letter, and within thou ſhall finde a marrow of ſpirituall matter, Puta lamentationem Eccleſiae militant is in hac terra, namely the lamentation of the Church militant
               
afflicted in this world, which mourning may be well ſpecified by their reall weeping. Super flumina Babilonis 
                     •
                  llic ſedimus &amp; fl
                     •
                  uimus, &amp;c. By the riuers of Babylon we ſate and wept, when we remembred Sion.
            
            The people of Iſrael being deliuered from vnder the bondage of Egipt, and tyrannie of Pharaoh with a mighty hand, led along by a ſafe conduct thorough the wildernes; and at laſt by the prouidence of God brought, into that bleſſed land that did flow with milke and honnie; where being in reſt they built vnto themſelues ſtrong holdes, forts and citties for their ſafegard, and habitation; for the which benefits the Lord doth deſire onely, that they obſerue his lawes, and marke his ſtatutes to keepe them; that they might inherit that good land: otherwiſe, if by their negligence therein, they did moue his wrath againſt them, then would he vtterly deſtroy them: as afterward came to paſſe, and at this day doth appeare; for being placed in proſperitie, and hauing all things according to their hearts deſire, they following the perſwa
                  •
               ion of their wicked rulers, ſuch as Ieroboam, Ahab, Ieho
                     •
                  akim, Z
                     •
                  dechi
                     •
                  , and others 1. King. 12. 28. &amp; 18. &amp; 23. 37. ſpent their daies in van
                     •
                  ie in working wickedneſſe; and worſhipping the workes of their owne hand; their hearts being fat, and groſſe with 
                  
                     •
                  atneſſe, forgot God that made 
               Deut. 15. 32. 
               them, and the ſtrong God of their ſaluation. Wherefore the Lord did giue them ouer into the hands of their enemies many times to be ouercome of them. Many times were 2. King 24. &amp; 25. &amp; Ier. 22. 9. they beſet and ſome of their tribes taken, as of Ephraim and Nepthalin: the Citie of Samaria being by them inhabited, was of the King of Syria enuironed, and brought to Eſa 8. &amp; Eſa. 9. 9. a great famine: the City of Ieruſalem often beſieged: as once of Antiochus, who did ranſacke the Citie, ſpoile the temple of her ornaments; and brought many of the inhabitants 
               1. Macab. 1. 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                to great miſerie. But for all this, they did ſtill continue in their crooked waies, in working wickedneſſe, following the ſteppes of Manaſſes, and doing according to all 2. King. 24. 3. that he did, wherefore at laſt the Lord did ſuffer Nebuk
                     •
                  d
                  
                     •
                  noſer the King of Babell with a great army of the Caldaeans
               
to come vpon them, and carrie them away captiues into Babylon, where they did remaine for the ſpace of ſeuentie yeares: ſo that it is the opinion of the moſt Diuines that this Pſalme was compoſed after their returning from captiuitie, to put them in minde of their former miſerie, which they then did ſuffer. although ſome are of the opinion that it was made long before, as before hath been ſaid.
            In the Hebrew text wee haue no tide prefixed vnto his Pſalme, but in the Greeke copies there is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , And in the old Latine, Pſalma
                     •
                   Dauid proper 
                     •…
                  remiam. Theodoret doth reiect this as too audacious to bee 
                  
                     •…
                  anu
                     •
                  . 
                     〈…〉
                  . prefixed, the reaſon he giues is: becauſe ſere
                     •…
                  
                was neuer in Babylon; but if yee marke the title aright, you ſhall not finde any thing, wherby he doth allo word 
                  •
               a
                  •
               low his being in Babylon, but only in that this Pſalme doth agree with the lam
                     ••
                  nations which Ieremie made of their exp
                  •
               iuit
                  •
               e by the ſpirit of propheſie, therefore not to be ſo much reiected. There is ſomething found in an Hebrew copie which will Ag
                     •…
                  
                well agree with this title, as, when Nab
                     •
                  z
                     •…
                  n, Nebuchadon
                     •
                  ſer the king; chiefe Steward did b
                  •…
               ng Ieremie along, with the people into the view of Babel: he put him to his choiſe, wher her he would remaine with the people in miſerie; or returne backe againe to Ieruſalem there to haue his libertie, and he chuſing rather to returne for to enioy his libertie, the people for his abſence did take vp this mournefull ſong, ſuper 
                     •…
                  na Babylonis &amp;c. by the w
                     •…
                  s of Babylon. But for the title, or the writer it is not ſo materiall, as to know that the ſpirit of God was the enditer hereof, and that it was written for our inſtruction, quae unque 
               1. Cor. 10. 11. 
               ſcripta ad noſtr
                     •
                  m aedificationem ſcripta, ſaith the Apoſtle Saint Paul, whatſoeuer things are written, are for our learning vpon whom the endes of the world are come.
            
               This whole Pſalme diuided is two fold

                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        , Narrati
                              •
                           us, a Narration of Diuiſion or parts. a ſtory, to the ſeuenth verſe.
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        , Precati
                              •
                           us, or a praier, againſt their enemies, to the end.
                  
               
               
                  
This verſe being part of the Narratiue part it containes two things

                     Their Affliction.
                     
                     Their Affection.
                     
                  
               
               In their affliction two things

                     Their Action.
                     
                     The places ſcituation.
                     
                  
               
               The Action two fold

                     Their geſture, ſedimus, wee ſate.
                     
                     Their mournefull behauiour, fleuimus, we wept.
                     
                  
               
               The places ſcituation two fold

                     Generall, Babel.
                     
                     particular, by the riuers of Babel
                     
                  
               
               Their Affection in two things

                     The manner by introduction, remember.
                     
                     The matter by deſcription, Sion.
                     
                  
               
            
            But right honorable, right worſhipfull, and welbeloued, if you will vouchſafe to conſider the words verbatim or diuiſim euery one by it ſelfe, you ſhall finde the whole ſtorie very patheticall, and full of pitie.
            
            
               1 They were not admitted to dwell in their citties nor townes, but expoſde to the riuers ſide, therefore pitifull.
               
               2 The place was barbarouſe and idolatrouſe where they could haue no ſolace to their ſoule being Babel, therefore pitifull.
               
               3 The time of their miſerie not ſhort, but for a long ſpace which is ſignified by the word ſitting, therefore pitifull.
               
               4 All the time of their captiuitie, they haue no comfort, for they ſpend their whole time in Lamentation, therefore pitifull.
               
               5 It is not the preſent miſerie that doth afflict them, but a remembrance of their former happineſſe, therefore pitifull.
               
               6 Neither any worldly want, that doth grieue them but the defect of the word which they had formerly

that doth onely vexe them, therefore pitifull.
                  
                     So that whether you diſmember them into parts, or collect them into a briefe ſ
                              •
                           mm
                              •
                           ,
                        
                           The totall ſhalbe nothing but pitie, paſſion and matter of Lamentation.
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            And firſt of their firſt action, which is ſet downe in 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  od. 12. 
                     〈…〉
                  . their geſture, wherein we haue the diutuinitie of the time. If they had ſtood vpon there feete with their ſtaue, in their hands and their loynes gift, like the Iſraelites at caring of the Paſ
                     •
                  ouer, they might had ſome hope of their de
                  •…
               erance. Or if they had made any progreſſe at all, although it had beene with neuer ſo ſlow a pace, by remoouing of their tent euery day as they did in the wilderneſſe▪
                yet after the ſpace of forty yeares, they might had hope to come to their wiſhed home; but to be brought to Babel that barbarouſe place, and thither to the bankeſide of their Riuers, their recouerie is vncertaine, for their deliuerance at the ſooneſt is after the ſpace of ſeuentie yeares propheſied by the Prophet Ieremie; to go forward they cannot, ſuper ſ
                     •
                  umina ſedent, they ſit by the riuers ſide, to go backeward they Ierem. 25 11. are not able for they are detained in captiuitie, if they turne to either hand, to paſſe thorough their countrey, the people is barbarouſe, the kingdome is Caldea, the prouince Babel, ſedere oportet, they muſt ſir downe by their bankes, which doth ſignifie a diuturnitie of time. A malefactor S
                     •…
                  . being apprehended vpon ſome heinous crime, and brought before a Iudge, ſo long as he is vnconuicted he will haue ſome hope of his deliuerie, may after ſentence paſt, he will thinke all the way as he goeth to the place of torment, that ſome friend or other will vſe ſome meanes to repriue him; but when he comes to the place of execution, ſeeing all hope paſt, nec vltra ſpes eſt, he takes vp his reſolution ſinging this ſtrange dutie of illic ſedimus, remembring his former time which he ſpent in his wicked waies, which cannot be recalled, for the ſentence is irreuocable, all meanes fallible, vndergo he muſt for a iuſt recompence

of his euill deedes: ſedere oportet doth much perplex him as it doth here the 
                  
                     •…
                  tes. For the great time that they ſpent in decking and decoring of their Idols, after the manner of the heathen round about them, they did worſhippe the workes of their owne handes and went a whoring after ſtrange gods. Now haue they time enough ab al
                     •…
                  eg
                     •…
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , being freed from all buſineſſe, to crie peccaui if that can any way auaile them. Much time did they ſpend in laſciuiouſneſſe, rioting, and prophaneſſe, ſomtime, in pleaſing their pallate with daintie rare, ſometimes in ſwilling of their paunch with the deluge of drunkenneſſe, to ſtirre vp their concupi'cible luſt to wantonneſſe: they ſaie downe to eate and drinke and roſevp to play. Much time did they ſpend in pride and vanitie; in decking their bodies, and currying of their Carkaſſes, according Cor. 1. 10. 7. to their phantaſticall humours, for an o
                  •
               tentation of their Lucifer-like ſpirits: Wee haue heard of the pride of 
               Eſa. 16. 6. 
               Moab, of his pride, and arrogantie, for he is very proude. But now they haue time enough to tame their fleſh, and to bring their bodies into ſubiection: their pride is turned into pouertie, their gay▪ clothing into 
                  •
               ack-cloth, and aſhes, a fit liuery for their mournfull habite: ſic hi qui noluere per Prophetas ſedari, iam extorres &amp; contempti ſedent: ſo that they that before would not be ruled by the Prophets and warned of them, now ſit in baniſhment forſaken, and contemned of all men. This puniſhment doth the Lord threaten to come vpon the people for the pride of the women, &amp; their wickednes, 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   as erit deſolata &amp; in terra ſedebit, their citie ſhall be deſolate, and the people ſhall Eſa. 3. 26. ſit ſolitarie vpon the ground, the puniſhment that the ſpirit doth inflict vpon that whore, that hath made the whole world drunke with her fornications, is this, quantum fuit in delicijs tantum date illi tormentum, In a much as ſhe liued in Apo. 18. 7. pleaſure, in ſo much giue her torment, and ſorrow, for the long time that they ſpent in plentie, they ſpend the reſt of their time in penurie, for taking their pleaſure in full meaſure; Now are they perplexed with ſorrow aboue meaſure,

               illic ſedimus is worthy of obſeruation, and remarkable here in this place.
            Remember this all ye that take ſo much delight, in pampering your fleſh, and ſpend ſo much time in beautifying your bodies: 
                     •
                  o
                     •
                   qui tamd
                     ••
                   in delicus i
                     •
                  m ſedetis: you that ſit ſo long in your delights; if you repent not in time, and take heede vnto your waies: olim ſed
                     •…
                   in panis, you ſhall end, and conſummate your daies euerlaſtingly in hell torments, Diue
                     •
                  , while he liued, fared deliciouſly euery Luke. 
                     〈…〉
                  
                day: and the text tels vs that he was gorgeouſly apparelled: did he take ſuch delight in his decking, or did he ſpend ſo much time, in trimming of his body, as the young gallants of theſe times; ſurely I thinke yes, for Abraham doth vpbraid him herewith, Recordare mi ſilt, tu bona recepiſts in vit a 
               V
                     •…
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                
               tua: Remember my ſonne that thou in thy life time didſt take thy pleaſure, and Lazarus receiued paine: wherefore thou art to mented, and he comforted; I haue read in a ſtorie of a certaine man named Pambo, that on a time 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                looking out at a window, and perceiuing a woman ſpend a great time in trimming of her ſelfe, fell a weeping; and being demanded the cauſe, anſwered, haue not I great cauſe to weepe; to ſee yonder worme, conſuming ſo long time in decking of her vglie carkaſe, to the ſight of man: and I ſpend ſo ſmall time in preparing my ſoule to God. If this man were aliue in theſe daies he would do nothing but weepe and lament; for let a man caſt his eies euerie where, vpon the Clergie and Laytie, Prieſt and people, and he ſhall ſee all men taken in loue with their foule carkaſſes; but their ſoules they little regard: women will ſpend the whole halfe day in poudring, painting, and frizling of their lockes to the luſtfull aſpect of the paſſers by: and our young Gentlemen ſcorne that the weaker veſſels, ſhould out go them in theſe trickes; they will rather ſpend the whole day in phinifying of their phantaſticall phiſnomies to ſatisfie their luſtfull Miſtris eye, and not once a weeke beſtow one ſmoothing of their ſoules: which if they doe by comming to the church once a week it is but for a ſhew

only like their ſpangled roſes; and gliſtering garters; it is 
                  •
               or no profit: but let them know that although now they ſpend their time in pleaſure, the time ſhall come that illie ſedimus the remembrance of it ſhall torment them aboue meaſure, as it doth here in this place the Iſraelites: and ſo I proceede to the ſecond action.
            By their ſecond action their miſerie is much aggrauated, 
                  
                     
                        〈1 line〉
                      par qu
                        •
                     ſium 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   ſecond 
                     〈◊〉
                   a mou
                     ••
                  
                  
                  
                     •…
                   
                  
                     •…
                  our. for although they had been detained for a long time in captiuitie; and yet had had all neceſſaries to comfort them; their caſe had not been ſo miſerable: but being depriued of their bodily ſuſtenance, remaining in captiuitie: and abridged of their ſoules ſolace, which was the comfort they receiued in Sion: they ſpend their whole daies in lamentation: cura dolor
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   anim
                     ••
                  , alimenta fuere. Teares were their meate and drinke night and day; their eſtate is moſt pittifull; The eye is the mindes meſſenger, whereby wee conceiue the imagination thereof: a ſorrow bred in the heart, can by no meanes be better expreſſed then by an inundation of teares: dum bene ſe habebant, ne l
                     ••
                   hryma quidem ab illis extorqueri poterat: While they liued in proſperitie, their could not one teare be drawne from them: 
                  
                     •
                  gnaui enim, &amp; ſtolidi eſt, lachrymas effundere: it is the ſigne of a Daſtard, to weepe like a childe: ſed aduerſa fortuna, facile ri
                     •
                  ulos emittunt: but now being ſent into baniſhment they ſend forth a fountaine of teares. Saint Ambroſe doth very well note the greatneſſe of Peters griefe; in that hee did weepe, and vtter no words; cur
                     •
                   l
                     •
                  ues loquuntur, ingentes 
               Ambroſ: 
                     •
                  n lathrymas Petri. 
               ſtupent: The greater our griefe is, the more ſilent we are, they weepe vnceſſantly, but not a word they do vtter: to expreſſe thei
                  •
                fulneſſe of griefe: fleuimus is ſufficient to ſet it forth. There be three ſorts of teares obſerued of the auncients, which may be well exemplified by the authority of Scripture.
            
               Deuotionis,
               Compaſſionis, Labrymarum 
                        〈◊〉
                      gener
                        •
                     .
               
               Et contritionis,
            
            
               That is

                     Of deuotion.
                     Of compaſſion.
                     And of contrition.
                  
               
            
            
               
Teares of Deuotion wee haue in Dauid, who out of an 1. 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . Pſal. 6. 6. holy deuotion did water his couch night and day with his teares. Teares of compaſſion we haue in Ieremie; that doth compaſſionately weepe, for the miſeries of other men. 2. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
               O that mine head were a well of water and my eyes a fountaine 
               
                  
                     ••
                  rem. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 1. 2. 
               of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſtaine of the daughters of Sion; Likewiſe in Dauid, mine eies guſh out with 
               Pſal. 119. 136. 
               riuers of water becauſe men keepe not thy law. Teares of contrition 
               3. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . we haue in Peter, who after he had remembred, the error of his imbecillity, went out of the place, and wept bitterly. All which three ſorts if we conſider their teares Math. 16. 75. aright, we ſhall finde them to reliſh of deuotion; I am ſure they are for it was an holy conſideration of bleſſed Sion: that did moue them hereunto, dum recordaremur Sionis, doth expreſſe it: of compaſſion no doubt they are, for they are ſurely mooued by the griefe of others according to that of Saint Paul, weepe with thoſe that weepe: omnes in vno 
               Rom. 12. 15. 
               peccant, omnes in vno pl
                     •…
                  ntur &amp; omnes ſimul lachrymas emittunt: they all offend in one tranſgreſſion; they are all puniſhed with one affliction; and all together ſend foorth teares of lamentation: fleuimus doth ſhew it. And of contrition doubtleſſe they are remembring their ſinnes to haue been the cauſe of this their great miſerie.
            But right honorable, right worſhipfull, and welbeloued if we diue in more deepely into this riuer of teares, ariſing from the deaw of their deuotion; drawen out from the weedes of their offences; by the fire of contrition: that we may cauſe ſome droppes thereof to fall vpon our faces, whereby we may ſhine gloriouſly before the lambe that ſits vpon the throne: the cauſe thereof wee ſhall finde threefold.
            
               Propter peccati commiſſionem, 
                     Cauſa 
                           •…
                        
                        marum 
                           〈◊〉
                        . The cauſe of 
                        〈◊〉
                      weep
                        ••
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
               
               Propter mundanam afflictionem,
               Propter virtutum defectionem,

                     That is

                           For their ſinne committed which was the cauſe of their miſerie.
                           
                           
                              
For the puniſhment inflicted being in captiuitie.
                           
                           And for their graces ecclipſed, that before had not grace to preuent this danger.
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            And now hauing not the abilitie to performe thoſe Chriſtian duties that are required in releiuing thoſe that are in miſerie and neceſſitie.
            The firſt cauſe of their weeping, is a chiefe cauſe of ſorrow: and alwaies proper to the children of God; which 
                  Prima cauſa lament 
                        •…
                     s The firſt cauſe Tropter 
                        〈◊〉
                      com
                        •…
                     m. For their ſinne committed. Cor. reſpecteth more the offending of ſo gratious a God; then the puniſhment inflicted vpon them this is that which the Apoſtle Saint Paul, calls a godly ſorrow, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : a ſorrow towards God: being grieued only that they haue offended ſo gratious and louing a father; which was the prodigall childes greateſt greife: I haue ſinned againſt heauen, and againſt thee; I am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne: Eſt
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
                
               Luke. 15. 18. 
               pa
                     ••
                   paenans quam meruiſſe minus; To an ingenious nature, it is more greife to deſerue; then to ſuffer puniſhment: an inſtance of this; likewiſe we haue in Dauid, when the Prophet Nathan came vnto him, and did lay before him his ſin by a ſimilitude: the Prophets threatnings did not afflict him; the offence done againſt his God, did only vexe him. I haue ſinned againſt the Lord. And in an other place, In te ſolum peccaui: Againſt thee onely haue I ſinned and done this 
               2. Sam. 12. 13. Pſal. 51. 4. Holcoth, in lib. Sap
                     •
                  . 
               euill in thy ſight. Holcoth maketh mention of a certaine bird, that hath the face and viſage of a man; and yet is moſt fierce, and cruell, againſt man; and doth only feede vpon mans fleſh: when it hath killed a man being dry, goeth to the brooke to quench his thirſt: but looking down into the cleare water, and beholding his owne countenance, conſidering what it hath done, that it hath deſtroied one of his owne likeneſſe, and image; returning preſently from the water, neither eates nor drinkes afterward; but goeth into the wilderneſſe, and their conſumes himſelfe in diſpleaſure, and ſo endes his daies in ſorrow: this is the behauiour of euery good and godly Chriſtian, conſidering

that by ſinne he hath deſtroied the image of God in him, he doth conſume away in diſpleaſure, what heart is ſo hardned conſidering how the ſinne of man hath procured the death of the ſonne of God: would not end his daies in ſorrow and lamentation.
            The ſecond cauſe of their weeping is, for that wo
                  •
               dly 
                  Se 
                        〈◊〉
                      ca
                        •…
                      l
                        •
                     me
                        •…
                     s. The ſecond cauſe is 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     . For their r
                     •…
                  ent in
                  
                     •…
                  ted. puniſhment inflicted that now they are ſent into baniſhment. When the Lord cannot winne man by his mercies: he will turne to his iuſtice: to trie if by affliction hee can bring him to acknowledge his ſ
                  •
               nne; they being in proſperitie at home, would neither hearken nor obey, but being now in baniſhment, and vnder captiuitie; they are drawne to lament for their offences. The heauie hand of Gods inſtice, is able to breake and bruiſe the hardeſt heart, and cruſh it in peeces; nay bring the moſt wicked, and impious man, to acknowledgement of his ſinne. Kames heart is ouerqueld herewith, wherefore he mournes grieuouſly and cries out, my ſinne is greater then can be forgiuen, it was Gen. 4. 1
                     •
                  . not his hypocriſie, the murdering of his brother; nor any other ſinne, that he had committed: but onely the great puniſhment inflicted vpon him: that did prouoke him hereunto. Pharaoh tooke on greiuouſly and confeſſed his Exod. 9 27. ſinne, it was not for a deteſtation thereof, but becauſe of the plagues that were ſent vpon him, and vpon his land. Saul is very ſorrowfull, but it is becauſe of Samuel
                     •
                  
                threatning, 1 Sam. 15. 2
                     •
                  . 
               Sunt quos peccaſſe paen
                     •
                  tet propter 
                     〈…〉
                   diſplicet euim, latroni, peccatum; qu
                     •…
                   
                  
                     •…
                  t 
               Auguſt 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  ▪ 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               vindictareuertitur ad crimma, ſaith S
                     •…
                   Auguſtine. There be many (ſaith he) that are greiued for their ſinne, becauſe of the preſent affliction vpon them. A theife is ſo
                  ••
               ie for his offence, when he feeles the puniſhment, but it being once ouer; he fals to ſtealing againe. This no doubt is the ſecond cauſe of their weeping, becauſe of the heauie croſſe laid vpon them.
            The third cauſe of their weeping, is the want of grace, both in that they could not preuent the danger, before it did aſſault: as alſo, that now they cannot performe thoſe

duties which they ought vnto others in diſtreſſe; for the former Peter doth weepe exceedingly, being ſo forward a little before, and ſo peremptory to ſtand to his owne ſtrength, that now ſhould falter in the performance and become ſo weake: he mournes abundantly; Miſit legatos, 
               C
                     •
                  prian. lib. 2. 
               pro ſuis doloribus lachrymas: dolorem probantes commiſſi criminis, &amp; dolorem. Like Rachel that wept for her children, becauſe they were not, euen ſo the children of God they weepe for their graces becauſe they are not; Dauid doth Pſal. 41. 3. proteſt that teares were his meat and drink night and day, becauſe he knew the want in him, that without his grace he could not ſtand. And the Apoſtle Saint Peter doth crie out of this want in him: The good, that I would do, that I do not, but the euill that I would not do, that I do. Againe the defect of the duties which in performance they owe to their brethren in diſtreſſe is a great cauſe of their weeping, for they ſeeing the citie ſpoiled; the temple ranſacked: the people carried into captiuitie; and they no waies able to help them, they cannot remember theſe things without great greife, fler
                     •
                  oportet, of neceſſitie they weepe, it is the greateſt greife that can come to a kinde ſoule, to ſee another man in miſerie, and not able to helpe him; this was Iobs greife, did not I weepe with thoſe that were in trouble, was not my ſoule in heauineſſe for the poore. This was Ieremies 
               Iob. 30. 25. ſorrow for the people being by the iudgement of God deſtroyed, that I might weepe for the ſlaine of the daughters of Sion: Whether it be for their ſinnes committed, their I
                     •
                  r. 9. 1. puniſhment inflicted; or their graces ecclipſed: weeping I finde them, where I leaue them, vntill I enquire after the place of their abiding, and I finde it to be Babel.
            
            The place is ominous, for if they had been baniſhed into ſome priuate place, where they might haue had libertie to 3. locus generalis. The place is 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                exerciſe the duties of Religion, and to ſerue their God: although they had been detained for a long ſpace; their exile had been the eaſier: but being expoſed to Babel that barbarous place; their eſtate is more miſerable. Babel here doth ſignifie, the prouince of Babilon, or countrey

of Caldea: for the City of Babel, ſtood vpon one riuer Euphrates onely: but here there is mention of more then one, By the riuers of Babilon. The country was idolatrous: the people ſauage: ſo that, to dwell in ſuch a place was dangerouſe. In this place was Bel and Dragon the two Idols of the Caldeans worſhipped: and the cheife metropolitan Citie Babel accurſed. His foundation was laide in Gen. 11. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . pride, Come let vs builde a tower whoſe top may reach vnto heauen to get vs a name. It was finiſhed by Nabuc
                     •…
                  zzar 
               Dan. 4 27. that proud puiſſant in ambition, Is not this great Babel which I haue built to the gloris of my maieſtie by the might of my power. And the end thereof was confuſion, for afterward it came to be an habitation of vncleane Diuels, as before was propheſied of it.
            To dwell in ſuch a place is greiuous to the children of God, Dauid 
               
                  ••
               ies out of this miſerie, Woe is me, that dwell 
               Pſal. 120. 5. 
               
                  
                     •
                  n Meſech; or haue my habitation ſo long among the tents of Kedar. A couetous worldling cares not where he dwelles; omne ſolum eſt ills patria; Euery dominion is a dwelling for him: to ſerue the Market, is all he lookes for in any place; that he may gaine by his commodity: although it bee to another mans great loſſe: but of all grei
                  •
               es it is the greateſt to a godly man to dwell in a lewd place, where there is no practice of religion, no goodneſſe exerciſed, but altogether prophaneſſe and abhomination. This doth much vexe the Prophets ſpirit being conſtrained hereunto: Wo's mee that I 
               Eſa. 6. 6. 
               dwell amongst a people of pollutea lippes: for the Prouerbe moſt commonly comes to paſſe in this: aliquid mali, propter vicinum malum; ſome euill doth happen, by reaſon of a wicked neighbor, either they are ſubiect to thoſe plagues which the Lord doth threaten vpon the diſobedient, being alwaies hanging ouer the wicked as wee ſee by Lot; that dwelling amongſt the wicked Sodomites, was taken priſoner Gen. 14. with them in the ouerthrow. Or elſe, they are likely to be tainted with them, dumſpectant laeſos, oculilaeduntur &amp; 
               
                  
                     •…
                  d. 
               ipſi, they can hardly eſcape the wicked without receiuing ſome blemiſh of them. Righteous Ioſeph being amongſt

the prophaneſeruants in Pharaohs court, learning to ſweare 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   of Pharaoh, if we then obſerue the prophaneſſe Gen. 41. 15. of the place, or the imp
                  •
               e
                  •
               ie of the people of that place; we ſhall finde their caſe miſerable, by reaſon of their habitation, and ſo I come to the fourth circumſtance of their 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . commiſeration, that they did dwell by the bankeſides, if they had been receiued into their Cities or townes where they might had ſ
                     •…
                  er, for their ſafegard, then had they receiued ſome comfort; but being expelled from their Cities, and from thence to the Riuerſides to remaine without ſhadow is a great miſerie vnto them: ſuper ſlumina ſedent: they remaine by the riuer ſide; in the countrey of Caldea, there were ſundry r
                     •…
                  rs, ſuch as Euphrates, Ne
                  
                     •…
                  rd
                     •
                  a, Ahaua, and Tigris, which doth ſhew the place to bevery fruitfull; to encreaſe their greife, becauſe they cannot be receiued into the Cities with them. The Caldeans darenot receiue them into their fellowſhippe: Inimicis fidere, &amp; cum illis habitare non tutum ſentiunt, to truſt their enemies, and to dwell with them they thinke it not ſafe enough, therefore are they expoſed into the Riuerſide, 
               Io. 4 19. when the woman of Samaria came to lacobs well, ſhee retained ſome comfort of her lourney: for ſhee found the Meſſias; the Sauiour of the world; that was able to deliuer; and did deliuer her from all her fornications: but here they come to the riuers of Bab
                     •
                  l, where they haue no hope of deliuerer nor comforter to help them, for the ſpace of ſeuenty yeares. Although Agar ſit ſorrowfull for Gen. 16. 9. a while by the Well in the wilderneſſe, yet at laſt the Angell came to comfort her: but here they ſit a long ſpace and haue no hope of Angell nor man to comfort nor releiue them. Theſe waters may be well called Maſſah or Meribah of ſtrife or tentation: Naturae enim repugnat, for it is againſt their nature, to be tied into ſuch a barren place, hauing had ſuch goodly aſpects of their owne before. Their goodly Orchards, gallant gardens, delicate fine walkes beſet with fruitfull trees, and ſweete buſhes; is now conuerted into a barren bankeſide ouergrowne with

               willowes: their pleaſant parlors, braue 
                  
                     ••
                  ls, and coſtly hung chambers, are now tranſlated into a poore tent, not able to defend them from the raine nor tempeſt: hoc miſeria plenum: the more I do diſcend into their miſerie, the greater I findetheir greife to be aggrauated, and ſo much of their affliction.
            In their affection wee haue firſt ſet downe the cauſe of The ſecond part is their affection. their conceiued ſorrow, which was the remembrance of their former happineſſe. Dura ſatis miſeris memoratio priſca bonor
                     •…
                  : Of all miſeries, it is the greateſt to remember the io
                  •
               litie of our former life, this torment doth father Abraham adde vnto the rich glutton lying in hell forments, R
                     •
                  cardarem
                     •
                   ſili, remember my ſenne that thou in Luke. thy life time receiuedſt thy pleaſure, which no doubt did afflict him more then all his former torments. Whileman is in proſperitie hee neuer thinke; of his future miſerie, which when it doth aſſault, of all afflictions it is the greateſt to remember his former happineſſe, in
                     •…
                  ciſſimum eſt in fortuny genus, meminiſſe fuiſſe foelicem: of all things it is the moſt vnhappie, to remember that we were once happie. King Creſus doth affirme this by that often repetition of Solon, when he was going to the place of torment, who Herod. 
                     〈◊〉
                   1. did on a time bragge of his happineſſe vnto Solon a Sage of Greece, and ſaid that hee thought himſelfe the happieſt man that liued, vnto whom Solon replying ſaid, no man can be ſaid to be happie before his death, and being afterward taken in battell of King Cyrus did vtter nothing but Solon, Solon, ſhewing that the remembrance thereof did onely vexe, and afflict him: ſurely the greateſt puniſhment that the damned ſhall receiue in hell torments wilbe the remembrance of their former pleaſure, Plungent quia mundum dilexerunt, plangent quia vitam non correxerunt, plangent quia paenam incurſerunt, They ſhall weepe, becauſe they haue loued the world; they ſhall mourne, becauſe they did not amend, their life while they liued in the world. They ſhall lament becauſe they did deſerue, by their wickedneſſe, to come to that place of torment, when

they departed out of the world, the remembrance of their former loſſe will be their greateſt griefe. But to come to the height of their vnhappineſſe, and to take a veiw of the depth of their miſerie, it is no earthly thing that doth greiue them, only the comfort which they wanted of S
                     •
                  on, is all that vexe, them. When we remembred Sion, Mary ſits Io. 11. very ſorrowfull in a mournefull habite as long as Chriſt was abſent from her, but when her ſiſter Martha came and told her that the Maſter was come and called for her, O how ſpeedily did ſhe ariſe and embrace him ioyfully, the want of the comfort of the word of God is the greateſt griefe that can come to a godly ſoule, Dauid accounts in his baniſhment this his greateſt loſſe, and the people there in captiuitie lament for the defect here of, while they were in their owne countrey they did not account of it, they diſpiſed the Prophets quid nobiſcūcum illis, what haue we to do with ſuch as propheſie euill vnto vs, but now being depriued of it, ô how they weepe for their want of it. Demoſthenes being baniſhed Athens, ô how he did weepe when he looked towards Athens, the Iſraclites being baniſhed into Babilon, ô how they do weepe when they remember Sion. Sion was an eminent place in Ieruſalem, where the Lord had ſet his name to be worſhipped, and where onely, they did receiue comfort in the word. Agar ſhe weepes becauſe Gen. 16. 7. ſhe is thruſt out of her Maſters houſe, they weepe, becauſe they are put out of Sion, and debarred from their Maſters preſence in his houſe; Diues being in proſperitie did not regard the word of God, nor take any delight therein, but in aduerſity lying in hell torments, he lamented▪ his careleſſeneſſe thereof, wherefore he wiſhed Abraham to ſend Lazarus to his fathers houſe, to giue his brethren notice Luke. 16. of their neglect herein, leaſt they ſhould come into that place of torment.
            Hauing ſpoken of the hiſtoricall ſenſe, according as it happened vnto theſe Iſraelites really, may it pleaſe you right honorable, right worſhipfull, and welbeloued, that I ſpeake of the my ſticall meaning. It is no allegorie which I

handle; but onely a moralitie drawne from the true hiſtorie, according to the opinion of all the auncient, as S. Auguſtine, lerome, Chryſoſtome, Hugo Cardinalis, Lyra, and others, as alſo Marlorate and Muſculus amongſt the mode
                  •…
                aſhrine the ſame. Saint Auguſtine hath made a great volume which he entitles de ciuitate Dei, the citie of God, where in hee comprehends all ſorts of people into two, namely the Citizens of Babel and the Citizens of Ston, both which I haue mentioned in my text, the one in bondage vnder the tyrannie of the other, and in oppoſition one to the other, the one in Babel corpore, bodilie, but in S
                     •…
                   animo, ſpiritually, Anima eſt vbi amat, non vbi animat, 
               A
                     •
                  g. P
                     •
                  il. 3. 20. the ſoule is where it loues, not where it liues. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                ſaith the Apoſtle S. Paul, our rule or gouernment, or as the vulgar hath it our conuerſation is in heauen. Omnis Catholicus (ſaith Saint Auguſtine) 
               Auguſt. in 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
               debet ſcire, vnde ciues ſumus, vnde peregrinamur. Euery Chriſtian ought to know, to what citie we do belong, that ſinne is the cauſe of our peregrination, and our iuſlification by grace in the merits of Ieſus Chriſt, the matter of our deliuerance. But to leaue myſticall moralities and wreſted allegories, I will onely make a compariſon in this, betweene the World wherein we liue, and this Babel wherein the people of Iſrael did liue, comparatiuely.
            This world wherein we liue may be well compared to 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               Babel, for ſundrie reaſons.
            1 Propter munditiam, for the pompe and glory thereof, Babel was a rich place, and very fruitfull as the hiſtoriographers For 
                     〈…〉
                   there of. Stra
                        •…
                     
                   Math. 4. 8. 9 do write of it, The World is fertill and very gorgeouſe in ſhew; the Diu
                     •…
                  l did reueale it vnto our Sauiour Chriſt, Omnia haec d
                     ••
                  o, all theſe things will I giue thee: is, a deſcription thereof. Diues fareth deliciouſly and goeth gorgeouſly euery day, Diues wants nothing in this world Luk 18. 
                     •
                  9 that his heart can wiſh.
            2. Propter affectionem, for the affection of her inhabitants, For their affection. Auguſt. in 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                
               Babel habet ſuos amatores, pac
                     •
                   temporali conſulentes, nihil vltra ſperantes: ſaith Saint Auguſtine: the citizens of

               Babel deſire no other dwelling, for there they haue taken vp their reſt, the world hath her louers, doth not the rich man in the Goſpell prouide onely for this life, Let vs eat 
               Luke. 12. 19. 
               and drinke: poſt mortem nulia voluptas, our life is ſhort and tedious, let vs take our pleaſure, that is preſent, for this is our 
               Wiſ. 2. 6. 
               lot and portion.
            
            3. Propter afflictionem, for the affliction which they ſuffer, 3 For their affliction. Ioh. 16. 33. 
               Babel is a place of torment for the Iſraelites, the World a place of affliction for the godly, for here they ſuffer violence of the wicked: in munde preſſuram ſuſtinebitis, in the world you ſhall ſuffer affliction, was a cognizance giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt to know his flocke by, The Apoſtle Saint Paul doth iuſtifie it by his often miſeries. A certaine Philoſopher being ſent into baniſhment, hee tooke it patiently, 2. Cor. 11. 23. and one day being vpbraided by an other as a diſgrace vnto him, anſwered mildely, ſum ciuis mundi, ſhewing that as long as he was in this world he was ſubject to the Moler. in lo
                     •
                  . ſame affliction.
            4. Propter confuſionem, for the confuſion of things in 4 For the confuſion of all thing. it, let a man conſider the world and all things in the world, the ſtate of things and manners of men, and he ſhall finde nothing but confuſion, as the word doth import. This 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                may be well ſaid to be 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , becauſe of the confuſion of things both in Church and Common wealth, Coelum mari admixtum, parua magnis confuſa, heauen and earth are confuſed together for vertue is hated, and vice is embraced, no man is regarded for his giftes; giftes, yes ſurely, ſi nihil attuleris this Homere for as, giftes carries all away In quad. Hiſt. now adaies. Amongſt the 
                  Ʋenetians there were certaine magiſtrates that were called praegads, becauſe at the firſt foundation of their Citie, men were entreated to take offices, but it is long ſince that order, it is now cleane worne out of vſe, and eſpecially in this Land, for now they are not entreated to enter into offices, but rather entreate, pray, and vſe all meanes poſſible to haue them, and if I miſtake not my ſelfe, they pay ſoundly for them, is not this confuſion? what greater confuſion can come to the

               Church, then Iudas and Symon Magus to ſhake hands together, what will ye giue? and what ſhall I giue? then all muſt needes come to confuſion: truly I thinke that ſuch a confuſion was neuer wrought in Babel, as is at this day practiſed in this Church, for they would not robbe their gods to beautifie themſelues as theſe Latrones beneficiorum 
               Mal. 3. 8. the Patrons of Benefices do. Let but a Iack-daw come to theſe Benefactors that beſtow benefices, onely for their owne priuate commoditie with a purſe in his mouth, (A birde that neuer came in at the doore; but at the window, or ſome little hole aboue) and he ſhall carry away the preſentation before a man of worth, is not this confuſion? nay it is condemnation vpon the delinquents. And ſhall I impute this abhomination onely vnto the Patrons: Many of them be Laymen, and cannot tell how to trie their Clarkes, but by the ſenſe of feeling: there be other members in the Church, that are to be blamed for it, Let Eliſha take heede that Gehez
                     •
                  
                his man be not the author of this confuſion, and ſo bring deſtruction vpon his ſoule.
            Is it not a great confuſion when Bel and Dragon are worſhipped in the Church, and idolatrie erected in the houſe of God, as it is in the Romiſh Church, where they giue that worſhip due and proper only to the Creator to the creature, They adore the hoſt, kneele at the crucifixe, and inuocate Saints departed; which is a 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               a ſeruice due only vnto God: diſtinguiſh it as they will, to be imparted to no Creature Ego ſum Dominus (ſaith the Lord by the Prophet) I am the Lord, this is my name, my glory will I giue 
               Eſay. 42. 8. 
               vnto none, nor my praiſe vnto grauen Images. Like vnto the heathen their Churches gorgeouſly, they garniſh inwardly, and within they ſacrifice vnto Deuils, where ſuch abhomination is wrought, it muſt needes bee Babel, nay that Apo
                     •
                  . Whore ſpoken of in the Reuelation that hath made the whole world drunke with her fornications, let vs, and all true Chriſtians pray the Lord to turne their hearts, that they may ſee this confuſion, or elſe to ſend a weſterly winde

and driue ſuch Caterpillers into the ſea.
            But to leaue them to Gods cenſure, and come to the common wealth, and you ſhall finde, that theſe lawes and ordinances, that haue beene formerly or deined to good purpoſe, beare no ſway in theſe daies. The law was in auncient time to be required at the Iudges mouth which thing is now greatly in practice, for the law now doth only depend on the Iudges voice. And I will not ſay, that the hea
                     ••
                  ble Iudges of this land doe follow the footſteps of Samuels ſonnes (looke after lucre) peruert iuſtice and 1. Sam. 8. 3. take rewards. I beleeue that neither cognatus aut argentum, bribe nor brother will cauſe them wrong their conſcience, neither do I hope to heare of ſuch confuſion wrought by men that feare God Neuertheleſſe looke into the intricate endleſſe enrolling of their proceedings in law, and you ſhal finde a great confuſion in making ſuch demurres, and delaies in their proceeding that oftentimes it comes to paſſe when the matter long depending is brought to an iſſue, that then the ſumme of expenſes ſhall weigh downe the worth of the ſentence; is not this confuſion? If the time would permit, I might take a view of all eſtates that by their faſhion, I ſhould finde a fit frame to make vp a Babel, Sycophants and flatteres are daily preferred, but Tom-teltroth little regarded, Dioniſius was often wont to bewaile the ſtate of 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  ita Dioniſ. Princes, and eſpecially in this, that men would not ſpeake freely before them, whereby the truth was hidden from them, and Lewes the eleuenth the French King was wont to ſay that he had plenty of all things in his court, but of one, and being demanded what it was, anſwered, it was truth; if truth be wanting in King, courts what confuſion is this to the common wealth. Sig
                     •…
                  
                the Emperor was wont to account thoſe Princes onely happie, 
                  〈◊〉
                it would baniſh proud men out of their Courts, and being 
                  •
               n courteous and humble men in their places, hee did not ſpeake of the expelling of Sicophants, 
                     •…
                  vers, diſſ
                     •…
                  , and tale-bearers, for (I thinke) he thought then that many of their Courts ſhould remaine vnfurniſhed, if you runne

thorough courts, citties, and countries to obſerue them, you ſhall hardly finde any thing but confuſion. The ſeruant rides on horſe-backe, the Maſter walkes on foote; the body is onely had in eſtimation, for they wilbe ſure to looke to the gilding of their goodly carkaſſes, Pluris opes nunc ſunt quam priſci temporis annis, the body neuer more regarded, but for the ſoule it may ſtarue, before it be reſtored of them. The Kings daughter is all glorious within Pſal. 45 (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) but Satans children are all gorgeous without, like painted ſepulchers, that within are full of rotten bones,; thus yee ſee that Babel may be well compared to the world, for the world is Babel, and nothing in it, almoſt but confuſion, which if it be not redreſſed in this life will bring a ſubuerſion vpon both body and ſoule in the world to come, and ſo I proceede with my compariſon.
            As the world may very well be compared to Babel, euen The things of this life, like vnto the riuers of Babel.
                ſo all the things therein, may be well compared into the Riuers of Babel, although Babel be a pleaſant place, yet it hath riuers in it, which carries all away, all things in the world are vaine, momentarie and ſubiect to mutabilitie like vnto the riuers of Babel, both ebbe and flow. It is written of Seſoſtris a King of the Aegiptians, that he had Herod▪
                his coach drawne with foure Kings, whom before he had conquered and one time perceiuing one of them to looke often backe did demaund the cauſe thereof, I doe (ſaith he) behold and obſerue that part of the wheele which was loweſt, becomes by and by higheſt, and the higheſt, loweſt, cogito de mutatione fortunae, I note the vnſtabilitie of things in this world, ſuch ſurely is the eſtate of all things in this world, that there is nothing ſtable vnder th
                  •…
               e. Conſider but the life of man, and you ſhall perceiue i
                  •…
                paſſe away like to the waters in the riuer as Gregorie Nazianzene 
               Greg. lib. 33. M
                     •
                  ral. cap. 7 doth well obſerue it, quae velut à fontis ſui origine naſcendo ſurgit, ſed ad ima defluens moriendo pertranſit, which from our birth as from a fountaine we ariſe to the height of our yeares, but by paſſing away our daies in vanitie, in the end we fall into the gulfe of death, as the riuers runne

into the ſea, which the woman of Tekoah very well noteth vnto Dauid, omnes morimur, &amp; ſicut aquae dilabimur in terram 
               2. Sam. 14 14. 
               quae non reuertuntur: we all die, and like water wee are powred out vpon the ground, which doth not returne. Not only our liues but alſo all things in this world which we do poſſeſſe. Honor, preferment, riches, ſtrength, all are momentanie, and ſubiect to alteration, they are of no continuance, for either wee are taken from them, or they depart from vs, what profit had the rich wretch in the Goſpell of his great ſubſtance, when his ſoule was ſnatcht away that very night from him in the midſt of his wealth, and what gaine get many couetous worldlings of their Luke. 12. 20. goods, when in the midſt of their yeares they forſake them, to paſſe away from vs they hauemany euaſions. The Prophet Ieremy ſaith that as a partridge doth hatch her yoong ones, and by her helpe in relieuing of them they come to 
                  Ierem. 17. 11. In 
                     〈◊〉
                   m
                     •
                  nto Arlet quod diu 
                     •
                  r
                     •
                  ſ
                     •
                  ebat ligeū
                ſom groth, then they forſake her: euen ſo when a rich man hath taken great paines in heaping together riches in the midſt of his daies they forſake him and leaue him like a foule. It is reported of Saladine the Emperor that mightie Monarch, that by his conqueſts obtained great wealth, on a time lying vpon his death bed, conſidering the vanitie and mutabilitie of earthly things, he commanded a ſheete to be tied to a poule, and carried about the Citie, and crie behold Saladine that great rich and mighty Prince of Aſia, for all his abundance in worldly things he carries nothing with him but this ragge. Wherefore the Apoſtle Saint Iohn did diſwade all men and women from the loue thereof, Loue not the world neither any thing therein, for in it there is n
                  •••
               ing but vanitie, And the world ſhall paſſe away with 
               1. Ioh. 2. 17. 
               the luſt thereof, but he that fulfilleth the will of God abideth for euer.
            
            And ſo from the compariſon betweene the world and Babel I come to obſerue the different behauiour betweene 1 The different behauiour of the godly and wicked. the Citizens of Babel, and the Citizens of Sion, and that in three things ſpecified in my text.
            1. The Citizens of Babel they ſit in the midſt of Babel
               
               
                  •
               either can they perceiue theſe things ſedent in fluminibus, they are ſo delighted with the pleaſures thereof that they cannot ſee the confuſion of them, but the children of God: ſedent inxta flumina vel ſuper flumina: ſit neere to the riuers or by the bankſide and diſcerne their abhomination, neither will they be ouertaken with them. A man that walketh Sim
                     •…
                  
                in the miſt cannot perceiue whence it commeth nor whether it goeth, but if he betake him aſide vnto ſome top of a mountaine neere adioyning, he ſhall diſcerne that it is nothing but a vapor ariſing from the ſerines and entrals of the earth, thickning in the cloudes, and vaniſhing in the aire: ſo long as the earthly mindes of couetous worldlings are ouerſhaddowed with the darkneſſe of ignorance, thickned with a greedie deſire of worldly things, as groſſe and palpable as the darke miſt of Egypt, they cannot ſee, perceiue, nor vnderſtand: a worldly man doth not vnderſtand theſe things that are of the ſpirit of God, as long as they are in the midſt of them they cannot perceiue the vanitie, nor frailty of them, but if they would take them aſide into the conſideration of Sion, and bee lifted vp in their mindes with an holy meditation, they ſhould perceiue that all the thinges of this life proceede from the bowels of the earth, and vaniſh away in the aire. The godly man he ſees this, and therefore ſits by them, and is not taken in delight with them, but the wicked man vnderſtands not, and therefore like a foole is ouertaken with Eccleſ. 31. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . them.
            O that the rich wretched worldling would but conceiue this, that takes ſuch pleaſure in his riches, and increaſeth his wealth by vnlawfull meanes, that ſets his whole delight vpon the tranſitory things of this world, and ſits in the midſt of Babel, that as long as he dwels in the delight of theſe things he is ſubiect to confuſion, ſurely I thinke hee would be more liberall to the poore, leſſe hurtfull and enuious to his neighbors, and put his riches to better vſe, then now he doth when hee puts his money to vſury, but becauſe he knowes not, nor perceiues he not in what danger

he is, therefore he cannot ſhunne it as long as he dwels in a greedie deſire things coueting worldly he cannot ſee, but if he would betake him to a liberall diſtribution, and by an heauenly contemplation conſider the eſtate of his preſent being, he ſhould be able to diſcerne it.
            
               Mathew ſitting at the receipt of cuſtome, following his couetous calling, with a greedle deſire after coine, roſe vp at Chriſts call, and followed him. I would to God that I could finde one ſoule ſitting here, in a greedie deſire after worldly things, that would be mooued with contrition of heart for their couetous behauiour, then ſhould I thinke my ſelfe moſt happie in diſcharging my calling and winning one ſoule vnto God, and alſo that ſoule ſaued in Sion euerlaſtingly.
            2 The Citizens of Sion ſpend not their time in mirth &amp; 2 The ſecond diſteren c
                     •
                  . melodie as the wicked Babilonians do, but rather in ſorrow &amp; heauineſſe; the wicked ſaith Iob (that liue in the delights of Babel) nihil vl
                     •
                  ra ſperantes, looking for no other felicitie but that which they preſently poſſeſſe, ſpend their daies in mirth, ſolace, and feaſting, and walke with their kinsſolkes, friendes, wiues, and children, and ſuddenly they go downe to hell 
               Iob. 21. 13. 
               together, but the godly paſſe ouer their daies, in ſorrow, heauineſſe and lamentation, and in the end are carried of the good Angels, after the ending of their dolefull daies, into Abrahams boſome, we read in ſtories of former times, how that the holy men in the primitiue Church did paſſe ouer their daies in ſolitarineſſe, praier, and faſting, as the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes doth very well obſerue it, ſed tempora mutantur, &amp; nos mutamur in illis, the times are altered, Heb. 11. 29. for men and women delight in theſe daies to ſpend their time in diſſoluteneſſe, rioting, playing and feaſting, they did conſider the miſerie of this preſent Babel wherein they did liue, their frailtie to yeeld vnto the wicked allurements of that curſed Countrey. But, I think men and women in theſe daies hope for no more ioy nor pleaſure hereafter, and therefore they make this life a recreation for their miſery to come, and ſatisfie themſelues herewith, while they

are here, but the wiſe man Salomon tell vs, that it is better Eccleſ. 7. 4. 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                to go into the houſe of mourning then into the houſe of feaſting, becauſe (ſaith he) where mirth is, there are the hearts of fooles, but where ſorrow is, there are the hearts of wiſe men, wherefore our Sauiour pronounceth a bleſſing vpon thoſe that lament in this life, for they ſhall be comforted. 
               
                  Math. 5. 4. Aug. de
                     •…
                  . 
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               Aut continui dolores cruciabuut paenitentem vitam meam, aut cruciatus aeterni vexabunt puniendam animam meā, neceſſe eſt peccatorem ſlerivel hic, vel in futuro, ſaith Saint Auguſtine: Either continuall ſorrowes, muſt afflict a mans penitent life, or elſe eternall torments ſhall vexe his damnable ſoule, and of neceſſitie a ſinner muſt weepe either heere in this life, or hereafter. The hearts of worldly men are ſo glutted with exceſſe of worldly pleaſure that to be ſorrowfull for their ſinnes they haue no leaſure. Peter denies his Maſter, and Peter weepes bitterly for his treſpaſſe, thou denieſt thy Maſter daily and howerly by thy ſwearing, lying
                  •
                and thy deceitfull actions, and yet thou neuer weepeſt for it, ipſi Petre ſtatim demiſit quia amariſſimè fleuit, 
               Amb. ſ. Ser. 46. 
               ſi tu non ſleas Chriſtus non ad tereſpiciet noc tua culpa recedit, Our Sauiour Chriſt gaue Peter a preſent pardon vpon his mourning, if thou weepe not for thy tranſgreſſion, neither will Chriſt looke towards thee, nor yet remit thy ſinne, for that ſentence of our Sauiour is againſt euery one that remaines hardened in ſinne, except ye repent ye ſhall all likewiſe 
               Luke. 13. 3 
               periſh. Mary Magdalene ſhee wept for her adulterie and fornication, but the Gallants of theſe times make it only a matter of recreation, adoleſcentem ſcortari non eſt vitiū, to be wanton is but a tricke of youth. If a man durſt aske many of theſe young Gentlemen that walke gallantly along the ſtreetes, and they would ingeniouſly anſwere them, they might as Diogenes did being demaunded whether he went, going from the Lacedemonians to the Athenians, eo à viris ad faeminas, I go from men to women, for Diog La
                     •
                  r 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  it. Pl
                     •
                  l. to an harlet, to the ſtewes, or to a tobaco. ſhoppe is their furtheſt iourney. But why ſhould I perſwade men or women to a ſolitarie life, ſeeing there is nothing in this world but

matter of miſerie, therefore I ſhould rather counſell them to take their recreation. Beloued, the wicked are too much giuen to worldly mirth, and therefore when any ſolitary fit ouertakes them they will take them to ſomelewd company to driue away melancholy: but let vs take heede, when we are moſt ſecure in our merry moode, then is Sathan moſt watchfull to winnow vs like wheat, while Iobs 
               Iob. 1. 19. children are feaſting in their elder brothers houſe, then the Diuell workes their ouerthrow. Awake therefore all yee that ſleepe in the ſecuritie of ſinne, and fill vp your meaſure of mirth beyond all meaſure, rouſe vp yourſelues ye that reioice in Babilon, and weepe for your tranſgreſſions. Awake ye drunkards and weepe, howle all ye drinkers of wine, 
               Ioel. 1. 5. 
               becauſe of the now wine, for it ſhalbe pulled from your mouthes. Rouſe vp your ſelues you Adulterers and Fornicators, that ſtretch your ſelues vpon the bed of fornication to fulfill your luſts, and lament for your vncleanneſſe, becauſe, without yee repent, in your pollution ye ſhall periſh. Ye Conetous-worldings 
               1. Cor. 6. ariſe from greedines, and from getting of vnlawfull goods, leaſt yee be puniſhed with Diues in hell Luke. 16. torments. And finally let vs all awake, ariſe and rouſe vp our ſelues from ſin and weepe and mourne for our tranſgreſſions. Auicen writeth that the Country of Caldea being Auicen. lib 8. full of riuers, the Hart being wearied in chaſe, and coming to the riuerſide, which ſhe cannot paſſe, goeth vnto the firſt man ſhe ſeeth, braies and weepes to him for releife, and ſo is taken. Which let euery Chriſtian man learn, to follow this example, that ſeeing himſelfe beſet with innumerable enemies, wearied with the burthen of ſin, let him turne to the man Ieſiu who is able, and will deliuer him from all dangers. O that we had mindes to conſider our miſdeeds, hearts truly touched with a greife for ſinne that they might relent, and eies of a ſpongie humor that by the diſtillation of our teares we might bedeaw our faces, that as Na
                     •…
                  
                was clean ſed from his leproſie, by waſhing 2. Kings. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . in the riuer Iordan; ſo wee being bathed in the pure fountaine of teares of a contrite heart, may be thoroughly purged

from the filthineſſe of ſinne. There is a certaine riuer in Cecilia that if blacke ſheepe be bathed in it, there wooll 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . ſhall turne white immediately, ſuch ſurely is the true nature of the fountaine of teares, for if thy ſinnes were as red as ſcarlet, in them if thou bath thy ſelfe, they ſhalbe as white as wooll. When Pharaohs daughter did di'cent into the 
                  
                     •
                  xod. 1. riuer, ſhe found a babe lying among the flagges, if thou diſcend into the riuers of teares thou ſhalt finde the babe Ieſus comfortable to thy ſoule. Lachryma enim lauat quod 
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               peccatumpolluit, Teares will waſh that which our ſinne
                  •
                hath defiled. Teare, are ſilent praiers, they craue not and yet they obtaine pardon, they plead not a mans cauſe, and yet they receiue mercy ſaith Saint Ambroſe, Peter by weeping was remitted, Suſanna by weeping was deliuered from the falſe accuſation, Ezechias by lamenting was reſtored to his former health, and his life prolonged let vs weepe then with Peter, lament with Mary Magdalene, mourne with Manaſſes, that our ſoules may be cleared from Satans falſe accuſation, and our liues prolonged in that celeſtiall kingdome euerlaſtingly.
            And laſtly I come to the laſt obſeruation, betweene the 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   The th
                     •
                  d difference. behauiour of the godly and wicked. The Citizens of Sion mourne for the want of it, but the Citizens of Babilon, neither remember Sion, nor regard. The wordly man may perhaps ſomtime weep, but his 
                  •
               e the tears of Eſau, only for want of the bleſſing, becauſe he cannot get ſome great bargaine to the vndoing of his poore brother.
            The carnall man may ſometimes be ſorrie, but it is the 2. Sam 13. 2. greife of Ammon, becauſe he cannot fulfill his luſt with his ſiſter Thamar.
            
            The Enuious man may perhaps greiue, but it is becauſe of his brothers proſperous eſtate, inuidus alteri
                     •
                  s rebus macreſcit opimis, the griefe of the wicked is only that they cannot do miſcheife, but the ſorrow of a godly ſoule, is when he wants ſome peaceable comfort to his ſoule, Sion is Nulla pax improbis ſed viſ
                     •
                  o Sion
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   grata his ſolace. The remembrance of Sion in reſpect of the depriuation thereof is a great vexation vnto them. The comfort

that a godly man receiues by the word of God preached vnto him cannot be expreſſed, of which when he is depriued like theſe Iewes in captiuitie, what a heauineſſe brings it to his tender heart, Dauid being in baniſhment, Pſal. 84. 3. accounts this his greateſt loſſe, therefore he eſteemes the ſparrow and ſwallow happie, becauſe they had libertie to lay their young neere vnto the altar of God, not that hee thought the birds did receiue any benefit hereby, but that he out of his compaſſionate affection, being rauiſhed with a deſire thereafter, doth vtter this patheticall depriuation, that he did want that which the birds did inioy, when the minde of man by an heauenly contemplation is rapt into the heauen of peace, to conſider mans miſerable eſtate in Babel, and his ioyfull and happie eſtate in Sion, he cannot expreſſe his greife without great lamentation, herefore wee 
               Bernard. in Ca 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
               ſigh and groane deſiring to be diſſolued, and be with Chriſt Ieſus, da amantem &amp; ſenſit quod loquer, euery ſoule that ſighes for Sion, and hath his cogitation there doth conceiue what I ſay. O ſancta Sion vbitotum ſtat nihil defluit, O bleſſed Sion where there is no penurie, no leading into captiuity, nor no complaining in her ſtreetes, but peace and plenty within her borders for euermore, happie ſhall he be that ſhalbe admitted into her gates, to pertake of her ſolace that hee may ſing Halelutah vnto the lambe that ſits vpon the throne for euer and euer.
            Hauing ended my text right honorable, right worſhipfull, and welbeloued, it followes in the next place to ſpeake of their iniquitie which was the cauſe of their miſerie, and to paralell them with the ſinnes of theſe times wherein wee liue, ſuch as Idolatrie, ſhedding of innocent blood, pride, drunkenneſſe, laſciniouſneſſe, and want of charity, as the ſcripture doth ſet them downe vnto us, but becauſe the time hath preuented me, I will only leaue them to your godly conſideration; firſt, becauſe, I know theſe things haue been ſpoken againſt out of this place many times, and therefore you are not ignorant of the heinouſnes of them. As alſo I ſpeake vnto Chriſtians, that haue the word of God daily

preached vnto them, to diſwade them from thoſe and the like ſinnes, and therefore a ſhame for ſuch to bee tainted with them, it ſhalbe eaſier for Sodome and Gomorah, nay and Babel in the day of the Lords appearance, then for this Citie, becauſe the word of God is ſo plentifully preached in it.
            You right Honorable and worſhipfull Magiſtrates of this Citie qui 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Cooperatores dei eſtis, Gods vicegerents 1. Cor. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . or aſſiſters vpon earth, weigh diligently the charge that is committed vnto you, remember that you are exalted to that place of dignitie to repreſſe iniquitie let not your too mild &amp; meek ſpirit encourage the wicked to do euill, for fooliſh pittie may mar the City. Conſider that the ſword is not giuen vnto you in vaine, but to take vengeance on them that do euill, the daies are dangerous, the people impious, Rom. 135 they will hardly obey, but by conſtraint, let ſin be your ſubiect to ſuppreſſe it, and the glorie of Sion the obiect of all your labors knowing that you ſtand alwaies in Gods ſight, from whoſe preſence nothing can be hid. I would to God that you had the ſpirit of Elias, and zeale of Phineas to ſuppreſſe ſinne in the action. I would to God that the Magiſtrates of this City were like vnto the watchmen of Iſrael to ſearch about the Corners thereof, and finde out the abhominations therein; to the oppreſſed be mercifull, to the wicked fierce, and terrible, that you being faithfull in a little, when your Lord and Maſter doth appeare he may make you rulers ouer great, and exalt you to that bleſſed Sion to remaine with him for euermore.
            And you honorable Iudges, that are ordeined to determine the cauſe of the oppreſſed; and to releiue the poore from wrong: let not the greatnes of the perſon, nor ſuperiority of place; cauſe you to haue any regard; but only to the ſinceritie of the cauſe. But let all iuſt iudges that wiſh to inhabite bleſſed Sion, haue only a reſpect vnto the truth of iuſtice, quia, non hominis, ſed deiiudicium exercetis, becauſe, Deut. 16. it is not mans cauſe but Gods which you take in hand; would to God that euery. Iudgo that ſits vpon the bench of

iuſtice would conſider, before he did determine, the charge that is laide vpon him; if, but once the rrmembrance of righteous Sion, would come into his conſideration, then would he feare to giue ſentence contrary to the right of the cauſe; the want whereof cauſeth much confuſion to be wrought in the land; let your ſcarlet robos put you in minde of righteous Iudgement. Remember that one day, (indicata r
                     •
                  iudic abitt Deus) thoſe things which now you ſhuſle vp without dexterity, ſhalbe opened again, &amp; iudged with ſinceritie, then neither your dialecticall diſtinctions; nor your phinicall fine phraſes, nor your Maſſe of graceleſſe coine ſhall any whit releiue you, for you ſhall be adiudged without mercy, that had no regard vnto the right of the cauſe ſed ſi rectam proſeratis ſententiam, videbitis Sion: but if you haue been conſcionable in giuing true ſentence according to your vpright iudgement, you ſhall enioy peaceable Sion ioyfully for euermore.
            And to conclude, You my beloued brethren, that heare mee this day; take heede vnto your ſelues, that you be not inueigled with glorious Babel; and taken with the delights thereof; leaſt you periſh in her confuſion: let not the loue of any earthly thing, withdraw you from the loue of Sion: Weepe and lament for your ſinnes; whereby you haue offended the Maieſtie of your Maker: take vp a new reſolution, to reforme your liues, by an holy conuerſation: in all your actions poſſeſſe your ſoules with a hope of enioying peaceable Sion, that at the end of your captiuitie, you being deliuered from all the miſeries of this life, and tranſlated into that happie Citie, of eternall bleſſedneſſe to raigne with Chriſt Ieſus for euermore: vnto which place, the Lord for his mercy ſake, through the merits of his ſonne our Sauiour, bring euery one of vs; to whom; with his bleſſed ſpirit, (the tri-vn-God) be aſcribed all glory, dominion, and power for euermore.
            Amen.
            
         
      
   

