
   
      
         
            The picture of a perfit common wealth describing aswell the offices of princes and inferiour magistrates ouer their subiects, as also the duties of subiects towards their gouernours. Gathered forth of many authors, aswel humane, as diuine, by Thomas Floyd master in the Artes.
            Floyd, Thomas, M.A., of Jesus College, Oxford.
         
         
            
               1600
            
         
         Approx. 239 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 165 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01013
            STC 11119
            ESTC S122030
            99857183
            99857183
            22867
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01013)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22867)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 495:9)
         
         
            
               
                  The picture of a perfit common wealth describing aswell the offices of princes and inferiour magistrates ouer their subiects, as also the duties of subiects towards their gouernours. Gathered forth of many authors, aswel humane, as diuine, by Thomas Floyd master in the Artes.
                  Floyd, Thomas, M.A., of Jesus College, Oxford.
               
               [24], 309, [3] p.   
               
                  By Simon Stafford, dwelling on Adling hill,
                  Printed at London :
                  1600.
               
               
                  The first two leaves and the last leaf are blank except for signature-mark "A" on first leaf.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               State, The --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-02
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-04
            Robyn AnspachSampled and proofread
         
            2008-04
            Robyn AnspachText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE Picture of a perfit Common wealth, deſcribing aſwell the offices of Princes and inferiour Magiſtrates ouer their ſubiects, as alſo the duties of ſubiects towards their Gouernours.
            
               Gathered forth of many Authors, aſwel humane, as diuine, by Thomas Floyd master in the Artes.
            
            Printed at London by Simon Stafford, dwelling on Adling hill. 1600.
         
         
            
            
            HONORAtiſs. &amp; magnifico Domino, D. Thomae Egertono, Equiti aurato, D. Cuſtodi magni ſigilli Angliae, ac Regii Senatus digniſſimo Cōciliario: Necnon D. Ioanni Egertono, vnico eius filio &amp; Haeredi. S. P. D.
            
               QVI celeberrimum iuriſprudētiae ſtadium ſtudium
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſiue philoſophiae, quam vulgo Ethicen appellant, ac aliqua ſaltem politices notitia contingere

autumāt: aut alternatim in Ethicis diſciplinis, &amp; politica philoſophia ſe anteire poſſe ſine iuriſprudētiae adminiculo arbitrantur: certe, illi, veluti piſces hamo irretiuntur, decipiuntur, &amp; toto aberrant coelo. Omnium rerum eſt viciſſitudo, diſcolor
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                vſusrerū, &amp; vnares adiumento alterius indiget: ſic mercatores viciſſim nobis aduehunt commoda.
            
               Mercibus ac Anglis mutant ſub ſole recenti.
               Rugoſum piper, &amp; pallentis grana cumini.
            
            
               Quippe iuriſprudētiae abſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                Ethicis &amp; politicis diſciplinis, leuidenſis, horridula, &amp; ſemianimis quaedam facultas, dicenda, &amp; ducenda eſt. Illarumque praecepta niſi iuriſprudentiae typo, ceu gemelli vrſarum foetus formentur, etiamque atque etiam lambantur minus, fermentata cenſentur, &amp; veluti veratro ſeu helleboro atro inebriantur. Nec iniuria itaque Bartalus, aliique iuriſprudentiae anteſignani vtraſque facultates tanquam

ſpeculatiuas cum practicis copulandas eſſe iudicant. In eo proculdubio iudicio tu (Nobiliſſime heros omnimodiſque literarū dotibus inſignite Iudex) es conſtitutus, qui ad nominis tui ſempiternam gloriā cum practicis ſpeculatiuasfa cultates ſemper coniūxiſti, idque non in philoſophia ſolū, ſed etiā (vt inquit Cicero de ſeipſo) in dicēdi exercitatione feciſti, ita vt iam, te eſſe in vtraque facultate parem quis niſi luſcus neget?

Quae quidem cum ego mecum alta mente reputauerim, hominum
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                huius tempeſtatis mores tam incultos, &amp; tam rudes eſſe animaduerterim, cōmouebar animo, &amp; quaſi oeſtro extimulabar, vt illis, quantum in me eſſet, conſulerem, vt
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                hoc qualecun
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſit opuſculum, conſtruerē, conſtructum
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                tibi, tuoque Gnato &amp; Haeredi, praeclarae indolis &amp; magnae ſpei Iuueni coniūctim conſecrarē. Quis enim in tanto morum

naufragio tacere poteſt? Ne ego quidem. Accipite igitur placida &amp; placata mente (magnifici DOMINI) hoc ingenioli mei ſymbolum, accipite (inquam) &amp; meipſum, cui cordi erit quicquid vobis &amp; honori &amp; gloriae fuerit, toto animo perficere. Deus optimus maximus amplitudines veſtras et dignitatē prorogare, fulcire, et cōſeruare dignetur. Oxonii, e collegio Ieſu, Anno a partu virginis. 1600.
            
            
               V. A. Thomas Floyd.
            
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               EVEN as the muſike of an Inſtrument, whoſe harmonious ſounde either delighteth or diſpleaſeth the hearers, according to the skill of him that plaieth thereon: So theſe my firſt fruits, proceeding from my barren inuention and ſhallow wit, do yeeld like content or diſcontent, reſembling well my ſillie Muſe, which makes mee more to feare, that it wil be as hard for mee to obtaine thy plauſible fauour, as it was for hard conceited Anthonie to gaine the good wil of the Senatours, when his deeds had proued him a peremptorie

foe to Rome. Neuertheleſſe, Ariſtotle, who all his daies in a maner had bin an Atheiſt, yet crying, O Ens entium miſcrere mei, in his laſt and loſt day, cauſed the people to thinke yt
                he had ſome knowledge of God. Whereupon afterward being dead, they eternized his name. So now I in like ſorte doe hope, thou wilt ſuſpence thy fauourable cenſure, and grant me a pardon of courſe, that I may vſe the like excuſe, differing in effect, as an aunſwere for my defence: which if it ſeem ſero to any one, yet ſerio, as obſerued of the Philoſophers &amp; huſbandmen, who with one aſſent agreed, perfectionē prioris eſſe aliquam priuationem conſequentis, proceeding frō the ſelfe ſame ſtocke: for the

tree yt
                beareth twiſe a yeere, or oft, firſt bringeth fruit ſauouring of ſweetnes, the laſt taſting ſomewhat ſowre. So this my little one and firſt borne hath more imperfections (I confeſſe) and therefore craueth ſome pardon: for as Hercules, which conquered and ouercame by his wreathes and victories, the moſt part of the world, and when hee could proceede no further, thereat ending and making a full period, cauſed pillers to bee ſet vp, which were termed after his name, on which was written non vltra: But of late daies, Chriſtophorus Columbus, finding a farther paſſage, and going beyond Hercules his non vltra, in reſpect thereof there were other pillers ſet vp, on

which was written, Plus vltra. So I in like maner (gētle Reader) with Hercules, being equal in number, though farre interiour in qualitie, wading as far as my ſimple abilitie could affoord, and my ſlender wit allow, according to that ſmall talent of learning and knowledge I had, hauing more perfectly compoſed and compild this my little pamphlet, that I might well with Hercules ſay, Non vltra. Of which I was by ſome domeſtical yonker priuily bereft, beeing thereat not a little mooued, &amp; almoſt diſcomfited, vnleſſe the entire loue and feruent affectiō I bare towards my high renowned Lord, &amp; towards the young vertuous Gentleman his ſonne, M. Iohn Egerton,
               
who ioyntly as a Paracelſiā Quinteſſens, reedified the wracke of my decay, and cauſed mee againe to take heart of grace, &amp; to redouble my courage, that I was therby rather enforced by affection, than perſwaded by reaſon, to attempt with Columbus, the finding out of Plus vltra, fearing to incurre the backbiting of the enuious, which might ſay, that my ſting was loſt in the firſt aſſault, and my courage was quailed in the bud; applying that ſaying vnto mee, that Milo Crotoniates vſed to apply to himſelfe, beeing not able to attempt and performe any Chiualrie or Act, which before hee vſed: and thereupon beholding his armes and thighes, lamented

and cried, At hi iam mortui ſunt. So ſhould it be ſaide of me, His ſpirits are dead, his courage abated, that hee can performe and accompliſh no more. Entring (courteous Reader) with a ſtrict regard of theſe conſiderations, iam tandem claſping hold on me, that I deemed it better to aduenture this my torn, rent and lacerated ſhip into the maine ſea, than to bee carped at, or to deſiſt from my intē
               ded purpoſe: which conſiderations cauſed mee raſhly to reach aboue my pitch, and to aduenture the more, preſuming vpon thy gentle curteſie, to pardon this my rude and barbarous ſtile, beeing willing (according to the prouerbe) to bee beaten on the anuill by Vulcane, &amp; withall,

to yeelde my ſelfe to the cenſure of thy verdict to cō
               iecture, committing thee to the tuition of Almightie God.
            
               T. F.
            
         
         
            
            A Table of all the contents and matter contained in this booke.
            
               FIrſt, what is a Common wealth, cap. 1.
f. 1.
               2 How many ſorts are there of Common wealths. cap. 2.
f. 11.
               3 What is an Ariſtocratie, cap. 3.
f. 12.
               4 What is a Democratie, cap. 4.
f. 14.
               5 What is a Monarchie, cap. 5.
f. 20.
               6 Which of theſe ſorts is beſt, cap. 6.
f. 24.
               7 What things are requiſite in a king, cap. 7.
f. 46.
               8 Magiſtrates ought to ſee iuſtice adminiſtred, cap. 8
f. 47.
               9 What is a Tyrant, cap. 9.
f. 48.
               
                  10 What is the nature and condition of an Oligarchie, cap. 10.
f. 53.
               11 What differēce between an Oligarchie and a Democratie, cap. 11.
f. 54.
               12 Of law, cap. 12.
f. 55.
               13 Of Magiſtrates, cap. 13.
f. 65.
               14 Of Counſailors, cap. 14.
f. 76.
               15 Of Iudges, cap. 15.
f. 85.
               16 Of Oeconomikes or domeſticall gouernment, cap. 16.
f. 93.
               17 Of Vertue, Cap. 17.
f. 106.
               18 Prudence, cap. 18.
f. 111.
               19 Fortitude, cap. 19.
f. 123
               20 Patience, cap. 20.
f. 135.
               21 Conſtancie, cap. 21.
f. 142.
               
                  22 Of Tēperance, cap. 22.
f. 150.
               23 Modeſtie, cap. 23.
f. 158
               24 Chaſtitie, cap. 24.
f. 164.
               25 Iuſtice, cap. 25.
f. 172.
               26 Charitie, cap. 26.
f. 182:
               27 Obedience, cap. 27.
f. 187.
               28 Hope, cap. 28.
f. 196.
               29 Faith, cap. 29.
f. 207.
               30 Truth, cap. 30.
f. 207.
               31 Friendſhip, cap. 31.
f. 212.
               32 Liberalitie, cap. 32.
f. 220.
               33 Clemencie, cap. 33.
f. 227.
               34 Peace, cap. 34.
f. 235.
               35 Of Idlenes, cap. 35.
f. 239.
               36 Pleaſures and delights, cap. 36.
f. 246.
               37 Intemperance and gluttonie, cap. 37.
f. 253
               
                  38 Luſt and lawleſſe delites, cap. 38.
f. 258.
               39 Enuie, cap. 39.
f. 264.
               40 Couetouſnes, cap 40.
f. 271.
               41 Vſurie, cap. 41.
f. 276.
               42 Ambition, cap. 42.
f. 281.
               43 Anger, cap. 43.
f. 288.
               44 Sedition, cap. 44.
f. 244.
               45 Warre, cap. 45.
f. 297.
               46 Concluſion to the magiſtrates, cap. 46.
f. 303.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            VVhat is a Common wealth. Cap. 1.
            
               A Commō wealth is a liuing body compact of ſundry eſtates and degrees of mē: this body is cōpoſed of two ſorts, namely of the ſoule the worthieſt wight, and of the members or parts.Ariſtotle The ſoule is the king or ſupreame gouernour: which I ſo terme, for two cōſiderations: firſt by a ſimile, in reſpect of his authoritie: for as Ariſtotle ſaieth, that anima is tot a in toto,
               Ariſtotle de anima lib. 2.
                
               et tota in qualibet parte. That is, is wholly in the whole body, and in euery part therof: ſo the king in regard of his authoritie is accounted. The

ſecond &amp; laſt reaſon, is in reſpect of his being &amp; ending, who is no ſooner ſaid a king, then a king of ſome Cōmon wealth, nor no Common wealth can be rightly a common wealth, without a king: ſo the body is no liuing body without the ſoule, nor no longer liueth, then the ſoule remaineth. For as Auguſtine ſaith,Auguſt. 
               Anima in hominem creando infunditur, infundendo creatur. Or as ſome would haue it, A common wealth is a cōgregation, or a multitude of inhabitants; beyng as it were,Ariſt. politic. the mother of vs all. Which we ought to hold ſo deare, that in defence therof we ſhuld not feare, to hazard our liues.Cicer. off. lib. 1.
                For (as Cic. ſaith) wee are borne not for our ſelues, but for our countrey,

kindred, friends &amp; parents: childrē, parents, and friends are deare to vs: but our coū
               trie chalēgeth a greater loue, and exacteth a farther duty. This word Common wealth is called of the Latine word, Reſpublica, quaſi res populica, the affaires of the people: which the latines cal the Gouernmēt of a cōmon wealth, or of a ciuill ſocietie, and is termed of the Greciās a politicall gouernment, deriued of the Greeke word Polutia, which ſignifieth the regimēt and eſtate of a citie, diſpoſed by order of equitie, and ruled by moderation of reaſon, which anſwereth and concurreth moſt fitly to this my preſent diſcourſe &amp; purpoſe, as the order &amp; eſtate wherby one or many townes are gouerned,

adminiſtered, ordained, to that end, that euery ſocietie ſhould by due order or policie be framed.Ariſt po
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . Al men are naturally borne to affect ſocietie, whereof there be 3. ſortes; the one being giuen to the engendring and procreating of humane race, as that of man and woman and this is wholy by nature, Nam omnium ſocietatum nulta eſt magis ſecundū naturam, quam maris &amp; foeminae.
               Plato. The other addicted to policie and ciuil gouernment, as lawmakers within their ſeueral precincts &amp; limits; &amp; this proceedeth partly by nature, partly by other cauſes. The 3. to lewdnes, and wickednes, as that of pyrates, theeues and conſpirators, which ſocietie nature needeth not: this hapneth in

many places, either for want of lawe, or the execution therof. This naturall inclination of ſocietie in generall, is in it ſelfe rude and barbarous, vnles it be gouerned by counſel, and tempered by wiſedome: wherefore ſome of themſelues, eyther by inſtinct of nature, or by diuine eſſence or ſecrete influence from aboue, haue deliuered vnto their poſterities, a perfect way and ſure reaſon, as a ſugred potion or ſweete balme of their beneuolence, to mitigate this humane ſocietie, among whome many were termed authors: but God alone hath ſo framed the ſtate of the whole cōmon wealth &amp; the gouernment thereof, by his owne eternall prouidēce, &amp; alſo cōſtituted

&amp; appointed Moſes, as an inſtrumēt, to publiſh the ſame, for our inſtructiōs &amp; knowledge, by which meanes, many profitable things, for the due ordering of a common wealth, may be reaped &amp; gathered, for whoſe preſeruations, as amōgſt the Grecians, Perſians, Iewes, &amp; in theſe our daies, many were accoū
               ted authors of reformations: yet howſoeuer, wee ought ſomewhat to reſtraine our libertie, diminiſh our credit, &amp; endammage our liues, in the greateſt ieopardy, for the ſafetie hereof. So deare was the loue of Vlyſſes to his coūtry,Homer Odiſs. that he preferred his natiue ſoile Ithaca, before immortalitie. Camillus a noble Romane, being Dictator ſix times, &amp; though baniſhed,

yet when the Frenchmen had taken the Citie of Rome, &amp; compelled the Romās to redeeme their heads with golde; he with the Ardeats, with whom hee liued exild, ſlewe the Frenchmen, &amp; ſaued the citie from bondage. So Horatius Cocles a valiant Romane, with two more, at a bridge that entred into Rome, kept backe, and cauſed the whole armie of Porſenna to retire, vntill the bridge was broken downe behind them; &amp; then in ſpite of his enemie, armed as hee was, did ſwim ſafe into the citie, and ſaued his countrie. So likewiſe Cynegirus a man of excellent vertue, willing to incurre any torture or torment for his countries ſafety: who after many conflicts

had with his enemies, whom hee put to flight, and hardly purſued, vntill they were cō
               pelled to take ſhipping, yet this valiant man being not willing to let them ſaile ſcot-free, faſtened his right hand on one of their ſhippes, not letting goe his hold, vntill it was cut off, and then he held with his left hand: of which alſo he being depriued, held at laſt with his teeth. Such was his excellencie,Trogus Pomp. and loyaltie towards his countrey, that no enterpriſe how great ſoeuer, could cauſe him to deſiſt, to patronize the ſafety therof. But cōtrariwiſe, Coriolanus, whome if the fates had preſcribed his end in his infancy, had not ſo treacherouſly, &amp; vnnaturally borne armes to the ruine of his own

naturall countrey.Dictis Cretenſ. Plutarc. Antenor alſo blemiſhed with this deteſtable vice, &amp; ſpotted with this ſtaine, moſt caitifly fled, with two thouſand men, into Italie, and yeelded his natiue citie into the handes of his enemies the Grecians. And no maruaile, ſeeing neyther the loue of their countrey, nor their owne loyalty could moue them to deſiſt from ſo lothſome &amp; deteſtable a fact. Alas, who is hee that would not lament, to ſee the wrack and ruine of his owne countrie, and the happy ſtay therof turned into helliſh ſtate? much more, peruerting the lawes of nature, yeeld his cō
               ſent to leuell at the bitter bane, and lay a plotte for the finall deſtruction of his natiue ſoyle, conſidering and

calling to minde the payne due to ſuch graceleſſe diſobedient conſpirators, &amp; lewd caterpillers, who neuer miſt to ſuppe of the ſame ſorrow, and taſt of the firſt fruite of their diſmall miſery. Happie then is that commō wealth, whoſe ſafetie is no leſſe ioyfull to it ſelfe, then to all, and whoſe loyaltie may bee ſaid with Syllas hoſt to crie out, to Sylla, Solus ego extinct a patria non relinquar, now that my countrey is deſtroied, I wil not liue alone. Moſt happy then is the citie and common wealth, where the people in generall do obſerue the cuſtomes and rightes of law, fearing them as a tirant.
            1 That life which is due to death is canonized; &amp; reaped double reward, if eclipſed

in the defence of his countrey.
            2 All men are by nature bound to embrace their natiue ſoile, not in regard of the poſſeſsions which they enioy therein, but for the meere loue thereof.
            3 In the loue of our coū
               try we ought to perſeuer, as being not ſufficient once to haue loued it, vnleſſe we cō
               tinue to the end.
         
         
            How many ſortes are there of Common wealths. Cap. 2.
            OF Cōmon wealths there are three ſortes,Ariſt. Po lit. lib. 3.
                Ariſtocratie, Democratie, and Monarchie.
         
         
            
            VVhat is an Ariſtocratie. Cap. 3.
            ARiſtocratie is a gouernment, or empire, depē
               ding on the arbitrement of the beſt nobilitie, deriued of the Greeke worde Ariſtocratiae, in Latin, Optimorum potentia, in Engliſh, the rule of men of the beſt diſpoſitiō, from which regiment Kings were diſcarded and excluded. Such was the gouernment or eſtate of Rome, wherein the Senators ruled: this in the originall had experience, of the Empire of Kings, which within a litle after was changed into an Ariſtocratie, as into a worſ &amp; meaner eſtate: at which time Tarquinius was baniſhed,

for the deteſtable cryme and rape of Lucrecia, committed by his ſonne: after which time, the tried moderation of nobles or ancient Pieres of Rome ſteeded as a lawe: for all the authoritie and iuriſdiction conſiſted in the hands of Senators or Aldermen, which were in number a hū
               dred; who were accuſtomed to creat two yeerely conſuls, ſo named, for the prouiſion and conſultation that they made for the cōmon wealth. The Thebans of a long time obſerued this gouernment. This maner of gouernment is this day in Venice, howbeit there is a Duke, which ſtā
               deth for naught els but for a vaine cipher. Such hath bene ye
                imperial ſtate of Carthage. In this Ariſtocraticall gouernment,

mercenarie craftſmen, haue not bene thought worthy, to haue any place of any deſert or eſtimation, appertaining to this or the like gouernment.
         
         
            VVhat is a Democratie. Cap. 4.
            DEmocracie is a popular regiment, tending to the common good.
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   de origine iur. 
                     〈◊〉
                   ex
                  
                     •••••
                   vſqu
                     •
                   ad §. This worde Democratie is deriued of the Greek word Democratia, in Latine Popularis potentia, in Engliſh, the Rule of the Comminalties, who obtained the ſuperiority. This Empire was ſuſtained by gentlemen, whō we this day in England doe terme Eſquires, ſuch a gouernment is at this preſent time at Switzerland, where

the people are deuided into Cantons or hundreds, from whence the nobility haue bin reiected and excluded. Such ſort of gouernment was at Florence, vntil 60. yeares agoe, which afterwardes was changed into a Monarchie. So likewiſe was that Empire of Athens, in which Democratie aforeſaid the ſeede of raſhnes &amp; lawleſſe luſt held the ſuperioritie: becauſe in a diſordinate multitude the fruites of diſpleaſure, as hate, rebellion, ſectes, &amp; factions, and other heynous crimes muſt needs be nouriſhed, by a confuſion of miſgouernment, for defect of one ſole ſoueraigne, in whoſe handes the firſt &amp; chiefeſt forme of gouernment depēded: which beyng rightly eſtabliſhed, is

termed a kingdome, or royaltie, which falling into theſe vices, hauing moſt affinitie therewith, and being neareſt vnto it, as into a tyranny of their abolition, ariſeth an Ariſtocratie, which is commō
               ly or often changed into an Oligarchie &amp; when the people conſpireth reuengement of the iniuſtice of the gouernours, there hapneth this inferior gouernmēt of Democratie, becauſe the vertue of commanders are not alwaies alike. Thoſe men are accoū
               ted good mēbers of the Cō
               mon wealth, which to themſelues liue leaſt, and moſt to their citizēs, &amp; is hardly to be found in the pernicious ſtate of Democratie, becauſe it is thought a cruell conflict in diuers, combred with ſundry

cogitations, to leuell &amp; ayme at the ſelf ſame marke: inſomuch that the deſire of the one is the content of the other, &amp; al their deſire tend to the cōmoditie of the Cōmon wealth: In which there are 3. principal things to be noted in the gouernors therof: Firſt their loue towards it that is now eſtabliſhed: Secondly, their authority in gouerning: Thirdly, their vertue and iuſtice: all which are baniſhed out of a Democratie. Wherefore I worthily iudge this ſort of gouernment, to be the meaneſt and worſt of the three, becauſe there are many that ſee the beginning of the miſeries which ariſe, but few reſpecting their own commoditie leaſt, that ſeeke to ſuppreſſe the ſame. There

is no Common wealth more looſe then that wherein the common people haue moſt liberty,Cicero. which is their wiſhed deſire, Nihil enim magis cupit popularis multitudo, quam poteſtatem viuendi vt velit,
               Cicero et Floren. The common people doe deſire nothing more, then libertie to liue at their pleſure, which argueth &amp; ſheweth their immoderate vanitie and lightnes, their head-long doings, and vnaduiſed dealings, void of diſcretion, which procureth deadly ſedition, mutinies, &amp; vproares, to the vtter deſtruction of their kingdome. Wherefore there can no greater daunger enſue, or happen to a Commō wealth then to tollerate the rude, &amp; common ſorte to rule, who (as their propertie is) are alwayes

noted to be vnconſtāt and wauering, toſſed with euery ſudden blaſt, and carried with euerie light chaffe, as the Prouerbe is, Scinditur in contrarium ſemper inſtabile vulgus. The weatherlike vulgar are prone to admire euery thing, &amp; ready to turne as often as the tide. Wherefore they are rightly accounted to reſemble the vgly Hydra, which is ſayd, no ſooner to loſe one head, then immediatly another groweth. Herehence they are called the monſterous beaſt of many heads, whoſe Empire beginning Ordine retrogrado reſembling the Hebrew, Chaldeake, and Syriake, that are written frō the right hand to the left with points in ſtead of vowels: ſo this Democraticall

gouernment beginneth topſie turuy, frō the meaneſt to the higheſt, and as wanting vowels, with the Hebrewes, that is, imperiall o
                  •
                royall gouernment, endeth without any point or period, with Fiat deſtructio.
            
         
         
            VVhat is a Monarchie. Cap. 5.
            A Monarchie is the royall eſtate of an empire or gouernment, where one ſole Prince moſt magnificently raigneth, aſsigned vnto vs as a perfect caulme of permanent felicitie, againſt ſturdy ſtormes of pinching miſery. This word Monarchy is deriued of the Greek word Monos &amp; Archos, which in Latine is Vnius principatus, in

Engliſh the gouernment of one, in which Cōmonwelth many cannot fitly gouerne,Homer. wherfore it is thought expediēt, that one ſhould be created ſoueraigne. In the beginning of the world, al people were willing to ſubiect themſelues vnto a Monarch which was Nimrod;
                  Gen. 11. and ſo they became ciuill, calling to minde, that mighty men did lay engines, traps &amp; deuices to rifle them. Not long after, being ſundry times annoyed by fierce and ſauage beaſtes, betooke themſelues to ſocieties, frequēted &amp; reſorted vnto conſorts of a ſetled ſtay, fenced and inuironed within one circuite as their defence and ſafegard, which were termed Cities. Likewiſe euery country

as hope of ſafety, deſire of ſecuritie, enforced them to chuſe a Monarchy, the Iewes only excepted, who were gouerned by Iudges and Commiſsioners eſpecially elected to adminiſter Iuſtice, &amp; continue peace: but they after the cuſtome and manner of other nations deſired to haue a king, to whom Saul, according to their wiſhed deſire was graunted, and then were al people gouerned by kings, and one king of al the world was the Monarch, which Empire or Monarchie firſt began in Babilon and Aſſyria, conſequently to the Perſiās, than to the Grecians, laſt to the Romanes it was tranſlated. Plato that diuine and famous Philoſopher, wiſhed that there were on earth but

one King, as there is in heauen but one God, to the end that humane gouernment might reſemble the diuine, which Lord of the world, as a true Meſſias or ſhepheard of mankind, ſhould affect &amp; loue all men alike, as his naturall ſubiects, guiding them with good maners, lawes &amp; iudgements, affording them a ſecure entercourſe in all places, ſo mightie a Soueraigne or Potentate, enuiyng no perſon, and deſiring no occaſion to enlarge has frontiers by ambition, which would bee a meanes of ceaſing ſo many enormities, warres, ſlaughters ſpoiles &amp; robberies, incident to men, in reſpect of pluralitie and diſſentions of gouernment.Plato de legibus. Likewiſe Zeno the firſt and

chiefeſt author of the ſectes of the Stolkes, imagined one vniuerſall forme of gouernment, tending to this effect, that all men ſhould not liue by people &amp; nations, being ſeparated by particular laws, rites, and cuſtomes, but that they ſhoulde acknowledge themſelues fellow citizens: &amp; as there was but one ſort of life, as there was but one world, none otherwiſe than as it were but one flock, feeding vnder one ſhepheard in common paſtures, which is more eaſily to bee wiſhed than effected, cōſidering the diſorder amongſt men.
         
         
            VVhich of theſe ſorts is the beſt. Cap. 6.
            THere is no eſtate ſo highly eſtabliſhed, or ſo perfectly

ordered &amp; managed, to be compared to the royall ſcepter of a Monarchie guarded with good and wholeſome lawes, preuenting perils, by impoſing penalties on ſuch as haply in tract of time eclipſed with laſciuious perturbations of the minde, might otherwhiles infringe the rights of Iuſtice, and derogate from equitie &amp; truth, if the ſeueritie of lawes did not ſomewhat bridle their haughty mindes, &amp; repreſſe their frowarde diſpoſitions, whereupon that the Empire of a Monarch is the ſoueraigneſt and chiefeſt, if my cenſure may ſtand for a ſentence, may be euidently proued by foure reaſons. Firſt, in that the peace, vnity, concord and tranquillity of the

communalties,ff de off. preſil. cō
                  gruit in princ. &amp; autem de mendatis princ. §. deinde conueniens col. 3.
                is ſaid and accounted to be the finall end of the gouernour. But this peace, vnity &amp; concord, may rather be maintayned and augmented through the rule of one, then of many: therefore a Monarchie is beſt. Secondly, by the rule and gouernment of one, the power of the Common wealth is rather fortified, which may be thus proued:Vt autem de cōſangui. &amp; vt e. infra. § quia igitur col. 6. Vertue by how much more it is vnited, is ſo much the more corroborated, then if it were diſperſed into many partes. If therefore the Common wealth be guided by the handes of one ſupreame gouernour, it is the rather munified, and by this meanes the Prince ſhal with greater power, pompe, and might rule.Vt. l. ſi pri. in. fi. cum l. ſequent. ff. de adop. Thirdly, arte or

handicraft is the more excellent, by how much more it doth imitate nature. But an vniuerſall Common wealth, is nothing els ſauing an imaginary,ff. de iure. l. preponebat &amp; de fideiuſ. l. mortuo. or artificiall perpolited bodie, ſeyng that in ſuch a naturall body, we do coniecture and ſee one head and many members: wherefore a Citie or Monarchie, if it be ſo gouerned, it farre exceedeth:Ad idem ex de off. oc. c. quoniā pleriſque &amp; hoc ver. determinatū vii. q. I. cum apibu
                     •
                  . becauſe it more imitates &amp; reſembles nature. Fourthly, prouinces which are ſubiect vnto many, cannot enioy peace &amp; tranquillitie, but are the rather moleſted &amp; cumbred with iarres, bickerings, turmoiles, neuer liuing in quietnes, or poſſeſſing reſt. But contrariwiſe, in a Monarchie men are ignorant of quarrels, liuing in

ſafetie &amp; ſecuritie voyd of all annoiances,Bart. tract. de regimine ciuitat. incombred with no care, abounding with ſtore, &amp; flowing with plentie of all aboundance: to which if any will obiect, that by how much the more the number of rulers are, by ſo much the more excellent is the gouernmēt,L. hac cōſultiſſima infi. et ar. c. de teſti. l. iure. becauſe many are more prouident to foreſee and preuent caſualties which might happen to enſue, &amp; withall, one is eaſier to be corrupted than many: Therefore the gouernment of many is to bee preferred before the gouernment of one: To which I anſwer, that although a king or Prince is but one, yet hee ought to haue many prudent and wiſe Counſellours, and in reſpect thereof he ſeemeth as many:

and amongſt many, one who cannot poſsibly bee corrupted, vnleſſe all be corrupted, peruerted, and proue mutable. Shal we then proue farre inferior, and more ſenceleſſe than the vnnaturall bruite beaſtes, which onely are by ſence guided? they do create &amp; elect one to be their king and chiefe gouernour, as experiēce of the Bees teacheth vs, which do make choiſe of the chiefeſt Bee, to be a king ouer all the hieue,l. hac cō
                  ſultiſsima infi. et ar. c. de teſti. l. iure. by which the whole ſwarme are ledde and guided, as being more prouident and wiſe than the reſt.
         
         
            VVhat things are requiſite in a King. Cap. 7.
            
               
               If. de iuſt. &amp; iure 
                     •
                  . 1.
                FIrſt a king ought to haue reaſon and knowledge to diſtinguiſh Iuſtice from iniuſtice, trueth from falſhood, lawfull from vnlawfull, allotting no priuiledge to defraude any of his right, remē
               bring dominion, power, and ſuperiority not onely graunted him: but withall confidence and truſt to be repoſed, not to that end he might at his pleaſure condemne whom hee luſt, and effect what hee wiſhed;Cicero. but what both law &amp; religion ſhould require, abandoning cruell feare: for the Prince, that is feared of many, needes moſt to feare manie. Quis enim cum diligat quem metuit, aut cum à quo ſe metui putet? Secondly, a king ſhould haue free will, a right and a true

meaning to leuy euery one, not according to affection, but to deſert &amp; Iuſtice, euery man by euen portion his owne:Ariſtot. for as the minde of man in it ſelfe is more precious and excellent then all the other partes, as beyng voyde of indignitie and blemiſh: ſo ought the iudgement and ſentence of a king be incorrupt and irreprehenſible in all points. Alſo hee ſhould haue a perfect conſtācy to perſeuere in wel doing, that at al times his deeds might proue his doctrines; for cōſtancie &amp; temperance in all points maketh vertue ſtrōg. This is proued by the definitiō of iuſtice,Inſtit. li. 1. Ariſt. Ethic. li. 1. cap. 4.
                which is a cōſtant &amp; a perpetual will, yeelding euery one his own. For the better accōpliſhmēt

hereof, foure things herein are to be noted: firſt, the ſubiect wherein this Iuſtice is contained, which is Mens omnium pars nobiliſsima. Secondly, the conſideration of the parties in behalfe of whō it is put in vre, who are the moſt deere and louing creatures of God: Thirdly, in reſpect of the originall cauſe from whence it proceedeth, that is to ſay, from the omnipotent God, from whom all good thinges doe proceed: Fourthly, in reſpect of the authoritie of the perſon whō he repreſenteth, which is the moſt glorious father. Alſo it is expedient for a K. to haue wiſedome to decide controuerſie, fortitude to defend his Common wealth, valour to patronize his communalties

ſecuritie. Wiſdome without iuſtice, is but craftines, iuſtice without temperāce is meere cruelty, temperance without fortitude is extreme ſauagenes. To the firſt, Nunquam enim temeritas cum ſapientiae comitatur,
               Cicero. 
               neque ad conſilium caſus admittitur. Raſhnes neuer accompanieth wiſdome, neither is blindhap admitted to coūſaile. Except wiſemen be made gouernours, or gouernours wiſemen, mankind ſhall neuer liue at reſt, nor vertue be able to patronize and defend her ſelfe.Plato. To the ſecond, it behoueth a Prince to haue ſuch a zeale &amp; godly courage, that he may alwaies ſhew himſelfe a ſtrong wall for the defence of the trueth and ſecuritie of his ſubiects. Quis enim non obſtare cupiat,
               Cicero.
               
               quis non tantum quantum audet et poteſt, conferat ad cōmunem ſalutem. It is requiſit for a king to haue ſeueritie tempered with lenitie, to repreſſe the furie of the froward and wicked men, as a ſcourge allotted to extirpate and roote out al iniquity, carying a maieſtie in his thought, which might gard his mid frō cowardice, as the only priuiledge to contēpt. Maieſty is accoū
               ted to reſemble the lightening from the Eaſt; and the threats of a king, the noiſe of a thunder: wherefore it behoueth a king to place ſuch in authoritie, as are of an exquiſite vertue, &amp; ayme leaſt thereat, and to repell them from gouernmēt, that preſſe moſt forwardes to attayne the ſame. Alſo it is expedient

for a King, in executing of iuſtice,Ariſtot. Ethi. in diuerſe matters to make no procraſtination or delay, which cauſeth oftentimes great daungers to happen: which had it beene obſerued at the firſt, might eaſly haue bin preuēted, whē as letters were ſent from Athens to Archias gouernour of Polemarches, detecting the treaſon of certain outlawes who had conſpired againſt him, which letters after the receipt thereof, careleſſe without any peruſing hee layed all night vnder his pillowe, ſaying, Becauſe I iudge they are waightie matters, I wil adiourne them till the morrow. But before the morning his life was takē frō him. Which caueat Cicero did put in practiſe beyng

conſull, hauing a decree and an order to ſuppreſſe rebels: who aſſoone as Fuluia the paramour of Quintus Curius had diſcloſed their intēt, preuented it, otherwiſe hee had the ſame night bin ſlain in his owne houſe, and the whole Citie fired. It is neceſſarie for a King to bee ſtout &amp; rich,Plutarc. that by the one he may boldly challenge his owne, and by the other repreſſe his enemies, which for want thereof many become tyrants, and of ouer aboundance become enuious.Ageſilaus. A King ought to gouerne his realme and reigne ouer his people, as a Father ouer his children, and conſider the cauſe of the innocent, folowing the example of God, in hearing and regarding the

complaint of the diſtreſſed &amp; needy, whō God regardeth and pittieth, and as he wil not ſuffer the reprobate to eſcape vnpuniſhed, ſo will he not permit the iniuries done to the innocent, to eſcape the graue without reuenge. Alſo it is expedient for a prince to haue a charie care to his coū
               ſellors, in noting who ſoothe his luſt, &amp; tender the publike commoditie, for therby ſhall he decerne the good frō the bad.Plutarc. In decerning good frō euill, he may eſchew al enormities and vices, as enuy, anger and other odious crimes: for enuie is a filthy ſlime and an impoſtume of the ſoule, a perpetuall torture to him in whome it reſteth, a venome, a bitter bane, a caterpiller or fretting coraſiue, which conſumeth

the fleſh,Socrat. and drieth vp the marrow of the bones. What deſtroyed coū
               tries? ſubdued kingdomes? depopulated Cities? but enuie. Iulius Ceſar waged war with his owne ſonne in lawe Pompeius, beyng mooued with enuie. Qui ſummum imperium in Repub. geſturi ſunt, tria habere debent, primo, amorem erga Rempub. iam conſtitutam, ſecundo facultatem adminiſirandi et gubernandi: tertio virtutem et iuſtitiam, according vnto that of Deutronomie,Deut. ca. 16.
                Thou ſhalt do according as they teach thee, and not bowe either to the right hand,Auguſt. or to the left. Iuſtice is to God the chiefeſt incenſe, and equitie without guile is a ſacrifice of ye
                ſweeteſt ſauour, whereby gouernours

muſt meaſure nothing by report, but by the way of cōſcience: for it litle auaileth a Prince to be Lord of many Monarchies, if on the otherſide he become a bondſlaue to vice: wherefore a Prince ought to abandon anger as a notorious vice. For as Salomon ſaith, Anger in a King is death: grimme &amp; terrible is his countenance, when he is puffed with wrath, hurtful to many, odious to al is the ſight thereof. Alexander waxed ſo furious and angry,Valerius li. 9. c. 3.
                that hee could not permit his deare friend Clitus, to cōmend his owne father king Philip of Macedony. O witleſſe wil, O fancie fraught ful of phrenſie &amp; furie, in ſtouping without a ſtall, to ſuch a frantike &amp; vaine furie, which in whoſoeuer

it reſteth, enforceth either to breake or bend: as therefore holding the flagge of defiāce againſt theſe lewd vices, let vertue be thy life, Iuſtice thy loue, honor thy fame, &amp; heauen thy felicitie.
            1 Kings ought to be the ſhelters to pouertie, their ſeats the ſanctuaries for the diſtreſſed.
            2 As a king excelleth in pompe, power and riches, ſo ought he to exceed in vertue and wiſedome.
            3 Rulers doe more heynouſly offend, in tolerating the companie of vitious perſons, yeelding ill example, becauſe the offence that is committed in his companie, is accompted euill.
            4 The dutie of a king is to liſten &amp; conſider the complaint

of his people without reſpect of perſon.
         
         
            Magiſtrates ought to ſee iuſtice adminiſtred. Cap. 8.
            THe greateſt parte of the office &amp; dutie of kings in auncient time, was to ſee the adminiſtratiō of Iuſtice. Homer the poet may be a ſufficient witneſſe, when he faieth of Agamemnon, that the Scepter &amp; law was committed to him by GOD, to doe right to euery man: anſwerable to the which (Virgil deſcribing the Queene of Carthage) ſaith ſhe ſate in iudgement in the middeſt of the people, as if there nothing beſeemed ſuch a perſon, but ſuch an action, and therefore

the poets not without a cauſe fame Iupiter alwaies to haue Themis, that is, Iuſtice, at his elbow: ſignifying, not that whatſoeuer Kinges or Princes did, was iuſtice and lawfull, be it neuer ſo vile in his owne nature, (as that wantō flatterer Anaxarchus ſaid to Alexander) but that equitie and iuſtice ſhould alwaies accompanie them, and neuer depart frō their ſides: &amp; hereupō it was that Adacus, Minos, and Rhadamanthus, the firſt king of Grecia, were ſo renowned of olde antiquitie, becauſe of their true and vpright execution of Iuſtice; and therfore were not honored with greater title, than with the name of Iudges. It is ſaid of K. Alexander, that although he was

alwaies buſied in the affaires of the wars &amp; in giuing battels, yet he would ſitte perſonally in iudgement to heare criminal cauſes &amp; matters of importance pleaded; &amp; whileſt the accuſed laid open his accuſation with one hand he would ſtop one eare, to the end the other might be kept pure, &amp; without preiudice for the defence &amp; anſwer of the accuſed. The Roman Emperors alſo were very careful &amp; diligent in this behalf: as firſt Iulius Ceſar, who is recorded to haue taken great paines in giuing audiēce to the parties, &amp; in dealing iuſtice between thē. In like maner Auguſtus Ceſar is cōmēded for his care in this behalfe, for he would ordinarily ſitte in iudgement vpon cauſes and cōtrouerſies

of his ſubiects, and that with ſuch delight &amp; pleaſure, that oftentimes night was fayne to interrupt him before he would giue it ouer: yea, although he found himſelf not well at eaſe, yet would he not omit to apply himſelfe to the diuiſion of iudgement, or els calling the parties before him to his bedſide. Iorā king of Iſrael ſonne of Achab, though a man that walked not vprightly before GOD, but gaue himſelfe to worke abominatiō in his ſight, yet he deſpiſed not the poore. A famiſhed womā of Samaria, when ſhe demaunded iuſtice at his hands, although it was in the time of warre, whē lawes vſe to be ſilent, and in the beſieging &amp; famiſhment of the citie, neyther did he

requeſt the Sunamite for the recouerie of her houſe and lands, but cauſed them to be reſtored vnto her. So that then it is manifeſt, that thoſe which in old time raigned ouer the people of God, albeit they had in euery citie Iudges, yea, and in Ieruſalem alſo, as it appeareth in the 19. chapter or the 2. booke of Chronicles, yet they ceaſed not to giue eare to ſuites and complaints that were made vnto them, and to decide cō
               trouerſies that came to their knowledge: &amp; for this cauſe it is that Wiſedome ſaieth, That by her kings raigne, &amp; Princes decree iuſtice: whervnto alſo belongeth that which is ſaide in an other place, that a King ſetting in the throne of iudgemēt, chaſeth

away all euill with his eyes.
         
         
            VVhat is a tyrant. Cap. 9.
            
               A Tyrant is a ſuperiour Gouernour that ruleth as he liſteth, who onely raigneth to pleaſure a few, &amp; not to the publike profit,Aristot. who is accoūted a rigorous ill diſpoſed king, that perſiſteth in extreames, perſeuering in moodleſſe modeſty, accuſtoming to chaſtice many for the fault of one, which is amōgſt euils the greateſt euil, &amp; amongſt tyrants the greateſt tyranny, that they of thē
               ſelues will not liue within the precincts, &amp; vnder the rights of law &amp; iuſtice, nor yet conſent that malefactors ſhould

receiue puniſhmēt: he eſteemeth it better to haue his own palace coſtly furniſhed, &amp; the common weale poore, than his palace poore, &amp; the common weale rich. A tyrāt is a king choſen by popular &amp; ambitious election, on the behalf of the cōmunalties, to patronize their cauſe againſt the chiefeſt citizens, preuenting iniuries, whoſe property is not to reſpect the publique vtilitie, but onely his priuate cōmoditie, whoſe glory conſiſteth in riches &amp; delight, in pleaſure and pompe. Such a one was Dioniſius the tyrāt choſē of the Syracuſiās. The like king was Atreus, brother to Thyeſtes, &amp; ſonne to king Pelops, who tyrānouſly ſlew without compaſsion three ſons of his brother Thyeſtes,

whoſe bloud hee cauſed his brother and their owne Father to drinke vnawares, and hauing hidden their bodies in a caue, cut off their members, and made their Father to eate thereof. So likewiſe Aſtyages played the tyrant, enforcing Harpagus to eate his owne ſonne,Trogus Pomp. dreſſed and ſerued at his table before Harpagus, of which as being ignorant he fed: but not long after, as a reward for this deteſtable tyranny, Harpagus cauſed his owne nephewe young Cyrus to wage warre againſt him: of whome hee was ouercome &amp; exiled out of his kingdome. Like as a battered or a crazed ſhip by letting in of water, not only drowneth her ſelfe, but all that are in her: ſo a king or a

vitious tyrant, by vſing deteſtable enormities, deſtroyeth not himſelfe alone, but all others beſide that are vnder his gouernment; and though vniuſt offences eſcape for a time without penaltie, yet neuer without reuēge: wherfore, as many haue beene remembred through equitie &amp; iuſtice, aduanced to great honor, euen ſo iniurious inuaſions, oppreſsions, curſed and reprobated ſpeeches, &amp; ſūdry enacted cruelties, haue bene the vtter wrack, ruine, and endles decay of famous men, and honorable peeres: therfore the miſerable wretchednes almoſt of all ſauage tyrants, may wel yeeld a ſufficient teſtimony: for not only they were bereued of their liues, and depriued of dignities,

but ſuch as were alied vnto them by blood &amp; conſanguinitie, or adherents by confederacy, in ſo much that the greateſt died the like death, &amp; the reſt being ſpoiled of their goods and poſſeſsiōs, hardly eſcaped death by baniſhment, neuertheleſſe they could not happely eſcape, and auoid the ſpot of ſlaunder and ſhamefull obloquie: and that I may here without offence ſpeake of Phalaris the lewdeſt and vnſatiableſt bloudſucker that euer nature yeelded, againſt whome rebelled the whole multitude of the citie Agrigētinum; &amp; that I may lightly paſſe ouer diuerſe others with ſilence, whoſe maners were infected with the like barbarous cruelty, as beyng

nulled with vice, and weaned from vertue, aſſuredly al the blood &amp; race of Phiſtratus by this onely way loſt their gouernment &amp; principalitie. What ſhould I ſpeak of the Tarquines? were not they traced in the ſame vice, and trayned in the ſame ininiquitie, and for the ſame cauſe baniſhed Rome, becauſe they regarded no right, but doing all by violence and extreame crueltie? and whereas Sextus Tarquinius, imitating the lewde and abominable ſteps and wickedneſſe of his Father, had after many iniuries, whereby he had wronged the Romanes, before committed, and vſed violence to chaſte Lucretia, liued with his Father and brethren as an

outcaſt and a ſtragling ſtraū
               ger in a ſtraunge countrey.Ariſtot. Wherefore it may be well imagined, that ſuch an Empire cannot long endure, becauſe all the gouernment therof cōſiſteth in extreames &amp; violence, doing all things without the conſideration of iuſtice, truth &amp; equitie. Laſtly, amōgſt gouernmēt or ſoueraintie, a tyrannicall gouernment is the worſt, Democratie the ſecond; but amōgſt theſe euils, Oligarchie is the leaſt euill.
            1 In vaine is that Prince which is fortified with terror, &amp; is not garded with Iuſtice.
            2 The tyrant that will loſe many friends, to be rid of one foe, may be admired for his policie, but condemned for his impietie.
            
               3 Tyrants, which by fained gouernment and blazed vertue doe win admirations, are ſaid to buy iuſt poſſeſsions with wrongs.
            4 The tyrānie of Princes openeth euery gappe for ruine to enter, which Iuſtice keepeth backe.
         
         
            VVhat is the nature and condition of an Oligarchie. Cap. 10.
            THe nature or condition of an Oligarchie is, that fewe nobles, and the chiefeſt rich men ſhould haue the ſuperioritie, becauſe the ſtate thereof doth conſiſt of aboū
               dance of wealth and riches: therfore what cities or Common wealths were noted to flouriſh with ſumptuous exceſſe

of varietie, wealth and chiualrie, and therein excelled, ſuch cities were termed an Oligarchie; as amōgſt the moſt people of Aſia.
         
         
            VVhat difference is betweene an Oligarchie, &amp; a Democratie. Cap. 11.
            
               Ariſtot. Politic.THe politike gouernment of an Oligarchie is more ſeuere and ſtrict, and more royall and magnificent, than the gouernment of a Democratie, being of equall authoritie in all degrees of perſons, &amp; more remiſſe &amp; mild; which gouernment continued in diuerſe places, &amp; eſpecially at Athens, vntil ſuch tyme they ſuſtained the heauie yoke of the thirty tyrants:Herodo. which Democraticall

Empire, as Cicero ſaieth, is moſt diſordinate: for there is no Common wealth more looſe, than that, wherein the people haue ouermuch libertie. This ſort of popular gouernment is two fold: the one conſiſting in the rule &amp; gouernment of the chiefeſt citizens, the other conſiſting in the rule of free men. The firſt, of Theſeus and Draco inſtituted, the ſecond, by Ariſtides, Pericles and others, haunting after popular applauſe.
         
         
            Of Lawe. Cap. 12.
            XEnophon that famous philoſopher, extolling the Perſian laws, teſtifieth,

that their citizens, from their very childhood, were taught to attempt, or almoſt imagine nothing diſhoneſt or vnlawful: after which maner, as it were for the confirming thereof, Draco, as Gellius reporteth being a citizen of Athens, and indued with wiſedome &amp; prudence, firſt of all decreed a law to the Athenians, the which, as Plutarch reporteth, was ſo bitter and ſtrict, impoſing deadly puniſhment to the tranſgreſſours thereof, for euerie light offēce. Whereof proceeded this excellent voyce of Demadis, ſaying, The laws of Draco were written with bloud, and not with inke. Of which ſpeach being demaū
               ded a reaſon, hee anſwered, that thoſe Lawes impoſed

ouermuch ſeueritie. This or the like ſpeaches haue beene vttered by Anaxerxes to the like effect, who hearing that Solon made a law to the Athenians, he ſmiled thereat, comparing it to the web of a ſpider, which is wont to take the leſſer flies, and ſuffer the greater flies to eſcape and breake the web. Wherby he meant, that Solon had vſed parcialitie in the conſtituting thereof, by which meanes growe many inconueniences: for the law is not too cruel in her frowns, nor too parciall in her fauours. Firſt, too much extremitie and ouermuch lenitie ſhould not bee vſed, becauſe extreame law ſometimes is thought to bee extreame wrong, and ouermuch lenitie breedeth illicentiouſnes

and ſundrie vices in all ſorts. But omitting theſe particularities, who ſo deemeth of the generall nature &amp; diſpoſition of lawes, taketh his ayme amiſſe, and ſhooteth wide frō the marke: for doubtleſſe the lawe will tolerate no parcialitie, the condition thereof beyng alike to all ages and all degrees: for as Cicero ſayeth, Vera lex eſt recta ratio, naturae congruens, diffuſa in omnes, conſtans ſempiterna. True Lawe is a right reaſon of nature, agreeyng therewith in all points, diffuſed &amp; ſpred in all Nations, conſiſting perpetuall: and though men erre in conſtruyng the true meaning thereof, and albeit diuerſe in the executing thereof haue vſed parciality,

being moued by affection or the like occaſion, as Alexander told his father Philippe of Macedonie, who hearing and iudging the cauſe of Macheta negligently, &amp; giuing no right iudgement, tolde his Father that he had done amiſſe: againſt whom alſo Macheta exclaimed. The which Philip hearing, demaunded, Whom doeſt thou meane? Hee anſwered, I ſpeak vnto you, deſiring that you would heare my cauſe more attentiue, &amp; iudge more circūſpect. But for that time departing as beyng angrie, within a litle after Macheta returned vnto him, hee conſidered thereupon, Et quaſi meliori iudicio, Taking counſell of his pillow, chaunged his

former ſentence and iudgemēt. Neuertheleſſe the law, God himſelfe beyng author thereof, cannot proue mutable: for as Plato ſaieth, Lex nullo affectu mouetur, non iraſcitur, non odit, non ambitione ducitur, diligit omnes, pariter
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   omnibus indulget. The Lawe is moued by no affection, and is not puffed vp with anger, hatred or ambition, for it loueth all men, and embraceth euery one alike, which breedeth quietnes to all, encreaſeth loue, augmenteth Charitie, and continueth peace and concorde amongſt all eſtates; whereof wee haue manifeſt proofe: For what cauſed Moſes to be highly eſteemed, and exceedingly beloued of the Iewes, but the

eſtabliſhing of their Lawe, which according to the originall hath beene inuented, both for the maintayning of equitie and Iuſtice, embracing of vertue, and to ſalue the decayed eſtate and frailtie of mās nature, which hath bene guided by iuſtice, tempered with honeſty, inſtructed by rules, examples and exhortatiōs, from which hauing ſwarued to chaſtice the inſolent and hauty behauiour of lewd perſons, lawes were inuented, enacted and deuiſed: wherof there were three ſortes: the lawe of nature, whoſe vertue is all one,Iuſtinianus inſtitu. lib. 1.
                and the ſame euery where in all, or rather a very notice of Gods lawes, engraffed in the minde of man. The ſecond is the law of nations, which no

otherwiſe may be deſcribed, than of cuſtomes, maners, and preſcriptions, which is of like condition to all people. Thirdly, Ciuil lawe, which is an abridgemēt derogating manie illicentious cuſtomes, which grewe by peruerſnes and corruptnes of nature: and this is termed Peculiar, vſed by one kind of people;Iuſtinian. lib. 1.
                ciuill, Quaſi vnius ciuitatis propriū. Beſides theſe, there haue bin other lawes called Morall, of the x. Commandements, &amp; ceremoniall lawes &amp; rites enioined to the Leuites, beſides the lawes of Moſes, &amp; many other iudicial ſtatutes of natural policies, of which I need not to ſpeake. But to draw neerer to my purpoſe, and to ſpeake more proper, I thinke it not amiſſe,

to lay downe ſomwhat of the law of Ariſtotle, which he calleth, Ius legitimū, &amp; ſeemeth to haue ſome affinitie with this our law of England, being made by cōmon conſent preſcribing thereunto: wherfore in my iudgement, it may wel chalēge the name of Statute law, or Act enacted and cōcluded in a parliament: all which lawes were inuented for the vpholding of trueth, maintaining of iuſtice, being as a meaſure which God hath ordained amongſt men in earth, to defēd the feeble frō the mighty, for the ſuppreſſing of iniuries, &amp; to root out the wicked from among the good, which preſcribeth theſe ſpeciall points, To liue honeſtly, to hurt no mā wilfully, to render euery man his due carefully, as proceeding

from the minde of God, furthering what is right, &amp; prohibiting what is wrong, according to the definition therof; which is termed a ſingular reaſō imprinted in nature, as an vnuiolable &amp; perpetuall good, without which no houſe, no citie, no countrey, no eſtate of man, no naturall creature, nor yet the world it ſelfe can firmely cō
               ſiſt: for thoſe cities, in which there are no lawes, impoſing penalties of ſinne, and yeelding a reward to the good, may be counted rather wild foreſts for Tigers, then inhabitable places for men: yet the moſt neceſſary lawe for the Common wealth is, that the people amōg themſelues liue in peace &amp; vnitie, without ſtrife and diſſention.
            
               1 Euery man in generall loueth law, yet they all hate the execution thereof in particular.
            2 The lawe iudgeth with extremitie, and equitie with lenitie.
            3 He is much to be cō
               demned, that liues in feare of iudgemēt, neglecting the rights of law.
            4 The heart that loueth the Prince loially, obſerueth his lawes carefully, and defendeth his coūtrey valiantly, is to be commended farre aboue all others.
         
         
            Of Magiſtrates. Cap. 13.
            FOr the executing of laws, and the obſeruing of Iuſtice, Magiſtrates are to bee

ordained, which are the tōgs of law, and lawe a mute Magiſtrate, who ſhould be both religious and godly: for the onely motions thereof, are the moſt ſpeciall garde of a flouriſhing Commō wealth, whoſe propertie aboue all others, is to ſhewe themſelues godly patterns of equity and pietie, becauſe the people might ſo much the more fear to liue reckleſſe and ruthful: in the diſcharging &amp; accompliſhing wherof, they ſhould remaine conſtant, &amp; not ſubiect to any chaunce or tranſmutatiō, nor by any way led eyther by friendſhip or affection, or ſeduced by any other ſiniſter meanes, as bribery, or riches, which though a man abound with neuer ſo great ſtore, yet deſerueth he

not to enioy the functiō of a magiſtrate, vnles he be adorned with ſundry vertues, and qualified with rare qualities, as diuerſe learned men haue verified, waying not the outward value, but the inward vertue. Wherfore Demonax when he ſaw a iolly ſwaine ſit in his Scarlet gowne, well pleaſing his own humor, beholding himſelf placed in the Theatre of dignitie, ſaid vnto him, Sir, this robe of yours was a ſheepes coate, before it came to your backe; noting that his wealth or gay attire could not ſhrowde his ruſtick maners. Wherby we may learne, that it is not only wealth, gay attire, or gorgeous robes, nor yet grauitie of yeeres without wiſdome, knowledge, prudence, and

other vertues, that can cauſe a man to deſerue that place, wherein he is to miniſter iuſtice &amp; equitie: riches cannot alter ſimplicitie, nor wealth procure prudencie; and as for grauity of yeeres &amp; ripenes of age, it is a thing which ought ſomewhat to bee regarded, if ſo bee it carieth a ſmacke of vertue and a taſte of wiſedome, for experience hath a great prerogatiue, becauſe grauitie of yeares furthereth credite: but as for wealth onely they are not to be eſteemed, neither ſhould a Magiſtrate in conſideratiō thereof be choſen; for aboundance of riches maketh him to liue ſecurely, and want of wiſedome, to attempt any thing wilfully, for ignorance is a blinde guide, and a rude

miſtres, &amp; none proue more bold then blinde bayardes: but yet I denie not, but meaſure of wealth is neceſſarie to maintaine honor: but how ſoeuer, it is harde to rule, and troubleſome to vndertake the charge: for the executing of iuſtice is an office that muſt be ſtrēgthned by zeale, and zeale maketh equitie inuincible, by which meanes they muſt needs offēd ſome; for that which ſeemeth iuſt to many, is offenſiue to others, and ſeemeth vniuſt: ſo by iudging rightly they muſt offend men, and in effecting the contrarie, they diſpleaſe God: wherefore as being difficult, and the burden ouerweighty, it was reported, that Pompey being cōbred with his honor, exclaimed to

ſee Scillas crueltie, beeing 
                  •
               gnorant after what ſorte to behaue himſelf in the dignitie he had, &amp; cried out, O perill and danger neuer like to haue an end. Whereby it appeareth, that he thought it farre better, to proceed from a meane and baſe ſtocke, that thereby he might lead a priuate and quiet life, then to be imployed in any politike gouernmēt. As therfore the conſideration of the charge is great, and the execution weighty, ſo for the better accompliſhmēt of both, ſhould none but the worthieſt approch therunto, whoſe worthines and dignity ſhould as much grace the place, as the place his perſon. But leauing theſe circūſtances, I will approch vnto the Magiſtrates,

of which, as Ariſtotle ſayeth, ther are in general two kinds which do beare office; wherof he calleth one a neceſſarie Magiſtrate, without which a citie cannot rightly ſtand. Of the ſortes of Magiſtrates belonging to the firſt kinde, there is one politike, which is imploied about ciuil matters, as were thoſe of the citie of Rome, conuerſant about ciuill affaires, &amp; munera municipialia, by which meanes they were partakers with the citizēs of any gift or reward, which by right they might challenge in regard of their ciuill offices. There is an other holy or godly magiſtrate which is buſied in diuine affaires. The aforeſaid politike Magiſtrate, is either a ſuperiour officer, or an inferiour:

ſuperiour officers were they, in whoſe handes all the gouernment did depend or cō
               ſiſt, as in the citie of Rome, wherein the Senatours were the ſuperiour officers, or as ſome would haue, the Patricians were the ſuperiour officers, who were made by the Centurian conuocation, and as thought neceſſary, confirmed Lege curia. The inferiour officer was accuſtomed to care and foreſee common matters, and enquired of any lawfull or vnlawfull thing committed, and after what ſort they were done, whether iuſt or vniuſt, &amp; aſsiſted other officers in executing their duties. Such officers alſo were in the citie of Rome, which were thought to be the common people, created

               Lege Tributa and this inferiour was of two ſorts, either of ſmall note or account, or of leſſer regard or eſtimatiō
               ▪ they that were of ſmall account, they againe were either in the towne, becauſe townſemen, or without the towne and precincts, which were termed of the ſuburbs, The vrbane and towne officers, were thoſe which were carefull ouerſeers, prouiding all things neceſſarie, &amp; ſupplying the want therof, inſtituted to make prouiſion, and procuring reformatiō either of dilapidations, or any decayed or ruinate thing to be amended. The Magiſtrates that were without the citie or ſuburbes, were the ouerſeers of the fieldes, and prouided wood and ſuch neceſſaries.

The foreſaid Diuine officers, were thoſe which were buſied in godly and holy matters: of which there were two ſorts, either thoſe which did accompliſh holy and diuine things, or els did care and prouide for holy matters: they that buſied themſelues in holy matters, were Prieſts and Preachers: thoſe that cared for holy and diuine affaires, were inferiour miniſters, vnto whom ye
                charge of the holy ſanctuarie was committed, and thoſe were termed, Quaeſtores ſacri: or High prieſts. The Magiſtrate belonging to the firſt kinde, that Ariſtotle called, Leſſe needfull, was required as an ornament for ciuill life, for reformation of maners.
            1. Magiſtrates are cōmonly

called Phiſicians of the publike weale, yeelding a potion for the ridding out of all diſtemperate humours.
            2. The Magiſtrate that politikely intendeth the good of the common weale, may be termed vpright, but hee that practiſeth onely for his own profit, is a vitious, and a lewd Magiſtrate.
            3. A Magiſtrate is likened to a running or ſpringing fountaine, which the more it runneth, the greater and wider it openeth the path: euen ſo a good Magiſtrate, the longer he ruleth, the greater ſway in ſubuerting vices he beareth.
            4. The onely ſcope of a magiſtrate, is to glorifie God in the executing of iuſtice, diſcharging of his dutie, and

cauſing men to liue vprightly, and further the trueth.
         
         
            Of Counſailours. Cap. 14.
            FOr the aduiſing and directing of the communalties in all affaires without cō
               fuſion, and the procuring of the ſecuritie of the common wealth in all eſtates, Counſellours are neceſſarie to bee required, and thought expedient, to reſolue al doubts, to decide debates, &amp; deliberate wiſely, as well in time of peace, as warre, what are to be effected, what enterpriſe to be taken in hand, leſt that follie giuing the mate, the communalties by their wiſedome might with more eaſe auoyde the checke: for hee

that is forewarned by counſaile, of imminent danger, againſt all future miſhap and calamitie, may thereby preuent perils, if it be poſſible, or if by ſiniſter fortune it may not bee eſchewed, then hee may beare the croſſe with more patience and ſmaller griefe: for happie is he that is warned by other mēs harms, and ſuch are moſt miſerable, that are wiſe by their owne woes. Counſailours are called by Licurgus, The Champions of the Common wealth, and by diuers other learned authours, The keyes of certaintie, The ſacred anker or defence of the Common weale, beeing one minde, ſeeing with many eyes, and working with ſundrie handes, and

for wiſedome, exceeding in conſultation, as being many, and yet conſenting in one, and all for the proſperitie of the common wealth, to which end they are conſtituted, ſome waying &amp; forecaſting imminent perils and inconueniences, which want no dammage; others, ſearching out remedies, which haue their profits and emoluments. Theſe Counſellours being garniſhed with learning and experience, ought deliberatly and vigilantly, to tender the ſecuritie of the common wealth, preferring the publike profit, before their particular commoditie, as hauing theſe circumſtances before their eyes, premeditating whether it be lawful or vnlawfull, whether neceſſarie,

with the conſiderations therevnto annexed, comparing honeſtie and credite, as twinnes and adherents together; and in the diuerſitie of theſe cauſes, which is moſt honeſt and moſt profitable, omitting no circūſtances: for as Cicero ſaith, A diſcreet and wiſe Counſailour neuer yeeldeth his conſent, or preſcribeth to any Act or Statute, to bee promulgated &amp; proclaimed, before hee hath ſome ſingular reaſon conceiued with himſelfe, as a ſufficient token and proofe therof, or elſe hath learned of others, the cauſe wherfore the ſame ſhould be worthily executed &amp; eſtabliſhed. He that doth nothing without counſell or aduice, needs not to repent him of his deed: for it

is the beginning and ending of euery good worke.Cicero. Hee that will not at the firſt hand buy counſell good cheape, ſhall at the ſecond hand, buy repentance deare. Wherfore let none cōtemne the counſel of their friends,Pythago. nor reiect the aduice of the wiſe, preferring his wit before their wiſedome, nor leane to wilfulnes, leſt had I wiſt come too late. For none is of ſuch perfection, that he may haue an inſtant remembrance of all things. Romulus the firſt king of the Romanes, in the firſt conſtitution of their cō
               mon weale, hauing of his own people, not aboue three thouſande footemen, and three hundreth horſemen, yet ſelected and picked out of the eldeſt and wiſeſt of

them all, one hundred counſellours, thinking that the common wealth could not rightly bee gouerned without them.
            A common wealth, is like the Celedonie ſtone, which retaineth her vertue no longer, than it is rubbed with golde: ſo the happie ſtate of the common wealth flouriſheth no longer, than it retaineth Counſellours: which whoſoeuer wanteth, though he poſſeſſeth neuer ſo great ſtore of riches, enioyeth care to himſelfe, enuie for his neighbours, ſpurres for his enemies, a pray for theeues, toyle for his perſon, anguiſh for his minde, a comberſome ſcruple and care for his conſcience, daunger for his friends, woe for his

children, wretchedneſſe to his heires, in that hee findeth readie way to heape riches, and wanteth counſaile to diſpoſe his gettings. The Niniuites ouerweaned with wantonneſſe, their ſurcoates being of bliſſe, all poliſhed with golde, pampering themſelues with palpable follies, as wanting counſell, vntill Ionas by his Ambroſian and diuine counſell, reclaimed them to a better conformitie.
            The Oracle of Apollo at Delphos, beeing demaunded, Why Iupiter ſhould bee the chiefeſt of the gods, ſith Mars was the beſt ſouldiour? anſwered, Mars is valiant, but Iupiter wiſe: concluding

by this, that counſell and policie are of more force to ſubdue, than valour: Parua ſunt arma foris,
               Cicero. 
               niſi ſit conſilium domi: Weapons doe little ſteade in warres, vnleſſe there bee Counſaile at home to direct them. The neceſſitie whereof, the equall authoritie in all degrees of a Democratic, may bee a liuely witneſſe, who did all things without counſell or aduice, voyde of diſcretion in their furious outrages and follies, impoſing moſt cruell tormentes vndeſeruedly vpon diuers innocent perſons, and condemning moſt ſage &amp; wiſe Counſailors by falſe ſurmiſes, as Solō, &amp; Phocion,

to the vtter decay and ruine of their Common wealth: &amp; therefore in no wiſe are coū
               ſellers to be wāted in a common weale, that are meet for ſo neceſſarie a charge, whoſe worthines (no doubt) conſiſteth in maner, wholy in their good example of honeſt and godly conuerſation &amp; orderly liuing. The which ſaying, Demoſthenes well declared to the people of Athens, when Philip king of Macedonie, vnder colour diſſembled peace with the citie, and ſo offered truce, vpon condition, that they would deliuer Demoſthenes and nine other, which hee thought of moſt force againſt him in their cōmon coūſels: of which if he had obtained his expectatiō, no doubt but

he thought, the want thereof would the ſooner cauſe him to captiuate their whole city, and endaunger their liues; which being denied, procured the cities ſecuritie.
            1 Counſell is a ſweete conſerue, and aduice the pureſt auditor.
            2 In counſailes we muſt be hard to reſolue, and conſtant to performe.
            3 Wee are warned by the wiſe, not to accept the counſell of the worldly man, whoſe aduice wil proue to be his owne deſire.
            4 Counſell is the ſure ground of reaſon, and the ſcourge of the wicked is law.
         
         
            Of Iudges. Cap. 15.
            
               IVdges are the Phiſicions of the Cōmon wealth, ordained to adminiſter iuſtice, to decide controuerſies, and for the puniſhing of malefactors, by whoſe means worldly quietnes is preſerued &amp; truth maintained. In theſe Iudges there are 4. things to be conſidered: firſt, to heare curteouſly, to anſwere wiſely, to conſider ſoberly, and to giue iudgemēt without parciality: which are no leſſe neceſſarie, then is the ſoule in a liuing bodie. For being indifferent to both parties, he reduceth that to equalitie, which he thinketh vnequall: not vnlike vnto a line cut into vnequall partes; that part which is too long is cut ſhorter, &amp; added to the other. So doth the Iudge, being the liuing

law, &amp; as it were an Oracle in the common weale. The Iudge ought alſo to account himſelf an interpreter to lawmakers, a miniſter of iuſtice, and his chiefe vertue muſt be, to know what is iuſt and true: he ought therefore not to ſwarue from law, and the meaning therof, but giue iudgemēt as the law, equity, &amp; iuſtice doth command: for which reſpect it behoueth him to be ſworne, to the end that God may be preſent to witnes his intēt &amp; cōſcience, which of al other things God hath made in man moſt diuine. Let ye
                Iudge be free frō ire, and all ſuſpition of hope, loue, and hatred, not corruptible with giftes, not fearfull of threates, nor by flatterie ſeduced: for where Iudges

are ſubiect to theſe paſsions, Iuſtice is farre remoued frō the iudiciall ſeate, and the Iudge himſelfe. For there is nothing that infecteth the Common wealth more with ſeditious hate, and iniuries, than the corruption and iniuſtice of Iudges, By good &amp; equall iudgements, the loue vniuerſall of men is preſerued, quarels, enmities, warres and ſedition are thereby appeaſed, becauſe they are in euery eſtate of ſuch great force, as by good iudgemēts, the whole Common wealth doth ſeeme to be maintained, and by euil Iudges ſubuerted. This Iuſtice which concerneth iudgement, hath greateſt power to extirpate vices in all eſtates: for if offenders be puniſhed, there

will be no place left for violence, fraude and audaciouſnes, preſumption &amp; iniuries. The perſon of Iudges was by the auncient Philoſophers painted like vnto a faire virgin, hauing a ſeuere &amp; fearful aſpect, piercing eies, chaſt and modeſt countenance, inclined to grauitie: which image ſeemeth to repreſent, that Iudges ought to bee incorrupt, chaſt, ſeuere, ſharpe witted, good conceiuers of all things, graue, conſtant, &amp; inexorable. Cambiſes, king of Perſia, cauſed the skinne of one vniuſt Iudge, to bee ſlayed from his bodie, &amp; hanged vp in the place of iudgement, to the end that thereby, all Iudges might be warned to be iuſt and vpright. In like maner ought our Counſellours

to take heed that their Iuſtice (which extendeth to all ſorts of people) may bee moſt dutifull, and that both in making and executing of Lawes, he may ſhewe himſelfe a man of a ſingular iuſtice: for it were ſhame for him not to obſerue Lawes, who is the executer of them. He commandeth others, &amp; the law cōmandeth him, not that law only which is writtē in books, &amp; tables of braſſe, but the liuing lawe of reaſon which remaineth in our minds. Iulius Ceſar had ſuch regard of equitie and iuſtice, after hee had obtained the gouernment of Rome, that he neuer omitted any paine or labour, as well in common cauſes, concerning the defence and aſsiſtaunce of

the innocent, as alſo in hearing and ſtudiouſly diſcuſſing all controuerſies, almoſt daily in his own proper perſon. But happy were thoſe daies wherein Baſil the Emperour of Conſtantinople liued, that whēſoeuer he came to his iudgement ſeat, found neither partie to accuſe, nor defendant to anſwere; which was a ſigne of an vpright liuing. Herein might that of Solon be ſaid to be obſerued, who being asked how the cōmon wealth might be preſerued: anſwered, If the people obey the Magiſtrates, &amp; the Magiſtrates be vigilant in executing iuſtice, and in obeying the Lawes. And alſo that of Bias verified, who ſaid, that the Common welth might be beſt aſſured,

where all men liued vprightly, not trāſgreſsing the laws, yet fearing thē no leſſe than a tyrant. It were then a thing moſt vnfit and vnconuenient in all eſtates, that the lawe ſhould be reputed, as the ſpiders webbe, to take holde of the weake or ſimple, and ſuffer the ſtrong and mighty to paſſe: of which errour Iudges ſhould be heedful, endeuouring themſelues to loue, obſerue, &amp; continually be carefull, how the Lawes may inuiolably be preſerued, to which all men are ſeruants, that they might be freemen.
            1 A wiſe Iudge alwaies preferres conſideration before concluſion.
            2 Iudges ought to diſpatch with ſpeed, and anſwer with patience.
            
               3 The Iudge himſelf incurreth the fault, when the guilty perſon is pardoned.
            4 Happy is the coūtrey, whoſe Iudges are iuſt mē, &amp; whoſe iuſt men are Iudges.
         
         
            Of Oeconomikes, or domeſticall Gouernment. Cap. 16.
            HAuing handeled of the two partes of regiment, which are requiſite in euery action in generall of all men, either in a Monaſtike life, that is ſolitarie, or in a politike; now it followeth next, that I ſhould handle of that parte, which is required in a Domeſticall gouernmēt, ordered for the right managing of the affaires therunto belonging, which conſiſteth

in the well gouerning &amp; diſpoſing thereof, whoſe end is to be prudently gouerned, for the credite of euery one that is a gouernour or maſter thereof: for a family conſiſteth either of thoſe things which are to be ordered or gouerned, or elſe of them which are the Lords, Maſters or gouernours thereof, who haue authoritie of all things thereunto appertaining, as of wife, children and ſeruants. Firſt, the man and wife being by a diuine ordinance of God, linked together in wedlocke, and of two bodies beyng made one, ſhould loue one another mutuallie without diſſention, iarres, &amp; broiles, comforting one an other in diſtreſſe, and reioicing with one another

in proſperity, ſo that ye
                deſire of the one, ſhould bee the content of the other, the huſband tendring the wife, as the weaker veſſell, and prouiding all things needefull, ſupplying the wants of his familie: ſo likewiſe the wife obeying her husband, with all modeſtie and decencie, and of that prouiſion made by the huſband, endeuouring her ſelfe to play the good huſwife, which procureth loue and vnitie on both parts: otherwiſe there would bee no domeſticall gouernment, neither is that man fit to gouern any where, or to beare authoritie, that cannot gouerne his owne houſe: the which was obiected to Philip King of Macedony, who would haue

pacified the ſtrife riſen in the Citie, and read a booke of exhortation vnto the people: to whō they ſaid, his admonitiō would litle preuaile to gouerne them, when hee could not gouerne his owne houſe at home, becauſe he, his wife and ſonne were at a continuall diſcord at home. Wherefore in this gouernment, and for the maintaining hereof, man and wife ſhould not diſagree, imitating the exāple of Hector &amp; Andromache his wife, who loued each other ſo entirely, that Hector grieued more at his departure from his wife, than for parents, children &amp; his whole coūtrey, as Homer teſtifieth. By the obſeruing hereof, all things may rightly be ordered, and houſhold

affaires well managed, being ſo gouerned. Firſt, the parēts of children are to haue great care in the orderly bringing vp of thē, who firſt begin to liue with the mother, which ſhould haue great care in the nurſing and tenderly vſing thereof, after the maner of the Grecians and Perſians, who neuer were accuſtomed to ſee their ſonnes, vntil they were ready to bee trained vp in warres: the mother hauing diſcharged her charge and done her taske, then the Father is to haue thē brought vp in learning, &amp; trained in nurture: for after what ſort they are at the beginning taught, they will taſte of the ſame in their old age, euē as a twig that yongly ſprowting is bent &amp; made

crooked, proueth a crooked old tree: which Ariſtotle in the end of his morall bookes teſtifieth, arguing vpon certaine opiniōs, that moſt of al may faſhion an honeſt &amp; ciuill life, to the which ſome partly therunto are enclined by nature, ſome reformed &amp; framed by good vſage &amp; cuſtom, as by doctrine &amp; other precepts: Hereupō he cōcluded at laſt, that vſe and cuſtome are of moſt force: for wherin childrē are trained vp in their yong &amp; tender age, therof they muſt needs ſauor in their ripe yeeres: As that of Horace, Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſeruabit odorē, teſta diu: That which is once bred in the bone, is hardly rooted out of the fleſh, wherfore educatiō is ſo neceſſary,

that it doth not onely guide thē, which nature hath made of a perfect diſpoſition: but alſo correcteth &amp; reformeth that which nature hath left vnpoliſhed. What difference is betweene man and beaſt, but reaſon? what inſtructeth reaſon, but education? without which we are worſe then the ſenceleſſe brute beaſtes. Doubtleſſe then wee are as much bound to our teachers for our education, as to our parents for the begetting of vs: for of the one wee haue our being, and of the other our well-being, who temper our crooked nature, which otherwiſe ſhould remain deformed. What force therfore this education worketh, may be well approued by Socrates anſwere to the

Phiſiognomer that iudged him lewde by his exterior countenance. To whom Socrates ſaid, I confeſſe that I am by nature ſuch a one, but by good inſtruction &amp; educatiō I am better faſhioned. By which anſwer, he likened youths vnto ſoft waxe, apt to receiue euery impreſsion, who ſhould bee handled as one would fill a glaſſe with a narrow mouth, by powring in the water with a pipe by litle and litle: meaning that the tēder childhood of yong ymps, is moſt gently to bee handled and mildly to be entreated, vntill they approch vnto the age of diſcretion, which is limited to be at 14. yeeres, at which time obedience &amp; good maners ſhould be engraffed in them. Hereof

may Phocion be a liuely witneſſe, who was wiſhed by a friend of his to prouide for his children, that they might encreaſe &amp; maintaine the honour of his anceſters: to whom he ſaid, As for my childrē if they embrace vertue, which I euer endeuoured to teach them, the litle poſſeſsions I haue ſhall make them deſerue more, but if they proue otherwiſe, let no man be of that opinion, that I their father will prouide any thing to maintaine their pompe &amp; riot. This is a worthy ſentence of all men to be embraced, and a right precept for the fathers to inſtruct their children, confirmed with that ſaying of Menedemus which he vſed to his ſonne Clinia,Terence, Ego te meum

                  
                     •
                  antiſper dici volo, dū id quod te dignum est facias. So long ſhalt thou bee my ſonne, as thou behaueſt thy ſelfe with honeſty: but if the father neglects to reforme his ſonne with this precept, or forgets to haue him inſtructed and brought vp by a right compaſſe of education, what pitie doth the want of education breed, wherof the child ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to curſe the parents, and the parents in their decrepit age to condemne themſelues, whē the child ſhall impute all to the ſecurity of his licentious nurturing, which bringeth ofttimes to the children an vnhappy end, and cauſeth the father with Auguſtus to repeat that ſaying of Homer, Coniuge non ducta natis vtinam

caruiſſem. I would that I had neuer maried wife, ſo that I had neuer beene troubled with children: which he vttered in reſpect of his vicious daughter Iulia, whom his ouermuch remiſneſſe at firſt had cauſed to proue ſo lewd. But omitting to ſpeake further of this reformation, leauing it to the conſideratiō of parents, who haue more diſcretiō in the gouerning hereof, then I cā preſcribe, I think it not a miſſe to ſpeake a word or two cōcerning ye
                gouernment of ſeruāts: for as magiſtrats &amp; officers are ordeined and inſtituted to miniſter iuſtice: ſo it is expediēt that euery houſeholder and maſter of ſeruāts, ſhould rightly gouerne the ſtate of his owne houſe, that ſeruants therein

excerſicing obediēce, might the rather be admitted to the general condition of the publike gouernment, imitating the good exāple of their Maſter laid before them, who is to vſe his ſeruants after a moderation of chaſtiſement: becauſe many ſeruaunts are of that nature and condition, that they wil do more by one mild or gentle worde, than with a thouſād ſeuere ſtripes: the Maſter thus teaching &amp; inſtructing them vnto honeſty, they may liue more vprightly, and thinke the yoke of ſeruice ſweet, and the burden light, which procureth credit to the Maſter, &amp; commendation to the ſeruants.
            1 Euery beginning cō
               meth by nature: but the progreſſe by houſhold educatiō.
            
               2 Gouernors of families not endued with wiſedome, in ſtead of good gouernmēt doe bring foorth briers and brambles.
            3 That man holdeth his goods in danger, his houſe in ſuſpitiō, his honor in balāce, and his life in peril, that cannot gouerne his own family.
            4 The force of Samſon, the prudence of Auguſtus, the cautels of Pyrrus, the patience of Iob, the ſagacity of Hanibal, &amp; the vigilancy of Hermogenes, be not ſufficient to gouerne that houſe, where man and wife are not at vnitie.
            5 That houſe may be rather termed a denne for wild beaſtes, and a receptacle of fooles, then a dwelling for mā &amp; wife, which is not rightly managed.
         
         
            
            Of Vertue. Cap. 17.
            NOw I come to entreat of the meanes whereby a Cōmon wealth is preſerued, ſafely munified, and rightly poliſhed.Ariſtot. Which as Ariſtotle &amp; diuers others doe affirme, is by vertue; for the end of a citie and Common wealth (that is, the happines and felicitie therof) is concluded to proceed of a good life, which muſt require vertue, which to vs is an impregnable towr, a floodde that needeth no flowing, a perpetuall during treaſure, an inuincible army, a ſtrong fortreſſe, a true harbinger, a burden ſupportable, a balme that preſently cureth, &amp; an eternall honor

that neuer dieth.Socrat. in Phoed. For (as Socrates ſaith) vertue is a thing that conducteth vs vnto immortality, and maketh vs equals with the heauens, and is called, An electiue habit of the mind, agreeing with reaſon and moderation of nature,Ariſtot. Politic. cap. 8. &amp; 9. conſiſting in a Mediocritie between two extreams, the one in defect, and the other in exceſſe: wherefore it excelleth all other things in goodnes. For if by liberality, ſubſtance, health, and liuing, our countrey, parents, and children do well, it hapneth in reſpect of vertue, which doth aduance all, and vnder whoſe wings all thinges are hatched, which reſēbleth the Cameleō, that is of al colors ſauing white: ſo vertue taſteth of all diuerſitie excepting

vice. This vertue is well compared by a wiſe Philoſopher, to the letter Y: which is ſmall at the foote, and broade at the head, meaning, that to attaine vertue, it was difficult and harde, but the poſſeſſions thereof were paſsing pleaſant, for thereby wee are ſaide to attaine euerlaſting felicity, that is to witte, by vertues actions, which are of two fold: The one variable or mutable, the which may ſoone be chaunged or hindred, eſpecially the obiectes &amp; meanes which are vſed in the attaining thereof being taken away: and this action hath no fellowſhip, ſocietie, or affinitie with felicitie. The other conſtant and inuariable, which is firme and perfect,

intending a good effect, alwaies perſeuering in action and contemplatiō, which by no meanes may be hindered or enforced to proue a changeling; and this action is meere felicitie, which ought to be in a Common welth wel eſtabliſhed: which beyng otherwiſe neglected, or lightly regarded, and ſlightly practiſed, or on the contrarie ſide immoderately vſed, might engender ſundry vices:Plato in Tymae
                     •
                  . for all immoderate actions on both ſides are hurtful to nature. For he that on this ſide flieth perill in an honeſt cauſe, is termed timorous and fearful: and he that on the other ſide aduentreth ouermuch, is termed raſhe: therfore vertue is ſaid to cō
               ſiſt betweene extreames, as

not participating thereof. The due obſeruation of this vertue, maketh a ſtraunger grow naturall in a ſtraunge countrey, and the vitious a meere ſtranger in his owne natiue ſoile, which if it be ſo, that the efficacy of this vertue is ſo great and worketh ſuch wonders, no maruaile that Aemilius Paulus, when it was reported him being a ſacrificing, that one of his ſonnes, the elder by birth, was ſlaine in the field: therewith being moued, threw off his lawrell and triumphing crowne, &amp; within a litle pawſing and deliberating with himſelfe, at laſt asked after what ſort his ſonne loſt his life, and yeelded vp the ghoſt: to whom it was told, that he was depriued thereof

valiantly fighting, &amp; at laſt breathing became breathleſſe. At which ſaying being comforted, he layed on his triumphing crowne againe, proteſting and calling the gods to witneſſe, that hee conceiued greater pleaſure at the death of his ſonne (becauſe of his vertue) then griefe and ſorrow for his death. Seeing vertue hath ſuch a diſpoſition and power of the reaſonable parte of the minde and ſoule of man, which bringeth vnto order and decency the vnreaſonable part being out of ſquare and frame, cauſing it anew to propound a conuenient end, to her owne affections &amp; paſsions, by which means the ſoule abideth in a comely and decent habite, accompliſhing

and diſcharging in all dutie and vprightnes of life, what ought to be done according to reaſon. Who thē reſpecting the properties thereof, would not with al might and maine, endeuour to be traced and trained herein, wearing this as his recognizance and chiefe badge, which euer gliſtereth and ſhineth, though it be neuer ſo much obſcured wherof Socrates hauing ſufficient triall, was wont to giue theſe precepts to his ſcholers, That they ſhould euery morning behold their Phiſiognomy in a looking glaſſe, wherin if they ſhould ſeeme faire, then they ſhould employ themſelues in Vertue, that they might inwardly reſēble the outward appearance: if deformed,

then ſhould they eſpecially endeuour thēſelues in vertuous actiōs, that therby they might by the inward vertue, ſhroud their outward deformity.
            1 It is the property of vertue, in ſuffering patiently to ouercome.
            2 The firſt degree to vertue, is, to admire vertue in an other man.
            3 Vertue getteth no ſuperiority by birth, nor prudence by yeeres: for there may be old fooles, and yong counſellers.
            4 Vertue is a ſeemely goddeſſe of toyle, imagination the miſtres of fooles, leuity the pride of nature, and diſſention the ruine &amp; ouerthrow of families.
         
         
            
            Of Prudence. Cap. 18.
            PRudence is a buſie ſearcher, and true inuentor of verity, which alloweth nothing to haue fellowſhip with the truth, except it be ſeaſoned with reaſon, and tempered with wiſdome. This vertue is allowed as a ſoueraigne precious good and is termed the very touchſtone of truth, which guideth the ſteps of men, in an vnfallible way, to the attaining and vnderſtanding of vertue, which procureth felicity. Cicero defineth this vertue to be the knowledge of things which ought to be wiſhed or obtained, &amp; of thoſe things which ought to be eſchewed, like a prouident mother foreſeing what

with decency ſhould be accompliſhed in euery enterpriſe, who prepareth a conueniēt &amp; fit abode, where all other vertues might ſecurely execute and diſcharge their ſeueral duties and offices: for ſhe accuſtometh to be conuerſant in the chooſing of good and euil, being the captaine and miſtreſſe of all other vertues whom ſhee feedeth. This vertue cannot eaſily be taynted, or inueigled with any lewd canker of vanity, nor fettered within the bonds of folly, being garded with al the troups of vertues, and tried in the fire of zeale, ſhining bright, and yeelding a fragrant ſmell and fauour to the noſtrels of the louers and poſſeſſors thereof, like a beame proceeding

from the cleere ſunne, which doth not onely lighten and kindle the affection, but alſo doth illuminate the vnderſtanding and knowledge of man: wherefore wiſe men haue laied a difference betweene ſcience &amp; prudence, ſaying, that ſcience is a dead knowledge of things, which of it ſelfe cannot change the will, in ſuch ſort that it may embrace and followe the knowne good, and auoid the euill, which is euident in wicked men, imbrued with vice, &amp; endued with knowledge. Wherefore Socrates was wont to admoniſh his ſcholers, that in all their life time, they ſhould haue theſe three things in memory, to witte, Prudence in minde, which is an inuiolable caſtell (as Antiſthenes

ſaith) Scilence in their tongue, and ſhamefaſtneſſe in their countenance, without which, nothing may bee done wiſely: becauſe prudence is the prince and guide to all other vertues, wherein the knowledge of our ſoueraigne good, and the ende of our life dependeth. Wherefore we may in no ſorte behaue our ſelues more prudently, then by cō
               ſidering how we may deale imprudently. Such a prudent man was Ageſilaus king of the Lacedemonians, who, when there was a battel to be pitched at Mantinia, by his ſubiectes the Lacedemonians, counſelled them thus wiſely, that they ſhould bēd all their force and ſtrength, and leuell at Epiminondas,

ſaying, It was a poinct of prudence to cut off the hartieſt ſouldier firſt of all; meaning that valiant men were the cauſers of victory, which when they had obſerued, obtained the conqueſt, and ſo preuented the daunger, and preſerued their liues &amp; ſafety. Whereby it was concluded, that in warre one prudent man was of greater force to ſubdue, then an whole army of vnwiſemen. For (as Homer ſaieth) Ille ſapit ſolus, volitant alii velut vmbrae. Likewiſe Ioſeph ſo excelled in prudence, in aduiſing Pharao to prouide a man of wiſedome and vnderſtanding, and ſet him ouer the land of Egypt, ſaying, Let Pharao make and appoint Officers ouer the

land, and take vp the firſt part of the land of Egypt in the ſeuen plenteous yeeres: alſo let them gather all the foode of theſe good yeeres that come, and lay vp corne vnder the hand of Pharao for foode in the citie, and let them keepe it; ſo the foode ſhalbe for the prouiſiō of the land,
                  Gen. 41. againſt the ſeuen yeres of famine which ſhall be in the land of Egypt, that the land periſh not for famine. &amp; the ſaying pleaſed Pharao and al his ſeruants, and therfore accoūted Ioſeph a moſt prudent and wiſe man. In like ſort the prudence of Licurgus, the reformer &amp; lawmaker of the Lacedemoniās was the cauſe of the maintenaunce of their flouriſhing eſtate aboue 500. yeeres,

ſo that it was the chiefeſt in all Greece, both for glory, &amp; excellency of gouernment: from whence they digreſſed not, vntill ſuch time as they wholy neglected thoſe lawes, and godly ordinances the which hee gaue them. Wherefore to conclude, the vigor &amp; ſtrength of this vertue in all actions, whether it be ingeneral to all in a Monaſtike life, or Oeconomicall appertaining to families, or politike which is the chiefeſt of all, vſed to the good of the Commō wealth, hath ſuch efficacy, that nothing without the ſame may rightly be effected: for the confirmation whereof and a finall concluſiō, we need no more then the liuely example of Argos, which had his head

inuironed with a hundred watching eies: ſignifying vnto vs, that he was euery way endued with great prudēce, and ſingular diſcretiō: wherfore if a Pagan and a Heathen man, by the reportes of the Poets, ſo excelled in the atchiuement of vertue, wiſedome, and prudence, how much the rather ought wee Chriſtians to bee furniſhed with the ſame, as an onely ornament of all actions? For although the wit of mā is moſt precious and apt to al goodnes, gliſtering as the yron &amp; braſſe, more &amp; more in wearing, whoſe ſharpnes and brightnes is like the ſparkle that ſooneſt kindleth deſire; though eloquence be a diuine influence, and inuentiō the daerling of nature: neuertheleſſe

inuention bringeth forth oft times a rude &amp; deformed matter, and eloquence ſingeth a ſong harſh, voide of tune &amp; concord of true melody, without prudence: by which men are alwaies cloathed and inueſted with a mild and ſetled diſpoſition, wherein it ſteadeth them no leſſe, then a ſhippe floting on the Sea, doeth the preſence of a Pilote that may prudently vndertake, &amp; wiſely execute whatſoeuer he knoweth to be good, after mature deliberation and cō
               ſideration of all the circumſtances of the fact. If therfore a gouernour be not endued with prudence &amp; learning, ciuill policy cannot be maintained, and his Empire or gouernment auaileth not.
            
               1 Prudence reformeth abuſes paſt, ordereth thinges preſent, &amp; foreſeeth things to come.
            2 Iuſtice without Prudēce, is diſſolued into cruelty, temperance into fury, and fortitude into tyranny.
            3 It is a point of great Prudence, to lament the life of a wicked man, more then the death of the iuſt.
            4 To the prudent it is more pleaſant to heare coū
               ſell mixt with mirth, then to the fooliſh to wāt ſport mixt with rudeneſſe.
            5 He that ſearcheth out prudence, findeth treaſure in this life and enioyeth perfect happines in the life to come.
         
         
            Of Fortitude. Cap. 19.
            
               FOrtitude is an inuincible vertue, or courage of the mind, vndertaking any peril in an honeſt &amp; good cauſe: alſo it is defined of ſome, to be a firie humor of the ſpirit, inflaming the minde with boldnes in all aſſayes, &amp; conducting the body thorow a million of perils, in attempting harde aduentures, becauſe nothing ought to bee hard for a valerous mā to attempt, which might daunt &amp; abate his courage. This vertue is of two ſorts, either conſiſting of the meere ſtrength of the body, which ought not to be termed fortitude, becauſe there be many men that haue ſtout bodies and great ſtrength, and yet cowards: And is therfore called naturall vigor, or els fortitude,

otherwiſe it is taken for the conſtancy of the minde, and ſo it is termed a morall vertue: wherefore by the aſſent of the Philoſophers, it deſerueth the vppermoſt roome and the greateſt dignitie amōgſt morall vertues, for two conſiderations. Firſt, in reſpect of the primate and chiefeſt man, whoſe minde attaineth this vertue. Secōdly, in reſpect of the whole citie which he enioieth, and in enioying defendeth her territories and turrets, aduenturing any enterpriſe for the ſecurity thereof. The properties of this vertue conſiſt in two things: Firſt in deſpiſing outward caſualties, not beeing moued to admire thereat: in admiring, not to deſire or wiſh any thing but

what is honeſt, holding the flagge of defiance againſt the allure and becke of fortune, ſuffering al things patiently, if any thing happen bitter or grieuous, which is a token of an inuincible minde, as Cicero ſaith,Cicero. 
               Si quid obtigerit, aequo animo parato
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   morear, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   enim turpis mors forti viro poteſt accidere, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   immatura conſulari, nec miſera ſapienti. The ſecond is, that if thou art of that minde and courage, ſee thou imploy thy ſelfe in thoſe thinges which are moſt difficult and full of perill, which may as well cō
               ſerue the life of man, as ſundry other things thereunto appertaining, that it may be ſaid as it was of a certaine Philoſopher, who being buſied touching his countreys

affaires, and pleading truce for his friends liues, hapned to fall into the lapſe of his enemies, and hauing many cowardly ſouldiers, who regarding neither their friends liues, nor their owne countreys ſecurity, moſt timerouſly flying, demaunded of this valiant mā what they ſhould do: to whom hee anſwered, that they ſhould report to thoſe that were aliue, that he valiantly fighting for their ſecurity died: and I will in like ſort report to the dead, that you eſcaped cowardly, as being the laſt in the field, and firſt in flight. We ſee therefore, that courage, and magnanimity, are daunted with no danger, and yet conquer by perſeuerance, &amp; triumph with honor. So then as

we ſhall finde our bounden dutie to honour our countrey, with all gratitude, &amp; to defend it with all power and might, ſhewing our ſelues valiant and couragious, following the example of Curtius the Romane, when there appeared a great gulfe in the market place, which could by no meanes be ſtopped; &amp; an anſwere being giuen by the Oracle, that it was onely to be ſtopped by that which was of moſt value to the city of Rome, he deeming that the citie had nothing ſo precious as ſtout &amp; valiant men, armed himſelf and leapt into the gulfe, which ſtopt immediatly: declaring thereby how light, men ought to eſteeme their liues, when as the ſame might yeeld profit

and cōmodity to their countrey, in regard of ſuch aduentures which euery man ought in the behalfe of his coūtrey to enterpriſe. Herehence it hapneth out ſometime, that diuers raſh &amp; wilfull mē, carried with an erronious opinion, do eſteeme it mere cowardnes, not to fight for euery light offēce, which is well approued to be otherwiſe, as Alexāder the ſonne of Mammena teſtifieth: who hearing that Artaxerxes the king of the Perſians, came with a great army of ſouldiors, about to inuade the Romane Empire: it behoueth valiant &amp; moderat men (ſaid Alexander) to wiſh alwaies the beſt, &amp; to beare patiently whatſoeuer happeneth contrary to their expectation:

for it is the point of fortitude, neither to encombate for euery ſmall trifle, triumph in proſperity, nor yet to be diſmaid in aduerſity: concluding with Cicero, that a valiant man ſhould bee alwaies girded with patience, &amp; garded with conſtancy: the one to perſeuer in wel doing, the other to tolerate ſundry enormities:Cicero. for, Fortes &amp; magnanimi ſunt, nō qui faciūt, ſed qui propulſant iniuriam. Calling to mind, that not onely they which do offend are valiant men, but they which do defend. Hereupō Laches demaunded of Socrates what Fortitude was: he anſwered, It was a vertue, by which a man not forſaking right and cuſtome, repelleth the force of his enemy: which he confuted,

ſaying,Plato. A mā after the maner of the Scythians, no leſſe in flying, then in perſiſting, ouercommeth his enemy, and ſo in like maner may be called a valiant man. Wherefore Homer calleth him a valiant man, which dareth according to opportunity, and as time, place, and occaſion ſhall require, boldly reſiſt or feare his enemy: gathering hereby, that a valiant man or light not for euery trifle or light occaſiō fight or encombat: For it is a rude thing (as Cicero ſaith) after the maner of beaſts to cōmit ſuch wilfull raſhnes, vnles it be in defence of countrey, or for vertue &amp; honeſty ſake, regarding both time, place, &amp; the perſon: for as he is called deſperate and raſh, that fighteth

for euery ſmall matter: ſo againe are they accounted valiant, that ſuffer and tolerate ſmall iniuries, vnleſſe they impaire their credit, or derogate 
                  ••
               om their honeſty: then if they reſiſt not an ini
                  ••
               e if it be offered, they are in as great a fault (as Cicero ſaieth) as if they ſhould forſake both countrey,Cicer. offic. parents, &amp; children: deeming it better to die free, then to liue captiue: of which opiniō was Mucius Scaeuola that valiant man, who willing to incurre any ſiniſter hap for the ſafety of his countrey, was taken of his enemies, at which time he thought to ſlay the king his enemy, but miſſing the king, ſlew the ſecretary, and was afterwards brought to a great fire to be burnt:

into the which he willingly thruſt his hand that had falled to ſlay the king, and ſuffered it to be burnt to aſhes. Likewiſe alſo Abraham was of ſuch excellent valure, that when he heard that his brother was taken by the kings of Sodome and Gomorrha,
                  Gen. 14. brought foorth of them that were borne and brought vp in his houſe three hundred &amp; eighteene, and purſued them vnto a place called Dan.
            In like maner Mithridates king of Pontus, after he had peſtered the Romanes with warres the ſpace of 40. yeres, during which time he behaued himſelfe no leſſe valiant in minde, then hardy in body, in reſiſting their ſtrong forces, and withal in attempting the fortitude of the Romanes,

thogh he was by fortune ſhaken in his old yeers, and eclipſed of his wealth, friēds, countrey, kingdome, &amp; al worldly chiualry, yet in deſpight of fortune went to Celta, meaning with them to tranſport into Italy, whereby the Romanes might haue intelligēce, that albeit he of his friends and countrey, by the frowne of fortune was depriued, yet neyther fortune, nor the Romanes could ſubdue his valiant hart. In this triumphed valiant men, becauſe they might not be vanquiſhed, and gloried, being free from ſubiection.
            1 Lightning or thunderclaps diſmay infants: and threates annoy fooles, but nothing diſmaieth the reſolution of a valiant man.
            
               2 Fortitude is the champion to equity, which neuer ought to ſtriue, except in righteous actions.
            3 Valure is a wiſe mans coate, &amp; a fooles cognizance.
            4 Thoſe that are ſtout in body &amp; cowards in mind, are diſſemblers with God &amp; mā: with God, becauſe they may be good and will not: with man, becauſe they ſeeme and are not.
         
         
            Of Patience. Cap. 20.
            PAtience is an excellent vertue, belōging aſwel to outward empire as to inward gouernance: it is ſaid to be the ſhielde of intolerable wrōgs, the vāquiſher of wickednes, that lighteneth the

burden of aduerſity, and is a ſure carde againſt all aſſaults and paſsions of the ſoule, ſeaſoning the ioys of proſperity, and retaining a continuall glad aſſemblāce in aduerſity and dolor, conſiſting ſtoutly and valiantly in ſuſtaining all labours and griefes for the loue of honeſty and vertue. For as S. Auguſtine ſayeth, it is more cōmendable to contēne an iniury, the therewith to bee grieued or to pine, by reaſon that in deſpiſing, we ſeeme a
                  •
                though we were not moued therewith, or felt nothing, regarding it nothing at all: but on the contraryſide, hee that is thereat ſturred or grieued, endureth torment &amp; feeleth the ſmart, becauſe the more impatient we be in ſuſtaining iniuries,

we aggrauate the griefe by ſo much the more, and grieuous, and vneaſie is the burden thereof. Patience then ſucking the dregges of ſorrow, and peſtered with the bitter pils of diſtreſſe is made more ſtrong and perfect: which ſeemeth to be wel approued by the Lacedemonians, who were noted to bee patterns of patience, ſuſtaining all paines, wars, vinde, and weather. So likewiſe, as Plinie reporteth Anarchus, of all men was moſt patient in all his torments: which is a ſpeciall token of an heroicall minde, to ſet light by ſmall wrongs, and litle regard meane aduentures: But as for this kinde of patience theſe examples may ſerue, becauſe wee haue ſufficient

daily before our eies: wherefore I will draw neerer vnto the inward gouernance, vpō whom patience ſhould attend, to the ſubuerſion and oppreſsing of naturall paſsions, to the ſuſtaining of the frowardnes of fortune, leſt that they which haue the fū
               ction of authority, &amp; be imploied in matters of great importance, their liues be not onely repleniſhed with toiles and heinous diſpleaſures, but withall bee ſubiect vnto diuers caſualties. To theſe the onely prouiſo and ready way to haue patience, is thought by two waies inuented. Firſt a direct and an vpright conſciēce, a true &amp; conſtant opiniō in the eſtimatiō of goodnes, which ſeldom procedeth by inſtinct of nature, vnleſſe

it be exquiſit, and excellent; but by the diligent ſtudy &amp; attaining of vertue. For hee which bendeth himſelfe to reuenge, doth imitate his doings who is moleſted with impatience, and he that imitateth an euil man, wil hardly proue good himſelfe: it were difficult and harde for a valiant man, to tolerate any iniury without reuenge, though oftentimes he is accoūted more valiāt in ſuffering, then in haſty reuēging: for he that enterpriſeth any thing haſtily, may repent him by leyſure: Neuertheleſſe I denie not, but it is almoſt a thing impoſsible for a couragious man, to tolerate an indignity, the which if he doth ſuffer, the onely and the ſureſt way to be reuēged,

is to contemne &amp; rebuke it, and to liue with ſuch godly courage, behauiour, and vpright life, that the doer and actor of the wrong, ſhal haue ſufficient occaſion thereat to be aſhamed, or at leaſtwiſe loſe the fruites of his enuy, hauing no ioy of thy hinderance and damage.Laerti. lib. 6.
                Antiſthenes was wont to glory that he had ſufficient vertue to the attaining of felicity, &amp; wanted nothing, ſaue onely the ſtrēgth of Socrates meaning, his mayle coate of patience, was a ſufficient armour of proofe. Tiberius Ceſar was in this one thing moſt highly cōmended, becauſe he refuſed honors that wer gratefully profered him,Guid. vitu vicen. ex Suet. ſhunned flattery, and ſuffered all reproches patiently,

ſaying, that in a free citie there ought to be free toūgs: that is to ſay, void of iniquity, and tempered with this mild ſoueraigne, named Patience. Whoſe aduice Iulius Ceſar ſeemed to imitate, whē Catullus the Poet wrote very many contumelious Epigrams againſt him, he notwithſtanding not onely forgaue him, but was recōciled, and often inuited him to his houſe. But omitting to ſpeak any more of this vertue, ſithens it ſeemeth ſufficient, to the inſtruction of a gouernour, if any thing remaine, I referre him to Plutarch and Plato, where he may find ſufficient to ſatisfie his minde, and accompliſh his expectation.
            1 The ſweeteſt ſalue to a

deformed ſhape, is patience, and no greater reuenge can be profered to Fortune, then to liue contentedly in the midſt of miſery.
            2 The final end of patiēce, is the expectatiō of promiſes.
            3 He may be well verified to be right patient, which in his outrage can bridle his owne affections.
            4 Patience winketh at apparant follies, and refraineth to proſecute manifeſt iniuries.
         
         
            Of Conſtancy. Cap. 21.
            
               Ariſtot.COnſtancy is a fortitude, as Ariſtotle ſaieth, perſeuering in well doing, defined of Cicero to be a prouident guide, teaching vs the force &amp; efficacy of wiſedome, and

directing vs to tread our ſteps ſtedfaſtly in the continuall trace of vertue, our nature beeing fraile, leſt that any puffe of vanity, or gale of winde ſhould toſſe our light affections: like the bramble, being wauering and wanting ſtay, wee are ready to ſhipwrack at euery ſudden waue or the leaſt blaſt, vnleſſe wee be cunningly guided by a Pilote of experience, whom, neither feare of aduerſitie, exterior dammage, nor priuate familiarity may cauſe to deſiſt from ſo commendable and comely a vertue as conſtancy, in which remaineth nothing worthy of blame as a note of blemiſh: for albeit we haue both by nature and nurture, obtained the guerdon due vnto our labour, &amp;

doe miſſe of conſtancy, when experience claſpeth hold on vs; if we then omit any parte of our gotten talent or effected vertue, moued by priuate affection, feare of aduerſity, or any other exterior dammage, deſiſting from conſtancy, prouing vnſtable and wauering in our actiōs, then is the eſtimation of our credit eclipſed, &amp; what may be worthy of commendations in vs. A man in nothing leſſe reſembleth a man, then to proue in his action vnconſtāt, which is a great blemiſh in any man, as appeared in Metellus, which after his maſter Diodorus being dead, laied vpon his ſepulchre a ſtone, made after the faſhion of a Crowe: which Cicero vnderſtanding, ſaid, that he

had well rewarded him,Plutarc. becauſe he taught him to flie, and not to ſpeake. Whereby he noted the inconſtancy of Metellus. Alſo heretofore men were rebuked for their inconſtancy, and likened to women and to children: to the one, becauſe in reſpect of their infancy and young yeeres, were not able to effect any thing: to the other, as being the weaker ſort, at whoſe handes no great exploit was to be expected; but now a daies it is contrary: for women are noted for the moſt part to bee of greater conſtancy then men, and if any proue vncōſtāt, the feminine ſort are accuſtomed to terme the ſame to reſemble ſome wauering or vncōſtant man: what ſhould bee the

cauſe of this, I know not, vnleſſe it might come to paſſe, that men for their leuity are too often ſaide to reſemble women, and ſo with Caeneus changing ſexe, who of a woman became man, ſo men become women. Conſtancy beyng a property only vnto man, ought to bee of no ſmall reputation: for as the wiſe man ſaieth, It is better to haue a conſtant enemy, then an vnconſtant friend, whereof we haue diuers liuely examples: therefore I will drawe a little neerer to the nature and property of conſtancy. The property of a conſtant man, (as the Philoſophers do affirme) is, not to inſult in proſperity, nor to pine in troubles or calamity, nor to mourne

in aduerſity, but as Plato ſaith, to holde a meane betweene ſubmiſsion &amp; ambition, guided by reaſon; wherby we may note the ambitious and enuious men to be excluded, of whom there is no meane obſerued, nor true conſtancy vſed, beeing by theſe vices, as by a cable rope, haled with vnſatiable deſire, making no period or comma, frō the higheſt Zodiack &amp; climate, to the loweſt Centre, by which meanes their mindes cannot be permanent. Moreouer we muſt not deceiue our ſelues, in deeming that the ſtiffe necked and ſtubborne man is conſtant, although hee continueth, as beyng void of al vertue, in his peruerſe opiniō, as Zeno the philoſopher

wel teſtifieth, ſaying, Facilius eſſe ventrem inflatum emergere, quam quemuis improbum ad aliquid agendum cogere: Who yeeldeth to no man is ſooner like a Serpent to be broken, then bent: but on the contrary ſide, the conſtant man perſiſteth not according to opinion as the ſtubborne man, which is grounded, Innanibus (as they ſay) &amp; quaſi labentibus fundamentis, vpon no certaine fundation, but vpon true knowledge or ſcience, wherein he is aſſured not to erre. Such a conſtant man was Anaxarcus the philoſopher, that when he was beaten in a hollow ſtone of Micocreon the tyrant, was of ſuch inuincible mind, that he bad the tirāt, Knock, knock this carcaſe of Anaxarcus,

but thou ſhalt neuer infringe his conſtancy. Likewiſe Alexander had ſuch great cō
               ſtancy, in truſting his friend againſt miſreport, that it ſaued his life, whereof all men deſpaired. Xantippe the wife of Socrates, did report that Socrates had alwaies the ſame countenance, both going from home, &amp; returning home, which was a ſigne of great conſtancy: wherefore nothing is more requiſite in a gouernour, then during all his life time, in all actions to proue ſtable and conſtant.
            1 To liue to God, to cō
               temne the world, to feare no miſhap, are the enſignes of conſtancy.
            2 The treaſure that men gather in proceſſe of time, may faile, friends may relent,

hope may deceiue, vaine glory may periſh, but cōſtancy may neuer be conquered.
            3 Conſtancy is the bleſſing of nature, the ſoueraine ſalue of pouerty, the miſtreſſe of ſorrow, the end of miſery.
            4 It is the ſigne of leuity and lightnes of wit, vnaduiſedly to promiſe, what a man may not, or will not performe.
         
         
            Of Temperance. Cap. 22.
            TEmperance is a vertue, moderating and bridling luſts, defined by Ariſtotle, to be a meane in moderating of the pleaſures of the body, &amp; may bee fitly likened to a lampe that ſhineth, lightneth

and expelleth away the dim and obſcure paſsions that may enuiron it: before this vertue can be rightly ſetled, wee muſt be void of diſtemperature, or annoyāce of cō
               trary vice: to the attaining whereof wee muſt vſe ſuch meanes, as the Chyrurgians doe: Before they apply any medicine or ſalue co cure any feſtered vlcer or wound, they firſt drawe out all bad and corrupt humors, dead and rotten fleſh, and then do proceede further to the cure thereof: ſo muſt we begin firſt, to cleanſe &amp; purge the mind of all diſtemperate humors, or noyſome paſsions which may ſeeke harbour &amp; reſt therin, ſo that this vertue may haue no ſeate or roome to abide: whereby as her nature

and property is, it may preſerue both priuate and humane ſociety, curing the ſoule, moſt miſerably throwē downe in vice, reſtoring it againe to her accuſtomed abode therin, foreſeing all diſordered and vnbridled appetites, to yeeld to the yoke of reaſon &amp; diſcretion, which is not onely effected by the abſtaining from meat and drinke: but alſo in vanquiſhing the luſt, and bridling laſciuious affections, and ſuppreſsing wanton wils, which are the vtter wracke and ruine of man, the which to ſubdue, is thought by wiſe men a greater conqueſt, thē to ouercome an enemy in the field, as by their deeds &amp; doctrine it euidently appeareth. Antiſthenes that famous

man, did ſo much loath vntēperate pleaſure, that he was wont to ſay, that he had rather waxe madde,Laertius. then to be moued thereby, proclaiming openly, I will be diſtracted, rather thē I wil delight in vntemperature, becauſe the Phiſition may cure this malady and madnes, but pleaſure or any vntemperature, when it cauſeth a man to be void of reaſon, &amp; without himſelfe, is a miſchiefe that hath no remedy, and is vncurable. Likewiſe Demoſthenes that famous Orator of Greece, affirmed, no greater euill to happen to any earthly wight, which had any taſt of vertue, then incontinence and vntemperature: accompting it the greateſt vertue that could bee, to abſtaine

and vtterly to abandon banquetting, ſwilling, and drinking, becauſe temperance doth very much auaile vs, which is eſpecially tried in contemning and abandoning pleaſures in all actions. This is it that deſerued that daily commendation of Solon which was wont to crie out, Ne quid nimis. Wherefore the Perſians liſtening thereunto, cauſed their children in all actions daily to bee exerciſed herein. Likewiſe the Turkes doe obſerue daily this vertue with all modeſty, in ſuch forte, that they excell the Greekes and the Romanes, who are wont in warre to ſuſtaine themſelues with bread half baked, and rice, with the pouder of fleſh which is dried

in the Sunne; their drinke is faire water, ſuch as the ancient Carthaginians vſed in warre by preſcription of law, as Plato ſaieth. In like maner, Ageſilaus king of the Lacedemoniās, paſsing through the city of Thracius, being mette and entertained by the Nobles and the people, with diuerſity of banquets and rare dainties, to gratifie his comming, who neuertheleſſe taſted not their dainties, feeding onely on bread and drinke, &amp; cōmanded his foote men to feed vpon ſuch cheere, ſaying, that a Prince ought not to pamper himſelfe with varieties or dainty cheere, but to abſtayne: meaning, that immoderate eating and drinking do inferre great dammages

to mans body, which were onely ordained to ſuſtaine the life of man, which otherwiſe vſed do cauſe great ſinne before God and man, and ingendreth diuers diſeaſes and ſickneſſes, as dropſies &amp; ſundry other infections. Who would not therefore, conſidering the diſcommodity hereof, refraine, and willingly loath all vnſatiable gluttons, as Vitellus &amp; Appitius, to which cormorāts, neither land, water, ayre, might bee ſufficient? which is the greateſt blemiſh that can be in any man. Iulius Ceſar ſo much abhorred intemperance, as Plutark rehearſeth, that he was accounted in regard thereof, the very lampe and Lanthorne of all Europe for his abſtinēce, &amp; thought

the very mirror of Italy, who by ouercōming of himſelfe, ouercame all Europe: ſo, no leſſe are all gouernours for their temperance and abſtinence to deſerue praiſe and fame, then dignity &amp; honour for their rule and Empire.
            1 Heroicall vertues are made perfect by the vnity of temperance, and fortitude, which ſeperated, becomes vitious.
            2 There is nothing in the world that deſerues greater felicity, then moderatiō, that ouercommeth the aſſaults of the fleſh, and the fruites of a good life are reuiued by it.
            3 Temperance enforceth vs to yeeld to reaſon, bringeth peace to the minde, and mollifieth the affections with concord and agreement.
            
               4 It is vnpoſsible for him to praiſe temperance, whoſe delight is in pleaſure, or affect gouernment, that delighteth in riot.
         
         
            Of Modeſty. Cap. 23.
            MOdeſty is a temperate vertue, or a precinct or limite, which honeſty commaundeth to be obſerued: ſo called, as Ariſtotle ſaith, becauſe it obſerueth a meane, not exceeding nor declining in any thing: And as Oſorius ſaieth, It is a vehement feare &amp; ſhamefaſtnes of ignominy or reproch: but Plato calleth it the onely preſeruer of all vertue, which firſt ſhineth or appeareth in youthes, like a lampe, and eſpecially

in thoſe which are of the greateſt towardnes, whō we perceiue to bluſh, not for any infamy or reproche which they haue cōmitted, but for feare of cōmitting any thing worthy the reprehēſiō, which is ye
                only felicity in all eſtates, and may be called, the onely repairer of decayed vertue. Sith then the country which we muſt deſire to inhabite, is ſo high and heauēly, and the way thither is Modeſtie, wherefore then deſiring to enioy this happy countrey, do wee refuſe the way? for doubtleſſe, as Oſorius ſaieth, that hee which altogether hath loſt this vertue, and paſſeth the goale, is either of preſumption or of meere ſlowneſſe reputed, and may bee well thought to haue no

ſparkle of honeſty. Was not impudence and ouerboldnes one of ye
                greateſt blemiſhes that Cicero was wont to reprehend in Cateline? But modeſty now a daies, as Plato ſaieth, is exilde out of the land. Wherefore did the Lacedemonians and Romanes baniſh out of their countrey, all vanity and other lewdnes paſsing the limits of modeſty: but becauſe they hated &amp; vtterly deteſted this vice, as deeming nothing honeſt which wanted this vertue? Ariſtotle admoniſhed, that no man ſhould praiſe or diſpraiſe himſelfe: which on the one ſide he thought to bee the property of a vaine glorious man, and on the other ſide to be the point of an vnwiſe and fooliſh perſon: deeming

on euery ſide, that it was the poinct of no modeſty, ſeeing it is accounted ſo vnſeemely a vice, &amp; deteſtable a crime amongſt all good men, who would be ouerſlow in the obſeruing hereof. The very Turkes do ſo embrace this vertue, and follow her traine ſo much, though being addicted vnto warres, yet to preuēt immodeſty which they greatly deteſt, they carie no weapons in court, townes, nor yet in campe: but when they are to fight, they ſhew great ſtaiednes in their maners, auoiding haughtines and lightnes in their deeds, geſtures, apparels, and ſpeaches: As for example, when Amirath, whō they account and canonize as a Saint, who was very valiant

and fortunate in armes, went to the temple to heare praiers without any pompe, accompanied only with two ſeruants, would not be ſaluted or flattered with acclamations. Seing ſuch modeſty hath beene vſed amongeſt thoſe Turkiſh infidels, what ſhould be vſed amōgſt Chriſtians, and in well ordered common weales, where nothing, but what with vertue and decency ſhould agree, ought to haue any place? for the chiefeſt point of honeſty conſiſteth in modeſty, which ſubiecteth and reclaimeth all diſtēperature, and enforceth it to obſerue a moderate decency. Conſider well the graue matrones of Rome, &amp; it ſhall ſuffice for an example, who vſed themſelues ſo

modeſtly &amp; decently, both in behauiour and diet, &amp; called thoſe ſhameleſſe and impudent, that did drinke wine or fauour thereof, the which Cicero teſtifieth in his fourth Booke De Rep. ſaying, that they obſerued it for a token of ſhamefaſtneſſe, &amp; not for any reprehenſion: wherefore Cato by report of Plinie in his 14. booke De hiſtoria naturali, ſaid, That the neighbours for no other reaſon did vſe to kiſſe and buſſe the female kinde, as wee do now for faſhion ſake vpon ſeldome meetings in kindnes, but for that purpoſe only, that they might know whether they ſauoured of wine, from which to abſtaine was a token of modeſty. Iuuenal.
            
            
               1 Modeſty hath often effected that, which no vertue nor reaſon can performe.
            2 Men are in nothing more like to their maker, thē in ſobernes and modeſty.
            3 The glorious ſeat and throne of the higheſt is in heauen: if thou preſumptuouſly endeuour to lift vp thy ſelfe vnto him, he will flie frō thee; but if otherwiſe thou obſerue true modeſty before him, he wil deſcēd vnto thee.
            4 After that Dio was made king of the Siracuſians, he would neuer change his accuſtomed diet and apparell, which hee was wont to weare being a ſtudent of the Vniuerſity.
         
         
            Of Chaſtity. Cap. 24.
            
               CHaſtity is a bridled temperance of lawleſſe luſt, or as Ariſtotle ſaith, is a ſweet bloſſome of the ſoule, and an integrity of life, which rayſeth vp ſlewces to auoid the floods of vaine pleaſure, or refraine the act of carnall appetite, whereunto a man is vehemently moued, or els enioyeth his wiſhed deſire therin: which to refraine, vndoubtedly is a thing almoſt impoſſible, and betokeneth a great wonder in a man of noble race &amp; of great dignity: but in whoſoeuer it happeneth to be, muſt of neceſſity be reputed of great wiſedome &amp; vertue, conſidering that it is enioyed onely of thoſe, that keep their bodies cleane and vnſpotted. This chaſtity abideth neither in

ſincere Virginity, not ſacred Matrimony, yet being good in wedlock, as a peace to deſire, commendable in virginity and widdowhood, as an onely dignity and grace to their bodies: gracious is that face that accompliſheth onely pure loue, and moſt celeſtiall is the reſolution grounded vpon chaſtity: for what can be more acceptable before GOD and man, then to keepe our bodies and mindes cleane from all blurres, ſpottes, or blemiſh? He that ſtoupeth to the lure of vaine delight, whereby hee might breed his owne content, and ſatisfie his lawleſſe luſt, ſtriketh often his foote againſt daungerous rocks, and by haunting after vaine follies, falleth into

moſt perillous daungers, not reſpecting the end, which is the onely ſalue to tame the fleſhe, that wanton is and bold, well to waigh what it ſhall bee, once dead and layde in molde: For, Non melius poterit caro luxurioſa dominari, quam bene (qualis erit poſt mortem) recordari. Which to forget, is a moſt deteſtable ſinne in all ages, and eſpecially in old yeeres to bee ſtayned with the ſpotte of incontinency. Wherefore it is reported by learned Authors, that amongſt the Caſpions there was a law decreed, that who ſoeuer ſhould marry after he had paſſed fifty yeres of age, ſhould in common aſſemblies be placed in the loweſt roome and the meaneſt ſeat,

as one that had committed a heinous fact againſt nature, whom they entituled no better then a filthy doting old leacher: meaning, that to liue chaſte, was the onely felicity of an earthly man, the which in this world could bee effected: wherefore Cyrus, as thinking it a thing moſt needfull to liue in chaſtity, abſtained from the ſight of Pantha: and when Araſpus told him, that ſhe was a woman of excellent beauty, and woorthy to be a kings paramour, Therfore, ſaid Cyrus, the rather muſt I abſtaine: for if by thy aduice I ſhall goe vnto her, when ſhe is ſolitary, peraduenture ſhe wil perſwade me to vſe &amp; frequent her company when ſhe hath no need; then muſt I daily be

with her, neglecting the ſerious buſines and affaires of the Cōmon wealth: concluding hereby, that he deteſted vnchaſtity: for if thereunto he ſhould be addicted, then he could not as a king, rightly diſcharge the duty of a gouernour: for hee had daily experience before his eies, of thoſe which haue beene imploied in warre, who after many wreaths and victories, being once intrapped &amp; inueigled with the loue of vnchaſtity (their minds being linkt thereunto) could no more vſe any of their former Stratagems, or buſie themſelues in ſuch affaires, being imploid otherwiſe: whereof we haue diuers examples, as namely that of Alexander, who in ſtead of his Pollaxe

and Curtilax, had a curtiſan, whoſe fauour hee wore, as a ſigne of the deuotiō he bare to this his miſtres: which is a thing greatly to be admired, that men of ſuch reſolutions and courage, ſhould bee ſo quickly entrapped and weaned from ſo great affaires, to ſuch toies &amp; vanities, cōſidering the diſcōmodities incident therunto: which Socrates well weyed, who beheld on a time Sophocles the writer of tragedies, following after a yong boy, being rauiſh
                  •
                with his beauty: To whom Socrates ſaid, O Sophocles, it is the part of a man, not onely to abſtaine his handes from incontinency, but alſo his eyes. Which is a ſaying worthy of all men to be embraced, &amp; eſpecially of ſuch

as haue authority or gouernment, or are admitted into any place of dignity, or eſtimation in the Common wealth.
            1 Pure chaſtity is beauty to our ſoules, a heauenly grace to our bodies, &amp; peace to our deſires.
            2 Chaſtity is the ſeale of grace, the marke of the iuſt, the crowne of virginity, the glory of life, and comfort in matrimony.
            3 Chaſtity is like the ſtars in heauen, and beauty is like the marigold which openeth her leaues no lōger then the ſunne ſhineth: ſo beauty endureth but for a moment.
            4 Chaſtity is a ſigne of true modeſty, which in extremity is crowned with eternity, whoſe preſence ſtriketh more ſhame, thē the ſight of

many wicked and immodeſt perſons can ſtirre to filthines with their immodeſt ſpeaches.
         
         
            Of Iuſtice. Cap. 25.
            IVſtice being an excellent and matchleſſe vertue, is thought expedient to be in all degrees, and eſpecially in the gouernours of the Common wealth, without the which nothing is cōmendable: for it is the right guide vnto godlines, goodnes, and the knowledge of God; the which vertue Cicero called the Queene and miſtreſſe of all vertues, and defined it to be the habite of the minde, which reſpecteth the publike cōmodity, &amp; yeldeth equally

euery man his owne. This vertue Ariſtotle calleth the affection of the minde, by which men are prone to adminiſter iuſtice, as being the fundatiō of all other vertues, which allots no priuiledge to defraude any mā of his right: wherefore, as being by the prouidēce of God inuented, for the accōpliſhment hereof, there were certaine Images of Iudges (by report) ſet vp at Athens, hauing neither hands nor eyes: deſcribing that rulers and Magiſtrates ſhould neither be infected with bribes, or any other way drawen from that which was lawfull &amp; right. To this purpoſe, as it ſeemeth, in the originall, an vpright and a iuſt man was choſen by full conſent and aſſent of the communalties,

of an equall indifferency, which ſhould excell in vertue, to decide all controuerſies, leſt the inferiour fort ſhould bee ouerpreſſed by mighty and wealthy mē: ſuch a man at that time held the ſuperiority, and ruled as a King. All this was effected for the executing of iuſtice, and the right adminiſtration thereof: which is ſo neceſſary, that no gouernors without it can rightly rule, nor no Common wealth be wel eſtabliſhed, which ought to bee of force amongſt the greateſt enemies, according to the nature and diſpoſition thereof,Iuſtin. de iustitia &amp; iure. which is a perpetual and a conſtant will, yeelding euery one his owne by euen portion, wherein prudence, magnanimity, and cōſtancy,

as aſsiſtants or gards, are requiſit: the one to diſtinguiſh lawful things from vnlawful: the other, not to be daunted or held backe by any ſiniſter chaunce: the third and laſt, to perſeuere in yeelding iuſtice. For as Oſorius ſaieth, In repub. bene cōſtituta, leges ſunt in armorum tutela: ſic in bene moratis animis omnia iuſtitiae praeſcripta, fortitudinis praeſidio, prudentiae auxilio, &amp; conſtantiae adminiculo muniūtur. In a well ordered Common wealth, lawes are in ſtead of weapons: ſo in well moderated mindes, all the rights and preſcripts of Iuſtice are patronized by the ſafegard of fortitude, by the ayd of prudence, and vnder the wing of conſtancy. Of this iuſtice, as Cicero ſayth, there be two

ſortes, the one Diſtributiue, the other Commutatiue, and is of Ariſtotle called in greek Diorthotick, in Engliſh Correctiue, or as the Philoſophers do ſay, there are foure ſorts of iuſtice, the firſt celeſtiall, the ſecond naturall, the third ciuill, the fourth iudiciall. Celeſtiall is the perfect conſideration and duty to God: naturall is that which al men haue among themſelues by nature: ciuil is that which is made eyther by lawes of nature, ye
                ſtatutes of the people, the conſultation of the Senators, or the authority of graue and wiſe men, and the deuice of Princes, as amōgſt the Athenians &amp; Romanes: iudiciall iuſtice depēded vpon lawes made for the commodity of the cōmon welth:

But becauſe of theſe, Plato (de legibus) and Cicero with diuers others haue ſpokē ſufficiently, I will leaue off to ſpeake any thing of the diuerſity of the ſortes and nature thereof, but yet not forgetting the quality, I thinke it meet to proceed farther, becauſe as Cicero teſtifieth, without this vertue there is nothing done or effected any maner of way, which in proceſſe of time weareth not away, excepting Iuſtice, which the more ancient it is, the more it flouriſheth: wherfore there ought to bee no time which ſhould bee void of iuſtice, as it well appeared by Byas the ſage and graue Philoſopher, being to iudge a man to die, bewailed and lamēted the miſery of ye
                mā,

and thought woorthily hee ſhould bewaile his ſiniſter fortune: whom a certaine mā beholding, demaunded why he ſhould weepe and powre teares, when it reſted at his pleaſure to condemne or free any man. To whom Bias anſwered, I muſt of neceſſity pardon the frailty of nature, but to erre frō iuſtice &amp; law, is a pernitious thing, and not to be tolerated: meaning that iuſtice was a meaſure ordained from God, amongſt his creatures, to his honor, &amp; the defence of the feeble and innocent, without which hee eſteemed nothing perfect, except it were guided by this vertue: wherefore he ought not to erre herein, nor derogate any thing from the property, being the fundation of

all creatures. Therfore, as it were for the auerring of this ſaying, Manlius Torquatus ſhewed himſelf ſo iuſt in the executing of iuſtice, that he condēned his owne ſonne, &amp; cauſed him to be put to deth, being againſt equity a conquerour: deeming that hee owed more duty to maintain the rights of iuſtice, then eyther loue towards his ſonne, or els to the triūph &amp; glory of the cōqueſt that his ſonne had gotten. Phocion alſo of Athens, being of Antipater requeſted, that hee would vſe iniuſtice priuily, anſwered him, Thou canſt not vſe me both a friend and a flatterer: for a friend doth ſo long continue a friend, as Iuſtice and equity doe permit him. Meaning, that

neither friends nor kinſmen ſhould be an occaſion to hinder the execution of iuſtice, which being neglected, both the loue of God &amp; mā is cō
               temned, and the deſtruction of the ſtate of the Common wealth almoſt in a moment decaied and ruinated, as we may ſee in diuers cities and countries, and alſo in the gouernours thereof: as King Philip was killed by Pauſanias a gentleman, for denying iuſtice at the marriage of his daughter Cleopatra, and diuers others by the tranſgreſsion hereof. Wherefore let euery good chriſtian, and eſpecially gouernors, eſchew iniuſtice, and be moued with zeale to diſcharge their dutie, and execute with equity and iuſtice whatſoeuer they

vndertake, for the reuerēce they do owe towards God, and the regard of their coū
               tries ſafety.
            1 Iuſtice is the mother of vertues, the right ſpouſe of fortitude, for which kings be created, and by whoſe vertue they rule.
            2 Iuſtice allots no pardon to the wicked, which might bring the hazard of the coū
               trey.
            3 Iuſtice requireth equity, equity iudgeth with lenity, lenity procureth lawes which doe iudge with extremity.
         
         
            Of Charity. Cap. 26.
            CHarity is a vertue proceeding from the higheſt throne, attributed to all

Chriſtians, as an vndiſſoluble yoke, for the knitting &amp; ioyning together with louing hearts of both body &amp; ſoule in Chriſt; without which there is no certainty, ſaue onely in the full aſſurance herof: for hope &amp; faith without charity are of no effect. This vertue in the middeſt of calamities is ſecure, that neither infinit toyles, nor cō
               tinuance of ſeruice abateth her courage, beeing in diſpleaſure meeke and humble, in concealing wrongs innocent, in trueth quiet; not like hatred, reioycing at others calamity, and pining with their proſperity: But on the contrary doth as humane nature is, Humanis caſibus ingemeſcere, at others misfortune ſhee bewayleth,

&amp; at their proſperity is ioyfull, obſeruing the right precepts of GOD, in obeying him, and louing her neighbours as her ſelfe. The Carthaginians &amp; Egyptians, of al vices hated immodeſty, and of al vertues embraced charity.Trogus Pomp. Thraſybilus was ſo charitably deuoted towardes his countrey, that ſafely he defended it from the thirty tyrants. Ionathan ſo entirely loued Dauid, that hee tolde him all whatſoeuer his father entended againſt him. Likewiſe the Turkes, which are inferiour to all others, as Hiſtories doe report, neuer vſe to bee aboue tenne in a companie, in which ſocietie they are ſo marueylous louing, and charitable one towardes an other, that

they neede of none other meanes to gouerne thēſelues within the compaſſe of comlines and decency, ſaue onely by ſignes of hand, &amp; beckning of coūtenance, without vttering any word, which is to be wondered at, that there ſhould be ſuch loue and charity amongſt thoſe, who doe wander in ſo great darkenes and obſcurity of life, which is of no leſſe maruaile thē truth as credible authors doe report. Seing they are ſo giuen to embrace this vertue, what ſhould wee, that haue the cleerenes of the goſpel, and the truth alwaies before our eyes? yea wee ſhould be ſo fettered and linkt thereunto, as the onely patterns of charity, whereby we might reſt blameleſſe before the preſence

of our glorious God, aboūding with ioies, hearing that cōfortable voice of our bleſſed Lord, which ſhal ſoūd vnto vs: Come, O ye bleſſed of my father, inherite the kingdome prouided for you. For the attaining of this vertue we haue a good example of a certaine elderly mā amōgſt the Egyptians, who being demaunded, why he refuſed to haue any thing in his houſe, which was eyther money, or els appertained to the vſe of humane life? he anſwered, that the vſe of thoſe thinges auailed not to the atchiuing of charity, but charity was ſufficient to procure any other thing: cōcluding hereby, that it was impoſsible for man, eyther to leuel his own life after a right

line, or els to gouerne others within the compaſſe or limits to him preſcribed according to duty, without charity; in accompliſhing whereof hee might be called abſolutely perfect, and a right vpholder of this vertue.
            1 Charity ranſometh vs from the fetters of iniquity, and deliuereth vs from the ſting of death.
            2 Charity is compared to an euerturning ſpie, alwaies prouiding and labouring for him in whom ſhe reſteth.
            3 It is the point of a charitable minded man, to inuite the poore, courteouſly to entertaine them, and ſpeedily to let them depart.
            4 Charity is commonly in the mouth of many, but regarded of a few.
         
         
            
            Of Obedience. Cap. 27.
            OBedience is the finall period or end, whereunto true felicity tēdeth, &amp; wherupon it depēdeth, becauſe it is a zeale and a teſtimony of an vpright and an hūble conſcience, ſhewing in all enterpriſes that we ſhould obſerue decency and honeſty, which conſtraineth the ſoule, Intus &amp; incute, willingly and wittily, without inſtigation to yeeld euery one his proper duty; as honor to whom honor belongeth, reuerence to to whom reuerence, tribute and ſuccour, to whom they belong; which is an infallible obſeruation to guide our ſteps vnto eternal bliſſe: for firſt, the neglecting of

this dutie ſheweth our rebellion, and in accompliſhing it, we leaue an example of the feare and diligent care we haue in the obſeruing &amp; effecting of that, that we are commaunded. The diuerſity of this vertue is manyfold, as belonging vnto diuers perſons. Firſt, our obedience towards God, vnto whom belongeth all honor, dutie, and obedience, whereupon all our ſtay, hope, and felicity is built: ſecondly, our obedience towards our king and ſuperiors, to whom we ought in all humblenes and ſubmiſſion, to ſhew our ſelues obedient and loyall, as wee are commaunded by the holy ſcriptures in theſe words, Let euery one ſubmit himſelf vnto the higher power. Thirdly,

wee are bound to obey our parents; for as Tully ſayleth in his booke of the anſwere of ſouthſaiers, that nature in the beginning had made a concord betweene vs and our parents: ſo then it were deteſtable to infringe the rights of nature, and not to obey them. Fourthly, and laſtly, is the obedience of ſeruants towards their maſters, whom in all honeſt &amp; meeke ſort they ſhould obey &amp; reuerēce. In neglecting of this generall duty, wee ſhew our ſelues baſtards &amp; reprobates deſeruing the curſe of our ſauiour, &amp; the ſeuerity of law, not imitating the example of Chriſt, who obeyed his father, euen to death. Is it not thē the duty of ſubiects, with all humblenes to obey their

ſuperiors, holding them in ſuch high eſtimatiō, and ſeruing them both with life and goods, which is the proper duty of euery naturall ſubiect? for therein conſiſteth the ſtay and ſtate of al countreys, becauſe nothing thriueth where there is ſtrife &amp; contention; and on the contrary ſide all things doe floriſh, where there do remaine loue, vnity, and obedience. When Salomon deliberated with himſelfe in this behalfe, viz. after what ſort a citie might be ſafely preſerued: he anſwered, If the citizēs obey the magiſtrates, and the magiſtrates obſerue the lawes: meaning, that obedience in the ſubiects was a ſigne of great loue and loyalty, and a cauſe why the cōmon wealth

ſhould lōg flouriſh, as hauing notice and ſufficient knowledge of the ruine &amp; wracke of many Cities, becauſe of diſobedience. Wherefore we ſhould vtterly deteſt this kind of vice, which hath bred ſo many calamities, &amp; engendred ſundry depopulatiōs &amp; deſtructions of countreys, &amp; ought to endeuour and ſhew our ſelues obediēt, imitating the exāple of Abraham, who obeied the will of God, in offering his ſonne Iſaac as a ſacrifice: ſo ought we with all might and maine, to behaue our ſelues obediētly toward our gouernours, ſo that neither the baniſhment of Ariſtides, neither the impriſonment of Anaxagoras, nor yet the deſtruction of Phocion ſhould terrifie or cauſe vs to

deſiſt from the executing of our obediēce. But leuing this generall duty, I meane to expreſſe ſomwhat in particular of our ſeueral duties &amp; obedience towards our parents, whereof we haue diuers and ſūdry exāples. Firſt, of Chriſt himſelfe, which obeyed his mother Marie and her huſband Ioſeph: then of Dauid, who after hee was anointed King, obeyed his parents, and followed their direction in all domeſticall affaires. Wherby we may gather, the great duty we owe vnto our parents, to be no leſſe then a firme bond of nature, fixt in the minds &amp; bowels of euery one:Cicer. pro Plan. the which obedience Cicero ſo highly commended, that he ſaid, The obedience of children towardes

their parents, is the fundation of all vertue. Of which mind Torquatus ſonne was, who thought nothing ſo wicked, as to diſobey the will of his parents: wherfore being vpon the diſpleaſure of his father baniſht, he killed himſelfe. So likewiſe the duety which ſeruants doe owe to their maſters, is not much inferior to this, whom they are to ſerue with al lowlines and ſeemely demeanure, ſuſtayning with patience all corrections, though I deeme them not ſo much ſubiects, as the ſeruants of Frēchmen were, ouer whome their maſters had power of life and death; and as Gellius ſaieth in his 15. booke and 19. chapter, The ten wiſemen thought, that authority not onely of

maſters ouer their ſeruants, but alſo of parents ouer their children, was very neceſſary throughout al dominions, by which means they report the Cōmon wealth long to haue ſtood. Doutles, if parents ouer their children, &amp; maſters ouer their ſeruants, had ſuch authority, that in reſpect therof the cōmon welth flouriſhed: then the ſupreme gouernour ſhould in equitie haue farre greater preeminence, being of both parents, children, maſters &amp; ſeruants a commaunder, vnto whom all ſhould bee moſt obedient, wherby the ſtate of the Common wealth might perfectly ſtande, and that it might bee ſayed in reſpect of this obedience, as it was of a certaine man comming

to Sparta, who beheld what honour, obedience, and reuerence, the yonger ſort did to the elders, and the elders to their ſuperiors, &amp; ſaid, It is expedient in this citie to become an old man, and of authority: meaning, that the Magiſtrates being ſo much regarded by the cōmunalties the Common wealth ſhould of neceſsity long continue. Herin I cōclude of obediēce, determining to paſſe further.
            1 Obediēce formeth peace, eſtabliſheth cōmon wealths, &amp; preuents diſcords: wicked men obey for feare, but good men for loue.
            2 It is a cōmendable vertue in a ſeruant, to know how to obey well.
            3 That countrey is well kept where the prince gouerneth

rightly, and the people are ſubmiſsiue &amp; obedient.
         
         
            Of Hope. Cap. 28.
            HOpe is a ſure ground of future things wiſhed for, whether they be diuine or trāſitory, extolling the mind of man with great extacy, being grounded vpon good fundation, &amp; hauing laid an vnfallible anchor, depending thereon with a ſure cō
               fidence to effect and accompliſh his deſire; which means is a ſure remedy to helpe our fraile nature being ful of miſtruſt and diffidency, whereby the ſpirite of man putteth great truſt in weighty affairs, repoſing ſuch certainty and confidence in himſelf, which

otherwiſe would be vaine &amp; vnperfit: for he that is voyd of all hope, may be accoūted to be partaker of the incidēt miſhap to an vnhappy man. Hauing then ſo ſure a ſoueraine kindling our deſire, &amp; emboldening our courage, wee cannot poſsibly miſſe a good effect proceding from ſo heauenly a ſtay, &amp; ſo ſure a ſafegard, who reſēbleth the pure Indian ſpice, which the more it is pund, the more fragrant ſmell it yeeldes: ſo the more our hope is, the greater is our comfort to enioy that happines which we expect; for a good and vertuous man ſhould alwaies hope wel and feare no miſhap, eſpecially beeing grounded vpon the grace of God. Such a man was one of Rhodes, who was

caſt of a tyrant into a hollow caue, wherein hee was fedde after the manner of a beaſt, being enforced to ſuſtain reuiles and torments, his face being mangled &amp; martyred with woundes: who being admoniſhed of one of his friēds, that he ſhuld ſeeke an end of his torments, anſwered, All things are to be hoped of man, as long as he enioyeth life. Euen ſo Thales Mileſius, being demaunded what was cōmon to all men, anſwered, Hope: meaning, it was a ſoueraine good, and a confederate to faith, which whoſoeuer hath, may wel aſſure himſelf, that he in continuāce of time, may attaine any thing how difficult ſo euer. Wherupō Socrates the Philoſopher ſaid, that it was

impoſsible, that either womā without man ſhould bring foorth good fruite, or good hope without labor: wherby hee iudged, that good hope ſhould not be groūded vpon any vncōſtancy, which is the ſubiect of a vaine and licentious life, wherupō euil hope which taketh no toile is planted: therefore Socrates ſaid, hope without labor could effect no good thing; which like a careful nurſe ſhould be alwaies imploid or buſied about ſome affaires or other, which hinder the increaſe of vice: for ſecurity and idlenes are accounted the mother of al enormities &amp; lewdnes: by which means true hope is excluded out of doores, which in whoſoeuer it remaineth, neuer fayleth them in the

greateſt extremity. Such a man was Daniel, who hoped ſo much in the mercy of God, that being throwen into the Lions denne, yet eſcaped harmeles onely by his meere hope. Likewiſe alſo Iob, a man that was full of good hope, who in his greateſt diſtres miſtruſted not, ſaying, Loe, though the Lord ſlay me, yet will I put my truſt in him. Wherby it may appere, that he that hopeth well, ſhal neuer be fruſtrated of his expectation.
            1 Hope groūded on God, neuer faileth, but built on the world, it neuer thriueth.
            2 Hope, of al the paſsions yeeldeth the ſweeteſt ſauour, and the moſt pleaſant delight: wherof it is ſaid, that hope onely comforteth the

miſerable.
            3 A daſtardly louer ſhall neuer without hope gaine faire loue, without frowning fortune.
            4 Mellifluous words procure hope, large proteſtations cheriſh it, and contempt ſpils it.
            5 Hope is the fooles ſoueraine, the Marchants comfort, the Souldiors confederat, and the ambitious mans poyſon.
         
         
            Of Faith. Cap. 29.
            FAith (as Cicero ſaieth) is a conſtant &amp; firme bond of all ſayinges, and contracts, appointed for the accompliſhing of promiſes, and what ſhould be aſſuredly decreed vpon, or as Diuines

terme it, is a ſure ſtay and rocke of all Chriſtians, whereuppon conſiſteth all their felicity, and if it bee firmly ſetled, it neuer deceiueth: the which to infringe, there can be nothing worſe vnto any man, eſpecially to him that ruleth, becauſe this blemiſh by how much the more excellent the party is wherein it reſteth, by ſo much the more openly it is to be ſeene, and more hardly to bee rooted out. Ennius reprehended the Carthaginians, becauſe they violated their faith and fidelity, which was the firſt cauſe of the ſubuerſion of their city, who contended for the empire of the whole world, with the Romanes, which of al nations, were a people of moſt

proweſſe and valour. But what maruaile is it that theſe were ſo ſlender in obſeruing of faith, which is the fundation of all equity, when in all places it is litle regarded, and vtterly excluded out of doones, begging her bread with teares, as a vagabond of no reputation, that I am almoſt aſhamed to ſpeake of the diffidency of men, and the litle regard which they haue of their faith, which ought to be of effect amōgſt enemies, vnleſſe it bee vnlawfull, by conſtraint and compulſion aſſured? And yet wee haue experience of many, that would rather die, then vpon compulſion or conſtraint pawne their faith and credite: as for example, Pōtius Ceſar the Centurion,

being taken of Scipio, the father in law of Pompey, to whom Scipio promiſed pardon, vpon condition that he would be the Souldiour of Cnaius Pompeius: to whom Pontius anſwered, Scipio, I yeeld thee thankes; but I need no ſuch condition of life, for I had rather die, then to violate my faith. Whoſe fidelity may be vnto vs a moſt liuely patterne to imitate: in ſo doing wee purchaſe our ſelues eternity, and the ſafety of our realme hereby is maintained: for what elſe doth cauſe the cōmon welth to bee ouerwhelmed, but where the people are vnloial and diſobedient towardes their gouernours? But on the contrary ſide, happy is that eſtate, wherein the ſubiects

are moſt louing and faithfull vnto their gouernour, and where the gouernour ſtudieth his communalties ſecurity, and is full of clemency, which is the nexte way to binde and vnite affection in duty: ſeing thē nothing keepeth together a Common wealth as faith, which is both the originall, and as it were the chiefe conſtitutor &amp; ſeruator thereof: therefore it is a reproch, eyther to promiſe lightly without performing, or in firmely promiſing to infringe and neglect it: as Alphonſus king of Aragon was often wont to ſay, that the very bare worde of a king to the performing of his fidelity, was ſo much reckoned, as the othe of priuate men, and ſaied, It was an vnſeemely

thing for any man to proue vnfaithful, much more for a king. But omitting many other notable exāples, which both in writing and of late remembraunce are extant, I will onely ſpeake of the diuerſity and difference of this word Faith, how it is taken. Sometimes it is called faith, ſometimes credance, ſomtimes truſt, after the imitation of the Latines, faith, by the Frenchmen, loialty. Firſt, in the aſſured beliefe of the precepts of God, it is termed faith: in contracts betweene man and man, it may be called credance: between perſons of equal degrees, it is called truſt: in reſpect of the ſeruāt or ſubiect to his ſoueraigne or maſter, it is properly named fidelity. And ſo

much touching the differēce hereof.
            1 Faith being honeſt, may reape diſdaine, but no diſgrace.
            2 Faith is the daughter of deſtiny, the Sympathy of affections is foreappointed by the ſtarres.
            3 Faith moueth mountaines, vanquiſheth tyrants, conquereth the malice of the enuious, reconcileth mortall foes, to perfect loue &amp; amity.
            4 Faith is not to be ſuppreſt by wiſedome, becauſe it is not to be comprehended by reaſon.
         
         
            Of Trueth. Cap. 30.
            TRueth is the iuſt performance of ſpeach, obſeruing

integrity, &amp; ye
                true meſſenger of God, which euery one ought to embrace for the loue of his maſter, as being an infallible way to reaſon, which reuealeth the creatiō of the world, the power of our creator, the eternall crowne of bliſſe, which wee hope for, &amp; the puniſhment due for our tranſgreſsions. It is alſo termed a vertue, whereby we attaine to ſpeak no otherwiſe with our toūgs, then our harts do conceaue: which conſiſteth not in gloſing ſpeaches, or ſugred melody, proceeding onely from the brimme of the mouth. This excellent champion lieth not hidden nor obſcured with any cloudy miſt, but ſhineth in the greateſt darknes, yet hiddē vnder a Chaos

like the Mineral, which lieth not vpō the face of the earth, that euery one ſhould careleſly without any paines find it: but in the bowels of the earth ſecretly hidden, to that purpoſe, that thoſe which were willing to attaine it, ſhould toyle &amp; labour in the getting therof. So is this vertue encloſed and compaſſed within the vale of bleſſednes, to the which, what man ſoeuer wil knock at that heauenly palace, ſhall haue enterance. This is the right ſquare of ſpeach, which effecteth ſtratagems in the harts of men: wherfore let all chriſtians endeuour to the artaining thereof, that they may boldly approch before the tribunal ſeate, &amp; be accepted before God: otherwiſe they

ſhall be diſinherited as baſtards and vnlawfull heires. For none is accepted before God, but hee that hath no guile, and ſpeaketh the truth from his hart.Elia. lib. 12.
                When as Pythagoras the Philoſopher diſputed of diuers matters, hee ſaid, that two thinges were diuinely giuen to man: the one was to embrace trueth, the other to do good turnes, which both were to bee compared to the workes of the immortal gods.Maximius. So likewiſe Demoſthenes beeing demaunded what men had, that moſt reſembled God, he anſwered, To be charitable and embrace the trueth. Concluding, that in all eſtates, and amongſt all degrees, nothing could bee rightly eſtabliſhed, or by due

courſe obſerued, without this vertue, which needeth no help of any eloquēt Orator, but is ſufficient of it ſelfe to effect all things.
                  Mat. 14 Mark. 6 Iohn Baptiſt was ſuch a louer of this truth, that he doubted not to tell King Herod openly of his inceſt, the which of all mē ought in like maner to be of ſo great account and reputation, that neither loſſe of goods, hazard or dammage of life, ſhould cauſe them to forſake it; by which meanes they might bee acceptable ſeruants vnto their maſters.
            1 Trueth hath no need to impaire: for it is a ſure pledge, a ſhield that is neuer pearced, a flower that neuer dieth, a ſtately ſtay that feares no frowne, a port that yeelds no daunger.
            
               2 Truth is the onely anchor whereon all things depend, the Carde whereby wee ſaile, the ſweete balme whereby wee are cured, the ſtrong towre whereon wee reſt, the gliſtering light, that lighteth vs, &amp; the only ſhield of our defence.
            3 Trueth may incurre blame, but neuer ſhamed, whoſe priuiledge is ſuch, that whē time may ſeeme to crop her wings, then as immortall ſhe taketh her defence.
            4 Trueth is a ſure pledge to maintaine iuſtice, to gouerne a common weale, to kill hate, to nouriſh vnity, &amp; to diſcloſe ſecrets.
         
         
            Of Friendship. Cap. 31.
            
               FRiendſhip,Ariſto. Ethic. ingenerall is a mutuall and ſecrete good will of thoſe, which do affectionat each other, and endeuor to profit and better the good: more particularly, it is termed a vertue, by which good and learned men, for conformity and likenes of maners, are conglutinated &amp; vnited in charity and loue. This connection of ſundry willes and mutual conſent of minds, is hardly to be found, vnleſſe it be betweene good men, and withall cannot be found without vertue: becauſe as Ariſtotle ſaieth, Friendſhip is a vertue ioyned to vertue, &amp; requireth equality. Wherfore in all that be good this friendſhip cannot be, except they be of like cō
               dition, equal degree, and not

exceeding one an other in age; for where there is repugnance of nature, there may be no amity, becauſe it is an entire conſent of willes and degrees. In reſpect hereof, Ariſtotle ſaith, that friendſhip hath three obiects, that is, Honeſty, profit, and pleaſure. According to the firſt, the friendſhip of good men conſiſteth (as I haue afore mentioned) that there could be no friendſhip but amongſt good men: according to the ſecōd, proceedeth a familiarity of daily conuerſion, and that is betweene marchants, and diuers other mercenary trades men, giuen to the world, and regarding profit, amongſt whom there is no friendſhip: for as Cicero ſaieth, Amicus eſt alter ego:

that is, I eſteeme my friend as my ſelfe: but they regard more their welth, thē friendſhippe, which they thinke may procure them ſufficient friends euery where. Is not this an odious thing in a Cō
               mon wealth, that friendſhip ſhould be contemned, which procureth concord and vnity, vnity peace, peace tranquillity, tranquillity ſecurity of life, which are the onely cauſes of the maintayning and long continuance of the good eſtate of the Common wealth? The third, &amp; laſt obiect, is pleaſure, according to which, the friendſhip of yōg youthes &amp; children dependeth, for the delight they enioy in pleaſure and paſtime together; which is not to be termed friendſhip, becauſe in

ſuch there wantes conſtancy and diſcretion, as it euidently appeareth: for this friendſhip endureth but for a time. The like vnto this (though a worſe) is that of theeues, robbers, conſpirators, and diuers other malefactors, who, as birds of the ſame feathers, do flocke and reſort together, not for any loue they owe one the other, but for the good will they beare vnto thoſe lewde practiſes which they do vſe. Wherefore they are excluded of all men, and in reſpect hereof, they conſort together for friendſhip ſake, as they terme it, which is no friēdſhip, but carrieth a ſhewe of friendſhip: becauſe friendſhip onely is ſaid to be amongſt good and vertuous mē, which is the neceſſarieſt

thing that ſhould be eſteemed amongſt men. For as Socrates was woont to ſay,Eraſm. lib. 3.
                there could not bee a more excellent poſſeſsion enioyed of any mā thē a good friend; wherein Epaminōdas much delighted, and was wont to glory, that he neuer returned from any towne, before hee had gotten the friendſhip of ſome man or other. Wherby hee coniectured, that there could be nothing of greater efficacy &amp; force, then friendſhip: which was well approued by Lucullus &amp; Volumnius, who were ſuch intimate friendes, that when Marcus Anthonius had the Empire of Rome after the death of Ceſar, and alſo had put Lucullus to death, for his conſpiracy againſt Ceſar, Volū
               nius

hearing of his friend Lucullus death, came with ſobs and teares before Anthony, requeſting on his knees one graunt, and deſiring Anthony to ſende his ſouldiors to kil him vpon the graue of his friend Lucullus: which being denied of the Emperour, then immediatly he wrote vpon a piece of paper, the which hee caried in his hand, vntil he had acceſſe vnto the graue wherein Lucullus was layed; and there holding faſt the paper in one hand, and his dagger in the other hande, imbrued his hand with his owne bloud, vpon the very graue of his friend, hauing alſo claſped his hand faſt vpon the piece of paper, wherein was written this worthy ſentence,

Thou that knoweſt the loyal friendſhip betwixt Volumnius and Lucullus, linke our bodies together, as our minds were one, being aliue. Such friendſhippe was betweene Pomponius and Ceſar, that the one wanted nothing that the other had: whoſe examples wee ſhould ingenerall imitate: for though wealth decay, fortune frowne, and we be of honours and dignities depriued: yet ſhall not fortune with all her troupes change or alter friends, who in proſperity or aduerſity might reioyce one with an other, or elſe in bewayling, eaſe one an others calamity, which is the chiefeſt ſacrifice that may bee offered vnto God, and the greateſt terror vnto our enemies.
            
               1 The ſmile of a foe that proceedeth of enuy, is worſe then the teares of a friend flowing with pitie.
            2 Wee make experience of a friend, as the goldſmith doth of his gold, in trying him before wee haue need.
            3 To ſet on forwards in folly, argueth no diſcretion, &amp; to diſſwade a mā in courſe of honour, were not the part of a friend.
            4 The counſell and perſwaſiō of a friend are alwaies fortunate in proſperity, and his company in miſery is alwaies delightfull.
         
         
            Of Liberality. Cap. 32.
            
               LIberality is a vertue, gratefully beſtowing gifts vpon others, and is ſaied to be the encreaſe and yerely fruits or annuities, of thoſe bleſsings which God hath beſtowed vpon vs, for the relieuing of the diſtreſſed. For the chiefeſt honor thereof cōſiſteth in helping of the poore. And as Ambroſe ſaith, this vertue is in league with iuſtice: wherefore it ſhould be ruled by moderation and reaſon, ayming at her reuenues, and thereof giuing freely: as Bion Boryſtenite was wont to ſay, it was good to beſtow a portion of that talent wee haue, vpon others, yea farre better then to receiue any gift, though beſtowed. So Demoſthenes beyng asked, what was moſt poſſeſſed of

men, that reſembled GOD, anſwered, To beſtow bountifully, and to effect good things. Neuertheleſſe in beſtowing we muſt be circumſpect, and conſider where, when, and to whom; becauſe liberality conſiſteth not in the quantity of the thing beſtowed, but in the true meaning and natural inclination and diſpoſition of the giuer. For he is neuer ſaid to giue in vaine, as Auguſtine ſaith, that giueth with a zeale and deuotiō: &amp; they are accoūted liberall and bountiful, which beſtow giftes vpon him that deſerueth well, &amp; requeſteth nothing. For doubtleſſe, that gifte is double to bee accepted, which proceedeth from a free hand and a liberall hart: becauſe Plautus ſaieth,

that he giueth too late, that giueth when he is asked: for the requeſt of the thing that is giuen, deſerueth the gift: wherfore he is rightly accoū
               ted liberal, that giueth of his owne accord, and receiueth not, and withall the benefite of the giuer doth more profit him that giueth, then the receiuer; which Phocion, the whole credit of Athens, did eſteeme rightly to be no otherwiſe, who when Alexander the great had preſented him with giftes, and ſundry coſtly Iewels frō Perſia, did ſhew a liuely example hereof in refuſing the gift, adding this ſentence, I wil not learne to take, leſt I forget to giue. Wherein hee ſhewed himſelfe a patterne of liberalitie, well befitting the worthines

of his perſon. Herby we may coniecture, that to be liberal, is a ſigne of an excellēt mind. This property of beſtowing, is a commendation in noble perſons: for in liberall giuing &amp; beneficial doing, are princes compared vnto God. For what may be more cōmendable in ſubiectes towards their Prince, then to be faithfull and loyall? or what may deſerue greater praiſe, thē liberality and clemency in a prince towards his ſubiects? What made Iulius Ceſar to be beloued of his ſouldiers, but magnificēce and liberality? who vanquiſhed Darius, whoſe treaſure and ſubſtance were brought before him, which amounted in ready coine, to two hundred thouſand pounds, beſide infinite

treaſures and iewels, wherof he tooke nothing from his ſouldiers, but a litle book, named Homers Iliades, in which he delighted much, onely to note the exploits of the Grecians, and the worthy feates of the Troians. This mā exceeded ſo much herein, that happy was that ſouldier, that could be a ſouldier to Ceſar. O liberal hart, O paſſing policy, O happy eſtate, and glorious ſtay of ſuch a Common wealth, wherein like liberality of Princes towards their ſubiects is found, &amp; ſuch loialty and fidelity of ſubiects is ſhewed and performed. Seing liberality is a vertue that deſerueth ſo great praiſe, what man is he that carieth neuer ſo baſe and abiect a mind, that hauing any poſſeſſions

or wealth, and would not be moued with ſome remorſe of cōſcience, to beſtow a ſmal portion thereof, vpon the poore diſtreſſed and needy? if not as being addicted to liberality, yet as being mooued with pity, he would gladly imparte ſome of the encreaſe therof, for his ſake that beſtoweth the ſtocke, and yeeldeth the encreaſe.
            1 Liberality hath a zealous hart, opē hands, inuincible faith in earth, and a perpetual dwelling in heauen.
            2 The liberall man recōcileth diſpleaſure, the vnliberall engendreth hate.
            3 A liberall man beginning to decay, ſhal in his feebleneſſe and want, finde his friends and foes.
            4 He that is liberal, concealeth

nothing from them whom he doth affectionate, by which meanes true loue encreaſeth, &amp; amity is made more firme, and ſtable.
         
         
            Of Clemency. Cap. 33.
            CLemēcy is a vertue which belongeth to the inuincible part of the ſoule, wherby we are ſlowly addicted to any kind of vices, which all decay in proceſſe of time: only this mercy or clemency encreaſeth. Haughtineſſe ſeing this vertue to be honored, deſireth oftentimes to be couered with the cloke therof, fearing, leſt appearing in her own ſhape, ſhe ſhould be litle regarded. The property

of this matchles virgine, is to ſuſtaine thoſe crimes which are layed vpon her, not tolerating her ſelfe to be haſtily carried to reuenge, nor eaſily ſpurred to wrath: but enforcing him in whō ſhe reſteth, to be of a ſetled &amp; ſtaied reſolution, and to carry a milde and gracious mind: for hee that purchaſeth otherwiſe, wanting clemency, is ſaied to cary duſt againſt the winde. Wherefore let all Gouernours, which do know for a certainty they haue their power from aboue, pōder in their minds in what caſe they themſelues be daily, if God did not abounde in mercy, who would ſpeedily, aſſoone as they had grieuouſly offended, ſmite them with his rod of correction, although as the

Scripture ſaieth, the pureſt man liuing paſſeth not one howre, which deſerueth not ſome puniſhment: but God being infinit in mercy, vpon hope of amendemēt pardoneth. As therefore imitating his example, and following his ſteps, let all mē moſt willingly embrace clemency, which is of ſuch excellency, that the hart of man cannot conceiue, nor his tongue vtter either the infinit goodnes thereof, or how admirably it linketh humane ſociety. Wherfore as Demonax was wont to ſay, mē ought not to want clemency, nor to waxe angry in correcting faultes, vſing the example of Phyſitions, which are not moued to fret at their ſicke patiēts, but mildly to cure the diſeaſe:

meaning hereby, that the only remedy, and ſureſt way to winne the good will of the ſubiects, is alwaies for the ruler to be courteous and gentle, which cauſeth loue in the ſubiects, and procureth the good of the Cōmon wealth. Of ſuch clemency was Pompey the great, who, when Tigranes king of Armenia by him conquered, kneeled before him, yeelding vp his Crowne and Scepter at his feete, and himſelf to his mercy as a captiue, tooke him vp in his armes, embraced him, put on his crowne on his head, and reſtored him to his kingdome againe. Was there euer Monarch more feared of his enemies, thē Alexander the great, inuincible in al enterpriſes he attēpted,

in ſo much that he could not onely force all humane powers, but alſo time &amp; place themſelues? &amp; yet who hath left greater proofe of meekneſſe then he? for as he was on his voiages, vndertakē for the conqueſt of the Indians, he &amp; Taxilles might not war one againſt the other. If thou (ſaith this king vnto him) art leſſe then I, receiue benefits: if greater, I will take them of thee. Alexander greatly cō
               mending, &amp; withal admiring the grauity and courteous ſpeach of this Indian, anſwered thus, At the leaſt we muſt cōbat for this, namely whether of vs twaine ſhalbe moſt beneficial vnto his cōpanion. So loath was this noble Monarch to yeeld to the other the ſuperiority in clemency.

What can more ſtir vp humane harts to great affections? what more maintaineth loue? what ioyneth the harts of ſubiectes vnto their ſoueraigne? Nothing ſo much as clemency. Adrian a noble Romane, conceyued great hatred againſt a famous gentlemā of Rome: but aſſoone as this noble Adrian was made Emperour, by chaunce meeting his enemy in the ſtreet, that very day that hee was created Emperour, ſaid with a loud voice, in the preſence of all the people, Euaſistime, Thou haſt wōne the conqueſt: meaning, that he being made a Prince, might in no ſort reuēge the wrongs that he conceiued before. O vnſpeakable humanity, and paſsing clemēcy in a Prince.

Iulius Ceſar was alſo of ſuch courteous behauior, that hauing conquered Pompey, &amp; all his enemies, hee wrote to his friends in Rome, that the greateſt and moſt eſtimable fruit, which he of his victory conceiued, cōſiſted in ſauing daily the life of men, being his owne countrey men, who had borne armes againſt him. For eſpeciall proofe of this meekneſſe and gentleneſſe, that ſpeach may ſerue which he vttered, when he vnderſtoode, that Cato returning vnto the towne of Vtica, after the loſſe of the battel, had violated his owne life. O Cato (ſaith this Monarch beyng then very penſiue) I enuy thee for this thy death, ſeing thou haſt enuied me the glory of ſauing thy life: I neuer

yet denied clemency (ſaid that good Emperour Marcus Aurelius) to him that demaunded it of mee, much leſſe haue I euil entreated, or offered diſhonor to any that repoſed any confidēce in me: affirming, that there could be no victory, which ſhould enioy the name of a true and perfect victory, excepting that which harboureth clemency, alleadging, To ouercome, was humane, but to pardon, was diuine. Wherfore, ſaith this Prince, of whō we made mention, that wee ought to eſteeme the magnificence of the immortall Gods, not ſo much for the chaſtiſement, as for the mercy which they vſe.
            1 Clemency is the character of an vnſpotted ſoule,

which neuer lightly ſuffereth innocency to be troden vnder feet.
            2 Pride is vaine, cruelty is hated, but clemēcy alone for her meekenes is canonized.
            3 Clemency ouermuch vſed, is no clemēcy: to be too ſubmiſsiue and humane ingenerall, is to proue humane to none, becauſe that generality can neuer at any time proue particular.
            4 Clemency in maieſty, is the righteſt path to binde affection in duty.
         
         
            Of Peace. Cap. 34.
            PEace is a vertue, that purchaſeth the ſecurity and quietnes of kingdomes, ſuppreſsing al tumults, vprores, and factions, planting quietneſſe

and tranquillity of life▪ But as Cicero ſaieth, Peace is the end of warre; dignity &amp; renowne, the ioy of peace; and in a well eſtabliſhed gouernmēt, an anchor to both, without which no life is quiet, no eſtate well ſtaied, nor no affaires rightly managed. Wherefore, they that wiſh the want hereof, and refuſe the conditions, may rightly be ſaid to deſerue the ſword of warre, which no man, except he be void of reaſon &amp; ſenceles, would willingly deſire: for as Cicero ſaith, there is nothing ſo much to bee wiſhed, as peace, by which, not onely thoſe things which haue ſence in thē by nature, but alſo the very walles and houſes do ſeeme to glory &amp; reioyce thereat: for when

there is no trouble of warre, the ſpirit is quiet, &amp; fitte for euery kind of honeſt reſt, iuſtice floriſheth, vertue ſheweth her effects, vice languiſheth, the zeale of pity encreaſeth, the diſcipline of the Church is authoriſed, both the noble and meane man preſerueth &amp; gouerneth his wealth, trade and trafficke is free: briefly, euery one receiueth good and commodity, &amp; ſo cōſequently the whole body of the common welth. Archidamus king of Lacedemonia, knowing well the effects of peace and warre here briefly touched by vs, and hearing that the Elians ſent ſuccour to the Archadians, to warre againſt him, tooke occaſion to write vnto them, after the Laconicall

maner, in ſteade of a long diſcourſe, Archedamus to the Elians: peace is a goodly thing. And an other time he gaue a notable teſtimony, how farre he preferred peace before warre, when he made anſwere to one that cōmended him, becauſe he had obtained a battaile againſt the foreſaid Archadians, It had bene better if wee had ouercome them by prudence, rather then by force: euery prince that deſireth war, ſtirreth vp againſt himſelf, both the hatred &amp; weapons of his neighbor, he vexeth his ſubiects vnworthily; ſeeking rather to rule ouer them by violence, then to gaine their good wil by iuſtice, he quite ouerthroweth his countrey.
            1 Peace triūpheth, where

reaſon ruleth, and ſecurity raigneth, where wiſdome directeth.
            2 It is a ſigne of godlines, to be at peace with men, and at warre with vices.
            3 Peace from the mouth of a tyrant, is often promiſed, but ſeldome performed.
         
         
            
               Hauing layed downe ſomewhat of the vertues, which are the cauſe of the flouriſhing eſtate of a Cōmon wealth, it followeth in briefe of the vices which are the deſtruction, and vtter ruine of all gouernments, and of euery Common wealth.
            
            Of Idlenes. Cap. 35.
            IDlenes is a feare of labour, deſiſting from neceſſary

actions, both of body and mind: it is the onely nurſe &amp; noriſher of ſenſual appetite, and the ſincke which entertaineth all the filthy chanels of vices, and infecteth the mind with many miſchiefes, and the ſole maintainer of youthly affectiōs. They therfore that doe nothing, ſaieth Cicero, learne to do ill, and through idleneſſe the bodies &amp; mindes of men languiſh away, but by labour great things are obtained; yet trauaile is a worke that continueth after death: therefore it was well ordeined in the primitiue Church, that euery one ſhould liue of his owne labour, &amp; ſweat of his owne brow, that the idle &amp; ſlouthfull might not conſume vnprofitably the goods of the

earth: which reaſon brought in that auncient Romane edict mentioned by Cicero in his booke of Lawes, that no Romane ſhould go through the ſtreets of the citie, vnleſſe he caried with him the badge of that trade whereby he liued; inſomuch that Marcus Aurelius ſpeaking of the diligence of the Romanes, writeth, that all of thē followed their labour. It is our duty therefore, to abide firme and conſtant in that good &amp; cō
               mendable kind of life, which we haue choſen from the beginning, ſo that the end therof be to liue well: and let vs ſhunne idlenes in ſuch ſorte, as to ſay with Cato, that it is one thing whereof we ought to repent vs moſt, if we know that we haue ſpent a whole

day, wherin we haue neither done nor learned any good thing. Phocilides minding to inſtruct vs in this matter, ſaide, that in the euening we ought not to ſleepe, before we haue thriſe called to memory whatſoeuer wee haue done the ſame day, repenting vs of the euill, and reioycing in our well dooing. Apelles the chiefeſt paynter that euer was, would not ſuffer one day to paſſe, without drawyng ſome line: meaning thereby (as hee ſaide) to fight againſt idleneſſe, as with an enemy. Eleas King of Scythia, ſaide, That hee deemed himſelf to differ nothing from his horſe-keeper when hee was idle. Dioniſius the elder, being demanded if hee was neuer idle,

anſwered, God keepe mee frō that horrible vice: for as a bow (according to the common Prouerbe) is broken, by keeping it in too much bending: ſo is the ſoule through too much idleneſſe. This is that which Maſiniſſa the Aphricā would learnedly teach vs, of whō Polibius writeth, that he died when hee was foureſcore and 10. yeeres of age, leauing behind him a ſonne that was but foure yeeres old a little before hee died, after he had diſcōfited the Carthaginians in a maine battell, hee was ſeene the next day eating of courſe browne bread, ſaying, to ſome that maruailed therat, That as yron is bright and ſhineth as long as it is vſed by the hande of man, and

as a houſe falleth to decay wherein no man dwelleth (as Sophocles ſaith) ſo fareth it with this brightneſſe and gliſtring light of the ſoule, wherby we diſcourſe, vnderſtand, and remember. The ſame reaſon moued Xerxes father to ſay to Darius, that in perilous times and dangerous affaires he increaſed in wiſdome. Likewiſe politicall knowledge, is ſo excellent a prudence, ſettled minde, iuſtice, &amp; experience, as knoweth full well how to make choiſe of, and to take fit time and opportunity in all things that happen, which cannot be maintained but by practiſe &amp; managing of affaires, by diſcourſing and iudging. Now to conclude our preſent treatiſe, ſeing we know

that we are borne to all vertuous actions, let vs flie from idlenes and ſlouth, the welſpring of al iniuſtice, and pouerty, the ſtirrers vp of infinite paſsions in the ſoule, and the procurers of many diſeaſes in the body, euen to the vtter deſtructiō of men: And let vs embrace diligēce, care, trauell, and ſtudy, which are ſure guides to lead vs to that end, for which wee ought to liue, wherin conſiſteth all the happines and cōtentation of the life of good men: and let vs not dout, but that all time otherwiſe ſpent, is loſt time, knowing that all times in reſpect of themſelues are like: but that which is imploied in vertue in regard of vs, and that which is vnprofitably waſted, &amp; in vices, is naught.
            
               1 Idlenes maketh of men women, of women beaſts, of beaſts monſters.
            2 To fly with idlenes frō that wee ſhould follow, is to follow our own deſtruction.
            3 To idlenes belongeth correction, to correction amendment, to amendment reward.
         
         
            Of Pleaſures and delight. Cap. 36.
            DElight is a pleaſure, that moueth and tickleth our ſenſes, rayſing our hopes on hilles of high deſire, which quickly fadeth &amp; vanquiſheth away, and rather leaueth behinde it an occaſion of repentaunce (how delectable ſoeuer theſe pleaſures bee) then any reaſon to call it againe to remembrance, albeit

amongſt the pleaſures &amp; delights which men haue in this worlde, ſome are decent, holy &amp; honeſt; as thoſe which we cōceaue in the reading and meditation of the law of God, in our obedience towards him, and of the faith and hope we haue in his promiſes. All which (as Dauid ſaith) are more to be deſired then gold, yea thē fine gold, &amp; are ſweeter then the hony &amp; hony cōbe. It is alſo a ſingular pleaſure to behold the prouidence, wiſedome and goodnes of God towards his creatures, and to conſider how euery one of them, and euery part of them, are appointed to ſome good purpoſe, and ordained for the vſe, pleaſure and profite of man: in theſe pleſures there is

neyther ſhame, ſorrow, nor repentāce: for euery thing is holy, and there is no euil, vnleſſe it be, that wee are not greatly deſirous to fall into theſe conſiderations, or becauſe we are ouer-weary of them. There are other pleaſures which are natural, as to eate when we are hungry, to drinke when we are thirſty, to reſt when we are weary, &amp; ſuch like; by the ſweetneſſe wherof, our good God, which is a louer of our welfare, would ſtirre vs vp to be carefull of our ſelues. There are alſo ſome which are ſuperfluous &amp; vnprofitable, as that of Socrates, which was accuſtomed to ſtand in one place gazing at the Sunne, frō the riſing therof vntill Sunne ſet: or as the Deere that delighteth

to gaze ſo long on the bowe, vntil he is hit with the bolt: or that of ſundry others, which they take in tricking toyes, as in engrauing or ſuch like: otherſome ſpend the moſt parte of the day at the dore, to ſhew their beauties, &amp; to behold the paſſengers by: not vnlike ye
                wolues of Syria, which delight to barke againſt the Moone, ſpēding their time about nothing, which euery mā ought to hold moſt precious, and eſpecially gouernours, who are alwaies to be emploied in matters of great conſequēce, whereof the charge is ſuch, that if they diſcharge their duty, they ſhall hardly haue ſo much leaſure, as to eat their meat, &amp; take their reſt, vnleſſe they omit ſome of

that time which ſhould bee emploied in publike affaires. Moreouer there are other pleaſures which are lewd, &amp; are termed by the name of carnall &amp; worldly pleaſures, &amp; theſe are they whereof at this preſent I purpoſed to diſcourſe. Herein let vs reſolue our ſelues, that it is not ſufficiēt to do our endeuour, that according vnto the example of S. Paul, &amp; following his aduice &amp; coūſaile, we do apply our ſelues to the perſons with whom we liue, and that we transforme our ſelues vnto them, though that their natures be oftentimes different &amp; diſagreeing from vs; but withall, wee muſt apply our ſelues to the ſuddaine chaunces and ſundry accidents of this life, and keepe

our minds alwaies in one eſtate and condition, whether wee be poore or rich, as it is ſaid of Socrates, that vnto what houſe ſoeuer he came, were it to the Kings palace, or the beggers cottage, were he in Silkes, Veluet or Friſe, he alwaies kept a decorum &amp; a comlines in his behauior, beſeeming ſuch a philoſopher as he was. So in like maner muſt we apply our ſelues &amp; learne to vſe al alterations and changes, whether they ſhould be eaſe or labour, honour, or diſhonor, pouerty &amp; riches, friends and enemies, health &amp; ſicknes, impriſonmēt &amp; liberty, reſt &amp; paines, ſorrow and gladnes, without doing any thing vnprofitable or not befitting a Chriſtian, or diſagreeing, &amp; not beſeeming

our eſtate &amp; conditions and in ſo doing, a man that ſhal moderately &amp; wiſely enioy any pleaſure as God ſhall miniſter him occaſiō, giuing thanks vnto him, &amp; acknowledging his goodnes, ought much more to be cōmended, thē he that refuſeth his grace and fauour, depriuing himſelfe of thoſe giftes &amp; talents which God hath giuen and offered him: for he doth it either through contempt, ſuperſtitiō, or deteſtable pride, thinking himſelfe to be more wiſe in reiecting, then accepting the goodneſſe that God hath offered him.
            1 Worldly gladneſſe rideth vpon the wings of time, but he that ſitteth ſureſt, may be ouerthrowne.
            2 Conceale thy delights

in thy heart, leſt ſhamefully they be diſcouered.
            3 Delight is the brook of euils, quenching the light of the ſoule, &amp; hindering counſell, turning men aſide from the right way.
            4 The delight of the hart addeth length to life, but ſorrow of life haſteneth death.
         
         
            Of Intemperance and Gluttony. Cap. 37.
            INtemperance is an enemy to frugality, a daughter to exceſſe, a foe to temperance, &amp; a fauourit to immoderate appetite, that craueth daily more then it needeth, like an vnthākful beaſt, vnwilling to gratify the pleaſure done it, which liues as a ſlaue to the mouth &amp; belly: for what can be more vile &amp;

loathſom, thē is the drūkard, whoſe mouth is the lodge of poiſoned ſauors, whoſe body through exceſſe doth trēble &amp; ſhake, whoſe promiſes are large, whoſe tongue bewraieth ſecretes, whoſe minde is ſoone changed, whoſe countenance is transformed: for where drunkennes raigneth there ſecretie beareth no ſway: for cōmonly when the head is ful of wine, the tōgue is ſet at liberty; beſides, this wine doth not onely ſuffice a drunkard, neither is he contēt with many ſorts of wine, as ſacke, baſtard, hipocras, &amp; ſuch like, but hee drowneth his ſenſes in all variety of liquor, making himſelf the mō
               ſter of exceſſe. O deſire inſatiable, O fire inquenchable. This is the nurſery of al cōtē
               tion

and ſtrife: for as the wiſe man ſaith, Much drinking of wine kindleth the coales of wrath, and is the roote of all miſbelief &amp; ruine, and the ſequel therof is fornication, yea fornication, wine, &amp; drūkennes, bereue noble minds of al ſtrength and courage, corrupt the bloud, diſſolue the whole man, &amp; finally make him forgetfull of himſelfe altogether. Therefore the Apoſtle writeth, Be not drūk▪ with wine, wherein is laſciuious wanton luſt. And that wiſe king ſaith, That wine is a leacherous thing, and that drunkennes is full of ſtrife &amp; diſſentiō. The childrē of Rachab, &amp; the ſons of Zachary dranke no wine, nor no other kinde of ſtrong drinke that might ouercome their ſēſes,

Gluttony the mother of vncleanneſſe, bringeth foorth a more vncleane daughter: for it is very agreable to reaſon, that what is already vncleane, ſhould become as it were more diſparged with vncleanneſſe. For all thoſe which commit fornication, are like vnto the bakers ouen made hote with fire. The princes &amp; rulers begā to rage through wine: for the belly which is daintily fed, moſt willingly of it ſelf embraceth carnall pleaſures, &amp; extreme rage of vncleane luſt, which doth not only effeminat the mind, but alſo weakneth the body, and indaungereth the perſon in this life, and bringeth both body and ſoule in peril of damnation in the life to come: for al the ſinne that

a mā committeth, is without the body, but he that offendeth infornication, committeth an offence againſt his owne body. Heate &amp; luſt are the harbingers of fornicatiō, &amp; it is alwaies combinat and accōpanied with vncleānes, &amp; vndecentneſſe, but ſorrow &amp; repentance do ſpeedily ouertake it: for the lippes of an harlot (ſaith Salomon) or like vnto a dropping hony cōbe, and her throat is more neate and cleaner then oile, but the and &amp; latter daies of her are as bitter as wormwood, and her tongue is as ſharpe as a two edged ſword. Let al men therefore eſchue this odious vice, which though at the firſt it ſeeme pleaſant, yet in the end it will wound like Baſi
               
                  •
               icocks, which ſlay &amp; kil men

with the poyſon of their ſight.
            1 Sobriety cōteineth that in a wiſe mans thought, which a foole without diſcretion hath in his mouth.
            2 Gluttony ſtirreth vp luſt, drieth the bones, and more die by it, then periſh by the ſworde.
            3 Intemperance is a root proper to euery diſeaſe, and he that too much pampereth himſelfe, is a heauy foe to his owne body.
            4 Intēperance increaſeth anger, &amp; anger in extremity extinguiſheth vnderſtāding opinion and memory.
         
         
            Of Luſt, and Lawleſſe delights. Cap. 38.
            
               LVſt is a deſire againſt reaſon, that enforceth vs to couet beyōd our power, a furious and an vnbridled appetite, which procureth vs to act beyond our nature, &amp; to die before our time, in that it rooteth al good motions out of the minde of man, leauing no abode for vertuous actions: for in the beginning of mans life bread &amp; water was his foode, &amp; a ſimple garmēt with a poore cottage were thought ſufficiēt to couer his deformity: but now the fruits of trees, the ſundry ſortes of graines, the rootes of hearbs, the fiſhes of the ſea, the beaſts of the land, the foules of the ayre, doe not ſatisfie the greedy appetites of gluttons, and rauening men; now they ſeeke for pleaſant

diſhes with painted colours, they procure delicates and hoat ſpices, choice meats, ſugred morſels for their dainty mouths, thoſe things do they feed vpon, which be curiouſly wrought by the art of cookery &amp; other officers: one by ſtamping &amp; ſtraining changeth ſome things from their proper nature, labouring by arte to make that accident, which of it ſelfe is a ſubſtāce: an
                  •••
               er compoūdeth things together, to make that delicate, which of it ſelf is vnpleſant: &amp; all this is to turne exceſſe to hunger, to bring an appetite to the ſtomacke oppreſt with ſaturity, and to fill the greedy deſire of gluttony, rather thē to ſuſtaine the weaknes of nature. Gluttony is an enemy to health, a

friend to ſicknes, the mother of wanton luſt, and the inſtrument of death. Bee not greedy, ſaith the wiſe man, at any banquet, nor feede not on euery diſh: for with the diuerſity of diſhes the health is indangered, and through ſurfet of wine many haue periſhed: meate is ordained for the belly, and the belly to receiue the meat, but God ſhal deſtroy both the one and the other. Gluttony requireth a coſtly &amp; chargeable tribute, but yet yeeldeth a very baſe and vile rent: for how much more delicate the meate is, ſo much more odious are the fruits thereof. Gluttony diſtēpereth the body, corrupteth the ſtomacke, and maketh al partes noiſome:
                  Gen. 3. gluttony did ſhut vp the gates of

Paradiſe againſt mankind: gluttony cauſed Eſau to ſell his inheritāce:
                  Gen. 25. gluttony was the maine path which ledde Pharaos baker to the gallowes:
                  Gen. 40.
               
                  Mat. 14 gluttony was the inſtrument that wrought Iohn Baptiſt his death: Nabuzardon the chiefe cooke of the king of Babilon, burnt the temple, and deſtroied the city Ieruſalem.
                  Dan. 5. Balthaſar the king of Babilon in his great and ſumptuous banquet, ſaw a hand writing on the wall, Mane, Thekel, Phares, &amp; the ſame night he was killed by the Caldeans. The people o
                  •
                Iſrael ſate downe to make good cheere, and roſe vp to play: but whileſt the meate was yet in their mouthes, the wrath of God fell vpō them, and deſtroied them all, for

their voluptuous and lewd kind of liuing. The rich man which did feaſt, banquet, and abound in worldly pompe &amp; vanity, is buried in hell. Vitellius alſo was ſo much giuen to gluttony and exceſſe, that at one ſupper he was ſerued with two thouſand ſeuerall kind of fiſhes, and with 7000. flying foules. Alſo Ariſtotle mocking the Epicures, ſaid, That vpon a time they went all to a temple together, beſeeching the gods, that they would giue them necks as long as Cranes and Herons, that the pleaſures &amp; taſte of meat might be more long, cōplaining againſt nature for making their neckes too ſhort.
            1 Lechery is a ſtrong tower of miſchiefe, and hath

many vpholders, as needines, paleneſſe, anger, luſt, diſcord, loue, and longing.
            2 Concupiſcence in decrepit olde age, is loathſomnes, in youth exceſſe, &amp; betweene both, the fruite of idlenes.
            3 Concupiſcence is an enemy to the purſe, and a foe to the perſon, a canker to the mind, procuring blindneſſe to the vnderſtanding, hardnes of hart, &amp; want of grace.
            4 Cōcupiſcence is a ſinne finiſhed with ſorrow, a luſt that groweth by cōtinuance, an infamy nouriſhed by laſciuiouſnes.
         
         
            Of Enuy. Cap. 39.
            ENuy is a griefe ariſing of other mens proſperity, to

which vice malignity is alwaies a confederat: this hate or enuy ſpringeth of certaine pleaſure or delight, conceaned by other mens harme, although it reapeth nor enioyeth pleaſure or profite thereby, yet as being an enemy to vnity, reioyceth thereat. This triuiall vice is ſaid to be the mother of wickednes, and accounted to ſit in an immaginary theater, her palace is a dim &amp; hollow vaute, wherin ſhe waxeth pale &amp; wanne, as hauing the cōſumption of the liuer, looking askwint, as borne vnder Saturne, flowing with gall, as hauing no affinity with the doue, neuer reioycing, being conceaued without a ſplene, yet ſmileth at other mens misfortune, being in a league with the

Crocodile: ſhee is alwaies carefull, and neuer reſting, as though ſhe were an arme of Ixions wheele. This vice, as the Poets doe ſay, is a monſtrous vermine, and an enemy to concord, engendred and hatched by the vgly Megera of hell, that feedes and crāmes her gorge with dragons, and fomes out againe deadly poyſon; then which vice, nothing is more pernicious to the eſtate of the cō
               mon welth: for what may be more vnſeemely and deteſtable, then one man to pine away at an others good eſtate, or reioyce at an others harme? The cauſes that doe bring foorth this vile bratte, are many, (as diuers doe rehearſe) whereof one, as I my ſelf by experiēce haue partly

knowne, is, that wheras ſome ſpringing from baſe ſtocke, and withall like the Scaribe, bearing lowe thoughts, yet haue enuied and grudged at others, that both by nature and nurture, were well qualified, &amp; of good deſerts, becauſe they were not willing to ſee any other proſper or of any eſtimation and dignity; not becauſe they hate praiſe or dignity themſelues, but becauſe they haue nothing in themſelues worthy of fame, nor any ſparkle left by their poſterities, that might rightly chalēge any prerogatiue: and this is the meaneſt ſort of enuy. Some other are enuied by the better ſort, for their hauty &amp; inſolent pride, who will admit no coequall, or ſecond. Such a one was

Seſoſtris, who was ſo proud &amp; haughty, that whenſoeuer he went to the temple or any whither in publike, cauſed his chariot to be drawne by foure tributary Kinges or great Lords, inſtead of horſes: ſhewing thereby, that none of the other kings or captaines were to be compared to him in vertue and proweſſe. And this ſorte of enuy is ſomewhat tolerable. Some others are enuied, being promoted to honour and dignity, or increaſing in wealth &amp; ſubſtance: ſo likewiſe the good of the euill &amp; lewd ſort, are hated for their goodnes and vertue, which vice is intolerable, and as vnſit to be in the Common weale, as a coward in warres: wherfore ſaith a worthy man

named Demor
                  •
               s, that the lawes did not forbid euery man to liue according to his owne wiſhed deſire, vnleſſe the one were enuious &amp; iniurious to the other: meaning, that enuy was the onely beginner and ſtirrer vp of hatred, and of other vices. Such was the enuy of Themiſtocles, who repined and was puffed vp with great enuy, when he perceyued Melciades to be honoured for his conqueſt, that he could not take quiet reſt, and beyng demaunded what might be the cauſe thereof, anſwered, that the triumphes of Melciades would not ſuffer him to take any reſt. Wherein he ſhewed himſelf a vitious man and worthy of reproch. But on the cōtrary ſide, Socrates

being told that he was enuied of one, appeaſed his anger and anſwered, It is not material: alleadging, The harme will be his, and not mine: for both his owne ill hap, and my good ſucceſſe, ſhall torment and put him to paine: Adding that of Horace, Inuidus alterius rebus macreſcit opimis: The enuious man pines away, to ſee an others proſperity.
            1 A diſcreet man had rather be enuied for prouident ſparing, then pitied for his prodigall ſpending.
            2 Enuy is the daughter of pride, the companiō of magnificence, the beginner of ſecrete ſedition, &amp; the perpetual corrupter of vertue.
            3 Enuy ſwalloweth vp the greateſt part of her own poiſon.
            
               4 The enuious man that carieth hatred in his face, and folly in his head, is combred with two wormes, the one fretteth life, the other conſumeth goods.
         
         
            Of Couetouſnes. Cap. 40.
            COuetouſnes is a deformity of the ſoule, wherby a man moſt greedily deſireth to heape riches frō all partes without meaſure, regarding not how vniuſtly hee detaineth goods belonging vnto others, ſo that he may augmēt his riches, which he gathereth with great trauailes, &amp; keepeth them with more dāger. The couetous man is alwaies ready to aske, but ſlow to giue, and bold to deny: all that hee ſpendeth, he

thinketh it loſt, and after expenſe he is full of ſorrow, full of complaints, froward and hard to pleaſe, hee is preſt with care, &amp; ſigheth through the remembraunce of that which is ſpent, he is troubled in minde, tormented in body, &amp; if ought goe from him, it is much againſt his will, GOD wote, hee maketh his owne gifts glorious, and embraceth not that which hee receiueth from others, he giueth in hope to receiue, and of his giftes he maketh his gaine, he is free of expenſe where others beare ye
                charge, very ſparing in ſpending of his owne, he forbeareth his food, his treaſure to encreaſe, he pineth his body, to multiply his gaine, hee putteth backe his hand, when hee

ought to giue, but he ſtretcheth it farre forth, when he is to receiue any thing: howbeit, the wealth &amp; ſubſtance of the vnrighteous ſhalbe dried vp as a riuer, becauſe goods euill gotten are ſoone againe conſumed; for it is a iuſt iudgement, that wealth of euill beginning, ſhould haue an euill ending, &amp; that thoſe things which be vniuſtly gathered, ſhould bee vniuſtly and vnthriftily ſcattered: The couetous man hath therefore his condemnation in this life, and in the life to come. Tantalus, as the poet ſaieth, thirſteth amidſt the waters; euen ſo the couetous man ſtādeth in need amōgſt all his great wealth, to whom that which hee hath, doth as much good, as that which he

hath not, becauſe hee neuer vſeth it, but alwaies gapeth after things not as yet obtained: hee is, ſaieth the Wiſe man, as though, hee were rich, when he hath nothing, and is as though hee were poore, when he flouriſheth in welth. The couetous man &amp; the pit of hell do both of thē deuoure, but they do not digeſt, they receiue both, but they doe not render againe: the niggard doth neither pitie thoſe that ſuffer affliction, nor yet haue compaſsion of thoſe that are in miſery, but hee forgetteth his dutie to GOD, and the due to his neighbour, ſeeking his owne harme and diſquietneſſe: for hee holdeth backe the due vnto God, he denyeth to his neighbour things neceſſary,

and withdraweth from himſelfe things that be needfull, he is vnthankfull to GOD, vnkinde to his neighbour, &amp; cruell to himſelfe. To what vſe hath the couetous man ſubſtaunce, and to what end hath the ſpitefull &amp; malitious man gold? how can he that is euill to himſelfe, be good to others? Or he that taketh no profite of his owne gotten goods? He that hath the ſubſtaunce of this worlde, and ſeeth his brother in neceſſity, and ſhutteth vp his compaſsion from him, howe dwelleth the loue of GOD in him? For hee loueth not his neighbour as himſelfe, whom he ſuffereth to periſh for hunger, and conſume for neede, neyther doth he loue God aboue all thinges, who

more then God, reſpecteth gold and ſiluer.
            1 The couetous man bettereth no man, and worſe befriendeth himſelfe.
            2 A couetous mans purſe is the deuils mouth, his life is to liue a begger, and his end to die in want.
            3 Riches gathered by the couetous, are lightly waſted by the prodigall perſon.
            4 The couetous man can learne no truth, becauſe hee lotheth the truth.
         
         
            Of Vſury. Cap. 41.
            VSury is an actiue element that conſumeth all the fewell that is layed vpon it, gnawing the detters to the bones, and ſucketh out the

bloud &amp; marrow from them, ingendring money of mony, contrary to the diſpoſition of nature, and holding a diſordinate deſire of wealth; of which it may be ſaid, as it was to Alexander, of the Scythians, What needeſt thou of riches which conſtraine thee alwaies to deſire? thou art the firſt, which of abūdance haſt made indigence, to the end that by poſſeſſing more, thou mighteſt with more eaſe by vnlawfull vſury enioy that thou haſt not. This vice is ſo lothſome, and contrary to equity and reaſon, that all nations, which were led by the inſtinct of nature, haue alwaies abhorred and cōdemned it, in ſo much as the conditiō of theeues hath bin more tolerated, then vſury:

for theft was wont to be puniſhed but with double reſtitution, but vſury with quadruple: and to ſpeake truly, theſe rich &amp; gallant vſurers do more robbe the people, &amp; purloine from them, then all the publike theeues that are made examples of iuſtice in the world. It is to be wiſhed, that ſome would examine vſurers books, &amp; make a bonfire of their obligatiōs, as that Lacedemonian did, whē Ageſilaus reported, that he neuer ſaw a cleerer fire: or that ſome Lucullus would deliuer Europe frō that contagion, as that Romane did Aſia in his time. Licurgus baniſhed this canker worme out of Sparta, Amaſis puniſhed it ſeuerely in Egypt, Cato baniſhed it out of Sicilia, &amp; Solon condemned

it in Athens. How much more ſhould it be held in deteſtation amongſt Chriſtians? S. Chryſoſtome compareth it fitly to the biting of an Aſpe: as he that is ſtung with an Aſpe, falleth aſleepe as it were with delectation, but dieth yer he awaketh: ſo money takē in vſury, delighteth &amp; contenteth at the firſt, but it infecteth all his poſſeſſours, &amp; ſucketh out the marrow of them ſuddenly. Seing that it is ſo abominable by the lawe of God and nature, let vs ſhūne it as a toad, &amp; fly from it as from a Cockatrice. But if theſe perſwaſions will not ſerue, let them turne their eies to theſe examples following, wherein they ſhal ſee the manifeſt indignation of GOD vpon it.

Sergius Galba, before hee came to be Emperour, being preſident of Affrica vnder Claudius, when as through penury of vitailes, corne, &amp; other food were very ſparingly ſhared and deuided amongſt the army, puniſhed a certaine ſouldier, that ſolde a buſhell of wheate to one of his fellowes, for a hundred pence, in hope to obtaine a new ſhare himſelfe: in this maner he commaunded the Queſtor or treaſurer to giue him no more ſuſtenāce, ſince he preferred lucre before the neceſsity of his owne body, and his friends welfare, neyther ſuffred he any man elſe to ſell him any, ſo that he periſhed with famine, and became a miſerable example to all the army of the fruites of

that foule dropſie couetouſneſſe.
            1 Vſury is like a whirle poole, that ſwalloweth what ſo euer it catcheth.
            2 The ſerpent hidden in the graſſe, ſtingeth the foote, &amp; the vſurer vnder ſhadow of honeſty, deceiueth the ſimple.
            3 Vſury deceiues the belly, taketh away the title of gentry, and becommeth careleſſe of the ſoules ſafety.
            4 Couetouſnes findeth out vſury, vſury nouriſheth idlenes, idlenes is the bringer foorth of euils.
         
         
            Of Ambition. Cap. 42.
            
               AMbition is an vnmeaſurable deſire to enioy honors, preferments, eſtates &amp; great places of dignity; it is a vice of exceſſe, and contrary to modeſty: repugnant to this, amongſt the Romanes there was decreed a law, to this end or purpoſe, viz. that none might obtaine any dignity, or other function, by proouing liberall, beſtowing giftes, or in vſing any other vnlawfull meanes; which law yeelded no fauour to the offender: For whoſoeuer were found guilty &amp; condemned, ſhould aſſuredly ſuffer death. Which law, doubtleſſe, was needfull, waying what ſundry calamities by ambition happen: for they that be ambitious, are, as it were, with Iccarus wings carried with

an vnſatiable deſire of ſufferaignty, admitting of no period, or ſtay, from the loweſt centure, to the higheſt heauēs. If they that are with this vice attainted, doe obtaine any authority, then as ſuppoſing the rights of law to bee in their owne handes, they will effect what they liſt, deeming whatſoeuer is pleaſing vnto them, is lawfull. By reaſon hereof, they do ſeuer themſelues, as though they were by nature melācholike, &amp; giuen to embrace ſolitarineſſe, fearing contradictions, or cenſure of any others touching their enormities, wherby diuers iniuries haue riſen: For as Oſorius ſaieth, The more hawtie mind and noble a man hath, that is deſirous of glory &amp; eſtimatiō, the

more eaſie hee is to and fro carried by euery blaſt, to accompliſh any thing againſt equity. To this lothſome vice couetouſnes, muſt needes be annexed a property, otherwiſe the vaine glory of ambition and prowde oſtentation of the ambitious man, could not bee ſuggeſted: whoſe ſummū decus &amp; chiefe decorū
                of honor, do conſiſt in being imperious, &amp; carie a great port, &amp; ſway: to the vnderpropting whereof, his authority muſt needes bee a means to procure him coine, to cure his care, and vphold his calling, which is contrary both to the law of God and man, &amp; againſt the right rule of modeſty. Ariſtotle termeth him modeſt, who deſireth honour as he ought, and

no otherwiſe then it becommeth him: but he that deſireth it more then he ought, by an vnlawfull meanes, is ambitious, &amp; is carried away with the perturbation of intemperācy. Ambition neuer ſuffreth thoſe that haue once entertained it, as a gheſt, to enioy their preſent eſtate quietly, but maketh them alwaies empty of goods, and needy, it cauſeth them to cō
               temne that which they haue gotten by great paines and trauaile, and which not long before they deſired very earneſtly, by reaſon of their new imaginations and conceites of great matters, which they continually practiſed, but haue neuer their minds ſatiſfied and contented: the increaſe of power &amp; authority

is the cauſe whereby they are induced, and carried headlong to commit all kinde of iniuſtice, flattering themſelues in furious and frantike actions, that they may haue acceſſe to the end of their infinite plottes, and enioy that proud and tirannicall glory, which contrary to all dutie they haūt after. Spurius Melius a Senatour of Rome was murthered for his ambition, and his houſe raſed by Ticimātus the dictator of Rome, becauſe he ſought by meanes of certaine dole or diſtribution of wheat, to make himſelfe king of Rome. Marcus Manlius was alſo for the like occaſion, throwen downe from the toppe of a rocke. Therfore it appeareth ſufficiently vnto vs, how pernitious

this vice of ambition is in the ſoules of great men, and woorthy of perpetuall blame.
            1 Ambition is a ſerpent, which pryeth into euery mans thoghts, &amp; ſlily inſinuateth her ſelfe into the bowels of men.
            2 The ambitious man, that endeuoureth to plunge and depreſſe another, to enioy prefermēt, in ſtead of ſuperiority, attaineth indignity.
            3 Men that are enuious, placing their thoughts in the hieſt theater of honour, their fortune beyng lowe, muſt needs liue a male-contented life.
            4 An ambitious perſon will alway wander aſtray out of the right way, to attaine to the height that his hart deſireth.
            
               5 The ambitious is of ſuch vnacquainted fittes, and mouing ſpirites tempered, that he neuer contents himſelfe in any vocation.
         
         
            Of Anger. Cap. 43.
            ANger is furor brenis, a ſhortfury, or as Ariſtotle ſaieth, the ſuddaine inflamation of the bloud, cauſing the motions of the ſpirits, and alteration of the hart: it is alſo a deſire of reuēge, or a rechleſſe care of friendſhip, and an enemy to reaſon; wherby ſpringeth ſuch a hurly burly in the mind, that reaſon, during this fury, cānot be heard, nor vnderſtanding obeyed, no more then lawes or magiſtrates are regarded in a

ſtate torne and rent with euil diſſentiō: but in this trouble, the paſsions, which do waxe moſt mutinous and troubleſome to the quiet reſt of the ſpirites, doe firſt ariſe in the appetible and concupiſcible part: that is to ſay, in that part where the ſoule doth exerciſe his facultie of deſiring or reiecting things preſented vnto her, as being things contrary to her welfare and preſeruation. Choller knoweth not how to be ſilēt, but is very raſh, vnwary &amp; vnaduiſed in all things: whereby it happeneth, that thoſe headlong perſons rūne often into ſuch daunger, as they neuer gette out, by reaſon of their anger. Clitus &amp; Caliſthenes were the occaſion of their owne deſtruction,

for that they had bene ouerbold in reproouing Alexander; wheras by modeſt &amp; humble admonition they might haue reclaimed him, ſaued themſelues, and gotten the grace and fauour of their lord and maſter. C. Flaminius, and M. Marcellus, two conſuls of Rome, both valiant and hardy ſouldiers, were notwithſtāding ſurpriſed and ouerthrowen in the end by Hannibal, by reaſon of their ouermuch frowardnes, &amp; making too haſty trial of their fortune: wheras contrarywiſe, Fabius Maximus being a more ſober and temperate Captaine, neuer enterpriſed any thing, but with great aduiſedneſſe, and with ſuch deliberation conſidered of the circumſtance of

each thing, that Hannibal could neuer entrappe him in his ambuſhes, though he placed them neuer ſo cunningly. When Hieron king of Sicilia had murthered certaine of his friendes, and the report knowne thorowe the countrey, Epicharmus, who vnderſtood of the matter, within a while after was biddē to ſupper with the king, and by reaſon of his aboundāce of choller he could not diſſemble, but cried out aſſoone as hee ſaw the king, and reproued him for his infidelity and horrible murther, ſaying, Why didſt thou not call mee to the ſacrifice that thou madeſt of thy friends? which was the cauſe that he loſt his owne life alſo, and by this meanes made

the tyraunt more fearce and cruell then hee was before. Plutarch alſo reporteth, that when Dionyſius the tyrant asked the wiſe men of his Court, which copper was the beſt, Antiphon anſwered very readily, that in his opinion that was the moſt excellent, whereof the Athenians had made the pictures of the two tyraunts, Armodius &amp; Ariſtogitō. This was a quicke anſwere, &amp; ſpoken in anger; which notwithſtanding ſo ſtucke in the minde of the tirant, that hee could neuer bee appeaſed, but with the life of him that vttered it: which verifieth the ſaying of Quintilian, cō
               cerning thoſe bitter and cholerike natures, viz. that had rather loſe their liues, then

haue a bitter girde.
            1 There is no ſafe counſſell to bee taken from the mouth of the angry man.
            2 He detaineth himſelfe frō anger, that remembreth his ende, and feareth GOD: the one reſtraineth preſumption, the other appeaſeth impatience.
            3 Anger is an inwarde griefe, and vexation of the minde, thirſting after reuenge.
            4 With the angry man we muſt not be importunate in matters of conſequence, but ſhould deferre our petition vntill a cōuenient time, which might mitigate his anger.
         
         
            
            Of Sedition. Cap. 44.
            SEdition is an euill quality, which ſo much troubleth the quiet reſt, &amp; paſsions of ye
                ſoule, &amp; is accompanied with moſt dangerous effects, and yet nothing ſo dangerous as thoſe which follow after. For why? Theſe firſt motiōs, being bred and formed in that part, by meanes of the obiect which preſenteth it ſelfe, doe paſſe forth in continently into the iraſcible part of the minde, that is to ſay, to that part, where the ſoule ſeekes all meanes poſsible of obtaining or auoyding that which ſeemeth vnto her good or bad: for the auoiding hereof we muſt not imitate nature,

which, as Empedocles ſaieth, vſeth no other means to deſtroy, ruinate and ouerthrow her creatures, then diſcord, &amp; ſedition, and (as Thucidides ſaith) comprehendeth in it al kind of euils. Seditiō thē being taken generally, is nothing els but an euill impoſtume, ſo hurtfull to al eſtates and Monarchies, that it is the ſeed and roote of all kind of euils, euen of thoſe that are moſt execrable, it ingendreth &amp; nouriſheth want of reuerence towards God, diſobediēce to magiſtrates, corruption of maners, change of lawes, contempt of iuſtice, &amp; baſe eſtimatiō of learning &amp; ſcience. Thucidides ſpeaking of the generall diſſention amongſt the Grecians, for diuerſitie of gouernmēts,

which they ſought to bring in among themſelues, ſome deſiring to be gouerned in a Democratie, others in an Oligarchie, rehearſeth incredible euils that aroſe of that warre. As ſoone (ſaith he) as any mutinies, diſturbāces or vprores were knowen to be cōmitted in one place, others were encouraged to doe worſe, as to enterpriſe ſome new Stratageme, to ſhewe that they were more froward then others, or more inſolent &amp; hote in reuēging thē
               ſelues. This is that which Diamades obiected to the Athenians by way of reproch, that they neuer intreated of peace, but in mourning gownes: namely after they had loſt many of their kinſfolks in battels &amp; skirmiſhes

after long ſedition.
            1 Sedition is a hell to the minde, a horror to the conſcience, ſuppreſsing reaſon, and inciting hatred.
            2 There is no greater cruelty then ſedition, whereby a man continually murthereth himſelfe liuing.
            3 A ſeditious man waxeth leane, with the fatnes of his neighbour.
            4 Hidden ſeditiō is more daungerous, then open enmity.
         
         
            Of VVarre. Cap. 45.
            WArre is of two ſortes; eyther ciuill, or forraine: ciuill warre is the ouerthrower of all eſtates &amp; monarchies, and the very roote of al euil,

which ingēdreth want of reuerence towards God, diſobedience to Magiſtrates, cō
               tēpt of iuſtice, being ſprung of the diuerſitie of religion; but in effect, ambition. And forreine warre is a more lawfull contention, as being ordained for religion ſake, and to procure peace and vnitie. This ciuil war ſtirreth vp againſt himſelfe, both the hatred &amp; weapōs of his neighbours, to him that deſireth it. For hee that vexeth his ſubiects vnworthily, ſeeking rather to rule ouer them by violence, then to gaine their good wil with iuſtice, he quite ouerthroweth his countrey, preferring dominion and greatnes of his power, before the benefit of the ſame: he is brought oftentimes in ſubiection

to his enemies, and diminiſheth his owne authoritie, whiles he laboureth to poſſeſſe another mans right by violence. Auguſtus the Emperour ſaid, That to haue lawfull warre, it muſt bee commended by the gods, and iuſtified by the philoſophers. And Elius Spartianus affirmeth, that Traian onely of the Romanes, was neuer ouercome in battel, becauſe hee vndertooke no warre, except the cauſe thereof was very iuſt. But wee may well ſay, that no warres betweene Chriſtians a ſo iuſtified, but that ſtill there remaineth ſome cauſe of ſcruple. Moreouer wee ſee, that the famine and peſtilence moſt commonly follow war: for the abundance

of all things being waſted, want of victuals muſt needes follow, wherupon many diſeaſes doe growe. Briefly it bringeth nothing with it, but a heape of miſeries, and eaſily draweth and allureth the violence and euill diſpoſitiō of many, to follow the eſtate of time: for they that deſire a chaunge, are very glad of ſuch an occaſion, to ground their platformes vpon, which they could not do in time of peace, becauſe men are then of better iudgement and affection, as well in publike, as alſo in priuate matters. It was for theſe conſiderations, that Phocion the great Captaine of the Athenians laboured to ſtoppe the warre, which the people of Athens determined to make againſt

the Macedonians, at the perſwaſion of Leoſthenes: and being demāded, whē would he counſaile the Athenians to warre? When I ſee (quoth he) that the yoong men are fully reſolued to leaue their riot, that rich men contribute money willingly, and Orators abſtaine from robbing the Common welth. Neuertheles, the crime was leuied againſt his counſell: and many wondring at the greatnes and beauty thereof, asked him, how hee liked that preparation. It is faire for one brunt, ſaid Phocion: but I feare the returne and continuance of the warre, becauſe I doe perceyue, that the city hath no other meanes to get money, or other furniture, or men of warre beſides thoſe.

And his foreſight was approued by the euent: for although Leoſthenes proſpered in the beginning of his enterpriſe, (wherupon Phocion being demaūded, whether hee would not gladly haue done al thoſe great and excellent things, anſwered that he would, but not haue omitted that counſell which he gaue) yet in the end hee was ſlaine in the voyage, the Grecian army ouerthrowne by Antipater &amp; Crateres too Macedonians, and the city of Athens brought to that extremity, that it was conſtrained to ſend a blanke for capitulatiō of peace, &amp; to receiue within it a garriſon of ſtrangers. Thus it falleth out cōmonly to thoſe, that ſeeke for warre by al means, either

by right or by wrong.
            1 Warre ſhould be conſiderately begū, but ſpeedily ended.
            2 The euents of warre are doubtfull, but the dammage certaine.
            3 Warre by might maketh his anceſtors whō he pleſeth.
            4 Where there is confuſion, there is diuiſion, &amp; both are the procurers of warre.
         
         
            A Concluſion to the Magiſtrates. Cap. 46.
            TO further the gouernmēt of a cōmon welth, many prouiſoes may be inuented, which muſt be aſwell noted to the ſimple, as to the careful magiſtrate, vpon whō relieth the charge hereof, not applying himſelfe outwardly to

that which his conſcience inwardly reprooueth, leſt hee ſhould be ſaid, wilfully to reſiſt the lawe of God. What greater felicity can happen to any earthly wight, when hee is by the higheſt Father preſſed with care of ciuil regiment, that wholy dependeth vpon vertue, and onely for the accōpliſhment therof is put in vre, then as beyng ſurcharged with this great burden, or ouerladen with it, to find a comfort to mitigate his diſtreſſe, tempered with a mild medicine of hope, that rooteth out the cākred fleſh of deſpaire, with the plaſter of truſt? In this forme of gouernment, &amp; in the flooriſhing ſtate of all people, by the reforming of all degrees, it is good to ſtrike the ſtith whilſt

the yron is hote, and amend al faults while they are green and freſh, which may not be but by the ſeruitude of laws; &amp; alſo to prouide, that in all points, the common ſort bee tractable and obedient, and the magiſtrates diligent and careful to rule, as conſcience and duty bindeth thē: which being once ſtained with iniuſtice, is alwaies tied with a guilty remorſe. Otherwiſe if they practiſe diſcreetly &amp; reuerently thoſe things that are godly and lawfull, that their conſciences may bee cleere, and others by their doings not offended, then it may bee ſaid generally, as it was of the great king of Muſcouy, (who was thought to controll all the Monarches of the world, hauing gotten

ſuch authority ouer his owne ſubiects, as well eccleſiaſticall as ſecular, to whome it was lawfull to diſpoſe, as it were, at his pleaſure, of their liues and goods: no man being willing to gaineſay him, they alſo confeſſing publikly &amp; openly his imperiall regiment, alledging withall, that the will of their Prince was the will of God, and all what ſoeuer he did, they acknowledging it to bee done by diuine prouidence. Hee is (ſaid they) The porter of Paradiſe, The chamberlain of God, and the executor of his will. By which meanes he grewe ſo mighty within a litle while, that all his neighbours, which were the Tartarians, Sueuians, yea and the Turks themſelues, canoniz'd

him. Where ſuch loue and obediēce is wrought in ſubiects towardes their ſoueraigne, and of the ſoueraigne towards his ſubiects, there ſhall vertue enioy her freedome, and poſſeſſe her priuiledge by the rights of law, &amp; all the people ſhall flouriſh with equity: Iuſtice ſhall maintaine peace, peace ſhall procure ſecurity, ſecurity ſhall nouriſh wealth, wealth felicity. Where want hereof breedes a flatte denial or not like ſufficiency to all, in reſpect of this defect, let none be diſmaied, at his ſmall talent, or grudge at an others greater proſperity: for without doubt, nature hath by her ſecrete motion, denied none ſome perfect quality to ſupply that want, which in

himſelfe breedes diſcontent or miſlike: for euē as the fiſh hauing no eares, hath moſt cleere eyes, ſo though want of dignity bee a diſgrace to ſome, though want of coyne diſcontent diuers, &amp; though lacke of wealth impaires the credite of many, yet nature hath ſupplied that outward ornamēt, with ſuch an internall guerdon, as a loyall and a louing heart guided with conſtancy, willingly dyeth for the good of the common wealth, or ſpendeth all his time in the procuring of the ſecurity thereof. But on the contrariſide, if the communalties continue rude, &amp; ſtifnecked in behauiour, reclaiming againſt the precepts of vertue; or if officers or magiſtrates ſecurely neglect the

execution of lawes: then will the want of gouernment breed licētious liberty, liberty procure opē wrong, wrōg doing eſcape ſcotfree: wherby the people, as taking hart at graſſe, are encouraged vnto laſciuious lewdnes, &amp; the moſt part ſhall be oppreſſed with violēce, by lawleſſe practiſes, robberies, &amp; intolerable oppreſsions; &amp; the ſilly ſimple ſhall be quelled with extremities, and preſſed with open wrōgs, &amp; the chiefeſt of all ſhall enioy ſecurely neyther life, nor goods, to the great diſhonour of officers, and vtter diſparagement and ſcandall of the Common wealth.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

