
   
      
         
            The most pleasant historie of Ornatus and Artesia Wherein is contained the vniust raigne of Thaeon King of Phrygia. Who with his sonne Lenon, (intending Ornatus death,) right heire to the crowne, was afterwardes slaine by his owne seruants, and Ornatus after many extreame miseries, crowned King.
            Ornatus and Artesia.
            Ford, Emanuel.
         
         
            
               1607
            
         
         Approx. 297 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01062
            STC 11169
            ESTC S113739
            99848970
            99848970
            14095
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01062)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14095)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1518:09)
         
         
            
               
                  The most pleasant historie of Ornatus and Artesia Wherein is contained the vniust raigne of Thaeon King of Phrygia. Who with his sonne Lenon, (intending Ornatus death,) right heire to the crowne, was afterwardes slaine by his owne seruants, and Ornatus after many extreame miseries, crowned King.
                  Ornatus and Artesia.
                  Ford, Emanuel.
               
               [136] p.   
               
                  Printed by Thomas Creede,
                  London :
                  1607.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Emanuell Ford.
                  The first leaf is possibly blank.
                  Running title reads: The historie of Ornatus and Artesia.
                  Signatures: A-R⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Romances, English --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-02
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2004-02
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE MOST PLEASANT Historie of Ornatus and Artesia. Wherein is contained the vniust Raigne of Thaeon King of Phrygia. Who with his sonne Lenon, (intending Ornatus death,) right Heire to the Crowne, was afterwardes slaine by his owne Seruants, and Ornatus after many extreame miseries, Crowned King.
            LONDON Printed by Thomas Creede. 1607.
         
         
            
            
            To the right vvorshipfull, Brian Stapleton of Carleton, in the Countie of Yorke Esquire, the heauens graunt health, content, and after life, euerlasting happinesse.
            
               THis vnpollisht Historie Right worshipfull, wanting the Ornament of Eloquence fit for rare inuention, presenteth it selfe in his naturall and selfe expressing forme, in well applied words, not in tedious borrowed phrases: wherein neither the lewde can finde examples to sute their dispositions, the vertuous no tearmes to discontent them, nor the well affected any cause of offence. Here shall you see lust Tyrannizing, auarice, guilty of murther, &amp; dignity, seeking his content with vsurpation, yet all subuerted by vertue. Which I am bold to present vnto you, not for the woorth, but to expresse my good will, which is not vnmindfull in some sort to gratifie the manifold curtesies I haue receiued of you. And although it be altogither not worth estimation, and to be accounted no requitall for so many good turnes, yet I desire you to accept the same in steed of a better, and the summe of that which my abilitie at this time can affoord: Which beeing but a fancie, vouchsafe to esteem, though not agreeing with your grauitie, yet (as many both Noble and wise in such like matters haue done) to be red for recreation. As the value of the gift expresseth not the affection of the giuer, nor the outward show the inward meaning, so I trust you will esteeme my good wil, not

by the worthinesse hereof, but the qualitie of my well affected intent, which is deuoted vnto you in the bands of perfect good will, and will be readie to shewe it selfe constant in any triall you shall make thereof. And for that I know your wisedome and curtesie to be such, as that you wil not misconceiue me, but esteeme well hereof, and my affection to you, to bee exprest in the dedicatiō, I haue aduētured to dedicate the same to your protection, though altogither vndeseruing the title of your patronage, which your further kindnesse shall binde me hereafter to requite the same, with some worthier worke collected by my labors. Thus being loth to be tedious and troublesome vnto you, I commit this silly present to your gentle acceptation, and your selfe, to the gratious protection of the Almightie.
            
               
                  Your Worships most readie at commaund, Emanuell Ford.
            
         
         
            
            TH
                  •
                EPISTLE to the Reader.
            
               GEntlemen, I haue published this Hystorie, at the intreaty of some of my familiar friends, beeing at the first collected with no intent to haue it printed, for as yet hauing taken but one flight, I durst not too boldely venture againe, lest my vnskilfulnesse might cause my repentance. But beeing supported by the assistance of your gentle fauours, I shall grow hardie, &amp; hereafter labour to procure your further delight: the rewarde I expect, beeing your kinde acceptance. But if contrary to my thought, this my summer fruite be gathered before it be ripe, I promise amends with olde fruite, that hath bene a yeare in ripening, and in the beginning of the next winter comming forth. In the meane time, peruse this Historie, which sauoureth more of pleasure, then Eloquence: &amp; although hastily compiled, yet let it pas
                  •
               e vnder your fauourable censure: and by your courtesies, be shrowded from the variable dislikes of Momu
                     •
                  
                vaine imitators.
            The learned, wise, and curteous, will according to the qualitie of their dispositions, esteeme well of this vnwoorthie worke, valuing the same, not by the worth, but by the will of the wryter.
            As for such as either rashly condemne without iudgement, or lauishly dislike without aduice, I esteeme them like the downe of Thistles, inconstantly dispearst with euery blast, accounting their discontent, my content: not caring for to please those that are pleased with nothing.
            But did my gaines, counteruaile my labours, I would then frame my fancie to sit their humours, but getting nothing, I can loose no lesse, onely to haue a good opinion of the well affected to learning, is all I craue: and that I hope your good mindes will affoord.
            
               As at a Banquet there are seuerall kindes of meates, some pleasant, other sharpe, yet all tasted. Amongst Grapes, some sowre, some sweete, yet all esteemed, so with indifferencie, amongst varietie of eloquent Histories, let this serue as one dish to furnish out a Banquet, and like sowre and sweete intermingled, make a pleasant taste, by your courteous construing of my good meaning, and your fauourable opinion of Ornatus loue. So shall I account my debt to you great, my labours wel bestowed, and my selfe bound to requite your kindnesse. You shall shewe your affection to learning, vertue in fauouring good indeuours, &amp; giue incouragement to mor
                  •
                worthie labours. I rest well contented, my reward rich, and hereafter be both readie and willing to deserue your curtesie. But if Ornatus loue breede my blame, as it bred his banishment, then may I wish I had neuer knowne thereof, and crie out of Mala fortuna, as my reward. With the bird Cel
                     •
                  s bred in Affrica, who wandring far from her nest, by forgetfulnesse cannot return: and so for euer after abandoneth company. So I too boldly building on your curtesie, may bee wounded with repentance, and by my ouersight bee brought in dispaire, vnlesse your curtesie preuent the same: on which my hopes depend. And so I cease.
            
               E. Ford.
            
         
      
      
         
            THE MOST PLEAsant Historie of Ornatus and Artesia.
         
            Chap. 1. How Ornatus was enamoured of the faire Artesia.
            
            
               IN the rich and renowmed countrey of Phrygia, in Prouinces not farre distant from néere neighbourhood, dwelt two auncient Knightes, the one named Allinus, the other Arbastus, men of great possessions, and much honoured. Betwixt whome, such extreame contention and hatred remained, by reason of the death of one Renō, brother to Allinus, long since slaine in a quarell by certaine gentlemen belonging to Arbastus, that neither their owne wisdome, nor the sundry perswasions of friendes to eyther partie allied, were of any force to mittigate the same. Both of them being inriched with innumerable blessings, especially in their faire progenie.
            
               Allinus hauing a sonne of goodly stature, and commendabl
                  •
                gifts, named Ornatus. And Arbastus a daughter called Artesia, of excéeding comelinesse, exterierlie beautified with aboundance of gyfts of nature, and inwardly a
                  •
               orned with aboundance of diuine perfections. Yet by reason of their parents discord, they remayned

as farre ignorant in knowledge one of the other, as if they had bin separated by an innumerable distance of straunge countries.
            
               Ornatus aboue all thinges delighted in Hawking, and on a day, being wearie, he wandred without company with his hawke on his fist, into a most pleasant valley, where hée shrowded himselfe vnder the shaddowe of a tuft of greene trees, with purpose to rest himselfe, and euen when his eyes were readie to yeelde to slumber, hée was reuiued from his drowsinesse, by the noyse of a kennell of hounds that past by him in chase of a Stagge, after whome Arbastus and diuers in his company (though to him vnknowne) followed, who being passed by whilest he was in a deepe studie to thinke what they should be, he espied a beautifull damsell entring the same valley▪ who being somewhat wearie, liking the prospect of that shadie tuft of trees, alighted there, which Ornatus seeing, withdrew himselfe from her sight, whilest shée tying her steed to a bush▪ laide her dilicate bodie downe vpon the cooling earth, to breathe her selfe, and drie vp her swet, which the sooner to accomplish, shée vnbraced her garmēts, and with a decēt and comely behauiour, discouered her milke-white necke &amp; brest, beautified with two round precious teats, to receiue the breath of the coole winde, which was affected with a delight to exhale the moystened vapors from her pure bodie. Ornatus seeing all, and vnséene himselfe, noted with delight each perfect linament of her proper bodie, beautie, sweete fauour▪ and other comelinesse, which filled his heart with excéeding pleasure, therewith growing into an vnrestrained aff
                  •
               ction towards her, and a great studie what shee should be, when suddainly his hawke féeling his fist vnmoouable, thinking to pearch herself with quiet, primde her self, and with the noyse of her belles, made Ar
                     ••
                  sia start, who as one halfe agast, with a fearefull behauior arose frō the ground, looking round about her from whence that sound came, she espied Ornatus (who vnwilling she shuld perceiue he had yet seene her, laie as if hée had slept) Artesia maruelling what he should be, &amp; accordingly thinging he had slept, closed her naked brest with great haste, and

vnloosing her horse, thought to go away vnespied. Which Ornatus perceiuing, and vnwilling without speaking to her to loose her sight, séemed to awake, and raising himselfe▪ stedfestly beheld her, which infused such a redde vermillion blush into her bewtifull chéekes, and withall such a bashfull confusion spred it selfe in her conceits, that shee stood like one halfe amazed or ashamed.
            Which Ornatus perceiuing, drew towards her, and gréeted her with these spéeches. Faire Damosel, be not abasht with my presence, though a straunger, which shall no way if I can chuse offend you, but rather commaund mee, and I wil be readie to doo you any seruice. Artesia notwithstanding his speeches, withdrew her selfe, leading her horse to a banke, where with ease shée mounted, and so rode away, not giuing him any aunswere at all. Ornatus maruelled thereat, yet rightly imputed her vnkinde departure to her feare, not discurtesie. And seeing himselfe depriued of her sight, the night approching, departed home to his fathers house. After supper, betaking himselfe to his chamber with intent to rest, he was possessed with such remembrance of the bewtifull Damosell he had seene, that his sleepe was transformed into continuall cogitations of her bewtie, forme and fauour, and the pleasing sight he had seene in the discouery of some of her hidden bewties, imprinted such a delight in his aff
                  •
               ctionate conceits, that hée could take no sleepe, but continued all that night in those meditations.
            The next day thinking to shake off all further remembrance of her, he gate into company of his most chosen friends, wherein before time hée tooke most delight, yet nowe by reason of his distemperature, hee rather seemed weary thereof. Hee had not continued long with them, but he was saluted by a gentleman named Phylastes, with whome he was familiarly acquainted: this gentleman belonged to an auncient Duke named Turnus, who in honour of his birth day, from which Allinus excused himselfe of purpose, because he thought hée should méete Arbastus there, but because the Duke should take no offence at him, hee graunted that his sonne Ornatus should goe to doe him honour.

Which Phylastes acquainted Ornatus withall, who glad therof, departed thither in companie of diuers other gentlemen: the Duke likewise had sent another messenger to request Arbastus cōpany, who being of a more m
                  •
               de nature then Allinus, willingly went, and with him, his L
                  •
               dy, and faire daughter Artesia.
            
         
         
            CHAP. II. How Ornatus came to knowledge of Artesia, &amp; intreated Adellena to make knowne his loue to her, and of the rebuke Artesia gaue her.
            
               AFter the feast was ended, and the Duke had honored his guests with all manner of curtes
                  •
               ie, he &amp; the principallest, amongst whom Arbastus was one of the chiefe, according to the custome vsed in ye countrey, seated themselues to behold certaine games and exercises to be performed by the young Gentlemen: which was, rūning, wrastling, and diuers other exercises, for triall of the strength, and nimblenesse of the bodie: amongst the rest, Ornatus (hauing neuer before made triall of himselfe) had such good successe, and behaued himselfe with such agilitie and strength, that he woonne the chiefest honour, and was presented before the Duke, to receiue a rich reward.
            Which when hée had receiued, casting his eyes vpon the beholders, hée espied Artesia whome hée perfectly knewe againe, 
                  •
               eadie to depart with her parents, who had bidden the Duke farewell. Ornatus comming to Philastes, asked if he knew that damosell, shewing him Artesia, who tolde him what shée was. Ornatus was glad of that small knowledge, which could add
                  •
                litle meanes to his hopes, yet somewhat discontented that shée was daughter to Arbastus. And thus the day being ended, euery one departed to their abodes.
            
               Ornatus hauing againe attained his chamber; spent his time of rest in sundrie cogitations of his loue, and howe to giue her

knowl
                  •
               dge of his affection, noting euery daunger, and pondering how discontentedly his parents would take the same, if it should by any meanes come to theyr knowledge, finding so many le
                  •
               tes to hinder him, that hée was oftentimes in vtter dispaire of attaining to the least hope of good successe. But finding his affections to increase more and more, and burning with a feruent desire, which nothing but onely her sauour could extinguish.
            After that night was past, earelie the next morning hée wandred towardes the place where hée hadde behelde her with such exceeding content, and by the way as hée went, hée met with a gentlewoman named Adellena, of meane birth, and small liuing, yet of good education, who oftentimes resorted to Arbastus house, and was going thither at that instant, into whose company hee insinuated himselfe, for that hée sawe her alone, and said as followeth.
            Gentlewoman, I am bolde to intreat a word or two with you. Sir replied she, with a good will, I will satisfie you in what I can. Know you not (quoth he) Arbastus? I do quoth she, both know him, and am very well acquainted with him, vnto whose house I am nowe going. So woulde I quoth hée if I durst, for I serue Ornatus, sonne to Allinus, whome I doo not doubt but you know well, of whom I would tell you more, but that I feare to commit his secrets to them I knowe not, and thereby vnwillingly doe him iniurie: but woulde you vouchsafe but to heare them, kéepe them secret, and withall adde your help
                  •
                to further him, which you may with safetie performe, you shoulde doo him an excéneding pleasure, and withall, bee so highly rewarded, and thankefully gratified, that you shoulde thinke your labour very well imployed: doo a béede of pittie, and binde him to you in the perpetuall bands of kinde friendship.
            Sir replied Adellena, I knowe not 
                  •
               he Gentleman, yet I haue heard him much commended, in whome if I coulde any way pleasure, I woulde vse both diligence and secrecie, promising you vpon my saith and credit, if you

will make mée acquainted with your minde, I will either doo my good will to further him, or else conceale what you shall commit to my priuitie.
            Then said hée, my maister not long since walking in yonder valley, beheld Artesia, faire Artesia, daughter to Arbastus, to whose beawtie hée is exceedingly inth
                  •
               alled, that vnlesse some meanes of comfort be found to ease his torments, I feare mée it will in daunger his life: whom you onely may pleasure, by making his loue knowne to her, in such sort as shall best agrée with your wisedome. This is all, and yet so much, that the reuealing thereof may doo much harme. And to effect such a contract, might procure peace and vnitie 
                  •
               wixt their parents. Therefore I intreate your aide and furtherance herein: with which good newes, if I returne to him, I knowe it will bréed no little comfort to his disquiet heart.
            Sir (said shée) since I perceiue his loue is grounded vpon vertue, not drawne thereto by any desire of reward, I vndertake to bée his assistant therein, and will to the vttermost of my best indeuours labour to procure his content: Which this day I will in some sort put in execution. And if you returne to mée to morrow, you shall knowe her answere. I wil said he, and so they departed. Ornatus hauing left her, entered into many cogitations of his rash attempt, accounting himselfe ouer credulous to commit his secrets to her priuitie, of whose fidelitie hee had neuer made tryall: sometimes comforting himselfe with hope of good euent, and againe dispairing of comfort, for that hée supposed Artesia would rather esteeme him as an enemie then a friend, by reason of their parents hatred, and therefore would the more hardly bee drawne to giue any credit to his sute. And reuoluing a chaos of these and such like confused cogitations, he attained his fathers house, thinking the time tedious vntill his appointed méeting with Adellena; which hée ouerpast with great care. Adellena after her departure from him, soone attained to Arbastus house, vsing her selfe as shee had formerly done, yet withall, carefull how to execute the charge shée had in hand, which shee could by no occasion vtter,

till after dinner when shée found Artesia all alone in the gardein, insinuated her self into her company, which Artesia kindly accepted, entring into varietie of discourses, and continuing some time in giuing certaine hearbes their proper names: amongst the rest, Artesia espied an hearbe with partie coloured leaues, demanding of Adellena if shee knewe the name thereof, which she told her she did not. I haue oftentimes quoth Artesia seene this hearbe, and it hath two prettie names, it is by some called Loue in Idlenesse, and by some Haris Case: with that Adellena fetcht a déepe (thogh counterfeit) sigh, which Artesia noting, said: What maketh you sigh to heare it named Haris Case? Mary (quoth shée) one way because those two names so all agrée, an other, for by the same I call to remembrance the hearts griefe I heard a young man complaine of procured by loue, which was not in idlenesse, but I think in good earnest. Why quoth Artesia, can loue procure such hartes griefe to any, and not rather content? Yea said shee, because the partie in loue, hath no hope to attaine the good liking of the partie be loueth. Thē quoth Artesia, I account him a foole that will loue so deeply without hope of reward: and that to bée rather fondnesse then true friendship, that pleaseth his affections with such inequalities. But I pray tel mée what is he into whose secrets you were so suddenly admitted? Not admitted (quoth she) for vnawares I heard his complaints, which afterwardes I promised him not to make any acquainted withall, but the partie whome he so in
                  •
               ierly loueth. Then quoth Artesia, I may not know, neither doo I care, for it is but a vanitie that troubleth ones cogitations. Yes quoth shée, you may and shall if you please, know who he is, conditionally you will neither be offended with me for telling you, nor reueale what I shall impart. Why quoth she, am I the pretie, or doth it any way concerne me, that I should be offended? If it be, then kéepe your counsels vnreuealed, for it will proue vnsauorie to my stomacke, for be it far from me to be troubled with the vaine sutes of doting louers. Yet let me answere quoth Adellena, you heare too greeuous a conceit of loue, which is the diuine puritie whereby heartes are vnited in vertue. Wit
                  •
               out the which, neither mortals can attaine heauen, nor other creatures haue their being:

therefore not to bée abhorred: and for that any shoulde loue your selfe, can that be an offence to you, but rather bée accepted in kinde sort? wée should by nature loue them that loue vs, then will you contrarie to nature, yéeld hatred for loue? For you indéed are the partie that is beloued, and the partie that is so farre in loue with you euery way to be commended, &amp; one way discōmended, whose name I will not reueale, &amp; then I hope I shall bréed no offence to your eares. Doe so quoth Artesia, for in concealing the same, you please me, &amp; if you will be welcome into my cōpany, vse no more of these speeches. Had I thought quoth she, they would haue bin offē
               sius, I would not haue vttered them, but in so doing, I did but fulfill your request: then at my request againe quoth shée, giue ouer. After this communication ended, they parted, Adellena, home to to her house, and Artesia to her supper, and afterwards to her chamber, where at first, some colde thoughts of those spéeches past in her fancie, but afterwards shée spent the rest of that night in quiet sléepe.
         
         
            CHAP. III. How Adellena cōueled Ornatus letter into Artesias Casket, and with what impatiencie Artesia tooke the same.
            
               THe morning being newly approched, Ornatus who had long expected the same, arose and soone gate to Adellenas house, where he arriued before shée was vp, who hauing knowledge thereof, soone came downe to him, (taking him to bée no other then Ornatus man) to whome shée declared the very truth of all her spéeches hadde with Artesia. Which nipt him at the heart, but being put in some hope by her perswasions, at last giuing her a purse full fraught with Gold in recompence of her paines past, and to entice her to vndertake more, hee saide as followeth.
            Good Adellena be not dismaied to prosecute my sute for Artesias first frowne, for I am not Ornatus man, but poore Ornatu
                     •
                  
               
               
himselfe, that languish with desire to attaine her loue, which I would my selfe prosecute, if the discords betwixt our parents did not hinder the same. Therefore I beséech you once againe doo something in my behalfe, for you sée how cruell desteny hath shut mée from all meanes to bée put in practise by my selfe, and you may pleasure mée without any hazard at all: for which I wil rest so thankfull vnto you, as that you shall account your paines taken wel bestowed.
            Sir replied shée, I would vndertake any thing to further you, if I kn
                  •
               w which way, but I perceiue Artesias frowardnesse is such, that nothing I shal bring her wil bée welcome: but if you wil aduise mée what I shal do, I wil once againe hazard the losse of her good liking for your sake. Which said, Ornatus wrote a Letter, which hée desired her by some meanes to conuey to her sight, the contents whereof were these.
            
               
                  To the faire Artesia.
                  
                  FAirest of creatures, bee not offended with my boldnesse, but rather fauourably censure of my good meaning: for being bound to honour none but most vertuous, I thought it my dutie to giue you knowledge thereof, desiring you to pittie the extremitie of my passions, procured by the attainture of your conquering perfections. I confesse you may alledge many things as reasons, to disswade you from giuing credit to my speeches, or yeelding me the least fauour in your conceits: yet I beseeeh you, make but triall of loyaltie, loue, and dutie, so farre as shall agree with your liking, and you shall finde mee constant in the one, and perseuerant in the other, as one that hath submitted himselfe to your commaund, vowed his deuotions to purchase your fauour, and euerlastingly bound himselfe to be onely yours: vnable to expresse my humble meaning: vnwilling to be offensiue, and desirous of fauour: then I beseech you be fauourable to me, though bearing the name of an enemie, in whom you shall finde the true heart of a

constant friend, whose safetie, comfort, and preseruation, resteth in your power. The first viewe of your bewties (which was in the valley when you were last hunting) surprised my heart with such humble regard to your vertue, that euer since my heart hath indured the bitter torments of feareful dispaire, which vrgeth me to this presumption, desiring from your sacred lippes to receiue my sentence of comfort, or affliction, rather then to spend my life in languishing vnreuealed torment. Then be you gracious to him, that is otherwise most miserable, and shewe fauour to an vndeseruing vnknowne friend, so shall you not onely shewe that you are mercifull, but also saue a miserable louer from vtter ruine.
                  
                     
                        Your humble friend Ornatus.
                  
               
            
            
               Adellena hauing receiued this Letter, tolde him shée would deliuer the same, which the next day shée performed in this sort: Being come to Arbastus house, shée continued most part of the day in Artesias company, not once renuing the least remembrance of the talke shée had with her the day before, but espying her open her Casket wherein shée put her workes, whilest Artesia was busie, she priuily conueyed the Letter vnseene into the same, which by and by Artesia locked, for none but her selfe had the vse thereof.
            
               Adellena thought long till she was gone fearing least Artesia should vpon some occasion open the Casket againe, and so find the Letter, whilest shée were there, therefore shée soone founde meanes to depart. When the time of rest was come, and Artesia alone in her bed, taking a booke (according to her vsuall manner) to reade a while, shee suddenly fell a sléepe, and in her sléepe was possessed with a dreame, wherein her thoughts called to remembrance Adellenas speeches, which mooued such a disquiet conceit of anger in her brest, that thinking shée had chid her, with the motions of her spirites shée awaked, féeling and excéeding distemperature

in all her parts, and séeing the light stil burning, she maruelled at her drowsinesse that had before forgate to put the same out, and by this meanes called to remembrance Adellenas spéeches, maruelling what hee should bee that was in loue with her, and suddenly againe, reprouing her selfe for giuing her mind libertie to think of loue, she would haue banisht al further remembrance thereof out of her minde, but the more shee laboured, the more vnable shee was to preuaile in ouermaistring her fancies, that being both vexed with her selfe, and Adellena, shee vttered these speeches.
            What disquiet is this possesseth my heart, procureth such vnwonted cogitations to rise in my fancies, and disturbeth my rest? I was not wont to trouble my thoughts with such vaine cogitations, which the more I labour to suppresse, the more they encrease.
            Coulde Adellenas speeches haue such force (which I had welnigh forgotten) as thus long to sticke in my remembrance? Or what reason haue I to regard them that were not worth the regarding? but rather tended to demonstrate the affection of some ouerfond louer, that se
                  •
               keth to intrappe my chastitie? Accursed be her lippes for vttering them, and would to God I had bene deaffe that I might not haue heard their inchaunting sound.
            This saide, she catcht vp her Booke, thinking by reading to driue away all remembrance thereof, but her heart was so fully possest with a kinde of cogitation what hée shoulde be, that she neither coulde reade, or when she did reade, remember what shee did reade: and finding this meanes not auaileable, shée started from her bedde, opening her Casket to take out her sampler, wherein shée tooke most delight, when suddenly shée espied the Letter, and reading the superscription, was halfe astonished thereat, especially howe it should come there, and what the contents should bée, béeing oftentimes in minde to teare the same in péeces and not to reade it, which her hearte woulde not suffer her to doo before shée had séene what was the contents: yet striuing to ouermaister her affections, shée tore the same

in the midst: which done, such a remorse rose in her fancie, vnited with a desire to know further thereof, that leaping into the bed, shée closed the same togither, and betwixt a willing and vnwilling minde, redde the same throughout. With that, fetching a déepe sigh, shee said: Aye me poore soule, how are my affections betraied to mine enemie? Was it Ornatus shée ment? can it bée that hée wil proue my friend, that is my professed enemie? O no: hée intendeth nothing lesse then loue, but rather vnder colour thereof, séeketh my ruine. Was it hée that I beheld in the valley? or it is possible that hée shoulde bée so déepely in loue with mée vpon that small sight? No, no, I wil not credit his spéeches, but stil repute him as an enemie, as indéed hée is: and henceforward abandon Adellenaes company, by whose meanes this Letter was conueyed into my Casket: then tearing the same into a thousand péeces, shée abstained (so neare as shée could) from all thought of yeelding the least consent to loue, and sought to increase her disdaine, and suspect of his falshood, spending the rest of that night in cōfused contrarieties of doubtful thoughts. Early in the morning shee gat vp, and within short time met with Adellena (who was come as desirous to know what issue her deuise had taken) and 
                  ••
               ading occasion fitte when none was by, she vttered these spéeches.
            
               Adellena, I maruell what follie ruleth your minde, that you (whom I had thought had bene vertuously giuen) should séeke my ruine: wherein haue I showne my selfe so vnkinde, that you should requite me in this discourteous sort? You remember the spéeches past betwixt vs the other day in the Gardein, when I finding out your intent by your spéeches, desired you to giue ouer to vse any more talke to that effect, which you faithfully promised, but now most vnfaithfully haue broken, and more impudently haue betraied my quiet with your disquiet &amp; ill sounding news: if your rudenesse had beene such that you could not desist, you might then haue deliuered Ornatus false and fained inchauntment into my hands, and not so secretly haue conueyed the same into my Casket, wherein you haue made me amendes for my

loue, to séeke to betray my life into the hands of mine enemy: for otherwise I neither can nor will estéeme him. Therefore henceforwards come no more into my co
                  •
               pany, for I forsweare your familiaritie, hate your counsell, and wil cause my father to banish you his house, and alienate his friendship from you for euer.
            
               Adellena would haue answered, but Artesia refusing to hear her, departed, and left her so much gréeued, that for extream vexation, she immediately departed towards her owne house.
         
         
            CHAP. IIII. How Ornatus dispairing, left his fathers house, and disguising himselfe, was entertained of Arbastus.
            
            
               
                  ORnatus desirous to heare how Artesia had accepted his Letter, came to Adellenaes house, and found her wéeping for anger, desiring to know the cause thereof, which shée declared to him at large, which wrought suche an excéeding passion of griefe in his mind, that without yéelding her either thāks for her paines or other spéech, hée departed: being so much ouercome with inward sorrow, that finding a solitarie place, hée laide himselfe downe vpon the earth, vttering these lamentations.
            O miserable castiffe, what haste thou to do but lament when thy ill fortune yéelds nothing but cause of lament? Why shoulde thy life last to endure these tormentes, and not rather to dissolue into vnséene essences? Could any thing haue happened to mée more miserable, then to beholde Artesia, and now to endure her crueltie? or more fortunate, if shée had bene mercifull? But my Destenies haue drawne mée to like her that hateth mée, and to become thrall to a cruell vnrelenting enemie. Well, my loue is swéeter then my life, and therefore I wil venture life and all to purchase her liking.
            Hauing said this, hée a while sat silent, when suddeinly to fauour

his extremities, hée behelde certaine of his familiars passe by, with whome he departed home.
            Earely the next morning (being excéedingly troubled in minde and impatient of delaie) hee l
                  •
               st his fathers house to visite Adellena againe, whome hée had the day before left so vnkindly, whome hee founde readie to goe to Arbastus house againe: saluting her, saide: Adellena, bée not offended at my last vnmannerly departure, for my hearte was so muche disquietted at the ill successe my sute tooke, that I coulde not vse that behauiour towardes you your paines deserued, but nowe I am returned to craue your counsell what is further to bée done herein.
            Syr replied shée, I know not what further meanes to vse, neither dare I any more attempt to trie Artesias curtesie, who is alreadie so much offended with me, that I feare to loose her friendship for euer, if I should vtter that againe that is so vnwelcome to her.
            
               Ornatus hearing her spéeches, thought shée was vnwilling to prosecute his sute any further, with a heauie hearte left her, entering into many thoughtes and cogitations which way to comfort himselfe. Oftentimes vtterly dispairing, and yet purposing to leaue no meanes vnassaied, nor daunger vnattempted, though with hazarde of his life to purchase some rest to his troubled heart.
            At length hée thought with himselfe what should make Artesia so hard hearted as to giue no credit to my spéeches: it is not her want of lenitie, pittie, or wisedome, for shée is yong, and therefore subiect to loue: bewtifull, and therefore to bée wonne wise, and therefore wil with consideration pittie my sorrowes. What then should alienate her good liking from mee, more then from an other? My Name: for by that shée reputeth mée an enemie: then were I not Ornatus, she woulde peraduenture giue some regard to my sutes. Therefore I will chaunge my name, and bée an other then I am, that shée not knowing mée, may (if not loue mée) yet disist to hate mée: then beganne hee to studie

what meanes to vse to enioy her sight (without the which hée could not liue,) and yet not be knowne what he was. Amongst many other deuises, this tooke déepest roote. Within fewe dayes after (hauing prouided all things necessary) he attired himselfe like a virgine of a straunge Countrey (which hée might well be esteemed to be by his youth.) And taking with him his Lute, whereon he could play excéedingly well, in the silent of the night he departed towards the sea coast, which was neare vnto Arbastus house: and seating himselfe vpon the Rockie shoare, beganne to play vpon his Lute. Early the next morning, a shepheard happened to passe by that way, and espying his straunge disguise, and hearing his swéete Musicke, was so excéedingly delighted therewith, that he stayed to sée what he was.
            
               Ornatus turning himselfe about, espied the olde man stand gazing vpon him, wherewith he drew towardes him, and saide as followeth.
            Good Father, muse not to sée me in this vnfrequented place, being by shipwrack cast on this shore, and preserued from a gréeuous death by sea, to perish for want of comfort on the land, in a straunge place, where I neither haue friendes, nor know which way to get comfort. Therefore I beséech you, yéeld comfort to my distresse, and succour 
                  •
               o my want. Faire Damosell quoth the shepheard, if my homely Cottage can yeeld you any comfort, so please you to accept therof, it shalbe at your command, whither so please you go, without more circumstance of spéeches, you shall be most hartily welcome. I thanke you quoth Ornatus, and I accept your gentle proffer; so they departed togither. And when they were entered, and the sh
                  •
               pheardesse in the best maner she could had welcomed him, and he had tasted of such foode as was set before him, hée tolde them his name was Syluia, and telling a tale of sufficient countenance to beare credite of the maner of their shipwracke, and the cause he vndertooke that voyage by Sea. Which the olde folkes beléeued▪ Likewise framing himselfe to such a kinde of behauiour, that it was almost 
                  •
               mpossible to discerne but that he was a woman indéede.
            
               Where Syluia (for vnder that name he shall a while passe) staied some two daies, yet without any hope how to enioy Artesias company. But the third day it fortuned Arbastas being abroad hunting, was by a violent storme driuen to séeke shelter, and must fortunately lighted on the shepheards Cottage, where he boldly entered without calling, and suddenly espying Syluia, was halfe astonisht to beholde a damosell so bewtifull and richly attired in that homely place, but after that he had a while viewed her well, (Syluia being alone) with a curteous behauiour he thus spake.
            Faire damosell, pardon my boldnesse, if I haue disquietted you, I little thought to haue found such guestes in this homely place. Syluia knowing him to be Arbastus, arose, but made him no answere: when presently the olde shepheard came in, vsing great reuerence to Arbastus, who demaunded of him, what damosell that was, whereupon the olde man declared all that he knew.
            
               Arbastus then thus said: Damosell, I vnderstand by this shepheard some part of your misfortunes, which I so much pitty, that offer to do any thing resteth in me to do you pleasure. And for that this homely place is not agréeable to your birth, which may be greater then I can iudge of, let me desire you to accept of such entertainment as my habitation yéeldeth, whither you shall be welcome. Syluia being glad of that profer, yet fearing to be discouered by his willingnesse to yéeld, made this answere. Sir, this homely place is best agréeing to my poore estate, being by misfortune brought to miserie: which I am also vnworthie of, for that I know not how to make my hoste amends, desiring rather to liue in this quiet pallace voyde of care, then in places of more dignitie: but for that I shall be too chargeable to this poore man, and you so earnestly desire me, I wil be so bolde as to take your profer, though vnable to be so grateful as I would. Many other spéeches past betwixt them, and in the ende they departed towards Arbastus Castle: where Syluia was kindly and worthily entertained, hauing his hearts desire, which was to enioy

the sight of faire Artesi
                     •
                  .
            
            
               Ornatus being alone by himselfe, began to meditate of the good successe he had in this attempt, and how fortunatelie all things had fallen out to further him in his loue. But most of all hée meruailed how the eyes of all that beheld him were blinded, that they could not perceiue what he was. In these &amp; many such like comfortable meditations he spent some thrée or foure dayes, taking most great content in beholding Artesiaes perfections, that he was more and more inthralled in the bands of vowed affection, hearing her spéech, noting her behauior, admiring her vertue, commending her curtesie, affecting her bewtie, and imprinting each liniament of her diuine torme, in his deuoted affection, with such immooueable resolue of constant loyaltie, that hée did not onely loue her, but also honor her as an I doll, beeing by Arbastus admitted her companie, that at all times hée was with her. Artesia likewise tooke no little pleasure in Syluians company, in whom so much curtesse abounded, that euery one both liked and commended her.
         
         
            CHAP. V. How Adellena brought newes to Arbastus house of Ornatus suddaine depature. How he naming himselfe Syluian, a long time enioyed her company, and what successe he had in his loue.
            
               
                  ADellena hauing heard of Ornatus departure from his fathers house, and of the excéeding care and grief his parents tooke, fearing least he might by some trecherie be murdred, with which newes shée came to Arbastus house, and soone published the same, that the newes came to Arbastus hearing who was excéedingly sorie to heare the same, for that hée estéemed well o
                  •
                
               Ornatus. And now comming into the garden where Artesia
               
was walking with Syluian, she could not withhold herselfe from speaking, but vttered her minde in these words.
            
               Artesia bée not offended with that I say, but rather bée displeased with your selfe, who are the originall of this woe. Ornatus whom you supposed your enemie, though indéede your most faithfull friend, taking your vnkind refusall most heauily, and accounting himselfe not worthy to liue if you dispised him, eyther hath wrought his owne vntimely death, or dispairing to finde fauour at your handes, hath abandoned both this parents, countrey and acquaintance, to liue in exile. What will bée sayd of you when the cause of his sorrow
                  •
                shall be knowne? how may your owne concience accuse your selfe of hard-hartednesse, that would not yéeld pittie to the distresse of so woorthie, vertuous, &amp; curteous a Gentlemā, who for his humble sute, was spightfully disdained, and his heartie good will, disdainfully reiected? Which cruell déed of yours, no doubt will be one day repayed with the like disdaine, where you shall most affect. I know his loue was firme, constant and immoueable, which maketh me so much the more pittie his estate: I know his meaning was both vertuous &amp; honorable, his birth you know, what vertues abounded in him, all can witnesse: and how hartily he loued you, the heauēs cā witnesse. Poore Ornatus farewell. Hard was thy hap, to place thy true loue so firmly, where thou reapest so little reward. Artesia hearing her spéeches, could not tell whether shée might blame her, or accuse her selfe, sometimes doubting whether she spake this of pollicie to try her, or of truth. Being as readie to blame her selfe, as Adellena, and yet willing to do neither. For she thought if she spake true, shée had good cause to say that shée did, and her selfe more to be blamed then any. For notwithstanding she had giuen Adellena so flat a denial, yet her conscience knewe, that some sparks of loue were kindled in her breast: That her heart being somewhat opprest with these thoughts, caused the water to stand in her eyes. Ornatus séeing all this, took no little comfort therat, especially whē he perceiued Artesias heart to relent, but for that by his disguise, being known no other then a woman, he kept silence, when saine

hée would haue spake, least he should discouer himselfe. Adellena séeing she had disquieted Artesia, being her selfe full of griefe, and vnwilling to vrge her any further, departed. And Artesia withdrawing her selfe from Syluians company, into an Arbor, vttered these spéeches. And can it be that Ornatus loue was so great, that for my sake hée hath done this? Coulde hee loue her so constantly that was his professed enemie? is loue of such a force, to draw one into these extreames? Then may I compare it to the hearb Artas, found in Persia, who being but holden in the hand, causeth a heat through all the bodie: so loue but entertained in thought, disquieteth all the sences. But why do I conceiue so well of Ornatus, when I know not the truth of Adellenaes report: it may be he hath hired her to doe this, and thereby I may be deceiued, yéelding to pittie, when there is no cause, and with the bird Akanthu
                  •
               , readie to come at euerie call. Admit it were so, I am not bound to fauour him, is he not my enemie, &amp; sonne vnto my fathers cheefest foe? what reason then haue I eyther to giue credit to his loue, or her protestation, when both may be fayned? Well I will be aduised before I yéelde my selfe to loues intangling baytes, and before I loue, I will know whome I loue. I but Artesia thy fancie yéeldeth remorse alreadie, and thy conscience bids thée pittie him because he loueth thée, for loue in a reputed enemie may be as constant and loyall as in an open friend, and an enemie becomming friend, will be the more constant: then what hast thou to do, but make further proofe of his constancie, and finding him true, yéelde reward to his desert? Soft Artesia, wade not too far: if he be constant, if hee be loyall, if he loue thée so intirely, if nowe thou hast made him forsake this countrey, or procure his vntimely death, then is there nothing else to be don for thée, but to pittie his death, and accuse thy selfe of some discourtesie. All this while Ornatus shrowding himselfe from her sight, by the thicknesse of the gréene leaues heard her spéeches, to his excéeding comfort, and againe closelie withdrew himselfe. Artesia hauing ended her spéeches, her hart being opprest with many doubts, arose and came to Syluian, to whom she said: My minde is much troubled with the newes Adellena told me of Ornatus absence, whom for that you know not, I wil tel you what he was.
            
               There dwelleth not far hence, one Allinus, that mortally hateth my father, and al that belong vnto him, whose sonne Ornatus was, whome if I should commend, you might thinke me too cruel to refuse his loue so vnkindly: onely thus much I wil say of him, he was euery way worthy to be beloued, though my fancie coulde neuer be drawne to like of him: who vpon what occasion I know not, but as Adellena tolde me, made his loue knowne to her, which she likewise told me of, but I refusing to heare her, answered her plainly, that I was greatly of
                  •
               ended with her, for making any such motion: and forbad her for euer to speake of him againe. But now this day you haue heard what shée hath told me, which I can hardly beléeue to be true, or that Ornatus would be so rash without wisedome to enter into such extreames. But if it bee so (as I would it were not) it gréeueth me for him, and I wish that I had not refused to heare his sute, though I am not willing to yéeld thereto. For I would not haue it said of me, nor my name so much blazed, that my crueltie procured him to that extremitie, though his wisedome might haue foreséene such mischéefe, and he more moderatelie haue tempered his loue.
            
               Ornatus taking occasiō said, I neither know the gentleman, nor how constant his loue was, but thus much my mind perswadeth me, that had not his loue bene great, he would not haue gréeued so much at your vnkindnesse: but loue is of this force, that it turneth the minde into extreames, or vtterly breaketh the heart, which force belike it had in him, else would he not haue done himselfe so much h
                  •
               rme. But it may be (as you say) Ornatus hath not done himselfe outrage, but onely abandoning company, liueth in dispaire, and so meaneth to die: which if it bee so, then in my fancie, you might do well to let him by some meanes vnderstand that you did pittie him Stay there quoth Artesia, you must first know whether I can do it or no: for If I should say I pittie with my lips, and he not find it so, it would driue him to more dispaire, and therefore I will leaue off to do that, vntill I can finde whether I can do so or no.
            These her spéeches draue Ornatus into a perplexed doubt

what to thinke, being no way assured o
                  •
                her loue, nor yet vtterly dispairing thereof, for that her spéeches gaue likelyhood of both. Therefore hée durst not speake too boldlie, least shée should suspect him, but onely rested in good hope to finde comfort, and by other meanes to trie her.
            Then taking his Lute, he began to play so swéetely, as would haue rauisht a comfortlesse minde, with great content: to heare which harmonie pleased Artesia so well, that when hée left, shée would request him, calling him Syluian, to play againe. Whilest he sat playing, Artesia sitting close by his side, fel fast a sléep, which hee perceiuing, left of his play, to sur
                  •
               et himself with beholding her sweete bewtie, in which hée tooke such delight, as almost rauisht his sences, sometimes thinking whilest she slept, to imprint a kisse vpon her swéete ruddie lippe, but fearing thereby to wake her, and loose that delightfull contemplation, hée desisted, beholding each part of her visible forme, which was most diuine, his minde was affected with inward suppose, what perfections her hidden bewties did comprehend, which his fancie perswaded him, he did in conceit absolutely contemplate. Then seeing her stirre, he suddainly catcht his lute againe, striking his swéete noate, to continue her in that slumber, and then againe, laying by the same, to enter into his former contemplation. Comparing his delight to excéed all heauenly ioy, and wishing though Artesia coulde not loue him, yet that shée woulde alwayes graunt him so to beholde her.
            When hée had a good while continued in these meditations, Artesia awooke, which somewhat gréeued him, but when hée beheld her bewteous eyes fired vppon him, he thought himselfe inriched with a heauenly happines, to whome A
                     •
                  tesia said, I thank thée good Syluian, for thy swéet musicke hath somewhat eased my heart, by this quiet sleepe. O what content do they enioy, that liue voyde of care, and how happie was I before I heard Ornatus name? With that she arose, and ther togither went in: when night approched (which Ornatus thought soo soone come, for by that he must loose Artesiaes sight) euery one betooke themselues

to their seuerall lodgings.
            
               Ornatus studying what meanes to vse to further his loue, wherein he found many difficulties, sometimes in thinking Artesia was in hope neuer to heare of him againe, and sometimes supposing she did pittie him, and being ouercome with contrarieties of doubts, he vttered these complaints.
            What shuld I do to procure my content, when my miseries are one way great, &amp; my ioyes as excéeding: when my dispaire excéedeth, and yet 
                  •
               y comfort aboundeth? I enioy not Artesiaes loue, yet she loueth me not: I enioy her sight, and yet not her sight. I haue as much comfort as fills me with ioy, &amp; yet I am desperate with dispaire. How can that be? She loueth me as I am Syluian, but hateth me, because she loueth not Ornatus. Vnder the name of Syluian, I enioy her sight, but not as Ornatus, and so am I depriued of her sight. I reape excéeding comfort by beholding her bewty, but I liue in dispaire, that shée wold shun loue if she knew what I were. Though I enioy many thinges by being Syluian, yet am I depriued of all comfort, as I am Ornatus. For she déemed him either dead or fled, hath no hope euer to sée him, and if I should shew any signe that hée were liuing or neare, shée would presently eschew my company: which being as I am, I may enioy: &amp; thus am I voyd of all meanes of attayning her loue, yet liuing as I am, I shall still enioy her loue. Why Ornatus, thou hast better meanes to giue her knowldge of thy loue in this disguise, then if thou liuedst as Ornatus. Suppose thou shuldest make knowne to her what thou art, thinkest thou shée would bewray thée, considering thou offerest no other behauiour towardes her, then that which agreeth with vertue? Or what if shée did betray thée, wert thou not better to indare the greatest extremitie by her don, then pyne away with griefe in her absence? Yes Ornatus, in being as thou art, thou art more happie, and therefore maiest thou be in some better hope of comfort. What if shée will not loue thée, yet for thy good will shée cannot hate thée. And though shée know what thou art, shee will rather conceale thée, then bewray thée then try whether she loueth thée or no, but how? Make my selfe

knowne.
            No. I will write a letter, which I will leaue in some place where she may finde it, and so by that meanes I shall sée whether shée will loue or no. And taking pen Inke and paper, he wrote as fo
                  ••
               oweth.
            
               
                  To the most vertuous Artesia, the forsaken Ornatus sendeth humble greeting.
                  WEre you but so mercifull as fayre, I woulde not dispaire of pittie. Or were you willing to know my truth and loyaltie, you woulde though not yeeld to my sute, yet pittie mee. I cannot vse protestations, nor dissemble greefe: but be you most assured, that what proceedeth out at my lippes, commeth from my heart: xtremitie maketh mee ouerbolde, and dispaire maketh me more desperate, in vttering my minde: I cannot chuse but say I loue you, for that I loue indeed. I cannot set foorth my loue with fyled termes, but in plaine truth, protest that my loue is constant, loyall, vertuous, &amp; immoueable: and though you hate, I must loue: and though you for euer denie to loue, yet will I persist in constancie: for the woorst I can indure is death: and that my soule alreadie inwardly feeleth. I haue forsaken my parents, friends, and all to become acceptable to you: for whilest I was Allinus sonne, you did hate me, then I beseech you, now that I am not Allinus sonne, nor Ornatus, pitty mee. For without your pitie I die, &amp; litle can my death profit you: but letting me liue, you shall for euer enioy a faithfull seruant. So most vertuous Artesia, I commit my cause to your wise consideration.
                  
                     
                        Your inseparablie, neyther Ornatus, nor himselfe, but your poore seruant.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               When hee had written this Letter, and sealed the same, the next morning he laid it in a place of the garden, where he knowe Artesia would walke. And from thence comming to her chamber, he found her readie to go forth.
            
               Artesia welcommed Syluia kindely, and forth they went together, and walking vp and downe a prittie while, Artesia espied the white paper, and desirous to sée what it was, took it vp, reading the superscription, maruelled what the contents shuld be, and how it should come there, and turning to Syluian, sée you this letter, it is directed to me, I maruell how it should come here, vnlesse it were laide of purpose: well howsoeuer that was, I will reade the contents, and you shall be partaker of them. When she had redde the same, and well vnderstood that it was Ornatus, at the first shee was so excéedingly v
                  •
               xed, that she said: I now perceiue, that Ornatus was wiser then I tooke him to bée, for I sée he hath committed no outrage vpon himselfe, but wiselie will trie me first, and if I will not yéelde to loue him, what will hée doo? marrie returne to his father againe. This is Adellenaes doing, and according as I thought they are agréed: shée left this letter here, and her may I blame, and not him. For did not she promise him to do it, he would neuer of himselfe attempt it. Syluian I pray thée counsaile me, what I should do herein, for my heart is oppressed with many thoughts, that I will not vtter vntill I know thy minde?
            
               Syluian thus answered: since you haue giuen me licence to speake that which my heart thinketh, first I say, i
                  •
                
               Ornatus loueth according as he protesteth, as no doubt but he doth, you haue good reason to pittie him, for that by your owne report, he is euery way worthy thereof, which if you doo, you shalbe sure of a constant friend, preserue his life, and make vnitie betwixt your parents. As for Adellena, if it were her déede, she did but the part of a friend, but it was very vnlikely, for that shée was not here since yesterday. Neither can I think any man can dissemble so much as to make these protestations, and yet be false. For his

words in my fancie, beare an euident likeliehood of truth. Therefore, if I may counsaile you, yéeld to that which is vertuous, and in so dooing, you shall purchase your owne good, his content, and perpetuall quiet to both your families.
            Would you haue mée then (quoth shée) yéelde to loue mine enemie? How is hee your enemie (quoth Syluian) when hée loueth you? Hée is mine enemie, because his father hating me, how can he loue me? Nay rather (quoth Syluian) his father not louing you, how can hee chuse but loue you, because he seeth them hate you, that are worthy to be beloued: besides their ha
                  •
               red being vniust, it sheweth his vertue the more, to loue those his parents hate: and it is commonly séene, where there is hatred betwixt the parents, the children haue loued most dearely, as in common experience it is séene: haue you not red the Histories of Pryamus and Thysbe, Romeo and Iuliet, and many other? whose loue was the more constant, by so much the more their parents hatred was deadly.
            I remember such Histories (quoth Artesia) but what was the end of their loue, was it not most miserable? I grant it was, (quoth Syluian) which was procured by their parents crueltie, but not their loue, wherein, notwithstanding, they tooke such felicitie, that they rather chose to die togither then to be parted: which argueth, that the enmity twixt parents, cānot break off loue twixt the children, yet might such tragical euents haue bin preuented by wisedom. But how know I (said Artesia) whether Ornatus loue bée so constant or no? Can you haue any greater proofe thereof, then his own letters, the forsaking of his parents, and liuing peraduenture in pennurie: but if you doubt of that, once againe trie him. Well (said Artesia) I asked but thy counsaile, but in stead thereof, thou vsest perswasion: but séeing thou art so forward to doo me good, which I hope is thy intent, if thou wilt keep my counsell, thou shalt know both my minde, and what I intend. Assure your selfe (quoth Syluian) I will rather loose my life then prooue vnfaithfull. Then said shée, I confesse to thée Syluian, that loue hath made entrance into my heart, that I would willingly both

pittie Ornatus, and grant him his request: for that with often remembring him, I cannot forget him, neither doth any thought please mee, but when I thinke of him. But there are so many slips to hinder our loue, that though I loue him, I shall neuer enioy him. For should my parents know hereof, they woulde prie so warily into my actions, that it were impossible for mée once to haue a sight of him, whome I doo scarce remember, I haue so seldome séene him. You may (quoth Syluian) both loue him, and inioy him, and since you haue begun to like of him, he being worthy thereof, and equalling you in affection, increase that loue: &amp; might I but once come to speake with him, I woulde not doubt but 
                  •
               ffect all things with such secrecie, that you should with quiet enioy him.
            Well quoth Artesia, I commit all to you, my life, for that dependeth on my loue, being willing to doo any thing that shall not disagrée with modestie. Destring you to kéepe my counsells secret, for to bewray them, may indaunger both his and my life.
            After many other spéeches past betwixt them, Adellena entered the garden. Artesia espying her, at the first thus gréeted her. God-morrowe Adellena, I know not whether I may salute thée as a friend, or a priuie foe, for that by thy meanes I am brought into bandage.
            I pray thée tell mée without dissembling (which I feare mée thou canst doo too well) when thou sawest Ornatus? and yet I know thy answere before I aske. Dost thou not know this letter? didst thou not hide it in this garden, that I might finde it? did not Ornatus hire thee to say, that hée was departed from his fathers, whilest he lyeth at home in thy house? I knowe thy aunswer
                  •
                will bee no: but howe may I beléeue that? Doest thou not likewise say hée loueth mée when thou knowest the contrarie, and doest but dissemble? If thou harborest any vertue in thee, tell mée the truth and dissemble not? for in doing so, thou shalt greatly con
               
                  •
               ent me, discharge thy conscience, and peraduenture doe Ornatus a good turne.
            
               
               Adellena hearing her spéeches, was so astonish at theyr strangenesse, that for a good while she stood as one sencelesse, but at the last, she made this answere. Your demaunds are such, as that I know not how to answere them: but heauens punish mée, if I dissemble. I saw not Ornatus since the time hée came to mée, to know how you accepted the letter I conueyed into your Casket. For that Letter I am altogither ignorant therein, neither did I euer sée the same before now: I neuer spake with Ornatus, sawe Ornatus, or heard from him since I last gaue him your answere: neither doo I know where hee is: but this I know, that hée is not to bée found: but poore Gentleman, languisheth in loue, which I dare protest, loueth you most dearely, neither neede you misdoubt that hée is absent, or thinke that hée is hidden at my house, for it is too true, hée hath taken such gréefe at your vnkindnesse, as will I feare me indaunger his life.
            I would it were not so, but that he were at my house, then would I counsaile him rather to forget to loue, then indaunger his life thereby.
            May I beléeue (quoth Artesia) that this thou sayest is true? Heauens let me liue no longer (quoth Adellena) if I dissemble. Then (quoth Artesia) howe should this Letter be conueyed into this garden, but by himselfe? With that the Christall teares fell from her eyes.
         
         
            CHAP. VI. Howe Ornatus loue was hindered by the newes of Arbastus death. Howe Floretus to attaine Sylulans loue, both confest hee slew Arbasius, and intended to poyson Artesia.
            
            
               TO augment Artesiaes teares, a messenger hastily running, came in and brought this newes, vttering the same with a gastly countenaunce.
            
               O Artesi
                     •
                  , heare my tragicke discourse, your Father as you know, rode forth this morning to chase the fearefull Déere, who wandring from his company, at last by his long stay was mist, and all of vs comming together, studied amongst our selues, what should be become of him, at last wée were commaunded by Floretus your Vnckle, to poste seuerall wayes in search of him: whom at last we found most gréeuously wounded and dead. Artesia hearing his words, with suddaine gréefe, fell downe deade. Which when Sylnian perceiued, caught her in his armes, rubbing her pale chéekes, vntill shée was reuiued againe. Then they conueyed her to her bed, in such extremitie with that suddaine gréefe, that they feared to loose her life, which exceedingly tormented Syluian to behold. Then was there such an vprore in Arbastus house, as al séemed in vtter dispaire, one coniecturing this, an other that of Arbastus death, but all in generall concluding, that it was done by Allinus in reuenge of his brothers death.
            
               Arbastus wife, likewise conceiued such sorrow at this vnexpected euent, that with very gréefe thereof shée dyed. Artesia with both together, was readie to yéelde vp her latest breath, and had done so, had shée not beene carefullie preserued by Syluian, and Adellena. Who by their counsaile and indeuours, pacified the extremitie of her perplexitie. This newes was soone spred into most places of the countrey: but because there was no iust proofe of the murtherer, there was no great question made thereof: Arbastus hauing neuer a trustie friende to prosecute reuenge. Floretus now tooke vpon him to rule and gouerne all that belonged to Arbastus, as his brother, and soone caused him and his Lady to be worthily interred, and built a sumptuous monument in their remembrance. Which being ouerpast, he came againe to Artesia, (as in the meane time he had oftentimes done) and finding her very weake, vsed many spéeches to comfort her, giuing such as were about her speciall charge, to minister all things necessarie to restore her to her former health: Séeming to bee most carefull of her guard, promising and protesting to bée vnto her instead

of a Father.
            
               Syluian all this while was excéedinglie gréeued in mind to sée his loue growne so weake, and in such danger of life, not once forsaking her in all the time of her siknesse, but continually comforting her with heartie spéeches, carefull tendance, not so much as once departing her chamber, but taking excéeding pains to pleasure her, that shée tooke great comfort in her supposed Syluian, who oftentimes would steale a swéete kisse from Artesiaes lips, which she permitted, taking the same to procéede from a curteous minde, when Syluian did it of déepe affection: accounting the estate wherin hée liued, to excéed all ioyes, and his delight past compare, profering many familiarities that Artesia tooke in kind part, which otherwise she would haue refused, had shée knowne whom her companion Syluian had beene. Ornatus marueiled that all this time she spake not of him, which he deuised to vrge her to do, by many occasions: but these extremities had bannished all remembrance of him out of her minde: Which excéedingly tormented Ornatus, fearing this delaye would some way turne to his ill. That wheras before time, he was pleasant, mery, and oftentimes would mooue Artesia to myrth by his disporte, now that humour was alienated, and he became continually melancholly and sad, oftentimes when Artesia was from him, getting into a sollitary place, to bewayle his hard fate. Which shée noted and woondred at, thinking the same had procéeded from being so long absent from his countrey and friends. One day she found her déemed Syluian sollitarie alone, and comming vnawares, heard her vtter these words. Oh how vnhappy am I, to loue and not to be beloued.
            
               Syluian espying her, left off: to whom Artesia said. Why how now Syluian, are you in loue, can it be, that your mind is attainted with that venemous serpent, that poysoneth the sences, altereth the complexion, &amp; troubleth the head and heart? Shake it off, and cast it out of your sight, for it neuer did any good, but hath brought many to perpetuall miserie.
            Since you haue ouerheard me (quoth Syluian,) I must néeds

confesse I am in loue, which doth not any way worke any such effect in me as you speake off, but I take all comfort therein, my sences, heart, head, &amp; all my parts, take excéeding pleasure therein. Why then (quoth Artesia) sit you thus pensiuely alone, as it séemeth to me bewayling your estate to be in loue? I do not (quoth Syluian) sorrow that I am in loue, but that I am not beloued againe: for being in loue, I haue vowed to liue so euer, and sooner shall end. What hard-harted man (said Artesia) is he ye knowing you loue him, wil not loue you againe? Such is my har
                  •
                estate (sayd Syluian) that the partie whom I loue, knoweth I loue, and yet causelesly doth hate me: neither am I farre absent from him, but inioy his company, without which, my life would decay. Is he in this house you loue? can it bée you are intangled since you came hither? No (quoth Syluian) I loued before I came hither. How can that be, when you are a stranger, and cast in this country by shipwracker? eyther you must néedes be some other then we take you for, otherwise, these things are impossible. But if you dare put trust in my secrecie, impart your minde to mée: and I promise you I will do the best I cā to further your loue. You may do much therein (quoth Syluian) and none more then your self, but I beséech you pardon me for reuealing the same, before you assure me of one thing, which you may do without any harm to your self and be not offēded with me if I ask you. Tel me what it is (quoth she) &amp; I will answer you? Then (said Syluian) I wold first know whether you loue Ornatus or no? With ye she started? saying: Ay me, that name bringeth death to my heart, &amp; thou woundest my souls with gréefe, to heare him named. Dost thou thinke I haue cause to loue &amp; not rather aboue al men to hate him: dost thou not sée my father lately murdred by him, or some by his appointment, and thinkest thou I can loue so deadly a foe, by whom I am brought to this miserie? No assure thy selfe Syluian, according as I haue iust cause I do hate him, as the greatest enemie I haue. Whose very name affrighteth mée with terror, and if thou hadst loued me as I was perswaded thou didst, thou wouldst not haue

troubled my heart with that omnious name. And yet for all this mischiefe that he hath done me, didst thou not see how he sued for my loue, and had so much preuailed, that my heart beganne to yéeld to his sute? With that she pulled out of her pocket the letter, saying: these lynes the trutes of his dissimulation, were actors in his villainie: with that she tare them into a thousand péeces. Syluian séeing the same, was readie to sound with gréefe, breathing soorth a hart burning 
                  •
               igh, said. O how is poore innocencie suspected.
            And being readie to say more, was disappointed by Floretus comming, who euen then entred the garden, and finding them out, vsed many curteous spéeches to thē both, especiallly cōforting Artesia. To whom he said. Dear coozin, since these mishaps cānot be remedied, let wisdome now ouersway your passionate sorrow: and with patience remit all further gréefe, for things past cure are not to be lamented: but now commit the care of your safety to my trustines, ye will as tenderly regard your good as mine owne life. Therfore be of comfort, &amp; whatsoeuer you desire, shalbe to ye vttermost accomplished. Artesia yeelded him many thanks, and so they went in. Artesia being alone by her selfe, could by no means forget what spéech she had with Syluian: eyther thinking shée did dissembl
                  •
               , or was some other then she seemed: or else that she was in loue with Floretus. Then she remembred her spéeches, saying. Howe is innocencie suspected. Which she knew she spake by her accusing of Ornatus
               ▪ which braue her into many doubtfull cogitotions, and troubled her sences excéedingly: but by reason of her little suspect of Syluians disguise, shée could not iudge any thing thereof. Syluian likewise not daring to offend her, and louing her so dearely, that hee could not indure to sée her disquietted, vsed no more spéeches tending to loue, but frequenting her company wherein hée tooke his whole fel
                  •
               ci
                  •
               ie, accounting himselfe most happie to liue and enioy her swéete presence, béeing out of hope to attaine her loue, refreshing his heart with many sollaces of sweete delight, in beholding that which shée little thought he had noted.
            
               Many daies continued Syluian in this disguise, in which time, Arbastus death was almost forgotten. And Floretus drawn by Syluians manifolde vertues, began exceedingly to affect her, shewing such kinde behauiour towards her, that she suspected that which afterwards she found true: for Floretus cōcealing his loue, felt the flame to burne the more inwardly, and liuing in that scorching pennari
                  •
               , thought it better for him to manifest his loue, thē by hyding the same, augment his torment. Assuring himselfe to obtain his desire, for that Syluian was a stranger, far frō friends, and without his friendship, likelie to come to pouertie, which hée thought woulde bée a meanes of importance to drawe her to like of him: besides, hée thought that hée might do as hée list with Artesia, for that shée was onelye in his custodie.
            And on a day finding Syluian alone in the garden, comming to her with a submisse behauiour, he said as followeth. My dear
                  •
                
               Syluian I would gladlie vtter a matter of an importance, if you will vouchsafe me gentle audience: So it is fayre Damosell, that my heart hath long time béen inthralled to your bewtie, which I haue retrained to vtter, fearing to be refused: but knew you how faithfully my heart is deuoted to your seruice, and with what torment I haue concealed the same, you would pittie me. My estate is sufficient to maintaine you well, though not so worthily as you deserue: you shall liue with me in contented ease, and haue so faithfull and constant a friend, as no torment nor affliction shall alter.
            Therefore I beséech you, let me receiue some hope of comfort by your gentle spéeches, which shall expell many cares from my troubled heart.
            
               Syluian had much adoo to abstaine from smiling, to thinke how vnfit he was so yéeld such a reward as Floretus expected: committing further consideration thereof, to time more conuenient, gaue him this answere. My minde sir is vnapt to entertaine loue, considering how farre I am from my countrey, and how soone I may bée ouertaken, therefore I pray you séeke not

that at my hands which I wil not graunt, but if with your fauour I may liue so quietly as since my comming I haue done, I shal thinke my selfe more beholding to you for that; then for your porfered loue, which I cannot yéelde vnto, Floretus thinking her soft answere was a signe she would soone yéeld, stil prosecuted his sute with earnestnesse, in so much th
                  •
               t Syluian tolde him that as yet she could not fancie him, because shée had no triall of him, but that she would consider further thereof. And so for that time they parted. Floretus in hope to attaine that which was not to bee had, and Syluian in hope by this meanes the sooner to attaine Artesias loue. First considering that Floretus had the disposing of her, and therefore he must please him: least otherwise he might bée depriued of her company. Then he began to thinke of Arbastus murther, knowing assuredly, that it was not acted by his fathers counsel, but rather by some secret foe, that might as well bée Floretus as any other, for that hée was the next heire, if Artesia hindred him not: which conceit tooke such effectuall instance in his fancie, that with that his suspect, beholding Floretus behauiour, countenance, and little inquiry for the murtherer, he plainly inspected him, which by the diuine prouidence, rather then by any euident proofe, was stirred in his opinion. Such murther is neuer vnreuealed, and though neuer so closely done, yet God by some extraordinary meanes or other reuealeth the same. So came it to passe with Ornatus, although hée was no war priuie to any such act, or had any probabilitie thereof, yet hée thought that Floretus countenaunce bewrayed his treacherie, and therefore hée longed to haue some conference with him, to sée if hée could gather the truth, whereby he thought both to discharge himselfe of that suspect Artesia had of him, and also when shée sawe his innocencie and constancie, she might yéelde to loue him: purposing to leaue no meanes vnattempted to trie him: which he did the next time be spake with him, in this sort.
            E
                  •
               rly the next morning, Floretus not vnmindfull of his loue which kept him from his sléepe that night, neuer left till bée had found Syluian, and comming to her, with manifolde submisse spéeches,

sollicited his sute: whom Syluian cunningly handled, stil putting him in hope, and yet making him no promise, which set him the more on fire, being so farre ouergone with affection, that hee purposely determined eyther to win her loue, or hazard his owne life, and to leaue no meane
                  •
                vnattempted, were it neuer so dangerous, to procure his owne content. That the more vnwilling he saw Syluian, the more importunate hee grew. Till at last Syluian sayd as followeth. Floretus I know no reason you haue to bee so importunate, when I sée in you no token of fidelitie: but once hauing attained your purpose, you will esteeme mee as lightly as easily woon: besides, I see not wherein you can performe any such matter as you promise, for I beeing in a strange countrey, haue nothing: and you for ought I sée, as little: then by matching with you, I shall but bring my selfe to pouertie, and miserie, and then your loue now so hotte, wil be as colde: and I as reiected, cast off to vtter miserie. Floretus not suffering her to procéed any further, made this answere. Syluian do you not sée A
                     •
                  bastus wealth, wil not ye bée sufficient? the great possessions I now enioy by him, are of substance to maintaine you in all quiet, and yeeld you your heartes content. Arbastus wealth said Syluian, that is A
                     •
                  tesiaes by right, then how can you possesse the same she liuing? Doo but graunt me loue, sayd he, and I will quicklie satisfie you in that. I haue a meane to get 
                  •
               ll into mine owne hands: and therefore I beséech you, let no such matter trouble your minde, but be assured, that in enioying me, you shal haue al happinesse and quiet, by my humble, dutifull, and constant loyaltie. Do but assure mee of this (quoth Syluian) and you shall knowe my resolution afterwards.
            
               Artesia entring the chamber, brake off their spéeches, whose presence vexed Floretus at the heart, beeing scarce able to speake, by reason of his inward rancor: for indéed hee hated Artesia, because she onely kept him from possessing his brothers liuing: the want whereof, kept him from attaining Syluians loue: therefore he resolued by some meanes to worke her downefall which within short time he acquainted Syluian withall by this occasion.
            
               One day finding her alone in a secret place in the garden, after many spéeches past betwixt them: whereby hée perceiued the chiefest things that hindred him, was his want of wealth, and after that Syluian had in some sort made him a grant (onely to trie him,) he began to vtter his intent in this sorte. My deare Syluian, I am so well perswaded of your vertue, and put such confidence in your trustinesse, that I wil reueale to you the very depth and secrets of my heart, would you but sweare to kéepe my counsell: for to purchase your content, I haue determined to put in practise a matter of secrecie, which concerneth my life to bée reuealed.
            
               Syluian hearing that, thought it better to sweare a thousand oathes and breake them all, then by nicenesse to indanger the life of Artesia, which she supposed he aymed at promised him by many protestations, to kéepe secret whatsoeuer he tolde her: wherevppon Floretus vrged with hope to win her loue, and imboldned in mischief, cared not what he did to attain his wil, said as followeth. Syluian, you sée Arbastus is dead, which was one stop that kept me from inioying great possessions, and my purpose is, so you wil but vouchsafe to ayde me therrin, to be ridde of Artesia: and then all that belongeth to her by her fathers death, shall bee yours to dispose of. Syluians heart throbde to heare his spéeches, but determining to sift him to the full, said as followeth. Floretus I am sure you speake this onely to trie me, and so intrap me, and not of any intent you haue to performe the same, wherein you shall doo me great wrong, and your selfe no good: for I cannot beléeue you beare the least thought to do it. By heauen quoth hee, it is my full intent, and for that you may be assured thereof, it was I that slew Arbastus, howsoeuer the matter is imputed to Allinus, and purpose likewise to be rid of Artesia, onely for your sake.
            Therefore make no doubt of my resolution: for I am absolutely purposed to do it. (O thought Syluian) rather shalt thou sée my blood, then spill one drop of hers: why Floretus would you haue me do any thing therin? You onely may doo it (quoth he) with more safetie then any other, and the maner how is this.
            
               Within some mile from this Castle, Arbastus hath a banquetting house in his Parke, where oftentimes hée would for his recreation lye, whither I will perswade Artesia to goe for a season to take the aire, and to recreate her sences dulled with gréefe: and none but you to keepe her company, and some two seruants whose trustinesse, I am assured of. This done, I will get a drinke to be made, the force whereof, shall expell life, and yet by no meanes nor any cunning or skil be found out, when you shall thinke it most conuenient giue vnto her: &amp; being once dead, who will make any enquirie, but that she died of a naturall sicknesse? and then you shall be mistresse both of her heritage and my selfe. Syluian said, when shall this be put in practise? Within these two daies at the farthest said he: in the meane time frequent you Artesiaes company, in such familiar sort as heretofore you haue done, and my selfe wil vse her with no lesse kindnesse. Many other spéeches being past betwixt them at that time, they parted.
         
         
            CHAP VII. How Ornatus told Artesia of Floretus intent, and vpon what occasion he discouered himselfe.
            
               
                  Floretus being by himselfe, began to consider howe rashly he had committed his secrets to Syluian, entring into these meditations; Doth Syluian thinke that my policie excéedeth not her shallow capacitie: poore simple straunger, she hath vndertaken a matter of great importance for me, that meane nothing lesse then good wil to her, she for my loue hath promised to poyson Artesia, and is likely that once done, to taste of the same sawce, for loued she me neuer so well, I will not trust her with my life, but peraduenture she hateth me, and will reueale my drift to Artesia. No Floretus thou

art deceiued, she is so farre in loue that she doteth, and would I am sure to any thing at my request. What a world is this, what villanie can be intended, that some either for fauour or reward, wil not execute? If I should trust her that is so easily wonne to do such a hainous déed, might I not be accounted madde? yes, and therefore I wil not trust her: Artesia being once dispatcht, she shall follow next. Ornatus on the countrary part, was glad that he had felt the depth of Floretus counsell, thinking likewise that he was so farre in loue with him (taking him for a woman,) that for his sake he sought. Artesias death: which was the onely meanes to helpe him attaine her loue, which he likewise determined to giue her knowledge of, and discouer himselfe, hoping that when she sawe his innocencie, his faithfull loue, and how by his meanes her life was preserued, she would yéeld him due guerdon for his good will. Whilst he was in the depth of those cogitations, he espied Artesia enter the garden, and taking his Lute, founde her seated vpon a flowrie banke, vnder the shade of a mirtle trée, and perceiuing that she was somewhat heauily inclinde, he satte downe by her, and with his swéete melodie, brought her a sléepe, when she had slept a good while, being excéedingly aff
                  •
               ighted with a dreame, she started vp, looking earnestly vpon Syluian, saying; I pray thée Syluian do not poyson mée. Syluian séeing her so affrighted, was excéedingly amazed, and she her selfe not yet fully recouered, séemed to be affraid of him, till at last Syluian said. I beséech you what is it that affrighteth you? O Syluian said she, I drempt thou wouldst haue murthered me. Heauens forbid (quoth he) that I should attempt to hainous a deede: But woulde you vouchsafe to heare my tragicke report, you should be rid of that doubt, though Syluian is much tempted to do such a déede: who estéeme your life more dearer then mne owne, and would rather with my owne hands teare out my wofull heart, then thinke the least thought to wrong you. But because I haue so fit occasion, and I hope your patience will permit me, I will reherse a most monstrous and hainous intended michiefe. The other day I remember you were excéedingly offended with me for naming Ornatus,
               
for that you supposed him to be an actor in Arbastus death, but both he and Allinus are innocent, and farre from any such thought, for your vncle Floretus was his murtherer, which hée tolde me himselfe: he hath béene oftentimes importunate to win my loue (which an other possesseth) but I suspecting as much as I now find to be true, held him of with this delay, that he had not wealth to maintaine me. Which when I had often alleaged, hée tolde me all that belonged to Arbastus was his: then I demaunded how that could be, since you were liuing? Quoth hee, sweare but to be secret, and I will tell you how, With that vpon my protestations▪ he tolde me that he had murdred Arbastus, and ment to poison you: perswading me to consent thereto, for that hée said, I onely could do it: with that (I not purposing to do it, but to preserue you) promised him my vttermost assistance, which he tolde me should be done, in this manner. I will (quoth he) perswade Artesia, to forsake this Castle, and to soi
                  ••
               rne some few dayes in a house Arbastus hath in his Parke, where none but you &amp; two others seruāts, whose secrecie I nothing doubt, shall kéep her company, where I will giue you such a potion, as shall end her life, and yet by no means be perceiued, neither can there be any doubt thereof: for that I and none else am left of her kindred, to search the truth. This is the summe of that he tolde me. Artesia hearing her words, sate like one without sence a good space, being so farre ouercome with greefe and feare, that she could not speake a word, but at the last burst foorth into these lamentations. Ay mee, vnknde, and most vnnaturall Vnckle, canst thou speake me so faire and intend me so much harm? Who would haue thought so foule impietie, had ben shrowded vnder so faire pretext? Couldst thou be so vnnaturall, as to murther thy owne most naturall louing and dear brother, and not contented with his tragedie, to séek my vntimely death? What frenzie or follie doth possesse thy brest, that I estéemed replete with vertue? How canst thou suffer so impious and haynous a thought to sink in thy brest, much lesse to act such a notorious outrage against him ye loued thee as his life, &amp; her that honoreth thee as her friend? O Syluian, may I credit thy words, and not rather accuse thée, and excuse him? May I thinke him so

simple, to trust thée with his secrets? no I feare mee this is some pollicie inuented by thee to some bad cud. Yet I pray thée pardon me: for what canst thou get by telling me so vnlesse it were so? or not rather haue kept his counsell, &amp; then thou mightest haue béen my heire. And pardon I ask of thée good Ornatus, though thou art absent, for that I accused thee as accessarie to my fathers death, when thou art innocent. With that a floud of teares stopt ye passage of her spéech, &amp; Syluian said, Artesia, yet vouchsafe to heare my counsel, which shal preuent al these imminent euils. You may peraduēture make some doubt of the truth, of that which I haue spoken: but I take heauen to record, no word is false: for I regard your good aboue all thinges, and your quiet aboue mine own content: for shuld you dye, I could not liue: for by you I draw my breath. I diued into Floretus counsails, not to ayd him, but to preuent them: for that I knew Ornatus was no way guiltie of any such treason, but would haue ventured his owne life, to haue preserued your Fathers, whome hée both loued &amp; honored as himselfe. Of whome I could haue told you more, but that fearing to offend you, &amp; partly séeing how vehemētly you accused him, I durst not, whose loue is loyall, &amp; theron I will pawn my life. Syluian (quoth Artesia) thou tellest mée things of woonder, but especially ye thou art so priuie to Ornatu
                     •
                  
                thoughts, and ye thou darest so boldely affi
                  •
               me he loueth me, when thou maiest be deceiued. Most vertuous Artesia (quoth he) were you but so priuie to ye thoughts of his hart as I am, you would say as much as I, &amp; beleeue all ye I tel you: and to put you in assurance of what I know, I giue you knowledge ye I am Ornatus, y• in the disguise haue sought to attaine your loue: for which boldnesse, I most humbly beséech you to pardon mee. With yt a ruddie blush spred it selfe in Artesias cheekes, before pale with feare, being so much ashamed y• hée had bin to priuie to many of her actions, that she could not tell with what countenaunce to behold him. Then Ornatus said, I beséech you pitie my sorment, which hath vrged mée to this boldnesse, being frustrated of other meanes to enioy your presence: my meaning being no other then vertuous, but resting at your mercifull disposition. Desiring you to put assured confidence in me, for preuenting Floretu
                     •
                  
                intent, which you had not doubt of, for to my gréefe I know it to bee soo true.
            
               
               Artesia maruelled excéedingly at the straungenesse of these newes, but most of all admired Ornatus loue, which shée could not tell how to reiect, for that she both well knewe, hée deserued loue, and the necessitie of time was such, that her safetie rested in his secrecie: yet being not willing at that instant to yeelde without further assault, said: I know not by what name to call you, when neither I know whether you are Syluian or Ornatus, but which of both, your words beare great shewe of true friendship, which I feare me is not grounded in your heart, neither do I greatly care: for since my vncle séeketh my life, let him take it, for I am weary thereof.
            Let not your gentle heart (quoth Ornatus) make any doubt that I am Ornatus, though my counterfeit disguise doth shewe me other, but either vouchsafe me loue, or giue me leaue to dis for Artesia, for that potion that should dispatch you, shall ende my life: for my life is bound to your commaund, and all my felicitie resteth in your fauour. Which vnlesse you graunt, my life without the same will be but shorte, and the time I haue to liue, an endlesse labyrinth of sorrow.
            
               Adellena by occasion entered the garden, and found Artesia wéeping, and Syluian in a heauie dumps, readie to torment himselfe to sée her sorrow, but Artesia espying her, said: Adellena, doest thou loue Ornatus; so much, as that thou wouldest hazard life and credit to doo him good? for that I knowe him to bée a most vertuous &amp; honest Gentleman? I but wouldest thou quoth shée kéepe my counsell if I reueale a secret of importance to you concerning Ornatus? And vpon Adelleanas promise, she said: doo you know Ornatus if you see him? behold there he is. Adellena was at the first halfe astonisht at her spéeches: but at last she perfectly remembred that was he indéed: reioycing most exceedingly to see him there, especially with Artesia. Then they declared vnto her all that had happened, and of Floretus intent, desiring her to be secret, and make no shewe of discontent, least he should suspect Syluian had bewrayed his secrets: and after some other speeches past, they went in togither.
         
         
            
            CHAP. VIII. How Artesia departed to the Lodge with Syluian, and from thence secretly departed to Adellenas house, and how Ornatus taken to be Syluian, was by Floretus accusation, and Artesias want, banished.
            
               IT fel so out the next day, that the King with diuers of his company, amongst whom was his only sonne and heire Lenon, being wearied with trauell, arriued at Arbastus house, thinking to haue founde him there, but the King hearing of his suddaine death, was excéedingly sorie, perswading himselfe as all men else did, that he was slaine by some of Allinus house? which made him make small tariance there, but departed to his Pallace. Now it fortuned that Lenon behelde Artesias bewtie, and was with the first view thereof, excéedingly bewitched, that after he was gone, he could by no meanes forget her? but determined ere long, to returne to sée if he could attaine her loue. Now the time was come that Floretus had appointed to set abroach his villany, and (according as Ornatus had before told Artesia) he came to her, perswading her for a season to lie in the Countrey, which she as forearmed consented vnto, and so the next morning, she with Syluian, Floretus, and diuers others, departed: at night Floretus returning, and leauing with her according as he had promised Syluian, and onely two seruants that were to prouide them necessaries, but knew no part of the conspiracie. When Ornatus and Artesia were alone togither, for that she was vndoubtedly assured of his loue, faith and sidelitie, she vsed these comfortable spéeches to him. Ornatus, whereas alwaies before this time too vnkindly I haue reputed you as a 
                  〈◊〉
               , I now craue pardon, being sorie that my h
                  •
               a
                  •
               t hath done you so much wrong, which now I will requite with kindnesse. I carresse

it was strange to me to entertaine loue, but now I willingly yeeld my selfe to be her subiect, and your true and faithful friend: committing my life to your custodie, and my loue and selfe to be yours to dispose of. Ornatus hearing her spéeches, was rauished with a heauen of ioy, with a gentle and kind behauiour, foulding her in his armes, and imprinting a swéete kisse vpon her rosiate lippes, he said. Neuer was poore wretch exalted to more happinesse then I am, by being inriched with this inestimable treasure of your loue. O how rich a reward haue I now reapt for my cares, and what glorie, ioy or wealth, can be compared to the riches of your loue? O heauenly Artesia, how fortunate haue you made Ornatus? how haue you blest Ornatus? how full of ioy is Ornatus, by your swéete consent? was euer any so vnworthie, so exalted, for his kindnesse and loue? I wil performe more then my tongue can vtter, and bee more faithfull then your heart can wish. Then began they to imbrace each other, and to surfet themselues in the sollaces, true loue yeeldeth. He sometimes lending her a kisse, and she with interest paying two for one: for one swéet looke two, and so many imbracings as are not to be explicated: their hands and hearts ioyned in such firme bandes of true affection, as is not to be dissolued: and sur
                  •
               etting with such excéeding content, as is impossible to be described. These stormes of loue somewhat mittgated, they began to consult of their daungerous estate, and to deuise how to preuent the intended mischiefe. In this place they continued some two dayes in excéeding content, still expecting to heare from Floretus: who the third day fearing to trust any with a matter of such waight, came himselfe to bring the potion, (yet in shew of kindnes to visite Artesia) deliuering the same to Syluian, willing her the next night to giue it her, which she promised him faithfully to accomplish.
            When he was gone, Artesia came to Ornatus to knowe what newes Floretus brought, who tolde her all, and shewed her the poyson in a glasse, which he had charged should be giuen to her the next day. With that Artesia beganne to wayle and exclaime against her Vnckle, in most extreame sort. But Ornatus
               
intreated her to cease such vaine griefe, which could not hurt him, but her selfe, promising her to preuent the same, if shée would follow his counsell▪ which she willingly yeelded vnto. Then quoth hée, let vs presently depart hence to Adellenaes house, which you know is not farre off, who you know is agreed with vs alreadie, where I will leaue you, and returne. Which said, while the seruants were absent vpon some speciall occasion, they departed with little labour, arriuing at Adellenas house, who was readie to receiue them, and after many farwels, Ornatus returned backe to the Lodge. And when it was supper time, the seruants brought vp meate, but Ornatus tolde them that Artesia was scarce well, and therefore they would not sup that night. And being alone by himselfe, he studied what excuse to make for Artesias absence, when Floretus should come, spending that night in much care, and many vnquiet cogitations, which tooke away his sleepe.
            
               Floretus was no sooner returned from the Lodge, but hée met Lenon, who of purpose came to méete Artesia, whom Floretus kindly saluted: maruelling much wherefore hée came: to ease which doubt, Lenon said.
            My friend Floretus, I come to visite the faire Artesia, to whose beawtie I am inthralled, not as regarding her wealth, but her sweete loue, of whome you onely haue the gouernment: therefore I pray befriend me so much, that I may come to spéech with h
                  •
               r. Floretus was so 
                  •
               xcéedingly amazed to heare his speeches, that he could not tell what answere to make, nor how to excuse her absence. Lenon séeing him in such a studie, continued his spéeches, saying: Floretus be not vnwilling I should match with Artesia, for that shall no way binder your preferment, who think peraduenture the longer shée liueth vnmarried, the more wealth you shall get by her, but to rid you of that doubt, be but a meanes to win her consent, and I vowe by heauen, I will not take one peniworth of Arbastus substance from you, but fréely giue it you all. For it is not her possessions I regard, but her loue, therefore I pray resolue me of your minde herein.
            
               My Lord replied hée, your offer is so bountifull, besides my dutie vrging me, I am readie to performe your will to the vttermost of my power. I thanke you good Floretus quoth Lenon, then I pray thée bring mée to her, for my loue is impatient of delay. My Lord replied he, that can I not do instantly, for Artesia some two daies past, with the straunge damosell Syluian, departed thence, and are nowe at the Lodge: whither (if you please to to take such entertainment as this place yéeldeth) wée wil both goe to morrow morning. Agreed quoth Lenon, I will accept your profer. When the time of rest was come, Floretus being alone by himselfe, entred into these cogitations. What inconueniences hast thou runne into Floretus? Thou hast hyred one to murther Artesia, in hope to get her wealth, and made Syluian acquainted with thy counsell, which wealth thou maiest now attaine by preseruing her life: and besides, winning her to loue Lenon, thou shalt finde him thy faithfull friend for euer. What wert thou then best to doo? if thou shouldest murther her, hée would make enquirie of her death, and so thou bée vndone: If not, then wil Syluian bée displeased, and so bewray thy drift: that the mischiefes thou by folly hast runne into, are so intricate, that thou knowest not which way to shunne them. Were it not better to saue her life, and winne her Loue for Lenon, then to poyson her, and so to die my selfe? If I saue her life, Syluian will be discontented: what of that? then let Sylùian smart for it, for if she wil not bée contented with that I shall doo, she shall neuer liue to bewray my counsell. And therefore wil I first trie her, and finding any suspition thereof, I will stabbe her my selfe, whose death I may eastlier answere then Artesias. Early the next morning, Lenon and he rode to the Lodge, where no sooner arriued, but he met with Syluian, to whom he said: How now Syluian, I haue newes of importance to bewray to thée, Lenon whome thou here beholdest, is sonne to the King, who is déeply in loue with Artesia, and hath giuen me assurance of all Arbastus liuings, if I can win Artesia to match with him, now I thinke it good to deferre our purpose as concerning her death, vntil wée haue made triall whether shée

wil loue him or no. Which if we can effect, we shall be quit of so cruel a déed, enioy her heritage, and haue an assured friend of Lenon whilest we liue: therefore let me know your opinion herein. Syluian was excéedingly amazed to heare his spéeches, thinking that if he did tel him where Artesia was, she should be wrested from his possession, and so himselfe disappointed of her loue: and on the other side, he thought what michiefe would arise if he should say he had already giuen her the poyson, yet his loue ouermaistring the feare of any daunger, made him say, All this I like: but Floretus, it is now too late, for I haue caused Artesia to drink the poyson you deliuered me, and she is dead, which was of such force, that all her bodie purpled into blisters and swellings, which because I knew would bewray what we had done, I tooke her bodie and conueyed it into a deepe pit, where it is impossible to be found. Floretus now fearing to haue his treason bewrayed, thought to stabbe Syluian; and so to be rid of them both, that in a monstrous rage he drew his dagger, and vnawares strooke Syluian in the left arme, who féeling the smart, with violenc
                  •
                more then Floretus expected, stept to him, and in spite of his vtermost strength, wroong the dagger out of his hands, and with the same wounded him in thrée places, and had not Lenon stept betwixt them, Floretus had bene slaine. With that Lenon parting them, demaunded what the matter was: Floretus thinking rather to accuse, then be accused himselfe, and terrified with affright, saide that wicked woman hath murthered Artesia. Syluian made no answer vntil Lenon laid hold on her, demanding where Artesia was, she answering, that by the intisemēt of that wicked Floretus, I gaue her a drinke that vnknowing to me hath poysoned her. O wicked creature saide Lenon, thou hast condemned thy selfe to death. With that he began to drawe his sword, but Ornatus thinking it now no time to 
                  •
               ally lest hee might by them be murthered, caught holde on Lenons sworde, hauing such aduantage, that he easily wroong it from him, and said; Worthie Lenon be aduised, do not thou s
                  •
               eke to spil my innocent blood, without further

cōsideration, least for the same thou loose thine owne. Thinkest thou I am as faultie and guiltie as Floretus is? be assured I am not. But if thou louest Iustice, late hands on that Traytor, for he not I, is culpable of sheading her innocent blood. By this time Lenons seruants perceiuing their contention, came running in with their swordes drawne, by their Lordes commaundement, apprehending Floretus, and a
                  •
               terwards saking by violence to take Syluian, but he standing in his owne defence, resiste
                  •
                them, alledging innocencie, till Lenon vowed and protested if he were not accessary thereto, he should haue no other then iustice, and that his cause should be heard before the King. Ornatus thought it better to yéelds by faire meanes, rather then by compulsion, and esteeming it lesse griefe to be made a prisoner, then to bewray where Artesia was, and so haue her taken 
                  •
               rom him, yéeldeth: both of them being conueyed to the Pallace, and for that night cōmitted to seuerall prisons. Floretus conscience so deeply accused him of villany, that he continued cursing and exclaiming against his hard fortune, with bitter bannings raging against himselfe for trusting Syluian, seeming with extreame feare of death, desperate.
            
               Ornatus on the other side, tooke that trouble patiently, as endured for Artesias sake fearing nothing, for that hee knew himselfe innocent, and could easily acquite himselfe of such accusation, purposing rather to hazard the worst, then bewray what he was: which to conceale, was his greatest care. The next day they were brought before the Prince, where Floretus vpon Syluians accusation confest the truth, both concerning Artesia, and how he slue Arbastus, for which hee was adiudged to die within two daies. And quoth he to Syluian, for that thou art a stranger, and by his counsell rather then of thine owne inclination, wer: drawne vnwillingly to doo that déed, I will pardon thy life, but adiudge thée to be banished this Countrey: and quoth he, because I feare that some wil séeke thy life, thou shalt presently be conueyed hence. Which doome shall stand irreuocable. Then gaue he commandement, hee should be conueyed to the hauen presently,

committing her to the custodie of certaine rude Moores. Who not staying to heare what answer shée would make (whereof poore Ornatus was not readily prouided of, in that extremitie) immediately carried her away: to whom Ornatus would haue tolde the truth of all, but hée spake to them that vnderstood him not, who with spéede executing their soueraignes commaund, rudely haled him aboord, and hoysing saile, neuer rested vntill they arriued neare the coast of Natolia, where they were commaunded to leaue her.
         
         
            
            CHAP. IX. Of the sorrow Artesia tooke for Ornatus banishment, and of the seuerall aduentures befel. him in Natolia.
            
            
               
                  ARtesia remaining in Adellenas house, maruelled shée heard not from Ornatus according to his promise, which draue her into some doubt of his safetie, that comming to Adellena, she desired her to haste to the Lodge, to intreate him to come to her, for that by her hearts misdoubt shée suspected some heauie newes. Adellena immediately hasted thither, finding the seruants in great sorrow, whom shée asked for Syluian. Ay me, quoth one of them, by this time shée is past speaking withall: for such heauie newes is befallen since your departure, as gréueth me to vtter, yet notwithstanding hée told her all that was happened.
            
               Adellena brooking no delay which in those affaires was daungerous, stood not to immitate of those gréefes, and how contrarily euery thing fell out, but with all haste returned to Artesia, who espying her comming, thought her countenance bewraied some vnwelcome accident; hastily enquiring how Ornatus did. Adellena for want of breath could not speake a good space, but at the last shée said. Artesia, tedious lament is not now to be vsed, but spéedie counsell how to saue Ornatus, for hée is carried before the King, is accused by Floretus to haue murthered you, for comming to the Lodge with Lenon the Kings sonne, who pretendeth great loue to you, and not finding you, Ornatus tolde Floretus he had giuen you the poyson, whereupon Floretus wold haue slaine him, but Ornatus taking his dagger from him, had done the like to him, had not Lenon stept betwixt them. Then Floretus accused him for your death, and he Floretus: and both were yesterday carried before the King.
            
               Ahlas poore Ornatus, said Artesia, what miserie is befallen thée for my sake? howe art thou rewarded for preseruing my life? Good Adellena, counsell me what is to be done: Ornatus being amongst them a reputed straunger, hauing no friend to pleade for him, and peraduenture ouerswayed by Floretus persurie, may haue his life indaungered, and the rather for that he is taken to be a Natolian. Therefore Adellena, if thou louest him or me, will saue both his and my life, and discharge him of that false accusation, runne to the Court, and finding out Lenon, tell him at my safetie, and request him for my sake to pittie poore Syluian. Adellena according to her commaundement, mounted a Horse, and with great spéede by that time it was night, attained the Court, and finding out Lenon, vttered these speeches. Most worthie Lenon, vouchsafe to heare me speake: The faire Artesia whome you suppose dead, is aliue and in safetie at my house, who hath sent me vnto you in the behalfe of Syluian, fearing some wrong might bée done to her, as inspected to bée her death, when she onely hath preserued her life.
            
               Lenon was so amazed at her spéeches, that hée could not tel what to say, being excéedingly gréeued for Syluian, but at length tolde her what his Father had done: which appalled her sences with deadly feare. Lenon, notwithstanding it somewhat gréeued him for Syluian, yet his heart was glad to heare of Artesias safetie, and therefore hée determined to goe with Adellena to visit her; which likewise hée performed, and entring where shee was, making excéeding lamentation, he said.
            I beséech you gréeue not faire Damosell for Syluian, for no harme is done to her, onely my father vppon her owne confession and Floretus accusation, hath banished her, to her owne Countrey.
            
               Artesia hearing his spéeches, with verie gréefe fell into a deadly traunce, both Lenon and Adellena hauing much a doo to bring her life againe. And being conueyed to her bed, when her sences were come to their perfect vse, and Lenon standing by her, whose sigh
                  •
                was most gréeuous to her, shée turned her

head from his sight, sheading such aboundance of teares, that shée bedrawed the place where shée laie. Lenon perceiuing that shee was displeased with his presence, withdrew himselfe, giuing Adellena this charge. Adellena, since Artesia is in thy custodie, I charge thée let her not depart hence, vntill thou hearest of mee againe, for if thou doest, thou shalt answere the same: but if thou wilt stand my friend, and in my behalfe intreat her fauour, I wil proue so gratefull a friend, as thou shalt account thy labour wel imployed.
            Hée was no sooner gone, but Artesia vttered these lamentations; Most accursed wretch that I am, to bée thus separated from my deare Loue, whose curteous minde is the fountaine of all vertue: how vnfortunate am I made by my fathers death, and my Vnckles crueltie, but especially by his losse, that is vniustly banished into a straunge Countrey, where hee prooe true and loyall Gentleman, neuer set foote? how vnhappie was hée made, when hée first beganne his loue? but now most miserable, by séeking to preserue my life, hath cast away his owne; and fearing to be disappointed of my loue, hath quite diss
                  •
               uered himselfe from my 
                  ••
               ght, to hazard his person by sea and land. Is it possible that hee should euer returne, béeing so farre conueyed from his natiue soyle, and left to the mercies of strange people, that will be readie to destroy his guiltlesse life. No I 
                  •
               eare mée, neuer shall I bée so happie as beholde him, and though I doo not, yet shall my loue to him remaine immoueable. Therefore nowe will I arme my selfe to endure all perilles, to liue in care, and continuall lament, for want of beloued Ornatus, whose heart I knowe is replete with sorrowe, and peraduenture misdoubteth my loyaltie, hauing bene so vnkinde to him before: and knowing Lenons affection, may suppose his dignitie might alter my constancie. But sooner shall Ornatus heare of my death, then that I haue altered my loue, or yéelded his right to an other, were hee the greatest Potentate in the worlde.
            Which saide, another flood of brinishe teares ouerflowed her eyes, and her passage of spéeche was stopt by heart-pearcing

sighings, which in confused multitudes issued with her swéete breath, neuer ceasing her lamentes, but still bewayling her true Loues absence, that it pearced Adellenaes hearte with suche sorrowe, that shée wept as fast as Artesia, both being so much greeued, that they seemed to striue howe to excéede one another in laments. In which sorrowfull estate, Artesia remained so long, that shée waxed extreame sicke; and grewe to that extremitie, that Adellena feared her death.
            
               Lenon likewise being come to the Court, gat
                  •
               e pardon of his Father for Floretus death, but notwithstanding hée remained in prison all the dayes of his life. Lenon likewise hearing of Artesias sicknesse, refrained from visiting her, onely he would oftentimes repaire to Adellenaes house, to enquire howe shée did.
            
               Ornatus being left in the Countrey of Natolia, tooke his misfortunes in such heauie sort, that had not his hope to see Artesia againe withheld him, hée had offered himselfe some outrage, for a season giuing himselfe to forlorne and carelesse desperation, neyther regarding which way to prouide for his safetie, nor otherwise respecting what daunger hee might runne into in that straunge Countrey, for the Moores had landed him in a waste and desolate Coaste of the Countrey.
            Thus carelesse did hée continue a whole night and a day, not so muche as séeing toode to preserue him from famine: but in the ende, hunger constrained him to séeke succour, but when his stomacke serued him, hee coulde finde no meate, that with the extremitie thereof, calling to remembrance his estate, hée vttered these plaints.
            Thus contrary is Nature to her subiects, sometimes hoysing them to the tappe of all felicitie, and then with violence tumbling them downe headlong into the depth of extreame miserie.
            Was euer more fortunate, and suddenly miserable then I am? Coulde euer any man whatsoeuer, attaine more heauenly felicitie and happinesse then I did, by being possess of Artesia?
               
and now againe more accurst being thus far absented from her: and banished my natiue soyle into a straunge Countrey, readie to be famished or deuoured by wild beasts, or that which is worst, neuer likely to see Artesia againe. How could any man containe himselfe from desperatenesse, being so miserable as I am? How can I withholde my hands from murthering my selfe, when by doing it, I should bee ridde out of a wretched life? What should I doo, which way should I goe? Here I am in a desolate and vnfrequented place, where no humane creatures inhabit, but wilde beasts, without foode, without weapons, in womans apparrell, and without hope of comfort. Shall I state here? then shall I bée famished: shall I leaue this place and trauell further? then I goe further from my beloued, and méeting with some rauenous beast, may be deuoured. Now being hungrie I want foode, and here is none, vnlesse I will eate the earth, leaues of trées, or rootes of the grasse. Well I will séeke my fortune, bée it good or ill: and in this desperate moode hee trauelled on, and by good fortune founde a Tree laden with excéeding, pleasant, and goodly fruite, with which hée slenched his hunger: not farre from which place, he tooke vp his nights lodging.
            Early the next morning he arose, first filling his belly, and then his lappe with that pleasant fruite, the taste whereof, was lyke pleasant wine, that being drunke in abundance, will make the head light: which made Ornatus hearte merrie, that he trauelled on space, but Fortune not contented with the miserie he had endured alreadie, sent him in an other affliction: hee entered into a place like a Forrest, beset with Trées of huge proportion, scattered here and there, where hée met with a wild and fierce Boore, that haunted those Desarts, who espying Ornatus, with a terrible groyning bristled himselfe comming towardes him, Ornatus being now driuen to his vttermost shiftes, beganne to runne with all his force from the beast, but hee making the more spéede had almost ouertaken him, when one of the Apples Ornatus carried about him fell downe, and the Boore espying the same, staled his haste to take it vp, whereby

               Ornatus had gotten some little ground of him, and séeing him so much affect the fruite, cast downe another Apple after which the Boore runne, with gréedinesse deuouring the same. Ornatus was glad of this poore shifte, and still cast downe one Apple and then another, that in the ende he had almost throwne away all, and notwithstanding that, feared to be destroyed, but the Boore féeling his belly full, and his hunger stauncht, left off his egar pursute and followed him more cearelesly, whom he still fedde with Apples, so long as his store lasted, that in the ende the Boore being drunke with the pleasant fruite, began to réele and stagger, and lying downe fast a sléepe, which Ornatus séeing, hauing no other then a knife about him, with the same approached the Boore, and without feare, violently thrust the same so déepe into the Boores briffled side, that it pearced his heart, and he after some strugling died.
            
               Ornatus then helde vp his hands to heauen for ioy, excéedingly applauding this his fortunate and vnexpected escape; which he tooke as a fortunate presage of good successe. But yet before he could determine what to doo, Fortune once againe showed her mutabilitie, for when Ornatus had parted the Boores head from his huge bodie, and with the same was readie to depart, there past by as it seemed, a knight gallantly mounted, in gréen armor, who espying a woman bearing the Boores head, drew towards her, and said: Woman where hadst thou that Boores head? I pray thée deliuer it me. Ornatus made this answere. Sir I néed not doo either, vnlesse I know more cause then as yet I doo. The Knight hearing that short answere, alighted, and saide: I will shewe no other reason but that I will haue it: with that he beganne to striue for the same, but Ornatus hauing more minde to his sword then to keepe the Boores head, suddenly caught holde on the Natalians sword, and drew the same out, which when he had gotten, he said: Disloyall and discourteous Knight, now wil I kéepe the Boores head in despight of thée, with that hee thrust at him, and contrary to his thought, wounded him so déepe that he le
                  •
               t him for dead, wishing that he had not done that déed, but not

knowing how discurteously he would haue vsed him, let passe all further remorse, and casting off his womans apparell, put on the Knights apparell and Armour, mounted the stéede, and with the Boores head, roads backe the same way hée sawe the Knight come, and within a little space, found a beaten way that conducted him to a goodly Towne, whose Turret toppes he sawe long before hée came to the same: then began hée to studie what to doe, sometimes thinking it best not to enter into the Towne, from whence it is likely the Knight hée slewe came, and so he béeing taken for him might bée knowne, and so afterwards indaungered for his death. For peraduenture the Knight might be of good estimation, and of purpose sent to slay the Boore, and if it should be knowne that he had slain him, his friends would for the same, and the rather for that he was a straunger, prosecute sharpe reuenge against him. Whilst he was in these meditations, he came neare the Towne, not fully resolued what to doo, where he was soone espied of some of the people, who séeing the Boores head, came running towards him making excéeding ioy: which when he saw, he thought it too late to turne back, but that he must go on and hazard the worst: and being entred the Towne, a number of the Inhabitants flocked about him, some with garlands, some with praises, and all with ioy, vttering these spéeches. Welcome home most braue Alprinus.
            
            
               Ornatus then perfectly knew that the Knights name was Alprinus, and went of purpose to 
                  •
               lea the Boore, whome they tooke him to be, and that he must of necessitie be knowne? which draue him into excéeding care what excuse to make, to auoide the danger of death. Then presently he beheld a troope of bewtifull Damosels, with the sowndes of swéete Musicke comming towards him, (amongst whom, one as chiefe and more bewtifull then the rest, was crowned with a wreathe of flowers, bearing another in her hand) who all at once applauded his victorie, dancing before him, vntill he came into the middest of the Towne where satte the chiefe Magistrates, where the Damosell that was crowned, thus spake to him.
            
               Syr Alprinus, your conquest hath released these Inhabitants of care, extolled thy fame, preserued thy life, and wonne me for thy Loue. You haue well performed the talke you vndertooke, and according to your desert, I come to Crowne you with these flowers, and to yéelde my selfe as yours for euer.
            
               Ornatus hearing her spéeches, thought to trie the end of this aduenture, which could be no worse then death, which of force he must now hazard, alighted, laying downe the Boores head vpon a Table that stood before the Auncients, with humble and comely behauiour kissing the Damoselles hande, who set the wreathe of Flowers vpon his head, and taking him by the hand, brought him before the Auncients, one of whome stoode vp and said? Worthie Gentleman, whereas before thou wert by vs adiudged to die as worthie thereof, for this thy valiant déed, we fréely pardon thee, and acquite thée from all trespasses that thou host commited against any whomsoeuer vntill this present houre.
            And taking the Damosell by the hand saide, Lucida, according to thy desire, and his desert, I yéelde thée vp to be his wife. And Gentleman quoth he, take her as thine owne, as freely as she was by birth adopted mine: and after my death, be thou inheritour of my land.
            To all this Ornetus gaue a reuerent consent, and the night now approaching, he with Lucida went to her fathers house, where was a great feast prouided, from which Ornatus excused himselfe in this sort. When he was entred the house, being still Armed, only lifting vp his Beuer, he tooke Lucida by the hand, and withdrawing her aside, said.
            
               Lucida, I nowe finde your loue to bée infallible, and your constancie to excell all women that I haue knowne? and that Alprinus is so farre indebted vnto you, as that he shall neuer (might hée liue a thousande yeares) bee able to recompence this inestimable fauour of your loue, which hath preserued my vnworthie life from destruction.
            But notwithstanding your Loue Alprinus, his debt is

so great as can no way bée gratified, I request one further fauour at your handes, wheron my chéefest felicitie dependeth, yea my life, your loue, and perpetuall good, which I feare to vtter, lest you should misconceiue the same, there being n
                  •
                other thing to hinder the content Alprinus séeketh, but onely your fauourable consent, so banish all mistrust of my faith.
            
               Lucida maruelled at his spéeches, indéed louing him so well, that she would haue spilt her owne blood for his sake, saying: Alprinus, what neede you make doubt of my consent to any thing whatsoeuer it be for your sake? knowe you not howe faithfull I haue continued, 
                  •
               hough you slue my onely brother? and that I estéemed your loue farre dearer then his life, and when you should haue died for that déed, obtained this at my fathers and the rest of the auncients handes, that slaying the Boore that destroyed many people, you should saue your owne life, and winne me as your Loue. And notwithstanding all this, doo you make a question whether I will yéelde consent to any thing that shall be for your good? O Alprinus, if your loue were so constant as mine, if you intended to continue my loue for euer, if your heart felt so déepe a sting of loue as mine, you would not make such a doubt of my loyaltie, of my truth true loue and constancie. For you knowe whatsoeuer you should aske, I will graunt: whatsoeuer you should request, I will performe: and wherein soeuer a Louer may shewe infallible tokenes of her truth, I will doo as much as any: but since you will not beléeue mee without an oathe, I sweare by my lo
                  •
               e, my vnspotted virginitie, and by all the good I wish my heart, I will consent, agrée, performe, or doo any thing: not be offended with any thing, be the newes neuer so vnwelcome, so it be for Alprinus good: nor leaue any thing vnperformed you shall require.
            
               Ornatus hearing with what constancie her spéeches procéeded from her, and how greeuously shée conceiued it, that any doubt should be made of her loyaltie, thought most certainely that he might put his life into her hands, and therefore hauing

alreadie studied a deuice, said, It ill agreeth with my nature to dissemble: and hardly could I haue béene drawne thereto, but that desire to preserue loue, drewe me thereto for knowe most worthy Lucida, that I am not Alprinus, but one that for his sake, hath vndertaken this: The truth whereof, if you will heare with patience, I wil declare.
            Yesterday, I trauailed through the Forrest, or desart, where I met Alprinus, sore wounded, and flying from the Boore that pursued him with celeritie: which when I behelde, to rescue him from death, I set vppon the Boore, and by good fortune slew him: which when he behelde, he declared to me the cause of his cōming: which when I heard, pittying his estate, I bid him take the boores head, and withall, helpe him to mount his stéed, but his woundes would not suffer him to ride, that I was in some feare of his life. When presently wée beheld an auncient Hermitte comming towards vs, who liued in a Caue in those w
                  ••
               ds, who vndertooke to cure his wounds, being glad of the Boores death. To whose Cell I conueyed Alprinus: At whose request, I haue performed this which you sée, and haue vndertaken to hazard my life, to discharge him of death, and to win the assured possession of your loue.
            Now I most humbly intreat you for his sake, to conceale what I am, that I be not knowne: and so both disappoint your selfe of his loue, and him of safetie. Onely deuise a meanes to excuse mee from this feast: which I trust you will doo for Alprinus sake, and then wee may haue time to studie for your further content.
            
               Lucidas loue, made her beléeue that all hée said was true, and therefore saide: Syr, I trust there is no cause why I should mistrust you: and therefore relying vppon the truth of that which you haue sad; I will tell my father you are wounded, and desire rather to goe to your Chamber, then to the feast, who I knowe will denie mee nothing. This said, she went to her father, and so preuailed with him, that he was contented shée should haue the tending of him: whome she tooke to a chamber, suffering none to

come at him, but her maide, whome shée trusted: and well might trust for her fidelitie. A
                  •
               terwardes Lucida came to Ornatus, to determine how shée might come to sée Alprinus, being most carefull of his health: and amongst many other spéeches, they concluded, that Ornatus the next morning should depart towardes the Forrest to Alprinus, and that shee by some meanes would come thither the next day after, if hee would méete her, to giue her directions where to finde him, which hée promised to doo. According to this agréement, Ornatus very earlie the next morning, armed himselfe, and as Lucida had instructed him, tooke his leaue of his father, who little suspected he had béene any other then Alprinus, gaue his consent, and so Ornatus in Alprinus armour againe departed the Towne, being glad that hée was escaped from death, which he was sure to haue ind
                  •
               red, if it had bin any waies knowne that he had slaine Alprinus.
            
            And being nowe alone by himselfe, hauing she wide world to trauell into 
                  〈◊〉
                neuer a friende to go too, voyd of feare, but not o
                  •
                care: hee 
                  〈◊〉
                whither to direct his iourney: sometimes his conscience accu
                  •••
               g him of too much disloyall dealing towardes Lucida, in betraying her vertues by his dissimulation, in tell
                  •••
                her Alprinus was liuing, when hee knewe it to the co
                  •••
               
               ry.
            Then hee contrarilie, thought it was lawfull for him to dissemble with her, to saue his owne life, and though he had slaine Alprinus, he did it but in defence of his honour.
            Amongst at these, this cogitation séemed most to acquite him o
                  •
                dishonour, that fortune and the destenies had by that meanes ordeined him to escape. Whilest hée rode on in these déepe meditations, he met with an ancient hermit, who comming towards him said: Discurteous gentleman, how cammest thou by that armor? and yet I need not aske thée, for I know thou slewest the worthy gentleman Alprinus, which I beheld to my gréefe. Father (quoth Ornatus) if thou didst beholde the same, thou canst witnesse I did it against my will, and in mine owne defence: for whose death I am so sory as thy self, and would as willingly haue done

any thing to preserue the same as any man liuing.
            Will you then (said the Hermite) doe this for him, vouchsafe to come and speake with him, who is in reasonable good estate in my Cell?
            I would to God (said Ornatus) thy wordes were true: for if hée be liuing, it will reuiue my heart with ioy, that is almost vanquisht with care: desiring nothing more then to sée him. Hée is liuing said the Hermit, and if you will goe, I will bring you to him presently.
            
               Ornatus being come to the Cell, accordingly found Alprinus very weake, by reason of his gréen
                  •
               us wound, to whom Ornatus declared al that happened betwéene him &amp; Lucida: which added no little comfort to Alprinus heart, that hée thought himselfe of sufficient strength to go and méete with her: and therefore told Ornatus he would goe and méete with her, and withall yeelded him so many thankes, as if by his meanes, his life had bin preserued.
            In the meane time they continued in the 
                  〈◊〉
                Hermittes Caue, Alprinus in great comfort, and Ornatus in no lesse care, for the absence of his deare Artesia, breaking foorth many a scalding sighe, and vttering many a sad and mournefull lamentation: sometimes vtterly dispairing of attaining her loue, and then againe by remembring her vertues, growing into some better confidence of her constancie. Yet most of all, fearing that Lenons loue to her, might eyther by perswasion of his death, force, affect of dignitie, or other meanes, winne her to consent to him, especially for that shee hadde no parente
                  •
                to gouerne her, nor hee neuer a faithfull friende to counsaile her.
            The next day Alprinus and hée went out to méete Lucida, whome they met at the entrance into the Forrest, and after many kinde salutations past betwixt the two louers, they altogether went backe into the Towne, to Lucidaes Fathers house, who that morning was departed to a Hauen, about businesse of importance.
            
               
               Ornatus was most kindly vsed of them, remaining there vntill Alprinus had wedded Lucida: but then hee thought it high time for him to depart: And on a time finding Alprinus alone, who had showne sufficient tokens of his friendship, hee declared vnto him, the whole truth of his forepassed loue to 
                  
                     •
                  rtesia, requesting his helpe, for his passage into Phrygia.
            
            
               Alprinus with great regard, attended the whole discourse, promising his vttermost assistance: which (quoth hee) none can effect so well as Lucida, whose father is a merchant, and sendeth for ships into sundrie Prouinces, who onely may pleasure you: which charge I will vndertake, and cause her to deale so 
                  •
               ffectually with him, that you shall attaine your desire. Ornatus continued in good hope, somewhat abandoning his former dispaire, whome for a time wee wil leaue, attending the time that some of the ships should depart, to speake of Artesia his carefull Louer.
         
         
            CHAP. X. How Lenon caused Artesia by violence to bee caried from Adellenaes house, to the greene Fortresse: of the miseries she indured there. How shee was rescued from thence by Allinus, and from him taken by Pyrates. And how Allinus accused by Lenon for her death, was imprisoned.
            
               AFter that Artesia by Adellenaes carefull tē
               
                  •
               ance had somewhat recouered her health, Lenon began to visit her againe, béeing vnable to indure the heauie burthen of burning loue: thinking her sicknesse had procéeded from feare of Floretus, not for want of Ornatus company, finding an occasion, saluted her in this sorte. Most fairest Artesia, my heart is so firmely inthralled to your beautie, and my affection
                  •
                so admire your vertues, that I am constrained to vtter my minde, and to tell you, I loue your Beautie, Vertues, and other most

rare perfections wherewith you are adorned. That I humblie sue to you for fauour, and prostrate my selfe your thrall, desiring to be inriched with those Iewels of inestimable price: which hauing once attained, I shall thinke I had more wealth in my possession, thē all the world besides my selfe, doth conteine. Your vnkinde vnckles crueltie, you néed not feare, nor other misfortune: neither haue you any parents to ouerrule you in making your choyse: then vouchsafe to accept my sute, and yéelde consent to my loue.
            My Lord (replied Artesia) I thanke you for your good will, but I know not how to accept of your loue, being yet so far from knowing what it is, that if I should but dreame thereof, my heart would be out of quiet: besides, many cares continually attend the same, and my meane estate so farre vnworthy thereof, with innumerable other discontents and cares that I would make my selfe subiect vnto: that I had rather a thousand times remaine in the estate I am now in. Therefore, I intreate you to settle your loue elsewhere, more agreeable to your estate and fancie: for I shall thinke my selfe most fortunate, if I neuer fall into that labyrinth of disquiets: but will during my life, labour to kéepe my selfe free from loues bands. Lenon would not take this for an answere: but with many other spéeches continued his sute, whom Artesia still put out of hope: that he departed for that time excéedingly discontēted, leauing her no lesse disquieted in her thoughts how to auoid his loue.
            In this sort did he daily visite her, still growing more importunate, amongst many other, this conference past betwixt them: Artesia (quoth he) how long shall I sue, and be frustrated in my hopes, by your vnkindnesse? is your heart hardned against me? Or am I of so base conditions, that you cannot conceiue well of me? Or is it possible you beare so hatefull a conceit of loue as you make shewe for? then may I accuse mine eyes, that haue betrayed my sences, in making them your thrall: then may I thinke my woe began, when I first began to loue. O Artesia be not so cruel, as to punish me with this disdaine.
            
               My Lord (replied shée) I séeke not your disquiet: for at the first motion I tolde you my minde, which shall neuer alter, neither is my heart hardened against you more then others: for I am determined not to loue: then seeing you sée my intent, it were a point of wisedome in you to shake off this fonde and foolish loue, which is but a toy, and an idle fancie, that is bred by vanitie: and doo not séeke to make loue growe without a roote, for in my heart it shall neuer take roote: but rather when it is rooted, I will pull out heart and all, but I will 
                  •
               oote it out. Then (quoth be) you are led by obstinacie and not by reason, for that you are subiect to loue, you cannot denie: then why not me before another, considering my loue is more faithfull then any other? And I being most worthy, why should I not be first accepted? Artesia was wearie of his spéeches, hauing her constant thoughts onely bent on Ornatus: therefore to rid him from her, she said; It is in vaine to vse many words, neither am I like to those that will at the first séeme 
                  •
               oye, but afterwards yéelde: but I desire you to bée satisfied with that which I haue alreadie sayde, that I cannot loue.
            Faire Damosell, how can I be satisfied with that vnreasonable answere, when my life dependeth on your consent: which your deniall will finish: then giue mée leaue to say, I cannot bée so satisfied: but being extreamely refused, I must growe perforce to be as vnreasonable in my request. Consider you not what dignitie I might aduance you too, by making you my wife, consider you not the pleasures, ioyes, and abaundance of all contents you might enioy with me, and how faithfully I loue you, and with what humilitie I séeke your loue, and yet notwithstanding you remaine obdurate? My power is great, that whereas I sue, I might commaunde, and by authoritie compell you to consent: then bée not so ouerconceited, as so obstinatelie to reiect your good. And think, that if my loue were not constant, I might vse extreames, which would soone alter your minde.
            Suppose (replied Artesia) I were so péeuish as you terme

me, yet being borne frée, I am not to be made bond by constraint: and were you the greatest king in the world, you could not rule the heart, though you might by iniustice punish the bodie: for it is not kingdomes, wealth, nor crueltie, can turne hatred to loue: but it may sooner turne loue into hatred. But by your spéeches I may partly know your thought, and the lippes vtter what the heart intendeth: doo with mée what you will, I cannot loue: neither will I loue you, were you Monarche of all the world.
            
               Leanon was so much gréeued and vexed at her spéeches, that hée was readie to tare his hayre, his loues extremitie making him rather madde then sober, that presently hée departed, saying no more but this: Farewell hard-harted Artesia.
            
            Shée was glad hée was gone, presently telling Adellena all that had past betwixt them: and how peremptorilie shée had answered his importunate sute, telling Adellena, that since Ornatus was for her sake bannished, shee would neuer loue any but him, and preserue her life in hope to sée him once againe: but the first knowledge of his death, should bée the latest date of her life: both shee and Adellena thinking that Lenon would neuer returne to prosecute his loue. But hée beeing come to the Pallace, betooke himselfe to his chamber, raging more like a mad man, then a passionate louer, sometimes swearing, cursing, and stamping, yéelding so much to that mad fancie, that in the end, he vowed to obtaine Artesiaes loue, though he hazarded his life, honour, and good name: that ranging in this sort, vp and downe his Chamber, hée espied an olde Gentlewoman, named Flera, going by his windowe, whom hée called vnto him, and thus saide. Flera, because I haue assured confidence in thy fidelitie; and purpose to reward thée liberally, I craue thy counsaile, and with it thy consent, to be faithfull in concealing my secretes, and very diligent in dooing my commaunde. The olde hagge making an euill fashioned lowe curtesie, sayd: My deare sonne Lenon, be it to do you good,

I will hazard my life, and rather bée torne into a thousande pe
                  •
               ces, then reueale what you shall vouchsafe to tell me. Then (quoth hée) counsaile me which way I should begin to win a faire Damosels loue. Marrie my Lord (quoth she) giue her knowledge thereof: and then with faire speeches woe her: i
                  •
                that will not preuaile, giue her gold, and there is no doubt, that faire bayse will catch her.
            No no (quoth he) these are of no force, I haue made my loue knowne to her, by humble sutes, submisse behauiours, and by all kinde of curteous meanes, intreated her consent: yet for all that, she remaineth obstinate: she is rich, and therefore gold with her is of no force: she is fayre, vertuous, noble, and chaste: then what engine hast thou to vndermine that chastifie? Meanes enough (quoth she) peraduenture shée is ruled by others counsell, which may preuaile more then your sute: but might I haue accesse vnto her, I would not doubt but to alter her minde: for being faire, young and rich, she cannot chuse but delight to be praysed: subiect to loue, and therefore yéeld to desire. Doest thou thinke (quoth he) thou couldest winne her, wert thou her kéeper? I warrant you, (quoth she) I would doe it.
            Then shalt thou bée her kéeper, sée that thou beest to morrowe at my fathers Castle in the gréene forrest, where to morrow by night this Damosell shall be, whose name is Artesia, daughter to Arbastus lately dead: vse her kindly, let her want nothing: nor be not in any wise knowne that thou knowest mée: nor that the Castle belongeth to my Father: nor speake not of loue in any case: vse her in this sort vntill I speake with thee, for thou onely shalt haue her custodie. Flera being gone about her businesse, be foūd out two of his trustiest seruants: to whom he imparted both his mind and intent: willing them the next morning with spéed to go to Adellenaes house, and either by force or faire meanes to take Artesia from thence, and carrie her vnto the gréene 
                  •
               ortresse in the gréen Forrest, where they should find Flera, 
               
                  •
               o to whose custodie they should commit Artesia: and themselues should remaine there to prouide all things necessarie vntill his comming.
            
               Early the next morning, the seruants rode to Adellenas house, whereinto they boldly entred, and comming to Artesia, first spake her faire, but afterwards tolde her shee must goe with them, i
                  •
                not willingly, by constraint. Artesia then began to bu
                  •
               st into teares, wéeping and lamenting excéedingly, vpon her knées intreating them, not to offer by violence to carry her from thence, but if they would néedes, that they would take Adellena with them: but all was in vaine, for they constrained her to mount vp béehinde one of them, and away they rode in great haste: this heauie parting was so sodaine, that Artesia coulde not a bid Adellena adue, but with teares, nor Adellena speake a word for griefe, their sences being so farre confounded with care, that their harts were readie to burst therewith. Artesia thought this was Lenons dooing, and therefore sorrowed the more: not that hée vsed her vnkindly, but that hée loued her, not fearing his crueltie, but his lust: not regarding what crueltie hée could vse by hatred, but fearing his loue would make him seeke her dishonour. Béeing come to the Fortresse, and committed to the custodie of Flera, the olde woman began to speake her faire, and vse her kindly, yet her verie wordes and countenaunce bewraying her guiltie conscience, to whome Artesia would not speake a word, least thereby shée should giue her occasion to prate: meate shée brought vnto her, but shée refused to taste thereof, and when shée came to her Chamber, shee laie on the rushes, refusing the bedde, tormenting her heart with care, vexing her head with thought, and busying her sences, or meditating to what issue this vsage would sorte, sometimes calling on Ornatus name for comfort, sometimes accusing Lenon of barbarous crueltie, and cursing her crooked destenies: vttering such plaints as would haue turned tyrants to ruth, wéeping her eyes drie, and her garments wet, tearing her h
                  •
               ire, and tormenting euery one of her sences with vexation, refusing sléepe, rest, ease, or quiet.
            The next day Lenon came thither, asking Flera howe shée fa
                  •
               ed, who tolde him that she would not speake, eate nor sleepe, but 
                  •
               ared like one madde and sencelesse. But let her alone quoth

shée, and you shall sée this fit
                  •
               e will soone bée ouer, the extremitie whereof, being once past, I will vse my skill to trie her.
            
               Lenon giuing order to haue all thinges necessarie prouided, departed. Dinner time being come, and meate set before Artesia, she refused to eate: likewise supper time being come, she determined to do the like. Which Flera perceiuing, said: Fayre gentlewoman, to behold your outward appearence, would make one iudge your minde harbored many hidden vertues, but I comparing your actions with your apparant shewe, suppose that you are either mad or carelesse: this behauiour, to séeme dumbe, to refuse sustenaunce, and to refraine from sleepe, are instances of follie, not of wisedome. What if you speake, what if you did eate, or take rest, should you be euer the worse? or refraining, can that doo you good, or banish griefe, and not rather make your estate worse? doo you thinke to preuent any thing by dooing your selfe harme? no fonde Childe, eate thy meate, and preserue thy 
                  •
               fie: for liuing thou maiest attaine thy desires, but dying thou art past hope. With that she departed smiling.
            
               Artesia hearing her spéeches, beganne to consider indéede what follie it was to refuse her meate, and for feare to shorten her selfe by distemperating her selfe, which might bee the meanes to further Lenons intent, whome shee knewe would seeke her life, if hée coulde not winne her loue, shée presently left off suche desperate behauiour, and with well wayed consideration, attended the euent of the worst misfortune, that from that time shee both eate her meate, and did all that shée coulde to comfort her selfe, still liuing in good hope of Ornatus returne.
            Some fewe dayes after, Lenon came to the Fortresse againe, enquiring of Flera howe Artesia fa
                  •
               ed. Well quoth shee, but you willed mee to conceale that it was your dooing to bring her hither, and some bodie else hath tolde her thereof, for shée knoweth the truth as well as your selfe or I, and therefore I would wishe you to visite her, and after that let

me alone to perswade her.
            
               Lenon was ruled by the olde woman, and came where Artesia was saluting her, but shée disdaining either to looke on him, or heare him speake, withdrewe her selfe from his presence. Wherewith hée departed, willing Flera to doo that which shée had vndertaken. And Flera finding her as shée thought in a fit moode, beganne to commune with her of many thinges, amongst which loue was one. Artesia a while heard her, but in the end, perceiuing her drift; cut her off with these spéeches.
            Olde iniquitie, I knowe whereto thy talke tendeth: thinkest thou I will euer harbour a thought of Lenon, that hath vsed mée thus dishonourably? no rather will I rent my wofull heart from out my brest before his face: neither néedest thou tell mée that hée hath intreated thee to speake for him, for I knowe too well both his and thy intent, which shall nothing preuaile, but harden my heart against him. Therefore doo not speake to me, for I will not heare thée, nor answere thée: but hate him, thée, and thy counsell, and remaine so constant in despising him, that a thousand deathes shall not alter mée. Is it loue that hath made him with violence carrie me from my friendes, make me a prisoner, and commit me to the custodie of such a hellishe hagge as thy selfe? If that be his loue, let him turne it to hatred, and neuer trouble me, but with hating me: for in so dooing, he shall better please me.
            Often Flera would haue replied, but Artesia would not suffer her, that shee beganne to w
                  •
               xe angrie, and in the ende to plaine furie, that running to Artesia, she caught holde on her, and beganne to teare her garments from her bodie, and withall, caught sometimes such firme holde on her pure fl
                  •
               she with her nayles, that the blood followed: that Artesia began to crie and shrike for feare, and smart.
            When the olde Beldame had executed some part of her intended reuenge and crueltie vpon her in this sort, shee saide:

Proud girle, thinkest thou to beare it away with out-facing mée? No, do not thinke I will leaue thée thus, but thou shalt repent that euer thou commest héere, and before I goe, I will haue my 
                  ••
               inde of thée: then puld shée out a knife, and catching holde on her, swore, that vnlesse she would promise to vse Lenon kindly, when hée next came, shée would cut her throate: which drane Artesia into that feare, that shée began to intreate her and speake faire, promising to condiscend to any thing that agreed to her honour. Stand not vpon those nice tearmes with mée quoth Flera, but here sweare to yéeld to loue him, for so thou maiest delay him, and frustrate his hopefull expectation, whom thou art not woorthie to touch, much lesse to beare such a presuming minde as thou doest, in scorne of his loue. Therefore yéelde to that which I request or stand to my mercy. Canst thou bestowe thy loue better then on so honourable a Prince? Canst thou attaine more dignitie, reape more content, or enioy more quiet with any then with him? Then do not denie mee, for I purpose not to be denied.
            
               Artesia trembling for feare, made this answere onely to satisfie her, I am contented to bée ruled by Lenon, whose meaning I knowe is honourable. Therefore I pray do not offer mée this ou
                  •
               rage, but suffer me to liue in quiet vntil his comming. If this will not satisfie you, then do the worst you can: for death is more welcome to mée then life in these extremities. Well quoth shée, I will trie you, but if you dally, beware what will ensue, for I am resolued what to doo. Artesia was glad shée had satisfied her, though it were with vttering words which shée neuer intended to performe.
            
               Adellena séeing how suddenly Artesia was taken from her, caused one of her seruants priuilie to followe them to the gréene Fortresse, who returning, tolde her what he had séene. Then Adellena began to studie how to release her from thence, and with all haste rode to Allinus house, where being arriued, she declared al that shee knew as concerning Ornatus, and how Lenon had carried Artesia by violence into the gréene Fortresse. Allinus being glad to heare that Ornatus was aliue, promised to redéeme

               Artesia from Lenons custodie, and that to eff
                  •
               ct, the next euening caused his men to mount themselues, and himselfe with some fi
                  •
               e of them, disguised from being knowne, came to the greene Fortresse, and one of them knocking whilest the other hid themselues, the seruants little suspecting any such ambush or intent, opened the gate, when presently they rushed in, and soone found out Artesia, whome Allinus told who he was, and to what intent hée came: Artesia was glad thereof, and willingly yeelded to go with him, but the olde woman made such an outcrie, that all the place rung thereof: one of Allinus seruants seeing shée would not bée pacified, drew his sword and thrust it through her bodie, and so with a yelling crie, shée gaue vp the ghoast. Then presently Allinus departed with her, intending to carry her to his owne house, to kéepe her there vnknowne, vntil he could heare of Ornatus. And remembring that the two seruants were fled, and would no doubt certifie Lenon what was done, would not go backe the same way hée came, though the readiest▪ for then hée thought hee should méete them, but went a more secret way, thinking by that means to passe vnséene, and entring into the plaines where cattell fed, Allinus espied a company comming towards them, whom hée presently suspected to be Lenon, which in reason he could not thinke, but that feare perswaded him thereto? the company likewise espying them (who were certaine Pyrates that were wandred from their shippes to steale cattel) wondred what they should be that were so late abroad, and being readie to any mischiefe, set vpon Allinus and his company, who thinking it had bene Lenon would by no meanes yéeld, nor speake, fearing he should descrie them, but resisted the Pyrates, who being vsed to many such méetings, soone slew two of Allinus seruants and had giuen himselfe many gréeuous wounds, enforcing him to yéeld. Who taking from him all that was good, constraining A
                     •
                  tesia to go with them, and hasted to their ships, when hauing conueyed her aboord, to preuent the worst, hoysed saile, and launched into the déepe. Then was Allinus left in most miserable estate, with all spéed hasting to his house. Lenons seruants likewise

were by that time it was mindnight gotten to the Pallace, and called their Lord out of his bedde, to cer
                  •
               ifie him what was happened, who presently mounted himselfe, and with a sufficient company rode to the Fortresse, and entring, found Flera slaine, and all else fled, then began he to muse who should do that déed, and what they should be that had carried away Artesia: by this time it was day-light, and Lenon rested in excéeding v
                  •
               xation to be dispossest of his bew
                  •
               ifull Loue, yet he commanded his men to poste by companies seueral waies, if it were possible to finde those that had done that deed: whilst he himselfe remained there bewailing that misfor
                  •
               une, his seruants had not rode far: but (by the light of the day, which discouereth things done in darknesse) they found Allinus two seruants, whose dead bodies they carried back to the fortresse. Lenon séeing them, presently assured himselfe that Allinus was a partie in this action, and that hee had taken away Artesia to séeke her death To preuent wihch mischiefe (as he thought then or neuer to be done) hee presently rode home to the Court, and humbly vpon his knée, intreated his father to graunt him licence with a sufficient power to rescue Artesia from Allinus, who intended to murder her, declaring how he himselfe found her in Adellenas house, and how that he had placed her in the gréene Fortresse, to defend her from Allinus and others crueltie, being left fatherlesse: and how that night Allinus had taken her from thence by treason, and intended no lesse then her ruine. The king hearing his sonnes speeches graunted his request. Then presently diuers to the number of t
                  •
               ree hundreth men, with as much speed as could possibly be, armed themselues, and in haste with Lenon, went to Allinus Castle, into which they violently and vnawares to any within entred. Lenon presently laide hands on Allinus, whom he 
                  •
               ounde sore wounded asking him for Artesia, who thinking some of his seruants had before bewrayed what he had done, presently confest the truth of all, both of his intent and howe Artesia was rescued from him, but by whom hee knewe not, and howe at that time two of his seruants were slaine.
            
               
               Lenon giuing no credit to his spéeches, neuer left till hée had searched the whole Castle throughout, but not finding her, accused Allinus that he had murthered her, commaunding his men to binde him, and carry him as a Traytor to the Court. Who being come before the King, confest the truth as before he had done, vtterly denying that hee neuer sought Artesias death, but her safetie: but yet notwithstanding the King was so ouerruled by Lenons accusations and perswasions, that he committed him to prison, his goods and lands were seized vppon as a Traytor, his Ladie wife turned out of do
                  •
               res in poore array, and al crueltie and outrage committed against his seruantes and kin
                  •
               folkes, and commaundement giuen, that none should succour them. Allinus being in prison laden with yrons, and hardly vsed, yet endured that affliction patiently, but hearing of his Ladies calamitie▪ and how she was vaiustly constrained to beg that all her li
                  •
               e long had bene tenderly brought vp, thought those sorrowes woulde soone bring her to an ende, and entered into many bitter lamentations for her and his owne misfortune which were too tedious to recite, his seruants were constrained to disguise themselues, and trauell into farther places of the Countrey to liue vnknowne, otherwise none would haue entertained them. His Ladie was compelled to séeke out kinswomen of hers, that liued in the countrey, of whom she was entertained, and there liued a poore life, far differing from her former life, which she tooke most patiently. And thus was Allinus house defaced, his goods and lands seized vpon, himself imprisoned, his wife in poore estate his seruants driuen to wander from place to place, readie of
                  •
               en to perish for want of succour and all his dignitie turnd to mise
                  •
               ie, onely by Lenons malice: who had no ground for those accusations he vsed against him, but onely of a vaine suppose, and mad franticke affection that ouerruled his heart, which so much preuailed with him, that he sought by all meanes he could, his death.
         
         
            
            CHAP. XI. How Ornatus gatte shipping into Phrygia. Howe Allin
                     •
                  s was set al libertie: and how the Pyrates cast lottes who should possesse Artesia.
            
            
               
                  ORnatus all this while remained in the countrey of Natolia, with Alprinus and Lucida, in great griefe, for want of meanes to depart into Phrygia, to sée what was become of his deare Loue Artesia: but being a long time frustrated by reason none of the ships that were at sea came home, he began to dispaire, thinking that Artesia supposing him to be dead by reason of his long absence, would now marry Lenon, which griefe, and many other doubtfull thoughts opprest his heart with such passion, that he began to waxe sicke, and afterwards fel into an excéeding feuer, which held him for the space of thrée moneths in great extremitie, which surely had abridged his dayes: had hee not bene most carefully nourisht by Lucida, who had an especiall care of his good. During which time of his sicknesse, certaine ships of Phrygia arriued on the coast of Natolia, some fourtéene miles distant from the Towne where Ornatus was, of which he had intelligence by certaine Factors belonging to Lucidas Father, which newes reuiued his spirits with ioy, before drouping with care, that within few dayes he recouered his former health, which greatly reioyced Alprinus and Lucida, whose hearts were linked vnto him, in hands of vnseparable friendship: who likewise dealt so effectually for him, that they attained warrant for his passage, and furnished him with all kinde of necessaries, and sufficient store of gold to beare his charges.
            
               Lucida likewise intreating her father to agrée with the Phrygian Marchants for his conuoy, for that himselfe would not be

knowne, disguising himselfe into the habit of a Pilgrime, whic
                  •
                kinde of people, might without disturbance passe vnexamined, and without molestation. And the time of his departure being come, he tooke his leaue of Lucida. Who tooke his departure with such excéeding sorrow, that the abundance of her flowing teares stopt the passage of her spéech. Alprinus likewise with many curtesies bad him farewell, and wished his prosperous successe. Thus departed he the confines of Natolia, where he was in so short space so well beloued, and so kindly vsed, that had not his, loue to Artesia, and hope to finde her in safety constrained him, he could haue bene contented to haue spent the terme of his life in that place.
            The Merchants of Phrygia had not sailed many dayes, but they arriued in a hauen some ten myles distant from the Court, whither Ornatus determined to trauell, and hauing taken his leaue of the Marriners, and paide them their due, furnished with all things fit for his disguise, he tooke his iourney, and the first night lodged at a village neare adioyning to his fathers Castle, the custome of which place he well knewe before, and therefor
                  •
                framed his behauiour accordingly. And beeing set at supper amongst such gues
                  •
               s as lodged in that house with him, the Hoste named Mylo, suddenly fight, which one of them noting, demanded what inward griefe draue him thereto. Marry sir quoth he, if you haue not alreadie heard the newes, I will tell you so much as I knowe, which I would I had neuer knowne. Within few
                  •
                dayes there dwelt an auncient Knight heereby named Allinus, excéedingly well beloued of all men, who is lately fallen into great miserie, the occasion whereof was this, then did hée declare the maner of all that had happened vnto Allinus, how Artesia was taken from him, but by whom no man 
                  •
               nows, himselfe in prison, his goods confiscated, and his wife &amp; seruants turned out of doores, with commaund that none should succour them.
            
               Ornatus heart was so pincht with this newes, that hée was readie to fall vnder the Table, which olde Mylo and the rest noted, perceiuing such a chaunge of countenance in him, that they

all denied him to be excéedingly sicke: but hée fearing to discoue
                  •
                himselfe, told them it was but an ordinarie course with him, to be so troubled: but being vnable to mittigate that passion, hee rose from the table, and gat to his chamber, where being alone, he began to meditate the depth of these mischances, imputing the originall thereof to procéed from himselfe. That he entred into these bitter plaintes. My misfortunes are without compare, and I more miserable then any wretch liuing: By my euill destenies, Artesia was first left in miserie, afterwards imprisoned, and now surprised by those that will intend her ruine, or dishonor. My father imprisoned, my mother bannished: all his landes, liuings, seruants, and friends, taken from him, and he subiect to Lenons mercie, that is mercilesse, cruell, deceitfull, and malitious.
            Onelie by my follie, are these mischances befallen. Can there then be any more wretched then my selfe? hath not my father cause to wish that hée had neuer begotten mee, and my mother that shée had neuer borne me? Hath not Artesia cause to accuse me, hate me, and forsake me? When for my sake, by my follie, and want of wisedome, she is brought to so many miseries? What shall I doo? or what remedie shall I séeke, when all things is past recure? Whome may I blame, but my selfe? Is there any that is interressed in the cause of these woes, but my selfe? Lenon, Lenon, as well as my selfe, hath procured these euils: his affection to Artesia, hath caused my banishmēt, my parents wo, and her losse. To trauell in her search, and leaue my father in prison, the one would be in vaine, when I knowe not whither shée is conueied, and the other dangerous to his sa
                  •
               etie, for Lenon no doubt of malice will séeke his death.
            In these and suche like plain
                  •
               s hee spent most part of that night.
            Earlie the next morning comming out of his Chamber, hée heard a great tumult in that Village: the occasion whereof, was this: Such as were Tenaunts and friendes to Allinus
               ▪ hearing of his vniust imprisonment, and with what crueltie Lenon
               
sought his ouerthrow, assembled themselues togither, with purpose to intreat the King for his release: that in the end there was thrée hundred of them assembled. The common people, and such as were idle persons, and readie to any attempt, misconceiuing their intent, and bearing a minde desirous of libertie, which they thought they were restrained from, by certain strickt lawes the King had made, gathered vnto them, that contrarie to theyr expectation, there was a multitude: the intent of whose assemblie, being demanded, they answered, that they meant to redéeme Allinus: amongst whom, Ornatus in his disguise, thrust himselfe, vsing many forcible perswasions to vrge them forwardes to that attempt. That they were readie to runne confusedlie to the Court, not regarding daunger, nor the displeasure of the King.
            One of Allinus friends named Thrasus, standing vppe amongst the rest, craued audience, to whom they all listned, whilest he said.
            I perceiue your intent is to release Allinus, wherein you shall shewe your loue to him, and doo a déede a worthie to be eternized, for that hée hath not at all deserued to haue such iniustice ministred vnto him: therefore be wise in this attempt, and first know against whom you beare armes: that is, against your lawfull King, who may punish this fact with death: for that we
                  •
                vndertake to breake those lawes which he hath ordained.
            But followe my counsell, and I will sette you downe a course, whereby you shall attaine your desire, and bee voyde of any such daunger, which is this. First lette vs all repaire to the Court, and humblie intreate the King for his release, if hee will not graunt that, then that hée woulde haue his cause tryed by the rest of the Péeres of the land; Which if hee also denye, then may wée with good cause venture our lines in his rescue: The multitude hearing Trasus, in signe of consent, all cryed, Trasus, Trasus, shall be our Captaine.
            
               Then presently euerie one with such furniture as they had, hasted to the Court, and comming togither, would not seeme to enter by force, but with a full consent yéelded to Thrasus directions. Who desired one of the guard to certifie his Maiestie that there were a number of his subiects gathered togither, with no intent of euill, but onely humbly to craue a boone at his highnesse hand. The King being certified hereof, was much troubled in his minde what the thing shoulde bée they would demaund, and being perswaded by Lenon, would not himselfe come out, but sent one of his Knights to demaund what was there request. Thrasus declared vnto him the cause of their comming, and what they demaunded. Which when the King vnderstood, béeing exceedingly inraged at their boldness
                  •
               , bad the knight make them this aunswere, that he was not by his subiects to be controlled, and therefore denied to performe the least of their demaund: commaunding them presently to depart euery man to their seuerall place, least hée punished their presumption with death. The messenger had not scarce ended his wordes, but presently the vnruly multitude began to rush in at the Court gates, some carelesly ruinating whatsoeuer came next hand, some breaking downe windowes, some assayling such as resisted them, and euery one bent to doo mischiefe. The King fearing the peoples vnruly rebellion, would come to some greater mischiefe then cou
                  •
               de suddeinly bée preuented, and might also indaunger his person, not knowing who had instigated them thereto, with the Quéene and Lenon fled. Which when Thrasus knew, calling to the multitude, hée willed them in any wise not to destroy the Kings house, not attempt any thing more to displease his Maiestie, for that the King was departed, and he had Allinus at libertie. But notwithstanding some bent onely to inrich themselues, spoyled the Kings treasure, and vtterly defaced the house: by which time the night drew nigh, and euery one began to withdr
                  •
               w themselues. Allinus séeing what excéeding mischiefe this attempt had bred, which was done contrary to his thought, and without his consent, yet thought it best not to trust to the Kings mercie, though hée were

neuer so innocent, for notwithstanding that he would suppose it was done by his procurement, therefore (after Thrasus had willed the vnruly multitude to depart as secretly as they could, euery one to his house, to preuent further daunger &amp; saue their liues, by kéeping themselues vnknowne) hée and Thrasus that night, without delay disguised themselues, and fled towards the coast to get shipping for Armenia, whither they intended to trauell.
            
               Ornatus was by and beheld all this, glad of his fathers escape, not purposing at all to discouer himselfe, vntill he had found Artesia, in whose search he meant presently to trauell: but such confused thoughts, whither to direct his steps, did so ouerwhelme his conceits, that hee rested like one metamorphosed, not knowing whether he would 
                  •
               éeke her by sea or by land. By sea he thought his labours would be in vaine, and if he should go to finde her by land, he knew not whether she might be at sea, and so conueyed into forraine Countries. At last remembring he had heard Mylo say she was rescued from Allinus in the desert where his Cattel fed, hée determined to trauell thither, though he had little hope to finde her there. And being come thither, sometimes bewayling her absence, accusing his hard fortune, breathing foorth bitter 
                  •
               ighs in remembrance of her losse, and renuing the remembrance of their loue, be spent some thrée daies in that place, vttering those plaintes to the trées and birdes, for otherwise there was none to heare him. Where for a while we will leaue him.
            The Pyrates hauing as is before saide, taken Artesia from Allinus, and with her such wealth as they could find about them, hauing withall furnished themselues with the spoyle of such Cattell as fed in those places, returned to their Ship, and with haste hoy
                  •
               ed faile, the night being nowe past. One that was chiefe amongst the rest, named Luprates, went downe to viewe Artesia, hauing as yet not séene her beawtie by reason of the night, and now comming neare her, and beholding her diuine forme, his mind was presently rauisht with that sight, and he thought that none but himselfe should enioy her, which tooke such efficacie, that whereas before he intended nothing but her dishonour, his

minde was now altered, and he intended to vse her in most reuerent and decent sort, and not by crueltie, but curtes
                  ••
               , to winne her loue. But beholding her teares, and excéeding lamentation, and how impatientlie she indured the extremities shée was driuen vnto, comming towards her with a most submisse gesture, friendlie countenaance, and gentle spéech, hée said. Faire Lady, be not any thing disquieted that you are made captiue to suche as delight in spoyle, for though our mindes are otherwise bent to all inciuilitie, yet to your selfe shall no wrong be offered, such vertue hath bewtie imprinted in my heart, and whereas heretofore without mercie, both I and the rest of my consorts haue not regarded the plaints, distresse, nor what wrong wee haue offered either to Ladie or damosell, yet towards your self is my heart altered, and my meaning honestly bēt: that I assure you not onely of quiet, and to bée voyd of all wrong by vs to be done, but also, wherein soeuer I may work your wil, quiet, ease, or desire, I wil most willingly imploy my vttermost indeuours. Then I beséech you mittigate these cares, bannish this sorrow, &amp; drie vp your teares: for you haue no cause of care, nor occasion of sorrow: but rather to say, this vertue resteth 
                  ••
               me, to alter rude and barbarous mindes, to ciuill &amp; vertuous behauior. Artesia looking earnestly vpon him, being indued with an excéeding wit, and thinking it best to speak him faire that vsed her so kindly, said. Sir, I know not how to mitigate my grief, when it increaseth: or how can I be voyd of care, vnlesse I should grow altogither carelesse, being only subiect to woe, &amp; none so vnfortunate as my selfe, hauing indured so many afflictions &amp; crosses in all respects, that I know not how to assure my selfe of the least quiet? Then giue me leaue to continue my endlesse plaints, &amp; doo not blame me of impatiencie, nor think I suspect your speeches, or distrust your fidelitie, if in some sort I continue my sorrowes: for I haue so long continued in them, as I can better away with thē then mirth: for that to me is a stranger. Yet notwithstanding my hart will harbour some quiet, if by your curtesie I may rest in securitie, and bée sheltred from wrong. By this time they were arriued at their place of harbour, which was betwixt the hollow

of two Rocks, or rather Rockie Ilands, where their ship lay safe from weather, and so farre vnder their shadowe, that it could not bée séene. Themselues conueying such wealth as they from time to time got into hollow Caues, of great largenesse, where was al things necessarie; and the rest of Luprates fellowes called him vp. When hauing fastned their ship, Luprates brought Artesia into the Caue, who beholding the same, was surprised with an excéeding discomfort, of euer getting from thence.
            Some of the ruder sort liking Artesia, began their rude behauiour towards her, but Lupratus stepping vnto them, vttered these spéeches. My maisters, thus long haue I liued your Captaine in this place, with care respecting your good as much as mine owne, and taking but an equall share with you, of such prizes as wée haue taken, and rather the least part, now onely in respect of my faith and fidelitie, I request to haue this Damosell as my prize, the rest of the wealth take you. In dooing which, you shall binde mée vnto you for euer. One of the rest liking Artesiaes bewtie as well as hée, and of a more rude minde, disdaining that hée alone should haue her possession, said. Captaine, all which you say wée confesse to be true: neither hath our care bin any way lesse thē yours: therfore, there is no reason why you shuld claime any peculier priuiledge aboue any of vs: besides, you knowe wée made a law, and bound our selues to performe the same by oath, which was, that none should possesse any thing without the general consent of vs all. Then performe those conditions, and let her belong to vs all, or to the chiefest of vs, &amp; in so doing, neither of vs shall sustaine wrong: thus began they to contend about Artesia, euery one desirous to possesse her, &amp; yet neither willing any shuld haue her but himselfe, that they were likely to mu
                  •
               inie and fal out, till at the last they cōcluded to cast lots &amp; she fel to Luprates share, that was the most worthy of that priuiledge, for that hée bare the most vertuous mind. Thus for a time this strife was ended, and Artesia was by Luprates kindly vsed for many daies: in the end their victuals began to waste, &amp; they thought it high time to seek for more, y• they determined to fetch in some as before they had done.

But then began Luprates to take care in whose custodie to lea
                  ••
                
               Artesia, least in his absence they should do her wrong. Amongst the rest he chose out one whome he thought fittest, and to him hée committed her, by whose meanes Artesia rested voyd of disturbance, though not void of excéeding care that continually torment
                  •
               d her, fearing neuer to sée Ornatus againe, nor to be released from that place of bondage.
         
         
            CHAP. XII. How Ornatus found Artesia, and preserued her life: and how shee was againe taken from him by Lenon, and what afterwards befell.
            
               
                  LVprates and the rest, being landed, came in the night into the plaines to steale Cattell, and by chaunce lighted on the place where Ornatus haunted, being directed to him by the sound of his lamentations: Luprates demaunded what he was, I am (quoth he) a most miserable forlorne creature, by misfortune drawne to all extremitie. Then quoth hée, art thou not for our company: and with that they departed, leauing him ther
                  •
               . Ornatus heart began presently to misdoubt that they were the verie same that had taken Artesia from Allinus which made him presently studie how to haue them apprehended: remembring that he had heard many complaine that their cattell were often stolne, hée supposed verily them to be the théeues, that with all the haste hée could, he ranne to the next village and raised the Townes-men, telling them what he had seene, who presently issued out, and with such weapons as came next to hand followed the Pyrates, and soone found them, setting vppon them, tooke two of them, and the rest, some sore wounded &amp; hurt, fled to their Shippe, and with all the haste they coulde get to their harbour.
            
               Early the next morning, the inhabitants conueied the Pyrates to the Court, who being come before the King, confest the manner of theyr life, and where they liued. Then Lenon presentlie supposed, that they were the very same that had taken Artesia from Allinus, and demaunding the same of them, they tolde him that there was su
                  •
               h a Damosell in their Caue, and that shee tolde them her name was Artesia. Then Lenon without delay strōgly accompanied, rode to the next Hauen, and there gat shipping by the Pyrates directions, to finde out their fort. Ornatus likewise, after he had raised the people, secretlie followed the Pyrates vnto the place, where their ship lay, and amongst the rest entred the same: who by reason of their haste &amp; excéeding feare, regarded him not, who thrust himselfe into that daunger, onely to sée it Artesia were in their custodie, not reking how his life might be indangered thereby, but the Pyrates by Luprates directions hasted to the fort, and from thence tooke Artesia into their shippe, not daring to stay there, for that they knew some of their fellowes were taken, who might by compulsion be constrained to reueal
                  •
                the place of their abode.
            
               Ornatus no sooner espied Artesia, but he knew her, and his heart leapt within him for ioy to sée that happie sighte, but he durst not speake to her, nor scarce settle his eyes to behode her, for feare of suspect, for that Luprates meruailed how hee came amongst them: demaunding what hee was, and what hée made thrre? I am (quoth hée) a poore Pilgrim, that against my will was by some of this company constrayned to come aboord.
            
               Luprates beléeuing he said true, made no farther question, but with hast sayled from Phrygia, conueying A
                     •
                  tesia into his Cabin, vsing many spéeches to comfort her.
            They hadde not sayled many houres, but a contrary winde began to arise, and the Heauens were darkened with thicke Cloudes, and such a mightie tempest arose, that the shippe was by violence driuen backe, theyr maine Maste broken and throwne ouerboorde, and all in daunger of destruction, had not the land béene neare, for the shippe driuen

by violence of the Sea, ranne a grounde, and there splitte in sunder, and the Pyrates with great hazard escaped drowning: none of them nor Luprates once regarding Artesia, but Ornatus seeing in what perill she was, caught holde on her, and getting on to a planke, being withall somewhat skilfull to swimme, with much adoo ga
                  •
               e on to the firme lande, and preserued her from a miserable death by drowning.
            He was no sooner past daunger, but Luprates would haue taken her from him, but Ornatus séeing none but himselfe there, &amp; all the rest fled for feare, tolde him since he had forsaken her in extremitie, he was not worthie of her, and therefore should not haue her. Villaine (quoth Luprates) yéelde her me with quiet, or else thy life shall not deteine her. With that Ornatus caught holde on a boord which he cleft in sunder with his foote, and with the same gaue Luprates so suddaine and deadly a wounde, that the braines fell about the place, and he died. By this time the storme was quite ouerpast, and Ornatus séeing his deare Loue verie weake with feare and distemperature, by the arme led her vnto a mossie banke, where the Sunnes bright beames had full force to drie her garments dropping with wet.
            
               Artesia séeing howe tenderly this straunger regarded her, and with what paine he had preserued her, when she was of all but him forsaken, being willing to shewe that she was gratefull, said▪ Sir the paines you haue taken, and friendship you haue showne to me, deserue more thankes and recompence then I am able to giue: and therefore I desire you so thinke, that if I were able I would requite the same: but my mis
                  •
               ortunes are so excéeding, that they withholde me from dooing that I would: onely thankes is the small requitall I can yéelde in token of a gratefull minde: being by your meanes at more quiet then many dayes I haue bene, though more disquietted then you would iudge: but now I relie vpon your vertues, with hope thereby to be preserued, and not driuen to further miserie.
            Faire Ladie, (quoth Ornatus) my life shall be spent in your defence, neyther will I parte from you vntill I haue brought

you to the place which you desire, requesting you to make us doubt of my loyaltie. I suppose your name is Artesia, because (quoth hée) in my trauels I haue met a Gentleman of this countrey named Ornatus, of whome I learned the truth of many of your misfortunes: who I assure you is in good health. O bless
                  •
               d newes (quoth shée,) then will I hope once againe to se
                  •
                my deare Ornatus, whose absence hath beene my onely cause of woe.
            She had scarce ended those words, but Ornatus espied a ship euen then come a shore, where theirs was cast away, most of the men landed, which was the shippe wherein Lenon was, who beheld the other shippe cast away, and the storme being ceased arriued there. From whome Ornatus knewe not howe to hide himselfe: and Artesia not so much as thinking Lenon had bene in it, but that it was some ship that likewise by the storme was driuen to lande there. Presently the men beganne to spredde themselues euery way, and some of them soone espied Artesia, giuing Lenon knowledge thereof, who immediately came towardes her, most kindely saluting her, but shée beeing excéedingly dismayed with his sight, whome shée most mortally hated, for verie griefe burst into teares, that in aboundance gusht from her eyes.
            
               Lenon maruelling thereat, (and little thinking howe much shée hated him, and how vnwelcome he was) rather expecting thankes for his paines then reproofe, said; My deare Artesia, bee not now discomforted, since there is no further cause of care, I haue most diligently laboured to release you from griefe euer since Allinus by treason conueyed you from my custodie: taking your absence in great heauinesse, for that it pinched my heart to thinke you shoulde fall into suche distresse: but nowe that all those misfortunes are past, I beseech you goe with mée to the Court, where I will labour to procure your content.
            
               Artesias heart was vexed to heare his speeches, that she made him this answere.
            
               Most discurteous Lenon, none but your selfe are cause of my woe, whose sight more tormenteth mée, then all the afflictions I euer endured: Allinus carried me indéed from the gréene Fortresse, not by treason, but to shelter me from dishonour, which you did intend, else would you not haue inffered mee to endure such miseries as I did by my hellish kéeper. Thinke you I haue cause either to thinke you intend my good, or take any comfort by your presence, when you onely disquiet me, not suffering me to enjoy my libertie, but would perforce constrain me to that I cannot like. Had you left me in Adellenas house, then had I not fallen into such miseries as since that I haue endured, nor Allinus for his vertue haue bene brought to pouertie, that being before my professed enemie, séeing my miserie, it so mollified his heart, that he hath pittied me, and sought my libertie, and onely by crueltie, not by iustice, haue you sought his ouerthrow. Then I beseech you leaue me here, for I had rather indure the hazard of my misfortune, then liue to be tormented with your importunacie. Lenon was so amazed to heare her vnkind reply, litle thinking he had bene so much out of her fauour, that he could not tel what to say: sometimes thinking to leaue her there, and vtterly to forsake her, but that thought was soone ouercome by his affection or violent sting of desire to enioy her loue: that once againe he said; Why Artesia doo you regard my good will no more, then for my paines, to yéelde me rebukes: and for my loue, disdaine? That I caused you to be brought from Adellenas house, was, for that being there you were subiect to many misfortunes. And if I imprisoned Allinus, it was for that I supposed him your enemy, and feared he would haue done you wrong: so that whatsoeuer I did with intent of good, you repay me with dislike: &amp; conuert all my doings to the worst meaning: wherein you shewe your selfe too cruell, that will not yéeld me the least fauour for my constant loue. O Artesia be not so hard hearted, Artesia notwithstanding many faire promises, vowes, and protestations he made, would not yéeld to go with him, but desired rather that he would leaue her there. Lenon tolde her, though not for his sake,

yet for her safetie, it were best for her to goe: which said, he commaunded his seruants to place her in a Litter. Which when shée sawe shée must néedes doo, shee called to Ornatus, saying: Good Palmer go along with mée, that for the kindnesse you haue showen in preseruing my life, I may yéeld you some recompence. And (quoth shée) to Lenon, I request nothing of you for my selfe, but for this straunge Pilgrim, who when by the storme the ship was cast away, I readie to perish, caught me out of the water and preserued my life: and do not for his good will to me, vse him as you did my deare Syluian, whom you banished, for that she preserued my life from my vnkind vnckle, with that shee wept excéedingly. Then Lenon asked Ornatus what hée was, I am (quoth hée) as you see, a Pilgrim, that was forced to come aboord the Pyrates ship, and (amongst the rest) was readie to perish, but that by the diuine prouidence, I was ordained to preserue that vertuous Damosels life. For that déede quoth Lenon, I will reward you most kindly: therefore go along with vs. Then they all departed to the Court. Lenon presently caused Artesia to bée lodged in a most sumptuous place of the Court, appointing diuers Damsels to attend her, thinking by those meanes to win her to consent to loue him: but all proued vaine, his care was cast away, his cost to little effect, and his kindnesse vnregarded. For Artesia was so constant to Ornatus, that shée hated Lenon: her heart was wholly imployed to wish his good, and Lenons ill. For she determined neuer to loue him, though shee were assured of Ornatus death: that she spent her time in continuall care &amp; sadnesse, shewing no signe of ioy, no shewe of comfort, but euen as one that regarded no rest, nor tooke felicitie in any thing, that Lenon both admired the same, and laboured by many meanes to alter that humour: but the more hée sought to please her, the more she was displeased: and more discontented at his kindnesse then any thing else. In this sort she continued many dayes, without the least shewe of alteration.
            
               Ornatus all this while remaining in the Court, (making the cause of his state) to receiue Lenons promised reward, whereas

indéed he staied to sée what would become of Artesia, or by what meanes to get her from thence To effect which, he sawe no possible meanes, nor could in many dayes come to sée Artesia, which filled his heart with griefe: only comforted himselfe with remembring her constant loyaltie And one day being by himselfe alone, hée entered into these cogitations. Ornatus thou hast remained many dayes in this place, kept from thy Loue, and sought no meanes to set thy heart at rest, or her at libertie. Doost thou make no more account of her loue, then to attempt nothing to attaine the same? or are thy spirits of no more courage? then they will do nothing: thy wit so shallow, thou canst deuise no stratagem
                  •
               , or thy mind so cowardly, thou darest not reuenge the wrong Lenon doth shée? What though hée be the Prince and heire of this land, is not both hée and his father hated, ruling by vsurpation, and with crueltie, not with iustice, hath sought the downe-fall of thy house? Can Artesia thinke either valour or vertue to rest in thée, when shée shall know how neare thou art her soe, but darest not touch him? will shée not estéeme shee a coward and vnworthie to enioy her loue? Nay when shée knoweth this, will she not alter her loue? Why shouldest not thou séeke thy owne content, though it bée with his discontent? thou art euery way as good as hée by birth, though hée now rule the land: hath not thy father said, that his father was but a Captaine in the last Kings dayes, and by treason put his lawfull King to death, and so wanne the rule? Then Ornatus reuiue thy spirites, séeme not dismaied with any daunger feare not misfortune, séeke to release thy Loue, and venture thy life therein: for liuing thus thou shalt be depriued of her loue. Lenon will by force or faire meanes ouercome her, and then maiest thou blame this delaie. The King is now sicke, and hee being dead, Lenon must raigne, who then may do what hée list. Then take the aduantage of the time, and do not frostrate thy blessed hope
                  •
                with slothfull delaie. Hauing ended this m
                  •
               ditation, he then began to studie how to performe his will: wherein hée found many contrarieties. But presently he beheld Lenon entering the Court, before whome he stood so opposite, that he could

not chuse but note him, and withall remembred how earnestly Artesia had intreated him on the Pilgrims behalfe, whome he thought she estéemed, and therefore suddenly this cogitation arose in his fancie, to vse him as an instrument to win her loue: that calling Ornatus vnto him, hée said: Pilgrim, I pray 
                  •
               hée blame me not for forgetting to performe my promise made to Artesia as concerning thée, which I haue not neglected for want of good will, but by reason of thousands of cares that daily torment me, only procured by her vnkindnesse: but if thou wilt vndertake on my behalfe to perswade her to yéelde to my iust request, for that I thinke thou maist preuaile with her aboue any, I will not onely reward thy former kindnesse so shewen to her, but also for thy paines herein, promote thee to high dignitie. Therefore I pray thee giue consent to follow my counsel herein. Ornatus was willing to be imployed in that businesse, which fell out according to his hearts desire: and therfore made him this answere. My Noble Lord, for that I perceiue your intent is good, I will be readie to follow your directions, and do you any seruice I can: wherein I know not whether I shall proue fortunate or no: but assuring you that I will deale both faithfully and effectually in that which I shall vndertake.
            
               Lenon was as glad as he, that he yéelded to do that which he thought least to performe: and therefore presently gaue command, that the Pilgrim onely should haue her in custodie, Artesia maruelled that her keepers were chaunged, misdoubted some intent of hard vsage, but séeing it was the Pilgrim that now had her custodie, her heart was comforted.
         
         
            
            CHAP. XIII. How Ornatus had the custodie of Artesia: how he discouered himselfe vnto her: how Allinus and Trasus arriued in Armenia, and gat the King to send Ambassadors into Phrygia.
            
            
               
                  ORnatus at his first comming, found her sitting in the darkest corner of the Chamber, bewayling her misfortune, with salt teares bedeawing her purple cheeks: her ornaments disorderly put on, and her golden tresses hanging carelesly downe, which added bewtie to her swéete beawtie, and though disordered, most comely. Leaning her arme vppon a Chaire, and her chéeke laide vppon the backe of her hand: when hee beheld her sitting in this discomfortable sort, his hart was ready to melt with remorse: and hée breathed forth so bitter a sigh, that shée heard the same, which he perceiuing came towards her with humble behauiour, saying. Most vertuous Ladie, pardon my presumption, in presuming thus vnmannerly to interrupt your quiet: Lenon the Prince hath appointed me to be your attēdant, therefore I beséeche you, notwithstanding I am his substitute: commaund me in any doubtful sort, and I will most willingly imploy my vttermost indeuours to purchase your content. Artesia raising her selfe from the ground, said. Pilgrim, I thanke you for your kinde profer, and am glad you are my keeper, for two causes: one, for that I trust your vertues will not suffer me to be iniured, the other, for that I would heare out your discourse of my deare friend Ornatus, which I was hindred from by Lenons suddaine finding me. Ladie, (quoth he) you shalbe assured of the one, and heare more of the other, if first you will vouchsafe without offence, to heare my spéech, and suffer me to execute the charge Lenon hath giuen mée, and I haue vndertaken. Why what is

that (quoth Artesia) I wil not be offended? Lenon hath made knowne to me his loue, and how long, and with what constancie it is grounded, commaunding and intreating me in his behalfe to become an humble suter vnto you: he telleth me that stil you vngently disdain him without cause, reason, or consideration. Therefore I humbly desire, both for that he is constant, a Prince, and of good and vertuous gifts, yéelde to his loue or else to satisfie me of the chiefest reasons that withold you from the same. Pilgrim (quoth she) for that my minde perswadeth me, you in wisedome will conceiue of reason: and will be faithfull in concealing that which I shall disclose: I answere you thus. First, admit Lenon did loue mée (yet by his vsage I finde the contrary) nor I cannot fancie him, for that I alreadie haue plighted my faith to another, more worthie then himselfe, which is that most vertuous &amp; kinde Gentleman Ornatus, who likewise equalleth me in affection: and therefore I should dishonour my name, breake my faith, and reape perpetuall infamy, if I should shewe my selfe so inconstant. These I thinke are reasons (to a reasonable creature) sufficient, and of such force, as none can contradict: and therefore no more can be said therein. Besides were not all this so, you haue no reason to perswade me to that which I haue so often denied, and will neuer yéeld vnto. Your reasons indéed (quoth he) are great, and the cause such, as should no way be violated: but now you are subiect to his mercie: and he may inforce you to that which you are most vnwilling to haue done: then what remedie haue you, but rather to yéelde, then indure such extremitie as he may vse? Yes, (quoth she) when I can preserue my selfe no longer from his lust, death shall rid mee from his power, which I will execute vpon my selfe, rather then condiscend to yéeld him so much as an outward shewe of fauour. Therefore I pray vse no more words tending to the breach of my faith, and furtherance of his loue, for kne
                  •
                you but how hatefull his name were vnto me, and howe odio
                  •
               s to thinke of his doting loue, you would of pittie desist to 
                  •
               orment one with the sound of that ominous monster, but rather seeke to comfort my distressed 
                  •
               tate, and poore pining heart, almost

most drowned with sorrow: being more vnfortunate, then euer any was by these afflictions, and the losse of my déere Ornatus, whose presence should release me from this thraldome, and labyrinth of discontent. Of whom if you can tell me any tidings, I beséech you impart them vnto me: thereby to adde comfort to mittigate my care.
            
               Ornatus was so rauished to heare her vtter such heauenly spéeches, that he had much adoo to refraine from imbracing her: vttering these spéeches. How happie is Ornatus by attaining the loue of so vertuous and constant a Ladie, worthy to be admired, eternized, and for euer honored? what comfort may these pleasing words bring to his heart? What torment can be not account pleasure, indured for so swéet a Ladies safety? and what paines should he refuse to procure her swéet content? O Artesia, diuine Artesia, Ornatus is not able to expresse his content, nor your desert: vnable to recompence your kindnesse, and euerlastingly bound to you in all f
                  •
               r
                  ••
               e bands of faithfull loyaltie. In your heart is the harbor of true loyaltie, grounded vpon vertuous loue. Then how happie is he by being inriched, and possest of such a loue? His reward is greater then his paine: his pleasure more then euer his sorrowe could be: and his gaines a thousands times beyond his losse. Why shuld I then conceale the troth of his safetie from you? With that he said: Behold Artesia, your Ornatus: with that he discouered himselfe vnto her, &amp; she perfectly knewe him. Being almost amazed with that heauenly sight: when with a swéete behauiour, they both imbraced eache other, intermingling their kisses, with teares of ioye that in aboundance distilled from their eyes, surfetting so much in that sweete delight, that they were loath to part, but that feare to be espied, compelled thm. Taking such excéeding com
                  •
               ort in each others presence, as is not to be expres
                  •
               : withal, vsing many kindnesses vsuall betwixt faithfull friends, to expresse their ioy, hée somtimes imbr
                  •
               cing her, &amp; she againe with a sweet kisse, welcomming him, being so many, kinde, and hartie, as wold ask a skilfull discretiō. At last hauing somewhat recreated themselues, and with sodaine ioy bannisht some part of their care, they thought it

time to studie how to procure their happinesse, least ye same might againe be crost by Lenon. Who by that time expected to heare from him. Therefore Ornatus said? My most deare and kind Artesia, by whose loue my life is preserued. I am not able to expresse the ioy my heart conceiueth, by this fortunate méeting, béeing likewise as sory to thinke of the misfortune you haue indured by my carelesse ouersight, and how to get you from this place, and from Lenons affection, whom I know to bée of such vnciuill a disposition, that he will leaue no disloyall meanes vnattempted to further his intent.
            Therefore in this vrgent extremitie, if you will be contented to estéeme me as your friend, and follow my directions, I will labor all that I can to get you from this place. My true friend Ornatus (said Artesia) I haue dedicated my self to your disposition, and made my selfe all one with you, both in heart, body, and minde, that whatsoeuer you would wish your selfe, you do to me, &amp; whatsoeuer pleaseth you, cānot displease me, for I am your selfe: therfore I commit all things to your wisdome &amp; rest to be ruled, counselled and ordered by you, in whatsoeuer you shall thinke conuenient: and will doo any thing you shall counsaile me vnto, both for our escape from hence, or otherwise: accounting my blisse yours, and yours mine, your cares mine, and your quiet, my content.
            
               Lenons loue is most hatefull vnto me, and iniutie to you, then what meanes can you work to ridde me, of that and reuenge your owne wrong, performe, for my consent is readie to yéeld to any thing you shall thinke conuenient.
            I most humbly thank you, said Ornatus, and first I think this is the best course, to procure my good liking with him, and to rid vs from hence, that at his next comming, you shewe a little more friendly contenance vnto him, then heretofore you haue done, as shall best agrée with your wisdome, and he perceiuing that my seruice hath done more for him then euer he could attaine, will not only credit me, but also be ruled by mée in any thing I shall counsa
                  •
               le him vnto. Which if you will performe cōmit the rest to me My deer Ornatus at your request I wil do this, which otherwise

I would neuer of my selfe yéelde vnto, for that my loue to you, and hate so him, would not suffer me so much to dissemble: but I pray God deliuer me well from forth of his power, that I may in quiet enioy your swéete company. These spéeches being ended, they parted with a swéete kisse, he sighing, and she for griefe shedding teares. Not long after Lenon came to Ornatus, requesting to know whether he had preuailed any thing with Artesia in his behalfe▪ My Lord (quoth he) I haue vsed many perswasions to her, which in some sort haue preuailed, but hereafter I doo not doubt by my perswasions, but to winne her full consent: if you with wisdome will be directed by me, and not with rashnesse marre all: therefore goe in vnto her, but not to rashly, and sée if she be not altered, Lenon imbraced him in his armes, saying: thou bringest me tydings of exceeding comfort, for which I will reward thee most bountifully, With that he gaue him a purse of gold: which Ornatus tooke, thinking that should be a meanes to further him, and hinder the giuer Lenon entred Artesias chamber, vsing many kinde speeches and submisse behauiours, whome she vsed more kindly then euer she had before done, which both filled his heart with ioy, and made him according to the Pilgrims directions, more carefull of his behauiour, least by any boldnesse he might offend her, that hauing past some small time with her, he departed.
            Now was Ornatus studying how to release Artesia, to further whose intent, the o
                  •
               casion thus fell out. Allinus and Trasus as is before said, gate shipping for Armenia, and arriued there with safetie: first directing their course to the Kings Pallace, where Allinus was most honourably entertained, being somewhat allied to the King, to whome he declared both the cause of his exile, and the iniury done to him by Thaeon, king of Phrigia. Turbul
                     •
                  s the Armenian King, comforted him all that he could, and bad him withall, request any thing at his hande &amp; hee would graunt it him. Allinus alledging many things to perswade T
                     ••
                  
                  bulus to yeeld thereto, requested him to send Ambassadours into Phrygia, either to request performance of certaine articles, or

else to giue him open defiance for war. The articles were these: that Allinus shoulde bée restored to his lands, and the dammage and losse he had sustained, should bée repaied to the full, that his wife should bée recalled from banishment, and that he should yéeld vp Artesia to Allinus, if shée should bée in his custodie and that the King and Lenon should bee sworne to performe all this. Turbulus was easily wonne, and therefore presently sent foure of his Noble men as Ambassadors, to request the performance of those conditions. Who euen at that instant were landed in Phrygia, and newes thereof brought to the Court, the King being himselfe somewhat sickly, sent Lenon to méete them, and giue them entertainment: who was loth to go from Artesias sight, but assuring himselfe of the Pilgrims faith, committed her wholly to his custodie. Ornatus thought it now the fittest time to séeke to escape, but he was hindred by other of Lenons seruants, whome he had secretly appointed as ouerseers to looke into the Pilgrims action: that it was impossible for him to attempt any thing that way, but it must needs both be discouered and preuented. Ornatus séeing himselfe disappointed of his purpose that way, made Artesia acquainted with what hée intended, and how he was preuented, spending the time of Lenons absence continually in her company. But hauing met the Armenian Ambassadors, brought them to the Court, where they were honourably entertained, and hauing declared their Embassage, Thaeon the King, tolde them they should receiue answere within two daies.
            
               Lenon hearing the articles, counselled his father not to yéeld to performe any such conditions, but rather to send Turbulus defiance For (quoth hee) your Maiestie are as absolutely King of Phrygia, as hee of Armenia, and then what dishonour were it vnto you to stoope to his commaund, and shewe your selfe as it were affraid of his threats? for to binde your selfe to this, were to become his subi
                  •
               ct: which would soone be published through the whole world to your dishonour. The King being ouerruled by his perswasions, gaue the Ambassadours this answere, that hée went not 
                  •
               o performe the least of those articles they demaunded,

nor feared their Kings threats of warre, for that hee was able to deale with a mightier foe then hée. Vsing many other words, and some of reproach, that the Armenians denouncing open warre according as they were commanded, departed.
         
         
            CHAP. XIIII. How Ornatus staying too late in Artesiaes chamber, was accused by Lenons seruants, whom he slew. How Allinus with a band of Armenians landed in Phrygia: and how Ornatus was imprisoned.
            
               
                  THaeon knew that the King of Armenia wold performe his word, and therefore gaue Lenon charge to muster vp men throughout the whole land: cōmitting the chiefe charge of the Armie and ordering of these affaires, vnto him, who more hardie bold, then wise, vndertooke all, and within short space, had gathered an exceeding great Armie, and furnished certaine shippes, to méete with the Armenians by Sea if it might bee possible, to vanquishe them before they shoulde land.
            These troubles fi
                  •
               led the Commons hearts with griefe, and their mouths with murmurings: for they vnderstanding that the King of Armenia did offer warre to Phrygia, in the behalfe of Allinus that was generallie beloued: there was fewe of those that were prest to those warres, but came vnwillinglie, and rather by constraint, being more readie to turne their swoord points against Thaeon, then against Allinu
                     •
                  .
            
            
               Ornatus likewise hearing of these warres, by his wisedome found out the opinion of the multitude, and with what vnwillingnesse they came to the warres, which when hee was in some sort assured off, hee came to the Campe, and amongst all the

rest of his Familiars, espied Phylastes, who alwaies loued him most dearely, him hee knewe to bee of a most faithfull and constant resolution, in performing his promise, and was by Lenon appointed one of the chéefest leaders.
            
               Ornatus finding him remote from the Camp, came to him, and after salutation, said: Sir Phylastes, I am sent vnto you by a deare friend of yours, named Ornatus who trusteth so much in your vertues, that he is willing to put his life into your hands, which you shall hazard, in denying him one small fauour, which with safetie you may graunt. First therefore, I request but your promise for your warrantie, and then I will declare what I haue in charge.
            My friend (quoth Phylastes) thou tellest me newes of wonder, when thou sayest thou comest from Ornatus, whom I feare is long since dead: but if thou knowest the contrary, and canst resolue me thereof, I promise and sweare to performe whatsoeuer thou shalt demaund: for I am sure Ornatus knoweth that I loue him, nor maketh any doubt thereof, which if hee doo, he iniurieth that loue and friendship that hath past betwéene vs.
            Then kinde sir (quoth he) that Ornatus is not dead, but in safetie, and I am that Ornatus, that notwithstanding my spéech, make no doubt of your loue.
            
               Phylastes beholding his countenance, knewe him well, and for ioy caught him in his armes. My deare friend Ornatus (quoth hee) I am gladde of your safetie, and accursed bee my soule▪ if I doo not any thing that you shall commaund.
            I thanke you (quoth Ornatus) to enter into the tedious discourse of my afflictions, would be tedious: but in few words I will tell you all. I loued Artesia long, but found no hope nor meanes to attaine my loue, which made mee disguise my selfe into womans apparell, naming my selfe Syluian, and was fortunately entertained by Arbastus, whose death I founde to bee acted by Floretus, who falling into loue with m
                  •
               e tolde

mée for my sake he would poyson Artesia at the Lodge, whither hee conueyed her, I fearing to haue her taken from me, and hauing wonne her loue, tolde her his intent, and conueyed her to Adellenas house: then Floretus and Lenon came thither, demanding her of me, whom I tolde I had poysoned her, according to his counsell: wée striuing, were brought before Thaeon, who banished me into Natolia, from whence I came backe, and by good fortune haue the kéeping of Artesia in this disguise, the manner I will tell you at more leisure. Now my deare friend Phylastes, my desire is to chaunge my place with you, you to haue the custodie of A
                     •
                  tesia in my Palmers wéedes, and I to march into the field in your Armour, which if you graunt, you shall bind mee vnto you for euer. Phylastes yéelded to fulfill his request, and so for that time they parted, appointing to méete the next day. Ornatus being come to Artesia, told her where he had bene, and what hee intended, which made Artesia sad, disswading him from his purpose in this sort: My deare Loue, what néed you venture your person in the daungers that are incident to war? will you leaue me heare in doubt, and not rather staie with me to my comfort? there are inough besides and too many in the field, and Phylastes is able to execute his own place: then I beséech you do not leaue mée in discomfort, for how can I be voyd of care, when I shall thinke you are amonst so many enemies readie to be slaughtered? My deare Loue (quoth he) that which I will do shalbe without any hazard at all, but shall procure both your and mine owne content. Then I beséech you remit this care for my safetie, for I will preserue my selfe from daunger for your sake. Besides Phylastes vertue is such, that you néed not once so much as thinke amisse of him: who I knowe would venture his life for my sake. Besides, my honor vrgeth mée, reuenge of iniuries done to your selfe and me, and my fathers safetie, are reasons sufficient to perswade your consent: besides many other causes more forcible then these, too tedious to recite. Then I beséech you denie me not: for when it shall be knowne that my father was in armor in the field, and I in this place not regarding to aide him, it wil turne to

my great dishonour: and those which before did estéeme well of me, will then begin to hate me: then let not your doubt and true loue to me, hinder my determination: for on that mine honour, your safetie, and my fathers life dependeth. Artesia seeing shee could by no meanes disswade him, thought not to let him depart so suddenly, but cla
                  •
               ping her tender armes about his necke, a thousands times kist his lippes, whilest with her abundant teares shee bedeawed his manly cheekes. Ornatus tooke great sorrow at her heauinesse, and delight in her imbracings, that the contrarieties of his conceits were excéeding: pleasure it selfe, séeming more pleasant intermingled with care, and care a pleasure to be endured with such delight. Artesia was loath to let Ornat
                     •
                  s depart that night, for that shée déemed hée should be in daunger the next 
                  •
               ay, and hée as vnwilling to leaue her in sorrowe: shee on the one side sollacing her selfe in his company, and hée by her kindenesse making him forget to depart, that before they were aware, night was come and well spent, and Ornatus then bethinking himselfe, thought it was too late to depart. And Artesia, hearing him make a motion to be gone, desired him to staye. And yet my deare Ornatus (quoth she) doe not you indaunger your selfe for my sake, for should Lenons seruants finde you heere, it might redo
                  •
               nd to our great disquiet. Ornatus likewise well considering the inconuenience, tooke his leaue of her, and left her sheadding aboundance of teares. Ornatus being gone, found the seruants awake, and watching his comming out, one of them saying; Pilgrim what maketh thée so sawcie as to court my Maisters Loue? Is this a fitte time of the night to be in her chamber? my Lord shall vnderstand your behauiour, and what familiaritie is betwixt you: wee take you to be some counterfeit, else would not such behauiours passe betwixt you as we haue behelde. Therefore héere shall you staye, vntill we giue him knowledge of your dooings and fidelitie: with that they lockt fast the doore, not suffering him to goe out or in. Ornatus by that perceyued that they ha
                  •
                seene the kindenesse betwixt him and A
                     •
                  tesia, which he knewe if Lenon should vnderstand, hee would finde out what he was: these thoughts troubled

his heart excéedingly, that hée was assured vnlesse he could bée rid of them, there was no meanes to escape death, if Lenon should knowe him. With these studies hee sat a good while silent, till hee perceiued them inclinde to sleepe, and casting his eye aside, espied a bill hanging by the wall, to which hee stole secretly, and taking hold of the same, he drew towards them, entring into these meditations. And shall I now commit murder, and indanger my soule by so hainous a sin? what will Artesia say if she know thou art so bloodily bent? and that thy heart is so hard, as to shead thine own countrey mens blood? Ornatus be wel aduised before thou do this déed, and bethink of some other meane: auoid the danger thou art readie to fall into. Other meanes Ornatus, yea but what other meanes hast thou? none at all, dost thou not sée how they haue betrayed thee, and made thée prisoner, what then needest thou make a question, to saue thy selfe, and by their deathes preserue thine owne life? which thy liuing, will be indangered, and being once done, thou art safe, but by delay, thy owne life may perish. With that lifting vp his armes with more then woonted force, hée smote the one on y• head, &amp; beate out his braines: wherewith y• other began to awake: but in his awaking, he strooke him so full on ye brest, that the bill piearst his heart, and hée laye breathlesse sprawling in his gore. This done, Ornatus foūd a vaw
                  •
               e and into the same hée cōueied their dead bodies, purposing neuer to reueale what he had don. Then returning, he bethought himself of the keies of ye dores that hee had thrown into yt vawte with their bodies, deuising how to get out, without suspition of the deed he had done, y• hée was inforced to take the bill, &amp; by maine force, and often striuing, wroong asunder the locks. His minde being excéedingly affrighted with these cares, he entred into Artesias chāber, to sée whether he had disquieted her or no with the noise, her he foūd in bed, &amp; fast a sleep with the light still burning by her-beds side, her brest vncouered downe to the waste, and nothing to shrowde her from his perfect view, but the single sheete, that say carelesly cast ouer her tender bodie, her armes c
                  •
               st to either side of the bed, and her head leaning on the one side, with so sweete an aspect, as would haue rauished

a thousand beholders. Ornatus heart was reuiued to behold this swéet sight, that the remembrance therof had bannished all remembrance of his troubles past, and affected his heart with incomparable delight: that he stood like one amazed to behold her swéet beawtie, and to take a surfetting viewe of those her perfections, so amiably faide forth. Artesia sodainly awaking blusht to see him so nie, yet therwith more comforted then dismayed she caught the clothes and couered her selfe▪ whilest hée folding his hand in hers, desired pardon for his boldnesse: but she viewing him well, behelde his pale and gastly countenance, which draue her into feare, and raysing her selfe vpright in her bed, caught him in her armes, asking what he ayled to looke so pale: M
                  •
                deare Artesia (quoth hée) since I parted from you, I haue endured great danger, &amp; past through 
                  •
                hell of calamities, which now I feare not. With that he let his head fall into her sweete bosome, and there made the period of his spéeche, feeling her tender heart pant, with the motions of her troubled spirits. In which pallace hée rested it a good while, whilest she wt her soft hand curled his haire, and with swéet kisses, mollified his lips. Vsing many other familiarities, &amp; sweete fauors, procéeding from the depth of kinde loue, wherwith Ornatus was so rauished, that hée not onely took heauenly comfort therin, but also desired a further content, &amp; possession of her loue, which he neuer before asked, nor thought she wold grant, but being hartned by the assurance of her Loue, hée vsed more bolde behauiour, which shée permitted: but at last growing more bolde then shée thought conuenient for her modestie to permit, with a kinde and louely behauiour, shée both blamed and hindred him, but the motions of affection so far preuailed with them both, that hée desired, and shée inwardlie yeelded, though outwardly shée refused, but his behauiour, her owne Loue, the present occasion, so fitte opportunitie, their hearts vnitie, and other sweete enticements, so farre preuailed, that shée yéelded vp her vnspotted body, &amp; pure chastitie, to his possession, and the impression of his attempt, dissolued her Virgin zo
                  •
               ne, giuing full interests of her heart, Loue, and body, to him, that pursued the possession of those riches, with earnestnesse: Sometimes blushing, sometimes shréeking, and yet yéelding,

denying, and yet graunting, willing and vnwilling: yet at last, she gaue that she could not recall, and let him possesse her spotlesse virginitie, which béeing past, her heart panted with the motion, and she felt her sences sadde, a little repenting, yet not al
                  •
               ogither sory: sighing for sadnesse, and yet not sad at all: whilest hée bathed himselfe in that hauen of Blisse, passing the rest of that night in such vnspeakeable pleasure as cannot be desciphered. Early the next morning hee arose▪ taking his farewell with a swéete Adie
                  •
               , leaui
                  •
               g Artesia sad for sorrowe, and lamenting his absence, but yet with earnest and hearty prayers, inuocating his happie successe: bathing her heart in luke-warme t
                  •••
               es, thinking she had béene too prodigall of her fauours to him, and yet estéeming him worthie of a thousand times greater gyft, if shée had it in her possession, with repentance reioycing, though déeming herselfe metamorphose, and other then shée was w
                  •
               nt to be, beeing glad shée had no more companie to conuerse withall; least her guilt should make her blush, and so bewraye her fault. And when Phoebus began to lighten the Chamber with his splendor, the hid herselfe within the bed, as if the day-light had accused her of that shee had done in the darke. Ornatus béeing come to the Campe, found out Phylastes, and brought him to Artesia
                     •
                  s lodging, by the way instructing him howe to order their businesse when Lenon should come. Where béeing entered, Phylastes hauing saluted Artesia, and a while conuersed about their affaires, they chaunged their habits. Ornatus with many a sorrowfull sigh taking his leaue of her; whilst her heart bled warme 
                  •
               rops of bloud. Ornatus againe tooke his leaue of Artesia, and entered the Campe, framing himselfe to such kinde of behauiour, that hée was of all taken for Phylaste
                     •
                  . N
                  •
               wes cam
                  •
                
               
                  •
               hat the Armenians were landed and had brought their Forces within a dayes march of T
                     •
                  aeons Campe, the King 
                  •
               ssembled all the chiefe Leaters together, to 
                  •
               ppoynt euery man his charge, and consult what to doe. Ornatus in Phylastes stead, had vnder his charge foure thousand men, whom by his owne séeking hee was appointed to conuoye into a wood that stood fitly to offend the ennemie, and the rest appointed to other

places that seemed for most aduantage. Ornatus hauing his souldiers alone, thought it time to execute what he intended, and therefore called vnto him such as were Captaines and chiefe vnder him, vttering these speeches Fellow souldiers, I would willingly vtter my mind which is troubled in some sort with remembrance of the iniuries. Allinus hath alreadie causelesly indured, against whome now wee addresse our selues to fight: wherein in my mind wee deale vniustly: for he was neuer traytor to his countrey, nor now commeth to disturbe the land with oppression, but only to claime his own inheritance and libertie, which our selues do permit: therefore I thinke it best before wée drawe our weapons, to consider against whome we drawe them, and whom we offend, one that loueth vs, his Countrey and people, and would not willingly shead a drop of our blood. Now if I could find a remedie for all this, which standeth with equitie, would you follow my directions? With that they all at once said, they would be ruled by him Then hée said, Thaeon that is now our King, destroyed all his familie, and such as are in any degrée neare to him in blood, the last of whome is Allinus, whose vtter ruine hee now séeketh, not by iustice▪ but that neitheir he nor any of his progenie should hinder his succession. Therefore if you wil follow my counsell, when the armies ar
                  •
                met let be not offer to offend the Armenians, but kéepe our selues from fight, vntill Lenon affrighted therewith, and fearing the peoples reuolt, will peraduenture yéeld to performe the articles the A
                     •
                  menian Embassadors demaunded: and by this meanes shall wee restore All
                     •
                  n
                     •
                  s to his right, saue the effusion of blood, and yet not wrong our reputation. The people hearing his spéeches, generally gaue their consent: crying, Phylastes, Phylastes. With that Ornat
                     •
                  s bestowed the golde among them that Lenon had before giuen him, which preuailed with the multitude excéedingly. Ornatu
                     •
                  
                hauing effected this according to his desire, went vnto the A
                     •
                  m
                     •
                  nian Campe, desiring to speake with Allinus the Generall, to whom he declared what he intended in his behalfe, not discouering him to be other then Phylastes. For which Allinus yeelded him many

har
                  •
               y thanks. Whilest Ornatus was absent, a Captaine named Ortonus, drawne by desire of reward, and aboue the rest fauouring Lenons party, stole from the wood, and comming into the Campe to Lenon, bewrayed what Phylastes intended, and how that hée was now gone to the Armenian Campe, to confer with Allinus.
            
            
               Lenon hearing that, thought it best, not to send for him by warrant, but amongst the rest, to assemble him to councell: and to that effect, sent a Herault. Ornatus being returned had knowledge of the generall assemblie, and willinglie went, little suspecting what Lenon intended, and being entred the Camp, &amp; Lenons Tent, he was before all the Estates, by a Herault arrested of high treason. Ornatus thē thought his intent was bewraied, demanding what they could lay to his charge: Wherevpon Ortonus before them all, declared what he had done, which he could not denie, vppon which accusation, he was presently sent to the Court, and there imprisoned.
         
         
            CHAP. XV. Howe Ornatus was deliuered out of prison &amp; carried Artesia from the court. How Ornatus in a single combat, ouercame Lenon, and caused Thaeons flight. And how Artesia to escape Thaeon, fled to Adellenaes house.
            
               TThe newes of Ornatus imprisonment was soone blazed through the whole camp, court, and country, &amp; at last came to Artesia hearing, who with excéeding lamentations bewailed his misfortune, but Phylastes comming vnto her, cōforted her all that he could, promising to set Ornatus at libertie (if quoth he) at Lenons next comming, yo
                  •
                will request his signet, to keepe as his warrant for your safetie. The next day the armies should méete, and therefore Lenon that night visited Artesia, finding her very sad, demanding the cause thereof: my Lord (quoth she how

can I be otherwise then sad, when I am ready euery houre to fall into more miserie, not knowing whither your life may be indangered by these warres, and I thereby subiect to some misfortune. Therefore in signe you loue mée, graunt me your signet, to bee my warrant and priuiledge, against all iniurie y• may bee offered mee: with y• shee kist him, which she had neuer be
                  •
               ore done, not drawne by any good will, but with desire to helpe Ornatus. Lenons heart was so ouercome, that hée presently gaue her the same, staying sometime with her, intreating her consent to his loue. He was no sooner gone, but Phylastes taking the ring of Artesia, went vnto the place where Ornatus was, and comming to the Iayler, tolde him that hée must deliuer Ornatus to his custodie, shewing him the Princes signet, as his warrāt: the Iailer séeing the same, and knowing that the Pilgrim was of great credit &amp; trust with Lenō, made no doubt, but presently deliuered Ornatus vnto him: both departing together, to Artesia, who séeing her beloued so fortunately deliuered shead teares of ioy for his escape. After salutations in the kindest sort past, Ornatus declared what hée intended, and howe hée was betrayed by Ortonus. Phylastes then counselled Ornatus, that night to conuey Artesia from thēce, vnto some place of better securitie, who sometimes thought to carrie her to Adellenaes house, but he thought Lenon wold misdoubt yt place, at last he concluded to conuey her to her castle, where Arbastus her father dwelt, which was still kept to her vse, by certaine of her fathers seruants. Foth Artesia &amp; Phylastes liked 
                  •
               his well, and therefore leauing the court, they departed thitherwards, Artesia not woonted to trauell, could scarcely indure to holde out, but by their help, they arriued there at midnight &amp; knocking, awaked the por
                  •
               er, who looking ouer the battlemēts, demanded who was below at that vnreasonable time of the night: My friend quoth Ornatus, it is Artesia that commeth in time of her most need, for harbor in this place. The Porter viewing her well by the bright light of Scynthia, &amp; knew her, calling vp the rest of his fellowes, came running down, and opened the gate, where he and the rest, receiued her in with great ioy.
            
               
               Ornatus was glad of this happie escape, but yet excéeding sad that he could not assist his father against Lenon, but that he must perforce be absent from his rescue, which filled his heart with such care, that all that night he could take no rest, and though hee enioyed Artesias company without controll, he could harbor no rest or quiet to his distempered thoughts: that Phylastes demanded the cause of his sadnesse. My assured friend Phylastes (quoth hée) the remembrance of my fathers estate, and feare of his mishap, maketh me thus sad, and griefs excéeding torment possesseth mee, that I cannot be present to aide him against Lenon, that by towardly malice, not with valour, will seeke his ruine before any others. O were I but present to defend him, though I offended none, my heart would bée at quiet. Artesia hearing his speeches said; Good Ornatus do not againe hazard your selfe, as you lately did: for had not fortune and Phylastes wisedome, assisted v
                  •
               , both your life, and with it mine, had bene cast away. My dear
                  •
                
               Artesia (quoth hée) that misfortune hath taught mée wisedome, and by remembring it, I wil learne to esch
                  •
               e such mischiefes, and know whome I trust: therefore I beséech you, grant I may once againe go to do my 
                  •
               utie in ayding my father, which I will nowe do without daunger, for that I wil make none priuie to that I intend, nor attempt more then I am able to performe. Artesia seeing howe fully hée was vent to goe, preferd his will before her owne desire, knowing her dutie not to contradict, but to counsell him, and therefore said; My deare Ornatus, my dutie bindeth me to consent, but my loue willeth me to denie: feare of your mishap maketh mée vnwilling, but will to fulfill your desire, maketh mée giue 
                  •
               n vnwilling consent: onely let me request this, that you will take Phylastes in your company and leaue me to the custodie of my seruants, whose fidelitie I am assured of: for hauing him with you, hi
                  •
                aid
                  •
                and counsell may much auaile to preserue your life, which if you loose (as heauens forbid) with the same shal mine expire for if so impossible Artesia should breathe, Orna
                     •
                  us being breathlesse. Ornatus with a fewe teares that by excéeding griefe were wroong from his heart, participated her laments.

First requesting the seruants to be carefull of her good, and then without delaye, both furnishing himselfe and Phylastes, with rich armor and horse, of which there was great choyce in that Castle: and for that the day began to appeare, they thought it time to depart, least their comming from thence might be discouered: There might one behold sorrow at parting in his right forme, hart-breaking sighes, breathing sad Farewels, and sorrowfull teares at so sad a parting, when their lippes were parted, their hands still fast, their hands disioynd, then their voyces oftentimes vttering, that woful word, Farewell: and when they were past hearing, their eyes vnwillingly leauing each others sight, he being without looking backe, and shée within looking after, so long as she could perceiue the glimering glance of his bright armor, and he being pass sight of her, with watry eyes beholding the place of her abode, thus parted they, as if they had parted neuer to méete. Drawing nigh the armies, they beheld them met and in hot skirmish, standing still a good space, to sée to whether partie it was likely the victorie would incline: and in the ende they beheld the Armenians begin to retrait, and Lenon with Thaeon his Father in the midst of the throng, making excéeding slaughter, and proud of their déemed conquest: which set Ornatus heart on fire, that hée rusht amongst the thickest of his Countrey men, yet not once offering a blow, nor sheading a drop of the bloud he loued, but onely making way to come to Lenon, which made them not offer to staye his passage: but admiring what he was, let him goe frée; after whom Phylastes hasted. The Souldiers séeing those two newe come Knightes offende none, admired what they should be, not one of them all offering a blow, because they offered none. By this time Ornatus was come to the place where Lenon was, who euen then &amp; not before had met Allinus, betwixt whom many blowes and some woundes were giuen and receiued, but Allinus had the worst by reason of his age. Ornatus knowing his Father by his armour, came betwixt them with his sword drawne, saying: Lenon staye thy hand: let age goe frée, and let thy youth cope with mée, that am come to challenge thée before both the Armies: and

therefore as thou art the Kings Son, a knight and honorest arms, giue order by thy Herault, to staye the furie of the Battailes, till thou and I haue tryed our valours, otherwise this Knight and I haue vowed to huht thée from place to place, and neuer giue ouer, vntil wée haue spilt thy bloud.
            
               Lenon, hearing this Champions proud challenge, sayd: If thou art a knight, a gentleman as I am, and canst shewe wherein I haue wronged thee, I will answere thée, otherwise knowe, that I scorne thée, although I know my selfe of sufficient strength to abate thy haughty presumption, were it neuer so great. With that two heraults were sent from either General, to part the souldiers, which done, Ornatus before the open assembly said. Lenon, first I saye I am a Gentleman, as absolute and as good as thy selfe: Prince I am none, neither art thou by right, but that by tyrannie and vsurpation thou holdest the same. I come as Artesias Champion, to challenge thée of disloyalty, as the outrages thou hast committed, by detaining her libertie, do manifest. I challenge thée for dooing iniustice against Allinus, whom thou withholdest from his right, by trecherous malice. I challenge thée, as a partaker of Arbastus death, for that thou sufferest and vpholdest his murtherer Floretus, that hath deserued death. I challenge thée for oppression laid vpon this whole land. And lastly, for detaining Ornatus liuing, who neuer was impeached of treason: and therefore if thou darest answere my challenge, I am here readie, otherwise, I here pronounce thée for a coward, &amp; a miscreant, not worthie to beare Armes. Lenon made this replie. Being accused by a straunger, without cause, I regarde it not, and béeing iudge my selfe, will not by thée be adiudged: but for thy proude challenge, I will answere thée, as little regarding what thou canst doo, as thou boastingly dost vaunt of thy valor. Therefore euen now before I deport, I will without delay abate thy haughtinesse, though thy accusations are manifestly false: for I both loue and esteeme Artesia as deerely as I doe my selfe: my title to the Crowne, is iust: for Allinus hee is both a traitor at home, and abroade: first in causing his comp
                  •
               ices to séeke my fathers life: and lastlie, for bringing these Armenian
               
bands, to destroye the Countrey. For Floretus pardon, it is mercie, not iniustice. As for oppression done to Ornatus, all knowe, I neuer iniuried him: but if hée take the Iustice that is done to his traiterous father, as done to him, I cannot helpe that: but reuenge it thou, since thou art his Champion. Ornatus had much adoo to stay to heare out his speeche, which galled him to the very heart, that without speaking a word more, hee smote at Lenon, and Lenon with courage, answered his blowes, beginning a most flerce and forceable incounter, and with like furie continuing the same, til both had receiued many wounds, and their steeds beganne to be furious and madde, with the smart of some strokes that mist their ayme.
            
               Ornatus calling to remembrance, first the iniuries he had receiued, and that Lenon &amp; none else could dispossesse him of Artesias Loue, and many other wrongs he had done him and his parents, thought nowe to reuenge them all, and dispossesse Thaeon of the Crowne by Lenons death, reuiued his spirits with such courage, that he began with renewed strength to assaile Lenon, who euen then began to fainte, &amp; would haue yeelded, but that shame withheld him. Which when Ornatus perceiued, hée thought at once to ende the strife, that with one forceable blow, hée gaue him so de
                  •
               p a wound on the right arme, where the Armour was broken away, that bee let fall his sworde, and fell sencelesse on his horse necke. Thaeon perceiuing his sonne in that danger, with his guard came rushing in, &amp; rescued him from Ornatus sword, which otherwise had p
                  •
               rted his head from his bodie. With this, both the Armies ioyned battel againe: the Armenians with new courage rushing vpon their enemies, whose hearts began to faile, seeing Lenon so neer death, which made such a confusion among thē, that they were readier to flie or yeeld to Allinus, thē to fight it out: that on a sodain, the Armeniās had slaine an infinit number of them, &amp; all the earth was dyed to a purple colour, with their blood. O
                     •
                  natus heart was vexed to see so much of his Countres blood shead, that hee intreated Phylastes to perswade the Souldiers to giue ouer, and himselfe rode betwixt the two Armies with a Herault, desiring them to

staie their furie for a while. Long it was before they would giue ouer, but at last by the Drums and Trumpet sound, hauing called backe the Armenians, Ornatus placing himselfe in the midst of his Countrey men, that a multitude might heare him, said. Renowned people of Phrygia, heare my spéech that am tormenmented to sée so much of your blood shead, the effusion whereof, I séeke by all meanes to stop, hauing as you sée for the loue I beare to you, not lifted my hand against any of you, but onely Lenon: the causes that vrge me to challenge him, is the manifest wrongs he and his father hath done to your selues, this Countrey, and all the Nobilitie: for the true testimony whereof, let euery one inwardly examime his owne conscience, and they will not deny my words, but finde themselues exceedingly gréeued with his oppression. Doo you not sée what destruction he hath brought vpon this land? Are not almost all the Nobilitie slaine and destroyed? Are not your liberties, goods and friends, taken from you? Is not the whole land in an vproare, and euery one driuen from his quiet at home, to venture his life in the fielde, and all this for satisfaction of his will and selfe commaund, not grounded vpon lawe nor iustice? Examine your consciences, is he your lawfull King? did he not murther your lawfull King, onely to make you his vassels? Againe, doth Allinus séeke to do his Countrey wrong? doth hée come to oppresse you? doth hée séeke to abuse your libertie? No: hée onely commeth to claime his possessions, by iniustice taken from him: he commeth as vrged by griefe, not to liue as a banished man, being himselfe, his wife, children and familie, driuen to liue in miserie and slauerie, for the satisfaction of his Lust. Then I beséech you good souldiers, consider well what you do, whom you defend, a traytor: and whom you resist, a deare friend, that loueth and tendereth your liues as deare as his owne: whose estate the Armenians pitie, to whome he was neuer gratious: but his own Countrey mens harts are hardned against him, repaying crueltie for his loue, and resistance to withhold his right. I could alledge so many reasons to disswade you from following Thaeons will, as would aske a tedious recital, but I know you are o
                  •
                wisedome

to conceiue the right: your hearts mercifull to pittie him, and your mindes apt to doe Iustice: then giue him ouer, discharge your mindes of care, and disburthen your selues of his oppression. I stand héere as an Aduocate to pleade for Allinus right, that hath indured too much wrong. I stand héere as A
                     •
                  tesias Champion, that is imprisoned by Lenon, abused by Lenon, and withhelde from her libertie by Lenon. I stand here to intreat you saue your owne liues, to preserue your libertie to execute Iustice, and to doe Allinus right. Then I beseeche you, lay aside your armes taken in defence of wrong, and turne your hearts to pittie innocencie: whereby you shall saue many of your liues, shew your selues men that are ruled by wisedome, and not by rage: and purchase libertie, fréedome, and peace, for euer. Then you that beare the true hearts of Phrygians, follow me, and giue ouer to follow that vsurper, and staye such ruines and destructions as are like to ensue by your refusall: and let the rightfull heire possesse the Crowne, who will loue you, cherish you, and séeke his Countreyes peace. The peoples hearts were so altered with his spéeches, that many came running to him, crying, Allinus, Allinus: and the rest that were not yet resolued, stood in a doubt what to doe. Whilest Duke Ternu: commaunded his Forces to follow him, who withdrew himselfe from the Campe, espying so fit occasion, determined likewise not to followe Thaeon longer, whom he neither hated nor loued, but yet estéemed as vnlawfull vsurper of that Kingdome: and rather desiring Allinus should possesse his right of inheritance, then any way willingly contradicting the same: beeing as many others were, forced to come to those warres, fearing T
                     •
                  aeons displeasure, who cared not in what sorte his will was performed. Ternus therefore drewe himselfe apart with this pollicie, that if Thaeon preuailed, yet hée could not impeach him: and if Allinus had the best, yet he could not alledge that Ternus withstood him, thinking it the greatest poynte of wisedome to keepe himselfe vpright. Thaeon had no sooner conueyed his Sonne to his Tent, and with much adoo recouered him to his sences, but there came a m
                  •
               ssenger Poasting from the Court, with newes that Phylastes was

two dayes since escaped out of prison. And presently after him, an other brought newes that Artesia with the pilgrim, was fled, but no man could tell whither. Lenon hearing the newes, became almost mad, and raged so extreamlie, that his wounds burst into fresh bléeding: and to fill vp his heart with sorrowe and vexation, an other messenger from the campe, came running in, crying, Flie Thaeon, flie, we are betrayed to the enemie, the lea
                  •
               ers captaines and souldiers are reuolted, and the enemie is neare at hād to surprise thée: Flie and saue thy life, for thine own subiects haue left thee, and refused thy gouernment. Thaeon was so amazed and terrified with feare, that without regard of Lenons life, he fled to saue himselfe. Euery one sauing those that were fled with Thaeō, with haste running to their reuolting fellowes to saue themselues. This newes was brought to Allinus, who hearing the same, and being past feare of Thaeons rage, sent a Herault
                  •
               e Turnus, to know whether hée were his friend, or still continued those bands to resist him as his foe? who returned this answere, that he was neuer foe to him, but alwaies wisht his good. Afterwards dismissing his souldiers, and sending euery one well rewarded to his owne house, himselfe comming backe to his Tent, where he met Allinus whome hee kindly saluted. Thither were assembled the chief states of the land, to whom Allinus said. My Lords, since Thoeon &amp; Lenon are fled, &amp; none left but your honours in place of iustice, with right and equalitie to minister the same to such as haue sustained wrong: I as one that haue abode the greatest losse, commit my cause to your wisedomes: you know what iniuries I haue indured by his malice, onelie for that I sought to set Artesia at libertie, that was by Lenon imprisoned, and badly vsed: requesting nothing of you, but that which by right is mine, and belongeth to me by inheritance. The nobles with a generall assent, granted that he should enioy his former possessions: and that his losse should be repaid out of the Kings treasure.
            
               O
                     •
                  natus standing by, said: Most noble peeres, you stand here debating masters, whilest the cause of your woe is liuing, and farre inough from yéelding to that you graunt, who now peraduenture

is mustering newe forces, to make frustrate what you intend, and to worke reuenge. Which to preuent, giue mée your consents to pursue him, and he being once taken, then may you without controll, either establish him, or chuse a new, that should by right be your king.
            To this all the nobles gaue consent, and Ornatus with thrée thousand horsmen, followed Thaeon, who first look the gréen Fort
                  •
               esse, with fiue hundred men, who continued firme, wonne by great rewards, but hearing of the Armenians approach, vnder the conduct of the stranger, that i
                  •
               ue Lenon, in the night hee fled with a hundreth of his nearest friends and allies, to Arbastus castle, where he thought to liue secure and vnknowne, for that he thought his enemies would least of all suspect that place. Hee arriued there in the dead time of the night: but knocking, was denied entrance, which made him almost desperate, that hee assayed to enter by force, and preuailed so, that hee gat in with the rest of his company, making fast the Gates againe after them.
            
               Artesias seruants knowing what hée was, some ranne one way, some another, to hide themselues from him. One amongst the rest, came running into Artesias chamber, declaring to her what had befallen, &amp; how that the king had taken the castle. Artesia hauing not yet heard of Lenons death: nor what successe Ornatus had in the campe, wringing her hands made this lamentation. Twice hath my deare Ornatus left me in this danger, and hazarded his owne life, hoping to attaine good successe, but cruell fortune hath still cross his laudable attempts, &amp; le
                  ••
                both him and my poore selfe, in extreame miserie. Now am &amp; assured hée is takē prisoner againe, and my selfe am like not long to go free, for I am sure the king hath heard of my béeing heere, which maketh him come thus late. Well, might I but bee made prisoner in the same place my Ornatus lyeth inthralled, that I might yet enioy his sight, then should I thinke my selfe happie in miserie, but I feare mée too much, they will pri
                  ••
               tie murther him, and neuer let mée knowe thereof, whereby I shall bée helde with long

frustrated hope to sée him, and in the end be deceiued. Neuer was poore mayden brought to such miserie, nor I thinke true loue neuer crost with such pitter aduersities, which both he for me, and I for him, haue bene continually subiect vnto euer since our first acquaintance. As shee was still continuing her laments, the same seruant whose name was Thristus, came running in again, saying D
                  •
               are mistresse, I haue found a meanes for your escape from hence vnespied, if you will attempt the same▪ which is without any danger at all. Neuer tell me what it is (quoth she) but be thou my guide and I wil follow thée: for I will attempt any thing to escape from him. Then (quoth he) feare nothing, but follow me. Then tooke he her by the hand, leading her out of that roome into a darke entrie, where by reason of the night, there appeared not the least glimse of light, and through that into many backe roomes and vnfrequented places of the Castle, vntil hée came to a postern gate which he opened, and after hée was out, shut the same fast againe, saying. Now mistresse you are out of the Castle, and past feare of the King, who litle knoweth you can passe out this way, therefore I pray tell mée whither I shal conduct you? I thanke thée good Thristus quoth she, for this thy good assistance, for which I will one day bee thankful vnto thée, and now I pray thee direct me to Adellenas house, who is my faithful friend, and wil rather die then discouer me. This said, they began their iourney, which was but thrée myles, and therefore they soone ouercame the same, euen by the morning light arriuing at the wished place. Adellena hearing some knocke at the gate, commaunded her mayd to rise, to see who it was, the Damsel comming downe, before shee would open the gate asked who was there? Artesia knowing her voyce, said; It is Artesia, good Anna let me in. With that the Damsel opened the gate, conducting her to her mistresse Chamber, who espying her, was so surprised with ioy, that she imbracing her, shed abundance of teares, saying: Welcome my deare Artesia, I was afraid I should neuer haue séene you againe, you haue bene so long time absent. Indéed (quoth she) I haue bin long absent from thée, though stil not far som thée: but I haue news of

importance to tell thée, which I will forbeare to speake of vntill I haue refreshed my selfe, for care and trauell hath made mée exceedingly weary. Then Adellena brought her into a swéet and pleasant Chamber, where she layde her downe to rest.
         
         
            CHAP. XVI. ¶ Howe Ornatus surprised Thaeon in Arbastus Castle, who was slaine by one of his Seruants.
            
               
                  ORnatus hearing the King had taken the gréen Fortresse, beset the same round with horsemen, who tooke certaine of the Kings followers, that béeing brought before him, tolde him the King was fled with some hundred in his companie to Arbastus Castle, which when hée heard, without delay hée rode thither, fearing leaste Thaeon getting in and finding A
                     •
                  tesia, would offer her some iniurie: hée was no sooner come, but hée sound it so: for hée was denyed entrance, nor could sée one of Artesias seruants, whom hée left as kéepers of the same, which so much disquietted his heart, that hée could not tell what to doe: thinking it best to intreate Thaeon kindely, least hée should séeke reuenge against Artesia, though she were innocent, and no way to be blamed for any thing: and such a multitude of contrarious feares arose in his fancie, that hée séemed therewith metamorphosed. Which Phylastes soone perceiued, and comming to him said; How now Ornatus what hath feare taken away your courage? O my friend Phylastes (quoth hée) Thaeon is within, and thereby possest of Artesia, whose minde is so farre from the least thought of vertue, that no doubt hée will seeke reuenge on her.
            Feare not that (quoth hée,) but summon him to the walles by the sound of a Trumpet, and will him to yeelde him selfe, and stand to the courtesie of his Nobles, and promise him with safetie to conduct him thither. Ornatus allowed his counsel, and therfore commaunded a Trumpet to sound a Parley, and therevpon one from

the King appeared on the walles, demaunding what hee would haue. To whom Ornatus said: Tell Thaeon the King, that wée come to him from the Péeres of the Realme. The messenger told the King what he said. Wherupon Thaeon came in sight, demanding what he would haue.
            Quoth hée, I would haue you yéelde, least by resistance, you procure a greater mischiefe to your selfe, then is by vs pretended. Suppose I should yéelde (quoth he) how would you vse mee? Like a King (quoth Ornatus) honourablie. I haue found (said hee,) so small cause to trust you, that it were fondnesse to put my life within compasse of your mercie: therefore I will kéepe my selfe where I am, not doubting ere many dayes, to haue so many friendes, as shall both chase thée, and the Armenians from the walles, and so out of this Countrey: which hée spake vpon the confidence he had in certaine friends, that had promised to gather newe forces, but meant neuer to performe the same.
            
               Ornatus was much troubles in his minde, to thinke what was become of Artesia, maruailing that hée spake not of her, nor could heare of any of her seruants, that hee might giue him knowledge howe shée fared. But séeing his faire words would not preuaile, said. Thaeon, since thou refusest the curteous profer I make thée, know, that my intent is altered, and since thou wilt not by faire meanes yéelde, I will inforce thée to submitte thy selfe to my mercie, or abide my rigour: for not all the friends thou canst finde shall shelter thee from my reuenge: for I haue sworne thy death, and nothing but that shall satisfie mée. Which vowe I will once againe reuoke, if thou will yéelde without inforcement, and deliuer mée Artesia, in safe
                  •
               ie, that is within that Castle. Artesia, (quoth Thaeon,) had I her in my custodie, I would be reuenged on her, because thou wishest her safetie, but shee is farre inough from me, therefore thou séekest her in vaine at my hands, who would as readily deliuer her vnto thee, as thou couldest ake, for that I estéeme her n
                  •
               t. But as for my selfe, it shall neuer be sayde, my minde would floupe to base submission, nor that a King yeelded to a slaue and base vassal as thou art. Doest thou think that a Royall minde

can put on so degenerate a habite? no I tell thée, whatsoeuer thou art, I had rather by inforcement die, then by submission liue: but be thou aduised what thou doest, nor stay long before these walles, for there are so many whetting their swordes, and putting on Armour in my defence, as ere the mornings Sun arise, will feare thée from hence. Ornatus heart could not indure these braued, and being withall vexed for feare that Artesia should sustaine some iniurie, thought spéedilie to worke reuenge. Which by Phylastes counsaile, hee remitted vntill it were night, that then vnawares they might by some meanes get entrance into the Castle, and so surprise them.
            
               Ornatus thinking to walke alone by himselfe, to breathe forth in sighes some part of the feare that possest his heart, and withall, determining to viewe the Castle, howe hee might with conueniencie get into the same without destroying it, for that it belonged to his dearest beloued, hée espyed the Posterne gate, whereat thrusting, it presently flewe open, which way as yet, neyther Thaeon nor any of his company had found. Ornatus heart was glad hée had found so good a means to accomplish his will, putting the same too againe, came to Phylastes and told him thereof. Then both of them presently agreed to enter that way and surprize them: conueying a hundreth of the best Souldiours secretly vnder the wall of that Posterne, and placing all the rest in the open viewe of the Castle, as if none of them had bene wanting.
            
               Ornatus and Phylastes entered, and after them she rest followed, who passing along through the waste roomes, at last came to the place where they had left Artesia, but found her not, and such successe had they in their attempt, that Ornatus comming behind Thaeon, smote him with his hand on the backe, before hée had any knowledge of his approache. Thaeon therewith starting, and looking backe, was amazed, but running forward, drewe out his sword, crying; My Friends saue and defende your selues: wherewith those that were about him drewe their swordes: To whom Ornatus said in this manner.
            Howe now vsurping King? where are those mightie Forces

should chase me hence? wil you yet yéelde, or stand to the triall by fight? I yéelde (quoth Thaeon,) but much against my will, for had friends dealt fai
                  •
               hfully, I had not bene left in this misery. But since fortune so much fauoureth thée, as to make mee thy prisoner, vse me well for that I am a King, and to none but thy selfe am in thrall. Tell me (quoth Ornatus) what is become of Artesia, that not many dayes since I left in this place? I sawe her not (quoth Thaeon) nor know I where shée is, onely I found certaine seruants in this place, whom I haue put to death, least they should bewray my béeing héere. Tyrant quoth Ornatus, thinkest thou their death shall goe vnreuenged, couldest thou be so cruell as to murther those that were innocent? with whom I feare me, thou hast made away Artesia. Why what art thou (quoth Thaeon?) that vsest such vndecense words to a King? that art thy selfe not worthie to speake to a King? and why makest thou such enquyrie after Artesia, that for ought I knowe hast no interest in her? suppose I haue slaine her, that was the cause of all this woe, what canst thou challenge at my handes for her? it had beene good shée had neuer been borne
                  •
               , for shee onely hath caused the originall of these troubles. Art thou a King quoth Ornatus, and bearest so vnkingly a minde, as to slaunder true vertue? No, thou art a villain, a murtherer, a Traytour to this Land, an vsurper of the Crowne, and a most wicked and cruell homicide: but for that thou wouldest knowe what I am, knowe that I haue more interest to the Crowne then thou hast, my name Ornatus, and thy enemie, to whom by right that Crowne belongeth: which thou shalt no longer enioye. Therefore said hée, such as are my friends lay holds out his Trator. Hée had no sooner spoken those words, but Thaeons owne Seruants were the first that apprehended him, béeing weary of his gouernement: and one amongst the rest, thinking that hée had commaunded them to slaye him, and withall, hoping for some reward for that forward exployte, hauing his sword readie drawne, suddenly (whilest Ornatus did but turne backe to confer with Phylastes) thr
                  •
               st the same through Thaeons bodie, that giuing a pitteous grone, he gaue vp the ghost. Ornatus turning

backe, demaunded who had done that déede, with that the murtherer drew backe, fearing to come before him, vntil he was compeld, To whom Ornatus said; What art thou that hast done this deede, art thou not one of his seruants, hast not thou bene maintained by him, did hée not trust thée with his life, was he not thy king, then howe durst thou presume to strike thy maister, be ingratefull to him that gaue thée gifts, proue false to him that trusted thee, and stay thine annointed king? My Lord (quoth he) I did mistake your wordes, and hope to preserue my owne life, made me to do that déede, which I thought would haue pleased yau. I am not (quoth he) sorie he is dead, but for that thou flewest him, who thou in all du
                  •
               ie oughtest to haue defended: for which thou shalt die a miserable death. Then he commaunded that hée should be drawne in péeces with horses, which before he departed thence, was performed.
         
         
            CHAP. XVII. How Ornatus was chosē King. How he departed vnknown in search of Artesia. How Lenon sought againe to betray him, &amp; was disappointed. How he was banished. Tyresus pardoned. And Orntius and Artesia royally married.
            
               THe King dead, Ornatus with Phylastes, returned to the Court, where all the Peeres were assembled, who before his comming, had by a voluntarie messenger, vnderstood the manner of Thaeons death, the care whereof was alreadie past, for that fewe or none at all loued him: but now their care was whom to chuse as their King, but first they welcommed Ornatus, none of them all knowing him, nor once suspecting what he was, who now could find no further occasiō to cōceale himselfe, but humbling himself before Allinus, 
               
                  •
               e said. My renowmed Lord, the cause I haue so long cencealed my sel
                  •
               , hath bin feare of the kings crueltie, and Lenons enuie, who both wold haue indangered me, but now being voyd of that misdoubt, your

poore sonne Ornatus, submitteth himselfe, humbly crauing pardon for my neglect of dutie. With that hee vnarmed his head, and his father knowing him, in most louing wife imbraced him, sheading teares for ioy of his safetie, whome he thought had bene long since dead. Duke 
                  
                     •
                  ernus and the rest, reioyced to see him, and with imbracings exprest their ioy, entring into admiration of his honoured parts and noble chiualrie. Plylastes being likewise known, was much commended, whom they déemed had bene murthered in the prison by Lenon, for that hée could not be found. Allinus beholding Ornatus, and with what valour he had bahaued himselfe, reioyced excéedingly, the Commons clapt their hands for ioy, and the Péeres amongst themselues began to relate howe vertuously, valiantly, and prudently, hée had behaued himselfe in all that he had vndertaken. After many welcomes past, Ternus crauing audience stood vp, vttering these spéeches: My Lordes, we néed not now defer giuing of Allinus his right, because there is none to contradict what we establish: besides, we being all now assembled togither, &amp; our late vsurping king dead, there can be no fitter time to chuse a new king, and such a one as by right of blood, and by our generall consents may rule vs. Thaeon you know was no way interessed in the Crowne but by vsurpation, and hath rooted out almost all that hee knew to haue any title or interest in our late kings blood: of wich house Allinus issue is the last, by marriage of the Ladie Aura, néece vnto our late king, therefore the right being in him, if there be any man in this assembly that can contradict that which I haue said, let him speak. Which when he had said, he again sat downe. Upon his speeches the Nobles conferd, the people consulted, and at last the common souldiers cryed out, Let Ornatus be our king, Ornatus is our king. The nobles likewise gaue consent to that the multitude liked, and Ornatus was chosen king, whom they wold haue crowned: but at his desire they defered the day of his Coronation for a month. In the meane time, estéeming him as their king, and that day with great royaltie setting him in possession thereof, all businesse for that day being ended, the Armenians richly rewarded,

feasted, and with ioy readie to returne. Allinus in quiet but for the want of his Ladie, and all things in good order, Ornatus being alone by himselfe endured much disquiet for Artesia, maruelling what was become of her, sometimes thinking she was slaine by Thaeon, and then supposing she was escaped out at the posterne gate which he found open, that in these contrarieties of doubts he continued, sometimes dispairing, and then again féeding himselfe with hope. After Artesia had rested her selfe, and receiued some part of her sléepe she had lost that night, though but with broken st
                  •
               mbers, she began to declare to Adellena what miseries she had indured, and troubles she had past since she was by Lenon carried from her house, how she met with Ornatus againe, and euerie thing that was befalne, with the cause of her flight at that instant. But Adellena said she, I feare me I shall neuer sée him againe, for had he not bin takē, and his father ouerthrown, Thaeon could not haue had so much leisure as to come to surprise mée there, but the heauens granted me a fortunate escape. And if I could be so happie as to heare that Ornatus were in safetie, though he had not that successe his desires did aime at, my heart would bée at some rest, which is now pinched with suspitious torment. His aduenterous valiant hart could not be withdrawne by any perswasion to leaue to aide his father, but notwithstanding infinit perils hung ouer his head, yet to shew the dutie of a louing son, and the mind of a vertuous v
                  •
               liant gentleman, he would not desist to hazard his person: which now I feare me is falne into the hands of his enemies. But yet Phylastes I hope wil by his good &amp; 
                  •
               riendly counsel be a meanes to kéepe him from danger. Many other speeches Artesia vsed: and Adellena vsed as many on the contrary part, to perswade her that Ornatus was in safetie, the truth wherof she told her, she shuld soone know: for (quoth she) I haue sent one of my seruants to learne the truth of all that is happened, who I know wil shortly returne. Which fel out euen as she had told, for the seruant returned, bringing newes of Lenons death, acted by a strange knight, and how that Thaeon was fled, and being likewise by the straunge knight surprised in A
                     •
                  bastus Castle, was slaine by one of his owne seruants.
            
               Which Knight, was now knowne to be Ornatus, and was elected King by the Peeres, but he had deferred his day of Coronation, by reason of some speciall griefe that troubled him. Artesias heart was reuiued with these newes, knowing the griefe Ornatus endured was for her absence, that presently she determined to send him word of her safetie: and wrote a Letter, the contents whereof were these.
            
               
                  MY deare Ornatus, no newes could haue come more welcome to me then your safetie, and nothing more vnwelcome, then to heare of your heauines
                        •
                     e, which I would intreat you to cease, for that I am in safetie at Adellenas house, being by one of my seruants the same night the King tooke my Castle, at a posterne gate in safetie brought hither, where I trust ere long to see you: which wil replenish my soule with exceeding comfort, for on your safetie, my life and felicitie dependeth.
                  
                     Yours for euer, Artesia.
                     
                  
               
            
            Hauing wrote this Letter, shée gaue it to Thristus, willing him to deliuer the same to Ornatus with all spéed.
            Destenies do allot many to excéeding misfortunes, and some men are of that dishonorable and vnmanly dispositions, that they account all meanes to attaine their desires lawfull, not regarding the shame and peril will ensue thereon. O
                  •
                which nature was Lenon, who being conueyed from the Campe by his frien
                  •
               s, soone recouered, and kept in a secret place, least he might be knowne, hauing no other meanes but by absenting himself to saue his life: whose supposed death, caused Thaeons flight to the gréene Fortresse, from whence likewise he was departed before Lenō
                could come to giue him knowledge of his safetie, and knowing that it was then too late to salue those miseries, he 
                  〈◊〉
                concealed himself, following Ornatus (though vnknowne to him) with intent to murther him, if he could by any meanes take him at aduantage. But he was still disappointed, and withall sawe the death of his

father done by his own seruant, stil intermingling hi
                  •
               self amongst the souldiers, that he was taken to be one of them, &amp; neuer suspected. But Ornatus being returned to the Court, Lenon was then compelled to leaue to follow him, and harboured sometimes in one place, and sometimes in an other, hauing knowledge of Artesias absence, he could not tell whether she were aliue or dead▪ but dead hée thought she could not be, but rather by some meanes escaped. And euen when Thristus was newlie come out of Adellenaes house, Lenō
                espied him, &amp; knowing him to be one of Artesias serseruants, be suspected his Mistresse was there, to whom he came, saying: My friend well met, I take you to be one of Artesias seruants, vnlesse I be deceiued: which if you wil resolue me of, I will do a message to you, that I am willed to deliuer to her from her dearest friend Ornatus. Indéed (quoth Thristus) I serue Artesia, and am now going to Ornatus with a letter from Artesia, who is in safetie in Adellenas house. Lenon hearing his spéech, being before determined what to do, drew out his dagger and suddainely stabbed him, casting his body into a pitte, and taking the letter frō him, brake off the seale and red the contents, which when hée had done, he beganne to studie which way to reuenge himselfe on Ornatus, and afterwardes to get Artesia into his possession, and for that he thought delay might hinder his intent, he first wrote a letter in Artesias name, the contents were these.
            
               
                  
                     ORnatus my dearest friend, the newes of your happy victorie, &amp; conquest of your enemies, is come to my knowledge, then which nothing could haue beene more welcome vnto me. Likewise I heare, that much heauines possesseth you for my absence, that am in safetie: and desire you to meete me to morrow night, and you shall finde me with Adellena, at the lodge in the Parke neere vnto my Castle: in the meane time, remitting all further report of my escape, &amp; manifestation of my Loue, vntill the happy time I may meete you.
                  
                     Yours in all Loue, Artesia.
                     
                  
               
            
            When he had written this letter, and imitated therein Artesias own hand so néere, that it could hardly be discerned, he went to the Court, &amp; behaueed the matter so cunningly, that hee was no way suspected, but was admitted into Phylastes presence, to whom hee

deliuered the letter. For Ornatus himselfe being excéedingly troubled in his minde, had left the Court, with some three in his company, to go in search of Artesia, &amp; left Phylastes in his chamber, and in his stead, to answere such as shuld come with any suites to him. Phylastes beeing taken of all, but of some certaine that attended him, receiued the letter, promising to meete Artesia there, at the same time appointed, giuing the messenger a reward. Lenon beeing d
                  •
               parted, went to a place where he found a certain kinsman of his named Lucerius, to whom he declared both what he was, and what meanes hée had wrought for his reuenge on Ornatus, who without respect ioyned hands with him, and promised with many oathes to exp
                  •
               ore his life in pursuite of reuenge, who with Lenon included before Ornatus comming, to be in the lodge with a sufficient company to surprize him, &amp; worke the premeditated reuenge. Lenon béeing assured of his aide, next determined to take Artesia from Adellenas house, and to bring her to Lucertus Castle, vntill the time appointed staying with Lucertus, to sée him depart with his ambush to the lodge, which he saw effectually performed. Phylastes presently vpon the receipt of that letter, sent out a messenger to séeke Ornatus, &amp; to certifie him, that Artesia would méete him at the lodge we 
               Adellena that euening, &amp; that he should find Phylastes there: who (béeing by Artesias messenger taken for himselfe) had appointed to be there, least he shuld not conueniently be found. The messenger with great haste departed, &amp; inquiring after foure Pilgrims (for in that habit Ornatus &amp; such as were with him wēt) by that time the day drew néere to an end, the messenger found out Ornatus, to whom he declared what Phylastes had giuen him in charge, only mistaking the place, for wheras he should by his direction haue said at t
                  ••
                lo
                  ••
               e, mistaking Phylastes words, he said at Adellena house. Ornatus hearing that heauenly tydings, leapt for ioy, presently hasting towards Adellenas house, which was not far off. Lenon to further his attempt (which he thought he could not with violence execute: for he thought if he should carrie her away perforce in the day time, he shuld be preuented) deuised an answere of the letter, that he had takē from Thristus, which he determined to deliuer to Artesia, as frō 
               Ornatus, y• consēts wherof were these.
            
               
                  MY most deare and beloued Artesia, I haue receyued the letter you sent me by your seruāt, whom I haue imployed

about a matter of great importance, that none could so fitly execute as himselfe, which newes was moste welcome to the comfort of my heart, that was almost ouercome with dispaire of your safetie, wheron my chiefest felicitie depēdeth. Therefore omitting further recitall of my ioy for your safetie, which this paper cannot expresse, therefore I will meete you soone, where this my seruant will bring you, whose fidelitie I assure you to be such, as that he will do nothing but what I haue giuen him in charge: vntil which time of meeting, I cease all further circumstance of speeches.
                  
                     Yours, Ornatus.
                     
                  
               
            
            With this letter Lenon went to Adellenas house, &amp; knocking at the gate, was brought to her, to whom hée deliuered the same, who reading the contents, &amp; being before not well acquainted with Ornatus hand, nothing at all suspected the contrary, but both beleeued that it came from him, and determined to goe with the messenger to méet him: whilest she was preparing to go with Lenon, Adellanaes maide came in, telling her, that there was another to speake with her from Ornatus: with that Lenon changed countenance, and Artesia willed her to bring him in. Ornatus beholding her, had thought to haue imbraced her, &amp; discouered himselfe, but séeing a straunger there, and a letter in her hand, hee stood in a studie. Artesia noting well his countenance, thought it was Ornatus himselfe, but standing in a doubt thereof, said, I haue receiued this letter from Ornatus alreadie, and therfore if you haue any further message from him tell it mée, for any newes from him shall be most welcome. Ornatus thought that it was sent by Phylastes, but not knowing the messenger, meruailed therat, saying: I cannot beléeue that it came from him, for while within this houre, hée had not knowledge of your béeing héere. With that Artesia gaue him the letter, willing him to read the same. Ornatus soone knew that it was inuented by some trecherie, and therfore said: I know this came not from Ornatus, for this is not his hand, nor hée that brought it any of his Seruants, for himselfe sent mée before, appointing to be héere within this houre.
            
               Lenon hearing his spéeches, wisht himselfe a thousand myles off, fearing to be discouered, for that he could not t
                  •
               ll how to excuse himselfe, nor by any colour auoyde that daunger. To whom Ornatus
               
said: My friend, when did hee deliuer thée this letter? Yesterday (quoth he.) Thou lyest said Ornatus, for he hath not beene at the Court these thrée daies. Lenon thinking with impudencie to out
                  ••
               ce, hauing no other meanes left, that was likely to helpe him, and therefore said: This letter came from Ornatus, and thou lyest in saying the contrary, being some villain that art set to betray this Ladie, therefore (quoth he) speaking to Artesia, beléeue him not for he is come with some euill intent. With that Ornatus bad those that were with him lay hands on him, who presently apprehended him, and pulling of his hat, &amp; a subtile disguise that he wore, knewe him to be Lenon, at the first being halfe afraide 
                  •
               o touch him, for that they would haue sworne he had bin dead. Ornatus séeing Artesia in an excéeding flight, discouered himselfe, and with great ioy imbraced her, desiring her to feare nothing, Artesia knowing him, soone forgat her feare, embracing him wt excéeding ioye. To whom hée said: Feare him not my deare Artesia, for be it himselfe or his ghost, I care not, it shall goe hard, if hée nowe escape my handes. To whom he said:
            Most discurteous and cowardly Villaine, couldest thou not be contented, to liue in quiet, hauing once escaped my Furie, but that thou must by further complo
                  •
               s séeke to betray this Ladie, that neuer did iniurie thée? How often hast thou interrupted her quiet, and from quietnesse brought her into misery? and knowing that she could not like thée, yet thou wert so impudent, as neuer to giue ouer thy sute: but to attaine thy desire, first depriuedst her of libertie, banishedst me in the disguise of Syluian, and soughtest to betray my Fathers life: &amp; not satisfied with all these, like a cowardly miscreant, séekest by villanie to betray her: and notwithstanding thou haste be held thy fathers wofull downfall and meritorious punishment, thou séekest to betray this Ladies life, by some vnknowne trecherie not yet reuealed. For all which, thou shalt suffer such punishment as I haue deuised, and haue power to execute. Lenon séeing himselfe discouered, gr
                  •
               w desperate, and scorning to be so rebuked at his hands, whom he still esteemed his inferior, but especially vexed, that it was hée that had so long hindered his Loue to Artesia, saide: Ornatus, I thinke thou hast either forgotten thy selfe, or else what I am, that at thy pleasure rebukest me in such vnciuill and ill beséeeming termes. Am I not thy better, and one that

not long since, might haue commaunded thee, and is thy minde so much eleuated &amp; proud, that thou wilt not acknowledge it? Thou makest brags of thy victorie, when thou mayst rather with shame kéepe silence, &amp; with remorse, repent that thou hast sought the death of thy lawfull king, béeing thy selfe a traitor. As hee would haue spake more, Ornatus interrupted him, saying: Hold thy peace, &amp; do not stir my mind to more sharp reuenge by thy replie, for I scorne to heare thée speake, therefore giue ouer, least I punish that tongue of thine for vttering such high words in defence of vice.
            Since (quoth Lenon) thou wilt not heare me speak in defence of my selfe, let me be conueyed from thy presence, for thy sight is as odious vnto mee, as mine to thée. Whilest they continued in Adellenas house, a messenger came running in breathlesse, vttering these speches: Behold most worthie Ornatus, I bring a message of much woe and heauie import: yesterday there was a messenger came to the court, that brought a letter in Artesias name to Phylastes, as supposing him to be your selfe, wherein shée requested you to méete her this night at the Lodge in her Parke. Phylastes, who presently sent out a messenger to giue you knowledge therof, not hearing of his returne, went himselfe with some twentie in his company, to the place appointed, and entring, hée found not Artesia there, but a crew of Rebells, amongst whom Lucertus was chiefe, who all at once set vpon him and his followers, taking him for your selfe, hauing so many aboue the small number that were with Phylastes, that they had soone slaine most of them that were with him, and himselfe not able to withstand such a multitude, had receiued many grieuous wounds, &amp; had bin surel
                  •
                slaine, but that the heauens sent them this ayde: It fortuned that day, that Duke Ternus was going from the Court to his owne house, who by great fortune hearing 
                  •
               he noise, with his men hasted thitherwards, &amp; hauing knowledge of what was done, most valiantly both himselfe &amp; his men set vppon Lucertus, whom they soone vanquished, hauing first slaine manie of his complices, and him hath he carried prisoner, with the rest of such as were aliue vnto the Court, &amp; with them Phylastes in great daunger of death. Ornatus heart was excéedingly vexed to heare of his déere friende Phylastes hurt, but especially, to thinke that hee had not before attached Lucertus, which he was once in minde to haue done, which would haue

preuented all these mischiefes. The night nowe béeing come, Ornatus caused Lenon to be bound hand and foote, and put into a strong place of the house, wt some to to watch him, least hée shuld doe himselfe violence: himselfe with Artesia spending that euening in many speeches, relating the maner o
                  •
                all these misfortunes, but especially comforting themselues in each others loue, with Adellena, calling to remembrance the whole manner of their troubles onely procured by Lenon, which sadde relations made the renuing of their Loue more pleasant and defectable. Early the next morning, Ornatus putting himselfe in his Palmers weedes, and couering Artesias face with a vale, &amp; carrying Lenon with them bound, departed towards the Court. The next morning the Péers of the Land being still there, assembled thēselues, amongst whom was Allinus, that likewise had found his Ladie, who hearing of his happie successe against Thaeon, was that morning newly arriued at the Court, and by him entertained with excéeding ioy.
            By that time they were assembled, &amp; had called Lucertus before them, Ornatus with his companie, were likewise come, thogh vnknowne and standing by, heard Lucertus confesse that Lenon had instigated him to worke that reuenge against Ornatus, himselfe being likewise gone to betray Artesia. The whole assembly maruelled when they heard him say that Lenon perswaded him to it, that Allinus stood vp, saying: Is not hée dead, then how can this bee? Lenon (quoth Lucertus is not dead) with that Ornatus stopping in thrusting Lenō
                before him, said: Here is the man that hath procured him to all this mischiefe. The Nobles beholding him, were amazed at his sight, but beeing assured it was he, by the perfect knowledge they had of him, Ternus said: Lenon, I had alwaies thought thou hadst borne the mind of a Gentleman, but now I finde the contrary in thée, and that in the most shamefulst degrée. What furie led thée to such mischieuous attempts, to hire Lucertus to slay Ornatus, which he hath almost performed? and thy selfe to séeke the death or miserie of that vertuous Ladie, that hath alreadie indured too much wrong by thy folly? Allinus had not as yet heard of Ornatus hurt, nor any knew the contrarie but that Phylastes was he, for hée according to the minde of a most vertuous and constant friend, stil cōcealed himselfe. Nor the Lady Aura had yet seene her sonne, whom she had but heard of, that Allinus
               
said: Is my son Ornatus almost slaine? O trayterous villaine▪ with that Aura likewise began to make exceeding lamentation: which Ornatus was not able to behold, and therfore pulling off his disguised habit humbly reuerenced himselfe before thē vpon his knee both his Parents knewe him, and with exceeding ioy imbr
                  •
               ced him shedding abundance of teares for his safetie. With that, Duke Ternus and all the rest came to him, vsing him with such behauiour as belonged to him they had chosen King, seating him in an Imperiall chaire. Hée being set thus, said: My Noble Lords, I thank you for intituling mée with this excéeding honeur: therefore my desire is, since you haue elected mée of your free and bounteous hearts so be your King, let mee this day and instantlie, be installed with possession of the Dyademe, for that I haue nowe no further cause of care to cause me defer the same: &amp; likewise, that I may giue iudgement against these most wicked conspirators. The Nobles with ioyfull hearts gaue consent, and immediately crowned him, with bended knées doing him reuerēce: which done, Ornatus rising from his imperiall seate, came to Artesia, taking her by the hand, and leading her vppe the throne, seated her in the chaire, placing the Crowne vppon her head, saying: My Lords, I pray likewise be contented we that I do, &amp; as you haue elected mée king make this your Quéene: thē puld hee off the vale from Artesias face, and her cleare beautie appeared to the admiration of all, who beholding, in humble sort did her reuerēce, making excéeding shouts for ioy, their harts being all excéedingly glad of her safetie.
            When this was done, she came downe and imbraced them, yéelding them many thankes, who all shewed such exceeding kindnesse, as exprest their hartie goodwill, and reioyced both her &amp; Ornatus to behold: especially Aura and Turnu
                     •
                  
                duchesse, with many imbracings which they thought they could not sufficiently expresse, reioyced to see her in that safety. By that time Ornatus was againe seated &amp; Artesia by him, Phylast
                     •
                  s hearing of Ornatus returne being though greeuously wounded, yet in no great danger of death, as well as he could came into the presence, where beholding Ornatus and Artesia crowned, kneeled down before them, his heart conceiuing excéeding ioy, to behold that heauenly sight. Whom O
                     •
                  natus kindly imbraced, reioycing to sée him in that good estate: after Artesias salutation, willing him to sit down amongst

them. Then Ornatus first commanding Floretus to be sent for out of prison, thus said: Now there resteth nothing but to giue sentence against these, that by conspiracies haue béene murtherers, which fact is so hainous, that it maketh them both odious to God and man, in which offence, both thou Lenon, Lucertus, &amp; Tyrefus are gu
                  ••
               tie: therfore Lenon (quoth hée) first declare what mooued thée from time to time, to commit so many and greedous actes us thou hast done. Lenons heart was dead with vexation to sée him crowned, and Artesia chosen his Queen, that hanging down his head, he would not speak: but Lucertus humbling himselfe vpon his knee, asked pardon. By this time Floretus was brought in, looking with such a meger and pale countenance, by reason of his long imprisoment, that Artesia wept to behold him, and could not chuse but run and imbrace him, vpon her knée intreating Orn
                     •
                  tus to pardon the offence he had cōmitted, which was against none but her self. Ornatus séeing her knéele, suddainly caught her vp, imbracing Floretus, &amp; cōmanding his hands to be vnloosed, withall saying: I not only we a willing hart pardon you, but also giue vnto you foreuer, al those possessions yt belōged vnto your brother Arbastus. Floretus before expecting nothing but death, which was turned to such excéeding ioy, humbly vppon his knée yeelded many thankes.
            Then Ornatus 
               
                  •
               easing himselfe againe, said: Because this day is the first of our raigne, which should begin with mercie, and not with rigor, there shall not a drop of blood by our command be spill: and therefore Lenon, though thou hast deserued no fauour, but a most miserable death, we pardon thée. And Lucertus, commaunding thée vppon paine of death, within tenne daies to depart this land, for ye we banish thée hence for euer: which doome is too merci
               
                  •
               ull for thy fact. For thée Lenon, we onely bannish thée this Court, where on paine of death set not thy foote, least they life ransome thy presomption. This said, taking Artesia by the hand, he was by the Péeres with a noyse of trumpets and exceeding ioy, conducted to a Chappell, and in royall sort that day married to Artesia, and from thence to an Emperiall feaste, spending all that day in great pleasure, and at night taking lawfull delight in her loue, both then and during the time of both their liues, liuing in most pleasant louing, and vertuous sort, that most places of the world were filled with the report of their vertuous life, and peaceable gouernment.
         
         FINIS.
         
      
   

