
   
      
         
            A letter first written and sent by Io. Forbes, pastour of the English Church at Middelburgh vnto certen of the companie of marchands adventurers at Stoade, at their earnest desire, for resolving this question: how a Christian man may discerne the testimonie of Gods spirit, from the testimonie of his owne spirit, in witnessing his adoption. And now againe renewed and enlarged by the authour, at the desire of divers good Christians, for the comfort of their troubled co[n]sciences, and published by those of his flocke, to whom he did dedicate it for the publike vse of the Church.
            Forbes, John, 1568?-1634.
         
         
            
               1616
            
         
         Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01028
            STC 11131
            ESTC S118027
            99853236
            99853236
            18605
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01028)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18605)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 837:09)
         
         
            
               
                  A letter first written and sent by Io. Forbes, pastour of the English Church at Middelburgh vnto certen of the companie of marchands adventurers at Stoade, at their earnest desire, for resolving this question: how a Christian man may discerne the testimonie of Gods spirit, from the testimonie of his owne spirit, in witnessing his adoption. And now againe renewed and enlarged by the authour, at the desire of divers good Christians, for the comfort of their troubled co[n]sciences, and published by those of his flocke, to whom he did dedicate it for the publike vse of the Church.
                  Forbes, John, 1568?-1634.
               
               93, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Richard Schilders,
                  At Middelburgh :
                  1616.
               
               
                  Running title reads: Gods spirit in vs discerned from our owne spirit.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Christian life --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A LETTER
Firſt written and ſent by Io.
FORBES, Paſtour of the Engliſh
Church at MIDDELBVRGH, vnto certen
of the companie of Marchands Adventurers
at STOADE, at their earneſt deſire,
for reſolving this Queſtion:
How a Chriſtian man may diſcerne the
testimonie of Gods ſpirit, from the testimonie
of his owne ſpirit, in witneſsing his Adoption.
            
            And now againe renewed and enlarged by
the Authour, at the deſire of divers good Chriſtians▪ for
the comfort of their troubled cōſciences▪ and publiſhed
by thoſe of his flocke, to whom he did dedicate
it for the publike vſe of the Church.
            
               Thy Rod and thy Staffe they comfort me,
               Pſal. 23. 4.
            
            AT MIDDELBVRGH,
Printed by Richard Schilders, 1616.
         
         
            
            
            To Mr Edw. Bennet, Mr.
Iohn Turner, and Mr Ed. Kay,
the Authour wiſheth increaſe
of all Spirituall bleſſing
in Chriſt.
            
               RECEYVE (beloved
in the Lord) a certen
Letter, which
above eight yeeres
ago, I firſt did write
at the deſire of Mr Io. Scharpuls,
now with God, and others of the
companie then at Stoade, &amp; now
againe have revewed and ſomewhat
enlarged the ſame, vpon occaſion
of the trouble of cōſcience
wherein I did perceyve manie
good Chriſtians to bee caſt for

want of ſufficiēt light in the ſame
queſtion which is heere handled,
deſiring to miniſter ſome comfort
vnto them, if it shall pleaſe
God to bleſſe this my endeavour,
in that meaſure of light which he
hath given me: vſe it, and if yee
finde any fruit in it, impart it to
ſuch as have need. The ſpirit of
comfort and true peace bee with
you to the end. Iuli 20. 1616.
            
               Yours in the Lord
Io. Forbes.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A ſhort Diſcourſe,
shewing how a Chriſtian
may diſcerne the teſtimonie of
Gods ſpirit from the teſtimonie
of his owne ſpirit, in witneſſing
his Adoption.
            
               The ſame ſpirit beareth witneſſe alſo togither
with our ſpirit, that wee are the
ſonnes of God,
               Rom. 8. 16.
            
            
               BELOVED
in the Lord, you
deſired by your
Letter at my departure
frō 
               Stoad,
that I would reſolve
you, in that ſaying of the
Apoſtle to the Rom. chap. 8. The
ſpirit of God beareth witnes with our
ſpirits, that we are the ſonnes of God.
               
How a man may know when that
ſpirit, doth beare witnes alſo with
our ſpirit. The occaſion moving
you to inquire this, being miniſtred
by ſome ſpeech vttered by
me in preaching: ſayinge it was
not enough for a man, that his
own ſpirit do beare witnes alone.
            Firſt, I will ſhewe you the occaſion
wherefore I did ſay ſo: and
next, I will doe my beſt to ſatisfie
your queſtion, as the Lord hath
given me to vnderſtand.
            It is moſt certaine, that a mans
owne heart (being a thing, as ſaith
Ieremie, Chap. 17. deceitfull above all
things) will oft times deceyve man
him ſelf, and yeeld him a falſe Teſtimonie
of him ſelfe, as alſo of his
actions and eſtate. Is it not ſaid of
the Angell of the Church of Laodicea:
that he ſaid of him ſelf: I am
ritch &amp; increaſed with goods,
               Reve. 3. 17▪
                
               &amp; have
need of nothing. This doubtles was

his owne teſtimonie of him ſelfe.
But what doeth the ſpirit of God
witnes of him: Thou art wretched,
and miſerable, and poore, and blind, &amp;
naked. And moreover doth affirme
that this Angell did not know he
was ſo.
            Doth not Chriſt alſo teach vs in
the Goſpell,Luke. 18. that there bee ſome
whoſe hartes deceyve them, making
them truſt in themſelves that
they are iuſt, and yet are not, and
cleares it by the example of the
Phariſee, giving thankes vnto God,
That he was not as other men, extortioner,
vniust, &amp;c. who notwithſtanding
is accompted of God vniuſt.
And to be ſhort, in this point the
Lord Ieſus ſheweth vs that many
men at his ſecond comming, ſhall
be miſerably deceived by the fooliſh
teſtimonie of their own harts:
ſome being confident becauſe of
the outward fellowſhip and familiaritie

they have had with Chriſt,
both in Word &amp; Sacraments, and
therefore pleading thus:Luc. 13. 22▪
                
               We have
eaten and dronke in thy preſence, and
thou has taught in our ſtreetes, ſhall
nevertheleſſe receyve this anſwer:
I tell you, I know you not whence you
are, depart from me. Others alſo vpon
the confidence of giftes beſtowed
vpon them by Chriſt for
the good of his Church, pleading
with him and ſaying:Mat. 7. 22. 
               Lord, Lord,
have we not by thy Name prophecied,
and by thy Name cast out Divels, and
by thy Name done many great works?
ſhall receyve the ſame anſwere.
            Heereby it is evident, that the
teſtimonie of a mans owne heart
being alone may be deceitfull, evē
when it is builded vpō profeſſion
and outward participation of the
holy things of GOD. Yea even
when it is builded vpon ſome rare
ſpeciall giftes of the holy ghoſt,

which although they bee neceſſarie
for the body or Church in generall,
yet are not requiſit in every
member to ſalvation, ſuch as is the
gift of Prophecying, &amp;c. and therefore
may both be wanting without
preiudice, and alſo had without
enioying of ſalvation.
            Thus have wee reaſon not to
truſt our Adoption and certaintie
of our ſalvation, to the naked teſtimonie
of our owne hearts, leaſt
we be found like the fooliſh Virgines.
It is true, the teſtimonie of
our owne hearts is needfull heerevnto,
becauſe ſayeth the Apoſtle,
If our heartes condempne vs,
               1 Ioh. 3. 20▪
                
               God is
greater then our heartes: and if our
hearts condempne vs not, then have
we boldnes towards God. But it muſt
not be alone, for ſo it ſhal never be
ſure, but having the ſpirit witneſſing
with it, then it is ſure.
            
               
Now yet before I ſpeake of the
diſcerning of the ſpirites teſtimonie,
I muſt forewarne you of this
one thing, to wit, that there bee
many effectes of the ſpirit in the
Saints oft times, which at the firſt
the Saintes know not to bee from
the ſpirit, and that both in their
firſt calling, and after they be called▪
and therefore wee muſt not
meaſure the working of the ſpirit
in vs by our diſcerning, neyther
muſt we iudge our ſelves deſtitute
of the ſpirit, albeit wee doe not
diſcerne the effectes wrought in
vs, to bee from the ſpirit: for the
Saints will feele ſtrange effectes
wrought in their mindes, which
they will neither knowe whence
they come, nor wherevnto they
tend. This is verified by Ieſus
Chriſt him ſelf, ſpeaking of the verie
working of the ſpirit in our ſpirituall

birth, whereby we are made
the children of God, comparinge
it to the winde: The winde (ſaieth
he) bloweth where it liſteth,
               Io. 3. 8. 
               and thou
heareſt the ſound thereof, but can not
tell whence it commeth, nor whether it
goeth: ſo is every mā (ſaith Chriſt)
that is borne of the ſpirit.
            
            This ſhall not ſeeme ſtrange to
vs if we marke what is ſaide of the
Diſciples at Epheſus, who were
baptized as appeareth by Apollos,
               Acts. 19. 2
and yet they confeſſe to Paul that
they had not ſo much as heard
whether there were an H. ghoſt.
It may bee alſo very apparantlie
thought, that Peter when hee did
witneſſe of Chriſt, that he was the
Chriſt the Sonne of the living God,
               Mat. 16. 16▪
               
did not knowe that teſtimonie to
have bene from the ſpirit of God,
and therefore Chriſt (to teach
him that that teſtimonie was not
the teſtimonie of his owne heart,

but by the ſpirit of God) did tell
him that fleſh and bloud had not
reveyled that to him, but his Father
that is in heaven.
            This I ſpeake not to make men
careleſſe in trying whether they
have the ſpirit or no, but to comfort
weake Chriſtians, who although
they have the livelie effectes
of the ſpirit, yet have not
come ſo farre as to bee able to diſcerne
them to be from the ſpirit,
as ſometimes they will bee taught
to vnderſtande, and can not tell
how at the firſt, and to repent, and
can not tell how, and to reioyce,
and can not tell how, and to love
God and his Saints, and can not
tell how, and to beleeve, and cannot
tell how, which all notwithſtanding
are the proper workes of
the ſpirit.
            Neither ſpeake I this to ſhunne
the anſwering of your queſtion

touching the diſcerning of the ſpirites
teſtimonie, which I pray the
Lord to teach vs all, ſeeing there
can indeed no ſolide ioy poſſeſſe
our mindes, till we feele the ſpirit
of Adoption ſealing vp the certaintie
of our electiō in our harts:
for if we bee ſonnes (as ſaieth the
Apoſtle) the Lord hath ſent forth the
ſpirit of his ſonne in our heartes,
               Galat 4. 6. 
               which
crieth Abba,
               Rom. 8. 10 
               Father: and therefore
if any mā hath not the ſpirit of Chriſt,
the ſame is not his.
            
            Seeing then it is even by the ſpirit
which he hath givē vs, that we
know our ſelves to bee the ſonnes
of God, and that God as our Father
abydeth in vs,1 Ioh. 3. 24. as ſaieth Iohn:
It is a moſt neceſſarie ſtudie, and
moſt commendable in a Chriſtian,
to trie if he hath the ſpirit.
            Now therefore to come to your
queſtion, I will ſpeake of it in all
ſobrietie accordinge to that meaſure

of faith which the Lord hath
given me.
            Firſt in generall, it ſhall not bee
amiſſe to know what is the Teſtimonie
of the ſpirit.
            Secondly, after what maner the
ſpirit doth give teſtimonie.
            And laſtly, we ſhall cleerlie ſee
how to diſcerne it from the teſtimonie
of our owne ſpirit.
            In generall, the whole word of
God is the teſtimonie of the ſpirit.
For whatſoever is therein contayned,
the ſpirit doeth witnes it, and
nothing els doeth the ſpirit witnes,
but that which is contayned
in the word: therefore is the word
of God called his Teſtimon.Pſal. 19. 
               The
teſtimonie of the Lord is ſure. And againe:
God establiſhed a Teſtimonie
in Iacob.
               Pſal. 79. And oft times in the 119.
Pſalme, the Lords wordes are called
his Teſtimonies, becauſe everie
ſentence of the word, is a teſtimonie

of Gods will: Therefore is it
that the Prophet commands vs to
goe to the Lawe and to the Teſtimonie.
Eſa. 8. For nothing can we know
of Gods minde towards vs, except
we hearken what the ſpirit ſpeakes
in his worde. and therefore, Chriſt
willeth vs to ſearch the Scriptures,Ioh. 5. 39.
becauſe they witnes of him. So,
whatſoever the worde doeth perſwade
our hearts touching GOD
and his love in Chriſt, that is the
Teſtimonie of the ſpirit: and therfore
when hearing the worde of
God, our hearts receyves anie aſſurance
or perſwaſion of redemption,
remiſſion of ſinnes, &amp;c. that
ſame is and muſt be the ſpirits teſtimonie.
As for example, whē by
the word a man is made to knowe
Chriſt to be the Lord, the Redeemer,
&amp;c. doubtleſſe that is a teſtimonie
of Gods ſpirit, by the word
witneſſing to the heart that trueth

and cauſing the heart to beleve it.
But heere wee muſt carefully take
heede, that our hearts bee not deceyved
touching that which you
moſt diſire to know, that is, touching
our Adoption, by miſtaking
the ſpirits teſtimonie. For eſchewing
this danger we have to vnderſtande
that the ſpirit by the worde
perſwades two maner of wayes, to
wit, generallie and ſpeciallie, generallie
when that which is reveyled
out of the worde is generally
beleeved as Gods truth: ſpeciallie
when it is ſpeciallie beleeved. The
generall is no warrant of adoptiō.
For in that ſort the very Divells
beleeve and tremble,Iam. 2. 19. ſaieth Iames: a
reprobate may beleeve generally
all to be true which is in the word
of God, and yet never have anie
teſtimonie of the ſpirit, of his particular
adoption, hee may beleeve
that Chriſt is a Saviour of ſinners,

and yet not beleeve that hee is a
Saviour vnto him: he may beleeve
that God in Chriſt will forgive
ſinners: and yet no wayes have
aſſurance of the remiſſion of his
owne ſinnes: yea hee may bee a
Preacher, and be witnes of all the
promiſes of God in Chriſt to others,
&amp; yet have no parte in them
him ſelfe. Therefore leaving this
generall teſtimonie of the ſpirit, I
come to the ſpeciall teſtimonie,
which wee muſt diſcerne before
our Adoption bee ſealed to vs.
And in diſcerning this, there is
alſo great wiſedome required:
for therein alſo may a man be deceyved.
For there is ſome ſort of
ſpeciall teſtificatiō that witneſſeth
not adoption. For vnderſtanding
hereof, we muſt conſider that the
ſpirits teſtimonie in ſpeciall maner
is of two ſortes.
            
               
The firſt is, when hee witneſſes
and reveiles grace particularlie to
a man, but imprints not the thing
reveiled in the heart, neither ſeales
it in his ſoule.
            The ſecond is, when not onely
he reveyles and witneſſes the promiſes
in ſpeciall manner to a man,
but alſo writeth them in his heart,
and ſeales them in his ſoule. Now
to make this more plaine, we muſt
conſider what are the wordes of
Gods covenant in Chriſt with the
elect. After theſe dayes (ſaieth the
Lord) I will put my Lawes in their
minde,
               Ier. 31. Heb. 8. 
               and in their heart I will write
them. If we waye theſe wordes aright,
we ſhall ſee that which I
have ſpoken, cleere. GOD in giving
his Lawe ſpake to his people,
and by his ſpirit witneſſed his will
to them: but this word which was
ſpoken, was not written in their
hearts, but in tables of ſtone: therfore

the Iewes did not abyde in
that covenant. The peculiar promiſe
of God to the elect in Chriſt
is,Hebr. 8. 9. that he ſhall write his wordes in
their hearts. When thē the Lords
ſpirit, witneſſeth, &amp; in witneſſing
writes the thing witneſſed, in the
heart, it is an aſſurance of Gods
effectuall ſpeaking: but when hee
witneſſes to the heart, &amp; yet writes
not that teſtimonie in the heart, it
is no teſtimonie of adoption. To
make this plaine: it is certaine,
there can be no true faith in the
heart, where the worde of GOD
abydeth not. Chriſt ſhewes this in
the fift chap. of Iohn,
               Ioh. 5. 38. ſpeakinge to
the Iewes, His worde (ſayeth hee)
have ye not abyding in you, becauſe yee
beleeve not in him whom he hath ſent:
declaring that the abyding of the
worde in man, and beleeving, doe
ſtill accōpanie one the other. And
if we will conſider his ſpeech in

the ſixt chap. of Iohn, wee ſhall ſee
that the cauſe why his worde did
not abyde in them,Ioh. 6. 45. was, becauſe
they were not taught of God, that
is, they had not hard nor learned
of the Father, according to his promiſe,
I will put my lawes in their
minde; and in their heart will I
write them: therefore it is that
Moſes ſpeakinge of the eſtate of
the choſen children of God vnder
grace, ſaith, that this cōmandement
which I command thee this
day (meaning thereby the worde
of the Father) is not hid from thee,
neither is it farre from thee,
               Deut. 30. 12. 
               it is not
in the heaven, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay,
who ſhall goe vp for vs to heaven, and
bring it vs, and cauſe vs to heare it,
that we may do it: neither is it beyond
the ſea, that thou ſhouldest ſay, who ſhall
goe over the ſea for vs, and bring it vs
and cauſe vs to heare it, that wee may
doe it: but the word is very neare vnto

thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy
heart for to doe it.
               Rom. 10. 68. The Apoſtle expounds
the ſame to the Rom. and
ſhewes that this is the word of the
Father which they did preach. For
this is the promiſe of God to his
Church vnder the Goſpell, by the
mouth of his Prophet:Eſay. 54. 13. 
               All thy children
ſhalbe taught of the Lord: and
this is the Lords teaching, evē the
writing of his word in the hart by
his ſpirit.Ioh. 8. 30. Of the firſt ſort of this
ſpeciall receyving the word, you
may read in Iohn: it is ſaid of the
Iewes, many beleeved in Chriſt, &amp; yet
theſe ſame doth Chriſt declare to
be the ſervants of ſinne, &amp; childrē
of the divel, &amp; murtherers. and in
the 37. verſe he ſhewes why they
were ſuch, becauſe his word had
no place in thē: therefore doth he
warn thē in the 31. ver. that if they
did cōtinue in his word, they were
verily his diſcipl. teaching thereby

that it is not the receyving of his
word ſimplie, that maketh vs diſciples:
but the abydiug in it,
which none can doe that hath it
not written in their heart by the
ſpirit. Of the ſecond ſorte of the
ſpeciall receyving the word, you
may read in the 17. chap. of Iohn,
in the wordes of Chriſt concerning
his Diſciples: I have given
them the wordes which thou gavest
mee,
               Ioh 17. 8. 
               &amp; they have receyved them, &amp;c.
Of both theſe ſortes of receyving
the ſpirites teſtimonie, you may
read in the Goſpell of Saint Math.
in the Parable of the Sower, the
one is like the ground which receyveth
ſeed,Mat. 13. 18. but yeeldeth no
fruit againe: the other is like the
ground which receiveth the ſeed,
and bringeth forth fruit in aboundance:
becauſe God the Father is
the Huſbande man thereof: as
Chriſt ſayeth in the 15. chapter of

Iohn. But you may aſke, how I
can call this ſorte of witneſſinge
which is fruitleſſe, to be the ſpirits
teſtimonie? Remēber I pray you
what the Apoſtle ſaieth to the Corinthians,
No man can call Ieſus
Lord but by the H. ghoſt.1 Cor. 12. 3. Whereby
it is plaine that there is no poſſibilitie
in man of receyving or acknowledging
any part of that myſterie
of godlynes, without the ſpirits
working. And yet, albeit this
be the worke of the ſpirit, yet doth
it not prove him in whom it is, to
be the childe of God. For Chriſt
ſaieth plainly,Mat. 7. 21. 
               Not every one that call
me Lord, Lorde, shall enter into the
kingdome of heaven.
            
            And becauſe this ſame effect in
the verie reprobate,1 Cor. 2. 14. is the work of
the ſpirit (for the naturall man can
not perceyve the things of the ſpirit)
therefore are the very reprobate
thus illuminate after this maner

ſaid, to have bene made partakers
of the H. ghoſt,Heb. 6. 4. not that ever
that ſpirit of Adoptiō, which God
ſendes foorth in the heartes of his
ſonnes to ſeale them vnto the day
of redemption, was ever ſent into
their hearts. But becauſe even that
light &amp; taſt of heavēly things whiche
they received, was by the working
of the H. ghoſt: although he
never did give thē ful poſſeſſion of
them by imprinting them in their
harts, &amp; ſealing thē in their ſoules.
For that which Chriſt ſaith to his
diſcip. (whē he promiſeth to ſend
thē the ſpirit of truth) remayneth
ſtill true, that the world can not receive
him,Ioh. 14. 17 becauſe it ſeeth him not
neither knoweth him: &amp; therfore
wee may iuſtly ſay, that they who
receive this taſt of Chriſt &amp; of the
good word of god, do not diſcern
the ſpirit to worke theſe thinges,
becauſe they neither ſee him nor
know him, neither cā they receive

him, but are like vnto natural men,
who albeit they have their being,Act. 17. 28▪
               
&amp; life, &amp; moving in God, yet ſtill
remain without God in this world.Ephe. 2. 12.
But it may thē be demanded how
it is that they are ſaid to bee made
partakers of the H. ghoſt? and what
difference is there betwixt them &amp;
the elect in the participatiō of the
ſpirit? To vnderſtand this, we muſt
remember that ther muſt be a certain
participatiō of the ſpirit wherſoever
any effect of the ſpirit is
foūd in whatſoever meaſure or maner.
But we are to mark a differēce
both of meaſure &amp; maner. For as a
mā that hath an excellent piece of
wine to ſel, wil give to al that com,
ſo much as is ſufficiēt to make thē
knowe the taſt of it, yet he giveth
not to every one ſuch a quātitie as
is ſufficiēt to bring nouriſhment &amp;
refreſhment to their bodyes &amp; ſpirits.
And as a phiſicion that hath
prepared a comfortable potiō for

the health of a beloved patient, he
will give to others a little of it to
make them apprehende the taſte
of it: but not ſo, as to have anie
ſtrength to make anie operation in
their ſtomacke: for that quantitie
hee gives onely to the patient for
whoſe health it is prepared.
            Nowe they who taſted of this
wine or potion, can diſcerne the
goodneſſe of it, albeit they never
did drinke it, nor ever be partakers
of the refreſhing power of it.
            So is it with the Lorde in his
diſpenſation: he vſeth ſometimes
onely to give a naked ſight and
knowledge of Chriſt, and his mercie
in him, to men: and this I called
before a generall perſwaſion of
the ſpirit, when men are made to
know Chriſt in generall, but without
all ſenſe of feelinge of him.
            Somtimes the ſpirit comes nearer,
and touches the heart with Chriſt

and with the powers of the world
to come, even ſo farre, as the heart
receiveth a taſt of the love of God,
&amp; of the mercies of God in Chriſt,
in ſuch ſorte, that they receive the
word incontinentlie with ioy:Math. 13. 20. as
ſaith Chriſt. The ſpirit havinge in
that meaſure teſtified the worde
to them, as is ſufficient to make
them to taſte the ſweetnes of it:
albeeit hee never fill their heart
with it, nor imprint it in their
mindes, that they may finde the
power of it vnto life. The laſt degree
of the ſpirites witneſſinge, is,
when not onely he touches the
lippes with grace to make the taſt
of it felt: but when hee poures in
the love of God, and all the graces
reveyled in the worde, and ſhedds
them abroad in the heart: as ſaith
the Apoſtle to the Romans,Rom. 5. 5. and
ſo makes the heart to enioy, receyve
and poſſeſſe the promiſe by

printing it therein. So that the
working and witneſſing of the ſpirit,
in the wicked, is like the ſmell
of an Apothecaris ſhop: which
one that paſſeth by, receyveth, although
hee never carrie anie of
theſe odoriferous things with him
But the witneſſing of the ſpirit, to
the elect, is by imparting the thing
witneſſed to the ſoule, &amp; making
it reallie to poſſeſſe it. So that if a
man could ſee the ſoule of a true
child of God, he ſhould ſee ingraven
in it, mercie, peace, love, righteouſnes,
life, ioy, and Chriſt himſelfe.
all the promiſes of God in
Chriſt, being written therein, by
the ſpirit, according to the covenant
of God. Conforme to this,
doth the Apoſtle ſpeake of the ſpirits
witneſſing to the hearts of the
Corinthians, when hee ſaieth, yee
are manifeſt to bee the Epiſtle of

Chriſt, miniſtred by vs, and written,
not with inck, but with the ſpirite
of the livinge GOD: not in
Tables of ſtone, but in fleſhly tables of
the heart.
            
            Nowe therefore wee come to
ſpeake of this witneſſinge of the
ſpirit which is proper to the elect:
And to the ende wee may cleerelie
diſcerne, the teſtimonie of
the ſpirit, which witneſſeth with
our ſpirits, that we are the ſonnes
of GOD: wee muſt yet more
deepelie marke and conſider this
teſtimonie.
            The worke of the ſpirit in aſſuring
vs of Adoption, is twoofolde.
            The firſte, for diſtinction, wee
ſhall call this firſt writinge of the
worde reveyled, in our hearts,
and ſo makinge vs to beleeve in
God,Eph. 1. 13. as our God and Father in
Chriſt.
            
               
               The ſecond, is our ſealling, after
we have beleeved. That it is
ſo, ye may ſee in the wordes of the
Apoſtle to the Epheſians. In whom
alſo (ſayes he) ye have trusted after
that yee heard the word of trueth,Eph. 1. 13. even
the Goſpell of your ſalvation, wherein
alſo after yee beleeved, yee were ſealed
with the holy ſpirit of promiſe.
            Marke firſt this worke of the
ſpirit, in cauſing vs to beleeve in
God, by the effectuall revelation
of the worde: next, marke that
other worke of the ſpirit, after we
have beleeved, in ſealing vs. The
firſt of theſe two, although it bee
felt by vs, yet at the firſt, wee can
not diſcerne it to be the worke of
the ſpirit, till afterward. For, before
we be made ſpirituall, we can
diſcerne nothing of the ſpirit: becauſe
the things of the ſpirit are
ſpiritually diſcerned.1 Cor. 2. But when
we receyve the ſpirit which is of

God, then are we able to knowe
the things which are given to vs
of God. Therefore that teſtimonie
whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to
the Rom. which witneſſeth with
our ſpirits: is to be vnderſtood of
the ſeconde worke of the ſpirit,
which is our ſealing.
            That we may vnderſtande this
aright, we muſt conſider that there
is ſomething that cōmeth in in vs
betwixt the firſt worke of the ſpirit
and the ſecond. And that is the
teſtimonie of our owne ſpirit, bearing
witnes, that we are the ſonnes
of God. For when God by his ſpirit,
hath imprinted in our heartes,
the word of promiſe, then begins
our hearts to ſay, we are the children
of God: being perſwaded by
the ſpirit, ſecretlie inſinuating the
worde in our hearts to beleeve,Pſal. 116. 10. &amp;
beleeving to ſpeak:1 Cor. 4. 13. according as it
is ſaid, I beleved &amp; therfore did ſpeak.
            
            
               
Now it might ſeeme there needed
no more. but let vs remember
what Chriſt ſaith to Peter,
               Luc. 22. 31. 
               Simon,
Simon, behold Sathan hath deſired to
ſift you as wheat, but I have prayed for
thee that thy faith faile not. So wee
have need that our heartes be eſtabliſhed
in that worke of the ſpirit,
otherwayes we ſhould bee in danger
to make ſhipwracke of faith &amp;
of a good conſcience: which is nothing
els but this teſtimonie of
our owne hearts. Therefore doth
the Church pray in the Pſalme:Pſal. 68. 28.
               Establiſh O God that which thou hast
wrought in vs. And the Apoſtle, after
hee hath given thankes vnto
God for the Theſſalonians effectuall
calling, he prayes to GOD,
That hee who had given them this
good hope through grace, would alſo eſtabliſh
them in everie word and good
worke. Therefore is it that our
God, for ſtabliſhing vs in faith, &amp;

in the aſſurance of our Adoption,
ſeales vs by the holy ſpirit of promiſe.
This is manifeſt out of the
former place to the Epheſ. where
he ſaieth, That after they beleeved,
they were ſealed with the holy ſpirit of
promiſe. This ſame doth the Apoſtle
to the Gallat. confirme, when
hee ſheweth that Chriſt was ſent
to this ende,Gal. 4. 6. to redeeme vs: That
we might receyve the Adoption of the
ſonnes: and then he addeth, and becauſe
yee are ſonnes, GOD hath ſent
foorth the ſpirit of his ſonne into your
hearts, that crieth Abba, Father. And
that this ſealing of vs, by ſendinge
forth the ſpirit of Adoptiō in our
hearts, is the meane whereby God
eſtabliſheth vs, it is manifeſt by
the Apoſtle to the Corinthians.2 Cor. 1. 21.
For when firſt hee hath ſhewed,
that it is God which eſtabliſheth,
ſaying, It is God which eſtabliſheth
vs with you in Christ: then addeth

he the meane whereby God did
ſtabliſh them, ſaying: and hath anointed
vs, who hath alſo ſealed vs, and
hath given the earnest of the ſpirit in
our hearts. Which three ſayings are
all one thing in ſubſtance. Therefore
doeth Iohn, from this anointing,
confirme and aſſure theſe to
whom he did write, againſt the
fearing to fall away: but (ſaith he)
The anointing which yee receyved of
him,
               1 Ioh. 2. 27. 
               dwelleth in you: and as it taught
you, yee ſhall abide in him. And the
Apoſtle to the Corinthians taketh
the Argument of his confidence
from this,2 Cor. 5. 5. 
               that God hath given vs the
earnest of the ſpirit. And the ſame
Apoſtle from this giving of vs the
ſpirit of libertie which crieth Abba
Father, proveth vs to bee the
ſonnes of God in that eight chap.
to the Romanes.Rom 8. 15▪ 16. Whereby it is
plaine, that by theſe three, the ſelfſame
thing is meant: albeit diverſlie

expreſſed: accordinge to the
three ſortes of confirmation, the
one by anointing, ſo were Kings,
Prieſtes and Prophetes confirmed
in their calling: the other by an
earneſt, which is a cōfirmation of
the bargaine, and of the payement
of the full ſomme:Dan. 6. 
                     •
                  . and the laſt, by
ſealing, which in all writes, contractes,
and obligations, is a confirmation
of all therein conteyned
and promiſed. Accordinge to
which, amongſt the Perſians, whatſoever
was ſealed with the Kinges
Ring, could not bee changed nor
revoked. Therefore, whomſoever
God ſeales vnto life, as his child:
he is made moſt ſure of eternall
life. For this cauſe is it, that in the
Revelatiō,Revel. 7. 3 God firſt will have his
childrē ſealed before the enemies
can have power to execute their
malice,Ma. 16. 18 and of theſe thus ſealed, it
is, that Chriſt ſaieth, that the gates

of hell ſhall not prevayle against them.
And that they shall never periſh, neither
ſhall any plucke them out of his
hande.
               Ioh. 10. 28
            
            Now, this ſame ſending foorth
of the ſpirit of Adoption in our
hearts, is our ſealinge. Therefore
ſaieth the Apoſt. to the Epheſians,
ye were ſealed with the holy ſpirit of
promiſe. And this ſame is alſo our
anointing, poured out vpon vs, as
that oyle on Aaron:
               Ioel 2. 28. therefore are
we ſaide to have this annointing
from him which is holy,Act. 2. 17. and that
it teacheth vs,1 Ioh. 2. 2. and that it is true, &amp;
not lying: according to that whiche
is ſaid by Chriſt of the ſpirit:
I will pray the Father,
               Io. 14. 
               &amp; he will give
you another comforter, that hee may abyde
with you for ever, even the ſpirit
of trueth, he shall teach you all things;
And the ſame alſo is our earneſt:2 Cor. 5. 5
therefore it is called the earneſt of
the ſpirit: and alſo the firſt fruites

of the ſpirit. So by the ſame ſpirit,
as by oyle, as by earneſt, as by a
ſeale, doth God ſtabliſh our harts,
in that which they doe witnes to
vs, touching our Adoption. And
that doth the Apoſtle ſignifie whē
he ſaieth,Rom. 8. 16. 
               the ſame ſpirit beareth witnes
with our ſpirits, that wee are the
ſonnes of God.
            
            Marke then the order of Gods
working. Firſt he ſpeakes the word
of trueth to the heart, and in ſpeaking,
writes it in the heart: heerevpon
the heart is made to beleeve
that which it hath heard &amp; receyved,
from the ſpirit: and when it
beleeves, it ſpeakes, and the thing
it ſpeakes, is that ſame, which is
engravē in it, by the ſpirit: to wit,
that God is his God, and hee his
child. For never can the hart of a
man ſpeak one word of mercie to
him, nor of Adoption, till the ſpirit
of God have ſpoken firſt mercie

to it. Nowe when the ſpirit of
man hath ſpoken, and given teſtimonie
to him, of his election, he
                  •
               
the Lord for eſtabliſhing the heart
in this, and confirming man in the
teſtimonie of his heart, he addeth
his ſpirit: and by the teſtimonie
thereof, ſeales this promiſe in the
heart, and makes Adoption and
eternall life, moſt certaine and ſure
to the ſoule, that he dare be bold
with the Apoſtle to ſay,Rō. 8. 33. 
               Who ſhall
lay any thing to my charge? who ſhall
condempne me? who ſhall ſeperate mee
from the love of Christ: I am perſwaded
that neither death nor life, nor
anguiſh, &amp;c. ſhall bee able to ſeperate
me from the love of God which is in
Ieſus Christ my Lord.
            
            And that we may yet more evidentlie
ſee the neceſſitie of this teſtimonie
of Gods ſpirit: we are to
conſider that albeit our own harts
have in them a power to witnes

vnto vs what wee are both by nature
and by grace, yet the teſtimonie
of our heartes touching our eſtate
by grace, is not ſo fullie and
confidentlie to bee repoſed vpon
and truſted, as the teſtimonie therof
touching our eſtate by nature.
For wee may aſſuredly truſt our
hearts and cōſciences,Deut. 27. 21. when vpon
anie guiltines they condemne vs,
ſeeing hee is curſed who abydes
not in everie jo
                  •
                of the Law to fulfil
it:Gal. 3. 10. &amp; he that trāſgreſſeth one cō
               mandment,
Iam. 2. 10. is guiltie of all: but we
are not always to give abſolut credit
to our conſciences, when vpon
conceit of innocēcie they iuſtifie
vs. For although our conſciences
accuſe vs of nothing, yet thereby
we are not iuſtified, as is plaine by
the ſaying of the Apoſt. touching
himſelf 1. Cor. 4. 4. the reaſon hereof
is, becauſe our conſciences doe
not ſo cleerlie ſee our eſtate which

is from God, neither can they of
them ſelves ſo truely iudge of it, as
they may do of their eſtate by nature,
when they are illuminate by
God: for then they are made to
know and cleerly to ſee that in vs
there is no goodnes, and therefore
ther is iuſt reaſon why they ſhould
condempne vs. And we are verily
to beleeve our harts vpō this ſight
and knowledge condempning vs.
but on the other part, although
we ſee the minde of God towards
vs in Chriſt, yet wee can not ſo
throughly apprehende his promiſes
vpon any ſight we receive, that
we dar truſt our felicitie abſolutly
to the teſtimonie of our owne
hearts. Firſt, becauſe our heartes
may be deceyved, as is evident by
ſcripture, that many ſhall bee. Secondly,
becauſe wee may miſtake
the working of God in vs, and lay
hold on a wrong ground. Thirdlie,

becauſe our heartes are more
prone to ſpeake good nor evill of
our ſelves, even when they have
neuer ſo ſmall occſion to doe ſo,
and when they have much more
occaſion to do the contrarie. And
laſtlie, becauſe all men are lyars, &amp;
onely God is true, and therfore we
muſt never give ſo much credit to
our conſciences, ſpeaking good of
vs, as when they ſpeake evill: ſpeciallie
when the queſtion is of being
the ſonnes of God, or not: ſo
that even when they witnes that
we are the ſonnes of God, wee are
not to reſt herevpon except God,
who only knoweth whom he hath
choſen, doe by his ſpirit confirme
the teſtimonie of our ſpirit. For
we may much more ſurely truſt
our heartes in that which is in our
ſelves and from our ſelves, then in
that which is neither from our ſelves
nor in our ſelves, but is the free

gift of God in Chriſt. Therefore
that we ſhould not bee deceyved
by our deceitful harts, God ſecoū
               deth
our owne teſtimonie touching
his taking of vs for his children,
by his ſpirit, witneſſinge the
ſame: even as by his owne mouth
cōfirming our adoptiō. For by the
mouth of two or three witneſſes
ſhal everie word be ſtabliſhed.
            Thus I have ſhewen you what
is the ſpirits teſtimonie, &amp; in what
manner he gives it, and how neceſſarie
it is. Now I come to that
which you deſired to know: that
is, how wee diſcerne the teſtimonie
of the ſpirit which ſeales our
Adoption from the teſtimonie of
our owne ſpirit. For knowledge of
this, Firſt, let vs conſider, that there
be three things, whereby wee diſcerne
our Election and Adoption
from the ſpirit of God. The firſt
is his preſence with vs. The ſecond

is his worke in vs. The third
is his voyce vnto vs.
            Touching the firſt: the verie
preſence of the ſpirit of Adoptiō,
is a witneſſe of our Adoption. For
the ſpirit is the earneſt of the inheritance
of God, as wee have
ſhewen before: therefore whoſoever
hath the ſpirit, the verie having
of him, is a ſure teſtimonie to
that man, that he is the ſonne of
God: For he that hath the ſpirit of
Christ,
               Rom. 8. 9. 
               he is Chriſtes: as by the contrarie, hee that hath not the ſpirit of
Chriſt, is not Chriſtes. Now the having
of the ſpirit is diſcerned by
the other two, that is, by the work,
and by the voyce: therefore thoſe
two are chiefly to be conſidered:
firſt his worke in vs, which muſt
go before his voyce: I meane this
voyce which ſeales Adoptiō: For
otherwayes his voyce alwayes goeth
before his worke: for it is by

the worde, that hee worketh, all
things in vs.
            For vnderſtanding of this work
and voyce of the ſpirit which ſealeth
adoption, marke the wordes
of the Apoſtle in that ſame eight
chap. of the Rom, touchinge the
ſpirit, Yee have not receyved (ſayeth
he) the ſpirit of bondage to feare againe,
               Rom. 8. 15▪
               
               but yee have receyved the ſpirit
of Adoption, whereby wee crye, Abba
Father. Heere Adoption (vnder
which is vnderſtood libertie) is opponed
to bondage, as the effect of
the ſpirit. Next, the voyce following
heerevpon, is manifeſt in the
wordes following: (whereby wee
crye, Abba, Father). Which crye,
more plainly is ſaide by the Apoſtle
to the Galathians, to bee the
crie of the ſpirit, ſaying: and becauſe
yee are ſonnes,
               Gal. 4. 6. 
               God hath ſent forth the
ſpirit of his ſonne in your harts which
cryeth Abba, Father. And therefore

is it that the Apoſtle to the Romans
ſaieth, that the ſame ſpirit beareth
witneſſe with our ſpirit, that we are the
children of God. What then is this
worke of the ſpirit in vs, that witneſſeth
Adoption? This ſpeciall
worke, is, libertie, or freedome: accompanied
ever with peace, boldnes,
confidence, and reioycing.
This is plaine by theſe places of
ſcripture. Firſt, the Apoſtle to the
Corinthians, ſpeaking of this firſt
great effect of the ſpirit,2. Cor. 3. 17. ſaith: Now
the Lord is the ſpirit, and where the
ſpirit of the Lord is, there is libertie:
and of the peace that accōpanies
this libertie,Eph. 2. 13. the Apoſtle ſpeakes
plainlie to the Epheſians, where,
after he hath ſhewē, that by Chriſt
we are delivered from the Law of
commandements &amp; hatred, that
thereby did lye vpon vs, and hath
ſpoken of the peace followinge
therevpon, hee proves this peace

by theſe wordes: for through him
wee both haue an entrance vnto the
Father by one ſpirit.
               Eph. 2. 18 Therefore the
ſame Apoſtle to the Romans,
ſayeth,Rom. 5. 1. 
               That being iustified by faith,
wee have peace towardes God. Of this
boldnes and confidence, the Apoſtle
ſpeakes to the Epheſians,
ſaying:Eph. 3. 12 
               By whom wee have boldnes
and acceſſe with confidence by faith
in him. Therefore is it that the
Apoſtle to the Romans, ſayeth:
That wee have not receyved the ſpirit
of bondage vnto feare, but the ſpirit
that is without feare, that is, of boldnes
and confidence. Touching reioycing,
the Apoſtle Peter ſpeaketh,
1 Pet. 1. 8. ſaying: In whom beleeving, yee
reioyce with ioye vnſpeakeable and
glorious. The ſame alſo affirmeth
the Apoſtle to the Rom. ſaying &amp;

we reioyce vnder the hope of the glorie
of God,
               Rom. 5. 2. 
               neither ſo onely, but wee reioyce
alſo in tribulations, and he addes the

reaſon, becauſe the love of God is ſhed
abroad in our heartes by the holy ghost
which is given vnto vs. This I call
the ſpeciall working of the ſpirit,
for ſealing our Adoption: becauſe
theſe effectes cannot poſſiblie bee
in vs, except the ſpirit of adoption
worke them. and therefore whoſoever
hath them, hee hath an vndoubted
teſtimonie of his adoption,
from the verie ſpirit of adoption.
For this libertie, and effectes
of it, are not the worke of a mans
owne hart: but the work of Gods
ſpirit, in the heart: making it free,
&amp; cauſing it to reioyce, &amp; making
it cōfident towards God, that this
may be cleere, we have to conſider
the eſtate of man, firſt, in ignorāce
and blindnes, before he knewe either
God, or him ſelfe. Secondly,
his eſtate vnder the Lawe. And
laſtlie, his eſtate vnder grace thorough
the Goſpell.
            
               
In the two former caſes, there is
nothing in mans heart, but blindnes,
or the ſpirit of bondage, vnto
feare: yea even in the verie elect,
before they receyve this ſpirit of
Adoption and grace, by the Goſpell.
            In man by nature, as he is borne,
there is nothinge but blindnes, I
ſay nothing, not that I exclude
bondage: for in both the firſt two
eſtates of man, blindnes and bondage
doe accompanie each other:
but in the firſt eſtate, blindnes ſo
reigneth, that bondage is not perceyved
nor felt. In the ſecond, although
blindnes be ſo farre taken
away, as man ſee and feele his bō
               dage:
yet it is not ſo taken away,
that it hide not from him his libertie
and freedome. Therefore in
the firſt he is the ſlave of blindnes
and darkneſſe: becauſe the power
thereof is predominant in him:

holding him in ignorāce of God,
of him ſelfe, of ſinne, and of true
righteouſnes. Therefore doth the
ſcripture ſay,Rom. 3. 11 
               There is none that vnderstandeth,
there is none that ſeeketh
God. And the Apoſt. to the Epheſians,
ſhewing the naturall eſtate
of man,Eph. 2. 12. declareth that he is without
Christ, an aliant from the common
wealth of Iſrael, a ſtranger from
the covenant of promiſe, without hope,
and without God in the worlde. And
therefore ſpeakinge of the vaine
converſation of men naturall, hee
ſheweth the cauſes of it to be this,
becauſe they have their vnderſtanding
darkened,
               Ep. 4. 8. 
               beeing ſtrangers from the
life of God, through the ignorāre that
is in them. And moſt cleerlie in the
fift chapter,Cha. 5. 8. 
               for ye were once darknes,
meaning by nature: and therefore
they who are effectuallie called to
grace, are in that ſame place ſaide,
to be light in the Lord. And by the

Apoſtle Peter,
               1. Pet. 2. 9. are ſaid, to be called of
God out of darknes to his marveylous
light.
               1. Theſ. 5. 5. And to the Theſſalonians,
they that are called, are ſaide, to be
of the day and of the light. And they
which are not called, are ſaide, to
be of the night, and of darknes. And
the Apoſtle to the Coloſſians (willing
to ſhewe the force of darknes
in holding men in bondage) expreſſes
their calling by GOD, in
theſe wordes:Coloſ. 1. 13. 
               who hath drawen vs
out vnder the power of darknes. So it
is manifeſt, that in our eſtate naturall,
wherein (as ſaith the Apoſtle
to the Galathians) wee knowe not
God.
               Gal. 4. 8. darknes hath power and dominion
over vs in ſuch ſorte, that
we have no libertie of minde, nor
body, to ſerve God: the minde
being kept in ignorance of God,
of righteouſnes and of ſinne. And
ſo conſequentlie, man in this eſtate,
is without feare. Not becauſe

he is not in danger, but becauſe
hee ſeeth not his danger.
Therefore alſo may he bee ſecure,
becauſe he is ſenſeleſſe: but confident
hee can not be, becauſe hee
hath no knowledge. It is true,
men in this caſe are commonly
moſt peart in ſinne, and bolde in
wickedneſſe, againſt GOD: becauſe
they know neither him, nor
them ſelves. And therefore, oft tymes,
as fooliſh flyes, they ruſh
vpon the candle: or blinde horſes
doe runne againſt the wall: but
bolde and confident in him, they
can not be, who knowes him not
in Chriſt. Therefore doth the Apoſtle
declare that the cauſe why
ſuch men give themſelves to wantonneſſe,
Eph. 4. 19. is, becauſe they have no
feeling.
            Now in the ſecond eſtate, vnder
the Lawe, we are further from
libertie, and the remaynant bleſſings

of the ſpirit of Adoptiō. For
albeit that ſome light ariſe in the
heart, by the Lawe: as the knowledge
of ſinne (conforme to that
of the Apoſtle,Rom. 7. 7 
               I knew not ſinne but
by the Law) yet this light, doeth
only reveyle to man his bondage:
but doth not remove nor remedie
it: becauſe that was impoſſible to
the Lawe, in as much as it was weak
becauſe of the fleſh, as ſaieth the ſame
Apoſtle.Rom. 8. 3. Therefore this light of
the Lawe, although it bee neceſſarie,
yet it is comfortleſſe. For it
ſhewes firſt to man,Rō. 7. 14. that he is ſolde
vnder ſinne,
               Gal. 3. 10. and that no good dwelleth
in him.
               Rō. 7. 10. Heerevpon, it reveiles
vnto him, that hee is vnder the
curſe of God, and ſo that hee is
dead. Wherevpon it comes to
paſſe, that God therein is ſo terrible
to man, that hee cannot abyde
him, nor heare him, but is compelled
to runne from him: as is

cleere by the 12. chapt. of the Hebrues,
verſe 19. 20. 21. compared
with Exod. chapt. 20. verſe 18. 19.
20. 21. Thus our former blindnes,
is turned into bondage, and the
fruit of blindnes, that is ſecuritie:
is turned in the fruit of bondage,
which is feare. Therefore the miniſterie
of the Lawe, is called, the
miniſterie of death and condempnatiō.
2 Cor. 3. And in the firſt act of Gods
calling, the ſpirit that ſpeaketh in
the Lawe, and is given by the miniſterie
of the Lawe, is called the
ſpirit of bondage, vnto feare. Becauſe
the ſight and knowledge of
our ſelves, and of God, which the
ſpirit gives vs by the Lawe,Rom. 8. 15 workes
theſe effectes. And therefore by
that name is diſtinguiſhed, from
the ſpirit of Adoption, which is
given by the Goſpell. and this will
the Apoſtle ſignifie to the Galathians,
when he (comparinge the

two Teſtaments to the two, by
whom Abraham begot Iſmael &amp;
Iſaack) doeth ſhewe,Gal. 4. 24. that the one,
which is from Mount Sinai, doeth
beget vnto bondage.
            This being the eſtate of man,
both by nature and by the Lawe:
it is manifeſt, that theſe effectes of
the ſpirit, which witneſſe adoption,
are not in man, neither by nature,
neither by the Lawe. But
when the free ſpirit of the Lorde
commeth, then commeth libertie
to the heart. And this ſpirit of the
Lord (otherwayes called the ſpirit
of promiſe) comes to vs by the
preaching of faith, and not of the
workes of the Lawe: as witneſſeth
the Apoſtle to the Galathians,Gal. 3. 2. and 14. and
the hiſtorie of the Actes of the Apoſtles.Act. 10. 44.
            
            Nowe then, when the man,
(who firſt by nature, was vnder
blindnes: and next, by the Lawe,

was vnder ſinne and death, kept
in bondage and feare) findes him
ſelfe, firſt delivered frō that blindnes
and ignorance of minde: and
next, from that bondage of ſinne
and death: and ſo conſequentlie
frō his feare, which was wrought
in him by his bondage, then may
he knowe, that the ſpirit of adoption,
grace, and libertie, hath ſpoken
to his heart, and hath taken
poſſeſſion of it: becauſe he findes,
that promiſe accōpliſhed in him,
whereof Zacharias ſpeaketh, in the
Goſpell, according to Luke: to
wit; that God would grant to vs, that
we being delivered out of the handes
of our enemies,
               Luk. 1. 74 
               ſhould ſerve him without
feare, all the dayes of our life, in
holynes and righteouſnes before him.
For this was the ende of Chriſtes
death, ſayeth the Apoſtle to the
Hebrewes, to witt, that hee might
deliver all them,
               Heb. 2. 15 
               who for feare of

death,
               Heb. 2. 15 
               were all their life tyme ſubiect
to bondage. Thus therefore, the mā,
who can diſcerne in his hearte,
which once was filled with the
ſpirit of bondage vnto feare, the
ioyfull libertie of the ſonnes of
God: whereby hee that was the
bondman and ſeruant of ſinne, by
the Lawe, is now by the Goſpell,
made the free man of Chriſt, (the
bandes of iniquitie being broken)
and ſo freed, both from the guiltines,
and alſo from the power of
ſinne: (being iuſtified by faith in
Ieſus Chriſt, and having grace, in
the ſuperabondance thereof; reigning
through righteouſnes vnto
eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt
our Lord:Rom. 5. 1. and 21. even in the ſoule, wherin
ſinne in the aboūdance thereof,
had reigned through vnrighteouſnes
vnto death): this mā I ſay, may
eaſilie diſcerne, the ſpirit, witneſſing
his adoption, by this his libertie

from the ſlauerie of ſinne Firſt
in his iuſtification, next in his ſanctification:
and ſo conſequentlie
from the feare of death following
thereon. In place whereof, ſucceeds,
a ioye vnſpeakeable &amp; glorious:
the hart iuſtified, reioycing
in the hope of the glorie of God.
For this cauſe is it,Pet. 1. 8. that the Apoſtle
Peter, willeth vs by ioyning vertue
to our faith,
               Rom. 5. 2. 
               and to vertue knowledge,
and to knowledge temperance,
               2 Pet. 1. 10
&amp;c. to make our calling and election
ſure. Becauſe our ſanctification
(being the worke of the ſpirit
of adoption) is a ſure ſeale of our
election. And therefore doeth the
Apoſtle Peter give this reaſon of
his threatning and rebuke againſt
Simon Magus, to wit, that albeit he
was baptiſed, yet the Apoſtle did
ſee, that he was in the gale of bitterneſſe,
and in the band of iniquitie:
wherein, Simon being ſtill

captive, could have no aſſurance
of adoption: albeit hee had outwardly
embraced the Goſpell:
and therefore is ſaid, to have beleeved.
And becauſe this worke,
is the great worke of Chriſt, in the
elect, and chief ende of his comming:
Therefore doeth the Prophet
Eſaie deſcribe the worke of
his comming, and effect of the
ſpirit of the Lord in him, in theſe
wordes:Eſa. 61. 1. 
               The ſpirit of the Lorde is
vpon mee, the Lord hath annointed
me, that I ſhould preach the Goſpell to
the poore: that I ſhould heale the broken
hearted: that I ſhould preach deliverie
to the captives, and receyvinge
of ſight to the blinde: that I ſhould ſet
at libertie them that are bruſed, and
that I ſhould preach the acceptable
yeare of the Lord: to appoint vnto
them that murne in Zion, and to give
vnto them beautie for aſhes, the oyle of
ioye for mourning, the garmentes of

gladnes for the ſpirit of heavines, that
they might be called trees of righteouſnes,
the planting of the Lord. Which
Propheſie, Chriſt ſheweth to bee
fulfilled by him ſelfe in the Goſpell
accordinge to Luc. in the
which it is manifeſt, that the work
of the ſpirit,Luk. 4. 18. in preaching the Goſpell,
is, to worke knowledge and
libertie, in making vs trees of righteouſnes,
planted by God: and by
libertie, to worke ioye and gladnes,
in place of mourning &amp; heavines.
            Therefore is it by good reaſon,
that the Apoſtle forbiddes vs, to
let ſinne reigne in our mortall bodies,
               Rom. 6. 12
               that we ſhould obey it in the luſtes therof:
in reſpect wee are made free
from ſinne, in Chriſt: and are
made the ſervants of God: having
our fruit in holines. And alſo biddeth
vs reioyce alwayes in the Lord:
               Phil. 4. 4.
               for there is no condempnation to vs,

that are in Christ,
               Rom. 8. 1. 2. 
               ſeeing we are freed
from the lawe of ſinne and death, by
the lawe of the ſpirit of life which is in
Christ Ieſus. This is then that great
effect of the ſpirit of Adoption, in
our heartes, whereby, as by a moſt
ſure teſtimonie, wee diſcerne, the
ſpirit ſealing our Adoption. Becauſe
this ſpirit of adoptiō, which
is given vs by the preaching of the
Goſpell, takes away, both theſe
miſeries: to witt, the blindnes,
wherein we are by nature, &amp; next
the bondage, reveiled by the law,
and feare cauſed thereby.
            Havinge thus ſpoken, of the
worke of the ſpirit, it followeth
that we conſider the voyce of the
ſpirit.
            This voyce of the ſpirit, is of
two ſortes. The firſt is, when the
ſpirit within vs, ſpeaketh to God
for vs. The ſecond is, whē the ſpirit
in vs, ſpeaketh from God vnto

vs. The voice of the ſpirit to God,
is, when we by the ſpirit, call vpon
God as our Father. And this voice
of the ſpirit, is not only an evidēce
that we have the ſpirit, but alſo a
witnes of our Adoption: making
manifeſt vnto vs, that the ſpirit
hath wrought in vs, that worke of
libertie, whereof we have alreadie
ſpoken.
            
               Touching the firſt, it is manifeſt,
in that, without the ſpirit, we
can not pray vnto God: as teſtifieth
the Apoſtle to the Romans,
               Rom. 8. 26
               ſaying: The ſpirit alſo helpeth our infirmities:
for wee knowe not what to
pray as we cought: but the ſpirit it
ſelf, maketh request for vs with ſighes
that can not be expreſſed. Conforme
to this alſo doth the ſame Apoſtle
ſay in that ſame place,
               Rom. 8. 23 Wee alſo who
have the firſt fruites of the ſpirit, even
wee doe ſigh in our ſelves, waitinge
for the Adoption.
            
               
And this is cleerly confirmed by
the words of the Prophet Zacharie:
Zacha. 12. 10. 
               In that day, ſayeth the Lord, I will
poure vpon the houſe of David, and
vpon the inhabitanes of Ieruſalem, the
ſpirit of grace and of compaſsion, and
they ſhall looke vpon me whō they have
pearched, and they ſhall lament for
him, &amp;c. The veritie of this point
may be ſhewed by the nature of
prayer: in which firſt it is required,
that it be made vnto God. Secondly,
that it bee made in the
Name of Chriſt. Thirdly, that it
be made accordinge to the will of
God.
            Concerning the firſt, it cannot
be without the ſpirit: becauſe we
have no entrance nor acceſſe to
God in Chriſt, but by the ſpirit.
This is manifeſt by the Apoſtle,
ſaying:Eph. 2▪ 18. 
               For through him, wee both
have acceſſe to tbe Father, by one ſpirit.
Secondly, we can not pray in

the Name of Chriſt, except wee
acknowledge God his Father, and
in him our Father: which we can
never doe, except we be taught by
the ſpirit. For (as ſaieth the Apoſtle)
The ſpirit beareth witneſſe with
our ſpirit,
               Rom. 8. 16. 
               that we are the ſonnes of
God. Thirdly, no prayer can bee
made accordinge to the will of
God, but by the ſpirit: becauſe,
None knoweth the mynde of God,
               1 Cor. 2 1
                     •
                  
                
               but
the ſpirit of GOD.
               Rom. 8. 27. According to
which the ſame Apoſtle ſayeth:
That he that ſearceth the heartes, knoweth
what is the meaning of the ſpirit.
For hee maketh interceſsion for the
Saincts, according to the will of God.
By all theſe it is plaine, that none
can pray which have not the ſpirit.
For the babling of hypocrits,
is no prayer: ſeeing it proceedes
not from the ſpirit. And this is to
be vnderſtoode of all manner of
prayer. For all manner of prayer,

be it confeſſion, petition, ſupplication,
or giving of thankes, muſt
ſtill be by the ſpirit. According to
the ſaying of the Apoſtle. And
pray alway in all maner of prayer and
ſupplication in the ſpirit.
               Ephe. 6. 18.
            
            Moreover, this voyce of the
ſpirit is the witneſſe of our adoption:
and of the worke of our freedome
in Chriſt. Which is evident
by the Apoſtle, Firſt, in that hee
ſayeth, That by this ſpirit we crye Abba
Father. And the ſame Apoſtle,
to witneſſe the ſame trueth, ſayeth
in another place: Becauſe yee are
ſonnes, God hath ſent foorth the ſpirit
of his ſonne into your heartes,
               Gal. 4. 6. 
               crying
Abba Father. Which crie of the
ſpirit can not bee in vs, vntill firſt
we be the ſonnes of God: ſeeing
this crye contayneth in it, a plaine
profeſſion of our Adoption, while
the ſpirit in vs, doth call vpō God,
as our Father: and maketh vs call

vpon him, as our Father.
            Secondly, this is manifeſt by the
deſcription, which the Apoſtle
ſetteth downe, of the ſpirit, whereby
we crye Abba Father:Rom. 8. 15 
               That it
is not the ſpirit of bondage vnto feare,
but the ſpirit of adoption. Which by
the contrarie, may be vnderſtood,
to comprehend freedome and libertie.
According to the ſaying of
of the Apoſtle,2 Cor. 3. 17. 
               Where the ſpirit of
the Lord is, there is libertie For they
who live in darkneſſe, and in the
bandes of iniquitie, not yet made
partakers of the ioyfull libertie of
the ſonnes of God, can never with
boldnes approch to the throne of
grace, to call vpon GOD as their
Father Heerevpon it is that the
Scriptures abſolutely conclude,Ioel. 2. 32.
               That whoſoever ſhall call vpon the
Name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved.
               Rom. 10. 13.
            
            Becauſe no man can call vpō God,
vntill hee beleeve, that God is his

God, and he his ſonne in Chriſt:
according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle,
Rom. 10. 
               How ſhall they call vpon him,
in whom they have not beleeved?
This ſheweth plainlie, that the ſpirites
crie, or our callinge vpon
God by the ſpirit, as out Father,
is a ſure teſtimonie of our Adoption,
and ſeale of our effectuall
calling. Therefore, vnder the calling
vpon the Name of the Lord,
is oft ſet downe, the true and infallible
deſcription of Gods children:
as namelie, to the Corinthians,
Vnto the Church of GOD
which is at Corinth,
               1. Cor. 1. 2 
               with all that call
vpon the Name of the Lord IESVS
Christ in every place. And the ſame
Apoſtle ſheweth, that the foundation
of God which remayneth
ſure (that is, the election of God)
hath this ſeale, Let every one that
calleth vpon the Name of the Lord,
               2. Tim. 2. 
                     •
                  . 19. 
               depart
from iniquitie. Declaring plainlie,

that to call vpon the Name of
the Lord, is as much as to be one
of Gods elect children: which in
that ſame place is made manifeſt,
2. Tim. 2. 22. by this other ſentence, Follow
after righteouſnes faith, love and peace
with them that call vpon the Name of
the Lord with pure hearts.
            
            Thus wee are to take our calling
or cryinge on the Name of
the Lorde, with boldnes, in that
confidence, and aſſruance which
faith bringeth, for a ſure teſtimonie
of the ſpirit of Adoption, poſſeſſing
our heartes, and ſo of our
Adoption.
            The other voyce of the ſpirit, to
wit, when the ſpirit ſpeaketh from
God to vs, is likewiſe a moſt ſolide,
firme, and infallible teſtimonie
of our Adoption. And this
ſorte of voyce, is that whereof the
Prophet ſpeaketh,Eſay. 30. 21. 
               And thine eare
ſhall heare the voyce of one behinde

thee, ſaying: This is the way, &amp;c. Of
the ſame doeth the Lord ſpeake in
another place, ſaying: I will allure
hir and bring hir in the wildernes,
               Hoſ. 2. 14 
               and
ſpeake kindly vnto hir. Which places,
are not onely to bee referred,
to the Lords ſpeaking to his
Church, in the externall miniſterie
of his word: but are ſpeciallie
to be vnderſtoode, of the inwarde
working of God in the heart, by
his ſpirit. Of which ſorte of voyce
David ſpeaketh, when hee ſayeth
to the Lord,Pſal. 51. 8. 
               Let mee heare ioye and
gladneſſe, that the bones which thou
haſt broken, may reioyce. And this
ſorte of voyce is three folde, for it
conſiſteth eyther in Gods teaching,
or in his confirminge of that
which he teacheth: or then in his
conforting of his children in their
afflictions. Of the firſt, that is his
teaching voyce, wee have ſpoken
before.
            
               
For God by his ſpirit, ſpeakes
to vs, when inwardlie he openeth
our heartes, and maketh vs heare
his word of grace, and to vnderſtande
it, &amp; to receyve it. Of this
worke Chriſt ſpeaketh, when hee
ſayeth:Io. 14. 26. 
               But the Comforter which is
the holy ſpirit, whom the Father will
ſende in my Name, hee ſhall teach you
all things. Secondly, God is ſaid to
ſpeake vnto vs, by his ſpirit, when
hee confirmeth to vs, the thinge
which he hath ſpoken: and of this
wee have alſo ſpoken in generall.
And of this kinde of voyce ſpeaketh
the Apoſtle in that place to
the Romanes,Rō. 8. 15. ſayinge: The ſame
ſpirit heareth witneſſe with our ſpirit,
that wee are the ſonnes of God. Of
this confirmation, the ſame Apoſtle,
ſpeaketh to the Corinht. whē
he ſaieth,1. Cor. 1. 6 
               As the testimonie of Ieſus
Christ was confirmed in you. Which
wordes ſhewe the cleere evidence

of that two fould teſtimonie of
the ſpirit, whereof wee did ſpeake
before: The one, when God writeth
his word in our hearts: which
heere is vnderſtood by the teſtimonie
of Chriſt. The other, when
he ſeales that which hee hath ſpoken,
and in ſpeaking hath written
in our heartes: and that is here vnderſtood,
by the cōfirming of the
teſtimonie of Ieſus in vs. And for
this work of cōfirmation, the ſpirit
is called the earneſt &amp; ſeale of God
            And as God by his ſpirit ſealeth
and confirmeth all the promiſes in
Chriſt, and alſo all what hee himſelfe
hath wrought in vs according
to the promiſe. So among other
things, he ſpecially cōfirmeth
our Adoption, whē the ſpirit beareth
witneſſe to vs, that we are the
ſonnes of God. After that firſt he
hath effectuallie called vs by teaching
vs and working faith in our

hearts, and alſo hath made our
hearts (now beleeving) ſpeake to
vs that we are ſonnes.
            Thirdly, God is ſaid to ſpeake
vnto vs by his ſpirit, whē he comforted
vs in our troubles: removing
by his ſpirit, the anguiſh and
grief of our hearts, &amp; reſtoring vs
to our wonted ioyes in him again.
Of which voyce of the ſpirit, David
ſpeaketh whē he prayeth, Make
me heare ioy and gladneſſe.
               Pſal. 51. 8. 12. And a
                  •
               aine,
Reſtore me to the ioye of thy ſalvation,
and establiſh mee with thy free
ſpirit. For this worke the ſpirit is
called the Comforter.
            
            Nowe wee come to the laſt
point: which is the principal thing
which yee demaund: and that is,
Howe wee ſhall diſcerne this Teſtimonie
of the Lords ſpirit, from
the teſtimonie of our owne ſpirit.
And this is to bee done, eyther in
the time of peace, or trouble: although

it is more difficile in proſperitie,
to diſtinguiſh them.
            There is two voyces of the ſpirit,
as we have ſaide, which both
witneſſe our Adoption. The firſt,
when the ſpirit in vs, ſpeakes to
God.
            This teſtimonie of the ſpirit, is
diſcerned three wayes: The firſt
thing whereby we diſcerne, it is
the great heavines of heart and
ſorrowe which the conſcience of
ſinne breedeth in vs, whē (as ſaith
the Prophet) God having poured
vpon vs the ſpirit of grace and cō
               paſſion,
Wee looke vppon him whom
we have pea
                     •
                  ſed,
               Zach. 12. 10. 
               and lament for him,
as men mourne for their onely begotten
ſonne: and are ſorrie for him, as
men are for their firſt begotten childe.
Of this nature was the mourning
of Peter, after his deniall, when (as
ſayeth the holy ſcripture) hee went
out, and weeped bitterlie: and becauſe

this is a ſure 
                  •
               oken of ſaving
grace, therefore they that mourne
are compted bleſſed. This mourning
hath alwayes ioyned with it
an hunger &amp; thirſt for righteouſnes.
For ther can be no true mourning
for ſinne, where there is no
deſire of righteouſnes. And becauſe
this is the proper effect of
the ſpirit of grace in all and everie
one of thoſe who receyve him.
Therefore doeth the Lord by his
Prophet declare what ſhall be the
worke of the ſpirit of grace and
compaſſion in that day whē God
ſhall poure him out vpon his children,
ſayinge:Math. 26. 75. 
               Then ſhall there bee
great mourning at Ieruſalem: like as
the lamentation of Adadrimmon in
the valey of Megiddon,
               Math. 5. 4▪
                
               &amp;c. In which
place mourning is attributed to
everie familie,Zach. 12. 11. to everie ſtate, and
everie perſon, and that apart by
them ſelves, to ſhewe that it is a

common effect wrought by the
ſpirit in all Gods children, &amp; that
vnfainedly.
            The ſecond thing whereby we
diſcerne this teſtimonie of the ſpirit,
is the earneſt longing with vehement
grones and ſighes in our
ſelves for to be with Chriſt.
            Of this voyce of the ſpirit the
Apoſtle ſpeaketh, when he ſayeth,
Wee alſo who have the first fruite of
the ſpirit,
               Rom. 8. 23 
               even wee ſigh in our ſelves,
wayting for the adoption. And in an
other place to the ſame effect hee
ſayeth, That wee ſigh, deſiring to bee
clothed vpon with our houſe which is
from heaven.
               2. Cor. 5. 2 For certainly, the naturall
diſpoſition of a man, can never
bring forth this ſtronge deſire
of heaven, neither yet could the
renewed heart, beeing yet burdened
with infirmitie and love of
this life, have ſo ſtrong a deſire of
removing from it, of it ſelfe, if the

ſpirit did not worke it: and therefore
the Apoſtle attributes theſe
ſighes for righteouſnes &amp; heaven,
to the ſpirit: and doth ſhewe vs,
that the ſpirit (in theſe cryes and
ſighes) helpeth our infirmities.
               Rom. 8. 26
            
            Thirdly, this teſtimonie of the
ſpirit is diſcerned, by the cōfident
requeſtes and petitions it maketh
to God in vs, in the full aſſurance
of faith, without doubting: when
with boldnes, wee drawe neare
vnto the Throne of grace, crying
vpon God,Phil. 4. 6. 
               Abba Father: and in
all things making our petitions manifeſt
to God, as ſayeth the Apoſtle.
For this confident boldnes of the
heart, towardes God, ſtill accompanied
with reverence and feare,
cannot be in the heart, except the
ſpirit did worke it. For the boldnes
of a blind heart, wanteth both
aſſurance of Gods love, and reverence
of his maieſtie.
            
               
But leaving this, wee come to
the diſcerning of the other voyce,
which more properly is called the
teſtimonie of the ſpirit: ſpeciallie
in that place to the Romans. And
that is, when God in vs, ſpeaketh
by his ſpirit vnto vs.
            This teſtimonie is to be diſcerned,
from the teſtimonie of our
hearte, three manner of wayes.
Firſt, in our firſt beleevinge. Secondly,
after wee have beleeved.
Thirdly, in the eclipſes of our faith,
and in our troubles.
            In our firſt beleeving, wee may
diſcerne the teſtimonie of Gods
ſpirit, from our owne, touchinge
our Adoption: becauſe our firſt
beleeving, is ever by the teſtimonie
of the ſpirit, and not by the teſtimonie
of our owne heart. For
our heart can never beare witnes
to vs, that wee are the ſonnes of
God, vntill firſt our heartes have

beleeved, that wee are his ſonnes.
and this our hearts can not do, except
the ſpirit, have firſt wrought
this faith, by the worde, in our
hearts. Therefore, my firſt beliefe
and aſſurace of my Adoption, is
alwayes the teſtimonie of the ſpirit
of God, and my owne hearts teſtimonie,
muſt ſtill followe vpon
this: ſo that in mans hearte, the
voyce that maketh it firſt cōceyve
Gods love, and beleeve it, is the
ſpirits teſtimonie: which, when
the heart of man hath receyved,
then it ſpeaketh. For till it beleeve,
it can not ſpeake: according as it
is written:Pſal. 116. 10. 
               I have beleeved, and
therefore I have ſpoken.
               2. Cor. 4. 13. Thus then
is this teſtimonie firſt diſcerned:
when I diſcerne, the voyce of the
ſpirit, which I beleeve, from the
voyce of my ſpirit, now beleving,
and bearing witnes to me, of that,
which firſt, the ſpirit of God did

witnes to it.
            Secondlie, after we have beleeved,
wee may alſo diſcerne the teſtimonie
of Gods ſpirit, from the
teſtimonie of our owne ſpirit, by
a plaine contrarie order. For in
the former, the ſpirites teſtimonie
did goe before, the teſtimonie of
our ſpirit: but heere, it followeth
after it: and is the confirmation of
it. So that, when after wee have
beleeved the ſpirit, ſpeakinge the
word vnto vs, and after that beleeving,
wee have ſpoken with our
owne ſpirit: if then wee heare a
new voyce, cōfirming that which
we beleeved, and which our ſpirit
did ſpeake: that cōfirming, ſealing,
and ſtabliſhing voyce, is the
teſtimonie of Gods ſpirit. Thus
wee muſt learne to diſcerne, betwixt
our beleeving, and the confirmation
of our belief: and ſo ſhal
wee know, the teſtimonie of Gods

ſpirit, from the teſtimonie of our
owne ſpirit. Therefore ſtill the holie
Scriptures of God, diſtinguiſh
betwixt the worke of God, in making
vs receyve the teſtimonie of
his ſpirit, and his worke, in confirming
in vs, that teſtimonie nowe
receyved. And alſo teacheth vs, to
knowe the teſtimonie of our own
ſpirit (which commeth in betwixt
theſe two) to bee different, from
them both. Accordinge to this
working of God, the Saincts pray,
Stabliſh O God,
               Pſal. 68. 28▪
                
               that which thou hast
wrought in vs.
            
            To ſpeake more plainly of this
point, there is a three folde voyce
in the heart that hath the teſtimonie
of Ieſus confirmed in it. The
firſt is the voyce of God by his ſpirit
in the worde ſpeaking vnto
our hearts, and perſwading them
to beleeve that the promiſe belongeth
vnto vs.
            
               
The ſecond voyce is the voyce
of our hearts receyving the word
wherby it ſpeaketh that which the
ſpirit hath perſwaded, and this in
effect is nothing but the very faith
of the heart now actually working
in vs. Whereas the firſt was the
worke of the ſpirit working this
faith in vs: ſo that in this firſt act
we are patients, in the other we are
agentes: in the firſt we are ſpoken
too by the ſpirit of God, in the ſeconde,
our owne heartes ſpeaketh
in vs. The third voice is the voyce
of Gods ſpirit following the voyce
of our hearts ratifying it: and this
is nothing els but the confirmation
of our faith. So wee may ſee
that the Lord performeth twoo
workes in vs for our comfort: the
firſt is, the working of faith &amp; beliefe:
the other is the confirmation
of the faith, which he him ſelfe
did work. But before his laſt work,

our hearts having faith wrought
in them, doe worke by it, or wee
with our hearts worke: and this is
nothing but beleeving with the
heart, or the hearts beleevinge.
Wherevpon followeth the ſealing
of vs in that which it beleeveth,
that is, in the teſtimonie which
the beleeving heart giveth of him
in whom it is.
            Thirdlie, we diſcerne this teſtimonie
of the ſpirit, in our trouble:
when we find any cōfort, or peace
wrought in our hearts, when they
are troubled: or anie ioye, vpon
the aſſurance of Gods love. If wee
finde a quiet calmneſſe of minde,
with patience, meeknes, and reioycing
in tribulation, vpon anie
ſight or knowledge of our Adoption:
all theſe are the vndoubted
teſtimonies of the ſpirit: who
ſhedding abroad the love of God

in our hearts, maketh vs to reioyce
in affliction: as the Apoſt. ſpeaketh
of the Hebrues,Heb. 10. 
               and ye ſuffered with
gladnes the ſpoyling of your goods,
knowing in your ſelves that yee have
in heaven a better, and an enduring
ſubstance. And touching the Apoſtles,
Act. 5. 41. it is ſaide, They departed reioycing
that they were compted worthie
to ſuffer for his Name. That this ioy,
is the work of the ſpirit, vpon the
teſtimonie of Gods love, is manifeſt
by the Apoſt. to the Romans,
where ſhewing the cauſe, why we
reioyce in afflictions, ſayth, Becauſe
of the love of God which is ſhed abroad
in our heartes, by the holy ſpirit
which is given vs. According to
this grounde it is, that the Saints
are brought in, wayting what God
will ſpeake to them in trouble: as
namely in the Pſalme 85. verſ. 8.
I will hearken what the Lord will ſay,

concerning mee: for hee ſhall ſpeake
peace vnto his people, and to his ſaints.
And the Prophet Habacuk in like
manner is brought in ſaying thus:
I will ſtande vpon my watch, and ſet
mee vpon the Towre, and will looke
and ſee what hee will ſay vnto mee.
Thus whē God ſpeaketh peace to
the Saincts in affliction, and quieteth
their thoughtes, and maketh
them heare ioye and gladnes, that
is the teſtimonie of the ſpirit of
the Lord, who is our onely Comforter.
For as ſayeth the Prophet
David,Pſal. 73. 25. 
               My fleſh and my heart faileth:
but God is the ſtrength of my heart.
And therefore Moſes prayeth: O
ſatisfie vs with thy mercie, ſo ſhall wee
reioyce and be glad all our dayes,
               Pſal. 90. 14. 15. 
               comfort
vs againe, &amp;c. We may hold it
for a moſt certaine trueth, that our
patient enduring of grievous trialls
ioyfully, the conſtant peace

of God in our hearts, in the tyme
when wee endure the enimitie of
the world: the cōſolations, wherewith
we are comforted, in all our
afflictions, are vndoubted teſtimonies
of our Adoption, proceeding
all from Gods ſpirit.
            But all this is moſt cleerlie diſcerned,
when the teſtimonie of
Gods ſpirit, and the teſtimonie of
our ſpirit, are ſeperate the one frō
the other: &amp; when they are found
to ſpeake one againſt the other:
and to give two contrarie teſtimonies.
For while theſe two goe together,
and are not ſevered or diſagreeing:
it is oft tymes hard to
diſcerne the one from the other.
But if we can finde them ſeperate,
ſo that the one faile vs, and the other
vphold vs, then may they
cleerly bee diſcerned. And this
commeth to paſſe, eyther when

God vpon the carnall preſumption
of our hearts, ſuffereth vs to
fall in ſome dangerous triall. or
then, when God him ſelfe ſeemeth
to become our enemie: ſo
that the heart hath to wreſtle
with GOD him ſelfe, vnder the
ſenſe of his wrath, all former feeling
of his mercie then ceaſing.
            Of the firſt, wee have example
in Peter, whoſe heart ſaide vnto
him, that no danger could make
him forſake Chriſt the Lorde, to
make him know, that this was not
the teſtimonie of Gods ſpirit: but
a carnall confidence of his owne
heart, ſuffered him to be tried, and
in the triall to fall: and ſo to finde,
it was but his owne carnall heart,
that did beare witnes to him. God
oft tymes for this cauſe tryeth his
owne children: to make them
diſcerne, betwixt the confidence

and aſſurance which their owne
hearts giveth them, and that confidence
and comfort which the
ſpirit of God worketh in them:
that they may not truſt in them
ſelves, or in their owne hearts, but
in the living God. This the Apoſtle
witneſſeth to the Corinthians,
ſaying:2 Cor. 1. 9 
               He maekth vs to receyve the
ſentence of death in our ſelves, becauſe
we ſhould not trust in our ſelves but in
God which raiſeth the dead.
            
            Of the ſecond, wee have example
in David and Iob. And this
diſcerning of the ſpirits teſtimonie
is two folde, one is by the
voyce of the ſpirit in vs, vnto God,
when our hearts ſpeake the contrarie.
The other is, by the voyce
of the ſpirit vnto vs, whē our own
hearts ſaith otherwayes.
            Of the firſt David is an example:
who in his proſperitie ſaide,

               hee ſhould never bee moved:
               Pſal. 31. 2. Yet
when God did hyde his face, his
heart fayled him: and he ſaide in
his haſte, I am caſt out of thy ſight.
and yet hee preſently addeth theſe
wordes: nevertheleſſe thou heardeſt
the voyce of my prayer. Heere wee
may perceyve Davids owne heart,
ſaying, hee was caſt out of Gods
ſight: but yet the ſpirit of GOD,
maketh requeſt vnto God for him,
and maketh him pray to God in
faith, as not reiected of God: and
the Lord did heare him. This him
ſelfe ſheweth plainlie, in an other
place,Pſal. 116. 10. when he ſayeth: I beleeved,
and therefore I ſpake: but I was ſore
troubled, I ſaide in my haſte, All men
are liers. At this time, David compaſſed
with the ſnares of death, &amp;
holden by the griefes of the grave,
finding trouble and heavines, declares
the eſtate of his owne heart:

that it ſaid, that all men are liers:
and therefore he gathers this concluſion,
that albeit his owne heart
did ſay, that Gods promiſe ſhould
not bee accompliſhed: yet doubtleſſe
he behoved to have faith: becauſe
he prayed. For except hee
had beleeved, he had not ſpoken.
And what can bee more cleere, to
let vs ſee, Gods ſpirit bearing witneſſe,
that God hath not forſaken
vs, when our owne hearts ſay the
contrarie. Then when by witneſſing
this, the ſpirit cauſeth vs, againſt
the diſtruſt of our owne
hearts, to pray to God: evē above
hope, yet vnder hope, truſting in
the Lord, as did Abraham. If we
examine our ſelves, what hath
bene the eſtate of our hearts, in the
like (or at leaſt in our greateſt
temptations) wee ſhall finde, that
many tymes, when our harts hath

ſpoken no comfort vnto vs: yet
the ſpirit of God, hath drawen
ſighes and cries to God, out of our
hearts: which alſo our God hath
heard moſt graciouſlie. Theſe
cries are teſtimonies of the ſpirit,
witneſſing to vs, that wee are the
ſonnes of God: when as they proceed
from vs, our hearts ſaying the
contrarie.
            Of the ſecond kinde of the ſpirits
voyce, in ſpeaking from God
vnto vs: wee have likewiſe example
in David, when his owne heart
ſaid vnto God,Pſal. 42. 
               Why hast thou forgotten
me? Behold an other voyce
ſpeakinge vnto his heart in that
ſame tyme, Why art thou vexed O
my ſoule, and why art thou ſo diſquieted
within mee? O put thy trust in
God, for I will yet give him thankes, he
is my helpe and my God. Heere the
heart ſpeaking no comfort, but

being wholy diſcouraged, and caſt
downe: the ſpirit of God in that
ſame heart, ſpeaketh to the heart,
and comforteth it, with this, that
God was his God. Nowe, that
theſe conſolations are the worke
and teſtimonie of Gods ſpirit, it
appeareth by that reaſon, which
David giveth, when hee boaſteth
in ſtrong cōfidence, that although
hee ſhould walke through the valey
of the ſhadowe of death, yet
would hee feare none evill, ſaying:
Pſal. 23. 
               For thou art with mee, thy rod
and thy ſtaffe they comfort mee. By
theſe wordes declaring, that the
experiēce he had of the comfort,
which Gods ſpirit did miniſter vnto
him, in his moſt deſperate troubles
paſt, even then when his
owne ſpirit did faile him, was the
ground of al his cōfidence againſt
all future trialls.
            
               
Wee have an example alſo of
this in Iob. Who when his owne
heart reaſoned, that God had hid
his face from him, and taken him
for his enemie: yet hee ſaith, Although
hee ſlaye mee, yet will I trust in
him, hee ſhalbe my ſalvation. Heere
two different ſpeeces in one heart:
the one from the ſpirit of Iob: the
other from the ſpirit of the Lord
in Iob. The one, perſwading that
God was his ſalvation, when the
other ſaide, God had hid his face
from him.
            Thus if wee would cleerlie diſcerne,
the teſtimonie of Gods ſpirit,
from the teſtimonie of our
owne ſpirit, let vs beholde our ſelves,
when God tryeth vs, rather
then when he maketh our mountaine
to ſtande ſtronge. or when
hee doeth wreſtle with vs himſelfe,
as he did with Iacob: and in

ſeeminge to fight againſt vs, yet
doeth ſuſtaine vs, by his owne
ſtrength in vs, when our ſtrength
faileth vs.
            Thus I have as diſtinctlie as I
could, and therefore ſomewhat
more largelie, then an epiſtle perhaps
requireth, given you ſuch ſatisfaction
to your queſtion, as it
hath pleaſed the Lorde to grant
me light. If you finde any comfort
thereby, you ſhall thank God
for it: And what is wanting in it,
for your full ſatisfaction in this
matter, the Lord ſhall ſupplie it by
his owne ſpirit: or by that ſufficiencie
of grace, which hee hath given
vnto others his ſervants, whō
he ſhall raiſe vp to write more fullie
of this matter: for the edification
of his Saints, in this and all other
thinges, I pray the Lord to

give you and vs all, his everlaſting
peace through Chriſt IESVS
our Saviour, reveyling more and
more the myſterie of godlineſſe
in your hearts, and makinge you
abound in all knowledge with
faith, feeling, and ioy of the holy
Ghoſt. The grace of the
Lord IESVS bee with
you, and all the
Brethren,
AMEN.
            
            
               Io. Forbes.
            
         
      
   

