
   
      
         
            The louers melancholy Acted at the Priuate House in the Blacke Friers, and publikely at the Globe by the Kings Maiesties Seruants.
            Ford, John, 1586-ca. 1640.
         
         
            
               1629
            
         
         Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01055
            STC 11163
            ESTC S102509
            99838290
            99838290
            2664
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01055)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2664)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 989:8)
         
         
            
               
                  The louers melancholy Acted at the Priuate House in the Blacke Friers, and publikely at the Globe by the Kings Maiesties Seruants.
                  Ford, John, 1586-ca. 1640.
                  Daniel, Samuel, 1562-1619. Hymens triumph.
               
               [8], 86, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed [by Felix Kingston] for H. Seile, and are to be sold at the Tygers head in Saint Pauls Church-yard,
                  London :
                  1629.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Iohn Ford.
                  The main plot is from:  Daniel, Samuel.  Hymens triumph.
                  Partly in verse.
                  With a final epilogue leaf.
                  A variant (STC 11163.3) has "printed for H.S." in imprint.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2000-00
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2001-07
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2001-08
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-12
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE LOVERS Melancholy.
            ACTED AT THE PRIVATE HOVSE IN THE BLACKE Friers, and publikely at the Globe by the Kings Maiesties Seruants.
            LONDON, Printed for H. Seile, and are to be sold at the Tygers head in Saint Pauls Church-yard. 1629.
         
         
            
            The Sceane Famagosta in Cyprus.
            
               The names of such as acted.
               IOHN LOWIN.
               IOSEPH TAYLOR.
               ROBERT BENFIELD.
               IOHN SHANCK.
               EYLYARDT SWANSTON.
               ANTHONY SMITH.
               RICHARD SHARPE.
               THOMAS POLLARD.
               WILLIAM PENN.
               CVRTEISE GRIVILL.
               GEORGE VERNON.
               RICHARD BAXTER.
               IOHN TOMSON.
               IOHN HONYMAN.
               IAMES HORNE.
               WILLIAM TRIGG.
               ALEXANDER GOVGH.
            
         
         
            
            TO MY WORTHILY RESPECTED FRIENDS, NATHANIEL FINCH, IOHN FORD, Esquires; Mt. HENRY BLVNT, Mr. ROBFRT ELLICE, and all the rest of the Noble Society of Grayes Inne.
            
               My Honour'd Friends,
            
            THe account of some leisurable houres, is here summ'd vp, and offered to examination. Importunity of Others, or Opinion of mine owne, hath not vrg'd on any confidence of running the hazard of a censure. As plurality hath reference to a Multitude, so, I care not to please Many: but wh
                  •
               re there is a Parity of condition, there the freedom of construction, makes the best musicks. This concord hath equally held betweene YOV THE PATRONES, and ME THE PRESENTOR. I am cleer'd of all scruple of dis-respect on your parts; as I am of too slacke a Merit in my selfe. My presumption of comming in Print in this kind, hath hitherto been vn-reprooueable. This Piece, being the first, that euer

courted Reader; and it is very possible, that the like complement with Me, may soone grow out of fashion. A practice of which that I may auoid now, I commend to the continuance of your Loues, the memory of HIS, who without the protestation of a seruice, is readily your Friend,
            
               IOHN FORD.
            
         
         
            
               
               To my Honour'd Friend, Master Iohn Ford, on his Louers Melancholy.
               IF that thou think'st these lines thy worth can raise,
               Thou do'st mistake: my liking is no prayse:
               Nor can I thinke thy Iudgement is so ill,
               To seeke for Bayes from such a barraine Quill:
               Let your true Critick, that can iudge and mend,
               Allow thy Sceanes and Stile: I, as a friend
               That knowes thy worth, doe onely sticke my Name,
               To shew my Loue, not to aduance thy Fame.
               
               George Donne.
            
            
               To his worthy Friend, the Author, Master Iohn Ford.
               
               I Write not to thy Play: Ile not begin
               To throw a censure vpon what hath been
               By th' Best approu'd; It can nor feare, nor want
               The Rage, or Liking of the Ignorant.
               Nor seeke I Fame for Thee, when thine owne Pen
               Hath forc'd a praise long since, from knowing Men.
               I speake my thoughts, and wish vnto the Stage
               A glory from thy studies; that the Age
               
                  May be indebted to Thee, for Reprieue
               Of purer language, and that Spight may grieue
               To see It selfe out-done. When Thou art read,
               The Theater may hope Arts are not dead,
               Though long conceal'd; that Poet-Apes may feare
               To vent their weaknesse, mend, or quite forbeare.
               This I dare promise; and keepe this in store;
               As thou hast done enough, Thou canst doe more.
               William Singleton.
            
            
               To the Author, Master Iohn Ford.
               
               
                  BLacke choler, Reasons ouer-flowing Spring,
               Where thirsty Louers drinke, or any Thing,
               Passion, the restlesse current of dull plaints
               Affords their thoughts, who deeme lost beauties, Saints:
               Here their best Lectur
                        •
                     s read, collect, and see
               Various conditions of Humanitie
               Highly enlighten'd by thy Muses rage;
               Yet all so coucht, that they adorn'd the Stage.
               Shun Phocions blushes thou; for sure to please
               It is no sinne, then what is thy disease?
               Iudgements applause? effeminated smiles?
               Studie's delight? thy wit mistrust beguiles:
               Establisht Fame will thy Physicion be,
               (Write but againe) to cure thy Iealousie.
               Hum. Howorth.
            
            
               
               Of the Louers Melancholy.
               TIs not the Language, nor the fore-plac'd Rimes
               Of Friends, that shall commend to after-times
               The Louers Melancholy: Its owne worth
               Without a borrowed prayse, shall set it forth.
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            THE PROLOGVE.
            TO tell yee (Gentlemen) in what true sense
            The Writer, Actors, or the audience
            Should mold their Iudgemēts for a Play, might draw
            Truth into Rules, but we haue no such law.
            Our Writer, for himselfe would haue yee know,
            That in his following Sceanes, he doth not owe
            To others Fancies, nor hath layne in wait
            For any stolne Inuention, from whose height
            He might commend his owne, more then the right
            A Scholer claimes, may warrant for delight.
            It is Arts scorne, that some of late haue made
            The Noble vse of Poetry a Trade.
            For your parts (Gentlemen) to quite his paines,
            Yet you will please, that as you meet with straines
            Of lighter mixtures, but to cast your eye
            Rather vpon the maine, then on the bye.
            His hopes stand firme, and we shall find it true,
            The Louers Melancholy cur'd by you.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE LOVERS MELANCHOLY.
            
               Actus. I. Scena I.
               Enter Menaphon and Pelias.
               
                  Menaphon.
                  DAngers? How meane you dangers? that so courtly
                  You gratulate my safe returne from dangers?
               
               
                  Pel.
                  From Trauailes (noble Sir.)
               
               
                  Men.
                  These are delights,
                  If my experience hath not Trewant-like
                  Mis-spent the time, which I haue stroue to vse,
                  For bettering my mind with obseruation.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  As I am modest, I protest 'tis strange:
                  But is it possible?
               
               
                  Men.
                  What?
               
               
                  Pel.
                  To bestride
                  The frothy fomes of Neptunes surging waues,
                  When blustring Boreas tosseth vp the deepe,
                  And thumps a thunder bounce?
               
               
                  
                  Men.
                  Sweet Sir, 'tis nothing,
                  Straight comes a Dolphin playing neere your ship,
                  Heauing his crooked backe vp, and presents
                  A Feather-bed, to waft'ee to the shoare,
                  As easily as if you slepti'th' Court.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Indeed, is't true, I pray?
               
               
                  Men.
                  I will not stretch
                  Your Faith vpon the Teinters, prethee Pelias,
                  
                  Where didst thou learne this language?
               
               
                  Pel.
                  I this language?
                  Alas, Sir, we that study words and formes
                  Of complement, must fashion all discourse,
                  According to the nature of the subiect.
                  But I am silent, now appeares a Sunne,
                  Whose shadow I adore.
                  Enter Amethus, Sophronos, and Attendants.
               
               
                  Men.
                  My honour'd Father.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  From mine eyes, son, son of my care, my loue,
                  The ioyes that bid thee welcome, doe too much speake me a child.
               
               
                  Men.
                  O Princely Sir, your hand.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Performe your duties where you owe them first,
                  I dare not be so sudden in the pleasures,
                  Thy presence hath brought home.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Here thou still findest
                  A Friend as noble (Menaphon) as when
                  Thou left'st at thy departure.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Yes, I know it,
                  To him I owe more seruice.—
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Pray giue leaue,
                  He shall attend your intertainements soone,
                  Next day, and next day, for an houre or two,
                  I would engrosse him onely.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Noble Lord.
               
               
                  
                  Ame.
                  Y'are both dismist.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Your creature, and your Seruant.
               
               Exeunt all but Ameth. Menap.
               
                  Ame.
                  Giue me thy hand, I will not say, Th'art welcome,
                  That is the common roade of cōmon friends,
                  I am glad I haue thee here—O, I want words
                  To let thee know my heart.
               
               
                  Men.
                  'Tis peec'd to mine.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Yes, 'tis, as firmely, as that holy thing
                  Call'd Friendship can vnite it. Menaphon,
                  
                  My Menaphon: now all the goodly blessings,
                  That can create a Heauen on earth, dwell with thee.
                  Twelue monthes we haue been sundred, but henceforth
                  We neuer more will part, till that sad houre,
                  In which death leaues the one of vs behind,
                  To see the others funerals perform'd.
                  Let's now a while be free. How haue thy trauailes
                  Disburth'ned thee abroad of discontents?
               
               
                  Men.
                  Such cure as sicke men find in changing beds,
                  I found in change of Ayres; the fancy flatter'd
                  My hopes with ease, as theirs doe, but the griefe
                  Is still the same.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Such is my case at home.
                  
                     Cleophyla, thy Kinswoman, that Maide
                  Of sweetnesse and humility, more pities
                  Her Fathers poore afflictions, then the tide
                  Of my complaints.
               
               
                  Men.
                  
                     Thamasta, my great Mistris,
                  Your Princely Sister, hath, I hope ere this,
                  Confirm'd affection on some worthy choice.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Not any, Menaphon. Her bosome yet
                  Is intermur'd with Ice, though by the truth
                  Of loue, no day hath euer past, wherein
                  
                     I haue not mention'd thy deserts, thy constancy
                  Thy—Come, in troth I dare not tell thee what,
                  Lest thou mightst thinke I fawnd vpon a sinne
                  Friendship was neuer guilty of; for flattery
                  Is monstrous in a true friend.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Does the Court
                  Weare the old lookes too?
               
               
                  Ame.
                  If thou mean'st the Prince,
                  It does, hee's the same melancholy man,
                  He was at's Fathers death, sometimes speakes sence,
                  But seldome mirth; will smile, but seldome laugh;
                  Will lend an eare to businesse, deale in none;
                  Gaze vpon Reuels, Anticke Fopperies,
                  But is not mou'd; will sparingly discourse,
                  Heare musicke; but what most he takes delight in,
                  Are handsome pictures; one so young, and goodly,
                  So sweet in his owne nature, any Story
                  Hath seldome mentioned.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Why should such as I am,
                  Groane vnder the light burthens of small sorrowes,
                  When as a Prince, so potent, cannot shun
                  Motions of passion? To be man (my Lord)
                  Is to be but the exercise of cares
                  In seuerall shapes; as miseries doe grow,
                  They alter as mens formes; but how, none know.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  This little Ile of Cyprus sure abounds
                  In greater wonders, both for change and fortune,
                  Then any you haue seene abroad.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Then any
                  I haue obseru'd abroad: all Countries else
                  To a free eye and mind yeeld something rare;
                  And I for my part, haue brought home one Iewell.
                  Of admirable value.
               
               
                  
                  Ame.
                  Iewell, Menaphon?
                  
               
               
                  Men.
                  A Iewell, my Amethus, a faire Youth;
                  A Youth, whom if I were but superstitious,
                  I should repute an Excellence more high,
                  Then meere creations are, to adde delight.
                  I'le tell yee how I found him.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Prethee doe.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Passing from Italy to Greece, the Tales
                  Which Poets of an elder time haue fain'd
                  To glorifie their Tempe, bred in me
                  Desire of visiting that Paradise.
                  To Thessaly I came, and liuing priuate,
                  Without acquaintance of more sweet companions▪
                  
                  Then the old In-mates to my loue, my thoughts;
                  I day by day frequented silent Groues,
                  And solitarie Walkes.
                        Vide Famistradam. lib. 2. Prolas. 6. Acad. 3. Imitat. Claudian.
                      One morning early
                  This accident incountred me: I heard
                  The sweetest and most rauishing contention,
                  That Art or Nature euer were at strife in.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  I cannot yet conceiue, what you inferre
                  By Art and Nature.
               
               
                  Men.
                  I shall soone resolue yee.
                  A sound of musicke toucht mine eares, or rather
                  Indeed intranc'd my soule: as I stole neerer,
                  Inuited by the melody, I saw
                  This Youth, this faire-fac'd Youth, vpon his Lute
                  With straines of strange variety and harmony,
                  Proclaiming (as it seem'd) so bold a challenge
                  To the cleare Quiristers of the Woods, the Birds,
                  That as they flockt about him, all stood silent,
                  Wondring at what they heard. I wondred too.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  And so doe I, good,—on.
               
               
                  Men.
                  A Nightingale.
                  
                     Natures best skill'd Musicion vndertakes
                  The challenge, and for euery seuerall straine
                  The wel-shapt Youth could touch, she sung her down;
                  He coo'd not run D
                        •
                     uision with more Art
                  Vpon his quaking Instrument, then she,
                  The Nightingale did with her various notes
                  Reply too, for a voyce, and for a sound,
                  
                     Amethus, tis much easier to beleeue
                  That such they were, then hope to heare againe.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  How did the Riuals part?
               
               
                  Mena.
                  You terme them rightly,
                  For they were Riuals, and their Mistris harmony.
                  
                  Some time thus spent, the young man grew at last
                  Into a pretty anger, that a bird
                  Whom Art had neuer taught Cliffs, Moods, or Notes,
                  Should vie with him for mastery, whose study
                  Had busied many houres to perfit practise:
                  To end the controuersie, in a rapture,
                  Vpon his Instrument he playes so swiftly,
                  So many voluntaries, and so quicke,
                  That there was curiositie and cunning,
                  Concord in discord, lines of diffring method
                  Meeting in one full Center of delight.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Now for the bird.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  
                     The bird ordain'd to be
                  Musicks first Martyr, stroue to imitate
                  These seuerall sounds: which, when her warbling throat
                  Fail'd in, for griefe, downe dropt she on his Lute,
                  And brake her heart; it was the quaintest sadnesse,
                  To see the Conquerour vpon her Hearse,
                  To weepe a funerall Elegy of teares,
                  That trust me (my Amethus) I coo'd chide
                  Mine owne vnmanly weakenesse, that made me
                  
                     A fellow-mourner with him. Amet. I beleeue thee.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  He lookes vpon the trophies of his Art,
                  Then sigh'd, then wip'd his eyes, then sigh'd, and cride,
                  Alas poore creature: I will soone reuenge
                  This cruelty vpon the Author of it;
                  Henceforth this Lute guilty of innocent blood,
                  Shall neuer more betray a harmelesse peace
                  To an vntimely end: and in that sorrow,
                  As he was pashing it against a tree,
                  I suddenly stept in.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Thou hast discourst
                  A truth of mirth and pitie.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  I reprieu'd
                  Th'intended execution with intreaties,
                  And interruption: but (my Princely friend)
                  It was not strange, the musicke of his hand
                  Did ouer-match birds, when his voyce and beauty,
                  Youth, carriage and discretion, must, from men
                  Indu'd with reason, rauish admiration:
                  From me they did.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  But is this miracle
                  Not to be seene?
               
               
                  Men.
                  I won him by degrees
                  To chuse me his Companion whence he is,
                  Or who, as I durst modestly inquire,
                  So gently hee would woo not to make knowne:
                  Onely for reasons to himselfe reseru'd,
                  He told me, that some remnant of his life
                  Was to be spent in Trauaile; for his fortunes,
                  They were nor meane, nor riotous, his friends
                  Not publisht to the world, though not obscure:
                  His Countrey, Athens; and his name, Parthenophill.
                  
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Came he with you to Cyprus?
               
               
                  
                  Men.
                  Willingly.
                  The same of our young melancholy Prince,
                  
                     Meleanders rare distractions, the obedience
                  Of young Cle
                           •
                        phila, Thamasta's glory,
                  Your matchlesse friendship, and my desperate loue
                  Preuail'd with him, and I haue lodg'd him priuately
                  In Famagosta.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Now th'art doubly welcome:
                  I will not lose the sight of such a rarity
                  For one part of my hopes. When d'ee intend
                  To visit my great-spirited Sister.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  May I
                  Without offence?
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Without offence? Parthenophill
                  
                  Shall find a worthy intertainement too.
                  Thou art not still a coward.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  Shee's too excellent,
                  And I too low in merit.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Ile prepare
                  A noble welcome. And (friend) ere we part,
                  Vnloade to thee an ouer-charged heart.
                  Exeunt.
               
               Enter Rhetius carelesly attyr'd.
               
                  Rhet.
                  I will not court the madnesse of the times,
                  Nor fawne vpon the Riots that embalme
                  Our wanton Gentry, to preserue the dust
                  Of their affected vanities in coffins
                  Of memorable 
                        •
                     hame▪ when Common-wealths
                  Totter and reele from that nobilitie
                  And ancient vertue, which renownes the great,
                  Who steere the Helme of gouernment, while Mushrooms
                  Grow vp, &amp; make new lawes to licence folly:
                  Why should not I, a May-game, scorne the weight
                  Of my sunke fortunes? snarle at the vices
                  
                     Which rot the Land, and without feare or wit
                  Be mine owne Anticke? Tis a sport to liue
                  When life is irkesome, if we will not hug
                  Prosperity in others, and contemne
                  Affliction in our selues. This Rule is certaine,
                  " He that pursues his safety from the Schoole
                  " Of State, must learne to be mad man, or foole.
                  Ambition, wealth, ease, I renounce the diuell
                  That damns yee here on earth, or I will be—
                  Mine owne mirth, or mine owne tormentor,—So,
                  Enter Pelius.
                  Here comes intelligence, a Buz o'the Court.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  
                     Rhetias, I sought thee out to tell thee newes,
                  New, excellent new newes. Cucolus, Sirra,
                  That Gull, that young old Gull, is comming this way.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  And thou art his forerunner?
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Prethee heare me:
                  In stead of a fine guarded Page,
                  We haue got him
                  A Boy, trickt vp in neat and handsome
                  Fashion;
                  Perswaded him, that tis indeed a Wench;
                  And he has entertain'd him, he does follow him,
                  Carries his sword and buckler, waits on his trencher,
                  Filles him his Wine, Tobacco, whets his knife,
                  Lackeyes his letters, does what seruice else
                  He would imploy his man in: being askt,
                  Why he is so irregular in Courtship?
                  His answer is, that since great Ladies vse
                  Gentlemen Vshers to goe bare before them,
                  He knowes no reason, but he may reduce
                  The Courtiers to haue women waite on them,
                  And he begins the fashion; he is laught at
                  
                     Most complementally. Thou't burst to see him.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  
                     Agelastus, so surnamed for his grauity,
                  Was a very wise fellow, kept his countenance
                  All dayes of his life as demurely, as a Iudge that
                  Pronounceth sentence of death, on a poore Roague,
                  For stealing as much bacon, as would serue at a meale
                  With a Calues head. Yet he smil'd once,
                  And neuer but once: Thou art no Scholler?
               
               
                  Pel.
                  I haue read Pamphlets dedicated to me:
                  Dost call him Agelastus? why did he laugh?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  To see an Asse eate Thistles.
                  Puppy, go study to be a singular Coxcomb. Cuculus is an
                  Ordinary Ape, but thou art an Ape of an Ape.
               
               Enter Cuculus and Grilla.
               
                  Pel.
                  Thou hast a Patent to abuse thy friends:
                  Looke, looke, he comes, obserue him seriously.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Reach me my sword and buckler.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  They are here, forsooth.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  How now (Minkes) how now? Where is your duty, your distance?
                  Let me haue seruice methodically tendred; you are now One of vs. Your cursey; good: remember that you are To practise Courtship▪ was thy father a Piper, saist thou?
               
               
                  Grill.
                  A sounder of some such wind instrumēt forsooth.
               
               
                  Cucull.
                  Was he so? hold vp thy head; be thou musicall
                  To me, and I will marry thee to a dancer: one
                  That shall ryde on his Foot-cloth, and maintaine thee
                  In thy Muffe and Hood.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  That will be fine indeed.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  That art yet but simple.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  Dee thinke so?
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  I haue a braine; I haue a head-piece;
                  O my conscience, if I take paines with thee, I shood
                  
                     Raise thy vnderstanding (Girle) to the height of a nurse,
                  Or a Court-midwife at least, I will make thee big
                  In time, wench.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  E'en doe your pleasure with me, Sir.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Noble accomplisht Cuculus.
                  
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Giue me thy fist, Innocent.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Would 'twere in thy belly, there tis.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  That's well, hee's an honest blade, though he be blunt.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Who cares? we can be as blunt as he for's life.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  
                     Cuculus, there is within a mile or two, a Sow-pig
                  Hath suckt a Brach, and now hunts the Deere, the Hare,
                  Nay, most vnnaturally the wilde Bore,
                  Aswell as any Hound in Cyprus.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Monstrous Sow-pig! ist true?
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Ile be at charge of a banket on thee for a sight of her.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Euery thing takes after the dam that gaue it suck:
                  Where hadst thou thy milke?
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  I? Why, my nurses husband was a most excellent maker
                  Of Shittle-cocks.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  My nurse was a woman-surgeon.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  And who gaue thee pap, Mouse?
               
               
                  Gril.
                  I neuer suckt that I remember.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  La now, a Shittle-cock-maker, all thy braines are stucke with corke and feather. Cuculus, this learned Courtier takes after the nurse too, a she-surgeon, which is in effect a meere matter of colours. Goe, learne to paint and dawbe complements, tis the next step to run into a new suit; my Lady Periwinckle here neuer suckt; suck thy Master, and bring forth Moonecalues, Fop, doe; This is good Philosophy, Sirs, make vse on't.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  Blesse vs, what a strange Creature this is?
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  A Gull, an arrant Gull by Proclamation.
               
               
                  
                  Enter Corax passing ouer.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  
                     Corax, the Princes chiefe Physicion;
                  What businesse speeds his haste—
                  Are all things well, Sir?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Yes, yes, yes.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Phew, you may wheele about, man, wee know y'are proud of your slouenry and practice, tis your vertue; the Princes melancholy fit I presume holds still.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  So doe thy knauery and desperate beggery.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Aha: here's one will tickle the ban-dog.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  You must not goe yet.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Ile stay in spight of thy teeth. There lyes my grauity:
                  Casts off his gowne.
                  Doe what thou darest, I stand thee▪
                  
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Mountebanck, Empricks, Quacksaluers, Mineralists, Wizards, Alchimists, cast-Apothecaries, old Wiues and Barbers, are all suppositors to the right Worshipfull Doctor, as I take it.
                  Some of yee are the head of your Art, &amp; the hornes too, but they come by nature; thou liuest single for no other end, but that thou fearest to be a Cuckold.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Haue at thee; thou affect'st railing onely for thy health, thy miseries are so thicke and so lasting; that thou hast not one poore denier to bestow on opening a veine. Wherefore to auoide a Plurisie, thou't be sure to prate thy selfe once a month into a whipping, and bleed in the breech in stead of the arme.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Haue at thee agen.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Come.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  There, there, there; O braue Doctor.
               
               
                  
                  Pel.
                  Let'em alone.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Thou art in thy Religion an Atheist, in thy condition a Curre, in thy dyet an Epicure, in thy lust a Goate, in thy sleepe a Hogge; thou tak'st vpon thee the habit of a graue Phisition, but art indeed an impostrous Emperike. Physicions are the bodies Coblers, rather the Botchers of mens bodies; as the one patches our tatterd clothes, so the other solders our diseased flesh. Come on.
               
               
                  Cuc.
                  Tot, tot, hold him tot, hold him toot, tot, tot, tot.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  The best worth in thee, is the corruption of thy minde, for that onely intitles thee to the dignity of a lowse: a thing bred out of the filth and superfluity of ill humours: Thou byt'st any where; and any man who defends not himselfe with the cleane linnen of secure honesty; him thou darest not come neere. Thou art Fortunes Ideot, Vertues Bankrupt, Times Dunghil, Manhoods Scandall, and thine owne scourge. Thou wouldst hang thy selfe, so wretchedly miserable thou art; but that no man will trust thee with as much money as will buy a halter: and all thy stocke to be sold, is not worth halfe as much as may procure it.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Ha, ha, ha; this is flattery, grosse flattery.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  I haue imployment for thee, and for yee all, Tut, these are but good morrowes betweene vs.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Are thy bottles full?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Of rich wine, lets all sucke together.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Like so many Swine in a trough.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Ile shape yee all for a deuise before the Prince, Wee'le trie how that can moue him.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  He shall fret or laugh.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Must I make one?
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Yes, and your feminine Page too.
               
               
                  
                  Gril.
                  Thankes most egregiously.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  I will not slacke my part.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Wench, take my buckler.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Come all vnto my chamber, the proiect is cast,
                  The time onely we must attend.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  The melody must agree well, and yeeld sport,
                  When such as these are, Knaues and Fooles consort.
               
               Exeunt.
               Enter Amethus, Thamasta and Kala.
               
                  Amet.
                  Does this shew well?
               
               
                  Tham.
                  What would you haue me doe?
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Not like a Lady of the trim, new crept
                  Out of the shell of sluttish sweat and labour,
                  Into the glittering pompe of ease and wantonnesse,
                  Imbroideries, and all these antike fashions,
                  That shape a woman monstrous; to transforme
                  Your education, and a Noble birth
                  Into contempt and laughter. Sister, Sister,
                  She who deriues her blood from Princes, ought
                  To glorifie her greatnesse by humility.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Then you conclude me proud.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Young Menaphon,
                  
                  My worthy friend, has lou'd you long, and truly,
                  To witnesse his obedience to your scorne,
                  Twelue moneths (wrong'd Gentleman) he vndertooke
                  A voluntary exile. Wherefore (Sister)
                  In this time of his absence, haue you not
                  Dispos'd of your affections on some Monarch?
                  Or sent Embassadors to some neighbouring King
                  With fawning protestations of your graces?
                  Your rare perfections, admirable beauty?
                  
                     This had been a new piece of modesty,
                  Would haue deseru'd a Chronicle!
               
               
                  Tham.
                  You are bitter;
                  And brother, by your leaue, not kindly wise.
                  My freedome is my births, I am not bound
                  To fancy your approuements, but my owne.
                  Indeed you are an humble youth, I heare of
                  Your visits, and your louing commendation
                  To your hearts Saint, Cleophila, a Virgin
                  Of a rare excellence: what though she want
                  A portion to maintaine a portly greatnesse?
                  Yet tis your gracious sweetnesse to descend
                  So low, the meeknesse of your pity leades yee.
                  She is your deare friends Sister, a good soule,
                  An Innocent.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  
                     Thamasta.
                  
               
               
                  Tham.
                  I haue giuen
                  Your Menaphon a welcome home as fits me;
                  For his sake entertain'd Parthenophill,
                  
                  The handsome Stranger, more familiarly
                  Then (I may feare) becomes me; yet for his part,
                  I not repent my courtesies, but you—
               
               
                  Amet.
                  No more, no more; be affable to both:
                  Time may reclaime your cruelty.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  I pitty
                  The youth, and trust me (brother) loue his sadnesse:
                  He talkes the prettiest stories, he deliuers
                  His tales so gracefully, that I coo'd sit
                  And listen, nay forget my meales and sleepe,
                  To heare his neat discourses. Menaphon
                  
                  Was well aduis'd in chusing such a friend,
                  For pleading his true loue.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Now I commend thee,
                  
                     Thou't change at last, I hope.
               
               Enter Menaphon and Eroclea in mans attire.
               
                  Tham.
                  I feare I shall.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Haue ye suruaid the Garden?
               
               
                  Men.
                  Tis a curious,
                  A pleasantly contriu'd delight.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Your eye (Sir)
                  Hath in your trauailes, often met contents
                  Of more variety.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Not any (Lady.)
               
               
                  Men.
                  It were impossible, since your faire presence
                  Makes euery place where it vouchsafes to shine,
                  More louely then all other helpes of Art
                  Can equall.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  What you meane by helpes of Art,
                  You know your selfe best, be they as they are:
                  You need none I am sure to set me forth.
               
               
                  Men.
                  'Twould argue want of manners, more then skill,
                  Not to praise praise it selfe.
                  
               
               
                  Tham.
                  For your reward,
                  Henceforth Ile call you Seruant.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Excellent Sister.
               
               
                  Men.
                  'Tis my first step to honour: May I fall
                  Lower then shame, when I neglect all seruice
                  That may confirme this fauour.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Are you well, Sir?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Great Princesse, I am well, to see a League
                  Betweene an humble loue, such as my Friends is,
                  And a commanding vertue, such as yours is,
                  Are sure restoratiues.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  You speake ingeniously.
                  Brother, he pleas'd to shew the Gallery
                  To this young stranger, vse the time a while,
                  
                     And we will altogether to the Court.
                  I will present yee (Sir) vnto the Prince.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Y'are all compos'd of fairenesse, and true bounty.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Come, come, wee'l wait thee, Sister: this beginning
                  Doth rellish happy processe.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  You haue blest me.
               
               Exeunt all but Thamasta and Kala.
               
                  Tham.
                  
                     Kala, O Kala,
                  
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Lady.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  We are priuate, thou art my Closet.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Locke your secrets close then:
                  I am not to be forc'd.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Neuer till now,
                  Coo'd I be sensible of being traytor
                  To honour and to shame.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  You are in loue.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  I am growne base—Parthenophill—
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Hee's handsome,
                  Richly indow'd; he hath a louely face,
                  A winning tongue.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  If euer I must fall,
                  In him my greatnesse sinkes. Loue is a Tyrant
                  Resisted; whisper in his eare, how gladly
                  I would steale time, to talke with him one houre;
                  But doe it honourably; preth'ee Kala
                  
                  Doe not betray me.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Madame, I will make it
                  Mine owne case; he shall thinke I am in loue with him.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  I hope thou art not Kala.
                  
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Tis for your sake:
                  Ile tell him so; but Faith I am not, Lady.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Pray vse me kindly; let me not too soone
                  Be lost in my new follyes. Tis a Fate
                  That ouer-rules our wisdomes, whil'st we striue
                  
                     To liue most free, wee'r caught in our owne toyles.
                  Diamonds cut Diamonds: they who will proue
                  To thriue in cunning, must cure loue with loue.
                  Exit.
               
               Finis Actus Primi.
            
            
               Actus II. Scena I.
               Enter Sophronos and Aretus.
               
                  Sophronos.
                  OVr Common-wealth is sick: tis more then time
                  That wee should wake the Head thereof, who sleepes
                  In the dull Lethargy of lost security.
                  The Commons murmur, and the Nobles grieue,
                  The Court is now turn'd Anticke, and growes wilde,
                  Whiles all the neighb'ring Nations stand at gaze,
                  And watch fit oportunity, to wreake
                  Their iust conceiued fury, on such iniuries,
                  As the late Prince, our liuing Masters Father,
                  Committed against Lawes of truth or honour.
                  Intelligence comes flying in on all sides,
                  Whilest the vnsteady multitude presume,
                  How that you, Aretus, and I, ingrosse
                  (Out of particular Ambition)
                  Th'affaires of gouernment, which I for my part,
                  Groane vnder, and am weary of.
               
               
                  Aret. Sophronos,
                  I am as zealous too of shaking of
                  My gay State fetters, that I haue bethought
                  Of speedy remedy; and to that end
                  
                     As I haue told yee, haue concluded with
                  
                     Corax, the Princes chiefe Physician.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  You should haue done this sooner, Aretus;
                  You were his Tutor, and could best discerne
                  His dispositions to informe them rightly.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  Passions of violent nature, by degrees
                  Are easili'st reclaim'd. There's something hid
                  Of his distemper, which wee'l now find out.
                  Enter Corax, Rhetias, Pelias, Cuculus and Grilla.
                  You come on iust appointment: welcome, Gentlemen,
                  Haue you won Rhetias (Corax?)
                  
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Most sincerely.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Saue yee, Nobilities: doe your Lordships take notice of my Page? Tis a fashion of the newest edition, spick and span new, without example. Doe your honour, Houswife.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  There's a cursey for you, and a cursey for you.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Tis excellent: we must all follow fashion, and entertaine Shee-waiters.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  'Twill be Courtly.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  I thinke so; I hope the Chronicles will reare me one day for a head-piece—
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Of Woodcocke without braines in't; Barbers shall weare thee on their Citternes, and Hucksters set thee out in Ginger-bread.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Deuill take thee: I say nothing to thee now; canst let me be quiet?
               
               
                  Gril.
                  Y'are too perstreperous, Sauce-box.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Good Girle, if we begin to puffe once.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Prethee hold thy tongue, the Lords are in the presence.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Mum, Butterflye.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  O the Prince: stand and keepe silence.
               
               
                  
                  Cucul.
                  O the Prince: Wench, thou shalt see the Prince now.
               
               Soft Musicke.
               Enter Pallador, the Prince, with a Booke in his hand.
               
                  Soph. Aret.
                  Sir; Gracious Sir.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Why all this Company?
               
               
                  Cora.
                  A Booke! is this the early exercise
                  I did prescribe? in stead of following health,
                  Which all mē couet, you pursue your disease.
                  Where's your great Horse, your Hounds, your set at Tennis,
                  Your Balloone ball, the practice of your dancing,
                  Your casting of the sledge, or learning how
                  To tosse a Pike; all chang'd into a Sonnet?
                  Pray Sir grant me free liberty to leaue
                  The Court, it do's infect me with the sloth
                  Of sleepe and surfet: In the Vniuersity
                  I haue imployments, which to my profession
                  Adde profit and report: Here I am lost,
                  And in your wilfull dulnesse held a man
                  Of neither Art nor honesty: you may
                  Command my head; pray take it, doe; 'twere better
                  For me to lose it, then to lose my wits,
                  And liue in Bedlam: you will force me too't,
                  I am almost mad already.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  I beleeue it.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Letters are come from Creete, which do require
                  A speedy restitution of such ships,
                  As by your Father were long since detain'd;
                  If not; defiance threatned.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  These neere parts
                  Of Syria that adioyne, muster their friends:
                  And by intelligence we learne for certaine,
                  
                     The Syrian will pretend an ancient interest
                  Of tribute intermitted.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Through your Land
                  Your subiects mutter strangely, and imagine
                  More then they dare speake publikely.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  And yet
                  They talke but odly of you.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Hang 'em Mungrels.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Of me? my subiects talke of me?
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Yes, scuruily,
                  And thinke worse (Prince.)
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Ile borrow patience
                  A little time to listen to these wrongs,
                  And from the few of you which are here present,
                  Conceiue the generall voyce.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  So, now he is nettled.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  By all your loues I charge ye, without feare
                  Or flattery, to let me know your thoughts,
                  And how I am interpreted: Speake boldly.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  For my part (Sir) I will be plaine, and briefe:
                  I thinke you are of Nature milde and easie,
                  Not willingly prouokt, but withall head-strong
                  In any passion that misleades your Iudgement.
                  I thinke you too indulgent to such motions,
                  As spring out of your owne affections,
                  To old to be reform'd, and yet too young
                  To take fit councell from your selfe, of what
                  Is most amisse.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  So—Tutor, your conceit?
               
               
                  Aret.
                  I think you doate (with pardon let me speak it)
                  Too much vpon your pleasures, and these pleasures
                  Are so wrapt vp in selfe-loue, that you couet
                  No other change of fortune: would be still
                  
                     What your birth makes you, but are loth to toyle
                  In such affaires of State as breake your sleepes.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  I thinke you would be by the world, reputed
                  A man in euery point compleat, but are
                  In manners and effect indeed a childe,
                  A boy, a very boy.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  May it please your Grace,
                  I thinke you doe containe within your selfe
                  The great Elixer, soule and quintessence
                  Of all diuine perfections: are the glory
                  Of mankind, and the onely strict example
                  For earthly Monarchies to square out their liues by:
                  Times miracle, Fames pride, in Knowledge, Wit,
                  Sweetnesse, Discourse, Armes, Arts—
               
               
                  Prince.
                  You are a Courtier.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  But not of the ancient fashion, an't like your Highnesse. Tis I; I, that am the credit of the Court, Noble Prince: and if thou would'st by Proclamation or Patent, create me Ouerseer of all the Taylers in thy Dominions; then, then the golden dayes should appeare againe; bread should be cheaper; fooles should haue more wit; knaues more honesty; and beggers more money.
               
               
                  Gril.
                  I thinke now—
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Peace you Squall.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  You haue not spoken yet.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Hang him, hee'l nothing but raile.
               
               
                  Gril.
                  Most abominable: out vpon him.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Away Cuculus; follow the Lords.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Close Page, close.
               
               They all fall backe, and steale out. Manet Prince and Rhetias.
               
                  Prince.
                  You are somewhat long a thinking.
               
               
                  
                  Rhet.
                  I doe not thinke at all.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Am I not worthy of your thought?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  My pitty you are—
                  But not my reprehension.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Pitty?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Yes, for I pitty such to whom I owe seruice, who exchange their happinesse for a misery.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Is it a misery to be a Prince?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Princes who forget their soueraignty, and yeeld to affected passion, are weary of command. You had a Father, Sir.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Your Soueraigne whiles he liu'd. But what of him?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Nothing. I onely dar'd to name him; that's all.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  I charge thee by the duty that thou ow'st vs, be plaine in what thou meanest to speake: there's something that we must know: be free, our eares are open.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  O Sir, I had rather hold a Wolfe by the eares, then stroake a Lyon, the greatest danger is the last.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  This is meere trifling—Ha? are all stollen hence?
                  We are alone: Thou hast an honest looke,
                  Thou hast a tongue, I hope, that is not oyld
                  With flattery. Be open, though tis true,
                  That in my younger dayes I oft haue heard
                  
                     
                        Agenors
                      name, my Father, more traduc'd,
                  Then I could then obserue; yet I protest,
                  I neuer had a friend, a certaine friend,
                  That would informe me throughly of such errors,
                  As oftentimes are incident to Princes.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  All this may be. I haue seene a man so curious in feeling of the edge of a keene knife, that he has cut his fingers. My flesh is not of proofe against the metall I

am to handle; the one is tenderer then the other.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  I see then I must court thee. Take the word
                  Of a iust Prince for any thing thou speakest.
                  I haue more then a Pardon, thankes and loue.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  I will remember you of an old Tale that somthing concernes you. Meleander, the great (but vnfortunate Statesman, was by your Father treated with for a Match betweene you and his eldest daughter, the Lady Eroclea. You were both neere of an age. I presume you remember a Contract, and cannot forget Her.
                  
               
               
                  Prince.
                  She was a louely beauty: Prethee forward.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  To Court was Eroclea brought, was courted by your Father, not for Prince Palador, as it followed, but to be made a prey to some lesse noble designe.—With your fauour I haue forgot the rest.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Good call it backe agen into thy memory,
                  Else losing the remainder, I am lost too.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  You charme me. In briefe, a Rape, by some bad Agents, was attempted; by the Lord Meleander her father rescude, she conuay'd away Meleander accus'd of treason, his Land seized, he himselfe distracted and confined to the Castle where he yet liues. What had ensude was doubtfull. But your Father shortly after dyed.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  But what became of faire Eroclea?
                  
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  She neuer since was heard of.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  No hope liues then
                  Of euer, euer seeing her againe.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Sir, I feare I should anger yee. There was, as I said, an old Tale: I haue now a new one, which may perhaps season the first with a more delightfull rellish.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  I am prepar'd to heare, say what you please.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  My Lord Meleander falling, on whose fauour my fortunes relyde, I furnisht my selfe for trauaile, and

bent my course to Athens, where a pretty accident after a while came to my knowledge.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  My eare is open to thee.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  A young Lady contracted to a noble Gentleman, as the Lady we last mentioned, and your Highnes were, being hindred by their iarring Parents, stole from her home, and was conueyed like a Ship-boy in a Merchant, from the Countrey where she liu'd, into Corinth first, and afterwards to Athens; where in much solitarinesse she liu'd like a Youth almost two yeeres, courted by all for acquaintance, but friend to none by familiaritie.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  In habit of a man?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  A handsome young man, till within these three moneths, or lesse, her sweet hearty Father dying some yeere before, or more, shee had notice of it, and with much ioy returned home, and as report voyced it, at Athens enioyed her happinesse: she was long an exile: For now Noble Sir, if you did loue the Lady Eroclea, why may not such safety and fate direct her, as directed the other? tis not impossible.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  If I did loue her, Rhetias: yes I did.
                  Giue me thy hand: As thou didst serue Meleander,
                  
                  And art still true to these, henceforth serue me.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  My duty and my obedience are my suretie,
                  But I haue been too bold.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Forget the sadder story of my Father,
                  And onely Rhetias, learne to reade me well,
                  For I must euer thanke thee; th'ast vnlockt
                  A tongue was vow'd to silence, for requitall
                  Open my bosome, Rhetias.
                  
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  What s your meaning?
               
               
                  Prince.
                  To tye thee to an oath of secrecy—
                  
                     Vnloose the buttons, man, thou dost it faintly,
                  What findst thou there?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  A picture in a Tablet.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Looke well vpon't.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  I doe—yes—let me obserue it—
                  Tis hers, the Ladies.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Whose!
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  
                     Erocleas.
                  
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Hers that was once Eroclea: for her sake
                  Haue I aduanst Sophronos to the Helme
                  Of gouernment; for her sake will restore
                  
                     Meleanders Honours to him; will for her sake
                  Beg friendship from thee, Rhetias. O be faithfull,
                  And let no politicke Lord worke from thy bosome
                  My griefes: I know thou wert put on to sift me:
                  But be not too secure.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  I am your Creature.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Continue still thy discontented fashion:
                  Humour the Lords, as they would humour me;
                  Ile not liue in thy debt.—We are discouer'd.
               
               Enter Amethus, Menaphon, Thamasta, Kala, Eroclea, as before.
               
                  Amet.
                  Honour and health still wait vpon the Prince.
                  Sir, I am bold with fauour to present
                  Vnto your Highnes, Menaphon my friend,
                  Return'd from trauaile.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  Humbly on my knees
                  I kisse your gracious hand.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  It is our duty
                  To loue the vertuous.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  If my prayers or seruice
                  
                     Hold—any value, they are vow'd yours euer.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  I haue a fist for thee too (Strippling) th'art started vp prettily since I saw thee. Hast learned any wit abroad? Canst tell newes, and sweare lyes with a grace like a true Traueller? What new Owzle's this?
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Your Highnesse shall doe right to your owne iudgement,
                  In taking more then common notice of
                  This stranger, an Athenian, nam'd Parthenophill.
                  
                  One, (whom if mine opinion doe not sooth me
                  Too grossely) for the fashion of his minde,
                  Deserues a deare respect.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Your commendations,
                  Sweet Cousin, speakes him Nobly.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  All the powers
                  That centinell iust Thrones, double these guards
                  About your sacred Excellence.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  What fortune led him to Cyprus!
               
               
                  Men.
                  My perswasions won him.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  And if your Highnesse please to heare the entrance
                  Into their first aquaintance, you will say—
               
               
                  Tham.
                  It was the newest, sweetest, prettiest accident,
                  That ere delighted your attention.
                  I can discourse it, Sir.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Some other time.
                  How is a cald?
               
               
                  Tham.
                  
                     Parthenophill.
                  
               
               
                  Prince.
                  
                     Parthenophill?
                  
                  Wee shall sort time to take more notice of him.
               
               Exit. Prince.
               
                  Men.
                  His wonted melancholy still pursues him.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  I told you so.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  You must not wonder at it.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  I doe not, Lady.
               
               
                  
                  Amet.
                  Shall we to the Castle?
               
               
                  Men.
                  Wee will attend yee both.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  All three—Ile goe too. Hark in thine eare, Gallant: Ile keep the old mad man in chat, whilest thou gabblest to the girle: my thumb's vpon my lips, not a word.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  I neede not feare thee, Rhetias.—Sister, soone
                  Expect vs: this day wee will range the City.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Well, soone I shall expect yee.—Kala?
                  
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Trust mee.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Troope on—Loue, Loue, what a wonder thou art?
               
               Exeunt.
               Kala and Eroclea stayes.
               
                  Kala.
                  May I not be offensiue, Sir?
               
               
                  Ero.
                  Your pleasure; yet pray be briefe.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Then briefly, good, resolue mee:
                  Haue you a Mistris, or a Wife?
               
               
                  Ero.
                  I haue neither.
               
               
                  Kala
                  Nor did you euer loue in earnest any
                  Faire Lady, whom you wisht to make your owne?
               
               
                  Ero.
                  Not any truly.
               
               
                  Kala
                  What your friends or meanes are
                  I will not be inquisitiue to know,
                  Nor doe I care to hope for. But admit
                  A dowre were throwne downe before your choyce,
                  Of Beauty, Noble birth, and sincere affection,
                  How gladly would you intertaine it? (Young man)
                  I doe not tempt you idly.
               
               
                  Ero.
                  I shall thanke you,
                  When my vnsettled thoughts can make me sensible
                  Of what tis to be happy: for the present
                  I am your debtor: and faire Gentlewoman,
                  Pray giue me leaue as yet to study ignorance,
                  
                     For my weake braines conceiue not what concerne me.
                  —Another time.—
               
               Enter Thamasta.
               
                  Tham.
                  Doe I breake off your Parley
                  That you are parting? Sure my woman loues you.
                  Can she speake well, Parthenophill?
                  
               
               
                  Ero.
                  Yes, Madame:
                  Discreetly chaste she can: she hath much won
                  On my beliefe, and in few words, but pithy,
                  Much moou'd my thankfulnesse. You are her Lady,
                  Your goodnesse aimes (I know) at her preferment:
                  Therefore I may be bold to make confession
                  Of truth, if euer I desire to thriue
                  In womans fauour. Kala is the first
                  Whom my ambition shall bend to.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Indeed.
                  But say a Nobler Loue should interpose?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Where reall worth, and constancy first settle
                  A hearty truth, there greatnesse cannot shake it,
                  Nor shall it mine: yet I am but an Infant
                  In that construction, which must giue cleare light
                  To Kala's merit: riper houres hereafter
                  Must learne me how to grow rich in deserts.
                  Madame, my duty waits on you.
               
               Exit Eroclea.
               
                  Tham.
                  Come hither.
                  If euer henceforth I desire to thriue
                  In womans fauours, Kala is the first
                  Whom my ambition shall bend to—'twas so.
               
               
                  Kal.
                  These very words he spake.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  These very words
                  Curse thee, vnfaithfull creature, to thy graue:
                  Thou wood'st him for thy selfe?
               
               
                  
                  Kala.
                  You said I should.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  My name was neuer mentioned!
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Madame, no:
                  We were not come to that.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Not come to that?
                  Art thou a Riuall fit to crosse my Fate?
                  Now pouerty and a dishonest fame,
                  The waiting-womans wages, be thy payment.
                  False, faithlesse, wanton beast, Ile spoile your carriage;
                  There's not a Page, a Groome, nay, not a Citizen
                  That shall be cast vpon yee. Kala,
                  
                  Ile keepe thee in my serui
                        ••
                      all thy life time,
                  Without hope of a husband or a suter.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  I haue not verily deseru'd this cruelty.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  
                     Parthenophill shall know, if he respect
                  My birth, the danger of a fond neglect.
               
               Exit Tham.
               
                  Kala.
                  Are you so quick? Well, I may chance to crosse
                  Your peeuishnesse. Now though I neuer meant
                  The young man for my selfe; yet if he loue me,
                  Ile haue him, or Ile run away with him,
                  And let her doe her worst then: what, we are all
                  But flesh and blood; the same thing that will doe
                  My Lady good, will please her woman too.
               
               Exit.
               Enter Cleophila and Trollio.
               
                  Cleo.
                  Tread softly (Trollio) my Father sleepes still.
               
               
                  Troll.
                  I forsooth: but he sleepes like a Hare with his eyes open and that's no good signe.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Sure thou art weary of this sullen liuing,
                  But I am not; for I take more content
                  In my obedience here, then all delights
                  The time presents elsewhere.
                  
                     
                     Menander within. Oh!
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Do'st heare that groane?
               
               
                  Troll.
                  Heare it? I shudder, it was a strong blast, young Mistris, able to roote vp heart, liuer, lungs and all.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  My much-wrong'd Father: let me view his face.
               
               Drawes the Arras, Meleander discouered in a chaire sleeping.
               
                  Troll.
                  Lady Mistris, shall I fetch a Barbour to steale away his rough beard, whiles he sleepes in's naps? He neuer lookes in a glasse, and tis high time on conscience for him to bee trimd, has not been vnder the Shauers hand almost these foure yeeres.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Peace, foole.
               
               
                  Trol.
                  I could clip the old Ruffian, there's haire enough to stuffe all the great Codpieces in Switzerland. A begins to stirre, a stirres. Blesse vs how his eyes rowle. A good yeere keepe your Lordship in your right wits, I beseech yee.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  
                     Cleophila?
                  
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Sir, I am here, how d'ee Sir?
               
               
                  Troll.
                  Sir, is your stomacke vp yet? get some warme porredge in your belly, 'tis a very good settle-braine.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  The Rauen croakt, and hollow shreeks of Owles
                  Sung Dirges at her funerall; I laugh'd
                  The whiles: for twas no boot to weepe. The Girle
                  Was fresh and full of youth: but, O the cunning
                  Of Tyrants that looke bigge, their very frownes
                  Doome poore soules guilty, ere their cause be heard.
                  Good. What art thou, and thou?
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  I am Cleophila,
                  
                  Your wofull daughter.
               
               
                  Troll.
                  I am Trollia your honest implement.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  I know yee both. 'las, why d'ee vse me thus!
                  
                     Thy Sister, my Eroclea, was so gentle,
                  That Turtles in their Downe doe feed more gall,
                  Then her spleene mixt with: yet when winds and storme
                  Driue dirt and dust on banks of spotlesse snow,
                  The purest whitenesse is no such defence
                  Against the sullying foulenesse of that fury.
                  So rau'd Agenor, that great man, mischiefe
                  Against the Girle—'twas a politick tricke,
                  We were too old in Honour.—I am leane
                  And falne away extremely; most assuredly
                  I haue not dyn'd these three dayes.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Will you now, Sir?
               
               
                  Troll.
                  I beseech yee heartily Sir. I feele a horrible puking my selfe.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Am I starke mad?
               
               
                  Troll.
                  No, no, you are but a little staring—there's difference betweene staring and starke mad. You are but whymsed, yet crotchetted, conundroun'd, or so.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Here's all my care: and I doe often sigh
                  For thee, Cleophyla: we are secluded
                  From all good people. But take heed, Amethus
                  
                  Was sonne to Doryla, Agenors Sister.
                  There's some ill blood about him, if the Surgeon
                  Haue not been very skilfull to let all out.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  I am (alas) too grieu'd to thinke of loue,
                  That must concerne me least.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Sirra, be wise, be wise.
               
               Enter Amethus, Menaphon, Eroclea (as before) and Rhetias.
               
                  Troll.
                  Who I? I will be monstrous and wise immediately. Welcome, Gentlemen, the more the merrier, Ile lay the cloth, and set the stooles in a readinesse, for I see here is some hope of dinner now.
               
               Exit Trollio.
               
                  
                  Amet.
                  My Lord Meleander, Menaphon your Kinsman
                  Newly return'd from trauaile, comes to tender
                  His duty t'ee: to you his loue, faire Mistris.
               
               
                  Men.
                  I would I could as easily remoue
                  Sadnesse from your remembrance, Sir, as study
                  To doe you faithfull seruice—my deare Cousin,
                  All best of comforts blesse your sweet obedience.
               
               
                  Clo.
                  One chiefe of 'em (worthy Cousin) liues
                  In you, and your well-doing.
               
               
                  Men.
                  This young stranger
                  Will well deserue your knowledge.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  For my friends sake,
                  Lady pray giue him welcome.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  He has met it, if sorrowes can looke kindly.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  You much honour me.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  How a eyes the company: sure my passion will betray my weakenesse—O my Master, my Noble Master, doe not forget me, I am still the humblest, and the most faithfull in heart of those that serue you.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Ha, ha, ha.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  There's wormewood in that laughter, tis the vsher to a violent extremity.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  I am a weake old man. All these are come To ieere my ripe calamities.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  Good Vncle!
               
               
                  Mel.
                  But Ile out-stare 'ee all, fooles, desperate fooles,
                  You are cheated, grossely cheated, range, range on,
                  And rowle about the world to gather mosse,
                  The mosse of honour, gay reports, gay clothes,
                  Gay wiues, huge empty buildings, whose proud roofes,
                  Shall with their pinacles, euen reach the starres.
                  Ye worke and worke like Moles, blind in the paths,
                  That are bor'd through the crannies of the earth,
                  To charge your hungry soules with such full surfets,
                  
                     As being gorg'd once, make 'ee leane with plenty.
                  And when ye haue skimd the vomit of your riots,
                  Y'are fat in no felicity but folly,
                  Then your last sleepes seize on 'ee. Then the troopes
                  Of wormes crawle round, &amp;, feast, good cheare, rich fare,
                  Dainty delicious—here's Cleophyl
                           •
                        
                     :
                  All the poore stocke of my remaining thrift;
                  You, you, the Princes Cousin: how d'ee like her?
                  (Amethus) how d'ee like her?
               
               
                  Amet.
                  My intents are iust and honourable.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Sir, beleeue him.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Take her.—we two must part, go to him, doe.
               
               
                  Ero.
                  This sight is full of horror.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  This is sence yet in this distraction.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  In this Iewell I haue giuen away,
                  All what I can call mine. When I am dead,
                  Saue charge; let me be buried in a nooke.
                  No guns, no pompous whining: these are fooleries.
                  If whiles we liue, we stalke about the streets,
                  Iustled by Carmen, Foot-poasts, and fine Apes,
                  In silken coates, vnminded, and scarce thought on;
                  It is not comely to be hal'd to the earth,
                  Like high fed lades vpon a Tilting-day,
                  In antique trappings: scorne to vse-lesse teares.
                  
                     Eroclea was not coffind so: she perisht,
                  And no eye dropt saue mine, and I am childish.
                  I talke like one that doates; laugh at me, Rhetias,
                  
                  Or raile at me: they will not giue me meate:
                  They haue staru'd me: but Ile henceforth be mine owne Cook.
                  Good morrow: tis too early for my cares
                  To reuell. I will breake my heart a little,
                  And tell yee more hereafter. Pray be merry.
               
               Exit Meleander.
               
                  
                  Rhet.
                  Ile follow him. My Lord Amethus, vse your time
                  Respectiuely. Few words to purpose soon'st preuaile:
                  Study no long Orations; be plaine and short,
                  Ile follow him.
               
               Exit Rhetias.
               
                  Amet.
                  
                     Cleophyla, although these blacker clouds
                  Of sadnes, thicken and make darke the sky
                  Of thy faire eyes, yet giue me leaue to follow
                  The streame of my affections: they are pure,
                  Without all mixture of vnnoble thoughts.
                  Can you be euer mine?
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  I am so low
                  In mine owne fortunes, and my Father woes,
                  That I want words to tell yee, you deserue
                  A worthier choice.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  But giue me leaue to hope.
               
               
                  Men.
                  My friend is serious.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Sir, this for answer: If I euer thriue
                  In an earthly happinesse, the next
                  To my good Fathers wisht recouery,
                  Must be my thankfulnesse to your great merit;
                  Which I dare promise for the present time:
                  You cannot vrge more from me.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Ho, Cleophyla?
                  
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  This Gentleman is moou'd.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Your eyes, Parthenophill,
                  
                  Are guilty of some passion.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Friend, what ailes thee?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  All is not well within me, Sir.
                  
                     Meleander within. Cleophyla?
                  
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Sweet Maid, forget me not; we now must part.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Still you shall haue my prayer.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Still you my truth.
               
               Exeunt omnes.
               Finis Actus secundi.
            
            
               
               Actus III. Scena I.
               Enter Cuculus and Grilla, Cuculus in a blacke veluet Cap, and a white Feather, with a paper in his hand.
               
                  Cuculus.
                  DOe not I looke freshly, and like a Youth of the Trim?
               
               
                  Gril.
                  As rare an old Youth as euer walkt crosse-gartered.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Here are my Mistrisses mustred in white and blacke. Kala the Waiting-woman. I will first begin at the soote: stand thou for Kala.
                  
               
               
                  Gril.
                  I stand for Kala, doe your best and your worst.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  I must looke bigge, and care little or nothing for her, because shee is a creature that stands at liuery. Thus I talke wisely, and to no purpose. Wench, as it is not fit that thou should'st be either faire or honest; so considering thy seruice, thou art as thou art, and so are thy betters, let them bee what they can bee. Thus in despite and defiance of all thy good parts, if I cannot indure
thy basenesse, tis more out of thy courtesie, then my deseruing, and so I expect thy answer.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  I must confesse—
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Well said.
               
               
                  Gril.
                  You are—
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  That's true too.
               
               
                  Gril.
                  To speake you right, a very scuruy fellow.—
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Away, away, do'st thinke so?
               
               
                  
                  Grill.
                  A very foule-mouth'd, and misshapen Cockscombe
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Ile neuer beleeue it by this hand.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  A Magot, most vnworthy to creepe in—
                  —To the least wrinckle of a Gentlewomans
                  (What d'ee call) good conceit, or so, or what
                  You will else.—Were you not refin'd by Courtship
                  And education, which in my bleare eyes
                  Makes you appeare as sweet as any nosegay,
                  Or sauory cod of Muske new fall'n from th'Cat.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  This shall serue well enough for the Waiting-woman. My next Mistris is Cleophyla, the old mad-mans daughter: I must come to her in whining tune, sigh, wipe mine eyes, fold my Armes, and blubber out my speech as thus: Euen as a Kennell of Hounds (sweet Lady) cannot catch a Hare, when they are full pauncht on the Carrion of a dead Horse: so, euen so the gorge of my affections being full cramm'd with the garboyles of your condolements, doth tickle me with the prick (as it were) about mee, and fellow-feeling of howling outright.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  This will doo't, if we will heare.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Thou seest I am crying ripe, I am such another tender-hearted foole.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  Euen as the snuffe of a candle that is burnt in the socket, goes out, and leaues a strong perfume behind it; or as a piece of toasted cheese next the heart in a morning is a restoratiue for a sweet breath: so, euen so the odoriferous sauour of your loue doth perfume my heart, (Hay ho) with the pure sent of an intolerable content, and not to be indur'd.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  By this hand tis excellent. Haue at thee last of all: for the Princesse Thamasta, she that is my Mistris

indeed, she is abominably proud. A Lady of a damnable, high, turbulent, and generous spirit. But I haue a loud-mouth'd Cannon of mine owne to batter her, and a pen'd speech of purpose obserue it.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  Thus I walke by, heare and minde you not.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Though haughty as the Diuell or his Dam,
                  Thou dost appeare, great Mistris: yet I am
                  Like to an vgly fire-worke, and can mount
                  Aboue the Region of thy sweet Ac—count.
                  Wert thou the Moone her selfe, yet hauing seene thee,
                  Behold the man ordain'd to mooue within thee.
                  —Looke to your selfe, Houswife; answer me
                  In strong Lines y'are best.
               
               
                  Gril.
                  Keepe off, poore foole, my beames will strike thee blinde:
                  Else if thou touch me, touch me but behind.
                  In Palaces, such as passe in before,
                  Must be great Princes; for at the backe dore
                  Tatter-demallians waite, who know not how
                  To get admittance: such a one—art Thou.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  S'foot, this is downe-right roaring.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  I know how to present a big Lady in her owne cue. But pray in earnest, are you in loue with all these?
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Pish, I haue not a ragge of loue about me. Tis only a foolish humour I am possest with, to be surnam'd the Conquerour. I will court any thing; be in loue with nothing, nor no—thing.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  A rare man you are, I protest.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Yes, I know I am a rare man, and I euer held my selfe so.
                  Enter Pelias and Corax.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  In amorous contemplation on my life;
                  Courting his Page by Hel. con.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Cucul.
                  Tis false.
               
               
                  Grill.
                  A grosse vntruth; Ile iustifie it, Sir, At any time, place, weapon.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Marry shall she.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  No quarrels, good'ee Whiske. Lay by your Trumperies, and fall to your practice. Instructions are ready for you all. Pelias is your Leader, follow him. Get credit now or neuer. Vanish, Doodles, vanish.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  For the Deuice.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  The same, get'ee gone, and make no bawling.
                  Exeunt.
                  To waste my time thus Droane-like in the Court,
                  And lose so many houres, as my studies
                  Haue horded vp, is to be like a man
                  That creepes both on his hands and knees, to climbe
                  A mountaines top, where when he is ascended,
                  One carelesse slip downe, tumbles him againe
                  Into the bottome whence a first began.
                  I need no Princes fauour: Princes need
                  My art. Then Corax, be no more a Gull,
                  The best of'em cannot foole thee, nay, they shall not.
               
               Enter Sophronos and Aretus.
               
                  Soph.
                  We find him timely now let's learne the cause.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  Tis fit we should—Sir, we approue you learn'd,
                  And since your skill can best discerne the humours
                  That are predominant, in bodies subiect
                  To alteration: tell vs (pray) what diuell
                  This Melancholy is, which can transforme
                  Men into Monsters.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Y'ar your selfe a Scholer,
                  And quicke of apprehension: Melancholy
                  
                  Is not as you conceiue. Indisposition
                  
                     Of body, but the mindes disease. So Extasie,
                  Fantastick Dotage, Madnesse, Phrenzey, Rupture,
                  Of meere imagination differ partly
                  
                     
                        Vid. Democrit. Iunior.
                     From Melancholy, which is briefly this,
                  A meere commotion of the minde, o're-charg'd
                  With feare and sorrow; first begot i'th' braine,
                  The Seate of Reason, and from thence deriu'd
                  As suddenly into the Heart, the Seate
                  Of our Affection.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  There are sundry kinds
                  Of this disturbance.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Infinite, it were
                  More easie to coniecture euery houre
                  We haue to liue, then reckon vp the kinds,
                  Or causes of this anguish of the minde.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Thus you conclude, that as the cause is doubtfull,
                  The cure must be impossible; and then
                  Our Prince (poore Gentleman) is lost for euer,
                  As well vnto himselfe, as to his subiects.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  My Lord, you are too quick; thus much I dare
                  Promise, and doe, ere many minutes passe,
                  I will discouer whence his sadnesse is,
                  Or vndergoe the censure of my ignorance.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  You are a Noble Scholer.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  For reward,
                  You shall make your owne demand.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  May I be sure?
               
               
                  Aret.
                  We both will pledge our truth.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Tis soone perform'd,
                  That I may be discharg'd from my attendance
                  At Court, and neuer more be sent for after:
                  Or if I be, may Rats gnaw all my bookes,
                  If I get home once, and come here againe,
                  
                     Though my necke stretch a halter for't, I care not.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Come, come, you shall not feare it.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Ile acquaint yee
                  With what is to be done, and you shall fashion it.
               
               Exeunt omnes.
               Enter Kala and Eroclea, as before.
               
                  Kala.
                  My Lady do's expect'ee, thinks all time
                  Too slow till you come to her: wherefore young man,
                  If you intend to loue me, and me onely,
                  Before we part, without more circumstance
                  Let vs betroth our selues.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  I dare not wrong 'ee;
                  You are too violent.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Wrong me no more
                  Then I wrong you: be mine, and I am yours:
                  I cannot stand on points.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Then to resolue
                  All further hopes, you neuer can be mine,
                  Must not, (and pardon though I say) you shall not.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  The thing is sure a Gelding—Shall not? well,
                  Y'are best to prate vnto my Lady now,
                  What proffer I haue made.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Neuer, I vow.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Doe, doe, tis but a kind heart of mine owne,
                  And ill lucke can vndoe me.—Be refus'd?
                  O sciruy.—Pray walke on, Ile ouertake 'ee.
                  What a greene-sickness-liuer'd Boy is this!
                  Exit Ero.
                  My Maiden-head will shortly grow so stale,
                  That'twill be mouldy: but Ile marre her market.
               
               Enter Menaphon.
               
                  Men.
                  
                     Parthenophill past the way; prethee Kala
                  
                  
                     Direct me to him.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Yes, I can direct'ee:
                  But you (Sir) must forbeare.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Forbeare!
               
               
                  Kala.
                  I said so.
                  Your bounty h'as ingag'd my truth; receiue
                  A secret, that will, as you are a man,
                  Startle your Reason: tis but meere respect
                  Of what I owe to thankfulnesse. (Deare Sir)
                  The Stranger whom your courtesie receiued
                  For Friend, is made your Riuall.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Riuall, Kala.
                  
                  Take heed, thou art too credulous.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  My Lady
                  Doates on him: I will place you in a roome,
                  Where, though you cannot heare, yet you shall see
                  Such passages as will confirme the truth
                  Of my intelligence.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Twill make me mad.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Yes, yes: it makes me mad too, that a Gentleman
                  So excellently sweet, so liberall,
                  So kind, so proper, should be so betray'd
                  By a young smooth-chind straggler: but for loues sake
                  Beare all with manly courage.—Not a word,
                  I am vndone then.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  That were too much pity:
                  Honest most honest Kala; tis thy care,
                  Thy seruiceable care.
               
               
                  Kal.
                  You haue euen spoken all can be said or thought.
               
               
                  Men.
                  I will reward thee:
                  But as for him, vngentle Boy, Ile whip
                  His falshood with a vengeance.—
               
               
                  Kala.
                  O speake little.
                  
                     Walke vp these staires, and take this key, it opens
                  A Chamber doore, where at that window yonder,
                  You may see all their courtship.
               
               
                  Men.
                  I am silent.
               
               Exit Menap.
               
                  Kala.
                  As little noyse as may be, I beseech yee;
                  There is a backe-staire to conuey yee forth
                  Vnseene or vnsuspected.—He that cheates
                  A Waiting-woman of a free good turne
                  She longs for, must expect a shrewd reuenge.
                  Sheepe-spirited Boy, although he had not married me,
                  He might haue proferd kindnesse in a corner,
                  And ne'er haue been the worse sor't. They are come;
                  On goes my set of Faces most demurely.
               
               Enter Thamasta and Eroclea.
               
                  Tham.
                  Forbeare the roome.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Yes, Madame.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Whosoeuer requires accesse to me, deny him entrance till I call thee, and wait without.
               
               
                  Kala.
                  I shall. Sweet Venus, turne his courage to a Snow-ball, I heartily beseech it.
               
               Exit.
               
                  Tham.
                  I expose
                  The Honour of my Birth, my Fame, my Youth,
                  To hazard of much hard construction,
                  In seeking an aduenture of a parley
                  So priuate with a Stranger; if your thoughts
                  Censure me not with mercy, you may soone
                  Conceiue, I haue laid by that modesty,
                  Which should preserue a vertuous name vnstain'd.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Lady, to shorten long excuses; time
                  And safe experience haue so throughly arm'd
                  My apprehension, with a reall taste
                  Of your most Noble nature, that to question
                  The least part of your bounties, or that freedome
                  
                     Which Heauen hath with a plenty made you rich in,
                  Would argue me vnciuill, which is more,
                  Base-bred, and which is most of all, vnthankefull.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  The constant Loadstone, and the Steele are found
                  In seuerall Mines: yet is there such a league
                  Betweene these Minerals, as if one Veine
                  Of earth had nourisht both. The gentle Mirtle
                  Is not ingraft vpon an Oliues stocke:
                  Yet nature hath betweene them lockt a secret
                  Of Sympathy, that being planted neere,
                  They will both in their branches, and their rootes
                  Imbrace each other; twines of Iuie round
                  The well growne Oake; the Vine doth court the Elme;
                  Yet these are different Plants. Parthenophill,
                  
                  Consider this aright, then these sleight creatures,
                  Will fortifie the reasons I should frame
                  For that vngrounded (as thou think'st) affection,
                  Which is submitted to a strangers pitie.
                  True loue may blush, when shame repents too late,
                  But in all actions Nature yeelds to Fate.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Great Lady, 'twere a dulnesse must exceed
                  The grossest and most sottish kind of ignorance,
                  Not to be sensible of your intents:
                  I clearely vnderstand them. Yet so much
                  The difference betweene that height and lownesse,
                  Which doth distinguish our vnequall fortunes,
                  Disswades me from ambition; that I am
                  Humbler in my desires, then Loues owne power
                  Can any way raise vp.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  I am a Princesse,
                  And know no law of slauery, to sue,
                  Yet be denied?
               
               
                  Ero.
                  I am so much a subiect
                  
                     To euery law of Noble honesty,
                  That to transgresse the vowes of perfect friendship,
                  I hold a sacriledge as foule, and curs'd,
                  As if some holy Temple had bin robd,
                  And I the thiefe.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Thou art vnwise, young man,
                  To inrage a Lyonesse.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  It were vniust
                  To falsifie a faith, and euer after
                  Disroab'd of that faire ornament, liue naked,
                  A scorne to time and truth.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Remember well who I am, and what thou art.
               
               
                  Ero.
                  That remembrance
                  Prompts me to worthy duty, O great Lady.
                  If some few dayes haue tempted your free heart,
                  To cast away affection on a stranger:
                  If that affection haue so ouersway'd
                  Your Iudgement, that it in a manner hath
                  Declyn'd your soueraignty of birth and spirit:
                  How can yee turne your eyes off from that glasse,
                  Wherein you may new Trim, and settle right
                  A memorable name?
               
               
                  Tham.
                  The Youth is idle.
               
               
                  Ero.
                  Dayes, months and yeeres are past, since Menaphon
                  
                  Hath lou'd and seru'd you truly: Menaphon;
                  A man of no large distance in his bloud,
                  From yours; in qualities desertfull, grac't
                  With Youth, Experience; euery happy gift
                  That can by nature, or by Education
                  Improue a Gentleman: for him (great Lady)
                  Let me preuaile, that you will yet at last,
                  Vnlocke the bounty, which your loue and care
                  Haue wisely treasur'd vp, t'inrich his life.
               
               
                  
                  Tha.
                  Thou hast a moouing eloquence; Parthenophill,
                  
                  
                     Parthenophill, in vaine we striue to crosse
                  The destiny that guides vs. My great heart
                  Is stoopt so much beneath that wonted pride
                  That first disguiz'd it, that I now preferre
                  A miserable life with thee, before
                  All other earthly comforts.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  
                     Menaphon, by me, repeates the selfe-same words to you:
                  You are too cruell, if you can distrust
                  His truth, or my report.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Goe where thou wilt,
                  Ile be an exile with thee, I will learne
                  To beare all change of fortunes.
               
               
                  Ero.
                  For my friend, I pleade with grounds of reason.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  For thy loue,
                  Hard-hearted youth, I here renounce all thoughts
                  Of other hopes, of other intertainements,—
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Stay, as you honour Vertue.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  When the proffers of other greatnesse—
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Lady.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  When intreats of friends;—
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Ile ease your griefe.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Respect of kindred;
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Pray giue me hearing.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Losse of Fame;
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  I craue but some few minutes.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Shall infringe my vowes, let Heauen—
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  My loue speake t'ee; heare then, goe on.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Thy loue, why tis a Charme to stop a vow
                  In its most violent course.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  
                     Cupid has broke
                  His Arrowes here; and like a child vnarm'd,
                  Comes to make sport betweene vs with no weapon,
                  
                     But feathers stolne from his mothers Doues.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  This is meere trifling.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Lady, take a secret.
                  I am as you are, in a lower ranke
                  Else of the selfe samesexe, a maide, a virgine.
                  And now to vse your owne words, if your thoughts
                  Censure me not with mercy, you may soone
                  Conceiue, I haue laid by that modesty,
                  Which should preserue a vertuous name vnstain'd.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Are you not mankind then?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  When you shall reade
                  The story of my sorrowes, with the change
                  Of my misfortunes, in a letter printed
                  From my vnforg'd relation; I beleeue
                  You will not thinke the sheading of one teare,
                  A prodigality that misbecomes
                  Your pitie and my fortune.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Pray conceale the errors of my passions.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Would I had
                  Much more of honour (as for life I value't not)
                  To venture on your secrecy.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  It will be
                  A hard taske for my Reason, to relinquish
                  The affection which was once deuoted thine,
                  I shall a while repute thee still the youth
                  I lou'd so dearely.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  You shall find mee euer, your ready faithfull seruant.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  O the powers
                  Who doe direct our hearts, laugh at our follies!
                  We must not part yet.
               
               
                  Ero.
                  Let not my vnworthines alter your good opinion.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  I shall henceforth
                  Be iealous of thy company with any;
                  
                     My feares are strong and many.
               
               Kala enters.
               
                  Kala.
                  Did your Ladiship call me?
               
               
                  Tham.
                  For what?
               
               
                  Kala.
                  Your seruant Menaphon desires admittance.
               
               Enter Menaphon.
               
                  Men.
                  With your leaue, great Mistris! I come—
                  So priuate: is this well, Parthenophill?
                  
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Sir, Noble Sir.
               
               
                  Men.
                  You are vnkind and treacherous.
                  This tis to trust a straggler.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Prethee seruant.
               
               
                  Men.
                  I dare not question you, you are my Mistris;
                  My Princes neerest Kinswoman, but he—
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Come, you are angry.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  Henceforth I will bury
                  Vnmanly passion in perpetuall silence.
                  Ile court mine owne distraction, dote on folly,
                  Creepe to the mirth and madnesse of the age,
                  Rather then be so slau'd againe to woman,
                  Which in her best of constancy is steddist
                  In change and scorne.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  How dare ye talke to me thus?
               
               
                  Men.
                  Dare? Were you not owne Sister to my friend,
                  Sister to my Amethus; I would hurle ye
                  As farre off from mine eyes, as from my heart;
                  For I would neuer more looke on yee. Take
                  Your Iewell t'ee. And Youth, keepe vnder wing,
                  Or—Boy—Boy.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  If commands be of no force,
                  Let me intreat thee, Menaphon.
                  
               
               
                  Men.
                  Tis naught, fye, fye, Parthenophill, haue I deseru'd
                  To be thus vs'd?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  I doe protest—
               
               
                  
                  Men.
                  You shall not,
                  Henceforth I will be free, and hate my bondage.
               
               Enter Amethus.
               
                  Amet.
                  Away, away to Court, the Prince is pleas'd
                  To see a Maske to night, we must attend him:
                  Tis neere vpon the time.—How thriues your suit?
               
               
                  Men.
                  The Iudge, your Sister, will decide it shor
                        •
                     ly.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  
                     Parthenophill, I will not trust you from me.
               
               Enter Prince, Aretas, Corax (with a Paper-plot) seruants with torches.
               
                  Cor.
                  Lights and attendance, I will shew your highnes,
                  A trifle of mine owne braine If you can,
                  Imagine you were now in the Vniuersity,
                  You'll take it well enough, a Schollers fancy,
                  A quab. Tis nothing else a very quab.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  We will obserue it.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Yes, and grace it too Sir.
                  For Corax else is 
                        •
                     umorous and testy.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  By any meanes, men singular in Art,
                  Haue alwayes some odde whimsey more then vsuall.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  The name of this conceit.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Sir, it is called the Maske of Melancholy.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  We must looke for nothing but sadnesse, here then.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Madnesse rather
                  In seuerall changes: Melancholy is
                  The Roote aswell of euery Apish Phrensey,
                  Laughter and mirth, as dulnesse. Pray my Lord
                  Hold and obserue the plot, tis there exprest
                  In kind, what shall be now exprest in action.
                  Enter Amethus, Menaphon, Thamasta, Eroclea.
                  No interpretation, take your places quickly.
                  
                     Nay, nay, leaue ceremony: sound to the entrance.
               
               Florish.
               Enter Rhetias, his face whited, blacke shag haire, long nailes, a piece of raw meate.
               
                  Rhet.
                  Bow, Bow, wow, wow; the Moone's eclipsed, Ile to the Church-yard and sup: Since I turn'd Wolfe, I bark and howle, and digge vp graues, I will neuer haue the Sunne shine againe, tis midnight, deepe darke midnight, get a prey, and fall too, I haue catcht thee now. Arre.
                  
               
               
                  Cora.
                  This kind is called, Lycanthropia, Sir,
                  When men conceiue themselues Wolues.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Here I finde it.
               
               Enter Pelias. A Crowne of feathers on, Antickly rich.
               
                  Pel.
                  I will hang 'em all, and burne my wife: was I not an Emperour; my hand was kist, and Ladies lay downe before me. In triumph did I ride with my Nobles about me, till the mad-dog bit mee, I fell, and I fell, and I fell. It shall be treason by Statute for any man to name water, or wash his hands throughout all my Dominions; breake all the looking-glasses, I will not see my hornes; my wife Cuckolds me, she is a whore, a whore, a whore, a whore.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  
                     Hydrophobia terme you this?
               
               
                  Cora.
                  And men possest so, shun all sight of water:
                  Sometimes, if mixt with iealousie, it renders them.
                  Incurable, and oftentimes brings death.
               
               
                  
                  Enter Philosopher in blacke rags, a copper chaine on, an old Gowne halfe off, and Booke.
               
               
                  Phi.
                  Philosophers dwel in the Moone Speculation and Theory girdle the world about like a wall. Ignorance like an Atheist, must bee damn'd in the pit. I am very, very poore, and pouerty is the phisicke for the soule: my opinions are pure and perfect. Enuy is a monster, and I defie the beast.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  
                     Delirium this is call'd, which is meere dotage,
                  Sprung from Ambition first, and singularity,
                  Selfe loue, and blind opinion of true merit.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  I not dislike the course.
               
               Enter Grilla in a rich Gowne, great Vardingale, great Ruffe, Musse, Fan, and Coxcombe on her head.
               
                  Grill.
                  Yes forsooth, and no forsooth, is not this fine, I pray, your blessing Gaffer, here, here, here did hee giue me a shough, and cut offs taile: busse, busse Nuncle, and ther's a pum for Daddee.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  You find this noted there, Phrenitis.
                  
               
               
                  Prince.
                  True.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Pride is the ground on't;
                  It raignes most in women.
               
               Enter Cuculus like a Bedlam singing.
               
                  Cucul.
                  They that will learne to drinke a health in Hell,
                  Must learne on earth to take Tobacco well,
                  To take Tobacco well, to take Tobacco well:
                  For in Hell they drink nor Wine, nor Ale, nor Beere,
                  But fire, and smoake, and stench, as we do heere.
               
               
                  
                  Rhet.
                  Ile soope thee vp.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Thou'st straight to execution.
               
               
                  Gril.
                  Foole, Foole, Foole, catch me and thou canst.
               
               
                  Philos.
                  Expell him the house, tis a Dunce.
               
               Cuculus sings.
               Harke, did yee not heare a rumbling,
               The Gobblings are now a tumbling:
               Il
                     •
                   teare 'em, Ile seare'em,
               Ile roare 'em, Ile goare 'em:
               Now, now, now, my braines are a Iumbling,—
               Bounce, the gun's off.
               
                  Prince.
                  You name this here, Hypocondriacall.
                  
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Which is a windy flattuous humour stuffing
                  The head, and thence deriu'd to th'animall parts
                  To be too ouer-curious, losse of goods,
                  Or friends, excesse of feare, or sorrowes cause it.
               
               Enter a Sea-nimph big-bellied, singing and dancing.
               Good your Honours,
               Pray your Worships,
               Deare your Beauties,
               
                  Cucul.
                  Hang thee.
                  To lash your sides,
                  To taeme your hides,
                  To scourge your prides,
                  And bang thee.
               
               
                  Nym.
                  Were pretty and dainty, and I will begin,
                  See how they doe Ieere me, deride me, and grin:
                  Come sport me, come court me, your Topsaile aduance,
                  And let vs conclude our delights in a Dance.
               
               
                  
                  All.
                  A Dance, a Dance, a Dance.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  This is the Wanton Melancholy; women
                  With child possest with this strange sury often,
                  Haue danc'd three dayes together without ceasing.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Tis very strange: but Heau'n is full of miracles.
               
               The Dance:—
               Which ended, they all run out in couples.
               
                  Prince.
                  We are thy debtor (Corax) for the gift
                  Of this inuention: but the plot deceiues vs;
                  What meanes this empty space.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  One kind of Melancholy
                  Is onely left vntouch'd; twas not in Art
                  To personate the shadow of that Fancy.
                  Tis nam'd Loue-Melancholy. As for instance,
                  Admit this stranger here (Young man, stand forth)
                  Intangled by the beauty of this Lady,
                  The great Thamasta, cherisht in his heart
                  The waight of hopes and feares: it were impossible,
                  To lymne his passions in such liuely colours,
                  As his owne proper sufferance coo'd expresse.
               
               
                  Ero.
                  You are not modest Sir.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Am I your mirth?
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Loue is the Tyrant of the heart, it darkens
                  Reason, confounds discretion, deafe to counsell:
                  It runnes a headlong course to desperate madnesse.
                  O were your Highnes but toucht home, and throughly,
                  With this (what shall I call it) Diuell—
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Hold, let no man henceforth name the word agen
                  Wait you my pleasure, Youth; tis late, to rest.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  My Lords—
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Enough, thou art a perfect Arts-man.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Panthers may hide their heads, not change the skin:
                  And loue pent ne're so close yet will be seene.
               
               Exeunt.
            
            
               
               Actus IIII. Scena I.
               Enter Amethus and Menaphon.
               
                  Amethus.
                  DOate on a stranger?
               
               
                  Mena.
                  Court him, plead, and sue to him,
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Affectionately?
               
               
                  Mena.
                  Seruilely; and pardon me, if I say basely.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Women in their passions,
                  Like false fiers flash, to fright our trembling sences;
                  Yet in themselues containe nor light nor heate.
                  My Sister doe this? Shee, whose pride did scorne
                  All thoughts that were not busied on a Crowne?
                  To fall so farre beneath her fortunes now?
                  You are my friend.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  What I confirme, is truth.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Truth, Menaphon?
                  
               
               
                  Mena.
                  If I conceiu'd you were
                  Iealous of my sincerity and plainnesse,
                  Then Sir—
               
               
                  Amet.
                  What then, Sir?
               
               
                  Mena.
                  I would then resolue,
                  You were as changeable in vowes of friendship,
                  As is Thamasta in her choice of loue.
                  That sinne is double, running in a blood,
                  Which iustifies another being worse.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  My Menaphon, excuse me, I grow wilde,
                  And would not willingly beleeue the truth
                  Of my dishonour: She shall know how much
                  
                     I am a debtor to thy noble goodnesse,
                  By checking the contempt, her poore desires
                  Haue sunke her fame in. Prethee tell me (friend)
                  How did the Youth receiue her?
               
               
                  Mena.
                  With a coldnesse,
                  As modest and as hopelesse, as the trust
                  I did repose in him, coo'd wish, or merit.
               
               Enter Thamasta and Kala.
               
                  Ame.
                  I will esteeme him dearely.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Sir, your Sister.
               
               
                  Tha.
                  Seruant, I haue imployment for yee.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Harke yee:
                  The maske of your ambition is fallen off,
                  Your pride hath stoop't to such an abiect lownesse,
                  That you haue now discouer'd to report
                  Your nakednesse in vertue, honors, shame—
               
               
                  Tham.
                  You are turn'd Satyre.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  All the flatteries
                  Of greatnesse haue expos'd yee to contempt.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  This is meere rayling.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  You haue sold your birth, for lust.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Lust?
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Yes, and at a deare expence
                  Purchast the onely glories of a Wanton.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  A Wanton?
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Let repentance stop your mouth.
                  Learne to redeeme your fault.
               
               
                  Kal.
                  I hope your tongue ha's not betrayd my honesty.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Feare nothing.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  If (Menaphon,) I hitherto haue stroue;
                  To keepe a wary guard about my fame;
                  If I haue vsed a womans skill to sift
                  
                     The constancy of your protested loue;
                  You cannot in the Iustice of your iudgment,
                  Impute that to a Coynesse, or neglect,
                  Which my discretion and your seruice aym'd
                  For noble purposes.
               
               
                  Mena.
                  Great Mistris, no:
                  I rather quarrell with mine owne ambition,
                  That durst to soare so high, as to feed hope
                  Of any least desert, that might intitle
                  My duty, to a pension from your fauours.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  And therefore Lady (pray obserue him well)
                  He henceforth couets playne equality;
                  Indeuouring to rancke his fortunes low,
                  With some fit partner, whom without presumption,
                  Without offence, or danger, he may cherish;
                  Yes and command too, as a Wife; a Wife;
                  A Wife, my most great Lady
               
               
                  Kala
                  all will out.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Now I perceiue the league of Amitye,
                  Which you haue long betweene yee, vow'd and kept,
                  I
                        •
                      s
                        •
                     cred and inuiolable, secrets
                  Of e
                        •
                     ery nature are in common t'ee:
                  I haue trespass'd, and I haue been faulty:
                  Let not too rude a Censure doome me guilty,
                  Or iudge my errour wilfull without pardon.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Gracious and vertuous Mistris.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Tis a tricke,
                  There is no trust in female cunning (friend)
                  Let her first purge her follies past, and cleere
                  The wrongs done to her honor, by some sure
                  Apparant testimony of her constancy:
                  Or wee will not beleeue these childish plots;
                  As you respect my friendship, lend no eare
                  
                     To a reply. Thinke on't.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Pray loue your fame.
               
               Exeunt Men. Amet.
               
                  Tham.
                  Gon! I am sure awakt. Kala I finde,
                  You haue not been so trusty as the duty
                  You ow'd, requir'd.
               
               
                  Kala
                  Not I? I doe protest, I haue been, Madam.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Bee no matter what.
                  I'me pay'd in mine owne Coyne; something I must,
                  And speedily—so,—seeke out Cuculus
                  
                  Bid him attend me instantly.
               
               
                  Kala
                  That Anticke!
                  The trim old Youth shall wait yee.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Wounds may be mortall, which are wounds indeed:
                  " But no wounds deadly, till our Honors bleed. Exeunt.
                  
               
               Enter Rhetias and Corax.
               
                  Rhet.
                  Thar't an excellent fellow. Diabolo. O this lousie close-stoole Empricks, that will vndertake all Cures, yet know not the causes of any disease. Dog-leaches. By the foure Elements I honor thee, coo'd finde in my heart to turne knaue, and bee thy flatterer.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Sirra, tis pitty th'ast not been a Scholer;
                  Th'art honest, blunt, and rude enough. O Conscience!
                  But for thy Lord now, I haue put him too't.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  He chafes hugely, fumes like a stew-pot; Is he not monstrously ouergone in frenzy?
               
               
                  Cora.
                  
                     Rhetias, tis not a madnesse, but his sorrow's
                  Close griping griefe, and anguish of the soule
                  That torture him: he carries Hell on earth
                  Within his bosome, 'twas a Princes tyranny
                  Caus'd his distraction, and a Princes sweetnes
                  Must qualifie that tempest of his minde.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  
                     Corax, to prayse thy Art, were to assure
                  The misbeleeuing world, that the Sunne shines,
                  
                     When tis in th'full Meridian of his beauty.
                  No cloud of blacke detraction can eclipse
                  The light of thy rare knowledge; henceforth casting
                  All poore disguises off, that play in rudenesse,
                  Call me your seruant: onely for the present,
                  I wish a happy blessing to your Labours;
                  Heauen crowne your vndertakings; and beleeue me,
                  Ere many houres can passe, at our next meeting,
                  The bonds my duty owes, shall be full cancelled.
               
               Exit.
               
                  Cora.
                  Farwell—a shrewd-braine Whorson, there's pith
                  In his vntoward plainenesse.—
                  Enter Trollio with a Murrion on.
                  Now, the newes!
               
               
                  Troll.
                  Worshipfull Master Doctor, I haue a great deale of I cannot tell what, to say t'ee; My Lord thunders: euery word that comes out of his mouth, roares like a Cannon: the house shooke once, my young Lady dares not be seene.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  We will roare with him, Trollio, if he roare.
               
               
                  Trol.
                  He has got a great Poll-axe in his hand, and fences it vp and downe the house, as if he were to make roome for the Pageants. I haue prouided me a Murrion forfeare of a clap on the Coxcombe.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  No matter for the Murrion, here's my Cap:
                  Thus I will pull it downe; and thus out-stare him.
               
               
                  Trol.
                  The Physicion is got as mad as my Lord.—
                  O braue, a man of Worship.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Let him come, Trollio, I will firke his Trangdido,
                  And bounce, and bounce in metall, honest Trollio.
                  
               
               
                  Trol.
                  Hee vapours like a Tinker, and struts like a Iuggler.
               
               
                  Menander within. So ho▪ So ho.
               
                  Troll.
                  There, there, there; looke to your Right Worshipfull, looke to your selfe.
               
               
                  
                  Enter Meleander with a poll-axe.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Show me the Dog, whose triple throated noyse,
                  Hath rowzd a Lyon from his vncoth den,
                  To teare the Curre in pieces.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Stay thy pawes,
                  Couragious beast, else lo, the gorgeous skull,
                  That shall transforme thee, to that restlesse stone,
                  Which Sysiphus roules vp against the hill;
                  Whence tumbling downe againe, it, with his waight
                  Shall crush thy bones, and puffe thee into Ayre.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Hold, hold thy conqu'ring breath, tis stronger far
                  Then Gun-powder and Garlike. If the Fates
                  Haue spun my thred, and my spent-clue of life
                  Be now vntwisted, let vs part like friends.
                  Lay vp my weapon, Trollio, and be gone.
               
               
                  Trol.
                  Yes Sir, with all my heart.—
               
               Exit. Trollio
               
                  Mel.
                  This friend and I will walke, and gabble wisely.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  I allow the motion: On.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  So Polititians thriue,
                  That with their crabbed faces, and sly tricks
                  Legerdemayne, ducks, cringes, formall beards,
                  Crisp'd haires, and punctuall cheats, do wriggle in
                  Their heads first, like a Foxe, to roomes of State,
                  Then the whole body followes.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Then they fill Lordships, steale womens hearts: with them and their's the world runnes round, yet these are square men still.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  There are none poore, but such as ingrosse offices.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  None wise; but vnthrifts, bankrupts, beggers, Rascals.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  The hangman is a rare Phisician.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Thats not so good, it shalbe granted.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  All the buz of Drugs, and Myneralls and Simples,
                  
                     Bloud-lettings, Vomits, Purges, or what else
                  Is coniur'd vp by men of Art, to gull
                  Liege-people, and reare golden piles, are trash
                  To a well-strong-wrought halter; there the Coute,
                  The stone, yes and the Melancholy deuill,
                  Are cur'd in lesse time then a paire of minutes.
                  Build me a Gallows in this very plot,
                  And Ile dispatch your businesse.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Fix the knot right vnder the left eare.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Sirra, make ready.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Yet doe not be too sudden, grant me leaue,
                  To giue a farewell to a creature long
                  Absented from me, tis a daughter (Sir)
                  Snatcht from me in her youth, a handsome girle,
                  Shee comes to aske a blessing.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Pray where is shee? I cannot see her yet.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  Shee makes more haste
                  In her quicke prayers then her trembling steppes,
                  Which many griefes haue weakened.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Cruell man!
                  How canst thou rip a heart, that's cleft already
                  With iniuries of time? whilst I am franticke,
                  Whilst throngs of rude diuisions huddle on,
                  And doe difranke my braines from peace, and sleepe;
                  So long I am insensible of cares.
                  As balls of wild-fire may be safely toucht,
                  Not violently sundred, and throwne vp;
                  So my distemper'd thoughts rest in their rage,
                  Not hurryed in the Ayre of repetition,
                  Or memory of my misfortunes past.
                  Then are my griefes strooke home,
                  When they are reclaym'd,
                  To their owne pitty of themselues—Proceed;
                  
                     What of your daughter now?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  I cannot tell yee,
                  Tis now out of my head againe; my braines
                  Are crazie; I haue scarce slept one sound sleepe
                  These twelue moneths.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  'las poore man; canst thou imagine
                  To prosper in the taske thou tak'st in hand,
                  By practising a cure vpon my weakenesse,
                  And yet be no Physician for thy selfe?
                  Goe, goe, turne ouer all thy bookes once more,
                  And learne to thriue in modesty; for impudence
                  Does least become a Scholer. Thou art a foole,
                  A kind of learned foole.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  I doe confesse it.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  If thou canst wake with me, forget to eate,
                  Renounce the thought of Greatnesse; tread on Fate;
                  Sigh out a lamentable tale of things
                  Done long agoe, and ill done; and when sighes
                  Are wearied, piece vp what remaines behind,
                  With weeping eyes, and hearts that bleed to death:
                  Thou shalt be a companion fit for me,
                  And we will sit together like true friends,
                  And neuer be deuided. With what greedinesse
                  Doe I hug my afflictions? there's no mirth
                  Which is not truly season'd with some madnesse.
                  As for example.—
               
               Exit.
               
                  Cora.
                  What new Crochet next?
                  There is so much sence in this wilde distraction,
                  That I am almost out of my wits too,
                  To see and heare him: some few houres more
                  Spent here, would turne me Apish, if not frantick.
                  Enter Meleander and Cleophyla.
                  In all the volumes thou hast turn'd, thou Man
                  
                  
                     Of knowledge, hast thou met with any rarity,
                  Worthy thy contemplation like to this?
                  The modell of the Heauens, the Earth, the Waters,
                  The harmony, and sweet consent of times,
                  Are not of such an excellence, in forme
                  Of their Creation, as the infinite wonder
                  That dwelles within the compasse of this face:
                  And yet I tell thee, Scholer, vnder this
                  Well-ord'red signe, is lodg'd such an obedience,
                  As will hereafter in another age,
                  Strike all comparison into a silence.
                  She had a Sister too: but as for her,
                  If I were giuen to talke, I coo'd describe
                  A pretty piece of goodnesse: let that passe—
                  We must be wise somtimes: What would you with her?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  I with her! nothing by your leaue, Sir, I:
                  It is not my profession.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  You are sawcy,
                  And as I take it, scuruy in your sawcinesse,
                  To vse no more respect—good soule, be patient:
                  We are a paire of things the world doth laugh at:
                  Yet be content, Cleophila; those clouds
                  Which barre the Sunne from shining on our miseries,
                  Will neuer be chac'd off till I am dead;
                  And then some charitable soule will take thee
                  Into protection. I am hasting on,
                  The time cannot be long.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  I doe beseech yee,
                  Sir, as you loue your health, as you respect
                  My safety, let not passion ouerrule you.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  It shall not, I am friends with all the world.
                  Get me some wine, to witnesse that I will be
                  An absolute good fellow, I will drinke with thee.
               
               
                  
                  Cora.
                  Haue you prepar'd his Cup?
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Tis in readinesse.
               
               Enter Cuculus and Grilla.
               
                  Cucul.
                  By your leaue, Gallants, I come to speake with a young Lady, as they say, the old Troianes daughter of the house.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Your businesse with my Lady daughter, Tosse-pot?
               
               
                  Gril.
                  Tosse-pot? O base! Tosse-pot?
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Peace; do'st not see in what case he is? I would doe my owne commendations to her; that's all.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Doe, come my Genius, we will quaffe in wine
                  Till we grow wise.
               
               
                  Cora.
                  True Nectar is diuine.
               
               Exit Mel. &amp; Cora.
               
                  Cucul.
                  So, I am glad he is gone. Page, walke aside. Sweet Beauty, I am sent Embassadour from the Mistris of my thoughts, to you, the Mistris of my desires.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  So Sir, I pray be briefe.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  That you may know, I am not as they say, an Animall; which is as they say, a kinde of Cokes, which is as the learned terme, an Asse, a Puppy, a Widgin, a Dolt, a Noddy, a—
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  As you please.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Pardon me for that, it shall be as you please indeed. Forsooth I loue to be courtly, and in fashion.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Well, to your Embasie; what, or from whom?
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Marry what is more then I know? for to know what's what, is to know what's what, and for what's what: but these are foolish figures, and to little purpose.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  From whom then are you sent?
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  There you come to me agen: O, to bee in the fauour of great Ladies, is asmuch to say, as to be great in Ladies fauours.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Good time a day t'ee; I can stay no longer.
               
               
                  
                  Cucul.
                  By this light but you must, for now I come toot. The most excellent, most wise, most dainty, precious, louing, kinde, sweet, intolerably faire Lady Thamasta commends to your little hands, this letter of importance. By your leaue, let me first kisse and then deliuer it in fashion, to your owne proper beauty.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  To me from her? Tis strange; I dare peruse it.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Good, O that I had not resolu'd to liue a single life! Heer's temptation able to coniure vp a spirit with a witnesse. So so: she has read it.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Is't possible? Heauen, thou art great and bountiful.
                  Sir, I much thanke your paines: and to the Princesse,
                  Let my loue, duty, seruice, be remembred.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  They shall Mad-dame.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  When we of hopes, or helpes, are quite bereauen,
                  Our humble pray'rs haue entrance into heau'n.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Thats my opinion cleerely and without doubt.
               
               Exit.
               Enter Aretas and Sophronos.
               
                  Aret.
                  The Prince is throughly mou'd.
               
               
                  Sophron.
                  I neuer saw him so much distemp'red.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  What should this young man bee,
                  Or whither can he be conuay'd?
               
               
                  Sophr.
                  Tis to me a mystery, I vnderstand it not.
               
               
                  Aret.
                  Nor I.
               
               Enter Prince Amethus and Pelias.
               
                  Prince
                  Yee haue consented all to worke vpon
                  The softnesse of my nature; but take heede:
                  Though I can sleepe in silence, and looke on
                  The mockery yee make of my dull patience;
                  Yet'ee shall know, the best of yee, that in mee
                  There is a masculin, a stirring spirit;
                  
                     Which prouokt, shall like a bearded Comet
                  Set yee at gaze, and threaten horrour.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Good Sir.
               
               
                  Prin.
                  Good Sir. Tis not your actiue wit or language,
                  Nor your graue politicke wisdomes (Lords) shall dare
                  To check-mate and controle my iust commands.
                  Enter Menaphon.
                  Where is the Youth your friend? is be found yet?
               
               
                  Men.
                  Not to be heard of.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Flye then to the desart,
                  Where thou didst first encounter this Fantasticke,
                  This airie apparition; come no more
                  In sight: Get yee all from me; he that stayes,
                  Is not my friend.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  Tis strange.
               
               
                  Aret. Soph.
                  We must obey.
               
               Exeunt all but the Prince.
               
                  Prince.
                  Some angry power, cheates with rare delusions,
                  My credulous sense: the very soule of Reason
                  Is troubled in me—the Physician
                  Presented a strange Maske, the view of it
                  Puzzl'd my vnderstanding: but the Boy—
                  Enter Rhetias.
                  
                     Rhetias, thou art acquainted with my griefes,
                  
                     Parthenophill is lost, and I would see him;
                  For he is like to some thing I remember
                  A great while since, a long, long time agoe.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  I haue been diligent (Sir) to pry into euery corner for discouery, but cannot meet with him: There is some tricke I am confident.
               
               
                  Prin.
                  There is, there is some practice, sleight or plot.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  I haue apprehended a faire Wench, in an odde
                  Priuate lodging in the Citie, as like the Youth
                  In face, as can by possibility be discern'd.
               
               
                  
                  Prince.
                  How Rhetias!
                  
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  If it be not Parthenophill in long coates,
                  Tis a spirit in his likenesse; answer
                  I can get none from her; you shall see her.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  The young man in disguise vpon my life,
                  To steale out of the Land.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Ile send him t'ee.
                  Exit Rhet.
                  Enter Eroclea in womans attire, and listens.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Doe, doe my Rhetias. As there is by nature
                  In euery thing created contrarietie:
                  So likewise is there vnity and league
                  Betweene them in their kind; but Man, the abstract
                  Of all perfection, which the workmanship
                  Of Heauen hath model'd, in himselfe containes
                  Passions of seuerall qualitie, the musicke
                  Of mans faire composition best accords,
                  When tis in consort, not in single straines.
                  My heart has been vntun'd these many moneths,
                  Wanting her presence, in whose equall loue
                  True harmony consisted; liuing here
                  We are Heau'ns bounty all, but Fortunes exercise.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Minutes are numbred by the fall of Sands;
                  As by an houre-glasse, the span of time
                  Doth waste vs to our graues, and we looke on it.
                  An age of pleasures reuel'd out, comes home
                  At last, and ends in sorrow, but the life
                  Weary of ryot, numbers euery Sand,
                  Wayling in sighes, vntill the last drop downe,
                  So to conclude calamity in rest.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  What Eccho yeelds a voyce to my complaints?
                  Can I be no where priuate?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Let the substance
                  As suddenly be hurried from your eyes,
                  
                     As the vaine sound can passe your eare,
                  If no impression of a troth vow'd yours, Kneeles.
                  
                  Retaine a constant memory.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Stand vp; tis not the figure stampt vpon thy cheekes,
                  The coozenage of thy beauty, grace, or tongue,
                  Can draw from me a secret, that hath been
                  The onely lewell of my speechlesse thoughts.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  I am so worne away with feares and sorrowes,
                  So wintred with the tempests of affliction,
                  That the bright Sunne of your life-quickning presence
                  Hath scarce one beame of force, to warme againe
                  That spring of chearefull comfort, which youth once
                  Apparel'd in fresh lookes.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Cunning Impostor,
                  Vntruth hath made thee subtle in thy trade:
                  If any neighbouring Greatnesse hath seduc'd
                  A free-borne resolution, to attempt
                  Some bolder act of treachery, by cutting
                  My weary dayes off. Wherefore (Cruell-mercy)
                  Hast thou assum'd a shape, that would make treason
                  A piety, guilt pardonable, blood-shed
                  As holy as the sacrifice of peace?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  The Incense of my loue-desires, are slam'd
                  Vpon an Altar of more constant proofe.
                  Sir, O Sir, turne me backe into the world,
                  Command me to forget my name, my birth,
                  My Fathers sadnesse, and my death aliue,
                  If all remembrance of my Faith hath found
                  A buriall, without pitie in your scorne.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  My scorne (disdainefull Boy) shall soone vnweaue
                  The web thy Art hath twisted: cast thy shape off,
                  Disroabe the mantle of a fained Sex,
                  And so I may be gentle; as thou art,
                  
                     There's witch-craft in thy language, in thy face,
                  In thy demeanors; turne, turne from me (prethee)
                  For my beliefe is arm'd else. Yet (faire subtilty)
                  Before we part (for part we must) be true,
                  Tell me thy Countrey.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  
                     Cyprus.
                  
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Ha: thy Father.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  
                     Meleander.
                  
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Hast a name?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  A name of misery, the vnfortunate Eroclea.
                  
               
               
                  Prince.
                  There is danger
                  In this seducing counterfeit, great goodnesse!
                  Hath honesty and vertue left the time?
                  Are we become so impious, that to tread
                  The path of impudence, is Law and Iustice?
                  Thou vizard of a beauty euer sacred,
                  Giue me thy name.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Whil'st I was lost to memory,
                  
                     Parthenophill did shrowd my shame in change
                  Of sundry rare misfortunes: but since now
                  I am, before I dye, return'd to claime
                  A Conuoy to my graue, I must not blush
                  To let Prince Pallador (if I offend,)
                  Know when he doomes me, that he doomes Eroclea.
                  
                  I am that wofull Maid.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Ioyne not too fast
                  Thy penance, with the story of my suffrings.
                  So dwelt simplicity with virgin truth;
                  So Martyrdome and holinesse are twins,
                  As innocence and sweetnesse on thy tongue.
                  But let me by degrees collect my senses,
                  I may abuse my trust. Tell me, what ayre
                  Hast thou perfum'd, since Tyranny first rauisht
                  
                     The contract of our hearts?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Deare Sir, in Athens haue I been buried.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Buried! Right, as I
                  In Cyprus.—Come to triall, if thou beest
                  
                     Eroclea, in my bosome I can finde thee.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  As I, Prince Palador, in mine: This gift
                  She shewes him a Tablet.
                  His bounty blest me with, the onely physicke
                  My solitary cares haue hourely tooke,
                  To keepe me from despaire.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  We are but Fooles
                  To trifle in disputes, or vainely struggle
                  With that eternall mercy which protects vs.
                  Come home, home to my heart, thou banisht-peace,
                  
                  My extasie of ioyes would speake in passion,
                  But that I would not lose that part of man,
                  Which is reseru'd to intertaine content.
                  
                     Eroclea, I am thine; O let me seize thee
                  As my inheritance. Hymen shall now
                  Set all his Torches burning, to giue light
                  Throughout this Land, new settled in thy welcome.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  You are still gracious. Sir, how I haue liu'd,
                  By what meanes been conuey'd, by what preseru'd,
                  By what return'd; Rhetias, my trusty seruant,
                  Directed by the wisdome of my Vncle,
                  The good Sophronos, can informe at large.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Enough, in stead of Musicke, euery night
                  To make our sleepes delightfull, thou shalt cloze
                  Our weary eyes with some part of thy story.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  O but my Father!
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Feare not: to behold
                  
                     Eroclea safe, will make him young againe;
                  It shall be our first taske. Blush sensuall follies,
                  
                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
                     A Cast-away, a poore despised Maid,
                  Onely for me to hope was almost sinne,
                  Yet troth I neuer tempted him.
               
               
                  Tha.
                  Chide not the grossenes of my trespasse (louely Sweetnes)
                  In such an humble language, I haue smarted
                  Already in the wounds, my pride hath made
                  Vpon thy sufferings. Henceforth tis in you
                  To worke my happinesse.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Call any seruice
                  Of mine a debt, for such it is; the Letter
                  You lately sent me, in the blest contents
                  It made me priuy to, hath largely quitted
                  Euery suspition of your Grace or goodnesse.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Let me imbrace thee with a Sisters loue,
                  A Sisters loue, Cleophila: for should
                  My Brother henceforth study to forget
                  The vowes that he hath made thee, I would euer
                  Sollicite thy deserts.
               
               Enter Amethus and Menaphon.
               
                  Ame.
                  We must haue entrance.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  Must? Who are they say, must? you are vnmannerly.
                  Brother is't you, and you too, Sir?
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Your Ladiship has had a time of
                  Scolding to your humour:
                  Does the storme hold still?
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Neuer fell a showre
                  More seasonably gentle on the barren
                  Parcht thirsty earth, then showres of courtesie
                  Haue from this Princesse been distilled on me,
                  To make my growth in quiet of my mind
                  Secure and lasting.
               
               
                  Tham.
                  You may both beleeue that I was not vnciuill.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  Pish, I know her spirit, and her enuy.
               
               
                  
                  Cleo.
                  Now in troth, Sir,
                  Pray credit me, I doe not vse to sweare▪
                  
                  The vertuous Princesse hath in words and carriage
                  Been kind, so ouer-kind, that I doe blush:
                  I am not rich enough in thankes sufficient
                  For her vnequall'd bounty.—My good Cousin,
                  I haue a suite to you.
               
               
                  Men.
                  It shall be granted.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  That no time, no perswasion, no respects
                  Of Iealousies past, present, or hereafter
                  By possibilitie to be conceiued,
                  Draw you from that sincerity and purenesse
                  Of loue, which you haue oftentimes protested
                  To this great worthy Lady she deserues
                  A duty more, then what the tyes of Marriage
                  Can claime, or warrant: be for euer hers,
                  As she is yours, and Heauen increase your comforts.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  
                     Clophila hath play'd the Church-mans part,
                  Ile not forbid the Banes.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Are you consented?
               
               
                  Tha.
                  I haue one taske in charge first, which concernes me.
                  Brother, be not more cruell then this Lady,
                  She hath forgiuen my follies, so may you:
                  Her youth, her beauty, innocence, discretion,
                  Without additions of estate or birth,
                  Are dower for a Prince indeed. You lou'd her;
                  For sure you swore you did: else if you did not
                  Here fixe your heart, and thus resolue, if now
                  You misse this Heauen on earth, you cannot find
                  In any other choice ought but a hell.
               
               
                  Ame.
                  The Ladies are turn'd Lawyers, and pleade handsomely
                  Their Clients cases. I am an easie Iudge,
                  And so shalt thou be Menaphon. I giue thee
                  
                     My Sister for a wise; a good one, friend.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Lady, will you confirme the gift?
               
               
                  Tham.
                  The errors of my mistaken iudgement being lost,
                  To your remembrance, I shall euer striue
                  In my obedience to deserue your pity.
               
               
                  Men.
                  My loue, my care, my all.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  What rests for me?
                  I'm still a Batchelor: Sweet Maid, resolue me,
                  May I yet call you mine?
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  My Lord Amethus,
                  
                  Blame not my plainenesse, I am young and simple,
                  And haue not any power to dispose
                  Mine owne will without warrant from my father:
                  That purchast, I am yours.
               
               
                  Amet.
                  It shall suffice me.
               
               Enter Cuculus, Pelias, Trollio and Grilla pluckt in by 'em.
               
                  Cucul.
                  Reuenge, I must haue reuenge; I will haue reuenge bitter and abominable reuenge; I will haue reuenge. This vnfashionable Mungrill, this Linsey-woolsey of mortality by this hand, Mistris, this shee-Roague is drunke, and clapper-clawd me without any reuerence to my person, or good garments, why d'ee not speake, Gentlemen.
               
               
                  Pel.
                  Some certaine blowes haue past, and't like your Highnesse.
               
               
                  Troll.
                  Some few knocks of Friendship, some loue-toyes, some Cuffes in kindnesse, or so.
               
               
                  Gril.
                  Ile turne him away, he shall bee my Master no longer.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Is this your she-Page, Cuculus? tis a Boy, sure.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  A Boy, an arrant Boy in long coates.
               
               
                  Troll.
                  He has mumbled his nose, that tis as big as a

great Cod peece.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Oh thou Cock vermine of iniquity.
               
               
                  Tha.
                  
                     Pelias, take hence the wag and schoole him for't.
                  For your part, seruant, Ile intreate the Prince
                  To grant you some fit place about his Wardrobe.
               
               
                  Cucul.
                  Euer after a bloody nose do I dreame of good lucke.
                  I horribly thanke your Ladiship.
                  Whil'st I'm in office, the old garbe shall agen
                  Grow in request, and Taylors shall be men.
                  Come Trollio, helpe to wash my face, prethee.
               
               
                  Trol.
                  Yes, and to scowre it too.—
               
               Exit Cuculus, Trollio, Pelias, Grill.
               Enter Rhetias, Corax.
               
                  Rhet.
                  The Prince and Princesse are at hand, giue ouer your amorous Dialogues. Most honor'd Lady, henceforth forbeare your sadnesse: are you ready to practise your instructions?
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  I haue studied
                  My part with care, and will performe it (Rhetias)
                  With all the skill I can.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Ile passe my word for her.
               
               Florish. Enter Prince, Sophronus, Aretius, and Eroclea.
               
                  Prince.
                  Thus Princes should be circled with a guard
                  Of truly noble friends, and watchfull subiects.
                  O Rhetias, thou art iust; the Youth thou told'st me.
                  That liu'd at Athens, is returnd at last
                  To her owne fortunes, and contracted I oue.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  My knowledge made me sure of my report, Sir.
               
               
                  
                  Prince.
                  
                     Eroclea, cleare thy feares, when the Sun shines,
                  Clouds must not dare to muster in the skie,
                  Nor shal they here—Why do they kneele? Stand vp,
                  The day and place is priuiledg'd.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  Your presence, Great Sir, makes euery roome a Sanctuary.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Wherefore does this young virgin vse such circumstance,
                  In duty to vs? Rise.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Tis I must raise her.
                  Forgiue me, Sister, I haue been too priuate,
                  In hiding from your knowledge any secret
                  That should haue been in common twixt our soules:
                  But I was rul'd by councell.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  That I shew my selfe a Girle (Sister) and bewray
                  Ioy in too soft a passion'fore all these,
                  I hope you cannot blame me.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  We must part:
                  The sudden meeting of these two faire Riuolets
                  With th' Iland of our armes, Cleophila,
                  
                  The custome of thy piety hath built
                  Euen to thy younger yeeres a Monument
                  Of memorable Fame; some great reward
                  Must wait on thy desert.
               
               
                  Soph.
                  The Prince speakes t'ee, Neece.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Chat low, I pray; let's about our businesse.
                  The good old man awakes: my Lord, with-draw;
                  
                     Rhetias, let's settle here the Coach.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Away then.
               
               Exit.
               Soft Musicke. Enter Melander (in a Coach) his haire and beard trimb, habit and gowne chang'd. Rhetias and Corax, and Boy that sings.
               
                  
                  The Song.
                  Fly hence, shadowes, that doe keep
                  Watchfull sorrowes, charm'd in sleepe;
                  Though the Eyes be ouertaken,
                  Yet the Heart doth euer waken
                  Thoughts, chain'd vp in busie snares
                  Of continuall woes and cares:
                  Loue and griefes are so exprest,
                  As they rather sigh then rest.
                  Fly hence, shadowes, that doe keepe
                  Watchfull sorrowes, charm'd in sleepe.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Where am I? Ha? What sounds are these? Tis day, sure.
                  Oh, I haue slept belike: tis but the foolery
                  Of some beguiling dreame. So, so, I will not
                  Trouble the play of my delighted Fancy
                  But dreame my dreame out.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Morrow to your Lordship:
                  You tooke a iolly nap, and slept it soundly.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Away, beast, let me alone.
               
               Cease musicke.
               
                  Cora.
                  O, by your leaue, Sir.
                  I must be bold to raise yee, else your Phisicke
                  Will turne to further sicknes.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Phisick, Beare-leech?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Yes phisick, you are mad.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  
                     Trollio, Cleophila.
                  
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Sir, I am here.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  I know thee, Rhetias, prethee rid the roome
                  Of this tormenting noyse. He tells me, sirra.
                  I haue tooke phisick, Rhetias, phisicke, phisicke.
               
               
                  
                  Rhet.
                  Sir true, you haue; and this most learned Scholer
                  Apply'd t'ee. O you were in dangerous plight
                  Before he tooke ye hand.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  These things are drunke,
                  Directly drunke. Where did you get your liquor?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  I neuer saw a body in the wane
                  Of age, so ouer spred with seuerall sorts
                  Of such diseases as the strength of Youth
                  Would groane vnder and sinke.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  The more your glory in the miraculous cure.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Bring me the Cordiall
                  Prepar'd for him to take after his sleepe,
                  Twill doe him good at heart.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  I hope it will, Sir.
               
               Exit.
               
                  Mel.
                  What do'st think I am, that thou should'st fiddle
                  So much vpon my patience? Foole, the waight
                  Of my disease sits on my heart so heauy,
                  That all the hands of Art cannot remoue
                  One graine to ease my griefe. If thou cood'st poyson
                  My memory, or wrap my senses vp
                  Into a dulnesse, hard and cold as Flints?
                  If thou cood'st make me walke, speake, eate and laugh
                  Without a sense or knowledge of my faculties,
                  Why then perhaps at Marts thou might'st make benefit
                  Of such an Anticke motion, and get credit
                  From credulous gazers, but not profit me.
                  Study to gull the wise; I am too simple
                  To be wrought on.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Ile burne my bookes (old man)
                  But I will doe thee good, and quickly too.
               
               Enter Aretus with a Patent.
               
                  Aret.
                  Most honor'd Lord Meleander, our great Master,
                  
                     Prince Palador of Cyprus, hath by me
                  Sent you this Patent, in which is contain'd
                  Not onely confirmation of the Honors
                  You formerly enioyed, but the addition
                  Of the Marshalship of Cyprus, and ere long
                  He meanes to visit you. Excuse my haste,
                  I must attend the Prince.—
               
               Exit.
               
                  Cor.
                  There's one Pill workes.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Do'st know that spirit? tis a graue familiar,
                  And talkt I know not what.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Hee's like, me thinks, the Prince his Tutor, Aretus.
                  
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Yes, yes; it may be I haue seene such a formality;
                  No matter where, or when.
               
               Enter Amethus with a Staffe.
               
                  Amet.
                  The Prince hath sent ye
                  (My Lord) this Staffe of Office, and withall
                  Salutes you Grand Commander of the Ports
                  Throughout his Principalities. He shortly
                  Will visit you himselfe: I must attend him.—
               
               Exit.
               
                  Cor.
                  D'ee feele your physick stirring yet?
               
               
                  Mel.
                  A Diuell is a rare Iuggler, and can cheate the eye,
                  But not corrupt the reason in the Throne
                  Of a pure soule.—Another? I will stand thee,
                  Be what thou canst, I care not.
               
               Enter Sophronus with a Tablet.
               
                  Soph.
                  From the Prince, deare Brother, I present you this rich Relique,
                  A Iewell he hath long worne in his bosome:
                  Henceforth he bade mee say, he does beseech you
                  
                     To call him sonne, for he will call you Father.
                  It is an honor (brother) that a subiect
                  Cannot but intertaine with thankfull pray'rs.
                  Be moderate in your loyes, he will in person
                  Confirme my errand, but commands my seruice.
               
               Exit.
               
                  Cora.
                  What hope now of your Cure?
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Stay, stay—What Earthquakes
                  Roule in my flesh? here's Prince, and Prince and Prince;
                  Prince vpon Prince: the dotage of my sorrowes
                  Reuells in magick of ambitious scorne,
                  Be they Inchantments deadly (as the graue)
                  Ile looke vpon'em: Patent, staffe, and Relick
                  To the last first. Round me, ye guarding ministers
                  And euer keepe me waking till the Cliffes
                  That ouer hang my sight fall off, and leaue
                  These hollow spaces to be cram'd with dust.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Tis time I see to fetch the Cordiall. Prethee
                  Sit downe: Ile instantly be here againe—
               
               Exit.
               
                  Mel.
                  Good, giue me leaue, I will sit downe indeed:
                  Here's Company enough for me to prate to,
               
               
                  Eroclea.
                  Tis the same, the cunning Artsman
                  Faultred not in a line. Coo'd he haue fashen'd
                  A little hollow space here, and blowne breath
                  To haue made it moue, and whispher, 't had bin excellent.
                  But faith, tis well, tis very well as tis.
                  Passing, most passing well.
               
               Enter Cleophila, Eroclea, Rhetias.
               
                  Cleo.
                  The soueraigne Greatnesse,
                  Who, by Commission from the powers of heauen,
                  Swayes both this Land and vs, our gracious Prince,
                  By me presents you (Sir) with this large bounty,
                  
                     A gift more precious to him then his birth-right.
                  Here let your cares take end; now set at liberty
                  Your long imprison'd heart, and welcome home
                  The solace of your soule, too long kept from you.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Deare Sir, you know me.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Yes, thou art my Daughter:
                  My eldest blessing. Know thee? Why Eroclea,
                  
                  I neuer did forget thee in thy absence.
                  Poore soule, how do'st?
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  The best of my well-being consists in yours.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Stand vp: the gods who hitherto
                  Haue kept vs both aliue, preserue thee euer.
               
               
                  Cleophila▪
                  
                  I thanke thee and the Prince,
                  I thanke thee too, Eroclea, that thou would'st
                  In pitie of my age, take so much paines
                  To liue, till I might once more looke vpon thee,
                  Before I broke my heart: O twas a piece
                  Of piety and duty vnexampled.
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  The good-man rellisheth his comforts strangely,
                  The sight doth turne me child.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  I haue not words that can expresse my ioyes.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Nor I.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Nor I: yet let vs gaze on one another freely,
                  And surfet with our eyes; let me be plaine,
                  If I should speake as much as I should speake,
                  I should talke of a thousand things at once,
                  And all of thee, of thee (my child) of thee:
                  My teares like ruffling winds lockt vp in Caues,
                  Doe bustle for a vent—on t'other side,
                  To flye out into mirth were not so comely.
                  Come hither, let me kisse thee—with a pride,
                  Strength, courage, and fresh blood, which now thy presence
                  Hath stor'd me with, I kneele before their Altars,
                  
                     Whose soueraignty kept guard about thy safety.
                  Aske, aske thy Sister (prethee) shee'le tell thee
                  How I haue been much mad.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  Much discontented,
                  Shunning all meanes that might procure him comfort.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  Heauen ha's at last been gracious.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  So say I but wherefore crop thy words in such a sloth,
                  As if thou wert afraid to mingle truth.
                  With thy misfortunes? Vnderstand me throughly,
                  I would not haue thee to report at large
                  From point to point, a Iournall of thy absence:
                  T'will take vp too much time, I would securely
                  Ingrosse the little remnant of my life,
                  That thou might'st euery day be telling somewhat,
                  Which might conuay me to my rest with comfort.
                  Let me be thinke me, how we parted first:
                  Puzzles my faint remembrance—But soft,
               
               
                  Cleophila,
                  thou toldst me, that the Prince
                  Sent me this present.
               
               
                  Cleo.
                  From this own faire hands I did receiue my Sister.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  To requite him, we will not dig his Fathers graue anew,
                  Although the mention of him much concernes
                  The businesse we inquire of—as I said,
                  We parted in a hurry at the Court,
                  I to this Castle, after made my layle.
                  But whither thou, deare heart?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Now they fall too't, I lookt for this.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  I by my Vncles care (Sophronos
                     ▪ my good Vncle) suddenly was like a Saylers Boy conuey'd a shipboord that euery night.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  A policie quicke and strange.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  The ship was bound for Corinth, whither first
                  Attended onely with your seruant Rhetias,
                  
                  
                     And all fit necessaries, we arriu'd:
                  From thence in habit of a youth we iourney'd
                  To Athens, where till our returne of late,
                  Haue we liu'd safe.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Oh what a thing is man,
                  To bandy factions of distemp'red passions,
                  Against the sacred prouidence aboue him?
                  Here in the Legend of thy two yeeres exile,
                  Rare pity and delight are sweetly mixt,
                  And still thou wert a Boy.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  So I obey'd my Vncles wise command.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Twas safely carried, I humbly thanke thy Fate.
               
               
                  Eroc.
                  If earthly treasures
                  Are powr'd in plenty downe from Heau'n on mortals;
                  They reigne amongst those Oracles, that flow
                  In Scholes of sacred knowledge; such is Athens:
                  
                  Yet Athens was to me but a faire prison:
                  The thoughts of you, my Sister, Country, Fortunes,
                  And something of the Prince, barr'd all contents,
                  Which else might rauish sence: for had not, Rhetias,
                  
                  Been alwaies comfortable to me, certainely
                  Things had gone worse.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Speake low Eroclea;
                  That something of the Prince beares danger in it:
                  Yet thou hast trauayl'd (Wench) for such Indowments,
                  As might create a Prince a wife fit for him,
                  Had he the World to guide: but touch not there;
                  How cam'st thou home?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Sir, with your Noble sauour,
                  Kissing your hand first, that point I can answer.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Honest, right honest Rhetias.
                  
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Your graue Brother
                  Perceiu'd with what a hopelesse loue his sonne,
                  
                     Lord Menaphon, too eagerly pursu'd
                  
                     Thamasta, Cousin to our present Prince;
                  And to remoue the violence of affection,
                  Sent him to Athens, where for twelue moneths space
                  Your daughter, my young Lady and her Cousin
                  Enioy'd each others griefes, till by his Father
                  The Lord Sophronos we were all call'd home.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  Enough, enough, the world shall henceforth witnesse
                  My thankfulnes to Heauen, and those people
                  Who haue been pitifull to me and mine.
                  Lend me a Looking-glasse—How now? How came I
                  So courtly in fresh rayments?
               
               
                  Rhet.
                  Here's the Glasse, Sir.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  I'm in the trim too.—O Cleophila,
                  
                  This was the goodnesse of thy care and cunning.—
                  Whence comes this noyse?
               
               Loud Musicke.
               
                  Rhet.
                  The Prince my Lord in person.
               
               Enter Prince, Sophronos, Aretas, Amethus, Menaphon, Thamasta, Corax, Kala.
               
                  Prince.
                  Ye shall not kneele to vs; rise all, I charge ye:
                  Father, you wrong your age, henceforth my armes
                  And heart shall be your guard; we haue o're-heard
                  All passages of your vnited loues.
                  Be young againe, Meleander, liue to number
                  An happy generation, and dye old
                  In comforts as in yeeres. The Offices
                  And Honours which I late on thee conferr'd,
                  Are not fantasticke bounties, but thy merit;
                  Enioy them liberally.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  My teares must thanke ye, for my tongue cannot.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  I haue kept my promise, &amp; giuen you a sure cordial.
               
               
                  
                  Mel.
                  O, a rare one.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Good man, wee both haue shar'd enough of sadnes:
                  Though thine ha's tasted deeper of th'extreme;
                  Let vs forget it henceforth. Where's the picture
                  I sent yee? Keepe it, tis a counterfeit,
                  And in exchange of that, I ceaze on this,
                  The reall substance: with this other hand
                  I giue away before her Fathers face
                  His younger ioy, Cleophila, to thee
                  Cousin Amethus: take her, and be to her
                  More then a Father, a deseruing husband.
                  Thus rob'd of both thy children in a minute,
                  Thy cares are taken off.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  My braines are dull'd;
                  I am intranc'd, and know not what you meane:
                  Great, gracious Sir, alas, why do you mocke me?
                  I am a weake old man, so poore and seeble,
                  That my vntoward ioynts can scarcely creepe
                  Vnto the graue, where I must seeke my rest.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  
                     Eroclea was you know, contracted mine;
                  
                     Cleophila, my Cousins by consent
                  Of both their hearts: We both now claime our owne;
                  It onely rests in you to giue a blessing
                  For confirmation.
               
               
                  Rhetias.
                  Sir, tis truth and iustice.
               
               
                  Mel.
                  The gods that lent ye to me, blesse your vowes:
                  O Children, children, pay your prayers to Heauen,
                  For they haue shew'd much mercy. But Sophronos,
                  
                  Thou art my Brother: I can say no more:
                  A good, good Brother.
               
               
                  Prince.
                  Leaue the rest to time.
                  Cousin Thamasta, I must giue you too:
                  She's thy wife, Menaphon. Rhetias, for thee
                  
                     And Corax, I haue more then common thanks.
                  On, to the Temple; there all solemne Rites
                  Perform'd, a generall Feast shall be proclaim'd.
                  The Louers Melancholy hath found cure;
                  Sorrowes are chang'd to Bride-songs. So they thriue,
                  Whom Fate in spite of stormes hath kept aliue.
               
               Exuent omnes.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            EPILOGVE.
            TO be too confident, is as vniust
            In any Worke, as too much to distrust;
            Who from the lawes of study haue not sweru'd,
            Know, beg'd applauses neuer were deseru'd.
            
               We must submit to Censure: so doth He,
            
            Whose houres begot this issue; yet being free
            For his part, if He haue not pleas'd you, then
            In this kinde, hee'le not trouble you agen.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

