
   
      
         
            Plouto-mastix: the scourge of covetousnesse: or, An apologie for the publike good, against privacie A sermon preached at the assises in Deuon, at the command of the Lord Byshop of Exon, anno, 1630. By Thomas Foster, Master of Arts and rector of Farway.
            Foster, Thomas, b. 1590 or 91.
         
         
            
               1631
            
         
         Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01090
            STC 11202
            ESTC S102538
            99838315
            99838315
            2689
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01090)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2689)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 837:14)
         
         
            
               
                  Plouto-mastix: the scourge of covetousnesse: or, An apologie for the publike good, against privacie A sermon preached at the assises in Deuon, at the command of the Lord Byshop of Exon, anno, 1630. By Thomas Foster, Master of Arts and rector of Farway.
                  Foster, Thomas, b. 1590 or 91.
               
               [8], 26, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by B. Alsop and T. Favvcet, for Michaell Sparke the younger, and are to be sold at the Blew-Bible in Greene Arbor,
                  London :
                  1631.
               
               
                  First word of title in Greek characters.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
               Avarice --  Sermons.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            ΠΛΟΥΤΟ-ΜΑΣΤΙΞ:
THE SCOVRGE
OF
Covetouſneſſe:
OR,
An Apologie for the Publike Good,
against Privacie. A Sermon Preached at the Aſsiſes in
Devon, at the Command of the Lord Byſhop
of Exon, Anno, 1630. BY
THOMAS FOSTER, Maſter of Arts and
Rector of Farway.
            
            Avaro nihil Scelestius.
            Eccleſ. 10. 9.
            Bonum, quò Communius, eò melius.
            Ethic. lib. 1.
            LONDON,
Printed by B. ALSOP and T. FAVVCET, for Michaell
Sparke the younger, and are to be ſold at the
Blew-Bible in Greene Arbor.
1631.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONble.
Sr. THOMAS RICHARDSON,
Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of his Majeſties
Common Pleas: And Sir IOHN DENHAM, one of his
Majeſties Barons of the Exchequer; All
Health and Happineſſe, here and
hereafter.
            
               Right Honourable:
            
            
               I Will not ſay, Importunity of
friends hath preſt this Sermon
to the Preſſe: that's a Common
Plea; and implies a Tacit Commendation
of the owne worke;
which is not ſo commendable;
it beeing as great Wiſdome in
our ſufficiency, not to know our
ſelves, as, in our Wants to know
our ſelues. But I may boldly avouch, Ambition has no
hand in the Impreſſion. For had I beene that way affected
I have had time enough, to be a foole in print (as well as
ſome others) long ere now-Scribimus indocti, doctique. But
I have ever beene as deſirous to Suppreſſe my Labours, in
this kinde, as others to Preſſe theirs. The truth is, the
reaſon, why I have ventur'd to come on the Publike

ſtage, and to make my Meditations Legible, is, To ſee
whether I can finde more Charitable Readers of my
Well-meant Endeavours, then I had ſome Hearers; whoſe
unhappy Miſpriſion (making themſelves, occaſionally,
guilty) would have made me guilty of that, I neyther
ſpake, nor meant; (of that which I hate) A perſonall
Invective. Whereas it may appeare (upon ingenuous
peruſall) neither the Perſon, nor the Place, but the too-well
knowne Offence (Negligence) of ſome perſons in
thoſe Places, is inveighed againſt. I can truely ſay
with Saint Ierome-Nullum loeſi, nullius nomen mea Scriptura
deſignatum eſt: Neminem ſpecialiter meus ſermo pulſavit
(ad Nepot.) And the Poet tels me (I take it) diſcreetly,-Licuit,
ſemper
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   licebit.-Parcere perſonis, dicere de
vitijs. Whoſoever takes offence at this, it is-Scandalum
acceptum, indeed; and I ſuppoſe, he is no Competent
Auditor. For if guilty Conſciences, who are Parties
ſhould be admitted Iudges of Divine Reprehenſion, the
Pulpit ſhould bee counted a Paſquil; every admonition
thence (how diſcreetly-zealous ſoever) an invective
Defamation. Guilty Conſciences are like the Elephant:
which being conſcious of his owne Deformity, cannot
abide to ſee his Face in the cleare Springs, but ſeekes
for troubled and muddy Chanels, to drinke in; So
they, knowing their ſoules to be ſo filthy, that they
dare not view them in the cleare waters of Truth, and
Sincere Admonition, flee to the troubled Chanels of Cavillation,
and Contradiction▪ Arbitror te veritate ſuperatum,
ad detractionem, vitae meae, et maledicta converti, ſaith
Ierome, (Contra Helvid.) But-Qui volens, detrahit famae
meae, nolens addit mercedi, ſaith Auguſt. (Cont. Petil. lib. 3.
cap. 7.) And thus,-Quandiu aegri, indignantur, whiles

men are ſicke of Impenitencie, they are Impatient of reproofe;-Sed
ſanati, gratulantur, but being cur'd by
Repentance, they ſhake hands with the Monitor, and
thanke him, ſaith Auguſt. (Ad Feſt. Epiſt. 166.) Then
they will acknowledge, 'Tis better once ſmart, then ever
ake: And ſo a Galling truth ſhall have more thankes,
at the laſt, than a ſmoothing Supparaſitation,-Hee that rebuketh
a man, ſhall finde more favour, at the length, than hee
that flattereth with his tongue, (Prov. 28. 23.) But hee
that can, now, play with his Euphemiſmes and Eulogium's,
and cry,-Pax pax, when there is no peace, makes
the beſt muſicke in the eares of this ſecure Age. He that
bids the wicked AHABS,-Goe vp to Ramoth Gilead, and
proſper, (1. King. 22. 12.) is now the beſt Politician. Hee
that that can-Dawbe with vntempered morter, is counted
the beſt Architect of Soules. This they call, Good temper,
Mildneſſe, Diſcretion. This is the way, they ſay, to
ſleepe in whole skinne, to riſe to Preferment.-(Obſequium
amicos, veritas odium,) Such preferment God
ſend them, who love the praiſe of Men, more than the praiſe
of GOD. And-whether it be right in the ſight of God, to obey
men, rather than God, iudge yee. But what ſhall I ſay?
            Pro captu Lectoris habent ſua fata Libelli.
            As Bookes, ſo Sermons have their Credit or diſcredit
from the fancy of their Readers or Hearers. And it is ever
an eaſier matter to Diſlike, than to Doe the like.—Facilia
ſic putant omnes, quae iam facta; nec de ſalebris cogitant
vbi via ſtrata, (Lipſ.) If you come to an Inne in
Germany, and diſlike your fare, dyet, lodging, the Dutch
Hoſt tels you, in a ſurly tone,-Aliud tibi quaeras diverſorium,
(Eraſm. Dial.) Such is my reſolution: who likes
not this, may reade ſome other thing.
            
               
My Lords, I have not without Cauſe, Inſcrib'd this
Sermon unto your Names. Firſt, it was Preach'd in the
great Aſſembly, whereof your ſelves were a Principall
part. Secondly, Preach'd on that Subiect, wherein your
Places have a Principall intereſt; The Common Good of
Church and Common-weale. A Subiect as neceſſary
for thoſe Times, as the Times are Subiect to Neceſsity:
Private ends having brought the Publike Good, almoſt,
to it's End; and Hungry Coveteouſneſſe, like PHARAOH's
leane kine, devour'd this fat and flouriſhing Commonweale.
To you therefore (as being-Patres Patriae, and-Eccleſiae
Patroni) this Weake, but Well-meant Labour of
mine, flees for Patrociny and protection. I ſhall make it
my humble Suite, that you will be pleas'd to entertaine
it, as DAVID, lame MEPHI
                  •
               OSHETH, for his Father
IONATHAN's ſake. Lame it is in both feet. (Lame
in the Birth, by vnskilfull handling, lame in the Nurſing,
by uncharitable ſcanning) yet entertaine it for it's fathers
ſake, Your Country's ſake, whoſe Love begat it. I remember
that Apologue in the Talmud; the grapes in Babel,
ſent, upon a time, to the Vine-leaves, in Iudaea deſiring
them, to come and over-ſhadow them; otherwiſe the
heat would conſume them, and ſo they ſhould never
come to Maturity. Your Lordſhips may eaſily gueſſe
at the Mythology. If Learning be not ſheltred by thoſe,
who are in Eminent place, and if they caſt not their
Shadow over it, it will ſoone periſh; But where they favour
it, it proſpers. If the Spring bee cold, the Plants,
Herbes, and Bloſſomes are nipt and wither; But where
the Influence is ſeaſonable, there all things reviue, thrive,
flouriſh. So where Great Perſons are averſe from Learning,
the Spirits, which would otherwiſe, bloſſome, doe

wither and decay. But when it is upholden by men of
Higher place, it is like a Fountaine of Living Water. For
my part I cannot praiſe my Preſent otherwiſe, then by
the Truth of that heart, from which it proceeds:
which ſhall bee Ambitious of all occaſions, that may
teſtifie a Gratefull acknowledgement of your Lordſhips
undeſerved favours; and wherewith, I will daily Petition
the Lord of Lords for the continuance of your Happineſſe
and Welfare.
            
            
               Your Lordſhips moſt obſequious
Servant, in the Lord,
THO: FOSTER.
            
         
         
            
            SOme faults (by reaſon of haſt) are eſcaped in the
printing. Blame the Printer, excuſe the Author:
Whom deſires you to Correct judiciouſly, and Iudge
charitably—
            In multis offendimus omnes.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE
SCOVRGE OF
Covetouſneſſe.
            
               PHILIP. 2. 4.
               Looke not every man on his owne Things, but every man
alſo on the thinges of other men.
            
            
               IT is an old ſaying, verified by common
Experience,-Senes nimis ſunt
ad rem attenti: And-Avaritia
in ſene juveneſſet, Covetouſneſſe
raignes moſt in old age. Thus this
Old age of the world dotes too
much on the things of the world.
And our Apoſtle foretold it long
agoe,-In the laſt dayes, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
men ſhall be Covetous,
(2. Tim. 3. 1, 2.) Covetouſneſſe is a Diſeaſe fallen into
the legs of thoſe latter times; And our Saviour (the great
Phyſician of Soules) tels us, by a double Caveat, 'tis a dangerous
one (very Epidemicall)-Take heed, and beware of Covetouſneſſe,
(Luk. 12.) Dangerous to the Church, Commonwealth,
our ſelves, Avarus nulli bonus, ſibi peſſimus: The
Covetous, as he is good to no man, ſo he is worſt to himſelfe.
            
               
It is an ill Habit-Remedijs non cedens, medendo exaſperatur
(B
                        •
                     daeus.)
                It growes the worſe for Curing, it yeelds to no
remedies. But whoſoever is infected with it, cannot have a
more ſoveraigne Remedy, than is here preſcribed,-Looke not
every man on his owne thinges, &amp;c.
            
            The Remedy conſiſts of a double Direction, delivered in a
double Propoſition,—
            
               1. Negat.—Looke not every man, &amp;c.
               2. Affirmat.—But every man alſo, &amp;c.
            
            And both theſe Vniverſall.
            
               1. 
                     Ʋniverſall Negat.—Not every man, Id est (in Equipollency)
No man; Contrary, I confeſſe, to the rule of Logick—Non
omnis, id est, quidam; But the Hebrew phraſe, having
the Signe, [Non omnis] aequipoſſet vniverſaeli neganti, (Keck.
Siſt. Log. lib. 2. de Aequip.) Neyther is it ſimply Negat. but—ad
modum: It is not meant, a man ſhould not, at all, looke
on (regard, intend) his owne things; but not meerely, or
too much affect them.
               2. 
                     Ʋniverſall Affirmat. Thus-Let every man intend the
Mutuall good. The One, you ſee, forbids Covetouſneſſe, and
Privacy: the other commands publike Community.
            
            I hope I ſhall not need to make an Apologie for my Diviſion:
indeed I might have Torne my Text into more parts
by diviſion and ſubdiviſion. But I have learn'd of the learned
Artiſts, that a Dichotomy is, commonly, moſt commendable.
It is a Canon,-Omnis diviſio, debet eſſe bimembris, (Keck.)
And a Philoſophicall Maxime, Fruſtra ſit per plura, &amp;c. It is
true-Variet as delectat.
               In this I profeſſe my ſelfe a Diſciple to Apollonius: I labor wholly to informe my Hearers underſtanding, not to pleaſe his eare. But I deſire, rather to profit, than
to pleaſe. Therefore, in imitation of the beſt Methodiſt,
who contracted 10. Com. into two.—Deum &amp; proximum,
(Math. 22. 20.) God and our Neighbour, I have divided
the Text into two naturall parts. And indeed, what is
our whole Chriſtian profeſſion, but a Dichotomy? Didacticall,
Practicall: the one to informe the underſtanding, th'other,
to Reforme the Will. And the Practicall is a Dichotomy too,
expreſſed by the Pſal.Phil. lib. 8. vit Apol, Declina à malo, Fac bonum. Eſchew
Evill, doe Good. (Pſal. 34. 14.) And accordingly, it is

office, of the Miniſtery, Bona decere, Mala dedocere. (Auguſt.
de Doct. Chriſtum. Lib. 4. Cap. 3.) To perſwade to
Good, to diſſwade from Evill. Here you have both Evill and
Good: And if I can perſwade to the one, and diſſwade from
the other, I ſhall thinke this houre happily ſpent.
            And ſo I begin with the former, the 
                  Ʋniverſall Negat.
Looke not every man on his owne things. The Greeke Text
reades—
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : wherein two words
are Emphaticall. 1. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ; This intimates, that worldly
men thinke they have an abſolute Propriety in thoſe
Goods of Fortune; that they are their Owne; Gotten by
their Owne Providence, Kept by their owne Diligence; Their
Owne to uſe, their Owne to diſpoſe. Their Owne, and
Theirs onely. As though God had no right in them, eyther by
Donation, or Diſpoſition. As though they were-Domini,
not-Diſpenſatores; (a meere Solaeciſme in Divinity) The
Church, the Common-wealth, the Poore, their Neighbours,
in neceſſity, ſhall have no part nor portion in them; They
are-
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , their owne things. Hence their common
Proverbe—Shall I not doe with mine owne as I list? Which
can ſuite to no man, but him that is God and Man—Is it
not lawfull for me, to doe with mine owne as I will. (Math.
20. 15.) 2. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : Which ſignifies-Obſervare, Conſiderare,
animo volutare. To obſerve, Contemplate, and thinke
on; To denote the vehemency of theſe mens affection, to
thoſe earthly things. It doth them good to thinke on them,
muſe on them, Gaze on them-Simul &amp; nummos Contemplorin
arca, ſaith he in the Poet—Imm
                     •
                  ritur ſtudijs, &amp; amore
ſeneſcit habendi, ſaith AVGVST. (Lib. 3. de lib. Arbitr.)
And SALOMON Engliſhes it—The greateſt benefit, they have
of them, is to looke on them with their eyes. (Eccleſ. 5. 10.)-Cernere
divitias oculis: a notable pleonaſmus, to ſhew the
bent of their affection to earthly things; They are as it were
raviſht with the very ſight of them, as Narciſſus with the
ſight of his ſuppoſed-ſelfe—Adſtupet ipſe ſibi, vultu
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   immotus
eodem—Haeret (Metam. lib. 3.) Or as the Diſciples
were, with Contemplating the Temple-Quales Lapides,

quales ſtructurae? (Mark. 13. 1.) So doe theſe men—Looke
on their owne things.
            
            The point of Obſervation then, muſt needs be this—It is
not lawfull, it is not Chriſtian-like for any man, too much to love,
to like his owne Private. This is a common place, ſo copious,
that the moſt barren invention may be luxuriant in proofes,
precepts, examples, to verifie, amplifie, exemplifie the truth
of this Poſition. If you pleaſe to peruſe the ſacred volumes,
you ſhall finde Covetouſneſſe and Selfe-love, ranked among the
greateſt ſinnes, and the Marke of Gods Minacings. ISAIAH
thunders on it—Theſe greedy Dogs can never haue enough: for
they all looke to their owne way, every one for his advantage, and
for his owne purpoſe. (Iſa. 56. 11.) And-For his wicked
Covetouſneſſe I am angry with him. (Cap. 57. 17.) IEREM.
ſeconds him-Thine eyes and thy heart are but onely for thy
Covetouſneſſe. (Ier. 22. 17.) Ezechiel joynes-Thou haſt taken
Vſury, and the increaſe, and thou hast defrauded thy Neighbours
by extortion. Behold therefore I have ſmitten my hands upon thy
Covetouſneſſe. (Ezech. 22. 12, 13.) Comploſi manus: To
ſhew how God is incens'd againſt Covetouſneſſe: He wrings
his fiſt, and beats his hands-Ad modum iraſcentis, &amp; ultionem
minantis. (Carth. in loc.) HABACCVK is ſent with a
Proclamation againſt it-Ho, he that coveteth an evill Covetouſneſſe
to his houſe, that he may ſet his neſt on high. (Cap. 2. 9.)
Our Saviour makes it good with an oath-Amen dico vobis:
Verely I ſay unto you, that a rich man, (a Covetous rich man)
ſhall hardly enter, &amp;c. (Mat. 19. 23.) Our Apoſtle ſtrikes
it dead-No covetous perſon hath any inheritance in the Kingdome
of Christ, (Eph. 5. 5.) He will give you good reaſon
for it. 1. It is-Radix omnum malorum. (1. Tim. 6.)
And humane reaſon hath eſpyed as much-Indè ferè ſcelerum
cauſae. (Iuven. Sat. 14.) All wickedneſſe, almoſt, ſprings
from this Roote. Pride, Ambition, Oppreſſion, Fraud, Fallacy,
Iniury, Perjury, Luxury, Inhamanity, Ʋſury, Bribery,
Anxiety of Mind, Hardneſſe of heart, Contempt of GOD,
Neglect of Death, Hell, and Judgement. For theſe things are
not ſuffered to approach the ſight or ſence of Covetous

worldlings-O death how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a
man, that liveth at reſt in his poſſeſſions▪ &amp;c. (Eccleſ. 41. 1.)
And thus Pullulat herba ſatis, quae nil habet Ʋtilitatis: This ill
Weed, this ſtinking Roote, growes a pace: No good Huſband,
(good Chriſtian) will ſuffer it in the Garden of his
heart.
            2. It makes men erre from the faith, (1. Tim. 6.) Covetous
men can have no true Faith in CHRIST,-Sibi ſcopum alium,
prefigentes, quam Chriſtum, (Eraſm. in loc.) The Covetous
mans object is not Chriſts Croſſe, but the worlds Droſſe. I
dare make it a part of my Faith, (yet avouch my ſelfe no
Hereticke) That a Covetous man hath no true Faith. 'Tis a
rare thing to ſee a rich man Religious. 3. And needs muſt
they erre from the Faith: for they are-Idolaters, (Epheſ. 5. 5.)
How Idolaters?-Sicut idolatra idola colit, magis quam Deum
verum, &amp;c. (Carth. in loc.) As an Idolater worſhips Idols,
more then the true GOD: ſo they make more of theyr
Mammon, then of theyr Maker. Our common Proverbe
ſhewes it: When Riches are conferr'd upon a man, they ſay-He
is a man made: as tho the Riches made the Man, not God.
Therefore Ioh. de Comb. ſayes,-Homo avarus exhibet Creaturae,
quod debe
                     •
                   Creatori, (De Avarit.) A Covetous man aſcribes
that to the Creature, which is due to the Creator; viz.-Fidem,
Spem, &amp; Delectationem, Faith, Hope, and Love. 1.
Faith: Thus in affiance, they Cry, like Iſrael,—Theſe are thy
Gods, O Iſrael, (Exod. 32. 4.) 2. Hope:—They make Gold
their hope, (Job, 31. 24.) And—The rich mans riches are his
ſtrong hold, (Prov. 8. 11.) Herein is his Confidence; this is
his—Anchora firma ſpei, his fort of Defence, to beare him
out; his friend, to Buy him out of dangers. But, as our tranſlation
has well expreſt it,—The rich mans riches are as an
high wall, in his well imagination, (Ibid.) It is but in Imagination,
not alwayes in fact: For Great riches have ſold more men, then
they have bought out of troubles, (Bac. Eſſ. 34.) Mens Great riches
doe, many times, rob them of their lives or liberties: It
makes them, eyther a Prey to Theeves, or a B
                     ••
                  ty to Tyrants.
What was the overthrow of the flouriſhing Roman ſtate, but

-Nimia falicitas, Too much Wealth? (Florus.) And this Great
Wealth was one cauſe of Cardinall Wolſey's ruine: who being
ſwollen ſo bigge by the blaſts of Promotion, as the Bladder
not able to containe more greatneſſe, ſuddenly burſt, and vented
forth the Wind of all former favours, (Speed. Chron. in vit.
Hen. 8.) 3. Delectation, or Love: Hereupon our Apoſtle
ſtiles Covetous men—
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Lovers-of-Money, (2. Tim.
3, 2.) and the Common definition ſhewes it,—Eſt immoderatus
amor habendi, an exceſſive love of Hauing, (Bonavent.
cap. 6. Diet. Salut.) And the Etymon expreſſeth as much,—Avarw,
quaſi avidus aeris, A covetous man has a greedy deſire
of Money.
            But marke our Apoſtles conjunction in the former place,—
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               :
Theſe two, Lovers-of-themſelves, and
Lovers-of-Money are one, as it were: ſo reciprocate, and
correlate in nature, that they can hardly bee ſeparated.
For what is Pride and Selfe-love, but the Daughter of Proſperity?
Decet res ſecundas Superbia; As Plautus ironically
jerkes at it. So odious and deteſtable is this Sinne, that th' Apoſtle
hates the ſhadow of it: forbids the Name and memory
of it-Nec nominetur, Let it not be once named among you.
(Eph. 5. 3.) Nec ſuſpicio ſit in vobis. (Ordin. Gloſ. in loc.)
Let there be no name nor fame of Covetouſneſſe; Let no man
be able juſtly to taxe you for it. For we muſt not onely, Bee
good, but not, Seeme ill; Bee good, for our ſelves (-Conſcientia
propterte) Not, Seeme, ill, for others (-Fama
propter Proximum) Appearance alone, which in good is too
little, in evill, is too much. It was well ſaid of CAESAR—Caeſars
wife ſhould not onely be free from ſinne, but from ſuſpicion;
So Gods Saints muſt not onely be voyd of the fact of Covetouſneſſe,
but of the Fame. So heynous a delinquent is the
Covetous, that our Apoſtle excommunicates him, Ipſo facto:
Separates him from Chriſtian ſociety—Cum ejuſmodi ne edatis
quidum. (1. Cor. 5. 11.) A curſed ſinner he is-Maledictus
diſpenſator avarus, cujus largus est Dominus. (Auguſt.)
Curſed is the Covetous Steward, that hath ſo liberall
a Lord-The Lord is bountifull, indeed. He gives all, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . (lā
                1. 17.) And he forgives all,
Which forgives all thine iniquities. (Pſa. 103. 3.) Therefore the
Covetous muſt needs be odious to God; For it is Likeneſſe
that cauſeth love—
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : And-Simile
gaudet ſimili, every thing delights in his like. Thus-Go
                     •
                  
loves (his like) a cheerfull giver. (2. Cor. 9. 7.)
            Haec res &amp; jungit, junctos &amp; ſervat amico
                  •
               . (Horat.)
            
            Whence is that ſecret ſympathy, and miraculous Combination
of love, betweene the Loadſtone and the ſteele, but
from a 
                  
                     •
                  ik
                     •
                  neſſe of qualities? But—Quam malè conveniunt?
How unlike are Chriſt and the covetous? He is an Antipathite
to Chriſt. What agreement hath the Temple of God with
Idols? (2. Cor. 6. 16.) And covetouſneſſe (you have heard) is
Idolatry. Surely as long as Idolatry it ſelfe, and this picture
of Idolatry (Covetouſneſſe) beares any ſway in this Kingdome,
God cannot be in love with us, in league with us,
there can be no good liking betweene us; we muſt looke for
Plague upon plague, Warre upon warre, Famine upon famine.
            But, I thinke you looke for Applicat. Beloved, marvell
not, that you heare covetouſneſſe ſo hammer'd on-Malus
cunens, Malo nodo: ſo tough a knot lookes for many blowes.
For though iterations be commonly, loſſe of time, yet it is
the beſt gaine of time to reiterate often the ſtate of the Queſtion.
I know Criticall eares ſurfeit of any thing, ſave Curioſity:
and Manna it ſelfe, often ſerved in, becomes Nauſeous
to ſqueamiſh Iſraelites. When PAMBO the holy Hermite
had this Leſſon read to him out of the Pſal.-I ſaid I will
take heed to my wayes, &amp;c. He came not neere his Maſter in a
long time after: at next comming his Maſter checked him
for his long abſence; he anſweres, he had beene buſie enough
all that while, to learne that one Leſſon. So ſay I to you: I
ſhall have enough to doe, this whole houre, and you, a long
time, to preach and practice this one Leſſon. When one
ask'd DEMOSTHENES, what was the chiefeſt part of an Orater,
he anſwered-Action: what ſecond? Action; what
third? Action. So if any aske me, what is the worſt part

of a Chriſtian? I ſhall anſwere, Covetouſneſſe: What next?
Covetouſneſſe: What againe? covetouſneſſe.—Avaronihil
ſceleſtius. (Eccl. 10. 9.) There was an ominous Prophet
roſe up in Jeruſalem, ſome foure yeares before the ſiedge of
the City by Titus Veſpatian: who cryed continually, this
one Note up and downe the ſtreets-Vae, vae, Jeroſolimis: Haec
interdiù noctu
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   clamitans. (Barrad. Tom. 3. lib. 4. cap. 2.)
Woe, woe to Ieruſalem; driving this tune both night and
day. And ſo our Saviour for many verſes together inculcates
this one ſentence—Woe to you Scribes and Phariſes,
Hypocrites. So may I ſay-Woe to you Politicians, covetous:
Woe to you Projectors, covetous: Woe to you Promotors,
covetous: Woe to you Ingroſſers, covetous: Woe to
you Regrators, covetous: Woe to you Depopulators, covetous:
Woe to you Oppreſſors, covetous: Woe to you Extortioners,
covetous: Woe to you Brokers, covetous: Woe to you Bribers,
covetous: Woe to you Vſurers, covetous: Woe to you
Sacrilegious Church-robbers, covetous: Woe to you contentious
Pettifoggers; covetous. But all theſe (faſt friends to
covetouſneſſe) will ehallenge me for an Enemy, with AHAB-Haſt
thou found me, O mine enemy, (Act. 19. 28.) And
cry out, with DEMETRIVS, Magna Diana Epheſiorum.
Magna Avaritia Anglorum, Great is Avarice of the Engliſh.
But I anſwere-Magna est veritas &amp; praevalet. (1. Eſdr. 4.
41.) Great is the truth, and prevaileth. And I demaund—Am
I your enemie, if I tell you the truth? (Gal. 4. 16.) Yes,
what elſe?-Veritas odium. This ſame Truth is a naked and
open Day-light, that doth not ſhew the fantaſticke Maſques
and Mummeries of the world, halfe ſo ſtately and daintily, as
the candle-lights of flattery and Pepularity,-Obſequium amicos.
But the truth is-Veritas non querit angulos, Truth ſeeks
no corners-Nihil Erubeſcit, preterquam obſcondi. (Tertul.)
She bluſheth at nothing, but Hiding; No better place than
the open Pulpit, to tell Gods plaine truth,-Nil poſſumus contra
veritatem, is the fitteſt Plea at this Barre. (2. Cor. 13.
8.) But then you will reply with AVGVSTINE,-Ama &amp;
objurga: Tell us the truth in love, ſmite us friendly; Content;

And there is hope of you, if you will ſo be content;
ſo farre ſubmit to the ingenuous cenſure of the Text. For
though it be true, (conſidering the abhominable Covetouſneſſe,
cold Charity, and abounding iniquity of thoſe times)-Difficile
est Satyram non ſcribere: it is hard for a zealous Miniſter
not to play the Satyr; yet, being now to take Charities part
againſt Covetouſneſſe, I ſhall be loath to breake charities head,
in her defence; (onely pardon the Accent of my voice, and
zeale to the truth) I confeſſe it is Heaven upon earth, to
have a mind Move in Charity, Rest in Providence, and Turne
upon the Poles of Truth.
            
            Well, beloved-without faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God.
(Heb. 11. 6.) But-Faith is dead without Charity. (Iam. 2.
17.) And Charity is dead too, without Bounty.-Benigna
est, She is bountifull. (1. Cor. 1. 4.) Eſt: Bounty is the
Being, and Eſſence of Charitie: She will not bee bounded
within the bankes of Selfe-love, Covetouſneſſe, and Privacy.
Her Councell is,-Deriventur fontes tui foràs, let thy fountaines
flow forth. (Prov. 5. 16.) That Charity will hardly
water the Neighbour-ground, which ſtayes long to fill its
owne Poole. True it is, Charity begins at home: but it may
not end there: for then it would tend, but to private ends;
It muſt goe abroad too, this is implyed in the Text: (if
yee pleaſe to marke the coherence.) A man may not-Looke
on his owne things, without an-Alſo: but-Alſo on the
things of other men.—Charity ſeekes not her owne things. (1.
Cor. 13.) Not her owne things, Greedily, covetouſly. And
will you looke every man on his owne things? Every man for
Himſelfe? It's a poore Centre of a Man's Actions, Himſelfe:
It is right earth; for that onely ſtands faſt upon his
owne Centre, whereas all things that have affinitie with
the Heavens. Move upon the Centre of another, which they
benefit. Doth the Sunne ſhine for it ſelfe? Doth it not extend
it's beames, univerſally, to all? He maketh his Sunne to
ariſe on the Evill and the Good. (Math. 5. 45.) Doth the
fire give heat for it ſelfe?
            
               
               —Sic vos, non vobis nidificatis aves.
               Sic vos, non vobis Mellificatis apes, &amp;c. 
               (Virg.)
            
            Every creature in it's kind, is extenſively good: onely a
Covetous man is good for nothing, but Himſelfe; Not for Himſelfe-Sibi
peſſimus, he is the worſt enemy to Himſelfe- 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
His ſilver is his ſoule. (H
                     •
                  ſ. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .) And-He will
ſell his owne ſoule for money. (Eccleſ. 10. 9.) Nay, he will
ſell his Saviour like IVDAS▪, with a-What will yee give me?
(Math. 26. 15.) Though it bee but to buy a halter to
hang himſelfe. Thus he is good, indeed, for nothing: like
our Saviours Salt. (Math. 5. 13.) He is good for nothing,
but to be caſt out, and troden under foote both of God, and all good
Men.
            
            Deere Chriſtians, your Soules are bought at too deare a
rate, to be caſt away on earthly things. In the Philoſophers
Scale, the Soule of a Fly is of more excellence, than the Sunne:
In a Chriſtians Scale, the Soule of Man is infinitely more precious,
than all Creatures under the Sunne. What ſhall it profit
you to winne the whole world, to looſe your owne ſoules? (Mat.
16. 26.) Your eyes are ſet like ſparkling Diamonds, in a
Gold ring, in too Noble and ſtately a place, to be baſely dejected
upon Gold and Silver, the droſſe of the Earth; Oculiſts
obſerve, that whereas all Creatures have but 4. Muſcles,
to turne their eyes round about: Man hath a fift, to pull
his eyes up to Heaven.
            
               —Os homini ſublime dedit, coelum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   tueri,
               Juſſit.
            
            !O then depreſſe not your eyes, as if they were fixed on earth,
nor turne them round by gazing on the fruitleſſe Treaſures
of the Earth. Which the God of nature hath (as of purpoſe)
hidden under the Earth, out of your ſight; and plac'd
under foote, to be trampled upon, 
                  •
                
               Nihil, quod avaritiam
noſtram irritaret, poſuit in aperto: pedibus aurum &amp; argentum
ſubjecit, calcandum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   dedit. (Sen. Epiſt. 94.)
                 Your eyes ſee
all other things but Themſelves: and will you invert the
courſe of Nature, To looke every man on himſelfe, his owne private,
his owne things? Nec potest quiſquam beaté degere, qui

ſe tantum intuetur. (Sen. Epiſt. 48.) No man can live happily,
that lives, that lookes to Himſelfe onely. An Ant, you
know, is a wiſe Creature, for it ſelfe: But it is a ſhrwd Thing
in an Orchard, or Garden: So, ſurely men that are great Lovers
of themſelves, are greateſt Enemies to the Commonwealth.
For whatſoever affaires paſſe through ſuch mens
hands, they crooke them to their owne ends; which muſt
needs be Eccentrick to the ends of the Church, and Common-wealth.
Selfe-love and private ends are like Suckers in the
ſtocke of a Graft, which draw all the Sap to themſelves, and
ſtarve the Graft. Such is the caſe of the Weale-publike among
us, in thoſe times: theſe Suckers, I told you of but now,
have drawne out the very heart-bloud of it; we can hardly
ſay we have a Common-wealth, it is a Common-woe; well defin'd
by Sir THOMAS MOORE, long agoe.-Quaedam couſpiratio
divitum, de ſuis negotijs, ac Commodis, Reipublicae nomine,
titulo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   tractantium. (Ʋtop.) There be too many both publike
and private perſons, that, Narſiſſus-like, dote upon the
conceited Image of Themſelves (their owne private fortune)
and looke with both eyes on their owne Things; worldly
Hermits, that deſire-To dwell alone in the midst of the earth-(Iſa.
5. 8.) Such extreame lovers of themſelves, as they
will ſet an houſe on fire, if it be but to roaſt their owne egs-Their
hearts are like I ſlands, cut off from other Lands: and
their voice is like CAIN'S,-Num ego ſum Fratris Cuſtos?
(Gen. 4.) And in other mens extremities, their reſolution
is, like Chriſt's Conſpirators,-Quid ad nos? (Mat. 27. 4.)
            But as the tree proſpers not, that's vnkindly embrac't
with the writhing Ivie: So the publicke ſtate muſt needs
wither, whiles theſe Inſinuating, Sucking ſelfe-lovers flouriſh
in her. I ſhall not breake the bounds of Charity to make
our Apoſtles wiſh-Vtinam abſcindantur, (Galat. 6. 12.) I
would to God theſe Suckers were even cut off (cut off by
Repentance, or by Gods iuſt vltion and vengeance) I would
theſe eies of Privacy and Selfe-love, that Looke but on their
owne Things, were either cur'd with ſpirituall Eye-ſalve, to
ſee with more Charity. (Revel. 3. 18.) Or elſe pluckt out.

For it is an-Evill eye▪
                An Enuiovs eye; which with a kind of
faſcinating ejaculation, bewitcheth the publick welfare.
And as the Sunne-beames beate hotter vpon a Banke, or,
ſteepe-riſing Ground, then upon a Flat; So doth a Covetous
man enuy the proſperity of others; ſeeking to ſinke them if
he can.
            —Alterius rebus macreſcit Opimi
                  •
               .
            It is ſaid of VESPASIAN Emp. That he did advance many
to promotion, that were moſt noted for Covetouſneſſe:
And to what end? That when they had well ſcrap'd and gathered,
he might uſe them as Sponges: and wring from them,
that which by extortion, they had wreſted from others; So,
it were no Injuſtice, at all, if theſe Jngroſſers, Extortioners,
Ʋſurers, and the like, that have Monopoliz'd the Common
Treaſure into their private hands, were wrung and preſt, to
yeeld out their Ill-gotten-Goods for the publike-good. It is obſerv'd
that during that Triumvirate of Kings, HENRY, 8. of
England, FRANCIS; 1. of France; CHARLES, 5. Emp. there
was ſuch a jealous watch kept; that none of the three, could
winne a palme of ground, but th'other two would ſtraightway
Ballance it. So ſhould Godly policy ſtill keepe centinell;
that neyther Selfe-wiſedome, nor Privacy, doe encroach too
farre upon the publike. Certaine it is, that if Deprav'd Policy,
and Corruption: if private Ingroſſing and Vſury, in Citie and
Country, be ſuffered much longer, to play the Game, all the
Money will be in the Box. And then though the Kingdome
may have good Limmes, yet it will have but empty Veines.
A ſuddaine Conſumption muſt needs ſurprize the Commonwealth.
            For what ſayes a Great Stateſ-man of France? Such is the
condition of the Commons, as of the Hand of a Dyall: the motion
of this proceeds-Senſim ſine Senſu, by inſenſible degrees;
and is not ſeene, till it hath finiſhed the courſe, and points
directly to the Houre; So the loſſe and decay of the Common-wealth
ſteales on, and is not perceiv'd, but in the finall
Ruine. (PASQV. Letter to the Qu. Reg. of Fra.) Perchance
I ſhall be accounted a Tribunitiall Oratour: But my Happineſſe
               
is, with our Apoſtle, that I ſpeake before Grave and
Honourable Senators, Who have knowledge of all Cuſtomes and
Lawes of the Kingdome. (Act. 26. 2. 3.) Whoſe cleare
eyes and uncorrupt affections (I hope) ſcorne to-Looke on
their owne things; But as they are ſet in publike place. For the
execution of Lawes, ſo doe they acknowledge the Concluſion
of the Rom. 12. Tables-Salus populi ſuprema lex; well knowing
that Lawes, except they be in Order to that End, are but
Things Captious, and Oracles not well inſpir'd; Making it
their Prime ſtudy and care,-To looke alſo on the things of other
Men.
            
            
               Which is the ſecond part. The Affirmat. propoſit. But every
man alſo on the things &amp;c,
            The Greeke Text reades,-
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . As
The eyes of Faith can have no better Object than GOD: So,
the eyes of Charitie cannot have a more pleaſing Object then
the Common-good. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , His owne Things, is like the colour
of Black-Congregat Viſum: it collects the ſight, and
makes it looke too narrowly, too neerely, too niggardly;
But 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                is like White-Diſgregat Viſum. it diſperſeth
the ſight, and makes it looke abroad on other mens Good.
As we are-One body in Chriſt, and every one, one anothers members.
(Rom. 12. 5.) So ſhould the Members-Have the ſame
care one for another. (1. Cor. 12. 25.) And, Every man alſo
looke on the things of other men. For whereas our Saviour
commands-Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. (Mat.
22. 39.) Our Apoſtle tranſlates it-
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                (Rom. 13.
8.) Id est, Every man, whatſoever he be, (be he friend or foe)
that ſtands in need of thy helpe. The love of our ſelves is but
the Patterne, the love of our Neighbour, the Picture limned,
and drawne thereby. The love of our Neighbour, muſt be a
Sicut,-ſicut teipſum: as, or like thy ſelfe. It is obſerv'd,
that our Saviour never regarded-
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                his private: But—
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
the publike good:-I ſeeke not mine owne praiſe. (Joh.
8. 50.) But—I lay downe my life for my Sheepe. (Iohn. 10.
15.
            Well, Faith and Charitie are like a paire of Compaſſes, to

take the Latitude of our Chriſtian Profeſsion: whiles Faith,
like the one Foot, ſtands fixt in the centre of Juſtification: Charity,
like th'other, muſt goe round in a continuall circle of Beneficent
operation; and-Delight to doe good, and diſtribute.
(Heb. 13. 16.) As Faith is neceſſarie to Juſtification; (Rom.
3, 28.) So are workes of Charity, to Sanctification. (Iam. 2.
24.) And as God lookes on our Faith, in the Court of Juſtification,
here: So, will he take account onely of our works,
in the Court of Remuneration, hereafter. Faith, having
brought us home to Chriſt, in this Kingdome of Grace,
leaves us (like our Temporall friends) at the Grave; But
Charity is an Inſeparable companion-It doth never fall away.
(1. Cor. 13. 8.) She, likethe Indian wives, who are
buried aliue with their Dead Husbands, goes to the Grave
with us, and keepes us company to heaven. Therefore is
Charitie preferr'd Maxima harum charitas. The cheifeſt of
theſe is Charitie. (Verſ. ult.) And why ſo?-Vt pote quae in
futura vita non aboleatur, ut aliae, ſed perficiatur, becauſe Charitie,
in the life to-come, is not aboliſhed, like Faith and
Hope; but perfected-(Beza. Annot. in loc.) Quum fides &amp;
ſpes inres promiſſas &amp; futuras ferantur, illas preſentes adepti,
quorſum fidem &amp; ſpem haberemus? For, ſeeing Faith and
Hope looke to things promiſed, and to-come, theſe things
being come, what need we Faith and Hope?
            
               Charity then, you ſee, is a Good Companion: It is ſtill
Communicative, Explicative. Shee is altogether Sociable, not
Solitary. Like Iob, ſhe cannot—Eate her 
                     •
                   Morſels alone.
(Iob. 31. 17.) She is noſooner—Diffuſa pe
                     •
                  ſpiritum, ſhed
abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt. (Rom. 5. 5.) But ſhe
is-Effuſa per effectum, cōmunicated to others by the Hand of
Bounty; and can no more be bounded within the Narrow
Limits of Selfe-wiſedome, than a Scaturient Fountaine
within his owne Banks. To inſtance this in the New
Converts of the Primitive Church. The multitude of them
that believed, were of one heart and of one ſoule, neither any
of them ſaid, that any thing of that he poſſeſſed, was his owne, but
they had all things in common. (Act. 4. 32.) This Community
               
of Goods would well ſtand with Chriſtianity, if the Commonweale
were well Conſtitute: and the people (like thoſe Converts)
Combined by the Spirit of Charity. This onely is the
Cement, that can joyne Hearts and Soules, and make men—Vnanimes,
to have but one ſoule in a Multitude of Bodies.
And from this Coniunction muſt needs grow a Community:
from the vnity of Aff
                     •
                  ctions, a Community of Charitable
Actions. When one ask'd AGESILAVS, why Sparta was
not fenc't about with walls? He anſwer'd, That in ſteed of
Walles and Caſtles, Cities ſhould be fenc't with the Vertue of the
Inhabitants—Quos ſi jungat concordia, nulius poteſt eſſe murus
inexpugnabilior, who being linck'd together by mutuall
concord, are more impregnable then the ſtrongeſt Caſtle; So,
it is vnity of Affections, and Community of brotherly Offices,
that muſt make vs Invincible againſt all Diabolicall Invaſion;
but without this-Nihil ſumus. (1. Cor. 13. 2.) we are Nothing;
nullivs valoris, aut vigoris, of no value, no vertve.
            But for fuller explanation of this point (a Riddle, a Paradox
to the Carnall ſence) we muſt a little mixe Philoſophy
and Divinity. In Philoſophy I find two contrary Opinions:
The one Plato's, That all things ſhould be common to all men,
in a Common wealth—Et quo ad poſſeſſionem, &amp; vſum (Plat.
pol.
               This Community is impious, abſurd, &amp; ridiculous it, takes away all ſplendor and Magnificence. Demeer. Iu.
                3.) But this is ridiculous, voide both of reaſon and religion:
For men in this Community, would never be at Vnity;
the Parity of perſons, that then muſt be, and the Diſparity
of profeſſions, vocations, Labors, Deſerts, would never agree.
Men of place would never abide to be ranked with baſeſt
Peſants: nor theſe of beſt Deſerts, to ſhare alike with
vnworthyeſt Drones. This would cauſe an Anabaptiſticall Anarchy.
The other Opinion is ARISTOTLES;That which is euery mans, is no mans. That
there ſhould be a Propriety of Poſſeſſion, but a Comunity of
Vſe: And this I take to be good Philoſophy and Divinity. 1.
A Propriety of poſſeſſion: Otherwiſe' how ſhould men have
Ability in themſelves, to Exerciſe their Bounty and Charity
towards others?—Rerum Communicate Constituta, Omnis
Munificentia perit, (Ariſt. pol. lib. 2. ca. 3.) grant a Community
of poſſeſſion, that each man may have a proper right in

another man's Goods, then how can any man ſhew himſelfe
bountifull? 2 A Community of vſe, there ought to be. Otherwiſe,
every man would looke but on his owne things; Thinke
himſelfe borne, but for Himſelfe, and Private Family; like
thoſe worldlings in the Pſal.—Who having goods conferr'd
vpon them, made no other diſtribution of them, but to their babes,
(Pſa.. 17. 14.) The heathen Orator could give better Counſell
—Non ſ
                     •
                  mus nobis nati: Not onely our wives Children,
and kinsfolke: but our King, Country, Church, Commonweale,
and private neighbours have a ſhare and intereſt, in
our Meanes and Money. Res tua eſt, vſus rei tuae meus eſt, ſaith
Seneca De Benef. lib 7. cap. 5. The Propriety is onely Thine,
but the vſe is thyne and myne. In this Senſe, the Philoſopher
ſpeakes true Divinity—Bonum quo Communius, eo melius,
(Eth. lib. 1.) Our Goods the more Common they are, the more
Commendable. And S
                     •
                  n.—Nullius boni ſine ſocio, jucunda
poſſeſſio. (Etiſt. 6.) Nothing that we poſſeſſe, can give vs true
content, without a Companion in the Vſe,—Ego ſic omnia
habeo, ut omnium ſunt, ſaith he againe. (De Benef. lib. 7.
cap. 10.) I have ſo the poſſeſsion of all things, that the 
                  Ʋſe
is common to all men. What difference is here, betweene
SEN. and IOB?—Job could not eate his morſels alone, but the
Fatherleſſe muſt have part (Iob. 31. 17.) Nay theſe Endowments
of the Intellect (Knowledge, Wiſdome, Learning, &amp;c.)
What were they without Communication?—In hoc gaudeo
aliquid dicere vt doceam, Saith SEN. It is my onely ioy
in ſpeaking, to teach others:—Nec me vila res delectabit,
licet eximia ſit et ſalutaris, quam mihi vni ſciturus ſim; neither
can I take pleaſure in any thing, be it never ſo excellent, leſt
others take part with me (SEN. loc. cit.) And all this is agreable
to the Morall Law of God: which gives every man
his owne, in point of Propriety; and requires this Duty,
with all, in point of Community. That the 
                  Ʋſe of our Goods
ſhould be, to help our neighbours in neceſſity; who, in this
reſpect, are called—The owners of thy Goods: (—Communicate
vſus) and it is injuſtice to with hold them, with a Niggardly
hand (Prou. 3. 27▪) And the very Beaſts, in Saint

BASIL. Doe teach vs this Community—Illa enim his, quae
ex terra naſcunter, à natura, in Commune vtuntur (Baſ. in famac
Sic. Hom. 40.) They, out of a naturall Goodneſſe, doe ſhare
each with other, in thoſe things that grow of the earth:
How lovingly doe our Flocks of ſheepe feede together in the
ſame Common? and our Heards of Cattle paſture together
in the ſame Leaſe? All of them doe yeild each to other in a
mutuall fruition of their bodily ſuſtenance.—Nos autem in
ſin
                     •
                  m abdimus ea, quae ſunt communia: ea, quae multorum ſunt,
ſoli habemus (Ibidem.) But wee (worſe then Beaſts) doe
hide, and hord thoſe things, which God hath made Common;
and that which ſhould be for the Common good, wee greedily
ingroſſe to our private gaine.
            
               Thus the Diſtinction of the Shcoolemen agrees, in ſenſe,
to this of the Philoſophers:—Jus proprietatis, Ius Charitatis,
A right of Propriety, A right of Charity; Right of Propriety,
is the ſame with Propriety of poſſeſſion: Right of Charity,
with community of Vſe. Right of Charity, that belongs to
the common good: Right of propriety, that appertaines to the
Private Owner. It was decreed in the Law—That a man,
when he came into a vineyard, might eate as many of the grapes,
as he pleaſed. [Deut. 23. 24.] This was Right of charity. But
he might carry none away with him, (Ibidem) This was Right
of Propriety. So the Diſciples, paſſing through the corne-fields on
the Sabboth, pull the eares, to ſatisfie their hunger (Mat. 12. 1)
This was Right of Charity. But they put not in their ſycle,
to cut downe the Corne, and carry it away: becauſe they
had not Right of Propriety. All this may be Compris'd in
Saint AMBRO'S deſcription of Iuſtice—Eſt virtus, quae vnicui
                  
                     
                  
                  que
               
quod ſuum eſt, tribuit, alienum non vendicat, vtilitatem propria
negligit, ut communem aequalitatem cuſtodiat. It is a vertue,
that gives to every man his due: it challengeth no right in
another mans Propriety, it neglects it's owne private for the
Publick good.
            Now, would you have all theſe particulars caſt up in a T
                     •
                  
                  tall?
The ſumme is this-It is the principall duety of our christian

Profeſſion, equally to reſpect the common Good: To approve
our ſelves true Members of the Body Myſticall. This
charity muſt we have, or we have not faith, (whatſoever we
confeſſe) To beleeve the communion of Saints. A crowd, is not
company; Faces, but a Gallery of Pictures; Talke, but a Tinckling
cymball, without charity, and brotherly community.
            
            Beloved, I hope, you will give me leave to goe ſo farre
with you, as my Text doth: To make the Application anſwerable
to the Propoſition. The one is 
                  Ʋniverſall.-Every
man: So muſt th'other be; Every man of you muſt be a good
common-wealths man; Muſt-Looke on the things of other men;
The Magiſtrate, the Miniſter, the Private man. 1. The
Magiſtrate, eſpecially: more ſpecially, the Iudge; who, as
his place is more eminent, ſo ſhould he be more intent on the
publike good. The higher he ſits, the more diſtant from the
earth, from the earthly ſpeculation of-His owne things, to-Looke
on the things of other men. This community is the greene
verdure, which delights the eye of Iuſtice; and nothing
dimmes it more, than when the rheugme of Avarice diſtils
into it-This blinds it. (Deut. 16. 19.) True it is, Iuſtice
in the Embleme, is blinde: Blinde to the perſons, ſees not the
ſuperficies of perſons; but-Lookes (clearely, impartially)
on the things (the cauſes) of other men. And that, not
with a ſquint eye, onely on one ſide: as PILAT look'd, more
on the clamour of the Accuſer, than the Innocence of the Priſoner.
(Luk. 23. 23. 24.) Nor with a poore-blind eye, onely
upward: as the Governors look'd on AHAB the King, not
on NABOTH the poore ſubject.
            
            Though the eye ſees not-per emiſſionem radiorum, (as the
Platonicks conceit) but-per immiſſionem ſpecierum, (as the
Ariſtotelians more probably affirme) yet, in this reſpect,
Juſtice is a
                  •
                
               Platonicke: and ſees not by Taking in the Goods of
other men; but by-Looking on other mens Good. And for
you (R. Hon.) I cannot impute unto you the leaſt blemiſh
of the eye: unleſſe I ſhould looke upon you with the eye of
M
                     •
                  mus; who, becauſe he could eſpy no deformity in Venus

body, would needs find fault with her ſlipper. Perſonall Imperfections,
no doubt you have: (who is without?)-Let
him cast the firſt ſtone. But for your Places, I may not, I cannot
ſay, Blacke is your eye. The one of you (to give CAESAR
his due) I thankfully acknowledge, to have had comfortable
experience of: not onely for mine owne, but the Countries
good;A famous Act of Iuſtice vpon an infamous Barrator. As Hercules was famous for purging the world of Monſters. So are Magiſtrates famous, that purge the Commonwealth of theſe men-monſters. which being a publike cauſe, why ſhould I not
give it a publike acknowledgement? For as Magiſtrates
are-Sent of God for the praiſe of them that doe well. (1. Pet.
2. 14.) So, great equity it is, That the praiſe and Encouragement
which they give to other Well-doers, ſhould reflect
from others on their owne Well-doings.
            
            Neyther let any envious Critick accuſe my Gratitude of
Adulation: ('Tis from where there is leaſt judgement, commonly,
that the heavieſt judgement comes.) For as wee
have a Negative command, Thou ſhalt not raiſe upon the Judges.
(Exod. 22. 28.) (So the former Tranſlation reades)
or-Dijsnon Detrabes: (So the Vulg.) Thou ſhalt not deprave
the perſons, nor inveigh againſt the places of Magiſtrates;
who are-Vice-dei, petty Gods upon earth. (Or
Earthly Gods.) So have we a poſitive Precept—Honour the
King. (1. Pet. 2. 17.) The King as ſupreame: and other
ſubordinate Magiſtrates, who are Repreſentative Kings; having
the ſtampe of Regall authoritie upon their places; theſe
muſt be honoured, encouraged by due reſpect to their places,
and true affection to their Graces and Vertues.
            
            —Laudataque Virtus-creſcit:
            As praiſe is the reflection of Vertue, ſo is it the
Nurſe of it. And it is a Forme due in civilitie, to Great
perſons-Landando precipere: This kind of commendative,
is a commandative; By telling men what they are, we
repreſent to them what they ſhould bee, more, and more.
Goe on then (R. Hon.) to looke on your Countryes good,
(the common good) being the ſpeciall Object of your Places;
And (if I miſtake not) at this time, a miſerable ſpectacle;
lying like him among the Theeves, in Adomin, loco ſanguinario,

a bloudy robbing place betweene Jeruſalem and Ieriche,
(Luk. 10.) Robb'd, wounded, and halfe dead; robb'd by
racking Landlords, wounded by Ingroſſing and Tranſporting
Marchants, Halfe-dead by Devouring Vſurers. Here is worke
for a Samaritan (for Iudges and Iuſtices) for ſurely the
Prieſt and the Levite (our inferiour Officers) paſſe it by, with
little or no regard, not-Looking on the things of other
men.
            
            And what doth the Miniſter in the ſecond place? What
Common-wealths men are we? We Spirituall men ought to-Looke
alſo on the things of other men. We have a Cōmon-weale to
take care of too-The common-weale of Iſrael. (Eph. 2. 12.)
This ſhould every Miniſter looke to; eſpecially the Biſhops,
who have their title from a compound of the Text; the ſimple
here (you heare) is, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                hence-
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : Inſpectors, Superviſors,
Superintendents; Such as are appointed, to-Looke
on the things of other men; to provide for the Common good
of the Church, both in Doctrine and Diſcipline. You know
what our Apoſtle ſayes of theſe men; The Elders that rule
well are worthy of double honour, ſpecially they which labour in
the word and Doctrine. (1. Tim. 5. 17.) 1. They that rule well.
(manage well the Paſtorall ſtaffe of Diſcipline) theſe are honourable
Common-wealths-men in Gods Iſrael. And this ſtaffe
had need be walking: for who ſees not, that Schiſme and
Faction begin to be too ſawcie and unruly? 2. But they that
labor in the word and Doctrine, (they that communicate Spirituall
Food to the Soules of the people) theſe are more Honourable-
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
ſpecially theſe. 3. And they that doe both
(both rule well, and preach well) are worthy of double Honour,
indeed; And they that deny it them, envie it them, are
worthy of Treble ſhame.
            Then cannot we, for ſhame, but acknowledge our Happineſſe:
and give hearty thankes to God,Give to every man his duety: honor to whom honor is due. for the Honourable
Common-wealths man of our Iſrael: Specially for his Indefatigable
Labors in the word and Doctrine, learnedly and liberally
communicated to the whole Church,Rom. 13. from Preſſo and

               Pulpit. And (without prejudice to the Pulpit) I may
ſay, ſome of us are not worthy of this Happineſſe: Some
Dunghill-Cockes, that cannot diſtinguiſh betweene a
Barly-corne, and a Iewell. But as Popiſh MOREN ſaid
of our Reverend IEVVELL, A
                     •
                  arem te, 
                     •
                  ewelle, ſi
non eſſes Zwinglianus: So may I of them, They would
love him, Si; if hee were not ſo good as hee is. Every
Critick will have a-Si, of Exception. You know the
fable of the Frogges, the croking Animals were never
pleaſed with their preſent Governour: when they had
a Storke, he was too ſtirring; when they had a Stocke,
hee was too ſtill. And ſo it ſhould ſeeme by their behaviour,
—Inſultant, deſultant: But a blow or two of
the Paſtorall ſtaffe will make theſe Frogs dive under
water. Meane time the Vulgar's envie is Vertues
foile; and if yee ſeeke Vertue, you ſhall commonly find
her by the Tracks of Envy; which, like a cunning
Bloud-hound, ſtill ſingles out the fatteſt Deere of the
Heard-Invidia pernitioſum, optimis, t
                     •
                  lum. Envie levels
her poyſonous dart to thoſe of beſt Deſert.
            
            Surely it much concernes all Clergie-men to looke
to the Common Good of the Church. For the—blood
of every ſoule, that periſheth vnder our hands, for want of a
liberall diſtribution of Spirituall Food, ſhall bee required of
vs. (Ezech. 3. 20.) And I wiſh our Apoſtles generall
Reproofe in this Chapter of my Text Did not come too
neare home to ſome of us,—Omnes, quae ſua ſunt quaerunt.
(Phil. 2. 21.) Some that have moſt profit from
the Church, yeeld, leaſt profit, to the Church. Right
like, that Inferiour Prieſt, of whom I have read: who
whilſt hee was without Preferment, had his Table, at
meales, ſpread with a Net; to mind him of the Myſterie
of his Profeſſion, and to tell him, He was a Fiſher
of men; Afterward, being preferr'd, hee bad his
ſervant:Phadr. lib. 3. 
               Take away the Net, I have caught that I fiſht
for.
               Aeſop Fab.
               Suſpitione ſi quis errabit ſua, et rapiet ad ſe, quo derit commune omnium, ſtulte nu
                     •
                  abit animi conſcientiam: Let them that be guilty, make the Application.
               
Of whom that Father ſaid truely,—Currunt ad Cathedram,
non ad curam: They love the Chaire, better then
the Pulpit. It's a wonder how men can have a Cure of
ſoules, without Care. Theſe men are rather Craſſiani,
than—Chriſtiani, (Bub. lib. 5. de Aſſe.) More Secular,
than Eccleſiaſticall; very Demaſſes, indeed. Neither doe
I ſpeake this, in enuy, to the places, or Dignities, of
any of my profeſſion: rather, I grieve to heare our Sacred
Calling, in them, play'd vpon, (not vniuſtly)Si quiſpiam offendatur, &amp; fibi vindicet, non habet quod expoſtulet cum eo, qui ſcripſit: ipſe, ſi volet, ſecum agat iniuriam, vrpote ſui proditor, qui declaravit hoc ad ſe proprie pertinere: Eraſm. Epiſt, ad Dorp.
               —Curae
leves loquuntur, Ingentes ſtupent. I deny not, but wee
may, by Lawfull meanes, ſeeke Riches, and Preferment:
—Wee have power to doe it as well as others. (1. Cor. 9. 1
2.) and—poteſtatem, non vſurpatam, ſed datam (Ierome
de paſtor. Eccleſ.) A power not vſurp'd, but lawfull
derived; But, take his Diſtinction with you: Wee
Miniſters are to be conſider'd in a double quality,—Vt
Chriſtiani, vt praepoſiti; As private men, as Miniſters;
In eo quod chriſtiani, attendatur vtilitas noſtra:
in eo quod praepoſiti, non niſi veſtra. In that wee are Private
men, wee have reaſon to have a provident care of
our Temporall eſtates, as other men: wee are not now
maintain'd by Miracle; But in that wee are Miniſters,
our cheifeſt care ſhould bee for our Cure. For—Wee
bee vnto the Shepheards of Iſraell, that feede themſelves,
ſhould not the Shepheards feed the flockes? (Ezech.
34. 2.) And my Text doth, as it were Comment on
this place,—Looke not every man (meerely) On his
owne things, but every man alſo on the things of other
men.
            
            And what Common-wealths-men are private men, in
the third place? O deare Chriſtians and Countrymen,
Gentlemen, Yeomen, and the like, who make vp
the Body of the Commons: Remember, you are one
anothers Members, knit together by the ſinewes of policy,
to one Monarchicall Head; Let it be your care,
to ſtudy the welfare of Him, and one another. There

bee three thinges, which doe much reioyce God
(and moſt beautifie our Chriſtian Religion) two whereof
are—The vnity of Brethren, The love of Neighbours
(Eccl. 25. 1) O quam bonum, et quam incundum;
how good, and how comely a thing it is, brethren to
dwell together in vnity, (Pſal. 133. 1.) Therefore as
you tender Vnity and communitie, avoide baſe covetouſneſſe,
which is ſtill of the nature of
                  Democritus told Hippocrates, They daily plead one againſt another: the ſonne againſt the Father. Brother againſt brother, Kindred and friends of the ſame quality, one againſt another; and all this for riches. Hippocr. Epiſt. ad Damoget.
                
               Dividing: it divides
the deereſt friends; Brother and Brother.—Maſter,
bid my brother divide the inheritance with mee,
(Luc. 12. 13.) Hereto SENECA alludes—Video ferrum
ex eiſdem tenebris eſſe prolatum, quibus aurum et argentum:
               So that, ſomtimes, for body and for minde, Torture and torment in one Mine we finde. Du. Bart. Fur.
                I ſee yron digg'd out of the ſame darke myne,
with gold and Siluer; Ne aut inſtrumentum in caedes
mutuas deeſſet, aut pretium; That no meanes might be
wanting of Mutuall contention; Meaning that couetouſneſſe
begets bloody quarrels, (De Benef. lib. 7. cap.
10) In which place the wiſe Heathen cryes out on the
ſeverall kinds of v
                  •
               ſury, ſpringing from covetouſneſſe, in
his time: and to one hee gives a bloody Epithet—Sanguinolentae
centeſimae, (Loc. cit.) Bloody vſury: Becauſe,
like the Dur-fly, whereſoever it lights, it fetches blood
of a Man's Eſtate.
            
            This is ſo the breach of Peace and Charity, that it
makes one man odious to another: So St. BASIL,—When
the Ʋſurious Creditor, and penurious Debtor meet,
Ille velut Canis ad praedam accurrit, hic verò, velut parata
praeda congreſſum formidat. (In Pſal. 15.) The one
runnes as a Dog to the Prey: th' other, fearing to bee
made a Prey, runnes away. For, ſaith hee, the Inſolencies
of the Creditor, (intollerable to an ingenuous ſpirit)
muſt needs cauſe a deteſtation,—Coram uxore pudefacit,
coram amicis contumelia afficit, in foro ſtrangulat,
malus in feſto occurſus, vitam non vivendam tibi ſubornat.
(Ibidem.) Hee ſhames a man before his wife, reproacheth
a man before his friends, takes a man by the

throat in the open Market, at a Feaſt, his meeting
marres a mans mirth, and he makes a man weary of his
life. And can this bee a good Common-wealths man?
For a Gentleman to bee an Vſurer, is moſt ungenerous;
for a Citizen, moſt uncivill; for a Miniſter, moſt unclarkely,
for any man-moſt unchriſtianlike.
            
               
                  O fie upon Covetouſneſſe!
               —Quid non mortalia pectora cogit?
            
            What miſchiefe doth it not bring upon the Commonweale?
Whence are warres and contentions among you?
Saint IAMES askes the queſtion. (Jam. 4. 1.) I will
anſwere, are they not hence, even from Covetouſneſſe,
Vſury, Fraud, Oppreſſion?
            
            —Hinc Ʋſura vorax, &amp; multis utile bellum.
(Lucan.)
            
            It was SOCRATES complaint.-Propria creſcunt,
communia neglecta jacent: So theſe men grow privately
rich by the publike Ruine: which muſt needs be, (if
the Scriptures bee true) the ruine of themſelves and
poſteritie in the end; For the curſe of God is denounced
againſt it-Woe unto him that buildeth a Towne with
bloud, and erecteth a Citie with iniquitiae. (Hab. 2. 12.)
Id est, curſed is that Fortune which is fram'd of Ill-gotten
goods: the very Inanimate Materials whereof (the
ſtone out of the Wall, and the beame out of the timber)
ſhall cry for vengeance againſt the founder. (Verſ. 11.)
And where this Curſe of GOD breathes upon any
thing, it muſt needs bee blaſted; Witneſſe the Figge-tree.
(Mat. 11. 21.)
            Therefore, for the love of GOD, yee Magistrates,
Miniſters, and private men; Gentlemen, Yeomen,
and all men, Remember the Common good of Church,
and Common-weale. O let this be-Anglorum Helena,
Chriſtianorum Diana, The ſumme of your earthly delight;
Fight for it, pray for it, preach for it, practice
for it; I ſay Remember it. And that you may remember
               
it the better, take an example or two, ere I conclude,
along with you-
            —Exempla plus 
                  •
               voent.
            —When POLYCRATIDAS, with others, was ſent
Ambaſſador into a Province of Grecia: it was demanded
them, before they could have Audience, whether
they came upon private Commiſſion, or publike Legation?
Whereto they anſwered, in a pithy Laconiſm
                     •
                  ,
—Si impetremus, publice: Sin minus, or
                     •
                  vat
                     ••
                  
                  ▪ (Eraſm.
Apoph. lib. 4.) Wherein they had a ſpeciall eye to
their Countreys good, both wayes: if theyr Meſſage
ſucceeded, it ſhould bee for their Countries Glory; if
they had the Repulſe, yet their Country ſhould have no
diſhonour; they would rather take it upon themſelves.
When SYLLA had taken the Citty Palestrina; he gave
order, to put all the inhabitants to death, ſave onely his
Host; on whom hee would beſtow his life, in requitall
of his former Entertainement. But the Host refus'd
his Courteſie, in theſe wordes:—Nolo patriae meae Extinctori
debere vitam. (Eraſm. Apoph. lib. 6.) I will
not bee beholden to the Deſtroyer of my Countrey,
for my life: It ſhall never bee ſaid, I'le out-live
my Countrey, and ſo dyed amongſt his fellow-Cittizens.
But to come neerer home: let the Vnited Provinces
learne vs to vnite our hearts, and to—Looke
every man on the things of other Men:
               Alterius ſic Altera poſ. cit opem Horat. Eget Omnis amicus amico. They
finding any fallen into decay (Specially by deſignement
of Divine providence) doe voluntarily Contribute
towards their Neceſſities: and that, by a kinde of Silent
and cloſe Beneficence; That neither themſelves, who
give, may doe it in Oſtentation; nor they, who receive,
may feare exprobation. A pious policy, and worthy
imitation.
            And now, becauſe Examples are like flaming Beacons,
which fame and time ſet on Hills, to draw vs to a Defence
of vertue, whenſo'ere vice invades the Common-wealth

of man; Let theſe examples▪ fyred by precepts,
now flaming in your eyes from this ſaecred Hill of the
Palpit, excite you all, to a Defence of Church and
Cōmon-wealth; which are dangerouſly invaded by Deprau'd
policy, and private Ends,—Looke not every man
on his owne things, but every man alſo &amp;c. That ſo the
Multiplicity of our perſons being joyn'd in a vnity of
Affections vnto CHRIST, wee may be fit to Enioy
the Glorious viſion of the Trinity in Vnity,
Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt.
One onely Wiſe, Inviſible, incomprehenſible
Majeſty. To
whom, &amp;c.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

