
   
      
         
            Panegyrick to the high and mightie monarch, Charles by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. by Walter Forbes.
            Forbes, Walter, 17th century.
         
         
            
               1633
            
         
         Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01044
            STC 11151.5
            ESTC S123110
            24478633
            ocm 24478633
            27719
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01044)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27719)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1851:26)
         
         
            
               
                  Panegyrick to the high and mightie monarch, Charles by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. by Walter Forbes.
                  Forbes, Walter, 17th century.
               
               [8] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Wreittoun,
                  Edinburgh :
                  1633.
               
               
                  Signatures:  A⁴.
                  Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Poetry.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Jason ColmanSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Jason ColmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            PANEGYRICK
TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE MONARCH,
CHARLES
By the grace of GOD, King of Great BRITAINE,
FRANCE, and IRELAND,
Defender of the Faith. &amp;c.
            By WALTER FORBES.
            EDINBVRGH.
Printed by Iohn Wreittoun. 1633.
         
         
            
            EPIGRAMME.
            ILLuſtrious Top-bough of heroick Stemme,
            Whoſe head is crownd with Glorie's Anademe,
            My ſhallow Muſe, not daring to draw neare
            Bright Phoebus burning flammes in his Carreere:
            Yet knowing ſurely that Apollo ſhines
            Vpon the dung-hill, as on golden Mines.
            And knowing this the bountie of beſt Kings,
            To marke the giver, not the gifted things,
            Doth boldly venture in this pompous throng
            To greet thy Greatneſse with a Well-come ſong.
            And with the Py doth Ave Caeſar ſing,
            Whilſt grauer witts doe greater offrings bring.
         
      
      
         
            
            PANEGYRICK
            
               ADmyred Phoenix, ſpringing from thoſe Syres,
            Whoſe Soules the heav'n, whoſe merit Fame admyres,
            Whoſe memorie is wrapped up in roles,
            Keept by Eternitie above the Poles:
            Thryſe-bleſſed CHARLES, ſprung from thy royall Syre
            Great IAMES, whoſe Fame ſhall with this frame expyre:
            And yet beginne a freſh for to bee ſung,
            By ſacred Quires, in a celeſtiall toung;
            O thou the Subject of this wel-borne thought!
            Immortall King, haſt neither ſaid nor wrought
            Any thing yet, which can detract Thy praiſe,
            Since Thou'rt more old in vertues than in dayes:
            Bred in the bed of honour, Thou art bleſt
            With rare perfections, farre above the reſt
            Of Mortall kynde: for as Thy birth is great,
            So is thy minde, too high a marke for hate:
            Envy may ſpew her ſpight, yet cannot harme
            The Man, whom all the hoaſt of Heav'n doth arme:
            When bright Apollo circling in his Carre,
            Doth drive away the day-denuncing Starre,
            His pow'rfull rayes diffuſe in mortall myndes
            A ſweete deſire of day, which ſtraight vnbindes
            Sleep-fettered-fences, and his chearefull light
            Doth waſte all vapours cloſde in cloudie night:
            So my deare Phoebus whilſt Thy face doth ſhyne
            Vpon this Land, which by diſcent is Thine
            
            From hundred and eight Kings, thy chearefull rayes,
            Doe change my nights in Halcyonian dayes:
            And ſtraight diſſolve theſe frightfull formes of woe,
            Which did poſſeſſe my troubled thoughts agoe.
            What ſad affliction did my ſoule poſſeſſe,
            When Ibers ſtreames reflex'd thy glorious face;
            My groanes are turn'd to greetings, and my wrongs
            Are chang'd in hymnes and ſweete Syrenean ſongs:
            My ſpirit then, which for thy abſence groan'd,
            Rejoyceth now to ſee Thee heere enthron'd.
            What greater joy can I conceive, than ſee
            My native Prince, his native Throne ſupplie:
            Thryſe happie CHARLES with all thoſe gifts enricht,
            Which heavens allot to Mortals, I'me bewitcht
            In admiration of theſe royall parts,
            Which makes thee more then Monarch of Mens hearts,
            My heart and hands, and all ſubmitted heere,
            Atteſt the Heav'ns that I accompt Thee deare,
            And deareſt deare of all this All: I place
            My chiefeſt joyes in favour of thy face,
            I doe not poynt my praiſes, nor this Land,
            Although rich Nature with a liberall hand
            Hath bravely deckt her with all kynde of things,
            Which from her wombe for humane uſe foorth ſprings,
            Both Pan and Pales, pleaſures, Gemmes and Ore,
            Which wretched worldlings for their god adore:
            I, onely I, when all the World by Warre,
            Was boylde in blood as red as Marſes Starre,
            Did ſafely ſleepe, ſecurd from forraine Armes,
            And did diſdaine Bellonas lowd alarmes:
            The Gothes, the Danes, the Saxones heere did feele,
            And Normanes fierce, the furie of my Steele:
            Heere Caeſar pitcht his tents, and prowdly thought
            His Trophees o're our Tombes to Rome haue brought,
            
            But all in vaine, his conquering hand was ſtayed,
            And by his troupes a wall-divyding layed
            At Carons bankes, whoſe ruines yet may tell,
            How farre in worth I did his force excell:
            And as in Mars, ſo in Minervas field
            For Armes and Artes I keepe rich Pallas ſhield,
            Did not the Germans borrow light from mee,
            And France, which all poſteritie ſhall ſee
            Ev'n to the fatall doome, when All's in fire,
            Then ſhall the records of my worth expyre:
            Thus Gratious CHARLES daigne with a loving eye,
            The ſweete deſires of my pure heart to ſpy.
            Looke with what loue and with what chearefull part,
            I conſecrate to Thee, a loyall heart,
            My humbled knees loe! and my heav'd vp hands,
            The ſacred oath of loue from thee demands:
            Thryſe Glorious CHARLES, how amiable's thy face,
            Whoſe loving lookes my clowds of care doe chaſe:
            I reape more joy from this thy comming heere,
            Then e're Penelope of Vliſſes deare:
            Who after thouſand dangers did returne,
            And cur'd thoſe griefes, which did her bowels burne:
            O Thou more worthie then Vliſses farre,
            Honours bright Ray, Goodneſſe, and Greatneſſe, Starre,
            Long did I wiſh to ſee thy ſacred Face,
            My Townes and Temples with thy preſence grace:
            Great Ioves Vice-gerent looke with kynd aſpect
            On my Emporium EDINBVRGH, direct
            No oblique Rayes, accept in loue Her Showes,
            Her Verdant Glorie which ſo brauely goes,
            To doe Thee ſervice, all her coſt compenſe
            With kind acceptance, with her faults diſpenſe,
            And if in Her omiſſion ſhall bee found,
            Let Her Endevours braue, Defects confound:
            
            If Iove who all the ſtarrie Heavens doth guyde,
            Delights ſometimes at Creta to abyde,
            As in the place, where firſt hee ſuck't th'aire.
            And if Apollo, Delos doth repaire,
            Leaving his Claros, Tenedos behind;
            Thus ſince th'immortall gods haue ſuch a mind
            To Natiue ſoyle, it is no wonder then
            Though Demi-gods bee mov'd, and earth-borne men
            May ſtill Great CHARLES thy Scotland Creta bee,
            And Delos where thou may delight, to ſee
            The Naides and the Mountaine Nymphes moſt faire,
            With vnaccuſtomd clamours beat the Aire,
            The Satyres dance, the Coribantean Prieſts
            O're-joyde with joy to pulſe their paunting brieſts:
            O what great joy hath Thy deare preſence brought,
            Let all the Annalls through all age bee ſought,
            The like was never ſeene, the ſenſeleſſe ſtones
            Doe melt for joy, the Mountaines leap at once,
            The winds are calmde, and Neptunes lowdeſt roare
            Deavde with my ſhouts of joy is heard no more,
            And when the Aire with thy great Name I wound,
            The Mountaines anſwere, and the Rockes reſound,
            The Woods re-echo'd, and the Floods proclame,
            Melodious murmures hearing of thy Name,
            The Fiſhes, Fowles, and Beaſtes are ſtruck with wonder,
            Whilſt to the clouds I tell my Ioyes in thunder.
            Thou art my rich Palladium, while I keepe
            My God and Thee, I may ſecurely ſleepe,
            And feare no terrour nor diſturbing foe,
            Whilſt I haue Thee, to ante-vert my woe,
            GOD hath by nature wall'd me round about,
            And given mee Neptune ſentinell and ſcout,
            Whoſe toſſed Trident threatneth death to ſuch
            As dare in deepe diſdaine my borders touch
            
            And if by Fates I bee enforc'd to warre,
            And make my Lyons roare bee heard afarre
            O may it bee for ſome ſuch ſacred cauſe!
            As doth ſubſiſt with Heav'n and humane Lawes.
            O! may it bee to vindicate the wrong
            Of thy deare Siſter, and her Children young
            Whoſe matcleſſe Worth and vertues merite praiſe
            From all which canſet, ſing, or ſound ſweet layes,
            Till ſhee, (deare ſhee,) bee re-inveſt againe
            With her owne Rights, poſſeſt with her demaine,
            Till ſhee bee ſafely ſituat on her Rhyne,
            
            (And as the Moone amongſt the Starres doth ſhyne)
            Till ſhee in greatneſſe doe exceede all thoſe,
            Who to her glorie did their rage oppoſe,
            Till that Sun-gazing Eagle bee forc'd to fall
            Before her feete, and for her pardon call:
            Let's beat Alarmes, and let our Trumpets ſound,
            Let Cornets ſhrill the yeelding aire now wound,
            Let frightfull ſhouts of Souldiers pierce the skye,
            And reach the convexe of Olympus high
            Above the thundring cloudes, let noyſes make,
            The ſoaring Eagle for feare of CHARLES to ſhake.
            Let Vienn's walls aſtoniſht with our cry
            Like ſtubble before the fire, fall downe and fly
            Scattred with winds of his revenging wrath,
            Who in his hand hath pow'r of life and death.
            Let Rome with her ſeven hills bee ſhaken too
            And at thy Name O CHARLES obedient bow,
            (Heav'n grant I may victorious ſtill returne,
            Drunk with the blood of foes ſleepe in the vrne
            Of my Anceſtors, whoſe Manes ſhall bee glad,
            When it ſhall bee to future Ages ſaid
            That I in worth did ſo exceed them farre,
            As doth the Sun in light each little Starre)
            
            O may thy Enſignes ever bee diſplayed!
            O may my heart and hand bee nere diſmayde
            In thy defence, till all the World adore
            Thy dreadfull Name from Veſper till Aurore.
            Thine bee the Night and Day, may ſtarres bright ſhine,
            And Planets wander o're no Land but Thine,
            And when by Death Thou ſhall ſhut up Thy dayes
            Thy memorie ſhall ſtill inherite praiſe,
            And After-age ſhall Obeliskes vpreare,
            In which thy Woorth and Vertues ſhall appeare,
            High Phanes and Temples ſhall by Thy Name bee calld
            And Thou amongſt th'immortall Gods enſtalld
            Shall ſee the Offrings and the yearely Vowes,
            Poſteritie unto thy Fame allowes.
            Religious rites and games for Thee erected,
            Shall ſhow on Earth how high Thou waſt reſpected.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

