
   
      
         
            Fortunes tennis-ball a warning to all that are nursers of pride, for justice is knowne to be eagle-ey'd .... Or, A proviso for all those that are elevated, to take heed of falling, for fortune spights more the mightie then the poore: according to the poet: qui cadit in terram non habet unde cadit.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01084
            STC 11198
            Thomason E160_5
            ESTC R212820
            99835836
            99835836
            61
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01084)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:06)
         
         
            
               
                  Fortunes tennis-ball a warning to all that are nursers of pride, for justice is knowne to be eagle-ey'd .... Or, A proviso for all those that are elevated, to take heed of falling, for fortune spights more the mightie then the poore: according to the poet: qui cadit in terram non habet unde cadit.
               
               [2], 6 p.   
               
                  Printed,
                  [London] :
                  anno Dom. 1640.
               
               
                  An attack upon William Laud.
                  In verse.
                  With a title-page woodcut.
                  Place of publication from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Laud, William, 1573-1645 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2000-00
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2001-11
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-01
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-01
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Text and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            Fortunes Tennis-ball:

                  A warning to all that are Nursers of Pride,
                  For Justice is knowne to be Eagle-ey'd;
                  Those that will climb must look to have a fall,
                  For Fortune will pat down her Tennis-ball:
                  Let no man frown, for ile have all know it,
                  This wicked age must have a biting Poet.
               
            
            OR, A Proviso for all those that are elevated, to take heed of falling, for Fortune spights more the mightie then the poore: According to the Poet:

                  Qui cadit in terram non babet unde cadit.
               
            
            
            Printed Anno Dom. 1640.
         
         
            
            On the Frontispiece.
            SEe for the Frontispiece here a Cedar tree,
            Whereon sits Fortune in her Majestie.
            Those that presume t'aspire unto its top,
            She slilie gives the highest branch a lop,
            And topsie turvie they come tumbling down,
            As dazled with the brightnesse of her crown.
            You that look on the root, pray look no higher
            Then its true Motto, Cease too high t'aspire.
         
      
      
         
            
            Pride will have a fall.
            
               The downfall of Pride, and aspiring wits,
               Painted at full in their ague fits.
            
            
               PRide that aspiring girle, whose soaring minde
               Flyes swifter then the ayre or Easterne wind,
               Hath got a downfall, when she thought to fly,
               Time held her tresses, pulld her back, her eye
               Which still was fixt upon the highest spheere,
               Is, taught now to look lower, and her eare
               Set to a lower key, her loftie front
               Must be new Christned in afflictions font.
               Our Noblemen, me thinks, I now espie
               Like splendent stars fixt on our azure skie:
               Where each man studies to out-shine the rest,
               And he most proud that can be counted best.
               Yet know ye stars, who bespankle our skie,
               Know that the Sun is still the worlds eye,
               From him you shall receive your lustre, and
               Must pay't again when he shall it demand;
               Our King, I mean, who is this Ilands eye
               Of Government by true Epitomie:
               The moon oftimes doth strive t' eclipse the sun,
               As overgiddie stars of late have done,
               I read how Phaeton Don Phebus sonne,
               That he might know from what race he was sprung,
               Swelling with pride, desir'd his father graunt
               
                  This one boone to him, who thus himself did vaunt,
               That he might guid his fathers horses and,
               Have his bright charret at his owne command;
               Which thing was granted caus'd the world burne,
               And threw the child to his untimely urne,
               'Tis no expedient for a vulgar eye,
               To stare upon superiour Maiestie,
               Nor can you great ones, though you're crept so high,
               Say you can rule the bright translucent skie:
               No god can thunder but the mightie Iove,
               
               Yet all are gods as well as he above;
               Therefore be wise, and cease to high t' aspire
               Least you do burne in Phaetontike fire,
               Let Soll's bays alone, I mean the crowne,
               Those that soare high are aptest to fall downe,
               Have you not seen the loftie Cedar fall,
               When shrubs fast rooted stand within the vale,
               'Tis not your riches, nor your pomp of state,
               Honours nor strength, nor can powers mitricate
               Secure you here on earth, fate will overthrow,
               When blastering stormes of fortune 'gin to blow
               
                  Cesar and Pompey in their golden prime.
               Whose armes did thunder terror in their time
               Wear queld by fate, pride nought avail'd there then,
               Their graves were digd on earth amongst other men,
               Ye kinglike eagles which on this Cedar top
               Do perch, pray look how soon mans life doth stop,
               'Tis as soone here and yet 'tis sooner done,
               Then the hot summers rain, or winters sun.
               Set fast your footing lest you catch a fall
               We hope to rise at honours trumpets call.
               I've seen our Bishops on the wings of hope
               Flying with swiftnesse to the reverend pope
               Thinking to cloake all with their fallacies,
               
                  Which had no credence from our watchfull eyes;
               First Metrapollitan, could not a Miter
               Suffice your little pate would you be whiter
               Then La
                     •
                  vne can make you, you strive to pull downe
               Religion here to gain the Triple crown:
               and how you bend and bowe to th' altar plac't
               In an old corner which is 
                     •
                  oward the east,
               And how you cringe and creep when ye shall hear
               The name of Iesus touch your reverend eare.
               Displace the Levite who shall 
                     •
                  eed his flocke
               Twice on a sabbath from the common stock.
               Beware, repent, for now the Scottish club,
               Hath drove the into Englands powdering tube:
               Scholiers are bound to curse thy aspiring minde,
               Nor here, nor there they can no comfort finde,
               But they are mercifull, and still will pray
               That great Iove would be pleasd to send a day
               That they might hear you preach on tower hill,
               Which thing they hope will rid thee from all ill.
               If the low keele of a great ship shall fayle,
               What 'ist the better for a brave top sayle,
               Or if the roote of a fayre tree doth rot,
               How can we well believe the tree doth not,
               The root of this our kingdome rotten found:
               But yet I hope the kingdom is still sound,
               The Land the root which was made rotten quite
               For some there were through weaknesse of their sight.
               Can't view its splendor, the kingdomes still sicke
               Being troubled with the subtile politick,
               Better some members perish then the whole
               Body should languish in continuall thrall;
               Our Judges are corrupt, they should dispence
               The Law according to each mans offence
               Which they wrest other wayes, pride bids them rise
               And mount above the bright bespangled skies,
               
                  But judgement pulls them down and they shall finde
               What dangers hap to the aspiring minde,
               Hear this proud courtier, whose aspiring braines
               Are never fed but with strong Ela straines,
               Refraine to soare aloft, lest that you fall
               With prides projecters to eternall thrall;
               Seek not to stop petitioners who sue
               To right old wrongs, for 'tis your scarlet crew
               That's Banisht, which for bribes, or hope of gaine
               You'l gain the devill, and stop justice raigne.
               Next leave your swearing, you strive to invent
               New oathes, and make them but a complement,
               Gods name is bare of honour in our hearing
               And quite worn out by our blasphemous swearing,
               It's taken in vain by iesters every day,
               Vnlesse that actors sweare, it is no play:
               An execrable vice when you shall die
               Your selves in sinnes vault, and crucifie
               Our Saviour, hourlie make his wounds bleed fresh,
               And thrust sharpe pricking speares into his flesh.
               Leave off for shame lest judgement over take you,
               For when that comes your pride must needs forsake (you)
               O how you'l cringe and prate if a great Pear
               Shall daigne to lend the audience of his care,
               Or how officious will you seeme to be
               If you shall but espy his Majesty,
               Superiors you adore, like Persians
               You'l worship the bright sun, not country Pans.
               
               Inferiours shall not gaine that curtesey
               As once to wag your hat, or bend your knee,
               But near me Squashers, let me tell you plaine,
               If you use those things my pen shall complaine,
               Let pride perswade what she can I know,
               If Fortune once shall kicke you downe below
               
                  We shall espie you, your supposed skie
               Will prove at length but a meer timpany:
               Your moon will waine, your hour's of pride will waste
               Then what will come to those who're Ianus fac'd.
               Gentiles refraine the sharking cards and dice,
               Hearken to counsell and hear sound advice,
               What pride doth bid you spend, give to the poore,
               Let hospitallitie fatten at your dore,
               So shall you rise when prides associates fall,
               Who yeeld themselves as Fortunes Tennis-ball.
               Expect a while, and you shall quicklie see
               The derivation of their pedigree.
            
            
               If any one of this proud troupe should die
               Then who should write their epitaphs but I.
            
            
               An epitaph on a noble man.
               Here lies the Cedar who aspired so tall,
               That Joue took notice of, and caus'd him fall.
            
            
               On a gentleman.
               Here lies the verie timpanie of pride,
               Which made him breake at length, and so he died.
            
            
               On our great Bishop. W. L. A. B. C.
               If anie stranger shall ask who lies here,
               Let this new toomb this for inscription beare.
               Paint Pope and divell, make the stranger laugh;
               Mix his own shame, and ther's his epitaph.
            
            
               
               On a Iudge.
               He that iudged many is condemned now,
               Because 'twas prov'd by law he broke his vow;
               Pride was his Goddesse, he thought still t'aspire,
               But sure his grave is nere a whit the higher.
            
            
               On a Courtier.
               He that took many bribes thought to bribe death,
               But death dealt cunningly, took bribe, and breath.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

