
   
      
         
            The totall summe. Or No danger of damnation vnto Roman Catholiques for any errour in faith nor any hope of saluation for any sectary vvhatsoeuer that doth knovvingly oppose the doctrine of the Roman Church. This is proued by the confessions, and sayings of M. William Chillingvvorth his booke.
            Floyd, John, 1572-1649.
         
         
            
               1639
            
         
         Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01011
            STC 11117
            ESTC S118026
            99853235
            99853235
            18604
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01011)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18604)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 837:07)
         
         
            
               
                  The totall summe. Or No danger of damnation vnto Roman Catholiques for any errour in faith nor any hope of saluation for any sectary vvhatsoeuer that doth knovvingly oppose the doctrine of the Roman Church. This is proued by the confessions, and sayings of M. William Chillingvvorth his booke.
                  Floyd, John, 1572-1649.
               
               104 p.   
               
                  English College Press],
                  [Saint-Omer :
                  Permissu Superiorum. 1639.
               
               
                  By John Floyd.
                  Place of publication and press from STC.
                  A continued discussion of: Chillingworth, William. The religion of protestants a safe way to salvation.
                  A continuation of STC 11110 "The church conquerant over humane wit" and usually bound with it.
                  Running title reads: The assured saluation of Roman Catholiques.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Chillingworth, William, 1602-1644. --  Religion of Protestants a safe way to salvation.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-02
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-03
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2008-03
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE TOTALL SVMME. OR No danger of Damnation vnto Roman Catholiques for any Errour in Faith: Nor any hope of Saluation for any Sectary vvhatſoeuer that doth knovvingly oppoſe the Doctrine of the Roman Church.
            
               This is proued by the Confeſsions, and Sayings of M. William Chillingvvorth his Booke.
            
            Summa eſt quae conficitur ex Confeſsis.
            Aug. princ. dialect. cap. 3.
            Vnum eſt neceſſarium.
            Luc. 10. v. 42.
            Permiſſu Superiorum. 1639.
         
         
            
            
            The Preface.
            
               THIS Diſcourſe was intended at firſt, as the Concluſion and cloſing vp of the Treatiſe I termed, The Church Conquerant ouer human VVit: but being when I wrote it, in great doubt, that the ſayd Treatiſe was loſt in the tranſporting therof from one place to another (which often happens in Countries which are infeſted with warre) I reſolued to make this Diſcourſe more large, by the diſcouery of many other Contradictions in this our Aduerſary, and with the Refutation of ſuch tergiuerſations, as Cauillers might deuiſe, to ſtay piouſly diſpoſed Proteſtants, from yielding prompt and aſſured aſſent to this moſt important Verity.
            And as they who make Bills of Account, whē they haue ſet downe diſtinctly for their diſcharge, the particular Summes of expences; are accuſtomed in the end in few Cyphers to

abbreuiate the Totall Summe; ſo this Treatiſe comming after the former, as the Concluſion thereof; I haue giuen it the name of Totall Summe, the Argument handled therein being worthy of that ſtile. For what is the finall marke, the Totall, the All in all 
               Deū time, &amp; mandata eius obſerua: hoc eſt enim omnis homo. Eccleſiastae c. 12. v. 13. of our pious endeauours, labours, cares, ſollicitudes in this mortall life, but only to find out the true Religion, wherein one shall be ſure of his Saluation, if ſimply and conſtantly he belieue the Doctrines, and liue according to the lawes thereof.
            Verily this is the pith, the marrow, the Summe, the quinteſſence of all Controuerſies ventilated betwixt Proteſtants and vs: and in particular it was the ſole ſcope of that short ſubſtantiall Treatiſe Charity miſtaken by Proteteſtants; which being by D. Potter, in his VVant of Charity, impugned, was defended and confirmed by the learned labours and elucubrations of Charity maintayned. For the maine Cō
               trouerſy debated in theſe three bookes is, whether Roman Catholiques &amp; Proteſtants may both be ſaued in their ſeuerall Religions: or which comes to the ſame iſſue, ſeing Proteſtants grant we may be ſaued in our Religion, becauſe our Errours

are not Fundamentall and damnable, whether it is not want of Charity in vs, that we will not requite them with the like mild, gentle, and comfortable doome; but conſtantly maintayne, that Saluation cannot be had in any courſe of Separation, and Oppoſition againſt Doctrine propoſed by the Roman Church, as matter of faith.
            And though this our Catholique determination hath beene in the before named Treatiſe demonſtrated, eſpecially in the two laſt Chapters thereof; which shew all Sects &amp; Diuiſioners, all Protesters, and Oppoſers againſt the Church of Rome, to be guilty of the two moſt heynous crimes, Schiſme, &amp; Hereſy: yet I haue thought fit &amp; conuenient, to hādle this Totall of Controuerſies in a particular short Treatiſe: wherin omitting the former two heads of proofe, I haue vrged peculiar, and proper Arguments, grounded vpon euident Truths confeſſed, approued, confirmed euen by this our Aduerſary, whoſe Booke Proteſtants ſo much eſteeme as they ſtand thereon againſt the cleere demonſtrations for the Catholique Church brought by Charity maintayned.
            
            If in this very Booke, in which they ſo

much confide (which beareth the title, The Religion of Proteſtants a ſafe way to Saluation) the happy ſecurity of Roman Catholiques, and togeather the vnauoydable danger of their Oppoſers be proued, and proclamed; if no ſafe path to Saluation for English Proteſtants be shewed in his Treatiſe; but they be forced to goe the broad way, wherein the moſt damned Heretiques that liue vnder the cope of Heauen, not onely Anabaptiſts and Arians; but alſo the new Samoſatenians, or Socinians may be ſaued aſwell as they: this being shewed, our Proteſtants will be compaſſed about on euery ſide with the light and euidence of this eternally importing Truth, No hope of ſaluation out of the Catholique Roman Church.
            
            And then, God forbid, they should not yield vnto ſo cleere Euictions, but fall into the extreme miſery of peeuish obſtinacy, whereof S. Auguſtine ſayth, Nihil infelicius homine,
               Lib 3. contra l
                     •
                  t Petil c. 13.
                
               qui non vult cedere veritati, quâ ita concluditur, vt exitum inuenire non poſsit: Nothing more vnhappy and wretched, then the man that will not yield vnto that truth, wherwith he is ſo concluded and incloſed, as he knowes not which way to get out.
         
      
      
         
            THE TOTALL SVMME. OR The aſſured Saluation of Roman Catholiques &amp;c.
         
            An Aduertiſement.
            
               IN this treatiſe as in the other, I haue beene exact, and euen ſcrupulous, to rehearſe fully and largely our Aduerſaries formall words: many times alſo, though they were cited before, repeating them agayne, for the Readers greater eaſe, and to make this poynt whereon the Totall of our Eternity doth ſo much depend, cleere and plaine. In the text I cite the Page, Number and Line, or whē there is no number in the page, or when the place cited comes before any number, only page and line. I haue alſo in the margent quoted the Chapter and number, whereby the Reader may find the wordes in the ſecond edition of London.
         
         
            
            The firſt Conuiction.
            1. THis is drawne from the conceſſion of Protestants, that Roman Catholiques may be ſaued in their Religion; becauſe their errours are but litle ons, not Fundamentall, or in themſelues damnable; wheras Roman Catholiques neyther do, nor can by the principles of their Religion grant the ſame warrant to any whatſoeuer, that continues vnto death an oppoſer of the Church of Rome. An argument often vrged by Charity maintayned, grounded on a teſtimony of D. Potter, which you ſay he buildeth on, in almoſt 
               Pag. 279. n. 64. 
               fourty, yea more then in 
               Pag. 397. n 18. 
               an hundred places of his booke: and you, as often at leaſt, ſtriue and ſtruggle with this Argument, labouring to remoue the preſſing difficulties thereof, with the ſame progreſſe &amp; ſucceſſe, as Sifiphus
               Saxū verſat ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   proficit hilū. is ſaid to make, who to aduance a huge ſtone vp-hill, ſtriueth eternally in vaine. Your euaſions and ſhiftes, I will particularly refute, and lay open their falſhood and vanity; wherby it ſhalbe made apparent, that both the booke of Charity maintayned reſteth hitherto vnanſwered, and that this Argument drawne from the confeſſion of Proteſtants, is altogether vnanſwerable. I ſhall firſt propoſe our Argument, ſtrenthened with D. Potters ſuffrage. Secondly, diſcouer how impudently you deny D. Potters text. Thirdly, how at laſt you acknowledge it, &amp; giue an explication therof full of groſſe ignorance. Fourthly, how weakly, and in vayne you would ſeeme to contemne this Argument as poore, and ſeely. Fiftly, I will declare the force of this Argument, and ſhew the reaſon why Proteſtants (that be wiſe, and not diſtempered with furious zeale) dare not condemne the Roman Religion &amp; Communion, as damnable of it ſelfe.
               
Finally, that not only Roman Catholikes, but that you your ſelues dare not maintaine, that the Religion of Protestants is a ſafe way to ſaluation; yea you grant the ſame not to be free from errours damnable of themſelues.
            
            
               The Argument propounded. §. 1.
               
               2. THe Argument I ſet downe in this manner. No man ſhalbe, or can be damned eternally, for errours, which be not damnable of themſelues. This is cleere; Becauſe God being iuſt, who renders to euery one according to their deſerts, cannot puniſh men more then their offences do of themſelues deſerue, but rather ſomewhat vnder their merit. But the errours pretended to be found in the Roman Church, cannot of thē
                  ſelues deſerue eternall damnation, being but veniall, but little ones, &amp; not damnable of themſelues, as Proteſtants grant. This Aſſumption needs no proofe, being notorious ouer all England. For what more dayly and vſuall, what more frequent and familiar, then for Proteſtants to reproach vs with want of Charity; becauſe we will not yield their errours not to be damnable nor deſtructiue of ſaluation, as they grant ours to be. This is cōfirmed by the often reiterated confeſſion of D. Potter ſpecially pa. 77. where he hath theſe words:

                     To forſake the errours of the Roman Church, and not to ioyne with her in thoſe practiſes we account erroneous, we are forced of neceſſity. For though in themſelues they be not damnanable to them which belieue as they profeſſe; yet for vs to profeſe what we belieue not, were without queſtion damnable. And they with their errours (by the grace of God) might go to Heauen, when we for our hypocriſy and diſſimulation without repentance, ſhould certainly be condemned to Hell. And agayne: To him who

in ſimplicity of heart belieues and profeſſeth them, &amp; withall feareth God and worketh righteouſneſſe, to him they ſhall proue veniall: ſuch a one ſhall by the mercy of God be deliuered from them, or be ſaued with them. But he that againſt Fayth and Conſcience ſhall go along with the ſtreame, to profeſſe &amp; practiſe them, becauſe they are but little-ones, his Caſe is dangerous, and without repentance deſperate. And againe. pag. 19. We belieue the Roman Religion ſafe, that is, not damnable to ſome, ſuch as belieue what they profeſſe; but we belieue it not ſafe, but very dangerous (if not certainly damnable) to ſuch as profeſſe it, when they belieue the contrary.
               
            
            
               Your impudent deniall of the text. §. 2.
               
               3. YOu acknowledge that Charity maintayned vrgeth this teſtimony of D. Potter, &amp; builds his diſcourſe theron often: which you ſay, he doth fraudulētly as an egregious Sophister, impudently without conſcience or modesty outfacing the truth. For Proteſtants
                     Pag. 400. n. 28. Cap. 7. n. 2
                        •
                     . you ſay, neither do, or euer did acknowledge, that our errours are not damnable: and that you for your part, though you were on the rack, ſhould not confeſſe it.
As for D. Potter you deny, that he ſayd of the errours he imputeth to the Roman Church, though in themſelues they be not damnable; yea you conteſt that his words are, though in themſelues they be damnable. 
                  Cap. 5. n. 58. lin. 8. Pag. 275. lin. 4. 
                     D. Potter confeſſeth no ſuch matter, but only that he hopes that your errours, though in themſelues ſufficiently damnable, yet by accident did not damne all that held them; ſuch he meanes, and ſayes, as were excuſably ignorant of the truth.
                  
And 
                     Cap. 5. n. 26. lin. 17. 
                  pag. 263. n. 26. Where doth D. Potter ſay any ſuch thing as you pretend &amp;c. He ſayth indeed, that

though your errours were in themſelues damnable, and full of great impiety; yet he hopes thoſe amongst you who were inuincibly ignorant of the truth, might by Gods great mercy haue their errours pardoned. Thus you. And you repeate it, almoſt in the ſame wordes, in an hundred paſſages of your Booke, ſtill noting theſe wordes, though in themſelues damnable, in a diſtinct character, as D. Potters formall text, which yet is no where found in any part of his Treatiſe.
               4. And in this denial of the text, in this conteſtation, that D. Potter ſaid of our Errours, though in themſelues they be damnable, you with great ſhew of confidēce perſiſt, till almoſt the very finiſhing of your Booke. Then being but three leaues from the end (as Theeues when they are ready to be caſt of the ladder, make true confeſſions) ſtrucken with remorſe of conſcience, you vtter this depoſition againſt your ſelfe Cap. 7. n. 29. Indeed D. Potter ſayes of your errours, though in themſelues they be not damnable to them which belieue as they profeſſe; yet for vs to profeſse what we belieue not, were without question damnable, Is this true? Doth D. Potter ſay of our errous though in themſelues they be not damnable? Hath he theſe very words indeed? See thē whether the reproach which you caſt vnworthily on Charity maintayned, the reproach of outfacing the truth without conſcience or modestie, do not fall heauily on your owne head. For now vpon the ending of your Booke you confeſſe, that D. Potter indeed ſayes of our Errours, though in themſelues they be not damnable, whereas before you ſaid and repeated it againe and againe, with deepe proteſtation, and inſolent inſultation againſt your Aduerſary, that D. Potter ſaid no ſuch thinge; yea that his wordes were the plaine contradiction, to wit, though in themſelues they be

damnable, and full of great impiety. How this can be excuſed from the crime of forgery, I do not ſee.
               5. More cunningly &amp; in ſhew not ſo enormouſly, but indeed no leſſe fraudulently &amp; maliciouſly, do you change the pointing of D. Potters text, and ſo turne his aſſertion into the plaine contrary. He pag. 79. in the name of Engliſh Proteſtants ſayth of the Roman Religion: We belieue it ſafe, that is, by Gods great mercy not damnable to ſome, ſuch as belieue what they profeſſe. Thus he; and he maketh a Comma between ſome, and ſuch, to deuide them, and to ſhew that ſuch is vſed not to limit the ſome that are not damned; but to declare who they be, to wit, all ſuch as cordially belieue our Roman Religion and profeſſe it. You reciting his words Pag. 404. lin. 20. Cap. 7. n. 29. leaue out the Comma, and ioyne ſome and ſuch togeather, making the Doctour ſay, We belieue her Religion ſafe, that is by Gods great mercy not damnable to ſome ſuch as belieue as they profeſse. As who ſhould ſay, D. Potter grants our Religion ſafe, and not damnable to ſome, who in ſimplicity of heart belieue and profeſſe it, not to all ſuch, but ſome ſuch only. Againſt his expreſſe Tenet and Pag. 76. lin. 26. text, yea further you vrge this text corrupted by your diſpunction thereof as an Argument, that D. Potter holdes our errours damnable in themſelues. Pag. 306. lin. 1. 
                     Cap. 5. n. 105. lin. 23. 
                  It is remarkable, that he confeſſes your errours to ſome men not damnable, which cleerely importes, that according to his iudgment they were damnable of themſelues, though by accident, to them who liued and dyed in inuincible ignorance, they might proue not damnable. Thus you argue vpon your owne corruption of D. Potters text. For in truth he confeſſes the errours imputed vnto vs not to be damnable, and our Religion to be ſafe, not to ſome ſuch only, but to all ſuch as belieue as they profeſſe, to all ſuch

as be not hypocriticall Profeſſours, but profeſſe it in ſimplicity of heart, belieuing it to be true. Nor doth he ſay, that vnto ſuch Roman belieuers our errours are not damnable by accident (as you feigne) but the expreſſe contrary, that euen in themſelues they be not damnable to them. Behold how oppoſite is D Potters true ſentence, to that you haue forged for him. You make him 
                     Pag. 278 lin. 8. cap. 5. n. 61. ſay, Our errours are euen in themſelues damnable, and only by accident pardonable; whereas he ſayth the contrary, they are in themſelues but littleons, but venial, and conſequently, if any ſincere Roman Catholiques be damned, this is by accident, by reaſon of ſome extrinſecal damnable circumſtance, not by the intrinſecal malignity of their errours, not by the force ſuch errours haue in themſelues, and in their owne nature to merit damnation.
               
               6. But ſome may obiect, that D. Potter doth not ſay abſolutely, Our errours be not in themſelues damnable, but only, not in themſelues damnable to them that belieue as they profeſſe, which is a different thinge. I anſwer, this is a ſubtilty which findeth a difference where there is no diuerſity. As to ſay of a potion, that it is not of it ſelfe deadly to ſuch as drinke it, &amp; take it into their bowells and heart, is all one as to ſay, it is deadly to none, but harmeleſſe and innoxious in it ſelfe: ſo to ſay, our errours are not in themſelues damnable to ſuch as heartily belieue and profeſſe them, is as much as to ſay, they are of themſelues damnable vnto none, but abſolutely veniall &amp; of their owne nature not deſtructiue of Saluation. For to whome may they be in themſelues damnable, if they be not ſo to them that take them into their heart by ſincere and cordiall beliefe. As none can be damned for ſinne, but ſuch as commit ſinne; ſo none can be damned for erring, but ſuch as erre, and are guilty of erring.

Now thoſe that in their heart belieue not errours, do not erre, nor are guilty of erring: wherefore, ſuch neither are, nor can be damned for erring, or holding of errours. For if they hypocritically, profeſſe Errours which they do not belieue, they be damnable indeed; but not for erring, but for their hypocriſy and diſsimulation, as D. Potter truly ſayth.
            
            
               Your ignorant expoſition of D. Potter. §. 3.
               
               7. HAuing at laſt acknowledged D. Potters text, that he ſaid of our errours, though in themſelues they be not damnable, you Cap. 7. n. 29. initio. tell vs; that we miſtake his meaning, by taking a ſuppoſition of a confeſsion, for a confeſsion, a Rhetoricall conceſsion of the Doctours, for a poſitiue aſſertion. For to ſay, though your Errours be not damnable we may not profeſſe them, is not to ſay, Your errours are not damnable, but only through they be not: As if you ſhould ſay; Though the Church erre in points not fundamental; yet you may not ſeparate from it; or,
Though we do erre in belieuing Chriſt really preſent, yet our errour frees vs from Idolatry.
                   I preſume you would not thinke it fayrely done, if any man ſhould interprete theſe your ſpeaches, as confeſſions that you do erre in points not fundamentall; that you erre in belieuing the Real Preſence. And therefore you ought not to haue miſtaken D Potters wordes, as if he confeſſed the Errours of your Church not damnable; when he ſayes no more, then this, though they be not damnable, or ſuppoſe, or put caſe they be not damnable.
                  
Thus you. Wherein your falſhood is notable,Pag. 77. and your ignorance admirable. Firſt, it is falſe, that D. Potter ſayes no more but this, though they be not damnable. For beſides this he ſayth, that Proteſtants who belieue them to be errours, muſt not preſume to

profeſſe them becauſe they are but littleons. He ſaith in the name of all Proteſtants: We belieue the Roman Religion to be ſafe, that is, not damnable to ſuch as belieue as they profeſse. We hope and thinke very well of all thoſe holy and deuout ſoules which informer ages liued and died in the Church of Rome &amp;c. We doubt not but they obtayned pardon of all their ignorances. Nay our Charity reaches further to All thoſe at this day who in ſimplicity of heart belieue the Roman Religion, and profeſſe it. Be theſe Rhetoricall Conceſsions, not Poſitiue Aſſertions, that the errours which Proteſtants impute to the Roman Church are not damnable of thē
                     ſelues; but onely by accident, when they are hypocritically againſt conſcience profeſſed?
               8. Secondly, I am amazed that you a Maister of Arts of Oxford, of ſo long ſtanding are ignorant of the difference in ſpeach, betwixt the Preſent Tenſe, and the Preter imperfect, which euery man and woman by common ſenſe doth feele and perceaue. For the particle though, ioyned with a verbe of the Preſent Tenſe, doth ſuppoſe a thing preſent, and exiſting in reality &amp; truth: ſo that, if you will ſuppoſe the exiſtence of a thing by imagination, or in conceyt onely; you muſt vſe the Preter imperfect. Wherfore neyther the Author of Charity maintayned, nor any Catholique that is intelligent, will ſay to you in the Preſent Tenſe, as you make him, Though the Church do erre in points not fundamentall, yet you muſt not ſeparate from it; but in the Preter imperfect; Though the Church did erre in points fundamentall, yet you were not to ſeparate from her. Nor will he, or any Catholique that is wiſe, vſe that eyther ſottiſh or impious ſpeach you haue penned for him, Though we erre in belieuing Christ really preſent, yet our errour frees vs from Idolatry. God forbid. This were not a Rhetoricall Conceſſion,

but a Diabolical Profeſſion, that our beliefe of the Reall preſence is an errour. A true Catholique that can vtter his mind in good Engliſh will ſay, Though we did erre in belieuing the Reall Preſence of our Lords Body in the Euchariſt; yet this errour would free vs from Idolatry. Thus the examples you bring of Rhetoricall Conceſsions make againſt you, being in deed poſitiue Aſſertions, and ſhew your diſcourſe to be neyther good Logick, nor Rhetoricke, nor Grammer.
               
               9. And I pray you, the Propoſition you haue forged for D. Potter, though the errours of the Roman Church be in themſelues damnable, and full of great impiety, yet by accident they do not damne all that hold them; is it not a Poſitiue Aſſertion that our doctrines are damnable and full of great impiety in D. Potters opinion? Wherfore this propoſition which is truly D. Potters: though the errours of the Roman Church be not in themſelues damnable, yet Protestants who know them to be Errours, may not profeſſe them, is a poſitiue Aſſertion, that our ſuppoſed errours be not damnable in his iudgement. Should one ſay to you, though in your iudgement you belieue Christ our Sauiour not to be true God, yet you dare not profeſſe it outwardly for feare of the fagot; would you take this as a Rhetoricall ſuppoſition, not as a Reall accuſation, that you are an Infidell in your heart? Is it poſſible you ſhould be guilty of ſo groſſe ignorance and non-ſenſe as this? No verily. But perchance the matter is this: you ſay 
                     Pag. 395. l. 3. If this did appeare, to perſuade any man to continue a Proteſtant, were to perſuade him to continue a Foole. that Proteſtants, to whome the Roman Religion appeareth, though but probably, the ſafer, cannot continue Protestants, except they continue fooles. Now Protestants by this confeſſion of D. Potter, cannot but ſee apparently, the Roman Religion to be the ſafer. Wherfore, that, this notwithſtanding, they may continue

ſtill Proteſtants; you would make them ſuch fooles, as to belieue, that, though, ioyned with a verbe in the Preſent Tenſe, doth import onely an imaginary, not a reall ſuppoſition. Wherefore if you ſhould ſay (as in effect you do ſay) though the Religion of Proteſtants be falſe and damnable, yet I will do my beſt to defend it; Proteſtāts muſt be ſuch fooles as to take this, not as a poſitiue aſsertion, that their Religion is falſe &amp; damnable in your iudgment; but as a Rhetoricall Conceſſion, as if you had ſaid; Imagine, or put caſe, the Religion of Proteſtants be falſe and damnable. I hope Protestants will be wiſer then to be made ſuch fooles by you as to continue in a Religion which cannot be maintayned, but by ſuch fopperies as theſe.
            
            
               Your Vanity in contemning the foreſayd Argument. §. 4.
               
               9. You many times ſeeme to contemne and ſcorne the Argument drawne from the confeſſion of Proteſtants, and the former teſtimony of D. Potter. You ſay we rely vpon his priuate Opinion, vpon his vncertaine 
                  Pag. 226. n. 63. 
                  Charitable hope, that 
                  Pag. 116. n. 158. in fine. 
                  his thinking ſo is no reaſon we ſhould thinke ſo, except we thinke him infallible, that whoſoeuer is moued with his argument is ſo ſimple &amp;c. Wherin you may ſeeme (which happens very ſeldome) to agree with D. Potter, who doth much ſleight our arguing from the Confeſſion of our Aduerſaries page. 81. If they haue no better ground of their beleefe then their Aduerſaries Charitable iudgment of their errours; they will be ſo farre from conuincing their Aduerſaries of lacke of wiſedome, that themſelues cannot eſcape the imputation of folly.
               
               10. Thus the Doctour endeauours to lay the imputation of folly vpon vs, for vrging our aduerſaries fauourable

iudgement of our errours, as a good argument, that may moue men to imbrace our Religion. But in this charging vs with folly, his owne lacke of wiſedome and conſideration may be conuinced, by what he writeth ſome few pages before againſt zelots: for theſe he condemneth not onely of want of charity, but alſo of lacke of wiſedome, for iudging ſo ſeuerely of our errours as to cut vs of from hope of Saluation. Pag. 76. The Roman Churches communion (ſayth he) we forſake not, no more then the Body of Christ; whereof we acknowledge the Church of Rome a member, though corrupted. And this cleeres vs from the imputation of Schiſme, whoſe property it is, to cut of from the Body of Christ, and hope of Saluation, the Church from which it ſeparates. And if any Zelots amongst vs haue proceeded to heauier cenſures, their zeale may be excuſed, but their Charity and Wiſedome cannot be iustifyed. Thus he. From which words I conclude a double truth; the one againſt you, the other againſt D. Potter himſelfe. The firſt; that this Charitable iudgement about the Saluation of Roman Catholiques, becauſe their errours are ſmall, and not in themſelues damnable, is not the priuate opinion of D. Potter; but the cenſure and doome of the whole Proteſtant engliſh Church, condiſtinct from zelots, or Puritans. For how can this whole Church be iuſtified, and cleered from the imputation of Schiſme, by reaſon of her Charitable iudgement of our errours, if this be not the Charitable iudgement of this whole Church, but only the opinion of D. Potter, and of ſome other few priuate Proteſtants? Secondly I gather, that this iudgement is not onely according to Chriſtian Charity; but alſo according to Chriſtian Wiſedome, and floweth from the rules and Principles of them both. Otherwiſe what cauſe or reaſon hath D. Potter to charge Zelots, who

iudge not fauourably of our errours, with want not only of Charity, but alſo of wiſedome: Their Charity (ſaith he) and Wiſedome cannot be iustified? If the iudgment of Proteſtants ſo fauorable about our errours be of meere Charity, not wiſe, not prudent, not ſolidely grounded on truth; why may not the wiſedome of Zelots, who will not conſent thereunto be iustified? On the other ſide, if the iudgment of Proteſtants be conforme to Christian wiſedome and Diuine truth, what wiſedome is it in D. Potter to charge vs with folly and want of wiſedome, for building and relying theron?
               11. Beſides, this iugdment of Proteſtants, that we may be ſaued in our Religion, our errours not being damnable, if it be voyde of wiſdome, and not ſolidly grounded on truth; how is it charitable, that is, how can it proceed from true Christian Charity? If fond loue and affection to the ſaluation of Creatures, not guided by the rules of Christian truth, be Christian charity; then the iudgment of Origen were ful of Chriſtian Charity, who extended ſaluation euen vnto Diuells. Wherfore your iudgment, that we may be ſaued, becauſe our errours are not damnable, cannot be charitable, vnleſſe it be conforme to the rules, and principles of Chriſtian truth and wiſdome: on which if it be grounded, why may we not build, and rely theron? Why may we not without imputation of folly, make this one pillar of our comfort, and conſtancy in the Roman Communion and Fayth?
               12. Adde hereunto, that it is euen ridiculous in D. Potter and other Proteſtantes of his ſtampe, to brag and boaſt as they doe, that forſooth it is 
                     Cap. 4. n. 63. lin. 22. Exceſſe of charity may make him cē
                     ſure your errours more fauorably, thē he ſhould do. 
                  exceſſe of their Charity and good will to the Roman Church, which makes them to iudge ſo kindly and fauourably of her errours.

For, by their wordes and writings, they ſhew themſelues to be voyd of all loue and Charity, and to be full of bitter zeale and paſſion towardes her; ſo farre, that though in their conſcience they iudge her free from damnable errours, yet in their paſsion they hate, &amp; abhorre, rate and reuile her, as if ſhe were the vildeſt Religion in the world. Theſe ſpeaches of D. Potter againſt her, ſhe hath many wayes played the Harlot, and in that regard deſerued a bill of diuorce from Christ, and the detestation of Chriſtians: the proud and curst Dame of Rome, which takes vpon her to reuell in the houſe of God: Popery is the contagion and plague of the Church. Theſe ſpeaches I ſay euery man will preſently perceiue, that they are voyd of Charity, wordes of contumely and reproach, proceeding not from cleere and calme iudgment, but from the fuming fornace of paſsion: you produce them, as if D. Potter by them did ouerthrow what we haue proued to be his iudgment, that our errors be not damnable: But in very truth they be only paſſionate ſpeaches, vttered without iudgment, reaſon, or diſcretion, yea againſt his owne iudgment; tokens of his mortall auerſion from that Church, in whome he can finde no mortall or damnable errour. It is not then Charity or kind affection, or any good will to Roman Catholiks, which moueth D. Potter, &amp; ſuch other Miniſters to maintaine the errours of the Roman Church to be but littleones, and not damnable; but becauſe they dare not hold the contrary, in regard of the vnchriſtian abſurdities, which they perceiue to be conſequent theron, as by the next Section will appeare.
            
            
               
               All Chriſtians of former ages damned, if the errours of the Roman Church be damnable of themſelues. §. 5.
               
               13. CAn any abſurdity be more vaſt and vnchriſtian then this contained in the title of this paragraph? What wonder, if Proteſtants (that be moderate, and not carried away with precipitous zeale) through horrour to be forced vnto this immanity, dare not affirme, that our errours are in themſelues damnable; though otherwiſe their little loue towardes vs conſidered, they could do it with all their heart. To proue this vaſt abſurdity to be conſequent vpon the ſaid propoſition, we muſt ſuppoſe, what no man doth or can deny, that for many ages before Luther, all the famous men for learning and ſanctity, who by heroicall actes of Charity, and other Chriſtian vertues, and working of Miracles maintained the credit of the Chriſtian name, held the doctrines of the Roman Church, which Proteſtants contend to be erroneous. The fame is alſo euident concerning the Fathers of the more Primitiue times, and is confeſſed by Proteſtantes,Defence againſt the reply of Cartwright pag. 47. namly D. Whitgift late Archbiſhop of Canterbury: Almost all the Biſhops and Writers of the Greeke Church, and of the Latin alſo, for the most part were ſpotted with the doctrines of freewill, of Merit, of Inuocation of Saintes, and ſuch like; So that, if the Doctrines of the Roman Church, which Proteſtantes traduce as erroneous, be damnable of themſelues; it is conſequent, that the moſt famous Biſhops, Doctours and Saints in ſo many former Chriſtian ages were guilty of errours in themſelues, and of themſelues damnable: which being ſo, they ſhould be

all certainly damned, without any hope of their Saluation.
               14. This conſequence I proue by what you by write Cap. 7. n. 26. lin. 30. 
                  pag. 403. lin. 30. They that haue vnderstanding and meanes to diſcouer their errours, and neglect to vſe them; we dare not flatter with ſo eaſy a cenſure as to giue them hope of Saluation. But the eminent Fathers and Chriſtian Saintes of ſo many ages before Luther, had ſufficient vnderſtanding, and meanes to diſcouer their errours; and yet neuer made vſe of them. They had excellent vnderſtandings, they were verſt in all manner of ſciences, &amp; they had the holy Scripture, which you ſay is the only meanes to know all neceſſary truth, and to diſcouer all damnable errours; a meanes not only ſufficient, but alſo, in your iudgment, moſt playne, and eaſy; ſo that men not only may, but alſo cannot but therin diſcouer which be damnable errours, except they wilfully ſhut their eyes againſt the light. Therefore there is no hope of the ſaluation of the Ancient Fathers, and Saintes of former Chriſtian ages, if your Propoſition be true, they who had ſufficient vnderstanding and meanes to diſcouer their errours, and neglected to vſe them, there is for them no hope of Saluation. Moreouer, Cap. 6. n. 64. lin 8. 
                  pag. 279. num. 64. lin. 8. you ſay, that which is in it ſelfe damnable, will actually bring damnation vpon them, that keep themſelues in it, by their owne voluntary and auoydable fault; But the Ancient Fathers and holy Saints in the ages before Luther held the doctrines of the Roman Church which you account damnable, full of great impiety and Idolatry, &amp; they kept thēſelues in them (according to your groūds) by their owne voluntary and auoydable fault: for they had ſufficient meanes to diſcouer their errours, to wit, they had the holy Scripture, wherin (as you ſay) theſe

errours are diſcouered, not onely with ſufficient, but alſo with abundant clarity, 
                     Preface. n. 11. lin. 17. How is it, poſſible any thing ſhould be plainer forbidden, then the worship of Angels &amp;c. pag. 181. n. 86. Places of ſcripture againſt our errours as cleere as the light at noone. that there cannot poſsibly be greater; you muſt therefore of neceſſity grant, that theſe damnable and impious errours (if they be ſuch as you ſay they are) brought actually damnation vpon the Fathers and Saints of former ages. Agayne, page 290. lin. 2. of liuing in the Communion of the Roman Church, and approuing her doctrines and practiſes you ſay, Cap. 5. n. 86. 
                  Though we hope it was pardonable in them who had no meanes to know their errour; yet of its owne nature, and to them who did or might haue knowne their errour, it was certainely damnable. Now the holy Fathers, and Chriſtian Saints of former ages might haue knowne our errours (if they be errours) becauſe they had the holy Scriptures in which, you ſay, ſuch errours are diſcouered, &amp; their damnable falſhood, ſo plainly, as nothing can be more: If then you ſay true, that the Roman Religion, is full of great impiety and damnable doctrines, it is euidently conſequent by your principles, that all holy Biſhops, Doctours, and Saints who are confeſſed to haue held the ſayd doctrines, are certainly damned for euer, no hope remaining of their ſaluation. Wherfore the reaſon why Proteſtants hold our Religion ſafe, and a ſure way to Heauen, as being free from damnable errour, is not Charity and exceſſe of good will they beare to our perſons, as they pretend; but feare of the vaſt abſurdity, which they ſee conſequent thereupon, that ſo many former ages, and worldes of holy Biſhops, Doctours, Conuerters of Nations, workers of Miracles, and admirable Saints, are certainly damned.
               15. There be many Proteſtant Miniſters that could find in their hearts to grant this dismall poſition of the damnation of the ancient euer eſteemed Saints, if the

ſame would ſtand them in ſteed to maintaine the diuiſion from the Roman Church; yet they dare not venture cleerly to auerre ſo much, for feare that this would produce the contrary effect, and moue many of their followers to recoyle back from them. For in the ſeparation made by Luther from the Roman Church, there be many piouſly inclined mindes, carefull of their future eternity either of weale or woe, cordially deſirous to be ſecure of the happines of the one, and mighty fearefull to fall into the miſery of the other. Should Proteſtant Miniſters cleerly deliuer their mindes, that the Roman Religion is damnable euen of it ſelfe, a direct way to Hell, and that ſuch as walke, or haue walked therein are certainely damded; theſe piouſly diſpoſed and timerous Soules would feele horrour to be of the Proteſtant Religion, which cannot be the way of ſaluation, except the Roman Chriſtianity ſo great, ſo glorious, ſo continued from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, contayning within her boſome, ſo many worlds of holy Biſhops, learned and pious Paſtours, and of admirable Saints be damned, at leaſt all the intelligent Profeſſors therof. The apprehenſion of this dreadfull and dangerous ſtate amazed euen the ſtout and curſt heart of Luther, whē he ſaw himſelfe engaged in a courſe, out of which he could not iſſue with ſaluation, except ſo many former ages of Saints were damned. 
                     Praefat. de abroganda Miſſa prinatâ, Quoties palpitauit mihi tremulum cor. &amp; reprehendens obiecit illud fortiſsimum argumentum; Tu ſolus ſapis, tot ne errāt vniuerſi? Tanta ſaecula ignorauerunt? 
                  How often (ſayth he) did my heart tremble and pant within my breast, obiecting againſt me that most stronge argument; Art thou onely wiſe? Did ſo many Christian worldes in former ages all erre? What, if perhaps thou thy ſelfe be in errour, and draw an infinite number of Souls after thee into errour, to be damned eternally with thee?
               
               16. You ſay, Pag. 397. n. 17. that your Saluation doth not depend

on ours, that you might be ſaued though we were Turkes and Pagans: this I well belieue. But now that the Roman Church is not Turciſme, nor Iudaiſme, but a Kingdome of Chriſt diffuſed ouer the earth, the onely Christian Catholique Religion in the world, which is come from our Sauiour by conſpicuous linage, and line of ſucceſſion by the Apoſtles; what Chriſtian will not tremble to be in a ſtate, wherein he muſt expect Saluation from Chriſt, by damning that Religion, which is ſo notoriouſly deſcended from him?
               17. The innated inſtinct of Godlineſſe, the ſparkes of Piety which nature hath hidden within the bowels of euery reaſonable ſoule, moue men to acknowledge and reuerence that Religion, as being of God, which they ſee marked and adorned with diuine and ſupernaturall workes, aboue the courſe and forces of nature. Which Maiesty of miracles ſhining ſo gloriouſly in the Roman Church, can any man that is Religious &amp; fearfull of God, iudge the ſame damnable, and venture his ſoule on the damnation thereof? Wherefore not Loue, not Charity, not Goodwill to the Roman Catholiques is that which moueth Proteſtants to pronunce her Religion ſafe, and free from damnable errour; but the horrour of damning togeather with vs, innumerable millions of holy and heauenly men of former Chriſtian worlds.
               18. Finally Proteſtants vnder pretence of fauouring and comforting vs ſeeke their owne comfort &amp; ſolace; that they may find ſome ſhelter of hope of ſaluation vnder the wings of the Roman Religion, who in their oppoſition againſt her find none, or only poore, meagre and miſerable hopes. For, laying for ground this truth, that our Religion is ſafe; &amp; then aſſuming this falſhood,

that theirs is the ſame with ours for ſubſtance and in all neceſſary points; they cheere vp many drooping hearts, that can feele no comfort in hoping to be ſaued by damning the Roman Church: ſo that care of their owne Sparta, deſire to ſtay the wiſer ſort of their followers in their courſe of Diuiſion from the Roman Church; this I ſay is one of the reaſons which maketh Miniſters to preach the certainty of Saluation in our Church, and to maske themſelues with a vizard of Charity and Friendſhip towards vs.
            
            
               That Protestant Religion is not ſafe, euen in your iudgment. §. 6.
               
               19. YOu ſay in your Preface n. 39. that you haue not vndertaken the peculiar defence of the doctrine of the Church of England; nor of any other particular Proteſtant Church, but the common cauſe of all Protestants, to maintayne the doctrine of them all; not that it is abſolutely true, (for, that is impoſsible ſeing they hold contradictions) but that it is free from all impiety and damnable errour. This drift pretended and profeſſed ſo gloriouſly in the Title and Preface of your booke, you croſſe and contradict in the boſome, and heart thereof, condemning Proteſtants of errours, euen in themſelues, damnable, as I ſhall make good and cleere by the foure enſuing teſtimonies. Firſt Pag. 218. lin. 34. I would not be mistaken, as though I thought the errours of ſome Protestants inconſiderable thinges, and matters of no moment: for the. Truth is, I am very fearfull, that ſome of their opinions either as they are, or as they are apt to be mistaken, though not of themſelues ſo damnable, but that iust and holy men may be ſaued with them; yet are frequent occaſions of remiſnes, and not ſeldome of ſecurity in ſinning &amp;c. Behold you, who in

your Preface made all Proteſtants ſecure of their Saluation, becauſe free from errours in themſelues damnable; now are very fearfull of them, and dare not acquit them of errours conſiderable, of moment, in themſelues damnable, though not ſo damnable, but iuſt and holy men may be ſaued, with them; Which qualification of your errours doth not ſo temper or allay their malignity, as to make them leſſe damnable then thoſe you impute to the Roman Church: ſeing you often acknowledge, that with them, and in them, good holy ſoules may be ſaued.
               20. Secondly Pag. 21. lin. 39. you write more cleerely to make Proteſtants, euen millions of them,Anſwere to the Preface n. 26. in fine. guilty of damnable errours. If any Protestant, or Papist be betrayed into, or kept in errour by any ſinne of his will (as it is to be feared many millions are) ſuch errour is (as the cauſe of it) ſinfull and damnable; yet not excluſiue of all hope of Saluation, but pardonable, if diſcouered vpon a particular and explicite repentance; if not diſcouered, vpon a generall and implicite repentance &amp;c. Thus you directly accuſe Proteſtants of ſinfull and damnable errours, of errours pardonable, and conſequently damnable in themſelues. For you ſay pag. 16. n. 21. lin. 15. the very ſaying they were pardonable, implies, they needed pardon, and therefore were in themſelues damnable. This being ſo, how haue you cleered the Doctrine of all Proteſtant Sects, though not from all falſhood, yet from all errour in it ſelfe damnable? How do they all of them goe a ſafe way to ſaluation, if millions of them walke in damnable errours, which you ſay, will bring damnation vpon all them that continue in them by their voluntary fault? What reaſon can you bring, why your Booke might not be inſcribed; The Religion of Papiſts a ſafe way to Saluation, aſwell as, the Religion of

Protestants? For you ſay Proteſtants erre damnably aſwell as we; Millions of them aſwell as millions of ours; their errours are damnable in themſelues aſwell as ours; Ours pardonable by Gods great mercy aſwel as theirs; they cannot be ſaued without repentance no more then we; and we may be ſaued in our errors by a generall repentance aſwell as they? How then is not our Religion a ſafe way to Saluation aſwell as theirs, euen by your Booke of purpoſe written to ſaue them, and damne vs.
               21. Thirdly, Pag. 280. n. 95. lin. 19. Cap. 5. n. 91. lin. 19.
                   
                  Though Proteſtants haue ſome Errours; yet ſeing they are neyther ſo great as yours, nor impoſed with ſuch tyranny, nor maintayned with ſuch obſtinacy, he that conceaues &amp;c. In theſe wordes you ſuppoſe, that Proteſtants haue errours, and great errours impoſed with tyranny, maintayned with obſtinacy. How then is their Religion a ſafe way of Saluation? Can ſaluation ſtand with impious errours, impoſed vpon others with tiranny, and maintayned with obſtinacy vntill death? But their errours are not (you ſay) ſo great as ours, nor impoſed with ſuch tiranny, nor maintayned with ſuch obſtinacy. Were this true; it would not proue Proteſtancy to be a good and ſafe way to Saluation, &amp; not in it ſelfe damnable; but only, that ours is more damnable, and a worſe way. Beſides that our errours be greater then theirs is ſaid by you many times, but not proued ſo much as once. And ſeing our errours though (as you ſay) damnable in themſelues yet be pardonable by Gods great mercy; how be the greater then yours, which are alſo damnable in themſelues, and only pardonable by Gods great mercy? From the number of all Proteſtants, whoſe Religion you defend to be a ſafe Way, I hope Socinians or new Samoſatenians are not excluded.

Theſe hold, that Chriſt Ieſus is not the Eternall only begotten Sonne of God; yea that he was, and is a meere man, though an holy man, and a great Prophet. Will you ſay that this errour which conceaues no more diuinely of Chriſt then do the very Turkes, is not greater then any we maintayne, not more fundamental, and eſſentially deſtructiue of Saluation? If you do, moſt Proteſtants in England will thinke you worthy of the Fagot?
               
               22. Fourthly, Pag. 290. num. 87. you write,Cap. 5. n. 87. that Proteſtants, ſeing they be not free from errours, that it is hardely poſſible, but they muſt be guilty of extreme impiety. In that place you endeauour to anſwere our Argument, that it was great imprudency in Proteſtants to forſake the whole viſible Catholique Church, for errours not fundamentall, ſeing they confeſſe, that in their ſeparation againſt her, they could not be ſure of not falling into errours of the like quality and note, yea into greater, to wit fundamental. You are in this point eager, and proteſt, that Protestants are ſo farre from acknowledging that they haue no hope to auoyd this miſchiefe (of erring at the leaſt vn-fundamentally) that they proclaime to all the world, that it is moſt prone and eaſy to do ſo, to all thoſe that feare God and loue the truth; and hardely poſsible, for them to do otherwiſe without ſupine negligence and extreme impiety. Ponder I pray you this place, and conferre it with other paſſadges of your booke, &amp; you will ſee, that you make all Proteſtants extremely impious. For it is moſt prone and eaſy for Proteſtants that feare God and loue the truth to auoyd all errours, ſpecially ſuch as need pardon, and be damnable in themſelues: ſo that it is hardely poſſible for them to be in any errour without ſupine negligence and extreme

impiety. Now there are not any Proteſtants in the world, no not Engliſh Proteſtants by name, whome you dare defend to be free from errours not fundamentall; and millions of them as you confeſſe are by the ſinne of their will betrayed into, and kept in errours damnable in themſelues. Ergo, it is hardly poſſible; but all Protestants muſt be guilty of ſupine negligence, and extreme impiety about matters of Fayth, Which being ſo; how is that Religion a ſafe way of Saluation, in which hardly any be ſaued? yea, how be not their errours vnpardonable, ſeing you write. Pag 275. lin. 15. that,
                     Cap. 5. n. 58. lin. 18. 
                  God is infinitely iust, and therefore (it is to be feared) will not pardon Catholiques who might eaſely haue come to the knowledge of the truth, but through negligence would not? How then will he pardon Proteſtants, to whome it was (you ſay) moſt prone and eaſy to haue come to the knowledge of the truth, and to haue auoyded all errours, but would not through ſupine negligence, and extreme impiety?
               
               23. I haue been the larger in declaring and ſtrenghthening this Argument, and ſhewing the inſuperable, force therof. Firſt, becauſe it is the Argument moſt vrged by the pithy, and learned Catholique Treatiſe of Charity mistaken, as alſo by Charity maintayned, both which bookes by the cleering of this point are ſhewed to remayne vnanſwered. Secondly, becauſe this Argument from the confeſsion of our Aduerſaries, as it is cleere, manifeſt, and conuincing; ſo it is within the reach and capacity of euery one. For who ſo ſtupide &amp; voyd of ſenſe, as not to ſee that Religion to be the ſafer, which is confeſſed to be ſafe, euen in her Aduerſaries iudgment grounded vpon the neuer fayling principles of Chriſtian Charity, wiſdome, and truth?
            
         
         
            
            The Second Conuiction.
            THough we ſhould grant that moſt vntrue and impoſsible ſuppoſition, that the Roman Church erreth; yet it would be impoſſible that Catholiks ſhould be damned for following her errours. The reaſon is, becauſe their erring cannot but be excuſed by ignorance inuincible: wheras Proteſtantes, if they erre damnably (as without doubt they do) neither by ſhelter of Ignorance, nor of Generall Repentance can they be ſaued.
            
               Three Suppoſitions. §. 1.
               
               1. TO proue this, we muſt ſuppoſe three thinges, which are knowne and notorious truths. Firſt, that Chriſtians who belieue in Chriſt the eternall Sonne of God and Sauiour of the world, cannot be damned for any errours of ignorance inuincible, or for any inuoluntary erring. This truth you often affirme in ſome paſſages of your booke, and deny it as often in other. Pag. 19. lin. 27. 1. Edit. pag. 19. lin. 9. you ſay, That if in me alone were a confluence of all ſuch errours of all Protestantes in the world that were thus qualified (with ignorance inuincible) I ſhould not be ſo much afrayd of them all, as I ſhould be to aske pardon for them &amp;c. To aske pardon of ſimple and purely inuoluntary errours, is tacitely to imply, that God is angry with vs for them, and that were to impute to him the ſtrange tyranny of requiring bricke, when he giues no ſtraw; of expecting to gather, where he ſtrewed not; to reape, where he ſowed not, of being offended with vs, for not doing what he knowes, we cannot do. Heare you make it a kind of blaſphemy to ſay, that involuntary errours are pardonable, or need pardon; becauſe the very ſaying they were pardonable importes

they need pardon, and conſequently, that God is offended with vs for them. Notwithſtanding, that errours purely inuoluntary, or of inuincible ignorance be pardonable, and need pardon from Gods great mercy, you frequently profeſſe ſpeaking of our errours. Pag. 308. lin. 41. We hold your errours damnable in themſelues, yet by accident through ignorance inuincible, we hope they were not vnpardonable. Pag. 291. lin. 4. Your erring was we hope pardonable, in them that had no meanes to know their errours. Pag. 263. lin. 27. Your errours were in themſelues damnable yet we hope that thoſe amongſt you that were inuincibly ignorant of the truth, might by Gods great mercy haue their errours pardoned, and their ſoules ſaued. This is your wauering and tottering manner of diſcourſing; but the truth is, God is not offended with errours of ignorance inuincible, becauſe God is offended only for ſinne, wheras inuoluntary erring cannot be ſinne; becauſe to be voluntary is of the nature and difinition of Sinne.
               2. Secondly, we ſuppoſe, that the Roman doctrines, which Proteſtants accuſe to be errours, are definitions of Generals Councells, and were for many ages the publike receiued doctrine in the whole viſible Chriſtian Church; for which reaſon you ſay Pag. 279. n. 64. lin. 8. cap. 5. n. 64. lin. 8. That euen the viſible Church, is not free from damnable errours. Thirdly, we ſuppoſe that it is vnlawfull and damnable for any man to depart from the Roman Church, to forſake her doctrine, or to oppoſe the definition of a Generall Councell, except he haue apparent and euident reaſons which demonſtrate that the truth ſtādeth on his ſide. This you teach, pag. 272. n. 53.
                     Cap. 5. n. 53.
                  
                     It concernes euery man, that ſeparates from any Churches Communion, euen as much as his Saluation is worth, to looke moſt carefully, that the cauſe of his ſeparation be

iuſt and neceſſary. And pag. 200. lin. 25. Cap. 3. n. 18. infine. 
                     I willingly confeſſe the iudgment of a Councell, though not infallible; yet is ſo far directiue and obliging, that without apparent reaſon of the contrary, it may be ſinne to reiect it; at leaſt not to afford it an outward ſubmiſsion. 
                  But D. Potter 
                  D. Potter pag. 166.
                   more cleerly and fully affirmeth, That Generall Councels, are the highest Tribunals which the Church hath vpon earth; that their authority is immediatly deriued &amp; delegated from Christ; that no Christian is exempted from their cenſures, and iuriſdiction; that their decrees bind all perſons to externall obedience, and may not be queſtioned, but vpon euident reaſons.
               
            
            
               That the belieuers of the Roman Church cannot erre, but through Ignorance inuincible. §. 2.
               
               3. FOr the title of this Section I argue thus: Thoſe errours are vnauoydable and inuincible, which cannot be auoyded without damnable ſinne: But Roman Catholiques cannot auoyd the errous of the Roman Church (if ſhe haue any) without damnable ſinne: Therfore their errours (if they do erre) muſt of neceſſity be ignorances inuincible, and vnauoydable, ſuch as they cannot ſhake of without damning themſelues. The Minor, or aſsumption of this argument I proue; becauſe Roman Catholiques that be ſincere and cordiall belieuers of the doctrine of the Roman Church, cannot haue neceſſary &amp; forcing reaſons, nor euident demonſtrations, that the Roman Church is in errour. This is cleere: For if they haue neceſſary and inforcing reaſons, and euident demonſtrations whereby they are conuicted in conſcience, that the Roman Church erreth, they be now no more Roman Catholiques nor belieuers of the Roman Church, but

Proteſtants, and her Aduerſaries in their iudgment. It is therefore impoſſible, that Roman Catholiques, ſo longe as they be ſincere and Cordiall belieuers of the Roman Doctrine, ſhould haue euident demonſtrations, that the Roman Church erreth: And if the
                     •
                   haue not euident demonſtrations, it were damnable for them to forſake her doctrines, which Proteſtants account erroneous nor can they do it without damning their ſoules. Who then doth not ſee, that their erring (if they erre) is enforced, vn auoydable, proceeding from ignorance inuincible, for which ſort of ignorance it is impoſſible they ſhould be damned.
               4. You to auoyde the force of this Argument contend, that though your reaſons are neceſsary, enforcing, as cleere as the light at noone; yet we are not conuicted by them in conſcience; not that they want euidence, but that we are obstinately peruerſe. This your ſhift &amp; cauill, is eaſily ſhewed to be friuolous and falſe. Friuolous, becauſe you only ſay without any proofe, that we are obſtinately peruerſe, and if to ſay it without proofe be inough, then the ſame anſwere will ſerue, and doth de facto ſerue euery Heretique, euery Sect-maiſter, euery forger of new Monſters; for when he findeth himſelfe in ſtraytes, and not able to bring ſo much as a probable reaſon for his new deuiſed impieties; he falleth preſently to cry, that his Texts of Scripture are as cleere as the ſunne; his Arguments euident demonſtrations; that the reaſon Catholiques neglect and reiect him, is not want of euidence in his arguing; but that we are wilfully blind, obstinately peruerſe, men that haue eyes to ſee and will not ſee, giuen ouer to ſtronge deluſions, and vnto a reprobate ſenſe. And what is this but to change ſchollerſhip into ſcolding, reaſoning into rayling, diſputing into clamorous

and contumelious wrangling; wherin he getteth the victory who is the ſtoufeſt Stentor, and can crye loudeſt againſt his Aduerſaries, You are willfully blind, you are obſtinately peruerſe. In which kind of arguing See pag. 380. n. 72. cap. 6. n. 72.
                   you are very eloquent, according to the ſtile of heretiques, quorum doctrina (ſayth In cap. 22. Jſaiae. S. Hierome) non in ſenſu, ſed in multiloquio &amp; elamore conſistit.
               
               5. Secondly it is falſe: becauſe neceſſary and enforcing reaſons, or euident demonſtrations preſented vnto the vnderſtanding, neceſſitate the ſaid Vnderſtanding, and compell the Conſcience to aſſent, let the Will be neuer ſo peruerſe. The peruerſity of Will may make a man deny with his mouth, what in Conſcience he knoweth to be true; it may make him hate &amp; impugne knowne truth, but it cannot poſſibly make him not ſee, what by the light of euident demonſtration is made cleere to his vnderſtanding. This I proue by your owne ſayings, as pag. 370. n. 50. 
                     Cap. 6. n. 50. 
                  Apparent arguments neceſſitate the vnderſtanding to aſſent. and Pag. 371. n. 81. You contend, that Proteſtants hold not that it is euidently certaine, that theſe bookes in particular are the word of God. For (ſay 
                     Cap. 6. n. 81. you) they are not, eyther ſo fond as to be ignorant, nor ſo vaine as to pretend, that all men do aſsent to it; which they would, if they were euidently certain: or ſo ridiculous as to imagine that an Indian that had neuer heard of Chriſt or Chriſtianity, reading the Bible in his owne language, would without miracle belieue it to be the word of God, which yet he could NOT CHOOSE but do, if it were euidently certaine. Heere you affirme, that all men in the world would belieue the Chriſtian Bible to be the word of God, yea they could not chooſe but aſſent vnto it as vnto Diuine truth, if it did ſhew it ſelfe to be ſuch with euident certainty. And yet there be millions in the

world that be obſtinately peruerſe againſt the Chriſtian Bible. Ergo demonſtrations which ſhew a truth to the vnderſtanding with euident certainty, neceſſitate the Vnderſtanding to aſſent, This is auerred alſo by M. Hooker, Eccleſ. Pol. Preface pag. 29. lin. 26. An argument neceſſary, and demonſtratiue, being propoſed to ANY MAN &amp; vnderſtood; the mind cannot chooſe but inwardly aſſent. though the Will be obſtinately peruerſe. But Catholiques though they vnderſtand, ponder, and conſider your pretended euident demonſtrations, and texts of Scripture as cleere as the ſunne, can diſſent from them, &amp; reſt perſuaded in their conſcience againſt your concluſions by pious conſtancy of fayth. Wherefore your Arguments be not euident demonſtrations, and conſequently no man can be moued with them to forſake the Roman Church, and her Doctrine of Generall Councels without committing damnable ſinne: yea they are ſo farre from being irreſiſtable, as they are vaine, weake, contemptible, euen thoſe which you pretend to be ſo cleere as none can poſſibly be cleerer, as I haue ſhewed in the former Treatiſe Cap. 6. Conuict. 6. n. 29.
            
            
               That Protestants if they erre, cannot be ſaued by ignorance, or generall repentance. §. 3.
               
               6. THe firſt part of the Title, that they cannot be ſaued by ignorance, I proue thus. Either Proteſtants haue demonſtrations &amp; euident certainty, that the Roman Church erreth, that her definitions which they forſake, and keep themſelues in oppoſition againſt them, be falſe and impious; or they haue not. If they haue, they be not ignorant, but full of cleere and manifeſt certainty about all thoſe points wherein they forſake the Roman Church. If they haue not, they are indeed in ignorance; but in ſuch ignorance as will not ſaue them, but rather make them more damnable, to wit, in the ignorance of Pride. For is it not damnable,

and execrable Pride, for a ſimple and ignorant man, to abandon the Roman Church, adorned with ſo many glorious markes of the true Chriſtian Church; to reiect the definition of Generall Councels without any neceſſary and inforing reaſons, without any ſure ground, or euident certainty that they be errours? No doubt ſuch an one, the more ignorant that he is, the more damnable wretch he is; and by ſo much is his pride more deteſtable. Wherfore Proteſtants, if in their vndertaking and venturing to reiect the definition of Councels, and the receaued Traditions of ſo many former Chriſtian ages, they chance to erre, though but out of ſimplicity and ignorance, this ſimplicity and ignorance, will not excuſe and mitigate, but rather accuſe and aggrauate the crime of their erring preſumption and pride.
               7. This truth, that Proteſtants cannot be ſaued by ignorance (as Roman Catholiques may,) you ſeeme to acknowledge pag. 285. lin. 7. We aſsure our ſelues, if our liues be anſwerable, we ſhall be ſaued by our knowledge. And we hope (and I tell you agayne, ſpes eſt rei incertae nomen) that ſome of you may poſsibly be ſaued by occaſion of their vnaffected ignorance. Behold the way of ſaluation by Ignorance you leaue vnto vs, and in your great exceſſe of charity hope, that ſome of vs may poſſibly be ſaued throgh ignorance. But you Proteſtants are ſure to be ſaued by your knowledge, by your euident certainty, that the truth ſtandes on your ſide, againſt the definition of former Chriſtian worlds. Now, if this be the caſe of Proteſtants, that they muſt be ſaued by their owne knowledge, by being ſure they haue ſuch euident certainty of truth as may counter poyſe the authority of ſo many Chriſtian ages and Councels; how pittifull and lamentable

is their caſe? They cannot be ſaued except they be furniſht with knowledge, and euident certainty, that they haue truth on their ſide: For if they want this knowledge, they cannot prudently nor without execrable Pride oppoſe Generall Councels, which ſtand for the Roman Doctrines. But Proteſtants, at leaſt millions of them, are as ſure and certayne as they liue, that they haue no ſuch knowledge, no ſuch euident demonſtration or certainty, that the Roman Church and Councels erre: Therefore they cannot (except they be ſtupide and ſenſeleſſe) but be ſure they are in a damnable ſtate, and ſhall certainly be damned except they change their courſe.
               8. The ſecond part of this Section that Proteſtants, if they erre cannot be ſaued from their ſinfull &amp; damnable errours by general repentance is proued; Becauſe Generall Repentance doth extend only to thoſe things, wherein the Penitent may lawfully, and with a ſafe conſcience apprehend,2. Edit. pag. 20. lin. 33. and feare there may be ſinne. For as you ſay pag. 20. lin. 45. Generall repentance is vniuerſall ſorow for all their ſinnes, both which they know they haue committed, or which they feare they may haue. But Proteſtants belieue their Religiō againſt the Church of Rome to be the Goſpell, to be the word of God, to be moſt infallible Chriſtian truth, and ſo do not feare any fault or ſinne in their beliefe; yea they cannot with a ſafe conſcience ſo much as apprehend that their beliefe may be ſinfull, falſe, or vncertayne. For (as you ſay cap. 5. n. 107.) this were to doubt of the certainty of the Goſpell. Ergo, the Generall repentance of Proteſtants neyther doth, nor can extend it ſelfe to recall virtually and implicitely the Doctrine they hold againſt the Roman Church; no more then they repent of the Doctrine they hold againſt

Iewes and Turkes. For they hold both theſe Doctrines, as much the one as the other, to be the word of God; and therefore not to be doubted of, much leſſe repented as though it might be ſinfull errour. Moreouer it is not poſſible, that a man ſhould at the ſame time repent himſelfe of a thing, and together deteſt from his heart all repenting thereof. But Proteſtants abhorre &amp; deteſt as impious all doubting, and much more all repenting of their Religion, as it is oppoſed againſt the pretended Superſtitions, Impieties, Idolatries of the Church of Rome; for they thinke it holy Scripture, Diuine Reuelation as certayne as the Goſpell. Wherfore it is impoſſible, that Proteſtants ſhould repent of their oppoſing the Church of Rome, ſo long as they be Proteſtants, and belieue the doctrine of Proteſtancy to be the Goſpell, and the Roman Religion to be full of Impiety and Idolatry. There is no hope ſuch Proteſtants can be ſaued, except God ſend into their heart, the light of his Spirit, and make them ſee their Religion, ſo farre as it is oppoſite to the Roman, to be but a maſſe of old damned Hereſies, and moue them to repent and to recall, and deteſt them in particular.
            
            
               Your impudent ſlandering of Charity Maintayned that he granteth Saluation vnto any Proteſtant that is ignorant, or repentant. §. 4.
               
               9. YOu are much vexed that the Roman Religion is proclaimed ſafe euen by her Aduerſaries; and that yours is wholly deſtitute of ſuch comfortable teſtimonies. Wherfore the warrant you cannot obtayne by truth and fayre dealing, you ſeeke to get by falſhood, fraud, and forgery, euen of our Maintayner
                  
to whome you ſpeake in this manner pag. 31. lin. 12.

                     That which you do ſay doth plainely inough affoard vs theſe Corollaries.
                        Cap. 1. n. 3. 1. That whatſoeuer Proteſtant wanteth capacity, or hauing it, wanteth ſufficient meanes of inſtruction to conuince his conſcience of the falſhood of his owne, &amp; the truth of the Roman Religion; by the confeſſion of his moſt rigide Aduerſaries, may be ſaued, notwithſtanding any errour in his Religion. 2. That nothing hinders, but that a Proteſtant dying a Proteſtant, may dye with Contrition for all his ſinnes. 3. That if he dye with Contrition, he may, and ſhall be ſaued. All theſe acknowledgements we haue from you, whiles you are (as you ſay) ſtating, but, as I conceaue, granting the very point in queſtion; which was (as I haue already proued out of C. M.) whether without vncharitableneſſe you may pronounce, that Proteſtants dying in their Religion, and without particular repentance and dereliction of it, cannot poſsibly be ſaued.
                  
               
               16. Thus without ſhame you falſify the Tenet of your Aduerſary &amp; the doctrine of our Church. Where doth our Maintayner ſay, that whatſoeuer Protestant notwithstanding any errour? Socinians be Proteſtants in your account becauſe they hold the Bible, the Bible, and only the Bible, who maintayne Chriſt Ieſus not to be the eternall Sonne of God incarnated. Where doth our Maintayner affirme, that theſe Proteſtants may be ſaued in this ſo vild errour, vpon any condition? yea where doth he ſay of any Proteſtant, that he may be ſaued in any errour, which the maintaynes knowingly againſt the Roman Religion, if he want ſufficient meanes of inſtruction to conuince his conſcience of the falſhood of his owne, and truth of the Roman? He hath no ſuch wordes, and his wordes from which you pretend to

draw this wine of Comfort for Proteſtants, haue not any the leaſt reliſh of that ſenſe. Theſe they are: when any man esteemed Protestant, leaueth to liue in this world, we do not instantly with precipitation auouch, that he is lodged in Hell. For we are not alwayes acquainted with what ſufficiency of meanes he was furniſhed for inſtruction; we do not penetrate his capacity to vnderstand his Catechist; we haue no reuelation what light might haue cleered his errours, or Contrition retracted his ſinnes in the last moment before death. Here our Maintayner requires ſufficient meanes of inſtruction that a man be bound to belieue: but he ſayth not, as you make him ſay, that this inſtruction muſt conuince his conſcience, that his owne Religion is falſe, and the Roman true. If a Proteſtant be thus farre inſtructed as to perceaue, that the Roman Religion is by the full conſent of former Chriſtian ages, and by the definition of Generall Councels deliuered as the doctrine of Chriſt Ieſus, and his Apoſtles; if I ſay, any Proteſtant be thus farre inſtructed, he is ſo ſufficiently inſtructed, that if he refuſe to belieue he is certainly damned. Do not you profeſſe, that to forſake any Church without neceſſary cauſes, is as much as a mans ſaluation is worth? Doth not D. Potter auouch, that it is not lawfull to goe againſt the definition of Generall Councels without euident reaſons? Wherefore Proteſtants that haue abandoned the Roman Church, are by your principles conuinced to be in a damnable ſtate, if they know the Roman Religion to be the Chriſtian tradition of their Anceſtours, the definition of Catholique Councels. Nor is it neceſſary, that they be conuinced in conſcience, that the Roman Religion is true, it ſufficeth they haue no conuictiue demonſtrations againſt it. Wherefore it is extreme want of conſcience in you

to ſay, that our Maintayner, and the moſt rigide Aduerſaries of Proteſtancy affirme, that no Proteſtant ſhall be damned for any errour whatſoeuer he holdes againſt the Roman Church; except he be conuicted in conſcience, that his owne Religion is falſe, and the Roman true.
               11. And yet not content to haue brought this falſhood as a Corollary from his wordes, you make it his formal ſaying, and ſet it downe in a diſtinct Character as his verball and formall aſſertion. Pag. 31. n. 4. lin. 6. Charity mistaken affirmed vniuerſally,
                  
                     Cap. 1. n. 4. lin. 6. 
                  and without any limitation, that Protestants that dye in the beliefe of their Religion, without particular repentance, cannot be ſaued: But this preſumption of his you qualify by SAYING; that this ſentence cannot be pronounced truly, and therefore not charitably, neyther of thoſe Protestants, that want meanes ſufficient to conuince them of the truth of your Religion, and falſhood of their owne; nor of thoſe, who, though they haue neglected the meanes they might haue had, dyed with Contrition, that is, with a ſorrow for all their ſinnes, proceeding from the loue of God. Thus you: ſhewing the Adamantinall hardnes of your Socinian for head and Samoſatenian conſcience. For this long ſentence which you ſet downe, charactered as the ſaying of Charity Maintayned with a direct affirmation, that it is his ſaying, is forged and feigned by your ſelfe from the firſt to the laſt ſyllable thereof: not only againſt his meaning in that place, but alſo the whole drift of his Treatiſe. For what is the drift thereof, but only to ſhew, that the Roman is the true Church; and that her propoſing of a doctrine to be belieued is ſufficient to bind men to belieue it, without any other Conuiction beſides the authority of her infallible word?
               
                  12. Alſo the ſecond aſſertion you impute to him, That nothing hinders, but that a Protestant dying a Proteſtant, may dye with contrition for all his ſinnes, is an impudent vntruth: no ſuch acknowledgment in all his book. You ſeeke to gather it from theſe wordes, We haue no reuelation, what light may haue cleered his errours; or Contrition haue retracted his ſinnes. This reaſon (ſay you) or contrition haue retracted his ſinnes, being distinct from the former, and deuided from it by the diſiunctiue particle (or) inſinuates, that though no light did cleere the errours of a dying Proteſtant, yet Contrition might, for ought you know, retract his ſinnes. This is a fond &amp; voluntary inference: for the clauſe (or contrition retracted his ſinnes) was not added to ſignify, that a Proteſtant may haue contrition of all his ſinnes, though his vnderſtanding be not cleered from his errours: but to declare, that though his vnderſtanding be cleered from errours; yet this will not ſuffice that he be ſaued, except after the abiuration of his errours, he do further conceaue hearty ſorow &amp; Contrition for the deadly and damnable ſinnes of affection and action he may haue committed.
               13. For, that a Proteſtant cannot be truly penitēt of all his ſinnes, vntill his vnderſtanding be cleered, or at leaſt his zeale allayed, that he become remiſſe in his Religion and doubtfull; this reaſon doth inuincibly conclude. It is impoſſible, that a man ſhould repent of a thinge, at that time, when he is in actual or habitual heat of affection vnto it. But Proteſtants (ſo long as they are Proteſtants, and their Vnderſtandings not cleered from their errours, or their zeale allayed with cold doubtfulnes) are alwayes either actually, or habitually in the heat of condemning the Roman Church for Impieties and Idolatries; in the heat of preſumptuous

Pride, whereby they preferre their ſeely conceits about the ſenſe of Scripture, before the iudgement of the Church, and her Generall Councels. Ergo, it is impoſſible, that a Proteſtant perſiſting ſtiffely in his Religion, ſhould be penitent of all his ſinnes knowne and vnknowne.
            
         
         
            The third Conuiction.
            IN this Conuiction I am to proue three things: firſt, that Roman Catholiques hold all fundamētall truth, and ſo are ſecure from damnation. Secondly, that it is madneſſe to perſuade any man to leaue the Roman Church. Thirdly, that it is impoſſible, that Proteſtants ſhould be ſure they belieue all Fundamentall truths.
            
               That Roman Catholiques are free from all Fundamentall Errours, and your Contradictions herein. §. 1.
               
               1. HE that belieues all Fundamentals, cannot be damned for any errour in fayth; though he belieue more, or leſſe to be Fundamentall then is ſo. This is your formall aſſertion in ſo many wordes, pag. 207. n. 34. 
                     Cap. 4. n. 34. lin. 2. which ſuppoſed I aſſume: But Roman Catholiques belieue all Fundamentals, that is, all neceſſary truth: Ergo, they cannot be damned for any errour in fayth. The aſſumption of this argument might be proued, by many teſtimonies from your Booke. I will inſiſt vpon two, the one in this Section, the other in the next. Pag. 16. lin. 8. We grant the Roman Church was a part of the whole Church. And if ſhe were a true part of the Church, ſhe retayned thoſe truths, which were ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation. For this is preciſely neceſſary to conſtitute any man, or Church a member

of the Church Catholique. In our ſenſe therefore of the word Fundamentall, we hope ſhe erred not fundamentally. Thus you, who 
                     Cap. 5. n. 95. 
                  pag. 280. n. 95. ſay the playne contrary, that our errours are fundamentall. And pag. 289. nu. 86. 
                     Cap. 5. n. 86. that our Church not onely might, but alſo did fall into ſubſtantiall errours.
               
               2. I know, that to ſalue this Contradiction, and to put the terme of fundamentall Errours vpon our Church you haue coyned a diſtinction of two kinds of fundamentall errours. 
                     Cap. 5. n. 88. 
                  Pag. 290. n. 88. Fundamentall Errours (ſay you) may ſignifie, eyther ſuch as are repugnant to Gods command, and ſo in their owne nature damnable; though to thoſe that out of ignorance inuincible practiſe them not vnpardonable: and ſuch as are not onely meritoriouſly, but remedileſſely pernicious and destructiue of Saluation. According to this diſtinction you grant, that the Roman Religion hath fundamentall errours of the first kind, though as you hope none of the ſecond. But this diſtinction (to omit that you ouerthrow the ſame in both the members thereof as will afterward appeare) will not ſerue your turne, nor reconcile your contradiction. For when you ſay we belieue all Fundamentals, you profeſſe to take the word in your owne ſenſe. But in your ſenſe the word Fundamentall ſignifies all kind of neceſſary truth; for ſo you warne vs Cap. 4. n. 52. in fine. 
                  pag. 220. lin. 5. May it pleaſe you to take notice now at last, that by fundamentall, we meane All, and onely that which is neceſſary; and then I hope you will grant, that we may ſafely expect Saluation in a Church which hath all things fundamentall to Saluation. Thus you: which is as much as if you had ſayd, that by Fundamentall you vnderſtand, not only the things which are remedileſſely and indiſpenſably neceſſary; but alſo thoſe that be neceſſary onely becauſe commanded. For how can men

ſafely expect Saluation without thoſe things, which by the commandement of God are neceſſary to Saluation? Though men with fundamentall errours of the firſt kind may (in your doctrine) poſſibly be ſaued; yet you ſay their ſtate is not ſafe, but 
                     Pag. 133. Their ſtate is dangerous though not deſperate. 
                  dangerous. Now ſuch as haue all truth Fundamentall to Saluation, they not onely may poſſibly be ſaued; but alſo ſafely expect Saluation, as you contend. Ergo, when you ſay our Church retaynes all Fundamentals to Saluation and erres not Fundamentally, you will haue vs take notice, that you meane, ſhe is free not onely from ſuch damnable errours, as abſolutely deſtroy, but alſo from thoſe which endanger Saluation. Conſequently, when you ſay abſolutely (as euery where you do) that our errours are Fundamentall, or ſubſtantiall, or damnable, or dangerous, you contradict your other aſſertion, that we retayned all things ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation, and erred not Fundamentally.
               3. Beſides in the frontiſpice of your booke, you haue printed this ſentence of our late King Iames, Things ſimply neceſſary to Saluation be thoſe, which eyther the Word of God doth expreſſely command to be belieued or done; or thoſe which the Ancient Church did by neceſſary conſequēce draw out of the Word of God. Now you grant in expreſſe termes, that the Roman Church retayned all things 
                     Pag. 16. lin. 7. 
                  ſimply neceſſary to Saluation. Ergo, you muſt grant, that ſhe retayned all thoſe things, which eyther the word of God doth expreſſely command to be belieued or done; or which from the Word of God, the Ancient Church deduced, and ſo can want nothing neceſſary by Diuine command, nor haue errours fundamentall, ſo much as of the firſt kind.
               4. The reaſon you are about this point ſo various

and continually contentious and fighting with your ſelfe, is the inward combat of your vnruly paſſions. On the one ſide, you are incited with fury to damne vs, and make our Religion damnable; on the other, vexed and galled, that neither euidence of truth, no nor D. Potter himſelfe will giue you full freedome to do it. Hence your waue and wander, you ſay and vnſay, you runne this way and that way vpon aduerſe and contrary aſſertions; ſo much, as euen in the ſame ſhort ſentence, you plainely contradict your ſelfe pag. 16. n. 21. lin. 11.2. Edit. pag. 16. n. 8. 
                  Though we ſay the errours of the Roman Church were not destructiue of Saluation, but pardonable, euen to them that dyed in them vpon a generall Repentance, yet we deny not but in themſelues they were damnable. Do not you perceaue, that this ſpeach deſtroyeth it ſelfe, that our errours are not deſtructiue of Saluation, and yet are in themſelues damnable? what is deſtructiue of Saluation, but that which of it ſelfe, and in its nature is apt and ſufficient to deſtroy Saluation, and to bring damnation on men? And is not damnable the very ſame? How then can our errours be in themſelues damnable, and yet not deſtructiue of Saluation? You ſay, a poyſon may be deadly in it ſelfe and yet not kill him, who togeather with it takes an antidote. Very true: but can poyſon be in it ſelfe deadly, &amp; not in itſelfe deſtructiue of life? Can it be of it ſelfe apt to cauſe death &amp; not apt to deſtroy life? How then are our errours not deſtructiue of Saluation, and yet damnable and apt to bring damnation on vs?
               5. In like manner you profeſſe very often, that the Roman Church retayned the ſubſtance and eſſence of a Chriſtian Church; that you do not cut her off from the hope of Saluation. And yet at other times being enraged with the title of Catholique giuen her by the conſent

of mankind; you proteſt, that 
                  
                     Pag. 362. li. 8. Cap. 6. n. 40. lin. 4
                        •
                     . 
                  ſhe is Catholique to herſelfe alone, and Hereticall to all the rest of Christian Churches. Which is as much as if you had ſaid; ſhe wantes the very eſſence of a Chriſtian Church. For pag. 332. n. 11. 
                     Cap. 6. n. 11. you write: It is not Hereſy to oppoſe any truth propounded by the Church; but only ſuch a truth as is an eſſential part of the Ghoſpell of Christ. Wherefore the Roman Church (if ſhe be hereticall) oppoſes ſome eſſentiall, part of the Ghoſpell of Chriſt, and conſequently ſhe wantes fayth of ſome eſſentiall part of the Ghoſpell. What is conſequent hereupon? That the Roman Church, not only is not an incorrupt Church, but not a Chriſtian Church ſo much as for ſubſtance and eſſence. The Conſequence is manifeſt. For that cannot be a Chriſtian Church for ſubſtance &amp; eſſence, which doth not hold the Goſpell of Chriſt the Chriſtian Religion for ſubſtance and eſſence, as the Roman Church doth not if ſhe be Heretical, as you ſay ſhe is. For as that cannot be a man which wantes an eſſential part of a man: ſo that cannot be the Goſpell of Chriſt, nor the Chriſtian Religion for eſſence, which the Roman Church holdes, if ſhe want an eſſential part thereof, as you ſay ſhe doth. Behold how furies of paſſion diſtract you into contrary parts. Yea this which now you ſo peremptorily decree, that hereſy is not to oppoſe any truth, but only an eſsential part of the Goſpell, you contradict an hundred times in your booke, where you diſtinguiſh hereſies fundamental againſt the Eſſentials of the Goſpell,Pag. 277. lin. vlt. 
                  and not fundamental againſt Truths of the Goſpell profitable, but not neceſſary. How can this ſubſiſt, if that only be Hereſy which oppoſes the Eſsentials of the Goſpell?
            
            
               
               The ſecurity in the Roman Church is ſo great, as it is Madneſſe to leaue it. §. 2.
               
               6. THis I ſhall make good and euident by your owne moſt true &amp; vndeniable ſayings. Our Maintayner obiectes, that ſome Protestants leauing the Roman Church haue fallen away by degrees, euen from the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity.
                  
                     Cap. 3. n. 63. lin. 14. You anſwer p. 168. lin. 9. 
                     What if ſome forſaking the Church of Rome, haue forſaken fundamental truths? Was this becauſe they forſooke the Church of Rome?
No ſure: this is, non cauſa pro cauſa: For elſe all that haue forſaken that Church, ſhould haue done ſo; which we ſay they haue not: but becauſe they went too farre from her. The golden meane, the narrow way is hard to be found, hard to be kept; hard but not impoſſible; hard, but yet you muſt not pleaſe your ſelues out of it, though you erre on the right hand, though you offend on the milder part: for this is the only way, that leades to life, and few there be that find it. It is true, if we ſaid, there were no danger in being of the Roman Church, and there were danger in leauing it, it were MADNESSE to perſuade any man to leaue it.
                  
Thus you. Before I come to the principall intent, let me note and put you in mind of two thinges. Firſt that here (as euery where alſo commonly) you argue fondly, that the cauſe why ſome forſaking the Roman Church, forſook alſo the fundamentals of Chriſtianity, was not their forſaking the Roman Church, For els, ſay you, all that haue forſaken her ſhould haue done ſo. An argument fond and full of ignorance. Otherwiſe, we might ſay, that Couetouſneſſe was not the cauſe, that Iudas betrayed his Maiſter; for elſe all couetous ſeruants ſhould betray their maiſters,

which we know is not ſo: we may ſay that zeale of Puritaniſme was not the cauſe, that Enoch ap euan murthered his Brother and Mother; becauſe many zealous Puritans do not murther their Brothers, and mothers that oppoſe them. Theſe inſtances and a thouſand more which might be brought lay open your ignorance, that you do not diſtinguiſh betwixt naturall neceſſary cauſes, whoſe force cannot be reſiſted; and morall cauſes, which freely incline the will, leauing it liberty to reſiſt, which is the reaſon they are effectuall in ſome, and not in others.
               7. Secondly I note, that you alſo heere keepe your wont of contradicting your ſelfe. What you heere ſay that the narrow and onely way to life and ſaluation is hard to be found, hard to be kept, without erring on the right hand or on the left; how doth it agree with, or how doth it not directly deſtroy what you teach 
                     Cap. 4. n. 53. lin. 
                     
                        •
                     9. 
                  pag. 221. lin. 20. about your Proteſtant ſafeway· This is a way ſo plaine, that fooles except they will cannot erre from it; becauſe in this way, not being free from errour, but indeauouring to be free, is the onely condition of Saluation. How is, not being free from errour, but endeauouring to be free, in your way the onely condition of Saluation; if keeping the golden meane, and the narrow way without erring eyther on the right hand or left, be in your doctrine the ſole meanes of Saluation? How is the way ſo plaine, that euen fooles, vnleſſe they will, cannot erre from it, if it be hard to be kept without erring on the right hand or left? And pag. 290. n. 87. Cap. 5. n. 87. in fine. whereas the Maintayner ſayth, that Proteſtants ſhould not haue left the Roman Church, for errours vn-fundamētall, ſeing they were not ſure by their departure to auoyd this kind of miſchiefe; yea they were ſure they could not auoyd it: you ſay

                  Proteſtants are ſo farre from acknowledging that they haue no hope to auoyd this miſchiefe (of errours vn-fundamentall) that they proclayme to all the world, that it is most prone and eaſy to do ſo, to all thoſe that feare God, and loue truth; and hardly poſsibly for them to do otherwiſe without ſupine negligence and extreme impiety. How do theſe ſayings hange together; The golden meane of ſauing truth the only way to life, is hard, difficile, and only not impoſſible to be kept without erring from it eyther on the left hand Fundamentally; or one the right vn-fundamentally: The way of ſauing truth is moſt prone and eaſy to be kept, without erring ſo much as vn-fundamentally; yea, it is hardly poſſible to erre from it, on eyther ſide, without ſupine negligence, and extreme impiety?
               8. But now to the Principall intent; by this your confeſſion it is euident, that it is madnes for any man to to leaue the Roman Church, and that your writing to perſwade them to leaue it was a fit of diſtemper in your brayne. For you confeſſe, that if you ſayd there were no danger in being of the Roman Church, and there were danger in leauing it; is were madneſſe to perſuade any man to leaue it. Now I aſſume: But you ſay both, that there is no danger in the Roman Church, and that there is extreme danger in leauing it. That you ſay the firſt, I proue, becauſe you ſay, that he who belieues all Fundamentall truth, cannot be damned for any errour in fayth. And pag. 376. n. 57. Cap. 6. n. 57. in fine. 
                  he that belieues all neceſſary truth, if his life be anſwerable to his fayth, how is it poſsible he ſhould fayle of Saluaton? But you affirme, that the Roman Church retaynes all fundamentall and neceſſary truth, in that you onely charge her of going from the Golden meane of exact truth, on the right hand, on the ſurer part. Wherfore in the Roman Church men may ſafely expect Saluation;

there is no danger, yea there is no poſsibility of damnation for errours in faith with in her Communiō. That you ſay the ſecond, that there is extreme dāger in leauing the Roman Church, I ſhew, euē by this teſtimony. For you ſay the Roman Church erreth on the right hand, on the milder part; ſo that they who leaue her, muſt of neceſſity depart ſo farre from her on the left hand, that is, into the direfull gulfe of fundamentall errours; except they keepe themſelues in the golden meane, in the narrow way; But the golden meane, the narrow way, is (as you profeſſe) hard to be found; hard, and onely not impoſsible to be kept: Ergo, in leauing the Roman Church there is danger, and exceeding great danger which can hardly be auoyded, of falling into errours fundamentall, remedileſſely, and fatally damnable. Theſe being your Cōfeſſions and otherwiſe of themſelues manifeſt truths, you muſt acknowledge it is euen madneſſe and fury for any man to forſake the Roman Church; and that your writing to diuert men from her Communion, was a fit of phrenſy.
            
            
               That Proteſtants can neuer be ſure that they belieue all fundamentall and neceſſary Truth. §. 3.
               
               9. IT being indiſpenſably neceſſary vnto Saluation to know diſtinctly and in particular all Fundamental &amp; eſsentiall truthes; how can Chriſtian ſoules that be pious, carefull of their eternity, fearfull to fall into damnation euerlaſting, reſt quiet or calme in conſcience, till they know an exact Catalogue of theſe Fundamentals; that ſo they may be ſure, they know and belieue them diſtinctly and in particular? Now Proteſtants neither do, nor can agree vpon an exact Catalogue of their Fundamētals, nor wil tel their

followers diſtinctly, and in particular which be the articles eſsentially neceſsary vnto Saluation, and you in many places ſignify, that they are innumerable.
               10. On the Forehead of your Booke, you haue printed this ſentence of King Iames: The number of thinges abſolutely neceſſary to Saluation is not great: Wherefore the ſhortest and ſpeediest way to conclude a general peace and concord in matters of Religion, would be to ſeuer exactly thinges neceſſary from thinges not neceſsary; and to vſe all induſtry, that in neceſsaries there may be agreement, and in thinges not neceſsary, place be left vnto Christian liberty. In your Dedicatory you profeſse, that your Booke in a manner is nothing elſe but a purſuance of, and a ſuperstruction vpon this Bleſsed Doctrine, wherwith you adorn'd &amp; arm'd the Frontiſpice thereof. This is the flattering of your forhead, and your ſetting a fayre Hypocriticall face of Friendſhip on this ſentence, which you hate &amp; blaſpheme in your heart, and in the heart and boſome of your Booke. For ſome few leaues from the beginning you fall to reiect, purſue, and perſecute this your Bleſsed ſentence; and your ſuperstruction theron is nothing elſe, but a load of reproaches. You 
                     Pag. 23. ſay, that to ſeuer exactly thinges neceſsary from thinges not neceſsary (which that learned Prince eſteemeth to be of great vſe, of great neceſſity, and the ſhorteſt way to conclude the generall peace of Chriſtendome about Religion, &amp; a thinge not only factible, but alſo which may eaſily &amp; ſpeedily be done;) this I ſay, which your Frontiſpicial ſentence proclaymeth moſt vſefull and factible, the inſide of your Booke declareth to be a thing of extreme great difficulty, and of extreme little neceſsity, an intricate peece of buſineſse, apparantly vnneceſsary, of no vſe, a vaine labour, to no purpoſe. Behold your wordes, Pag. 23. lin. 5.

                  To ſeuer exactly and punctually theſe verities the one from the other &amp;c. is a buſineſse of extreme great difficulty, and of extreme litle neceſſity. He that ſhall goe about it ſhall find an intricate peece of buſineſse of it, and almost impoſsible that he ſhould be certaine he hath done it, when he hath done it. And then it is apparently vnneceſſary to goe about it, becauſe he that belieues all, certainly belieues all neceſſaries. And againe, ibid. lin. 15. And when they had done it, it had been to no purpoſe, there being as matters now stand, as great neceſsity of belieuing thoſe truths of Scripture which are not fundamental, as thoſe that are. Theſe be your wordes: by the force of which you knocke on the head, the ſentence of king Iames, nayled on the forehead of your Booke: and alſo giue a deadly ſtabbe on the heart of poore Proteſtants, and driue out of it all hope of Saluation.
               11. For you neither do, nor can tell them, which points of fayth are Fundamentall, and neceſſary to be knowne diſtinctly of all; without the leaſt of which you ſay Cap. 6. n. 75. in fine. 
                  it implies contradiction they ſhould be ſaued. How then ſhall they be ſure they haue all Fundamental truth? You ſay, he that belieues all, certainly belieues all that is neceſſary. And pag. 225. lin. 1. Cap. 4. n. 59. in fine. to a Proteſtant requeſting of you to know, which in particular be fundamental truths, you anſwere; It is a vaine question: belieue all, and you ſhall be ſure to belieue all that is Fundamentall. This rule of aſſurance you repeate almoſt in the ſame formal wordes, I dare ſay a thouſand times, which is craftily couched in equiuocal, and ambiguous termes, and hath a double ſenſe, being in the one falſe, and deceitfull; in the other impoſſible to be kept. If (belieue all) import no more, then, belieue in general and confuſedly all contayned in the Holy Bible to be true, your rule

is falſe, deceitfull, damnable, that men by belieuing all, ſhall certainly belieue all neceſſaries, as they ought, vnto Saluation. For you ſay 
                     Cap. 4. n. 3. 
                  Pag. 163. n. 3. Fundamental and eſsential points be ſuch, as are, not only plainly reuealed of God, and ſo certaine truths; but alſo commanded to be preach't to all men, and to be distinctly belieued of all, and ſo neceſsary truths. And 
                     Cap. 4. n. 4. lin. 20. 
                  Pag. 194. lin. 16. you teach, that to the conſtitution of Fundamental pointes, is required, that they be, First actually reuealed of God; Secondly commanded vnder paine of damnation to be particularly knowne (I meane, knowne to be Diuine reuelations) and distinctly to be belieued. Wherfore your rule (Belieue all in generall, and you ſhall be ſure to belieue all Fundamentals ſufficiently vnto ſaluation) is by your owne definitions proued falſe, and damnable. But, if your rule haue this ſenſe; Belieue all that is in the Bible explicitly, diſtinctly, &amp; in particular, and then you ſhall be ſure to belieue all neceſsaries, if this (I ſay) be your meaning, you lay on your Proteſtants a moſt heauy burthen, a moſt vnſupportable load, a moſt tyrannicall and impoſſible command. For what you ſay that the burthen is light, and that all Proteſtants comply with this your command, pag. 129. n. 5. 
                     Cap. 3. n. 5. lin. 4. 
                  that all of them agree with explicite fayth in all thoſe thinges, which are plainly and vndoubtedly deliuered in Scripture, that is in All, that God hath plainly reuealed; this, I ſay, is ridiculous; there being millions of truths plainly &amp; vndoubtedly deliuered in Scripture, which millions of Proteſtants neuer heard: yea, there be, I dare ſay, a thouſand ſuch truths which your ſelfe are ignorant off.
               12. In contradiction of this your inconſiderate aſſertion, you grant pag. 137. lin. 5. 
                     Cap. 3. n. 19. lin. 20. That there be many truths, which in themſelues are reuealed plainly inough, which yet are not plainly reuealed vnto ſome Proteſtantes of

                  excellent vnderstanding, nor are belieued of them, becauſe they are prepoſſeſt with contrary opinions, and with preiudices, by the strange power of education, instilled vnto their mindes. How then is it true, that Proteſtantes, all of them agree with explicite fayth in all thinges which are plainly reuealed of God? How can thoſe Proteſtantes (who diſbelieue many truths reuealed in Scripture plainly inough) be ſure they belieue all fundamentall and neceſsary truth; ſeing they obſerue not your command, Belieue all, and you ſhalbe ſure to belieue all that is fundamentall? Who doth, or can aſſure them, that among theſe many points of Fayth reuealed in Scripture plainly inough, none be fundamental. It is therfore manifeſt that Proteſtants (except you giue them an exact Catalogue of all your fundamentals which they are bound vnder payne of uamnation diſtinctly and explicitly to belieue) can neuer be ſure they belieue all fundamentall truth. And it is ſeely for you, Pag. 158. n. 52. lin. 19. pag. 160. n. 33. lin. 31. pag. 162. lin. 20.
                   when Charity Maintayned vrgeth you for a Catalogue of your Fundamentals, to thinke that you may ſtop his mouth, with importuning him, for a Catalogue of our Churches Propoſals; for we ſay of our Churches Propoſals, that it is ſufficient to belieue them implicitly: we do not ſay, they muſt be belieued of all distinctly and in particular. What need then is there of a Catalogue, wherin ſuch Propoſals are ſet downe diſtinctly, and in particular? Now you affirme of your Fundamentals, that all men are bound vpon their ſaluation, to know and belieue them in particular and yet obſtinatly refuſe to giue them an exact account, which in particular they be.
               13. Beſides, what an intricate and infinite obligation do you charge vpon Proteſtantes, in ſaying, that there is (as thinges now stand) at great neceſsity of belieuing

thoſe truths of Scripture which are not fundamentall, as thoſe that are ſo. For the neceſſity of belieuing fundamentals deliuered in holy Scripture is vnder paine of damnation to know them in particular, and diſtinctly; which obligation is ſo ſtrict, that you ſay it implies contradiction, that Saluation be had without the leaſt of them. Now if the neceſſity of belieuing not fundamentals, be as great as this; yea the ſame with this; no Proteſtant can be ſaued that doth not belieue ſuch paſſages of Scripture as be not fundamentall diſtinctly &amp; in particular, euen as he is bound to belieue fundamentals. You often (as pa. 169. lin. 12.) 
                     Cap. 3. n. 64. lin. 33. eagerly and bitterly declame againſt vs for requiring harder and heauier conditions of Saluation, then God requires, or then were required in the dayes of the Apoſtles. Who more guilty of this crime then your ſelfe? For this your neceſſity of belieuing the not fundamentall truthes of Scripture, as much as the fundamental, was not euer in Gods Church; ſeeing your ſelfe onely ſay it is ſo as matters now stand. Wherby you inſinuate, that as matters stood anciently, this great neceſsity and obligation had no place in Gods Church. Nor can you ſay, that it is required of God: for then it would be deliuered in Scripture and conſequētly perpetuall in the Church euer ſince the Ghoſpell was written: wheras your wordes vrging this obligation onely (as now matters stand) imply the contrary. It is therefore manifeſt, that this neceſſity ſo heauy and direfull, is layd vpon Proteſtants, not by Apoſtolicall commaund, not by diuine Precept; but by your ſelfe and other proud ignorant Miniſters, who neither know which be Fundamentals, nor can agree vpon any ſhort rule, within the compaſſe of which they are all comprized. Hence they are forced to ſend euery Proteſtant to fiſh for

Fundamentals, in the vaſt and deepe Ocean of holy Scripture; not giuing them any direction, any rule, any aſſurance of finding them all, except they can comprehend cleerly and diſtinctly all the innumerable truthes plainely reuealed therein.
               14. Finally, what you ſay pag. 134. lin. 24. That may be ſufficiently declared to one, which is not ſufficiently declared to another; and conſequently, that may be fundamentall to one, which to another is not. And pag. 281. lin. 4. 
                     Cap. 5. n. 17. 
                  The ſame errour may be not Capitall to men that want meanes of finding the truth; and Capitall to others, who haue meanes and neglect to vſe them. This doctrine by you often repeated, driueth Proteſtants into a Thicket of Thornes and briers: into new inſuperable difficulties &amp; vncertainties of their Saluation. For though a Proteſtant were ſure (which in Proteſtācy he can neuer be) that he diſtinctly belieues all capital &amp; eſsential truthes, which are to be belieued of all; how ſhall he be ſure, that he belieues all truthes, which to him in particular (in regard of his greater knowledge and capacity) are, you ſay, Capitall and Fundamentall? How can he be certaine, that there are not ſome capitall and ſubſtantiall truths, which he hath not found in Scripture, though he had meanes of finding them? And if he want beliefe of theſe Fundamentall and Capitall truths; how can he poſsibly be ſaued? For though you ſhould ſay, that theſe are the leaſt of thinges fundamentally neceſsary to ſaluation; yet this will not poſsibilitate their ſaluation: it being contradiction, to ſay, that Saluation may be had, without any the LEAST thing neceſsary to Saluation, as you affirme, Cap. 6 in fine totius capitis. 
                  Pag. 382 lin. 1.
            
         
         
            
            The fourth Conuiction.
            YOu could find no Way to make good the Saluation of Engliſh Proteſtants, againſt the demonſtrations of Charity maintayned; but onely ſuch a Way, wherein the vildeſt Heretiques that now liue, or euer liued vnder the cope of Heauen, may be ſaued as well as they; yea euen Iewes and Turkes: theſe two conſequences frō your principles, I will demonſtrate in two Sections of this Conuiction.
            
               That in your VVay English Proteſtants cannot be ſaued more then Socinians; with fixproofes, that you are of this impious Sect. §. 1.
               
               1. YOu ſay in your Preface n. 39. that you haue not vndertaken the particular defence of the Church of England, but the common Cauſe, and Religion of all Proteſtants.
And pag. 375. n. 56. you profeſſe, that by the Religion of Protestants, which you mayntaine to be a ſafeway to ſaluation, you do not vnderſtand 
                     the doctrine of Luther, or Caluin, or Melancton; nor the Confeſſion of Augusta, or Geneua; nor the Catechiſme of Hiedelberge; nor the articles of the Church of England; no nor the Harmonie of Proteſtants Confeſſions: but that wherin they all agree as a perfect rule of their fayth and actions, the BIBLE, the BIBLE, I ſay the BIBLE onely is the Religion of Proteſtants. This is the onely Religion, the onely way you could find to ſaue Engliſh Proteſtants, wherin they can no more be ſaued, then any other that belieue the Bible, and only the Bible, as a perfect rule of their life and actions.
Now in the number of Proteſtants, Ghoſpelers, and Bibliſts, the new Ebionites, or Samoſatenians whon we terme Socinians, are comprehended;

the moſt blaſphemous Heretiques againſt the Fundamentall articles of Chriſtianity that euer breathed, worſe then Arians: For Arians acknowledged the Eternity of our Lord Chriſt Ieſus, that he had an Eternall moſt perfect diuine Eſſence; only they would not confeſſe him to be coequall, and conſubstantiall to his Father▪ But Socinians deny him to be the eternall Sonne of God, affirme him to be meere man, and tearmed the ſonne of God, as other Iuſt and holy men and Prophets are.
               2. Now that Socinians are by your account in the number of them, that goe the ſafe way to Saluation, as well as Engliſh Proteſtants, is manifeſt; not only becauſe they profeſſe the Bible, and onely the Bible; but alſo becauſe they are that ſort of Chriſtians, whoſe Religion you follow as theſe ſix arguments euince.
               3. Firſt, becauſe being ſo much ſuſpected and accuſed euen in publique writing to be of that impious Sect: and if you were not prouoked to make a cleere profeſſion of the Chriſtian fayth againſt them, you haue not done it: you ſay ſometimes, that Chriſt is the Sonne of God; but neuer his Eternall Sonne, which omiſſion of the word Eternall in a man ſo ſuſpected of Socinianiſme as you are, is in the iudgement of our late Soueraigne 
                     Proceeding against D. Ʋorstius. pag. 81. For of Vorstius his booke ſtiled de Filiatione Christi, without aeterna; the King fayth: For this title only, an Authour ſo ſuſpected as he, is worthy of the fagot. King Iames a ſigne of guiltines, &amp; maketh your Booke worthy of the fagot.
               4. Secondly, becauſe you diſlike words about matters of Fayth not found in the Scripture, which Chriſtians vſe for the better declaration of the Creed. This you tearme, 
                     Pag. 198. li. 16. 
                  a vayne conceit, that we can ſpeake of the things of God, better then in the word of God. You declame alſo bitterly againſt, perſecuting curſing, damning of ſuch as will not ſubſcribe vnto the words of men, as the words of God. No

reader of vnderſtanding in Eccleſiaſticall affayres can doubt, but you gird at the word 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , conſubstantiall, decreed by the firſt Councels of Nice, to declare the ſubſtantiall Equality betwixt the three diuine Perſons: and at the word 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Deipara, Gods Mother, commanded by the Councel of Epheſus to be giuen to the Bleſſed Virgin; to ſignifie, that ſhe was mother to him, that was perſonally, not onely true man, but alſo the eternall God: Theſe Canons of the firſt generall Councels, theſe ſacred formes of Eccleſiaſticall ſpeach, you cannot indure; becauſe they thunder againſt Socinians; they proclaime them to be Heretiques, and ſtrike their Impieties dead.
               5. Thirdly, becauſe you 
                     Pag. 381. n. 72. cap 6. n. 72. lin 21. reprehend them, who by firme reſolution of their will vphold themſelues in the beliefe of their Religion, though their reaſon and vnderstanding fayle them Which is as much as if you had ſayd, We are not, through pious affection and reuerence of Gods word, to belieue things aboue the reach of reaſon; things in the apprehenſion of which our naturall vnderſtanding faileth: as are the myſteries of the Trinity, &amp; of the Eternall Generation of the Sonne of God.
               6. Fourthly, becauſe you ſay, 
                     Pag. 218. lin. 15. 
                  that they who captiuate their vnderſtanding, to the beleefe of thoſe things, which ſeeme irreconcileable contradictions; may aſwell belieue reall contradictions, 
                  
                     Pag. 217. n. 47. Cap. 4. n. 47. 
                  which no wiſeman will do. But he that belieues the myſtery of the B. Trinity, &amp; the Sonne of God his Eternall Generation, muſt of neceſſity captiuate his vnderſtanding to the beliefe of impoſſibilities, implicancies, contradictions, ſeeming to be ſuch in human reaſon, as euery true Chriſtian by experience findeth. Therefore in your opinion no wiſe man doth, or will belieue them.
               
                  7. Fiftly, becauſe you ioyne with the Carpocrates, Ebion, Cerdo. auncient enemyes of Chriſt Ieſus his God head, to diſparage the Goſpell of S. Iohn; wherein 
                     Ioannes aduerſus Ebionem ſcripſit Euangelium, Diuinam Chriſti ediſſerens natiuitatē. Hieron. de. Script. Eccleſ.
                   the eternall Generaation of the Word, the onely begotten Sonne of God, is moſt fully and plainely deliuered; as alſo the indiſpenſable neceſſity of belieuing the ſame, Ioan. 3.8. He that belieueth in him is not damned; he that belieueth not is already damned; becauſe he belieues not in the Name of the onely begotten Sonne of God. For though you dare not ſay plainely that S. Iohns Ghoſpell is of no authority, yet in effect you ſay as much; contending, that in his Ghoſpell 
                     Pag. 211. in. 42. lin. 11. 
                  nothing is contayned of neceſsary beliefe, which is not cleerely &amp; plainely ſet downe 
                     Pag. 212. lin. 1. Such a perfect Goſpel. in S. Lukes Goſpell. Wherfore; becauſe Chriſt Ieſus his being the Eternall Word and ſonne of God, is no where ſet downe ſo cleerly in the Goſpell of S. Luke, you Socinians will not be bound to belieue it; through our Lord himſelfe in S. Iohns Goſpell pronoūce, that he who belieues it not, is already damned, that is, as ſure to be damned, as if he were already in Hell. Now what is this, but in fauour of Socinianſme to giue the lye to S. Iohn; yea to our Sauiour himſelfe?
               8. Sixtly, you are proued to be not onely a Socinian, but alſo impiouſly obſtinate in the defence of that Sect, by your changing the ſacred text of Gods word, that they may not ſeeme therin accurſed. S. Iohn in his firſt Epiſtle Cap. 4. v. 2. giueth this ſigne to know the ſpirit of true Prophets and Preachers, Euery ſpirit which confeſſeth Ieſus Chriſt to be come in fleſh is of God; and euery Spirit which confeſſeth not Ieſus Christ to be come in fleſh is not of God, but of Antichriſt. And Ep. 2. v. 7. Many Deceyuers are come out into the world, who do not confeſſe Ieſus Christ to be come in fleſh; this is a Deceyuer &amp; an Antichrist.
                  
In which places it is manifeſt, that S. Iohn ſpeakes of falſe Chriſtians, namely the Ebion confitebatur Ieſum Chriſtum, ſed eum nudum eſſe hominem afferebat, non autem Deum vnigenitum, Sapientiam &amp; Ʋerbū Dei. Ignatius Epist. ad Philadelphos.
                   
                  Ebionites, who deny Chriſt Ieſus to be a Perſon come from the boſome of God veſted with humane fleſh who deny him to be the Word made fleſh, the Sonne of God incarnate. Which being your Socinian Beliefe, that the ſame might not ſeeme damned as Antichriſtian; you make bold with Gods word, and thruſt in your owne wordes in place therof, Preface num. 12. The rule, S. Iohn giues to make this trial of Spirits by, is to conſider whether, they confeſſe Ieſus to be the Chriſt, that is, the guide of their fayth, and Lord of their actions. And pag. 339. lin. 4. you ſay, S. Iohn Ep. 2. v. 7. ſpeabes not of Heretiques, but of no Chriſtians, of Antichrists, of ſuch as denied Ieſus to be the Chriſt. Thus ſtill, as often as S. Iohn ſayth, ſuch as deny Ieſus Chriſt to be come in fleſh be falſe Prophets, deceyuers, Antichriſts, you change the text into ſuch as deny Ieſus to be the Christ, as though S. Iohn had ſpoken in this place againſt Iewes, who deny Ieſus to be the Christ, or the promiſed Meſsias. Whereby you not only chauge the text; but alſo foyſt in a falſhood into Gods Word. For it is falſe, that whoſoeuer confeſseth Ieſus to be the Christ, is therby knowne to be of God, and a true Chriſtian: ſeing Turkes confeſſe Ieſus to be the Christ, that is, the Meſsias promiſed to the Iewes; and yet are not Chriſtians. And that S. Iohn ſpeaketh againſt Heretiques, who vnder the name of Chriſtians, went about preaching, that Ieſus Christ is not the eternal ſonne of God, is cleere by the wordes which immediatly follow: He 
                  
                     Epist. 2. v. 
                     
                        •
                     . 
                  that departeth, and abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God: He that abideth in his doctrine, hath the Father and the Sonne. If any come to you, and bringe not this Doctrine, receiue him not into your houſe; bid him not God

ſpeed: For he that ſayth to him, God ſpeed, is partaker of his malignant workes.
               
               9. What then may we thinke of thoſe Engliſh Proteſtants, and of their ſtate and Saluation, who haue made you the Patron of their Religion, and Paſtour of their ſoules? can they be excuſed from being partakers with you in your malignant workes, tending to the peruerſion and damnation of many? I confeſſe you haue rewarded them as they deſerue. For you giue them no better aſſurance, or hope of Saluation, then to Socinians, who deny Chriſt Ieſus to be the Eternal only begotten Sonne of God, whoſe damnation goeth before them vnto iudgment. Miſerable they are, who be ſo deſperately bent againſt Charity maintayned by Catholiques, as rather then yield to be ſaued in the Catholique Roman Church, will be defended by ſuch a Socinian Patron, and in a Way which giueth them no hope of ſaluation; but together with Heretikes, who deny the Incarnation of the eternal Sonne of God, who are branded in Scripture with the note of Deceyuers and Antichriſts: and by the mouth of our Lord himſelfe, men already damned.
               
            
            
               That in your VVay Iewes and Turkes may be ſaued aſwelll as Protestants. §. 2.
               
               10. PRoteſtants of your ſtampe who pretend to belieue the Bible, and only the Bible, being deuided into 
                     King Iames, Proceeding against Worstins pag. 65. 
                  innumerable ſects (agreeing in nothing but in their vnion against the Pope) cannot but be full of many contrary and aduerſe errours, as you grant. Wherefore in your Way they are ſaued in their errours by inuincible ignorance; or if their ignorance be vincible, ſinfull, and damnable, by General Repentance. But by your Principles, Iewes and Turkes may be ſaued in their

falſe Religions through inuincible ignorance, or generall Repentance. That they may be ſaued by inuincible ignorance, is proued by what you write Pag. 393. lin. 1. Cap. 7. n. 8. lin. 26. ante finem. 
                  Certainly Religion is one of thoſe thinges, which are neceſſary only becauſe commanded. For if none were commanded vnder paine of damnation, how could it be damnable to be of any? Neither can it be damnable to be of a falſe Religion, vnleſſe it be a ſin to be ſo.
                  Thus you: whereupon I aſsume this Hypotheſis: to Turkes, Iewes, Pagans, that are inuincibly ignorant of the falſhood of their owne Religion, and truth of the Chriſtian, it is no ſinne to be of their falſe Religion and enemies of Chriſt our Lord: This hath been already ſhewed by your acknowledgments; that God cannot be offended with men for errours purely inuoluntary, nor can he damne them for not doing what he knowes they cannot do.
Wherefore it is impoſſible, that God ſhould damne Iewes, or Turkes, or Pagans for errous of inuincible and inuoluntary ignorance: ſo that if your Theſis be true, that no falſe Religion is damnable, but only becauſe it is ſinne: it is comequent, that men may be ſaued in any Religion euen in Iudaiſme, Turciſme, Paganiſme through inuincible ignorance.
               11. You ſay 2. Ed. pag. 24. lin. 23. 
                  Pag. 24. lin. 34. Who can find fault with D. Potter for ſaying, If, through want of meanes of instruction, incapacity, inuincible or probable ignorance a man dye in errour be may be ſaued? Now many Iewes, and Turkes, and Pagans dye in their errours, through want of inſtruction, or incapacity, or inuincible ignorance. Ergo, they may be ſaued in their falſe Religions &amp; impious errours. If you anſwer that your propoſition, that men who dye in their errours may be ſaued, is to be vnderſtood of ſuch as dye in errours that be damnable only

meritoriouſly, becauſe ſinnes, and againſt Gods commande, not of errours which remedileſſely, fatally, vnauoydably destroy Saluation, which no ignorance can excuſe, for which no repentance can begge pardon without a dereliction of them, as you ſay pag. 336. n. 19. I reply that this anſwere confirmes the Saluation of Iewes and Turkes &amp; Pagans in your doctrine and Way. According to which, to dye in any falſe Religion cannot be damnable, remedileſſely, but only meritoriouſly, becauſe a ſinne, and an offence of God: wherefore if any Iew, or Turke, or Pagan want capacity, or meanes of inſtruction, and ſo be inuincibly ignorant, he may be ſaued, euen as Proteſtants are ſaued in your ſafe Way.
               
               12. I omit that you plainely contradict your ſelfe in ſaying that there be ſome errours which remedileſly deſtroy Saluation, becauſe the contrary truth is neceſſary,
                  
                     Cap. 6. n. 19. lin. 33. non ſolum neceſſitate praecepti, ſed medij, not only becauſe commanded, but alſo becauſe the ſole meanes or remedy againſt ſinne. This doctrine I ſay doth not agree with your aſſertion, that Religion it ſelfe is neceſſary only becauſe it is commanded; and that it cannot be damnable to be of any falſe Religion, but only becauſe it is a ſinne. For what thinges or doctrines can be neceſſary, not only becauſe commanded, but alſo becauſe the ſole remedy againſt ſinne, if Religion (which is, to belieue that God is, and that he is are warder of them that ſeeke him) be neceſſary only becauſe commanded; not becauſe the meanes without which no man can be iuſtifyed from ſinne and ſaued? If to be of a falſe Religion, or of no Religion be damnable onely meritoriouſly; becauſe a ſinne; what errour can be imagined ſo malignant, as to deſtroy Saluation not onely meritoriouſly, but alſo remedileſsely, or fatally, as you ſpeake?
               
                  13. Secondly that Iewes and Turkes may according to the Principles of your ſafe way, be ſaued in their errours by Generall repentance for all their ſinnes, is proued: becauſe there is no repugnance, but they may conceaue contrition for all their ſinnes. For they belieue in one only God, Creatour of heauen and earth. The Iewes further belieue the truths reuealed in the old teſtament, the Turkes belieue in Ieſus, that he is the Chriſt, the meſſias, which is to belieue in him as farre as Socinians belieue in him; yea, they pray vnto him and inuocate him, which ſome Bellarmin. l. 1. de Chriſto. c. 1.
                   
                  Socinians refuſe to doe, becauſe they hold we are to inuocate the true God only; and to them Chriſt is not God, but a meere holy man. Why then may not Iewes, &amp; Turkes loue the true God, and conceaue ſorow of all their offences and ſinnes againſt ſo good a Lord, ſo worthy of all loue, of all their ſinnes I ſay knowne and vnknowne, in which number all ſinfull errours must of neceſsity be contayned as you ſay pag. 21. lin antepenullina, and pag. 20. lin vltima.
               
               14. To this purpoſe very forcible and pregnant it is, what you ſay to vs ſpeaking indefinitely of different Religions and Sects, pag. 32. n 4. You must not hereafter affirme, that of men of different Religions, one ſide onely can be ſaued; but you must temper the crudeneſſe of this aſſertion; by ſaying, One ſide only can be ſaued, except want of conuiction, or elſe repentance excuſe the other. This your Charitable exception comprehends Turkes, &amp; Iewes, that are of a different Religion from Chriſtians; that they may be excuſed frō damnation through want of Conuictiō, or through a generall Repentance of all their ſinnes knowne and vnknowne. You giue vs warning in the ſame place ſaying to vs: You must abſtayne frō affirming, that Protestants dying in their Religion cannot be ſaued;

For you must alwayes remember to adde this caution, vnleſſe they were excuſably ignorant, or dyed with contrition. A goodly aduiſe, which becauſe S. Paul obſerued not, you muſt ſay he was to blame &amp; vncharitable in pronouncing, 1. Co. 6 9 10. Galat. 5.20.21.
                   
                  that impious men, drunkards, Heretiques, ſectaries ſhall not poſſeſſe the Kingdome of God. For he ſhould haue remembred to adde this caution; except they be excuſably ignorant, or dye with contrition. Nor muſt you ſay, that Turkes and Iewes dying in their Religion cannot be ſaued; but you must alwayes remember to adde this caution; vnleſſe they were excuſably ignorant of the falſhood of it; or dyed with contrition. And then conſidering, that you cannot know, whether or no they were ſufficiently conuinced of the truth of christian Religion, you are obliged in charity to iudge the best, &amp; hope they are not. And is not this to mantayne, that men may be ſaued in any Religion, Chriſtian, Iewiſh, or Turkiſh, aſwell in the one as in the other? No Religion among Chriſtians, no Sect among Proteſtants is found which you doe Preface n. 39. or dare defend to be free from errours againſt fayth and Religion; and ſo in your Way none are ſure to be ſaued, but through ignorance, or generall Repentance for their errours. But Iewes and Turkes may be ſaued in eyther of theſe wayes; their errours (according to your principles) not being remedileſſely damnable.
               
            
         
         
            The fifth Conuiction.
            THis Conuiction ouer throweth the chiefe cauſe for which you charge our Religion to be damnable, &amp; ſheweth: firſt that the thing for which you would ſend vs to Hell, is the neceſſary duty of a conſtant Chriſtian Fayth. Secondly, that your contrary mutability and leuity is Apoſtaticall and impious.
            
               
               You damne vs to Hell for being faythfull, and conſtant Chriſtians. §. 1.
               
               1. YOu often proclame vs, to be men wilfully blind, ſure to fall into the ditch of damnatiō. For this your cenſure of vs you giue this reaſon; Pag. 380. n. 72. 
                  becauſe we will not enter into any triall of our Religion, with indifference, with liberty of iudgement, with are ſolution to doubt of it, if vpon examination, the grounds of it proue vncertaine; or to leaue it, if they proue apparantly falſe: my owne experience aſſures me, that herein I do you no wronge; but it is very apparent to all men from your ranking doubting of any part of your doctrine, among mortall ſinnes. Thus you. And we willingly grant, and openly profeſſe, that we hold it a mortall ſinne to doubt deliberately of any poynt of our fayth. But muſt we be damned in this reſpect? O how doth malignancy againſt our ſaluation confound your memory and wit? For againſt doubting in matters of Religion you write moſt earneſtly pag. 195. n. 11. lin. 20. which of vs euer taught, it was not damnable to deny or doubt of the truth of any thing, whereof we eyther know or belieue, that God hath reuealed it? Thus you. Now if it be damnable to doubt of the truth of any thing we belieue to be reuealed of God; what an obliuious Creature are you, who will haue vs damned for not yielding to do that very thing, which you proclame damnable to be done? you will haue vs ſent to Hell, becauſe we ranke doubting of any part of our fayth (which we hold reuealed of God) among deadly and damnable ſinnes; and yet your ſelfe ranke this doubting among deadly and damnable crimes, with an earneſt tacite deteſtation of the contrary Doctrine, which of vs euer taught it is not damnable?
               
               
                  2. Haue you ſo ſoone forgot your ſelfe? Are your ſayings no ſooner out of your pen, then out of your memory and head? which of vs (ſay you) euer taught it is not damnable? Euen your ſelfe good Sir, you William Chilling worth teach it is not damnable, yea you hold it damnable for any man to ranke doubting of the Religion, which he holdes reuealed of God among mortall ſinnes, which you proue; becauſe ſeing euery man must reſolue neuer to commit mortall ſinne, it followes, that he must neuer examine the grounds of his Religion, for feare of doubting; or if he doe, he must reſolue, that no motiues, be they neuer ſo strong, ſhall moue him to doubt. This is your argument, vpon which you conclude we are a company of blind inconſidering men, louers of the darkeneſſe, and not of light. And yet your ſelfe, are ſo blind, ſo inconſidering, and your wits are ſo dulled and darkened, as you do not perceaue, that this very argument proueth you &amp; all your Bibliſts to be in the ſame caſe we are; to wit obſtinately blind: for you grant, that all of you ranke doubting of your Religion among mortall ſinnes, that is, you all teach that it is damnable to doubt of the truth of any thing you belieue to be reuealed of God. Hence it followes that ſeing you must reſolue neuer to commit damnable ſinne; that you must neuer examine the grounds of it at all, for feare you ſhould be moued to doubt; or if you do you muſt reſolue that no motiues, be they neuer ſo ſtrong, ſhall moue you to doubt. You ſee your argument agaynſt vs turneth vpon your ſelues, and proueth you are obſtinate and blind, and in danger of the Ditch as much as we are.
               3. And do not you further teach and contend, that it is damnable for you to doubt of the Doctrine of Diuels: if you belieue it to be Diuine Reuelation?Cap. 2. n. 122. lin. 21. Pag. 99. n. 122. l. 22.

                     If by the diſcourſe of the Diuel I be (I wil not ſay

conuinced, but) perſuaded, though falſely, that it is a Diuine Reuelation, and ſhall deny to belieue it, I ſhall be a formal (though not a material) Heretique; For he that belieues any thinge to be a Diuine Reuelation, and yet will not belieue it to be true; muſt of neceſſity belieue, that God is falſe, which according to your doctrine, is the Formality of an Heretique.
                  
You who teach, that he who will not belieue (and he that will doubt, will not belieue) that thing to be truth, which falſely by the perſuaſion of the Diuel, he belieues to be Diuine Reuelation, is a formal Heretique, and a blaſphemous wretch: you (I ſay) that teach this, who will not wonder, how you could be ſo inconſiderate, as to make vs damnable, becauſe we reſolue not to doubt of that doctrine, which by the Tradition of ſo many Chriſtian Ages, by our Paſtours and Anceſtours, men renowned for Learning, Sanctity, Miracles, for expelling of Diuels, for conuerting of nations, hath been deliuered, &amp; perſuaded vnto vs to be reuealed of God?
            
            
               That your Proteſtant VVay to be firme to no Religiō, but ſtill in motion and change, is damnable. §. 2.
               
               4. ABout your ſelfe, and your being vngrounded and vnſetled in matters of Religion, thus you write, and ſincerely profeſſe pag. 278. lin. 29. Cap. 5. n. 16. in. fine. 
                  I truly for my part, if I did not find in my ſelfe a loue and deſire of all profitable truth; if I did not put away idleneſſe, &amp; preiudice, and worldly affections, and ſo examine to the bottome all my opinions of Diuine matters, being prepared in mind to follow God, and God only, which way ſo euer he ſhall lead me; If I did not hope, that I eyther do, or endeauour to do, theſe thinges; certainly I ſhould haue litle hope of obtayning Saluation. Here you profeſſe, that neither Chriſtian

Religion, nor any truth thereof, hath been as yet firmely rooted, or deepely by the fingar of God printed in your heart. You declare your ſoule to be a Blanke, noted with no Religion: but prepared for any, which to you ſhall ſeeme of God, to wit you are ready to belieue not abſolutly, but Preface n. 5.
                  as most probable for the preſent; but reſolued neuer to belieue God ſo firmely, as to ranke doubting of what you haue receaued as his word, among mortall ſinnes.
               
               5. That this your practiſe implyeth doubting of all Chriſtian Religion, I proue; becauſe you profeſſe, to queſtion and examine all your opinions of Diuine matters; to make an if, or a doubt of the certainty and truth of them all; that is, you examine them, prepared in mind to leaue them all and euery one, if vpon trial they ſeeme to you falſe. But among your opinions of Diuine matters, your perſuaſion that our Chriſtian Scriptures and doctrines are Diuine oracles, and Gods word, is one; for you hold the Diuinity of Scriptures, &amp; conſequently of the Doctrines contained therein, only as an opinion very probable, as is hereafter 
                     Conuict. 6. ſhewed. Ergo you queſtion the holy Scripture, the Religion and Goſpell of Chriſt; you make an if of the truth and certainty thereof: You examine it doubtingly, with liberty of iudgment, prepared in mind to leaue it, if perchance you find the grounds thereof apparently falſe. What is this, but to be a Nullifidian, a man ſetled in no Religion, but doubtfull of all? Such an one as they were whome the Apoſtle 2. Ti. 3.7. checketh, terming them, men still learning, but neuer attayning to the aſſured knowledge of any thinge. Againe Cap. 5. n. 107. initio. 
                  Pag. 307. n. 107. you write, thus ſpeaking vnto our Maintayner: Your eleauenth falſhood is, that our first reformers ought to haue doubted, whether

their opinions were certaine: which is to ſay, they ought to haue doubted of the certainty of Scripture: which in formall and expreſſe termes contaynes many of theſe opinions. From this teſtimony I conclude, that you doubt of the cetainty of the Scripture. You profeſſe to examine and queſtion all your Protestant opinions of Diuine matters; to make a doubt of the certainty of them. But you contend, that ſome of your Protestant opinions of Diuine matters, be ſuch as to make a doubt or queſtion of the certainty of them, is to doubt of the certainty of formall and expreſſe Scripture. Ergo, your Way, and practiſe of doubting of all your opinions about Diuine matters, is doubting euen of the truth of the Chriſtian Scripture, and Ghoſpell of Chriſt. A thinge moſt impious and execrable as you now ſuppoſe, &amp; yet ſo fond and forgetfull you are, as to ſay, you ſhould haue litle hope of Saluation did you not do it, or endeauour to do it.
               6. In fine, your ſafe Way is a Labyrinth of implicatory and inextricable errours. Proteſtants, that are concluded therein, are loſt in a maze of vncertainties, and in an intricate mixture of contrary doctrines, being ſure to find nothing therein but damnation, which way ſo euer they turne themſelues. Do they doubt of the truth of their Religion which they belieue to be the Ghoſpell? They are both according to truth, and in your doctrine, damnable wretches, as being formall Heretiques. Be they ſo firme in their Religion, as they ranke doubting thereof among deadly ſinnes? Then they are (you ſay) obſtinately blind, ſure to fall into the pit of perdition, as much as we are, at the leaſt you affoard them litle hope of obtayning Saluation.
               
            
         
         
            
            The ſixt Conuiction.
            1. THis Conuiction ſheweth, that only Roman Catholiques haue ſauing fayth, which is demonſtrated by three Arguments. The firſt: Sauing fayth, is that, 
                  Hebr. 11.6. 
               without which it is impoſsible to pleaſe God. Now fayth which pleaſeth Gods muſt be on the one ſide certaine and infallible; otherwiſe it is not worthy of God, to whoſe word we owe ſo firme beliefe; that, if an Angel from heauen ſhould Euangelize against that we haue receaued as his word, he were not to be heard, but to be accurſed. On the other ſide, it muſt be a free and voluntary aſſent; not enforced by the euidence of the thinge. For if the reaſon of belieuing be euident, and ſuch as doth neceſſitate the Vnderſtanding to aſſent, the aſſent is not pleaſing to God; becauſe it is not voluntary obedience and ſubmiſſion to his word. Roman Catholiques by belieuing the Church to be infallible in all her propoſals, obtaine a perſuaſion about Diuine myſteries firme and infallible, and yet of voluntary obedience and ſubmiſſion. But the Oppoſers of the Roman Church, not only want certainty in truth; but alſo know not which way to challenge infallible certainty, without euidence.
            2. This may be proued by what you write, Cap. 6. n. 7. circa medium. 
               Pag. 329. lin. 31. The infallible certainty of a thing which though it be in it ſelfe; yet is not made appeare to vs infallibly certaine, to my vnderſtanding is an impoſsibility. What is this but to ſay, that fayth of a thing cannot be infallibly certaine; except the thinge belieued be made ſo cleere and apparent, that the vnderſtanding cannot chooſe but aſſent vnto it? For what appeares to vs to be infallibly certaine, is ſeen of vs to be infallibly certaine:

What we ſee to be infallible certaine, we cannot chooſe but aſſent, that it is ſo. So that, a firme 
               
                  Hebr. 11.1.6. Fides ſperandarum ſubſtantia rerū, argumē
                  tum non apparentium. 
               grounded beliefe of the truth of thinges not appearing, without which it is impoſsible to pleaſe God, is by your doctrine to Proteſtants impoſſible.
            3. Moreouer, that Proteſtants cannot haue fayth pleaſing to God, that is, fayth infallibly certayne not grounded on euidence, I demonſtrate in this ſort. No man can be aſſured infallibly of the truth of things not ſeene, nor to him euidently certaine, but by the word of an Authour infallibly veracious in all his words, deliuered vnto him by a witneſſe of infallible truth: For if the witneſſe, or meſſenger of the word be fallible, let the Authour of the word be neuer ſo infallible, our aſſent to the truth of the thing propoſed cannot be infallible. Now Proteſtants haue not the word of God by meanes of a witneſſe and meſſinger infallible: For the witneſſe, propoſer, and meſſenger of the word of God is the viſible Catholique Church, which Proteſtants hold to be fallible, full of falſe Traditions, not free (ſo you 
                  Pag 279. n. 64. The viſile Church is not free frō all errours in it ſelfe damnable. ſay) from errour in it ſelfe damnable, and in this ſenſe 
                  Pag. 291 lin. 8. From ſuch fundamentall errours the Church Catholique is not ſecured. 
               Fundamentall. Wherfore it is demonſtratiuely certaine, that onely Roman Catholiques (who belieue the Church to be infallible) can haue Fayth worthy of God; Fayth of voluntary ſubmiſſion to Gods word, that is, fayth of things to them not euidently yet infallibly certayne, and conſequently they only pleaſe God, by their belieuing and are ſaued.
            4. The ſecond Argument. You ſay Cap 3. n. 36. lin. 23. 
               pag. 148. lin. 16. There is no other reaſon to belieue the Scripture to be true, but onely becauſe it is Gods word: ſo that you cannot belieue the doctrines and myeſtries reuealed in Scripture to be true, more firmely and infallibly then you belieue

the Scripture to be Gods word: for we muſt be ſurer of the proofe, then of the thing proued thereby, otherwiſe it is no proofe, as you ſay pag. 37
                  •
               . n. 59. But your aſſurance that the Scripture is the word of God, is onely human, probable, and ſo abſolutely fallible. For you belieue the bookes which were neuer doubted of in the Church to be Gods word, and a perfect rule of fayth, onely by the tradition or teſtimonies of the ancient Churches 
               
                  Cap. 2. n. 27. 
               pag. 63. lin. 35. But, the ioynt tradition of all the Apostolicall Churches with one mouth and one voyce teaching the ſame doctrine, is onely a very probable argument, as you affirme 
                  Cap. 6. n. 40. 
               pag. 361. n. 40. Ergo, your fayth, that Scripture is Gods word, &amp; conſequently of all the myſteries therin reuealed, is but human and probable, and therefore vnworthy of God, being not firmer then the credit we yield to euery morall honeſt man. For to vs his word is probable and credible, and to you the word of God is no more.
            5. Proteſtants commonely pretend, that their fayth, that theſe Bookes be the word of God, reſteth finally, not vpō the credit of human Tradition, but vpon the Scripture onely; which ſhewes it ſelfe with euident certitude to be diuine and ſupernaturall truth and ſo reuealed of God, 
                  Caluin. l. 1. Instit c. 7. n. 2. Quod autem rogant, vnde perſuade bimur ſcripturas à Deo fluxiſſe: perinde eſt ac ſi quis roget, vnde diſcemus lucem diſcernere à tenebris, ſuaue ab amaro &amp;c. 
               Euen as light is ſeene by its owne brightneſse, and hony is proued to be ſweet by the very tast thereof. But this point of Proteſtancy you reiect, as fond, vaine, ridiculous, pag. 371. n. 51. and proue it to be ſuch. Becauſe, if the Bookes of Scripture were euidently certayne, if they did with euident certitude demonſtrate themſelues to be Diuine truth; then all men that haue vnderſtanding and capacity to apprehend the right ſenſe and ſentence of Scripture would belieue them to be true, which experience ſheweth be otherwiſe. If Proteſtants anſwere,

that ſuch as haue their taſt diſtempered, to them hony is bitter; ſo Infidels, through preiudice and diſtemper of paſſions, do not perceaue, and taſt the Diuinity of the Doctrines of the Scripture. Againſt this, the reply is ready and conuincing: For they who through diſtemper of their palate, iudge hony to be bitter, do not apprehend the true taſt of hony, but a taſt contrary to the true taſt thereof; which being in their palate, they conceaue it to be in the meate. But Infidels by their vnderſtanding do rightly apprehend, and conceaue the true ſenſes of Scripture, and the myſteries of fayth deliuered therein more cleerely then many Chriſtians of meane capacity do: and yet they do not iudge them to be Diuine truth, or truth at all. Ergo the very true ſenſe and ſentence of Scripture, doth not with euident certainty ſhew it ſelfe to be Supernaturall truth, ſuch as could not be reuealed, but of God.
            6. Finally, if the Proteſtants beliefe of Scripture be grounded vpon ſight of the truth thereof, this their beliefe is not ſauing fayth: for Fayth by which men are ſaued (as hath beene ſayd) is that wherby they ſubmit by voluntary obedience, their vnderſtanding to Gods word; belieuing firmely and aſſuredly vpon the Authority thereof, things in themſelues incredible, and aboue the reach of human reaſon. But Proteſtants do not belieue the doctrine of Scripture becauſe it is the word of God, but becauſe (as they ſay) they ſee it to be Diuine truth, and conſequētly the word of God. Ergo, they haue not the fayth of humble ſubmiſſion to Gods word, which is the onely fayth that pleaſeth God, and by which men are ſaued.
            7. The third Argument: Proteſtants haue not fayth of infallible adherence, that is, fayth worthy of

God, about the ſenſe, and interpretation of Scripture. For holding the Churches interpretation to be fallible; they pretend to be ſure by this rule, that what they belieue, to them ſeemes plainely, cleerely, euidently reuealed, and propoſed in the Scripture. But this rule of aſſurance is not infallible, but very fallible and deceytfull. For euen Proteſtants thēſelues contend, that many texts and places of Scripture, which ſeeme plaine and cleere, are to be vnderſtood figuratiuely againſt the plaine, proper, and literall ſenſe. For example the words of our Lord about the chiefe Sacrament &amp; myſtery of fayth, THIS is My Body, This is My BLOVD, in their plaine, proper and literall ſenſe deliuer and eſtabliſh Tranſubstantiation (as Proteſtants 
                  B. Morton l. 2. de enchar. initio. grant.) Hence Proteſtants, that are reſolued not to belieue a myſtery ſo high aboue reaſon, &amp; ſeemingly repugnant to ſenſe, will by no meanes allow theſe wordes to be true in their proper and literal ſenſe: they will not yield to the plain euidence of the Diuine text. Whereupon it is euidently conſequent, that they cannot be ſure, about any myſtery of fayth, by vertue of the ſole ſeeming euidence of the ſacred Text. For inſtance; take the moſt fundamental text of Scripture, about the moſt fundamētal myſtery of Chriſtian Religion, to wit, the Incarnation of the Sonne of God, Ioan. 1. 12. 
               The Word was made fleſh. How doth this text euidently conuince, that the Eternal Word, and Sonne of God was made Man truely, ſubſtantially, perſonally? What Proteſtants ſay of the word of Chriſt, This is my Body; why may not Nestorians affirme about this text, The Word was made ffeſh, that it is not true in a proper, plaine, and literal ſenſe, but metaphorically, figuratiuely, that God and Man were made one in Chriſt by affectual vnion, as two

great friendes are ſaid to be one? How can Proteſtants be themſelues aſſured, or how can they proue by the ſole euidence of the text, that this Nestorian interpretation is falſe? And if their beliefe of the myſtery of the Incarnation be not ſolide and firme, grounded on a rule of interpretation infallibly certaine; how can they be ſaued?
            8. Learned and iudicious Readers may find in your booke a world of laughter about your anſwering the arguments of Charity Maintayned: you do it ſo vnſcholler-like, ſo okerly and vntowardly. Let your anſwere to this argument ſerue for a patterne. Our Maintayner vrgeth D. Potter, that if the Church may erre in points of fayth not fundamentall, you can neuer be ſure of any ſuch point: For as you erre about ſome, deceyued by the ſeeming euidence of the Scripture, ſo you cannot be ſure you do not erre about other. You anſwere Cap. 2. n. 160. 
               Pag. 117. n. 160. A pretty Sophiſme depending vpon this principle, that whoſoeuer poſsibly may erre, he can neuer be certaine, that he doth not erre. A Iudge may poſsibly erre in iudgment: can he therefore neuer be ſure he hath iudged aright? A Traualler may poſsibly mistake his way; must I therefore be doubtfull, whether I am in the right way from my Hall to my chamber? Or can our London-Carrier haue no certainty in the middle of the day, when he is ſober, and in his wits, that he is in the way to London? And a litle after nu. 161. whereas our Mayntainer argueth, that you cannot be ſure it is an errour to make the Church Iudge of Controuerſies, becauſe you pretend to be ſure by the ſeeming euidence of Scripture; but this rule is not infallible, &amp; ſo you cānot be ſure by the warrant thereof.

                  The ground of this Sophiſme (ſay you) is very like the former, viz. that we can be certaine of the falſhood of no propoſition,

but thoſe only, that are damnable errours. But I pray, good Sir, giue me your opinion of theſe: The ſnow is balcke, the fire is cold, M. Knot is Arch-Bishop of Toledo, the whole is not greater then a part of the whole, that twiſe two make not foure, in your opinion, good Sir, are theſe damnable hereſies? Or becauſe they are not ſo, haue we no certainty of the falſhood of them. I beſeech you, Sir, conſider ſeriouſly with what ſtrāge captions you haue gone about to delude your King and your Country: &amp; if you be conuinced they are ſo, giue glory to God, and let the world know it by your deſerting that Religion, which standes vpon ſuch deceytfull foundations.
               
This you write, which you could neuer haue written, had you been with your London Carrier ſober, and in your wits. You haue proued Guſman de Alfarache his ſaying, that the Fooles Hoſpital is of large extent, to be moſt true: He can range and reuell within the compaſſe thereof in a world of ſottiſh extrauagances; from hoat to cold, from, ſnow to fire, from Oxford to London, from London to Toledo, from Toledo backe againe to King and Country, and then fetch a new carriere ouer the whole Vniuerſe, and euery part thereof, to be ſure, that no part is greater then the whole. What is impertinentcy, what is deſerting the matter and argument in hand, if this be not?
            Good Syr, be pleaſed to vnderſtand, that the Controuerſy betwixt D. Potter and our Maintayner, is not about all Kind of propoſitions, nor whether, ſnow be blacke, or fire cold, nor about your not being Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, nor about the way from your Hall to your Chamber: but about propoſitions pertayning to Chriſtian faith, not euident to ſenſe, but only to be knowne by reuelation from heauen. Our Maintayner auoucheth,

that theſe Diuine truths cannot be knowne aſſuredly, but by the teaching of Gods Church, infallible in all her propoſals. This he proueth not (as you feigne) by this principle, He that may poſsibly erre, can neuer be ſure he doth not erre, but by this: He that may erre, and hath ſome times erred by following ſome certaine Rule, can neuer be ſure he doth not erre by following the ſame rule. If a Iudge condemne a man to death wrongfully, vpon euidence giuen againſt him by two witneſſes, how can he be ſure, that he doth not condemne another man vniuſtly; if he haue no greater aſſurance, then the depoſition of two witneſſes, not knowne to be of better credit &amp; conſcience? A traueller hath been miſguided out of his way, by inquiring of the firſt man he met, &amp; truſting his direction; how can he be ſure he is not out of his way by crediting the word of another directour equally vnknowne vnto him? This then is the Argument of Charity Maintayned, which you durſt not encounter; but ran about the world in the wild-gooſe chaſe, to auoyd the force thereof. No man can be ſure he doth not erre by following a rule which is fallible and deceitfull; But to iudge of the ſenſe of the Scripture, by the ſole ſeeming euidence of the text, is a rule fallible, which often fayleth, and deceaueth them who rely thereon: becauſe many places are not taken in their plain, proper, literall ſenſe; and many texts conſidered by themſelues, ſeeme cleere and plaine, which conferred with other texts (that ſeeme to ſay the contrary) become darke and obſcure: Therefore to diſcerne the true ſenſe and meaning of Scripture by the ſole ſeeming euidence of ſome text thereof, is a rule fallible: &amp; Proteſtāts by the ſole direction therof can neuer be ſure, or infallibly certain about any myſtery of faith.
            
               10. And I pray you, good Sir, leaue your wild vagaries, come home to the litle cloſet of your wits, hold them cloſe to the matter, and then tell vs: A Proteſtant who denyes the wordes of Chriſt, This is my Body, to be true in their plain, proper and literall ſenſe; how can he be ſure himſelfe, or how can he aſſure others, that this text, The word was made fleſh, is to be taken, and true in the plain, proper and literal ſenſe? Do not tell vs, that you know the way from your Hall to your chamber, that ſnow is white, fyre hoat, M. Knot is not Arch-Biſhop of Toledo; but giue vs an aſſured rule whereby to know, that this text, The word was made fleſh, is literally to be vnderſtood in the plain ſubſtantial ſenſe: &amp; the text, This is my body, ought to be figuratiuely interpreted, ſo that the Body of Chriſt, be taken for but a peece of Bread? The meane while I conclude that Proteſtants ſeing they haue not any infallible rule to aſſure them of the ſenſe of Scripture; cannot firmely belieue the Myſteries reuealed therein: and ſo they haue, not ſuch a perſuaſion of the truth of Gods word, as is worthy of God, and pleaſing to him: nor will they euer obtayne ſauing fayth, till they ioyne with Roman Catholiques, to acknowledge the infallible authority of the viſible Catholike Church.
         
         
            The ſeauenth Conuiction.
            BEcauſe you cannot damne Roman Catholiques for any want of neceſſary and fundamentall truth; you endeauour to procure their damnation, and plead earneſtly for it, in regard they do not endeauour to know all profitable truth. In which diſcourſe you prodigiouſly contradict other aſſertions of your Booke. By the diſcouery of which, damnation will be ſeene to fall a

way from vs vpon your owne head, togeather with the cauſe meritorious thereof, the not caring to auoyd vnfundamentall hereſies.
            1. Firſt you contradict your ſelfe in the ſame ſentence, wherby you make your Way plaine, and yet impoſſible to be gone. Pag. 221 lin. 19. Cap. 4. n. 53. post medium. 
               This is a way ſo plaine, as fooles cannot (except they will) erre from it. Becauſe not knowing abſolutely all truth; nay not all profitable truth, &amp; not being free from errour, but endeuoring to know the truth and obey it, and to be free from errour, is by this Way made the onely condition of Saluation. It is ſtrange you ſhould ſay, that fooles cannot erre from your Way, vnleſſe they will: whereas your ſelfe being ſo wiſe a man haue erred ſo mightily from your Way, (no doubt againſt your will) as you are gone a contrary way. In the firſt part of your ſaying you pronounce your Way to be ſo plaine as fooles, except they will, cannot miſſe of being ſaued therein: but in the ſecond, you require ſo much, and ſo hard conditions of Saluation, as you make the ſame wholy impoſſible for fooles and ignorant perſons; and morally impoſſible euen to the learned'ſt leaders of your flocke. For you require to Saluation, that men know, not onely all neceſſary truth, but alſo that they endeauour to know all profitable truth, yea abſolutely all truth. For by vertue of your ſpeach they are bound to endeauour for the knowledge of that truth, which in this ſentence, you ſay, they are not bound to know. But the truth you ſay in this ſentence they are not bound to know, is not all neceſſary truth, but all profitable truth, yea abſolutely all truth: Ergo your followers are bound, as they will be ſaued, though not to know, yet to labour, endeauour, ſtudy to know all profitable truth, yea abſolutely all truth about Diuine matters. Which is, as

much as to ſay, that none can be ſaued in your way, but ſuch as haue ſtudied Diuinity, and haue not omitted ſo much as one queſtion thereof, not only about profitable points of that Science, but alſo about vnneceſſary and vnprofitable quirks, abſolutely all. What can be imagined more vaine fond, and abſurd, then to bind all men, as they will be ſaued, to ſtudy and endeauour for the knowledg of all Diuinity, and Diuine truth? And yet ſuch is your deſire to damne vs, as you will do it vpon any condition; though your ſelfe, and all other Proteteſtants be damned in our company.
            2. Secondly you groſſely contradict your ſelfe, whiles your declame againſt our Religion as extreme dangerous, becauſe we do not (you ſay) care to auoyd errours not fundamentall: which declamations are frequent in your booke, particularly Pag. 277. n. 61. lin. 29. 
                  Cap. 5. n 61. lin. 28. 
               Neither is there any reaſon, why ſuch a Church ſhould pleaſe her ſelfe too much for retayning fundamentall truths; whiles ſhe remaynes ſo regardleſſe of others.
For, though the ſimple defect of ſome truths profitable onely, and not ſimply neceſſary, may conſiſt with Saluation; yet who is there that can giue her ſufficient aſſurance, that the neglect of ſuch truths is not damnable? Beſides, who is there, that can put her in ſufficient caution, that theſe errours about profitable matters may not (according to the vſuall fecundity of errour) bring forth others of a higher quality, ſuch as are peſtilent and pernicious &amp;c. Laſtly, who can ſay, that ſhe hath ſufficiently dicharged her duty to God and man, by auoyding onely fundamentall Hereſies; if in the meane tyme ſhe be negligent of others, which though they do not deſtroy Saluation, yet obſcure and hinder, &amp; onely not blocke vp the way to it.
               
Thus you: who ſeeme as

forgetfull of your ſelfe, as he was, who is ſayd to haue had ſo little wit, as he could not remember his owne name. For had you remembred your name, to the queſtions, Who can giue ſuch a Church ſufficiēt aſſurance? who can put her in ſufficient caution? Who can ſay, ſhe hath done her duty ſufficiently? You would haue readily anſwered, I William Chillingworth: for you often vndertake for a Church that retaynes all Fundamentall truths, to be her ſurety, and giue her aſſurance of Saluation agaynſt all theſe pretended dangers. You ſay, they who belieue all fundamentals, belieue all neceſsaries, and ſo wee must confeſſe, that they may ſafely expect Saluation: except we will ſay, that more is neceſsary, then that which is neceſſary.
               You ſay, poynts circumstantiall (that is not fundamentall) be thoſe of which we may be ſecurely ignorant, ſuch as euen the Paſtours themſelues are not bound to know, or belieue, or not disbelieue them abſolutely and alwayes, but then only when they do ſee, &amp; know them to be deliuered in Scripture as Diuine Reuelations. I ſay when they do ſo, and know, and not onely when they may &amp;c. Otherwiſe it ſhould be a damnable ſinne in any learned man actually to disbelieue any one particular Hiſtoricall verity contayned in Scripture: for though he did not know it to be reuealed, yet he might haue knowne it, had he with diligence peruſed Scripture.
               
You ſay, he that belieues all fundamentals, cannot be damned for any errour of fayth. You earneſtly demand, He that belieues all neceſſary truth, how can he poſsibly fayle of Saluation if his life be anſwerable to his fayth?
            
            3. By theſe ſayings do not you giue men, that retayne all fundamentals, good cauſe of too much (that is of exceſſiue) pleaſure and content; by telling them they cannot poſſibly be damned for any errour in fayth? Do

not you affoard abundant aſſurance, that neglect to know truths not fundamentall, is not damnable, there being no obligation to know them, or to vſe diligence to find them? The people, and euen the Paſtours may ſecurely be ignorant of them, yea actually disbelieue them? Do not you put ſuch a Church in ſufficient caution, that errours not Fundamentall cannot bring forth errours peſtilent and pernicious? that ſhe hath performed her duety to God and man ſufficiently vnto Saluation, by auoyding Fundamentall Hereſies? Except you will ſay more is neceſsary, then that which is neceſſary; that can be which cannot be; that is poſſible which is altogether impoſſible; men are bound to know that which they are not bound to know; men are damned for not caring to know, that whereof they might be ſecurely ignorant. Into this maze of contradictions you are brought by your will to damne vs, which is much ſtronger then your wit.
            4. Your third Deuiſe to damne vs, it yet more full of ſtrange forgetfulneſſe, and contradiction of your ſelfe. You ſuppoſe, that we diſtinguiſh Hereſies into two kinds, ſome fundamentall, ſome not fundamentall; that we hold the firſt damnable and vtterly deſtructiue of Saluation, and ſo to be carefully auoyded; but that men may be ſaued in their hereſies of the ſecond kind. Hence you ſay, we regard not Hereſies vnfundamentall, we are careleſſe and negligent to auoyd them; being perſuaded, that if we hold all fundamentall truth, we cannot be damned for any errour or hereſy againſt fayth. In regard of this looſe doctrine and our negligence conſequent thereupon; you ſay, we are in great danger of damnation. This is your Plea againſt our Saluation, ſo dull, and ſo voyd of memory as you

may ſeeme to haue forgotten euen the argument of the whole booke of Charity manitayned, and of your owne. For this diſtinction of Hereſies into two ſortes, ſome Fundamentall, ſome not Fundamental, is taught by Proteſtants, who by the largeneſſe &amp; laxitie of this doctrine would draw ſome kind of Heretiques, to wit Heretiques not fundamentall, within the compaſſe of the fold of Chriſt, and the number of them that be ſaued. This is the ſubſtance of D. Potters whole treatiſe, which our maintayner impugneth. Is it not thē prodigious want of memory to charge the Roman Church with this Doctrine, and to ſeeke her damnation, becauſe (forſooth) ſhe doth not care to auoyd Hereſies not Fundamentall? For our Roman Theology doth not allow the diſtinction of errours or hereſies agaynſt fayth into Fundamentall and not Fundamentall in your ſenſe: for we hold Hereſies damnable, and equally damnable, as much thoſe, that are againſt Truths profitable only, as thoſe that deſtroy truths ſimply neceſſary. Hence in the Way of the Roman Church, he that knowing Tranſubſtantiation to be propoſed as matter of fayth, by the definition of the Church, ſhall preſume to gaine ſay it, is as full, formall, and very an Heretique, as he who denyes the perſonall vnion of two Natures, Diuine and Human in Chriſt. For the greatnes of the malice of Hereſy is not meaſured by the greatneſſe of the matter denyed; but by the greatnes of the pride, wherby an Heretique preferres his fancies of Scripture before the definition of the Church; &amp; by the greatnes of that impiety, wherby he preſumes to reiect that doctrine, which he hath ſo many ſtronge reaſons to belieue to be reuealed of God.
            
            5. If you ſay, that Charity maintayned doth ſuppoſe, that the Roman Church hath ſome corruptions and

errours in fayth not Fundamentall; I anſwere it is impudently in you ſo to affirme; and great vanity to gather your affirmation from theſe his wordes, As for our Churchs corruptions in doctrine (I ſpeake vpon the vntrue ſuppoſition of our Aduerſaries): you vpon no better warrant then this; ſay to our Maintayner pag. 274. n. 58. Cap. 5. n. 58. &amp; 59. 
               You are ſo courteous as to ſuppoſe corruptions in your doctrine. And a little after pag. 275. n. 59. I thanke you for your courteous ſuppoſall, that your Church may erre. And pag. 276. lin. 2. You ſuppoſe your Church in errour; &amp; yet excommunicate thoſe that belieue your owne ſuppoſition. What found vanity is this? To ſay, Our Aduerſaries do vntruly ſuppoſe there be corruptions in our Church, is this a courteous ſuppoſall, and not rather a conſtant deniall that ſhe doth erre, and a charge of falſhood vpon them that ſo ſuppoſe? Is the vntrue ſuppoſition of our Aduerſaries our owne ſuppoſition? I was euen amazed at your inconſideration when I read theſe words in your Booke pag. 280. n. 95. lin. 8. 
                  Cap. 5 n 95. lin. 8. 
               Why I pray may not a man of iudgement continue in the communion of a Church confeſsedly corrupted; aſwell as in a Church ſuppoſed to be corrupted? A ſtrange aſſertion; A man may aſwell imbrace the cōmunion of a Church corrupted confeſſedly by the conceſſion of her friends; as of a Church vntruly ſuppoſed by her Aduerſaries to be corrupt. So that with you, for a Chriſtian to ſay, S. Ioſeph was the Father of Chriſt, and the Bleſſed Virgin corrupt, according to the vntrue ſuppoſition of the Iewes, is all one, as to ſay, S. Ioſeph was the Father of Chriſt, and the Bleſſed Virgin corrupt confeſſedly euen by the conceſſion of Chriſtians. Wherfore if it be damnable to neglect Hereſies not Fundamentall (as without queſtion it is) this proueth Proteſtants damnable, who thinke it not againſt Saluation to hold errours in

fayth, and hereſies againſt the definition of the whole Church, if ſuch hereſies be about matters profitable onely, and not ſimply neceſſary.
         
         
            The eight Conuiction.
            1. YOu inſcribe the pages of your laſt Chapter with this title: The Religion of Protestants a ſafer Way to Saluation then the Religion of Papists. For which aſſertion (beſides bare and bold affirmations, &amp; earneſt verball expreſſions, manifeſt tokens (as you ſay) of a weake cauſe) you haue one Argument which is this, pag. 393. n. 
               Cap. 5. n. 9. 9.

                  If the ſafer way for auoyding ſinne, be alſo the ſafer way for auoyding damnation, then certainly the way of Proteſtants muſt be more ſecure, and the Roman way more dangerous. Take into your conſideration theſe enſuing controuerſies. Whether it be lawfull to worſhip Pictures? To picture the Trinity? To inuocate Saints and Angels? To deny laymen the Cup in the Sacrament? To prohibite certayne Orders of men and women to mary. To celebrate the publique ſeruice of God in a language the aſsiſtants generally vnderstand not? and you will not chooſe but confeſſe, that in all theſe you are on the more dangerous ſide for the committing of ſinne; and we on that which is more ſecure. For in all theſe things (if we ſay true) you do that which is impious. On the other ſide, if you were in the right, yet we might be ſecure inough; for we ſhould onely not do ſomething, which you confeſſe not neceſſary to be done. We pretend, and are ready to iuſtify out of Principles agreed vpon betweene vs; that in all theſe things you violate the manifeſt Commandements of God; and alleage

ſuch texts of Scripture againſt you, as (if you would weigh them with any indifferēcy) would put the matter out of queſtion: but certainely you cannot with any modeſty deny, but that at leaſt they make it questionable.
               
This argument I haue ſet downe at large, becauſe it is the beſt in your booke, and yet vaine and weake, as I now demonſtrate.
            
               The ground of your Safety, onely falſe ſuppoſitions, and foolish braggs. §. 1.
               
               2. FIrſt it is falſe, that if Proteſtants ſay true, we do that which is impious. For Proteſtants againſt Zelots maintayne, that our practiſes though erroneous in their iudgement, yet are not impious, and in themſelues damnable; and that they who in ſincerity of heart profeſse them, ſhall this notwithſtanding D. Potter pag. 78. 
                  without doubt be ſaued.
               
               3. Secondly, it is falſe, that if we be in the right, yet you may be ſecure inough in your refuſing to vſe theſe our practiſes, becauſe they be not neceſſary. For though it be no ſinne of it ſelfe purely to omit pious practiſes, and profitable deuotions: yet to omit them out of proud cōtempt, and much more out of an Hereticall perſuaſion, that they be impious, is vndoubtedly an heynous and damnable crime. It is not neceſſary that you marry a wife, you may be ſaued if you lead a chaſt ſingle life: but if you omit mariage out of an opinion, that it is a thing impure, or out of contempt of that doctrine, that 
                     Epheſ. 5.32. 
                  Mariage is a great Sacrament in Christ and his Church; you will (except you repent) certainly be damned. In like manner, if we be in the right, and that theſe be pious

Chriſtian practiſes of voluntary deuotion, you who relinquiſh them out of contempt, and Hereticall perſuaſion that they are impious, cannot eſcape damnation without a dereliction of your errour.
               4. Thirdly, it is falſe, that if we be in the right, yet you only do not ſomething which we confeſſe not neceſſary to be done. For we do not ſay of all theſe practiſes, that they be not neceſſary to be done; yea we ſay, it is neceſſary to Saluation to receaue the B. Sacrament, and in receauing to adore it. Beſides we ſay, that you not only omit to do what is not neceſſary to be done, but alſo condemne the vniuerſall practiſes of Gods Church, and definitions of her Generall Councells; which is not only not neceſſary to be done, but alſo execrable, impious, hereticall to be done.
               5. Fourthly, it is a fooliſh bragge that you can alleadge ſuch cleere texts of Scripture againſt theſe our practiſes. For if you can alleade them, why do you conceale them? Why are you aſhamed to bring them to light? Why haue you not ſtored your booke with ſuch allegations as are able to put the matter out of question? Some very few you haue produced,Church Conquerant cap. 6. conuict. 8. and thoſe which you tearme the playnest that poſsibly may be, I haue ſhewed to be darke, obſcure, yea by you falſifyed in the text?
               6. Fiftly, it is alſo a fooliſh bragge, that your texts of Scripture be certainly ſuch as make the matter queſtionable: which you proue very grauely, becauſe we cannot with any modeſty deny it. Verily had you any modeſty or ſhame, you would bluſh to diſpute ſo poorely, miſerably, ſeelily in a Controuerſy of ſuch moment which concernes the eternal damnation of your Country. I adde, though it were true (as it is moſt falſe)

that your texts make the matter queſtionable; yet your abandoning the Roman Church is damnable. For, Arguments which make the matter queſtionable, be not neceſſary nor euident: But it is damnable to forſake the Church of Rome, and the definition of General Councels without reaſons neceſſary and euident, as both you and D. Potter affirme, as hath beene often noted.
            
            
               Theſe doctrines and practiſes are proued by manifest and plaine Scripture. §. 2.
               
               ON the other ſide, Roman Catholiques do not boaſt ridiculouſly, as you do, of their texts of Scripture; but by manifeſt euiction ſhew euen theſe, of the impiety of which you ſeeme moſt cōfident, to be Chriſtian and pious, and conſequently, that your damning of them is damnable and impious.
               7. For images of Chriſt crucifyed vſed in the Church with Apoſtolicall allowance we haue the plaine words of S. Paul Gal. 3.1. O ſenſeleſse Galathians, who hath be witched you not to obey the Goſpel, before whoſe eyes Christ Ieſus, is painted Crucifyed among you. The Greeke word is 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   liuely ſet forth in the picture of his Crucifixion; ſo that S. Paul proueth the Galatians were ſenſeleſſe people, that honoring Chriſt Ieſus pictured before their eyes as crucifyed; yet did not hope for Saluation by his Croſſe and Crucifixion; but by Circumciſion, and the obſeruances of the Law. This ſenſe being according to the plaine proper, and literall ſenſe of the wordes, Proteſtants are bound by the rule of their Religion to admit thereof, and cannot without impiety refuſe it, and expound the place of metaphoricall Painting; except they can euidently

demonſtrate this ſenſe to be falſe or incongruous againſt the Apoſtles intent, which they will neuer be able to do.
               8. If you ſay, that this text at the moſt proueth the vſing of Images for the repreſentation,Appeale to Caeſar pag. 254.255.
                   not honoring of them: I anſwere with the learned M. Montague your Biſhop of Chicheſter, that in the vſing of Images for memory ſake, the honouring of them is neceſſarily included, which he proueth euidently, and together affirmes, that it is strange, that any Chriſtian ſhould be diſpleaſed with the Doctrine, That reſpect and honour is to be giuen to Images.
               
               9. The Perſons of the Trinity we picture not, but only the perſon of Goa the Sonne in the forme and ſhape of man, as perſonally he was. Onely we repreſent the type wherein God the Father appeared, to wit, the forme of the Ancient of dayes, deſcribed Dan. 7. and the type, wherein the Holy Ghoſt appeared the forme of a Doue, recorded Math. 3.
               10. For Inuocation of Angels, we haue the practiſe and example of holy Iacob Gen. 84.15. The Angell which deliuered me from all euill, bleſſe theſe Children: which text, you cannot anſwere without iugling and changing the Angell into the figure of another ſubſtance.
               11. For the ſufficiency of the Sacrament vnder the forme of bread, we haue the expreſſe warrant of our Lord, Ioan. 6.59. He that eateth this bread ſhall liue for euer. And for the practiſe of Communion in one kind for lay men we haue his example Luc. 24.30.31.
               12. For the adoration of the Sacrament, we haue the Scripture in the plaine and proper ſenſe. For (ſayth D. Morton 
                  Lib. 2. initio. your B. of Durham) If the words of Chriſt be true in a proper and literall ſenſe, we muſt yield vnto Papists the

whole cauſe of Tranſubstantiation &amp;c. the proper adoration of the Sacrament.
               
               13. That we prohibite certaine orders of men &amp; women to mary is a ſlander. They freely without conſtraint prohibite themſelues, whiles by vow they bind their fayth, and fidelity vnto Chriſt, to liue ſingle and chaſt, &amp; peculiarly conſecrated to his ſeruice. Which fayth and fidelity, if they violate and make voyd by conſequent Mariage (as your firſt reformer the Frier did, who married a Nunne), we hold their ſtate ſacrilegious and damnable, which is the expreſſe doctrine of S. Paul, 1. Tim. 5.12.
               14. The Controuerſy, which language is fitteſt, and of moſt edification in Church ſeruice: whether the vulgar, which is beſt knowne in this or that particular country; or ſome learned language, Greeke or Latin, which be beſt knowne in the whole Chriſtian Church; cannot be determined by Scripture, as hath beene already proued. So that meaſuring the way of Saluation euen by the rule of the Bible only, the Roman Religion is the plainer, and ſafer Way, better warranted, euen by expreſſe texts of Scripture.
            
         
         
            The Ninth Conuiction.
            THe chiefe Fundamental ground of the ſecurity Roman Catholiques enioy, that they are in the right Way of Saluation, according to which if they walke they cannot be damned; is the direction of an infallible guide, the holy Catholique Church, which is no other but the Roman. This is conuinced by what your ſelf are forced to grāt, as hath been ſhewed, Church Conquerant cap. 5.6. &amp;. 7. but

becauſe this buſineſſe is the maine and the totall, I will here repeate ſome of the paſſages though very briefly.
            1. Firſt, conuicted by the wordes of S. Paul, you grant, that the viſible Catholique Church is the pillar and ground of truth, that is, the teacher of all neceſſary, and profittable truth by duty and office; yea that ſhe is always in fact the teacher of all truth neceſſary to Saluation. For (ſay you) that the true Church alwayes ſhall be the maintayner and teacher of all neceſſary truth, we grant, and must grant: For it is of the eſſence of the Church to be ſo; and any company of men were no more a Church without it, then any thing can be a man, and not be reaſonable. Thus you grant, that there is and alwayes ſhall be a Catholique Church, which ſhall not only belieue inwardly and in heart; but alſo teach and (a) propoſe without fayle all diuine reuelation 
               The viſible Church ſhall alwayes without fayle propoſe ſo much of Gods reuelation, as is ſufficiēt vnto Saluation. For otherwiſe it will not be the viſible Church. 
               neceſsary to Saluation. For it is her very eſsence to be ſo. Wherefore not only in belieuing, but alſo in teaching and propoſing all neceſſary truth, ſhe can no more faile then from her owne being which is indefectible. Hence ſhe is (and you muſt grant ſhe is) an infallible guide in Fundamentalls: Becauſe to ſhew men the way to heauen, by teaching them all reuealed truth that is neceſſary to bring them thither; what is it, but to be a guide of men vnto Saluation; ſhewing them the Fundamental doctrines of Chriſtian Religion, without which no man is ſaued?
            2. Secondly, the viſible Catholique Church, being (as you grant ſhe is) an infallible teacher or guide in Fundamentalls, muſt of neceſſity be alſo infallible in all her propoſalls. The neceſſity of this conſequence you deny a thouſand tymes, and almoſt in euery period of your third Chapter; yet you affirme it in expreſſe termes. Pag. 105 n. 139. lin. 23. To ſay, that the Church is an infallible guide in Fundamentals, were to oblige our ſelues

to find ſome certain Society of men, of whome we might be certain, that they neither do, nor can erre in Fundamentals; nor in declaring what is Fundamental, and what is not: and conſequently to make any Church an infallible guide in Fundamentals would be to make her infallible in all thinges ſhe propoſes; and requires to be belieued. Which truth you proue vnanſwerably. Pag. 148. n. 36.
            3. Thirdly, the viſible Catholique Church being a guide in Fundamentals, that is, alwayes a Teacher of all neceſsary truth, is a Church (c) of one denomination, that is, ſome ſettled certaine Society of Christians knowne and distinguiſhed from other Societies, by adhering to ſuch a Biſhop. This is proued by this Syllogiſme, wherein both the premiſes be your owne formall aſſertions. The Church is appointed of God to be the teacher and guide of men in the way of Saluation, and ſo ſhe is able and fit for that office. For God would not by his word haue appointed her an office, for which ſhe is vnfit and vnable to perferme it; yea, you ſay, the Church is not only able to performe the office of guide; but alſo that alwayes in fact ſhe doth exerciſe the ſame in teaching all neceſſary truth. But you ſay Cap. 3. n. 55.
                
               pag. 163. lin. 9. A Church of one denomination distinguiſhed from all others by adhering to ſuch a Biſhop; ſuch a determinate Church alone can performe the office of Guide and Directour. And Pag. 
               Cap. 2. n. 139. 105. n. 239. lin. 30. No Church can poſsibly be fit to be a guide, but only a Church of ſome certaine denomination, as the Greeke, the Roman, the Ahiſsine. Wherefore the Viſible Catholique Church being fit, and able to performe the office of Guide and Directour (as you grant ſhe is, and that it is eſſentially neceſsary that ſhe be ſo) ſhe is, and of neceſſity muſt be a Church of one denomination, ſubiect to one certaine ſupreme Guide and Biſhop.
            
               4. From theſe moſt certaine truthes by you granted, approued and proued, it is neceſſarily and euidently conſequent; that the Roman Church is the Viſible Catholique Church of God, an infallible Teacher of all fundamentall and neceſſary truth: yea infallible in all thinges she propoſes as matter of fayth: This I ſay, is cleerely conſequent of the former grants. For the viſible Church being the Guide, Teacher and Directour of men, is on the one ſide a Church of one denomination; elſe ſhe could not performe that office of guide which ſhe doth (as you confeſse) alwayes actually performe. On the other ſide, being the Catholique, that is, the Vniuerſall Church, ſhe muſt be ſpread ouer the face of the earth; as the Roman is in Europe, Africa, Aſia, America, and in many of the particular Kingdomes, and Prouinces of theſe foure quarters of the world. So that the wordes of S. Paul to the Romans, come to be verified no leſſe now, then at that time, your fayth is renowned and published in the whole world. Which vniuerſality, or vniuerſal Vnity agrees to no other Church of one denomination, as is manifeſt. Wherefore the Roman Church is the Holy Catholique Church, the infallible guide of men in the way of Saluation.
            5. Hence is concluded the ſecurity of Roman Catholiques, that they cannot poſſibly erre about matters of fayth, ſo long as they follow the dogmatical directions and definitions of the Roman Church. Contrariwiſe they who oppoſe what they know to be propoſed by her, as matter of fayth, erre Heretically &amp; damnably, and cannot poſſibly be ſaued without expreſse repentance of their errours.
         
         
            
            The Concluſion.
            6. THis argument of the aſsured Saluation of Roman Catholiques, and of the aſſured damnation of all the knowing oppoſers of their Religion and Church, being thus euidently demonſtrated; for Concluſion I could wiſh an Ocean of teares of bloud, endued with the quality of mollifying hearts, as hard as the Adamant: for ſo I might condignely and fruitefully deplore the pittifull ſtate, the commiſerable condition, the vnfortunate thraldome in Errour of many millions in our deare Country, cauſed by mortall auerſion from the true Catholique Church, which is inſtilled into their mindes by Heretical education.
            
            7. They grant, conuicted by the euidence of Gods word, that the Catholique Church is the ground and rocke of Truth, wheron men may ſecurely reſt and rely; an infallible Guide and teacher of all Fundamentals; conſequently of all euen profitable truth about Diuine matters. They further acknowledge, conuicted by experience and reaſon, that the Church cannot be fit orable to performe the office of guide &amp; Directour, except it be of one denomination, of one obedience, ſubiect to one determinate Biſhop as her ſupreme Paſtour and Gouernour. They cannot but ſee with their eyes, there is no Church Catholique, or vniuerſally diffuſed, of one Fayth, of one Obedience, of one Denomination, ſubiect to one Paſtour, acknowledged of all of that Religion, but the Roman: Conſequently, that there is no Church beſides the Roman fit, or able to performe the office of Guide and Directour to men that are ſaued, as

the true Catholique Church is bound to do, and alwayes actually doth. Theſe thinges they confeſſe, or ſee; and yet ſo inflexible is the obſtinacy, the paſſion, &amp; pride againſt the Roman Church, wherwith Education (like Meduſa's head) hath dulled, ſtupifyed, and inſtoned their ſoules, as they contemne her Direction, forſakes her Communion, hate her Authority, ſcorne her Motherly care of their Saluation, running to perdition in the way of their owne fallible, and palpably falſe conceytes fancied to be Scripture.
            8. Why did our Sauiour make his Church the pillar and ground of truth, that is, an infallible Teacher of the doctrine of Saluation; but that he would haue men to make vſe of her teaching? As knowing, that, through a world of errours, which carry with them a faire ſhew of truth, they could not attayne to eternal Happineſſe, without a Viſible infallible Guide. No doubt when he gaue her the office of Mother, he bound vs as we would be his Children and Heyres, to loue, honour, and reuerence Her; and to liue alwayes in the lap of her Communion. When he gaue her the office of Guide, he bound vs to follow her directions, as we deſire to ſpeed in our iourney to him, and to come to ſee for euer his Bleſſed face. When he gaue her the office of Rocke, he obliged vs to build our fayth and hope of Saluation on her Teaching; aſſuring vs that no ſublimity of wit &amp; vnderſtanding, no Omnis caelo inferenda ſublimitas in huius Petrae firmitate conſurgit. S. Leo. ſerm. 3. in anniuerſ. Aſſump. ſuc.
                height of perfection, be it in our conceite neuer ſo eleuate, can reach to Heauen, which is not grounded on the neuer-fayling fortitude of this Rocke.
            9. They then that haue diſioyned themſelues from the wombe and lap of this Mother, can neuer be ſo in Gods fauour, as to be his Children, the Heyres of his glory

the fellow heyres with Christ: They that follow not the Directions of this euer vn-erring Guide, be not in the way towardes him, that is Truth and Life, but wander in a wilderneſse of Errour, the iſſue wherof is eternall Death· They that haue not ſetled the feete of their Fayth and Affection on this Rocke, the ſole Rocke of ſafety in this vaſt Ocean of dangers; what are they but wauing and wauering Babes, floating in a ſea of vncertainties, toſſed this way and that way with euery gust of erroneous doctrine?
            10. For a man not to belieue, that our Sauiour did inſtitute his Church to continue for euer, the Teacher of all ſauing truth; the Rocke of Saluation, againſt which the gates of Hell ſhall neuer preuayle; what is this, but to ſtop his eares againſt the cleer and plaine voyce of his word? For a man to ſay, that he gaue the office of Guide to a confuſed multitude and Chaos of different Religions and Obediences and not to a Church of one denomination, which alone is able to performe that office; what is it but to open his mouth into blaſphemies againſt his Diuine Wiſedome? For a man not to ſee, that there is no vniuerſally diffuſed Church in the world of one fayth, and obedience, all the Profeſſours thereof adhering vniuerſally to one certayne Biſhop, beſides the Roman; what is it but in a deſperate moode of neglect, to ſhut his eyes againſt the truth, that may ſaue his ſoule, the cleere euidence whereof ſhineth ouer the world?
                  Hebr. 2.3. So that I may ſay with the Apoſtle, Quomodo nos effugiemus ſi tantam neglexerimus ſalutem? How ſhall we eſcape from being damned, if we neglect ſo great a meanes; ſuch an aſſured way of Saluation?
            11. A Way ſo ſecure to be followed, ſo obuious to be found ſo cleere to be ſeene, ſo facile to be gone, ſo

hard to be loſt? In which we haue the ſuccour of ſo many Sacraments, not onely that of Baptiſmes to put vs in the Way, and giue vs Gods Holy Spirit to walke therein; but alſo that of the Bread of life, to refreſh vs when we faynt; that of Chriſme to confirme vs when we are ſtronge; that of Pennance, or impoſition of Hands, to help vs vp, when we are fallen, that of Holy Oyle to heale vs, when we are ſicke.
            12. A Way beaten &amp; made plaine by the precedent walking therein, of ſo many former Chriſtian worlds; proued to be the ſole Way to Heauen, by the writings of ſo many moſt holy and learned Ancient Fathers; ſealed and enobled for ſuch with the ſacred bloud of innumerable Martyrs; confirmed by the perpetuall, and vnto this day continued Conuerſion of Nations to the Roman Church; by the glorious labours of her Apoſtolical Preachers.
            13. Finally a Way printed with the foote-ſtepps of Sanctity of ſo many millions of admirable pious and Religions Chriſtians; who went this Way to Eternall Happines; and haue from thence ſent vs tidings of their ſafe arriuall, by the teſtimony of euident miracles and vndoubted apparitions: to aſſure vs, we cannot fayle of comming thither, if we walke conſtantly in the Way of the ſame fayth they profeſſed; and in the exerciſe of the ſame Chriſtian Vertues they practiſed.
         
         FINIS.
      
      
         
            
            The contents of the Booke, &amp; the ſumme of ech of the Nine Conuictions.
            
               The firſt Conuiction.
               THe Confeſſion of Proteſtants, that our Religion is a ſafe Way to Saluation, proued againſt M. Chillingworths falſifications, and ignorant explications of D. Potters words. §. 1.2.3.
               That the argument drawne from the confeſſion of Proteſtants is not voluntary and of meere charity, but enforced by the principles of Chriſtianity. §. 4.5.
               That M. Chillingworth doth expreſſely teach the errours of Proteſtants to be damnable in themſelues, and the Roman Religion to be as ſafe as it. §. 6.
            
            
               The ſecond Conuiction.
               Though the falſe ſuppoſition were granted, that the Roman Church erreth; yet Roman Catholiques cānot be damned for following her errours; becauſe they cannot but be excuſed by ignorance inuincible. §. 1.2.
               That Proteſtants if they erre (as certainty they do) cannot be ſaued by Ignorance, or General Repentance. §. 3.
               
                  M. Chillingworth his impudent falſifying of the Tenet of Charity Maintayned. §. 4.
            
            
               The third Conuiction.
               The Roman Church holding all fundamentall and neceſſary truth, no man can poſſibly be damned in her Communion for any errour in fayth; ſo that it is madneſſe to leaue it. §. 1.2.
               That Proteſtants cannot poſſibly be ſure they belieue all neceſſary truth; &amp; what impoſſible conditions

of Saluation M. Chillingworth layes vpon them. §. 3.
            
            
               The fourth Conuiction.
               That in M. Chillingworth his Way Engliſh Proteſtantes can be no more ſaued then Socinians, who deny Chriſt to be God; yea no more then Iewes and Turkes: with ſix proofes, that he is a Socinian. §. 1.2.
            
            
               The fifth Conuiction.
               That M. Chillingworth damneth Roman Catholiques for being faithfull and conſtant Chriſtians. § 1.
               That in his Way Proteſtants are bound to be ſtill doubtfull, and changing the articles of their Religion, and that this is damnable. §. 2.
            
            
               The ſixt Conuiction.
               That only Roman Catholiques can haue fayth which pleaſeth God, and ſaueth the Belieuer, demonſtrated by three arguments.
            
            
               The ſeauenth Conuiction.
               
                  M. Chillingworth his vayne &amp; contradictious endeauour to damne the Roman Church, becauſe forſooth ſhe doth not care to auoyd Hereſies not Fundamental; &amp; that this is the dānable ſtate of Proteſters againſt her.
            
            
               The eight Conuiction.
               
                  M. Chillingworth his inſtances in ſome points wherin he pretendes the way of Proteſtants to be ſafer then ours, proued to be falſe ſuppoſitions &amp; idle brags. §. 1.
               The Roman Doctrine and practiſe euen in thoſe inſtances proued by plaine texts of Scripture. §. 2.
            
            
               The Ninth Conuiction.
               That the true Catholique Church is infallible in all

her Propoſals, known by ſubordination to one ſupreme Biſhop; &amp; that this church cā be no other thē the Roman.
            
            
               The Concluſion.
            
         
         
            Faults eſcaped in the Print.
            
               
                  
                     PAge.
                     Line.
                     Errour.
                     Correction.
                  
                  
                     6.
                     20.
                     in marg. omitted
                     
                        Lib. 3. cont. lit. Petil. c. 18.
                  
                  
                     37.
                     5.
                     inforing
                     inforcing
                  
                  
                     52.
                     7.
                     ſo farre
                     too farre
                  
                  
                     63.
                     21.
                     change
                     change
                  
                  
                     84.
                     13.
                     your
                     you
                  
                  
                     88.
                     2.
                     impudently
                     impudency
                  
               
            
         
      
   

