
   
      
         
            Feudigraphia The synopsis or epitome of surueying methodized. Anatomizing the whole corps of the facultie; viz. The materiall, mathematicall, mechanicall and legall parts, intimating all the incidents to fees and possessions, and whatsoeuer may be comprized vnder their matter, forme, proprietie, and valuation. Very pertinent to be perused of all those, whom the right, reuenewe, estimation, farming, occupation, manurance, subduing, preparing and imploying of arable, medow, pasture, and all other plots doe concerne. And no lesse remarkable for all vnder-takers in the plantation of Ireland or Virginia ... Composed in a compendious digest by W. Folkingham. G.
            Folkingham, W. (William)
         
         
            
               1610
            
         
         Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01017
            STC 11123
            ESTC S102453
            99838238
            99838238
            2605
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01017)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2605)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 727:07)
         
         
            
               
                  Feudigraphia The synopsis or epitome of surueying methodized. Anatomizing the whole corps of the facultie; viz. The materiall, mathematicall, mechanicall and legall parts, intimating all the incidents to fees and possessions, and whatsoeuer may be comprized vnder their matter, forme, proprietie, and valuation. Very pertinent to be perused of all those, whom the right, reuenewe, estimation, farming, occupation, manurance, subduing, preparing and imploying of arable, medow, pasture, and all other plots doe concerne. And no lesse remarkable for all vnder-takers in the plantation of Ireland or Virginia ... Composed in a compendious digest by W. Folkingham. G.
                  Folkingham, W. (William)
               
               [8], 88 p., folded table   
               
                  Printed [by William Stansby] for Richard Moore, and are to be solde at his shop in Saint Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleete-streete,
                  London :
                  1610.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Running title reads: The art of suruey.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Surveying --  Early works to 1800.
               Agriculture --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-05
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-05
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               FEVDIGRAPHIA.
            
            THE SYNOPSIS OR EPITOME OF SVRVEYING METHODIZED.
            Anatomizing the whole Corps of the Facultie; Viz.
            
            The Materiall, Mathematicall, Mechanicall and Legall Parts,
            Intimating all the Incidents to Fees and Poſſeſſions, and whatſoeuer may be comprized vnder their Matter, Forme, Proprietie, and Valuation.
            
               
                  Ʋery pertinent to be peruſed of all thoſe, whom the Right, Reuenewe, Estimation, Farming, Occupation, Manurance, Subduing, Preparing and Imploying of Arable, Medow, Paſture, and all other Plots doe concerne.
            
            And no leſſe remarkable for all Vnder-takers in the Plantation of Ireland or Virginia, for all Trauailers for Diſcoueries of forraine Countries, and for Purchaſers, Exchangers, or Sellers of Land, and for euery other Intereſſe in the Profits or Practiſe deriued from the compleate SVRVEY Of Manours, Lands, Tenements, Edifices, Woods, Waters, Titles, Tenures, Euidences, &amp;c.
            
            Compoſed in a compendious Digeſt by W. FOLKINGHAM. G.
            
               Quae proſunt ſingula, multa iuvant.
            
            LONDON Printed for Richard Moore, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Saint Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleete-ſtreete, 1610.
         
         
            
            ¶ The Contents of the foure Sections of the Art of Surueying.
            
               The firſt Section.
               INtreateth of the Materialls of Poſſeſſions, of the diuerſities of Earthes, Waters, Quarries, Mines, of the Cruſts and Inveſtures of Grounds with their peculiar Subduing, Manuring and Imploying, of fitting ſeuerall ſorts of Graine, Hearbes, Rootes, Plants with Plots of Conuenient Temper and appropriate Layer, of the Natures and kindes of Marle and Compoſt, of Ground-Plots, and Edifices.
            
            
               The ſecond Section.
               Sheweth the Situation, Reſidence and lying of Grounds ſuiting their ſeuerall Tempers, their Boundage and Neighbourage, with markeable obſeruations ariſing from the ſame; the Meaſuring, Calculation, Plotting and Proiection of Lines, Figures, Bodies, Buildings, the Tricking of Plots and Maps with Colours, Characters, Charts, and other Complements.
            
            
               The third Section.
               Intimateth the Natures and Proprieties of Poſſeſſions, Tenures, Seruices, Titles, Rights, Fees, Immunities, Diſcents, and other Incidents.
            
            
               The fourth Section.
               Demonſtrateth how Lands and Poſſeſſions are valueable in reſpect of their ſeuerall Iſſues, Rents, Perquiſites, Priuiledges and other Accrewments, and Reuenueables, duely regarding their Repriſes.
               The Marſhalling and digeſting of the whole Suruey, contriuing of Field-Entries in Rough-books, Engroſſing of the Exemplificatiōs, the Surueying and abbreuiating of Deedes, Compoſing of Terrars, Rentals, Particulars, &amp;c.
            
         
         
            
            
               ❧To the Right Honourable and moſt Noble Lord, WILLIAM Lord Compton, Baron of Compton, Neſtors yeeres, with the felicitie of both Worldes.
            
               TO deriue my inducements (Right Honourable) of Dedicating theſe ſhallow Deſeignes vnto a Mecaenas of ſuch Supereminence, from Preſidents of worthy witts and particular Obligees to eminent Patrons, my Fortunes haue not ſo auſpiciouſly endeared me their happy Fauourite. But the Vniuerſall concurrence of good Hearts with hearty zeale (from the Verge of a vaſte extent) in the Center of true affectionated praiſe of your worth, and prayers for your weale, hath haſted &amp; haled-on the whole Current of my affections to runne with the Generall Concurſe of vnfained welwillers, to congratulate your Lordſhips hopefull and happie Conſolidations: For ſuch and ſo manifold are thoſe worthy Attributes of accompliſhed Amplitude and magnified Merits dimayning from the ſacred Source of true Nobility, that they haue euen winged my feruent Deſires, (more animated with ſelf-approument of deuote ſinceritie then amazed with myrrors of Magnificence) to the conſecrating of theſe my preſt Deſeignemēts to your Honourable Patrocinie. But if ſuch Motiues bee incompetent to giue due Colour of excuſe to Intruſions ſo exorbitant, I beſeech

your Lordſhip giue me leaue to flee to the proſtrate Plea of praying your gracious Indulgence for my rude Preſume in daring from the remote Nadir of obſcurity, to eleuate the flaggie Wing of ſo weake a Pineon towards the Zenith of Perfection, the mark and Pitch for Skie-towring Faulcons, whoſe Quills imped with ſtrong Sarcells of the Grace of Greatnes, are inliſened and inhabled to tranſcende and climbe-aboue the miſtie Vapours that cloude and Eclipſe all Flights which peirce not to the Welkin of the Worthies. For who ſees not that Heroes (Gods Vice-gerents) can dignifie euen the inglorious Groome, &amp; giue ſuch Gloſſe, and Tincture to home-made Statuaes, as ſhal attract the Eye of wonder to magnifie the potent Artiſts for refining &amp; remoulding their (now) new creatures, as well as with the Touch-ſtone of refined knowledge detrud &amp; baniſh all Deſeignes, disfurniſht of true &amp; due ſelf-worth, from the Confines of high Repute? But leaſt in labouring, with invulgar Ingredients, to palate an ill ſeaſoned Seruice, I ſhould by tedious and vnreliſhed Tearmes, impart a worſe diſtaſte, I will ſcrew-vp this Key with the proſtrate ſacring of my ſelfe and my poore Endeauours at the Shrine of your gracious Clemencie. And ſo euer wiſhing vnto your Honour the happie fruition of vnconfined Felicity. I reſt, now and euer,
            
               
                  London at the White Hart in Cheape-ſide,
                  Iunij. 6. 1610.
                  
               
               
                  Your Lordſhips humbly deuoted. W. Folkingham.
            
         
         
            
            To the Beneuolent and iudicious READER.
            
            
               SHould I inſiſt vpon tedious Appologies for due approuement of the Faculty of Surueying impugned by the vulgar and ſhallow Diſputes of refractorie Oppoſites, which abſurdly transferring their hard Imputations againſt it, from the faulty and defectiue Abuſe, to the iuſt and lawfull Vſe of the ſame, doe moſt iniuriouſly, and vniuſtly traduce and ſcandalize this vnblameable Arte &amp; all her Agents, 'tis hazard but I ſhould heare of Mindaes Cynical Memento, if I incurred no harder a Cenſure. It is a World to ſee the ſottiſh preſſures vrged againſt the admeaſuring of land, yet the Vſe of Ponderous and Concaue Meaſures (both Dry and Liquid) are no leſſe commendable than Common in venting of Wares and Merchandize, and what greater iniquity in the vſing admeaſurements in Grounds than in Graine? Cloath and Stuffes were retailed by the yard, when a ſumptuous Potentate might be hoſed for 3 ſhillings, which now will ſcarce hoſe a frugall Peaſant. Bilanx est arbiter aequus; the Hand may faile in certaintie of Poize, and the Eye in Randon ſans Rule, but the Beame and Chaine balke no Truthes, nor blaunch Vn-truthes; the Empirick or the Methodiſt, which is the better Phiſician? Take away Number, Weight, Meaſure, you exile Iuſtice, and reduce and haile-vp from Hell the olde and odious Chaos of Confuſion. Priuate Intelligencers, intimating (by their roaued Aymes at Quantities and Qualities) vnder-hand and ſiniſter informations, abuſe the Leſſor &amp; wrong the Leſſee, where the iuſt and iudicious Feudigrapher (who aymes at competent Improuements ſans preſſure of the Feudatarie, or oppreſſure of the Fermor) duly and diſcreetly obſeruing all particulars incident to the Plot, certifies a true Relation, by the Leuel-draught of whoſe impartiall Parallels, may be produced that Meane in Rating of Eſtimates, which the due Port of men of Place and Eminence (no way ſupportable (Rebus ſic ſtantibus) with Reuenewes of former Ages) doth moſt iuſtly challenge. What ſhould I ſpeake of ſcanted Eſtimates of Acres exacted from ouer-awed Tenants, or rated

by poſitiue Will? of the Ouertures of ſcandall raiſed againſt Surueyors by the Owners concealing of failing Contents, or vouching of Validities and Extents aboue the Feudigraphia impoſturà fit Pſeudographia. Record? of letting by Port-ſaile aduanced by prepared out-bidding Competitors? of parcelling forth engroſſed lands to Vnder-tenants at intollerable Termes? of Riot, Pride, Plenty of People &amp; Coyne (though confined to a few Cofers) with high-enhaunced Rates of all Commodities? who is ſo Owle-eyed that ſees not, that the extending of Rents doth neceſſarily dimaine from theſe and the like cauſes? Yet Tenancies (I cannot gaine-ſay) are too oft tendered to too-Racking Valuations, the Reciprocall Regard (in ſome) is Choyſe to take by Racke, or leaue a Packe, and it is ſo ordinary with too many Land-lords (like abſolute Lords and Allodiſts of their Lands (within the Verge at leaſt) á ſuperis ad inferos) Fundum hastae ſubijcere, the frequencie of the practize growes familiar. And for Feudataries, who ſees not how much they faile of true agnizing their due dependance vpon Meſne Lords,Dwarenus. ſith Feudum (comprehending Fealty (at leaſt) which obliges Per ſacramentū ſub pena foris facturae Feodi) is Res Clientelaris, &amp; neuer deuolues to the Succeſſor ſans original Burthens impoſed by him which had Nouel Fee, howſoeuer they now ſlight their Lords and amoundre their Obligence. Sed haec parerga; and to Rectifie ſuch irregularities, the Field requires a better Champion, in the meane time let euery one for his owne particular propoſe vnto himſelfe the entertainment of a good conſcience. For this Tractate, I am not ſo arrogant to magnifie, nor ſo vnnatural to vilifie my own iſſue, though I could retriue Centuries of Defects, but leaue it to thy fauourable Cenſure, crauing (withall) thy courteous tolleration of my new-coyning of ſome Words, with the Reuiuing of the obſolete and Endenizing of Forraine, ſith without ſuch priuiledge, an indigeſted Chaos of Principles and Concluſions cannot (ex nouo &amp; ex facili) be conciſely contriued into a Methodicall Arte. For any vaine-glorious Geodetor, which makes baſe Detraction the Trumpet to rumour, and emblaſon his ſelfe-boaſted perfections, ſo with facility to purchaſe (or rather fore-ſtall) the Palme of Repute,

               Ore &amp; Dente petat, &amp; naſo ſuspenſo huiuſmodi effundat Scommata:
               
                  
                     Quam lepidè lexeis compostae vt teſſerulae, omnes
                  
                  
                     Arte pauimento at
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         Emblemate vermiculato?
                  
                  What curious-quaint Emelliſhments diffuſe?
                  Muſaick-Mazes-Marquetrizing Muſe?
               
            
            
               Suſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   de
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   fero; who can be ſecured from baſe carping Blatancie? But wherevnto tendes this preciſe particularizing of Plots, Layers, Pregnances, Productions, &amp;c. when an Arte-leſſe Agent can (by famed Name, and abſolute power to diſpoſe) with the bare vouch of the generall goodneſſe of the Ground (ſans ground of Reaſon or Poſſibility) haile on the poore Peſant to Farme and Fine according to the braue boaſt of his roauing Eſteemes &amp; abſurd Oſtentations, which he daignes not (nor dare they vrge) by any rationall inſtances to make probable? I ayme not at the Racke nor the Slack, the qualified Meane is the Maine of my Marke; and to extunde and beat-out this true Proportion, I obſerue the Circumſtances proiected: let peremptorie Agents balke inſtance, barre Reply, and Racke ſans Rule and Reaſon, it behoues an honeſt and faithfull Feudigrapher, by infallible Principles &amp; warrantable Demonſtrations, to approue himſelfe, an intelligent and diligent-Improuer, not a ſenſeleſſe and arrogant Impoſtor; and what warrant more current than Knowledge founded vpon the induſtrious ſearch and ſerious obſeruations intimated (or rather glaunced at) in this Epitome? But leaſt too large Gates ſhould promiſe a faire Plat-forme of a ſpatious Towne, hauing thus borrowed leaue to wade into the ſhallow Foordes of the Faculty, I will leaue the Profundities to be ſounded with a Plumbe-line of more Poize and Fadomes.
            
               
                  Helpringham neere to Folkingham the
                  
                     ſecond of Februarie, 1609.
               
               Velle pro Poſſe. Thine W. F.
            
         
         
            
            The Author to his Feudigraphia.
            WHen thus I had (by peice-meale paines) compilde
            Of diuers Elements thy ſlender Bulkes,
            I deem'de to haue (too ominouſly) ſtylde
            Thy Name ſo neere the Pheud of Border-Hulkes,
            That thy abortiue Limbes I rather choſe
            In cloſe concealement from this captious Age
            To ſmoother ay, than raſhly thus t'expoſe
            To Pheudiſts Theonine thy Puſilage;
            But a great Monarch hath thoſe dire Combines
            Hatcht in the Heart by Sauage Enion,
            
            Calm'de with a Fame that happily Confines
            All Oppoſites, to ſacred Vnion:
            So wert thou Patroniz'de by Celſitude,
            The Cryticke-Coale ſhould not thy Browes ybrand
            For Dis-analogies ſtrange, ſtrained, rude,
            Nor Deviations curious-ill-ſcande;
            Gaine then, O gaine (in Lieu of ſelfe demerit)
            By heart-free Tender with true zeale repleate,
            His grac'de Aſpect, who truely doth inherit.
            A ſplendid Fame for worthynes Compleate,
            To daigne the Patronage I (humble) craue
            Of Worthy Comptons Noble Family,
            Whoſe iuſtly-honourd Names Shield from Depraue,
            Couch rabid Blatants, ſilence Surquedry:
            Then Carping Momus wilbe euer-mute,
            And rather Burſt with Spleene, than vent his Gall,
            The Mainger-Curre nil bawle (how-euer brute)
            But crouching fawne, or leering voide the Stall;
            Such Grace dimaines from ſacred Eminence
            Ay to ſuppreſſe inſulting Inſolence.
            
               Et habent ſua Fata Libelli.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE SYNOPSIS OR EPITOME OF SVRVEY METHODIZED.
            SECTION .I.
            
               Of the Materials of Poſſeſſions, the ſeuerall kinds of Earths, Waters, Stones, Minerals: the Cruſts and increaſe of Grounds, the peculiar ordering, mastering, manuring and imploying of ſeuerall Soyles, the due beſtowing of Graine, Herbs, Plants; with the diuerſitie of Ground-plots and Edifices.
            
            
               CHAP. I.
               
                  SVruey in generall is an Art wherby the view and trutinate intimation of a ſubiect, from Center to Circumference is rectified.
               The Suruey of Poſſeſſions (the ſubiect of this Treatiſe) is the Arte by which their Graphicall Deſcription is particularized.
               
                  This Suruey is Symbolized and diſtinguiſhed into Actiue and Paſſiue.
               
                  Actiue.The Actiue may be referred to the Feudigrapher, and conſiſts in Operation and Eſtimation.
               The Operation is Mathematicall and Mechanicall.
               
                  Mathematicall.Mathematicall Operation is a part of Suruey by which the dimenſions of the Plots propounded are performed.
               
                  Mechanical.Mechanicall Operation is the Manuall acting and proiecting of the workes.
               The Eſtimation of Poſſeſſions is Materiall &amp; Legall.
               
                  Materiall.The Materiall part is conuerſant in Eſtimating the valuations incident to the ſubiect, by relation to the Materials, and Elementarie parts of the Plot.
               
                  Legall.The Legall part preſcribes Methodicall &amp; Iuridiciall confines to the whole courſe of Suruey: and comprehends the Symboliographie or Clarke-ſhip, and penning of the Suruey with the Rectifying of Euidences and Records.
               The ſeuerall functions of theſe partes are diffuſed thorough the whole Proceſſe enſuing.
               And ſo much for the Actiue part.
            
            
               CHAP. II.
               
                  Paſſiue.The Paſſiue part of Suruey, hath reference to Poſſeſſions, as they conſiſt of parts Eſſentiall and Accidentall.
               
                  Eſſentiall.The Eſſentiall partes comprehend the matter and forme coincident to Poſſeſſions.
               
                  Matter.The Matter compriſes the Elementarie compoſition and conſtitution of Poſſeſſions: and in diſcuſſure thereof, the Materiall parte is moſt conuerſant.
               The Matter is either Naturall, whoſe ſtate hath admitted of no ſubſtantiall alteration, other then the hand

of Nature hath impreſſed therein: or Artificiall, tranſformed and chaunged from the Natiue and Originall Habite by humane induſtrie.
               Naturall matter may bee diuided into Appropriate and Communicate.Naturall.
               
               Appropriate is that which is peculiar and proper to ſome certaine perſon, place, or other particular limitation; and hath reference here to Earth and Water.
               In the Earth the Qualitie and Compoſure thereof are to be conſidered.Earth.
               
               In the firſt the Species and Habitude require to bee iudiciouſly obſerued.
               The Species of the Earth is either Vulgar or Pretious.Species.
               
               The Vulgar is either Simple, as Clay, Moulde,Vulgar. Moore, Grauell, Sande: Or Commixt; as Creachie, Claulkie, Clayie, Sandie Earth.
               Pretious Earth is that which conſiſts of a middle Nature twixt Stones and Mettals;Pretious. and all ſorts thereof are Friable and conuertible to Powder: And theſe are either Liquable or Not-Meltable.Liquable.
               
               The firſt are Iuices Concrete; as Salt, Alume, Bitumen, Vitrioll.
               Salt (Naturall) is found either in the Earth or Water. Of the firſt kind is Salt Armoniake, Sal-gem,Salt. Sal-niter, and Indian Salt.
               The other ſort is digged vp in Fountaines, Riuers, Waſhes, Salt-Meeres, Sea-ſhoares.
               Alume is either white or blacke,Alume. The firſt (and beſt) is either Liquid or Compact.
               Liquid Alume is the ſoft, fat and limpid Roch (or Red) Alume.
               The Compact is ether Sugar like, or Shiuering.
               The blacke is a kinde of Alume wherewith gold is purged and purified.
               Bitumen is either hard, as Aſphaltus, Piſſaſphaltus,Bitumen.
                  
Roſin; Or Liquid, as Naphta, Petroleum, Amber, Vitriol, Coppras.
               
                  Not-meltable.The Pretious Earths, which are not Meltable, nor indurated into Stones nor Mettals, are Stibium, Azure, Auripigmentum or Arſenicke, Sandaracha, Calx, Playſter, Chaulke, Coale, Canole, Marle, Oker, Terra-ſigillata, or Lemnia, Armenia, Germanica, &amp;c. Tuckers or Fullers Earth, Argilla or clay for Pots, Gallie and Thacke Tiles, Bricke, Water and Tabacco Pipes, Purſlaine.
               And thus much for the Species.
            
            
               CHAP. III.
               
                  Habitude.THe Habitude of the Earth dependes vpon the inherent diſpoſition and temperature of the ſame in Heate, Colde, Moiſture and Drineſſe. For although in regarde of the Colde and Drie ſubſtance and Nature, whereof the Earth generally conſiſts, it may be ſaide to be of one temperature; yet vppon occaſion of the diuerſitie of Situations, Affinitie, Intercourſe and participation it hath with things of repugnant qualitie, it purchaſeth and acquireth contrarie qualities.
               And therefore it would be alſo perueſtigated, whether it be light,, looſe, ſofte, fatt, oylie, ſlipperie, mouldring, cleauing, tough, ſtiffe, moorie, leane, barren, fertile, water-ſwallowed, ſoale bound, conſtipated, or what other due or vndue poize nad proportion of temper predominates.
               
                  Compoſure.The Compoſure of the Earth compriſes the Baſe and vpper Cruſt of the ſame.
               
                  Baſe. Pregnance.The Baſe of the Earth offers due obſeruation to perueſtigate the Pregnance wherewith the Earth is imbowelled, whether it bee Prime; as in the precedent

Species; or Concrete, as in Quarries and Mines.
               In the firſt diſcouer, what Ragge, Freeſtone,Quarries. Milſtone, Grind-ſtone, Syth-ſtone, Emeril-ſtones, Sanguinin-ſtones, Hones, Tutch, Ieate, Slude, Slate: What Marbles, as Alablaſters, Ophites, Porphyris, &amp;c. Alſo what Gemmes, as harde Adamants, viz. the Cenchros, Macedonicke, Cypricke, Siderite: the flammid Carbuncle, purple Amethiſt, greene Emeraulde, and Opall Paderas, with their Trineuned luſter: the vyolet Hyacinth, Skie-coloured Saphire, Luſtrie Diamonde, ſhining Topaz, ſtarrie Calchedonie, ſparkling Rubie, golden Chryſolite, ſplendid Aſterite, various Achate, horny Corneol, greene Iaſper, pellucid Onyx, cerule Tarqueis, candid Cryſtall, harde Blood-ſtone, attracting Loade-ſtone, white yellow and Falerne Agate.
               For the ſecond note, what Mettals or Minerals,Mines. are therein generated? whether Pure as Golde, Siluer; or impure as Leade, Tinne, Braſſe, Iron, Steele, Lattin, Copper, Coperas, Quickſiluer, Stibium, Antimonie, Chryſocolla or Boras, Minium or Vermilon naturall, Sandaracha, Verdigreece, Salt, Allome, Brimſtone.
               Alſo Coale, Canole, Colours amongſt the Minerall Oare of Gold and Siluer, as Sil, Azure.
               The vpper Cruſt is the Soile or Seale of the Earth through which the irradiation of the Sun penetrating,Cruſt. corroborates &amp; cheeres vp the Natiue heate with temperate calefaction, which together with the infuſion of moderate ſhowers and moiſtures, ſoaked from ſoilings enlifens the radicall humour, and doth ſo foment and ferment the whole Maſſe of Moulde, that Dame Veſta is inuited and extimulated to inueſt her ſelfe in her richeſt Roabes of painted brauerie, and to produce and power foorth her Cornu-copia of ſelected plenties.
               
                  
                  The Craſſitude.The Craſſitude of the Soale, is diuerſified in ſeuerall Plots, and particular Modulets, as from 3. foote, to ½ foote more or leſſe, and is diſtinguiſhable from the Baſe by compacture, by qualitie, by colour, by extention of the roots and fibers of graſſe, herbes, plants. And vpon this Craſſitude of the Cruſt, together with the Qualitie and Habitude of the ſame, doth the production principally depend (although the eſtate of the Baſe (by reaſon of the imparture of the innate facultie) be not vtterly excluded all importance of fertilitie) and offers due obſeruation, what Trees, Plants, Shrubs, Graine, Graſſe, Herbes, Weeds, Moſſe, and other Vegitables are in each Plot voluntarily or plentifully produced.
               
                  Inueſture.And hence dimaines the Inueſture of the earth, which giues conſideration of the Grouth &amp; Repletion of productions, both Vegetant and Animall.
               
                  GrouthIn Grouth, the thriuage, verdure, fruitage, prematurance &amp;c. of particular Vegetables are regardable; as the boaling, ſpreading, arming, timbring &amp; tapering of trees, braunching and bearing of Plants, Buſhing of Shrubs, prolation and ſeedage of roots and herbs, depth and colour of graſſe, &amp;c. For thereby (ſans further ſearch) the Species and Habitude of the ground, wherein they grow, are ingeniouſly intimated.
               
                  Soils known by their productions.For if they proſper and thriue in burgening, ſappines, flowers, fruit and the like, according to their ſeuerall kinds, in extraordinarie good proportion, it implies that either the ground is very fertile in generall, or that they are implanted in Plots Sympathizing with their Natures.
               As the high timbring Oake dilating mightie armes in large extent, denotates a rich and battle ſoile; where on the contrarie, the knurly, crooked and crabbed harde ſparing ſtarueling, bewraies his barren and hungrie bedde.
               The large and looſe grained timber of the red Oake

and fruſſhie Aſh ſhowes a light, moiſt, rich &amp; déepe ſoile: the like doth the largeneſſe and wateriſhneſſe of rootes and fruit.
               But the firme and ſolid graine of the white Oake and tough Aſh, ſignifies a more faſt and cloſe ground. ½
               High grounds produce wood of a more beautifull-featherd and better graine, than the low, except in Apple trees and Peare trées.
               Reſt-harrowes growing rancke and rooting farre abroad, intimate a fat, fruitfull, and long laſting ſoile.
               The lowe ſtubbed Heath, argues a barren grauellie cold ground, the rancke and high ſhowes it to be a more warme and tillable; and commonly the white flowred Heath hath better layer, than the purple.
               Diuels-bit, Eye-bright and yarrow by plentie in repletion, and mean in proportion, point foorth a Sandy earth, of moderate heat and moiſture, and a ſweet ſhallow and wel-ſwoorded Cruſt: and thus are theſe herbes frequent in the Iriſh Soile.
               Grounſwell, Thiſtles, Nettles, and other wéedes by their rankeneſſe ſhow a rich tilth.
               Blackiſh, miſliking and vnkinde herbes ſhow a leane hungrie and bitter, or ſowre ground.
               Burnt &amp; ſcorched herbes, and harſh, reddiſh, blewiſh ſpirie and prie-graſſe bewray a cold, vnkind, rough, ſtarued and baked, or ſoaked ſoile.
               Baſe herbes, and rough ſandy ſtone, denotate a leane greety ſandie or grauelly ground, according to the Poet:

                     Nam Ieiuna quidem cliuoſi glarea ruris
                     Vix humiles apibus caſias rorem
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         miniſtrat,
                     Et tophus ſcaber &amp;c.
                  
               
               Iuniper demonſtrates a chalky, drie and meane ſeat.
               The knagged Moſſe mattes and cloathes the barrenneſt Mountaines with horned ſhoots, but promiſes that the Minerals of Iron, Leade, Tinne and Coale, ſhall Counteruaile the infertiltie of Soile with the rich Ballaſte

enwombing the intrals of his ſpacious Baſe.
               And thus much for the obſeruations to bee collected from the grouth of Vegetables.
            
            
               CHAP. IIII.
               
                  Animalia.THe qualitie of the Soile is alſo not obſcurely intimated by conſideration of the breedage of the Animals therein produced: for it is commonly ſeene that Cattle, Fowle, Fiſh, and other liuing Creatures doe differ and varie in colour, Bone, proportion and other peculiar attributes according to their places of Breede.
               The large limbed Neate, Horſe and Sheepe betoken that they had their breeding in fat and rich ſoiles. But the ſmall and ſound Sheepe, cleane limbed Horſe and Beaſt of meane bigneſſe bewraies a harde Country and ſhallow Cruſt.
               In Ireland, where the ſoile is not déepely rancke, but moderately fertile, both in tillage and forrage, their Cattle and all other liuing Creatures (Men &amp; Greyhounds onely excepted) are of a meane and middle ſtature and proportion, ſuitable to the ſoilage.
               Yet the Shéepe of Cotſwolde (quamuis ſitus ſit &amp; collinus &amp; gracilis) are of great bone, large Necks and ſquare Bulkes.
               But according to the Nature of the Countries, diuers Animals are famouſed for peculier parts: ſo Virgil ſaith.
               
                  —Viroſa
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Pontus
                  Caſtorea, Eliadum palmas Epeiros equarum;
                  Continuo has leges aeterna
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      foedera certis
                  Impoſuit Natura locis &amp;c.
               
               So wee haue the Ripon Colt, Northerne Bilder, Scotch &amp; Welch Nags, Iriſh Hobbie, Spaniſh Iennet.
               
                  The Engliſh and Frizeland Stéedes, Barbarian-Courſers, Cappadocian Hunters.
               The Sicilian Horſe is praiſed for ſwiftneſſe as are alſo the bréede of Libia and Siculia, the Moorian for valour and courage, the Dutch Mare is in requeſt for the Caroach, and Theſſalonian Mares for battell.
               The Parthian Horſe is famed for nimbleneſſe and dexteritie in running: The Median is excéeding faire and great: the Sardinian faire and nimble: the Miſſeean is goodly, ſhapie, eaſie and ſubmiſſiue.
               The Marſh and Holland Oxe is preferred for draught, the Lancaſhire and Darbyſhire for tallow, hide and horne, and theſe are ſhort legged, of ſquare bulke and black haire, the other are tall, and (for the moſt part) party-coloured.
               The Methol Rabbet is famed for fatneſſe and fleſhineſſe: the Cotſwould weather for large body, déepe, fine, white, and ſoft fléece: Norffolke Mutton for ſwéetneſſe, but Lemſter Ore merits the preheminence (though it be ſhort) for a purely-fine, ſoft and criſped Staple.
               The Goates of Angori are hung with ſhag ground-déepe, but thoſe of Morroco haue their haire of ordinary length and refined ſmallnes.
               Engliſh For bignes, ſtrength, and fierceneſſe. Maſtiffes, Gaſe Hounds (or Lurchers) and Tūblers, are in ſpecial requeſt: ſo Weſtphalian Bacon.
               Ruſſia bréeds white Beares and blacke Foxes, and Iſland white Partridges, Pheſants, Faulcons, and Hares. Pegu carries the Palme for Parrets, &amp; Muſke-Cats, and Ceiland (nigh Calicut) for Elephants.
               The Vandall Trout is held in high eſtéeme, and wée approoue Wytham and Ancam, this for Eeles, and that for Pikes, Engliſh Pikes, and Oyſters.
               So the Barbarie and Pembrokeſhire Faulcons, and Tercell-gentles, Iſland Ierfalcon and Ierkin, Iriſh Merline, Gooſe-hawlke, and Cocke of the wood, Engliſh Hobbie, and Sparrow-hawlkes.
               
                  And in regard of ſuch diuerſities coincident to many creatures, by reaſon of their Countreys of bréede, it is remarkeable to obſerue the ſeuerall particulars peculiar vnto them: as in Horſes their ſtature, courage, cleanneſſe of limbes, ſoundneſſe and ſeruiceableneſſe; in ſhéep their bulke, depth and puritie of Staple; in Neat their bone, hide, and haire, in Rabbets their furre and fatneſſe: and the like of other things according to their kind.
               And thus much of earth appropriate.
            
            
               CHAP. V.
               WAter Appropriate is either Commorant, viz. confined within the plot.Waters. Or Current, not terminated within the limits thereof.
               
                  Comorant. Stagnant.The firſt is either Stagnant, as ſtanding Pooles, Ponds, Lakes, Loughes, Méeres: Or ſtillant, viz: Springing or burſting forth of the bowels of the earth, as Wels, Fountaines, Bathes, &amp;c.
               
                  Fluent. Current.The ſecond is either Fluent, as Rils, Brookes, Riuers, ſpringing, and appearing with their firſt ſource within the bounds of the Plot:Influent. Or Influent, viz: dimayning from elſewhere, and flowing or paſſing by or through the precincts and confines of the Plot. And to this place may alſo bee referred all ſwéeping or floating Waters, which flit and fléete to and fro with wind-catches,Floating. ſuch as bee the Waters falling &amp; deſcending from Vplandiſh countreys by land-floods ſurrounding Fens, and other Flats.
               And both theſe ſorts of Current Waters, though they paſſe thorow, and beyond both the plot and Priuiledge of the ſame, yet ſo farre forth as they may be preſcribed and intituled to the bounds or liberties thereof, they are thereunto appropriate. So much for Matter Appropriate: Communicate followes.
            
            
               
               CHAP VI.
               COmmunicate Matter is that which is participable to the Plot together with other Places,Matter cō
                     municate. and may bee referred to Water Tranſient and to the Climate.
               Waters Tranſient are Riuers, Brookes,Waters Tranſient. Flouds (whence ſo euer dimayning) which paſſing beyond the extention and priuiledge of the Plot are communicably imparted to it, and to ſome other.
               The Climate may alſo not improperly bee admitted as Communicate,Climate. in regard it may be ſaid to bee the ſame (and in ſome ſort not immateriall, by reaſon of the inſeperabilitie thereof) ſans manifeſt change, in a greater circuit then the limits of one Lordſhip, or an ordinarie Plot, doe vſually extend vnto, yet in the Suruey of whole Continents and vaſt Countries the Climate is not excluded from Appropriates:Latitude. But howſoeuer you diſtinguiſh, it is not impertinent perticularly to be penned downe, viz: in what degrée of longitude and latitude the Plot is ſituate, and alſo in what Ayre, as Pellucid, milde, ſubtill, cleare, ſwéet, perſant, ſoone hot and colde, healthfull: Or groſſe, cloſe, foggie, ſharpe,Aire. fenny, vaporous, vnholeſome: in what proportion of heat, colde, moiſture, drineſſe: what windes, ſtormes, guſts, are moſt remarkeable: what ordinarie effects and accidents, are vſually obſerued to enſue, and ſuccéede vpon immoderate fals of wet, or long continuance of drowth: And what Diſeaſes as Catarrhes, Feuers-Fluxes, &amp;c. are moſt frequent and common. And the like for Cattell.
               And beſides theſe and the former obſeruations &amp; diſtinctions,Nature of Waters. there is a peculiar intimation to be made of the nature and goodneſſe of Waters.
               
                  Clay-waters are ſwéet, thick, fat, and potable, requiring the leaſt proportion of Malt for Brewing.
               Waters which haue a ſtony and grittie Current, doe by ſtrayning thorough the ſame become cooler, pure, ſwéet, holeſome, and light of diſgeſture.
               Springs dimayning from thicke ſand, and ſlender grauell, quickly gather mudde, and they are not durable, pibbles and groſſe grauell affoord good and pleaſant waters, were they of continuance.
               The Marle grauell, ſtonie ſand, and redde ſtones produce beſt Waters.
               The red ſtones with Plinie carry chiefe preheminence for euerlaſting Springs, and water, coole and ſimply the beſt.
               But the particular notifying of the Natures of ordinarie Waters, may bee with facilitie effected by the exact knowledge of the peculiar attributes, and properties of good Water.
               
                  Cogniſance of good Water.The beſt Waters are thoſe that deriue their Sources, and Originals from Rockes, or ſtonie Fountaines irradiated with the Orient-Sunne, ſliding in channels of hard and compact grauell or ſand, repleat with redde ſtones, or blacke and burnt carbuncle ſtones, of limpid cléereneſſe, light in poize and diſgeſtion, quicke in conuerſion of heat and coldneſſe, cooler in Summer then in Winter, ſans taſte, ſmell, and colour, yet readily taking tinctures and qualities infuſed, leauing no diſcoloured ſpots by ſtanding ſimple in a cleane veſſell, nor excrements by decoction, by imparting neat and pure complexions, ſound breaſts, and cléere voices to the natiue Inhabitants.
               
                  Aquae Calidae.Beſides theſe ordinary waters, there be Aquae Calidae, other waters indued with medicinable qualities acquired by vertue of ſome Minerall, from whence they dimaine: as Bathes, Wels, Fountaines, ſpringing from Mines of Nitre, Sulphure, Allome, Bitumen, &amp;c.
               
                  There be alſo Waters both vpon the Coaſt and within the land (as at the Namptwich, &amp;c,) of ſo brackiſh a Brynage, that they wil be conuerted to Salt by boyling.Brynage.
               
               Other waters tho they be not conuertable in approued meaſure and goodnes to Salt, yet they haue vertue to augment and refine ſalt which is boyled in them: ſo the Zéelanders boyle Spaniſh ſalt in Sea-water, to the increaſe of 45. in the hundred, that of Portingale 35, and that of Brouage 25.
               Some Fountaines creame with a liquid Bitumen, like to the lake Aſphaltus, as at Pitchford in the Countie of Salop.
               Now for Repletion,Repletion. it intimates howe and wherewith the Plot is fraught, ſtored and repleniſhed both with Vegetants, and Animals: viz.
               
               For woods, how peruiable, how penetrable, how enterlaced, as Timber with Tinſell, Coppice, or vnderwood: what Trées, Plants, Shrubs: what Fruitage, Maſtage, Gummage: what Hawlkes, Fowle, Venery, &amp;c. are therein found and produced.
               For Paſture, and Meadow; how and with what Herbage the Cruſt or Sword is matted, mantled and ſwarthed: what decrement by Moſſe, Wéedes, Water, Stones, &amp;c.
               So in Waters, the kinds, goodneſſe, and ſtore of Fiſh, and Fowle, both peculiar and common, would bee recorded.
               And thus much may ſuffice for the Naturall Matter; It followeth to entreat of the Artificiall.
            
            
               CAP. VII.
               THe matter may alſo be ſaid to be Artificiall,Matter Artificiall. in reſpect of labour and induſtrie conferred vpon or about the Subiect and Adiunct of the Plot.
               
                  Theſe incidents to the Subiect are comprehended vnder Tillage, and ground Plots.
               
                  Tillage.Tillage generally taken may comprehend all maner of husbandings of grounds, but it is heere limited to Vertilage and Fertilage.
               
                  Vertilage.Vertilage conſiſts in Deluage and Fictilage.
               
                  Deluage.Deluage is applyed about preparing, and putrifying of the Earth by ſtirring, toſſing and turning of the ſame, according to the Poet.
               
                  Et cui putre ſolum, nam
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      hoc imitamur arando: viz. Vt arando ſolum ſit putre: Ne
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      enim (inquit Columella) aliud eſt colere quam ſoluere &amp; fermentare terram.
               
               And this Deluage is diſtinguiſhable into Caruage and Scaphage.
               
                  Caruage.Caruage comprehends all ſorts of plowing of Grounds, as well ordinarie, viz. for Graine, Hempe, Line, &amp;c. As Extraordinarie, viz. for Woods, Woade, Dyers-wéede, Rapes, Cole, Saffron, Mill, Millet, Panick,Scaphiage. Amilcorne, Spelt-corn, Garences, Dewgraſſe, Iobs-teares, Comin-ſéede, Anniſe-ſéede, Worme-ſéede, Cotton-ſéede, Canarie-ſéede, &amp;c.
               Scaphage is the digging, deluing, and preparing of the Soile with Spades or other handie-tooles for the ſowing, ſetting, planting, and propagating of Séedes, Hearbs, Plants, Trées, &amp;c. and is moſt conuerſant in Gardens, Hort-yards, Hop-yards, Vine-yards.
               And here it is expedient to animaduert what choice, ſelected, and endenized Hearbes, Plants, Fruits and Phiſicall Simples be implanted &amp; beſtowed, with their Growth, Repletion, Fruitage, Fecunditie, with Contriuage both of Plots and Plants.
               
                  Fictilage.Fictilage is the forming &amp; tranſforming of ye Matter in form or ſubſtance; as in making of Tile (for thack, roofe, creſt, gutter, pauing) Brick, Pots, Tabaccopipes, Tōnel or Conduit-pipes, Glaſſe, Purſlane, and other Plaſmature. If therefore the Plot doe affoord any Earth or

Clay, which may be accommodated to ſuch purpoſes, it behooues to record the ſame.
            
            
               CHAP. VIII.
               FErtilage conſiſts in the enriching of the Soyle,Fertilage. and the Rectifying of the Production. And in purſuite of this practiſe, diligent conſideration muſt be had of the variation of the Plot, from the due Habitude of a rich and battle ground; to the like and equall condition, whereof, it muſt be endeuoured by appropriate meanes to reduce the ſame, or at leaſt to correct and qualifie the vndue Habitude in the eminenteſt exorbitance.
               And it ſhall not bee amiſſe to particularize the Natures and qualities both of good and badde ſoyles, to the end their diſtinctions may be facilized.
               The Nature and goodneſſe of ground is diuers waies be-tout and manifeſted; as by the mixture, temperature,The Nature of grounds how known. colour, compacture, touch, weight, taſte, ſmell, &amp;c. together with the voluntarie Production and Repletion of the Plot.
               Such a diffuſed mixture of Clay and Sande,Mixture. moyſture and dryeth, heat and cold as confounds their diſtinctions of deriuing appellation, from the eminent predominance of any particular qualitie inherent in the ſoyle, carries a generall approouement of goodneſſe.
               
                  Virgill infers the beſt layer for Tillage to be an Earth which is blackiſh and darke, not too compact,Blacke. of a déepe cruſt, viz. fat vnder the ſhare, though it goe a déep pitch, well putrified and reſolued, &amp;c.

                     Nigra fere &amp; preſſo pinguis ſub vomere terra
                     Optima frumentis &amp;c.
                  
               
               And Mancinellus ſaith, it muſt bee neither moyſt nor drie, waxing black after the plow, eaſie to be tilled, and where Rooks runne fluttering after the ſhare at the verie

héeles of the holder, and that not of ranke, but moderate fruitfulneſſe, with which the deprecation of the Poet, doth not vnfitly concurre, where he ſhewes that moiſt layers, are knowne by ranke and aboundant graſſe.
               
                  Humida maiores herbas alit, ipſa
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      iuſto
                  Laetior: ah nimium ne ſit mihi fertilis illa,
                  Neu ſe praeualidam primis oſtentat ariſtis.
               
               But notwithſtanding the preheminence giuen to the blacke and darke colour,Red. ſome are induced to preferre the red layer, and ſo much the rather for that Adam (who was immediatly created of Earth) importeth Earth of a redde or ruddy colour: And experience alſo giues inſtance of diuers ſuch ſoyles (though not ſo frequent to confirme euerie man in the ſame opinion) of wondrous worth and fertilitie, amongſt which the Territories of the Towne of Armagh in Ireland, are famouſed for laſting and perpetuall battlenes, as hauing time out of minde, as appeares partly by their vaſte dung-hils, peſtering both yards and ſtréets, without any kinde of manuring, yéelded plentifull increaſe of graſſe and graine, howſoeuer the Natiues attribute this continuing richneſſe of the ſoyle to the ſpeciall benediction of their Sainted Patron Saint Patricke.
               
               
                  Compacture found by the ſtowage.Some let not to conclude in commendation of the Soile vpon the bare experiment laid downe by Virgil for diſtinguiſhing betwéene open and rare ſoyles, and ſuch as are condenſe &amp; cloſe, where he wils to ſinke a pit in ſome ſolid place, and to take out, and breake the earth, and after to tread it in againe, and if it ſwell aboue the former height, they iudge it rich according to the proportion of the ſupereminence, if it prooue euen and flat, they eſtéeme it meane, if it ſettle vnder, in
                     •
                  ertile. But the Poet commends that which is rare, and not condenſe, for producing of graſſe and plants fit for broouage, and browſage of ſhéepe, and for Vines; and that which by

filling the Foſſe appeares to bee compact and denſe, hee intimates to yéeld large and tough furrowes, and deſtinates it to Tillage.
               
                  Rara ſit, an ſupra morem ſit denſa requiras,
                  Altera frumentis quoniam fauet, altera Baccho,
                  Denſa magis Cereri, rariſſima quae
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Lyaeo;
                  Antè locum capies oculis, alte
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      iubebis
                  In ſolido puteum demitti, omnem
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      repones
                  Rurſus humū, &amp; pedibus ſummas aequabis arenas:
                  Si deerunt, rarum; pecori
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      &amp; vitibus almis
                  Aptius vber erit: ſin in ſua poſſe negabunt
                  Ire loca, &amp; ſcrobibus ſuperabit terra repletis
                  Spiſſus ager; glebas cunctanteis craſſa
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      terga
                  Expecta, &amp; validis terram proſcinde Iuuencis.
               
               And the fat ſoyle he ſaith, diſſolues not,Moulding. being laboured in the hands, but becomes clammy, coheres, &amp; cleaues to the fingers: and that Earth that by moulding in the hand doth clift and cleaue, and reſolue into powder, or moulde, argues a barren, and leane layer.
               
                  Pinguis item quae ſit tellus, hoc deni
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      pacto
                  Diſcimus; haud vnquam manibus iactata fatiſcit,
                  Sed picis in morem ad digitos lenteſcit habendo.
               
               The poize and colour (ſaith the Poet) are euident,Weight. but the ſcorched and noyſome chilneſſe of the ſoyle is bewrayed by the voluntarie growth of Pitch-trées, Ewes and blacke Iuie:

                     —At ſceleratum exquirere frigus
                     Difficile eſt; piceae tantum taxi
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         nocentes
                     Interdum, aut hederae pandunr veſtigia nigrae.Taſte.
                     
                  
               
               For deprehending and finding out the taſte of the Earth, Virgil preſcribes a generall Specimen in his concluſion for triall of ſalt and bitter ſoyles; viz. to fill cloſe wicker baskets with the earth and water, and then to runne and ſtraine through the water by treading or preſſing, and ſo by the taſte of the water to iudge of the Earth by the qualitie imparted:

                     
                     —tu ſpiſſo vimine quallos
                     Cola
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         praelorum fumoſis diripe tectis;
                     Huc ager ille malus dulceſ
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         a fontibus vndae
                     Ad plenum calcentur, aqua eluctabitur omnis
                     Scilicet, &amp; grandes ibunt per vimina guttae,
                     At ſapor indicium faciet manifeſtus, &amp; ora
                     Triſtia tentantûm ſenſu torquebit amaror.
                  
               
               Ponticke Worme-wood bewraies a bitter and barren ſoyle, according to Ouid:
                  
                     Turpia deformes gignunt abſinthia campi,
                     Terraque de fructu, quam ſit amara docet.
                  
               
               
                  Smell.If ſomewhat before Sunne-ſet in the firſt rain-fall enſuing a drought, or in earing, the Earth ſhall breath forth an aromaticall odour and ſwéet ſauour, it is held an infallible ſigne of a temperate fertilitie: And that ground which exhailes and breathes-forth exile and fumie vapours quickly vaniſhing, which attracts humors and ſelfely expels them, which inueſts and cloathes it ſelf with a cloſe ſwoord of freſh-gréene graſſe is parabile, gentle, and plyant for the plowe, good for graine, Elmes, Vine-yards, and Oliuets.
               
                  Quae tenuem exhalat nebulam, fumoſque volucreis,
                  Et bibit humorem, &amp; cum vult ex ſe ipſa remittit,
                  Quaeque ſuo viridi ſemper ſe gramine veſtit,
                  Nec ſcabie &amp; ſalſa &amp;c.
               
               
                  Cato in two ſignificant Epithites (ſed per tranſennam) comprehends the ſeuerall attributes,Pulla &amp; Carioſa. both of a good and bad ſoyle, viz: Pulla and Carioſa.
               
               
                  Plinie diſentrauerſes the meaning of Pulla to imply a blackiſh, gentle, mellow, and tender ſoyle, and ſuch a one (ſaith he) is determined to be beſt, both for Tillage, and worke, becauſe by Tenera is intended a ſoft and plyable earth.
               
                  Production.And amongſt other ſignes of a good ſoyle, hée enumerates Wall-wort, Skeg-trées, Brambles, the little wilde bulbous Crow-toes, (called our Ladies Cow-ſlip)

Clauer-gras, Trefoile, Melilot, Oakes, Wilde Peare-trées, and Wildings, to betoken a temper appropriate for Wheate and White-Corne. And this is the more probable, if they be plentifull in number, and ranke in growth. And both he and Virgil, commend the ſoyle to bee ſingular good for Corne, where woods haue béen lately ſtocked vp:

                     Aut vnde iratus ſiluam deuexit arator,
                     Et nemora euertit multos ignaua per annos:
                  
               
               The qualities of a badde ſoyle are implyed in the Epithite Carioſa,
                  Barren layer. which Plinie explaines to import a Wood-like rottenneſſe, viz: drie, ſpungeous, ful of holes, rugged, hoarie, olde, and hollowe.
               And Virgil affirmes, that the barren ground waxeth pallid and whitiſh after the plowing:
At rudis enituit impulſo vomere campus.
               
               To theſe may be added ſalt, bitter, chauning, burnt, parched, ſoale-bound, choaked, colde, and wet ſpewing grounds.
               To conclude:Characters of rich ſoyles. Out of the premiſſes it may be colected, that the beſt ſoyle in generall, conſiſts in a wel-ſeaſoned mixture of a blackiſh moulde which is light, déepe-fat, ſwéet in taſte and odour, murling, plyable, mellow, of moderate warmth, not ſtowable in the primer continent, ſhining blacke after the ſhare, dulcique vligine laeta, and rich in radicall humour.
               So much for the knowledge of ground.
            
            
               CHAP. IX.
               THe Nature and qualitie of Grounds thus layde downe,Enriching. and the preſent ſtate and Habitude duely conſidered, the meanes befitting for the Enriching of the Soyle will be more euident.
               
                  The enriching of Grounds doth conſiſt in Clearing and Chearing.
               The clearing of the Ground is conuerſant in disburthening the Soile from incumbrances and annoyances, as Water, Stones, Wéedes, &amp;c.
               
                  Surroundings.Surrounded grounds may be won by Sewing them with competent Draines, Tonnels, Goats, Sluces, and ſuch like, if the Water-fall be ſufficient; otherwiſe ſome Enginarie aide muſt bee aſſiſtant to mount the water by Screwes, Pullies, Poizes, by cauſing Vacuums, or reinforcing of Spirits into narrow ſtraights and Cylinders.
               And to retriue the difference twixt the line of Leuel, and the Circular or Water-leuel; to the Earths Semi-diameter (viz: 3436 4/11 Italian Miles) ſquared, add the ſquare of the diſtance propounded, from the ſquare roote of their Totall take 3436 4/11: the Remainder is the difference.
               
                  Bogges.Spungy and boggy grounds muſt be intertraced (correſponding to the Current or Diſcent) with Trenches of ſome eightéene inches breadth both at toppe and bottome, and where the toughneſſe of the ſwarth or turffe wil permit ſome ſpare ſpaces, may be vnder mined; but to preſerue all the ſweard, you may couch good coggles, al-alongſt the Trenches a competent height, and the ſoddes vpon them, ſo the water will ſoake and draine thorow: And this practiſe is moſt approouable and peculiar in mildring Clay, which otherwiſe by ſhooting and melting downe into open Trenches, would choake vp the water-paſſages.
               
                  Stones.For Coggles, Flint, Pibbles, Shingles, and other ſtones hindring the earing, and oppreſſing the graine or graſſe, the conceit (in Aiax) of ſetting hable Vagrants to earne their Almes, is not vnworthie imitation, whether to the Lime-kill, houſe, high-way, ponde, foord, or other vſe.
               
                  For Vegetable impediments, as Buſhes, Shrubs,Buſhes. Broome. Bryers, Furres, Whynnes, Broome, &amp;c. they being once rooted vp by dogging or grubbing, the Plot muſt be well plyed with the Plow, and ſewen ſome Crops ſucceſſiuely after: to which earing if well-ſoyling with good Marle, and Stall-dung be added, they will bee vtterly extinguiſhed, though they be rooted in a barren, hot and drie ſoile, their proper element; but the cauſe being remooued (vt ſupra) the effects of producing theſe bad burthens muſt néeds ſurceaſe by conſequence.
               The infuſion of Lupine flowers in Hemlocke iuyce caſte vpon Shrubbe roots, is ſaid to kill them; but this is too curious.
               Linge, Heath or Hather, in ſalt, ſandie,Heath. drie and barren ſoyles will die and decay, if the diſtemper inherent be reformed by manurings with fatte marle, rich and rotten moulde, &amp;c.
               If they grow in grauelly colde Earth, they require Stable dung, but in grauelly colde Clay drenched with blacke water, Lime and Chalke worke beſt effects, by ſoaking vp the ſuperfluous Water, killing the Heath and comforting the Earth.
               Brakes Brakin or Ferne,Ferne. though it cannot be cured with avulſion, by reaſon of the ranke power of regerminating or increaſe, retained in euerie particle of their roots, which are ſo recurued as they are not poſſible to be plucked vp without ſome Remainders: Yet being cut downe in their infancie, and caſt vpon their own roots, they will ſuffocate and deſtroy themſelues, eſpecially if they be therewithall Shéepe-folded and ground-fedde with ruminant Cattell.
               Flags, Sedge, Ruſhes,Flags. and other wéeds abounding in boggie and ſpungie grounds, doe wither and waſte away, by the ſuperfluous moiſture which bréeds and féeds them, being drawne forth by draynage; but if the Plot be peſtered with Alders, you labour in vaine to euacuate

the wet before the Trées or Buſhes bee eradicated, for their roots do naturally attract ſo much moiſture for their nutriment, that all the ground adiacent will be eft-ſoones choaked with a continuall cold wet.
               
                  Thiſtles.But the former wéeds with Thiſtles, Hemlocks, and all ſappie wéedes cut downe in Wood-ſeare, and often mowne againe whilſt they are tender, their roots will putrifie and rotte ouer-burthened with affluent iuyce wanting due and woonted paſſage for growth: and the Thiſtle ſtalke, muſt not be permitted to reſt gréene néere to the earth, for by the euaporation thereof, it will adder-like reuiue and roote againe.
               
                  BurresRich Grounds peſtered with Burs, Hemlocks, Nettles, &amp; ranke wéeds are commodiouſly diſburthened by ſowing them with Hempe, Line, Muſtard-ſéede, &amp;c.
               
                  Ruſhes.Ruſhes, ranke ſower graſſe, Prie and Quitch-graſſe, Moſſe, Wéedes, &amp;c. In waterie colde Clay, are deſtroyed with Marle, Lime, Chalke, Vraic, Soote, Cole-duſt, Soape and other Aſhes, Shauings of Horne, Burning of Beate.
               
                  Moſſe.Moſſe generally is deſtroyed with Doues and Hens-dung, and it putrifies being turned-in with the Plow: But Buſhes, and Shrubs, muſt bee alſo remooued, for by their oft-droppings of wette retained after ſhowers, miſts and deawes, the ſwarth or turffe is ſo infrigidated and chilled, that being continued for or conuerted to meadowe, or grazing, it eft-ſoones reaſſumes his moſſie habite, though the Plot bee not naturally prone and inclining thereto.
               But a ſcurffie hungry Moſſe and ſmall Lung-wort, diſperſed ouer an hot, drie, and heartleſſe ground, is beſt deſtroyed with a ſlimie, and oylie Marle.
               
                  Ant-Hils.Where Moſſe, Ant-hils, and Mole-hils doe abound, it is excellent husbandrie to eare it, and ſowe certaine Crops of Oates, for they prepare all lay-grounds, eſpecially if they be ſower and ſoaked with wet.
               
                  And for Ant-hils I haue obſerued a rich increaſe of Oats (in an indifferent ſoyle) ſowne in the very mould of the hils (being many and great) caſtabroad and well harrowed without plowing-vp the plain turffe, the ſummer ſeaſon proouing not too drie.
               The quartering of the ſweard of Ant-hils, caſting their ballas't, &amp; playning their Plots for paſture, are ſo frequent &amp; approoued, as there néeds no demonſtration.
               Wilde Oates peſtering and pilling of Tilthes, are beſt deſtroyed by Summer fallowings.Oates.
               
               And ſo much for Clearing of Grounds.
            
            
               CHAP. X.
               THe Chearing of Grounds conſiſts in the curing of their infirmities,Chearing. inherent naturally or by acquiſition, and in the refection, and refreſhing their weake and languiſhing vertues.
               Clayes and all grounds diſtempered with colde and moiſture, are cured and cheriſhed with ſtable-dung,Cold and moiſt. Doues-dung, folding, burning, lime, ſoote, iron ſinders of the furnace beat ſmall and ſowen thinne, and with Coale, Ferne, and Soape-Aſhes.
               Barren hot ſandy-ſoyles, and hot drie Earth producing parched graſſe and dwarffie Moſſe,Hot and drie. doe craue ſtal-dung, ſtréet-ſoyle, pond-mudde, rich mould, fat marle, Mawme or Riuer-ſlubbe, ſcowrings of hedge-rowd Ditches, ſlimie or mooriſh earth or Murgeon to helpe all defects.
               And Virgil ſaith,

                     —Arida tantum
                     Ne ſaturare fimo pingui pudeat ſola:
                  
               
               Nor is the ſhéepe-folding and foddering, and the Compoſt of putrified Henbane, Hemlockes, leaues of Apple-trées, willowes, &amp;c. of leſſe efficacie.
               Brittle and fickle Mould of meane temperature

twixt hot and cold,Brittle Mould. is beſt ſoyled with well rotted horſe-dung.
               
                  Spewing.Spewing grounds ouer-ſoaked with ſower moiſture are well reléeued by being ſowne with Oates, for by their arifying and drying qualitie they ſucke out and conſume that noyſome humour.
               
                  Boggie.Boggie and ſpungie grounds are not a little ſetled, faſtened and firmed by frequent ouer-flowing them with Fords or Land-flouds,A Paradox. affording a fatte and ſlimie ſubſtance or ſlubbe.
               
                  Stiffe-Clay.The ſtiffe colde Clay craues Aſhes, eſpecially of roots ſtocked vp, Chaulke, Sea-ſand, Malt duſt ſowen thinne on the tilth, lime incorporated with Stable-dung, ſalt.
               
                  Soal-bound.Cruſt-clung and Soale-bound ſoyles craue Caruage for preſt and peculiar Gaole deliuerie, this lightens and looſeth the ſoyle, and enlargeth and prepares way to the operation of the radicall humour, and conſequently ſerues in lieu of Compoſt.
               
                  Chapping.Chapping grounds, chinking, or chauming with Cranies are cured, and ſtiffe-cold ſpuing grounds, are admirably relieued and fertilized, by burning the ſtubble, fegge, or turffe; whether that by cloſing vp the Chinks, it auerts the extremities of wet, winde, froſt, and Sunne, whereby the ſéede might be ſuffocated, blaſted, ſtarued or parched, or the ſoyle diſtempered; Or that it exhales and purges forth, and euaporates al hurtfull and pernicious humours; Or that it pinguifies the ſoyle, and imparts to the ſéede ſome ſecret nutrimentiue power; Or that by ſtirring vp the natiue heat of the Earth, it reuiues the radical and vliginque humour, and by opening and enlarging the obſtructed paſſages, and vaines, giues entrance to the airie ſpirit, and iuyce that quickens the graine:

                     Saepe etiam ſterileis incendere profuit agros,
                     At
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         leuem ſtipulam crepitantibus vrere flammis:
                     Siue inde occultas vires, &amp; pabula terrae
                     
                        Pinguia concipiunt; ſiue illis omne per ignem
                     Excoquitur vitium, atque exudat inutilis humor;
                     Seu plureis calor ille vias, et caeca relaxat
                     Spiramenta, nouas veniet qua ſuccus in herbas:
                     Seu durat magis, &amp; venas adſtringit hianteis,
                     Ne tenues pluuiae, rapidiuè potentia Solis
                     Acrior, aut Boreae penetrabile frigus adurat.
                  
               
               But generally all grounds, be they neuer ſo barren, are much bettered by burning the dryed heapes of the turffe or ſwarth delued, howed, pared, or plowed vp and dried, and after ſpread all ouer the excoriated Tilth, whether it worke as aforeſaid, or that according to Plinie, it burnes vp and deſtroies the Seminarie of graſſe and wéedes, which would robbe and depriue the ſoyle of the rich Iuices and vertues which ſhould féede the graine.
               And the excellent effects deriued from this Beat-burning,Denſhiring. haue brought the ſame into ſuch approoueable requeſt in Deuonſhire, that of the frequent vſe and fruitfull practiſe thereof in thoſe partes, the name of Denſhiring deduceth the originall.Meddowe
               
               Sommer-cating doth greatly enhearten weake Medowes, and reſtore their decaying heat and vigour impeached by yéerely mowing.
               In the North of Ireland,Kreatings. they do with much conuenience, by kreating &amp; ſhifting their Boolies frō ſéed-fur til harueſt bée inned, both depaſture &amp; ſoile their grounds, and preſerue their graine from deſtruction by their cattell, and them from the Wolfe and Wood-kerne.
               And the ſowing of the ſéede of Trefoyle, or Clauers,Sowing of Seedes. Melilot, Prunel, Milfoyle, Ribwort, Septfoile, Cinquefoyle, &amp;c. Mixed with Murling Mould, doth much inrich Meddowes and Paſtures both in Forrage and Fenage.
               Sea-ſand diffuſed amongſt infertile Tilthes,Sea-ſand. infuſes animall power of ſuch efficacie, that it produces Crops equiualent to burthens of very battle Glebes.
               
                  And Reſt to a meane layer, ſerues no leſſe in lieu of Compoſt:
Nec nulla in terra eſt inaratae gratia terrae:
               
               Alſo,

                     Alternis item tonſas ceſſare noualeis
                     
                        Aſhes.Et ſegnem patiere ſitu dureſcere campum.
                  
               
               And all Emacerated Soyles are much amended with fatte Aſhes:

                     —Neue
                     Effetos cinerem immundum iactare per agros.
                  
               
               And there is ſo much attributed to Reſt and Aſhes for inriching of ſoyles, that they are numbred amongſt the thrée things ſeruing to increaſe productiōs of Crops:
Laetas faciunt ſegetes ſtercoratio, intermiſſio &amp; cinerum ſparſio.
               
               Of diuers Aſhes we haue before (and ſhal hereafter) vpon ſpeciall occaſions, made mention for their approoued efficacie in ſeuerall diſtempers. And Plinie reports that Aſhes are in ſuch requeſt, for ſoylings néere vnto Po, that they burne their Horſe-dung to make them; but wée are too wiſe, holding it ridiculous to innouate, nay to imitate any thing not approoued by continual practiſe, howſoeuer we haue authenticke records from antiquities to animate vs thereunto.
               
                  Rich Soyles.Wée willingly wiſh the fruition of ſoiles parallell to the Territories of Bi
                        •
                     acium in Affricke, which is ſo plyable to the Plow, that after a good ground ſhowre, a ſorry Aſſe and a ſilly old Trot, may roundly trot away with the Téeme, and ſo plentifull in production, that it yéeldes increaſe one hundred and fifty folde, but wée would grudge at the ſtubborneſſe of the ground in a dry ſeaſon, when wée found it ſcarce tillable with a ſtrong Téeme of Oxen.
               Or we could plauſibly approoue the light &amp; eaſie Tilage, and rich Graynage, by Winterton in Norfolke: the Auſtrian ſoyle tilled with a ſingle horſe; the fruitfull Plaines of Podolia where they ſow but euery other

yéere (the ſhaked corne ſeruing (like Rapes) for the ſecond ſéedage) the Hungarian treble harueſt, the fertile Meddowes of Komora (Iled with Danubius) which produces graſſe man-high, yet farre ſhort of the Meade vnder a Bourne néere to Saliſbury, where the production extendes to ſixtéene foote.
               The Meades of Interamna, yéelding yéerely foure Mathes of Hay, &amp;c. but we would not with like alacrity imitate the induſtrious paines of the ingenious Chimiſts, who by their diligent and intentiue huſbanding their fertile fieldes, ſupport their ſtrangely populous Territories in farre greater wealth and plenty, then can be deriued from their trebled fruitage and afluent vintage, without their own extraordinary induſtry and diligence.
               In rich ſoyles we are ſlacke and ſupine, neuer practiſing any new or invulgar inuention (how probable ſoeuer) to helpe Nature and fertilize our fieldes, but wée plod-on in the common Road of habituated huſbandry, and ſo oftentimes come ſhort of that proportion which good huſbands reape in a farre meaner layer.
               In barren and harde Countries,1. Lime. wee are force perforce vrged to ſome induſtry more then ordinary: As in the Countries of Salop, Denbigh, Flint, &amp;c. they fetch Lime ſtone foure or fiue miles, to burne for battleing, and Sea-ſand ſixe miles to ſcatter on their Tilthes, in Cornewall, Deuon, Somerſet, &amp;c. And in ſome partes of Hartfordſhire (not to defraude the induſtrious of any praiſe due to diligent devoires) they fetch Mault-duſt further, and ſhauing of Horne aboue twenty miles,Mault-duſt. Horne-ſhauings. to ſtrow vpon their Arable (though it be a good ſoyle of it ſelfe) to kill the wéedes, and cheare the ſoyle, and therby doe much increaſe their Crops.
               In Denbighſhire, and elſe where, they plow vp the Cruſt of barren ſoyles in thinne Turffes, with a broad winged ſhare, then dry it in round heapes, and about

September,Burning of Beate burne in and diſperſe the Aſhes all ouer the bared and Excoriated groundes, and thereby refreſh their faint and hungry ſterility, to an incredible production of Oates.
               In Flintſhire, they ſoile their ſandy layers (both blacke and red) being ſeckie,2. Lime. tough and wet, with lime made of a dunny gray ſtone, hewed forth of the Rockes and broken with yron malls (though the ſmooth hard beach on the Sea-ſhoares burnes to a purer white) and after burning, lay it thicke vpon the layer, leauing it to be ſlecked with the next ſhowre, by which being diſſolued and then intermedled by the plow with the ſoyle, it puffie-lights and party colours the ſame, and produces diuers rich Crops; The vſe thereof is alſo well approued for their Claies in thinner quantitie: but they teaſil their perring wild ſand with ſtall dung.
               
                  Slecked Lime.About Workenſope in Nottinghamſhire, their beſt Compoſt is ſlecked Lime (ſixe quarters to an Acre) ſowne vpon the Tilth, for two Crops, for Winter corne in Sommer, the other contrary, and this giues good increaſe, not ſo much through the imparture of any faſtening facultie, as by faſtening the wilde looſe ſand of their light, hotte, and red layers: And though the ſmall ſhow of winter verdure giues wanne hope, yet his faire May-floriſh reviues the drooping ſpirits of the doubtful and wauering experimenter, with ful aſſurance of a rich veſture for harueſt.
               
                  The quantity of Compoſt.And generally for the quantity of dung, it is held beſt to Manure oft &amp; little, for ouer dunging burnes away the heart of the ſoyle.
               The better the ſoyles are, the leſſe Compoſt they craue, but grounds not dunged grow cold and weake, howſoeuer ſome are ſo battle in fertilitie, that their ranckenes cannot with continued tillage be ſufficiently abated; as the Territories of Tacape mentioned by Plinie.
               
               
                  But, to ſpeake ſomewhat of the qualities of Compoſt, there are diuers kindes of dung,The quality. and ſundry opinions touching their goodnes and efficacie.
               
                  Marcus Varro attributes the chiefe eſtéeme to the dung found in the Bartons of mewed Blacke-birdes,Birdes. both for tillage and forrage.
               Pullen and Landfowle are commended for their dung, but all water fowle reiected.Poultry.
               
               
                  Columella commends Pidgens dung,Doues. and with vs it carries chiefe preheminence for due prizall of worth.
               Many giue the firſt place to mans excrements (the Ballaſt of Ajax) but the exceſſiue heate therof would be qualified and abated with the ſwéepings, parings,Ajax. and filth of houſe floares.
               Some preferre mens Vrine, when hide-haire hath béene ſoaked therein, with Lime in a Tanne-fat, others commend the Vrine mixt with water.
               Diuers affirme the Aſſes dung to bee beſt, moſt prepared,Aſſe. and preſently fit for the earth (whereas other dungs require time to putrifie) but Plinie is contradictory.
               But for generall approouement, the Treddles of Shéepe and Goates may paſſe for current.Sheepe.
               
               Next followes the dung of Neate,Neate and Horſes. then of Horſes and Mules.
               The Ordure of Swine is current with ſome for good Compoſt, but it ſéemes by Columella,
                  Swine. that it beſt fits the Aſſe-paſture, whoſe forrage is Burres, and worſe baggage, but doubtleſſe the immoderate heat therof burnes vp the radicall humour of the ſoyle.Lime
               
               For Lime I haue ſpoken ſufficiently before of the Moderne vſe thereof, nor was it in leſſe requeſt amongſt the Heduans and Pictones for fertilizing their fields.
               
                  Cato preſcribes an Artificiall Compoſt of Litter,Compoſt. Artificiall. Lupines, Chaffe, Beane ſtalkes, Leaues and Branches of Maſt-holme, and Oakes laide to putrifie.
               
                  
                  Optimum Stercus.But as Oculus Domini ſaginat equum, ſo dayly experience approoues Domini Veſtigia to be Stercus optimum.
               
               
                  Vegetables.Dane-wort, Hemlocks, dead-leaues, ranck-wéedes, Ferne mowne in Auguſt, Sea-wéedes &amp;c. withered, caſt on Tilthes and foulded with ſhéepe, doe very much profit. And no leſſe béeing caſt into the Cratch-yard all Winter, and beſtowed on the fallowes next September and October.
               
                  Vraic.And Vraic or Orewood, (Alga Marina) is diuersly applyed for ſoyling. In Ireland they rot it in great heapes, from Sommer to Sommer, and then caſt it on their Tilthes for two or thrée Crops.
               In Angleſey, they plow it in without putrifying for two Crops in any ſoyle.
               In the Ile of Gerſey, they dry the wéede for fewell, and with Aſhes fertilize their fallowes no leſſe then with Marle.
               In Cornewal they vſe both Orewood, Sea-ſand, and Sea-flubbe for ſoylings,
               
                  Sata.The very fruites of the earth being ſowne doe ſerue well for batling, as Buck-wheat or Brancke, Peaſe, Vetches, Beanes, Faſells, Madder.
               Sic quoque mutatis requieſcunt faetibus arua.
               And Columella ſaith, Medica agrum Stercorat.
               
               
                  Lupines.The ſowing of Lupines is no leſſe approoued for bettering the Tilth, but eſpecially if they be turned in with the Plowe, and ſo left to putrifie, about their flowring.
               And becauſe white corne is commonly a ſoaker of the ſoyle, the Poet counſels to ſowe it after Pulſe and fatning graine.
               
                  Aut ibi flaua ſeres mutato ſidere farra
                  Vnde prius laetum ſiliqua quaſſante legumen,
                  Aut tenueis faetus viciae, triſtiſque lupini
                  Suſtuleris fragiles calamos, Syluamque ſonantem.
               
               
                  Saffron.Nor is Saffron inferior to fatning graine, inſomuch

as their bulbous rootes doe ſo inrich the ground, that after thrée yéeres continuing the ſame with Saffron, (as Maſter Camden affirmes) at the rate of eightie or one hundred poundes new (but twenty dryed) vpon an Acre, the ſoyle about Saffron Walden, produces great ſtore of Barley, for ſome eightéene yéeres without Compoſt, and then againe refuſes not his former fruit.Pillers of the ſoyle.
               
               But Wheate, Barley, Woade, Vetches, Fenigréeke and all Pulſes, plucked vp by the rootes, are great impairers and ſoakers of the ſoyle: And Line, Poppy, and Oates doe burne and pill the Tilth. Solo virus Ciceris &amp; Lini; the one with his ſalt, and the other with his hotte qualitie. Tremelius. The Poet.
               
                  Vrit enim lini campum ſeges, vrit auena,
                  Vrunt lethaeo perfuſa papauera ſomno.
               
               And Theophraſtus ſaith, that Oates by their dryneſſe and multiplicity of rootes, doe arifie and extenuate all Soyles.
               And in this place it ſhall not be impertinent,Marle. to make ſome mention of Marle, ſith the good approoument both of the ancient and moderne vſe thereof is ſuch, as may iuſtly challenge to be had in no meane eſtéeme for manurings.
               
                  Plinie affirmes that there are but two kinds of Marle in Nature, viz. either hard and churliſh,Two ſortes of Marle. or gentle and fat, and theſe are tryed by the hand: and both for graine and graſſe (though we ſay Marle kills both wéedes and graſſe in arable) held in good requeſt.
               And the various ſorts of Marles, found out by inuentiue wits, doe all of them fall vnder the two former kinds, whether they bee white, red, Columbine, ſtony, Sandie, Clay-ſoyle, &amp;c. or what others.Leucargilla.
               
               The white Clay or Marle is fat, ſharpe and mordant and yet the beſt. It is vſed for moiſt cold grounds in Magara, as our Chaulke with vs.
               And the white Chaulkie Clay,Tripela. vſed by Gold-ſmithes

lies déepe in Britaine, and laſteth for ſoyling eighty yeares.
               The Fullers Chaulky Clay mixed with a viſcous and fattiſh Earth,Gliſcomargon. is another white Marle, and is better for graine then for graſſe, yet, howſoeuer it ſuppreſſes wéedes and graſſe in corne (as all Marles doe) the Tilthe, after harueſt be inned, growes ſo growthſome that it yéeldes an after-math, for Crowen Hay.
               This Marle continues the ſoyle in good plight thirty yéeres, but if it be laide on ouer thicke it choketh the ground.
               
                  Capnumargos.The light red Marle intermingled with ſome ſtony gritte full of Sand, fertilizeth both Tillage and Forrage for fifty yéeres.
               In Angleſey they approoued red Marle, and in ſome places white, to refreſh and giue life to the ſpent and tired Glebes.
               Columbine or Pidgeon Marle, lies in lumpes and cloddes,Pelias. but with Sunne and Froſt, it reſolues and cleaues into thinne ſlakes or flakes, and ſerues both for corne and Hay.
               In ſome parts of Cheſ-ſhire, they beſtow forty loades of Doue-diſcoloured Marle vpon an Acre,The quantity. and this being Froſt-mellowed &amp; ſpread abroad, diſſolues and incorporates with the Glebe, and ſo fattens the Sandy and hungry Soyle, that it repaires the charge of thrée or foure pound, with rich increaſe for twelue or ſixtéene yéeres. Inſomuch, as to farme this wel-nigh worthleſſe ground, they will Marle, Till, and Séede it for halfe the increaſe: And they let and ſet ſuch Marled grounds, vnder twenty yéeres at an incredible rate of monies in hand.
               
                  Stony Marls.Stony and Grauelly white Marle, found amongſt Springs and Fountaines, cauſes infinite fruitfulneſſe though it be rough, but if it be laid on too thicke, it parches the very ground.
               
                  And Sandy Marle ſerues (for want of other) chiefely in cold moiſt and wéely grounds.Sandie Marle.
               
               The dry Marle ſortes with moiſt Soyles, and fatty Marle hits the dry and leane.
               For Soyles of middle temperature it ſkils not whether you vſe the White Gold-ſmithes Chaulke, or the Columbine Marle.
               But generally moſt Marles, (ſaith Plinie) craue to follow the Plow, that their medicinable vertues and ſubſtance may the ſooner and more gréedily be attracted and receiued: and a medly of dung were not amiſſe, to correct the ouer-rough hardneſſe of maine Marles.
               The Vbians enrich moſt fertile grounds, with any earth digged from thrée foote depth, and lay it foote-thick for tenne yéeres.
               At Chatmoſſe in Lancaſhire, their vliginous and ſoaked Moſſes doe recompence their meane ayre with vnctious Turffes, Wood for woorke, fewel and Candel and fat Marle to manure their Soyles.
               And were we as iudicious in inuention, or induſtrious in imitation of the diligent, as we are ſuperſticious in plodding in habituated &amp; accuſtomed courſes of huſbandry, we would endeuour (all idle pretenſes abandoned) to make ſeuerall Soyles ſerue interchangeably,Interſoilings each to other in true validity of Compoſt, by inter-ſoyling or ſeaſoning the one with the other.
               As Grauell and Chaulke, Clay and Sand, So light and ſadde, tough and friable, hot and colde, battle and barren, &amp;c.—Yet Plinie ſaies it is a méere folly and waſt expence to lay fatte earth vpon leane and hungry, or dry light and thirſty vpon ouer moiſt and fatte.
               But land-flouds,Waterings. fatte Riuers and Guſts of water participating of a ſlimie and muddy ſubſtance, induced and brought into Meddowes and paſtures in the ſpring by draines, dams, inuerſions from towne ditches, ſewers,

wayes, ſtréetes Tilthes, do very much comfort and reuiue them.
               So Virgill:
                  
                     —Huc ſummis liquuntur rupibus amnes
                     Faelicemque trahunt limum.
                  
               
               Alſo,

                     Et cum exuſtus ager morientibus aeſtuat herbis
                     Ecce ſupercilio cliuoſi tramitis vndam
                     Elicet: illa cadens raucum per leuia murmur
                     Saxa ciet, ſcatebrisque arentia temperat arua.
                  
               
               
                  The Riuer. Nilus.So the Egyptian Soyle (though it bee a blacke and battle layer) deriues the aboundant fruitfulneſſe from the Riuer Nile, whoſe inundation ſupplies the want of raine, and féedes and fattes the Earth with the ſlime and mud left behind it.
               But I ſhal be taxed for this tedious penning of thoſe petty experciments, and therefore I will omit to ſpeake of the parti
                     •
                  ular beſtowing of Salt, Soote, Aſhes and Powder of Hornes, Oiſterſhels, &amp;c. the infuſion of Lupine flowers, Wine Lées, and the like, and ſo much the rather becauſe their coſt or ſcarcitie derogates from their goodnes in efficacie.
               This may therefore ſerue for chearing of grounds, and conſequently for enriching of the ſoyle.
            
            
               CAP. XI.
               
                  Rectifying.THe Rectifying of Production, is accompliſhed by beſtowing the grounds to purpoſes, ſuiting their appropriate Natures with due regard to the Sympathie and Antipathie, betwéene Séedes and Soyles, Plants and Plottes.
               
                  Sande.The great faſt Yellow Sand, is not vnfit for Graine The cloſe Sand with ſome earthy mixture is good for Grazing; The White and dry for Woodes and Wilde

fruits; But a looſe and light Sant ſwords ſlow and thin, yet with reſt and lecking ſommers it yéelds good Corne:
               More particularly:
               Wheat craues a fat Clay (and dry to make it hard and compact) and durty Séedage.Graine.
               
               Barley loues a mellow Clay and a duſtie March.Barly.
               
               Rie ſuits with a Sandy ſoyle and drownes i'th hopper.Rie.
               
               Beanes looke for a ſtrong moiſt Clay,Beanes. if you expect ſtiffe ware and great Burthens.
               Peaſe preſſe for a putryfied Clayie mould of meane ſtrength.
               Vetches are fruitfull in Creachie Countries.
               Lentills like well of a leane and vntilde Sandy Soyle and a dry ſeaſon.
               Lupines loue dry Sand and Grauell and neede no Plow.
               Oates doe well in a leane dry Clay, though they péele a better and prepare a moiſt.
               But for rough dry and barren ſoyles Buck-wheate is beſt to fill the meaſure and manure the fielde.
               Spelt-corne in a fat moiſt layer degenerats from bad to better viz. in thrée yéeres ſpace to Wheat.
               Tare, Cich and Mill loue moiſture, this with looſeneſſe, that with fatneſſe, the firſt with leanneſſe.
               
                  Pannicke is pleaſed with a leane grauelly or ſtony Earth, ſo it be light and moiſt.
               
                  Medica in putri ſolo hyeme decocto &amp; ſtercorato vno ſatu amplius trecentis annis durat. Plinius.
               
               Rice requires to be ſowne in a fennye and wateriſh layer.
               Saffron ioyes in a frée Chaulkie or red ſandie ſoyle, indifferently huſbanded, but manured with Neats and Doues dung.
               Woad and Blaunch would haue a ſtrong ground, and this brookes well the roughneſſe, yea in the coldeſt

clime, but the other muſt haue it in good plight.
               Commin couets a layer that is fat, hot and putrified.
               Hollie, Worme-wood or Wormeſéede, loues both labour and a hot clime.
               Caruwaies craue a good cleane &amp; manured ground.
               Anni-ſéede muſt haue a blacke rich mellow-mould, or a battle and well-dunged earth: and thoſe and other earely ſowne ſéedes, doe néede a thin ſtrowing of Horſe dung to rebate the force of froſtie coldes.
               Muſtard multiplies well in a plot repleat with grauelly rubbiſh, but it would be moiſt and battle; and wel tilde alſo for the whitiſh ſéede.
               Rapes require a broken-vp lay and a rich layer.
               Hempe lookes for a fat moiſt laboured land plowed plaine and déepe.
               Line loues a meane depth, but a very fine light, gentle and fat mould, yet a leane layer refines it, and Plinie commends Grauell.
               
                  Roots.Rootes require fat, cleane, looſe and light grounds, as Potatoes, Earth-nuts, Turneps; and this in ſandy layers, growes more ſound, firme and delicious.
               But clay produces ſound, dry, delicate and large-Parſeneps, and enlarges the Parſlies Roote.
               Onyons, Chiballs and Chiues thriue well in a red ſhort, murly and moiſtiſh earth.
               Garlicke delights in a dry vndunged but laboured ground.
               Sowbread likes both labour and Compoſt: ſo doth Teaſell with flattes two foot and an halfe déepe.
               But large and long-rootes muſt alſo haue their layer déepe and well dunged in the bottome, if you would enlarge their growth: as for theſe Meateable Rootes, Parſnep, Carrot, Skirrot, Radiſh, Goates-beard, Caruwaies, Mirrhis.
               And the like for Medicinable Rootes, as Endiue, Succory, Scammony, Ariſtolachia.
               
                  But if you intent a plot for ſéedage, let their beds bée incorporated in a medley of mould and dung.
               Liquerice runnes downe with ſtraight ſmooth rootes in a light looſe battle and cleane laboured bed of 4. or 5. foote depth and bredth wel manured withſtal-dung &amp; Columbine Marle.
               Madder reſpects not ſo much the ſtrength of the groūd ſo it be light moiſt ſandy frée well-dunged and digged 6. foote déepe and broad.
               Eringoes ſhoote forth long rootes to a large but ſhallow extent, in a rough dry ſandy and ſtony ſhoare.
               But generally ſtrong and long rootes neuer Sympathize with firme hard and ſolid ſoyles; nor the fibrous and flender with light and looſe layers.
               Artichokes, Beetes, Beanes of Egypt prooue beſt in fat moiſt and laboured plots.Olera.
               
               The fat Ground for Phaſelles or Kidney Beanes and Carduus Benedictus, with moderate warmth for Corianders Mandrake and Balme, with labour for Spikenarde, with moiſtneſſe and lightneſſe for Lettice and Purſlaine, with ſpungineſſe and cleanneſſe for Aſparagus, with cloſeneſſe for Baſill.
               The Coley-florey, Rape-cole, Muſke-melon, Cucumber, Gourd, Pumpion, Thorne-Apple, Apples of Loue, Spinnage, Arach, Sun-flower, &amp;c. muſt haue horſedung labour and a fat layer.
               Léekes looke for a looſe, plaine and battle plot.
               The meanly fat with dunging and digging, for Cole-worts, and Cabbage.
               Sage is ſuited with cold clayie Earth.
               The leane layer for Aſarabacca, Time, Cammamile and dry for all, ſtony for two laſt, with rubbiſh for Capers and Orobus.
               
               The ſtony grauell gratifies Fennell.
               Rubbiſh with fine dry earth is a repaſt of beſt reliſh for the Roſe, if rough brickie and hot, for Rue.Hearbs.
               
               
                  The rough dry and barren for Plowmans Spikenard.
               Rough leane layers ſuite both Sauouries.
               The Chalice or Chin-cough Moſſe créeps along the barren dry grauelly ditch banckes.
               The dry earth for Peionie, with ſand for Paunces, ſand and ſtones for ground-Pines, Mullein, Egrimony and (if grauelly yellow) for Neuewes.
               Dry ſtony layers are deſtinate to white Saxifrage, Bugle, Lauender.
               Roſemary and Ieſamines rampe vp in a rotten earth, mixt with rubbiſh or broken tiles and bricks.
               The moiſt layer for Conuall-lillie, Peruincle, Biſtorte, Orpon, Pimpernel and meanly fat for Mints and Calamint, with compoſt for Chiruill and (if olde) for Margerom, if battlef or Dragons, and Liuerwort, if ſtony for Harts-tongue, if laboured for Peniroyall, if light for Endiue and Succory, if coole for Muncks Reubarb, and Betony, if ſtony and ſandy for Parſly, according to the Etymologie.
               The Fenny wateriſh Soyle by lakes and Pooles fits Comfrey, Torneſele, Butter-Burre, Marſh-Mallow, Clownes Wound-worke.
               The Boggie, Sandy and Sunny plot, ſuits with Sun-dewe, Marſh Whorts.
               Spungie lowe grounds are good for Hops (ſo is a crumbling fenny layer) vntrencht and wet for the Ozier-Hope which will parrallell the profit of the beſt Wheate in a rich ſoyle of equall extention.
               The Knot-berries and Cloud-berries climbe and clad the tops of Moutanous fells.
               Marigolds, Clary, Melilot, Spoone-wort content neither for place, clime or layer.
               
                  Trees.And all ſoyles are acceptable to Burrage, Bugloſſe, Violet.
               The Apple aſkes a fat moiſt mould, blacke and Aſhcolored.
               
                  Peares, Peaches, Wardens, a good clay.
               Plumbes preſſe for a looſe layer,
               The Apricot, a hot ſand, the Cherry a cooel and moiſt with ſome mixture of clay.
               The moiſt plot fits the Aſh, Agnus Caſtus, Tamariske Quince, Seruice.
               The Grauell if moiſt is beſt (and ſand not amiſſe) for the Elme, if ſton for the Almond.
               The Chaulke layer for Iuniper &amp; Yew, though this brooke a light barren ſoyle.
               Knée-holme thriues in a rough, dry barren earth.
               The ſtony ſolid Clay is for Fig-trées.
               The blacke ſoft ſoyle for Cheſnuts.
               Philberds, loue dankiſh places, but Walnuts hate them, and wiſh a hot ſoyle though meane in fatnes.
               The Medlar and Corneill contend for a ſand and fat cruſt.
               The ſandy nitrous ſoyle ſerues beſt for Dates: Sandy, light, leane and brittle for Mirrh and Mirtle: but theſe brooke no colde Regions.
               Pome-granates, preſſe for Compoſt and hot Countries.
               The Bay and Mulbery, beg a temperate aire, and this earnes after fat manurings, the other reſts ſatiſfied with a leane layer, ſo that it be ſolid.
               The mountanous hils, delight the Almond, Seruice, Firre, Larch.
               The Quince ioyes in the Plaines, ſo doth Béech, though Birches kéepe the Hilles.
               But the Indian Moly repleniſhes the lowly Vales.Sunne.
               
               Diuers Plants couet to bath in Sunny rayes, as the Figge, Apricot, Peach, Plumbe, Quince, Cherry.
               All whcih produce more delicate fruits being ſpread vpon a South wal, to ſhield them from Northerne iniuries, and reflect the Sunne-beames.
               Nor doe many Hearbes with leſſe purſuit of affection,

preſſe for the Sunnes enlifening comfort, as the Peiony, Goates-bearde, Sothernewood, Rue, Fennel, Lauender, Iſope, Mints, Saffron, Carnations, Pinkes: Alſo Roſes, Hoppes, Time, Spikenerd, Sage, the great Sun flower and the Ozier.
               But Turneſol with oppoſite eager eie al daylong gazes in Titans face nere daunted with his eye-dazing luſtre according to the Poet: Herba velut Clitie ſemper petit obuia ſolem: contrary to the Pudifetan which droops by day, &amp;c.
               In aprico quidē aëre multa faelicius viv unt, quae denſa et craſſa conſiſtunt ſubſtantia, quoniam ſole, ad calorē lentum ſuum excitandum, &amp; adducendum indigent.
               But the ſhady repoſure refreſhes the Bay, Tamariſke, Red Winter Cherrie, Liuerworte, Harts-tongue Betony,Shade. Margerom, Smallage, Aſarabacca, Sowbread, Auens, Dragons, Mandrake, Peruincle, Orpin, Pimpernell, Baſill, Strawberries, Louage, Spreading Time, Garden Creſſes, Cúm multis alijs quorum tenuis &amp; ſubtilis facultas nimia aëris tenuitate diſſipatur &amp; diſperditur, ideoque denſo optimè gaudent aëre.
               
               Yet Vegetables Sympathize with plots differing in temperature from their Natures.Sympathies.
               
               The hot and dry ſubtile Cedar crownes the tops of the ſtony and ſnowie-cold Mountaines.
               And hot and dry Hearbes are produced in cold moiſt ſoyles; as Pennie-royall, Margerom, Betony, Landcreſſes, Engliſh Saxifrage, Marſh-mallow, hedge Hyſſop.
               The dry Adders-tongue, Cowſlip, Prime-Roſe, and Teaſill, ioy in moiſt and dankiſh places.
               The hot and dry Smallage, Bitter-ſwéet, &amp; Clownes Wound-worte, delight in colde and moiſt ditches.
               Nor can the grauelly colde of rilling fountaines, extinguiſh the hot and dry temperatures of the water Creſſe, Becabunga, Agnus Caſtus, Butter-Burre, Gaule.
               
                  The Bog-berry retaines his colde and dry aſtringence, and Roſa-Solis his hot and dry cauſticke qualitie, maulger the looſe moiſtures of their layers.
               
                  Calamus Aromaticus hotte and dry craues a moariſh couch.
               The dry (though cold) and aſtringent Quéene of the Meddowes repleniſheth the watry moiſt plaines.
               The White Poppy colde and moiſt, couets a hot and dry place.
               The colde Mandrake and Sycomore couet hot Regions.
               The Cucumber, Gourd, Melon cold by nature couet hot ſtable-dung.
               So Apples of Loue, of Aethiopia, of Peru and Mad Apples relinquiſh not their cold and moiſt temperature, notwithſtanding their hot regions and Horſe-dung.
               Peculiar Compoſts are alſo requiſite for refreſhing of ſeuerall vegetables.Compoſts, Peculiar.
               
               Rue and Sage doe battle with bucke or other Aſhes.
               Roſemary requires Shéepes-dung, horne-ſhauings brickie rubble, Tartaror Wine lées.
               Liquerice loues Stall-dung, and Saffron the ſame, and Doues dung.
               Freſh mould medled with horne-ſhauings, is the beſt bed for the Vine.
               Lime-ſtones fertilize both Vine and Oliues, and the drooping Vine reuiues with the owne Aſhes.
               In planting of trées it is good to mixe Sand-ſtones and old ſhells with the mould and dung, the reaſon is rendred by the Poet.
               
                  —Quaecunque premes virgulta per agros
                  Sparge fimo pingui &amp; multa memor occule terra:Spiritus Intrabit &amp; Seminaria Plantarum erigent vigorem ſuum.
                  
                  Aut lapidē bibulū, aut ſqualenteis infode conchas;
                  Inter enim labentur aquae, tenuisque ſubibit
                  Halitus, atque animos tollent ſata: Iamque reperti
                  Qui ſaxo ſuper atque ingentis pondere teſtae
                  
                     Vrgerent: hoc effuſos munimen ad imbreis:
                  Hoc, vbi hiulca ſiti findit Canis aeſtifer arua.
               
               Nitre and Oile doe make Beanes great, tender and ſooner ſod.
               
                  Semina vidi equidem multos medicare ſerenteis
                  Et nitro prius et nigra perfundere amurca,
                  Grandior vt faetus ſiliquis fallacibus eſſet,
                  Et, quamuis igni exiguo, properata maderent.
               
               
                  Quidam ſi (faba) triduo ante satum vrina et aqua maceretur praecipue adoleſcere putant. Vino ſemina perfuſa minus aegrotare exiſtimant.
               
               
                  Antipathies.But as there is affinitie betwéene Plants and Plots, ſo is there a kind of Enmitie and naturall repugnance.
               The Roſe and Colewort abhorre grauell and ſand; nor do the Cheſnut and Fennel brooke too ſandy a layer.
               And dung it ſelfe is an enemie to Penny-royal, Rue, Ferne, Garlicke, Flower-de-luce, Plumbe, Cherry, Vine.
               Neither doth Iſope or Sage delight in dung or fat ſoyles.
               And although diuers Vegetables are indifferently beſtowed in ſoyles aires and climes, not ſo preciſely ſuitting their propper exigence and that with good ſucceſſe; yet could Plots of peculiar temper be conueniently contriued, no doubt their productions would bee much bettered either in quantity or qualitie.Chiefe Productions.
               
               And hence it comes that we haue in cheife requeſt the Heſton Wheate, Fulham Parſenep, Hackeney Turneps, Sandich Carrot, Walſingham Saffron, Workenſop Liquerice, Birtport Hempe, Kirton Pippin, Cambridgeſhire Pearemane, Engliſh Hops, Hony and Iuniper, Halliwel Moſſe, Teukeſbury Muſtard, Droitwich Salt.
               So forren fruites, drugs, ſimples. &amp;c, are as farre famed as fetched, for preheminence in meliority, acquired by appropriate ayre and layer; as Candy Oyle, Oliues,

Cipres, Zeilan Cloues, Paleſtine Dates, Arabian Mirrh, Banda Nutmegs, Malauar Cinamon, and Pepper, Stagonian Frankencenſe, Iaua Saunders, Perſian Bezar, Canarie Sackes and Sugers, Oruieto Muſcatell, Cracus Tabacco, China Rice, Ruber be and China-Rootes, Quito Mechoacan, Italian Sowbread, Chauchinchina Purcelain, Pruſſian Amber, Venice Turpentine, Spaniſh Cordoua, Malta Cottonwool, Camba Turbith, Syrian Scammonie, Norway Firres, Apulian and Tarentinian Wooll, Apulian Barley, Oates, Hearbes, Melons, Lemons, Siuill Orenges, Indian Ebony and Iuory,
               So Maſticke of Chios, Sene of Alexandria, Potatos of Virginia, Zarza parilla of Peru, Lacer of Syrene.
               
                  Hic ſegetes, illîc veniunt faelicius Vuae,
                  Arboreifaetus alibi, &amp;c.
                  Nec veró terrae ferre omnes omnia poſſunt.
               
               Experience alſo ſhewes that the Change of Soyles for Séed, is not the leaſt point of Fertilage;Change of Seede. as to beſtow Clay Corne in ſandy ſoyles and contrary.
               So the leane Vine is beſt fitted with a fertile ſoyle, and the fertile with a leane.
               The thicke and rancke braunching Vine, muſt bée reſtrained from immoderate ſpreading with a ſolid and compact layer: the thin brauncher néedes a battle ſoyle to enlarge the Dilation.
               And Plinie ſaies that in Venafrano their Vines are beſt fitted with a glareous ſoyle, viz. dry, leane and creachy; but in Betica the fatteſt layer is fitteſt.
               But the exact and full knowledge of ſeuerall ſoyles with their due and peculiar maſtering, ſubduing, preparing, compaſſing and imploying, with their ſeuerall orders and ſeaſons for fallowing, twifallowing, trifallowing and ſéed-furre; as breaking-vp, ſtirring, cruſhing, ſetting-vp, caſting-downe, requires more copious handling in ſome peculiar volume. It ſhall ſuffice in this Compendium, to haue giuen onely this ſuperficiall

toutch or taſte, relinquiſhing the perveſtigation of the ſecrets of Agriculture to more capable and ingenious ſpirits.
               And hetherto of Tillage; Ground-plots ſuccéede.
            
            
               CHAP. XII.
               GRound-plots are proiectures, eleuations, and all fundamentall contriuances,Ground Plotts. deſtinated and accomodated to ſome ſpeciall and propoſed ende. And they are either Internal as Vaults, Cellers, Caues, Sincks:
               Or Externall, as Groues, Arbours, Bowers, Cabinets, Allies, Ambulatories, Mounts, Mazes, Snailes, Cocke-Pittes, Bowling-Gréenes, Moates, Pondes, Stewes, Draines, Dammes, Sluces, Iitties.
               To theſe may be added Rampers, Counter-ſcarpes, Rauelins, Forts, Flanckers, Vammures, Curtins, Parapets, Sconces, Caualires, Palliſadoes, Bulwarks, Baſtions and ſuch like fortifications.
               But I haue béene too prolixe in the Subiect: I will be more compendious in the Adiunct.
            
            
               CHAP. XIII.
               
                  Adiunct.LAbour and Arte imployed about the Adiunct comprehends the Leuying and Erecting of Edifices, and Engines, in or vpon the Subiect or Plot.
               
                  Edifices.Edifices are either Principall; as Minſters, Monaſteries, Churches, Chappells, Pallaces, Courts, Caſtels, Manour &amp; Manſion Howſes, Meſuages, Watch-Towers, Lodges, Cottages;
               Or Collaterall, as Darie-howſes, Conduit-howſes, Stables, Barnes, Granaries, Maltings, Mil-howſes, Doue-Coates.
               
                  Alſo buildings of Pleaſure and proſpect; as Tenniſcourts, Banquet-howſes, Towers, Theaters, Amphitheaters.
               And buildings of Monument, as Piramides, Laberinthes, Obeliſkes, Statuaes, Tombes.
               Engines are either Militarie; as Battering-Rams,Engines. Sowes, Horſes, Tortuſes, Trepanes, Briccols, Towers, &amp;c,
               Or Ciuill, as Mills, for Siewing of ſurrounded grounds, ſawing of Timber and Board, beating of Hempe, Iron-Mils, Blomaries or Finaries and Hammer Forges, Griſt-milles, Gun-powder mils, Papermils, Fulling-mils, Shere-mils, Turne-broach-milles, Oyle-mills, Barke-mills, Madder-mills, whether they goe with winde, water, hand, or horſe.
               Likewiſe Cranes, Pumpes, Aquaducts, Conduits, Goates, Sluces, Tonnells.
               And thus haue I paſſed thorrow the Matter, being the firſt Eſſentiall part of Poſſeſſions: It followes to ſpeake of the Forme.
            
         
         
            
            
            THE SYNOPSIS OR EPITOME OF SVRVEY METHODIZED.
            SECTION .II.
            
               Diſcourſing of the Reſidence and laying of Grounds, their increaſe, Boundage, and Neighbourage; and of the admeaſuring, calculating and proiecting of lines, ſurfaces, bodies, Edifices, compoſing and tricking of Plottes.
            
            
               CHAP. I.
               THe Forme Conſiſts in Situation and Proportion of the Subiect,Forme. and Adiunct; and in the practiſe thereof, the Mathematicall, and Mechanicall parts are moſt perſpicuous.
               Situation,Situation. may be ſaid to be Reſident, and Reſpicient.
               Reſident Site depends vpon the ſetling,Primarie. laying and lying of the grounds, and is either Primarie viz. the

Maine Forme &amp; proiecture of the Baſe and Body of the Soile, wherin it is remarkeable to obſerue, how it is proiected in Plaines, eleuated and lifted-vp into Hills and Mountaines, debaſed into Dales and Vallies, or wauing in moderate ſwellings and fallings, aſcents and deſcents, &amp;c.
               
                  Secundarie.Or Secundary bearing reference to a further reſidence of the Soyle, eſpecially if it bee arable; And then we are to conſider whether it be laid in due and appropriate poſition ſuitable to the qualitie and exigence of the Habitude.
               
                  
                     Selio eſt terra elata inter duos ſulcos.
                     
                        Ridges. Flats.
                     
                  Arable grounds are eared in Selions and that either Flats or Ridges.
               The firſt is neceſſarily required in light and leane land, to the end it may the better retaine any inforced vertue, againſt the waſhing away by ſhowers.
               The ſecond are either laide in landes or Ridges large and high or round; or in Stitches.
               The lands or Ridges are fitteſt in fat ſtrong and fertile grounds that be tough, ſtiffe, binding cold and wet, leaſt the fatnes ſhould ſuffocate the ſéede, or the ſoaking cold obtunde and dull the natiue heate and confound the vigour thereof: and in ſuch ſoyles it were frugall prouidence to ſpare from the plow a graſſe-balke of ſome competent breadth.
               
                  Stitches.But ſmall Ridges or Stitches are accomodated to cold and ſtiffe ground inclining to barrenneſſe, to preuent conſtipation and binding together of the ſoile, wherby the ſéed wold ſooner burſt with ſwelling, than get frée paſſage for ſprowting. And theſe Stitches are common in Norfolke and Suffolke, euen in their light grounds, and in Hartfordſhire where the Tilthes are rich: and though the Iriſh ſoile be neither immoderately colde, ſtiffe nor barren, yet their tillage is generally eared in ſmall Stitches, peraduenture for that the ſoile is ſo apte to faſt-matting and ſwoording.
               
                  
                  Plinie approoues the beſt Situation for a rich Plot to be a plaine declining into the South from the foote of a Hill: ſo the Poet.—Qui
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      editus Auſtro.
                  The beſt Site
               
            
            
               CAP. II.
               REſpicient Situation hath dependance vpon Boundage and Neighbourage.Boundage.
               
               Boundage is the compaſſing and deſcribing of Plots with their buttalls, metes, bounds and Coaſtage.
               Boundage is either contiguall or Remote.
               Contiguall Boundage preſcribes &amp; limits-forth the extention of lands, by immediate and ſelfe-continuance of the confining Boundaries; &amp; is either ſimple or compound, both which may be either Actiue, intimating that the ſenſing or incloſing of the Plot appertaines to the Poſſident; Or Paſſiue inferring that it is incloſed or laid in ſeueraltie by the adiacent.
               Simple Boundage is Confrontage and Collaterage, both which with all other Boundages are capable of diuers peculiar variations deriuable from the diuerſity of the cauſes and occurrents obſerued in perambulation.
               Confrontage Actiue may enter the Plot with theſe or the like Epithetons, Abutting, Heading, facing, fronting,Confrontage ſteighing, &amp;c. Or Paſſiue headed, faced, &amp;c.
               Collaterage Actiue, as ſiding, ſurrowing, balking,Collaterage dyling, haying, hedging or ſhawing, immounding, impayling, immuring, ſkirting, Girding, verging, mazing, couruing, recouruing, bordering, confining; alſo lying, Bounding, extending betweene: Or Paſſiue.
               Compound Contiguall Boundage is more ſignificant, as ſide-haying, head-ſhawing, &amp;c.Compound. likewiſe bounded, limitted, preſcribed, compaſſed, included, terminated, determinated, collaterally, triangularly, quarterly,

circularly, irregularly, or as the Agent. Or more particularly, as with ſome angle, point, corner, or ſtripe pointing, ſhooting, running, extending vpon, &amp;c.
               And ſometimes this Compound Boundage implies a mutuall propertie or duety participable to the Conterminants, as bancking, balking, dyking, drayning, ſewing, ſewaging, rilling, brooking, riuaging, foording, alwaies confining the conterminants with the particle Cúm: And yet more ſpecially, as head-diking, ſide-ſewing, &amp;c. and the like Paſſiuely: and any of theſe may be admitted into the rough-booke.
               
                  Remote.Remote Boundage is requiſite for retriuing and manifeſting the locall proiection of Plots in ſupply of the defect of memorie and metes and markes contingent; and is accompliſhed either by Obiects remarkeable (inuiſible are improper, though our Hollanders, will néedes bound their Coaſt-lands vpon Normandy miſtaking it for Norman-déepe ſtumbled vpon in ſome obliterate déedes, where Germanie might better be admitted.) as Mountaines, Hills, Towers, Stéeples, or other Edifices, Trées of ſuper-eminence and Markes, and ſometimes waies, balkes, hedges, Riuers, pits and ſuch like, may effect as much being lined, rainged, rectified, opened, diſcloſed or cut by extention of common right-lines from fixed or noted ſtations.
               There is another ſpecies of this Remote or Mediate Boundage, where the Plot extendes not fully to the Méets or Bounds deſcribed, but is intercepted by ſome ſmal Intermediall; as Balke, Méere, bancke, lane, path, Rill or ſuch like; but this manner of Bounding, though it bée frequent, is improper and defectiue, wanting that perſpicuity which ſhould giue viue Validity to all Records.
               
                  Degrees.Or by Degrées of angular production obſerued by ſome Dioptrall inſtrument, whether by taking the angle,

it makes with ſome permanent marke, or the ſwaruing of the Line or Néedle from the Meridian.
               For Coaſtage as Eaſt, Southeaſt, South, &amp;c.Coaſtage. it is inſeperably incident to all Boundage, as the moſt Materiall and Eſſentiall part thereof, and in the recording thereof a vigilant and circumſpect care is required to preuent errors.
               And thus much for Boundage.
            
            
               CHAP. III.
               IN Neighbourage it is not impertinent to particularize, how the Plot is accommodated for Tillage, Meddow,Neighbourage. Paſture, Wood, water, Fewel, Fiſh, Fowle, Ayre, &amp;c. as alſo the Confinage with Champion, Wood-land, other Lords and Mannors, with the Commodities and conueniences deriuable from the propinquitie and competent diſtance of Cities, Townes, Markets, Faires, Ports, Hauens, Seas, Forreſts, Woodes, Waſts, Commons, Meres, Moores Riuers, Quarries, Mines, &amp;c. by opportunity for vent and intercourſe of paſſage for Commerce, and inter-parlée for Conuerſe, &amp;c. with the Waies and Venues to the ſame &amp; their conueniency of Conduct, as by land ouer ſmooth, facill and firme plaines, and by water, nauigable Riuers, loughes, Lakes, &amp;c.
               And this may ſuffize for Situation: It followes to ſpeake of Proportion.
            
            
               
               CHAP. IIII.
               
                  Proportion.PRoportion conſiſts in the generall Modell and partiticular Modulets of the Plot, and procreats Menſuration and Content.
               Menſuration is conuerſant in extunding the lineall extentions of longitudes, amplitudes, craſſitudes, altitudes, profundities, arches, circumferences, &amp;c.
               
                  Lineal Fals.Lineall dimenſions are diuerſified according to the cuſtome of the Country, as Inches, Palmes, Spannes, Féete, Cubits, &amp;c. and their compoſures and graduations are from Barley Cornes; as thrée Béere-Cornes in length make an Inch, thrée Inches a Palme, thrée Palmes a Spanne, one Span and ⅓ or twelue Inches make a Foote, one Foote ½ makes a Cubit, two Cubits or thrée Foote makes a Yard, fiue Féete make a Pace Geometricall, ſixtéene Foote ½ make a Pearch, Pole or Lug, forty Pearches make a furlong, whereof eight make a Mile, and theſe are by the Standard meaſure of England, tho ſome of them in name bee but confirmed by Cuſtome.
               But the Pearch in diuers places is of different extent,Perches. diuers. as eightéene foote in ſome Countries, in others twenty one, in the Country of Stafford twenty foure, and twenty fiue in the Forreſt of Sherewood.
               And theſe dimenſions are found or performed either Cominus or Eminus.
               
               The firſt with Palme, Foote, Pace, Rod, Raipe: but vſually the Rule is moſt in requeſt for Board,Meaſures Stone Timber, &amp;c, and the Chaine for land meaſure.
               
                  DecimatedAnd to accomodate theſe for exact and expedite operation diſme or deuide each foote of the Rule and Perch of the Chaine into decimals or Tenths, and each Tenth or Prime of the Rule into Seconds, but it ſhall ſuffice

to diuide the Prime of the Chaine into two lincks, with thrée rings betwéene euery lincke to kéepe it from croſſing.
               The ſecond is retriued with Plaine-Table,Cominus. Theodelite, Sector, Circumferentor, Geodeticall-Staffe, &amp;c. Or without inſtrument by the ſame Geometrical grounds.
               The firſt being accompliſhed by approach or contingence néedes no amplification, but for preciſe kéeping in the Wadd or right line.
               The Wadd is delineated either to a marke in ſight or out of ſight.Wadding.
               
               If the Firſt; let the Chaine-leaders Wadd vpon the marke by ſome intermediall eminence and at the ſetting down of euery pricke, let each man waue his mate into the right Wadd.
               If out of ſight and in Champion not much ſwelling,To a Place not in view. it is expedient to place two Aſſiſtants, the one at the marke, and the other at the eminenteſt Medium, and then your ſelfe ſtanding at (or directly beyond or ſhort) the ſtation giuen, and the firſt Aſſiſtant erecting ſome viſible obiect, waft the Wadders into the Wadd. The like by Night with lanthorne or Torch-light. Or from ſome eminent Mount or tranſcendence (beyond the marke and in the ſame extenſion) ſurmounting or Surueying the whole tract, purſue the Wadd.
               But if the place cannot bee brought within view, inſtrumentalize the tract at Randon, the difference of interſection, found by protracting the trauerſe or by angular compariſon, ſhewes the point or degrée to be purſued.
               Now for remote lines the operation is produced by the doctrine of Triangles, one ſide and two angles,Eminùs. or one angle and two ſides being giuen; As to inſtrumentalize a diſtance, firſt point-forth two competent ſtations, and from the firſt quantulate the angle betwixt the marke and ſecond ſtation, and at the ſecond ſtation take

the angle betwixt the firſt Station and marke: Now the ſolution may be wrought either by Calculation or Proiection.Calculation.
               
               The firſt depends vpon the knowledge of Sines and Tangents, and is founded vpon this Theoreme.
               
                  In all right-lined Triangles the mutuall proportion of one Latus to another, is ſuch, as the Sines reſpecting their Angles are proportionall.
               
               But for as much as this concluſion is more familiarly found out by protraction, I will deferre, the Propoſition vntill another time.
               By Proiection: Protract or proiect firſt a line repreſentig the ſtationall diſtance,Proiection. and from each extreame extend a line including an angle equall to the peculiar angle found: the interſection of theſe two lines demonſtrates the marke, and the diſtances are manifeſted by the Scale.
               The ſame reaſon ſerues for heights and depthes.
               And by the continued progreſſe of ſuch operations the Plots and Mapps of landes, tenements, Cities Townes and Countries are produced, &amp;c.
            
            
               CHAP. V.
               
                  Plotting.THe Plotting of lands and poſſeſſions comprehends their Topographicall and Mathematicall Deſcription, and Conſiſts in Delineation &amp; Tricking.
               Delineation is conuerſant in pourtraying the Types, Surfaces, and Scheames of the Subiect and Adiunct.Delineation
               
               And for exact working of both theſe, the Plaine-Table is moſt accomodate: for the vſe whereof and of other inſtrumm
                     •
                  ts there are peculiar Treatiſes extant, and therefore I will onely touch ſome fewe Rules in briefe.
               
                  Plaine-Table
                  To Plot with Plaine-Table.
               
               At each alternate angle produce diagonalls for plant-lines to the antegrade ſtation, and ſo compaſſe the Plot.
               
                  
                  To Plot a field at 2. or moe ſtations.
               
               Extende lines from each ſtation to euery marke (chayning the ſtationall line onely)
               
                  To Rectifie the
                  
                     
                        Plot: diagone alternate angles.
                     
                        Table: retro grade the Ruler.
                  
               
               
                  To Rectifie the ſtationall line
               
               From ſome competent plaine, inſtrumentalize the leuell diſtance.
               
                  To retriue leuell or horizontall lines and angles in vnleuell and hypothenuſall Plots.
               
               From 2. or more competent ſtations vpon a plaine (either naturall by poſition or rectified from remote) in the Plot or adiacent delineate the whole Plot.Horizontalls And by this Plot to giue the true content, note each line with the ſuperficiall dimenſions found by the Chaine.
               
                  To Plot irregular Arch-lines.
               
               From the mids of the Chorde-extend a perpendicular to ye Arch, or proiect a Triangle by producing 2.Irregulars. Crures from the Chords extreames: a iudicious eye (rectified with theſe menſurations may (ad vnguem) pricke downe the Delineations.
               
                  The beſt way to expedite the exact Plotting of mixte irregulars, and conſequently of any Fielde.
               
               Plant not the Table at euery Angle,Generall. but to preuent puſſing and to aſſure a iuſt cloſing, extend from ſome fewe Maine Angles (or competent ſtations in the Plot) Baſe lines (ſecants, contingents, parallels, &amp;c.) for Boundaries or deleble Plant-lines, and from conuenient diſtances in the ſame, diſtantiate euery By, diſperſed in the Plot, and ſo pricke forth the Angles, Curues and Deuiations.
               For Delineating of Adiuncts, as Edifices and other erections, the Proſpectiue glaſſe is facil &amp; compendious, but for want thereof take this generall Rule.
               Proiect all Plumbe-lines in Parallelizme perpendicular to a Parallel or ſuppoſed Common Baſe of conſpicuous eminence.Plotting 
                        〈◊〉
                      Archi
                        ••
                     ture
               
               
                  So the Baſe of the Building proiected in due Site, the modulets right angles by peculiar erection retaine like qualitie in Plano ex oppoſito, but ex obliquo they doe alternately appeare acute and obtuſe. Other Delineations dependant ſuccéed by conſequence, and the eye by ſerious obſeruation of ſtationall aſpect may with facilitie giue the Vmbrage: but the Tranſpoſition and fore-ſhortening of ſome lines require more particular Rules, which with diuers other matters I am héere conſtrained to cut-off, leaſt this worke intended for a Breuiat, ſhould grow vnto too great a Volume.
               And therefore for this time this ſhall ſuffize for Delineation.
            
            
               CHAP. V.
               
                  Tricking.THe Tricking of Plots conſiſts in Complements, and Compartiments.
               Complements comprehende the Flie or Flies, Scale and Compaſſe, Kalender, Characters, Colours, &amp;c.
               
                  The Flie.The Flie is a Card diuided into eight, ſixtéene, thirty two equall parts in the Limbe with competent extention to ſhew the Meridian and Coaſtages of the Plot.
               
                  Meridian.Meridians are diuers wayes found-out, but moſt ſpéedily and exactly by helpe of a Dyall, or by ſtriking a line vpon your Table, or erecting poles vpon your Plot in a right line, directing to the Cynoſure or Poleſtarre, when it is perpendicular to Alliot the Thilhorſe of Charles-Waine.
               Otherwiſe at the Sunnes firſt cutting of the Horizon, ſtrike a line towards the ſame vpon your Table and erect a marke in the field-line: At the Sunnes going

downe (the ſame day) plant your Table as before by helpe of the marke erected, and ſtrike another line to the Sunne from the firſt point: Now deſcribe a Circle vpon this ſtationall point to cut the two extended lines at equall lengthes: The Diameter that mediates the Arch of each Sector is the Meridian, &amp;c.
               The Scale and Compaſſe are no leſſe requiſite,Scale. and may be floriſhed with Fruitage or Imagery.
               The Kalender or Index ſerues for a Directory to expedite the intimation of particulars with ſignance of due Characters.Kalender.
               
               The Colours would bee appropriated and ſuited to the ſeuerall Modulets of the Plot to diſtinguiſh their Natures, Tenures, Owners,Colours. or ſuch like:Arable. — As
               Arable for Corne may be daſhed with a pale Strawcolour compounded of Yellow Oker, and White leade, or of Pincke and Verdigreece.
               Meddowes may be waſhed with a light Gréene by taking more Verdigreece and leſſe Pincke.Meddowes.
               
               Paſture would be put into a déeper Gréene made of the mixture of Azure and Smalts with Pincke;Paſture.
               
               Heathes and Fennes may be diſtinguiſht with deader Gréene deriued from Yellow and Indico.Heathes.
               
               Trées may haue a ſadder Gréene compoſed of white Leade and Verdigreece.Trees.
               
               Barke, Blocks, Timber, Stone, &amp;c.Barke. may bee fitted with Vmber and White.
               Waies and Mud-wals, may haue white-leade with ruſt of Iron, or with Oker and Browne of Spaine.Waies.
               
               Water, Siluer, Glaſſe, Cryſtal,Water. &amp;c. may be repreſented with Indico and Azure or blacke Leade.
               Seas may haue their gréeniſh Skie-colour expreſſed with Indico (Smalts or Azure) White leade and Verdigreece.Sea.
               
               And thus, both theſe and diuers other colours with their due proportion, may with ſmall practiſe be eaſily

produced and multiplyed; And it will ſuffice to tract the Verges onely of Land-Modulets whatſoeuer you pleaſe to ſignifie thereby.
               But howſoeuer you beſtow theſe Colours of diſtemper, they muſt be ground and bound with Gum-water very thinne and bodileſſe.
               And it ſhal not be amiſſe to pounce the ground with a Stainſh Graine of burnt Allome and a double quantity of pounded Roſſin both finely fearced and lightly pummiced, thereby to preſerue the Paper or Parchment from thorowe-piercing with the Colours.
               Compartiments are Blankes or Figures bordered with Anticke Boſcage or Croteſko-woorke,Compartiments. wherein Euidences or other Memorables may be abreuiated.
               And theſe may bee contriued in Parallelograms, Squares, Circles, Oualls, Lunaries, or other mixt or voluntary proportions compaſſed and tricked ad libitū.
               
               Vnder this Title may alſo be rainged the Lordes-Coate with Creſt and Mantells.
               And theſe Compartiments with the Scale, Carde and Kalender muſt bee beſtowed in couuenient ſpare and voide places.
            
            
               CHAP. VII.
               
                  Content.HItherto of Menſuration: Content in generall is Couchant and Creſcent.
               The Couchant is either Superficiall or Solid.
               The firſt is of Land, Water, Board, Glaſſe and all Surfaces and Figures.
               But before wee come to entreat of the Areas of Figure, it is not immateriall to enumerate how this Superficiall Content is diuersly diſtinguiſhed for Land; as into Pearches, Daies-woorkes, Roodes, Acres, Oxegangs, Yard-lands, Plow-lands, Hydes.
               There be alſo other quantities of Land taking their denominations from our vſual Coine; as Fardingdeales, Obolates, Denariates, Solidates, Librates.
               
                  Foure ſquare Pearches make a Daies worke, 10. Daie-workes a Roode or Stong, 4. Roodes an Acre.
               The Fardingdeale or Farundell (Quadrantata terrae) ſignifies a Roode or ¼ of an Acre,Quadrantata Terrae. ſo that if Obolata D
                        •
                     nariata, Solidata, and Librata, doe ariſe in proportionable graduation from Quadrantata as the moneyes do increaſe in valuable Eſtimate, then muſt the Obalat be ½ Acre, the Denariat an Acre, the Solidat 12. acres &amp; the Librat 240. vide Crompton luriſd: and Regiſt: Origin .1. But we read Viginti libratas terrae vel reditus in Fitzh .87. and Regiſt. Orig. 49. and 248. importing (it ſéemes) ſo much land as yéeldes 20. s. per annum.
               
               So you ſhall read further 249. Regiſt. Centum Solidatas terrarum tenementorum &amp; redituum.
               
               But for Roodes and Acres,Acrarum diuerſitas. they differ in Content according to the power of the extent or lineall Fall of the Pearch. Potentia rectae eſt quadratum. Et dupla, ratione quadrupla proportione.
               
               Yet the Surueyor, whether he be imployed in Woodland, or Champion, in the Forreſt of Shéere-Wood, where the Acre containes aboue 2 ¼ of Statute Acres, in Corne-wal where it amounts almoſt to 140. acres, or elſewhere, howſoeuer Cuſtomes haue accrewed, muſt make his Computation by the ſtandard: Notwithſtanding that the Lords Demaines (as appeares by auncient Surueys) haue béene meaſured by the 20.Menſura Maior &amp; Minor. foote Pole called Maior Menſura, and the Cuſtomary lands by a Pole called Menſura Minor viz. 16. ½ though ſome claime 18. foote· So the French Arpent or Acre containing 100.Arpent. ſquare Poles is laid-out in th'admeaſurement of woodes by the 22 foot Pole, &amp; this is called the Kings Arpent, their other lands are computated by the Pole of 20. 19 ⅓ or 18. foot Poles.
               The Oxe-gang,Bouata. Terrae. or Oxengate (according to Skene) called Bouata terrae containes after the originall repute 13. acres but we find it more or leſſe as the cuſtom of the place inures, and Bouata is properly vſed of Lands in

                  Gainour viz. vſually plowed.
               
                  Librata Terrae. Virgata Terrae.Foure Oxe-gangs of land extend to a Pound-land (Librata terrae,) of old extent.
               The Yard-land (Virgata terrae ſiue quatrona terrae) varies from 20, 24, 30 acres. M. Lamberd: and it is not reputed in Demeſne, but in Gainor, as are alſo fodi
                        •
                     a, minera, mercatus.
               
               
                  Carucata. Terrae.A Plow-land or Carue of land (Carucata terrae, that is, quantū aratrum arare poteſt in nouali tempore:) is ſaid to containe 4 Yard-land at 30 acres to the Yard-land.
               
                  Hida.A Hide of Land (Hida or Hilda terrae) is ſaide to be ſuch a portion of land, as may be tilled with one teame (according to the ſeuerall tilthes and ſeaſons) in a yéere and a day, and ſo Crompton and the Author of the new Tearmes affirme it to be 100 acres by ſtatute, &amp; therby confound Hida with Carucata, or make them little different. Others ſay, that euery Hide of land containes 4 Plow-land at 120 acres, and 4 Hides a Knights Fée.
               
                  Feudum Militare.A Knights Fée (Feudum Militare) is ſo much Inheritance as is ſufficient yearely for the maintenance of a Knight, and his competent retinewe with conuenient reuenewe, which in the time of H. the 3. was 15 pound; but Sir Thomas Smith (Repub. Anglorum,) rateth it at 40 pounds per annum. But for the quantity of land, M. Camden recordes it to be 680 acres or 800 acres. After ſome computations it containes 5 Hydes of land, each Hyde 4 Yard-land at 24 acres.
               In the Dutchie of Lancaſter a Knights Fée contains 4 Hydes of land, each Hyde 4 Plow-land, each Plow-land 4 yard-land at 30 acres amounting to 1920 acres.
               
                  Cantred Baronie. Earledome.Two Knights Fées make a Cantred, 2 Cantreds ½ and ⅙ make a Barony, one Barony and ½ makes an Earledome: viz. 38400 acres.
               But though theſe proportions of land doe not alwaies hold with their titles of honour, yet their denominations continue the originall inſtitution, and howſoeuer

they be diſmembred quoad quantitatem,
                  Dignities indiuiſible. yet the right and dignitie is indiuiſible, inſomuch as if a Capitall Meſſuage be Caput Comitatus vel Baroniae, it may not be parcelled.
               And the Reliefe depends vpon the dignity (rather then the quantity) after the firſt allotment,Reliefes of Dignities. 
                  viz. 100 s for a Knights Fée, 100 Marks for a Barony, and an 100 pounds for an Earledome. Mag. Chart. But to returne to the finding out of the Areaes of Figures.
            
            
               CAP. VIII.
               FIgures with their Calculations for ſuperficiall contents may be thus rainged.Superficiall.
               
               
                  To areate Figures.
               
               1. Multiply the perpendicular in the demibaſe:1. Triangles. 
                  vel Contra.
               
               2. From the mediatie of the ſides vnited, ſubduct each ſide ſeuerally; eradicate the ductat of the ſaid mediatie and remainders. Ramus.
               
               Multiply the length by the breadth.2. Parallelograms. 3. Squares. 
                  Idem. lib. 11.6.
               Square the latus. Idem. l. 12.23.
               
                  4. Polygonons. 5. Circles. Multiply the ſemiperipherie by the perpendicular, from the Center to the midſt of one ſide. Idem. 19.1.
               1. Multiply the Radius in the ſemiperipherie. Idem. 19.2.1.
               
                  2. Multiply the quadrated
                  
                     
                        Diameter by 11 diuide the product by 14 19.22.
                     
                        Radius by 22 diuide the product by 7 19.22.
                     
                        ſemiperiphery by 7 diuide the product by 22 19.22.
                  
               
               Multiply the Radius in the demi-Arch line. 19.4.Sectors. Sections.
               
               Turne it to a Sector (by proiecting a Radius from each extreame of the Chorde to the Center) then woorke vt ſupra deducting the Triangle. Ibidem.
               
               Adde the Baſe to the other Areaes,
               
               
                  
                  Cones.Multiply the ſide in the ſemiperipherie of the Baſe. 22.10.
               
                  Cylinders.Multiply the altitude in the periphery of the Baſe. 21.12. In theſe 2. add Baſall Areaes.
               
               Multiply the diameter in the Circumference. Or the Plaines Area by 4. R. 21.5.Globes.
               
               
                  1, Multiply the Baſall Area by 6.
                  2. Duplicate the ſquared diameter of the contayning Spheare.
                  
                     Cubes or Hexaedrons.3. Triple the ſquare of the diagonall line.
                  4. Multiply the ſides double by the Triple of the ſide. So much for Figure or ſuperficiall Content.
                  
               
               For Addition, Subtraction, Multiplication, Diuiſion, Reduction, Rule of thrée, &amp;c. in lines or Figures, I wil referre them til the next impreſſion, which I intend ſhortly to publiſh with much inlargement to the more compleat inveſting of the Arte, with due and appropriate Ornaments.
            
            
               CHAP. IX.
               
                  Solid.THe Content Solid is of Timber, Stone, and other Bodies or Figurates, whereof a touch in briefe.
               
                  Pyramides and Cones.Multiply the perpendicular in ⅓ of the Baſall Area. R. 27.71.
               
                  Priſmaes Cylinders.Multiply the perpendicular in the Baſall Area. 27.6
               
                  1 Cube the craſſitude; Or multiply it in the Baſal Area.
                  
                     Cubes.3. Or the Axis in the ſquared diagonall line, Or the ſuperficies in ⅙ of the altitude.
                  1 Multiply the diameters Cube by 11. diuide the product by 21. Ramus. 26.5.
                  
                     Gloabes.2. Multiply the ſuperficies in ⅙ of the diameter.
               
               
                  Leſſe then ½: Subtract the altitude from the ſemidiameter, multiply the Remainder by the Area of the circular baſe, deduct the product from the ſemidiameter and conuexe ſphericall ſuperficies multiplyed together, and diuide the remainder by 3.Globie Sections.
               
               More then ½; ſubtract the ſemidiameter frō th'altitude, multiply the remainder by the Area of the circular baſe, add the product to the ſemidiameter and convexe Sphericall ſuperficies multiplyed together, and diuide the totall by 3.
               
                  To retriue the mutuall proportion of Cubes or Gloabs
               
               Cube the ſeuerall Cubes ſides (or Gloabes diameters) Multiply the Contents giuen by the Cube of the Figurate ſought, diuide the product by the Cube of the knowne Figurate. And ſo much for Content Couchant.
               
               
                  Of Content Creſcent in a woord.
               
            
            
               CHAP. X.
               THe Creſcent Content is of Increaſes renewing at ſeuerall ſeaſons,Content Creſcent. and thence the denominations of Aeſtiuall and Brumall are deriued.
               The firſt is of Corne, Hay, Line, Hempe, Rapes, Woade, Fruite, Sommer-Herbage, &amp;c.
               The ſecond is of Maſtage, Edge-grouth, Winter-Herbage, &amp;c.
               In theſe Contents and Increaſes it is remarkeable to Recorde their Productions both in kind and proportion; as what and how much Graſſe, Graine and other Growthes are vſually reaped vpon an Acre; how many Cattell ſuch a Plot will Winter and Sommer, féed or kéepe, &amp;c.
               
                  And this ſhall ſuffice for Proportion.
               
            
         
         
            
            
            THE SYNOPSIS OR EPITOME OF SVRVEY METHODIZED.
            
               
                  SECTION .III. Capitulating the Natures and Incidents to Poſſeſsions, Tenures, Landes, Titles, Fees, Diſcents, Tenants, &amp;c.
            
            
               CHAP. I.
               HItherto of the Eſſentiall Parts:Accidentall. Partes. the Accidentall Parts incident to Poſſeſſions are comprehended vnder Propriety and Valuation.
               The Propriety of Poſſeſſions intimates their particular ſtate and condition,Proprietie. and may be deuided into Vocall and Euidential.
               Vocall Propriety denotates the Properties of particulars by due Appellation,Vocall which is either Nominate or Cognominate.
               
               The firſt is deriued from the Kinde and Species of the Particulars, and that either Generall;Nominate. as Vp-land

and Maritime, Woodland and Champion, Molland and Fen-land: Or Speciall; as Wealdes, Woulds, Plaines, Downes, Vales, Vallies, Mountaines, Fels, Hilles, Bogs, Bathes, Spawes, Moſſes, Loughs, Moores, Fennes, Woodes, Copſes, Heathes, Marſhes, Meddowes, Paſture, Arable.
               
                  Cognominate.The Second deduces deriuation from Forme, Site, Climate, Obiect, Seaſon, Perſon, Action or other circumſtance; as Harpe-Cloſe, Mountacute, Gilden-Vale Diffrin Cluyd, Saliſbury Plaine, Weſt-woodes, Vale of Belvoir, Lammas Paſture, Bel-Acre, Beaumeade, Nightingale Lane, Lough Erno.
               
               So much for the Vocall Proprietie of Poſſeſſions.
            
            
               CAHP. II.
               
                  Evidentiall. Proprietie.EVidentiall Proprietie decyphers the qualities and attributes coincident to the Poſſident and Poſſeſſion: and in the proceſſe hereof the Legall part of Suruey is moſt eminent.
               
                  Poſſident.In the Poſſident or Feudatarie his Title and Diſcent muſt be intimated.
               His Title reſpects either Dignitie of Birth or Calling; Or Right of Poſſeſſion.
               
                  Dignitie.Title of Dignitie; as King, Prince, Duke, Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, Abbot, Prior, Marqueſſe, Earle, Vicount, Baron, Knight, Eſquire, Gentleman, Yeoman, Artificer, Labourer.
               
                  Right.Right of Poſſeſſion may be deuided into perpetuall and Terminall.
               Perpetuall is either Allodium or Feudum.
               
               
                  Allodium
                  Allodium is an entire propertie and perpetuall Right in Poſſeſſions without dependance; and this is proper ſolely to the King in Right of his Crowne.
               And all the Crowne land within this Realme in the

daies of the Saxon King Edward the Confeſſor are called Auncient Demeſne. Kitch. 98. Booke Tit. Demeſne.
               
               And theſe Landes in the generall Suruey called Doomes-day Booke (made according to Geruaſius Tilburenſis and Ingulfus, in the time of William the Conquerour) remaining in the Exchequer,Terra Regis are amongſt others) recorded vnder the Title of Terra Regis.
               
               
                  Fitzh. inferres (13. and 14. Na. Br.) that no landes are to be accounted Auncient Demaine,Auncient. Demaine. but ſuch as are held in Socage.
               All other Landes within the Realme are called Frank-Fée,Frank. Free. (Feudum Francum ſeu liberum) which is defined to be a Tenure in Fée-ſimple, of landes pleadable at the Common-law, in oppoſition to the other, whoſe tenents cannot be impleaded out of the L. Court.
               
                  Feudum is that which is held of a ſuperiour by Seruice, Rent or both:Feudum. Or Feudum or Fée is a Right conſiſting in the perſon of the true heire, or of ſome other that by iuſt Title hath purchaſed or acquired the ſame: vide Bracton.
               
               And this is alwaies diriued either Immediately or Mediately from the Crowne.
               The firſt is where ye Fée reſides ſtil in the firſt Feoffée.
               The other is where the Kings Feudataries doe againe enfeoffée others.Feifz and Arrierfiefz. The French terme the firſt of theſe Feifz and the other Arrierfiefz.
               
                  Feudum is either Fée-ſimple or Fée-taile.
               Fée-ſimple is an abſolute ſeiſure to the Feudatarie and his heires for euer.Feodum ſimplex.
               
               And though many Feudiſts doe holde that Feudatarius hath not an entire property in his Fée, I may not conclude vpon Iacobutius his inſinuated probabilities, that theſe Fées (or ſome of them) were at their firſt creation temporary and not perpetuall and hereditary.
               
                  Tantum aevi longinqua valet ſolidare vetuſtas.
               
               
                  
                  Feodum. Taliatum.Fée-taile or Fée Expectant is a conditionall ſeizure to the Feudatary and his heires with limitation, and is either Generall or Speciall.
               General, is where a man is ſeized of land to himſelfe and the heires of his body for euer.
               Speciall, where the man and his wife are ſeized of lands to themſelues and the heires of their two bodies.
               The nature of this Fée is implyed by the ſignification of the word Talliatum which the Normans make Tailler, and in Latine it is as much as Scindere: ſo this Feodum or Ius Talliatum doth abſcinde and cut-off the before-General ſucceſſions reſtraining them to the particular Heires of Families, yet the locall poſſeſſions are vſuall tranſ-ferred from one family to another, but Dignities whether Datiue or Natiue are therewith neither conferred nor auferred.
               
                  Terminable Right.Terminall Right is either an Eſtate for life, as the Dowagers, Grauntées for life; &amp;c. Or for Yeares, as by Leaſe, Mortgage, &amp;c.
               
                  Tenant.And in reſpect of theſe and other ſeueral Rights, the Tenant is diuersly taken and vnderſtood, and implies aſwell the Feudatary or Owner, as the Farmor or Termer.
               
                  Dutie.Tenant in the firſt ſignification ſometimes imports duety of Tenurage: as Tenant by Knight-ſeruice, Socage, Tenant in Villenage, Burgage, Frank-Fée, Tenens per Catapultam, tenens Nativus.
               
               
                  Euidence.Sometimes it intimates his Euidence: as Tenant by Charter, Copie of Court-Roll, Verge.
               
               
                  Limitation.Somtimes it implies the extent of his eſtate of right; as Tenant in Fée-ſimple, Fée-taile, at will of the Lord according to the cuſtome of the Manour or by common Lawe.
               Sometimes it beares relation to the L. of the Fée; as Tenant in chiefe, very Tenant, viz. holding immediatly of his L. Meſn. Tenant Parauaile, viz. the loweſt

Tenants, &amp; moſt remote from the L. Paramount.
               There is alſo ioint-tenant, ſole-tenant, tenant in Common.
               Tenant ſignifying the Termer is diuerſified according to the exigence of the efficient cauſes of Poſſeſſions;Termer. as Tenant in Dowre, by Courteſie, by Will, Leaſe, Copie, Extent, Elegit, Execution, Statute Merchant, or of the Staple, &amp;c. And thus much for the Title.
            
            
               CHAP. III.
               DIſcent is the deuolution of Poſſeſſions deriued to the Heire apparant from his Aunceſtrie,Diſcent. by vnauoidable Right and Succeſſion.
               And this Diſcent is either of Bloud or of Inheritance.
               Diſcent of Bloud is either Lineal or Collaterall.
               Lyneal Diſcent is conueyed downe in a right line from Grand-father, Father, Sonne, Nephew,Lineall. &amp;c. And here is produced an Heire Generall.
               Collateral Diſcent ſprings foorth of the ſide of the whole Blood or Kinne; as Grand-fathers brother,Collaterall Fathers brother, &amp;c. And in this caſe the Heire is ſaide to be Speciall.
               This Diſcent of Blood is retriued by deriuage of Pedegrées from Aunceſtrie,Pedigrees. by inherent Birth-right and lawfull ſucceſſion.
               Diſcent of Inheritance is deduced by deriuing Sequences of Déedes from the Crowne,Sequences or from him that had Nouell Fée. And both theſe are very requiſite to be intimated for the manifeſtation of the Validities of Eſtates, whether the right dimaine from Heritage or forraigne acquiſition.
               And hitherto of the Poſſident: It followes to entreat of the Poſſeſſions.
            
            
               
               CHAP. IIII.
               
                  Poſſeſſion.IN the Poſſeſſion the Nature and Tenure require to be iudiciouſly diſcuſſed and recorded.
               
                  Eminence.For the Nature 'tis expedient to notifie the Eminence thereof, whether Grande, as Honours, Courts, Caſtels, Manours, Seignories, Forreſts, Chaſes, Parks, Demeſnes: Or Petty, as Graunges, Farmes, Tenements, Meſſuages, Cotages, Curtilages, Lofts, Crofts, Commons.
               
                  Incidents.In both theſe kinds diligent and particular enquirie muſt be had of their Incidents, by Royalties, Prerogatiues, Iuriſdictions, Franchiſes, Priuiledges, Liberties, Rights, &amp;c. conferred vpon them by Act of Parliament, Statute, Charter, letters Patents, Graunts, or acquired and confirmed by cuſtome or preſcription.
               
                  Lordſhips.Hence comes the Lordſhip Marcher or Royall vſing iura Regalia. Vide Stowe 176.
               
                  Courts.And Forreſts haue their Courts of Attachment, Swanimote, Eyre or Iuſtice Seate. So Markets, Faires, &amp; Court of Pie-Powders for Faires. Court-Léete (Law-day, or View of Franck Pledge) Court Baron. Alſo Wrecks, Swannage, Warrenage, Commonage, Piſeage, &amp;c.
               
                  Immunities.Immunities and Exemptions from Theolonie, Pontage, Picage, Murage, Pannage, Paſſage, Tranage, Laſtage, Chiminage, Stallage, Caiage, &amp;c. of all which Tenentes Honoris &amp; Dominij de Richemonde per conſu etudinem Angliae ſunt quieti per totum Regnum: ſo other Honours haue their Priuiledges, as Ampthil, Tickhil, Follingham, &amp;c.
               
               
                  Auncient Demeiſme.The Tenants of Manours holding fréely by Charter in ancient Demeiſne cannot be impleaded, nor empanelled

vpon Enqueſts out of the ſame Manour, and they are Toll-frée for all things concerning their ſuſtenance and huſbandrie, and exempt from contribution towards the expenſes of Knights of the Parliament or Shiere. Vid. Fitzh. Na. br. 14. &amp; 128.
               Infeoffing with Toll,Toll. implies Fréedome from Cuſtome, &amp;c.
               With Caruage, from taxation by Carues.
               With Bruckboote, from repairing and reedifying of Bridges, with Burghboote, from the like for Caſtels.
               
                  Foote-geld implies a Priuiledge to kéepe Dogges within the Forreſt not expeditated or lawed ſans controule.Foote-geld.
               
               
                  Horne-geld fréedome from taxe for Horne-beaſts there.
               Waiues, Weifes, or waiued goods,Waiues. import all goods and chattels, which being ſtolne, are left or forſaken by the thiefe in his fugacie.
               
                  Infangthef enables the L. of the Manour to iudge of Felons enhabiting within the Fée. And Vtfangthef,
                  Infangthef. to iudge, or (at leaſt) to execute iudgement of Felons apprehended within the Fée.
               For Accrewments to the L. of the Manour by Felons,Felonies. not onely their goods both Reall and Perſonal are forfaited, but alſo their lands not entailed eſcheat to the Lord (Poſt annum diem &amp; vaſtum) except in Glouceſterſhiere where the lands reuert to the right heire after the Kings yéere and day. Alſo in the Tenure of Gauelkinde in Kent, where the father to the Bough, the ſonne to the Plough.
               Baronies infeoffed with Theame alias Them,
                  Theame. haue power to diſpoſe of Villaines their Children, goods, and Chattels.
               
                  Abiſherſing, alias Miſherſing,
                  Abiſherſing, implies both forfaitures and Amerciaments of all tranſgreſſions within the Fée, and alſo the immunity from like penalties.
               
                  
                  Blood-wit.Blood-wit confers all Amerciaments of Courts for effuſion of blood.
               
                  Eſtouers.Eſtouers granted out of Woods or Forreſts, include Houſe-boote, Hay-boote, and Plow-boote.
            
            
               CAP. V.
               
                  Tenure.OF the Nature of Poſſeſſions I haue ſpoken ſomewhat: The Tenure of Lands and Tenements, is the manner whereby they are helde of their Lords. Grande Cuſt. Cap. 28.
               In euery Tenure the Confinage &amp; Condition therof are remarkable.
               
                  Confinage.The Confinage ſhewes to what Lord, Honour, Caſtell, Manour, &amp;c. the Seruice and Suitage (whereunto the Lands and Tenements are lyable) is due.
               
                  Condition.The condition intimates the Nature of the ſeruice or duty which the Tenant, by reaſon of his Fée, oweth vnto the Lord.
               
                  Seruice.This Seruice is by Hotoman defined to be Munus obſequij clientelaris; and this muſt be of ancient Commencement and continuance, ſith it is not now erigible or to be created (but by the Kings prerogatiue) as parcel of a Manour, though it may by contract be eſtabliſhed in a kinde of Seignorie in Groſſe.
               
                  Manour.For a Manour is a Seignorie or Dominium conſiſting of Demeſnes and Seruices of long continuance; and theſe may be comprehended vnder parts Eſſentiall and Accidentall.
               
                  Court Extinct.Here note, if the Lord ſo diſmember his Manour, as that hee leaues not Frée-holders, or if all the Frée-holders ſaue one doe eſcheate, then is hee diſabled to kéepe a Court Baron for want of Suitors.
               
                  Non-Parcels vnited.Land may holde of a Manour by certaine Seruices

which may be Parcel of the Manour, and the land Non-Parcel; but by Eſcheat the Seruice is extinguiſht, and the land comes in place and becomes Parcell in due conſolidation.
               But forraigne land cannot be vnited to a Manour,Manour diuiſible. yet may a Manour be deuided into diuers by Partition of Coparceners.
               Nor can two diſtinct Manours by practiſe be made one in perfect Vnion,Not vniable. howſoeuer ſuch an innouation continued without contradiction, may in proceſſe of time become to be reputed one in name and vſe, there being no Record extant to the contrarie: Yet one Manour holding of an other, may by Eſcheat be annexed to the ſame, and ſo be conſolidated and become one in vſe.
               But to returne: Demeſnes are all ſuch lands,Demeſnes. as haue béene time out of minde helde in occupation and manurance, together with the Site of the Manſion or Manour Houſe (called in ſome places Berries, Halls, Manour places, Courts and Court-houſes) for maintenance of the Lords houſe.
               Theſe Demeſnes were called of the Saxons (who had the ſubſtance, though not the name of Manours) Inlandt (and by Bracton (lib. 4.) Bord-lands) and the Seruices Vtlandt in oppoſition,Out-landt how reſtraind. though it may in ſome ſort be reſtrained to comprehend onely Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments yéelding Rents of Aſſize (viz. originall and ſet in certainty) as for Frée-hold, Copie-hold,Rents of Aſſize. or Cuſtomarie land; all which are Parcel in Seruice.
               For the Diuiſion of Seruices,Seruices deuided. they may be all comprehended vnder Chiualrie and Soccage.
               Chiualrie, or Seruitium Militare,
                  Chiualry. is a Tenure or Seruice, obliging the Feudatarie perſonally to performe vnto his Lord ſome honorable or Martiall office; And this confers to the Lord (the Heire being in Non-age at the Fathers death) the Reall Seruices of Wardſhip,

Marriage and Reliefe, in lieu of the Perſonal Seruice, which the Heire in regard of minority is not able to execute.
               Chiualry or Knight-ſeruice is deuided into Regall and Common.
               
                  Regall. Chiualry. Capite.Regall Chiualrie is ſolely confineable to the King, and is properly called Sergeantie. And this holdes either méerely and immediately of the King as of his Crowne (which is a Corporation and Seignorie in Groſſe) and is then further called Tenure in Capite or Chiefe: Or mediately of the King by reaſon of ſome Honour, Manour, Caſtel. Fitzh. Kitch.
               
               
                  Sergeantie.Sergeantie (Sergeantia or Seriantia) is either Grande or Petit.
               
               
                  Grande.
                  Grande Sergeantie is where Lands are helde of the King by ſome noble Seruice, performeable by the Tenant perſonally.
               
                  Petit.
                  Petit Sergeantie is where Lands are held of the King, to yéeld him annually ſome ſmall military furniture towards his warres.
               
                  Common Chiualry.Common Chiualrie is that Seruice which may indifferently be confined to the Prince, or to a common perſon; and is called Eſcuage (viz. Shield-ſeruice) which is either Vncertaine or Certaine.Eſcuage.
               
               
                  Vncertaine.
                  Eſcuage vncertaine is of two ſorts: Firſt, where the Tennant is Tenure-bound at his owne coſt and charges, to follow his Lord in the Kings warres, or to ſend a ſufficient man in his ſteade, there to continue according to the proportion of his Fée: viz. after the rate of 40. daies for a Knights Fée.
               
                  Caſtel-ward.Secondly, where he is bound by himſelfe or his Deputy to defend a Caſtell, ſo oft as it ſhall come to his courſe or turne, and is called in this caſe Caſtel-warde. Ma. Cha. 20.
               
                  Certaine.Eſcuage Certaine is where the Tenant is ſet at a certain pecuniarie charge (viz. 20 ſhillings for a Knights

Fée) in lieu of ſuch vncertaine Seruices, as aforeſaide. And this léeſeth the nature of Knight-ſeruice, and is in effect Socage (though not méerely. becauſe it ſmels not of the Plowe) though it ſtill retaine the name of Eſcuage. Na. Br. 84. Litl.
               
            
            
               CHAP. VI.
               SOccage (Soccagium) is a Tenure of Lands obliging the Feudatary to the performance of certaine inferiour and huſbandly ſeruices vnto the Lord of the Fée,Soccage. ſans Wardſhip, mariage, Reliefe.
               Soccage is alſo capable of the diſtinction of Chiefe and Common.
               Soccage in Chiefe or Capite,
                  Chiefe. is that which holdes immediatly of the King as of his Crowne. Praerog. 41.
               Common Soccage is that which holdes of the King or ſome other Capitall Lord, by meanes of ſome Manour. Ibidem.
               
               Soccage is either Franck (liberum) or Baſe (Villanum.)
               Franke Soccage is where in lieu of ſeruice in kinde aſumme of money is paid to the Lord.Franke.
               
               Baſe Soccage is a Seruile kinde of Tenure,Baſe. and is deuided into Villanum Soccagium, and Purum Villenagium.
               
               The firſt is, where a determinat Seruice is performable by reaſon of the Tenement, and not of the perſon of the Tenant.
               The other is where the Feudatarie is lyable to vncertaine and indeterminat Seruice at the abſolute and inſtant will and demaund of the Lord.Villenage. 
                  Bracton. &amp; Na. Br. 94.
               Yet may a man ſans impeach of fréedome (in regard of his perſon) hold in Pure Villenage;The perſon, nor the Freehold impeached. Nor is liberum tenementum impeached to him that holdes it in Villano

Soccagio, if it be to him and to his heires. Bracton.
               
               There be other branches of Soccage, as Burgage; Frank-Almoine.
               
               
                  Copy-hold.And Copy-hold (ſaith Kitchin 80) is a baſe Tenure, and was originally called Villenage, Fitz. 12.
               
                  Meere Copy-hold.But (to retaine the moderne appellation) ſome of this is Méere Copy-hold, and eſcheats forthwith to the Lord by Felony. Kitch. 81.
               And ſome is of more eminence, and held by Verge in auncient Demeiſne, according to the Cuſtome of the Manor, being in effect a kinde of Frée-hold (though reputed Copy) and yéelds to the King Annum, diem &amp; Vaſtum vpon Felony.
               Some Copy-holds are fineable at the Lords will; and ſome only are lyable to a certain rate,Fines. and this is a kind of inheritance called Cuſtomary, not ſimply at the will of the Lord.
               But there is a kinde of Cuſtomary Land of the Ancient Dutchy of Cornewall and other places,Cuſtomary. where the Tenants haue no Tranſcripts of the entries of their admittances;Folk-land. And this was called Folke-land, and the Tenants may be termed Tenants by Court-Roll, according to the Cuſtome of the Manour.
               But where the Tenants are, by reaſon of the Tranſcripts of admittances, called Tenants by Copy of Court-Roll, there the Land is Charter-land or Bockland.Bock-land. 
                  Kitch. 86.89.
               For the Definition of a Copy-holder, reade Weſt in his Symbol. 1. parte. 646.
               And for the various Cuſtomes of Copy-holders in ſeueral Manours, 'tis as néedleſſe as endleſſe to capitulate or enumerate them in this Tractate.
               But both méere Copy-holde may be conuerted into Fée,Conuerſion of Fees. and likewiſe Fées changed from their firſt inſtitution by feofment; as out of Chiualry for certaine yéerely Rent into Fée-Farme, ſans further duty than is ſpecially

compriſed in the Graunt, except Fealty alone, which by probability is ſtill on foote, becauſe it is inſeperably incident to all Tenures.Fealty. For whoſoeuer is inveſted in Fée, though in the fréeſt maner, holdeth perfidem &amp; fiduciam, that is, by Fealty at leaſt. Smith Rep. Anglorum. 3.
               And Dwarenus ſaith, that Fidelitas eſt ſubſtantia Feudi.
               
               Fée-Farme is a Fée,Fee-Farme. and importeth a perpetuity to the Inueſtée and his heires, for an annuall Rent of the third or fourth part of the Value. Fitzh. 210. But if the Rent reſerued be behinde and vnpaide for the ſpace of two yéeres, then may the Feoffour or his heires by Action recouer the Lands as their Demeſnes. Britton. 66. And land thus held comes néere to the Nature of Ager vectigalis amongſt the Ciuillians.
               
                  And hitherto of the Propriety of Poſſeſſions:
                  It remaines to intreate of their Valuations.
               
            
         
         
            
            
            THE SYNOPSIS OR EPITOME OF SVRVEY METHODIZED.
            SECTION .IIII.
            
               How Poſſeſsions are to be valued by reaſon of their ſeuerall iſſues, Rents, Perquiſites, Priuiledges and other profits, with particular reſpect to their Reuenewes and Repriſes.
            
            
               CHAP. I.
               
                  THE Valuation of Poſſeſſions conſiſts in the due Eſtimate and Prizall of all Parts and Particulars Eſſentially and Accidentally thereunto belonging:Valuation. And to the exact performance hereof both the Materiall and Legall Parts are very requiſite.
               This Valuation is either Reiterant or Determinant.
               Reiterant Valuation depends vpon the exact knowledge both of the Reuenewes and Repriſes.
               
                  
                  Reuenewes.Vnder Reuenewes (or Eſplees after Ingham) I comprehend all and ſingular Rents, Seruices, Iſſues, and profits accrewing and renewing to the Feudiſt or Poſſident by, through or by reaſon of Fées and Poſſeſſions.
               And theſe Reuenewes may be ſaid to be Conuentuall and Incident.
               Conuentuall Reuenewes comprize al Rents both in Eſſe and in Poſſe.
               
               
                  Rents.Rents in Eſſe are Receipts certaine or couenanted, and payable at daies and termes limited: and they are either Proper or Improper.
               
                  Proper.Rents Proper (whether Rent-ſeruice, Rent-charge, or Rent-Secke) may be for Landes, tenements, Paſture, Engines, Mils, Mines, Quarries, Warrens, Fiſhing, Fowling, Wood-ſayles, Heath, Furſe, Turbarie Maſtage, (of Béech, Oake, Holme, &amp;c.) Herbage, Broovage, &amp;c. And Rent-Prouiſion, as Beifes, Muttons, Veniſon, Fiſh, Fowle, Graine and other voluntarie reſeruations vpon graunts or eſtates for liues or yeres.
               
                  Improper.Rents Improper are where, of an vncertaine and caſual commodity, a certaine Rent or Receipt is by contract created &amp; raiſed: as for Licences, Swan-markes, Profits of Faires, Markets, Courts, Cuſtomes, Tollage, Pontage, Caiage, Cranage, Ferriage, Boonage, &amp;c.
               
                  Poſſe.Conuentuall Reuenewes in Poſſe are all iſſues and aduantages ariſing of Poſſeſſions not demiſed (though Rentable) and therefore neceſſarily valueable by Eſtimate: as Demaine-Landes, Timber, Manuells, Waſts, &amp;c.
            
            
               CHAP. II.
               
                  Incident.INcident Reuenewes are either profitable as Perquiſites, or Parallels to profits.
               
                  Perquiſites may be diuided into Renouant and Dormant.Perquiſites.
               
               Renouant Perquiſites are Accrewments acquired by Increaſe and Caſualty.
               Increaſe comprehends all profits deriued from the Pregnance and Production of the Earth.Pregnance.
               
               Of the firſt ſort are Stones, Metalline Oares and Mineralles vt ſupra.
               
               Of the ſecond ſort are Wines, Pirry, Cider, Hony,Production. Waxe, Bombace, Raw-ſilkes, Hops, Sumach, Pitch, Tarre, Campheire, Opponax, Taccamahacca, Caranna, Maſticke, and other Gums: Likewiſe Drugs, as Mechoacan, Kermez, Methium, Alkanet, Agaricke, Amber-Gréece, Acacia, Lignum Aloes, Saſſafras, Spikenard, Rubarbe: Alſo Muſke, Ciuet, Ben, Beniamin, Caſtoreum, Cantarides, Cocheneil, with other Simples Fruite, Rootes. And Furres as Armins, Sables, Minivers, Lewzernes, Martins, Beauers, &amp;c.
               By Caſualty are intended all duties and ſeruices that be Appurtenant and Appendant to a Manour,Caſualtie. whether it be Capitall or Non-Capitall.
               Vnder Appurtenants, may be rainged all Royalties Prerogatiues, Iuriſdictions, Franchiſes, Priuiledges,Appurtenants. Liberties, Seruices, Cuſtomes, &amp;c.
               And all emoluments and aduantages deriueable from them: Perquiſites of Courts; as Pleas, Fines, Amerceaments, Heriots, (Seruice, Cuſtome, Couenant) Releifes, Aydes, Farewels, Waiues, Eſtraies, Deodands, goods of Felons and Fugitiues (by ſpeciall graunt) cō
                  morant in the Manour, Forfeitures, Eſcheates, Wards (in Non-age, Idiocy Lunacy) Marriages, Villaines, Treaſure-Troue: Warrens of Birds, Conies, Hares, Commons of Paſture, Turbary, Piſcarie, &amp;c.
               Appendant are Hoſpitalls,Appendant. Patronages of Churches and Benefices (Valuable not in contriuing commodities by Church-Chaffering, but equiualent in validitie

by reaſon of the priuiledge of electing or preſenting a worthy Clarke, (who muſt be Idoneus) to ſuccéede and ſupply the vacancie of the Church) Alſo Common of Fiſhing, of Eſtouers, of Vicinage.
               
                  Dormant.Dormant Perquiſites are ſuch things as are euer preſt and ready at the inſtant commaund and pleaſure of the Lord; as Villaines &amp; Neifes, which are alwayes ſaide to be Regardant to a Manour.Regardant. And to this place may alſo be indifferently referred Salt Naturall, Sande, Grauell, Marle, Earth and ſuch other thinges as are alwaies diſpoſeable by the Poſſident for deriuing an immediate profit or Reuenewe.
               
                  So much for Perquiſites: Parallels enſue.
               
            
            
               CAP. III.
               
                  Parallels.BY Parallels I intend all purſuites of wilde Game, which for moderate exerciſe of the body and delight full refection of the minde, are held in priuate eſtéeme of Purſuite, or in valueable validity of the Purchaſe of the Pray, equiualent to profitable Accrewments. And they are either Generous, as Hunting and Hawlking: Or Plebeious, as Fiſhing and Fowling.
               It is therefore not impertiment to the purpoſe to intimate what ſeuerall Games are vſually found within the Precincts and Priuiledges of the Plot or Fée, and how the Countrie is accommodated for Chace, View, Flight, &amp;c.
               
                  Hunting.For Hunting, Record what Beaſts of the Forreſt there be, and how frequent: as the Hart, the Hinde, the Hare, the Boare, the Woolfe: Of the Chace, Buckes, Does, Foxes, Martrones, Roes: In like manner what Beauers, Badgers, Otters, Wilde-Cats.
               
                  Hawlking.Firſt for Hawlking: Fowles of Warren, as Feſant

and Partridge: then the Elke, buſtard, Heron, Mallard, Ducke, Teale, Heath-Cocke, Rayle, Rock-doue, Pie, Black-bird, Thruſh.
               Fiſhing is either in Freſh-waters; as for Samon,Fiſhing. Trout, Carpe, Pike, Manat, Breame, Barbell, Tench, Perch, Cheuin, Dace, Roach, Ruffin, Eeles, Lampreys Gudgeon, Minnowes, Crea-fiſh.
               Or in Seas and other Salt-waters, for the Sturgion, Turbot, Porpuis, Seale, Bret, Tunie, Holibut, Mullet, Rochet, Gurnets, Gilt-heade, Baſe, Dorce, Macheril, Whiteing, Hering, Haddock, Thornbacke, Codfiſh, Kéeling, Hake, Dog-fiſh, Horne-fiſh, Conger, Lampſon, Bowman, Soles, Playce, Buts: the Lobſtar, Crabbe, Pearle-fiſh, Prawne, Sea and Wood Torteiſe Oyſters, Conchyles, Winkles, Purples, Cutle, Callough, Cockles, Muſkles, Shrimps. Alſo for the Sea-Pike, Carpe, Troute, Breame, Tench.
               Fowling may be for the Bittour, Curlewe, Mallard,Fowling. Pyntayl, Stockard, Duck, Teal, Snipe, Shouelar, Stork Cormorant, Gaunt, Sheldrake, Cob, Oliue, Puffin, Pewet, Yarwhelpe, Redſhank, Ruffe or Reue: the Godwit, Gnat-ſnap, Knot: Gray, Gréene and Baſtard Plouer, Quaile, Dottrill, May-Chit, Spawe, Churre, Péeper, Grindle, Skirwingle, Sea and Land Larkes: The Crane, Storke, Cocke of the Wood, Wood-Cocke, Heath-Cocke, Heath-Poote, Grouſe, Turtill; with which the Cuckow, and Owle, may for their delicatie bée rancked: then the Eſtridge, Birdes of Paradiſe, Canary Birdes, Parrots, &amp;c.
               Likewiſe for Hawlkes: as the Falcon, Ierfalcon, Tercel-gentle, Lanar, Lanaret, Leto, Ierkin, Saker, Sakret, Marline, Hobby. And ſhort winged Hawlkes: as the Goſſe-Hawlke, and Spare-Hawlke.
               
                  And this may ſuffize for Reuenewes: It Reſts now to intreat of Repriſes.
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. IIII.
               
                  Repriſes.REpriſes are impoſitions and duties whereunto the Plot or Fée is in peculiar lyable; and they are Reall and Perſonall.
               
                  Reall.Reall Repriſes are al Charges and payments impoſed, whether by Cuſtome or by Couenant, for maintenance or repaire of Bridges, Sea-banckes, Hauens, Sluces, Ietties, Wharfes, Goates, Cauſeyes, Waies, &amp;c.
               And in this Rancke may be Marſhalled al Reſolutes Dechaſhes, Decrements.
               
                  Perſonall.Perſonall Repriſes are Seruices, Duties, and Payments by Tenure to the Lord or Lordes Meſn or Paramount: as Fealty, Homage, Eſcuage, &amp;c. Court-ſuite, Out-Rents, Boonage, Fines, Heriots, Reliefes, Reſpight of Homage, &amp;c. Or by Graunt or Déed to Couenantées; as Rent-Charge, Extents, Pentions, Portions, Fées, Corrodies, Salaries, Stipends, Dowres, Annuities, &amp;c. to Diuines, Artiſts, Linguiſts, Lawyers, Patentées, Feoffées, Seruitors, Officers, &amp;c.
               
                  Valuation Reiterant is thus decyphered:
               
               
                  The Determinant remaines.
               
            
            
               CHAP. V.
               
                  Determinant Valuation.DEterminant Valuation concludes and determines the Right and Intereſt of the Poſſident by Alienation of the Fée or Poſſeſſion.
               And in this Action, ſith it is not Reiterable, it is expedient to retriue the vtmoſt Value and worth; to

which purpoſe that due prizalls may be produced, eſtimate all particulars both in Reuenew vt ſupra: And alſo Reſpectiue; as Edifices, Heire-Loomes, Engines, Timber, Tinſel, Ward-ſhips, Aduowſions, Villaines, Commons, Waſts, and other things in Groſſe, with all Perquiſites of like Nature.
               Now by oppoſing the Eſtimation of Repriſes to the Totall Valuation, the Remanet is rectified, and the true Value retriued.
               And thus much for the firſt part of a Compleate Suruey.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            Briefe directions for orderly marſhalling of Surueyes, for accommodating of Field-entries in Rough-Bookes, for Engroſſements and their Exemplifications with framing of Terrars, Rentals, Cuſtome and Court-Rolls, Particulars, &amp;c.
            FOr other Inſtructions and Preſidents requiſite for methodical operations in Surueying of Lands &amp; Euidences, with formal Exemplifications incident therevnto, I muſt deferre them till the impreſſion of the Second part.
            In the meane time, not altogether to defraud the expectation of the diligent, I haue intimated theſe fewe Inductions enſuing, which though they may ſéeme too curſorie and incompetent, to giue full ſatiſ-faction and information for the due diſpoſures of the copious remarkables, occurrent in a compleat Suruey, in fit Symboliographie; yet I doubt not but the ingenious Practizer may pick-forth more ample Preſidents, than may ſéeme (at firſt viewe) to be comprizable in the decurted Paſſages, as well of the former Tractate, as of this Supplement.
            To Suruey a Manour: Out of the Series and Protaſis
               
formerly dilated, contriue the Articles (ſuiting the exigence of the Seignorie) to be giuen in charge to the Iurie, and that in writing for more ſubſtantiall and direct procéeding.
            The Tenants, both Feudataries and Termors, entred, the Charge ended, and their Eſtates ſummarily recorded, your Aſſiſtants ready, and all things prepared, procéede to the Suruey, deſcribing Plots and noting in a Rough-booke (in Folio) all occurrents as they fall remarkable.
            And in this practiſe you are not cōfined to imitate or inſiſt vpon the precedent Protaſis or other Preſident, nor abridged of a voluntary propoſition of any other iudicious Method.
            The alternate Pages may bee delineated into certaine generall and Collaterall Heads for expedition, as well of the entries inſtant, as of engroſſements to be ſelected, noting all Extrauagants orderly in the appropriate parallel of the oppoſite Page; ſo ſhall you auoide diffuſed accumulations, which would confound and puzzle the ſpeciall Head in marſhalling forth particular and due contriuances.
            Nor ſhall it be impertinent to Kalander or Characterize each Modulet of the Ploat with the rough Entrance, thereby to facilize and expedite the ingroſſements incident, in contriuing whereof an indigeſted Chaos of obſeruations, would much intricate you, in regard the order purſued in perambulation, muſt neceſſarily be inuerted in the Exemplification.
            
               Page. 1.
               
                  
                     
                        Tenant and Character.
                        Appellation. Place.
                        Boundage.
                        Menſuration.
                        Content
                        Improuement.
                     
                     
                         
                         
                         
                        
                           P.
                        
                        
                           a. r. P.
                        
                        l.
                     
                     
                        
                           Hugo
                        
                        
                           Belham
                        
                        
                           E. Hayed. M. Tremaine
                        
                        24/5.
                        15.2.20
                        10.
                     
                     
                        
                           Elwood.
                        
                        
                           Greene.
                        
                        
                           VV Siewing. Th. Dewhurſt.
                        
                        25/5.
                        —
                        —
                     
                     
                         
                        —
                        
                           N. Shawing I. Franckiſh.
                        
                         
                        Rent.
                        Eſtimate.
                     
                     
                        A.
                        
                           Eaſt-field.
                        
                        
                           S. Shawing C. Gifford.
                        
                        100
                        
                           l. s. d.
                        
                        
                           l.
                        
                     
                     
                         
                         
                         
                         
                        7.10.0
                        150.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               Page 2. oppoſite.
               This Paſture is proiected in large Ridges extended and declining South; the Soile is a ſandy Clay of 18 inches Cruſt cloſe ſworded and well repleate with Trefoiles, Cinquefoile, Ribwort, Morſus, Yarrow, and other graſing Herbes of good growth, with a Dayrie Houſe in the N. W. corner of two good Bayes, and a faire Pond 7 pole direct Eaſt from the Houſe, ſpringing from the Weſt forth of a male grauell the Baſe of the Soile: the Hedge-Rowes are well growne and ſtored with Peare-trées and Appletrées of good Fruite, &amp;c.
               1. In theſe entries the Tenant is both expreſſed and aſſigned his Modulet with the Character.
               2. There are opponed Reſidence, Species, Habitude, Craſſitude, Inueſture, Ground-Plots, Edifices (Engines) tho laſt 3 muſt alſo be plotted.
               Now to Engroſſe a compleate Suruey:Engroſſement. Modulize Alternate Pages, and particulate the Oppoſite with due obſeruations, and characterize the Euidences.
               To exemplifie the Engroſſement without delineation of the Models, there is a method to be purſued in the particular Entries (according to their Eminences and kindes) of Eſtates and Euidences.
               In Frée-holds Record the Poſſident, Title, Poſſeſſions,Free-hold. Tenure, Deſcent and Reſeruation.
               In Copy-holds; the Poſſident, Title, Poſſeſſions,Copie-hold. 
                  Habendum, Fine, Reſeruation.
               In Leaſes; Commencement, Parties, Demiſe,Demiſe. 
                  Habendum, Reddendo, Couenants.
               In ſpirituall liuings; Site, Edifices, Glebe, Decimals,Rectorie. vicarage. Repriſes, Valuation, Eſtimate, Patronage, Incumbent.
               Medowe, Paſture, Arable, require ſeueral Contents.
               In the Entries of all ſaue the firſt, the Boundage &amp; Extent of Cartelages muſt-be-recorded.
               
                  In Edifices and Engines their dimenſions, matter, forme, and Repaire are remarkable.
               Out of the Exemplification of the whole Compoſition and Body of the Suruey, theſe ſubſequents may be ſelected (viz. Terrars, Rentals, Cuſtomaries, Suit-Rolls, and Particulars) and thus framed.
               
                  Terrars.Digeſt in orderly compoſure, Edifices, Homeſteads, Curtelages, lands, ground-plots, &amp;c. with their qualities, ſites, and proportions.
               
                  Rentalls.Compoſe in computable digeſtment all the Tenants with their Tenements and Rents in particular.
               
                  Cuſtomaries. Suit-Rolls.Recorde in fit contriuance all and ſingular the Cuſtomes and Priuiledges of the Manour.
               Inroll all the Feudataries &amp; Suiters to the Court with their Fées, Tenurage, Rents, and Seruices.
               
                  Particulars.Particularize Qualities, Contents, Rents (inſtant and improueable) Perquiſites, Parallels and other Reuenewables and Reſpectiues, with vendible and diſtinct Eſtimates; Reduce all Repriſes to a due Method and Record the Remanet.
               
                  Sequences.And for retriuing validities of eſtates, it is not impertinent to deriue the Sequences in Déeds from Aunceſtrie, and thereby to contriue Offices for the Tenure.Offices.
               
               
                  Non-parcel.For other the Lords Poſſeſſions compriſed in the Suruey, and reputed no part or member of the Manour, they require to be recorded apart in the Infra, vnder the Title of Non-Parcels: Vizt, Churches, Chappels, Almes-houſes, &amp;c. Alſo Patronages, Villaines, Commons, Annuities, and other particulars helde in Groſſe.
               
                  Memorandum.Regiſter all Omiſſions vnder the title of Memorandums.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            Errata.
            FOl. 5. line. 10. read Pederas. f. 12. l 10. r. Male. f. 14-l. 19. r. Chauning. f. 26. l 3. r. Interea. f. 36. l. 3. r. Holie Wormewood. f. 38. l 23. r. Wound-wort. f. 38. l. 25. r. Mariſh. f. 44.16. Cauallirs. f. 61. l. vlt Piramides &amp; Priſmaes wanting in ſome Copies to be ſet in the Margent.
            
         
      
   

