
   
      
         
            A vvonderfull, strange and miraculous astrologicall prognostication for this yeere 1591 Discouering such wonders to happen this yeere, an neuer chaunced since Noes floud. Wherein if there be found one lye, the author will loose his credit for euer. Newly corrected. By Adam Fouleweather, student in astronomy.
            Wonderfull, strange and miraculous, astrologicall prognostication for this yeer of our Lord God. 1591.
            Foulweather, Adam.
         
         
            
               1591
            
         
         Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01097
            STC 11210
            ESTC S113749
            99848979
            99848979
            14106
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01097)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14106)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1518:10)
         
         
            
               
                  A vvonderfull, strange and miraculous astrologicall prognostication for this yeere 1591 Discouering such wonders to happen this yeere, an neuer chaunced since Noes floud. Wherein if there be found one lye, the author will loose his credit for euer. Newly corrected. By Adam Fouleweather, student in astronomy.
                  Wonderfull, strange and miraculous, astrologicall prognostication for this yeer of our Lord God. 1591.
                  Foulweather, Adam.
                  Nash, Thomas, 1567-1601, attributed name.
               
               [26+] p.   
               
                  By Thomas Scarlet,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1591]
               
               
                  Sometimes attributed to Thomas Nash.
                  Written at the time of the Marprelate controversy in reply to an attack by Richard Harvey, in his Theological discourse of the Lamb of God and his Plaine Percevall, against Thomas Nash, Robert Greene, and John Lyly--MiU.
                  Signatures: A-C⁴ D1+.
                  Imperfect; lacks all after leaf D1.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Harvey, Richard, 1560-1623? --  Plaine Percevall the peace-maker of England.
               Harvey, Richard, 1560-1623? --  Theological discourse of the Lamb of God and his enemies.
               Marprelate controversy --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-05
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-06
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2002-06
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            Imprinted for Edwarde White, and Thomas Man.
         
         
            
            A Wonderfull, strange and miraculous Astrologicall Prognostication for this yeere 1591.
            Discouering such wonders to happen this yeere, as neuer chaunced since Noes floud.
            Wherein if there be found one lye, the Author will loose his credit for euer.
            Newly corrected.
            By Adam Fouleweather, Student in Astronomy.
            Imprinted at London by Thomas Scarlet.
            
         
         
            
            
            ¶ To the Readers health.
            
               SItting Gentlemen vpon Douer cliffes, to quaint my selfe with the art of Nauigation, and knowe the course of the Tides, as the Danske Crowes gather on the Sandes against a storme: so there appeared on the downs such a flock of knaues, that by Astrological coniectures I began to gather, that this yeere would proue intemperate by an extreme heat in Sōmer, insomuch that the stones in Cheap side should be so hot, that diuers persons should feare to goe from Poules to the Counter in the Poultrye: wherupon I betook me to my Ephimerides, and erecting a figure, haue found strange accidents to fall out this yeere, Mercurye being Lord and predominate in the house of Fortune, that many fooles shall haue full cofers, and wise men walke vp and downe with empty pursses: that if Iupiter were not ioyned with him in a fauourable aspect, the Butchers

of East-cheape should doo little or nothing all Lent but make prickes: seeing therefore the wonders that are like to fall out this present yeere, I haue for the benefit of my Countrymen taken in hand to make this Prognostication, discoursing breefelye of the Eclipses both of Sunne and Moone, with their dangerous effectes like to followe, which if God preuent not: many poore men are like to fast on Sondaies for want of food, and such as haue no shooes to goe barefoot, if certaine deuout Coblers proue not the more curteous: but yet Astrologie is not so certaine, but it may fayle: and therfore diuers Hostesses shall chaulke more this yeere then their Guests wil wipe out: so that I conclude, whatsoeuer is saide by art. Sapiens dominalitur astris.
            
            
               Your freend and Student in Astrologie.
Adam Fouleweather.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            Of the Eclipses that shall happen this present yeere, to the great and fearfull terrifying of the beholders.
            
               
                  IF we may credit the authenticall censures of Albumazar and Ptolomey, about the motions of celestial bodies, whose influence dooth exitat and procure continuall mutability in the lower region: we shall finde that the Moone this yeere shall be eclipsed, which shall happen in one of the twelue moneths, and some of the foure quarters of the yeere, whose pointes as they shall be totally durkened, so the effectes shall be wondrous and strange.
            For Cancer being the sole house of the Moone, dooth presage that this yeere fruites

shall be greatly eaten with Catterpillers, as Brokers, Farmers, and Flatterers, which feeding on the sweat of other mens browes, shall greatly hinder the beauty of the spring, and disparage the growth of all hot hearbs, vnlesse some northerlye winde of Gods vengeance cleere the trees of such Catterpillers, with a hot plague and the pestilence.
            But Cancer being a watry signe and cheefe gouernour of flouds and streames, it foresheweth that fish-mongers if they be not well lookt to, shall goe downe as farre as Graues end in Wherries, and forestall the market, to the great preiudice of the poore, that all Lent ground their fare on the benefit of Salt fishe and red Herring.
            Besides it signifieth, that Brewers shall make hauocke of Theames water, and put more liquour then they were accustomed amongst their Maulte: to the ouerthrowe of certaine crased Ale knights, whose morning draughtes of strong Beere is a great staye to their stomacks: a lamentable case if it be not lookt into and preuented by some speedy supplication to the woorshipfull order of ale cunners. But in this we haue great hope that because the effects cannot surprise the cause, diuers Tapsters shall trust out more then they can get in: and although they fill their

Pots but halfe full: yet for want of true dealing dye in the Brewers debt.
            Thus much for the watry signe of Cancer, and because this Eclipse is little visible in our horison, I passe it ouer with this prouiso to all seafaring men, to cary more shirts then one with them a ship boord, lest to their great labour they spend many houres in murthering their vermin on the hatches.
            
               ¶ The Eclipse of the Sunne.
               THe Eclipse of the Sun according to Proclus opinion, is like to produce many hot and pestilent infirmities, especially amongst Sunmers and Pettyfoggers, whose faces being combust with manye fierye inflamations, shall shewe the dearth that by their deuout drinking is like to ensue of Barly, if violent death take not awaye such consuming maultwoormes.
               Diuers are like to be troubled with such hot rewmes in their heads, that their haire shall fall off: and such hot agues shall raigne this yeere, with strange feuers and calamities, that if the Sunne were not placed in a colde signe, Renishe Wine would rise to ten

pence a quart before the latter end of August.
               But diuers good planets being retrograde, foretelleth that Lemmans this yeere shal be plenty, insomuch that many shall vse them to bedward, for the quallifying of their hot and inflamed stomackes.
               And Mars being placed neere the Sunne, sheweth that there shall be a great death among people, olde women that can liue no longer shall dye for age: and yong men that haue Usurers to their father, shall this yeere haue great cause to laugh, for the Deuil hath made a decree, that after they are once in hell, they shall neuer rise againe to trouble their executors.
               Beside that by all coniecturall argumentes the influence of Mars shall be so violent, that diuers souldiers in partes beyond the seas, shall fall out for want of their pay, and heere in our meridionall clime, great quarrels shal be raised between man and man, especiallye in cases of Law: gentry shal goe check mate with Iustice, and coyne out-countenance oft times equitie: the poore sitting on pennylesse benche, shall sell their Coates to striue for a straw, &amp; Lawyers laugh such fooles to scorn as cannot keep their crowns in their purses.
               Further there is like to be great falling out amongst Church men, and certaine fond sects

of religion like to trouble the commons: selfe conceipters and ouer holy counterfeites that delight in singularitie, shall rise vp and despise authoritie, presuming euen to abuse the higher powers, if Saturne with a frowning influence, did not threaten them with Tibornes consequence.
               But wheras the Sun is darkned but by digits, and that vpon the south points, it presageth great miseries to Spaine and those Southerlye Countries, Friers and Monks shall heat them so this yeer with confessing of harlots, that their crownes shall wax balde of their own accord, to the great impouerishing of the Spanish Barbers: Surgeons in Spain shall wax rich, and their Hospitals poore: such a pestilent mortallitye is like to fall amongst those hipocriticall Masse-mongers. The dukes, Marquesses and Counties, shall haue their dublets closed with such Spanish buttons, that they shall neuer proue good quiresters, for the hot and inflamed rewms fallen downe into their throats.
               It is further to be feared that because the Eclipse hapneth in Iulye, there will through the extreame heat growe such abundance of Fleas, that women shall not go to bed before twelue a clocke at night, for the great murthers and stratagems they are like to commit vpon those little animalls.
               
                  And whereas this Eclipse falleth out at three of the clocke in the afternoone, it foresheweth that manye shall goe soberer into Tauernes then they shall come out: and that he which drinkes hard and lyes cold, shal neuer dye of the sweate.
               Item, Gemini combust and retrograde, sheweth that some shall haue so sore a sweating, that they may sell their haire by the pound to stuffe Tennice balles: but if the Beadles of Bride well be carefull this Summer, it may be hoped that Peticote lane may be lesse pestered with ill aires then it was woont: and the houses there so cleer clensed, that honest women may dwel there without any dread of the whip and the carte.
               And I finde that the altitude of that place and of Shordich are al one eleuated, and two degrees, and vnder ye zenith or verticall point of venus, which presageth that sundry sortes of men &amp; women shalbe there resident: some shall be so short heelde and so quesie stomackt, that they shal lye in their beds while noon, by which means they shal grow so full of grosse humors, that they shalbe troubled wt strange timpanies and swellings in their bellies, vncurable for forty weeks vntill they be helped by the aduice of some skilfull Midwife.
               Besides, other of the same sex and faction,

shall learn to cosin young nouices, and fetch in young Gentlemen, to the great ouerthrow of youth, if some sharpe and speedye redresse be not fetcht from the woorshipfull Colledge of Phisitions in the parrish of S. Brides.
               But heere by the waye gentle Reader, note that this Eclipse sheweth, that this yeer shall be some strange birthes of Children produced in some monstrous forme, to the greefe of the Parentes, and fearefull spectackle of the beholders: but because the Eclipse chaunseth Southerlye, it is little to be feared that the effectes shall fall in England: yet some what it is to bee doubted, that diuers Children shall be borne, that when they come to age shall not knowe their owne Fathers: others shall haue their fingers of the nature of Lyme twigges, to get most parte of their liuing with fiue and a reache: some shall be born with feet like vnto Hares, that they shal run so swift, that they shall neuer tarry with maister, but trudge from poste to piller, till they take vp beggars bush for their lodging: Others shall haue Noses like Swine, that there shall not be a feast within a myle, but they shall smell it out: But especiallye it is to be doubted, that diuers women this yeere shall bee borne with two tungs, to the terrible greefe of such as shall marry them,

vttering in their furye such rough cast eloquence, that knaue and slaue shalbe but holyday woords to their husbands.
               And whereas this fearefull Eclipse dooth continue but an houre and a half, it signifieth that this yeere womens loues to their husbands shal be very shorte, some so momentary, that it shal scarse continue from the church doore to the wedding house: and that hennes, capons, Geese, &amp; other pullin shall little haunt poore mens tables, but flye awaye with spits in their bellies to fat Churls houses, yt pamper themselues vp with delicates &amp; dainties.
               And although verye fewe other effectes are to be prognosticated, yet let me giue this caueat to my Countrymen, as a clause to this wonderfull Eclipse. Let such as haue clothes enow, keep themselues warme from taking of coldes and I would wishe rich men all this winter to sit by a good fire, and hardlye to goe to bed without a Cuppe of Sack, and that so quallified with Suger, that they proue not rewmatick: let them feede daintilye and take ease enough, and no doubt according to the iudgement of Albumazar, they are like to liue as long as they can, and not to dye one hower before their time.
               Thus much for this strange Eclipse of the Sunne.
            
            
               
               ¶ Of the second Eclipse of the Moone, which is like to fall out when it chaunseth either before the 31. of December or els not at all, this present yeere, 1591.
               THe second Eclipse of the Moon shalbe but little seene in England, wherevpon the effectes shall be nothing preiudiciall to our clyme: yet as the bodye of the Moone is neuer obscure in part or in whole, but some dangerous euents doo followe: so I meane to set downe breefely what is to be lookte for in these westerne partes of the worlde.
               First therefore it is to bee feared, that the Danes shall this yeere bee greatlye giuen to drincke, insomuch that Englishe Beere shall there be woorth fiue pence a stoape, that their Hoffes and tappehouses shall be more frequented, then Parishe Churches, and manye shall haue more Spruce Beere in their bellies, then wit in their heads: wherevpon shall growe Apoplexies and colde palsies in their legges, that they shall diuers times not bee able to stand on their feete.
               Upon this shall grow great commodity to the Potters and Glasse makers, for it is like

there shall be a great ouerthrowe of them, if there bee not some act made for drinking in blacke Iackes.
               But if the weather prooue seasonable, and the Haruest great, and the Barnes full of Corne: Rye is like to be cheap in Denmark, and bread to be of a reasonable size, for the releeuing of the poore.
               Marty, Fraunce is like to haue a great dearth of honest men, if the King preuaile not against these mutenous rebels of ye League, and Papists in diuers places to be plenty, if God or the King route them not out with a sharpe ouerthrowe: But this hope we haue against that rascall rabble of those shauelinges, that there was found in an olde book this Prophecy spoken about Ierusalem long since by a Iew: The tree that God hath not planted shall be pulled vp by the roots.
               Some curious Astronomers of late dayes that are more Propheticall then Iudiciall, affirme that Martin the kill-hog for his deuout drincking (by the Pope canonized a Saint) shall rise againe in the apparell of a Minister, and tickle some of the baser sorte with such fond humors in their brains, that diuers selfe conceited fooles shall become his disciples, &amp; grounding their witlesse opinion on an heriticall foundation, shall seeke to ruinate

authoritie, and peruert all good orders established in the Church, to the great preiudice of vnity and religion, tituling themselues by the names of Martinistes as the Donatistes grewe from Donatus.
               
               Were it not that the Moone being in Taurus, which gouernes the necke and throate, shewes that the Squinancye shall raigne amongst them, and diuers for want of breath dye of the strangling.
               Now for that Capricornus is a signe wherin Luna is often resident, it prognosticateth a great death amongst hornde beastes. The Butchers shall commit wilfull murther vpon Sheepe and Oxen, and diuers Keepers kill store of Buckes, and reserue no other fees to their selues but the hornes, insomuche that if the Parson of Horne-Church in Essex take not heede, there maye hap to prooue this yeere some Cuckoldes in his Parrish.
               But there is like to bee concluded by an act set downe in Graues ende Barge, that hee that wypes his Nose and hath it not, shall forfeite his whole face.
               And that all such as are Iealous ouer their wiues without cause, are worthie to bee punisht with the horne plague for their labour.
               
                  And whereas this Eclipse is farre from the signe Pisces, it shewes that there shall bee much stinking fish this yere at Billings gate, and that Quinborowe oyster boates shall ofte times carrie knaues as well as honest men.
               But let the Fish-wiues take heede, for if most of hem proue not scoldes, because Pisces is a signe that gouernes the feete, they shall weare out more shooes in Lent then in anie two months beside through the whole yeere, and get their liuing by walking and crying, because they slaundered Ram alley with such a tragical infamie. The rest I conceale as friuolous, and little necessarie to be touched in this Prognostication.
            
            
               A declaration of the generall disposition of sundrie conceited qualities incident vnto mens mindes &amp; natures throughout these foure quarters of the yere, by the merrie influence of the Planets, with some other tragicall euents and obseruations worthie the noting, contayned vnder each seperated reuolution. And first of the inclination of the Winter quarter.
               
                  Winter the first Astronomicall quarter of the yeare, according to my vsuall account, whatsoeuer Ptolomie sayes beginneth sooner with poore men than with rich, graunted so by the malignant influence of Saturne, whose constellation is that suche as haue no mony nor credit, shal want coales &amp; woode and be faine to stande and starue for colde, while olde pennifathers sit and toast them selues by the fire.
               The winter beginning at that instant, whē the Sun makes his enterance into the first degree of Capricornus, that Hiemall solstitial signe shewes that by natural inclination this quarter is generally fleugmatike, and that Ale shall bee of so greate authoritie, that the Bakers basket shall giue the wall vnto the Brewers barrell, and a halfe pennye drie doe homage vnto a halfe pennye wet.
               The weather and season wilbe so cold that diuerse for feare of the frost shall sit all daye at Tables and Cardes, while their poore wiues &amp; familes fast at home for their folies.
               And in respecte that I finde three of the seauen Planetes to be in waterie signes as Iuppiter, Mars, and the Moone, it signifieth that diuerse persons both men and women for want of wine or strong drinke shall goe to bedde sober against their willes.
               That Sea-faring men shall haue ill lucke

if either their shippes hit agaynst rockes or sticke in the sandes.
               That ther shal be such great hoarie frosts, that men &amp; women shall creep to bed together, &amp; some of them liee so long, till they bee fetcht out with a Bason.
               Heere Saturne retrograde in Gemini shewes that there shall this Winter fall such greate fogges and mistes, that diuerse riche men shall loose their purses by the highe waie side, and poore men bee so weather beaten by the crafte of vsurers, that they shall begge their bread by the extremitie of such extortion. But Mercurie &amp; Uenus cōgregated in Sagitarie, prognosticateth yt for want of faire weather, such as haue but one shirt shall go woolward till that be a washing, and that water-men that want fares shall sit and blowe their fingers till theyr fellowes row betwixte the olde Swan and Westminster.
               And by reason that Mars that malignant Planet, hath nothing to doe in that Hiemall reuolution, souldiers this Winter for the most parte, shall lie still in garrisons, and shall not be troubled with more monie than is necessarie.
               Being also greatly to be feared, yt through extreame colde poore men shall die at riche mennes doores: pittie shall bee exiled, good woorkes truste ouer the sea with

Iacke a lent and Hospitalitie banisht as a signe of popish religion: and were it not that some moist shoures shal moderate the hardnes of the frost, Charitie should for want of house rome lie &amp; freeze to death in ye streets.
               Diuerse greate stormes are this yeere to be feared, especially in houses where the wiues weare the breeches, with such lowde windes, that the women shall scolde their husbands quight out of doores, wherevpon is like to fall great hailestones as bigge as ioynd stooles, that some shall haue their heads broken, and all through the froward disposition of Uenus.
               But Mars comes in and playes the man, who beeing placed in Gemini, that gouernes the armes and shoulders, presageth that sundrie tall fellowes shall take heart at grasse, who beeing armed with good cudgels, shall so lambeake these stubborne huswiues, that the wind shall turne into another quarter, and so the weather ware more calme and quiet. Such great flods are like to insue, through this hiemall distemperature, yt diuerse men shall bee drowned on drie hils, &amp; fish if they could not swim, were vtterly like to perish.
               Eeles are like to bee deere if there bee few or none taken, and plentie of poutes to bee had in all places, especiallie in those coastes and Countries where weomen

haue not their owne willes. Now gētle reader in respect of diuers particular circūstances drawn frō the daily motions, progressions, stations, retrogradations, aspects and other appointments of fixed and wandring stars, I am induced to set downe that such as haue no fire, shall feele most cold and that wierdrawers, if they plye not their worke, shall feele no great heate, that they in Russia shall suffer more preiudice by the sharpenesse of Winter than the Spaniards,
               And one thing is to bee hoped for at the handes of Mercurie, that this winter mony shall haue a fall, for Philip and Mary shillings that heretofore went for 12. d. shall now passe from man to man for 6.d. a peece.
               The distemperance of this quarter, is like to breede many sickenesses and sundrie diseases as well in young as in old, proceeding either of corrupt and vicious bloud or of superabundance of crude and raw fleugmatike humors. As Cephalagies or paines in the head which shall make men dizzy that some shal stagger &amp; stumble vp &amp; downe the streetes till they haue stolne a nappe to quiet their braines.
               Ache in the shoulders shall raine aamongest diuerse women that haue shrewes to their husbands, and diuerse drunken men shall bee pestured with surfets.
               Maidens this winter shall haue strange

stitches &amp; gripings of the collick, which diseses proceed by to much lying vpright.
               Men shall bee troubled with such paine in the eies, that they shal not know their owne wiues from other women, with coughes, ruines and itchings, which I omit.
            
            
               Of the Spring time.
               Winter being finished with the last grade of the watry signe Pisces, at the Suns ioyful progresse into the first degree of Aries. The second quarter of our vsuall yere commonly called the spring cōmeth next, which beginneth when grasse begins to sproute, &amp; trees to bud. But to treate of this present season, forasmuch as I find the planets to be contradictorily disposed, in signs &amp; mansiōs of diuerse repugnaunt qualities, I gather that this spring will be very il for schollers, for they shal studie much and gain litle, they shall haue more wit in their heads then money in their purses.
               Dunces shal proue more welthie then diuers doctors, insomuch that sundry vnlettered fooles should creep into the ministerie, if the prouident care of good Bishops did not preuent them.
               And by the opinion of Proclus, women are like to grow wilful, &amp; so variable, that they shall laugh &amp; weepe, and all with a winde:

Butchers shal sell their meate as deare as they can, and if they bee not carefull, horne beastes shall be hurtfull vnto them.
               Some shall bee so wedded to swines flesh, that they shall neuer bee without a sowe in their house as long as they liue.
               This spring or vernall resolution being naturally hot &amp; moist, is like to bee verie forward for sprouting fields blooming trees, &amp; because Saturne is in his proper mansion, old men are like to be froard, &amp; crafty knaues shal need no Brokers, vsurie shall bee called good husbandrie, &amp; men shal bee counted honest by their wealth, not by their vertues.
               And because Aquarius hath somthing to do wt this quarter, it is to bee doubted yt diuers springs of water will rise vp in vintners sellers, to the great weakning of their Bascon wine, &amp; the vtter ruine of the ancient order of the red noses. March Beere shalbe more estemed than ale.
               Out of the old stock of heresie, this spring it is to be feared, will bloome new scismaticall opinions and strange sects, as Brownists, Barowists, &amp; such balductum deuises to the great hinderance of the vnitie of the Church &amp; confusion of the true faith, if the learned doctor sir T. Tiburne be not taskte to confute such vpstart companions, with his plain &amp; dunstable philosophie.

Cancer is busie in this spring tide, and therfore it is like that florishing bloomes of yong gentlemens youth shalbe gretly anoid with caterpillers, who shall intangle thē in such statutes &amp; recognances, that they shall crie out against brokers, as Ieremy did against false prophets.
               Besides, thogh this last winter nipt vp diuers masterlesse men and cut purses, yet this spring is like to afford one euery tearme this ten yere in Westminster hall. Barbers if they haue no worke are like to grow poore, and for that Mercury is cōbust and many quarelles like to growe amongst men, lawiers shall proue rich &amp; weare side gowns and large consciences, hauing theyr mouths open to call for fees, and theyr purses shut when they shoulde bestowe almes.
               But take heed O you generatiō of wicked Ostlers, that steale haie in the night from gentlemens horses, and rub their teth with tallow, that they may eate little when they stand at liuery, this I prognosticate against you, that this spring, which so euer of you dies, shall leaue a knaues carcasse in the graue behind him, and that they which liue shal hop a harlot in his cloths al ye yere after
               But aboue all let mee not hide this secret from my countrymen, that Iupiter being in aspect with Luna, discouereth that diuers men shal drinke more thē they bleed,

&amp; Tailers shall steale nothing but what is brought vnto them, that poulters shall bee pestered with rotten egs, &amp; Butchers dogs make libels against Lent, that affoordes no foode but herring cobs for their diet.
               Diseases incident to this quarter, as by Astrologicall &amp; philosophicall coniectures I can gather, are these following: Prentises that haue ben sore beaten, shall be troubled with ach in their armes, and it shall be ill for such as haue sore eies, to looke against the Sun.
               The plague shall raigne mortally amongst poore men, that diuerse of them shal not be able to change a man a groate.
               Old women yt haue taken great cold, may perhaps be trobled with the cough, and such as haue paine in their teeth, shall bee grieuouslie troubled with the tooth ach. Sicke folke shal haue worse stomacks then they which be whole, and men that cannot sleepe, shall take verie little rest: with other accidentall infirmities, which I ouerpasse.
            
            
               A declaration of the disposition and inclination of the Summer quarter.
               When the Sunne hath made his course through the vernal signs, Aries, Taurus &amp;

Gemini at his passage vnto the solsticiall estiuall signe Cancer. The third parte of an English yeere called Summer, taketh his beginning this yere, as Ptolomie sayth, the twelfch of Iune but as my skill doth coniecture, it beginneth when the wether waxeth so hot, that beggers scorne barnes and lie in the field for heate, and the wormes of Saint Pancredge Church build their bowers vnder the shadow of Colman hedge.
               The predominant qualities of this quarter is heate and drynesse, whereby I doe gather, that through the influence of Cancer, bottle Ale shall bee in greate authoritie, and wheat shall doe knights seruice vnto malt.
               Tapsters this quarter shall be in greater credite than Coblers, and many shall drinke more then they can yearne.
               And yet because Mercurie is a signe that is now predominant, women shall be more troubled with fleas then men, and such as want meate shall go supperlesse to bed.
               Besides, this quarter great hurlie burlies are like to be feared, and greate stratagems like to be performed, through the opposition of Mars and Saturne.
               Butchers are like to make great hauock amongst flies: beggers on Sun shine daies to commit great murthers vpon their rebellious vermine.
            
         
      
   

